<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2F1475-4932.12331" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>As a way to improve health and equity in access 
to health services for children as well as adults, 
many LMICs are moving towards universal health 
coverage (UHC), defined by the World Health 
Organization (WHO) as 'all people receiving 
quality health services that meet their needs 
without being exposed to financial hardship in 
paying for the services' (WHO, 2014). While UHC 
is currently very high on the global health agenda, 
the road to achieving it is far from straightforward. 
Currently little consensus exists on how LMICs 
should structure their reforms to move towards 
UHC (Lagomarsino et al., 2012). There are mul-
tiple ways to increase the funds available to health 
care, including taxation, health insurance, out-of-
pocket payments and innovative mechanisms such 
as external donor assistance (WHO, 2010). In 
reality, countries employ a mix of these strategies. 
It is generally agreed that out-of-pocket payments 
are a regressive form of health financing with 
harmful consequences for the poor. WHO (2010)  makes strong policy recommendations to reduce 
direct payments for health care through risk 
pooling and prepayment for people who can afford 
to pay, either through taxation and/or insurance 
contributions (WHO, 2010). 
Health insurance has become an important mech-
anism through which many LMICs are committing to 
UHC. Systems typically comprise a collection of 
contributory and non-contributory schemes targeted to 
a range of population groups. Most systems include 
all or a combination of the following: a compulsory 
contributory scheme for civil servants and formal 
sector employees; a non-contributory scheme for 
social beneficiary groups such as the poor and persons 
with disabilities; and a voluntary contributory scheme 
for informal sector workers and anyone else willing to 
pay a private premium. In theory, through the 
collection of premiums from the non-poor, the system 
is able to subsidise premiums for the poor or near-
poor. However in practice, premiums collected from 
the formal sector in LMICs are insufficient and states 
commonly subsidise the premiums of voluntary 
schemes. Yet the take-up is often low, as demon-
strated by the case of Vietnam where approximately 
40 per cent of the population remains uninsured, the 
majority of whom are people working in the informal 
sector. 
1 Thailand represents a unique case where since 
2001, premiums for the informal sector have been 
paid fully out of the state budget with enrollees </p>

<p>subject to a 30 baht co-payment, making it the first 
LMIC to achieve UHC. In most instances, schemes 
are publicly provided. India presents an exception, 
with significant efforts being made to expand the 
private insurance system alongside state government-
sponsored health insurance schemes (La Forgia &amp;  Nagpal, 2012). 
2 Schemes may be provided at the 
national or community level, with the former seem-
ingly most common. 
Children can be covered under any of the 
contributory or non-contributory schemes out-
lined above. There are schemes that specifically 
target children and schemes for the general 
population under which children may become 
eligible, such as non-contributory schemes for the 
poor or as dependants of compulsory contributory 
schemes. Many countries have expanded health 
insurance coverage to school-aged children 
through targeted non-contributory programs. For 
instance, in 1992, Egypt introduced its School 
Health Insurance Programme, which provided 
free health insurance to children of primary 
school age (Yip &amp; Berman, 2001). The Philip-
pines expanded insurance coverage among 
school-age children seeking care in 30 randomly 
selected treatment sites (Quimbo et al., 2011). In 
Vietnam, by contrast, school-aged children were 
included among 'voluntary' insurance target 
groups yet were strongly encouraged by schools 
to pay the state-subsidised private premium. 
Later, in 2005, preschool-aged (&lt;6 years) chil-
dren in Vietnam became eligible for non-con-
tributory health insurance. It is also common for 
children to be included in non-contributory health 
insurance programs targeted to mothers and their 
children. For example, Colombia created its 
Contributive and Subsidised Regimes of insur-
ance coverage during the 1990s, which provided 
generous benefits to mothers and their newborns 
(Camacho &amp; Conover, 2013). Bolivia established 
its National Maternal and Child Insurance before 
expanding it into a national public health insur-
ance program. Similarly, Malawi introduced 
maternal and newborn health insurance in 2004 
in response to the MDGs (Brenner et al., 2014). 
Several reviews of the impact of health insur-
ance exist, but none specific to children (e.g. 
Giedion &amp; D ıaz, 2010; Spaan et al., 2012). There 
is a clear need for a review of the impact of health </p>

<p>1 Calculation by authors using the Vietnam House-
hold Living Standards Survey 2010. </p>

<p>2 By 2010, 19 per cent of the population was covered 
by the government-sponsored schemes while another 25 
per cent held private insurance. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>insurance programs on children, given the central 
role of the health of children to human develop-
ment, and because a number of countries have 
implemented reforms to expand health insurance 
coverage through programs targeted at children 
(e.g. Vietnam). The demand for health care for 
children may have a different price elasticity than 
that for adults (Leibowitz et al., 1985; Sauerborn  et al., 1994; Ching, 1995), which may lead to 
different effects for children than for adults. To 
our knowledge, this article is the first systematic 
and comprehensive examination of the effect of 
health insurance on utilisation, financial protec-
tion and health outcomes for children in LMICs. 
It aims to inform future research and interven-
tions related to UHC in general, and for children 
in particular. We limit our review to studies that 
apply rigorous impact evaluation methods as 
those that best inform evidence-based policy. 
Studies were identified based upon an extensive 
search of bibliographic databases covering pub-
lished articles in health services research, medical 
and social sciences journals. We provide a 
theoretical and empirical background for the 
study, then organise and synthesise results before 
discussing the findings and their implications for 
future research. </p>

<p>II Background </p>

<p>(i) Expected Impact of Health Insurance 
According to economic theory, health insur-
ance coverage is expected to lead to greater 
health-care utilisation by reducing the cost of 
care (Phelps, 1997). In turn, health insurance is 
expected to improve health. The effect on total 
out-of-pocket health expenditures, however, is 
less clear due to the offsetting effect of an 
increased number of visits. If the price elasticity 
of demand for health care is less than 1, then 
health insurance should reduce out-of-pocket 
health expenditures for the individual. 
If all household members are covered by health 
insurance, then health insurance should reduce 
out-of-pocket health expenditures for the family. 
If only some household members are eligible for 
health insurance, there might be an offsetting 
effect across members. For instance, household 
out-of-pocket expenditures may stay the same, 
while increasing for those without insurance and 
decreasing for those with insurance. Finally, with 
respect to health status, to the extent that health 
insurance improves access to quality services, 
health insurance is expected to improve health. </p>

<p>The analysis of the expected impact of health 
insurance on health-care utilisation is complex as 
one looks into the type of service, supply-side 
considerations and the broader context of health 
systems in LMICs. One expects an increase in 
outpatient visits, whether for preventive care or 
acute care. For children, this is especially the case 
for preventive care, with, for instance, an expected 
increase in immunisations. The expected effect is 
less clear for inpatient visits due to increased 
preventative and primary health-care usage. Buch- mueller et al. (2005) claim that a lack of insurance 
may cause inefficient use of medical care and 
avoidable hospitalisations (inadequate prevention 
and excessive reliance on inpatient care). Expand-
ing health insurance coverage may thus lead to 
reductions in some types of hospital utilisation. 
The nature of the effect on the utilisation of different 
types of services is also affected by the characteristics 
of the health insurance program (benefits, co-pay-
ments) and supply-side considerations, which are not 
homogeneous across programs and countries. Extend-
ing coverage to the uninsured may impact the aggre-
gate demand for health-care services. Health-care 
providers may consequently adjust to changes in 
demand. Given capacity constraints, providers may 
adjust their services to respond to the demand from the 
newly insured, which may change the nature of public 
services provided, that is, towards those who would 
typically be covered by health insurance program 
expansions. In turn, this might lead to a reduction in the 
quality of public services provided and to a subsequent 
switch to the utilisation of private services. 
Finally, factors specific to the LMIC context 
may influence the impact of health insurance, 
including a lack of awareness of or trust in public 
programs and a lack of access to health-care 
infrastructure (e.g. Svoronos et al., 2014). </p>

<p>(ii) Identification Issues 
Identifying the effects of health insurance is 
very challenging. A simple comparison of means 
for the insured and the uninsured using observa-
tional data does not help, since health insurance 
coverage is not random, but rather the outcome of 
demand and supply factors, some of which are a 
function of health status and individual or house-
hold preferences. A simple comparison would 
give biased estimates: it would reflect the causal 
effect of health insurance combined with the 
effect of unmeasured characteristics that are 
correlated with health insurance coverage. The 
direction of the bias due to unobserved hetero-
geneity is unclear. It could be positive due to </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>adverse selection. Children in worse health are 
more likely to demand health insurance, but also 
to demand more health care. The bias could be 
negative when health insurance programs are 
made available to children who are likely to be 
healthier, such as children enrolled in school. An 
additional challenge is that health insurance 
expansions could be part of broader health sector 
reforms that simultaneously affect the supply and 
demand side of health care, which makes it 
difficult to isolate the effect of health insurance. 
The best-known, and only long-term, experi-
mental study on the impact of health insurance on 
care utilisation and health outcomes is the RAND 
Health Insurance Experiment conducted in the 
USA in the 1970s and 1980s, which found that 
participants who received free care used more 
health care than those who paid a co-payment 
(Manning et al., 1987). The study showed little 
difference in the health outcomes of participants 
who received free care compared to those who 
paid a share of their health care. It is noted that 
the study did not evaluate the impact of having 
insurance per se but rather randomised individ-
uals by level of co-payment. </p>

<p>III Methodology </p>

<p>(i) Inclusion Criteria 
This review included evaluation studies that 
had the following characteristics: </p>

<p>1 Studies assessed the impact of health insurance 
on at least one quantifiable outcome for chil-
dren and/or households. 
2 Studies were conducted in LMICs as per the 
World Bank country classification. 
3 Studies were published or made available since 
2000. This criterion was used to include studies 
with recent or current relevant policy contexts. 
4 Studies covered universal health insurance 
programs (for the entire population) and health 
insurance programs targeted at children. Health 
insurance programs targeted at pregnant moth-
ers are beyond the scope of the study. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 This literature review is limited to studies that 
use a rigorous econometric analysis that 
attempts to address the endogeneity of health 
insurance. This can be done when subjects are 
randomly assigned to different health insur-
ance coverage as in the case of the RAND 
experiment mentioned above. Besides ran-
domised controlled trials, most commonly used 
methods mainly include the following: differ-
ence-in-difference estimation, propensity score 
matching, regression discontinuity, instrumen-
tal variable methods, or a mix of these methods 
(Khandker et al., 2010). Using one of the 
methods above was not necessarily considered 
enough for a study to be included: three of the 
authors read and assessed the quality of the 
evaluation design for all screened papers. </p>

<p>(ii) Search Strategy 
Relevant reports and papers, both published 
and unpublished, were identified according to the 
following steps: </p>

<p>1 Electronic databases. We conducted several 
database searches. We started with three 
databases where relevant quantitative impact 
evaluations were expected to be found: Econ-
Lit, the Impact Evaluation Repository of the 
International Initiave for Impact Evaluation 
(3ie), and PubMed. In addition, as a check, we 
performed a cross-database search using the 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">EBSCO</rs> Discovery Service (<rs id="software-0" type="software">OneSearch</rs>) that 
covered the following databases: Medline, 
SocIndex, Science Direct, JSTOR journals, 
PsycInfo and SocWork Abstracts. 
2 Citation chasing. The reference list of every 
included paper was checked to identify any 
possible additional studies. 
3 Internet searches. Finally, we used the 
advanced search options in <rs type="software">Google</rs> and <rs type="software">Google Scholar</rs> for a search of the World Wide Web. </p>

<p>In each database, we used combinations of 
keywords that dealt with: (i) relevance to the 
research question (health insurance, health cover-
age, children); (ii) relevance to the LMIC context 
(LMIC, developing country); (iii) outcomes such 
as health-care utilisation, health expenditures, and 
health outcomes (e.g. stunting, child wasting); and 
(iv) econometric analysis (impact evaluation). The 
search was restricted to English-language studies. </p>

<p>(iii) Screening 
Several database searches led to several thou-
sand citations in total. Many citations could </p>

<p>3 However, in studies of universal health insurance 
programs, and in studies of programmes targeted at 
children in settings that also have maternal pro-
grammes, the measured impact of health insurance on 
children may include, to some extent, the impact on 
children of providing health insurance to pregnant 
mothers. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>easily be excluded given the lack of relevance 
based on the title. If the study was included based 
on the title, the abstract was then reviewed. If the 
study was included based on the abstract, the full 
text of the article was retrieved and checked 
against the inclusion criteria above. We report 
below on our main database searches. Other 
searches (within the same database using differ-
ent terms, or in different databases) did not lead 
to any additional results. 
The EconLit search with 'health insurance' and 
'children' as search terms connected with the 
Boolean operator (AND) yielded 246 papers, of 
which we included seven published or working 
papers. 
The 3ie repository, using 'health insurance' as 
a search term, led to 69 results, of which we 
included six papers (two of these six papers had 
already been found in EconLit). 
The PubMed database (using 'health insur-
ance', 'children' and 'developing countries') led 
to 211 papers: we excluded all but two studies, 
both of which had already been found in the 
EconLit and 3ie searches. 
We checked the results of the above searches 
with a cross-database search using the EBSCO 
Discovery Service for the cross-database search. 
This search yielded 838 records, none of which 
were in addition to those that had been previously 
identified through the search of EconLit, Pub Med 
and the 3ie repository. 
Finally, through citation chasing and internet 
searches, we identified two more papers, leading 
to a total of 13 papers. 
It should be noted that we do not aggregate the 
outcomes of the studies into a meta-analysis. 
Many of the outcome measures and estimation 
strategies that we found were not comparable 
across studies, and the insurance programs were 
different across countries. It would thus be 
misleading to aggregate their results. </p>

<p>IV Results 
In total, the review led to 13 papers that cover 
health insurance expansion programs in seven 
countries: Burkina Faso, Colombia, China, the 
Philippines, Rwanda, Thailand and Vietnam. The 
characteristics of each of these programs are 
presented in Appendix Table A1. An overview of 
these articles is given in Table 1 and each of them 
is synthesised in Table 2. Results in Tables 2-4 
are first listed for programs targeted at children 
and then for other programs. Seven out of 13 
papers are concerned with health insurance </p>

<p>expansion for the general population in Burkina 
Faso (Fink et al., 2013), China (Wagstaff &amp; Yu,  2007; Chen &amp; Jin, 2012), Colombia (Giedion &amp;  Uribe, 2009; Miller et al., 2013), Rwanda (Lu  et al., 2012), and Thailand (Gruber et al., 2014). 
Five papers cover health insurance programs 
targeted at children in the Philippines (Kraft  et al., 2009; Quimbo et al., 2011) and Vietnam 
(Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005; Nguyen &amp; Wang,  2013; Guindon, 2014; Palmer et al., 2015). It 
should be noted that one paper (Guindon, 2014)  deals with both a program targeted at children and 
a program for a larger population. </p>

<p>4   With respect to methodology, three articles 
used a difference-in-difference design (Nguyen &amp;  Wang, 2013; Gruber et al., 2014; Guindon,  2014), one paper used propensity score matching 
(Lu et al., 2012), four papers used difference-in-
difference and propensity score matching com-
bined (Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005; Wagstaff &amp;  Yu, 2007; Giedion &amp; Uribe, 2009; Chen &amp; Jin,  2012), three papers used a randomised controlled 
trial (Kraft et al., 2009; Quimbo et al., 2011;  Fink et al., 2013), and two papers used a regres-
sion discontinuity design (Miller et al., 2013;  Palmer et al., 2015). </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Overview of 13 Studies in the Review </p>

<p>Number of 
studies </p>

<p>Scope of insurance programs* 
Programs targeted at children 
5 
Other programs 
9 
Methodology 
Difference-in-difference (DID) 
3 
Propensity score matching (PSM) 
1 
DID and PSM combined 
4 
Randomised controlled trial 
3 
Regression discontinuity design 
2 
Relevant outcomes 
Service utilisation 
10 
Financial protection 
9 
Health outcomes 
10 </p>

<p>Note: 
* One study (Guindon, 2014) covers a program targeted 
at children and another program that is not targeted, hence the 
number of studies here sums to 14. </p>

<p>4 Its characteristics and results are listed for the two 
programs separately in Tables 2-4. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Descriptions of Studies </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Insurance 
program </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Utilisation </p>

<p>Financial 
protection </p>

<p>Health 
Outcomes </p>

<p>Programs targeted at children 
Guindon 
(2014) </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Free Care for 
Children under </p>

<p>Six (FCCU6) </p>

<p>DID </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Household </p>

<p>Living 
Standards 
Survey 
(VHLSS) 2004, </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>6,923 
children </p>

<p>Number of 
inpatient visits </p>

<p>Number of 
sickness </p>

<p>days </p>

<p>Number of 
outpatient visits </p>

<p>Number of </p>

<p>bed days </p>

<p>Kraft et al. 
(2009) </p>

<p>Philippines </p>

<p>Philippine </p>

<p>Child Health 
Insurance and 
Policy 
Experiment </p>

<p>Randomised 
controlled </p>

<p>trial </p>

<p>Quality 
Improvement 
Demonstration </p>

<p>4,070 
children </p>

<p>Delay in 
utilisation </p>

<p>Total health 
expenditures </p>

<p>C-reactive 
protein 
positive 
(infection) 
wasting </p>

<p>Study (QIDS) 
2003/2004, </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>Nguyen and 
Wang (2013) </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Free Care for 
Children under </p>

<p>Six (FCCU6) </p>

<p>DID </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Household </p>

<p>Living </p>

<p>4,093 
children </p>

<p>Outpatient </p>

<p>visits (public, 
private) </p>

<p>OOP 
expenditures </p>

<p>Number of </p>

<p>sick days </p>

<p>Control group </p>

<p>of 6 </p>

<p>-7-year-</p>

<p>olds </p>

<p>Standard 
Survey 
(VHLSS) 2004, </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>Inpatient visits 
(public only) </p>

<p>Probability of 
catastrophic 
expenditures </p>

<p>Palmer et al. 
(2015) </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Free Care for 
Children under </p>

<p>Six (FCCU6) </p>

<p>Regression 
discontinuity </p>

<p>design </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Household </p>

<p>Living 
Standards 
Survey 
(VHLSS) 2006, </p>

<p>2008, 2010 </p>

<p>18,517 
children </p>

<p>Outpatient </p>

<p>visits (number 
and probability, 
public and 
private) </p>

<p>Expenditures </p>

<p>per visit </p>

<p>Inpatient visits 
(number and 
probability) </p>

<p>Quimbo et al. 
(2011) </p>

<p>Philippines </p>

<p>Philippine </p>

<p>Child Health 
Insurance and </p>

<p>Randomised 
controlled trial </p>

<p>Quality 
Improvement 
Demonstration </p>

<p>Study (QIDS) </p>

<p>1,100 
children </p>

<p>Wasting </p>

<p>and 
having an 
infection </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
(continued) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Insurance 
program </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Utilisation </p>

<p>Financial 
protection </p>

<p>Health 
Outcomes </p>

<p>Policy 
Experiment </p>

<p>2003/2004, </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>tested 
through 
C-reactive 
protein at 
discharge </p>

<p>and lagged </p>

<p>Targets poor 
children, 
hospital users </p>

<p>Other programs 
Chen and Jin 
(2012) </p>

<p>Rural 
China </p>

<p>New 
Cooperative </p>

<p>Medical System 
(NCMS); 
introduced to </p>

<p>some provinces 
by 2006 </p>

<p>PSM and DID 
combined </p>

<p>China 
Agricultural </p>

<p>Census (CAC) 
2006 for eight 
low income 
rural counties </p>

<p>1.4 million 
individuals 
children: </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Under-5 
mortality </p>

<p>Fink et al. 
(2013) </p>

<p>Burkina 
Faso </p>

<p>Community-</p>

<p>Based 
Insurance </p>

<p>Randomisation </p>

<p>of the rollout of 
the insurance 
scheme </p>

<p>Nouna 
Health and 
Demographic 
Surveillance </p>

<p>Site Survey, 
2003 </p>

<p>-2008 
240 children 
under 5 </p>

<p>OOP 
expenditures </p>

<p>Under-5 
mortality </p>

<p>Catastrophic </p>

<p>level 
expenditures </p>

<p>Giedion and 
Uribe (2009) </p>

<p>Colombia </p>

<p>Subsidised 
Regime (SR) </p>

<p>For 
expenditures: 
Instrumental </p>

<p>variable for </p>

<p>CR and PSM 
for SR </p>

<p>Demographic </p>

<p>and Health 
Survey 1995, 
2005 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>Likelihood for </p>

<p>child under age </p>

<p>1 to visit 
health-care </p>

<p>facility if 
coughing or 
suffering from 
diarrhoea </p>

<p>Probability of 
catastophic </p>

<p>health care 
expenditures </p>

<p>for SR 
population </p>

<p>Contributory </p>

<p>Regime (CR) </p>

<p>For other 
outcomes: </p>

<p>PSM and DID 
combined </p>

<p>Living 
Standards 
Measurement </p>

<p>Survey 2003 </p>

<p>Immunisations </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
(continued) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Insurance 
program </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Utilisation </p>

<p>Financial 
protection </p>

<p>Health 
Outcomes </p>

<p>Guindon 
(2014) </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Free Care for 
Children under </p>

<p>Six (FCCU6) 
Voluntary 
Health 
Insurance for 
school children 
and students </p>

<p>DID </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Household </p>

<p>Living 
Standards 
Survey 
(VHLSS) 2004, </p>

<p>2006 </p>

<p>1,119 
children </p>

<p>Number of 
inpatient visits </p>

<p>Number of 
sickness </p>

<p>days </p>

<p>Number of 
outpatient visits </p>

<p>Number of </p>

<p>bed days </p>

<p>Gruber et al. 
(2014) </p>

<p>Thailand </p>

<p>30 Baht 
program: 
Coverage of 
general 
population for 
services at 
public 
facilities, 
reduction of </p>

<p>copay down to 
30 baht (75c per 
visit) </p>

<p>DID </p>

<p>Health &amp; 
Welfare Survey 
2001, 2003, 
2005 </p>

<p>383,469 
individuals </p>

<p>Inpatient 
utilisation rate </p>

<p>Infant 
mortality </p>

<p>rate at the 
province </p>

<p>level </p>

<p>Lu et al. 
(2012) </p>

<p>Rwanda </p>

<p>Mutuelles, 
community-</p>

<p>based health 
insurance 
program </p>

<p>PSM </p>

<p>Integrated </p>

<p>Living 
Conditions </p>

<p>Survey 2000, 
2005/2006 </p>

<p>7,304 
children </p>

<p>Health care 
facility visit for 
acute 
respiratory 
infection, fever </p>

<p>or diarrhoea for 
children 
under 5 </p>

<p>OOP 
expenditures </p>

<p>PSM with 
instrumental </p>

<p>variable </p>

<p>Rwanda 
Demographic </p>

<p>Health Survey 
2000, 2005, 
2007/2008 </p>

<p>Catastrophic </p>

<p>health 
spending </p>

<p>Miller et al. 
(2013) </p>

<p>Colombia </p>

<p>Subsidised </p>

<p>regime </p>

<p>Regression 
discontinuity </p>

<p>design </p>

<p>2005 
Demographic &amp; </p>

<p>Health Survey </p>

<p>1,161 
children </p>

<p>Use of 
preventive care </p>

<p>Individual 
inpatient </p>

<p>Days lost 
due 
to illness </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
(continued) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>Insurance 
program </p>

<p>Methodology </p>

<p>Data </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Utilisation </p>

<p>Financial 
protection </p>

<p>Health 
Outcomes </p>

<p>medical 
spending </p>

<p>2003 Encuentas 
de Calidad de 
Vida </p>

<p>Use of curative 
care </p>

<p>Individual 
outpatient 
medical 
spending </p>

<p>Cough, 
fever, 
diarrhoea </p>

<p>Any health 
problem 
Birthweight </p>

<p>Wagstaff and 
Pradhan 
(2005) </p>

<p>Vietnam </p>

<p>Voluntary </p>

<p>health 
insurance 
DID and PSM 
combined </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Household </p>

<p>Living Standard 
Survey 
(VHLSS) 1992/ </p>

<p>1993, 1997/ 
1998 </p>

<p>17,824 
individuals 
children: </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>At least one 
contact with a 
health service 
provider among </p>

<p>sick 
(probability) 
OOP health 
expenditures </p>

<p>Weight </p>

<p>for age 
(children) </p>

<p>Non-medical 
household 
expenditures </p>

<p>Height for 
age 
(children) </p>

<p>Wagstaff and </p>

<p>Yu (2007) </p>

<p>China 
(Gansu 
Province) 
World Bank's 
Health VIII 
Project: 
program which 
includes 
supply-and 
demand-side </p>

<p>reforms, incl. 
community </p>

<p>health 
insurance for 
general 
population 
DID and PSM 
combined </p>

<p>Gansu Survey </p>

<p>of Children and 
Families, June </p>

<p>2000 to mid-
2004 Survey 
focused on 
families with 
children aged </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>-12 </p>

<p>1,334 
children 
Taken to doctor </p>

<p>in last year </p>

<p>Catastrophic </p>

<p>health 
spending </p>

<p>Ill in the 
last year </p>

<p>Highest level 
provider used in </p>

<p>12 months </p>

<p>Notes: 
This table only includes outcomes relevant to children or to their households. The definition of catastrophic spending may vary from study to study. It is usually 
expressed as a share of out-of-pocket (OOP) expenditures out of per capita income. For instance, Wagstaff and Yu (2007) define catastrophic spending as share of annual 
spending in excess of 10% per capita income. NA stands for not available. DID refers to difference in difference, and PSM to propensity score matching. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>The studies use a variety of outcomes: ten 
studies have service utilisation outcomes, nine 
have financial protection outcomes, and ten have 
health outcomes. It should be noted that in these 
studies, utilisation and health outcomes are mea-
sured at the child level, while financial protection 
is typically measured at the household level. Only 
three studies pay attention to subgroups of 
children or their households: Giedion and Uribe 
(2009) among urban, rural, poorest and poor 
quintiles; Wagstaff and Pradhan (2005) and 
Wagstaff and Yu (2007) by income quintile. </p>

<p>(i) Effects on Service Utilisation 
Ten studies assessed the impact of health 
insurance on health-care utilisation in six coun-
tries. Their main results are presented in Table 3. 
Broadly, health-care utilisation refers to individ-
uals seeking care for ailments, injuries or pre-
ventive care. Services may include well care 
visits, sick and emergency outpatient care, and 
inpatient care (hospital admissions). Several 
papers use broad health-care utilisation outcome 
measures, such as any contact with a service 
provider (Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005) while other 
papers use specific service utilisation indicators 
such as visits to health-care providers among 
children under 5 with acute respiratory infections, 
diarrhoea or fever (Lu et al., 2012). 
Six of these ten studies find positive effects of 
health insurance on care utilisation for children 
(Giedion &amp; Uribe, 2009; Kraft et al., 2009; Lu  et al., 2012; Miller et al., 2013; Gruber et al.,  2014; Palmer et al., 2015). For instance, for 
Colombia, Giedion and Uribe (2009) find that 
the likelihood that a child gets immunised and 
that a child with a cough visits a health-care 
facility were 6.1 per cent and 10.7 per cent 
greater respectively for those under the insurance 
program (Giedion &amp; Uribe, 2009). For Thailand, 
Gruber et al. (2014) show that the '30 Baht' 
program led to a 12 per cent increase in inpatient 
health service utilisation for the overall popula-
tion during its first 4 years. For infants (0-1 years 
of age) and women of child-bearing age service 
utilisation grew 2.5 times faster. In the Philip-
pines, Kraft et al. (2009) find that delays in 
seeking care were 5.3 per cent lower in health 
insurance intervention sites than compared to 
control sites. 
The other four studies have mixed results, 
depending on the age group of children, the type 
of services (e.g. inpatient versus outpatient), the 
unit of analysis or the evaluation methodology. </p>

<p>Wagstaff and Yu (2007) have mixed results on the 
impact of the World Bank's Health VIII project in 
Gansu province, China, on the use of health 
services. For instance, it leads to an increase in 
hepatitis B immunisation at the county level, but 
has a negative impact on immunisations overall at 
the village level (this latter result is sensitive to 
the econometric specification). For the case of 
Vietnam, Wagstaff and Pradhan (2005) find for 
the Voluntary Health Insurance program that the 
probability of contact with a health-care provider 
for a sick person increases for children 5 and 
over, but not for children under 5. Guindon  (2014) finds that Vietnam's health insurance 
program for children under 6 increases outpatient 
visits by 17 per cent but has no significant effect 
on inpatient admissions, while Nguyen and Wang  (2013) find for the very same program a signif-
icant increase in inpatient care but no significant 
change in outpatient care. Both Guindon (2014)  and Nguyen and Wang (2013) use difference-in-
difference estimation strategies and the Vietnam 
Household Living Standard Survey. However, 
they use different control groups, which may 
explain the difference in results. Using an alter-
native regression discontinuity design, Palmer  et al. (2015) find a positive utilisation impact for 
both inpatient and outpatient services. Consistent 
with Guindon (2014), the authors find a larger 
impact on outpatient service utilisation. </p>

<p>(ii) Effects on Financial Protection 
We reviewed ten studies that analysed the 
effects of health insurance on financial protec-
tion. Financial protection is measured through 
catastrophic health spending and/or out-of-pocket 
health expenditures, and the variability of med-
ical spending (Table 3). Catastrophic spending is 
understood as a level of health-care expenditures 
that exceeds a given threshold of income, which 
is typically proxied by consumption expenditures 
as a more permanent measure of income in 
LMICs settings. Thresholds and consumption 
expenditure types vary from study to study. For 
instance, Wagstaff and Yu (2007) define it as 
spending exceeding 10 per cent of total consump-
tion expenditures, which is the most commonly 
used threshold when total expenditure is used as 
the denominator. In addition, one has to bear in 
mind that financial protection is usually measured 
at the household level. In the case of household-
level outcomes, for insurance programs targeted 
at children, a lack of change in expenditures, for 
instance, could be due to a redistribution of </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>expenditures towards uninsured individuals in the 
household. Results thus need to be interpreted 
with caution. 
The five papers that use catastrophic spending 
as a financial protection indicator find that health </p>

<p>insurance reduces the likelihood of catastrophic 
spending (Wagstaff &amp; Yu, 2007; Giedion &amp;  Uribe, 2009; Lu et al., 2012; Fink et al., 2013;  Nguyen &amp; Wang, 2013). Out of the six papers that 
use out-of-pocket health expenditures as an </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Main Results on Utilisation and Expenditures </p>

<p>Reference 
Results </p>

<p>Programs targeted at children 
Guindon (2014)  Increase in outpatient visits by 17% for children under 6 
No significant effect found on inpatient admissions for children under 6 
Kraft et al. (2009)  Delays in seeking care were 5.29% lower in the intervention sites (insurance) than in the 
control sites 
Nguyen and Wang  (2013)   An increase in total utilisation (private and public), but not statistically significant 
Increase in inpatient admissions in public hospitals. No consistent effect was found on 
the number of outpatient contact in the public sector, nor in the private sector 
OOP spending and the probability of catastrophic spending was significantly reduced in 
one of two models 
Palmer et al. 
(2015) </p>

<p>Insurance for children under 6 increases the probability of an inpatient visit (+6.8%) and 
an outpatient visit (+21.7%) 
Insurance increases the average number of inpatient (+1.13) and outpatient visits (+0.75) 
No significant impact with respect to OOP expenditures 
Other programs 
Fink et al. (2013)  Insurance had negative but small effect on average OOP expenditures in the target areas, 
but reduced by 30% the likelihood of catastrophic health expenditure 
Giedion and Uribe  (2009)   Insurance improved access and utilisation for both the SR and the CR programs (e.g. 
child taken to health care facility when coughing (+10.7%) or having diarrhoea (+7.4%), 
child immunisation complete (+6.1%)) 
Insurance has reduced the incidence of catastrophic health spending, especially among 
more disadvantaged groups (those in rural areas, poorest and self-employed) 
Guindon (2014)  Twofold increase in inpatient admissions for school-age children and students, but no 
effect found on outpatient visits 
Gruber et al. 
(2014) </p>

<p>Increase by 12% for the general population of the overall inpatient utilisation rate 
Increase in overall utilisation rate is 2.5 times bigger for women and infants 
Substitution of public for private care for general population 
Lu et al. (2012)  Visits to health-care facilities for under-5 children with acute respiratory infection, 
diarrhoea, or fever increased two-to threefold due to insurance 
Reduction in OOP expenditures and in the probability of catastrophic health-care 
spending for overall population with health insurance 
Miller et al. (2013)  SR eligibility is associated with reductions in the variability* of inpatient medical 
spending 
Significant increase in use of preventive care (preventive physician visit and number of 
growth development checks last year) 
No change found for curative medical care among children 
Wagstaff and  Pradhan (2005) </p>

<p>The probability of contact with a health-care provider for a sick person increased for 
children 5 and over (+3.9%), but not for children under 5 
Some reduction in OOP expenditures 
Increase in non-medical expenditures, by more than reduced OOP 
Wagstaff and Yu  (2007)   Little impact is found on the use of services (for instance, Increase in hepatitis B and 
polio immunisation at the county level, but negative impact on overall immunisations at 
the village level (although this result holds only for one specification) 
Reduced OOP spending, and the incidence of catastrophic spending and impoverishment 
through health expenses </p>

<p>Note: 
* Variability is defined as the difference between individual spending and county mean spending. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>indicator of financial protection, five find that 
health insurance has a negative and significant 
effect (Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005; Wagstaff &amp;  Yu, 2007; Lu et al., 2012; Fink et al., 2013;  Nguyen &amp; Wang, 2013). Only Palmer et al.  (2015) does not find evidence of a significant 
effect on out-of-pocket health expenditures for 
Vietnam's health insurance program for children 
under age 6. This result is consistent with the 
result of the Nguyen and Wang (2013) study of 
the same program for children aged 0-3, but 
different from the negative and significant impact 
on expenditures they find for children aged 4-5. 
This difference in results for children aged 4-5 
could come from the difference in sample and 
methodology: Nguyen and Wang (2013) use a 
sample of non-poor children only with two waves 
of the Vietnam Household Living Standard </p>

<p>Survey (2004 and 2006) and with a difference-
in-difference estimation, while Palmer et al.'s  (2015) estimates are for all children near the age 
cut-off of 6 using regression discontinuity and 
based on 2006, 2008 and 2010 Vietnam House-
hold Living Standard Survey data. 
Finally, Miller et al. (2013) find that insurance 
in Colombia is associated with reductions in the 
variability of inpatient medical spending, where 
variability is defined in terms of the difference 
between the individual medical spending and the 
county mean medical spending. </p>

<p>(iii) Effects on Health Outcomes 
Ten of the 13 studies we examined assessed the 
impact of health insurance on health outcomes in 
LMICs. Their main results are presented in 
Table 4. Among the health outcomes were </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Main Results on Health Outcomes </p>



<p>Programs targeted at children 
Kraft et al. (2009) 
Authors infer that insurance may have positive effects on health outcomes and 
expenditures given that health insurance reduces delays 
Delays in seeking care by 2+ days increased probability of wasting by 4.6% 
Nguyen and Wang 
(2013) </p>

<p>Number of sick days was reduced (statistically significant only at 10%) in one of two 
models 
Quimbo et al. 
(2011) </p>

<p>At discharge: no effect on C-reactive protein (CRP) </p>

<p>Post-discharge (4 -10 weeks later): intervention reduces probability of testing CRP 
positive by 4 -9 percentage points and of wasting by 9 -12 percentage points 
Other programs 
Chen and Jin 
(2012) </p>

<p>Effect found on child mortality and school enrolment with raw data or PSM model. 
However, after controlling for selection bias by combining 
DID and PSM, the New Cooperative Medical System (NCMS) has no effect on under-5 
mortality 
Fink et al. (2013) 
No significant effect on under-5 mortality was found 
Guindon (2014) 
No signicant effect of voluntary health insurance program found on number of sick or bed 
days for students 
Gruber et al. 
(2014) </p>

<p>Reduction in infant mortality: a 10% increase in the fraction enrolled in the program 
reduced infant mortality by 0.65 per 1,000 births 
Miller et al. (2013) 
SR enrolment is associated with 1.4 fewer child days absent from usual activities due to 
illness in the past month 
18 percentage point reduction in the self-reported incidence of cough, fever or diarrhoea 
among children, but not statistically significant 
Wagstaff and 
Pradhan (2005) </p>

<p>Children under 5 increased height-and weight-for-age by 2.35 cm (2%) and 0.75 kg 
(4%), respectively. No significant effect found for older children 
Wagstaff and Yu 
(2007) </p>

<p>Reduction of illness among children* </p>

<p>Note: 
* This result for children is presented in the working paper of Wagstaff and Yu (2007) and is consistent with a similar effect 
for the entire population given in the published version. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>mortality (Chen &amp; Jin, 2012; Fink et al., 2013;  Gruber et al., 2014), morbidity (Wagstaff &amp; Yu,  2007; Quimbo et al., 2011; Miller et al., 2013;  Nguyen &amp; Wang, 2013; Guindon, 2014), anthro-
pometric outcomes (Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005;  Kraft et al., 2009; Quimbo et al., 2011) and broad 
activity limitation (Miller et al., 2013). 
Four of the ten studies find that health insur-
ance leads to health improvements (Wagstaff &amp;  Yu, 2007; Kraft et al., 2009; Nguyen &amp; Wang,  2013; Gruber et al., 2014). For instance, Gruber  et al. (2014) find a reduction in infant mortality: a 
10 per cent increase in the fraction enrolled in the 
program reduced infant mortality by 0.65 per 
1,000 births. 
Three studies had results that were mixed 
(Wagstaff &amp; Pradhan, 2005; Quimbo et al.,  2011; Miller et al., 2013). Quimbo et al. (2011)  find that insurance sites during the random trial </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>experienced a 9 per cent reduction in the prob-
ability of wasting but no statistically significant 
difference between insured and uninsured in the 
rate of infection detected at hospital discharge. 
Miller et al. (2013) find no significant effect on 
the incidence of cough but a significant reduction 
in the number of days when children are not able 
to do their usual activities. Wagstaff and Pradhan  (2005) find improvements in anthropometric out-
comes among children under 5 but not among 
older children. 
Finally, three other studies (Chen &amp; Jin, 2012;  Fink et al., 2013; Guindon, 2014) do not find any 
significant effect on health outcomes (number of 
sickness or bed days and under-5 mortality, 
respectively). </p>

<p>V Discussion and Conclusions 
Despite a growing and large literature on the 
impact of health insurance in LMICs (Giedion &amp;  D ıaz, 2010; Spaan et al., 2012), we find only 13 
studies for seven countries that assess the impact 
of health insurance on children. Nine out of 10 
studies reviewed in this paper provide consistent 
evidence that health insurance provides financial 
protection. The results are more mixed when it 
comes to health-care utilisation and health out-
comes: a positive effect was found in six out of 10 
studies for health-care utilisation and in four out 
of 10 studies for health outcomes. For health-care </p>

<p>utilisation, the other four studies offer mixed 
results. 
A number of interesting discussion points 
emerge from this review. The general synthesis 
of results for the 13 studies is that insurance helps 
with financial protection while providing mixed 
impact on utilisation and health outcomes for 
children. This stands in contrast to results of other 
reviews. For instance, Giedion et al. (2013), 
considering broadly universal health care, finds 
that insurance tends to increase levels of utilisa-
tion across all services but has little to no impact 
on financial protection. For the informal sector, 
Acharya et al. (2013) find no evidence that health 
insurance in the informal sector impacts utilisa-
tion, financial protection and health outcomes. 
The mixed results in this review regarding 
overall utilisation may be explained by the fact 
that children under insurance tend to use primary 
and preventative services at a higher rate than 
inpatient services. Two studies in Vietnam found 
a larger impact of health insurance on the use of 
outpatient relative to inpatient care for children 
under the age of 6 (Nguyen et al., 2012; Palmer  et al., 2015). This finding is consistent with the 
RAND experiment where co-payments did not 
affect the probability of an inpatient visit of 
children (Manning et al., 1987). Improved access 
to primary and preventative care such as immu-
nisations through outpatient contacts may have 
led to a reduction in the probability of hospital-
isation for insured younger children. These ser-
vices are also typically better covered than 
inpatient services under insurance, which may 
explain negative impacts on the financial burden 
of accessing care. 
Several studies cover the same programs in 
Vietnam. Two studies cover the Voluntary Health 
Insurance program and its impact on school-age 
children and have consistent results overall, 
although the data come from the 1990s for 
Wagstaff and Pradhan (2005) and from the 
2000s for Guindon (2014). In addition, three 
studies assess Vietnam's health insurance pro-
gram for children under age 6 using the same data 
but different methods. They return findings that 
are somewhat different on health-care utilisation 
and financial protection. For instance, Palmer  et al. (2015) find a significant increase in both 
outpatient and inpatient utilisation, while Guin-
don (2014) finds a significant effect only for 
outpatient visits, and Nguyen and Wang (2013)  do not. </p>

<p>5 The trial was conducted in the late 1990s and early 
2000s. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>To the extent that different methods address 
endogeneity in differing degrees, concerns of 
self-selection and unobserved heterogeneity may 
be a significant issue, at least in the case of health 
insurance for young children in Vietnam. Fur-
thermore, the estimation of different treatment 
effects -local average treatment effect for 
regression discontinuity (Palmer et al., 2015)  versus average treatment effect for the differ-
ence-in-difference estimation strategy for the 
other two papers -may have contributed to the 
different findings. These different results for 
Vietnam's programs contrast with those from a 
review of the literature in the United States where 
studies with different methods lead to similar 
results (Buchmueller et al., 2005). 
This review is not without limitations, and thus 
gives rise to opportunities for further research. 
The greatest limitation relates to the small num-
ber of robust studies on the topic. More research 
is needed that evaluates the impact of health 
insurance programs on children in LMICs, as 
many countries are adopting or are considering 
adopting health insurance programs, or are 
broadly moving towards universal health care. 
The findings of the review are of course con-
strained by the limitations of the studies in the 
literature. Many studies on the impact of univer-
sal health insurance programs in LMICs do not 
present separate results for children and thus did 
not meet the search criteria of this review (e.g. 
Jowett et al., 2003; Axelson et al., 2009; Wag- staff, 2010; Nguyen, 2011). This represents a 
missed opportunity to understand the health-
seeking behaviours and health outcomes of this 
important subpopulation. More research is needed 
that evaluates the impact of health insurance 
programs targeted at children, and studies that 
assess the impact of insurance programs for all 
ages need to separate out effects on children. 
In addition, in the seven studies on health 
insurance programs for all ages included in this 
review, a comparison of results on utilisation and 
health outcomes for adults and children is done in 
only three studies (Chen &amp; Jin, 2012; Fink et al.,  2013; Lu et al., 2012). In three studies, the 
comparison is not possible because different 
utilisation or health outcome indicators are used 
for children (e.g. immunisations completed). 
When generic indicators are used (e.g. number 
of inpatient or outpatient visits), studies should, 
when possible, break down results for adults and 
children due to potentially different health-care-
seeking behaviours as well as the inherent </p>

<p>importance of child health to human develop-
ment. 
Future studies also need to document and 
identify the effects of specific characteristics of 
health insurance programs (e.g. benefits, co-
payments) and of supply-side factors. Three-
quarters of the papers under review are focused 
on Asian countries so there exists a geographical 
limitation, with only few impact evaluations for 
Africa and Latin America. In addition, only three 
studies reviewed in this paper evaluated impacts 
on subgroups of children. More nuanced research 
is needed on how health insurance affects chil-
dren from ethnic minorities, children with dis-
abilities, children with chronic health conditions 
and poor children. 
Only three of the studies in the review analyse 
the supply-side aspects of the health insurance 
program or of a broader health-care reform 
(Wagstaff &amp; Yu, 2007; Giedion &amp; Uribe, 2009;  Gruber et al., 2014), and three more studies 
mention in the discussion how supply-side factors 
could be affecting their results (Chen &amp; Jin, 2012;  Fink et al., 2013; Palmer et al., 2015). Results 
suggest that supply-side considerations are 
important factors influencing the consequences 
of health insurance reforms on children. For 
instance, Gruber et al. (2014) find that increased 
funding of hospitals for the poor, and reduced co-
payments, increased health-care utilisation, espe-
cially among the poor and reduced infant mor-
tality in poorer provinces in Thailand. More 
attention needs to be paid to the supply-side 
factors and how they may influence results of 
health insurance programs. 
Finally, the outcomes covered in the studies 
reviewed in this paper are limited by the data 
under study. They tend to be short-term outcomes 
and come from general household survey data 
that are collected for purposes other than studying 
health care and health insurance. They often lack 
details on insurance plans, health-care services 
and health status. For instance, regarding inpa-
tient care, we found several studies that examine 
the effects of insurance on any hospital utilisation 
by children. However, these studies do not 
differentiate between avoidable and unavoidable 
inpatient care, as has sometimes been done in the 
literature in high-income countries (Buchmueller  et al., 2005). Some of the mixed results on the 
impact of health insurance on care utilisation and 
health outcomes are perhaps due to the limited 
information available in standard household sur-
veys. For instance, measures of any contact with a </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>health provider in the past year are crude mea-
sures of health-care utilisation, and these may 
explain the Wagstaff and Pradhan (2005) finding 
that availability of health care has no effect for 
children under 5. Mortality used in some studies 
may be too crude a measure of health to capture 
health improvements that may result from health 
insurance and may explain why Chen and Jin  (2012) and Fink et al. (2013) find no effect on 
under-5 mortality. 
Further research is needed that enhances the 
study of service utilisation, financial protection, 
and health outcomes among children under insur-
ance in LMICs. Service utilisation indicators 
should be directly related to the benefits expected 
for the health insurance program under study. 
Health outcome indicators should be directly 
related to the health-care services that are 
expected to be affected by health insurance and 
that are likely to lead to health improvements 
(e.g. immunisation). Non-health outcome indica-
tors should also be considered: only one of the 
studies in this review covered a non-health 
outcome: Chen and Jin (2012) considering school 
enrolment. </p>



<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>



<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

<p> 
HEALTH INSURANCE AND CHILDREN </p>



<p>TABLE A1 </p>

<p>Characteristics of the Insurance Programs </p>

<p>Country </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Scheme name </p>

<p>Target beneficiaries </p>

<p>Eligibility </p>

<p>age </p>

<p>Financing </p>

<p>Administration Level </p>

<p>Programs targeted at children 
Philippines Kraft et al. </p>

<p>(2009), </p>

<p>Quimbo et al. 
(2011) </p>

<p>Philippine Child </p>

<p>Health Insurance &amp; 
Policy Experiment </p>

<p>(or the Quality 
Improvement 
Demonstration </p>

<p>Study) </p>

<p>Young children </p>

<p>6 Months 
to 5 Years </p>

<p>Government revenue </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>Regional </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Guindon (2014), 
Nguyen and Wang 
(2013), Palmer </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(2015) </p>

<p>Free Care for 
Children Under Six 
(FCCU6) </p>

<p>Young children </p>

<p>&lt;6 </p>

<p>Government revenue </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>National </p>

<p>Other programs 
Burkina 
Faso </p>

<p>Fink et al. </p>

<p>(2013) </p>

<p>Community-Based </p>

<p>Insurance (CBI) </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Private premium </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>Community </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>Chen and Jin 
(2012) </p>

<p>New Coorperative 
Medical System 
(NCMS) </p>

<p>Poor, rural </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Government revenue, </p>

<p>private payments 
(coinsurance) </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>Regional </p>

<p>Wagstaff and Yu 
(2007) </p>

<p>World Bank's 
Health VIII Project </p>

<p>Poor, rural </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Government revenue, </p>

<p>private payments 
(coinsurance) </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>Regional </p>

<p>Colombia 
Giedion and Uribe 
(2009) </p>

<p>Contributory </p>

<p>Regime (CR) </p>

<p>For those not 
targeted by other 
plans </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Private premium </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>individuals and 
employers </p>

<p>Private </p>

<p>National </p>

<p>Giedion and Uribe 
(2009), Miller </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(2013) </p>

<p>Subsidised Regime </p>

<p>(SR) </p>

<p>Poor </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Government revenue, </p>

<p>private payments 
(coinsurance) </p>

<p>Public and 
private </p>

<p>National </p>

<p>Rwanda </p>

<p>Lu et al. </p>

<p>(2012) 
Mutuelles de Sant e 
For all those not 
targeted by other 
plans </p>

<p>All 
60% private premium, 
low coinsurance; 40% 
government revenues </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>Community-</p>

<p>based but 
available 
nationally </p>

<p>Thailand 
Gruber et al. 
(2014) </p>

<p>30 Baht </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Government revenue </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>low co-pay </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>National </p>

<p>Vietnam 
Guindon (2014), 
Wagstaff and 
Pradhan (2005) </p>

<p>Voluntary Health 
Insurance </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>All </p>

<p>Private premium </p>

<p>Public </p>

<p>National </p>

<p>Appendix </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
SEPTEMBER </p>

<p>© 2017 The Authors. Economic Record published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd on behalf of 
Economic Society of Australia. </p>

</text></tei>