<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10290-016-0264-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract In May 2012 the Spanish government announced a debt-financed 
recapitalization of the undercapitalized Spanish banking system. Although there was 
a wide consensus among economists and policymakers that this was key to solving 
Spain's economic troubles, both bank CDS and sovereign CDS further increased in 
the days following the announcement while lower bank CDS spreads were expected. 
Higher sovereign debt discounts deteriorated the fiscal position of the Spanish 
government. We propose a mechanism that can explain the events in Spain, namely 
the interaction whereby weak banks that are heavily exposed to risky domestic 
sovereign debt and weak government finances set off a negative amplification cycle: 
additional debt issue leads to higher sovereign debt discounts, resulting in capital 
losses on existing sovereign debt, deteriorating the capital base of banks, additional 
rounds of interest rate increases, a perverse amplification cycle substantially off-
setting the initial recapitalization. We construct a DSGE model with balance-sheet-
constrained financial intermediaries that finance private loans to the real economy, 
as well as sovereign debt subject to sovereign default risk. We calibrate the model to 
Spanish data, and find that our model is capable of matching the developments in 
the sovereign bond market in Spain in May/June 2012 quite well. We investigate an </p>

<p>We acknowledge the generous support of the Dutch Organization for Sciences, through the NWO 
Research Talent Grant No. 406-13-063. We thank Matthijs Knijnenburg for excellent research 
assistance. </p>

<p>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this article (alternative policy, direct recapitalization by a foreign entity, such as the ESM, 
which avoids the negative sovereign risk amplification cycle. </p>

<p>In May 2012 the Spanish government announced a debt-financed recapitalization of 
the Spanish banking system, after the capital base of Spanish banks had been severely 
eroded following the end of the housing and construction boom of the 2000s. 
Conventional theory predicts that such a recapitalization should decrease bank CDS 
spreads, as happened in the US after the forced recapitalization of the larger US banks 
under the SCAP program of May 2009 (Hoshi and Kashyap 2014). And since the 
main risk to the Spanish government at the time seemed to be the risk of having to 
bail out the banking system, expectations were that CDS spreads on sovereign debt 
would fall as well. But contrary to predictions and apparently at variance with the US 
2009 experience, CDS spreads for the banks, after a short temporary dip immediately 
following the recap announcement, continued their rise after the announcements, and 
so did sovereign CDS spreads, as can be seen from Fig. 1. This is remarkable since, 
under normal circumstances, a recapitalization increases loss absorption capacity of 
the bank concerned and should result in lower CDS spreads. In turn looser leverage 
constraints for banks should lead to increased loan supply to non-financial firms, 
eventually generating higher tax revenues for the government. In addition, better 
capitalized banks reduce the probability of the need for a fiscally costly bail out. Both 
factors would lead one to expect lower CDS spreads for sovereigns too. Yet in Spain 
CDS spreads continued their upward drift with consequent effects on interest rates, 
deteriorating the fiscal position of the Spanish government further. In June 2012, the 
Spanish government applied for emergency funding from the EFSF/ESM. 
We will argue that the observed response can be explained by a negative 
feedback loop arising between undercapitalized banks that hold risky sovereign debt 
on the one hand and weak government finances on the other: 
1 issuing additional 
risky sovereign debt to fund a government bailout of commercial banks will lead to 
falling bond prices everything else equal; when commercial banks have a large 
exposure to this debt, they will therefore incur capital losses on these bonds. So 
falling bondprices imply that bank capital will take a hit, thereby limiting the 
headroom for new loans. Credit spreads and interest rates increase, and lead to lower 
private credit provision. Higher interest rates on government debt further increase 
the amount of debt the government needs to issue to fund its operations.But higher 
debt issue leads to a second round of bond price drops, and so on, setting off a 
vicious cycle whereby weak banks and weak sovereigns get into a negative </p>

<p>1 As in Acharya et al. (2014) and Van der Kwaak and Van Wijnbergen (2014). </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>amplification cycle. In such an environment, the capital losses on existing holdings 
of sovereign debt can potentially offset the initial increase in bank capital due to the 
recapitalization by the government. 
A key feature of this negative feedback loop is the fact that Spanish commercial 
banks were undercapitalized after the end of the housing and construction boom of 
the 2000s (International Monetary Fund 2011; Hoshi and Kashyap 2014). We 
therefore follow Gertler and Karadi (2011) and introduce balance-sheet-constrained 
financial intermediaries into a standard New-Keynesian DSGE model. 
2 We extend 
their setup in two directions: The first extension is to allow financial intermediaries 
to hold sovereign debt in addition to loans to the private sector. To allow for the 
possibility of capital losses on sovereign debt holdings, we introduce long-term 
maturity government bonds in a setup which is very similar to Woodford </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>02/05/2011 
02/06/2011 
02/07/2011 
02/08/2011 
02/09/2011 
02/10/2011 
02/11/2011 
02/12/2011 
02/01/2012 
02/02/2012 
02/03/2012 
02/04/2012 
02/05/2012 
02/06/2012 
02/07/2012 
02/08/2012 
02/09/2012 
02/10/2012 
02/11/2012 
02/12/2012 
02/01/2013 
02/02/2013 
02/03/2013 
02/04/2013 </p>

<p>5 yrs. Sovereign CDS </p>

<p>5 yrs. Bank CDS, fully restructured, senior 
unsecured </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Figure displaying CDS spreads. The blue slotted line depicts the CDS spread for Spanish 
sovereign debt with a maturity of 5 years, while the red solid line depicts the average CDS spread for 
Spanish banks (5 years, fully restructured, senior unsecured). The first vertical line is May 9th, 2012, at 
which the Spanish government announced the restructuring of the Spanish financial sector, while the 
second vertical line depicts June 25th, 2012, at which the eurogroup approved financial sector aid to 
Spain. Banks in the sample include Banco Popolare Espanol, Banco Santander, Caixa Bank and BBVA. 
Source: <rs type="software">Datastream</rs>, own calculations (color figure online) </p>

<p>2 Throughout the paper, we use 'commercial banks' and 'financial intermediaries' interchangeably to 
denote the same group of economic agents, which capture all kinds of credit institutions: commercial 
banks, savings banks, postbanks, and specialized credit institutions, among others. </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain </p>

<p>
(1998, 2001). Such a setup avoids the escalating dimension of the state space that a 
less parsimonious approach to lengthening maturity would lead to. The second 
extension is to introduce endogenous sovereign default risk following Schabert and  Van Wijnbergen (2014), which is a second channel that gives rise to potential 
capital losses on sovereign debt. The resulting default model is also used in Van der  Kwaak and Van Wijnbergen (2014). The production sector contains price-stickiness 
and monopolistic competition to have real effects from monetary policy. House-
holds consume, provide labor and save through deposits placed at financial 
intermediaries. Because our goal is to investigate whether the negative amplification 
cycles between weakly capitalized banks and weak sovereign finances can explain 
the failure of the Spanish government to recapitalize the Spanish financial sector, we 
calibrate the model to Spanish data by using parameters from the Bayesian 
estimation results by Burriel et al. (2010) where applicable, using in addition 
several specific sources for aggregate Spanish data (see the calibration appendix) to 
match moments in the data. 
The main contribution of our paper is that we provide an explanation for the 
inability of the Spanish government to implement a debt-financed recapitalization of 
the Spanish financial sector in May/June 2012. To the best of our knowledge, we are 
the first paper to do so within a DSGE framework specifically calibrated to capture 
the dynamics of the Spanish economy. A second contribution of our paper is to 
investgiate the effectiveness of alternative recapitalization policies by foreign 
entities such as the EFSF/ESM. 
Our first and main result is that we find that the above mentioned negative 
amplification cycle between undercapitalized banks with large holdings of risky 
sovereign debt and weak government finances explains the developments in Spanish 
bond markets in May/June 2012. A second result is that contrary to a debt-financed 
recapitalization by the sovereign, which is the standard macroeconomic policy 
prescription to tackle banking problems, an external recap by a foreign entity such 
as the EFSF/ESM can break the vicious cycle between weak banks and weak 
sovereigns. In such circumstances, commercial banks obtain the beneficial effects of 
a recapitalization, without incurring the negative feedback effects on bond prices, 
since the recapitalization does not add to domestic sovereign debt anymore. 
Several papers in the literature have paid attention to this two-way feedback loop 
between undercapitalized banks and weak sovereigns. Empirical studies suggest that 
distress in financial markets can spill over to the sovereign debt market and vice 
versa (Acharya et al. 2014; Laeven and Valencia 2013; Haidar 2012; De Bruyckere  et al. 2013; Alter and Schüler 2012), while the interdependence of banks and 
sovereigns has been shown to have grown over time (Alter and Beyer 2012). Models 
specifically designed to simulate the Spanish economy can be found in Burriel et al.  (2010) and Fernandez-Villaverde and Ohanian (2010). Burriel et al. (2010) perform 
a Bayesian estimation with Spanish data for policy purposes. They do not focus on 
financial fragility so banks play no role in their set up. Fernandez-Villaverde and 
Ohanian (2010) do add financial frictions in a similar way as Bernanke et al. (1999)  in an otherwise standard New-Keynesian closed economy model, but abstract from 
fiscal policy and government debt which plays a crucial role in our paper. </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>2 Stylized facts </p>

<p>It is obviously important to investigate whether the feedback loop between weak 
banks and weak sovereigns can be so strong that the gains from a bank 
recapitalization are substantially eroded by the subsequent capital losses on 
sovereign debt issued for that very bank recapitalization. If Spain indeed fell victim 
to the two-way feedback loop between a distressed financial sector and increased 
sovereign credit risk, our model has important policy implications for countries that 
are in a similar position as Spain was before the attempted intervention. That would 
be most Southern European countries, such as Italy, Portugal and Greece, who also 
face issues related to sovereign debt sustainability, while commercial banks in these 
countries are heavily exposed to the domestic sovereign, as can be seen from Fig. 2, 
which shows the exposure to the domestic sovereign as a percentage of Tier-1 
capital. Spanish banks have an exposure to Spanish sovereign debt of 150 % of 
Tier-1 capital while Italian banks and Greek banks have an exposure of 200 % 
respectively 250 % of Tier-1 capital. From these figures it is clear that domestic 
sovereign debt holdings of commercial banks are substantial and that stress in the 
sovereign debt market will seriously and negatively affect the financial sector. 
Countries like Greece, Italy and Portugal could face the same troubles should they 
attempt to recapitalize their financial sector through additional debt issue. The 
potential failure of such a recap severely limits the policy options for these 
governments, and might leave them in a situation where only a direct </p>

<p>ES GR 
IE 
IT 
PT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>as perc. of total holdings </p>

<p>ES GR 
IE 
IT 
PT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>as perc. of Tier−1 capital </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Figure displaying sovereign debt exposure of European periphery banks to their own country's 
sovereign as a percentage of their total sovereign debt holdings (left), and as a percentage of their Tier-1 
capital (right). The sample only contains Spanish banks that participated in the 2011 stress-test of the 
EBA (European Banking Authority). Source: European Banking Authority (2011), own calculations </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
515 </p>



<p>recapitalization by a foreign entity such as the EFSF/ESM is capable of breaking the 
feedback link between weak banks and weak sovereigns. Such a direct recapital-
ization is the final policy experiment we will perform with our model. A major 
conclusion is that without such Eurozone institutions, weak banks and weak 
governments would form a much more poisonous mix. </p>

<p>3 Spain's financial sector problems </p>

<p>3.1 Run up to the sovereign debt crisis </p>

<p>Spain experienced a booming economy in the decade leading up to the Great 
Recession of 2008-2009, with an annual average growth rate above 3.5 %. Strong 
economic growth and low interest rates led to a booming construction sector, with 
banks massively pooring funds into Spanish real estate. The subprime mortgage crisis 
spilled over from the United States into Europe in 2008 through the international 
banking system. Even though Spanish commercial banks had experienced relatively 
few losses during the global financial crisis of 2008-2009, due to a regulatory 
prohibition to invest in subprime mortgage products, the global financial crisis ended 
the housing boom that had endured in Spain during most of the 2000s. Falling real 
estate prices and losses on mortgages and construction loans resulted in significant 
bank losses, which first started to hit the Spanish financial sector in late 2010, with 
output falling after the first quarter of 2011. The burst of the real estate bubble left 
Spanish banks undercapitalized, which together with the broader sovereign debt crisis 
that had erupted in Greece in May 2010, started a vicious cycle exposing the negative 
link between losses on the balance sheets of banks, exploding borrowing costs, 
increases in public debt and a decrease in access to credit. A shrinking economy and 
vast unemployment were the result (International Monetary Fund 2011, 2014). </p>

<p>3.2 The Spanish financial sector reforms of 2012-2013 </p>

<p>In response to the financial crisis which had substantially hurt its national banks, 
Spain committed in May 2012 to provide new capital to banks (through additional 
debt issue) in case they failed to raise it privately. At the time, the government 
expected that an injection of public capital in the hurting Spanish banks would restore 
financial markets confidence, and relax the leverage constraints of banks, creating 
more space on bank balance sheets for loans to the Spanish private sector. 
Expectations of a significant increase in Spanish public debt, however, put upward 
pressure on Spanish bond yields and drove bond prices down, as can be seen from 
Fig. 3: we clearly see financial markets reacting to announcements regarding financial 
aid for Spanish banks during this timespan, with the bond yield increasing by 1.2 % 
and the CDS spread by 100 basis points. These are significant numbers, especially 
given the timespan of \2 months. When the Spanish government nationalized BFA-
Bankia on May 9th, both the yield and CDS spread experienced a sharp increase the 
very same day. The announcement of plans to restructure the bank with an additional 
capital injection of 19 billion Euro on May 23th reversed a downward movement in </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>the yield and CDS spread, indicating a new perception on the markets of increased 
risk. When it became clear at the beginning of June 2012 that Spain would not be able 
to fund a recapitalization on its own as a result of dampening demand for its debt 
papers, the yield and CDS spread again started to increase rapidly, driving borrowing 
costs to unsustainable levels, thereby preventing the Spanish government from 
obtaining the necessary funds for the recapitalization on the financial markets 
(Reuters 2012). Instead, the Spanish government was forced to apply for a loan from 
the EFSF/ESM (European Financial Stability Facility/European Stability Mechanism) 
to perform the much needed recapitalization of the financial sector (Eurogroup 2012). 
The announcement by the Spanish government that it would need up to 100 billion 
Euro from the EFSF/ESM on June 9th marked the start of an extended period of 
sharply increasing bond yields and CDS spreads. On June 25th, 2012 the Spanish 
government submitted an official request to obtain the necessary funds from the 
EFSF/ESM. This request was approved by the Eurogroup and the responsibility for 
the financing of the bank rescue programme was transferred to the newly established 
ESM (European Stability Mechanism) in November 2012. 
The most important aspect of the programme was the recapitalization of banks 
with a capital shortfall. An independent stress test of the balance sheets of all 
Spanish banks identified ten banks that were unable to reach a Core Tier-1 capital 
ratio of 6 % by the end of 2014 under an adverse scenario. The identified capital 
shortfalls totalled 56 billion euros, or 5.5 % of GDP. Public capital injections in the 
first quarter of 2013 accounted for approximately 70 % of these shortfalls, while the 
remaining capital shortfalls were addressed by bailing-in junior debt and private 
capital injections (International Monetary Fund 2014). Although the exact days in 
which the recapitalizations took place are unknown, a similar trend as in May/June 
2012 can be discerned around January 2013, the month in which the bulk of the 
capital injections was completed. This can be seen in Fig. 4. After a drop in the yield </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Spanish 10 year government bond yield in per cent (solid line, left axis) and Spanish sovereign 
credit default swap in basis points (slotted line, right axis) from 26 April 2012 to 18 June 2012. Vertical 
lines represent: 9 May 2012, nationalization of BFA-Bankia; 23 May 2012, announcement of 19 billion 
euro capital injection in BFA-Bankia; 9 June 2012, Spain requests bailout of up to 100 billion euros. 
Source: Bloomberg, Datastream </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
517 </p>



<p>and CDS spread till January 11th, a slight upward trend is visible during the next 
month while the Spanish government increases its debt and transfers capital to its 
banks. After February, the yield and CDS spread shows a decreasing trend, 
indicating the positive effects of the recapitalization. 
At present day, the Spanish sovereign is controlling owner of a significant share 
of the Spanish banking system. Partially as a result of the loans taken from the ESM, 
the ratio of government debt has increased from nearly 70-94 % of GDP in the 
period from 2011 to 2013. In comparison, government debt amounted to only 36 % 
of GDP before the start of the crisis in 2007 (Eurostat 2014). </p>

<p>4 Model description </p>

<p>We start from a standard New-Keynesian model with a private and a public sector, 
but extend it to include financial intermediation subject to frictions and a portfolio 
choice for commercial banks between corporate loans and long term government 
debt subject to sovereign default risk. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4.1 Households </p>

<p>The household sector consists of a continuum of identical, infinitely lived 
households. Following Gertler and Karadi (2011), we assume that each household 
consists of both workers and bankers. A fraction 1 À f are workers and earn wages 
that are transferred to the household. A fraction f are bankers managing a financial 
intermediary from which the dividends are also transferred to the household. Each 
period a banker has a probability of h to remain a banker in the next period. With 
probability 1 À h the banker will exit the financial sector, in which case she transfers 
the net worth of her financial intermediary to the household and becomes a worker. </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Spanish 10 year government bond yield in per cent (solid line, left axis) and Spanish sovereign 
credit default swap (slotted line, right axis) from 10 December 2012 to 11 March 2013. Source: 
Bloomberg, Datastream </p>

<p>3 The model is closely related to the one developed in Van der Kwaak and Van Wijnbergen (2014). </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>Every banker exiting the financial sector is replaced by a worker, who receives some 
net worth from the household to start operating a new financial intermediary. Exit 
and entry from the financial sector is such that the fraction of bankers and workers 
in the economy remains constant. The income from both bankers and workers are 
pooled, and equally divided among household members. 
Households derive utility from consumption c t and disutility from providing 
labour h t . Expected life-time utility is maximized subject to the household's budget 
constraint: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>fc tþs ;h tþs ;d tþs g </p>

<p>1 
s¼0 </p>

<p>E t 
X 1 </p>

<p>s¼0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>
log c tþs À tc tÀ1þs 
ð 
Þ À W 
h </p>

<p>1þu 
tþs </p>

<p>1 þ u </p>

<p>
" 
# </p>

<p>s:t:c t þ d t ; þs t ¼ w t h t þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>d 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
d tÀ1 þ P t ; </p>

<p>where c t is household consumption, h t labour supply, and w t the wage rate for 
workers. d 1À1 are household deposits from the previous period over which a net real 
interest rate r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t is received, s t is a lump sum tax that is paid to the government and 
P t are profits from both financial and non-financial firms owned by the household. </p>

<p>4.2 Financial intermediaries </p>

<p>Financial intermediaries hold assets in the form of claims issued by intermediate 
goods producers, government bonds and external bonds. External bonds are placed 
at the financial intermediaries in case of a recapitalization. The assets are financed 
through household deposits and equity (net worth). The balance sheet of the 
financial intermediary is given by </p>

<p>p j;t ¼ n j;t þ d j;t ; </p>

<p>where n j;t represents the intermediary's net worth, d j;t funds deposited by house-
holds and p j;t the assets held by the intermediary. The asset side of the balance sheet 
is represented by: </p>

<p>p j;t ¼ q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t ; </p>

<p>with q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t denoting the price of claims on intermediate goods producers, 
respectively government bonds; s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t and s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t denote the amount of claims respectively 
bonds held, while s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t represents the number of external bonds. 
Each period, bankers face an exogenous probability 1 À h that they have to exit 
the financial sector. In that case they pay out all net worth to the household, the 
ultimate owner of the intermediary. With probability h intermediaries continue 
operating and retain all net worth. The continuation value V j;t of financial 
intermediary j is therefore given by: </p>

<p>V j;t ¼ E t bK t;tþ1 ð1 À hÞn j;tþ1 þ hV j;tþ1 
Â 
Ã 
È 
É 
; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where bK t;tþ1 denotes the household's stochastic discount factor. Following Gertler 
and Karadi (2011), we assume that corporate governance problems limit the extent 
to which the intermediary can leverage its net worth n j;t . Each period, after the size </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
519 </p>



<p>and composition of the balance sheet have been determined, but before the shocks in 
the next period arrive, bankers have the possibility to divert assets. In that case, 
deposit holders force the financial intermediary into bankruptcy, but they can only 
recoup a fraction 1 À k </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t of asset class a 2 fk; b; eg. Hence bankers effectively keep 
a fraction k </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t of asset class a. Deposit holders take this diversion possibility into 
account, and ensure that in equilibrium the gains from diverting assets are smaller 
than the continuation value of the financial intermediary. </p>

<p>V j;t ! k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>This requirement effectively links the amount of net worth to the assets a financial 
intermediary can acquire through a leverage constraint / t (see ''Appendix 1.1'' for 
the formal derivation): </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t ¼ / t n j;t ; 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>An increase in k </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t increases the effective gains from diversion of asset a to the 
banker. As a consequence, deposit holders will reduce deposits, which causes a 
tightening of the leverage constraint. We will therefore model a financial crisis as a 
sudden increase in k </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t , see also Dedola et al. (2013). In particular, we assume the 
following processes for the diversion rates k </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t : </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ 
k k þ q k k k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 À 
k k 
À 
Á 
þ e k k ;t ; </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>
k b </p>

<p>k k </p>



<p>k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ; </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t ¼ 
k e ; </p>

<p>where we assume that the ratio k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t =k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t is constant across time, and denote it by 
k b = 
k k . 
In addition, we assume that e k k ;t $ Nð0; r </p>

<p>2 
k k </p>

<p>Þ. 
Finally, the number of external bonds is determined by the size of externally 
financed capital injections to banks: </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t ¼ s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ð1 À j e Þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t Àñ </p>

<p>g 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
; </p>

<p>where j e determines the share of the capital injection that is financed by the gov-
ernment, see Sect. 4.3. The optimization problem the financial intermediary faces, 
and its solution, is set out in ''Appendix 1.1''. </p>

<p>4.3 Government </p>

<p>The government issues long term ''Woodford bonds'', which are consols where the 
cashflow payment r c shrinks over time at a rate q. 
4 The shrinkage parameter q 
determines the effective maturity of the bond. The bond price in period t is denoted by </p>

<p>4 The advantage of this particular way of modeling long term debt is that longer maturity can be 
introduced without having to expand the number of state variables. See Woodford (1998, 2001). </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t . Clearly for such a security the stream of payments of one unit is equivalent to the 
cashflows generated by paying out r c in the first period and receiving a fraction q of a 
similar new security going into the second period where the process repeats itself (see 
for more details the ''Appendix 1.1.1''). So we get for the return on such a security: </p>

<p>1 þ r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>r c þ qq </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>q b </p>

<p>tÀ1 </p>

<p>Furthermore government bonds are subject to sovereign default risk, which is intro-
duced by assuming there is a maximum level of taxation, beyond which additional tax 
increases become politically unsustainable, as in Schabert and Wijnbergen (2014), 
and similar to the 'fiscal limit' in Davig et al. (2011). This fiscal limit, which is 
assumed to be constant across time, can be mapped one to one into a (constant) 
maximum level of debt, beyond which the government will (partially) default on its 
outstanding liabilities. We first take a look at the government budget constraint in case 
the government would honor all outstanding obligations. To finance its expenditures 
in period t, the government would issueb t , the number of bonds that need to be 
issued to prevent a default, at price q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t and levies a lump sump tax of s t . In addition, 
it receives j eñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t from financial intermediaries as repayment of past financial aid, 
where j e determines the share of the capital injection that is financed by the gov-
ernment. j e ¼ 1 implies that the government pays for the full recapitalization, while 
j e ¼ 0 represents a situation in which the capital injection is completely done by an 
external party (e.g. the ESM). These funds are used for g t ¼ 
g government pur-
chases, net worth provision (recapitalization) j e n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t to financial intermediaries and 
refinancing of outstanding government liabilities 1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 b tÀ1 , where r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t is the 
default exclusive net real return in period t on bonds purchased in period t À 1. The 
no default budget constraint would then be given by: </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tb t þ s t þ j eñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t ¼ g t þ j e n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 b tÀ1 : 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>The lump sump tax depends on the level of outstanding debt and financial sector 
support and is given by the following tax rule: </p>

<p>s t ¼ 
s þ j b ðb tÀ1 À 
bÞ þ j n n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t ; 0\j b 1; 0 j n 1; </p>

<p>where 
s is the steady state tax level and 
b is the steady state level of debt. The 
feedback parameter of debt on taxes j b must be strictly positive to obtain debt 
sustainability in the sense of satisfying the intertemporal budget constraint in the 
absence of defaults (Bohn 1998). 
5 The value of j n determines whether aid to the 
financial sector is financed by tax increases, debt or a combination of the two. Wheñ 
b t is smaller than b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t , actual government debt b t equals the no default level of 
government debtb t . But whenb t [ b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t , the government will default over a fraction 
D t of the debt, with D t large enough to set the actual level of debt b t equal to the 
maximum level of debt b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t , so we get: </p>

<p>5 Note that this does not exclude a ''mildly explosive'' debt path, just a debt stock that grows at less than 
the rate of interest. </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
521 </p>



<p>b t ¼ minb t ; b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>À max b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>Àb t ; 0 
À 
Á 
: 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>The second term has the payoff structure of a put option with underlying processb t 
and strike price b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t . This approach is used by Claessens and van Wijnbergen  (1993) in their evaluation of the Mexican Brady plan debt restructuring. 
A few comments are in order. This approach to sovereign default falls under 
what Aguiar and Amador (2013) call non-strategic default. The sovereign defaults 
after an unanticipated large shock drives the debt over a maxumum level 
compatible with the maximum tax revenue cosntraint the sovereign faces. The 
defaults are not a strategic choice, as they are for example in Arellano (2008) and 
in much of the recent debt crisis literature surveyed in Aguiar and Amador (2013), 
our default model is closer in spirit to the debt overhang literature in corporate 
finance. Also, in line with that latter literature, defaults are partial, while most of 
the strategic default literature assumes default to be a 0-1 decision, once a 
sovereign defaults it defaults on all outstanding debt. However this is mostly an ad 
hoc assumption made to avoid having to endogenize post-default bargaining, and 
in striking contradiction of almost all actual sovereign defaults (Cruces and  Trebesch 2013). Finally since we do not model default as the outcome of a 
strategic choice, there is no need to incorporate an explicit punishment mechanism 
(like exclusion of capital markets after a default). Our focus is on the bond price 
impact after an increase in ex ante sovereign default risk, rather than the losses 
arising from an actual default. 
For numerical reasons we approximate the sharply kinked ex-post default rule (5) 
by the ex ante option pricing based valuation formula derived in Claessens and van  Wijnbergen (1993) which closely approximates the kinked pay out curve for 
appropriately chosen parameters but avoids the discontinuity at b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>(see 
''Appendix 1.3''). When a default occurs, all creditors accept the discount D t on 
the gross default exclusive return 1 þ r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t . The default inclusive return r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t is then 
given by: </p>

<p>1 þ r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t ¼ 1 À D t 
ð 
Þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>The actual government budget constraint is given by: </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t b t þ s t þ j eñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t ¼ g t þ j e n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t þ 1 À D t 
ð 
Þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 b tÀ1 : 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>The amount of net worth provision in period t depends on the intermediairies' 
diversion rate of private loans k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and is given by: </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t ¼ , k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀl À 
k k 
À 
Á 
n tÀ1 ; , 0; l ! 0; </p>

<p>where l determines the number of lags with which the recapitalization is imple-
mented. We assume that the repayment of government support will occur in the very 
far future, and hence we setñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t ¼ 0. </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>4.4 Production sector </p>

<p>4.4.1 Intermediate goods producers </p>

<p>A continuum of intermediate goods producers, that face perfect competition, acquire 
capital k i;tÀ1 from capital producers at the end of period t À 1 for a price q </p>

<p>k 
tÀ1 </p>

<p>through a state-contingent loan s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>i;tÀ1 ¼ k i;tÀ1 from the financial intermediaries. Next 
period's profits can credibly be pledged to the intermediaries, as in Gertler and  Kiyotaki (2010). After realization of the shocks, the producers hire labour h i;t at a 
wage w t , and start producing intermediate goods with previous period capital k i;tÀ1 
and labor h i;t as input. After production, the intermediate goods producers pay a 
state-contingent net real return r </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t over claims issued in period t, with the following 
production technology: </p>

<p>y i;t ¼ a t ðk i;tÀ1 Þ 
a h </p>

<p>1Àa </p>

<p>i;t : </p>

<p>Total factor productivity a t is driven by exogenous AR(1) processes. 
Output y i;t is sold to retail firms for a price m t . The effective capital stock (after 
depreciation) is sold to the capital producers for a price q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and used to pay back the 
loans and a net return to the financial intermediaries. A more elaborate description 
of the maximization problem of the intermediate goods producers can be found in 
the Online Appendix. </p>

<p>4.4.2 Capital producers </p>

<p>Capital producers purchase the effective capital stock that is left after production 
(including depreciation), ð1 À dÞk tÀ1 , from the intermediate goods producers. They 
also purchase an amount i t of final goods (see Sect. 4.4.4), and convert the old 
capital stock and newly purchased final goods into new capital. The newly produced 
capital stock k t is subsequently sold to the intermediate goods producers at the same 
price q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t that was paid for the capital after production. The capital producers face 
convex adjustment costs, so that for every unit i t only 1 À Wði t Þ units of capital are 
produced, with i t ¼ i t =i tÀ1 representing the change in the investment level. The 
expression for the capital stock after the capital producers have produced (or output 
of capital producers) is then: </p>

<p>k t ¼ ð1 À dÞk tÀ1 þ 1 À Wði t Þ 
ð 
Þ i t ; withWði t Þ ¼ 
c 
2 
ði t À 1Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4.4.3 Retail firms </p>

<p>A continuum of differentiated retail firms indexed by i 2 ½0; 1 transform 
intermediate goods y i;t into differentiated retail goods y f ;t ¼ y i;t under perfect 
monopolistic competition. Each period, only a random portion ð1 À wÞ of retail 
firms is allowed to reset their prices P f ;t , while the other firms can only (partially) 
index prices with previous period inflation, see Calvo (1983) and Yun (1996). Retail </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
523 </p>



<p>firms face the demand function y f ;t ¼ P f ;t =P t 
À 
Á À y t , with [ 1 and price index </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>1À 
t </p>

<p>¼ 
R 1 
0 P </p>

<p>1À </p>

<p>f ;t df . The resulting first order conditions are standard, and can be 
found in the Online Appendix. </p>

<p>4.4.4 Final goods producers </p>

<p>Final goods producers purchase the differentiated retail goods y f ;t to produce final 
goods. They face the following technology constraint: </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>ðÀ1Þ= 
t </p>

<p>¼ </p>

<p>Z 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>ðÀ1Þ= 
f ;t </p>

<p>df ; </p>

<p>where represents the elasticity of substitution between goods bought from the 
retail firms. Final good producers operate in a perfectly competitive market. Hence 
they take prices as given, and sell their goods for the same price P t . Final goods are 
sold to households and government for consumption, and to capital producers as 
input for investment. </p>

<p>4.5 Central bank </p>

<p>The nominal interest rate on deposits follows a standard Taylor rule: </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ¼ ð1 À q r Þð r 
n þ j p ðp t À 
pÞ þ j y log ðy t =y tÀ1 ÞÞ þ q r r </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ e r;t ; 
j p [ 1; j y [ 0; 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>where e r;t $ Nð0; r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r Þ. 
r 
n is the nominal interest rate in steady state, 
p the target level 
of inflation, and q r a smoothing parameter. The real return on deposits is given by: </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t ¼ 1 þ r </p>

<p>n 
tÀ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
=p t À 1: 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>4.6 Equilibrium </p>

<p>In equilibrium, there is clearing in all markets. For the goods markets this entails 
that aggregate supply equals aggregate demand: </p>

<p>y t ¼ c t þ i t þ g t : 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>In the asset markets, the number of loans to the intermediate goods producers must 
equal the size of the capital stock and the number of bonds owned by financial 
intermediaries must equal the number of bonds issued by the government: </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ k t ; 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ b t : 
ð12Þ </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>5 Calibration and matching business cycle statistics </p>

<p>5.1 Calibration </p>

<p>The model described above is calibrated to match the Spanish economy as closely 
as possible. We will shortly explain the calibration targets (Table 1), while leaving a 
more detailed description of the calibration procedures for ''Appendix 2''. Several 
parameters are taken from Burriel et al. (2010), who perform a full blown Bayesian 
estimation of their model with data from the Spanish economy. 
We assume the average lifetime of bankers to be equal to 24 quarters, resulting in 
a survival rate h of 0.9583. The maturity structure parameter q is calibrated to reflect 
the weighted average maturity of government bonds in Spain between 1998 and 
2008, which is 6.1 years according to the OECD Stats database. The annual fixed 
real payment on long-term government bonds is set to 4.1 %, which is the 
1998-2008 average of the interest rate on Spanish government bonds with a 
maturity of 10 years found in the <rs type="software">Statistical Data Warehouse</rs> of the European Cen-
tral Bank (2014). 
The ratio of investment, government consumption and government debt over 
GDP are derived from <rs type="software">Eurostat</rs> (2014). The 15-year average percentage of GDP that 
can be ascribed to private investment and government consumption is taken 
between 1994 and 2008. This results in steady state ratios of 22.6 % for investments 
over GDP and 17.8 % for government consumption over GDP. For the steady state 
credit spread C, the difference between the loans to non-financial corporations 
(''Total'') and the deposit rate on ''Household deposits redeemable at notice, Total, 
New Business'' for the period between 2003 and 2007 is taken. Loan rates are not 
available before 2003. We end the sample at the end of 2007 to exclude data from 
the Great Recession. For the 2003-2007 period we arrive at an average annual credit 
spread in Spain of 188 basis points (annually), which amounts to a steady state 
quarterly spread of 47 basis points. We calibrate the diversion parameter for 
government bonds k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t to equal 0.5 times the diversion rate for private loans k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t in all 
periods, as in Gertler and Karadi (2013). To make sure that this value does not drive 
our results, we investigate the model response for different values of k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t =k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ 
k b = 
k k 
in the Online Appendix. We set the diversion rate for external bonds equal to zero, 
as these are assumed to be safe and liquid assets. 
For the steady state leverage ratio we take the average ratio of consolidated 
equity to consolidated financial assets of the Spanish financial sector between 2001 
and 2008 from the OECD Stats database. This results in a steady state leverage ratio 
of 5.1, which resembles the leverage ratio chosen by Gertler and Karadi (2011) of 4. 
Given the fact that the loans to the private sector are state-contingent, and thus more 
equity-like, more volatility is generated in bank net worth everything else equal. 
hence a lower steady state leverage ratio can compensate the higher volatility 
induced by the equity-like debt contracts, just as Gertler and Karadi (2013), who 
choose a lower steady state leverage ratio for the same reason. This leverage ratio 
results in a sovereign debt exposure of approximately 146 % of net worth, which is 
close to the number in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain </p>

<p>
The steady state ratio of government debt to annual output is set to 53.2, or 
212.8 % of quarterly output, which is the 1995-2008 average of the Spanish 
government debt to GDP ratio, while we set the maximum level of government 
liabilities at 60 % of annual steady state GDP. A more detailed explanation of the 
calibration of the default parameters can be found in the Online Appendix. 
The smoothing parameter of the nominal interest rate q r is set to 0.8, which is in 
line with the literature. For the price-indexation parameter c P with which retail firms 
that are not allowed to freely change prices can (partially) index prices with 
previous period inflation we take 0.241 following Gertler and Karadi (2011). In the 
Online Appendix we perform simulations for q r ¼ 0:4 and c P ¼ 0:7, to make sure 
our results do not depend on the particular parameter value chosen for q r and/or c P . 
Finally we choose q k k and r k k for the AR(1) process that is driving the diversion 
rate k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t . We calibrate these parameters to match the fall in Spanish quarterly output 
of 1 % after December 2010, and to have the shock die out after approximately 10 
quarters. We then find q k k ¼ 0:7 and r k k ¼ 0:025. </p>

<p>5.2 Matching business cycle statistics </p>

<p>To assess whether the calibrated model can mimic the dynamics in the Spanish data, 
we compare basic business cycle statistics generated by the model with Spanish data 
over the period 2003-2007. We choose this period, because key variables like the 
loan rate, necessary for calculating the credit spread, are only available from 2003. 
We end the sample at the end of 2007 to exclude data from the Great Recession and 
the European sovereign debt crisis. As sovereign default risk was basically non-
existent during the 2003-2007 period, we perform the moment-matching exercise 
assuming sovereign default risk is absent, which we implement by setting the 
maximum level of government debt very far away from the steady state level of 
government debt. 
We minimize the distance between the standard deviation of output, credit spread 
and investment from the data and the standard deviation of output, credit spread and 
investment generated from simulating the model for 20 quarters by adjusting the 
parameters of the two shocks in our model, namely the productivity shock 
parameters q a ; r a and the monetary policy shock r r . We take the standard 
deviations of the cyclical components of Spanish real GDP and gross fixed capital 
formation to match the standard deviations of the cyclical components of output and 
investment from the simulated model. For the credit spread, we take the timeseries </p>

<p>Table 1 List of steady state 
calibration targets and source of 
calibration </p>

<p>Target Definition 
Value Data source </p>

<p>i= y 
Investment ratio 
0.226 
1994-2008 average </p>

<p>
g= y 
Government spending ratio 0.178 
1994-2008 average </p>

<p>b= y 
Government debt ratio 
2.128 
1995-2008 average </p>

<p>C 
Credit spread 
0.0047 2003-2007 average </p>

<p>/ 
Leverage ratio 
5.1 
2001-2008 average </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>described in Sect. 5.1. Simulated moments from the model are then compared to the 
data. In addition, we report the first order autocorrelations for the same variables. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The results of this exercise are reported in Table 2. We indicate the statistical 
significance of differences between the empirical moments and the simulated 
moments by reporting the associated t-statistics in square brackets. We see that the 
standard deviations for GDP, credit spread and investmentl are matched well by the 
model, as indicated by an absolute value of the t-statistic below 2. This is not 
surprising, as these were the three moments we targeted in our simulation. In 
addition, we report the standard deviation of bank capital for both the data and the 
simulated model, and we find that the model matches the data in this dimension as 
well, as the accompanying t-statistic is below 2 in absolute value, in spite of the fact 
that this variable was not included in the target list. 
We also inspect another aspect of the dynamics of our model, namely the first 
order autocorrelations for the same variables, in columns 4 and 5 of Table 2. Similar 
to the standard deviation for bank capital, we did not target these moments in the 
moment matching exercise. We nevertheless find that the first order autocorrelations 
of the simulated model and the data do not differ statistically significant, as the t-
values for all variables are below 2 in absolute value. We conclude that our 
calibrated model captures the dynamics observed in the data reasonably well. </p>

<p>Table 2 List of standard deviations of data and model (columns 2 and 3), and first order autocorrelations 
of data and model (column 4 and 5) </p>

<p>Standard deviation 
Autocorrelations </p>

<p>Data 
Model 
Data 
Model </p>

<p>GDP 
0.0025 
0.0049 [1.3151] 
0.7009 
0.6954 [0.0450] </p>

<p>Credit spread 
0.0013 
0.0016 [0.6605] 
0.6831 
0.4513 [-1.1933] </p>

<p>Investment 
0.0086 
0.0211 [1.5564] 
0.5463 
0.6995 [1.2729] </p>

<p>Bank capital 
0.0311 
0.0521 [1.5962] 
0.4947 
0.4083 [-0.4368] </p>

<p>t-statistics are reported between square brackets </p>

<p>6 For output and investment we take data from the Eurostat website. We take quarterly data that are 
seasonally and calendar adjusted, chain linked volumes (2010) in million euros. For the credit spread, we 
take the timeseries described in Sect. 5.1, which comes from the ECB website. Bank capital is also 
retrieved from the website of the ECB (''Capital and reserves''), which is a monthly timeseries. First we 
convert bank capital to real terms by dividing by the monthly CPI level in Spain. A single model 
simulation starts from the non-stochastic steady state and lasts for a 1020 periods. We discard the first 
1000 observations as a burn-in. We perform 10,000 simulations for each gridpoint of the state space. Next 
we take the natural logarhitm of output, investment and bank capital for both the empirical and the 
simulated data, but not for the credit spread. The quarterly timeseries are obtained by taking an 
unweighted average of the monthly data, insofar as needed. We then find the cyclical components of the 
empirical data and the simulated data by applying the Hodrick-Prescott filter with a smoothing parameter 
of 1600. The estimation consists of minimizing g T ðhÞ 
0 g T ðhÞ, where g T ðhÞ is a vector with the difference </p>

<p>between the standard deviation from the data and the simulations for output, credit spread and investment, 
and T the number of observations, in our case 20. We restrict the search for the parameters ðq a ; r a ; r r Þ in 
the following way. 0:8 q a 0:999, 0:001 r a 0:030 and 0:001 r r 0:010. </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
527 </p>



<p>6 Recapitalizing the Spanish banking sector </p>

<p>To analyze the surprizing responses to the Spanish attempts to rescue their banking 
system, we first simulate an internally financed bank recap. We compare the case 
with no additional government policy, and contrast the results with the case where 
the government issues additional debt to fund a recapitalization of the Spanish 
banking system (Sect. 6.1). Next we compare the debt-financed recap with the case 
where the recap is executed by an external party outside Spain, such as the EFSF or 
ESM (Sect. 6.2). We pin down the timing of our simulation by looking at the 
unfolding of the events in Spain. Losses on mortgages and construction loans first 
started to hit the Spanish financial sector in late 2010, with output falling after the 
first quarter of 2011. The first period in our simulations therefore coincides with the 
beginning of 2011. The actual recapitalization of the Spanish banks mainly took 
place at the start of 2013. We therefore set the recapitalization to occur 8 quarters 
after the start of the financial crisis. Since 70 % of the total costs of the financial 
reform was accounted for by direct injections of public capital, we set the size of the 
recapitalization to 39.2 billion Euros. This is approximately equal to 3 % of annual 
Spanish GDP before the start of the financial crisis. Our policy intervention will 
therefore in both simulations consist of a capital injection of 12 % of quarterly 
steady state GDP, announced when the crisis erupts but implemented 8 quarters 
later. As to the financial crisis to which the policies are a response, we follow a 
different approach than most of the Financial Frictions literature sofar. Following 
Gertler and Karadi (2011), the crisis is typically modeled as a quality shock 
lowerering the effective stock of capital and its price, which in turn leads to capital 
losses on the banks' asset portfolio. In this setup the crisis originates in the real 
sector and spills over into the financial sector. Instead we let the original shock 
occur within the financial sector itself, with subsequent negative real sector effects 
through the ensuing credit tightening. In particular the original crisis is mimicked by 
a shock to the diversion parameter k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t for private loans, the closest we can come to a 
confidence shock in the financial sector. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>6.1 Debt financed recaps </p>

<p>The results from this first experiment are displayed in Fig. 5. The no intervention 
case is a financial crisis initiated through a positive one standard-deviation shock to 
the diversion rate for private loans k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t . As a consequence, the diversion rate for 
government bonds is also shocked, since k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>
k b </p>

<p>k k </p>

<p>
k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t . This case is displayed by the 
solid blue line. The red slotted line represents the case where the same shock to k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>arrives, but now the government performs a debt-financed recapitalization equal to 
3 % of annual steady state output (and thus 12 % of steady state quarterly output). 
Consider first the no intervention case. When the financial crisis hits, the balance-
sheet-constraint of financial intermediaries becomes more binding, as a higher k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>and k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t , respectively, imply that bankers can costlessly divert more private loans and </p>

<p>7 We thank a referee for this suggestion. </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>government bonds, respectively, everything else equal. A tighter balance-sheet-
constraint pushes up credit spreads, which reduces the demand for private loans with 
a drop in the price of capital as a consequence. A lower resale price of capital 
further decreases the ex post return on the loans to intermediate goods producers 
(remember that the return on private loans (partially) consists of the proceeds from 
selling the capital used for production). A lower return on private loans reduces 
banks' net worth. But losses on private loans are not the only source of losses: 
balance sheet tightening also pushes up interest rates on sovereign debt and lowers </p>

<p>Financial crisis, no recap vs. debt financed recap </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Diversion rate private loans </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Output </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Consumption </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Investment </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−60 </p>

<p>−40 </p>

<p>−20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Intermediary Net Worth </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Credit Spread E[r 
k −r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>Abs. 
Δ from s.s. 
in basis pts. </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
0.01 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>Default Fraction </p>

<p>Abs. level. 
of indicator </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Price of bonds </p>

<p>Rel. 
Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Impulse response functions for the model runs including sovereign default risk and long term debt 
with a delayed recapitalization by the government (red, slotted) of 12 % of quarterly steady state output 
occurring eight quarters after the shock to the diversion rates k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t , and for the simulations without 
additional government policy (blue, solid) (color figure online) </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
529 </p>



<p>bond prices, resulting in capital losses for existing bond holders. Bank equity value 
drops by more than 20 % of steady state net worth, resulting in a drop in investment 
of 5 % of steady state value, which reduces the capital stock. A lower capital stock 
results in lower marginal productivity of labor, pushing down wages and labor hired 
(both not shown), resulting in a drop in consumption and output. 
The increased credit spread, however, increases bank profits from credit 
intermediation, and therefore restores bank equity after approximately 5 quarters, 
which allows an expansion of the balance sheet. Investment increases to 10 % of its 
steady state level, and drives the medium-run recovery in output. 
The announcement of a recapitalization 8 quarters into the future has dramatic 
consequences: the large recapitalization package (12 % of quarterly steady state 
GDP) pushes the debt level significantly up with lower bond prices and higher 
interest rates (on new debt) as a consequence. Higher interest rates on sovereign 
bonds reflect both the increased risk of sovereign default and arbitrage induced 
higher interest rates on bonds, as loan rates go up as credit spreads go up for 
corporates. The banks anticipate the increase in net worth 8 quarters from now due 
to the capital injection, but the size of the debt increase and the subsequent losses on 
the portfolio of bonds outstanding on the banks' balance sheet is so large that the 
losses on sovereign debt inflict capital losses larger than what is gained by the 
capital injection: net worth actually goes down instead of up when compared with 
the no intervention case, although there is a temporary dip in the credit spread at the 
time of the recap. The upfront drop in the bond price increases from 3 % of the 
steady state bond price in the no recap case to more than 15 % in the recap case. 
The anticipation of a future recap, and hence a future alleviation of the balance-
sheet-constraint, together with an immediate fall in bondholdings due to lower bond 
prices, allows financial intermediaries to expand lending to the private sector. Credit 
spreads fall at the time of the intervention, and further accelerate the recovery. 
Investment increases to more than 10 % above the steady state level of investment, 
and leads to a stronger recovery in GDP. </p>

<p>6.2 Externally financed recapitalization </p>

<p>Consider now the impact of a direct recap funded by an external party, such as the 
EFSF or the ESM, which would avoid the large increase in Spanish sovereign debt 
that caused the trouble in the runs discussed in the previous section. Member states 
of the Eurozone are still individually responsible for rescuing their banks, but they 
can receive funding for bank recaps from the ESM (European Stability Mechanism). 
However that would run into the problem outlined in the previous session as the 
sovereign debt would increase too, to another creditor perhaps, but debt levels 
would rise. An alternative has been considered after these problems did in fact 
emerge during the interventions in the Spanish banking crisis: one of the proposed 
solutions to break the vicious cycle between weak banks and weak sovereigns in the 
Eurozone is allowing the ESM to directly recapitalize banks that face a capital 
shortfall. Such a restructuring method would not force a sovereign to issue 
additional bonds to finance the recap, and recapitalize banks without the sovereign 
incurring additional debt. The positive effects from a bank recap remain, while the </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>negative consequences of increased sovereign default risk are absent. In order to 
simulate this scenario, we set the parameter j e equal to zero. Banks are now 
recapitalized by an external party (ESM), and receive external assets s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t , together 
with an increase in net worth. Figure 6 shows the differential results, comparing the 
consequences of a debt financed intervention with an externally financed direct 
recapitalization by say the ESM: 
The differential impact of an externally financed recapitalization is most clearly 
reflected in the different developments of the bond prices. When banks are </p>

<p>Financial crisis, debt financed recap vs. externally financed recap </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Diversion rate private loans </p>

<p>Rel. Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Output </p>

<p>Rel. Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Consumption </p>

<p>Rel. Δ 
from s.s. </p>

<p>in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Investment </p>

<p>Rel. Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Intermediary Net Worth </p>

<p>Rel. Δ 
from s.s. </p>

<p>in percent </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Credit Spread E[r </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>−r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>Abs. Δ from s.s. 
in basis pts. </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
0.01 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>Default Fraction </p>

<p>Abs. level. 
of indicator </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
−20 </p>

<p>−10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Price of bonds </p>

<p>Rel. Δ from s.s. 
in percent </p>

<p>Quarters </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 6 The blue (solid) line represents the model runs with sovereign default with a delayed 
recapitalization financed with government bonds of 3 % of annual steady state output occurring eight 
quarters after the shock to the diversion rates k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t , and the model with a delayed external 
recapitalization (red, slotted) (color figure online) </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
531 </p>



<p>recapitalized directly by an external party, the drop in the bond price from the direct 
recap is avoided altogether. Less debt issued by the government results in lower 
sovereign debt discounts, and hence lower or no capital losses on sovereign debt for 
existing bondholders. Net worth of the financial intermediaries is now above the 
steady state level of net worth over the entire time path and so the leverage 
constraint becomes less binding which in turn results in a lower credit spread and 
less crowding out. All this results in a level of investment, output and consumption 
that is consistently above the levels that are attained by a bond financed 
recapitalization in the first 20 quarters after the financial crisis starts. 
This experiment shows that an external recapitalization has considerable 
advantages over a debt-financed recapitalization. So a direct recapitalization is 
beneficial from an economic point of view for the receiving country. Of course 
political factors might interfere, particularly if external support is linked to painful 
reforms. We abstain, however, from these political considerations, but conclude that 
for countries in severe sovereign debt trouble with banks deeply involved in the 
placement of sovereign debt, externally financed direct recapitalizations may be the 
only way a banking system can actually effectively be recapitalized. </p>

<p>7 Discussion </p>

<p>The funds for the recap were ultimately provided by the ESM in December 2012, 
but they consisted of loans/debt to the Spanish government who then implemented 
the actual recapitalizations (European Stability Mechanism 2012a, b, 2015). The 
development of the bond price around these announcements closely resembles the 
results from our simulations, in which the announcement of a (sizeable) 
recapitalization causes a drop in bond prices (or equivalently a rise in bond yields). 
Compare the data in Figs. 3 and 4 with our simulations in Fig. 5. While our 
simulations have the bond price drop immediately by more than 15 % with respect 
to the steady state, the yield on the 10 year bond increases by 1.2 % in Fig. 3 over 
the timespan of \2 months. Compared with the average interest rate of 4.1 % on 
10 year Spanish bonds over the period 1998-2008, this marks an increase of almost 
30 %. Taking the interest rate at the start of May 2012 of 5.9 % in Fig. 3, which 
already includes sovereign default risk (see the accompanying CDS spread), this 
still constitutes an increase of 20 %. The negative feedback mechanism between the 
sovereign and the domestic commercial banks, whereby an increase in sovereign 
debt to fund the recap causes bond prices to drop and further impair commercial 
bank balance sheets, therefore seems to be apparent in the data during the 
restructuring of the Spanish financial sector, which is also indicated by a marked 
increase in the sovereign CDS spread. 
Our simulations show that bond prices are not recovering after the recap has been 
announced because of the pending debt issue. They only start to recover after the 
recapitalization has taken place. The (expected) return on bonds, which is similar to 
the 10 year bond yield in the data, jumps upwards at the moment the recap is 
implemented. A similar development can be seen in Fig. 4, where yields and CDS 
swaps increase during January, the month in which most of the recaps were </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>implemented, only to fall after the implementation of the recap has been concluded 
at the beginning of February. 
Apparently the main mechanism of our model, the negative amplification cycles 
arising between weak bank balance sheets and increased sovereign default risk due 
to additional debt issue, is capable of generating the patterns observed in the data. 
So it seems that amplification cycles are important in an environment where 
undercapitalized banks have a substantial exposure to risky domestic sovereign 
debt, as was the case in Spain in 2012 and in many other countries where 
governments face funding problems. The negative feedback mechanism might 
substantially affect the effectiveness of conventional recapitalization operations to 
the point where such a recap harms the recovery in the short run. In that case 
unconventional ways of recapitalizing the banking system are necessary. One of the 
options we have explored in this paper is a direct recapitalization by an external 
party: this way the negative feedback effects on bond prices, because of increased 
debt issuance and higher sovereign default risk, is absent, while bank capital is 
increased with subsequent positive effects on the real economy. </p>

<p>8 Conclusion </p>

<p>In May 2012 the Spanish government announced a debt-financed recapitalization of 
the Spanish banking system, after the capital base of Spanish banks had been severely 
damaged following the end of the housing and construction boom of the 2000s. 
Contrary to the standard theory, CDS spreads on both Spanish sovereign debt and 
Spanish banks went up, indicating that banking risks increased, in spite of the attempt 
to provide the banks with a higher capital base. Sovereign debt discounts increased 
dramatically in the days following the announcement, deteriorating the fiscal position 
of the Spanish government, which had already incurred several setbacks due to lower 
tax revenues after the end of the housing and construction boom. 
We propose a mechanism that can explain the events in Spain: additional debt 
issue to finance a recapitalization of the banking sector increases sovereign default 
risk, and is translated in lower sovereign bond prices. Since the undercapitalized 
Spanish banks are heavily exposed to risky Spanish sovereign debt, lower bond 
prices translate into capital losses for those banks, thereby undermining the recap 
they were intended to fund. In repsonse, credit spreads and interest rates increase on 
non-financial corporate loans, but through arbitrage also on sovereign bonds. An 
additional fall in bond prices results, and so on, giving rise to a negative 
amplification cycle between weak commercial bank balance sheets and weak 
government finances. 
To assess the relevance of this mechanism, we construct a DSGE model with 
balance-sheet-constrained financial intermediaries that finance private loans to the 
real economy, as well as sovereign debt with endogenously determined default risk 
and calibrate the model to Spanish data. We find that our model is capable of 
generating the negative amplification cycles between undercapitalized commercial 
banks and sovereign default risk: a pre-announced debt-financed recapitalization, 
calibrated to match the size of the Spanish recapitalization in January 2013, finds the </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
533 </p>



<p>bond price falling by almost 20 % with respect to the steady state bond price, 
comparable to the 20 % increase in the interest rate on 10-year Spanish sovereign 
debt in May 2012 after the announcement of the recap. We therefore conclude that 
the negative amplification cycle between weak banks and weak sovereigns can 
explain the events that unfolded in Spain in May/June 2012 and has probably played 
a major role during that tumultuous period. 
Our analysis highlights the limits to the conventional approach to bank rescues 
when undercapitalized banks are heavily exposed to the risky sovereign debt of the 
government: a debt financed recap might backfire, and become ineffective. In that 
case alternative policies have to be considered, such as assistance by another actor 
with a stronger balance sheet. We look at one such approach, namely a direct 
recapitalization by a foreign entity such as the ESM. We find that the results of such 
an external recap are positive: bond prices do not experience the steep fall that 
occurs after a debt-financed recap, and there is less crowding out of private loans, 
leading to a faster recovery. Although the economic benefits of such an external 
assistance seem clear, political factors might of course complicate this option, vide 
the resistance by Germany to direct recaps by the ESM. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distri-
bution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and 
the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>

<p>Appendix 1: Derivations </p>

<p>Appendix 1.1: Financial Sector </p>

<p>The maximization problem of the financial intermediary is given by: </p>

<p>V j;t ¼ maxE t bK t;tþ1 ð1 À hÞn j;tþ1 þ hV j;tþ1 
Â 
Ã 
È 
É 
; </p>

<p>s:t: </p>

<p>V j;t ! k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t ; </p>

<p>subject to the law of motion for net worth. bK t;tþ1 is the stochastic discount factor of 
the household, since the household is the ultimate owner of the intermediary. We 
conjecture the solution to be of the following form, and later check whether this is 
the case: </p>

<p>V j;t ¼ m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t þ g t n j;t : 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>The optimization problem implies the following Lagrangian: </p>

<p>L ¼ 1 þ l t 
ð 
Þ m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t þ g t n j;t </p>



<p>À l t k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>



<p>: </p>

<p>where l t is the Lagrangian multiplier on the balance sheet constrain of the inter-
mediaries. We get the following first order conditions: </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t : 1 þ l t 
ð 
Þq </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t À k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t l t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ 0 () m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t l t 
1 þ l t 
; </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t : 1 þ l t 
ð 
Þq </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t À k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t l t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ 0 () m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t l t 
1 þ l t 
; </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t : 1 þ l t 
ð 
Þm </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t À k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t l t ¼ 0 () m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t l t 
1 þ l t 
; </p>

<p>l t : m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t þ g t n j;t </p>



<p>À k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ k </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>



<p>h 
i 
l t ¼ 0: </p>

<p>From the first order conditions we find that m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>
m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t and m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>
m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t . Hence the 
incentive compatibility constraint of the bankers can be rewritten in the following 
way: </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>þ g t n j;t </p>

<p>! k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>¼) q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>

<p>/ t n j;t ; </p>

<p>ð14Þ </p>

<p>/ t ¼ 
g t 
k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t À m k </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>; 
ð15Þ </p>

<p>where / t can be seen as the leverage constraint of the financial intermediary. The 
intuition for the leverage constraint is straightforward: a higher shadow value of 
assets m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t implies a higher value from an additional unit of assets, which raises the 
continuation value of the financial intermediary, thereby making it less likely that 
the banker will steal. A higher shadow value of net worth g t implies a higher 
expected profit from an additional unit of net worth, while a higher fraction k </p>

<p>a 
t </p>

<p>implies that the banker can steal a larger fraction of assets, which induces the 
household to provide less funds to the banker, resulting in a lower leverage ratio 
everything else equal. 
Substitution of the conjectured solution into the right hand side of the Bellman 
equation gives the following expression for the continuation value of the financial 
intermediary: </p>

<p>V j;t ¼ E t 
h 
X tþ1 n j;tþ1 
i 
; </p>

<p>X tþ1 ¼ bK t;tþ1 
È 
ð1 À hÞ þ h½g tþ1 þ m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tþ1 / tþ1 </p>

<p>É 
: </p>

<p>X tþ1 can be thought of as a stochastic discount factor that incorporates the financial 
friction. Now substitute the expression for next period's net worth into the 
expression above: </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain </p>

<p>
V j;t ¼ E t 
h 
X tþ1 n j;tþ1 
i </p>

<p>¼ E t 
h 
X tþ1 
ÈÀ 
r </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>À 
r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b 
j;t </p>

<p>þ 
À 
r </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t þ </p>

<p>À 
1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 þ s </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tþ1 Às </p>

<p>n 
tþ1 </p>

<p>Á 
n j;t 
É i 
: 
ð16Þ </p>

<p>After combining the conjectured solution (13), with (16) we find the following first 
order conditions: </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ E t X tþ1 ðr </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þ </p>

<p>Â 
Ã 
; </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ E t X tþ1 ðr </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þ </p>

<p>Â 
Ã 
; </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>k 
t </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t ¼ E t X tþ1 ðr </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þ </p>

<p>Â 
Ã 
; </p>

<p>g t ¼ E t X tþ1 ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 þ s </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tþ1 Às </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tþ1 Þ </p>

<p>Â 
Ã 
; </p>

<p>with X tþ1 ¼ bK t;tþ1 ð1 À hÞ þ hðm </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tþ1 / tþ1 þ g tþ1 Þ </p>

<p>È 
É 
; </p>

<p>As described in section 4.1, each period a number of bankers the size of a fraction 
ð1 À hÞf of the households will become a worker and vice versa. The other bankers 
continue operating their financial intermediary. The aggregate net worth of these 
continuing intermediaries, abstracted from government aid and repayment, can 
therefore be given by </p>

<p>n e;t ¼ h ðr </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þq </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ðr </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þq </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ðr </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þs </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þn tÀ1 </p>

<p>Â 
Ã </p>

<p>Exiting bankers take the net worth of their intermediaries, ð1 À hÞ of aggregate net 
worth, to the household, of which a share is provided as starting capital to entering 
bankers. This share is v=ð1 À hÞ of the assets held by the indermediaries of exiting 
bankers. Adding financial sector support by the government and repayment of 
support, the total net worth of the financial sector is </p>

<p>n t ¼ h ðr </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þq </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ðr </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þq </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ðr </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 À r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þs </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þn tÀ1 </p>

<p>Â 
Ã </p>

<p>þ vp tÀ1 þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t Àñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t : 
ð17Þ </p>

<p>Appendix 1.1.1: Long term government debt </p>

<p>The government can issue debt which is long term, and has a maturity structure 
similar to Woodford (1998, 2001). A bond that is issued at price q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 pays out a 
fixed cash flow (in real terms) of r c in period t, qr c in period t þ 1, q 
2 r c in period 
t þ 2 and so on. Hence in any given period the cash flow of a bond issued in period 
t À 1 is a factor q smaller than the cash flow of a bond issued in period t. Thus the 
return flows are equivalent to one first payment of the bond plus a fraction q of a 
similar bond issued one period later: r c þ qq </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t . The net real return in period t on 
bond puchases q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 b tÀ1 from period t À 1 is therefore: </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>1 þ r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ </p>

<p>r c þ qq </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>q b </p>

<p>tÀ1 </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>The duration of public debt is then equal to: 
P 1 
j¼1 jb 
j ðq 
jÀ1 r c Þ 
P 1 
j¼1 b 
j ðq jÀ1 r c Þ 
¼ 1=ð1 À bqÞ 
ð 18Þ </p>

<p>Appendix 1.2: Derivation of structural equations financial intermediaries 
in presence of sovereign default risk </p>

<p>The introduction of sovereign default risk changes the equations for the financial 
intermediaries. In this section we show that the net worth of an individual 
intermediary is given by the same expression as the case with no default, except for 
the fact that we replace r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t by r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t . Hence we only have to replace r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t in the equations 
governing the financial intermediaries by r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t , and include the expression for r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t in 
the first order conditions. We start by observing that the funds obtained from selling 
the bonds in period t þ 1, that were purchased in period t, are reduced by 1 À D tþ1 , 
just as the fixed real payment r c per bond is reduced to ð1 À D tþ1 Þr c . Hence the law 
of motion for the net worth of an individual intermediary changes into the following 
equation: </p>

<p>n j;tþ1 ¼ 1 þ r </p>

<p>k 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ 1 À D tþ1 
ð 
Þ r c s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ 1 À D tþ1 
ð 
Þ qq </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tþ1 s </p>

<p>b 
j;t </p>

<p>þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t À ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þd j;t þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>j;tþ1 Àñ </p>

<p>g 
j;tþ1 </p>

<p>¼ 1 þ r </p>

<p>k 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ 1 À D tþ1 
ð 
Þr c þ qq </p>

<p>b 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>b 
j;t </p>

<p>þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t À ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þd j;t þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>j;tþ1 Àñ </p>

<p>g 
j;tþ1 </p>

<p>¼ 1 þ r </p>

<p>k 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ 1 À D tþ1 
ð 
Þ 
r c þ qq </p>

<p>b 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>q b </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b 
j;t </p>

<p>þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t À ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þd j;t þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>j;tþ1 Àñ </p>

<p>g 
j;tþ1 </p>

<p>¼ 1 þ r </p>

<p>k 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ 1 À D tþ1 
ð 
Þ1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b 
j;t </p>

<p>þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>e 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;t À ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þd j;t þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>j;tþ1 Àñ </p>

<p>g 
j;tþ1 </p>

<p>¼ r </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>j;t þ r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>j;t þ r </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e 
j;t </p>

<p>þ ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>tþ1 Þn j;t þ s </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tþ1 n j;t Às </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>tþ1 n j;t ; </p>

<p>where r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t is given by: </p>

<p>1 þ r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t ¼ 1 À D t 
ð 
Þ 1 þ r </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ 1 À D t 
ð 
Þ 
r c þ qq </p>

<p>b 
t </p>

<p>q b </p>

<p>tÀ1 </p>



<p>
: </p>

<p>We replace r </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t by r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t in the equation for the shadow value of government bonds, and 
the law of motion of net worth: </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain </p>

<p>
m </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t ¼ E t </p>

<p>h 
X tþ1 
À 
r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>tþ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
tþ1 </p>

<p>Á i 
; </p>

<p>n t ¼ h 
ÂÀ 
r </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d 
t </p>

<p>Á 
q </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ </p>

<p>À 
r </p>

<p>bÃ </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>d 
t </p>

<p>Á 
q </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 s </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>tÀ1 þ r </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>tÀ1 À r </p>

<p>d 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
s </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>j;tÀ1 þ ð1 þ r </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>t Þn tÀ1 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>þ vp tÀ1 þ n </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t Àñ </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>t : </p>

<p>The other equations for the financial intermediaries remain the same. </p>

<p>Appendix 1.3: Approximation of the default function </p>

<p>We can also write the debt level structure (5) in the following way: </p>

<p>b t ¼ minb t ; b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>À max b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>Àb t ; 0 
À 
Á 
: 
ð19Þ </p>

<p>We can interpret the second term of the new debt level as the payoff of a put option at 
maturity with underlying processb t and strike price b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t . The formula for b t , however, 
does not have a defined derivative atb t ¼ b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t . Therefore we apply an approximation 
for the payoff structure of the put option, and use the option pricing formula, which 
gives the price of the put option when time to maturity is equal to T, compounded risk-
free interest rate r, and volatility of the underlying process r. This is an approximation 
to the actual mapping fromb t to b t . The dashed line in Fig. 7 is the approximation to the 
actual mapping ofb t to b t . We then get the following approximation for b t , with UðÁÞ 
denoting the standard normal CDF, which is indeed continuous: </p>

<p>b t ¼ b </p>

<p>max 
t </p>

<p>À put t ; 
ð20Þ </p>

<p>put t ¼ Xe 
ÀrT U Àd 2;t 
À 
Á 
À S t U Àd 1;t 
À 
Á 
; 
ð21Þ </p>

<p>d 1;t ¼ </p>

<p>log ðS=XÞ þ r þ </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>



<p>T </p>

<p>r 
ffiffiffi ffi 
T 
p 
; 
ð22Þ </p>

<p>d 2;t ¼ </p>

<p>log ðS=XÞ þ r À </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>



<p>T </p>

<p>r 
ffiffiffi ffi 
T 
p 
; 
ð23Þ </p>

<p>X ¼ b </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>t ; 
ð24Þ </p>

<p>S t ¼b t : 
ð25Þ </p>

<p>Appendix 2: Calibration and moment-matching </p>

<p>Appendix 2.1: Calibration </p>

<p>The model described above is calibrated to match the Spanish economy as closely 
as possible. The steady state calibration targets can be found in Table 3, which </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>coincides with Table 1 in the main text. The calibrated parameter values can be 
found in Table 4. The subjective discount factor b, the share of effective capital in 
production a and the coefficients of the Taylor rule j p and j y are taken from Burriel  et al. (2010). The smoothing parameter of the nominal interest rate q r is set to 0.8, 
in line with the literature. We set the inverse Frisch elasticity of labour supply u 
equal to 0.1, and adjust the disutility of labor coefficient W to have steady state labor 
supply of 1/3. Parameters that have been approximated using Bayesian estimation 
include habit formation t, the elasticity of substitution between intermediate goods 
, the Calvo probability w and the investment adjustment parameter c. Burriel et al.  (2010) find a value for the Calvo probability w of 0.898. This, however, gives only 
explosive solutions. Therefore, the Calvo probability is reduced to 0.8, for which the 
model has a unique, stable solution. The price-indexation parameter c P is set to 
0.241, following Gertler and Karadi (2011). We follow the value from Gertler and  Karadi (2011) for the investment adjustment cost parameter c. 
We assume the average lifetime of bankers to be equal to 24 quarters, resulting in 
a survival rate h of 0.9583. The maturity structure parameter q is calibrated to reflect 
the weighted average maturity of government bonds in Spain between 1998 and 
2008, which is 6,1 years according to the OECD Stats database. q is therefore set to 
0.97 (duration in quarters ¼ 1=ð1 À bqÞ). The annual fixed real payment on long-
term government bonds is set to 4.1 %, which is the 1998-2008 average of the 
interest rate on Spanish government bonds with a maturity of 10 years found in the 
Statistical Data Warehouse of the European Central Bank (2014). </p>

<p>Debt structure mapping in presence of default risk </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
3.5 
4 
−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>Debt structure payoff </p>

<p>Value </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Plot showing the mapping from the no default level of debtb t to the actual debt level b t . The solid 
blue line is the actual mapping, while the dashed red line is an approximation to it, where option pricing 
formulas have been used </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
539 </p>



<p>The ratio of investment, government consumption and government debt over 
GDP are derived from Eurostat (2014). The 15-year average percentage of GDP that 
can be ascribed to private investment and government consumption is taken 
between 1994 and 2008. This results in steady state ratios of 22.6 per cent for 
investments over GDP and 17.8 per cent for government consumption over GDP. 
This pins down the depreciation rate d at a quarterly 3.55 per cent. The steady state 
ratio of government debt to output is set to 53.2 per cent, which is the 1995-2008 
average of Spanish government debt to GDP ratio. For the steady state credit spread 
C, the difference between the loans to non-financial corporations (''Total'') and the 
deposit rate on ''Household deposits redeemable at notice, Total, New Business'' for 
the period between 2003 and 2007 is taken. Loan rates are not available before 
2003. We end the sample at the end of 2007 to exclude data from the Great 
Recession. For the 2003-2007 period we arrive at an average annual credit spread in 
Spain of 188 basis points (annually), which amounts to a steady state quarterly 
spread of 47 basis points. We calibrate the ratio of the diversion parameter for 
government bonds k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t and the diversion rate for private loans k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t to be constant and 
equal to 0.5 times, as in Gertler and Karadi (2013). To make sure that this value 
does not drive our results, we investigate the model response for different values of 
k </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>t =k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t in the Online Appendix. We set the diversion rate for external bonds equal to 
zero, as we assume that these bonds are be safe and liquid assets that cannot be 
diverted. This results in a bank balance sheet of which approximately 25 % consists 
of sovereign debt. The target value of gross inflation 
p is set to 1.005, implying a 
2 % net inflation target, which is in line with the ECB inflation target. 
There exist large differences between leverage ratios across the financial sector in 
Spain. Leverage ratios go as high as 34 for Banco Santander, whereas other financial 
institutions clearly have lower leverage ratios. To attempt to average across these 
different segments of the financial sectors, the average ratio of consolidated equity 
to consolidated financial assets of the Spanish financial sector is taken between 2001 
and 2008 from the OECD Stats database. This results in a steady state leverage ratio 
of 5.1, which resembles the leverage ratio chosen by Gertler and Karadi (2011) of 4. 
Given the fact that the loans to the private sector are state-contingent, and thus more 
equity like, more volatility is generated in bank net worth everything else equal. 
hence a lower steady state leverage ratio can compensate the higher volatility 
induced by the equity like debt contracts, just as Gertler and Karadi (2013), who 
choose a lower steady state leverage ratio for the same reason. This leverage ratio 
results in a sovereign debt exposure of approximately 146 % of net worth, which is 
slightly lower but close to the number in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Table 3 List of steady state 
calibration targets and source 
of calibration </p>

<p>Target Definition 
Value Data Source </p>

<p>i= y 
Investment ratio 
0.226 
1994-2008 average </p>

<p>
g= y 
Government spending ratio 0.178 
1994-2008 average </p>

<p>b= y 
Government debt ratio 
2.128 
1995-2008 average </p>

<p>C 
Credit spread 
0.0047 2003-2007 average </p>

<p>/ 
Leverage ratio 
5.1 
2001-2008 average </p>

<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>



<p>Table 4 List of calibrated 
parameter values and source 
of calibration </p>

<p>Parameter Definition 
Value </p>

<p>Households </p>

<p>b 
Subjective discount factor 
0.990 </p>

<p>t 
Degree of habit formation 
0.847 </p>

<p>W 
Disutility weight of labour 
3.342 </p>

<p>u 
Inverse Frisch elasticity 
0.100 </p>

<p>Financial intermediaries </p>

<p>h 
Survival rate of bankers 
0.9583 </p>

<p>k k 
Steady state diversion rate private loans 
0.4419 </p>

<p>k b 
Steady state diversion rate domestic bonds 
0.2210 </p>

<p>k e 
Steady state diversion rate external bonds 
0 </p>

<p>v 
Transfer share to new bankers 
0.0015 </p>

<p>Production sector </p>

<p>a 
Effective capital share 
0.362 </p>

<p>
Elasticity of substit. (goods) 
8.577 </p>

<p>w 
Calvo prob. (price stickiness) 
0.800 </p>

<p>c P 
Price-indexation 
0.241 </p>

<p>c 
Investment adjustment cost par. 
1.728 </p>

<p>d 
Depreciation rate 
0.0355 </p>

<p>Policy parameters </p>

<p>q 
Government debt maturity par. 
0.97 </p>

<p>r c 
Real payment to bondholder 
4.1 </p>

<p>q r 
Interst rate smoothing par. 
0.8 </p>

<p>j b 
Gov. debt feedback on taxes 
0.05 </p>

<p>j p 
Inflation feedback on r </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>1.700 </p>

<p>j y 
Output feedback on r </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>0.125 </p>

<p>
p 
Inflation rate target 
1.005 </p>

<p>AR(1) parameters </p>

<p>q z 
Productivity shock 
0.9137 </p>

<p>q kk 
Financial crisis shock 
0.7 </p>

<p>Shocks </p>

<p>r z 
Std. productivity shock 
0.0010 </p>

<p>r r 
Std. monetary policy shock 
0.0010 </p>

<p>r kk 
Std. financial crisis shock 
0.025 </p>

<p>Default parameters </p>

<p>D 
Steady state share of default indicator 
0.0128 </p>

<p>Option parameters </p>

<p>r 
Risk-free interest rate 
-0.0278 </p>

<p>r 
Standard deviation 
0.4722 </p>

<p>T 
Time to maturity 
0.0591 </p>

<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain 
541 </p>



<p>Appendix 2.2: Default calibration </p>

<p>In this section we describe the calibration when sovereign default risk is introduced. 
The calibration of the real economy is not affected by the introduction of sovereign 
default risk. For the financial sector, the steady state bond price 
q b changes, and 
hence 
b. We calibrate the maximum level of government liabilities 
q b 
b max = y to be at 
70 % of annual steady state GDP. Different values could have been chosen, but the 
main point of the paper is to show the mechanisms that interplay when debt levels 
get close to the maximum level of debt. We leave the steady state fraction of 
government liabilities 
q b 
b= y at 53.2 % annual steady state output target. The reason 
for this freedom is the fact that we have a new variable, the level of debt in case of 
no government debtb t , and the steady state tax rate that we can adjust in order to 
still be able to hit our original targets. The steady state default probability is set at a 
rather conservative estimate of 
D ¼ 0:0025, which implies an annual default 
probability of 1 %, which is small given the observed bond spreads in the European 
periphery. We now apply calibration strategy 1 to find the parameters of the (option) 
approximation. Calibration strategy 1 cannot go further than a maximum level of 
government liabilities of 65 % of annual steady state GDP. We therefore use the 
option parameters that we found for a maximum level of government liabilities 
equal to 70 % of annual steady state GDP, and change to calibration strategy 2 
which can still be applied, and calibrate the model at a maximum level of 
government liabilities of 60 % of annual steady state GDP. This changes the steady 
state default probability to 
D ¼ 0:0128. </p>



<p> 
C. van der Kwaak, S. van Wijnbergen </p>





<p>Sovereign debt and bank fragility in Spain </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>