<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fsaje.12137" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract 
The literature on determinants of cross-border capital flows has consistently assumed the 
determinants of such flows to be constant throughout the sample. This paper investigates 
this notion by estimating the time varying relationship between portfolio flows to South 
Africa and two widely accepted determinants of such flows: the sovereign spread and global 
risk (measured by the CBOE Volatility Index, henceforth VIX). The results show that the 
time variation is highly significant and a constant parameter model will give biased estimates 
of the effects of risk on capital flows. The paper also gives important insights to South 
African policy makers and financial practitioners: Bond flows (non-resident purchases of 
South African bonds) have become more sensitive to the VIX after 2010. Share flows were 
particularly sensitive at the peak of the 2008 global financial crisis, but have at other times 
not responded in a statistically significant manner to changes in global risk. The relation-
ships are estimated using a time varying parameter vector autoregressive (TVP VAR) model 
with stochastic volatility. 
South Africa and several other emerging markets including Mexico, Poland, Hong 
Kong, Turkey and Chile have received average annual net bond inflows amounting 
to more than 2% of their respective GDP since 2009. Equity inflows to these 
economies have remained significantly lower in the same period (International Mon-
etary Fund, 2013). This paper aims to contribute to the large literature studying 
the determinants of such flows by providing partial answers to the following ques-
tions: What explains the divergence between bond flows and share flows into South 
Africa and other emerging markets? Are the determinants of such flows always the 
same or do they change over time? We approach this problem by estimating the 
time varying effect of two factors that have been widely recognised as important </p>

<p>* Corresponding author: University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa. Tel: 012 420 3820. 
E-mail: viegin@gmail.com 
 † University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa. 
The Authors thank, without implicating, Lucrezia Reichlin, Shakill Hassan, Johannes 
Fedderke and two anonymous referees for helpful comments. We also thank Economic 
Research Southern Africa and the South African Reserve Bank for financial support. </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. 
doi: 10.1111/saje.12137 
3 </p>

<p>South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>South African Journal 
of Economics </p>

<p>drivers of cross-border portfolio flows: bond yields and global risk (as measured by 
the CBOE Volatility Index, henceforth VIX). </p>

<p>1,2 </p>

<p>For the first time to our knowledge, we estimate a truly time varying model of 
bond and equity flows where the contemporaneous covariance matrix and the 
lagged coefficients are all time varying. This allows us to estimate the impact of 
shocks to each explanatory variable on portfolio flows to South Africa as they were 
at any particular month in our sample. We can thus plot the impulse response of 
capital flows to shocks in the determinants at different points in time, providing a 
dynamic picture of these relationships. If the relationship was constant, this would 
be a pointless complication of the estimation procedure, but our results confirm 
that the time variation is indeed a crucial feature in these relationships. 
The findings of this research are significant on two levels. First, there is substantial 
time variation in the effect of both bond yields and global risk on the portfolio flows to 
South Africa. This time variation will induce a strong bias to coefficients estimated on a 
sample where the relationship is assumed to be constant. This will be particularly severe 
if the sample in question includes the global financial crisis of 2008. 
Secondly, our results give important guidance to understand the dynamics of 
portfolio flows to South Africa. We learn that, contrary to what may be expected, 
global risk has had no impact on monthly bond or equity flows to South Africa in 
the period between 1998 and 2008. At the peak of the crisis however, global vola-
tility and/or risk aversion appears to have caused large volumes of bond and share 
outflows. During the recovery from the crisis, share flows have remained unaffected 
by changes in the global risk, whilst bond flows have become more sensitive than 
they were even at the peak of the financial crisis. We speculate that this recent sen-
sitivity is not caused by the risk itself, but rather by what causes changes in volatil-
ity: announcements about the unprecedented monetary policy interventions that 
have occurred over the same time period. </p>

<p>1.1 Capital Flows to South Africa 
Foreign capital that enter South Africa is recorded on the Financial Account in the bal-
ance of payments under direct investments, portfolio investments, other investments or 
as a change in the Reserve Bank's net foreign reserves. Net portfolio flows (purchases of 
bonds and shares by non-residents less South African residents purchases of foreign 
bonds and shares) are the most volatile of the different categories, both relative to the its 
own volume and in rand terms. Quarterly net portfolio flows have a standard deviation 
of 21 billion rand compared to 16 billion rand for the current account deficit as a whole. 
It is the portfolio flows that will be the focus of this paper. 
The net portfolio flows as reported on the Balance of Payments consists of changes to 
South Africa's foreign liabilities (that is foreigners' assets in South Africa) and South Afri-
ca's foreign assets. Fig. 1 illustrates the importance of portfolio flows in funding South </p>

<p>1 The VIX calculates the volatility that is priced into options on the S&amp;P 100 index according to 
the Black Scholes formula (Black and Scholes, 1973). For an excellent introduction and discussion 
of the VIX index and the older VXO index, see Carr and Wu (2004). 
2 See for example Calvo et al. (1996); Taylor and Sarno (1997); Fratzscher 
(2011); McCauley (2012); Bruno and Shin (2013) and others; all discussed further in section 2. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>Africa's current account deficit prior to the global financial crisis in 2008 and the drastic 
outflows at the peak of the crisis. Such portfolio inflows can either be sourced from the 
disposal of foreign assets, or from foreigners purchasing domestic assets. The latter of the 
two is the only sustainable option in the medium to long run. 
3 Thus, of particular inter-
est is the gross portfolio inflows, that is non-resident purchases of South African assets or 
equivalently changes in South Africa's foreign liabilities. 
We have singled out portfolio inflows as the important components in total foreign 
currency inflows and volatility. We may study these flows in more detail by looking at 
data on non-resident purchases of South African shares and bonds on the Johannesburg 
Stock Exchange (JSE). The JSE reports such transactions to the Reserve Bank on a daily 
basis. The cumulated non-resident net purchases of South African shares and government 
bonds are plotted in Fig. 2. Notably there has been a pronounced shift from equities to 
bonds beginning in late 2009. 
Non-resident net purchases between January 2000 and July 2013 added to a total of 
184 billion rands in bonds and 300 billion rands in shares. In the period from January 
2009 to July 2013, the purchases added to R227 billion in bonds and only R92 billion 
in shares. The standard deviation of monthly bond purchases was 6.7 billion rands, 
whilst the standard deviation of monthly share purchases was 5.3 billion rands. In com-
parison, the current account deficit for 2011 was approximately 100 billion rand, thus 
approximately 8 billion per month. There seems to be good reasons to suspect that this 
volatility has the potential to contribute significantly to volatility in the South African </p>

<p>Figure 1. Quarterly balance of payment figures -actual (top) and smoothed (bottom) </p>

<p>3 Clearly, sustained portfolio inflows also come with certain risks, for example sudden stops as 
argued by Calvo (1998). </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>economy and particularly in the exchange rate. South Africa has a constant demand for 
foreign currency to fund its imports, but foreigners have a highly volatile demand for 
South African shares and bonds. It is therefore crucial that policy makers strive to gain 
further understanding of what determines the foreign demand for South African financial 
assets. 
(i) Some Eyeballing Our literature review (section 2) suggests that monetary policy, 
interest rates and global risk/risk appetite are important determinants of the volume and 
direction of cross border capital flows. The remaining figures of this introductory section 
will aid us in a simple eyeballing exercise to form some prior ideas of what relationships 
we may expect to find between these variables. 
Figs 2 and 3 plot the cumulative net purchases of South African bonds and shares by 
non-residents with the yield spread and the VIX, respectively. 
4 There is no obvious rela-
tionship that can be discerned from these graphs, other than the negative correlation 
between the VIX and share flows at the onset of the global financial crisis in 2008. 
Once we move on to Fig. 4 we find a very clear relationship between the VIX and the 
yield spread. The Asian crisis and Russian default in 1998 caused a spike in risk (the 
VIX) at the same time as a spike in the yield on South African government bonds. From 
this point onwards the yield spread fell more or less in line with the VIX until their com-
mon trough in 2006 before both started climbing as we approached the financial crisis. 
Interestingly, the yield spread has remained rather stable since the onset of the crisis, 
whilst the VIX has been highly volatile before falling to levels well below average. It 
appears as if their relationship (if there indeed was one) broke at the onset of the finan-
cial crisis. We can hardly say more about this relationship without a more rigorous econ-
ometric analysis. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Cumulative portfolio flows (left axis) and the yield spread between 10 year 
South African and 10 year US Treasury bonds (right hand axis) [Colour figure can be 
viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>4 The yield spread refers to the difference between South African government bond yields and US 
government bond yields. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>In Fig. 5 we point out the actual dates where the US Federal Open Market Commit-
tee announced significant changes to their monetary policy. The graph does not prove 
any causal links, but certain patterns are interesting. In short, the figure suggests that the 
so-called Quantitative Easing responds to high risk and causes risk to fall. 
5 The threat of 
reducing such asset purchases appear to cause an increase in risk. The coincident timing 
of monetary policy announcements and sharp movements in the VIX suggests that the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Cumulative portfolio flows (left axis) and VIX (right hand axis) [Colour figure 
can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>Figure 4. Are the large inflows after 2008 explained by the fact that the spread remained 
high despite the falling risk [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>5 In the literature review we see that Adrian and Shin (2009) and Adrian and Shin (2010) con-
struct a theoretical model that explains such a relationship and find empirical evidence in support 
of it. </p>

<p>7 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>two are highly interrelated and further that it may be difficult to distinguish the effects 
of each one variable on portfolio flows. The solution may be to compare the response of 
flows to the VIX before and after the financial crisis. These unconventional monetary 
policy measures were not present prior to 2008, and any relationship with the VIX prior 
to 2008 may therefore be more likely to be caused by the actual risk premium rather 
than the monetary policy of the USA. 
Figure 6 plots the cumulative portfolio flows in this period post 2008 and indicates 
the dates of important monetary policy announcements. It is not obvious that there is a 
relationship between these dates and the actual flows and again a more rigorous econo-
metric analysis is necessary. 
This brief review of the raw data suggests that there are indeed important relations 
between monetary policy, global risk/risk premia/risk appetite and the yield spread 
between South African long term government bonds and US long term government 
bonds. It is not immediately obvious from a superficial look at the data whether these 
variables are linked to capital flows into South Africa, but our expectation of such a rela-
tionship is supported by the vast literature on the subject. The next section will provide a 
rather selective review of this literature before the paper moves on to present the method-
ology used and the resulting estimates. </p>

<p>2. LITERATURE REVIEW </p>

<p>Cross-border banking and capital flows have been the focus of academic research and 
debate for a long time. See for example, IMF (2012), Brookings Institution (2012), Allen </p>

<p>Figure 5. The VIX (left hand axis) and the yield spread between 10 year South African 
and 10 year US Treasury bonds (right hand axis) [Colour figure can be viewed at 
wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>et al. (2011) for policy oriented debates, and Borio and Zhu (2008), Borio and Disyatat 
(2011), Bruno and Shin (2012) and Bruno and Shin (2013) for recent academic 
contributions. 
The text book view of capital flows suggests that international financial markets 
are used to hedge risk to future consumption. Without trade, a country can only 
consume what it produces and is highly vulnerable to swings in production caused 
by unpredictable states of nature (Obstfeld and Rogoff, 2005). Through intratempo-
ral trade a country trades assets for assets with another country to smooth their 
consumption under different stochastic states of nature at a future date. On the 
other hand, in intertemporal trade a country trades goods for assets (current con-
sumption for future consumption) (see for example Obstfeld, 2012). Trading goods 
for assets would result in an entry on the country's current account, whereas a 
trade in assets for assets will not. This distinction has recently been drawn into the 
spotlight, most notably by Borio and Disyatat (2011) who argue that more research 
should focus on gross capital flows. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Borio and Disyatat suggests that the financial crisis is too often explained as the conse-
quence of current account imbalances and the net capital flows this entails. Examples of 
such reasoning include Eichengreen (2009) and Bernanke (2009). According to Borio 
and Disyatat (2011), this focus on excess savings "diverts attention away from the global 
financing patterns that are at the core of financial fragility" (Borio and Disyatat, 2011). </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Cumulative portfolio flows since January 2008 and important US monetary 
policy announcements [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>6 Note the potentially confusing terminology: gross inflows equals net non-resident purchases of 
domestic assets, whilst net inflows refer to net-non-resident purchases of domestic assets net of resident 
net purchases of foreign assets. 
7 Other research argues along the same lines. For example, Lane and McQuade (2013) find that 
"the current account balance is a misleading indicator in understanding the inter-relation between 
international capital flows and domestic credit growth" (Lane and McQuade, 2013). </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>Forbes (2012) emphasises the volatility of gross flows and find that both inflows and out-
flows have been "extremely volatile" in most countries around the world, and that this 
volatility has sharply increased since the mid-2000s. Again, this volatility is often not visi-
ble in net flows, as "gross capital inflows and outflows tend to move simultaneously in 
opposite directions and be roughly the same magnitude" (Forbes, 2012). Forbes and 
Warnock (2012) find evidence that while net flows show no significant reaction to global 
risk, there is a highly significant response in gross capital flows. </p>

<p>8,9 </p>

<p>2.1 Models of Risk, Monetary Policy and Capital Flows 
In what the authors describe as a "speculative" and "exploratory" analysis, Borio and 
Zhu (2008) argue that the traditional view of the monetary policy transmission mecha-
nism has ignored the price of risk and capital regulation. The "risk-taking channel" refers 
to the effect of interest rates on the perception of risk and risk tolerance. For example, 
lower interest rates will raise asset prices as well as income and profits. The higher profits 
may induce higher risk tolerance and/or reduce the perception of market risk (Borio and 
Zhu, 2008). Since then, a series of papers by Hyun Song Shin and co-authors have made 
a significant contribution in modelling the risk-taking channel of monetary policy. In 
addition they demonstrate how this risk taking channel links monetary policy to gross 
cross-border bank flows. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Adrian and Shin (2009) study the role of financial intermediaries and risk in the 
transmission mechanism from monetary policy to credit supply. Banks have tradi-
tionally been dominant in supplying credit, but are now supplemented by market 
based institutions (financial intermediaries that raise funds in the money market to 
invest in longer term debt securities). Adrian and Shin (2009) develop a model 
that demonstrates how these market based institutions may provide a transmission 
mechanism for monetary policy through the risk taking channel suggested by Borio 
and Zhu (2008). 
Adrian and Shin (2010) demonstrate that market based banks tend to increase 
leverage when total assets increase. They point out that this must be caused by 
active leverage management, as an increase in asset prices would otherwise reduce 
leverage. 
11 The positive correlation between assets and leverage may indicate that an 
increase in the valuation of assets induces the bank to expand its balance sheet 
even further by taking up debt to purchase more assets. They do this to such an 
extent that leverage becomes pro cyclical. Adrian and Shin (2009) build a model 
which produces this outcome from profit maximising behavior of banks. The model </p>

<p>8 Another important finding of their paper is that gross flow volatility is not sensitive to capital 
controls (Forbes, 2012). 
9 The fact that the current account does not tell the full story, does not, however, mean that it has 
become irrelevant. Obstfeld (2012) refers to evidence that links current account imbalances to 
credit booms and financial crises (for example Jorda et al., 2011; Ostry et al., 2011). 
10 See for example Adrian and Shin (2010), Adrian et al. (2010), Adrian and Shin (2009), Dan-
ielsson et al. (2011), Bruno and Shin (2012) and Adrian et al. (2010). 
11 For example, as the price of a home increases the home owner will be less leveraged because her 
equity in the home increases by the same absolute amount as the home price itself, while debt 
remains unchanged. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>shows that banks maximise profits by keeping their Value at Risk (henceforth VaR) 
at a binding constraint where the probability of bankruptcy is constant. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Importantly, Adrian and Shin (2009) demonstrate how higher asset prices, ceteris paribus 
will reduce leverage and Value at Risk (VaR) on bank's balance sheets. This leads to increased 
risk appetite as the market based banks aim to increase VaR back to its binding limit. Invest-
ment banks are now willing to pay more for risky assets, reducing the risk premium. There 
is some self enforcing feedback here, as higher asset prices will by themselves increase the bal-
ance sheet and reduce leverage which again induces more borrowing and asset purchases to 
keep VaR constant. This has important implications for monetary policy as the policy rate 
can influence the profitability and thus the balance sheet of these investment banks. 
Based on these insights, Bruno and Shin (2012) and construct a model of cross border 
financial flows. Bruno and Shin (2013) utilise this model in a study of the relationship 
between monetary policy in advanced economies (the USA) and capital flows across bor-
ders, particularly into emerging markets. It is a popular notion that low interest rates in 
the USA and EU drives capital into Ems, 
13 but the exact economic reasoning behind this 
idea has been weak. Bruno and Shin argue and demonstrate formally how financial inter-
mediary behaviour may affect these capital flows. The focus is on the banks' balance 
sheet management. They build on the result from Adrian and Shin (2009) that market 
based banks actively keep VaR its binding limit to maximise profits and therefore must 
increase leverage as soon as markets are less volatile (risky). One way of adding risk to 
their balance sheet is by investing in EM assets. 
In this model, the EM borrowers take up debt in dollars to fund projects. 
14 If the value of 
the project is less than the face value of the debt at maturity, the borrower will default. The </p>

<p>12 Commercial deposit based banks do not tend to have pro cyclical leverage. This is because 
deposits are rather stable and the banks can not actively increase leverage unless they turn to whole-
sale markets for funding. Hahm et al. (2011) show that a large increase in wholesale funding indi-
cates a lending boom and increased vulnerability to financial crises. The liabilities of an 
investment bank, on the other hand, are continuously marked to market and can be expanded or 
reduced at the will of the bank, typically through repurchase or reverse-repurchase agreements 
(henceforth repo). The high leverage of these institutions make their balance sheet highly sensitive 
to changes in the borrowing cost. This strengthens the pro-cyclical tendencies of asset and leverage 
growth, as rapid de-levering will push down asset prices which induces further de-levering (Adrian 
and Shin, 2009) (further explanations of how leverage accelerates falling asset prices can be found 
in Brunnermeier, 2009; Brunnermeier and Oehmke, 2012). 
13 See for example The South African Reserve Bank's governor Gill Marcus' letter to the Financial 
Times (Marcus, 2012), discussing this issue. 
14 The model thus assumes a certain demand for foreign currency loans from local clients. Brown 
and De Haas (2012) point out that banks' propensity to extend local loans in foreign currency will 
reflect the local demand for such loans. This implies that the characteristics of the client base will 
affect the bank's share of foreign currency denominated assets and liabilities. Thus, their conclu-
sion is that recent increases in foreign currency lending (in Eastern Europe) cannot be fully 
explained by foreign banks optimal supply of these loans. In related papers, Cowan (2006) and 
Brown et al. (2011) show that such client demand for foreign currency depends on factors that are 
included in the Bruno and Shin model derived above (interest rate spread and exchange rate vola-
tility), but also on the extent to which the client earns its income in foreign currency. This is natu-
ral, as a foreign currency loan will hedge the exchange rate risk implicit in the foreign currency 
income. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>dollar value of the debt is normally distributed and will increase with local currency appreci-
ation. That is, a stronger domestic currency relative to the dollar will increase the dollar value 
of the project and therefore make default less likely. 
The model solution implies that a lower funding rate (e.g. from a cut in the US policy 
rate) will increase EM credit supply. This increase is fully funded by an increase in for-
eign borrowing by the emerging market bank. By assumption, this will lead to apprecia-
tion of the exchange rate which makes the local project (borrower) more valuable in 
dollar terms, and thus a lower default probability (Adrian et al., 2010; Bruno and Shin, 
2012). The reduced risk of default reduces the risk of the global bank's balance sheet, 
and the global bank must extend more credit to readjust its Value at Risk to the binding 
limit. This leads to further appreciation of the emerging market currency, even lower 
probability of default, and so on. </p>

<p>15,16 </p>

<p>(i) Empirical Literature The theoretical literature discussed above is useful in deepening 
our understanding of how different structural factors interrelate and determine cross bor-
der capital flows. Lane and Milesi-Ferretti (2007b) provide a seminal empirical overview 
of the international balance sheets and their relation to capital flows. They demonstrate 
that such balance sheets differ significantly across countries, both in their allocation to 
different asset classes, maturity and liquidity. This implies that there are asymmetric 
exposures to different shocks and therefore such shocks will have different effects on 
portfolio flows in different countries. Such capital flows are caused by the rebalancing of 
international portfolios as the relative value of the assets within the portfolio is affected 
by shocks. This kind of portfolio rebalancing has also been studied by Hau and Rey 
(2006) who build a general equilibrium model where portfolio rebalancing causes a capi-
tal flow out of economies where asset prices are rising. They find strong empirical evi-
dence in support of this model. </p>

<p>17,18 </p>

<p>15 There are several papers that build general equilibrium models where leverage plays an impor-
tant role. One important recent contribution to this literature is Mendoza (2010). In this model, 
leverage is growing with economic expansion, but once leverage reaches a threshold the collateral 
constraint becomes binding. This causes the cost of credit to increase and may force agents to liqui-
date assets used as collateral. If this liquidation leads to lower asset prices it may turn into a so 
called "debt deflation" scenario (ala Fisher, 1933) where the value of collateral falls relative to the 
book value of debt or revenue. This debt deflation may in turn cause large scale fire sales that spiral 
into further drops in the collateral value. This negative feedback loop gives rise to sudden stops in 
the model. 
16 There are several strands of literature modelling cross border capital flows (see for example Pav-
lova and Rigobon, 2011 for a good review of this literature). One of the major puzzles in this litera-
ture is the documented presence of home bias in international portfolio allocation French and 
Poterba (1991). The macro finance literature has now come a long way to explain this puzzle, with 
important contributions from Obstfeld and Rogoff (2001), Kollmann (2006), Engel and Matsu-
moto (2006) and Coeurdacier and Gourinchas (2011). 
17 For other important empirical papers on the determinants of external positions (i.e. the stocks 
rather than the flows studied here), see for example Gourinchas and Rey, 2012; Herrero and 
Peria, 2007; Lane and Milesi-Ferretti, 2007a,b; Lane and Shambaugh, 2010). 
18 It may be noted that the only paper to have tested for rebalancing flows in South Africa found 
higher equity returns on the Johannesburg Stock Exchange to cause further equity inflows to the 
country (French, 2011). This is in contrast to the prediction of Hau and Rey (2006). </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>In this paper we are interested in understanding the importance of global and local 
factors as determinants of portfolio flows (where we distinguish between bond and equity 
flows) to South Africa. The following paragraphs give a brief overview of empirical 
research conducted on this very specific issue. 
Taylor and Sarno (1997) find empirical evidence that bond flows to Latin America 
and Asia between 1988 and 1992 were predominantly caused by global factors, whilst 
both global and local factors were equally important in determining long-term equity 
flows. Similar findings were made by Calvo et al. (1996) who showed that external fac-
tors (which they gave the term "push factors" as opposed to domestic "pull factors") 
were important determinants of capital flows to Latin America in the 1990s. Both papers 
find US interest rates to be one of the most dominant determinants. (See Calvo, 2013 
for a more recent discussion of this and other related papers). </p>

<p>19,20 </p>

<p>There are several recent papers that have shown the importance of monetary policy 
(interest rates) as a driver of capital flows also in more recent times. For example, Taylor 
(2013) argue that monetary policy in the US tends to force other economies to follow 
suit with similar policy to avoid the large capital flows caused by the initial change in the 
USA. The link between monetary policy and risk can be very tight, and it is not always 
straight forward to distinguish the effects of one from the other. For example, Rey 
(2013) demonstrates forcefully that monetary policy drives capital flows by affecting 
leverage of global banks and risk/risk aversion. These findings are in strong support of 
the models developed by Adrian and Shin (2009), Bruno and Shin (2013) as discussed 
above. McCauley (2012) finds additional evidence that variations in global asset price 
volatility are driving factors of portfolio flows into emerging market bonds and shares. 
An important feature of our approach that was not present in the above mentioned 
literature is the time-varying parameters of our model. This enables us to capture both 
gradual and sudden changes in the importance of different determinants of bond and 
share flows. Past empirical literature has found such time variation to be highly signifi-
cant. Fratzscher (2011), for example, estimates a constant parameter model, but includes 
dummy variables to control for changes in the relationships during and after the global 
financial crisis of 2008. He finds that global risk and macro factors ("push factors") 
became the dominant driver of cross-border capital flows during the financial crisis. Dur-
ing the recovery after the crises he finds that domestic "pull factors" have come to domi-
nate in many emerging economies in Asia and Latin America. The finding that push 
factors become dominant during times of financial stress can potentially explain the 
strong empirical finding that global asset markets become highly correlated when global 
volatility is high (Forbes and Rigobon, 2002). The only empirical results from a time </p>

<p>19 Chuhan et al. (1998) conduct a panel study of both bond and equity flows to Latin America 
and Asia for the same period as Taylor and Sarno (1997), 1988-1992. Their findings indicate that 
local factors are "at least as important" determinants of capital inflows. In addition they find equity 
flows to be more sensitive to global factors than bond flows, a finding that goes directly against the 
evidence found by both Taylor and Sarno (1997) and Calvo et al. (1996). 
20 Chai-Anant and Ho (2008) make the interesting finding that equity inflows in Asia tend to be 
driven by common regional (Asian) factors, whilst equity outflows tend to be driven by idiosyn-
cratic local factors. Their results also support the argument of Hau and Rey (2006) that positive 
asset returns cause a capital outflow from the respective economy as foreign investors rebalance 
their portfolio. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>varying parameter model were done by Duca (2012). He finds significant time variation 
in the determinants of daily portfolio flows to emerging markets between 2007 and 
2012. The results indicate that local factors are more important when market tension 
increases, but they lose importance when volatility turns into panic and changes in risk 
becomes the dominating factor. 
The literature on portfolio flows to African economies is practically non-existent. The 
same goes for any literature on time varying parameters to explain cross-border portfolio 
flows. This paper thus places itself in the current literature by extending the research to 
the African continent and importantly by estimating a time varying parameter model 
with stochastic volatility (to avoid the unrealistic homoskedasticity assumption) on a 
sample of monthly data from 1988 to 2013. This allows us to estimate gradual changes 
that cannot be captured by a dummy variable as well as the sudden structural breaks that 
may come with financial crises. Such empirical results should give important insights 
that may support or reject models discussed above. </p>

<p>3. DATA AND THE EMPIRICAL ESTIMATION PROCEDURE </p>

<p>3.1 Data 
We aim to estimate the response of portfolio flows to South Africa to changes in global 
volatility and bond yields. To measure global risk we use the CBOE S&amp;P 100 VIX (?). 
Data on flows and yield on South African government bonds come from the South Afri-
can Reserve Bank's Quarterly Bulletin (?). We use the following data series: KPB2003M 
(Yield on South African government bonds with maturity of ten years and over), 
KBP2050 (Net purchases of shares by non-residents), KBP2051 (Net purchases of bonds 
by non-residents). US 10 year government bond yields are accessed from the US Federal 
Reserve Economic Data (??). The sample period is from February 1988 to January 2015. 
The variables are later referred to with the names: BondFlow, ShareFlow, VIX, Spread. 
Portfolio flows are adjusted for inflation by inflating past values to January 2015 rands 
using the linked historical headline CPI index provided by StatsSA (?). </p>

<p>3.2 Estimation 
The empirical analysis is conducted using a Bayesian Time Varying Parameter Vector 
Autoregression (TVP-VAR) model with stochastic volatility. There are several reasons for 
this approach. First, we choose a structural VAR framework in order to capture the 
dynamic interrelations between the different macroeconomic variables at play. This 
allows us to calculate the estimated impulse responses of each variable where all the 
dynamics are taken into account. As such we avoid the many endogeneity issues that 
plague macroeconomic variables (Sims, 1980). 
If one assumes a constant covariance matrix (homoskedasticity) and constant parame-
ters and normal distribution of the residuals, one may efficiently estimate this model and 
derive the impulse responses using Ordinary Least Squares (OLS). Unfortunately, neither 
the parameters nor the covariance matrix between the variables are likely to be constant 
over the entire sample (1988-2013). South Africa has gone through significant changes 
over this time period. Most important for this study is the gradual liberalisation of cross-
border capital flows and the financial integration with global markets. We also suspect 
that the global investor may have different behaviour during financial crises compared to 
calm times. Such time variation implies that a VAR with constant parameters may be </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>highly inaccurate and will ignore important changes to the relationship between the 
respective variables. We therefore choose to use a TVP-VAR framework which allows 
both coefficients to be time varying. 
Several algorithms have been developed to estimate a TVP-VAR with constant covari-
ance matrix (for example, Sims (1993), Canova (1993), Stock and Watson (1996) and 
Cogley and Sargent (2001)). This would allow give time varying estimates of the coeffi-
cients in a reduced form model. A structural model on the other hand will derive the 
parameters from the reduced form coefficients and the covariance matrix. The simultane-
ous relationships are purely derived from the covariance matrix. Thus, for this to be time 
varying, one must allow the covariance matrix to be time varying. The time varying 
covariance matrix will also capture any heteroskedasticity in the data and thus we avoid 
mistakenly attributing volatility changes to changes in coefficients Cogley and Sargent 
(2005). 
There are several algorithms that allow for both coefficients and the covariance matrix 
to be time varying. These algorithms have since been widely used in economics to esti-
mate monetary policy models (see Koop and Korobilis (2010) for an overview). Impor-
tant contributions include Primiceri (2005) and Cogley and Sargent (2005) and 
examples of more recent extensions include Koop et al. (2009) and Canova and Ciccar-
elli (2009). One could use switching models rather than TVP models with drifting 
parameters to capture sudden structural changes. These models have the advantage of 
estimating fewer parameters, and they would be likely to successfully capture changes 
caused by sudden events such as the global financial crisis. However, they are too rigid to 
capture longer transitions such as the gradual liberalisation of capital flows in and out of 
South Africa. For the purposes of this paper, the framework of Primiceri (2005) will be 
sufficient. This methodology allows us to estimate a TVP structural VAR with stochastic 
volatility by using an efficient Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm. One 
should note that this is a smoothing algorithm which means that we find the posterior 
distribution of the parameters at each point, conditional on the entire dataset. 
21 As such, 
the technique is not suitable for forecasting, but the smoothed estimates are more effi-
cient when the goal is to estimate the true time varying parameters (Primiceri, 2005). 
(i) The Model The paper uses the model specification from Primiceri (2005). We have 
a state space model where the observation equation (1) is the reduced form VAR where 
the last term is the reduced form residual (u t 5A t R t t ). Note we express the reduced 
form residual (u t ) in its decomposed form, where holds the residuals from the corre-
sponding structural VAR. 
22 B t includes all coefficient estimates for time t, a t refers to the 
non-zero elements of the lower diagonal A t . Lastly, r t contains the diagonal elements of 
the diagonal matrix R, where r j,t represents the standard deviation of variable j. </p>

<p>y t 5c t 1B 1;t y t21 1 Á Á Á 1B m;t y t2m 1A </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>t R t t 
(1) </p>

<p>B i;t 5B i;t21 1v t 
(2) </p>

<p>21 This is in contrast to particle filters which find the posterior distribution conditional on past 
observations only. 
22 The A t matrix solves the equation A t XA </p>

<p>&gt; </p>

<p>t 5R t R </p>

<p>&gt; </p>

<p>t , where X t is the time varying covariance 
matrix of the reduced form residuals: u t 5A t R t t . </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>a t 5a t21 1n t </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>log r t 5log r t21 1g t 
(4) </p>

<p>We impose the assumption that the error terms are independent (this is necessary in 
order to interpret the estimates as a structural model): </p>

<p>V 5Var </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>v t </p>

<p>n t </p>

<p>g t </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B 
B 
B 
B 
B 
@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
A </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>I n 0 0 0 </p>

<p>0 Q 0 0 </p>

<p>0 0 S 0 </p>

<p>0 0 0 W </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B 
B 
B 
B 
B 
@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
A </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>Equation (2) imposes a random walk process on the coefficients in the reduced 
form VAR model. This allows the coefficients to drift over time, and by making 
prior assumptions about the variance of this random walk we affect the probabil-
ity distribution of the process. For example, a larger variance implies that the 
coefficients are more likely make larger moves from observation to observation. If 
the variance is set to be too large, the estimated the coefficients will move enough 
to explain all variation in the data, resulting in overfitting. A very small variance 
may be too restrictive and thus cause the estimates to miss structural changes in 
the relations. 
Equation (3) defines a random walk for the non-zero elements of A t . This is allows 
the covariance matrix to be time varying, which again gives us time varying simultaneous 
relations. The prior assumption of the variance of n t has the same implications as dis-
cussed for equation (2). Equation (4) makes the variance of y t a stochastic process, which 
implies that the true underlying variance (r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) is unobserved. 
(ii) Estimation Procedure The goal is to estimate the parameters B,A,R and the 
hyper parameters in V. To do this we utilise a Gibbs sampler in an MCMC algo-
rithm based on Carter and Kohn (1994). 
23 We impose the same set of priors as Pri-
miceri (2005): We assume independent inverse-Wishart distributions of the blocks 
of V (that is Q, W and S) which implies normal conditional distributions of B, a 
and log r. The prior values of the coefficient are set to the OLS estimate of these 
coefficient from a regression on the first 70 observations. The time-varying parame-
ters are then estimated over the remaining sample from 1995 to 2015. We follow 
the same rule of thumb as Primiceri (2005) in setting priors for the variance of 
parameter processes. Each block of these hyper parameters in V are set such that the 
degrees of freedom equals one plus the dimension of the block (see Primiceri, 2005 
for a discussion). 
We can now list all our priors: </p>

<p>23 The model is estimated using <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Mathworks</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">Matlab</rs> [textregistered]. Our code is based on code 
written by Koop and Borilis which is available on his website in the file TVP VAR CK: http://per-
sonal.strath.ac.uk/gary.Koop20/bayes_matlab_code_by_Koop20_and_korobilis.html </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>B 0 $ N ðB OLS ; ðk11Þ Ã VarðB OLS ÞÞ </p>

<p>A 0 $ N ðÂ OLS ; ðk11Þ Ã VarðÂ OLS ÞÞ </p>

<p>log r 0 $ N ðlogr OLS ; I n Þ </p>

<p>Q $ IW ðk </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Q Ã 90 Ã VarðB OLS Þ; 90Þ </p>

<p>W $ IW ðk </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>W Ã ðk11Þ Ã VarðB OLS Þ; ðk11ÞÞ 
S i </p>

<p>i51:k </p>

<p>$ IW ðk </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>S Ã ðj11Þ Ã VarðB OLS Þ; ði11ÞÞ </p>

<p>where ðk Q ; k W ; k S Þ5ð0:01; 0:1; 0:10Þ as in Primiceri (2005). One can see here that 
smaller values for these constants (k Q , k W , k S ) imply lower variance of the random walks, 
a t and B t , and thus less time variation in the estimated parameter series. 
After imposing these priors, we estimate two models, both with a lag order of two: </p>

<p>Model 1 : y t 5 VXO t BondFlow t Spread t 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>Model 2 : y t 5 VXO t Spread t ShareFlow t 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>where the ordering is such that the latter variables may respond to contemporaneous val-
ues of the former variables. The ordering of Model 1 implies that the spread respond 
contemporaneously to shocks in bond flows while the share flows respond with a lag to a 
shock to the spread, as we assume that it takes time for the information coming from the 
bond market to affect the stock market. </p>

<p>4. RESULTS </p>

<p>The most important contribution of this paper is the estimated effect of risk (measured 
by the VIX) on portfolio flows. We find that neither bond flows nor share flows have 
responded to shocks in the VIX prior to the global financial crisis of 2008. At the peak 
of the crisis, both share and bond flows appear to respond as expected with a negative 
sign. Figure 7 plots the impulse response of bond flows and the soveriegn spread 1 month 
after a shock occurs in the respective variables. Figure 8 plots the same impulse responses 
from the model with share flows. Impulse responses after longer lags are plotted in the 
appendix (see Figs 10 and 11). 
Interestingly, the most significant response, both in magnitude and statistical certainty, 
is found during the recovery from the crisis. During the past 3 years, 2010-2013, bond 
flows have been highly influenced by changes in the VIX, more so than by changes in 
the yield spread. We attribute this to the role of quantitative easing in the USA. Changes 
in the VIX during the financial crisis were presumably driven by severe risk aversion as 
well as market volatility. This drove both share and bond flows out of emerging markets. 
During the recovery, however, changes in the VIX have been driven by two factors: 
announcements regarding quantitative easing and the sovereign (bond) crisis in Europe 
(see Fig. 5). Our results suggest that these shocks have been important determinants of 
bond flows, but not important for share flows. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2005 
2010 
−5 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−3 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>15th Percentile 
Mean 
85th Percentile </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
BondUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.4 </p>

<p>−0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−8 </p>

<p>−6 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
BondUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>Figure 7. Model 1 -Bond flows (in US Dollars): Time varying impulse response after 1 
month from a standard deviation shock to the VXO (top), Bond Flows (middle) and Sov-
ereign Yield Spread (bottom) [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2005 
2010 
−3 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>15th Percentile 
Mean 
85th Percentile </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
ShareUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.2 </p>

<p>−0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−4 </p>

<p>−3 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
ShareUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>Figure 8. Model 2 -Share flows (in US Dollars): Time varying impulse response after 1 
month from a standard deviation shock to the VXO (top), Share Flows (middle) and Sov-
ereign Yield Spread (bottom) [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>The lessons learned can be summarised as follows. Any model that assumes constant 
parameters throughout the sample period will produce highly biased estimates of the 
coefficient on risk if the sample includes the financial crisis. Risk has only been an impor-
tant variable during and after the crisis. The importance of the sovereign spread in 
attracting bond flows to South Africa has also changed over time, and was more signifi-
cant during the build-up to and at the peak of the financial crisis. During the recovery it 
appears that the yield spread has lost significance while risk (VIX) has become the domi-
nant determinant. 
The remaining panels in Figs 7 and 8 tell a story that matches common understand-
ing of financial markets. The sovereign spread has consistently, though to varying degree, 
responded to increased risk. This can be explained by a higher risk premium on emerg-
ing markets vs. the US safe haven government bonds. Bond inflows to South Africa have 
consistently caused lower yields on South African bonds compared to US bonds as the 
flow increases demand for these assets. The response have become smaller over time, 
most likely due to an increasing value of the total outstanding South African government 
debt and possibly also due to higher liquidity of these bonds. 
The temporarily negative impulse response of bond flows to shocks in the sovereign 
spread during the 1990s can possibly be explained by the high degree of South African 
specific risk and uncertainty at this time. This would imply a risk premium that was not 
caused by the VIX, and this higher risk premium would be accompanied by bond out-
flows as foreign investors aim to reduce this South African specific risk in their portfolio. 
At last, we note without further analysis that bond flows have become more persistent 
during the recent recovery, whilst the sovereign spread appears to have become less 
persistent. </p>

<p>4.1 In Context of the Literature 
The most comparable research in the current literature are Fratzscher (2011) and Duca 
(2012) who both look at shorter term, higher frequency relationships. Fratzscher (2011) 
uses constant parameters, but include a separate dummy for the financial crisis. Our find-
ings for South Africa correspond to his findings for Latin America and Asia in that we 
find an increase in the VIX during the financial crisis to cause outflows from both equi-
ties and bonds in emerging markets, of which the response of bond flows is more signifi-
cant. Fratzscher (2011), however, finds local factors to become dominant during the 
recovery 2009-2010. Given this finding, it is interesting that we estimate the VIX to be 
even more important during the more recent recovery 2010-2013 than it was during the 
financial crisis. Notably, Fratzscher (2011) uses a sample from 2005 to 2010, and thus 
his results are not in direct conflict to our findings. 
We could only find a single paper using time varying parameters to estimate the deter-
minants of capital flows. Duca (2012) does this on a sample of daily equity flows to 
emerging markets from 2007 to 2012. His model allows the coefficient on lagged deter-
minants to be time varying, but he assumes a constant covariance matrix (homoskedastic-
ity) with zero same-day determinants. 
24 Under this framework, he finds the variation in 
risk and risk aversion to be the dominant factor during times of panic, but he finds local </p>

<p>24 Figure 9 in the appendix illustrates the significant time variation in the standard deviation of 
the variables included in our model. </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>(regional) factors to become more important when risk increases moderately. Interest-
ingly, he notes that the sovereign crisis in Europe and subsequent US rating downgrade 
in 2011 did not generate panic and the corresponding increase in the VIX did not drive 
equity flows out of emerging markets. We don't find significant responses in share flows 
to changes in the VIX during this time. However, it is interesting that bond flows 
respond very sharply to the VIX during this time period. This diverging behaviour of the 
two types of portfolio flows emphasises the importance of studying each flow separately. </p>

<p>5. CONCLUDING REMARKS </p>

<p>The paper has reviewed the literature on the determinants of cross border capital flows 
and highlighted a need to study the time variation of such relationships further. In partic-
ular we set out to answer two questions: What explains the divergence between bond 
flows and share flows into South Africa and other emerging markets? Are the determi-
nants of such flows always the same or do they change over time? 
The research has provided partial answers, but much remains unknown. We found 
that the determinants of bond and share flows are not the same all the time. In fact, it 
appears that the VIX, a variable that is widely expected to be a significant driver of port-
folio flows, has only been so during and after the financial crisis. In the case of share 
flows, the VIX was important at the peak of the crisis, but not at any other periods in 
our sample. This is quite remarkable, and implies that caution is of crucial importance 
when interpreting the impact of risk and risk aversion on capital flows. We note here 
that our results are found for monthly data and do not rule out short term day to day 
effects of the VIX. 
It was mentioned in the opening paragraph that bond flows to emerging markets have 
been unusually high in the last four years, especially when compared to share flows. We 
do not have a conclusive answer as to why this is, but we found that bond flows have 
responded very strongly to changes in the VIX over this same time period. The VIX has 
indeed been falling rapidly throughout most of the period, possibly due to monetary pol-
icy actions in the USA. The estimates imply that this falling level of the VIX is predicted 
to drive large amounts of bond flows into South Africa. However, the estimates are 
inconclusive as to whether this relation to the VIX is driven by an underlying relation to 
market volatility or to monetary policy actions. 
In general, we have found that bond flows have in the last five years been driven by 
both the sovereign spread and the VIX while share flows do not respond to neither of 
the two. This suggests that share flows are determined by variables not included in this 
model, most likely more local so called "pull factors." Financial media frequently dis-
cusses the risk of portfolio outflows from emerging markets once pace of asset purchases 
by the US Federal Reserve is reduced. Our results suggest that this may indeed be a very 
real risk in the bond market, but not a significant risk in the share market. </p>



<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>



<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>



<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>APPENDIX </p>

<p>Table 1. Correlation matrix on differenced monthly data -bold print indicates signifi-
cance at the 5% level </p>

<p>VIX 
Bonds 
Shares 
ZAR 
SA 10y 
US 10y 
Spread </p>



<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>





<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2005 
2010 
−8 </p>

<p>−6 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>85th Percentile 
Mean 
15th Percentile </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
BondUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
BondUSD 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−1 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−2 </p>

<p>−1.5 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
BondUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>Figure 10. Model 1 -Bond flows (in US Dollars): Time varying impulse response after 5 
months from a standard deviation shock to the VXO (top), Bond Flows (middle) and 
Sovereign Yield Spread (bottom) [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2005 
2010 
−3 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>85th Percentile 
Mean 
15th Percentile </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
ShareUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.4 </p>

<p>−0.3 </p>

<p>−0.2 </p>

<p>−0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
ShareUSD 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−1 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
VIX </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−3 </p>

<p>−2.5 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>−1.5 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>−0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
ShareUSD </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>2000 
2005 
2010 
−0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>5 Month Impulse response of 
Spread 
to shock in 
Spread </p>

<p>Standard Deviations </p>

<p>Figure 11. Model 2 -Share Flows (in US Dollars): Time varying impulse response after 
5 months from a standard deviation shock to the VXO (top), Share Flows (middle) and 
Sovereign Yield Spread (bottom) [Colour figure can be viewed at wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p> 
South African Journal of Economics Vol. 85:1 March 2017 </p>

<p>V C 2017 Economic Society of South Africa. </p>

</text></tei>