<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F17421770903541772" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT This paper places the key issues and implications of the new 'introductory' book on 
spatial econometrics by James LeSage &amp; Kelley Pace (2009) in a broader perspective: the argument in 
favour of the spatial Durbin model, the use of indirect effects as a more valid basis for testing whether 
spatial spillovers are significant, the use of Bayesian posterior model probabilities to determine which 
spatial weights matrix best describes the data, and the book's contribution to the literature on spatio-
temporal models. The main conclusion is that the state of the art of applied spatial econometrics has 
taken a step change with the publication of this book. </p>

<p>Relever le niveau de l'économetrie spatial appliquée </p>

<p>RÉ SUMÉ La pre´sente communication place les principales questions et implications du nouvel ouvrage 
d'introduction sur l'e´conome´tries spatiale de James LeSage &amp; Kelley Pace (2009) dans un contexte 
plus ge´ne´ral: l'argument favorisant le mode`le spatial de Durbin, l'emploi d'effets indirects comme base 
plus valable pour e´valuer l'aspect significatif des de´versements spatiaux, l'emploi des probabilite´s d'un 
mode`le baysien poste´rieur pour e´valuer laquelle des matrices de poids spatiaux de´crit le mieux les 
donnes, et la contribution de l'ouvrage la documentation sur les mode`les spatio-temporels. La principale 
conclusion est qu'avec la publication de cet ouvrage, l'e´tat de l'art de l'e´conome´tries spatiale applique a 
effectue´un grand pas en avant. </p>

<p>Alzar el nivel de la econometría espacial aplicada </p>

<p>RÉ SUMÉ Este trabajo plantea las cuestiones e implicaciones clave del nuevo libro introductorio sobre 
econo´metra espacial de James LeSage &amp; Kelley Pace (2009) dentro de una perspectiva ma´s amplia: el 
argumento a favor del modelo espacial Durbin, el uso de efectos indirectos como una base ma´s válida 
para poner a prueba si los desbordamientos espaciales son significativos, el uso de probabilidades 
posteriores bayesianas para descubrir que matriz de pesos espaciales describe mejor los datos, y la 
contribucio´n del libro a la biblio´grafa sobre modelos espaciotemporales. La principal conclusio´n es que la 
econometría espacial aplicada ma´s avanzada ha experimentado un cambio radical con la publicacio´n de 
este libro. </p>

<p>The year 2007 marks a sea change in spatial econometricians' way of thinking. 
Prior to this they were interested mainly in models containing one type of spatial 
interaction effect: the spatial lag model and the spatial error model. The first model 
contains a spatially lagged dependent variable, while the second model incorporates 
a spatial autoregressive process in the error term. The seminal book by Anselin 
(1988) and the testing procedure for a spatial error or a spatial lag model based on 
robust Lagrange multiplier tests developed by Anselin et al. (1996) may be 
considered as the main pillars behind this way of thinking. After 2007 the interest in 
models containing more than one spatial interaction effect increased. In his keynote 
speech at the first World Conference of the Spatial Econometrics Association in 
2007, Harry Kelejian advocated models that include both a spatially lagged 
dependent variable and a spatially autocorrelated error term (based on Kelejian &amp; 
Prucha, 1998 and related work), while James LeSage, in his presidential address at 
the 54th North American Meeting of the Regional Science Association Interna-
tional in 2007, advocated models that include both a spatially lagged dependent 
variable and spatially lagged explanatory variables. In analogy to Durbin (1960) 
for the time series case, Anselin (1988) labelled the latter model the spatial 
Durbin model. 
The argument in favour of the spatial Durbin model is now laid down in a 
new 'introductory' book on spatial econometrics by James LeSage &amp; Kelley Pace 
(2009), and may be considered a landmark in raising the bar in the field of 
applied spatial econometrics. One strength of the spatial Durbin model is that it 
produces unbiased coefficient estimates also if the true data-generation process is a 
spatial lag or a spatial error model. Another strength is that it does not impose 
prior restrictions on the magnitude of potential spatial spillover effects. In contrast 
to other spatial regression specifications, these spillover effects can be global or 
local and be different for different explanatory variables. These and other 
important issues put forward in LeSage &amp; Pace's book (hereinafter with page 
numbers shown in parentheses) will be summarized in this paper. This paper, 
however, is more than just a book review. In each of the following sections, 
I will first give my own view of the state of the art of one theme in 
applied spatial econometrics, and then I will discuss the contribution of LeSage &amp; 
Pace's book. </p>



<p>2. A Taxonomy of Linear Spatial Dependence Models for Cross-section 
Data </p>

<p>To give a full explanation of the claim that the spatial Durbin model produces 
unbiased coefficient estimates, also if the true data-generation process is a spatial lag 
or a spatial error model, I first consider a taxonomy of linear spatial dependence 
models for cross-section data. 
The standard approach in most empirical work is to start with a non-spatial 
linear regression model and then to test whether or not the model needs to be 
extended with spatial interaction effects. This approach is known as the specific-to-
general approach. The non-spatial linear regression model takes the form </p>

<p>Y 0 ai N 'Xb'o; 
(1) </p>

<p>where Y denotes an N)1 vector consisting of one observation on the 
dependent variable for every unit in the sample (i 01, . . ., N), i N is an N)1 
vector of ones associated with the constant term parameter a, X denotes an 
N)K matrix of exogenous explanatory variables, with the associated parameters 
b contained in a K)1 vector, and o 0 (o 1 ; :::; o N ) 
T is a vector of disturbance 
terms, 
1 where o i are independently and identically distributed error terms for all i 
with zero mean and variance s 
2 . Since the linear regression model is commonly 
estimated by ordinary least squares (OLS), it is often labelled the OLS model. 
Furthermore, even though the OLS model in most studies focusing on spatial 
interaction effects is rejected in favour of a more general model, its results often 
serve as a benchmark. 
The opposite approach is to start with a more general model containing, nested 
within it as special cases, a series of simpler models that ideally should represent all 
the alternative economic hypotheses requiring consideration. Manski (1993) points 
out that three different types of interaction effects may explain why an observation 
associated with a specific location may be dependent on observations at other 
locations: (i) endogenous interaction effects, where the decision of a spatial unit (or 
its economic decision makers) to behave in some way depends on the decision 
taken by other spatial units; (ii) exogenous interaction effects, where the decision of 
a spatial unit to behave in some way depends on independent explanatory variables 
of the decision taken by other spatial units*if the number of independent 
explanatory variables in a linear regression model is K, then the number of 
exogenous interaction effects is also K, provided that the intercept is considered as a 
separate variable; and (iii) correlated effects, where similar unobserved environ-
mental characteristics result in similar behaviour. 
The Manski model takes the form </p>

<p>Y 0 rWY 'ai N 'Xb'WXu'u; 
(2a) </p>

<p>u 0 lWu'o; 
(2b) </p>

<p>where the variable WY denotes the endogenous interaction effects among the 
dependent variables, WX the exogenous interaction effects among the independent 
variables, and Wu the interaction effects among the disturbance terms of the 
different spatial units. r is called the spatial autoregressive coefficient, l the spatial </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 11 </p>

<p>autocorrelation coefficient, while u, just as for b, represents a K)1 vector of fixed 
but unknown parameters. 
W is an N )N matrix describing the spatial arrangement of the spatial units in 
the sample. Lee (2004) shows that W should be a non-negative matrix of known 
constants. The diagonal elements are set to zero by assumption, since no spatial unit 
can be viewed as its own neighbour. The matrices I Á rW and I Á lW should be 
non-singular, where I represents the identity matrix of order N. For a symmetric 
W, this condition is satisfied as long as r and l are in the interior of (1/v min , 
1/v max ), where v min denotes the smallest (i.e. most negative) and v max the largest 
real characteristic root of W. If W is row normalized subsequently, the latter 
interval takes the form (1/v min , 1), since the largest characteristic root of W equals 
unity in this situation. If W is an asymmetric matrix before it is row normalized, it 
may have complex characteristic roots. LeSage &amp; Pace (pp. 88Á89) demonstrate 
that in that case r and l are restricted to the interval (1/r min , 1), where r min equals 
the most negative purely real characteristic root of W after this matrix is row 
normalized. Finally, one of the following two conditions should be satisfied: (a) the 
row and column sums of the matrices W, (I Á rW) 
Á1 and (I Á lW) 
Á1 before W is 
row normalized should be uniformly bounded in absolute value as N goes to 
infinity, or (b) the row and column sums of W before W is row normalized should 
not diverge to infinity at a rate equal to or faster than the rate of the sample size N. 
Condition (a) originates from Kelejian &amp; Prucha (1998, 1999), and condition (b) 
from Lee (2004). Both conditions limit the cross-sectional correlation to a 
manageable degree, i.e. the correlation between two spatial units should converge 
to zero as the distance separating them increases to infinity. 
When the spatial weights matrix is a binary contiguity matrix, (a) is satisfied. 
Normally, no spatial unit is assumed to be a neighbour to more than a given 
number, say q, of other units. By contrast, when the spatial weights matrix is an 
inverse distance matrix, (a) may not be satisfied. Consider an infinite number of 
spatial units that are arranged linearly. The distance of each spatial unit to its first 
left-and right-hand neighbour is d; to its second left-and right-hand neighbour, 
the distance is 2d; and so on. When W is an inverse distance matrix and the off-
diagonal elements of W are of the form 1/d ij , where d ij is the distance between two 
spatial units i and j, each row sum is 2)( 1 =d ' 1 =2d ' 1 =3d '. . .); representing a 
series that is not finite. This is perhaps the reason why some empirical applications 
introduce a cut-off point d 
+ such that w ij 00 if d ij d </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>. However, since the ratio 
2)( </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>=d ' </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>=2d ' 1 =3d '. . .)=N 00 as N goes to infinity, condition (b) is satisfied, 
which implies that an inverse distance matrix without a cut-off point does not 
necessarily have to be excluded in an empirical study for reasons of consistency. 
The opposite situation occurs when all cross-sectional units are assumed to be 
neighbours of each other and are given equal weights. In that case all off-diagonal 
elements of the spatial weights matrix are w ij 01. Since the row and column sums are 
N Á 1, these sums diverge to infinity as N goes to infinity. In contrast to the previous 
case, however, (N Á 1)/N01 instead of 0 as N goes to infinity. This implies that a 
spatial weights matrix that has equal weights and that is row normalized subsequently, 
w ij 01/(N(1), must be excluded for reasons of consistency. 
Figure 1 summarizes a family of eight linear spatial econometric models, among 
which are the non-spatial model in (1) on the right-hand side and the Manski 
model in (2) on the left-hand side. Each model to the right of the Manski model 
can be obtained from that model by imposing restrictions on one or more of its 
parameters. The kinds of restrictions are reported alongside the arrows in Figure 1. </p>



<p>Figure 1. The relationships between different spatial dependence models for cross-section data. </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 13 </p>

<p>Some of the models recorded in Figure 1 are well known and frequently used 
in applied research, while other models are not. LeSage &amp; Pace (p. 32) denote the 
model with a spatially lagged dependent variable (WY) and a spatially 
autocorrelated error term (Wo) by the term SAC, though without pointing out 
what this acronym is standing for. Since Kelejian &amp; Prucha (1998) have been the 
main advocates of this model, it is therefore renamed the KelejianÁPrucha model 
in this paper. The model with a spatially lagged dependent variable (WY) and 
spatially lagged independent variables (WX) has been introduced by Anselin 
(1988) and is labelled the spatial Durbin model. A model with spatially lagged 
independent variables (WX) and a spatially autocorrelated error term has hardly 
been used in the literature. LeSage &amp; Pace (pp. 41Á42) label it the spatial Durbin 
error model. 
Figure 1 seems to indicate that the best strategy to test for spatial interaction 
effects is to start with the most general model, i.e. the model that includes a spatially 
lagged dependent variable, spatially lagged independent variables, and a spatially 
autocorrelated error term simultaneously. However, as Manski (1993) notes, at least 
one of the K'2 interaction effects must be excluded, because otherwise the 
parameters are unidentified. To verify this, I carried out a simple Monte Carlo 
experiment generating Y by (2a) and (2b), one X variable drawn from a uniform 
distribution on the interval [Á1,1], r 0 a 0 b 0 u 0 l 0 0:25; s 
2 00.01, N060, 
and a spatial weights matrix W corresponding to the corners of the seams in a soccer 
ball (in <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> known as the Bucky Ball). Based on 1,000 repetitions, I found biases 
in the parameter estimates of the endogenous and exogenous interaction effects 
(r and u, respectively) that may be as great as 0.0423 and, related to that, standard 
deviations that may be as great as 0.2677. These results corroborate Manski's (1993, 
p. 534) finding that there are no technical obstacles to estimating a model with 
interaction effects among the dependent variable, the independent variables and the 
disturbance terms, but that the parameter estimates cannot be interpreted in a 
meaningful way since the endogenous and exogenous effects cannot be 
distinguished from each other. 
Following LeSage &amp; Pace (pp. 155Á158), the best option in such circumstances 
is to exclude the spatially autocorrelated error term. 
2 The cost of ignoring spatial 
dependence in the dependent variable and/or in the independent variables is 
relatively high since the econometrics literature has pointed out that if one or more 
relevant explanatory variable are omitted from a regression equation, the estimator 
of the coefficients for the remaining variables is biased and inconsistent (Greene, 
2005, pp. 133Á134). In contrast, ignoring spatial dependence in the disturbances, if 
present, will only cause a loss of efficiency. Furthermore, the spatial Durbin model 
produces unbiased coefficient estimates also if the true data-generation process is 
any of the other spatial regression specifications recorded in Figure 1, except for the 
Manski model. By contrast, if the KelejianÁPrucha model is taken as the point of 
departure, it will suffer from omitted variables bias if the true data-generation 
process is a spatial Durbin or a spatial Durbin error model. Similarly, if the spatial 
Durbin error model is taken as the point of departure, it will suffer from omitted 
variables bias if the true data-generation process is a spatial lag, KelejianÁPrucha or 
spatial Durbin model. 
A concomitant advantage of the spatial Durbin model is that it produces correct 
standard errors or t-values of the coefficient estimates also if the true data-
generating process is a spatial error model. This is because the spatial error model is 
a special case of the spatial Durbin model (see Figure 1), as a result of which error </p>

<p>14 J. P. Elhorst </p>

<p>dependence is correctly taken into account in its varianceÁcovariance matrix. 
Whether inference regarding dispersion of the explanatory variables is also correct if 
the true data-generating process is a KelejianÁPrucha or spatial Durbin error model 
is an issue that, according to LeSage &amp; Pace, needs further exploration (p. 158). 
This is because neither of these models is a special case of the others (see Figure 1), 
indicating that the implicit specification of spatial error dependence in the spatial 
Durbin model is different from that in the other two models. </p>

<p>3. Methods of Estimation </p>

<p>Three methods have been developed in the literature to estimate models that 
include spatial interaction effects. One is based on maximum likelihood (ML), one 
on instrumental variables or generalized method of moments (IV/GMM), and one 
on the Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) approach. One important 
limitation of LeSage &amp; Pace's book is that it discusses the ML method (Ch. 3) and 
the Bayesian method (Ch. 5) extensively, but does not pay any attention to the IV/ 
GMM method. 
One advantage of IV/GMM estimators is that they do not rely on the 
assumption of normality of the disturbances. One disadvantage is the possibility of 
ending up with a coefficient estimate for r or for l outside its parameter space. 
Whereas these coefficients are restricted to the interval (1/r min , 1) by the Jacobian 
term in the log-likelihood function of ML estimators or in the conditional 
distribution of the spatial parameter of Bayesian estimators, they are unrestricted 
using IV/GMM since these estimators ignore the Jacobian term. 
One of the reasons for developing IV/GMM estimators was as a response to 
perceived computational difficulties (Kelejian &amp; Prucha, 1998, 1999). Estimation of 
spatial econometric models involves the manipulation of N)N matrices, such as 
matrix multiplication, matrix inversion, the computation of characteristic roots 
and/or Cholesky decomposition. These manipulations may be computationally 
intensive and/or may require significant amounts of memory if N is large. Since 
IV/GMM estimators ignore the Jacobian term, many of these problems could be 
avoided. In Chapter 4 of their book, however, LeSage &amp; Pace produce conclusive 
evidence that these computational difficulties have become a thing of the past, as is 
the case for ML and Bayesian estimators. 
In spite of this, Fingleton &amp; Le Gallo (2007, 2008) show that IV/GMM 
estimators are extremely useful in those cases where linear spatial dependence 
models contain one or more endogenous explanatory variables (other than the 
spatially lagged dependent variable) that need to be instrumented. In applied 
econometrics work, the presence of endogenous variables on the right-hand side is 
a common occurrence, as endogeneity may be the result of measurement errors on 
explanatory variables, of omitted variables correlated with included explanatory 
variables or of the existence of an unknown set of simultaneous structural 
equations. ML or Bayesian estimators of models with a spatial lag (i.e. the spatial 
lag model and the spatial Durbin model) and additional endogenous variables do 
not feature in the spatial econometrics literature and would be difficult, if not 
impossible, to derive. The same applies to models with a spatial error process (i.e. 
the spatial error model and the spatial Durbin error model). By contrast, models 
including a spatial lag and additional endogenous variables can be straightforwardly 
estimated by two-stage least squares (2SLS). To instrument the spatially lagged 
dependent variable, Kelejian et al. (2004) suggest [/X t WX t . . . W 
g X t ]; where g is a </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 15 </p>

<p>pre-selected constant. 
3 Typically, one would take g 01 or g 02, dependent on the 
number of regressors and the type of model. For example, in the case of the spatial 
Durbin model g should be greater than one, since this model already contains 
the variables X and WX on the right-hand side. If one or more of the explana-
tory variables are endogenous, the set of instruments must be limited to 
[/X </p>

<p>ex 
t </p>

<p>WX </p>

<p>ex 
t </p>

<p>. . . W 
d X </p>

<p>ex </p>

<p>t ]; where 'ex' denotes the X variables that are exogenous. 
Another difference is that this set may also be used to instrument the additional 
endogenous explanatory variables. A similar type of extension applies to Kelejian &amp; 
Prucha's (1999) GMM estimator for models including a spatial error process 
together with endogenous explanatory variables (Fingleton &amp; Le Gallo, 2007). In 
addition, Fingleton &amp; Le Gallo (2008) consider a mixed 2SLS/GMM estimator of 
the KelejianÁPrucha model extended to include endogenous explanatory variables. </p>

<p>4. Model Comparison </p>

<p>Many practitioners are in two minds about whether to apply the general-to-specific 
or the specific-to-general approach. This is understandable. Whereas LeSage &amp; 
Pace argue that the spatial Durbin model is the best point of departure, Florax et al. 
(2003) have found that the expansion of a linear regression equation with spatially 
lagged variables, conditional on the results of misspecification tests, outperforms 
the general-to-specific approach for finding the true data-generation process. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>I therefore propose the following test procedure to find out which model is the 
most likely candidate to explain the data. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>First estimate the OLS model and test whether the spatial lag model or the 
spatial error model is more appropriate to describe the data. For this purpose, one 
may use the classic LM-tests proposed by Anselin (1988), and the robust LM-tests 
proposed by Anselin et al. (1996). 
6 Both the classic and the robust tests are based on 
the residuals of the OLS model and follow a chi-squared distribution with one 
degree of freedom. 
If the OLS model is rejected in favour of the spatial lag, the spatial error model 
or in favour of both models, then the spatial Durbin model should be estimated. If 
these models are estimated by maximum likelihood, a likelihood ratio (LR) test can 
subsequently be used to test the hypotheses H 0 : u00 and H 0 : u'rb00. The first 
hypothesis examines whether the spatial Durbin can be simplified to the spatial lag 
model, and the second hypothesis whether it can be simplified to the spatial error 
model (see Figure 1). Both tests follow a chi-squared distribution with K degrees of 
freedom. 
If both hypotheses H 0 : u00 and H 0 : u'rb 00 are rejected, then the spatial 
Durbin best describes the data. Conversely, if the first hypothesis cannot be 
rejected, then the spatial lag model best describes the data, provided that the 
(robust) LM tests also pointed to the spatial lag model. Similarly, if the second 
hypothesis cannot be rejected, then the spatial error model best describes the data, 
provided that the (robust) LM tests also pointed to the spatial error model. If one of 
these conditions is not satisfied, i.e. if the (robust) LM tests point to a model other 
than the LR tests, then the spatial Durbin model should be adopted. This is because 
this model generalizes both the spatial lag and the spatial error model (see Figure 1). 
If the OLS model is estimated and not rejected in favour of both the spatial lag 
and the spatial error model, 
7 the OLS model should be re-estimated including 
spatially lagged independent variables (WX) or a particular selection of these K 
variables to be able to test the hypothesis H 0 : u00. If this hypothesis cannot also be </p>

<p>16 J. P. Elhorst </p>

<p>rejected, then it may be concluded that the OLS model best describes the data. In 
that case there is no empirical evidence in favour of any type of spatial interaction 
effect. By contrast, when this hypothesis must be rejected, the spatial Durbin model 
should be estimated to be able to test the additional hypothesis H 0 : r00. If the 
latter hypothesis is also rejected, then the spatial Durbin model best describes the 
data. If it is not, it may be concluded that a model with spatially lagged independent 
variables only suffices. </p>

<p>5. Selection of the Spatial Weights Matrix </p>

<p>One major weakness of spatial econometric models is that the spatial weights matrix 
W cannot be estimated but needs to be specified in advance and that economic 
theory underlying spatial econometric applications often has little to say about the 
specification of W (Leenders, 2002). For this reason, it has become common 
practice to investigate whether the results are robust to the specification of W. 
A recent influential paper by Ertur &amp; Koch (2007) is illustrative of this approach. By 
including spatial dependence structures in theoretical economic relationships 
explaining economic growth per capita, they end up with an empirical model 
that takes the form of a spatial Durbin model. However, since the theoretical model 
offers no guidance as to how to specify the spatial weights matrix, they consider 
two alternatives: one matrix whose non-diagonal elements are measured by 1/d 
2 , 
where d reflects the distance between two units, and another matrix whose 
elements are measured by e </p>

<p>Á2d </p>

<p>. Since many other specifications have been 
considered in the spatial econometrics literature, among which are a binary 
contiguity matrix, an inverse distance matrix with or without a cut-off point, a 
q nearest-neighbour matrix (where q is a positive integer, such as 5 or 10), a 
question that recurs is how the selection procedure of the spatial weights matrix 
might be improved. 
A recent Monte-Carlo study by Stakhovych &amp; Bijmolt (2009) demonstrates 
that a weights matrix selection procedure that is based on 'goodness-of-fit' criteria 
increases the probability of finding the true specification. The most widely used 
criterion is the log-likelihood function value. If a spatial interaction model is 
estimated based on S different spatial weights matrices and the log-likelihood 
function value of every model is estimated, one may select the spatial weights 
matrix exhibiting the highest log-likelihood function value. Harris &amp; Kravtsova 
(2009) criticize this approach, because it would only find a local maximum among 
the competing models and not necessarily a correctly specified W (unless it is 
unknowingly included in the set of competing models considered). However, the 
Monte Carlo results found by Stakhovych &amp; Bijmolt (2009) partly refute this 
critique. Although there is a serious probability of selecting the wrong spatial 
weights matrix if spatial dependence is weak, the consequences of this poor choice 
are limited because the coefficient estimates are quite close to the true ones. 
Conversely, although the wrong choice of a spatial weights matrix can distort the 
coefficient estimates severely, the probability that this really happens is small if 
spatial dependence is strong. 
One of the merits of LeSage &amp; Pace's book is that they offer another criterion 
to select models, namely the Bayesian posterior model probability. Whereas tests 
for significant differences between log-likelihood function values, such as the LR-
test, can formally not be used if models are non-nested (i.e. based on different 
spatial weights matrices), Bayesian posterior model probabilities do not require </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 17 </p>

<p>nested models to carry out these comparisons (p. 162). The basic idea is to set prior 
probabilities equal to 1/S, making each model equally likely a priori, to estimate 
each model by Bayesian methods, and then to compute posterior probabilities 
based on the data and the estimation results of this set of S models. Although the 
mathematics of this approach might deter potential users (Chs 5 and 6), my 
experience with this approach is positive. First, posterior model probabilities may 
differ widely even if the estimation results appear to be quite robust to different 
specifications of the spatial weights matrix. In a study I did on cross-country 
differences in governance (Seldadyo et al., 2010), the posterior model probability of 
a 10 nearest-neighbour matrix appeared to be more than six times as large as that of 
an inverse distance matrix, more than three times as large as that of a five nearest-
neighbour matrix, and more than twice as large as an inverse distance matrix with a 
cut-off point. Second, since Matlab routines applying Bayesian methods to the 
spatial lag, spatial error and spatial Durbin models are made downloadable for free 
on LeSage's website (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">www.spatial-econometrics.com</rs>), these kinds of comparisons 
can be carried out relatively easily. Furthermore, since <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">LeSage</rs> also provides <rs id="software-1" type="software">Matlab</rs> 
routines applying the Bayesian method to the spatial lag, spatial error and spatial 
Durbin models of limited dependent variables, similar types of selection procedures 
as discussed in this and the previous sections can be used for empirical problems 
requiring a probit or tobit approach (Ch. 10). 
Another approach to capture spatial interaction effects is to extend the linear 
regression model by a finite number of unobserved factors that affect all units 
(Pesaran, 2006). Factor models are potentially powerful in that they do not require 
strong and unverifiable assumptions on the nature of spatial dependence. On the 
other hand, common factors only model interaction effects among the error terms 
and, often, these factors are difficult to interpret. Nevertheless, a careful elaboration 
of the relative merits of the multifactor approach, for example, in combination with 
the spatial Durbin model is an interesting topic for further research. </p>

<p>6. Direct, Indirect and Spatial Spillover Effects </p>

<p>Many empirical studies use point estimates of one or more spatial regression model 
specifications to test the hypothesis as to whether or not spatial spillovers exist. One 
of the key contributions of LeSage &amp; Pace's book (p. 74) is the observation that this 
may lead to erroneous conclusions, and that a partial derivative interpretation of the 
impact from changes to the variables of different model specifications represents a 
more valid basis for testing this hypothesis. To illustrate this, they give an example 
of a spatially lagged independent variable WX whose coefficient is negative and 
insignificant (table 3.3), while its spatial spillover effect is positive and significant 
(table 3.4). 
If the spatial Durbin model is taken as the point of departure and rewritten as </p>

<p>Y 0 (I (rW ) 
(1 ai N '(I (rW ) 
(1 (Xb'WXu)'(I (rW ) 
(1 o; 
(3) </p>

<p>the matrix of partial derivatives of Y with respect to the kth explanatory variable of 
X in unit 1 up to unit N (say x ik for i 01, . . ., N, respectively) is relatively easy to 
obtain: </p>



<p>@Y </p>

<p>@x 1k 
: 
@Y </p>

<p>@x Nk </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>@y 1 </p>

<p>@x 1k 
: 
@y 1 </p>

<p>@x Nk 
: 
: 
: 
@y N </p>

<p>@x 1k 
: 
@y N </p>

<p>@x Nk </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>0 (I (rW ) </p>

<p>(1 </p>

<p>b k 
w 12 u k : w 1N u k 
w 21 u k 
b k 
: w 2N u k 
: 
: 
: 
: 
w N 1 u k w N2 u k : 
b k </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
5 ; 
(4) </p>

<p>where w ij is the (i, j)th element of W. However, it is the unfamiliarity with or the 
complexity of this expression that troubles many practitioners. To provide a better 
understanding of the properties of the partial derivatives, I will give the simplest 
example possible without loss of generality, and use this example to explain LeSage 
&amp; Pace's claim step by step. </p>

<p>6.1. Properties of Partial Derivatives </p>

<p>Suppose we have three spatial units that are arranged linearly: unit 1 is a neighbour 
of unit 2, unit 2 is a neighbour of both units 1 and 3, and unit 3 is a neighbour of 
unit 2. 
8 Then the row-normalized spatial weights matrix W and the spatial 
multiplier matrix (I (rW) 
Á1 are </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>W 0 </p>

<p>0 1 0 
w 21 0 w 23 
0 1 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 and (I (rW ) </p>

<p>(1 </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>1 ( r 2 </p>

<p>1(w 23 r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r 
r 
2 w 23 
rw 21 
1 
rw 23 
r 
2 w 21 
r 1(w 21 r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 ; 
(5) </p>

<p>where w 12 0w 32 01 since units 1 and 3 have only one neighbour, and w 21 'w 23 0 
1 (w 21 and w 23 might be different). Substituting the second matrix of (5) into (4), 
the impact of a change in successively units 1, 2 and 3 of variable x k on units 1, 2 
and 3 of the dependent variable turns out to be </p>

<p>@Y </p>

<p>@x 1k </p>

<p>@Y </p>

<p>@x 2k </p>

<p>@Y </p>

<p>@x 3k </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ( r 2 </p>

<p>(1(w 23 r 
2 )b k '(w 21 r)u k rb k 'u k 
(w 23 r 
2 )b k '(rw 23 )u k 
(w 21 r)b k 'w 21 u k 
b k 'ru k 
(w 23 r)b k 'w 23 u k 
(w 21 r 
2 )b k '(w 21 r)u k 
rb k 'u k (1(w 21 r 
2 )b k '(w 23 r)u k </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>5 : </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>The results obtained in (5) and (6) illustrate that the partial derivatives of Y with 
respect to the kth explanatory variable in the spatial Durbin model in (4) have three 
important properties. First, if a particular explanatory variable in a particular unit 
changes, not only will the dependent variable in that unit itself change but also the 
dependent variables in other units. The first is called a direct effect and the second an 
indirect effect. Note that every diagonal element of the matrix of partial derivatives </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 19 </p>

<p>represents a direct effect, and that every non-diagonal element represents 
an indirect effect. Consequently, indirect effects do not occur if both r00 and 
u k 00, since all non-diagonal elements will then be zero [see (4) and (6)]. 
Second, direct and indirect effects are different for different units in the sample. 
Direct effects are different because the diagonal elements of the matrix (I Á rW) </p>

<p>Á1 </p>

<p>are different for different units, provided that r"0 [see the diagonal elements of (5) 
and (6)]. Indirect effects are different because both the non-diagonal elements of 
the matrix (I Á rW) 
Á1 and of the matrix W are different for different units, provided 
that r"0 and/or u k "0 [see the non-diagonal elements of (5) and (6)]. 
Third, indirect effects that occur if u k "0 are known as local effects, as opposed 
to indirect effects that occur if r"0 and that are known as global effects. Local effects 
got their name because they arise only from a unit's neighbourhood set; if the 
element w ij of the spatial weights matrix is non-zero (zero), then the effect of x jk on 
y i is also non-zero (zero). Global effects got their name because they also arise from 
units that do not belong to a unit's neighbourhood set. This follows from the fact 
that the matrix (I(rW) 
Á1 , in contrast to W, does not contain zero elements 
(provided that r"0) [see W and (I Á rW) 
Á1 in (5)]. </p>

<p>6.2. Implications for Reporting Direct and Indirect Effects </p>

<p>Since both the direct and indirect effects are different for different units in the 
sample, the presentation of these effects is a problem. If we have N spatial units 
and K explanatory variables, we obtain K different N )N matrices of direct and 
indirect effects. Even for small values of N and K, it may already be rather difficult 
to report these results compactly. To improve the surveyability of the estimation 
results of spatial regression model specifications, LeSage &amp; Pace therefore propose 
to report one direct effect measured by the average of the diagonal elements of the 
matrix on the right-hand side of (4), and one indirect effect measured by the 
average of either the row sums or the column sums of the non-diagonal elements 
of that matrix. The average row effect quantifies the impact on a particular 
element of the dependent variable as a result of a unit change in all elements of an 
exogenous variable, while the average column effect quantifies the impact of 
changing a particular element of an exogenous variable on the dependent variable 
of all other units. However, since the numerical magnitudes of these two 
calculations of the indirect effect are the same, it does not matter which one is 
used (pp. 33Á42). 
Table 1 reports the direct and indirect effects of the models that have been 
recorded in Figure 1 for the example with N03 and the spatial weights matrix 
in (5). In the case of the spatial Durbin model [using (6)], we obtain a direct effect of </p>

<p>(3 ( r 
2 ) </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) 
b k ' 
2r </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) 
u k </p>

<p>and an indirect effect of </p>

<p>3r ' r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) 
b k ' 
3 ' r </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) 
u k : </p>

<p>Unfortunately, since every empirical application will have its own unique number of 
observations (N) and spatial weights matrix (W), these formulae cannot be </p>



<p>generalized. Nevertheless, the results in Table 1 do illustrate that the direct and 
indirect effects of different model specifications have the general properties as 
described below. </p>

<p>6.3. Properties of the Proposed Direct and Indirect Effects </p>

<p>If the OLS model is adopted, the direct effect of an explanatory variable is equal 
to the coefficient estimate of that variable (b k ), while its indirect effect is zero by 
construction. If the OLS model is augmented with a spatially autocorrelated error 
term, the direct and the indirect effects remain the same. This is because the 
spatial autoregressive model for the disturbances does not come into play when 
considering the partial derivative of the dependent variable with respect to 
changes in the explanatory variables [see (3) and (4)]. These properties also hold 
for the extension of the spatial lag model and of the spatial Durbin model with 
spatial autocorrelation, i.e. the KelejianÁPrucha and the Manski models, 
respectively. 
If the spatial Durbin error model is adopted, the direct effect of an explanatory 
variable is equal to the coefficient estimate of that variable (b k ), while its indirect 
effect is equal to the coefficient estimate of its spatial lagged value (u k ). This means 
that the interpretation of the coefficients of the OLS model, the spatial error model 
and the spatial Durbin error model is straightforward and that a comparison of these 
coefficients is valid. 
The interpretation of the coefficients gets complicated when moving to one of 
the other models. If the direct effect and the indirect effect of the spatial lag model 
(as well as the KelejianÁPrucha model) are compared with those of the OLS model, 
two notable differences can be observed. First, whereas the direct effect of the kth 
explanatory variable in the OLS model is b k , the direct effect in the spatial 
lag model is b k pre-multiplied with a number that will be greater than or equal 
to unity. Table 1 shows that this number in the example amounts to 
(3(r 
2 )=3(1(r 
2 ): Second, whereas the indirect effect in the OLS model is 
zero by construction, it is non-zero in the spatial lag model. 
The property that the number with which b k is pre-multiplied when 
calculating the direct effect is greater than or equal to unity is due to the spatial 
multiplier matrix (I (rW) 
Á1 that can be decomposed as follows (pp. 40Á41): </p>

<p>(I (rW ) 
(1 0 
X </p>

<p>q00 </p>

<p>r 
q W </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>
0I 'rW 'r 
2 W 
2 ' . . . 
(7) </p>

<p>Table 1. Direct and indirect effects of different model specifications </p>

<p>Type of model 
Direct effect 
Indirect effect </p>

<p>Spatial Durbin model/ </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>(3(r 2 ) 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>b k ' </p>

<p>2r 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>u k </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>3r'r 2 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>b k ' </p>

<p>3'r 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>u k 
Manski model 
Spatial lag model/ </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>(3(r 2 ) 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>b k </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>3r'r 2 
3(1(r 2 ) </p>

<p>b k 
KelejianÁPrucha model 
Spatial Durbin error model 
b k 
u k 
OLS model/ 
b k 
0 
Spatial error model </p>

<p>Note: N03, W as in (4). </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 21 </p>

<p>Since the non-diagonal elements of the first matrix term on the right-hand side (the 
identity matrix I) are zero, this term represents a direct effect of a change in X only. 
Conversely, since the diagonal elements of the second matrix term on the right-
hand side (rW) were assumed to be zero (see Section 2), this term represents an 
indirect effect of a change in X only. Furthermore, since W is taken to the power 1 
here, this indirect effect is limited to first-order neighbours only, i.e. the units that 
belong to the neighbourhood set of every spatial unit. All other terms on the right-
hand side represent second-and higher-order direct and indirect effects. Higher-
order direct effects arise as a result of feedback effects, i.e. impacts passing through 
neighbouring units and back to the unit itself (e.g. 1 02 01 and 1 02 03 02 01). 
It is these feedback effects that are responsible for the fact that the overall direct 
effect eventually increases. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>One important limitation of the spatial lag model is that the ratio between the 
indirect and the direct effect of a particular explanatory variable is independent of 
b k . Table 1 illustrates that b k in the numerator and b k in the denominator of this 
ratio cancel each other out: </p>

<p>(3 ( r 
2 ) </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) </p>

<p>b k = </p>

<p>3r ' r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3(1 ( r 2 ) 
b k 0 
3 ( r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3r ' r 2 
: </p>

<p>This property implies that the ratio between the indirect and direct effects in the 
spatial lag model is the same for every explanatory variable, and that its magnitude 
depends on the spatial autoregressive parameter r and the specification of the spatial 
weights matrix W only. In many empirical applications, this is not very likely. 
Finally, if the spatial Durbin model is adopted, both the direct effect and the 
indirect effect of a particular explanatory variable will also depend on the coefficient 
estimate u k of the spatially lagged value of that variable (see Table 1). The result is 
that no prior restrictions are imposed on the magnitude of both the direct and 
indirect effects and thus that the ratio between the indirect and the direct effect may 
be different for different explanatory variables. As a result of this property, the 
spatial Durbin is a more attractive point of departure in an empirical study than 
other spatial regression specifications. </p>

<p>6.4. Testing for Spatial Spillovers </p>

<p>The estimated indirect effects of the independent explanatory variables should 
eventually be used to test the hypothesis as to whether or not spatial spillovers exist, 
rather than the coefficient estimate of the spatially lagged dependent variable and/or 
the coefficient estimates of the spatially lagged independent variables. However, 
one difficulty is that it cannot be seen from the coefficient estimates and the 
corresponding standard errors or t-values (derived from the varianceÁcovariance 
matrix) whether the indirect effects in the spatial Durbin model are significant 
(note: the same applies to the spatial lag model). This is because the indirect effects 
are composed of different coefficient estimates according to complex mathematical 
formulae and the dispersion of these indirect effects depends on the dispersion of all 
coefficient estimates involved (see Table 1). For example, if the coefficients r, b k 
and u k in the spatial Durbin model happen to be significant, this does not 
automatically mean that the indirect effect of the kth explanatory variable is also 
significant. Conversely, if one or two of these coefficients are insignificant, the 
indirect effect may still be significant. </p>



<p>One possible way to calculate the dispersion of the direct and indirect effects is 
to apply formulae for the sum, the difference, the product and the quotient of 
random variables (see, among others, Mood et al., 1974, pp. 178Á181). However, 
owing to the complexity of the matrix of partial derivatives [see (6)] and because 
every empirical application will have its own unique number of observations (N) 
and spatial weights matrix (W), it is almost impossible to derive one general 
approach that can be applied under all circumstances. In order to draw inferences 
regarding the statistical significance of the direct and indirect effects, LeSage &amp; Pace 
(p. 39) therefore suggest simulating the distribution of the direct and indirect effects 
using the varianceÁcovariance matrix implied by the maximum likelihood 
estimates. 
Elhorst &amp; Fréret (2009) show that the varianceÁcovariance matrix of the 
parameter estimates of the spatial Durbin model, a matrix that is not reported in 
LeSage &amp; Pace's book, takes the form: </p>

<p>Var(r;â;b;û;ŝ 
2 ) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>trace(WW 'W 
TW )' 
1 
s 2ĝX </p>

<p>TW TWXĝ </p>

<p>: 
: </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>TWXĝ </p>

<p>1 
s 2X </p>

<p>TX </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>1 
s 2 
trace(W ) 
0 
N </p>

<p>2ŝ 4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>(1 </p>

<p>; (8) </p>

<p>whereW 0 W (I (rW ) 
(1 ;X 0 [i N X WX] andĝ 0 [âb TûT ] 
T to 
simplify notation. Since this matrix is symmetric the upper diagonal elements 
are not shown. 
Using the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Matlab</rs> routine 'sar' posted on <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">LeSage</rs>'s website (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">www.spatial-econometrics.com</rs>), one particular parameter combination drawn from this 
varianceÁcovariance matrix (indexed by d ) can be obtained by: </p>

<p>[r d a d b </p>

<p>T 
d </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>T 
d </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>d ] 
T 0 P 
T q '[râb TûTŝ2 ] 
T ; 
(9) </p>

<p>where P denotes the upper-triangular Cholesky decomposition of Var(r;â;b;û;ŝ 
2 ) 
and q is a vector of length 3'2K (the number of parameters that have been 
estimated) containing random values drawn from a normal distribution with mean 
zero and standard deviation one. If D parameter combinations are drawn like this 
and the (in)direct effect of a particular explanatory variable is determined for every 
parameter combination, the overall (in)direct effect can be approximated by 
computing the mean value over these D draws and its significance level (t-value) by 
dividing this mean by the corresponding standard deviation. If m kd denotes the 
indirect effect of the kth explanatory variable of draw d, 
11 the overall indirect effect 
over all draws and the corresponding t-value will be: </p>

<p>m k (ind: eff : kth var:) 0 
1 
D </p>

<p>X D </p>

<p>d01 </p>

<p>m kd ; 
(10a) </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 23 </p>

<p>t-value (of ind: eff : kth var:) 0m k = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>D ( 1 </p>

<p>X D </p>

<p>d01 </p>

<p>(m kd (m k ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>
: 
(10b) </p>

<p>Given the t-value of this indirect effect, one can finally test whether the kth variable 
causes spatial spillover effects. </p>

<p>7. Spatio-temporal Models </p>

<p>Figure 1 uncovered the relationships between eight different spatial dependence 
models for cross-section data. A similar type of scheme for space-time data has been 
reported in Elhorst (2001), with as the most general model a first-order 
autoregressive distributed lag model in both space and time: </p>

<p>Y t 0 tY t(1 'rWY t 'hWY t(1 'X t b'WX t u'X t(1 8 'WX t(1 f'o t : (11) </p>

<p>In this specification Y t denotes an N)1 vector consisting of one observation 
on the dependent variable for every unit in the sample (i01, . . ., N), and X t 
an N)K matrix of exogenous explanatory variables, both measured at different 
points in time. The model in (11) subsumes several simpler econometric 
models, among which is the spatial Durbin model (/t 0 h 0 8 0 f 0 0): 
However, just as with the Manski model discussed in Section 2, it suffers 
from an identification problem (see Anselin et al., 2008). This raises the 
question as to which spatio-temporal models are feasible. Up to now, at least 
two interesting candidates have been proposed in the literature, including one 
by LeSage &amp; Pace (Ch. 7). The names of these models are taken from Anselin 
et al. (2008). 
The first candidate is the time-space dynamic model </p>

<p>Y t 0 tY t(1 'rWY t 'hWY t(1 'X t b'o t ; 
(12) </p>

<p>whose properties have been analysed by Yu et al. (2008). 
12 By continuous 
substitution of Y t-1 up to Y t((T(1) into this equation and rearranging terms, (12) 
can be rewritten as: </p>

<p>Y t 0 (I (rW ) 
(T (tI 'hW ) 
T Y t(T ' 
X T </p>

<p>p01 </p>

<p>(I (rW ) 
(p (tI 'hW ) </p>

<p>p(1 </p>

<p>Â (X t((p(1) b'o t((p(1) ): 
(13) </p>

<p>Anselin et al. (2008) criticize this model because it might still create identification 
problems. The difficulty is that two global spatial multiplier matrices are at work at 
the same time, (I (rW ) 
(p and (tI 'hW ) 
p(1 ; rather than one process that 
produces global spatial spillover effects and another one that produces local spatial 
spillover effects. Anselin et al. (2008) therefore suggest setting h 0 0 (the model so 
obtained is labelled the time-space simultaneous model). In his keynote speech at 
the third World Conference of the Spatial Econometrics Association in 2009, James 
LeSage suggested h 0(tr: This restriction has the effect that all higher-order 
terms of the two spatial multiplier matrices cancel each other out, except for the 
factor t, as a result of which (13) simplifies to: </p>



<p>Y t 0 t 
T Y t(T ' 
X T </p>

<p>p01 </p>

<p>t 
p(1 (I (rW ) 
(1 (X t((p(1) b'o t((p(1) ): 
(14) </p>

<p>Using (7), (14) can be rewritten as: </p>

<p>Y t 0 t 
T Y t(T ' 
X T </p>

<p>p01 </p>

<p>
t </p>

<p>p(1 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>q00 </p>

<p>r 
q W 
q (X t((p(1) b'o t((p(1) ) </p>

<p>: 
(15) </p>

<p>This equation shows that the impact of a change in one of the explanatory variables 
gradually diminishes over both space and time, provided that jtjB1 Á r if r]0 
and jtj B1 Á rr min if rB0 (see Elhorst, 2008). Furthermore, both effects can be 
separated from each other mathematically. The impact of a change in one of the 
explanatory variables over space falls by the factor rW for every higher-order 
neighbour, and over time by the factor t for every next time period. It is these 
kinds of schemes that might be used to uncover short-term and long-term direct 
effects, as well as short-term and long-term indirect effects. Furthermore, these 
kinds of schemes will further contribute to a better understanding (e.g. Groote 
et al., 2009) and thus to the popularity of spatio-temporal models. 
Since (15) does not contain local spillover effects, the original model in (12) 
may be extended to include spatially lagged independent variables WX t u, provided 
that this model is estimated under the condition h 0(tr to avoid identification 
problems. In doing so, this spatio-temporal model can be used, just as with the 
spatial Durbin model for cross-sectional data, to estimate both global and local 
spatial spillover effects without imposing prior restrictions on the magnitude of 
these effects. 
The second candidate is the time-space recursive model </p>

<p>Y t 0 tY t(1 'hWY t(1 'X t b'WX t u'o t ; 
(16) </p>

<p>introduced by LeSage &amp; Pace (pp. 190Á191). By continuous substitution and 
rearranging terms, this model can be rewritten as: </p>

<p>Y t 0 (tI 'hW ) 
T Y t(T ' 
X </p>

<p>T (1 </p>

<p>p00 </p>

<p>(tI 'hW ) 
p (X t(p b'WX t(p u'o t(p ): (17) </p>

<p>This equation shows that Y t depends not only on present but also on past values of X t 
and WX t . This is exactly the reason why the extension of (16) with X t(1 and WX t(1 
would create identification problems. If the stationarity conditions are satisfied, 
13 the 
impact of the matrix (tI 'hW ) 
p diminishes over both space and time. To determine 
the extent of this, the matrix of partial derivatives with respect to the kth explanatory 
for every spatial unit may again be contemplated. One difference between this and 
the earlier spatio-temporal model is that the decomposition of the matrix (tI 'hW ) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>is more complex. If t is non-zero, we have: </p>

<p>(tI 'hW ) 
p 0 t 
p (I ' </p>

<p>h 
t </p>

<p>W ) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>0 t 
p [I 'p </p>

<p>h 
t </p>

<p>W ' </p>

<p>p( p(1) 
2! </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>h 
t </p>

<p>W ) 
2 ' </p>

<p>p( p(1)( p(2) 
3! </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>h 
t </p>

<p>W ) 
3 '. . .]: (18) </p>

<p>This equation shows that the impact of a change in one of the explanatory variables 
over time falls by the factor t for every next time period, and that the impact over 
space falls by the factor </p>

<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 25 </p>



<p>p'1 
O </p>

<p>(1 </p>



<p>h 
t </p>

<p>W </p>

<p>for every higher-order neighbour, where O denotes the order number of that 
neighbour (e.g. when moving from first-to second-order neighbours, O02). 
Therefore, this spatio-temporal model can, just as the spatial Durbin for cross-
sectional data and the earlier spatio-temporal model, be used to estimate both global 
and local spatial spillover effects without imposing prior restrictions on the 
magnitude of these effects. </p>

<p>8. Conclusions </p>

<p>The overall conclusion of this paper is that the state of the art of applied spatial 
econometrics has taken a step change with the publication of LeSage &amp; Pace's 
book. One can no longer restrict oneself to the spatial lag and/or the spatial error 
model, or to simply interpreting their point estimates and testing whether these 
point estimates are robust to different specifications of the spatial weights matrix. 
A state-of-the-art application of spatial econometrics should also consider the spatial 
Durbin model, and interpret its direct and indirect effects, unless statistical tests 
show that simpler models suffice. There are two major reasons why the spatial 
Durbin model cannot be ignored. First, it is the only means of producing unbiased 
coefficient estimates, even if the true data-generation process is a spatial lag, spatial 
error, KelejianÁPrucha or spatial Durbin error model. Second, it produces both 
global and local spillover effects and, related to that, it does not impose prior 
restrictions on the magnitude of these effects. 
The conclusion from the short overview of spatio-temporal models is that 
models with similar types of properties are also available for space-time data. An 
application and a comparison of these spatio-temporal models are the topic of 
further research. 
One important limitation of LeSage &amp; Pace's book is that it does not pay 
attention to instrumental variables or generalized method of moments (IV/GMM) 
techniques. Whereas IV/GMM estimators can easily handle linear spatial 
dependence models containing one or more endogenous explanatory variables 
(other than the spatially lagged dependent variable), single equation maximum 
likelihood and Bayesian estimators cannot. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>1. The superscript T denotes the transpose of a vector or matrix. 
2. Lee (2007) has found that a Manski type of model is not beyond the bounds of possibility, provided that one is 
willing to accept that the interaction effects among the error terms have a different spatial weights matrix than 
the interaction effects among the dependent variable and among the independent variables. Lee considers G 
groups, each consisting of N g cross-sectional units, and assumes that the elements of the spatial weights matrix 
measuring the endogenous and exogenous interaction effects are w ij 01/(N g Á 1) if units i and j belong to the 
same group (except if i0j ), and zero otherwise. To account for correlated errors among the members of each 
group, Lee considers group fixed effects. Mathematically, these group fixed effects can be represented by a 
spatial weights matrix whose elements are all equal to w ij 01/N g if units i and j belong to the same group, 
including the diagonal elements (i.e. if i0j ), and zero otherwise. Starting with these spatial weights matrices, 
Lee proves that the parameters are identified either if both N and N g tend to infinity, with at least two units in 
each group, or if the number of units in each group does not tend to infinity faster than or equal to the number 
of groups. </p>

<p>26 J. P. Elhorst </p>

<p> 
7. If the (robust) LM tests reject these extensions of the OLS model, it is still useful to estimate the spatial lag and 
the spatial error model. In case the spatial autoregressive coefficient r and/or the spatial autocorrelation 
coefficient l turns out to be significant, we may again conclude that the OLS model must be rejected in favour 
of the spatial lag, the spatial error model or in favour of both models, and continue estimating the spatial 
Durbin model. 
8. In order to obtain an asymmetric spatial weights matrix W, unit 1 is not assumed to be a neighbour of unit 3. If 
these units were also assumed to be neighbours, we would have a symmetric matrix which is not general 
enough. 
9. I abstract here from the problem that a cross-sectional model with an intercept, WY, X and WX variables 
cannot be estimated on the basis of N03 observations. 
10. This also holds if the spatial autoregressive parameter is negative. The first term that produces feedback effects 
is r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>W 
2 . This term will always be positive. The second term is r 
3 W 
3 . Since r is restricted to the interval 
(1/r min , 1) and the non-negative elements of W after row normalization are smaller than or equal to 1, 
the diagonal elements of r </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>W 
3 are smaller in absolute value than those of r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>W </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Since the series r 
2 W 
2 ' 
r 
3 W </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>'r 
4 W 
4 ' . . . alternates in sign if r is negative, the sum of the diagonal elements of the matrix 
represented by this series will always be positive. 
11. For example, the indirect effect of the kth variable in the spatial Durbin model of draw d that is used for 
illustration purposes in Table 1 would be equal to </p>

<p>m kd 0 </p>

<p>3r d 'r 2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>3(1(r 2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>(b k ) d ' </p>

<p>3'r d 
3(1(r 2 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>(u k ) d : </p>

<p>12. They also include spatial fixed effects. 
13. jtjB1 Á h if h]0 and jtjB1 Á hr min if hB0. </p>



<p>Applied Spatial Econometrics 27 </p>



<p>28 J. P. Elhorst </p>

</text></tei>