<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2F1475-4932.12059" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>New regulations to improve the quality of early childhood 
education and care came into force in Australia in 2012. Using a 
simultaneous, structural model of labour supply and child care 
demand we predict the effects on the labour supply of partnered 
women, on demand for child care and on household finances for two-
parent households in Australia. Using estimated cost impacts of this 
new National Quality Framework from government and non-govern-
ment sources, we find modest effects on household behaviour. For a 
mid-range cost scenario, we find that partnered women's labour force 
participation will decrease by just over one-half of one percentage 
point, a change of less than 1 per cent. Working hours for partnered 
women decrease by 20 minutes or approximately 2 per cent. 
Household disposable income decreases by $12.50, a 0.6 per cent 
decrease. Given widespread agreement about the benefits of investing 
in children, these quantitatively small effects for two-parent house-
holds strengthen the case for the National Quality Framework. </p>

<p>*In the course of our research on child care in Australia, the list of people to whom we are indebted has grown 
quite large. At the risk of omitting key people, we would like to thank I Introduction 
In December 2007, the Commonwealth Govern-
ment of Australia and state and territory govern-
ments, through the Council of Australian 
Governments (COAG), agreed to pursue reform 
in early childhood education and care (ECEC), see 
The Commonwealth of Australia (2007). A key 
component of the proposed reform agenda was a 
commitment to develop and implement improved 
quality standards for early childhood education 
and care in Australia. Subsequently, at their 
December 2009 meeting, COAG agreed to a new 
National Quality Framework (NQF) for ECEC. 
The aim of this article is to evaluate the cost 
and labour supply impacts on two-parent house-
holds of the NQF. Specifically, we examine 
partnered women's labour force participation, 
household child care demand, household budgets 
and government expenditure. Our article is the 
only attempt, as far as we are aware, to provide an 
estimate of the expected effects of these aspects 
of the reform in a way that accounts for household 
behavioural responses. As we indicate in the title, 
we examine some effects, not the total impact of 
the programme. We examine a price increase 
which is the same for all subgroups of the 
population; we do not examine how demand 
may respond to increased quality of child care 
nor do we examine how supply of child care may 
respond to the NQF. In Section V, we discuss 
these issues and their relationship to our results. 
Our estimates provide richer input into a discus-
sion of the costs and benefits of the NQF and one 
important piece for understanding the reform. 
The communique from the 2009 COAG meet-
ing 
1 states </p>

<p>Giving children the best possible start in life 
provides the foundation for better education in 
school and later in life, and delivers long-term 
social benefits. The National Quality Agenda 
for Early Childhood Education and Care will 
create new quality standards, including higher 
staff to children ratios and better trained carers 
and early childhood teachers with requirements 
phased in over the next decade. Through a new 
ratings system, parents will be given better 
information on the quality of child care ser-
vices so that they can make the best decisions 
for their children. Child care providers will 
benefit from streamlined regulatory arrange-
ments .... </p>

<p>There is widespread and growing agreement 
among both medical and social scientists about 
the important of early childhood development in a 
whole range of social, psychological, health and 
economic outcomes. (e.g. McCain et al., 2007; 
Heckman and Masterov, 2007; Irwin et al., 2007; 
Currie, 2009.) The consensus view from this 
literature is that investing in young children helps 
a society realise its full potential and minimise 
inequality. Some economic policies present us 
with a trade-off between growth and equality; 
investing in children appears to be a win-win 
situation. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Implementing the NQF will require hiring more 
staff per children, providing more educational 
training for those staff and improving physical 
space and safety standards. All of these imply 
increased costs which will flow through to some 
degree as higher prices for child care. Using a 
model of household behaviour that builds upon a 
standard labour economics approach (e.g. Kil-
lingsworth, 1983; Van Soest, 1995) and a detailed 
model of the Australian tax and transfer system, 
we address four questions relating to two-parent 
households. How will the increased costs 
(i) affect women's labour force participation? 
(ii) affect the amount of child care demanded by 
households? (iii) affect household budgets? 
(iv) affect government expenditure? We refer to 
'married' women to include both those in legal 
marriages and those in de facto relationships. We 
focus on married women, who represent the 
largest group with care responsibilities for young 
children at home. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>To preview the results, we find negative and 
statistically significant effects on women's labour 
supply and on household budgets across a range 
of cost scenarios. However, we find that these 
effects are relatively small. In the next section, 
we review the details of the NQF. We then 
discuss our approach to estimating the effect of 
child care costs on married women's decisions 
about how much to work and whether to work. In 
the fourth section, we present six different 
scenarios for child care fee changes and their </p>

<p>1 See The Commonwealth of Australia (2009a). </p>

<p>2 An accessible overview of this literature is pro-
vided in Appendix S1 of The Commonwealth of 
Australia (2009b). 
3 It would be inappropriate to apply the model we 
estimate for two-parent households to lone parents. 
Kalb (2002) and other research show that married 
women's and lone parents' labour supply are dissimilar 
and need to be modelled separately. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>effects on married women's labour supply. We 
conclude in the final section and discuss some of 
the caveats to our conclusions. </p>

<p>II The National Quality Framework 
The new NQF, part of the National Quality 
Agenda (NQA) for Early Childhood Education 
and Care, is an attempt by the Australian govern-
ment to address problems of varying quality 
across early childhood education and care ser-
vices, the existence of complex administrative and 
regulatory arrangements across different states 
and child care types, excess state and Common-
wealth bureaucracy, and the lack of information 
available to families about quality and availability 
of child care and education. 
4 The NQA proposes 
to address these issues by raising standards for 
early childhood education and care and harmon-
ising them across states and territories; publishing 
a quality rating system which families can use to 
assess their childhood care options; and introduc-
ing streamlined regulatory arrangements. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The main factor affecting child care costs 
arising from the NQF is the requirement for more 
and higher-educated staff. Specifically, the NQF 
proposes moving to a national standard for staff-
to-child ratios in pre-schools and long day care 
centres of: </p>

<p>1:4 staff-to-child ratio for 0-24 month olds 
effective from 1 January 2012 
1:5 staff-to-child ratio for 25-35 month olds 
effective from 1 January 2016 
1:11 staff-to-child ratio for children older than 
35 months from 1 January 2016 </p>

<p>These changes do not affect all states equally. 
Victoria already requires a staff-to-child ratio of </p>

<p>1:4 for 25-35 month olds. New South Wales, 
Western Australia and Tasmania require a 1:10 
staff-to-child ratio for children older than 
35 months. In both cases, these stricter require-
ments are not superseded by the new standards. 
The NQF will also raise required minimum 
educational qualifications of staff working in the 
early childhood education and care sector. For 
family day care (FDC), long day care (LDC) and 
pre-schools, by 1 January 2014: </p>

<p>A degree-qualified early childhood teacher will 
need to be in attendance all of the time when 
LDC and pre-school services are being pro-
vided to 25 children or more, and some of the 
time when services are being provided to fewer 
than 25 children. 
Within each LDC centre or pre-school, half of 
all staff will need to have (or be actively 
working towards) a diploma-level ECEC qual-
ification or above, and the remaining staff will 
all be required to have (or be actively working 
towards) a Certificate III level qualification, or 
equivalent. 
All FDC coordinators will need to have a 
diploma-level qualification or above. 
All FDC carers will be required to have (or be 
actively working towards) a Certificate III level 
qualification, or equivalent. </p>

<p>Also, by 2020, the NQF requires a second early 
childhood teacher, or another suitably qualified 
leader, to be in attendance all of the time when 
LDC and pre-school services are being provided 
to more than 80 children, and at least half of the 
time when services are being provided to between 
60 and 80 children. 
The main costs of the NQF will relate to hiring 
more and better trained staff. Access Economics 
(2009) states that 'labour costs represent[ing] up 
to 70 per cent of services' total operating costs...' 
(p. 51). We spoke with several long day centres in 
Canberra including the largest one, and staffing 
costs make up 60-90 per cent of their current 
operating costs. 
We next discuss the model we use to estimate 
how increased costs of child care associated with 
the NQF will impact on partnered women's 
labour supply. </p>

<p>III Married Women's Labour Supply and Child 
Care Demand: Modelling, Estimation and Data 
The estimates of the effects of cost increases on 
married women's labour supply and demand for 
child care in this article are based on simulations </p>

<p>4 The NQF is described in the Commonwealth of 
Australia (2009b), the Commonwealth of Australia 
(2009e) and the Commonwealth of Australia (2009a) 
and summarised in a four-page factsheet in the Com-
monwealth of Australia (2009d) and in a short infor-
mation sheet in the Commonwealth of Australia (2011). 
The National Partnership Agreement on the National 
Quality Agenda for Early Childhood Education and 
Care is available in the Commonwealth of Australia 
(2009c). Our discussion is drawn from these sources as 
well as from Access Economics (2009). 
5 Access Economics (2009) discusses in some detail 
the kind of benefits that one might expect from 
improved childhood outcomes, a streamlined regulatory 
system and a quality rating system. We refer the 
interested reader to that report and Appendix S1 of 
The Commonwealth of Australia (2009b). </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p>2014 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>



<p>from a joint, discrete structural labour supply and 
child care demand model which we develop and 
estimate in Gong and Breunig (2012). In this 
section, we discuss the main features of that 
model and highlight the innovations which we 
have made relative to previous research. 
6 We then 
briefly indicate how the model is estimated and 
describe the data that we use. </p>

<p>(i) The Economic Model 
We highlight seven key aspects of the eco-
nomic model and approach we have developed to 
analyse this question. First, we simultaneously 
model demand for child care and married 
women's decisions about whether to work and 
how much to work. This is important because it 
allows child care to be used for other purposes 
besides freeing up time for mothers to work. 
Second, we assume that married women choose 
working hours and hours of child care for their 
children from those points which are commonly 
observed in the data. This makes the model more 
realistic. Women cannot choose to work any 
amount of hours they want, but must choose from 
those offered by employers -35 and 20 h, etc., 
which are commonly observed in the data. Like-
wise, when children are enrolled in a child care 
centre, hours choices are generally restricted and 
households must choose a full week, full days, 
half-days, etc. Hours cannot be adjusted in 
arbitrarily small amounts but must respect the 
real-life constraints of the labour market and slots 
typically offered by child care providers. A third 
important feature of our model is that it includes 
constraints which require that children be cared 
for at all times by someone other than the mother 
while the mother is working. Although this may 
seem obvious, much of the previous empirical 
literature in this area does not formally integrate 
such constraints into model estimation. Such 
constraints are important to avoid bias in the 
estimated effects of child care prices. (See 
Duncan et al., 2001). A fourth feature is that the 
model allows hours worked by the mother to 
exceed hours of formal child care, with the </p>

<p>difference being made up by informal and/or 
paternal care. Again, this is intuitively appealing 
but the only previous papers that have imposed 
hours constraints have required that formal hours 
of child care are greater than or equal to hours 
worked by the mother. In the data, we observe 
that this type of restriction is violated in almost 
one-third of households. 
A fifth important aspect of our approach is that 
we use data that is more detailed than that which 
has previously been available to construct local 
child care prices for each Labour Force Survey 
Region. 
7 This is important because it allows us to 
identify a price of child care that represents the 
approximate average price that women must pay 
to send their children to child care to work. This 
price removes, to at least some degree, the 
variation in price which we observe across 
families that is driven by different choices of 
child care quality. 
A sixth feature is that we model and include 
effects of the personal tax system and major 
transfer payments including Newstart Allowance, 
Parenting Payment Partnered, Family Tax Bene-
fits, Child Care Rebate, Child Care Benefit and 
the Low Income Tax Offset. Finally, the combi-
nation of directly estimating the utility function 
and incorporating the non-linearity of the tax and 
transfer system allows us to estimate net price 
elasticities. Net price elasticities are essential to 
evaluate policy changes because they reflect 
families' responses to changes in the actual out-
of-pocket costs which they must pay for child 
care. Any policy which changes out-of-pocket 
costs can be evaluated using these net price 
elasticities even if that policy involves changing 
key programmes such as Child Care Benefit or 
Child Care Rebate. 
Early research on child care abstracted from the 
non-linearity of the tax and transfer system by 
specifying a linear labour supply model, for 
example Connelly (1992), or estimated a reduced 
form model (e.g. Ribar, 1995; Blau &amp; Hagy, 
1998). Previous research on Australia by Ram-
mohan and Whelan (2005, 2007) follows this 
approach. Kalb (2009) and Breunig et al. (2012) 
both provide lengthier reviews of the literature on 
labour supply and child care. </p>

<p>6 The research which we summarise in this section 
has been the product of multiple collaborations over 
several years. The original work which provides the 
background to this section appears in working paper 
and journal format in Gong et al. (2010b), Gong et al. 
(2010a), Breunig et al. (2011), Gong et al. (2011) and 
Gong and Breunig (2011). We refer interested readers 
to these papers for the technical details. </p>

<p>7 Labour Force Survey (LFS) Regions are described 
in Australian Bureau of Statistics (2004). There are 77 
LFS regions at the time of our data with size ranging 
from less than 100,000 to over 1,000,000 individuals in 
each LFS region. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>Our approach of specifying and directly esti-
mating the utility function has also been used by 
Blau and Robins (1988), Ribar (1992, 1995), Blau 
and Hagy (1998), Duncan et al. (2001) and 
Kornstad and Thoresen (2006, 2007). These last 
three papers incorporate hours restrictions that 
require formal hours of child care to be greater 
than hours worked by the mother. As we indicate, 
this is violated in approximately one-third of the 
cases in our data. Our improved hours restric-
tions, which require that children be cared for at 
all times but which also allow informal or 
paternal care to make up for the difference 
between hours worked by the mother and hours 
of formal care is an important methodological 
innovation in the international literature. 
Before applying the model to understand the 
likely effects of increased child care costs, we 
elaborate on several key aspects. The main diffi-
culty which arises in modelling the effect of 
changing costs of child care on married women's 
labour supply is attempting to separate out the two 
reasons for which people use child care: (i) to free 
up time to work; and (ii) as an input to child 
development. If child care were only a cost of 
working the problem would be quite simple and 
child care costs could simply be added to the 
standard labour supply model as an additional cost. 
This is clearly not the case. We observe that 
families do not simply choose the least expensive 
option for child care (which they would do if they 
were just minimising cost with no regard for the 
intellectual, social and psychological develop-
ment of their children) but rather they attempt to 
balance cost with quality, proximity and other 
factors. Furthermore, child care is not used exclu-
sively for freeing up time to work. A quick look at 
the data reveals a rich array of patterns. Some 
women who do no paid work nonetheless put their 
children in child care. Some women who engage in 
paid work use no paid child care. Most use some 
mix, and there is not necessarily a direct match 
between hours worked and hours in child care. 
To estimate the effect of changing costs of 
child care on married women's labour supply, we 
need to model both working decisions of women 
and family child care decisions, allowing them to 
be related to one another but allowing child care 
to serve multiple purposes. Our model provides 
this realistic framework, as described in detail 
above. 
Related to this difficulty of modelling the 
multiple reasons for which people use child care 
is understanding the price of child care that </p>

<p>families face when deciding whether or not to 
work. The price that we observe an individual 
family pay for child care can be thought of as 
having two components -a component which 
represents the minimal cost of obtaining child 
care and a discretionary component that repre-
sents the price for additional attributes such as 
quality or proximity. Consider two families which 
live next door to each other but which pay 
different amounts for child care even though they 
have children of the same age using the same 
amount of child care. We cannot reasonably think 
of them as purchasing their child care in different 
markets. Rather, the price difference represents a 
differential bundle of attributes and may reflect a 
differential valuation of such attributes. 
Therefore, it would be incorrect to take the 
price that a family pays as the cost of working 
component of child care, because we will be 
confounding the family's preferences about child 
care quality and proximity with the costs that a 
family must pay for child care if the mother 
decides to work. This is important because when 
we evaluate how changing costs of child care 
might affect married women's decisions to work, 
we do not want to impose the preferences of one 
family on another. To evaluate cost changes, we 
also need to estimate the price which families 
who do not use child care would pay if they 
decided to use child care. 
To address these problems, we construct local 
area average prices. Technically, this is a crucial 
issue. Previous research in Australia using house-
hold-level price data (see Rammohan &amp; Whelan 
2005, 2007) found no impact of child care price 
on married women's labour supply decisions. 
Similarly, in their report, Access Economics 
(2009) states, 'The findings of research commis-
sioned by the ECDSC (Access Economics) sug-
gest the cost, quality and availability of child care 
have no statistically significant impact on par-
ents' labour supply decisions.' In Breunig et al. 
(2012), we show that this finding of no significant 
impact appears to be driven by measurement error 
in the child care price. When we use local area 
average prices, we find a statistically significant 
(and negative) effect of the price of child care on 
partnered women's labour supply using child-
level data that was not available to Rammohan 
and Whelan. </p>

<p>(ii) Econometric Specification 
Parameter estimates and the full model speci-
fication can be found in Gong and Breunig </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p> 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>(2012). The household is assumed to maximise 
utility by choosing mother's working hours h and 
formal child care hours c f of her young children 
(the average hours if more than one child) from a 
set of discrete options: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>h;cf </p>

<p>UðvÞ ¼ v 
0 Av þ b 
0 v; v ðlogy; logl m ; logc m Þ </p>

<p>ð1Þ </p>

<p>s:t: y sðy 0 þ wh; XÞ À N k wðp f c f ; y 0 þ wh; XÞ 
À N s wðp s c s ; y 0 þ wh; XÞ </p>

<p>ð2Þ </p>

<p>y is general consumption net of child care costs, 
which is determined through the budget con-
straint (2) by asset income and father's income 
(both captured in y 0 ), the mother's wage (w) and 
working hours, and the tax/welfare system which 
is captured by the function s and which depends 
on household characteristics which determine tax 
payments and benefit receipt, X. 
8 c s is formal child 
care hours of her school-aged children, which is 
assumed to be fixed. N k and N s are the number of 
pre-school and school-aged children and p f and p s 
are prices of formal child care for pre-school and 
school-aged children respectively. The function w 
captures child care subsidies which depend on 
child care costs (price multiplied by usage) and 
household characteristics. 
The parameters of the utility function are 
summarised in A, a symmetric 3 9 3 parameter 
matrix with entries A ij , and a vector 
b ¼ ðb 1 ; b 2 ; b 3 Þ 
0 . b 1 is a constant, but b 2 and b 3 
are specified to allow both observed and unob-
served individual and household characteristics to 
affect utility: </p>

<p>b k ¼ </p>

<p>X Tk </p>

<p>t¼1 </p>

<p>b kt x </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t þ 
pk ; ðk ¼ 2; 3Þ; 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>where x 
k ¼ ðx </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>1 ; . . .; x </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>Tk Þ 
0 are vectors of exogenous 
characteristics including age, immigrant status 
and indigenous status of the mother, a dummy if 
the mother is educated overseas, number of 
children in age groups 0-4, 5-12 and 13-15, 
average age of pre-school children, age of youn-
gest child, a dummy if there are older children </p>

<p>present in the household, a dummy if there are 
other female adults in the household, dummy 
variables which capture the father's educational 
attainment, father's immigrant status and educa-
tion background (domestic or overseas) and state-
level controls for the percentage of child care 
staff with teaching experience and with formal 
child care qualifications. Immigrant status and the 
presence of extra female adults are used as 
proxies for the presence of other potential care-
takers at home (or nearby) which may capture 
differences in costs and benefits of informal care. 
We control for child care quality by adding state-
level variables from administrative data which 
capture the average number of qualified staff per 
child in formal day care centres. The terms </p>

<p>pk </p>

<p>may be interpreted as random preferences due to 
unobserved characteristics. 
The choice set for working hours and formal 
child care hours can be described by the follow-
ing: </p>

<p>h 2 0; s; 2s; . . .; ðm À 1Þs; 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>c f 2 0; r; 2r; . . .; ðg À 1Þr; 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>We create 48 combinations of working hours/ 
child care sessions formed by setting s = m = 8 
and r = 10 to reflect the typical length of child 
care sessions in this age group. We set g = 6. 
These settings allow a wide range of part-time 
and half-day possibilities for both work and 
formal care. 
To the utility of each alternative in the choice 
set, we add random disturbances l j which are 
independently and identically distributed with a 
type I extreme value distribution, and are inde-
pendent of all X and the other unobservable terms 
in the model. This creates a multinomial logit 
type setup where the mother chooses alternative j 
if U j is the largest among all the alternatives. 
To predict wage rates for non-workers and 
workers whose wages are missing in the data and 
to allow for correlation between wage rates and 
unobserved utility preferences ( 
pk ), a standard 
wage equation is simultaneously estimated with 
(1) and specified as: </p>

<p>log w ¼ p 
0 z þ 
w ; 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where z is a vector of the mother's characteristics 
including educational attainment, a dummy equal </p>

<p>8 In s, we include Newstart Allowance, Parenting 
Payment Partnered, Family Tax Benefits A and B, 
together with income tax, Medicare Levy, Pharmaceu-
tical Payment and Low Income Tax Rebate (LITO). </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>to one if the mother obtained her education 
overseas, potential experience, immigrant and 
indigenous status. We also include a variable 
equal to one if the mother lived with both of her 
parents when she was 14 and current area of 
residence measured by capital city and state 
variables which are omitted from the utility 
function and serve the role of exclusion restric-
tions. p is a vector of parameters to be estimated. </p>

<p>w is an unobserved term, assumed to be normally 
distributed with mean zero, independent of z, but 
is allowed to be correlated with 
pk . 
The three error terms 
w , 
p2 and 
p3 are 
specified to follow a joint normal distribution of 
which the parameters are to be estimated: </p>



<p>w </p>



<p>p2 </p>



<p>p3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A $ Nð0; RÞ; where R ¼ </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 
w </p>

<p>r wp2 r </p>

<p>2 
p2 </p>

<p>r wp3 0 r </p>

<p>2 
p3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>ð7Þ </p>

<p>The numerical multidimensional integral is 
approximated by a simulated mean: for each 
individual, we take R draws from the joint 
distribution of 
w , 
p2 and 
p3 and compute the 
average of the R likelihood values conditional on 
these draws. </p>

<p>(iii) Data 
We use Household Income and Labour 
Dynamics in Australia (HILDA) data, described 
in Wooden and Watson (2007). We take advan-
tage of data which has only been available since 
wave five (2005) in which households were 
asked about child care expenditure for specific 
types of care and for specific age ranges of 
children. Further, we use the in-confidence </p>

<p>version of the data which allows us to match 
households to the Australian Bureau of Statistics 
Labour Force Survey Region to construct our 
key variable, local area child care price. By 
averaging across households in each Labour 
Force Region, we eliminate the effect of the 
family's decision about how much quality to 
purchase. Our modelling assumption is that 
households react to the average (median) price 
level irrespective of the quality they choose. 
This is akin to assuming that shifts in median 
prices affect all quality levels. We eliminate 
measurement error by using actual hours spent in 
child care to construct prices rather than hours 
worked by the mother as some studies have 
done. Our model is estimated pooling waves five 
through seven of HILDA. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>HILDA provides a very rich set of variables 
that we can use to model child care demand and 
married women's labour supply. A final consid-
eration which favours using post-2005 data is that 
the Australian Bureau of Statistics (2010) created 
a gross child care price index from 2005, which 
we use to make the price comparable across 
waves and to project prices for future years. </p>

<p>(iv) Estimates 
Table 2 of Gong and Breunig (2012) provides 
the parameter estimates of Equations (3) and (6). 
Table 1 presents the main elasticities of interest 
from the model using probability weighted sums 
of hours over each possible choice. Standard 
errors are from 100 Monte Carlo repetitions. One 
caveat is that we do not account for the clustering 
in the data which result from pooling over </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Elasticities (Average Over Whole Sample) </p>

<p>With respect to: </p>

<p>Labour supply 
Child care demand </p>

<p>Hours 
employment 
Hours 
Use of formal care </p>

<p>Gross child care price 
À0.135(0.04) 
À0.085(0.02) 
À0.287(0.05) 
À0.169(0.03) 
Net child care price 
À0.099(0.03) 
À0.063(0.01) 
À0.217(0.05) 
À0.129(0.02) 
Wage 
0.475(0.11) 
0.299(0.06) 
0.329(0.07) 
0.213(0.04) 
Income 
À0.126(0.05) 
À0.090(0.04) 
À0.128(0.05) 
À0.100(0.04) </p>

<p>Note: Standard errors in parentheses. 
All estimates are significant at 5% level or smaller. 
Table taken from Gong and Breunig (2012). </p>

<p>9 Sample descriptive statistics can be found in 
Table 1 of Gong and Breunig (2012). </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p>2014 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>



<p>three years of panel data. Some individuals 
appear more than once in the data and this will 
cause our standard errors, which treat the data as 
a random sample, to be understated. To account 
for clustering, we would need to draw from an 
array of multidimensional matrices like Equation 
(7) rather than a single matrix. This additional 
computational complexity makes estimation 
infeasible. We think that the effect of this is 
small for two reasons: the average number of 
appearances in the data per individual is close to 
one and a half, so the degree of clustering is fairly 
small; secondly, in previous work (see Breunig 
et al., 2012), where we similarly pool across 
three waves of data but estimate a linear labour 
supply model where it is possible to correct for 
clustering, we find that the correction for clus-
tering changes the standard errors by very little. 
Our estimates fall within the range of many 
recent studies. The literature over the last </p>

<p>15 years shows that female labour supply and 
child care demand respond negatively to child 
care prices, but the range of estimated elasticities 
is quite wide. Labour supply elasticities are 
estimated to be between 0 and À1.26 (see Blau, 
2003 or Breunig et al., 2012). Estimates of own 
price elasticities for child care vary equally 
widely, ranging from À0.07 in v to À1.0 or more 
in, for example, Connelly and Kimmel (2003), 
Powell (2002) and Cleveland et al. (1996). 
10 Blau 
(2003) notes that the variation in estimates is 
likely a result of differences in specification and 
estimation. The complexity of the underlying 
economic problem and inadequate data both 
contribute to the specification and estimation 
issues. Appendix S1 in Gong et al. (2010a) </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
'Total Impact' 
y of National Quality Framework Table Reports Average Weekly Changes per Household </p>

<p>Price increase per child per day 
Baseline 
Scenario 1 $4.02 Scenario 2 $13.00 Scenario 3 $25.00 </p>

<p>Married women's labour supply effects 
Change in hours worked 
15.534 
À0.087 
À0.294 
À0.584 
(0.022) 
(0.074) 
(0.145) 
Change (%) in participation 
61.1% 
À0.162% 
À0.573% 
À1.192% 
(0.038) 
(0.132) 
(0.265) 
Child care demand effects 
Change in hours of formal care 
9.552 
À0.121 
À0.410 
À0.816 
(0.035) 
(0.111) 
(0.206) 
Change (%) in participation in 
formal care </p>

<p>50.4% 
À0.214% 
À0.760% 
À1.600% 
(0.041) 
(0.139) 
(0.275) 
Change in gross costs ($) of formal 
child care </p>

<p>95.384 
4.658 
14.212 
25.322 
(0.811) 
(2.624) 
(5.013) 
Change in net costs ($) of formal 
child care </p>

<p>12.784 
2.169 
7.252 
14.142 
(0.807) 
(2.588) 
(4.854) 
Change in hours of informal care 
6.032 
0.034 
0.113 
0.224 
(0.041) 
(0.132) 
(0.252) 
Income and program effects 
Change in disposable income ($) (less 
child care costs) </p>

<p>$1,888.594 
À1.576 
À5.290 
À10.422 
(0.403) 
(1.329) 
(2.566) 
Change in disposable income ($) 
(including child care costs) </p>

<p>$1,901.378 
À3.745 
À12.542 
À24.564 
(0.509) 
(1.614) 
(3.029) 
Change in child care subsidy ($) 
received </p>

<p>82.601 
2.489 
6.960 
11.180 
(0.297) 
(0.920) 
(1.620) 
Change in government expenditure ($) 
(net of child care subsidies) </p>

<p>408.337 
3.632 
10.821 
18.801 
(0.460) 
(1.494) 
(2.797) </p>

<p>Note: Numbers in parentheses are standard errors. 
All estimated effects are statistically significant at 5 per cent level except for informal care hours. Net government expenditure is 
income support, family tax benefit and child care subsidies (Child Care Benefit and Child Care Rebate) less tax revenue. 
y The effect in 2012 of 'total impact' costs of the NQF (see Section IV.(i)). </p>

<p>10 See Baker et al. (2008) and Kalb (2009) for 
additional references and discussion. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>provides a table summarising the approach and 
results of 20 international and Australian studies 
on child care and labour supply. </p>

<p>IV Results 
In this section, we first present the various 
price change scenarios that we consider. We 
then look at four types of effects: the effect on 
married women's labour supply, the effect on 
child care demand and expenditure, the effect on 
household disposable income and the effect on 
government balances including child care sub-
sidy costs and the net effect on government 
expenditure. 
It is important to first note that the Australian 
government assumes, in its modelling of the 
NQF, that labour supply is unaffected by the child 
care price. The Regulation Impact Statement for 
Early Childhood Education and Care Quality 
Reforms (The Commonwealth of Australia 
(2009e)) notes, '...there is no reliable evidence 
to suggest that incremental increases in the 
quality of ECEC results in significant behavioural 
responses of parents (when both quality and the 
countervailing impacts of price are considered), 
including workforce participation'. They quote 
Access Economics (2009), who state that '...it is 
assumed that the NQA will have no statistically 
significant impact on the workforce participation 
of parents, and therefore no impacts have been 
modelled in this regard'. These propositions are 
relying on the previous Australian literature, 
notably Doiron and Kalb (2005), Rammohan 
and Whelan (2005) and Rammohan and Whelan 
(2007), which find no statistically significant 
effect of child care price on married women's 
labour supply. As we discuss above, our solution 
to the mis-measurement of child care price using 
newly available data and our improved modelling 
and estimation strategy explain why we find 
significant effects. 
To summarise our results before passing to the 
details, we find modest but statistically significant 
effects. If we assume an increase of $13 per child 
per day in the costs and gross price of child care 
(a 17 per cent increase in gross costs), we find that 
married women's labour force participation 
decreases by just over one-half of one percentage 
point. Without the change, married women's 
labour force participation is 61.1 per cent. We 
find that hours worked decreases by 20 min per 
week (on a base of 15.5 h per week) on average 
across the population of married women. In 
interpreting these numbers it is important to </p>

<p>remember that many households will not change 
at all while some households may have changes 
much larger than the average. 
Demand for formal child care goes down as the 
price goes up. For a price increase of $13 per 
child per day, we find a decrease in formal child 
care demand of 25 min per week (on a base of 
9.6 h per week) and a decrease in formal child 
care usage of three-quarters of one percentage 
point. Without the change, 50.4 per cent of 
households use child care. Average household 
disposable income decreases by $12.50 per week 
and net government expenditure increases by 
$10.82 per week (this includes reduced tax 
revenue as well as the effect of subsidies on 
child care being paid out against higher gross 
prices). Household disposable income without the 
change is $1,888.59, therefore this represents a 
0.6 per cent decrease in average household 
disposable income. </p>

<p>(i) Price Change Scenarios 
We consider three scenarios for the effect on 
child care prices of the NQF. For each scenario, 
we consider two possibilities which we refer to as 
total impact and initial impact. The total impact 
calculation is as an estimate of the full impact of 
the NQF if it were fully implemented in 2012. We 
also consider an initial impact as roll-out of some 
of the NQF reforms is scheduled for post-2012, 
and there is a possibility that even the 2012 
reforms may take time to be implemented fully. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>The initial impact is calculated as being just over 
one-half of the total impact. We take this from the 
estimates of Access Economics (2009). Together 
they provide six different cost scenarios. 
The three 'total impact' scenarios are as 
follows: </p>

<p>1 Gross child care price increases by $4.02 per 
day. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>This corresponds to cost scenarios two and 
three in Access Economics (2009) and is also 
quoted in The Commonwealth of Australia 
(2009e). 
2 Gross child care price increases by $13 per day. 
Based on 'average' expected cost increase, see </p>

<p>11 Access Economics (2009) assumes that the NQF 
reforms will only be gradually implemented due to lack 
of qualified staff. 
12 Costs from Access Economics (2009) are in 
2009 dollars -we translate these to 2012 dollars as 
described below. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p> 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>



<p>Australian Childcare Alliance (2011), Simon 
(2011) and Laura (2011). </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>3 Gross child care price increases by $25 per day. 
An upper bound for maximum daily price 
increases from Australian Childcare Alliance 
(2011) and quoted by Benson (2011) and 
Brodnik (2011). </p>

<p>The three 'initial impact' scenarios are scaled 
versions of scenarios 1 through 3 which consider 
gross child care price increases of $2.13 per day 
(this corresponds to scenario three in Access 
Economics, 2009), $6.89 per day and $13.25 per 
day. 
Scenarios one and three represent lower and 
upper bounds that we have found in our survey of 
available sources. Scenario three appears to be a 
worst-case scenario, as Australian Childcare 
Alliance (2011) states, '25 per cent of centre 
providers say their parents will be hit by cost 
increases of $25 per child per day.' Importantly, 
these price changes are changes in addition to the 
normal trend of child care prices. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Our model estimates are, as discussed above, 
net of current policy settings, so they are appro-
priate for estimating the impact of a policy 
change. The assumptions we make to generate 
predictions are as follows: </p>

<p>As the baseline price, we use the child care 
price that we estimate from the HILDA data. 
We inflate this child care price in our sample to 
2012 using the average annual growth rate 
calculated with the gross child care price 
index. 
15 For 2011 and 2012, we use the average 
inflation rate over the past five years. </p>

<p>We assume that real wage and non-labour 
income grow at an annual rate of 2 per cent 
and then inflate to 2012 dollars. 
We assume that the per day cost is applied to a 
base of 10 h per day. The full-day rate at many 
child care centres covers a 10-h slot. </p>

<p>In section 4.5, we discuss how altering these 
assumptions may affect our results. </p>

<p>(ii) Labour Supply Effects 
Labour supply effects are modest, but statisti-
cally significant at the five per cent level or 
smaller. If the NQF were completely adopted in 
2012, we find that married women's labour force 
participation would decrease somewhere between 
0.16 and 1.2 percentage points depending on the 
size of the price increase. Average hours worked 
would decrease by between five and 35 min per 
week. If we consider the scenario of only partial 
compliance with the NQF in 2012, we find effects 
about half that size. Tables 2 and 3 present the 
total and initial impacts respectively. The second 
column of Table 2 provides the baseline levels of 
variables in the data from which the changes are 
calculated. 
In Table 4, we consider the effects for the 
initial impact of the intermediate price scenario 
(an increase of $6.89 per day per child) by 
population subgroup. Columns 2 and 3 of Table 4 
compare the effects for households with multiple 
children to those with only one child. Unsurpris-
ingly, the effects are nearly double for those 
households with multiple children compared to 
those with only one child. Participation of mar-
ried women decreases 0.4 percentage points in 
response to the price increase in multiple-child 
households, whereas in those households with 
only one child, participation decreases by 0.23 
percentage points. 
Columns 4 and 5 of Table 4 compare the effects 
for high-and low-wage women (defined relative 
to median wages). Interestingly, we find slightly 
larger effects on households with high-wage 
women compared to low-wage women. This 
could be because higher-wage women work more 
to begin with and are using more child care, so the 
impact on them is greater. Because of means-
testing of child care benefit, the net price impact 
on higher-wage women (who live in wealthier 
households) is also larger. We also split the 
sample by education levels of women, education 
levels of men and level of unearned income in the 
household. The relative impacts across these </p>

<p>13 Laura (2011) names the Productivity Commission, 
but this appears to be a mis-citation. Simon (2011) 
reports similar information but only quotes 'an industry 
report'. The industry report would appear to be from 
Australian Childcare Alliance (2011), who also quote 
Productivity Commission (2011). The Productivity 
Commission report mentions the possibility of 
increased costs from the NQF, but from our reading 
appears to contain no quantitative estimates. 
14 In our modelling, the average price per hour paid 
in the sample from HILDA is inflated using the child 
care price index as described below to give an average 
projected child care price in 2012 of $7.59 per hour or 
$75.90 for a full day. Our sample average price 
corresponds roughly with prices from the child care 
census if we compare years where both are available. 
The results in this section are insensitive to a reason-
able range of base prices. 
15 See Australian Bureau of Statistics (2010) </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>subgroups is very similar to columns 4 and 5 of 
Table 4. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Households with higher-educated hus-
bands, higher-educated wives, and which are 
wealthier are all affected more than their coun-
terparts. In this respect, the increases in costs 
which we model appear to be slightly more 
favourable to the less well-off. 
17 This relies upon 
a homogeneous price increase. If prices increase 
more for those who are less well-off, this 
conclusion would change as we discuss in Section 
V below. </p>

<p>(iii) Effects on Child Care Demand 
The second panel of Tables 2 through 4 
presents the effect on demand and expenditure 
for child care. We find that formal care decreases 
by between seven and 45 min per week on 
average across the scenarios with the 'initial 
2012 impact' half of these amounts. Again, we 
find a larger effect in wealthier and better-
educated households. 
Net, out-of-pocket costs on child care can be 
expected to increase between $2.17 and $14.14 
per week per household. Again, the 'initial 2012 
impact' is approximately half of these amounts. 
Informal care increases, as expected. As formal 
child care becomes more expensive, informal care 
becomes a more attractive alternative. However, 
our estimates for the change in informal care are 
not statistically different from zero. In our 
estimates, these are the only quantities that are 
not statistically different from zero at the five per 
cent level. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
'Initial Impact' 
y of National Quality Framework Table Reports Average Weekly Changes per Household </p>

<p>Price increase per child per day </p>

<p>Scenario 4 
$2.13 </p>

<p>Scenario 5 
$6.89 </p>

<p>Scenario 6 
$13.25 </p>

<p>Married women's labour supply effects 
Change in hours worked 
À0.045 
À0.151 
À0.300 
(0.012) 
(0.039) 
(0.076) 
Change (%) in participation 
À0.084% 
À0.287% 
À0.585% 
(0.020) 
(0.067) 
(0.134) 
Child care demand effects 
Change in hours of formal care 
À0.063 
À0.211 
À0.419 
(0.019) 
(0.060) 
(0.113) 
Change (%) in participation in formal care 
À0.111% 
À0.380% 
À0.776% 
(0.022) 
(0.072) 
(0.141) 
Change in gross costs ($) of formal child care 
2.499 
7.837 
14.462 
(0.429) 
(1.391) 
(2.675) 
Change in net costs ($) of formal child care 
1.135 
3.772 
7.397 
(0.427) 
(1.382) 
(2.636) 
Change in hours of informal care 
0.018 
0.058 
0.115 
(0.022) 
(0.070) 
(0.135) 
Income and program effects 
Change in disposable income ($) 
(less child care costs) </p>

<p>À0.825 
À2.741 
À5.396 
(0.212) 
(0.697) 
(1.355) 
Change in disposable income ($) 
(including child care costs) </p>

<p>À1.960 
À6.513 
À12.792 
(0.271) 
(0.868) 
(1.644) 
Change in child care subsidy ($) received 
1.364 
4.065 
7.066 
(0.158) 
(0.505) 
(0.936) 
Change in government expenditure ($) 
(net of child care subsidies) </p>

<p>1.962 
6.060 
11.004 
(0.243) 
(0.794) 
(1.522) </p>

<p>Note: See footnotes to Table 2. </p>

<p>16 A table of these results is available upon request 
from the authors. 
17 This is true in both absolute and percentage terms-
households with women below median wages have 
À$4.51 change in disposable income, whereas those 
above median wage are À$8.52. These correspond to 
decreases of 0.28 per cent and 0.39 per cent respec-
tively. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p> 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>



<p>(iv) Effects on Income and Expenditure of 
Households and Government 
We find that household disposable income 
decreases between $3.75 and $25.56 per week 
under the total cost change scenarios. These 
results are in the third panel of Tables 2 and 3. 
The effect is larger in wealthier and better-
educated households (Table 4). In the Tables, 
we provide these figures including and excluding 
child care costs to show which part of this 
decrease in disposable income is generated by 
labour force behaviour and which part is gener-
ated by higher child care prices. 
If the government were to compensate house-
holds for this lost income, one possibility would 
be to increase Child Care Benefit (CCB) and 
Child Care Rebate (CCR). Gong and Breunig 
(2012) show that increasing CCB is more bene-
ficial for low-income households while increasing 
CCR is more beneficial to higher-income house-
holds. </p>

<p>The NQF will affect both the revenue and 
expenditure sides of the government balance 
sheet. As married women work less, tax revenue 
will decrease. As gross child care price increases, 
CCB and CCR payments will increase. We find 
that the overall effect is an increase in net 
government expenditure (benefits less tax) of 
between $3.63 and $18.80 per household per 
week. </p>

<p>(v) Caveats 
There are several important caveats to our 
results. Perhaps, the biggest caveat is that our 
analysis is partial equilibrium; we assume the 
macroeconomic environment remains the same. 
The effects of the NQF are small relative to, for 
example, the resources boom or the effect of 
global financial shocks. We take the cost esti-
mates as given as we have no way of generating 
our own estimates. As most labour supply liter-
ature does, we ignore the demand side of the </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
'Initial Impact' 
y of National Quality Framework Response to Price Increase of $6.89 per Day by Population Sub-
group Table Reports Average Weekly Changes per Household </p>

<p>Population sub-group </p>

<p>Households 
with multiple 
children </p>

<p>Households 
with one child </p>

<p>Women with 
above median 
wages </p>

<p>Women with 
below median 
wages </p>

<p>Married women's labour supply effects 
Change in hours worked 
À0.182 
À0.135 
À0.166 
À0.137 
(0.049) 
(0.035) 
(0.043) 
(0.035) 
Change (%) in participation 
À0.402% 
À0.226% 
À0.309% 
À0.265% 
(0.097) 
(0.053) 
(0.071) 
(0.064) 
Child care demand effects 
Change in hours of formal care 
À0.240 
À0.196 
À0.241 
À0.181 
(0.091) 
(0.047) 
(0.059) 
(0.064) 
Change (%) in participation in formal care 
À0.440% 
À0.348% 
À0.441% 
À0.319% 
(0.102) 
(0.060) 
(0.081) 
(0.066) 
Change in gross costs ($) of formal child care 
10.226 
6.563 
8.879 
6.797 
(2.177) 
(1.050) 
(1.447) 
(1.375) 
Change in net costs ($) of formal child care 
4.095 
3.599 
4.907 
2.638 
(2.112) 
(1.045) 
(1.407) 
(1.397) 
Change in hours of informal care 
0.055 
0.054 
0.074 
0.042 
(0.103) 
(0.060) 
(0.067) 
(0.074) 
Income and program effects 
Change in disposable income ($) 
(less child care costs) </p>

<p>À3.462 
À2.357 
À3.617 
À1.867 
(0.910) 
(0.597) 
(0.934) 
(0.466) 
Change in disposable income ($) 
(including child care costs) </p>

<p>À7.558 
À5.956 
À8.524 
À4.506 
(1.464) 
(0.659) 
(0.782) 
(1.059) 
Change in child care subsidy ($) received 
6.130 
2.964 
3.971 
4.159 
(0.968) 
(0.284) 
(0.455) 
(0.564) 
Change in government expenditure ($) 
(net of child care subsidies) </p>

<p>8.864 
4.565 
6.574 
5.546 
(1.313) 
(0.544) 
(0.874) 
(0.736) </p>

<p>Note: See footnotes to Table 2. </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

<p>labour market. Just because the discrete hours 
points are the most common in the data, does not 
mean that they are necessarily available at a 
micro level for each individual. 
We are unable to quantify the effects of 
improved child care quality on child care 
demand. There is evidence in Australia that 
families care about quality and that local self-
reported levels of satisfaction with child care 
quality are related to women's labour supply and 
participation. However, it is impossible to sepa-
rate these out from concerns about cost and 
availability (see Breunig et al., 2011). One could 
estimate, using existing (but not publicly avail-
able) administrative data, the response of 
women's labour supply to changes in measurable 
quality indices such as staff-to-child ratios or 
staff qualification levels. This would then provide 
a 'quality elasticity' that could be used to 
evaluate the NQF changes. We do not know of 
any such quantitative estimates. 
We believe the child care demand response to 
quality improvements is likely to be small 
based on the international literature. Blau and 
Mocan (2002) and Blau (2001, Chapter 4) find 
small income and price elasticities of quality, 
and this is confirmed in Mocan (2007), who 
finds that while parents claim they care about 
quality they have difficulty in distinguishing 
between the quality levels of alternative child 
care providers. If child care demand increases 
in response to the quality improvements of the 
NQF, then our estimates above will over-esti-
mate the negative impact on child care demand. 
Our estimates of the change in the government 
budget will be an underestimate. The effect on 
labour supply is ambiguous. Our model would 
allow inclusion of a quality elasticity if one 
were available. 
Our price change assumptions are based on a 
common price increase across all types of child 
care. One might argue that the reforms are likely 
to have a larger impact on the price of lower-
quality child care centres than on higher-quality 
ones. Our approach would allow for modelling 
the effects of a heterogeneous price increase, but 
we have chosen not to do this as we do not have 
any good estimates of how price increases might 
differ across different child care centres. We 
think the homogeneous price increase that we 
have modelled is easier to interpret and under-
stand. How might this assumption affect our 
results? If price increases are larger for those 
paying less for child care, then our estimates of </p>

<p>the effect for low-wage women might be under-
estimated. Their labour supply and child care 
demand might fall more than we have indicated. 
Government expenditure would increase by more 
than we have estimated. It is important to note 
that price increases are mitigated for those at the 
bottom of the income distribution as the govern-
ment subsidies are most generous at this income 
level. So the effect on government expenditure 
would certainly be larger, but the changes for 
labour supply and child care demand might be 
fairly small. 
We ignore further repercussions from the 
supply side of the child care market which may 
also determine price changes. For example, child 
care centres altering the number of places in 
response to changed demand by parents. Access 
Economics (2009), in generating their cost sce-
narios, assumes no further supply-side effects. In 
Section 5.3.3, they write, 'The NQA reforms are 
assumed to not deviate growth in ECEC places 
from its projected path.' They further justify the 
assumption of no supply-side reaction by quoting 
a survey that finds '95.3 per cent of services ... 
would increase staff costs rather than decrease 
places'. The assumption of no additional supply-
side response relies on a low price elasticity of 
demand. We find a net price elasticity of demand 
of À0.25, which is slightly higher (in absolute 
value) than previous research. Therefore, the 
ability of child care centres to fully pass 
increased costs to parents may not be as great as 
is assumed by Access Economics (2009). We do 
not know what the other studies have assumed. 
In general in the literature, our understanding 
of the supply side is not as developed as that of 
the demand side. What determines the opening of 
a new child care centre, the closing of one, the 
number of places offered? What is the nature of 
competition in the child care industry? Quantita-
tive work on the supply side of the child care 
industry should be an important priority for future 
research. 
Lastly, we have focused on partnered women 
and provided estimates for that subpopulation. 
Lone parents and their response are important 
aspects to consider in understanding the full 
effects of the NQF but is beyond the scope of 
the current article. This is a priority for future 
research. </p>

<p>V Conclusion 
We find that the increase in child care costs 
associated with the implementation of the NQF is </p>

<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p> 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>



<p>likely to have modest negative effects on the 
labour supply of married women. Assuming that 
the NQF causes an increase in the gross price of 
$13.00 per child per day (a mid-range price 
scenario out of the range considered in the 
article), we find that average hours worked will 
decrease by approximately 20 min per week, 
while participation in work will decrease by a 
little over one-half of one percentage point. Child 
care demand will decrease by slightly larger 
amounts, while out-of-pocket child care costs for 
families will increase by $7.25 per week after 
accounting for off-setting government subsidies 
to child care. Overall, household disposable 
income will decrease by $12.54 per week which 
comprises both increased child care costs and 
reduced income from working less. Net 
government expenditure, taking into account 
decreased tax revenues, increased child care 
subsidies and changes to income support and 
family tax benefit payments caused by changing 
working hour patterns will increase by $10.82 per 
household per week. The effects are statistically 
significant. 
In the introduction, we highlighted the wide-
spread agreement among educators, psycho-
logists, economists and health professionals 
about the importance of and potential gains from 
investment in children. The NQF represents an 
investment in children which is hoped to bring 
long-term benefits. We have tried to quantify the 
costs which relate to two-parent households in 
four dimensions labour supply, child care 
demand, household income and government bal-
ance sheet; these do not represent all the costs. 
Our analysis excludes lone parents. We might 
expect a slightly larger labour supply response for 
lone parents relative to two-parent households (see 
Kalb, 2010), although cost increases group will be 
mitigated by higher benefit levels. Government 
costs will therefore likely be larger for this group, 
on average, than for two-parent households. 
Given expected future benefits for Australia's 
children, the costs outlined here seem relatively 
small, at least for two-parent households. Our 
intuition tells us that the investment is worth it. 
This of course is a matter of judgement. The main 
contribution here is to provide estimates of 
behavioural responses to better inform the debate. </p>

<p>Supporting Information 
Additional Supporting Information may be 
found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix S1. <rs type="software">Gauss</rs> program for simulations 
for female labour supply. </p>



<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>



<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>

<p> 
THE NEW NATIONAL QUALITY FRAMEWORK </p>

<p>15 </p>



<p>© 2013 Economic Society of Australia </p>



<p>ECONOMIC RECORD 
MARCH </p>

</text></tei>