<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecin.12482" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This study experimentally examines the effect of electoral delegation on providing 
global public goods shared by several groups. Each group elects one delegate who 
can freely decide on each group member's contribution to the global public goods. Our 
results show that people mostly vote for delegates who assign equal contributions for 
every group member. However, in contrast to standard theoretical predictions for our 
delegation mechanism, unequal contributions across groups drive cooperation down 
over time, and it decreases efficiency by almost 50% compared to the selfish benchmark. 
This pattern is not driven by delegates trying to exploit their fellow group members, as 
indicated by theory. It is driven by conditional cooperation of delegates across groups. 
Since one of the potential sources of the resulting inefficiency is the polycentric nature 
of global public goods provision together with other-regarding preferences, we use the 
term P-inefficiency to describe our finding. (JEL C92, D72, H41) </p>

<p>Compared to club goods such as highways 
or community swimming pools, maintaining 
an efficient provision of public goods on the 
international or global level is a difficult task. 
Despite the large number of examples of global 
public goods-for example, climate protection, 
biodiversity, international security, and scientific 
knowledge-economic research on the efficient 
management of these goods is still in its infancy. </p>

<p> *  We thank the responsible editor and two anonymous ref-
erees, Daniel Houser, Jens Grosser, Ernesto Reuben, Matthias 
Sutter, Roberto Weber, Johanthan Woon, participants of the 
ESA European Conference in Cologne, the ESA North Amer-
ican Meeting in Tucson, the first joint workshop between the 
University of Innsbruck and the Max Planck Institute for Tax 
Law and Public Finance, the 88th Western Economic Asso-
ciation International Annual Conference in Seattle, as well 
as seminar participants at the Universities of Amsterdam, 
Munich, Vermont, and Zurich for helpful comments and sug-
gestions. All remaining errors are ours. 
Kocher: Professor, Department of Economics, Univer-
sity of Munich, 80539 Munich, Germany; Institute 
of Advanced Studies, Vienna; Department of Eco-
nomics, University of Gothenburg. Phone +49 
89 21809726, Fax +49 89 2180999726, E-mail 
martin.kocher@lrz.uni-muenchen.de 
Tan: Max Planck Institute for Tax Law and Public Finance, 
80539 Munich, Germany. Phone +1 650 4506026, Fax 
+49 89 242465299, E-mail fangfang.tan@tax.mpg.de 
Yu: Department of Economics, University of Munich, 80539 
Munich, Germany. E-mail yj0787@googlemail.com </p>

<p>In general, global public goods (common goods) 
are vital to human welfare, yet often under-
provided, or they are over-exploited because of 
their nonexcludable benefits spilling over country 
borders. For instance, about 90% of marine fish 
stocks in the oceans have been over-exploited, 
fully exploited, or have completely collapsed by 
2009 (Froese et al. 2012). 
The management of global public goods 
is usually organized on multiple, hierarchical 
scales. This means that global public goods are 
often governed through a delegated institution 
whose officials (representatives) are elected or 
appointed by national (or regional) provision 
collectives. As a consequence, there is at least a 
two-tier or two-level provision organization. Is 
electoral delegation an effective mechanism in 
sustaining efficient provision levels of a global 
public good? Despite its obvious relevance, an 
empirical assessment of the effectiveness of 
delegation mechanisms of global public goods 
provision in the field is difficult due to lack of 
controlled data. Laboratory experiments based on 
the public goods game are one possible remedy </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>EU: European Union 
MPCR: Marginal Per Capita Return </p>

<p>381 
Economic Inquiry 
(ISSN 0095-2583) 
Vol. 56, No. 1, January 2018, 381-397 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/ecin.12482 
Online Early publication July 27, 2017 
© 2017 Western Economic Association International </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>(see Bernard et al. 2013; Hamman, Weber, and  Woon 2011). 1  The straightforward advantage of a provision 
collective consisting of delegates is that dele-
gates can make efficient use of the resources by 
taking centralized decisions that keep up coordi-
nation within and across societies. Nevertheless, 
the absence of global authority means that there 
is a temptation to free ride and that global pub-
lic goods are likely to be under-provided or not 
provided at all (e.g., Aronsson and Johansson- Stenman 2014; Barrett 2007; Conceicao 2003;  Löschel and Rübbelke 2014). Another possible 
cause for the failure is related to an interesting 
behavioral dilemma for voters in the selection 
of their representatives. Is it better to delegate a 
pro-social representative who strives for cooper-
ation when interacting with representatives from 
other groups, but runs the risk of being exploited 
by the latter? Or, is it better to elect an egois-
tic representative who increases own-group profit 
by free-riding on other groups' contributions, but 
who might be inclined to abusing her power at 
hand by exploiting her fellow group members? 
In this study, we focus on a key determinant 
of electoral delegation in the provision of global 
public goods: the interactions between voters 
and political representatives/delegates. 2 To do so, 
we devise a laboratory experiment that abstracts 
from the complexity in real-world global pub-
lic goods provision, but highlights the poly-
centric nature. This concept, first discussed in 
Ostrom, Tiebout, and Warren (1961), describes 
the complexity of global public goods provision 
as involving "many centers of decision-making 
that are formally independent of each other" (for 
a more detailed discussion, see Ostrom 2010). 
In our two-level provision mechanism, the del-
egate is able to determine the provision vector 
of all members of her provision group on the 
lower level (the group level), and she interacts 
with other delegates on the super-group or society </p>

<p>1. Surveys of public goods experiments that do not imple-
ment delegation are provided in Ledyard (1995) and Chaud- huri (2011). By design our setup is related to a small body 
of literature on public goods provision that involves multi-
ple layers of independent contribution decisions (see, e.g., 
Blackwell and McKee 2003; Fellner and Lünser 2014). A key 
feature that differentiates our study from theirs is that in other 
papers decision makers in multilevel public goods games need 
to trade off contributions between a local and a global level 
public good. Our setting, however, focuses on the provision 
of global level public goods only. 
2. Delegation in principal-agent settings has attracted 
considerable attention in the experimental economics litera-
ture recently (see, e.g., Bartling and Fischbacher 2012).   level when providing global public goods. Think 
of her as a national minister or a head of state in 
the European Union (EU), who makes decisions 
on global public goods contributions (e.g., the 
national contribution to European battle groups) 
on behalf of the voters in the country she repre-
sents. Notice that the group contribution decision 
in the real world can also be implicit through a 
national decision on the distribution of the tax 
burden or through a decision on the design of the 
redistributive system of a jurisdiction. The deci-
sions of all representatives of all EU countries 
determine the total contributions at the EU level. 3  An egoistic representative might be an asset in 
the interaction on the super-group level because 
she is not taken advantage of by other represen-
tatives, but she might exploit part of her own 
citizens (the own group members) when financ-
ing the contributions to the public good by let-
ting them contribute over-proportionately (and/or 
free-riding on them). In contrast, a cooperative 
representative might use a fair proportional con-
tribution rule within her own group that does not 
exploit anybody, but her group could be exploited 
on the society level by the potentially egoistic 
representatives of other groups. 
To sum up, our setup is able to address empir-
ically (1) the overall effect of electoral delegation 
on the efficiency of global public goods provi-
sion, (2) to what extent and how precisely del-
egation might be able to overcome the lack of 
global authority and to coordinate the provision 
of global public goods, and (3) the potential of 
an election procedure to (partly) curb the abuse 
of power by representatives. A laboratory exper-
iment allows us to isolate the incentive effects 
and should be viewed as a platform for study-
ing cooperation and delegation, complementary 
to field studies. It enables us to assess coopera-
tive preferences and their impact on elections and 
public goods provision by delegates at the indi-
vidual level. 4  More precisely, in our experiment, nine deci-
sion makers form a society, and they are divided 
into three groups of population size 3 each. In 
the Baseline treatment in the experiment, play-
ers in each group have to make simultaneous and </p>

<p>3. Likewise, in mitigating global warming, decisions of 
all representatives of countries determine the total reduction 
of CO 2 emissions via multilateral agreements such as the 
Kyoto protocol. 
4. Having field data on the important aspects in our setup 
would be desirable. However, some of the variables are, by 
their very nature, difficult to observe in the field or strongly 
confounded. </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>independent decisions about how much to con-
tribute to a global public good provided at the 
level of the nine-person society. The total con-
tributions from all members of the three groups 
are multiplied by a parameter larger than 1 and 
are then equally distributed among all players in 
the groups. The parameter is chosen in a way to 
induce a linear social dilemma that maximizes 
the distance between the individually optimal and 
the socially optimal choices of the group mem-
bers. In the Delegation treatment, we introduce a 
Borda count as the election rule for the delegation 
mechanism. The candidate with the smallest total 
sum of ranks in each group becomes the dele-
gate for her group for the upcoming three periods 
of interaction. In the contribution stages of the 
public goods game in each period, only the three 
delegates make decisions for each of their three 
group members. More specifically, they submit 
a contribution vector for the three members of 
their groups (including themselves). This vector 
can induce equal or unequal contributions within 
a group. Other group members than the dele-
gates remain passive observers of the provision 
decisions. This design feature captures the fact 
that delegates are able to maximize their per-
sonal gain at the expense of the majority of vot-
ers. It can, for instance, be viewed as the poten-
tial for corrupt office-holding by the delegate or 
as "pork barrel" politics; but within the logic of 
the public goods game, it is simply free-riding 
on the benefits of the public good without con-
tributing oneself. In reality, there are of course 
limits to such kinds of behavior, but in order to 
have a clear incentive structure, we maximize the 
potential for exploitation by the delegate in our 
experiment. 
We implement a standard finitely repeated lin-
ear public goods game without delegation (Base-
line treatment). The unique sub-game perfect 
equilibrium of this game is zero contributions 
for all players. In the Delegation treatment, a 
profit-maximizing delegate would fully exploit 
the other two members of her group, because 
she benefits from the contributions of the other 
group members. More specifically, she would 
force the two other group members to contribute 
fully and thus free ride on them. Therefore, by 
construction, compared to the Baseline treatment, 
efficiency (i.e., the total earnings of all players) 
in the Delegation treatment increases in equilib-
rium. Models taking inequity-averse preferences 
into account (e.g., Fehr and Schmidt 1999) give 
slightly different predictions, but exploitation is 
still likely to take place in the stage game. </p>

<p>Our experimental results of Baseline are by 
and large in line with theoretical predictions 
based on standard preferences. Without delega-
tion, cooperation quickly declines to low levels 
in the finitely repeated game. Compared to Base-
line, both contributions and earnings are higher 
in Delegation. In contrast to standard predic-
tions, the elected delegates avoid exploiting other 
group members by assigning equal contributions 
to the three group members, driven either by 
genuine other-regarding preferences or an oppor-
tunistic re-election (reputation) motive. However, 
despite the existence of other-regarding prefer-
ences, we observe that the actual contribution 
levels in Delegation are significantly below the 
theoretical benchmark with self-regarding pref-
erences, and they steadily decline over time. 5 In 
effect, delegates who over-contribute compared 
to other delegates in the society are less likely 
to be re-elected. As a consequence, a downward 
spiral of contribution levels for the global pub-
lic good sets in. It seems that a combination of 
(1) delegation based on (re)-election and (2) het-
erogeneity in other-regarding preferences leads 
to an inefficiency for which we use the term 
P-inefficiency, associating it with a global pub-
lic good's polycentric nature. Our data indicate 
that both ingredients, the re-election concern, and 
heterogeneity across different groups in terms of 
other-regarding preferences, might be necessary 
for existence of the P-inefficiency. However, any 
of the two elements seems natural in the provision 
and management of global public goods. 
Despite the enormous amount of evidence on 
the private provision of public goods based on 
laboratory experiments and a growing number of 
papers on delegation in principal-agent settings, 
the literature closely related to our setup is very 
small. Hamman, Weber, and Woon (2011) study 
the effect of electoral delegation in a linear pub-
lic goods game. In their delegation treatments, 
nine players in a group have to choose a single 
allocator who decides about the amount of con-
tributions for everyone in the group. Although 
they find that a couple of minimum winning 
coalitions in the election game for allocation 
power reap the benefits of the public good at the 
cost of other players in the group, most groups </p>

<p>5. Note that efficiency is maximized when all delegates 
contribute for every group member (including themselves) the 
entire endowment to the public good. The full exploitation 
solution according to which the three delegates free ride and 
make the two other members within their respective groups 
provide full contributions gives another benchmark for the 
achievable level of efficiency. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>in their experiment elect high contributors who 
implement full contribution levels for all group 
members including themselves. Bolle and Vogel  (2011) examine a similar setting and report that 
both elected and randomly appointed allocators 
increase the levels of public goods provision over 
the benchmark of the standard linear public goods 
game, although the effect becomes smaller with 
repetition. In addition, Oxoby (2013) and Fleiß  and Palan (2013) find that contributions increase 
when a randomly selected delegate can choose 
contribution levels for all group members. 6  The difference between our study and those 
discussed in the previous paragraph lies in the 
particular group and society structure naturally 
caused by global public goods provision. In the 
existing studies, the delegates act like dictators 
since they can determine the level of contribu-
tions for every person in society without any 
restrictions. In other words, the public goods pro-
vision contains no hierarchical structure. In our 
setting, however, the decision power of the del-
egate is confined to her own group. The total 
level of public goods provision is determined 
by the simultaneous and independent decisions 
of the three delegates on behalf of their groups. 
Hence, not only do they face a redistribution 
problem within their groups, but they also have 
to deal with the strategic interactions with other 
delegates across groups. As a consequence, inef-
ficiency in the public goods provision quickly 
arises in our setup, in contrast to the setup in 
Hamman, Weber, and Woon (2011). 
The only study that introduces both the sub-
group and the delegation elements, to the best 
of our knowledge, is Bernard et al. (2013). They 
compare several voting schemes in extracting 
common pool resources, which share a similar 
payoff structure as the public goods game. In 
one of these mechanisms, a randomly chosen 
player in every period votes, on behalf of her 
group, on the level of extractions for the entire 
group. They find that this mechanism is effective 
in overcoming the tragedy of the commons, since 
the decisions of the delegate affect the group 
as a whole. In their setting, the median of all 
extraction proposals made by the delegates was 
implemented automatically, making it easier to 
prevent a group from implementing an extreme </p>

<p>6. There is a growing body of literature that studies 
the effects of delegating punishment or implicit punishment 
to a centralized authority and the willingness of groups to 
do so (see, e.g., Andreoni and Gee 2012; Baldassarri and  Grossman 2011; Kosfeld, Okada, and Riedl 2009; Markussen,  Putterman, and Tyran 2014; Tan and Xiao 2012). </p>

<p>extraction level by construction. In the other 
mechanism, each player votes for the level of 
extractions implemented at their own group level 
in each period. They find that the extraction level 
is not only higher but also increases over time 
with this mechanism due to defection by other 
groups that extract from the common pool. Com-
pared to their study, our study focuses on elected 
delegates instead of randomly assigned dele-
gates. Data from the elections help us uncover 
the motives and expectations of players and 
enable us to assess the preferences of group 
members with regard to the characteristics of 
their representatives. Moreover, our study allows 
the delegates to choose contribution strategies 
for each member of their own groups without 
any restrictions throughout their tenures, making 
exploitation of ordinary group members by the 
delegates possible. 
The remaining paper is organized as follows: 
Section II presents our experimental design. 
Section III derives theoretical predictions based 
on both self-interested and inequity-averse pref-
erences. In Section IV, we present our empirical 
results, and Section V concludes the paper. </p>

<p>II. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN AND PROCEDURES </p>

<p>We implement two treatments in our study: 
Baseline (no delegation) as our control treatment 
and Delegation. Every experimental session with 
18 experimental participants divides the partici-
pants into two cohorts (matching groups) of nine 
subjects each at the beginning of the experiment. 
Possible re-matching takes place only within a 
cohort in order to guarantee strict statistical inde-
pendence at the level of the super-group (society) 
of nine subjects. A total of seven experimen-
tal sessions provide us with six independent 
observations for Baseline and eight independent 
observations for Delegation. At the beginning of 
a session, subjects are informed that the exper-
iment will consist of four parts. They receive 
instructions (see Section C in Appendix S1, Sup-
porting Information) for the four parts separately, 
always before the start of a specific part. 
The basic game that we use is a standard 
linear public goods game, presented in a neutral 
(i.e., context-free) frame to the participants. The 
first three parts of the experiment are identical 
across treatments; the treatment variation was 
introduced only in the fourth part. 
At the beginning of Part 1, subjects are ran-
domly matched within their cohort into groups of 
three. Each of the three group members receives </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>an endowment of 20 experiment points, and they 
have to decide simultaneously about their indi-
vidual contribution (c i ) to a public account. The 
marginal per capita return (MPCR) is set at 0.5. 
The payoff function (π i ) for subject i is </p>

<p>(1) 
π i = 20 − c i + 0.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>c j </p>

<p>with c j as the contribution of the j 
group members. 
Part 1 measures cooperative preferences 
at the individual level. It is a one-shot public 
goods game based on the strategy vector method 
introduced by Fischbacher, Gächter, and Fehr  (2001) and validated for repeated interactions by 
Fischbacher and Gächter (2010) as well as by 
Fischbacher, Gächter, and Quercia (2012). Sub-
jects make an integer unconditional contribution 
to the public good. Then, they specify condi-
tional contribution levels. In particular, they have 
to fill in a contribution table that indicates how 
much they want to put into the public account 
for each of the 21 possible average contributions 
of the other two group members (rounded up to 
the next integer). To make both decisions, the 
unconditional contribution and the contribution 
table, incentive compatible, the computer ran-
domly selects one subject within each group in 
the end and makes her conditional contribution 
table payoff-relevant. The two unconditional 
contributions from the other two group members 
and the corresponding conditional contribution 
of the randomly chosen subject constitute the 
group's contribution to the public account. Then 
Equation (1) is applied. We do not give any 
feedback on others' choices and earnings from 
Part 1 until the end of the entire experiment to 
avoid contamination across parts. All details 
mentioned so far (except for the existence of 
two cohorts in one session) are common knowl-
edge among participants. Control questions, 
examples, screenshots, and the possibility to ask 
questions before the start of Part 1 make sure 
that participants fully understand their available 
strategies and the nature of the interaction. 
Part 2 collects subjects' distributional pref-
erences as dictators. At the beginning of this 
part, experimental participants are randomly re-
matched into groups of three within their cohorts. 
Part 2 is a one-shot three-person allocation game 
(for instructions, see Section C in Appendix S1). 
It uses exactly the same payoff function as in 
the previous part (see Equation (1)), and it aims </p>

<p>to provide a measure of distributive or other-
regarding preferences at the individual level that 
is independent of any reputational concerns. Each 
group member decides on her own contribution to 
the public good as well as on the contributions 
of the other two group members. The program 
randomly selects one member from each group 
ex-post and implements her allocation decision, 
that is, the allocation choice of one of the three 
group members is implemented for the entire 
group with equal probability. Similar to the first 
part, no feedback on the results from Part 2 is pro-
vided until the very end of the experiment. All 
procedures are common knowledge. 
Part 3 provides our participants with enough 
experience for Part 4, which is a more compli-
cated environment due to the delegation proce-
dure in Delegation. In Part 3, subjects interact 
with each other for eight identical periods in a 
standard linear public goods game based on the 
payoff function in Equation (1). At the begin-
ning of the third part, random matching within 
the cohort into groups of three takes place, and 
groups now stay together for the entire eight peri-
ods of Part 3 (for the experimental instructions, 
see Section C in Appendix S1). After each period, 
subjects receive feedback on the contributions 
and earnings of all members in their group. Each 
period and every decision is payoff-relevant in 
Part 3. 
Part 4, the main part of our experiment, differs 
in the two treatments (see Section C in Appendix 
S1). In both treatments, subjects are told that the 
composition of their group and their experimental 
IDs remain unchanged from the ones in Part 
3. They are, further, informed that their group 
and two other groups (from the same matching 
cohort) will be matched into a super-group of 
nine members for the next (and final) 18 periods 
of interaction. 
In Baseline, every member in the three 
groups simultaneously decides on how much 
to contribute to the super-group account. The 
super-group account collects the sum of all con-
tributions from the nine super-group members. 
Define c iK as the contribution of member i in 
group K. The payoff function (π iK ) for subject i 
in group K is </p>

<p>(2) 
π iK = 20 − c iK + 
1.5 
9 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>K=1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>c jK . </p>

<p>The sum of the contributions by all nine 
super-group members (denoted by C in the 
following) is multiplied by the social marginal </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>benefit 1.5 and then equally distributed across 
the three groups. Within each group, the amount 
is also divided equally, and, hence, each member 
receives 0.5C/3. Therefore, the increase in group 
size is counterbalanced by the decrease in the 
MPCR. Moreover, the standard game-theoretic 
equilibrium and the social optimal choices 
remain unchanged (see Section III for details). 
In Delegation, we use exactly the same pay-
off function. However, groups need to elect a 
delegate who makes a binding decision for the 
contributions of each group member, that is, she 
submits a contribution vector consisting of three 
elements, one for each of the three group mem-
bers including the contribution of herself. Dele-
gates are elected for a three-period tenure. New 
elections take place after these three periods. 
The delegate is elected via a Borda count, which 
is simple to explain, easy to implement, and it 
allows researchers collecting a complete prefer-
ence list for the candidates. That is, every mem-
ber of a group is a voter and ranks the candidates 
(including herself) in order of individual prefer-
ences (with 1 as the most preferable rank). The 
computer, then, sums up the ranks of the three 
candidates within a group and appoints the can-
didate with the lowest rank sum as the delegate. 
In case of ties, one of the tied candidates is ran-
domly selected as delegate for her group. When 
casting their vote, subjects can see the average 
contributions of the three members within their 
groups from Part 3 of the experiment as well as 
the following pieces of information from Part 4 
(starting from the vote before period 4 in Part 
4 onwards): (1) the ID of the delegate of their 
group in the previous three periods, (2) the vec-
tors of contributions and earnings of all members 
in one's own group for the previous three periods, 
and (3) the average contributions of the two other 
groups within the super-group in each of the pre-
vious three periods. It is important to note that 
our design implies that members from the other 
two groups can neither influence the contribution 
decisions nor the election/replacement of a dele-
gate outside their groups. 
After the election, everyone within a group 
is informed about the IDs of the three delegates 
who make contribution choices on behalf of their 
group members for the next three periods. At 
the end of each single period in Part 4, everyone 
within a group receives information regarding the 
delegate ID, the contributions and earnings of 
each member in her own group, and the total con-
tributions of each of the three groups. To facili-
tate comparisons, we present subjects in Baseline </p>

<p>with exactly the same information without any 
reference to delegation or elections. Communi-
cation is not allowed in either treatment. 7  The experiment was conducted in the 
MELESSA laboratory at the University of 
Munich from February to April 2012. A total 
number of 126 undergraduate and postgrad-
uate (master) students with various academic 
backgrounds were recruited via <rs id="software-2" type="software">ORSEE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Greiner</rs>  2015). Subjects remained anonymous throughout 
the experiment and cash payments were made 
privately. The experiment was programmed and 
conducted with the software <rs id="software-3" type="software">z-Tree</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Fischbacher</rs>  2007). An experimental session lasted for a bit 
less than 2 hours. Subjects earned an average of 
€22.05 (including a €4 show-up fee). </p>

<p>III. THEORETICAL EXPECTATIONS </p>

<p>In this section, we derive equilibrium predic-
tions for our experiment. We start with standard 
preferences and extend our analysis to inequity-
averse preferences. Our focus is on Parts 3 and 4. 
Predictions for the earlier parts in our experiment 
follow immediately from the discussion regard-
ing Parts 3 and 4. </p>

<p>A. Predictions Based on Selfish Preferences </p>

<p>The predictions for Baseline and the eight-
period public goods game in Part 3 are straight-
forward. With rational, selfish, and risk-neutral 
group members and common knowledge thereof, 
the unique sub-game perfect equilibrium in the 
finitely repeated game is to contribute 0 to the lin-
ear public good. The MPCR of the public good is 
always lower than the marginal return of keeping 
one's endowment in our game. The social opti-
mum, however, is to contribute the entire endow-
ment to the public account, since the social return 
is larger than 1. </p>

<p>Hypothesis 1(a) for Baseline: Players will con-
tribute 0 to the global public good. </p>

<p>We now turn to Delegation. Under the homo 
economicus assumption, the unique sub-game 
perfect equilibrium collapses to the following 
stage game equilibrium of the finitely repeated 
game: The delegate fully maximizes her mone-
tary payoff by contributing 0 and forcing the other </p>

<p>7. Obviously, introducing communication is a very inter-
esting extension to our setup. However, we wanted to start 
with the most parsimonious experimental design and thus do 
not take communication into account. </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>two group members to contribute their entire 
endowment to the public good. Doing so maxi-
mizes the delegate's monetary earnings because 
she can free ride on the contributions of the other 
two group members. </p>

<p>Hypothesis 1(b) for Delegation: The elected 
delegate will assign full contributions for the 
other two group members and zero contribution 
for herself. </p>

<p>Let us now consider the voting stage that 
takes place every three periods in Delegation. We 
assume here that it takes place at the beginning of 
the stage game. Since the delegate has the poten-
tial to earn more than the other group members, 
a profit-maximizing player will try to maximize 
the chance of being elected in the voting stage. 
There are several voting equilibria, but all imply 
ex ante equal chances to be elected as the dele-
gate for one's group if all voters vote rationally. A 
corollary of this result is that there are no individ-
ual characteristics that play a role in the elections. 
Proofs can be found in Section A in Appendix S1. </p>

<p>Hypothesis 1(c) for the Election: All voting 
equilibria imply ex ante equal chances to be 
elected as the delegate in a group. </p>

<p>B. Predictions Based on Other-Regarding 
Preferences </p>

<p>In this section, we relax the self-interest 
assumption by considering other-regarding 
preferences. All other assumptions remain 
unchanged. The detailed predictions for a pop-
ular outcome-based other-regarding preference 
model, the inequity-aversion model by Fehr and  Schmidt (1999) as an example, can be found 
in Section A in Appendix S1. Here we briefly 
sketch the intuition. 
For Part 4, one can derive predictions that dis-
tinguish between two different reference-group 
concepts: for a delegate or a group member the 
reference group can either be the own three-
person group or the nine-person super-group. The 
distinction is based on the well-established find-
ing in the social identity literature that people dif-
ferentiate between their in-group members and 
members of the out-group (see, e.g., Chen and  Li 2009; Meier et al. 2012). It turns out that 
how we define the size of the reference group 
does not affect equilibria in Baseline. This is 
an immediate consequence of the fact that the 
return of the public good is linear in proportions 
of contributions. This means, Part 3 predictions 
and Part 4 predictions for Baseline are identical. </p>

<p>A cut-off level of β-the parameter for advanta-
geous inequity aversion-for all group members 
determines whether cooperative equilibria exist. 
However, the size of the reference group 
affects the conditions that determine cooperative 
equilibria in Delegation. When the reference 
group is the three-person group, a delegate faces 
two motivations. First, she has to trade-off her 
monetary earnings and income inequity within 
her own group. Second, she has an incentive 
to free ride on contributions of other groups, 
since income for members of other groups 
does not affect her utility. When the reference 
group is the nine-person super-group, the weight 
of each in-group member in the social utility 
part of the delegate's utility function decreases 
from 1/2 (two members of the own group taken 
into account) to 1/8 (all eight members of the 
super-group taken into account), that is, the 
weight of each out-group member increases 
from 0 to 1/8. Intuitively, free-riding on in-group 
members, who weigh less now, becomes com-
paratively more attractive, while free-riding on 
out-group members becomes less attractive, 
since the disutility from contributing less than 
them becomes larger. Further, it is possible to 
show that, depending on the size of the reference 
group and on the other delegates' inequity-
aversion parameters, players with sufficiently 
strong advantageous inequity aversion will be 
elected as delegates. If none of the candidates is 
sufficiently inequity-averse, players will vote for 
themselves, and everybody is equally likely to 
become the delegate within her group. 
The above analysis holds for the stage game. 
It is noteworthy that in the repeated game, there 
are many more equilibria, and they only require 
lower levels of β because of the incentive to 
build a reputation as a cooperative delegate (e.g., 
Oechssler 2013). Our delegation mechanism, 
however, implies a complication for the reputa-
tion building process because of the election and 
of the chance that a delegate is suspended from 
her "job." </p>

<p>IV. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS </p>

<p>We organize the presentation of our results as 
follows. Section IV.A compares average contri-
butions and earnings across the two treatments. 
Section IV.B studies contribution and allocation 
choices of the delegates. Section IV.C analyzes 
how delegates are elected and what deter-
mines the rankings of the voters. Section IV.D </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 
Average Super-group Contribution Levels as a 
Percentage of Endowment in Parts 3 and 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Percentage of endowment </p>

<p>Delegation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 26 
Period </p>

<p>Baseline </p>

<p>Prediction based on standard preferences for baseline </p>

<p>Prediction based on standard preferences for both treatments 
Prediction based on standard preferences for delegation </p>

<p>explains heterogeneous contribution dynamics 
across societies. Unless specified differently, 
the nonparametric tests in this section are two-
sided Mann-Whitney rank sum tests, with 
each super-group as a statistically strictly 
independent observation. </p>

<p>A. Treatment Differences </p>

<p>Figure 1 presents the average group contribu-
tions to the public good by treatment. Before the 
treatment manipulation, the dynamics of contri-
butions in both treatments are highly consistent 
with the previous literature: The average con-
tributions amount to about 45% of the endow-
ment in the first period of the public goods 
game, and then they decline steadily to about 
15% by the eighth period (at the end of Part 
3). The two treatments do not exhibit significant 
differences in contribution levels (p &gt; .4), mak-
ing sure that the initial experience is on aver-
age the same before the start of Part 4 in the 
two treatments. 
After the introduction of the treatment vari-
ation, however, the two treatments exhibit stark 
differences. In Baseline, we observe the typ-
ical "restart" effect in the voluntary contribu-
tion mechanism, with an average contribution 
level of about 30%, but contributions decay to 
less than 10% after a couple of periods. This 
pattern suggests that, without any institution, 
the free-riding incentive is dominant even in 
the repeated interaction, and social preferences 
are not strong enough to sustain high levels 
of cooperation. </p>

<p>In Delegation, average contributions start 
out at about 60% of the total endowment in 
period 1, but gradually decline to around 35% 
in the ultimate period of Part 4. The treatment 
difference is obviously highly significant (aver-
ages for Part 4 are 9.6% vs. 48.3%; p &lt; .01). 
Due to the linear nature of the public goods 
game, the significant differences in contri-
butions directly translate into differences in 
earnings, that is, efficiency. Controlling for the 
decay and for the general level of coopera-
tiveness on the group level measured in Part 
3, the results of a random-effect regression 
analysis unambiguously confirm the findings 
from nonparametric tests (see Table B1 in 
Appendix S1). 
Predictions based on standard preferences for 
Delegation indicate that if the delegates play the 
stage-game outcome by fully exploiting the other 
two group members, the average contributions at 
the society level should stay constant at 66.7% 
of the total endowment throughout the 18 peri-
ods of play in Delegation. This is clearly not the 
case. Contributions in Delegation are on average 
significantly below the benchmark (p = .03; two-
sided Wilcoxon signed-rank test). This is evi-
dence for the P-inefficiency. Result 1 summarizes 
the findings. </p>

<p>RESULT 1. Neither Hypothesis 1(a) nor an 
alternative reasoning based on inequity aversion 
is fully supported. In Baseline, average contri-
butions are significantly larger than 0 (p &lt; .05, 
two-sided Wilcoxon signed-rank test), although 
they quickly decline over time. Average contri-
butions in Delegation are significantly higher 
than in Baseline; however, on average, they fall 
significantly below the theoretical prediction 
of 66.67%. Delegation is significantly less effi-
cient than what standard theory predicts (the 
"P-inefficiency"). </p>

<p>B. Delegates' Distribution Choices </p>

<p>We first analyze the allocation decisions of 
the delegates within their subgroups, followed by 
their contributions relative to other subgroups. 
Table 1 classifies the elected delegates into three 
types based on their average contributions in Part 
3, relative to the two other group members, and 
denote them High, Middle, and Low delegates. 
There is a strong correlation between a delegate's 
own contribution in Part 3 and their allocation 
to the public goods in Part 4. High contributing 
delegates assign on average 55.4% of the total </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>TABLE 1 
Decisions of the Elected Delegates </p>

<p>Contribution Ranks of Delegates in Part 4 </p>

<p>High 
Middle 
Low 
All </p>

<p>Contributions in % (mean) 
55.4 
4 0 .7 
4 0 
4 8 .3 
Contributions in % (standard dev.) 
26.3 
2 5 .2 
2 5 .3 
2 6 .8 
Distribution of Allocation Decisions (%) 
EQUAL 
89.8 
8 0 .0 
8 1 .9 
8 5 .4 
FULL 
12.9 
2 .2 
0 .0 
7 .4 
EXPLOIT ONE 
4.0 
9 .6 
1 .4 
5 .3 
EXPLOIT BOTH 
6.2 
7 .4 
1 1 .1 
7 .4 
OTHER (ALTRUISTIC) 
0.0 
3 .0 
5 .6 
1 .9 
No. of observations 
225 
135 
72 
432 </p>

<p>Notes: FULL means that the delegate contributes the entire endowments of all three group members to the global public good. 
EQUAL means that the delegate lets every member contribute the same to the global public goods (including full contributions). 
EXPLOIT ONE means that the delegate contributes the same as or more than one group member and forces the other member 
to contribute the most (uniquely) of the three. EXPLOIT BOTH means that the delegate contributes the least (uniquely) among 
the three. OTHER includes all contribution vectors of altruistic types (delegate contributes the most [uniquely or together with 
one other group member]). </p>

<p>endowment to the public account, which is sig-
nificantly higher than the assignment levels by 
middle or low contributors. 8 The lower part of 
Table 1 reports contribution assignment frequen-
cies, treating each allocation decision as indepen-
dent. These figures indicate that, 85.4% of the 
time, the elected delegates choose equal contribu-
tions for all group members. This is particularly 
true if the delegate has been the high contributor 
in her group: Roughly, 90% of the time she will 
implement an equal contribution vector, among 
which 12.9% of the time she requires all group 
members to contribute fully. Interestingly, mid-
dle and low contribution delegates also assign 
equal contribution levels with very high frequen-
cies (80% and 81.9%, respectively). Overall, only 
about 10%-15% of the time do they attempt to 
exploit other group members. 
Given such high proportions of equal contribu-
tions within subgroups, what about relative con-
tributions across groups and the inter-temporal 
adjustment? To address this question, Table 2 
reports results of random-effect panel regressions 
where the dependent variable is the difference in 
contributions of the delegate's own group across 
two periods, either for the delegate herself, for the 
average of the other two members, or for both. 
The results from the regression in Table 2 and 
the following regressions have to be taken with a 
grain of salt. So far in the results sections, we have </p>

<p>8. The random-effect regression results in Table B2 in 
Appendix S1 support this claim. The contribution difference 
between high and low delegates is significant at the 10% level 
(Wald test). </p>

<p>been relying on treatment differences that provide 
us with causal inference. When we want to look 
at the structure of the data within our treatments, 
endogeneity issues cannot be excluded, since 
becoming a delegate potentially depends on con-
tributions and contributions potentially depend 
on elections. We think that addressing the struc-
ture of behavior is still interesting, but it should 
be borne in mind that identification is not causal. 
The significant coefficients β 2 and β 3 , when 
pooling all data together, suggest that the del-
egates attempt to coordinate the contributions 
of their own groups with the average of the 
entire super-group. Specifically, if they realize 
that their own group over-contributed in the 
last period, they lower their contributions in the 
subsequent period (β 2 ). Similarly, in case of 
under-contribution, the delegates adjust their own 
contributions upwards (β 3 ). 
The insignificant coefficients β 4 and β 5 indi-
cate that the contribution changes applied to the 
other two group members do not significantly 
differ from the changes applied to oneself as 
delegate. In other words, the delegates adjust con-
tribution behavior similarly for the other group 
members as for themselves. Only in 4.17% of 
cases (18 out of 432), a delegate behaves exactly 
according to standard theory in the stage game 
by fully exploiting the other two members of her 
group, 13.66% of the time (59 out of 432) the del-
egate assigns zero contributions to everyone, and 
7.41% of the time (32 out of 432) she assigns full 
contributions to everyone. 
Two potential explanations are consistent with 
delegates' egalitarian behavior. First, they are </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Random-effect Regressions on Contribution Dynamics </p>

<p>Changes of Contributions Across Periods 
All 
Delegates 
Average of Others </p>

<p>β 1 : Changes apply to the other two members 
(=1, if yes) </p>

<p>−0.442 
-
-
(0.305) 
β 2 : Positive deviation from the super-group 
average (t−1) </p>

<p>−0.855 *** 
−0.829 *** 
−0.536 ** 
(0.148) 
(0.164) 
(0.228) 
β 3 : Negative deviation from the super-group 
average (t−1) </p>

<p>0.557 *** 
0.519 *** 
0.532 *** 
(0.139) 
(0.117) 
(0.128) 
β 4 : Changes apply to the other two 
members × Positive deviation from 
super-group average (t−1) </p>

<p>0.304 
-
-
(0.214) </p>

<p>β 5 : Changes apply to the other two 
members × Negative deviation from 
super-group average (t−1) </p>

<p>0.017 
-
-
(0.075) </p>

<p>β 6 : Period 
−0.098 
−0.109 * 
−0.051 
(0.067) 
(0.060) 
(0.083) 
Constant 
−0.186 
0.128 
−0.907 
(0.632) 
(0.578) 
(0.712) 
R 2 overall 
0.141 
0.167 
0.113 
No. of observations 
576 
288 
288 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors (clustered at the subgroup level) are reported in parentheses. In particular, the variable "Changes 
apply to the other two members" is a dummy variable equal to 1 if the dependent variable is the average change of contributions 
for the other two members across periods of each period. "Positive (Negative) deviation from the super-group average" measures 
the amount group average contributions exceeds (falls short of) that of the super-group averages in the last period. We do not 
report marginal effects instead of regression coefficients, because the former make little sense for interaction terms. 
* p &lt; .1, ** p &lt; .05, *** p &lt; .01. </p>

<p>motivated by other-regarding preference. Sec-
ond, at least some delegates mimic the strategy of 
the other-regarding type to increase their chances 
to be re-elected. 9 To tear apart the relative impor-
tance of preference and strategic concerns, we 
look into the correlation between the allocation 
decisions of delegates in Part 2 (the one-shot allo-
cation game) and their decisions in Part 4. We 
exclude data in the last three periods of Part 4 for 
the moment, since then delegates have no incen-
tive anymore to build up reputation. 
The main observation from Table 3 is that 
both preferences and strategic concerns explain 
the behavioral pattern of delegates. The allocators 
who shared equally in Part 2, if elected as a dele-
gate in Part 4, continue assigning equal contribu-
tions for all group members in more than 90% of 
cases (157/168). The exploiting types based on 
the behavior in Part 2, on the other hand, also 
equalize contributions in about 85% of the time 
(164 out of 189). Result 2 summarizes the above 
findings. </p>

<p>RESULT 2. Neither Hypothesis 1(b) nor alter-
native reasoning based on inequity aversion is </p>

<p>9. A feeling of responsibility on the side of the dele-
gates could be another reason that leads to equal contributions. 
However, we cannot directly assess its influence and disentan-
gle it from other-regarding preferences in our setup. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Correlation between Delegates' Distribution 
Preferences in Part 2 and Decisions in Part 4 
(except for the last three periods) </p>

<p>Part 4 </p>

<p>Part 2 
Equal </p>

<p>Exploit 
One 
Member </p>

<p>Exploit 
Both 
Members Others Total </p>

<p>Equal 
157 
10 
0 
1 
168 
Exploit one 
member </p>

<p>3 
0 
0 
0 
3 </p>

<p>Exploit both 
members </p>

<p>164 
9 
10 
6 
189 </p>

<p>Total 
324 
19 
10 
7 
360 </p>

<p>Note: The interpretations of the categories "Equal," "Ex-
ploit one member," "Exploit both members," and "Others" are 
the same as in Table 1. </p>

<p>fully supported when looking at the contribution 
assignment decisions of the delegates: Instead of 
complete free-riding on the contributions of the 
other two group members, they most frequently 
assign equal non-zero (medium) levels of contri-
butions in their groups. </p>

<p>C. Elections and Rankings of Delegates </p>

<p>Election of Delegates. From the previous 
sections, two main patterns in contradiction 
with standard theoretical predictions arise. </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>TABLE 4 
Summary Statistics on the First Election </p>

<p>Percentage 
of Rank 1 </p>

<p>Average 
Rank 
Assigned </p>

<p>Number 
Elected </p>

<p>Self 
63.9 
-
-
High contributor 
55.6 
1 .6 
1 9 
Middle contributor 
26.4 
2 
3 
Low contributor 
18.0 
2 .4 
2 
No. of observations 
72 
72 
24 </p>

<p>Note: The distinction between High/Medium/Low con-
tributors is based on contribution data from Part 3. </p>

<p>First, contributions fall below the efficiency 
benchmark, and exhibit a declining trend, even in 
Delegation. Second, the elected delegates mostly 
assign equal contributions within their groups. 
This section offers a set of empirical analyses 
from the elections and from ranking data that 
allow for a better understanding of our main 
findings from Section IV.B. 
We start by presenting summary statistics 
from the very first election in Table 4. Despite 
the obvious fact that a lot of subjects assign the 
most favorable rank to themselves, the majority 
of groups still favor high contributors as their del-
egates. In particular, 55.6% of the most preferred 
ranks go to the high contributor in the group, 
whereas only 18.1% go to the low contributor. As 
a result, high contributors receive the most favor-
able ranks (the lowest average) and are elected 
most frequently (in 19 out of 24 groups). 10 
Table 5 reports the regression analysis for later 
elections, that is, the five elections in Part 4 of 
the experiment excluding the very first. In the first 
election, the only information voters could condi-
tion their ranking on is the average contributions 
of all players in Part 3. In later elections, however, 
the voters have extra information on the perfor-
mance of the incumbent delegate and the previous 
group-level contributions of the other two groups. 
The results from Table 5 indicate that there 
is significant path dependency to elect the 
incumbent delegate (β 1 ). The coefficient β 5 
is significantly negative, which means that 
the incumbent delegate is less likely to be re-
elected, the more the group she represented was </p>

<p>10. The regression analysis in Table B3 in Appendix S1 
further supports this result: the outcome of the first election 
depends on choices of a subject in (each of) the three previous 
parts. In all the specifications, the high contributor is more 
likely to be elected, regardless of whether we control for 
cooperative or distributive preferences (based on Parts 1 and 
2) or not. Since results from Parts 1 and 2 are not public, this 
is just because of the correlation of behavior across the parts 
at the individual level. </p>

<p>exploited by the other groups in the society 
during her tenure. Moreover, the more delegates 
exploit both of their own group members during 
their tenure, the less likely they will be re-elected 
(β 9 ). 11 Result 3 summarizes the main findings. </p>

<p>RESULT 3. Hypothesis 1(c) is rejected, while 
predictions from inequity-aversion models are 
partly supported: Voters significantly prefer pro-
social delegates (high contributors in Part 3) in 
the first election, In later elections, incumbent 
delegates have a much higher chance to be re-
elected. However, their chances decrease, (i) the 
more the average contributions of their groups 
exceed that of the society's average, and (ii) the 
higher contribution levels they choose for the 
other two group members compared to their own 
contributions (i.e., how fair the choices are within 
the group). </p>

<p>The above findings are consistent with what 
we observe as the stylized behavior of the elected 
delegates. In particular, group members use elec-
tions as a device to deselect "unsuccessful" del-
egates, that is, if the delegate was exploited by 
other groups. They also refrain to re-elect dele-
gates who act selfishly. In response, the elected 
delegates assign equal contributions for all mem-
bers within their groups. Moreover, they try not to 
over-contribute compared to the two other groups 
within the society. The latter motive leads to the 
decaying trend in contributions that was surpris-
ing at first sight because it is at odds with most 
theoretical predictions. </p>

<p>Ranking of Delegates. Individual ranking behav-
ior in the course of the election provides a 
more detailed picture of the election. We employ 
ordered logit regressions to study the determi-
nants of the ranks that voters assign to different 
candidates. Similarly to the previous sub-section, 
we run regressions separately for the first election 
and the later ones, since ranking behavior might 
be different if the interaction has a history, which 
is true from the second election onwards. 
The aggregated ranking behavior in later 
periods is most easily described when we dis-
tinguish again between high, middle, and low 
contributors, based on the behavior of group 
members in Part 3 of the experiment. Table 6 
provides the results of regressions, with voter 
i's rank assigned to candidate j. Pooling all 
data together suggests that voters have a strong </p>

<p>11. All results remain robust if we only consider the final 
election period (see Table B4 in Appendix S1). </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 5 
Election Analysis in Later Periods (Probit Model) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: Whether a 
Subject Is Elected (1 = yes) 
Model 1 
Model 2 
Model 3 
Model 4 </p>

<p>β 1 : Incumbent delegate (=1, if yes) 
2.345 *** 
2.345 *** 
2.335 *** 
2.401 *** 
(0.575) 
(0.574) 
(0.580) 
(0.591) 
β 2 : Part 3 rank within group 
−0.086 
−0.085 
−0.077 
−0.049 
(0.149) 
(0.144) 
(0.152) 
(0.151) 
β 3 : Incumbent delegate × Part 3 rank within 
group </p>

<p>−0.277 
−0.277 
−0.275 
−0.317 * 
(0.196) 
(0.197) 
(0.195) 
(0.192) 
β 4 : Positive deviation from super-group 
average </p>

<p>0.123 
0.123 
0.106 
0.116 
(0.082) 
(0.084) 
(0.077) 
(0.082) 
β 5 : Incumbent delegate × Positive deviation 
from the super-group average </p>

<p>−0.372 * 
−0.373 * 
−0.349 * 
−0.370 * 
(0.194) 
(0.200) 
(0.184) 
(0.192) 
β 6 : Negative deviation from the super-group 
average </p>

<p>0.076 
0.076 
0.081 
0.073 
(0.082) 
(0.082) 
(0.085) 
(0.088) 
β 7 : Incumbent delegate × Negative deviation 
from the super-group average </p>

<p>−0.160 
−0.160 
−0.159 
−0.155 
(0.185) 
(0.185) 
(0.184) 
(0.187) 
β 8 : Average extent of exploiting both 
0.051 *** 
0.051 *** 
0.055 *** 
0.065 *** 
(0.017) 
(0.017) 
(0.017) 
(0.019) 
β 9 : Incumbent delegate × Average extent of 
exploiting both </p>

<p>−0.754 *** 
−0.754 *** 
−0.783 *** 
−0.802 *** 
(0.133) 
(0.131) 
(0.141) 
(0.160) 
β 10: Re-election period (1-5) 
0.010 
0.010 
0.006 
0.008 
(0.011) 
(0.011) 
(0.012) 
(0.012) 
β 11 : Constant 
−1.007 *** 
−1.009 *** 
−1.039 *** 
−1.043 *** 
(0.347) 
(0.356) 
(0.364) 
(0.393) 
Additional controls 
None 
Part 1, unconditional 
contribution </p>

<p>Part 1, cooperative 
preferences </p>

<p>Part 2, distributive 
preferences 
Log-likelihood 
−173.87 
−173.87 
−172.57 
−171.88 
N 
360 
360 
360 
350 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors (clustered at the subgroup level) are reported in parentheses. In particular, the variable 
"Incumbent delegate" is a dummy variable equal to 1 if this subject was the previous delegate in the last three periods. "Part 3 rank 
within group" captures the subject's rank in levels of cooperation from Part 3 (low rank means a higher level of cooperativeness). 
"Positive (Negative) deviation from the super-group average" measures the amount the group average contributions exceed 
(fall short of) that of the super-group average in the past three periods. The variable "Incumbent delegate × Positive (Negative) 
deviation from the super-group average" captures the interaction term between these two variables. The variable "Average extent 
of exploiting both" measures the contribution difference between the delegate and the average of the other two members in the 
past three periods (only if the delegate exploited the other two members). "Re-election period" takes the value 1-5 as there are 
six elections altogether in Part 4 (and election 1 is omitted). In different specifications, we add the choices of a subject in previous 
parts of the experiment as additional controls. We do not report marginal effects instead of regression coefficients, because the 
former make little sense for interaction terms. 
* p &lt; .1, ** p &lt; .05, *** p &lt; .01. </p>

<p>preference for self-promotion, that is, to rank 
themselves significantly more favorably than 
others (β 10 ). However, if we break down the 
voters based on their contributions in Part 3, the 
ranking patterns vary substantially. The ranking 
patterns of the high contribution voters are highly 
consistent with the election outcomes. Namely, 
voters assign more favorable ranks to the incum-
bent delegate (β 1 ), and less favorable ranks to 
low contributors in Part 3 (β 2 ), especially if this 
low contributor is the incumbent delegate (β 3 ). 
Negative ranking consequences for the candidate 
are, furthermore, due to contributing more than 
the super-group average (a higher rank to the 
incumbent captured by β 5 and a lower rank to 
other candidates by β 4 , or by forcing the other 
two members to contribute more than oneself 
in the previous periods [a significantly positive </p>

<p>effect on the rank to other candidates by β 8 ]). 
Interestingly, there is lack of intention to seek 
for other candidates if the incumbent delegate 
under-contributes compared to other groups. The 
ranking patterns for middle-and low-contribution 
voters are less robust. Their idiosyncratic ranking 
pattern might cancel out during the aggregation 
process, leading high-contribution voters to win 
the election. The only consistent pattern in rank-
ing is that they move away from delegates who 
exploited the two other group members (β 8 and 
β 9 ). Result 4 summarizes the findings from our 
analysis. 12 </p>

<p>12. Not surprisingly, the ranking pattern of the first period 
is highly consistent with the voting outcome: Voters have 
a strong preference to vote for themselves. However, after 
controlling for that, high contributors are the most preferred 
candidates. Table B5 in Appendix S1 provides the regression 
results. </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>TABLE 6 
Ranking Analysis in Later Elections (Ordered Logit Model) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: Voter i's 
Rank to Candidate j </p>

<p>High 
Contributor </p>

<p>Middle 
Contributor </p>

<p>Low 
Contributor </p>

<p>Aggregate 
Data </p>

<p>β 1 : Incumbent delegate (=1, if yes) 
−4.374 *** 
0.812 
−1.618 
−1.308 ** 
(1.163) 
(0.723) 
(1.135) 
(0.532) 
β 2 : Part 3 candidate's rank within group 
1.323 *** 
0.638 ** 
−1.268 *** 
0.239 
(0.373) 
(0.282) 
(0.343) 
(0.173) 
β 3 : Incumbent delegate × Part 3 candidate's 
rank within group </p>

<p>1.262 *** 
−0.894 ** 
0.497 
0.145 
(0.443) 
(0.433) 
(0.387) 
(0.211) 
β 4 : Positive deviation from super-group 
average </p>

<p>−0.169 * 
−0.139 
0.189 
−0.031 
(0.093) 
(0.136) 
(0.156) 
(0.078) 
β 5 : Incumbent delegate × Positive deviation 
from super-group average </p>

<p>0.783 *** 
0.232 
−0.498 
0.120 
(0.296) 
(0.353) 
(0.490) 
(0.225) 
β 6 : Negative deviation from the super-group 
average </p>

<p>−0.099 
0.099 * 
−0.004 
0.020 
(0.088) 
(0.052) 
(0.099) 
(0.045) 
β 7 : Incumbent delegate × Negative deviation 
from super-group average </p>

<p>0.316 
−0.221 
−0.110 
−0.060 
(0.271) 
(0.172) 
(0.270) 
(0.144) 
β 8 : Average extent of exploiting both 
−0.043 *** 
−0.028 
−0.030 
−0.035 
(0.016) 
(0.020) 
(0.030) 
(0.024) 
β 9 : Incumbent delegate × Average extent of 
exploiting both </p>

<p>0.608 
0.207 ** 
0.002 
0.105 
(0.676) 
(0.087) 
(0.106) 
(0.087) 
β 10 : Candidate is the voter herself (=1, if 
yes) </p>

<p>-
-
-
−1.965 *** 
(0.295) 
β 11 : Re-election period 
−0.034 
0.030 
−0.025 
−0.015 
(0.026) 
(0.021) 
(0.018) 
(0.009) 
Log-likelihood 
−300.69 
−391.09 
−340.93 
−1033.39 
No. of observations 
360 
375 
345 
1.180 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors (clustered at each voter) are reported in parentheses. The variables "Incumbent delegate," 
"Part 3 candidate's rank within group," and "Candidate is the voter herself" are referring to the candidates. All other variables 
here are the same as in Table 5. We do not report marginal effects instead of regression coefficients because the former make 
little sense for interaction terms. 
* p &lt; .1, ** p &lt; .05, *** p &lt; .01. </p>

<p>RESULT 4. Voters unambiguously assign 
favorable ranks to high contributors in the first 
election. In later elections, the ranking pattern 
of the high contribution voters is in line with the 
aggregated election outcome described in Result 
3. Delegates who over-contribute or exploit 
the two other group members are consistently 
deselected. </p>

<p>D. Contribution Dynamics and Preference 
Heterogeneity </p>

<p>Figure 2 gives a descriptive overview of con-
tributions over time by each of the three groups in 
a super-group. The abbreviations on top of each 
panel (Bx, Dx) indicate the super-group ID num-
bers in our two treatments (B for Baseline and D 
for Delegation). 
There are stark differences between the Base-
line and the Delegation treatments in terms of 
the dynamics. In Baseline, most super-groups 
quickly converge to zero contributions after 
three to four periods of interaction. The dynam-
ics in Delegation is much more heterogeneous. </p>

<p>Figure 2 suggests that very few delegates initially 
start with full cooperation (two groups in D5 and 
one group in D7). Most of them contribute cau-
tiously (i.e., about half of the group endowment) 
supposedly to gauge the inclination to cooperate 
by the other two delegates in the society. The del-
egates in some super-groups (such as D3, D7 and 
to a lesser extent D8) manage to coordinate and 
sustain a certain cooperation level throughout 
Part 4 (56% for D3, 58% for D7, and 54.4% for 
D8). Some other super-groups (such as D1, D2, 
and D4) exhibit a lot of fluctuations and a lower 
overall cooperation level (36.0% for D1, 31% for 
D2, and 25% for D4). Only one super-group con-
sistently contributes more than the benchmark 
based on self-regarding preferences (76.5% for 
D5). Results from a hierarchical cluster analysis 
confirm that the contribution dynamics of the 
eight super-groups can be divided into three 
categories: successful (D5), failed (D1, D2, D4), 
and mixed (D3, D6, D7, D8). 
What causes electoral delegation to perform 
worse in some super-groups than in others? One </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 
Contribution Dynamics of Each Super-group in Parts 3 and 4 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 </p>

<p>0 
50 100 </p>

<p>1 
9 
17 
25 
1 
9 
17 
25 </p>

<p>1 
9 
17 
25 
1 
9 
17 </p>

<p>D1 
D2 
D3 
D4 </p>

<p>D5 
D6 
D7 
D8 </p>

<p>B1 
B2 
B3 
B4 </p>

<p>B5 
B6 </p>

<p>Group 1 
Group 2 
Group 3 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Period </p>

<p>Percentage of endowment </p>

<p>Note: The letters combined with numbers in each panel represent treatment and super-group number (B stands for Baseline 
and D stands for Delegation). </p>

<p>common feature of the three failed super-groups 
is that contributions of some groups fall to a 
very low level (usually 0) in early periods. In 
the first three periods, the average contributions 
of the three failed super-groups are already sig-
nificantly lower than those in other super-groups 
(8.75 vs. 13.64, p &lt; .05). Another feature is that 
failed super-groups exhibit a steady downward 
sloping trend in contributions, while the more 
successful super-groups are better at coordinat-
ing at a certain positive contribution level. Based 
on these features, we conjecture that some dele-
gates in failed super-groups attempt to free ride 
on the other groups in the initial periods, trig-
gering an immediate response to decrease contri-
butions by other group delegates in subsequent 
periods, which is in contrast to standard theoret-
ical predictions if it happens below the threshold 
of the 66.7% contribution level. 
To provide more rigorous evidence, we ana-
lyze contribution dynamics separately for failed </p>

<p>and other super-groups. Results of the regression 
models are reported in Table B7 in Appendix S1. 
The contribution dynamics in failed super-groups 
exhibit two distinctive features from those of 
other super-groups. First, some delegates attempt 
to exploit their fellow group members. While 
the delegates lower contributions for everyone, 
the magnitude of the decrease is higher for her-
self than for the other two members within her 
group. Delegates in other super-groups, on the 
other hand, treat their fellow group members 
equally. Second, while delegates in other super-
groups increase contributions significantly when 
they learn that they have under-contributed com-
pared to the others, delegates in failed super-
groups are insensitive in this respect. Despite the 
fact that contribution dynamics differ between 
failed and other super-groups, there are no sys-
tematically different patterns in terms of elec-
tions. Table B8 in Appendix S1 reports random-
effect Probit models that assess this issue and </p>

<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>



<p>TABLE 7 
Average Characteristics of Failed and Other Super-groups </p>

<p>Characteristics of Members within a Super-group </p>

<p>Failed Super-groups 
(1, 2, 4) </p>

<p>Other Super-groups 
(3, 5, 6, 7, 8) </p>

<p>Part 3: Average contributions (p = .15) 
5.52 
8.14 
Part 1: Unconditional contributions (p = .61) 
7.37 
8.31 
Part 1: Percentage of free-riders (p = .11) 
22.22 (6/27) 
8.89 (4/45) 
Part 2: Percentage of type "Exploit both members" (p = .27) 
66.67 (18/27) 
53.33 (24/45) </p>

<p>Note: The tests comparing percentages are two-sided proportional test. Chi-squared tests and Fisher's exact tests yield very 
similar results. </p>

<p>confirm the conclusion. Result 5 summarizes our 
main findings. </p>

<p>RESULT 5. Heterogeneity between super-
groups in terms of success lies in contribution 
dynamics combined with the equal contribu-
tion norm rather than the way delegates are 
elected. </p>

<p>One possible explanation could be that, 
as long as a previous delegate from a failed 
super-group protects her group members from 
being exploited by other groups and does not 
exploit fellow group members, her performance 
is viewed as satisfactory, and hence she is re-
elected. If this is true, the failed super-groups 
might elect relatively more defensive and con-
servative delegates compared to their successful 
counterparts. According to Fischbacher and  Gächter (2010), the observed dynamics of 
contributions in a public goods game could 
be influenced by heterogeneity in preferences 
or beliefs. Can we attribute the observed het-
erogeneity in contribution dynamics in our 
data to the composition regarding cooperative/ 
distributive preferences of the players in these 
super-groups? Table 7 compares cooperative and 
distributive preferences of members in failed and 
in other (successful and mixed) super-groups. 
Indeed, failed super-groups consist of a higher 
fraction of noncooperators, that is, the average 
unconditional contribution of their members 
is lower in both Part 1 and Part 3. A higher 
percentage of players in those three super-groups 
are classified as free riders (according to the clas-
sification criteria in Fischbacher, Gächter, and  Fehr 2001), and they also fully free ride on the 
other two members in the one-shot distribution 
decision in Part 2. Nevertheless, none of the com-
parisons is statistically significant. While this 
could be caused by the limited number of obser-
vations, it also suggests that the composition in </p>

<p>terms of cooperative and distributive preferences 
alone cannot fully account for super-group 
heterogeneity in performance. </p>

<p>V. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This study examines the effects of electoral 
delegation in global public goods provision, with 
a focus on the strategic interactions between vot-
ers and the elected delegates. Our results sug-
gest that compared to a nonhierarchical situation, 
electoral delegation significantly increases inter-
group cooperation levels. Moreover, the elec-
tion process effectively prevents voters to be 
massively exploited by the delegates. Never-
theless, the actual levels of contribution with 
delegation fall significantly short of the the-
oretical predictions, under the assumption of 
selfish preferences. Interestingly, we observe a 
decrease in cooperation levels over time, in con-
trast to theoretical predictions based on selfish 
preferences and on most parameter combina-
tions for inequity-averse preferences. The reason 
potentially lies in the heterogeneity in cooper-
ative attitudes across groups, combined with a 
strong motive among voters for equal contribu-
tions within the group. 
It seems that the combination of (1) delegation 
based on (re)-elections and (2) heterogeneity in 
other-regarding preferences leads to an ineffi-
ciency that we call P-inefficiency, because it 
could be related to the polycentric nature of the 
public good provision and management. Our data 
indicate that both ingredients-delegation based 
on elections (or more generally: reputational con-
cerns) and heterogeneity across different groups 
in terms of other-regarding preferences-might 
be necessary for existence of the P-inefficiency. 
As one of the referees correctly points out, 
we do not necessarily need heterogeneity in 
other-regarding preferences. Some noise in the 
contribution of strongly inequity averse players </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>(for instance, as a consequence of heterogeneous 
beliefs regarding the cooperation levels of others) 
can create a coordination problem and, poten-
tially, dwindling contribution levels over time. 
Such reasoning implies that delegation-how 
we implemented it-solves the intragroup social 
dilemma, but not the intergroup social dilemma. 
Still, the explanation requires some underlying 
heterogeneity, but not necessarily in preferences. 
Notice that the level of the inefficiency is not 
negligible. For our parameters, towards the end 
of the interaction with delegation, it amounts 
to almost half of the maximal efficiency level 
implied by the standard solution. Intuitively, 
group members neither want to be exploited by 
their delegates nor by other groups in the society. 
As a consequence, if the level of contributions 
across groups is different, we observe a simi-
lar, albeit slower, decay of contribution levels 
as in the standard linear public goods game. 
With delegation, groups cannot coordinate on 
the Pareto-optimal outcome, even in a repeated 
interaction. Interestingly, when levels of coop-
eration decay over time, there does not seem 
to be an increase in the number of exploitation 
instances in which group members are exploited 
by their delegates. Rather, contribution levels get 
stuck on low levels. 
On a more general account, we provide evi-
dence for a setup in which the combination of 
reputational concerns and other-regarding prefer-
ences lead to potential inefficiencies. Angelova, 
Güth, and Kocher (2012) study a completely 
different setup-a principal agent game with 
partly incomplete contracts in which the principal 
employs a short-term agent and a long-term agent 
alongside each other, where only the latter has 
reputational concerns-but also observe a sim-
ilar kind of inefficiency whose existence requires 
a certain level of other-regarding preferences. 
Additionally, the results of our experiment 
are able to offer insights on the general trade-
off regarding the appropriate characteristics of 
representatives in delegation problems: On the 
one hand, since no one wants to be exploited 
by other groups, voters would like to be rep-
resented by smart and strategic delegates (lead-
ers). On the other hand, voters face the risk 
that such a delegate (leader) may be opportunis-
tic and thus may favor herself or small interest 
groups at the cost of the majority. Such sorts 
of dilemmas in selecting the best candidate do 
not only exist in politics, but also in corpora-
tions, organizations, and communities, where the 
(elected) delegate has some discretionary power </p>

<p>over the distribution of benefits and costs. More 
research in a similar spirit seems warranted as 
a perquisite for better understanding delegation 
decisions and leadership. 
The results of this study imply that the 
efficiency effects of delegation mechanisms 
in organizing global public good provision 
could be problematic. Albeit oversimplified, 
this conclusion is consistent with the fact that 
many self-enforcing international environmental 
agreements (such as the Kyoto protocol) seem 
to fail in improving efficiency substantially over 
the noncooperative outcome in the delegation 
setting. Other results suggest that a big obstacle 
to such international cooperation is the lack of 
effective enforcement and monitoring power at 
the global level. The P-inefficiency seems to be 
an additional obstacle that has been overlooked 
so far. Future work is needed to explore issues 
such as supra-national linkages to reduce the 
strategic uncertainty in delegates' interactions 
(Sandler 1998) and to confirm existence of 
the P-inefficiency in similar environments, the 
conditions under which it is relevant, and the 
external validity of our results. Statements of 
head of states or envoys like the ones in climate 
negotiations that explicitly formulate conditional 
offers for the level of climate gas emission reduc-
tions make us confident that our setup is also 
relevant for the real world, albeit being stylized. </p>



<p>KOCHER, TAN &amp; YU: PROVIDING GLOBAL PUBLIC GOODS </p>





<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Appendix S1. Experimental Instructions and Additional 
Analyses. </p>

</text></tei>