<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10258-013-0091-1" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract This paper investigates changes in the dynamics of linkages between 
selected national stock markets during the period 1995-2009. The analysis focuses 
on the possible effects of globalization and differences between crisis and non-crisis 
periods. We model the dynamics of dependencies between the series of daily returns 
on selected stock indices over different time periods, and compare strength of the 
linkages. Our tools are dynamic copula models and a formal sequential testing pro-
cedure based on the model confidence set methodology. We consider two types of 
dependencies: regular dependence measured by means of the conditional Spearman's 
rho, and dependencies in extremes quantified by the conditional tail dependence coef-
ficients. The main result consists of a collection of rankings created for the considered 
subperiods, which show how the mean level of strength of the dependencies have 
been changing in time. The rankings obtained for Spearman's rho and tail dependen-
cies differ, which allows us to distinguish between the results of crises and the effect 
of globalization. </p>

<p>In the paper, we look for the effects of globalization and crises on the pattern of link-
ages in global stock market by modeling the conditional dependencies between the 
series of daily returns on selected stock indices during various periods. The depen-
dencies in each period are modeled using a regime-switching copula model. Two 
types of dependencies are considered: regular dependence measured by means of the 
conditional Spearman's rho, and dependencies in extremes quantified by the condi-
tional tail dependence coefficients. The main result is a collection of rankings created 
for the considered subperiods, which show how the average level of strength of the 
dependencies have been changing in time. The rankings obtained for Spearman's rho 
and tail dependencies differ, which allows us to distinguish between the results of 
crises and the effect of globalization. 
The main motivation for the analysis originates from a common opinion explain-
ing why the web of inter-market linkages become more dense and stronger. It states 
that this is because financial capital can now move very quickly from one part of the 
world into another and any information reaches investors in all the world almost in 
the same time when it appears. 
The increase of dependencies influences world economies and markets creating 
new investment possibilities but, at the same time, new risks. Because of the impor-
tance of this process for risk management and macroeconomic policies, the attempts 
to describe and explain it form a significant part of research in many areas of finance. 
Among the first empirical papers dealing with this subject, the papers by Levy and  Sarnat (1970) and Solnik (1974) analyzing correlations across national markets and 
international portfolio diversification should be mentioned. Many empirical research 
papers concerning the problem of market linkages arose in the 1990s (for instance, 
Ammer and Mei (1996), Campbell and Hamao (1992), and Pindick and Rotemberg  (1993)). The sequence of financial crises that occurred at the end of the 20th century 
gave impact to intensive work on the subject. For instance, in 2003 a special issue 
of Journal of Economics and Business edited by Bailey and Choi (2003) was dedi-
cated to the international market linkages analysis focused on the degree of financial 
and economic integration. The crisis of 2007-2009 further intensified the attempts 
to describe and explain the mechanism of the dependencies in global financial 
market. 
In the wide literature on the subject many theoretical papers exist that address 
the problem of the strengthening of market dependencies and the related problem 
of propagation of shocks that arise in one country and spread to some other ones. 
The papers consider diverse approaches and use variety of methodologies. The broad 
set of theories concerning the topic can be generally divided into two groups: crisis-
contingent and non-crisis-contingent theories (Forbes and Rigobon 2002; Gallo and  Velucchi 2009). The former explain whether cross-market linkages increase after a 
shock, whereas the latter assume that transmission mechanisms are always the same 
and that cross-market linkages do not increase after a shock. In this paper, we are 
not concerned with studying the related phenomena of contagion, interdependence or 
spillover (see, for example, Gallo and Otranto 2008) but just investigate whether and 
to what extent the dynamics of the linkages changes. </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>The question about the best way to describe the dependencies between different 
markets is still open. For a long time the most common method applied to mea-
sure the linkages was correlation (e.g., Hamao et al. 1990; Karolyi and Stulz 1996). 
Next, multivariate GARCH models were used to describe the time-varying condi-
tional correlations of global equity returns (see e.g. Capiello et al. 2006). There also 
exist papers using cointegration as a tool to examine the long-run equilibrium rela-
tionships between national capital markets (Bachman et al. 1996; Gérard et al. 2003). 
Another useful tool applied recently to describe inter-market dependencies are cop-
ulas (Jondeau and Rockinger 2006; Bartram et al. 2007; Rodriguez 2007; Chen and  Poon 2007; Okimoto 2008; Chollete et al. 2009; Markwat et al. 2009). 
In the presented research we try to answer the following questions: Can the 
globalization effect be measured by means of econometric tools? Do the results 
of measurement of the strength of market linkages indicate an increasing ten-
dency? Did the market linkages dynamics change during the crises periods? Did 
tail dependencies, especially lower tail dependence, become stronger when a crisis 
occurred? 
To answer these questions we need an econometric measure of dependencies that 
is robust to specific properties of financial return series. As it was mentioned before, 
classic studies on interdependencies between financial returns commonly use sim-
ple, dynamic or exceedance, correlation. However, outside the world of elliptical 
distributions using the linear correlation is not appropriate because of possibility of 
quite misleading inference (Embrechts et al. 2002; McNeil et al. 2005). To avoid 
such problems we use copulas as a tool to describe the pattern of connections. These 
functions have the property to join any kind of margins into a multivariate distribu-
tion function. An advantage of the copula approach is that it allows to separate the 
dependence structure from the marginal distributions. By means of copulas it is also 
possible to model tail behavior in the joint distribution, and different kinds of asym-
metry, what is of great importance in our investigation. However, in order to capture 
changes in the conditional dependence structure, the copula that describes it must 
be time varying. Time variation in the conditional copula was introduced in 2002 by 
Patton (2004, 2006), and it had the form of an ARMA-type process involving the 
dependence parameter of the copula and a function of return innovations. Another, 
alternative approach, which is also applied in the present paper, may be that the model 
includes a number of regimes that are switched according to a Markov chain, and 
different copulas prevail at particular regimes (Rodriguez 2007; Markwat et al. 2009;  Garcia and Tsafack 2011). 
The analysis presented in this paper focuses on the linkages between stock 
indices representing 11 countries and is based on the series of percentage loga-
rithmic daily returns. It is performed for 16 pairs of stock indices, 10 of which 
include the S&amp;P 500, and 6 the DAX. The dataset under scrutiny embrace quota-
tions from January 3, 1995 to December 11, 2009. The dynamics of market linkages 
is described using Spearman's rho and the coefficients of tail dependence. After 
estimation of the models and computing the sequences of the considered condi-
tional dependence measures we compare the strength of linkages in different periods 
using the Model Confidence Set methodology (Hansen et al. 2011) and create a 
set of rankings. This allows us to draw some conclusions about the impact of the </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>globalization process and financial crises on the pattern of dependencies in global 
financial market. </p>

<p>2 Regime-switching copula models </p>

<p>Modeling the dependencies between financial returns is a difficult task because of 
special properties of these series. Typical return series usually exhibit conditional het-
eroskedasticity, different types of asymmetries, and structural breaks, which strongly 
influence estimation results for models of the dependence structure. Moreover, the 
dynamics of dependencies can significantly change in time. For example, it is well 
documented in many studies that dependence between returns on different assets is 
usually stronger in bear markets than in bull markets (Ang and Bekaert 2002; Ang  and Chen 2002; Patton 2004). This example of asymmetric dependence in financial 
markets is of great importance for portfolio choice and risk management. The main 
problem connected with this phenomenon is, however, that from the theoretical point 
of view, the mentioned asymmetry cannot be produced by a statistical model for 
the returns that assumes an elliptical multivariate conditional distribution, and thus 
applying the linear correlation is not justified. An alternative concept that allows for 
modeling the dependence in general situation is copula. Roughly speaking, a bivari-
ate copula is a mapping C : [0, 1] × [01] → [0, 1] from the unit square into the unit 
interval which is a distribution function with standard uniform marginal distributions. 
Assume that (X,Y) is a 2-dimensional random vector with joint distribution H 
and marginal distributions F and G. Then, by a theorem by Sklar (1959), H can be 
written as 
H (x, y) = C(F (x), G(y)). 
(1) </p>

<p>If F and G are continuous then the function C is uniquely given by the formula </p>

<p>C(u, v) = H (F 
−1 (u), G 
−1 (v)), 
(2) </p>

<p>for u, v ∈ [0, 1], where F −1 (u) = inf{x : F (x) ≥ u}. In this case, C is called the 
copula of H or of (X,Y). Since the marginals and the dependence structure can be 
separated, it makes sense to interpret C as the dependence structure of the vector 
(X,Y). We refer to Patton (2009) and references therein for an overview of financial 
time series applications of copulas. There one can also find more information about 
advantages and limitations of copula-based modeling. 
The simplest copula is defined by C (u, v) = uv and it corresponds to 
independence of marginal distributions. 
In the empirical part of this paper we will also use the Gaussian and Joe-Clayton 
copulas. They are defined as follows: </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Gauss 
ρ </p>

<p>(u, v) = ρ ( 
−1 (u), 
−1 (v)), 
(3) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>(u, v) = 1−(1−([1−(1−u) 
κ ] 
−γ +[1−(1−v) 
κ ] 
−γ −1) 
−1/γ ) 
1/κ (4) </p>

<p>Here in (3), ρ denotes the distribution of a 2-dimensional standardized normal 
vector with the linear correlation coefficient ρ, and stands for the standard normal </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>distribution function. The parameters in the Joe-Clayton copula (4) are assumed to 
satisfy the conditions: κ ≥ 1, γ &gt; 0. For κ = 1, the Joe-Clayton copula becomes the 
Clayton copula C </p>

<p>Clayton 
γ </p>

<p>. In the limit case γ = 0, the Clayton copula approaches the 
independence copula C (Nelsen 2006). 
The density associated to an absolutely continuous copula C is a function c 
defined by </p>

<p>c(u, v) = 
∂ 2 C(u, v) 
∂u∂v 
. 
(5) </p>

<p>For an absolutely continuous random vector, the copula density c is related to its joint 
density function h by the following canonical representation: </p>

<p>h(x, y) = c(F (x), G(y))f (x)g(y), 
(6) </p>

<p>where F and G are the marginal distributions, and f and g are the marginal density 
functions. 
In the case of nonelliptical distributions, measures of dependence that are more 
appropriate than the linear correlation coefficient are provided by two important 
copula-based tools known as Kendall's tau and Spearman's rho (Embrechts et al.  2002). Since the dynamics of Spearman's rho is exploited in this paper, we recall a 
suitable definition. If (X,Y) is a random vector with marginal distribution functions F 
and G, then Spearman's rho for (X,Y) can be defined as </p>

<p>ρ S (X, Y ) = ρ(F (X), G(Y )) 
(7) </p>

<p>where ρ denotes the usual Pearson correlation. For continuous marginal distributions, 
Spearman's rho, ρ S (X, Y ), depends only on the copula C linking X and Y, and, in 
particular, it is given by the formula </p>

<p>ρ S (X, Y ) = ρ C = 12 </p>

<p>[0,1] 2 </p>

<p>C(u, v)dudv − 3 
( 8 ) </p>

<p>(Nelsen 2006). It follows from (8) that if a copula C is a mixture of copulas C 1 and 
C 2 : C = αC 1 + (1 − α)C 2 , 0 ≤ α ≤ 1, then </p>

<p>ρ C = αρ C 1 + (1 − α)ρ C 2 . 
(9) </p>

<p>For the Gaussian copula C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>, Spearman's rho equals </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>π arcsin </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 ρ, and for the 
Joe-Clayton copula it can be computed numerically using (8). 
A very important concept connected with copula, relevant to dependence in 
extreme values, is tail dependence. If X and Y are random variables with distribution 
functions F and G then the coefficient of upper tail dependence is defined as follows </p>

<p>λ U = lim q→1 − P (Y &gt; G 
−1 (q)|X &gt; F 
−1 (q)), 
(10) </p>

<p>provided a limit λ U ∈ [0, 1] exists. Analogously, the coefficient of lower tail 
dependence is defined as </p>

<p>λ L = lim q→0 + P (Y ≤ G 
−1 (q)|X ≤ F 
−1 (q)), 
(11) </p>

<p>provided that a limit λ L ∈ [0, 1] exists. If λ U ∈ (0, 1] (λ L ∈ (0, 1]), then X and 
Y are said to exhibit upper (lower) tail dependence. Upper (lower) tail dependence </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>quantifies the likelihood to observe a large (low) value of Y given a large (low) value 
of X. The coefficients of tail dependence depend only on the copula C of X and Y: </p>

<p>λ L = lim q→0 + 
C(q, q) 
q 
, 
(12) </p>

<p>λ U = lim q→0 +Ĉ 
(q, q) 
q 
, 
(13) </p>

<p>whereĈ(u, v) = u + v − 1 + C(1 − u, 1 − v). For the Gaussian copula it holds 
λ U = λ L = 0 (see Embrechts et al. 2002), meaning asymptotic independence in the 
tails. In the Joe-Clayton copula, λ U = 2 − 2 1/κ and λ L = 2 −1/γ for γ &gt; 0 (Patton  2006). Thus both upper and lower dependence can be nonzero, and, moreover, they 
can change freely of each other. 
Introduced by Patton (2004), the notion of conditional copula allows to apply cop-
ulas to modeling the joint distribution of r t conditional on information set t −1 , 
where r t = (r 1,t , r 2,t ) is a bivariate vector of financial returns. In this paper we 
consider the following general conditional copula model </p>

<p>r 1,t | t −1 ∼ F t (·), r 2,t | t −1 ∼ G t (·), 
(14) </p>

<p>r t | t −1 ∼ C t (F t (·), G t (·)| t −1 ), 
(15) </p>

<p>where the set t includes the up to time t information on the returns on both consid-
ered financial assets, and C t is the conditional copula linking the marginal conditional 
distributions. Further, we assume that </p>

<p>r t = µ t + y t , µ t = E(r t | t −1 ), 
(16) </p>

<p>y i,t = σ i,t ε i,t , σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i,t = var(r i,t | t −1 ), 
(17) </p>

<p>ε i,t ∼ iid Skew t (0, 1, ξ i , η i ), 
(18) </p>

<p>where Skew t (0, 1, ξ, η) denotes the standardized skewed Student t distribution with 
η &gt; 2 degrees of freedom, and skewness coefficient ξ &gt; 0 (Lambert and Laurent  2001). To the marginal return series r i,t , i = 1, 2, we fit ARMA-GARCH models 
with skewed Student's t distributions for the 1-dimensional innovations. 
When modeling the joint conditional distribution, the evolution of the conditional 
copula C t has to be specified. Usually (Patton 2004, 2006), the functional form of 
the conditional copula is fixed, but its parameters evolve through time. In this paper, 
however, an alternative approach is applied. Similarly to Garcia and Tsafack (2011), 
we assume that there are regimes where a fixed copula prevails, and they switch 
according to some homogeneous Markov chain. 
In a Markov-switching copula model (MSC model) we use for modeling the con-
ditional dependence between financial returns, the joint conditional distribution has 
the following form 
r t | t −1 ∼ C S t (F t (·), G t (·)| t −1 ), 
(19) </p>

<p>where S t is a homogeneous Markov chain with state space {1, 2}. Hence, the param-
eters of the applied MSC model are the parameters of the univariate models for the 
marginal distributions (ARMA-GARCH with the standardized skewed Student's t </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>distributions for the innovations), the parameters of the copulas C 1 and C 2 , and the 
transition probabilities </p>

<p>p 11 = P (S t = 1|S t −1 = 1), p 22 = P (S t = 2|S t −1 = 2) 
(20) </p>

<p>of the Markov chain. 
The parameters of the MSC model were estimated by the maximum likeli-
hood method. The main by-product of the estimation are the predicted probabilities 
P (S t = j | t −1 ), j = 1, 2. They are calculated by means of Hamilton's filter 
(Hamilton 1994): </p>

<p>P (S t = j | t −1 ) = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>p ij P (S t −1 = i| t −1 ), 
(21) </p>

<p>P (S t = j | t ) = 
c j (u t |S t = j, t −1 )P (S t = j | t −1 ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>c i (u t |S t = i, t −1 )P (S t = i| t −1 ) </p>

<p>, 
(22) </p>

<p>where p 12 = P (S t = 2|S t −1 = 1) = 1 − p 11 , p 21 = P (S t = 1|S t −1 = 2) = 
1 − p 22 , u t = (u 1,t , u 2,t ), </p>

<p>u 1,t = F t (r 1,t ), u 2,t = G t (r 2,t ), 
(23) </p>

<p>and c j (·|S t = j, t −1 ) is the density of the conditional copula coupling the condi-
tional marginal distributions in regime j. By the arguments of Hamilton (1994) and 
(6), the maximized log-likelihood function is of the form </p>

<p>L = </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =1 </p>

<p>ln </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎝ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>j =1 </p>

<p>c j (u t |S t = j, t −1 ; θ)P (S t = j | t −1 ; θ) </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎠ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =1 </p>

<p>ln f t (r 1,t | t −1 ; θ 1 ) + </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =1 </p>

<p>ln g t (r 2,t | t −1 ; θ 2 ) , 
(24) </p>

<p>where f t and g t are the density functions corresponding to F t and G t , fitted using 
ARMA-GARCH models. </p>

<p>3 The model confidence set </p>

<p>The Model Confidence Set (MCS) methodology was originally introduced by Hansen  et al. (2003) in order to improve choosing the best volatility forecasting models from 
a larger set. The objective of this approach is to determine the set M 
 *  that consists 
of the best models from some collection M 
0 . Given a significance level α, the MCS </p>

<p>procedure produces a subsetM </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1−α of M 
0 that contains M 
 *  with confidence level </p>

<p>1 − α. Thus the MCS resembles a confidence interval for a parameter. In fact, M </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>can be a finite set of objects indexed by i = 1, . . . , m 0 and evaluated in terms of a 
loss function that assigns to the object i in period t the loss L i,t , t = 1, . . . , n. When 
one defines the relative performance variables as d ij,t ≡ L i,t − L j,t for i, j ∈ M </p>

<p>0 </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>and assumes that the mean μ ij ≡ E(d ij,t ) is finite and does not depend on t, then the 
set of superior objects is defined by </p>

<p>M 
 *  ≡ i ∈ M 
0 : μ ij ≤ 0 for all j ∈ M 
0 . 
(25) </p>

<p>In order to determine M 
 *  , one tests the hypotheses of the form </p>

<p>H 0,M : μ ij = 0 for all i, j ∈ M, </p>

<p>where M ⊂ M 
0 . The alternative hypothesis, μ ij = 0 for some i, j ∈ M, is 
denoted by H A,M . The MCS procedure is based on an equivalence test δ M that tests 
the hypothesis H 0,M for any M ⊂ M 
0 , and an elimination rule e M that identifies 
the object of M that is to be removed from M when H 0,M is rejected. The MCS 
algorithm proposed by Hansen et al. (2003) is as follows: </p>

<p>Step 0: Set M = M 
0 . 
Step 1: Test H 0,M using δ M at significance level α. 
Step 2: If H 0,M is not rejected define,M </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1−α = M, otherwise use e M to 
eliminate an object from M and repeat the procedure from Step 1. </p>

<p>It is proved in Hansen et al. (2011) that under some standard requirements for the 
equivalence test and the elimination rule, it holds that </p>

<p>lim inf n→∞ P M 
 *  ⊂M </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1−α ≥ 1 − α, 
(26) </p>

<p>lim n→∞ P i ∈M </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1−α = 0 for all i / 
∈ M 
 *  , 
(27) </p>

<p>lim n→∞ P M 
 *  =M </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1−α = 1 if M 
 *  is a singleton. 
(28) </p>

<p>If P H 0 ,M i denotes the p-value associated with the null hypothesis H 0,M i (with con-
vention that P H 0 ,M m 0 = 1) then the MCS p-value for model e M j ∈ M 0 is defined 
asp e M j ≡ max i≤j P H 0 ,M i . 
It is shown in Hansen et al. (2011) that H 0,M can be tested using traditional 
quadratic-form statistics or multiple t-statistics. The latter approach has an advan-
tage that it simplifies the construction of an elimination rule that satisfies the notion 
of coherency formulated in Hansen et al. (2011). We focus on the t-statistic T R,M 
because we apply it in this paper. It is defined as </p>

<p>T R,M = max </p>

<p>i,j ∈M </p>

<p>|t ij |, 
(29) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>t ij =d </p>

<p>ij </p>

<p>v ar d ij </p>

<p>for i, j ∈ M, 
(30) </p>

<p>andd ij = n −1 n 
t =1 d ij,t . The asymptotic distribution of the statistic T R,M is 
nonstandard but it can be estimated with bootstrap methods. The bootstrap imple-
mentation of the MCS procedure involving this statistic is described in Appendix B 
in the paper by Hansen et al. (2003). For generating B resamples the block bootstrap </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>is used. The estimated bootstrap distribution of T R,M , under the null hypothesis, is 
given by the empirical distribution of </p>

<p>T </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>b,R = max </p>

<p>i,j ∈M </p>

<p>d  *  
b,ij −d ij </p>

<p>v ar d ij </p>

<p>, 
(31) </p>

<p>whered  *  
b,ij = </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t =1 d ij,τ b t is the bootstrap resample average, andv ar d ij = </p>

<p>1 
B </p>

<p>B 
b=1 </p>

<p>d  *  
b,ij −d ij </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. The p-value of H 0,M is given by </p>

<p>P H 0,M = 
1 
B </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>b=1 </p>

<p>1 T </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>b,R &gt; T R,M . 
(32) </p>

<p>It should be mentioned here that even though the MCS methodology was origi-
nally designed to select the best volatility forecasting models it can also be applied 
in any situation where one want to compare the means of two or more popula-
tions. We use the MCS procedure to establish rankings of subperiods with respect 
to the strength of linkages between the investigated stock markets calculated by the 
discussed dependence measures. </p>

<p>4 The data </p>

<p>The analysis is performed for 16 pairs of stock market indices. We consider five 
European indices (FTSE, DAX, CAC 40, the Russian RTS, and the Polish WIG20), 
four Asian (the NIKKEI 225, the South Korean KOSPI, the Singaporean STI, and 
the Indian BSE 30), the Brazilian BOVESPA, and the S&amp;P 500. In fact, we analyze 
only the dependencies between the S&amp;P 500 and all the other indices, and between 
the DAX and the FTSE, WIG20, RTS, NIKKEI, BSE 30 and KOSPI. The quota-
tion series were obtained from the service Stooq. The period under scrutiny is from 
January 3, 1995 to December 11, 2009.  Since the patterns of non-trading days in national stock markets differ, for the pur-
pose of modeling the dependencies, the dates of observations for the considered pairs 
of indices were checked and observations not corresponding to ones in the other index 
quotation series were removed. As the result, the number of observations changes 
from 3404 to 3732, depending on the pair of indices. The time series under scrutiny 
are percentage logarithmic daily returns calculated by the formula </p>

<p>r t = 100(ln P t − ln P t −1 ), 
(33) </p>

<p>where P t denotes the closing index value on day t. 
Since we use international daily data, an issue of non-synchronous trading arises. 
None of the existing attempts to tackle this difficulty is fully satisfactory. In partic-
ular, using weekly data only seemingly solves the problem and, moreover, discards 
important information. For this reason, we adopt here the following approach. Prior 
to modeling, we compared by means of Pearson's correlation coefficient the strength 
of concurrent and one day lagged dependence between the components of pairs of </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary statistics for daily log returns (in %) for the period from January 2, 1995 to December 
11, 2009 </p>

<p>Index 
Mean 
Maximum 
Minimum 
Stand. Dev. 
Skewness 
Kurtosis </p>

<p>BOVESPA 
0.0783 
28.832 
−17.208 
2.4278 
0.4414 
14.916 </p>

<p>BSE 30 
0.0414 
15.99 
−17.184 
1.7992 
−0.4047 
10.4106 </p>

<p>CAC 40 
0.0190 
10.595 
−9.4715 
1.5051 
−0.0101 
7.7121 </p>

<p>DAX 
0.0276 
10.797 
−9.791 
1.5877 
−0.0635 
10.9230 </p>

<p>FTSE 
0.0146 
9.3843 
−9.2656 
1.2418 
−0.0939 
9.0418 </p>

<p>KOSPI 
0.0137 
11.284 
−16.115 
2.0693 
−0.2841 
7.5669 </p>

<p>NIKKEI 
−0.0187 
13.235 
−12.111 
1.6046 
−0.2246 
8.4993 </p>

<p>RTS 
0.0768 
22.723 
−21.199 
2.9858 
−0.2151 
10.6200 </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 
0.0238 
10.957 
−9.4695 
1.289 
−0.1783 
10.9195 </p>

<p>STI 
0.0060 
12.874 
−15.517 
1.4538 
−0.2677 
12.6767 </p>

<p>WIG20 
0.0302 
13.709 
−14.161 
1.9544 
−0.1548 
6.7066 </p>

<p>the investigated return series. The presented results are obtained for those lags for 
which the correlation was the strongest. Consequently, we use one day lagged S&amp;P 
500 returns in links with the indices WIG20, RTS, NIKKEI, STI and KOSPI. 
Summary statistics for the analyzed return series are presented in Table 1. They 
are calculated for the return series coupled with the S&amp;P 500 data, and the values for 
the S&amp;P 500 returns come from the series that was coupled with the FTSE. </p>

<p>5 Empirical analysis </p>

<p>In this paper, the changes in the strength of dependence are investigated in the fol-
lowing way. Given the total time period covered by our sample, we form a cascade 
of partitions of it into 2, 4, 8, and 15 intervals of equal length. For each partition, we 
try to fit the MSC models describing the dynamics of linkages between the S&amp;P 500 
or DAX and the other stock indices in subperiods constituting the partition. In order 
to choose the best fitting models, we employ various copulas and apply information 
criteria, and likelihood ratio tests for the comparison of nested models (e.g. involving 
C </p>

<p>Clayton 
γ </p>

<p>and C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>, or C and C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>). Using the estimated MSC copula 
models, we compute predicted values for Spearman's rho and tail dependence coef-
ficients. Here, by the predicted value for Spearman's rho at time t we mean the value 
ρ t calculated as </p>

<p>ρ t = ρ(1)P (S t = 1| t −1 ) + ρ(2)P (S t = 2| t −1 ), 
(34) </p>

<p>where ρ(j ) is Spearman's rho for a copula applicable in regime j. The predicted val-
ues of the lower and upper tail dependence coefficients are defined analogously. It 
follows from (8) that the ρ t is Spearman's rho for the mixture of copulas governing </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Table 2 Linkages with the S&amp;P 500: parameter estimates for the MSC models for the period 1995-2002 
S&amp;P500 and </p>

<p>FTSE </p>

<p>DAX </p>

<p>CAC 40 </p>

<p>WIG20 </p>

<p>RTS </p>

<p>NIKKEI </p>

<p>STI </p>

<p>BSE 30 </p>

<p>KOSPI </p>

<p>BOVESPA </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>0.9833 </p>

<p>0.9994 </p>

<p>0.9920 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.8556 </p>

<p>0.9961 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.8113 </p>

<p>0.9992 </p>

<p>0.9950 </p>

<p>(0.0123) </p>

<p>(0.0007) </p>

<p>(0.0064) </p>

<p>(0.0772) </p>

<p>(0.0038) </p>

<p>(0.3628) (0.0008) </p>

<p>(0.0036) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>0.9719 </p>

<p>0.9989 </p>

<p>0.9854 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.8851 </p>

<p>0.9942 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.9991 </p>

<p>0.9970 </p>

<p>0.9754 </p>

<p>(0.0205) </p>

<p>(0.0017) </p>

<p>(0.,0114) </p>

<p>(0.0734) </p>

<p>(0.0050) </p>

<p>(0.0012) (0.0027) </p>

<p>(0.0134) </p>

<p>Copula </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>in regime 1 
ρ </p>

<p>0.3237 </p>

<p>0.3276 </p>

<p>0.3092 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.2241 </p>

<p>0.2986 </p>

<p>-0.9974 </p>

<p>0.1337 </p>

<p>0.4072 </p>

<p>(0.0357) </p>

<p>(0.0235) </p>

<p>(0.0323) </p>

<p>(0.0346) 
(0.0198) (0.0022) (0.0269) </p>

<p>(0.0261) </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.3104 </p>

<p>0.3143 </p>

<p>0.2964 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2144 </p>

<p>0.2862 
−0.9971 0.1277 </p>

<p>0.3915 </p>

<p>Copula </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Clayton </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>in regime 2 
κ </p>

<p>1.5320 </p>

<p>1.6879 </p>

<p>1.5446 </p>

<p>1.0518 </p>

<p>1.0451 </p>

<p>1.1203 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1.2482 </p>

<p>1.9667 </p>

<p>(0.1448) </p>

<p>(0.1102) </p>

<p>(0.1708) </p>

<p>(0.0229) </p>

<p>(0.0384) </p>

<p>(0.0597) </p>

<p>(0.0927) </p>

<p>(0.3064) </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>0.6914 </p>

<p>0.8166 </p>

<p>0.6372 </p>

<p>0.2036 </p>

<p>0.6207 </p>

<p>0.5254 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.0907 </p>

<p>0.4116 </p>

<p>0.6402 </p>

<p>(0.1229) </p>

<p>(0.1119) </p>

<p>(0.1232) </p>

<p>(0.0318) </p>

<p>(0.1222) </p>

<p>(0.0827) </p>

<p>(0.0256) (0.0776) </p>

<p>(0.1879) </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.3669 </p>

<p>0.4279 </p>

<p>0.3370 </p>

<p>0.0332 </p>

<p>0.3273 </p>

<p>0.2673 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.0005 </p>

<p>0.1857 </p>

<p>0.3387 </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>0.4278 </p>

<p>0.4922 </p>

<p>0.4336 </p>

<p>0.0671 </p>

<p>0.0589 </p>

<p>0.1434 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.2575 </p>

<p>0.5775 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.5411 </p>

<p>0.5999 </p>

<p>0.5322 </p>

<p>0.1725 </p>

<p>0.3659 </p>

<p>0.3601 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.0650 </p>

<p>0.3702 </p>

<p>0.6240 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 3 Linkages with the S&amp;P 500: parameter estimates for the MSC models for the period 2002-2009 
S&amp;P500 and </p>

<p>FTSE </p>

<p>DAX </p>

<p>CAC 40 </p>

<p>WIG20 </p>

<p>RTS </p>

<p>NIKKEI </p>

<p>STI </p>

<p>BSE 30 </p>

<p>KOSPI </p>

<p>BOVESPA </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>0.9601 </p>

<p>0.9958 </p>

<p>0.9596 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.9565 </p>

<p>0.9688 </p>

<p>0.9972 </p>

<p>0.9943 </p>

<p>0.9681 </p>

<p>0.9824 </p>

<p>(0.0272) </p>

<p>(0.0027) </p>

<p>(0.0194) </p>

<p>(0.0586) (0.0312) </p>

<p>(0.0049) </p>

<p>(0.0060) </p>

<p>(0.0365) </p>

<p>(0.0102) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>0.8356 </p>

<p>0.9956 </p>

<p>0.8664 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.8723 </p>

<p>0.9542 </p>

<p>0.9976 </p>

<p>0.9441 </p>

<p>0.9594 </p>

<p>0.9815 </p>

<p>(0.0929) </p>

<p>(0.0032) </p>

<p>(0.0380) </p>

<p>(0.1511) (0.0416) </p>

<p>(0.0031) </p>

<p>(0.0425) </p>

<p>(0.0386) </p>

<p>(0.0099) </p>

<p>Copula </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>in regime 1 
ρ </p>

<p>0.4728 </p>

<p>0.5051 </p>

<p>0.4955 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.3304 </p>

<p>0.3998 </p>

<p>0.2828 </p>

<p>0.1597 </p>

<p>0.3035 </p>

<p>0.4873 </p>

<p>(0.0278) </p>

<p>(0.0248) </p>

<p>(0.0296) </p>

<p>(0.0675) (0.0420) </p>

<p>(0.0450) </p>

<p>(0.0300) </p>

<p>(0.0430) </p>

<p>(0.0424) </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.4558 </p>

<p>0.4876 </p>

<p>0.4782 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.3169 </p>

<p>0.3844 </p>

<p>0.2710 </p>

<p>0.1526 </p>

<p>0.2909 </p>

<p>0.4701 </p>

<p>Copula </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>in regime 2 
κ </p>

<p>2.1647 </p>

<p>1.7861 </p>

<p>2.4116 </p>

<p>1.0462 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1.3715 </p>

<p>1.2414 </p>

<p>1.2867 </p>

<p>1.1575 </p>

<p>2.2722 </p>

<p>(0.4347) </p>

<p>(0.0981) </p>

<p>(0.3095) </p>

<p>(0.0241) </p>

<p>(0.1246) </p>

<p>(0.0692) </p>

<p>(0.2198) </p>

<p>(0.0667) </p>

<p>(0.1571) </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>1.4384 </p>

<p>1.1566 </p>

<p>2.2652 </p>

<p>0.2028 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.8315 </p>

<p>0.4832 </p>

<p>0.6451 </p>

<p>0.5729 </p>

<p>1.2973 </p>

<p>(0.3682) </p>

<p>(0.1165) </p>

<p>(0.5195) </p>

<p>(0.0343) </p>

<p>(0.1506) </p>

<p>(0.4832) </p>

<p>(0.2721) </p>

<p>(0.1339) </p>

<p>(0.1495) </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>0.6176 </p>

<p>0.5492 </p>

<p>0.7364 </p>

<p>0.0328 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.4345 </p>

<p>0.2382 </p>

<p>0.3415 </p>

<p>0.2982 </p>

<p>0.5861 </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>0.6226 </p>

<p>0.5258 </p>

<p>0.6670 </p>

<p>0.0603 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.3424 </p>

<p>0.2522 </p>

<p>0.2862 </p>

<p>0.1800 </p>

<p>0.6433 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.7397 </p>

<p>0.6667 </p>

<p>0.8074 </p>

<p>0.1685 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5329 </p>

<p>0.3934 </p>

<p>0.4610 </p>

<p>0.3927 </p>

<p>0.7390 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>the dependence in regimes 1 and 2, with the weights equal to the predicted proba-
bilities P (S t = 1| t −1 ) and P (S t = 2| t −1 ). Formulas (12) and (13) imply that an 
analogous property holds for the lower and upper tail dependence coefficients. 
Our comparison of the mean values of the mentioned dependence measures taken 
in the subperiods of equal length uses the model confidence set (MCS) methodology. 
The ranking of the periods according to the mean value of Spearman's rho is obtained 
with the MCS procedure applied sequentially-after each run, the series constitut-
ing the MCS are excluded. The higher score means the stronger dependence. In the 
case where the MCS consists of at least two periods, the arithmetic mean of the cor-
responding scores is assigned to each of them. The same procedure is conducted for 
the series of the predicted values of tail dependence coefficients. All MCSs (with 
the significance level α = 0.1) have been estimated using the package MulCom of 
Hansen and Lunde (2010) written in <rs id="software-3" type="software">Ox</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Doornik</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">2006</rs>). 
Maximizing jointly the log-likelihood function (24) can be very computationally 
intensive. Therefore, as in many papers dealing with dynamic copula models, we 
separate the estimation of models for marginal distributions from the estimation of 
the model for the dependence structure. This two-stage estimation, proposed by Joe  and Xu (1996), is not fully efficient but there are some simulation results that moti-
vate this approach (Patton 2009). For marginal distributions, we use ARMA-GARCH 
models. Since some of the analyzed periods are quite long and encompass periods of </p>

<p>Table 4 Linkages with the DAX: parameter estimates for the MSC models for the period 1995-2002 </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
KOSPI </p>

<p>P 11 
0.9896 
0.9953 
0.9851 
0.9810 
0.9949 
0.9994 </p>

<p>(0.0056) 
(0.0042) 
(0.0089) 
(0.0159) 
(0.0038) (0.0008) </p>

<p>P 22 
0.9828 
0.9979 
0.9832 
0.9613 
0.9931 
0.9992 </p>

<p>(0.0120) 
(0.0019) 
(0.0108) 
(0.0331) 
(0.0053) (0.0011) </p>

<p>Copula 
C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C 
C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>in regime 1 </p>

<p>ρ 
0.5402 
0.1180 
0.1255 
0.1769 
-
0.2214 </p>

<p>(0.0250) 
(0.0470) 
(0.0426) 
(0.0379) 
(0.0275) </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.5223 
0.1127 
0.1199 
0.1691 
0 
0.2118 </p>

<p>Copula 
C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>in regime 2 </p>

<p>κ 
2.0218 
1.1614 
1.1800 
1.2498 
1.1509 
-</p>

<p>(0.1851) 
(0.0422) 
(0.0765) 
(0.1370) 
(0.0537) </p>

<p>γ 
1.3401 
0.5585 
0.5882 
0.5231 
0.2422 
-</p>

<p>(0.1816) 
(0.0514) 
(0.0999) 
(0.1346) 
(0.0620) </p>

<p>λ L 
0.5962 
0.2890 
0.3078 
0.2658 
0.0572 
0 </p>

<p>λ U 
0.5911 
0.1836 
0.2007 
0.2588 
0.1738 
0 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 0.7164 
0.3890 
0.4065 
0.4102 
0.2517 
0 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>low and high volatility, the fitted models include asymmetric GARCH (APARCH or 
GJR-GARCH) with a skewed Student t distribution for the innovations ε i,t . The fit-
ted models are sometimes fractionally integrated models but this is rather a result of 
possible structural breaks in the data than long memory effects (Beine and Laurent  2001). 
The standardized residualsε i,t from the fitted models were routinely examined 
for the presence of desirable distributional and serial properties. Next, they were 
transformed by means of the corresponding distribution functions into the series of 
the form (23). The parameters of the MSC models were estimated by the maximum 
likelihood method, using the first summand in (24). In order to model adequately 
the dynamics of the linkages, we tried to use copulas from various families. As it 
was mentioned above, the best models were selected using information criteria, and 
likelihood ratio tests in the cases where nested models were compared. 
In Tables 2 and 3 we present the estimation results for the linkages with the S&amp;P 
500 for the case where the total sample period is partitioned into two subperiods: 
1995-2002 and 2002-2009. The tables include parameter estimates of the fitted MSC 
models, the values of Spearman's rho for copulas prevailing in a given regime, and 
the values of the coefficients of tail dependence (where applicable). Tables 4 and 5 
show the corresponding results for the linkages between the DAX and the indices 
FTSE, WIG20, RTS, NIKKEI, BSE 30, and KOSPI. Due to space limitations, we </p>

<p>Table 5 Linkages with the DAX: parameter estimates for the MSC models for the period 2002-2009 </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
KOSPI </p>

<p>p 11 
0.9808 
0.9994 
0.9852 
0.9436 
0.9992 
0.9748 </p>

<p>(0.0080) 
(0.0008) 
(0.0086) 
(0.0698) 
(0.0011) 
(0.0288) </p>

<p>p 22 
0.9689 
0.9994 
0.9809 
0.8887 
0.9990 
0.8936 </p>

<p>(0.0110) 
(0.0007) 
(0.0106) 
(0.1116) 
(0.0016) 
(0.1089) </p>

<p>Copula 
C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>in regime 1 </p>

<p>ρ 
0.7859 
0.6432 
0.2113 
0.2438 
0.4103 
0.2887 </p>

<p>(0.0135) 
(0.0181) 
(0.0483) 
(0.0445) 
(0.0268) 
(0.0320) </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
0.7713 
0.6253 
0.2021 
0.2334 
0.3946 
0.2767 </p>

<p>Copula 
C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Clayton 
γ </p>

<p>C Gauss </p>

<p>ρ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>J oe−Clayton 
κ,γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Clayton 
γ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Clayton 
γ </p>

<p>in regime 2 </p>

<p>κ or ρ 
0.9284 
--
0.6221 
1.2262 
-
-</p>

<p>(0.0084) 
(0.0358) 
(0.1159) </p>

<p>γ 
-
0.6055 
-
0.5755 
0.2530 
0.8913 </p>

<p>(0.0531) 
(0.1972) 
(0.0700) 
(0.3149) </p>

<p>λ L 
-
0.3183 
-
0.2999 
0.0646 
0.4595 </p>

<p>λ U 
-
-
-
0.2400 
-
-</p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
0.9219 
0.3408 
0.6041 
0.4191 
0.1675 
0.4451 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>01/04/1995 11/06/1995 09/06/1996 07/09/1997 05/18/1998 03/18/1999 01/12/2000 11/14/2000 09/24/2001 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
Lambda_L 
Lambda_U </p>

<p>Fig. 1 S&amp;P 500 and KOSPI. Period 1995-2002. Predicted values for Spearman's rho and tail dependence 
coefficients </p>

<p>do not report parameter estimates of the remaining 432 MSC models corresponding 
to the finer partitions of the total time period. Based on these models we obtained 
rankings of the linkages presented in Tables 7, 8, 9, 11, 12 and 13. 
The MSC models presented in Tables 2 and 3 fit well the data. The only exceptions 
in which a non-switching model is selected are the WIG20 (in both subperiods) and 
the STI. In the case of the RTS, in both subperiods one of the regimes is govern by 
the independence copula. The values of Spearman's rho are always higher in regimes 
where tail dependence is present. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>07/11/2002 05/12/2003 03/16/2004 01/11/2005 11/09/2005 09/11/2006 07/11/2007 05/16/2008 03/13/2009 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
Lambda_L 
Lambda_U </p>

<p>Fig. 2 S&amp;P 500 and KOSPI. Period 2002-2009. Predicted values for Spearman's rho and tail dependence 
coefficients </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>01/05/1995 10/27/1995 08/20/1996 06/18/1997 04/09/1998 02/04/1999 11/24/1999 09/14/2000 07/09/2001 05/07/2002 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
Lambda_L 
Lambda_U </p>

<p>Fig. 3 DAX and S&amp;P 500. Period 1995-2002. Predicted values for Spearman's rho and tail dependence 
coefficients </p>

<p>The results for the DAX (Tables 3 and 4) are generally similar to those for the 
S&amp;P 500. There are two cases where Spearman's rhos calculated for a copula with 
tail dependence are lower than for the Gaussian copula. This is true for the pairs 
(DAX,WIG20) and (DAX, BSE 30) in the second subperiod. Usually, it is expected 
that during a crisis period the dependencies are stronger and that this is accompanied 
by an increase in tail dependence. The above examples show that the strength of 
regular linkages in a regime with no tail dependence can be higher than in a regime 
where tail dependence is present. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>07/11/2002 05/05/2003 02/24/2004 12/09/2004 09/28/2005 07/19/2006 05/10/2007 02/29/2008 12/16/2008 10/09/2009 </p>

<p>Spearman's rho 
Lambda_L 
Lambda_U </p>

<p>Fig. 4 DAX and S&amp;P 500. Period 2002-2009. Predicted values for Spearman's rho and tail dependence 
coefficients </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Table 6 The ranking of the strength of linkages with S&amp;P 500: two subperiods </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 and 
FTSE DAX CAC40 WIG20 RTS NIKKEI STI BSE30 KOSPI BOVESPA </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-2002 
1 
1 
1 
2 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
2 
2 
2 
1 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-2002 
2 
1 
1 
2 
2 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
1 
2 
2 
1 
1 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-2002 
2 
1 
1.5 
2 
2 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
1 
2 
1.5 
1 
1 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>To give a reader an impression of the dependence dynamics we present in 
Figs. 1 and 2 the plots of the predicted values of Spearman's rho and the tail 
dependence coefficients for the S&amp;P 500 and KOSPI in periods 1995-2002 and  2002-2009, respectively. Figures 3 and 4 show the corresponding plots for the pair 
(DAX, S&amp;P 500). 
Tables 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12 and 13 present the rankings of subperiods obtained 
as a result of comparison of strength of linkages between the considered indices 
and the S&amp;P 500 or the DAX. The idea behind our analysis is that increase in 
the strength of linkages during longer subperiods (Tables 6, 7, 10 and 11) can 
be interpreted as the effect of globalization. The analysis performed for shorter </p>

<p>Table 7 The ranking of the strength of linkages with S&amp;P 500: four subperiods </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 and 
FTSE DAX CAC40 WIG20 RTS NIKKEI STI BSE30 KOSPI BOVESPA </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-1998 
1 
1 
1 
1 
3 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
2 
2 
2 
4 
2 
2 
3 
2 
2 
3 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
3 
3 
3 
3 
1 
3 
2 
3 
3 
2 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
4 
4 
4 
2 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-1998 
1 
1 
1 
3 
1 
1 
1 
2 
1 
3 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
4 
2 
3 
1 
4 
3 
4 
3 
3 
1.5 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
3 
3 
4 
4 
3 
2 
2 
4 
2 
4 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
2 
4 
2 
2 
2 
4 
3 
1 
4 
1.5 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-1998 
1 
1 
1 
4 
2.5 2 
1 
1.5 
1 
3 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
4 
2 
4 
2 
2.5 2 
2 
1.5 
4 
1.5 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
3 
3.5 
3 
2 
2.5 2 
3 
1.5 
2 
4 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
2 
3.5 
2 
2 
2.5 4 
4 
1.5 
3 
1.5 </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 8 The ranking of the strength of linkages with S&amp;P500: eight periods </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 and 
FTSE DAX CAC40 WIG20 RTS NIKKEI STI BSE30 KOSPI BOVESPA </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-1996 
1 
1 
1 
1 
3.5 2 
2 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
3 
3 
3 
6 
7 
1 
1 
3 
2 
2 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
2 
2 
2 
3 
1.5 4 
5 
2 
4 
5.5 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
6 
7 
5.5 
7 
3.5 3 
6 
6 
5 
4 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
5 
6 
5.5 
4 
1.5 5 
3 
5 
7 
3 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
4 
4 
4 
8 
5 
6.5 
4 
4 
3 
5.5 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
7 
5 
7 
5 
8 
6.5 
8 
7 
8 
8 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
8 
8 
8 
2 
6 
8 
7 
8 
6 
7 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-1996 
4 
1 
2 
2 
6 
7 
3.5 3 
2.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
5 
3.5 
4 
5 
8 
3 
3.5 5 
2.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
6 
3.5 
5 
4 
5 
3 
8 
4 
6 
2.5 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
8 
6 
2 
1 
3 
3 
3.5 6 
2.5 
2.5 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
3 
8 
8 
7 
1 
3 
7 
8 
2.5 
7 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
7 
2 
2 
8 
4 
3 
3.5 7 
5 
2.5 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
1.5 
5 
6 
6 
2 
6 
3.5 1 
7.5 
2.5 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
1.5 
7 
7 
3 
7 
8 
3.5 2 
7.5 
8 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-1996 
2 
1.5 
2.5 
7 
3.5 4 
3 
7 
6 
3 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
4 
1.5 
5 
6 
8 
4 
6 
3 
2.5 
7 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
5 
3 
6 
5 
3.5 4 
3 
6 
5 
3 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
8 
6 
2.5 
2.5 
3.5 4 
3 
8 
2.5 
3 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
6 
8 
8 
2.5 
3.5 4 
3 
3 
2.5 
6 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
7 
4 
2.5 
8 
3.5 4 
8 
3 
7 
3 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
2 
5 
2.5 
2.5 
3.5 8 
3 
3 
8 
3 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
2 
7 
7 
2.5 
7 
4 
7 
3 
2.5 
8 </p>

<p>Shaded fields indicate crises periods </p>

<p>periods (Tables 8, 9, 12 and 13) allows us to discover the impact of market 
events (especially crises) on the strength of dependence. The rankings for Spear-
man's rho show the behavior of regular dependence and the rankings calculated 
based on the tail dependence coefficients describe the changes of dependence in 
extremes. 
The first observations is that the rankings depend on the applied measure of 
dependence. The results obtained for Spearman's rho are in favor of the glob-
alization effect. Tables 6 and 10 show that in the case of partitioning into two 
subperiods an increase in the strength of dependencies between the markets is 
visible. The only and easy to explain exception is the pair (S&amp;P 500, WIG20). </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Table 9 The ranking of the linkages with S&amp;P500: fifteen periods (years) </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 and 
FTSE DAX CAC 40 WIG20 RTS NIKKEI STI BSE 30 KOSPI BOVESPA </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995 
1.5 
1 
1 
1 
-
1.5 
6.5 6 
2.5 
2 </p>

<p>1996 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
5 
1 
3.5 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>1997 
3 
3 
4 
9 
14 
3.5 
2.5 5 
2.5 
3 </p>

<p>1998 
8 
6 
5 
12 
3 
1.5 
2.5 4 
4 
8 </p>

<p>1999 
4 
6 
7.5 
3 
7.5 5.5 
9.5 3 
5 
5.5 </p>

<p>2000 
5 
6 
2.5 
15 
7.5 12 
8 
8 
15 
11 </p>

<p>2001 
12 
14 
11.5 
10 
5 
7 
11 12 
12 
7 </p>

<p>2002 
12 
12.5 11.5 
7 
7.5 8 
5 
2 
7.5 
4 </p>

<p>2003 
10 
12.5 
9 
6 
2 
9 
4 10 
12 
9 </p>

<p>2004 
7 
6 
6 
11 
4 10.5 
6.5 7 
6 
10 </p>

<p>2005 
6 
6 
7.5 
14 
11 10.5 
12 
9 
7.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>2006 
12 
9.5 13.5 
8 
12 
5.5 
14.5 11 
9.5 
13 </p>

<p>2007 
14 
9.5 13.5 
4 
13 13 
13 13.5 
14 
14 </p>

<p>2008 
9 
11 
10 
13 
10 14 
14.5 13.5 
12 
12 </p>

<p>2009 
15 
15 
15 
2 
7.5 15 
9.5 15 
9.5 
15 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995 
14 
4 
4.5 
3.5 
-
12 
3.5 5 
4.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>1996 
4.5 
2 
4.5 
9 
7 14 
8 
6 
4.5 
11.5 </p>

<p>1997 
4.5 
9 
9.5 
13 
13 
5.5 
9.5 10 
4.5 
8.5 </p>

<p>1998 
4.5 
5 
4.5 
3.5 
8 
5.5 
11.5 9 
4.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>1999 
4.5 
2 
4.5 
8 
13 12 
15 
8 
4.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>2000 
11 
10.5 
9.5 
3.5 
3.5 5.5 
9.5 13 
9.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>2001 
15 
6 
12 
3.5 
3.5 5.5 
3.5 11 
13 
8.5 </p>

<p>2002 
11 
10.5 13 
11 
11 
5.5 
3.5 7 
9.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>2003 
11 
15 
15 
10 
3.5 5.5 
3.5 15 
4.5 
11.5 </p>

<p>2004 
4.5 
7.5 11 
15 
9 
5.5 
7 12 
4.5 
13 </p>

<p>2005 
11 
2 
4.5 
14 
13 
5.5 
13 14 
14 
14.5 </p>

<p>2006 
4.5 13 
4.5 
3.5 
10 
5.5 
11.5 3 
15 
10 </p>

<p>2007 
4.5 12 
4.5 
12 
3.5 15 
14 
3 
11.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>2008 
4.5 
7.5 
4.5 
3.5 
3.5 12 
3.5 3 
11.5 
14.5 </p>

<p>2009 
13 
14 
14 
7 
3.5 5.5 
3.5 3 
4.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995 
5.5 
3.5 
5.5 
13 
-
12 
5.5 14 
4.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>1996 
5.5 
3.5 
5.5 
6 
7 13 
5.5 6.5 
9 
5.5 </p>

<p>1997 
5.5 
8 
11 
14 
14 
6 
5.5 6.5 
4.5 
11 </p>

<p>1998 
5.5 
7 
5.5 
6 
7 
6 
11 13 
4.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>1999 
5.5 
3.5 
5.5 
6 
7 14 
5.5 6.5 
4.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>2000 
12 
10 
5.5 
6 
7 
6 
12 
6.5 
14 
5.5 </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 9 (continued) </p>

<p>S&amp;P 500 and FTSE DAX CAC 40 WIG20 RTS NIKKEI STI BSE 30 KOSPI BOVESPA </p>

<p>2001 
15 
3.5 
5.5 
6 
7 
6 
5.5 15 
13 
5.5 </p>

<p>2002 
13.5 15 
13.5 
6 
7 
6 
5.5 6.5 
10 
5.5 </p>

<p>2003 
5.5 13 
13.5 
6 
7 
6 
14 
6.5 
4.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>2004 
5.5 
3.5 15 
6 
7 
6 
5.5 6.5 
4.5 
12 </p>

<p>2005 
13.5 3.5 
5.5 
15 
7 
6 
13 
6.5 
4.5 
14 </p>

<p>2006 
5.5 14 
5.5 
6 
7 
6 
15 
6.5 
12 
13 </p>

<p>2007 
5.5 10 
5.5 
6 
7 
15 
5.5 6.5 
15 
5.5 </p>

<p>2008 
5.5 10 
5.5 
6 
7 
6 
5.5 6.5 
11 
15 </p>

<p>2009 
11 
12 
12 
12 
7 
6 
5.5 6.5 
4.5 
5.5 </p>

<p>Shaded fields indicate crises periods </p>

<p>The Polish stock market is traditionally strongly connected with the U.S. one. 
The EU joining process, however, resulted in weakening these linkages due to 
a natural effect of approaching the Polish economy the EU one. In the case 
of four subperiods (Tables 7 and 11), more exceptions is observed, but gen-
erally the rankings indicate a more or less regular increase in the strength of 
connections. 
The results concerning dependencies in tails are more diverse. Although very often 
higher score corresponds to the period 2002-2009, there are some interesting excep-
tions. The first of them is the pair (S&amp;P 500, FTSE) for which our results indicate 
weakening of tail dependencies in the second period. Similar results were obtained 
for the pairs (S&amp;P 500, RTS), (DAX, FTSE), (DAX, WIG20), (DAX, RTS), and, with 
reference to upper tail dependence, for (DAX, NIKKEI) and (DAX, BSE 30). These 
results show that the globalization effect does not necessarily mean an increase in 
the strength of tail dependencies, and again that the behavior of regular dependence 
measured by means of Spearman's rho can be different from that of dependence in </p>

<p>Table 10 The ranking of the strength of linkages with DAX: two subperiods </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
KOSPI </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-2002 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-2002 
2 
2 
2 
1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
1 
1 
1 
2 
2 
2 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-2002 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 
1 </p>

<p>2002-2009 
1 
1 
1 
1 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Table 11 The ranking of the strength of linkages with DAX: four subperiods </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
KOSPI </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-1998 
1 
1 
1 
2 
1 
1 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
2 
3 
3 
1 
2 
2 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
3 
2 
2 
3 
3 
3 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-1998 
3.5 
1 
4 
2 
3 
1 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
3.5 
3 
3 
4 
1 
2 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
1 
4 
2 
3 
4 
4 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
2 
2 
1 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-1998 
3 
2 
3 
2 
3 
2.5 </p>

<p>1998-2002 
4 
4 
4 
2 
1 
2.5 </p>

<p>2002-2006 
1 
2 
1 
4 
4 
2.5 </p>

<p>2006-2009 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2 
2.5 </p>

<p>extremes. Moreover, the rankings obtained based on the dynamics of the lower and 
upper tail dependence coefficients often differ from each other. 
The period under scrutiny includes two subperiods in which severe financial crises 
appeared. In years 1997-1998 the financial market experienced a turmoil starting 
from emerging economies, and from 2007 to 2009 it suffered from the U.S. sub-
prime crisis. The analysis of Tables 8, 9, 12 and 13 allows one to explore the issue 
of increasing strength of market dependencies during the crisis periods. Although 
none of the analyzed subperiods can be perceived as a crisis period, a systemic 
increase in the strength of dependence during crises should result in a significantly 
higher level of dependence for periods encompassing a crisis. In the analysis we 
have to take into account effects of globalization, thus, for example, we do not 
expect the level of dependence in the period 1997-1998 to be the highest, but if 
there were an increase in the strength of linkages during the crisis, the level should 
be the highest from among those in the first four periods considered in Table 8 or 
in the first seven periods in Table 12. Hence our results do not, as a rule, indi-
cate an increase in the strength of dependence during the crisis periods. The results 
are rather ambiguous and depend on the analyzed markets. For example, Table 8 
shows that in years 1997-1998 the linkages between the S&amp;P and the Polish WIG20 
belong to the highest, but in years 2007-2009 are located among the lowest. In 
the case of the S&amp;P and RTS, the scores for these two subperiods are very close. 
This diversity of results is observed in the case of all the considered measures of 
dependence. 
An interesting observation supporting the use of the MCS methodology is that we 
find pairs of the indices with the same score for different periods with a non-zero 
level of dependence. The examples are: (S&amp;P 500, CAC 40) (Tables 6, 8 and 9), (S&amp;P </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 12 The ranking of the strength of linkages with DAX: eight subperiods </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
KOSPI </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995-1996 
1 
1 
1 
6 
2 
1 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
2 
2.5 
3 
1 
3.5 
2 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
3 
6 
6 
2.5 
1 
3 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
4 
4 
5 
2.5 
5 
4 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
5 
5 
2 
4 
3.5 
5 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
6 
2.5 
4 
7.5 
6 
6.5 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
7 
7 
8 
7.5 
7 
6.5 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
8 
8 
7 
5 
8 
8 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995-1996 
8 
2 
3.5 
2 
3 
5 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
7 
4 
7 
4 
7 
2.5 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
6 
6 
3.5 
7 
6 
2.5 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
3 
2 
3.5 
2 
3 
2.5 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
3 
7 
3.5 
5.5 
8 
6 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
3 
8 
3.5 
8 
3 
7 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
3 
5 
3.5 
5.5 
3 
2.5 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
3 
2 
8 
2 
3 
8 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995-1996 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
6 </p>

<p>1997-1998 
8 
4 
4 
4 
4 
3 </p>

<p>1998-2000 
4 
4 
4 
4 
8 
3 </p>

<p>2000-2002 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
3 </p>

<p>2002-2004 
4 
8 
4 
8 
4 
7.5 </p>

<p>2004-2006 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
3 </p>

<p>2006-2007 
4 
4 
4 
4 
4 
3 </p>

<p>2008-2009 
4 
4 
8 
4 
4 
7.5 </p>

<p>Shaded fields indicate crises periods </p>

<p>500, BOVESPA) (Table 8) and (DAX, NIKKEI) (Tables 12 and 13). Thus different 
dynamics can result in statistically indistinguishable average levels of dependence. 
Our findings can be summarized as follows. First, an observed increase in the 
strength of market linkages is due rather to the globalization, and not specifically 
to crises. In fact, in the considered crisis periods no general increase in dependence 
measured by Spearman's rho is detected. Moreover, what is even more surpris-
ing, we do not observe any systemic higher level of lower tail dependence during 
the crises. Another unexpected result is that for some pairs of the indices upper 
tail dependence turns out to be greater than the lower one. An example for this is 
shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Table 13 The ranking of the strength of linkages with DAX: fifteen periods (years) </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 30 
K OSPI </p>

<p>Spearman's rho </p>

<p>1995 
2 
1 
-
4 
2. </p>

<p>1996 
1 
2 
1 
14 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1997 
3 
3.5 
2 
2.5 </p>

<p>1998 
6 
11.5 
9.5 
6.5 
5 
4 </p>

<p>1999 
5 
10 
7.5 
2.5 
2.5 
5 </p>

<p>2000 
4 
6 
6 
6.5 
0 </p>

<p>2001 
9 
8.5 
7.5 
5 </p>

<p>2002 
7 
5 
9.5 
9 </p>

<p>2003 
8 
7 
3 
8 
1 </p>

<p>2004 
11 
11.5 
4.5 
15 
1 
4.5 </p>

<p>2005 
10 
3.5 
4.5 
11 
10 
8 </p>

<p>2006 
12 
8.5 
11 
10 
1 </p>

<p>2007 
13.5 
13 
12 
13 
13 
14.5 </p>

<p>2008 
13.5 
15 
13.5 
12 
15 
13 </p>

<p>2009 
15 
14 
13.5 
1 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Lambda L </p>

<p>1995 
4.5 
3.5 
-
7 
4. 
0 </p>

<p>1996 
12 
7 
9 
11 </p>

<p>1997 
4.5 
3.5 
4.5 
12.5 
4.5 
8.5 </p>

<p>1998 
11 
10.5 
14 
3.5 
1 
.5 </p>

<p>1999 
9 
3.5 
4.5 
10 
9 
3.5 </p>

<p>2000 
13 
12 
12 
3.5 
4.5 
3.5 </p>

<p>2001 
4.5 
3.5 
4.5 
3.5 
11 
3.5 </p>

<p>2002 
15 
14 
4.5 
3.5 
10 
3.5 </p>

<p>2003 
4.5 
15 
4.5 
8 
1 
3 </p>

<p>2004 
14 
3.5 
10 
14 
4.5 
14 </p>

<p>2005 
4.5 
13 
4.5 
3.5 
1 
5 </p>

<p>2006 
4.5 
8 
4.5 
3.5 
15 
11.5 </p>

<p>2007 
4.5 
9 
11 
12.5 
4. 
.5 </p>

<p>2008 
4.5 
10.5 
4.5 
15 
4. 
1.5 </p>

<p>2009 
10 
3.5 
13 
9 
4. </p>

<p>5 
3 </p>

<p>6 
1 </p>

<p>7 
1 </p>

<p>9 
9 </p>

<p>4 
6 </p>

<p>8 
1 </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>2 
7 </p>

<p>4 
1 </p>

<p>5 
1 </p>

<p>8 
7 </p>

<p>4 
3 </p>

<p>3 
1 </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>5 
3 </p>

<p>5 
1 </p>

<p>5 
8 .5 </p>

<p>Lambda U </p>

<p>1995 
6 
6.5 
-
13 
5.5 
10 </p>

<p>1996 
6 
6.5 
10 
15 
13 
12 </p>

<p>1997 
6 
6.5 
5 
11 
5.5 
9 </p>

<p>1998 
6 
6.5 
11 
5 
5.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>1999 
6 
6.5 
5 
5 
11 
4.5 </p>



<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>

<p>Table 13 (continued) </p>

<p>DAX and 
FTSE 
WIG20 
RTS 
NIKKEI 
BSE 3 
OSPI </p>

<p>2000 
14 
6.5 
5 
5 
5.5 
4.5 </p>

<p>2001 
6 
6.5 
5 
5 
15 
4.5 </p>

<p>2002 
15 
6.5 
5 
5 
1 
.5 </p>

<p>2003 
6 
13 
5 
14 
5. 
3 </p>

<p>2004 
13 
6.5 
12 
12 
5.5 
14 </p>

<p>2005 
6 
6.5 
5 
5 
14 
4.5 </p>

<p>2006 
6 
6.5 
5 
5 
5. 
.5 </p>

<p>2007 
6 
14 
14 
5 
5. 
.5 </p>

<p>2008 
6 
15 
5 
10 
5. 
1 </p>

<p>2009 
12 
6.5 
13 
5 
5. </p>

<p>0 
K </p>

<p>2 
4 </p>

<p>5 
1 </p>

<p>5 
4 </p>

<p>5 
4 </p>

<p>5 
1 </p>

<p>5 
1 5 </p>

<p>Shaded fields indicate crises periods </p>

<p>6 Conclusions </p>

<p>The aim of the presented analysis was to examine the impact of globalization and 
crises on the strength of linkages between stock markets. Our analysis was performed 
for pairs of national stock markets represented by the daily returns on stock indices 
including the S&amp;P 500, DAX, FTSE, CAC 40, RTS, WIG 20, NIKKEI, STI, BSE, 
and BOVESPA. We considered 10 pairs containing the S&amp;P 500, and 6 holding 
the DAX. The applied approach used a Markov switching copula model to describe 
the dynamics of dependencies during subperiods of the period 1995-2009. We con-
sidered two types of dependencies: regular dependence measured by means of the 
conditional Spearman's rho, and dependencies in extremes quantified by the condi-
tional tail dependence coefficients. To compare the strength of linkages in different 
subperiods the Model Confidence Set methodology was applied. Our main results 
are the following. In the case of long subperiods (4, 7 years), a systematic and signif-
icant increase over time in the mean level of the linkages (measured by Spearman's 
rho) between the national stock markets is observed. This can be interpreted as an 
effect of globalization. On the other hand, the globalization effect does not necessar-
ily cause a systematic increase in the strength of tail dependencies. The mean level 
of dependence in shorter subperiods (1-2 years) is sensitive to the market situation. 
In general, however, an increasing trend can be observed. Our results seem to con-
tradict the prevailing opinion about an increase in the strength of the linkages during 
the crisis periods. They are also not consistent with the known belief that lower tail 
dependence becomes stronger in such periods. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The authors are very grateful to two anonymous referees for their helpful com-
ments and suggestions. Useful comments and remarks from the participants of the 17th International 
Conference "Forecasting Financial Markets" (May 2010, Hannover, Germany) and the 4th Conference on 
Computational and Financial Econometrics (December 2010, London, UK) are also much appreciated. 
This work was financed from the Polish science budget resources in the years 2010-2013 as the 
research project N N111 035139. </p>

<p>Dynamic linkages between stock markets: the effects of crises and globalization </p>



<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License 
which permits any use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and 
the source are credited. </p>





<p>M. Doman, R. Doman </p>



</text></tei>