<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F00220485.2017.1353464" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>THE JOURNAL OF ECONOMIC EDUCATION 
, VOL. , NO. , - 
https://doi.org/./.. </p>

<p>FEATURES AND INFORMATION </p>

<p>Building research skills in the Macalester economics major </p>

<p>J. Peter Ferderer and Gary Krueger </p>

<p>Department of Economics, Macalester College, St. Paul, MN, USA </p>

<p>KEYWORDS </p>

<p>Econometrics; research; 
writing </p>

<p>JEL CODES </p>

<p>A; A </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Economics majors at Macalester College have won numerous awards for their 
research papers, and this success has helped them land jobs in finance, con-
sulting, and the nonprofit sector, as well as gain admission to top graduate 
programs. This article describes how the Economics Department at Macalester 
promotes economic research among its students. </p>

<p>According to a recent report from the Macalester College Institutional Research Office, Macalester ranks 
13th among liberal arts colleges in terms of baccalaureate origins of people receiving U.S. doctorates 
between 2005 and 2014. When the data are disaggregated, the Economics Department at Macalester 
ranks 8th. In addition, we have a strong track record of placing students in top finance and consulting 
positions as well as those in the nonprofit sector. What accounts for this success? 
We believe it is due, in part, to the emphasis we place on economic research. All Macalester students 
take a first-year course that emphasizes writing, and we build on that by progressively incorporating 
more research into the economics major over the next three years. An important element of this is our 
Introduction to Econometrics course, which not only covers estimation methods, but also teaches students 
how to write an original research paper. Students then write a senior honors thesis or complete a large 
research paper in their senior capstone course. Many of these students have won awards given by the 
Minnesota Economics Association and other professional organizations. </p>

<p>An overview of the college </p>

<p>Founded in 1874, Macalester is a residential liberal arts college located in the heart of the Twin Cities 
metropolitan area. The student body has grown in recent years, from around 1,850 students a decade 
ago to over 2,000 today. 
The Macalester campus is a short drive from both downtown Saint Paul and Minneapolis. The Twin 
Cities are home to 19 Fortune 500 companies (more than any other metropolitan area its size), includ-
ing industry leaders in manufacturing (3M), retail (Target), and health care (UnitedHealth) (Thompson 
2015). There are many universities and colleges nearby, including the Minneapolis and Saint Paul cam-
puses of the University of Minnesota, and both the state capitol and Minneapolis Fed provide educational 
opportunities for our students as they pursue various research interests. 
Despite its Midwestern location and ethos, Macalester College has a long history of international-
ism. Macalester has a higher percentage of international students than most other liberal arts colleges, 
and significant resources are dedicated to international programming. Around 50 percent of our eco-
nomics majors are international students, with many coming from the United World College high school 
program. These students enrich the culture of our department and help create an environment where 
academic achievement is highly valued. </p>

<p>CONTACT J. Peter Ferderer 
ferderer@macalester.edu 
Edward J. Noble Professor and Department Chair, Department of 
Economics, Macalester College,  Grand Avenue, St. Paul, MN , USA. </p>

<p>© J. Peter Ferderer and Gary Krueger. Published with license by Taylor &amp; Francis. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/./), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, pro-
vided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. </p>



<p>J. P. FERDERER AND G. KRUEGER </p>

<p>Macalester's endowment grew significantly in the 1990s with a generous gift from the family of DeWitt 
and Lila Wallace, founders of Reader's Digest. These resources have been used to lower student-faculty 
ratios and place greater emphasis on faculty-student collaborative research and writing. </p>

<p>The Economics Department and major </p>

<p>The Economics Department has eight tenure-track economists, one full-time accountant and an ex-
investment banker who teaches courses in applied finance. Our program is consistently one of the largest 
on campus with between 45 and 65 majors graduating each year. Although we only have one major and 
one minor (both in economics), we offer two types of courses: Group E courses, which are typical of those 
offered by an economics department; and Group B courses, which include accounting, entrepreneurship, 
and applied finance. Many of our students also major in mathematics, applied mathematics and statistics, 
or computer science. Double majors with international studies, geography, and political science are also 
common. Macalester is somewhat unique with its large geography department, and we encourage our 
students to take courses in geographical information systems in order to expand their empirical tool kit. 
To complete the economics major, students take a minimum of 12 courses: </p>

<p>r Four required courses: Principles of Economics (micro and macro combined in one semester), </p>

<p>Intermediate Microeconomics, Intermediate Macroeconomics, and Introduction to Econometrics. </p>

<p>r Six electives at various levels, including a senior capstone course with a significant research com-</p>

<p>ponent. Only two of the six can be Group B courses. </p>

<p>r Two math courses: Multivariate Calculus and Statistics. </p>

<p>Our mathematics department has, to a significant degree, tailored the two math courses to meet 
the needs of our majors, although these courses also serve students in other divisions and majors. We 
attribute much of our students' success to the time they spend with the mathematicians. 
Economics majors do a number of different things after graduating. Many pursue careers in business 
and finance. Particularly noteworthy here is our long history of placing graduates in investment bank-
ing. Students interested in this path take our accounting and finance courses, as well as Introduction to 
Investment Banking, which includes a class trip to New York where they interact with alumni working on 
Wall Street. Consulting has become a popular career path in recent years, and many alumni have gone 
on to work for Accenture, Analysis Group, Brattle Group, Cornerstone, Deloitte, McKinsey, and other 
firms. A large number of students are interested in economic development and the nonprofit world, with 
many finding positions at organizations like the Urban Institute, World Bank, the Federal Reserve Sys-
tem, Peace Corps, and so on. Approximately two to four of our students enter PhD programs each year. 
For instance, this past fall, two began PhD programs in economics, one in computer science and another 
in health care management. </p>

<p>Three stages of research </p>

<p>Hoyt and McGoldrick (2017) summarize the goals of student research that economics departments typ-
ically pursue: "[T]hey want students to identify and ask worthwhile questions, connect these to the lit-
erature, hypothesize, gather and process data accordingly, effectively employ analytical tools, interpret 
findings, and present their work in writing and orally" (p. 656). At Macalester, we attempt to achieve 
these goals by asking students to engage in research at three different points in the economics major. </p>

<p>Stage 1: The 200-level elective course </p>

<p>Students are first asked to conduct economic research in the 200-level (sophomore) elective course. Prior 
to this, during their first semester at the college, students take a first-year course that has a significant 
writing component. This includes sessions with library staff who teach students how to use library 
resources, the difference between academic and popular press articles, the rules regarding plagiarism, 
proper citation methods, and so on. Therefore, students enter the 200-level elective with a general 
understanding of the academic literature and how it can be used to write a term paper. </p>

<p>MACALESTER ECONOMICS MAJOR </p>



<p>One approach taken is illustrated by the term paper required for World Economic History. In this 
course, students write a 10-page paper where they pose a question (e.g., Why did the Industrial Revo-
lution begin in England and not China?) and utilize the academic literature to address it. This assign-
ment helps students learn how to (a) formulate a question, (b) locate academic resources and properly 
cite them, and (c) write a persuasive and well-organized paper (i.e., one with an introduction, theory 
and evidence sections, and a conclusion). In addition, exposure to the academic literature introduces 
students to methodologies utilized by economists, including mathematical modeling and regression 
analysis. </p>

<p>Stage 2: The econometrics course </p>

<p>The second stage of research occurs in Introduction to Econometrics, usually taken in the junior year. 
This course convenes in our econometrics lab, which has 28 computers. Enrollments are capped at 22 
students per section due to the heavy burden that draft editing imposes on the professor. The course 
covers standard econometric topics: estimation using OLS, hypothesis testing, serial correlation and 
time series, as well as introduction to more advanced topics such as panel data, instrumental variables, 
and logit/probit estimation. Data analysis is conducted with <rs type="software">STATA</rs>, which students begin using the sec-
ond week of class, and the instruction tends to be applied rather than mathematical/algebraic. A required 
one-hour lab was added 25 years ago to provide extra instruction time to cover research methods. The 
course also receives extensive support from our library staff who have developed instruction modules 
and resource guides to assist students with their research. 1 
The econometrics course builds on knowledge students acquire in Introduction to Statistics, the 
200-level elective, and the intermediate micro and macro theory courses. Because the introductory statis-
tics course covers a significant amount of regression analysis, students hit the ground running in econo-
metrics and are prepared to immerse themselves in the mechanical process of technical writing in eco-
nomics. Throughout the semester, they simultaneously work on problem sets and their research paper. 
With guidance from the instructor, students choose their own research topic and locate relevant datasets. 
There is no final exam; rather the research paper serves as the final for the course. This approach has 
proved successful, and a large number of papers from this course have won prizes from the Minnesota 
Economic Association and other professional organizations. 
We also offer an advanced econometrics course that provides upper-level students an opportunity to 
explore the underlying mathematics of econometrics. Enrollments in this course have increased sharply 
over the past decade. </p>

<p>Stage 3: The capstone project </p>

<p>Research continues during the senior year when all students are required to complete a capstone project. 
About 8 to 12 of our seniors do this by writing a senior honors thesis. Those who aspire to write a thesis 
must have a minimum GPA of 3.3 and submit a short proposal toward the end of their junior year. If the 
proposal is accepted, they enroll in the senior honors seminar in the fall of their senior year where they 
learn more about the research process and critique each other's work. It is not uncommon for the honors 
thesis to be an extension of a project that began in the econometrics course. Students continue working 
on their thesis during the spring semester and provide an oral defense in mid-April. Typically, some of 
these students will also present their work at conferences such as those held by the Midwest Economics 
Association. Seniors who do not write an honors thesis enroll in a 400-level capstone course and com-
plete a large research project related to the focus of the course. We currently offer six capstone courses: 
Advanced Econometrics, Applied Dynamic Macroeconomics, Behavioral and Experimental Economics, 
Economics of Public Policy, Empirical Finance, and International Economic Development. Each course 
requires a term paper and enables students to expand their methodological toolkit. 
Both approaches to capstone research have been fruitful. A few years ago, two students conducted 
a public goods experiment in Behavioral and Experimental Economics and provided evidence that 
free-riding fell significantly in treatments with designated punishers (compared to treatments where </p>



<p>J. P. FERDERER AND G. KRUEGER </p>

<p>punishment responsibility was decentralized). This paper was published in the Atlantic Economic Jour-
nal. A junior in Advanced Econometrics recently studied the link between terrorist attacks and bond 
yields, and extended this analysis in his honors thesis the next year to examine the effect of U.S. drone 
strikes on Al Qaeda terrorist attacks. This student won the 2016 Frank W. Taussig Article Award given 
by the Omicron Delta Epsilon Honor Society. </p>

<p>Resources and incentives </p>

<p>In addition to the curricular structure discussed above, we attempt to promote student research by allo-
cating resources in particular ways and structuring incentives to raise the return to research activity. 
We seek to hire faculty who are passionate about research and view themselves as both teachers and 
scholars. We find that those who do applied research are better able to involve students in their research, 
and we attempt to identify people who enjoy working collaboratively. Faculty are also incentivized to 
publish papers with students. For instance, they are asked to highlight Macalester student co-authors on 
their CV, and this type of collaboration is valued by the committee that makes tenure and promotion 
decisions. 
Faculty-student research is funded internally three different ways. First, faculty receive $1,750 each 
year for travel and research. Second, they can compete for Wallace Scholarly Activities grants that are 
often used to hire research assistants. Finally, Student-Faculty Collaboration &amp; Summer Research grants 
can also be obtained rather easily and, as the name suggests, promote co-authorship. 
A number of articles have been published in peer-reviewed journals by Macalester faculty and stu-
dents. For example, in 1998, Professor Gary Krueger and Marek Ciolko published, "A Note on Initial 
Conditions and Liberalization during Transition" in the Journal of Comparative Economics. Professor 
Liang Ding has written four articles with students, and in 2012 he and Macalester mathematics professor 
Vittorio Addona worked with Hao Zou, who is currently completing his PhD in finance at the Univer-
sity of Rochester, and published "Semi-Transparency, Dealership Market and Foreign Exchange Market 
Quality" in the Review of Financial Economics. Professor Amy Damon has published two papers with 
students, and she and Devon Kristiansen wrote "Childhood Obesity in Mexico: The Effect of Interna-
tional Migration, " which appeared in Agricultural Economics in 2014. Sarah West has written papers with 
several students, and in 2014 she and Needham Hurst published "Public Transit and Urban Redevelop-
ment: The Effect of Light Rail Transit on Land Use in Minneapolis, Minnesota" in Regional Science and 
Urban Economics. 
We look for ways to increase the efficiency of classroom teaching in order to free up time for research 
and one-on-one work with students. This includes reducing the overall number of course preps, teaching 
back-to-back sections of the same course in a given semester, and hiring student preceptors to grade 
problem sets and tutor peers. Our proximity to the University of Minnesota makes it relatively easy for 
us to hire part-time replacements and thus encourage sabbatical extensions. 
We are fortunate to have facilities that support student research. About three decades ago, the depart-
ment received an NSF grant to build a computer lab, and the college continues to invest in this space with 
new hardware (28 Macs) and software (<rs type="software">STATA</rs>). Our introductory and advanced econometrics courses 
benefit a great deal from the lab, and it is a hub for research activity throughout the year. The walls of 
the lab are covered with plaques that commemorate research-paper prizes our students have won, and 
we hope that they inspire the younger students. 
Throughout the year, each honors thesis writer has their picture and thesis title prominently displayed 
in the hallway leading to the economics department office. To further shine a spotlight on thesis writers 
and hopefully inspire younger students to follow in their footsteps, economics classes are canceled on a 
Friday in April and all honors defenses occur on that day. Extra credit and food are used to incentivize 
students to attend presentations, and parents and grandparents have been known to show up on occasion. 
Each year, we hold a ceremony to honor our seniors in late April. Those who have completed an honors 
thesis are given the podium for a few minutes to summarize their research. In addition, departmental 
awards with cash prizes are announced. These awards provide another incentive for students to invest 
time into research because they are based, in part, on course performance and term paper grades. </p>

<p>MACALESTER ECONOMICS MAJOR </p>



<p>The Macalester Journal of Economics is published once each year and contains the best five to six 
course term papers as judged by the student-run editorial board. The MJE provides visibility to those 
who have written outstanding term papers at all levels of the curriculum. 
Finally, we have experimented with social media to promote student research. Once students declare 
an economics major, they are invited to join the department Facebook page, which has over 600 current 
and former majors as members. Here, they have a window on the professional lives of alumni, many of 
whom are engaged in academic research, and gain access to job postings, academic articles, datasets, and 
so forth. The page also enables students to interact with professors on an informal basis for the purpose 
of discussing economics and sharing research ideas. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Relatively few economics majors at Macalester College will go on to academic careers. Nonetheless, the 
skills developed during the research process (i.e., learning to ask good questions, engage in abstract rea-
soning, locate and analyze data, and communicate persuasively through the written and spoken word) 
are important in many different walks of life. If the goal is to get our students to "to think like economists, " 
there is no better way than to immerse them in the research process. </p>

<p>Note </p>

<p>1. http://libguides.macalester.edu/econ381 </p>



</text></tei>