<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1468-0351.2009.00346.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>This article empirically investigates how the transition to a market economy affected 
the relationship between motherhood and labour force outcomes in Poland. We 
estimate different probit models on two panel datasets covering a three-year 
period before the reform (1987-1989) and a three-year period afterwards (1994-
1996). Contrary to a priori expectations, our findings indicate that during transition 
young children were much less of a deterrent to the employment probability of 
their mother than they were before transition. </p>

<p>JEL classifications: J13, J22, P23, C23. 
In this article we investigate the role of motherhood in shaping the employment 
outcomes of Polish women before and during transition to a market economy. A 
priori expectations, based on a few indisputable phenomena -the nearly universal 
female labour market participation in the pre-transition period, the rapid deteriora-
tion of child-care facilities during transition, and the increasing discrimination in 
the labour market against women who could become mothers -suggest that being 
a mother in transition Poland entailed greater difficulties in combining paid work 
and family responsibilities than before. However, we will show that employment 
was more responsive to motherhood before than during transition. In our analysis 
we will investigate some explanations for this puzzling result and we will discuss 
the results in the final part of the article. 
There has been very little research on mothers' labour supply choices in transition 
economies. Fong and Lokshin (2000) examined how women's labour force activity 
depends on household child-care choices in Romania. They showed that after 
transition women's labour market activity was strongly affected by the presence of 
children and was highly responsive to the cost of child care. Saget (1999) estimated 
a model of labour supply decisions of married women in Hungary to measure the 
impact of the number and age of children on women's labour supply (in addition 
to a host of women's characteristics, such as individual wages and a household's 
non-labour income). Using post-transition data, she found that the presence of 
young children decreased the probability of a woman participating in the labour 
market, while the presence of teenagers had the opposite effect. 
These studies suggest that, during transition, women and mothers in Central 
and Eastern European countries tended to display a labour market behaviour more 
and more similar to the one of women in Western economies. In their study of 
participation behaviour of East German women after German unification, Bonin  and Euwals (2002) examined precisely this issue. They wondered how the high 
unemployment rate and the change in public policies that followed transition 
impacted the high female labour market participation of the pre-transition period, 
and whether East German women will eventually adapt their behaviour to West 
German patterns, characterized by a much lower female employment rate. They 
found that labour force participation was negatively affected by the number of 
pre-school children, and that this negative effect increased over time after the 
unification. However, they do not use data from the period before the unification 
to estimate how different women's labour market behaviour was before 1990. 
To our knowledge no specific study exists for Poland and in particular no 
comparison of pre-and post-transition female labour market behaviour has ever 
been carried out. In this article we ask the following questions: was motherhood in 
Poland a significant constraint to women's employment during transition? Was it the 
case before the transition? In our analysis we use panel data for both periods (1987- 1989 and 1994-1996) to disentangle the direct effect of children on female employment </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>from women's unobserved taste for children and employment, while controlling for 
relevant individual and household characteristics. We will argue, based on our results, 
that in the pre-transition period characterized by virtually no constraints to join the 
labour market (no unemployment, availability of child-care facilities), preferences 
-including cultural attitudes and social expectations about the role of mothers in 
a traditional society such as Poland -played a fundamental role in shaping mothers' 
employment patterns. On the other hand, during transition, the need for a second 
earner in the household, the great uncertainty in the labour market, and (for highly 
educated women) the new opportunities offered by a rapidly developing private sector 
were powerful reasons for mothers to be in employment, and be able to overcome 
the increasing difficulties represented by the deterioration of child-care facilities. 
The article is structured as follows: Section 1 contains an Introduction with a 
sub-section to provide background information to describe the position of women 
in the Polish labour market, as well as the family policies existing in the pre-
transition period and during transition. Section 2 describes the dataset used for our 
investigation. In Section 3 we provide some descriptive statistics on the participation 
and fertility behaviour of women in Poland across transition. Section 4 presents the 
econometric approach we adopted to estimate the female employment probability. 
The empirical evidence from the estimated probit models and the interpretation of 
the main findings are reported in Section 5. Section 6 provides concluding remarks. </p>

<p>1.1 Background </p>

<p>Before 1989, despite the high female labour market participation, the absence of 
unemployment, and the generous provision of maternity benefits and public child 
care, women were in a position of disadvantage in the labour market. In a patriarchal 
society such as Poland, women were expected to fulfil the role of main child-care 
providers. At the same time, women were also expected to work in remunerative 
employment, both for wages needed to support their family, and because women's 
labour was essential to the production system in a period of rapid industrialization 
(Nowakowska and Swêdrowska, 2000). As Leven (2008) very effectively pointed 
out, gender equality was ideologically consistent with a socialist state and women-
friendly policies were mandated by a government that lacked popular support. 
Employed women were concentrated in low skilled and low paid occupations, 
despite being disproportionally highly educated. 
2 Because supply of part-time jobs </p>

<p>2 It should be noted, however, that the pre-transition Poland had one of the lowest female activity rates of 
all Central and Eastern European countries. Around 1989, about 68 percent of women in 15 -54 years of age 
were participating in the labour force -a much lower percentage than, for example, in Czechoslovakia, the 
Baltic States, Belarus, Moldova, Russia, or Ukraine, all with more than 80 percent of female labour market 
participation. Still, women's activity rates were substantially higher in Poland than in most Western 
countries. More specifically, all women in the labour force were employed (unemployment being non-
existent in socialist countries) and almost all employed women were working full-time, given the negligible 
size of part-time employment (UNICEF, 1999). </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>was very limited in socialist countries, almost all employed women were employed 
full-time and the availability of child-care facilities and family-friendly policies 
allowed women to combine paid work and family responsibilities. However, 
because women were the main ones responsible for child care and the secondary 
earners inside the family, they had to sustain the double burden of careers and 
family obligations (Ruminska-Zimny, 2002). 
During transition, activity rates dropped considerably, for both women and 
men. Polish women experienced a dramatic drop in employment -about 900,000 
jobs were lost by women from 1989 to 1995. Unemployment, non-existent in the 
communist period, was 13 percent in 1997 for women of all ages, and 10 percent 
for men (UNICEF, 1999). Transition hit women in particular, not just because 
women were more likely to lose their job and less likely to find one -thus becoming 
the majority of the long-term unemployed -but also because they were systematically 
discriminated against in the labour market (especially in the nascent private one). </p>

<p>3   While published statistics and empirical studies on Polish transition extensively 
document the changes in the social and economic position of women in general 
following the 1990 events, data on changes in the labour market participation of 
mothers are hard to find. Some evidence exists on two adverse phenomena for 
mothers' position in the labour market in transition Poland -the rapid increase in 
women's discrimination in the private labour market and the substantial decrease 
in public child care provision. Despite the fact that the cost of maternity leave was 
still fully covered by the social insurance system, employers in post-1990 Poland 
were reluctant to hire women who could become pregnant -either to avoid the 
hassle of finding a temporary replacement or due to the assumption that, once back 
to work after the childbearing period, mothers would become unenthusiastic workers 
with outdated skills (Lohmann and Seibert, 2003; World Bank, 2004). According to 
some studies, increasing discrimination in the private sector meant that women 
with children were disproportionately more likely to be out of work. A UNICEF 
study based on the Polish Labour Force Survey finds that 'Poland marriage status 
-a reliable proxy for the presence of children -was not a factor for unemployed 
men in finding work, but was a serious handicap for unemployed women' 
(UNICEF, 1999, p. 29). However, it should be noted that, according to the same 
study, the presence of children did not increase the chances of employed women 
losing jobs with respect to men, indicating that many women needed and were 
actually able to combine paid work and family commitments. 
As far as the decrease in public child-care provision is concerned, it is undeniable 
that child-care services were severely cut during transition (especially in kindergartens), 
and their fees increased considerably. Nowakowska and Swêdrowska (2000) estimate 
that at the end of the 1990s the typical kindergarten fee could account for 30-45 percent 
of an average salary of a woman with a university diploma. Some authors have stressed </p>

<p>3 For an overview of women's position in the labour market in pre-transition Poland and the changes that 
occurred during transition see Lohmann and Seibert (2003) and Paci (2002). </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>that, during transition, increasing costs of child care and demand-side factors were 
actually more important than the closure of child-care centres in explaining the 
decrease in enrolment rates. For example, Meurs and Giddings (2004) show that in 
the case of Bulgaria the drop in fertility rates, as well as the increase in unemploy-
ment rates and decrease in real wages -which accounted for a substantial decrease 
in disposable income and thus in the ability to pay for increasingly expensive child 
care -were the main drivers behind the decrease in enrolment rates. In Poland, 
some of the decrease in availability of state-subsidized child care can be explained 
by a drop in fertility, however the decreased supply of kindergartens and nurseries 
outweighed the drop in demand -the majority of kindergartens were full or 
above their capacity during transition (Lohmann and Seibert, 2003), although large 
geographical variations existed. In any case, it is unquestionable that the cost of 
raising a child increased substantially, as did the conflict between women's family 
duties and professional careers (Lohmann and Seibert, 2003). </p>

<p>4   The lack of adequate and affordable child-care services together with labour 
market discrimination could have 'encouraged' women to drop out of the labour 
force to raise children. On the other hand, women's dependency on their spouses' 
and other family members' income as well as their increased inability to return to 
paid work after long spells out of the labour force 
5 were powerful reasons for 
mothers with a job to stay employed, even at the cost of exceptional efforts to 
juggle work and family responsibilities. </p>

<p>6   Which of the above contrasting forces prevailed in shaping employment oppor-
tunities for mothers during transition is an open question. In addition, it is unclear 
whether having children affected women's participation in the labour market more 
during transition than in the pre-transition period. We will explore these issues in 
the current analysis. </p>

<p>4 It should be stressed that, while child-care provision suffered substantial cuts during transition, the duration 
of maternity leave and the amount of maternity benefits were maintained at the pre-transition levels. 
Mothers were paid a basic maternity benefit corresponding to 100 percent wage replacement for 16, 18, or 
26 weeks after delivery (of the first child, any subsequent children, or in case of multiple births, respectively) 
and, if employed, were entitled to unpaid parental leave until the third birthday of the child, while retaining the 
right to their previous job (Golinowska et al. , 2003). Until 1996, the last year of our sample data, these provisions 
remained unchanged, and are therefore not responsible for changes in women's labour supply which we may 
observe between the two periods. Overall, means-tested and insurance-based family benefits characterized 
Poland as one of the least generous countries in the pre-transition Central and Eastern Europe (Fodor et al. , 2002). 
5 In 1997, the female unemployment rate was 13 percent, and almost half of unemployed women (43 
percent) were long-term unemployed (out of work for longer than one year) (UNICEF, 1999). 
6 Rostgaard (2004) comments that the high cost of child care and the policy of means-tested cash benefits 
'. . . runs the risk of encouraging low-income women to withdraw from the labour market to care for their 
children at home, while high-income women are likely to combine work and caring responsibilities because 
they can better afford costly day care' (p. 34). However -referring to evidence provided by Kurzynowski 
-Golinowska et al. (2003) claim that '. . . In the late 1990s, women with low-paid but permanent jobs tended 
to take parental leave and claim parental allowance over four times less frequently than at the time the 
benefit was introduced' (p. 26). </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>2. Data </p>

<p>To answer these questions we use the panel data for Poland available in the Panel 
Comparability Project (PACO) -the original source is the Polish Household Panel 
(PHP) survey. 
7 PACO is an international comparative database provided by CEPS/ 
INSTEAD (based in Luxembourg) integrating micro-data from various national 
household panels over a large number of years. </p>

<p>8   For Poland, the available data consist of two separate panels: the first includes 
four waves from 1987 to 1990, the second includes three waves from 1994 to 1996. 
Although the individuals observed are not the same in the pre-and post-transition 
period, we can still exploit all the advantages of using panel data to estimate a 
model of mothers' employment and compare the results in the two periods. The 
main advantages of using the Polish datasets through PACO are the consistency of 
variable definition over time (the original variables have been standardized and 
codified according to standardized international classifications), and (potentially) 
the comparability of the results with other countries included in the database 
(Hungary, among transitional economies, and some West-European economies like 
Germany and the UK). Moreover, in the case of Poland, PACO includes two 
panels, one covering the pre-reform period and the other covering the transition 
period -overall a relatively long time span that allows for comparisons before and 
after the reform. 
The data comprises extensive information on labour force and work history 
(employment status, professional status, working time, sector of employment), and 
includes a set of household-and individual-level income variables, education and 
family background variables, household composition and demographic characteristics 
of each individual, and territorial division. 
Table A1 in the Appendix presents summary statistics for the main variables 
used in this study. </p>

<p>3. Female labour supply and fertility in Poland </p>

<p>Using the Polish Household Panel in PACO we start by providing some stylized 
facts about the employment and fertility behaviour of Polish women. Figure 1 
shows the proportion of women aged 16-44 years with a partner 
9 and household 
responsibilities (namely, who are either head of the household or the spouse of the </p>

<p>7 The PHP is managed by the Department of Economics at the University of Warsaw in Poland. The LFS 
(which includes a panel component) could have been an appropriate choice for our study, but it only started 
in 1992, and was therefore not available in the pre-transition period. 
8 For more information about PACO, see website &lt;www.ceps.lu.paco/acceuil.cfm&gt;. 
9 In this article we do not distinguish between married and cohabiting women and we may use the words 
'partner', 'spouse' and 'husband' (or 'wife') interchangeably. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>head) who were in employment in the period before the transition (1987-1989) and 
during transition (1994-1996), by age of the youngest child. It should be stressed 
that the first period panel made available through PACO also includes 1990, but 
we chose to drop this last wave given that reforms in Poland were adopted starting 
from the 1 January 1990 (Poland is probably the best-known application of the 
'shock therapy' among the newly emerging economies of Central and Eastern 
Europe and the former Soviet Union). We chose 16-44 years as the relevant age 
interval to account for the existence of a non-zero percentage of very young 
mothers (lower bound); the upper threshold of 44 is typically chosen as the oldest 
fertile age in studies on fertility behaviour. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows a very interesting and unexpected pattern. For women aged 
16-44 years the employment rate dropped very little, on average from 69 percent 
in the first period to 67 percent in the second period. However, the employment </p>

<p>10 Moreover, we focused on women who were either the head or the spouse because it was only possible 
for this group of women to unambiguously identify their own child from other children living in the 
household. See footnote 16. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Percentage of women aged 16-44 years with partner and household 
responsibilities who are employed, by age of youngest child. </p>

<p>Notes: (i) Women with household responsibilities are defined as those who are either the head of household 
or the spouse of the head. (ii) Dependent children are children aged 17 and younger. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>rate of mothers varied substantially depending on the age of the youngest child; 
moreover, the patterns were quite different in the two periods. Before the transition, 
only 41 percent of women with a child aged 0-2 years were employed, compared 
with 68 percent of mothers of a youngest child aged 3-5 years, and 79 percent of 
mothers of a youngest child aged 6-11 years. 
11 During transition, the employment 
rate of mothers also increased with the age of the youngest child, but the differences 
were much less pronounced. Thus, a higher percentage of mothers of a child aged 
0-2 years were employed than before the transition -50 vs. 41 percent. However, 
only 59 percent of mothers of a youngest child aged 3-5 years and 71 percent of 
mother of a youngest child aged 6-11 years were employed during transition 
(while the corresponding pre-transition figures were 68 and 79 percent). 
To some extent, the decline in labour market participation of mothers of 
pre-school children (3-5 years old) can be accounted for by the decline in state-
subsidized child-care. Children aged 3-5 years were much more likely to be in 
kindergarten before than during transition, and even before transition much more 
likely to be in child care than children aged 0 -2 years old. The largest difference in 
the employment rate before and during transition existed for the group of women 
without dependent children, 87 vs. 73 percent. However, the surprising finding is 
the comparatively large percentage of mothers of children aged 0-2 years old who 
were employed during transition -larger than in the first period. These patterns 
suggest that there were substantial differences in the probability of women to be 
employed between the two periods that were unrelated to motherhood (as 
illustrated by the differences in employment rates for women without dependent 
children between the 1987-1989 and the 1994-1996 periods). 
The stylized facts presented in Figure 1 also suggest that the presence and the 
age of children was a crucial element in explaining women's employment before 
transition rather than during transition. That is, during transition the female 
employment rate was much less responsive to the age of the youngest child than 
it was before transition. This is in contrast with the general notion of universal 
female labour market participation before transition (which, in the case of Poland, 
was less than universal) and the foreseeable negative impact on mothers' employ-
ment during transition due to the deterioration of child-care facilities, as well as 
the increased discrimination in the private labour market. 
Figure 1 shows the employment rates of women by age of the youngest child 
but does not take into account the total fertility and the changes in fertility patterns 
between the two periods. It can be argued that fertility is endogenous to labour 
supply -in fact, fertility rates dropped during transition and postponement of 
marriage and childbearing became one of the strategies to decrease the conflict 
between family commitments and paid work (UNICEF, 1999; Lohmann and </p>

<p>11 Variations in women's employment rates are expected to be independent of variations in family policies, 
given that no change occurred over the whole period considered in our analysis (in particular, the duration 
of maternity and parental leave was the same in 1987-1990 and 1994 -1996). </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors  Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Siebert, 2003). Therefore, the large differences in employment rates of mothers with 
children of different ages observed before the transition could have been driven by 
a total higher fertility. This is to say that the age of the youngest child heavily 
influenced the employment rate of the mother due to the presence of more siblings 
in the first period than in the second period. Table 1 shows that, if there is some 
validity in this explanation, it is very limited. 
The average number of children generally decreased between the two periods, 
but not dramatically so (the decrease in fertility patterns accelerated in the late 
1990s, that is, after the period considered in this study). For example, the average 
number of children aged 0-2 years for each woman aged 16-44 years was not 
much lower in the second period when, as Figure 1 shows, the employment rates 
of mothers of these very young children was 8 percentage points higher in 1994-
1996. Moreover, Table 1 also shows that the difference in the average number of 
children between working and non-working women was lower in the second than 
in the first period for the children aged 0-2 and 3-5 years. Therefore, the stylized 
facts presented in Figure 1 do not seem to be driven by dramatic changes in fertility 
behaviour. 
Another element that should not be overlooked in this analysis is the role of 
educational qualification. Women with different education levels are likely to have 
different attitudes toward employment and were also affected differently by labour 
market changes during transition. In Table 2 we show the proportion of women in </p>

<p>Table 1. Average number of dependent children of women aged 16-44 years with 
partner and household responsibilities, by mother's employment status and age 
of the child </p>

<p>1987-1989 
1994 -1996 </p>

<p>Working Not working 
All 
Working Not working 
All </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 0-2 yrs old </p>

<p>0.15 (0.40) 
0.47 (0.58) 
0.25 (0.49) 0.13 (0.37) 
0.27 (0.50) 
0.18 (0.42) </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 3-5 yrs old </p>

<p>0.34 (0.55) 
0.60 (0.69) 
0.41 (0.61) 0.24 (0.49) 
0.37 (0.57) 
0.28 (0.52) </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 6 -11 yrs old </p>

<p>0.80 (0.82) 
0.83 (0.89) 
0.81 (0.84) 0.71 (0.81) 
0.77 (0.86) 
0.73 (0.83) </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 12 -17 yrs old </p>

<p>0.70 (0.84) 
0.44 (0.77) 
0.62 (0.83) 0.75 (0.85) 
0.64 (0.86) 
0.71 (0.86) </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 0 -17 yrs old </p>

<p>1.99 (1.15) 
2.34 (1.16) 
2.10 (1.17) 1.83 (1.17) 
2.05 (1.26) 
1.90 (1.21) </p>

<p>Notes: (i) Women with household responsibilities are defined as those who are either the head of household or the 
spouse of the head. (ii) Dependent children are children aged 17 years and younger. (iii) Standard deviations in 
brackets. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>employment disaggregated by educational qualifications, as well as by the age of 
the youngest child. As shown in Figure 1, both before and after transition, mothers 
had lower employment rates than non-mothers or mothers of children aged 18 
years or older. Moreover, the younger the age of the youngest child, the lower the 
employment rate of the mother. This pattern was common across education levels, 
although some important differences should be stressed. 
First, highly educated mothers (third level education) 
12 had substantially higher 
employment rates than mothers of children of the same age but with lower educa-
tional qualifications in both periods. Moreover, highly educated women re-entered 
employment when the child was still very young -the employment rates of highly 
educated mothers with a child aged 3-5 years was over 80 percent both before and 
after transition. </p>

<p>12 Third level education (or tertiary education, or higher education) refers to universities and other tertiary 
institutions that award degrees and advanced research qualifications as well as to other post-secondary 
institutions that also provide programs that would be classified at a lower level than a degree. </p>

<p>Table 2. Proportion of women aged 16-44 years with partner and household 
responsibilities who are employed, by age of the youngest child and educational 
qualifications </p>

<p>Age of the 
youngest child </p>

<p>Second level, 
first stage 
and lower </p>

<p>Second level, 
second stage 
high school </p>

<p>Second level, 
second stage 
professional </p>

<p>Third level </p>

<p>1987-1989 
Children 0-2 yrs old 
0.45 (0.50) 
0.38 (0.49) 
0.40 (0.49) 
0.53 (0.50) 
Children 3 -5 yrs old 
0.65 (0.48) 
0.72 (0.45) 
0.62 (0.49) 
0.80 (0.40) 
Children 6-11 yrs old 
0.71 (0.45) 
0.88 (0.33) 
0.75 (0.43) 
0.89 (0.32) 
Children 12-17 yrs old 
0.73 (0.45) 
0.93 (0.25) 
0.84 (0.37) 
0.93 (0.27) 
No dependent children 
0.83 (0.38) 
0.93 (0.26) 
0.82 (0.39) 
1.00 (0.00) 
1994-1996 
Children 0-2 yrs old 
0.48 (0.50) 
0.52 (0.50) 
0.42 (0.49) 
0.70 (0.46) 
Children 3 -5 yrs old 
0.53 (0.50) 
0.63 (0.48) 
0.53 (0.50) 
0.81 (0.39) 
Children 6-11 yrs old 
0.61 (0.49) 
0.75 (0.44) 
0.65 (0.47) 
0.89 (0.32) 
Children 12-17 yrs old 
0.63 (0.68) 
0.80 (0.40) 
0.74 (0.44) 
0.96 (0.21) 
No dependent children 
0.73 (0.44) 
0.81 (0.40) 
0.60 (0.49) 
0.86 (0.35) </p>

<p>Notes: (i) Women with household responsibilities are defined as those who are either the head of the 
household or the spouse of the head. (ii) Dependent children are children aged 17 and younger. (iii) Each 
child category indicates that the woman is mother of children in the corresponding age category and has 
no younger children. (iv) Standard deviations in brackets. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Second, the transition does not seem to have affected the employment rate of 
mothers as much as it affected the employment rate of non-mothers. While women 
with non-dependent or no children had substantially lower employment rates in 
the period 1994 -1996 than they had in the period 1987 -1989 at almost all educational 
qualifications, the employment rate of mothers was lower in the post-transition 
period but not by the same large amounts and in the case of mothers of children 
aged 0-2 years it actually increased during transition. An age effect is likely to 
drive this result -transition negatively affected older women more than it did 
younger women. 
Third, women were differently affected by the drop in employment rates 
during transition depending on their educational qualifications. Highly educated 
women (with third level education) who were mothers did not experience any 
drop in employment rates, while the employment rate of non-mothers of the same 
educational level decreased in the second period. Women with lower educational 
qualifications (mothers and non-mothers), by contrast, generally experienced large 
drops in employment rates, the exception being the mothers of children aged 2 
years and younger. It seems therefore that the education level was a key factor in 
explaining employment outcomes following transition, more than having or not 
having children. 
Finally, Table 3 shows the employment rates of married women depending on 
the participation in employment of their partner. Before transition -when the 
employment rate of men and women was very high -having a partner out of 
employment was associated with a very high employment participation of the 
wife, while women with a working partner were less likely to work. This could be 
due to a genuine effect of the husband's employment status on his wife's employ-
ment status (compatible with the added worker effect, as well as with the effect 
produced by an increase in the household non-earned income on the woman's 
labour supply). Interestingly, after transition, the difference in the employment 
rates of the two groups of women is reversed, and having a partner out of employ-
ment is associated with a lower probability that the wife is employed. During this 
period, the employment rate of men also dropped; therefore it is much more common </p>

<p>Table 3. Proportion of women aged 16-44 years with partner and household 
responsibilities who are employed, by employment status of their partner </p>

<p>Partner not 
employed </p>

<p>Partner 
employed </p>

<p>Percent of women with 
partner in employment </p>

<p>1987-1990 
0.699 (0.460) 
0.669 (0.471) 
94.7 
1994 -1996 
0.620 (0.486) 
0.673 (0.469) 
84.3 </p>

<p>Notes: (i) Women with household responsibilities are defined as those who are either the head of household 
or the spouse of the head. (ii) Standard deviations in brackets. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>to observe couples where both partners do not work. These patterns suggest that 
the higher-than-expected participation in employment of mothers (especially of 
young children) in transition Poland is probably not driven by the spouse being 
unemployed or inactive. At the same time, the differences between the two periods 
in the employment behaviour of the two partners suggest that it is important to 
control for the spouse's characteristics in the multivariate analysis, to account for 
a certain degree of heterogeneity among women (women whose partner is in 
employment are likely to be different from women whose partner is out of 
work). </p>

<p>13   In the multivariate analysis we will explore more rigorously the candidate 
explanations put forward in the descriptive analysis presented in this section. In 
particular, we will account for the possibility that fertility and participation in 
employment are simultaneously determined. Moreover, we will control for the 
partner's characteristics, in particular his employment status and level of earnings. 
Finally, we will control for a host of personal and household characteristics of the 
woman, in particular to address the possibility of correlation between level of 
education and presence and age of children. It should be noted that the model we 
estimated and present in the next section is a reduced form, which does not allow 
disentangling supply-and demand-side effects. Despite this limitation, it can give 
a good indication of whether any of the explanations put forward thus far is a 
plausible one. </p>

<p>4. Econometric modelling </p>

<p>The study of female labour supply and its correlation with the presence of young 
children has a long tradition in the applied econometric literature. Two exhaustive 
surveys are given by Browning (1992) and Nakamura and Nakamura (1992). These 
articles review the main issues concerning the estimation of the effects of the 
presence of children on women's labour supply and examine some select studies 
on this topic. The vast majority of the empirical studies find a negative correlation 
between fertility and women's labour supply. However, the interpretation of this 
result must consider a number of issues. The existence of heterogeneity among 
women, differing in their fixed unobserved preferences for work and children, 
introduces selection effects that can bias 'genuine' effects. For example, it could be 
that women with a higher 'taste' for children are those with lower unobservable 
abilities and skills in the labour market. In that case, it would be this selection effect 
to drive the observed association between a higher number of children and lower 
labour market participation, rather than a 'true' causal effect due to discrimination </p>

<p>13 In a previous version of this article we estimated the model only for the sample of women whose partner 
is employed, obtaining very similar results to those presented here using the broader sample. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>against mothers or to a change in tastes following maternity. Availability of panel 
data in the more recent empirical investigations of female labour supply allows for 
a proper consideration of unobserved heterogeneity. However, when this woman-
specific time invariant component is correlated with the desired number of children, 
a problem of endogeneity of the fertility variables arises. A possible approach to 
this problem is to follow Chamberlain (1984) and parametrically specify the 
individual unobserved heterogeneity allowing for correlation with the observed 
fertility variables. We follow this suggestion in our empirical analysis, given the 
major problems characterizing alternative solutions, like the Instrumental Variable 
(IV) estimation. 
14 Such an approach allows for simultaneous correlation between 
fertility and labour supply behaviour, but still rests on the strict exogeneity 
assumption, ruling out any correlation pattern between fertility and past and 
future working status, and thus a possible feedback from past employment on 
future fertility. Given the difficulties arising from relaxing the strict exogeneity 
assumption, we will follow Wooldridge (2002) and run a test to get some evidence 
on its plausibility in our specific application. 
A related important feature to consider and understand women's employment 
behaviour has to do with the inter-temporal nature of labour supply. There is 
evidence of a high degree of serial persistence in individual participation decisions, 
possibly due to state dependence (with current participation depending on past 
participation) and persistent heterogeneity (when the unobserved individual 
component determines current participation irrespective of past participation). As 
a consequence, econometric models of female labour supply should explicitly 
include dynamic factors. Recent studies by Hyslop (1999) and Troske and Voicu  (2004) adopt a dynamic framework to evaluate the interaction between fertility and 
labour supply decisions. Unfortunately, this approach is not viable in our case, 
given that the two panels we use are too short. 
15 In the following sub-section we 
present the empirical strategy we adopted for our analysis, which is based on static 
models, but fully exploits the panel dimension of our dataset. </p>

<p>4.1 Empirical specification </p>

<p>Our sample includes women aged 16-44 years, who were either the spouse of the 
head of the household or the head of the household themselves (we were able to 
ascertain the parental relationship with children living in the household only for </p>

<p>14 Angrist and Evans (1998) suggested the use of the sibling-sex composition to construct IV estimation, 
given the observed correlation between having two children of the same sex and further childbearing. 
However, this strategy is difficult to implement with the available sample sizes in most studies (in Central 
and Eastern Europe, as in most developed countries, the number of women with at least two children is 
typically very small). 
15 Voicu and Buddelmeyer (2003) adopt an alternative approach and model participation with panel data 
without specifying a random effect individual component, but allowing for a general correlation pattern of 
the error terms over time. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>the head and his/her spouse). 
16 Moreover, we excluded from the analysis single 
women, whose higher heterogeneity with respect to partnered women is well 
documented in the literature on female labour supply (see Browning, 1992). These 
selection criteria left us with a sample of 3,056 person-waves in the first panel 
(period 1987-1989), and 5,055 person-waves in the second panel (period 1994- 1996). 
We defined participation as the status of being employed, in a similar way to 
the more recent empirical studies of female labour force participation (see Hyslop,  1999), and modelled the binary indicator (employed/not employed) by means of 
probit models. As a starting point and benchmark for our analysis, we considered 
two classical models: the pooled cross-section probit and the random effects (RE) 
panel probit model. 
The cross-section (CS) probit model ignores the repeated observations on the 
same individuals, and can be sketched in terms of a continuous latent variable as: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where i = 1, . . . N ; t = 1, . . . T , with the binary dependent variable indicating 
participation given by the indicator function: 
. The vector x it contains 
observed human capital, demographic, household structure and other variables 
which may affect the participation decision, while u it captures the effects of 
unobserved factors and it is assumed to be I.I.D. standard normal. Accordingly, the 
likelihood function of the CS probit model is built on the assumption that: </p>

<p>with Φ (.) denoting the standard normal cumulative density function. 
The RE probit model splits the error term into a time invariant individual 
random effect and an idiosyncratic random error: </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>with ε it ~ I.I.D. N (0, 1), 
, and the unobserved individual effect α i 
is assumed to be independent of X i . The presence of such a time invariant 
component implies a non-diagonal covariance matrix of the composite error term 
u it = α i + ε it , with 
, and 
, interpretable 
as the proportion of the overall error variance which is explained by the individual 
effect. The likelihood function of the RE probit model relies on the probabilities: </p>

<p>16 The PACO dataset only records the relationship of household members with respect to the head of the 
household. We assume that the children of the household head are automatically children of the spouse of 
the household head or have the same effect on her labour market behaviour as her own children. </p>

<p>y 
x 
u </p>

<p>it 
it 
it </p>

<p>* = ′ + 
β </p>

<p>y 
I y </p>

<p>it 
it </p>

<p>( *) 
= </p>

<p>Pr( 
) 
( 
) 
y 
x 
x </p>

<p>it 
it 
it </p>

<p>= 
= 
′ 
1 | 
Φ β </p>

<p>y 
x </p>

<p>it 
it 
i 
it </p>

<p>* = ′ + 
+ 
β α ε </p>

<p>α 
σ α </p>

<p>i 
i </p>

<p>X N 
~ ( , ) 
| 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Var( ) 
u it = 
+ 
σ α </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
ρ 
σ σ </p>

<p>α 
α </p>

<p>( 
) 
/( 
) 
= 
= 
+ 
Corr u u </p>

<p>it is </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Integrating out the unobservable component introduces an integral of the above 
probabilities in each individual contribution to the sample likelihood function. 
Estimation by maximum likelihood of both models can be automatically 
implemented in <rs type="software">STATA</rs>, although the maximization of the likelihood function of 
the second model requires the evaluation of an integral by Gaussian Quadrature 
(Butler and Moffitt, 1982). The first model ignores individual heterogeneity and 
does not exploit the repeated observation available on the same woman. The infer-
ence requires the use of a robust covariance matrix to take into account the error 
serial correlation induced by the unobserved individual component not varying 
with time. 
The second model allows us to incorporate the individual unobserved effects, 
which is generally found to represent a very substantial component in estimated 
female labour participation equations (Hyslop, 1999, finds that the individual-
specific RE accounts for 78 percent of the latent error variance) but relies on two 
main assumptions: (i) absence of correlation between the individual heterogeneity 
and the regressors, (ii) strict exogeneity of the explanatory variables conditionally 
on the individual heterogeneity component. Whenever either of these hypotheses 
fails, the estimates we obtain for the effects of the children on labour supply are 
not consistent (notice that in this instance the pooled probit would suffer from the 
same problem). We addressed the first limitation by adopting as a final specifica-
tion a correlated random effect (CRE) probit model, which allows the unobserved 
preferences for working to be correlated with observed fertility. We followed 
Chamberlain's suggestion (1984) and postulated: </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>where: z i denotes the time average, t = 1, . . . T, of the vector z it = (z i1t , . . . , z iMt )′ 
containing the M elements of x it describing the observed fertility; 
, 
I.I.D. and independent of Z i . 
Among the regressors, we inserted the variables commonly used to explain 
labour supply. The educational qualification of the woman is included using a set 
of dummies indicating the highest level of education attained. The woman's age is 
included in quadratic form. To control for household income that might affect the 
woman's labour supply, we inserted a dummy for her partner being employed and 
used available information on his personal earnings 
17 as well as his age and 
education. A dummy indicating house ownership is meant to proxy for other non-
labour income. Completed fertility is represented by a set of variables indicating 
the number of children in different age categories (0-2, 3-5, 6-11, and 12-17). </p>

<p>17 About 14 percent of the working partners reported zero earnings (zero or negative in the second period). 
We controlled for these anomalous observations by means of a dummy variable. </p>

<p>Pr( 
, ) Pr( 
, ) 
( 
). 
y 
X 
y 
x 
x </p>

<p>it 
i 
i 
it 
it 
i 
it 
i </p>

<p>= 
= 
= 
= 
′ + 
1 
1 
| 
| 
α 
α 
β α 
Φ </p>

<p>α 
ξ η </p>

<p>i 
i 
i </p>

<p>= ′ + 
z </p>

<p>η 
σ η </p>

<p>i 
i </p>

<p>Z N 
: ( , ) 
| 
0 </p>

<p>2 </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Finally, we included among the explanatory variables a set of year dummies to 
capture trend effects and a set of territorial dummies -corresponding to the 49 
Polish voivodships -to control for the unobserved factors describing the different 
economic context at a regional level. Some recent applied studies (Boni, 2002;  Newell and Pastore, 2000; Sibley and Walsh, 2002) illustrated the crucial importance 
of accounting for the strong geographical differentiation in development levels and 
potential of the Polish regions. Moreover, because child care facilities are much 
more available in big urban centres than in rural areas, we expect mothers' decisions 
and opportunities to vary across Polish regions. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>5. Results </p>

<p>In Tables A2 and A3 in the Appendix we report the estimation results for the two 
periods: 1987-1989 (pre-transition) and 1994-1996 (transition period). For each 
period, we present three sets of results corresponding to the pooled CS probit 
model (equation 1), the RE probit model (equation 2), and the CRE probit model 
(equations 2 and 3). 
Before discussing the evidence we obtained on the determinants of women's 
employment in the two periods, we show that the panel probit models represent 
an improvement over the benchmark pooled CS specification. First, the estimated 
value ⁄ within the RE and CRE specification is about 0.80, and statistically significant 
in both periods. This result shows that the relative importance of the unobserved 
effect is very high and that allowing for unobserved heterogeneity represents an 
important improvement of the model (the huge increase in the log-likelihood with 
respect to the pooled CS specification supports this conclusion). 
Some of the CRE coefficients (the elements of the parameter vector ξ) of the 
variables entering the expected value of the unobserved effect are statistically 
significant in both periods. We are also able to reject in both periods the null 
hypothesis that all the ξ elements are simultaneously equal to zero, although with 
weaker evidence in the second period. This evidence supports the existence of 
simultaneous correlation between the individual effect and the fertility variables. 
As mentioned before, the hypothesis of strict exogeneity of the included regressors 
is maintained in all the estimated models. We follow Wooldridge (2002) and test 
for this hypothesis by inserting the one-year forwarded fertility variables on the 
right-hand side and testing whether their coefficients are jointly equal to zero. 
The results of the tests are reported in Table A4 in the Appendix. Interestingly, the </p>

<p>18 As one of the referees correctly pointed out, voivodships do not necessarily fully control for the availability 
of child-care facilities. Child-care can vary within a voivodship; in particular, it can be more available in urban 
than in rural areas. Unfortunately, we do not have any information about whether the woman resides in an 
urban or rural area. Still, the use of voivodship dummies allows us to (partially) control for local labour 
market conditions and, to some extent, availability of infrastructures, including child-care. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>hypothesis could not be rejected for both panel data models within the CRE 
framework. This indicates that the specified correlation between the fertility 
variables and the individual unobserved heterogeneity is able to capture at least 
part of the mechanism generating a feedback effect from past participation to 
future fertility behaviour, although we cannot claim that the validity of our 
estimation results is free from any threat due to endogeneity of the fertility variable. 
In particular, in case of (neglected) feedback from past employment to current 
fertility, the coefficients of the fertility variable are likely to suffer from an 
attenuation bias, as it is reasonable to argue that past participation is positively 
related to both current fertility and participation. With this caveat in mind, we can 
nevertheless look at the general pattern displayed by the estimated coefficients of 
the fertility variables -the key variables of interest in our analysis -and observe 
that they are negative in both the pre-reform and transition period (that is, having 
children negatively impacts the probability of working, as expected). Not surpris-
ingly, the size of this effect decreases as the age of the child increases, indicating 
that a lower amount of mother's time is needed for child-care of older children. </p>

<p>19   The most striking pattern emerging from our results is the decrease in the absolute 
value of the coefficients of the fertility variables moving from the first to the second 
period, for all three models. Within the CRE model, while in the first period all the 
fertility variables have significant coefficients, during the transition period the only 
significant effect is associated with the presence of very young children (aged 0-2 
years). The pattern presented in Figure 1 and discussed in the descriptive analysis 
is therefore confirmed, even after controlling for the potential endogeneity of 
fertility, and all the relevant personal and household characteristics of the woman, 
including the characteristics of her partner. 
To analyze the numerical effect of the presence of children on employment 
outcomes we present in Table 4 a set of estimated average probabilities of working 
and average partial effects evaluated with the three models. More precisely, we 
look at the absolute and percentage change in the (average population) probability 
of working observed when each observed woman moves from the condition of 
childless woman to that of mother of a young child (aged 0-2 years). The descrip-
tive analysis of Section 3 suggests looking at this impact by level of education. 
The comparison between the two periods confirms the smaller effect in the 
second period, occurring (with different magnitude) at all levels of education. This 
pattern is common to the three estimated models, although it can be observed that </p>

<p>19 We incidentally note that within the RE model the estimated coefficients of the fertility variables are 
higher in absolute value than those obtained within the pooled CS model. This pattern suggests that the 
unobservable characteristics affect positively both the probability of employment and the realized fertility. 
The CRE children's coefficients are smaller than the RE children's coefficients; the coefficients that are most 
affected when changing the estimation technique are those of the dummies indicating the presence of very 
young children (number of children aged 0 -2 and 3 -5 years). This suggests that it is the presence of very 
young children that is most likely correlated with the mother's taste for work -a very plausible result. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>the results obtained from Pooled CS are rather different from those of the RE and 
CRE models, which are instead similar to each other. Before the transition to a 
market economy, women with low or professional education were the most 
penalized by the presence of a young child. Being highly educated was associated 
with a lower but still sizable percentage drop in the probability of working with 
respect to childless women. Similarly, during the transition period, the biggest 
effects -in absolute terms -were estimated for women with low or professional 
education, while the likelihood of employment of women with high educational 
qualifications was less affected by the presence of a young child. These results 
confirm that the educational level was a key dimension affecting employment after </p>

<p>Table 4. Impact of having one child aged 0-2 years on the probability of the mother 
working, by mother's educational level </p>

<p>1987-1989  1994-1995   Pooled 
RE 
CRE 
Pooled 
RE 
CRE </p>

<p>Low education 
Average probability (no child 0 -2) 
0.74 
0.67 
0.65 
0.73 
0.64 
0.64 
Average probability (1 child 0 -2) 
0.64 
0.42 
0.43 
0.68 
0.49 
0.51 
Absolute change 
0.10 
0.25 
0.22 
0.05 
0.15 
0.13 
% change 
13.51 
37.31 
33.85 
6.85 
23.44 
20.31 
High school 
Average probability (no child 0 -2) 
0.78 
0.78 
0.78 
0.77 
0.74 
0.73 
Average probability (1 child 0 -2) 
0.69 
0.54 
0.57 
0.72 
0.60 
0.62 
Absolute change 
0.09 
0.24 
0.21 
0.05 
0.14 
0.11 
% change 
11.54 
30.77 
26.92 
6.49 
18.92 
15.07 
Professional education 
Average probability (no child 0 -2) 
0.75 
0.70 
0.69 
0.74 
0.64 
0.64 
Average probability (1 child 0 -2) 
0.66 
0.45 
0.47 
0.68 
0.49 
0.51 
Absolute change 
0.09 
0.25 
0.22 
0.06 
0.15 
0.13 
% change 
12.00 
35.71 
31.88 
8.11 
23.44 
20.31 
Third level 
Average probability (no child 0 -2) 
0.81 
0.87 
0.87 
0.80 
0.85 
0.85 
Average probability (1 child 0 -2) 
0.77 
0.73 
0.75 
0.78 
0.76 
0.77 
Absolute change 
0.04 
0.14 
0.12 
0.02 
0.09 
0.08 
% change 
4.94 
16.09 
13.79 
2.25 
10.59 
9.41 </p>

<p>Notes: (i) Predicted probabilities are averaged over the observed sample, with simulated values of 
educational levels and presence of kids aged 0 -2 years as indicated. (ii) For RE and CRE models, predicted 
probabilities are population averaged on the distribution of the random effect. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>transition, eventually more important than family circumstances. There is 
abundant evidence that during transition the increase in unemployment hit the 
lowest educated people in particular, 
20 while the demand for employees with high 
level of human capital increased steadily. 
21 On the other hand, the demand for 
employees with primary or incomplete primary education, and for graduates from post-
secondary schools declined significantly (Kwiatkowski, Socha and Sztanderska, 2001). 
Our main finding of a smaller impact of having children on the probability of 
employment in the second period was confirmed in the multivariate analysis; this 
implies that it cannot be assigned to any of the factors that were accounted for in 
the regressions. According to our results, the increasing difficulty of combining 
family and work during transition does not result in a lower participation 
probability of mothers with respect to the pre-transition period, despite a decrease 
in state-subsidized child-care (or the negative effect of the decrease in child-care is 
totally compensated by forces of opposite sign). None of the variables included in 
the model (women's age and education, partner's employment status, earnings of 
the partner, area characteristics) can reverse the finding of a smaller (in absolute 
value) effect of children in the second than in the first period, nor can the fact of 
having allowed for endogenous fertility using the CRE model. But what other 
potential explanations that are not captured by our model can explain this finding? 
There are essentially two categories of explanations that can be put forward at 
this point. A first possibility could be that there is some omitted variable from our 
regressions, and that this(these) variable(s) -correlated with being a mother of 
children of different age groups -is (are) the 'true' explanation(s) of mothers' 
labour supply either before or during transition or both. For example, an increase 
in part-time employment in the transition period could explain why mothers were 
more likely to be employed -availability of part-time employment usually mitigates 
the negative effect of children on women's labour supply. Unfortunately we do not 
have information of whether employment was part-time or full-time, so we cannot 
control for this variable. However, there is evidence of no increase in part-time job 
opportunities in the second period; data provided by enterprises indicate instead 
that a slight drop in the share of part-time employment occurred, from about 10 
percent before transition to 8.8 percent in 1998 (Kwiatkowski, Socha and Sztanderska,  2001). Also, we do not have information on women's earnings and other non-
earned income. It is possible that during transition mothers were pressured to stay 
in employment (if they had a job) or to take up employment because of the 
powerful, negative income effect produced by the drop in real wages (theirs and 
their husband's). </p>

<p>20 Among the unemployed, the majority had only primary (33.4 percent) or basic vocational (37 percent) 
educational qualifications, while only 2.5 percent of the unemployed were graduates of universities 
(Kowalska, 2002). 
21 In the period 1994 -1998, the employment of Polish people with higher education rose the fastest, by 29.1 
percent, while for those with secondary vocational education rose by almost 17 percent. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>The second type of explanation is that the coefficients of the children dummies 
are 'true' effects, that is they capture real preferences, attitudes, or individual or 
social constraints that cannot be incorporated into the regressions. We can think of 
reasons why mothers in the transition period may have had an incentive to remain 
in the labour market. The change in the general economic environment represented 
by the transition to a market economy was characterized by tremendous 
adjustments and restructuring, high layoff rates and low re-employment rates. The 
resulting uncertainty in the labour market could have represented a powerful 
incentive for women to work despite the presence of young children. Moreover, in 
the first period, despite labour market constraints (including no unemployment) 
being much lower and women's labour market participation rate being higher, the 
traditional role of caregiver assigned to women represented a powerful disincentive 
for mothers of young children to join the labour market. 
Finally, the two phenomena that lead us to expect a stronger disadvantage for 
mothers in the second period -increasing labour market discrimination and 
substantial cuts in child-care facilities -may have been overemphasized as far as 
their effects on the labour market participation of mothers of young children are 
concerned. Lohmann and Seibert (2003) report that, during transition, employers 
preferred women aged 25 -35 years over older women. The reasons for this preference 
probably being that younger women are better educated, better able to adapt to a 
free market economy, more likely to master ICTs and foreign languages, and also 
more physically attractive. That is, as much as employers may have disliked the 
possibility that these women could become mothers, there were plenty of advantages 
in hiring younger rather than older women that compensated for the risk of the 
employee becoming pregnant. On the other hand, younger women, many of them 
highly educated, were eager to stay in employment even after the birth of a child 
to make the most of career opportunities that were much more exciting than in the 
pre-transition period. As for child-care provision, while it dramatically decreased 
during the 1990s and its cost soared, this was much less the case for nurseries, 
which were very few even before transition. In general, child care was not 
adequate before transition and was less widespread than in other countries of the 
former Socialist Block, especially in rural areas. As a matter of fact, only 4 percent 
of children below 3 years were enrolled in day nurseries in the 1980s. </p>

<p>22   Interestingly, a demographic study on the propensity of becoming a mother 
before 1989 reaches conclusions that are coherent with our findings. In comparing 
first-birth intensity in Hungary and Poland during state socialism, Oláh and  Fratczak (2004) find that in Poland, where the family policies were less generous 
than in Hungary, the propensity to become a mother was reduced for employed 
women. Although they investigate fertility choices (rather than labour supply 
behaviour), one of their main findings is that the combination of full-time employment </p>

<p>22 Statistical Yearbook for Poland, as reported in Oláh and Fratczak (2004). </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>and family responsibilities was more difficult in pre-transition Poland than in 
Hungary. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>6. Concluding remarks </p>

<p>In this article we have analyzed the relationship between motherhood and employ-
ment probabilities of Polish women before and during transition using panel data 
for the periods of 1987-1989 and 1994 -1996. Before transition, despite the very high 
female participation in employment, Polish mothers -especially mothers of young 
children -were substantially less likely to work than childless women. During 
transition, to our surprise, the negative effect of motherhood was substantially 
lower than in the pre-transition period. In the multivariate analysis, a significant 
coefficient was estimated only for mothers of children aged 0-2 years old and even 
in this case the average population effect turned out to be much smaller than in the 
pre-transition period. This result goes in the opposite direction to what one would 
have expected, based on the common notions of very high female labour market 
participation in the communist Poland, sustained by the existence of family-friendly 
policies and a publicly-funded affordable network of child-care facilities, which 
were dismantled during transition, making women's participation in employment 
theoretically more difficult. 
Our findings are not driven by a change in the association of the 'taste for 
children' and the 'taste for employment' in the two periods, because our estimates 
-obtained with CRE panel probit models -control for unobserved heterogeneity 
in the two samples. The most plausible interpretation is that, before transition, in 
absence of constraints in accessing the labour market, women could realize their 
preferences for lower employment in coincidence of motherhood or were 'forced' 
out of work by the expectations of a traditional society that required mothers 
(especially of very young children) to be the primary caretakers of their children. 
At the same time, although child-care services were much more affordable before 
than during transition, in the pre-1989 Poland availability of child care was already 
a problem, especially for very young children and in the rural areas of the country. 
On the other hand, during transition, the uncertainty in the labour market, the 
process of restructuring, the necessity of relying on two earners in the household, 
the need (and desire) of not being cut out of new job opportunities in the growing 
private sector, and the gloomy perspective of long-term unemployment after a 
prolonged period out of the labour market could have represented more powerful 
'pushing' factors for women to work than the disincentive produced by the 
deterioration of child-care facilities. This is not to say that women were not experi-
encing growing difficulties in combining paid work and family responsibilities, </p>

<p>23 They estimate that in Poland housewives and part-time employed women had more than 30 percent 
higher propensity to have a first child than childless women working full-time. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>nor that this conflict was without potentially negative consequences for women's 
employment. It rather stresses how powerful were constraints other than the 
decrease in child-care availability (many of them on the demand-side) in shaping 
women's employment opportunities during transition. </p>



<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>







<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Table A1. Descriptive statistics. Women aged 16-44 years with partner and 
household responsibilities </p>

<p>Balanced panel 
1987-1989 
1994-1996 </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Mean 
SD </p>

<p>Employed 
0.67 
0.47 
0.67 
0.47 
Age 
33.62 
5.14 
35.30 
5.56 
High school 
0.37 
0.48 
0.39 
0.49 
Professional education 
0.32 
0.48 
0.35 
0.48 
University 
0.07 
0.25 
0.10 
0.29 
Number of children 0 -2 yrs old 
0.26 
0.49 
0.18 
0.42 
Number of children 3 -5 yrs old 
0.45 
0.62 
0.30 
0.53 
Number of children 6 -11 yrs old 
0.85 
0.85 
0.78 
0.84 
Number of children 12-17 yrs old 
0.59 
0.80 
0.72 
0.86 
Partner high school education 
0.21 
0.40 
0.26 
0.44 
Partner professional education 
0.47 
0.50 
0.51 
0.50 
Partner university education 
0.08 
0.27 
0.08 
0.27 
Age of the partner 
36.51 
6.37 
38.13 
6.11 
Working partner 
0.95 
0.22 
0.86 
0.35 
Partner's earnings (only positive values, if working) 
143.69 
106.77 
751.18 
710.073 
House ownership 
0.64 
0.48 
0.60 
0.49 
Number of observations 
3,063 
5,055 </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table A2. Estimation results, pre-transition period (1987-1989) </p>

<p>Pooled cross 
section probit 
model (1) </p>

<p>Random effect 
probit model (2) </p>

<p>Correlated 
random effect 
probit model (3) </p>

<p>Coefficient 
SE 
Coefficient 
SE 
Coefficient 
SE </p>

<p>Age 
0.359*** 
0.109 
0.572** 
0.235 
0.540** 
0.240 
Age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>−0.005*** 
0.002 
−0.007** 
0.003 
−0.007** 
0.003 
High school 
0.514*** 
0.134 
0.974*** 
0.278 
1.038*** 
0.282 
Professional education 
0.178 
0.122 
0.290 
0.251 
0.298 
0.253 
University 
1.052*** 
0.236 
1.999*** 
0.478 
2.034*** 
0.484 
Number of children 0 -2 yrs old 
−0.946*** 
0.085 
−1.914*** 
0.157 
−1.739*** 
0.219 
Number of children 3 -5 yrs old 
−0.418*** 
0.065 
−0.930*** 
0.133 
−0.952*** 
0.225 
Number of children 6 -11 yrs old 
−0.2085*** 
0.055 
−0.535*** 
0.113 
−0.821*** 
0.219 
Number of children 12 -17 yrs old 
0.043 
0.063 
−0.072 
0.124 
−0.479** 
0.218 
Average number of 
children 0-2 yrs old </p>

<p>−0.665** 
0.336 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 3-5 yrs old </p>

<p>−0.014 
0.305 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 6-11 yrs old </p>

<p>0.376 
0.249 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 12-17 yrs old </p>

<p>0.615** 
0.272 </p>

<p>Year 1988 
0.016 
0.044 
−0.033 
0.110 
0.063 
0.114 
Year 1989 
0.276** 
0.113 
−0.007 
0.199 
0.187 
0.208 
Partner high school education 
−0.007 
0.148 
−0.016 
0.307 
−0.002 
0.311 
Partner professional education 
−0.047 
0.119 
−0.106 
0.242 
−0.115 
0.244 
Partner university education 
−0.484** 
0.214 
−1.226*** 
0.454 
−1.170** 
0.459 
Age of the partner 
−0.032 
0.0712 
0.036 
0.153 
−0.019 
0.157 
Age of the partner </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.0003 
0.001 
−0.0006 
0.0019 
0.0001 
0.002 
Working partner 
0.067 
0.188 
−0.482 
0.358 
−0.438 
0.361 
Partner's earnings/1,000 
−0.022*** 
0.005 
−0.014 
0.009 
−0.015 
0.009 
House ownership 
0.183** 
0.092 
0.313* 
0.182 
0.333* 
0.183 
Constant 
−5.183*** 
1.667 
−9.159*** 
3.539 
−7.256** 
3.679 
⁄ 
0.821*** 
0.015 
0.823*** 
0.015 
Number of observations 
3,056 
3,056 
3,056 
Number of groups 
1,021 
1,021 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.277 
Log-likelihood 
−1,397.16 
−1,060.02 
−1,053.36 
Likelihood ratio test of 
ρ = 0 (P &gt; χ 
2 ) </p>

<p>674.28 
(0.00) </p>

<p>676.08 
(0.00) 
Joint significance of average 
number of children variables 
in CRE (P &gt; χ 
2 ) </p>

<p>13.03 
(0.01) </p>

<p>Notes: (i) The base categories of the dummy variables are: primary education or first level secondary 
education; no children or children over 18 years old; year 1987; partner with primary education or first level 
secondary education. (ii) Regressors also include 49 voivodship dummies and a dummy for the partner in 
employment reporting zero earnings. (iii) Standard errors (SE) (in italics) are adjusted for clustering on 
individuals. (iv) *** Significant at the 1% level, ** 5% level and *10% level. </p>



<p>Bardasi and Monfardini </p>

<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table A3. Estimation results, post-transition period (1994-1996) </p>

<p>Pooled cross 
section probit 
model (1) </p>

<p>Random effect 
probit model (2) </p>

<p>Correlated 
random effect 
probit model (3) </p>

<p>Coefficient 
SE 
Coefficient 
SE 
Coefficient 
SE </p>

<p>Age 
0.150* 
0.079 
0.321* 
0.170 
0.301* 
0.171 
Age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>−0.002* 
0.001 
−0.004* 
0.002 
−0.004 
0.002 
High school 
0.336*** 
0.096 
0.665*** 
0.205 
0.659*** 
0.206 
Professional education 
0.0371 
0.091 
0.016 
0.190 
0.003 
0.190 
University 
0.798*** 
0.148 
1.756*** 
0.327 
1.754*** 
0.328 
Number of children 0-2 yrs old 
−0.427*** 
0.064 
−0.979*** 
0.116 
−0.808*** 
0.159 
Number of children 3-5 yrs old 
−0.243*** 
0.051 
−0.393*** 
0.095 
−0.101 
0.162 
Number of children 6-11 yrs old 
−0.097*** 
0.036 
−0.212*** 
0.076 
−0.043 
0.149 
Number of children 12-17 yrs old 
0.007 
0.038 
−0.039 
0.073 
−0.007 
0.124 
Average number of 
children 0-2 yrs old </p>

<p>−0.122 
0.263 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 3-5 yrs old </p>

<p>−0.603*** 
0.228 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 6-11 yrs old </p>

<p>−0.166 
0.169 </p>

<p>Average number of 
children 12-17 yrs old </p>

<p>0.042 
0.156 </p>

<p>Year 1988 
−0.064 
0.042 
0.051 
0.095 
0.004 
0.092 
Year 1989 
−0.069 
0.047 
0.050 
0.097 
0.035 
0.098 
Partner high school education 
0.039 
0.106 
0.183 
0.227 
0.183 
0.228 
Partner professional education 
0.012 
0.091 
0.123 
0.191 
0.117 
0.191 
Partner university education 
0.056 
0.149 
0.172 
0.327 
0.173 
0.328 
Age of the partner 
−0.059 
0.055 
−0.088 
0.127 
−0.114 
0.127 
Age of the partner </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.0007 
0.0007 
0.001 
0.002 
0.001 
0.002 
Working partner 
0.052 
0.073 
0.037 
0.126 
0.077 
0.126 
Partner's earnings/1000 
−0.000002 
0.000009 −0.000008 
0.00012 −0.00013 
0.00012 
House ownership 
0.297* 
0.060 
0.582*** 
0.120 
0.578*** 
0.120 
Constant 
−1.546 
1.159 
−4.027 
2.392 
−2.911 
2.454 
⁄ 
0.822*** 
0.011 
0.822*** 
0.011 
Number of observations 
5,055 
5,055 
5,055 
Number of groups 
1,685 
1,685 
Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.096 
Log-likelihood 
−2,905.954 
−2,189.373 
−2,182.358 
Likelihood ratio test of 
ρ = 0 (P &gt; χ 
2 ) </p>

<p>1,433.2 
(0.000) </p>

<p>1,424.8 
(0.000) 
Joint significance of average 
number of children variables 
in CRE (P &gt; χ 
2 ) </p>

<p>8.19 
(0.085) </p>

<p>Notes: (i) The base categories of the dummy variables are: primary education or first level secondary 
education; no children or children over 18 years old; year 1996; partner with primary education or first level 
secondary education. (ii) Regressors also include 49 voivodship dummies and a dummy for the partner in 
employment reporting zero earnings. (iii) Standard errors (in italics) are adjusted for clustering on 
individuals. (iv) *** Significant at the 1% level, ** 5% level and * 10% level. </p>

<p>Women's Employment, Children and Transition </p>



<p>© 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation © 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table A4. Tests of strict exogeneity of fertility variables </p>

<p>χ χ χ 
χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P &gt; χ χ χ 
χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Pre-transition period (1987-1989) 
Pooled cross-section probit model 
5.99 
0.1998 
Random effects probit model 
5.24 
0.2640 
Correlated random effects probit model 
1.82 
0.7692 
Transition period (1994 -1996)  Pooled cross-section probit model 
3.69 
0.4498 
Random effects probit model 
16.20 
0.0028 
Correlated random effects probit model 
6.25 
0.1810 </p>

<p>Notes: (i) This is a test of joint significance of the 1 period forwarded variables: number of children 0-2 yrs old, 
number of children 3 -5 yrs old, number of children 6 -11 yrs old, number of children 12-17 yrs old. (ii) The 
required estimation involves the loss of the last year in both samples. This delivers a sample of 2,037 
observations in the first period, 3,370 in the second. </p>

</text></tei>