<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1002%2Fpam.22030" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Using difference-in-difference and difference-in-difference-in-difference designs, we 
study California's Paid Family Leave (CA-PFL) program, the first source of government-
provided paid parental leave available to fathers in the Unites States. Relative to the 
pre-treatment mean, fathers of infants in California are 46 percent more likely to be 
on leave when CA-PFL is available. In households where both parents work, we find 
suggestive evidence that CA-PFL increases both father-only leave-taking (i.e., father on 
leave while mother is at work) and joint leave-taking (i.e., both parents on leave at the 
same time). Effects are larger for fathers of first-born children than for fathers of later-
born children. C 
2017 by the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management. </p>

<p>Paid family leave (PFL) policies provide workers with paid time off from work to 
care for newborn or newly-adopted children, as well as seriously ill family members. 
PFL policies may be especially important for new parents, who often struggle to 
balance competing work and family responsibilities. Parents with access to PFL can 
stay home to care for and bond with their new children, and then return to work 
with minimal career interruptions. But despite the importance of these benefits, the 
United States is one of just a handful of countries without a national PFL policy. 
The Unites States offers 12 weeks of unpaid leave to some (but not all) workers 
through the federal Family and Medical Leave Act (FMLA). 1 However, three recent 
state-level PFL programs in California, New Jersey, and Rhode Island supply nearly 
all workers with access to PFL, and similar programs in New York and the District 
of Columbia will take effect in 2018 and 2020, respectively. 
Although historically paid leave policies only applied to women, modern PFL 
programs typically cover (although not necessarily equally) both male and female 
workers. This paper uses large-scale data to study the effects of California's first-in-
the-nation gender-neutral PFL (CA-PFL) policy on paternal leave-taking, as well as 
on how fathers and mothers in dual-earner households share leave-taking responsi-
bilities. 2 CA-PFL was introduced in 2004 and offers six weeks of paid leave to nearly </p>

<p>1 Because of the strict eligibility requirements, less than 60 percent of private sector workers are eligible 
for FMLA (Klerman, Daley, &amp; Pozniak, 2012), and the impacts of the law are concentrated among 
relatively advantaged workers, who are more likely to be eligible and able to afford unpaid time off work. 
2 Five states, including California (as well as Hawaii, New Jersey, New York, and Rhode Island), have 
offered paid maternity leave to birth mothers through their Temporary Disability Insurance (TDI) systems </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management, Vol. 37, No. 1, 10-37 (2018) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2017 by the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management 
Published by Wiley Periodicals, Inc. View this article online at wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/pam 
DOI:10.1002/pam.22030 </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 11 </p>

<p>all new parents, with a 55 percent wage replacement rate up to a ceiling (a maximum 
benefit of $1,173 per week in 2017). 3 This leave is not directly job protected, but job 
protection is available if the job absence simultaneously qualifies under the FMLA. 
Our focus on the leave-taking outcomes of fathers is particularly salient in light of 
recent evidence that American fathers report equal or greater levels of work-family 
conflict as do mothers (Auman, Galinsky, &amp; Matos, 2011; Rehel &amp; Baxter, 2015). 
Understanding how PFL policies specifically affect fathers is important because 
they may respond to such policies differently from mothers for at least two reasons. 
First, despite some convergence in earnings between men and women over the 
last several decades, fathers continue to be the main breadwinners in many U.S. 
families. 4 Thus, the financial shock to the family associated with only partial wage 
replacement and a lack of job protection during leave (as in CA-PFL) may be more 
consequential when fathers take leave than when mothers do. Second, new fathers 
have less biological need for leave than new mothers, who need time off from work 
to recover from childbirth and establish breastfeeding. 
Fathers' access to paid leave on the private market is very low. For instance, a 
2012 report indicates that only 14 percent of U.S. employers offer paid paternity 
leave to most or all of their male employees (Klerman, Daley, &amp; Pozniak, 2012). As a 
consequence, new fathers tend to take very little time off work when their children 
are born. In 2013, less than 2 percent of employed fathers of children under the 
age of one reported being on leave (vs. 14 percent of employed mothers), and these 
rates have remained very stable over the last decade. 5 Even in California, where 
both mothers and fathers are covered by PFL, a large majority of parental leave 
claims have been made by mothers. However, paternal take-up has increased sub-
stantially over the first decade of the policy. In 2005, only 19.6 percent of all CA-PFL 
claims were filed by men. By 2013, fathers were responsible for about 30 percent 
of claims. Low rates of paternal leave-taking make analysis of PFL among fathers 
difficult because most data sets lack sufficient numbers of fathers who are on leave 
to produce reliable estimates of program effects. To address this issue, we use data 
from the 2000 Census and the 2000 to 2013 waves of the American Community Sur-
vey (ACS), together with difference-in-difference (DD) and difference-in-difference-
in-difference (DDD) methods, to identify the causal effects of CA-PFL on paternal 
leave-taking. Our preferred DDD specification compares employed fathers of infants 
in California to employed fathers of children aged 1 to 3, relative to corresponding 
fathers of the same age children in other states, before and after the introduction 
of CA-PFL. We perform an analogous analysis of mothers to enable comparisons of 
effects across parental gender within the same data set. In dual-earner households, 
we also separately examine impacts on joint leave-taking-where both parents are 
simultaneously on leave-vs. "father-only" or "mother-only" leave-taking while the 
other parent is at work, or "either parent" leave-taking (i.e., either the mother or the 
father is on leave). Further, our relatively large sample sizes enable us to examine het-
erogeneity in the program's effects by birth order, child gender, and family income. </p>

<p>since 1979. TDI allows pregnant and post-partum women to take six to 10 weeks of paid leave to prepare 
for and recover from childbirth. TDI covers birth mothers only. CA-PFL is the first source of legislation 
providing paid paternity leave in the United States. 
3 CA-PFL covers essentially all private sector workers. To be eligible for the program, individuals 
are required to have earned at least $300 in wages during a "base period" of five to 18 months 
before the PFL claim begins. Additional information on the California program is available at 
http://www.edd.ca.gov/disability/FAQ_PFL_Benefits.htm. 
4 According to the Bureau of Labor Statistics, even in two-earner families, men bring in over half of 
family earnings in approximately 70 percent of households. 
5 These estimates come from the 2013 American Communities Survey. The outcome refers to individuals 
who are employed but absent from work in the week prior to the survey (i.e., survey reference week). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>In our preferred specification, we find that CA-PFL raises the share of fathers 
of infants on leave from work in a given week by about 0.9 percentage points, or 
46 percent relative to the pre-PFL mean of 2 percent. Among households with two 
married and employed parents, about half of this increase is driven by fathers taking 
leave at the same time as the child's mother and the other half by fathers who take 
leave on their own, while the mother is at work. The 2 percent baseline leave-taking 
rate is consistent with fathers taking about one week of leave on average after 
their child's birth, and CA-PFL increases that amount to nearly 1.5 weeks. 6 We 
also find some heterogeneity in parental leave-taking by birth order-the effects on 
leave-taking are almost entirely driven by fathers of first-born children (i.e., those 
with no other siblings in the household), while the corresponding differences for 
mothers are much smaller. We do not find robust statistically significant evidence 
of heterogeneity in leave-taking effects along the other dimensions that we consider 
(child gender and family income). The lack of significant heterogeneity by income 
suggests that the policy is relatively neutral with regard to distributional implica-
tions, and that our results from California may be generalizable to other states that 
are considering similar PFL programs but have different income distributions. 
Our study is most closely related to a recent paper by Baum and Ruhm (2016), 
who use data from the National Longitudinal Survey of Youth (NLSY) to estimate 
the impacts of CA-PFL on both mothers' and fathers' leave-taking and maternal 
labor market outcomes. Our paper makes four contributions relative to Baum and 
Ruhm. First, our analysis is able to confirm Baum and Ruhm's main finding for 
fathers-a two to three day increase in leave-taking-using a much larger and more 
representative data set. Second, the larger sample size in our study permits us to 
examine new forms of heterogeneity in the effects of CA-PFL on paternal leave-
taking. 7 Third, we provide novel insights into simultaneous vs. separate leave use 
within households with two employed parents. Fourth, we address a critical issue 
affecting inference in the DD and DDD analyses commonly used in the literature 
on CA-PFL (including Baum &amp; Ruhm, 2016; Rossin-Slater, Ruhm, &amp; Waldfogel, 
2013). These studies have a small number of treated groups (most often, just one) 
and variation in the number of observations per group, making standard errors 
clustered at the group level unsuitable (Bertrand, Duflo, &amp; Mullainathan, 2004; 
Donald &amp; Lang, 2007; Ferman &amp; Pinto, 2016; MacKinnon &amp; Webb, 2017). Here, we 
explicitly examine the sensitivity of our estimates to alternative inference methods 
accounting for both the small number of treatment groups and heteroskedasticity 
in the error structure. </p>

<p>RELATED LITERATURE AND HYPOTHESES </p>

<p>Understanding the extent to which CA-PFL increases paternal leave-taking is impor-
tant because we know relatively little about the effects of parental leave programs 
on fathers. 8 While several papers study European and Canadian paternity leave 
reforms aimed at increasing fathers' leave-taking, this evidence may have limited </p>

<p>6 This assumes births are uniformly distributed throughout the year. We discuss the validity of the 
assumption of a uniform distribution of births in the third section below. 
7 Baum and Ruhm's sample contained only 158 fathers in the post-PFL treatment group. 
8 The literature on the effects of leave policies for mothers typically finds large effects on paid leave 
take-up rates (see Olivetti &amp; Petrongolo, 2017, and Rossin-Slater, 2017, for recent overviews), but mixed 
effects on subsequent labor market outcomes (Baker &amp; Milligan, 2008; Bergemann &amp; Riphahn, 2015; 
 &amp; , 2016; Dahl et al., 2016; Lalive et al., 2014; Lequien, 2012; Schönberg &amp; Ludsteck, 
2014; Stearns, 2016). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 13 </p>

<p>relevance to the current U.S. policy landscape for a few reasons. 9 In particular, CA-
PFL is much less generous in terms of the wage replacement rate and duration than 
many of the European policies, and does not offer job protection. 10 The broader 
policy landscape could matter for understanding the impacts of PFL-a reform that 
expands PFL in a setting with subsidized child care and universal health insurance 
(e.g., as in Sweden) may be dramatically different from one where PFL is introduced 
for the first time and neither child care nor health insurance are guaranteed (as in 
the United States today). Finally, CA-PFL is a gender-neutral program where eligi-
ble parents are entitled to take the same amount of leave, either simultaneously or 
separately. In contrast, parental leave in many European countries is allocated at 
the household level and parents must decide how to share it. 
Despite the differences between the Unites States and European context, the 
existing literature suggests that the introduction of CA-PFL should increase pater-
nal leave-taking rates. Although we hypothesize that father's leave-taking should 
increase as a result of the policy, we expect that the effect size may be smaller 
than it is for mothers. 11 Because a newborn places higher biological demands on 
mothers, and fathers are on average higher earners, mothers may experience larger 
absolute increases in leave-taking than fathers. On the other hand, fathers may have 
larger relative increases in leave-taking because their baseline leave-taking rates are 
substantially lower than those of mothers and they are less likely to have access to 
employer-provided PFL. 
It is less clear how CA-PFL will affect when fathers take leave relative to their 
spouse in dual-earner households. Baum and Ruhm (2016) show that in the ab-
sence of PFL, fathers take about a week of leave on average immediately after the 
child's birth. CA-PFL may increase joint leave-taking if it encourages fathers to take 
additional time off around the birth, rather than later in the year after the mother 
has returned to work. But CA-PFL gives parents access to six weeks of leave that 
can be used anytime during the first year of the child's life, and does not have to 
be used all at once. If dual-earner families try to maximize the total amount of 
time the infant spends at home with a parent, the policy may increase "father-only" 
leave-taking as well. 
We also look for heterogeneity in the effects of CA-PFL by birth order, child 
gender, and family income. Recent studies suggest that there is heterogeneity in 
leave-taking patterns by birth order for both mothers (Han et al., 2008) and fathers 
(Nepomnyaschy &amp; Waldfogel, 2007; Patnaik, 2015), motivating our exploration of 
whether the effects of CA-PFL also vary with birth order. We hypothesize that the 
effects of CA-PFL will be larger for parents of first-born than later-born children. 
Substantial "start-up" costs are associated with having a family-both mothers and 
fathers must adjust to becoming a parent, and they are also typically less experienced 
in newborn care and may not yet have any child care arrangements when their first 
child is born (Cowan &amp; Cowan, 2000; Waldfogel, 2006). By contrast, the marginal 
cost of a subsequent child is arguably smaller-parents of second or higher-order 
children may be more prepared and their lives may be less disrupted by the birth. </p>

<p>9 These policies are sometimes referred to as "daddy quotas" or "daddy months" and have been studied 
in Sweden (Duvander &amp; Johansson, 2012; Ekberg, Eriksson, &amp; Friebel, 2013), Norway (Cools, Fiva, &amp; 
Kirkebøen, 2015; Dahl, Løken, &amp; Mogstad, 2014), Germany (Schober, 2014), and Canada (Patnaik, 2015). 
10 Recent work suggests that the impacts of leave are non-linear in duration (Olivetti &amp; Petrongolo, 2017; 
Ruhm, 1998). Han, Ruhm, and Waldfogel (2009) estimate that the unpaid leave made available to fathers 
under the FMLA increased their leave-taking by an average of around two days. Job protection is available 
in the Rhode Island and New York PFL policies, but not in California, New Jersey, or Washington, DC. 
11 Several studies outside the Unites States have examined the effects of gender-neutral family leave 
reforms on men's and women's leave-taking, finding bigger impacts on mothers than fathers (e.g., Kleven, 
Landais, &amp; Sogaard, 2017; Patnaik, 2015; Sundström &amp; Duvander, 2002). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Given the large literature on paternal son-preference (marriage and divorce: 
Bedard &amp; , 2005; Dahl &amp; Moretti, 2008; Lundberg, McLanahan, &amp; Rose, 
2007; Lundberg &amp; Rose, 2003; paternity acknowledgment: Almond &amp; Rossin-Slater, 
2013; paternity leave: Tanaka &amp; Waldfogel, 2007), we also expect that fathers' 
response to CA-PFL may be greater when they have sons compared to daughters. At 
least two explanations are there for this phenomenon. First, it may be that fathers 
get more utility from spending time at home with sons rather than daughters. 
Second, they may perceive that paternal time spent caring for boys is relatively 
more productive than time spent caring for girls. While we cannot distinguish 
between these two channels in our data, the latter explanation seems less plausible 
given that it is unlikely that fathers have a relative advantage in caring for boys 
around the time of birth. 
Finally, there are reasons to expect that the effects of CA-PFL may differ by 
family income. 12 The lack of job protection and the relatively low wage replacement 
rate available under CA-PFL may be more prohibitive for fathers in lower-income 
families, suggesting larger effects among higher-income families. Fathers in higher-
income families are more likely to have access to employer-provided paid paternity 
leave, however, and face a higher opportunity cost of taking leave (Klerman, Daley, 
&amp; Pozniak, 2012). This may mean that they have less demand for government-
provided PFL than men in lower-income families. In fact, research on the effects of 
CA-PFL on mothers finds that the largest effects on leave-taking are concentrated 
among the least advantaged mothers (Rossin-Slater, Ruhm, &amp; Waldfogel, 2013). </p>

<p>DATA </p>

<p>We use data from the 2000 Census and the 2000 to 2013 waves of the ACS to estimate 
the effects of CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking. The ACS is conducted throughout the 
year and samples 1 percent of the population in most years; thus, it has the major 
advantage of providing the large samples needed to examine leave-taking behavior 
among fathers. 13 When weighted, the ACS is a nationally representative survey that 
provides information about labor market experiences and demographic factors. For 
our purposes, what is particularly important is that individuals are questioned about 
their labor market status in the week prior to the survey-referred to as the "survey 
reference week"-allowing us to identify leave-taking during that week. Although 
the ACS does not ask about parental leave vs. other specific types of leave, it does 
identify individuals who are temporarily absent from work during that week. The 
main dependent variable that we examine below is whether the father (or mother) 
is on leave from work in the survey reference week. This absence could be for many 
reasons including parental leave, vacation, or illness. 14 This lack of specificity is not </p>

<p>12 We adjust family income to account for the number of adults and children in the household. This 
adjustment is explained below in the fifth section. 
13 Data come from the Integrated Public Use Microdata Series (<rs type="software">IPUMS</rs>) database (Ruggles et al., 2010). 
The ACS started in 2000, and was only a 0.13 percent sample in that year. For the next four years, it 
was approximately a 0.5 percent sample of the population. The questions used in this study are very 
comparable in the ACS and the 2000 long-form Census. This analysis combines the 2000 ACS with the 
1 percent 2000 Census sample in order to increase the sample size in that year. We also show that our 
main results are robust to dropping the 2000 data. 
14 Specifically, the question asked is: "LAST WEEK, was this person TEMPORARILY absent from a job 
or business?" Respondents can answer "Yes, on vacation, temporary illness, labor dispute, and so forth." 
or "No." The Current Population Survey (CPS) asks about maternity and paternity leave specifically and 
is used to identify the effect of CA-PFL on mothers' leave-taking in Rossin-Slater, Ruhm, and Waldfogel 
(2013). However, the sample of fathers on leave in California in the CPS is too small to produce meaningful 
estimates. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 15 </p>

<p>a problem for our analysis because we are interested in any type of leave taken by a 
father of an infant, regardless of whether it is called parental leave, vacation leave, 
sick leave, or something else. 
As detailed below, our empirical strategy focuses on whether leave-taking of any 
kind increases more among fathers of infants in California post-law than it does for 
the comparison groups. The use of appropriate control groups nets out changes in 
other types of leave-taking that may have occurred for reasons unrelated to the PFL 
law. Unfortunately, the survey does not inquire about the length of the temporary 
work absence, so we do not know whether it lasted longer than the survey reference 
week. 15 
In addition to not specifying the length of leave, there are two other limitations 
of the ACS data. First, fathers can only be linked to children who live in the same 
household. The analysis therefore excludes fathers who do not live with their chil-
dren. 16 Assuming that non-resident fathers are less involved with their children than 
resident fathers, our results will overstate the increase in leave-taking for the aver-
age new father (including those not living with their infants). Second, the ACS lacks 
precise information on children's birth dates, and only reports the age of the child in 
years. Although CA-PFL can be used at any time in the first 12 months of the child's 
life, as noted above, most fathers take only brief leaves that occur soon after the 
birth (Baum &amp; Ruhm, 2016). Since we observe leave-taking in only a single week, 
we will therefore miss most of these leaves. 17 However, under the assumptions that 
births and the average length of leave are both approximately uniformly distributed 
throughout the year, the percentage change in leave-taking estimated to result from 
the policy will be accurately captured, although the levels will be understated. 18 
The analysis sample is limited to fathers who are 16 to 54 years old and employed 
in the survey reference week. We condition on employment because those who are 
not employed are less likely to be eligible for PFL and because we will not observe 
them as leave-takers in the ACS. 19 However, we show below in the sixth section 
that the results are robust to including all fathers in the analysis, regardless of 
employment status. We also demonstrate that CA-PFL does not affect the probability 
that fathers of infants are employed, which is unsurprising given the short amount 
of paid leave available. We do not observe CA-PFL eligibility status directly, and 
so our estimation procedure treats all employed fathers in California as eligible for 
paid leave if their youngest own child in the household is less than 1-year-old. To 
the extent this assumption is incorrect (e.g., some fathers working in the public </p>

<p>15 The ACS question about temporary work absences should only be answered by individuals who report 
not working at all during the survey reference week, and so therefore should only capture work absences 
that last at least a full week. Our results are likely underestimated if CA-PFL increases partial-week 
leave-taking. Data on hours of work during the survey reference week are not available in the ACS, so we 
cannot examine this. Another limitation is that the ACS does not distinguish between paid and unpaid 
leave. 
16 In our data, 74.5 percent of infants are identified as living with their biological father (more specifically, 
67 percent live with both parents, while 7.5 percent live with only their father). 88 percent of infants are 
identified as living with their mother. 
17 Both of these limitations also apply to mothers, but to a lesser extent, since most children in single 
parent households live with mothers, and mothers typically take much longer leaves than fathers. 
18 We checked the validity of the assumption that U.S. births are uniformly distributed throughout the 
year using 2011 birth record data from the National Center for Health Statistics (NCHS) Vital Statistics. 
The shortest month, February, had the lowest number of births in 2011 (7.5 percent). April had the 
second lowest number of births (7.9 percent). August had the most births (9.1 percent). The ACS does 
not contain information about the month of the survey, so we cannot measure the timing of leave relative 
to birth even under these assumptions. 
19 Some non-employed fathers, who previously worked, may be eligible for CA-PFL benefits because the 
work history requirements for receiving it are so weak. However, we will not observe this in our data 
since such men will not be classified as being temporarily absent from work. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Notes: This figure plots the mean leave-taking rate for California fathers of youngest children aged less 
than 1-year-old (in the solid line) and fathers of youngest children aged less than 1-year-old in all other 
states (in the dashed line). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Fathers' Leave-Taking in CA Compared to Other States, Youngest Child 
Less Than Age 1. </p>

<p>sector are not eligible), we will understate the increases in leave-taking occurring 
for eligible fathers. 
The first five columns of Appendix Table A1 report summary statistics for the 
sample of fathers used in our preferred empirical specification, which compares 
employed fathers of infants less than 1-year-old to employed fathers of youngest 
children aged 1 to 3, in California vs. corresponding fathers in other states. 20 For 
comparison, we also report the same summary statistics for employed mothers in 
the subsequent five columns. All statistics are weighted by the ACS person weights. 
Several important differences exist between parents of infants in California and 
parents of infants in other states. Most notably, California parents are more likely to 
be Hispanic and less likely to be non-Hispanic white. A substantially higher fraction 
has less than a high school education and are not citizens, although mean household 
income (in 2010 dollars) is somewhat higher. Finally, parents of infants in California 
are more likely to be on leave than those in other states, suggesting that CA-PFL 
may have had an effect on leave-taking. 
Figure 1 plots the percentage of fathers with infants on leave in California vs. all 
other states. After CA-PFL is implemented, there is a large increase in leave-taking 
in California relative to elsewhere in the United States in most years. 21 We explore 
this relationship further using regression models. </p>

<p>20 All appendices are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's 
website and use the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. 
21 The jump in leave-taking rates between 2000 and 2001 is likely because we combine data from the 
Census and the ACS in 2000 and use only the ACS starting in 2001. Results are robust to dropping 
2000. The national downward trend in fathers' leave-taking starting in 2008 may be due to the recession, 
as leave-taking is negatively correlated with the unemployment rate. Our preferred DDD specification 
includes state-by-year interactions to account for differential impacts of the Great Recession across 
states. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 17 </p>

<p>EMPIRICAL STRATEGY </p>

<p>To identify the impact of CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking behavior, we begin 
with a DD framework, comparing leave-taking rates among fathers of infants in 
California before and after the implementation of CA-PFL to the same difference 
for a comparison group of either California fathers with slightly older children, 
who are not expected to be affected by the policy, or fathers of infants in other 
states. Specifically, we estimate: </p>

<p>Y ist = β 0 + β 1 Treat ist + β 2 Treat ist  *  Post t + γ X ist + ρ C st + δ s + φ t + ε ist 
(1) </p>

<p>where the outcome Y ist is an indicator equal to one if individual i living in state s 
who is surveyed in year t is on leave from work in the survey reference week and 
zero otherwise. The dummy variable Treat ist is equal to one for California fathers 
of infants and Post t is an indicator equal to one if the individual is surveyed in 2005 
or later. 22 The vector X ist contains the following individual-level indicator variables: 
father's age in bins (less than 20, 20 to 24, 25 to 29, 30 to 34, 35 to 39, 40 to 44, 45 
to 49, and 50 to 54), race or ethnicity (non-Hispanic White, Black, Hispanic, Asian, 
other race), education categories (less than high school, high school, some college, 
four-year degree or more), marital status, citizenship status, the age of the youngest 
child in the household in years, and the total number of children in the household. 
We also include the following state-year controls in vector C st to account for labor 
market conditions and other state-specific factors affecting the decision to work: 
unemployment rate, average welfare benefit for a four-person family, poverty rate, 
state minimum wage, per capita income, the log of the population, and an indicator 
for whether or not the governor is Democratic. 23 State and year fixed effects are 
captured by δ s and φ t , respectively, with the Post t main effect being subsumed into 
the time fixed effects. The coefficient of interest, β 2 , is the DD estimate of the effect of 
CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking in California. We estimate equation (1) as a linear 
probability model, but results are very similar when instead estimating a probit 
model. These results are available upon request. 
The DD estimate in equation (1) will be biased if trends in leave-taking rates 
between the treatment and control groups would have been different in the absence 
of CA-PFL. Although this assumption is fundamentally untestable, we explore the 
robustness of our results to the use of several alternative comparison groups. First, 
we compare California fathers of infants to corresponding fathers in other states. 24 
The key identification assumption is that of common trends in leave-taking for 
fathers of infants in California and in other states (in the absence of the policy). This 
assumption could be violated if there are differential changes in the rate of types of 
leave-taking that are unrelated to CA-PFL (e.g., vacation or sick days). However, as 
long as any such changes are not specific to fathers of infants, this concern can be </p>

<p>22 CA-PFL started paying out benefits in July 2004. Because only survey year and age in years can be 
identified in the ACS, a reported infant in 2004 may have been born as early as January 2003. Assuming 
births and survey responses are both approximately uniformly distributed throughout the year, only 
around 12.5 percent of surveyed infants in 2004 would have been born after the implementation of CA-
PFL, compared with 87.5 percent of surveyed infants in 2005. Therefore, we treat 2005 as the first year 
of the policy. 
23 The state-year controls come from the University of Kentucky Poverty Research Center National 
Welfare Data. 
24 Individuals from New Jersey are excluded from the analysis because the state implemented its own 
PFL policy in 2008. Ideally, we would use New Jersey as another treatment state. However, sample sizes 
of fathers on leave in New Jersey are too small (between four and 20 per year on leave) to produce 
meaningful estimates. Rhode Island is the only other state to have also started a PFL program, but it did 
so in 2014, after our sample ends. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>addressed instead by comparing California fathers of infants to California fathers of 
youngest children aged 1 to 3 (or 2 to 4) at the survey date. 25 Fathers of older children 
in California are not eligible to receive paternity leave benefits under CA-PFL, and 
therefore will serve as a second control group. Interpreting the resulting treatment 
effect as causal requires the assumption that rates of leave-taking in California are 
not differentially changing among fathers of infants and of slightly older children 
for reasons unrelated to CA-PFL. 26 
These two sets of control groups can be combined into a DDD model that compares 
fathers with infants to fathers of older children, in California vs. other states, before 
and after the policy. This DDD specification allows for differential trends in leave-
taking across states and by age of youngest child as long as the difference in the 
rate of change between fathers of infants and older children in California would 
have been the same as that in other states in the absence of CA-PFL. Under this 
assumption, we estimate the DDD equation: </p>

<p>Y ist = β 0 + β 1 Under1 ist + β 2 C A s  *  Post t + β 3 C A s  *  Under1 ist + β 4 Post t  *  Under1 ist </p>

<p>+ β 5 C A s  *  Post t  *  Under1 ist + γ X ist + δ s + φ t + θ st + ε ist 
(2) </p>

<p>where Y ist , Post t , X ist , δ s , and φ t are as above, Under1 is an indicator equal to 
1 if the individual's youngest child is less than 1-year-old and zero otherwise, and 
C A s is an indicator for the respondent residing in California. The DDD model also 
allows for the estimation of state-by-year fixed effects (θ st ), which replace the state-
year controls. The fixed effects make it unnecessary to include the main effects of 
C A s and Post t explicitly in the model, and the DDD coefficient is β 5 . This coeffi-
cient represents the effect of CA-PFL on paternity leave among fathers of infants in 
California. Although the outcome variable captures work absences overall and not 
just paternity leave, there is no reason to think that CA-PFL would differentially 
affect work absences for other purposes among fathers of infants. </p>

<p>Inference </p>

<p>Typically, studies that exploit policy variation across states conduct inference 
using standard errors clustered at the state level. However, this approach may be 
challenging in cases where the number of treated clusters is small (Bertrand, Duflo, 
&amp; Mullainathan, 2004; Donald &amp; Lang, 2007). Other inference methods developed 
to improve upon cluster robust standard errors when either the number of groups 
is small or there is cluster heterogeneity do not perform well when the proportion 
of treated groups approaches zero or one, as is true in this setting (MacKinnon 
&amp; Webb, 2017). Moreover, recent work suggests that inference methods should 
account for the fact that there may be variation in the number of observations per 
group (Ferman &amp; Pinto, 2016). As such, we explore the sensitivity of our results to 
alternative inference approaches. 
Specifically, for both the DDD models and the DD specifications where we 
compare fathers in California to fathers in other states, we first present results from </p>

<p>25 State-year controls and state fixed effects are omitted from equation (1) when using fathers in 
California with older children as the control group. 
26 CA-PFL may increase leave-taking among these fathers because the program also covers time off 
to care for sick family members. But fathers of older children may be less likely to take leave if they 
compensate for having taken leave earlier. To test this, we estimated a DD model comparing fathers of 
1-to 3-year-olds in California to those in other states. If anything, we find evidence that fathers of 1-to 
3-year-olds are more likely to take leave after CA-PFL, meaning our estimates may understate the effect 
for fathers of infants. These results are available upon request. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 19 </p>

<p>specifications with standard errors clustered at the state level. 27 In addition, we 
implement a new method of inference developed by Ferman and Pinto (2016) 
(hereafter, F-P) that provides an improvement in hypothesis testing for situations 
where there are few treated groups and many control groups in the presence of het-
eroskedasticity. Heteroskedastic errors are particularly likely in state-level DD and 
DDD models, where there is substantial variation in the number of observations used 
to calculate each group-time average. However, several common methods of infer-
ence, including cluster-residual bootstrapping (Cameron, Gelbach, &amp; Miller, 2008), 
the Donald and Lang (2007) two-step approach, and the Conley and Taber (2011) 
method, all rely on a critical homoskedasticity assumption. The F-P method is an ex-
tension of the cluster-residual bootstrap with a heteroskedasticity correction applied 
to the residuals. F-P develop their method in a standard DD setting, and we extend 
it to the DDD case (see Appendix B for more details). 28 We follow F-P and assume 
that the heteroskedasticity is generated by the variation in group size, and present 
p-values calculated using this method for all results. Finally, we also present results 
from DD models that use the Donald and Lang (2007) two-step approach to conduct 
inference. </p>

<p>Indirect Tests of the Identifying Assumption </p>

<p>To interpret the DDD effect as the causal effect of CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking, 
the implementation of the policy must be uncorrelated with other time-varying de-
terminants of leave-taking in our sample of employed fathers of young children. This 
assumption would be violated if the CA-PFL law induced selection into our sample 
through impacts on fathers' employment or fertility patterns. Moreover, since we 
can only observe fathers who reside with their children in our data, we face a threat 
to our identification assumption if the policy influences father-child cohabitation 
rates or is correlated with differential migration into or out of California. 
To evaluate the plausibility of these concerns, Table 1 presents results from re-
gressions that estimate the DDD model (equation (2)) using observable paternal 
characteristics as dependent variables (and omitting the controls in X ist ). Since we 
do not include individual-level controls in these specifications, we collapse the data 
to the father-group and state and year level, where father-group denotes whether 
the father has an infant or a child aged 1 to 3. Table 1-and most of the subse-
quent tables-show p-values from inference with standard errors clustered at the 
state level in parentheses, and p-values calculated using the F-P method in brackets 
below. 29 
The results in columns 1 and 2 of Table 1 show that CA-PFL does not either 
significantly or materially affect employment status or the probability of having an 
infant in the household. 30 For example, the 95 percent confidence interval of the </p>

<p>27 DD models that compare fathers within California use heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors. 
28 All appendices are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's 
website and use the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. 
29 The F-P method is a cluster-residual bootstrap with a correction for heteroskedasticity. The purpose 
of this bootstrap is to provide asymptotic refinement in the presence of clustered errors. It essentially 
performs a permutation test by imposing the null hypothesis and resampling the residuals-rather than 
re-estimating the key coefficient of interest-and then asking how likely it would be to observe the key 
coefficient by chance. As such, only p-values (not standard errors) are generated. See Ferman and Pinto 
(2016) for more details. 
30 Column 2 of Table 1 is based on a DD model comparing fathers of children age 3 and younger in 
California to those in other states. Using all men aged 15 to 55, we find a significant negative correlation 
between PFL and having an infant. This is driven by a relative increase in the number of single immigrants 
to California, and disappears when we control for the share of citizens. Our main results control for </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Table 1. Correlation between CA-PFL and fathers' characteristics. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>Outcome: </p>

<p>Employed Has infant </p>

<p>Mean 
age </p>

<p>Married 
Less than 
high school </p>

<p>High 
school </p>

<p>Some 
college </p>

<p>4-Year 
degree or 
more </p>

<p>White </p>

<p>Under-
represented 
minority </p>

<p>Predicted 
leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 0.00171 </p>

<p>−0.299 −0.00133 −0.000541 </p>

<p>−0.00236 </p>

<p>0.0125 
−0.00961 −0.00534 −0.00294 −0.00166 </p>

<p>(0.6490) </p>

<p>(0.0010) (0.7380) </p>

<p>(0.9080) </p>

<p>(0.7720) 
(0.0988) (0.1670) (0.2020) </p>

<p>(0.5490) </p>

<p>(0.6520) </p>

<p>[0.918] </p>

<p>[0.444] [0.931] </p>

<p>[0.984] </p>

<p>[0.942] </p>

<p>[0.628] </p>

<p>[0.684] </p>

<p>[0.757] </p>

<p>[0.864] </p>

<p>[0.915] </p>

<p>CA*post </p>

<p>−0.000622 
(0.7620) 
[0.940] </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>700 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>1,400 </p>

<p>R-squared </p>

<p>0.685 </p>

<p>0.288 </p>

<p>0.937 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.844 </p>

<p>0.786 </p>

<p>0.795 </p>

<p>0.882 </p>

<p>0.978 </p>

<p>0.969 </p>

<p>0.718 </p>

<p>Individual 
controls </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>State-year 
controls </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Time FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>0.899 </p>

<p>0.290 </p>

<p>32.75 </p>

<p>0.890 </p>

<p>0.123 </p>

<p>0.259 </p>

<p>0.295 </p>

<p>0.323 </p>

<p>0.720 </p>

<p>0.230 </p>

<p>0.121 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Cluster robust p-values 
in parentheses. p-values 
calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are in brackets. Outcomes are shown in column headings. </p>

<p>Data are collapsed by state, year, and whether or not the father has a child under 1. Regressions in columns 1 and 3 through 11 identify correlation between 
CA-PFL and the outcome shown, comparing fathers of infants to fathers with a youngest child 1 to 3 years old, in California vs. other states, before and after the 
implementation of CA-PFL. Column 2 compares fathers in California to fathers in other states, before and after the policy. Columns 2 through 11 condition on </p>

<p>the father being employed. Coefficient of interest (DDD or DD in column 2) is shown. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 21 </p>

<p>employment effect is −0.6 to 0.9 percentage points, compared to a baseline average 
of 89.9 percent. Given the relatively modest benefit available (up to 55 percent of 
wages for up to six weeks), this finding is not surprising. We also show that the 
policy is uncorrelated with other paternal demographic characteristics, including 
age, marital status, education, share of fathers who are non-Hispanic white, and 
share of fathers who are from an under-represented minority (URM) group, which 
includes Blacks, Hispanics, and other non-White, non-Asian races. Finally, in the 
last column, we show results when "predicted leave-taking"-generated using a 
large set of fathers' demographic characteristics and their interactions-serves as 
the outcome. 31 These findings suggest that CA-PFL is uncorrelated with paternal 
demographics that predict leave-taking behavior. Therefore, it is unlikely that 
differential demographic trends among fathers of infants in California drive the 
results shown in the next section. </p>

<p>ESTIMATED EFFECTS ON LEAVE-TAKING </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the estimated effect of CA-PFL on parents' leave-taking behavior in 
California. The first six columns show results for fathers. The first three of these 
show the DD estimates using a control group of fathers of infants in all other states, 
and control groups of fathers of 1-to 3-and 2-to 4-year-olds in California, respec-
tively. 32 The fourth through sixth columns show results from DDD models, with 
varying sets of time and location controls, and where our preferred specification, in 
column 4, is the most comprehensive in that it controls for a full set of state-by-year 
fixed effects. The last column shows DDD results for mothers using our preferred 
specification. In specifications that compare across states (columns 1 and 4 through 
7), we present p-values from models with standard errors clustered at the state level 
in parentheses and the F-P p-values in brackets. The F-P p-values are consistently 
larger than the p-values from inference with clustered standard errors, due to the 
fact that we only have one treatment state (California), and substantial variation 
in group sizes (i.e., different numbers of observations across states) that results 
in heteroskedasticity. In specifications that compare fathers within California 
(columns 2 and 3), we do not use clustered standard errors as we no longer need 
to account for spatial correlation in errors within states; thus, we simply present 
p-values from models with heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors. 
The DD coefficients in columns 1 through 3 suggest that CA-PFL leads to a 
0.88-1.25 percentage point increase in fathers' leave-taking during the survey 
reference week, representing a 44 to 63 percent increase from the pre-treatment 
mean of 1.99 percent. Figures 2 and 3 show the corresponding event-study plots for 
the models using fathers of infants in other states and fathers of 1-to 3-year-olds in 
California as control groups, with the coefficients normalized to zero in 2004. 33 Al-
though the estimates are somewhat noisy, there is an indication of an upward trend </p>

<p>citizenship status, and we have also controlled for citizenship-year fixed effects and limited the sample 
to citizens, with similar results (available upon request). 
31 Specifically, we use the underlying individual-level data to regress leave-taking rates on paternal 
demographic controls for: age of youngest child, marital and citizenship status, fathers' age, and race 
and education, and all race-education interactions. We then use the predicted values from this regression 
as a "summary index" of selection. 
32 We present results with fathers of 2-to 4-year-olds as the control group because infant age could be 
misreported if parents state that they are 1-year-old instead of less than 1. The data suggest that this is 
not an issue. In the sample of fathers with youngest children 0 to 3 in California, 28.04 percent have an 
infant less than 1-year-old and 27.18 percent report having a 1-year-old. 
33 Appendix Figures A1 and A2 show the corresponding event studies for mothers. All appendices are 
available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's website and use the 
search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Table 2. Effects of CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking behavior. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
All parents sample </p>

<p>Father is on leave </p>

<p>Mother is 
on leave </p>

<p>DD 
DD 
DD 
DDD 
DDD 
DDD 
DDD 
Infants in 
other 
states </p>

<p>1-3-year-
olds 
within 
CA </p>

<p>2-4-year-
olds within 
CA </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.00915 0.00898 0.00894 0.0233 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) (&lt;0.0001) (&lt;0.0001) (&lt;0.0001) 
[0.044] 
[0.049] [0.050] 
[0.000] 
CA*post 
0.0088 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.037] 
Post*under1 
0.0102 
0.0125 
(0.0016) 
(0.0002) 
Observations 
251,685 109,064 
99,688 
879,873 878,377 878,377 682,872 
R-squared 
0.013 
0.014 
0.013 
0.013 
0.012 
0.011 
0.057 
Individual 
controls </p>

<p>YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>State-year 
controls </p>

<p>YES 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
YES 
NO </p>

<p>Time FE 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
State FE 
YES 
NO 
NO 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
State-year FE 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
NO 
NO 
YES 
State linear 
trend </p>

<p>NO 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
NO 
NO </p>

<p>Pre-treatment 
mean for CA 
parents of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0199 
0.0199 
0.0199 
0.0199 
0.0199 
0.0199 
0.177 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust p-values in parentheses. Specifications that compare across states (columns 1 and 4 
through 7) have cluster-robust p-values, clustered at the state level. In specifications that compare across 
states, p-values are also calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method and are shown in brackets. p-values 
calculated from robust standard errors are shown in parentheses for within-California specifications 
(columns 2 and 3). Coefficient of interest (DD or DDD) is shown. Individual controls include dummies 
for age of youngest child, number of children, citizenship status, marital status, five-year age bins, race 
(White, Black, Hispanic, Asian, Other), education level (less than high school, high school, some college, 
four-year degree or higher), and indicators for employed and in the labor force. State-year controls 
include unemployment rate, average welfare benefit for a four-person family, poverty rate, an indicator 
for whether the governor is democratic, state minimum wage, log of population, and per capita income. 
DDD compares fathers of infants to fathers with a youngest child aged 1 to 3, in California vs. other 
states, before and after the policy. The "All parents" sample includes all employed fathers or mothers. </p>

<p>after the policy takes effect. Such an increase over time (rather than an immediate 
jump) might occur if fathers are learning about the availability of CA-PFL; this inter-
pretation of the figures is consistent with the 146 percent increase in male "bonding" 
claims (from 24,021 to 59,256) filed in California between 2005 and the 2012 to </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 23 </p>

<p>Notes: This figure plots the coefficients and 95 percent confidence intervals from an event-study regres-
sion that compares the leave-taking rate of California fathers of infants relative to fathers of infants in 
other states in each year before and after CA-PFL implementation. The omitted category is 2004. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Event Study Graph for Leave-Taking: Fathers of Infants in CA vs. Fathers 
of Infants in Other States. </p>

<p>Notes: This figure plots the coefficients and 95 percent confidence intervals from an event-study regres-
sion that compares the leave-taking rate of California fathers of infants relative to California fathers 
of youngest children aged 1 to 3 years old in each year before and after CA-PFL implementation. The 
omitted category is 2004. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Event Study Graph for Leave-Taking: Fathers of Infants in CA vs. Fathers 
of Children aged 1 to 3 in CA. </p>

<p>2013 fiscal year. 34 However, the figures should be viewed as suggestive since they 
do not rule out the possibility of an upward pre-trend in leave-taking prior to 2004 </p>

<p>34 CA-PFL program statistics were obtained from the State of California Employment Development 
Department. See http://www.edd.ca.gov/about_edd/quick_statistics.htm for more information. Bonding 
claims are for taking leave to stay home with an infant rather than to provide care for a sick relative. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>among fathers of infants in California relative to those in other states. Consequently, 
we prefer the DDD specification that allows us to flexibly control for state-by-year 
fixed effects and thus account for differential trends in leave-taking across states. 
The DDD specification, shown in column 4 of Table 2, suggests that the policy 
causes a 0.9 percentage point, or 46 percent, increase in leave-taking during the 
survey reference week from the pre-treatment baseline of 1.99 percent. This model 
compares fathers of infants to fathers of youngest children aged 1 to 3, in California 
vs. other states, before and after the introduction of the policy. Results are very 
similar if fathers of youngest children aged 2 to 4 are used instead, and therefore 
are not shown. Columns 5 and 6 of Table 2 show that the DDD results are robust 
to the inclusion of state-specific linear time trends and the exclusion of state-year 
fixed effects. As mentioned, since the DDD model allows for both national trends 
in leave-taking among fathers with infants, as well as state-specific trends in leave-
taking overall, subsequent results are only presented for the DDD model. However, 
results from the DD models are similar. 
We cannot directly translate the estimated PFL program effects into the number 
of additional days of leave taken, because the ACS contains only binary information 
about temporary absences from work during the survey reference week. However, 
if we assume that these men were off the job for the full week and births of infants 
were approximately uniformly distributed throughout the year, our preferred esti-
mates suggest that the program added approximately 2.4 days of leave (0.00915 × 52 
weeks × 5 days per week) from a pre-treatment baseline of around 5.2 days. The last 
column of Table 2 shows the effect of CA-PFL on maternal leave-taking behavior 
using our preferred DDD specification. 35 Similar to Rossin-Slater, Ruhm, and 
Waldfogel (2013) and Baum and Ruhm (2016), we find that mothers are also 
more likely to take leave after the introduction of CA-PFL. CA-PFL leads to a 2.3 
percentage point increase in leave-taking during the survey reference week among 
mothers with infants, which represents a 13 percent increase from the pre-treatment 
baseline. In percentage terms, this is much smaller than the effect estimated for 
men (13 vs. 46 percent) but it is much larger in absolute terms, since new mothers 
are more likely to be on leave. Assuming that temporary work absences last for the 
full survey reference week of five work days, CA-PFL is estimated to increase the 
leave-taking of new mothers by six days from a base level of around 46 days. </p>

<p>Heterogeneity </p>

<p>We next examine heterogeneity by birth order, child gender, and family income. 
Columns 1 and 3 of Table 3 show that birth order matters more for fathers' than 
mothers' leave-taking. Column 1 of Table 3 indicates that CA-PFL increases the 
predicted leave-taking of fathers after first births by almost 2 percentage points 
during the survey reference week, or 95 percent. However, following second or 
higher-order births, the effect is only 0.35 percentage points (18 percent). This 
finding is interesting, in part, because it cannot be explained by differences in 
information about the policy. In supplementary analyses, we found no differences 
in the effect on leave-taking for the second or higher birth depending on whether 
the first child was born before or after the policy went into effect. The pre-policy 
mean rates of leave-taking do not vary significantly by birth order, so this difference 
is not driven by pre-existing patterns either. Interestingly, the birth order difference </p>

<p>35 Appendix Table A2 shows all columns of Table 2 for mothers instead of fathers. All appendices are 
available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's website and use the 
search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 25 </p>

<p>Table 3. Heterogeneous effects of CA-PFL on parents' leave-taking behavior. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>All parents sample </p>

<p>Father is on leave 
Mother is on leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.0191 
0.0116 
0.0268 
0.0222 
(Effect for 1st parity birth or 
boy) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.019] 
[0.126] 
[0.093] 
[0.156] 
CA*post*under1*higher 
parity 
−0.0156 
−0.00728 </p>

<p>(Higher vs. first parity 
difference) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) 
(0.2770) 
[0.033] 
[0.561] 
CA*Post*under1*girl 
−0.00536 
0.0156 
(Girl vs. boy difference) 
(0.0347) 
(0.0006) 
[0.568] 
[0.465] 
Observations 
879,873 
874,759 
682,872 
637,774 
R-squared 
0.013 
0.013 
0.057 
0.058 
Pre-treatment mean for CA 
parents of infants </p>

<p>0.0199 
0.0199 
0.177 
0.177 </p>

<p>Notes: Cluster-robust p-values in parentheses. p-values calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are 
in brackets. The coefficient in the first row is the DDD effect of CA-PFL on fathers' (or mothers') leave-
taking, comparing fathers (or mothers) of infants to those of 1-to 3-year-olds, in California vs. other 
states, before and after the introduction of CA-PFL for fathers (or mothers) with a first parity birth 
(columns 1 and 3) or whose youngest child is a boy (columns 2 and 4); the second coefficient is the 
differential effect for fathers (or mothers) whose youngest child is a higher parity birth (columns 1 and 
3) or whose youngest child is a girl compared to those with a boy (columns 2 and 4). All models also 
include controls for individual and spouse characteristics, state and time dummy variables, and state-
year fixed-effects. </p>

<p>in the effects of CA-PFL is unique to fathers: There is a much smaller (and never 
significant) corresponding birth order difference in the DDD effects of the policy 
when looking at the probability that the mother is on leave (column 3). Several 
possible explanations exist for the relatively stronger effect of CA-PFL on father's 
leave-taking after first births. Mothers may need the most help caring for their first-
born child given this is their first experience with newborn care and they do not 
have other child care arrangements in place, so having the father at home may be 
especially beneficial. Fathers may also feel they need more time off at a first birth 
to adjust to the changes starting a family entails. Alternatively, fathers may be more 
willing to take time off to be involved with the care of their first child, but revert 
back to more traditional gender roles with later children, particularly if the mother 
is no longer employed or has shifted to a part-time schedule. It is also possible that 
employer attitudes play a role-companies may be more accepting of a father taking 
leave for the birth of a first child, and less so for the birth of a subsequent child. Our 
data do not allow us to distinguish between these channels. 36 
To analyze whether or not fathers of boys are more likely to take PFL than fathers 
of girls, column 2 of Table 3 shows the effect of CA-PFL for fathers whose youngest 
child is male and the differential effect for fathers whose youngest child is female. </p>

<p>36 Appendix Table A3 shows that the effects of CA-PFL are driven by fathers of first-born children both in 
household where the mother does not work and in households with two employed parents. All appendices 
are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's website and use 
the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>The coefficients suggest that fathers of sons are more likely to take paternity leave af-
ter CA-PFL goes into effect than fathers of daughters, although the coefficient on the 
interaction term is only significant with clustered standard errors and not according 
to the F-P method. 37 These results, while tentative, are suggestive of son preference 
among fathers, in line with what would be expected from related research. Inter-
estingly, if anything, the opposite appears to be true among mothers. Column 4 of 
Table 3 shows that the policy may have a larger effect on mothers of daughters 
than it does on those with sons (although, again, the interaction coefficient is not 
significant with the F-P method). 
Table 4 shows the effects of CA-PFL on fathers' and mothers' leave-taking for 
families in each quartile of the adjusted household income distribution. Household 
income is adjusted for the number of adults and number of children in the fam-
ily with the equivalence scale used in the Census Bureau's supplemental poverty 
measure (Renwick &amp; Fox, 2016). 38 This measure accounts for family size while also 
recognizing that expenses are not the same for all family members due to economies 
of scale (Betson &amp; Michael, 1993). The first four columns show the effects of CA-PFL 
on fathers' leave-taking by quartile. The results suggest the effects of this policy are 
nonlinear and appear to be driven by fathers in the top and bottom quartile. The 
last four columns show analogous estimates for mothers' leave-taking. The effects 
for mothers are again non-monotonic in household income, but the effect is largest 
(and only statistically significant with the F-P method) for those in the 26th to 50th 
percentile of the adjusted income distribution. Interestingly, the mean leave-taking 
rates are also different across family income. However, while the results in Table 4 
provide suggestive evidence of some heterogeneity in effects of PFL by household 
income, we note that the differences across groups are not statistically significant. 
Moreover, these results should be interpreted with caution as the measure of house-
hold income available in the ACS is endogenous to past leave-taking decisions. 39 
Finally, in exploratory analyses, we also examined heterogeneity in leave-taking 
by fathers' demographic characteristics. We obtain suggestive evidence that the 
effects are smallest among Hispanic fathers (relative to non-Hispanic White, African-
American, and Asian fathers), although small sample sizes prevent us from making 
definitive conclusions. 40 We also found that CA-PFL may have a larger effect on 
fathers with some college or a high school degree than for those with a four-year 
degree. However, there is no corresponding positive effect for fathers who have not 
graduated from high school. These results are available upon request. </p>

<p>37 Lundberg and Rose (2002) find that fathers' labor supply and wages increase more in response to 
births of sons than daughters, which is in contrast to our finding that fathers spend more time at home 
with newborn boys than girls. However, their study covers a time period with very little availability of 
PFL for U.S. men. The patterns we find in our data could also be in part driven by selection, since fathers 
of sons are more likely to live with their children than fathers of daughters (Dahl &amp; Moretti, 2008). 
However, this effect is relatively small. 
38 We divide household income by the equivalence scale, which is computed as follows: 
Equivalence Scale = (adults + 0.8  *  f irst child + 0.5  *  other childr en) 0.7 for single-parent households, 
and Equivalence Scale = (adults + 0.5  *  childr en) 0.7 for two-parent households. 
39 Results using a measure of adjusted predicted household income are available upon request. We 
predict household income by regressing it on all observable demographic characteristics of the parents 
included in equation (1). 
40 Small sample sizes arise in part because we require the fathers in our sample to be employed and 
residing with their children. For example, there are only 49 Black fathers of infants on leave in California 
in the whole sample, and only 1000 Black fathers of infants in California overall. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 27 </p>

<p>Table 4. Heterogeneous effects of CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking behavior by adjusted household income. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Sample: Adjusted household income quartile of parent </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Father is on leave </p>

<p>Mother is on leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 </p>

<p>0.0123 </p>

<p>0.00413 </p>

<p>0.00710 </p>

<p>0.0167 </p>

<p>0.0171 </p>

<p>0.0378 </p>

<p>0.00198 </p>

<p>0.0286 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(0.122) 
(0.0057) (&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(0.005) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(0.692) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>[0.041] </p>

<p>[0.534] </p>

<p>[0.290] </p>

<p>[0.031] </p>

<p>[0.257] </p>

<p>[0.032] </p>

<p>[0.868] </p>

<p>[0.312] </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>220,018 </p>

<p>219,940 </p>

<p>219,994 </p>

<p>219,921 </p>

<p>170,721 </p>

<p>170,718 </p>

<p>170,716 </p>

<p>170,717 </p>

<p>R-squared </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.055 </p>

<p>0.066 </p>

<p>0.082 </p>

<p>Individual controls </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Time FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Pre-treatment Mean for CA parents of infants </p>

<p>0.0128 </p>

<p>0.0264 </p>

<p>0.0190 </p>

<p>0.0228 </p>

<p>0.155 </p>

<p>0.137 </p>

<p>0.192 </p>

<p>0.213 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Cluster-robust p-values 
in parentheses. p-values 
calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are in brackets. The coefficient is the DDD effect of CA-PFL </p>

<p>on fathers' (or mothers') leave-taking, comparing fathers (or mothers) of infants to those of 1-to 3-year-olds, in California vs. other states, before and after the 
introduction of CA-PFL for fathers (or mothers). Each column limits the sample to parents in the specified quartile of the adjusted household income distribution, </p>

<p>where household income is adjusted for family size using the equivalence scale used in the supplemental poverty measure. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Table 5. Effects of CA-PFL on household leave-taking behavior. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>Two parent households sample: 
Mother not 
employed </p>

<p>Both parents employed </p>

<p>Father is on 
leave </p>

<p>Either 
parent is on 
leave </p>

<p>Both parents 
are on leave </p>

<p>Father only 
is on leave </p>

<p>Mother only 
is on leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.00424 
0.0404 
0.00412 
0.0053 
0.0309 
(0.0040) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(0.0009) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.318] 
[0.027] 
[0.263] 
[0.168] 
[0.073] 
Observations 
343,184 
468,134 
468,134 
468,134 
468,134 
R-squared 
0.016 
0.055 
0.007 
0.012 
0.063 
Pre-treatment mean 
for CA parents of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0167 
0.187 
0.0149 
0.0105 
0.162 </p>

<p>Notes: Cluster-robust p-values in parentheses. p-values calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are in 
brackets. The "Two parent households" sample is conditional on the father being married. The "Mother 
not employed" sample in the first column is conditional on only the father (and not the mother) being 
employed. The "Both parents employed" sample in columns 2 through 5 is conditional on both parents 
being employed (such that the leave variable is non-missing for both). The DDD specification is estimated 
in all columns, comparing fathers of infants to those with a youngest child 1 to 3 years old, in California 
vs. other states, before and after the implementation of CA-PFL. The DDD coefficient is shown. All models 
also include controls for individual characteristics, state and time dummy variables, and state-year fixed-
effects. </p>

<p>Household Leave-Taking </p>

<p>CA-PFL provides paid parental leave to any eligible parent and not just the primary 
caregiver. To examine household leave-taking, Table 5 explores effects on leave-
taking in two-parent households. In column 1, we study households where the father 
is employed and the mother does not work. Columns 2 through 5 further limit the 
sample to households with fathers who have employed spouses, so that both parents 
are potentially eligible to take paid leave. Demographic controls for both spouses are 
included in the regressions, which are weighted by the ACS household weights. 41 
The estimated coefficients suggest that fathers in both types of households are 
more likely to take leave after CA-PFL goes into effect. Column 1 shows that the 
policy increases leave-taking during the survey reference week among fathers in 
households where mothers do not work by 0.4 percentage points, or 25 percent 
at the sample mean. However, this coefficient is only significant with clustered 
standard errors, and not according to the F-P method. Column 2 demonstrates that, 
in households where both parents work, CA-PFL increases leave-taking during the 
survey reference week by either parent by 4 percentage points, or 22 percent. The 
increase in fathers' leave-taking is driven both by a 0.41 percentage point rise in the 
probability that both parents are on leave at the same time (a 28 percent increase) 
and a 0.53 percentage point increase in father-only leave, while the mother is at work </p>

<p>41 The sample is essentially the same if we condition on the mother and father of the youngest child 
residing in the same household (but not necessarily being married). This is a function of how IPUMS 
links children to parents: If both parents are present but not married to each other, the least proximate 
parent is unlinked. We do not distinguish between stepmothers and biological mothers. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 29 </p>

<p>(a 50 percent increase). Note, however, that these results are only suggestive as the 
F-P p-values are above 0.1. 42 The increase in father-only leave-taking indicates that 
providing CA-PFL to fathers-in addition to mothers-may increase the total num-
ber of days that at least one parent stays home with the infant. Married employed 
mothers are substantially more likely to take leave after the CA-PFL program comes 
into effect as well, and they are almost always on leave while the father is at work. 
Finally, Appendix Tables A3 and A4 show the heterogeneous effects for the house-
hold leave-taking outcomes by birth order and gender, respectively. 43 Although the 
results are often imprecisely measured using the F-P method, the point estimates 
are consistent with the earlier results. Fathers are more likely to take leave on their 
own when their child is male, but no more likely to do so if the child is a girl. This 
gender difference is also reflected in the probability that both parents are on leave 
at the same time. The increase in father-only leave-taking is driven entirely by leaves 
taken after first births. </p>

<p>ROBUSTNESS </p>

<p>An important limitation of a DD analysis is that one must rely on an assumption that 
the outcomes in treatment and control groups would have followed parallel trends 
in the absence of the policy reform. While this assumption is inherently untestable, 
the fact that our results are very consistent across the DD and DDD specifications 
and robust to different sets of controls is reassuring. We also perform a variety of 
other robustness tests that lend credibility to the identifying assumption. 
Table 6 shows that the findings are similar if the data are collapsed down to 
the state-year level or if control groups are chosen to best match pre-policy trends 
in fathers' leave-taking using synthetic control methods (Abadie, Diamond, &amp; 
Hainmueller, 2010). The first column shows the DD estimate of the effect of the 
policy on the share of fathers of infants on leave in California compared to all 
other states. The Donald and Lang (2007) two-step approach is used to obtain the 
estimates and standard errors, so inference is conducted using a t-distribution 
with 12 degrees of freedom. The effect size is very similar to the estimate obtained 
using individual-level data, with CA-PFL predicted to raise paternal leave taking 
by 0.8 percentage points in both cases. The Donald and Lang approach for 
calculating standard errors is often used to conduct inference when there are a 
small number of clusters. While 50 clusters are normally assumed to be large 
enough for the asymptotic results of cluster-robust standard errors to apply, recent 
work shows that the "effective" number of clusters is smaller when the number 
of observations per cluster varies across groups, as is true in the uncollapsed data 
(Carter, Schnepel, &amp; Steigerwald, 2017), so that the cluster-robust standard errors 
could be underestimated. However, the fact that, for most cases, inference is the 
same using the Donald and Lang two-step approach and when using cluster-robust 
standard errors on the uncollapsed data suggests this is not a major issue. 
The remaining columns of Table 6 show the DD effect when comparing California 
to synthetic control groups that may better match pre-policy trends in leave-taking. 
In each column, the synthetic control group is formed by matching on different 
combinations of state-year characteristics, and the treatment effect is obtained </p>

<p>42 The total increase in leave-taking for fathers in households where both parents work is 0.00943 (the 
sum of columns 3 and 4) with an F-P p-value of 0.036. This effect is much larger than the estimated 
increase in leave-taking for fathers in households where the mother does not work (0.0044), but the 
difference is not statistically significant at conventional levels. 
43 All appendices are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's 
website and use the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>Table 6. Estimates based on collapsed data. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>Outcome: Father is on leave </p>

<p>Not 
matched </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Synthetic </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>CA*post </p>

<p>0.00809 </p>

<p>0.00968 </p>

<p>0.0107 </p>

<p>0.0107 </p>

<p>0.0137 </p>

<p>0.0139 </p>

<p>0.0144 </p>

<p>0.0133 </p>

<p>0.0107 </p>

<p>0.0134 </p>

<p>0.0132 </p>

<p>(0.0608) [0.0625] [0.0625] </p>

<p>[0.104] 
[0.0208] [0.0208] [0.0208] [0.0208] [0.0625] [0.0417] [0.0417] </p>

<p>O b s e r v a t i o n s </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>1 4 </p>

<p>R-squared </p>

<p>0.324 </p>

<p>0.330 </p>

<p>0.310 </p>

<p>0.195 </p>

<p>0.388 </p>

<p>0.405 </p>

<p>0.433 </p>

<p>0.399 </p>

<p>0.310 </p>

<p>0.430 </p>

<p>0.353 </p>

<p>Individual controls </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Time FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>State FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Pre-treatment mean </p>

<p>in CA </p>

<p>0.0203 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>0.0211 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Donald-Lang p-values 
in parentheses (column 1). p-values 
constructed by estimating "in-space" placebo effects as in Abadie, Diamond, and Hainmueller </p>

<p>(2015) in brackets (note these p-values </p>

<p>are not the F-P p-values 
used in the main analysis). The samples compare fathers of infants in California to fathers of </p>

<p>infants in other states. The first column shows the specification from column 1, Table 3 using the Donald-Lang method to adjust the standard errors. Columns 2 
through 11 show the raw DD effect of fathers of infants in California compared to the fathers of infants in the synthetic control state, matched on different sets of 
variables. Synthetic 1 matches on the share of fathers on leave averaged over the pre-treatment period; Synthetic 2 matches on share on leave in each year of the 
pre-treatment period; Synthetic 3 matches on leave, share employed, and share in the labor force averaged over the pre-treatment period; Synthetic 4 matches </p>

<p>on share on leave, employed, labor force, and race in the pre-treatment period; Synthetic 5 matches on share on leave in the pre-treatment period and share 
employed, in the labor force, and race averaged over the whole period; Synthetic 6 matches on the share on leave, employed, in labor force, race, and education 
averaged over the pre-treatment period; Synthetic 7 matches on share on leave in the pre-treatment period and share employed, in the labor force, race, and 
education averaged over the whole period; Synthetic 8 matches on share on leave in each year of the pre-treatment period and race and education averaged over </p>

<p>the whole period; Synthetic 9 matches on two-year averages of the share on leave in the pre-treatment period and race and education averaged over the whole 
period; and Synthetic 10 matches on share on leave averaged over the pre-treatment period and race and education averaged over the whole period. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 31 </p>

<p>by regressing differences in the rate of leave-taking between California and the 
synthetic control group in each year on an indicator for years after the policy 
takes effect. We follow Abadie, Diamond, and Hainmueller (2015) and construct 
p-values by estimating placebo effects for each other state in the sample, and then 
calculating the fraction of placebo effects that are greater than the estimated effect 
for California. (Note that these p-values are calculated differently from the F-P 
p-values used in the main analysis.) The effect sizes are similar across columns, 
and statistically significant (at least at the 10 percent level) in all but one case, 
suggesting that the results are not sensitive to the choice of control groups. 44 
Appendix Table A5 replicates the main results in Table 2 omitting the individual 
and state-year controls and dropping year 2000 from the analysis. 45 The similarity of 
the results with and without controls suggests that they are not driven by correlations 
between the policy and changing demographic trends. Because the majority of data 
in 2000 comes from the Census, instead of the ACS, one may be concerned about 
comparability between 2000 and the other years. In particular, the Census data are 
collected over a relatively short time span whereas the ACS is conducted throughout 
the year. If differences exist in leave-taking behavior across different parts of the 
year, this sampling design may pose a problem. However, the results are robust to 
both of these changes. 
As noted above, because only fathers with some recent work experience are eligible 
for CA-PFL, all of our results condition on employment. However, the work history 
requirements are relatively weak and some fathers who report being not employed 
could qualify for paid leave benefits. With this in mind, Appendix Table A6 shows 
that the findings are robust to relax this employment restriction. 46 Specifically, 
the results in Table 2 hold if all fathers who have worked any positive number 
of weeks in the previous 12 months are included in the sample, or if all fathers 
with age-eligible children are included in the sample, regardless of employment 
status. This latter specification should be expected to attenuate the results slightly, 
as a smaller fraction of the treated sample is eligible for leave. However, given the 
high employment rate among fathers, the samples do not change dramatically, and 
estimated CA-PFL effects remain substantial, although slightly smaller on average 
than previously. 47 </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>California's PFL program is the first explicit source of government-provided paid 
parental leave available to fathers in the United States, and, consistent with expecta-
tions, we find that the law had a marked effect on fathers' leave-taking. Our results 
show that the policy raised leave-taking among fathers of infants by a substantial </p>

<p>44 We have also done a placebo analysis, in which we assign each of the other 48 states (excluding 
New Jersey, which implemented a PFL program during our sample time frame) to be the treatment state 
instead of California and run our baseline DDD model for fathers' leave-taking as the outcome. For 41 out 
of the 48 states, we do not find any statistically significant DDD coefficients. The states with significant 
DDD coefficients are: AL, AR, ID, LA, NM, RI, and VT, and only two of them (ID and LA) have a positive 
DDD coefficient. 
45 All appendices are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's 
website and use the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. 
46 All appendices are available at the end of this article as it appears in JPAM online. Go to the publisher's 
website and use the search engine to locate the article at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com. 
47 Results are robust to including only private sector (those not working for local, state, or federal 
government, or the military) in the analysis. Essentially all private sector workers are eligible for CA-PFL, 
but not all government employees participate in the program (although some do). As some government 
employees are not eligible, excluding them from the analysis increases the magnitude of the estimates 
slightly, but the results are very similar to those presented here (and are available upon request). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>and statistically significant 46 percent. In relative terms, this increase is much larger 
than the 13 percent growth estimated for mothers of infants, although because moth-
ers take so much more leave, the absolute rise is much smaller (at around two days). 
Interestingly, the predicted increase in male leave-taking is similar to the estimate 
found in Baum and Ruhm's (2016) analysis of CA-PFL, using a much smaller and 
non-representative sample, while the rise in mother's leave-taking is considerably 
smaller than that obtained by either Baum and Ruhm (2016) or Rossin-Slater, Ruhm 
and Waldfogel (2013). 48 The increases we find are meaningful but nevertheless sug-
gest that fathers are taking up only about a quarter of the leave for which they are 
eligible-an average of 1.5 weeks out of a total of six possible weeks. As such, our 
results suggest that any possible increases in employer costs associated with fathers 
using CA-PFL are likely to be small. In contrast, mothers are taking up about nine 
weeks on average of the 12 weeks total they are potentially eligible for (combining 
six weeks of TDI leave for birth mothers and six weeks of PFL for all mothers). 
Our analysis goes beyond the existing studies of CA-PFL by examining novel 
household-level leave-taking outcomes. We find that the law increases both joint 
leave-taking and "father-only" leave-taking. In households where both parents are 
employed, about half of fathers' leave-taking occurs at the same time that the mother 
is off work and the other half takes place when she is working. This suggests that 
CA-PFL increases the total amount of time that a parent spends at home with a new 
child. 
Our analysis also breaks new ground by considering heterogeneity across birth 
order, child gender, and family income. As hypothesized, we find that the effect of 
CA-PFL on fathers' leave-taking is larger for fathers of first-borns than for fathers of 
higher order children, while there is no such difference for mothers. These patterns 
may reflect joint decisions made by mothers and fathers together, if, for example, 
they feel there is less need for exclusive paternal care for a second or later child 
(perhaps because the family has existing child care arrangements or because the 
mother has stopped working or moved to part-time work), or they may reflect 
greater financial constraints on leave-taking by (often higher paid) fathers for later 
children. 
We do not find robust evidence of heterogeneity along the other dimensions we 
consider. The results are suggestive of the effect on fathers' leave-taking being larger 
for fathers of sons than fathers of daughters, which is consistent with prior literature 
on son preference. We also find suggestive evidence of non-monotonic differences 
in the magnitude of the effects by family income, although these differences are not 
significant at conventional levels. 
Our findings are robust across a variety of alternative DD and DDD specifica-
tions, inference methods, and to the inclusion of numerous individual-level and 
state-year controls. We demonstrate that there are no statistically significant pre-
trends in leave-taking behavior in the years before CA-PFL and similar findings were 
obtained when collapsing the data to the state-year level and using synthetic control 
methods with a variety of control groups. This consistency of estimates increases 
our confidence that we are accurately measuring causal effects of CA-PFL. 
Our results, when combined with the relative lack of employer-provided paternity 
leave in the United States, indicate that new fathers respond to expanded opportuni-</p>

<p>48 The ACS does not report reasons for temporary work absence, so it is possible that the ACS captures 
less parental leave-taking than other data sets such as the NLSY (used by Baum &amp; Ruhm) and the CPS 
(used by Rossin-Slater, Ruhm, &amp; Waldfogel). In light of this possibility, our estimates can arguably serve 
as lower bounds. Also, we only observe leave-taking after the birth, whereas Ruhm and Baum captured 
increased leave-taking prior to the birth as well. This is likely to explain a portion of the smaller effect we 
obtained for mothers. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 33 </p>

<p>ties to take PFL. The evidence of increased father-only leave taking, among married 
households where both parents work, suggests that these fathers may become more 
actively involved in child care, spending more time alone with their infants than they 
would have in the absence of the policy. If so, such policies would have implications 
for reducing gender disparities. 
Although women currently make up nearly half of the United States labor force, 
the gender wage gap still persists, with full-time female workers earning 77 percent 
of what their male counterparts earn. 49 Further, mothers have traditionally per-
formed a disproportionate share of child care and housework, and this disparity also 
persists today (Bianchi, 2011; Bianchi et al., 2012; Blair &amp; Lichter, 1991; Hochschild 
&amp; Machung, 1989). The unequal burden faced by women in the home, combined 
with a lack of flexibility in work schedules at most jobs, may be an important ex-
planation for why the gender wage gap still exists despite tremendous progress 
in women's educational and labor market performance over the last half century 
(Goldin, 2014). Increased leave-taking by fathers-including time at home while 
mothers work-has the potential to promote gender equality. Moreover, to the extent 
that gendered patterns of child care provision develop early on, even relatively small 
changes in initial paternity leave decisions may have important consequences. 50 
Overall, we find that California's PFL policy has led to a large relative increase 
in leave-taking among fathers of infants when compared to the low pre-PFL mean. 
Although the average number of days spent on leave is small compared to mothers, 
there has been a substantial increase in the share of fathers who take at least some 
time off work. Results are fairly consistent across demographic groups, suggesting 
that the effects of the policy are likely to be generalizable across states. 
However, the effects we observe for California fathers are much smaller than 
those found in European countries, which, as discussed earlier, have considerably 
higher rates of wage replacement than is available through CA-PFL. The low level 
of wage replacement and lack of job protection may be a factor in the relatively 
lower rates of increased take-up. If so, this would have important implications for 
the design of future programs, whether in other states or at the national-level in the 
United States. </p>

<p>ANN P. BARTEL is the Merrill Lynch Professor of Workforce Transformation at 
Columbia Business School, 3022 Broadway, New York, NY 10025. She is a Research 
Associate at the National Bureau of Economic Research (e-mail: apb2@columbia.edu). </p>

<p>MAYA ROSSIN-SLATER is an Assistant Professor of Health Research and Policy at 
Stanford University School of Medicine, Redwood Building, T101C/D, 150 Governor's 
Lane, Stanford, CA 94305. She is a Faculty Research Fellow at the National Bureau 
of Economic Research and a Research Affiliate at the Institute of Labor Economics 
(e-mail: mrossin@stanford.edu). </p>

<p>CHRISTOPHER J. RUHM is a Professor of Public Policy and Economics at the 
University of Virginia, Frank Batten School of Leadership and Public Policy, P.O. 
Box 400893, Charlottesville, VA 22904-4893. He is a Research Associate at the </p>

<p>49 See: https://www.whitehouse.gov/issues/equal-pay#top. 
50 The amount of time fathers spend in child care is correlated with the generosity of paternity leave 
policies (Boll, Leppin, &amp; Reich, 2014; Fuwa &amp; Cohen, 2007) and fathers who take more leave around 
the time of birth may be more involved in child care throughout the child's life (Haas, 1990; Haas &amp; 
Hwang, 2008; Nepomnyaschy &amp; Waldfogel, 2007; Tanaka &amp; Waldfogel, 2007). There could also be other 
benefits related to health and well-being (Cools, Fiva, &amp; Kirkebøen, 2015) and longer-term effects on 
gender norms and role models (Ray, Gornick, &amp; Schmitt, 2009). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>



<p>National Bureau of Economic Research and the Institute of Labor Economics (e-mail: 
ruhm@virginia.edu). </p>

<p>JENNA STEARNS is an Assistant Professor of Economics at the University of 
California at Davis, 1118 Social Studies and Humanities, Davis, CA 95616 (e-mail: 
jestearns@ucdavis.edu). </p>

<p>JANE WALDFOGEL is the Compton Foundation Centennial Professor for the Preven-
tion of Children and Youth Problems at Columbia University School of Social Work, 
1255 Amsterdam Avenue, New York, NY 10025. She is a Research Associate at the 
Institute of Labor Economics (e-mail: jw205@columbia.edu). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Kelly Bedard, Bruno Ferman, Shelly Lundberg, Jonathan Simonetta, Dick Startz, 
three anonymous referees, and seminar participants at UC Santa Barbara, Columbia Univer-
sity, and the APPAM and AEA conferences for helpful comments. We gratefully acknowledge 
funding from the Department of Labor Contract No. DOL-OPS-14-C-0003. All errors are our 
own. </p>



<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking / 35 </p>

<p>, A., &amp; , K. (2016). Career breaks after childbirth: The impact of family 
leave reforms in the Czech Republic. IZA Discussion Papers No. 10149, Institute for the 
Study of Labor (IZA). Retrieved June 16, 2017, from http://ftp.iza.org/dp10149.pdf. 
Blair, S. L &amp; Lichter, D. T. (1991). Measuring the division of household labor gender segre-
gation of housework among American couples. Journal of Family Issues, 12, 91-113. 
Boll, C., Leppin, J., &amp; Reich, N. (2014). Paternal childcare and parental leave policies: Evi-
dence from industrialized countries. Review of Economics of the Household, 12, 129-158. 
Cameron, A. C., Gelbach, J. B., &amp; Miller, D. L. (2008). Bootstrap-based improvements for 
inference with clustered errors. Review of Economics and Statistics, 90, 414-427. 
Carter, A. V., Schnepel, K. T., &amp; Steigerwald, D. G. (2017). Asymptotic behavior of a t test 
robust to cluster heterogeneity. Review of Economics and Statistics, forthcoming. 
Conley, T. G. &amp; Taber, C. R. (2011). Inference with "difference in differences" with a small 
number of policy changes. Review of Economics and Statistics, 93, 113-125. 
Cools, S., Fiva, J. H., &amp; Kirkebøen, L. J. (2015). Causal effects of paternity leave on children 
and parents. Scandinavian Journal of Economics, 117, 801-828. 
Cowan, C. P. &amp; Cowan, P. A. (2000). When partners become parents: The big life change for 
couples. Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers. 
Dahl, G. B., Løken, K. V., &amp; Mogstad, M. (2014). Peer effects in program participation. 
American Economic Review, 104, 2049-2074. 
Dahl, G. B., Løken, K. V., Mogstad, M., &amp; Salvanes, K. V. (2016). What is the case for paid 
maternity leave? Review of Economics and Statistics, 98, 655-670. 
Dahl, G. B. &amp; Moretti, E. (2008). The demand for sons. Review of Economic Studies, 75, 
1085-1120. 
Donald, S. G., &amp; Lang, K. (2007). Inference with difference-in-differences and other panel 
data. Review of Economics and Statistics, 89, 221-233. 
Duvander, A. &amp; Johansson, M. (2012). What are the effects of reforms promoting fathers' 
parental leave use? Journal of European Social Policy, 22, 319-330. 
Ekberg, J., Eriksson, R., &amp; Friebel, G. (2013). Parental leave-A policy evaluation of the 
Swedish "daddy-month" reform. Journal of Public Economics, 97, 131-143. 
Ferman, B. &amp; Pinto, C. (2016). Inference in differences-in-differences with few treated groups 
and heteroskedasticity. MPRA Paper, University Library of Munich, Germany. Retrieved 
June 16, 2016, from http://EconPapers.repec.org/RePEc:pra:mprapa:67665. 
Fuwa, M. &amp; Cohen, P. N. (2007). Housework and social policy. Social Science Research, 36, 
512-530. 
Goldin, C. (2014). A grand gender convergence: Its last chapter. American Economic Review, 
104, 1091-1119. 
Haas, L. (1990). Gender equality and social policy: Implications of a study of parental leave 
in Sweden. Journal of Family Issues, 11, 401-423. 
Haas, L. &amp; Hwang, C. P. (2008). The impact of taking parental leave on fathers' participation 
in childcare and relationships with children: Lessons from Sweden. Community, Work and 
Family, 11, 85-104. 
Han, W., Ruhm, C. J. &amp; Waldfogel, J. (2009). Parental leave policies and parents' employment 
and leave-taking. Journal of Policy Analysis and Management, 28, 29-54. 
Han, W., Ruhm, C. J., Waldfogel, J., &amp; Washbrook, E. (2008). The timing of mothers' employ-
ment after childbirth. Monthly Labor Review/U.S. Department of Labor, Bureau of Labor 
Statistics, 131, 15-27. 
Hochschild, A. &amp; Machung, A. (1989). The second shift: Working parents and the revolution 
at home. New York, NY: Viking. 
Klerman, J. A., Daley, K., &amp; Pozniak, A. (2012). Family and medical leave in 2012: Tech-
nical report, prepared for the U.S. Department of Labor, Contract #GS10FOO86K. Cam-
bridge, MA: Abt Associates. Retrieved September 5, 2015, from http://www.dol.gov/asp/ 
evaluation/fmla/FMLA-2012-Technical-Report.pdf. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>





<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>APPENDIX A </p>

<p>Notes: This figure plots the coefficients and 95 percent confidence intervals from an event-study regres-
sion that compares the leave-taking rate of California mothers of infants relative to mothers of infants in 
other states in each year before and after CA-PFL implementation. The omitted category is 2004. </p>

<p>Figure A1. Event Study Graph for Leave-Taking: Mothers of Infants in CA vs. Moth-
ers of Infants in Other States. </p>

<p>Notes: This figure plots the coefficients and 95 percent confidence intervals from an event-study regres-
sion that compares the leave-taking rate of California mothers of infants relative to California mothers 
of youngest children aged 1 to 3 years old in each year before and after CA-PFL implementation. The 
omitted category is 2004. </p>

<p>Figure A2. Event Study Graph for Leave-Taking: Mothers of Infants in CA vs. Moth-
ers of Children aged 1 to 3 in CA. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A1. Summary statistics. </p>

<p>Employed fathers </p>

<p>Employed mothers </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 0-3, 
all states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 0-3, 
all states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Age </p>

<p>33.554 </p>

<p>33.061 </p>

<p>32.002 </p>

<p>34.762 </p>

<p>34.019 </p>

<p>30.848 </p>

<p>30.836 </p>

<p>29.612 </p>

<p>32.107 </p>

<p>31.114 </p>

<p>(0.007) </p>

<p>(0.037) </p>

<p>(0.013) </p>

<p>(0.024) </p>

<p>(0.009) </p>

<p>(0.007) </p>

<p>(0.042) </p>

<p>(0.015) </p>

<p>(0.027) </p>

<p>(0.009) </p>

<p>Married </p>

<p>0.909 </p>

<p>0.895 </p>

<p>0.905 </p>

<p>0.902 </p>

<p>0.914 </p>

<p>0.706 </p>

<p>0.760 </p>

<p>0.735 </p>

<p>0.724 </p>

<p>0.692 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Citizen </p>

<p>0.850 </p>

<p>0.695 </p>

<p>0.874 </p>

<p>0.685 </p>

<p>0.875 </p>

<p>0.909 </p>

<p>0.799 </p>

<p>0.927 </p>

<p>0.790 </p>

<p>0.922 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>White </p>

<p>0.653 </p>

<p>0.378 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.360 </p>

<p>0.697 </p>

<p>0.633 </p>

<p>0.388 </p>

<p>0.685 </p>

<p>0.360 </p>

<p>0.660 </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Black </p>

<p>0.077 </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>0.081 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.083 </p>

<p>0.141 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.139 </p>

<p>0.071 </p>

<p>0.154 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Hispanic </p>

<p>0.199 </p>

<p>0.437 </p>

<p>0.160 </p>

<p>0.452 </p>

<p>0.161 </p>

<p>0.160 </p>

<p>0.382 </p>

<p>0.121 </p>

<p>0.404 </p>

<p>0.132 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Asian </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.136 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>0.138 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.054 </p>

<p>0.155 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.153 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>Less than high school </p>

<p>0.133 </p>

<p>0.213 </p>

<p>0.121 </p>

<p>0.228 </p>

<p>0.119 </p>

<p>0.090 </p>

<p>0.122 </p>

<p>0.079 </p>

<p>0.145 </p>

<p>0.086 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>High school diploma </p>

<p>0.245 </p>

<p>0.203 </p>

<p>0.246 </p>

<p>0.206 </p>

<p>0.253 </p>

<p>0.223 </p>

<p>0.185 </p>

<p>0.212 </p>

<p>0.204 </p>

<p>0.231 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Some college </p>

<p>0.283 </p>

<p>0.259 </p>

<p>0.285 </p>

<p>0.258 </p>

<p>0.287 </p>

<p>0.338 </p>

<p>0.321 </p>

<p>0.324 </p>

<p>0.329 </p>

<p>0.345 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>BA or higher </p>

<p>0.339 </p>

<p>0.325 </p>

<p>0.348 </p>

<p>0.308 </p>

<p>0.341 </p>

<p>0.349 </p>

<p>0.372 </p>

<p>0.385 </p>

<p>0.323 </p>

<p>0.338 </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>Usual hours worked </p>

<p>44.852 </p>

<p>43.670 </p>

<p>44.837 </p>

<p>43.739 </p>

<p>45.101 </p>

<p>35.759 </p>

<p>36.144 </p>

<p>35.998 </p>

<p>35.838 </p>

<p>35.649 </p>

<p>(0.011) </p>

<p>(0.059) </p>

<p>(0.023) </p>

<p>(0.037) </p>

<p>(0.014) </p>

<p>(0.014) </p>

<p>(0.078) </p>

<p>(0.028) </p>

<p>(0.048) </p>

<p>(0.017) </p>

<p>On leave </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.064 </p>

<p>0.199 </p>

<p>0.148 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.001) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A1. Continued. </p>

<p>Employed fathers </p>

<p>Employed mothers </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 0-3, 
all states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 0-3, 
all states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child </p>

<p>&lt;1, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
CA </p>

<p>Youngest </p>

<p>child 1-3, 
other 
states </p>

<p>Total household 
income 
86,122.59 93,164.62 82,412.74 94,140.33 85,947.91 81,607.77 100,429.75 81,544.49 95,840.09 78,968.89 
(82.515) (494.842) (157.089) (310.324) (103.203) (89.094) (646.093) (181.592) (364.376) (106.213) </p>

<p>Total personal income 59,926.93 61,722.46 56,407.75 64,420.77 60,536.90 33,305.20 39,925.57 33,056.39 38,288.22 32,458.47 
(67.567) (384.039) (125.602) (252.047) (85.744) </p>

<p>(44.094) (325.882) (89.542) (179.229) </p>

<p>(52.753) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>879,873 </p>

<p>30,534 </p>

<p>221,664 </p>

<p>78,530 </p>

<p>549,145 </p>

<p>682,872 </p>

<p>19,428 </p>

<p>159,961 </p>

<p>55,390 </p>

<p>448,093 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Standard errors in parentheses. In the first 5 columns, the sample is limited to employed fathers 16 to 54 years old. In the subsequent 5 columns, the </p>

<p>sample is limited to employed mothers 16 to 54 years old. Statistics are weighted by the ACS person weights. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A2. Effects of CA-PFL on mothers' leave-taking behavior. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Mother is on leave </p>

<p>DD state 
DD 1-3 
DD 2-4 
DDD 1-3 
DDD 1-3 
DDD 1-3 </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.0233 
0.0233 
0.0231 
(&lt;0.0001) (&lt;0.0001) (&lt;0.0001) 
[0.000] 
[0.024] 
[0.029] 
CA*post 
0.0267 
(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.000] 
Post*under1 
0.0329 
0.0302 
(0.0005) (0.0094) 
Observations 
178,934 
74,818 
71,208 
682,872 
681,354 
681,354 
R-squared 
0.014 
0.074 
0.078 
0.057 
0.055 
0.055 
Individual controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
State-year controls 
YES 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
YES 
Time FE 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
State FE 
YES 
NO 
NO 
YES 
YES 
YES 
State-year FE 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
NO 
NO 
State linear trend 
NO 
NO 
NO 
NO 
YES 
NO 
Pre-treatment mean 
for CA mothers of 
infants </p>

<p>0.177 
0.177 
0.177 
0.177 
0.177 
0.177 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust p-values in parentheses. Specifications that compare across states (columns 1 and 4 
through 7) have cluster-robust p-values, clustered at the state level. In specifications that compare across 
states, p-values are also calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method and are shown in brackets. p-values 
calculated from robust standard errors are shown in parentheses for within-California specifications 
(columns 2 and 3). This table replicates Table 2, looking at the effect of CA-PFL on mothers instead of 
fathers. The sample includes all employed mothers. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A3. Heterogeneous effects by child parity-Two-parent household sample. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>Two-parent households </p>

<p>Both parents employed </p>

<p>Father is 
on leave, 
mother 
does not 
work </p>

<p>Either 
parent is 
on leave </p>

<p>Both 
parents are 
on leave </p>

<p>Father only 
is on leave </p>

<p>Mother 
only is on 
leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.011 
0.0456 
0.00726 
0.0132 
0.0251 
(0.00161) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.198] 
[0.159] 
[0.290] 
[0.001] 
[0.346] 
CA*post*under1* 
higher parity 
−0.00973 
−0.0103 
−0.00558 
−0.0131 
0.00838 
(0.0191) 
(0.164) 
(0.0134) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(0.257) 
[0.375] 
[0.771] 
[0.486] 
[0.000] 
[0.719] 
Observations 
343,184 
468,134 
468,134 
468,134 
468,134 
R-squared 
0.016 
0.055 
0.007 
0.012 
0.063 
Pre-treatment mean 
for CA parents of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0169 
0.188 
0.0143 
0.0106 
0.164 </p>

<p>Notes: Cluster-robust p-values in parentheses. p-values calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are 
in brackets. The "Two-parent households" sample is conditional on the father being married. The "Both 
parents employed" sample is conditional on both parents being employed (such that the leave variable 
is non-missing for both). The coefficient in the first row is the DDD effect of CA-PFL on the leave-taking 
outcome, comparing fathers (or mothers) of infants to those of 1-to 3-year-olds, in California vs. other 
states, before and after the introduction of CA-PFL for fathers (or mothers) whose youngest child is a 
first parity birth (within the household); the second coefficient is the differential effect for fathers (or 
mothers) whose youngest child is a higher parity birth. All models also include controls for individual 
characteristics, state and time dummy variables, and state-year fixed-effects. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A4. Heterogeneous effects by gender of youngest child-Two-parent household sample. </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>Two-parent households </p>

<p>Both parents employed </p>

<p>Father is 
on leave, 
mother 
does not 
work </p>

<p>Either 
parent is 
on leave </p>

<p>Both 
parents are 
on leave </p>

<p>Father only 
is on leave </p>

<p>Mother 
only is on 
leave </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 
0.000358 
0.0433 
0.00833 
0.0103 
0.0247 
(0.0820) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
[0.956] 
[0.175] 
[0.085] 
[0.021] 
[0.320] 
CA*post*under1*girl 
0.00674 
−0.00715 
−0.00762 
−0.0104 
0.0109 
(0.0138) 
(0.1980) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(&lt;0.0001) 
(0.0574) 
[0.408] 
[0.752] 
[0.312] 
[0.148] 
[0.696] 
Observations 
340,838 
466,661 
466,661 
466,661 
466,661 
R-squared 
0.016 
0.055 
0.007 
0.012 
0.063 
Pre-treatment mean 
for CA parents of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0169 
0.188 
0.0143 
0.0106 
0.164 </p>

<p>Notes: Cluster-robust p-values in parentheses. p-values calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are 
in brackets. The "Two-parent households" sample is conditional on the father being married. The "Both 
parents employed" sample is conditional on both parents being employed (such that the leave variable 
is non-missing for both).The coefficient in the first row is the DDD effect of CA-PFL on the leave-taking 
outcome, comparing fathers (or mothers) of infants to those of 1-to 3-year-olds, in California vs. other 
states, before and after the introduction of CA-PFL for fathers (or mothers) whose youngest child is a 
boy; the second coefficient is the differential effect for fathers (or mothers) whose youngest child is a girl 
compared to those with a boy. All models also include controls for individual characteristics, state and 
time dummy variables, and state-year fixed-effects. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A5. Results excluding controls and excluding year 2000. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Outcome: Father is on leave, all parents sample </p>

<p>Excluding controls </p>

<p>Excluding year 2000 </p>

<p>DD state </p>

<p>DD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD 2-4 </p>

<p>DDD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD state </p>

<p>DD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD 2-4 </p>

<p>DDD 1-3 </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 </p>

<p>0.00882 </p>

<p>0.00731 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>[0.055] </p>

<p>[0.154] </p>

<p>CA*post </p>

<p>0.0117 </p>

<p>0.00945 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>[0.034] </p>

<p>[0.030] </p>

<p>Post*under1 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.0122 </p>

<p>0.0083 </p>

<p>0.00997 </p>

<p>(0.0022) </p>

<p>(0.0004) </p>

<p>(0.0204) </p>

<p>(0.0066) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>252,198 </p>

<p>109,064 </p>

<p>99,688 </p>

<p>879,873 </p>

<p>224,937 </p>

<p>97,683 </p>

<p>89,427 </p>

<p>789,026 </p>

<p>R-squared </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>Individual controls </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year controls </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Time FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year FE </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Pre-treatment mean </p>

<p>for CA fathers of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0199 </p>

<p>0.0199 </p>

<p>0.0199 </p>

<p>0.0199 </p>

<p>0.0226 </p>

<p>0.0226 </p>

<p>0.0226 </p>

<p>0.0226 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Robust p-values 
in parentheses. Specifications that compare across states (columns 1, 4, 5, and 8) have cluster-robust p-values, </p>

<p>clustered at the state level. </p>

<p>In specifications that compare across states, p-values 
calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are shown in brackets. p-values </p>

<p>calculated from robust standard </p>

<p>errors in parentheses for within-California specifications (columns 2 and 3). This table replicates the first four columns of Table 2, but columns (1) through </p>

<p>4 omit individual and state-year controls and columns 5 through 8 exclude observations from 2000 because the Census might be different from the ACS. The 
sample includes all employed fathers. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Table A6. Estimates based on alternative samples of fathers. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Outcome: Father is on leave 
Father worked at least one week last year </p>

<p>All fathers </p>

<p>DD state </p>

<p>DD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD 2-4 </p>

<p>DDD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD state </p>

<p>DD 1-3 </p>

<p>DD 2-4 </p>

<p>DDD 1-3 </p>

<p>CA*post*under1 </p>

<p>0.00804 </p>

<p>0.00755 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>[0.060] </p>

<p>[0.048] </p>

<p>CA*post </p>

<p>0.00769 </p>

<p>0.00735 </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>(&lt;0.0001) </p>

<p>[0.061] </p>

<p>[0.073] </p>

<p>Post*under1 </p>

<p>0.00907 </p>

<p>0.0112 </p>

<p>0.00857 </p>

<p>0.0108 </p>

<p>(0.0024) </p>

<p>(0.0003) </p>

<p>(0.0029) </p>

<p>(0.0003) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>269,010 </p>

<p>117,707 </p>

<p>107,542 </p>

<p>937,452 </p>

<p>279,603 </p>

<p>123,769 </p>

<p>113,194 </p>

<p>976,475 </p>

<p>R-squared </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>Individual controls </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year controls </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Time FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State FE </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>State-year FE </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Pre-treatment mean </p>

<p>for CA fathers of 
infants </p>

<p>0.0181 </p>

<p>0.0181 </p>

<p>0.0181 </p>

<p>0.0181 </p>

<p>0.0176 </p>

<p>0.0176 </p>

<p>0.0176 </p>

<p>0.0176 </p>

<p>Notes: 
Robust p-values 
in parentheses. Specifications that compare across states (columns 1, 4, 5, and 8) have cluster-robust p-values, </p>

<p>clustered at the state level. </p>

<p>In specifications that compare across states, p-values 
calculated using the Ferman-Pinto method are shown in brackets. p-values </p>

<p>calculated from robust standard </p>

<p>errors in parentheses for within-California specifications (columns 2 and 3). This table replicates the first four columns of Table 2, but includes all fathers who 
worked at least one week in the previous year in columns 1 through 4, instead of conditioning on employed fathers. Columns 5 through 8 include all fathers, 
regardless of employment status. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>APPENDIX B </p>

<p>This appendix derives the formulas for W and G(M) needed to perform inference 
on a DDD coefficient (β 5 in equation (2)). These estimates are used to implement 
the Ferman and Pinto (2016) method of inference. See Ferman and Pinto (2016) for 
more details on the full implementation of their method. 
We start with a standard DDD model collapsed down to the group level, where s 
is state, t is year, and a is the age of the father's youngest child: 51 </p>

<p>Y sat = β 0 + β 1 C A + β 2 Treat + β 3 Under1 + β 4 C A  *  Post + β 5 C A s 
 *  Under1 </p>

<p>+β 6 Post  *  Under1 + αC A  *  Post  *  Under1 + η sat </p>

<p>The estimated DDD coefficient, ˆ 
α, can be written as: </p>

<p>ˆ 
α = α + 1 </p>

<p>S 1 </p>

<p>S </p>



<p>s =s  *  </p>



<p>1 
A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T 
t =t  *  η sat − 1 </p>

<p>A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 η sat </p>



<p>− </p>

<p>
1 
A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T 
t = t  *  η sat − 1 </p>

<p>A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 η sat </p>



<p>− 1 </p>

<p>S 0 </p>

<p>s  *  −1 </p>



<p>s = 1 </p>



<p>1 
A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T 
t = t  *  η sat − 1 </p>

<p>A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 η sat </p>



<p>− </p>

<p>
1 
A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T 
t = t  *  η sat − 1 </p>

<p>A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 η sat </p>



<p>where S 1 is the number of treated states, S 0 is the number of control states, S is the 
total number of states, s  *  is the first treated state, A 1 is the number of infant groups, 
A 0 is the number of non-infant groups, A is the maximum age of children in the 
sample, T 1 is the number of treated periods, T 0 is the number of untreated periods, 
T is the total number of periods, and t  *  is the first treated period. Here we assume 
there is only one infant group, a = 0, but this can easily be generalized to allow for 
multiple treated ages. 
We can write this as: </p>

<p>ˆ 
α = α + 
1 
S 1 </p>

<p>S </p>



<p>s =s  *  </p>

<p>W s − 
1 
S 0 </p>

<p>s  *  −1 </p>



<p>s = 1 </p>

<p>W s </p>

<p>where 52 </p>

<p>W s = </p>

<p>
1 
A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>



<p>a=0 </p>

<p>T </p>



<p>t=t  *  </p>

<p>η sat − 
1 
A 1 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>



<p>a=0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>



<p>t=1 </p>

<p>η sat </p>



<p>− </p>

<p>
1 
A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 1 </p>

<p>A </p>



<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T </p>



<p>t = t  *  </p>

<p>η sat − 
1 
A 0 </p>

<p>1 
T 0 </p>

<p>A </p>



<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>



<p>t = 1 </p>

<p>η sat </p>



<p>51 In implementation, we first regress out the individual level controls as recommended in F-P. 
52 W s is referred to as W j in F-P. </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

<p>Paid Family Leave and Fathers' Leave-Taking </p>

<p>Assuming that errors are correlated within states and M(s, a, t) is the number of 
individual-level observations in cell s, a, t, </p>

<p>η sat = ν st + 
1 
M (s, a, t) </p>

<p>M(s,a,t) </p>



<p>i = 1 </p>

<p>ε isat </p>

<p>so: </p>

<p>var (W s ) = var </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T 
t =t  *  ν st − 1 </p>

<p>T 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 ν st </p>



<p>− </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T 
t =t  *  ν st − 1 </p>

<p>T 0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 
t = 1 ν st </p>



<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  </p>



<p>1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>i = 1 </p>

<p>ε isat </p>

<p>
− 1 </p>

<p>T 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 </p>



<p>1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>i = 1 </p>

<p>ε isat </p>

<p>
− </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  </p>



<p>1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>i = 1 </p>

<p>ε isat </p>

<p>
− 1 </p>

<p>T 0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 </p>



<p>1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>i = 1 </p>

<p>ε isat </p>

<p>
This can be expressed as: </p>

<p>var (W s ) = A + B </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>2 A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 0 </p>

<p>2 A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>



<p>where A and B are constants. 
Let </p>

<p>q = </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 0 </p>

<p>2 0 </p>

<p>a = 0 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 1 </p>

<p>2 A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t =t  *  
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>
1 
T 0 </p>

<p>2 A </p>

<p>a = 1 </p>

<p>t  *  −1 </p>

<p>t = 1 
1 
M(s,a,t) </p>

<p>Following F-P, the predicted G(M) is obtained by regressingˆW  s on q and a con-
stant, and then 
G(M) is a consistent estimator for var (W s ). </p>

<p>Journal of Policy Analysis and Management DOI: 10.1002/pam 
Published on behalf of the Association for Public Policy Analysis and Management </p>

</text></tei>