<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1108%2Fjes-01-2015-0013" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>If you would like to write for this, or any other Emerald publication, then please use our Emerald 
for Authors service information about how to choose which publication to write for and submission 
guidelines are available for all. Please visit www.emeraldinsight.com/authors for more information. </p>

<p>About Emerald www.emeraldinsight.com </p>

<p>Emerald is a global publisher linking research and practice to the benefit of society. The company 
manages a portfolio of more than 290 journals and over 2,350 books and book series volumes, as 
well as providing an extensive range of online products and additional customer resources and 
services. </p>

<p>Emerald is both COUNTER 4 and TRANSFER compliant. The organization is a partner of the 
Committee on Publication Ethics (COPE) and also works with Portico and the LOCKSS initiative for 
digital archive preservation. </p>

<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Purpose -The purpose of this paper is to investigate how trade openness affects the structural 
vulnerability of developing countries. The analysis is conducted on both the entire sample of 
105 countries as well as two sub-samples, namely least developed countries (LDCs) and non-LDCs. 
Design/methodology/approach -To perform the analysis, the author employs fixed-effects 
(within) regressions supplemented by instrumental variables technique based on the two-step 
generalized methods of moments approach. 
Findings -The author finds empirical evidence that although trade policy liberalization reduces the 
structural vulnerability on the entire sample developing countries, no statistically significant effect of 
such liberalization is obtained either on LDCs or non-LDCs. However, trade policy liberalization 
appears to reduce countries' exposure to shocks, result that applies to the entire sample as well as the 
two sub-samples. The author also observes that trade policy liberalization exerts no (statistically) 
significant effect on the size of shocks that affect developing countries, result that applies to both the 
full sample and the sub-samples of LDCs and non-LDCs. 
Research limitations/implications -In the absence of a well-established theoretical framework on 
how trade openness affects the structural vulnerability of developing, the author adopts a pragmatic 
approach by drawing upon many insights of Loayza and Raddatz (2007) who study the structural 
determinants of external vulnerability. 
Practical implications -Developing countries in general and LDCs in particular could address 
their structural weaknesses by making optimal use of their trade policies. In particular, they could 
better use the flexibilities available to them in provisions of the World Trade Organization (WTO)' 
Agreements. In this respect, the international community, notably donors of the developed world has a 
key role to play. 
Originality/value -This is the first study exploring how trade openness, capturing here through 
trade policy liberalization affects the structural vulnerability of developing countries. 
Journal of Economic Studies 
Vol. 43 No. 1, 2016 
pp. 70-89 
© Emerald Group Publishing Limited 
0144-3585 
DOI 10.1108/JES-01-2015-0013 </p>

<p>Received 17 January 2015 
Revised 5 March 2015 
Accepted 1 April 2015 </p>

<p>The current issue and full text archive of this journal is available on Emerald Insight at: 
www.emeraldinsight.com/0144-3585.htm </p>

<p>JEL Classification -F10, O11 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Should developing countries, in particular least developed countries (LDCs), 
fear opening up their economies to international trade? More specifically, would trade 
policy liberalization contribute to enhancing or reducing these countries' vulnerability 
to shocks? This paper strives to provide an answer to this question. 
While trade openness could provide many benefits to countries -especially the 
poorest -under certain conditions, the international trade literature has also 
established that it exposes them to exogenous shocks. Countries' vulnerability to 
shocks has traditionally been captured in the empirical literature by the volatility of 
aggregate output (see, e.g. Easterly et al., 2001; Haddad et al., 2011; Loayza and  Raddatz, 2007; Raddatz, 2007). However, this measure has been criticized as it 
encompasses not only countries' vulnerability to shocks but also the economic policies 
implemented to mitigate the effects of these shocks. To assess the impact of trade 
openness on countries' vulnerability, we take a different approach by using a 
vulnerability indicator that measures structural vulnerability, that is, countries' 
vulnerability that does not depend on their economic policies. In so doing, we make a 
distinction between countries that are classified as LDCs -a category of countries 
designated by the United Nations as the poorest and most vulnerable to shocks in the 
world -and those that are not. Our study is close in spirit to that of Loayza and  Raddatz (2007) who, in exploring the structural determinants of external vulnerability, 
measure these according to trade impact in terms of trade shocks on output. 
To our knowledge, this is the first study to explore the impact of trade openness on 
developing countries' structural vulnerability. We obtain prima facie evidence that trade 
policy liberalization in developing countries in general and LDCs in particular has 
contributed significantly to reducing their economic vulnerability, in particular their 
exposure to shocks. This could in principle help to dissipate the view of many governments 
in developing countries, notably in LDCs, that protectionist measures complemented by the 
strengthening of domestic demand -to spur growth -would be the right solution to 
protect themselves from the vulnerability of their economies to external shocks. 
The rest of the paper is structured as follows. Section 2 provides a brief literature 
review on the concept of economic vulnerability and its association with trade openness. 
Section 3 describes the model and the econometric methodology and Section 4 discusses 
the expected effect of the explanatory variables. Section 5 discusses the measurement 
of the explanatory variables and presents the data sources. Section 6 interprets the 
estimation results and Section 7 concludes. </p>

<p>2. Economic vulnerability and trade openness 
The concept of "vulnerability" refers to that of "risk." There are several definitions 
associated with the concept of "risk" depending on the disciplines in which it is studied. 
In economics, the concept of vulnerability has generally been approached from both 
macroeconomic and microeconomic perspectives. The microeconomic perspective 
places emphasis on the impact of shocks on the well-being of individual households, 
whereas the macroeconomic perspective focusses on the impact of these shocks on 
economic growth (see also Seth and Ragab, 2012). Naude et al. (2009) provide a general 
definition of "vulnerability," considering it to be the risk that a "system" undergoes 
from negative change due to a "perturbation." In the same spirit, Gallopín (2006) defines 
"vulnerability" as the likelihood of a system being affected negatively by some sort of 
perturbation or sudden "shock" going beyond the normal range of variability. 
Following Essers (2013), in a macroeconomic setting, one can consider the system to be 
an individual country and the perturbation to be a number of macroeconomic shocks. </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>More specifically, in the area of macroeconomics, the concept of "economic 
vulnerability" was defined for the first time in 1990 by the Maltese Ambassador, His 
Excellency Alexander Borg Olivier, who stated: </p>

<p>[…] such an index is important because it reiterates that the per capita GDP [gross domestic 
product] of island developing countries is not itself an adequate measurement of the level of 
development of these countries as it does not reflect the structural and institutional weaknesses 
and the several handicaps facing island developing countries (Malta Government, 1990, p. 7). </p>

<p>Briguglio (1993, 1995) was then among the first to apply this concept in the context of 
small island developing states. Since then, many conceptual and empirical studies have 
been conducted on the issue of economic vulnerability. Since then the concept of 
macroeconomic economic vulnerability has gained currency. Briguglio et al. (2008, p. 1), 
for example, define economic vulnerability as "as the exposure of an economy to 
exogenous shocks, arising out of economic openness." Guillaumont (2009, p. 197)  provides a dynamic definition of vulnerability, considering it to be "the risk that 
economic growth [in a given country] is markedly and extensively reduced by shocks." 
The empirical literature on the macroeconomic vulnerability of countries has usually 
considered the variability of output (see, e.g. Ramey and Ramey, 1995) or similar 
indicators as the manifestation of the vulnerability phenomenon. As far as international 
trade is concerned, the applied literature has established that under suitable conditions, 
trade openness is positively associated with growth outcomes (see also Frankel and  Romer, 1999). However, the sign of the average effect of trade openness on countries' 
proneness to shocks (macroeconomic vulnerability) remains an issue of hot debate. 
The strand of the empirical literature that examines the "destabilizing effects" of trade 
openness on countries' vulnerability to shocks has tended to use the volatility of 
aggregate output as a means of capturing the measure of this vulnerability. Some studies 
(e.g. di Giovanni and Levchenko, 2009; Haddad et al., 2011; Loayza and Raddatz, 2007;  Raddatz, 2007) find that an increase in the degree of trade openness leads to higher 
volatility in outcome variables such as aggregate income, especially in developing 
countries. Others (e.g. Cavallo and Frankel, 2008; Kose and Yi, 2001) either find no 
significant relationship between an increase in the degree of trade interdependence and 
domestic macroeconomic volatility, or just a temporary relationship (see Santos-Paulino,  2010). All this leads Montalbano (2011) to conclude that the applied literature on trade 
and instability itself gives the impression of instability (this author provides a good 
critical survey of the empirical literature on the subject matter). 
The variability of output or similar indicators usually considered the manifestation of 
the vulnerability phenomenon also capture other factors such as the resilience policies 
(economic policies) implemented by these countries in the face of shocks or policies to 
reduce their exposure to shocks. Recognizing the weaknesses of using aggregate output 
volatility to capture the vulnerability of countries, the United Nations Committee for 
Development Policy (CDP) has developed and progressively refined (through successive  revisions in 2003, 2006 and 2009) an economic vulnerability index (EVI), which captures 
vulnerability caused by structural factors. Structural economic vulnerability as employed 
in this study refers to the "retrospective EVI," jointly calculated and updated on an 
annual basis by the FERDI[2] (see, e.g. Guillaumont and Cariolle, 2011) with the United 
Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs (UNDESA). The EVI is the result of 
three components: first, the size and frequency of exogenous shocks, either observed 
(ex post vulnerability) or anticipated (ex ante vulnerability); second, exposure to shocks; 
third, the capacity to react to shocks, or resilience. Therefore, structural vulnerability </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>(that is, the EVI), which results from factors that are independent of a country's current 
political will, differs from vulnerability deriving from policy, which results from recent 
policy choices. In other words, an index of structural economic vulnerability is related to 
structural factors -not policy factors -that are beyond the present control of the country 
and also influence global vulnerability, mainly through resilience (Guillaumont, 2009). 
This structural vulnerability index is a composite index of "shocks" and "exposure to 
shocks"; both indicators are equally weighted. The last update was in November 2013. 
The structure of this index is provided in Appendix 1. 
Other macroeconomic vulnerability indicators have been proposed in the empirical 
literature. The first is that of Baritto (2008), which is termed the Global Vulnerability 
Index. This index encompasses trade, production structure, reserves and the poverty ratio. 
It therefore entails both structural and economic policy factors and thus is not suitable for 
our analysis. Another interesting indicator is that of the International Monetary Fund: 
as noted by Essers (2013), the most comprehensive and systematic approach to measuring 
and monitoring developing country vulnerabilities today is embodied in the IMF's 
Vulnerability Exercise for Low-Income Countries (VELIC) and Vulnerability Exercise for 
Emerging Economies (VEE) (see, e.g. IMF, 2011). Unfortunately, the results of neither the 
VELIC nor the VEE are publicly available, at least not at the level of individual developing 
countries, mainly because of market sensitivity. </p>

<p>3. Model and econometric methodology 
Our analysis is based upon an unbalanced panel of 105 developing countries (for the 
list of countries, see Appendix 2), comprising 41 LDCs and 64 non-LDCs (non-LDCs) 
and covering the period 1995-2011. The countries were chosen on the basis of time 
coverage for all the variables used in the model, as described below. 
Given the absence of a complete theoretical model for analyzing structural policies 
that affect structural vulnerability, our approach is more pragmatic. We estimate an 
empirical model that draws upon many insights from Loayza and Raddatz (2007) who 
study the structural determinants of external vulnerability. 
The model can be described as follows: </p>

<p>Log EV I 
ð 
Þ it ¼ a 0 þ a 1 Log TradePolicy 
ð 
Þ it þ X itÀ1 G þ m i þ e it 
(1) </p>

<p>where i is an index capturing the country, i ¼ 1, …, 105; t is an index capturing the time 
period, t ¼ 1995, …, 2011; EVI represents the measure of a country's structural 
economic vulnerability; Trade Policy is the measure of the trade policy stance of a given 
country i (as described below); α 0 , α 1 and Γ are parameters to be estimated; X is a vector 
of control variables measuring structural policies and structural factors that 
characterize country i and that will likely influence the effects of trade openness on 
the EVI variable. These variables include global financial integration or financial 
openness (denoted by gross financial integration (GFI)), financial development (denoted 
by FD), and human capital, proxied here by the Human Assets Index (HAI). All these 
control variables are in "log" form and lagged by one year so that they are 
predetermined with respect to our dependent variable. μ i are country-specific effects, 
which could be fixed or random effects. The disturbance ε i,t is assumed to be 
independently and identically distributed (i.i.d., 0, s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e ), that is, it is assumed not to 
be correlated with the explanatory variables of the model and its normality is not 
required (Baltagi, 2002). </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>We first undertake several diagnostic tests on model (1) over the full sample. 
These tests include the cross-sectional dependence test, the Hausman test, which takes 
into account the result obtained in the previous test, the Breusch-Pagan test of 
heteroskedasticity, and the Wooldridge (2002) test of serial correlation. 
The dimensions of our panel data set (T ¼ 17 and n ¼ 105) suggest the potential 
presence of cross-sectional dependence in the data. To check whether fixed effects or 
random effects are suitable for our analysis, we perform the Hausman test, as suggested 
by Hoechle (2007), which takes into account the possibility of cross-sectional dependence 
in our data. This test is a slightly modified version of the panel-robust version of the 
Hausman test suggested by Wooldridge (2002, p. 288ff). Hoechle's (2007) adaptation of 
Wooldridge's (2002) test is robust to very general forms of spatial and temporal 
dependence in the residuals. In addition to the "modified standard Hausman test," we also 
undertake two further tests, respectively a test for the presence of heteroskedasticity and 
one for serial correlation in the residuals. If the Hausman test rejects the random effects in 
favor of the fixed effects, and if our residuals are heteroskedastic and serially correlated, 
then we estimate model (1) with fixed effects by simultaneously taking into account the 
possibility of heteroskedasticity, serial correlation, and cross-sectional dependence in the 
residuals. In other words, we estimate a fixed-effects (within) regression model with 
Driscoll and Kraay[3] (1998) standard errors (henceforth referred to as FE-DK), which 
Hoechle (2007) adapted in Stata for unbalanced panels. 
However, our variable "TradePolicy" could be considered endogenous with respect to 
the "EVI" variable, especially in real world scenarios under which future shocks to EVI 
may drive today's policy decisions toward changing trade openness (see also Haddad et al.,  2013 for this argument). To address this endogeneity issue regarding our variable of 
interest, we adopt the instrumental variable approach based on the two-step generalized 
methods of moments (GMM) technique. This is known to provide more consistent results 
compared to the simple two-stage least squares procedure. We first use the one-year 
lagged values of the variable "TradePolicy" as our initial instrument on the premise that 
the trade policy stance of a country in a given year could depend on its stance in the 
previous year. In addition, we choose as a second instrument the workers' remittances, 
expressed as a percentage of GDP. Remittance inflows to countries generally accrue to 
households, which can save or spend them by purchasing domestic goods and services, 
thereby potentially increasing domestic prices. As a result, the real exchange rate could 
appreciate, possibly generating the "Dutch disease," i.e., a negative impact on the economy 
resulting from foreign currency inflows. In response to this real exchange rate 
appreciation, which would undermine the competitiveness of the recipient country's 
economy, governments may be tempted to use trade policy to offset the negative effect of 
real exchange rate appreciation, that is, they will reduce trade barriers by softening trade 
measures. Moreover, in countries highly dependent on remittances to finance their budgets 
and where a non-negligible share of these remittances is used to finance imports, 
governments may be tempted to lower trade barriers to reduce the costs of imports for 
their citizens. Against this background, we conjecture that remittances are associated with 
trade policy liberalization and therefore expect the variable representing remittances, 
expressed as a share of GDP (denoted by "Remitgdp") to be positively correlated with the 
variable "TradePolicy." To test whether our two instruments are correlated with our 
dependent variable, we estimate model (2) by means of FE-DK (as for model 1): </p>

<p>Log TradePolicy 
ð 
Þ it ¼ b 0 þ b 1 Log TradePolicy 
ð 
Þ itÀ1 þ b 2 Log Remitgdp 
ð 
Þ it þ n i þ o it </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>where i ¼ 1, …, 105; t ¼ 1995, …, 2011; β 0 , β 1 , and β 2 are parameters to be estimated; ν i are 
fixed-country effects; ω it is the error term. 
All in all, if the coefficients β 1 , and β 2 are statistically significant at the conventional 
level, we use the two instruments to perform our instrumental variable (IV) technique 
through the two-step GMM technique to model Equation (1). It is important to 
emphasize that in performing the IV two-step GMM procedure, we take account of the 
likely cross-sectional dependence of residuals by correcting the standard errors 
following the method suggested by Driscoll and Kraay (1998) (see footnote 3). 
To sum up, we estimate model (1) using the FE-DK technique, but also take into account 
the possible endogeneity of our variable "TradePolicy," estimating it by means of the 
two-step GMM technique where the cross-sectional dependence in residuals is considered. 
As the "EVI" variable entails two main components, namely the exposure to shocks 
variable (denoted by "Exposure") and the shock variable (denoted by "Shock"), we also 
estimate model (1) following the steps described below by replacing the "EVI" variable 
with each of its components. This allows us to examine how the trade policy 
implemented by the governments of these countries affects their exposure to shocks 
(notably the size of this exposure), and whether this trade policy is associated with the 
rise in the size of the shocks faced by these countries. </p>

<p>4. Expected effect of the explanatory variables on structural 
vulnerability 
In this section, we discuss the expected effect of each of the explanatory variables on 
structural vulnerability in turn. </p>

<p>4.1 Trade policy liberalization 
It is well known that as trade integration deepens, economies are naturally prone to 
external shocks. This is one of the most important rationales that militates against 
developing countries adopting export-led growth strategies. Does this mean that 
greater openness to trade necessarily increase countries' vulnerability to shocks? 
At this stage of the analysis, we are still agnostic regarding the expected sign of the 
average effect of trade openness (connectivity) on the countries' structural economic 
vulnerability. On the one hand, greater trade liberalization (openness) can come at the 
expense of structural vulnerability if countries that open up their economies to 
international trade are exposed to frequent external shocks (uncontrolled by 
governments) because the benefits from trade do not outweigh the losses due to 
frequent external shocks. These shocks will in turn push up the countries' structural 
vulnerability by increasing their exposure to shocks. Therefore a negative effect of 
trade openness on the structural vulnerability of developing countries can be expected. 
The detrimental effect of trade openness on exposure to external shocks (leading to a 
rise in this exposure) can be observed when a weakening of export performance 
triggers a sudden cessation of capital flows. Eichengreen and Rose (1999), Glick and  Rose (1999), and Forbes (2002) provide strong evidence of the role of trade linkages in 
spreading crisis in regions. 
On the other hand, we can follow Haddad et al. (2011) and argue that trade openness 
can reduce countries' structural economic vulnerability if it enhances the possibility of 
international risk sharing. This can happen through better integration in a broader range 
of global value chains, and implicit and explicit insurance schemes such as joint ventures, 
international lending, production diversification, and formal insurance contracts. </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Trade openness can also help countries deal with natural and environmental 
shocks by providing foreign exchanges, thereby reducing, all things being equal, 
the structural economic vulnerability of these countries. In the same vein, trade 
openness can reduce countries' exposure to foreign shocks by helping them adjust to 
a cut-off in international financing (Montalbano, 2011). Rose (2005) provides empirical 
support for this hypothesis, and Cavallo and Frankel (2008) show evidence that 
trade openness makes countries less vulnerable to both severe sudden stops and 
currency crashes. 
The effect of trade openness on countries' economic vulnerability can be mediated 
by its degree of export diversification. Melitz (2003) shows that trade openness can 
induce export diversification by increasing the number of exporters in those countries 
facing improved export opportunities. In such a situation, opening up an economy to 
trade can, all things being equal, reduce the country's structural economic 
vulnerability. However, the Heckscher-Ohlin model suggests that trade openness can 
increase the profitability of traditional sectors in countries experiencing a concentration 
of primary commodities, thereby exerting a negative incentive to diversify its exports 
away from commodities. As a result, exposure to shocks and consequently economic 
vulnerability will increase. 
Finally, if trade openness reinforces a country's production specialization and 
concentration (for instance in the agriculture sector) through the exploitation of 
its comparative advantage, it could increase the risk of structural vulnerability. 
Conversely, trade openness could reduce a country's economic vulnerability by 
increasing technological diffusion and expansion of the potential markets. </p>

<p>4.2 Financial openness 
Openness in capital account transactions can facilitate risk sharing and enhance capital 
allocation. Accordingly, it can either increase production specialization and therefore 
the risk of economic vulnerability, or result in product diversification, which can 
potentially reduce countries' economic vulnerability. In addition, countries opening up 
their financial accounts could increase their exposure to external financial shocks and 
therefore increase their economic vulnerability. The average effect of financial 
openness on countries' structural economic vulnerability is a priori unknown and may 
well depend on whether we rely on de facto or de jure measures of financial integration 
(see the next section for a discussion on this matter). </p>

<p>4.3 Financial development 
By reducing liquidity constraints, financial development can not only facilitate export 
diversification by increasing the number of exports but can also act as a risk-sharing 
scheme when countries encounter shocks. Hence, we can expect a negative effect of 
financial development on structural vulnerability. In the same spirit, Feeney and  Hillman (2001) contend that the strong functioning of domestic financial markets can 
facilitate the diversification of domestic risk (through hedging opportunities) in the 
presence of shocks, and consequently reduce a country's economic vulnerability. 
However, if financial markets, including banks, are reluctant to extend credit when 
countries face severe shocks, one could expect financial development to generate 
an increase in structural vulnerability. Financial development could dampen the risk 
of an increase in economic vulnerability, notably through the country's exposure to 
shocks, by helping to promote innovation activities. </p>

<p>76 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Manova (2008) shows that the positive effect of financial development will be 
stronger in sectors with greater requirements for outside finance or fewer collateral 
assets; only then can financial liberalization induce lower economic vulnerability by 
financing dependent industries to produce more differentiated products. In contrast, if 
investors do not want to take risks with untried ventures and decide to concentrate 
financial resources in existing activities in which the economy has already been shown 
to be competitive, the development of capital markets could lead to export 
concentration and increase the risk of economic vulnerability for the country (see 
also Agosin et al., 2012). 
Rodrik (1998) noted that if trade increases aggregate risk, it is possible to diversify 
this risk in purely domestic financial markets. Thus, a degree of international risk 
sharing is expected to reduce the country's economic vulnerability. That said, Svaleryd  and Vlachos (2002) point out that whatever measures we use to capture the degree of 
domestic financial development, these will capture the effect of international financial 
integration. Hence, it is possible that the effect of financial development on economic 
vulnerability absorbs the effect of financial integration and vice versa. </p>

<p>4.4 Human capital 
An important structural factor with the potential to help countries benefit from trade 
openness and reduce their structural vulnerability is the level of their human capital. 
A good level of human capital (captured through the level of education and health) can 
enhance the ability of nations to create or adapt new technologies (Borensztein et al.,  1998). In addition, Bravo-Ortega and de Gregorio (2005) note that human capital can 
contribute as a direct input in the production process, and complement other factors of 
production such as physical capital and natural resources. Overall, we can expect a 
country with a high level of human capital accumulation to take advantage of trade 
openness to reduce its economic vulnerability, including through increasing export 
diversification (thereby reducing the country's exposure). </p>

<p>5. Measures of explanatory variables and data sources 
In this section, we discuss the measures of each of our explanatory variables and 
present the source of the data associated with the variable concerned. </p>

<p>5.1 Measure of trade openness 
In the empirical literature, trade openness has been measured in various ways as there 
is no perfect way to do so. While some researchers use incidence-based indicators, such 
as the average level of tariffs, the level of export taxes, the percentage of imports 
subject to nontariff restrictions, or a combination of these partial trade policy 
instruments (see, e.g. the Sachs and Warner indicator), others use outcome indicators in 
terms of prices (Dollar, 1992) and quantities, such as trade openness (measured by the 
ratio of exports plus imports of goods and services in percentage of GDP), which is 
commonly used in the literature. 
The drawback of incidence-based measures is that they do not reflect the entirety of 
trade measures implemented by a country to regulate its trade flows. In addition, 
a combination of these partial trade policy instruments, such as that proposed by Sachs 
and Warner, is limited to the extent that the indicator of trade liberalization is a dummy 
variable, which does not necessarily reflect the intensity or the degree of trade 
liberalization undertaken by a country. Moreover, such an indicator is not available for 
many LDCs, the set of countries of interest in this study. </p>

<p>77 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Outcome trade policy indicators related to prices, such as the Dollar-type index, also 
have their limitations. The Dollar-type index proposed by Dollar (1992) is calculated on 
the basis of the regression of the real exchange rate on its non-policy determinants. 
An indicator of trade policy is therefore derived from this regression as the ratio of the 
actual real exchange rate relative to its predicted value. Such an index would be 
sensitive to the set of countries used in the regression. 
The same limitation applies to outcome indicators in terms of quantities, notably the 
one commonly used in the literature: trade openness measured by the ratio of exports 
plus imports of goods and services in percentage of GDP. This ratio is not suitable for 
our analysis as it encompasses geographic and demographic factors (which are also 
included in our EVI), as well as trade and trade-related policies (the latter comprising 
economic policies and political factors that are liable to affect trade flows). 
One could also follow the practice in the empirical literature of regressing the trade 
share on the non-policy determinants of trade flows (demographic and geographic 
factors) to discriminate between "natural openness" and "residual openness." 
The former is the fitted value of the regression, whereas the latter is the residual of 
the regression and represents the "man-made choices" shaping a country's trade 
openness. However, "residual openness" considered as a measure of trade policy could 
be misleading for two reasons: First, it includes not only the effect of trade policies on 
trade flows, but also the effects on non-trade policies such as economic policies, 
institutions, and other political factors that influence trade flows. Second, as it is a 
residual of a regression, it will sum up to zero so that the measure obtained is not 
"absolute" but "relative," as well as depending on the countries selected in the data set. 
In this study, we measure our trade policy variable using the "freedom to trade" 
indicator proposed by the Heritage Foundation and also well used in the empirical 
literature. This indicator is a component of the Economic Freedom Index[4] developed 
by the Heritage Foundation, and combines measures of trade taxes, tariff rates and 
trade barriers, and capital market controls. Despite its drawbacks, it presents the 
advantage of providing both an annual (starting from the year 1995) "absolute" and not 
"relative" measure of the degree of trade policy liberalization of a given country, and 
covers many countries in the world, including LDCs. </p>

<p>5.2 Financial openness 
Kose et al. (2009) discuss the choice between quantity-and price-based measures of 
financial integration and argue in favor of quantity-based, i.e., de facto measures. In the 
early literature, de jure measures, such as those based on the IMF's Annual Report on 
Exchange Arrangements and Exchange Restrictions, have also been used extensively. 
However, Baltagi et al. (2009) and Friedrich et al. (2013) argue that such measures do not 
fully capture the degree of enforcement and effectiveness of capital controls, or 
regulations in other fields that affect capital flows. Moreover, Baltagi et al. (2009)  provide a lengthy discussion on de jure vs de facto measures of financial openness and 
conclude that there are difficulties in settling the debate concerning the theoretical pros 
and cons of these measures. 
We opt primarily for a de facto indicator of financial integration in our study. This is 
because it best suits our aim to capture the extent to which the financial connection of a 
country with the rest of the world affects its structural economic vulnerability. 
In addition, a country can open up its financial accounts to the rest of the world without 
necessarily being affected severely by an external financial shock because its 
dependence on external financial assets and liabilities is relatively low. Therefore, we </p>

<p>78 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>use the standard measure of GFI, defined as the sum of total foreign assets and total 
foreign liabilities in percentage of GDP. Gross measures of financial integration have 
the advantage of capturing the risk-sharing benefits of financial integration. 
The alternative use of total foreign liabilities in percentage of GDP to capture only 
the financing side of financial integration does not quantitatively or qualitatively 
change our results[5]. To compute this indicator, we use the External Wealth of Nations 
Mark II Database, constructed and updated by Lane and Milesi-Ferretti (2007). </p>

<p>5.3 Financial development 
We measure financial development by the ratio of private credit provided by banks and 
other financial institutions to GDP (expressed in percent). This variable is drawn from 
the database of Beck et al. (2000), updated in 2013. The missing data are obtained from 
the World Development Indicators for 2014. Although there is no single variable to 
capture the extent of financial development, this financial development index is 
expected to grasp adequately the developments in the financial sector in LDCs, 
this sector being characterized by the dominance of the banking sector. </p>

<p>5.4 Human capital 
Human capital is measured through the HAI, provided by FERDI and used by the 
United Nations CDP as one of the criteria for the identification and ranking of a country 
from the list of LDCs. The HAI was calculated by Korachais (2011) up to 2008 and was  updated up to the year 2011 in July 2014 by Closset et al. (2014). It measures human 
capital through an arithmetic average of four indices: the child mortality rate index, the 
prevalence of undernourishment index, the literacy rate index, and the secondary 
enrollment gross rate index. All these indices, including the HAI itself, are bounded 
between 0 and 100 where 0 reflects the lowest level and 100 the highest attainable level. </p>

<p>6. Estimation results and discussion 
We report the outcome of the diagnostic tests in Table I. It was not possible to 
performance the cross-sectional dependence test given the unbalanced nature of our 
panel. However, we believe that there is potentially a contemporaneous correlation 
between individual characteristics of the panel and subsequently take this into account 
in our analysis. We therefore perform the Hausman test of fixed vs random effects, 
as proposed by Wooldridge (2002, p. 288ff). </p>

<p>Diagnostic tests </p>

<p>Model with 
"EVI" variable </p>

<p>Model with 
"Exposure" 
variable </p>

<p>Model with 
"Shocks" variable 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) </p>

<p>Hausmann test: statistic ( p-value) 
4.94 (0.0030) 
7.06 (0.0002) 
0.22 (0.8797) 
Breusch-Pagan test of heteroscedasticity 
(F-statistic and its associated p-value) 
3.22 (0.0121) 
10.94 (0.0000) 
2.98 (0.0182) 
Wooldridge (2002) test of autocorrelation 
(F-statistic and p-value associated) 
247.823 (0.0000) 
247.823 (0.0000) 
247.823 (0.0000) 
Note: NB: the Hausmann test performed here is the one recommended by Hoechle (2007), which takes 
into account the cross-sectional dependence in the residuals </p>

<p>Table I. 
Diagnostic tests 
on model (1) </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>The Hausman test rejects the null hypothesis of no fixed effects for all specifications 
except for the specification of model (1) with the variable "shock." This suggests that 
model (1) should be estimated by fixed effects for specifications with either the variable 
"EVI" or the variable "Exposure." Notwithstanding the acceptance of the null 
hypothesis for the specification with the variable "Shock," we estimate it with fixed 
effects given the endogeneity issue raised above. 
For all specifications, the Breusch-Pagan test of heteroskedasticity strongly rejects 
the null hypothesis of homoskedasticity. Furthermore, the Wooldridge test of serial 
correlation also rejects the null hypothesis of the absence of autocorrelation in the 
residuals. Given these results, we proceed to estimate model (1) using the FE-DK 
technique over the full sample, as well as the sub-samples of LDCs and non-LDCs, and 
alternatively with the dependent variables EVI, Exposure, and Shock. The results of the 
estimations are reported in Table II. 
In columns (1), (2), and (3) of this table, we present the results of estimations over the 
entire sample with, respectively, the variables EVI, Exposure, and Shock. Columns (4), (5), 
and (6) contain the results for the sub-sample of LDCs with, respectively, the variables 
EVI, Exposure, and Shock. Finally, columns (7), (8), and (9) contain the results for the 
sub-sample of non-LDCs with, respectively, the variables EVI, Exposure, and Shock. 
For the full sample, structural vulnerability appears to be significantly and 
negatively associated with trade policy at the 5 percent level of statistical significance. 
However, and surprisingly, the coefficient of this variable is statistically insignificant 
(at the conventional level) for the sub-samples. 
Trade policy liberalization exerts a significant and negative effect on the size of 
countries' exposure to shocks, a result that also applies to the sub-samples of LDCs and 
non-LDCs. However, the coefficient of the variable TradePolicy is higher in the case of 
LDCs (−0.033) than non-LDCs (−0.298), although both coefficients are lower than that 
of the entire sample ( À 0.044). 
With respect to the response of the size of countries' shocks to trade policy, 
we find that trade policy liberalization significantly (at the 1 percent level) increases the 
size of LDCs' shocks. However, no significant effect is obtained for the entire sample 
or for the sub-sample of non-LDCs. This shows that in contrast to non-LDCs, LDCs 
are highly susceptible to external shocks when they open their economies to 
international trade. 
However, all the estimation results presented above are based on the premise 
that the variable TradePolicy is weakly exogenous, a hypothesis that is unlikely 
to hold. 
In Table III, we report the results of the model (2) estimations over the entire sample. 
From Table III, we observe that the higher the degree of a country's trade policy 
liberalization in year t-1, the higher it is in year t: the coefficient of the one-year lagged 
value of TradePolicy is positive and statistically significant (at the 1 percent level of 
statistical significance). Moreover, as expected, workers' remittances (percent of GDP) 
contribute to trade liberalization, as the coefficient associated with the variable Log 
(Remitgdp) is positive and statistically significant. We can therefore use these two 
variables as our instruments for the variable TradePolicy in model (1). 
We subsequently report in Table IV the outcome of the model (1) estimations using 
the IV technique based on the two-step GMM procedure. 
The weak identification test (which tests for the strength of our instrumental variables) 
is evaluated against the critical value for 10 percent maximal IV relative bias, provided by 
Stock and Yogo (2005). For all our regressions except those for LDCs (see columns (4), (5), </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Full sample </p>

<p>LDCs </p>

<p>Non-LDCs </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) Log(Shock) </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) </p>

<p>Log 
(Shock) </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) Log(Shock) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>Log(TradePolicy) </p>

<p>−0.0427 </p>

<p>−0.0444 </p>

<p>−0.0307 </p>

<p>0.0280 </p>

<p>−0.0333 </p>

<p>0.117 </p>

<p>−0.0112 </p>

<p>−0.0298 </p>

<p>0.0306 </p>

<p>(0.0176)** (0.0147)*** (0.0260) </p>

<p>(0.0239) 
(0.0113)*** (0.0565)** (0.0123) </p>

<p>(0.00955)*** (0.0210) </p>

<p>Log(GFI) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.0328 </p>

<p>−0.00820 </p>

<p>−0.0706 </p>

<p>0.0152 </p>

<p>−0.00954 </p>

<p>0.0692 </p>

<p>−0.0310 </p>

<p>−0.00462 </p>

<p>−0.0782 </p>

<p>(0.0112)*** (0.00464)* </p>

<p>(0.0238)*** (0.0198) </p>

<p>(0.00571) 
(0.0343)* (0.00803)*** (0.00419) </p>

<p>(0.0220)*** </p>

<p>Log(FD) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.0536 </p>

<p>−0.0278 </p>

<p>−0.101 </p>

<p>−0.0634 </p>

<p>−0.0333 </p>

<p>−0.124 </p>

<p>−0.0221 </p>

<p>−0.0159 </p>

<p>−0.0329 </p>

<p>(0.0128)*** (0.00673)*** (0.0259)*** (0.0281)** </p>

<p>(0.00846)*** (0.0487)** (0.0105)** </p>

<p>(0.00422)*** (0.0282) </p>

<p>Log(HAI) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.210 </p>

<p>−0.151 </p>

<p>−0.215 </p>

<p>−0.097 </p>

<p>−0.126 </p>

<p>0.0281 </p>

<p>−0.776 </p>

<p>−0.338 </p>

<p>−1.322 </p>

<p>(0.0213)*** (0.0153)*** (0.0548)*** (0.0278)5*** (0.0166)*** (0.0615) </p>

<p>(0.0291)*** (0.0595)*** (0.0937)*** </p>

<p>Constant </p>

<p>4.880 </p>

<p>4.545 </p>

<p>4.962 </p>

<p>4.049 </p>

<p>4.530 </p>

<p>2.961 </p>

<p>7.044 </p>

<p>5.187 </p>

<p>9.256 </p>

<p>(0.132) </p>

<p>(0.101)*** 
(0.220)*** (0.170)*** 
(0.0783)*** (0.262)*** (0.128)*** </p>

<p>(0.281)*** </p>

<p>(0.356)*** </p>

<p>Number of countries </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>observations </p>

<p>105-1,346 </p>

<p>105-1,357 </p>

<p>105-1,346 </p>

<p>41-440 </p>

<p>41-451 </p>

<p>41-440 </p>

<p>64-906 </p>

<p>64-906 </p>

<p>64-906 </p>

<p>Within R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.1620 </p>

<p>0.2108 </p>

<p>0.0694 </p>

<p>0.1353 </p>

<p>0.3691 </p>

<p>0.0662 </p>

<p>0.3019 </p>

<p>0.1758 </p>

<p>0.2004 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors are in parenthesis. *p </p>

<p>o0.1; **p 
o0.05; ***p </p>

<p>o0.01 </p>

<p>Table II. 
Estimation of the 
effect of trade policy 
on the "structural 
economic 
vulnerability" in 
developing countries 
within regressions 
with correction of 
heteroscedasticity, 
autocorrelation, and 
cross-sectional 
dependence </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>and (6)), the null hypothesis of weak instruments is rejected as the Kleibergen-Paap rk 
Wald F-statistic always exceeds the critical value for instrument strength. For LDCs, 
although the Kleibergen-Paap rk Wald F-statistics obtained are lower than the critical 
value of 10 percent maximal IV relative bias provided by Stock and Yogo (2005) (see the 
bottom of columns (4), (5), and (6)), they remain higher than the Staiger and Stock (1997)  threshold of ten for strong instruments. We thus confirm the strength of the instruments 
in the estimations of the model (1) specifications for LDCs. In all cases, 
the overidentification test (Hansen's J test) suggests the rejection of the null hypothesis 
that the identifying instruments are endogenous at the 1 percent of statistical significance. 
All in all, these results suggest the statistical validity of our model. 
Turning to the estimates, we note that the coefficients and their statistical 
significance in Table IV are different from those in Table II. More specifically, for the 
full sample (column (1) of Table IV), we find that trade policy liberalization leads to a 
reduction in structural vulnerability in developing countries: an increase in the index of 
trade policy of 1 percent leads to a reduction in developing countries' structural 
vulnerability of 0.077 percent. Surprisingly, we do not observe such a significant effect 
for the sub-samples (LDCs and non-LDCs). However, trade policy liberalization appears 
to reduce countries' exposure to shocks, a result that applies to the entire sample as well 
as to LDCs and non-LDCs. Interestingly, the coefficient obtained for LDCs (0.159) is 
significantly higher than that for non-LDCs (0.0385). Regarding the variable Shock, we 
obtain no significant effect of trade policy, a result that applies to both the entire sample 
and the sub-samples. 
Let us now turn to the control variables. We find for the entire sample that financial 
openness, financial development and human capital accumulation reduce the size of 
both the variables EVI and its components. In the case of non-LDCs, we observe the 
same results except for the variable capturing "financial development," for which the 
size of the shocks affecting these countries and the size of their exposure to shocks do 
not respond to trade policy liberalization. However, financial openness is associated 
with greater structural vulnerability in LDCs, the rise in this vulnerability stemming 
from a rise in shocks, but not from exposure to shocks. Put differently, an increased 
financial openness on the part of LDCs increases the structural vulnerability of these 
countries, and more specifically the shocks affecting these countries, but does not 
increase their exposure to shocks. This may be explained by the lack of a well-
developed financial infrastructure in such countries to help them take advantage of 
their financial openness. Nevertheless, financial development in these countries is 
associated with the diminishing of their structural vulnerability, and this result also 
applies to the Exposure and Shock components of the EVI variable. It is no surprise that 
the accumulation of human capital reduces LDCs' structural vulnerability, notably </p>

<p>Log(TradePolicy) </p>

<p>Log(TradePolicy) t-1 
0.602 (0.0719)*** 
Log(Remitgdp) 
0.0191 (0.00804)** 
Constant 
1.632 (0.281)*** 
Number of countries -observations 
99-1,218 
Within R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.4117 
Notes: Estimator: within regressions with correction of heteroscedasticity, autocorrelation, and cross-
sectional dependence. Robust standard errors are in parenthesis. *p o0.1; **p o0.05; ***p o0.01 </p>

<p>Table III. 
Estimation of the 
effect of Lagged 
Trade Policy and 
Current workers' 
Remittances on the 
Trade Policy in 
developing countries </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Full sample </p>

<p>LDCs </p>

<p>Non-LDCs </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) </p>

<p>Log(Shock) </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) </p>

<p>Log(Shock) </p>

<p>Log(EVI) </p>

<p>Log 
(Exposure) </p>

<p>Log(Shock) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>Log 
(TradePolicy) </p>

<p>−0.0771 </p>

<p>−0.0671 </p>

<p>−0.0803 </p>

<p>0.0511 </p>

<p>−0.159 </p>

<p>0.236 </p>

<p>−0.0190 </p>

<p>−0.0385 </p>

<p>0.0104 </p>

<p>(0.0307)** 
(0.0207)*** (0.0508) </p>

<p>(0.0757) </p>

<p>(0.0449)*** </p>

<p>(0.151) </p>

<p>(0.0203) </p>

<p>(0.0129)*** </p>

<p>(0.0400) </p>

<p>Log(GFI) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.0280 </p>

<p>−0.00937 </p>

<p>−0.0484 </p>

<p>0.0238 </p>

<p>−0.0172 </p>

<p>0.0857 </p>

<p>−0.0241 </p>

<p>−0.0102 </p>

<p>−0.0589 </p>

<p>(0.0112)** </p>

<p>(0.00561)* </p>

<p>(0.0200)** </p>

<p>(0.0134)* </p>

<p>(0.0110) </p>

<p>(0.0149)*** </p>

<p>(0.00783)*** </p>

<p>(0.00498)** </p>

<p>(0.0228)*** </p>

<p>Log(FD) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.0453 </p>

<p>−0.0190 </p>

<p>−0.0864 </p>

<p>−0.108 </p>

<p>−0.0364 </p>

<p>−0.191 </p>

<p>−0.0130 </p>

<p>−0.00240 </p>

<p>−0.0185 </p>

<p>(0.0141)*** (0.00709)*** (0.0247)*** </p>

<p>(0.0285)*** </p>

<p>(0.0154)** </p>

<p>(0.0516)*** </p>

<p>(0.00650)** </p>

<p>(0.00786) </p>

<p>(0.0171) </p>

<p>Log(HAI) </p>

<p>t-1 </p>

<p>−0.292 </p>

<p>−0.136 </p>

<p>−0.406 </p>

<p>−0.142 </p>

<p>−0.0737 </p>

<p>−0.141 </p>

<p>−0.758 </p>

<p>−0.292 </p>

<p>−1.306 </p>

<p>(0.0378)*** (0.0135)*** (0.0823)*** </p>

<p>(0.0552)** </p>

<p>(0.0227)*** </p>

<p>(0.123) </p>

<p>(0.0434)*** </p>

<p>(0.0625)*** </p>

<p>(0.113)*** </p>

<p>Number of 
countries </p>

<p>-
observations </p>

<p>96-1,168 </p>

<p>96-1,179 </p>

<p>96-1,168 </p>

<p>35-336 </p>

<p>35-347 </p>

<p>35-336 </p>

<p>61-832 </p>

<p>61-832 </p>

<p>61-832 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(centered) </p>

<p>0.217 </p>

<p>0.165 </p>

<p>0.113 </p>

<p>0.309 </p>

<p>0.181 </p>

<p>0.185 </p>

<p>0.294 </p>

<p>0.144 </p>

<p>0.203 </p>

<p>Weak 
identification </p>

<p>test (Kleibergen-
Paap rk Wald 
F-statistic) </p>

<p>36.354 </p>

<p>36.646 </p>

<p>36.354 </p>

<p>11.143 </p>

<p>11.011 </p>

<p>11.143 </p>

<p>80.020 </p>

<p>80.020 </p>

<p>80.020 </p>

<p>Stock-Yogo </p>

<p>weak 
identification </p>

<p>test </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>critical </p>

<p>values (10%) </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>19.93 </p>

<p>Hansen's J ( </p>

<p>χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>p-value) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.9721) </p>

<p>1.114 
(0.2911) </p>

<p>0.313 
(0.5760) </p>

<p>1.733 
(0.1880) </p>

<p>2.688 
(0.1011) </p>

<p>2.496 
(0.1141) </p>

<p>1.023 
(0.3118) </p>

<p>1.339 
(0.2473) </p>

<p>1.611 
(0.2044) </p>

<p>Notes: Estimator: within regressions 
-instrumental variable/2SLS based on the two-step GMM technique and correction of cross-sectional dependence. Robust </p>

<p>standard errors are in parenthesis; The two-step GMM estimations take account of the presence of heteroscedasticity, autocorrelation and cross-sectional 
dependence in the residuals. We use the Driscoll-Kraay (1998) technique to correct the standard errors for the possible cross-sectional dependence in the residuals. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>This is the critical value at the level of 10 percent maximal IV relative bias, suggested by Stock and Yogo (2005). *po0.1; **po0.05; ***po0.01 </p>

<p>Table IV. 
Estimation of the 
effect of trade policy 
on the "structural 
economic 
vulnerability" in 
developing countries </p>

<p>83 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>their exposure to shocks. However, the negative effect obtained for the Human capital 
variable on the Shock variable is not statistically significant. 
Table V provides descriptive statistics for the variables used in the study. </p>

<p>7. Conclusion 
In this paper, we investigate the effects of trade openness on the structural economic 
vulnerability of a set of 105 developing countries, of which 41 are LDCs and 64 are non-
LDCs, over the period 1995-2011. To perform our analysis, we use the indicator of trade 
policy liberalization (namely, freedom to trade internationally) proposed by the Heritage 
Foundation, together with the EVI developed by the United Nations for the inclusion and 
ranking of a country in the LDC category. We observe empirical evidence that trade 
policy liberalization reduces (on average) countries' exposure to shocks, with this result 
applying not only to the entire sample, but also to LDCs and non-LDCs. However, trade 
openness does not appear to increase the shocks faced by these countries. 
Overall, this study shows that several structural policies (trade policy liberalization, 
financial openness, domestic financial development, and human capital accumulation) 
could contribute to a significant reduction in structural vulnerability, and notably 
exposure to shocks in developing countries in general and LDCs in particular, thereby 
dampening the fears of the governments of many of these countries with regard to 
opening up their economies, notably to international trade. 
As far as trade policy in developing countries is concerned, developing countries -in 
particular LDCs -have at their disposal several flexibility measures (beyond 
tariff-related measures) in the provisions of World Trade Organization's (WTO) 
Agreements that they can harness to address the structural weaknesses that hamper 
their economic development. A survey undertaken by the UNDESA (see Cortez, 2011)  shows that many LDCs do not make full use of the flexibility measures afforded in the 
WTO's Agreements, including the support available to them. The reason for this is 
the low awareness of existing measures among LDCs, which reflects a lack of full 
understanding of the agreements and their provisions, as well as the lack of availability 
of qualified human resources to follow up on complex World Trade Organization legal 
matters. In this respect, although the responsibility for making use of these measures lies 
primarily with the governments of LDCs, the international community, notably donors 
in the developed world, have a key role to play in supporting LDCs, enabling them to 
seize the opportunities offered by the global trading system to address their structural 
weaknesses (including reducing their exposure to shocks). </p>

<p>Variable 
Observations 
Mean 
SD 
Minimum 
Maximum </p>

<p>EVI 
1,088 
34.70847 
11.99712 
12.41827 
71.18571 
Exposure 
1,088 
41.09971 
18.3266 
5.84993 
81.36403 
Shock 
1,088 
28.0314 
12.47137 
2.725405 
73.8308 
TradePolicy 
982 
61.11039 
15.7146 
0 
90 
GFI 
1,081 
175.6993 
467.1887 
17.03549 
7550.584 
FD 
1,079 
38.26323 
29.4805 
2.036451 
165.8018 
HAI 
1,054 
77.82742 
15.02619 
35.52649 
98.70177 
REMIT 
1,004 
4.235792 
5.50489 
0.0026706 
36.49304 
Note: "Remit" denotes the variable "workers' remittances, expressed as a percentage of GDP" </p>

<p>Table V. 
Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>84 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p><rs type="software">stata</rs></p>



<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>



<p>Appendix 1. Description of the structure of the "structural vulnerability index" 
The structural vulnerability index is a composite index of "shocks" and "exposure to shocks"; 
both indicators are equally weighted (see, e.g. Guillaumont and Cariolle (2011) for a discussion on 
the weight of indicators). We display below the structure of the (retrospective) EVI where the 
weights of indices are in brackets. </p>

<p>Source: Guillaumont (2011) </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>JES 
43,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Appendix 2 </p>

<p>About the author 
Sena Kimm Gnangnon is currently acting as an Economist, in the Development Division of the 
Secretariat of World Trade Organization (WTO). He is currently working in the World Trade 
Organization (WTO) -Switzerland. His primary field of interest is macroeconomics development, 
including macroeconomic aspects of international trade. After his Bachelor Degree in Statistics and 
his Master Degrees in respectively "Research in Development Economics" and "Economic Analysis 
and Development Project Management", he has acquired his experiences mainly in the field of 
macroeconomic applied to development issues, notably international economics. More specifically, he 
has worked in the French Agency of Development at Paris as a Consultant (for a short period), in the 
World Trade Organization (in Geneva), in CEMAGREF (for a short period) at Clermont-Ferrand as 
well as a Teaching Assistant and a Researcher in CERDI. He has also worked in the "Organisation 
Internationale de la Francophonie" (in Paris) as an "Economist". He is a holder of a PhD in 
Development Macroeconomics. Sena Kimm Gnangnon can be contacted at: kgnangnon@yahoo.fr </p>

<p>Algeria 
Congo 
India 
Mozambique 
South Africa 
Angola 
Costa Rica 
Indonesia 
Namibia 
Sri Lanka 
Argentina 
Côte d'Ivoire 
Iran (Islamic 
Republic of) </p>

<p>Nepal 
Sudan </p>

<p>Bahrain 
Democratic Republic 
of the Congo </p>

<p>Jamaica 
Nicaragua 
Suriname </p>

<p>Bangladesh 
Djibouti 
Jordan 
Niger 
Swaziland 
Belize 
Dominica 
Kenya 
Nigeria 
Syrian Arab 
Republic 
Benin 
Dominican Republic Lao People's 
Democratic Republic </p>

<p>Pakistan 
Thailand </p>

<p>Bhutan 
Ecuador 
Lebanon 
Panama 
Timor-Leste 
Bolivia 
Egypt 
Lesotho 
Papua New Guinea Togo 
Botswana 
El Salvador 
Liberia 
Paraguay 
Tonga 
Brazil 
Eritrea 
Libyan Arab 
Jamahiriya </p>

<p>Peru 
Trinidad and 
Tobago 
Burkina Faso Ethiopia 
Madagascar 
Philippines 
Tunisia 
Burundi 
Fiji 
Malawi 
Rwanda 
Turkey 
Cambodia 
Gabon 
Malaysia 
Saint Lucia 
Uganda 
Cameroon 
Gambia 
Maldives 
Saint Vincent and 
the Grenadines </p>

<p>United Republic 
of Tanzania 
Cape Verde 
Ghana 
Mali 
Samoa 
Vanuatu 
Central 
African 
Republic </p>

<p>Guatemala 
Mauritania 
Sao Tome and 
Principe </p>

<p>Venezuela </p>

<p>Chad 
Guinea 
Mauritius 
Senegal 
Vietnam 
China 
Guinea-Bissau 
Mexico 
Seychelles 
Yemen 
Colombia 
Guyana 
Mongolia 
Sierra Leone 
Zambia 
Comoros 
Honduras 
Morocco 
Solomon Islands 
Zimbabwe 
Note: NB: the list of least developed countries (LDCs) could be obtained online on: www.un.org/en/ 
development/desa/policy/cdp/ldc/ldc_list.pdf </p>

<p>Table AI. 
Full sample 
considered in 
the data set </p>

<p>For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: 
www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm 
Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>Trade 
openness and 
structural 
vulnerability </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:05 29 March 2018 (PT) </p>

</text></tei>