<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fjems.12172" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A monopolist bookmaker may set betting odds on a fairly even contest to induce match-fixing 
by an influential corrupt punter. His loss to the corrupt punter is more than made up for by 
enticing enough ordinary punters to bet on the losing team. This result is in sharp contrast 
to competitive bookmaking, where even contests have been shown to be immune to fixing. The 
analysis also reveals a surprising result that the incidence of match-fixing can dramatically fall 
when match-fixing opportunities rise. This is shown by comparing two scenarios-when only 
one team is corruptible and when both are corruptible. For both teams corruptible, the bookmaker 
is uncertain about to which team the influential punter will have access, so carefully maneuvering 
the odds to induce match-fixing is too costly. </p>

<p>Match-fixing and betting-related corruption seem widespread if one goes by media 
headlines, and legal scholars are beginning to pay attention. 
1 Yet formal research on 
this issue is relatively lacking. 
2 If a small group of bettors with financial muscles, to 
be referred as the influential punter (in short, IP or fixer), can access player(s) who, by </p>

<p>We especially thank an anonymous reviewer and an associate editor for detailed comments and suggestions 
on earlier drafts. We also thank Murali Agastya, Aditya Goenka, Satoru Takahashi, and participants at the 
2011 (XXIst) Annual Conference on Contemporary Issues in Development Economics at Jadavpur University, 
2012 SAET Conference in Queensland, 2013 AEI-Four Economic Theory Workshop hosted by Seoul National 
University, 2014 APET Conference in Seattle, and seminars at the Indian Institute of Management (Kolkata), 
and Indira Gandhi Institute of Development Research, for various feedbacks. The project was partly funded 
by a Singapore MOE AcRF Tier 1 grant (grant no. R-122-000-151-112). For any shortcomings, we remain 
responsible. 
1. See an edited volume (Haberfeld and Sheehan, 2013) titled, Match-Fixing in International Sports: 
Existing Processes, Law Enforcement, and Prevention Strategies. Betting-related match-fixing makes frequent 
headlines. Latest is the allegation of an entire soccer league being fixed in Canada ("Revealed: Entire 
'rogue league corrupted by match-fixing'"-October 14, 2015 news at The Telegraph, http://www.telegraph. 
co.uk/sport/football/11932437/Revealed-Entire-rogue-league-corrupted-by-match-fixing.html). The high 
profile Indian Premier League (or IPL) in which many top international cricketers participate was rocked 
by betting and fixing allegations in the recent past-see the report "Fixing? It's people like us doing it" on 
May 22, 2013 at http://www.espncricinfo.com/magazine/content/story/637034.html. For fixing allegations 
in other sports including soccer in Europe, ATP tennis tournaments, basketball, horse races, etc., see links to 
various news reports in Bag and Saha (2011). 
2. There are some empirical papers on sports corruption. Duggan and Levitt (2002) study corruption in 
Sumo wrestling but not betting. Strumpf (2003), Wolfers (2006), Winter and Kukuk (2008), etc. study betting-
related corruption in sports. See also two very recent contributions on detecting match-fixing-De Muinck 
and Quatacker (2013) for soccer, and Rodenberg and Feustel (2014) for tennis. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. 
Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy, Volume 26, Number 1, Spring 2017, 257-289 </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>underperforming, can tilt the outcome of a sports contest that has high visibility and on 
which many people bet, the competitive show is hit at its foundation. 
In an earlier work (Bag and Saha, 2011), we presented a formal model of match-
fixing in the context of a (Bertrand) competitive fixed odds betting market. There the 
bookmakers' desire to steal business by undercutting rivals' odds exposes the contest 
to fixing, whereby a favorite deliberately underperforms. Such destructive effects of 
competition are felt mostly in uneven contests; even contests are generally safe. One 
question then is what happens if a bookmaker has market power. Will he try to protect 
the market and his profit from the corrupt punter? Or, will he abuse his power to steer 
the market in the direction of odds rigging? We address this question here, by restricting 
our attention mainly to even or near-even contests. 
In our model a monopolist bookmaker posts betting odds, or equivalently sets the 
"prices" of bets, for a contest between two teams to attract bets from a mass of ordinary 
bettors. An anonymous influential punter may be able to bribe some members of one of 
the teams to underperform, and then place a large sum of bets on the other team. Such 
possibilities as well as the ordinary bettors' response are factored in by the bookie, at 
the time of posting the odds. 
Bettors' responses (including IP's) depend on their position in the information 
hierarchy. We assume that the ordinary bettors have exogenous and heterogenous beliefs 
and are unaware of the risk of match-fixing. So they respond to market prices naively. 
The bookie and the IP, on the other hand, have superior information; they both know 
the teams' true win probabilities. Further, the IP can rise to the top of the information 
hierarchy, if he can fix the match. 
Aware of the fact that IP will never have less information than him, the bookie 
cannot expect to make profit from the IP. But he needs to be mindful of how IP's 
incentives will be affected by the prices he will set. If the prices are so high that IP's 
betting becomes unprofitable despite match-fixing, the integrity of the contest will be 
protected, but only after sacrificing a sizeable chunk of the ordinary bettors' market. On 
the other hand, if the prices are set appropriately low, IP can find match-fixing profitable; 
if he gets to bribe one team, his return from the bet on the other team will be large enough 
to cover the cost of bribery. In this case, the bookie faces a clear loss to IP, but the loss may 
be partially (if not fully) offset by attracting a significant number of ordinary bettors. 
So his profits from these two alternative price regimes can go either way. Since which 
price regime is his own choice, the question is whether he would go for the first regime, 
which we call bribe prevention or the second regime, which we call bribe inducement. 
In contests where teams are (near) evenly matched, which regime would he choose? 
When only one team is corruptible, we find that he would choose bribe inducement 
for any positive chance of secret liaison with the corruptible team (given some standard 
assumptions). 
3 This is because bribe prevention is too costly; it requires giving up too 
much on the ordinary punters' betting. In some extreme instances, when the probability 
of accessing the corrupt team is very high, the bookie actually welcomes the fixing role 
of the IP. With his tacit help he can drastically increase the losing chance of the corrupt 
team and steer most of the ordinary bettors to bet on it. Here, the loss to the IP is much 
smaller than the substantial gain of capturing (nearly) the whole of the unsuspecting 
bettors' market. </p>

<p>3. We assume that the corruptible team's identity is known. Teams with good reputation or regimentation 
and discipline are likely to be immune to outside influence. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>Surprisingly though, this perverse incentive loses its force when both teams are 
corruptible. In that case, though match-fixing opportunities are greater, the bookie is 
unsure of which team the IP will be able to bribe, and therefore, he needs to make 
concession on the bet prices of both teams, which means yielding a much greater loss to 
not only IP but also a section of ordinary bettors; lowering both prices does not help to 
tilt the market in one way or other. Therefore, bribe inducement will be preferred less 
frequently. 
The finding of the monopoly setup is in sharp contrast to the competitive case 
analyzed in Bag and Saha (2011), where even contests are generally immune. Either 
the competitive prices are above the bribery threshold level, or the bookmakers (non-
cooperatively) coordinate on the threshold prices for fear of letting the IP in. Under 
monopoly, despite his full market power, the bookie may not try to protect the market. 
The underlying market microstructure of our model assumes that the median bettor 
always believes the contest to be dead even. So when the contest is truly an even (or a 
near even) contest, the bookie's informational superiority disappears, and his expected 
profit will be minimum. In such cases, an anonymous fixer can come handy to make the 
contest lop-sided and in anticipation of that the bookie can induce the ordinary bettors 
en masse to back the losing team. But whether this will be optimal depends on how 
large is the expected cost of fixing, which can significantly vary depending on whether 
one team or both teams are corruptible. 
Though our main analysis is presented assuming "uniform" distribution of the 
ordinary bettors' beliefs, we show that our key insight that the bookie will be most 
keen to orchestrate match-fixing in even or near even contests will hold under general 
(but symmetric) belief distributions. However, the other assumptions regarding the 
bettors, such as their exogenous beliefs and their naivety of not suspecting foul play, 
are important. That bettors have diverse beliefs and less precise information than the 
bookie are somewhat essential to organize betting. 
4 There is also considerable evidence 
on leisure betting, which is most likely to be based on naive beliefs (Saunders and Turner, 
1987; Bruce and Johnson, 1992; Winter and Kukuk, 2008). But if we allow the bettors to 
be suspicious of match-fixing, when they see the posted odds that are too good to be 
true (based on their initial beliefs), market manipulation will backfire; the bookie will 
be better off by driving the fixer out of the market. We accommodate this argument, 
albeit less formally; but the message is clear: the more unsuspecting the bettors are, the 
stronger the incentives to induce match-fixing. 
At a theoretical level, our exercise is also useful for extending the literature from 
insider betting to fixing and betting. The insider betting model of Shin (1991), from which 
we adapt the basic setup, is similar to insider trading (Glosten and Milgrom, 1985; Kyle, 
1985; Seyhun, 1992), where some agents use privileged information which might have 
been randomly or costlessly acquired. Match-fixing on the other hand is about generating 
privileged information at a positive cost and then using it. 
5 This is also related to the 
idea of market manipulation in finance where even an uninformed trader may buy a 
stock to bid up its price with the intent of selling the stock at a later date and profit 
from it (e.g., Allen and Gorton, 1992; Chakraborty and Yilmaz, 2004). Further, our study 
provides insights into the extent by which sabotages can be controlled through market 
prices-a relatively neglected issue so far in the industrial organization research. </p>

<p>4. Diversity of beliefs naturally follow from our assumption of exogenous beliefs; allowing correlated 
beliefs will largely eliminate demand for bets. 
5. A similar theme, namely sabotage, has been studied in contest models with completely different con-
cerns than ours. There the focus is on the saboteur's incentives; see, for instance, Konrad (2000), Chen (2003). </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>From an empirical point of view, we question a common perception of the book-
makers as victims of match-fixing. 
6 We argue that in many plausible scenarios they may 
indirectly benefit from match-fixing. Should the authority go after only the fixer, or the 
bookmaker as well? When the bookmaker is merely trying to avoid losses he cannot be 
blamed; but when he profits from fixing, he should be held culpable. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>We acknowledge that the insights from our model should not be directly applied to 
parimutuel betting markets. Such markets are differently organized and the bookmaker's 
role is different with very little power in setting market odds, as analyzed in a number 
of works by Ottaviani and Sorensen (2005, 2008, 2009, 2010). Fixed odds are practised 
by bookmakers in the UK and Europe, e.g., ChoiceOdds, Ladbrokes, Paddy Power, and 
William Hill. 
The paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we present the model and an 
analysis of betting and bribery decisions. Sections 3 and 4 contain the main results, with 
some related examples and simulations appearing in Section 5. Sections 6 and 7 extend 
the earlier analysis to more general environments, followed by conclusions in Section 8. 
The formal proofs appear in the Appendix. </p>

<p>2. The Model </p>

<p>The setup is similar to that of Bag and Saha (2011), which in turn draws upon Shin (1991). 
A monopolist bookmaker, the bookie, sets the odds on each of two teams winning a sports 
match (i.e., sets the prices of two tickets); the match being drawn is not a possibility. 
Ticket i with price π i yields a dollar if team i wins and yields nothing if team i loses. 
There are a continuum of naive punters, parameterized by individual and exogenous 
belief, the probability q , that team 1 will win; q is distributed "uniformly" over (0, 1). 
The assumption of uniform distribution is justified on the ground of the bettors 
having well spread-out beliefs. However, later with a general distribution function of 
beliefs we show that our key results are likely to hold, if the distribution is continuous 
and symmetric with mean 1/2. 
Bettors' beliefs are not only exogenous and unrelated to the nature's draw of a 
team's win probability, but also naive in the sense that bettors are unaware of the risk 
of match-fixing. Later we relax the naivety assumption and show how the results might 
change if the bettors are "rational." 
In the absence of any external influence, the probability that team i will win is 
0 &lt; p i &lt; 1. External influence is exerted through bribery of a (few) corruptible (members 
of a) team to underperform. If team i is bribed, its probability of winning is secretly 
lowered from p i to λ i p i (0 ≤ λ i &lt; 1). We assume λ i to be exogenous. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6. In the famous 2007 tennis episode involving Davydenko and Vassallo Arguello, the Internet bet-
ting company, Betfair, voided all its bets following suspicious betting patterns-the market odds as re-
flected in bets drifted significantly against 4 th seeded Davydenko while ahead in the match. In its 
December 2011 review the UK gambling commission requires licensed sports bet operators to provide 
the relevant sports-governing body with information that they suspect may lead the gambling commis-
sion to consider making an order to void a bet. See Section 15.1 of the Gambling Commission doc-
ument available at http://www.gamblingcommission.gov.uk/PDF/LCCP%20consolidated%20version%20-
%20December%202011.pdf. 
7. See "Football match-fixing: How betting odds gives the game away" at http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/ 
world-europe-11789671. 
8. The team may have honest players who cannot be bribed, and therefore, λ i = 0 is not appropriate in a 
team game. One can make λ i sensitive to bribe at the cost of some complexity. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>We assume the bookmaker to be honest. There is an anonymous influential punter, 
IP, who may bribe a team and bet against it. He can access team i with probability 0 ≤ 
μ i ≤ 1. Note that the probabilistic access makes the prospect of match-fixing uncertain, 
even when λ i = 0. 
The bookie, IP, and the team players-all initially observe the draw p 1 . The law 
enforcement authority investigates the losing team i with an exogenous probability 
0 &lt; α i &lt; 1. 
9 On conviction, the corrupt players are fined f in total and the match-fixer f I . 
The distribution of the ordinary bettors' wealth is "uniform" over [0, 1], with 1 
dollar each and a collective wealth of y dollars. The wealth of IP is z = 1 − y dollars. All 
agents are risk-neutral. </p>

<p>2.1. Betting and Bribe-Taking </p>

<p>ORDINARY BETTORS' BETTING DECISION. The ordinary bettors adopt the following 
betting rule: Bet on team 1 if and only if </p>

<p>q 
π 1 </p>

<p>≥ max{ </p>

<p>1−q 
π 2 </p>

<p>, 1}; bet on team 2 if and only if </p>

<p>1−q 
π 2 </p>

<p>≥ max{ </p>

<p>q 
π 1 </p>

<p>, 1}. </p>

<p>PLAYER INCENTIVES FOR BRIBE-TAKING AND SABOTAGE. Suppose a corrupt player 
(or a group of corrupt players) of team i is contacted by IP with probability μ i and a deal 
is struck, by which the corrupt player is promised a bribe b i to underperform. The bribe 
will be paid only if the team loses. In the event team i wins, regardless of the player's 
underperformance the bribe money is not paid; the corrupt player in that case collects 
only the team reward w. 
Given any belief p i and α i , a bribe deal involving b i is accepted and honored by 
the corrupt player, if the expected payoff from underperformance is at least as great as 
the expected payoff from honest performance. That is to say, the deal is struck </p>

<p>if and only if 
λ i p i w + (1 − λ i p i )(b i − α i f) ≥ p i w + (1 − p i )(b i − α i f) (1) </p>

<p>that is, if and only if 
b i ≥ w + α i f. </p>

<p>The inequality (1) makes underperformance incentive compatible and the agree-
ment self-enforcing. 
10 The minimum bribe required to entice underperformance is 
b i = w + α i f. We assume that IP holds all the bargaining power so that b i = b i . 
We should emphasize that if the players of two teams had different beliefs regarding 
the teams' chances (different from p 1 ), inequality (1) could be easily replicated for those 
beliefs, because (1) corresponds to the players' beliefs, and the lower bound on b i is 
not sensitive to any belief. Therefore, divergence in players' beliefs from each other's 
and/or from true p 1 does not alter the analysis. If b i were set in excess of b i , say via 
Nash bargaining of the surplus, then IP's belief (i.e., p 1 ) would be relevant, but not the 
players' beliefs. </p>

<p>2.2. Bribery Game </p>

<p>There are two key players, the bookmaker and IP, in the bribery game. </p>

<p>STAGE 1. Nature draws p 1 and reveals it to the bookie, IP and the players; the or-
dinary punters draw their respective private signals q . The bookmaker sets </p>

<p>9. It does not employ sophisticated game-theoretic inferences about match-fixing by observing π i or p i . 
10. The IP will honor his promise with the bribe, as is commonly assumed in corruption models. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>the prices (π 1 , π 2 ) for the tickets on respective teams' win, where 0 ≤ π 1 , 
π 2 ≤ 1. 
STAGE 2. IP secretly finds out if he could access team 1 or team 2 or neither, 
11 and 
decides, on gaining access, whether to bribe the team to influence the contest 
outcome. 
STAGE 3. All punters including IP place bets according to their "eventual" beliefs. The 
match is played out according to the teams' winning probabilities ( p 1 , 1 − p 1 ) 
or (λ 1 p 1 , 1 − λ 1 p 1 ) (when team 1 is bribed), or (1 − λ 2 p 2 , λ 2 p 2 ) (when team 2 
is bribed) and the match takes place. 
STAGE 4. Finally, the enforcement authority follows its investigation policy, α i . On suc-
cessful investigation, fines are imposed on the corrupt player(s) and IP. || </p>

<p>2.3. Influential Punter's Betting and Bribery Incentives </p>

<p>Before we analyze IP's incentives, it should be obvious that IP will hold either superior 
or same information as the bookie. The bookie can thus never make positive expected 
profit from IP. In particular, when IP has superior information (on the fixing) the bookie's 
expected profit from IP will be negative. 
This is a consequence of our assumption that IP has precise knowledge of p i 
(just like the bookie). Admittedly, this is a somewhat strong assumption, but it helps 
to underscore his role as a fixer. We make the bookie's choice difficult by introducing 
a certain cost through this assumption. One can allow greater realism by making IP's 
information set coarse, which we do not study here. 
Now, consider IP's incentives. Having learnt p i and observed π i (i = 1, 2), when 
p i ≤ π i for all i = 1, 2, the influential punter can profitably bet only if he succeeds in 
bribing one of the teams, because otherwise his expected gains from betting is zero. 
Further, to permit bribery of team i and betting on team j, it must be the case that 
1 − λ i p i ≥ π j . That is, the eventual probability of team j winning must not fall below 
π j . Assuming that is the case, his expected profit from bribing team i is calculated as 
E 
I (b i ) = (1 − λ i p i ) </p>

<p>z 
π j </p>

<p>− b i − α i f I − z. Substituting b = w + α i f, </p>

<p>E 
I (b i ) = (1 − λ i p i )z 
1 
π j 
− i − z = (1 − λ i p i )z 
1 
π j 
− 
1 
φ i 
, </p>

<p>where i = 
w + α i (f + f I ) 
z 
, 
and 
φ i = 
1 − λ i p i 
1 + (1 − λ i p i ) i 
. </p>

<p>Clearly, for E 
I to be positive π j must be smaller than φ i . By corollary then IP is 
prevented from bribing team i if π j &gt; φ i . In the event of π j = ϕ i , we make a tie-breaking 
rule to ensure that the bookie's optimal bribery program always has a solution. </p>

<p>Assumption 1 (Tie-breaking rule): If "bribing and betting" and "betting without bribing" 
yield zero expected profit, then IP will choose an option (including "not betting at all") in 
accordance with the bookie's preference. </p>

<p>11. The timing of IP's access to teams (after or before the odds are posted) is immaterial. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>Given Assumption 1 , if the bookie wishes to induce match-fixing of team i, he needs 
to set π j subject to the following constraint (along with setting π i ≥ p i for both teams): </p>

<p>π j ≤ 
1 − λ i p i 
1 + (1 − λ i p i ) i 
≡ φ i . 
( 2 ) </p>

<p>What will be the IP's incentives, if p i &gt; π i were set instead? In this instance, IP 
can make positive gains from "honest" betting, and therefore there is an opportunity 
cost to fixing. φ i will no longer be the threshold price for π j . In Bag and Saha (2011) 
we have characterized these cases exhaustively. In this paper we restrict our attention 
only to the case where p i ≤ π i for both teams. Setting both π 1 and π 2 below p 1 and 
p 2 , respectively, would imply money pump scenario. We impose the following (no) 
Dutch-book restriction to rule it out: </p>

<p>Assumption 2: The bookie must always choose prices 0 ≤ π 1 , π 2 ≤ 1 such that π 1 + π 2 ≥ 1. </p>

<p>3. Prevent, Tolerate, or Encourage Match-Fixing? </p>

<p>Our main interest is to see whether the bookie would choose not to prevent match-fixing, 
and if so in which type of contests that is most likely to happen. To develop an early 
insight we first consider the benchmark case of "honest" betting where match-fixing is 
not possible by assumption. </p>

<p>3.1. No IP Scenario </p>

<p>Suppose there is no IP so that the teams' winning probabilities are maintained at ( p 1 , p 2 ). 
Given Assumption 2, bettors with beliefs q ∈ [0, 1 − π 2 ] will buy ticket 2 and q ∈ [π 1 , 1] 
will buy ticket 1; punters with q in(1 − π 2 , π 1 ) will buy neither. Thus the bookie's objec-
tive is: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>π 1 ,π 2 </p>

<p>E = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>π 1 </p>

<p>y 1 − 
p 1 
π 1 
dq </p>

<p>ticket 1 profit </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>1−π 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>y 1 − 
p 2 
π 2 
dq </p>

<p>ticket 2 profit </p>

<p>= y 3 − π 1 − π 2 − 
p 1 
π 1 
− 
p 2 
π 2 
. 
( 3 ) </p>

<p>The solution to this problem is π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 = 
√ p 1 and π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 = 
√ p 2 , resulting in expected </p>

<p>profit: </p>

<p>E 0 = y 3 − 2 
√ p 1 − 2 1 − p 1 . 
( 4 ) </p>

<p>Figure 1 depicts the profit curve, perfectly symmetric and U-shaped. The bookie 
makes the most when the contest is highly uneven. By setting the price of the weak 
team's ticket very low, he induces most naive punters to bet on it and earns nearly y. On 
the other hand, at the perfectly even contest his profit is the lowest. Here, those bettors 
who believe that the contest is even or nearly even abstain from betting. 
It is around the even contest the bookie would wish that p 1 were different from 1/2, 
say for example 1/8. Then the bookie's expected profit would rise from 0.17y to 0.42y. 
Indeed, the same gains in profit would be achieved, if the bookie could engage the IP 
for a fixed fee (not more than 0.25y) to bribe team 1 with probability 4/5 and reduce p 1 </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>[3 − 2 2]y </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>1/2 </p>

<p>EΠ 0 </p>

<p>1/8 
p 1 </p>

<p>0.42y </p>

<p>0.17y </p>

<p>√ </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. EXPECTED PROFIT WHEN THERE IS NO IP </p>

<p>from 1/2 to 1/32. The ex ante probability of team 1 winning would then be exactly 1/8. 
Of course, when the bookie has no link with IP, the only way he can engage the IP is 
by inducing him through market prices, which clearly will have to be distorted from 
what is shown in Figure 1. Nevertheless, the intuition is that the monopolist's incentive 
to manipulate the market is the strongest around the even contest. 
This observation is, of course, made on the basis of the uniform distribution of 
bettors' (naive) beliefs with mean 1/2. That being the case, the intuition is likely to be 
more general. We show later on with a general distribution function that as long as it is 
symmetric with mean 1/2, even contests are likely to be rife for fixing. However, if the 
mean belief diverges from 1/2, the minimum profit point will also diverge from 1/2, but 
probably not stray too far from 1/2. For the uniform distribution, the minimum profit 
point will be between the mean belief and 1/2. We show this in Section 6. The main point 
is that the minimum profit point will be fairly close to the dead even contest, and hence 
the bookie's incentive to induce fixing will also be stronger here. </p>

<p>3.2. Bribe Prevention Program </p>

<p>We now return to our game , and first analyze the bookie's bribe prevention strategy. 
Formally, the bookie solves the following bribe-prevention program: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>π 1 ,π 2 </p>

<p>E B P = y 3 − π 1 − π 2 − 
p 1 
π 1 
− 
p 2 
π 2 
, </p>

<p>subject to: π 1 + π 2 ≥ 1, 
π 1 ≥ max{ p 1 , φ 2 }, and π 2 ≥ max{ p 2 , φ 1 }. </p>

<p>Lemma 1(Optimal bribe prevention prices): If IP can potentially bribe team j to bet on 
team i, bribe prevention price of ticket i at any given p i , is π </p>

<p>B P 
i </p>

<p>= max{ 
√ p i , φ j }, i, j = 1, 2 </p>

<p>and i = j. </p>

<p>It is easy to verify that φ 2 is an increasing function of p 1 and it intersects the curve 
√ p 1 from above at a unique point. Let p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 be this point of intersection. Clearly, at all 
p 1 &lt; p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>i the bribe prevention constraint binds on π 1 , implying that profit on ticket 1 will 
have to be sacrificed if bribery of team 2 is to be prevented. Likewise, φ 1 is downward 
sloping in p 1 like 
√ p 2 and φ 1 intersects 
√ p 2 from below. Let this intersection point be </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 . That means, at all p 1 &gt; p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 the bribe prevention constraint binds on π 2 implying loss </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>of profit from ticket 2, if bribery of team 1 is to be prevented. Combining these two 
observations the following can be stated. </p>

<p>Lemma 2 (Costless or costly prevention of match-fixing): If p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 &lt; p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 then at all p 1 ∈ 
[ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 , p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ] bribe prevention is costless (on either tickets), relative to the "no IP" case. Alternatively, 
if p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 then at all p 1 ∈ [ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 , p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ] bribe prevention is costly. 
These two regimes have different implications for the bookie. When trying to 
prevent fixing is costly, he has a hard choice to make. If he chooses "not to prevent," it 
should be seen as a "loss minimizing" strategy in a corrupted environment over which 
he has no control. But when prevention of fixing is costless, he is certainly on a safer 
ground. But if he still chooses not to prevent fixing, it must be due to his intention to profit 
from the evil influence of the fixer. Though both decisions favor bribe inducement, and 
are based on similar profit comparisons, they are qualitatively different. To underscore 
their difference we will call the decision to induce bribery in the first scenario bribe 
tolerance and in the second scenario bribe encouragement. In the first case, there is very 
little sense to go after the bookie, whereas in the second case he can be held guilty of 
wrongdoing. </p>

<p>3.3. Bribe Inducement: Only One Team Corruptible </p>

<p>We will first analyze the case where only one team, namely team 1, is corruptible. That 
means, to induce bribery the bookie needs to set π 2 below the threshold level φ 1 as 
given by (2). No such constraint will apply to the price of ticket 1, because team 2 is not 
corruptible. The formal statement of the bribe inducement (B I ) program is as follows: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>π 1 ,π 2 </p>

<p>E B I = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>π 1 </p>

<p>y(1 − 
p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>π 1 
) dq </p>

<p>ticket 1 profit </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>1−π 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>y(1 − 
1 − p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>π 2 
) dq + μ 1 z(1 − 
1 − λ 1 p 1 
π 2 
) </p>

<p>ticket 2 profit </p>

<p>= y 3 − π 1 − π 2 − 
p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>π 1 
− 
1 − p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>π 2 
− μ 1 z 
1 − λ 1 p 1 
π 2 
− 1 
(5) </p>

<p>subject to 
p 2 ≤ π 2 ≤ φ 1 (&lt; 1 − λ 1 p 1 ), 
π 1 ≥ p 1 , 
π 1 + π 2 ≥ 1, </p>

<p>where λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = μ 1 λ 1 + (1 − μ 1 ) is the dampening impact of bribery on team 1's winning 
chances. 
Let us note that the solution to the BI problem is </p>

<p>π 1 = 
p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 , ∀μ 1 ∈ (0, </p>

<p>p 2 
1−λ 1 </p>

<p>] 
p 1 , 
∀μ 1 ∈ ( </p>

<p>p 2 
1−λ 1 </p>

<p>, 1), 
π 2 = 
1 − p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 + μ 1 </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>(1 − λ 1 p 1 ), ∀μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ] </p>

<p>φ 1 ( p 1 ), 
∀μ 1 ∈ (μ 1 , 1], 
(6) </p>

<p>where by setting 1 − p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 + μ 1 (z/y)(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) = φ 1 , we obtaiñ </p>

<p>μ 1 = 
y 
1 − λ 1 p 1 − yp 2 
φ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 − p 2 . 
( 7 ) </p>

<p>EVEN CONTESTS. Although the above solution is given for any given p 1 , for the rest of 
this section we will concentrate on a specific value of p 1 , namely 1/2, for our suspicion 
that it is at and around the even contest the bookie's incentive to induce fixing is strongest. 
If we find bribe inducement optimal at p 1 = 1/2, then by continuity at all p 1 close to 1/2 
also bribe inducement will be optimal. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Now we set out to compare the profit from bribe prevention with that from bribe 
inducement at p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. Given that only team 1 can be bribed, if 1/2 &lt; p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 then at p 1 = 1/2 
bribe prevention is costless (relative to the benchmark case), and the bookie's profit 
will be E B P = y[3 − 2 
√ 
2] ≡ E 0 . Alternatively, if p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; 1/2, then his bribe prevention 
profit will be lower: </p>

<p>E B P = y[3 − 
√ 
2 − φ 1 − 
1 
2φ 1 
] &lt; E 0 . 
( 8 ) </p>

<p>Turning our attention to bribe inducement profit, we see from equation (6) that at 
any given p 1 , such as 1/2, the expected profit critically depends on the range of μ 1 , that 
is, whether μ 1 falls in between or below/above the two critical values of μ 1 , namelyμ 1 
and </p>

<p>p 2 
1−λ 1 </p>

<p>which is simply </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>at p 1 = 1/2. However, a priori we cannot guarantee if 
μ 1 ( </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>) &gt; or &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>, and of the two cases the first one is less tractable. Hence, we focus 
onμ 1 ( </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>) &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>by assuming the following: </p>

<p>Assumption 3: For any given λ, y and are such thatμ 1 ( </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>) &lt; min 1, </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>If λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, our assumption automatically holds, becauseμ 1 &lt; 1. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>We now write the bookie's profit function for bribe inducement for three ranges of 
μ 1 . 
13 At each range of μ 1 total profit is broken into two terms, showing profit from each 
ticket, as follows: </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I = y 1 − </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ y 
3 
2 
+ μ 1 · 
2 − y(1 + λ 1 ) 
2y 
− 2 1 + μ 1 
2 − λ 1 
y 
− 1 </p>

<p>∀μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ] , (9) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I = y 1 − </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ y 
3 
2 
+ μ 1 · 
2 − y(1 + λ 1 ) 
2y 
− φ 1 − 
1 
φ 1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
+ 
μ 1 
2y 
(2 − y − λ 1 ) </p>

<p>∀μ 1 ∈ μ 1 , 
1 
2(1 − λ 1 ) 
, 
(10) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I = y </p>

<p>μ 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
2 
+ y 
3 
2 
+ μ 1 · 
2 − y(1 + λ 1 ) 
2y 
− φ 1 − 
1 
φ 1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
+ 
μ 1 
2y 
(2 − y − λ 1 ) </p>

<p>∀μ 1 ∈ 
1 
2(1 − λ 1 ) 
, 1 . 
(11) </p>

<p>From the above we can make the following observations. 
At sufficiently small values of μ 1 , bribe inducement profit is arbitrarily close to 
the benchmark (i.e., no IP) profit. As μ 1 → 0, from (9) we see that E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I → E 0 (with 
λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 → 1). Now if p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>(so that E B P &lt; E 0 ), then we can claim that at all sufficiently </p>

<p>12. But if λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , then we need w + α 1 (f + f I ) &gt; max 2(1 − y)[ </p>

<p>y(1−λ 1 ) 
y(1−2λ 1 )+2−λ 1 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 
2−λ 1 </p>

<p>] , 0 . </p>

<p>13. Implicitly, for E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I we are assuming λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , otherwise the interval [ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2(1−λ 1 ) , 1] would be empty. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>μ 1 
μ 1 </p>

<p>1 
2(1-λ 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>BP </p>

<p>BI </p>

<p>μ 1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>EΠ </p>

<p>EΠ 0 </p>

<p>EΠ </p>

<p>EΠ </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. INDUCEMENT OF BRIBERY AT ALL μ 1 ∈ (0, 1] </p>

<p>small values of μ 1 bribe inducement is optimal. This is our first result, and it does not 
depend on any additional assumptions. 
The reason is that for a very small chance of bribery, prices do not need to be 
distorted much from their unconstrained levels in order to induce bribery. But to do the 
contrary, price of ticket 2 has to be discretely raised to φ 1 which forces a significant loss. 
Therefore, tolerating a small chance of match-fixing is preferable. 
At moderate or higher values of μ 1 , the optimality of bribe inducement depends 
on how long E B I continues to be greater than E B P . If E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I , E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I and E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I were 
all declining in μ 1 , then the prediction is straightforward. After a critical value of μ 1 the 
cost of inducing bribery would be far greater than the cost of preventing bribery, and 
hence match-fixing will be prevented. Furthermore, E B I will never exceed E 0 , and 
hence bribe encouragement will never happen. 
But if E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I and E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I are increasing in μ 1 then some interesting possibilities arise. 
In Figure 2, we present this scenario. It is then possible that the whole profit curve E B I 
can be above E B P , which means that at all values of μ 1 bribe inducement is preferred 
(provided E B P &lt; E 0 ). Indeed, sufficient conditions can be specified to ensure this 
possibility. A key requirement for this to happen is to make sure that E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I is increasing 
in μ 1 . It can be verified that as μ 1 → 0, E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I → E B P . Further, imposing a positive 
slope condition on E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I ensures that E B I would be above E B P for at least up to 
μ 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>, and also guarantees positive slope of E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I . 
Formally, the sufficient condition comes down to restricting the wealth of the 
ordinary punters within a critical range, which we denote by 1 introduced in Definition 
1 below (see Lemma A1 in Appendix for the derivation of 1 ; some simulations are also 
included). </p>

<p>Definition 1: Suppose J (y) ≡ y − </p>

<p>2(1−φ 1 )−λ 1 
1− 
√ 
2[ 
√ 
2−(1−λ 1 )]φ 1 </p>

<p>= 0 at two values of y, say y 0 and y 1 . </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Then define 1 to be the set of all y ∈ (y 0 , y 1 ), such that at all y ∈ 1 we have J (y) &gt; 0. </p>

<p>14. J (y) = 0 is quadratic in y (φ 1 is a function of z = 1 − y). </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>The condition says that y should not be too high or too small. The reason for this 
lies in the fact that the bookie must do a tricky balancing act if he were to induce bribery. 
On the one hand, he must reduce the price of ticket 1 to entice the naive punters to bet 
on team 1. Hence their wealth and consequently their wagers on team 1 should not be 
too small. However, higher y also releases some countervailing effect via ticket 2. As IP 
is to be conceded enough gains to finance his fixed cost of bribery, the price of ticket 
2 must be so adjusted that if IP's wealth (z) falls, the price of ticket 2 must be lowered 
appropriately to enable him to generate the same surplus as before to cover the cost of 
bribery. Thus, lower z means lower π 2 (via lower φ 1 ), which in turn attracts many naive 
punters as well to bet on team 2-something the bookie must try to avoid. Essentially, 
enabling the IP to fix the match creates a free riding opportunity for some ordinary 
bettors. Hence, z should not be too small, that is, y should not be too high. We now state 
our first set of results. </p>

<p>Proposition 1(Inducing match-fixing): Consider even and near even contests, and suppose 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, so that bribe prevention is costly. </p>

<p>(i) Then there is always a range of μ 1 starting from μ 1 = 0 where inducing match-fixing is 
optimal. 
(ii) Suppose Assumption 3 holds. If y ∈ 1 , inducing match-fixing will be optimal at all μ 1 ∈ 
(0, 1]. </p>

<p>Thus, for the even and near-even contests match-fixing is very likely. Although 
that could be due to the high cost of preventing match-fixing, our next result will show 
that the bookie may have good reasons to even encourage match-fixing, because E B I 
can potentially exceed E 0 at some high value of μ 1 , as shown in Figure 2. For this 
to happen we need two things: (i) E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I must be increasing in μ 1 , and (ii) E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I must 
exceed E 0 at μ 1 sufficiently close to 1. It turns out that both requirements are met if 
we ensure E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E 0 (as μ 1 → 1), which boils down to another critical range of y, 
denoted as 2 . 
15 See Appendix for some simulations of 2 . 
Because 2 is defined in terms of E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I which presupposes λ &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, we need to 
consider λ ≥ 1/2 as well, in which case E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I applies to all μ 1 ≥μ 1 . There, we define 
the critical region of y in terms of the limiting value of E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I (exceeding E 0 ) as </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 . </p>

<p>Definition 2: Define </p>

<p>L(y) ≡ (2 − λ 1 ) 
y 
2 + (2 − λ 1 ) 1 
+ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
. </p>

<p>(i) Suppose λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, and let 2 be the set of all y such that y[2 
√ 
2 − </p>

<p>3 
2 </p>

<p>− λ 1 ] − L(y) &gt; 0. </p>

<p>(ii) Suppose λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, and let </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 be the set of all y such that y[2 </p>

<p>√ 
2 − </p>

<p>3 
2 </p>

<p>− λ 1 ] + y 
√ 
λ 1 − </p>

<p>1 
√ 
2 </p>

<p>2 − </p>

<p>L(y) &gt; 0. </p>

<p>If y ∈ 2 when λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, or if y ∈ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 when λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, then by definition E B I &gt; E 0 
as μ 1 → 1. Once again the critical range of y specifies the size of the ordinary punters' 
wealth to be neither too high nor too low. The explanation is same as before. If it is 
too high, match-fixing is potentially rewarding, but the scope of free riding (by some 
ordinary punters) is also great. But if it is too low, the potential gain from bribery is 
small. </p>

<p>15. Let μ 1 → 1 in E B I and write the expression for E B I − E 0 &gt; 0, which gives y[2 
√ 
2 − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 − p 1 − 
λ 1 ] &gt; yφ 1 + (1 − λ 1 p 1 ) 1 . Substitute p 1 = 1/2 on the right-hand side to obtain L(y). </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>Table I. 
Comparison of Results </p>

<p>Proposition 1 
Proposition 2 </p>

<p>Type of contests 
Even 
Even 
Bribe prevention (relative to the benchmark case) 
Costly 
May or may not be costly 
Bribe inducement is preferred 
At all μ 1 
At high values of μ 1 
Nature of bribe inducement highlighted 
Bribe tolerance 
Bribe encouragement 
The required range of y 
Relatively narrow 
Relatively wide </p>

<p>Now in Proposition 2 we claim that if y ∈ 2 or </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 , then above a critical value of 
μ 1 , not only is bribe inducement optimal, but it is of the "bribe encouragement" type. </p>

<p>Proposition 2 (Actively encourage bribery): Consider the even or a near-even contest 
and suppose Assumption 3 holds. Then there exists a critical value of μ 1 , say μ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ∈ (μ 1 , 1), such 
that at all μ 1 &gt; μ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 the expected profit from bribe inducement exceeds the expected profit of the 
"no IP" case, if (i) y ∈ 2 , when λ 1 &lt; 1/2, or (ii) y ∈ </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>2 , when λ 1 ≥ 1/2. 
It is notable that we have not insisted on p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and/or y ∈ 1 in Proposition 
2 . Although those assumptions along with the condition specified in Proposition 1 
give rise to the graph we have presented in Figure 2, they are not necessary for bribe 
encouragement. As long as y ∈ 2 , E B I will cross E 0 at some high μ 1 , and bribe 
encouragement will take place. So, Propositions 1 and 2 focus on two different aspects-
general bribe inducement for unrestricted μ 1 (Proposition 1) vs. a specific type of bribe 
inducement for a smaller range of μ 1 (Proposition 2 )-and it is not always possible to 
rank the corresponding y-value sets. Table I provides a comparison of results. 
The main message of Propositions 1 and 2 is that when contests are close the 
bookmaker may prefer to orchestrate match-fixing (via market prices). Though in most 
cases, such orchestration is merely a strategy of cutting losses, we cannot rule out a 
perverse motive of market manipulation with the tacit help of an anonymous fixer, quite 
legally. </p>

<p>4. Both Teams Corruptible </p>

<p>When both teams are corruptible, how does the prospect of match-fixing change? We can 
see that the bookie now has a choice of targeting a specific team or either teams (to bribe). 
If a specific team is bribed, the analysis is similar to that of the previous section. 
16 So 
we extend our analysis to bribery of either teams. Prima facie the scope for match-fixing 
increases under this option. But as the bookie does not know which team the IP might 
get access to, he will have to concede sufficient rents on either ticket. This makes bribe 
inducement quite costly and less often preferable. 
To simplify the analysis, we impose symmetry: 0 &lt; μ 1 = μ 2 = μ ≤ 1/2, λ 1 = λ 2 = 
λ ≥ 0, α 1 = α 2 = α and 1 = 2 = . As before, we assume that at most one team can 
be accessed (with probability 2μ). </p>

<p>EVEN CONTESTS. We focus on p 1 = 1/2, and recall from Lemma 1 that the optimal 
bribe prevention prices are π i = max{ 
√ p i , φ j }. At p 1 = 1/2, if the price constraints don't </p>

<p>16. There is one difference though. The team which is not targeted must be protected from bribery. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>bind (i.e., p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ), E B P = E 0 = y[3 − 2 </p>

<p>√ 
2]; but if the constraints bind (i.e., 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ), the bribe prevention profit (at p 1 = 1/2) is </p>

<p>E B P = y 3 − 2φ − 
1 
φ 
. 
(12) </p>

<p>For bribe inducement, we need to consider first the ex ante probability of each team's 
win. For team 1 it is r 1 = μ(λp 1 + (1 − λp 2 )) + (1 − 2μ) p 1 = p 1 + μ(1 − λ)(1 − 2 p 1 ); for 
team 2 it is r 2 = p 2 + μ(1 − λ)(1 − 2 p 2 ). Curiously, at p 1 = 1/2 we have r 1 = r 2 = 1/2. The 
prospect of bribing either team cancels out each other's gains in winning probability. 
However, an exact offset occurs only at p 1 = 1/2; at p 1 &gt; 1/2, r 1 &lt; p 1 and consequently 
r 2 &gt; p 2 . So in general bribery of either team reduces the gap between the favorite and 
the longshot, making the contest more even. 
If at the perfectly even contest the probability of win does not change with bribery, 
then what is the potential benefit of inducing bribery? The simple answer is: none, unless 
bribe prevention is costly. In other words, in this environment there is no hope for getting 
higher profit than the "no IP" case. Bribe encouragement cannot occur here; at best there 
may be bribe tolerance. 
The general statement of the bribe inducement problem is </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>π 1 ,π 2 </p>

<p>E B I = y 3 − π 1 − π 2 − 
r 1 
π 1 
− 
1 − r 1 
π 2 
− z 
μ(1 − λp 2 ) 
π 1 
+ 
μ(1 − λp 1 ) 
π 2 
− 2μ (13) </p>

<p>subject to 
p 2 ≤ π 2 ≤ φ 1 (&lt; 1 − λp 1 ), 
p 1 ≤ π 1 ≤ φ 2 (&lt; 1 − λp 2 ), 
π 1 + π 2 ≥ 1. </p>

<p>The unconstrained solution is given by </p>

<p>π 1 = r 1 + μ(z/y)(1 − λp 2 ),π 2 = 1 − r 1 + μ(z/y)(1 − λp 1 ). 
(14) </p>

<p>At p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, the symmetric unconstrained solution isπ 1 =π 2 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>+ μ </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>(2−λ) 
2 </p>

<p>, leading to 
profit </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I = y[3 − 4π ] + 2μz = 3y − 2 2y y + μz(2 − λ) + 2μz. 
(15) </p>

<p>On the other hand, if the constraints bind the profit is restricted to be </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>B I = y 3 − 2φ − </p>

<p>1 
φ 
+ μz 2 − 
2 − λ 
φ 
= E B P − (2 − λ) μz. 
(16) </p>

<p>Clearly, bribery is not preferred. Further, if bribe prevention is costless, that is, 
E B P = E 0 , bribe inducement will be out of question. Therefore, the best prospect for 
bribe inducement arises when π i =π i &lt; φ, in addition to E B P &lt; E 0 and we would 
be looking for the scenario E B P ≤ E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &lt; E 0 . We find that the conditionπ &lt; φ (at 
p 1 = 1/2) is satisfied if y belongs to a critical range, which we call 3 . </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>In the Appendix we show through simulation that under suitable parameter spec-
ifications 3 is nonempty (see Table A3). With higher μ and λ the set 3 shrinks. Intu-
itively, the expected payout to IP increases with μ. So the bookie will try to optimize on </p>

<p>17. It can be checked thatπ is declining in y (with the second-order derivative positive), and drops from 
infinity (at y = 0) to 1/2 at y = 1. Likewise, φ is also declining in y (but with the second-order derivative 
being negative) and drops from a fraction at y = 0 to zero at y = 1. If the two curves cross each other, they will 
cross twice. Let these two intersection points be denoted asŷ 0 (&gt; 0) andŷ 1 (&lt; 1). Let us denote all the values of 
y strictly lying between the two points by 3 = {y|ŷ 0 &lt; y &lt;ŷ 1 }. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>this loss, by raising the unconstrained prices, but then the likelihood of the constraint 
binding also increases. 
Assuming y ∈ 3 , we are guaranteed to have unconstrained prices for the BI prob-
lem. Now we try to identify the values of μ at which we will get E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . We 
note that E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I is a decreasing function of μ, as </p>

<p>∂ E </p>

<p>U 
B I </p>

<p>∂μ 
= 2z 1 − 
2 − λ 
π 
&lt; 0 
sinceπ &lt; φ = 
2 − λ 
2 + (2 − λ) 
&lt; 2 − λ. </p>

<p>From equation (15) we also see that E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I approaches E 0 when μ → 0, and 
thereby at all μ sufficiently small we must have E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . At the other end of μ, 
that is, μ = 1/2, we impose E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &lt; E B P with the help of the following assumption. </p>

<p>Assumption 4: Let 2 </p>

<p>2−λz 
y </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>&gt; 2φ + </p>

<p>1 
φ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Now we state the main result of this section. </p>

<p>Proposition 3 (More match-fixing possibilities imply less match-fixing): Suppose 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (so that E B P &lt; E 0 ), y ∈ 3 (so that E B I = E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I ), and Assumption 4 
holds. Then at all even and near-even contests bribe inducement of either team is preferred to 
bribe prevention if μ is less than a critical valueμ &lt; 1/2. For μ aboveμ match-fixing will be 
prevented. Bribery in the range μ ≤μ will be of the "bribe tolerance" variety. </p>

<p>The message of Proposition 3 is strikingly different from that of Propositions 1 
and 2 . No longer does bribery yield higher profit than the "no IP" case. So the bookie 
has no incentive to "welcome" the IP. He can tolerate him but only up to a certain level 
of μ. The intuition is that, to induce bribery the bookie must incur losses to IP on both 
tickets. This loss steadily rises with μ outweighing the relative cost of bribe prevention, 
rendering bribe inducement quickly suboptimal. 
It can also be shown that if λ is sufficiently small the E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I curve will be U-shaped 
and symmetric (against p 1 ), which will shift down with μ, as illustrated in Figure 4 for 
an example. An implication is that even when the incentive to induce bribery disappears 
at the perfectly even contest, it may still persist at nearby contests. Example 2 in the next 
section makes this point sharper. </p>

<p>5. Examples and Simulations </p>

<p>Example 1: We present some simulations on the basis of an example assuming only team 1 
is corruptible. Here, the entire range of p 1 is considered, though our main interest lies around 
p 1 = 1/2. As our simulations show, the theoretical results are generalizable to a large set of p 1 . </p>

<p>We set λ 1 = 0, w + α(f + f I ) = 0.05 and y = 0.8, which implies z = 0.2 and therefore 
= 0.25. Because λ = 0, φ 1 = φ 2 = 1/(1 + ) = 0.8 at all p 1 ; we can also calculate the 
upper limit of y to be 0.88 that supports Assumption 3. Further, it is clear that y = 0.8 
belongs to the set 1 = (0.29, 0.83) (see Table A1 in the Appendix). Hence the conditions 
for Proposition 1 are satisfied. So we can expect bribe inducement to be optimal at all μ 1 
at p 1 = 1/2. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table II. 
Bribe Inducement Range of p 1 </p>

<p>E B I −E B P 
E B P </p>

<p>at p 1 = 0.5 </p>

<p>E B I −E 0 
E 0 </p>

<p>at p 1 = 0.5 </p>

<p>μ 1 
p 10p1 
p 11 
(%) 
(%) </p>

<p>0.05 
0.245 
0.450 
1 
3.87 
0.10 
0.198 
0.465 
1 
3.10 
0.20 
0.194 
0.505 
1 
6.98 
0.73 
0.30 
0.189 
0.540 
0.660 
14.73 
8.02 
0.40 
0.183 
0.579 
0.695 
27.13 
19.70 
0.50 
0.178 
0.610 
0.710 
43.41 
35.04 
0.60 
0.171 
0.632 
0.720 
62.79 
53.28 
0.70 
0.169 
0.646 
0.725 
82.17 
71.53 
0.80 
0.168 
0.656 
0.728 
101.55 
89.78 
0.90 
0.166 
0.665 
0.732 
120.93 
108.02 
0.95 
0.166 
0.669 
0.733 
131.00 
118.25 </p>

<p>In Table II we present several values of μ 1 over which bribe inducement is optimal. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>p 10 is the critical probability at which E B I = E 0 (also = E B P ).p 1 is the critical value 
of p 1 at which E B I = E 0 (&gt; E B P ). p 11 is the probability at which E B I = E B P . So 
at all p 1 &lt; p 10 and at all p 1 &gt; p 11 (provided p 11 &lt; 1), bribe inducement is not optimal. 
Alternatively, bribe inducement is optimal at all p 1 ∈ [ p 10 , p 11 ], of which at all p 1 ∈ 
[ p 10 ,p 1 ] bribery is of the "bribe encouragement" type, and at all p 1 ∈ [p 1 , p 11 ] bribery is 
of the "bribe tolerance" type. 
Columns 2-4 of Table II give these critical values of p 1 against μ 1 . As can be seen, 
with successive increases in μ 1 , p 10 declines andp 1 increases; thus, clearly the region of 
bribe encouragement expands. As p 11 also decreases with μ the region of bribe tolerance 
contracts. It is also seen that when team 1 is a strong favorite, bribery is not optimal at 
μ 1 = 0.3. On the other hand, when team 1 is moderately underdog ( p 1 slightly greater 
than p 10 ) not only is bribery optimal, but it gives higher profit than the benchmark case. 
More importantly, bribery is always optimal at the perfectly even contest ( p 1 = 
1/2), a confirmation of Proposition 1. At μ 1 = 0.20 or higher values, we have bribe 
encouragement at p 1 = 1/2. Columns 5 and 6 give the percentage of profit gained from 
bribe inducement, over and above the bribe prevention profit and the benchmark profit, 
respectively, at the perfectly even contest. We see that these proportions also rise with 
μ 1 . With μ 1 = 0.9 the profit gains from bribery exceed 100%. For Column 6, we should 
note that the condition for Proposition 2 is met; y = 0.8 ∈ 2 = (0.16, 0.92) (for which 
see Table A2 in the Appendix). 
Figures 3a, 3b, and 3c show the profit curves for three values of μ 1 . The red curve 
represents profit from bribe inducement and the blue curve profit from bribe prevention. 
The yellow curve is the expected profit from the "no IP" case. Three sets of graphs are 
based on the same parameter values except μ 1 . In Figure 3a, we assume μ 1 = 0.05, in 
Figure 3b, μ 1 = 0.3 and in Figure 3c μ 1 = 0.7. 
As should be obvious, the bribery incentive is concentrated around p 1 = 1/2. When 
μ 1 is as low as 0.05 (Figure 3a), bribe inducement profit actually exceeds the "no IP" 
profit between p 1 = 0.245 and p 1 = 0.45. But as μ 1 increases (see Figure 3b or 3c) the 
match-fixing incentive disappears from the higher end of p 1 . The bribing incentives </p>

<p>18. All the simulation work in the paper has been done in <rs type="software">Microsoft Excel</rs>. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>(a) Bribe inducement is opƟmal at p 1 =0.245 onward at all p 1 ; μ 1 =0.05 </p>

<p>(b) Bribe inducement is opƟmal at all p 1 in [0.189, 0.66]; μ 1 =0.3 </p>

<p>(c) Bribe inducement is opƟmal at all p 1 in [0.136, 0.725]; μ 1 =0.7 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.800 </p>

<p>0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 </p>

<p>Bribe 
prevenƟon 
profit 
Bribe 
inducement 
profit 
No IP profit </p>

<p>Bribe 
encouragement </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.800 </p>

<p>0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 </p>

<p>Bribe prevenƟon 
profit </p>

<p>Bribe inducement 
profit </p>

<p>No IP profit </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.800 </p>

<p>0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 0.6 0.7 0.8 0.9 1 </p>

<p>Bribe prevenƟon 
profit </p>

<p>Bribe inducement 
profit </p>

<p>No IP profit </p>

<p>Bribe 
tolerance </p>

<p>Bribe 
tolerance </p>

<p>Bribe 
encouragement </p>

<p>Bribe 
tolerance </p>

<p>Bribe 
encouragement </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. DATA COMMON TO THREE FIGURES ABOVE: λ 1 = 0, 1 = 0.25, φ 1 = 0.8, 
y = 0.8 </p>

<p>generally increase in moderately uneven contests with team 1 being weak. The even 
contests remain vulnerable and the payoff from match-fixing around these contests 
keeps increasing with μ 1 . In fact, higher the value of μ 1 , stronger the incentive to fix the 
match (around the even contest). This heightened incentive spreads to uneven contests </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.36 
0.4 
0.44 
0.48 
0.52 
0.56 
0.6 
0.64 </p>

<p>p 1 </p>

<p>No IP profit </p>

<p>Bribe inducement 
Profit (μ=0.05) </p>

<p>Bribe inducement 
Profit (μ=0.15) </p>

<p>Bribe prevenƟon 
Profit </p>

<p>Profit </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. BRIBE TOLERANCE IN EVEN CONTESTS </p>

<p>Table III. 
Bribe Tolerance Range of p 1 </p>

<p>μ 
E B I at p 1 = 0.5 </p>

<p>E B I −E B P 
E B P </p>

<p>at p 1 = 0.5 
E B I &gt; E B P at p 1 </p>

<p>0 
0.137 
14.16 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.03 
0.132 
10.00 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.05 
0.129 
7.50 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.08 
0.124 
3.33 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.10 
0.121 
0.83 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.11 
0.120 
0 
∈ [0.36, 0.64] 
0.13 
0.117 
−2.50 
∈ [0.36, 0.42] and [0.58, 0.64] 
0.15 
0.114 
−5.00 
∈ [0.36, 0.39] and [0.61, 0.64] 
0.17 
0.111 
−7.5 
= 0.36, and = 0.64 </p>

<p>(moving leftward) where team 1 is an underdog. This also confirms our discussion based 
on Figure 1 that the bookie's incentive to induce bribery is strongest at p 1 = 1/2. </p>

<p>Example 2: This example is for the case of both teams corruptible. We assume symmetry 
and consider similar parameter values, λ 1 = λ 2 = 0, 1 = 2 = 0.25 and y = 0.8; but we 
restrict our attention to p 1 ∈ [ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(1+ ) 2 , 1 − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(1+ ) 2 ]= [0.36, 0.64]. Also verify from Table A3 in the 
Appendix that y = 0.8 belongs to 3 for any μ ≤ 0.15, given λ = 0. Hence the unconstrained 
solution will hold for the BI problem. Further, Assumption 4, required for Proposition 3 , is also 
satisfied. </p>

<p>Figure 4 shows two expected profit curves from bribe inducement, at μ = 0.05 
and μ = 0.15, and the benchmark and the bribe prevention profit over the interval of 
p 1 , [0.36, 0.64]. Here, 
√ p i &lt; φ(= 1/(1 + )) for both i = 1, 2. That is, bribe prevention </p>

<p>is costly at p 1 = 1/2. E B P is constant at 0.120. The benchmark profit E 0 is 0.137 at 
p 1 = 1/2, but higher elsewhere. 
How the B I profit varies with successive changes in μ at p 1 = 1/2 (in reference to 
Proposition 3 ) is given in Table III by simulating the B I and B P profits for a range of μ. 
We see that E B I is equal to E 0 only at μ = 0. As μ rises, E B I falls (see Column 2 of 
Table III); but still bribe inducement is preferred at all μ ≤ 0.11, as shown by column 3 
of Table III. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>From Figure 4 we see that the optimality of bribe inducement holds over the entire 
interval [0.36, 0.64] at μ = 0.05. At μ = 0.15, no longer is bribery optimal at the perfectly 
even contest (see Table III). However, contests with p 1 ∈ (0.36, 0.39) and p 1 ∈ (0.61, 0.64) 
are still suitable for fixing. These two intervals gradually shrink and disappear at μ &gt; 
0.17 (see column 4 in Table III). 
If we compare the maximum incidence of match-fixing at the perfectly even contest 
( p 1 = 1/2) between the two examples, it falls from 1 in Example 1 to 2μ = 0.22 in Example 
2. Greater scope of bribery drastically reduces the incidence of bribery. </p>

<p>6. More General Distribution Functions of Bettors' Beliefs </p>

<p>We now examine whether our analysis of the bookie's incentives is specific to uniform 
beliefs assumption. One way to do that would be to extend the "no IP" case to a class 
of more general distribution functions, and see if the bookie's profit is still minimum 
around even contests. 
Suppose the bettors' beliefs are given by a probability density function g(q ) over 
q ∈ [a , b] with 0 ≤ a &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; b ≤ 1; g(q ) &gt; 0 at all q ∈ (a , b). The cumulative density 
function is G(q ). One advantage of this formulation is that we can allow the bettors' 
beliefs to be correlated with the draw of p 1 . For example, we may have a = a &gt; 0 
with b = 1 for any draw of p 1 &gt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, b = b &lt; 1 with a = 0 for any draw of p 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, and 
(a = 0, b = 1) if p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. 
Bettors with beliefs q ∈ [π 1 , b] buy ticket 1, and with beliefs (1 − q ) &gt; π 2 (or q ∈ 
[a , 1 − π 2 ] ) buy ticket 2. They each have one dollar to bet. Restricting π 1 &lt; b and π 2 &lt; 
1 − a for positive sale of tickets, the bookie maximizes the following, subject to (no) 
Dutch-book, that is, Assumption 2: </p>

<p>E 0 = y </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>π 1 </p>

<p>1 − 
p 1 
π 1 
g(q )dq + y </p>

<p>1−π 2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 − 
p 2 
π 2 
g(q )dq </p>

<p>= y 1 − G(π 1 ) − 
p 1 
π 1 
+ p 1 
G(π 1 ) 
π 1 
+ G(1 − π 2 ) − p 2 
G(1 − π 2 ) 
π 2 
. </p>

<p>The first-order conditions for profit maximization are: </p>

<p>∂ E 0 
∂π 1 
= y · 
p 1 g(π 1 ) 
π </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>1 − G(π 1 ) 
g(π 1 ) 
− 
(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 
π 1 = 0, 
(17) </p>

<p>∂ E 0 
∂π 2 
= y · 
p 2 g(1 − π 2 ) 
π </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>G(1 − π 2 ) 
g(1 − π 2 ) 
− 
(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 
π 2 = 0. 
(18) </p>

<p>The second-order conditions are satisfied if the following assumption is made, 
which also helps to ensure monotonicity of the optimal prices. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Assumption 5: The hazard rate </p>

<p>1−G(x) 
g(x) </p>

<p>is decreasing, and </p>

<p>G(x) 
g(x) </p>

<p>is increasing, in x. </p>

<p>19. Second-order 
conditions 
are: </p>

<p>∂ 2 E 0 
∂π 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>= − </p>

<p>[g(π 1 )] 2 +(1−G(π 1 ))g (π 1 ) 
[g(π 1 )] 2 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>2π 1 − p 1 
p 1 </p>

<p>&lt; 0, </p>

<p>∂ 2 E 0 
∂π 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>[g(1−π 2 )] 2 −G(1−π 2 )g (1−π 2 ) 
[g(1−π 2 )] 2 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>2π 2 − p 2 
p 2 </p>

<p>&lt; 0. The first terms (inclusive of the negative sign) are the deriva-</p>

<p>tives of </p>

<p>1−G(π 1 ) 
g(π 1 ) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>G(1−π 2 ) </p>

<p>g(1−π 2 ) that are negative by Assumption 5. Because π i &gt; p i for positive profit, 
second-order conditions follow. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>It is easy to see that the above assumption will be satisfied by densities symmetric 
around </p>

<p>(a +b) 
2 </p>

<p>= 1/2 with support [a , b] where 0 ≤ a &lt; 1/2 &lt; b ≤ 1, and also for asymmet-
ric distributions generated by mildly moving away from the symmetric distributions. 
The following lemma shows that the bookie's problem has a unique interior so-
lution and prices are (weakly) monotonic in p 1 . Moreover, the bookie will never set π 1 
below a and π 2 below 1 − b because by raising π 1 up to a and π 2 up to 1 − b, profit can 
be raised without losing ticket sales. </p>

<p>Lemma 3 (Monotonic prices): Optimal prices (π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 , π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) solving the bookie's problem are unique: 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ( p 1 ) ≥ max{ p 1 , a } , π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ( p 2 ) ≥ max{ p 2 , 1 − b}. π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 is non-decreasing in p 1 and π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 is non-
increasing in p 1 . Further, the "price markup" on ticket i (i.e., </p>

<p>π i − p i 
p i </p>

<p>) is decreasing in p i . At 
p 1 &gt; b ticket 1 is not sold and at p 1 &lt; a ticket 2 is not sold. </p>

<p>The markup behavior noted above is implied by Assumption 5. 
Substituting (π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 , π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) into the profit function, we derive E 0 ( p 1 ). There are two 
aspects of interest-the level of E 0 at extreme values of p 1 , and the slope of E 0 . At 
p 1 &lt; a , when only ticket 1 is sold, E 0 = y(1 − </p>

<p>p 1 
a </p>

<p>) when π 1 = a . That is, the expected 
profit is close to y. Similarly, at p 1 &gt; b, expected profit is again close to y, as E 0 = 
y(1 − </p>

<p>p 2 
1−b </p>

<p>) when π 2 = 1 − b. The slope of E 0 is negative at p 1 &lt; a and positive at 
p 1 &gt; b. But at p 1 ∈ [a , b] that we are primarily interested in, the slope can vary from 
negative to positive, as can be seen from the following expression, on the basis of which 
we arrive at our claim (Proposition 4 ) about the shape of the profit function: </p>

<p>k( p 1 ) ≡ 
∂ E 0 
∂ p 1 
= y − 
1 − G(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ( p 1 )) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ( p 1 ) </p>

<p>+ 
G(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ( p 2 )) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ( p 2 ) </p>

<p>. 
(19) </p>

<p>Proposition 4 (A class of distribution functions &amp; corruption-free betting): </p>

<p>(i) The bookie's profit E 0 ( p 1 ) is (nearly) U-shaped with a unique minimum at p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 , which solves 
k( p 1 ) = 0 in (19). 
(ii) Further, if g(q ) is symmetric and a + b = 1, then p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = 1/2. 
(iii) Suppose g(q ) is symmetric. Also assume that at p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, the price markups satisfy </p>

<p>π 1 
p 1 
≤ (&gt;) 
π 2 
p 2 
if a + b ≥ (&lt;)1. 
(20) </p>

<p>Then, for a + b &gt; 1, p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 ∈ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>if </p>

<p>at p 1 = 
1 
2 
π 1 − π 2 ≤ a + b − 1 ≤ π 1 − π 2 
at p 1 = 
a + b 
2 
; 
(21) </p>

<p>and for a + b &lt; 1, p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 ∈ </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>if </p>

<p>at p 1 = 
a + b 
2 
π 1 − π 2 ≤ a + b − 1 ≤ π 1 − π 2 
at p 1 = 
1 
2 
. 
(22) </p>

<p>(The second assumption in part (iii), that is, condition (20), suggests that when 
team 1 is already a favorite, the price markup on ticket 1 should be smaller than that on 
ticket 2, reflecting the difficulty of making a profit from a team that has a greater chance 
to win.) </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>As an illustration we derive the minimum profit point for "unbalanced" uniform 
distribution, which automatically satisfies Assumption 5, the second assumption in 
part (iii), and conditions (21)-(22). Optimal prices are </p>

<p>π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = min b, max{a , bp 1 } , π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 = min (1 − a ), max{1 − b, (1 − a ) p 2 } . </p>

<p>Substituting π 1 = 
√ 
bp 1 and π 2 = (1 − a ) p 2 into equation (19) we obtain the mini-</p>

<p>mum profit point as 
√ p 1 = </p>

<p>b 
1−a </p>

<p>p 2 , or p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = </p>

<p>b 
1+b−a </p>

<p>. If b = 1 − a (symmetry) then p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>But if a + b &lt; 1, p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = </p>

<p>b 
1+b−a </p>

<p>∈ ( </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>), and if a + b &gt; 1, </p>

<p>b 
1+b−a </p>

<p>∈ ( </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>). 
The main message of Proposition 4 is that for a symmetric distribution the mini-
mum profit point will diverge from the even contest, only if the support is "unbalanced" 
(i.e., a + b = 1). Even then, p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 will not stray too far from 1/2, as long as the prices observe 
some regularity conditions (i.e., (21) or (22)). Therefore, our insight into the bookie's de-
sire to orchestrate fixing at even and near-even contests remains valid for a class of 
(general) distribution functions. </p>

<p>7. Partially Rational Bettors </p>

<p>So far our analysis relied on naive bettors assumption. Here we briefly consider the 
case of rational bettors. Intuitively, like in markets for financial assets involving noise 
and sophisticated/informed traders where the latter group benefits at the expense of 
the former, in our model naive bettors create an environment in which unscrupulous 
fixers and monopolist bookmaker can implicitly collude or coordinate to the detriment 
of fair contest and fair betting. It is to be expected that if the market is populated more 
by rational bettors, the monopolist's hands will be somewhat tied limiting his prof-
itable match-fixing opportunities. We will verify this simple intuition using a plausible 
description of rational bettors. 
There are at least two counts on which the bettors' rationality can be improved. 
First, bettors may become aware that there is a possibility of match-fixing, and second, 
they can try to extract information about the teams' winning chances from the posted 
odds. 
If we were to admit rationality only on the first count, then our model can be 
easily extended by allowing the bettors to revise their q as q [μ 1 λ 1 + (1 − μ 1 )] when only 
team 1 is corrupt and [μλq + μ(1 − λ(1 − q )) + (1 − 2μ)q ] when both teams are corrupt. 
Bettors may apply this belief regardless of the bookie's strategy. This belief revision 
will effectively compress the support of the bettors' belief distribution. 
20 Then using 
the insight of Proposition 4 we can tell the bookie's expected profit curve (ignoring his 
potential loss to the fixer, if any) will certainly be somewhat dampened at very low and 
very high values of p 1 , but will still have a minimum point at or near p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, which 
suggests that the bookie's match-fixing incentive may weaken, but will not disappear. 
An alternative would be to allow for rationality on both counts. Admittedly, mod-
eling information extraction from the posted odds is a challenging problem and it is 
beyond the scope of this paper. In our setting, by observing the bet prices the bettors 
cannot infer p 1 (even if they know all parameters of the model), simply because they 
cannot be sure which strategy the bookie is pursuing-bribe prevention or inducement. 
Therefore, we introduce a simple assumption on the bettors' behavior, which makes the </p>

<p>20. In the first case the support is [0, μ 1 λ 1 + (1 − μ 1 )], and in the second case, it is [μ(1 − λ), 1 − μ(1 − λ)]. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>bettors at least partially rational. We assume that the knowledge of the presence of a 
fixer makes them suspicious of foul play, if they see the posted odds are really "too far 
away" from the odds induced by their initial belief. Our assumption is couched as a 
"behavioral rule" as follows: 
If the market odds are too good to be true, a "partially rational" bettor would apply 
extreme caution and may revise his prior q before placing any bets. If the posted prices offer a 
rate of return in excess of an exogenous threshold R &gt; 0 on a particular ticket, say ticket 1, then 
the rational bettor reasons that it is too good to be true; team 1 is going to be bribed, and it is wise 
not to bet on it at all. 
Suppose for a bettor with belief q , ticket 1 is a preferred bet: max{ </p>

<p>1−q −π 2 
π 2 </p>

<p>, 0} ≤ </p>

<p>q −π 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>. As 
long as </p>

<p>q −π 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>≤ R, he sticks to his belief q and bets on team 1. But if </p>

<p>q −π 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>&gt; R, he completely 
withdraws from betting (i.e., revises q = 0). Similar rule applies for a bettor when ticket 2 is his 
preferred bet. 
There are several justifications for the above strategy. First, in reality, most investors 
are weary of projects that promise too high a return, when they are conscious of the pos-
sibility of foul play. In gambling too, betting odds that are "too good to be true" should 
make them nervous. It is also nearly impossible for the bettors to do sophisticated guess-
work and extract precise information from posted odds, due to cognitive limitations, 
bounded rationality, or just lack of expertise. A simple cut-off strategy can be the most 
practical way to make decisions in such environments. 
Second, though our assumption pertains to a sudden withdrawal from betting, one 
could alternatively model gradual withdrawal. Discontinuous participation in markets 
populated by rogue elements is similar in spirit to how prices may not smooth transac-
tions in markets with asymmetric information, as shown in the credit-rationing model of 
Stiglitz and Weiss (1981). The theoretical basis for the cut-off strategy can also be traced 
to studies on market manipulation in finance, where insiders' profitable trading oppor-
tunities become restricted for fear of unfavorable response by uninformed participants 
if prices signal informed trading; see, for instance, Chakraborty and Yilmaz (2004). 
Third, our behavioral assumption can be seen as an alternative to allowing bettors' 
beliefs to be correlated with the nature's initial draw (which makes them "less naive," a 
point we mentioned in Section 6). Even without such information precision, the bettors 
may bet conservatively (for other reasons), which in turn can limit the monopolist's 
hands in inducing match-fixing. 
Fourth, the real world betting market is likely to have a mix of both types of 
bettors-naive and rational (full or partial, whichever way it is defined). The first group, 
called leisure/amateur bettors, takes a punt of a few dollars on a sport that they love for 
the enjoyment of gambling (Saunders and Turner (1992), Bruce and Johnson (1987, p. 3), 
Winter and Kukuk (2008)). The second type of bettors, who may not be fully rational but 
are instinctively watchful, are very likely to conform to our behavioral assumption. In a 
simple tractable way, we aim to incorporate this mix of bettors in our model. Admittedly, 
an ideal treatment of rational bettors requires a richer model borrowing insights from 
recent developments in the market manipulation and learning literature. 
In what follows, we will refer to our "partially rational" bettors simply as "rational" 
bettors. 
Betting rule for rational bettors. Given the above definition of rationality, a rational 
bettor bets on team 1 if and only if π 1 ≤ q ≤ π 1 (1 + R), and bets on team 2 if and only 
if π 2 ≤ 1 − q ≤ π 2 (1 + R), or 1 − π 2 (1 + R) ≤ q ≤ 1 − π 2 . 
The above rule implies that there are now two additional groups of bettors who 
will not bet. All (rational) bettors with q &lt; 1 − π 2 (1 + R) and q &gt; π 1 (1 + R) will not bet, </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>in addition to bettors with q ∈ (1 − π 2 , π 1 ). That also means under no circumstances, 
the bookie will be able to induce all bettors to bet in a preferred direction and collect 
the entire fund y. This is probably an early indication of the difficulty of defrauding a 
rational bettor. 
We now present an analysis of the bookie's problem for the case where both teams 
are corrupt, and μ i , λ i , and i are symmetric (μ &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>). The analysis is comparable with 
Section 4 for p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, and for better comparison we will assume that the ordinary bettors 
are of two types: naive as in previous sections and rational as defined above; ρ proportion 
of the ordinary bettors is naive and 1 − ρ proportion is rational. Their prior beliefs are 
"uniform." 
Given any p 1 (ignoring bribery), the bookie's profit from rational bettors is calcu-
lated as: </p>

<p>(1 − ρ) </p>

<p>π 1 (1+R) </p>

<p>π 1 </p>

<p>y 1 − 
p 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>dq </p>

<p>ticket 1 profit </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>1−π 2 </p>

<p>1−π 2 (1+R) </p>

<p>y 1 − 
p 2 
π 2 </p>

<p>dq </p>

<p>ticket 2 profit </p>

<p>= (1 − ρ)yR [π 1 + π 2 − 1] . </p>

<p>Note that, the expected profit from the rational bettors becomes independent of p 1 . 
The expected profit from the naive bettors is unchanged from the previous section(s). 
Combining all bets (including IP's) we write bookie's aggregate profit and the bribe 
inducement program as: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>π 1 ,π 2 </p>

<p>E = (1 − ρ)yR π 1 + π 2 − 1 + ρ 3 − π 1 − π 2 − 
r 1 
π 1 
− 
r 2 
π 2 </p>

<p>+ μz 2 − 
1 − λp 1 
π 2 
− 
1 − λp 2 
π 1 
, </p>

<p>subject to 
p 2 ≤ π 2 ≤ φ 1 (&lt; 1 − λp 1 ), 
p 1 ≤ π 1 ≤ φ 2 (&lt; 1 − λp 2 ), 
π 1 + π 2 ≥ 1, </p>

<p>where r 1 = q + μ(1 − λ)(1 − 2q ) and r 2 = 1 − r 1 . Differentiating E with respect to π i 
yields: </p>

<p>∂ E 
∂π i 
= (1 − ρ)yR + ρy −1 + 
r i 
π </p>

<p>2 
i </p>

<p>+ μz(1 − λp j ) 
1 
π </p>

<p>2 
i </p>

<p>, i = j. </p>

<p>Because ρ &lt; 1, π i has to be potentially much larger now for an interior optimum. In 
particular, consider the special case of ρ = 0 (all bettors are rational). Then the above 
derivative is strictly positive, and by (2), the bookie should set π 1 = φ 2 and π 2 = φ 1 , 
yielding match-fixing inducement profits: </p>

<p>E B I = yR φ 1 + φ 2 − 1 − μz [2 − λ]. </p>

<p>On the other hand, in this special case if the bookie were to prevent bribery, his 
profits would be at least: </p>

<p>E B P = yR φ 1 + φ 2 − 1 . </p>

<p>Thus, we have the following result: </p>

<p>Proposition 5 (Rational bettors and no match-fixing): When almost all ordinary bettors 
are rational (i.e., ρ → 0), the monopolist bookie prefers bribe prevention over match-fixing. With 
a mix of bettors, match-fixing may be optimal less often than when all bettors are naive. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>The above result shows that rational bettors are an obstacle to orchestrating match-
fixing. Although the complete elimination of match-fixing result (obtained in the special 
case) is rather extreme, we should keep in mind that the underlying assumptions are also 
extreme, such as complete withdrawal from betting, and both teams being corruptible. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Also, with all rational bettors, if withdrawal from betting is gradual, then match-fixing 
is likely to become optimal in some cases. 
An additional consideration that we have ignored due to the one-shot nature of 
the game is the bookie's reputation effect. If match-fixing is uncovered, ordinary bettors 
would be reluctant to bet in the future. This will work against bribe inducement. 
Does Proposition 5 cast a serious doubt on our model of match-fixing? We definitely 
think not. In real-life sports betting, markets are likely to have a mix of naive and rational 
bettors. So long as there are considerable number of naive bettors, who follow the game 
with their exogenous beliefs and completely unmindful of the dark side of betting, 
unscrupulous fixers will always have their negative influence. </p>

<p>8. Enforcement Issues and Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>We have presented a model of monopoly betting with the risk of match-fixing, and shown 
that the market outcome is vastly different from the competitive case for even contests. 
The monopolist bookmaker abuses his market power sometimes and encourages match-
fixing. But other times, he tolerates match-fixing as more of a survival strategy. The 
undesirable outcome of course depends on several market microstructure elements, 
such as the bettors' beliefs, information hierarchy, market concentration and the extent 
to which fixing can tilt the outcome. 
One key element of our analysis is exogenous enforcement. Clearly strategic en-
forcement would add a particular type of interaction between the bookie and anti-
corruption authority. But in light of our present analysis it can be said that even if 
enforcement is made clever, it would hardly pick an even contest to investigate, because 
its outcome is "meant" to go either way. We can also see that in many cases of interest, the 
optimal odds by the bookie give away whether the bookie is trying to orchestrate match-
fixing. Shouldn't then the bookie be prosecuted as well? Particularly when match-fixing 
is encouraged, he is as much culpable as the match-fixer. 
It is also well known, and often discussed in the public media, how bookmakers 
can tell whether some unusually high wagers or betting activity and even the odds 
pattern (where odds are generated endogenously as in parimutuel setting) can be the 
tell-tale sign of fixing (see footnote 7). But then shouldn't the enforcement's investigation 
policy be accordingly more sophisticated to extract information from market data? 
In the real world, there may also be a lack of will, and appropriate regulation 
and coordination among different agencies. A random report on the Internet about 
football governance by the sport's highest body, FIFA, expresses disappointment in the 
following (source: http://www.fifa.com/aboutfifa/organisation/footballgovernance/ 
news/newsid=2001014/index.html): 
"In football, a national association can sanction a member of the football family 
if they are found guilty of contravening the legal, football framework....But for people 
outside of football, currently the custodial sentences imposed are too weak, and offer 
little to deter someone from getting involved in match-fixing." </p>

<p>21. Recall, for naive bettors, both teams being corruptible may imply less match-fixing. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>Our analysis highlights that enforcement in sports betting is a complex task requir-
ing sophisticated guesswork about what the bookie is trying to do and what he knows, 
and there are also legislative challenges. </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma 1: First consider the case of no IP. Maximizing the bookie's payoff as 
given in (3) we obtain the following first-order conditions: </p>

<p>∂ E 
∂π 1 
= y −1 + 
p 1 
π </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>= 0, and 
∂ E 0 
∂π 2 
= y −1 + 
p 2 
π </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>= 0. </p>

<p>These determine the unconstrained optimal prices for the bookie: π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = 
√ p 1 , π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 = 
√ p 2 . </p>

<p>Clearly, the Dutch-book constraint is satisfied, as 
√ p 1 ≥ p 1 , 
√ p 2 ≥ p 2 . If team 1 is cor-</p>

<p>ruptible, then π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 must be at least φ 1 , hence π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 = max{ 
√ p 2 , φ 1 }. If not, then π </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 = 
√ p 2 . </p>

<p>Derivation of bribe inducement profit when only team 1 is corruptible. From 
equation (5) we can write the ticket 1 profit as E B I (Ticket 1) = y(1 − π 1 )(1 − </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>). 
From equation (6) substitute π 1 = p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 assuming λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 &gt; p 1 (i.e., the constraint on 
π 1 does not bind), and obtain </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 1) = y(1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 ) 
2 ; 
( A 1 ) </p>

<p>when λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 &lt; p 1 (i.e., the constraint on π 1 does bind), we have 
E B I (Ticket 1) = yμ 1 p 2 (1 − λ 1 ). 
(A2) </p>

<p>Table A1. 
Critical Range of y: 1 </p>

<p>w + α 1 (f + f I ) = 0.05 
w + α 1 (f + f I ) = 0.06 </p>

<p>λ 1 </p>

<p>1ȳ </p>

<p>λ 1 </p>

<p>1ȳ </p>

<p>0 
(0.29, 0.83) 
0.88 
0 
(0.33, 0.77) 
0.855 
0.05 
(0.32, 0.81) 
0.87 
0.05 
(0.44, 0.725) 
0.845 
0.10 
(0.37, 0.78) 
0.86 
0.10 
(0.57, 0.62) 
0.83 
0.15 
(0.44, 0.73) 
0.85 
0.15 
null 
0.82 
0.19 
(0.60, 0.62) 
0.838 
0.19 
null 
0.805 
0.20 
null 
0.835 
0.20 
null 
0.805 </p>

<p>Table A2. 
Critical Range of y: 2 </p>

<p>w + α 1 (f + f I ) = 0.05 
w + α 1 (f + f I ) = 0.06 </p>

<p>λ 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>λ 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
(0.16, 0.925) 
0 
(0.19, 0.909) 
0.05 
(0.17, 0.922) 
0.05 
(0.2, 0.904) 
0.10 
(0.18, 0.917) 
0.10 
(0.215, 0.895) 
0.15 
(0.19, 0.91) 
0.15 
(0.23, 0.886) 
0.20 
(0.2, 0.9) 
0.20 
(0.27, 0.878) </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table A3. 
Critical Range of y: 3 </p>

<p>w + α 1 (f + f I ) = 0.05 </p>

<p>3 
3 
3 </p>

<p>λ 
at μ = 0.05 
at μ = 0.10 
at μ = 0.15 </p>

<p>0 
(0.11, 0.88) 
(0.21, 0.87) 
(0.29, 0.87) 
0.10 
(0.13, 0.86) 
(0.24, 0.85) 
(0.33, 0.84) 
0.15 
(0.14, 0.85) 
(0.26, 0.84) 
(0.36, 0.83) 
0.30 
(0.22, 0.76) 
(0.40, 0.75) 
(0.55, 0.70) 
0.40 
(0.37, 0.61) 
null 
null 
0.45 
null 
null 
null </p>

<p>On the other hand, as the IP bets on team 2, ticket 2 profit is </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 2) = y(1 − π 2 ) 1 − 
1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 
π 2 
+ zμ 1 1 − 
1 − λ 1 p 1 
π 2 </p>

<p>= y 1 − π 2 − 
1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 (z/y)(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) 
π 2 
+ 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 </p>

<p>z 
y 
. </p>

<p>Substituting λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = μ 1 λ 1 + (1 − μ 1 ) and z = 1 − y in the third term above rewrite it as </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 2) = y (1 − π 2 ) − 
1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 (z/y)(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) 
π 2 </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. </p>

<p>From equation (6) substitute π 2 = 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 (z/y)(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) into the above 
and obtain </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 2) = y 1 − 2 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 </p>

<p>z 
y 
(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. </p>

<p>Further, we can simplify 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 + μ 1 </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) to be p 2 + </p>

<p>μ 1 
y </p>

<p>{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} and 
write </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 2) = y 1 − 2 p 2 + 
μ 1 
y 
{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. 
( A 3 ) </p>

<p>Now suppose π 2 is constrained to be ϕ 1 . Then ticket 2 profit is </p>

<p>E B I (Ticket 2) = y 1 − φ 1 − 
p 2 + </p>

<p>μ 1 
y </p>

<p>{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} </p>

<p>φ 1 </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. 
( A 4 ) </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>In order to calculate total profit we need to consider two cases depending on the 
size of λ 1 . 
Case1 :λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>andμ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>&lt; 1. This is the case presented in equations (9)-(11). 
When neither of the two prices are constrained, the total bribe inducement profit is given 
by the sum of the profit expressions given in equations (A1) and (A3) as follows: </p>

<p>E B I = y 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ y 1 − 2 p 2 + 
μ 1 
y 
{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. 
( A 5 ) </p>

<p>Substitute p 1 = 1/2, and with some rearrangement of terms obtain equation (9), referred 
as E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I . 
Next, consider π 1 to be unconstrained and π 2 to be constrained. The total profit is 
now given by the sum of (A1) and (A4), which yields </p>

<p>E B I = y 1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ y 1 − φ 1 − 
p 2 + </p>

<p>μ 1 
y </p>

<p>{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} </p>

<p>φ 1 </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. 
( A 6 ) </p>

<p>Once again substitute p 1 = p 2 = 1/2 and rearrange terms to obtain E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I as given in 
equation (10). 
Finally, when both prices are constrained we need to sum up the profits given in 
equations (A2) and (A4) to derive the total profit, which is </p>

<p>E B I = yμ 1 p 2 (1 − λ 1 ) + y 1 − φ 1 − 
p 2 + </p>

<p>μ 1 
y </p>

<p>{ p 1 (y − λ 1 ) + 1 − y} </p>

<p>φ 1 </p>

<p>+ p 2 + μ 1 
1 − y 
y 
+ p 1 (1 − λ 1 ) 
. 
( A 7 ) </p>

<p>Set p 1 = 1/2 in the above to obtain E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I in equation (11). This completes the derivation 
of equations (9)-(11). 
Case2 :λ ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>orμ 1 &lt; 1 ≤ </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>. This case arises if λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. Here the constraint on π 1 
never binds. Total profit from bribe inducement will be E B I = E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I at all μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ] 
as before, and E B I = E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I at all μ 1 ∈ (μ 1 , 1]. 
There are two other possible cases. The case of </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>&lt; 1 &lt;μ 1 does not apply, 
because the constraint on π 2 will always bind at some μ 1 (given p 1 = 1/2). Henceμ 1 is 
always less than 1. Finally, the case of </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>&lt;μ 1 &lt; 1 is ruled out by Assumption 3. 
|| 
Next, we develop two lemmas for subsequent use in the proof of Proposition 1. </p>

<p>Lemma A1: If y ∈ 1 , then the profit expression E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I is increasing in μ 1 ∈ (0, </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>] 
when λ 1 &lt; 1/2, and increasing over the entire interval μ 1 ∈ (0, 1] when λ 1 ≥ 1/2. Also, atμ 1 , 
E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma A1: First note that E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I is the highest B I profit at μ 1 ∈ 
[μ 1 , min{ </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>, 1}]. But E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I is also feasible over μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ), because setting π 2 = φ 1 </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>induces bribery at this range of μ 1 ; but the bookie does better by setting π 2 = 
1 − λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 p 1 (&lt; φ 1 ). Hence we can check the slope of E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I over its entire feasible range. 
Consider E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I as given in equation (10) and differentiate with respect to μ 1 : </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 
B I </p>

<p>∂μ 1 
= y (1 − λ 1 ) 
1 
2λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>− 
1 
2 
+ 
2 − y(1 + λ 1 ) 
2y 
− 
2 − y − λ 1 
2yφ 1 
. </p>

<p>This derivative is positive if </p>

<p>(1 − λ 1 ) 
√ 
2yφ 1 
y(2φ 1 − 1) + 2(1 − φ 1 ) − λ 1 
&gt; λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 . </p>

<p>The right-hand side expression is largest (= 1) when μ 1 → 0. So we try to identify 
the values of y such that the left-hand side expression is strictly greater than 1. If such 
values of y are found, then clearly at any μ 1 the above inequality will hold. For that we 
need </p>

<p>y &gt; 
2(1 − φ 1 ) − λ 1 </p>

<p>1 − φ 1 
√ 
2[ 
√ 
2 − (1 − λ 1 )] 
. </p>

<p>But note that φ 1 is also a function of y (via 1 which depends on z). Let us denote the 
right-hand side expression as K (y), and write J (y) = y − K (y). 
Higher y means lower z and higher 1 , which in turn implies lower φ 1 . In particular 
at y = 0, 0 &lt; K (0) &lt; 1; on the other hand, when y → 1, φ 1 → ∞ and by L'Hospital's 
theorem K (1) = </p>

<p>2 
2− 
√ 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>&gt; 1. So by Intermediate value theorem there must be at least </p>

<p>two values of y, say y 0 and y 1 , such that for all y ∈ 1 = (y 0 , y 1 ) we must have J (y) &gt; 0 
(see Definition 1); in fact, as footnote 14 asserts, the {y 0 , y 1 } pair is unique. Thus, if y ∈ 1 , 
at all μ 1 , E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I will be increasing. 
Now note from equation (10) that, if E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I were evaluated at μ 1 = 0, it would be 
just equal to E B P . Then by the positive slope of E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I it is implied that atμ 1 we must 
have E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . </p>

<p>Lemma A2: If y ∈ 1 , then E B I is increasing in μ 1 at all μ 1 &gt;μ 1 . </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma A2: Consider firstμ 1 ≤ </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>(&lt; 1), where E B I is given by E </p>

<p>2 
B I </p>

<p>as in equation (10). By Lemma A1 we know E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I is increasing in μ 1 if y ∈ 1 . 
Next, consider μ 1 ∈ ( </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>, 1], where E B I is given by E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I as in equation (11). 
We know E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I = E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I at μ 1 = 1/[2(1 − λ 1 )]. Therefore, all we need is to ensure that 
E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I is increasing in μ 1 in this range. We obtain </p>

<p>∂ E </p>

<p>3 
B I </p>

<p>∂μ 1 
= y 
1 
2φ 1 
− 2 + 1 − 
2 − λ 1 
2φ 1 
&gt; 0, 
if y &gt; 
2 − 2φ 1 − λ 1 
1 − 2λ 1 φ 1 
. </p>

<p>This restriction is automatically satisfied if y ∈ 1 , because </p>

<p>2−2φ 1 −λ 1 
1−2λ 1 φ 1 </p>

<p>&lt; </p>

<p>2(1−φ 1 )−λ 1 
1−φ 1 
√ 
2[ 
√ 
2−(1−λ 1 )] </p>

<p>. Therefore, E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I is also upward-sloping if y ∈ 1 . 
The case of λ 1 ≥ 1/2 is trivial. Here E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I is not relevant; E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I applies to the whole 
range of [μ 1 , 1]. As y ∈ 1 guarantees increasing E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I , the claim is true. </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>Proof of Proposition 1: </p>

<p>(i) The proof of this part involves only E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I . Recall, </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I = y 1 − </p>

<p>λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ y 
3 
2 
+ μ 1 
2 − y(1 + λ 1 ) 
2y 
− 2 1 + μ 1 
2 − λ 1 
y 
− 1 
∀ μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ]. </p>

<p>As μ 1 → 0, E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I → y(3 − 2 </p>

<p>√ </p>

<p>2) = E 0 . Now because p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, we must have E B P &lt; 
E 0 . Then as μ 1 → 0, E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . Hence, at all μ 1 quite close to zero, E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . 
That proves part (i). 
(ii) There are two ranges of λ 1 to consider: λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Before we consider each of these cases, let us first note that E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I is decreasing in 
μ 1 at sufficiently small values of μ 1 . </p>

<p>Deriving </p>

<p>∂ E </p>

<p>1 
B I </p>

<p>∂μ 1 </p>

<p>and then letting μ 1 → 0 (i.e., λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 → 1) we obtain (with some simpli-
fication): </p>

<p>∂ E </p>

<p>1 
B I </p>

<p>∂μ 1 μ 1 →0 
= 
1 − y </p>

<p>2 
√ 
2 
2λ 1 − (4 − 2 
√ 
2) &lt; 0 at all λ 1 ∈ [0, 1]. </p>

<p>Case 1 :λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>andμ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>(&lt; 1). The expected profit from bribe prevention at 
p 1 = 1/2 is given in equation (8). The B I profit is given in equations (9)-(11), with the 
underlying prices as </p>

<p>For μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ], 
π 1 = λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 /2, π 2 = </p>

<p>2 − λ </p>

<p> *  
1 </p>

<p>2 
+ μ 1 
z 
y </p>

<p>(2 − λ 1 ) 
2 
; </p>

<p>For μ 1 ∈ μ 1 , 
1 
2(1 − λ 1 ) 
, 
π 1 = λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 /2, π 2 = φ 1 (1/2) ; </p>

<p>For μ 1 ∈ 
1 
2(1 − λ 1 ) 
, 1 , 
π 1 = 1/2, π 2 = φ 1 (1/2) . </p>

<p>Now recall equations (9)-(11). It turns out that comparing E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I with E B P is 
cumbersome; therefore, we will take an indirect route by comparing E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I with E B P 
and then compare E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I with E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I (for μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ]). We should note that when μ 1 ∈ 
(0,μ 1 ], the bookie could have chosen for ticket 2 any price from the interval [ p 2 , φ 1 ], but 
he chose π 2 = 1 − p 1 λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 + μ 1 </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>(1 − λ 1 p 1 ) &lt; φ 1 . Therefore, it must be that E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I ≥ E </p>

<p>2 
B I </p>

<p>at all μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ], if E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I was evaluated in this interval. 
Comparing E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I and E B P we see that the latter is constant in μ 1 , whereas the 
former is increasing in μ 1 (refer to Lemma A1). Moreover, as μ 1 → 0 we have </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I = E B P = y 3 − </p>

<p>√ 
2 − φ 1 − 
1 
2φ 1 
. </p>

<p>Thus, E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P at all μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ]. Then as E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I ≥ E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I at all μ 1 ∈ (0,μ 1 ], we 
must have E B I &gt; E B P . Further, by Lemma A2 E B I is increasing at all μ 1 &gt;μ 1 . 
Therefore, E B I &gt; E B P at all μ 1 &gt;μ 1 as well. 
Case 2 : λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>orμ 1 &lt; 1 ≤ </p>

<p>1 
2(1−λ 1 ) </p>

<p>. In this case, E B I = E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I at all μ 1 ∈ (μ 1 , 1]. 
Here E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I does not apply. We know that if y ∈ 1 , E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I will be an increasing function </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>of μ 1 (refer to Lemma A1), and E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P at all μ 1 ≥μ 1 . At μ 1 &lt;μ 1 , we must also 
have E B I ≡ E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P by the same reasoning given in case 1 above. Hence, at all 
μ 1 bribe inducement will be optimal. </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 2: </p>

<p>(i) Suppose λ 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and consider E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I − E 0 at μ 1 = 1. After simplification the expres-
sion for E </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B I − E 0 &gt; 0 (i.e., E B I − E 0 &gt; 0) becomes </p>

<p>y[2 
√ 
2 − 1 − p 1 − λ 1 ] &gt; yφ 1 + (1 − λ 1 p 1 ) 1 . </p>

<p>At p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>the LHS expression becomes y[2 
√ 
2 − </p>

<p>3 
2 </p>

<p>− λ 1 ], and the RHS expression 
becomes </p>

<p>L(y) = (2 − λ 1 ) 
y 
2 + (2 − λ 1 ) 1 
+ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
, </p>

<p>which we have introduced in Definition 2. So if y ∈ 2 then the above inequality 
holds. We know from Proposition 1 that atμ 1 , we have E B I &lt; E 0 . Then by the 
Intermediate value theorem there must exist a critical μ 1 , namelyμ 1 ∈ (μ 1 , 1) such 
that at all μ 1 &gt;μ 1 we have E B I &gt; E 0 . That is, bribe encouragement takes place. 
(ii) For λ 1 ≥ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>the proof is identical, except that now we consider E </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B I − E 0 at 
μ 1 = 1. </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 3: Given p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 , we have E B P &lt; E 0 . Further, given 
y ∈ 3 , the unconstrained prices given in equation (14) solve the B I problem. The 
resultant B I profit at p 1 = 1/2 is given by equation (15), whereas the B P profit is given 
by equation (12). We have already checked that E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I is declining in μ, and at μ close to 
0, E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &gt; E B P . At μ = 1/2 by setting E </p>

<p>U </p>

<p>B I &lt; E B P and rearranging terms we get 
2 </p>

<p>2−λz 
y </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>z 
y </p>

<p>&gt; 2φ + </p>

<p>1 
φ </p>

<p>, which is precisely our Assumption 4. 
Hence, there must exist a unique critical valueμ ∈ (0, 1/2), such that at all μ ≤μ 
we have E B I ≥ E B P and at all μ &gt;μ we have E B I &lt; E B P . B I is optimal up 
toμ. </p>

<p>Simulation of the critical ranges of y-refer Tables A1, A2, and A3. </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma 3: It is obvious that it will never be optimal to set π 1 &lt; a and π 2 &lt; 1 − b. 
If π 1 is set below a , the expected profit from ticket 1 is y(1 − </p>

<p>p 1 
π 1 </p>

<p>) which can be increased 
by raising π 1 toward a . Similarly, if π 2 &lt; 1 − b, E 0 = y(1 − </p>

<p>p 2 
π 2 </p>

<p>) can be improved by 
raising π 2 . Hence, π 1 ≥ max{ p 1 , a } and π 2 ≥ max{ p 2 , 1 − b}. Next, to show existence and 
uniqueness, we need to consider three cases, depending on the range of p 1 . </p>

<p>Case 1 [ p 1 ∈ [a , b]]. Consider equation (17). For any given p 1 neither π 1 = a nor π 1 = b 
can be a solution. If π 1 = a , the bracketed expression is </p>

<p>1−G(a ) 
g(a ) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>( p 1 −a )a 
p 1 </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>1 
g(a ) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>( p 1 −a )a 
p 1 </p>

<p>&gt; 0 (and infinitely large if g(a ) is arbitrarily small). Similarly, if π 1 = </p>

<p>b, the bracketed expression is </p>

<p>1−G(b) 
g(b </p>

<p>) − </p>

<p>(b− p 1 )b 
p 1 </p>

<p>. Because b &gt; p 1 and G(b) = 1, 
the sign of the bracketed term depends on whether g(b) &gt; 0 or g(b) = 0. If 
g(b) &gt; 0 then the term is clearly negative. If g(b) = 0 then by L'Hospital rule 
lim x→b </p>

<p>1−G(x) 
g(x) </p>

<p>= − lim x→b </p>

<p>g(b) 
g (b) </p>

<p>= 0 because g (b) &gt; 0 due to our assumption that 
g(q ) &gt; 0 at all q ∈ (a , b). Hence, here too the bracketed term is negative. Hence, 
by the Intermediate value theorem, there must be a unique π 1 ∈ (a , b) such that </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>



<p>∂ E 0 
∂π 1 </p>

<p>= 0. Similar reasoning applies for the unique interior solution of π 2 with 
respect to equation (18). 
Case 2 [ p 1 &lt; a ]. Here ticket 2 will not be sold, because p 2 &gt; 1 − a . For ticket 1, π 1 is 
either given by equation (17) or π 1 = a , whichever is greater. 
Case 3 [ p 1 &gt; b]. Here ticket 1 sale is zero. For ticket 2, the solution given by equation (18) 
must not fall below 1 − b, and the maximum of the two will be optimal. </p>

<p>Next, we consider (weak) monotonicity of prices. We know that each price is 
constant over at some values of p 1 . Specifically, at p 1 &lt; a we have π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 = a over a range of 
p 1 , and at p 1 &gt; b we have π 2 = 1 − b over a range of p 1 . But when (π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 , π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) is given by 
equations (17) and (18), strict monotonicity holds due to Assumption 5, which we show 
as follows. From equation (17) we can derive: </p>

<p>∂ 
2 E 0 </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>∂ p 1 
+ 
∂ 
2 E 0 </p>

<p>∂π 1 ∂ p 1 
= 0, or 
∂ 
2 E 0 </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>∂ p 1 
+ 
(π </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>1 ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>= 0. </p>

<p>Because </p>

<p>∂ 
2 E 
∂π </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>&lt; 0 by the second-order condition, we must have </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>∂ p 1 </p>

<p>&gt; 0. </p>

<p>Symmetric argument establishes </p>

<p>∂π </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>∂ p 2 </p>

<p>&gt; 0 from equation (18). </p>

<p>For the markups consider equations (17)-(18). By Assumption 5, </p>

<p>1−G(π 1 ) 
g(π 1 ) </p>

<p>decreases </p>

<p>with p 1 . Then it follows that </p>

<p>(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 </p>

<p>π 1 also decreases in p 1 . Because π 1 is increasing in p 1 , </p>

<p>π 1 − p 1 
p 1 </p>

<p>must be falling. Similarly, from equation (18) it follows that </p>

<p>(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 </p>

<p>π 2 must fall if π 2 </p>

<p>rises, and π 2 rises if p 2 rises; therefore, the fall in </p>

<p>(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 </p>

<p>π 2 must be attributable to </p>

<p>π 2 − p 2 
p 2 </p>

<p>. 
This completes the proof. </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 4: </p>

<p>(i) To establish that E 0 ( p 1 ) is (nearly) U-shaped we determine its slope in three ranges 
of p 1 : p 1 &lt; a , p 1 &gt; b and p 1 ∈ [a , b]. It is straightforward to check that at p 1 &lt; a , 
E 0 ( p 1 ) = −y/a if π 1 = a and E 0 ( p 1 ) = −y(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 )π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 if π 1 = π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 . Similarly, at p 1 &gt; 
b, E 0 ( p 1 ) = y/(1 − b) if π 2 = 1 − b and E 0 ( p 1 ) = y(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 )π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 if π 2 = π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 . 
For p 1 ∈ [a , b], consider the slope function k( p 1 ) (equation (19)). At p 1 = a , k( p 1 ) = 
− </p>

<p>1−G(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (a )) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (a ) </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>G(a ) 
1−a </p>

<p>= − </p>

<p>1−G(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (a )) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 (a ) </p>

<p>&lt; 0 as π 2 = 1 − a . At p 1 = b, k( p 1 ) = − </p>

<p>1−G(b) 
b </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>G(1−π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 (b)) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 (b) </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>G(1−π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 (b)) 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 (b) </p>

<p>&gt; 0. </p>

<p>Next, to show that k( p 1 ) is an increasing function, we differentiate the terms given 
in (19): </p>

<p>∂ 
∂ p 1 </p>

<p>1 − G(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ) 
π </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>= − 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 g(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ) + (1 − G(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 )) 
(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ( p 1 ) &lt; 0, </p>

<p>∂ 
∂ p 1 </p>

<p>G(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) 
π </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>= − 
π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 g(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) + G(1 − π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) 
(π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>π </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ( p 1 ) &gt; 0, </p>

<p>because π 1 ( p 1 ) &gt; 0 and π 2 ( p 1 ) &lt; 0. By combining these two expressions, we obtain: </p>

<p>k ( p 1 ) ≡ 
∂ 
2 E (π </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>1 , π </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>2 ) 
∂ p </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>= − 
∂ 
∂ p 1 </p>

<p>1 − G(π </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>1 ) 
π </p>

<p>h 
1 </p>

<p>+ 
∂ 
∂ p 1 </p>

<p>G(1 − π </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>2 ) 
π </p>

<p>h 
2 </p>

<p>&gt; 0. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Now, as k( p 1 ) is strictly increasing in p 1 , and k(a ) &lt; 0 and k(b) &gt; 0, there must be a 
unique p 1 between a and b at which k( p 1 ) = 0. This proves the claim that p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 is unique. 
It gives minimum profit because E 0 (.) is convex (as confirmed by k ( p 1 ) &gt; 0). 
Assume symmetry of g(q ) around </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, and consider three cases. 
(ii) Case a + b = 1. g(q ) is symmetric around </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. At p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, by symmetry π 1 = π 2 and 
also g(π 1 ) = g(1 − π 2 ) and therefore, 1 − G(π 1 ) = G(1 − π 2 ); hence we must have 
k( p 1 ) = 0 ⇒ p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 = 1/2. 
(iii) For the remaining two cases, impose condition (20). The proof here involves eval-
uating k( p 1 ) at two points-p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>. For that, we make use of the 
optimal price conditions by substituting </p>

<p>1−G(π 1 ) 
π 1 </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 </p>

<p>g(π 1 ) from equation (17), </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>G(1−π 2 ) 
π 2 </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 </p>

<p>g(1 − π 2 ) from equation (18), into equation (20), to rewrite k( p 1 ) 
as </p>

<p>k( p 1 ) = y − 
(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 
g(π 1 ) + 
(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 
g(1 − π 2 ) . </p>

<p>We also note that from the symmetry of g(.) it follows that g(π 1 ) = g(a + b − π 1 ) and 
g(1 − π 2 ) = g(a + b − 1 + π 2 ). Now consider each case. 
Case a + b &gt; 1. Here the even contest ( p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>) is to the left of the midpoint of 
the distribution, as majority of the bettors believe team 1 to be favorite. Therefore, 
π 1 = π 2 at some p 1 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and π 1 &gt; π 2 thereafter. Now first evaluate k( p 1 ) at p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, 
where </p>

<p>sign of k( p 1 ) = sign of [−(π 1 − p 1 )g(π 1 ) + (π 2 − p 2 )g(1 − π 2 )] . </p>

<p>As π 1 &gt; π 2 , the sign of k( p 1 ) critically depends on whether g(π 1 ) &gt; g(1 − π 2 ). Because 
π 1 &gt; π 2 &gt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, we must have 1 − π 2 &lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>where g (.) &gt; 0, because p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>is to the left 
of the midpoint </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>. This implies that due to the symmetry of g(.) at p 1 = a + b − 
(1 − π 2 ), the density function g(.) must be decreasing. However, we cannot ascertain 
whether π 1 would be greater or less than </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>. As long as π 1 ≤ a + b − 1 + π 2 , or 
π 1 − π 2 &lt; a + b − 1, g(π 1 ) ≥ g(1 − π 2 ). Then k( p 1 ) &lt; 0 at p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. This confirms the 
upper bound on π 1 − π 2 as specified in (21). 
Now evaluate k( p 1 ) at p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, at which p 1 &gt; p 2 . Here, </p>

<p>sign of k( p 1 ) = sign of − 
(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 
g(π 1 ) + 
(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 
g(1 − π 2 ) . </p>

<p>By our assumption, </p>

<p>(π 1 − p 1 ) 
p 1 </p>

<p>&lt; </p>

<p>(π 2 − p 2 ) 
p 2 </p>

<p>. Because π 1 &gt; </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, g(π 1 ) must be declining at 
π 1 , whereas g(1 − π 2 ) must be upward-sloping at 1 − π 2 (because π 2 &gt; 1 − </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>). 
Also as g(1 − π 2 ) = g(a + b − 1 + π 2 ) by the symmetry of g(q ), g(π 1 ) &lt; g(1 − π 2 ) if 
π 1 &gt; a + b − 1 + π 2 . This is what is given as the lower bound on π 1 − π 2 in (21). Then 
at p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, k( p 1 ) &gt; 0. Hence, p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 must lie between </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>. 
Case a + b &lt; 1. Here </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>&lt; </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>and π 1 &lt; π 2 at all p 1 ≤ </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>. Follow the same reasoning 
as above and make use of the markup assumption. At p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, g(π 1 ) &gt; g(1 − π 2 ) 
if π 1 − π 2 &lt; a + b − 1; this makes k( p 1 ) &lt; 0 at p 1 = </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>as specified in condition 
(22). Similarly, at p 1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>, g(π 1 ) &lt; g(1 − π 2 ) if π 1 − π 2 &gt; a + b − 1; then k( p 1 ) &gt; 0. 
Therefore, k( p 1 ) = 0 at some p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 ∈ ( </p>

<p>a +b 
2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Match-Fixing in a Monopoly Betting Market </p>





</text></tei>