<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fcaje.12091" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:44+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Empirical studies of bilateral foreign direct investment (FDI) activity show 
substantial differences in specifications with little agreement on the set of included co-
variates. We use Bayesian statistical techniques that allow one to select from a large set of 
candidates those variables most likely to be determinants of FDI activity. The variables 
with consistently high inclusion probabilities include traditional gravity variables, cultural 
distance factors, relative labour endowments and trade agreements. There is little support 
for multilateral trade openness, most host-country business costs, host-country infras-
tructure and host-country institutions. Our results suggest that many covariates found 
significant by previous studies are not robust. </p>

<p>Résumé. Les déterminants de l'investissement directà l'étranger. Lesétudes empiriques 
des déterminants des activités d'investissement direct bilatéralà l'étranger ont des 
spécifications substantiellement différentes et peu d'accord sur les variables co-reliées 
incluses. On utilise des techniques statistiques bayesiennes qui permettent de balayer un 
vaste ensemble de variablesà la recherche de celles qui sont davantage susceptibles d'être 
des déterminants des activités d'investissement directà l'étranger. Les variables qui se 
retrouvent de manière régulière dans la liste de haute probabilité d'impact sont les vari-
ables reliéesà la gravité, les facteurs liésà la distance culturelle, les dotations relatives en 
facteur travail, et les accords commerciaux. Il y a peu de support pour des variables comme 
l'ouverture au commerce multilatéral, la plupart des coûts d'affaires, les infrastructures 
et les institutions dans les pays hôtes. Ces résultats suggèrent que plusieurs co-variations 
qu'on a jugées significatives dans lesétudes antérieures ne sont pas robustes. </p>

<p>Empirical analyses of the factors determining foreign direct investment (FDI) 
across countries have employed a variety of econometric specifications. Many 
previous studies of cross-country FDI activity have used a gravity equation, 
which controls mainly for the economic size of the parent and host countries, the </p>

<p>We thank Theo Eicher, Gordon Hanson, Kathryn Russ, Deborah Swenson, anonymous referees 
and session participants at a Western Economic Association session for helpful comments. 
Blonigen is also a research associate of the National Bureau of Economic Research. Any errors 
or omissions are completely our own. 
Corresponding author: J. Piger, jpiger@uoregon.edu </p>

<p>Canadian Journal of Economics/Revue canadienne d'économique, Vol. 47, No. 3 
August 2014. Printed in Canada / Août 2014. Imprimé au Canada </p>

<p>0008-4085 / 14 / 775-812 / 
C Canadian Economics Association </p>



<p>geographic distance separating the countries and proxies for certain economic 
frictions. Like trade flows, this specification does a reasonably good job of fitting 
the observed data, but leaves one wondering if such a parsimonious specification 
captures all relevant factors. 
Recent papers by Carr, Markusen and Maskus (2001; CMM) and Bergstrand  and Egger (2007) have developed theoretical models of multinational enterprise's 
(MNE's) foreign investment decisions that suggest additional possible factors that 
determine FDI patterns. These studies point out a number of modifications to a 
standard gravity model that may be necessary to accurately explain FDI patterns. 
First, while gravity variables may adequately capture "horizontal" motivations 
for FDI, where firms look to replicate their operations in other countries to be 
more proximate to consumers in those markets, additional controls are necessary 
to allow for "vertical" motivations of FDI, where firms look for low-cost locations 
for labour-intensive production. For example, these studies introduce measures 
of relative labour endowments in the host country with the expectation that 
countries with relatively high shares of unskilled labour will be attractive locations 
for MNEs due to lower wages. In addition, these studies show that FDI decisions 
by MNEs are complex enough that interactions between key variables (e.g., 
GDP and skilled labour endowments) may be necessary to account for nonlinear 
effects of these variables on FDI patterns. Head and Ries (2008) differs from 
these previous studies by modelling FDI as arising from decisions by firms to 
acquire and control foreign assets (i.e., cross-border mergers and acquisitions), 
rather than development of new (or greenfield) plants. Their analysis of FDI 
patterns highlights the potential role of common culture and language between 
countries. 
While these prior studies have been important in deepening our understanding 
of the factors that determine cross-country FDI patterns, they have generally 
focused on regression models involving specific sets of covariates determined by 
the researcher and the particular theoretical framework for FDI they chose to 
examine. By conditioning on a particular regression model specification, this 
practice ignores uncertainty regarding the model specification itself, which can 
have dramatic consequences on inference. 
1 Most notably, inference regarding the 
effects of included covariates can depend critically on what other covariates are 
included versus excluded. 
In this paper, we take a Bayesian approach to confront uncertainty regarding 
the appropriate set of covariates to include in a regression model explaining 
FDI activity. From a Bayesian perspective, incorporating such uncertainty is 
conceptually straightforward. The choice of covariates, or "model," is treated as 
an additional parameter that lies in the space of potential models, which allows us 
to compute the posterior probability that each potential model is the true model 
that generated the data. Posterior distributions for objects of interest, such as </p>

<p>1 For discussion and examples, see Leamer 1978, Hodges 1987, Moulton 1991, Draper 1995, 
Kass and Raftery 1995, Raftery 1996 and Fernandez, Ley and Steel 2001a. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 777 </p>

<p>the effect of a particular covariate, are then averaged across alternative models, 
using the posterior model probabilities as weights. This procedure, known as 
Bayesian Model Averaging (BMA), produces inferences that are not conditioned 
on a particular model. 
To be clear, we are taking a purely empirical approach to determine the 
correlates with observed FDI patterns. As we discuss in the next section, there 
is very little consistency in the empirical FDI literature about the covariates one 
should use when empirically modeling cross-country FDI. We view this paper as 
a first step in pointing out these inconsistencies and providing evidence of the 
empirically robust determinants of FDI. 
Although conceptually straightforward, BMA is practically difficult when the 
set of possible models is large, as direct calculation of posterior probabilities for 
all models becomes infeasible. In our application, we have a large set of potential 
covariates, which yields an extremely large set of possible models (&gt; 7 × 10 
16 ). 
To sidestep this difficulty, we use techniques designed to obtain random draws of 
models from the probability distribution defined by the posterior model probabil-
ities. Such draws are made possible even when the posterior model probabilities 
are unknown by using the MC 
3 algorithm of Madigan and York (1995). These 
random model draws are then used to construct estimates of the posterior model 
probabilities. </p>

<p>2   Our set of potential FDI determinants is meant to be comprehensive and 
includes a combination of covariates proposed by the previously mentioned 
studies, as well as other prior literature on FDI. We examine mainly cross-
sectional patterns for the year 2000. 
2 We examine both levels and log-linear 
regressions, placing more weight on our results for the log-linear regressions 
because most previous studies have used a logarithmic transformation to address 
skewness in the FDI variable. We also examine three measures of FDI-FDI 
stock, affiliate sales and cross-border mergers and acquisitions activity-in order 
to better compare with a broader set of prior studies. At the end, we also explore 
a specification that first differences observations across the years 1990 and 2000 
to control for bilateral country-pair fixed effects as well as a negative binomial 
specification to better model the nature of our dependent variable. 
Our analysis indicates that many of the covariates used in prior FDI studies 
(and often found statistically significant) do not have a high probability of in-
clusion in the true FDI determinants model once we consider a comprehensive 
set of potential determinants using BMA. A fairly parsimonious set of covari-
ates is suggested by our analysis. The covariates with consistently high inclusion 
probabilities include traditional gravity variables, cultural distance factors, rela-
tive labour endowments and trade agreements. Variables with little support for 
inclusion are multilateral trade openness, most host-country business costs, host-
country infrastructure (including credit markets) and host-country institutions. </p>

<p>2 Focusing on the year 2000 maximized our available sample size by allowing us to use datasets 
that have not been updated recently along with datasets that began being collected in 2000. </p>



<p>A few variables that have rarely been included in prior FDI studies, namely 
host-country remoteness, parent-country real GDP per capita and host is an 
oil-exporting country, have surprisingly high inclusion probabilities. 
The remainder of the paper proceeds as follows. The next section reviews 
previous empirical literature on the determinants of FDI and makes the case 
that the appropriate model specification for explaining FDI patterns is far from 
settled. Section 3 then lays out the BMA methodology we use to assess model 
uncertainty. Section 4 describes the data and its sources, while section 5 reports 
the results and compares to the existing literature. Section 6 concludes. </p>

<p>2. Prior FDI literature </p>

<p>There is little consensus on how to empirically model bilateral FDI patterns, 
with many past empirical FDI papers using a base model consisting of gravity-
type covariates (country-level GDP and distance) because of its popularity for 
explaining trade flows. As mentioned in the introduction, there have been a few 
recent efforts to develop specifications based on theoretical models-namely the 
knowledge-capital (K-K) model developed by James Markusen and co-authors, 
which was brought to data in CMM (2001), Bergstrand and Egger's (2007) model 
incorporating physical capital and Head and Ries' (2008) model of acquisition 
FDI. 
There is little consistency in the covariates that are postulated to explain world-
wide FDI patterns across these three papers. To see this, the first three columns 
of table 1 lists the covariates used in each of these papers. Distance between 
countries is the only covariate common to all three studies. There are 22 different 
covariates between the three studies, even though each study averages only about 
10 covariates. While all three specifications postulate a role for economic size 
and trade frictions as driving forces of FDI, it is surprising how differently they 
construct and define variables meant to proxy for these common factors. 
Of course, there have been many other papers that have empirically examined 
FDI patterns using specifications that differ from these three papers. Columns 4 
through 8 of table 1 list the covariates used in a number of other highly regarded 
recent papers. Across these eight studies in columns 1 through 8, there are a 
combined 47 covariates. However, no covariate is shared by all eight studies and, 
on average, a covariate is used in only 1.7 of the eight studies. Interestingly, almost 
85% of the covariates included in these 8 studies are found to be statistically 
significant. Given that the average study includes very few of the total set of 
possible covariates, the possibility of spurious correlations is quite real. 
In addition to the substantial differences in covariates used across FDI studies, 
there are also differences across studies in whether variables are logged or whether 
panel data were used (these are noted in the first few rows of table 1). Given these 
wide differences in specifications, there clearly is no consensus on how to specify 
the determinants of bilateral FDI patterns. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 779 </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Specifications of prior studies of FDI determinants </p>

<p>Carr, </p>

<p>Bergstrand </p>

<p>Head </p>

<p>Markusen, </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>and Ries </p>

<p>Eaton and </p>

<p>Wei </p>

<p>di Giovanni </p>

<p>Stein and </p>

<p>Chakrabarti </p>

<p>Maskus (2001) Egger (2007) </p>

<p>(2008) 
Tamura (1994) (2000) </p>

<p>(2005) </p>

<p>Daude (2007) </p>

<p>(2001) </p>

<p>Data and specifications 
Dependent variable </p>

<p>Sales </p>

<p>Sales </p>

<p>Stock and 
M&amp;A </p>

<p>Stock </p>

<p>Stock </p>

<p>M&amp;A </p>

<p>Stock </p>

<p>Flows </p>

<p>Variables logged </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Some </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Panel data </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Two-way or one-way flows </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>One-way </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>Two-way </p>

<p>One-way </p>

<p>Gravity measures 
PARENT GDP </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST GDP </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Distance </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Other GDP-related terms 
PARENT per capita GDP </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST per capita GDP </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>PARENT population </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST population </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>GDP similarity </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>GDP sum </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>GDP difference </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>GDP per capita differences </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST GDP growth </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Rest-of-the-world GDP </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Other geography measures 
Contiguous border </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Time zone differences </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Country-level endowments 
Relative skilled-unskilled 
labour endowments (skill 
difference) </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Interaction of skill differences </p>

<p>and GDP differences </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>



<p>TABLE 1 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Carr, </p>

<p>Bergstrand </p>

<p>Head </p>

<p>Markusen, </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>and Ries </p>

<p>Eaton and </p>

<p>Wei </p>

<p>di Giovanni </p>

<p>Stein and </p>

<p>Chakrabarti </p>

<p>Maskus (2001) Egger (2007) </p>

<p>(2008) 
Tamura (1994) (2000) </p>

<p>(2005) </p>

<p>Daude (2007) </p>

<p>(2001) </p>

<p>Relative capital-labour 
endowments </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST wages </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>HOST population density </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST education levels </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Bilateral cultural and colonial 
linkages 
Common language </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Colonial links </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Multilateral trade openness 
HOST trade costs </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>PARENT trade costs </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST trade openness 
(imports plus exports 
divided by GDP) </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>HOST trade costs times skill 
difference term squared </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Bilateral trade openness 
BILATERAL transport costs </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>BILATERAL trade 
flows/deficit </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Regional trade agreement </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Customs union </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Common service sector 
agreement </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Host country FDI/business 
costs 
HOST FDI costs </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST taxes </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 781 </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Carr, </p>

<p>Bergstrand </p>

<p>Head </p>

<p>Markusen, </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>and Ries </p>

<p>Eaton and </p>

<p>Wei </p>

<p>di Giovanni </p>

<p>Stein and </p>

<p>Chakrabarti </p>

<p>Maskus (2001) Egger (2007) </p>

<p>(2008) 
Tamura (1994) (2000) </p>

<p>(2005) </p>

<p>Daude (2007) </p>

<p>(2001) </p>

<p>PARENT taxes </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>PARENT country has tax 
credit system </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Change in HOST consumer 
prices </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Bilateral tax and investment 
agreements </p>

<p>Tax treaty </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Investment treaty </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Host country communications 
infrastructure </p>

<p>Telephone traffic </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Host country financial 
infrastructure </p>

<p>HOST market capitalization </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST domestic credit </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Political environment and 
institutions </p>

<p>HOST political stability </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>HOST legal institutions </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>HOST corruption </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>Exchange rates 
Exchange rates </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>z </p>

<p>Volatility of exchange rates </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>NOTES: An "x" signifies that a variable is included and statistically significant in the majority of specifications reported in the paper. A "z" signifies that a 
variable is included, but it is not statistically significant in the majority of specifications reported in the paper. We exclude from this table variables that 
Chakrabarti (2001) posited as ex ante 
doubtful and that did not come in statistically significant in that analysis. The type of dependent variable in these </p>

<p>studies varied in construction but can be characterized by data on affiliate sales, which we term Sales </p>

<p>in the table; FDI stock, Stock; </p>

<p>FDI flows, Flows; </p>

<p>and/or counts (or value) of cross-border mergers and acquisitions activity, M&amp;A. </p>



<p>The final paper documented in table 1 (last column) is Chakrabarti (2001). 
This paper is similar to ours in its motivation to understand which covariates 
are more likely to be robust determinants of bilateral FDI. However, the analysis 
considers a surprisingly small set of possible covariates, perhaps because it came 
before some of the recent advances in the literature. Also, it follows a different 
methodology (extreme bounds analysis) from ours, feasible implementation of 
which requires the model space be restricted a priori. The approach we take 
to implement BMA requires no such restriction and is designed to identify and 
explore relevant portions of the entire model space. That said, Chakrabarti (2001)  serves as a potential warning signal for the literature and motivation for further 
study, as it finds that most of the covariates investigated are not statistically 
robust using typical extreme bounds criteria. 
On a final note, Eicher, Helfman and Lenkoski (2010; EHL) and Jordan and  Lenkoski (2012) are recent works that are similar to ours in their use of BMA to 
evaluate an extensive set of potential FDI determinants (including many of those 
included in table 1). However, there are a number of major differences. Both of 
these prior papers focus on determinants of FDI flows, whereas our focus is on 
the (static) cross-country distribution of FDI, typically measured by FDI stock 
or affiliate sales. This is an important distinction. Examination of FDI flows has 
been the purview of primarily the international finance literature, where the role 
of exchange rates, capital market shocks and short-run changes to other financial 
variables are the focus. In contrast, we wish to inform the empirical FDI literature 
that has focused on stock measures of FDI in order to directly assess the main 
general equilibrium theories of the long-run factors that explain the distribution 
FDI across countries. General equilibrium predictions are static in nature and 
therefore pertain to levels, not (short-run) changes, of the variables of interest. 
An additional focus of these papers is on modeling the selection issue of whether 
there is any FDI activity between bilateral country pairs in the first place. Since 
almost all prior empirical FDI studies do not address this issue, and our primary 
focus is on comparing our BMA results directly with these prior studies, we do 
not explore this issue either. </p>

<p>3. Methodology </p>

<p>3.1. FDI determinants model and Bayesian model averaging 
To study the determinants of bilateral foreign direct investment (FDI), we focus 
on the linear regression model: </p>

<p>Y = αι N + X j β j + ε, 
(1) </p>

<p>where Y is an N x 1 vector holding the measure of bilateral foreign direct invest-
ment, ι N is an N x 1 vector of 1's, X j is an N x k j matrix of FDI determinants 
and ε is an N x 1 vector of independent, normally distributed disturbances, each </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 783 </p>

<p>with mean zero and variance σ 
2 . We are interested in the realistic case where 
there is uncertainty about the appropriate variables to include in X j . In particu-
lar, suppose there are K potential determinants of FDI, collected in the N x K 
matrix X, and the variables in X j are chosen as a subset of X, so that k j ≤ K. 
We assume that the only aspect of model uncertainty in (1) is the selection of 
X j , so that a particular selection of X j defines the j 
th model, denoted M j . If we 
place no restrictions on the combinations of the variables in X that can enter the 
regression model, there are R = 2 
K different models to consider. 
The Bayesian approach to comparing alternative models is based on the pos-
terior probability that M j is the true model that generated the data: </p>

<p>Pr M j |Y = 
f Y |M j Pr M j </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>f (Y |M i ) Pr (M i ) </p>

<p>, j = 1, ..., R, 
(2) </p>

<p>where (2) follows directly from application of Bayes' rule. In (2), Pr M j is the 
researcher's prior probability that M j is the true model, while f Y |M j is the 
marginal likelihood: </p>

<p>f Y |M j = f Y |α, β j , σ, M j p α, β j , σ |M j dα dβ j dσ, 
(3) </p>

<p>where f Y |α, β j , σ, M j is the likelihood function for model M j and 
p α, β j , σ |M j is the researcher's prior density function for the parameters of 
M j . In words, the marginal likelihood function is the likelihood function inte-
grated with respect to the researcher's prior density function. It thus has the 
interpretation of the average value of the likelihood function, and therefore the 
average fit of the model, over different parameter values, where the averaging is 
done with respect to the prior density of model parameters. 
The posterior model probabilities in (2) can be used to confront the model 
uncertainty present in the FDI determinants regression. One approach for using 
Pr M j |Y is to select the model with highest posterior probability and then make 
inferences about the effects of alternative FDI determinants based on this "best" 
model alone. However, this focus on one chosen model (which mimics much of 
the model selection literature based on hypothesis tests and information criteria) 
ignores information in models other than the chosen model and thus does not 
yield inferences that fully incorporate model uncertainty. When the posterior 
model probability is dispersed widely across a large number of models, basing 
inferences on a single model can yield grossly distorted results. 
Instead of basing inference on a single highest probability model, BMA pro-
ceeds by averaging posterior inference regarding objects of interest across alter-
native models, where averaging is with respect to posterior model probabilities. </p>



<p>Specifically, for a generic object of interest λ, the BMA posterior distribution is 
calculated as: </p>

<p>p (λ|Y ) = </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>p λ|Y, M j Pr M j |Y , 
(4) </p>

<p>where p λ|Y, M j is the posterior distribution for λ conditional on model M j . 
For common choices of λ, this conditional posterior distribution will often be 
available analytically. We discuss several such cases in section 3.4 below. The 
BMA posterior distribution in (4) follows from direct application of rules of 
probability and is thus the obvious solution to incorporate model uncertainty 
into inference from the Bayesian perspective. 
3 It is worth emphasizing that p (λ|Y ) 
is not conditioned on a particular model being the true model, but is instead 
conditioned only on the data. That is, BMA has integrated out uncertainty 
regarding the identity of the true model. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3.2. Priors 
To implement BMA, we require posterior model probabilities. From (2) and 
(3), calculation of these probabilities requires a choice for both the prior density 
function for the parameters of M j , p α, β j , σ |M j and the prior model probability, 
Pr M j , j = 1, ..., R. In this section, we describe how each of these priors are set 
in our study of FDI determinants. 
In BMA applications, specification of the prior parameter densities poses a 
significant challenge. One approach is to elicit prior densities for the parameters 
of each model individually. However, this becomes intractable when the space of 
potential models is large, as will be true for the FDI determinants model. In such 
cases, it is useful to use prior parameter densities that are "automatic," in that they 
are set in a formulaic way across alternative models. One simple, and seemingly 
attractive, way to do this is to use non-informative priors for the parameters 
of all models under consideration. Unfortunately, the use of non-informative 
priors for those parameters not common to all models will yield posterior model 
probabilities that mechanically favour models with fewer parameters over those 
with more. For our application, the slope parameters β j are not common to all 
models, as they depend on the set of variables included in X j . Thus, using non-
informative priors for β j is not an option, as it will paradoxically generate model 
comparison results that are solely a consequence of the prior. This is not the case 
for parameters that are common to all models, for which non-informative priors </p>

<p>3 For an introduction to BMA and a review of related literature, see Hoeting, Madigan, Raftery 
and Volinsky (1999). 
4 In addition to BMA, we have produced results using the weighted average least squares (WALS) 
procedure of Magnus, Powell and Prüfer (2010), which is an alternative approach to model 
averaging from BMA. The results using WALS were quite similar to those from BMA and are 
available upon request. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 785 </p>

<p>yield posterior model probabilities that are not a function of the prior but only 
of sample information. For this reason, non-informative priors are a popular 
choice for parameters common to all models. 
Here we use two different automatic procedures for setting priors. For our pri-
mary analysis, we use the priors suggested by Fernandez, Ley and Steel (2001a), 
hereafter FLS, who provide an automatic procedure for setting parameter prior 
densities for a group of linear regression models that differ only with respect 
to the choice of covariates. This procedure is designed for the case where the 
researcher wishes to use as little subjective information in setting prior densities 
as possible and was shown by FLS to both have good theoretical properties and 
perform well in simulations for the calculation of posterior model probabilities. 
As a robustness check, we also present results for a prior advocated by Eicher,  Papageorgiou and Raftery (2011; EPR). We will describe the FLS prior in detail 
here, while the alternative prior is discussed in section 5.5. 
The FLS procedure begins by factoring the prior parameter density function 
as follows: </p>

<p>p α, β j , σ |M j = p β j |α, σ, M j p α, σ |M j . 
(5) </p>

<p>For parameters common to all models, namely α and σ , FLS use the standard, 
improper non-informative prior density for location and scale parameters: </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>p α, σ |M j ∝ σ 
−1 . 
(6) </p>

<p>To set p β j |α, σ, M j , FLS use the natural conjugate Normal-Gamma prior 
density: </p>

<p>β j |σ, M j ∼ N β </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j , σ V </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j . 
(7) </p>

<p>This natural conjugate form is advantageous as it allows for analytical calcu-
lation of the integrals in (3), which greatly speeds computing time. We set the 
prior mean, β </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j , to a k j x 1 vector of zeros. This centres the prior distribution 
for all model slope parameters on values consistent with the FDI determinants 
in X j having no effect on FDI. To set the prior variance-covariance matrix, FLS 
suggest the g-prior specification of Zellner (1986): </p>

<p>V </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j = gX j X j </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. 
(8) </p>

<p>5 This prior specification is independent of the model and thus assigns a common prior density 
for the intercept and conditional variance parameters across models. To ensure that the model 
intercept has the same interpretation across all models, we demean the FDI determinant 
variables before inclusion in the regressions. This gives the intercept parameter the role of the 
unconditional mean of the bilateral FDI measure for all models. </p>



<p>This prior specification is useful as it reduces the input from the researcher to 
a single hyperparameter, g, rather than needing to specify the entire k j x k j matrix 
V </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j . FLS discuss theoretical motivations for alternative choices of g and, based 
on this theory and extensive Monte Carlo experiments, suggest the following 
rule: </p>

<p>g = </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎩ </p>

<p>1 
K 2 if N ≤ K </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
N 
if N &gt; K </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎭ 
. 
(9) </p>

<p>In our study of FDI determinants, we consider several possible measures of 
Y with corresponding varying values for N. For all of these variations on the 
dependent variable, we have either N &lt; K 
2 or N ≈ K 
2 , and thus g ≈ 1/K 
2 in our 
analysis. 
To specify the prior model probability, we begin by defining an indicator 
variable, τ i , which is one if the i 
th variable is included in the true model and 
is zero otherwise. Our prior assumption is that each potential regressor enters 
the true model independently of all others with prior probability θ , so that 
Pr (τ i = 1) = θ , ∀ i. This implies prior model probabilities of the form: </p>

<p>Pr M j = θ 
k j (1 − θ ) 
K−k j . </p>

<p>A popular choice in the BMA literature is to set θ = 0.5, which implies equal 
prior probability across all possible models: </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Pr M j = 
1 
2 K = </p>

<p>1 
R 
. 
(10) </p>

<p>Because it is uniform across individual models, the model prior in (10) implies a 
lack of prior information about which specific model is the true model. However, 
this prior does not imply a uniform prior for the model size, defined as the 
number of covariates included in the true model. 
7 Indeed, as shown in Ley and 
Steel (2009), the prior probability distribution over model size implied by (10) 
will be binomial: </p>

<p>Pr </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>τ i = Bin (K, θ). </p>

<p>This binomial distribution will peak near K/2 and, for moderate to large K, 
place very low probability on models with either only a few or a very large number </p>

<p>6 See, for example, Raftery, Madigan and Hoeting (1997) and Fernandez, Ley and Steel (2001a, 
2001b). 
7 This is because the number of models for alternative model sizes can be different. For example, 
there is a single model with no covariates, but K models with one covariate. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 787 </p>

<p>of potential covariates. For example, in our study of FDI determinants, this prior 
would peak near 26 and place cumulative prior probability of less than 0.001 on 
all model sizes below 16 or above 40. 
Here, we instead use a prior suggested in Ley and Steel (2009). Rather than fix 
θ as a prior hyperparameter, we treat this prior inclusion probability as a random 
variable that follows a Beta(a, b) distribution, where a and b are hyperparameters 
of the prior. This is an example of a hierarchical prior, which Ley and Steel (2009) 
argue increases the flexibility of the prior and reduces the dependence of posterior 
model probabilities on prior assumptions. In this particular case, the hierarchical 
prior implies a beta-binomial prior distribution for model size, where a and b 
can be set to accommodate a wide variety of prior beliefs regarding model size. 
Ley and Steel (2009) recommend setting a = 1 and setting b to match a prior 
mean for model size, denoted m. Here we set b so that m = K/2, which generates 
a uniform prior for model size: </p>

<p>Pr </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>τ i = 
1 
K + 1 
. </p>

<p>Thus, our prior over models will be agnostic regarding the number of covari-
ates that are in the true model. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>3.3. Calculating posterior model probabilities 
Given these specifications for the prior densities, posterior model probabilities 
are conceptually straightforward to calculate. In particular, model probabilities 
can be computed directly by calculating the marginal likelihood for all possible 
models, each is available analytically for the linear regression model in (1) and 
the parameter prior densities in (6) to (9). However, when K is large, the size of 
the model space makes direct calculation of Pr M j |Y based on (2) practically 
infeasible. For example, we will consider K = 56 potential FDI determinants, 
meaning there are greater than R = 7 × 10 
16 possible models to consider. Even 
if each model could be considered in 1/100,000 
th of a second, an ambitious 
estimate at current computing speeds, it would still take over 22,000 years to 
evaluate all possible models. 
When the model space becomes too large for direct calculation of posterior 
model probabilities, a popular alternative approach is to estimate these proba-
bilities by sampling the model space. In particular, define a model indicator that 
takes on values from 1, . . . ,R, with a value of j indicating that model M j is the 
true model and assume that this model indicator follows a multinomial proba-
bility distribution with probabilities given by Pr M j |Y . Further, suppose that </p>

<p>8 We also considered a prior in which m = K / 10; this places substantially more prior weight on 
smaller models than the prior with m = K / 2. We do not report the results for this prior as they 
were nearly identical to the m = K / 2 case. </p>



<p>we are able to obtain random draws of this model indicator from its probabil-
ity distribution. It is then possible to construct a simulation-consistent estimate 
of Pr M j |Y as the proportion of the random draws for which model M j was 
drawn. In particular, we can construct the following estimate of Pr M j |Y : </p>

<p>p j = </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>I s </p>

<p>S 
, 
(11) </p>

<p>where S is the number of random draws of the model indicator and I s is an 
indicator function that is one if the s 
th draw of the model indicator was j. Note that 
(11) will estimate Pr M j |Y to be zero if M j is never drawn. However, assuming a 
large number of simulations are conducted, it will be exactly these models that are 
likely to have very low posterior model probability. Thus, estimates of Pr M j |Y 
constructed by simulating from the model space provide an efficient approach to 
identifying the set of models with relatively high posterior probability. 
Note that if we condition on Pr M j |Y equalling zero if M j is never drawn, 
equation (2) suggests an alternative, approximation-free approach to evaluating 
the posterior model probabilities for the visited models: </p>

<p>p j = 
f Y |M j Pr M j </p>

<p>i∈ </p>

<p>f (Y |M i ) Pr (M i ) </p>

<p>, j ∈ , 
(12) </p>

<p>where 
denotes the set of models that are visited by the sampler. As this 
set of models will be feasible to consider individually, the summation in the 
denominator of (12) will be feasible, whereas the summation in the denominator 
of (2) was not. If the models never visited by the sampler are assumed to have zero 
probability, model probabilities based on (12) will be exact, while those based on 
(11) will contain estimation error. All results presented for our FDI determinants 
analysis use model probabilities based on (12). 
To simulate from the model space, we use the Markov Chain Monte Carlo 
Model Composition (MC 
3 ) algorithm of Madigan and York (1995). This ap-
proach relies on the Metropolis-Hastings algorithm, which can be used to pro-
vide random samples from any probability distribution provided it is known up 
to a proportionality constant, which, by inspection of (2), is true for Pr M j |Y . 
MC 
3 was implemented by Raftery, Madigan and Hoeting (1997) for BMA in lin-
ear regression models and has been used in a number of economic applications 
involving linear regression (e.g., Fernandez, Ley and Steel 2001a, 2001b). </p>

<p>9   The MC 
3 algorithm requires an arbitrary model to initialize the sequence of 
model draws. Given this initial model, model draws obtained from the algorithm </p>

<p>9 For details of the implementation of MC 
3 in the context of a linear regression model, see Koop 
(2003). </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 789 </p>

<p>form a Markov chain that converges to draws from Pr M j |Y . An important 
issue with such Markov-chain based samplers is assessing the convergence of 
the chain. In producing the results described in section 5 below, we assume that 
200,000 draws is sufficient to ensure convergence and then base our estimates 
of posterior model probabilities on 1 million additional draws. We performed 
three checks to ensure convergence of the sampling procedure. First, results from 
an independent simulation using a longer convergence sample of 400,000 draws 
were very similar to those based on the shorter convergence sample. Second, our 
results are insensitive to two widely dispersed initial models: one with no FDI 
determinants and one with all possible FDI determinants. This insensitivity of 
results to the size of the convergence sample and the initialization of the chain 
suggests the sampler has converged. Finally, FLS suggest using the correlation 
between the probability estimates based on (11) and (12) as a check on the 
convergence of the sampler. For all results we present, this correlation was above 
0.99. </p>

<p>3.4. Calculating BMA posterior distributions 
In this section, we describe calculation of the BMA posterior distributions for the 
various objects of interest, λ, that we will use in our analysis of FDI determinants. 
The primary BMA posterior distribution we construct is the so-called "posterior 
inclusion probability," which is the BMA posterior probability that a covariate 
belongs to in the true model. In this case, λ = τ i , and the model dependent 
posterior distribution, p τ i |Y, M j , is simply an indicator variable that is one if 
the i 
th variable is included in model M j and is zero otherwise. From equation (4), 
the posterior inclusion probability is then: </p>

<p>p (τ i |Y ) = </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>p τ i |Y, M j Pr M j |Y = </p>

<p>j∈ω </p>

<p>Pr M j |Y , 
(13) </p>

<p>where ω denotes the set of models that include the i 
th covariate. 
We are also interested in the BMA posterior distribution for the marginal 
effect of the i 
th potential covariate. Denote the K x 1 vector of marginal effects 
for the K potential covariates as β. We then wish to construct the BMA posterior 
distribution: </p>

<p>p (β|Y ) = </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>p β|Y, M j Pr M j |Y . </p>

<p>Define a K x k j selection matrix, T j , such that β = T j β j is the K x 1 vector of 
marginal effects for model M j . Here, the i 
th element of β is the appropriate slope 
parameter from β j if model M j includes the i 
th covariate and is zero otherwise. As 
discussed in Magnus, Powell and Prüfer (2010), the BMA posterior distribution </p>



<p>for β then has the following moments: </p>

<p>E (β|Y ) = </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>T j E β j |Y, M j Pr M j |Y , 
(14) </p>

<p>Var (β|Y ) = −E (β|Y ) E (β|Y ) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>Pr M j |Y T j Var β j |Y, M j + E β j |Y, M j E β j |Y, M j T j , 
(15) </p>

<p>where E β j |Y, M j and Var β j |Y, M j are the moments of the posterior distri-
bution for β j conditional on M j . Given the linear regression model and natural 
conjugate parameter priors presented above, these moments of the conditional 
posterior distribution are given by: </p>

<p>E β j |Y, M j = 
1 
1 + g 
X j PX j </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>X j PY, </p>

<p>Var β j |Y, M j = 
Y PA j PY 
(1 + g) (N − 3) 
X j PX j </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>where P = I N − </p>

<p>1 
N </p>

<p>ι N ι N and A j = </p>

<p>g 
1+g </p>

<p>P + </p>

<p>1 
1+g </p>

<p>P − PX j X j PX j </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>X j P . </p>

<p>4. Data </p>

<p>Measurement of FDI and related activity is far from ideal. Unlike for trade flows, 
reliable measures of FDI are unavailable for many countries. In addition, there is 
no common source for FDI data; prior studies have therefore employed a number 
of different measures of FDI. As we wish to compare our results to these prior 
studies, we have collected data on three different FDI measures typically used. 
Our first source of cross-country FDI activity is bilateral FDI stocks reported 
by members of the Organization of Economic Cooperation and Development 
(OECD), which is the most comprehensive source of reliable data on total FDI 
stocks that we are aware of. 
10 OECD provides excellent coverage of FDI activity 
between OECD countries. It also has some coverage of FDI between OECD 
and non-OECD countries, though many transactions with small non-OECD 
countries are missing. OECD does not report any observations of FDI between </p>

<p>10 These data can be obtained from SourceOECD, www.sourceoecd.org. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 791 </p>

<p>countries where they are both non-OECD. The FDI stock data will be the bench-
mark measure of FDI used in our study, but we will also compare and contrast 
our results when using two alternative measures of FDI activity, described next. 
Some studies (e.g., CMM 2001; Bergstrand and Egger 2007) have stressed 
the use of affiliate sales as the most appropriate measure of actual multinational 
firm activity in a host country, as FDI stock data can be significantly affected 
by financial transactions of a firm not related to current productive activity. 
Unfortunately, affiliate sales data are much less available than FDI stock data. 
To our knowledge, Braconier, Norback and Urban (2005; BNU) have collected 
the most extensive database of cross-country affiliate sales and have graciously 
provided it to us. Their database provides information on outward affiliate sales 
involving 56 parent countries and 85 host countries over roughly four years from 
the late 1980s to 1998. Despite this, the number of observations is much smaller 
than with the FDI stock data. </p>

<p>11   Finally, we employ data on cross-border mergers and acquisitions (M&amp;A) 
that have been used in such studies as Rossi and Volpin (2004) and Head and  Ries (2008). These data come from Thomsen's SDC Platinum database on M&amp;A 
activity, meant to be a comprehensive census of worldwide M&amp;A above the 
$1 million threshold since the early 1990s. While this level of country coverage 
in the M&amp;A data clearly dominates the other two measures of FDI activity, the 
M&amp;A measure also has relative disadvantages. First, it measures only one type 
of FDI, though M&amp;A does account for the majority of worldwide FDI activity. 
Second, because many of the transactions are between private firms, over half of 
the M&amp;A in the database do not have any recorded value. Thus, we rely on counts 
of the number of M&amp;A occurring between country pairs. 
12 More specifically, we 
use cumulated sums of counts of prior and current-year M&amp;A by country pair to 
create a measure analogous to cross-country FDI stocks. Head and Ries (2008)  also use cumulated measures of M&amp;A activity and find a quite high correlation 
(greater than 0.80) between the FDI stock and M&amp;A measures of FDI activity. 
It is important to note that virtually all theory and empirics of worldwide FDI 
has focused on the (static) cross-country patterns rather than the dynamics of 
worldwide FDI flows. We follow this pattern and primarily focus on the year 2000, 
since it comes before the world recession following the events of 9/11 and most </p>

<p>11 We refer the reader to Braconier, Norback and Urban (2005) for further details on country 
coverage and data sources. 
12 Prior studies, including Rossi and Volpin (2004) and Head and Ries (2008), assumed that the 
missing M&amp;A transactions' values were random and summed up remaining observations of 
values to create their measure of cross-border M&amp;A activity. There are some obvious 
advantages and disadvantages with using M&amp;A count versus (non-missing) value data. One 
clear disadvantage for our purposes was how many missing observations are created when using 
the value data-many of the bilateral country pairings show M&amp;A activity, but the value data 
for all the M&amp;A transactions for that pairing are missing. For this reason, and because the 
correlation between the M&amp;A counts and values by bilateral-country pairs is 0.96, we use the 
M&amp;A count data. </p>



<p>closely matches the most recent data we have for the affiliate sales database. 
13 For 
those FDI measures where it was available, we also collected data for 1990. This 
allows us to examine specifications where we first difference the data to control 
for country-pair fixed effects. 
The set of potential covariates we consider is intended to be comprehensive 
and is listed in table 2. The variables in table 2 are grouped into broad categories 
of factors that plausibly determine FDI. We have included all covariates from 
previous studies listed in table 1 with only a few exceptions. First, we do not 
include exchange rate variables or changes in recent consumer prices, as we wish 
to examine the long-run determinants of FDI decisions, leaving examination of 
dynamic, short-run changes for other work. Second, bilateral trade flows are 
clearly endogenous and so we do not include this covariate as some studies have 
done. Finally, there are a few variables where available data are so limited (e.g., 
wage data) that we feel the cost in terms of reduced sample size is too great. 
We also include a number of additional variables. First, a few recent stud-
ies have found that geographic spatial issues are important for understand-
ing bilateral FDI patterns (see Baltagi, Egger and Pfaffermayr 2007, BBEP;  Blonigen, Davies, Waddell and Naughton 2007, BDWN). To account for such 
spatial features of the data to some extent, we include a remoteness variable for 
both the host and parent country, constructed as the distance-weighted average of 
all other countries' GDP. Possible agglomeration effects within countries also led 
us to add a measure of urban concentration for both the host and parent country. 
Previous studies have hypothesized that endowments may matter, particularly if 
FDI is motivated to find lower cost locations (i.e., vertically motivated FDI). 
However, these studies have included only measures of relative labour and capi-
tal endowments. We include measures of land and oil as well. Business costs in 
the host country have been included in some previous studies, but they often use 
proxies that have limited country coverage, which we found significantly reduces 
the potential sample. Thus, we rely on relatively recent measures of host-country 
business costs collected by the World Bank that measure the average time it takes 
to enforce a contract, register property, start a business and resolve an insolvency. 
We also include measures from the World Bank's World Development Indicators 
on communications infrastructure, which previous studies have not included but 
plausibly could affect FDI decisions. 
These additions and subtractions from the combined set of regressors from 
previous studies leave us with 56 variables to examine as potential covariates with 
FDI. The data sources for our variables are primarily the Penn World Tables, 
the World Development Indicators database and the Gravity database at CEPII 
(www.cepii.org). A full list of data sources is available from the authors upon 
request. </p>

<p>13 The most recent data we have available for the affiliate sales database is 1998. Our analysis will 
use FDI stock and M&amp;A count data for the year 2000 and affiliate sales data for the year 1998. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 793 </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Variables </p>

<p>Included in 
previous study 
Variable 
Definition 
listed in table 1 </p>

<p>Dependent variables 
FDI stock 
FDI position of PARENT country in HOST country 
(in millions of U.S. dollars) 
Affiliate sales 
Sales of PARENT-owned affiliates in HOST country 
M&amp;A counts 
Cumulated counts of PARENT country acquisitions 
of HOST country targets prior to year of 
observation 
Gravity measures 
1. PARENT real GDP 
Real GDP of PARENT country (in trillions) 
X 
2. HOST real GDP 
Real GDP of HOST country (in trillions) 
X 
3. Distance 
Distance between the two most populous cities in the 
PARENT and HOST countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Other GDP-related 
terms 
4. PARENT real GDP 
per capita </p>

<p>Real GDP per capita of PARENT country (constant 
price: Chain Series) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>5. HOST real GDP per 
capita </p>

<p>Real GDP per capita of HOST country (constant 
price: Chain Series) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>6. Sum of HOST and 
PARENT real GDP </p>

<p>Sum of HOST and PARENT real GDP 
X </p>

<p>7. Similarity of HOST 
and PARENT real 
GDP </p>

<p>Share of HOST real GDP in the sum of HOST and 
PARENT GDP x Share of PARENT real GDP in 
the sum of HOST and PARENT GDP </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>8. Squared GDP 
difference </p>

<p>Squared real GDP difference between HOST and 
PARENT country </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>9. Squared GDP per 
capita difference </p>

<p>Squared real GDP per capita difference between 
HOST and PARENT countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>10. HOST urban 
concentration </p>

<p>Urban population (% of total) in HOST country </p>

<p>11. PARENT urban 
concentration </p>

<p>Urban population (% of total) in PARENT country </p>

<p>Geography measures 
other than distance 
12. Contiguous border 
Dummy variable indicating PARENT and HOST 
countries are geographically contiguous </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>13. HOST remoteness 
Distance of HOST country from all other countries 
in the world weighted by those other countries' 
share of world GDP (does not include host 
country in calculations) 
14. PARENT 
remoteness </p>

<p>Distance of PARENT country from all other 
countries in the world weighted by those other 
countries' share of world GDP (does not include 
host country in calculations) 
15. Time zone difference Time zone difference between capital cities of HOST 
and PARENT countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Relative labour 
endowments 
16. HOST education 
level </p>

<p>Average education years in HOST country 
X </p>

<p>17. HOST skill level 
Percent of employment by skilled labour in HOST 
country </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Included in 
previous study 
Variable 
Definition 
listed in table 1 </p>

<p>18. PARENT education 
level </p>

<p>Average education years in PARENT country </p>

<p>19.PARENT skill level 
Percent of employment by skilled labour in PARENT 
country 
20. Squared education 
difference </p>

<p>Squared difference in average education years 
between PARENT and HOST countries (proxy for 
relative skilled labour endowments) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>21. Squared skill 
difference </p>

<p>Squared difference in % of employment by skilled 
labour between PARENT and HOST countries 
(proxy for relative skilled labour endowments) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>22. Interaction of GDP 
differences with 
education differences </p>

<p>Interaction of GDP differences with education 
differences </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>23. Interaction of GDP 
differences with skill 
differences </p>

<p>Interaction of GDP differences with skill differences 
X </p>

<p>Other relative 
endowment measures 
24. HOST capital per 
worker </p>

<p>Capital per worker in HOST country </p>

<p>25. PARENT capital per 
worker </p>

<p>Capital per worker in PARENT country </p>

<p>26. Squared difference in 
capital per worker </p>

<p>Squared difference in capital per worker between 
HOST and PARENT countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>27. HOST land area 
Land area (sq. km) in HOST country 
28. PARENT land area 
Land area (sq. km) in PARENT country 
29. HOST population 
density </p>

<p>Population divided by land area in HOST country 
X </p>

<p>30. HOST is oil country 
Indicator variable that the HOST country is a top 10 
producer or top 10 exporter of oil 
Cultural distance 
31. Common official 
language </p>

<p>Indicator variable that PARENT and HOST 
countries share a common official language </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>32. Common language 
overlap </p>

<p>Indicator variable that PARENT and HOST 
countries share a language that at least 9% speak 
in each country 
33. Colonial relationship Dummy variable indicating PARENT and HOST 
countries have had (or do have) a colonial link </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Multilateral trade 
openness 
34. HOST trade 
openness </p>

<p>HOST country openness (imports plus exports 
divided by GDP) in constant prices (constant 
prices, in %) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>35. PARENT trade 
openness </p>

<p>PARENT country openness (imports plus exports 
divided by GDP) in constant prices (constant 
prices, in %) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>36. Interaction of 
education differences 
with HOST trade 
openness </p>

<p>Interaction of education differences with HOST 
trade openness </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 795 </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Included in 
previous study 
Variable 
Definition 
listed in table 1 </p>

<p>37. Interaction of skill 
differences with 
HOST trade openness </p>

<p>Interaction of skill differences with HOST trade 
openness </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Bilateral trade openness 
38. Regional trade 
agreement </p>

<p>Indicator variable for regional trade agreement 
between PARENT and HOST countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>39. Customs union 
Indicator variable for customs union between 
PARENT and HOST countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>40. Service sector 
agreement </p>

<p>Indicator variable for economic integration 
agreement in services between PARENT and 
HOST countries </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Host country 
FDI/business costs 
41. HOST time to 
enforce contract </p>

<p>Time required to enforce a contract (days) in HOST 
country 
42. HOST time to 
register property </p>

<p>Time required to register property (days) in HOST 
country 
43. HOST time to start 
business </p>

<p>Time required to start a business (days) in HOST 
country 
44. HOST time to 
resolve insolvency </p>

<p>Time to resolve insolvency (years) in HOST country </p>

<p>Host country tax 
policies 
45. HOST corporate tax 
Highest marginal tax rate, corporate rate (%) in 
HOST country </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>46. HOST is tax haven 
Indicator variable that the HOST country is 
considered a tax haven by OECD 
Bilateral tax and 
investment 
agreements 
47. Bilateral investment 
treaty </p>

<p>Dummy variable indicating a bilateral investment 
treaty in place between HOST and PARENT 
countries before July 1 of year </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>48. Double taxation 
treaty </p>

<p>Dummy variable indicating a double taxation treaty 
governing "income and capital" in place between 
HOST and PARENT countries before July 1 of 
year </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Host country 
communications 
infrastructure 
49. HOST telephones 
Mobile and fixed-line telephone subscribers (per 100 
people) in HOST country 
50. HOST Internet users Internet users (per 100 people) in HOST country 
51. HOST computers 
Personal computers (per 100 people) in HOST 
country 
Host country financial 
infrastructure 
52. HOST domestic 
credit </p>

<p>Domestic credit provided by banking sector in 
HOST country (% of GDP) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Included in 
previous study 
Variable 
Definition 
listed in table 1 </p>

<p>53. HOST market 
capitalization </p>

<p>Market capitalization of listed companies (% of 
GDP) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Political environment 
and institutions 
54. HOST legal 
institutions </p>

<p>Strength of legal rights index (0 = weak to 10 = 
strong) in HOST country </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>55. HOST political 
rights </p>

<p>Political rights index for HOST country (ranges from 
1 to 7, with highest score indicating the lowest level 
of freedom) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>56. HOST civil liberties 
Civil liberties index for HOST country (ranges from 
1 to 7, with highest score indicating the lowest level 
of freedom) </p>

<p>5. Results </p>

<p>Because previous studies have employed a variety of FDI measures and specifica-
tions (e.g., logging variables or not), the reported results below proceed through 
a number of possible combinations of the FDI measure and variable transfor-
mation, before we compare our results to those in previous studies. </p>

<p>5.1. Base results 
We begin with results using our benchmark measure of FDI (FDI stock) as 
our dependent variable, considering both a specification where all (non-binary) 
variables are logged and a specification where all variables are not logged. We 
refer to these as the "log-levels" and "levels" specifications, respectively. Note 
that interactive variables drop out of the log-levels specifications as they generate 
perfect collinearity in the regression upon taking logarithms. For each potential 
covariate, table 3 reports the posterior inclusion probability and the mean of 
the BMA posterior density for the covariate's slope coefficient for both the levels 
(columns 1 and 2) and log-levels (columns 3 and 4) specifications using our sample 
of 2000 data. Again, the posterior inclusion probability and mean of the BMA 
posterior distribution are computed as in equations (13) and (14), respectively. 
One striking similarity between the levels and log-levels specifications is the 
relatively small set of variables out of the 56 potential covariates that have high 
inclusion probabilities. Only seven variables have inclusion probabilities at or 
above 50% in the levels specification, while the analogous number of variables is 
16 in the log-levels specification. This suggests a fairly parsimonious specification 
is sufficient to explain cross-country FDI patterns. In the levels specification, 
only GDP-related variables, the colonial relationship variable and the bilateral </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 797 </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Level and log-level regressions to explain FDI stocks in 2000 </p>

<p>Levels 
Log-levels </p>

<p>Variable 
Inclusion 
Posterior Inclusion 
Posterior 
probability mean 
probability 
mean </p>

<p>1. PARENT real GDP 
100 
6,322.22 100 
1.40 
2. HOST real GDP 
100 
6,606.47 100 
1.74 
3. Distance 
39 
−0.15 100 
−0.94 
4. PARENT real GDP per capita 
9 
0.05 100 
2.31 
5. HOST real GDP per capita 
1 
0.00 
2 
0.01 
6. Sum of HOST and PARENT real GDP 
0 
0.00 
0 
0.00 
7. Similarity of HOST and PARENT real 
GDP </p>

<p>86 
21,097.71 
2 
0.00 </p>

<p>8. Squared GDP difference 
100 
−326.09 
1 
0.00 
9. Squared GDP per capita difference 
8 
0.00 
1 
0.00 
10. HOST urban concentration 
0 
0.08 
52 
0.63 
11. PARENT urban concentration 
0 
0.00 
1 
0.00 
12. Contiguous border 
3 
158.15 
1 
0.00 
13. HOST remoteness 
0 
0.00 100 
2.29 
14. PARENT remoteness 
2 
−0.01 
30 
0.27 
15. Time zone differences 
4 
−15.68 
5 
0.01 
16. HOST education level 
0 
−0.03 
1 
0.00 
17. HOST skill level 
39 
6,090.09 
97 
1.94 
18. PARENT education level 
0 
0.67 
1 
0.00 
19. PARENT skill level 
1 
83.09 
1 
0.00 
20. Squared education difference 
0 
−0.04 
7 
−0.01 
21. Squared skill difference 
1 
0.00 
89 
1.11 
22. Interaction of GDP differences with 
education differences </p>

<p>100 
−3.53 NA 
NA </p>

<p>23. Interaction of GDP differences with skill 
differences </p>

<p>0 
−5.02 NA 
NA </p>

<p>24. HOST capital per worker 
4 
−0.01 
1 
0.00 
25. PARENT capital per worker 
8 
−0.02 
36 
0.25 
26. Squared difference in capital per worker 
1 
0.01 
4 
0.00 
27. HOST land area 
7 
0.00 
3 
0.00 
28. PARENT land area 
1 
0.00 
1 
0.00 
29. HOST population density 
0 
0.52 
3 
0.01 
30. HOST is oil country 
2 
−67.25 
92 
−0.92 
31. Common official language 
39 
2,613.06 
92 
1.08 
32. Common language overlap 
1 
13.52 
1 
0.00 
33. Colonial relationship 
81 
8,071.84 
87 
1.14 
34. HOST trade openness 
6 
1.63 
95 
0.79 
35. PARENT trade openness 
0 
0.05 
1 
0.00 
36. Interaction of education differences with 
HOST trade openness </p>

<p>0 
0.00 NA 
NA </p>

<p>37. Interaction of skill differences with HOST 
trade openness </p>

<p>1 
1.42 NA 
NA </p>

<p>38. Regional trade agreement 
0 
8.80 100 
1.47 
39. Customs union 
1 
22.61 
97 
1.15 
40. Service sector agreement 
49 
2,887.97 
4 
0.03 
41. HOST time to enforce contract 
0 
0.01 
1 
0.00 
42. HOST time to register property 
3 
−0.61 
26 
0.05 
43. HOST time to start business 
6 
−2.27 
3 
−0.01 
44. HOST time to resolve insolvency 
0 
−0.16 
1 
0.00 
45. HOST corporate tax 
0 
0.07 
67 
−0.56 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>



<p>TABLE 3 
(Continued) </p>

<p>Levels 
Log-levels </p>

<p>Variable 
Inclusion 
Posterior Inclusion 
Posterior 
probability mean 
probability 
mean </p>

<p>46. HOST is tax haven 
0 
10.81 
4 
0.10 
47. Bilateral investment treaty 
50 
−1,838.23 
1 
0.00 
48. Double taxation treaty 
0 
−3.21 
23 
0.10 
49. HOST telephones 
2 
−0.72 
1 
0.00 
50. HOST Internet users 
2 
0.80 
1 
0.00 
51. HOST computers 
6 
5.28 
2 
0.00 
52. HOST domestic credit 
3 
0.63 
1 
0.00 
53. HOST market capitalization 
4 
0.72 
7 
0.02 
54. HOST legal institutions 
1 
5.72 
85 
−0.68 
55. HOST political rights 
0 
−1.09 
5 
−0.02 
56. HOST civil liberties 
1 
−9.07 
1 
0.00 
Sample size 
1,066 
1,066 </p>

<p>NOTES: "Inclusion probability" refers to the posterior probability that the associated variable is in 
the true FDI determinants model. "NA" denotes "not applicable" when the variable is not included 
because it is perfectly collinear with other variables once logged. </p>

<p>investment treaty variable have high inclusion probabilities for explaining FDI 
stock. 
Our preferred specification is the log-levels specification because of the sub-
stantial skewness in the dependent variable. In that specification, the evidence 
suggests that standard gravity variables with a few friction variables comprise 
the bulk of the variables with explanatory power for cross-country FDI patterns. 
The key gravity variables-real GDP for the host and parent countries, distance, 
common language and colonial relationships-all have inclusion probabilities 
above 85% in the log-levels specification. In addition, the trade openness vari-
ables indicating the presence of a custom union, the presence of a regional trade 
agreement and host-country country openness, all have inclusion values above 
90%. There is also evidence that endowment differences across the host and 
parent country may matter, as predicted by some models of FDI, such as the 
knowledge-capital model of CMM (2001). The host-country skill level and the 
squared skill difference between the host and parent country have high inclusion 
probabilities, though all other endowment variables (including those capturing 
capital and land differences) have very low inclusion probabilities. 
14 In general, 
other broad categories of variables receive little statistical support, particularly 
those related to business costs, infrastructure and institutions in the host country. 
The exception is some support for legal institutions (85%) and the corporate tax 
level (67%) in the host country. On the other hand, there are a few variables not </p>

<p>14 The exception is an indicator for whether the host country is an oil-producing country. 
However, as will be discussed in section 5.3, oil production in the host country is associated with 
reduced FDI rather than increased FDI. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 799 </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Inclusion probabilities above 50% using alternative measures of FDI (logged 2000 data) </p>

<p>Variable 
FDI stock 
Affiliate sales 
Cross-border M&amp;A </p>

<p>PARENT real GDP 
100 
100 
100 
HOST real GDP 
100 
100 
100 
Distance 
100 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP per capita 
100 
99 
100 
HOST remoteness 
100 
100 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
100 
4 
100 
Customs union 
97 
1 
100 
HOST skill level 
97 
1 
100 
HOST trade openness 
95 
3 
2 
Common official language 
92 
1 
100 
HOST is oil country 
92 
1 
94 
Squared skill difference 
89 
2 
1 0 
Colonial relationship 
87 
1 
97 
HOST legal institutions 
85 
22 
1 
HOST corporate tax 
67 
95 
3 
HOST urban concentration 
52 
0 
1 
PARENT remoteness 
30 
0 
100 
Squared GDP per capita difference 
1 
82 
2 
PARENT urban concentration 
1 
0 
98 
PARENT skill level 
1 
1 
100 
HOST time to resolve insolvency 
1 
2 
91 
Sample size 
1,066 
395 
1,066 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays all variables that have at least a 50% inclusion probability in one of the 
listed specifications. Instances where the inclusion probability is 50% or higher are in bold. </p>

<p>typically included in empirical FDI studies that have very high inclusion proba-
bility in our log-levels specification. These are real GDP per capita in the parent 
country (100%), remoteness of the host country (100%) and, to a lesser extent, 
urban concentration of the host country (52%). 
Our results to this point use FDI stock as our measure of cross-country 
FDI activity. Table 4 next compares results when we use two other measures of 
FDI that have been used by prior studies-affiliate sales and cross-border M&amp;A 
activity. The table displays all variables that receive at least 50% in one of our 
three specifications (FDI stock, affiliate sales or M&amp;A). For ease in reading the 
table, we bold the instances where the inclusion probability is 50% or higher. 
For comparison sake, we report only the results for the log-levels specification, 
and, for the M&amp;A sample, we use only observations for the 1,066 country pairs 
for which we observe the FDI stock variable. (We have many more country-pair 
observations for the M&amp;A sample that we will analyze and discuss below.) We use 
all observations available for affiliate sales, but this provides just 395 observations. 
Despite these data issues, many of the patterns found in the FDI stock specifi-
cation are also found when using these other FDI measures. First, the traditional 
gravity variables (real GDP of both countries and distance) all have inclusion 
probabilities of 100% across all three specifications. Parent-country real GDP per </p>



<p>capita also has at least a 99% inclusion probability across all three, suggesting 
that the wealth of the source country is a key determinant of FDI. Interest-
ingly, host country real GDP per capita does not have similarly high inclusion 
probabilities. There is a similar asymmetry in that host country remoteness 
generally garners high inclusion probabilities across all the measures of FDI 
activity, whereas parent country remoteness does not. It has a high inclusion 
probability only in the cross-border M&amp;A specification. These asymmetric re-
sults are an example of empirical patterns our analysis finds that have not been 
examined by prior theory or empirical studies of FDI to our knowledge. 
In general, the M&amp;A and FDI stock samples share many variables with high 
inclusion probabilities beyond the ones we have mentioned, including common 
official language, colonial relationship, regional trade agreement, customs union, 
host oil country and host skill level. One interesting difference between the M&amp;A 
and FDI stock results are that while legal institutions and corporate taxes in the 
host country have modestly high inclusion probabilities for FDI stock, they 
have very low ones in the M&amp;A sample. Instead, days to resolve insolvencies in 
the host country is the only host country business cost variable to have a high 
inclusion variable in the M&amp;A sample. One final notable difference is that parent-
country remoteness and urban concentration have high inclusion probabilities in 
the M&amp;A sample, but not in the other samples. 
The FDI stock and affiliate sales specifications find less commonality in the 
variables that have high inclusion probabilities. We have also produced results for 
the FDI stock and affiliate sales specifications on a common, overlapping sample 
of 253 observations and found much more similarity in results that mirror those 
for affiliate sales in table 4. This suggests that the differences across the affiliate 
sales and FDI stock specifications in table 4 are due primarily to the relatively 
small sample available for the affiliate sales measure. Overall, the general patterns 
noted in earlier specifications reported above continue to hold-gravity finds very 
strong support, while cultural distance and endowment variables find support as 
well. In contrast, there continues to be much less support for variables capturing 
host country business costs, infrastructure or institutions. 
As mentioned, the data on FDI stock and affiliate sales is limited primarily 
to OECD country pairs, though there is some information on FDI from OECD 
into less-developed countries, but not on FDI patterns between less-developed 
countries. On the one hand, this selection may not be a significant issue be-
cause the vast majority of FDI in the world economy is between the developed 
economies, which are well represented in our sample. On the other hand, it is 
useful to know how FDI determinants may differ when a more representative 
sample of countries is examined. Our M&amp;A data source has the ability to address 
this as it is a census of worldwide M&amp;A activity. 
Table 5 lists all variables with inclusion variables above 50% for three specifi-
cations using logged data for the year 2000. The first two columns of inclusion 
probabilities are for comparison purposes and are for the FDI stock specifica-
tion and the M&amp;A specification when limited to the same observations as the </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 801 </p>

<p>TABLE 5 
Inclusion probabilities above 50% for OECD and worldwide samples (logged 2000 data) </p>

<p>OECD sample 
Worldwide sample </p>

<p>Variable 
FDI stock Cross-border M&amp;A Cross-border M&amp;A </p>

<p>HOST real GDP 
100 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP 
100 
100 
100 
Distance 
100 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP per capita 
100 
100 
100 
HOST remoteness 
100 
100 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
100 
100 
100 
Customs union 
97 
100 
100 
HOST skill level 
97 
100 
71 
HOST country trade openness 
95 
2 
2 
Common official language 
92 
100 
99 
HOST is oil country 
92 
94 
92 
Squared skill difference 
89 
10 
3 
Colonial relationship 
87 
97 
100 
HOST legal institutions 
85 
1 
1 
HOST corporate tax 
67 
3 
99 
HOST urban concentration 
52 
1 
1 
PARENT remoteness 
30 
100 
100 
Double taxation treaty 
23 
2 
100 
Squared education difference 
7 
38 
97 
Service sector agreement 
4 
1 
97 
Similarity of HOST and PARENT real GDP 
2 
1 
54 
PARENT education level 
1 
1 
85 
PARENT urban concentration 
1 
98 
100 
PARENT skill level 
1 
100 
76 
Bilateral investment treaty 
1 
14 
100 
HOST education level 
1 
3 
100 
HOST years to resolve insolvency 
1 
91 
98 
Contiguous border 
1 
1 
95 </p>

<p>Observations 
1,066 
1,066 
3,429 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays all variables that have at least a 50% inclusion probability in one of the 
listed specifications. Instances where the inclusion probability is 50% or higher are in bold. </p>

<p>FDI stock sample. The third column is the M&amp;A specification when we use all 
observations for which we have available data (we call this the "worldwide" sam-
ple), as opposed to the restricted sample (we call this the "OECD" sample). This 
more than triples the sample size over the other two listed specifications to 3,429 
observations, adding many more observations involving non-OECD countries. </p>

<p>15   The results from the worldwide M&amp;A sample show a lot of commonalities with 
the previous results. Gravity variables, cultural distance and relative skilled labour 
variables all show very high inclusion probabilities. In fact, all of the variables 
that have high inclusion probabilities in the OECD M&amp;A sample specification 
(column 2) also have high inclusion probabilities in the worldwide M&amp;A sample </p>

<p>15 In the "OECD" sample, all country-pair observations involve at least one OECD country, and 
40% of the country-pair observations are between OECD countries. In the "worldwide" sample, 
32% of the country-pair observations do not involve at least one OECD country, and only 18% 
of the country-pair observations are between OECD countries. </p>



<p>specification. However, the worldwide M&amp;A sample also shows high inclusion 
probabilities for a number of additional variables. These include a few more 
endowment variables (education levels in both the host and parent country as well 
as the squared difference in education levels between the two countries), as one 
might expect when one includes many more observations between relatively poor 
non-OECD countries and OECD countries. It also includes variables connected 
with bilateral treaties (bilateral investment treaty, double taxation treaty and 
service sector agreements) as well as the presence of a contiguous border. This 
suggests that these bilateral treaties may be much more important for spurring 
FDI into non-OECD countries than into OECD ones. </p>

<p>5.2. Implications for prior studies 
With our BMA results in hand, we now turn to address the fundamental question 
of how our BMA results compare to those of previous studies. Virtually all of the 
prior studies include gravity-related variables, and, thus, our results confirm the 
inclusion of such variables. Common official language also finds robust support 
in our analysis and is included in five of the prior eight studies in table 1. Beyond 
this small set of variables, however, prior studies vary significantly in what they 
include, and what they include does not necessarily match very well with the 
variables our analysis finds to have high inclusion probabilities. For example, our 
analysis finds that parent country wealth (real per capita GDP) has strong and 
robust support, yet only one study (Head and Ries 2008) of the eight studies 
in table 1 includes this variable. In contrast, four of the studies in table 1 in-
clude host country wealth, yet we find this variable does not have strong support 
for inclusion. The reason for this asymmetry in wealth effects on FDI is also 
something that past theoretical papers, to our knowledge, do not address. Only 
four of the prior eight studies include variables related to relative skilled-labour 
endowment levels or differences, whereas our analysis finds that such variables 
should be included. There is little evidence that other relative endowments matter 
besides the presence of oil in the host country. Colonial relationships, host coun-
try remoteness, trade agreements and customs unions are additional variables 
that find strong support in our analysis but are rarely included in prior studies. 
On the other hand, a number of the prior studies include variables connected 
to host country business costs, infrastructure and institutions, but these do not 
find robust support in our analysis. Finally, the studies in table 1 whose main 
focus is on a particular hypothesized relationship between a potential covariate 
and FDI generally do not fare very well in terms of the inclusion probabilities 
we estimate for the same covariate. This includes Wei (2000), whose focus is on 
corruption; Stein and Daude (2007), whose focus is on time zone differences; and 
di Giovanni (2005), whose partial focus is on financial market institutions. </p>

<p>5.3. Slope coefficient magnitudes 
To this point, we have focused only on inclusion probabilities. In table 6, we report 
estimates of the slope coefficient of the variables listed in table 5. In particular, </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 803 </p>

<p>TABLE 6 
Posterior mean and variance of slope coefficients for OECD and worldwide samples (logged 2000 
data) </p>

<p>OECD sample 
Worldwide sample </p>

<p>Variable 
FDI stock 
Cross-border M&amp;A 
Cross-border M&amp;A </p>

<p>HOST real GDP 
1.74 (0.02) 
0.97 (0.00) 
0.61 (0.00) 
PARENT real GDP 
1.40 (0.00) 
1.02 (0.00) 
0.79 (0.00) 
Distance 
−0.94 (0.02) 
−0.63 (0.01) 
−0.44 (0.00) 
PARENT real GDP per 
capita </p>

<p>2.31 (0.14) 
1.29 (0.01) 
0.61 (0.01) </p>

<p>HOST remoteness 
2.29 (0.24) 
1.24 (0.05) 
0.64 (0.01) 
Regional trade agreement 
1.47 (0.09) 
1.37 (0.04) 
1.19 (0.02) 
Customs union 
1.15 (0.11) 
1.23 (0.04) 
0.92 (0.04) 
HOST skill level 
1.94 (0.36) 
1.40 (0.08) 
0.26 (0.04) 
HOST country trade 
openness </p>

<p>0.79 (0.07) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) </p>

<p>Common official language 
1.08 (0.20) 
1.08 (0.04) 
0.45 (0.01) 
HOST is oil country 
−0.92 (0.13) 
−0.56 (0.04) 
−0.29 (0.01) 
Squared skill difference 
1.11 (0.25) 
0.05 (0.03) 
0.01 (0.00) 
Colonial relationship 
1.14 (0.31) 
0.93 (0.08) 
1.22 (0.02) 
HOST legal institutions 
−0.68 (0.12) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) 
HOST corporate tax 
−0.56 (0.19) 
−0.01 (0.00) 
−0.32 (0.01) 
HOST urban concentration 
0.63 (0.44) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) 
PARENT remoteness 
0.27 (0.21) 
1.17 (0.05) 
0.59 (0.01) 
Double taxation treaty 
0.10 (0.04) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.42 (0.00) 
Squared education 
difference </p>

<p>−0.01 (0.00) 
−0.03 (0.00) 
−0.06 (0.00) </p>

<p>Service sector agreement 
0.03 (0.03) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.68 (0.05) 
Similarity of HOST and 
PARENT real GDP </p>

<p>0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.13 (0.02) </p>

<p>PARENT education level 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.34 (0.03) 
PARENT urban 
concentration </p>

<p>0.00 (0.00) 
−0.76 (0.05) 
−0.50 (0.00) </p>

<p>PARENT skill level 
0.00 (0.00) 
1.19 (0.06) 
0.32 (0.05) 
Bilateral investment treaty 
0.00 (0.00) 
−0.04 (0.01) 
−0.36 (0.00) 
HOST education level 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.01 (0.00) 
0.69 (0.02) 
HOST years to resolve 
insolvency </p>

<p>0.00 (0.00) 
0.25 (0.01) 
0.15 (0.00) </p>

<p>Contiguous border 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.00 (0.00) 
0.21 (0.01) </p>

<p>Observations 
1,066 
1,066 
3,429 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays the posterior mean and variance (in parentheses) of slope coefficient 
for all variables that have 50% or higher inclusion probability for at least one of the listed 
specifications. Coefficients where the associated inclusion probability is 50% or higher are in 
bold. </p>

<p>for the variables and specifications in table 5, we report the mean and variance of 
the BMA posterior density for the slope coefficient on each variable, calculated 
as inequations (14) and (15). With few exceptions, the coefficient signs are as 
one would expect and consistent with prior studies. This includes the gravity 
variables, cultural distance variables and bilateral trade openness variables. For 
many of the coefficients, the magnitude of the effect is smaller in the worldwide 
M&amp;A sample than for the OECD sample, which suggests that FDI responds </p>



<p>much less to economic forces for host countries that are less developed. A few of 
the coefficients have unexpected signs. One of the more intriguing results is that 
while the bilateral distance between country pairs lowers FDI (as expected), the 
remoteness of both the parent and host countries (that is, how far they are from 
the entire world's markets, not just the other country in the country pair) has 
positive coefficients. This distinction has not been made before to our knowledge 
but certainly deserves future investigation. Another surprising result is that the 
presence of oil in the host country is associated with lower FDI, as is the strength 
of host country legal institutions. 
The posterior mean and variance of the slope coefficients can also be used to 
construct a "pseudo t-ratio" by dividing the posterior mean by the posterior stan-
dard deviation. This statistic is a natural candidate as a measure of the relative 
importance of potential covariates in a linear regression setting and is some-
times reported along with BMA inclusion probabilities. In our application, the 
pseudo t-ratios (not reported) provide very similar conclusions to those reached 
from the BMA inclusion probabilities regarding the relative importance of the 
candidate FDI determinants. As a specific example, for the log-levels specifica-
tion using FDI stocks as the dependent variable, the ranking of FDI determi-
nants by the two metrics is nearly identical, with the Spearman rank correlation 
statistic between the pseudo t-ratio and the BMA inclusion probability equal 
to 0.98. </p>

<p>5.4. Controlling for country-pair effects 
Many prior studies of FDI determinants include country or country-pair effects. 
A simple way to control for such effects is to difference the data by country-
pair combinations. Table 7 provides results from log-linear specifications for a 
1990-2000 differenced sample for our FDI stock, OECD M&amp;A and worldwide 
M&amp;A samples. First-differencing in this manner eliminates a number of time-
invariant variables, as is typical. It unfortunately also eliminates a very large 
portion of the observations, due to many more missing values for variables in 
1990. This may be why the FDI stock and OECD M&amp;A samples have only 
one variable between them that comes in with an inclusion probability over 
50%, though a possible alternative explanation is that bilateral FDI patterns are 
largely driven by slow-moving or time-invariant factors that are then differenced 
out of these regressions. However, the worldwide M&amp;A sample still has over 
1,200 observations and finds 12 variables to have inclusion probabilities over 
50%. What we find most important is that these high-inclusion probabilities 
in the first-differenced worldwide M&amp;A sample are largely the same ones as 
we have found throughout the many varied permutations we have evaluated in 
this paper: GDP-related variables, skilled-labour variables and trade agreements. 
Distance and cultural distance factors do not show up in this table because 
first-differencing leaves no (or virtually no) variation from which to identify the 
impact of these factors. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 805 </p>

<p>TABLE 7 
Inclusion probabilities above 50% for OECD and worldwide samples (logged and first-differenced 
2000 data) </p>

<p>OECD sample 
Worldwide sample </p>

<p>Variable 
FDI stock 
Cross-border M&amp;A 
Cross-border M&amp;A </p>

<p>PARENT real GDP per capita 
96 
17 
2 
PARENT real GDP 
2 
22 
100 
PARENT remoteness 
1 
0 
97 
PARENT urban concentration 
0 
44 
100 
HOST real GDP 
0 
8 
100 
PARENT education level 
0 
2 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
0 
1 
100 
Service sector agreement 
0 
0 
100 
Customs union 
0 
0 
97 
GDP similarity 
0 
6 
96 
HOST real GDP per capita 
0 
1 
97 
PARENT skill level 
0 
1 
92 
HOST skill level 
0 
17 
78 
Observations 
244 
244 
1,246 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays all variables that have at least a 50% inclusion probability in one of the 
listed specifications. Instances where the inclusion probability is 50% or higher are in bold. </p>

<p>5.5. Robustness to an alternative parameter prior 
The results presented in 5.4 were generated for a specific choice of parameter 
prior distribution, namely those suggested in FLS, as described in section 3. It 
is well known that BMA results can be sensitive to parameter priors, although, 
for the relatively large sample sizes available in our application, this sensitivity 
should be muted. To verify this, we also present results from an alternative prior 
specification known as the Unit Information Prior (UIP). The UIP is designed to 
contain roughly the same amount of information as a typical single observation 
(Kass and Wasserman 1995). EPR (2011) argue for the UIP as a reasonable 
"default" prior based on evidence that it outperforms the prior of FLS for 
prediction. As discussed in Kass and Wasserman (1995) and Raftery (1995), 
the UIP suggests a convenient approximation to the marginal likelihood based 
on the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC), which makes this prior simple to 
implement. 
Table 8 compares results from the FLS parameter priors to those based on 
the UIP for the FDI stock measure of FDI and the log-levels specification. 
The table displays all variables that receive a 50% or higher inclusion proba-
bility for at least one of the alternative priors. For ease in reading the table, 
we bold the instances where the inclusion probability is 50% or higher. The 
inclusion probabilities suggest that the BMA results are not very sensitive to 
parameter priors, which again is what we might have expected given the rela-
tively large sample size. In particular, the inclusion probabilities are generally 
close in magnitude for the two alternative priors, and there is no case where the </p>



<p>TABLE 8 
Inclusion probabilities above 50% using alternative parameter priors (FDI stock -logged 2000 data) </p>

<p>Variable 
FLS 
UIP </p>

<p>PARENT real GDP 
100 
100 
HOST real GDP 
100 
100 
Distance 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP per capita 
100 
100 
HOST remoteness 
100 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
100 
100 
Customs union 
97 
97 
HOST skill level 
97 
99 
HOST trade openness 
95 
97 
Common official language 
92 
93 
HOST is oil country 
92 
97 
Squared skill difference 
89 
97 
Colonial relationship 
87 
95 
HOST legal institutions 
85 
94 
HOST corporate tax 
67 
84 
HOST urban concentration 
52 
67 
PARENT capital per worker 
36 
50 
Observations 
1,066 
1,066 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays all variables that have 50% or higher inclusion probability for at least 
one of two alternative specifications for parameter priors. Instances where the inclusion probability 
is 50% or higher are in bold. Results are for the FDI stock dataset and log-levels specification. FLS 
refers to priors suggested by Fernandez, Ley and Steel (2001a), as described in section 3. UIP refers 
to the Unit Information Prior of Kass and Wasserman (1995), as described in section 5. </p>

<p>two priors yield radically different conclusions regarding the importance of a 
covariate. </p>

<p>5.6. Robustness to a nonlinear specification 
Due to the computational intensity of the BMA approach, our analysis to this 
point was restricted to linear regression models. However, there are some po-
tential issues with a linear specification for the measures of FDI used as the 
dependent variable. First, there are many country pairs for which the FDI mea-
sure is zero. This creates an issue in the log-level regressions, as the logarithm of 
these observations is undefined. In the results presented above, we retained these 
observations in the sample by adding a small constant to each FDI measure 
before taking logarithms. Alternatively, we could have eliminated these obser-
vations from the sample. As is discussed in Santos Silva and Tenreyro (2006), 
each of these solutions might distort inference from that produced by an appro-
priate nonlinear model estimated on the levels of the dependent variable. These 
authors argue for the use of Poisson regression methods to effectively deal with 
zero observations. Second, our measure of FDI based on M&amp;A activity is a dis-
crete count variable, a fact that is ignored when working in the linear regression 
framework. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 807 </p>

<p>In this section we evaluate the robustness of the conclusions regarding the 
determinants of FDI when a nonlinear model is used to link FDI to potential 
covariates. We focus on M&amp;A counts as the FDI measure, as this data displays 
both of the features discussed above-zero observations and discreteness. We use 
a negative binomial regression to model the M&amp;A counts. This framework models 
the level of the M&amp;A counts directly, which eliminates any issues associated with 
the need to take logarithms of zero observations. Also, the negative binomial 
distribution is a discrete distribution with a natural interpretation for count 
data. </p>

<p>16   Extending the MC 
3 algorithm discussed in section 3 for linear regression mod-
els to conduct BMA for negative binomial regressions is conceptually straightfor-
ward. Specifically, the only change is that the marginal likelihood in (3) is replaced 
by the marginal likelihood for the negative binomial model. Unfortunately, unlike 
the case of the linear regression model with natural conjugate priors, the marginal 
likelihood for the negative binomial model is not available analytically and needs 
to be approximated. One approach would be to compute a simulation-consistent 
estimate of the marginal likelihood using Markov chain Monte Carlo techniques. 
However, when incorporated inside of the large number of simulations necessary 
for the MC 
3 algorithm, this would be very computationally demanding. Instead, 
we use an asymptotic approximation to the marginal likelihood based on the BIC. 
This requires only the maximum likelihood estimates of the negative binomial 
regression and can be computed relatively quickly. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Table 9 shows the posterior inclusion probabilities computed for the log-level 
linear regression model, along with those based on the negative binomial model, 
when we use the sample of cross-border M&amp;A counts across OECD countries, 
i.e., the sample identical to the one used in the last column of table 4. We use the 
sample of OECD countries, rather than the larger worldwide sample, to reduce 
the computational time needed to calculate the SIC for the negative binomial 
specification. Results across the linear and negative binomial models are very 
similar, suggesting model misspecification bias from running linear models in this 
setting is small. Out of 52 potential covariates, there are only four instances where 
the inclusion probability of a covariate is very high in one specification but close 
to zero in the other. In particular, urban concentration of the parent country 
and host country oil production have very high inclusion probabilities in the 
linear specification but inclusion probabilities near zero in the negative binomial </p>

<p>16 A common starting point for modelling count data is the Poisson regression model. However, 
our sample of M&amp;A count data has sample variance far greater than sample mean, suggesting a 
model that incorporates this overdispersion is better suited for M&amp;A counts. The negative 
binomial regression model, which arises from a natural extension of the Poisson regression, is a 
popular choice for overdispersed count data in the applied literature. Indeed, we experienced 
substantial convergence issues when estimating a simple Poisson specification, which further 
indicated that it is important to model overdispersion in these data. 
17 The BIC approximation to the marginal likelihood is a common choice in applied work. See, for 
example, Brock, Durlauf and West (2003) and Doppelhofer, Miller and Sala-i-Martin (2004). 
For additional discussion of the BIC-based approach to model averaging, see Raftery (1995). </p>



<p>TABLE 9 
Inclusion probabilities for linear and negative binomial specifications (cross-border M&amp;A for OECD 
sample -logged 2000 data) </p>

<p>Variable 
Linear model 
Negative binomial </p>

<p>HOST real GDP 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP 
100 
100 
Distance 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP per capita 
100 
100 
HOST remoteness 
100 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
100 
100 
Customs union 
100 
100 
HOST skill level 
100 
100 
Common official language 
100 
100 
PARENT remoteness 
100 
100 
PARENT skill level 
100 
95 
PARENT urban concentration 
98 
2 
Colonial relationship 
97 
100 
HOST is oil country 
94 
0 
HOST years to resolve insolvency 
91 
100 
Squared education difference 
38 
95 
HOST political rights 
12 
100 
HOST country trade openness 
2 
64 
Similarity of HOST and PARENT real GDP 
1 
98 
HOST legal institutions 
1 
53 
Observations 
1,066 
1,066 </p>

<p>NOTES: The table displays the inclusion probability for every potential covariate listed in 
table 2, with the exception of the interaction terms, which become perfectly collinear when variables 
are logged. </p>

<p>specification, while GDP similarity and host country political rights are estimated 
to have high inclusion probabilities in the negative binomial specification but 
inclusion probabilities near zero in the linear model. Three other variables, the 
squared education difference, host country trade openness and host country legal 
institutions, receive more support in the negative binomial specification, with 
inclusion probabilities roughly 50 percentage points above those for the linear 
model. Outside of these seven exceptions, which is less than 15% of the covariates 
we consider, the average absolute difference in inclusion probabilities across the 
linear and negative binomial models is just 2.6 percentage points. Also, it is 
notable that of the five variables for which the negative binomial model provides 
more support than the linear model, four have high inclusion probabilities for the 
linear model applied to the FDI stock or worldwide sample M&amp;A count data. 
Thus, the negative binomial specification is not revealing a substantial number of 
additional relevant covariates beyond those identified elsewhere in our analysis. </p>

<p>5.7. BMA on trade flows 
A related BMA analysis we can perform using our covariates is an examina-
tion of the determinants of trade flows. This is an interesting litmus test for the 
BMA procedure, as we would be concerned, for example, if standard gravity 
variables did not have high inclusion probabilities for trade flows using our BMA </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 809 </p>

<p>TABLE 10 
Inclusion probabilities above 50% for explaining FDI vs. bilateral trade (worldwide sample -logged 
2000 data) </p>

<p>Variable 
Cross-border M&amp;A 
Bilateral trade </p>

<p>PARENT real GDP 
100 
100 
HOST real GDP 
100 
100 
Distance 
100 
100 
PARENT real GDP per capita 
100 
100 
HOST remoteness 
100 
100 
PARENT remoteness 
100 
100 
Regional trade agreement 
100 
100 
Customs union 
100 
100 
Colonial relationship 
100 
94 
HOST education level 
100 
13 
Double taxation treaty 
100 
100 
Bilateral investment treaty 
100 
100 
Parent urban concentration 
100 
1 
Common official language 
99 
96 
HOST corporate tax 
99 
20 
HOST time to resolve insolvency 
98 
6 
Squared education difference 
97 
1 
Service sector agreement 
97 
2 
Contiguous border 
95 
19 
HOST is oil country 
92 
62 
PARENT education level 
85 
100 
PARENT skill level 
76 
1 
HOST skill level 
71 
0 
Similarity of HOST and PARENT real GDP 
54 
100 
PARENT trade openness 
4 
98 
Squared skill difference 
3 
100 
HOST trade openness 
2 
51 
HOST land area 
2 
95 
HOST legal institutions 
1 
100 
HOST urban concentration 
1 
60 
HOST Internet users 
1 
100 
HOST domestic credit 
1 
70 
HOST time to start business 
1 
99 </p>

<p>Observations 
3,429 
3,429 </p>

<p>methods. The analysis also provides a comparison of the determinants of FDI and 
trade flows within the same framework. We gather data on bilateral trade flows 
from the dataset connected with Rose and Spiegel (2011) and made available on-
line by Andrew Rose at faculty.haas.berkeley.edu/arose/RecRes.htm#Software. 
Specifically, the data are CIF imports measured in US$, taken from Interna-
tional Financial Statistics' <rs type="software">Direction of Trade CD-ROM</rs>, deflated by U.S. CPI 
for All Urban Consumers (CPI-U), all items, 1982 to 1984 = 100. For compari-
son purposes, we sample the year 2000 for the same observations we use for our 
cross-border M&amp;A results, which yielded the largest sample size out of all the 
FDI measures. 
Table 10 provides inclusion probabilities for our BMA analysis of trade flows, 
as well as repeats the cross-border M&amp;A inclusion probabilities for comparison </p>



<p>purposes. The table displays all variables that receive a 50% or higher inclusion 
probability for explaining at least one of either trade flows or M&amp;A counts. 
Reassuringly, our BMA analysis of trade flows yields results that are quite in line 
with accepted practice on how to specify trade flows. The gravity variables and 
typical frictions (including trade and FDI agreements) show very strong support. 
This also means that our analysis suggests very similar determinants for trade and 
cross-border M&amp;A, though there is much less support generally for endowment 
terms with trade than for cross-border M&amp;A. The biggest differences between the 
two come in which business cost, infrastructure and other host-country attributes 
matter for trade versus cross-border M&amp;A. For example, the number of Internet 
users, legal institutions and domestic credit have high inclusion probabilities for 
trade but not for cross-border M&amp;A. 
This is not the first BMA analysis of trade flows. Eicher, Henn and 
Papageorgiou (2012) use BMA methods to examine the impact of preferential 
trade agreements on trade flows. They estimate very similar inclusion probabili-
ties for the common overlap of variables between their study and ours, including 
strong support for GDP terms, geographic features (such as distance) and cul-
tural distance terms. </p>

<p>6. Conclusion </p>

<p>The prior literature examining the determinants of FDI comprises a limited 
number of studies that typically propose fairly parsimonious specifications, but 
quite varied in their specifications and FDI measurement. This suggests signifi-
cant uncertainty in the true model of bilateral cross-country FDI patterns. Our 
approach is to provide some needed systematic investigation of the determinants 
of FDI by using Bayesian Model Averaging. Our analysis does not support the 
inclusion of many variables found in prior FDI studies and suggests that the sta-
tistical importance of the main focus variables in many prior studies is not robust 
to considering a much wider set of covariates. The results also suggest a fairly 
parsimonious FDI specification comprised of mainly gravity variables, cultural 
distance factors, parent-country per capita GDP, relative labour endowments 
and trade agreements. 
Of note, our results reflect much less support for government policies to 
encourage FDI, as there is little robust evidence in our analysis that policy 
variables controlled by the host country (such as multilateral trade costs, business 
costs, infrastructure or political institutions) have an effect on FDI. Exceptions 
include policies that are often negotiated bilateral agreements, including trade 
agreements, bilateral investment treaties, customs unions and service agreements 
in the case of M&amp;A. However, we caution that exogeneity of these variables may 
be more in doubt than many of the other covariates we consider. </p>

<p>Determinants of foreign direct investment 811 </p>







</text></tei>