<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10614-014-9465-4" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Standard solution methods of DSGE models do not necessarily deliver 
minimal state space forms. When the ABCD form is non-minimal, the conditions 
in the literature are not necessary for the existence of a VAR representation of the 
observables. In this paper we present necessary and sufficient conditions that are valid 
in general, and hence can be applied to minimal and non-minimal ABCD forms. If 
the state space form is minimal, our conditions coincide with those in the literature. 
These results also clarify that it is possible to have unstable eigenvalues together with 
a (possibly finite) VAR representation of the observables. </p>

<p>Economic shocks of DSGE models cannot always be recovered from VARs. This situ-
ation has been discussed e.g. in Chari et al. (2005), Christiano et al. (2006), Kapetanios </p>

<p>Electronic supplementary material The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s10614-014-9465-4) 
contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users. </p>

<p>M. Franchi 
Sapienza University of Rome, P.le A. Moro 5, 00185 Rome, Italy 
e-mail: massimo.franchi@uniroma1.it </p>

<p>P. Paruolo (B) 
Joint Research Centre, European Commission, Via E.Fermi 2749, 21027 Ispra, VA, Italy 
e-mail: paolo.paruolo@jrc.ec.europa.eu </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>et al. (2007), Ravenna (2007), and it is related to the non-fundamentalness of economic 
models, see Hansen and Sargent (1980), Lippi and Reichlin (1993, 1994) for early 
treatments of the problem. 
Solutions of linear (or linearized) DSGE models can be expressed in linear state 
space form using several solution methods, such as Binder and Pesaran (1997), Uhlig 
(1999), Klein (2000), Sims (2001). In the following, we refer to the linear state space 
form as the ABCD form. When the number of shocks is equal to the number of 
observables and the matrix that loads the former into the latter is non-singular, the 
ABCD form is called square. We observe that the ABCD form of the solution dynamics 
need not be minimal, i.e. it may involve a non-minimal number of state variables. This 
is illustrated for example in Komunjer and Ng (2011), who show that the state space 
solutions in Christiano et al. (2005), An and Schorfheide (2007), Smets and Wouters 
(2007), García-Cicco et al. (2010) are all non-minimal. 
In this paper we investigate population conditions for fundamentalness of the ABCD 
form and for the existence of a finite VAR representation of the observables. 1 Fun-
damentalness is currently checked using the 'poor man's invertibility condition' in 
Fernández-Villaverde et al. (2007); applications of this approach can be found in 
Leeper et al. (2013), Schmitt-Grohé (2010), Kurmann and Otrok (2011), Sims (2012) 
inter alia. The poor man's invertibility condition consists in the stability of the associate 
state matrix, F say, i.e. the state matrix in the system in which the role of inputs and 
outputs is interchanged, see Bart et al. (2008). Conditions for the VAR to be of finite 
order are given in Ravenna (2007), where a 'unimodularity condition' is proposed as a 
check. This condition consists in the unimodularity of the matrix polynomial I − Fz, 
z ∈ C, 2 or equivalently in the nilpotency of F, see Franchi and Vidotto (2013). 
When the square ABCD form is minimal, we show that the poor man's invertibility 
condition and the unimodularity condition are proper checks, i.e. they are necessary 
and sufficient conditions for fundamentalness. When the ABCD form is non-minimal, 
we find that the poor man's invertibility condition and the unimodularity condition 
are not necessary. In other words F can be unstable while the square ABCD form is 
fundamental and I − Fz can be non-unimodular while the square ABCD form has a 
finite order VAR representation. 
Because in current economic practice systems are not always in minimal state space 
form, in this paper we present alternative orthogonality conditions that are necessary 
and sufficient and which hold in possibly non-minimal square systems. This provides 
a check that does not require to transform the system to minimal ABCD form. These 
orthogonality conditions involve the eigenvectors associated with eigenvalues of the 
associate state matrix F, and correspond to the case where there exist states that are 
cancelled in the VAR representation of the observables. For fundamentalness, the 
orthogonality conditions must apply to all the unstable eigenvalues, while for the </p>

<p>1 Recall that a square ABCD form is called fundamental if there exist a (possibly infinite order) VAR 
representation for the observables with respect to the economic shocks, see Hansen and Sargent (1980), 
Brockwell and Davis (1987), Lippi and Reichlin (1993, 1994). 
2 A matrix polynomial is called unimodular if its determinant is a nonzero constant, see e.g. Antsaklis and 
Michel (2007, p. 283). </p>



<p>VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>existence of a finite VAR representation, the orthogonality conditions must hold for 
every nonzero eigenvalue. 
When the orthogonality conditions hold, we find that the eigenvalues of the associate 
state matrix F are also eigenvalues of the state matrix, A say. This implies that when 
the eigenvalues of A and F are different, the orthogonality conditions do not hold. 
This provides a simplified strategy based solely on eigenvalues of A and F. Finally 
we find that if the ABCD form is minimal, the orthogonality conditions coincide 
with the poor man's invertibility condition and the unimodularity condition. This 
shows that the present orthogonality conditions are an extension of the conditions in 
the literature that apply to general (i.e. not necessarily minimal) linear state space 
forms. 
Therefore, invertibility of linearized DSGE models should be checked either using 
the present orthogonality conditions or by first transforming the state space form to a 
minimal representation and then by applying the poor man's invertibility condition to 
the minimal state space form. Similarly, existence of a finite VAR representation should 
be checked either using the present orthogonality conditions or by first transforming the 
state space form to a minimal representation and then by applying the unimodularity 
condition to the minimal state space form, see Franchi (2013) for an illustration on 
the Smets and Wouters (2007) model. 
The results of the paper employ well-known concepts from systems theory, see e.g. 
Kailath (1980), Antsaklis and Michel (2007). The possibility to have cancellations of 
the type discussed in this paper in non-minimal state space systems was noticed by 
Rosenbrock (1970) inter alia, see his remark after Theorem 1.2, page 38 and Corollary 
3, page 115. Here we give explicit algebraic condition on the system matrices that 
characterizes this situation. These tools are meant to be used by macro-economists, 
who deal with non-minimal state space representations of linearized DGSE models in 
practice and who are interested in determining if the observables in their model admit 
a VAR representation. 
The results in this paper are also related to cointegration. 3 The possibility to have 
unstable states within a non-minimal state space gives in fact one more way to 
incorporate cointegration in DGSE models, by allowing unit-root stochastic trends 
in the states that can be canceled in the stable VAR representation of observ-
ables. 
The rest of the paper is organized as follows. Section 2 introduces the square 
case. Section 3 shows that fundamentalness and the existence of a finite order VAR 
can be characterized in terms of an appropriate transfer function. Section 4 presents 
the orthogonality conditions. Section 5 specializes results to minimal square ABCD 
forms, showing that for minimal state spaces the orthogonality conditions coincide 
with the poor man's invertibility condition and the unimodularity condition. Section 6 
concludes. All proofs are collected in the Appendix. </p>

<p>3 Inversions of matrix polynomials are used in the representation theory for non-stationary processes 
developed in Johansen (1988, 1996, 2009); see also Franchi and Paruolo (2011a, b). Howlett (1982) focuses 
on a similar problem in the context of input retrieval for linear systems. </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>2 Square ABCD Forms </p>

<p>Consider an equilibrium dynamics of a linearized DSGE model with representation </p>

<p>x t = Ax t−1 + Bw t 
y t = C x t−1 + Dw t 
(1) </p>

<p>where x t has dimension n x × 1, y t has dimension n y × 1 and w t is a white noise of 
dimension n w × 1 with identity covariance matrix. A is called the state matrix and we 
refer to (1) as the ABCD form. 
The following assumption is maintained throughout the paper. </p>

<p>Assumption 2.1 (Square ABCD form). The matrix D is square and invertible. </p>

<p>In square ABCD forms the number of economic shocks is equal to the number of 
observables and the matrix that loads the shocks into the observables is non-singular. 
In this case one can substitute w t = D −1 (y t − C x t−1 ) in the first equation in (1) and 
rewrite the square ABCD form in the 'associate state space form', see e.g. Ch.2.2 in 
Bart et al. (2008), </p>

<p>x t = F x t−1 + B D −1 y t , 
F = A − B D −1 C, 
w t = −D −1 C x t−1 + D −1 y t , 
(2) </p>

<p>where the role of input and output of system (1) are interchanged; F is called the 
'associate state matrix'. 
The ABCD form is called minimal, see e.g. Ch.6 in Kailath (1980) or Ch.2 in 
Hannan and Deistler (1988), if the dimension of x t is as small as possibile. Minimality 
holds if and only if the ABCD form is both controllable and observable, i.e. if rank C = 
rank O = n x , where </p>

<p>C = </p>

<p>B AB · · · A n x −1 B 
, 
O = </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎜ 
⎜ 
⎜ 
⎝ </p>

<p>C 
C A 
. . . </p>

<p>C A n x −1 </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎟ 
⎟ 
⎟ 
⎠ 
(3) </p>

<p>are respectively called controllability and observability matrix. 
Some remarks are in order. </p>

<p>Remark 2.2 The state matrix A may be stable or unstable. 4 Cases with unstable A are 
interesting from an economic point of view because they arise from models with unit 
roots in the endogenous state variables as well as those with non-stationary exogenous 
shocks, as in Chang et al. (2007). </p>

<p>4 A square matrix is called stable when all its eigenvalues are stable, i.e. of modulus strictly less than one; 
if it has unstable eigenvalues then it is called unstable. </p>



<p>VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>Remark 2.3 The ABCD form may be minimal or non-minimal. Non-minimal ABCD 
forms are natural outcomes of standard solution methods: for example, Komunjer 
and Ng (2011) show that, using gensys and dynare, the ABCD forms in 
Christiano et al. (2005), An and Schorfheide (2007), Smets and Wouters (2007), 
García-Cicco et al. (2010) are all non-minimal. </p>

<p>3 Transfer Function </p>

<p>In square ABCD forms, it is of interest, see e.g. Fernández-Villaverde et al. (2007), 
to characterize situations in which the economic shocks can be recovered from the 
infinite history of the observable variables, i.e. cases in which y t admits an infinite 
order VAR representation </p>

<p>A(L)y t = u t , 
A(z) = I n y − </p>

<p>∞ </p>



<p>j=1 </p>

<p>A j z j , 
u t = Mw t , 
(4) </p>

<p>where the sequence {A j } ∞ 
j=1 is absolutely summable and M is a non-singular matrix 
that links economic shocks and reduced form errors. When (4) holds, (1) is said to 
be invertible (and w t fundamental), see Hansen and Sargent (1980), Brockwell and 
Davis (1987), Lippi and Reichlin (1993, 1994). Furthermore it is of interest, see e.g. 
Ravenna (2007), to have conditions that describe when the VAR representation of y t 
has finite order, i.e. when A(z) is a matrix polynomial. 
In this section we link the existence of a (possibly finite) VAR representation of y t 
to properties of the transfer function from y t to Dw t , T (L)y t = Dw t , implied by the 
associate state space form (2), where </p>

<p>T (z) = I n y − C(I n x − Fz) −1 B D −1 z, 
z ∈ C. 
(5) </p>

<p>The relationship between the VAR representation of y t and the transfer function 
T (z) is presented next; in the following we say that a function is regular if it is finite 
on the unit disc, i.e. for all z ∈ C such that |z| &lt; 1 + δ, for some δ &gt; 0, see Johansen 
(2009) for a similar notion of regularity. Remark that the coefficients of the expansion 
of a regular function f (z) = 
∞ 
j=0 f j z j are geometrically decreasing and hence 
absolutely summable. </p>

<p>Proposition 3.1 (Transfer function conditions). The vector of observables y t admits 
an infinite order VAR representation if and only if T (z) is regular. Moreover, the VAR 
representation is of finite order if and only if T (z) is a matrix polynomial. In either case, 
the coefficients of the VAR representation of y t and the mapping between economic 
shocks and reduced form errors in (4) are given by A(z) = T (z) and M = D. </p>

<p>The properties of the matrix function T (z) depend on those of (I − Fz) −1 = 
adj(I − Fz)/|I − Fz|. The roots of |I − Fz| = 0 are poles of (I − Fz) −1 ; because 
|I − Fz| = 0 if and only if z = λ −1 
u , where {λ u } are the nonzero eigenvalues of 
F, if F is stable then (I − Fz) −1 is regular because min u |λ −1 
u | &gt; 1. Hence T (z) </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>is regular and, by Proposition 3.1, this implies that y t admits an infinite order VAR 
representation. Moreover, if F is nilpotent then I − Fz is unimodular and (I − Fz) −1 
is a matrix polynomial; hence T (z) is a matrix polynomial and, by Proposition 3.1, 
this implies that y t admits a finite order VAR representation. 
Observe that T (z) can be regular even if F is unstable and it can be a matrix 
polynomial even if F is not nilpotent. In fact, when F is unstable, (I − Fz) −1 has 
poles in the (closed) unit disc and thus it is non-regular, but those singularities may be 
absent from C(I −Fz) −1 B due to the presence of B and C. In this case C(I −Fz) −1 B is 
regular and thus the same holds for T (z). This possibility is illustrated in the following 
example, which serves as a running example in the rest of the paper. </p>

<p>Example 3.2 (Running example). This is a special case of the model in Chang et al. 
(2007). Let n x = 4, n w = n y = 2 and </p>

<p>A = 
1 0 </p>

<p>0 
I 2 </p>

<p>
, 
B = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 I 2 
I 2 </p>

<p>
, 
C = 
1 2 
, 
D = 2 + 
1 
2 
I 2 , </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>1 = </p>

<p>
1 1 
− 1 
2 − 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>
, 
, 2 = </p>

<p>
1 1 
1 1 </p>

<p>
. </p>

<p>Observe that D is non-singular so that the ABCD form is square. Moreover F = 
A − B D −1 C has eigenvalues {1, 3/5, 0, 0}, and (I − Fz) −1 has a pole at z = 1 and 
thus it is non-regular. At the same time T (z) is regular, because </p>

<p>C(I n x − Fz) −1 B = 
5 
4(3z − 5) </p>

<p>
4z − 6 4z − 6 
z − 3 z − 3 </p>



<p>has no pole at z = 1 (it only has a pole at z = 5 
3 ) and hence the expansion T (z) = 
∞ 
j=0 T j z j has absolutely summable coefficients. This illustrates that one can have 
fundamentalness together with unstable F. </p>

<p>Similarly, one can construct examples in which B and C cancel every pole of 
(I − Fz) −1 so that C(I − Fz) −1 B is a matrix polynomial, which in turn implies 
that the same holds for T (z). This shows that the poor man's invertibility condition in 
Fernández-Villaverde et al. (2007) and the unimodularity condition in Ravenna (2007) 
are not necessary conditions for a VAR representation of a square ABCD form. The 
next proposition proves that they are sufficient conditions. </p>

<p>Proposition 3.3 (Sufficient conditions). If F is stable, then y t admits an infinite order 
VAR representation; the converse does not hold. If F is nilpotent, then y t admits a 
finite order VAR representation; the converse does not hold. </p>



<p>VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>4 Conditions for the Existence of a VAR Representation </p>

<p>In this section we state necessary and sufficient conditions for fundamentalness and 
for the existence of a finite order VAR, in the form of orthogonality conditions or rank 
conditions. These conditions apply both to minimal and non-minimal square ABCD 
forms, and they are based on the idea of pole cancellations in C(I − Fz) −1 B in the 
matrix function T (z). 
We introduce the following notation: let λ u , u = 1, . . . , q, be all the distinct nonzero 
eigenvalues of F and apply the partial fraction expansion 5 </p>

<p>(I − Fz) −1 = P(z) + H (z), 
P(z) = </p>

<p>q </p>



<p>u=1 </p>

<p>P u (z), 
P u (z) = </p>

<p>m u </p>



<p>j=1 </p>

<p>P λ u ,m u − j 
(1 − λ u z) j , </p>

<p>P λ u ,0 = 0. 
(6) </p>

<p>Here H (z) is a matrix polynomial, P(z) is the sum of the principal parts P u (z) of 
(I − Fz) −1 at z = λ −1 
u and m u is the order of the pole of (I − Fz) −1 at z = λ −1 
u . Note 
that zero eigenvalues of F are absent from |I − Fz| and hence they do not appear in 
the principal part P(z). A characterization of the pole cancellations in C(I − Fz) −1 B 
due to the presence of B and C is given in the following Lemma, which define our 
orthogonality conditions. </p>

<p>Lemma 4.1 (Orthogonality conditions). T (z) has no pole at z = λ −1 
u if and only if 
the orthogonality conditions </p>

<p>C P λ u ,m u − j B = 0, 
j = 1, . . . , m u , 
(7) </p>

<p>hold. If the orthogonality conditions hold, then λ u is also an eigenvalue of A. </p>

<p>Because P u (z) fully characterizes the singularity of (I − Fz) −1 at z = λ −1 
u , in 
order for C(I − Fz) −1 B to have no pole at z = λ −1 
u , B and C must be such that 
C P u (z)B = 0. This requires each coefficient of the principal part to be 0 when pre 
and post-multiplied by C and B. Lemma 4.1 also states that if a pole cancellation 
occurs for a given eigenvalue of F, then this must also be an eigenvalue of A; this 
observation leads to the following necessary conditions. </p>

<p>Proposition 4.2 (Necessary conditions). The vector of observables y t admits an infi-
nite order VAR representation only if each unstable eigenvalue of F is also an eigen-
value of A. Moreover, the VAR representation is of finite order only if each nonzero 
eigenvalue of F is also an eigenvalue of A. </p>

<p>The main characterization result is stated next. </p>

<p>5 See e.g. Fischer and Lieb (2012, Ch. III.2). </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>Proposition 4.3 (Necessary and sufficient orthogonality conditions). The vector of 
observables y t admits an infinite order VAR representation if and only if the orthogo-
nality conditions hold at each unstable eigenvalue of F. Moreover, the VAR represen-
tation is of finite order if and only if the orthogonality conditions hold at each nonzero 
eigenvalue of F. </p>

<p>An infinite order VAR representation requires the cancellation of all the poles 
associated with the unstable eigenvalues of F; the VAR has finite order when the 
cancellation also involves the stable nonzero eigenvalues. Note that if all eigenvalues 
are stable, the first orthogonality condition for invertibility is automatically satisfied 
because there are no unstable eigenvalues. Similarly, if F is nilpotent, all eigenvalues 
are equal to 0, so that q = 0 in (6) and this implies P(z) = 0; hence also the second 
orthogonality condition for the existence of a finite order VAR is automatically satis-
fied. This illustrates that the poor man's invertibility condition (and the unimodularity 
condition) implies the orthogonality conditions in Proposition 4.3 but not viceversa. 
That is, in square ABCD forms the former is stronger than the latter, and that the 
conditions differ. 
An equivalent and more directly implementable rank condition is provided next. 6 </p>

<p>Proposition 4.4 (Rank conditions). Let λ u be a nonzero eigenvalue of F, rank decom-
pose F − λ u I = αβ , where α, β are n x × r full column rank matrices, and define 
α ⊥ , β ⊥ as bases 7 of the orthogonal complements of the column spaces spanned by 
α and β respectively. Then the orthogonality condition holds at λ u if and only if 
rank(α 
⊥ B) &lt; n x − r or rank(Cβ ⊥ ) &lt; n x − r (or both). </p>

<p>In the light of this equivalence one can thus restate the main characterization result 
in Proposition 4.3 replacing orthogonality conditions with rank conditions. </p>

<p>Proposition 4.5 (Necessary and sufficient rank conditions). The vector of observables 
y t admits an infinite order VAR representation if and only if the rank condition holds 
at each unstable eigenvalue of F. Moreover, the VAR representation is of finite order 
if and only if the rank condition holds at each nonzero eigenvalue of F. </p>

<p>A <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> script that implements this check is available in the Additional Material 
to the present paper. </p>

<p>Example 4.6 (Continuation of Example 3.2). We illustrate our results using the run-
ning example, where the eigenvalues of F and A are σ F = {1, 3/5, 0, 0} and 
σ A = {1, 1, 1/2, 0} respectively. Because 3/5 is not an eigenvalue of A, the nec-
essary condition in Proposition 4.2 is not satisfied and one immediately sees that y t 
does not have a finite order VAR representation. Because 1 is also an eigenvalue of 
A, the necessary condition in Proposition 4.2 is satisfied and we proceed to check the 
rank condition for the eigenvalue equal to 1. </p>

<p>6 Here and in the following a indicates the conjugate transpose of a, which reduces to transposition for a 
real. 
7 Hence of full column rank n x − r . </p>



<p>VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>Rank-decomposing F − I = αβ , where α, β have dimension 4 × 3, and defining 
α ⊥ , β ⊥ of dimension 4 × 1 as bases of the orthogonal complements of col α and col β, 
one finds α ⊥ = (−3 : −3 : 2 : 1) and β ⊥ = (0 : 0 : 1 : −1) . Because </p>

<p>C = </p>

<p>
1 
1 
1 1 
− 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>− 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 1 </p>

<p>
, </p>

<p>one has Cβ ⊥ = 0 and hence the rank condition in Proposition 4.4 is satisfied at the 
unstable eigenvalue equal to 1. This correctly indicates, see Proposition 4.5, that the 
vector of observables y t has an infinite order VAR representation. </p>

<p>5 Minimal Square ABCD Forms </p>

<p>In this section we treat the special case of square minimal ABCD forms. Minimality 
could be directly obtained as a property of the DSGE's solution or it could be derived 
from a non-minimal solution by eliminating irrelevant states, as described e.g. in 
Rosenbrock (1970). Here we show that if the square ABCD form is minimal, then the 
orthogonality conditions coincide with the poor man's invertibility condition and with 
the unimodularity condition. We conclude this section by illustrating the result via the 
running example. </p>

<p>Proposition 5.1 (Equivalence in minimal state space forms). If the square ABCD form 
is minimal, then the vector of observables y t admits an infinite order VAR represen-
tation if and only if F is stable. Moreover, the VAR representation is of finite order if 
and only if F is nilpotent. </p>

<p>When the ABCD form is minimal, C P u (z)B = 0 for any eigenvalue and hence no 
cancellation is possibile. Then each pole of (I − Fz) −1 is a pole of C(I − Fz) −1 B and 
the orthogonality condition for an infinite order VAR holds (trivially) if and only if F 
has no unstable eigenvalues. Similarly, it holds (trivially) for a finite order VAR holds 
if and only if all eigenvalues are equal to zero. This shows that when the square ABCD 
form is minimal, the poor man's invertibility condition and the unimodularity condition 
are equivalent to the orthogonality conditions and thus they become necessary and 
sufficient. </p>

<p>Example 5.2 (Continuation of Examples 3.2 and 4.6). We illustrate the last result on 
the running example, in which the controllability and observability matrix in (3) are 
such that rank C = 4 and rank O = 2. The ABCD form is thus controllable but not 
observable, and hence non-minimal. 
A minimal representation can be derived as follows; here we use the subscript m 
to index quantities in the minimal state space representation. Write C as C = C m v , 
where </p>

<p>C m = </p>

<p>
1 
1 
− 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>
, 
v = </p>

<p>
1 1 0 0 
0 0 1 1 </p>

<p>
, </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>and observe that v A = A m v , where A m = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
0 1 </p>

<p>
. Define x m,t = v x t and </p>

<p>B m = v B, pre-multiply the state equation by v and write the system as </p>

<p>x m,t = A m x m,t−1 + B m w t </p>

<p>y t = C m x m,t−1 + Dw t . </p>

<p>This system is minimal; in fact the controllability and observability matrices of this sys-
tem satisfy rank C m = rank O m = 2. Obviously, C A j B = C m v A j B = C m A </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>m v B = 
C m A </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>m B m and hence the so-called Markov coefficients of the two systems are equal. 
We next apply Proposition 5.1 to this square minimal ABCD form. The eigenvalues 
of F m are {3/5, 0}; hence they are all stable, and the poor man's invertibility condition 
correctly signals that y t has an infinite order VAR representation. The unimodularity 
condition does not apply, because F m has one nonzero eigenvalue. This correctly 
signals that the system does not have a finite order VAR representation. </p>

<p>6 Conclusions </p>

<p>Standard solution methods of DSGE models do not necessarily deliver minimal state 
space forms. When the ABCD form is non-minimal the poor man's invertibility condi-
tion in Fernández-Villaverde et al. (2007) and the unimodularity condition in Ravenna 
(2007) are not necessary for the existence of a VAR representation of the observables. 
In this paper we have presented a check that is valid in the general square case, 
and hence can be applied to minimal and non-minimal ABCD forms. This illustrates 
that it is possible to have unstable eigenvalues in the state matrix and in the associate 
state matrix together with a VAR representation; this is possible because there may 
exist irrelevant unstable states that are cancelled in the VAR representation of the 
observables. Finally we show that if the state space form is minimal, the orthogonality 
condition coincides with the poor man's invertibility condition and the unimodularity 
condition, because irrelevant states cannot exist. 
The present results show that invertibility of linearized DSGE models should be 
checked either using the present orthogonality conditions or by first transforming the 
state space form to a minimal representation and then by applying the poor man's 
invertibility condition to the minimal state space form. Similarly, existence of a finite 
VAR representation should be checked either using the present orthogonality condi-
tions or by first transforming the state space form to a minimal representation and then 
by applying the unimodularity condition to the minimal state space form. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The paper previously circulated with the title "On ABCs (and Ds) of VAR repre-
sentations of DSGE models". We thank, without implications, the following people for discussions and 
useful comments on previous versions of the paper: Andrea Attar, Søren Johansen, Marco Lippi, Daniele 
Massacci, Franco Peracchi, Frank Schorfheide, and James Stock as well as seminar participants. Financial 
support from the following institutions and grants is is gratefully acknowledged: Einaudi Institute for Eco-
nomics and Finance (EIEF), Italian MUR Prin Project 2010J3LZEN, University of Rome "La Sapienza" 
and University of Insubria. </p>



<p>VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>Appendix: Proofs </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 3.1. Observe that A(0) = T (0) = I n y . (Sufficiency.) By def-
inition. (Necessity.) If (4) holds, then w t = M −1 A(L)y t and hence T (L)y t = 
DM −1 A(L)y t , which implies M = D and T (z) = A(z). </p>

<p>
Proof of Proposition 3.3. If F is stable, then (I − Fz) −1 is regular and so is T (z); 
then apply Proposition 3.1. If F is nilpotent, then I − Fz is unimodular, (I − Fz) −1 
is a matrix polynomial and so is T (z); then apply Proposition 3.1. </p>

<p>
Proof of Lemma 4.1. Consider (5) and (6); if C P u (z)B = 0 then C(I − Fz) −1 B 
has no pole at z = λ −1 
u and hence the same holds for T (z). Conversely, assume 
T (z) has no pole at z = λ −1 
u ; then the same holds for C(I − Fz) −1 B and thus 
C P u (z)B = 0. Because C P u (z)B = 
m u </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>C P λu ,mu − j B </p>

<p>(1−λ u z) j , one has C P u (z)B = 0 if and 
only if C P λ u ,m u − j B for j = 1, . . . , m u . 
Next we show that if the orthogonality condition holds, then λ u is also an eigenvalue 
of A. If the orthogonality condition holds, C P λ u ,0 B = 0. Write I − Fz = (I − 
Fλ −1 
u ) + (1 − λ u z)λ −1 
u F and (6) as (I − Fz) −1 = P u (z) + P −u (z), where P −u (z) = 
q 
v=1,v =u P v (z) + H (z); then (I − Fz)(I − Fz) −1 = I implies </p>

<p>(I − Fλ −1 
u )P u (z) + (I − Fλ −1 
u )P −u (z) + (1 − λ u z)λ −1 
u F(I − Fz) −1 = I. (8) </p>

<p>Consider the first term (I − Fλ −1 
u )P u (z) and substitute P u (z) = 
m u </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>P λu ,mu − j </p>

<p>(1−λ u z) j ; one 
finds </p>

<p>(I − Fλ −1 
u )P u (z) = </p>

<p>(I − Fλ −1 
u )P λ u ,0 
(1 − λ u z) m u 
+ </p>

<p>m u −1 </p>



<p>j=1 </p>

<p>(I − Fλ −1 
u )P λ u ,m u − j 
(1 − λ u z) j 
. </p>

<p>Because (I − Fλ −1 
u )P λ u ,0 is the only term in (8) that loads (1 − λ u z) −m u , then (8) 
implies (I − Fλ −1 
u )P λ u ,0 = 0. Similarly, starting from (I − Fz) −1 (I − Fz) = I one 
finds that P λ u ,0 (I − Fλ −1 
u ) = 0. Hence (I − Fλ −1 
u )P λ u ,0 = P λ u ,0 (I − Fλ −1 
u ) = 0, 
where P λ u ,0 = 0. Because λ u is an eigenvalue of F, one can write F − λ u I = αβ , 
where α, β are n x × r full column rank matrices, and r = rank(F − λ u I ) &lt; n x ; 
moreover, because λ u = 0, one finds I − Fλ −1 
u = −λ −1 
u αβ . One then has P λ u ,0 = 
β ⊥ ϕα 
⊥ = 0, where α ⊥ , β ⊥ are bases of the orthogonal complements of the column 
spaces spanned by α, β and ϕ = 0, and hence C P λ u ,0 B = Cβ ⊥ ϕα 
⊥ B = 0. Because 
rank(Cβ ⊥ ) = rank(α 
⊥ B) = n x − r imply ϕ = 0, it must be that rank(Cβ ⊥ ) &lt; n x − r 
and/or rank(α 
⊥ B) &lt; n x − r . Next use the projection identities I = α ¯ 
α + ¯ 
α ⊥ α 
⊥ = 
¯ 
ββ + β ⊥ ¯ 
β 
⊥ , where ¯ 
a = a(a a) −1 , and write </p>

<p>A − λ u I = F − λ u I + B D −1 C = αβ + B D −1 C = 
α B </p>

<p>
I r 
0 
0 D −1 </p>

<p>β </p>

<p>C </p>



<p>= 
α ¯ 
α ⊥ </p>

<p>
I r 
¯ 
α B 
0 α 
⊥ B </p>

<p>
I r 
0 
0 D −1 </p>

<p>
I r 
0 
C ¯ 
β Cβ ⊥ 
β </p>

<p>¯ 
β </p>

<p>⊥ </p>

<p>
. </p>



<p>M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>

<p>Because rank(Cβ ⊥ ) &lt; n x − r or rank(α 
⊥ B) &lt; n x − r , one has that A − λ u I is 
singular; this shows that λ u is an eigenvalue of A. </p>

<p>
Proof of Propositions 4.2 and 4.3. T (z) is regular if and only if C P u (z)B = 0 for all 
unstable eigenvalues and it is a matrix polynomial if and only if C P u (z)B = 0 for all 
eigenvalues. The statement then follows from Proposition 3.1 and Lemma 4.1. </p>

<p>
Proof of Proposition 4.4. (Sufficiency.) If the orthogonality condition holds at λ u , 
then C P λ u ,0 B = 0; because C P λ u ,0 B = Cβ ⊥ ϕα 
⊥ B and ϕ = 0, it follows that 
rank(Cβ ⊥ ) &lt; n x − r and/or rank(α 
⊥ B) &lt; n x − r , see the proof of Lemma 4.1. 
(Necessity.) We first show that if rank(Cβ ⊥ ) &lt; n x − r and/or rank(α 
⊥ B) &lt; n x − r , 
then λ u is non-controllable and/or non-observable; we then apply Kalman's decom-
position theorem for non-controllable and/or non-observable linear systems. 
For the PBH rank test, see e.g. Kailath (1980, Theorem 6.2.6), one has that λ u is 
controllable if and only if rank(A − λ u I : B) = n x and it is observable if and only if 
rank(A −λ u I : C ) = n x . Observe that rank(A−λ u I : B) = rank(F −λ u I : B D −1 ); 
in fact </p>

<p>
A − λ u I B </p>

<p>
I n x 
0 
−D −1 C D −1 </p>

<p>
= </p>

<p>F − λ u I BD −1 </p>

<p>and similarly one finds that rank(A −λ u I : C ) = rank(F −λ u I : −C D −1 ). Recall 
that F − λ u I = αβ and use the projection identities I = α ¯ 
α + ¯ 
α ⊥ α 
⊥ = ¯ 
ββ + β ⊥ ¯ 
β </p>

<p>⊥ </p>

<p>to write </p>

<p>F − λ u I BD −1 = 
αβ α ¯ 
α B D −1 + ¯ 
α ⊥ α 
⊥ B D −1 </p>

<p>= 
α ¯ 
α ⊥ </p>

<p>β ¯ 
α B D −1 
0 α 
⊥ B D −1 </p>

<p>
, </p>

<p>F − λ u I 
−D −1 C </p>

<p>
= </p>

<p>
αβ 
−D −1 C ¯ 
ββ − D −1 Cβ ⊥ ¯ 
β </p>

<p>⊥ </p>



<p>= </p>

<p>
α 
0 
−D −1 C ¯ 
β −D −1 Cβ ⊥ 
β </p>

<p>¯ 
β </p>

<p>⊥ </p>

<p>
. </p>

<p>Similar expressions hold replacing F, B D −1 , −D −1 C with A, B, C. This shows that 
λ u is non-controllable and/or non-observable, both for the original ABCD form (1) 
and for the associate state space (2). 
We next apply Kalman's decomposition theorem, see e.g. Theorem 6.6 in Antsaklis 
and Michel (2007, p. 245), to the associate state space (2), with (A, B, C, D) replaced 
by (F, G, H, D −1 ), G = B D −1 , H = −D −1 C. From Antsaklis and Michel (eq. 
(7.6) 2007, p. 278), one has that the transfer function D −1 T (z) has representation 
D −1 + H 1 (I − F 11 z) −1 G 1 z where F 11 has eigenvalues that are both controllable and 
observable, and H 1 , G 1 are constructed as C 1 , B 1 in eq. (7.6) of Antsaklis and Michel 
(2007). This implies that T (λ −1 
u ) is finite, and hence that C P u (z)B = 0 by Lemma 
4.1. </p>

<p>
Proof of Proposition 4.5. Direct consequence of Propositions 4.3 and 4.4. </p>



<p>
VAR Representations for DSGE Models </p>



<p>Proof of Proposition 5.1. (Sufficiency.) See proof of Proposition 3.3. (Necessity.) For 
the PBH rank test, see e.g. Kailath (1980, Theorem 6.2.6), one has that if the ABCD 
form is minimal then rank(A −λI : B) = rank(A −λI : C ) = n x for all λ ∈ C. This 
implies, see the proof of Proposition 4.4, that rank(Cβ ⊥ ) = rank(α 
⊥ B) = n x − r ; 
hence C P λ u ,0 B = Cβ ⊥ ϕα 
⊥ B = 0 contradicts ϕ = 0 and thus the orthogonality 
condition cannot hold. This implies that T (z) is regular only if F is stable and it is a 
matrix polynomial only if F is nilpotent. Finally apply Proposition 3.1. </p>





<p>
M. Franchi, P. Paruolo </p>





</text></tei>