<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs11123-009-0142-x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract We show that the monotonicity condition is 
conceptually important in Stochastic Frontier Analysis 
(SFA). Despite its importance, most empirical studies do 
not impose monotonicity-probably because existing 
approaches are rather complex and laborious. Therefore, 
we propose a three-step procedure that is much simpler 
than existing approaches. We demonstrate how monoto-
nicity of a translog function can be imposed regionally at a 
connected set (region) of input quantities. Our method can 
be applied not only to impose monotonicity on translog 
production frontiers but also to impose other restrictions on 
cost, distance, or profit frontiers. </p>

<p>The analysis of technical efficiency is a widely used tool in 
empirical production studies. It is generally based on a 
''frontier'' production function that represents the maxi-
mum output quantities attainable from each set of input 
quantities (Coelli et al. 2005). This methodology accounts </p>

<p>for the fact that not all producers succeed in optimizing 
their production processes and might not achieve the 
maximum output level given their input quantities. It is 
often used to explore and compare the (relative) efficien-
cies of different producers and to determine factors that 
influence the producer's efficiency. 
Microeconomic theory implies that production functions 
should monotonically increase in all inputs. The impor-
tance of theoretical consistency in frontier analysis has 
been already stressed by Sauer et al. (2006). We show that 
the monotonicity property is particularly important for 
estimating the (relative) efficiencies of individual firms 
because otherwise a reasonable interpretation of the results 
is impossible (see also O'Donnell and Coelli 2005). The 
non-parametric non-stochastic Data Envelopment Analysis 
(DEA) implicitly imposes monotonicity while the para-
metric Stochastic Frontier Analysis (SFA) with flexible 
functional forms generally disregards this condition. Many 
empirical applications of SFA present results in which the 
monotonicity condition is not fulfilled, despite its impor-
tance (Sauer et al. 2006). Although procedures for impos-
ing monotonicity of frontier functions have been proposed 
in the literature, they are rarely used 
1 -probably because 
these procedures are rather complex and laborious. 
Therefore, we present a new three-step procedure that is 
much simpler and can be used also by practitioners. Fur-
thermore, we demonstrate how monotonicity of a translog 
function can be imposed not only locally at a single data 
point but regionally at a connected set (region) of data 
points. </p>

<p>A. Henningsen Á C. H. C. A. Henning 
Department of Agricultural Economics, University of Kiel, 
Olshausenstr. 40, 24229 Kiel, Germany </p>

<p>A. Henningsen (&amp;) 
Institute of Food and Resource Economics, University of 
Copenhagen, Rolighedsvej 25, 1958 Frederiksberg C, Denmark 
e-mail: arne.henningsen@gmail.com </p>

<p>1 This is in contrast to empirical estimations of standard (non-
frontier) microeconomic models. These models are frequently 
estimated under restrictions derived from microeconomic theory 
since three decades (see e.g. Lau 1978). </p>

<p>123 </p>

<p>J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 
DOI 10.1007/s11123-009-0142-x </p>

<p>2 Theoretical consistency of production frontiers </p>

<p>2.1 Monotonicity </p>

<p>As noted above, microeconomic theory requires that pro-
duction functions monotonically increase in all inputs, i.e. 
the output quantity must not decrease if any input quantity 
is increased. The rationale for the monotonicity assumption 
is as follows: if (in rare cases) there is indeed a negative 
technical input-output relationship (e.g. too much fertilizer 
burns the crops), a wise manager would simply leave a part 
of the input unused (e.g. leave some of the fertilizer in the 
bag). Therefore, increasing the (unused) quantity of this 
input would leave the output (at least) unchanged. 
Given the production function </p>

<p>y ¼ f ðx; bÞ; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where y is the output quantity, x is a vector of n input 
quantities, and b is a vector of parameters, monotonicity 
requires that all marginal products (f i ) are positive </p>

<p>f i ðx; bÞ ¼ 
of ðx; bÞ 
ox i 
! 0 8 i 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>If a production frontier is not monotonically increasing, 
the efficiency estimates of the individual firms cannot be 
reasonably interpreted. We illustrate this problem in Fig. 1. 
In this example, we have a non-monotone production 
frontier. Firm A is below the production frontier and hence, 
considered to be inefficient, while firm B is on the 
production frontier and hence, considered to be efficient. 
However, firm B uses much more of the input to produce 
the same output as firm A, which means that firm B uses its 
input less efficiently than firm A. Thus, the efficiency 
measures based on this non-monotone production frontier 
imply just the opposite of the actual situation and hence, 
the (relative) efficiency estimates based on a non-monotone 
production frontier cannot be reasonably interpreted. </p>

<p>We stress that it is not sufficient to ensure that the 
marginal products at all data points are non-negative. The 
same problem as demonstrated in Fig. 1 might occur if 
there are some non-monotone intervals between the data 
points. This is demonstrated in Fig. 2, in which the pro-
duction frontier increases in the input quantity at both data 
points but decreases in the input quantity in an interval 
between the two data points. 
The problem of a non-monotone production frontier 
inhibits not only a reasonable interpretation of the indi-
vidual (relative) efficiency estimates, but also the analysis 
of factors that might affect technical (in)efficiency. This is 
because the non-monotonicity distorts the efficiency esti-
mates, which are the endogenous values in this analysis 
(e.g. in the ''Technical Efficiency Effects Model'' proposed 
by Battese and Coelli 1995). 
If an estimated production frontier is not monotonically 
increasing in all inputs, the question of what to do arises. If 
the monotonicity condition is violated at many data points, 
the model is likely misspecified and we suggest changing 
the model specification. If the monotonicity condition is 
violated only at a few data points, these are probably 
random deviations from the ''true'' monotonically 
increasing production frontier and we suggest imposing the 
monotonicity condition in the estimation. </p>

<p>2.2 Quasiconcavity </p>

<p>Besides monotonicity, microeconomic theory often 
assumes that production functions are also quasiconcave in 
all inputs Lau (1978), because this implies convex input 
sets and hence, decreasing marginal rates of technical 
substitution. However, quasiconcave production functions 
do not guarantee that the input demand functions are 
''everywhere'' differentiable (Dhrymes 1967; Barten et al.  1969). </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Non-monotone production frontier </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Production frontier with non-monotone interval </p>

<p>2 We thank an anonymous reviewer for pointing this out to us. </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>



<p>If all inputs are perfectly divisible and different pro-
duction activities can be applied independently, production 
functions are generally quasiconcave (e.g. Varian 1992). 
Furthermore, a non-quasiconcave point of the production 
function cannot reflect profit-maximizing behavior under 
standard microeconomic assumptions. However, the 
assumptions of perfectly divisible inputs and independent 
applicability of different production activities are not 
always fulfilled in the real world and measuring technical 
efficiency generally assumes only that producers maximize 
output given their input quantities but not that producers 
maximize their profit. Hence, in contrast to the monoto-
nicity assumption, there is not necessarily a technical 
rationale for production functions to be quasiconcave. 
Moreover, even a non-quasiconcave point of the produc-
tion function might reflect profit-maximizing behavior if 
not all of the prices are exogenously given or there are 
restrictions on input use (e.g. fertilizer use in water pro-
tection areas). 
Hence, we suggest abstaining from imposing quasicon-
cavity when estimating (frontier) production functions. 
However, we propose to check for quasiconcavity after the 
econometric estimation because some standard results of 
microeconomic theory (e.g. convex input sets) do not hold 
in case of non-quasiconcavity. 
A function is quasiconcave if </p>

<p>f ðkx 
0 þ ð1 À kÞx 
00 ; bÞ ! min f ðx 
0 ; bÞ; f ðx 
00 ; bÞ 
ð 
Þ 
ð 3Þ </p>

<p>with 0\k\1: 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>In the case of a twice continuously differentiable 
production function f, quasiconcavity can be checked 
using its bordered Hessian matrix </p>

<p>B ¼ </p>

<p>0 f 1 f 2 . . . f n 
f 1 f 11 f 12 . . . f 1n 
f 2 f 21 f 22 . . . f 2n 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. </p>

<p>f n f n1 f n2 . . . f nn </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>; 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>where f ij ¼ o 
2 f =ðox i ox j Þ is the second derivative of the 
production function with respect to the ith and jth input 
quantity. Because all input quantities are generally non-
negative (x i ! 08i), a necessary condition for quasiconcavity is </p>

<p>jB 1 j 0; jB 2 j ! 0; jB 3 j 0; . . .; jB n j Á ðÀ1Þ 
n ! 0; 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>jB 1 j ¼ 
0 f 1 
f 1 f 11 </p>









<p>; jB 2 j ¼ </p>

<p>0 f 1 f 2 
f 1 f 11 f 12 
f 2 f 21 f 22 </p>













<p>
; . . .; jB n j ¼ jBj </p>

<p>ð7Þ </p>

<p>(Chiang 1984, p. 393f). If there is only one input (n = 1), 
monotonicity implies quasiconcavity (Takayama 1994,   p. 62). In case of two or more inputs (n [ 1), monotonicity 
does not (necessarily) imply quasiconcavity. </p>

<p>3 Restricted estimation of frontier functions </p>

<p>3.1 Approaches proposed in the literature </p>

<p>Despite the importance of monotonicity, our search of the 
literature found only a very few applications that impose 
this condition in SFA. One approach is a restricted maxi-
mum likelihood (ML) estimation, i.e. the likelihood func-
tion is maximized subject to the restriction that the 
theoretically derived properties of the frontier function are 
fulfilled. For instance, Bokusheva and Hockmann (2006)  estimate a translog production frontier under monotonicity 
and quasi-concavity restrictions. However, they impose 
these restrictions only locally at the sample mean, which is 
not sufficient for obtaining reasonable efficiency estimates 
(see above). Furthermore, the maximization of the likeli-
hood function under constraints is rather complex and the 
algorithms used for the optimization frequently have con-
vergence problems or converge to local maxima. 
As another solution, O'Donnell and Coelli (2005) use 
the Bayesian MCMC method to estimate a stochastic 
frontier distance function with all desirable theoretical 
conditions imposed at all data points. This is probably the 
most suitable and most sophisticated approach, but it is 
rather complex and laborious. 
The main reason why the constrained ML and the MCMC 
approaches have been used so rarely is probably because 
these methods are not available in standard econometrics 
software packages. Hence, their application requires 
advanced skills in econometrics and in computer program-
ming and many (applied) researchers and practitioners do not 
have the knowledge or the time to apply these methods. </p>

<p>3.2 Three-step procedure </p>

<p>As a solution, we propose a much simpler three-step pro-
cedure that is based on the two-step method suggested by 
Koebel et al. (2003). 
In the first step, we estimate an unrestricted stochastic 
production frontier </p>

<p>ln y ¼ ln f ðx; bÞ À u þ v 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>E½u ¼ z 
0 d; 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>where u C 0 captures technical inefficiency, v captures 
statistical noise, z is a vector of variables explaining 
technical inefficiency, and d is a vector of parameters to be 
estimated. This estimation can be done by a standard 
software package for SFA. We extract the unrestricted </p>

<p>J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 
219 </p>



<p>parameters of the production frontierb and their covari-
ance matrixR b from the estimation results. 
In the second step, we obtain restricted b parameters by 
a minimum distance estimation 
3 : </p>

<p>b 
0 ¼ arg minb 
0 Àb </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>À1 
bb </p>

<p>0 Àb </p>

<p>
ð10Þ </p>

<p>s.t. f i ðx;b 
0 Þ ! 0 8 i; x 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>This restricted minimization can be easily done by several 
software packages. 
4 The restricted parameters (b 
0 ) are 
asymptotically equivalent to a (successful) restricted one-
step ML estimation (Koebel et al. 2003). However, it might 
be problematic to obtain a (consistent) covariance matrix of 
the restricted parametersR </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>b , because standard bootstrap-
ping leads to an inconsistent covariance matrix if the 
restricted parameters are at the boundary of the feasible 
parameter space (Andrews 2000; Dhrymes 2006). </p>

<p>5   Andrews (2000) suggests alternative methods, e.g. rescaled 
bootstrapping, that lead to a consistent covariance matrix 
even in the case of binding inequality constraints. How-
ever, these alternative methods are only valid under spe-
cific conditions that need to be checked for our specific 
case. Thus we leave this interesting topic for future 
research. </p>

<p>6   In the third step, we determine the efficiency estimates 
of the firms and the effects of the variables explaining 
technical inefficiency based on the theoretical consistent 
production frontier. We estimate the stochastic frontier 
model </p>

<p>ln y ¼ a 0 þ a 1 lnỹ À u 
0 þ v </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ð12Þ </p>

<p>E½u 
0 ¼ z 
0 d 
0 ; 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>where the only ''input variable'' is the ''frontier output'' of 
each firm calculated with the parameters of the restricted 
model:ỹ ¼ f ðx;b 
0 Þ. Again, this estimation can be done 
with a standard software package for SFA. Parameters a 0 
and a 1 allow an adjustment of the restricted production 
frontier, which gets </p>

<p>y ¼ e 
a 0 f x;b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>
a 1 
: 
ð14Þ </p>

<p>As long as a 1 is positive, this adjustment is a strictly 
monotonically increasing transformation. Hence, it does 
not affect the monotonicity and quasiconcavity (Arrow and  Enthoven 1961, p. 781) condition of f ðx;b 
0 Þ. However, if 
desired, an adjustment can be prevented by restricting a 0 to 
zero and a 1 to one. 
7 Since the estimation of Eq. 12 includes 
a generated regressor (ỹ), the standard errors obtained in 
the third step might be biased (see Pagan 1984). 
The monotonicity restrictions can be checked by sta-
tistical tests. In a first step, the inequality restrictions in 
(11) that are binding in the distance minimization (10) are 
determined. In a second step, standard statistical tests such 
as the Wald test or the likelihood ratio test are applied by 
treating the binding inequality restrictions as equality 
restrictions. </p>

<p>3.3 Translog production function </p>

<p>A popular functional form in SFA is the translog function. 
It satisfies second-order flexibility (Diewert 1974) and its 
logarithmic form has the advantage that inefficiencies are 
captured by an additive term rather than by a multiplicative 
term, which considerably simplifies the econometric esti-
mation. A translog production function is defined as </p>

<p>ln y ¼ ln f ðx; bÞ ¼ b 0 þ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>b i ln x i þ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x i ln x j </p>

<p>ð15Þ </p>

<p>with b ij = b ji . Its marginal products are </p>

<p>f i ¼ 
f ðx; bÞ 
x i 
b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x j </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>ð16Þ </p>

<p>and the second derivatives are </p>

<p>f ij ¼ 
f ðx; bÞ 
x i x j 
b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>b ik ln x k </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>Â b j þ 
X n </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>b jk ln x k À D ij </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>À b ij </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>ð17Þ </p>

<p>where D ij is Kronecker delta with D ij = 1 if i = j and D ij = 0 
otherwise. 
Because all input quantities must be non-negative and 
the translog functional form guarantees that the output 
quantity is always positive, the monotonicity conditions for 
the translog production function reduce to </p>

<p>3 The inclusion of the d parameters in the distance minimization is 
discussed in Appendix 1. 
4 The speed and probability of convergence of the non-linear distance 
minimization can be increased by providing analytical gradients: </p>

<p>ob 
0 Àb </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>À1 
bb </p>

<p>0 Àb </p>

<p>. 
ob 
0 ¼ 2R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>b ðb 
0 ÀbÞ. </p>

<p>5 We thank two anonymous reviewers for pointing this out. 
6 Bayesian MCMC estimations deliver a consistent covariance 
matrix, but their estimation results are often sensitive to assumptions 
about prior distributions and starting values. In this regard, the 
estimators of our three step procedure can still be useful to specify 
prior distributions and starting values for Bayesian MCMC 
approaches. We thank Christian Aßmann for this comment. </p>

<p>7 While a 1 can be easily restricted to one by using ðln y À lnỹÞ as the 
output variable and using no input variable in Eq. 10, not all software 
packages allow the restriction of a 0 to zero. However, in our empirical 
applications, a 0 and a 1 were always very close to zero and one, 
respectively, which means that there was virtually no adjustment. </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>



<p>b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x j ! 0 8 i: 
ð18Þ </p>

<p>Because these conditions are linear in parameters, they can 
be transformed into matrix form </p>

<p>Rb ! 0; 
ð19Þ </p>

<p>where R is a matrix of dimension n 9 (1 ? n (n ? 3)/2) 
with </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>b ¼ b 0 ; b 1 ; b 2 ; . . .; b n ; b 11 ; b 12 ; . . .; b 1n ; b 22 ; . . .; b 2n ; . . .; b nn 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ð21Þ </p>

<p>contains the linearly independent coefficients of the trans-
log production function (15). Should the monotonicity 
condition be checked or imposed not at one but at T [ 1 
data points, the matrix R in Eq. 20 can be created for each 
data point and then all of these (sub)matrices can be 
stacked to a new R matrix with T Á n rows. 
Given that the monotonicity restrictions of the translog 
function are linear in parameters, the quadratic distance 
minimization in (10) can be converted to a usual quadratic 
programming problem </p>

<p>s 
Ã ¼ arg min </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c 
0 s þ 
1 
2 
s 
0 Qs; 
ð22Þ </p>

<p>s.t. As b; 
ð23Þ </p>

<p>where s ¼b 
0 Àb, c ¼ ð0; . . .; 0Þ, Q ¼ 2R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>b , A = R, and 
b ¼ ÀRb. After solving this quadratic programming 
problem, the restricted b coefficients can be obtained bŷ 
b 
0 ¼ s 
Ã þb. Hence, this distance minimization can be 
done easily by any quadratic programming software. 
As stated in Theorem 1 below, the translog functional 
form has the advantage that monotonicity can be easily 
imposed regionally, i.e. in a closed connected set of the 
input quantities. </p>

<p>Theorem 1 (Regional monotonicity of translog func-
tions) 
A translog function f ðx; bÞ is monotonic in x on 
a closed connected set that consists of all ln x in the 
convex polyhedron with vertices ln x 1 ; . . .; ln x p ; if and only </p>

<p>if each of its partial derivatives retains the sign over all 
vertices: </p>

<p>s i f i ðx; bÞ ! 0 8 i 2 1; . . .; n 
f 
g; x 2 x 1 ; . . .; x p 
È 
É 
ð24Þ </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>s i ¼ 
1 if f ð:Þ is monotonically increasing in x i 
À1 if f ð:Þ is monotonically decreasing in x i </p>

<p>&amp; 
ð25Þ </p>

<p>The proof is given in Appendix 2. </p>

<p>Theorem 1 implies that if the input quantities are mea-
sured in logarithmic terms, imposing monotonicity at the 
vertices of a convex polyhedron in the n-dimensional space 
of (logarithmic) input quantities ensures that monotonicity 
is fulfilled in the entire polyhedron. 
8 Hence, if monoto-
nicity is imposed at all sample points, the monotonicity 
condition also is fulfilled on all points on the straight lines 
between each two sample points (given that input quanti-
ties are measured in logarithmic terms) and the problem of 
non-monotone intervals between sample points (as dem-
onstrated in Fig. 2) is ruled out. If the input quantities are 
measured in natural (non-logarithmic) terms, monotonicity 
is imposed in a closed connected set of the input quantities 
but it is not a convex polyhedron because the edges of this 
set are not straight but rather they are curved. This is 
illustrated in Fig. 3. 
Another option is to impose monotonicity at the vertices 
of a box (n-dimensional cuboid) that includes the region at 
which monotonicity should be imposed (e.g. all data 
points). The lower left vertex of this box should be (at 
most) at the position (min x 1 , minx 2 ,…, minx n ) and the 
upper right vertex of this box should be (at least) at the 
position (maxx 1 , maxx 2 ,…, maxx n ), where the edges of this 
box are parallel to the axes of the n-dimensional space of </p>

<p>R ¼ </p>

<p>0 1 0 . . . 0 
0 0 1 . . . 0 
. . 
. . . 
. . . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. </p>

<p>0 0 0 . . . 1 </p>

<p>ln x 1 ln x 2 . . . ln x n 
0 
lnx 1 . . . 
0 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. </p>

<p>0 
0 
. . . ln x 1 </p>

<p>0 
. . . 
0 
. . . 
0 
ln x 2 . . . ln x n . . . 
0 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. </p>

<p>0 
. . . ln x 2 . . . ln x n </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
5 
ð20Þ </p>

<p>8 Terrell (1996) imposes regional monotonicity on a (non-frontier) 
translog cost function by imposing this condition at each point of a 
fine grid that spans the desired region. Given our finding, it is 
unnecessary to use the interior of the grid because imposing 
monotonicity only at its vertices is sufficient for guaranteeing 
monotonicity in the entire region. </p>

<p>J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 
221 </p>



<p>logarithmic input quantities. This ensures that the region at 
which monotonicity is imposed is also a box in the space of 
natural (non-logarithmic) input quantities. This is illus-
trated in Fig. 4. 
If the unrestricted production frontier (9) is of the 
translog functional form, the adjusted restricted frontier 
function (14) is also of the translog form. Its coefficients 
can be calculated bŷ </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 ¼â 0 þâ 1b </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>ð26Þ </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>i ¼â 1b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>i 8 i [ 0 
ð27Þ </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ij ¼â 1b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ij 8 i; j; 
ð28Þ </p>

<p>whereb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>: are the restricted coefficients obtained from the 
distance minimization (10) andâ are the coefficients for 
adjusting the restricted production frontier estimated in the 
final stochastic frontier estimation (12). </p>

<p>4 An empirical example </p>

<p>We demonstrate this method using panel data collected 
from 43 smallholder rice producers in the Tarlac region of 
the Philippines from 1990 to 1997. This data set is published 
as a supplement to Coelli et al. (2005). 
9 The data include 
one output (tons of freshly threshed rice) and three inputs: 
area planted (in hectares), labour used (in man-days of 
family and hired labour), and fertilizer used (in kg of active 
ingredients). We explain technical inefficiency according to 
the education of the household head (in years) and the 
percentage of area classified as ''bantog'' (upland) fields. 
All estimations and calculations have been done within 
the ''<rs id="software-8" type="software">R software environment for statistical computing and graphics</rs>'' (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">R Development Core Team</rs> 2009) using the ''R'' </p>

<p>0.0 
0.5 
1.0 
1.5 
2.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>log( quantity of input 1 ) 
log( quantity of input 2) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>quantity of input 1 </p>

<p>quantity of input 2 </p>

<p>data point 
vertex of the polyhedron/set 
minimum mononotic region </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Imposing regional 
monotonicity of translog 
functions </p>

<p>0.0 
0.5 
1.0 
1.5 
2.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>log( quantity of input 1 ) 
log( quantity of input 2) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>quantity of input 1 </p>

<p>quantity of input 2 </p>

<p>data point 
vertex of the box 
minimum mononotic region </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Imposing monotonicity 
of translog functions at a box </p>

<p>9 It can be downloaded from http://www.uq.edu.au/economics/cepa/ 
software/CROB2005.zip. </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>



<p>packages ''frontier'' (Coelli and <rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Henningsen</rs> 2009), ''<rs id="software-10" type="software">mic- Econ</rs>'' (Henningsen 2008), and ''quadprog'' (Turlach and  Weingessel 2007). The commands that have been used for 
this analysis are available in Appendix 3. 
The estimation results of the unrestricted stochastic 
frontier production function are presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>10   The b and d coefficients are defined as before, r 
2 is the 
total error variance (r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>u þ r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>v ), and c is the proportion of the 
variance of technical inefficiency in the total error variance 
(r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>u =r 
2 ). The monotonicity condition is violated at 39 out 
of 344 observations and quasiconcavity is not fulfilled at 
four observations. While the education of the household 
head has no significant influence on technical efficiency, 
the proportion of ''bantog'' (upland) fields significantly 
(at the 10% level) increases the farm's efficiency. 
The coefficients obtained by the minimum distance esti-
mation are presented in Table 2. Many coefficients have 
changed considerably (column ''diff''), but all changes are less 
than two times the standard error of the first-step estimation 
(column ''diff/std.err''). The last column (''adj.coef'') shows 
the restricted coefficients after adjusting the production 
frontier with a 0 and a 1 estimated in the final step. Of course, 
the monotonicity condition is fulfilled at all observations now. 
Moreover, the quasiconcavity condition also is fulfilled at all 
observations. Interestingly, we obtained the same result, i.e. 
imposing monotonicity implies quasiconcavity, also for other 
empirical applications (e.g. Wiebusch 2005; Henning and 
Mumm 2009; Henning and Han 2009). Barnett (2002) argues 
that imposing curvature but not monotonicity increases the 
incidence of monotonicity violations. Hence, imposing 
monotonicity first and checking for curvature thereafter-as 
in our approach-seems more effective than imposing cur-
vature alone. However, monotonicity has a closer relationship 
to quasiconcavity than to concavity (see above) so that it is 
questionable if imposing monotonicity generally implies 
concavity in empirical applications. 
The results of the final SFA are presented in Table 3. As 
expected, the coefficient of the intercept is virtually zero and 
the coefficient of the ''frontier output'' is virtually one. Hence, 
the coefficients of the adjusted and non-adjusted restricted 
production frontier are almost identical (compare columns 
''coef'' and ''adj.coef'' of Table 2). The effects of education 
and the proportion of ''bantog'' (upland) fields on technical 
efficiency are rather similar to the unrestricted model. The 
imposition of the monotonicity restriction caused an increase 
of the total error variance (r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) from around 0.41 to 0.46. In 
contrast, the proportion of the variance of technical ineffi-
ciency in the total error variance (c) does not change much. 
We test the monotonicity restrictions by a Wald test and 
a likelihood ratio test. Both tests do not reject the </p>

<p>monotonicity restrictions with P-values of 0.39 and 0.42, 
respectively. 
Figures 5, 6, and 7 illustrate the effect of imposing mono-
tonicity on the partial production elasticities of the inputs. The 
estimates based the unrestricted and the restricted model are 
highly correlated with coefficients of correlation of 0.99, 0.97, 
and 0.99 for land, labor, and fertilizer, respectively. While the 
partial production elasticities of fertilizer are very similar in 
both models, imposing monotonicity reduces the average 
elasticity of land from 0.49 to 0.45 and increases the average </p>

<p>Table 1 Unrestricted stochastic frontier estimation </p>

<p>Estimate 
Std. error 
t value 
Pr([|t|) </p>

<p>b 0 
-7.5546 
1.6898 
-4.4708 
0.0000 
b 1 
-2.0886 
0.7812 
-2.6735 
0.0079 
b 2 
3.0734 
0.7954 
3.8641 
0.0001 
b 3 
0.7890 
0.5472 
1.4420 
0.1502 
b 11 
-0.3972 
0.2139 
-1.8568 
0.0642 
b 12 
0.5829 
0.1778 
3.2776 
0.0012 
b 13 
0.0428 
0.1415 
0.3025 
0.7625 
b 22 
-0.5647 
0.2755 
-2.0496 
0.0412 
b 23 
-0.1276 
0.1410 
-0.9051 
0.3661 
b 33 
-0.0030 
0.0924 
-0.0321 
0.9744 
d 1 
-0.0103 
0.0489 
-0.2097 
0.8341 
d 2 
-1.0724 
0.5914 
-1.8134 
0.0707 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.4089 
0.1720 
2.3771 
0.0180 
c 
0.9168 
0.0386 
23.7612 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Table 2 Minimum distance estimation </p>

<p>coef 
diff 
diff/std.err 
adj.coef </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>-4.8927 
2.6619 
1.5753 
-4.8918 
b </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>-0.9999 
1.0887 
1.3935 
-0.9998 
b </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>1.8159 
-1.2575 
-1.5811 
1.8157 
b </p>

<p>0 
3 </p>

<p>0.6851 
-0.1040 
-0.1900 
0.6850 
b </p>

<p>0 
11 </p>

<p>-0.1918 
0.2055 
0.9603 
-0.1918 
b </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>0.3323 
-0.2506 
-1.4091 
0.3323 
b </p>

<p>0 
13 </p>

<p>0.0168 
-0.0260 
-0.1838 
0.0168 
b </p>

<p>0 
22 </p>

<p>-0.2431 
0.3216 
1.1674 
-0.2430 
b </p>

<p>0 
23 </p>

<p>-0.1275 
0.0002 
0.0013 
-0.1275 
b </p>

<p>0 
33 </p>

<p>0.0217 
0.0246 
0.2667 
0.0217 </p>

<p>Table 3 Final stochastic frontier estimation </p>

<p>Estimate 
Std. error 
t value 
Pr([|t|) </p>

<p>a 0 
0.0005 
0.0469 
0.0110 
0.9912 
a 1 
0.9999 
0.0190 
52.5687 
0.0000 
d </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>-0.0231 
0.0571 
-0.4045 
0.6861 
d </p>

<p>0 
2 </p>

<p>-1.1885 
0.6733 
-1.7653 
0.0784 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.4620 
0.2039 
2.2656 
0.0241 
c 
0.9277 
0.0333 
27.8679 
0.0000 
10 The last column shows the (asymptotic) marginal significance 
level assuming that the t-values have a standard normal distribution. </p>

<p>J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 
223 </p>



<p>elasticity of labor from 0.25 to 0.29. Furthermore, imposing 
monotonicity clearly reduces the ranges and variances of the 
partial production elasticities of land and labor, i.e. small 
values (including negative values) increase and large values 
decrease. 
The efficiency estimates of the unrestricted and restric-
ted models are contrasted in Fig. 8. The average technical </p>

<p>efficiencies of the unrestricted (0.7749) and the restricted 
model (0.7744) are almost identical and most individual 
technical efficiencies of the restricted and unrestricted 
models are very similar (i.e. lying on the 45°line). How-
ever, a few technical efficiencies are considerably smaller 
in the theoretically consistent model, where the observa-
tions with the largest differences in the efficiency estimates 
are those with the monotonicity condition violated in the 
unrestricted model. Hence, the unrestricted model leads to 
some inconsistent efficiency estimates. </p>

<p>5 Conclusions </p>

<p>We have shown that efficiency estimates based on non-
monotone frontier functions cannot be reasonably inter-
preted. Given the importance of monotonicity we suggest that 
non-monotone production frontiers should no longer be used 
in empirical production analysis, particularly since we have 
proposed a three-step procedure that is much simpler than 
existing approaches. We show that imposing monotonicity at 
one point is not sufficient to obtain reasonable efficiency 
estimates and we demonstrate how monotonicity of a flexible 
translog function can be imposed on a closed set (region) of 
input quantities. Our three-step method can be used to impose 
theoretical consistency not only on translog production 
frontiers but also on other functional forms and other frontier 
functions such as distance, cost, or profit frontiers. Although 
the theoretical restrictions for these functions are more 
complex than the monotonicity restrictions of a translog </p>

<p>0.0 
0.5 
1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>partial production elasticities of land (unrestricted model) 
partial production elasticities of land (restricted model) </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Partial production elasticities of land. Note: the unfilled circles 
indicate observations with monotonicity violated in the unrestre-
stricted model </p>

<p>0.0 
0.5 
1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>partial production elasticities of labor (unrestricted model) 
partial production elasticities of labor (restricted model) </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Partial production elasticities of labor. Note: the unfilled 
circles indicate observations with monotonicity violated in the 
unrestrestricted model </p>

<p>0.1 
0.2 
0.3 
0.4 
0.5 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>partial production elasticities of fertilizer (unrestricted model) 
partial production elasticities of fertilizer (restricted model) </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Partial production elasticities of fertilizer. Note: the unfilled 
circles indicate observations with monotonicity violated in the 
unrestrestricted model </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>



<p>production frontier, our proposed three-step procedure still is 
probably less complex than a restricted ML or a Bayesian 
Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) estimation. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors thank Christian Aßmann, Uwe 
Jensen, Subal Kumbhakar, two anonymous referees, the participants 
of the 2nd Halle Workshop on Efficiency and Productivity Analysis 
(Halle, Germany, May 26-27, 2008) and the participants of the Fifth 
North American Productivity Workshop (New York City, USA, June 
24-27, 2008) for their very helpful comments and suggestions. Of 
course, all remaining errors are the sole responsibility of the authors. 
The first author is grateful to the H. Wilhelm Schaumann Stiftung and 
the German Research Foundation (Deutsche Forschungsgemeins-
chaft, DFG) for financially supporting this research. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the 
Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which per-
mits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any 
medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited. </p>

<p>Appendices </p>

<p>Appendix 1: Distance minimization with d parameters </p>

<p>It also is possible to include the d parameters in the dis-
tance minimization (10, 11): </p>

<p>h 
0 ¼ arg minĥ 
0 Àĥ </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>À1 
hĥ </p>

<p>0 Àĥ </p>

<p>
; 
ð29Þ </p>

<p>s.t. f i ðx;ĥ 
0 Þ ! 0 8 i; x; 
ð30Þ </p>

<p>where h ¼ ðb 
0 ; d 
0 Þ 
0 . This approach also adjusts the d coef-</p>

<p>ficients, but both approaches result in identical restricted b </p>

<p>coefficients (see proof below). We suggest including only 
the b coefficients in this minimization because d coeffi-
cients based on a theoretically consistent frontier produc-
tion function are obtained in the third step anyway. </p>

<p>Distance minimization of the b coefficients </p>

<p>b 
0 ¼ arg min </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 0 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
; 
ð31Þ </p>

<p>s.t. Rb 
0 ! r 
ð32Þ </p>

<p>Lagrangian function </p>

<p>L ¼ b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 0 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
þ l 
0 r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
ð33Þ </p>

<p>Kuhn-Tucker conditions </p>

<p>oL 
ob </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð34Þ </p>

<p>l ! 0 
ð35Þ </p>

<p>r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
ð36Þ </p>

<p>l r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð37Þ </p>

<p>Distance minimization of the b and d coefficients </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>
¼ arg min </p>

<p>b 
0 ;d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>b 
0 À b 
d 
0 À d </p>

<p>
0 R 11 R 12 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>R 22 </p>

<p>! À1 b 
0 À b 
d 
0 À d </p>



<p>
; </p>

<p>ð38Þ </p>

<p>s.t. Rb 
0 ! r 
ð39Þ </p>

<p>Lagrangian function </p>

<p>L ¼ 
b 
0 À b 
d 
0 À d </p>

<p>
0 X 11 X 12 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>X 22 </p>

<p>! 
b 
0 À b 
d 
0 À d </p>



<p>þ l 
0 r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>ð40Þ </p>

<p>Kuhn-Tucker conditions </p>

<p>oL </p>

<p>o 
b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2 
R 11 R 12 
R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R 22 </p>

<p>! À1 b 
0 À b 
d 
0 À d </p>



<p>þ 
ÀR 
0 l 
0 </p>



<p>¼ 0 </p>

<p>ð41Þ </p>

<p>l ! 0 
ð42Þ </p>

<p>r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
ð43Þ </p>

<p>l r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð44Þ </p>

<p>Equation 41 can be split into </p>

<p>oL 
ob </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2X 11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
þ 2X 12 d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð45Þ </p>

<p>oL 
od </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2X 21 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
þ 2X 22 d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð46Þ </p>

<p>with </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>technical efficiency calculated from the unrestricted model 
technical efficiency calculated from the restricted model </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Efficiency estimates of the restricted and unrestricted model. 
Note: the unfilled circles indicate observations with monotonicity 
violated in the unrestrestricted model </p>

<p>J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>

<p>
X 11 X 12 
X 22 X 22 </p>

<p>! 
¼ 
R 11 R 12 
R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R 22 </p>

<p>! À1 </p>

<p>The inverse of this (partitioned) R matrix is 
X 11 X 12 
X 21 X 22 </p>

<p>! 
¼ 
R 11 R 12 
R </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>R 22 </p>

<p>! À1 
ð47Þ </p>

<p>¼ 
R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 þ R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 R 12 Q 
À1 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R </p>

<p>À1 
11 </p>

<p>ÀR </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 R 12 Q </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>ÀQ 
À1 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R </p>

<p>À1 
11 </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>! 
ð48Þ </p>

<p>¼ 
P </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>ÀP 
À1 R 12 R </p>

<p>À1 
22 </p>

<p>ÀR </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 þ R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R 12 R </p>

<p>À1 
22 </p>

<p>! 
ð49Þ </p>

<p>with Q = R 22 -R 12 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>R 11 R 12 and P ¼ R 11 À R 12 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 
12 </p>

<p>(Harville 1997, p. 99). From Eq. 46 we get </p>

<p>d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
¼ ÀX </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 X 21 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
ð50Þ </p>

<p>Substituting this into (45) and applying (48) we get 
oL 
ob </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2X 11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À 2X 12 X </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 X 21 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 </p>

<p>ð51Þ </p>

<p>¼ 2 X 11 À X 12 X </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 X 21 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð52Þ </p>

<p>¼ 2 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 þ R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 R 12 Q 
À1 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R </p>

<p>À1 
11 </p>

<p>À R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 R 12 Q 
À1 QQ 
À1 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 R </p>

<p>À1 
11 </p>

<p>
b 
0 À b </p>

<p>À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð53Þ </p>

<p>¼ 2R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð54Þ </p>

<p>From Eq. 54 we get </p>

<p>b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
¼ 
1 
2 
R 11 R 
0 l 
ð55Þ </p>

<p>Substituting this into (46) and applying (49) we get </p>

<p>oL 
od </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ X 21 R 11 R 
0 l þ 2X 22 d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð56Þ </p>

<p>¼ ÀR </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R 11 R 
0 l þ 2 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 þ R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R 12 R </p>

<p>À1 
22 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð57Þ </p>

<p>Hence, the Kuhn-Tucker conditions (41-44) can be 
re-written as </p>

<p>oL 
ob </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ 2R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>11 b 
0 À b 
À 
Á 
À R 
0 l ¼ 0 
ð58Þ </p>

<p>oL 
od </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>¼ À R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R 11 R 
0 l þ 2 R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 þ R </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>22 R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>12 P 
À1 R 12 R </p>

<p>À1 
22 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>d 
0 À d 
À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð59Þ </p>

<p>l ! 0 
ð60Þ </p>

<p>r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
ð61Þ </p>

<p>l r À Rb </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ 0 
ð62Þ </p>

<p>Because the Kuhn-Tucker conditions (58) and (60-62) are 
identical to the conditions (34-37) and Eq. 59 does not </p>

<p>contain a b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>, both minimization approaches result in the 
same values for b 
0 . </p>

<p>Appendix 2: Proof of Theorem 1 </p>

<p>Proof (Theorem 1) The partial derivatives of a quadratic 
function </p>

<p>gðw; bÞ ¼ a 0 þ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>b i w i þ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij w i w j 
ð63Þ </p>

<p>evaluated at point w k are </p>

<p>g i ðw k ; bÞ ¼ 
ogðw; bÞ 
ow i </p>





<p>
w¼w k </p>

<p>¼ b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij w j;k : 
ð64Þ </p>

<p>If we set w equal to ln x, the partial derivatives of the 
quadratic function evaluated at the point w k ¼ ln x k become </p>

<p>g i ðw k ; bÞ ¼ g i ðln x k ; bÞ ¼ b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x j;k 
ð65Þ </p>

<p>Since f ðx; bÞ [ 0 and x 1 ; . . .; x n ) 0, the partial derivatives 
of f ðx; bÞ and gðw; bÞ always have the same sign: </p>

<p>sgn f i ðx; bÞ 
½ 
¼sgn 
f ðx; bÞ 
x i 
b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x j </p>

<p>! 
" 
# </p>

<p>ð66Þ </p>

<p>¼ sgn b i þ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>b ij ln x j </p>

<p>" 
# </p>

<p>¼ sgn g i ðln x; bÞ 
½ 
¼sgn g i ðw; bÞ 
½ </p>

<p>
8 b; w ¼ ln x; and i 2 1; . . .; n 
f 
g </p>

<p>ð67Þ </p>

<p>Hence, Eq. 24 implies that each of the partial derivatives of 
gðw; bÞ retains the sign over a set of points w 1 ; . . .; w p , 
where w k ¼ ln x k 8k 2 f1; . . .; pg: 
s i g i ðw; bÞ ! 0 8 i 2 1; . . .; n 
f 
g ; w 2 w 1 ; . . .; w p 
È 
É </p>

<p>ð68Þ </p>

<p>Tangian (2002, p. 134) shows that this implies that gðw; bÞ 
is monotonic in w on the convex polyhedron P with 
vertices w 1 ; . . .; w p : 
s i g i ðw; bÞ ! 0 8 w 2 Pðw 1 ; . . .; w p Þ 
ð 69Þ </p>

<p>This further implies that f ðx; bÞ is monotonic in x, if ln x is 
in the convex polyhedron with vertices ln x 1 ; . . .; ln x p : 
s i f i ðx; bÞ ! 0 8 x with ln x 2 Pðln x 1 ; . . .; ln x p Þ ð70Þ </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>Appendix 3: Source code </p>

<p>Commands used for the estimation </p>

<p>The following commands have been used to estimate a 
theoretically consistent stochastic frontier production 
function: </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>







<p>Final stochastic frontier estimation (step 3) </p>

<p>Testing monotonicity restrictions </p>

<p>Partial production elasticities of the restricted and the 
unrestricted model </p>

<p>Efficiency estimates of the restricted and the unrestricted 
model </p>

<p> 
J Prod Anal (2009) 32:217-229 </p>







</text></tei>