<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.24.4.187" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>Around 1970, many departments of economics did not advertise assistant 
Around 1970, many departments of economics did not advertise assistant 
professor positions. Instead, jobs were fi lled by word of mouth and through letters 
professor positions. Instead, jobs were fi lled by word of mouth and through letters 
of inquiry, and the market was relatively thin. More recently, the annual ASSA 
of inquiry, and the market was relatively thin. More recently, the annual ASSA 
meetings, long organized by the AEA, have become a central venue for conducting 
meetings, long organized by the AEA, have become a central venue for conducting 
interviews. Since 1974 the AEA has also helped make the market thicker by 
interviews. Since 1974 the AEA has also helped make the market thicker by 
publishing Job Openings for Economists (JOE), initially as a hardcopy periodical 
publishing Job Openings for Economists (JOE), initially as a hardcopy periodical 
and since 2002 exclusively online. 
and since 2002 exclusively online. 
In January 2005, Dan McFadden, then AEA president, asked Al Roth to chair a new 
In January 2005, Dan McFadden, then AEA president, asked Al Roth to chair a new 
Ad Hoc Committee on the Job Market. The Committee took as its initial goal to assess 
Ad Hoc Committee on the Job Market. The Committee took as its initial goal to assess 
whether the AEA could better promote a thick market for new Ph.D.s in economics, 
whether the AEA could better promote a thick market for new Ph.D.s in economics, 
while reducing problems of congestion and coordination failure (Roth, 2008a). 
while reducing problems of congestion and coordination failure (Roth, 2008a). 
U.S. institutions awarded 1,091 doctorates in economics in 2008 (Fiegener, 
U.S. institutions awarded 1,091 doctorates in economics in 2008 (Fiegener, 
2009). For that year's job market, 1,910 unique new academic jobs (both junior and 
2009). For that year's job market, 1,910 unique new academic jobs (both junior and 
senior) and 1,004 unique new nonacademic jobs were posted on Job Openings for 
senior) and 1,004 unique new nonacademic jobs were posted on Job Openings for 
Economists (Siegfried, 2008). These numbers make a fairly thick market possible. 
Economists (Siegfried, 2008). These numbers make a fairly thick market possible. 
However, recruitment and job search involves matching heterogeneous employers 
However, recruitment and job search involves matching heterogeneous employers 
and candidates under incomplete information about both characteristics and pref-
and candidates under incomplete information about both characteristics and pref-
erences. In this situation, thick markets have to deal with the congestion caused by 
erences. In this situation, thick markets have to deal with the congestion caused by 
the many possibilities to be considered (Roth and Xing, 1997). 
the many possibilities to be considered (Roth and Xing, 1997). 
For candidates, the marginal cost of an additional application is very low, 
For candidates, the marginal cost of an additional application is very low, 
and candidates apply widely-to an average of 80 employers, according to surveys 
and candidates apply widely-to an average of 80 employers, according to surveys 
of job market candidates in the years 2006-2008, conducted by our Committee. 
of job market candidates in the years 2006-2008, conducted by our Committee. 
As a result, many employers receive hundreds of applications, which can be very 
As a result, many employers receive hundreds of applications, which can be very 
time-consuming to review carefully. The large number of applications sent by each 
time-consuming to review carefully. The large number of applications sent by each 
candidate also implies that, for most employers, it would be a mistake to devote all 
candidate also implies that, for most employers, it would be a mistake to devote all 
their interview slots to the most accomplished applicants, because many of those 
their interview slots to the most accomplished applicants, because many of those 
candidates may be unattainable as they are likely to secure other jobs they prefer. 
candidates may be unattainable as they are likely to secure other jobs they prefer. 
Consequently, it may be optimal for some employers to decline to interview some 
Consequently, it may be optimal for some employers to decline to interview some 
of the candidates they like best and instead to interview 
of the candidates they like best and instead to interview at least some candidates 
at least some candidates 
who they think are more likely to accept an offer. As this process unfolds, there 
who they think are more likely to accept an offer. As this process unfolds, there 
is a risk of coordination failure in which employers and candidates who would be 
is a risk of coordination failure in which employers and candidates who would be 
well-suited do not match. 
well-suited do not match. 
We begin with an overview of the job market for new economics Ph.D.s, and 
We begin with an overview of the job market for new economics Ph.D.s, and 
then focus on recent developments. 
then focus on recent developments. </p>

<p>The Job Market for New Economists, Step by Step 
The Job Market for New Economists, Step by Step </p>

<p>The annual job market for new economics Ph.D.s typically starts in September. 
The annual job market for new economics Ph.D.s typically starts in September. 
Job openings for Ph.D. economists are listed in the monthly issues of Job Openings 
Job openings for Ph.D. economists are listed in the monthly issues of Job Openings 
for Economists (JOE), and in a number of other places in recent years: for example, 
for Economists (JOE), and in a number of other places in recent years: for example, 
in the 
in the Chronicle of Higher Education; AcademicKeys.com; the 
; AcademicKeys.com; the Economist magazine; 
magazine; 
MRM Professional Announcement and Job Openings (a division of Social Science 
MRM Professional Announcement and Job Openings (a division of Social Science 
Electronic Publishing and Social Science Research Network); Economics Research 
Electronic Publishing and Social Science Research Network); Economics Research </p>

<p>Peter Coles, John Cawley, Phillip Levine, Muriel Niederle, Alvin Roth, and John Siegfried 189 </p>

<p>Network (ERN) Professional Announcements and Job Openings (automatically 
Network (ERN) Professional Announcements and Job Openings (automatically 
posted each week to all ERN subscribers); Inomics.com; walras.org (which aggre-
posted each week to all ERN subscribers); Inomics.com; walras.org (which aggre-
gates job listings from a variety of sources including JOE); and EconJobMarkets.org. 
gates job listings from a variety of sources including JOE); and EconJobMarkets.org. 
Candidates submit applications and advisors submit letters of reference through 
Candidates submit applications and advisors submit letters of reference through 
a number of modalities, including mail, e-mail, university-specifi c web servers, and 
a number of modalities, including mail, e-mail, university-specifi c web servers, and 
third-party web servers. Employers review applications throughout the fall and 
third-party web servers. Employers review applications throughout the fall and 
in December invite some applicants to interviews at the January ASSA meetings. 
in December invite some applicants to interviews at the January ASSA meetings. 
The interview marketplace is divided into two parts: interviews in hotel rooms and 
The interview marketplace is divided into two parts: interviews in hotel rooms and 
suites, and interviews at one of many tables in a large ballroom. Academic institu-
suites, and interviews at one of many tables in a large ballroom. Academic institu-
tions and those that participate more frequently in this market tend to interview in 
tions and those that participate more frequently in this market tend to interview in 
suites. The Illinois Department of Employment Security (IDES) has organized the 
suites. The Illinois Department of Employment Security (IDES) has organized the 
ballroom interviewing since 1968. 
ballroom interviewing since 1968. 
1 1 About 600 interview suites and 150 interview 
About 600 interview suites and 150 interview 
tables have been booked at recent ASSA meetings. 
tables have been booked at recent ASSA meetings. 
In early December, immediately following publication of the December 
In early December, immediately following publication of the December 
JOE, applicants have the option of sending no more than two signals of special 
JOE, applicants have the option of sending no more than two signals of special 
interest to employers through the AEA signaling service. After interviews at the 
interest to employers through the AEA signaling service. After interviews at the 
ASSA meetings, university employers invite some candidates for campus fl y-outs, 
ASSA meetings, university employers invite some candidates for campus fl y-outs, 
starting almost immediately after the meetings and continuing for several months. 
starting almost immediately after the meetings and continuing for several months. 
During this period, employers make job offers. Some are exploding offers that 
During this period, employers make job offers. Some are exploding offers that 
must be accepted or rejected quickly (often in one to two weeks), while some are 
must be accepted or rejected quickly (often in one to two weeks), while some are 
extended for a much longer period. Typically only the most established and desir-
extended for a much longer period. Typically only the most established and desir-
able employers, who can make multiple offers for a position, make offers without 
able employers, who can make multiple offers for a position, make offers without 
deadlines. (Anecdotal evidence suggests that owing to tight budgets in early 2010, 
deadlines. (Anecdotal evidence suggests that owing to tight budgets in early 2010, 
many universities were constrained to make no more than one offer at a time and 
many universities were constrained to make no more than one offer at a time and 
were more likely than in previous years to make offers with short deadlines.) 
were more likely than in previous years to make offers with short deadlines.) 
In March, applicants still looking for jobs and employers with unfi lled jobs may 
In March, applicants still looking for jobs and employers with unfi lled jobs may 
indicate their continued availability on the AEA scramble website. Applicants who 
indicate their continued availability on the AEA scramble website. Applicants who 
have not secured a position by late April may continue to explore the nonacademic 
have not secured a position by late April may continue to explore the nonacademic 
job market; seek temporary academic employment as one-year visiting assistant 
job market; seek temporary academic employment as one-year visiting assistant 
professors, lecturers, and research associates (non-tenure-track, soft money posi-
professors, lecturers, and research associates (non-tenure-track, soft money posi-
tions); or may postpone graduation and re-enter the job market the following year. 
tions); or may postpone graduation and re-enter the job market the following year. 
Most new Ph.D.s are awarded around June, and academic jobs typically begin at the 
Most new Ph.D.s are awarded around June, and academic jobs typically begin at the 
start of the fall semester. 
start of the fall semester. 
Each step of this process is worthy of attention from a market design standpoint. 
Each step of this process is worthy of attention from a market design standpoint. 
For example, consider the logistics of scheduling interviews at the ASSA meetings. 
For example, consider the logistics of scheduling interviews at the ASSA meetings. 
These meetings help make the market thick, but thickness invites congestion. It 
These meetings help make the market thick, but thickness invites congestion. It 
can be nontrivial for employers even to inform interviewees of the location of the 
can be nontrivial for employers even to inform interviewees of the location of the </p>

<p>1 From 1968 until 2001, IDES provided a physical bulletin board that allowed employers to post open-
ings and job applicants to post their availability. Each side of the market would hunt through postings 
by the other side. Much of the coordination between employers with open positions and job appli-
cants occurred on-site, and interviews were arranged for the same or next day. In 2001, IDES began 
a computerized job listing and encouraged candidates to contact employers to schedule interviews 
in advance. Today, virtually all ballroom interviews are organized in advance of the ASSA meetings 
through this online system. </p>



<p>interview suite because interviewers only learn the room number when they check in 
interview suite because interviewers only learn the room number when they check in 
to their hotel shortly before the interviews. In the 1950s and 1960s, candidates called 
to their hotel shortly before the interviews. In the 1950s and 1960s, candidates called 
hotels to ask for the room numbers of the people with whom they were to inter-
hotels to ask for the room numbers of the people with whom they were to inter-
view. In the 1970s, hotels, concerned about safety and privacy, adopted the policy of 
view. In the 1970s, hotels, concerned about safety and privacy, adopted the policy of 
refusing to disclose room numbers. This forced candidates to wait until the inter-
refusing to disclose room numbers. This forced candidates to wait until the inter-
viewers had checked in, call the hotel, ask to be connected to the interviewer's room, 
viewers had checked in, call the hotel, ask to be connected to the interviewer's room, 
and hope to catch the interviewer there. Hotel switchboards were overwhelmed by 
and hope to catch the interviewer there. Hotel switchboards were overwhelmed by 
such calls just before the ASSA meetings began; interviewers felt constrained to stay 
such calls just before the ASSA meetings began; interviewers felt constrained to stay 
in their rooms in case a candidate called; interviews were interrupted by calls; and 
in their rooms in case a candidate called; interviews were interrupted by calls; and 
candidates and interviewers were frustrated by the diffi cult, time-consuming system. 
candidates and interviewers were frustrated by the diffi cult, time-consuming system. 
In 2000, the AEA helped overcome this congestion by introducing disclosure codes: 
In 2000, the AEA helped overcome this congestion by introducing disclosure codes: 
employers requested a disclosure code from the AEA and gave that code to inter-
employers requested a disclosure code from the AEA and gave that code to inter-
viewees in advance of the meetings. The employer, after learning the room number 
viewees in advance of the meetings. The employer, after learning the room number 
for the interview suite, would provide that information to the AEA, which would 
for the interview suite, would provide that information to the AEA, which would 
then publicly post room numbers next to disclosure codes. At fi rst, this information 
then publicly post room numbers next to disclosure codes. At fi rst, this information 
was posted on a bulletin board in the conference hotel, but since fall 2008 it has 
was posted on a bulletin board in the conference hotel, but since fall 2008 it has 
been posted online. This allows candidates to easily learn the locations of their inter-
been posted online. This allows candidates to easily learn the locations of their inter-
views while preserving confi dentiality for interviewers. This example illustrates how 
views while preserving confi dentiality for interviewers. This example illustrates how 
thick markets can experience congestion and coordination failure but appropriately 
thick markets can experience congestion and coordination failure but appropriately 
designed mechanisms can ameliorate these problems. 
designed mechanisms can ameliorate these problems. </p>

<p>Signaling Signaling </p>

<p>Since November 2006, the AEA signaling mechanism has offered candidates 
Since November 2006, the AEA signaling mechanism has offered candidates 
the opportunity to send signals of particular interest to up to two employers via an 
the opportunity to send signals of particular interest to up to two employers via an 
AEA website. The signals are meant to let candidates credibly express interest in 
AEA website. The signals are meant to let candidates credibly express interest in 
employers, and to help employers identify candidates interested in their positions. 
employers, and to help employers identify candidates interested in their positions. 
What gives the signals credibility is that each applicant is limited to two, so there is 
What gives the signals credibility is that each applicant is limited to two, so there is 
an opportunity cost to sending a signal (Chakrabortya and Harbaugh, 2007). The 
an opportunity cost to sending a signal (Chakrabortya and Harbaugh, 2007). The 
Committee provided suggestions for how candidates might use and employers might 
Committee provided suggestions for how candidates might use and employers might 
interpret signals; this guide, "Signaling for Interviews in the Economics Job Market," 
interpret signals; this guide, "Signaling for Interviews in the Economics Job Market," 
is available at 
is available at 〈 〈http://www.aeaweb.org/joe/signal/ http://www.aeaweb.org/joe/signal/〉 〉 (AEA Ad Hoc Committee on the 
(AEA Ad Hoc Committee on the 
Job Market, 2010b). 
Job Market, 2010b). 
Signals can serve as a coordination mechanism. For example, in breaking ties 
Signals can serve as a coordination mechanism. For example, in breaking ties 
to fi ll interview slots, employers can place more weight on candidates who signaled. 
to fi ll interview slots, employers can place more weight on candidates who signaled. </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>To see how signals can help coordinate matches and increase welfare even in 
To see how signals can help coordinate matches and increase welfare even in 
the simple case in which match quality is unimportant, consider an example of two 
the simple case in which match quality is unimportant, consider an example of two 
fi rms that each can offer one interview (for one job) and two workers, and assume 
fi rms that each can offer one interview (for one job) and two workers, and assume 
that fi rms and workers are indifferent with whom they match. If the fi rms can do 
that fi rms and workers are indifferent with whom they match. If the fi rms can do </p>

<p>2 One recruiting chair confi dentially admitted that in 2005 by the time the fi rst half of the applica-
tions had been read, his committee found enough acceptable applicants to fi ll all the school's January 
interview slots. The remaining applications, of which there were several hundred, went unread. </p>

<p>The Job Market for New Economists: A Market Design Perspective 191 </p>

<p>no better than to play a symmetric mixed strategy, they randomly choose which 
no better than to play a symmetric mixed strategy, they randomly choose which 
worker to interview, and with probability one-half one worker will receive two inter-
worker to interview, and with probability one-half one worker will receive two inter-
view offers, and the other will receive none. If each worker were allowed to fi rst 
view offers, and the other will receive none. If each worker were allowed to fi rst 
send one signal and sent it randomly, then half the time each fi rm would receive 
send one signal and sent it randomly, then half the time each fi rm would receive 
exactly one signal, which would solve the coordination problem. (When one fi rm 
exactly one signal, which would solve the coordination problem. (When one fi rm 
receives two signals the coordination problem is the same as if no signals were 
receives two signals the coordination problem is the same as if no signals were 
sent.) Thus signals can reduce coordination failure by half in this simple example. 
sent.) Thus signals can reduce coordination failure by half in this simple example. </p>

<p>3 3 </p>

<p>One particular coordination problem in this market is that candidates can "fall 
One particular coordination problem in this market is that candidates can "fall 
through the cracks" because an employer that valued them highly guessed incor-
through the cracks" because an employer that valued them highly guessed incor-
rectly that the candidate was "un-gettable." The employer, even though it ranks 
rectly that the candidate was "un-gettable." The employer, even though it ranks 
the candidate highly, perceives that the candidate is unlikely to accept a job offer, 
the candidate highly, perceives that the candidate is unlikely to accept a job offer, 
so the employer declines to spend an interview or fl y-out slot on the candidate. 
so the employer declines to spend an interview or fl y-out slot on the candidate. </p>

<p>4 4 </p>

<p>This phenomenon may be widespread; in one survey conducted by our Committee, 
This phenomenon may be widespread; in one survey conducted by our Committee, 
83 percent of responding departments reported that their Ph.D. students were 
83 percent of responding departments reported that their Ph.D. students were 
sometimes "declined interviews because employers viewed them as excessive long-
sometimes "declined interviews because employers viewed them as excessive long-
shots (even though the department's assessment suggested otherwise)." 
shots (even though the department's assessment suggested otherwise)." 
A job candidate can try to avoid falling through the cracks by attempting 
A job candidate can try to avoid falling through the cracks by attempting 
to signal interest informally, but this may be seen as noncredible cheap talk: the 
to signal interest informally, but this may be seen as noncredible cheap talk: the 
candidate could be reaching out in this way to many departments. For candidates 
candidate could be reaching out in this way to many departments. For candidates 
who have idiosyncratic preferences for schools that might otherwise presume them 
who have idiosyncratic preferences for schools that might otherwise presume them 
to be out of reach, signals can be a means of credibly expressing these preferences. 
to be out of reach, signals can be a means of credibly expressing these preferences. 
Furthermore, in contrast to informal signaling (whose effectiveness often depends 
Furthermore, in contrast to informal signaling (whose effectiveness often depends 
on the reputation and dedication of advisors) signals can transmit preference 
on the reputation and dedication of advisors) signals can transmit preference 
information equitably: each candidate has at most two signals. 
information equitably: each candidate has at most two signals. 
Using data from the 2006-2009 job markets, we analyze how signals were used 
Using data from the 2006-2009 job markets, we analyze how signals were used 
by candidates. We also provide a preliminary assessment of the effectiveness of 
by candidates. We also provide a preliminary assessment of the effectiveness of 
signals in securing interviews with potential employers. 
signals in securing interviews with potential employers. 
Table 1 displays statistics on use of the signaling mechanism from 2006 to 2009. 
Table 1 displays statistics on use of the signaling mechanism from 2006 to 2009. 
The number of participating job candidates held steady at roughly 1,000 signalers 
The number of participating job candidates held steady at roughly 1,000 signalers 
per year. In a December 2008 survey of those appearing on departmental lists of 
per year. In a December 2008 survey of those appearing on departmental lists of 
job candidates, 66 percent of respondents reported signaling. Of the remaining 
job candidates, 66 percent of respondents reported signaling. Of the remaining 
33 percent of respondents, 26 percent reported that they missed the deadline, 
33 percent of respondents, 26 percent reported that they missed the deadline, 
21 percent reported they didn't know about the mechanism, 41 percent thought 
21 percent reported they didn't know about the mechanism, 41 percent thought 
signaling wouldn't help, and 5 percent thought signaling would hurt their chances 
signaling wouldn't help, and 5 percent thought signaling would hurt their chances 
of getting an interview. Almost all participating candidates sent two signals. 
of getting an interview. Almost all participating candidates sent two signals. </p>

<p>3 For a theoretical exploration of the gains from signaling in a job matching context, useful starting 
points are Coles, Kushnir, and Niederle (2009), Stack (2007), Avery and Levin (forthcoming), and 
Haque (2009). 
4 When candidates fall through the cracks, the result is an unstable matching because after the fact the 
candidate and a potential employer would both prefer to be matched with each other than with their 
eventual partner (for background, see Gale and Shapley, 1962; Roth and Sotomayor, 1990). Note that 
the relevant matching models for interviews are many-to-many matching because both employers and 
candidates can participate in multiple interviews. </p>



<p>Roughly 25 percent of the listings in JOE (or between 450 and 500 employers) 
Roughly 25 percent of the listings in JOE (or between 450 and 500 employers) 
received at least one signal. 
received at least one signal. 
Our surveys also show that, among those sending signals in years 2006-2009, 
Our surveys also show that, among those sending signals in years 2006-2009, 
about two-thirds were current Ph.D. students. At 9 percent of the total, assistant 
about two-thirds were current Ph.D. students. At 9 percent of the total, assistant 
professors were the second largest identifi ed group. Despite the mechanism being 
professors were the second largest identifi ed group. Despite the mechanism being 
open to anyone, 99 percent of signalers held (or are about to receive) Ph.D.s, 
open to anyone, 99 percent of signalers held (or are about to receive) Ph.D.s, 
92 percent had economics as the primary fi eld in their doctorate, and 85 percent 
92 percent had economics as the primary fi eld in their doctorate, and 85 percent 
received their degree from a U.S. institution. 
received their degree from a U.S. institution. 
We examined whether candidate participation in the signaling mechanism 
We examined whether candidate participation in the signaling mechanism 
was correlated with the rank of their home institution. Specifi cally, we verifi ed 
was correlated with the rank of their home institution. Specifi cally, we verifi ed 
the participation of job candidates listed on web pages of the 100 highest-ranked 
the participation of job candidates listed on web pages of the 100 highest-ranked 
economics departments, using ranking data from econphd.net. 
economics departments, using ranking data from econphd.net. 
5 5 Signaling rates 
Signaling rates 
were virtually fl at across institution rank. 
were virtually fl at across institution rank. 
Figure 1 shows how number of signals received by employers is correlated with 
Figure 1 shows how number of signals received by employers is correlated with 
their rank. Given the widely-recognized imprecision in ranking and to protect 
their rank. Given the widely-recognized imprecision in ranking and to protect 
confi dentiality, we group employers into blocks of fi ve. Thus, the fi rst point on 
confi dentiality, we group employers into blocks of fi ve. Thus, the fi rst point on 
Figure 1 shows the total number of signals received by the top fi ve ranked employers 
Figure 1 shows the total number of signals received by the top fi ve ranked employers 
over the four years 2006-2009. Those fi ve employers collectively received just over 
over the four years 2006-2009. Those fi ve employers collectively received just over 
180 signals in four years, an average of just over nine each per year. Generally, 
180 signals in four years, an average of just over nine each per year. Generally, 
the remainder of the graph depicts that better-ranked departments received more 
the remainder of the graph depicts that better-ranked departments received more 
signals, up until roughly the 100 
signals, up until roughly the 100 
th th ranked employer, after which there is a fairly 
ranked employer, after which there is a fairly 
even distribution of signals received by rank. "Spikes" in the graph in many cases 
even distribution of signals received by rank. "Spikes" in the graph in many cases 
correspond to employers in popular geographic areas. It is worth noting that signals 
correspond to employers in popular geographic areas. It is worth noting that signals </p>

<p>5 These rankings are based on economics research productivity of institutions as weighted by journal 
quality: 〈http://www.econphd.net〉 (now available on the Internet archive at 〈http://web.archive. 
org/web/20071217125412/www.econphd.net/rank/nrallec.htm〉). We used econphd.net's "network 
rankings." Strengths of the econphd.net rankings include that 1) they are deep, covering nearly 
500 employers, and 2) they include nonacademic employers. A weakness of the rankings is that they 
rank institutions, not economics departments. For any analysis we do that involves rankings, we 
consider only signals to economics departments in ranked institutions and to nonacademic employers 
who are ranked. We do not examine signals to noneconomics departments in ranked institutions 
because we think that the rankings are less accurate for such departments than for either economics 
departments or nonacademic employers. Specifi cally, Figure 1 includes signals to economics depart-
ments and to nonacademic employers, while Table 2 looks at the subset of signals sent to economics 
departments only (including departments outside of the United States). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Number of Signal Senders, Signals Sent, and Signal Recipients, 2006-2009 </p>

<p>Year 
# signalers 
# signals </p>

<p># employers 
signaled </p>

<p># JOE listings 
signaled </p>

<p># JOE listings 
(entire year) </p>

<p>Fraction of JOE 
listings signaled </p>

<p>2006 
971 
1,890 
519 
674 
2,643 
25.5% 
2007 
1,022 
2,010 
489 
672 
2,914 
23.1% 
2008 
979 
1,926 
461 
687 
2,881 
23.8% 
2009 
978 
1,922 
449 
666 
2,285 
29.1% </p>

<p>Peter Coles, John Cawley, Phillip Levine, Muriel Niederle, Alvin Roth, and John Siegfried 193 </p>

<p>are being sent to departments of all ranks, including those ranked 400-500. Given 
are being sent to departments of all ranks, including those ranked 400-500. Given 
the diffi culty that departments at that rank may have in identifying job candidates 
the diffi culty that departments at that rank may have in identifying job candidates 
who wish to join their faculty, these signals may be improving coordination, one of 
who wish to join their faculty, these signals may be improving coordination, one of 
the mechanism's intended purposes. 
the mechanism's intended purposes. 
Table 2 provides insight into signal fl ow, that is, how candidates trained in 
Table 2 provides insight into signal fl ow, that is, how candidates trained in 
departments of a given rank allocate their signals to departments of a given rank. 
departments of a given rank allocate their signals to departments of a given rank. 
For this table, we consider only signals to economics departments, which we divide 
For this table, we consider only signals to economics departments, which we divide 
into tiers: tiers 1-4 are departments ranked 1-10, 11-50, 51-150, and 151-480, 
into tiers: tiers 1-4 are departments ranked 1-10, 11-50, 51-150, and 151-480, 
respectively. Economics departments not appearing in the rankings form a fi fth, 
respectively. Economics departments not appearing in the rankings form a fi fth, 
"unranked" category. There is a clear tendency for students from higher tiers to 
"unranked" category. There is a clear tendency for students from higher tiers to 
signal to departments in lower tiers. For example, from 2006-2009, 3,148 signals 
signal to departments in lower tiers. For example, from 2006-2009, 3,148 signals 
came from students in tiers 1 and 2 (see the top two rows of the far-right column), 
came from students in tiers 1 and 2 (see the top two rows of the far-right column), 
while just 1,426 signals went to those departments (see the fi rst two columns of the 
while just 1,426 signals went to those departments (see the fi rst two columns of the 
bottom row). Unranked schools received many signals-2,346 over four years-
bottom row). Unranked schools received many signals-2,346 over four years-
while just 412 signals were sent by job candidates trained by unranked schools. 
while just 412 signals were sent by job candidates trained by unranked schools. 
Thus, while unranked schools do not produce many Ph.D. economists (who use the 
Thus, while unranked schools do not produce many Ph.D. economists (who use the 
signaling mechanism), they are a relatively popular destination for signals. 
signaling mechanism), they are a relatively popular destination for signals. 
The 21 employers (both academic and nonacademic) that received the most 
The 21 employers (both academic and nonacademic) that received the most 
signals over the four-year period 2006-2009 received approximately one-sixth of 
signals over the four-year period 2006-2009 received approximately one-sixth of 
all signals. (There was a tie for 20 
all signals. (There was a tie for 20 
th th place, which is why we used the top 21.) The 
place, which is why we used the top 21.) The 
composition of this group is suggestive of how candidates use signals. Perhaps the 
composition of this group is suggestive of how candidates use signals. Perhaps the 
most notable feature of the top 21 signal recipients is their concentrated geography. 
most notable feature of the top 21 signal recipients is their concentrated geography. </p>

<p>Fi gure 1 
Signals Received by Employer Rank, 2006-2009 </p>

<p>Notes: Includes only signals to employers appearing in the rankings of econphd.net. Signals to 
noneconomics programs (for example, public policy, health) within institutions listed in the rankings 
are excluded. An additional 2,993 signals were received by "unranked" employers. Employers are 
ranked in blocks of fi ve; 5 = employers ranked one through fi ve, 10 = employers ranked six through 
ten, etc. Rankings are according to econphd.net. </p>

<p>Employer rank </p>

<p>Signals received </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
120 
140 
160 
180 
200 
220 
240 
260 
280 
300 
320 
340 
360 
380 
400 
420 
440 
460 
480 </p>



<p>Ten of these employers are in the Boston, New York, or the Washington, D.C., 
Ten of these employers are in the Boston, New York, or the Washington, D.C., 
metropolitan areas. Three of the remaining employers are in California. More-
metropolitan areas. Three of the remaining employers are in California. More-
over, it appears that within this group, geography trumps employer rank. Of the 
over, it appears that within this group, geography trumps employer rank. Of the 
21 employers receiving the most signals, only seven are economics departments 
21 employers receiving the most signals, only seven are economics departments 
ranked 21 or better. Within popular geographic areas, we observe concentrations 
ranked 21 or better. Within popular geographic areas, we observe concentrations 
of signals to departments that are not the most highly ranked in that area. For 
of signals to departments that are not the most highly ranked in that area. For 
example, Boston is home to two top-fi ve economics departments but only one of 
example, Boston is home to two top-fi ve economics departments but only one of 
these made the list of the 21 employers that received the most signals-and just 
these made the list of the 21 employers that received the most signals-and just 
barely. Meanwhile, three other Boston employers were among the top 21 signal 
barely. Meanwhile, three other Boston employers were among the top 21 signal 
recipients, and the average ranking of these economics departments was just over 
recipients, and the average ranking of these economics departments was just over 
60. This pattern of signals could arise because candidates want to live in these 
60. This pattern of signals could arise because candidates want to live in these 
desirable locations, perhaps as a result of dual job searches focusing on big cities to 
desirable locations, perhaps as a result of dual job searches focusing on big cities to 
try to fi nd two nearby jobs. But the pattern of signaling to mid-ranked institutions 
try to fi nd two nearby jobs. But the pattern of signaling to mid-ranked institutions 
also suggests that candidates are concerned not to waste signals on the most highly-
also suggests that candidates are concerned not to waste signals on the most highly-
selective employers, which are unlikely to take signals into account. 
selective employers, which are unlikely to take signals into account. 
To measure the impact of sending a signal on the probability of getting an 
To measure the impact of sending a signal on the probability of getting an 
interview, we would ideally like to know both the probability of getting an interview 
interview, we would ideally like to know both the probability of getting an interview 
if a signal had been sent and the probability of getting an interview if a signal had 
if a signal had been sent and the probability of getting an interview if a signal had 
not been sent. 
not been sent. 
6 6 One way to measure the causal effect of the signal would be to 
One way to measure the causal effect of the signal would be to 
conduct a randomized experiment. For example, we might have asked people to 
conduct a randomized experiment. For example, we might have asked people to 
submit three signals, randomly deleted one, and then tracked the interview rates 
submit three signals, randomly deleted one, and then tracked the interview rates 
for both the sent and unsent signals. 
for both the sent and unsent signals. 
7 7 Unsurprisingly, many colleagues found this 
Unsurprisingly, many colleagues found this 
kind of experimentation in an ongoing labor market inappropriate (Roth, 2007). 
kind of experimentation in an ongoing labor market inappropriate (Roth, 2007). 
Furthermore, randomly deleting some signals could compromise signal credibility; 
Furthermore, randomly deleting some signals could compromise signal credibility; </p>

<p>6 How signals affect the chances of receiving fl y-outs or job offers is also of interest, but data for these 
outcomes are too sparse to draw conclusions. 
7 In a similar spirit, Lee, Niederle, Kim, and Kim (2009) performed an experiment on a Korean dating 
site in which participants were allowed different numbers of signals. They observed that participants 
allowed more signals were more successful in fi nding matches. </p>

<p>T able 2 
Flow of Signals by Rank of Economics Department, 2006-2009 </p>

<p>Signals to… </p>

<p>Signals from… 
Tier 1 
Tier 2 
Tier 3 
Tier 4 
Unranked 
Total </p>

<p>Tier 1 
101 
368 
274 
105 
159 
1,007 
Tier 2 
111 
478 
521 
385 
646 
2,141 
Tier 3 
40 
165 
339 
385 
706 
1,635 
Tier 4 
15 
84 
116 
179 
603 
997 
Unranked 
13 
51 
54 
62 
232 
412 
Total 
280 
1,146 
1,304 
1,116 
2,346 
6,192 </p>

<p>Notes: Includes signals to and from economics departments only. Tiers 1-4 are economics departments 
ranked 1-10, 11-50, 51-150, and 151-480, respectively. </p>

<p>The Job Market for New Economists: A Market Design Perspective 195 </p>

<p>applicants might report to employers that they sent a signal, and employers would 
applicants might report to employers that they sent a signal, and employers would 
have no way of knowing whether the signal had indeed been randomly deleted. 
have no way of knowing whether the signal had indeed been randomly deleted. 
Instead, sacrifi cing the control of a randomized experiment, in 2007 and 2008 
Instead, sacrifi cing the control of a randomized experiment, in 2007 and 2008 
we asked candidates the following question: "If you could have sent a third signal, 
we asked candidates the following question: "If you could have sent a third signal, 
where would you have sent it?" This was asked at the same time the candidate's two 
where would you have sent it?" This was asked at the same time the candidate's two 
signals were submitted. In 2008 we also surveyed candidates who did not 
signals were submitted. In 2008 we also surveyed candidates who did not use the 
use the 
signaling mechanism, asking them, "If you had used the signaling mechanism, 
signaling mechanism, asking them, "If you had used the signaling mechanism, 
where would you have sent your signals?" For these hypothetical signals, we followed 
where would you have sent your signals?" For these hypothetical signals, we followed 
up later by asking questions about outcomes, just as we did for the actual signals. 
up later by asking questions about outcomes, just as we did for the actual signals. 
(Descriptive statistics of survey respondents and nonrespondents suggest the two 
(Descriptive statistics of survey respondents and nonrespondents suggest the two 
groups are similar.) 
groups are similar.) </p>

<p>8 8 </p>

<p>During 2007 and 2008, 2,001 candidates sent 3,936 signals. Of these candidates, 
During 2007 and 2008, 2,001 candidates sent 3,936 signals. Of these candidates, 
785 responded to survey questions asking if they received interviews, fl y-outs, or 
785 responded to survey questions asking if they received interviews, fl y-outs, or 
job offers from employers to whom they sent signals. Furthermore, 572 candidates 
job offers from employers to whom they sent signals. Furthermore, 572 candidates 
reported a hypothetical third signal, of which 325 also responded to a follow-up 
reported a hypothetical third signal, of which 325 also responded to a follow-up 
survey about corresponding outcomes. An additional 54 students who did not use 
survey about corresponding outcomes. An additional 54 students who did not use 
the signaling mechanism reported two hypothetical signals, along with outcomes 
the signaling mechanism reported two hypothetical signals, along with outcomes 
for those applications. 
for those applications. 
These data were used to estimate a random-effects, ordinary least squares, 
These data were used to estimate a random-effects, ordinary least squares, 
linear probability model in which the unit of observation is a pairing of a candi-
linear probability model in which the unit of observation is a pairing of a candi-
date and an employer. 
date and an employer. 
9 9 Only employers that were signaled or would have been 
Only employers that were signaled or would have been 
signaled by the candidate (had the candidate sent any signal or had the candi-
signaled by the candidate (had the candidate sent any signal or had the candi-
date been able to send a third signal) are included in the sample. The dependent 
date been able to send a third signal) are included in the sample. The dependent 
variable is an indicator variable for whether the candidate received an interview 
variable is an indicator variable for whether the candidate received an interview 
from the employer. (We assume that in each of these cases the candidate did 
from the employer. (We assume that in each of these cases the candidate did 
apply for the job and thus was considered for an interview.) The regressor of 
apply for the job and thus was considered for an interview.) The regressor of 
interest is an indicator variable that equals one if the candidate signaled that 
interest is an indicator variable that equals one if the candidate signaled that 
employer, and zero if the candidate would have signaled the employer if either 
employer, and zero if the candidate would have signaled the employer if either 
the candidate had had a third signal (if they sent two) or the candidate had sent 
the candidate had had a third signal (if they sent two) or the candidate had sent 
any signals (if they sent none). 
any signals (if they sent none). 
Thus, in all cases, the candidate was interested in the employer and presum-
Thus, in all cases, the candidate was interested in the employer and presum-
ably considered that employer to be a good match. For candidates who sent two 
ably considered that employer to be a good match. For candidates who sent two 
signals, one can think of this model as exploiting something akin to a regression 
signals, one can think of this model as exploiting something akin to a regression 
discontinuity: the third-choice employer was presumably about as good a match 
discontinuity: the third-choice employer was presumably about as good a match 
for the candidate as the fi rst-and second-choice employers, but only the top two 
for the candidate as the fi rst-and second-choice employers, but only the top two </p>

<p>8 We investigated the possibility of nonresponse bias by comparing the characteristics of those who 
responded to our survey about job market outcomes to those of all signalers. These characteristics 
include indicator variables for current graduate student, economics as primary fi eld, degree from 
a U.S. institution, tier of degree-granting institution (as defi ned in Table 2), and tier of employers 
signaled. Ratios for these variables in the survey sample and population were virtually identical. 
9 In the reported regression results, we use the applicant as the panel variable to address unobserved 
applicant quality. We also ran each regression using the employer as the panel variable and using a 
two-way clustered standard errors ordinary least squares model, fi nding similar results. Using appli-
cant fi xed effects instead of random effects, and logit specifi cations rather than ordinary least squares, 
again produces similar results. </p>



<p>employers were sent signals. For candidates who did not send any signals, one can 
employers were sent signals. For candidates who did not send any signals, one can 
think of this model as exploiting something akin to a natural experiment: the 
think of this model as exploiting something akin to a natural experiment: the 
treatment group sent their two signals, and the control group did not send their 
treatment group sent their two signals, and the control group did not send their 
two signals (perhaps because they were unaware of the signaling mechanism, or 
two signals (perhaps because they were unaware of the signaling mechanism, or 
because they missed the deadline). What makes this comparison meaningful is that 
because they missed the deadline). What makes this comparison meaningful is that 
in all cases job candidates thought themselves good matches with the employers, 
in all cases job candidates thought themselves good matches with the employers, 
but in only a subset of cases were signals actually sent. 
but in only a subset of cases were signals actually sent. 
Table 3 displays the main results. In column A of Table 3, the intercept shows 
Table 3 displays the main results. In column A of Table 3, the intercept shows 
that applications to economics departments that were unaccompanied by signals 
that applications to economics departments that were unaccompanied by signals 
resulted in interviews with a 24.7 percent success rate. (If this seems high, recall 
resulted in interviews with a 24.7 percent success rate. (If this seems high, recall 
that every observation in this sample concerns a job that the candidate considered 
that every observation in this sample concerns a job that the candidate considered 
a suffi ciently good match that the candidate ranked it in the top three for sending 
a suffi ciently good match that the candidate ranked it in the top three for sending </p>

<p>Table 3 
The Association of Sending a Signal with Receiving an Interview </p>

<p>(A) 
(B) 
(C) 
(D) 
(E) </p>

<p>Sample 
Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>All 
employers </p>

<p>Panel data grouping 
Candidate 
n/a 
Candidate 
Candidate 
Candidate </p>

<p>Signal 
0.0680** 
0.158*** 
0.0321 
0.0580* 
0.0634** 
(0.0287) 
(0.0443) 
(0.0328) 
(0.0317) 
(0.0271) </p>

<p>Is graduate student 
0.176*** 
(0.0481) </p>

<p>(Is graduate student) 
-0.101* 
* Signal 
(0.0556) </p>

<p>Applied to liberal arts 
-0.0482 
school 
(0.0587) </p>

<p>(Applied to liberal arts 
0.177*** 
school) * Signal 
(0.0675) </p>

<p>Applied to international 
-0.0295 
school 
(0.0654) </p>

<p>(Applied to international 
0.0583 
school) * Signal 
(0.0739) </p>

<p>Applied to nonacademic 
0.132* 
employer 
(0.0765) </p>

<p>(Applied to nonacademic 
-0.130 
employer) * Signal 
(0.0827) </p>

<p>Constant 
0.247*** 
0.114*** 
0.259*** 
0.252*** 
0.254*** 
(0.0256) 
(0.0376) 
(0.0296) 
(0.0283) 
(0.0242) </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.003 
0.012 
0.015 
0.004 
0.003 
Observations 
1,529 
1,520 
1,529 
1,529 
1,868 
Number of candidate 
groups </p>

<p>728 
n/a 
728 
728 
785 </p>

<p>(continued on next page) </p>

<p>Peter Coles, John Cawley, Phillip Levine, Muriel Niederle, Alvin Roth, and John Siegfried 197 </p>

<p>a signal.) The coeffi cient on the indicator variable for having sent a signal indicates 
a signal.) The coeffi cient on the indicator variable for having sent a signal indicates 
that sending a signal (relative to not sending a signal but considering it a suffi ciently 
that sending a signal (relative to not sending a signal but considering it a suffi ciently 
good match that a signal would have been sent had the candidate participated in 
good match that a signal would have been sent had the candidate participated in </p>

<p>Table 3 (continued) </p>

<p>(F) 
(G) 
(H) 
(I) 
( J) </p>

<p>Sample 
U.S. 
economics 
departments </p>

<p>U.S. 
economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Economics 
departments </p>

<p>Panel data grouping 
Candidate 
Candidate 
Candidate 
Candidate 
Candidate </p>

<p>Signal 
0.0191 
-0.00325 
0.00712 
0.00122 
0.104*** 
(0.0378) 
(0.0395) 
(0.0370) 
(0.0373) 
(0.0345) </p>

<p>Town (pop. &lt; 50,000) 
-0.0665 
-0.0419 
(0.0593) 
(0.0656) </p>

<p>Town * Signal 
0.133** 
0.0601 
(0.0661) 
(0.0735) </p>

<p>Applied to liberal arts 
-0.0433 
-0.0314 
school 
(0.0676) 
(0.0669) </p>

<p>(Applied to liberal arts 
0.178** 
0.115 
school) * Signal 
(0.0778) 
(0.0767) </p>

<p>Applied to unranked 
-0.0370 
-0.0221 
school 
(0.0514) 
(0.0588) </p>

<p>(Applied to an unranked 
0.152** 
0.109 
school) * Signal 
(0.0591) 
(0.0674) </p>

<p>Received many signals 
0.00227 
(≥ than 7) 
(0.0307) </p>

<p>(Received many signals) 
-0.0648* 
* Signal 
(0.0347) </p>

<p>Constant 
0.271*** 
0.278*** 
0.265*** 
0.266*** 
0.246*** 
(0.0344) 
(0.0363) 
(0.0340) 
(0.0344) 
(0.0274) </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.015 
0.015 
0.012 
0.015 
0.006 
Observations 
1,266 
1,266 
1,529 
1,529 
1,529 
Number of candidate 
groups </p>

<p>638 
638 
728 
728 
728 </p>

<p>Notes: The data are from surveys conducted in 2007 and 2008. This table summarizes coeffi cients in 
a random-effects ordinary least squares linear probability model in which the unit of observation is a 
single application from a candidate to an employer. The dependent variable is an indicator variable for 
whether the candidate received an interview from the employer to which the application was sent. The 
regressor of interest is an indicator variable that equals one if the candidate signaled that employer 
and zero if the candidate would have signaled the employer if either the candidate had been allowed 
a third signal (if they sent two) or the candidate had sent any signals (if they sent none). In columns 
B-J, we include additional indicator variables for characteristics of the candidate or the employer, 
along with the interaction of these variables with the indicator variable for whether the candidate sent 
a signal. We use the candidate as the panel variable to address unobserved candidate quality (with 
the exception of the regression in column B, which measures the impact of a candidate-specifi c trait: 
being a graduate student). Robust standard errors are in parentheses. 
***, **, and * represent signifi cance at 1 percent, 5 percent, and 10 percent levels respectively. </p>



<p>the process or had one more signal) is associated with a 6.8 percentage point higher 
the process or had one more signal) is associated with a 6.8 percentage point higher 
probability of receiving an interview; this difference is statistically signifi cant at the 
probability of receiving an interview; this difference is statistically signifi cant at the 
5 percent level. That is, applications accompanied by signals resulted in interviews 
5 percent level. That is, applications accompanied by signals resulted in interviews 
with a 31.5 percent success rate. 
with a 31.5 percent success rate. 
This suggests (but given the study design, cannot prove) that signals are helpful 
This suggests (but given the study design, cannot prove) that signals are helpful 
in securing interviews. We next investigate whether the association of signaling with 
in securing interviews. We next investigate whether the association of signaling with 
receiving an interview is higher for some groups than for others. In column B of 
receiving an interview is higher for some groups than for others. In column B of 
Table 3, we compare the signaling outcomes of current graduate students to those 
Table 3, we compare the signaling outcomes of current graduate students to those 
for non-graduate students (like postdocs or assistant professors). This comparison 
for non-graduate students (like postdocs or assistant professors). This comparison 
requires two additional indicator variables: one for whether the applicant is a 
requires two additional indicator variables: one for whether the applicant is a 
graduate student, and the other an interaction term for being a graduate student 
graduate student, and the other an interaction term for being a graduate student 
who signaled. Column B in Table 3 shows that for current graduate students, 
who signaled. Column B in Table 3 shows that for current graduate students, 
signals are associated with a 5.7 percentage point increase in the probability of 
signals are associated with a 5.7 percentage point increase in the probability of 
receiving an interview (adding the coeffi cient of .158 on sending a signal to the 
receiving an interview (adding the coeffi cient of .158 on sending a signal to the 
coeffi cient of -.101 on the interaction of sending a signal and graduate student 
coeffi cient of -.101 on the interaction of sending a signal and graduate student 
status). Absent a signal, the probability of an interview for a graduate student is 
status). Absent a signal, the probability of an interview for a graduate student is 
29.0 percent (adding .114 and .176); with a signal, the probability is 34.7 percent. In 
29.0 percent (adding .114 and .176); with a signal, the probability is 34.7 percent. In 
contrast, for non-graduate students, signals are associated with a 15.8 percentage 
contrast, for non-graduate students, signals are associated with a 15.8 percentage 
point increase in the probability of receiving an interview. A potential explanation 
point increase in the probability of receiving an interview. A potential explanation 
for this difference is that non-graduate students might be more likely to be over-
for this difference is that non-graduate students might be more likely to be over-
looked-for example, they are less likely to appear on department web-pages of job 
looked-for example, they are less likely to appear on department web-pages of job 
candidates-so signals are particularly helpful for attracting attention. 
candidates-so signals are particularly helpful for attracting attention. 
Liberal arts colleges may be particularly interested in signals because they 
Liberal arts colleges may be particularly interested in signals because they 
often have different preferences than research universities regarding teaching. 
often have different preferences than research universities regarding teaching. 
Liberal arts colleges might also be concerned that they are receiving applications 
Liberal arts colleges might also be concerned that they are receiving applications 
from candidates who have strong preferences for a job in a research university 
from candidates who have strong preferences for a job in a research university 
but are applying widely. In 2009, we sent surveys to 50 economics departments in 
but are applying widely. In 2009, we sent surveys to 50 economics departments in 
liberal arts colleges asking how they view signals. Of the 35 responding depart-
liberal arts colleges asking how they view signals. Of the 35 responding depart-
ments, 17 reported receiving signals. Of these, 12 reported offering interviews 
ments, 17 reported receiving signals. Of these, 12 reported offering interviews 
to candidates "in part because of the signals." Of course, receiving a signal did 
to candidates "in part because of the signals." Of course, receiving a signal did 
not guarantee that an interview would be offered. However, no schools reported 
not guarantee that an interview would be offered. However, no schools reported 
interpreting the signal negatively; in particular, no candidate was removed from 
interpreting the signal negatively; in particular, no candidate was removed from 
the interview list for sending a signal. The data corroborate these survey fi ndings. 
the interview list for sending a signal. The data corroborate these survey fi ndings. 
Column C in Table 3 indicates that a signal to an economics department in a 
Column C in Table 3 indicates that a signal to an economics department in a 
liberal arts college was associated with a 20.9 percentage point higher probability 
liberal arts college was associated with a 20.9 percentage point higher probability 
of receiving an interview; in contrast, signals sent to economics departments 
of receiving an interview; in contrast, signals sent to economics departments 
not in liberal arts colleges were associated with a 3.2 percentage point higher 
not in liberal arts colleges were associated with a 3.2 percentage point higher 
probability of an interview (which is not statistically signifi cant). Candidates 
probability of an interview (which is not statistically signifi cant). Candidates 
who consider signaling a liberal arts college because of this fi nding should 
who consider signaling a liberal arts college because of this fi nding should 
recognize this result is likely driven by selection-those who may have benefi ted 
recognize this result is likely driven by selection-those who may have benefi ted 
from sending signals to liberal arts colleges were likely good matches for those 
from sending signals to liberal arts colleges were likely good matches for those 
colleges, while a randomly chosen candidate who signals a liberal arts college 
colleges, while a randomly chosen candidate who signals a liberal arts college 
based on these regression results may not enjoy any increase in the probability of 
based on these regression results may not enjoy any increase in the probability of 
an interview. 
an interview. </p>

<p>The Job Market for New Economists: A Market Design Perspective 199 </p>

<p>Another group of employers we hypothesized might fi nd signals particularly 
Another group of employers we hypothesized might fi nd signals particularly 
informative is economics departments outside the United States. They may also 
informative is economics departments outside the United States. They may also 
have to separate candidates with real interest from applicants who have strong 
have to separate candidates with real interest from applicants who have strong 
preferences for a job in North America and those seeking all-expenses-paid inter-
preferences for a job in North America and those seeking all-expenses-paid inter-
national trips disguised as campus visits. We test this hypothesis in column D 
national trips disguised as campus visits. We test this hypothesis in column D 
of Table 3. It is not possible to reject the null hypothesis that the association of 
of Table 3. It is not possible to reject the null hypothesis that the association of 
signaling with probability of interview is the same for international as domestic 
signaling with probability of interview is the same for international as domestic 
U.S. employers. 
U.S. employers. 
Column E of Table 3 compares outcomes for signals sent to academic and to 
Column E of Table 3 compares outcomes for signals sent to academic and to 
nonacademic positions. (For this model only, the sample is expanded from just 
nonacademic positions. (For this model only, the sample is expanded from just 
economics departments to all employers.) There is no evidence that signaling a 
economics departments to all employers.) There is no evidence that signaling a 
nonacademic employer is associated with a higher probability of receiving an inter-
nonacademic employer is associated with a higher probability of receiving an inter-
view, though applications to nonacademic employers are associated with higher 
view, though applications to nonacademic employers are associated with higher 
interview rates regardless of signals. 
interview rates regardless of signals. 
Schools in small towns might face a similar informational challenge to liberal 
Schools in small towns might face a similar informational challenge to liberal 
arts colleges: that is, distinguishing candidates with serious interest from those 
arts colleges: that is, distinguishing candidates with serious interest from those 
who are simply risk-averse and have applied everywhere. Column F in Table 3 
who are simply risk-averse and have applied everywhere. Column F in Table 3 
displays outcomes for economics departments in towns with population under 
displays outcomes for economics departments in towns with population under 
50,000. Signals to these departments were associated with a 15.2 percentage point 
50,000. Signals to these departments were associated with a 15.2 percentage point 
higher probability of an interview, compared to a 1.9 percentage point higher 
higher probability of an interview, compared to a 1.9 percentage point higher 
probability of an interview for signals sent to departments in larger cities. This 
probability of an interview for signals sent to departments in larger cities. This 
difference is signifi cant at the 1 percent level. When controlling for whether the 
difference is signifi cant at the 1 percent level. When controlling for whether the 
school is a liberal arts college, as shown in column G of Table 3, there is still 
school is a liberal arts college, as shown in column G of Table 3, there is still 
a 6.0 percentage point difference based on city size, but the result is no longer 
a 6.0 percentage point difference based on city size, but the result is no longer 
statistically signifi cant. (Signaling a liberal arts college that is not in a small town 
statistically signifi cant. (Signaling a liberal arts college that is not in a small town 
is associated with a 17.8 percentage point increase in the probability of interview, 
is associated with a 17.8 percentage point increase in the probability of interview, 
which is statistically signifi cant.) 
which is statistically signifi cant.) 
The fi nal employers we consider are departments that do not appear in 
The fi nal employers we consider are departments that do not appear in 
econphd.net's rankings of economics departments. These 361 schools received 
econphd.net's rankings of economics departments. These 361 schools received 
1,188 signals over the two-year period 2007-8, representing 37 percent of all 
1,188 signals over the two-year period 2007-8, representing 37 percent of all 
signals to economics departments during that time. Column H in Table 3 shows 
signals to economics departments during that time. Column H in Table 3 shows 
that signals to unranked departments are associated with a 15 percentage point 
that signals to unranked departments are associated with a 15 percentage point 
higher probability of interview relative to signals sent to ranked schools. When 
higher probability of interview relative to signals sent to ranked schools. When 
controlling for whether the institution is a liberal arts college (see Column I of 
controlling for whether the institution is a liberal arts college (see Column I of 
Table 3), the difference drops to 10.9 percentage points, which is no longer statis-
Table 3), the difference drops to 10.9 percentage points, which is no longer statis-
tically signifi cant. 
tically signifi cant. 
Column J in Table 3 examines the role of the total number of signals that an 
Column J in Table 3 examines the role of the total number of signals that an 
employer receives. We divide employers into two groups: those that received seven 
employer receives. We divide employers into two groups: those that received seven 
or more signals and those that received six or fewer. 
or more signals and those that received six or fewer. 
10 10 A signal to an employer who 
A signal to an employer who </p>

<p>10 In the sample used for these regressions, 10 percent of job postings received seven or more signals 
(and these accounted for 36 percent of signals in the sample). For comparison, within our entire 
dataset, 12 percent of postings in 2007 and 2008 received seven or more signals (accounting for 
37 percent of signals). </p>



<p>received six or fewer signals was associated with a 10.4 percentage point higher prob-
received six or fewer signals was associated with a 10.4 percentage point higher prob-
ability of an interview. In contrast, sending a signal to an employer who received 
ability of an interview. In contrast, sending a signal to an employer who received 
seven or more signals was associated with just a 3.9 percentage point increase in the 
seven or more signals was associated with just a 3.9 percentage point increase in the 
probability of interview. Although we are cautious about interpreting these results 
probability of interview. Although we are cautious about interpreting these results 
as causal effects, it may be that signals are less effective when sent to schools that 
as causal effects, it may be that signals are less effective when sent to schools that 
receive many of them. 
receive many of them. 
In general, these results should be interpreted with care. Those who send 
In general, these results should be interpreted with care. Those who send 
signals may well have been better fi ts for the institutions they signaled than those 
signals may well have been better fi ts for the institutions they signaled than those 
who only designated the institution for a hypothetical signal. To some extent, 
who only designated the institution for a hypothetical signal. To some extent, that 
better fi t may have been detectable to the employer even in the absence of the 
signal. The ability to send the signal may also mean that job candidates can make 
less effort along other dimensions to convey their personal interest in certain 
employers. Most concisely, these results should be interpreted as showing that 
signaling was associated with a higher probability of receiving an interview for 
the particular candidates who signaled these particular employers. Candidates deciding 
where to signal should choose employers appropriate for themselves. 
A limitation of this analysis is that, while we have data on whether signals 
A limitation of this analysis is that, while we have data on whether signals 
were sent, we lack data on whether they were received. In some cases, the AEA's 
were sent, we lack data on whether they were received. In some cases, the AEA's 
e-mail containing the signals may have remained unopened or was not seen by 
e-mail containing the signals may have remained unopened or was not seen by 
the recruiting committee. To the extent this occurred, the results presented here, 
the recruiting committee. To the extent this occurred, the results presented here, 
which are suggestive regarding the effect of sending a signal, understate the effect 
which are suggestive regarding the effect of sending a signal, understate the effect 
of a signal being received. 
of a signal being received. 
Employers may respond to an interesting signal by adding an interview slot, 
Employers may respond to an interesting signal by adding an interview slot, 
but it is also possible that a successful signal by one candidate displaces another 
but it is also possible that a successful signal by one candidate displaces another 
candidate from the interview list. This represents a cost or at least a consequence 
candidate from the interview list. This represents a cost or at least a consequence 
of the signaling mechanism. Even if one supposes a "zero-sum" game in which no 
of the signaling mechanism. Even if one supposes a "zero-sum" game in which no 
employer adds slots upon receiving signals, to the extent that matches generated 
employer adds slots upon receiving signals, to the extent that matches generated 
by signals are higher value than those crowded out, the signals can nevertheless 
by signals are higher value than those crowded out, the signals can nevertheless 
increase allocative effi ciency. 
increase allocative effi ciency. </p>

<p>The Scramble 
The Scramble </p>

<p>As candidates are hired and positions fi lled, the market becomes thinner, and 
As candidates are hired and positions fi lled, the market becomes thinner, and 
information obtained from fall applications and advertisements and from January 
information obtained from fall applications and advertisements and from January 
interviews becomes dated. To reduce search costs in this thin, late stage of the 
interviews becomes dated. To reduce search costs in this thin, late stage of the 
market, in 2006, the AEA formalized a secondary market scramble. The initial 
market, in 2006, the AEA formalized a secondary market scramble. The initial 
announcement stated: 
announcement stated: </p>

<p>Occasionally prospective employers of new Ph.D. economists exhaust their 
candidates before hiring someone during the winter/spring " job market" 
period. Similarly, new economics Ph.D.s seeking a job sometimes fi nd that 
all of the prospective employers interested in them have hired someone else 
before they have secured an appointment. </p>

<p>Peter Coles, John Cawley, Phillip Levine, Muriel Niederle, Alvin Roth, and John Siegfried 201 </p>

<p>To address these problems, the AEA will establish a "Job Market Scramble" 
website to facilitate communication between employers and job seekers in 
late spring. Between March 15 and March 20, 2006, employers that continue 
to have an available position advertised in Job Openings for Economists ( JOE) 
prior to January 1, 2006 may post a short notice of its availability (with a link 
to the JOE listing). Similarly, new or recent economics Ph.D. job seekers still 
looking for a position may post a short announcement of their continued 
availability at that time, with a link to their application materials (cv, papers, 
references). The website will open for viewing at noon on Wednesday, March 
21, 2006 Eastern time. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Table 4 provides some descriptive statistics for the scramble from 2006 to 2010. 
Table 4 provides some descriptive statistics for the scramble from 2006 to 2010. 
The number of employers has ranged from 67 to 100; employers typically advertise 
The number of employers has ranged from 67 to 100; employers typically advertise 
one position each; the number of job applicants has ranged from 361 to 535. 
one position each; the number of job applicants has ranged from 361 to 535. 
From 2006-2009, we surveyed participants to gauge the results of the 
From 2006-2009, we surveyed participants to gauge the results of the 
scramble. The response rates have been modest: about 30-40 percent of 
scramble. The response rates have been modest: about 30-40 percent of 
employers and 20-30 percent of job candidates. The survey results suggest that 
employers and 20-30 percent of job candidates. The survey results suggest that 
about half of employers initiate an interview as a result of the scramble. The 
about half of employers initiate an interview as a result of the scramble. The 
survey results also allow us to identify some of the jobs that have been fi lled, and 
survey results also allow us to identify some of the jobs that have been fi lled, and 
confi rm that at least 10 percent of the jobs listed in the scramble have been fi lled 
confi rm that at least 10 percent of the jobs listed in the scramble have been fi lled 
through the contacts it facilitated. In the 2008 follow-up survey, 17 of the 22 
through the contacts it facilitated. In the 2008 follow-up survey, 17 of the 22 
responding employers who contacted applicants in the scramble were academic 
responding employers who contacted applicants in the scramble were academic 
economics departments, as were 8 of the 10 responding employers who reported 
economics departments, as were 8 of the 10 responding employers who reported 
hiring through the scramble. 
hiring through the scramble. 
In 2009, the scramble underwent a noteworthy change. Some employers 
In 2009, the scramble underwent a noteworthy change. Some employers 
complained that they were inundated with e-mails and calls from candidates 
complained that they were inundated with e-mails and calls from candidates 
in the scramble, and expressed reluctance to participate again unless they 
in the scramble, and expressed reluctance to participate again unless they </p>

<p>11 The AEA description continues: "The scramble webpage will not be updated to include new list-
ings. The committee does not want the website to become a pernicious waste of time for job market 
candidates; if new listings could be posted, candidates might be tempted to log on to the site frequently 
in search of new jobs. To avoid this, the only information that will ever be contained on the webpage 
is that which is on it the fi rst minute it goes online." See 〈http://www.aeaweb.org/joe/scramble/guide. 
pdf〉 (AEA Ad Hoc Committee on the Job Market, 2010a). </p>

<p>Table 4 
Basic Descriptives of the Job Market Scramble </p>

<p>2006 
2007 
2008 
2009 
2010 </p>

<p>Employers registered 
70 
67 
100 
78 
67 
Total positions 
70 
75 
103 
87 
71 
Job applicants registered 
518 
535 
361 
395 
374 </p>

<p>Note: Prior to the 2008 scramble, it was emphasized that the scramble was primarily for new Ph.D.s, 
which accounts for much of the decline in applicants registered. </p>



<p>could remain invisible to job applicants while still viewing which job candidates 
could remain invisible to job applicants while still viewing which job candidates 
remained available. The committee, wanting the market to be thick, agreed, 
remained available. The committee, wanting the market to be thick, agreed, 
somewhat reluctantly. In 2009, 17 of the 87 positions were not made visible even 
somewhat reluctantly. In 2009, 17 of the 87 positions were not made visible even 
to registered applicants; these were openings with employers who preferred to 
to registered applicants; these were openings with employers who preferred to 
lurk-that is, to observe available applicants but not to be observed by them. The 
lurk-that is, to observe available applicants but not to be observed by them. The 
Committee was unable to detect a pattern in which employers chose to remain 
Committee was unable to detect a pattern in which employers chose to remain 
visible and which chose to be invisible. 
visible and which chose to be invisible. </p>

<p>12 12 </p>

<p>Transmission of Job Market Materials 
Transmission of Job Market Materials </p>

<p>There is presently a good deal of coordination in certain aspects of the 
There is presently a good deal of coordination in certain aspects of the 
American job market for Ph.D.s, such as the dissemination of information about 
American job market for Ph.D.s, such as the dissemination of information about 
available positions through Job Openings for Economists, and the synchroniza-
available positions through Job Openings for Economists, and the synchroniza-
tion of initial interviews at the ASSA meetings. However other aspects of the job 
tion of initial interviews at the ASSA meetings. However other aspects of the job 
market are uncoordinated, such as how job market materials and reference letters 
market are uncoordinated, such as how job market materials and reference letters 
are transmitted. Until recently, these were all sent by mail, but the Internet has 
are transmitted. Until recently, these were all sent by mail, but the Internet has 
made possible submission by e-mail or web application. In the last several years, job 
made possible submission by e-mail or web application. In the last several years, job 
seekers and their references have had to use multiple channels, which may be more 
seekers and their references have had to use multiple channels, which may be more 
costly in time and effort than if all information were transmitted the same way. 
costly in time and effort than if all information were transmitted the same way. 
Two kinds of web applications have a presence in the market. Some depart-
Two kinds of web applications have a presence in the market. Some depart-
ments are in institutions that use a university-wide platform, usually purchased 
ments are in institutions that use a university-wide platform, usually purchased 
commercially and then operated by the human resources department. Such 
commercially and then operated by the human resources department. Such 
university-specifi c systems impose high costs on applicants and references because 
university-specifi c systems impose high costs on applicants and references because 
they require individual uploading for each application and letter of reference. 
they require individual uploading for each application and letter of reference. 
Other employers use third-party services such as <rs type="software">EconJobMarket.org</rs>, 
Other employers use third-party services such as EconJobMarket.org, 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">AcademicJobsOnline.org</rs> (run by <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Duke's Math Department</rs>, offering services to 
AcademicJobsOnline.org (run by Duke's Math Department, offering services to 
all sorts of departments), and others such as <rs type="software">Academic Careers Online</rs> at 
all sorts of departments), and others such as Academic Careers Online at 〈 〈http:// http:// 
www.academiccareers-job.com/ www.academiccareers-job.com/〉 〉, <rs type="software">Economist Jobs</rs> at 
, Economist Jobs at 〈 〈http://www.econ-jobs.com/ http://www.econ-jobs.com/〉 〉, , 
<rs type="software">EconCareers</rs> at 
EconCareers at 〈 〈http://www.econcareers.com/ http://www.econcareers.com/〉 〉, and <rs type="software">LiberalArtsFacultyJobs.com</rs>. 
, and LiberalArtsFacultyJobs.com. 
The job listing aggregator <rs type="software">walras.org</rs> has also explored offering such a service. 
The job listing aggregator walras.org has also explored offering such a service. 
The website of <rs type="software">EconJobMarket.org</rs> (accessed March 1, 2010) indicates some 
The website of EconJobMarket.org (accessed March 1, 2010) indicates some 
consolidation: their service has been merged with that of the European Economic 
consolidation: their service has been merged with that of the European Economic 
Association and has been endorsed by other economics organizations. 
Association and has been endorsed by other economics organizations. 
The setup costs for job applicants and references would be reduced if there 
The setup costs for job applicants and references would be reduced if there 
were fewer services transmitting data to employers. Universities with unique 
were fewer services transmitting data to employers. Universities with unique </p>

<p>12 The visible employers in 2009 consisted of 20 universities with graduate programs, 18 four-year 
colleges, 10 consulting or research fi rms, seven federal government agencies, four banking or fi nance 
fi rms, and two "other." The employers who chose to remain invisible consisted of eight universities 
with graduate programs, three four-year colleges, three federal government agencies, two consulting 
or research fi rms, and one banking or fi nance fi rm. </p>

<p>The Job Market for New Economists: A Market Design Perspective 203 </p>

<p>websites for job applicants could urge their software providers to make it easy for 
websites for job applicants could urge their software providers to make it easy for 
candidates and references to upload materials to other sites. 
candidates and references to upload materials to other sites. </p>

<p>13 13 </p>

<p>For comparison, the American Mathematical Society (AMA), like the AEA, 
For comparison, the American Mathematical Society (AMA), like the AEA, 
publishes job openings and facilitates an "Employment Center" at its annual meeting. 
publishes job openings and facilitates an "Employment Center" at its annual meeting. 
But in addition, since August 2000, the AMA sponsors an automated job application 
But in addition, since August 2000, the AMA sponsors an automated job application 
system, <rs type="software">MathJobs.Org</rs>, that both lists jobs and transmits job packets and letters of refer-
system, MathJobs.Org, that both lists jobs and transmits job packets and letters of refer-
ence. MathJobs.Org reported in February 2010 that in the previous year 307 employers 
ence. MathJobs.Org reported in February 2010 that in the previous year 307 employers 
used the site and 5,552 applicants submitted an average of 22.7 applications each. 
used the site and 5,552 applicants submitted an average of 22.7 applications each. 
In contrast, the web-based services that offer to serve as a clearinghouse for 
In contrast, the web-based services that offer to serve as a clearinghouse for 
job packets and letters of recommendation haven't gained as much traction among 
job packets and letters of recommendation haven't gained as much traction among 
economists. <rs type="software">AcademicJobsOnline.org</rs> (launched in 2006 and offering services to 
economists. AcademicJobsOnline.org (launched in 2006 and offering services to 
disciplines other than mathematics) had 155 participating employers (including a 
disciplines other than mathematics) had 155 participating employers (including a 
small number of economics departments) using the site in the 12 months prior to 
small number of economics departments) using the site in the 12 months prior to 
February 2010, in which 8,285 applicants submitted an average of 3.7 applications 
February 2010, in which 8,285 applicants submitted an average of 3.7 applications 
each. <rs type="software">EconJobMarket.org</rs> reports that 262 employers had signed up by the end 
each. EconJobMarket.org reports that 262 employers had signed up by the end 
of 2009 and that the average number of applications per job candidate was 13 
of 2009 and that the average number of applications per job candidate was 13 
(personal communication, John Rust, 2/28/10). 
(personal communication, John Rust, 2/28/10). </p>

<p>14 14 </p>

<p>Should the AEA play some role in operating, endorsing, or collaborating with 
Should the AEA play some role in operating, endorsing, or collaborating with 
one or more services for transmitting job market information? Our committee has 
one or more services for transmitting job market information? Our committee has 
been presented with several such proposals, but so far has not recommended that 
been presented with several such proposals, but so far has not recommended that 
the AEA select one or more to support. It seems likely that there will be further 
the AEA select one or more to support. It seems likely that there will be further 
consolidation in the coming years, which may affect how vacant positions are 
consolidation in the coming years, which may affect how vacant positions are 
announced and advertised. If many competing providers persist, candidates and 
announced and advertised. If many competing providers persist, candidates and 
letter writers may continue to face high transaction costs. But if one independent 
letter writers may continue to face high transaction costs. But if one independent 
site becomes dominant, it could raise prices or expand or limit its scope in ways 
site becomes dominant, it could raise prices or expand or limit its scope in ways 
that might adversely affect the economics profession. These developments deserve 
that might adversely affect the economics profession. These developments deserve 
continued attention. 
continued attention. </p>

<p>Concluding Remarks 
Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>Members of the Ad Hoc Committee on the Job Market have been asked why 
Members of the Ad Hoc Committee on the Job Market have been asked why 
the market for economists does not move toward computer matching based on 
the market for economists does not move toward computer matching based on 
preference rankings. Precedents for this include the American market for medical 
preference rankings. Precedents for this include the American market for medical 
residents, in which about 20,000 graduating physicians are centrally matched with 
residents, in which about 20,000 graduating physicians are centrally matched with 
residency programs based on rankings fi lled out by both applicants and programs 
residency programs based on rankings fi lled out by both applicants and programs 
(Roth, 1984; Roth and Peranson, 1999). Other examples include many other 
(Roth, 1984; Roth and Peranson, 1999). Other examples include many other </p>

<p>13 However, university-specifi c application protocols may partly serve to impose a small cost on appli-
cants who may be deterred from making the most marginal applications. 
14 John Rust writes: "[Y]ou can get a sense of the rate of growth from the date the account applications 
were approved: 39 by end of 2007 (EJM's fi rst year of operation), 139 by end of 2008, and 172 as of 
today [Sept. 23, 2009]" (personal communication). He further writes (2/28/10): "EJM is starting to 
see increasing "secondary market trading" for tenured professorships and other positions that are not 
connected with the North American new Ph.D. hiring cycle." </p>



<p>medical and healthcare labor markets (Roth, 2008b), and several public school 
medical and healthcare labor markets (Roth, 2008b), and several public school 
systems, including about 90,000 students each year in New York City who are 
systems, including about 90,000 students each year in New York City who are 
centrally matched to high schools based on their listed preferences and other rules 
centrally matched to high schools based on their listed preferences and other rules 
(Abdulkadiro (Abdulkadiro ˘ 
g lu, Pathak, and Roth, 2005, 2009; Abdulkadiro 
g lu, Pathak, and Roth, 2005, 2009; Abdulkadiro ˘ 
g lu, Pathak, Roth, 
g lu, Pathak, Roth, 
and Sönmez, 2005). 
and Sönmez, 2005). 
Decentralized markets that adopted centralized clearinghouses were most 
Decentralized markets that adopted centralized clearinghouses were most 
often experiencing such costly and pervasive market failure that there was wide-
often experiencing such costly and pervasive market failure that there was wide-
spread interest in a radical change (Niederle and Roth, 2003, 2009a, b). We do not 
spread interest in a radical change (Niederle and Roth, 2003, 2009a, b). We do not 
detect such interest in economics, so it is unlikely that such a change is presently 
detect such interest in economics, so it is unlikely that such a change is presently 
feasible, even if we were sure it would be desirable. 
feasible, even if we were sure it would be desirable. 
Investigating the desirability of a clearinghouse would involve exploring ways 
Investigating the desirability of a clearinghouse would involve exploring ways 
in which the market for economics Ph.D.s might differ from markets that have 
in which the market for economics Ph.D.s might differ from markets that have 
adopted clearinghouses. These might involve, among other things, the large costs 
adopted clearinghouses. These might involve, among other things, the large costs 
that employers willingly incur simply determining their preferences over potential 
that employers willingly incur simply determining their preferences over potential 
hires, costs that involve reading papers, interviewing, one-on-one meetings, and 
hires, costs that involve reading papers, interviewing, one-on-one meetings, and 
job market seminars that convene a substantial part of a department's faculty. In 
job market seminars that convene a substantial part of a department's faculty. In 
the decentralized market, departments may be able to contain these costs by fl ying 
the decentralized market, departments may be able to contain these costs by fl ying 
out the most likely candidates fi rst. 
out the most likely candidates fi rst. 
Practical market design is often a response to particular problems. The 
Practical market design is often a response to particular problems. The 
choice of mechanisms will be guided by theory and experience, but often, 
choice of mechanisms will be guided by theory and experience, but often, 
practical questions are addressed before fi rm theoretical foundations are estab-
practical questions are addressed before fi rm theoretical foundations are estab-
lished (Roth, 2002). This is one reason why new market institutions should be 
lished (Roth, 2002). This is one reason why new market institutions should be 
monitored and why a new market design will often lead the way to developing 
monitored and why a new market design will often lead the way to developing 
new knowledge. 
new knowledge. 
In just this way, a number of questions arose when we considered signaling. For 
In just this way, a number of questions arose when we considered signaling. For 
example, how many signals should be allowed? We settled on two, in part because 
example, how many signals should be allowed? We settled on two, in part because 
if signals were more plentiful, then employers might view negatively candidates 
if signals were more plentiful, then employers might view negatively candidates 
who did not send them a signal. Should job candidates be allowed to announce 
who did not send them a signal. Should job candidates be allowed to announce 
publicly that they were not 
publicly that they were not sending any signals? We decided against facilitating 
sending any signals? We decided against facilitating 
such announcements, again to avoid bad equilibria in which signals were inter-
such announcements, again to avoid bad equilibria in which signals were inter-
preted negatively (perhaps as signs of candidates who were not confi dent they 
preted negatively (perhaps as signs of candidates who were not confi dent they 
could otherwise effectively indicate interest to employers) with the potential result 
could otherwise effectively indicate interest to employers) with the potential result 
that no signals are sent. At what point or points in the job market might signaling 
that no signals are sent. At what point or points in the job market might signaling 
do the most good? If signaling before interviews reduces congestion, why not also 
do the most good? If signaling before interviews reduces congestion, why not also 
allow candidates, after the ASSA interviews, to signal their interest in a fl y-out? 
allow candidates, after the ASSA interviews, to signal their interest in a fl y-out? 
As we learn more about the role that signaling plays for interviews, this may be a 
As we learn more about the role that signaling plays for interviews, this may be a 
future direction. The theory of signaling and matching in decentralized markets 
future direction. The theory of signaling and matching in decentralized markets 
is being pushed forward by such questions (see for example, Coles, Kushnir, and 
is being pushed forward by such questions (see for example, Coles, Kushnir, and 
Niederle, 2009; Niederle and Yariv, 2009). 
Niederle, 2009; Niederle and Yariv, 2009). 
Market design is different from some parts of theoretical mechanism design 
Market design is different from some parts of theoretical mechanism design 
in that it is not committed only to mechanisms for which all equilibria have certain 
in that it is not committed only to mechanisms for which all equilibria have certain 
properties; instead, it is more pragmatic-it would be satisfactory to implement a 
properties; instead, it is more pragmatic-it would be satisfactory to implement a 
mechanism with one desirable equilibrium as long as that equilibrium is achieved. 
mechanism with one desirable equilibrium as long as that equilibrium is achieved. 
This is why we also give advice, as in the advice to signalers on the AEA webpage. If 
This is why we also give advice, as in the advice to signalers on the AEA webpage. If </p>

<p>Peter Coles, John Cawley, Phillip Levine, Muriel Niederle, Alvin Roth, and John Siegfried 205 </p>

<p>the goal is to reach a good equilibrium, advice that accompanies the introduction 
the goal is to reach a good equilibrium, advice that accompanies the introduction 
of a new mechanism can be viewed as part of the mechanism itself. 
of a new mechanism can be viewed as part of the mechanism itself. 
Well-functioning markets do not always spring up spontaneously. As econo-
Well-functioning markets do not always spring up spontaneously. As econo-
mists, we are well-positioned to monitor and modify the market through which new 
mists, we are well-positioned to monitor and modify the market through which new 
members enter our profession. 
members enter our profession. </p>

<p>■ We thank Jenna Kensey for tireless support, Matt Chao for dedicated research assistance, 
John Rust and Raphael Auer (for information about 〈https://econjobmarket.org/ 〉 and 
〈https://www.walras.org 〉 respectively). Niederle and Roth gratefully acknowledge support 
from the National Science Foundation. </p>







<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



<p>18. Carmit Segal. 2012. Working When No One Is Watching: Motivation, Test Scores, and Economic 
Success. Management Science 58:8, 1438-1457. [Crossref] </p>

<p>19. Alvin E. Roth. 2012. Marketplace Institutions Related to the Timing of Transactions: Reply to Priest. 
Journal of Labor Economics 30:2, 479-494. [Crossref] </p>

</text></tei>