<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecin.12477" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Reputation is a commonly cited check on opportunism, but it is often unclear what 
motivates an agent to report another's behavior when it is easy for the aggrieved 
individual to move on. In a sharply focused laboratory experiment, we find that many 
cooperators pay to report a defecting partner without the possibility of pecuniary benefit 
when this has the potential to deprive the latter of future gains and to help his next 
partner. We illustrate how a social preference can explain such costly reporting, and 
also discuss evidence for a role of emotions. (JEL C91, D03, D63) </p>

<p>People face many situations marked by 
potential benefits of cooperating with others 
and accompanying dangers of being exploited 
by them. The fact that it is sometimes possible 
to choose interaction partners based on their 
reputations for cooperativeness and that one 
might accordingly have an incentive to invest in 
such a reputation, is an oft-noted factor capable 
of incentivizing cooperation. But what moti-
vates actors to transmit the required reputational 
information? 
Both sentiment-focused moral philosophers 
like Adam Smith (1761) and more recent evo-
lutionary psychologists argue that human nature, 
which the latter view as having evolved during </p>

<p> *  Funding for this project came from the Murata Science 
Foundation, with additional support from Brown University. 
We wish to thank Cheewadhanaraks Matanaporn for program-
ming of the experiment software, and Benjamin Chowdhury, 
Kathleen Hu, and especially Hui Wen Ng for assistance with 
the literature review, theoretical analysis, and data analysis. 
We also thank Yan Chen for her hospitality while the authors 
conducted the experiments at the University of Michigan, and 
we thank two anonymous reviewers, Pedro Dal Bó and other 
participants at the Brown University theory lunch, and partici-
pants at the 2015 Social Dilemmas Conference at Brown, and 
at the ESA World Meeting in Sydney, Australia in July 2015 
for helpful comments. 
Kamei: Associate Professor, Department of Economics and 
Finance, Durham University, Durham DH1 3LB, UK. 
Phone +44-0191-334-7230, Fax +44-0-191-334-5249, 
E-mail kenju.kamei@durham.ac.uk 
Putterman: Professor, Department of Economics, Brown 
University, Providence, RI 02912. Phone 508-517-
6976, Fax 401-863-1970, E-mail Louis_Putterman@ 
Brown.Edu </p>

<p>millennia of small band existence, includes innate 
dispositions towards cooperation. 1 Built-in incli-
nations that help us to overcome dilemmas of 
cooperation may include special interest in oth-
ers' cheating, emotions of anger supporting will-
ingness to expend resources to punish cheaters, 
and emotions of guilt and shame that func-
tion as self-punishments when indiscretions are 
not detected. 
Closer to our topic of information transmis-
sion is gossip, said to account for much of human 
social interaction in every known culture (Dun- bar 2004). A considerable fraction of gossip con-
sists of reports of others' misdeeds. Feinberg  et al. (2012) report evidence that "individuals 
who observe an antisocial act experience nega-
tive affect and are compelled to share information </p>

<p>1. An accessible book-length treatment is provided by 
Pinker (2003). Discussions by economists include Bowles and 
Gintis (2011). See also Gintis et al. (2005) and Wilson (2012). </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>HC: High Cost 
H-C-SP: Hypothesis on Cooperating with Inequity-
Averse Social Preferences 
H-R-SP: Hypotheses on Reporting Decisions with 
Inequity-Averse Social Preferences 
H-SPO: Hypotheses Allowing for Belief in Social 
Preferences among Others 
H-SRC: Hypotheses with Self-Interest, Rationality and 
Common Knowledge 
LC: Low Cost 
MC: Medium Cost 
NC: No Cost 
SRC: Strictly Selfish Preferences, Rationality, and 
Common Knowledge </p>

<p>158 
Economic Inquiry 
(ISSN 0095-2583) 
Vol. 56, No. 1, January 2018, 158-172 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/ecin.12477 
Online Early publication August 10, 2017 
© 2017 Western Economic Association International </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>

<p>159 </p>

<p>about the antisocial actor with a potentially vul-
nerable person," and that "individuals possessing 
more prosocial orientations are the most moti-
vated to engage in such gossip, even at a personal 
cost" (p. 1015). Such information appears to have 
a distinct power to grab attention, and psycholog-
ical normalcy includes a desire to avoid being the 
subject of negative gossip. 2  Being the subject of negative reports may 
also have direct material consequences, if oth-
ers hesitate to interact with individuals known for 
past reneging or defection. In modern economies, 
individuals can choose where to shop, which 
plumber to hire, and so forth. But the same mobil-
ity that puts potential cooperation partners in 
competition with each other threatens the reputa-
tional mechanism if a cost is entailed in spreading 
the word about an interaction partner's defection. 
If one has already decided to leave the untrust-
worthy partner behind and there is no incentive 
to encourage her to change, how will others learn 
whom to avoid? If all victims care only about 
own material payoffs, if they cannot profitably 
exchange the information, and if there is any cost 
associated with conveying it, then there will be no 
such reporting. 3 However, there may be nonmate-
rial motivations for the costly reporting of cheat-
ing or opportunistic behavior. First, engaging in 
negative gossip may be a direct source of satis-
faction, paralleling reports that pleasure centers 
in the brain are activated when experimental sub-
jects punish selfish counterparts in a trust game 
(de Quervain et al. 2004). Second, tipping others 
off not to naively cooperate with the miscreant 
may bring satisfaction not for the act itself but 
thanks to anticipation of the punishment that this 
may visit on that actor. The large literature show-
ing cooperative subjects' willingness to spend 
money to reduce free riders' earnings in volun-
tary contribution experiments (Chaudhuri 2011;  Falk et al. 2005; Gächter and Herrmann 2009)  suggests that such motives are widespread, and 
raises the possibility that punitive motives might 
also motivate reporting. Third, conceivably the 
victim feels empathy or obligation towards others </p>

<p>2. As Adam Smith (1761) wrote: "Man natu-
rally … dreads, not only blame, but blame-worthiness." 
3. Note that in network theory (see, e.g., Jackson and  Zenou 2014), the standard assumption is that while creation 
of links may itself be costly, information travels costlessly 
among those actors who are linked together, and that infor-
mation is passed along by default whenever two agents are 
linked and the informed agent is indifferent to having trans-
mission occur. We could locate no discussion of behavioral or 
social preference explanations of willingness to incur costs to 
transmit information, in this literature. </p>

<p>who are in danger of being victimized, and may 
accordingly try to warn them. 
Given the importance of reputational mech-
anisms to solving dilemmas of cooperation and 
the rapid growth of behavioral economics and 
social preference research using the techniques 
of experimental economics, one might expect the 
costly reporting of partners' behaviors to be the 
focus of numerous studies. Rather than focus-
ing on the decision to engage in costly report-
ing, however, the most closely related papers 
have focused on the design of reputation mecha-
nisms or the effects of information transmission. 
We address this gap by conducting an exper-
iment that investigates both the willingness to 
pay to report an interaction partner's uncooper-
ativeness, and subjects' beliefs about how com-
mon that willingness is. Our experimental design, 
which builds on familiar prisoners' dilemma 
stage games, allows us to isolate the willingness 
to engage in reporting when a personal monetary 
payoff is absent, so that only desires to punish 
the individual, to protect her future interaction 
partner, or to engage in information sharing for 
its own sake (gossip) are potential motives for 
reporting. We demonstrate that reporting is sig-
nificantly less common when it is costly than 
when free, but that costly reporting does occur 
often. We show cooperator-defector reporting to 
be far more common than cooperator-cooperator, 
defector-cooperator, or defector-defector report-
ing. Indeed, a majority of cooperators meeting 
defectors report them despite its cost and lack of 
personal benefit, in our study. We identify condi-
tions under which such reporting, and its relative 
frequency across behavior pairings, is consistent 
with an illustrative model of social preferences, 
the inequity aversion model of Fehr and Schmidt  (1999). 
One condition which must be satisfied to 
make reporting attractive to an inequity averse 
agent, in our setting, is belief that a sufficient 
share of the population chooses cooperation. 
Although reporting at positive cost is never ratio-
nal for strictly selfish agents in our experiment, 
there exist configurations of beliefs such that the 
same does not apply to cooperating. We con-
duct an incentivized elicitation of beliefs about 
others' cooperation and reporting, and with the 
resulting data we calculate which subjects could 
be rationally choosing or rejecting cooperation 
out of simple payoff maximization, and which 
choose cooperation (or defection) in error or due 
to a social preference or emotion. Almost all 
observed decisions to defect in the experiment </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>are explicable by payoff maximization under own 
beliefs regarding others' cooperation and report-
ing probabilities. Rational maximization of own 
payoff also explains many choices to cooperate, 
but a substantial number of cooperation choices 
require alternative explanation. In addition to 
social preference analysis, we keep in mind that 
our data on reporting, especially, are compatible 
with more psychological explanations, and we 
bring to bear evidence on the role of emotions in 
a final portion of our discussion. 
The rest of the article is organized as fol-
lows: Section II briefly summarizes related lit-
erature; Section III describes our experimental 
design; Section IV provides the theoretical pre-
dictions and hypotheses under both monetary 
payoff maximization and our illustrative social 
preference theory; Section V reports results; and 
Section VI concludes. </p>

<p>II. LITERATURE </p>

<p>Although many decisions to cooperate are 
explicable by rational and self-interested agents' 
believing that others' actions may be nonstandard 
(Kreps et al. 1982), decisions to engage in costly 
reporting are never compatible with material self-
interest in our set-up. Social preferences and 
emotions, as discussed for instance by Camerer  and Loewenstein (2003) and Sobel (2005), may 
be required to explain such reporting, if present. 
The literature on the experimental study of 
costly punishment, beginning with rejections in 
ultimatum game experiments (Camerer 2003;  Camerer and Thaler 1995) and continuing into 
work on public goods games with punishment 
opportunities (Fehr and Gächter 2000), includes 
numerous attempts to explain actions without 
material benefit to the actor. Experiments find that 
many subjects incur a cost to punish when there 
can be no material benefit, and that the threat of 
punishment can reduce or eliminate incentives to 
free-ride. 4 One way to understand costly punish-
ment in such games is to see punishers as hav-
ing an aversion to others free-riding or defecting 
while they themselves cooperate. For such indi-
viduals, imposing an earnings reduction on free 
riders at a monetary cost to themselves delivers </p>

<p>4. For example, Ertan et al. (2009), find that ex post, indi-
vidual subjects earn more the more they contribute to the 
public good when opportunities to engage in costly punish-
ment are available. Reviews of the literature on punishment in 
voluntary contribution experiments include Gächter and Her- rmann (2009) and Chaudhuri (2011).   a utility gain that offsets their lowered money 
earnings. While such punishing can be thought of 
as resulting from a psychological trait of negative 
reciprocity (Bowles and Gintis 2004; Hoffman,  McCabe, and Smith 1998) perhaps linked to an 
emotional state of anger, it might also be ratio-
nalized or rendered mathematically tractable by 
a simpler framework of inequity aversion (Fehr  and Schmidt 1999). 
From a structural standpoint, costly reporting 
and costly punishing represent different stages 
in a possible sequence of actions. To study 
punishment conditioned on contributions, Fehr  and Gächter (2000) provided their subjects with 
accurate, cost free information on the contribu-
tions of individual team members, but this left 
unaddressed the question of how such informa-
tion is obtained and shared in practice. Costly 
reporting or monitoring is a needed precursor 
to costly punishment except where effort-free 
mutual observability is an automatic by-product 
of working together. The motives underlying 
reporting need not be identical to those for 
punishment, so the decision deserves study in its 
own right. 
Several scholars have researched costly 
reporting in the form of online product reviews 
(Dellarocas 2003). Resnick and Zeckhauser  (2002) look at the relationship between eBay 
reviews and sales, as well as the prevalence 
of and motivation behind reviewing. They find 
reviewing to be frequent and suggest that the 
giving of feedback despite the absence of pri-
vate material gain might be understood as the 
carrying out of a "quasi-civic duty" or as part 
of a "high courtesy equilibrium." Gregg and  Scott (2006) find that eBay reviews are a major 
deterrent to fraud, helping to reduce asymme-
try of information between buyers and sellers. 
Wang (2010) addresses the motivations behind 
leaving a review, specifically with respect to 
Yelp, a for-profit business review site. He finds 
strong evidence that social image and reviewer 
productivity are correlated. Bolton, Greiner, and 
Ockenfels (2013) study structural issues related 
to online reviews, conducting an experiment 
that provides evidence that negative reviews in 
environments like eBay can be deterred by the 
fear of retaliation. 
But while the boom in e-commerce provides 
much of the impetus for recent studies of reputa-
tion formation, traditional economic interactions 
not amenable to the same fixes also justify 
attention to costly reporting. As Abraham et al.  (2016) write, "there now exists a huge literature </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>that aims at evaluating and designing reputation 
mechanisms for internet trading" but still "we 
know surprisingly little about the determinants 
which allow for the formation of reputation in 
economic systems." Like those authors, our main 
interest is in "traditional economic transactions, 
i.e., in environments where no mechanisms exist 
that make reputational information publicly 
available." 
Abraham et al. is one of a few recent papers, 
including also Gërxhani, Brandts, and Schram  (2013) and Fehr and Sutter (2016), in which 
costly reporting without clear private bene-
fit plays a part in an experiment. Gërxhani,  Brandts, and Schram (2013) study transmission 
of information about employee trustworthiness 
among employers, in one treatment making 
such transmissions anonymous so that direct 
reciprocity is ruled out as an incentive. However, 
their players interact in the same condition for 
20 periods, which can give rise to incentives 
for "reputation building." 5 Also, their report-
ing cost is small, partly a by-product of their 
experiment's multiperiod structure, and they 
do not focus on motivations to report, includ-
ing possibly asymmetric motivations to report 
"bad actors." Abraham et al. (2016) compare 
dyadic private information transmission at both 
zero and positive cost within small popula-
tions playing a series of 36 trust games. The 
repeated setting here too contributes to the cost 
of any single reporting action being quite small, 
and it creates incentives to build cooperation 
in reporting, although reporting is much less 
common in their experiment when costly than 
when free. Our paper is the first of which we 
are aware that studies costly reporting in a con-
trolled setting where the reporting cost can be 
appreciable and private material gain is fully 
ruled out. 6 </p>

<p>5. If players believe it to be widely believed that some 
people are "conditionally cooperative," then they may find 
it privately beneficial to invest in promoting such beliefs by 
behaving cooperatively, since this may support a "cooperative 
culture" within the group until "end game" behaviors set in. 
See, for example, Palfrey and Prisbrey (1997), Healy (2007), 
and Kamei and Putterman (2016). 
6. Another study of reporting that effectively rules out 
private material gain from reporting is Fehr and Sutter (2016). 
Like us, they explicitly relate their findings to the anthropo-
logically observed human propensity to gossip. Rather than 
fix the cost, they study willingness to pay to pass on a report, 
and find considerable willingness to spend amounts averaging 
about 0.3 Euro, or about 18% of what the third party earns in a 
period if not sending a message. But unlike in our experiment 
their costly reporters are third parties rather than parties to the 
exchanges. Whereas the third party feature is what accounts </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 
Payoff Matrix </p>

<p>Player 2 </p>

<p>Player 1 </p>

<p>X 
Y </p>

<p>X 
$10, $10 
$4, $11 </p>

<p>Y 
$11, $4 
$5, $5 </p>

<p>III. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN </p>

<p>Our experiment consists of four main treat-
ments with opportunities to report a counterpart's 
decision, in three of which reporting is costly. (An 
additional costly reporting treatment conducted 
by strategy method is discussed later.) In each 
treatment, subjects play two one-shot prisoners' 
dilemma games, each with different, anonymous, 
randomly selected participants. The payoff struc-
tures of the first and second games are identical 
and of equal money value to end-of-session earn-
ings. The payoff table of each round in U.S. dol-
lars is summarized in Figure 1. 7  A key feature of our design is that subjects 
decide whether to play the cooperate (denoted X) 
or the defect (denoted Y) option in both games 
at the outset. Thus, in the instructions read by 
the participants, we write XX (YY) to repre-
sent the cooperate (defect) option, duplicating the 
letter choice to indicate its play in two games. 
In what follows (but not in the subject instruc-
tions, which avoid such terms) we refer to a 
subject who chooses XX (YY) as a cooperator 
(defector), or occasionally XX-(YY-) chooser. 
Committing subjects at the outset to a single 
choice captures the notion that people have ten-
dencies that they carry from interaction to inter-
action. Adoption of this feature simplifies both 
analysis and reporting decisions, since it means </p>

<p>for absence of material benefit to the reporter, in Fehr and Sut-
ter, it is limited repetition and perfect stranger matching that 
has this effect in our design. 
7. Payoffs were quoted in dollars; no "lab currency" was 
used. While predictions for the PD game are the same over a 
wide range of payoff configurations, the degree of "tempta-
tion" to defect, "fear" of being defected on, and the potential 
to gain from mutual cooperation relative to mutual defection, 
are impacted by the specific payoff structure, so that con-
clusions from an experiment with one payoff configuration 
may not extend, behaviorally, to alternative payoffs. See, for 
instance, Ahn et al. (2001) and Charness et al. (2016). We 
made both the "temptation" and the "fear" small because we 
anticipated that predictions about the share of cooperators, 
and actual inclinations to cooperate, would thus be larger, in 
turn increasing reporting of defectors. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>that reporting, for example, a defector, can be 
a reliable warning about the kind of agent the 
next partner will encounter. Of course, we need to 
take into consideration that imposition of this rule 
affects players' strategic calculations. Accord-
ingly, precommitment for two rounds of play 
should not be misconstrued as being a mech-
anism to force type revelation in the sense of 
the theoretical literature. Indeed, we will show 
shortly that under some beliefs, it becomes ratio-
nal for a strictly self-interested agent to select 
XX (cooperate). 
After being randomly matched with a coun-
terpart, selecting between the two options, and 
being informed of the outcome of their first round 
interaction, each player in the reporting treat-
ments decides whether to report the decision of 
her first counterpart. If a player is reported, then 
the second-period counterpart of the reported 
player is told what that player chose in the first 
round 8 and is given the option to change his ini-
tial choice of X or Y taking into account the 
report he received-this being the sole excep-
tion to the rule that an initial choice is binding 
for two rounds of play. Subjects know that they 
will certainly not play the game a second time 
with the same counterpart, so reporting in the 
hope that one might oneself be the beneficiary 
of the information is ruled out. The counterpart 
will also be told whether she was reported on by 
her initial partner, which determines whether the 
player whose initial choice was reported to her is 
in a position to select a new action. 9 For example, 
consider two players, A and B. Suppose that both 
A and B are paired with other randomly assigned 
partners (not each other) in the first game. Sup-
pose also that A chooses XX (cooperate) and B 
chooses YY (defect). Now imagine that B's first 
round partner decides to report her (B's) deci-
sion to B's second interaction partner, namely A. 
Since B was reported, A has a chance to change 
his initial choice from X to Y so as to avoid 
being exploited by B. A is also free to stick to the 
choice of X. Suppose, finally, that A (the coop-
erator) is not reported by his initial partner. A 
is thus informed that B has no opportunity to </p>

<p>8. That is, the computer delivers a truthful report. The 
potential issues of deciding whether to report truthfully and 
whether to believe a report that has been received are thus 
eliminated as concerns. We discuss the impact of this simpli-
fying element in the conclusion. 
9. To preserve maximum anonymity among the subjects 
in the experiment, those who had no opportunity to change 
their own choice were asked to answer a trivia question 
bearing no relation to the experiment, to keep number of 
computer clicks consistent across all those in the lab. </p>

<p>change her choice, so A knows with certainty that 
B is playing Y in his interaction with her. In this 
example, A knows that switching to Y will pro-
tect him with certainty and that the choice would 
carry no danger of foregoing a mutual coopera-
tion payoff. 
As another example, consider a cooperator 
(XX-chooser) C who learns that her second coun-
terpart D had selected XX and has no opportunity 
to change his decision (C's initial counterpart did 
not report C's choice). C may wish to switch to 
Y to exploit D, but might decide to stick with 
X in order to avoid feeling guilty, experiencing 
disutility from advantageous inequality, and so 
on. In the otherwise similar situation in which D 
can change his choice, C would have that infor-
mation and would need to factor in her belief 
about the likelihood of D changing to Y (which 
may in turn be influenced by D's belief about 
the likelihood of C switching). 10 To check sen-
sitivity of reporting to its cost, we vary it across 
treatments. A reporting cost of $1, $0.50, $0.05, 
and $0 is present in the high-cost (HC), medium-
cost (MC), low-cost (LC), and no-cost (NC) treat-
ments, respectively. 11 
Subjects are also asked, after their own choice 
of XX or YY, for their beliefs about the per-
centage of their peers choosing XX, and-after 
their reporting decisions-for their beliefs about 
the percentages of defectors and of coopera-
tors who will be reported. The elicited beliefs 
extend our ability to explore possible motiva-
tions behind subjects' decisions. So as not to 
raise its salience too much, we do not tell sub-
jects about the presence of the belief elicita-
tion tasks before they make the corresponding </p>

<p>10. While our design is one of finite repetition, we view 
the question addressed-that of lack of monetary incentive 
to engage in costly reporting-as relevant also to a world of 
indefinitely repeated interactions, since agents in such envi-
ronments may also periodically need to seek new interaction 
partners and may avoid dealing again with an individual found 
to be opportunistic, but have no selfish material motive for 
incurring a cost to convey the information to others, espe-
cially when interacting in a population so large that inducing 
reciprocal reporting from others is not a plausible motive. 
Having only two interactions makes practical relatively large 
stakes in the lab for each interaction, while the fact that the 
report affects only one future interaction makes the motiva-
tional problem more challenging by limiting the punishment 
that reporting can inflict. 
11. We suspected that a cost of $1 would suffice to deter 
many from reporting in the context of an experiment with 
expected total earnings in the neighborhood of $15 to $25, 
thought we might see more reporting with that cost halved, 
and we included the much lower cost $0.05 in case substantial 
reporting were forthcoming only at a more trivial cost. We 
included zero cost to observe the inclination to report when 
cost is not a factor. </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>choices. Subjects are asked for their expectations 
regarding behaviors of other participants only 
(themselves not included), to avoid hedging. Elic-
iting beliefs is incentivized by offering a $1 bonus 
payment for guesses that are within 5 percentage 
points of the actual percentage. At the end of their 
session, subjects are also asked about emotions 
potentially affecting their reporting decisions: (1) 
their level of anger toward their initial partners 
and (2) their feelings of obligation to help the 
third party in the second round via reporting. </p>

<p>IV. THEORETICAL PREDICTIONS WITHOUT 
AND WITH SOCIAL PREFERENCES </p>

<p>Although our main focus is on costly report-
ing, we discuss here predictions of subject 
decisions with regard to both the cooperating 
and reporting decision, since each may be con-
ditioned by beliefs about the other. We begin 
with the extreme assumption of strictly selfish 
preferences, rationality, and common knowl-
edge (SRC), then relax the common knowledge 
assumption to allow for beliefs that some may be 
otherwise motivated, and finally relax the selfish 
preference assumption to allow that the decision-
maker herself may have a social preference 
capable of explaining actual costly reporting 
and some decisions to cooperate contrary to 
material self-interest. We leave consideration of 
emotional factors to be discussed when we view 
the experimental results. </p>

<p>A. Common Knowledge of Rationality and 
Self-Interest </p>

<p>The standard theory predictions in the exper-
iment (with SRC) are straightforward. In the 
HC, MC, and LC treatments, it is never payoff-
enhancing to report, since reporting is costly 
and players are never matched with the same 
partner twice. Even if there were to be report-
ing, which subjects could randomly choose to 
do in the NC treatment, YY would remain the 
predicted first choice and Y the free second 
choice of those receiving reports, thus having 
no impact on how the PD games themselves 
are played. </p>

<p>HYPOTHESES 
WITH 
SELF-INTEREST, 
RATIONALITY AND COMMON KNOWLEDGE 
(H-SRC) </p>

<p>In the HC, MC, and LC treatments, each subject 
chooses not to pay to report choices of her first inter-
action partner, while reporting occurs randomly in the </p>

<p>NC treatment. Subjects in all treatments choose YY 
(defect). A subject having the opportunity to make a 
free second choice (which, by the above, occurs only 
in the NC treatment) always selects Y. </p>

<p>B. Dropping Common Knowledge </p>

<p>Even if a subject is strictly self-interested and 
rational, belief that others might behave pro-
socially and/or that others believe such types 
exist can lead to a different choice over XX ver-
sus YY. Let a i be the fraction of subjects that i 
believes will cooperate (select XX), b i the frac-
tion she believes will report a cooperating coun-
terpart, and c i the fraction she believes will report 
a defecting one (0 ≤ a i , b i , c i ≤ 1). We solve for 
the conditions under which i selects XX or YY 
under assumptions representing two ends of a 
continuum of beliefs i might have about free 
second game choices; we call the two beliefs 
"pessimistic" and "optimistic," respectively. If 
pessimistic, i assumes that an individual free to 
revise her second choice always selects Y, in 
line with self-interest, whereas if optimistic, i 
assumes that cooperatively-oriented participants 
(XX-choosers) will stick with X given an oppor-
tunity to make a fresh choice, provided that they 
are informed that they are meeting another sub-
ject who chose XX. 12  As shown in Section A.1 in Appendix S1, 
Supporting Information, under the pessimistic 
second game belief, we obtain: </p>

<p>selfish player i cooperates (defects) if 
(1) </p>

<p>5a i 
( 
c i − b i 
) 
+ c i &gt; 2 (≤ 2) . </p>

<p>By contrast, under the optimistic second game 
belief, as shown in Section A.2 in Appendix S1, 
we obtain: </p>

<p>selfish player i cooperates (defects) if 
(1 ′ ) </p>

<p>5a i c i + a i b i + c i &gt; 2 (≤ 2) . </p>

<p>A higher fraction of subjects chooses to 
cooperate based on criterion (1 ′ ) compared with 
criterion (1). </p>

<p>12. Clearly the "optimistic" assumption is strong in 
that it eschews distinctions based on whether the XX-
chooser being met with can also change her choice. Its 
optimism is nonetheless bounded in that YY-choosers free 
to revise their second choice are still assumed always to 
stick to Y. Our data show that some (but not all) cooper-
ators stick to cooperation when having the report of meet-
ing a cooperator, but no defector switches to cooperation in 
this situation. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>HYPOTHESES ALLOWING FOR BELIEF IN 
SOCIAL PREFERENCES AMONG OTHERS 
(H-SPO) </p>

<p>If i is a material payoff maximizer, but believes that 
others might cooperate and pay to report (coopera- tors, defectors) with probabilities a i , b i , and c i ≥ 0, 
then i will never pay to report her first interaction part-
ner, and will randomly report or not report if reporting 
is cost free. Subject i will choose cooperation (defec-
tion) if 5a i (c i − b i ) + c i &gt; 2 (≤2), assuming that i has 
"pessimistic" beliefs about cooperators' free second 
choices, and will choose cooperation (defection) if 
5a i c i + a i b i + c i &gt; 2 (≤2), assuming that i has "opti-
mistic" beliefs about those choices. 13 </p>

<p>C. Social Preferences and Decisions to Report </p>

<p>Unlike cooperating, costly reporting can never 
be optimal for an agent aiming to maximize own 
monetary payoff. Explaining its occurrence thus 
requires error, emotion, or nontraditional ele-
ments in the utility function. We illustrate how 
the latter can work if the potential reporter i has 
the inequity-averse preferences proposed by Fehr  and Schmidt (1999): </p>

<p>u i 
( 
π i |π j 
) 
= π i − α i · max 
{ 
π j − π i , 0 
} 
(2) </p>

<p>− β i · max 
{ 
π i − π j , 0 
} 
, </p>

<p>where α i ≥ β i ≥ 0, meaning that aversion to 
inequality that is unfavorable to the decision-
maker (reflected in weight α i ) is at least as strong 
as that to favorable inequality (reflected in weight 
β i ), and that the decision-maker never values the 
latter ("aheadness") for its own sake (β i takes 
no negative values). Also assume that β i &lt; 1. 
There are four possible situations under which 
reporting might occur: </p>

<p>Case 1: subject i cooperates and learns that 
her counterpart has also cooperated. 
Case 2: subject i cooperates and learns that 
her counterpart has defected. 
Case 3: subject i defects and learns that her 
counterpart has cooperated. 
Case 4: subject i defects and learns that her 
counterpart has also defected. </p>

<p>13. Note that by writing conditions (1) and (1 ′ ) as shown, 
we assume that subjects whose beliefs render them rationally 
indifferent between XX and YY will select the latter, if 
strictly self-interested. This means that when analyzing our 
experiment results in Section V, we place the few cases 
in which (1) or (1 ′ ) hold with exact equality in the set of 
observations for which an observed choice of XX requires a 
social preference explanation. </p>

<p>For simplicity, we assume that the only other 
individual, j, whose payoff π j affects u i if α i (and 
perhaps β i ) &gt; 0, is the first interaction partner 
of decision-maker i, with respect to whom i's 
decision to engage in reporting is made. 14 Then 
it can be shown (details are in Section A.4 in 
Appendix S1) that costly reporting will occur: </p>

<p>in Case 1 if 6a i &gt; ρ, (α + β) b i -β &gt; 0 and 
(3a) 
( 
6a i -ρ 
) 
&gt; ρ∕ 
[ 
(α + β) b i -β 
] </p>

<p>(3b) 
in Case 2 if 
( 
6a i -ρ 
) 
&gt; ρ∕α </p>

<p>in Case 4 if 6a i &gt; ρ, (α + β) c i -β &gt; 0 and 
(3c) 
( 
6a i -ρ 
) 
&gt; ρ∕ 
[ 
(α + β) c i -β 
] </p>

<p>where ρ is the reporting cost. 15 The analysis in 
Supporting Information shows that the conditions 
for Cases 2 and 4 hold regardless of whether i 
applies the pessimistic or the optimistic assump-
tion about free second choices, whereas the con-
dition for Case 1 applies only when i makes the 
pessimistic assumption; if she makes the opti-
mistic assumption instead, i will never pay to 
report. As for Case 3, the analysis indicates that 
a defector i will never report a cooperating coun-
terpart if β i &lt; 1, as assumed above. Even if some 
individuals have unusually high β values, the 
individuals in question would be unlikely to be 
defectors (see Section IV.D), so costly report-
ing of cooperators by defectors will rarely if 
ever occur. 
Condition (3b) indicates that the more averse 
to disadvantageous inequality is the cooperator 
(the higher her α i ), the more others she believes 
to have chosen to cooperate (the higher her a i ), 
and the lower is the reporting cost ρ, the more 
likely she is to report a defector. Aversion to 
advantageous inequality, β, plays no role in this 
decision. In addition, the condition implies that 
all inequity-averse cooperators report defectors at 
zero cost (in the NC treatment), as long as a i &gt; 0. </p>

<p>14. i's potential concern for j's next partner, whom i may 
wish to warn or at least inform of j's type, is a plausible 
additional concern that we discuss later. The simple Fehr-
Schmidt model also abstracts from explicit considerations 
of reciprocity (Rabin 1993; Charness and Rabin 2002) and 
concern for others' intentions (Cox et al. 2007; Dufwenberg  and Kirchsteiger 2004; Falk and Fischbacher 2006) as such. 
Finally, unlike Saito (2013), we assume that the decision-
maker cares only about ex ante expected differences (see also 
Brock et al. 2013 and Kamei 2016). 
15. i is indifferent between reporting and not reporting if 
the right hand inequality in each line holds instead with the 
equals operator. i (subscripts on alpha and beta) omitted in 
(3) to conserve space. </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>These conditions suggest that if distributions 
of types (that is, of α and β values) are not 
different in each case, then the threshold belief 
a i required for costly reporting is lowest for 
Case 2. 16 In conditions (3a) and (3c), there is 
also the further implication that costly report-
ing is conditional on the belief that others do it 
(a cooperator [defector] is more likely to report 
another cooperator [defector] if she has a high 
belief b i [c i ]). As for relative frequency of report-
ing in Cases 1 and 4, the two conditions show 
reporting to be more likely in Case 4 than Case 1 
if c i &gt; b i , an intuitively appealing idea that turns 
out to be strongly supported by our experimen-
tal data. Adding to this the finding that reporting 
is not predicted for any individual making the 
optimistic assumption about free second choices, 
we arrive at the implication that, assuming suf-
ficient variation of belief a i not systematically 
linked to preference type, costly reporting should 
be most common in the case of cooperators meet-
ing defectors (Case 2), with the cases of defectors 
meeting defectors (Case 4) and cooperators meet-
ing cooperators (Case 1) following in that order. </p>

<p>HYPOTHESES 
ON 
REPORTING 
DECI-
SIONS WITH INEQUITY-AVERSE SOCIAL 
PREFERENCES (H-R-SP) </p>

<p>(i) Costly reporting due to inequity averse preferences 
is most likely in the case of a cooperator meeting a 
defector, followed by the case of a defector meeting a 
defector, with reporting of cooperators by cooperators 
still less common and that of cooperators by defectors 
rarely if ever occurring; (ii) defectors (cooperators) 
are more likely to report their defector (cooperator) 
counterpart the greater the share of others they believe 
report (the greater is their belief c i [b i ]); (iii) the 
higher is belief a i , and the lower is reporting cost ρ, 
the larger the share of individuals who will engage in 
costly reporting. </p>

<p>D. Social Preferences, Beliefs, and Decisions to 
Cooperate </p>

<p>Although decisions to cooperate can occur 
without a social preference, as shown above, hav-
ing a social preference may cause an agent for 
whom neither (1) nor (1 ′ ) holds to nonetheless 
select X (XX). Using again inequity-averse utility 
function (2) for purposes of illustration, assuming 
beliefs a i , b i , and c i , and adopting in turn the pes-
simistic and optimistic beliefs about free second 
choices, we work out conditions for cooperation </p>

<p>16. Notice that α − [(α + β)b i − β] = (α + β)(1 − b i ) ≥ 0. 
α − [(α + β)c i − β] = (α + β)(1 − c i ) ≥ 0. </p>

<p>in Section A.3 in Appendix S1, and simply sum-
marize here the conclusion: </p>

<p>HYPOTHESIS ON COOPERATING WITH 
INEQUITY-AVERSE SOCIAL PREFERENCES 
(H-C-SP) </p>

<p>A subject i who has inequity-averse preferences will be 
more likely to choose XX the more others she expects 
to cooperate (the higher her belief a i ), the more averse 
to advantageous inequality she is (higher β i ), and 
the less averse to disadvantageous inequality she is 
(lower α i ). </p>

<p>V. RESULTS AND ANALYSIS </p>

<p>A. Overview of the Experiment </p>

<p>A total of 172 students (152 in the four 
main reporting treatments and 20 in the strat-
egy method treatment) participated in ten experi-
ment sessions in 2013 and 2014 at the University 
of Michigan. 17 Among them, 58.7% of subjects 
(101) were female. No subject participated in 
more than one session, and the sessions lasted 
about an hour on average, about half of this 
time being spent on reading of instructions and 
answering comprehension questions. The exper-
iment was programmed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">z-tree</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Fischbacher</rs>  2007). All instructions (for the example of the 
LC treatment, see Supporting Information) were 
neutrally framed, avoiding terms such as "cooper-
ate," "trust," and so on. Subjects had to answer a 
number of control questions (see the instructions) 
to confirm their understanding of the experiment. 
Communication between subjects was not per-
mitted. Average earnings were $20.84, including 
a $5 participation fee, with a standard deviation 
of $4.16. 
Figure 2 summarizes key subject behaviors 
and beliefs, with panels (A) (at left), (B) (upper 
right), and (C) lower right displaying cooper-
ation decisions, decisions to report defectors, 
and decisions to report cooperators, respectively. 
We begin with our main focus, costly reporting. 
A glance at panel (B) makes clear that there 
was much costly reporting, but overwhelm-
ingly reporting of defectors by cooperators, 
as predicted. Focusing on the left panel of </p>

<p>17. Sessions were conducted by Kamei while he was 
Assistant Professor at Bowling Green State University. All 
subjects were recruited from the University of Michigan 
experimental lab's subject pool using solicitation messages 
via <rs type="software">ORSEE</rs> (Online Recruitment System for Economic 
Experiments). We aimed to recruit 20 participants to each ses-
sion, but actual numbers varied somewhat due to differing 
show-up rates, averaging 17.2. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 
Choices of XX or YY, Reporting Decisions, and Beliefs: (A) % of Choosing XX, (B) % of Reporting 
YY, and (C) % of Reporting XX </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>10.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>30.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>50.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>70.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>90.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>Actual % reporting YY </p>

<p>beliefs of XX'ers who reported YY </p>

<p>beliefs of XX'ers who didn't report YY </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>10.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>30.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>50.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>70.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>90.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>Actual % reporting XX </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>10.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>30.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>50.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>70.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>90.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>Actual % reporting YY </p>

<p>XX-choosers' belief </p>

<p>YY-choosers' belief </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>10.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>30.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>50.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>70.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>90.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>Actual % 
reporting XX </p>

<p>XX-choosers' 
belief </p>

<p>YY-choosers' 
belief </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>10.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>30.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>50.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>70.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>90.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>HC 
MC 
LC 
three costly 
reporting 
treatments </p>

<p>NC </p>

<p>Actual % XX-choosers </p>

<p>XX-ers' belief of % choosing XX </p>

<p>YY-ers' belief of % choosing XX </p>

<p>% of choosing XX </p>

<p>% of reporting XX </p>

<p>% of reporting YY </p>

<p>XX reports YY 
YY reports YY </p>

<p>XX reports XX 
YY reports XX </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>Figure 2B, we see that some 45%-65% of 
cooperators who encountered a defector chose to 
report when costly, and that reporting occurred 
considerably more often (almost 90% report) at 
cost zero (NC treatment) than at positive costs 
(an overall average of 58.6% report in LC, MC, 
and HC). The remainder of this panel and the 
panel below it, in Figure 2C, show that there is 
also some, but considerably less, costly reporting 
of cooperators by cooperators and of defectors by 
defectors, and no costly reporting of cooperators 
by defectors. Overall, an average of 8.0% of 
subjects in the cooperator-cooperator, defector-
cooperator, and defector-defector situations 
choose to report. </p>

<p>RESULT 1. (a) Costly reporting of defectors by 
cooperators is common (almost 59% report); (b) 
costly reporting in other cases is significantly less 
common (overall, 8%); (c) there is significantly 
less reporting at a positive than at a zero cost. 
These results are consistent with H-R-SP. </p>

<p>Turning to cooperation decisions and expecta-
tions, Figure 2A shows that regardless of the pres-
ence of reporting costs and their size if present, 
around 50%-60% of the subjects choose XX in 
each of the main treatments. 18 The diamonds and 
triangles in the same panel indicate that cooper-
ators' average expectation regarding the fraction 
of others who would choose cooperation was sig-
nificantly higher (around 70%) than that of defec-
tors (around 40%). The difference is highly sig-
nificant (p &lt; .001, see Table B.4 in Appendix S2). 
With respect to reporting, the right side of panel 
(B) shows that the average cooperator believed 
more defectors would be reported than did the 
average defector, a difference significant for LC 
subjects and in all costly reporting treatments 
pooled (p &lt; .001, see Table B.4 in Appendix S2). 
The displayed frequencies of cooperation and 
reporting are clearly inconsistent with H-SRC, 
which, based on the assumption of rational self-
ish individuals with common knowledge, pre-
dicts neither costly reporting nor cooperation. 19 </p>

<p>18. The fractions of cooperators are not significantly 
different between any two treatments, according to two-sided, 
two-sample tests of proportions. See panel (C) of Table B.1 in 
Appendix S2. 
19. We performed binomial probability tests for the con-
servative null hypothesis that the probability of choosing XX 
equals 5%, assuming that errors occur with a probability of 
5%. This hypothesis was rejected in each treatment. We also 
performed binomial probability tests for the conservative null 
hypothesis that the probability that cooperators report the ini-
tial choices of their defecting partners equals 5%, assuming </p>

<p>We now discuss in more detail the reporting deci-
sions, considering in Section V.B their consis-
tency with the illustrative social preference model 
discussed above, and discussing evidence for a 
role of emotions in Section V.C. </p>

<p>B. Predicting Reporting Decisions with 
Inequity-Averse Preferences </p>

<p>In the three treatments in which reporting 
is costly, 58.6% of cooperators meeting defec-
tors, 16.6% of defectors meeting defectors, 8.8% 
of cooperators meeting cooperators, and 0% of 
defectors meeting cooperators, pay the cost to 
report their counterpart, an ordering of frequen-
cies exactly matching part (i) of H-R-SP. 20 We 
use again the Fehr-Schmidt model to illustrate the 
ease or difficulty of predicting reporting choices 
with a model of social preference. Although we 
can't identify individual utility function parame-
ters in order to predict which subjects will report 
their counterparts, as an exercise we estimate 
the proportion who would be expected to report 
based on conditions (3a), (3b), and (3c), and self-
reported beliefs a i , b i , and c i if we assume that 
each subject has the same likelihood of belong-
ing to each of the four preference types identified 
and assigned estimated population proportions 
by Fehr and Schmidt, in precisely those pro-
portions. 21 These calculations imply that about 
68.9% of the cooperators who encountered defec-
tors, 13.5% of the cooperators who encountered 
cooperators, and 14.2% of the defectors who 
encountered defectors would engage in reporting 
at the costs obtaining in their treatments given 
their beliefs and the prevalence of each type. 
These predicted shares are rather similar to the 
shares actually reporting, the similar differences 
between the high share for Case 2 reporting and 
the low shares for Cases 1 and 4, in estimate and 
reality, being especially remarkable. 
We can also estimate multivariate regressions 
to check for patterns consistent with the reporting </p>

<p>that errors occur with a probability of 5%. This hypothe-
sis was also rejected in each treatment. See Table B.2 in 
Appendix S2. 
20. The percentage of defectors being reported by coop-
erators is significantly larger than the percentage being 
reported in the other action pairings according to two-sample 
z-tests of proportions using pooled data of the three costly 
reporting treatments (see panel B.2 of Table B.1 in Appendix 
S2). 
21. Specifically, Fehr and Schmidt estimate that about 
30% of individuals have α = β = 0, about 30% have α = .5, 
β = .25, 30% have α = 1, β = .6, and 10% have α = 4, β = .6. 
See also Table 1 in Fehr and Schmidt (2010). </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>conditions of inequalities (3a)-(3c). In Table B.8 
in Appendix S2, we show estimates of simple 
linear regressions to predict reporting, where the 
independent variables are the values of the three 
beliefs and two treatment dummies to control 
for reporting cost. The regressions for Cases 1 
and 4 show partial consistency with conditions 
(3a) and (3c) in that the belief variables b i and 
c i obtain positive and significant coefficients in 
their respective estimates. These coefficients sug-
gest a sort of "conditional cooperativeness" with 
respect to reporting: the higher the fraction of 
others a subject believes report a player who 
behaves like her counterpart (one who cooper-
ates, in Case 1, one who defects, in Case 4), the 
more likely that the subject herself pays to report. 
The estimate for Case 2 suggests a similar sort 
of conditionality: among cooperators who meet 
a defector, those believing that a higher share of 
defectors are reported are themselves more likely 
to report. 22  The estimated coefficients on the expected 
share cooperating (a i ) and on treatment dummy 
variables are insignificant (in one case marginally 
significant), however, failing to support expec-
tations (based on conditions (3a)-(3c)) that fre-
quency of reporting would be increasing in a i 
and decreasing in ρ. 23 H-R-SP is supported, 
with respect to the relationship between cost 
and reporting frequency, insofar as there is far 
more reporting at a cost of zero than at a posi-
tive cost, in general, and more reporting at zero 
cost than at each specific positive cost taken 
individually (see panels (A) and (B) of Table 
B.1 in Appendix S2). 24 A finer-scale correlation 
between reporting cost and reporting incidence 
is also found insofar as subjects' self-reported </p>

<p>22. There have been numerous behavioral findings of ten-
dency to perform a pro-social or cooperative act conditional 
on beliefs that others do so, for example, Fischbacher and  Gächter (2010) for conditional contributing in public goods 
games and Kamei (2014) for conditional costly punishing in 
public goods games with punishment opportunities. 
23. Failure of belief a i to obtain a significant positive 
coefficient, whereas c i obtains one, in the regression for the 
Case 2 data, is inconsistent with condition (3b), which implies 
that a i rather than c i should be significant. The estimated 
coefficient on a i is insignificant even in specifications that 
exclude b i and c i terms. 
24. The fact that reporting is far greater at zero cost than 
at a money cost as low as $0.05 might reflect a "mental 
accounting" distinction between money and time costs, or 
a peculiarity of the zero cost as discussed, for example, by 
Shampanier et al. (2007). This suggests that there could be 
a substantial number of individuals willing to provide online 
reviews with what they treat psychologically as spare time, 
but who would be deterred if even a small monetary cost were 
involved. </p>

<p>expectations are ones of greater reporting in treat-
ments with lower reporting cost (Table B.4 in 
Appendix S2), but between the different positive 
costs there is no correlation with actual reporting 
frequency. 25 </p>

<p>RESULT 2. (i) The percentages of subjects 
engaging in costly reporting are well pre-
dicted using Fehr and Schmidt's estimates of 
the prevalence and strength of aversion to 
disadvantageous inequality and our subjects' 
self-reported beliefs about frequency of cooper-
ation. Specifically, costly reporting of defectors 
by cooperators is by far the most frequent case, 
with costly reporting of cooperators by defectors 
(predicted to occur rarely if ever) not observed 
and reporting in the remaining two cases rela-
tively infrequent. (ii) Sensitivity of reporting to 
its cost is supported by significantly more report-
ing at cost 0 than at costs $0.05, $0.50, and 
$1.00, and by close correlation between expecta-
tions of others' reporting and specific reporting 
cost. </p>

<p>C. Reporting and Emotions </p>

<p>Whereas social preference models like that 
of Fehr and Schmidt assume rational calculation 
of utility maximizing choices subject to socially 
interdependent preferences, observed reporting 
may sometimes have more emotional underpin-
nings. We turn to evidence that emotions played 
a part in our subjects' decisions. 
Our first source of evidence that emotions 
helped to trigger some of the observed costly 
reporting is an additional treatment that resem-
bles the MC treatment in all respects except 
that rather than having subjects decide whether 
to report their initial counterpart's choice after 
learning what that choice was, they are asked 
to decide in advance whether to send a costly 
report if the participant with whom they are 
matched turns out to have selected XX, and like-
wise whether to send a report if their counterpart </p>

<p>25. We note that insensitivity to reporting cost within the 
range studied by us is consistent with Fehr and Schmidt's 
assumptions. Specifically, calculations show that with the 
frequencies of types (α i , β i settings, see footnote 21) assumed 
by those authors, little sensitivity to reporting cost is predicted 
within the range of our treatments. For example, calculations 
predict that 70% of cooperators will report a defector in both 
treatments LC and MC, with a drop only to 66.7% predicted 
to report defectors in HC. Of course, the insensitivity of 
reporting frequency to cost in our data may be more a quirk 
of small numbers than a fundamental finding. </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>turns out to have selected YY. 26 Of the 20 sub-
jects that participated in this strategy method ses-
sion, 11 selected XX, similar to the 50% share 
in the MC treatment. Thanks to the set-up, we 
got decisions from all 11 about whether they 
would report if meeting a YY-chooser. Only 2 
of the 11 (i.e., 18%) chose to pay the required 
$0.50 to report their first counterpart if that per-
son chose YY. In the MC treatment, with the 
same payoffs and cost but a sequential design 
in which subjects first learned the actual deci-
sion of their assigned counterpart, there were nine 
who chose XX and learned the counterpart had 
chosen YY, and six of them chose to engage in 
costly reporting upon learning of their counter-
part's action, that is, 66.7%. A two-sided two-
sample z test of proportions says that the 18% 
and 66.7% proportions are statistically signifi-
cantly different from each other (p = .028). The 
substantial difference suggests that "hot" emo-
tion (Loewenstein 2000) may have played a role 
in reporting in our main treatments. 
Other evidence for a role of emotions comes 
from the survey that all subjects in the main treat-
ments completed following their decisions. Sub-
jects were asked-following all decisions, so as 
not to contaminate them-to state how pleased 
or angry they felt about their first counterpart's 
decision, and how much (if any) sense of obli-
gation they felt to help their first counterpart's 
next partner. The answers to the anger ques-
tion indicate that the greatest amount of anger 
was felt by cooperators who encountered defec-
tors in their first interaction. Self-reported anger 
is always significantly less for subjects in other 
pairings-XX meets XX, YY meets XX, and 
YY meets YY. Figure 3A shows that among the 
cooperators who encountered defectors, average 
self-reported anger towards the counterpart is sig-
nificantly higher (p = .04) for those who chose to 
report than for those who did not choose to report. 
Thus, the strength of anger could have been a fac-
tor prompting decisions to report, although the 
ex post nature of the answers gives reason for 
caution. 27 </p>

<p>26. These reporting decisions were taken after each sub-
ject had made her own choice between XX and YY and 
had indicated what percentage of others she expected would 
choose XX. Following the reporting decisions, subjects stated 
their beliefs about others' reporting decisions under each con-
tingency. To minimize the impact of the expectation elici-
tation processes, subjects were not informed in advance of 
the fact that expectations were to be elicited, as in our other 
treatments. 
27. The anger variable is a subject's response to the 
question: "How did you feel about your first counterpart's </p>

<p>RESULT 3. Indications that emotions played a 
part in costly reporting consist of (i) a signifi-
cantly smaller share of cooperators choosing to 
report defectors in a strategy method treatment 
than in the corresponding sequential treatment, 
and (ii) a significantly higher self-report of anger 
towards a defector by reporting than by nonre-
porting cooperators. </p>

<p>D. Obligation, Altruism, and Normative 
Motives for Reporting </p>

<p>The postdecision exit survey is consistent with 
presence of another potential motive for a cooper-
ator to report a defecting counterpart: a desire or 
sense of obligation to help that individual's next 
partner (say k) avoid being exploited. Figure 3B 
shows that more than 50% of those actually 
reporting indicate having felt an obligation to 
help k, versus less than 25% of those not report-
ing. 28 Self-reported feelings of obligation to help 
are much smaller in the XX-meets-XX, YY-
meets-YY, and YY-meets-XX cases (see Figure 
B.1 in Appendix S2). 
Although a social preference model might 
also attach value to helping k, we did not include 
this motive in our simple illustration using the 
Fehr-Schmidt model because, with its focus 
on inequalities and inattention to intentions 
and other sources of deservingness, that model 
predicts reporting to help this third party (the 
counterpart's next partner) only under a nar-
row range of cases. An alternative explanation, 
in which reporting to help k is motivated by 
belief that cooperators not only cooperate but 
report conditional on others doing the same, 
is discussed in Supporting Information and 
is consistent with Table B.8's finding that for 
every 1% increase in the proportion of subjects 
whom i believed would report a YY-chooser, 
there is an 0.84% increase in i's likelihood of 
reporting a YY-chooser oneself, consistent with 
conditional cooperation. </p>

<p>decision? Please rate on a scale from 1 = very pleased to 
7 = very angry." That many people view defecting against a 
cooperating partner as grossly unfair is suggested by the fact 
that more than half of unaffected third parties chose to incur a 
cost to punish a unilateral defector in a laboratory experiment 
by Fehr and Fischbacher (2004). 
28. The obligation to help variable is a subject's response 
to the question: "Did you feel a sense of obligation to help 
your first counterpart's next counterpart by sending a report? 
Please rate on a scale from 1 = did not feel obligated at all, to 
7 = felt strongly obligated." </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 
Average Anger Level and Average Feeling of Obligation to Help Third Party k </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Anger </p>

<p>XX-choosers who report YY-choosers </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>XX-choosers who do not report YY-choosers </p>

<p>p = .0446** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Obligation </p>

<p>XX-choosers who report YY-choosers </p>

<p>XX-choosers who do not report YY-choosers </p>

<p>p = .0009*** </p>

<p>Notes: p values indicate Mann-Whitney test results (two-sided). The Anger variable is a subject's response to the following 
question: "How did you feel about your first counterpart's decision? Please rate on a scale from 1 = very pleased to 7 = very 
angry." The Obligation variable is a subject's response to the following question: "Did you feel a sense of obligation to help 
your first counterpart's next counterpart by sending a report? Please rate on a scale from 1 = did not feel obligated at all, to 
7 = felt strongly obligated." ***Significant at 1% level; **significant at 5% level; *significant at 10% level. </p>

<p>E. What Accounts for Cooperation and 
Defection? </p>

<p>Although decisions to engage in costly report-
ing are our focus, we briefly report here to what 
degree decisions to cooperate or defect are expli-
cable by self-interest given beliefs about others' 
choices (see Table B.3 in Appendix S2 for the 
details). We also discuss briefly whether the Fehr-
Schmidt model can account for instances of coop-
eration that are inconsistent with self-interest, 
given beliefs. 
A substantial majority of choices between 
cooperation and defection-63.8% with the pes-
simistic second game belief, 79.6% with the opti-
mistic belief-are consistent with self-interested 
rationality. Specifically, assuming each subject's 
self-reported beliefs to be those on which she 
in fact conditioned her decision, criterion (1) 
correctly predicts about 64% of choices between 
XX and YY, and criterion (1 ′ ) about 80%, mean-
ing that a selfish rational subject would have cho-
sen as the subject in question did in almost two 
thirds (80%) of cases, if she were pessimisti-
cally (optimistically) assuming that all free sec-
ond choices by XX-choosers are Y (X). However, 
while 90% or more of decisions to defect are 
consistent with self-interest under the pessimistic </p>

<p>assumption in each treatment, the proportion of 
XX choices that are consistent with self-interest 
is considerably smaller: 26.1% (43.5%), 31.6% 
(63.2%), 61.9% (90.5%), and 43.5% (78.3%) 
of cooperators had beliefs making cooperating 
payoff-maximizing under the pessimistic (opti-
mistic) belief in the HC, MC, LC, and NC treat-
ments, respectively. In all, H-SPO is capable 
of accounting for many decisions to cooperate, 
but still leaves either the majority or a sub-
stantial minority of those decisions unexplained, 
depending on what the subject was assuming 
about others' second game choices. 
Can the latter decisions to cooperate be 
explained by a simple social preference, for 
example, the one used illustratively by us? 
Leaving details to Supporting Information, we 
find that only a small fraction of the cooper-
ators whose stated beliefs failed to selfishly 
dictate cooperation under even the optimistic 
assumption-specifically, about 12%-would 
have chosen to cooperate out of inequity averse 
utility maximization given the frequencies of 
α and β values assumed by Fehr and Schmidt  (2010). Many of the remaining cooperation 
choices can be explained by aversion to advanta-
geous inequality, but the majority of these cases </p>

<p>KAMEI &amp; PUTTERMAN: REPUTATION TRANSMISSION IN EXPERIMENTAL FOCUS </p>



<p>are consistent with the Fehr-Schmidt model only 
at degrees of aversion to advantageous relative 
to disadvantageous inequality that exceed the 
levels assumed in Fehr and Schmidt's typology. 
Put differently, the decision-makers in question 
must strongly wish to avoid defecting against a 
cooperator and be willing to take a substantial 
risk of being defected against, equivalent to 
having β &gt; α in the Fehr-Schmidt model. </p>

<p>VI. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Numerous studies have focused on the roles 
social preferences and emotions may play in 
accounting for decisions favorable to social wel-
fare but lacking benefit to the actor. Surprisingly, 
the potentially costly act of transmitting informa-
tion has received little attention. A preference-
or emotion-triggered tendency to report at some 
cost to oneself could be indispensable to social 
efficiency in situations in which individuals have 
the option of simply leaving behind undesir-
able interaction partners without incurring the 
time, effort or cost to warn others about them. 
Inclinations to engage in reporting-perhaps 
closely related to the anthropological and psy-
chological identification of gossip as a human 
universal-may be crucial to the viability of 
many reputation-based incentive systems. 
Our experiment underscores the fact that 
reputation formation may involve costs to those 
sharing or transmitting the information on which 
reputational knowledge is based, and it illus-
trates how laboratory experiments can enhance 
our understanding of the motivations relevant 
to decisions to bear such costs. We simplified 
the problem by assuming that whatever infor-
mation is transmitted is accurate, and that the 
recipient knows this to be so with certainty. 
Although the complications introduced when 
the message transmitted is a free choice of the 
reporter and when the recipient must accordingly 
decide whether to place trust in it require further 
research, a body of emerging results provides 
some assurance that most of our findings are 
likely to hold in such an environment as well. 29 </p>

<p>29. A recent example is Fonseca and Peters (2015), who 
find that the preponderance of reports about the trustworthi-
ness of trust game players are truthful, and that the availabil-
ity of such reports raises efficiency. Abraham et al. (2016)  and Fehr and Sutter (2016) permit false reports but find few, 
with Abraham et al. stating "ratings typically provide a true 
account" and Fehr and Sutter stating "it turned out that only a 
small fraction of gossip contains wrong information." In both 
experiments, subjects appear to act upon reports presuming 
their truthfulness. </p>





<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>



<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Appendix S1. Theoretical analysis 
Appendix S2. Additional tables and figures 
Appendix S3. Instructions for the LC treatment </p>

</text></tei>