<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.20140850" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>Improvements to the h -index have been suggested. Consider, for example, the 
g -index (Egghe 2006a,b), which is the largest number g such that the total citation 
count of the g most cited papers is at least g 2 . The g -index is intended to correct 
for the insensitivity of the h -index to the number of citations received by the h most 
cited papers. Many other variations have been suggested since. Yet, like the h -index, 
they are ad hoc measures based almost entirely on intuition and rules of thumb 
with insufficient justification given for choosing them over the infinitely many other 
unchosen possibilities. But for a novel empirical approach to selecting among a new 
class of h -indices, see Ellison (2012, 2013). 2 
To illustrate the difficulties that can arise when a systematic approach to choos-
ing an index is not followed, let us consider the very practical and well-recognized 
problem of comparing the records of individuals in different fields or subfields. 3 
There is compelling evidence to suggest that for such comparisons to be meaning-
ful, one must rescale each individual's citation list by dividing each entry in it by the 
average number of citations in that individual's field. Indeed, Radicchi, Fortunato, 
and Castellano (2008) observe that while the distributions of citations vary widely 
across a variety of fields (from agricultural economics to nuclear physics), after res-
caling by the average number of citations within a field, the distributions all become 
virtually identical (see Section III). 
With this in mind, suppose that two macroeconomists, A and B, are being consid-
ered for a single position and it is noted that A has the higher h -index and so should 
be the preferred candidate. But before a final decision is made, a second position as 
well as a new candidate, C, become available. Candidate C, however, is an industrial 
organization (IO) economist and so a rescaling of the citation lists is necessary to 
compare the three records across the two fields. But a serious difficulty arises. The 
rescaling has reversed the ranking of the two macroeconomists. That is, applying the 
h -index to the rescaled lists produces the ranking: B preferred to C preferred to A, 
and it is now entirely unclear which one of the two macroeconomists should be 
hired! 
But do such reversals occur in practice? According to data collected by Ellison 
(2013), 4 the average number of citations per paper among macroeconomists at the </p>

<p>top 50 US universities is 98 , while among IO economists it is 55 . 5 That is, macro-
economists are cited 1.8 ( = 98/55 ) times more often per paper, on average, than 
IO economists. Applying the h -index to Ellison's (2013) data, both before and after 
reducing the macroeconomists' citations by a factor of 1.8, we find that 95 percent of 
them experience at least one pairwise ranking change with another macroeconomist </p>

<p>2 Ellison (2013) introduces the following class of generalized Hirsch indices. For any a, b &gt; 0 and for any cita-
tion list, h (a, b) is the number of papers, h, that each have at least a h b citations. Ellison estimates a and b so that h (a, b) 
gives the best fit in terms of ranking economists at the top 50 US universities in a manner that is consistent with 
the observed labor market outcome. Ellison (2012) is a related paper that instead uses data on computer scientists. 
3 See, e.g., Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008) and the references therein. 
4 See Section IV for more details. 
5 These figures pertain to individuals who are classified by Ellison (2013) as being in a unique field, in this case 
either IO or macroeconomics. There are 88 out of 226 such macroeconomists and 64 out of 120 such IO economists. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>and 60 percent of them experience at least one strict ranking reversal (see Figure 3 
in Section IV). 6,7 So, for the h -index, the problem of ranking reversals is quite real. 
To avoid this and other difficulties, we take an axiomatic approach in our search 
for an index. 8 The methodology of this approach is to select, with care, a number of 
basic properties that an index should have. The advantage of this approach is that 
it focuses attention on the properties that an index should possess rather than the 
functional form that it should take. After all, it is the properties we desire an index 
to possess that should determine its functional form, not the other way around. The 
five properties that we identify are quite natural for the problem at hand and lead 
uniquely to the Euclidean index. 
Still, one might wonder how well the Euclidean index performs in practice rel-
ative to the h -index. To get a sense of this with Ellison's (2013) data, we assigned 
a score to each index by considering how well its ranking of economists at the top 
50 US universities matched the National Research Council's (NRC) ranking of the 
departments in which they are employed. More specifically, we increased an index's 
score by 1 whenever its ranking of two economists agreed with the NRC's ranking 
of their departments and we decreased an index's score by 1 otherwise, ignoring all 
ties. 9 The Euclidean index outscored the h -index in this test and it also outscored a 
whole family of indices which satisfy a strict subset of our axioms (see Figure 4 in 
Section IV). 10 Thus, at least with respect to this test, the Euclidean index performs 
rather well. 
The Euclidean index is intended to judge an individual's record as it stands. It is 
not intended as a means to predict an individual's record at some future date. If a 
prediction is important to the decision at hand (as in tenure decisions, for example) 
then separate methods must first be used to obtain a predicted citation list to which 
our index can then be applied. 11 
Finally, it should be noted that our index is ordinal. Indeed, we would argue that 
virtually all citation indices are ordinal because they do not provide decision mak-
ers (administrators, tenure committees, funding committees, etc.) with information 
such as individual A is "worth twice as much" as individual B. On the other hand, 
citation indices can and do provide usefully interpretable ordinal information such 
as " A is equivalent to an individual who receives twice as many citations as B on 
every paper" (see Section IIA). It is up to decision makers to apply this interpreta-
ble information to decide how much A should be paid relative to B, or how much 
teaching A should be assigned relative to B, or how much funding A should receive </p>

<p>6 The changes in rank that occur in the data often arise between individuals with similar initial h -indices. Such 
reversals are then less likely to occur between two randomly chosen individuals. Of course recruitment targets are 
not chosen at random. To the extent that departments tend to consider individuals of similar stature, and to the extent 
that the h-index is positively correlated with stature, the frequency of reversals reported here is potentially quite 
relevant in practice. 
7 One might instead suggest rescaling the h -index itself since this will not affect the within-field ranking. But 
unless one can justify why the h -index is preferable to an ordinally equivalent index, say h + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>h , this adjustment 
too will lead to difficulties. See Section III. 
8 We are certainly not the first to do so. See, e.g., Queseda (2011); Woeginger (2008a,b); Marchant (2009a,b); 
and Chambers and Miller (2014). But in each of these cases, except Marchant (2009b), the stated goal is to provide 
axioms for a preexisting citation index. As far as we are aware, the functional form that our axioms identify has not 
been proposed for use as a citation index until now. 
9 That is, we assign scores according to Kendall's (1938) rank correlation coefficient. 
10 All of the indices in the family outscore the h -index. 
11 We thank Glenn Ellison for helpful discussions on this point. </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>relative to B, etc. Given our ordinal perspective, we will have little to say about 
assigning scores to scholarly journals (e.g., Palacios-Huerta and Volij 2004, 2014) 
since such scores are typically used to translate publications from distinct journals 
into a common cardinal currency. 
The rest of the paper proceeds as follows. In Section I, we list the five proper-
ties that characterize the Euclidean index. Section II contains the statement of our 
main result as well as a brief discussion of the roles of each property. Section III 
discusses the important issue of how to eliminate the well-recognized biases that 
arise when comparing citation lists of individuals from different fields or subfields. 
Understanding this issue is central to understanding why we introduce the property 
that we call "scale invariance." Section IV provides the details of the two empirical 
exercises described above. </p>

<p>I. Five Properties for Citation Indices </p>

<p>In this section, we present five properties that lead to a unique index. Unless 
otherwise stated, these properties should be thought of as pertaining to citation lists 
whose cited papers differ only in their number of citations but otherwise have com-
mon characteristics, e.g., year of publication, field, number of authors, etc. Taking 
into account differences in such characteristics is an important issue that is touched 
upon in Section III. 
Citation indices work as follows. First, an individual's record is summarized by a 
finite list of numbers, typically ordered from highest to lowest, where the i th number 
in the list is the number of citations received by the individual's i th most highly cited 
paper. The list of citations is then operated upon by some index function to produce 
the individual's index number. As already mentioned in the introduction (see also 
Section III), one must sometimes rescale one individual's citation list to adequately 
compare it to another individual's list. Consequently, one must be prepared to con-
sider noninteger lists. We therefore take as our domain the set L consisting of all 
finite nonincreasing sequences of nonnegative real numbers. Any element of L is 
called a citation list. 12 
A citation index is any continuous function, ι : L → ℝ, that assigns to each 
citation list a real number. 13 Consider first the following four basic properties. A 
discussion of them follows: </p>

<p>(i) Monotonicity.-The index value of a citation list does not fall when a new </p>

<p>paper with sufficiently many citations is added to the list. </p>

<p>(ii) Independence.-The index's ranking of two citation lists does not change </p>

<p>when a new paper is added to each list and each of the two new papers 
receives the same number of citations. </p>

<p>12 Implicit in the convention to list the numbers in decreasing order is that the index value would be the same 
were the numbers listed in any other order. 
13 Continuity means that for any citation list x , if a sequence of citation lists x 1 , x 2 , … each of whose length 
is the same as the finite length of x, converges to x in the Euclidean sense, then ι( x 1 ), ι( x 2 ), … converges to ι(x). 
The use of the Euclidean metric here is not important. Any equivalent metric, e.g., the taxicab metric, would do. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>(iii) Depth Relevance.-It is not the case that, for every citation list, the index </p>

<p>weakly increases when any paper in the list is split into two and its citations 
are divided in any way between them. </p>

<p>(iv) Scale Invariance.-The index's ranking of two citation lists does not change </p>

<p>when each entry of each list is multiplied by any common positive scaling 
factor. </p>

<p>The first property, monotonicity, says that for each citation list there is a number 
(which can depend on the list) such that the index does not fall if a new paper with </p>

<p>at least that number of citations is added to the list. All indices that we are aware 
of satisfy this property. In fact, all indices that we are aware of satisfy the stron-
ger property that they weakly increase when any new paper is added, regardless of 
how few citations it receives. In contrast, our less restrictive monotonicity property 
allows (but does not require) the index to fall if a new but infrequently cited paper 
is added. Note that monotonicity says nothing about the behavior of the index when 
an existing paper receives additional citations. 
The second property, independence, is natural given that our index is intended 
to compare the records-as they currently stand-of any two individuals. 14 It says, 
in particular, that a tie between two records cannot be broken by adding identical 
papers to each record. The h -index fails to satisfy independence. For example, if 
individual A has 10 papers with 10 citations each, and B has 5 papers with 15 cita-
tions each, then A 's h -index is 10 and B 's is 5. But if they each produce 10 identical 
new papers that receive 15 citations each, then A 's h -index is still 10, but B 's h -index 
increases from 5 to 15 . Note that the independence property is agnostic about the 
effect on the index of adding new papers. Independence allows that adding identi-
cally cited papers to two records could separately increase or decrease the indices, 
so long as the rankings are not reversed. 
It is often suggested that a good index should encourage "quality over quantity," 
i.e., encourage a smaller number of highly cited papers over a larger number of 
infrequently cited papers. The third property, depth relevance, takes a very weak 
stand on this important trade-off. It says that it should not be the case that for any 
fixed number of citations, the index is maximized by spreading them as thinly as 
possible across as many publications as possible. Depth relevance is satisfied by all 
indices that we are aware of with the exception of the total citation count. 
When distinct fields have significantly different average numbers of citations 
per paper, citation lists must be rescaled in order to make meaningful cross-field 
comparisons (see Section III). The fourth property, scale invariance, ensures that 
the final ranking of the population is independent of whether the lists are scaled 
down relative to the disadvantaged field or scaled up relative to the advantaged field. 
Because the h -index is not scale invariant it can, as already observed in the introduc-
tion, reverse the order of individuals in the same field when their lists are adjusted to 
account for differences across fields (Section IV illustrates this with empirical data). </p>

<p>14 Marchant (2009b) appears to be the first to apply this independence property to the bibliometric index 
problem. </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>In addition to the four basic properties above, let us now introduce a fifth property 
that we call "directional consistency." It is motivated as follows. 
Consider two individuals with equally ranked citation lists who, over the next 
year, each receive the same number of additional citations on their most cited paper, 
and the same number but fewer additional citations on their second most cited paper, 
etc. Suppose that at the end of the year their lists remain equally ranked. Directional 
consistency requires that if their papers continue to accrue citations at those same 
yearly rates, then their lists will continue to remain equally ranked year after year. 
The formal statement is as follows: </p>

<p>(v) Directional Consistency.-∀ x, y, d ∈ L, if ι(x) = ι(y) and ι(x + d) 
= ι(y + d), then ι(x + λd) = ι(y + λd) for all λ &gt; 1. 15 </p>

<p>Observe that each of properties (i)-(v) is ordinal in the sense that if an index 
satisfies any one of the properties, then any monotone transformation of that index 
also satisfies that property. The independence of properties (i)-(v) is established in 
the next section following the statement of Theorem 1. </p>

<p>II. The Euclidean Index </p>

<p>Call two citation indices equivalent if one of them is a monotone transformation 
of the other. We now state our main result, whose proof is in the Appendix. </p>

<p>THEOREM 1: A citation index satisfies properties (i)-(v) if and only if it is equiva-
lent to the index that assigns to any citation list, ( x 1 , … , x n ) , the number </p>

<p>√ </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Since this number is the Euclidean length of ( x 1 , … , x n ), we may call this index the 
Euclidean index, and we denote it by ι E . </p>

<p>It may be helpful to briefly discuss the roles of properties (i)-(v). Even though 
we make no such assumption directly, properties (i)-(iv), together with continuity, 
imply that the index strictly increases when any existing paper receives additional 
citations. Independence then implies that the (continuous) index must be equivalent 
to one that is additively separable (a direct application of Debreu 1960). The sym-
metry built into the index (see footnote 12) implies that the summand in the addi-
tively separable representation consists of a single common function, which must be 
strictly increasing. Scale invariance then implies that the index must be equivalent </p>

<p>to an index of the form ( ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1/σ for some σ &gt; 0, and depth relevance implies </p>

<p>that σ &gt; 1. Thus, as Part I of the proof of Theorem 1 shows (see the Appendix), </p>

<p>15 If, for example, x ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>∩ L and d ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>∩ L and n &lt; m, then x + d = ( x 1 + d 1 , … , x n + d n , d n+1 , … , d m ). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>properties (i)-(iv) determine the index up to the single parameter σ &gt; 1 . Property 
(v) pins σ down to the value σ = 2. 16 </p>

<p>While the functional form ( ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1/σ is novel for citation indices, it has a long </p>

<p>tradition in other areas. It is an l σ norm from classical mathematics, a constant elas-
ticity of substitution (CES) utility function as derived in Burk (1936), an Atkinson 
(1970) measure of income inequality, and a Foster, Greer, and Thorbecke (1984) </p>

<p>poverty index. In addition, there are several well-known axiomatic characterizations 
already in the literature, including Burk (1936), Roberts (1980), and Blackorby and 
Donaldson (1982). The main ingredients of each of these characterizations include 
assumptions of continuity, symmetry, independence, coordinate-wise monotonicity, 
and scale invariance. In contrast, we do not impose any monotonicity conditions on 
the coordinates of the index function. The monotonicity property specified here is 
quite distinct from those in the literature because it refers to the effect of increasing 
the dimension of the vector that is being evaluated. For example, the index func-
tion ∑ i ( x i − 10) 3 is not an increasing function of any of its coordinates, yet it satis-
fies our monotonicity property because adding a paper with more than 10 citations 
increases the index. Relatedly, the literature cited above focuses on domains whose 
dimension is fixed at a particular value of n (and it is often assumed that n ≥ 3) 
whereas our analysis must include and patch together all possible dimensions 
n ∈ { 1, 2, … }. Finally, we provide a novel condition that isolates the value σ = 2. 
Properties (i)-(v) are independent. That is, no single property is implied by the 
other four. This can be demonstrated by displaying, for each property, a citation 
index that satisfies the other four properties but is not equivalent to the Euclidean 
index identified in Theorem 1. Finding five such indices is not difficult. 17 </p>

<p>A. Linear Homogeneity </p>

<p>Of all the equivalent indices satisfying properties (i)-(v), only the Euclidean </p>

<p>index ι E (x) = ( ∑ i x i 2 ) </p>

<p>1/2 and its positive multiples are homogeneous of degree 1. </p>

<p>This turns out to be convenient. 
For example, suppose that the Euclidean index of x is twice that of y, 
i.e., ι E (x) = 2 ι E (y). How might one describe how the two lists compare to one 
another in terms that would be helpful to an administrator or someone outside the 
field in question? The answer is that one could say that "list x is as good as the list 
that has as many papers as in y, but receives twice as many citations on each of 
them." 
The reason that this statement is correct is that, by linear homogeneity, 
2 ι E (y) = ι E (2y). Therefore, ι E (x) = 2 ι E (y) if and only if ι E (x) = ι E (2y), and </p>

<p>16 It is interesting to note that properties (i)-(iv) alone imply that for any two lists x, y ∈ L ∩ ℝ n , if x 1 ≥ y 1 
and x 1 + x 2 ≥ y 1 + y 2 and ⋯ x 1 + ⋯ + x n ≥ y 1 + ⋯ + y n , with at least one inequality strict, then the index 
must rank x strictly above y. This follows directly from Hardy, Littlewood, and Pólya's (1934) well-known result on 
second-order stochastic dominance since ∑ i=1 
n x i 
σ is an increasing and strictly convex function for any σ &gt; 1. Thus, </p>

<p>some lists can be compared without appealing to property (v). 
17 For example, ι = 1/n satisfies all properties but monotonicity; ι = max ( x 1 , … , x n ) satisfies all properties </p>

<p>but independence; ι = ∑ i=1 
n x i satisfies all properties but depth relevance; ι = ∑ i=1 
n x i </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+ n satisfies all properties </p>

<p>but scale invariance; and ι = ∑ i=1 
n x i 
3 satisfies all properties but directional consistency. In addition, the lexico-
graphic order satisfies all properties but continuity. None of these indices is equivalent to the Euclidean index. </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>this last equality means precisely what is stated in the quotation marks in the previ-
ous paragraph. 
Thus, the Euclidean index, ι E , is particularly convenient because the ratio, λ, of 
the Euclidean index of x to that of y tells us that "list x is as good as the list that has 
as many papers as list y, but receives λ times as many citations on each of them." In 
particular, if an individual's Euclidean index is twice that of the median Euclidean 
index in his field, then the individual is equivalent to one who produces twice as 
many citations per paper as the median researcher in his field. </p>

<p>III. Why Rescale the Lists? </p>

<p>Our justification for the scale invariance property rests on the claim that the 
appropriate way to adjust for differences in fields is to divide each entry in an indi-
vidual's citation list by the average number of citations in that individual's field. 
We now support this claim by reviewing the work in this direction due to Radicchi, 
Fortunato, and Castellano (2008). 18 
In Figure 1, we reproduce Figure 1 in Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008), 
showing normalized (relative to the total number of citations) histograms of unad-
justed citations received by papers published in 1999 within each of 5 fields out 
of 20 considered. The main point of this figure is to show that the distributions 
of unadjusted citations differ widely across fields. For example, in Developmental </p>

<p>18 It should be noted that, for the most part, Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano hold fixed the year of publica-
tion so that the age of the papers considered is the same. </p>

<p>Number of citations c </p>

<p>Percent of eld's papers with </p>

<p>c citations </p>

<p>10 −5 </p>

<p>10 −4 </p>

<p>10 −3 </p>

<p>10 −2 </p>

<p>10 −1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 −6 </p>

<p>Engineering, Aerospace c 0 = 5.65 
Biology c 0 = 14.60 
Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics c 0 = 23.77 
Hematology c 0 = 30.61 
Developmental biology c 0 = 38.67 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Note: Histograms of raw citations across fields in 1999, where c 0 is the average number of cita-
tions per paper published in 1999 in that field. </p>

<p>Source: Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008), Copyright (2008) National Academy of 
Sciences, USA </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>Biology, a publication with 100 citations is 50 times more frequent than in Aerospace 
Engineering. However, after adjusting each citation received by a year-1999 paper 
by dividing it by the average number of citations of all the year-1999 papers in the 
same field, the distinct histograms in Figure 1, remarkably, align to form a single 
histogram, shown in Figure 2 (in both figures, the axes are on a logarithmic scale). 19 
We encourage the reader to consult Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008) 
for details, but let us point out that several statistical methods are used there to ver-
ify what seems perfectly clear from the figures, namely, that dividing by the aver-
age number of citations per paper in one's field corrects for differences in citations 
across fields in the very strong sense that, after the adjustment, the distributions of 
citations are virtually identical across fields. 20 </p>

<p>A. Why Not Rescale the Index Itself? </p>

<p>Another way to adjust for differences in fields might be to adjust the index itself. 
For example, a popular method for comparing h -indices across fields is to divide </p>

<p>19 A consequence of this alignment is that the suggested adjustment is unique in the following sense. Restricting 
to papers published in 1999, let c ̃ j denote the random variable describing the distribution of citations in field j, and 
let c -j denote its expectation. The suggested adjustment is to divide any field j paper's number of citations, c, by c -j , 
giving the adjusted entry c / c -j . If any increasing functions ϕ 1 , ϕ 2 , . . . align the distributions across fields-i.e., are 
such that the adjusted random variables ϕ 1 ( c ̃ 1 ), ϕ 2 ( c ̃ 2 ), . . . all have the same distribution-then there is a common 
increasing function f such that ϕ j (c) = f ( </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>__ 
c -j ) </p>

<p>for every j. 
20 In Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008), the common histogram in Figure 2 is estimated as being log 
normal with variance 1.3 (the mean must be 1 because of the rescaling). </p>

<p>Percent of eld's papers with </p>

<p>c/c </p>

<p>0 citations </p>

<p>10 −5 </p>

<p>10 −4 </p>

<p>10 −3 </p>

<p>10 −2 </p>

<p>10 −1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>Number of adjusted citations c/ </p>

<p>10 −2 
10 −1 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 </p>

<p>Agricultural economics &amp; Policy 
Allergy 
Anesthesiology 
Astronomy &amp; Astrophysics 
Biology 
Computer science, Cybernetics 
Developmental biology 
Engineering, Aerospace 
Hematology 
Mathematics 
Microbiology 
Neuroimaging 
Physics, Nuclear 
Tropical medicine </p>

<p>c 0 </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Note: Histograms of adjusted citations across fields in 1999. </p>

<p>Source: Radicchi, Fortunato, and Castellano (2008), Copyright (2008) National Academy of 
Sciences, USA </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>each individual's h -index by the average h -index in his/her field. 21 This produces, 
for each individual, an adjusted h -index, called the h s -index in the literature, that is 
then used to compare any two individuals in the population, regardless of field. This 
adjustment has the obvious but important property that it does not affect the ranking 
of individuals within the same field. The following example shows, however, that 
the final ranking of the population depends on the particular numerical representa-
tion of the h -index that is employed. </p>

<p>Example 1: There are two mathematicians, M 1 and M 2 , and two biologists, B 1 
and B 2 , with each individual representing one-half of his field. Their h -indices are 2, 
8, 7, and 27, respectively so that their ranking according to the raw h -index is </p>

<p>(3.1) 
M 1 ≺ B 1 ≺ M 2 ≺ B 2 , </p>

<p>where ≺ means "is ranked worse than." To compare mathematicians to biol-
ogists, let us divide each of the mathematician's indices by their field's average 
( (2 + 8)/2 = 5) and divide each of the biologist's h -indices by their field's average 
((7 + 27)/2 = 17). The resulting adjusted indices, h s , are respectively, 0.4, 1.6, </p>

<p>0.41, and 1.58, producing the final adjusted ranking, </p>

<p>(3.2) 
M 1 ≺ B 1 ≺ B 2 ≺ M 2 . </p>

<p>But suppose that instead of starting the exercise with the h -index, we start with 
the monotonic transformation h  *  = h + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>h . The h  *  -indices of M 1 , M 2 , B 1 , and B 2 
are, respectively, 2 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>2 , 8 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>8 , 7 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>7 , and 27 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>27 , i.e., 3.4, 10.8, 9.6, and 
32.2, yielding the same ranking (3.1) as the ordinally equivalent h -index. 
However, if for h  *  we follow the same procedure and divide each individual's 
h  *  -index by the average h  *  in his/her field (i.e., divide the mathematicians' 
h  *  -indices by 7.1 and divide the biologists' by 20.9), then the final adjusted ranking 
becomes </p>

<p>(3.3) 
B 1 ≺ M 1 ≺ M 2 ≺ B 2 . </p>

<p>Comparing (3.2) with (3.3), we see that the ranking of M 1 and B 1 and of M 2 
and B 2 depend on which of the ordinally equivalent indices h or h  *  that one begins 
with. 22 Absent a compelling argument for choosing one over the other, one must 
conclude that this adjustment procedure is not well founded. </p>

<p>21 This h -index adjustment is suggested by Kaur, Radicchi, and Menczer (2013) and it is used by the online citation 
analysis tool <rs id="software-1" type="software">Scholarometer</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://scholarometer.indiana.edu</rs>), whose popularity for computing and comparing 
the h -indices of scholars across disciplines seems to be growing. 
22 Indeed, the ranking in (3.2) is impossible to obtain through any rescaling of the mathematicians' and the biol-
ogists' h  *  indices because there is no λ &gt; 0 such that λ(2 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>2 ) &lt; (7 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>7 ) &lt; (27 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>27 ) &lt; λ(8 + √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>8 ). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>IV. Two Empirical Exercises </p>

<p>We conclude by providing the details of the two empirical exercises described 
in the introduction. 23 In both exercises we rely on a dataset constructed by Glen 
Ellison who graciously made it available to us. Ellison (2013, p. 68) describes his 
data as follows: "The dataset includes citation records of almost all faculty at the 
top 50 economics departments in the 1995 NRC ranking. Faculty lists were taken 
from the departmental websites in the fall of 2011. Citation data for each economist 
were collected from <rs type="software">Google Scholar</rs>. Economists were classified into one or more of 
15 subfields primarily by mapping keywords appearing in descriptions of research 
interests on departmental or individual websites. Slightly less than one-half of econ-
omists are classified as working in a single field." 
When one looks, even casually, at Ellison's citation data, one cannot help but 
notice the large differences in the average numbers of citations across fields, from 
a high of 108 per paper in international trade to a low of 30 per paper in economic 
history. To correct for these differences when comparing scholars from different 
fields, one must first rescale the individual citation lists, as explained in Section III, 
by dividing each scholars' citations, paper by paper, by the average number of cita-
tions in that paper's field. For scholars whose papers are in a single field, all citations 
should be divided by the average number of citations in that field. 
Our first exercise illustrates that use of the h -index can lead to serious practical 
problems when efforts are made to correct for differences in fields of study because 
rescaling has a nontrivial effect on the h -index's within-field rankings. In this exer-
cise we restricted attention to individuals in Ellison's (2013) data who are classified 
as working in a single field. For the 88 individuals who are classified as macroecon-
omists, the average number of citations per paper is 97.9, while the average number 
of citations per paper for the 64 IO economists is 55.17. Therefore, to adequately 
compare macroeconomists to IO economists one must scale down the macroecono-
mists' citation lists by a factor of (97.9)/(55.17) = 1.77. 
Figure 3 shows that the h -index's within-field ranking of macroeconomists is 
nontrivially affected by this rescaling. Each numbered space on the horizontal axis 
corresponds to a macroeconomist, with space k denoting the macroeconomist with 
the k th highest h -index before rescaling. The heights of the bars indicate either the 
total number of ranking changes (lighter colored bars) or the number of strict rank-
ing reversals (darker colored bars) experienced by each macroeconomist as a result 
of rescaling. 
For example, after rescaling all of the macroeconomists' lists, macroecono-
mist number 47 experiences 8 within-field strict ranking reversals and a total of 13 
within-field ranking changes. That is, there are 8 macroeconomists (the height of the 
darker colored bar) who either have a strictly higher h -index than macroeconomist 
47 before rescaling but a strictly lower h -index after or vice versa; and there are 5 
additional macroeconomists (for a total of 13, the height of the lighter colored bar) 
who either have the same h -index as macroeconomist 47 before rescaling but a dif-
ferent h -index after or vice versa. </p>

<p>23 We are very grateful to the editor and referees for encouraging us to include some empirical facts along with 
our theoretical analysis. </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>While a number of macroeconomists experienced no ranking changes at all (e.g., 
macroeconomist number 1 was top-ranked both before and after rescaling), 95 per-
cent of the 88 macroeconomists experienced at least one pairwise change in their 
h -index ranking as a result of rescaling, and 60 percent experienced at least one 
strict pairwise ranking reversal. In contrast, the Euclidean index, being scale invari-
ant, generates the same within-field ranking of macroeconomists before and after 
rescaling. 
Our second exercise is intended to provide an empirically relevant and reason-
ably objective comparison between the Euclidean index and the h -index. Inspired 
by Ellison (2013), and again using his data, we tested each index to see how well 
its ranking of economists at the top 50 US universities matched the NRC's ranking 
of the departments in which they are employed. To do this, we first rescaled the 
citation lists of each economist by the average number of citations in his/her field 
(with economic history as the numeraire). We then assigned a score to each index as </p>

<p>follows. Starting from a score of zero, we increased an index's score by 1 whenever 
its strict ranking of two economists agreed with the NRC's strict ranking of their 
departments and we decreased an index's score by 1 otherwise, ignoring all ties. 
Summing all the +1s and −1 s and then dividing by the total number of distinct 
pairs of economists yields the index's score, a number between − 1 and +1 . That 
is, we computed Kendall's (1938) rank correlation coefficient (or "tau coefficient") 
between the ranking of economists according to each of the two indices' ( h -index 
and Euclidean index) and the NRC's ranking of their departments. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>1 3 5 7 9 11 13 15 17 19 21 23 25 27 29 31 33 35 37 39 41 43 45 47 49 51 53 55 57 59 61 63 65 67 69 71 73 75 77 79 81 83 85 87 </p>

<p>Number of ranking changes </p>

<p>
Number of strict ranking reversalss </p>



<p>88 macroeconomists listed by their h-index rank before rescaling </p>

<p>Figure 3. The h-Index Is Susceptible to Ranking Changes after Rescaling for Differences in Fields </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>The Euclidean index outscored the h -index in this test, producing a score of 
0.1846 , over 14 percent higher than the h -index's score of 0.1614 . And both indices' 
rankings of economists reject (with a p-value of 0.4 percent for the Euclidean index 
and 2.6 percent for the h -index) the null hypothesis of mutual independence with 
the NRC's ranking. 24 
In addition to testing the Euclidean index against the h -index, we tested the 
Euclidean index against a whole family of indices that nest the Euclidean index. 
Specifically, we computed Kendall's rank correlation coefficient between the rank-</p>

<p>ing of economists given by the " σ -index" ( ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1/σ with σ &gt; 1, and the NRC's </p>

<p>ranking of their departments. We did this for all values of σ between 1 and 4. The 
family of σ -indices with σ &gt; 1 is precisely the family of indices that satisfy prop-
erties (i)-(iv) (see the discussion following Theorem 1 in Section II). </p>

<p>Figure 4 (solid line) graphs the value of Kendall's correlation coefficient as 
a function of σ. For comparison, we have also included in Figure 4 the value of 
Kendall's coefficient achieved by the Euclidean index (dashed line) and the lower 
value achieved by the h -index (dotted line). As is evident from the figure, for all val-
ues of σ between 1 and 4, Kendall's coefficient for the σ -index is larger than that for 
the h -index. Moreover, Kendall's coefficient achieves its maximum value of 0.1849 
when σ = 1.85, a value of σ that is remarkably close to the value of σ = 2 that 
defines the Euclidean index. Thus, the Euclidean index, in addition to outscoring the 
h -index, outscores a whole family of indices satisfying properties (i)-(iv), namely 
the family of σ -indices for values of σ &gt; 1 that are not too close to 1.85 . </p>

<p>24 Under the null hypothesis of mutual independence between an index's ranking and the NRC's ranking, the 
scores are (see Kendall 1938) well approximated by a normal distribution with mean zero and standard deviation 
2/(3 √ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>n ) = 0.071 , where n = 88 is the number of economists who are classified as working in the single field 
of macroeconomics. </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.165 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.175 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.185 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Euclidean index </p>

<p>h-index </p>

<p>Kendall's correlation coefficient </p>

<p>σ-index </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>Figure 4. The Euclidean Index Outperforms the h-Index in Matching Labor Market Data </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>PROOF OF THEOREM 1: 
Since sufficiency is clear, we focus only on necessity. We separate the proof of 
necessity into two parts. Part I imposes only properties (i)-(iv), and shows that 
the index must be equivalent to ∑ i x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>for some σ &gt; 1. Part II shows that for any 
σ &gt; 1, the index ∑ i x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>satisfies property (v) only if σ = 2. </p>

<p>Part I: Suppose that the (continuous) citation index ι : L → ℝ satisfies properties 
(i)-(iv). For every n, it will be convenient to extend ι from the set of nonin-</p>

<p>creasing and nonnegative n -vectors to all of ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>by defining, for any ( x 1 , … , x n ) 
∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>, ι( x 1 , … , x n ) := ι( X 1 , X 2 , … , X n ), where X i is i th order statistic of x 1 , … , x n . 
Thus, ι is now defined on the extended domain L  *  : = ∪ n ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>in such a way that it is 
symmetric; i.e., if x ∈ L  *  is a permutation of x′ ∈ L  *  , then ι(x) = ι(x′ ). Clearly, 
the extended function ι satisfies the extensions to L  *  of properties (i)-(iv), and for 
any n ≥ 1 its restriction to ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>is continuous. We work with the extended index ι 
from now on. 
Let us first show that adding a paper with zero citations leaves the index 
unchanged. Let z be any element of L  *  . We wish to show that ι(z) = ι(z, 0). By 
depth relevance, there is a list ( x 1 , w) ∈ L  *  , where w may be the empty list, and 
there are numbers y 1 , y 2 ≥ 0 with y 1 + y 2 = x 1 such that ι( x 1 , w) &gt; ι( y 1 , y 2 , w). 
By independence, ι( x 1 ) &gt; ι( y 1 , y 2 ) and by scale invariance, ι(λ x 1 ) &gt; ι(λ y 1 , λ y 2 ) 
for all λ &gt; 0. Taking the limit as λ → 0 + gives, by continuity, that ι(0) ≥ ι(0, 0). 
Applying independence once gives ι(z, 0) ≥ ι(z, 0, 0) and applying it again gives 
ι(z) ≥ ι(z, 0). For the reverse inequality note that by monotonicity, there is m &gt; 0 </p>

<p>such that ι(m, 0) ≥ ι(0). By scale invariance, ι(λm, 0) ≥ ι(0) for all λ &gt; 0. 
Taking the limit as λ → 0 + gives, by continuity, that ι(0, 0) ≥ ι(0). Then, by 
independence, ι(z, 0, 0) ≥ ι(z, 0), and applying independence once more gives 
ι(z, 0) ≥ ι(z), as desired. </p>

<p>We next show that ι(1) &gt; ι(0). By monotonicity, there is m &gt; 0 such that 
ι(m, 0) ≥ ι(0). Since by the previous paragraph ι(m, 0) = ι(m) , we have 
ι(m) ≥ ι(0). Since m &gt; 0, scale invariance implies that ι(1) ≥ ι(0). It remains </p>

<p>to show that ι(1) ≠ ι(0). Suppose, by way of contradiction, that ι(1) = ι(0). 
Then, by scale invariance, ι( x 1 ) = ι(0) for all x 1 ≥ 0. Then for all x 2 ≥ 0, by 
independence, ι( x 1 , x 2 ) = ι( x 2 , 0) = ι( x 2 ) = ι(0), where the second equal-
ity follows from the previous paragraph. Continuing in this manner shows that 
ι( x 1 , … , x n ) = ι(0) for all n and all x 1 , … , x n ≥ 0, contradicting depth relevance. </p>

<p>We conclude that ι(1) &gt; ι(0). 
We next show that, for every n ≥ 1, ι is strongly increasing on ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>, i.e., </p>

<p>(A1) 
ι( x i ′ , x −i ) &gt; ι( x i , x −i ), ∀ x ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>, ∀ i, and ∀ x i ′ &gt; x i . </p>

<p>To establish (A1), it suffices to show, by independence, that x i ′ &gt; x i implies 
ι( x i ′ ) &gt; ι( x i ); note that x i and x i ′ here are real numbers (e.g., x i is a list consist-</p>

<p>ing of 1 paper with x i citations). By scale invariance, it then suffices to show that 
ι(1) &gt; ι ( </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>x i ′ ) . So, let λ = x i / x i ′ &lt; 1 and suppose, by way of contradiction, that </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>ι(λ) ≥ ι(1). Then λ &gt; 0 since ι(1) &gt; ι(0) as shown above. Hence, we may </p>

<p>apply scale invariance to ι(λ) ≥ ι(1) using the scaling factor λ. Doing so k times 
gives ι( λ k+1 ) ≥ ι( λ k ) ≥ ⋯ ≥ ι(λ) ≥ ι(1). Taking the limit as k → ∞ of 
ι( λ k+1 ) ≥ ι(1) implies, because ι is continuous and λ &lt; 1 , that ι(0) ≥ ι(1). But </p>

<p>this contradicts ι(1) &gt; ι(0) and so establishes (A1). 
For any n ≥ 1, let ι n : ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>→ ℝ be the restriction of ι to ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>. For any subset I of 
{ 1, … , n} and for any x ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>let x I = ( x i ) i∈I and let I c = { 1, … , n}\I. 
We next show that ι n satisfies Blackorby and Donaldson's (1982) "complete strict 
separability" condition. 25 That is, ∀ x, x′, y ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>and ∀ I ⊆ { 1, … , n}, </p>

<p>(A2) 
ι n ( x I , x I c ) ≥ ι n ( x I , y I c ) if and only if ι n ( x I ′ , x I c ) ≥ ι n ( x I ′ , y I c ). 26 </p>

<p>To see that (A2) holds, note that ι n ( x I , x I c ) ≥ ι n ( x I , y I c ) if and only if ι( x I , x I c ) 
≥ ι( x I , y I c ) if and only if ι( x I c ) ≥ ι( y I c ) if and only if ι( x I ′ , x I c ) ≥ ι( x I ′ , y I c ) if and </p>

<p>only if ι n ( x I ′ , x I c ) ≥ ι n ( x I ′ , y I c ) as desired, where the second and third equivalences 
follow from independence. 
Because, for each n, the continuous and symmetric function ι n : ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>→ ℝ satis-</p>

<p>fies (A1), (A2) , and scale invariance, we may apply Theorem 2, part (i), in Blackorby 
and Donaldson (1982) (see also Theorem 6 in Roberts 1980) to conclude that for 
all n ≥ 3, there exist a n ∈ ℝ and a strictly increasing ϕ n : ℝ ++ → ℝ such that </p>

<p>ι n (x) = ϕ n ( ( </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>) 
, for all x ∈ ℝ ++ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>where we adopt the convention that ( ∑ i x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n := Π i x i if a n = 0. From this we </p>

<p>may conclude that ι n is equivalent to ( ∑ i x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n on the strictly positive orthant ℝ ++ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>. 
We claim that a n &gt; 0. Indeed, let w(α) = (1, … , 1, α) ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>and suppose </p>

<p>first that a n &lt; 0. Then lim α→ 0 + ( ∑ i ( w i (α)) a n ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>= 0. Consequently, because </p>

<p>the functional form of ι n above implies that ι n (1, 0, … , 0) ≤ ι n (w(α)), we </p>

<p>have </p>

<p>ι n (1, 0, … , 0) ≤ lim α→ 0 + ι n (w(α)) = lim α→ 0 + ϕ n ( ( ∑ i ( w i (α)) a n ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>) &lt; </p>

<p>ϕ n (λ n </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>a n ) = ι n (λ 1 n ) holds for any λ &gt; 0, where the strict inequality follows </p>

<p>because ϕ n is strictly increasing and lim α→ 0 + ( ∑ i ( w i (α)) a n ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>= 0 &lt; λ n </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>__ </p>

<p>a n . 
Hence, ι n (1, 0, … , 0) ≤ lim λ→ 0 + ι n (λ 1 n ) = ι n (0, … , 0), which contradicts (A1). 
A similar argument holds for a n = 0. 
Hence, for every n ≥ 3, a n is strictly positive and ι n is equivalent to ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>on ℝ ++ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>. But since both ι n and ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>are continuous on ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>we may conclude 
that ι n is equivalent to ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>a n </p>

<p>on ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>. And because adding a paper with zero 
citations does not change the value of the index, we may further conclude that 
a n = a n+1 for all n ≥ 3. </p>

<p>25 Or, equivalently, Debreu's (1960) " factor-independence" condition. 
26 Where, e.g., x I = ( x i ) i∈I . </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>Thus, we have so far shown that there exists σ &gt; 0 such that, for any n ≥ 3 
and for any lists x, y ∈ ℝ + </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>of the same length n, ι n (x) ≥ ι n (y) if and only 
if ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>≥ ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>y i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>. We must also characterize the index when comparing lists 
whose common length is less than 3, and when comparing lists of different lengths. 
But such comparisons can be made by first adding zeros to the two lists to be com-
pared so that the lengths of the resulting lists are equal and at least 3. Since adding 
zeros does not affect the value of the index the correct comparison can now be 
obtained by applying to the lengthened lists the function ∑ i x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>. Hence, we may con-
clude that ι is equivalent to the index that assigns to any citation list ( x 1 , … , x n ) ∈ L  *  
of any length n the number ∑ i=1 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>. 
It remains only to show that σ &gt; 1 . But this follows from depth relevance 
because 0 &lt; σ ≤ 1 implies ( x 1 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>+ x 2 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) ≥ ( x 1 + x 2 ) σ ∀ x 1 , x 2 ≥ 0, which implies 
( x 1 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>+ x 2 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) + ∑ i z i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>≥ ( x 1 + x 2 ) σ + ∑ i z i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>for all nonnegative z = ( z 1 , … , z n ), 
which implies ι( x 1 , x 2 , z) ≥ ι( x 1 + x 2 , z), and so depth relevance fails. 27 This com-
pletes part I of the proof. </p>

<p>Part II: We must show that if σ &gt; 1 and ι(x) = ∑ i x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>satisfies property (v), 
then σ = 2. In fact, we will show the even stronger result that if σ &gt; 1 and ∑ i x i </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>satisfies property (v) for lists of length 2 then σ = 2. So, from now on we restrict 
attention to lists of length 2, i.e., to vectors in L ∩ ℝ + </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
Let x = ( (1 / 2) 1/σ , (1 / 2) 1/σ ) and let y = (1, 0). Then, </p>

<p>ι(x) = ι(y) = 1 . </p>

<p>By Lemma A1 below, there exists d 1 &gt; 1 such that </p>

<p>(A3) 
((1/2 ) 1/σ + d 1 ) σ + ((1/2 ) 1/σ + 1) σ = (1 + d 1 ) σ + 1. </p>

<p>Since d 1 &gt; 1, the vector ( d 1 , 1) is in L ∩ ℝ + </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. Letting d = ( d 1 , 1) , (A3) says 
that </p>

<p>ι(x + d) = ι(y + d). </p>

<p>Therefore, by property (v), we must have </p>

<p>ι(x + λd) = ι(y + λd) ∀ λ &gt; 1. </p>

<p>That is, </p>

<p>((1/2 ) 1/σ + λ d 1 ) σ + ((1/2 ) 1/σ + λ ) σ = (1 + λ d 1 ) σ + λ σ , ∀ λ &gt; 1. </p>

<p>Dividing this equality by λ σ , letting α = (1/2) 1/σ , and letting β = 1/λ gives </p>

<p>(A4) 
(βα + d 1 ) σ + (βα + 1) σ = (β + d 1 ) σ + 1, ∀ β ∈ (0, 1). </p>

<p>27 For σ ∈ (0, 1 ] , the function ( x 1 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>+ x 2 </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>) − ( x 1 + x 2 ) σ has nonnegative partial derivatives when x 1 , x 2 &gt; 0 and </p>

<p>so it achieves a minimum value of 0 on ℝ + 
2 at, for example, x 1 = x 2 = 0. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>Assume, by way of contradiction, that σ is not a positive integer. Then, for any 
integer k = 1, 2, 3, … we may differentiate (A4) k times with respect to β and take 
the limit of the resulting equality as β → 0 giving , </p>

<p>(A5) 
α k ( d 1 ) σ−k + α k = ( d 1 ) σ−k . </p>

<p>Solving for d 1 gives </p>

<p>(A6) 
d 1 = ( 
α k </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>1 − α k ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>σ−k </p>

<p>= ( 2 k/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>k−σ </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>where the second equality uses the definition α = (1/2) 1/σ . 
Since (A6) holds for every k = 1, 2, 3, … it must also hold in the limit as 
k → ∞. We claim that </p>

<p>(A7) 
lim </p>

<p>k→∞ </p>

<p>( 2 k/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>k−σ </p>

<p>= 2 1/σ . </p>

<p>To see this, replace k with the continuous variable z ∈ (1, ∞) and take the limit of 
the log of the expression of interest. This gives </p>

<p>lim </p>

<p>z→∞ </p>

<p>log ( 2 z/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>z−σ </p>

<p>= lim </p>

<p>z→∞ </p>

<p>log ( 2 z/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>z − σ </p>

<p>= lim </p>

<p>z→∞ </p>

<p>( 2 z/σ − 1 ) 
−1 2 z/σ log ( 2 1/σ 
) </p>

<p>____________________ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>= log ( 2 1/σ 
) , </p>

<p>where the second equality follows by l'Hôpital's rule This proves (A7). 
Since, (A6) must hold, in particular, for k = 1, and also in the limit, we must 
have </p>

<p>2 1/σ = ( 2 1/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>____ </p>

<p>1−σ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Raising both sides to the power 1 − σ gives </p>

<p>2 (1−σ)/σ = 2 1/σ − 1. </p>

<p>Since the left-hand side is (1/2) ( 2 1/σ ), we obtain </p>

<p>(1/2)( 2 1/σ ) = 1, </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>

<p>or, equivalently, </p>

<p>2 1/σ = 2. </p>

<p>But this last equality implies that σ = 1, which is a contradiction since σ &gt; 1 . 
Hence, σ must be an integer greater than 1. 
Next, assume by way of contradiction, that σ ≠ 2, i.e., that σ is an integer 
greater than 2. Since (A6) is valid for all k = 1, … , σ − 1, it is valid, in particular 
for k = σ − 1 and k = σ − 2 ≥ 1. Hence, </p>

<p>( 2 (σ−1)/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>_______ </p>

<p>(σ−1)−σ </p>

<p>= ( 2 (σ−2)/σ − 1 ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>_______ </p>

<p>(σ−2)−σ , </p>

<p>which is equivalent to </p>

<p>(2( 2 −1/σ ) − 1) </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>= (2( 2 −2/σ ) − 1) 
−1/2 , </p>

<p>which, after cross-multiplying and squaring, is equivalent to </p>

<p>2( 2 −2/σ ) − 1 = (2( 2 −1/σ ) − 1) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>= 4( 2 −2/σ ) − 4( 2 −1/σ ) + 1. </p>

<p>Gathering terms, this is equivalent to </p>

<p>0 = 2( 2 −2/σ ) − 4( 2 −1/σ ) + 2 </p>

<p>= 2 ( 2 −1/σ − 1) 
2 , </p>

<p>which is a contradiction, because the last expression on the right-hand side is posi-
tive for all finite values of σ &gt; 1. We conclude that σ = 2. ∎ </p>

<p>LEMMA A1: There exists d 1 &gt; 1 that solves (A3). </p>

<p>PROOF: 
Since the functions in (A3) are continuous, it suffices to show: (i) when d 1 = 1 
in (A3), the left-hand side is larger than the right-hand side; and (ii) the right-hand 
side of (A3) is larger than the left-hand side for all d 1 sufficiently large. 
Starting with (i), set d 1 = 1 in (A3). We wish to show that </p>

<p>(A8) 
2((1/2 ) 1/σ + 1 ) σ &gt; 2 σ + 1. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
SEpTEMbER 2016 </p>

<p>The left-hand side of (A8) is equal to (1 + 2 1/σ ) </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>. Taking the σ th root of both sides, 
we see that (A8) holds if and only if, </p>

<p>1 + 2 1/σ &gt; ( 2 σ + 1) 1/σ , </p>

<p>which can be rewritten as </p>

<p>( 1 σ + 0 σ ) 1/σ + ( 1 σ + 1 σ ) 1/σ &gt; ( 2 σ + 1 σ ) 1/σ . </p>

<p>But this last strict inequality holds by the Minkowski inequality for the vectors (1, 0), </p>

<p>(1, 1) , and (2, 1) under the l p norm ‖( a 1 , a 2 )‖ p = ( a 1 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>+ a 2 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>) 1/p with p = σ &gt; 1, </p>

<p>because (1, 0) and (1, 1) are not proportional. 28 This establishes (A8) and therefore 
(i). We now turn to (ii). </p>

<p>Let α = (1/2) 1/σ . It suffices to show that </p>

<p>lim </p>

<p>w→∞ </p>

<p>[ (1 + w) σ − (α + w) σ ] = +∞ . </p>

<p>We can establish this limit as follows: </p>

<p>lim </p>

<p>w→∞ </p>

<p>[ (1 + w) σ − (α + w) σ ] = lim </p>

<p>r→ 0 + [ ( 1 + 1 </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>r ) 
σ − ( α + 1 </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>r ) </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>] </p>

<p>= lim </p>

<p>r→ 0 + </p>

<p>[ (r + 1) σ − (αr + 1) σ ] </p>

<p>__________________ </p>

<p>r σ </p>

<p>= lim </p>

<p>r→ 0 + </p>

<p>[ (r + 1) σ−1 − α (αr + 1) σ−1 
] </p>

<p>______________________ </p>

<p>r σ−1 </p>

<p>= + ∞, </p>

<p>where the third equality follows by l'Hôpital's rule because σ &gt; 0, and the fourth 
since the numerator of the third line tends to 1 − α &gt; 0 and the denominator tends 
to 0 from the right because σ &gt; 1 . This proves (ii). ∎ </p>



<p>28 We thank Sergiu Hart for this Minkowski inequality argument. </p>

<p> 
Perry and reny: How to count citations if you must 
VoL. 106 no. 9 </p>



<p>This article has been cited by: </p>

<p>1. Daniel S. Hamermesh. 2018. Citations In Economics: Measurement, Uses, and Impacts. Journal of 
Economic Literature 56:1, 115-156. [Abstract] [View PDF article] [PDF with links] </p>

</text></tei>