<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F09645292.2018.1426732" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>DHS data is combined with school supply statistics to study primary school 
attendance in the 2005-06 school year in Benin, a country that has seen 
almost unparalleled increases in attendance since the 1990s. Results of a 
logistic regression model highlight the important role played by factors 
such as household wealth or religion and that gender disparities in 
education persist in Benin. The opportunity cost of attending school is 
also investigated. In order to explain regional disparities in attendance, a 
multilevel model is estimated; results from a random-slopes model 
highlight those communes where reductions in the cost of schooling 
could see the greatest improvements in primary school attendance rates. </p>

<p>Benin has witnessed almost unparalleled improvements in primary school attendance since 1990, yet 
remains virtually ignored in the literature surveying education outcomes in developing countries. The 
Gross Enrolment Rate (GER), defined as the number of students attending school as a percentage of 
the school age population, soared from around 50% to well over 100% between 1990 and 2012. 
1 By 
2012, the Net Enrolment Rate (NER), defined as the percentage of school age students attending 
school, stood at 95 percent (UIS 2017), well above the average in Sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) of just 
77 percent. However, despite this impressive progress, severe geographical disparities persist in 
Benin's primary school attendance rates. According to the most recent Beninese Demographic and 
Health Survey (DHS) in 2012, there are still communes where less than one third of children attend. 
This study aims to shed light these disparities by assessing the relative importance of demand-(i.e. 
on the part of the student, or their family) and supply-side factors (i.e. availability of school facilities) 
on primary school attendance rates during the 2005-06 school year. 
2 That is to say, I investigate 
whether some communes lag behind others due simply to a lack of schools, or whether other socio-
economic or sociocultural factors at the household level help to explain attendance rates. 
To approach this question, individual-and household-level data from the Beninese DHS is com-
bined with detailed commune-level schooling data from the Beninese Institute for Statistics 
(INSAE). Results from a logistic regression model suggest that household wealth, religion, parental 
education and the supply of schools all predict the likelihood of a child attending school. Further-
more, results also indicate that as average distance to school increases, the likelihood that boys 
who work in the field attend school decreases to a greater extent than those who did not work. </p>

<p>© 2018 UNU-WIDER. Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License (http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. </p>

<p>CONTACT Kyle McNabb 
Mcnabb@wider.unu.edu 
UNU-WIDER United Nations University World Institute for Development 
Economics Research, Katajanokanlaituri 6B, FI-00160 Helsinki, Finland 
Supplemental data for this article can be accessed https://doi.org/10.1080/09645292.2018.1426732. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS, 2018 
https://doi.org/10.1080/09645292.2018.1426732 </p>

<p>This echoes the findings of, for example, Lincove (2012) or Huisman and Smits (2009) and also pre-
sents evidence that distance to school captures the opportunity cost of attending, which is greater 
when time spent travelling replaces potentially-income generating work. There is little evidence to 
suggest that simply living in a rural area, for example, explains lower attendance. 
Whilst a number of existing studies on primary school attendance (e.g. Huisman and Smits 2009) 
have acknowledged that factors at the community, district or national level play an important role in 
explaining school attendance, few have explicitly accounted for such cluster-level interdependence 
in the estimation strategy. Therefore, this study also presents results from a multilevel logistic model, 
which accounts for unobserved heterogeneity between higher level clusters (i.e. at the household 
and commune level), in order to assess the level at which most variation in school attendance 
rates is seen. A three-level random intercepts model shows that there are a large number of commu-
nes with a significantly lower than average primary attendance rate, but that only around 11% of this 
variation is attributable to factors at the commune level. After controlling for both household and 
commune level factors, less than 5% of the variation in attendance is due to commune-level 
factors, suggesting that the majority of the between-commune variation in attendance rates is 
attributable to household-level characteristics. In a similar vein to Delprato and Sabates (2015), a 
random slopes model is also estimated, where the wealth coefficient is allowed to vary between com-
munes. This identifies those communes where attendance is below average, but the effect of house-
hold wealth on school attendance is above average. Such results could potentially be of use to 
policymakers in identifying those areas where interventions that raised household wealth (or 
lowered the cost of schooling) might be most effective in increasing school attendance rates. 
In addition to explaining the regional disparities present in Benin's primary school attendance 
rates, this study also examines differences in attendance by gender. Despite impressive progress 
in reducing the gender gap since 1990, the results presented herein suggest that the factors explain-
ing girls' school attendance differ to those for boys. In particular, adopted girls and those that worked 
(either alongside or in place of attending school) were significantly less likely to attend school, whilst 
these variables were not significant explanatory factors for boys. At the same time, however, the 
results suggest that distance to school was not an important factor in girls' attendance. These 
results are explored further below. 
The broad contributions to the literature are therefore twofold: Firstly, evidence is presented on 
the determinants of primary school attendance for Benin, a context that has not previously been con-
sidered in the empirical literature surrounding primary schooling, but in which vast changes have 
been seen over recent years. Secondly, the use of a multilevel model helps to provide additional 
insights on regional disparities that many similar studies, from other developing countries, neglect 
to consider. 
This study proceeds as follows. Section 2 describes the Beninese context in detail. Section 3 dis-
cusses the theoretical predictions and empirical results surrounding primary school attendance in 
developing countries, with an emphasis on not only the economic rationale, but also the sociocultural 
factors that might dictate whether or not a child is sent to school. In particular, results from similar 
studies in Sub Saharan Africa (SSA) are surveyed. Section 4 presents the variables and methodology 
chosen for this study. Results for the single-level logistic model are presented in section 5, whilst the 
multilevel strategy is outlined and presented in section 6. Section 7 concludes. </p>

<p>2. The Beninese context </p>

<p>Benin provides an intriguing case study in education and development. Along with an economic 
crisis that forced the closure of teacher training colleges and large scale cuts to the civil service in 
the 1980's, the socialist regime's failed attempts at reform (see Allen 1989) left Benin ranking 
amongst the worst performing countries in the world with regards primary school enrolment and 
gender parity; just 51 per cent of all children and less than one in four girls were attending 
primary school in 1990 (UIS 2017); the ODI (2011, 4) describes the education system at this time as </p>

<p>2 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>'deeply dysfunctional and inequitable'. However, the democratically elected government prioritised 
education in 1990 and as a result of systemic reform, Benin has seen almost unparalleled (at least in 
SSA) progress in terms of primary school enrolment rates. 
3 Between 1990 and 2010, average adult 
years of education (Barro and Lee 2013) increased from 2.13 to 4.35 (only Mali saw a greater increase 
in the same period), gross and net enrollment soared and the gender gap was virtually eliminated in 
many regions. In October 2006, primary education was made free for all. Benin also performs well in 
terms of primary school availability. INSAE and Macro International (2007) report that in the 2005-06 
school year -which is studied in detail below -93.7% of households lived within 4 km of a primary 
school; 79.1% lived less than 1 km away. Furthermore, there was relatively little difference between 
rural and urban areas, where 91.9 and 96.2% of households respectively resided within 4 km of the 
nearest primary school. 
Figure 1 plots Benin's progress in net primary school enrolment rates against the average for SSA, 
developing countries and the world -despite missing data for many years, the trend is clear: NERs 
rose from around 40% (52% male, 27% female) in 1990 to 94% (99% male, 88% female) in 2012. </p>

<p>4   Gross primary enrolment rose from 51% to 123% in the same period. Progress in increasing enrol-
ment of girls in primary school has been particularly impressive: The Gender Parity Index (GPI) rose 
from 0.50 in 1990 to 0.89 in 2012 -only Guinea matched this progress in SSA. </p>

<p>5   Yet these figures do not tell the whole story in Benin, as large regional disparities persist at both 
the department and commune level. To examine these, I turn to data from the 2006 wave of the DHS, 
where the ratio presented might best be defined as the Net Primary Attendance Rate as it shows the 
percentage of primary school age children whose parents reported that they were attending primary 
school in 2005-06. Some departments were still struggling with net primary attendance rates of as 
little as 29% (unweighted department average), whilst others saw rates of over 75%. The national 
average was 56%. Figure 2 shows net primary attendance (male and female combined) by 
commune in 2006. </p>

<p>6   It is clear that estimates of the net primary enrolment rate for, e.g. 2006 are somewhat higher than 
the net primary attendance rate. This is likely due to a number of factors. Firstly, measures of enrolment 
might include those children who enroll, but do not subsequently regularly attend school (see e.g. 
Omoeva et al. 2013). Secondly, there is evidence that over-reporting by public officials can lead to 
upward bias in enrolment statistics; Sandefur and Glassman (2015), for example report evidence of 
this in contexts such as Kenya or Rwanda, where pupil fees had been replaced by top-down per 
pupil grants, creating a financial incentive to inflate enrolment numbers. These explanations might 
well go some way to explaining the observed discrepancy between enrolment and attendance in Benin. 
Whilst it is clear that commune-level attendance rates vary widely across the country, there also 
exists significant intra-department variation. Take, for example, the department of Borgou; Net </p>

<p>Figure 1. Net enrolment ratios 1990-2012. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
primary attendance rates in 2006 ranged from just 23% in the commune of Kalale to almost 80% in 
Parakou. Despite the Beninese government's continued prioritisation of access to education, regional 
disparities such as these persist. Indeed, even by 2012 many communes had net primary attendance 
rates close to 90%, but some still lagged behind in the 20-30% range. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Whilst the NER (or in this case, the net primary attendance rate) represents a significantly more 
useful indicator than gross primary enrolment, it still does not tell the whole story; the official defi-
nition (UNESCO 2012) is </p>

<p>The number of children of official primary school age who are enrolled in primary education as a percentage of 
the total children of the official school age population. </p>

<p>It therefore pays no attention to what grade a child is in; an 11-year-old, who is, strictly speaking, of 
school age, having just entered the first grade is counted as enrolled -yet they have arrived in 
primary school some 5 years late. Whilst the empirical analysis here does not specifically consider </p>

<p>Figure 2. Net primary school attendance (%) by commune, 2006. Source: Author's own calculations from the 2006 DHS (Mean = 
56%). </p>

<p>4 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>on-time-enrolment, a look at the age distribution of those attending primary school is nonetheless 
interesting. Figure 3 uses data from two waves of the DHS in order to highlight progress in the 
age distribution of primary school attendance in Benin between the 2005-06 and the 2011-12 
school years. In 2011-12, the mode age of primary school attendees was 9 years old, at which 
over 75 percent of children were attending primary school, compared to 10 years old in 2005-06. 
Some of the most notable improvements come when looking to younger children: the earlier 
survey showed that, for example, just 35% of 6 year olds (the official starting age in Benin) were 
attending primary school in 2005-06; by 2011-12 this had risen to 61%. Thus, in addition to the 
increases in enrolment outlined above, there is also evidence of improvements in on-time 
enrolment. </p>

<p>8   3. Theoretical predictions and empirical evidence </p>

<p>3.1. Demand side </p>

<p>Becker (1975, 45) argues that 'The most important single determinant of the amount invested in 
human capital may well be its profitability or rate of return.' In other words, it makes sense to 
invest in human capital, or in this case send a child to school, if the expected benefits outweigh 
the costs incurred. 
9 Costs, of course, are measured in both direct and indirect terms -the former con-
stitute items such as school fees, books, transport or uniforms, and the latter the opportunity cost of 
attending (Becker 1975). The opportunity cost of attending school is often higher in developing 
countries, where children commonly contribute to total household income through work. Children 
might make a direct contribution to household income, whereby the child works on the farm or in 
the marketplace, or an indirect contribution, where their help around the home or family business 
frees up the time of adults to earn more money (Colclough, Rose, and Tembon 2000). Such 'indirect 
contributions' are particularly pertinent for girls, who are more often required to assist with childcare 
etc. However, working and school attendance are rarely mutually exclusive in developing countries. 
Evidence from Burkina Faso (De Hoop and Rosati 2014), Kenya (Buchmann 2000) and Ethiopia 
(Admassie 2003) suggests that it is commonplace across Africa that children both work and attend 
school. Indeed, de Hoop and Rosati (ibid) found that the amount of time children in Burkina Faso 
spent working or helping with chores did not fall substantially (and in some cases even increased) 
even following the receipt of subsidies that reduced the cost of schooling. However, there is evidence 
that in rural areas, children enrolled at the start of the school year might be pulled out of school in 
order to help with the harvest in autumn Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000). 
Empirical work often proxies cost of schooling with a measure of distance to school; time spent 
travelling to school could be used, for example, to work on the family farm, or help with household </p>

<p>Figure 3. Primary attendance age distribution: 2005-06 vs. 2011-12. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
chores. Lincove (2012) or Huisman and Smits (2009) found distance to school to be inversely related 
with the likelihood of school attendance; Delprato and Sabates (2015), however, found no effects on 
the likelihood of late entry in Nigeria. </p>

<p>10   Turning to the benefits of attending primary school, these might not be immediately clear to 
parents or students in a developing country context. If there is a lack of job market opportunities 
in an area, then there will be a limited expected return to education. Even if opportunities were to 
arise in the future, parents might not reasonably be able to foresee this happening. If a child is 
expected to, for example, work on a family plot of land, then numeracy and literacy skills might 
well be of limited value, at least compared to the physical strength that he or she could have 
been building, which may prove more valuable for his or her future work. Similarly, Colclough,  Rose, and Tembon (2000) highlight that in contexts where gender discrimination exists and the 
gender balance in labour markets is skewed in favour of males, that the benefits of education will 
be lower for girls. Thus, even with equitable access to schooling, there may still be significant chal-
lenges to convince parents of the benefits of educating daughters. 
In developing countries, it is by no means guaranteed that parents will be able to accurately 
measure or estimate the benefits of educating a child. If information on job market opportunities 
is unavailable, education is deemed unnecessary for rural farm labour, or if families live in a commu-
nity where few adults are educated, then parents (especially those who have not attended school 
themselves) are likely to undervalue the benefits. In a context where either the future returns to edu-
cation are unknown, the benefits of education will be undervalued. The costs, whether direct or indir-
ect, are more easily observable. 
Costs and benefits must also be weighed in terms of household wealth, income or expenditures. If 
the costs are small in relation to either of these measures, then it is more likely that parents can afford 
to send their children to school. It is commonplace for household surveys to stratify households into 
wealth quintiles (the DHS, for example, does this via a principal components analysis); empirical 
results often find that the likelihood of attending school increases from the lowest quintile to the 
highest (Huisman and Smits 2009; Kazeem, Jensen, and Stokes 2010), although this is not necessarily 
always the case; e.g. Lincove (2012), found no direct effect of household wealth on primary school 
attendance in Uganda, but did find that the effects of other explanatory variables varied in magni-
tude according to wealth quintile. 
The economic rationale for sending a child to school is, however, just one side of the story: there 
are various sociocultural differences with respect to religion, caste, tradition or tribe that might inter-
link with economic decisions to dictate the norms followed by parents with regard to education. 
Indeed, it is probable that these factors might be driven more by norms at the community or 
state level, than at the household level (Delprato and Sabates 2015). In societies where patriarchal 
norms persist, parents may place a higher value on the education of boys over girls. This often 
stems from the lack of social security or pension system, meaning that male children are expected 
to provide for their parents in old age; concurrently, it is common that daughters join their husband's 
family at marriage (Colclough, Rose, and Tembon 2000; Huisman and Smits 2009), and thus their own 
parents will realise no financial reward to their education. However, the findings of Eloundou-
Enyegye and Calvès (2006) provide a challenge to this traditional viewpoint: their study suggests 
that in some contexts, married women often remitted to their own families (e.g. in Cameroon) and 
that their capacity to do so actually increased, the more educated they were. Their study also 
notes the significant control that women in West Africa, and Benin in particular, have over their 
own earnings. 
11 A further disadvantage for girls arises if the nearest school is quite far away; it 
might be that they are not allowed to attend until they are slightly older, due to the perceived 
dangers of walking alone, or physical effort of walking a long distance. 
Religion also plays a significant role in the likelihood of children, specifically girls, being sent to 
school. Csapo (1981) cites the distrust of Western education by Muslims or the more traditional 
Islamic views on the education of women, as outlined in the Qur'an, as potential barriers to education 
for girls in Nigeria. Lincove (2015) found that Muslim children in Nigeria were, on average, 23% less </p>

<p>6 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>likely to attend school -but the effect was more than double for girls (31%) than for boys (15%), a 
finding echoed by Kazeem, Jensen, and Stokes (2010) who found the same result for Nigeria, 
although the order of magnitude is dramatically larger -their regressions suggest that Muslim chil-
dren were five times less likely to attend school than Christians. Lincove (2012), however, found no 
effect of being a Muslim on primary school attendance in Uganda and Buchmann (2000)'s regression 
results found that Muslim children were no less likely to attend school than their Christian counter-
parts in Kenya. So, whilst theory predicts that different religions or traditions might place different 
importance on schooling, the empirical evidence for SSA is mixed. 
The education level of parents is also an important consideration: it is highly probable that if 
parents have attended school themselves, and benefitted from the education received, that they 
would be more likely to send their own children to school. In terms of the economic rationale, this 
might allow the parent to better appreciate and estimate the benefits of education for their own 
child; this may be particularly true for girls if their mother has attained a certain level of education. </p>

<p>12   Various household or family level factors such as household size, birth order, whether or not a child 
is adopted, etc. might also be considered as explanatory factors with regards a child's likelihood of 
attending school. In terms of economic rationale, a larger number of children increases competition 
for limited household resources (Lincove 2015). As a result, it might be that children with more sib-
lings cannot attend school as they are required to complete more tasks at home in order to contrib-
ute to household income and the direct costs of sending many children to school are obviously 
higher. At the same time however, a larger number of children might increase the likelihood that 
any one child can attend school as there are more hands to work and contribute to overall household 
income. Thus, the direction of this effect is, ex ante, unclear. Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000) pre-
sents evidence that in Ethiopia, the average number of children in a household was higher for school 
attendees than for dropouts; Glick and Sahn (2006) found that as the number of children in a house-
hold increased, there was no impact on the likelihood that a child would attend a public primary 
school in Madagascar, although it did decrease the likelihood of a child attending private school. 
Similarly, Lincove (2015) found no effect of the number of children in a household in Uganda and 
only marginally significant effects for girls in Nigeria. </p>

<p>3.2. Supply side </p>

<p>The above discussion has highlighted that numerous factors interlink to dictate whether or not a child 
will be sent to school by his or her parents. However, considering only factors on the demand side 
ignores many of the considerations that a parent might make. Including estimates of the supply of 
schooling is crucial to avoid omitted variable bias when carrying out empirical analyses of school attend-
ance. Often, however, institutional data for the total number of schools, pupil teacher ratios (PTR) etc., is 
only available at the national or regional level, making consolidation with survey data at the community 
or village very level difficult. As a result, many studies fail to accurately account for the supply of school-
ing. 
13 School quality is often measured by the PTR, although this variable is clearly endogenous in 
regressions where the dependent variable is school attendance rates. Other variables that have been 
used to represent school quality include the percentage of teachers who are qualified (e.g. Lavy 
1996; Huisman and Smits 2009), percentage of teachers who are female (often considered key in 
explaining girls' participation in education e.g. Glick 2008; Huisman and Smits 2009) the use of multi-
grade teaching (Glick and Sahn 2006) and the condition of classrooms etc. However, the effect of 
these variables on primary school attendance is mixed and it is not unreasonable to argue that some 
of these measures might matter more for explaining school achievement than attendance. </p>

<p>4. Data and methodology </p>

<p>Whilst geographical variation in primary attendance rates is explored in detail below in the form of a 
multilevel model, a simple logistic regression is presented first. The advantage of doing this lies in the </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
ability to compute average marginal effects which allow us to gain an understanding of the relative 
magnitudes of the covariates considered. The single level logit regression estimated takes the follow-
ing form </p>

<p>ln 
p i 
1 − p i 
= b 0i + b 1 S i + b 2 H i + b 2 C i + e i 
(1) </p>

<p>where the dependent variable is a dummy equal to 1 if child i was of official primary school age and 
attended school during the 2005-06 school year. S is the vector of student-level characteristics; H the 
vector of household level characteristics and the vector C contains commune-level characteristics. 
The dependent variable used in the empirical analysis is a dummy variable equal to 1 if a child of 
primary school age was attending primary school in 2005-06 Interviewees were asked 'During the 
2005-06 school year, which ended in June 2006, did (name) attend school at some point' (Author 
translation from French original in INSAE and Macro International 2007, 370). 
14 The 2006 DHS for 
Benin took place between the 3rd of August and 18th November 2006. It should be noted that 
there was a policy change in mid-October 2006, whereby the elimination of school fees was com-
pleted in all regions. However, this is unlikely to impact upon the analysis here, as the question per-
tains to the school year ending in June 2006. 
The DHS data is stratified as follows: </p>

<p>Benin 
↓ 
Departments (12) 
↓ 
Communes (77) 
↓ 
'Clusters' (Primary Sampling Unit [PSU]) (750) 
↓ 
Households (17,511) 
↓ 
Individuals (90,650) </p>

<p>↓ 
↓ </p>

<p>Not School Age (73,556) School Age (17,094)   Of the 90,650 individuals, 17,094 were of school age. Of these, 57% were attending primary school. 
Control variables are included at the individual, household and commune level; Table 1 presents 
summary statistics of these. Just under half of the sample was female (48%), 3.5% were adopted 
and it appears common that children of school age also work; some 73% did so. 
15 With regard to 
those children who were adopted, the definition reveals that they are in 'foster care' and not 
related to any other household member; 89% of their mothers and 77% of their fathers were still 
known to be alive; fewer than 4% had lost both parents. It is thus difficult to speculate on the 
reasons for adoption, but one reason could be due to infertility of adoptive parents: DHS (2004b), 
suggests that in Benin, 61% of primarily sterile women reside in a household with at least one 
adopted child (compared to 38% of primarily fertile women), the highest in the sample of 48 devel-
oping countries considered. Indeed, in the West African region, the study found that more than half 
of childless couples lived in a household with an adopted child. An alternative explanation is that chil-
dren are adopted principally to help out with work around the house. Adopted girls, for example, 
were more likely to carry out domestic work (78%) than biological daughters (64%) and less likely 
to attend primary school conditional on also carrying out this type of work (29% v 58% for adoptees 
and biological daughters respectively). There was no significant difference between adopted sons 
and biological sons in terms of work (70% and 71% did, respectively). 
Turning to the household level variables, a set of dummy variables is included in order to control 
for the household head's religion, the DHS wealth index (a composite index constructed using prin-
cipal components analysis ranking households from 1 ['Poorest'] to 5 ['Richest']) and the education 
level of the household head (a set of dummy variables for none, primary, secondary or tertiary). </p>

<p>16   One quarter of households were Catholic, 26% Islamic and 21% Vodoun. Around 65% of household </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>heads had no formal education whatsoever; of the remainder that did attend school, 21% had 
primary, 13% had secondary and the remaining 2% had a university education. Whilst ideally the 
child's mother or father's education level would be included in the analysis here (as the head is 
not always the parent of the children included in the sample), it was not possible to identify the 
parent of each child from the 2006 Beninese DHS due to missing data. School Essential is a 
dummy variable taking the value equal to one if the respondent answered yes to the survey question 
'Do you need to be able to send children to school'. 
17 This variable captures household stated pre-
ferences for education -some 79% of households considered school to be essential. Parents who 
undervalue education (even if they themselves have gone to school) might be less likely to 
educate their own children. The average household size was just over 8 and this ranged from 2 to 
36. Also included is a dummy variable equal to one if the child resided in a rural area (64% did so). 
At the commune level, controls are included for the average distance to school and the (log) 
number of schools per school-age children in each commune. 
18 To construct a measure of 
average distance to school, I follow Huisman and Smits (2009) as follows </p>

<p>Avg Distance = </p>

<p>km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>No of Schools 
p 
(2) </p>

<p>One unavoidable weakness of this approach lies with those children who reside close to the border of 
one commune, but might attend a school situated in another. However, this is perhaps the best 
approximation available, given the data on hand. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary statistics. </p>

<p>Variable 
Mean 
Std. Dev. 
Min 
Max </p>

<p>Net attendance 2005-06 
0.570 
0.495 
0 
1 
Individual level 
Female 
0.475 
0.499 
0 
1 
Adopted 
0.035 
0.183 
0 
1 
Worked 
0.729 
0.444 
0 
1 
Worked in the field 
0.318 
0.444 
0 
1 
Domestic Work 
0.367 
0.482 
0 
1 
Other 
0.044 
0.206 
0 
1 
Household level 
Household religion 
Christian </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.432 
0.495 
0 
1 
Islam 
0.256 
0.437 
0 
1 
Traditional / Other 
0.312 
0.463 
0 
1 
Household wealth 
Poorest 
0.222 
0.416 
0 
1 
Poorer 
0.220 
0.414 
0 
1 
Middle 
0.205 
0.404 
0 
1 
Richer 
0.193 
0.395 
0 
1 
Richest 
0.160 
0.366 
0 
1 
Household head education level 
Primary 
0.214 
0.410 
0 
1 
Secondary 
0.130 
0.337 
0 
1 
Higher 
0.018 
0.132 
0 
1 
School considered essential? 
0.790 
0.407 
0 
1 
Household size 
8.174 
4.104 
2 
36 
Rural 
0.639 
0.480 
0 
1 
Commune level 
Distance to school 
1.279 
0.971 
0.134 
5.399 
(log) Schools per 5-14 year olds 
−5.977 
0.238 
−6.577 
−5.471 
Observations: 17,094 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Christian includes 'Catholic', 'Protestant', 'Celeste' and 'Other Christian'. Traditional/Other includes the cat-
egories 'Vodoun', 'Other Traditional', 'Other Religion' and 'No Religion'. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
5. Results </p>

<p>Table 2 presents benchmark results for equation (1). In all following tables, the dependent variable is 
as outlined above. It can be considered a close approximation to the NER, although is again perhaps 
best defined as a net primary attendance rate. The Log-odds ratio is shown, along with average mar-
ginal effects (the latter in square brackets). 
20 Both are included, as the log odds are more comparable 
with the multilevel results later (as it is not possible to obtain marginal effects following that pro-
cedure) whilst the marginal effects are somewhat more intuitive and help to give a sense of the mag-
nitude of the effects of the covariates. 
21 Column 1 includes the entire sample, whilst columns 2 and 3 
perform the same regression for boys and girls respectively. Looking first at the individual level 
factors, the likelihood of attending primary school is significantly lower for girls than it is for boys: 
this is in line with expectations, given the considerable gender disparities that exist(ed) in enrolment 
at primary school for Benin's young girls. 
Specifically, the results suggest that girls aged 6-11 were around 9% less likely to attend primary 
school than are boys. Age and its square suggest a non-linear relationship with the dependent vari-
able, reflecting the pattern outlined in Figure 3 above. The results also suggest that adopted children 
are less likely to attend school than those related to the family; in a context where income might be 
low it is understandable that households might give preference to the education of biological chil-
dren. Interestingly, however, column three highlights that the significance of this variable comes 
entirely from girls who are around 20% less likely to be enrolled in school than a biological daughter; 
adopted sons appear to face no such disadvantage compared to biological ones. Further inquiry 
showed that of four types of child (biological son, biological daughter, adopted son and adopted 
daughter), adopted daughters were the least likely of any to attend school, even when compared 
to adopted sons. 
22 An alternative way to frame this inquiry is to include an interaction term 
( female * adopted) in the full sample. When tested, this yielded an identical result, with a similar mar-
ginal effect (0.19). Lincove (2012) found a similar result in Uganda, however her results actually 
showed a larger impact for fostered boys than fostered girls -the opposite of what is presented 
here, whilst Huisman and Smits (2009) found an overall negative effect on the likelihood of foster 
children attending school in their panel of 30 developing countries. Worked is a dummy variable 
equal to 1 if children in the sample carried out any kind of work alongside studying. Again, girls 
appear to be at a disadvantage compared to boys, with the likelihood of being in school 5% lower 
for those girls who worked, compared to those who did not. 
23 This is explored in more detail below. 
Turning to the household's religion, the results suggest that children of Islamic households were 
around 7% less likely to be sent to school than those from Christian homes (the reference category). </p>

<p>24   Those of parents following traditional / other religion were about 4% less likely to attend. The DHS 
surveys also inquired as to the ethnicity of individuals, however this was often closely correlated 
to religion and did not provide any additional insights when tested in the model (not shown). It is 
clear that as household wealth increases, so too does the likelihood that children attend primary 
school. For instance, those in the lowest wealth quintile were some 29% less likely to attend 
school than those in the richest (the reference category). This echoes results in studies such as 
Huisman and Smits (2009), or Delprato and Sabates (2015) (Nigeria), which also found an increasing 
likelihood of school attendance as household wealth level increased, although Lincove (2012) found 
no effects of household wealth on primary school attendance in Uganda. The effects of household 
wealth again suggest some difference by gender: girls from the poorest households face a slightly 
lower disadvantage to boys, compared to the upper quintile, perhaps a reflection of the higher 
value placed on boys' work. This is explored in more detail below. Similarly, household heads that 
had attended primary or secondary school were more likely to send their own children to primary 
school than those with no education (the reference category); there is little difference here by 
gender. Obviously, it might be the case that richer families are often more educated, or it might 
be the case that Christian families are more likely to be wealthier (reside in wealthier regions, etc.). 
In order to investigate, Tables 3 and 4 display the predictive margins of being in a Christian home </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>Table 2. Determinants of primary school attendance, logit estimation. </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
All 
Boys 
Girls 
All 
All 
All 
All 
Boys 
Girls 
Female 
−0.446*** 
−0.444*** 
−0.444*** 
−0.444*** 
−0.444*** 
(0.055) 
(0.055) 
(0.055) 
(0.056) 
(0.056) 
[−0.088***] 
[−0.088***] 
[−0.088***] 
[−0.088***] 
[−0.088***] 
Age 
2.440*** 
2.650*** 
2.259*** 
2.441*** 
2.440*** 
2.437*** 
2.436*** 
2.650*** 
2.259*** 
(0.116) 
(0.148) 
(0.167) 
(0.115) 
(0.115) 
(0.116) 
(0.116) 
(0.146) 
(0.165) 
[0.481***] 
[0.490***] 
[0.469***] 
[0.484***] 
[0.481***] 
[0.481***] 
[0.481***] 
[0.491***] 
[0.471***] 
Age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>−0.128*** 
−0.137*** 
−0.120*** 
−0.128*** 
−0.128*** 
−0.128*** 
−0.128*** 
−0.137*** 
−0.120*** 
(0.007) 
(0.009) 
(0.010) 
(0.007) 
(0.007) 
(0.007) 
(0.007) 
(0.009) 
(0.010) 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
[−0.025***] 
Adopted 
−0.681*** 
−0.086 
−0.980*** 
−0.674*** 
−0.675*** 
−0.689*** 
−0.690*** 
−0.095 
−0.978*** 
(0.182) 
(0.178) 
(0.214) 
(0.183) 
(0.184) 
(0.180) 
(0.180) 
(0.178) 
(0.216) 
[−0.134***] 
[−0.016] 
[−0.203***] 
[−0.134***] 
[−0.135***] 
[−0.136***] 
[−0.136***] 
[−0.018] 
[−0.204***] 
Worked 
−0.117 
0.0163 
−0.230*** 
−0.122 
−0.121 
−0.125 
−0.122 
0.451*** 
−0.122 
(0.080) 
(0.091) 
(0.089) 
(0.079) 
(0.079) 
(0.079) 
(0.079) 
(0.134) 
(0.178) 
[−0.023] 
[0.003] 
[−0.048***] 
[−0.024] 
[−0.023] 
[−0.025] 
[−0.024] 
[0.084***] 
[−0.026] 
Household size 
−0.015** 
−0.018** 
−0.013 
−0.017*** 
−0.017*** 
−0.016** 
−0.016** 
−0.019*** 
−0.016* 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.008) 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.007) 
(0.009) 
[−0.003**] 
[−0.003**] 
[−0.003] 
[−0.003***] 
[−0.003**] 
[−0.003**] 
[−0.003**] 
[−0.004***] 
[−0.003*] 
Religion 
Islam 
−0.369*** 
−0.480*** 
−0.273** 
−0.391*** 
−0.389*** 
−0.426*** 
−0.429*** 
−0.515*** 
−0.290** 
(0.100) 
(0.117) 
(0.111) 
(0.109) 
(0.109) 
(0.0957) 
(0.0947) 
(0.124) 
(0.122) 
[−0.073***] 
[−0.089***] 
[−0.057**] 
[−0.078***] 
[−0.072***] 
[−0.084***] 
[−0.085***] 
[−0.095***] 
[−0.061**] 
Traditional / Other 
−0.205*** 
−0.247*** 
−0.183** 
−0.192*** 
−0.194*** 
−0.188*** 
−0.190*** 
−0.253*** 
−0.175** 
(0.054) 
(0.070) 
(0.074) 
(0.059) 
(0.059) 
(0.056) 
(0.057) 
(0.075) 
(0.079) 
[0.040***] 
[0.046***] 
[0.038**] 
[0.038***] 
[0.041***] 
[0.037***] 
[0.038***] 
[0.047***] 
[0.037**] 
Household wealth level 
Poorest 
−1.453*** 
−1.708*** 
−1.364*** 
−1.450*** 
−1.465*** 
−1.509*** 
−1.524*** 
−1.710*** 
−1.363*** 
(0.101) 
(0.125) 
(0.129) 
(0.103) 
(0.098) 
(0.099) 
(0.099) 
(0.123) 
(0.128) 
[−0.287***] 
[−0.316***] 
[−0.283***] 
[−0.288***] 
[−0.291***] 
[−0.298***] 
[−0.301***] 
[−0.317***] 
[−0.284***] 
Poorer 
−1.001*** 
−1.335*** 
−0.821*** 
−1.018*** 
−1.035*** 
−1.042*** 
−1.057*** 
−1.365*** 
−0.846*** 
(0.087) 
(0.116) 
(0.099) 
(0.090) 
(0.086) 
(0.085) 
(0.084) 
(0.116) 
(0.103) 
[−0.197***] 
[−0.247***] 
[−0.171***] 
[−0.202***] 
[−0.202***] 
[−0.206***] 
[−0.209***] 
[−0.253***] 
[−0.176***] 
Middle 
−0.543*** 
−0.916*** 
−0.323*** 
−0.559*** 
−0.575*** 
−0.580*** 
−0.594*** 
−0.931*** 
−0.353*** 
(0.075) 
(0.115) 
(0.090) 
(0.083) 
(0.075) 
(0.074) 
(0.073) 
(0.111) 
(0.097) 
[−0.107***] 
[−0.169***] 
[−0.067***] 
[−0.111***] 
[−0.111***] 
[−0.115***] 
[−0.117***] 
[−0.172***] 
[−0.074***] 
Richer 
−0.159* 
−0.499*** 
0.022 
−0.171* 
−0.183** 
−0.183** 
−0.193** 
−0.515*** 
−0.001 
(0.084) 
(0.117) 
(0.092) 
(0.091) 
(0.084) 
(0.080) 
(0.080) 
(0.114) 
(0.100) 
[−0.031*] 
[−0.092***] 
[0.005] 
[−0.034*] 
[−0.035**] 
[−0.036**] 
[−0.038**] 
[−0.0954***] 
[−0.000] </p>

<p>(Continued ) </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>



<p>Table 2. Continued. </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
All 
Boys 
Girls 
All 
All 
All 
All 
Boys 
Girls </p>

<p>Household head's education 
Primary 
0.362*** 
0.337*** 
0.372*** 
0.386*** 
0.386*** 
0.366*** 
0.364*** 
0.359*** 
0.399*** 
(0.057) 
(0.084) 
(0.075) 
(0.055) 
(0.055) 
(0.057) 
(0.057) 
(0.082) 
(0.073) 
[0.073***] 
[0.064***] 
[0.080***] 
[0.079***] 
[0.073***] 
[0.074***] 
[0.074***] 
[0.068***] 
[0.086***] 
Secondary 
0.658*** 
0.684*** 
0.642*** 
0.673*** 
0.675*** 
0.659*** 
0.660*** 
0.697*** 
0.654*** 
(0.068) 
(0.096) 
(0.086) 
(0.069) 
(0.068) 
(0.067) 
(0.067) 
(0.100) 
(0.085) 
[0.130***] 
[0.125***] 
[0.136***] 
[0.134***] 
[0.131***] 
[0.131***] 
[0.131***] 
[0.128***] 
[0.139***] 
Tertiary 
0.347* 
0.964*** 
0.200 
0.354* 
0.361* 
0.359* 
0.362* 
1.039*** 
0.210 
(0.206) 
(0.236) 
(0.266) 
(0.199) 
(0.202) 
(0.206) 
(0.205) 
(0.237) 
(0.257) 
[0.071*] 
[0.170***] 
[0.043] 
[0.072*] 
[0.073*] 
[0.073*] 
[0.074*] 
[0.182***] 
[0.045] 
School considered essential? 
0.039 
0.022 
0.061 
0.085 
0.083 
0.049 
0.052 
0.051 
0.104 
(0.075) 
(0.086) 
(0.097) 
(0.070) 
(0.069) 
(0.076) 
(0.077) 
(0.080) 
(0.095) 
[0.008] 
[0.004] 
[0.013] 
[0.017] 
[0.007] 
[0.010] 
[0.010] 
[0.009] 
[0.022] 
Rural 
−0.104 
−0.161** 
−0.0671 
−0.119* 
−0.055 
−0.104 
1.655 
−0.182** 
−0.080 
(0.065) 
(0.079) 
(0.076) 
(0.070) 
(0.131) 
(0.064) 
(1.374) 
(0.082) 
(0.080) 
[−0.021] 
[−0.030**] 
[−0.014] 
[−0.024*] 
[−0.003] 
[−0.021] 
[0.327] 
[−0.034**] 
[−0.017] 
Distance to school 
−0.083 
−0.174*** 
0.007 
−0.172*** 
−0.143** 
−0.014 
−0.013 
(0.053) 
(0.058) 
(0.063) 
(0.052) 
(0.067) 
(0.072) 
(0.082) 
[−0.016] 
[−0.032***] 
[0.002] 
[−0.034***] 
[−0.008] 
[−0.003] 
[−0.003] 
ln Schools per 5-14 year olds 
0.806*** 
0.825*** 
0.795*** 
0.923*** 
0.717*** 
(0.225) 
(0.224) 
(0.271) 
(0.202) 
(0.229) 
[0.159***] 
[0.152***] 
[0.165***] 
[0.182***] 
[0.142***] 
Rural*distance 
−0.046 
(0.074) 
[−0.013] 
Rural*ln schools per 5-14 year olds 
0.294 
(0.229) 
[0.058] 
Worked*distance 
−0.345*** 
−0.088 
(0.072) 
(0.101) 
[−0.064***] 
[−0.018] 
Constant 
−4.845*** 
−5.498*** 
−4.572*** 
−9.539*** 
−9.558*** 
−4.169*** 
−5.382*** 
−10.590*** 
−9.269*** 
(1.443) 
(1.503) 
(1.738) 
(0.485) 
(0.490) 
(1.318) 
(1.452) 
(0.631) 
(0.685) 
Observations 
17,094 
8969 
8125 
17,094 
17,094 
17,094 
17,094 
8969 
8125 
Standard errors, clustered at the commune level, in parentheses. *p &lt; 0.1; **p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.01; Log odds shown. Average Marginal Effects shown in square brackets. 
Controls for the survey month included but not shown. </p>



<p>K. MCNABB </p>

<p>by wealth level and the predictive margins of having a more educated household head by wealth 
level respectively. 
It is clear that, holding wealth level constant, household religion and household head's education still 
have an impact on the likelihood of a child attending school. In particular, children of Christian parents 
are consistently around 5-6% more likely to attend school, regardless of household wealth level. 
Turning to Table 4, again it is clear that holding wealth constant, the likelihood that a child is sent to 
school is greater for those household heads with primary, compared to no, education and greater for 
those with secondary compared to primary education. Interestingly, holding wealth level fixed, the 
household head having a tertiary education does not increase the probability that a child will attend 
school compared to a secondary level education. Potential explanations for this finding are (i) Secondary 
education may be sufficient for a household head to obtain a job that pays well enough to cover the 
costs (both direct and indirect) of schooling so that most or all children in their household can 
attend, or (ii) Anyone capable of completing secondary school already fully understands the benefits 
of sending a child to at least primary school; it does not require a tertiary education to appreciate this. </p>

<p>25   Looking at the commune-averaged variables in Table 2, male children in rural areas are less likely 
to be enrolled than males in urban areas; it also seems that distance to school matters only for boys. 
This result emerges in direct conflict to the thinking that parents will be less likely to send their female 
children to school because of the long distance to walk, fear of attack etc. The supply of schools is 
however important -the variable Schools per 5-14 year olds reflects the number of schools in a </p>

<p>Table 3. Predictive margins of religion, by household wealth level. </p>

<p>Wealth level 
Christian 
Predictive margin </p>

<p>Poorest 
No 
0.394 
Yes 
0.455 
Poorer 
No 
0.489 
Yes 
0.551 
Middle 
No 
0.585 
Yes 
0.644 
Richer 
No 
0.655 
Yes 
0.710 
Richest 
No 
0.675 
Yes 
0.728 </p>

<p>Table 4. Predictive margins of household head's education, by household wealth level. </p>

<p>Wealth level 
Head education 
Predictive margin </p>

<p>Poorest 
None 
0.383 
Primary 
0.464 
Secondary 
0.528 
Tertiary 
0.446 
Poorer 
None 
0.478 
Primary 
0.561 
Secondary 
0.623 
Tertiary 
0.543 
Middle 
None 
0.575 
Primary 
0.655 
Secondary 
0.710 
Tertiary 
0.637 
Richer 
None 
0.647 
Primary 
0.720 
Secondary 
0.769 
Tertiary 
0.704 
Richest 
None 
0.667 
Primary 
0.738 
Secondary 
0.785 
Tertiary 
0.723 </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
given commune, divided by the population aged 5-14 years. The positive and significant coefficient 
on this variable for children of both genders suggests that having controlled for demand-side factors, 
school availability also matters for primary attendance rates. However, these results warrant closer 
inspection; due to the relatively high correlation between average distance to school and number 
of schools (−0.57), the effects of these variables are examined in isolation. The results in columns 
4 and 6 suggest that both distance and the number of schools respectively appear to affect the like-
lihood that a child is enrolled. However, when interacted with the rural dummy (columns 5 and 7), it 
appears that neither distance to school nor the number of schools have a stronger effect in rural 
areas, although the signs are in the expected direction. 
As a further check on the role of distance to school, columns 8 and 9 investigate the extent to 
which this variable can shed light on the opportunity cost of primary school attendance by subdivid-
ing the sample by gender and examining the interaction of distance to school and whether or not a 
child worked. 
26 There is no significant effect of distance on girls' attendance if they worked (column 
9), however the result for boys presents evidence that the distance to school is an important concern 
for those that worked alongside studying (column 8). The negative and significant coefficient on the 
interaction term suggests that boys who worked alongside studying were even less likely to attend a 
school the further away it was, compared to those who did not work. This lends supports to the 
hypothesis that the opportunity cost of schooling is taken into account when deciding whether or 
not to send a child to school. Indeed, it suggests that the opportunity cost of sending boys to 
school was higher than girls. 
Table 5 investigates the role of work further, examining the effect of distance to school on the like-
lihood that a child attends school, according to gender and the type of work carried out. The sample 
is subdivided by those who 'worked in the field' and those carrying out 'domestic work'. 
27 The results 
show that those working in the field faced the greatest opportunity cost to attending school; an 
increase in average distance to school of 1 km reduced the likelihood that boys (girls) would 
attend by around 8% (4%). We also see that distance is a significant determinant of primary 
school attendance for boys who carried out domestic work, but not girls. A number of explanations 
for the differences observed between genders might be considered: Firstly, boys' labour, or the 
nature of their labour, may contribute more to family income than girls' and so the opportunity 
costs of travel time are more heavily felt. Indeed, of those children carrying out 'work in the field', 
68% were boys; conversely, only 37% of children that carried out 'domestic work' were boys. The sig-
nificant coefficient on distance for those boys carrying out domestic work suggests that the nature of 
this work might differ between genders -and that the domestic tasks carried out by boys was more 
valuable to the household. Secondly, the climate in Benin at that time, of promoting primary school 
enrolment for all, might have seen parents under pressure to (be seen to) send daughters to school, 
so even those required to work were encouraged to attend to a greater extent than were sons. This 
result complements the findings of, for example, Colclough, Rose, and Tembon (2000) who found 
that boys in both Guinea and Ethiopia that had dropped out of school did so primarily to earn 
money. Although, Buchmann (2000) found that from a sample of 146 children who had dropped 
out of school in Kenya, only one did so for employment and one to help in the household. </p>

<p>Table 5. Effect of distance to school, by gender and work status. </p>

<p>Gender 
Boys 
Girls </p>

<p>Work status 
No 
Yes 
No 
Yes </p>

<p>Type of work 
n/a 
All 
Field 
Domestic 
n/a 
All 
Field 
Domestic 
Distance to school 
−0.072 
−0.325*** 
−0.390*** 
−0.299*** 
−0.044 
−0.088 
−0.214** 
−0.098 
(0.090) 
(0.065) 
(0.081) 
(0.091) 
(0.083) 
(0.065) 
(0.098) 
(0.076) 
[−0.012] 
[−0.062***] 
[−0.079***] 
[0.044***] 
[−0.009] 
[0.019] 
[−0.044**] 
[−0.019] 
Observations 
2562 
6407 
3708 
2302 
2063 
6062 
1738 
3941 
The model estimated here contains all covariates as in Column 4 of Table 2, but only the distance to school variable is shown. Stan-
dard errors, clustered at the commune level, in parentheses. *p &lt; 0.1; **p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.01; Log odds shown. Average Marginal 
Effects shown in square brackets. </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>5.1. Testing an alternative dependent variable </p>

<p>Whilst the dependent variable used above adheres closely to a measure of net primary attendance in 
Benin, it is not a perfect barometer of primary school attendance. Figure 3 showed that many children 
in primary school in 2005-06 fell outside the official age category of 6-11. Furthermore, related 
studies in this field have imposed different criteria for classifying primary school attendance status: 
Huisman and Smits (2009) consider only those aged 8-11 in a panel of 30 countries; Lincove  (2015), those aged 6-13 in Nigeria and Uganda (although crucially, omit any children that had 
already progressed to secondary school); Buchmann (2000) those aged 13-18 in Kenya; Lincove  (2012), those aged 6-12 years old in Uganda. To the best of my knowledge, only Deininger (2003)  provides estimates for a number of alternative age ranges (Uganda). 
Whilst some of this disparity in the choice of dependent variable naturally results from differ-
ent official starting ages and length of school cycles in each country, it can hamper the compar-
ability of results across studies and across countries. An appealing approach is outlined in 
Omoeva et al. (2013), who argue in favour of classing the school age as between 7 and 14 
years old and abandoning the arbitrary definitions of 'primary' or 'secondary'. These bounds 
are influenced by the fact that ' … in all countries, compulsory education begins by age 7 or 
earlier' and ' … the ILO minimum age convention establishes age 15 as the minimum legal age 
for entering any form of employment … ' (Omoeva et al. 2013, 48). As a result, any child falling 
within this age bracket should be expected to be in school. To follow this definition for the Beni-
nese sample would lead to the loss of those children aged 5 or 6 who are, by all accounts, of 
school age. However, by extending the upper age range of the sample to 14, the analysis can 
account for many more children attending, or who have completed, primary school. In the robust-
ness checks included in Appendix A, the dependent variable is thus a dummy equal to 1 if (i) a 
child is aged between 5 and 14 and (ii) (s)he is in, or has completed, primary school. 
28 All of 
the previously reported results hold using this alternative dependent variable; the only differ-
ences arising are small changes in the magnitude of certain independent variables. </p>

<p>6. A multilevel approach </p>

<p>The results in section 5 have highlighted that factors on both the demand and supply side were 
important determinants of primary school attendance in Benin in the 2005-06 school year. As 
shown in section 2, stark regional disparities exist Benin with regards to primary school attend-
ance rates. Whilst a number of studies acknowledge that factors at the household, community 
or district level might impact on school attendance in SSA (for example Lavy [1996]; Handa  [2002] or Huisman and Smits [2009]), only Delprato and Sabates (2015) have explicitly modelled 
this econometrically by taking account of unobserved heterogeneity between higher level clus-
ters. However, their study focused on late entry as opposed to primary attendance. The conse-
quence for the econometric analysis of ignoring this is a violation of the assumption that 
observations are independent from one another; unobserved heterogeneity at higher levels 
leads to cluster-level interdependence between units (Skrondal and Rabe-Hesketh 2004). The 
traditional approach to dealing with such data is to turn to a multilevel (or hierarchical) 
linear model (MLM) (HLM), the simplest of which is the random-intercepts or variance com-
ponents model which estimates a random intercept for every higher-level unit, such as 
commune or department etc. </p>

<p>6.1. Random intercepts model </p>

<p>After testing various multilevel structures, it turned out that whilst all performed better than the 
single level model above, a three-level model, as estimated below, was preferred to any two-level 
model. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
The basic variance components model takes the form </p>

<p>ln 
p ijkl 
1 − p ijkl 
= b 0 + m k + w jk + 1 ijk 
(3) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>m k N(0, s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m ) 
w jk N(0, s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>w ) 
1 ijk N(0, s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 ) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>ln 
p ijk 
1 − p ijk 
is the log-odds that child i in household j in commune k is attending school. b 0 is the </p>

<p>intercept shared by all individuals, households and communes. m k is the effect of commune k, w jk . 
The effect of household j and 1 ijk is the child level residual error. 
The models here are computedsing second-order penalized quasi-likelihood (PQL2) in MLwiN 
(Rasbash et al. 2015) via the Stata module runmlwin (Leckie and Charlton 2013). When selecting 
the appropriate means by which to estimate multilevel equations, it is necessary to choose a 
method at is both the most unbiased, but also computationally feasible. Simulations in Rodriguez  and Goldman (2001) show that 2nd order Penalised Quasi Likelihood (PQL) estimation provided 
the closest approximation to maximum likelihood estimation (MLE), out of the choice of 1st and 
2nd order marginal quasi-likelihood (MQL) and 1st and 2nd order PQL. Whilst, ideally, MLE would 
be used to obtain all the estimates, this is computationally very intensive for models beyond the 
null; <rs type="software">Stata</rs>'s commands such as xtmelogit often take many hours or days to converge, if at all. Appen-
dix B displays estimates of the variance of the random effects in equation (3) using MQL1, MQL2, 
PQL1, PQL2 and MLE; Whilst there is still a downward bias in the estimates of s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m and s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>w compared 
to MLE, PQL2 performs substantially better than the other quasi-likelihood estimators. Given that MLE 
estimates for models beyond the null are computationally very difficult to obtain, PQL2 is the pre-
ferred method here. 
Column 1 of Table 6 displays results from the random intercepts model, as per equation (3). Odds 
ratios are displayed; it is not possible to compute marginal effects for multilevel models. The estimate 
of b 0 suggests that the log-odds of a child of school age attending primary school in an 'average' 
household / commune is 0.32. 
In order to examine and interpret each of the variance components outlined above in [4], a var-
iance partition coefficient (VPC) can be calculated which, for the model estimated in column (1) of 
Table 6, ' … report[s] the proportion of the observed variance at each level of the model hierarchy' 
(Leckie 2013, 21) Thus the VPC provides an indication of those levels at which most residual variation 
in the likelihood of attending school exists. The discussion in section 2 has already highlighted the 
significant inter-commune disparity in primary school attendance rates, so the expectation is that 
a significant amount of variation will exist at this level. The VPC's are calculated for the commune 
and household respectively, as follows: </p>

<p>VPC m = 
s </p>

<p>2 
m </p>

<p>s 2 
m + s 2 
w + s 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>VPC w = 
s </p>

<p>2 
w </p>

<p>s 2 
m + s 2 
w + s 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>In the case of a binary outcome, s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 is fixed at </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 
≈ 3.29, the variance of the standard logistic dis-
tribution. For the null model, the VPC's are 0.240 and 0.113 for the household and commune respect-
ively. Thus, for the null model considered in column 1, 24% of variation in primary school attendance 
rates is between households, but only 11.3% between communes. An alternative means by which to </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>interpret variance components is the intra-class correlation coefficient (ICC), which measus corre-
lation or similarity between observed responses within a given higher-level cluster unit. The ICC 
for the commune level, r m , and the household level, r w is calculated as follows </p>

<p>r m = 
s </p>

<p>2 
m </p>

<p>s 2 
m + s 2 
w + s 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>Table 6. Multilevel models. </p>

<p>Random intercepts 
Random slopes 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
Individual level characteristics 
Female 
−0.538*** 
(0.042) </p>

<p>−0.582*** 
(0.043) </p>

<p>−0.582*** 
(0.043) </p>

<p>−0.578*** 
(0.043) 
Age 
3.171*** 
(0.139) </p>

<p>3.183*** 
(0.140) </p>

<p>3.182*** 
(0.140) </p>

<p>3.163*** 
(0.139) 
Age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>−0.167*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>−0.167*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>−0.167*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>−0.166 
(0.008) 
Adopted 
−0.658*** 
(0.117) </p>

<p>−0.924*** 
(0.118) </p>

<p>−0.917*** 
(0.118) </p>

<p>−0.929*** 
(0.117) 
Worked 
−0.297*** 
(0.055) </p>

<p>−0.167*** 
(0.055) </p>

<p>−0.156*** 
(0.054) </p>

<p>−0.137** 
(0.054) 
Household level characteristics 
Household size 
−0.019*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>−0.015** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>−0.015*** 
(0.007) 
Religion 
Islam 
−0.386*** 
(0.078) </p>

<p>−0.311*** 
(0.079) </p>

<p>−0.327*** 
(0.079) 
Traditional / Other 
−0.401*** 
(0.063) </p>

<p>−0.414*** 
(0.063) </p>

<p>−0.413*** 
(0.063) 
Grand mean -centred wealth level 
0.507*** 
(0.024) </p>

<p>0.497*** 
(0.024) </p>

<p>0.498*** 
(0.033) 
Household head's education 
Primary 
0.460*** 
(0.063) </p>

<p>0.447*** 
(0.063) </p>

<p>0.329*** 
(0.063) 
Secondary 
0.714*** 
(0.089) </p>

<p>0.701*** 
(0.089) </p>

<p>0.696*** 
(0.089) 
Tertiary 
0.418** 
(0.207) </p>

<p>0.368* 
(0.206) </p>

<p>0.371* 
(0.206) 
School essential? 
0.154** 
(0.064) </p>

<p>0.134** 
(0.064) </p>

<p>0.125*** 
(0.064) 
Rural 
−0.248*** 
(0.062) </p>

<p>−0.236*** 
(0.062) 
Commune level characteristics 
Distance to school 
−0.165** 
(0.079) </p>

<p>−0.0210 
(0.077) 
(ln) Schools per 5-14 year olds 
1.073*** 
(0.303) </p>

<p>1.128*** 
(0.289) 
Intercept (β 0 ) 
0.322*** 
(0.089) </p>

<p>−13.528*** 
(0.577) </p>

<p>−13.544*** 
(0.603) </p>

<p>−6.646*** 
(1.842) </p>

<p>−6.422*** 
(1.764) 
Random effects 
Level 2: Household 
Intercept variance 
1.223 
1.800 
1.418 
1.422 
1.373 
VPC w : 
0.240 
0.310 
0.279 
0.287 
-
ICC: 
0.353 
0.430 
0.352 
0.336 
-
Level 3: Commune 
Intercept variance 
0.573 
0.700 
0.368 
0.241 
0.214 
VPC m : 
0.113 
0.120 
0.073 
0.049 
-
ICC: 
0.113 
0.120 
0.073 
0.049 
-
Wealth slope variance 
-
-
-
-
0.037 
Intercept -Wealth slope covariance 
-
-
-
-
−0.043 
Observations: 
17,094 
17,094 
17,094 
17,094 
17,094 
Odds ratios shown. Standard errors in parentheses; *p &lt; 0.1; **p &lt; 0.05; ***p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
r w = </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>m + s </p>

<p>2 
w </p>

<p>s 2 
m + s 2 
w + s 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Thus, an ICC of 0.113 for the commune level represents the between-commune correlation in the 
odds that a child is attending school. An ICC of 0.353 shows that the between-household within-
commune correlation is much higher, suggesting a higher correlation in the odds that any two chil-
dren from different households in the one commune are attending school, compared to any two chil-
dren from different households in different communes. 
A caterpillar plot of the commune-level residuals, in Figure 4, shows a significant number of com-
munes where the 95% confidence interval does not overlap with zero, suggesting that primary 
attendance rates are significantly higher or lower than average in these communes. The significant 
between-commune-within-department variance, discussed in section two, is also confirmed here; 
Figure 5 illustrates that whilst some departments, such as Alibori or Plateau, contain only communes 
with a negative random intercept residual, others such as Atacora, Borgou or Zou, contain communes 
where the random effect is both above and below the average. </p>

<p>30   In column 2 of Table 6, covariates are included at the individual level. The VPC in columns 2-4, 
takes on a slightly different interpretation; in these models, it represents the degree of unexplained 
variance that exists at each higher level. Having controlled for individual level factors, we see that 
the 12% of residual variance in primary school attendance exists between communes and some 
31% between households. 
When household-level variables are included in column 3 of Table 6, the variance component 
attributable to the household level falls from 1.800 to 1.418, representing a reduction in between-
household variance of 21%. 
31 Thus, the household covariates included (household wealth, religion, 
size and stated preferences for education) explain around a fifth of the residual variation in 
primary school attendance rates. The remaining household-level variation is attributable to unob-
served household factors. The VPC for the household and commune fall to 27.9% and 7.3% 
respectively. 
In column 4, commune-level variables are added to the model. Immediately clear is that the 
commune-level variance component falls from 0.355 to 0.241; the VPC for communes falls from 
7% to 4.9%. Thus, the inclusion of distance to school and number of schools in the model helps to 
explain around one third of the commune-level variation in primary school attendance. This result 
suggests that the regional differences observed in Benin are down to other unobserved factors at 
the commune-level. These might be, for example, regional differences in labour markets, culture </p>

<p>Figure 4. Random intercept residuals by commune. </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>or traditions. The model has also shown that overall, relatively little of the regional variation in 
primary school attendance rates displayed in Benin is attributable to commune-level factors: Only 
4.9% of the total remaining variation is at the commune-level, whilst some 30% is due to unobserved 
factors at the household level. </p>

<p>6.2. Random slopes model </p>

<p>The random-intercepts model of section 6.1 assumed that the effects of each of the independent vari-
ables was fixed across communes, and across households within communes. In order to test the val-
idity of this assumption, it is possible to estimate a random slopes model, that allows both the 
intercept and the coefficient (slope) of explanatory variables to vary randomly across higher level 
units. The particular focus here is on commune-level effects of household wealth on primary 
school attendance. 
32 The model takes the form </p>

<p>ln 
p ijk 
1 − p ijk 
= b 0 + b 1 x 1ijk . . . . . . + m 0k + m 1k x 1 k + w jk + 1 ijk 
(9) </p>

<p>Column 5 of Table 6 reports the results of equation (9), which allows the slope of mean-centered 
wealth to vary across communes. The effect of wealth on the log-odds of attending school in 
commune k (i.e. the average effect of wealth) is given by b 1 + m 1k , which in this case is estimated 
to be 0.498 + m 1k . The between-commune variance in the effects of wealth, m 1k , is estimated to 
be 0.037. 
The between-commune variance in primary attendance, m k , falls from 0.241 to 0.214, which 
suggests that the distribution ofealth does indeed vary across communes (otherwise m k would 
have remained unchanged). The estimated commune intercept -wealth slope covariance is negative 
(−0.043) which shows that those communes with below average primary school attendance rates (i.e. 
where m 0k &lt; 0) also tend to have above average effects of wealth on attendance (i.e. where m 1k . 0). 
Figure 6 plots m 1k against m 0k . 
In terms of potential policies to improve primary school attendance rates, this exposition is useful. 
Communes in the upper left quadrant represent those where the effect of wealth on primary school 
attendance is above average, whilst attendance itself lies below average. Therefore, these communes </p>

<p>Figure 5. Between-commune within-department variation in random intercepts. </p>

<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
represent those areas where the greatest improvements in primary school attendance rates could be 
realized through policy interventions that either raise income or lower the cost of schooling. Interest-
ingly, the average household wealth level of the 33 communes lying in this quadrant is below the 
national average. 
33 This suggests that, by and large, interventions or policies that increased house-
hold income in the poorest communes nationally could see large increases in primary school attend-
ance rates. 
34 The analysis of section 5 suggests that by lowering average distance to school (by 
building more schools, improving the road network etc.), this might free up time for boys to work 
(and as such contribute to family income) alongside studying, thus lowering the opportunity cost 
of attending school. This provides a clear example of how supply and demand side considerations 
work hand-in-hand to determine whether a child is sent to school. 
Conversely, those communes lying in the lower left quadrant represent communes where primary 
attendance rates are below average, but the effect of wealth is also limited; increasing household 
wealth in such regions might have a limited impact on primary school attendance. </p>

<p>7. Conclusion </p>

<p>This study has sought to shed light on the determinants of primary school attendance rates in Benin, 
a country that despite seeing almost unparalleled improvements in attendance, gender parity and 
completion of primary school over the last two decades, has been practically ignored in the literature. 
These results have presented numerous insights. Large regional disparities existed during the year of 
study (2005-06) and indeed, still do, in the most recent DHS data (2011-12). The empirical analysis 
has presented evidence that factors on both the demand and supply side are predictors of whether 
or not a child will be enrolled in school. Richer households, those following a Christian religion and 
those with more educated household heads were more likely to send their children to school. Despite 
the narrowing gender gap in Benin at the time, girls still faced a lower likelihood of attending school 
than boys; adopted girls seemed at the greatest disadvantage. Focusing on the role of child labour, 
the empirical results highlight that those boys that worked alongside studying faced a higher oppor-
tunity cost of travel time to school than girls. In particular, it appears that distance to school mattered 
more for boys who worked in the field than those carrying out domestic work and that distance was 
only a significant determinant for those girls who worked in the field. In so far as working in the field 
generated more income for the household than did domestic work, then these results might be taken 
as an indication that distance to school goes some way to capturing the opportunity cost of 
attending. 
Whilst much of the literature investigating the determinants of school attendance or enrolment 
has acknowledged that factors at the community or state level might play a part in determining </p>

<p>Figure 6. Commune slopes vs commune intercepts. </p>

<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>

<p>enrolment trends, many studies continue to ignore higher level clustering in the data. In attempting 
to shed light on the large regional disparities that exist in Beninese primary school attendance, the 
present work explicitly accounts for higher level variation in school attendance by using a multilevel 
modelling strategy. A three-level random intercepts model, estimated at the individual, household 
and commune level, highlighted that there were a number of communes where primary school 
attendance was significantly lower than average. After controlling for individual, household and 
commune-level factors, the model is able to explain a large portion of the between -commune var-
iance in primary attendance rates. However, it also suggests that much of the residual variance in 
primary school attendance between communes is actually due to factors at the household level. A 
random slopes model suggests a number of communes where primary school attendance is 
below average and the effect of household wealth on attendance is above average. Such regions 
might stand to benefit most, in terms of primary school attendance rates, from government policies 
that raised household incomes, or reduced the costs of schooling. </p>

<p>Notes </p>



<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
school attendance would not be captured. Secondly, the dependent variable is measured at the individual level 
and the distance variable at the commune level, so reverse causality is not likely to be an issue. 
20. See Bartus (2005) for explanation of why it is preferable to present AMEs when a model contains a large number 
of dummy variables. 
21. As such, I comment on the marginal effects below. 
22. Results not shown, but available upon request 
23. The results of a logit model where female and worked were interacted revealed a similar result (not shown), with 
the AME around −5%. 
24. The 'Christian' category includes 'Protestant', 'Catholic', 'Celeste' &amp; 'Other Christian. 
25. It might also be the case that the sample of heads with tertiary education is simply too small to accurately capture 
the effect. Only 300 children lived in a household with such a head, out of the sample of 17,094. 
26. No significant differences were uncovered here when differentiating between rural and urban, or when including 
the 'Number of Schools' variable. 
27. The types of work considered are 'work in the field' and 'domestic work'. These categories represent 50 and 44% 
of the respondents, whilst the vast majority of the remaining children were categorised as "other". 
28. Thus, children currently in secondary school and those who have completed primary school but not gone on to 
secondary education are also included. 
29. This judgement was made on the basis of LR-test statistics. 
30. Initial diagnostics deemed that the computational complexity of adding a department level to the model in Table 
6 led to little gain in model performance. As such it was not included, but the graphical insight here is nonetheless 
useful. 
31. In the multilevel models here, mean-centred wealth is included rather than the individual wealth quintiles, allow-
ing estimation of the random slopes model, below. 
32. This was deemed the most policy-relevant variable to focus on in this section. That is, the results help us to ident-
ify those communes where interventions that raised household wealth (or reduced the costs of schooling) would 
be most productive in increasing primary school attendance. It could have focused on, for example, household 
head's education level, but as that variable measures past educational attainment (and not something like literacy 
or numeracy), it is more difficult to envisage an appropriate policy response to influence this. 
33. 23 of 33 had mean wealth levels below the national average. 
34. Of course, any increases in attendance may potentially be limited by the availability of schools, teachers or 
supplies. However, such considerations are beyond the scope of the current analysis and, indeed, could not 
be investigated with the data at hand. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement </p>

<p>This article was prepared within the UNU-WIDER project on Gender and Development. I am grateful for useful comments 
from two anonymous referees. Any remaining errors are my own. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author. </p>



<p> 
K. MCNABB </p>



<p>EDUCATION ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>