<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2F000282805774669772" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>and full-time non-tenure-track faculty members 
are unlikely to see this as part of their 
responsibilities. </p>

<p>I. Encouraging Students to Consider Ph.D. 
Study in Economics </p>

<p>During the first 25 years that I spent at Cor-
nell University I chaired the Ph.D. committees 
of over 35 graduate students, but very few un-
dergraduate students from my college went on 
for Ph.D.s in economics. 
3 I decided about five 
years ago that if I cared about the flow of future 
Ph.D.s in economics it was important for me to 
produce future Ph.D. students, as well as Ph.D.s, 
and that involving undergraduate students in 
research early in their academic careers was the 
best way to try to accomplish this. 
One strategy that I pursue is to recruit under-
graduate research assistants prior to their arrival 
at Cornell. I read through the folders of the 
students who have accepted offers of admis-
sions to my college (approximately 160) and 
search for students with strong mathematics, 
statistics, or economics backgrounds. This usu-
ally means students who have taken calculus 
and/or either advanced-placement economics or 
advanced-placement statistics in high school. 
4 I 
write several of these students prior to their 
arriving at Cornell and offer them positions as 
research assistants at CHERI. Given the large 
fraction of our students who must take out loans 
or work as part of their financial-aid packages, 
the take-up rate on these offers is high. </p>

<p>5   The current generation of entering first-year 
students is so computer-literate that they rapidly 
learn how to use spreadsheet and statistical soft-
ware programs, such as <rs type="software">EXCEL</rs>, <rs type="software">Stat/Transfer</rs>, 
and <rs type="software">STATA</rs>. I heuristically explain the econo-
metric models we are using to them, and even if 
they have not had classes in statistics, they 
quickly understand the research that I am con-
ducting. Within a short time, we are working 
together on empirical research projects. These 
students also mention our work to their friends, 
and I often link up with other bright students 
through these referrals. 
Typically the type of research I do with my 
undergraduate students is not as sophisticated as 
the research I do with my graduate students or 
postdoctoral fellows. However, the research is 
of sufficiently high quality that since 2000 I 
have published six papers that had at least one 
undergraduate coauthor, and I have supervised 
the preparation of another two published papers 
in which undergraduates were the only authors 
(Dmitry Kotlyarenko and Ehrenberg, 2000;  Ehrenberg and Christopher L. Smith, 2003,  2004; Daniel B. Klaff and Ehrenberg, 2003;  Ehrenberg et al., 2004a, b; Peter M. Crosta and  Iris G. Packman, 2005; Matthew P. Nagowski,  2005). Seven different undergraduate students 
were associated with these papers. 
One of these students, who came to Cornell 
wanting to be a lawyer, is now a second-year 
Ph.D. student in economics at MIT, and another 
would-be lawyer is a first-year Ph.D. student in 
the Economics of Education program at Colum-
bia Teachers College. A third student is apply-
ing to economics Ph.D. programs this year. A 
number of papers are in progress with other 
undergraduates, and I anticipate at least two 
more applications to Ph.D. programs will come 
from my group within the next two years, in-
cluding one from an underrepresented minority 
student. 
My students' decisions to pursue Ph.D. study 
is due partially to the enjoyment that they see I 
have working with them, partially to the fun that 
they have doing the research, and more gener-
ally from their learning what the life of an </p>

<p>3 But those that did were superb-for example, Alan 
Krueger (Princeton), David Bloom (Harvard), and Phil Le-
vine (Wellesley). 
4 All the students admitted to ILR-Cornell are interested 
in careers in law, human resources, collective bargaining, 
union organization and administration, or applied social 
sciences. Thus, it is easy for me to quickly go through the 
application files and pick out the few top students who may 
prove to be interested in economics. Economists teaching in 
liberal-arts colleges would need to focus their attention on 
applicants who express interest in mathematics or social 
science. Economists at large universities would need to 
establish good relationships with admissions staff at their 
institutions, explain to the admissions officers the types of 
students that they are looking for, and ask them to make 
referrals of student names to them. 
5 Of course one needs money to pay the students, and I 
am deeply indebted to the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation 
and the Atlantic Philanthropies (USA), Inc. for providing 
the funding to CHERI that makes this possible. The sums of 
money involved here are not large, and Cornell University's </p>

<p>experience is that alumni are very willing to contribute 
funds to enhance undergraduates' research experiences. I 
encourage economics departments to raise funds for this 
purpose. </p>

<p> 
VOL. 95 NO. 2 
PERSPECTIVES ON RESEARCH AND TEACHING IN ECONOMICS </p>

<p>academic economist is like. To be honest, I 
emphasize to them the uncertain nature of the 
academic job market and discuss the types of 
positions for Ph.D. economists that are avail-
able outside of academia. They know, for ex-
ample, about former Ph.D. students of mine 
who have been employed at the Rand Corpora-
tion, the Urban Institute, Mathematica Policy 
Research, the Center for Naval Analysis, the 
World Bank, the OECD, the Congressional 
Budget Office, the Bureau of Labor Statistics, 
Merrill Lynch, the Federal Trade Commission, 
and Merck Pharmaceuticals. I also encourage 
them to have an experience as a junior econo-
mist in a nonacademic setting before they apply 
to graduate school, so that they can see firsthand 
what nonacademic Ph.D. economists do. The 
three I mentioned above spent time, respectively, 
at the Center on Budget and Policy Priorities, 
Mathematica, and the Brookings Institution dur-
ing or after their undergraduate studies. </p>

<p>II. Involving More Undergraduate Students in 
Research </p>

<p>Once I began worrying about attracting 
more students into Ph.D. study, it was a nat-
ural extension to think more broadly about 
how to involve more undergraduate students 
in research. After all, if what is unique about 
research universities is the extent to which the 
faculty is involved in research, shouldn't our 
students, who bear some of the costs of the 
research, also derive some of the benefits in 
terms of being exposed to the research pro-
cess? 
6 I decided to require group econometric 
research papers in my two undergraduate 
classes: a sophomore-level labor-economics 
class (with an enrollment of about 35-40) and 
a junior/senior-level class on the economics 
of the university (with an enrollment of about 
65). The papers are group projects (students 
may work in groups of up to four; on average 
they tend to work in groups of two) to allow 
me time to meet with each group multiple 
times during the semester to check on their 
progress and to help guide their work. </p>

<p>I provide each class with a list of suggested 
research topics. Given that my current research 
interest is the economics of higher education, 
the topics relate to that area. Table 1 provides 
examples of some of the topics that I share with 
students in the labor-economics class (in paren-
theses I indicate to what section of the course 
each topic corresponds). I emphasize to the stu-
dents that they are not restricted to these topics 
and that they can discuss other topics with me 
(and many do), but that these are topics for 
which I know data are readily available. 
Student responses to these projects have been 
overwhelmingly positive. The projects allow 
them to make use of statistical methods that 
they have learned to confront "real world" is-
sues. They allow them to test economic theories 
and to understand better, the ceteris paribus 
nature of the predictions of these theories. The 
projects give them experience in conducting 
empirical research and, for some, this experi-
ence leads them to consider future study in 
economics, or careers as economists. Many of 
these students will not have the mathematical 
background necessary to go on directly on for 
an economics Ph.D.; however, some pursue de-
grees in public policy, and others go on to Ph.D. 
programs in other applied social-science fields. 
Given the nature of my college, a number of the 
students go on to law school, but some of these 
students now think about careers as law profes-
sors, in which they can blend legal and eco-
nomic analyses. </p>

<p>III. Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>Involving undergraduate students in research, 
both within and outside of the classroom, is a 
very time-consuming activity. However, the 
benefits I receive from doing this have been 
enormous. In addition to these students having 
helped to pad my vita and to my sense of the 
importance of helping to contribute to the pool 
of potential Ph.D. students in economics and 
engaging undergraduates in the major activity 
of a research university, I have gotten to know 
many undergraduate students much better than I 
would have if I were not engaged in these 
activities. Many of the relationships that I have 
established with these students will be very 
long-lasting in nature, and I will follow their 
careers and personal lives with great interest 
and pride. </p>

<p>6 A forthcoming paper (Ehrenberg et al., 2005) presents 
evidence that undergraduate students bear part of the cost of 
increased faculty research in the forms of increased student/ 
faculty ratios, increased exposure to non-tenure-track fac-
ulty, and somewhat increased tuition payments. </p>

<p> 
AEA PAPERS AND PROCEEDINGS 
MAY 2005 </p>

<p>My goal in writing this essay is to encourage 
senior economists in academia to emulate my 
behavior. In particular, economists at major re-</p>

<p>search universities, many of which attract our 
nation's best undergraduate students, should re-
alize that they have an obligation to the profes-
sion to enhance the flow of undergraduate 
students into Ph.D. study, as well as to train 
those students who show up in their Ph.D. 
programs. </p>



<p>TABLE 1-EXAMPLES OF UNDERGRADUATE EMPIRICAL 
RESEARCH PROJECTS (SECTION OF THE LABOR-ECONOMICS 
CLASS TO WHICH THE PROJECT RELATES) </p>

<p>1) Each year average faculty salary data is published in 
Academe for male and female faculty, at each rank, by 
institution. The ratio of female to male salaries varies 
widely across institutions, as does the ratio of female 
to male faculty members. What factors other than 
differences in gender discrimination across institutions 
are responsible for these differences? (Gender, Race 
and Ethnicity in the Labor Market) </p>

<p>2) There are many ways to measure the research 
productivity of faculty-two are the number of 
citations to an individual's published work and the 
number of his or her publications. Human-capital 
theory predicts that the productivity of an individual 
should vary over the life cycle. What do the life cycle 
productivity profiles actually look like for Cornell 
economists? Why should Cornell economists' research 
productivity vary across individuals at a point in time? 
(Human Capital Theory) </p>

<p>3) In the Yeshiva decision, the Supreme Court effectively 
barred collective bargaining for tenured and tenure-
track faculty members at private colleges and 
universities. However, state laws permit faculty at 
public institutions to bargain in a number of states. 
What determines whether faculty members at a public 
institution are covered by a bargaining contract, and 
do unionized faculty members at public higher-
education institutions earn more than their otherwise 
comparable nonunion faculty colleagues? (Unions and 
the Labor Market) </p>

<p>4) Faculty/student ratios vary widely across colleges and 
universities in the United States. According to the 
theory of labor demand, when faculty salaries are 
high, one should expect to observe, ceteris paribus, 
lower faculty/student ratios. However, those 
institutions with the highest faculty salaries also tend 
to have the highest faculty/student ratios. Does this 
observation mean that the theory of labor demand is 
irrelevant or incorrect for nonprofit and public 
institutions? (Labor Demand) </p>

<p>5) Average faculty salary levels vary widely across 
academic institutions, even if one confines one's self 
to universities that produce Ph.D. degrees. Every 
decade or so, the National Research Council (NRC) 
conducts a study that subjectively rates the quality of 
Ph.D. programs in different fields. As part of the 
NRC's 1995 study, information on objective measures 
of faculty research productivity was also collected. 
How should average faculty salaries vary with average 
faculty research productivity? What other variables 
might be associated with differences in faculty salaries 
across institutions? (Pay and Productivity, Labor 
Mobility) </p>

<p> 
VOL. 95 NO. 2 
PERSPECTIVES ON RESEARCH AND TEACHING IN ECONOMICS </p>



<p> 
AEA PAPERS AND PROCEEDINGS 
MAY 2005 </p>

<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



</text></tei>