<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fcwe.12158" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The debate over whether boarding school is benefi cial for students still exists in both 
developing and developed countries. In rural China, as a result of a national school 
merger program that began in 2001, the number of boarding students has increased </p>

<p>dramatically. Little research has been done, however, to measure how boarding status </p>

<p>may be correlated with nutrition, health and educational outcomes. In this paper, we </p>

<p>compare the outcomes of boarding to those of non-boarding students using a large, </p>

<p>aggregate dataset that includes 59 rural counties across fi ve provinces in China. We </p>

<p>fi nd that for all outcomes boarding students perform worse than non-boarding students. </p>

<p>Despite these differences, the absolute levels of all outcomes are low for both boarding </p>

<p>and non-boarding students, indicating a need for new policies that will target all rural </p>

<p>students regardless of their boarding status. </p>

<p>Since the early 2000s, one of the most prominent endeavors of China's Ministry of </p>

<p>*Aiqin Wang, PhD candidate, School of Economics and Management, Northwest University, China. Email: </p>

<p>shxiwangaiq@163.com; Alexis Medina, Research Fellow, Freeman Spogli Institute for International Studies, </p>

<p>Stanford University, USA. Email: amedina5@stanford.edu; Renfu Luo (corresponding author), Associate </p>

<p>Professor, School of Advanced Agricultural Sciences, Peking University, China. Email: luorf.ccap@igsnrr. </p>

<p>ac.cn; Yaojiang Shi, Professor, Center for Experimental Economics in Education, Shaanxi Normal University, </p>

<p>China. Email: shiyaojiang7@gmail.com; Ai Yue, Associate Professor, Center for Experimental Economics in </p>

<p>Education, Shaanxi Normal University, China. Email: yueai@163.com. The authors acknowledge the fi nancial </p>

<p>assistance of the National Natural Science Foundation of China (grant number 71473239) and the 111 talent </p>

<p>recruitment base of the Chinese Ministry of Education and State Administration of Foreign Expert Affairs (grant </p>

<p>number B16031). </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Education (MOE) has been the implementation of the rural primary school Merger </p>

<p>Program (Luo et al., 2009). Over the past 10 years, enrollments in village-level rural </p>

<p>primary schools have declined sharply (Wu and Shi, 2011). In response, the Merger </p>

<p>Program began to close down smaller schools in more remote villages and merge </p>

<p>them with larger "central" schools. The idea was that with fewer schools, the quality </p>

<p>of facilities and teaching staff could be raised more effectively by concentrating </p>

<p>investments. Nationwide, the number of primary schools in rural China fell by nearly </p>

<p>50 percent from 2001 to 2010 (Yuan and Li, 2012; NBS, 2013). Consequently, many </p>

<p>rural students are no longer able to attend school in their home villages and, instead, </p>

<p>have to room and board at schools far away from home. Since the implementation of the </p>

<p>primary school Merger Program, the number of boarding students has increased rapidly. </p>

<p>By 2008, more than 30 million primary and junior high school students were boarders </p>

<p>(MOE, 2008). </p>

<p>Given this rapid growth in the number of rural boarding students, it is important </p>

<p>to ask: What is the link between boarding and student wellbeing? On the one hand, </p>

<p>boarders are exposed to a collective learning and living environment through boarding </p>

<p>school, which may afford these students more time with and better access to school </p>

<p>facilities such as libraries and gymnasiums relative to non-boarders (Adetunji and </p>

<p>Oladeji, 2007; Behaghel et al., 2015; Shu and Tong, 2015). Boarding students may </p>

<p>also have more opportunities to communicate with and learn from their classmates and </p>

<p>teachers (Fauziyah, 2012; Martin et al., 2014). In addition, boarding schools have more </p>

<p>opportunities to model positive social norms than non-boarding schools, which, in turn, </p>

<p>may position them to better address emotional issues and correct student misbehavior. </p>

<p>For example, teachers and roommates may be able to teach and/or model better lifestyle </p>

<p>choices to disadvantaged and problem students, thereby helping them adapt to the rigors </p>

<p>of academic life (Bronfenbrenner, 1970; Adams, 1995; Xu et al., 2000; Papworth, 2014). </p>

<p>On the other hand, boarding schools may also have negative effects on students. </p>

<p>Boarding students are removed from safe family environments, and may miss the care </p>

<p>and support of their parents (Cookson, 2009). Combined with weak support networks, </p>

<p>this may lead to social isolation (Ak and Sayil, 2006). Boarding students may also adopt </p>

<p>negative behaviors, such as drinking, smoking or fi ghting, due to their constant close </p>

<p>proximity to problem students or low achievers (Henderson et al., 1998; Zhu et al., </p>

<p>2008; Zhang et al., 2014). Boarding schools in remote rural regions may also have poor </p>

<p>living conditions, such as underequipped dormitories (Luo et al., 2009; Pang and Han, </p>

<p>2005; Lu, 2009; Wang and Li, 2009), low nutritional composition of dining hall food (Luo </p>

<p>et al., 2009) or fewer reading materials (Yang, 2009). Finally, boarding students may </p>

<p>lack close adult supervision. For example, high student-teacher ratios may mean that </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>teachers have insuffi cient time to address students' problem behaviors (Moswela, 2006; </p>

<p>Zai and Xuan, 2011; Yue et al., 2014). </p>

<p>Quantitative evidence on the link between boarding and student performance </p>

<p>is mixed. Some studies find better academic performance and reading outcomes at </p>

<p>boarding schools compared with non-boarding schools (Adetunji and Oladeji, 2007; </p>

<p>Adetunde and Asare, 2009; Fauziyah, 2012). Others fi nd that the nutritional status of </p>

<p>boarders is equally as good as that of non-boarders (Intiful et al., 2013; Bolajoko et al.,   2014). </p>

<p>However, a majority of existing studies fi nd that boarding is associated with worse </p>

<p>educational, behavioral and nutritional outcomes in developing countries. Data from </p>

<p>Turkey and Africa show lower academic achievement among boarders in grades 5-9 </p>

<p>than among non-boarders in the same grades (Ak and Sayil, 2006; Bozdogan et al., 2014). </p>

<p>Boarders have also appeared to have more behavioral problems (such as aggressiveness, </p>

<p>coercion, use of physical force and alcohol dependency) than non-boarders (Henderson   et al., 1998; Ak and Sayil, 2006; Moswela, 2006; Agmon et al., 2015). Researchers have </p>

<p>also found boarders to have more mental health problems than non-boarders (Murfi n   and Jamieson, 1977; Ak and Sayil, 2006; Agmon et al., 2015). </p>

<p>In China, the evidence is also mixed. Some studies have found that boarding is </p>

<p>linked with higher word recognition and numerical skills (Shu and Tong, 2015) and </p>

<p>lower mental health problems (Ma and Jin, 2010). Other studies have found that </p>

<p>boarders have a higher probability of being sick (Shu and Tong, 2015) and of exhibiting </p>

<p>more aggressive and violent behaviors (Pang and Han, 2005; Zhao, 2011), and have </p>

<p>more problems with substance abuse (alcohol and cigarettes) (Zhu et al., 2008). </p>

<p>Unfortunately, nearly all of the papers cited above, both in China and in other </p>

<p>developing countries, suffer from two main methodological weaknesses. First, their </p>

<p>sample sizes are all quite small, containing generally fewer than 10 boarding schools. </p>

<p>Second, most studies only consider a limited number of nutrition or education </p>

<p>outcomes among boarding students. As a result, these papers can only provide limited </p>

<p>understanding of the overall boarding experiences. </p>

<p>The goal of the present paper is to describe a wide range of health, nutrition, </p>

<p>education and behavioral outcomes among both boarding and non-boarding students </p>

<p>using a comprehensive and empirically rigorous methodology. In total, we will be </p>

<p>measuring 11 outcomes among a population of 37 181 students in rural China. This </p>

<p>study represents the biggest and most comprehensive study of boarders of which we are </p>

<p>aware to date. </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>II. Data and Methods </p>

<p>1. Data </p>

<p>The data used for this study are aggregated from seven different school-level surveys </p>

<p>that the authors and their collaborators conducted in the rural areas of fi ve provinces in </p>

<p>China from 2008 to 2013. Table 1 shows the provinces, years, sample sizes and primary </p>

<p>outcomes of the surveys. The total sample includes 37 181 children aged 8 to 15 years. </p>

<p>These sample provinces are located in China's western region, which is one of the </p>

<p>nation's poorest areas (Gerard, 2006). </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Table 1. Description of Surveys and Datasets </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
Project number 
Province 
Year 
Sample size Primary outcome variables </p>

<p>1 
Shaanxi 
2008 
4058 
BMI, math scores, mental health, 
hemoglobin 
2 
Ningxia, 
Qinghai </p>

<p>2009 
7484 
Math scores, mental health, 
hemoglobin 
3 
Gansu 
2010 
2650 
Math scores, mental health, 
self-esteem, hemoglobin 
4 
Ningxia 
2011 
900 
Math scores, mental health, 
self-esteem, hemoglobin 
5 
Shaanxi, 
Ningxia </p>

<p>2011 
2976 
Math scores, self-esteem, hemoglobin </p>

<p>6 
Gansu, Qinghai, 
Shaanxi </p>

<p>2011 
16 938 
Math scores, Chinese language scores, 
hemoglobin 
7 
Guizhou 
2013 
2175 
WAZ, HAZ, BMI, STH, working 
memory, processing speed, hemoglobin 
Total 
37 181 </p>

<p>Source: The authors and collaborators conducted seven different surveys in rural areas of fi ve of China's </p>

<p>provinces. </p>

<p>Notes: BMI, body mass index; HAZ, height-for-age Z-score; STH, soil-transmitted helminthes; WAZ, weight-</p>

<p>for-age Z-scores. </p>

<p>2. Sample Selection </p>

<p>The data from the seven surveys are based on random sampling strategies that were 
identical across studies. First, we obtained a list of all the counties in each of the fi ve </p>

<p>provinces. Second, we randomly selected study counties from those meeting our study </p>

<p>criteria. Third, using offi cial records, we created a list of all primary (and/or secondary) </p>

<p>schools in the sample counties. Fourth, we used offi cial records and telephone calls to </p>

<p>school principals to identify all schools with a set of fi xed characteristics (e.g. all schools </p>

<p>of a certain size). Fifth, we randomly selected schools and created our sampling frame. </p>

<p>1 For the interested reader, more information is available through Stanford University's website (http://reap. </p>

<p>stanford.edu./docs/628/). </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Finally, within each of the randomly selected schools we randomly selected students </p>

<p>(or classes of students) for inclusion in the studies. The exact sampling protocols are </p>

<p>described in the papers from which the source data come; these papers have been </p>

<p>published elsewhere and interested readers are encouraged to refer to those papers for </p>

<p>more details (Luo et al., 2010; Lai et al., 2013; Chen et al., 2014; Yue et al., 2014). </p>

<p>3. Data Collection and Outcome Measures </p>

<p>The dataset established from these individual surveys can be considered a mega-dataset </p>

<p>with successive waves of observations on students from rural schools. All of the surveys </p>

<p>included in this study followed uniform data collection protocol and employed the </p>

<p>same set of experienced enumeration team leaders and supervisors. The enumerators </p>

<p>were undergraduate and graduate students from local universities who were recruited </p>

<p>from academic departments relevant to the survey material. All enumerators underwent </p>

<p>comprehensive multi-day training that lasted from 2 to 7 days, depending on the </p>

<p>complexity of the survey and testing instruments. All of the survey enumerators were </p>

<p>blind to children's boarding status when outcomes were measured. </p>

<p>In total, the dataset includes information on almost 500 schools in 59 counties </p>

<p>from the fi ve provinces. During the survey, we collected data on the basic demographic </p>

<p>information of students, including whether the student is a boarder. As outcome </p>

<p>variables, we collected information on the education, nutrition and health conditions of </p>

<p>the students. We have data on weight-for-age Z-scores (WAZ), height-for-age Z-scores </p>

<p>(HAZ), body mass index (BMI), anemia prevalence, rates of infection with soil-</p>

<p>transmitted helminths (STH), mental health tests and self-esteem. We collected four </p>

<p>measures of academic performance: test scores from standardized tests of math and </p>

<p>Chinese language, working memory, and cognitive processing speed. The exact variable </p>

<p>defi nitions are shown in Table 2. </p>

<p>Children's height and weight were measured and recorded by trained nurses </p>

<p>from local provincial hospitals. The children were measured in light clothing without </p>

<p>shoes. Body weight was measured with a calibrated electronic scale and body height </p>

<p>was measured using a standard tape measure. Weight-for-age Z-scores (WAZ) were </p>

<p>calculated using a <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> program for the 2000 CDC growth chart for children aged 0-20 </p>

<p>years (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">WHO</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2009</rs>). 
2 Physical indicators of height and weight were used to construct </p>

<p>height-for-age Z-scores (HAZ) and body mass index (BMI) using <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">WHO</rs> <rs id="software-2" type="software">AnthroPlus</rs>, </p>

<p>a software application of the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">WHO</rs> Reference 2007 for children aged 5-19 years that </p>

<p>2 See: US Center for Disease Control and Prevention, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2002</rs>, A <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS</rs> Program for 2000 CDC Growth Charts </p>

<p>(0 to &lt;20 years old). For more information, please see <rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.cdc.gov/nccdphp/dnpao/growthcharts/ resources/sas.htm</rs>. </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>is used to monitor the growth of school-aged children and adolescents. We followed </p>

<p>internationally recognized cutoffs to consider children whose HAZ, BMI or WAZ </p>

<p>fall more than two standard deviations below the international mean to be stunted, </p>

<p>malnourished or underweight, respectively (WHO, 2006). </p>

<p>Table 2. Variable Defi nitions </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
Variable 
Descriptions 
WAZ 
A person's weight in kilograms divided by the age or date of birth and date of 
interview 
HAZ 
A person's height in kilograms divided by the age or date of birth and date of 
interview 
BMI 
A person's weight in kilograms divided by the square of height in meters </p>

<p>Anemia rate 
Hemoglobin concentration &lt;115 g/L, if age &gt;=9 and &lt;=11 (1 = yes, 0 = no); 
Hemoglobin concentration &lt;120 g/L, if age &gt;=12 and &lt;=14 (1 = yes, 0 = no) 
STH infection 
Child is infected with any of the three types of STH: Ascaris, hookworm or 
whipworm (1 = yes, 0 = no) 
Standardized 
math test score </p>

<p>% of questions answered correctly on standardized math test </p>

<p>Standardized 
Chinese test score </p>

<p>% of questions answered correctly on standardized Chinese test </p>

<p>WMI 
Standardized score on the working memory module of the WISC-IV 
PSI 
Standardized score on the processing speed module of the WISC-IV 
MHT 
Mental health test 
Self-esteem score 
Standardized score on Rosenberg Self-esteem Scales I &amp; II (SES) </p>

<p>Source: The authors and collaborators conducted seven different surveys in rural areas of fi ve of China's </p>

<p>provinces. </p>

<p>Notes: BMI, body mass index; HAZ, height-for-age Z-score; MHT, mental health test; PSI, processing speed </p>

<p>index; STH, soil-transmitted helminthes; WAZ, weight-for-age Z-scores; WISC-IV, Wechsler intelligence </p>

<p>scale for children; WMI, working memory index. </p>

<p>Hemoglobin concentrations were measured onsite using a Hemocue Hb 201+ </p>

<p>fi ngerprick system. The WHO recommends an anemia cutoff of 115 g/L for children </p>

<p>aged 9 to 11 years and 120 g/L for those aged 12 to 14 years. STH infection was </p>

<p>assessed using the Kato-Katz smear test for Ascaris lumbricodes (Ascaris), Trichuris </p>

<p>trichuria (Whipworm), and Ancylostoma duodenale or Necator americanus (hookworm) </p>

<p>(CCDCP, 2008). Stool samples were considered positive for infection if the test on the </p>

<p>same day showed signs of infection with one or more types of STH. </p>

<p>Students were also given a standardized math test and a standardized Chinese </p>

<p>language test. Our enumeration team carefully proctored the test to minimize cheating, </p>

<p>and strictly enforced the time limits. Scores on both standardized tests were normalized </p>

<p>(with mean zero and standard deviation equal to one) and used as two of our measures </p>

<p>of student academic performance. </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>We used a psychological test of well-being, the mental health test (MHT), to </p>

<p>measure children's mental health. The test is a variation of the children's Manifest </p>

<p>Anxiety Scale (CMAS), a scale that has been widely used in the United States and other </p>

<p>developed countries for more than a decade as a screening and clinical tool. Professor </p>

<p>Zhou Bucheng of East China Normal University (1991) developed the MHT scale used </p>

<p>in the present study. Researchers have used this test extensively across China to measure </p>

<p>the mental health of grade school students in urban contexts. The purpose of the test is </p>

<p>to measure students' anxiety levels. The test is scored out of 90 points, where a lower </p>

<p>score corresponds to lower anxiety. The test results can be broken down into eight </p>

<p>subcategories, each of which represents a specifi c aspect of anxiety: learning anxiety, </p>

<p>personal anxiety, loneliness anxiety, self-blaming tendency, sensitivity tendency, </p>

<p>body anxiety, phobia anxiety and impulsive tendency. A score of &gt;8 on any subpart </p>

<p>is considered clinically high and indicates a need for treatment. A total score of 65 or </p>

<p>higher indicates high risk for mental health problems and an urgent need for professional </p>

<p>intervention. Self-esteem was assessed using the Rosenberg Self-esteem Scales I &amp; II </p>

<p>(SES) created by Rosenberg (1965). The SES consists of 10 statements, each of which is </p>

<p>scored as a Likert scale. </p>

<p>Two additional cognitive measures were generated using the Wechsler Intelligence </p>

<p>Scale for Children, Fourth Edition (WISC-IV): Working Memory and Processing </p>

<p>Speed (Wechsler, 2003). The working memory index (WMI) was assessed through two </p>

<p>core subtests: the Digit Span subtest and the Letter Number Sequencing subtest. The </p>

<p>processing speed index (PSI) was also assessed through two core subtests: the coding </p>

<p>subtest and the symbol search subtest. Raw scores obtained from these subtests were </p>

<p>converted to age-scaled index scores using tables of norms from the offi cial WISC-IV </p>

<p>administration and scoring manual for China. </p>

<p>4. Statistical Approach </p>

<p>Calculations of WAZ, HAZ, BMI and standardized test scores for working memory, </p>

<p>processing speed, self-esteem, mental health, mathematics and Chinese are described as </p>

<p>means of the standardized score of each sample. Anemia rates and STH infection rates </p>

<p>are presented as percentages. A χ 
2 -test was used to compare differences in percentage </p>

<p>rates between boarders and non-boarders (Table 4). </p>

<p>5. Ethical Approval </p>

<p>All of these individual studies were approved by the relevant Chinese authorities and the </p>

<p>Stanford University Institutional Review Board (IRB). The caregivers of all participants </p>

<p>provided informed oral consent, and the children themselves provided oral assent prior </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>to the start of any study activities. </p>

<p>III. Results </p>

<p>Overall, a total of 17 percent of students were boarders; the remaining 83 percent of </p>

<p>students were non-boarders. With the exception of Ningxia (where the proportion of </p>

<p>boarders is relatively low, at 7 percent), the proportion of boarders is fairly consistent </p>

<p>across provinces, at around 25 percent. </p>

<p>Health and nutrition indicators for the full sample are poor (Table 3). The WAZ </p>

<p>and HAZ of the sample children are both −1.39, indicating lower than ideal heights </p>

<p>and weights for all children. The average BMI is 16.16. Approximately one-fi fth of all </p>

<p>children are anemic (19.27 percent), and nearly half (41.87 percent) are infected with </p>

<p>STH. </p>

<p>Table 3. Description of Sample Children in Rural China </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
Variable 
Sample size 
Unit 
Mean value </p>

<p>WAZ 
2174 
Z-score 
-1.39 
HAZ 
2174 
Z-score 
-1.39 
BMI 
5800 
Kg/cm2 
16.16 
Anemia rate 
25 954 
% 
19.27 
STH infection rate 
2175 
% 
41.84 
Working memory 
2175 
45-150 points 
78.59 
Processing speed 
2175 
45-150 points 
86.18 
MHT 
14 635 
0-90 points 
39.72 </p>

<p>Self-esteem </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>3550 
10-40 points 
25.17 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' data. </p>

<p>Notes: </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>In this table, we do not include standardized test scores of math and Chinese language scales because </p>

<p>these scores are only used to compare students' relative performance; 
b Higher scores indicate higher </p>

<p>self-esteem. BMI, body mass index; HAZ, height-for-age Z-score; MHT, mental health test; STH, soil-</p>

<p>transmitted helminthes; WAZ, weight-for-age Z-scores. </p>

<p>Measures of academic and non-academic outcomes among the full population are </p>

<p>also poor. Average scores of working memory and processing speed as measured by the </p>

<p>WISC test are 78.59 and 86.18, respectively, well below the internationally scaled mean </p>

<p>of 100. The average score on the MHT is 39.72, which is comparable to measures found </p>

<p>in previous studies of rural children in China (Ye, 2000; Luo, 2012; Zhang et al., 2013). </p>

<p>In addition, the average score on the self-esteem test is 25.17, which is lower than both </p>

<p>the global average (30.85 [Schmitt and Allik, 2005]) and the urban Chinese average </p>

<p>(31.19 [Liu, 2014]) calculated in previous studies. </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>In terms of health and nutrition, boarders have poorer outcomes than non-</p>

<p>boarders for most of the variables (Table 4, rows 1 to 5). HAZ among boarders is </p>

<p>-1.53, compared with -1.34 among non-boarders (p &lt; 0.01). WAZ of boarders is also </p>

<p>significantly lower among boarders versus non-boarders (p &lt; 0.02). Boarders also </p>

<p>have signifi cantly higher anemia rates (p &lt; 0.01) and signifi cantly higher rates of STH </p>

<p>infection (p &lt; 0.01) compared with non-boarders. The one exception to this trend is for </p>

<p>BMI, where boarders signifi cantly outperform non-boarders (16.22 vs 16.13, p &lt; 0.1). </p>

<p>Table 4. Comparison of Health, Nutrition and Educational Status of </p>

<p>Boarders and Non-boarders in Rural China </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Variable 
Sample size 
Units 
Boarders 
Non 
-boarders 
p-value </p>

<p>Health and nutrition </p>

<p>WAZ 
2174 
Z-score 
-1.48 
-1.35 
0.02 </p>

<p>HAZ 
2174 
Z-score 
-1.53 
-1.34 
0.00 </p>

<p>BMI 
5800 
kg/cm2 
16.22 
16.13 
0.06 </p>

<p>Anemia prevalence 
25 954 
% 
24.06 
18.34 
0.00 </p>

<p>STH infection rate 
2175 
% 
47.36 
39.89 
0.00 </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>Standardized 
math test 
24 644 
SD 
0.01 
0.02 
0.31 </p>

<p>Standardized Chinese 
test 
7075 
SD 
-0.06 
0.06 
0.02 </p>

<p>Working memory 
2175 
45-150 
points 
77.31 
79.05 
0.00 </p>

<p>Processing speed 
2175 
45-150 
points 
85.25 
86.51 
0.05 </p>

<p>Mental health </p>

<p>MHT 
14 635 
0-90 points 
40.52 
39.42 
0.00 </p>

<p>Self-esteem 
3550 
10-40 points 
24.99 
25.18 
0.43 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' analyses of seven different surveys that the authors and collaborators conducted in rural areas </p>

<p>of fi ve of China's provinces. </p>

<p>Notes: BMI, body mass index; HAZ, height-for-age Z-score; MHT, mental health test; SD, standard deviation; </p>

<p>STH, soil-transmitted helminthes; WAZ, weight-for-age Z-scores. </p>

<p>In regards to educational performance and cognition, boarders underperform relative </p>

<p>to non-boarders in terms of all of the outcome variables (Table 4, rows 6 to 9). Non-</p>

<p>boarders scored signifi cantly higher than boarders on the standardized Chinese language </p>

<p>test (p &lt; 0.05). Non-boarders also scored higher than boarders on both the working </p>

<p>memory (p &lt; 0.01) and processing speed scales (p &lt; 0.1). Boarders and non-boarders </p>

<p>performed similarly on the standardized math test (p = 0.31). </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Boarders had slightly poorer mental health outcomes than non-boarders (Table </p>

<p>4, rows 10 and 11). Boarders performed signifi cantly worse than non-boarders on the </p>

<p>MHT, both overall and for all MHT subscales (except for impulsive tendency and </p>

<p>personal anxiety: Table 5). There was no difference in self-esteem between boarders and </p>

<p>non-boarders (p = 0.43). </p>

<p>Table 5. Comparison of Categorical Breakdown of the Mental Health </p>

<p>Test Score between Boarders and Non-boarders </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Subscales of MHT 
Mean 
Units 
Boarders 
Non 
-boarders 
p-value </p>

<p>Learning anxiety 
8.50 
0-15 points 
8.60 
8.47 
0.01 
Personal anxiety 
4.38 
0-10 points 
4.43 
4.37 
0.13 
Loneliness anxiety 
3.13 
0-10 points 
3.20 
3.10 
0.01 </p>

<p>Self-blaming tendency 
5.57 
0-10 points 
5.74 
5.50 
0.00 
Sensitivity tendency 
5.10 
0-10 points 
5.23 
5.05 
0.00 
Body anxiety 
5.56 
0-15 points 
5.66 
5.52 
0.01 
Phobia anxiety 
4.69 
0-10 points 
4.88 
4.62 
0.00 
Impulsive tendency 
2.79 
0-10 points 
2.79 
2.79 
0.91 
Total 
39.72 
0-90 points 
40.52 
39.42 
0.00 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' analyses of seven different surveys that the authors and collaborators conducted in rural areas </p>

<p>of fi ve of China's provinces. </p>

<p>Note: MHT, mental health test. </p>

<p>IV. Discussion </p>

<p>The main aim of this study has been to show the link between boarding status and </p>

<p>student education, health and nutrition outcomes in rural China. We fi nd that across all </p>

<p>of our outcomes, boarding students perform worse than non-boarding students. Given </p>

<p>the large increase in boarding students in rural China over the past several years, these </p>

<p>fi ndings raise serious concerns. </p>

<p>This study has a number of strengths. First, our aggregated sample, comprised of </p>

<p>seven different datasets, is much larger (&gt;35 000) than that used in any similar study. </p>

<p>This gives the research a high degree of statistical power and considerable external </p>

<p>validity, at least in relatively poor regions of rural China. Second, all of the observations </p>

<p>were collected using a common sampling strategy by a single research team. The data </p>

<p>collection instrument was standardized, as was the enumeration process. Because of </p>

<p>this, we can compare outcome variables across boarders and non-boarders. </p>

<p>We identify two main limitations to our study. First, given the nature of the sample, </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>we are unable to extrapolate our findings to boarding schools in non-poor or urban </p>

<p>areas. Second, although this paper measures differences in education, health and </p>

<p>nutrition between boarders and non-boarders, we are unable to identify an exact causal </p>

<p>relationship between boarding status and these outcomes. </p>

<p>Despite these limitations, the present study makes a signifi cant contribution to the </p>

<p>domestic and international literature on the status of boarding students. In China, most </p>

<p>existing studies were conducted in a single province or sub-provincial region and only </p>

<p>focus on a limited number of outcomes. To our knowledge, ours is the fi rst study of </p>

<p>Chinese boarding students that examines multiple outcome variables, including health, </p>

<p>nutrition and education, for a large sample (covering fi ve provinces). </p>

<p>Our results should not be construed to mean that students ought not attend boarding </p>

<p>school. Indeed, the absolute levels of education, health and nutrition among all students </p>

<p>are still low. In comparison with international standards, children in rural China (both </p>

<p>boarders and non-boarders) are shorter and lighter. Approximately 20 percent of students </p>

<p>suffer from anemia and over 40 percent are infected with intestinal worms. Other work </p>

<p>has documented the poor levels of educational performance among rural children </p>

<p>relative to urban children (Wang et al., 2011). Perhaps a more accurate interpretation of </p>

<p>the results of this paper is that all children in rural China are vulnerable. They all require </p>

<p>extra care, attention and resources. </p>

<p>From a policy perspective, our results point to serious weaknesses in the existing </p>

<p>rural school system. Both boarders and non-boarders perform poorly in terms of all of </p>

<p>the indicators considered in this study. A handful of non-government organizations, </p>

<p>government departments and research centers have already begun developing initiatives </p>

<p>such as training student guidance counselors, building school libraries and training </p>

<p>library staff, introducing more nutritional meals, and launching extracurricular computer </p>

<p>assisted learning programs (Luo et al., 2009; Mo et al., 2012; Lai et al., 2013; Yue et al.,   2014). These programs have completely or partly succeeded in improving education, </p>

<p>health and nutrition outcomes among boarders. Based on our fi ndings, we suggest that </p>

<p>these special programs be expanded to cover all students in rural China. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Adams, D. W., 1995, Education for Extinction: American Indians and the Boarding School </p>

<p>Experience, 1875-1928, Lawrence, KS: University Press of Kansas. </p>

<p>Adetunde, A. I. and B. Asare, 2009, "Comparative performance of day and boarding students in </p>

<p>secondary school certifi cate mathematics examinations: A case study of Kasena-Nankana </p>

<p>and Asuogyaman Districts of Ghana," The Academia Arema, Vol. 4, No. 1, pp. 7-10. </p>

<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Adetunji, A. and B. O. Oladeji, 2007, "Comparative study of the reading habit of boarding and </p>

<p>day secondary school students in Osogbo, Osun State, Nigeria," Pakistan Journal of Social </p>

<p>Science, Vol. 4, No. 4, pp. 509-12. </p>

<p>Agmon, M., C. Zlotnick and F. Anat, 2015, "The relationship between mentoring on healthy </p>

<p>behaviors and well-being among Israeli youth in boarding schools: A mixed-methods </p>

<p>study," BMC Pediatrics, Vol. 15, No. 1, p. 11. </p>

<p>Ak, L. and M. Sayil, 2006, "Three different types of elementary school students' school </p>

<p>achievements, perceived social support, school attitudes and behavior-adjustment </p>

<p>problems," Educational Sciences: Theory &amp; Practice, Vol. 6, No. 2, pp. 293-300. </p>

<p>Behaghel, L., C. D. Chaisemartin and M. Gurgand, 2015, "Ready for boarding: The effects of </p>

<p>a boarding school for disadvantaged students," Warwick Economics Research Papers </p>

<p>Series (TWERPS) No. 1059, University of Warwick, Department of Economics, Coventry, </p>

<p>England. 
Bolajoko, O., G. A. Ogundahunsi, O. Folahan, B. A. Odugbemi and O. Alakuro, 2014, "Nutrient </p>

<p>adequacy of foods eaten by students attending boarding and day secondary schools in </p>

<p>Owo," Current Research in Nutrition and Food Science Journal, Vol. 2, No. 2, pp. 84-87. </p>

<p>Bozdoğan, A. E., E. Günaydın and A. Okur, 2014, "An examination of secondary school </p>

<p>students' academic achievement in science course and achievement scores in performance </p>

<p>assignments with regard to different variables: A boarding school example," Participatory </p>

<p>Educational Research, Vol. 1, No. 2, pp. 95-105. </p>

<p>Bronfenbrenner, U., 1970, "Reaction to social pressure from adults versus peers among Soviet day </p>

<p>school and boarding school pupils in the perspective of an American sample," Journal of </p>

<p>Personality and Social Psychology, Vol. 15, No. 3, p. 179. </p>

<p>CCDCP (Chinese Center for Disease Control &amp; Prevention), 2008, Report on the National Survey </p>

<p>of Current Status of Major Human Parasitic Diseases in China, Beijing: People's Medical </p>

<p>Publishing House. </p>

<p>Chen, X. X., H. M. Yi, L. X. Zhang, D. Mo, J. Chu and S. Rozelle, 2014, "Do poor students </p>

<p>benefi t from China's merger program? Transfer path and educational performance," Asia </p>

<p>Pacifi c Journal of Education, Vol. 34, No. 1, pp. 15-35. </p>

<p>Cookson, P. W., 2009, "Boarding schools," in R. A. Shweder, ed., The Child: An Encyclopedic </p>

<p>Companion, Chicago: University of Chicago Press, pp. 112-14. </p>

<p>Fauziyah, M. H., 2012, "The English achievement between Islamic boarding and non-boarding </p>

<p>students of the eighth grade students of MTS Ma'ahid Kudus in the academic year </p>

<p>2011/2012," Doctoral Dissertation, Universitas Muria Kudus, Gondangmanis, Indonesia. </p>

<p>Gerard, A. P., 2006, Education and Social Change in China: Inequality in a Market Economy, </p>

<p>Armonk: M.E. Sharpe. </p>

<p>Henderson, E., S. J. Kunitz, K. R. Gabriel, A. McCright and J. E. Levy, 1998, "Boarding and </p>

<p>public schools: Navajo educational attainment, conduct disorder, and alcohol dependency," </p>

<p>American Indian and Alskan Native Mental Health Research, Vol. 8, No. 2. pp. 28-49. </p>



<p>Aiqin Wang et al. / 52-66, Vol. 24, No. 3, 2016 </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Intiful, F. D., L. Ogyiri, M. Asante, A. A. Mensah, R. K. Steele-Dadzie and L. Boateng, 2013, </p>

<p>"Nutritional status of boarding and non-boarding children in selected schools in the Accra </p>

<p>metropolis," Journal of Biology, Agriculture and Healthcare, Vol. 3, No. 7, pp. 156-62. </p>

<p>Lai, F., L. X. Zhang, X. Hu, Q. H. Qu, Y. J. Shi, Y. J. Qiao, M. Boswell and S. Rozelle, 2013, </p>

<p>"Computer assisted learning as extracurricular tutor? Evidence from a randomised </p>

<p>experiment in rural boarding schools in Shaanxi," Journal of Development Effectiveness, </p>



<p> 
To Board or Not to Board </p>

<p>©2016 Institute of World Economics and Politics, Chinese Academy of Social Sciences </p>

<p>Statistics Press. </p>







</text></tei>