<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2F1468-0106.12204" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. We develop a new robust-to-outliers dummy estimator that we subsequently apply to 
investigate the impact of various democratic attributes on foreign direct investment in recent 
years. We find that democracy has generally a positive impact on foreign direct investment, 
once outliers are controlled for, but that this relationship is very specific to each host country's 
characteristics. </p>

<p>The impact of democracy on foreign direct investment (FDI) in developing 
countries is a hotly debated issue. Jensen (2003, 2008) and Azémar and  Desbordes (2009) provide an overview of the literature on FDI and democracy. 
On the one hand, it has been argued that democratic forms of government at-
tract FDI because they tend to be predictable and credible, thanks to vertical 
and horizontal accounting mechanisms. The combination of periodic elections 
and widespread diffusion of information ensures that politicians make clear their 
preferences, do not renege on their promises once in power, and, more broadly, 
do not abuse their position for private gains. Strong checks and balances in-
crease policy stability, and, ultimately, the protection of property rights, because 
the existence of several distinct veto players hinders any changes in the status 
quo. When policy changes do occur, institutionalized channels of influence/ 
lobbying can allow foreign investors to mitigate any adverse effects. Consoli-
dated democracies also guarantee orderly and non-violent changes of govern-
ment within the current institutional framework. 
On the other hand, the virtues of democracy can easily be seen as disadvan-
tages to countries wanting to attract multinational enterprises. Politicians' desire 
to win elections may lead them to promise and adopt popular but economically 
harmful policies. Political turnover creates uncertainty about the persistence of 
policies, whereas an increase in the number of veto players has the potential to 
result in long-term reform sclerosis. Foreign firms may suffer from a political li-
ability of foreignness and be discriminated against relative to their better 
politically-connected domestic competitors. Finally, a related but more sinister 
view is that freedom of expression and open media can prevent foreign firms </p>

<p>*Address for Correspondence: Department of Economics, Sir William Duncan Building, University 
of Strathclyde, 130 Rottenrow, Glasgow G4 0GE, Scotland, UK. E-mail: rodolphe. 
desbordes@strath.ac.uk. Vincenzo Verardi is associated researcher of the FNRS and gratefully ac-
knowledges their financial support </p>

<p>Pacific Economic Review, 22: 1 (2017) 
pp. 43-82 
doi: 10.1111/1468-0106.12204 </p>

<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>bs_bs_banner </p>

<p>from colluding with officials in order to obtain generous entry deals or to de-
crease market competition. Hence, FDI may be attracted by autocracies. 
This ambiguous theoretical impact of democracy on FDI is mirrored in the 
empirical literature. As described in Table 1, studies find positive (Harms and  Ursprung, 2002; Jensen, 2003; Busse, 2004; Azémar and Desbordes, 2009), neg-
ative (Li and Resnick, 2003) or insignificant (Blanton and Blanton, 2007; Büthe  and Milner, 2008; Choi and Samy, 2008) impacts, depending on the econometric 
model, the proxy for democracy and the sample used. 
The presence of outliers (i.e. observations that are substantially different from 
the bulk of the data) has sometimes been blamed for this variety of findings. 
Some researchers have attempted to deal with these atypical observations 
(Jakobsen and De Soysa, 2006; Choi, 2009; Li, 2009). However, it is unlikely 
that they have solved this issue in a satisfactory manner. Popular robust estima-
tors (e.g. median regression estimator or M-estimator) are sensitive to outliers 
present in the values of explanatory variables and outlier diagnostics (e.g. the 
Cook distance) frequently fail to detect atypical observations as they fundamen-
tally rely on the extremely non-robust-to-outliers least-squares estimator 
(Verardi and Croux, 2009). Problems of inadequate econometric identification 
and treatment of outliers thus remain pervasive in the FDI literature. 
A related issue is the increasing use of the fixed effects estimator to control for 
unobserved time-invariant unit-specific effects that may be correlated with the 
explanatory variables. While this estimator may reduce any omitted variable 
bias, it does not protect against outlier contamination. An aggravating problem 
is that the most resistant robust regression methods are ill-designed to analyse 
econometric models, which include a large number of dummies. While some 
robust panel data estimators have been proposed, they appear not to be consis-
tent when the number of time periods is small, and cannot deal with dummies 
not related to the within transformation (Aquaro and Pavel, 2010). 
In this paper, we revisit the link between FDI and democracy in develop-
ing countries, during the 1998-2006 period. We pay particular attention to 
the multi-faceted nature of democracy, the influence of outliers, and the het-
erogeneous relationship that may exist between these two variables. We use 
a variety of measures to explore how each particular dimension of democ-
racy can influence FDI. We develop a new robust dummy estimator, which 
allows us to control for outliers in a fixed effects panel data model. Finally, 
we investigate whether the impact of democracy on FDI depends on natural 
resources, income inequality, and their interaction. Our results show that 
democracy generally has a positive impact on FDI, once outliers are con-
trolled for, but that this relationship is very specific to each host country's 
characteristics. 
The rest of the paper proceeds as follows. Section 2 introduces our new robust 
dummy estimator and explains its advantages over existing robust regression 
methods. Section 3 provides Monte-Carlo simulations highlighting the good 
performance of our estimator. Section 4 replicates a key study on FDI and 
democracy to highlight that the correct treatment of outliers is a key issue. 
Section 5 describes the data used in our original empirical analysis and motivates </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 1. Selective review of the impact of democracy on FDI </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Citations </p>

<p>Sample 
Main estimator(s) </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Main proxy (proxies) </p>

<p>Explicit control 
for outliers </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Harms and 
Ursprung (2002) </p>

<p>258 
62 developing 
countries; 
1989-1997 </p>

<p>Between 
(cross-sectional); </p>

<p>fixed effects </p>

<p>FDI/population </p>

<p>Freedom house 
indexes of 
political 
rights and 
civil rights </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Positive but 
statistically 
significant only </p>

<p>with a between 
estimator </p>

<p>Jensen (2003) </p>

<p>653 
114 developed 
and developing 
countries; 
1970-1997 
Fixed effects; 
dynamic </p>

<p>FDI/GDP </p>

<p>Polity III score </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Positive 
direct impact </p>

<p>Li and 
Resnick (2003) </p>

<p>587 
53 developing 
countries; 
1982-1995 </p>

<p>Pooled </p>

<p>FDI </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Negative direct 
impact; indirect 
positive impact </p>

<p>via strengthening 
property rights 
protection </p>

<p>Jakobsen and </p>

<p>De Soysa (2006) </p>

<p>88 
99 developing 
countries; 
1984-2001 </p>

<p>Pooled; 
dynamic </p>

<p>ln(FDI) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>Yes; log 
transformation </p>

<p>to attenuate 
influence of 
outliers in 
dependent 
variable; China 
dummy variable </p>

<p>Positive direct 
impact </p>

<p>Blanton and 
Blanton (2007) </p>

<p>114 
129 developing 
countries; 
1980-2003 </p>

<p>Pooled </p>

<p>FDI/GDP </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Statistically 
insignificant </p>

<p>impact </p>

<p>Busse and 
Hefeker (2007) </p>

<p>576 
83 developing 
countries; 
1984-2003 
Fixed effects/ 
DIFF-GMM; </p>

<p>dynamic </p>

<p>ln(FDI + sqrt(FDI </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>+1)) ICRG </p>

<p>democracy </p>

<p>index </p>

<p>No but 
dependent 
variable is 
transformed </p>

<p>Positive direct 
impact </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 1. (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Citations </p>

<p>Sample 
Main estimator(s) </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Main proxy (proxies) </p>

<p>Explicit control 
for outliers </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Büthe and 
Milner (2008) </p>

<p>433 
122 developing 
countries; 
1970-2000 </p>

<p>Fixed effects </p>

<p>FDI/GDP </p>

<p>POLCON III; </p>

<p>Polity IV 
score; Freedom 
House score </p>

<p>Yes (exclusion 
East Asian or 
transition countries) </p>

<p>Stronger political 
constraints increase </p>

<p>FDI; coefficients 
on other proxies 
are not statistically 
significant </p>

<p>Choi and 
Samy (2008) </p>

<p>47 
80 developing 
countries; 
1985-2002 
Fixed effects; 
dynamic </p>

<p>FDI/GDP </p>

<p>POLCON III </p>

<p>or Van Belle 
(1997) Global 
Press Freedom 
+ combination 
Polity IV and 
Institutional 
Investor's 
country credit </p>

<p>risk ratings </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Stronger political 
constraints increase </p>

<p>FDI; coefficients 
on other proxies 
are not statistically 
significant </p>

<p>Choi (2009) </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Replication Li </p>

<p>and Resnick 
(2003) </p>

<p>Pooled </p>

<p>FDI or 
FDI/GDP </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>Yes; DFBETAs 
leading to dummy 
variables for China </p>

<p>and Albania; robust 
regression (Àrreg-
command in <rs type="software">Stata</rs>) </p>

<p>Positive direct 
impact when 
outliers are 
controlled for </p>

<p>with or wihout 
controlling for 
property rights 
protection </p>

<p>Li (2009) </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>Replication Li </p>

<p>and Resnick 
(2003) </p>

<p>Pooled </p>

<p>FDI or 
ln(FDI + x) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>Yes; median 
regression (Àqreg-</p>

<p>in <rs type="software">Stata</rs>); use of 
ln(FDI) </p>

<p>Confirmation of </p>

<p>original results </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 1. (Continued) </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>Citations </p>

<p>Sample 
Main estimator(s) </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Main proxy (proxies) </p>

<p>Explicit control 
for outliers </p>

<p>Findings </p>

<p>Asiedu and 
Lien (2011) </p>

<p>127 
122 developing 
countries; 
1982-2007 </p>

<p>DIFF/SYS-</p>

<p>GMM; 
dynamic </p>

<p>FDI/GDP </p>

<p>Freedom House 
political rights; 
Polity IV score; 
ICRG democracy 
index </p>

<p>Positive (negative) 
direct impact of 
democracy when </p>

<p>natural resource 
abundance is low </p>

<p>(high) </p>

<p>Notes: FDI, foreign direct investent inflows. See Table 1 in Section 5 for definitions and sources of the various proxies for democracy. Citations taken from Google Scholar. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>

<p>47 </p>

<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>our econometric approach. Section 6 presents and interprets our empirical 
results. Section 7 concludes. </p>

<p>2. THE ROBUST DUMMY ESTIMATOR </p>

<p>The objective of linear regression analysis is to examine how a dependent vari-
able is linearly related to a set of explanatory variables. Technically speaking, 
it consists in estimating the vector θ of unknown parameters in: </p>

<p>y ¼ X θ þ ε; 
(1) </p>

<p>where y is the dependent variable and X is the (n × p) matrix of regressors. 
Matrix X = (X 1 , X 2 ) is composed of two blocks: X 1 , which is the (n × p 1 ) matrix 
of dummy variables, and X 2 , which is the (n × p 2 ) matrix of the continuous 
variables (p = p 1 + p 2 ). 
On the basis of the estimated parametersθ , it is possible to predict the 
dependent variableŷ and to fit the residual r i ¼ y i Àŷ i . Although θ can be 
estimated in several ways, the underlying idea is always to try to get as close 
as possible to the true model by minimizing an aggregate measure of dispersion 
of the residuals. In the case of the well-known ordinary least squares (LS) 
estimator, the measure of spread used is the variance. The vector of parameters 
estimated by LS is, therefore: </p>

<p>θ 
LS ¼ arg min </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i θ 
ð Þ: 
(2) </p>

<p>A well-known feature of the variance (and, consequently, of LS) is that it is 
extremely sensitive to the presence of outliers. To take this into account, 
Rousseuw and Yohai (1984) propose another estimator, an S-estimator, that is 
based on the minimization of another measure of dispersion, s, of the residuals, 
an M-estimator of scale. 
An M-estimator of scale is a very general class of estimators of dispersion that 
do include the variance. Indeed, the M-estimator of scale is defined as a value of 
s satisfying equality </p>

<p>1 
n </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>ρ 
r i θ 
ð Þ 
s </p>



<p>¼ δ; 
(3) </p>

<p>where δ = E[ρ(Z)] with Z ∼ N(0, 1). If we choose as ρ function the square func-</p>

<p>tion, δ = 1 and this equality becomes </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>n ∑ </p>

<p>n 
i¼1 </p>

<p>r i θ 
ð Þ 
s </p>

<p>2 
¼ 1, which can be rewritten </p>

<p>as </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>n ∑ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i¼1 r i θ 
ð Þ 
2 ¼ s 
2 , which is the definition of the variance (because r θ 
ð Þ ¼ 0). 
As previously stated, an S-estimator of regression minimizes an M-estimator 
of scale of the residuals. Because LS minimizes the variance of the residuals, 
the LS estimator is a special type of S-estimator. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>A common choice for the ρ function in equation 3 is Tukey's biweight func-
tion as defined in equation 4: </p>

<p>ρ u 
ð Þ ¼ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
1 À 1 À 
u 
k </p>

<p>2 
! 3 
! </p>

<p>if u 
j j ≤ k </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
if u 
j j &gt; k </p>

<p>8 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; : 
; 
(4) </p>

<p>where u corresponds to standardized residuals. The loss function of LS can still 
be obtained by considering a tuning parameter k going to infinity, as </p>

<p>lim k→∞ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>1 À 1 À </p>

<p>u 
k </p>

<p>À Á 2 
h 
i 3 </p>

<p>
¼ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 u 
2 : </p>

<p>To increase robustness, the loss function should award less importance to 
atypical observations (i.e. observations associated with very large residuals). 
This is obtained by reducing the value of tuning parameter k. Figure 1 shows 
Tukey's biweights function for different values of the tuning constant. In the 
LS case (k = ∞), the importance of the standardized residuals u increases with 
u. In the other cases, the importance awarded to residuals is bounded. If one sets 
the tuning parameter very low, the resistance to outliers is very high but this will 
come at a cost because the Gaussian efficiency of the estimator will be low. 
There is, therefore, a trade-off between robustness and efficiency. A common 
value for the tuning constant k is 1.546, which results in an estimator that has 
a breakdown point of 50% (i.e. an estimator that withstands a contamination 
of up to 50% of outliers before producing an arbitrary result). 
Explicit formulas forθ are generally not available and it is necessary to call 
on numerical optimization based on subsampling and iteratively reweighted al-
gorithms to find a solution to equation 3. Unfortunately, it can be shown that 
these algorithms turn out to be inapplicable when several dummy variables are 
present, as can be the case in a fixed effects panel data setting. Indeed, as </p>

<p>Figure 1. Tukey's biweights function for different values of the tuning constant (k). </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>emphasized by Maronna and Yohai (2000), subsampling algorithms can easily 
lead to collinearity within subsamples if various dummies are among the 
regressors. 
To cope with this issue, several procedures have been proposed. Rousseeuw  and Wagner (1994) propose a procedure that guarantees that individuals in all 
the categories identified by the dummies are present in the subsets, therefore 
circumventing the issue of perfect multicollinearity. This algorithm, however, 
leads to a great number of replications and, therefore, becomes excessively 
slow (and unapplicable) when data sets are large. Hubert and Rousseeuw  (1997) suggest using a multivariate outlier detection tool to identify leverage 
points (i.e. outliers in the x-dimension), which they then apply a weight zero 
to, and subsequently, to use an estimator that withstands contamination on 
the vertical dimension (such as median regression), but that does not need 
to be robust against leverage points (because these have already been re-
moved). However, they focus exclusively on continuous right-hand side 
variables. 
Finally, Maronna and Yohai (2000) propose two estimators. First is the M-
GM estimator, which is similar to that of Hubert and Rousseeuw (1997), but 
where the influence of dummies in the multivariate setup is tackled by 
partialling them out. This estimator has a low breakdown point. Second is 
the M-S estimator, which alternates two estimators: an M-estimator and an 
S-estimator. Regression monotonic M-estimators are easy to compute and 
minimize the sum of a less rapidly increasing function of the residuals than 
the quadratic loss function. The drawback of these estimators is that they 
can only be used when outliers belong to the dependent variable and there 
is no outlyingness in the space of the explanatory variables (i.e. when no le-
verage points are present). This is the case when a continuous variable is 
regressed on a set of dummy variables. In contrast, S-estimators cope well 
with leverage points but their practical implementation is often unfeasible 
when several dummies are present due to the existence of collinear subsam-
ples. The MS algorithm alternates, therefore, between an M-estimator after 
partialling-out continuous variables and an S-estimator after partialling-out 
dummy explanatory variables. The partialling-out is done using the estimated 
parameters obtained in the previous M or S step. A disadvantage of this 
method is that the algorithm has to be stopped after a set number of itera-
tions, even though there is no guarantee that no better solution would have 
appeared in further replications. Indeed, as stated by Maronna and Yohai  (2000), the scale (the measure of dispersion of the residuals) does not neces-
sarily decrease after each iteration. 
To avoid these drawbacks, we advocate working with an S-estimator that has 
good properties and that can theoretically handle dummies. However, we pro-
pose modifying the optimization code in a manner that avoids perfectly collinear 
subsamples. The algorithm is described in detail in the Appendix. Once the pa-
rameters are estimated, it is straightforward to identify outliers. This is done by 
calculating standardized residuals (i.e. robust residuals divided by their disper-
sion) and identifying those larger than a given cut-off point. The cut-off point </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>that we use is 2.25. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Having identified the outliers, we can award them a weight 
zero and run a standard LS regression. 
In the next section, we present some Monte-Carlo simulations to show the 
good behaviour of the S-estimator programmed in this way. </p>

<p>3. MONTE-CARLO SIMULATIONS </p>

<p>We run three different simulations: </p>

<p>a. For a first set of simulations, three design variables, X 1 , X 2 , X 3 and an error 
term u are generated from four N(0, 1) series. The dependent variable y is 
generated according to the data generating process (DGP): y it = X 1it + X 2it 
+ X 3it + u it . 
b. For a second set of simulations, 20 dummy variables, generated from inde-
pendent Bernouilli distributions (p = 0.5), are added to the design space. 
The DGP becomes y it ¼ X 1it þ X 2it þ X 3it þ ∑ </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>j¼1 d j þ u it : 
c. For a final set of simulations, a panel fixed effects (FE) setup is created. Var-
iables X 2 , X 3 and the error term u are generated from three independent 
N(0, 1) series. Variable X 1 and the individual constants are not independent 
and are generated in the following way: 
(i) variables X 1 and d come from a bivariate normal distribution N(μ, Σ), </p>

<p>where μ = (0, 0) and Σ ¼ 
1 0:8 </p>

<p>0:8 1 </p>

<p>! 
: </p>

<p>(ii) the d variable is modified according to transformation d = round(d * 5) 
and the DGP becomes y it = X 1it + X 2it + X 3it + d i + u it , with Corr(X 1it , 
d i ) ≠ 0. The unit-specific effects will be estimated using dummy 
variables. </p>

<p>To create outliers, 10 observations for the X 1 variable are modified and ran-
domly picked from an N(0, 10) series. For all simulations the sample size is 
200 and the number of simulations is 1000. In all simulations, y is regressed 
on the Xs and the dummies using, respectively, a robust dummy estimator (the 
S-estimator programmed using the code we propose) and a classical LS estima-
tor. We report </p>

<p>• in Figure 2, the histogram of the coefficients associated to variables X 1 , X 2 and 
X 3 , in all three scenarios. We call the estimated coefficients B 1 , B 2 and B 3 ; 
and 
• in Tables 2 and 3, the bias and the mean squared error (MSE) of the param-
eters estimated using the robust dummy estimator and the classical LS 
estimator. </p>

<p>1 If the residuals were normally distributed, values above or below these cut-off points would be 
strongly atypical because they would be 2.25 standard deviations away from the mean (which is zero 
by construction), with a probability of occurrence of 0.025. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Figure 2. Behaviour of the robust dummy estimator. </p>

<p>Table 2. Bias and MSE of the robust dummy estimator </p>

<p>Setup1 
Setup 2 
Setup 3 </p>

<p>Bias 
MSE 
Bias 
MSE 
Bias 
MSE </p>

<p>B1 
À0.004 
0.007 
À0.007 
0.016 
À0.004 
0.044 
B2 
À0.003 
0.006 
À0.01 
0.015 
À0.004 
0.016 
B3 
À0.003 
0.007 
À0.005 
0.0131 
À0.015 
0.014 </p>

<p>Note: Values for parameters B1, B2, B3: 1, 1, 1. MSE, mean squared error. </p>

<p>Table 3. Bias and MSE of the LS estimator </p>

<p>Setup 1 
Setup 2 
Setup 3 </p>

<p>Bias 
MSE 
Bias 
MSE 
Bias 
MSE </p>

<p>B1 
À0.829 
0.688 
À0.806 
0.651 
À1.001 
1.003 
B2 
À0.013 
0.006 
À0.042 
0.007 
0.003 
0.008 
B3 
À0.119 
0.020 
0.091 
0.014 
0.008 
0.010 </p>

<p>Note: Values for parameters B1, B2, B3: 1, 1, 1. MSE, mean squared error. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>As can be seen from the simulations, the robust dummy estimator behaves 
well when dummies are present. All estimated coefficients are normally dis-
tributed (Fig. 2) and the bias and MSE are minimal (Tables 2 and 3). In 
contrast, and as expected, the least squares estimator behaves poorly in 
every scenario. 
Having shown the good behaviour of our robust-to-outliers dummy estima-
tor, we now investigate the robustness of the findings of a key study on the rela-
tionship between FDI and democracy. </p>

<p>4. REPLICATION </p>

<p>According to Google Scholar, Jensen (2003) is the most cited empirical study on 
the relationship between FDI and democracy. It has been cited 650 times, and, 
as shown in Figure 3, it remains a key reference today. In this section, we inves-
tigate the robustness of this study's findings to outliers. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The sample covers 112 
countries over the period 1970-1997, the dependent variable is FDI inflows as a 
share of GDP, and the proxy for democracy is Polity IV score (see Table 5 for a 
description). We focus on the key regression of the paper: model 10 in Table 4. 
The estimates suggest that a fully autocratic government (score of 0) becoming 
fully democratic (score of 20) can be expected to attract 0.4% more FDI flows 
as a percentage of GDP). Given that the average level of FDI flows in the 
sample is 1.3% of GDP, this is a sizeable amount. 
Table 4 presents our results. Column (1) replicates perfectly the estimates 
found in Jensen (2003). In column (2), we remove the observations identified 
as outliers by the Cook distance, which is a scaled measure of the distance be-
tween the coefficient vectors when a given observation is omitted. Five percent 
of the observations are deemed to be outliers. Their omission has no qualitative 
impact on the results. In column (3) we use an M-estimator, which gives a lower 
weight to observations with large standardized residuals but is not robust to le-
verage points. The estimated impact of democracy falls by half. In column (4), 
the M-estimator is used again, but the sample now only includes observations 
that have not been identified as outliers, and, therefore, potential leverage 
points, in column (2). This is essentially what the <rs type="software">Stata</rs> command -rreg-is doing. 
Results are similar to those in column (4). </p>

<p>Figure 3. Citations of Jensen (2003). </p>

<p>2 Data are downloaded from Nathan Jensen's website (http://www.natemjensen.com/replication-
data/). </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 4. The sensitivity of Jensen (2003)   findings to outliers </p>

<p>Dependent variable: FDI inflows/GDP </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>R-FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>MS </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>R-FE </p>

<p>Omission 
'Cook' 
outliers </p>

<p>Omission 
'Cook' 
outliers </p>

<p>Outliers 
only </p>

<p>Omission 
transition 
countries </p>

<p>Interaction 
regional 
dummies </p>

<p>Interaction 
regional 
dummies </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>Lagged FDI </p>

<p>0.364*** 
(0.072) </p>

<p>0.451*** 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.498*** 
(0.036) </p>

<p>0.509*** 
(0.022) </p>

<p>0.601*** 
(0.016) </p>

<p>0.200* 
(0.106) </p>

<p>0.583*** 
(0.014) </p>

<p>0.356*** 
(0.072) </p>

<p>0.328*** 
(0.061) </p>

<p>0.522*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>Market size </p>

<p>À0.554 
(0.448) </p>

<p>À0.498** 
(0.242) </p>

<p>À0.267 
(0.188) </p>

<p>À0.287* 
(0.151) </p>

<p>À0.055 
(0.081) </p>

<p>0.063 
(1.713) </p>

<p>À0.021 
(0.078) </p>

<p>À0.184 
(0.432) </p>

<p>À0.212 
(0.251) </p>

<p>0.178* 
(0.093) </p>

<p>Growth </p>

<p>0.024*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.013*** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.010*** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.009*** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.003* 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.086*** 
(0.025) </p>

<p>0.004* 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.026*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.023*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.003*** 
(0.001) </p>

<p>Development level </p>

<p>0.834* 
(0.447) </p>

<p>0.782*** 
(0.279) </p>

<p>0.508** 
(0.203) </p>

<p>0.519*** 
(0.170) </p>

<p>0.180* 
(0.097) </p>

<p>0.250 
(1.673) </p>

<p>0.111 
(0.092) </p>

<p>0.477 
(0.420) </p>

<p>0.669** 
(0.297) </p>

<p>À0.020 
(0.113) </p>

<p>Budget deficit </p>

<p>À0.023** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>À0.000 
(0.005) </p>

<p>0.003 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.003) </p>

<p>À0.002 
(0.002) </p>

<p>À0.077** 
(0.033) </p>

<p>0.000 
(0.002) </p>

<p>À0.021** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>À0.024** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.002) </p>

<p>Government 
consumption </p>

<p>À0.039** 
(0.017) </p>

<p>À0.024*** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>À0.010 
(0.007) </p>

<p>À0.009 
(0.006) </p>

<p>À0.005 
(0.004) </p>

<p>À0.074 
(0.058) </p>

<p>À0.006 
(0.004) </p>

<p>À0.044** 
(0.017) </p>

<p>À0.042*** 
(0.014) </p>

<p>À0.002 
(0.003) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>0.021*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.021*** 
(0.006) </p>

<p>0.011*** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.011*** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.005** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.037 
(0.043) </p>

<p>0.006** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.008) </p>

<p>À0.008 
(0.006) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.002) </p>

<p>Eighties </p>

<p>À0.077 
(0.187) </p>

<p>À0.042 
(0.076) </p>

<p>À0.040 
(0.075) </p>

<p>À0.034 
(0.052) </p>

<p>À0.035 
(0.025) </p>

<p>À0.334 
(0.714) </p>

<p>À0.008 
(0.031) </p>

<p>À0.106 
(0.185) </p>

<p>À0.188 
(0.151) </p>

<p>À0.051* 
(0.027) </p>

<p>Nineties </p>

<p>0.263 
(0.289) </p>

<p>0.131 
(0.125) </p>

<p>0.102 
(0.116) </p>

<p>0.081 
(0.082) </p>

<p>0.030 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.021 
(1.159) </p>

<p>0.090** 
(0.046) </p>

<p>0.144 
(0.289) </p>

<p>À0.091 
(0.337) </p>

<p>À0.029 
(0.040) </p>

<p>Nineties × EAS </p>

<p>2.624*** 
(0.394) </p>

<p>1.852*** 
(0.068) </p>

<p>Nineties × SSA </p>

<p>À0.280 
(0.231) </p>

<p>À0.166*** 
(0.044) </p>

<p>Nineties × LAC </p>

<p>1.055*** 
(0.316) </p>

<p>0.332*** 
(0.044) </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 4. (Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: FDI inflows/GDP </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>R-FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>MS </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>R-FE </p>

<p>Omission 
'Cook' 
outliers </p>

<p>Omission 
'Cook' 
outliers </p>

<p>Outliers 
only </p>

<p>Omission 
transition 
countries </p>

<p>Interaction 
regional 
dummies </p>

<p>Interaction 
regional 
dummies </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>1628 </p>

<p>1541 </p>

<p>1628 </p>

<p>1541 </p>

<p>1229 </p>

<p>399 </p>

<p>1257 </p>

<p>1562 </p>

<p>1628 </p>

<p>1227 </p>

<p>Number of countries </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>112 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.613 </p>

<p>0.798 </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>0.873 </p>

<p>0.945 </p>

<p>0.518 </p>

<p>0.944 </p>

<p>0.612 </p>

<p>0.627 </p>

<p>0.951 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Cluster-robust standard errors are in parentheses. Country </p>

<p>fixed effects are included but not reported. FE, standard </p>

<p>fixed effects </p>

<p>estimator; R-FE, robust 
fixed effects estimator; M-S, estimator of regression, another robust 
fitting approach; M, Huber M-estimator of regression, robust to vertical outliers </p>

<p>only. Cook, Cook distance: a diagnostic tool to detect outliers after estimation by OLS. Eighties: dummy variable for period 1980-1999; Nineties: dummy variable for period 
1990-1997. EAS: dummy variable for transition countries; SSA: dummy variable for Sub-Saharan African countries; LAC: dummy variable for Latin American and Caribbean 
countries. Estimation of model 10 in Table 4 of Jensen (2003) using various robust estimators and different specifications. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>In column (5), we now use our robust-to-outliers dummy estimator. The coef-
ficient on democracy remains positive and statistically significant. However, the 
estimated effect of democracy on FDI is only 25% of the magnitude of the initial 
estimate. A fully autocratic government becoming fully democratic can now be 
expected to attract only 0.1% more FDI flows as a percentage of GDP. It is 
worth noting than the fit of this regression is much better than that of column 
(1): the R 
2 increases from 0.613 to 0.945. This reflects the fact that a sizeable 
number of observations (25%) are not well explained by the empirical model. 
In column (6), the model is estimated using the outlying observations. It can 
be seen that the vast majority of countries had experienced atypical FDI flows. 
These episodes are not well predicted by past FDI flows and tend to coincide 
with changes in economic growth and fiscal stance. In column (7), we use the 
MS estimator. Results are very close to those in column (5). </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Figure 4 provides a way of assessing the most outlying countries. Countries 
are classified as outliers when the value of the mean of the residuals standardized 
by a robust estimate of their standard deviation is greater than 2.25 (dashed 
lines). The most outlying countries tend to be small countries, located in Eastern 
Europe, Latin America or Sub-Saharan Africa. It is often not straightforward to 
explain why some observations are outliers. However, in the case of Eastern 
Europe countries, it is easy to interpret their atypical behaviour as the conse-
quence of the fall of the Berlin Wall, and their subsequent adoption of 
market-based economic systems with mixed results. Figure 5 shows that the 
Eastern Europe countries in the sample experienced a boom in FDI and rapid 
democratization after the year 1989, despite deteriorating macroeconomic con-
ditions. These two concomitant trends may explain the positive relationship be-
tween FDI and democracy identified in column (1). </p>

<p>3 In the final estimation stage, the M-S estimator uses all (weighted) observations, whereas our ro-
bust dummy estimator omits identified outliers. This explains why the reported number of observa-
tions is different in columns (5) and (7). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Large outliers. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>We investigate this possibility in column (8) where we remove Eastern Euro-
pean countries from the sample (4% of the observations). We now fail to find 
a statistically significant impact of democracy on FDI. It could be argued that 
these observations provide valuable information because they could be 
interpreted as encompassing a 'natural experiment' on the effects of democracy 
on FDI. Hence, in column (9), we use the full sample but we include interaction 
terms between the nineties dummy variable and three regional dummy variables 
(EAS, Eastern Europe; SSA, Sub-Saharan Africa; LAC, Latin America and the 
Carribean). In that way, we control for common effects in each region that may 
influence FDI and may also be correlated with democracy. The coefficients on 
the interaction terms indicate that the EAS and LAC regions have, indeed, 
attracted, holding other factors constant, much more FDI than other regions 
in the nineties. Once we control for these regional effects, the coefficient on de-
mocracy becomes negative and statistically insignificant, suggesting that democ-
ratization occurred at the same time as the improvement of the business 
environment for foreign investors, but did not have a direct effect on a country's 
attractiveness. Finally, in column (10), we estimate the model of column (9) 
using our robust-to-outliers dummy estimator. Relative to column (5), the num-
ber of outliers identified is roughly the same but we now fail to find a statistically 
significant impact of democracy on FDI. 
To sum up, we initially found that the estimated impact of democracy on FDI 
put forward by Jensen (2003) is reduced by three-quarters when we control for 
outliers. The outlying observations were not identified by common robust 
methods and diagnostic tools. Analysis of the outliers suggested the adoption 
of a more flexible model, which took into account that some regions have expe-
rienced dramatic changes in their political and economic conditions. When we 
did so, controlling for outliers or not, we failed to find a statistically significant 
positive impact of democracy on FDI. Hence, the findings of Jensen (2003) </p>

<p>Figure 5. Key indicators for transition countries.Note: FDI, foreign direct 
investment. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>seems to stem from model misspecification (a restrictive empirical model) that 
we were able to identify and mitigate thanks to our robust-to-outliers dummy 
estimator. 
We now turn to our contribution to the empirical literature. </p>

<p>5. EFFECTS OF DEMOCRACY ON FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT: EMPIRICAL 
MODEL AND DATA </p>

<p>Democracy is an elusive concept. Schumpeter (1942, p. 250) adopted a minimal-
ist perspective by defining it as 'the institutional arrangement for arriving at po-
litical decisions in which individuals acquire the power to decide by means of a 
competitive struggle for the people's vote'. His vision revolves around the exis-
tence of contested elections, which can be interpreted as a disciplining device, 
but does not involve any reference to the institutional arrangements constraining 
the abuse of political powers between elections. These constitutional checks and 
balances are, nevertheless, often judged to be a vital democratic attribute 
(Munck and Verkuilen, 2002). Media freedom is also perceived as a crucial com-
ponent of a well-functioning democracy as it guarantees that formal and real ac-
countability overlap. The various proxies that we use in this paper cover these 
various aspects of democracy. Table 5 provides detailed information on each 
measure. To facilitate comparison of estimates, we normalize all variables: each 
proxy of democracy is rescaled to have a mean of zero and a standard deviation 
of one. 
We will test each of these democracies' proxies, using the following fixed 
effects dynamic panel data model: </p>

<p>ln FDI 
ð 
Þ it ¼ γ 1 ln FDI 
ð 
Þ itÀ1 þ β 1 Democracy it þ β 2 Regulatory Quality it 
þβ 3 ln GDP 
ð 
Þ it þ β 4 ln POP 
ð 
Þ it þ C i þ T t þ ε it </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>where C i are time-invariant country-specific effects, T t are country-invariant 
time effects and ε it is the error term. Our measure of FDI is the log of financial 
FDI stock (liabilities), which have been carefully compiled for a large sample of 
countries over the period 1970-2006 by Lane and Milesi-Ferretti (2007). Note 
that unlike the studies reported in Table 1, we use FDI stocks instead of FDI 
flows. As explained by Egger and Merlo (2007), theoretical models of FDI sug-
gest that this is the appropriate dependent variable; change in the value of a 
given determinant leads to FDI flows until a new steady-state FDI stock is 
reached. 
We wish to keep the sample constant across all regressors. Data for the 
Worldwide Governance Indicators (WGI) voice and accountability indicator 
start in 1996, and are only available in even years from 1998 to 2002. We de-
cided, therefore, to work with the same 2-year interval data set, whichever the 
measure of democracy tested. Overall, our sample covers 111 developing coun-
tries and 5 years: 1998, 2000, 2002, 2004 and 2006. For each country, we have, 
therefore, a maximum of five observations. 
This short time dimension of our panel, the presence of a lagged dependent 
variable and the inclusion of fixed effects, motivate us to keep our empirical </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 5. Various proxies of democracy </p>

<p>Full name </p>

<p>Database name </p>

<p>Source </p>

<p>Definition </p>

<p>Original scale 
(worst to best) </p>

<p>Availability </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>POLITY2 </p>

<p>Marshall </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(2010) 
Computed as subtracting the autocracy score form the democracy </p>

<p>score. Both scores are derived from codings of the competitiveness </p>

<p>of political participation, the openness and competitiveness of 
executive recruitment, and constraints on the chief executive. </p>

<p>À10 to 10 </p>

<p>167 countries; 
1800-2014 </p>

<p>Freedom House </p>

<p>(FH) political 
rights </p>

<p>PR </p>

<p>Freedom House 
(2010b) 
Based on a checklist of 10 political rights questions. The political 
rights questions are grouped into three subcategories: electoral 
process, political pluralism and participation, functioning of 
government. </p>

<p>7 to 1 </p>

<p>195 countries; 
1973-2015 </p>

<p>Polity IV 
constraints on 
executive </p>

<p>XCONST </p>

<p>Marshall </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(2010) 
Extent of institutionalized constraints on the decision-making 
powers of chief executives, whether individuals or collectivities. 
Such limitations may be imposed by any </p>

<p>'accountability groups'. </p>

<p>1 to 7 </p>

<p>167 countries; 
1800-2014 </p>

<p>Henisz 
political 
constraints </p>

<p>POLCONIII 
Henisz (2000) 
Degree of constraints on policy change using data on the number </p>

<p>of independent veto points in the policy system (executive, 
legislative, judicial, and sub-federal branches of government) and </p>

<p>the distribution of political preferences both across and within 
these branches. </p>

<p>0 to 1 </p>

<p>208 countries; 
1800-2012 </p>

<p>Database of 
Political 
Institutions </p>

<p>(DPI) checks 
and balances </p>

<p>CHECKS </p>

<p>Beck et al. 
(2001) 
Number of veto players in a political system, adjusting for 
whether these veto players are independent of each other, as 
determined by the level of electoral competitiveness in a </p>

<p>system, their respective party affiliation, and the electoral rules. </p>

<p>1 to 18 </p>

<p>181 countries; 
1975-2012 </p>

<p>Worldwide 
governance 
indicators (WGI) </p>

<p>voice and 
accountability </p>

<p>VA </p>

<p>Kaufmann </p>

<p>et al. </p>

<p>(2004) 
Perceptions of the extent to which a country's citizens are able </p>

<p>to participate in selecting their government, as well as freedom 
of expression, freedom of association, and a free media. 
Aggregation of 32 different measures of democracy. </p>

<p>À2.5 to 2.5 </p>

<p>215 countries; 
1996-2013 </p>

<p>Freedom House </p>

<p>(FH) press 
freedom </p>

<p>GLOBAL </p>

<p>Freedom House 
(2010a) 
Assesses the degree of print, broadcast, and internet freedom </p>

<p>100 to 0 </p>

<p>199 countries; 
1980-2015 </p>

<p>Notes: In the empirical analysis, all variables are standardized; they have been rescaled to have a mean of zero and a standard deviation of one. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>model parsimonious. In addition to democracy, we control for four other vari-
ables. The lagged dependent variable captures the sluggish adjustment of FDI 
stocks towards their long-run levels over time (Kinoshita and Mody, 2001). 
Market size (GDP) is the most accepted determinant of FDI (Chakrabarti,  2001). The combination of GDP and population size allows us to control for 
the level of development, which can be seen as a catchall proxy for various fac-
tors attracting or deterring FDI (e.g. consumers' purchasing power or labour 
costs; Benassy-Quere et al., 2007; Cheung and Qian, 2009; Lane, 2015). Finally, 
we include the World Bank governance measure of regulatory quality. This gov-
ernance dimension has frequently been found to be one of the most statistically 
significant institutional determinants of FDI (Globerman and Shapiro, 2003;  Daude and Stein, 2007) and is well-correlated with the different measures of de-
mocracy (r≃0:60). We do not include other governance variables because we do 
not want to eliminate the channels of influence through which democratic 
changes can influence FDI (e.g. a strengthening of property rights protection). 
Finally, we assume that other FDI determinants are captured adequately by 
the fixed effects, including time-invariant country characteristics that may be 
correlated with democracy. 
It could be argued that the time-series dimension of our panel is too short to 
identify the impact of democracy on FDI through the investigation of how 
changes in FDI are related to changes in democracy. However, Table 6 shows 
that the within variation of the measures of democracy is relatively high, with 
values ranging between one-third and half of the between-variation. This rela-
tively high time-series variation indicates that many countries have experienced 
changes in their political regimes over the period 1998-2006. In more economet-
ric terms, although we do not exploit the between-variation of the data, the 
within-variation of the data is high enough to allow the relatively precise identi-
fication of the parameters of our empirical model. 
It is well known that the fixed effects estimator for dynamic panel models is 
biased and inconsistent for fixed T time periods, due to the correlation of the 
within transformed lagged dependent variable with the within transformed er-
ror term (Nickell, 1981). Using instrumental variables methods to obtain con-
sistent estimates would singularly complicate the implementation of our </p>

<p>Table 6. Between and within components of the standard deviations of democratic 
proxies </p>

<p>Measure 
Between 
Within 
Ratio B/W </p>

<p>Polity IV score 
0.95 
0.26 
0.27 
FH political rights 
0.95 
0.29 
0.31 
Polity IV constraints on executive 
0.95 
0.30 
0.32 
Henisz strength of veto players 
0.90 
0.43 
0.48 
DPI strength of veto players 
0.92 
0.40 
0.43 
FH press freedom 
0.93 
0.33 
0.35 
WGI voice and accountability 
0.96 
0.24 
0.25 </p>

<p>Notes: DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FH, Freedom House; WGI, Worldwide Governance Indi-
cator. Between-variation: standard deviation of x i . Within variation: standard deviation of (x it À x i Þ.) </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>robust-to-outliers dummy estimator and distract us from our main focus. We 
circumvent this issue by constraining γ 1 = 0.75, which is the value that we ob-
tain when we estimate this coefficient over the 1980-2006 period for our sam-
ple of countries, using a robust application (see Desbordes and Verardim 
2011) of the Anderson and Hsiao (1981) dynamic panel data estimator. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6. EMPIRICAL RESULTS </p>

<p>6.1. Baseline results </p>

<p>Our initial empirical results are presented in Table 7. For each measure of de-
mocracy, we provide the classical FE estimates, the robust dummy (R-FE) esti-
mates, and, for comparison, Maronna and Yohai (2000) M-S estimates. 
Supporters of democracy would find the FE estimates extremely disappoint-
ing as no democratic attribute appears to exert a substantial and statistically sig-
nificant effect on FDI. Furthermore, it is disconcerting to find that GDP, the 
most robust FDI determinant in the literature, is not statistically significant. In 
contrast, the R-FE estimates paint a much different and nuanced picture. For 
most proxies, democracy appears to have a positive and statistically significant 
impact on FDI. A one standard deviation increase in democracy would increase 
FDI by approximately 3-10% in the short run. These effects are not negligible 
because they are equivalent to a 20-40% rise in GDP (holding population con-
stant), which is now also a statistically significant determinant of FDI, along 
with population. Foreign investors seem to be particularly attracted by countries 
in which political decisions become more constrained by institutional checks and 
balances and greater media freedom. Column (8 
0 ) of Table 7 shows that a free 
press trumps other democratic attributes defining a 'liberal democracy', includ-
ing checks and balances. 
Media freedom does not necessarily coincide with free and fair elections 
(r ≈ 0.82) or the level of political constraints faced by policy-makers (r ≈ 0.49). 
In other words, autocracies and (partially) free media seem compatible. Egorov  et al. (2009) suggest that this coexistence results from the need for an autocrat to 
obtain some independent feedback on the performance of the bureaucracy. In 
column (9 
0 ) of Table 7, the Freedom House (FH) Press Freedom index is 
decomposed into its three subcategories: (1) legal environment, which assesses 
'both and examination of the laws and regulations that could influence media 
content as well as the government's inclination to use these laws and legal insti-
tutions in order to restrict the media's ability to operate'; (2) political environ-
ment, which measures 'the degree of political control over the content of news 
media'; 3) economic environment, which is related to 'the economic consider-
ations that can influence the media's activities' (Freedom House, 2010a, pp. 
12-13). Only the last two dimensions appear to be significant FDI determinants. 
Freille et al. (2007) find a similar outcome when investigating the impact of </p>

<p>4 Due to data availability, the estimated empirical model did not include the World Bank gover-
nance measure of regulatory quality. Results are similar when we use different values within the 
95% confidence interval [0.77,0.84] of the coefficient. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 7. Foreign direct investment (FDI) and democracy </p>

<p>Dependent variable: </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (1) </p>

<p>R-FE (1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) M-S (1″) </p>

<p>FE (2) </p>

<p>R-FE (2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) M-S (2″) </p>

<p>FE (3) </p>

<p>R-FE (3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) M-S (3″) </p>

<p>FE (4) </p>

<p>R-FE (4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) M-S (4″) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>0.014 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.031** 
(0.015) </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.020) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>À0.002 
(0.028) </p>

<p>À0.007 
(0.013) </p>

<p>À0.023** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>Polity IV 
constraints </p>

<p>on executive </p>

<p>0.020 
(0.032) </p>

<p>0.090*** 
(0.020) </p>

<p>0.012 
(0.014) </p>

<p>Henisz political 
constraints </p>

<p>À0.022 
(0.018) </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>(0.009) </p>

<p>À0.019*** </p>

<p>(0.006) </p>

<p>ln(market size) </p>

<p>0.155 
(0.102) </p>

<p>0.160*** 
(0.038) </p>

<p>0.201*** 
(0.048) </p>

<p>0.155 
(0.103) </p>

<p>0.176*** 
(0.033) </p>

<p>0.205*** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>0.157 
(0.102) </p>

<p>0.217*** 
(0.029) </p>

<p>0.179*** 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.153 
(0.100) </p>

<p>0.172*** </p>

<p>(0.035) </p>

<p>0.200*** </p>

<p>(0.034) </p>

<p>ln(population) </p>

<p>À0.149 
(0.509) </p>

<p>À0.950*** 
(0.117) </p>

<p>À0.555*** 
(0.089) </p>

<p>À0.124 
(0.488) </p>

<p>À1.007*** 
(0.123) </p>

<p>À0.586*** 
(0.013) </p>

<p>À0.157 
(0.507) </p>

<p>À0.626*** 
(0.125) </p>

<p>À0.571*** 
(0.073) </p>

<p>À0.109 
(0.492) </p>

<p>À1.024*** </p>

<p>(0.123) </p>

<p>À0.520*** </p>

<p>(0.053) </p>

<p>WGI Regulatory 
Quality </p>

<p>0.121*** 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.072*** 
(0.018) </p>

<p>0.037*** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>0.123*** 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.078*** 
(0.018) </p>

<p>0.036** 
(0.016) </p>

<p>0.119*** 
(0.040) </p>

<p>0.109*** 
(0.015) </p>

<p>0.039*** 
(0.013) </p>

<p>0.126*** 
(0.038) </p>

<p>0.074*** </p>

<p>(0.019) </p>

<p>0.039*** </p>

<p>(0.009) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>357 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>358 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>352 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>357 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>0.821 </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p>0.822 </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (5) </p>

<p>R-FE (5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (5″) </p>

<p>FE (6) </p>

<p>R-FE (6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (6″) </p>

<p>FE (7) </p>

<p>R-FE (7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (7″) </p>

<p>R-FE (8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R-FE (9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>À0.005 
(0.021) </p>

<p>DPI checks and 
balances </p>

<p>À0.024 
(0.021) </p>

<p>0.032*** 
(0.012) </p>

<p>0.057*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.026) </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 7. (Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (5) </p>

<p>R-FE (5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (5″) </p>

<p>FE (6) </p>

<p>R-FE (6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (6″) </p>

<p>FE (7) </p>

<p>R-FE (7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
M-S (7″) </p>

<p>R-FE (8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R-FE (9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FH press freedom </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.026) </p>

<p>0.057*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.040*** 
(0.014) </p>

<p>0.067*** 
(0.020) </p>

<p>WGI voice and 
accountability </p>

<p>À0.007 
(0.040) </p>

<p>0.087*** 
(0.020) </p>

<p>0.103*** 
(0.022) </p>

<p>FHP legal 
environment </p>

<p>0.013 
(0.011) </p>

<p>FHP political 
environment </p>

<p>0.035*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>FHP economic 
environment </p>

<p>0.029*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>ln(market size) </p>

<p>0.144 
(0.100) </p>

<p>0.218*** 
(0.029) </p>

<p>0.209*** 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.153 
(0.102) </p>

<p>0.248*** 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.225 
(0.181) </p>

<p>0.154 
(0.103) </p>

<p>0.194*** 
(0.046) </p>

<p>0.121 
(0.098) </p>

<p>0.182*** 
(0.054) </p>

<p>0.173*** 
(0.036) </p>

<p>ln(population) </p>

<p>À0.128 
(0.486) </p>

<p>À0.711*** 
(0.127) </p>

<p>À0.800*** 
(0.063) </p>

<p>À0.136 
(0.509) </p>

<p>À0.813*** 
(0.115) </p>

<p>À0.663* 
(0.338) </p>

<p>À0.119 
(0.510) </p>

<p>À0.768*** 
(0.147) </p>

<p>À0.707*** 
(0.189) </p>

<p>À0.817 
(0.189) </p>

<p>À0.713 
(0.114) </p>

<p>WGI regulatory 
quality </p>

<p>0.130*** 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.036** 
(0.014) </p>

<p>À0.015 
(0.021) </p>

<p>0.122*** 
(0.039) </p>

<p>0.100*** 
(0.014) </p>

<p>0.050 
(0.087) </p>

<p>0.124*** 
(0.038) </p>

<p>0.088*** 
(0.016) </p>

<p>0.036 
(0.042) </p>

<p>0.071*** 
(0.027) </p>

<p>0.120*** 
(0.012) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>352 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>351 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>331 </p>

<p>349 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>108 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.819 </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.825 </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>0.980 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Cluster-robust standard errors are in parentheses, except when the M-S estimator is used (heteroskedasticity-robust only). Time and </p>

<p>country effects are included but not reported. FDI, foreign direct investment; FH, Freedom House. For each proxy of democracy, the empirical model is estimated using a (i) 
standard 
fixed effects estimator (FE); (ii) our robust 
fixed effects estimator (R-FE); and (iii) a M-S estimator of regression (M-S), another robust </p>

<p>fitting approach. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>media freedom on corruption. Overall, these results suggest that the key factor 
that explains why democracies attract more FDI than autocracies is their ten-
dency to exhibit greater media freedom, which presumably restrains bureau-
cratic corruption and enhances policy transparency. From another perspective, 
an autocracy can be as successful as a democracy in terms of attracting FDI 
as long as these two outcomes are met; the success of Singapore immediately 
comes to mind. 
The other dimension of public governance, regulatory quality, always exerts a 
positive and statistically significant impact on FDI, whatever the estimator used, 
although its influence appears to be smaller when outliers are controlled for. 
Based on column (6 
0 ), a one standard deviation improvement in the quality of 
regulations would have approximately twice the short-run positive impact as a 
one standard deviation move towards more media freedom (10%). Amin and  Djankov (2009) show that democratic regimes tend to favour pro-business 
microeconomic reforms. On this basis, it is likely that the direct impact of 
democracy on FDI that we have estimated represents a lower bound effect 
because it does not account for the positive impact of democracy via better 
regulatory quality. 
For each regression, approximately 28% of the observations are flagged as 
outliers by the R-FE estimator. As can be seen at the bottom of Table 7, many 
countries are occasionally outliers during the period 1996-2006. Predominant 
sources of R-FE and M-S outliers for regressions (7 
0 ) and (7″) can be observed in 
Figure 6a. This Figure indicates the countries for which the average standard-
ized residual is outside the non-outlying range delimited by the two horizontal 
lines. When [only] the median standardized residual is also outside this range, 
a square [triangle] is used instead of a circle. The two estimators tend to identify 
the same countries as sources of large outliers although divergences occur. For 
example, the R-FE estimator considers that some observations related to Haiti 
are large outliers, whereas this is not the case for the MS estimator. The choice </p>

<p>Figure 6. Identification of outliers: (a) R-FE estimator and (b) M-S estimator. 
Notes: Circle: value of the average standardized residual smaller than À2.25 or 
greater than 2.25. Triangle: value of the median standardized residual smaller than 
À2.25 or greater than 2.25. Square: values of both the average and median stan-
dardized residuals smaller than À2.25 or greater than 2.25. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>between these two estimators can be based on the R 
2 values, reported at the bot-
tom of Table 7. It can be seen that the R-FE estimator drastically increases the 
fit of the empirical model, whereas this is not true for the MS-estimator. Hence, 
the former estimator seems more suitable to explain the typical response of FDI 
to democratic changes. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The presence of few squares and triangles in the left and right panels of 
Figure 6 shows that very few countries are block concentrated outliers (Bramati  and Croux, 2007); that is, for most countries, the volume of FDI that they re-
ceived was, most of the time, well predicted by the empirical model estimated. 
For regression (7), the block outliers are Djibouti and Lybia. Interestingly, the 
FDI performance of the so-called BRICS countries, </p>

<p>6   which accounted for 
48% of the change in total FDI liabilities during the sample period, does not 
appear to have been atypical, despite the fact that some studies have frequently 
suggested that they are outliers (Choi, 2009). Hence, contrary to some of the 
worries raised in the political science literature (Li, 2009), the use of robust 
regression methods does not necessarily imply a drastic loss of coverage of the 
activities of foreign investors. Large FDI recipients are not necessary outliers, 
as long as the empirical model is reasonably well specified. 
The use of summary statistics in Figure 6a is not informative about the FDI 
trajectory of 'atypical' countries and obscures the fact that not all observations 
related to these countries are outliers. Figure 7 illustrates these two issues by 
plotting the yearly standardized residuals for four countries previously flagged 
as source of outliers. It shows that the empirical model was unable to explain 
the large fluctuations in FDI received by countries like Botswana (BWA) or 
Zambia (ZMB) over the period 1998-2006 or the greater attractiveness of </p>

<p>5 An additional advantage of our estimator is that it allows easy correction of the standard errors for 
clustering. </p>

<p>Figure 7. Foreign direct investment attractiveness of four atypical countries. </p>

<p>6 BRICS countries are Brazil, Russia, India, China and South Africa. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Zambia (ZMB) or Tajikistan (TJK) after the year 2002. Figure 7 reflects the dif-
ficulty for the researcher to model the economic developments of heterogenous 
countries with a parsimonious set of control variables; the empirical model 
may explain well the average response but necessarily struggle to account for 
country-specific idiosyncracies. </p>

<p>6.2. Democracy and natural resources </p>

<p>Asiedu and Lien (2011) argue that democracy promotes FDI only in non-
resource exporting countries. Their rationale, supported by their empirical anal-
ysis is that, in resource-exporting countries, which tend to attract FDI mainly 
concentrated in extractive industries, foreign investors prefer the stability and 
easy access to natural resources that an autocracy presumably offers. This is a 
remarkable finding as it goes against the alleged benefits of democracy outlined 
in the Introduction and because Guriev et al. (2011) and Jensen and Johnston  (2011) have shown that autocracies are more likely to expropriate foreign inves-
tors, including in the petroleum, natural gas and mining sectors. Nevertheless, 
we re-estimate our econometric model, which now includes the proxy of Asiedu 
and Lien (2011) for natural resource rich countries, the share of fuel and min-
erals in total merchandise exports, and its interaction with our different mea-
sures of democracy. Data on exports come from UNCTAD. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Table 8 shows that estimates based on the classical FE estimator would, to a 
certain extent, support the arguments of Asiedu and Lien (2011). However, once 
again, the R-FE estimates tell a different story. In most regressions, the coeffi-
cient on the interaction term is positive, large, and statistically significant, indi-
cating that the higher a country's natural resource export intensity, the more 
positive the effect of democracy on FDI. Figure 8 summarizes the relationship 
between the effect of democracy on FDI and natural resource abundance; the 
impact of democracy is presented at different deciles of the share of fuel and 
minerals in total merchandise exports. For high levels of natural resources, 
whichever the measure of democracy employed, the impact of greater democ-
racy is positive, statistically significant and substantially much larger than in 
resource-poor countries. 
The negative association between violent conflicts and democracy may ex-
plain why the latter matters particularly for FDI in extractive industries. Given 
the high sunk costs that foreign firms in the mining and oil sectors incur, they are 
likely to be strongly deterred by violent sociopolitical instability and other forms 
of destructive conflicts (e.g. riots and guerilla warfare) that threaten their assets 
(Barham et al., 1998). Democracy may reduce social and political unrest, which 
may also be more likely in resource-exporting countries. 
From an exogenous perspective, it can be expected that democracy provides 
to dissatisfied groups both the political opportunity to become actively involved 
into the decision-making progress and peaceful channels of expression to voice </p>

<p>7 Data available from: http://unctadstat.unctad.org/. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 8. Foreign direct investment (FDI), democracy and natural resource abundance </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (1) </p>

<p>R-FE (1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (2) </p>

<p>R-FE (2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (3) </p>

<p>R-FE (3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (4) </p>

<p>R-FE (4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>À0.006 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.358*** 
(0.041) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.027) </p>

<p>À0.017 
(0.015) </p>

<p>Polity IV constraints 
on executive </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.031) </p>

<p>0.115*** 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Henisz political 
constraints </p>

<p>À0.017 
(0.022) </p>

<p>À0.002 
(0.012) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À0.144 
(0.099) </p>

<p>À0.215*** 
(0.057) </p>

<p>À0.189* 
(0.105) </p>

<p>À0.115*** 
(0.040) </p>

<p>À0.136 
(0.107) </p>

<p>À0.189*** 
(0.056) </p>

<p>À0.191** 
(0.095) </p>

<p>À0.251*** 
(0.058) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>0.075 
(0.067) </p>

<p>0.318*** 
(0.052) </p>

<p>À0.021 
(0.078) </p>

<p>0.117*** 
(0.038) </p>

<p>0.075 
(0.075) </p>

<p>0.220*** 
(0.046) </p>

<p>À0.019 
(0.054) </p>

<p>0.136*** 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>348 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>345 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>341 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>345 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>107 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.993 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.857 </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p>0.857 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>FE (5) </p>

<p>RÀFE (5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (6) </p>

<p>RÀFE (6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (7) </p>

<p>RÀFE (7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R 
ÀFE (8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>À0.015 
(0.027) </p>

<p>DPI checks and 
balances </p>

<p>À0.013 
(0.026) </p>

<p>À0.022 
(0.015) </p>

<p>À0.057** 
(0.022) </p>

<p>FH press freedom </p>

<p>0.009 
(0.022) </p>

<p>0.041*** 
(0.015) </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.026) </p>

<p>WGI voice and 
accountability </p>

<p>0.013 
(0.033) </p>

<p>0.054*** 
(0.018) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À0.176* 
(0.091) </p>

<p>À0.060 
(0.048) </p>

<p>À0.189 
(0.120) </p>

<p>À0.034 
(0.050) </p>

<p>À0.221** 
(0.111) </p>

<p>À0.105** 
(0.041) </p>

<p>À0.356*** 
(0.092) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.028 
(0.069) </p>

<p>0.175*** 
(0.025) </p>

<p>À0.023 
(0.109) </p>

<p>0.062 
(0.047) </p>

<p>À0.068 
(0.081) </p>

<p>0.061* 
(0.034) </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 8. (Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (1) </p>

<p>R-FE (1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (2) </p>

<p>R-FE (2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (3) </p>

<p>R-FE (3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (4) </p>

<p>R-FE (4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FH political rights × 
Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>0.234** 
(0.098) </p>

<p>DPI checks and balances × 
Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>0.262*** 
(0.069) </p>

<p>FH press freedom × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.026 
(0.070) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>346 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>346 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>104 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>105 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>108 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.993 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.993 </p>

<p>0.856 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.990 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Cluster-robust standard errors are in parentheses. Time and country effects are included but not reported. All regressions control for </p>

<p>market size, population, and regulatory quality. FH, Freedom House; FHP, Freedom House Press freedom; DPI, Database of Political Institutions; WGI, Worldwide Gover-
nance Indicator. Natural resource abundance: share of fuel and minerals in total merchandise exports. For each proxy of democracy, the empirical model is estimated using: (i) a 
standard 
fixed effects estimator (FE); and (ii) our robust 
fixed effects estimator (R-FE). Relative to the initial regression model, an interaction term between natural resource </p>

<p>abundance and democracy is included. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>their grievances (Rummel, 1995; Ellingsen, 2000). Hence, stronger checks and 
balances, which may not only proxy for policy stability but also for the degree 
of political inclusiveness (Reynal-Querol, 2005), and media freedom, may guar-
antee that discontent is expressed in non-violent and destructive ways, such as 
protests (Przeworski et al., 2000; Pal, 2011). From an endogenous perspective, 
democratization may have been the rational choice of the elites that do not wish 
to be expropriated when faced with the likelihood of a revolution too costly to 
repress or to avoid via redistributive policies (Acemoglu and Robinson, 2006). 
Even though democracy and violence are again negatively correlated, it is the 
threat of the later that has triggered the emergence of the latter. Whichever the 
causality sense, the premium that FDI in extractive industries put on non-
violence can explain their attractiveness for democracy. </p>

<p>6.3. The mediating role of inequality </p>

<p>It is possible that the link between FDI, democracy and natural resources de-
pends on an additional factor. A prominent candidate from the growth literature 
is income inequality. In a textbook median voter model, greater income inequal-
ity leads to more demands for redistribution, resulting in more taxation (Alesina  and Perotti, 1994). A government wishing to maximize its chances to be </p>

<p>Figure 8. Foreign direct investment (FDI) in resource exporting countries and 
democracyNote: Dashed lines delimit the 95% confidence interval. DPI, Database 
of Political Institutions; FH, Freedom House; WGI, Worldwide Governance 
Indicators. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 9. Foreign direct investment (FDI) in resource exporting countries, democracy and income inequality </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>À 1 ) </p>

<p>FE (1) </p>

<p>R-FE (1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (2) </p>

<p>R-FE (2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (3) </p>

<p>R-FE (3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (4) </p>

<p>R-FE (4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>À0.191 
(0.178) </p>

<p>À0.528*** 
(0.064) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>À0.258 
(0.202) </p>

<p>0.348*** 
(0.125) </p>

<p>Polity IV constraints 
on executive </p>

<p>À0.135 
(0.162) </p>

<p>À0.416*** 
(0.124) </p>

<p>Henisz political 
constraints </p>

<p>À0.233 
(0.156) </p>

<p>À0.191*** 
(0.068) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À0.383 
(0.731) </p>

<p>À1.404*** 
(0.339) </p>

<p>À0.417 
(0.779) </p>

<p>0.998*** 
(0.249) </p>

<p>À0.128 
(0.683) </p>

<p>À0.801* 
(0.462) </p>

<p>À0.564 
(0.645) </p>

<p>0.998*** 
(0.312) </p>

<p>Gini index </p>

<p>0.009 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.006** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.008 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.019*** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.009 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.008** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.008 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.012*** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance × Gini index </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.015) </p>

<p>0.030*** 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.016) </p>

<p>À0.035*** 
(0.006) </p>

<p>À0.001 
(0.014) </p>

<p>0.006 
(0.010) </p>

<p>0.007 
(0.013) </p>

<p>À0.033*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
Resources </p>

<p>0.595 
(0.433) </p>

<p>3.126*** 
(0.294) </p>

<p>0.886* 
(0.494) </p>

<p>À0.089 
(0.233) </p>

<p>0.926* 
(0.499) </p>

<p>2.464*** 
(0.301) </p>

<p>0.445 
(0.531) </p>

<p>0.722*** 
(0.243) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini index </p>

<p>0.004 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.017*** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.005) </p>

<p>À0.008** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.003 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.009*** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.005 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.004*** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini index </p>

<p>× Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À0.011 
(0.009) </p>

<p>À0.067*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>À0.017 
(0.011) </p>

<p>0.010* 
(0.006) </p>

<p>À0.017 
(0.011) </p>

<p>À0.046*** 
(0.007) </p>

<p>À0.010 
(0.012) </p>

<p>À0.011** 
(0.005) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>282 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>279 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>281 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>95 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>93 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.922 </p>

<p>0.994 </p>

<p>0.923 </p>

<p>0.991 </p>

<p>0.923 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>0.922 </p>

<p>0.992 </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>tÀ1 ) </p>

<p>FE (5) </p>

<p>R-FE (5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (6) </p>

<p>R-FE (6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (7) </p>

<p>R-FE (7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R-FE (8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>0.151 </p>

<p>(0.173) </p>

<p>DPI strength of veto players </p>

<p>0.032 
(0.130) </p>

<p>À0.278*** 
(0.069) </p>

<p>À0.049 </p>

<p>(0.075) </p>

<p>FH press freedom </p>

<p>À0.381* 
(0.197) </p>

<p>À0.174* 
(0.100) </p>

<p>À0.524*** </p>

<p>(0.188) </p>

<p>WGI voice and accountability </p>

<p>À0.252 
(0.221) </p>

<p>0.167 </p>

<p>(0.108) </p>

<p>Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.780 
(0.671) </p>

<p>À0.835** 
(0.373) </p>

<p>À0.476 
(0.835) </p>

<p>0.865*** 
(0.245) </p>

<p>À0.419 
(0.837) </p>

<p>0.609** </p>

<p>(0.251) </p>

<p>À0.507 </p>

<p>(0.442) </p>

<p>Gini index </p>

<p>0.011 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.010** 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.008 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.017*** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.008 
(0.007) </p>

<p>0.011*** </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>(0.004) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.520 
(0.484) </p>

<p>2.873*** 
(0.404) </p>

<p>1.064** 
(0.464) </p>

<p>1.128*** 
(0.267) </p>

<p>0.950** 
(0.425) </p>

<p>0.254 </p>

<p>(0.263) </p>

<p>DPI strength of veto players × 
Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.602* </p>

<p>(0.323) </p>

<p>FH political rights × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>6.376*** </p>

<p>(0.941) </p>

<p>FH political rights × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À2.324*** </p>

<p>(0.852) </p>

<p>Natural resource abundances </p>

<p>× Gini index </p>

<p>0.012 
(0.014) </p>

<p>0.012 
(0.008) </p>

<p>0.007 
(0.017) </p>

<p>À0.024*** 
(0.006) </p>

<p>0.006 
(0.017) </p>

<p>À0.018*** </p>

<p>(0.006) </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>(0.011) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini index </p>

<p>À0.001 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.005*** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.009* 
(0.005) </p>

<p>0.006** 
(0.002) </p>

<p>0.006 
(0.005) </p>

<p>À0.003 </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>DPI strength of veto players × 
Gini index </p>

<p>À0.000 </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>FH political rights × Gini index </p>

<p>0.015*** </p>

<p>(0.004) </p>

<p>FH press freedom × Gini index </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>Table 9. (Continued) </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 9. (Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>tÀ1 ) </p>

<p>FE (5) </p>

<p>R-FE (5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (6) </p>

<p>R-FE (6 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>FE (7) </p>

<p>R-FE (7 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>R-FE (8 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>) 
À0.005 </p>

<p>(0.004) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini index × </p>

<p>Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>0.013 
(0.011) </p>

<p>À0.055*** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>À0.024** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>À0.029*** 
(0.006) </p>

<p>À0.021** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>(0.006) </p>

<p>DCHECKS × Gini index × </p>

<p>Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>0.025*** </p>

<p>(0.008) </p>

<p>FHPF × Gini index × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.168*** </p>

<p>(0.023) </p>

<p>FHPR × Gini index × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>0.073*** </p>

<p>(0.020) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>281 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>278 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>277 </p>

<p>271 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.922 </p>

<p>0.993 </p>

<p>0.923 </p>

<p>0.995 </p>

<p>0.923 </p>

<p>0.993 </p>

<p>0.995 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>92 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>97 </p>

<p>103 </p>

<p>91 </p>

<p>101 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Cluster-robust standard errors are in parentheses. Time and country effects are included but not reported. All regressions control for </p>

<p>market size, population and regulatory quality. DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FH, Freedom House; FHPF, Freedom House Press Freedom; FHPR, Freedom House 
Political Rights; WGI, Worldwide Governance Indicator. Natural resource abundance: share of fuel and minerals in total merchandise exports. For each proxy of democracy, </p>

<p>the empirical model is estimated using: (i) a standard </p>

<p>fixed effects estimator (FE); and (ii) our robust 
fixed effects estimator (R-FE). Relative to the initial regression model, </p>

<p>interaction terms between natural resources abundance, Gini index, and democracy are included. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>reelected would tend to avoid taxing domestic producers and, therefore, prefer 
to redistribute income via an increase in the tax burden of foreign investors, or 
other means of (creeping) expropriation (Caves, 1996; Desbordes and Vauday,  2007). In periods of high commodity prices, such as the 1998-2006 period, for-
eign firms in extractive industries are ideal targets as governments can easily ar-
gue that the visible windfall profits of those firms, unrelated to the intrinsic merit 
of their operative capabilities and generated by the exploitation of territorial re-
sources, ought to be shared in a more balanced way. Furthermore, given the rel-
atively scarcity of natural resources and the extremely high level of sunk costs 
required to extract, process and distribute them, capital mobility in these indus-
tries is low. Foreign firms cannot credibly threaten to move their operations 
abroad in response to an increase in taxation or the formulation of adverse pol-
icies. Hence, while democracy may reduce the risk of conflict, it may also in-
crease regulatory uncertainty. We investigate this possibility by including in 
our model the Gini index of net income inequality and its interactions with de-
mocracy, natural resource export intensity and both. Data on the Gini coeffi-
cient come from Solt (2009). 
Table 9 and Figure 9 summarize our results. 
8 The number of outliers remains 
about the same as in previous regressions (approximately 30%), despite our </p>

<p>Figure 9. Foreign direct investment (FDI) in resource exporting countries, de-
mocracy and income inequality. DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FH, 
Freedom House; WGI, Worldwide Governance Indicators. </p>

<p>8 For clarity's sake, confidence intervals are not reported in Figure 9. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 10. M-S estimation: Foreign direct investment (FDI), democracy and natural resource abundance </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stock </p>

<p>t ) 
À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stocktÀ1) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>0.011 (0.034) </p>

<p>FH political Rights </p>

<p>À0.030** (0.013) </p>

<p>À0.004 (0.008) </p>

<p>Polity IV constraints 
on executive </p>

<p>0.025 (0.019) </p>

<p>Henisz political constraints </p>

<p>À0.012* (0.007) </p>

<p>DPI checks and balances </p>

<p>0.062*** (0.015) </p>

<p>0.043*** (0.014) </p>

<p>WGI voice and 
accountability </p>

<p>0.095** (0.038) </p>

<p>FH press freedom </p>

<p>0.027 (0.113) 0.022*** (0.008) </p>

<p>Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.110 (0.097) 
0.031 (0.097) 0.025 (0.147) </p>

<p>0.007 (0.087) 
0.010 (0.087) 0.053 (0.215) </p>

<p>À0.102 (0.304) </p>

<p>0.047** (0.024) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>0.025 (0.139) 
0.024 (0.081) 0.009 (0.106) </p>

<p>À0.022 (0.025) </p>

<p>À0.021 (0.032) 
À0.006 (0.054) 0.068 (0.576) </p>

<p>FH political Rights × 
Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.071*** (0.027) </p>

<p>DPI checks and balances × 
Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>0.047* (0.025) </p>

<p>FH press freedom × 
Natural resource abundance </p>

<p>0.065*** (0.023) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>489 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>111 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.827 </p>

<p>0.819 </p>

<p>0.822 </p>

<p>0.822 </p>

<p>0.818 </p>

<p>0.824 </p>

<p>0.824 </p>

<p>0.824 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors in parentheses. Time and country effects are included but not reported. All regressions </p>

<p>control for market size, population, and regulatory quality. DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FH, Freedom House; FHP, Freedom House Press freedom; WGI, World-
wide Governance Indicator. Natural resource abundance: share of fuel and minerals in total merchandise exports. For each proxy of democracy, the empirical model is esti-
mated using a MS-estimator. Relative to the initial regression model, an interaction term between natural resource abundance and democracy is included. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 11. M-S estimation: Foreign direct investment (FDI), democracy and natural resource abundance </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stockt) </p>

<p>À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stockt-1) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>Polity IV score </p>

<p>À0.298*** (0.077) </p>

<p>FH political rights </p>

<p>À0.182 (0.189) </p>

<p>0.296 (0.187) </p>

<p>Polity IV constraints 
on executive </p>

<p>0.095 (0.271) </p>

<p>Henisz political constraints </p>

<p>À0.238 (0.240) </p>

<p>DPI checks and balances </p>

<p>À0.244*** (0.035) </p>

<p>À0.426*** (0.085) </p>

<p>WGI voice and 
accountability </p>

<p>À0.060 (0.726) </p>

<p>FH press freedom </p>

<p>0.267*** (0.073) </p>

<p>À0.122 (0.144) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance 
0.066 (0.526)À0.014 (0.000) </p>

<p>À0.364 (0.592) </p>

<p>0.266 (1.578) 
À0.065 (0.128)À0.677 (4.734) </p>

<p>À0.416** (0.162) </p>

<p>À0.368 (0.287) </p>

<p>ln(Gini index) 
0.010*** (0.003) 0.007 (0.010) </p>

<p>0.006 (0.009)0.006*** (0.002) 
0.005 (0.004) 0.009 (0.105) 0.008*** (0.002) </p>

<p>0.002 (0.004) </p>

<p>Democracy × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>À0.043 (0.211) 0.381 (1.002) </p>

<p>À0.111 (0.232) </p>

<p>0.130 (1.457) 
0.004 (0.164)À0.230 (0.588)À0.416*** (0.143) </p>

<p>DPI checks and balances 
× Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>0.544*** (0.174) </p>

<p>FH political rights × 
Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À1.889*** (0.367) </p>

<p>FH press freedom × 
Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>1.350*** (0.221) </p>

<p>Natural resource 
abundance × Gini index 
À0.002 (0.015)À0.002 (0.008)0.006*** (0.002) </p>

<p>À0.008 (0.041) 
À0.000 (0.003) 0.014 (0.133) </p>

<p>0.004 (0.004) </p>

<p>0.007 (0.007) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini index 
0.007*** (0.002) 0.003 (0.002) </p>

<p>À0.000 (0.007) 
0.006 (0.006) 0.006*** (0.001) 0.003 (0.004)À0.006*** (0.002) </p>

<p>DPI strength of veto 
players × Gini index </p>

<p>0.010*** (0.002) </p>

<p>(Continues) </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Table 11. (Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: ln(FDI stockt) </p>

<p>À 0.75 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln(FDI stockt-1) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>FH political rights × 
Gini index </p>

<p>À0.007 (0.004) </p>

<p>FH press freedom × 
Gini index </p>

<p>0.004 (0.004) </p>

<p>Democracy × Gini </p>

<p>index × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>0.001 (0.004)À0.007 (0.014) </p>

<p>0.001 (0.005) </p>

<p>À0.005 (0.035) 
0.000 (0.003) 0.005 (0.015) 0.011*** (0.003) </p>

<p>DPI strength of veto 
players × Gini index × 
Natural resource 
abundance </p>

<p>À0.010*** (0.003) </p>

<p>FH political rights 
× Gini index × Natural 
resource abundance </p>

<p>0.038*** (0.008) </p>

<p>FH press freedom 
× Gini index × 
Natural resource 
abundances </p>

<p>À0.029*** (0.005) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>411 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>109 </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.89 </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>Notes: ***p 
&lt; 0.01; **p </p>

<p>&lt; 0.05; *p 
&lt; 0.10. Heteroskedasticity-robust standard errors in parentheses. Time and country effects are included but not reported. All regressions </p>

<p>control for market size, population, and regulatory quality. DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FH, Freedom House; FHP, Freedom House Press Freedom; FHPR, Free-
dom House Political Rights; WGI, Worldwide Governance Indicator. Natural resource abundance: share of fuel and minerals in total merchandise exports. For each proxy of 
democracy, the empirical model is estimated using a MS-estimator. Relative to the initial regression model, interaction terms between natural resource abundance, democracy, </p>

<p>and the log of the Gini index are included. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>adoption of a more flexible specification. A comparison of the classical and 
robust FE estimates shows again that results tend to be very different once the 
influence of outliers is controlled for. Focusing on the R-FE estimates, the 
impact of democracy on FDI is now less clear-cut than before as it is the product 
of the proxy used, natural resource export intensity and income inequality. As 
hypothesized, when a country's natural resource export intensity is high, the 
positive impact of democracy is weaker when income inequality is high. Foreign 
investors in the oil or mining industries presumably discount the benefits of more 
democracy by the probability of being confronted, now or once the investment 
has been 'sunk', with higher taxation or more stringent regulations. 
For some measures, when a country's natural resource export intensity is 
low, democracy exerts its strongest positive impact on FDI when income 
inequality is high. Assuming that FDI in extractive industries is relatively 
low, this effect can be interpreted as the belief that democratic progress, in 
addition to all the previously mentioned benefits, will favour socio-political 
stability, while high capital mobility ought to deter greater taxation of foreign 
firms. 
Remarkably, in high resource exporting/income inequality countries, greater 
press freedom seems to deter FDI. That is possibly because more press freedom 
allows the emergence, persistence and dissemination of redistribution demands 
beyond the election date. In other words, it is possible that media freedom acts </p>

<p>Figure 10. M-S estimation.Notes: Dashed lines delimit the 95% confidence 
interval. DPI, Database of Political Institutions; FDI, democracy and natural 
resources; FH, Freedom House; WGI, Worldwide Governance Indicators. </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>as a commitment device, guaranteeing that politicians hold their electoral prom-
ises (Besley et al., 2002). Column (8 
0 ) of Table 9 and Figure 9 (bottom right) 
show that this negative impact of greater media freedom outweighs the positive 
impact of other democratic attributes when both natural resources and income 
inequality are high. The recent expropriations, nationalizations, forced renegoti-
ations of contracts, and higher taxes and royalties that foreign firms operating in 
extractive industries have endured in relatively democratic countries meeting 
these two criteria (e.g. Bolivia, Ecuador or Zambia) provide additional factual 
support to our hypothesis. 
The coefficients on the proxies of democracies, in Tables 8 and 9, correspond 
to the impact of democratic changes when a country is characterized by an 
absence of natural resources and perfectly equal distribution of income. In this 
hypothetical case, stronger democracy often appears to deter FDI (e.g column 
(1 
0 ) in Table 9). As shown in Figure 9, for low values of natural resource abun-
dance, this is especially the case when the proxy for democracy corresponds to 
the degree of political constraints on policy change. This result shows again that 
the impact of a given democratic attribute on FDI is context-specific. When the 
threat of socio-political instability is low and foreign firms do not incur high 
sunk costs to extract natural resources, multinational enterprises may be reluc-
tant to invest in countries where the likelihood of reforms becomes smaller 
due to a rise in veto players. 
Before concluding, it is worth investigating whether our results would have 
been different if we had estimated our models with an M-S estimator. In the </p>

<p>Figure 11. M-S estimation: The mediating role of inequality. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Appendix, Tables 10 and 11 report the M-S estimates and Figures 10 and 11 
summarize the results. In Figure 10, it can be seen that we often fail to find 
that the effect of democracy on FDI is a function of natural resource 
abundance. In Figure 11, democracy tends to exert its highest impact in 
countries characterized by high income inequality and high natural resource 
abundance. These findings are different from those obtained using an R-FE 
estimator. We can use the R 
2 of the R-FE and M-S regression models to 
make a choice between the two sets of 'robust' results. The empirical models 
estimated by R-FE fit much better the data than those estimated by the M-S 
estimator; the average R 
2 is 0.99 with the former and 0.82 (0.87) for 
Figure 10 with the latter, worse than the R 
2 obtained with the standard fixed 
effects estimator. On that basis, the results obtained using a R-FE estimators 
ought to be preferred. </p>

<p>7. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>The contributions of this paper have been twofold. First, we developed a new 
robust-to-outliers dummy estimator, which ought to be extremely useful to 
applied economists, given the increasing preference for panel data fixed effects 
models in economics. Second, we used this estimator to investigate the recent 
impact of democracy on FDI. We show that once outliers are controlled for, 
democratic attributes tend to attract FDI, especially when they are associated 
with stronger checks and balances, greater inclusiveness or media freedom. 
Furthermore, we find that the positive effects of democracy are even larger when 
FDI is concentrated in natural resources. A plausible explanation is that democ-
racy reduces the occurrence of violent conflicts, which are a major deterrent for 
FDI in extractive industries characterized by large sunk costs. Finally, we put 
forward the case that other factors, such as income inequality, also play a medi-
ating role in the relationship between FDI and democracy. Even though democ-
racy may reduce social and political unrest in highly unequal societies, it may 
also trigger damaging redistributive policies for FDI in resource-abundant coun-
tries. Overall, this paper demonstrates that the impact of democracy on FDI is 
extremely complex and difficult to measure as it depends on the democratic 
attribute considered, the host country's characteristics and the estimator used. </p>



<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>



<p>APPENDIX: ALGORITHM FOR THE ROBUST IDENTIFICATION OF OUTLIERS </p>

<p>Intuitively, the least squares (LS) estimator of θ isθ LS ¼ </p>

<p>∑XX X 
0 X ∑ XX Þ 
À1 ∑Xy X 
0 y ∑ Xy </p>

<p>, where ∑ XX and ∑ Xy are, respectively, n times </p>

<p>the covariance of X and (X, y). If we replace ∑ XX and ∑ Xy by some robust </p>

<p>FOREIGN DIRECT INVESTMENT AND DEMOCRACY </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>counterparts, this estimator will become resistant to outliers. Hence, we propose 
to use the Stahel-Donoho estimate (see Maronna and Yohai, 2000) to identify 
and remove multivariate outliers in the set M = (y, X) = (y, X 1 , X 2 ) and obtain 
robust ∑ XX and∑ Xy : Once we have preliminary estimates for parameters θ and 
residuals r i , we can use an iterative algorithm to find a solution to equation 3. 
Our algorithm is, therefore: </p>

<p>1. Use a multivariate outlier detection tool (more precisely, as suggested by 
Maronna and Yohai (2000), the Stahel-Donoho estimate) to measure the 
'outlyingness' of each individual considering the data cloud M= (y, X 1 , 
X 2 ). This estimator is a multivariate outlier identification tool based on 
univariate projections. Outlyingness distances correspond to the largest 
distance of each point with respect to a centre of the projected data cloud 
when considering all possible directions for the projections. The effect of 
dummies is partialled-out in each projection. This has the advantage of taking 
into account the effect of dummies, but without facing the issue of collinear 
subsamples. Because these distances are distributed for Gaussian data as 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
χ 2 </p>

<p>p 2 þ1 </p>

<p>q 
we can flag individuals as being outliers when their outlyingness </p>

<p>distance is larger than a given quantile of </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
χ 2 </p>

<p>p 2 þ1 </p>

<p>q 
(generally the 95 
th or 99th </p>

<p>percentile). </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>2. Apply a weight zero to all the outliers, and use a standard LS estimator to fit 
the model robustly and to estimate 'robust' residuals for all observations. 
3. Use the robust residuals to start a standard iterative algorithm. Note that 
dummies are now treated like the other explanatory variables because no 
subsampling is needed anymore. </p>

<p>MS estimates </p>

<p>Tables 10 and 11 report the M-S estimates. Figures 10 and 11 summarize the 
results. </p>

<p>9 Note that the degree of freedom is p 2 + 1 and not p + 1 because dummy variables will be partialled-
out. </p>

<p>R. DESBORDES AND V. VERARDI </p>



<p>© 2017 John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

</text></tei>