<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs00148-015-0566-8" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract We quantify the importance of family background and neighborhood 
effects as determinants of criminal convictions and incarceration by estimating sib-
ling correlations. At the extensive margin, factors common to siblings account for 
24 % of the variation in criminal convictions and 39 % of the variation in incarcera-
tion. At the intensive margin, these factors typically account for slightly less than half 
of the variation in prison sentence length and between one third and one half of the 
variation in criminal convictions, depending on crime type and gender. Further anal-
ysis shows that parental criminality and family structure can account for more of the 
sibling crime correlation than parental income and education or neighborhood char-
acteristics. The lion's share of the sibling correlation, however, is unaccounted for by </p>

<p>Responsible editor: Erdal Tekin </p>

<p>Sweden </p>

<p>220 </p>

<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>these factors. Finally, sibling spacing also matters-more closely spaced siblings are 
more similar in their criminal behavior. </p>

<p>There is extensive evidence of similarities in criminal behavior between members of 
the same family and between households in the same neighborhood. For instance, 
The Bureau of Justice Statistics reports that approximately 50 % of fathers and 
mothers in state prison had at least one other family member that had also been incar-
cerated: 6 % had an incarcerated mother, 19 % had an incarcerated father, 34 % 
had an incarcerated brother, 7 % had an incarcerated sister, 2 % had an incarcerated 
child, and 2 % had an incarcerated spouse (Glaze and Maruschak 2008). What is it 
about these individuals that cause them to engage in similar antisocial behaviors? 
Answering this question and identifying the relative contribution of different family 
and community factors to criminal behavior is crucial in our quest to both identify 
the fundamental causes of criminal behavior and to develop public policies to combat 
crime. 
Thus, the aim of this paper is to contribute to a better understanding of the impor-
tance of family background and neighborhood effects as determinants of crime. We 
do this in two ways. We first quantify the role of family and community background 
for criminal activity by estimating sibling correlations in criminal convictions and 
incarceration. Siblings share (among other things) genes, parents, family values, and 
common influences from peers and neighborhoods. The sibling correlation, therefore, 
provides us with a broad measure of the importance of family and community fac-
tors. It tells us what share of the variation in criminal behavior can be traced back to 
common influences stemming from family and community background. We then run 
an accounting exercise to see the extent to which a large set of family-wide variables 
(parental income and education, parental criminality, family structure, and neighbor-
hoods) can account for the sibling correlations in criminal behavior that we report. 
While a literature studying sibling correlations in crime certainly exists, as does a 
literature studying the importance of family and community background effects on 
crime, 1 we are aware of little research that has combined these two strands of litera-
ture to assess the extent to which various family-wide control variables can account 
for sibling similarities in crime. 2 </p>

<p>1 From the economics literature see, e.g., Case and Katz (1991), Pezzin (2004), Currie and Tekin (2012), 
Doyle (2008), Hjalmarsson and Lindquist (2010, 2012, 2013), Akee et al. (2010), and Meghir et al. (2012) 
for work on family background effects and Case and Katz (1991), Ludwig et al. (2001), Kling et al. (2005), 
and Damm and Dustmann (2014) for work on neighborhood effects. 
2 Important exceptions include twin studies and the early work of Rowe and Farrington (1997). </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Sibling correlations in criminal behavior have been documented in a number of 
contexts: varying countries, different types of sibling pairs, administrative versus 
survey data, various crime types, and different measures of criminality. These esti-
mates range from a low of 0.25 (Mazumder 2008) to a high of 0.69 (Johnson 2007). 3 
Twin studies also report strong sibling similarities in antisocial behavior and crime. 4 
Many of these studies, however, use data from small, selected samples, while studies 
using data from the NLSY or PSID rely on self-reported data covering a limited time 
period. Frisell et al. (2011) is an important exception. Their study reports (perhaps 
for the first time) population-wide sibling correlations using police register data in 
Sweden, albeit only for violent crime at the extensive margin. They find an extensive 
margin correlation of 0.41 for brothers and 0.48 for sisters. 
This paper builds on the existing literature by estimating sibling correlations in 
criminal convictions and incarceration using Swedish register data on a nationally 
representative sample of more than 700,000 brothers and sisters born between 1958 
and 1968. We have information on all criminal convictions, crime types, and sen-
tences received between the years 1973 and 2007, which allows us to estimate both 
extensive and intensive margin sibling correlations for different crime types and for 
both genders. 
At the extensive margin, our estimated sibling correlations indicate that factors 
shared by siblings account for 24 % of the variation in convictions and 39 % of 
the variation in incarceration. At the intensive margin, we find much larger sibling 
correlations for higher numbers of crimes and longer prison sentences. For example, 
the brother correlation in having committed at least one crime is 0.29, while the 
brother correlation in having committed at least 10 crimes is 0.51. We also see similar 
patterns for sibling correlations after breaking down the data by crime type (violent, 
property, and other) and no systematic difference between brother correlations and 
sister correlations. Lastly, we show that closely spaced siblings are more similar in 
terms of their criminal behavior than are siblings who are born many years apart from 
each other. 
We then go on to study the different factors that could potentially explain why 
siblings are so similar in terms of their criminal behavior. We first look at the effects 
of family-wide variables that siblings share: parental income and education, parental 
criminality, and family structure. These variables have been chosen based on our 
reading of the previous literature on family background and crime. After including </p>

<p>3 Using data from the Cambridge Study in Delinquent Development, Rowe and Farrington (1997) report 
sibling correlations in criminal convictions of 0.45-0.50 for same-sex siblings and 0.27 for opposite-sex 
siblings. Mazumder (2008) uses data from the NLSY to estimate a sibling correlation in illegal drug use 
of 0.30 and a brother correlation in incarceration of 0.25. Using a somewhat different approach, Pezzin 
(2004) argues that 44-55 % of the total variation in crime among siblings in the NLSY can be attributed 
to family influences even after controlling for a number of individual and family attributes. Using PSID 
data, Johnson (2007) reports a brother correlation in having ever been charged or booked with a crime of 
0.31 and in incarceration of 0.69. 
4 See Ishikawa and Raine (2002) and Moffit (2005) for reviews of the behavioral genetics literature con-
cerning antisocial behavior and crime. For an overview of earlier work on sibling similarities in the 
criminology literature, see Lauritsen (1993). </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>these potentially important family characteristics as control variables (when estimat-
ing the variance components used to construct our sibling correlations), we assess 
how much of the sibling similarities in criminal behavior they account for. While 
this decomposition approach has been used to investigate the determinants of sib-
ling similarities in income, health, and education (Mazumder 2008, 2011; Björklund 
et al. 2010; Anger and Schnitzlein 2013), it has not been applied to criminal behavior. 
Sibling correlations decrease by at most 9 % when we control for parental 
income and education, by at most 21 % when we control for parental criminality, 
and by at most 19 % when we control for family structure. The largest decrease 
is seen for the extensive margin measures. Including all of the controls simulta-
neously decreases the sibling correlations by at most 27 %. These results imply 
that sibling associations in criminal behavior appear to be driven mainly by factors 
common to siblings other than parental income and education. Parental criminal-
ity and family structure appear more important. 5 But the largest share remains 
unexplained. 
We then show that closely spaced siblings are more similar in terms of their 
criminal behavior than widely spaced siblings, even after controlling for our full set 
of family background variables. We argue that part of this effect may be due to a 
stronger sibling peer effect between closely than widely space siblings. However, 
using a correlated random-effects model proposed by Altonji et al. (2013), we find 
little empirical evidence of a direct effect of older siblings' crime on that of their 
younger sibling in the following period. 
We continue our analysis by examining the role of shared neighborhood influences 
(e.g., schools, peers, local labor markets, etc.) by estimating neighborhood correla-
tions that can (under certain assumptions) be viewed as upper bounds on the potential 
effects of neighborhood influences (Solon et al. 2000). These correlations tell us that 
neighborhoods account for only 1 % of the variation in aggregate crime at the exten-
sive margin (or 3 % of sibling similarities) and 2 % of the variation in incarceration at 
the extensive margin (or 5 % of sibling similarities). At the intensive margin, neigh-
borhood correlations tend to be somewhat larger and explain up to 13 % of the sibling 
correlation. In a supplementary experiment, we conclude that neighborhood quality 
may explain part of the neighborhood effect. We also investigate the potential role of 
family-neighborhood interaction effects. 
Together, family-wide variables and neighborhood effects can account for one 
third of the sibling similarities that we observe in our data, leaving the lion's share 
unexplained. What these other influences on siblings' behavior might be is discussed 
in the conclusion. We also discuss several important caveats that must be kept in mind 
when interpreting the results from our accounting exercise. </p>

<p>5 Since the goal of this paper is to gain a better understanding of what makes siblings so similar in terms of 
criminal behavior, the metric that we use to measure the "importance" of a control variable is the degree 
to which it lowers the sibling correlation after being introduced as a control in the fixed part of our mixed-
effects model. Our framework allows us to present a structured and informative descriptive analysis of 
the data in hand. This descriptive analysis does not, however, allow us to judge the relative importance of 
various causal mechanisms of crime in general. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>In the next section, we outline our statistical model and empirical estimation 
methods. This is followed, in Section 3, by a presentation of our data and descriptive 
statistics. In Section 4, we present extensive and intensive margin sibling correlations 
in crime and incarceration. We then proceed in Section 5 to see what share of these 
correlations can be accounted for by parental income and education, parental crim-
inality, family structure, sibling peer effects, and neighborhood effects. Section 6 
concludes. </p>

<p>2 Statistical model and estimation method </p>

<p>Criminal behavior , c if n , for sibling i in family f living in neighborhood n can be 
modeled in a simple linear additive model as </p>

<p>c if n = μ + a f + b n + e if n , 
(1) </p>

<p>where μ is the population mean, a f is a permanent component common to all sib-
lings in family f , b n is a permanent component common to all children living in 
neighborhood n, and e if n is unique to individual i in family f from neighborhood 
n. 6 The component e if n captures individual deviations from the family and neighbor-
hood components (including measurement error in our crime variable). If we assume 
that these components are independent, then the variance of c if n is the sum of the 
variances of the family, neighborhood, and individual components: </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>c = σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>a + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>b + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e . 
(2) </p>

<p>We can also allow families to sort into neighborhoods based on (for example) income 
and education, which induces a covariance term, 2σ 2 
ab , so that 7 
σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>c = σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>a + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>b + 2σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ab + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e . 
(3) </p>

<p>The share of the variance in the outcome variable, c if n , which can be attributed to 
family background and neighborhood effects, is </p>

<p>ρ = 
σ 2 
a + σ 2 
b + 2σ 2 </p>

<p>ab </p>

<p>σ 2 
a + σ 2 
b + 2σ 2 
ab + σ 2 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>. 
(4) </p>

<p>This share coincides with the correlation in the outcome variable of randomly 
drawn pairs of siblings, which is why ρ is called a sibling correlation. 8 
A sibling correlation can thus be thought of as an omnibus measure of the impor-</p>

<p>6 We discuss the potential role played by family-neighborhood interaction effects in Section 5.4. 
7 We abstract from the additional complication that measurement error may also be correlated with either 
family and/or neighborhood effects due to, for example, differential conviction rates by family socio-
economic status or higher policing rates in certain neighborhoods. This type of measurement error would 
bias our estimated sibling and neighborhood correlations upwards. 
8 Although this common formulation of the sibling correlation is a well-defined statistical entity, it is 
important to keep in mind that it is still a somewhat arbitrary model of the process that generates sibling 
similarities. It rules out, for example, the fact that sibling correlations could in theory be negative. Along 
some dimensions, families may promote inequality. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>tance of family background and neighborhood effects. It includes anything shared 
by siblings: genes, parental income, and parental influences such as aspirations 
and cultural inheritance, as well as things not directly experienced in the home, 
such as school, church, and neighborhood effects. If such shared factors are rela-
tively more important than non-shared factors for criminal behavior, the variance 
of the family effects will be large relative to the variance of the individual effects 
and the sibling correlation will be high. Thus, the more important the factors that 
siblings share are, the larger is the sibling correlation. Genetic traits not shared 
by siblings, differential treatment of siblings, time-dependent changes in neighbor-
hoods, schools, etc. are captured by the individual component e if n . Importantly, the 
existence of such non-shared factors implies that the sibling correlation should be 
viewed as a lower bound on the importance of family background and neighborhood 
effects. 9 
In order to calculate the total sibling correlation (including neighborhood effects), 
ρ, we need estimates of the between-family variation, σ 2 
a , and of the total remaining 
variation. These can be obtained by estimating the following mixed-effects model: </p>

<p>c if = x if β + a f + e if , 
(5) </p>

<p>where the neighborhood effect, b n , is now subsumed by the family effect, a f . Gender 
and birth year dummies are included in x if . 
Since our outcome variables are binary, we reformulate Eq. 5 as a latent linear 
response model 
c </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>if = x if β + a f + e if , 
(6) </p>

<p>where we only observe C if = I (C  *  
if &gt; 0). We estimate Eq. 6 using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s 
xtlogit command. The variance components σ 2 
e and σ 2 
a are estimated using maximum 
likelihood. The random family effect is estimated conditional on the random indi-
vidual effect being logistically distributed with mean zero, variance σ 2 
e = π 2 /3 and 
independent of a f . 
Inspired by the approach used in Mazumder (2008) and Björklund et al. (2010), 
we then go on to include potentially important family-wide variables, either one 
at a time or simultaneously, in the x if matrix. For example, consider the inclusion 
of parental income and education in x if . These additional control variables should 
reduce the residual variation in the outcome variable and produce a lower esti-
mate of the between-family variation, σ a 
2 *  , than the estimate produced without the 
added controls. Abstracting from measurement error, we can interpret the difference 
between these two estimates, σ a 
2 − σ a 
2 *  , as an upper bound on the amount of the 
variance in the family component that can be explained by parental income and edu-
cation. It is viewed as an upper bound since it includes other factors that are correlated 
with parental income and education. 10 </p>

<p>9 Björklund and Jäntti (2012) discuss this issue in great detail and provide quantitative examples of its 
importance. 
10 In the presence of measurement error, this difference, σ 2 
a − σ 2 *  
a , is more correctly viewed as a down-
wardly biased estimate of the upper bound on the amount of the variance in the family component that can 
be accounted for by parental income and education. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>This experiment also produces a new sibling correlation ρ  *  . From what we know 
about the relationship between parents' income and education and children's crime 
(see, e.g., Hjalmarsson and Lindquist 2012), we expect this new sibling correlation 
to be lower but still substantial in magnitude. 
The purpose of this accounting exercise is to see which family-wide variables are 
most important for making siblings similar in terms of their criminal behavior. The 
metric used in this paper to judge the "importance" of any particular control variable 
is the degree to which it lowers the sibling correlation after being included as a con-
trol in the fixed part of our mixed-effects model. We will use this metric to provide 
important clues about what is potentially important and unimportant in explaining 
sibling similarities in crime; this accounting exercise does not, however, allow for a 
causal interpretation of the determinants of crime. Specifically, we will explore the 
potential roles played by (i) parental income and education, (ii) parental criminality, 
and (iii) family structure. The choice of these particular variables is motivated by our 
reading of the existing literature on family background and crime. 
We then go on to explore the potential importance of neighborhood effects for 
producing sibling similarities. We do this by estimating neighborhood correlations 
net of sorting into neighborhoods. In the absence of family-neighborhood interaction 
effects, these act as "tight" upper bounds on the share of the sibling correlation that 
can be attributed to common neighborhood influences (see Solon et al. 2000). 
The share of the variance in the outcome variable, c if n , which can be attributed to 
neighborhood effects alone (net of sorting), is </p>

<p>γ = 
σ 2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>σ 2 
a + σ 2 
b + σ 2 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>. 
(7) </p>

<p>In order to calculate γ , we need an estimate of the between-neighborhood varia-
tion, σ b 
2 , as well as an estimate of the remaining variation, σ a 
2 + σ e 
2 . These can 
be obtained by ignoring the between-family variation and estimating the following 
mixed-effects model 
c in = x in β + b n + e in . 
(8) </p>

<p>Once again, x in allows for the inclusion of multiple control variables. Note that the 
family component, a f , is now subsumed by the individual component, e in . To net out 
sorting into neighborhoods (i.e., to remove the covariance term), we include controls 
for parents' income, education and criminality, and family structure in x in . 11 We also 
include gender and birth year dummies. 12 </p>

<p>11 Sorting on unobservables may also occur. To the extent that these unobservable characteristics are 
uncorrelated with our control variables, they will bias our estimated neighborhood correlations upwards. 
12 In practice, we estimate neighborhood correlations after first randomly drawing one child from each 
family. We do this, so that large families living in small neighborhoods will not dominate the estimation. 
Alternatively, one could estimate neighborhood, family, and individual variance components simultane-
ously by applying <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtmelogit to the whole sample and estimating a model with three levels. But 
due to our large sample, our use of control variables, and the large number of correlations that we need 
to calculate in this paper, this approach becomes infeasible; running time and convergence become prob-
lematic. In some cases, we have used both methods and the answer does not change. The fact that we 
randomly sample one child from each family does not seem to matter much either. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>3 Data and descriptive statistics </p>

<p>3.1 Data </p>

<p>The sample used in this paper was created in the following manner. We start with a 
25 % random sample from Sweden's Multigenerational Register, which includes all 
persons born from 1932 onwards who have lived in Sweden at any time since 1961. 
We then match on all of their brothers and sisters. This matching is made possible 
by the fact that all family ties (biological and adoptive) are recorded in Sweden's 
Multigenerational Register. 13 Those who died or emigrated from Sweden before their 
16th birthday are dropped from the sample. We also remove those who immigrated 
to Sweden after their 25th birthday. 
Siblings are defined as those having the same biological or adoptive mother. 
Among non-singletons, 98 % have at least one full sibling in the sample (i.e., 2 % of 
the non-singletons have a maternal half sibling but no full sibling). 14 
Our sibling sample was then matched with Sweden's official crime register. This 
matching is made possible by the unique personal identification number that each 
Swedish resident possesses. Our data include a full record of criminal convictions for 
the years 1973 to 2007 for each individual in the data set. Records include crime type 
and sanctions received. 
Given the years for which crime data are available, we choose to restrict our sam-
ple to siblings born between 1958 and 1968. This means that siblings are born at most 
ten calendar years apart. These age restrictions also imply that we have 35 years of 
crime data for our oldest cohort (born 1958) and that the crime data for this cohort 
span the ages of 15 to 49. For the youngest cohort (born 1968), we will use 25 years 
of crime data that span the ages 15 to 39. The age of criminal majority in Sweden 
is 15. 
We use our crime data to construct a number of different crime variables. The 
first variable, Crime, is a measure of crime at the extensive margin. That is, it is 
equal to one if a person has ever been convicted of a crime between 1973 and 
2007 and zero if he has not. The next three variables consider the types of crimes 
committed: violent, property, and other. We create variables indicating whether a 
person has been convicted of each of these three types of crimes between 1973 and 
2007. 15 We also create an intensive margin measure of aggregate crime that we </p>

<p>13 Very few children in these cohorts lived with pure social siblings, i.e., together with other children that 
they had no blood relationship with. 
14 We drop all observations with missing mothers from the analysis. In total, 26,907 observations have 
missing mothers; 96 % of these observations are immigrants. Among the dropped observations, 25 % have 
been convicted of a crime as compared to 29 % of the observations kept in the sample. 
15 Violent crimes, or crimes against persons, are crimes covered by chapters 3-7 in the Swedish crimi-
nal code (brottsbalken). Property crimes are those included in chapters 8-12 in the criminal code. These 
are standard definitions used by Sweden's National Council for Crime Prevention. All remaining crimes </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>label Number of Crimes. This variable is the total number of crimes that a person 
has been convicted of. This variable is also broken down by crime type: violent, 
property, and other. 
One conviction may include several crimes. Our crime type variables are created 
by looking over all of the crimes within every conviction. 16 Speeding tickets, parking 
tickets, and other forms of minor disturbances (ticketable offenses) are not included 
in our crime measure. It must be an offense that is serious enough to be taken up in 
court and that results in an admission of guilt or a guilty verdict. 
We create variables for the extensive and intensive margins for incarceration. The 
variable Prison is equal to one if the individual has ever been sentenced to prison 
and zero otherwise, and Days Sentenced to Prison tells us the total number of days 
an individual has been sentenced to prison between 1973 and 2007. This variable is 
summed across all prison sentences if the person has received more than one prison 
sentence during this time period. However, one should keep in mind that even the 
extensive margin Prison variable tells us about the intensity of one's criminal career, 
as one is only eligible for prison if the intensity of the convicted offense(s) is great 
enough (in terms of offense severity or quantity) or the criminal history is severe 
enough. 
The crime variables described above are also created for the parents of our sample 
of siblings. The main difference is that parents are much older when we observe them 
in our crime data. We also have data on parental education and income, as well as 
family structure when our siblings are young. Siblings can be placed into the neigh-
borhoods they were raised in as children based on their parish of residence. More 
detailed information concerning parent and neighborhood variables are presented in 
Sections 5. </p>

<p>3.2 Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>Table 1 shows the number of families having N children and Table 2 presents 
descriptive statistics. Our final sample consists of 707,613 individuals (363,234 men 
and 344,379 women) from 414,697 families. The mean number of siblings in each 
family is 1.7. In our sample, 29 % of the individuals are singletons (i.e., they have no </p>

<p>are labeled as "other." The five most common violent crimes are (in order of frequency) assault, molesta-
tion, unlawful threat, aggravated assault, and aggravated unlawful threat. The five most common property 
crimes are petty theft (mainly shoplifting), theft, vandalism, larceny, and fraud. The five most common 
"other" crimes are dangerous driving, driving without a license, unlawful driving, smuggling, and minor 
narcotic offenses. 
16 Thus, if you steal a car, then commit an armed robbery and then get caught after a high-speed chase, you 
will have one trial and one sentence that include convictions for at least three crime types. In this case, the 
individual would receive violent = 1 (armed robbery), property = 1 (car theft), and other = 1 (serious 
traffic offense + resisting arrest). </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>Table 1 Number of families with N children </p>

<p>N children 
Nr of families 
Nr of individuals </p>

<p>1 
206,901 
206,901 </p>

<p>2 
144,096 
288,192 </p>

<p>3 
47,872 
143,616 </p>

<p>4 
11,798 
47,192 </p>

<p>5 
2909 
14,545 </p>

<p>6 
804 
4824 </p>

<p>7 
228 
1596 </p>

<p>8 
68 
544 </p>

<p>9 
15 
135 </p>

<p>10 
3 
30 </p>

<p>11 
1 
11 </p>

<p>12 
1 
12 </p>

<p>15 
1 
15 </p>

<p>Total 
414,697 
707,613 </p>

<p>All children of the same mother are defined as belonging to the same family </p>

<p>siblings in the sample). We include singletons to increase the precision of the esti-
mate of the between-family variation, though our results are not sensitive to their 
inclusion/exclusion. 
Turning to the measures of criminal behavior, 28.5 % of the sample individuals 
have been convicted of a crime. Criminal convictions are 3.5 times more common 
among men than women; 43.7 % of men and 12.5 % of women have been convicted 
of a crime. For both men and women, violent crimes are least frequent while other 
crimes are most frequent. Only 5.5 % of the individuals have been convicted of a 
violent crime, while 13.7 % have been convicted of a property crime and 22.5 % of 
some other crime. 17 
Among the individuals convicted of a crime, the average number of crimes is 6.8. 
This number is 7.7 for men and 3.8 for women. Among the individuals convicted of a 
violent crime, the average number of violent crimes is 2.7. The corresponding number 
is 4.4 for other crimes and 5.9 for property crimes. Thus, given that an individual 
has been convicted of a crime of a specific type, the intensive margin frequency of 
that crime type is highest for property crimes and lowest for violent crimes. This 
pattern applies to both men and women. 4.4 % of the individuals have been sentenced 
to prison. Prison sentences are 11.1 times more common among men than among 
women; 7.8 % of the men compared to only 0.7 % of the women have been sentenced </p>

<p>17 While some of these statistics may seem high, it is important to note that they are (i) comparable to 
other studies of crime in Sweden (see for instance Hjalmarsson and Lindquist (forthcoming) and Meghir 
et al. 2012) and (ii) largely driven by the other crime category, which includes a number of alcohol-related 
offenses. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>to prison. For an individual sentenced to prison, the average prison sentence (summed 
over all prison sentences) is 455 days, 463 days for men and 367 for women. The 
median is 91 days (3 months) for both men and women. </p>

<p>4 Sibling correlations in criminal convictions and incarcerations </p>

<p>4.1 Extensive margin </p>

<p>We report the extensive margin sibling correlations in Table 3. 18 The overall pooled 
correlation in crime is 0.24, suggesting that about one fourth of the variation in crime 
at the extensive margin can be attributed to factors shared by siblings. The sister cor-
relation is 0.24 and the brother correlation is 0.29. The correlation for mixed siblings 
is 0.23. 19 
Throughout Table 3, the correlation for mixed siblings is always somewhat less 
than the sibling correlations reported for brothers and/or sisters. This suggests that 
siblings of different genders have fewer shared family or community factors; this 
could be driven by a number of explanations, including that parents treat sons and 
daughters differently, males and females have different peer groups and school expe-
riences, and males and females are simply differentially affected by the same family 
characteristics. It could also be that sibling peer effects are stronger for same-sex 
siblings. 
Investigating one crime type at a time, the sibling correlation is 0.33 for property 
crime, 0.35 for violent crime, and 0.21 for other crime. For prison, the correlation is 
0.39. The correlation for all siblings is thus substantially higher for property crimes 
and violent crimes than for other crimes, and higher for prison than for all crime out-
comes. That is, shared family and community factors appear to explain more of the 
variation in serious crime than minor crime. This pattern also applies to the brother 
and sister correlations. The brother correlations are slightly higher than the sister cor-
relations for crime (0.29 versus 0.24), property crime (0.38 versus 0.34), and other 
crime (0.24 versus 0.21). For violent crime, the brother and sister correlations are the 
same (0.37), and for prison, the brother correlation is lower than the sister correla-
tion (0.39 versus 0.44). The sister correlation in prison, which is the highest of all 
extensive margin sibling correlations, suggests that 44 % of the variation in female 
incarceration at the extensive margin can be accounted for by family and community 
factors shared by sisters. 20 </p>

<p>18 These correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command. The outcome variables are always 
dichotomous. Year and gender dummies are included in these estimations. Singletons are included, except 
when estimating the sibling correlations for mixed siblings. The estimated correlations are never sensitive 
to the inclusion/exclusion of singletons. 
19 Mixed siblings are defined as follows. In a group of siblings of size N ≥ 2, x ≥ 1 siblings do not have 
the same gender as the other N − x siblings. Singletons are, therefore, always excluded. 
20 Finally, we note that when looking at sibling correlations for different birth cohorts, there is no notable 
trend in the correlations over time. This is true when controls are included and excluded and when looking 
at neighborhood correlations as well. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>Table 2 Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>All 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Number of observations 
707,613 
363,234 
344,379 </p>

<p>(100 %) 
(51.33 %) 
(48.67 %) </p>

<p>Year of birth 
1963.1 
1963.1 
1963.1 </p>

<p>(3.130) 
(3.130) 
(3.130) </p>

<p>Crime 
0.285 
0.437 
0.125 </p>

<p>(0.452) 
(0.496) 
(0.331) </p>

<p>Property crime 
0.137 
0.207 
0.064 </p>

<p>(0.344) 
(0.405) 
(0.245) </p>

<p>Violent crime 
0.055 
0.095 
0.012 </p>

<p>(0.228) 
(0.294) 
(0.109) </p>

<p>Other crime 
0.225 
0.363 
0.079 </p>

<p>(0.418) 
(0.481) 
(0.270) </p>

<p>Nr of crimes|Nr of crimes &gt; 0 
6.825 
7.655 
3.764 </p>

<p>(21.248) 
(23.118) 
(11.543) </p>

<p>Nr of property crimes|Nr of property crimes &gt; 0 
5.944 
6.661 
3.514 </p>

<p>(14.926) 
(16.403) 
(7.633) </p>

<p>Nr of violent crimes|Nr of violent crimes &gt; 0 
2.663 
2.779 
1.688 </p>

<p>(3.549) 
(3.683) 
(1.841) </p>

<p>Nr of other crimes|Nr of other crimes &gt; 0 
4.372 
4.691 
2.826 </p>

<p>(12.465) 
(13.110) 
(8.518) </p>

<p>Prison 
0.044 
0.078 
0.007 </p>

<p>(0.204) 
(0.269) 
(0.083) </p>

<p>Prison|Nr of crimes &gt; 0 
0.153 
0.179 
0.055 </p>

<p>(0.360) 
(0.384) 
(0.229) </p>

<p>Days sentenced to prison|days sentenced to prison &gt; 0 
455.258 
462.639 
367.062 </p>

<p>(927.970) 
(947.832) 
(638.470) </p>

<p>Standard deviations (or %) in parentheses </p>

<p>4.2 Intensive margin </p>

<p>The intensive margin correlations are computed using binary outcome variables. 21 
For crime, we have constructed binary outcome variables taking the value 1 if an 
individual has committed at least x crimes (where x is equal to 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 10 
crimes). For prison sentence length, we have constructed binary outcome variables 
indicating if an individual has spent a total of at least x months in prison (where x is </p>

<p>21 These correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command. Year and gender dummies are 
included in these estimations. Singletons are included, except when estimating the sibling correlations for 
mixed siblings. The estimated correlations are never sensitive to the inclusion/exclusion of singletons. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Table 3 Extensive margin sibling correlations </p>

<p>All siblings 
Brothers 
Sisters 
Mixed siblings </p>

<p>Crime 
0.244 
0.287 
0.242 
0.228 </p>

<p>(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.007) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Property crime 
0.331 
0.375 
0.335 
0.308 </p>

<p>(0.004) 
(0.005) 
(0.009) 
(0.005) </p>

<p>Violent crime 
0.348 
0.371 
0.374 
0.315 </p>

<p>(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.021) 
(0.007) </p>

<p>Other crime 
0.213 
0.243 
0.209 
0.196 </p>

<p>(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.009) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Prison 
0.387 
0.386 
0.435 
0.364 </p>

<p>(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.026) 
(0.008) </p>

<p>Nr of observations 
707,613 
363,234 
344,379 
311,020 </p>

<p>Sibling correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command. All outcome variables are dichoto-
mous. Birth year and gender dummies are included. Standard errors are in parentheses. Singletons 
are included, except in the estimation of the mixed siblings. Estimates are not sensitive to the inclu-
sion/exclusion of singletons </p>

<p>equal to 0.5, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, or 12 months). We show the intensive margin correlations 
in Fig. 1 along with approximate 95 % confidence intervals. 
The trend line in Fig. 1 is upward sloping for sibling correlations in crime. This 
means that factors shared by siblings account for a larger share of the variation in 
crime at the intensive margin. For instance, for sisters, the share of the variation that 
can be attributed to factors shared by siblings is more than twice as high for "at least 
10 crimes" than for "at least 1 crime." 
This upward-sloping trend line is present across all different crime types (see 
Appendix Fig. 7) and is quite similar for both brothers and sisters. The intensive 
margin correlations for mixed siblings, however, are noticeably lower than those 
for same-sex siblings, though the same upward trend in the correlation persists. For 
prison sentence length, there is a weakly upward-sloping trend for brothers but not for 
sisters; it should be noted, however, that the sister correlations are relatively imprecise 
due to the low rate of female incarceration. 
Taken together, the sibling correlations presented above suggest that family back-
ground is a stronger determinant of crime at the intensive margin than it is at the 
extensive margin. It is responsible for between 33 and 57 % of the variation in crime 
at the intensive margin, depending on crime type, the number of crimes committed, 
and gender. This conclusion is also supported by the findings that (i) the extensive 
margin correlations for property and violent crimes, which tend to contain more rela-
tively serious offenses, were greater than those for other crimes and (ii) the extensive 
margin incarceration correlation was stronger than that for convictions, as having any 
incarceration spells can be seen as a proxy for the severity of criminality since more 
severe crimes or more convictions (concurrently or in the past) are more likely to 
result in an incarceration spell. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brothers 
Sisters </p>

<p>Mixed Siblings 
95% CI </p>

<p>Crime </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Prison </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Sibling correlations in crime and prison </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Thus, while family and community background are important determinants of 
whether an individual begins a criminal career, they appear to be even more impor-
tant determinants of the intensity (severity and length) of that criminal career. This 
naturally leads to the question of why? One possible explanation is social inter-
actions or peer effects within a family: each sibling's criminal behavior reinforces 
the criminal behavior of the other. 22 Alternatively, different risk factors may clus-
ter within families or be strongly correlated over time. Parental attitudes, parenting 
strategies, and family resources (broadly defined) may also affect how success-
ful parents are at correcting episodes of deviant behavior that many teenagers 
experience. </p>

<p>4.3 Sibling spacing </p>

<p>In our baseline sample, siblings can be born up to 10 years apart from each other. In 
Fig. 2, we report estimates of the brother and sister correlation in crime between pairs 
of brothers and sisters born (i) at most 4 years apart, (ii) 4 to 6 years apart, (iii) 6 to 
8 years apart, and (iv) 8 to 10 years apart. At the extensive margin, we see that the 
share of the variation in crime explained by common family background is similar for 
those born within 4 years of each other and those born 4 to 6 years apart; given that 
a majority of siblings in the sample are within 6 years of each other, these estimates 
also correspond to our baseline estimates for the full sample. In contrast, the share of 
variation in crime explained by common family background is lower for those born 
more than 6 years apart. This is particularly true for sisters born more than 8 years 
apart. 23 Two patterns emerge at the intensive margin. First, for all siblings, regardless 
of how far apart they are in age, the same upward trend in the correlation is seen 
as the number of crimes studied increases. Second, the intensive margin correlations 
monotonically decreases as the sibling spacing increases: this is true regardless of 
which intensive margin is being studied (i.e., at least two offenses, at least three 
offenses, etc.). 
So why might sibling spacing matter for the size of the sibling correlation? We 
believe that there are two main reasons for this. First, siblings born further apart 
may, in fact, not experience the same types of environments while growing up. 
This can be true even if siblings grow up with their biological parents in an intact 
family, as, for instance, they may experience the same factor (e.g., parental earn-
ings) at different ages and corresponding periods in their development. Second, it </p>

<p>22 See Altonji et al. (2013) for a study of sibling peer effects in substance abuse, Bayer et al. (2008) for 
evidence of similar reinforcing peer effects in juvenile correctional facilities, and Lindquist and Zenou 
(2014) for a study on peer effects in networks of co-offenders. 
23 One should keep in mind that sibling pairs born many years apart comprise only a small fraction of the 
baseline sample. The standard errors on these estimates are also very large. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Baseline, &lt;= 10 years 
&lt;= 4 years apart </p>

<p>4-6 years apart 
6-8 years apart </p>

<p>8-10 years apart </p>

<p>Crime, Brothers Born X Years Apart </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Crime, Sisters Born X Years Apart </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Sibling correlations in crime for brother and sister pairs born X years apart </p>

<p>may be the case that siblings born close together have a stronger influence on each 
other's behavior. That is, closely spaced siblings may experience stronger sibling 
peer effects. Regardless of the mechanism, we need to consider sibling spacing when </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>accounting for the size of the sibling correlation. We return to this discussion in 
Section 5.2 below. </p>

<p>5 Accounting for sibling correlations in criminal convictions 
and incarcerations </p>

<p>5.1 The role of parental education, income, and crime and family structure </p>

<p>Can family-wide factors explain sibling similarities in crime? In this section, we 
present the results of our accounting exercise, which explores a number of character-
istics that are common to individuals within the same family, but which vary across 
families, to gauge the extent to which these factors contribute to the high sibling cor-
relation in crime. In particular, we consider parental education and income, parental 
criminality, and family structure. 
We choose these particular variables because of the existing literature demon-
strating their relative importance in explaining crime. For instance, an individual's 
education has been demonstrated to have a causal impact on his own criminal behav-
ior (Lochner and Moretti 2004; Machin et al. 2011; Hjalmarsson et al. forthcoming) 
and has even been demonstrated to have an impact on the next generation's criminal 
behavior (Meghir et al. 2012). These facts, combined with the evidence on the inter-
generational transmission of education (see, e.g., Holmlund et al. 2011), suggest that 
parental education may explain a substantial share of sibling crime correlations. Sim-
ilar findings have been found for parental income. Akee et al. (2010) demonstrate 
that parental income has a causal impact that lowers the probability of minor offenses 
among children and the likelihood that a child self-reports that he/she has sold drugs. 
There is also evidence that parental criminality is a strong predictor of child crim-
inality; for example, Hjalmarsson and Lindquist (2013) find that having a father 
(mother) with at least one conviction increases the son's chance of conviction by 
12.1 (13.4) percentage points, respectively. 24 Finally, there is an extensive sociol-
ogy literature demonstrating the positive relationship between family structure (e.g., 
teenage mothers, female-headed households, or single-parent households) and chil-
dren's criminal behavior, though it is often hard to distinguish correlation from 
causality. 25 
As discussed in Section 3, our measures of parent criminality and incarceration 
are constructed in the same manner as those for siblings. Mothers' and fathers' edu-
cations are measured in seven levels ranging from grade school to graduate school. 
These levels are included separately for each parent as dummies in our regressions. 
We also include a dummy for missing education. Parental income is measured as the </p>

<p>24 In addition, Hjalmarsson and Lindquist (2012) find that sons whose fathers have at least one sentence 
have 2.06 times higher odds of having at least one criminal conviction than sons whose fathers do not have 
any sentence. 
25 Cáceres-Delpiano and Giolito (2012) provide recent evidence of a causal relationship, as they demon-
strate that the change in US divorce laws to unilateral divorce (i.e., making divorce easier) increased violent 
crime rates by almost 9 %. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>log of average real income for the years 1968-2007 (zeros are averaged in, while the 
very few missing observations are left out). Once again, this is entered separately for 
each parent. 
We have created several different measures of family structure, and we always 
include all of them simultaneously. First, we have a measure of household size for 
when the child was age 15. Second, we include a dummy if the father is unknown. 
Third, we include the mother's age at the birth of her first child. Lastly, we include 
a measure of household type at age 15, which includes six categories: (i) unknown, 
(ii) single mom, (iii) single dad, (iv) both parents living together, (v) mother and new 
father, and (vi) father and new mother. 
We show the sibling correlations estimated with and without controls for up to 10 
crimes in Fig. 3 and for up to 1 year in prison in Fig. 4. In Appendix Figs. 9, 10, 
and 11, we show the results broken down by crime type. Note that these three cat-
egories of controls (i.e., parental income/education, parental criminality, and family 
structure) are first entered separately in the model and then, in a final specification, 
simultaneously. When discussing the results of these specifications, we refer to the 
degree to which the sibling correlation is lowered when adding the various controls; 
this is our metric for measuring the "importance" of a control variable. 26 
When we control for both parental income and education at the same time, the 
brother correlations decrease by at most 9 % (for "at least one violent crime") and the 
sister correlations decrease by at most 8 % (for "at least two crimes"). The brother 
correlations in prison sentence length decrease by at most 9 % (for "at least 2 weeks 
in prison"), while none of the decreases in the sister correlations in prison sentence 
length are statistically significant. 
Compared to the baseline correlations with no controls, controlling for just 
parental criminality decreases the correlations in criminal convictions by at most 
13 % for brothers (for "at least one other crime") and 17 % for sisters (for "at least 
one other crime"). The correlations in prison sentence length decrease by at most 
11 % for brothers (for "at least 2 weeks in prison") and 21 % for sisters (for "at least 
1 month in prison"). In general, the percentage decreases are larger for sisters than 
for brothers. 
Are these results in line with what one might expect given the results reported in 
the literature on intergenerational crime? Hjalmarsson and Lindquist (2013) report a 
father-offspring association of 0.121 and a mother-offspring association of 0.134 for 
having at least one conviction of any type. Squaring these numbers (i.e., applying 
Solon's (1999) decomposition formula) and then dividing by the sibling correlation 
tells us that parental criminality (and its correlates) should account for between 6 and 
7 % of the sibling correlation if only one parent has a conviction. 27 If both parents are 
convicted, then the parent-offspring association is 0.228 (Hjalmarsson and Lindquist 
2013) and can account for 21 % of the sibling correlation in crime. 28 Thus, our new </p>

<p>26 "Importance" refers to the ability of the control variable to explain the sibling correlation in crime, not 
the ability of the variable to explain crime more generally. 
27 0.121 2 /0.244 = 0.060, 0.134 2 /0.244 = 0.074. 
28 0.228 2 /0.244 = 0.213. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>.1 .2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in Crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in Crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in Crime </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Sibling correlations in crime controlling for parental income and education, parental criminality, 
and family structure. Note: We show the sibling correlations estimated with (without) controls in grey 
(black) </p>

<p>findings appear to be in line with what one might expect from the results reported in 
the intergenerational crime literature. 
Despite this, we are still concerned that we might be underestimating the impor-</p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Brother correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Brother correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Brother correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 
.3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Brother correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Sister correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Sister correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Sister correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Sister correlations in prison sentence 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Sibling correlations in prison controlling for parental income and education, parental criminality, 
and family structure. Note: We show the sibling correlations estimated with (without) controls in grey 
(black) </p>

<p>tance of parental criminality. The parents used in this study are quite old, which 
means that their crime data are heavily censored (recall that our crime data start in </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>1973 when parents in our data are on average 39 years old). In order to examine 
this potential issue of measurement error in parental crime, we split our sample into 
two groups; the older cohorts born 1958-1962 with (on average) older parents and 
the younger cohorts born 1964-1968 with (on average) younger parents. If crime 
among the younger cohorts of parents accounts for a larger share of the sibling corre-
lation than does crime among the older cohorts of parents, then this may indicate that 
measurement error in parental criminality is biasing our measures of its quantitative 
importance downwards. 29 
After splitting the sample this way, we see that the amount of the brother corre-
lation in Crime that can be accounted for by parental criminality rises from 10 to 
14 %. The amount of the sister correlation explained by parental criminality, however, 
remains fairly constant across samples, changing from 13 to 12 % when moving from 
the older to the younger parents. Similar increases for brothers, and no increases for 
sisters, can be seen across all extensive margin variables. Importantly, we do not see 
the same increase in explanatory power of parental income and education if we re-
run that experiment after splitting the sample into younger and older cohorts. Thus, 
we conclude that measurement error in parental criminality may bias the explanatory 
power of parental criminality downwards more for brothers than for sisters. Thus, 
parental criminality may explain the same amount of the variation among brothers as 
among sisters. 
When we add controls for just family structure, the correlations in criminal con-
victions decrease by at most 19 % for brothers (for "at least one crime") and 16 % 
for sisters (for "at least one crime") compared to the baseline with no controls. The 
correlations in prison sentence length decrease by at most 15 % for brothers (for 
"at least 2 weeks in prison"), while for sisters the decrease is never statistically 
significant. 
These results suggest that both parental criminality and family structure are rel-
atively more important in explaining sibling correlations in crime than parental 
education and income. One possible explanation for this is that both the parental 
criminality and family structure variables are themselves impacted by parental edu-
cation and income, and thus controlling for either of these variables actually captures 
some of the effect of parental income and education in addition to the direct effect 
of parental criminality or family structure. While this is true to some extent, a factor 
analysis of our explanatory variables concludes that there are three clearly distinct 
factors. Factor 1 is based on parents' education and income. Factor 2 represents 
parental criminality. Factor 3 represents household structure. Mother's age at first 
birth, however, loads equally onto all three factors. 
When we include all the above controls at once, the correlations in criminal 
convictions decrease by at most 27 % for brothers (for "at least one crime") and </p>

<p>29 As we suspected, only 23 % of the older fathers have a conviction and 4 % have a prison sentence, while 
27 % of the younger fathers have a conviction and 5 % have a prison sentence. For mothers, we see that 
8 % of the older mothers have a conviction and 0.2 % have a prison sentence, while 9 % of the younger 
mothers have a conviction and 0.4 % have a prison sentence. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>26 % for sisters (for "at least one crime"), and the correlations in prison sen-
tence length decrease by at most 23 % for brothers (for "at least 2 weeks in 
prison") and 26 % for sisters (for "at least 1 month in prison"). We, therefore, 
conclude that around one fourth of the sibling similarities in criminal outcomes 
can be accounted for by our set of family-wide controls, suggesting that sibling 
associations in criminal behavior are driven mainly by factors common to sib-
lings other than parental income and education, parental criminality, and family 
structure. </p>

<p>5.2 Sibling spacing </p>

<p>Siblings born many years apart may, in fact, experience quite dissimilar home envi-
ronments. This could explain why our set of family-wide variables does not account 
for the majority of the sibling correlation. Household type at age 15 and household 
size at age 15 vary across siblings. But our measures of parental income, parental 
education, parental crime, father unknown, and mother's age at first birth do not. The 
influence that these variables may have on the environments experienced by children 
is not allowed to vary over time. 
To gauge the importance of sibling spacing for our accounting exercise, we 
re-run the experiment using pairs of brothers and sisters born at most 4 years 
apart and compare these results to those obtained when using sibling pairs born 
6 to 10 years apart. In Fig. 5, we see that our family-wide variables account 
for as much of the sibling correlation among widely spaced siblings as they do 
for closely spaced siblings. (For instance, the extensive margin correlations for 
brothers born within 4 years of each other and those born six or more years 
apart are both reduced by 26 % when including the full set of controls). This 
implies that the larger correlation between closely spaced siblings is being driven 
by unobserved family factors that differ between these two types of siblings. It 
also implies that these unobservables are quite important. Sibling peer influences 
might be one such factor (see, e.g., Schrøter Joensen and Skyt Nielsen 2015). Other 
factors could include time-varying family factors or time-varying neighborhood 
influences. </p>

<p>5.3 Sibling peer effects </p>

<p>In this section, we attempt to explore to what extent our sibling correlations in crime 
are driven by direct sibling peer effects. That is, we examine if the criminal behav-
ior of an individual directly influences the criminal behavior of their sibling. Our 
focus in these experiments is on unique sibling pairs, i.e., on families that contribute 
exactly one pair of siblings to our sample. We first examine the impact that older 
siblings' crime has on younger siblings' crime after controlling for both observable 
family characteristics and unobservable family effects. We then differentiate this 
direct sibling effect by gender. 
Research emanating from several disciplines (including child psychology and 
child development) provides support for the hypothesis that older siblings influ-
ence younger siblings' risky behaviors and delinquency, while younger siblings </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>no controls </p>

<p>with controls </p>

<p>Brothers Born &lt;= 4 Years Apart </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Brothers Born &gt;= 6 Years Apart </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sisters Born &lt;= 4 Years Apart </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Sisters Born &gt;= 6 Years Apart </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Sibling correlations in crime for closely spaced siblings and widely spaced siblings with and 
without controls for family background </p>

<p>tend to have much less of a direct influence on older siblings' behaviors (see, 
e.g., Needle et al. 1986, Rodgers and Rowe 1988, Buhrmester 1992, Slomkowski </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>et al. 2001). Empirical work done by economists lends further support to this hypoth-
esis (Oettinger 2000; Ouyang 2004; Altonji et al. 2013). 30 Two mechanisms stand 
out in this literature: (i) older siblings act as role models and (ii) older siblings act as 
suppliers of substances, opportunities, and/or delinquent peers. 
Direct sibling effects may also be gender specific. A stronger same-sex transmis-
sion of criminal behavior could be an indication of the presence of role modeling. 
Role model identification theory implies that role models are more often of the same 
gender (Ruef et al. 2003). More generally, homophily is prevalent in many rela-
tionships; that is, individuals have a tendency to bond easier with similar others 
(McPherson et al. 2001). 
In this section, we switch to using a panel estimator, since we intend to use the 
timing of siblings' crimes to help us identify potential sibling peer effects. Our work-
ing hypotheses are (i) that peer influences flow from older to younger siblings and 
(ii) that these influences will be stronger for same-sex siblings. 
In Eq. 9, we estimate the raw association between a younger sibling's crime in 
year t, C 2 
t , and the older sibling's lagged crime in year t − 1, C 1 
t−1 , </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t = β 0 + ρC </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 + u </p>

<p>2 
t </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>Superscript 2 denotes the younger sibling and superscript 1 denotes the older sibling. 
We then re-estimate this association including all of our shared family background 
controls, X f , and age dummies, age 2 
t , at time t for the younger sibling, </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t = β 0 + ρC </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 + X 
f + age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t + ε </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t . 
(10) </p>

<p>In order to estimate Eqs. 9 and 10, we have created an annual panel data set for 
the years 1973-1993. We restrict the analysis to sibling pairs with a maximum age 
difference of 10 years and to years when the younger sibling is at least 15 years 
old (the age of criminal majority in Sweden). Thus, for the younger siblings, we are 
including all peak years of crime (ages 18-21), as well as all available teenage years 
(15+). We create annual extensive margin variables for all crimes and by crime type. 
Keep in mind, however, that individuals may have extensive margin values equal to 1 
in more than 1 year, which makes the estimated results (as we shall see in a moment) 
look more similar to those of our intensive margin analysis than our extensive margin 
analysis. 31 Equations 9 and 10 are estimated using logistic models (as are our sibling 
correlations). We report both odds ratios and sibling correlations. Standard errors are 
clustered on individuals (the younger sibling). 
The results estimated from Eqs. 9 and 10 are reported in the first two columns of 
Table 4 for all crime. Having an older sibling who is convicted of at least one crime 
in year t − 1 raises the younger sibling's odds of receiving at least one conviction in </p>

<p>30 Schrøter Joensen and Skyt Nielsen (2015) report a causal influence of older male siblings' choice of 
academic curricula on their younger male siblings' choice of academic curricula. 
31 None of the results in the section change if we, instead, use the number of convictions each year, that is 
if we instead create a panel of annual intensive margin variables. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Table 4 Estimates of potential sibling peer effects in crime </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>C 1 </p>

<p>t−1 </p>

<p>2.88  *  *  *  
2.01  *  *  *  
1.03 
1.03 </p>

<p>(0.046) 
(0.033) 
(0.030) 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Sib. corr. 
ρ = 0.41 
ρ ≈ 0.28 
ρ ≈ 0.01 
ρ ≈ 0.01 </p>

<p>C 1 </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>1.19  *  *  *  
3.15  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.034) 
(0.050) </p>

<p>Sib. corr. 
ρ ≈ 0.07 
ρ = 0.41 </p>

<p>Controls: </p>

<p>Family background 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Age younger sibling 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Age older sibling 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>C 1 
t−1 + C 1 </p>

<p>t+1 </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>C 1 
t−1 + C 1 
t + C 1 </p>

<p>t+1 </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Nr obs. 
1,831,259 
1,831,259 
1,831,259 
1,831,259 
1,831,259 </p>

<p>Odds ratios (OR) are estimated using logistic regressions. Standard errors clustered on individuals, i.e., 
the younger sibling, are reported in parentheses. Family background controls include parental income and 
education, parental criminality, and family structure (household size at age 15, unknown father, mother's 
age at first birth, and household type at age 15). Sibling correlations in columns (1) and (5) are estimated 
using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command. Sibling correlations reported in columns (2-4) are approximated using 
the following formula: 
ρ ≈ (OR φ − 1)/(OR φ + 1), where φ is calibrated using the odds ratios and sibling correlations estimated 
in columns (1) and (5). In the first row of sibling correlations (involving C 1 
t−1 ), φ is equal to 0.82. In the 
second row of sibling correlations (involving C 1 
t ), φ is equal to 0.76 
 *   *   *  p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>year t by 2.88. The associated sibling correlation is 0.41, which is in line with our 
intensive margin results reported earlier. When controlling for the full set of family 
background variables and the younger sibling's age at time t, the odds ratio (sibling 
correlation) is reduced by 30 % (32 %). These reductions echo our previous results. 
The question now is: How much of the remaining association can be ascribed to a 
direct sibling influence that the older sibling has on his/her younger sibling and how 
much is due to correlated random family effects that are unobservable? To answer 
this important question, Altonji et al. (2013) propose the use of a correlated random-
effects regression to estimate the direct sibling effect, which takes advantage of the 
temporal nature of sibling effects and relies on the assumption that younger siblings 
do not influence older siblings. 32 They use the sum of the older sibling's crime at </p>

<p>32 A second important identifying assumption is that parents do not change their behavior towards the 
younger sibling after the older sibling is caught committing a crime, e.g., that they do not monitor both 
children more stringently. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>t −1 and t +1 as a control for correlated random effects (i.e., the unobservable family 
component). Including this control, Eq. 10 can be re-written as </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t = β 0 + β 1 (C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 + C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t+1 ) + λ 0 C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 + X 
f + age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t + age </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t + ε </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t , 
(11) </p>

<p>where λ 0 , the coefficient on the early behavior, represents the direct sibling influence 
that the lagged crime of an older sibling has on his/her younger sibling. 33,34 We can 
also allow for a contemporaneous effect, i.e., a direct influence of the older sibling's 
current crime, C 1 
t , on the younger sibling's current crime </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t = β 0 +β 1 C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 + C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t + C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t+1 +λ 0 C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t−1 +λ 1 C </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t +X 
f +age </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t +age </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t +ξ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t , (12) </p>

<p>where the contemporaneous effect is given by λ 1 . 
We report results from estimating Eqs. 11 and 12 in columns (3) and (4) in Table 4. 
Controlling for the correlated random effect appears to explain the remainder of the 
relationship between the younger sibling's crime at time t and the older sibling's 
crime at t − 1. That is, our estimate of λ 0 is small and statistically insignificant in 
both columns, suggesting that there is no direct effect of the older sibling's crime at 
time t − 1 on the younger sibling's crime at time t. However, as shown in column 4, 
our estimate of λ 1 results in a statistically significant odds ratio of 1.19 and a sibling 
correlation of 0.07. The results from estimating these regressions for each crime type 
follow the same pattern as above: no effect of the older sibling's lagged crime and 
a positive contemporaneous effect. Lastly, the contemporaneous sibling correlation 
in our panel data set is 0.41 (see column (5) of Table 4). This implies that a direct 
contemporaneous sibling peer effect could at most account for 100  *  0.07/0.41 = 
17 % of the raw sibling correlation. But, much of this contemporaneous correlation 
could also simply be due to unobservable family-wide contemporaneous shocks. 
We now turn to the gender-specific results. In Table 5, we show results from 
estimating Eq. 12 separately for the four different gender combinations of siblings: 
sister-sister, sister-brother, brother-sister, and brother-brother. The most important 
finding from the gender-specific analysis is that the positive contemporaneous effect 
is present for same-sex siblings but insignificant for mixed-sex siblings. Just as for the 
pooled sample, the effect of the older sibling's lagged crime is insignificant. The raw 
brother (sister) correlation is 0.36 (0.43), which means that a potential direct contem-
poraneous same-sex sibling effect could at most account for 100  *  0.06/0.36 = 17 % 
(100  *  0.11/0.43 = 26 %) of the raw correlation. 
We draw two main conclusions from this exercise. First, we find no evidence of 
a direct influence of the older sibling's lagged crime on the younger sibling's crime. 
This result may indicate that lagged sibling effects are not important determinants of 
our sibling correlations in crime. However, having an older sibling commit a crime 
(and get convicted) may deter a younger sibling from committing crime by resulting </p>

<p>33 This equation is derived from a pair of discrete choice models (one for each sibling) and relies on a set 
of very strong identifying assumptions. We refer the reader to Section 5.2 in Altonji et al. (2013) for a 
detailed discussion of these assumptions. 
34 Altonji et al. (2013) clearly recognize the advantage of the simplicity of the correlated random-effects 
approach but also note its disadvantages-namely that state dependence and non-stationarity with respect 
to age could bias the estimate of the older sibling's influence, though the direction of the bias is unknown. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Table 5 Estimates of potential sibling peer effects in crime using different gender combinations of 
siblings </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>F1F2 
F1M2 
M1F2 
M1M2 </p>

<p>C 1 </p>

<p>t−1 </p>

<p>0.81 
1.03 
1.08 
1.05 </p>

<p>(0.116) 
(0.071) 
(0.087) 
(0.033) </p>

<p>Sib. corr. 
ρ ≈ −0.05 
ρ ≈ 0.01 
ρ ≈ 0.02 
ρ ≈ 0.01 </p>

<p>C 1 </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>1.52 
1.07 
1.05 
1.24 </p>

<p>(0.223)  *  *  *  
(0.074) 
(0.081) 
(0.039)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Sib. corr. 
ρ ≈ 0.11 
ρ ≈ 0.02 
ρ ≈ 0.01 
ρ ≈ 0.06 </p>

<p>Family background 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Age younger sibling 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Age older sibling 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>C 1 
t−1 + C 1 
t + C 1 </p>

<p>t+1 </p>

<p>Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Nr of observations 
425,593 
464,553 
462,589 
478,524 </p>

<p>In the column titles, F1 denotes that the older sibling is female, M1 that the older sibling is male, F2 
that the younger sibling is female, and M2 that the younger sibling is male. Odds ratios are estimated 
using logistic regressions. Standard errors clustered on individuals (the younger sibling) are reported in 
parentheses. Family background controls include parental income and education, parental criminality, and 
family structure (household size at age 15, unknown father, mother's age at first birth, and household type 
at age 15). Sibling correlations are approximated using the following formula, ρ ≈ (OR 
φ − 1)/(OR 
φ − 
1), where φ is calibrated using the appropriate gender-specific or mixed-gender odds ratio and sibling 
correlation, both estimated without controls. See also the note to Table 4 
 *   *   *  p &lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>in an updating of their beliefs regarding expected punishment. Thus, our results may 
also result from positive (role model) and negative (deterrence) sibling peer effects 
that cancel each other out. Second, we find a positive and significant effect of the 
older sibling's current crime. This effect may indicate that there is a direct contem-
poraneous sibling effect, for instance because siblings provide each other with crime 
opportunities. 35 Alternatively, siblings may be exposed to family-or neighborhood-
specific shocks, not captured by our family-wide control variables or by our controls </p>

<p>35 The contemporaneous effect may be partly driven by siblings committing crimes together. We have 
access to data on co-offending (see Lindquist and Zenou 2014 for a description of these data). In these 
data, we see that siblings co-offend when they are teenagers and presumably still living together. Adult 
siblings rarely co-offend. In contrast to this, the size of our contemporaneous sibling effect does not vary 
substantially by siblings' age (results not reported here). Thus, we do not believe that co-offending is the 
main driver of the contemporaneous effect. Furthermore, girls rarely co-offend with their sisters. Despite 
this, estimates of the contemporaneous sister effect are still significant. Girls are more likely to co-offend 
with a brother than a sister. But we see no contemporaneous effect for mixed-sex siblings. These results 
also speak against co-offending as being the main source of the contemporaneous same-sex sibling effect 
that we see in our data. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>for the correlated random effects, inducing them to commit crimes at the same point 
in time. </p>

<p>5.4 Neighborhood effects </p>

<p>Although we have been able to account for a significant share of the sibling cor-
relation, an even larger share remains unexplained. In this section, we explore the 
potential role of neighborhood effects that are shared by siblings. Studies in eco-
nomics suggest that neighborhoods may have causal effects on individual crime (e.g., 
Ludwig et al. 2001, Kling et al. 2005, and Damm and Dustmann 2014). In contrast 
to these studies, Sariaslan et al. (2013) present evidence that Swedish neighborhoods 
do not appear to have a direct effect on violent crime and substance abuse among 
youths aged 15 to 20, at least not at the extensive margin. 36 
Here, we present neighborhood correlations in crime at the extensive and inten-
sive margin broken down by crime type and gender. In the absence of family-
neighborhood interaction effects, these neighborhood correlations act as an upper 
bound on the part of the sibling correlation that shared neighborhood environments 
could potentially account for (see Solon et al. 2000 and our discussion in Section 2). 
To net out sorting into neighborhoods, we include all of the family-wide control 
variables used in the previous section. 
We define a neighborhood as the parish that a child lived in at (or around) age 
15. 37 Parishes are the smallest administrative unit in Sweden. For the cohorts that we 
study in this paper, parishes correspond quite closely to school districts (catchment 
areas). We use data from the 1975, 1980, and 1985 bidecennial censuses to assign 
parish codes. From the 1980 census, we have, for example, information from 2,602 
parishes. The smallest parish contains only 1 family; the median number of families 
is 43, the mean is 157, and the largest contains 3,034 families. 
We report the extensive margin neighborhood correlations in Table 6. The neigh-
borhood correlation in crime for all individuals is 0.01, suggesting that (at most) 1 % 
of the total variation in crime can be explained by factors that individuals growing 
up in the same neighborhood share. Investigating the neighborhood correlations for 
each of the crime types separately, the correlation is 0.02 for property crime, 0.02 for 
violent crime, and 0.01 for other crime. For prison, the neighborhood correlation is 
0.02. The neighborhood correlation is thus lower for other crimes than for property 
crimes, violent crimes, and prison. 
The highest correlations are the correlations for property crime for men and 
women, which are both 0.03. These correlations indicate that at most 3 % of the 
variation in property crime can be attributed to shared neighborhood factors. These </p>

<p>36 Most Swedish studies using observational data tend to find limited influences of neighborhoods on chil-
dren's outcomes (e.g., Brännström 2004 and Lindahl 2011). However, several quasi-experimental studies 
have demonstrated that growing up in an ethnic enclave in Sweden does have an important effect on 
children's outcomes (e.g., Edin et al. 2003 andÅslund et al. 2011). 
37 We cannot get information on schools attended nor on the Small Area Marketing Statistics used to define 
neighborhoods in Sariaslan et al. (2013), since the cohorts we study are too old. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Table 6 Extensive margin neighborhood correlations </p>

<p>Men and women 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Crime 
0.008 
0.010 
0.011 </p>

<p>(0.001) 
(0.001) 
(0.001) </p>

<p>Property crime 
0.023 
0.025 
0.026 </p>

<p>(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.003) </p>

<p>Violent crime 
0.016 
0.017 
0.012 </p>

<p>(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Other crime 
0.007 
0.009 
0.007 </p>

<p>(0.001) 
(0.001) 
(0.001) </p>

<p>Prison 
0.020 
0.021 
0.021 </p>

<p>(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.007) </p>

<p>Nr of observations 
409,207 
269,672 
259,674 </p>

<p>Neighborhood correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command after first randomly drawing one 
individual from each family. This random draw is done separately for each of the three sample used. All 
outcome variables are dichotomous. Birth year and gender dummies are included. Controls for parental 
education and income, parental criminality, and family structure are also included in order to net out 
sorting into neighborhoods. Standard errors are in parentheses </p>

<p>should be contrasted with our brother and sister correlations in "at least one property 
crime," which are 0.38 and 0.34, respectively. Thus, neighborhood effects appear to 
be able to explain approximately 7 % of the sibling correlation in property crime at 
the extensive margin. Given that we have included all of the family-wide controls 
used in Section 5, these 7 % can be added on to the 27 % explained in the previous 
section. Thus, it appears that we can account for as much as one third of the sibling 
correlation at the extensive margin. 
The intensive margin neighborhood correlations are again computed using binary 
outcome variables. We show the neighborhood correlations for up to 10 crimes and 
up to 1 year in prison in Fig. 6. In Appendix Fig. 8, we show separate figures for each 
crime type. 
Similar to our sibling correlations, neighborhood correlations also increase along 
the intensive margin. For women, the increase in the neighborhood correlation in 
aggregate crime is from 0.011 (for "at least 1 crime") to 0.045 (for "at least 10 
crimes") and, for prison, it rises from 0.021 (for "at least 2 weeks") to 0.059 (for 
"at least 1 year"). For men, the increase in the neighborhood correlation in aggregate 
crime is from 0.010 (for "at least 1 crime") to 0.033 (for "at least 10 crimes") and, 
for time in prison, it rises from 0.021 (for "at least 2 weeks") to 0.048 (for "at least 
1 year"). 
Overall, neighborhood correlations are quite small for all but the most severe 
offenders, and even these are much lower than their corresponding sibling corre-
lations. If the simple linear additive model posited in Eq. 1 is correct, then this 
result would indicate that factors shared by siblings other than shared neighbor-</p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x crimes </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Men and Women 
95% CI </p>

<p>Crime </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 </p>

<p>at least x months </p>

<p>Prison </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Neighborhood correlations in crime and prison </p>

<p>hoods are more important for an individual's criminality than factors shared by 
individuals growing up in the same neighborhood. At the same time, if we relate </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>the size of our estimated neighborhood correlations to the size of the compara-
ble sibling correlations, neighborhood correlations have the potential to explain 
between 7 and 13 % of the sibling correlation beyond that explained by our full 
set of family-specific control variables. This is similar to the amount accounted for 
by parental education and income. As such, neighborhoods cannot be disregarded 
as unimportant. 
One potential explanation for our small estimated neighborhood correlations is 
that our definition of neighborhoods is too broad, both in the geographical sense 
and in the sense that neighborhoods may not map well into peer groups. Alter-
natively, one might want to focus more on the schools that children attend (as in 
Gaviria and Raphael 2001, Calvó-Armengol et al. 2009, and Liu et al. 2012) or on 
close neighbors. Sariaslan et al. (2013) study younger cohorts and, therefore, have 
access to more narrow measures of neighborhoods. They look within the Small Area 
Marketing codes created by Statistics Sweden to define small, homogenous neigh-
borhoods. They also look within schools. But they still find no large neighborhood 
effect. 
Brännström (2004) argues that the small neighborhood effects reported in many 
Swedish studies may be due to the success of the Swedish welfare state. This is 
certainly one possibility. For the USA, Johnson (2007) reports large neighborhood 
correlations in criminal behavior and incarceration. He also reports that growing up 
in low-quality neighborhoods increases the likelihood that one has ever been incar-
cerated. On the other hand, neighborhood correlations in educational attainment are 
quite similar in the USA and Sweden and quite small. 38 It may, therefore, be hard to 
argue that our result is "Sweden specific". Lastly, one should keep in mind that we 
are studying the overall neighborhood effect and not the effect of growing up in an 
extremely disadvantaged neighborhood. 39 
To assess the impact that neighborhood quality might have on our sibling 
correlations, we run an additional experiment. We start by defining a measure 
of neighborhood quality based on the average education level of parents in the 
neighborhood, the average income level of parents, and the share of immigrant 
parents in each neighborhood. 40 We then create a dummy variable equal to 
one for the 10 % of our sibling sample living in the highest quality neighbor-
hoods and a second dummy variable equal to one for the 10 % of our sibling 
sample living in the lowest quality neighborhoods. We estimate neighborhood </p>

<p>38 For the USA, see Solon et al. (2000). For Sweden, see Lindahl (2011). 
39 The Moving to Opportunity program focuses more on helping families leave extremely low-quality 
neighborhoods (Ludwig et al. 2001; Kling et al. 2005). Krivo and Peterson (1996) also study the 
connection between particularly disadvantaged neighborhoods and crime. 
40 Neighborhood quality refers to the characteristics of all of the parents living in the same parish as the 
sibling when the sibling was 15 years old. We first create three different percentile rankings for each 
parish: one based on parental education, a second based on parental income, and a third based on the share 
of parents who were not born in Sweden. Immigration status has been included in order to reflect the 
potential effects of segregation, discrimination, and the feeling of social exclusion that is often discussed in 
the Swedish debate concerning troubled neighborhoods. These three percentile rankings are then weighted 
equally into a final percentile ranking of neighborhood quality. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>correlations for high-and low-quality neighborhoods, and we produce new esti-
mates of the sibling correlation for siblings living in these high-and low-quality 
neighborhoods. 41 
In Table 7, we see that the neighborhood correlations are consistently higher 
in low-quality neighborhoods than in high-quality neighborhoods. More impor-
tantly, the ratio between the neighborhood correlation and the sibling correlation 
is always larger for low-quality neighborhoods than for high-quality neighbor-
hoods. This means that neighborhood effects can potentially explain more of the 
sibling correlation in low-quality neighborhoods, which leads us to conclude that 
neighborhood quality may be one of the factors that makes siblings similar in 
terms of their criminal behavior. However, such neighborhood effects are still 
smaller in magnitude than the roles played by parental criminality and family 
structure. </p>

<p>5.5 Family and neighborhood interaction effects </p>

<p>It is important to keep in mind that any discussion of the relative importance of 
family versus neighborhood effects in accounting for the sibling correlation is only 
really meaningful in the linear additive world described by Eq. 1. If important family-
neighborhood interaction effects do exist, then interpreting the results from our 
accounting exercise is no longer straightforward. For example, the effect of parental 
education on children's outcomes may be quite different in a neighborhood with good 
schools versus one with bad schools. Alternatively, the impact of ethnicity on out-
comes may depend on the number of co-ethnics a person lives close to (see, e.g., Edin 
et al. 2003 andÅslund et al. 2011). 
In principle, we would like to test a version of the following random-effects model, </p>

<p>c if n = μ + a f + a f b n + b n + e if n , 
(13) </p>

<p>which includes a family-neighborhood interaction term, a f b n , in order to ascertain 
whether or not there exist quantitatively meaningful interaction effects. If not, then 
the linear additive model may actually be a good representation of the data, even 
though we know that it is a highly stylized model. In practice, however, the compu-
tational burden of estimating this two-way crossed-effects model with an interaction 
term is extremely challenging (given the very large number of families and neigh-
borhoods in our data). But, more importantly, the ideal data needed to estimate this 
model simply do not exist-i.e., two relatively closely spaced siblings who grew up 
in different neighborhoods (of varying quality), but who still lived with both parents 
in the same intact family. </p>

<p>41 In this exercise, our full set of control variables and age and gender dummies are included in all estima-
tions of both the neighborhood correlation and the sibling correlation. We want to see how much of the 
unexplained part of the sibling correlation could be potentially explained by differences in neighborhood 
quality. In order to do this, we need to control for sorting across different types of neighborhoods that 
could affect the size of both the neighborhood and the sibling correlation. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Table 7 Sibling and neighborhood correlations in high-and low-quality neighborhoods </p>

<p>Men and women 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Crime </p>

<p>Low quality </p>

<p>Neighborhood corr. 
0.009 
0.008 
0.014 </p>

<p>(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Sibling corr. 
0.187 
0.232 
0.199 </p>

<p>(0.010) 
(0.016) 
(0.025) </p>

<p>100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
5 % 
3 % 
7 % </p>

<p>High quality </p>

<p>Neighborhood corr. 
0.002 
0.002 
0.005 </p>

<p>(0.001) 
(0.001) 
(0.002) </p>

<p>Sibling corr. 
0.168 
0.226 
0.113 </p>

<p>(0.011) 
(0.017) 
(0.030) </p>

<p>100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
1 % 
1 % 
4 % </p>

<p>Neighborhood corr. 
0.033 
0.027 
0.094 </p>

<p>(0.008) 
(0.007) 
(0.035) </p>

<p>Low quality </p>

<p>Sibling corr. 
0.438 
0.458 
0.458 </p>

<p>(0.020) 
(0.025) 
(0.078) </p>

<p>At least 
100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
8 % 
6 % 
21 % </p>

<p>10 crimes 
Neighborhood corr. 
0.014 
0.014 
0.007 </p>

<p>(0.006) 
(0.006) 
(0.018) </p>

<p>High quality 
Sibling corr. 
0.385 
0.406 
0.591 </p>

<p>(0.031) 
(0.038) 
(0.079) </p>

<p>100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
4 % 
3 % 
13 % </p>

<p>Neighborhood corr. 
0.022 
0.016 
0.072 </p>

<p>(0.006) 
(0.005) 
(0.031) </p>

<p>Low quality 
Sibling corr. 
0.328 
0.318 
0.345 </p>

<p>(0.021) 
(0.025) 
(0.101) </p>

<p>100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
7 % 
5 % 
21 % </p>

<p>Prison 
Neighborhood corr. 
0.007 
0.008 
0.000 </p>

<p>(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.000) </p>

<p>High quality 
Sibling corr. 
0.327 
0.332 
0.380 </p>

<p>(0.030) 
(0.036) 
(0.136) </p>

<p>100  *  
neighbor corr. 
sib corr. 
= 
2 % 
2 % 
0 % </p>

<p>Neighborhood correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command after first randomly drawing 
one individual from each family. This random draw is done separately for each of the three samples used. 
All outcome variables are dichotomous. Birth year and gender dummies are included. Controls for parish 
size, parental education and income, family structure, and parental criminality are also included in order to 
net out sorting into neighborhoods. Sibling correlations are estimated using <rs type="software">STATA</rs>'s xtlogit command. All 
outcome variables are dichotomous. Birth year and gender dummies are included. Controls for parental 
education and income, parental criminality, and family structure are included, as are birth year and gender 
dummies. Singletons are included, except when estimating the sibling correlations for the mixed siblings </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>Table 8 Interaction effects between family SES and average neighborhood quality in a model of crime at 
the extensive margin </p>

<p>Crime 
Property crime 
Violent crime 
Other crime 
Prison </p>

<p>Fam 1 × neighbor 1 
0.946  *  *  
0.917  *  *  
0.916  *  
0.969 
0.912  *  </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.032) 
(0.046) 
(0.029) 
(0.050) </p>

<p>Fam 1 × neighbor 2 
0.954  *  
0.979 
1.005 
0.966 
1.043 </p>

<p>(0.026) 
(0.033) 
(0.050) 
(0.028) 
(0.057) </p>

<p>Fam 1 × neighbor 4 
1.098  *  *  *  
1.120  *  *  *  
1.135  *  *  
1.099  *  *  *  
1.227  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.033) 
(0.040) 
(0.059) 
(0.035) 
(0.070) </p>

<p>Fam 1 × neighbor 5 
1.058  *  
1.042 
1.042 
1.069  *  
1.066 </p>

<p>(0.035) 
(0.041) 
(0.061) 
(0.038) 
(0.069) </p>

<p>Fam 2 × neighbor 1 
0.992 
1.008 
0.959 
1.013 
0.997 </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.034) 
(0.046) 
(0.029) 
(0.054) </p>

<p>Fam 2 × neighbor 2 
0.964 
0.974 
0.986 
0.970 
0.956 </p>

<p>(0.025) 
(0.032) 
(0.048) 
(0.027) 
(0.052) </p>

<p>Fam 2 × neighbor 4 
0.997 
0.985 
1.041 
1.024 
1.036 </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.033) 
(0.051) 
(0.030) 
(0.057) </p>

<p>Fam 2 × neighbor 5 
1.047 
1.000 
0.989 
1.099  *  *  *  
1.036 </p>

<p>(0.030) 
(0.036) 
(0.053) 
(0.034) 
(0.061) </p>

<p>Fam 4 × neighbor 1 
1.004 
0.964 
0.961 
1.042 
1.049 </p>

<p>(0.029) 
(0.035) 
(0.051) 
(0.032) 
(0.062) </p>

<p>Fam 4 × neighbor 2 
0.998 
1.013 
0.954 
1.018 
1.035 </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.035) 
(0.050) 
(0.030) 
(0.061) </p>

<p>Fam 4 × neighbor 4 
1.007 
0.973 
0.989 
1.024 
1.048 </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.032) 
(0.049) 
(0.029) 
(0.059) </p>

<p>Fam 4 × neighbor 5 
0.968 
0.897  *  *  *  
0.918 
1.012 
0.940 </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.031) 
(0.048) 
(0.030) 
(0.055) </p>

<p>Fam 5 × neighbor 2 
1.071  *  *  
1.077  *  
1.021 
1.079  *  *  
1.066 </p>

<p>(0.033) 
(0.045) 
(0.067) 
(0.036) 
(0.079) </p>

<p>Fam 5 × neighbor 4 
0.984 
1.005 
0.938 
1.000 
0.988 </p>

<p>(0.028) 
(0.037) 
(0.055) 
(0.030) 
(0.065) </p>

<p>Fam 5 × neighbor 5 
0.991 
0.982 
0.854  *  *  *  
0.990 
0.886  *  </p>

<p>(0.027) 
(0.036) 
(0.050) 
(0.030) 
(0.058) </p>

<p>Observations 
734,520 
734,520 
734,520 
734,520 
734,520 </p>

<p>Coefficients are odds ratios from logistic regressions. Standard errors in parentheses are robust. All regres-
sions include birth year and gender dummies. Controls for parish size, family SES, family structure, 
parental criminality, and neighborhood quality are also included. Family SES 3 and neighborhood quality 
3 are the reference categories 
 *  Significant at 10 % </p>

<p> *  *  Significant at 5 % </p>

<p> *   *   *  Significant at 1 % </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>Thus, we consider an alternative test for the presence of family-neighborhood 
interaction effects that uses standard regression techniques (see, e.g., Winkleby et al. 
2006). Specifically, we use our neighborhood quality index to place neighborhoods 
into quality quintiles, with 1 being the lowest and 5 the highest. We then create a 
similar index for family socio-economic status based on the incomes and education 
levels of both parents. Families are also placed into five SES quintiles, with 1 being 
the lowest and 5 the highest. To look for significant interaction effects, we estimate 
different versions of the following equation: </p>

<p>Crime if n = β 0 + β 1 age i + β 2 sex i + β 3 family SES if + β 4 neighborhood SES in 
+β 5 family SES if × neighborhood SES in + β 6 neighborhood size in 
+β 7 family structure if + β 8 parental crime if + ε if n . 
(14) </p>

<p>We estimate Eq. 14 using a logistic regression and report odds ratios. We use neigh-
borhood quality 3 and family SES 3 as the excluded categories and allow all other 
levels to interact. What we are mainly interested in here is the sign, size, and 
significance of the set of interaction effects given by β 5 . 
Estimation results are presented in Table 8. Although most of the estimated odds 
ratios are small and statistically insignificant, we do see two distinct patterns. First, 
individuals from families that are "well matched" with neighborhoods, i.e., SES 1 
families living in SES 1 neighborhoods and SES 5 families living in SES 5 neigh-
borhoods, appear to experience a small, but statistically significant, protective effect. 
Second, siblings from low-SES families (SES 1) fair worse if they live in rela-
tively high-SES areas (quality 4 and 5) at age 15. This second result could simply 
be due to negative selection; for instance, these families may have been placed by 
the social services in these neighborhoods. If this is the case, then these significant 
coefficients do not represent true interaction effects. Alternatively, it could be that 
a sense of relative deprivation and/or frustration gives rise to a higher crime rate 
among those who come from low-SES families but grow up in relatively high-quality 
neighborhoods. 
In summary, studying family-neighborhood interaction effects is a difficult task. 
But our regression analysis indicates that nontrivial interaction effects may exist. 
However, controlling for these family-neighborhood interactions directly in our cor-
relations analyses does not account for any additional share of the observed sibling 
crime correlations. 42 </p>

<p>42 If we add the interaction effects as controls to the fixed part of our mixed-effects model, they can 
(on their own) account for at most 4-5 % of the sibling correlation depending on the measure of crime 
considered. If we simply add them as additional controls along with our full set of controls, then they do 
not provide any additional accounting power. They add nothing that is not already accounted for by the 
direct effects. </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>6 Conclusion </p>

<p>Our analysis of sibling correlations in criminal behavior yields five main findings. 
First, we find that family background and community factors shared by siblings 
account for 24 % of the variation in the likelihood of having any conviction. Second, 
we find even larger sibling correlations for measures of the intensity and sever-
ity of the criminal career: violent and property offenses versus other offenses, the 
likelihood of incarceration, the number of convictions, and longer prison sentences. 
These patterns are similar across (i) crime types, (ii) male, female, and mixed sib-
ling pairs, and (iii) siblings more and less closely spaced. Third, our analysis of 
which family and community background characteristics account for the sibling 
crime correlations suggests that neighborhood identifiers and parental education and 
income play a relatively less important role than parental criminality and family 
structure. These results are in line with the previous literature on intergenerational 
crime. Neighborhood effects, however, tend to receive much more attention in the 
US literature. Fourth, all of these controls taken together still only explain one 
third of the sibling crime correlation, even for siblings spaced close together. Fifth, 
siblings spaced more closely together are more similar in terms of their criminal 
behavior. 
Several important caveats must be placed on the interpretation of our quantita-
tive accounting exercise. First, when discussing the relative importance of different 
control variables, one must keep in mind that the metric used in this paper to dis-
cuss the importance of different family-wide and neighborhood variables is the 
degree to which they lower the sibling correlation after being included as controls 
in the fixed part of our mixed-effects model. This is not the same as saying which 
effect would be the most policy relevant or cost-effective-although our hope is 
that a better understanding of the sibling correlation may, in the long run, help us 
to better understand the etiology of crime and, hence, aide in the design of better 
policy. 
A second caveat is that our accounting exercise relies on the use of a simple, lin-
ear additive model. The existence of meaningful interaction effects would make it 
much harder to determine the relative importance of one factor over another. Third, 
the results presented in this paper are conditional on the structure of the environment 
in place in Sweden during the time period studied, and cannot readily be extended 
to make statements about the importance of (for example) neighborhood effects in 
the USA today. However, the fact that sibling correlations in crime are so high, even 
in Sweden with its high degree of relative income equality and extensive welfare 
state polices, should be of great interest to a broader audience. It really does put the 
spotlight on the role of family background and circumstances as important determi-
nants of criminal behavior. A final caveat-and our fourth result listed above-is 
that it is striking that we are only able to account for one third of the large sibling 
correlation. </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>This leaves us with the question of what actually does explain the sibling cor-
relation in crime. Of course, we recognize that there are a number of mechanisms 
that our limited set of control variables does not capture. One possibility is genes 
and inherited characteristics that are correlated with criminal behavior. For instance, 
adoption studies that use the criminal records of the biological and adoptive parents 
to disentangle the importance of pre-birth (genes, prenatal environment, and perinatal 
conditions) and post-birth factors for generating intergenerational criminal relation-
ships find evidence that pre-birth factors do play a significant role (Hjalmarsson and 
Lindquist 2013). Twin studies also report an important role for genetic factors in 
the etiology of antisocial behavior and crime (Ishikawa and Raine 2002; Eley et al. 
2013). We would argue, however, that by controlling for the education, income, and 
criminal behavior of both biological parents, we have indeed controlled for most of 
the relevant genetic factors (albeit very imprecisely). 
Using survey data from the Stockholm Birth Cohort, Björklund et al. (2010) show 
that parental involvement in school work, parenting practices, and maternal attitudes 
are important for generating sibling similarities in their adult incomes. In particu-
lar, a mother's willingness to plan and save for the future appears to matter. These 
remain important even after controlling for measures of parental income and edu-
cation, family structure, and social problems. There is also increasing evidence that 
siblings may have a large influence on each other through sibling peer effects (see, 
e.g., Rowe and Farrington 1997, Altonji et al. 2013 and Schrøter Joensen and Skyt 
Nielsen 2015). However, we are not able to provide clear evidence of this in our con-
text. Lastly, we have only begun to scratch the surface on understanding the potential 
role of family-neighborhood interaction effects. Continued work in the area of neigh-
borhood effects, peer effects, sibling peer effects, and sibling similarities in criminal 
behavior is one avenue for moving beyond the analysis of statistical risk factors and 
into the realm of understanding the mechanisms underlying antisocial behavior and 
crime. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments We would like to thank Anders Björklund, Fredrik Carlsson, Magnus Johannesson, 
Mikael Lindahl, Erdal Tekin, two anonymous referees, and seminar participants at EALE 2013, Stock-
holm School of Economics, and ASSA 2014 for their valuable comments and suggestions. Karin Hederos 
Eriksson and Matthew Lindquist gratefully acknowledge financial support from the Swedish Research 
Council for Health, Working Life and Welfare (FORTE). </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) 
and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Figures 7, 8, 9, 10, and 11 </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 </p>

<p>.4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 
correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in property crime </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 
correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in violent crime </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 
correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in other crime </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 
correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in property crime </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in violent crime </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in other crime </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Sibling correlations in property crime, violent crime, and other crime </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Men 
Women </p>

<p>Men and Women 
95% CI </p>

<p>Property Crime </p>

<p>-.1 0 
.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Violent Crime </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Other Crime </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Neighborhood correlations in property crime, violent crime, and other crime </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>



<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in property crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in property crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
at least x property crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in property crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>Fig. 9 Sibling correlations in property crime controlling for parental income and education, parental 
criminality, and family structure. Note: We show the sibling correlations estimated with (without) controls 
in grey (black) </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>



<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x violent crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in violent crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>Fig. 10 Sibling correlations in violent crime controlling for parental income and education, parental crim-
inality, and family structure. Note: We show the sibling correlations estimated with (without) controls in 
grey (black) </p>



<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 .2 
.3 .4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Brother correlations in other crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>.6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Parental Income and Education </p>

<p>.1 
.2 .3 
.4 .5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Parental Criminality </p>

<p>.1 .2 </p>

<p>.3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in other crime 
Controlling for Family Structure </p>

<p>.1 .2 .3 .4 </p>

<p>.5 .6 .7 </p>

<p>correlation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>at least x other crimes </p>

<p>Sister correlations in other crime 
Controlling for All Family Background Variables </p>

<p>Fig. 11 Sibling correlations in other crime controlling for parental income and education, parental crim-
inality, and family structure. Note: We show the sibling correlations estimated with (without) controls in 
grey (black) </p>

<p>Family background, neighborhood effects, and crime </p>







<p>K. Hederos Eriksson et al. </p>



</text></tei>