<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F00036846.2016.1218430" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>This article presents analysis of households' intentions to comply with government constraints on 
the use of urban water, or so-called water restrictions. The data are drawn from Australian cities 
and was collected during a severe drought. Structural equation modelling is employed to 
operationalize constructs taken from the theory of planned behaviour and to answer important 
policy questions related to compliance. The modelled data support the view that attitudes, social 
norms and perceived behavioural control (PBC) have a positive and significant influence on 
intentions to comply. PBC has the strongest influence on intentions, suggesting policy directed 
at assisting households to meet regulatory criteria might be at least as effective as advertising 
expenditures aimed at shaping attitudes and norms. Importantly, intentions to comply are also 
shown to have a positive and significant influence on reported compliance behaviour. </p>

<p>KEYWORDS </p>

<p>Urban water policy; 
compliance behavior; 
structural equation 
modelling; theory of 
planned behavior </p>

<p>JEL CLASSIFICATION </p>

<p>Q25; Q28; Q58 </p>

<p>Applied economists have long been interested in the 
relative importance of different influences on behaviour. 
This extends beyond simply understanding the rational 
consumer's choice and encompasses a range of domains 
including the motivations for altruism (e.g. Wintrobe 
1981), job selection (Clark 1997), voting (e.g. Chari, 
Jones, and Marimon 1997; Barton, Castillo, and Petrie 
2016), risk taking (e.g. Kanbur 1981) and compliance 
with authority (e.g. Becker 1968). Understanding the 
motivations for compliance is particularly important 
for governments since poorly targeted interventions 
run the risk of weakening the impact of state interven-
tion and can simultaneously generate extraordinary 
costs. These risks are particularly high when govern-
ments are inclined to defer to intervention as a matter 
of course, without due consideration to the possibility of 
government failure, as is often the case when water has 
to be allocated in times of scarcity. 
An extended and severe drought in southern 
Australia early in the 2000s resulted in most state 
governments mandating restrictions on how water 
could be used in urban areas (locally referred to as 
'water restrictions'). These constraints included limits 
on which households could apply water outdoors (e.g. </p>

<p>odd numbered houses one day and even numbers 
others), what could be watered outdoors (e.g. lawns 
versus gardens versus filling swimming pools), the 
types of devices that could be used to irrigate out-
doors (e.g. sprinklers versus hand-held hoses) and the 
times at which watering could occur (e.g. days of the 
week and/or number of hours per day). Similar policy 
responses are currently being witnessed in California, 
despite protestations from economists that prices are 
generally more efficient mechanisms for dealing with 
scarcity than rationing based on behavioural con-
straints (see, e.g. Crase and O'Keefe 2009; Grafton et 
al. 2011; PPIC 2015). Setting aside the welfare losses 
that attend these types of restrictions, questions arise 
about why (and if) residents would comply with water 
restrictions imposed by the state. 
There are several reasons why the Australian 
experience with water restrictions in the 2000s pro-
vides a useful context for considering these ques-
tions. First, the parallel with drought responses in 
other parts of the World offers useful contrasts, 
especially as similar restriction regimes are being 
encouraged in places like California (see, PPIC 
2015). Second, despite the fact that the Australian 
drought eased in the late 2000s, legislation for water </p>

<p>CONTACT Bethany Cooper 
b.cooper@latrobe.edu.au 
Present address of Bethany Cooper is University of South Australia, Adelaide, Australia. </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS, 2017 
VOL. 49, NO. 14, 1426-1439 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00036846.2016.1218430 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-
nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built 
upon in any way. </p>

<p>restrictions remain in place, with anecdotally strong 
support from the populace, regardless of estimated 
welfare losses (see, e.g. Cooper, Burton, and Crase 
2011; Allen Consulting Group 2007; Harman, Lynch, 
and McEachern 2008; Edwards 2008). Third, this 
context offers the opportunity to investigate the 
effectiveness of compliance regimes empirically and 
to shed light on the relative importance of psycho-
metric and other exogenous variables. In that regard, 
it is worth noting that the legislation governing 
water restrictions and compliance is not uniform 
across Australian jurisdictions. For example, the fre-
quency and severity with which financial punish-
ment was meted out for recalcitrant behaviour 
differed between states, with Sydney having a history 
of employing substantially more water patrol inspec-
tors and fining residents more often than Melbourne 
(see Cooper, Rose, and Crase 2012). In contrast 
Melbourne residents were subjected to intense 
advertising campaigns aimed at shaping attitudes 
and norms about water conservation. This offers an 
opportunity to reflect on the relative strength of 
differing motivations to comply and matching this 
against the efficacy of alternative compliance 
regimes. 
The theoretical foundation of this study is the 
theory of planned behaviour (TPB) pioneered by 
Ajzen and Fishbein (1970). Accordingly, this article 
also adds to the applications of TPB, which has 
increasingly been shown to be useful in understand-
ing complex economic behaviours (e.g. Kautonen, 
van Gelderen, and Tornikoski 2013). The article 
uses data on compliance behaviour based on a sam-
ple from the two most populous states of Australia -
New South Wales and Victoria. The data set was 
designed to provide representation across a number 
of dimensions -including regional and metropolitan 
cities, water-rich and water-poor communities, and 
differing compliance legislation -but the focus here 
is on behavioural constructs from TPB that should 
be relatively consistent across those dimensions. The 
data are scrutinized using structural equation mod-
elling (SEM), a technique shown to be particularly 
useful where complex behavioural relationships are 
of interest (e.g. Kautonen, van Gelderen, and 
Tornikoski 2013; Powdthavee and Wooden 2015). 
The article itself is divided into five additional 
sections. Section II briefly introduces the TPB and 
summarizes several hypotheses based on related </p>

<p>constructs. The background to the SEM is covered 
in Section III and the survey design and data collec-
tion processes described in Section IV. The results of 
the SEM are presented in Section V. Section VI 
reports on the core findings before offering some 
brief concluding remarks. </p>

<p>II. The conceptual framework -TPB </p>

<p>The TPB is attributed to Ajzen and Fishbein (1970) 
and represents a refinement of earlier models of 
rational decision-making, like the theory of proposi-
tional control (Dunlany 1967) and the theory of 
reasoned action (Ajzen and Fishbein 1970). TPB 
posits that individuals behave rationally to the extent 
that they systematically consider the consequences of 
their actions (Ajzen 1991). The approach is particu-
larly useful for exploring behaviour when individuals 
require skills and resources in addition to the will to 
act (d'Astous, Colbert, and Montpetit 2005; Eagly 
and Chaiken 1993). The model has been widely 
applied (e.g. Ajzen and Fishbein 1977; Bryan, Ruiz, 
and O'Neill 2003; Sheppard, Hartwick, and Warshaw 
1988) and specifically employed to consider delin-
quent behaviour, like cheating and lying (Beck and 
Ajzen 1991), software piracy (Peace, Galletta, and 
Thong 2003), music piracy (d'Astous, Colbert, and 
Montpetit 2005; Kwong and Lee 2002) and shoplift-
ing (Tonglet 2001). Applications in the context of 
economics are also becoming more common (e.g. 
Kautonen, van Gelderen, and Tornikoski 2013; 
Karppinen 2005). The TPB is based on the presump-
tion that three antecedents attend behavioural inten-
tions: namely, the attitude towards the behaviour, 
social norms and perceived behavioural control 
(PBC) (Ajzen and Fishbein 1970). 
Attitudes are broadly defined as 'an evaluative 
predisposition towards the behaviour as a function 
of its determinant personal consequences' (d'Astous, 
Colbert, and Montpetit 2005, 292) implying that the 
relative benefits and costs of choosing a particular 
behaviour underlie attitudes; consequently, the pro-
cess of attitude formation broadly mirrors neo-clas-
sical utility maximization (Becker 1968). The role of 
attitudes in the context of water use and conserva-
tion is somewhat contested with Aitken et al. (1994) 
finding that attitudes had a weak relationship with 
conservation behaviour whilst Moore, Murphy and 
Watson (1994) found significant correlations </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
between water conservation behaviour, intentions 
and attitudes. 
Subjective or social norms can be defined as 'the 
perceived social acceptability of behaviour' 
(Kernsmith 2005, 758), usually by those most sig-
nificant to us, although wider society expectations 
also underpin norms. The positive relationship 
between social norms and compliance is well estab-
lished in the literature (see, e.g. Sutinen and Kuperan 
1999) and undoubtedly the intensive media cam-
paigns used to rein in water use in some Australian 
cities in the 2000s sought to shift norms and even 
encourage community reporting of delinquent beha-
viour of individuals (see, e.g. Wells 2007; Worrall 
2008). The ongoing influence of these campaigns, 
witnessed by an enduring focus on conservation 
regardless of available water supplies, can arguably 
be attributed to the successful alignment of descrip-
tive and injunctive norms, as predicted by Cialdini, 
Reno and Kallgren (1990). 
PBC relates to an individual's perception of their 
capacity (i.e. resources and opportunities) to achieve a 
behaviour (d'Astous, Colbert, and Montpetit 2005). 
Kernsmith (2005) contends that this antecedent com-
prises two parts -generality and strength. The former 
deals with the range of situations over which the 
individual can exercise control and the latter relates 
to the confidence that attends the behaviour. PBC will 
also be shaped by past experiences (Ajzen 1991). 
Behavioural intention is thought to directly influ-
ence behaviour (Ajzen and Fishbein 1970). 
Numerous studies have employed valuation methods 
in an attempt to identify individuals' intentions to 
avoid the impacts of water restrictions (see, e.g. 
Brennan, Tapsuwan, and Ingram 2007; Cooper, 
Rose, and Crase 2012; Gordon, Chapman, and 
Blamey 2001; Griffin and Mjelde 2000; Hensher, </p>

<p>Shore, and Train 2006). However, the literature is 
silent regarding what actually drives individuals' 
intention to comply with urban water restrictions. 
Given the wide acceptance of the TPB, four 
hypotheses follow in the context of water restrictions. 
First, it is hypothesized that there is a positive rela-
tionship between one's attitude towards water restric-
tions and the intention to comply with water 
restrictions. Second, a positive relationship between 
the positive perceptions of important others to water 
restrictions and the intention to comply with those 
restrictions is anticipated. Third, there should be a 
positive relationship between perceptions about the 
ability to comply with water restrictions and the 
intention to comply. Fourth, and importantly, there 
should be a positive relationship between intention to 
comply with water restrictions and actual compliance. 
Previous studies also suggest that there is a corre-
lation between each of the three antecedents to 
intention -i.e. correlation between attitudes and 
social norms, attitudes and PBC, and social norms 
and PBC (see e.g. Ajzen 1991; Swartz and Douglas 
2009). Accordingly, a fifth hypothesis is that an 
individual's attitude towards water restrictions, 
their perception that important others think that 
he/she should comply with water restrictions and 
one's perception that he/she possesses the necessary 
abilities to comply are all correlated. 
The framework of these hypotheses is presented 
in Figure 1. </p>

<p>III. Modelling strategy </p>

<p>The empirical aspects of this study are focused on 
creating the latent constructs that comprise the var-
ious elements of TPB. This is done using multiple 
observed variables (items or manifest variables) and </p>

<p>Figure 1. The conceptual framework. 
This figure illustrates the conceptual framework for this study. The framework shows the relationships between each of the factors 
included in the research hypotheses. </p>

<p> 
B. COOPER </p>

<p>then investigating the causal relationships amongst 
the factors. SEM, also known as simultaneous equa-
tion modelling, is a multivariate (i.e. multi-equation) 
regression model that has the capacity to assist in 
testing the research hypotheses. 
SEM has proven a robust tool for use in statistics, 
economics and the social sciences (e.g. Kautonen, 
van Gelderen, and Tornikoski 2013; Bollen 1989; 
Castellanos-Ryan and Conrod 2010; Cunningham 
et al. 2008; Pearl 2000). SEMs facilitate efficient 
inferences from observations and allow researchers 
to answer questions regarding predictions, interven-
tions and counterfactuals (Harwood and Scheines 
2002). 
Key seminal authors of SEM include Wright 
(1921), Haavelmo (1943) and Koopmans (1953). 
The technique has been described as a combination 
of factor analysis and path analysis (including multi-
ple or multivariate regression) (Ullman 2001). SEM 
is usually deployed as a confirmatory technique, but 
can also be used for exploratory purposes (Schreiber 
et al. 2006). Basically, SEM allows for the testing of 
theoretical propositions about how constructs are 
related and the directionality of significant relation-
ships (see, Ullman 2001). It offers a straightforward 
method of addressing multiple relationships simul-
taneously while providing statistical efficiency (Hair 
et al. 2006). 
SEM considers a series of dependence relation-
ships simultaneously. The method is particularly 
valuable when one dependent variable becomes an 
independent variable in subsequent dependence 
relationships. This set of relationships, each with 
dependent and independent variables, is the basis 
of SEM (Hair et al. 2006). SEM techniques are char-
acterized by two main elements. First, the technique 
provides estimation of multiple and interrelated 
dependence relationships. Second, SEM has the 
capacity to represent unobserved concepts in these 
relationships and account for measurement error in 
the estimation process (Hair et al. 2006). A rudimen-
tary mathematical form of SEM is illustrated in 
equation (1). </p>

<p>x 1 ¼ α 1 þ Xβ 1 þ e Á x 1 </p>

<p>x 2 ¼ α 2 þ Xβ 2 þ e Á x 2 </p>

<p>x 3 ¼ α 3 þ Xβ 3 þ e Á x 3 </p>

<p>x 4 ¼ α 4 þ Xβ 4 þ e Á x 4 </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>Here, x i are observed variables, Xis a vector of 
observed and/or potentially unobserved (latent) vari-
ables and e j represents error terms. The power of the 
SEM approach is that a wide variety of model types 
can be represented within the same structure, 
depending on the definition of the observed vari-
ables and the structure of the relationships between 
them and the latents. Thus, the model can be pre-
sented as a measurement model, a measurement 
error model or even a regression model. 
SEM has a number of advantages over the more 
conventional regression and/or path analysis 
approaches (see, e.g. Schreiber et al. 2006; Teo 
2010). Some of the more important benefits include 
the fact that SEM can (1) combine multiple observed 
measures of a latent construct (unobserved vari-
ables) and then model the causal relationships 
amongst these constructs rather than amongst single 
observed variables, which are simply proxies for the 
latent constructs; (2) use unique measurement errors 
associated with the measurement of each observed 
variable; (3) provide unequal weightings for the mul-
tiple indicators of a latent construct; (4) allow for 
correlations amongst the measurement errors 
(Loxton 2011; Pearl 2000). </p>

<p>Determining model fit </p>

<p>There is contention within the literature regarding 
determination of model fit, which is one of the most 
important steps in SEM (Barrett 2007; Hooper, 
Coughlan, and Mullen 2008; Mulaik 2007). In recent 
years, fit indices have come under intense scrutiny 
with some authors even suggesting their complete 
abandonment (Barrett 2007). Others have taken a 
more nuanced perspective and recognize the merit 
in reporting a number of fit indices (Crowley and 
Fan 1997; Hooper, Coughlan, and Mullen 2008) 
because different indices reflect a different aspect of 
model fit. 
The Chi-square value is the traditional measure 
for evaluating overall model fit. The null hypothesis 
is that the fitted covariance matrix (based on the 
paths between variables implied by the fitted 
model) and mean vector of the observed variables 
are equal to the matrix and vector of the sample. A 
rejection of the model implies that there are signifi-
cant paths between variables that have not been 
represented in the model. Whilst this test retains </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
its popularity, there are several substantial limita-
tions in its application. First, as the test is essentially 
a statistical significance test, it is sensitive to sample 
size, which means that the model Chi-square statistic 
frequently rejects the model when large or small 
samples are used (Hooper, Coughlan, and Mullen 
2008; Joreskog and Sorbom 1993). Second, the Chi-
Square test assumes multivariate normality and sig-
nificant deviations from normality could result in 
model rejections, even when the model is accurately 
specified (McIntosh 2006). The Bollen-Stine boot-
strap (Bollen and Stine 1992) is one approach that 
can be used to adjust for lack of multivariate nor-
mality. Basically, it is a bootstrap modification of 
model Chi-square and is used to test model fit. 
However, it is also affected by large sample size, 
thus making other fit indices relevant. Given the 
restrictiveness of the model Chi-square, researchers 
have pursued alternate indices to evaluate model fit 
(refer to Appendix for a review of these). </p>

<p>IV. Survey design and data collection </p>

<p>As emphasized earlier, social and psychological cog-
nition models demonstrate that attitudes play an 
important predictive role in the individual's decision 
to comply with regulations (see, for instance, 
d'Astous, Colbert, and Montpetit 2005; Peace, 
Galletta, and Thong 2003; Tonglet 2001). 
Accordingly, in the first part of the survey, respon-
dents were asked to rate their agreement with a 
series of attitude statements on a 5-point Likert 
scale, following the approach of Hayes and 
Darkenwald (1990) and Blunt and Yang (2002). 
Several topics were critical to this part of the 
survey: namely, the extent of PBC, the degree of 
influence from significant others, the individual's 
intention to comply, and general attitudes towards 
compliance with water restrictions (see, e.g. Ajzen 
and Fishbein 1980; d'Astous, Colbert, and Montpetit 
2005; Giles et al. 2004). The survey design process 
involved identification of existing attitude scales that 
stem from TPB, conducting focus groups and survey 
pretesting. Specific psychographic items were thus 
included on the basis of earlier published work and 
the interrogation of data from six focus groups, 
which were conducted in six cities across Victoria 
and New South Wales. </p>

<p>Development of construct measures </p>

<p>Perhaps predictably, the three antecedent constructs 
from TPB featured prominently in respondents' com-
ments during the focus group phase. First, SOCIAL 
NORMS were voiced by one participant as 'I don't 
want to be seen as doing the "wrong" thing by others' 
and another: 'I don't want to be scorned by neigh-
bours'. Second, respondents were generally keen to 
voice their opinion regarding ATTITUDE towards 
complying with water restrictions. For instance, one 
respondent stated that 'Water restrictions are neces-
sary and they have become our "way of life"'. However, 
the attitudes towards compliance were not entirely 
positive with one participant claiming 'Water restric-
tions are "unfair" and "ridiculous"'. Similarly, partici-
pants articulated both positive and negative views in 
the context of PBC. For instance, a negative perspective 
of PBC was voiced by one participant as 'It is impos-
sible for me to comply with water restrictions', 
although not all respondents held this view. 
The final items chosen for this section of the 
survey were a composite of previously employed 
items (i.e. Ajzen 2002; d'Astous, Colbert, and 
Montpetit 2005; Giles et al. 2004; Lam 2006), albeit 
with slightly different terminology to reflect the 
unique setting of this study, and responses emanat-
ing from the focus group discussions. Care was also 
taken to include both positively and negatively 
worded items in the hope of eliciting truthful and 
thoughtful responses. 
The interview process also revealed the influence of 
respondents' lifestyle on their decision to comply with 
water restrictions, such as whether they had a garden, 
swimming pool or owned their own home. These 
types of variables (as well as demographics e.g. age 
and income) are prima facie related to some of the 
constructs, such as PBC. Thus, the final part of the 
survey presented questions that were framed to elicit 
socio-demographic information pertaining to resi-
dential location, age, education, gender, income, 
number of children in the household, whether the 
respondent had a lawn and/or garden, home owner-
ship and ownership of an outdoor swimming pool or 
spa. Another section of the survey contained ques-
tions relating to a stated preference experiment, how-
ever, this is not used or reported here (see Cooper, 
Burton, and Crase 2011; Cooper, Rose, and Crase 
2012; for a review of this part of the survey). </p>

<p> 
B. COOPER </p>

<p>The survey was pretested in both paper-based and 
on-line formats. In the first instance, 52 paper sur-
veys were completed by a random sample of parti-
cipants, who resided in one of the cities selected 
across New South Wales and Victoria. The purpose 
was to trial the specific items and the response for-
mats. Preliminary analyses were conducted on the 
attitude items with a focus on reliability of items. In 
this case, Cronbach's alpha was generated to exam-
ine if likely factors would load to form sub-scales. 
This allowed further refinement of item wording and 
as a result some minor changes were made to the 
instrument itself, mainly to improve clarity. Once 
the survey was modified from the initial pilot 
phase, a second pilot was conducted, where 27 
online surveys were completed. This information 
was used to again refine the survey design resulting 
in the measurement of each construct as follows. 
Attitude towards water restrictions: This concept 
was measured using six items (e.g. 'I think that it is a 
good idea to comply with water restrictions') where 
respondents had to indicate their level of agreement 
using a 5-point Likert scale anchored by totally dis-
agree and totally agree. Some of these items were 
adapted from d'Astous, Colbert and Montpetit 
(2005). 
Subjective norm: The subjective norm measure 
was adapted from Ajzen (2002) and Lam (2006). It 
consisted of five items (e.g. 'Most members of my 
family think I should comply with water restric-
tions') and used a similar Likert scale format to 
that deployed for other constructs. 
PBC: This concept was measured using five items 
(e.g. 'I find it easy to stick to water restrictions') 
adapted from Giles et al. (2004) and d'Astous, 
Colbert and Montpetit (2005). 
Intention to comply with water restrictions: Five 
items were used to measure the behavioural intent 
concept (e.g. 'I intend to follow water restrictions in 
the future'). These items were adapted from Giles 
et al. (2004) and d'Astous, Colbert and Montpetit 
(2005). Respondents were required to specify their 
level of agreement on a 5-point Likert scale. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>In addition to the above items, the survey also 
presented a scale item to act as a proxy for actual </p>

<p>compliance behaviour (i.e. 'How often would you 
say that you comply with water restrictions?'). 
Participants were required to respond to five ordered 
response categories that ranged from 'less than 20% 
of the time' to '90% or more of the time'. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Data collection and sample description </p>

<p>The main survey was distributed online to a sample 
of respondents from six cities across the Australian 
states of Victoria and New South Wales during April 
2008. A total of 512 surveys were completed 
(Wodonga: 54; Albury: 94; Melbourne: 106; Sydney: 
102; Goulburn: 51; Bendigo: 105), which represented 
a response rate of 59%. A Chi-squared (χ 
2 ) test of 
representativeness against the Australian census data 
(Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS) 2006) revealed 
significant differences in the age, highest education 
and income; with the sample being younger, more 
educated and enjoying higher educational attain-
ment, as is common with on-line data collection. 
The gender profile of the sample was not signifi-
cantly different to the general population. </p>

<p>V. SEM results </p>

<p>The software package <rs id="software-1" type="software">AMOS</rs> (Analysis of Moment 
Structures) by <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Arbuckle</rs> (2006) was used to analyse 
the data. Initially, a test of multivariate normality was 
conducted and, as a result, six observations were 
removed. These observations had Mahalanobis dis-
tance values that deviated significantly from the 
other observations 
3 -their removal resulted in a 
sample size of 504. 
The manifest variables were tested to evaluate if the 
correlations amongst measures validated them as 
indicators of the underlying constructs. Initially, 
each construct was developed and analysed separately. 
The squared multiple correlations and the standar-
dized regression weights were used to assess the 
strength of the correlations between the constructs 
and the manifest variables. If the standardized regres-
sion weights exceed 0.3 they are generally considered 
to be adequate measures of the construct (Loxton 
2011). In total, four items were removed from the </p>

<p>1 Refer to Cooper (2010) for a full review of the psychographic scale questions used in this study. 
2 Notably, this aspect of the study is limited by the subjective nature of the data. 
3 These observations were removed as the significantly inconsistent responses to positively and negatively worded questions for each of these individuals 
indicated that the participant was not responding accurately to the questions. </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
models due to their lack of ability to provide a good 
measure of the constructs (one item was removed 
from each of the four latent constructs). The manifest 
variables with the ability to provide a good measure of 
the constructs appear in Table 1. </p>

<p>SEM: model 1 </p>

<p>The constructs that were individually developed 
where then modelled together to empirically esti-
mate the conceptual framework presented in 
Figure 1. Thus, in this case, a confirmatory SEM 
analysis was conducted. A recursive SEM was </p>

<p>estimated and the measurement and structural com-
ponents are illustrated in the path diagram in 
Figure 2. Each of the observed variables in the 
model is illustrated using rectangles, and circles are 
used to reflect the unique measurement errors. The 
latent constructs are illustrated using oval shapes 
and the direct relationship between variables is por-
trayed using one-headed arrows (e.g. the latent vari-
able ATTIUDES is determining the responses given 
to the observed manifest variables attq#). The theo-
retical relationship posited by the TPB between 
latents is represented by the three latents titled 
ATTITUDES, SOCIAL NORMS and PBC which in 
turn are determining the latent variable 
INTENTION to comply. A two-headed arrow is 
used to demonstrate covariance between variables. 
The values that appear on the arrows in Figure 2 
are the standardized coefficients for the relationship 
between the variables (e.g. 0.77 between 
ATTITUDES and attq1). In the standardized 
model, identification is achieved by imposing a con-
dition that all variances are equal to 1. The figures 
adjacent to the rectangle box (e.g. 0.59 for attq1) 
represent the squared multiple correlations. For 
example, it is estimated that the predictors of attq1 
explain 59% of its variance. Put differently, the error 
variance of attq1 is approximately 41% of the var-
iance of attq1 itself. </p>

<p>Table 1. Standardized regression weights (SRW). </p>

<p>Latent construct 
Manifest variable 
SRW </p>

<p>ATTITUDES 
attq1 
0.719 
attq55 
0.786 
attq35 
0.708 
attq23 
0.590 
attq45 
0.820 
SOCIAL NORMS 
snfamc 
0.769 
sngovc 
0.524 
sneec 
0.689 
sncit 
0.613 
PBC 
pbcq9 
0.604 
pbcq25 
0.593 
pbcq36 
0.617 
pbcq47 
0.696 
INTENTION 
intq22 
0.684 
intq11 
0.781 
intq44 
0.852 
intq57 
0.922 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Model 1: Recursive structural equation model, Standardised coefficients. 
This figure illustrates the recursive structural equation model with standardised coefficients, which is used to empirically estimate 
the conceptual framework in Figure 1. </p>

<p> 
B. COOPER </p>

<p>To ensure stable results, a criterion of five subjects 
per parameter is optimal (Cunningham 2008). The 
model comprises 41 parameter estimates, which pro-
vides a parameter ratio of 12.3:1, such that the 
observation to parameter ratio is easily met. 
Assessment of normality on the distribution of the 
data revealed Mardia's coefficient to have a value of 
185.97 (z-value = 77.79), which suggests a relatively 
significant departure from multivariate normality. 
Accordingly, the Bollen-Stine bootstrap p became 
the statistical test for the model, in preference to 
model Chi-square. Estimation revealed the Bollen-
Stine bootstrap p-value to be significant (p = 0.005). 
This suggests there is a significant difference 
between the sample data variance/covariance matrix 
and the model implied variance/covariance matrix. 
This could be a result of the large sample size used in 
this study (see Section III) 
4 and analysis of the 
Standardized Residual Covariance Matrix appears 
to be warranted (Joreskog and Sorbom 1993). In 
this case, if the estimated model is a 'good fit', 
most of the residual covariances should be less 
than two in absolute value. Approximately 97% of 
the residual covariances are less than two in absolute 
value, thus this does not indicate serious misfit 
between the model and the data. (Refer to Table 2 
for reporting of the Standardized Residual 
Covariance Matrix.) 
This result was further confirmed by evaluating a 
number of fit statistics. More specifically, the root 
mean square error of approximation, comparative fit 
index, parsimony fit indices, goodness-of-fit statistic 
and adjusted goodness-of-fit statistic values of model 
fit all met the required thresholds. Moreover, the 
normed Chi-square ratio also falls within the accep-
table range. Table 3 presents model fit indices. 
Examination of the regression coefficients for the 
structural paths revealed numerous positive and sig-
nificant relationships at the 5% level. Table 4 presents 
the unstandardized and standardized regression coef-
ficients for the structural paths. 
A reference variable has been assigned to each 
latent construct when estimating the un-standardized 
parameters that appear in Table 4 (i.e. the parameter 
is constrained to equal 1). This simply ensures that 
the latent variable will be measured on the same scale </p>

<p>Table 2. Standardized residual covariances (Group number 1 </p>

<p>-default model). </p>

<p>attq45 </p>

<p>sncitc </p>

<p>sneec 
snfamc sngovc compq14 </p>

<p>pbcq9 
pbcq54 pbcq36 pbcq47 </p>

<p>intq22 </p>

<p>intq11 </p>

<p>intq44 </p>

<p>intq57 </p>

<p>attq35 
attq23 attq55 attq1 </p>

<p>attq45 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>sncitc </p>

<p>−0.586 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>sneec </p>

<p>0.165 </p>

<p>−1.205 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>snfamc </p>

<p>−0.791 </p>

<p>1.115 </p>

<p>−0.318 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>sngovc 
−0.352 −0.096 </p>

<p>1.043 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>compq14 
−1.165 −0.012 −0.935 −0.636 −0.485 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>pbcq9 </p>

<p>0.287 </p>

<p>0.625 </p>

<p>0.761 </p>

<p>0.093 </p>

<p>−0.617 </p>

<p>−1.708 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>pbcq54 </p>

<p>−0.047 </p>

<p>1.562 </p>

<p>2.255 </p>

<p>2.152 </p>

<p>1.457 </p>

<p>−1.356 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>pbcq36 </p>

<p>0.978 </p>

<p>−0.706 </p>

<p>0.417 </p>

<p>−1.424 </p>

<p>0.143 </p>

<p>1.720 </p>

<p>0.682 </p>

<p>−0.330 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>pbcq47 </p>

<p>1.245 
−0.876 −1.070 −1.612 −0.651 </p>

<p>1.079 </p>

<p>−0.553 </p>

<p>−1.948 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>intq22 </p>

<p>−0.937 </p>

<p>0.724 </p>

<p>0.091 
−0.529 −0.885 </p>

<p>0.305 </p>

<p>0.162 </p>

<p>−0.070 </p>

<p>0.099 </p>

<p>−0.769 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>intq11 </p>

<p>−1.281 </p>

<p>1.219 
−0.121 −0.769 −1.397 </p>

<p>0.485 </p>

<p>0.833 </p>

<p>0.817 </p>

<p>−0.487 </p>

<p>−0.533 </p>

<p>0.287 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>intq44 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>1.156 </p>

<p>0.645 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>−0.087 </p>

<p>−0.791 </p>

<p>−0.947 </p>

<p>−1.022 </p>

<p>−0.709 </p>

<p>1.325 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>−0.566 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>intq57 </p>

<p>0.166 </p>

<p>0.123 </p>

<p>−0.106 </p>

<p>0.315 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.388 </p>

<p>−0.087 </p>

<p>0.713 </p>

<p>0.767 </p>

<p>1.191 
−0.287 −0.284 </p>

<p>0.227 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>attq35 </p>

<p>−0.283 </p>

<p>1.289 </p>

<p>2.166 </p>

<p>0.779 </p>

<p>1.654 </p>

<p>0.778 </p>

<p>−0.328 </p>

<p>0.271 </p>

<p>−1.035 </p>

<p>−1.412 </p>

<p>0.641 </p>

<p>0.306 </p>

<p>1.802 </p>

<p>1.344 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>attq23 </p>

<p>1.716 </p>

<p>−1.949 </p>

<p>0.392 
−2.814 −1.683 </p>

<p>−0.807 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>−0.763 </p>

<p>2.729 </p>

<p>1.658 
−1.499 −1.274 −1.576 −0.035 −0.317 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>attq55 </p>

<p>1.377 
−0.222 −0.076 −0.441 −0.310 </p>

<p>−0.465 </p>

<p>−0.388 </p>

<p>−0.160 </p>

<p>0.266 </p>

<p>0.949 
−0.629 −0.116 −0.182 −0.046 −0.359 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>attq1 </p>

<p>−0.691 </p>

<p>1.231 
−1.109 −0.732 −1.938 </p>

<p>0.086 </p>

<p>0.169 </p>

<p>−0.953 </p>

<p>−0.879 </p>

<p>−1.144 </p>

<p>0.550 </p>

<p>1.559 </p>

<p>0.322 </p>

<p>0.312 </p>

<p>−0.467 </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>4 Notably, when half of the sample was randomly selected and then estimated (when n = 210) the Bollen-Stine bootstrap p-value became insignificant. This 
supports the notion of large sample sizes impacting on this fit statistic. </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
as this reference variable. The results presented in 
Table 4 reveal that all of the z-statistics for the un-
standardized coefficients are greater than 1.96, thus all 
of the estimates (factor loadings) are significantly 
different from zero. These results offer strong support 
for the hypotheses derived from TPB. More specifi-
cally, this finding suggests that the three antecedent 
constructs (ATTITUDES, SOCIAL NORMS and 
PBC) had a positive and statistically significant impact 
on the intention to comply with water restrictions. 
Moreover, the endogenous construct (INTENTION) 
had a positive and significant impact on actual com-
pliance with water restrictions, at least as specified in 
this survey. 
The standardized coefficients presented in Table 4 
suggest that in predicting INTENTION, PBC (0.389) 
is the strongest predictor of the three constructs. 
This estimate suggests that PBC has a relatively 
strong effect on INTENTION to comply with water 
restrictions. The standardized coefficient for the </p>

<p>ATTITUDES/INTENTION (0.313) constructs implies 
that ATTITUDES is the second strongest predictor of 
INTENTION to comply. The SOCIAL NORMS con-
struct is the lowest of the three constructs in terms of 
effecting INTENTIONS, where the standardized coef-
ficient is (0.248). The results also show that the effect 
that INTENTION has on actual COMPLIANCE is 
very strong as the standardized coefficient for this 
effect exceeds 0.5 (0.507). 
The R-squared value for the INTENTION con-
struct is 0.847. This suggests that approximately 84% 
of the variation in INTENTION is explained by the 
three exogenous variables in the structural model 
(ATTITUDES, SOCIAL NORMS and PBC). 
The covariances between three of the latent con-
structs and eight of the measurement errors were 
found to be significant, as shown in Table 5. The 
estimated correlations that appear in the overall 
model are also presented in Table 5. 
The empirical correlation between the three ante-
cedents to INTENTION to comply offers strong sup-
port for the final hypothesis -i.e. that the three 
antecedents are interrelated. These correlations could 
be interpreted as a limitation of the model, insomuch 
as this could mean there is a common preceding vari-
able to ATTITUDES, SOCIAL NORMS and PBC. In 
this context, Ajzen (1991) suggests that an individual's 
beliefs about the behaviour are the underlying founda-
tion of attitudes, subjective norms, and PBC. However, 
he also notes that the exact form of these relationships 
is uncertain. Of particular concern are studies display-
ing only modest correlations between belief-based 
measures of the TPB constructs relative to other, 
more global measure of these constructs (Ajzen 
1991). Moreover, Fulton, Manfredo and Lipscomb 
(1996)'s cognitive hierarchy model of human beha-
viour, which depicts the hierarchical relationship 
between cognitive variables, implies that beliefs fall </p>

<p>Table 3. Model 1: Fit indices. </p>

<p>Fit indices (suggested acceptable range) 
Value </p>

<p>RMSEA ð&gt;0:7Þ 
0.06 (90% CI: 0.055-0.069) 
CFI ( ! 0:95Þ 
0.95 
PNFI ð&gt;0:5Þ 
0.76 
GFI ! 0:9 
ð 
Þ 
0.92 
AGFI ! 0:9 
ð 
Þ 
0.90 
Normed Chi-square (&lt;5, or possibly &lt;2) 
2.93 </p>

<p>RMSEA: Root mean square error of approximation; CFI: comparative fit 
index; PNFI: parsimony fit indices; GFI: goodness-of-fit statistic; 
AGFI: adjusted goodness-of-fit statistic. </p>

<p>Table 4. Model 1: structural un-standardized B 
ð Þ and standar-
dized regression β 
ð Þ coefficients. </p>

<p>Manifest variable Latent construct 
ðBÞ 
S.E. z-Statistic 
β 
ð Þ </p>

<p>Intention 
Attitudes 
0.365 
b 0.173 
2.116 
0.313 
Intention 
PBC 
0.487 
b 0.166 
2.932 
0.389 
Intention 
Social_Norms 
0.139 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.033 
4.153 
0.248 
attq1 
Attitudes 
1.000 
0.766 
attq55 
Attitudes 
1.378 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.079 
17.427 
0.739 
attq35 
Attitudes 
1.203 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.067 
17.822 
0.753 
attq23 
Attitudes 
1.199 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.099 
12.157 
0.538 
attq45 
Attitudes 
1.388 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.074 
18.780 
0.787 
sncitc 
Social_Norms 
1.000 
0.670 
sngovc 
Social_Norms 
1.001 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.081 
12.353 
0.684 
snfamc 
Social_Norms 
0.753 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.085 
8.905 
0.473 
sneec 
Social_Norms 
1.047 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.081 
12.897 
0.720 
pbcq47 
PBC 
1.000 
0.501 
pbcq54 
PBC 
1.006 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.176 
5.732 
0.264 
pbcq9 
PBC 
1.468 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.127 
11.597 
0.708 
pbcq36 
PBC 
1.117 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.096 
11.591 
0.509 
intq57 
Intention 
1.000 
0.700 
intq44 
Intention 
0.927 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.055 
16.876 
0.795 
intq11 
Intention 
0.988 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.055 
18.101 
0.856 
intq22 
Intention 
1.025 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.054 
19.015 
0.904 
compq14 
Intention 
0.644 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.059 
10.905 
0.507 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at the 1% level. 
b Significant of the 5% level. </p>

<p>Table 5. Model 1: Covariances ε 
ð Þ and correlations E 
ð Þ. </p>

<p>Variables 
ε 
ð Þ 
S.E. 
z-Statistic 
E 
ð Þ </p>

<p>Attitudes &lt;-&gt; PBC 
0.262 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.027 
9.706 
1.109 
Attitudes &lt;-&gt; Social_Norms 0.392 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.042 
9.413 
0.740 
PBC 
&lt;-&gt; Social_Norms 0.391 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.049 
7.954 
0.792 
e17 
&lt;-&gt; e16 
0.209 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.056 
3.763 
0.177 
e19 
&lt;-&gt; e18 
0.227 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.037 
6.225 
0.317 
e3 
&lt;-&gt; e5 
0.078 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.029 
2.687 
0.130 
e12 
&lt;-&gt; e11 
0.172 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.090 
1.914 
0.103 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at the 1% level. 
b Significant at the 5% level. 
c Significant at the 10% level. </p>

<p> 
B. COOPER </p>

<p>into a higher hierarchical level than attitudes and 
norms. This model also suggests that beliefs are slower 
and harder to change, compared to attitudes and 
norms (Fulton, Manfredo, and Lipscomb 1996). 
Thus, from a practical perspective, understanding 
and appealing to one's attitudes, social norms, and 
PBC is potentially going to be more appealing from a 
policy perspective, especially if change is needed 
sooner rather than later. 
The correlations between four pairs of measure-
ment errors are consistent with each of the correla-
tions lying within a particular latent construct. For 
instance, measurement errors e19 and e18 for two of 
the manifest items for PBC are correlated and this 
empirical correlation becomes cogent conceptually 
when we compare the scales for these two manifest 
items: (1) 'My lifestyle does not allow me to stick 
with the water restrictions times' and (2) 'It is 
impossible for me to comply with water restrictions'. </p>

<p>VI. Discussion and concluding remarks </p>

<p>The restriction policy surrounding urban water during 
scarcity does not consider individual preferences or 
behaviour and there has been only limited research 
into the drivers of compliance with water restrictions 
(see Cooper, Rose, and Crase 2012). Against that back-
ground, there is much to be gained from the insight 
from these empirical data. Generally, these data offer 
evidence that the TPB is a useful framework for exam-
ining compliance intentions in the context of water 
restrictions. Notwithstanding the subjective nature of 
some of these data, key findings suggest that the deci-
sion to comply with water restrictions is founded on 
attitude towards water restrictions, a perception that 
important others value compliance, and the perceived 
capabilities to actually undertake compliance beha-
viour. More specifically, attitudes, social norms and 
PBC have a positive and significant influence on inten-
tions to comply and intentions to comply has a positive 
and significant influence on the compliance behaviour 
associated with water restrictions. 
In this case, PBC has the strongest effect on inten-
tions to comply. Thus, the greater an individual's 
perception of his or her own capacities to success-
fully comply with water restrictions, the more likely 
they are to form intentions to comply. Accordingly, 
if individuals feel that they do not have the resources 
or capacity to conform to the required watering </p>

<p>times or activities, they may make little effort to 
comply with water restrictions. 
From a policy perspective, this highlights the 
importance of giving at least some consideration to 
individuals' perceptions and preferences when devel-
oping demand management responses. Moreover, 
stringent enforcement of water restrictions when 
PBC is low is likely to generate additional enforce-
ment costs for only small gains in compliance. 
Failure to consider the resources available to facil-
itate compliance could also raise equity concerns and 
thus have a significant impact on the social welfare 
of groups with least capacity to respond. Water 
restrictions, as presently conceived, result in high-
income earners being better positioned than lower 
income households to increase their PBC. For exam-
ple, high-income households are likely to have the 
resources to put in place technical devices to assist 
with compliance (e.g. installing timing devices to 
switch garden sprinklers on and off at the requisite 
times). In contrast, poorer households may be forced 
to give up hours of work (or sleep) to undertake 
outdoor irrigation. Thus, one approach to increasing 
compliance could involve increasing the PBC of 
poorer households, say by offering subsidies for tim-
ing devices. Clearly, this is an empirical issue against 
which the relative costs and benefits should be com-
pared, but the data provided by this study provide a 
vehicle for undertaking such an analysis. 
In addition, consideration could be given to chan-
ging the way water restrictions are administered. 
Restricting outdoor water use by quota rather than 
by time and activity would be one possible solution, 
since this diminishes the specific resource require-
ments of households to deal with restrictions based 
on time/activity. Fortunately, this is evident is some 
parts of the Californian approach to drought restric-
tions, where quota of use is the focus rather than 
prescribing the time of watering or irrigation activity. 
Respondents' attitude towards water restrictions 
was the second strongest predictor of intentions. 
This provides evidence that persuasive message cam-
paigns that feature the benefits of water restrictions 
are likely to influence an individual's attitude and 
hence have an impact on their intentions to comply. 
Water-saving campaigns such as 'save every drop' 
have been highly successful in creating a positive 
attitude towards complying with water restrictions. 
However, promoting the universality of water </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
'saving' remains problematic (see e.g. Crase and 
O'Keefe 2009) and the gains in compliance versus 
the costs of such campaigns is an empirical question, 
and one which should be considered against the 
cost-effectiveness of alternatives. 
Although social norms appeared as the weakest pre-
dictive construct of intention to comply, its impact was 
nonetheless positive and significant. This implies that 
the social pressures acting on the individual in this 
context effect intentions to comply, but not to the 
same extent as PBC and attitudes. As noted earlier, 
there have also been numerous media reports detailing 
instances where individuals took enforcement into their 
own hands (see Wells 2007; Worrall 2008). However, the 
extent to which this can cost-effectively act as a substitute 
for formal enforcement (i.e. water patrol inspectors) and 
the wider social consequences of vigilantism is unclear. 
Nevertheless, it does highlight that the drivers of com-
pliance go far beyond the calculative motivations asso-
ciated with fines and that doing the 'right thing' by 
important others is one of the significant drivers. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Thanks are owed to Dr Michael Burton for helpful com-
ments on SEM and Professor Lin Crase for insights into 
water policy. This article presents analysis of households' 
intentions to comply with government constraints on the 
use of urban water, or so-called water restrictions. The data 
are drawn from Australian cities and was collected during a 
severe drought. SEM is employed to operationalize con-
structs taken from the TPB and to answer important policy 
questions related to compliance. The modelled data support 
the view that attitudes, social norms and PBC have a positive 
and significant influence on intentions to comply. Perceived 
behavioural control has the strongest influence on intentions, 
suggesting policy directed at assisting households to meet 
regulatory criteria might be at least as effective as advertising 
expenditures aimed at shaping attitudes and norms. 
Importantly, intentions to comply are also shown to have a 
positive and significant influence on reported compliance 
behaviour. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author. </p>



<p>1436 
B. COOPER </p>



<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>



<p>
 
B. COOPER </p>



<p>Appendix </p>

<p>An alternate fit statistic to model Chi-square that minimizes 
the impact of sample size is the relative/normed Chi-square 
χ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>
df 
À 
Á 
developed by Wheaton et al. (1977). An acceptable 
ratio of this statistic ranges from less than 5.0 (Wheaton et al. 
1977) to less than 2.0 (Tabachnick and Fidell 2007). Based on 
the guidelines presented by Hooper, Coughlan and Mullen 
(2008), Kline (2005) and Boomsma (2000), additional fit 
indices that are informative and appropriate to report 
include the following: (1) the root mean square error of 
approximation, where a value less than 0.07 (Steiger, 2007) 
indicates a good fit; (2) the standardized root mean square </p>

<p>residual, where a value less than 0.05 is considered a well-
fitting model (Diamantopoulos and Siguaw 2000) or the 
comparative fit index, where a value greater than or equal 
to 0.95 is presently recognized as indicative of good fit 
(Hooper, Coughlan, and Mullen 2008); (3) the parsimony 
fit indices, where it is possible to obtain parsimony fit with a 
value greater than 0.5; and (4) the goodness-of-fit statistic 
and the adjusted goodness-of-fit statistic, where values of 0.9 
or greater indicate well-fitting models. In addition, reporting 
of the Akaike or Bayesian Information Criterion when com-
paring models has also been recognized as good practice 
(Barrett 2007). </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>