<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F13504851.2016.1167817" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The study investigates the impact of adopting mechanized processing of cassava on farm-
ers' production efficiency in Uganda. A stochastic production function, using translog 
functional form, was used to compare efficiency measures of farmers in mechanized 
cassava-processing villages compared with the farmers in nonmechanized cassava-proces-
sing villages in 2014. Given the specification of the translog production function, the mean 
technical efficiencies of the farmers were 0.69 and 0.52 in mechanized and nonmechanized 
villages, respectively. The significant determinants of technical inefficiency among the 
respondents are farming experience, education, membership of farmer association, access 
to markets, sale of cassava to processors and farmers who planted cassava as sole crop are 
all negative, which confirm to a priori expectations and significant at different levels. The 
policy implication of the study is that mechanization of cassava processing, particularly if 
done at the right scale, could create demand that can transform primary production for 
increased yields, higher incomes and production efficiency of smallholder farmers who 
constitute a significant proportion of Uganda's agricultural sector. </p>

<p>Cassava is an important rural food for commu-
nities in Uganda. It has tolerance to poor soils 
and resistance to drought, a cheap and reliable 
source of food that fits well into the food security 
strategy of smallholders (Nweke, Spencer, and  Lynam 2004; FAO 2003). Cassava has, therefore, 
served many times as food of last resort to ame-
liorate the effect of food deficits which occur 
from erratic weather conditions and reduce the 
yields of cereals. 
The main response to the shortage of food 
production in developing countries has been to 
invest in increased food production. Many years 
of investment in crop production technologies 
have generated a great number of innovative tech-
nologies for crop production and protection. 
However, the food crisis in Africa has persisted 
(Rusike et al. 2010). 
In the last decade, the International Institute of 
Tropical Agriculture and national research </p>

<p>institutions introduced and promoted an exten-
sive range of processing technologies that allows 
farmers to harvest and process cassava into shelf-
stable value-added products. The adoption of 
these simple, mechanized postharvest processing 
steps (such as grating, chipping and pressing) and 
technologies such as the production of high-qual-
ity cassava flour and cassava chips were expected 
to increase the demand for fresh cassava in the 
rural areas. In addition, they could enhance farm-
ers' willingness to adopt improved production 
technologies, particularly new varieties, fertilizer 
and improved farming practices, which can 
increase cassava productivity and expand 
production. 
After 10 years of intervention in the region's 
cassava subsector, this study was conducted to 
examine the impact of adoption of mechanized 
postharvest cassava-processing technologies as it 
affects smallholder farmers' efficiency in cassava 
production in Uganda. </p>

<p>CONTACT Paul Amaza 
amazap@unijos.edu.ng </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS LETTERS, 2017 
VOL. 24, NO. 2, 102-106 
http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/13504851.2016.1167817 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), 
which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. </p>

<p>II. Study area and sample selection </p>

<p>The survey was carried out in 10 villages each 
where mechanical methods of cassava processing 
were introduced or used (mechanized-processing 
villages) and communities where mechanical 
methods of cassava processing were not used 
(nonmechanized-processing villages). The study 
villages were purposively selected based on 
whether or not mechanized processing of cassava 
was introduced. The nonmechanized villages 
served as counterfactuals. Records from the 
National Agricultural Research Organization of 
Uganda suggest that all the survey villages had 
received planting materials of high-yielding dis-
ease-resistant cassava varieties at various periods 
during the 1980s-2000s (MAAIF 2011). 
A multistage sampling technique was used to 
select respondents for the study. For the villages 
where mechanical processing methods were intro-
duced, 412 processors and 420 cassava farmers 
were randomly selected from both the mechan-
ized-and nonmechanized-processing villages. </p>

<p>III. The stochastic frontier model for Uganda 
cassava farmers </p>

<p>The stochastic production frontier model by 
Parikh and Shah (1994), which in turn derives 
from the composed error model of Aigner,  Lovell, and Schmidt (1977), Meeusen and van  den Broeck (1977) and Forsund, Knox Lovell,  and Peter (1980), was used to examine the impact 
of cassava-processing technologies on farmers' effi-
ciency in cassava production, following similar 
efficiency studies by Fakayode et al. (2008), 
Ogundari, Amos, and Okoruwa (2012) and Girei  et al. 2014). This was done by comparing the 
efficiency measures of farmers that are located in 
mechanized-processing villages with farmers in 
nonmechanized villages. 
The empirical stochastic frontier production 
model with translog functional form is specified as 
follows: </p>

<p>ln Y t ¼ β 0 þ </p>

<p>X 
β k ln X ki </p>

<p>þ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>X X 
β kj ln X ki ln X ji </p>

<p>þ v i À μ i 
À 
Á 
(1) </p>

<p>ln Y ij β 0 þ β 1 lnðX 1ij Þ þ β 2 lnðX 2ij Þ þ β 3 lnðX 3ij Þ </p>

<p>þ β 4 lnðX 4ij Þ þ β 5 lnðX 5ij Þ þ β 6 lnðX 6ij Þ </p>

<p>þ β 7 lnðX 1ij Þ 
2 þ β 8 lnðX 2ij Þ 
2 þ β 9 lnðX 3ij Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>þ β 10 lnðX 4ij Þ 
2 þ β 11 lnðX 5ij Þ 
2 þ β 12 lnðX 6ij Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>þ β 13 lnðX 1ij Þ lnðX 2ij Þ 
þ β 14 ðX 1ij Þ lnðX 3ij Þβ 15 ðX 1ij Þ lnðX 4ij Þ 
þ β 17 lnðX 1ij lnðX 5ij Þ þ β 18 lnðX 1ij ÞðX 6ij Þ 
þ β 19 lnðX 2ij Þ lnðX 3ij Þ 
þ β 20 ðX 2ij Þ lnðX 4ij Þβ 21 ðX 2ij Þ lnðX 5ij Þ 
þ β 22 lnðX 2ij ÞlnðX 6ij Þβ 23 lnðX 3ij Þ lnðX 4ij Þ 
þ β 24 ðX 3ij Þ lnðX 5ij Þβ 25 ðX 3ij Þ lnðX 6ij Þ 
þ β 26 lnðX 4ij ÞlnðX 5ij Þβ 27 lnðX 4ij Þ lnðX 6ij Þ 
þ β 28 ðX 5ij Þ lnðX 6ij Þ </p>

<p>where ln represents logarithm to base e; subscripts ij 
refer to the jth observation of the ith farmer; Y is the 
gross margin from cassava production (valued in 
Uganda shillings) for the ith farmer; X 1 represents 
farm size (in hectares); X 2 represents cassava cut-
tings (in kilogram); X 3 represents fertilizer used (in 
kilogram); X 4 represents family labour used (in man 
days); X 5 represents hired labour used (valued in 
Uganda shillings); X 6 represents tractor services 
(valued in Uganda shillings). 
It is assumed that the technical inefficiency effects 
are independently distributed and υ ij arises by trun-
cation at zero at normal distribution with mean υ ij 
and variances σ 
2 where υ ij is defined by Equation (2): </p>

<p>uij ¼ d 0þ d 1 ln Z 1ij þ d 2 ln Z 2ij þ d 3 ln Z 3ij 
þ d 4 ln Z 4ij þ d 5 ln Z 5ij þ d 6 ln Z 6ij 
þ d 7 ln Z 7ij þ d 8 ln Z 8ij þ d 9 ln Z 9ij 
þ d 10 ln Z 10ij 
(2) </p>

<p>where υ ij represents the technical efficiency of the 
ith farmer; Z 1 denotes years of farming experience of 
the ith farmers; Z 2 denotes years of formal educa-
tion; Z 3 is a dummy variable scored 1 if farmer 
belongs to farmers' association and zero otherwise; 
Z 4 is a dummy variable scored 1 if farmer uses 
improved cassava cutting and zero otherwise; Z 5 is 
a dummy variable scored 1 if farmer has access to 
markets and zero otherwise; Z 6 is a dummy variable 
scored 1 if farmer uses mechanized cassava-proces-
sing technology and zero otherwise; Z 7 is dummy 
variable score 1 if farmer has access to credit and 
zero otherwise, Z 8 is a dummy variable scored 1 if 
farmer has off-farm income and zero otherwise; Z 9 is </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS LETTERS </p>

<p>
a dummy variable scored 1 if farmer sells cassava to 
processors and zero otherwise and Z 10 is a dummy 
variable scored 1 if farmer plants cassava as a sole 
crop and zero otherwise. The maximum likelihood of 
the estimates of β and δ coefficients in Equations (1) 
and (2), respectively, are estimated simultaneously 
using the computer program <rs id="software-2" type="software">FRONTIER</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">4.1c</rs> in 
which the variance parameters are expressed in 
terms of σ 
2 ¼ σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>υ </p>

<p>þ σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ν and λ ¼ σ u =σ v (Coelli 1996). </p>

<p>IV. Empirical results and discussions </p>

<p>Adoption rates of mechanized-processing 
technologies </p>

<p>The proportion of processors that adopted the respec-
tive postharvest cassava-processing technologies in 
mechanized and nonmechanized villages is presented 
in Figure 1. Most of the adopters of the different proces-
sing technologies are located in the mechanized-proces-
sing (or intervention) villages. The technology that was 
adopted most was the mechanical milling with 68% and 
49% mean adoption rates in mechanized-and nonme-
chanized-processing villages, respectively. Others are 
sun drying of cassava on raised platform with 68% 
and 3% mean adoption rates in mechanized-and non-
mechanized-processing villages, respectively; mechani-
cal graters and pressers were each adopted by 56% of the 
processors in mechanized-processing villages; cassava 
starch technology, waste management technique and 
mechanical dryer were 27%, 12% and 8%, respectively, 
in the mechanized-processing villages. </p>

<p>Determinants of farmers' production efficiency </p>

<p>Given the specification of the translog production 
function, the mean technical efficiencies of the farm-
ers were 0.69 and 0.52 for farmers in mechanized 
and nonmechanized villages, respectively. The tran-
log maximum likelihood estimation (MLE) estimates 
and inefficiency effects results are presented in 
Table 1. 
Given the specification of the translog model, the 
estimate of the sigma-squared (σ 
2 ) is statistically 
significant at 1%, thus indicating a good fit and 
correctness of the specified assumptions of the com-
posite error term. The variance output (γ) is esti-
mated to be 0.88, suggesting that more than 80% of 
the variation in output among farms is due to differ-
ences in technical efficiency. 
The generalized likelihood ratio is significant at 
0.01 level, suggesting the presence of the one-sided 
error component. This means technical efficiency is 
significant and a classical regression model of pro-
duction function based on ordinary least square 
estimation technique would be an inadequate repre-
sentation of the data. Thus, the results of the diag-
nostic statistics confirm the relevance of stochastic 
frontier production function using maximum like-
lihood estimator. 
The estimated coefficient for farm size is positive, 
which conform to a priori expectation, and significant 
at 1%. The magnitude of the coefficient of land, which 
is 1.18, indicates that margin in cassava production is 
elastic to changes in the level of cultivated land area. </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
6 0 
7 0 </p>

<p>MECHANICAL DRYER </p>

<p>WASTE MANAGEMENT </p>

<p>CASSAVA STARACH TECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>PRESSER MACHINE </p>

<p>GRATER MACHINE </p>

<p>SUN-DRYING (RAISED PLATFORM) </p>

<p>MILLING MACHINE </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>56 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>68 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>% of Adopters of post-harvest cassava processing technologies 
Type of cassava processing technologies </p>

<p>Non-mechanized processing villages 
Mechanized processing vilages </p>

<p>Figure 1. Adoption of cassava-processing technologies in mechanized-and nonmechanized-processing villages of Uganda. </p>

<p> 
A. ABASS ET AL. </p>

<p>This suggests that land is a significant factor asso-
ciated with changes in cassava output. 
The production elasticity with respect to fertilizer 
is positive as expected and statistically significant at 
10% level. The magnitude of the coefficient of ferti-
lizer, which is 0.56, indicates that farm gross margin 
in cassava production is inelastic to changes in the 
level of chemical fertilizer used. Thus, 1% increase in 
inorganic fertilizer use would induce an increase of 
0.56% in the farm gross margin and vice versa. The 
significance of the fertilizer variable derives from the 
fact that fertilizer is a major land-augmenting input 
in the sense that it improves the productivity of 
existing land by increasing crop yields per hectare. </p>

<p>The production elasticity with respect to hired 
labour and tractor services is negative and statisti-
cally significant at the 5% and 1% levels, respectively. 
This suggests that a 1% increase in hired labour and 
use of tractor services each would, respectively, cause 
a decrease of 0.56% and 0.29%in the cassava gross 
margin and vice versa. This negative sign, though 
unexpected, is plausible given the fact that the farm-
ers cultivated small land area, mostly less than 2 ha, 
which makes it economically unviable to engage the 
services of hired labour and tractor services. 
The sources of inefficiency are examined by using 
the estimated δ-coefficients associated with the vari-
ables in Equation (2). The estimated coefficients of 
farming experience, education, membership of 
farmer association, access to markets, sale of cassava 
to processors and farmers who planted cassava as 
sole crop are all negative, which confirm to a priori 
expectations and significant at different levels. This 
implies that farming experience, education, member-
ship of farmer association, access to markets, sale of 
cassava to processors and planting cassava as sole 
crop are significant determinants of technical ineffi-
ciency among the respondents. The negative coeffi-
cients of these variables imply that an increase in any 
of or all of these variables would lead to decline in 
the level of technical inefficiency, suggesting that 
these variables have positive influences on technical 
efficiency in cassava production among the respon-
dents. In other words, cassava farmers with better 
education and farming experience belong to farmers' 
association and who relatively had access to markets, 
sold cassava to processors and who planted cassava 
as sole crop achieved higher levels of technical effi-
ciency in cassava production in Uganda. </p>

<p>V. Conclusion </p>

<p>The mechanized cassava-processing activities moti-
vated efficient management of resource utilization in 
cassava production among farmers in the intervention 
villages by facilitating improvement in their produc-
tion efficiency through greater access to markets and 
sales of cassava roots to mechanized processors. This 
has enhanced the efficiency of resource utilization in 
cassava production among the farmers. Consequently, 
many of the cassava farmers in the mechanized-</p>

<p>Table 1. Translog MLE estimates and inefficiency effect. </p>

<p>Variables 
Coefficient 
SD 
t-Ratio </p>

<p>Production factors 
Constant 
12.460 
0.906 
13.74*** 
Farm size 
1.179 
0.446 
2.64*** 
Cassava cuttings 
0.112 
0.164 
0.68 
Fertilizer 
0.565 
0.352 
1.57* 
Family labour 
0.134 
0.278 
0.48 
Hired labour 
−0.561 
0.279 
−2.01** 
Tractor services 
−0.288 
0.094 
−3.08*** 
Farm size </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.003 
0.067 
0.56 
Cassava cuttings </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.019 
0.010 
1.80** 
Fertilizer </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>−0.006 
0.020 
−0.32 
Family labour </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.014 
0.051 
0.26 
Hired labour </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.089 
0.031 
2.85*** 
Tractor services </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.006 
0.084 
0.77 
Farm size × cuttings 
−0.054 
0.052 
−1.05 
Farm size × fertilizer 
0.051 
0.046 
1.10 
Farm size × family labour 
−0.027 
0.069 
−0.38 
Farm size × hired labour 
−0.017 
0.062 
−0.28 
Farm size × tractor services 
−0.002 
0.044 
−3.83*** 
Cuttings × fertilizer 
−0.049 
0.052 
−1.93** 
Cuttings × family labour 
−0.026 
0.028 
−0.94 
Cuttings × hired labour 
0.026 
0.028 
0.94 
Cuttings × tractor services 
0.017 
0.015 
1.15 
Fertilizer × family labour 
0.038 
0.028 
1.74* 
Fertilizer × hired labour 
−0.042 
0.024 
−1.70* 
Fertilizer × tractor services 
−0.006 
0.010 
−0.66 
Family labour × hired labour 
0.041 
0.029 
1.40 
Family labour × tractor services 
0.019 
0.025 
0.84 
Hired labour × tractor services 
0.024 
0.018 
1.29 
Inefficiency effects 
Constant 
1.634 
0.846 
1.93** 
Farming experience 
−2.531 
0.841 
−3.01*** 
Education 
−0.033 
0.018 
−1.91** 
Farmers' association 
−0.096 
0.060 
−1.60* 
Used improved cuttings 
0.828 
0.763 
1.085 
Access to markets 
−1.272 
0.611 
−2.08** 
Used mechanized processing 
1.126 
0.838 
1.34 
Access to credit 
0.597 
0.922 
0.65 
Off-farm income 
−0.408 
1.008 
−0.40 
Sells cassava to processors 
−4.560 
0.091 
−4.18*** 
Planted cassava as sole crop 
−0.704 
0.212 
−3.32*** 
Variance parameters 
Sigma-squared (σ 
2 ) 
5.089 
0.999 
5.09*** 
Gamma (γ) 
0.883 
0.035 
28.89*** 
Log likelihood function = −606.15 </p>

<p>***Significant at 1%; ** at 5% and * at 10%. </p>

<p>APPLIED ECONOMICS LETTERS </p>

<p>
processing villages were brought closer to their pro-
duction frontier, thereby greatly enhancing profit. 
The study recommends that there should be an 
increased promotion of postharvest technologies 
that can help processors engage in mechanical pro-
cessing of crops, especially highly perishable crops 
such as cassava. The adoption of postharvest tech-
nologies stimulates increased demand for fresh cas-
sava roots for processing, which in turn had positive 
impact on farmers' production efficiency through 
increased access to markets. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the authors. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by the Common Fund for 
Commodities of the Netherlands: [grant number CFC/FIGG 43]. </p>



<p> 
A. ABASS ET AL. </p>

</text></tei>