<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F00036846.2015.1021547" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Since the onset of the financial crisis significant interest rate spreads have 
arisen between euro area countries, both for public and private debt. We 
check whether these spreads could be made to work towards the goal of 
providing more stability to the euro area. In particular, we focus on 
reducing the imbalances that arose between the core and peripheral mem-
bers of the euro area in the first decade of its existence. The idea is that 
stable positive spreads in peripheral countries could have decreased 
domestic demand, preventing the boom-bust cycles that plagued these 
economies. They could also prevent such developments in the future. We 
construct a panel model for euro area countries and estimate the relation-
ship between real interest rates and the current account balance. Next, we 
use the estimated parameters to perform simulations. We find that spreads 
on real interest rates of 0.6-5.5 percentage points would have been 
necessary to stabilize external positions of the four peripheral euro area 
member countries. </p>

<p>Over the first decade of its existence the euro area 
witnessed deep imbalances between its core and per-
ipheral members. One of the most important reasons 
behind their build-up was (approximately) equal 
nominal interest rates across the common currency 
area. According to several studies, these rates were 
too low for some members and too high for others 
(Blanchard, 2007; Honohan and Leddin, 2006; in't 
Veld et al., 2012; Brzoza-Brzezina et al., 2014). </p>

<p>Inflation differentials aggravated the problem since 
inflation rates in peripheral countries tended to be 
relatively high, bringing real rates to even lower 
levels (ECB, 2003; Zdarek and Aldasoro, 2009). As 
a result, several peripheral economies of the euro area 
faced boom-bust cycles. 
1 Rapid growth of internal 
demand, driven by mild financing conditions, 
boosted somewhat domestic output but the bulk of 
additional demand was supplied from abroad. At the 
same time domestic inflation picked up and started to 
exceed that of core euro area countries. As a result of </p>

<p>*Corresponding author. E-mail: michal.brzoza-brzezina@nbp.pl 
1 As a matter of fact, the problem also affected (and sometimes even more) countries that adopted hard pegs against the 
euro, Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania (Brixiova et al., 2009; Kuodis and Ramanauskas, 2009). </p>

<p>Applied Economics, 2015 
Vol. 47, Nos. 34-35, 3696-3709, http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/00036846.2015.1021547 </p>

<p>3696 
© 2015 Taylor &amp; Francis </p>

<p>high demand and lost competitiveness, CA deficits 
swelled. Figure 1 shows a synthetic picture of these 
developments, plotting the change of real interest 
rates before and after 1999 against the CA balance 
after 1999 for 11 euro area countries. Those countries 
where real interest rates declined the most witnessed 
highest CA deficits. 
Things changed when the financial crisis broke 
out. Interest rates started to diverge. Risk premia in 
highly indebted countries enforced by speculation 
contributed to higher spreads on sovereign debt and 
bank loans to the private sector (see Figs 2 and 3). 
Domestic demand in peripheral economies collapsed 
and CA deficits narrowed sharply (for instance, the 
unweighted average CA/GDP ratio for Greece, </p>

<p>Ireland, Portugal and Spain increased from −10.0% 
in 2007 to −0.3% in 2012). Their external positions 
improved amid a deep recession, whose seeds were 
sown during the preceding boom. 
These developments bring forward the idea that 
the interest rate spreads between euro area countries 
could be exploited in a way that brings more stability 
to the euro area. However, it should be made clear 
from the very beginning that we do not speak of 
variable spreads as they emerged since the onset of 
the crisis. These proved to work in exactly the oppo-
site way we propose. They increased in depressed, 
peripheral countries only after the outbreak of the 
crisis, making recovery even more difficult. This 
was deemed worrying by the ECB President Mario 
Draghi (2012) who rightly pointed out that this could 
impair the proper working of monetary transmission 
in the euro area. 
In contrast, we speak of stable spreads that could 
bring more stability to the euro area. If peripheral 
countries had faced higher average interest rates in 
the past, imbalances would not have been so dramatic 
and, as a result, the adjustment that these countries 
have been undergoing since 2009 could have been 
much less painful. Higher average interest rates for 
peripheral countries could also prevent macroeco-
nomic imbalances from increasing again in the 
future. In contrast to the case when countercyclical 
spreads destabilize the economy, here we discuss 
equilibrium spreads that are constant over time so 
that they do not interfere with the monetary policy. 
The bottom line of this argument is that the idea of 
spreads between monetary union countries should 
possibly not be rejected completely. If financial </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Real interest rate change versus current 
account (CA) balance 
Note: Average CA balance (1999-2012) on horizontal 
axis against average change of the real lending rate for 
nonfinancial corporations (1999-2012 versus 1990-1998) 
on vertical axis; EA-11. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Yields on sovereign debt in selected EA 
countries 
Note: Yields are for the long-term (10 year) government 
bonds (Maastricht definition). </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Lending rates in selected EA countries 
Note: Lending rate to nonfinancial corporations (up to 
1 year maturity, new business). </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
markets provided relatively stable spreads of the 
right size (possibly with some educated guidance 
of the ECB), the gains for euro area stability could 
be substantial. Referring again to President 
Draghi (2013), he also pointed out that the ECB 
would not reduce those parts of sovereign bond 
yields that are 'fundamentally justified'. This is 
exactly what our article is about, although we go 
one step further and postulate keeping 'fundamen-
tally justified' spreads on private borrowing as well. 
The policy conclusion from this article would be 
that the ECB should not condemn and fight spreads 
across the board but rather take into account their 
equilibrium level for various countries. 
While interest rate spreads in a monetary union do 
not, at first, look like an attractive idea, one has to 
bear in mind three things. First, if the renewed rise of 
imbalances is to be prevented, some sort of break 
must be put on more spending-oriented parts of the 
euro area. If it is not spreads (higher price), it must be 
quantitative restrictions on capital inflows (e.g. lim-
ited credit supply). One has to consider what is less 
appealing in a monetary union. Second, whether one 
likes it or not, spreads are already there (as well as 
quantitative restrictions as a matter of fact). With 
some guidance, they could possibly benefit the com-
mon currency. Lastly, despite the last reforms of 
macroprudential policy in the euro area in the wake 
of sovereign debt crisis, especially stronger enforce-
ment of the limits on fiscal deficits, implementation 
of fiscal policy is still a competence of the Member 
States. The idea underlying this model (e.g. centra-
lized monetary policy with independent fiscal policy) 
is still that the incentives for fiscal discipline should 
largely come from the financial markets that are able 
to distinguish and properly price country-specific 
risk (which nevertheless proved false in the first 
decade of the EMU). 
The idea of using spreads to stabilize a heteroge-
neous monetary union is, to our knowledge, a new one. 
The closest thing in the literature in terms of concept 
and methodology is probably the estimation of equili-
brium exchange rates. For instance, in his fundamental 
equilibrium exchange rate concept Williamson (1994) 
calculates the theoretical real exchange rate that (i.a.) 
brings the CA balance to an exogenous target. We do 
the same for real interest rates. 
We define equilibrium spreads as the difference 
between a country's real interest rate and the euro </p>

<p>area average real interest rates that would, on 
average, keep its CA balance in equilibrium. 
Given the described developments, the CA bal-
ance seems to provide a relatively universal mea-
sure of a currency union member's overheating. 
To this end, we estimate a panel data model and 
use it to calculate the elasticity of the CA balance 
with respect to the real interest rate. Next, we use 
the IMF's External Sustainability (ES) methodol-
ogy to calculate equilibrium CA balances for 
individual euro area Member States. Finally, 
both results are used to calculate theoretical real 
interest rate spreads that would have bridged the 
gaps between CA balances and the norms for 
individual countries. 
Our findings show that indeed interest rate spreads 
could have significantly lowered the gaps between 
CA balances and their equilibrium levels (norms). 
For the four peripheral countries, we show that inter-
est rate spreads against euro area average that would 
have closed the gaps between CA balances and their 
respective norms in the period 1999-2007 range 
from 5.5 percentage points in Portugal to 0.6 percen-
tage points in Ireland. 
The rest of the article is structured as follows: 
Section II describes the methodology for calculating 
CA norms. Section III presents the data, and Section 
IV presents estimation methods and results. In 
Section V, we calculate the theoretical equilibrium 
spreads. Section VI concludes. </p>

<p>II. Current Account Norms </p>

<p>As already mentioned in Section I, we proceed in 
three steps. First, we calculate reference levels 
(norms) for CA balances. Second, we estimate elas-
ticity of the CA with respect to the real interest rate. 
Finally, we calculate the interest rates that would 
have closed the gaps between CAs and their refer-
ence levels. This chapter presents the first step. 
The literature on calculating equilibrium/refer-
ence/norm levels for CA balances is vast. A substan-
tial part of research has been conducted by the 
International Monetary Fund. Several methodologies 
were developed by its Coordinating Group on 
Exchange Rate (CGER) Issues in the 2000s 
(IMF, 2006; Isard and Faruqee, 2008). The so-called 
S-I norms are based on applying medium run values </p>

<p>3698 
M. Brzoza-Brzezina et al. </p>

<p>of regressors to coefficients of an estimated CA 
equation. ES norms rely on the notion of stabilizing 
the net foreign asset (NFA)-to-GDP ratio (more 
details below). A more recent approach of the Fund 
is the external balance assessment (EBA; IMF, 2013). 
This method starts with estimating a CA regression 
and then applying normative policy benchmarks 
for selected regressors, including the fiscal balance, 
capital controls and monetary policy. Nevertheless, 
aside of this fairly advanced method, EBA also uses 
the ES approach known from the CGER. 
We decided to follow the IMF's ES approach 
embedded in the CGER and EBA methodologies. 
This method, as described in detail below, is sim-
ple and transparent. In particular, ES does not 
involve discretionary choices. We believe that 
given our exercise, the great simplicity of the 
norm calculation is a serious advantage. 
Considering how rich the literature on equilibrium 
CA balances is, we do not want to leave the 
impression that our results can be made for ES 
norms only. While clearly the final answer (interest 
rate spread) depends on the norm, we treat the 
estimated interest rate semi-elasticities as the 
main and fixed ingredient for calculating the 
spreads. The ES norms only provide an illustration 
and if one has a different view on equilibrium CA 
balances, it is trivial to substitute it. 
The ES methodology calculates the CA balance 
that stabilizes the NFA position of the economy. It 
relies on the intertemporal budget constraint which 
requires that the present value of future trade sur-
pluses suffices to repay the country's external debt. 
The intertemporal budget constraint can be satisfied 
by ensuring that the NFA-to-GDP ratio is stabilized, 
thus preventing assets or liabilities from growing 
without bound. 
The starting point for calculating the CA norm is 
the accumulation equation for NFAs: </p>

<p>NFA t À NFA tÀ1 ¼ CA t 
(1) </p>

<p>where NFA t denotes the NFA stock and CA t the CA 
balance. Denoting with lower case letters the ratio of 
a given variable to GDP this equation can be writ-
ten as: </p>

<p>nfa t À nfa tÀ1 ¼ ca t À 
g t 
1 þ g t 
nfa tÀ1 
(2) </p>

<p>where g t stands for nominal GDP growth. Hence, the 
CA-to-GDP ratio that stabilizes the NFA position at 
previous year's level is: </p>

<p>ca t ¼ 
g t 
1 þ g t 
nfa tÀ1 
(3) </p>

<p>From Equation 3, we calculate CA norms for the 
11 euro area countries in our sample for the period 
1999-2007, that is the time when imbalances were 
growing. Next, we calculate the gap between each 
country's CA position and its norm. Table 1 shows 
the average CA balance, norm and gap. Clearly all 
numbers differ between countries. In particular, the 
peripheral countries that noticed large CA deficits 
also show the biggest gaps between CA balances 
and norms, ranging from 1.9% of GDP in Ireland to 
7% of GDP in Portugal. </p>

<p>III. Data </p>

<p>The estimation was conducted for 11 euro area coun-
tries which formed initially the monetary union: 
Austria, Belgium, Finland, France, Germany, 
Greece, Ireland, Italy, the Netherlands, Portugal and 
Spain. Due to the high share of the financial sector to 
GDP which could distort the estimation results, we 
excluded Luxemburg from the sample. The time span 
used for the estimation covers the period 1995-2012 
providing 18 annual observations. We used data 
since 1995 because in the period preceding the euro 
adoption fluctuations of the nominal exchange rates 
in our sample were limited allowing us to lengthen </p>

<p>Table 1. CAs norms and gaps </p>

<p>Country 
CA balance 
CA norm 
CA gap </p>

<p>Austria 
1.3 
−0.8 
2.1 
Belgium 
3.3 
1.7 
1.6 
Finland 
5.9 
−3.4 
9.3 
France 
0.6 
−0.1 
0.7 
Germany 
2.7 
0.3 
2.4 
Greece 
−7.9 
−3.9 
−4.0 
Ireland 
−1.6 
0.2 
−1.9 
Italy 
−0.5 
−0.4 
0.0 
Netherlands 
5.3 
−0.3 
5.6 
Portugal 
−9.3 
−2.2 
−7.0 
Spain 
−5.5 
−3.1 
−2.3 </p>

<p>Note: The table presents average values for the period 
1999-2007, all numbers expressed in per cent of GDP. </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
our sample by 4 years making the estimation results 
more robust. While we used panel data estimation 
techniques with a relatively small number of coun-
tries (N) the extension of the sample could be bene-
ficial for the properties of the estimators (see the 
'Estimation methods' section). The simulation of 
the equilibrium spreads has been, however con-
ducted for the period 1999-2007 when imbalances 
in the euro area were emerging. 
The choice of a single appropriate interest rate 
which determines the relationship between domestic 
savings and investments, and finally the CA position, 
is not straightforward. The heterogeneity in the struc-
ture of savings across the euro area countries, the 
changes in their structure over time as well as differ-
ent horizons for savings and investments motivate us 
to use several measures of interest rates. In turn, we 
employed three different interest rates: the yield on 
10 year sovereign bonds, the average lending rate for 
nonfinancial corporations (maturity up to 1 year) and 
the average interest rate on deposits from the non-
financial sector (both for new contracts). The yield on 
sovereign bonds is a long-term interest rate, while 
two latter variables may be perceived as medium 
term interest rates. All interest rates have been 
adjusted for HICP (Harmonized Index of Consumer 
Prices) inflation. 
While investigating the role of the interest rates in 
determining the CA balance, we should also account 
for other variables which influence the relationship 
between domestic investments and savings in the 
medium to long-term and are not related to the busi-
ness cycle. The list of potential determinants of the 
CA balance is very comprehensive (see Chudik 
et al., 2012; IMF, 2013), and it depends both on the 
underlying theory and the sample of the countries 
under interest. While selecting control variables, we 
focus only on 'structural' (long-term) indicators to 
avoid a contemporaneous relationship with interest 
rates. The idea is to allow the interest rate to capture 
the whole cyclical component of the CA movement. 
From among the most widely used structural CA 
determinants, we use the following variables which 
we find suitable for the euro area countries: NFAs 
position, demographic factors, structural fiscal bal-
ance, the variables expressing the stage of develop-
ment like GDP per capita or productivity, the rule of 
law and the capital-to-output ratio. Below we 
describe the selected control variables and their 
expected impact on the CA balance. </p>

<p>• NFAs position. In the literature most specifica-
tions of the CA equation include the country's 
lagged or initial NFA position expressed usually 
in relation to GDP. Nevertheless, the sign of the 
relationship with the CA balance is ambiguous. 
On the one hand, countries with a more positive 
NFA position tend to have a higher CA balance 
due to more favourable income balance stem-
ming from higher net foreign investments. On 
the other, countries with a less favourable NFA 
position may afford a lower trade balance to 
maintain the constant NFA to GDP relationship. 
The potentially negative relationship between 
the initial NFA position and the CA may also 
result from the fact that highly indebted countries 
may be forced to improve their CA balance to 
increase their solvency. The latter explanation 
may be suitable for the euro area countries in 
the period covered by our research. 
• Demographic factors. We expect a negative 
relationship between the number of economic-
ally dependents in the population and the level 
of national savings and further the CA balance. 
Following the literature, we account for demo-
graphic factors in the model by using a variable 
expressing population growth. 
• Stage of development. Due to the shortage of 
domestic savings, lower income countries are 
usually forced to finance investments by exter-
nal borrowing, which results in a CA deficit. 
This process stays in line with the theory that 
capital flows from higher to lower productivity 
countries. We express the stage of development 
by two alternative measures: GDP per capita 
and the level of productivity. 
• Structural fiscal balance. According to several 
theoretical models, we expect a positive rela-
tionship between the fiscal balance and the CA 
balance. Only when Ricardian equivalence 
holds, changes in the budget deficit do not 
affect aggregated savings and investments. In 
the model, we test the significance of the fiscal 
balance with respect to CA. To avoid the con-
temporaneous link with the interest rates, we 
use the structural fiscal balance (in relation to 
GDP), that is, the fiscal balance adjusted for the 
business cycle position of the economy. 
• Rule of law. Better institutions and regulations 
increase productivity and export performance 
in many ways. First, they reduce quasi-fixed </p>

<p>3700 
M. Brzoza-Brzezina et al. </p>

<p>costs like corruption or time needed to com-
plete administration duties. Second, they mini-
mize excessive uncertainty in doing business, 
resulting from, for example, low contract 
enforcement, which allows firms to plan long-
term investments or cooperate and make use of 
synergy. As a variable in the model we use the 
perceived rule of law from the World 
Governance Index data set. We expect the para-
meter's sign to be positive. 
• Capital-to-output ratio. This variable repre-
sents endowment in capital and is a proxy for 
foreign capital needs. Moreover, more produc-
tive technologies are usually capital-embodied 
therefore we expect the sign to be positive. </p>

<p>The data comes from the IMF, Eurostat and AMECO 
(the annual macro-economic database of the 
European Commission's Directorate General for 
Economic and Financial Affairs) databases. </p>

<p>IV. Estimation Results </p>

<p>Estimation methods </p>

<p>In this section, we discuss the estimation technique 
applied by us. In particular, we concentrate on two 
issues. First, we explain why, in contrast to the much 
of the literature, we use a dynamic panel data model. 
Second, we explain our choice of preferred estimator. 
In panel data analysis of macroeconomic data, the 
dynamic nature of a process is often ignored by 
researchers, partly due to econometric limitations 
(see below). Indeed, a number of panel data studies 
on CA use static models with autocorrelation correc-
tion (e.g. IMF, 2013). In this article, we decided to 
include the lagged CA on the right-hand side of the 
regression. Our arguments for such an approach are 
as follows: First, one of our goals is to assess the 
long-term effect of real interest rate changes on CA. 
Thus, while in static specifications one assumes that 
all shocks in explanatory variables affect the CA only </p>

<p>in the same period, in the dynamic case the long-term 
impact of change in the explanatory variable x k is 
given by </p>

<p>x k </p>

<p>1Àρ , where ρ stands for the autoregressive 
coefficient of the lagged dependent variable. Second, 
the decision whether to include a lagged dependent 
variable or not depends in our opinion on the state-
dependency of the CA. In our view, agents' decision 
on whether to invest abroad or trade with foreign 
markets is affected by the past choices. Factors like 
(partial) irreversibility of investment, sunk costs of 
foreign market research, long-term contractual agree-
ments between parties or involvement into global 
supply chains may be good examples. Third, our 
approach allows us to address the issue of autocorre-
lation existing in the data as well. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Regarding the appropriate estimation technique, 
our choice may be perceived as a trade-off between 
methods that minimize the bias and those that give 
lower SEs. This is because, as it is often the case for 
macroeconomic data, the time dimension of our data 
set is quite large (T = 18) but the cross-sectional 
dimension is rather low. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>As well documented in the literature, OLS yields 
inconsistent estimates in the presence of unobserved 
heterogeneity. In a dynamic specification, the bias of 
the OLS autoregression coefficients is positive 
(Baltagi, 2005). A straightforward way to deal with 
heterogeneity between units and omitted variable bias 
would be to include a set of country dummies, that is, 
fixed effects (FEs). However, there are two problems 
with a dynamic FE estimator. First, including unit-
specific dummies is very likely to make parameter 
estimates of rather time-invariant variables statistically 
insignificant, even if their importance for a given 
economic phenomenon is deeply verified and docu-
mented in the theoretical literature (see Plümper 
et al., 2005 and references). Fortunately, interest rates 
that we focus on show enough volatility over time. The 
second (and far more important) problem with the FEs 
approach is however a downward bias of the autore-
gressive coefficient, known as Nickell bias named 
after the seminal work by Nickell (1981). This bias is </p>

<p>2 As a cross-check, we ran our regressions also in a static form with panel-corrected SEs. Obtained estimates of an 
immediate impact of a change in the real interest rate on the CA were similar to those in our preferred dynamic model. 
However, the high estimated coefficient of autocorrelation of residuals from the static model as well as high and robust 
significance of the lagged CA in the dynamic specification suggest that the latter one should be our preferred choice. 
3 Time dimension of 18 observations may, indeed, seem quite large for a panel data set. However, it is rather small for 
cointegration time-series methods, such as panel ECM models proposed by Pesaran and Smith (1995); Pesaran 
et al. (1997). What is more, power of unit root test for our data set seems rather low, as their asymptotic properties depend 
on T and N being large. Instead, we prefer to include lagged dependent variable to control for autocorrelation and year 
dummies to control for common shocks and possible trends in the data. </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
especially important in short data sets with highly 
persistent variables, as it diminishes as T ! 1 but 
is significant if ρ ! 1. In our case, T = 18 which may 
diminish the bias, yet the dependent variable is highly 
persistent (autocorrelation coefficient of first order is 
as big as 0.95 and autocorrelation coefficient of even 
third order is still higher than 0.8). 
In this context, it is useful to employ the bias-
corrected dynamic FE estimator, an estimator that is 
particularly well-designed for a data set like ours 
(Bruno, 2005). It borrows from Kiviet (1995) and 
later works by Judson and Owen (1997), Bun and 
Kiviet (2003) and Bun and Kiviet (2006). Such a 
strategy allows us to verify if the time dimension of 
our data set is large enough to bring the Nickell bias 
of our parameters to acceptably low levels. 
Alternatively, one could use instrumental variable 
estimation, such as Anderson and Hsiao (1982) first-
difference (FD) estimator to deal with the possible 
bias of the FE estimator. However, apart from the fact 
that asymptotic efficiency of the FD estimator 
depends on the sample's cross-section dimension 
(which is very low in our case), weak instrumentation 
issues can make the FD estimation a cure worse than 
disease. This is also the case for us. For all three 
interest rates, the F-statistic in the first-stage regres-
sion is far below 10 (which is a rule-of-thumb value 
to identify problems with weak instrumentation, fol-
lowing influential work by Staiger and Stock, 1997) 
and Kleibergen-Paap Wald rk F-statistic is unaccep-
tably low (less than 2, while 19.93 critical value by 
Stock and Yogo (2002) corresponds to 10% IV bias). 
Similarly, high autocorrelation of dependent variable 
weakens instruments also for the difference GMM 
estimator (see Blundell and Bond, 1998). </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Summing up, given the pros and cons of each 
estimator, we decided to estimate an AR(1) panel 
data model (with year dummies), using three estima-
tors: OLS, FE and bias-corrected FE. FE and OLS 
estimates constitute lower and upper bounds for our 
results (Mátyás and Sevestre, 2008), while the use of 
bias-corrected FE estimator allows us to assess the size 
of the Nickell bias, and, consequently, the reliability of 
the FE estimator. For the reasons listed above, we do 
not use IV/GMM methods that could be perfectly fine 
in some macroeconomic applications but for different </p>

<p>data set size, for example, one with a wider set of 
countries and a shorter time dimension. </p>

<p>Estimation results </p>

<p>Now we turn to the estimation results. We followed a 
from general to specific approach and, in the first 
step, we included the full set of variables listed in 
Section III. Part of them (i.e. structural deficit, rule of 
law, capital-to-output ratio, GDP per capita and the 
level of productivity) however turned out to be insig-
nificant in almost every model. One reason for that 
could be that these variables show such low volatility 
in time that their variance was absorbed by country-
specific dummies. Alternatively, some variables that 
truly influence the CA position in a broader set of 
countries may not be crucial in our sample. For 
example, the perceived rule of law may be decisive 
for the choice of FDI location between two emerging 
economies while the differences in regulatory envir-
onments between EA countries could be negligible in 
this context. Eliminating these statistically insignif-
icant variables from the regression did not change our 
core results, therefore, for the sake of simplicity, in 
the remaining part of this article we refer to the model 
of CA with only four regressors. Those are, respec-
tively, the lagged CA-to-GDP ratio, the lagged NFA-
to-GDP ratio, the real interest rate and the rate of 
population change. Our regression is then: </p>

<p>CA i;t ¼ ρCA i;tÀ1 þ β 1 NFA i;tÀ1 þ β 2 r i;t 
þ β 3 Population i;t þ μ i </p>

<p>þ 
X </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>d t þ ε i;t 
(4) </p>

<p>where μ i is a country-specific effect, 
P 
t d t is a set of 
year dummies and ε i;t is the error component 
(assumed to be i.i.d.). 
Table 2 shows the estimation results of our regres-
sion for three real interest rates. Columns (1)-(3) 
show OLS, FE and bias-corrected FE estimates for 
a model with the lending rate for nonfinancial cor-
porations (lending), Columns (4)-(6) refer to the 
interest rate on deposits from the nonfinancial sector 
(depo), while Columns (7)-(9) present the estimates 
of a model with the yield on sovereign bonds </p>

<p>4 As a cross-check, we also used system-GMM estimates that have better properties if ρ → 1, keeping in mind that due to 
overidentification (large number of instruments relative to the number of observations) they should be interpreted with 
great caution (see Roodman, 2009 for extensive discussion). These results, however, are fairly similar to those obtained by 
OLS and FE estimators and are available on request. </p>

<p> 
M. Brzoza-Brzezina et al. </p>

<p>Table 2. Estimation results </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>lending </p>

<p>lending </p>

<p>lending </p>

<p>depo </p>

<p>depo </p>

<p>depo </p>

<p>Maastricht </p>

<p>Maastricht </p>

<p>Maastricht </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>BC-FE </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>BC-FE </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>FE </p>

<p>BC-FE </p>

<p>L.CA </p>

<p>1.005*** </p>

<p>0.815*** </p>

<p>0.815*** </p>

<p>0.993*** </p>

<p>0.834*** </p>

<p>0.834*** </p>

<p>1.003*** </p>

<p>0.870*** </p>

<p>0.913*** </p>

<p>(0.0299) </p>

<p>(0.0439) </p>

<p>(0.0701) </p>

<p>(0.0306) </p>

<p>(0.0450) </p>

<p>(0.0736) </p>

<p>(0.0303) </p>

<p>(0.0479) </p>

<p>(0.0543) </p>

<p>Population change </p>

<p>−0.272 </p>

<p>−0.584** </p>

<p>−0.568 </p>

<p>−0.201 </p>

<p>−0.520* </p>

<p>−0.507 </p>

<p>−0.0197 </p>

<p>−0.170 </p>

<p>−0.133 </p>

<p>(0.203) </p>

<p>(0.270) </p>

<p>(1.787) </p>

<p>(0.198) </p>

<p>(0.288) </p>

<p>(1.864) </p>

<p>(0.194) </p>

<p>(0.344) </p>

<p>(1.376) </p>

<p>Real interest rate </p>

<p>0.104 </p>

<p>0.254*** </p>

<p>0.244 </p>

<p>0.265** </p>

<p>0.281*** </p>

<p>0.267 </p>

<p>0.303*** </p>

<p>0.281*** </p>

<p>0.267*** </p>

<p>(0.0870) </p>

<p>(0.0735) </p>

<p>(0.444) </p>

<p>(0.113) </p>

<p>(0.106) </p>

<p>(0.570) </p>

<p>(0.0452) </p>

<p>(0.0505) </p>

<p>(0.0663) </p>

<p>L.NFA </p>

<p>−0.00799** </p>

<p>−0.0147*** </p>

<p>−0.0137 </p>

<p>−0.00792** </p>

<p>−0.0150*** </p>

<p>−0.0140 </p>

<p>−0.00384 </p>

<p>−0.0103** </p>

<p>−0.0138*** </p>

<p>(0.00335) </p>

<p>(0.00447) </p>

<p>(0.0247) </p>

<p>(0.00359) </p>

<p>(0.00469) </p>

<p>(0.0250) </p>

<p>(0.00372) </p>

<p>(0.00486) </p>

<p>(0.00501) </p>

<p>Constant </p>

<p>1.537*** </p>

<p>1.593*** </p>

<p>1.687*** </p>

<p>1.901*** </p>

<p>0.730** </p>

<p>1.071*** </p>

<p>(0.585) </p>

<p>(0.600) </p>

<p>(0.557) </p>

<p>(0.603) </p>

<p>(0.340) </p>

<p>(0.404) </p>

<p>AR(1) test </p>

<p>0.053 </p>

<p>0.266 </p>

<p>0.084 </p>

<p>0.287 </p>

<p>0.269 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>AR(2) test </p>

<p>0.389 </p>

<p>0.457 </p>

<p>0.497 </p>

<p>0.502 </p>

<p>0.833 </p>

<p>0.299 </p>

<p>Heteroscedasticity test </p>

<p>0.245 </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.310 </p>

<p>0.052 </p>

<p>0.216 </p>

<p>0.077 </p>

<p>Notes: Year dummies included. AR(1) and AR(2) are p-values of Arellano-Bond test. 
Heteroscedasticity test is p-value of White-Koenker test. </p>

<p>SEs robust for autocorrelation and heteroscedasticity in parentheses. 
*** p &lt; 0.01, ** p &lt; 0.05, * p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
(Maastricht) as a regressor. Now we discuss the 
results given by the three estimators and explain the 
choice of the preferred one. The signs of parameters 
given by all three estimators seem well in line with 
the expectations. In particular, the parameter for the 
real interest rate is always positive regardless of the 
choice of interest rate. A negative sign of the para-
meter for population change suggest that, not surpris-
ingly, a shrinking (ageing) society is more likely to be 
dissaving and therefore soaking up the capital from 
abroad. Although population change did not always 
turn statistically significant, due to strong priors we 
keep this variable in the model. Finally, the negative 
sign of lagged NFA coefficient shows that no country 
may run CA deficits/surpluses forever. 
In the next step, we explain the choice of our 
preferred model. As expected, OLS estimates of 
parameter ρ are somehow larger than those of FE. 
However, reported point estimates of parameters 
using bias-corrected FE (we employed <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bruno</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2005</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">Stata</rs> routine) are almost the same as the FE 
estimates, which suggest that the Nickell bias seems 
negligible in our context (and that OLS estimates 
suffer from omitted variable bias). Also the signifi-
cance of country dummies suggests that OLS esti-
mates may not be the most reliable ones. Finally, it 
should be noted that the FE estimates have a rela-
tively small variance, especially if compared to 
consistent estimators as GMM (Mátyás and 
Sevestre, 2008) or bias-corrected FE. For these rea-
sons, we choose the simple FE estimator as the 
preferred one. Regarding the specification tests, 
the Arellano-Bond test for autocorrelation shows 
that including the lagged dependent variable and 
year dummies reduces problems with autocorrela-
tion. At no reasonable significance level, the null 
hypothesis (i.e. that there is no autocorrelation) 
should be rejected. To deal with heterogeneity we 
use robust SEs. 
Our core results may be then summarized as fol-
lows: An exogenous increase of the real interest rate 
(medium or long-term) by 1 percentage point results 
in an improvement in the CA-to-GDP ratio of 0.25-
0.28 pp in the same year. Including lagged NFA as a 
regressor makes the basic formula for a long-term 
multiplier invalid, therefore we present simulations 
based on the regression results in detail in Section V. 
To give some intuition, though, we can say that 
(ceteris paribus) an increase in a medium term real 
interest rate by 1 pp results in a rise in the NFA-to-
GDP ratio by 0.93-1.09 that is obtained after </p>

<p>7-8 years and is diminishing afterwards. For the 
long-term interest rate, a rise by 1 pp translates into 
an improvement of the NFA-to-GDP ratio of about 
1.36 after 10 years. Not surprisingly, also the long-
term effect of an increase in the real interest rate on 
NFA-to-GDP ratio is clearly higher for the long-term 
interest rate (Maastricht rate) than that for the 
deposit rate or lending rate, which suggests that it is 
the structural factors rather than short-term ones that 
have the biggest influence on the external position of 
an economy. 
Additionally, as a robustness check for a possible 
structural break in 1999, we estimated the model 
using data for the period 1999-2012 only. 
However, we obtained very similar results to those 
for the full sample. Specifically, the estimates of the 
core parameters ρ and β 2 were similar in size to those 
for the full sample, did not differ for the FE and the 
BC-FE model and remained statistically significant 
at 5% level in the FE model. 
In this section, we presented estimation results of a 
dynamic panel data model of the CA-to-GDP ratio 
for a set of 11 EA countries. We argue that in our 
case, the best possible trade-off between efficiency 
and consistency is given by the FE estimator and our 
results show a significant impact of real interest rates 
on the CA. In the next section, we use them to 
calculate the hypothetical levels of the interest rate 
spreads that would have been necessary to stabilize 
external position of the EA countries in the first 
decade after the euro adoption. One final question 
that could be posed is why our results show a strong, 
significant and robust impact of the real interest rate 
on the CA while several other studies have not found 
such link. We believe that the answer is related to the 
explanation given in IMF (2013). When discussing 
their failure to find a statistically significant relation-
ship between real rates and the CA, the authors point 
to the two channels of interest rates transmission. On 
the one hand, higher real rates increase savings and 
reduce investments, thus improving the CA. 
However, at the same time higher interest rates 
bring about an exchange rate appreciation and, as a 
result, reduce net exports and the CA. These effects 
may cancel out, at least in the short and medium term, 
IMF (2013) concludes. However, our research is 
conducted for a panel of monetary union members, 
where the second channel is closed by construction. 
What remains is the first channel, which works in the 
desired direction and is confirmed in our regressions. 
Of course this reasoning is only a hypothesis which </p>

<p>3704 
M. Brzoza-Brzezina et al. </p>

<p>we do not verify explicitly in this project. It looks like 
an interesting topic for future research. </p>

<p>V. Equilibrium Spreads </p>

<p>In the next step, we assess to what extent a potentially 
stronger than historically observed divergence in the 
level of real interest rates between euro area countries 
could have prevented the substantial increase of 
external imbalances in the period after forming the 
monetary union and fixing nominal exchange rates. 
To answer this question, we conduct a counterfactual 
simulation, in which we calculate country-by-coun-
try the hypothetical level of the real interest rates that 
would have stabilized its CA balance at the equili-
brium level calculated in Section II. 
Before we move to the simulations three things 
should be mentioned. First, as shown above, our 
estimation results point to a large difference between 
short-and long-term multipliers for the real interest 
rate. This means that it is potentially much more 
difficult to stabilize the CA every period than to do 
it on average in a longer time span. Second, our 
model has another hidden dynamic element -the 
lagged NFA position. This must be taken into 
account when running the simulations. Third, since 
the norm depends on the past NFA position, which 
changes during the simulation, the norm has to be 
dynamically adjusted as well. To summarize our 
simulation seeks for the real interest rates that solve 
for each country the following system of equations: </p>

<p>where spread to actual real interest rates Ár has 
been set to fulfil the condition that in the years 
1999-2007 (2001-2007 for Greece) the difference 
between CA and its norm must be zero on 
average: </p>

<p>X 2007 </p>

<p>t¼1999 </p>

<p>ca t À ca </p>

<p>s 
t </p>

<p>À 
Á 
¼ 0 
(6) </p>

<p>In Equation 5, nfa t is the NFA position at the 
end of period t. Variables ca t and c" a t stand for 
CA balance and its norm in period t while the 
valuesp,β 1 andβ 2 denote parameter estimates 
from Equation 4. The superscript s stands for the 
counterfactual simulated values. In the starting 
period, t = 0 the simulated CA balance is the 
actual CA increased or decreased by the short-
term impact of change in real interest rates. The 
simulated NFA position is the actual NFA stock 
plus the difference between the simulated counter-
factual and the actual CA. Since CA in Equation 
4 depends on its lagged value and lagged NFA 
position in the next periods the changes of CA 
and NFA from the past must be taken into 
account. That is why for deriving the simulated 
CA for the periods t &gt; 0 we add the difference 
between simulated and actual values of CA and 
NFA position from the preceding period. 
Accordingly our exercise has been designed as 
follows. For each country we find the level of real </p>

<p>ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0 ¼ ca 0 þβ 2 Ár 
nfa </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0 ¼ nfa 0 þ ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0 À ca 0 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>ca 0 ¼ ca 0 </p>

<p>ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 ¼ ca 1 þβ 2 Ár þρ ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0 À ca 0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
þβ 1 nfa </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>0 À nfa 0 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>nfa </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 ¼ nfa 1 þ ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 À ca 1 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>ca 1 ¼ </p>

<p>g t 
1þg t </p>

<p>nfa </p>

<p>s 
0 </p>

<p>8 
&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; &gt; : </p>

<p>. . . </p>

<p>ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t ¼ ca t þβ 2 Ár þρ ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>tÀ1 À ca tÀ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
þβ 1 nfa </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>tÀ1 À nfa tÀ1 </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>nfa </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t ¼ nfa t þ ca </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t À ca t </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>ca t ¼ </p>

<p>g t 
1þg t </p>

<p>nfa </p>

<p>s 
tÀ1 </p>

<p>8 
&gt; &lt; </p>

<p>&gt; : </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
interest rates, which would have stabilized the aver-
age CA in the period from adopting the euro in 1999 
(in 2001 for Greece) to the onset of the global finan-
cial crisis in 2007. Hence, the difference between the 
CA and the norm for the years 1999-2007 must be 
zero on average (2001-2007 for Greece). However, 
taking into account the substantial discrepancy 
between values of short-and long-term multipliers 
we set the interest rates at the desired level already 
2 years before adopting the euro (in 1999 for Greece 
and in 1997 for remaining ten countries). This 
assumption stays in line with the observation that 
approximately 1.5-2 years before euro adoption 
financial markets started to perceive countries as 
future euro area Member States what resulted in 
acceleration of nominal interest rate convergence 
and a substantial decrease of spreads. 
The simulation results are collected in Table 3. We 
present the outcome for our three interest rates. The 
numbers in the table are the differences between 
historical real interest rates and our counterfactual 
rates. The results clearly show that for four euro 
area countries Ireland, Portugal, Greece and Spain 
the historical real interest rates were too low to pre-
vent these economies from building up external 
imbalances. The highest discrepancy between actual 
and desired interest rates can be observed for 
Portugal and Greece. Depending on the choice of 
the interest rate, the difference ranges from 5.8 to 
7.5 pp for Portugal and from 4.3 to 5.4 pp for Greece. 
Slightly lower but still negative spreads are calcu-
lated for Spain (2.0-2.5 pp) and Ireland (1.5-2.0 pp). 
For two countries France and Italy the historical real 
interest rates were almost in line with the simulated 
counterfactual rates. Five euro area countries </p>

<p>experienced real interest rates which resulted in aver-
age surplus of CA over their norm in the reference 
period. For these countries, the historical real rates 
were above the desired rates by 1.3-1.6 pp in case of 
Belgium, by 1.7-2.2 pp for Austria and by 1.9-2.5 pp 
for Germany. The highest positive discrepancy 
between historical rates and the rates stabilizing the 
CA balance show up for Finland (7.7-10.1 pp) and 
the Netherlands (4.7-6.0 pp). However, the results 
for both countries may be to some extent biased. In 
the first case, there were large jumps in the NFA stock 
in years 1999 and 2000 due to valuation effects. For 
the Netherlands, gas exports and the role of the port 
of Rotterdam are likely to substantially improve the 
average CA. 
In Table 3, we collect the results of the simulation in 
terms of spreads to the historical real interest rates. 
However, although up to 2007 the differences in his-
torical nominal interest rates between euro area 
Member States were in general negligible, real interest 
rates differed due to discrepancy in the inflation rates. 
In Fig. 4, we present the counterfactual average histor-
ical real interest rates calculated as a sum of spreads 
from Table 3 and the historical average real rates for 
years 1999 and 2007 for subsequent countries related 
to the historical average real interest rate for the euro 
area (EA11 weighted by GDP contribution). In other 
words, we show the spread against the EA 11 average 
instead of each country's historical average. For three 
euro area countries France, Italy and Ireland the 
desired real long-term interest rate should have been 
slightly above the average real rate for the euro area 
(from 0.4 to 0.6 pp). Spain should have had real 
interest rates higher than an average interest rate for </p>

<p>Table 3. Spreads between actual and desired real 
interest rates (stabilizing NFA stock) </p>

<p>Country 
Maastricht rate Depo rate Lending rate </p>

<p>Finland 
−7.7 
−8.7 
−10.1 
Netherlands −4.7 
−5.2 
−6.0 
Germany 
−1.9 
−2.2 
−2.5 
Austria 
−1.7 
−2.0 
−2.2 
Belgium 
−1.3 
−1.5 
−1.6 
France 
−0.5 
−0.7 
−0.7 
Italy 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
Ireland 
1.5 
1.8 
2.0 
Spain 
2.0 
2.2 
2.5 
Greece 
4.3 
4.7 
5.4 
Portugal 
5.8 
6.5 
7.5 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Spreads of desired real interest rates versus 
EA-11 average 
Notes: The EA11 average interest rate has been weighted 
by GDP shares. The results are presented for the 
Maastricht rate. </p>

<p>3706 
M. Brzoza-Brzezina et al. </p>

<p>the euro area by 1.6 pp, while for Greece this spread 
should have equalled 3.8 pp. According to our calcu-
lations, the highest positive spread would have been 
necessary for Portugal, amounting to 5.5 pp. 
Finally, we look at the time series of simulated CA 
deficits in our four most interesting countries. Since 
we introduce a constant spread between historical and 
counterfactual rates, the simulated CA equals the 
norm only on average. The question is: how much it 
deviates from the norm over time? As shown in Fig. 5, 
not surprisingly, the counterfactual CA deficits do not 
overlap perfectly with the respective norms. However, 
at least in Greece, Portugal and Spain the deviations 
are not large and a clear improvement of the situation 
can be observed -the simulated CA is clearly closer to 
the norm than to its historical level. The situation is 
less obvious in Ireland, and this is for two reasons. 
First, the average gap between the CA and the norm 
was relatively small in this country. Moreover, valua-
tion effects for NFAs increased the volatility of the 
norm. However, even there a clear improvement of the 
counterfactual over the historical CA can be observed. </p>

<p>VI. Conclusions </p>

<p>This research project originates from two observa-
tions. First, large macroeconomic imbalances </p>

<p>plagued the euro area since its creation. Peripheral 
countries faced too low interest rates which increased 
domestic demand, undermined competitiveness and 
resulted in large CA deficits. Second, substantial 
interest rate spreads emerged recently between mem-
ber countries of the euro area. In fact, these spreads 
played an important role in destabilizing the euro 
area, since spreads increased mostly in countries hit 
by deep recession. 
In this article, we check whether interest rate 
spreads could potentially play a stabilizing role as 
well. Instead of time-varying spreads, we consider 
constant spreads which are higher for countries with 
a higher propensity to spend and lower in more sav-
ing-oriented countries. To this end we estimate a 
model that links CA deficits to real interest rates, 
and then calculate by how much real interest rates 
would have to differ from the euro area average in 
order to bring CA balances to assumed targets. Our 
results show that spreads between real interest rates 
of 0.6-5.5 percentage points would be necessary to 
reduce CA deficits in the four peripheral countries 
(Greece, Portugal, Ireland and Spain) to their equili-
brium levels. 
The policy conclusion from this article is that the 
existence of relatively stable spreads of the right size 
on public and private borrowing would be beneficial 
for the stability of the euro area. We believe that the </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Historical and counterfactual CA in selected countries Greece, Ireland, Portugal and Spain </p>

<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
ECB may play a role in guiding the financial markets 
to keep these spreads close to 'fundamentally justi-
fied' levels using verbal interventions as well as 
monetary policy instruments like haircuts. 
Otherwise, it cannot be excluded that the history of 
diverging CA balances, lost competitiveness and 
sharply rising spreads at the least desirable moment 
will repeat itself in a few years. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
We would like to thank Alistair Dieppe, Michele Ca' 
Zorzi and Enchuan Shao as well as the participants of 
the seminars at Narodowy Bank Polski, the Third 
ISCEF Conference in Paris, the IFABS Conference 
in Lisbon, the WIEM conference in Warsaw and the 
ECOMOD conference for valuable comments. The 
views expressed herein are those of the authors and 
not necessarily those of Narodowy Bank Polski or 
the Warsaw School of Economics. </p>

<p>Disclosure Statement 
No potential conflict of interest was reported by the 
authors. </p>



<p>Can interest rate spreads stabilize the euro area? </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>