<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2F1467-8462.12152" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Rapid urban growth is occurring across 
Australia. This has implications for planning 
and management of cities. Data is key to 
tackling this. Hitherto, an extensive range of 
organisations has held the data for Australian 
cities, crossing government, industry and 
academia. With the growing demand for 
open data and capabilities to support big 
data analytics, new opportunities now exist to 
rectify this situation. The Australian Urban 
Research Infrastructure Network (AURIN) 
project has been funded to provide seamless, 
secure access to data from definitive organ-
isations of Australia. We describe the AURIN 
platform; it's data, together with a representa-
tive big data case study. </p>

<p>Globally, more people now live in urban areas 
than elsewhere (United Nations 2011). The 
urban population was growing at 3.5 per cent 
per annum during the 2000s and there are now 
estimated to be 500 urban agglomerations with 
populations in excess of 1 million people 
(Garland 2014). It is projected that the number 
of people living in cities will increase to over 
5 billion over the next two decades, with most 
of that increase being in the developing world 
(McKinsey Global Institute 2011). There are 
also projected to be 135 megacities, with 
populations over 10 million, by the end of 2015 
(World Bank 2009). Cities and the populations 
they comprise are more than just collections 
of individuals and infrastructure (housing, 
schools, roads etc) built around them. Depend-
ing on how they are planned and developed, 
cities can play pivotal roles of great societal 
impact for most of the planet's inhabitants. 
Poorly designed cities can cause a range of 
challenges and frustrations to the inhabitants: 
transport systems, environmental challenges, 
over-population and challenges of increasing 
numbers of migrants, socioeconomic chal-
lenges stemming from the evolving global 
economies and associated employment oppor-
tunities are just some of the issues that city 
planners should be aware of in the future 
growth and form of the urban environments 
they are ultimately responsible for. 
Tackling such issues should be based on the 
definitive quantititative and qualititative data 
for the associated urban settlements. Within 
Australia, there is a multitude of organisations 
that hold, and are responsible for, data related </p>

<p>* Department of Computing and Information Systems, 
The University of Melbourne, Victoria 3010 Australia. 
Corresponding author: Sinnott, email &lt;rsinnott@unimelb. 
edu.au&gt;. The AURIN technical team includes Christopher 
Bayliss, Andrew Bromage, Gerson Galang, Philip Green-
wood, Dr Glenn Tesla Jayaputera, Davis Mota Marques 
Luca Morandini, Ghazal Nogoorani, Dr Hossein Pursultani, 
Muhammad Sarwar, Dr William Voorsluys and Dr Ivo 
Widjaja. The AURIN project is funded through the 
Australian Education Investment Fund SuperScience initia-
tive. We gratefully acknowledge their support and the 
broader network of AURIN collaborators. </p>

<p>The Australian Economic Review, vol. 49, no. 2, pp. 208-23°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research 
Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>to the urban environments. These organisations 
cover government (federal, state and local), 
industry and, in some cases, academia. Ideally, 
all of these data would be directly accessible to 
city planners and researchers more generally. 
Until recently, this was not the case and a siloed 
set of data enclaves existed. 
However, recently there has been a signifi-
cant momentum through the implementation of 
'Open Data' initiatives across the world and 
new approaches for tackling the challenges of 
large-scale and heterogeneous data resources, 
often referred to as 'big data' (Clifford 2008). 
One example of such an initiative is the 
Australian Urban Research Infrastructure 
Network (AURIN) (Stimson, Sinnott and 
Tomko 2011). 
The AURIN project was established in 2010 
to provide an Australia-wide infrastructure 
supporting access to, management and integra-
tion of, datasets related to the urban settlements 
of Australia. In developing such an infrastruc-
ture, it was essential that the infrastructure 
developed was flexible, searchable with 
enriched metadata, scaleable and essentially 
extensible. Thus, there was/is no fixed set of 
data providers and datasets, nor a pre-defined 
set of tools that must be incorporated into 
this infrastructure. Rather, the system had to 
be developed to accommodate flexible and 
streamlined ingestion of new, heteregeneous 
data from new organisations and include new 
tools as they arrive. Developing such extensi-
bility demanded that a data-driven approach 
was taken. Thus, rather than building bespoke 
solutions to access and use data from particular 
organisations, generic data-driven solutions 
were required that work across a multitude of 
organisations and support a variety of research 
efforts. 
At the heart of the AURIN approach was 
access to data. Rather than establish an 
independent data warehouse of data collected 
from various agencies that would become 
outdated, the project sought to build live 
(programmatic) access to the official data 
sources from a multitude of agencies. This 
article provides an overview of the infrastruc-
ture used to achieve this, and importantly, 
provides a snapshot of the data and tools that </p>

<p>are currently available through the AURIN 
environment. 
The rest of the article is structured as 
follows. Section 2 describes the background 
to the AURIN project and presents a summary 
of related work. Section 3 focuses on the 
AURIN architecture and the components it 
supports for data-driven, urban research, with 
an overview of the kinds of data that are 
currently accessible through the platform. 
Section 4 focuses on the utility of this 
e-infrastructure through a data-driven example 
case study regarding areas of advantage 
and disadvantage across Australia. Finally, 
Section 5 draws some conclusions on the work 
and plans for the future. </p>

<p>2. Australian Urban Research Infrastructure 
Network: Background and Related Work </p>

<p>All research disciplines are becoming increas-
ingly driven by the volume of data that can be 
created and/or exist in various forms on the 
Internet. Many research endeavours in dispa-
rate disciplines are now limited by the ability to 
discover, access and optimally use data. The 
work on e-infrastructures, allowing seamless 
access to distributed data resources, has been 
ongoing for decades: from the original efforts 
in large-scale data grid efforts, typified by 
Hey and Trefethen (2003), Shiers (2007) and 
Per ez-S anchez et al. (2015), to more recent 
Cloud-based efforts, typified by Amazon. 
'Big data' is the current buzz word that 
captures the nature of the challenge facing 
many research communities. Cities are 
extremely diverse with numerous potentially 
inter-related datasets: health, housing, trans-
port, population demographics amongst many 
other issues. To tackle this, AURIN focused on 
a set of key themes (lenses) of particular 
importance to the urban research community of 
Australia. Each of these lenses had their own 
datasets, services and tools that needed to be 
brought together. The set of AURIN lenses 
included: population and demographic futures 
and benchmarked social indicators; economic 
activity and urban labour markets; urban 
health, well-being and quality of life; urban 
housing; urban transport; energy and water </p>

<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform 
209°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p>supply and consumption; and innovative 
urban design. These lenses are described in 
McCafferty et al. (2010). Each of these lenses 
represented a significant urban research area in 
its own right. However, each of these is inter-
related. Thus, the changing profile of popula-
tion demographics in cities is essential for 
planning for urban transport, housing, energy, 
water use and health care. 
Across Australia (and indeed in most other 
countries), a huge array of organisations 
collects and holds datasets that are fundamental 
to tackling the current and future challenges 
facing cities. On the one hand, some of these 
data providers have data that are directly 
accessible on the Web. For example, the 
Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS, 
&lt;http://www.abs.gov.au&gt;) has over 1 million 
web pages through which a huge array of past 
and present Census data can be accessed, as 
well as an extensive array of surveys and 
reports related to the Australian population. On 
the other hand, many other national and state-
based agencies do not offer access to their 
'data', preferring instead to release data in 
aggregated forms; for example, as written 
reports. Being able to access and combine 
distributed data from multiple independent and 
autonomous organisations through a unified 
environment would greatly simplify the life of 
many urban researchers and allow major urban 
research challenges to be systematically tack-
led. Ideally, such a solution would offer live 
(programmatic) access to in situ remote data 
resources from the definitive data providers 
and avoid web scraping or other ad hoc data 
collection mechanisms that would break when 
websites and their content change. The solution 
should provide tools to support collection and 
enrichment of provider-specific metadata to 
enable complex data analytics scenarios using 
this diverse ecosystem of data. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
platform has delivered such an integrated, 
data-rich research environment. AURIN is not 
unique in this endeavour and a range of efforts 
is currently ongoing-albeit on a much more 
focused domain; for example, with a fixed or 
known set of data providers. 
The UK Economic and Social Research 
Council-funded Data Management through </p>

<p>e-Social Science project (&lt;http://www.dames. 
org.uk&gt;) developed a variety of specialised 
research environments, through which a range 
of distributed social science datasets and 
associated tools was provisioned, including: 
occupational data resources; educational data 
resources; ethnicity or minority data resources; 
and e-Health data resources (Higgins et al. 
2009). These are used to support specialised 
solutions; for example, in the area of mental 
health, combining data from the UK Census, 
the National Health Service and data from 
geospatial data providers (EDINA) (Birkin et al. 
2010). 
The National e-Infrastructure for Social 
Simulation (&lt;http://www.geog.leeds.ac.uk/ 
projects/neiss/about.php&gt;) project developed 
a portfolio of e-social science solutions that 
allowed researchers to explore a variety of 
what-if urban scenarios, using datasets such as 
the UK Census and the British Household 
Panel Survey combined with real-time data 
such as Twitter. 
A range of efforts has been ongoing to 
harmonise international data resources and 
archives of relevance to urban and built 
environment researchers. Examples of these 
include the European Council for European 
Social Science Data Archives (&lt;http://www. 
cessda.org&gt;) and the EU INSPIRE initiative 
(&lt;http://inspire.ec.europa.eu/&gt;). The Open 
Indicators Consortium initiative (&lt;http:// 
www.oicweave.org&gt;) developed a visualisa-
tion platform for any dataset by anyone. Other 
commerical initiatives, such as www.qgi-
scloud.com and www.giscloud.com, offer 
Cloud-based hosting and visual interfaces to 
user-provided geospatial information system 
(GIS) datasets. These are useful tools for 
sharing GIS data amongst distributed user 
groups or for sharing with the public, but so 
far they do not offer advanced analytical 
capabilities. Furthermore, the interfaces are 
aimed at expert GIS users. 
Across Australia, the Australia National Data 
Service (&lt;http://www.ands.org.au&gt;) has been 
established to help support community-wide 
access to, and use of, research datasets. Core 
services include support for metadata cata-
logues and persistent data object identifiers;°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>however, these are primarily at the metadata 
level only and do not provide live access to 
definitive data from the actual data providers. 
Data storage solutions are now widely available 
across Australia through projects such as the 
Research Data Services (&lt;http://www.rds.edu. 
au&gt;); however, these are technology-supporting 
activities and do not in themselves tackle data 
re-use and integration issues, which are typically 
domain-specific. 
All of these efforts showcase the pace of data 
generation brought about by the rise in the use 
of the Internet and associated technologies. 
This accelerated pace has overtaken the way in 
which researchers are able to discover and 
utilise the ever-expanding volumes of digital 
data. The urban research landscape faces acute 
challenges in this regard due to its heterogene-
ity since urban research can require access to a 
multiplicity of inter-disciplinary datasets. Each 
urban sub-domain (health, transport etc) has its 
own particular demands and knowledge that 
are often as isolated as the datasets themselves. </p>

<p>There is no urban-wide standard format, no 
defined ontology, and as such, a spectrum of 
data use and re-use challenges exist. 
The primary challenges faced by the 
AURIN project were the development of an 
e-infrastructure through which an already 
existing and extensive set of data from a large 
portfolio of organisations could be provisioned 
in a federated manner and ensuring that future 
datasets and tools could be accommodated and 
incorporated into the platform. A distributed, 
Cloud-enabled, and importantly, data-driven 
architecture has been developed to tackle this 
challenge and is described in the following 
section. It is noted that this architecture has 
evolved and been hardened over time with 
different earlier realisations of the platform 
described in detail in Sinnott et al. (2012, 2013) 
and Nino-Ruiz et al. (2014). A simplified 
version of the overall AURIN architecture is 
shown in Figure 1. 
It is important to note that AURIN offers 
single sign-on to all of the datasets, services </p>

<p>Figure 1 Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network (AURIN) Implementation Architecture </p>

<p>Note: NECTAR denotes National eResearch Collaboration Tools and Resources and RDSI denotes Research Data Storage 
Infrastructure. </p>

<p>Source: Sinnott et al. (2012).°C </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
and tools offered by all providers through 
federated authentication to the <rs id="software-3" type="software">AURIN</rs> portal, 
available at &lt;<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">https://portal.aurin.org.au</rs>&gt;; that 
is, users authenticate at their (potentially 
remote) home organisation and are subse-
quently able to access all data without further 
challenge or response demands from any data 
provider. It is important to note that single 
sign-on here does not imply that all data and 
tools are accessible to all users at all times. 
Several data providers place specific demands 
on who can access their data and tools and what 
they can subsequently do with these data. 
The Public Sector Mapping Agency (PSMA, 
&lt;http://www.psma.com.au&gt;) is one example 
of a commercial partner that requires restricted 
usage to their data. It should also be pointed 
out that through the federated authentication 
model, any academic across Australia (that is, 
those with an email address ending in 
'.edu.au') is able to access the portal directly. 
Other non-academics (for example, those from 
industry and government) are able to access the 
portal through targeted accounts that are set up 
through the access federation virtual home 
organisation. </p>

<p>3. Australian Urban Research Infrastructure 
Network: Data Landscape </p>

<p>There are at present (December 2015) 1,661 
datasets that are accessible through the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
platform from 66 separate organisations. These 
data providers and the nature and number of data 
they make available are summarised in Table 1. 
As seen, these datasets cross federal govern-
ment, state government, local government, 
industry and academia. The data shown in 
Table 1 represent the total data that are currently 
available across Australia. However, it is often 
(typically) the case that researchers are interested 
in data related to a particular regional setting; for 
example, transport issues in Melbourne or 
property prices in Sydney. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform 
provides a user-driven interface that allows 
researchers to access data through selecting the 
area of interest through a map-based interface, as 
shown in Figure 2, or through selection of data 
based upon the geospatial aggregation level, as 
shown in Figure 3. </p>

<p>It is important to note that the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
platform provides an extensive variety of 
geospatial coordinate systems that capture 
changes over time. Thus, Figure 2 shows the 
postal areas as defined by the ABS in 2011. A 
different set of polygons for those portal areas 
existed historically-this is the case for the 
many other flavours of geospatial classification 
that exists or has existed across Australia: local 
government areas, statistical local areas, 
working zones, statistical areas (SA4 down 
to SA1) as shown in Figure 3, labour force 
regions, greater capital city areas, statistical 
divisions, urban centre localities, suburbs, 
Commonwealth electronic divisions amongst 
many others. Capturing these changes over 
time is essential for researchers so that they can 
compare meaningful data in meaningful con-
texts. This is especially the case for those 
interested in longitudinal studies of cities. 
The datasets cover an extensive variety of 
information related to Australian urban settle-
ments. As an example of the diversity of the 
information available through the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
platform, searching across a range of keywords 
returns extensive data, as shown in Table 2. It is 
noted that the platform supports a range of 
fuzzy search capabilities; for example, search-
ing for employ will return matching datasets 
with data or metadata including terms such as 
unemployed and employment. 
The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform allows much more 
targeted searching for specific data that might 
be available. Thus, transport researchers might 
be interested in terms such as train (34), tram 
(21), car (79), station (12), bus stop (2), 
accident (31), bicycle (10), pedestrian (4) and 
commute (7), where the numbers in parentheses 
represent the number of datasets that include 
the italicised keywords. 
It is essential that the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform 
supports the access to, and integration of, 
diverse datasets. In supporting access to data, 
it was recognised that each remote data 
provider is autonomous and can make its data 
available through technologies that it deems 
appropriate; that is, AURIN cannot demand 
that the provider install a particular software 
stack. A rich variety of technical solutions has 
been developed and delivered to meet the°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>Table 1 Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network Data Providers 
and Number/Type of Datasets Made Available (December 2015) </p>

<p>Organisation </p>

<p>Federal 
government </p>

<p>State 
government </p>

<p>Local 
government Industry Academia </p>

<p>Australian Energy Market Operator (AEMO) 
2 
Australian Bureau of Statistics (AU_Govt_ABS) 
557 
Australian Children's Education and Care Quality 
Authority (AU_Govt_ACECQA) 
1 
Bureau of Infrastructure, Transport and Regional 
Economics (AU_Govt_BITRE) 
38 
Bureau of Meteorology (AU_Govt_BoM) 
2 
Department of Employment (AU_Govt_DE) 
8 
Department of the Environment (AU_Govt_DotE) 
1 
Geoscience Australia (AU_Govt_GA) 
6 
National Water Commission (AU_Govt_NWC) 
1 
Ausgrid 
1 
Central Highlands Water (CHW) 
1 
City West Water Corporation (CWW) 
1 
Energex 
1 
Ergon 
2 
Energy Supply Association of Australia (ESAA) 
1 
Grattan Institute (GI) 
3 
Griffith University Urban Research Program (GU_URP) 
3 
Internode Pty Ltd (INODE) 
1 
Jemena 
1 
Melbourne Water Corporation (MW) 
6 
National Information and Communications Technology 
Ltd Australia (NICTA) 
6 
New South Wales -Department of Planning and the 
Environment (NSW_Govt_DPE) 
102 
New South Wales Fair Trading (NSW_Govt_FT) 
36 
Public Sector Mapping Agency (PSMA) 
15 
Queensland Department of Natural Resources and Mines 
(QLD_Govt_NRM) 
1 
Queensland Treasury and Trade (QLD_Govt_QTT) 
1 
Queensland Townsville County Council 
(QLD_LGovt_TCC) 
2 
Queensland Smart Transport Research Centre 
(QLD_STRC) 
30 
Regional Australia Institute (RAI) 
10 
South Australia Attorney General's Department 
(SA_Govt_AGD) 
10 
South Australia Department for Communities and Social 
Inclusion (SA_Govt_DCSI) 
11 
South Australia Department for Education and Child 
Development (SA_Govt_DECD) 
1 
South Australia Department of Environment, Water and 
Natural Resources (SA_Govt_DEWNR) 
5 
South Australia Department of Planning, Transport and 
Infrastructure (SA_Govt_DPTI) 
94 
South Australia Department for State Development 
(SA_Govt_DSD) 
1 
South Australia Local Government Association of South 
Australia (SA_Govt_LGA) 
3 
Renewal South Australia (SA_Govt_RenewalSA) 
41 
South Australia Health (SA_Govt_SA_Health) 
5 </p>

<p>Continued°C </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>Organisation </p>

<p>Federal 
government </p>

<p>State 
government </p>

<p>Local 
government Industry Academia </p>

<p>South Australia City of Salisbury (SA_Lgovt_CSC) 
7 
South East Water Corporation (SEW) 
1 
Sydney Water (SW) 
1 
University of Adelaide Australian Population and 
Migration Research Centre (UA_APMRC) 
1 
University of Adelaide Population Health Information 
Development Unit (UA_PHIDU) 
169 
University of Canberra National Centre for Social and 
Economic Modelling (UC_NATSEM) 
25 
University of New South Wales City Futures Research 
Centre (UNSW_CFRC) 
7 
University of Newcastle -Centre of Full Employment 
and Equity (UoN_CofFEE) 
33 
University of Queensland eResearch Group (UQ_ERG) 
38 
University of Queensland -Queensland Centre for 
Population Research (UQ_QCPR) 
3 
Victoria Government Department of Environment, Land, 
Water and Planning (Vic_Govt_DELWP) 
16 
Victoria Government Department of Environment and 
Primary Industries (Vic_Govt_DEPI) 
55 
Victoria Government Department of Education and 
Training (Vic_Govt_DET) 
34 
Victoria Government Department of Human Services 
(Vic_Govt_DHS) 
10 
Victoria Government Department of Health 
(Vic_Govt_DOH) 
3 
Victoria Government Department of State Development, 
Business and Innovation (Vic_Govt_DSDBI) 
10 
Victoria Government Environmental Protection Agency 
(Vic_Govt_EPA) 
3 
Victoria Government Sustainability Victoria 
(Vic_Govt_SV) 
1 
Victoria Government -Victoria Commission for 
Gambling and Liquor Regulation 
(Vic_Govt_VCGLR) 
5 
Government of Victoria VicHealth 
(Vic_Govt_VicHealth) 
42 
Government of Victoria VicRoads 
(Vic_Govt_VicRoads) 
11 
Local Government of Victoria -Brimbank City Council 
(Vic_LGovt_Brimbank) 
5 
Local Government of Victoria -City of Melbourne 
(Vic_LGovt_COM) 
16 
Local Government of Victoria -Hume City Council 
(Vic_LGovt_Hume) 
1 
Local Government of Victoria -Melton City Council 
(Vic_LGovt_Melton) 
3 
Local Government of Victoria -Wyndham City Council 
(Vic_LGovt_Wyndham) 
5 
Western Australia Government Landgate 
(WA_Govt_LGATE) 
144 
Yarra Valley Water (YVW) 
1°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p>214 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>Figure 2 2011 Geospatial Area Selection (Postal Areas) </p>

<p>Source: Australian Bureau of Statistics. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Geospatial Area Selection </p>

<p>Source: Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network.°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
diversity of the urban data ecosystem across 
Australia. Many of these are based around 
geospatial software systems and standards; for 
example, Open Geospatial Consortium stand-
ards (&lt;http://www.opengeospatial.org/ogc&gt;). 
To support the integration of data, the 
platform utilises next-generation Cloud-based 
noSQL systems (<rs type="software">CouchDB</rs>) and associated 
data translation systems. We demonstrate the 
data integration capabilities through a repre-
sentative case study. </p>

<p>4. Case Study </p>

<p>Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas (SEIFA) is 
a product developed by the ABS that ranks 
areas in Australia according to relative socio-
economic advantage and disadvantage. The 
indices are based on information from the 
5 yearly Census. SEIFA 2011 is (at present) 
the latest version of this product and consists 
of four indices. The Index of Relative 
Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage 
(IRSAD) summarises information about 
the economic and social conditions of people 
and households within an area, including 
both relative advantage and disadvantage 
measures. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform provides 
access to the IRSAD data from the ABS-
specifically, the data classified across the SA2s 
across Australia. 
One typical scenario in using the IRSAD 
data is to identify regions facing particular 
challenges regarding disadvantage. Creation 
of a choropleth map through the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> </p>

<p>environment allows visualisation of the levels 
of advantage and disadvantage for all SA2s of 
Australia, as shown in Figure 4. As seen from 
Figure 4, there are areas of particular disad-
vantage in the Northern Territory, South 
Australia and northern Queensland. Here, the 
paler colour represents a lower SEIFA IRSAD 
score and the darker colour represents areas of 
higher scores. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform allows 
arbitrary selection of the classification scales. 
As seen from Figure 4, the table (lower left) 
shows the actual numeric values associated 
with the SEIFA IRSAD score. 
Understanding the issues surrounding SA2s 
with a lower IRSAD score can be explored 
through the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform. Here, we 
consider the number of children in welfare-
dependent or low income families (earning less 
that $20,799), which is available from 
UA_PHIDU. Combining (merging) the SEIFA 
dataset and the UA_PHIDU dataset allows for 
a range of statistical analyses to be undertaken. 
Through selecting data at the SA2 level, these 
datasets can be combined directly (utilising the 
unique codes associated with the SA2s across 
Australia). Once merged, a range of analyses 
can be undertaken. Here, we consider a basic 
linear regression, although we note that the 
<rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform contains over 100 analytical 
tools that are available for richer geospatial 
analytics. These tools are outlined in Sinnott 
and Voorsluys (2015). 
Figure 5 shows the correlation between the 
SEIFA IRSAD score and the number of lower 
income or welfare-dependent families in the 
SA2s across Australia. It is noted that the 
<rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform enforces intelligent decision-
making where it can; for example, by checking 
that the datasets that are joined are at the same 
geospatial aggregation level (SA2). Outliers in 
these correlations (for example, areas with low 
SEIFA scores or areas with large numbers of 
children in welfare-dependent or low income 
families) can be seen directly. What is key here 
is that these are independent datasets from 
independent organisations that hitherto have not 
allowed direct comparison. Instead, researchers 
typically have to source these datasets them-
selves through ad hoc means and undertake such 
analysis using a range of tools. </p>

<p>Table 2 Volume and Variety of the Australian 
Urban Research Infrastructure Network Data </p>

<p>Search term </p>

<p>Number of datasets from data providers 
with the corresponding matching data </p>

<p>Economy 
123 
Industry 
74 
Education 
74 
Transport 
128 
Health 
157 
Population 
347 
Crime 
14 
Business 
49 
Employment 
120 
Indigenous 
28°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>A further analysis that might be considered 
is the SEIFA IRSAD score and the percentage 
of 16 year olds in secondary college; that is, do 
we observe more people leaving school earlier 
in more disadvantaged areas? This dataset is 
also available from UA_PHIDU. Using the 
<rs type="software">AURIN</rs> tools to merge the datasets and analyse 
the data, we see the correlation shown in 
Figure 6. The data points in the lower-left 
portion of the scatter plot represent those SA2s 
with a low SEIFA IRSAD score and lower 
school-leaving age. 
Figure 4 shows that many of the disadvan-
tages arise in areas with increased numbers of 
Indigenous persons. A further dimension to 
this analysis is to explore the correlation 
between the poor health of the Indigenous 
communities and the SEIFA IRSAD score. </p>

<p>Information on the health of the Indigenous 
population is available from UC_NATSEM. 
The correlation between the SEIFA IRSAD 
score and poor-health information of the 
Indigenous population of Australia is shown 
in Figure 7. Figure 7 also shows the interactive, 
user-oriented nature of the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> portal. 
Thus, the outlier in the scatter plot is shown 
(in red) along with the location (East Arnhem) 
on the map (top). This interactivity of the 
underlying data is key to helping support the 
advanced visual analytics of the urban data 
landscape. 
The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform supports rich spatial 
data analytics capabilities. One scenario of 
interest is whether areas of advantage 
and/or disadvantage tend to cluster together 
geospatially. As one example of a spatial </p>

<p>Figure 4 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Score for the SA2s of Australia and Visualisation through the Choropleth Map </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage, SA denotes statistical area and 
SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Source: Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network.°C </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
autocorrelation tool, Moran's I supports com-
parison of similarity in location with similarity 
in attribute values (Sinnott 2015). Here, 
similarity of location is based upon the sharing </p>

<p>of a boundary with a given SA2; that is, here we 
seek to explore whether SA2s that share a 
boundary with other SA2s share similar SEIFA 
scores. </p>

<p>Figure 5 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Score versus Children in Welfare-Dependent/Low Income Families </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage and SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic 
Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Sources: SEIFA IRSAD score is from Australian Bureau of Statistics and Welfare-Dependent/Low Income Families is from 
UA_PHIDU, Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network. </p>

<p>Figure 6 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Score versus Percentage of 16 Year Olds in Secondary School </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage and SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic 
Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Sources: SEIFA IRSAD score is from Australian Bureau of Statistics and Welfare-Dependent/Low Income Families is from 
UA_PHIDU, Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network.°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>To support these analyses, it is necessary to 
spatialise (add the geometry) to the SA2s and 
calculate their contiguous spatial weights; that 
is, count SA2s if they share a border or a corner 
with other SA2s. The range of possible 
Moran's I values is between -1 and 1. An 
estimate of 0 implies no spatial autocorrelation 
exists. For a significant estimate, the closer it 
gets to 1, the greater the degree of positive 
spatial autocorrelation, while the closer it 
is to -1, the stronger the negative spatial 
autocorrelation. 
Applying the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> statistical analysis 
tools to the 2011 SEIFA IRSAD scores for 
the SA2s of Australia produces the spatial 
autocorrelation scores shown in Figure 8. As 
shown, there is a slight correlation between the 
spatial correlation (0.1922) of the 2011 SEIFA 
IRSAD scores and the SA2s of Australia. 
A Moran scatter plot is used to visualise and 
identify the degree of local spatial instability in 
spatial association that is present in the Moran's 
I statistic. The scatter plot is useful in identifying 
those observations that do not conform; that is, 
they differ significantly from the global Moran's 
I in magnitude and/or direction. </p>

<p>The scatter plot centres on the point where 
the mean of the variable meets the mean 
of the lagged variable and the four quadrants of 
the plot relative to this point give information 
about the type of association that is present. 
The upper-right and lower-left quadrants 
shown in Figure 9 represent positive spatial 
association, while the upper-left and lower-
right quadrants show those observations that 
have negative spatial association. The density 
of each of the quadrants indicates which spatial 
pattern dominates and also provides informa-
tion on the distribution of the individual spatial 
associations and the contribution of each to the 
global statistic. Furthermore, the plot shows 
outliers and leverage points and can provide an 
overall picture of the consistency of the global 
indicator. 
Moran's I is just one of the more advanced 
spatial statistical correlations that are available in 
the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform. These tools represent best 
practice in statistical analyses. Detailed docu-
mentation on all of these tools is available 
through the AURIN website (&lt;http://docs.aurin. 
org.au&gt;), together with a range of advanced 
tutorials covering which analyses should be </p>

<p>Figure 7 Indigenous Health and 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Score </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage and SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic 
Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Sources: SEIFA IRSAD score is from Australian Bureau of Statistics and Indigenous health is from National Centre for 
Social and Economic Modelling.°C </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
Figure 9 Moran's I Scatter Plot of the 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Scores for the SA2s of Australia </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage, SA denotes statistical area and 
SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Source: Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network. </p>

<p>Figure 8 Moran's I Spatial Correlation of the 2011 SEIFA IRSAD Scores for the SA2s of Australia </p>

<p>Note: IRSAD denotes Index of Relative Socio-Economic Advantage and Disadvantage, SA denotes statistical area and 
SEIFA denotes Socio-Economic Indexes for Areas. </p>

<p>Source: Australian Urban Research Infrastructure Network.°C </p>

<p>2016 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>

<p>applied in which context. Such capabilities allow 
more advanced analyses to be made available to 
non-spatial statistics experts. 
It is noted that whilst many researchers 
derive great benefit from the rich variety of 
tools that is available within the portal, some 
researchers prefer to simply have access to the 
AURIN datasets and download them to their 
own desktop to undertake their own desktop-
based analytics; for example, using tools such 
as <rs type="software">ArcGIS</rs>, <rs type="software">STATA</rs> or <rs type="software">SPSS</rs>. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
portal supports the download of data in 
comma-separated-variable format, Javascript 
Object Notation and as Shapefiles. The 
platform also supports the notion of projects 
and a range of separate experiments can be 
supported. 
The platform also allows researchers to 
upload their own data and compare or analyse 
their datasets with other datasets that are made 
available through the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> environment. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>In this article, we described the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> 
e-infrastructure and its support for diverse 
data use/re-use and integration scenarios. 
The system currently supports seamless and 
secure access to data from, at present, 66 
independent and typically definitive and auton-
omous data organisations across Australia, 
with over 1,661 unique datasets currently 
accessible. These cover unit-level datasets 
through to aggregated data across a multitude 
of scales (both temporal and spatial). These 
systems are driven by metadata with tools to 
support data harvesting and subsequent enrich-
ment by data providers. The AURIN model of 
data access, use/re-use and integration 
has already demonstrated its flexibility and 
scaleability, with new data sources being 
continually added with minimal impact on 
the underlying infrastructure. 
The work described here has primarily 
focused on the technical aspects of the 
e-infrastructure and exemplar uses. It should 
be noted that the systems have gained signifi-
cant traction across the urban research land-
scape, and interestingly, in government, with 
many government agencies now accessing and </p>

<p>using the systems for their own needs. There 
have been over 50,000 user sessions in 
accessing the <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform, with major 
acceptance by academic and non-academic 
users. There are over 3,000 regular users of the 
<rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform. 
The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform is very much focused 
on urban and built environment research 
challenges, but it is broadly applicable to other 
domains of application. For example, it is now 
used as the basis for a range of other new 
projects including the Department of the 
Environment's $8.8 million Clean Air and 
Urban Landscapes initiative. 
This article has focused upon the openly 
accessible aggregate data; however, many 
urban researchers face considerable challenges 
in accessing disaggregated (unit-level) data-
sets. The <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform has capabilities 
for secure data access and usage. These are 
described in more detail in Ma (2015). 
Furthermore, many researchers require access 
to real-time information on the state of cities. 
Social media is one example of data that can 
capture what is happening in cities at any given 
time. Future work on <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> will include data 
from organisations such as Twitter. 
Future work on <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> involves the 
extension of the platform to include more 
datasets, and importantly, more recent datasets; 
for example, the 2016 Census. Work is also 
ongoing in supporting an open application 
programming interface for direct program-
matic access to the data and tools within the 
platform. Initial prototyping of mobile appli-
cations has already commenced in both the <rs type="software">iOS</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Android</rs> platforms (Moran 1950; Zhang 
2015). 
One of the challenges facing <rs type="software">AURIN</rs> is its 
longer term sustainability. In 2015, the project 
faced challenges due to the economic uncer-
tainty of the national funding landscape. As a 
result, certain commercial (fee-for-use) data-
sets, such as the Fairfax Australian Property 
Monitor housing data, had to be withdrawn due 
to lack of funds. These datasets were amongst 
the most widely accessed and used within the 
<rs type="software">AURIN</rs> platform. Despite the obvious uptake 
of the platform by the research community and 
technical sophistication of the solution, such°C </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
funding issues remain a challenge of long-term 
sustainability going forward. </p>

<p>January 2016 </p>



<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
June 2016 </p>



<p>Sinnott and AURIN Technical Team: Australian Data-Driven Urban Research Platform </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>