<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1086%2F654078" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>What is the source of business cycle fluctuations? Most theories take the 
answer to this question to be axiomatic. The essence of Keynesian theories 
is that in the short-run the willingness of agents to absorb the output of the 
economy determines the quantity of output produced. On the other hand, 
classical and new classical theories do not allow the possibility that output 
can deviate from capacity, except for very short intervals. In these theories, 
prices and rates of return adjust so that a change in aggregate demand does 
not cause output to change. Here, we attempt to quantify the sources of 
economic fluctuations by making minimal and plausible identifying restric-
tions that do not depend on a theory of the business cycle. 
Standard textbook treatments of macroeconomic fluctuations separate 
the high frequency, business cycle fluctuations from the low frequency, 
growth fluctuations. This dichotomy lies at the heart of most Keynesian 
and rational expectations models.1 In these models, shocks to aggregate 
demand temporarily move the economy away from some "full-em-
ployment" "potential," or "natural" level of output. The natural level of 
output is determined by the capital stock, the labor force, and technology 
in long-run equilibrium.2 These supply-side factors are assumed to be 
independent of the business cycle phenomenon. This dichotomy, which is </p>

<p>1. Textbook treatments of Keynesian economics treat business cycles as fluctuations around a 
long-term deterministic trend. Sophisticated Keynesian macroeconometric models, such as 
the Fair model, incorporate a production function that determines output in the long-run. 
Rational expectations with misperceptions models of the cycle (Lucas, 1973) also have 
monetary impulses that move output temporarily from a trend level. 
2. In Milton Friedman's (1968) words, the natural rate is "ground out by the Walrasian system 
of general equilibrium equations" (p. 8) even if unexpected monetary disturbances move 
output in the short-run (p. 9). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>central to the neoclassical synthesis, superimposes business cycles as 
short-run disequilibrium phenomena on an economy in long-run equilib-
rium. 
This business cycle/growth dichotomy has been vitiated by new research 
on two fronts. First, research on the time series properties of main 
economic aggregates indicates that output can be characterized as follow-
ing an integrated process.3 Extracting the long-run trend from data gener-
ated by integrated process cannot be accomplished by simple regression 
detrending methods. Auxiliary assumptions concerning the covariation of 
the trend and cyclical components of the data are necessary. Once cova-
riation of the trend and cyclical components is allowed, the rationale for 
detrending loses much of its appeal. 
Second, some recent theories of macroeconomic fluctuations attribute all 
of the variability in output to real factors.4 These real business cycle theories 
account for fluctuations at all frequencies by the same shock. There is, then, 
no meaningful dichotomy between the short-run and the long-run. 
In this paper, we take seriously the message of these challenges to the 
neoclassical synthesis; shocks that move the economy at business cycles 
frequencies may also affect the economy in the long-run. Indeed, we use 
economic theory about the long-run impacts of different shocks to identify 
our model. Yet, we do not take this challenge to its extreme. Specifically, 
we do not maintain that all fluctuations in output are attributable to growth 
shocks. To the contrary, we view fluctuations as arising from a mixture of 
shocks; our goal is to disentangle these shocks. 
The key identifying restriction underlying our empirical work is the 
simple, but powerful assumption made by Blanchard and Quah (1988), 
which we state as: </p>

<p>The level of output is determined in the long-run by supply shocks, such as shocks 
to technology and labor supply. </p>

<p>This identifying assumption does not exclude the possibility that these 
shocks also account for the high frequency movements in output as they 
would, for example, in a real business cycle model. It also does not exclude 
the possibility that short-run fluctuations are largely explained by aggre-
gate demand shocks, such as shocks to the money supply or velocity, or by 
shocks to fiscal policy or animal spirits. It only excludes the possibility that 
the aggregate demand shocks permanently affect the level of output. The 
assumption allows the data to choose a description closer to the Keynesian </p>

<p>3. See Nelson and Plosser (1982) and Campbell and Mankiw (1987a). 
4. See Kydland and Prescott (1982), Long and Plosser (1983), and Prescott (1986). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
113 </p>

<p>view, in which fluctuations are predominantly transitory, or fit a descrip-
tion closer to the real business cycle view, in which fluctuations are largely 
the result of permanent shocks.5 
In the next section of the paper, we sketch the economic model that 
guides our empirical analysis. In Section 3, we give the precise econometric 
specification. We present our findings in Section 4 and offer concluding 
remarks in Section 5. </p>

<p>2. Model </p>

<p>Our econometric specification is motivated by a model in which the 
long-run properties of real variables are determined by a simple neoclassi-
cal growth model. In this model, long-run movements in output can be 
attributed entirely to exogenous changes in labor input and technological 
progress. In the short-run, output may deviate from its long-run steady 
state value. These deviations may arise from shocks to the permanent 
levels of labor input and technology, which lead to a transition from one 
steady state to another, or they may be caused by aggregate demand 
disturbances. Hence, movements in output arise from three sources: labor 
supply disturbances, technological disturbances, and aggregate demand 
disturbances. The first two of these-the supply shocks-have a perma-
nent effect on the level of output; the third has only a temporary effect. 
Interest rates and the rate of inflation are also included in the empirical 
model. All three sources of shocks are allowed to have both long-run and 
short-run effects on the level of inflation and the level of the nominal 
interest rate, but not on the real interest rate. 
Two identifying assumptions allow us to separate these three sources of 
shocks from a dynamic reduced form, which includes labor input, output, 
inflation, and nominal interest rates. The first was alluded to above, 
aggregate demand disturbances have no long-run effect on output. This 
assumption allows us to determine the historical influence of aggregate 
demand and aggregate supply on the variables in the model. The second 
identifying restriction is that the long-run level of labor supply is exoge-
nous. This assumption allows us to divide the aggregate supply effect into </p>

<p>5. Blanchard and Quah (1988) use this assumption in a bivariate model of output and 
unemployment. They assume that output is integrated, but that unemployment is 
stationary, and that supply shocks are responsible for the stochastic growth component of 
output. Other researchers have relied on the distinction between permanent and transitory 
shocks for identification. Campbell and Mankiw (1987b) identify long-run movements in 
output as the part of output orthogonal to unemployment changes. King, et al. (1987) 
identify the long-run movement in output as the common long-run component in output, 
consumption, and investment. Blanchard (1986) analyses a model where the identifying 
assumption is long-run homogeneity of demand schedules. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>the components arising from labor input and from technology. In the 
long-run, labor supply is influenced neither by aggregate demand nor by 
the level of technology. We could relax this assumption to allow permanent 
real wage growth to affect labor supply, but doing so would only affect the 
decomposition of the permanent supply component into labor supply and 
technology. The decomposition between supply and demand would not be 
affected. 
In standard models of long-term growth, the shocks to technology and 
labor supply together with capital accumulation determine the level of 
output in the long-run. Suppose that labor supply and technology evolve 
according to </p>

<p>h = h + h~ + Oh(L)vt (2.1) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>E = 8 ? </p>

<p>-t1 </p>

<p>+ O8(L)et (2.2) </p>

<p>where uF and hf are the log levels of technology and labor supply and 
where vt and et are serially and mutually uncorrelated shocks. The lag 
polynomials Oh(L) and O~(L) are assumed to have absolutely summable 
coefficients and roots outside the unit circle. That is, the dynamics de-
scribed by the polynomials are transitory.6 
We define the long-run log level of output y* as </p>

<p>yt= ahI + (1-a) kt + EF (2.3) </p>

<p>where kt is the long-run level of capital. That is, we assume that the 
production function is Cobb-Douglas in the long-run. Yet, as shown below, 
we allow output to deviate in the short-run from this relationship. 
We now introduce our first restriction from economic theory by assum-
ing that the steady state capital-output ratio is a constant </p>

<p>k*t = y + r (2.4) </p>

<p>where q is the constant log capital-output ratio. The Solow-Swan7 growth </p>

<p>model would generate a constant 7q, which is a function of hr, 6E, and the </p>

<p>6. Unless otherwise stated, all of the lag polynomials that we use in this paper will have these 
properties. Thus, they will always give rise to transitory dynamics. Where necessary we 
will invert them. 
7. Solow (1956) and Swan (1956). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
115 </p>

<p>economy's saving and depreciation rates. Substituting (2.4) into (2.3) and 
rearranging yields </p>

<p>y* = h* + (1/a) cE (2.5) </p>

<p>where the constant 77(1 -a)/a is suppressed. </p>

<p>If we were willing to identify yt and h* with the actual log levels of output 
and labor, the equations above would define a real business cycle model 
with a much simpler propagation mechanism for the shocks than, for 
example, Kydland and Prescott's (1982). We close our model, however, by 
adding aggregate demand disturbances that allow output and inputs to 
deviate temporarily from their long-run levels. 
To allow output and labor to move independently of the labor and 
productivity shocks in the short-run, we introduce two aggregate demand 
shocks, denoted by vt and vt. These can be thought of as goods market (IS) 
and money market (LM) shocks. They are assumed to be serially uncorre-
lated and uncorrelated with the growth shocks. We cannot disentangle 
these shocks. Reasonable specifications of the goods and money market do 
not restrict just one of these shocks to affect the price level in the long-run. 
Both labor input, ht, and output, Yt, can deviate temporarily from their 
long-run values because of these aggregate demand shocks, or because of 
transitory adjustments to permanent labor and or technology shocks.8 
Namely, </p>

<p>ht 
= h* + Sh(L) [vt et v: ]' (2.6) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>Yt = Y&gt; </p>

<p>+ ,y(L) [vt et vi ]'. (2.7) </p>

<p>The dependence of ht on all of the shocks in the model allows flexible 
responses of labor to aggregate demand and real wages. Equation (2.6) 
allows labor supply to be elastic in the short-run. Indeed, in the short-run, 
workers can be off their labor supply schedules. Output and hours can 
deviate from their long-run levels as they would in a wide range of models, 
such as the inflation-augmented Phillips curve, the Lucas supply model, or 
the Fischer-Taylor contract model. Moreover, equations (2.6) and (2.7) 
break the tight link between output and inputs so that "off the production </p>

<p>8. Tobin's (1955) dynamic aggregative model is the first to superimpose a business cycle model 
on a neoclassical growth model. It features wage inflexibility as the source of cyclical 
fluctuations. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>116 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>function" behavior or labor hoarding can be captured in the estimates. We 
only assume that the production function holds in the long-run (equation </p>

<p>2.3). </p>

<p>Differencing (2.6) and (2.7) and applying (2.1) and (2.2) yields </p>

<p>Aht 
= Oh(L)vt + (1 -L)Bh(L) [vt et vt]' (2.8) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>Ayt = O,(L)vt </p>

<p>+ a -le(L)Et + (1 -L),Y(L) [vt et g vt]' (2.9) </p>

<p>which are two of the reduced form equations that we estimate.9 
To complete the model we add equations describing the inflation rate 
and the nominal interest rate. The inflation reduced form is </p>

<p>A Tt = ,(L) [vt et v t]', (2.10) </p>

<p>which implies that the rate of inflation is integrated, its first difference is 
stationary, and that all of the shocks can have a long-run effect on the level 
of inflation. 
Equations (2.3) and (2.4) imply that the long-run real interest rate is 
constant. Shocks to the system can have only short-run effects on the real 
rate, so the real rate is stationary. Given the definition of the real interest 
rate as the difference between the nominal interest rate and the expected 
inflation rate, the restriction on the real rate implies a restriction on the joint 
behavior of the nominal interest rate it and the inflation rate. Specifically, 
the nominal interest rate and the inflation rate are cointegrated, leading to 
the reduced form </p>

<p>it -Tt= ,i(L) [vt e, v ]. (2.11) </p>

<p>Summarizing, the model can be written as </p>

<p>9. Here, and for the remainder of the paper, constant terms are suppressed. They are included 
in the estimated equations. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
? 
117 </p>

<p>Aht 
vt </p>

<p>AYt = A(L) 
et 
(2.12) </p>

<p>LA7Tt 
Vt </p>

<p>it -at 
rt </p>

<p>The matrix polynomial A(L) is a function of the polynomials wh(L), Wy(L), 
7r(L), i(L), Oh(l), and Oy(L) appearing in (2.8) through (2.11). Our 
identifying restrictions can be written in terms of the long-run multipliers, 
that is, the elements of A(1). Setting the lag operator L equal to one in (2.8) 
and (2.9) shows that the long-run multiplier from v, and 
vt 
to ht and Yt are 
zero, and that the long-run multiplier from et to ht is zero. Consequently, 
the matrix of long-run multipliers A(1) is lower block triangular, i.e. </p>

<p>all 0 0 0 </p>

<p>a21 a22 0 0 </p>

<p>A(1) = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>(2.13) </p>

<p>a31 a32 a33 a34 </p>

<p>.a41 a42 a43 a44. </p>

<p>Because we place no restrictions on a3 the identification scheme we 
employ cannot be used to separate the two aggregate demand shocks.10 We 
report only their joint impact in our empirical analysis. 
The model summarized in (2.12) and (2.13) might reasonably character-
ize aggregate hours, output, inflation, and interest rates, were it not for the 
large oil shocks that occurred in the 1970s and 1980s. We introduce 
exogenous oil price changes into our model. Below, we support this 
specification for oil shocks. We also assume that oil price changes have no 
long-run effect on labor supply, which is consistent with our assumption 
that there are no wealth effects in labor supply. Oil prices are allowed to 
have a permanent effect on all of the other variables in the model. Denoting 
the change in real oil prices by </p>

<p>Aot = t (2.14) </p>

<p>the model becomes </p>

<p>10. With conventional exclusion restrictions, which we adjure in this paper, one could identify 
these shocks. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Aht 1 
vt </p>

<p>Aot 
&amp;t </p>

<p>Ayt 
= C(L) et (2.15) </p>

<p>it-"Iit 
.l </p>

<p>where C(1) retains the lower block triangular structure of A(1). 
We estimate equations (2.15) and discuss the results in Section 4. Before 
proceeding to that discussion, we give details in the next section of the 
econometric method and specification. </p>

<p>3. Econometric Method and Specification </p>

<p>In this section, we present the precise form of our estimated equations and 
discuss how we impose the identifying restrictions introduced in the last 
section. These restrictions are a combination of covariance restrictions and 
restrictions on long-run multipliers. There are several equivalent methods 
for imposing these identifying restrictions. We discuss a simple instrumen-
tal variables approach. 
We assume that the C(L) in equation (2.15) is invertible, so that it can be 
written as </p>

<p>D(L) Xt = rot (3.1) </p>

<p>where D(L) = C(L)-1, Xt is the 5 x 1 vector (Aht, Aot, Ayt, A t, it --rrt)' and </p>

<p>wt is the vector of disturbances (vt, 45, et, vg, 't)'. Following the assumptions </p>

<p>made in Section 2, we assume that the roots of ID(z)l are outside the unit 
circle and that o, is vector white noise. Our goal in the empirical analysis is 
to use the observed data to estimate the disturbances wo and the moving 
average polynomial C(L). To do so, we appeal to identifying assumptions 
derived from the model in Section 2. The classical approach to the 
identification problem is to impose exclusion restrictions in the equations 
so that "endogenous" variables have no effect on "exogenous" variables, 
and specific exogenous variables affect some, but not all of the endogenous 
variables. Criticisms of these restrictions are well known. In rational 
expectations models, restrictions across the coefficients in D(L) and cova-
riance restrictions on the matrix of structural disturbances are used to 
identify the model. These restrictions typically impose tight constraints on 
the dynamics of the model. 
In "structural" VAR approaches (Bernanke (1986), Blanchard and Wat-
son (1986), or Sims (1986)), the dynamics of the model are left uncon-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
? 
119 </p>

<p>strained and identification is achieved by imposing constraints on 
contemporaneous relations of the data through D(O) and the covariance 
matrix of ot. These restrictions are similar to the classical exclusion 
restrictions and are often difficult to justify on a priori grounds. 
An alternative identification scheme is used by Blanchard and Quah </p>

<p>(1988).11 They constrain D(1), the long-run multipliers, as well as the </p>

<p>covariance matrix of ot, to identify the model. We use this approach in our 
empirical analysis. In particular, we use the block lower triangular structure 
of D(1) (inherited from C(1)), together with the assumption that the supply 
shocks vt, et, and ?t are mutually uncorrelated with each other and 
uncorrelated with the demand disturbances, to identify the supply distur-
bances, the impulse response functions of these disturbances, and a linear 
combination of the demand disturbances. To this end, we write the first 
equation of (3.1), the equation for Aht as </p>

<p>P P P </p>

<p>aht = </p>

<p>P hh,jAht-j + E Pho,jAot-j + 1 8hy,jyt-_j </p>

<p>j=1 
j=O 
ji= </p>

<p>P 
P 
+ E 8h.iAAit-j </p>

<p>+ E 8hij,(it-i -Tt-i) + vt. (3.2) </p>

<p>j=o 
j=o </p>

<p>Since D(1) is the lower triangular, the long-run multipliers from Aot, AYt, </p>

<p>Art7, and it -n to Aht are zero, so the coefficients of their lags each sum to 
zero. Imposing these constraints yields </p>

<p>p 
p-1 
p-1 </p>

<p>Aht = </p>

<p>8 hh,jAht-_j </p>

<p>+ 
Yho,jA2t-_j 
+ 
Yhy,jA2Yt-j </p>

<p>j=1 
j=O 
j=O </p>

<p>p-1 
p-1 
+ Y ,Yhr,jA27rt-j + ? </p>

<p>Yhiij(Ait-j -A Tt-j) + Vt (3.3) </p>

<p>j=O 
j=O </p>

<p>so that only differences of Aot, Ayt, Awt, and it -wt enter the equation. </p>

<p>Clearly, equation (3.3) cannot be estimated by ordinary least squares, since 
it includes contemporaneous values of some of the regressors, which are 
correlated with vt. We estimate the equation by instrumental variables 
using lags one through p of Aht, Ayt, Art, it -ivt, and lags zero through p </p>

<p>11. A closely related identification procedure is employed in King, et al. (1987). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
. 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>of Aot as instruments. The current value of &amp;o, can be used because it is 
exogenous. 
Similarly, the equation for Ay, is specified as </p>

<p>P 
P 
p </p>

<p>AYt </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>yh,jAht-j + 
! yo,jAot-j </p>

<p>+ + </p>

<p>Iyy,jAyt-j </p>

<p>j=1 
j=O 
j=1 </p>

<p>p-1 
p-1 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-
YyijA2Tt-j + E </p>

<p>yi,j(Ait-j-A 't-j) </p>

<p>+ ?yvvt + et (3.4) </p>

<p>j=o 
j=o </p>

<p>where the differences of Anat 
and it -r are included in the equation to </p>

<p>impose the constraint that the long-run multipliers from r, and i, -at </p>

<p>to </p>

<p>Ayt are zero. Equation (3.4) can be estimated using the same set of 
instruments as (3.3) plus, vt, the estimated residual for (3.3). Recall that vt 
is uncorrelated with et. The instrumental variables procedure makes their 
sample analogues uncorrelated by construction. 
The equations estimated for r and it -7rT are reduced forms. They are </p>

<p>P P P </p>

<p>A rt = </p>

<p>P, ih,ht-i + E 3,o,Aot-i + E P3ry,jAyt-j </p>

<p>j=1 
j=O 
j=1 </p>

<p>p 
p </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>PrAt-j + 
Pri(it rt-j) </p>

<p>j=1 
j=1 </p>

<p>+ 37roVt 
+ 3,reet </p>

<p>+ aI (3.5) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>it -</p>

<p>th,EjAht-</p>

<p>= </p>

<p>hot--</p>

<p>+ E f31,oyj </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>j 
+E </p>

<p>iy,jAyt-j </p>

<p>j=1 
j=O 
j=1 </p>

<p>P 
P </p>

<p>+ 1 Pi3,AlTt-j + 1 
:_(iti 
-r-j) </p>

<p>j=1 
j=1 </p>

<p>+ PivVt + Pieet + at2. (3.6) </p>

<p>The error terms at and at are linear combinations of the structural aggregate 
demand shocks v1 and v2. Since these disturbances are uncorrelated with </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
121 </p>

<p>the regressors, equations (3.5) and (3.6) can be estimated by ordinary least 
squares. We include the estimated v, and et in equations (3.5) and (3.6) as </p>

<p>regressors and instruments; the estimated a' and af are by construction </p>

<p>uncorrelated with those estimated supply shocks.12 
Finally, oil prices are exogenous, so they are simply specified as </p>

<p>Aot = t. (3.7) </p>

<p>All equations include constant terms. The results from estimating (3.3) 
through (3.7) are the subject of the next section.13 </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. DATA </p>

<p>The variables considered in our model are total hours worked (ht), output </p>

<p>(yt), inflation (rr,), the nominal interest rate (it), and real oil prices (or). The 
Appendix gives the details of the sources of the data. Estimates reported in 
this paper are based on quarterly U.S. data from 1951:1. Data before 1951 
are used as initial conditions in autoregressions. The end of the sample 
period is discussed below. The data for labor hours, output, and price are 
for the nonfarm private economy, excluding housing. We choose output 
for the nonfarm, non-housing private sector, rather than the whole 
economy because there are serious conceptual difficulties in relating the 
output to the inputs of housing, government, and farms. Housing and 
government are imputed in the national accounts. Farmers are largely </p>

<p>12. In the <rs type="software">RATS</rs> packages, the equations can be estimated without including the disturbances 
and then transformed via the standard Cholesky decomposition. This decomposition 
picks out a different linear combination of the aggregate demand shocks, but since only 
their joint effect is identified, this difference is inessential. 
13. Blanchard and Quah (1988) use a different technique to estimate models subject to these 
long-run Wold causal orderings. They estimate the unrestricted vector autoregression for 
X, and then transform the system by post-multiplying the VAR by a matrix that imposes 
the necessary restrictions on the long-run multipliers and the residual covariance matrix. 
There is unique matrix that simultaneously diagonalizes the VAR innovation covariance 
matrix and triangularizes the matrix of long-run multipliers. When the only constraints on 
the system are a lower triangular matrix of long-run multipliers and a diagonal innovation 
covariance matrix, the model is just-identified, and this procedure can be thought of as 
"indirect least squares." The instrumental variable approach that we outline can be 
thought of as two stage least squares. When the model is just-identified, these two 
estimation methods produce identical estimators and are equivalent to the FIML estima-
tor. The model that we estimate is overidentified. In particular, oil prices are assumed to 
be strictly exogenous, and this imposes overidentifying restrictions. These overidentifying 
restrictions are easy to impose in our instrumental variable approach, but are much more 
difficult to impose in the indirect least squares approach. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>self-employed, so measures of their hours of work are unreliable. More-
over, studying the nonfarm business sector allows us to abstract from the 
major changes in aggregate labor productivity caused by workers leaving 
farms.14 </p>

<p>4.2. DATA ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Our modelling and estimation strategy depends critically on the correct 
differencing of our time series. In Table 1 we present a variety of unit root 
test statistics that underlie our choice of specification. In the top panel we 
present the familiar Dickey-Fuller t-statistics, which test for a root of unity, 
versus a root less than unity. In the next column we present the largest 
estimated root from a sixth order autoregression, denoted by ^. In the 
hours, output, and productivity regressions we included a time trend in the 
autoregression to eliminate deterministic drift in these series. The t-
statistics for hours, output, labor productivity, inflation, and interest rates 
are far less extreme than the 10 percent critical values. The estimated values 
of 
^ 
are less than unity, but under the null hypothesis of a unit root, these 
estimates have a substantial negative bias. As pointed out in Schwert 
(1987), this bias is particularly severe when the first differences of the data 
have a large moving average component. Such moving average compo-
nents might explain the small value of P for inflation. 
Unit root tests cannot be performed on the unobserved ex ante real 
interest rate; we present results for the ex post real rate. Since the null 
hypothesis of a unit root in the ex ante real rate implies a unit root in the ex 
post real rate, little is lost in this substitution. The results for the ex post real 
interest rate i, -rt,1 are qualitatively different from the results for the 
other variables. The Dickey-Fuller t-statistic is much closer to the 10 percent 
critical value (its p-value is approximately 12 percent), and the estimated 
value of p is only 0.81. Thus, there is stronger evidence supporting the </p>

<p>hypothesis that the real rate is stationary than there is supporting the 
hypothesis that the other variables are stationary. 
In the bottom panel of the table we present the multivariate unit root </p>

<p>tests developed in Stock and Watson (1987). The first statistic, 
Qf4,3), 
tests 
the null hypothesis of 4 versus 3 unit roots among the four variables ht, Yt, </p>

<p>r~r, and it. The null of four unit roots is strongly rejected: the p-value of the </p>

<p>test is 0.3 percent. The data, therefore, appear to be cointegrated. The next 
statistic, Qf3,2) tests for 3 versus 2 unit roots in the four variable system. 
Here the data are consistent with the null of 3 unit roots: the p-value for the </p>

<p>test is 85 percent. Thus, there appears to be only one cointegrating </p>

<p>relationship among the data. </p>

<p>14. See Denison, 1974, pp. 62-4. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations * 123 </p>

<p>In summary, these results suggest that ht, Yt, y, -ht, rwt, and it each 
contain a unit root, that there is one cointegrating relationship, and that the 
stationary linear combination of the data is it -"at, implying a stationary 
real interest rate. Recall that stationarity of the real interest rate is one of the 
restrictions imposed on the data by our neoclassical model of long-term 
growth. 
Unit root tests never provide sharp discrimination between the unit root 
hypothesis and the hypothesis that the data are stationary, but highly 
serially correlated. It is possible, especially in the case of inflation, that we 
are making a type two error by falsely accepting the null of a unit root, or 
in the case of the real rate, making a type one error by falsely rejecting the 
null. The univariate results for the nominal interest rate suggest that either 
inflation or the real rate has a root very close to unity. If the large root is less 
than one, then an expectations theory of the term structure suggests that 
interest rates should become more stationary (that is, have smaller AR(1) 
coefficients) as the term increases. But, interest rates do not get more 
stationary as the term increases. The values of i for 6-month, 1-year, 5-year, 
10-year, and 20-year nominal Federal interest rates vary between 0.96 and 
0.98. The conclusion is that either inflation or the real rate has a unit root. 
Our data analysis, together with our priors, leads us to accept the unit root 
in inflation and reject the unit root in the real rate. </p>

<p>Table 1 UNIT ROOT DESCRIPTIVE STATISTICS </p>

<p>A. Univariate Unit Root Tests </p>

<p>Dickey-Fuller 
Series 
t-statistic </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>h, 
-2.71 
.93 
Yt 
-2.47 
.93 </p>

<p>yt-ht </p>

<p>-0.99 
.98 </p>

<p>"at 
-1.96 
.85 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>-1.84 
.96 
it 
-t +1 
-2.48 
.81 </p>

<p>B. Multivariate Unit Root Tests </p>

<p>Four Variable System: ht, Yt, rt', it </p>

<p>4 vs. 3 Unit Roots 
Q(4,3) = -62.84 
p-value = 0.3 percent 
3 vs. 2 Unit Roots 
Q(3,2) = -13.83 
p-value = 84.8 percent </p>

<p>Note: The Dickey-Fuller t-statistics are calculated from a regression, including six lags of the differenced 
data. The regressions for ht, Yt, and yt-ht included a constant and time trend. The regressions for 
"at, it, and 
it-"rt+i 
included a constant. The 10% critical values for h,, Yt, and yt-ht are -3.12. The 10% critical values 
for </p>

<p>.it, </p>

<p>it, and it-vt+1 are -2.57. j is largest autoregressive root in the sixth order autoregression used to 
calculate the Dickey-Fuller t-statistics. The multivariate tests (Qf) are described in Stock and Watson (1987). 
They are calculated using linearly detrended data with a VAR(6) correction. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Finally, before proceeding to the results, we offer support for our 
specification of exogenous oil price changes. Oil prices are, in principle, 
endogenous. On average, real oil prices should increase by the real rate of 
interest, with innovations in the price reflecting shocks to demand and 
supply. Yet, over our sample period oil price changes are dominated by 
four exogenous events: the Yom Kippur War in 1973, the fall of the Shah in 
1979, price decontrol in 1981, and the 1986 "collapse" of OPEC. That these 
events dominate the data is obvious from Figure 1, which plots the 
percentage change in real oil prices over the sample period. </p>

<p>4.3. RESULTS FOR BASIC MODEL </p>

<p>We estimated the model in equations (3.3) through (3.7) using six lags of 
the data together with a constant. Initially, we carried out the analysis 
using data through 1987:2, but it quickly became obvious that this led to a </p>

<p>Figure 1 OIL PRICE CHANGES </p>

<p>a) 
0 </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>4--</p>

<p>C 
a) </p>

<p>U 
a) </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>120 -</p>

<p>80 -</p>

<p>40-</p>

<p>-40 -</p>

<p>-80 -</p>

<p>-120 -</p>

<p>-160 
11 
1f 
III </p>

<p>51 54 57 60 63 66 69 72 75 78 81 84 87 </p>

<p>Ye a r </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations * 125 </p>

<p>possible serious misspecification for the role of oil prices. The largest oil 
shock during the sample period occurred during the 1986 collapse of 
OPEC: during 1986 oil prices fell 50 percent. This dramatic decrease in 
prices coincided with sluggish growth. Averaging this period of positive 
covariation between oil price changes and output growth together with the 
1974-1975 and 1979-1981 periods of negative covariation misses the possi-
bility that the dynamic response of the variables in the model is different for 
oil price decreases than it is for oil price increases. The most straightforward 
way to allow for this asymmetric response is to interact the lags of oil prices 
over the 1986-1987 period with a dummy variable. Since we allow six lags 
of oil prices in our model, full interaction of the lags with the dummy 
variable over the 1986:1-1987:2 period results in a perfect fit over that 
period. Consequently, we present results for the estimated model using 
data through 1985:4. 
The results for the estimated model are summarized in Figure 2 and 
Table 2. The graphs give the response of the logs of labor, output, the price 
level, inflation, and the nominal and ex ante real interest rates to shocks in 
labor supply, oil and technology.15 The impulse responses are normalized 
as follows: the labor supply shock has a unit long-run impact on hours, the 
oil shock represents a 1 percent increase in oil prices, and the technology 
shock has a long-run impact of 1.6 on output. The long-run elasticity of 
output with respect to technology is 1/a (see equation 2.5). Since the share 
of labor averages approximately 0.625, our impulse response functions 
trace out the effect of a 1 percent long-run increase in technology. 
Since our identification procedure does not enable us to untangle the two 
aggregate demand shocks, we do not report the aggregate demand 
impulse response functions. Any impulse response functions that we 
reported would depend on arbitrary normalizations that would make 
interpretation difficult. 
A 1 percent shock in long-run labor supply has a 0.4 percent impact ef-
fect on hours. After five to six quarters, hours reach 80 percent of their 
long-run level. The labor shock increases output by 0.6 percent in the 
long-run. Recall that we expect a unit long-run elasticity of output with 
respect to the labor supply shock. We cannot reject the null that the 
elasticity is one.16 
Oil price increases lead to reductions in hours and in output. The output 
response reaches a trough after six quarters when a 1 percent oil price </p>

<p>15. The ex ante real interest rate is computed using the expected inflation rates implied by the 
model. 
16. The t-statistic for this null hypothesis equals 1.7. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>126 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>increase leads to a decline in output of 0.1 percent. The point estimate of 
the long-run elasticity of output with respect to oil prices is -0.07. Oil 
prices have a small, positive long-run effect on inflation. A 1 percent </p>

<p>Figure 2 IMPULSE RESPONSE FUNCTIONS: </p>

<p>STOCHASTIC TREND IN HOURS </p>

<p>Response of Hours </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>3.0 
Response of Output </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 --* ----------------</p>

<p>-1.0 
1 </p>

<p>I 
I </p>

<p>I 
I 
1 </p>

<p>0 3 6 9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Price Level </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>I 3 6 9 2 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response to Labor Supply--
Response to Oil Price 
---
Response to Technology ---</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations * 127 </p>

<p>increase in oil prices leads to an increase in the price level of roughly 0.09 
percent after two years. 
Increases in technology have little effect on hours. Their effect on output 
is immediate; the impact effect of output is 80 percent of the long-run effect. </p>

<p>Figure 2 (Continued) </p>

<p>Response of Inflation </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.I -
' .'% \II </p>

<p>-.2 -</p>

<p>-.3 
I </p>

<p>II 
I </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Nominal Interest Rate </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 3 6 9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Real Interest Rate </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.I -</p>

<p>-.2 -</p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I </p>

<p>0 
3 
6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response to Labor Supply----
Response to Oil Price 
Response to Technology </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>Table 2 DECOMPOSITIONS OF VARIANCE: 
STOCHASTIC TREND IN HOURS </p>

<p>Fraction of hours explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
58.9 (20.8) 
0.3 (2.0) 
4.3 (10.1) 
36.5 (19.5) 
4 
57.7 (21.0) 
0.8 (2.6) 
1.4 (7.2) 
40.1 (19.0) 
8 
64.7 (19.4) 
2.1 (3.0) 
2.1 (6.3) 
31.0 (15.8) 
12 
68.7 (17.9) 
2.3 (3.1) 
1.8 (5.9) 
27.2 (14.0) 
20 
76.8 (14.6) 
1.7 (2.3) 
1.2 (5.2) 
20.3 (11.1) 
36 
86.2 (10.0) 
1.0 (1.4) 
0.7 (4.3) 
12.1 (7.2) 
00 
100.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>Fraction of output explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
45.9 (17.7) 
0.8 (2.7) 
25.2 (15.1) 
28.1 (17.6) 
4 
48.4 (18.4) 
1.1 (2.0) 
22.2 (14.5) 
28.3 (17.1) 
8 
40.1 (16.3) 
8.0 (6.1) 
32.3 (13.7) 
19.5 (13.1) 
12 
38.1 (15.4) 
9.9 (7.0) 
35.3 (13.6) 
16.7 (11.2) 
20 
40.3 (15.2) 
10.6 (7.3) 
36.6 (13.9) 
12.5 (8.7) 
36 
45.2 (15.7) 
10.4 (7.5) 
36.5 (14.4) 
7.8 (5.9) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>61.7 (20.8) 
7.5 (9.4) 
31.9 (15.9) 
0.0 </p>

<p>Fraction of price level explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
10.3 (15.2) 
0.4 (2.3) 
0.0 (14.2) 
89.2 (19.1) 
4 
6.3 (12.3) 
5.6 (5.7) 
0.1 (12.9) 
88.1 (16.9) 
8 
5.3 (11.7) 
6.2 (6.9) 
0.5 (12.0) 
88.0 (16.7) 
12 
4.3 (11.7) 
4.7 (6.8) 
0.8 (12.2) 
90.2 (16.9) 
20 
3.6 (12.0) 
3.6 (7.1) 
1.4 (12.5) 
91.5 (17.3) 
36 
3.0 (12.7) 
2.9 (7.4) 
1.8 (12.7) 
92.3 (18.0) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>1.6 (15.3) 
2.4 (9.8) 
2.5 (11.1) 
93.5 (19.1) </p>

<p>Note: See text for details of these computations. Standard errors are in parentheses. </p>

<p>Table 2 contains the variance decompositions for a variety of forecast 
horizons.17 The table presents the fraction of the forecast errors variance for 
each of the variables that is attributed to each of the shocks. Since we can </p>

<p>17. The standard errors reported in Tables 2 and 3 were calculated using Monte Carlo 
simulation. The simulations were carried out using draws from the normal distribution for 
the innovations in hours, output, price, and the interest rate. The historical sample path 
of oil prices was used in all of the simulations. Three hundred Monte Carlo draws were 
carried out. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
129 </p>

<p>Table 2 DECOMPOSITIONS OF VARIANCE: 
STOCHASTIC TREND IN HOURS (CONTINUED) </p>

<p>Fraction of inflation explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
10.3 (15.2) 
0.4 (2.3) 
0.0 (14.2) 
89.2 (19.1) 
4 
7.6 (10.7) 
9.8 (5.9) 
0.6 (10.7) 
82.0 (14.5) 
8 
6.3 (9.3) 
10.4 (5.4) 
1.5 (9.2) 
81.8 (12.4) 
12 
5.3 (9.3) 
8.9 (5.5) 
1.7 (9.4) 
84.1 (12.6) 
20 
4.6 (10.0) 
7.0 (5.7) 
2.0 (10.1) 
86.4 (13.5) 
36 
3.7 (11.5) 
5.3 (6.2) 
2.2 (11.0) 
88.8 (15.0) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>1.6 (15.3) 
2.4 (9.8) 
2.5 (11.1) 
93.5 (19.1) </p>

<p>Fraction of real interest rate explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
10.3 (15.2) 
0.4 (2.3) 
0.0 (14.2) 
89.2 (19.1) 
4 
14.9 (14.0) 
3.2 (3.7) 
1.5 (12.0) 
80.4 (16.7) 
8 
21.3 (13.1) 
7.3 (4.8) 
2.3 (10.0) 
69.1 (14.6) 
12 
22.5 (13.6) 
6.6 (4.7) 
2.2 (10.0) 
68.6 (14.6) 
20 
24.0 (14.3) 
6.7 (4.8) 
2.3 (10.2) 
67.1 (14.9) 
36 
24.9 (15.0) 
6.5 (4.9) 
2.3 (10.5) 
66.3 (15.3) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>34.1 (17.6) 
10.2 (8.5) 
3.6 (11.1) 
52.1 (19.1) </p>

<p>Fraction of nominal interest rate explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Labor supply 
Oil 
Technology Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.7 (5.5) 
8.5 (6.5) 
7.8 (10.9) 
83.0 (12.1) 
4 
11.7 (10.5) 
14.3 (7.8) 
3.4 (7.0) 
70.6 (12.2) 
8 
13.8 (12.4) 
11.5 (8.2) 
2.4 (6.4) 
72.3 (13.2) 
12 
12.0 (12.3) 
11.3 (8.8) 
2.2 (6.7) 
74.4 (13.7) 
20 
8.4 (11.9) 
10.5 (9.1) 
1.9 (7.3) 
79.2 (14.4) 
36 
4.8 (12.2) 
8.2 (8.9) 
1.9 (8.7) 
85.1 (15.5) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>1.6 (15.3) 
2.4 (9.8) 
2.5 (11.1) 
93.5 (19.1) </p>

<p>Note: See text for details of these computations. Standard errors are in parentheses. </p>

<p>observe a linear combination of the aggregate demand shocks, we report 
the variance explained by aggregate demand. Our identifying restrictions 
imply that 100 percent of the variance of hours is explained by the labor 
supply shock at the infinite horizon, and that 100 percent of the variance of 
output is explained by shocks to labor supply, oil, and technology at the 
infinite horizon. At shorter horizons, aggregate demand is allowed to have 
an impact on these variables. The results in Table 2 suggest that this impact 
is substantial. Approximately 40 percent of the variability in hours and 30 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
. 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>percent of the variability in output over the one year horizon is attributed 
to aggregate demand. Shocks to technology account for roughly 20 percent 
of the variability in output, but explain little of the variation in hours during 
the first year. As the horizon increases from 4 to 8 to 20 quarters, the 
variability in output attributed to aggregate demand falls from 28 percent to 
20 percent to 12 percent; the variability attributed to technology increases 
from 22 percent to 32 percent to 37 percent. Oil prices explain only a small 
fraction of the variability in output. 
Our results are quite close to results found by other researchers who use 
different measures of output and different specifications. King, Plosser, 
Stock, and Watson (1987) find that about 30 to 40 percent of the 8 quarter 
ahead variability in per capita GNP can be attributed to transitory factors 
(corresponding to aggregate demand in our framework, but unspecified in 
theirs). Blanchard and Quah (1988) use data on real GNP and unemploy-
ment. They attribute from 10 to 40 percent of the 8 quarter ahead variability 
of GNP to the temporary, aggregate demand shock, depending on the 
detrending procedure for the unemployment rate. All of these results 
attribute less than half, but still a substantial fraction of the variance of 
output to shocks that have a temporary effect on the level of output. 
Aggregate demand is the main determinant of the variability in prices, 
inflation, and the nominal and real interest rate. It explains approximately 
90 percent of the variability in prices and inflation, from 70 to 90 percent of 
the variability in nominal interest rates, and roughly the same percentage 
of the ex ante real rate. 
The variance decompositions show the importance of the shocks in 
explaining the average variability in output. Of equal importance is the role 
that these shocks played in specific historical episodes. Our procedure 
produces estimates of the quarter-to-quarter shocks. Because these are 
serially uncorrelated, they are difficult to interpret. In Figure 3, we plot the 
8 quarter ahead forecast error in output and its components. These are 
simply an eight-period weighted average of estimated shocks, where the 
weights are given by the impulse response functions. Again, the parameter 
estimates are based on data through 1985:4. 
A striking feature of the graph is the post-sample 1986-1987 period. 
Using the estimated model through 1985:4, the oil price decline during 1986 </p>

<p>provides a dramatic stimulus to growth. Actual output growth was </p>

<p>sluggish, so the positive stimulus from oil is countered by large negative 
contributions from labor and technology. Given the sharp drops in output </p>

<p>following the oil shocks of the 1970's, as well as during the pre-OPEC era 
(Hamilton, 1983), our model predicts a strong increase in output following </p>

<p>the big decline in oil prices in 1986. Given that the boom did not occur 
during that period of time, our procedure offsets the positive effect of the </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
131 </p>

<p>oil price decrease on output with negative shocks to the other components 
that permanently affect output. As noted above, one would like to 
accommodate this episode by allowing for an asymmetric response of 
output to oil prices. Given that oil prices fell by a large amount only once 
in the sample, it is not possible to estimate such an asymmetric response. 
The results through 1985:4 are not complicated by the asymmetric 
response to oil prices. Throughout the early 1980, oil prices were important 
factors that negatively affected output. Declines in aggregate demand 
coincide nearly perfectly with the output "double dip"; the decline is 
particularly severe during 1981-1982. Labor supply is essentially neutral 
until the very end of the 1981-1982 recession when it turns down sharply, 
while technology does not play a role in the recessions of the 1980s. 
Oil and labor supply are the major factors in the 1974-1975 recession. 
Aggregate demand does not play a role during this period, although it 
fluctuates noticeably in the years immediately following it. 
The largest negative impact of technology occurs during the 1970 
recession and corresponds to the beginning of the productivity slowdown. 
Note also that there is a lower frequency contribution of technology to the 
forecast errors in output that corresponds to the extremely strong perfor-
mance of measured productivity growth in the 1960s, and its subsequent </p>

<p>slowdown in the 1970s.18 </p>

<p>In addition to its roles in the recessions of the 1980s, aggregate demand 
appears to have played the major role in the recessions of 1957-1958 and 
1960. 
Finally, at the beginning of the sample, there is a large movement in the 
labor supply variable related to the Korean demobilization. This anomaly 
remains in the results even if an exogenous variable accounting for military 
employment is included in the system.19 </p>

<p>4.4. ROLE OF PERMANENT LABOR SHOCKS IN OUTPUT </p>

<p>FLUCTUATIONS </p>

<p>A striking feature of our results is the large role that permanent labor 
supply shifts play in the variability of output at all frequencies. Labor 
supply explains 40 percent of the 8 quarter ahead variability in output 
(Table 2). Moreover, permanent shifts in labor input are the first or second 
most important factor in the recessions of 1954, 1958, and 1975 (Figure 3). 
Why do these results arise and should they be regarded as surprising? </p>

<p>18. Note that negative values for the contribution of technology in Figure 4 usually do not 
correspond to declines in the level of technology because it has a positive drift. 
19. This variable is the ratio of military employment to the civilian labor force. Its movements, 
which closely match those of the ratio of Federal purchases to private output, are 
dominated by the Korean war and to a lesser extent by the Vietnam War. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Figure 3 COMPONENTS OF FORECAST ERROR FOR OUTPUT: 
STOCHASTIC TREND IN HOURS </p>

<p>Percent 
(Annual Rate) 
Percent Varionce </p>

<p>2.0 
Total 
0 
00 </p>

<p>Labor Supply 
0 
40 
-2.0 </p>

<p>2.0 
Oil Price 
0 
-
--
-2.0 </p>

<p>2.0 
Technology 
0-
32 
-2.0 </p>

<p>Ag regate 
0 
20 </p>

<p>Demand 
-2.0 </p>

<p>55 57 59 61 63 65 67 69 71 73 75 77 79 81 83 85 87 </p>

<p>Economists have long attributed about half of long-run changes in the level 
of output to exogenous changes in labor input.20 This decomposition of 
variance at very long horizons is almost entirely noncontroversial.21 Now 
consider why, in our estimates, the shock to labor should be important at 
all frequencies. Labor supply shocks are important because we allow them 
to have a stochastic, rather than a deterministic trend and because the 
stochastic trend is estimated to have a large variance. Our findings are 
based on a simple, standard, and widely accepted model of long-term 
growth on which business cycle dynamics are superimposed. Because we 
find our specification so plausible, we are reluctant to dismiss it. Yet, 
because the important role of the permanent labor shock is inconsistent 
with our prior beliefs, we investigate alternative specifications. </p>

<p>4.4.1. Measure of Labor Input We measure labor input as total hours 
worked in the sector. Given that a production function is at the heart of our 
growth model, using hours worked as the labor variable is appropriate. For 
questions of low frequency movements in labor input, smoother variables, 
such as labor force or population are perhaps just as appropriate. In the 
notation of the model of Section 2, labor force or population could be used </p>

<p>20. See many careful studies by Denison (1974, for example) and others. 
21. It has been challenged recently by Romer (1987). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
133 </p>

<p>in an equation for h* with actual hours worked fluctuating in a stationary 
manner about h*. In such a formulation, the labor supply shock would be 
the structural error in the labor force equation. The residual stationary 
deviations of hours from labor force would be attributed to aggregate 
demand. 
This solution, attractive as it may seem, fails because the deviation of 
hours worked from labor force is not stationary. The first graph in Figure 4 
shows the deviation of hours worked from labor force (in logarithms). This </p>

<p>Figure 4 HOURS AND LABOR FORCE </p>

<p>Ratio of Hours Worked to Labor Force 
(Logarithms) </p>

<p>-6.4 </p>

<p>-6.6-</p>

<p>-6.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1951 
1957 
1963 
1969 
1975 1981 
1987 </p>

<p>Detrended Ratio of Hours Worked to Labor Force 
(Logarithms) </p>

<p>.08 </p>

<p>.04 </p>

<p>-.04 </p>

<p>.08 </p>

<p>1951 1957 1963 1969 1975 1981 1987 </p>

<p>Detrended Hours Worked 
(Logorithms) </p>

<p>.08 </p>

<p>.04 </p>

<p>-.04 </p>

<p>1951 
1957 
1963 
1969 
1975 
1981 
1987 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
. 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>deviation clearly contains a trend.22 The trend arises from a convolution of 
the decline in the average work week, the increase in female participation 
in the labor force, and the recent increase in part-time work. If we treated 
this trend as stochastic, it would play a role nearly identical to labor supply 
shock in the estimates just discussed. Alternatively, we could treat it as 
deterministic and abstract from issues of weekly hours and participation in 
the calculations.23 
The fluctuations of the detrended deviation of the logs of hours and labor 
force are very similar to those of detrended log hours. These series are 
graphed in the second two panels of Figure 4. Because the series are so 
similar, the model we are about to discuss--one with trend-stationary 
hours but ignoring the labor force data--is very similar to the trend-
stationary labor supply model which includes the labor force data. </p>

<p>4.4.2. Trend-Stationary Labor Supply As discussed above, we find that the 
permanent labor stock is important at all frequencies because labor appears 
to have a stochastic trend with large estimated variance. Harvey (1985), 
Watson (1986), and Clark (1987) point out that the sum of a stochastic trend 
(a random walk) and an independent, highly serially-correlated stationary 
process have an ARIMA representation with long-run properties that are 
poorly approximated by low order autoregressions. A low order autore-
gression could attribute some of the cyclical variability in the series to the 
stochastic trend. Therefore, the large stochastic trend in hours that we find 
may arise from a confusion between trend and stationary components. 
To check for misspecification of this form we have carried out a variety of 
experiments, including doubling the lag length on all variables in the 
model, and doubling the lag length of the variable in the hours equation.24 
Qualitatively, the results are unchanged. Labor supply remains an impor-
tant determinant of the business cycle variability in output. Including many 
lags of output in the hours equation should provide ample opportunity for 
removing the cyclical movements from its disturbance. </p>

<p>22. The detrended deviation of log hours from log labor force is highly serially correlated. 
Indeed, one marginally cannot reject the null hypothesis that it has a unit root. The 
deviation has a P of 0.90 and a Dickey-Fuller t-statistics of -3.4. See the notes to Table 1 
for details of these computations. 
23. Blanchard and Quah (1988) face a nearly identical problem in dealing with the trend in the 
unemployment rate. Their results are sensitive to whether or not unemployment is 
detrended. 
24. This is only a partial response to the criticism, since we have estimated unconstrained 
autoregressive models. Proponents of unobserved component models would estimate 
parsimonious constrained ARIMA models. See below for a further discussion of this 
econometric issue. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
135 </p>

<p>The most extreme case of this misspecification occurs when hours 
contain no stochastic trend component and are characterized as stationary 
deviations from a deterministic trend. Differencing hours would introduce 
a unit moving average root into the model, which could not be inverted to 
yield an autoregressive representation. In this case, our models with 6 lags 
and our model with much longer lags would both be misspecified. It is 
unlikely, however, that they would give the same qualitative results. Even 
if the long lags could not eliminate the stochastic trend, they could make its 
variance small. 
The estimates based on the differenced-stationary specification for labor 
are valid even if labor supply is trend stationary, but only if the estimation 
procedure allows for unit moving average roots. We do not undertake the 
difficult task of estimating a loosely parameterized vector ARMA model. 
Yet, it is instructive to consider the univariate ARMA process for hours to 
check for the presence of unit MA roots. Campbell and Mankiw (1987a) 
discuss the difficulties in estimating processes where a unit MA root might 
cancel an over-differenced dependent variable. For aggregate GNP, their 
results indicate that it is difficult to distinguish the trend-stationary AR(2) 
model from the ARIMA(1,1,1). For our log hours variable, the trend-
stationary AR(2) estimates are (with constant and trend suppressed): </p>

<p>ht = 1.54 ht_1 -0.61 ht-2 + vt, S.E.E. = 0.757, Q(36) = 26.5. </p>

<p>(.07) 
(.07) </p>

<p>The ARIMA(1,1,1) estimates are (with the constant suppressed) </p>

<p>Aht = 0.38 Aht-1 + vt + 0.39 vt-1, S.E.E. = 0.776, Q(36) = 29.3 </p>

<p>(.10) 
(.11) </p>

<p>Here S.E.E. is the standard error of estimate and Q(36) is the Box-Pierce 
test.25 Note that in the univariate setting there is no evidence that the 
moving average root is near unity. Were there a unit moving average root 
in the hours equation of the vector system, there would also be one in the 
univariate equation. Although the univariate test is not as powerful as a 
multivariate test, and we have explored only a limited number of ARIMA 
models, the univariate estimates do suggest that excluding MA compo-
nents from the VAR estimates is not a serious problem. Hence, we believe 
that a unit moving average root is not a major source of misspecification. </p>

<p>25. The estimates of the ARIMA model are exact maximum likelihood and are computed 
using a computer program kindly provided by John Campbell. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Notwithstanding these findings, one can still argue that the estimate of 
i reported in Table 1 for hours is 0.93 which, if it was a precise estimate, 
would suggest that hours exhibit persistent, but stationary deviations 
about a linear trend. The estimate is not precise. A value of ^ equal to 0.93 
is roughly the median value one would expect to find if the true value of p 
was 1. That is, there is significant downward bias in 
^ 
when the true value 
of p is close to one. On the other hand, despite the bias in the estimate of 
p, one also cannot reject the hypothesis that hours are borderline-sta-
tionary. 
Prior knowledge is needed to resolve the problem. One possible prior is 
that the true underlying trend in hours comes from population growth 
whose trend is very smooth and is likely to be well-approximated by a 
deterministic function of time. An alternative prior is that the stochastic 
growth component in hours is trivially small compared to its stationary 
component. Both priors suggest that deviations of hours from a determin-
istic trend are, for all practical purposes, stationary. 
Therefore, we present estimates consistent with this prior by estimating 
a model where labor is stationary around a deterministic trend. We view 
the estimates with detrended labor as an extreme but instructive case. They 
show the consequence of a prior that the stochastic trend in labor has low 
variance by taking the extreme position that the variance is zero. The 
trend-stationary model is a special case of our basic model with stochastic 
labor, but with the variance of the long-run component in labor set to zero. 
An econometric difficulty (estimating a loosely parameterized vector 
ARMA model) necessitates estimating the trend-stationary model as a 
separate, special case. In principle, it is nested by the stochastic trend 
model. If we estimate the stochastic labor model with labor differenced 
(and, in fact, the process is trend stationary) the estimated process will have 
a unit-moving average root, which should undifference the labor model. 
Yet, because we do not have explicit moving average components in our 
estimation, this undifferencing cannot take place in practice. 
Specifically, the model with trend-stationary labor is as follows: Hours 
are assumed to be stationary around a deterministic trend. Output is still 
integrated, since we maintain the assumption that productivity is 
integrated.26 Since detrended hours are now stationary, there are now 
three transitory shocks in the model. We now associate these shocks with 
aggregate demand. Oil prices and technology permanently affect the level 
of output. A summary of the results for this model can be found in Figures 
5 and 6 and in Table 3. </p>

<p>26. From Table 1, the estimated 
^ for average productivity is 0.98. Hence, there is less doubt </p>

<p>about the non-stationarity of output or output per hours than for hours. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
137 </p>

<p>In Figure 5 we present the impulse response functions. The responses to 
changes in oil prices are much the same as they were in the model with 
stochastic labor supply growth. The responses to shocks in technology are 
different. Hours now fall sharply in response to shock to technology and 
output increases very slowly. 
Table 3 presents the variance decompositions. Oil explains roughly the 
same fraction of output as it does in the model with differenced-stationary 
hours. The contributions from aggregate demand and technology are 
substantially different. In this model, aggregate demand explains 90 
percent of output over the first year, and 80 percent at the 8 quarter 
horizon. Indeed even though we constrain aggregate demand to have no 
long-run effect on output, it still accounts for roughly 35 percent of the 
variability of output at the 8-year horizon. This result is a consequence of 
labelling shocks in the hours equation as aggregate demand rather than as 
labor supply. Recall that these shocks are very persistent. 
The historical 8 quarter decomposition, shown in Figure 6, tells much the 
same story as the variance decompositions. Aggregate demand is now 
more important, oil retains its importance for the 1974 and 1980-1982 
periods, and technology is somewhat less important. 
The two sets of estimates tell markedly different stories about the sources 
of economics fluctuations in the postwar United States. Unfortunately, the 
data do not clearly support one model or the other. It is necessary to refer 
to priors when considering the likely role of permanent labor supply 
responses. While the models give very different answers to the question of 
the relative importance of transitory/permanent shocks, much of these 
differences can be attributed to the allocation of the shock to hours. That is, 
our results suggest that permanent components other than labor supply-
productivity and oil prices-have been less important than is suggested by 
others. Productivity is somewhat more important at business cycle fre-
quencies in the model with stochastic labor supply growth, but even there 
it explains only one-third of the 8 quarter variation in output. </p>

<p>4.5 SOLOW RESIDUAL 
We would also like to incorporate explicitly a measure of technology, such 
as the Solow (1957) residual, into the estimation. It might seem consistent 
with our modelling strategy to assume that the long-run changes in the 
Solow residual measure long-run changes in technology. But a difficulty 
arises in using the Solow residual because it is inherently measured as a 
rate of change. If this measure contains errors due either to data or 
specification problems, these errors will accumulate in the measures of the 
level of technology. Hence, the accumulated Solow residual will contain a 
permanent component that is attributable to measurement error in addition </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>to the permanent component that represents technological progress. Such 
difficulties could arise from measurement issues alone. Specifically, transi-
tory measurement error in capital accumulation leads to a permanent error 
in the accumulated Solow residual. Additionally, if measured input flows </p>

<p>Figure 5 IMPULSE RESPONSE FUNCTIONS: 
DETERMINISTIC TREND IN HOURS </p>

<p>Response of Hours </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.0 --
-</p>

<p>-2.0 0 3 6 9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of Output 
2.0 </p>

<p>I 3 6 9 -2 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Price Level </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 
3 6 
9 1 2 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response to Oil Price </p>

<p>Response to Technology---</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
139 </p>

<p>are not always equal to input services (labor is hoarded) then the accumu-
lated Solow residual will have a permanent component similar to that 
arising from measurement error. Similarly, Hall (1988) shows that the 
measured Solow residual contains a business cycle component if the 
assumption of perfect competition is incorrect. </p>

<p>Figure 5 (Continued) </p>

<p>Response of Inflation </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>01/ </p>

<p>-.2 
-
/ </p>

<p>0 3 6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Nominal Interest Rote 
.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>0 
3 6 
9 
2 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response of the Real Interest Rate </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>-.I </p>

<p>V\ </p>

<p>-.2 
-</p>

<p>-.3 </p>

<p>0 
3 6 
9 12 15 18 21 24 27 30 33 </p>

<p>Response to Oil Price -</p>

<p>Response to Technology </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>Figure 6 COMPONENTS OF FORECAST ERROR FOR OUTPUT: 
DETERMINISTIC TREND IN HOURS </p>

<p>Percent </p>

<p>(Annual Rote) 
Percent Vorionce </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Total 0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>-2.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Oil Price 
o-
14 </p>

<p>-2.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>Technology 
0 
52 </p>

<p>-2.0 </p>

<p>Aggregate 
2.00 
81 
Demond 
-2.0 </p>

<p>55 57 59 61 63 65 67 69 71 73 75 77 79 81 83 85 87 </p>

<p>Despite these difficulties in explicitly incorporating the Solow residual 
into the model, it is interesting to see how our estimated technological 
shock relates to this widely-studied measure of technological progress. In 
the previous paragraph we suggest that the relationship at high frequencies 
is likely to be weak. Yet, if the measurement errors are fairly small, one 
might expect to find a relationship in the long-run between the Solow 
residual and our technological shock. We compute the fraction of variance 
at frequency zero of the Solow residual accounted for by our estimated 
shocks to technology.27 In brief, we find that our technological shocks are 
closely related to the Solow residual at low frequencies. For our basic model 
with differenced-stationary hours, the technological shock accounts for 62 
percent of the variation of the Solow residual in the long-run; for the model 
with trend-stationary labor, that figure is 75 percent.28 Therefore, we </p>

<p>27. The definition of and data for the Solow residual are discussed in detail in the Appendix. 
The variance decompositions are computed based on a regression of the Solow residual on 
current and six lagged values of the five shocks, plus a constant six lags of the Solow 
residual itself. 
28. In the hours differenced-stationary model, labor shocks account for 6%, oil price shock for 
8%, aggregate demand for 16%, and the residual for 8% of the long-run variation in the 
Solow residual. In the hours trend-stationary model, the decompositions are 6% for labor, 
4% for oil prices, 9% for aggregate demand, and 6% for the residual. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
141 </p>

<p>conclude that our estimated technological shock corresponds closely to 
more familiar estimates of technological progress.29 </p>

<p>4.6. FURTHER CONSIDERATIONS 
We conclude this section with a discussion of a few minor empirical issues, 
and some general comments about the identifying assumptions that we 
use. First, consider an empirical observation about the long-run output-
capital ratio, which is assumed to be constant in our equation (2.4). With 
our data, the ratio wanders between 1.04 at the beginning of the sample to 
0.85 at the end of the sample. Its sample path looks more like a random 
walk than stationary oscillations around a constant mean. We are skeptical 
that building a variable output-capital ratio into our model would be 
fruitful. The mean and variance of its drift is small relative to the other drifts 
in the model, so we believe that ignoring it does not substantially affect our 
results. 
An important limitation of our model is that aggregate demand distur-
bances are synonymous with transitory disturbances. Purely transitory 
aggregate supply and technological disturbances will be misclassified as 
aggregate demand disturbances. If aggregate demand disturbances have a 
long-run impact on capacity, they will be misclassified as labor supply and 
technological disturbances. We would be reluctant to apply this technique 
to European countries that appear to display hysteresis in unemployment 
(Blanchard and Summers, 1986). For postwar U.S. data, there is a stronger 
case for stationarity of the unemployment rate.30 
We now turn to the limitations of the technique. For many VAR 
exercises, the degree of differencing and cointegration of the data is not a 
crucial issue. The researcher can estimate the model in levels and let the 
VAR estimate unit roots if it chooses. Inference issues can be subtle, but 
many of the usual inference procedures are asymptotically valid even in the 
presence of unit roots and cointegration. Identification procedures, such as 
ours, that rely on the long-run multipliers depend critically on the location 
of unit roots. So, for example, we have already seen how the results can 
change when the assumption that hours are difference stationary is 
changed. In addition, our assumption that inflation contains a unit root is 
not innocuous. We have estimated a modification of our five variable </p>

<p>system replacing 7rt = (1 -L)pt with (1 -AL)pt where A is estimated by </p>

<p>maximum likelihood. We find that values of A greater than 0.9 provide local </p>

<p>29. See Shapiro (1987) for further discussion and evidence that the Solow residual is a good 
measure of technological innovations despite the potential presence of cyclical errors. 
30. Unemployment is the only series for which Nelson and Plosser (1982) reject the null 
hypothesis of a unit root. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>maxima of the likelihood function and that results similar to those reported 
in the paper follow from this model. There is another local maxima of the 
likelihood function of comparable size near A = 0. Those estimates yield 
results somewhat different from those reported in the paper. We believe 
those results are unreliable. They are based on autoregressive models with 
roots near unity, and consequently the long-run multipliers, upon which 
our identification rests, are close to being undefined. </p>

<p>Table 3 DECOMPOSITIONS OF VARIANCE: DETERMINISTIC TREND IN 
HOURS </p>

<p>Fraction of hours explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.0 (1.9) 
61.1 (24.9) 
38.9 (24.9) 
4 
0.2 (2.0) 
51.4 (23.1) 
48.3 (22.9) 
8 
6.4 (6.3) 
41.5 (19.8) 
52.1 (19.7) </p>

<p>12 
8.4 (7.7) 
40.2 (19.2) 
51.4 (19.1) </p>

<p>20 
8.6 (7.9) 
39.9 (18.9) 
51.5 (19.0) 
36 
8.7 (7.9) 
39.7 (18.8) 
51.6 (19.0) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>1.9 (9.4) 
40.2 (29.6) 
57.8 (29.4) </p>

<p>Fraction of output explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.4 (2.5) 
0.8 (12.0) 
98.8 (12.2) 
4 
2.2 (3.5) 
3.9 (11.2) 
93.9 (11.7) 
8 
14.2 (8.6) 
5.2 (10.0) 
80.7 (11.7) 
12 
16.4 (9.3) 
10.4 (11.2) 
73.2 (12.3) 
20 
15.2 (8.7) 
26.4 (13.1) 
58.5 (13.0) 
36 
11.0 (7.7) 
51.7 (12.5) 
37.3 (11.3) </p>

<p>00 
2.0 (8.9) 
98.0 (8.9) 
0.0 </p>

<p>Fraction of price level explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.3 (2.3) 
4.9 (16.9) 
94.7 (16.9) 
4 
6.6 (5.6) 
6.0 (16.1) 
87.4 (16.4) 
8 
8.3 (7.4) 
3.3 (14.0) 
88.4 (15.1) 
12 
7.5 (8.1) 
2.1 (13.5) 
90.5 (15.0) 
20 
7.9 (9.6) 
0.6 (12.8) 
91.5 (15.0) 
36 
9.5 (11.4) 
0.6 (13.1) 
89.9 (15.7) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>13.9 (14.8) 
6.6 (16.0) 
79.5 (19.8) </p>

<p>Note: See text for details of these computations. Standard errors are in parentheses. Aggregate demand 
includes the shock to hours worked. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
143 </p>

<p>Finally, VARs do not eliminate omitted variable bias. It is critical in all 
structural VAR exercises that the VAR forecast errors span the space of 
structural disturbances. Except in unusual circumstances, the number of 
variables in the VAR must be at least as large as the number of structural 
disturbances driving the variables. Hence, the statistical model must be 
based on an underlying economic model that takes into account the major 
shocks impinging on the aggregate economy. </p>

<p>Table 3 DECOMPOSITIONS OF VARIANCE: DETERMINISTIC TREND IN 
HOURS (CONTINUED) </p>

<p>Fraction of inflation explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.3 (2.3) 
4.9 (16.9) 
94.7 (16.9) 
4 
11.0 (5.5) 
4.8 (12.7) 
84.2 (13.1) 
8 
11.8 (5.6) 
4.1 (10.6) 
84.1 (11.2) 
12 
11.1 (6.2) 
3.4 (10.2) 
85.5 (11.1) </p>

<p>20 
10.8 (7.3) 
3.2 (10.1) 
86.0 (11.5) 
36 
11.5 (9.1) 
4.0 (11.2) 
84.5 (13.2) </p>

<p>013.9 </p>

<p>(14.8) 
6.6 (16.0) 
79.5 (19.8) </p>

<p>Fraction of real interest rate explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>

<p>1 
0.3 (2.3) 
4.9 (16.9) 
94.7 (16.9) 
4 
3.6 (3.9) 
4.6 (12.5) 
91.9 (12.3) 
8 
6.5 (4.3) 
7.4 (10.3) 
86.0 (10.2) 
12 
6.0 (4.2) 
7.4 (10.3) 
86.6 (10.2) 
20 
5.5 (4.3) 
7.9 (10.7) 
86.6 (10.5) 
36 
5.2 (4.4) 
8.3 (11.3) 
86.4 (10.9) </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>15.0 (4.3) 
17.0 (8.0) 
68.0 (8.1) </p>

<p>Fraction of nominal interest rate explained by shock to </p>

<p>Quarter 
Oil 
Technology 
Aggregate demand </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>144 -SHAPIRO &amp; WATSON </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>We now summarize the main results from our model in which labor supply 
is allowed to have a stochastic trend. Aggregate demand accounts for 
between 20 and 30 percent of the variation in output at business cycle 
horizons. Moreover, it is an important factor in most episodes labelled as 
recessions in the NBER chronology. Technological change accounts for 
roughly one-third of output variation. Adverse technological shocks are not 
an important factor in recessions except for the recession in 1970, which 
roughly coincides with the beginning of the productivity slowdown. 
Favorable technological shocks play an important role in explaining strong 
growth in the 1960s. Additionally, our estimated technological shocks and 
the observed Solow residual are highly correlated at low frequencies. 
Oil price shocks are a key factor in explaining the recessions that 
followed the two OPEC crises, but are unimportant on average. 
The estimates imply that permanent shifts in labor input play a large role 
in explaining output fluctuations at all frequencies. It is not surprising to 
find that changes in labor are important in explaining low frequency 
movements in output. Our estimate that labor supply changes account for 
one-half the long-run changes in the level of output corresponds closely 
with the findings of growth accounting research. 
Our finding that the permanent shocks in labor account for at least 40 
percent of output variation at all horizons is, however, quite surprising. 
Yet, this finding follows from a simple and widely accepted growth model, 
together with our specification for the stochastic process followed by hours. 
We find that changes in hours have a permanent component and that 
changes in output do not account for much of the cyclical variability of 
hours. Hence, permanent, autonomous shocks to hours will play an 
important role at business cycle frequencies. 
In order to accommodate the prior belief of many economists--which we 
share--that changes in labor supply are fairly smooth, we estimate an 
alternative model where hours worked are stationary about a deterministic 
trend. Detrending hours is an extreme solution because it implies there is 
no stochastic component to the trend in labor supply. Our basic model with 
stochastic trend could have told us that variance of the trend is small. 
Indeed, had we allowed for unit moving average roots in the estimates, the 
trend-stationary case is nested in the basic model with stochastic trend. We 
do not find a unit moving average root in the univariate ARIMA model for 
hours, and so we believe that explicitly incorporating moving average 
components into the model would not alter the results. 
Despite our belief that the model with stochastic trend in labor is the best 
econometric specification, we present results with trend-stationary labor </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations 
. 
145 </p>

<p>because of our prior that labor supply changes smoothly and because of the 
econometric difficulty in distinguishing between stochastic and determin-
istic trends. In the model with deterministic labor, aggregate demand is 
very important in explaining output at business cycle frequencies and has 
a very persistent effect on output. This result arises because the low 
frequency, high variance, autonomous movements in labor input are 
attributed to aggregate demand rather than labor supply. Because taking 
out a deterministic trend is an overly stringent way of imposing the prior 
that labor supply shocks are smooth, these estimates provide a loose upper 
bound on the contribution of aggregate demand to output fluctuations. 
The statistical difficulty in distinguishing between the two models should 
be viewed in proper perspective. The basic model with the stochastic trend 
in labor supply implies that the permanent components of output account 
for two-thirds to three-quarters of business cycle frequency variation in 
output. This finding is similar to those of other researchers. We are 
surprised that permanent movements in labor input are so important in 
explaining output fluctuations in the short-run. Yet, we would not want to 
label these shocks as aggregate demand, as is done effectively in the 
trend-stationary estimates. The estimated labor supply shocks are autono-
mous movements in labor input. The estimates take into account Okun's 
law by purging the estimated labor shock of movements in hours that can 
be explained by business cycle frequency movements in output and other 
variables. A theory that would attribute these shocks to aggregate demand 
must be able to explain why there are large movements in hours that are 
not explained by movements in output. </p>

<p>Data Appendix </p>

<p>This Appendix discusses the data used in the estimates. 
All data are quarterly. The estimates are carried out on data from 1951:1 
to 1987:2. All data are seasonally adjusted unless otherwise noted. 
Output and the price level are measured as the 1982 dollar quantity and 
the deflator for total gross domestic product, less the gross domestic 
product of farms, the government, and the housing sector. These data are 
available in the National Income and Product Accounts. Given that our 
estimates are based on a model of long-run growth relating measured 
inputs to measured output, this measure is more appropriate than gross 
national product. First, this level of aggregation (private domestic nonfarm 
and nonresidential) matches hours and capital stock data. Second, this 
aggregation abstracts from the major imputations in the national accounts: 
output of owner-occupied housing is imputed based on its rental value; 
output of the government is imputed as its wage bill. Third, farmers are </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>largely self-employed, so there is no meaningful hours data for them. 
Shocks hitting the farm sector also might be very different from shocks to 
the non-farm sector. 
The hours data are hours of all persons in the nonfarm business sector. 
This index is published by the Bureau of Labor Statistics as part of its 
productivity data. 
The labor force is defined as the civilian labor force minus agricultural and 
civilian government employment. These data are also published by the 
BLS. 
The interest rate data are average of monthly data for three-month 
Treasury bills on the secondary market. 
The oil price series is the producer price index for crude oil (PW561, not 
seasonally adjusted) deflated by our general price index. 
Computation of a quarterly Solow residual is complicated by the unavail-
ability of quarterly compensation and capital stock data. Hence, our 
procedure necessarily involved some interpolation. 
The formula for the Solow residual is </p>

<p>AS = Ayt -s Aht -(1 -s) Akt (A.1) </p>

<p>where s' is the share of labor compensation in nominal output and Ayt, Aht, 
and Akt are growth in output, labor, and capital. The capital stock is the 
beginning-of-period stock. Output and labor are measured as above. The 
net capital stock on a constant dollar basis for nonfarm business is available 
on an end-of-year, not end-of-quarter basis (see August 1987 Survey of 
Current Business, for example). We calculate the quarter-to-quarter changes 
in the capital stock by using the quarterly gross investment series (gross 
private domestic nonfarm fixed investment) from the NIPA. We know the 
net change in the capital stock over the year from the annual capital stock 
data. We use this information to convert the gross flows to net flows by 
assuming that the ratio of gross to net investment is the same within each 
quarter of a given year. 
The compensation for nonfarm private business employees is also only 
available annually (Table 6.4 of the NIPA). We add to employee compen-
sation of proprietor's income (net of depreciation) to arrive at the annual 
estimate of si. The quarterly figure is then defined as a weighted average 
of the previous years and the current years share. The weights for the first 
quarter are 3/4 on the previous year and 1/4 on the current year; for the 
second quarter are 1/2 and 1/2; for the third 1/4 and 3/4; and 0 and 1 for the 
fourth quarter. This procedure approximates the standard Divisia index 
approximation, which is, in annual data, to take a moving average of the 
current and lagged year's data as an estimate of the current share. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Business Cycle Fluctuations * 147 </p>

<p>We are grateful for extensive discussions with Olivier Blanchard and Robert Hall and for 
many helpful comments from Joseph Altonji, Francis Diebold, Robert Engle, Stanley Fischer, 
Robert Gordon, James Hamilton, Danny Quah, Christopher Sims, James Stock, and partici-
pants in the Conference and a seminar at Yale. We gratefully acknowledge financial support 
from NSF Grants Nos. SES-8521791 (Shapiro) and SES-8510289 and SES-8618984 (Watson). </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>





<p>What makes macroeconomics different from microeconomics? Macro is 
interested in the fundamental sources of economic fluctuations, whereas 
micro almost always considers movements of one actor or one market as 
the result of changes elsewhere in the economy. In this paper, Shapiro and 
Watson tackle the issue of driving forces head on. Their menu of alternative 
sources of fluctuations contains aggregate demand shocks, shifts of tech-
nology, movements of oil prices, and shifts of labor supply. The big 
surprise in the paper is that labor supply shocks are important not only in 
the longer-run movements of the economy, but also in the shorter-run 
business cycle. Neither of the major schools of macroeconomic thinking 
active today--real business cycles or modern Keynesianism-puts any 
weight on labor supply as a driving force. Taken at face value, Shapiro and 
Watson's results call for a major rethinking of macroeconomics. 
All attempts to measure fundamental driving forces must rest on strong </p>

<p>assumptions about identification. Following Blanchard and Quah, Shapiro 
and Watson use timing properties to achieve identification. Their setup </p>

<p>requires that all long-run effects on output come either from labor supply or 
from oil. They claim that fairly general theoretical considerations support 
this identifying assumption. Certainly it can be true of the Solow growth 
model, where labor supply is the dominant determinant of output in the 
long-run. What is surprising about Shapiro and Watson's findings, how-
ever, is that shifts in labor supply are an important determinant of output 
in business cycle frequencies. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 14:21:07 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

</text></tei>