<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1515%2Fjbnst-2018-0002" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We present a dataset called "PASS-ADIAB -PASS survey data linked to adminis-
trative data of the IAB" 1 which integrates survey data from the household panel 
study "Labour Market and Social Security" (PASS, see Trappmann et al., 2013) 
with administrative labour market biographies from registers at the German Fed-
eral Employment Agency (BA) using record linkage techniques. The dataset is 
provided by the Research Data Centre (FDZ) of the Federal Employment Agency 
at the Institute for Employment Research (IAB) and is available for on-site use as 
well as through remote data access. 
Combining the two data sources enhances research opportunities for a wide 
range of socioeconomic topics, especially in the fields of unemployment and 
poverty research. PASS provides ten waves of survey data from household and 
individual interviews on a wide variety of issues relating to the socioeconomic 
situation. Administrative biographies complement these data with the full history 
of individual labour market records concerning employment, unemployment, 
programme participation etc. </p>

<p>1 See http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Individual_Data/PASS.aspx and Antoni et al. (2017) for further 
details. </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: Manfred Antoni, Research Data Centre (FDZ), Institute for 
Employment Research (IAB), Regensburger Str. 104, 90478 Nuremberg, Germany, 
E-mail: manfred.antoni@iab.de 
Arne Bethmann, Munich Center for the Economics of Aging (MEA), Max Planck 
Institute for Social Law and Social Policy, Amalienstr. 33, 80799 Munich, Germany, 
E-mail: a.bethmann@mea.mpisoc.mpg.de </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and A. Bethmann </p>

<p>2 Research opportunities </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB offers a unique combination of high quality, long running house-
hold panel survey data on poverty, unemployment, and welfare with detailed 
data on individual labour market biographies from administrative registers. While 
administrative data can give exact accounts of welfare dynamics themselves, aug-
menting them with survey data can foster insights concerning the impact of more 
subjective measures (e.g. reservation wages) on these processes. The same is 
true for welfare dynamics with regard to household context. Apart from struc-
tural information like household composition, the survey data contain detailed 
accounts of the household situation, e.g. on material deprivation and child care 
arrangements. On the other hand enriching survey data with full administrative 
biographies enhances the validity of research into, for instance, the interplay of 
health and unemployment. Another important benefit of the administrative data 
is reliable longitudinal information on the earnings and benefit receipt of linked 
respondents. 
The data are also well suited for a wide range of research questions going 
beyond aspects of welfare and poverty dynamics. The linked PASS surveys 
include detailed information on individual and more subjective topics not found 
in the register data, including: 2 
-Attitudes (e.g. towards employment, minimal wages, managing finances, 
gender roles, reciprocity) 
-Job quality 
-Interaction with job-centers 
-Life satisfaction (general and domain specific) and social inclusion 
-Social networks 
-Health issues (e.g. SF-12 Physical and mental health scale) 
-Psychological traits (e.g. Big Five, self-efficacy, impulsiveness) 
-Migration background </p>

<p>In addition to substantive research, PASS-ADIAB provides ample opportunity for 
methodological research. Several measures are collected in both the survey and 
the administrative data. This allows for analyses of, for instance, underreporting 
of welfare receipt (see Bruckmeier et al. 2014; Kreuter et al. 2010). Selection pro-
cesses in the linkage procedure, which might influence the validity of results, can </p>

<p>2 The full survey instruments for all PASS surveys are available here: 
http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Individual_Data/PASS.aspx </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB </p>



<p>be analysed using characteristics of survey respondents (see Beste 2011). Inter-
viewer effects can be evaluated via an anonymised interviewer identifier in the 
survey data. </p>

<p>3 Data sources </p>

<p>3.1 PASS household panel survey </p>

<p>In 2005 German labour market reforms -especially the introduction of Unem-
ployment Benefit II (UB II) -prompted an additional demand for research into the 
effects of welfare policies. PASS was established at IAB shortly thereafter funded 
by the German Federal Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs in order to provide a 
new data source for welfare research. The study's main focus is on topics related 
to pathways into and out of UB II receipt, the dynamics of the material and social 
situation of individuals and households as well as behaviour and attitudes of 
individuals over time. 3 
PASS is an annual panel study that has been conducted by the IAB since 2006. 
Interviews are conducted on the household level as well as with every individual 
in the household aged 15 or older. Data collection is done using a sequential 
mixed mode design starting in a face to face mode (CAPI) and followed up by 
telephone (CATI) if the household or individual could not be contacted or prefers 
a telephone interview. Due to a large number of individuals with migration back-
ground in the sample, Turkish and Russian translations of the questionnaire were 
used if necessary. 
The initial survey sample consisted of two subsamples. The first one is a 
sample of households containing at least one welfare benefit recipient drawn 
from the UB II register at the Federal Employment Agency. The other one was 
drawn from the German resident population. This sampling scheme gives higher 
statistical power in analysing welfare recipients but still allows for projections to 
the German resident population when using the proper weights included in the 
dataset. In all consecutive waves a refreshment sample was drawn from the UB II 
population in order to correct for changes in the composition of UB II recipients. 
In wave 5 (2011) an additional refreshment sample was drawn for both popula-
tions. The sampling was conducted via a two stage approach with postal codes as 
the primary sampling unit and sampling probabilities proportional to size (PPS). 
While the survey data provide information on a wide variety of topics rel-
evant to unemployment, poverty, and welfare research, most of theses data are </p>

<p>3 For more details on the PASS study see Trappmann et al. (2013) and Bethmann et al. (2016). </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and A. Bethmann </p>

<p>subjective in nature since they were reported by respondents and are therefore 
prone to errors arising from the response process (see Tourangeau et al. 2000). 
This might be especially problematic for topics that individuals are reluctant to 
report on as is the case for welfare receipt (see e.g., Bruckmeier et al. 2015). But 
even if respondents are willing to give proper answers, retrospective reporting of 
labour market histories is likely to produce errors, even more so as individuals get 
older and biographies increase in length and complexity. This is where adminis-
trative data can add considerably to data quality and hence improve the validity 
of substantive conclusions drawn from analyses. </p>

<p>3.2 Administrative labour market biographies </p>

<p>The PASS survey data are augmented by administrative data available at the 
IAB. These data contain every person in Germany that, at some point since 1975, 
held one of the following employment statuses: employment subject to social 
security (since 1975), marginal part-time employment (since 1999), benefit receipt 
according to the German Social Code III (since 1975) or II (since 2005), registered 
job-seeking (since 1997) and (planned) participation in programmes of active 
labour market policies (since 2000). 
The administrative data have two sources: first, employment spells stem from 
compulsory notifications by employers to the social security system. Such notific-
ations on their employees have to be given by each employer at least once a year 
or when the employment relationship ends before the end of the year. Notifica-
tions in the course of the year have to be given when any of the characteristics 
required by the notification scheme change (e.g., the health insurance company 
or residential address of a given employee). Second, the data on benefit receipt, 
job search and participation in labour market programmes are mainly entered by 
the caseworkers at the local employment agencies while registering these statuses 
or providing the corresponding services. Observations from each of these sources 
have a longitudinal structure with start-and end-dates that are detailed to the day. 
Employment spells can be enriched with administrative establishment data. 4 
These data contain detailed and reliable information on establishment charac-
teristics, the structure of employees (e.g., by age, sex, qualification, occupation, 
type of employment) and the average wage of full-time employees. These charac-
teristics are given for establishments at which the jobs included in the employee </p>

<p>4 The structure of the establishment data contained in PASS-ADIAB is identical to that of 
the Establishment History Panel (BHP). For more details see Schmucker et al. (2016) or 
http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Establishment_Data/Establishment_History_Panel.aspx. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB </p>



<p>data are held. Like the employee data, the establishment data have a longitudinal 
structure. Instead of daily spell data, the establishment data are created as yearly 
cross-sections with a reference-date of June 30th. 
In addition to these yearly cross-sectional files, additional extension files may 
be requested. On the one hand, they contain the structure of inflows and out-
flows of employees (e.g., by sex, type of employment, occupational groups, age). 
On the other hand, the extension files contain information on entries and exits 
of the establishments themselves. These variables allow a distinction between 
openings and closings of establishments from, for instance, changes of establish-
ment numbers merely due to restructuring or relabeling of the establishments' 
superordinate firms. 
Generally, these administrative data are very reliable, especially for inform-
ation that is directly relevant for the amount of unemployment or pension 
insurance claims. However, some characteristics are only reported for statistical 
purposes in some sources, while being essential for other sources. For example, 
information regarding a person's qualification or occupation is highly important 
for appropriate job offers sent out by caseworkers. In contrast, these characterist-
ics have only statistical value when reported for employment relationships. Many 
employers therefore put in less effort in keeping such variables up to date com-
pared to when reporting on, for instance, a person's wage sum during the year. 
The latter, on the other hand, is directly relevant for social security contributions 
and unemployment insurance entitlements. This leads to a somewhat higher 
share of cases with missing or potentially outdated data on some characterist-
ics. Variables that are subject to these potential shortcomings are documented in 
great detail by Antoni et al. (2016) and Schmucker et al. (2016). Figure 1 provides 
an overview of the data sources of PASS-ADIAB. </p>

<p>4 Record linkage </p>

<p>The starting point of the record linkage (Christen 2012) are all participants of the 
PASS survey that provided informed consent to the linkage of their survey data 
with information given on them within the the administrative data of the IAB. The 
question for linkage consent was asked in every wave of the PASS survey since its 
beginning, with an average consent rate over waves 1-8 of 81%. 
The linkage of new consenters from waves 1-5 was performed in separate 
rounds after each of these waves had been concluded, whereas the linkage for 
waves 6-8 was done jointly after wave 8. During that time, alternating people and 
departments were responsible for different steps of the linkage process. Besides 
the department responsible for the PASS study and the FDZ, the main contributors </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and A. Bethmann </p>

<p>Data from BA working processes and the agencies 
responsible for the implementation of SGB II </p>

<p>Social 
security 
notifications </p>

<p>Employee 
History 
(BeH) </p>

<p>Benefit Recipient 
History 
(LeH) </p>

<p>Participants-in-
Measures History 
Files 
(MTH) </p>

<p>Jobseeker History </p>

<p>Integrated Employment Biographies (IEB) </p>

<p>Establishment 
History Panel 
(BHP) </p>

<p>Sample of Integrated Labour Market 
Biographies (SIAB) </p>

<p>ASU 
XASU </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Benefit II 
Recipient History 
(LHG) </p>

<p>Surveys </p>

<p>PASS survey 
waves 1 -9 </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB 7515 </p>

<p>Figure 1: Data sources of PASS-ADIAB. </p>

<p>Source: translated from Antoni et al. (2017). </p>

<p>were staff of the IAB department Data and IT-Management and the German Record 
Linkage Center (GRLC, see Antoni and Schnell 2017). The GRLC was responsible 
for the linkage rounds of waves 1 and 5-8. 
The methods of linkage, their combination and their sequence vary between 
the two types of samples and the linkage rounds. During each of the linkage 
rounds, a so-called Goldstandard linkage was attempted for all consenters of 
the UB II sample. This linkage takes advantage of the fact that the UB II sample 
was drawn from the administrative data in the first place. For these cases, the 
linkage only had to identify members within a given benefit community (Bedarfs-
gemeinschaft), which only requires the name, sex and the birth date of a person. 
For the remaining consenters, deterministic and probabilistic methods were used 
to compare the name, sex, birth date and address of consenters and to identify 
them in the IAB's administrative data. Antoni et al. (2017) provide more details on 
the applied methods and the overall success rate of all linkage rounds. 
For the result of the first linkage round, Beste (2011) examines potential link-
age consent bias and whether linkage success is selective. His results show very 
low consent bias, but they hint at some selectivity in linkage success regard-
ing age, educational level or employment status of respondents. Nevertheless, </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB </p>



<p>in further analyses he verifies that the existing bias does not influence research 
results. To do so, he estimates exemplary models, once based on all respondents 
and alternatively only based on successfully linked respondents. A comparison 
of these results shows no significant differences in the findings based on the 
different estimation samples. </p>

<p>5 Data structure </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB consists of the PASS Scientific Use File (SUF, see Bethmann et al. 
2016) and several datasets containing the administrative labour market biograph-
ies for all PASS respondents that could be linked. Table 1 gives an overview of the 
number of household and individual interviews in each of the nine panel waves 
as well as the number of individual interviews with linked administrative data 
available. 5 
It is important to bear in mind that, although only consenters of waves 1 
through 8 have been linked so far, PASS-ADIAB also contains survey data from 
PASS wave 9. The numbers of individuals and households in this part of PASS-
ADIAB is therefore identical to those in the PASS SUF released after wave 9. While 
the survey data in PASS-ADIAB partially cover the year 2015, the administrative 
data only cover the years 1975-2014. 
The two main datasets in the PASS SUF are the one containing the house-
hold interviews (HHENDDAT) and the one containing the individual interviews 
(PENDDAT). These are both provided in long format, i.e. each row in the dataset </p>

<p>Table 1: Numbers of observations in PASS-ADIAB by wave. </p>

<p>Households 
Individuals 
Linked individuals 
Wave 1 
12794 
18954 
13514 
Wave 2 
8289 
12487 
9294 
Wave 3 
9345 
13439 
10069 
Wave 4 
7739 
11768 
8975 
Wave 5 
10185 
15607 
11132 
Wave 6 
9455 
14619 
10556 
Wave 7 
9460 
14449 
10575 
Wave 8 
8946 
13460 
9790 
Wave 9 
8878 
13271 
8553 
Total 
24047 
37993 
25048 </p>

<p>Source: PASS-ADIAB 7515, own calculation. </p>

<p>5 Only individual interviews can be linked to the administrative data. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and A. Bethmann </p>

<p>contains the responses collected from an individual (or household) in a specific 
wave. Individuals and household can be identified by their unique identifiers 
(pnr and hnr). Apart from the two main datasets the PASS SUF includes register 
datasets, datasets with weights, self-reported welfare and labour market bio-
graphies (only for a two year retrospective period) and a few others. The PASS User 
Guide (Bethmann et al. 2013) gives in-depth information on the separate datasets 
comprising the SUF and on how to work with them. 
The administrative data in PASS-ADIAB, whose structure is identical to that 
of the Sample of Integrated Labour Market Biographies (SIAB, see Antoni et al. 
2016), consist of a number of files. The main file is the individual file that contains 
the longitudinal labour market biographies of all linked respondents. In order 
to use the linked administrative data they have to be merged to the individual 
interviews from the PASS SUF prior to analysis. To do so, one merges records 
that belong to the same person identifier pnr, which is contained in the survey 
datasets as well as in the administrative individual file. This is also shown in the 
User Guide: the procedure applicable to administrative data is similar to using 
PASS's own biography dataset (<rs type="software">Stata</rs>: ibid, Example 9.4; <rs type="software">SPSS</rs>: Fuchs et al. 2015, 
Example 1.4). 
For each employment record in the individual file, basic yearly information 
on the establishment a respondent was employed at is stored in the establishment 
file. Several extension files contain additional variables on the establishment 
level as well as on worker flows (inflows/outflows) and establishments dynamics 
(entries/exits). All establishment variables can be linked to employment records 
in the individual file using the establishment identifier betnr. 
Using the person identifier pnr, researchers can add variables on technical 
aspects of the linkage procedure on the individual level. These variables as well 
as the person identifier pnr are stored in a separate linkage quality file. Figure 2 
gives an overview of the data structure of PASS-ADIAB. </p>

<p>Survey 
Data: 
Household </p>

<p>Survey 
Data: 
Individual </p>

<p>Administrative 
Data: 
Individual </p>

<p>Linkage 
Quality Data </p>

<p>Administrative 
Data: 
Establishment </p>

<p>hnr </p>

<p>betnr </p>

<p>pnr </p>

<p>Figure 2: Data structure of PASS-ADIAB. </p>

<p>Source: own illustration. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>

<p>PASS-ADIAB </p>



<p>6 Data access </p>

<p>Due to the comprehensive information on linked respondents provided in the 
linked data, there is no Scientific Use File of PASS-ADIAB. To assure privacy for 
respondents on the one hand and to retain the analytic potential of the linked 
data on the other hand, PASS-ADIAB can only be used via access modes that 
provide the highest level of data security. PASS-ADIAB therefore is available to 
researchers via on-site use at one of FDZ's locations both in Germany and abroad 6 
and via subsequent remote data access using the application JoSuA (see Eberle 
et al. 2017). 
To achieve data access, researchers have to submit a request form to the FDZ 
via email. Any requests are verified for compliance with the provisions of Section 
75 of the German Social Code Book X by the FDZ and need approval by the Federal 
Ministry of Labour and Social Affairs. The whole procedure usually takes up to 
one month. 7 </p>



<p>6 See http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Data_Access/FDZ_On-Site_Use/Standorte.aspx for details on 
these locations. 
7 See http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Data_Access/FDZ_On-Site_Use.aspx for more details on the 
application procedure. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 5/18/18 11:56 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and A. Bethmann </p>



</text></tei>