<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecin.12086" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Access to information may represent an important barrier to learning about and 
ultimately transferring to 4-year colleges for low-income community college students. 
This article explores the role that access to information technology, in particular, plays 
in enhancing, or possibly detracting from, the transfer function of the community college. 
Using data from the first-ever field experiment randomly providing free computers 
to students, we examine the relationships between access to home computers and 
enrollment in transferable courses and actual transfers to 4-year colleges. The results 
from the field experiment indicate that the treatment group of students receiving free 
computers has a 4.5 percentage point higher probability of taking transferable courses 
than the control group of students not receiving free computers. The evidence is less 
clear for the effects on actual transfers to 4-year colleges and the probability of using 
a computer to search for college information (which possibly represents one of the 
mechanisms for positive effects). In both cases, point estimates are positive, but the 
confidence intervals are wide. Finally, power calculations indicate that sample sizes 
would have to be considerably larger to find statistically significant treatment effects and 
reasonably precise confidence intervals given the actual transfer rate point estimates. 
(JEL J24, O33, I23, I24) </p>

<p>Community colleges enroll nearly half of all 
students attending public universities and an even </p>

<p> *  We thank the Community Technology Foundation of 
California (ZeroDivide), UCACCORD, and Computers for 
Classrooms, Inc. for funding. We thank Julie Cullen, Chris 
Jepsen, and participants at seminars and workshops at the 
Center for Human Potential and Public Policy, the University 
of Chicago, UCLA, University College Dublin, UC Irvine, 
the University of Wisconsin, San Francisco Federal Reserve, 
UCSC, and APPAM meetings for comments and suggestions 
on the research project. We also thank Mike Rasmussen, 
Karen Micalizio, Katalin Miko, Bev McManus, Linda Cob-
bler, Zeke Rogers, and others at Butte College for helping with 
administering the program and providing administrative data, 
and Miranda Schirmer, Luba Petersen, Caitlin White, Anita 
McSwane-Williams, Matt Jennings, Emilie Juncker, and 
Cody Kennedy for research assistance. Finally, special thanks 
go to Pat Furr for providing computers for the study and for 
her extensive help in administering the giveaway program. 
Disclaimer: The Securities and Exchange Commission 
disclaims responsibility for any private publication or state-
ment of any SEC employee or commissioner. This article 
expresses the author's views and does not necessarily reflect 
those of the commission, the commissioners, or other mem-
bers of the staff. </p>

<p>Fairlie: Professor, Department of Economics, University of 
California, Santa Cruz, CA 95060. Phone 1-831-459-
3332, E-mail rfairlie@ucsc.edu </p>

<p>Grunberg: Financial Economist, U.S. Securities and 
Exchange Commission, Washington, DC 20549. Phone 
1-240-274-0221, E-mail shgrunberg@gmail.com </p>

<p>larger share of low-income and minority students 
(U.S. Department of Education 2011). 1 Commu-
nity colleges are likely to play an increasingly 
important role in higher education and educat-
ing the future high-skilled workforce. Growth in 
the total number of enrollments in 2-year col-
leges has outpaced the growth rate for 4-year 
colleges over the past 3 decades, and Presi-
dent Obama recently proposed an unprecedented 
funding increase for community colleges with 
the goal of boosting the number of graduates by 
5 million by 2020 (U.S. White House 2009). One </p>

<p>1. In some states the share is even higher. For example, 
in California, community colleges enroll more than 70% of 
all students attending public colleges (Sengupta and Jepsen 
2006). </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>CSU: California State University 
GE: General Education 
GED: General Educational Development 
GPA: Grade Point Average 
ITT: Intent-to-Treat 
IV: Instrumental Variables 
LATE: Local Average Treatment Effect 
OLS: Ordinary Least Squares 
TOT: Treatment-on-the-Treated 
UC: University of California </p>

<p>1040 
Economic Inquiry 
(ISSN 0095-2583) 
Vol. 52, No. 3, July 2014, 1040-1059 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/ecin.12086 
Online Early publication March 27, 2014 
© 2014 Western Economic Association International </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>of the primary goals of community colleges is 
to provide basic requirements training for entry 
to 4-year colleges. The cost savings from spend-
ing 2 years at a community college before enter-
ing a 4-year college can be substantial-average 
full-time annual tuition at a community college 
is $2,439 compared with $7,136 at a public uni-
versity and $22,771 at a private university (U.S. 
Department of Education 2011). In some states 
with large community college systems, such as 
California, nearly half of all students attending a 
4-year college previously attended a community 
college (California Community Colleges Chan-
cellor's Office 2009). 
A potential constraint to transferring to 4-year 
colleges for some students, however, is limited 
access to information (American Association of 
Community Colleges 2004; Dowd and Gabbard 
2006; Furchtgott-Roth, Jacobson, and Mokher 
2009). Acquiring information about 4-year uni-
versity choices, admission requirements, tuition, 
financial aid, and which courses are transferable 
is likely to be greatly enhanced through the use 
of information technology. 2 In California, for 
example, the widely used web page, assist.org, 
provides detailed school-to-school information 
on transferable courses, articulation agreements, 
and majors for all community colleges and 4-year 
universities in the state. 3 But, 1.2 million com-
munity college students do not have access to 
computers at home with the Internet. 4 The lack 
of access to home computers is especially acute 
among low-income students attending commu-
nity colleges-roughly one third of students liv-
ing in households with income less than $20,000 
do not have computers with Internet access at 
home (Figure 1). These disparities reflect broader 
patterns of disparities in access to home com-
puters, Internet, and other technology by income 
(Fairlie 2004; Goldfarb and Prince 2008; Hoff-
man and Novak 1998; Mossberger et al. 2003, 
2006; Ono and Zavodny 2003; U.S. Depart-
ment of Commerce 2008; Warschauer 2003). 
Unlike 4-year colleges, where many students live 
on campus and have access to large computer </p>

<p>2. Proliferation of web sites, such as collegeboard.com, 
fastweb.com, and www.fafsa.ed.gov, provides information on 
financial aid, application, course, SAT, and other information 
about 2-and 4-year colleges. 
3. All 4-year public institutions in California also pro-
vide college admission notifications on password protected 
web sites (Venegas 2007). 
4. Estimates are derived from microdata from the 2010 
Computer and Internet Supplement to the Current Population 
Survey. </p>

<p>labs, community college students often have lim-
ited access to on-campus technology making 
home access important for acquiring information. 
Additionally, the increased time and flexibility 
provided by having access to computers at home 
may improve the ability of community college 
students to perform better in college and take 
more challenging transferable courses. 5 There-
fore, disparities in access to technology might 
represent an inefficient barrier for low-income 
students who could otherwise benefit from trans-
ferring to 4-year colleges. 
On the other hand, having access to a home 
computer may enhance the ability of community 
college students to acquire information about 
the value, requirements, and career opportunities 
provided by 2-year college degrees and certifi-
cates. Although the original goal of community 
colleges was to provide basic requirements 
training for entry to 4-year colleges, their role in 
providing terminal degrees, workforce training, 
and basic skills education has expanded (Leigh 
and Gill 2007). The labor market returns for 
the various degrees, diplomas, and certificates 
offered by community colleges are large (Jepsen 
et al. 2009). The acquisition of this information 
may divert students away from transferring to 4-
year colleges. A similar concern has been raised 
about the overall "diversion" effect of commu-
nity colleges. Several previous studies find that 
attending a community college lowers the likeli-
hood of ultimately obtaining a bachelor's degree 
possibly due to increased opportunity costs, 
inadequate preparation, part-time enrollment, 
and displacement through curricular emphasis 
on vocational degrees (Alfonso 2006; Long and 
Kurlaender 2009). 6 The increased autonomy 
offered by access to a home computer may also 
lead to extensive use for games, networking, 
downloading music and videos, communicating 
with friends, and other entertainment, potentially 
crowding out schoolwork time, college search, </p>

<p>5. The previous literature provides some evidence of 
positive effects of home computers on educational outcomes 
such as test scores, grades, and graduation, but overall the 
evidence is mixed (see Attewell and Battle 1999; Fuchs 
and Woessmann 2004; Fairlie 2005; Fairlie, Beltan, and Das 
2010; Fairlie and Robinson 2013; Fiorina 2010; Malamud 
and Pop-Eleches 2010; Vigdor and Ladd 2010; Schmitt and 
Wadsworth 2006, for example). 
6. Previous research, however, also finds evidence that 
community colleges have increased overall access to higher 
education often referred to as the "democratization" effect 
(Gonzalez and Hilmer 2006; Leigh and Gill 2003, 2004; 
Rouse 1995, 1998). </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 
Home Computer with Internet Access Rates for Enrollees in Community College </p>

<p>65.6% </p>

<p>77.1% </p>

<p>84.7% </p>

<p>95.2% </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>40.0% </p>

<p>60.0% </p>

<p>80.0% </p>

<p>100.0% </p>

<p>Income: Less than $20,000 Income: $20,000-40,0000 
Income: $40,000-75,000 
Income: $75,000 or more </p>

<p>Source: Current Population Survey, October 2007 Microdata. </p>

<p>and interest in taking more demanding transfer-
able courses (Jones 2002; Lenhart 2009; U.S. 
Department of Commerce 2004). 7 
Because of these potentially opposing forces, 
the net effect of having access to a home com-
puter on transferring among community college 
students is theoretically ambiguous. An empiri-
cal test of the hypothesis is therefore needed, but 
has not been conducted in the previous literature. 
This is due, in part, to the inherent selection 
problems in estimating the effects of personal 
computers on educational outcomes. To address 
the lack of empirical evidence on the question 
and concerns about causal inference, we use data 
from the first-ever field experiment providing 
free computers to community college students 
for home use to explore the relationship between 
access to computers and transferring to 4-year 
colleges. Participating students were randomly 
selected to receive free computers and their 
course-taking and transfer behavior was tracked 
in subsequent years. The random-assignment 
evaluation is conducted with 286 entering 
students receiving financial aid at a large </p>

<p>7. The impact of the extensive use of Facebook among 
college students on academic outcomes has recently received 
some attention (Karpinski 2009 and Pasek and Hargittai 
2009). The attention is partly due to the dramatic increase in 
the use of social networking sites such as Facebook in the past 
few years (Lenhart 2009). These concerns are similar to those 
over television (Zavodny 2006). </p>

<p>community college in Northern California. Pre-
vious findings from the experiment provide some 
evidence that the randomly selected group of 
students receiving free computers achieved better 
educational outcomes than the control group that 
did not receive free computers, but the study does 
not examine the potential transfer function of the 
community college (Fairlie and London 2012). 8 
In this article, we conduct a detailed analysis 
of the causal effects of home computers on the 
transfer function of community colleges for 
low-income students. In an examination of the 
effects of home computers on several differ-
ent educational outcomes, Fairlie and London 
(2012) find positive estimates of the effects 
on taking transfer courses. We expand on that 
finding in several ways. First, and foremost, 
we obtain new data from the National Student 
Clearinghouse on actual transfers to 4-year col-
leges among all participants in the experiment. 9 
These data allow for an analysis of not only </p>

<p>8. Previous results from the experiment also indicate 
that estimates of the effects of home computers on graduat-
ing from community college are much smaller than nonex-
perimental estimates from matched CPS data suggesting that 
nonexperimental estimates may be biased upward (Fairlie and 
London 2012). 
9. The Institutional Research Department at the commu-
nity college recently analyzed transfer rates of all of its stu-
dents through specially commissioned data from the National 
Student Clearinghouse. We obtained these data for our sample 
of 286 students participating in the study providing a 4-year 
window in which to observe transfers. </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>whether computers affect interest or intent to 
transfer to a 4-year college but also whether they 
affect actual transfers. These data as well as data 
on transfer course enrollment are taken from 
administrative data removing concerns about dif-
ferential attrition or reporting biases. Second, we 
report new estimates on treatment heterogeneity 
by educational goals. Focusing on the effects 
of computers on transfers to 4-year colleges 
suggests that students with the initial goal of 
transferring versus those with another goal might 
be affected differently. Third, new results on 
the effects of home computers on self-reported 
college search are reported. These results provide 
suggestive evidence on possible mechanisms. 
The findings on the effects on taking trans-
fer courses, searching for college information, 
heterogeneity by educational goal, and actual 
transfer rates are also discussed in the context 
of the literature examining what contributes 
to transfer rates among community college 
students. </p>

<p>II. THE FIELD EXPERIMENT </p>

<p>To examine the effects of home computers 
on transferring to 4-year colleges, we randomly 
assigned free computers to entering community 
college students who were receiving financial aid. 
The students attended Butte College, which is 
located in Northern California and has a total 
enrollment of over 20,000 students. Compared 
with the average community college in the United 
States, Butte College is larger, but does not dif-
fer substantially in the composition of its student 
body. For example, Butte College has a roughly 
similar share of female students as the U.S. total 
(55.0% compared with 58.5%) and roughly sim-
ilar share of nonminority students (65.4% com-
pared with 60.8%). 
To implement the field experiment, letters 
advertising the computer giveaway program were 
sent to all financial aid students with less than 
24 units attending the college in fall 2006 (see 
Fairlie and London 2012 for more details on the 
field experiment). In fall 2006, there were 1,042 
financial aid students and 6,681 students in total 
who met the course unit restriction. Participat-
ing students were required to return a baseline 
questionnaire and consent form releasing future 
academic records from the college for the study. 
Students who already owned computers were not 
excluded from participating in the lottery because 
their computers may have been much older and 
not fully functional with the latest software and </p>

<p>hardware. 10 There were 286 students who par-
ticipated in the study with 141 of these students 
receiving free computers. All the computers were 
refurbished and were provided by Computers for 
Classrooms, Inc., a computer refurbisher located 
in Chico, California. 11 Internet service was not 
provided as part of the experiment, but we found 
at the end of the study that more than 90% of the 
treatment group had Internet service. Because of 
high rates of Internet subscription among com-
puter owners we cannot identify separate effects 
of computers and the Internet, which has been 
a problem in previous studies (Fairlie, Beltan, 
and Das 2010). More than 90% of eligible stu-
dents picked up their free computers by the end 
of November 2006. </p>

<p>A. Who Applied for the Computer Lottery? </p>

<p>Table 1 reports administrative data from the 
original application to the college for students 
applying to the computer giveaway program, all 
financial aid students, and all entering students. 12 
The racial composition of study participants is 
very similar to that of all financial aid students, 
the group initially targeted for the study. A total 
of 60.1% of study participants are white com-
pared to 61.3% of all financial aid students. The 
largest minority group, Latinos, comprise 16.8% 
of study participants compared to 15.6% of all 
financial aid students. A similar percentage of 
primarily English language students also partic-
ipated in the study compared to all financial aid 
students. The one difference between study par-
ticipants and the population of financial aid stu-
dents is that a larger percentage of women applied 
for the computer lottery than men. Women com-
prise 62.6% of all study participants which 
is higher than the 54.7% for all financial aid 
students. 
A comparison to all students reveals that study 
participants are more likely to be female than the 
total student body. Women comprise 55.2% of 
all students attending the college. Study partici-
pants as well as all financial aid students are more </p>

<p>10. Twenty-eight percent of students reported already 
owning a computer. The results presented below are not 
sensitive to the exclusion of these students. 
11. The computers were refurbished Pentium III 
450 MHz machines with 256 MB RAM, 10 GB hard drives, 
17" monitors, modems, ethernet cards, CD drives, and Win-
dows 2000 Pro Open Office (with Word, Excel, and Pow-
erPoint). Computers for Classrooms offered to replace any 
computer not functioning properly during the 2-year study 
period. 
12. Baseline and follow-up survey data is only available 
for study participants. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Application Information for Study Participants, Financial Aid Students, and All Entering Students </p>

<p>Study Participants 
All Financial Aid Students 
All Entering Students </p>

<p>Gender 
Female 
62.6% 
54.7% 
55.2% 
Male 
35.7% 
43.6% 
43.6% 
Missing 
1.7% 
1.7% 
1.2% 
Race/Ethnicity 
White 
60.1% 
61.3% 
65.2% 
Asian and Pacific Islander 
8.0% 
8.2% 
7.0% 
African American 
3.1% 
3.2% 
2.6% 
Latino 
16.8% 
15.6% 
13.1% 
Native American 
2.1% 
2.9% 
2.2% 
Other 
1.0% 
1.2% 
1.2% 
Unknown 
8.7% 
7.6% 
8.7% 
English language 
English 
81.8% 
83.7% 
80.1% 
Non English 
7.0% 
6.7% 
7.8% 
Unknown/Uncollected 
11.2% 
9.6% 
12.1% 
Sample size 
286 
1,042 
6,681 </p>

<p>Note: Based on administrative data provided by Butte College for entering students in Fall 2006. </p>

<p>likely to be from minority groups than all stu-
dents, but are less likely to be nonprimary English 
language students, which may be related to apply-
ing for financial aid. These differences, however, 
are small. 
Although study participants are a self-selected 
group from all financial aid students, they do 
not appear to be very different from either finan-
cial aid students or the entire student body along 
observable characteristics. They may differ, how-
ever, along dimensions directly related to partic-
ipation in the study. Specifically, they may have 
less access to computers and disposable income 
than other financial aid students. These differ-
ences have implications for our ability to gen-
eralize the results based on study participants to 
all community college students receiving finan-
cial aid. But, students with limited access to 
computers and financial resources are the pop-
ulation of most interest for any policy interven-
tion involving the provision of free or subsidized 
computers. </p>

<p>B. Comparability of Treatment and Control 
Groups </p>

<p>Table 2 reports a comparison of background 
characteristics for the treatment and control 
groups. All study participants were given a base-
line survey that included detailed questions on 
gender, race, age, high school grades, household 
income, parents' education, and other character-
istics. The average age of study participants is 25. 
More than half of the students have a parent with </p>

<p>at least some college education, and about one 
third of students received mostly grades of A's 
and B's in high school. A little over one quarter 
of study participants have children and one third 
live with their parents. As would be expected 
among financial aid students, study participants 
have low-income levels with only 17% having 
current household incomes of $40,000 or more. 
The majority of study participants have house-
hold incomes below $20,000 and more than half 
are employed. 
The similarity of the mean values of these 
baseline characteristics confirms that randomiza-
tion created comparable treatment and control 
groups for the experiment. We do not find 
large differences for any of the characteristics, 
and none of the differences are statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>C. Educational Goals at Time of Application </p>

<p>Butte College provided us with administrative 
data on the educational goals of all students 
as reported on their original application to 
the college. Table 3 reports the distribution 
of educational goals for all study participants, 
the treatment and control groups, all financial 
aid students, and all entering students. For all 
study participants, the most common response 
is "undecided on goal," which represents 37.4% 
of study participants. The next most common 
goal reported by applicants is to transfer to a 
4-year institution, with 31.5% of study partic-
ipants reporting this goal. Roughly one fourth </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
Background Characteristics of Study Participants from Baseline Survey </p>

<p>All Study 
Participants </p>

<p>Treatment 
Group </p>

<p>Control 
Group </p>

<p>p Value for Treatment-
Control Difference </p>

<p>Female 
63.3% 
64.5% 
62.1% 
.666 
Latino 
17.8% 
15.6% 
20.0% 
.333 
Other minority 
18.2% 
21.3% 
15.2% 
.182 
Age 
25.0 
2 4 .9 
2 5 .0 
.894 
Parent some college 
37.8% 
41.8% 
33.8% 
.161 
Parent college graduate 
22.0% 
18.4% 
25.5% 
.150 
High school grades A's and B's 
30.4% 
32.6% 
28.3% 
.426 
High school grades B's and C's 
56.6% 
55.3% 
57.9% 
.657 
Live with own children 
27.3% 
27.7% 
26.9% 
.885 
Live with parents 
34.6% 
31.2% 
37.9% 
.234 
Household income: 10,000-19,999 
31.5% 
30.5% 
32.4% 
.728 
Household income: 20,000-39,999 
25.9% 
27.7% 
24.1% 
.498 
Household income: 40,000 or more 
16.8% 
14.9% 
18.6% 
.401 
Sample size 
286 
141 
145 </p>

<p>Note: Based on baseline survey administered to all study participants. </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Educational Goals at Time of Application </p>

<p>Study 
Participants </p>

<p>Treatment 
Group </p>

<p>Control 
Group </p>

<p>p Value for 
Treatment-
Control 
Difference </p>

<p>All Financial 
Aid Students </p>

<p>All Butte 
College 
Students </p>

<p>Educational goals at initial application 
Transfer goal 
31.5% 
29.8% 
33.1% 
.548 
33.6% 
24.5% 
Nontransfer goal 
24.5% 
26.2% 
22.8% 
.495 
25.7% 
32.2% 
Undecided goal 
37.4% 
36.9% 
37.9% 
.855 
36.5% 
33.9% 
Unknown goal 
6.6% 
7.1% 
6.2% 
.765 
4.2% 
9.4% 
Sample size 
286 
141 
145 
1,042 
6,681 </p>

<p>Notes: Based on administrative data provided by Butte College for students at the time of application. Nontransfer goals 
include obtaining degree or certificate without transferring, and discovering career interest, preparing for a new career, updating 
job skills, maintaining occupational certificates or licenses, intellectual or cultural development, improving basic skills in English, 
reading or math, and completing credits for a high school diploma or general educational development (GED). </p>

<p>of study participants reported a goal other than 
transferring to a 4-year college. 13 Due to ran-
domization, the treatment and control groups do 
not differ in their educational goals as reported 
on their admission applications. In comparison 
to all financial aid students, study participants 
are very similar in their educational goals. In 
comparison to all entering students, study partic-
ipants are less likely to report having a transfer 
goal and are more likely to report having a 
nontransfer goal, but the overall patterns are </p>

<p>13. These goals include obtaining an associate's degree, 
vocational degree, or vocational certificate without transfer-
ring, and discovering career interests, preparing for a new 
career, updating job skills, maintaining occupational certifi-
cates or licenses, intellectual or cultural development, improv-
ing basic skills in English, reading, or math, and completing 
credits for a high school diploma or GED. </p>

<p>roughly similar. These patterns are also generally 
consistent with those found for the entire Cal-
ifornia Community College System (Sengupta 
and Jepsen 2006). We control for educational 
goals in estimating treatment effects and explore 
differential treatment effects by educational goal 
below. </p>

<p>D. Data on Transfer Courses and Transfer 
Rates </p>

<p>Following previous research, we use the 
course-taking behavior of students as a measure 
of the interest and likelihood of transferring to 
4-year colleges (California Community Colleges 
Chancellor's Office 2009, Sengupta and Jepsen 
2006). From an analysis of a special cohort of 
entering students for the 1997-1998 school year </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>linked through system-wide administrative data, 
Sengupta and Jepsen (2006) find that enrollment 
in transferable courses in the first and second 
years of study is a major predictor of who 
eventually transfers. Butte College provided us 
with administrative data on all courses taken by 
study participants over a 2-year period starting 
at the beginning of the experiment. All of the 
courses taken by students can be identified as 
being transferable to the California State Uni-
versity (CSU) or University of California (UC) 
systems. 
For all courses offered at Butte College, 71% 
are transferable to CSU or UC campuses. Trans-
ferable courses are spread across a large number 
of different departments with 86% of departments 
offering at least one transferable course. The 
number of transferable courses offered by the 
college and in each department is reported in 
Table A1. Transferable courses can be higher 
level courses even though they satisfy lower divi-
sion credit. In Mathematics, for example, Inter-
mediate Algebra is not transferable and Analytic 
Geometry/Calculus I is transferable to CSU and 
UC campuses. Of all courses taken by partici-
pants in the experiment 63% are transferable to 
CSU or UC systems. 
We also examine actual transfer rates of stu-
dents participating in the study. For a special 
study of transfer rates to 4-year colleges, the Insti-
tutional Research Department at Butte College 
purchased data tracking college enrollment activ-
ity from the National Student Clearinghouse. 
Data tracking college enrollment activity through 
summer 2010 were purchased for every student 
attending Butte College over the previous several 
years. We recently found out about the project, 
and the Institutional Research Department pro-
vided us with the data from this special run for all 
students participating in our random experiment. 
The system tracks attendance at most colleges in 
the United States and includes information from 
CSU and UC campuses. This source is essen-
tial because community colleges do not collect 
(and have no easy way of collecting) informa-
tion themselves on which students leave and ulti-
mately transfer to 4-year universities. Using these 
data we find that 21.6% of study participants 
transfer to a 4-year college in the 4-year win-
dow. Most of the transferring students transfer to 
CSU campuses (89.9%). Of these students trans-
ferring to CSU campuses, most transfer to Cali-
fornia State University Chico (75.9%). No study 
participants transfer to University of California 
campuses. </p>

<p>III. THE ROLE OF COMMUNITY COLLEGE AS A 
GATEWAY TO 4-YEAR COLLEGES </p>

<p>Before turning to the results from the 
experiment, we examine how the California 
Community College System provides a transfer 
function to 4-year universities. Butte College 
is part of the California Community College 
system, which is the largest higher educational 
system in the nation. The system includes 112 
colleges and educates 2.6 million students per 
year (California Community Colleges Chancel-
lor's Office 2012). As stated in the Master Plan 
for Higher Education in California, the primary 
mission of community colleges is to provide 
academic and vocational instruction through 
the first 2 years of undergraduate education 
(University of California Office of the President 
2009). The Plan specifically calls for community 
colleges to play an important role in admission to 
the state's 4-year universities. Eligible students 
transferring from community colleges are given 
priority in the admissions process at CSU and 
UC campuses, and CSU and UC campuses are 
required to establish a specified lower division to 
upper division ratio to facilitate transfers. 
Agreements between California community 
colleges and CSU or UC campuses often make it 
easier for students to transfer as long as they meet 
specific criteria about taking courses and obtain-
ing grade thresholds. The most common 4-year 
college that Butte College students transfer to is 
CSU Chico, which is the closest CSU campus. 
The eligibility requirements for an upper divi-
sion transfer to CSU Chico are that students have 
at least 60 semester (or 90 quarter) transferable 
units, with 30 semester units of general educa-
tion (GE). The student must receive a grade of 
C or higher in the GE courses, and have a 2.0 or 
higher overall grade point average (GPA). Trans-
fers to CSU Chico from community colleges that 
are outside of their local admission area often 
face higher GPA requirements. Community col-
lege students can also apply to a 4-year college 
at an earlier stage (referred to as a lower division 
transfer), but these students have a lower prior-
ity in admissions than the upper division transfer 
applicants. 
Attending a community college before attend-
ing a 4-year university may be especially attrac-
tive to low-income students. The tuition savings 
from attending 2 years at a community college 
are substantial. At the national level, average 
annual tuition at community colleges is $2,439 
compared with $7,136 for public universities and </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>FIGURE 2 
Total Number of California Community College Students Transferring to 4-Year Colleges </p>

<p>80 000 </p>

<p>85 000 </p>

<p>90 000 </p>

<p>95 000 </p>

<p>100 000 </p>

<p>105 000 </p>

<p>110 000 </p>

<p>2002-2003 
2003-2004 
2004-2005 
2005-2006 
2006-2007 
2007-2008 </p>

<p>Source: California Community Colleges Chancellor's Office (2002-2008). </p>

<p>$22,771 for private universities (U.S. Depart-
ment of Education 2011). In California, the cost 
at community colleges is $36 per unit or $864 
per year for a full-time student (California Com-
munity Colleges Chancellor's Office 2011). The 
average annual costs of full-time tuition at a CSU 
campus are $6,489 and $13,200 at a UC cam-
pus and have been rising rapidly (California Col-
leges.edu 2012). 14 In addition to the substantial 
savings on the cost of education, attending a com-
munity college may allow students to improve 
their academic record and ultimately attend a 
higher quality 4-year college (Hilmer 1997). 
The number of community college students 
transferring to 4-year colleges in California has 
increased steadily over the past several years 
(California Community Colleges Chancellor's 
Office 2009). In 2007-2008, 105,957 students 
transferred to 4-year colleges, which represents 
a 16% increase from 2002-2003 (Figure 2). 
Among all entering California community col-
lege students, roughly 15% transfer to a 4-year 
institution within 7 years (Sengupta and Jepsen 
2006). Transfer rates increase to 26% when 
focusing on community college students who 
take primarily transfer-eligible courses in their 
first year and 38% for students taking primarily </p>

<p>14. Average annual tuition was $8,062 at UC cam-
puses and $3,797 at CSU campuses in 2008-2009 (California 
Teachers Association 2012). </p>

<p>transfer-eligible courses in both their first and 
second years. 
From the perspective of the UC and CSU sys-
tems, a strikingly large percentage of students 
first attended a community college in Califor-
nia (California Community Colleges Chancel-
lor's Office 2009). In the CSU system, 55.3% of 
students from the 2007-2008 cohort previously 
attended a community college. Of the 42,416 
students in the 2007-2008 cohort in the Uni-
versity of California system, 29.4% previously 
attended a community college. The community 
college system clearly provides a route to univer-
sity education for many students in California. 
Identifying the potential barriers to transferring 
to 4-year colleges for other students is important 
for improving overall access to higher education. 
Informational constraints may represent one such 
barrier to attending 4-year colleges, especially 
among low-income students (American Associ-
ation of Community Colleges 2004; Dowd and 
Gabbard 2006; Furchtgott-Roth, Jacobson, and 
Mokher 2009). </p>

<p>IV. HOME COMPUTER IMPACTS </p>

<p>The impact of home computers on students 
deciding to transfer is ambiguous. Home com-
puters may provide an important tool for finding 
information about 4-year colleges and help 
students take challenging transferable courses 
and ultimately transfer to 4-year colleges. For </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Transfer Course Regressions </p>

<p>OLS Estimates 
IV Estimates </p>

<p>Lower Bound 
Upper Bound 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.0479 (0.0239) 
0.0445 (0.0226) 
0.0494 (0.0251) 
0.0625 (0.0318) 
Baseline controls 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Control group mean (Y) 
0.6116 
0.6116 
0.6116 
0.6116 
Sample size 
2,658 
2,658 
2,658 
2,658 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is whether the course is transferable to a California State University or University of California 
campus. Robust standard errors are reported and adjusted for multiple courses taken by study participants. Baseline controls 
include gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' highest education level, high school grades, presence of own children, live with 
parents, family income, and educational goals. The dependent variable in the first-stage regression in the IV model is obtaining 
a new computer. The lower (upper) bound estimate assumes that all control group noncompliers obtained computers at the end 
(beginning) of the survey period. </p>

<p>example, students with home computers and 
access to the Internet would have more flexibility 
to explore websites such as "assist.org," which 
allows California community college students to 
enter their current college and 4-year college of 
interest and obtain detailed information on which 
courses are transferrable, different majors, gen-
eral requirements to earn a degree in that major, 
and links to other college-related websites. How-
ever, computers also allow students to gather 
more information on the value and requirements 
of getting an associate's or vocational degree, 
which may discourage students from transfer-
ring to 4-year colleges, as well as provide a 
distraction through their entertainment value. In 
this section, we turn to the field experiment to 
estimate the transfer function of home comput-
ers. We first examine impacts on the likelihood 
that community college students take courses 
that are transferable to the CSU or UC systems 
before turning to an analysis of data on actual 
transfers. Enrollment in transfer courses prox-
ies for potential interest in transferring which 
is an important outcome in addition to actual 
transfers. 
Among study participants, 63% of all courses 
taken over the study period are transferable. 
Of all courses taken by the treatment group, 
66% are transferable to a CSU or UC cam-
pus compared with 61% of courses taken by 
the control group. Table 4 reports estimates of 
the treatment-control difference from regres-
sions for which there is an indicator variable for 
whether a course is transferable to a CSU or UC 
campus. The regression equation is straightfor-
ward in the context of the field experiment: </p>

<p>(1) 
y ij = α + βX i + δT i + λ t + u i + ϵ ij , </p>

<p>where y ij is whether the course is transferable to 
a CSU or UC campus for student i in course j, X i 
includes baseline characteristics, T i is the treat-
ment indicator, λ t are quarter fixed effects, and 
u i + ϵ ij is the composite error term. The effect of 
winning a free computer or the "intent-to-treat" 
(ITT) estimate of the giveaway program is cap-
tured by δ. All specifications are estimated using 
ordinary least squares (OLS) and robust standard 
errors are reported with adjustments for multiple 
observations per student (i.e., clustered by stu-
dent). Marginal effects estimates are similar from 
probit and logit models, and are thus not reported. 
Specification 1 reports estimates of the treat-
ment effect without any controls. The point esti-
mate for δ implies that the treatment group of 
students receiving free computers has a 4.8 per-
centage point higher likelihood of taking transfer 
courses than the control group not receiving free 
computers. 15 The treatment-control difference 
of 4.8 percentage points is statistically significant 
and represents roughly 8% of the control group 
mean. The 95% confidence interval for this esti-
mate is 0.001-0.095. Including detailed controls 
for gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' highest 
education level, high school grades, presence of 
own children, live with parents, family income, 
and educational goals does not change the result 
(Specification 2). 16 These control variables are </p>

<p>15. We do not find evidence of a trend over the two 
academic years. The levels and treatment/control difference 
are very similar in each quarter. 
16. Fairlie and London (2012) report a larger positive 
estimate which is also statistically significant. The sample 
used in that study only includes nonrecreational courses, 
which were used in the estimation of the other educational 
outcomes (e.g., course pass rate) to maintain a consistent 
sample size. Thus, these estimates are not sensitive to the 
inclusion or exclusion of recreational courses. </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>TABLE 5 
Percent Transfer Course Regressions </p>

<p>OLS Estimates 
IV Estimates </p>

<p>Lower Bound 
Upper Bound 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.0542 (0.0280) 
0.0545 (0.0291) 
0.0598 (0.0318) 
0.0770 (0.0410) 
Baseline controls 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Control group mean (Y) 
0.6051 
0.6051 
0.6051 
0.6051 
Sample size 
259 
259 
259 
259 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is the percent of courses transferable to a California State University or University of California 
campus taken by each student. Robust standard errors are reported. Baseline controls include gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' 
highest education level, high school grades, presence of own children, live with parents, family income, and educational goals. 
The dependent variable in the first-stage regression in the IV model is obtaining a new computer. The lower (upper) bound 
estimate assumes that all control group noncompliers obtained computers at the end (beginning) of the survey period. </p>

<p>taken from the baseline survey administered to 
all study participants before receiving free com-
puters. We continue to find a positive difference 
between the treatment and control groups. With 
the controls, the confidence interval is slightly 
smaller at 0.0002-0.0888. Although the point 
estimates are statistically significant, the confi-
dence intervals just rule out zero. 
These estimates are not sensitive to alterna-
tive methods of measuring transfer course enroll-
ment. First, we estimate specifications in which 
the dependent variable measures the percent-
age of courses taken that are transferable by 
students. In this case, each student contributes 
only one observation to the sample. Estimates 
are reported in Table 5. We find a difference 
of 5.4 percentage points between the treatment 
and control groups, which holds with or without 
controls. 
We also estimate regressions for a dummy 
variable indicating whether the majority of 
courses taken by students are transferable, fol-
lowing the approach of Sengupta and Jepsen 
(2006). We find a difference of 7.1 percent-
age points between the treatment and control 
groups. Including the full set of controls, we 
find a very similar estimate for the treatment 
effect. 
We focus on the probability that a course 
taken is a transferable course in the regressions 
above (conditioning on taking the course). We 
also estimate regressions for the total number 
of courses of any type taken over the sample 
period and the probability of being enrolled 
in each quarter. In both cases, we find no evi-
dence of treatment effects. Thus, the computers 
appear to have affected the types of courses 
taken (i.e., transfer vs. nontransfer), but not the </p>

<p>total number of courses or enrollment at the 
college. 17 </p>

<p>A. Adjusting for Noncompliance </p>

<p>The estimates presented thus far capture the 
ITT from the experiment and do not adjust for 
noncompliance in the treatment and control 
groups. Some of the students in the treatment 
group did not pick up their free computers, 
and some of the students in the control group 
purchased their own computers during the study 
period. Although the ITT estimate is often a 
parameter of interest in evaluating policies to 
address the consequences of disparities in access 
to technology, the "treatment-on-the-treated" 
(TOT), or more general, local average treatment 
effect (LATE) estimates are also of interest. They 
provide estimates of the effects of having a home 
computer on the probability of taking transfer 
courses. 
Of the 141 students in the study that were eli-
gible to receive a free computer, 129 students (or 
92%) actually picked them up from Computers 
for Classrooms. To adjust for this noncompliance 
by the treatment group and obtain the TOT esti-
mate, an instrumental variables (IV) regression is 
estimated. Computer eligibility (winning a free 
computer) is used as an instrumental variable for 
whether the student picked up the free computer. 
The first-stage regression for the probability of 
computer receipt is: </p>

<p>(2) 
C i = ω + γX i + πT i + λ t + u i + ϵ ij . </p>

<p>17. Given these results, we find that mechanically the 
treatment group takes more transferable courses than the 
control group. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>The second-stage regression is: </p>

<p>(3) 
y ij = α 2 + β 2 X i + ΔĈ i + λ t + u i + ϵ ij , </p>

<p>whereĈ i is the predicted value of computer own-
ership from 2. In this case, Δ provides an estimate 
of the TOT effect. The IV estimates for the trans-
fer course rate are reported in Specification 3 of 
Table 4. Given the high compliance rate for stu-
dents in the treatment group, the estimates are 
only slightly larger than the ITT estimate and 
approximate the simple OLS coefficient divided 
by the pick up rate of 92%. 
The control group cannot be prevented from 
purchasing a computer on their own during the 
study period. This problem of the control group 
receiving an intervention that potentially has the 
same effect as the treatment intervention is a sim-
ilar problem in most social experiments. Results 
from the follow-up survey taken at the end of 
the study period indicate that 28% of the control 
group reports getting a new computer, although 
no information is available on when they pur-
chased the computer. The more general LATE 
estimator is used to expand on the TOT estimates. 
Specification 3 can be thought of as implicitly 
assuming that all students in the control group 
received their computers at the end of the study 
period. In Specification 4, we instead assume that 
all of the students in the control group report-
ing obtaining a computer in the follow-up sur-
vey received that computer at the beginning of 
the study period. This new "upper bound" esti-
mate of the LATE is 6.3 percentage points. Given 
this range of IV estimates, the LATE estimate 
is between 0.049 and 0.063, which represents 
8-10% of the mean level of taking transfer-
able courses. The 95% confidence intervals for 
these estimates range from just above zero to </p>

<p>0.099-0.125. We continue to report the LATE 
estimates in all tables, but focus the discussion 
below on the ITT estimates. </p>

<p>B. Impacts on Transfers to 4-Year Colleges </p>

<p>We now turn to estimating the effects of home 
computers on actual transfers to 4-year colleges. 
Although home computers increase the likeli-
hood of taking transferable courses they might 
have a different effect on actual transfers to 4-
year colleges in which students face additional 
constraints. Constraints may include the high 
cost, reduced flexibility in course offerings to 
accommodate working, and more challenging 
coursework of 4-year universities (Council on 
Postsecondary Education 2004). As noted above, 
information on transfers to 4-year colleges is 
obtained from college enrollment data from the 
beginning of the experiment through 4 years later. 
We find that 21.3% of the treatment group trans-
fers to a 4-year college compared with 20.0% 
of the control group. The difference of 1.3 per-
centage points, however, is not statistically sig-
nificant. Table 6 reports estimates of treatment 
effects using 1 for the transfer rate to 4-year col-
leges. After controlling for baseline characteris-
tics, we find a similar point estimate for the treat-
ment effect, but the coefficient is also statistically 
insignificant. Some caution is warranted in inter-
preting these estimates, however, as the 95% con-
fidence intervals are very large. With the full set 
of controls, the confidence interval is −0.081 to 
0.101. Relative to the base transfer rate, this con-
fidence interval ranges from −40% of the con-
trol group mean to +51% of the control group 
mean implying that only very large negative and 
positive treatment effects can be ruled out from 
the experiment. The top end of this confidence </p>

<p>TABLE 6 
4-Year College Transfer Regressions </p>

<p>OLS Estimates 
IV Estimates </p>

<p>Lower Bound 
Upper Bound 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.0128 (0.0485) 
0.0103 (0.0464) 
0.0113 (0.0508) 
0.0145 (0.0655) 
Baseline controls 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Control group mean (Y) 
0.2000 
0.2000 
0.2000 
0.2000 
Sample size 
281 
281 
281 
281 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is whether the student transfers to a 4-year college. Robust standard errors are reported. 
Baseline controls include gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' highest education level, high school grades, presence of own 
children, live with parents, family income, and educational goals. The dependent variable in the first-stage regression in the 
IV model is obtaining a new computer. The lower (upper) bound estimate assumes that all control group noncompliers obtained 
computers at the end (beginning) of the survey period. </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>TABLE 7 
California State University Transfer Regressions </p>

<p>OLS Estimates 
IV Estimates </p>

<p>Lower Bound 
Upper Bound 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.0272 (0.0465) 
0.0274 (0.0446) 
0.0301 (0.0488) 
0.0387 (0.0629) 
Baseline controls 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Control group mean (Y) 
0.1714 
0.1714 
0.1714 
0.1714 
Sample size 
281 
281 
281 
281 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is whether the student transfers to a California State University campus. Robust standard errors 
are reported. Baseline controls include gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' highest education level, high school grades, presence 
of own children, live with parents, family income, and educational goals. The dependent variable in the first-stage regression 
in the IV model is obtaining a new computer. The lower (upper) bound estimate assumes that all control group noncompliers 
obtained computers at the end (beginning) of the survey period. </p>

<p>interval implies extremely large effects: an invest-
ment of $400-500 for a computer would raise 
the probability that a community college student 
transfers to 4-year colleges by one half. 
With these concerns in mind, the magnitudes 
implied by the point estimates for the actual trans-
fer rates are smaller than the magnitudes implied 
by the point estimates for taking transferable 
courses. The coefficient estimates of 0.0103 (with 
controls) and 0.0128 (without controls) for the 
transfer rate represent 5.1-6.4% of the control 
group mean. These point estimates are smaller 
relative to the control group mean than for the 
point estimates on taking transfer courses. The 
point estimates for the treatment effect on taking 
transfer courses represent 7.3% (with controls) 
and 7.8% (without controls) of the control group 
mean. We might expect home computers to have 
a larger effect on influencing interest in transfer-
ring and taking transfer courses than on actual 
transfers. For actual transfers there are likely to be 
many additional constraints, especially the inabil-
ity to pay for higher 4-year college tuition costs. 
The estimates are not precise enough, however, to 
reach a definitive conclusion on this issue. 
Focusing on transfers to public universities 
in California, we also estimate specifications in 
which the dependent variable is whether the stu-
dent transfers to a CSU campus. Transfers to CSU 
campuses capture 90% of all transfers to 4-year 
colleges among study participants. Indeed, one 
of the primary goals of the California community 
college system is to encourage students to trans-
fer to CSU campuses. Additionally, there are no 
transfers to the University of California system in 
the data and some of the transfers to other 4-year 
colleges are to religious or other specialized 
colleges, which could be influenced by different </p>

<p>factors than transfers to the California State Col-
lege system. We find that 19.9% of the treatment 
group transfers to a CSU campus compared with 
17.1% of the control group. Table 7 reports esti-
mates of treatment effect estimates for the CSU 
system. We find larger, positive point estimates, 
but the estimates remain statistically insignifi-
cant. 18 The confidence intervals also remain rela-
tively large, ranging from −0.060 to 0.115 for the 
specification with all of the controls. </p>

<p>C. Power Calculations for Actual Transfer 
Estimates </p>

<p>It is useful to consider how large of a sample 
size would be needed to estimate economically 
meaningful estimates for the actual transfer rate. 
Power calculations are relatively simple when 
comparing two proportions because the variance 
of the treatment and control means are deter-
mined by the base proportion along with the sam-
ple size (i.e., no assumptions about the variance 
of the two means are needed). From the experi-
ment, the control group mean for the actual trans-
fer rate is 0.20, and the point estimates indicate 
treatment effect sizes of roughly 0.010-0.013. 
Table A2 reports power calculations assuming 
different effect sizes. 19 To detect a statistically 
significant effect for a treatment-control differ-
ence of 0.01 at the α = 0.05 level of significance 
it would require a sample size of more than 
25,000 observations. Given the cost of computers 
at $400-500 conducting an experiment with this </p>

<p>18. Consistent with this finding, we find negative point 
treatment estimates (but very imprecise) for the probability of 
transfers to other 4-year colleges (i.e., not a CSU campus). 
19. Power calculations can be performed in <rs type="software">STATA</rs> using 
sampsi or <rs type="software">SAS</rs> using proc power. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>many participants would clearly be prohibitively 
expensive. 20 To detect a treatment-control differ-
ence of 0.02, which is 10% of the control group 
mean, the sample size would have to be 6,510 
observations. The effect size would have to be 
0.10 (or 50% of the control group mean) to be sta-
tistically detectable with sample sizes in the range 
of what is available in this experiment. 
How do we translate these hypothetical treat-
ment effects sizes into whether they are eco-
nomically meaningful, and thus whether we can 
detect economically meaningful treatment effects 
with different sample sizes? One way is to place 
them in the perspective of reducing disparities 
in transfer rates. For example, the state-wide 
difference in transfer rates between underrep-
resented minorities and whites is roughly 10 
percentage points (Sengupta and Jepsen 2006), 
suggesting that a policy intervention that could 
reduce this racial gap by one fifth (a 0.02 treat-
ment effect) would be economically meaningful. 
Another method of assessing the magnitude is to 
examine the total cost of influencing one more 
student to transfer and comparing it to the poten-
tial returns to transferring. A treatment effect of 
0.02 which is 10% of the control group mean 
implies that 50 computers (at a total cost of 
roughly $22,500) would have to be given out to 
increase the number of students transferring by 
1. A total cost of $45,000 would be required to 
induce one more transfer with a treatment effect 
of 0.01 (5% of the control group mean). U.S. Cen-
sus Bureau (2011) estimates indicate that mean 
annual earnings for individuals with a bache-
lor's degree are nearly $25,000 higher than with 
an associate's degree. However, the actual aver-
age returns to transferring are likely to be much 
lower with the uncertainty of obtaining a degree. 
If these returns were only $5,000 per year then 
the total cost of the computers would be recov-
ered in a few years if the treatment effect is 0.02, 
but would take much longer for an effect size of 
0.01. Although it is difficult to determine what an 
economically meaningful effect size would be in 
this context, it appears as though an effect size 
of 0.02 is clearly large, economically meaning-
ful, and policy relevant, but even in this case we 
would need 6,510 observations to obtain statisti-
cal significance. 
For convenience, Table A2 also presents infor-
mation from power calculations in terms of the </p>

<p>20. Nonproportion outcome measures that have high 
variances require especially large sample sizes to reach sta-
tistical significance (see Lewis and Reiley 2011, for an 
example). </p>

<p>confidence intervals generated by the sample size 
of the experiment (N = 286) and a much larger 
sample size (N = 5,000) for the same set of possi-
ble treatment effects. With the sample size used in 
the experiment the confidence intervals on all of 
the effect sizes are large, often around 10 percent-
age points or 50% of the control group mean on 
either side of the estimate. Even in the case of the 
larger sample size with 5,000 observations, which 
would represent a very expensive experiment, the 
sample size is not large enough to detect a 0.01 
or 0.02 treatment effect. The confidence intervals, 
however, would be slightly more than 2 percent-
age points on either side of the estimate (or 10% 
of the control group mean). These power calcu-
lations demonstrate how difficult it is to find a 
statistically significant treatment effect or obtain 
relatively tight confidence intervals for an expen-
sive per-participant experiment. </p>

<p>D. Treatment Heterogeneity by Educational 
Goal </p>

<p>The focus thus far has been on estimating 
the average treatment effect for all study partic-
ipants. The literature on the transfer function of 
community colleges, however, has emphasized 
the importance of controlling for the educational 
goals of community college students (see Leigh 
and Gill 2003, 2007; Alfonso 2006; and Long and 
Kurlaender 2009, for example). Students attend 
community colleges for many different reasons 
potentially placing them at varying levels of risk 
of having a desire to take transfer courses and 
transfer to 4-year colleges. As reported in Table 3 
and discussed above, we find from administrative 
data based on the self-reported educational goals 
of students on their original application to the col-
lege, 37.4% of study participants reported being 
"undecided," 31.5% reported "transfer to a 4-year 
institution," and 24.5% reported a goal other than 
transferring to a 4-year college. Controlling for 
these educational goals has little effect on the 
treatment effect estimates, but there is the pos-
sibility that having a home computer may have 
differential effects on transfer behavior depend-
ing on the initial goals of the student. 
Table 8 provides evidence on this question 
from regressions in which treatment status is 
interacted with the three major educational goals 
at the time of application. The main treatment 
effect captures the treatment effect for the most 
common educational goal, "undecided." For tak-
ing transfer courses, we find that home com-
puters have essentially no effect on "undecided" </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>TABLE 8 
Transfer Course and 4-Year College Transfer Regressions with Interactions for Educational Goals </p>

<p>OLS Estimates </p>

<p>Transfer Course 
4-Year College Transfer </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
−0.0160 (0.0384) 
0.0592 (0.0360) 
0.0202 (0.0776) 
−0.0242 (0.0610) 
Treatment × transfer goal 
0.0740 (0.0572) 
0.0267 (0.1282) 
Treatment × nontransfer goal 
0.1341 (0.0628) 
−0.1412 (0.1078) 
Treatment × above median 
percentage of transferable courses 
taken prior to treatment (fall 2006) </p>

<p>−0.0272 (0.0451) 
0.0640 (0.0957) </p>

<p>Above median percentage of 
transferable courses taken prior to 
treatment (fall 2006) </p>

<p>0.1092 (0.0334) 
0.0452 (0.0687) </p>

<p>Baseline controls 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Mean of dependent variable 
0.6343 
0.6343 
0.2064 
0.2064 
Mean for "unknown'' goal 
0.5812 
0.1667 
Mean for "transfer'' goal 
0.6761 
0.3146 
Mean for "other'' goal 
0.6088 
0.0882 
Sample size 
2,658 
2,658 
281 
281 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is whether the course is transferable to a California State University or University of California 
campus in Specifications 1 and 2 and whether the student transfers to a 4-year college in Specifications 3 and 4. Robust standard 
errors are reported and adjusted for multiple courses taken by study participants. Baseline controls include gender, race/ethnicity, 
age, parents' highest education level, high school grades, presence of own children, live with parents, family income, and 
educational goals. </p>

<p>students. The effects of home computers on tak-
ing transfer courses are stronger, however, for 
students with an initial goal of transferring to a 
4-year college. We also find that students with 
nontransfer goals are relatively more likely to 
take transferable courses when receiving a free 
computer. The computer may have changed their 
goal or simply allowed these students to take 
more challenging and demanding courses at the 
community college. 
We also explore heterogeneity in treatment 
effects on transfers to 4-year colleges by ini-
tial educational goal. Specification 3 of Table 8 
reports these estimates. The results are less clear. 
We find a positive point estimate on the treatment 
interaction with having a transfer goal, but the 
coefficient is small and insignificant. We also find 
a large negative point estimate on the treatment 
interaction with having a nontransfer goal, but the 
coefficient is not significant at conventional levels 
(t-stat = 1.31). Although we should interpret this 
coefficient with some caution, it suggests the pos-
sibility that home computers facilitated these stu-
dents in taking more advanced transfer courses, 
but did not ultimately increase their likelihood of 
transferring to a 4-year college. 
Instead of using educational goals self-
reported by students at the time of application 
as a measure of transfer goals, we can use 
pre-treatment transfer course-taking behavior </p>

<p>in fall 2006. 21 Fall 2006 is generally the first 
year of courses taken for study participants, and 
course choices for this term were made prior 
to when the computers were distributed, which 
was in October and November 2006. We create a 
variable that measures the percentage of courses 
taken in fall 2006 that are transferable for each 
student. The average value for this variable is 
60.5% for the control group and 61.4% for the 
treatment group. The difference of 0.9% is small 
and not statistically significant. We interact a 
dummy variable indicating whether the student 
had a fall 2006 transfer course percentage higher 
than the median (0.67) and treatment status, 
and include it in the regressions reported in 
Specifications 2 and 4 of Table 8. For the trans-
fer course regression we find a positive main 
effect of computers, but find a small negative 
and insignificant coefficient on treatment inter-
acted with taking a large percentage of transfer 
courses prior to treatment. In the actual transfer 
regression, we find a small negative coefficient 
on the main treatment effect and a large positive 
coefficient on the treatment effect interacted with 
taking a large percentage of transfer courses in 
fall 2006. Although the interaction coefficients </p>

<p>21. Sengupta and Jepsen (2006) argue that first-year 
course taking represents a more reliable measure of transfer 
goals than responses on the application form. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 9 
College Search Regressions </p>

<p>OLS Estimates 
IV Estimates </p>

<p>Lower Bound 
Upper Bound 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Treatment 
0.0921 (0.0717) 
0.1090 (0.0709) 
0.1194 (0.0777) 
0.1539 (0.1001) 
Baseline controls 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Control group mean (Y) 
0.3409 
0.3409 
0.3409 
0.3409 
Sample size 
185 
185 
185 
185 </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is whether students used computers to search for information on colleges. Robust standard 
errors are reported. Baseline controls include gender, race/ethnicity, age, parents' highest education level, high school grades, 
presence of own children, live with parents, family income, and educational goals. The dependent variable in the first-stage 
regression in the IV model is obtaining a new computer. The lower (upper) bound estimate assumes that all control group 
noncompliers obtained computers at the end (beginning) of the survey period. </p>

<p>are not precisely measured, they line up with 
the findings for treatment interactions with the 
educational goals students reported at the time of 
application to the college. 
Overall, we find some suggestive evidence 
indicating that home computers might have 
helped community college students with the goal 
of transferring more in taking transfer courses 
and ultimately transferring to a 4-year college. 22 
For community college students who did not 
have the goal of transferring, home computers 
may have encouraged them to take more chal-
lenging and demanding transfer courses, but had 
no differential effect on actual transfers. Unfortu-
nately, we cannot draw strong conclusions from 
any of these results because of the general lack 
of precision of estimates. </p>

<p>E. College Search </p>

<p>Students receiving free computers may have 
been more likely to search for information about 
colleges because of the increased time, flexibil-
ity, and autonomy of use offered by having a 
home computer. Finding more information about 
4-year college choices, requirements, financial 
aid, and what courses are transferable may repre-
sent one of the main reasons computer recipients 
are more likely to take transferable courses. It 
also might explain why treatment students have 
a higher level of actual transfers (although we 
note again the lack of statistical significance). 
On the follow-up survey, we asked students what 
they used computers for in the past month. 23 In </p>

<p>22. We also examine treatment heterogeneity by race 
and gender. Jepsen (2008) finds differences in 2-and 4-year 
college completion rates by race and gender. We find no 
evidence of different effects by race or gender. 
23. We conducted a follow-up survey of study partici-
pants (treatment and control) in late spring/summer 2008 with </p>

<p>particular, we asked them whether they searched 
for information about college choices. We found 
that the treatment group was nearly 10 per-
centage points more likely to report searching 
for college information than the control group 
in spring/summer 2008. Among the treatment 
group, 43.3% of students reported searching for 
college information in the past month compared 
with 34.1% of the control group. The difference, 
however, is not statistically significant at conven-
tional levels. 
From a regression analysis reported in Table 9, 
we find that the treatment effect estimate is not 
sensitive to the inclusion of controls. We find 
that the treatment group has a 10.9 percentage 
point higher likelihood of searching for college 
information than the control group. Although the 
difference is not significant at conventional lev-
els for a two-tailed test (the p value is .126 for 
a two-tailed test), the point estimate suggests a 
potentially large effect. The point estimates imply 
an effect of 9.2-10.9 percentage points. These 
point estimates imply large effects relative to the 
average probability of searching for college infor-
mation among the control group of 34.1%, but 
the confidence intervals are also large. The confi-
dence interval for the treatment effect estimates 
including controls is [−0.030 to 0.248]. Power 
calculations indicate that slightly larger sample 
sizes would be needed to detect a statistically sig-
nificant treatment effect given the control group 
mean of 0.34 and an effect size of 10 percent-
age points. The detection of smaller treatment </p>

<p>a response rate of 65%. The baseline characteristics of the 
respondent sample look roughly similar to those of the full 
sample (see Fairlie and London 2012). The response rate was 
61% for the control group and 69% for the treatment group. 
The difference is not statistically significant. </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>effects, however, would require much larger sam-
ple sizes. 
These findings are consistent with previous 
qualitative research indicating the importance 
of computers and the Internet for acquiring 
college information (Jones 2009; Owens 2007; 
Venegas 2007). Venegas (2007) finds that the 
Internet is used extensively by students in the 
search and application process for college and 
financial aid. She finds that low-income students 
in her study were at a major disadvantage in 
applying to colleges and for financial aid because 
of their lack of access to computers at school 
and home. In her study of African American 
students, Jones (2009) finds that middle-class 
families have better access to computers at home 
than working-class families, and take advan-
tage of this access to search more for college 
information. There is also direct evidence on the 
extensive use of technology among community 
college students, especially with colleges' online 
systems, to help in the transfer process to 4-year 
colleges (Owens 2007). In contrast, there is 
some evidence of the varying, "haphazard," or 
"accidental" quality of transfer counseling at 
community colleges (Dowd and Gabbard 2006), 
and criticism of transfer advising because of 
the use of part-time faculty and large caseloads 
(Council on Postsecondary Education 2004). 
The increased flexibility, time, and autonomy 
offered by having access to a home computer may 
enable low-income community college students 
to expand their ability to search for information 
about 4-year colleges. 24 Although home comput-
ers also improve the ability to search for infor-
mation about 2-year degrees and certificates, the 
relative effect may be much lower because these 
students are already enrolled in a community col-
lege where nonelectronic information is readily 
available on campus. Improving college search 
might be an important mechanism for the causal 
relationship between home computers and tak-
ing transferable courses, although there is also 
the possibility that it reflects another measure of 
desire to transfer. </p>

<p>V. CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>Rapidly rising tuition costs and recent calls to 
expand 2-year college enrollments suggest that 
community colleges will provide an increasingly </p>

<p>24. Having access to a home computer may be especially 
useful for finding financial aid and scholarship information 
(Grazzi and Vergara 2009a, 2009b). </p>

<p>important transfer function to 4-year colleges. 
Community colleges in some states, such as Cal-
ifornia, already play a major role in university 
education with nearly half of all 4-year col-
lege students having previously attended a com-
munity college (California Community Colleges 
Chancellor's Office 2009). In this paper, we use 
data from the first-ever randomized field exper-
iment providing free computers to students for 
home use to explore whether having access to 
home computers improves the transfer function 
of community colleges. If limited information is 
an important constraint for transferring to 4-year 
colleges, especially among low-income commu-
nity college students, then having access to com-
puters at home may help overcome this barrier 
and lead to higher labor market returns. 
The results from the field experiment indi-
cate that the treatment group of students receiv-
ing free computers to use at home has a 4.8 
percentage point higher probability of taking 
transferable courses than the control group of stu-
dents not receiving free computers. Of courses 
taken by the treatment group, 66% are transfer-
able to CSU or UC campuses compared with 61% 
of courses taken by the control group. Control-
ling for baseline characteristics does not change 
the conclusion-the treatment group of students 
receiving free computers has a 4.5 percentage 
point higher likelihood of taking transferable 
courses. LATE estimates of the effects of having 
a home computer on taking transferable courses 
range from 4.9 to 6.3 percentage points. 
The results are less clear for the effects of 
home computers on actual transfers to 4-year col-
leges. We find positive point estimates for the 
treatment effect on actual transfers, but the esti-
mates are not statistically significant. The confi-
dence intervals for these estimates are wide and 
only rule out very large negative and large pos-
itive effects. Power calculations also reveal that 
large, prohibitively expensive sample sizes would 
be needed to obtain statistical significance unless 
the point estimates were larger. 
Although the sample sizes would have to be 
considerably larger to reach statistical signifi-
cance, the point estimates provide some sugges-
tive evidence that the effects of home computers 
might be smaller on actual transfer rates than 
the effects on taking transferable courses. Home 
computers may have changed the desire to trans-
fer or increased student confidence in taking more 
challenging and demanding transfer courses, but 
other barriers to transferring to 4-year colleges 
were just too large. Barriers such as the cost of </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>4-year colleges, added challenge of taking 4-year 
college courses, and lack of courses offered to 
accommodate nontraditional or working students 
might be especially restrictive (Council on Post-
secondary Education 2004). We find some evi-
dence that students who did not initially have 
a goal of transferring to a 4-year college had 
larger positive effects from the computers than 
undecided and transfer goal students. We also 
find some suggestive evidence that students with 
transfer goals benefit more from home computers 
in terms of increasing their likelihood of transfer-
ring to 4-year colleges. 
We also find suggestive evidence that col-
lege search increases from receiving home com-
puters. Point estimates indicate that the treat-
ment group has a roughly 10 percentage point 
higher probability of using a computer to search 
for college information than the control group 
(although again confidence intervals are large). 
The expanded ability of low-income community 
college students to find information about 4-year 
colleges may represent one of the mechanisms 
by which home computers increase transferable 
course taking. 
Although there is concern that information 
constraints may limit interest in and the likeli-
hood of transferring to 4-year colleges among </p>

<p>low-income community college students, there is 
little direct evidence on the question. The find-
ings from this experiment suggest that having 
access to a home computer may be useful for find-
ing information about 4-year university choices, 
admission requirements, tuition, financial aid, 
and which courses are transferable, which ulti-
mately may counteract some of the "diversion" 
effects of attending a community college. The 
1.2 million community college students in the 
United States without access to home comput-
ers and the Internet, however, may be at a dis-
advantage in acquiring information helpful for 
transferring to 4-year universities and obtaining 
jobs requiring these skills. To overcome this bar-
rier, policies that provide access to computers for 
low-income students, such as tax breaks or spe-
cial loans for educational computer purchases, 
expanded computer refurbishing programs, and 
laptop checkout programs may be needed (Ser-
von 2002, Warschauer 2006). Addressing this 
barrier may become increasingly important as 
more application, financial aid, registration and 
course information is being placed online and 
public institutions reduce staff in response to bud-
get cutbacks. More research on these important 
questions, preferably with larger sample sizes, is 
clearly needed. </p>

<p>APPENDIX </p>

<p>TABLE A1 
Number of Transferable Courses for CSU and UC Campuses by Department </p>

<p>CSU or UC 
Transferable </p>

<p>Department Code 
Title 
N 
% </p>

<p>Total Number of 
Courses Offered </p>

<p>Total 
673 
71 
942 
AB 
Agricultural Business 
6 
100 
6 
ACCT 
Accounting 
6 
55 
11 
ADS 
Addiction Studies 
17 
100 
17 
AET 
Agricultural Engineering Technology 
8 
80 
10 
AGR 
Agriculture 
1 
17 
6 
AGS 
Agricultural Science 
4 
80 
5 
AJ 
Administration of Justice 
13 
100 
13 
AJLE 
AJ-Law Enforcement 
0 
0 
6 
AJS 
Agriculture Job Skills 
1 
0 
1 
ALH 
Allied Health 
1 
33 
3 
ANS 
Animal Science 
3 
100 
3 
ANTH 
Anthropology 
8 
100 
8 
ART 
Art 
57 
89 
64 
AUT 
Automotive Technology 
22 
81 
27 
BCIS 
Business and Computer Information Systems 
31 
60 
52 
BIOL 
Biological Sciences 
12 
86 
14 
BIT 
Building Inspection Technology 
6 
86 
7 
BUS 
Business 
13 
87 
15 
CDF 
Child Development and Family Relations 
32 
80 
40 
CHEM 
Chemistry 
6 
86 
7 
CLP 
Career Life Planning 
3 
38 
8 </p>

<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>



<p>TABLE A1 
Continued </p>

<p>CSU or UC 
Transferable </p>

<p>Department Code 
Title 
N 
% </p>

<p>Total Number of 
Courses Offered </p>

<p>COS 
Cosmetology 
0 
0 
4 
CS 
Career Skills 
0 
0 
2 
CSCI 
Computer Science 
28 
90 
31 
CSL 
Counseling 
4 
100 
4 
DFT 
Drafting and CAD Technology 
5 
100 
5 
DRAM 
Drama 
8 
53 
15 
DSPS 
Disabled Student Programs and Services 
0 
0 
6 
ECON 
Economics 
5 
100 
5 
EDUC 
Education 
2 
29 
7 
EH 
Environmental Horticulture 
10 
71 
14 
EMT 
Emergency Medical Technology 
0 
0 
4 
ENGL 
English 
11 
85 
13 
ENGR 
Engineering 
7 
100 
7 
FASH 
Fashion 
10 
91 
11 
FN 
Food and Nutrition 
2 
67 
3 
FREN 
French 
2 
50 
4 
FSC 
Fire Science 
17 
52 
33 
GEOG 
Geography 
8 
100 
8 
GEOL 
Geology 
3 
100 
3 
GERM 
German 
4 
100 
4 
HIST 
History 
11 
100 
11 
HLTH 
Health 
1 
100 
1 
HMT 
Environmental Technology 
0 
0 
4 
HON 
Honors 
6 
100 
6 
HUM 
Humanities 
4 
100 
4 
ID 
Interior Design 
13 
100 
13 
IDST 
Interdisciplinary Studies 
2 
67 
3 
ITAL 
Italian 
2 
50 
4 
JOUR 
Journalism 
2 
100 
2 
JPN 
Japanese 
4 
100 
4 
LATN 
Latin 
3 
100 
3 
LEAD 
Language Education/Development 
0 
0 
23 
LIS 
Library and Information Science 
1 
100 
1 
LM 
Life Management 
1 
100 
1 
MATH 
Mathematics 
14 
64 
22 
MCS 
Multicultural Studies 
2 
100 
2 
MS 
Machine Shop 
1 
33 
3 
MSP 
Multimedia Studies Program 
7 
64 
11 
MUS 
Music 
13 
100 
13 
NR 
Natural Resources 
8 
100 
8 
NSG 
Nursing 
32 
97 
33 
PE 
Physical Education 
47 
43 
110 
PHIL 
Philosophy 
8 
100 
8 
PHO 
Photography 
13 
93 
14 
PHYS 
Physics 
9 
100 
9 
PLS 
Plant Science 
4 
100 
4 
POS 
Political Science 
6 
100 
6 
PSC 
Physical Science 
7 
100 
7 
PSY 
Psychology 
12 
100 
12 
READ 
Reading 
1 
33 
3 
REC 
Recreation 
1 
100 
1 
RLS 
Real Estate 
7 
100 
7 
RT 
Respiratory Therapy 
0 
0 
13 
RTVF 
Radio, Television, and Film 
9 
100 
9 
SBM 
Small Business Management 
0 
0 
3 
SOC 
Sociology 
9 
90 
10 
SPAN 
Spanish 
5 
71 
7 
SPCH 
Speech Communication 
4 
80 
5 
SPE 
Special Education 
0 
0 
4 
TOUR 
Tourism and Travel 
13 
93 
14 
WKE 
Work Experience 
0 
0 
1 
WLD 
Welding 
15 
88 
17 </p>

<p>Note: Based on administrative data from Butte College. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE A2 
Power Calculations for Experiment Control Group Sample Proportion = 0.20 </p>

<p>Confidence Interval 
Confidence Interval </p>

<p>N = 286 
N = 5,000 </p>

<p>Treatment-Control Difference N Needed for Statistical Significance Lower 
Upper 
Lower 
Upper </p>

<p>0.00 
−0.093 
0.093 
−0.022 
0.022 
0.01 
25,583 
−0.084 
0.104 
−0.012 
0.032 
0.02 
6,510 
−0.074 
0.114 
−0.003 
0.043 
0.05 
1,094 
−0.047 
0.147 
0.027 
0.073 
0.10 
294 
0.000 
0.200 
0.076 
0.124 
0.20 
82 
0.096 
0.304 
0.175 
0.225 </p>

<p>Notes: All power calculations are for proportion outcomes and assumed 0.05 level of significance, 0.8 power, and no continuity 
correction. In STATA used sampsi and SAS used proc power. </p>



<p>FAIRLIE &amp; GRUNBERG: COMPUTERS AND TRANSFERS </p>





</text></tei>