<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1515%2Fjbnst-2017-1004" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Linking data on the same units (such as persons, enterprises or patents) is 
an increasingly popular research strategy, also in the social sciences (Schnell,  2014b). Since in many cases the required information resides in different organ-
izations, for many applications, a central linkage unit is needed as trusted third 
party. Because of the federal structure of Germany and the strict data protection 
jurisdiction, the legal requirements for a linkage operation have to be negoti-
ated for each project separately. Due to this obstacle, no general purpose central 
linking unit has been available in Germany. 
To foster the application of record linkage in the social sciences, the last 
author and Stefan Bender, the former director of the Research Data Centre (FDZ) 
of the German Federal Employment Agency at the Institute for Employment 
Research (IAB), applied for a research grant at the German Research Foundation 
(DFG) in 2010. They were awarded with this research grant in 2011 to establish the 
first academic data linkage facility in Germany. 1 The focus of the group in Duis-
burg was research and development of record linkage methods, while the group 
at the IAB primarily provided services like consulting of and conducting record </p>

<p>1 The DFG grants were awarded to Rainer Schnell (SCHN 586/17-2) and Stefan Bender (BE 3172/1-
2). The funding for the two groups ended in 2016 and 2015, respectively. </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: Rainer Schnell, Research Methodology Group, University Duisburg-
Essen, Duisburg, Germany, E-mail: rainer.schnell@uni-due.de 
Manfred Antoni, Research Data Centre (FDZ), Institute for Employment Research (IAB), Regens-
burger Str. 100, D-90478 Nuremberg, Germany, E-mail: manfred.antoni@iab.de </p>

<p>Open Access. © 2017 Antoni and Schnell, published by De Gruyter. 
This work is licensed under 
the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 License. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>

<p>linkages commissioned by academic institutions. The main goal of the GRLC was 
to increase the number of record linkage applications using administrative data, 
especially within -but not limited to -the social sciences. Furthermore, GRLC 
aimed for internationally leading research in record-linkage methodology. </p>

<p>2 Research and development </p>

<p>2.1 Research </p>

<p>Research within the GRLC focused on two topics, which are central to most record 
linkage problems: Computational speed and privacy. Since most linkage projects 
involving more than one data holding agency have to use encrypted identifiers 
(names etc.), record linkage in these cases is usually based on encrypted iden-
tifiers. This field of research is called privacy preserving record linkage or PPRL 
(Vatsalan et al., 2013). </p>

<p>2.1.1 High-speed PPRL </p>

<p>We systematically compared different approaches for high-speed PPRL (Schnell,  2013, 2014a; Sehili et al., 2015). In large record-linkage operations not all pos-
sible pairs of records are being compared, but only subsets (blocks). The choice 
of these blocks is an active field of research within record-linkage (Christen, 2012). 
The current recommendation (Schnell, 2015) for linking with encrypted identifi-
ers are multibit-trees (Kristensen et al., 2010) with additional encrypted identifiers 
such as year of birth as blocking variable. Combing external blocks such as year 
of birth with multi-bit trees allows for privacy preserving linkage of two census 
scale data sets within a few hours (Schnell, 2014a). For most applications, this 
solution is sufficient with regard to speed, accuracy and privacy (Brown et al.,  2017). Therefore, this combination is provided with the record-linkage software of 
the GRLC (see Section 2.2). </p>

<p>2.1.2 Security against de-anonymization </p>

<p>However, the more important challenge in PPRL is security against de-
anonymization attacks and privacy (Vatsalan et al., 2014). Although not one 
real-world attack on research data bases has been reported in the scientific 
literature (Emam et al., 2011), academic research focuses on attacks within the 
linkage unit. Therefore, the resilience of PPRL encodings against all known 
cryptographic attacks is widely considered as essential for the successful imple-</p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>

<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>



<p>mentation of PPRL protocols. It has to be noted that the accepted practice of 
record linkage within cancer registries in Germany would fail these criteria. 
This is due to the fact that a simple alignment of the most frequent names 
and the most frequent encoded names would identify at least some records 
(Domingo-Ferrer and Muralidhar, 2016). Therefore, research on privacy within 
the GRLC concentrated on technical measures to prevent these kinds of attacks 
(Niedermeyer et al., 2014; Schnell and Borgs, 2016). The currently recommended 
parameter settings (Christen et al., 2017) yield encryptions which can not be 
successfully attacked by any known method. However, in general, there are no 
absolute guarantees in cryptography: </p>

<p>"Breakthroughs in cryptanalysis can happen suddenly and unexpectedly (. . . ). We can 
choose to design cryptographic primitives [functions, MA/RS] conservatively, but we can 
never guarantee security against an unknown future" (Martin, 2012, p. 69). </p>

<p>Therefore, data custodians have to be convinced that the privacy demands of the 
EU privacy regulation are met. These regulations do not require absolute anonym-
ization, but demands that "(. . . ) costs of and the amount of time required for 
identification, taking into consideration the available technology" has to be con-
sidered in evaluating pseudonymisation techniques (Council of European Union, 
2016, art 26). 
The effort required to break the currently recommend encryption within a 
linkage unit is considered by current research as more than sufficient to fulfill this 
EU criterion. Thus, the remaining problem is the actual implementation within a 
national framework (see Section 2.3). </p>

<p>2.1.3 Data quality </p>

<p>Finally, a further line of research uses record linkage to study data quality. Since 
access to administrative data is required for this kind of research, this field is 
tackled by GRLC staff at the IAB. This research uses linked data to determine and 
quantify errors or sources of bias in either of the originally distinct data sources. 
Along these lines, Sakshaug et al. (2017) describe the linkage of paradata on the 
gross sample of a large household panel study to administrative data of the IAB. 
Based on these data, their future work will focus on, for instance, the utility of 
such linked data for nonresponse bias adjustments for survey data. Alternatively, 
ongoing research focuses on the quality of linked data themselves, which may be 
affected by linkage consent bias, low quality of linkage identifiers and a resulting 
imperfect linkage result. The overview by Sakshaug and Antoni (2017) puts such 
potential linkage errors into the context of a more comprehensive total survey 
error framework. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>

<p>2.2 Linkage software </p>

<p>During the last decade, the research group of the second author has developed 
a Java program for record linkage called <rs id="software-6" type="software">Merge Toolbox</rs> (MTB, <rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Schnell</rs> et al.,  2004). GRLC has extended the capabilities of the program by including routines 
for privacy preserving record linkage (Schnell et al., 2009), special routines 
for self-generated-identification codes (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Schnell</rs> et al., 2010) and updated the 
input/output-options so that <rs id="software-7" type="software">MTB</rs> is able to read and write CSV files and native 
binary Stata-15 files. <rs type="software">MTB</rs> consists of different modules such as a data editor for 
record linkage and the main linkage module. Since 2012, <rs type="software">MTB</rs> has been down-
loaded by 1104 researchers. <rs type="software">MTB</rs> is discussed in the leading textbook on record 
linkage by Christen (2012). An implementation of multibit-trees for privacy pre-
serving record linkage based on Bloomfilters (Schnell, 2015) is provided as a C++ 
stand-alone program and as a library for R. 
Due to the research on privacy preserving record linkage within the GRLC, 
many new functions for encrypting linkage keys have been developed (Schnell  and Borgs, 2016). These new functions have not been implemented in <rs type="software">MTB</rs>, but 
in a new R library <rs type="software">PPRL</rs>. Since record linkage often involves large datasets with 
millions of records, most functions within <rs type="software">PPRL</rs> have been been optimized for 
speed using C++ as the main language. The <rs type="software">PPRL</rs> library will be released within 
2017 as an open-source project. </p>

<p>2.3 The politics of implementing a prototype for population 
covering privacy preserving record linkage in Germany </p>

<p>Administrative databases covering the whole population are rare within Germany. 
Accessing those databases for research purposes is a challenging problem. Due 
to the federal structure, most databases are scattered across the federal states 
(Bundesländer). Therefore, only the registries of social security administrations 
have regularly been used as population covering databases. 2 Due to the lack 
of actual regular data linkages across different federal states or across different 
organizations, data custodians often reject research proposals since no prototype 
for such linkages exist in Germany. The Duisburg group of the GRLC therefore 
tried to implement such a prototype for more than a decade. </p>

<p>2 Of course, even these are incomplete: Persons not covered by the general social security system 
(children, civil servants and self-employed) are not within these databases. However, in Ger-
many, even medical research databases including cancer registries operate within federal states 
and not nationwide. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>

<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>



<p>Each year, about 714,000 births occur in about 750 hospitals in Germany. For 
each birth, about 400 medical variables are collected ('perinatal data'). Since 
about 110,000 newborns are assigned to further medical treatment, additional 
data ('neonatal data') is available for these cases. These two datasets are linked 
nationwide. However, about 20% of the records can not be linked due to the lack 
of information to discriminate between similar records (Schnell and Borgs, 2015). 
The organization responsible for this linkage is a federal institution, the Federal 
Joint Committee ('Gemeinsamer Bundesverband', GBA). 3 Hence it has been sug-
gested by a technical working group consisting of medical, mathematical and 
record linkage experts to include more information, for example an encrypted 
version of the name of the mother to the two datasets (Schnell et al., 2015). As 
researchers of the Federal Institute for Data Security (BSI) have been involved in 
the proposal, it has been adopted by the GBA (Gemeinsamer Bundesausschuss,  2015). The Duisburg group of the GRLC is involved in the technical implement-
ation of the procedure (Meier et al., 2017). This implementation will be the first 
population covering record linkage in Germany using modern methods of PPRL. 
This linkage model has also been suggested for the planned German National 
Mortality Register (Rat für Sozial-und Wirtschaftsdaten, 2011). GRLC has been 
consulted repeatedly as technical experts by the Working Group for the Mortality 
Registry of the of German Data Forum (RatSWD) and the commercial advisor (Pro-
gnos, 2013) for the Federal Ministry of Health. Although the federal government 
failed for two legislation periods to pass the bill for the registry, we are confident 
that it will happen within the next legislation period and that it will be based on 
methods developed within the GRLC. </p>

<p>2.4 International cooperation </p>

<p>During the last decade, record linkage has received an increasing amount of 
attention in official statistics, medicine, economics, demography and the social 
sciences. Researchers have begun to meet on international conferences on record 
linkage and established a first international organization, the International Pop-
ulation Data Linkage Network (IPDLN). GRLC has been one of the earliest institu-
tional members of this group and attended all conferences organized by IPDLN. In 
2017, IPDLN started its own journal, the International Journal of Population Data 
Science (IJPDS). The journal's first issue contains the conference proceedings of 
the IPDLN conference in 2016 and contains four extended abstracts of present-
ations by members of the GRLC. In 2016, a British group initiated a six month </p>

<p>3 For details, see www.english.g-ba.de. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>

<p>workshop at the Isaac Newton Institute for Mathematical Studies in Cambridge, 
to which international researchers in record linkage methodology were invited. 
During this workshop, members of GRLC started cooperations with record-linkage 
research groups in Vancouver, Canberra and Perth. GRLC applied for research 
grants with all three groups. Due to this collaborative efforts, two joint papers 
have been published so far (Brown et al., 2017; Christen et al., 2017). </p>

<p>2.5 Future research </p>

<p>Concerning methodological problems, GRLC will focus future research on solu-
tions for record linkage despite (some) missing identifiers (Ong et al., 2014) and 
cryptographic techniques for making attacks on encrypted identifiers even harder 
than today (Schnell and Borgs, 2016). In collaboration with the Canadian and 
Australian partners, GRLC will develop and test PPRL solutions for census scale 
data bases. Moreover, the research collaboration of the IAB group with the Leib-
niz Institute for Educational Trajectories (LIfBi) and the University of Manchester 
on issues of linkage errors and data quality will be continued. </p>

<p>3 Services </p>

<p>3.1 Completed linkage projects </p>

<p>During the period funded by the German Research Foundation, both groups of 
the GRLC have conducted numerous linkages on behalf of third parties. The 
linked data originated from a variety of sources such as individual, household 
or establishment surveys, administrative data (mainly from the IAB), commer-
cial company data and publicly available data (e.g., German higher education 
institutions). Table 1 lists some examples of completed linkage projects. </p>

<p>3.2 Future linkage projects </p>

<p>While the GRLC was funded by the DFG, all linkage projects could be performed 
free of charge. Since the DFG funding ended, any future linkage project done by 
either group of the GRLC have to be financed either directly by funds of a client or 
by third-party funding acquired in collaboration with the GRLC. 
The effort necessary for and the feasibility of a linkage project strongly 
depends on the number and size of the databases to be linked, on the availability </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>

<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>



<p>Table 1: Examples of completed linkage projects. 
Project partner </p>

<p>Description </p>

<p>Reference </p>

<p>BMAS, LIfBi 
Linkage of waves 4 and 5 of Starting Cohort 6 of </p>

<p>National Educational Panel Study </p>

<p>(NEPS) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Bureau van Dijk, IAB 
Linkage of Bureau van Dijk's company database </p>

<p>Orbis to administrative estab-</p>

<p>lishment data of the IAB </p>

<p>Schild (2016) </p>

<p>IAB </p>

<p>Linkage of waves 1 and 5-8 of Panel Study </p>

<p>Labour Market and Social Security </p>

<p>(PASS) to administrative data of the IAB </p>

<p>Antoni and Bethmann (2014) </p>

<p>IAB, Leibniz-Institute for Economic 
Research (RWI), SOEP 
Geocoding of administrative data of the IAB, creation of cluster data to measure 
neighbourhood effects </p>

<p>Bügelmeyer et al. (2015), </p>

<p>Scholz et al. (2012) </p>

<p>Federal Joint Committee (GBA) 
Consultation and support for the establishment of a national perinatal register </p>

<p>Schnell et al. (2015) </p>

<p>German Institute for Economic Research 
(DIW) </p>

<p>Linkage of establishment survey 
SOEP-LEE to administrative establishment data </p>

<p>of the IAB </p>

<p>Eberle and Weinhardt (2016), 
Weinhardt et al. (2017) </p>

<p>German Institute for Economic Research 
(DIW), IAB, Socio-Economic Panel (SOEP) 
Deriving areas with specific shares of migrant population using geocoding as a 
basis for the 
IAB-SOEP migrant sample </p>

<p>Kroh et al. (2015) </p>

<p>Gesis </p>

<p>Linkage of 
PIAAC-L survey data with administrative employment data of the IAB </p>

<p>Perry and Rammstedt (2016) b </p>

<p>Max Planck Institute for Research on Col-
lective Goods 
Linkage of data on state exams in law from the Hamm Court of Appeals and the 
Faculty of Law of the University of Münster </p>

<p>Towfigh et al. (2014) </p>

<p>Munich Institute for the Economics of 
Aging (MEA) </p>

<p>Linkage of 
Saving and Old-Age Provision in Germany (SAVE) survey data to </p>

<p>administrative employment data of the IAB </p>

<p>Coppola and Lamla (2013) </p>

<p>Office for quality assurance in Hesse 
(GQH) 
Record linkage of distinct databases on three levels of stroke therapy </p>

<p>Gramlich (2014) </p>

<p>University of Bielefeld, Collaborative 
Research Center (SFB) 882 
Linkage of survey data of respondents and their partners to administrative 
employment data of the IAB </p>

<p>Schild and Antoni (2014) </p>

<p>University of Mannheim 
Linkage of company data on private equity transactions to administrative estab-
lishment data of the IAB </p>

<p>Antoni et al. (2017) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The linkage of previous waves way done by the NEPS working group at the IAB. The resulting data set NEPS-SC6-ADIAB will be made available by the 
research data centers of IAB and LIfBi in 2018. See Fuß et al. (2016) for more details on the NEPS. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The linked data set called PIAAC-L-ADIAB is available to members of the PIAAC-Leibniz-Network (PIAAC-LN) through the FDZ at the IAB. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>

<p>of and legal restrictions regarding access to linkage identifiers and on regula-
tions regarding subsequent access to the linked data. The required personnel 
resources and therefore funding for a linkage project as well as its very feasib-
ility will therefore have to be determined on a project-by-project basis. We thus 
encourage potential scientific clients or cooperation partners to contact the GRLC 
to discuss the feasibility of any linkage ideas. 4  Due to administrative constraints of the GRLC hosting institutions, any link-
age project will have to cover personnel and overhead costs of GRLC staff for at 
least three months full-time equivalent. Even if these financial requirements are 
fulfilled, a requested linkage project has to be declined by the GRLC if not all legal 
requirements for a linkage are met. Finally, since both GRLC hosting institutions 
are public organizations, GRLC might have to decline a linkage project due to 
other duties. However, both GRLC units welcome suggestions for collaborations 
on linkage projects. </p>

<p>3.3 Data access </p>

<p>In general, all clients or project partners of the GRLC retain access to their respect-
ive linked data. Depending on the legal or proprietary restrictions governing the 
original databases, storage of and access to the linked data are implemented in 
different ways. If clients own or are allowed to store all elements of the linked data 
at their own institution, no restrictions arise from the linkage by the GRLC. How-
ever, depending on the project, access to some or all components of the linked 
data may be restricted, for instance by legal issues. In these cases, the result-
ing linked data cannot be shared with researchers outside of the original project 
context. Since all GRLC linkages of data covered by privacy regulations are done 
within the Research Data Centre (FDZ) of the Federal Employment Agency, the 
legal rules of the FDZ may apply to these datasets. 
The FDZ provides cost-free access to several linked data sets to the gen-
eral scientific community (see, for instance, Antoni and Seth, 2012; Antoni and  Bethmann, 2014; Trübswetter and Fendel, 2016). Some of the underlying linkage 
operations were done by members of the GRLC, some by staff of the FDZ after con-
sulting the GRLC. Access to these and other linked standard data sets of the FDZ 
is provided through the FDZ's secure infrastructure. As the administrative data of 
the IAB are subject to strict social security data protection (see Hochfellner et al.,  2014), access to such linked data is limited to on-site use or remote access. 5 </p>

<p>4 Any request should be addressed to contact@record-linkage.de. 
5 See Eberle et al. (2017) or http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Data_Access.aspx for more details. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>

<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>



<p>While FDZ's standard data sets can be accessed by academic researchers 
without any fee, this does not apply to custom-built data sets linked by the GRLC. 
As described above, data access of researchers that own all elements of the linked 
data is not affected by data linkage. In such cases, linked data can be stored and 
accessed within any environment permissible for the underlying data. However, 
as soon as external data are linked with data of the IAB, the combined data may 
not leave the secure computing environment of the FDZ. As FDZ's potential access 
modes for linked data, on-site use and remote data access, both require extensive 
output checking to comply with data protection requirements, access to any cus-
tomized linked data will be restricted to the project group of the respective client 
and will be subject to an additional fee. </p>

<p>3.4 Consulting and training </p>

<p>Members of the GRLC have conducted several training workshops on methods 
of record linkage, both in Germany and different international contexts. These 
workshops covered a broad range of topics like the prototypical record linkage 
process, preprocessing, blocking, comparison, classification, privacy preserving 
record linkage and software options. The training format ranged from university 
classes over short workshops of up to two days (e.g., within the Joint Program 
in Survey Methodology, JPSM) to online workshops with video-recorded lectures 
and live online sessions. 6  Within the limits of professional courtesy, the GRLC will continue to consult 
academic researchers on topics such as record linkage techniques, the wording of 
linkage consent questions, the general feasibility of linkage projects or on suitable 
software solutions. While such a limited consulting will remain free of charge, any 
more extensive form of knowledge transfer will be fee-based. 7 </p>

<p>3.5 Online information portal </p>

<p>The GRLC hosts the website www.record-linkage.de. The site contains about 50 
pages of information (in English) on record-linkage methodology in general, on 
privacy preserving record-linkage, record-linkage projects in Germany and record-
linkage software. All software and papers (co-)authored by members of the GRLC 
are available for download. </p>

<p>6 See, for instance, https://survey-data-science.net/courses/all/introduction-record-linkage-
big-data-applications. 
7 Institutions interested in receiving or hosting a training workshop by members of the GRLC are 
encouraged to address requests to contact@record-linkage.de. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:48 PM </p>



<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>

<p>4 Future prospects </p>

<p>The advantages of linking multiple surveys, of linking surveys with existing data-
bases or of linking multiple existing databases containing information on the 
same units are obvious. Since the amount of information on persons or institu-
tions is increasing, the demand for record linkage will increase as well. The new 
data protection regulation of the EU (Council of European Union, 2016) allows 
such linkages for research purposes and asks for the use of pseudonymization 
techniques. Therefore, research on these techniques will also increase (Schnell  et al., 2017). The recently founded International Journal of Population Data Sci-
ence (IJPDS) will facilitate the publication of research on data linkage. This ever 
more favorable research climate for linkage will yield more and more requests 
for linkage solutions. By developing and implementing such solutions, the GRLC 
will continually contribute to improvements of the international research data 
infrastructure. </p>



<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>







<p>M. Antoni and R. Schnell </p>



<p>German Record Linkage Center </p>





</text></tei>