<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10368-017-0398-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract This paper analyses the existence of a bubble in the Chinese real estate 
market and examines its driving factors with a state-space model. The model considers 
macroeconomic and real estate time series variables as inputs and employs a Kalman 
filter to obtain an estimated fundamental price using demand and supply for Chinese 
real estate. We then measure the deviation between actual and estimated fundamental 
real estate prices to test for the existence of a bubble. We find evidence for the existence 
of a bubble especially post 2010, when the deviation ratio is found to be significantly 
higher with a peak of 80% in 2012. Our estimation of overvaluation is generally much 
higher than in other studies. </p>

<p>There have been many bubbles in the real estate market in different economies since the 
1980s culminating in the bubble in the US real estate sector which resulted in the global 
financial crisis in 2008-2010. The Chinese real estate market has experienced rapid 
price rises particularly during the period end 2000 to end 2015 when the national house 
price index rose by 332%; with house price rises being driven by the strong growth and 
rapid urbanization of the Chinese economy, as well as lack of alternative investment 
opportunities. According to Bordo and Jeanne (2002) property booms and busts have 
been a fairly frequent occurrence in the global economy topic as compared to stock 
market booms and busts. 
The issue of the possibility of a real estate bubble in China is an issue of increasing 
concern given the rapid price rises of recent years, for example, Zhang and Sun (2006)  highlights the risks to Chinese banks of real estate credit exposure, the possible impact 
on local government finances and the dangers to foreign capital flows of large house 
price fluctuations. There are many ways in which to measure the existence of property 
bubbles, including using price to average income, price to rent and rental yield 
compared to the cost of mortgages. In this paper, we take a less direct approach and 
we regard the market value of a property as a state output variable changing over time; 
we similarly regard the economic factors determining the fundamental real estate price 
as changing inputs. 
A key advantage of using a state space model is that it is able to process nonsta-
tionary time series while allowing for the addition of variables that cannot be observed. 
The variables that cannot be observed are referred to as state variables. A linear state 
space model is typically composed of two equations, a state equation and a signal 
equation. The state equation can be used to represent the relation between observable 
and unobservable variables, while the signal equation describes the trends of unob-
servable variables. In our case, the extent of overvaluations is an unobservable variable 
and we therefore use the state space model to avoid the issue of inappropriate model 
specification in order to predict the extent of the deviation between market prices and 
fundamentals in the Chinese real estate sector. 
The structure of the paper is as follows. In section 2 we review some of the previous 
literature on bubbles in the real estate market. Section 3 provides an outline of the state 
space model used in our analysis. Section 4 outlines the state space model that we 
employ for our empirical analysis. Section 5 estimates demand and supply equations in 
order to calculate the unobservable fundamentals real estate prices and estimates the 
deviation of market prices from the fundamental. Section 6 attempts to link the 
deviation of prices to changes in the most important Chinese national policies and 
section 7 concludes. </p>

<p>2 The development of the Chinese real estate market </p>

<p>Up until 1980 China operated a centrally planned housing system but over time a 
number of reforms have changed the system to a much more market-oriented housing 
sector. Prior to 1980 urban housing in China was basically either owned by work units 
of State Owned Enterprises (SEOs) or housing management departments of local </p>

<p>484 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>governments. Residential housing was allocated to SEOs or housing management 
departments which in turn rented it to employees at very low rents with the State 
retaining the ownership of property. The central government played a significant role in 
determining the amount of housing investment and its allocation. The development of a 
private market in real estate in China began with reforms that were started in 1980 
when the Chinese government implemented a variety of housing market commercial-
ization policies. Those culminated in the 1988 central government document 
BImplementation Plan for a Gradual Housing System Reform in Cities and Towns^, 
which marked the beginning of a major programme of nationwide housing reform. The 
reforms permitted public housing units to be sold to their existing tenants at substan-
tially discounted prices. In addition, there was also a programme to raise the rents 
towards more market oriented levels, which had limited success as the new rents were 
often still insufficient to cover the maintenance. 
A second reform effort started in 1994, when the Chinese central government issued 
BThe Decision on Deepening the Urban Housing Reform.^The reform tried to improve 
both the supply and demand sides to create a housing market. On the supply side there 
was provision of subsidized housing for low income groups, while high-income groups 
were expected to purchase regular market housing. On the demand side, a dual housing 
finance system was established using a combination of social savings and private 
savings. Further emphasis was given to privatize more of the public housing stock at 
more realistic market prices. 
The most important set of reforms came with the 1998 notice: BNotification from the 
State Council on Further Deepening the Reform of the Urban Housing System and 
Accelerating Housing Construction.^This notice banned SOEs from either building or 
buying new housing units for their employees, replacing it with a system of employee 
subsidies. It also encouraged the private sector to step into housebuilding and banks to 
lend to consumers with the object to create a proper functioning private market for 
housing. Over the period 1998-2002 there were a number of measures taken to 
stimulate the private housing market in China, including reductions in personal income 
tax, sales taxes and mortgage rates set at levels aimed at stimulating housing demand. It 
should be noted that revenues from land sales have become and an important source of 
local government revenues over this period, accounting for over 30% in Cities such as 
Beijing and Zhejiang. 
The results of all these reforms means that some 80% of the Chinese housing stock 
is in now in private hands. The proportion of housing transactions as a percentage of 
GDP has risen from 4.1% in 2002 to 13.3% of GDP in 2016 and house price growth 
has averaged 9.4% per annum over this period. During the period 1998 to 2010 
outstanding residential mortgage loans have grown 112 times to 4.76 Trillion RMB 
($697 billion) and all outstanding real estate-related loans have grown 24 times to 7.33 
Trillion RMB. For a fuller discussion of housing policy in China see Li (2016). </p>

<p>3 Literature review </p>

<p>Ultimately house prices are determined simply by the forces of supply and demand and 
the price will adjust over time with changes in the factors affecting the demand and 
supply. Bourassa et al. (2001) use selected fundamental variables such as real income </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
(employment and the real wage rate), real construction costs, and the real after-tax 
interest rate as key determinants of supply and demand when looking for house price 
bubbles in three major cities in New Zealand. Liang and Cao (2007) and Chen and Zhu  (2008) identify rapid GDP growth, bank lending and the rapid urbanization of China, as 
people move from rural locations to the Cities, as key drivers of the demand side in 
China. Another important factor on the demand side is economic agents' expectations 
relating to future prices, with expectations of price rises or falls influencing the decision 
of whether to buy or sell. Prices can also be influenced by government policies such as 
the building of roads, transport links to other cities, schools, hospitals, greenspace and 
planning permission. Governments can also heavily influence housing demand through 
changes in taxes on income and property and through the amount of land that can be 
used for housing stock which affects both the demand and supply and hence the 
equilibrium price. Ahuja et al. (2010) note that central government and local 
government fiscal relations, land development policies and land prices are key 
determinants of the supply of housing in China. According to Lai (2017) using a user 
cost approach framework, a combination of high income growth, rapid credit expansion 
and low interest rates lies behind the rapid rise in prices in the Chinese housing market 
with demand persistently outstripping supply. The basic argument behind the user cost 
approach is that Chinese citizens have a choice between saving money at low interest 
rates or buying housing stock with a prospective higher rental yield and capital appre-
ciation and this is the main explanation of the imbalance in the Chinese property market. 
The monetary policy of central banks and credit conditions can have a large 
influence on the real estate market. Cesa-Bianchi et al. (2015) argues that real estate 
prices can be explained by global monetary liquidity conditions especially in emerging 
markets. In the case of the dramatic Japanese property bubble of 1985-1990 Okina and  Shiratsuka (2004) argue that lax monetary policy by the Bank of Japan was a prime 
driver of the housing bubble. While McDonald and Stokes (2013) look at house price 
rises in 10 US cities over the period 1987-2010 using the Case-Shiller house price 
indices. Using the VAR modelling procedure and Granger causality tests they find that 
the reductions of interest rate by the Federal Reserve were a significant cause of the US 
housing bubble. 
There are various fundamental approaches to valuing real estate, for example, 
Leamer (2002) points out that the fundamental price of property should be the present 
value of the future rent. Leamer argues that using large deviations of price to rental 
ratios from their historical norms can be a useful method of detecting housing bubbles. 
In their study, Björklund and Söderberg (1999) look at Swedish house prices over the 
period 1985 to 1994. They argue that a fundamental determinant of house prices is the 
Gross Income Multiplier (GIM). Their study finds that the ratio of house prices to rental 
income was too high and conclude that a bubble existed in the Swedish market. Ortalo-
Magne and Rady (2006) use a life-cycle model of the housing market combined with a 
property market ladder to show that the income of young households is a prime 
determinant of their ability to afford a down-payment on a starter home. They show 
that, in such circumstances, changes in income may yield a housing price over-reaction 
with the house prices of trade-up homes exhibiting the most volatility. Their model also 
finds some empirical support when applied to the UK and US housing markets. 
As well as fundamental determinants of house prices there is also the possibility of 
speculative activity pushing up the price driven by herding behaviour and irrational </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>expectations of future price rises which can lead to a significant deviation of prices 
from those justified by fundamental determinants. Caballero (2006) point out that an 
additional reason for house price inflation is that that in many countries, especially 
developing countries, there is a shortage of investment assets which, in turn, leads to 
over speculation in the real estate market and the frequent emergence of bubbles in the 
sector. Real estate is often the focus of investors in emerging markets because it 
generally has better property rights and legal protections in place for investors. 
According to Herring and Wachter (1999) bank behaviour can lead to exaggerated 
movements in house prices. In a market with real estate prices rising, banks lend more 
loans for property purchases as rises in real estate prices increase the value of bank 
capital to the extent that banks own real estate. Banks may then perceive that there is a 
lower risk of real estate lending. As such, an increase in real estate prices can increase 
the amount of banking loan exposure to the real estate sector which in turn leads to 
further rises in real estate prices. Once prices of real estate peak, a fall in the price of 
real estate will lower the value of the banking sectors real estate assets and the value of 
loans collateralized by real estate. There may also be defaults, which further depletes 
banks capital, increasing the perceived riskiness of the real estate sector and in turn 
reduces the supply of credit to the real estate industry leading to further falls in prices 
and further reductions in loans to the real estate sector. Regulators may intervene to the 
weakening of bank capital positions by increasing capital requirements and instituting 
stricter rules for classifying and provisioning against real estate assets ultimately 
leading to even less activity in the real estate sector and lower prices. 
Studies on the Chinese property market have grown in recent years. Liang and Cao  (2007) investigate the relationship between property prices and bank lending for the case 
of China over the period 1999-2006, and find that there is unidirectional causality 
running from bank lending to property prices. Zhang et al. (2012) show that Chinese 
house prices can also be linked to changes in the macroeconomic variables using a non-
linear autoregressive moving average with exogenous inputs approach combined with 
the vector error correction model over the period 1999-2010. Their estimations show 
that the mortgage rate, money supply growth rate, producer prices and the real exchange 
rate are key drivers of Chinese house prices while surprisingly they do not detect a 
significant role for personal disposable income, international trade or real incomes. Guo  and Huang (2010) show that hot money from abroad has been a significant driver of the 
Chinese stock and property prices. While Liu and Wray (2010) argue that the liquidity 
driving the property prices in China is the result of massive intervention in the foreign 
exchange market by the Peoples Bank of China as reflected in the large increase in 
Chinese foreign exchange reserves. The increase in the Renminbi money supply 
resulting from the intervention means artificially low interest rates and high money 
supply and credit growth. Dreger and Zhang (2013) argue that that there was a large rise 
in the real estate market as a direct result of the fiscal stimulus package unleashed by the 
Chinese authorities as a result of the global financial crisis and also the very loose money 
market conditions permitted by the Chinese monetary authorities. Using a dataset 
covering some 35 major Chinese cities over the period 1998 to 2009, the authors apply 
a panel model along with cointegration techniques and find that Chinese real estate was 
some 25% higher than the equilibrium value implied by the fundamentals at the end of 
2009, with the overpricing especially high in cities in southeast coastal areas and special 
economic zones. </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
Xu and Chen (2012) also argue that Chinese monetary policy actions are the key 
driver of real estate price growth in in China over the period 1998 to 2009. They 
examine the impact of monetary policy variables which includes the money supply 
growth rate, the long term bank loan rate and a mortgage credit policy indicator to 
analyse real estate price growth dynamics in China. Their empirical results show a two 
way causal connection, with a lower interest rate, higher money supply growth rate and 
a loosening of mortgage down payment requirements leading to rapid price rises for 
real estate. This then leads to even more loans to the sector and a further loosening of 
credit standards. Du et al. (2011) look at the connection between Chinese land policy 
and its impact on the dynamic relationship between the house prices and land prices in 
the Chinese real estate market. Using panel data sets for Beijing, Shanghai, Tianjin and 
Chongqing they demonstrate that there exists a long-run equilibrium between Chinese 
urban housing and land markets. Wu et al. (2012) show that price to rent ratios have 
risen substantially over time in China being over 40 in some cities. They also show that 
rises in land prices has been a major force in driving up real estate prices in China with 
land prices rising over 800% between 2003 and 2010. This has created bubble like 
conditions in certain Chinese cities. 
The existence of housing bubble in China has previously been explored by Man Hui  and Yue (2006) who use a macro based econometric model to detect the existence of a 
housing bubble in Beijing and Shanghai in 2003. Interestingly while they are not able 
to detect the existence of a bubble in Beijing they are able to detect one in Shanghai 
which is shown to be approximately 22% overvalued. While Ahuja et al. (2010) find 
that as of mid-2010 house prices in China were not significantly overvalued except in 
cities such as Shanghai and Shentzhen. Although, they also detect signs of overvalu-
ations in the luxury segment in both Beijing and Nanjing. 
In the following section, we use a state space model to examine the existence of a 
real estate bubble in China. A deviation of property prices from their market funda-
mentals involves estimating a variable that cannot be observed. To overcome this 
problem we choose a state space model. The state space model has been increasingly 
used in recent years economic research. See for example Bertus and Stanhouse (2001)  who uses it to test for a bubble in the gold market. Lau et al. (2005) apply it to 
investigate the existence of rational stock market bubbles in the Asian economies. Man 
Hui and Gu (2009) use a state space model to analyse house prices in Guanzhou and 
find that house prices peaked with a 43% overvaluation in October 2007. Han et al. 
(2008) also use a state space model to measure the extent of overvaluation of the 
property market in Shanghai and show that the market become approximately 22% 
overvalued. While Teng et al. (2013) use the state space model to detect and estimate 
the size of housing market bubbles in both Hong Kong and Taipei. </p>

<p>4 State space modelling of real estate in China </p>

<p>For our analysis of the Chinese property market, we adopt a State Space Model (SSM), 
which is a powerful framework -widely used in physics, engineering and other 
sciences-for the analysis of dynamic systems. In many applications, the driving forces 
behind the evolution of economic variables are (at least partially) not observable or 
measurable. For example, at an individual level a person's income may depend on their </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>intelligence, special abilities, social skills, and so on. Similarly, at an aggregate level, 
economic theory suggests that macroeconomic variables such as economic 
growth are driven by unobservable factors, e.g. technological change or human 
capital accumulation. For this reason, SSMs have been applied in the econo-
metrics literature to model unobserved variables such as; expectations, measure-
ment errors, missing observations, permanent income, unobserved components 
(cycles and trends) and the non-accelerating rate of unemployment. Extensive 
surveys of applications of state space models in econometrics can be found in 
Hamilton (1994a, Chapter 13) and Harvey et al. (2004). 
In the presence of both correlated and unobserved variables, adopting SSM 
represents an improvement upon standard regression analysis as a SSM can 
allow for endogeneity. While linear regression models use exogenous variables 
to distinguish the explained variation from the unexplained variation, a SSM 
relies on the dynamics of the state variables and the linkage between the 
observed variables and state variables to draw statistical inference about the 
unobserved states. In this respect, a SSM can represent an improvement also 
upon VAR techniques. Comparing SSM to standard VAR models when explan-
atory variables are not observable, standard VAR models can no longer be 
applied to study the evolution of the endogenous variables. However, it is easy 
to extend the VAR framework to analyse scenarios with unobservable explana-
tory variables by using SSM. In fact, a wide range of time series models, 
including the classical linear regression model and ARIMA models, can be 
written and estimated as special cases of a state space specification. 
In this paper we use a SSM to analyse real estate demand, real estate supply 
and the unobservable overvaluation component. Modelling real estate demand 
and supply typically suffers from issues of omitted variables and endogenous, 
i.e. mutually correlated, variables. The first benefit of using a SSM is to be 
able to include non-stationary and endogenous macro-economic variables in the 
demand and supply equations. This improves upon a VAR technique, where 
only co-integrated variables can be included and a vector error correction model 
(VECM) should be imposed. The second benefit of using a SSM is to be able 
to estimate the unobserved overvaluation component by estimating a fundamen-
tal price through the Kalman filter, which is the standard estimation technique 
in SSM. 
SSMs allow the researcher to model an observed (multiple) time series, y t 
f g </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t¼1 , as 
being explained by a vector of (possibly unobserved) state variables, ξ t 
f g </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t¼1 , which are 
driven by a stochastic process. A basic linear state SSM is formed by two equations. 
The first equation, called measurement equation, describes the relation between the 
observed time series, y t , and the (possibly unobserved) state ξ t : </p>

<p>y t ¼ Aξ t þ ν t ; ν t ∼N 0; R 
ð 
Þ measurement equation 
ð 
Þ : 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>In general, it is assumed that the data y t are measured with error, which is reflected in 
the measurement error ν t that enters the measurement equation. The standard approach 
is to model ν t as a Gaussian error term normally distributed with zero mean and some 
given variance R. </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
The second equation, the transition equation, describes the evolution of the (possibly 
unobserved) state variables as being driven by the stochastic process of innovations ω t : </p>

<p>ξ t ¼ Bξ t−1 þ ω t ; ω t ∼N 0; Q 
ð 
Þ transition equation 
ð 
Þ 
ð 2Þ </p>

<p>It is typically assumed that also innovations are normally distributed with zero mean 
and a given variance Q. State space models can also be formulated much more 
generally than this specification. For example, the system matrices A and B could 
depend explicitly on time, or one could introduce policy variables and constants in the 
specification. However, our model will be characterized by a simple formulation where 
state variables follow a random walk model, i.e. B is an identity matrix. 
Generally, in practical applications the system matrices A and B together with the 
variances R and Q are unknown and have to be estimated. Whenever the explanatory 
variables are not observable Least Squares estimation is not the correct way to go. 
However, even in this case, one can apply likelihood based inference, since the Kalman 
filter allows to construct the likelihood function associated with a state space model. 
The SSM is therefore estimated by maximizing the estimated likelihood function 
through a numerical procedure. We apply this procedure by using the <rs type="software">Sspace</rs> package 
in the <rs type="software">EViews</rs>® software. 
Our first step is to obtain consistent estimations of real estate demand and supply 
functions for China. To do this, we select a number of macroeconomic variables for 
each function. We verify their stationarity properties and co-integration. We opt to only 
include co-integrated variables in each function, even if in principle a SSM can handle 
variables that are not co-integrated. By doing this, we do not have to impose any 
structure on the functions and we can still obtain consistent estimations. In particular, 
we model that all macro variables evolve as a random walk, so that no stationarity in 
the estimated demand and supply is superimposed by the modelling assumptions. 
After finding consistent estimations for demand and supply, we move to the second 
step of our analysis. We interpret that estimated demand and supply represent the 
fundamental forces beyond price movements and we estimate the unobserved funda-
mental price that would equate demand and supply through a new SSM iteration, by 
modelling the unobserved fundamental price as a random walk. As for the other 
macroeconomic variables, modelling a random walk process for the fundamental price 
is a natural choice because we do not want to impose any structure that could influence 
the fundamental price beyond the estimated factors. Finally, we compare the estimated 
fundamental price with the observed price, we compute their deviation ratio and 
analyse its properties. 
Compared to other approaches in the literature reviewed in section 3, the novel 
contribution of our methodology is that the deviation ratio measures a purely irrational 
bubble component. In other words, our bubble component does not include price 
changes that are due to non-equilibrium between supply and demand, where demand 
includes not only the users' market but also investors' demand. This feature is 
important because real estate markets can be characterized by a fundamental mismatch 
between supply and demand which can take time to correct and by a component of 
demand that is investment driven and that is typically not decreasing in price. 
1 A fair </p>

<p>1 See for example DiPasquale and Wheaton (1992). </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>account of the bubble component should therefore exclude those components. 
Moreover, in our analysis we do not consider rents on purpose, because those are co-
determined in the economy with the observable market prices, whereas we want to 
have a measure of the fundamental unobservable real estate price that depends as much 
as possible on fundamental macro-economic factors. </p>

<p>5 Empirical analysis </p>

<p>The model is estimated by using 44 quarterly observations from 2004Q1 to 2014Q4 for 
various time series. The data are obtained from the National Bureau of Statistics of 
China. We consider the following variables: </p>

<p>1) SS: National Real Estate Selling Space 
2) FS: National Real Estate Completion Space 
3) P: Real Estate Sale Price reported in (reported in CNY/square meters) 
4) GDP: Gross Domestic Product 
5) PDI: Disposable income(reported in CNY/person) 
6) MR: Loan Interest Rate (official 3 to 5 years interest rate) 
7) CPI: Consumer Price Index 
8) M1: Narrow Money Supply </p>

<p>As it is often the case with this type of macro variables, evaluating the data with 
Augment Dickey-Fuller test reveals that these variables are non-stationary in levels, but 
become stationary in first differences. We also adjust for seasonality with the <rs type="software">Eviews</rs> 
Census X12 method and take the log of all variables to correct for heteroscedasticity. 
SS is our measure for real estate demand and FS is our measure for real estate supply. 
We carry out Johansen tests to select co-integrated variables for demand and supply. 
After that we estimate the two functions by a SSM. </p>

<p>5.1 Demand side </p>

<p>We include five variables in the demand equation: real estate sale space SS, sale price P, 
disposable income PDI, interest rate MR and consumer price index CPI. The variables 
are chosen on the basis of the Johansen test. Table 1 shows that there are five co-
integrated relationship within the chosen variables of the demand equation. This implies 
that their relationship is stable across the sample period, indicating that the demand 
equation has economic meaning. The resulting demand equation is the following: </p>

<p>ln SS t 
ð Þ ¼ dv 1t Â ln P t 
ð Þ þ dv 2t Â ln PDI t 
ð 
Þþdv 3t Â ln MR t 
ð 
Þþdv 4t Â ln CPI t 
ð </p>

<p>Þþμ t ð3Þ </p>

<p>Since each variable is in time series, they are subscripted with time sign-t before 
being transformed into the natural logarithm. The coefficients are also time-varying and 
are assumed to be random walk series in the signal equations: </p>

<p>dv 1t ¼ dv 1t−1 þ ε </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t ; dv 2t ¼ dv 2t−1 þ ε </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t ; dv 3t ¼ dv 3t−1 þ ε </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>t ; dv 4t ¼ dv 4t−1 þ ε </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>t ð4Þ </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
The residuals of the above five equations are assumed to have independent and 
identical distributions. Equations (3) and (4) form a SSM are estimated by Kalman filter 
using the Sspace analysis tools in <rs type="software">Eviews</rs>7.0®. The estimated coefficients represent the 
long term and stable elasticity of sold real estate space with respect to each variables. 
Results are reported in Table 2 below. 
We notice from Table 2 that the coefficient DV1 is positive and significant, this 
implies that demand for real estate increases in price. This apparently unusual 
positive relation of prices on demand is not uncommon in markets characterized 
by a strong investment, or speculation, motive. We notice that the coefficient DV2 
is not significant and is excluded from the demand equation in the following steps 
of our analysis. Coefficients DV3 and DV4 are significant and they show a 
positive effect of interest rates and a negative effect of inflation. Similarly to what 
happens with the coefficient of price, the positive coefficient of interest rates, 
apparently a non-standard result, is due to the fact that Chinese national govern-
ment policies have systematically raised interest rates in periods of strong demand 
as discussed in section 6. The negative coefficient of inflation is as expected and 
due to household budget constraints (Table 3). </p>

<p>5.2 Supply side </p>

<p>We repeat the same procedure in order to estimate the supply function. 
We check that five co-integrated relationships exist also in the variables of the 
supply equation and we include the five variables in the supply equation: real estate </p>

<p>Table 1 Co-integration test for the demand equation </p>

<p>Hypothesized No. of CE(s) 
Eigenvalue 
Trace Statistic 
0.05 Critical Value </p>

<p>None * 
0.566740 
91.26551 
69.81889 </p>

<p>At most 1 * 
0.372167 
56.13594 
47.85613 </p>

<p>At most 2 * 
0.316227 
36.58574 
29.79707 </p>

<p>At most 3 * 
0.264359 
20.62033 
15.49471 </p>

<p>At most 4 * 
0.168020 
7.725774 
3.841466 </p>

<p>Trace test indicates 5 cointegrating eqn(s) at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>*denotes rejection of the hypothesis at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>Table 2 Estimation of the parameters in the demand equation </p>

<p>Final State 
Root MSE 
z-Statistic 
Prob. </p>

<p>DV1 
2.377801 
2.298454 
1.034522 
0.0034 </p>

<p>DV2 
−0.154792 
0.006288 
−7.951273 
0.8957 </p>

<p>DV3 
0.052206 
0.053696 
0.972257 
0.0061 </p>

<p>DV4 
−0.351807 
1.056569 
−0.332971 
0.0091 </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>completed real estate space FS, sale price P, money supply M1, interest rate MR and 
GDP. The resulting supply equation is the following: </p>

<p>ln FS t 
ð Þ ¼ sv 1t Â ln P t 
ð Þ þ sv 2t Â ln M 1 t 
ð 
Þþsv 3t Â ln MR t 
ð 
Þþsv 4t Â ln GDP t 
ð </p>

<p>Þþη t ð5Þ </p>

<p>Also the coefficients are assumed to be random walk series with i.i.d. errors in the 
signal equations: </p>

<p>sv 1t ¼ sv 1t−1 þ ξ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>t ; sv 2t ¼ sv 2t−1 þ ξ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t ; sv 3t ¼ sv 3t−1 þ ξ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>t ; sv 4t ¼ sv 4t−1 þ ξ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>t ð6Þ </p>

<p>In this case, eqs. (5) and (6) form a SSM are estimated by Kalman filter using the 
Sspace analysis tools in <rs type="software">Eviews</rs>7.0®. The estimated coefficients represent the long term 
and stable elasticity of completed real estate space with respect to each variable. Results 
are reported in Table 4 below. 
We notice from Table 4 that all coefficients are significant. SV1 is positive 
and this implies that demand for real estate increases in price as expected. We 
notice that the coefficient SV2 is positive implying that money supply increases 
real estate supply. Coefficients SV3 and SV4 show a negative effect of interest 
rates and a positive effect of GDP. The positive effect of money supply and the 
negative effect of interest rates are due to the fact that national policies have 
systematically used money supply and base interest rate to stimulate or alter-
natively curb real estate development activity. The positive effect of GDP on 
real estate supply is standard. </p>

<p>Table 3 Co-integration test for the supply equation </p>

<p>Hypothesized No. of CE(s) 
Eigenvalue 
Trace Statistic 
0.05 Critical Value </p>

<p>None * 
0.839862 
128.2216 
69.81889 </p>

<p>At most 1 * 
0.514890 
64.11154 
47.85613 </p>

<p>At most 2 * 
0.432954 
38.79323 
29.79707 </p>

<p>At most 3 * 
0.285672 
18.71895 
15.49471 </p>

<p>At most 4 * 
0.185068 
4.20499 
3.841466 </p>

<p>Trace test indicates 5 cointegrating eqn(s) at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>*denotes rejection of the hypothesis at the 0.05 level </p>

<p>Table 4 Estimation of the parameters in the supply equation </p>

<p>Final State 
Root MSE 
z-Statistic 
Prob. </p>

<p>SV1 
0.284715 
0.425151 
0.669680 
0.0031 </p>

<p>SV2 
0.060843 
0.068098 
0.893456 
0.0095 </p>

<p>SV3 
−0.598513 
0.629294 
−0.951086 
0.0086 </p>

<p>SV4 
0.301307 
0.686145 
0.439130 
0.0046 </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
5.3 Equilibrium price </p>

<p>We use the results from the previous estimations and estimated demand and 
supply from the measurement equations, and we estimate the unobservable 
fundamental price (FP). </p>

<p>ln SS t 
ð Þ ¼ DV1 Â ln FP t 
ð 
ÞþDV3 Â ln MR t 
ð 
ÞþDV4 Â ln CPI t 
ð 
Þþμ t 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>ln FS t 
ð Þ ¼ SV1 Â ln FP t 
ð ÞþSV2 Â ln M 1 t 
ð 
ÞþSV3 Â ln MR t 
ð 
ÞþSV4 Â ln GDP t 
ð </p>

<p>Þþη t ð8Þ </p>

<p>As in the case of the estimation of demand and supply, in order not to super-impose 
assumptions, we model that the fundamental price follows a random walk in the signal 
equation: </p>

<p>ln FP t 
ð Þ ¼ ln FP t−1 
ð 
Þþε t 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>where μ t , η t , ε t are i.i.d. 
The unknown series ln(FP t ) is then estimated as the unknown of the SSM formed by 
(7), (8) and (9) by Kalman filter. We interpret the difference between ln(P t ) -ln(FP t ) as 
it is the portion of price that is not explained by the dynamics of demand and supply, 
where the demand and supply have been estimated on the basis of broad macro-
financial factors and not simply imposed to be at equilibrium. By standard results we 
obtain that: </p>

<p>ln P t 
ð Þ−ln FP t 
ð Þ≈ P t − FP t 
ð 
Þ = FP t 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>Equation (10) defines the deviation ratio which is our measure of the irrational (i.e. 
bubble) component in the observed real estate price. We plot this ratio in Fig. 1. 
As we can notice from Fig. 1, the deviation ratio is generally positive throughout the 
sample period and substantial in terms of magnitude. As a robustness check, we also 
perform an ADF test on the deviation ratio. 
From Table 5, we notice that the deviation ratio is nonstationary in levels but 
becomes stable in first differences, therefore indicating that the deviation ratio is a 
I(1) series. This confirms that an irrational component exists in the real estate price and 
is significant. We also find evidence of a structural break in the deviation ratio at the 
end of 2010. After this period, the deviation ratio increases substantially. In the 
following section we analyse the dynamics of the deviation ratio over time and we 
relate those to policy changes. </p>

<p>6 Policy discussion </p>

<p>There is relatively limited research on Chinese housing policies published in English. 
The papers of Li and Chiang (2012) and Li (2016) are notable exceptions and </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>extensively review those policies over the last decade. They explain that the Chinese 
central government has substantially advocated three types of policies to cool down the 
property market and to curb potential housing bubbles over the past decade: restricted 
bank loan (xiandai), restricted sale price (xianjia) and restricted housing purchase 
(xiangou). Those policies have changed frequently, in an attempt to effectively control 
the market with objectives of promoting growth and stability. We can now analyze the 
dynamics of the deviation ratio with respect to the policy changes. There are various 
interesting features of the deviation ratio that are worth noticing in Fig. 1. First, 
we observe that the deviation ratio seems to have a cyclical behaviour over one 
calendar year; this behaviour, which is common to many western economies, 
can be explained by the fact that more properties tend to come on the market 
in the spring-summer period. 
Looking at the deviation ratio from 2004 to 2006 shows the effects of some 
important policies introduced by the State Council in 2005 aimed at stabilizing property 
prices. The introduction of those policies in 2005 marks an important shift from the 
previous 2001-2004 period when State Council policies had as primary objective to 
sustain and promote the real estate market (see Li 2016). In particular, in a market </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Quarterly Deviation Ratio from end 2003 to end 2014 </p>

<p>Table 5 Unit root test for the deviation ratio </p>

<p>ADF test statistic 
0.05 critical value 
0.10 critical value 
conclusion </p>

<p>deviation ratio 
−1.897304 
−2.931404 
−2.603944 
not stable </p>

<p>deviation ratio (first diff.) 
−4.742939 
−2.936942 
−2.606857 
stable </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
dominated by low interest rates, in March 2005 the People's Bank of China (PBOC) 
increased the minimum down payment ratio for homebuyers from 20% to 30%. We 
notice that the deviation ratio decreases from 35% in mid-2005 to 5% at the end of 
2006, showing that the effect of the price-stabilizing policies while not immediate are 
quite powerful. 
Next we notice that despite the cyclical behaviour, the deviation ratio in 2007 is 
much lower than in the previous years. Li and Chiang (2012) explain that from 
March 2007 to August 2008, the PBOC increased the residential loan rates 6 times 
and the deposit reserve ratio 13 times. These were extreme measures that the 
PBOC had never adopted before. Moreover, the Ministry of Housing and Urban-
Rural Development increased the Housing Provident Fund (HPF) loan rates 6 
times in a row. 
2 Researchers have commented that those policies may have a 
distortive impact and unintended consequences. Moreover, the suppression on the 
bubble in the real estate market does not last long as the deviation ratio still 
reaches 30% in 2007, signalling that the real estate market is overheated and is 
little impacted by the by the monetary policy in short term. 
With the financial crisis happening around the world in 2008, the real estate market 
in China became suddenly weaker. To avoid an economic recession, a series of new 
policies were formulated by the PBOC in October 2010. In particular, from October 
27th the central bank decided to adjust the lower bound of the personal loan interest rate 
to 0.7 times the benchmark interest rate and revert the down payment portion back to 
20%. There were five issuance of Notice on Lowering the RMB Benchmark Interest 
Rates for Loans and Deposit Reserve Rate of Financial Institutions. For low-cost 
housing, affordable housing and housing rental, policies provided tax free land for 
developers according to a defined portion of the total space. This welfare policy aimed 
at protecting the rigid demand of inhabitants while the loan interest and the subsidy are 
both unfavorable in this period. We notice that the trend of the deviation ratio is 
different in 2008 with respect to other years, as it reaches its bottom, rather than a 
peak, in the second quarter. In this period, due to the global economic recession, 
investors and speculators had less funds and confidence even in China, despite the still 
booming property market. Despite the global recession in 2008, the real estate market 
in China remains quite stable throughout 2009 mainly due to the effects of the 
favourable policies. 
We then find evidence of a structural break in the deviation ratio from 2010 
onwards. The behaviour is still cyclical but the average ratio from 2010 to 2014 is 
35%, whereas it is 15% in the preceding sub-sample. Moreover, the magnitude of 
volatility is also higher after 2010. It can therefore be noticed that the real estate market 
of China recovers quickly from the recession but after the stimulating policy interven-
tion sale prices rise quickly and significantly shift away from the estimated fundamental 
value. For this reason, April 2010 marks the start of a new set of policy measures aimed 
at restricting purchases and loans with the objective of limiting real estate appreciation 
and to keep the market stable. On 30 April 2010, the State Council issued the restrictive 
purchase policy (xiangou) to cool down the overheated property market. Restrictive </p>

<p>2 Chen and Deng (2014) explain that the HPF is self-funded circuit institution separated from the market-based 
financial system and it is a compulsory savings scheme to provide self-funded housing, where employers and 
employees of the public sector contribute 5% of employees' monthly incomes to individual HPF accounts. </p>

<p> 
T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>purchases set purchase limits on the number of flats that could be sold to households. In 
40 major cities, residents with local hukou (i.e., household registration) can buy up to 
two flats, nonlocal residents or foreigners can only buy one flat, and the interval for 
buying a second flat must be at least 2 years. Moreover, to control construction targets 
in an attempt to stabilize the market expectations, the central government required 
regional governments to issue property price controls in 2011 and by March 2011 608 
cities in China issued policies to control real estate prices according to the Construction 
Department Database. Li (2016) comments that after the Chinese government imple-
mented the restrictive purchase policy, none of the cities had any signs of housing 
bubbles in 2010/11. However, eight cities had bubbles detected in 2011/12 and most 
cities have shown signs of bubbles since 2012. We notice that despite the restrictive 
policies from 2011 to 2013, the deviation ratio peaks at 80% at the beginning of 2012 
and stays at an average in excess of 40% thereafter. </p>

<p>7 Conclusions </p>

<p>Based on discussion and analysis above, we have employed the SSM as a means to 
detect a real estate bubble in the Chinese real estate market. By estimating the real 
estate demand and supply with a SSM using a broad number of macroeconomic and 
financial factors, we have been able to isolate the non-fundamental price component. 
We have then compared the market price to the fundamental price to calculate a 
deviation ratio, which is our measure of the extent of the bubble in the Chinese real 
estate market. Using the deviation ratio, we have described how the bubble component 
changes over time and we attempt to highlight how the deviation responds to changes 
in relation to policies of the Chinese authorities. 
In line with some of the previous literature, we have found quite strong evidence of a 
bubble, especially after 2010, when the deviation ratio has an average value in excess 
of 40%. Compared to previous approaches in the literature, the novel contribution of 
our methodology is that the deviation ratio measures a purely bubble component. In 
other words, our bubble component does not include price changes that are due to non-
equilibrium between supply and demand, where demand includes not only the users' 
market but also investors' demand. This feature is important because real estate markets 
are characterized by a fundamental mismatch between supply and demand, due to the 
time to develop property, and by a component of demand that is investment driven and 
that is typically not decreasing in price and a fair account of the bubble component 
should not include those components. 
Looking at the dynamics of the deviation ratio with respect to policy changes 
broadly shows that stimulating monetary policies (especially post 2008) had strong 
positive effects on the bubble component, whereas policies that aimed to limit or 
reverse the bubble component had only limited and short lived effects. In line with 
Li (2016) we find evidence that interest rate policies or restricted housing purchase 
policies in specific cities post 2011 did not limit the bubble component at the aggregate 
national level. Given this evidence, we attribute a fundamental role in the inefficacy of 
interest rate policies to the role played by shadow banking. As the recent literature 
shows that bank lending is increasingly independent from the PBOC, it remains an 
open question whether shadow banking lending supports, weakens, or amplifies the </p>

<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
effects of monetary policy. Gabrieli, Pilbeam and Shi (2018 forthcoming) contribute to 
this recent debate by showing that Chinese Shadow Banking works independently from 
official monetary policy: it amplifies increases in the money supply but weakens the 
effects of restrictive interest rate-based monetary policy decisions. Given that virtually 
all of the official interest rate changes in the last decade have been motivated by policy 
objectives focussed on the real estate market, we conclude that the inability to curb the 
real estate bubble is very much related to the opposing role played by Shadow Banking. 
Future research could take a further step and specifically investigate the role of shadow 
banking in real estate price dynamics in China. </p>

<p>498  T. Gabrieli et al. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We are grateful to seminar participants at University College London, University of 
Birmingham, City University of London and the European Economic and Finance Society annual conference 
2016 for many helpful comments. We are also grateful to two anonymous referees for their extensive 
comments that led to significant improvements in the paper. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a 
link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>Estimation of bubble dynamics in the Chinese real estate market: a... </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>