<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fjems.12230" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>This paper studies the effect of word-of-mouth communication on the optimal pric-
ing strategy for new experience goods. I consider a dynamic monopoly model with </p>

<p>asymmetric information about product quality, in which consumers learn in equilib-
rium from both prices and other consumers. The main result is that word-of-mouth </p>

<p>communication is essential for the existence of separating equilibria, wherein the 
high-quality monopolist signals high quality through a low introductory price (lower </p>

<p>than the monopoly price), and the low-quality one charges the monopoly price. The 
intuition is simple: low prices are costly, and will only be used by firms confident </p>

<p>enough that increased experimentation (and therefore communication among con-
sumers) will yield good news about quality and increased future profits. Additional 
results are the following: for the high-quality seller, the expected price (quantity) is </p>

<p>increasing (decreasing) over time; whereas for the low-quality one, the opposite is 
true. Moreover, signaling becomes more difficult when consumers pay less attention </p>

<p>to their peers' reports and more attention to past prices. Finally, word-of-mouth com-
munication improves consumer welfare. </p>

<p>Word-of-mouth (WOM) communication is a powerful instrument to disseminate product information prior to purchase. When 
consumers face uncertainty about the quality of a new product, they are able to learn from their peers and, specifically, tend to 
pay attention to what their fellow consumers observed after their own purchases (Arndt, 1967; Chen &amp; Xie, 2008; Zhu &amp; Zhang, 
2010). This information, communicated via WOM or eWOM, 1 is likely to be more credible, and therefore more persuasive than 
advertising or other seller-created information, because it is based on personal experience and usage (Bughin, Doogan, &amp; Vetvik, 
2010; Dellarocas, 2003; Mayzlin, 2006). As such, WOM can be an important component of a firm's marketing strategy, and may 
also act as a substitute for advertising, as it promises more impact than any other communication channel (Chen &amp; Xie, 2008; 
Godes &amp; Mayzlin, 2004). After all, "Marketers may spend millions of dollars on elaborately conceived advertising campaigns, 
yet often what really makes up a consumer' s mind is not only simple but also free: a word-of-mouth recommendation from a 
trusted source" (Bughin et al., 2010). 
Firms understand the importance of WOM and use it strategically. When firms are better informed about the characteristics 
and quality of the product, prices may also provide valuable information to consumers, as they can be used as signals of quality 
(Bagwell &amp; Riordan, 1991; Milgrom &amp; Roberts, 1986). Thus, prices become a signaling instrument to encourage or discourage 
experimentation and thereby control the diffusion of information. In particular, low prices that generate WOM buzz can signal 
high product quality. Low prices (and higher sales) lead to increased product exposure, which amplifies the good (or bad) news 
generated through WOM communication. </p>

<p>J Econ Manage Strat. 2018;27:53-70. 
© 2017 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. 
53 
wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/jems </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>This is particularly true in the case of experience goods, whose quality is unobserved at the time of purchasing, and only 
becomes known after consuming and "tasting" the product. 2 Travelers, for example, would be remiss to reserve an <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> 
property without first consulting online reviews to ensure that previous guests confirm the host-reported quality. For their part, 
hosts would be equally remiss not to incorporate this fact into the pricing strategy. Here, eWOM can bridge the information 
gap between past consumers and potential consumers and help turn views into purchases. Indeed, Aerosolve, the dynamic open-
source algorithm used by <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> to provide hosts with date-specific price suggestions, prioritizes the capture of a first and second 
review via penetration pricing. The fact that a property has no reviews is a negative "feature", which puts significant downward 
pressure on the suggested price. Even in a machine-learning environment (as in the <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> case), prices provide a signal from 
which consumers can infer product quality, even as they influence the rate of information transmission via interpersonal com-
munication. 
Empirical evidence shows the positive effect of eWOM on sales for experience goods 3 (Chevalier &amp; Mayzlin, 2006; Cui, 
Lui, &amp; Guo, 2006; Duan, Gu, &amp; Whinston, 2008; Liu, 2006; Lu, Ba, Huang, &amp; Feng, 2013). Moreover, eWOM is shown to 
be particularly influential for recently introduced goods: the volume of reviews has a significant effect on new product sales in 
the early period and decreases over time (Liu, 2006; Zhu &amp; Zhang, 2010). On the other hand, extensive economic literature has 
explored the optimal pricing strategy and dynamics for new products of initially uncertain quality. Nevertheless, most signaling 
models have ignored learning from others and the question of whether and how interpersonal communication across consumers 
affects or is affected by prices. It is therefore interesting to study how a high-quality seller can take strategic advantage of 
experimentation and WOM when choosing his pricing strategy. This paper addresses these questions by providing a simple 
model in which WOM communication is combined with strategic pricing and signaling. 
Specifically, I consider a two-period model, in which a long-lived monopolist introduces a new experience good of unknown 
quality to consumers. The monopolist is privately informed about his type (either high or low), and a high-type seller is more 
likely to produce high-quality products. Consumers are short-lived and the satisfaction they receive from buying is a function of 
both objective quality and personal preference (or taste). First-period consumers can only rely on prices to infer the monopolist's 
type (and therefore expected quality). Second-period consumers, on the other hand, learn through the observation of noisy signals 
of past prices and observed quality. Notably, past prices are not directly observable, as public price information usually refers to 
the posted price, which does not accurately reflect the final transaction price because sales, discounts, and/or geographic price 
variations are not taken into account. Furthermore, consumers have been shown to have imprecise memories when it comes to 
the final price paid for the product. 4 Still, past consumers report through WOM communication the satisfaction obtained from 
the product, if purchased. Reports from past consumers are noisy signals of the observed quality as higher satisfaction can come 
either from high quality or from strong personal preference. Moreover, communication between past and present consumers 
is incomplete because social interaction remains limited by time, geography, and other constraint. 5 Nevertheless, information 
gathered through WOM communication is more precise when the fraction of consumers who bought in the past is high. 
I focus on the role of prices as signals of quality when consumers learn in equilibrium through both prices and WOM com-
munication. First, I characterize the benchmark case without WOM communication among consumers, and show that there is 
no separating equilibrium. I then show that, when allowing for WOM communication, there exists a separating equilibrium in 
which prices signal quality. Given a sample information structure, I study how the separating equilibrium responds to variation 
in the signal precision and compare consumer welfare in the benchmark and WOM case. Finally, I present model extensions. 
The main result is that WOM communication is essential for the existence of separating equilibria. Moreover, in any separating 
equilibrium, the high-quality monopolist signals quality through a low introductory price (lower than the monopoly price). 
The intuition is simple: low prices are costly, and will only be used by firms confident enough that increased experimentation 
(therefore communication among consumers) will yield good news about quality and increased future profits. The low-quality 
monopolist, on the other hand, avoids information transmission by choosing a higher price (the monopoly price), which limits 
sales and the possibility of learning through WOM. An additional implication: for the high-quality seller, the expected price 
(quantity) is increasing (decreasing) over time; whereas for the low-quality one, the opposite is true. Since the second-period 
price is a function of beliefs, it will be higher (lower) if good (bad) news is revealed in the first period when the product 
is introduced. Moreover, the (low) separating price charged by the high-quality monopolist in equilibrium decreases as the 
impact of signaling on consumers' beliefs increases: a high-quality seller must work harder to discourage the low-quality one 
from mimicking its behavior if consumers pay less attention to their peers' reports. Finally, consumers are better off with WOM 
communication. As a robustness check, I show that WOM communication and advertising can be either substitute or complement 
instruments for the firm. In particular, when allowed to use WOM, the firm will never use "money-burning" advertising as a 
signal of quality. On the contrary, when advertising is demand-enhancing, firms might use both instruments to signal quality. 
Finally, the equilibrium is robust to reporting bias by first-period consumers. </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>This paper contributes to the existing literature in at least three dimensions. I extend the signaling literature by allowing 
consumers' communication about product quality and by focusing on the case in which quality and costs are not correlated. The 
standard "you get what you pay for" result from the signaling literature is reverted when allowing for WOM communication 
among generations of consumers. Moreover, the situation in which quality is independent of marginal costs is particularly 
relevant for tech products with previously and exogenously research and development (R&amp;D)-determined quality. The result also 
extends the marketing literature, by offering a point of reference for comparison vis-à-vis the heretofore dominant marketing 
strategy-advertising. Even though WOM and advertising are related (both are forms of communication about product quality), 
the former is consumer-created communication and the latter is firm-created communication. Indeed, WOM communication is 
more effective than traditional advertising because it is more informative, persuasive, and trustworthy. Finally, the results are 
consistent with empirical evidence: WOM has positive effect on sales (see empirical literature cited above), but also high prices 
signal low quality (Jin &amp; Kato, 2006). </p>

<p>1.1 Related literature </p>

<p>This paper is closely related to the literature on signaling quality through prices and/or advertising. Milgrom and Roberts (1986) 
study a dynamic monopoly model in which both (introductory) price and advertising can signal quality. The main result is that 
price signaling will typically occur and (dissipative) advertising will be used in equilibrium when separation through prices 
is too costly. The extent to which price signaling occurs (through high or low prices) depends on the relationship between 
quality and marginal costs. In the general case, in which quality is correlated with costs, both high prices (supra-monopoly) and 
dissipative advertising signal quality. 6 Low prices are enough to signal quality when high-quality producers are more efficient. 7 
Prices and advertising are complementary instruments in the former case and substitute instruments in the latter when both act 
as demand-enhancing forces. Linnemer (2002) extends the previous model to consider a monopolist of intermediate age, so 
that some but not all consumers are informed about quality. Informed consumers here play a role similar to repeat-purchases in 
Milgrom-Roberts (1986). He confirms the Milgrom-Roberts (1986) result that (high) prices and advertising are complementary 
instruments to signal quality. Linnemer (2011, 2012) provides a third explanation that justifies signaling through both high prices 
and dissipative advertising: two-dimensional types, which allow for different degrees of correlation between production costs 
and product quality. Bagwell and Riordan (1991) show that high (and declining) prices signal quality in a static monopoly for 
durable goods and for different informational settings. This result is due to cost effects: signaling through high prices generates 
lower sales, which cause less damage to a higher cost producer. Judd and Riordan (1994) obtain the same result by examining 
a two-period signal-extraction model with learning. Even though no correlation between quality and costs is assumed, private 
information on both sides of the market allows the seller to signal quality through high prices. I extend the signaling literature 
by considering WOM communication among consumers and analyzing how it affects the firm' s pricing strategy. 
This paper is also related to a growing branch of the marketing literature that focuses on WOM communication as a new form 
of advertising. Mayzlin (2006) explores the situation in which advertising takes the form of promotional chat on the Internet, 
so that advertising and WOM act like perfect-substitute learning mechanisms. He shows the existence of a unique (pooling) 
equilibrium in which low-quality firms advertise more than high-quality ones (contrary to what the advertising literature pre-
dicts), who instead rely more on consumer recommendations. Chen and Xie (2008) argue that the direction of the interaction 
between advertising and WOM depends on product characteristics and market conditions. Given sufficiently informative con-
sumer reviews, advertising and WOM are complements when product cost is low and/or the ratio of expert consumers is high. 
On the other hand, when product cost is high, and consumers are mostly novices, advertising and WOM are substitutes. I extend 
the marketing literature by studying how WOM communication can be affected by prices and then used as a signal of product 
quality. 
Finally, this paper is related to the literature on strategic experimentation. When both firms and consumers are uncertain about 
product quality, initial sales help both sides of the market obtain information, so that low prices are optimal (Bergemann &amp; 
Valimaki 1996, 1997; Caminal &amp; Vives, 1999; Schlee, 2001). Without information asymmetries, no signaling arises. However, 
signaling quality through quantities is the main scope of Caminal and Vives (1996) and Vettas (1997). In a duopoly model, 
Caminal and Vives (1996) show that firms cut prices in an attempt to make consumers think the product sells more because of 
its higher quality and not simply because it is cheap. Their main focus is on market shares as signals of quality, even though 
there is no communication among consumers. Vettas (1997) studies the informational role of quantities when allowing for WOM 
communication among consumers in a monopoly market for durable goods. In this model, there is no separating equilibrium, but 
only a pooling one in which a high-quality seller spreads sales to incentivize communication between consumers, and therefore 
information transmission. I extend the last model by allowing learning in equilibrium from both prices and other consumers. 
In particular I nest WOM learning, as modeled in Banerjee and Fudenberg (2004), in a two-period signaling model, in which </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>learning in equilibrium comes from both prices and other consumers. Moreover, I exploit the fact that learning is noisy in the 
second period and the signals consumers receive can be ordered according to the precision criteria established by Ganuza and 
Penalva (2010), which facilitates the existence proof. 
The rest of the paper is organized as follows: the next section presents the model. Section 3 defines the separating equilibria 
and presents the main results. Sections 4 shows an application of the model and addresses comparative statics and consumer 
welfare. Section 5 presents extensions and discusses the robustness of results. Finally, Section 6 concludes. All proofs are in the 
Appendix. </p>

<p>2 THE MODEL </p>

<p>Consider a two-period model, in which a long-lived monopolist introduces a new experience good of unknown quality to con-
sumers. Quality is a random variable distributed according to ( ), with positive and differentiable density ( ). The param-
eter ∈ { , } represents the monopolist's type, which is private information and can be high or low. The distributions ( ) 
are ordered by first-order stochastic dominance (FOSD), with 
( ) &lt; ( ), for all . 8 Quality is exogenous and can be thought 
of as determined by R&amp;D prior to production, therefore unrelated to marginal costs, which I assume zero for both types. 
Consumers are short-lived and represented by a continuum of mass 1. They have unit demand for the product and receive 
satisfaction ( , ) from purchasing and zero otherwise. Satisfaction ( , ) is an increasing function of the common valuation 
(objective quality) and the individual valuation (taste) , an independent draw from distribution ( ) with positive and 
differentiable density ( ). 9 Therefore, consumer satisfaction provides valuable, but noisy, information about observed quality. 
The timing of the game is as follows: the monopolist learns and chooses the introductory price. First-period consumers 
observe the price, but not (nor ), update beliefs on the monopolist's type (therefore product quality), and make their purchase 
decisions. If they buy, satisfaction is then observed. At the beginning of the second period, new consumers enter the market and 
form their beliefs by observing noisy signals of past price and observed quality. The monopolist then sets the second-period 
price. Given second-period beliefs and price, consumers make a purchase decision. Second-period profits are realized and the 
game ends. </p>

<p>2.1 Consumer beliefs and information structure </p>

<p>Consumers share the prior belief 0 that the monopolist is a high-quality producer. First-period consumers can only rely on 
prices to update beliefs. Separating prices ( , 
) induce beliefs = 0 if = 
and = 1 if = 
. 10 Moreover, I 
restrict off-the-equilibrium path beliefs such that any deviation is attributed to the low-quality seller. Consumers learn their 
personal valuation and decide whether to buy given , and . They buy if and only if [ ( , ) − ] ≥ 0, which leads 
to the aggregate first-period demand ( , ), increasing in beliefs and decreasing in price. 
Second-period consumers have two mechanisms to infer the monopolist's type: noisy signals of past price and observed quality. 
They observe a noisy signal of , from which they (imperfectly) infer the belief (price signal). 11 Additionally, they communi-
cate with randomly sampled first-period consumers, who report the satisfaction obtained from the product, if purchased. From 
their average (random) report ( , ), 12 second-period consumers update the belief ( ) = ℙ( = H | r(q, v i )) (quality signal), 
whose expected value is Λ( ) = ( ( )) 13 and whose precision depends positively on ( , ). 14 After observing both signals, 
consumers form second-period beliefs 2 , which can be written as a function of , Λ( ) , and ( , ), 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )). 
The relative influence of each signal on second-period beliefs 2 depends on its respective informative content and precision. 
The signal ordering relies on the notion of supermodular precision as defined by Ganuza and Penalva (2010), which allows 
signals to be ordered in terms of their relative impacts on the distribution of conditional expectations. 15 The quality signal Λ( ) 
is more supermodular precise if the past quantity ( , ) is higher, as it increases the number of useful reports. On the other 
hand, the price signal is independent of ( , ). Moreover, more precise (informative) signals will have higher influence on 
updating consumers' beliefs (see lemma 1 in Ganuza &amp; Penalva, 2010). Therefore, second-period beliefs satisfy the following 
conditions: </p>

<p>1. </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>( , ) Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0, </p>

<p>2. </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0, </p>

<p>which imply that an increase in the quantity sold in the first period (directly or through higher first-period beliefs) makes WOM 
communication more informative. Moreover, I assume that second-period beliefs are increasing in . 16 After observing their </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>individual taste , second-period consumers decide whether to buy given 2 , 2 , and . They buy if and only if 2 [ ( , ) − </p>

<p>2 ] ≥ 0, which leads to the aggregate second-period demand ( 2 , 2 ). </p>

<p>2.2 Profits </p>

<p>Let Π( , , ) denote the expected profits of a monopolist of type who charged price in the first period, inducing beliefs : </p>

<p>Π( , , ) = 
( , ) + ∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) ( ) , 
(1) </p>

<p>where ( 2 ) represents second-period profits, which are increasing and convex in beliefs, and satisfy the following assumption: </p>

<p>Assumption 1. Second-period marginal profits are decreasing in observed quality: </p>

<p>2 ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) &lt; 0. </p>

<p>Assumption 1 ensures that low prices, therefore higher demand, are more beneficial to the high-quality monopolist that is 
more likely to produce high quality. An increase in ( , ) will be detrimental to beliefs when news is bad and quality poor, 
whereas it will improve the monopolist's reputation and profits when news is good. Note that this effect is more pronounced for 
the low-quality seller who has a worse (in terms of FOSD) quality distribution. </p>

<p>3 SEPARATING EQUILIBRIA </p>

<p>This paper considers the role of prices as signals of quality when consumers learn in equilibrium through WOM communication. 
Therefore, it is natural to focus on separating equilibria. In this context, separating equilibria are perfect Bayesian equilibria such 
that consumers can distinguish between the high-and low-quality producer by their different pricing choices. It is important to 
note that signaling occurs only in the first period. 17 In a separating equilibrium, consumers know the monopolist's type once 
the introductory price is chosen. A separating equilibrium ( , 
) induces beliefs = 0 if = 
and = 1 if = 
. 
Moreover, off-equilibrium prices ≠( , 
) are assumed to induce pessimistic beliefs = 0. </p>

<p>Definition 2. A (first-period) separating equilibrium is a pair ( , 
) such that: </p>

<p>C1. Π( , , = 0) ≥ Π( , , = 0), for every ≠ 
. </p>

<p>C2. Π( , , = 0) ≥ Π( , 
, = 1). </p>

<p>C3. Π( , 
, = 1) ≥ Π( , , = 0), for every ≠ 
. </p>

<p>For the low-quality monopolist, the equilibrium price 
must dominate any price ≠ 
that induces the same pessimistic 
beliefs (C1). Moreover, the low-quality monopolist should not have incentives to mimic its high-quality counterpart, even if 
this implies optimistic beliefs (C2). For the high-quality monopolist, 
must dominate any other price , knowing that any 
deviation will be treated as though it comes from a low-quality seller (C3). Lemma 9 follows from Definition 2. </p>

<p>Lemma 3. In any separating equilibrium 
= 
 *  , where 
 *  is the low-quality full-information monopoly price. For the </p>

<p>high-quality monopolist, it is sufficient to control for the best deviation, Π( , 
, = 1) ≥ Π( , 
 *  , = 0), where </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>maximizes expected profits under beliefs = 0. </p>

<p>Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>3.1 Benchmark case: in the absence of word-of-mouth communication </p>

<p>It is useful to establish a benchmark to compare the effects of WOM on the existence and characterization of separating equilibria. 
I consider the static version of the game, in which consumers learn from prices while they are not allowed to communicate with 
their peers. 18 When no communication among consumers is permitted, there is no fully revealing equilibrium in which prices 
signal quality. The only existing equilibria are pooling. Moreover, the only pooling equilibrium that survives the undefeated 
criterium proposed by Mailath, Okuno-Fujiwara, and Postlewaite (1993) is one in which the high-quality monopolist chooses 
its preferred price-the price that maximizes profits under the prior belief 0 -and the low-quality one mimics him. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>Lemma 4. Without WOM communication, there is no separating equilibrium. Indeed, the only pooling equilibrium that survives 
the undefeated refinement is  *  , the maximizer of 
( , 0 ). </p>

<p>Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>If consumers are not allowed to communicate about the observed quality, any price chosen by the high-quality seller can be 
costlessly mimicked by the low-quality counterpart. This is true because the high-quality monopolist cannot profitably use the 
price to manipulate information revelation and transmission between consumers' generations. Therefore, any equilibrium will 
be a pooling one. Nevertheless, the restriction on off-equilibrium beliefs makes most pooling equilibria implausible. The only 
pooling equilibrium that satisfies the undefeated criterium is the one in which the high-quality seller chooses his preferred price 
and is imitated by the low-quality seller. </p>

<p>3.2 Prices with word-of-mouth communication </p>

<p>I now consider the model in which consumers can learn through prices and WOM communication, and solve the game using 
backward induction. Following any history of separation (  *  , 
), consumers update beliefs to 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) and 
second-period prices maximize 2 ( 2 , 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))), which leads to second-period profits ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))). 
I look for separating equilibria as defined in Definition 2, and apply the intuitive criterion refinement (Cho &amp; Kreps, 1987) 
to eliminate implausible off-equilibrium beliefs. As shown in Lemma 3, the low-quality monopolist cannot do better than to 
behave as in the complete-information setting, by choosing the monopoly price. Thus, if the high-quality monopolist is to sep-
arate, then he must choose a price that the low-quality seller would not mimic (and from which he would not deviate). To 
focus on the case in which signaling is costly, I assume that the full-information monopoly price 
 *  *  does not satisfy C2, or </p>

<p>equivalently Π( , 
 *  *  , = 1) &gt; Π( ,  *  , = 0). 19 The main result is that WOM communication allows the existence of </p>

<p>separating equilibria, in which the high-quality monopolist signals high quality through a low introductory price (lower than 
the full-information monopoly price), whereas the low-quality monopolist charges a higher introductory price (higher than the 
full-information monopoly price). </p>

<p>Proposition 1. With WOM communication, there is always a separating equilibrium (  *  , 
) with 
&lt; 
 *  *  . </p>

<p>Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>The intuition behind this result is simple: low prices are costly, and will only be used by firms confident enough that increased 
experimentation (and therefore communication among consumers) will yield good news and therefore increased future profits. 
The high-quality monopolist aims to maximize the benefits from consumer communication through increased sales, and therefore 
uses a low price as a signal of quality. The low-quality monopolist, on the other hand, tries to avoid information transmission by 
choosing a higher price, which limits sales and the probability that future consumers learn through WOM. This result contradicts 
the standard signaling literature, according to which high prices signal high quality. Moreover, it complements both the literature 
on quantity as signals of quality and the marketing literature by characterizing the signaling equilibrium when WOM is allowed. 
As shown in Figure 1, the existence of a separating equilibrium is implied by two conditions: (i) 
2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0 (standard </p>

<p>single-crossing) and (ii) 
2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0 ("sensitivity" single-crossing). Condition (i) implies that the cost of signaling through </p>

<p>low prices is lower for the high-quality monopolist. So that, even when allowed to choose the optimal price, the high-quality 
monopolist will prefer to set a lower price than his low-quality counterpart, holding beliefs constant. The second condition (ii) 
requires that the shift from pessimistic to optimistic beliefs is more attractive to the high type than to his low-type counterpart. 20 
It follows, from Proposition 5, that there is no separating equilibrium in which high prices signal high quality. The result is 
due to the properties of second-period beliefs, which guarantee that standard single-crossing is negative. As more supermodular 
precise signals have stronger influence on updating consumers' beliefs, an increase in ( , ) ensures a higher impact of the 
quality signal on second-period beliefs. Therefore, more sales will be detrimental to beliefs when news is bad and quality is poor, 
whereas they will improve the monopolist's reputation and profits when news is good. Bacause the high-quality seller is more 
likely to spread good news, he will benefit more from high first-period demand. This fact makes the existence of separating 
equilibria in which high prices (low quantities) 21 signal high quality impossible. Some additional implications: for the high-
quality seller, the expected price (quantity) dynamic is increasing (decreasing) over time; whereas for the low-quality one, the 
opposite is true. Because the second-period price is a function of beliefs, it will be higher (lower) if good (bad) news is revealed 
in the first period when the product was introduced. 
Most of these separating equilibria involve beliefs that are implausible, bacause any deviation is interpreted as coming from 
a low-quality seller. To solve the problem of multiplicity of equilibria, I apply the intuitive criterion proposed by Cho and Kreps </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>F I G U R E 1 Sketch of the proof </p>

<p>(1987). A separating equilibrium (  *  , 
) fails the intuitive criterion if there exists a price ' such that: (a) Π( , 
′ , = </p>

<p>1) ≥ Π( , 
, = 1) and (b) Π( , 
′ , = 1) &lt; Π( ,  *  , = 0). That is, if there exists a price 
′ such that the high-quality </p>

<p>monopolist prefers to deviate and the low-quality monopolist makes more profits following the equilibrium strategy, even if the 
deviation would have generated optimistic beliefs. Intuitively, if such a price exists, consumers should interpret such a deviation 
as if it comes from a high-quality seller, which would collapse the equilibrium. </p>

<p>Proposition 2. The only pair that satisfies the intuitive criterion is (  *  , ), where the price charged by the high-quality 
monopolist is the least costly among the ones that induce separation, that is, 
=̄such that </p>

<p>Π( , , = 1) = Π( , </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>, = 0). </p>

<p>Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>4 TRUTH OR NOISE APPLICATION </p>

<p>I now provide an example of information structure that can be ranked according to the supermodular precision criterium. When 
second-period consumers enter the market, they observe a noisy signal of past prices, from which they infer the belief̃( ) 
(price signal). Additionally, they communicate with past consumers about the satisfaction obtained from the product, and 
update beliefs to ( ) (quality signal), whose expected value is Λ( ). Moreover, the number of reports received is proportional 
to the quantity sold by the monopolist in the first period, so that 
is increasing in ( , ). Therefore, 2 , the conditional 
expectation on the monopolist's type after receiving the two signals, can be written as 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )). The information 
structure I consider here is the "truth or noise" technology, as first defined by Lewis and Sappington (1994), or linear experiment, 
as defined by Ganuza and Penalva (2010). A "truth or noise" signal returns the true parameter with some probability, and pure 
noise with the complementary probability. Let the monopolist's type ∈ Θ be distributed according to a function ( ) with 
mean 0 , and let̃and be two signals about the true parameter . With probability ,̃= , and with probability 1 − , 
= , with = 0 . Similarly, with probability ( ( , )), ( ) = Λ( ), and with probability 1 − ( ( , )), no reports are 
received, so that ( ) = , with = 0 . Then, </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) ∶= ( = 
|̃, ) = 
+ (1 − ) ( ( , ))Λ( ) + (1 − )(1 − ( ( , ))) 0 . </p>

<p>It is easy to see that second-period beliefs satisfy the following conditions: </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>( , ) Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0 and </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0, 
which ensure that an increase in the quantity sold in the first period (directly or through higher first-period beliefs) makes 
the quality signal Λ( ) more supermodular precise, and therefore increases its impact on beliefs 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )). In </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>particular: </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) 
( , ) Λ( ) 
= 
( ( , )) 
( , ) 
(1 − ) &gt; 0, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) 
Λ( ) 
= 
( ( , )) 
( , ) 
( , ) (1 − ) &gt; 0. </p>

<p>4.1 Comparative static on the equilibrium price </p>

<p>As shown in Section 3.2, the only pair that survives the intuitive criterion is (  *  , ). The low-quality monopolist charges 
the full-information monopoly price, whereas the high-quality one charges the highest of the low prices that the low-quality 
monopolist would not find profitable to mimic. Consider now the "truth or noise" information structure with associated second-
period beliefs: </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( ( , ))) = 
+ (1 − ) ( ( , ))Λ( ) + (1 − )(1 − ( ( , ))) 0 . </p>

<p>It is interesting to analyze how the equilibrium price changes when the signaling channel becomes more important, or equiv-
alently how reacts to an increase in . The main result is that signaling becomes more difficult when consumers pay less 
attention to their peers' reports and more attention to past prices. Indeed, a good signal in the first period ( = 
) carries 
more positive information to second-period buyers about the monopolist's type, making it more attractive. To discourage the 
low-quality seller from mimicking, a lower price must be charged by the high-quality monopolist. </p>

<p>Proposition 3. The separating equilibrium price is decreasing in . </p>

<p>Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>4.2 Consumer welfare </p>

<p>I now compare consumer welfare under the separating equilibrium with WOM communication (  *  , ) to the benchmark case 
without information transmission, in which firms charge in both periods  *  , the solution to max 
( , 0 ) (see Lemma 4). 
The result here is that consumer welfare improves in both periods when allowing for WOM communication between generations. 
First-period consumers benefit from lower prices due to signaling. Second-period consumers gain, in expectation, from prices 
that reveal information by reflecting better the expected product quality. </p>

<p>Proposition 4. If </p>

<p>1.  *  &gt; 
 *  . </p>

<p>2. The inverse price elasticity </p>

<p>1 
( , ) </p>

<p>is convex in . </p>

<p>Then, both first-and second-period consumers are better off with WOM communication. </p>

<p>Proof. Proof. See Appendix A. 
□ </p>

<p>Assumption 1 ensures that, absent signaling motives, even low-quality firms benefit from generating some level of WOM 
buzz. This is true whenever the low-type monopolist produces high-quality products with a sufficiently high probability. Indeed, 
Assumption 1 is satisfied if, on average, news about quality is good news. 22 Assumption 2 is satisfied whenever beliefs gen-
erate a parallel shift of the demand function. As an example consider the following demand functions: ( , ) = − , or 
( , ) = ( ) + ( ) , with ( ) concave in . If both assumptions hold, then consumers are better off in both periods under 
the separating equilibrium with WOM. Note that both assumptions, particularly the first, are (overly) restrictive because I seek a 
strong result-one that guarantees a welfare improvement from WOM independent of the monopolist's type and for consumers 
in both periods. If I drop the first assumption, for example, WOM improves consumer welfare only if the seller is a high-type 
monopolist. Given this result, any policy that protects consumers ability to communicate about product quality without restric-
tion or bias yields a positive result. Again, this is particularly relevant for newly introduced technological and digital products, 
for which online WOM has been shown to have strong effects on sales. Regulation of online consumer fora, which may or may 
not be firm-hosted, would improve consumer welfare to the extent that it permits a free flow of information about product quality 
between consumers. </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>5 EXTENSIONS </p>

<p>This two-period framework allows for many interesting extensions. For example, the firm might communicate quality through 
other instruments, such as advertising, discounts, or return policies. First, I highlight the differences between WOM and adver-
tising by showing that no separating equilibrium exists when replacing the former with the latter. Next, I allow the monopolist 
to use WOM and advertising, and show that both instruments can be substitutes or complements depending on the nature of 
advertising (dissipative or informative). Finally, I endogenize the information transmission technology by allowing consumers 
to misrepresent quality and show how the separating equilibrium responds to reporting bias. </p>

<p>5.1 WOM versus advertising </p>

<p>I analyze a simplified version of the model presented in Section 2. Specifically, quality can only take two values, either high 
or low, ∈ {1, 0}, and the monopolist can signal quality through both prices and advertising. So that the expected profits of a 
monopolist of type who chooses the pair ( , ) in the first period, inducing beliefs , are: </p>

<p>Π( , , , ) = 
( , , ) + [ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 1), ( , , )))] + (1 − )[ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 0), ( , , )))], 
(2) </p>

<p>where ( , , ) represents (first-period) demand and ( 2 ) (second-period) indirect profit function. Note that advertising can 
be either dissipative, 23 as in the standard Milgrom-Roberts (1986) setup, so that 
( , , ) = 0 or it can be informative or 
"demand-enhancing," 
( , , ) &gt; 0 (see Appendix B.1 for a detailed description of the simplified model). </p>

<p>5.1.1 WOM versus dissipative advertising </p>

<p>A high-quality monopolist will never use "money burning" (dissipative) advertising to signal quality, regardless of whether or 
not WOM communication is used. In particular, when replacing WOM with advertising, there is no separating equilibrium and 
the only existing equilibrium is a pooling one, which entails no advertising expenditure. 24 The intuition of the result is analogous 
to the benchmark case (Lemma 4). If the high-quality monopolist cannot profitably use price and/or advertising to manipulate 
information transmission among consumers, then any choice he makes will be costlessly mimicked by the low-quality firm. 
Similarly, when the monopolist can use both instruments to signal quality, he will only rely on low prices (therefore WOM) to 
signal quality, so that a separating equilibrium exists and it is the same as the one characterized in Section 3.2. Therefore, WOM 
(driven by low prices) and advertising are substitute instruments for the firm. The two instruments are similar in that, from 
the monopolist's point of view, they are both ways of throwing money away. Nevertheless, WOM entails a cost proportional to 
demand, whereas dissipative advertising is a fixed cost. Thus, low prices are less costly for the high-quality firm who benefits 
more from spreading news through high WOM buzz. See Appendix B.2 for a formal argument. </p>

<p>5.1.2 WOM versus informative advertising </p>

<p>Consider now the case in which advertising is informative or "demand-enhancing," so that it can be used as an instrument 
to amplify the (good or bad) news about quality. This can happen through two alternative mechanisms. First, advertising can 
amplify the quality signal by enhancing first-period demand, 
( , , ) &gt; 0. As an example consider the demand function 
( , , ) = ( ) ( , ) with (⋅) increasing and concave in , where advertising's main function is to expand the market 
size, therefore WOM. 25 This model can be thought of as one in which WOM is advertising-dependent (not only price-dependent). 
Second, advertising can operate as a "megaphone" for second-period consumers by stressing the effect of the quality signal on 
second-period beliefs. For example, suppose that firms pay information intermediaries a commission fee in return for a more 
favorable quality recommendation or pay search engines for prominent placement. Therefore, second-period beliefs can be </p>

<p>written as 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ), ) with </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0. In both cases, there exists a separating equilibrium in which WOM 
(driven by low prices) and informative advertising might be both used as signals of quality. In particular, prices and informative 
advertising are complementary instruments that can help the high-quality monopolist to separate from the low-quality one. See 
Appendix B.3 for a formal argument. </p>

<p>5.2 Reporting bias </p>

<p>Consumers may face incentives to lie about quality, for example, in order to obtain lower prices. Indeed, the firm may incentivize 
first-period consumers to misreport quality by offering a discount. 26 Consider the simplified version of the model with two 
quality levels, ∈ {1, 0}, and the firm implementing the following "please lie" campaign, with intensity . At a cost ( ), </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>increasing and convex, only a fraction of first-period consumers misreport quality. In particular, a fraction reports̃( , ) = 
( = 1, ), whereas the remaining fraction 1 − reports the truth, ( , ). The monopolist can signal quality through both 
instruments, namely, prices and the "please lie" campaign. So that the expected profits of a monopolist of type who chooses 
the pair ( , ) in the first period, inducing beliefs , are: </p>

<p>Π( , , , ) = [ 
( , ) − ( )] + ( + (1 − ))[ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 1), ( , )))] </p>

<p>+ (1 − )(1 − )[ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 0), ( , )))]. </p>

<p>The main result is that the high-quality monopolist will not use the strategy in any separating equilibrium, still preferring 
low prices (WOM) to signal quality. This is mainly because the low-quality seller benefits more from (overly) biased reports 
achieved through the "please lie" campaign. Therefore, the least-costly signaling strategy for the high-quality monopolist is to 
avoid biased reports. For a detailed analysis, see Section 5.2 of the Appendix. </p>

<p>6 CONCLUSION </p>

<p>This paper studies the optimal pricing strategy for new experience goods in a dynamic monopoly with private information 
about quality and WOM communication. Prices provide a signal from which consumers can infer product quality, even as they 
influence the rate of information transmission via interpersonal communication. More sales lead to higher product exposure 
in the subsequent period, which amplifies the good (or bad) news generated by the product through WOM communication. 
Thus, prices become an instrument through which firms may signal quality by encouraging or discouraging experimentation 
and thereby controlling the diffusion of information. In this framework, I show the existence of separating equilibria in which 
low prices signal high quality. Furthermore, I extend the model to check robustness and endogenize some model features. I 
compare the effectiveness of WOM-affected pricing and advertising in allowing high-quality firms to separate from low-quality 
ones, and find that (low) prices (that generate more WOM communication) allow separation, whereas advertising does not. I 
also investigate incentives for bias in consumer reporting, finding that in this context, consumers are driven to report observed 
quality truthfully. Finally, I show that WOM communication is beneficial to consumers and discuss policy implications. 
The main contribution is to allow learning in equilibrium from both prices and other consumers, in a setting in which 
firms are equally efficient (quality and costs are not correlated). In particular, learning via WOM, as modeled in Banerjee 
and Fudenberg (2004), is introduced in a two-period signaling model. From a technical point of view, the paper provides an 
insight on how to characterize separating equilibria when the Spence-Mirrlees condition is not sufficient. In particular, two 
cross-derivatives, standard single-crossing and "sensitivity" single-crossing properties, are sufficient for the existence of sep-
arating equilibria. Moreover, I use the precision criteria proposed by Ganuza and Penalva (2010) to order signals received by 
second-period consumers. This innovative approach allows consumers to rank signals based on their relative precision and 
impact on the belief function. As first-period demand increases, so does the weight consumers assign to information from WOM 
communication. 
This framework can be extended in many interesting ways. For example, exploring price dynamics in the infinite-horizon 
version of the model. Moreover, relaxing the assumption that consumers are short-lived to allow for a fraction of long-lived 
consumers may reveal interesting insights on consumers' incentives to truthfully report quality. Introducing competition among 
firms in order to investigate its implication on the equilibrium price and welfare is also of interest. An ambitious extension that 
evaluates the effect of WOM communication using networks and influential consumers (digital influentials such as bloggers and 
celebrities, for example) on signaling quality is very intriguing. Here, consumers give more weight to information coming from 
within tight and trusted friend and family networks, as well as recommendations made by experts and even celebrities. Finally, 
it would be nice to further explore the situation in which firms make use of WOM communication through both pricing and 
(nondissipative) advertising strategies. </p>

<p>E N D N O T E S </p>

<p>1 WOM refers to product-related commentary shared between friends, family, neighbors, etc. Moreover, advances in information technology and the </p>

<p>digital revolution both facilitate and amplify the exchange of information on products via social networking sites and other online fora, such as 
<rs type="software">Facebook</rs>, <rs type="software">Twitter</rs>, forums, blogs, etc., referred to as eWOM. </p>

<p>2 Creative goods such as books (unless judged by the cover), restaurants, movies, and records are examples, as are services like hotels, vacation rentals, </p>

<p>and consumer electronics like video games, mobile phones, apps, and digital cameras. </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>3 According to Bughin et al. (2010), "In the mobile-phone market, for example, we have observed that the pass-on rates for key positive and negative </p>

<p>messages can increase a company's market share by as much as 10 percent or reduce it by 20 percent over a two-year period, all other things being 
equal. This effect alone makes a case for more systematically investigating and managing word of mouth." </p>

<p>4 See Caminal and Vives (1996) for a more detailed explanation of why price histories may be nonobservable. </p>

<p>5 See Banerjee and Fudenberg (2004) for a more detailed explanation of why consumers are often allowed to communicate with just a fraction of </p>

<p>previous users. </p>

<p>6 The high-cost, high-quality monopolist suffers less from contracting demand in the first period (lower markup), but also suffers more in the second </p>

<p>period because of lower sales (repeat-purchases effect). Due to these counteracting effects, the high-quality monopolist may have no better option 
than to use dissipative advertising, along with a distorted price, to avoid copycat behavior (while high prices increase costs proportional to demand, 
wasteful advertising is a fixed cost that does not allow the low-quality monopolist to benefit from copying). </p>

<p>7 In this case, both the markup and the repeat-business effects point in the same direction and high prices are more costly to the high-quality seller. </p>

<p>8 I assume permanent types; therefore, quality realizations are independent draws from the same distribution ( ) in both periods. Moreover, quality </p>

<p>is the same for all units produced in each period. </p>

<p>9 For example, satisfaction can be one of the following functions: ( , ) = + or ( , ) = 
. </p>

<p>10 By observing the separating price, consumers will automatically know from which distribution quality has been drawn. On the other hand, pooling </p>

<p>prices do not provide any information and the posterior is unaltered, = 0 . </p>

<p>11 Specifically, they observe a noisy signal of , from which they infer the belief̃( ) about the monopolist's type (price signal), as a function of the </p>

<p>true . </p>

<p>12 For simplicity, I drop the problem of integrality of the number of reports. </p>

<p>13 Λ( ) is the update on the monopolist's (high) type after the observed quality, absent the noise caused by individual shock . </p>

<p>14 The number of reports received is proportional to first-period demand. </p>

<p>15 Basically, an information structure (the joint distribution of the unknown parameter and the signal) is more informative (more precise) than another </p>

<p>if it generates a more disperse distribution of conditional expectations. </p>

<p>16 The belief generated by signaling, , has a dual effect on second-period beliefs. The first one is direct, whereas the second one operates through an </p>

<p>increase in ( , ), which, in turn, amplifies the effect of the quality signal. I assume that the direct effect dominates the indirect one. </p>

<p>17 The assumption that types are permanent prevents the need to consider dynamic signaling. Moreover, as it is a finite-horizon game, in = 2, there </p>

<p>is no reason for firms to separate. </p>

<p>18 The same result holds for the two-period model without WOM communication, as well as for the case in which WOM is exogenous (therefore </p>

<p>independent of first-period demand). </p>

<p>19 The high-quality full-information monopoly price 
 *  *  is defined as the price that maximizes high-quality monopolist's expected profits under </p>

<p>correct beliefs = 1, Π( , , = 1). </p>

<p>20 In Spence's job-market signaling model, good-type workers signal high-quality via increased education, which at some critical point, bad types are </p>

<p>unable to replicate because education is assumed to be more costly for them. Here, the logic of the signaling mechanism does not depend on cost 
differences across types, instead copycat behavior is prevented by the existence of a second period with improved information (standard single-
crossing). Nevertheless, in contrast to Spence's model where the worker's utility, quasi-linear in beliefs, ensures condition (ii), in our setup, signaling 
also requires profits to be marginally more sensitive to type for beliefs (sensitivity single-crossing). </p>

<p>21 Note that in the experimentation process, second-period consumers observe some noisy signal of the past quantity (for instance, the number of people </p>

<p>they meet who tell them they have purchased the product and how satisfied they were). Hence, signaling through (low) prices or (high) quantities 
will yield the same result. </p>

<p>22 A sufficient condition for Assumption 1 to be satisfied is ∫ </p>

<p>( 2 ( =0,Λ( ), ( , =0))) </p>

<p>2 ( =0,Λ( ), ( , =0)) </p>

<p>2 ( =0,Λ( ), ( , =0)) 
( , =0) </p>

<p>( ) &gt; 0. </p>

<p>23 Any ad campaign that conveys no direct information about the quality of the product. </p>

<p>24 Without WOM communication, profits 2 reduces to Π( , , , ) = 
( , , ) + ( 2 ( )), which are independent of the monopolist's type. </p>

<p>25 Consider, as an example, the referrals program implemented by <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> to encourage inviting friends by giving both the sender and recipient $25 of </p>

<p>travel credit when the invited user completes their first trip. The idea is to increase WOM by stimulating the demand. </p>

<p>26 Consumers may also spontaneously misreport quality (imagine that consumers are friends of a restaurant owner or recently opened store). In this </p>

<p>case, the bias can be one of the two types. First, consumers may report a satisfaction level higher than what they actually experienced, that is, 
( , ) = ( , ) + . Second, consumers may report as high quality was observed, that is,̃( , ) = ( = 1, ). In the first scenario, the quality 
signal Λ( ) is unchanged due to the systematic bias in consumers Bayesian updating. In other words, if misreporting generates differences in reports, 
then second-period consumers can filter it out. Thus, the separating equilibrium is the same as the one characterized in Section 3.2. In the second 
scenario, the quality signal is Λ( = 1), as low quality is never reported. Expected profits are then independent of the monopolist's type and the 
high-quality monopolist can no longer use prices to manipulate information transmission. Therefore, there is no separating equilibrium. </p>

<p>27 Again, I restrict off-the-equilibrium path beliefs such that any deviation is attributed to the low-quality seller. </p>

<p>28 Again, no opportunities for signaling remain in the second period; therefore, ( 2 , 2 ) are the solution to the problem: max ( 2 , 2 ) 2 ( 2 , 2 , 2 ) − 
( 2 ). </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>



<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>APPENDIX A </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma 3. A necessary condition for C1 to be satisfied is that the low-quality monopolist charges in equilibrium 
the full-information monopoly price, 
 *  , which is the price that maximizes expected profits under the correct beliefs ( = 0). </p>

<p>Moreover, C3 requires that the high-quality monopolist should not have any incentive to deviate from the equilibrium price, 
as such deviation implies pessimistic beliefs. Then, it is sufficient to control for the best deviation, which occurs at 
 *  , the </p>

<p>maximizer of Π( , , = 0). 
□ </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma 4. We show this result by contradiction. Let ( , ) = 
( , ) denote the one-period profits of a monopolist 
of type who sets the price , inducing beliefs . As a corollary of Lemma 3, two conditions guarantee the existence of a 
separating equilibrium: </p>

<p>C1 (  *  , = 0) ≥ ( 
, = 1), and </p>

<p>C2 ( 
, = 1) ≥ (  *  , = 0). </p>

<p>Consider a separating equilibrium (  *  , 
) where 
= such that (  *  , = 0) = ( , = 1). At this price, the high-
quality seller should not have any incentive to deviate to his monopoly price, ( , = 1) &gt; (  *  , = 0), or equivalently 
(  *  , = 0) &gt; (  *  , = 0). This cannot be true basause 
 *  = 
 *  . Therefore, the only existing equilibrium is a pooling </p>

<p>one. Note that all the prices such that ( , = 0 ) ≥ (  *  , = 0) are pooling equilibria. Nevertheless, most of them are 
supported by implausible off-equilibrium beliefs, because every deviation is thought of as coming from a low-quality seller. 
Such implausible equilibria can be ruled out by the undefeated refinement proposed by Mailath et al. (1993). In particular, 
the only pooling equilibrium that survives the undefeated refinement is  *  , the price that maximizes ( , 0 ). Consider a 
proposed equilibrium &lt;  *  and the price  *  , chosen in an alternative equilibrium by some firm's type. If some type prefers 
the alternative equilibrium price  *  to the proposed one (and this preference is strict for at least one type), then consumers' 
beliefs that the deviator is of that type are increasing. Then, a profitable deviation appears for the firm that upset the equilibrium. 
Note that here, both types would strictly prefer to deviate to the alternative equilibrium price; therefore, the only undefeated 
equilibrium involves firms pooling at  *  . 
□ </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 5. As a corollary of Lemma 9, two conditions guarantee the existence of a separating equilibrium: </p>

<p>C1 Π( ,  *  , = 0) ≥ Π( , 
, = 1), and </p>

<p>C2 Π( , 
, = 1) ≥ Π( , 
 *  , = 0). </p>

<p>Consider the price &lt; 
 *  , such that the low-quality monopolist is indifferent between following the equilibrium strategy </p>

<p>or mimic his high-quality counterpart, Π( , , = 1) = Π( ,  *  , = 0). A separating equilibrium exists if at this price, the 
high-quality monopolist has no incentive to deviate to his monopoly price: </p>

<p>Π( , , = 1) − Π( , 
 *  , = 0) &gt; 0 = Π( , , = 1) − Π( , 
 *  , = 0) 
(A.1) </p>

<p>[Π( , , = 0) − Π( , 
 *  , = 0)] + [Π( , , = 1) − Π( , , = 0)] </p>

<p>&gt;[Π( , , = 0) − Π( , 
 *  , = 0)] + [Π( , , = 1) − Π( , , = 0)]. </p>

<p>For (A.1) to be satisfied, the following two conditions are sufficient: </p>

<p>1. [Π( , , = 0) − Π( , 
 *  , = 0)] &gt; [Π( , , = 0) − Π( ,  *  , = 0)]. </p>

<p>2. [Π( , , = 1) − Π( , , = 0)] &gt; [Π( , , = 0) − Π( ,  *  , = 0)]. </p>

<p>As shown in Figure 1, these two conditions are implied by: </p>

<p> *  &lt; 
 *  , 
(A.2) </p>

<p>2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0, 
(A.3) </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0. 
(A.4) </p>

<p>As (A.2) is implied by (A.3), then it is enough to show that 
2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0: </p>

<p>2 Π( , , ) = 
{ 
( , ) + ∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) ( ) </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) 
( ) 
} </p>

<p>= ∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) 
( ) . </p>

<p>Since the family of distributions ( ) is ordered by FOSD, then the integral is negative for every decreasing function in . Note 
that the function 
( 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , ))) is decreasing in by Assumption 1. Finally, sensitivity single-crossing should be positive, </p>

<p>2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0: </p>

<p>2 Π( , , ) = 
{ </p>

<p>∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) 
( ) 
} </p>

<p>= ∫ 
( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) 
( ) . </p>

<p>Because the family of distributions ( ) is ordered by FOSD, then the integral is positive for every increasing function in . 
Therefore, it is enough to show that 
( 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , ))) is increasing in : </p>

<p>2 ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) = 
{ ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>= 
Λ( ) 
( 2 ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) </p>

<p>2 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) 
Λ( ) </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>+ 
Λ( ) 
( ( 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))) </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) 
Λ( ) </p>

<p>) 
, </p>

<p>which is positive because second-period profits are increasing and convex in beliefs, second-period beliefs are increasing in 
the quality and price signal, and the quality signal Λ( ) is increasing in the observed quality. Moreover, second-period beliefs </p>

<p>satisfy : </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , )) </p>

<p>Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0 (an increase in first-period beliefs generates more demand, which, in turn, makes the quality 
signal Λ( ) more informative, and therefore increases its impact on beliefs 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))). 
□ </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 6. The proof consists of two steps. I first show that there is no equilibrium price &lt; that satisfies the 
intuitive criterion. Consider the price &lt; such that (  *  , ) is a separating equilibrium. Define 
′ = + . Then, it is easy </p>

<p>to see that (a) Π( , 
′ , = 1) ≥ Π( , , = 1) and (b) Π( , 
′ , = 1) &lt; Π( ,  *  , = 0). Noting that 
 *  *  &gt; 
 *  and 
 *  &gt; &gt; 
′ , it follows that 
 *  *  &gt; 
′ &gt; . Therefore, Π( , 
′ , = 1) ≥ Π( , , = 1). Moreover, by Proposition 5, </p>

<p>Π( , , = 1) &lt; Π( ,  *  , = 0), then by continuity, Π( , 
′ , = 1) &lt; Π( ,  *  , = 0). Thus, for any price, &lt; con-</p>

<p>dition (a) is not satisfied, violating the intuitive criterion. I now show that (  *  , ) is the only separating equilibrium that 
satisfies the intuitive criterion. If 
′ &lt; , condition (a) is not satisfied. Then, 
′ ≥ . But if 
′ &gt; , there is no separating </p>

<p>equilibrium, because any deviation at 
′ &gt; is profitable for the low-quality seller, as shown in Proposition 5. Then, it must </p>

<p>be 
′ = , and (  *  , ) is the only separating equilibrium that satisfies the intuitive criterion. 
□ </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 7. The least costly equilibrium price is such that Π( ,  *  , = 0) = Π( , , = 1). It is therefore 
enough to analyze how the last equality varies with : </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>Π( ,  *  , = 0) = 
Π( , , = 1) </p>

<p>× </p>

<p>{ 
 *  ( 
 *  , = 0) + ∫ 
( 2 ( , = 0, Λ( ), ( 
 *  , = 0))) ( ) </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>{ 
( , = 1) + ∫ 
( 2 ( , = 1, Λ( ), ( , = 1))) ( ) </p>

<p>} 
. </p>

<p>Therefore: </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>[ </p>

<p>( 2 ( ,0,Λ( ), (  *  ,0))) </p>

<p>2 ( ,0,Λ( ), (  *  ,0)) </p>

<p>2 ( ,0,Λ( ), (  *  ,0)) − </p>

<p>( 2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1))) </p>

<p>2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1)) </p>

<p>2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1)) </p>

<p>] 
( ) </p>

<p>[ 
( 
( ,1) + ( , 1)) + ∫ </p>

<p>( 2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1))) </p>

<p>2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1)) </p>

<p>2 ( ,1,Λ( ), ( ,1)) 
( ,1) </p>

<p>( ,1) </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>] 
&lt; 0. </p>

<p>Note that the equilibrium price is decreasing in as from the last expression, the numerator is negative and the denominator 
is positive. The numerator is negative because second-period beliefs are increasing in , the weight consumers attribute to sig-
naling, when beliefs generated by signaling are the most optimistic, = 1; whereas the contrary occurs for the most pessimistic 
case, in which = 0. The denominator is the sum of two terms, both positive. In particular, the first term represents first-period 
marginal income, which is positive given &lt; 
 *  *  . The second term is also positive because first-period demand is decreasing </p>

<p>in price, and second-period beliefs are decreasing in demand-the weight placed on the quality signal-when the price signal 
is the most favorable, = 1. 
□ </p>

<p>Proof of Proposition 8. Consumers' surplus is given by </p>

<p>( , ) = ∫ =  *  ( ) </p>

<p>[ </p>

<p>∫ 
( ( , ) − ) ( ) </p>

<p>] 
( ) , </p>

<p>where  *  ( ) is defined by ∫ ( ,  *  ( )) ( ) = . Consider first = 1. Given Assumption 1, first-period consumers benefit 
from WOM communication independent of the monopolist's type. Indeed, the price charged by either firms is lower than the 
price consumers would pay in the benchmark without WOM, that is,  *  &gt; 
 *  &gt; . First, note that 
 *  &gt; by definition. </p>

<p>Then, consider the low-type monopolist maximization problem, with first-order condition (FOC): </p>

<p>[ 
( , = 0) + ( , = 0) 
] </p>

<p>+ ( , = 0) ∫ 
( 2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0))) </p>

<p>2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0)) </p>

<p>2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0)) 
( , = 0) 
( ) = 0. </p>

<p>Let denote the myopic monopoly price by 
. Note that </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>( 2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0))) </p>

<p>2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0)) </p>

<p>2 ( = 0, Λ( ), ( , = 0)) 
( , = 0) 
( ) &gt; 0 </p>

<p>is a sufficient condition for Assumption 1 to be satisfied, so that the marginal income is positive and 
&gt; 
 *  . Moreover, 
 *  &gt; 
because is increasing in . Therefore,  *  &gt; 
 *  &gt; . Consider now = 2. Following any history of separation, </p>

<p>second-period prices maximize 2 ( 2 , 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , ))). Note that second-period belief 2 ( , Λ( ), ( , )) is a martin-
gale (specifically, it is a weighted average of martingales). Think, for example, of the belief 2 derived by the "truth or noise" 
information structure, for the particular case in which quality is a discrete variable, either high or low. I now show that demand 
functions that satisfy Assumption 2 are such that 2 is a supermartingale with respect to  *  . Let 0 be a martingale, that is, </p>

<p>0 = Λ(1) + (1 − )Λ(0) , ∈ (0, 1), and consider the maximization problem </p>

<p>max 
( , ) </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>with solution ( ) = − </p>

<p>( , ) 
( , ) </p>

<p>, for any ∈ { 0 , Λ(1), Λ(0)} . It is enough to show that if 0 is a martingale, then ( 0 ) is a 
supermartingale: </p>

<p>− 
( , 0 ) 
( , 0 ) 
≥ − 
( , Λ(1)) 
( , Λ(1)) 
− (1 − ) 
( , Λ(0)) 
( , Λ(0)) 
, </p>

<p>( , 0 ) 
( , 0 ) 
≤ 
( , Λ(1)) 
( , Λ(1)) 
+ (1 − ) 
( , Λ(0)) 
( , Λ(0)) 
, </p>

<p>which is true for any demand function with (inverse) price elasticity </p>

<p>1 
( , ) </p>

<p>convex in . For example, for every demand function 
of the form ( , ) = − , or ( , ) = ( ) + ( ) , if ( ) is concave in . Therefore, on average, 2 ≤  *  . Basically, 
because consumer surplus is convex in prices, a mean preserving spread in prices is beneficial to consumers. As long as prices 
are a supermartingale, which is guaranteed by Assumption 2, prices are in average lower under the separating equilibrium. 
In conclusion, consumer welfare in the second period is not reduced with WOM communication. Therefore, consumers are 
unequivocally better off when allowing for WOM communication. 
□ </p>

<p>APPENDIX B: EXTENSIONS </p>

<p>B.1 The simplified model with Advertising </p>

<p>Consider now a simplified version of the model in which quality can only take two values, high or low, ∈ {1, 0}. Quality 
depends on the monopolist's type, ∈ { , }, with = ℙ(q = 1). A high-quality monopolist has higher probability of produc-
ing high-quality products. The monopolist is long-lived and each period chooses price and advertising, ( , ). Marginal costs 
are zero for both types, and denote by ( ) the cost of advertising expenditure, which is increasing and convex. Consumers are 
short-lived and represented by a continuum of mass 1. They have unit demand for the product and receive satisfaction ( , ) 
if they purchase and zero otherwise. The timing of the game is as follows: the monopolist learns his type and chooses the intro-
ductory price and advertising level. After observing the pair ( , ), consumers update beliefs on the monopolist's type (and 
therefore product quality) and make their purchase decisions. If they buy, satisfaction is then observed. At the beginning of the 
second period, new consumers enter the market and form their beliefs by observing noisy signals of past price, advertising and 
observed quality. The monopolist then sets the second-period price and advertising expenditure. Given second-period beliefs 
and price, consumers make a purchase decision. Second-period profits are realized and the game ends. 
Consumers' beliefs and information structure. Consumers share the prior belief 0 that the monopolist is a high-
quality producer. First-period consumers observe ( , ) and update beliefs on . A separating strategy [( , ), ( 
, 
)] 
induces beliefs = 0 if ( , ) = ( , ) and = 1 if ( , ) = ( 
, 
). 27 Given , 
and consumers' demand is 
given by ( , , ). Note that advertising can be both dissipative, as in the standard Milgrom-Roberts (1986) setup, so 
that 
( , , ) = 0, or it can be informative or "demand-enhancing," 
( , , ) &gt; 0. Second-period consumers observe 
noisy signals of past price and advertising expenditure ( , ), from which they infer the belief̃( ) about the monopolist's 
type, as a function of the true . Additionally, they communicate with 
randomly sampled first-period consumers, who 
report the satisfaction obtained from the product, if purchased. From their average (random) report ( , ), second-period con-
sumers update the belief ( ) = ℙ( = H | r(q, v i )) (quality signal). Note that the belief ( ) is a noisy signal of the true belief 
Λ( ) = ℙ( = H | q): </p>

<p>Λ( = 1) = </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>+ (1 − 0 ) 
, Λ( = 0) = 
0 (1 − ) 
0 (1 − ) + (1 − 0 )(1 − ) </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>whose precision depends positively on ( , , ). After observing both signals, consumers form second-period beliefs </p>

<p>2 ( , Λ( ), ( , , )) that can be ordered by supermodular precision. Second-period consumers decide whether to buy given 
2 , 2 , and , which leads to second-period demand ( 2 , 2 ). 28 
Profits. Let Π( , , , ) denote the expected profits of a monopolist of type who chooses the pair ( , ) in the first period, 
inducing beliefs : </p>

<p>Π( , , , ) = 
( , , ) + [ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 1), ( , , )))] + (1 − )[ ( 2 ( , Λ( = 0), ( , , )))], </p>

<p>where ( 2 ) represents the indirect profit function of the monopolist in the second period (increasing and convex in beliefs). </p>

<p>GUADALUPI </p>



<p>Separating equilibria are defined according to Definition 2 and Lemma 3. Therefore, two conditions guarantee the existence 
of a separating equilibrium: </p>

<p>1. Π( ,  *  ,  *  , = 0) ≥ Π( , 
, 
, = 1). </p>

<p>2. Π( , 
, 
, = 1) ≥ Π( , 
 *  , 
 *  , = 0). </p>

<p>I focus on the least costly separating equilibrium (i.e., the equilibrium that satisfies the intuitive criterium) that the low-quality 
monopolist would not mimic, that is, the pair ( , ) that solves the following problem: </p>

<p>max </p>

<p>( , ) </p>

<p>Π( = , , , = 1) </p>

<p>. . Π( = , 
 *  , 
 *  , = 0) ≥ Π( = , , , = 1) </p>

<p>with associated Lagrangian </p>

<p> = Π( = H, P, A, = 1) + 
[ 
Π( = L, P 
L *  , A 
L *  , = 0) − Π( = L, P, A, = 1) 
] 
. 
(B.1) </p>

<p>B.2 WOM versus dissipative advertising </p>

<p>Lemma 9. If advertising is dissipative, then, in any separating equilibrium, the high-quality monopolist chooses low prices and 
no advertising to signal high quality. </p>

<p>Proof. Existence. The existence proof follows the same reasoning as Proof of Proposition 5. In particular, two single-crossing 
properties guarantee the existence of a separating equilibrium given that advertising is dissipative. 
Characterization. Suppose that the solution to problem (B.1) entails positive advertising. Then, the FOC with respect to 
advertising reduces to = 1, because dissipative advertising implies that Π( , , , ) depends on only through − 
′ ( ). </p>

<p>Consider now the FOC with respect to price. Using = 1: </p>

<p>Π( , , , = 1) − 
Π( , , , = 1) = 0, </p>

<p>which cannot be satisfied because standard single-crossing implies 
2 Π( , , , ) &lt; 0 (LHS&lt;0). Therefore, advertising is not used </p>

<p>in equilibrium by a high-quality monopolist. 
□ </p>

<p>B.3 WOM versus informative advertising </p>

<p>Lemma 10. If advertising is informative, in any separating equilibrium, the high-quality monopolist might use either instru-
ments, prices, and advertising, to signal high quality. </p>

<p>Proof. Existence. Following Proof of Proposition 5, the existence of a separating equilibrium is guaranteed by three single-
crossing properties: 
2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0 (standard SCP), 
2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0 (sensitivity SCP) and (advertising SCP) 
2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0. The </p>

<p>last condition states that informative advertising is marginally more profitable for the high-quality producer. Because he is more 
likely to produce high-quality products, he benefits more from amplifying the good news about the observed quality through 
informative advertising. 
Characterization. Suppose that the solution to problem (B.1) entails positive advertising. Then, FOCs can be written as </p>

<p> ∶ </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>= &gt; 1, </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF ECONOMICS &amp; MANAGEMENT STRATEGY </p>

<p>since 
2 Π( , , , =1) &gt; 0 . Note that for the case in which advertising is demand-enhancing, 
2 Π( , , , =1) &gt; 0 given </p>

<p>( , , ) &gt; 0, ( 2 ) convex in beliefs, and condition 1 on second-period beliefs: </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , , )) </p>

<p>( , , ) Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0. Similarly, when </p>

<p>advertising acts as a "megaphone", 
2 Π( , , , =1) &gt; 0, given ( 2 ) convex in beliefs and </p>

<p>2 2 ( ,Λ( ), ( , , )) </p>

<p>Λ( ) </p>

<p>&gt; 0. Moreover, </p>

<p> ∶ </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>= &gt; 1, </p>

<p>since standard single-crossing implies 
2 Π( , , , ) &lt; 0. Therefore, informative advertising and low introductory prices are com-</p>

<p>plementary instruments for the firm to signal quality: 
2 Π( , , , =1) &gt; 0 and 
2 Π( , , , ) &lt; 0. In fact, the monopolist will use </p>

<p>both instruments if Inada conditions hold. 
□ </p>

<p>B.4 Reporting bias </p>

<p>Lemma 11. In any separating equilibrium, the high-quality monopolist chooses low prices and no investment in the "please 
lie" campaign, to signal high quality. </p>

<p>Proof. Existence. Following Proof of Proposition 5, the existence of a separating equilibrium is guaranteed by three single-
crossing properties: 
2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0 (standard SCP), 
2 Π( , , ) &gt; 0 (sensitivity SCP), and (advertising SCP) 
2 Π( , , ) &lt; 0. The </p>

<p>last condition states that the strategy or "please lie" campaign is marginally more profitable for the low-quality producer 
because he is less likely to produce high-quality and therefore receiving a high-quality report (similarly, the high-quality monop-
olist is less willing to invest in the strategy since if a consumer observe = 1-which occurs with higher probability-then 
the resource is wasted). </p>

<p>Characterization. Suppose that the solution to problem (B.1) entails positive . Then, FOCs can be written as </p>

<p> ∶ </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>= &lt; 1, </p>

<p>given 
2 Π( , , , =1) &lt; 0 . Nevertheless, </p>

<p> ∶ </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>Π( , , , =1) </p>

<p>= &gt; 1, </p>

<p>given standard single-crossing 
2 Π( , , , ) &lt; 0, which is a contradiction. 
□ </p>

</text></tei>