<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1515%2Fjbnst-2016-1001" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The Establishment History Panel (Betriebs-Historik-Panel -BHP) is one of the 
most comprehensive datasets on firms in Germany: it covers the population of 
establishments with at least one employee subject to social security. Only the 
data from the German Federal Statistical Office (Wagner 2015) and commercial 
data collections, such as the ORBIS database from Bureau van Dijk, 1 include 
similarly wide-ranging information on firms or establishments. The BHP is 
exceptional in that the data are not collected within a survey but come from 
an administrative source: the notifications to the German social security system. 
Every employer has to report every employment relationship subject to social 
security contributions at least once a year. The gathered data therefore contain 
information on all the employees concerned from the year 1975 onwards. These 
notifications also include a unique identifier for every employer, the establish-
ment number, which is assigned by the German Federal Employment Agency 
(BA). Using this identifier, data obtained from individual employment notifica-
tions are aggregated to the establishment level to compile the BHP. The BHP 
includes the industry and location of the establishments as well as detailed 
information on the employment structure in terms of gender, age, qualification 
level, occupation, or average gross wages. </p>

<p>*Corresponding author: Alexandra Schmucker, Forschungsdatenzentrum der Bundesagentur 
für Arbeit im Institut für Arbeitsmarkt-und Berufsforschung, Regensburger Str. 100, 90478 
Nürnberg, Germany, E-mail: Alexandra.Schmucker@iab.de 
Johanna Eberle, Forschungsdatenzentrum der Bundesagentur für Arbeit im Institut für 
Arbeitsmarkt-und Berufsforschung, Regensburger Str. 100, 90478 Nürnberg, Germany, 
E-mail: Johanna.Eberle2@iab.de </p>

<p>1 See www.bvdinfo.com (accessed 15 November 2016). </p>

<p>Journal of Economics and Statistics 2017; 237(6): 535-547 </p>

<p>Open Access. © 2017 Eberle and Schmucker, published by De Gruyter. 
This work is licensed 
under the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 License. </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>The first version of the BHP was released in 2007 by the Research Data 
Centre (FDZ) of the BA at the Institute for Employment Research (IAB) 
(Spengler 2008). 2 Since then the BHP has been updated with minor changes 
several times. For the current update, however, more substantial changes in 
the data preparation procedures and the catalogue of variables have been 
implemented for several reasons. First, adjustments in the social security 
notification system have led to modifications in the data reported on occupa-
tion, education and part-time work. Second, solutions developed by the IAB to 
improve the data quality, such as the imputation of earnings above the upper 
earnings limit and the validation of the information on education and voca-
tional training, have been applied. Third, researchers' requirements and the 
increase in the individual data volume have been taken into consideration. As 
a result of this redesign, a new and enhanced BHP version for the years 1975 
until 2014 has been created. The data preparation has been modified in certain 
respects in order to improve suitability for scientific research and may con-
tribute to more comprehensive and precise research findings. 
In this paper, we give an outline of the original data source, data preparation, 
and the contents of the final data set. In addition, we provide information on data 
access, working tools and the analysis potential of the BHP. A more detailed 
description of the BHP including frequency tables is provided by Schmucker et al. 
(2016). </p>

<p>2 Data source </p>

<p>2.1 Employee data </p>

<p>The BHP is based on individual data which are collected in the context of the 
employment notifications for the social security system. This procedure has been 
mandatory for all employees who are liable to contribute to the health, pension 
and unemployment insurances since 1973 in western Germany and since 1991 in 
eastern Germany. In 1999, the obligation to report was extended to marginal 
part-time workers. Employers have to submit notifications at the beginning and 
end of any employment relationship, once a year for continuous employment, </p>

<p>2 Before that affiliated researchers of the IAB could use the Establishment File of the German </p>

<p>Social Insurance Statistics (Fritsch/Brixy 2004) for their analyses, which was generated using 
the same data source. External researchers, however, were not entitled to use these data. </p>

<p>536 </p>

<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>and whenever there are any changes relevant for social security. 3 The notifica-
tion contains information on the beginning and ending dates of the employ-
ment, gross wage, employment status, occupation, education and nationality. 
Characteristics of the establishment (location and industry classification) can be 
merged. These individual employment notifications are integrated into the 
Employee History of the IAB (Beschäftigten-Historik -BeH). The current BHP is 
based on a version of the BeH that comprises information on 1.5 billion employ-
ment episodes of 81 million individuals from 1975 until 2014. </p>

<p>2.2 Coverage </p>

<p>Although the BeH is a census, it does not cover total employment in Germany. 
Freelancers and civil servants are not subject to social security contributions 
and are therefore not included. Additionally, marginal part-time workers were 
not recorded in the data until 1998. With respect to the aggregate data set at 
establishment level, these restrictions mean that the data comprise only infor-
mation on establishments with at least one employee subject to social security, 
or -since 1999 -at least one marginal part-time worker. As a result, a certain 
proportion of the working population and establishments are not observed 
in the BHP. This proportion is not evenly distributed across regions and 
industries and varies over time. 4 As far as the industries are concerned, the 
manufacturing industry (excluding construction) and the private service 
sector (trade, logistics, warehousing, hospitality, IT and communications, 
finance, insurance, business services, and property) currently exhibit the </p>

<p>3 Within the employment notification procedure a certain time lag is unavoidable. Although </p>

<p>changes in employment relationships have to be reported immediately and existing employ-
ment relationships have to be confirmed annually, some notifications actually arrive years later. 
It can thus be assumed that the number of employees and establishments is underrecorded 
slightly for the years 2012 and 2013 and that there are larger gaps for 2014. Analyses based on 
previous years suggest that about two per cent of the employees and three per cent of the 
establishments are still missing for 2014. 
4 In order to determine what share of the total employment in Germany is included in the BHP </p>

<p>data, the total number of employees per establishment as of 30 June 2013 is summed up for all 
establishments in the respective region or industry. These statistics are then compared to 
annual employment figures for 2013 obtained by the German Federal Statistical Office 
(Arbeitskreis 'Erwerbstätigenrechnung des Bundes und der Länder'), which also cover civil 
servants, the military and the self-employed (including family workers). The varying time 
reference is assumed to have little impact on the reported shares since seasonality is at a 
comparatively neutral stage in June, the reference date of the BHP. </p>

<p>Establishment History Panel </p>



<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>highest coverage. For these industries, the BHP covers more than 85 % of the 
total employment. For the construction industry, with its high share of self-
employment, the coverage in the BHP amounts to only 78 %. For the public 
service, defence and social security, which have a large share of public 
servants, the coverage is only 69 %. In education, where the overwhelming 
majority of teachers are public servants, the share is 56 %. The lowest shares 
are found for agriculture, forestry and fishing (51 %) as well as for private 
households (41 %) due to their high percentage of self-employment. The cover-
age may also vary significantly between regions. With respect to the sixteen 
federal states, coverage is lowest in Berlin (77 %) and the other eastern 
German states (82 %), and higher on average in western German states (85 %) 
(see Figure 1). The varying coverage of employment needs to be given careful 
consideration when drawing statistical inferences. </p>

<p>2.3 Data quality </p>

<p>Administrative data have considerable advantages for researchers as they cover 
the total population and comprise precise and reliable information. Yet they are 
primarily collected for administrative purposes and research is only their sec-
ondary use. The suitability of the data for analysing research questions is not 
taken into consideration in the data collection process. Relevant information 
may therefore be missing: For example, exact information on gross wages is only 
provided up to the upper earnings limit for statutory pension insurance con-
tributions. All earnings above this limit are censored at that limit. In addition, 
changes in the data collection method and the recorded information may result 
in inconsistent time series. Several approaches to deal with biases and incon-
sistencies have been implemented in the BHP (see chapter 3.1). 
For the current BHP version we had to deal with a substantial change in the 
information gathered: the occupation code is an array where employers give 
information on the employee's occupation, school and vocational training, and 
other job details. In 2011, the former recording scheme was superseded by a new 
occupation code in the social security notification procedure (see Bertat et al. 
2013). Table 1 compares the contents of the new and the old occupation codes. In 
addition to the changes in the categories for education and occupation, it is to 
be noted that the new occupation code no longer records any information on 
occupational status (see Table 1 for more information on this variable), but now 
contains information on agency work and fixed-term contracts. </p>



<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>Moreover, there was a transitional period of six months during which the 
verification programs of the notification procedure permitted the omission of 
information on the occupation codes. About 20 % of the notifications for this 
period therefore do not include valid information on the occupation code. It can 
be seen that the number of notifications with missing information is not dis-
tributed randomly, but differs systematically across regions and sectors of the 
economy (for more details see Schmucker et al. 2016). For some of these 
changes, missing-data solutions were developed and applied during the creation 
of the BHP (see chapter 3.1). </p>

<p>77.5 -80.0 
80.0 -83.0 
83.0 -85.0 
85.0 -86.6 </p>

<p>Figure 1: BHP coverage of total employment in 2013 (%), German federal states. 
Source: Authors' calculations based on Establishment History Panel 7514 and annual employ-</p>

<p>ment figures by Arbeitskreis Erwerbstätigenrechnung des Bundes und der Länder; Geographic 
allocation © GeoBasis-DE/BKG 2015. </p>

<p>Establishment History Panel </p>

<p>539 </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>3 Data preparation </p>

<p>3.1 Pre-processing of the employee data </p>

<p>The BHP is compiled by aggregating the employment notifications of the BeH at 
establishment level using the establishment ID. Before this aggregation, the data </p>

<p>Table 1: Contents of the new and the old occupation codes. </p>

<p>Contents 
Values of old occupation code 
Values of new occupation code </p>

<p>Occupation 
performed </p>

<p>Classification of Occupations  
(KldB ) </p>

<p>Classification of Occupations  
(KldB ) 
Occupational 
status </p>

<p>Trainees/apprentices; unskilled 
employees; skilled workers; master 
craftsmen, foremen; home workers and 
freelance home workers </p>

<p>Not recorded </p>

<p>Part-time 
Full-time; part-time (less than  
hours); part-time ( hours and more) </p>

<p>Full-time; part-time </p>

<p>Education and 
vocational 
training </p>

<p>-Lower/intermediate secondary </p>

<p>school leaving certificate without 
completed vocational training 
-Lower/intermediate secondary </p>

<p>school leaving certificate with 
completed vocational training 
-Upper secondary school leaving </p>

<p>certificate without vocational training 
-Upper secondary school leaving </p>

<p>certificate with vocational training 
-Degree from a university of applied </p>

<p>sciences (Fachhochschule)-
University degree 
-Education and training unknown, no </p>

<p>statement possible </p>

<p>Education: 
-None 
-Lower secondary school leaving </p>

<p>certificate 
-Intermediate school leaving </p>

<p>certificate or equivalent school 
education 
-Upper secondary school leaving </p>

<p>certificate (general or subject-
specific aptitude for higher 
education) 
Vocational training: 
-No vocational qualification 
-Qualification from a recognised </p>

<p>vocational training programme 
-Master craftsman, technician, or </p>

<p>equivalent qualification from a 
technical college 
-Bachelor degree 
-Diploma, Magister, Master's degree, </p>

<p>state examination 
-Doctorate </p>

<p>Agency worker Not recorded 
Yes; no 
Fixed-term 
contract </p>

<p>Not recorded 
Permanent; fixed-term </p>



<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>on individuals are subjected to numerous validation procedures. The most 
important improvements affect the variables on income, education and part-
time work, which are described in the following. 
Information on earnings in the social security notifications is very precise 
and valid in general. However, earnings are only reported up to the upper 
earnings limit for statutory pension insurance contributions. For this reason, 
approx. 10 % of the data on full-time employees' earnings is censored. This 
leads to biased results due to aggregation at the establishment level. In order 
to remedy this bias, the information on earnings was imputed following the 
procedure developed by Card et al. (2015) (see also Schmucker et al. 2016: 125). 
The number of employment notifications with missing information on 
education and vocational training qualifications had grown substantially 
over time. The switch to the Occupation Code 2010 in the notification proce-
dure then caused the rate of missing values to rise as high as 50 % in 2011. 
Furthermore, from 2011 onwards the employers no longer report qualifications 
in a combined variable, but split into school education and vocational educa-
tion and training (see Table 1). Hence no time-consistent information is avail-
able for the entire period. In order to provide researchers with time-consistent 
information on school and vocational education, every combination of values 
from the new occupation code is assigned to the most suitable value of the 
combined education and vocational training variable according to the old 
occupation code. This has no effect on missing values, however. In addition, 
the quality of the education and training data is improved by means of an 
imputation procedure using a deterministic replacement rule that was sug-
gested by Fitzenberger et al. (2005, 2006) and enhanced by Kruppe et al. 
(2014). The result of this procedure is that there are now hardly any missing 
values, especially for employees who are not in marginal part-time employ-
ment (see Schmucker et al. 2016: 115ff). 
As mentioned above, the possibility to leave out the information on the 
occupation code for six months after the introduction of the new occupation 
code resulted in many missing values in the data. The information regarding 
working hours (full-time or part-time) was also affected. This problem was 
crucial for the creation of the BHP as the full-time employees are often used 
as the basis for generating employment groups in the BHP. In order to remedy 
this problem a logit model was developed at the IAB which can be used to 
impute the missing information (see Ludsteck/Thomsen 2016). 
The Classification of Economic Activities has changed several times during 
the observation period of the BHP. Inconsistencies in the classification scheme 
make it difficult to conduct longitudinal analyses. To address this issue, the IAB 
developed a method to construct time-consistent industry codes. A detailed </p>

<p>Establishment History Panel </p>



<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>description can be found in Eberle et al. (2011). These variables are available in 
the BHP in addition to the original classifications. 
A similar problem arises due to local government reorganisations through-
out the entire period. The regional information on districts (Kreise) was therefore 
corrected according to the territorial allocation as of 31 December 2014. A more 
detailed description of all validation procedures can be found in Schmucker 
et al. (2016: 22 ff.). </p>

<p>3.2 Compiling the establishment data </p>

<p>After the data on individuals have been pre-processed, the BHP is compiled by 
aggregating the employment information at establishment level by using a 
unique establishment identifier. Each establishment is allocated a unique estab-
lishment number according to the following principle: branch offices of one 
company which belong to the same economic class and are located in the same 
municipality are given one joint establishment number (see Bundesagentur für 
Arbeit 2007). As the identification of establishments in the BHP is based on these 
establishment numbers, the definition of an 'establishment' is specific and may 
differ from other concepts. It is not possible to distinguish between branch 
offices with a joint establishment number in the data. It should also be noted 
that there is no information available on whether establishments belong to the 
same company. 
The final BHP contains information on the establishments' employee struc-
ture and details about the wage structure of the full-time employees in the 
establishment. All of the data are stock data as of the reference date of 30 
June of any given year. 
In addition to details about the stock, the BHP also includes information on 
worker inflows and outflows. Inflows are defined as the number of employees 
who were working in the establishment on the respective reference date but 
were not working there on the reference date of the previous year. A correspond-
ing definition applies to outflows. Similar to the stock values, inflows and 
outflows can be distinguished according to various characteristics such as age 
groups. 
Finally, the BHP has been enriched with information on establishment start-
ups and closures. A new establishment ID, which defines an establishment in 
the BHP, does not necessarily imply that a whole new establishment has been 
set up. Also, the disappearance of an establishment ID does not necessarily 
mean that the establishment has closed down. The classification provided helps 
to distinguish between genuine start-ups and closures and changes in </p>



<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>establishment numbers, takeovers or spin-offs. Establishment entries and exits 
are classified by analysing worker flows. The decisive factor here is the propor-
tion of workers who were employed in one and the same establishment in the 
previous or in the subsequent year. A detailed description of the classification 
can be found in Hethey and Schmieder (2010). </p>

<p>4 Data availability </p>

<p>4.1 The BHP sample </p>

<p>The BHP is made available to the scientific community via the FDZ. Access is 
granted to a 50 % simple random sample of all establishments included in the 
BHP from 1975 to 2014. Due to the random selection, the sample shows no 
systematic bias. The BHP data are provided as Stata data sets and contain 
both German and English labels. 
Figure 2 shows the number of establishments per year in the BHP sample 
over the period 1975-2014. There are two remarkable rises in 1992 and 1999, 
which are highlighted by two vertical lines. The first is caused by the inclusion </p>

<p>600,000 </p>

<p>800,000 </p>

<p>1,000,000 </p>

<p>1,200,000 </p>

<p>1,400,000 </p>

<p>1975 
1980 
1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 
2010 
2014 </p>

<p>Figure 2: Number of establishments per year in the BHP 50 % sample. </p>

<p>Establishment History Panel </p>



<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>of establishments in eastern Germany, the second is due to the integration of 
marginal part-time workers in the notification procedure. </p>

<p>4.2 Availability of BHP information in FDZ data products </p>

<p>Selected information drawn from the BHP can also be merged with other data 
products provided by the FDZ. For example, BHP modules are available for the 
IAB Establishment Panel (Fischer et al. 2009), a comprehensive survey of estab-
lishments in Germany conducted by the IAB. BHP data on employers is also 
available for all individuals covered in the Sample of Integrated Labour Market 
Biographies (SIAB) (Antoni et al. 2016), a data set comprising information on 
employment, unemployment benefit receipt, registered job search, and partici-
pation in training schemes. The SIAB data include an establishment file holding 
basic information on these establishments (total number of employees, full-time 
and marginal part-time workers, mean wage, industry, and region). In addition 
to basic establishment characteristics, several modules and blocks of variables 
can be provided upon request. Selected BHP modules are also available for 
many other FDZ data products. 5 By adding administrative information on estab-
lishments, FDZ aims to meet a growing demand for combined research data sets 
providing data on both employees and employers. </p>

<p>4.3 Data access </p>

<p>Access to the BHP is only possible via on-site use at the FDZ and remote data 
processing. For on-site use, the FDZ provides several workplaces for visiting 
researchers within a secure computing environment at different locations in 
Germany and abroad (Bender/Heining 2011). 6 For remote data processing, 
researchers submit scripts to the FDZ that execute commands for data prepara-
tion and analysis. The scripts are processed on secure servers within the FDZ 
and the results are transferred to the researchers after a disclosure review. 
Remote data processing at the FDZ is conducted via the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Job Submission 
Application</rs> (JoSuA) developed by the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Institute for the Study of Labour</rs> (IZA), </p>

<p>5 For a list of available modules please see http://doku.iab.de/fdz/access/BHP_Variablen_EN. </p>

<p>pdf (accessed 24 November 2016). 
6 For an up-to-date list of external FDZ locations, see http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Data_Access/ </p>

<p>FDZ_On-Site_Use/Standorte.aspx (accessed 23 November 2016). </p>



<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>which allows users to submit jobs and access their results via a custom-built 
web interface (see Eberle et al. forthcoming). 
Researchers intending to use the BHP are required to apply for data access 
via on-site use and remote data processing at the FDZ. Access can be granted to 
non-commercial research institutions conducting research projects in the fields 
of employment research. 
After the request for data access has been accepted, the FDZ and the 
research institution conclude a data use agreement. The data can only be used 
for a specific research project and within the time period stated in the contract. 
Students intending to use the BHP for their theses are also welcome to apply for 
the data. In this case, the data use agreement is concluded with the department 
supervising the thesis. 
Since direct access to the data is only possible during on-site use, the FDZ 
provides artificial test data sets for download on its website, which can be used 
by researchers to develop scripts for data preparation and analysis and to test 
their functionality. 7 The test data were designed in such a way as to resemble the 
structure of the real data as closely as possible, but do not allow any valid 
analyses. Values are switched randomly between observations within certain 
subgroups. Test data are also smaller in size since they are based on a 
subsample. </p>

<p>5 Analysis potential </p>

<p>The BHP facilitates a wide range of studies in the field of labour market research. 
In the past it has been the basis for analyses on start-ups and closures as well as 
on the survival of newly founded firms (Brixy 2014; Fackler 2014). Additionally, 
projects on the development of specific regions (Braakmann/Vogel 2011) or 
industries (Bossler/Oberfichtner 2016) have used the BHP. Finally, analyses on 
employment adjustment over the business cycle (Bossler/Upward 2016) or on 
(cultural) diversity (Brunow/Nijkamp 2016) have also been possible. </p>

<p>6 Conclusion </p>

<p>As demonstrated in this article, the BHP is a rich administrative data set with 
longitudinal information on establishments in Germany from 1975 to 2014. It was </p>

<p>7 See http://fdz.iab.de/en/FDZ_Establishment_Data/Establishment_History_Panel/Establishment_ </p>

<p>History_Panel_Working_Tools.aspx (accessed 24 November 2016). </p>

<p>Establishment History Panel </p>



<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

<p>designed to make a multitude of research projects in the fields of employment 
research possible. More detailed information on the BHP can be found in the 
corresponding data report (Schmucker et al. 2016). A list of relevant articles 
concerning the BHP, such as data reports, method studies and research papers 
using the BHP can be found by navigating through the FDZ literature database. 8 
For the latest news on the BHP, including updated versions, please refer to the 
FDZ website fdz.iab.de. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements: The authors would like to thank Rebecca Hussen for her 
assistance in assembling statistics for this article and fellow staff members at the 
IAB who were involved in the compilation of the BHP. </p>





<p>J. Eberle and A. Schmucker </p>

<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>





<p>Brought to you by | The University of Texas at Austin 
Authenticated 
Download Date | 3/30/18 6:45 PM </p>

</text></tei>