<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1468-0351.2009.00367.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:35+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We extend the literature on transition economies' wage structures by investigating 
the returns to tenure and experience. This study applies recent panel data and esti-
mation approaches that control for hitherto neglected biases. We compare the life-
cycle structure of East and West German wages for fulltime employed men in the 
private sector. The patterns in the returns to seniority are similar for the two regio-
nal labour markets. The returns to experience lag behind in the East German labour 
market, even almost 20 years after unification, with significant differences particu-
larly for high-skill workers. The results are robust when only individuals who 
started their labour market career in the market economy are considered. We expect 
that the different returns are related to the heterogeneity of work experience gath-
ered in East as compared with West Germany. </p>

<p>JEL classifications: J31, J24. 
Much interest has been focused on the adjustment of transition economies' 
wage structures on the path to becoming market-oriented economies. Numerous </p>

<p>Received: November 23, 2008; Acceptance: April 13, 2009 </p>

<p>1 We thank two anonymous referees, the editor, Jennifer Hunt, Katja Sonderhof as well as participants of the 
economics seminar at the University of Regensburg, the DFG-SPP summer school 2008, and the DFG-SPP 
Oct. 2008 workshop at RWI Essen for helpful comments. </p>

<p>Economics of Transition 
Volume 17(4) 2009, 629-659 </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development. 
Published by Blackwell Publishing Ltd, 9600 Garsington Road, Oxford OX4 2DQ, UK and 350 Main St, Malden, MA 02148, USA </p>

<p>contributions investigate the development of returns to human capital in transi-
tion economies and test whether the abolition of wage grids and socialist wage 
compression has led to more dispersed wages and to increases in the returns to 
human capital (see, for example, Andrén et al., 2005; Boeri and Flinn, 1999; 
Flanagan, 1998; Gorodnichenko and Peter, 2005; Liu, 2006). In their meta-analy-
sis of this literature, Fleisher et al. (2005) present a record of rising returns to 
education throughout. 
However, the focus on rising returns to education might be misleading if at 
the same time wages remained irresponsive to other dimensions of human capi-
tal. Interestingly, only a handful of studies in this literature investigate the 
development of returns to tenure and experience. Among them are Jones and 
Simon (2005) who take advantage of Bulgarian employer-employee data. They 
find that returns to education roughly doubled after transition while returns to 
experience stayed constant at low levels. Mü nich et al. (2005) look at the devel-
opment of the Czech wage structure and confirm a dramatic increase in the 
returns to education, yet no shift in the returns to experience at the end of the 
communist regime. Noorkoiv et al. (1997) study the case of Estonia where 
returns to schooling increased sharply between 1989 and 1995 whereas the age-
earnings profile flattened. 
For the case of East Germany, Bird et al. (1994) show that prior to unification 
returns to experience and tenure were half those earned in West Germany. Life-
cycle wage heterogeneity was much below West German levels (Krueger and Pis-
chke, 1995). Burda and Schmidt (1997, p. 195) studied East German wages through 
1993 and concluded that 'returns to age were depressed under socialism and con-
tinue to be so (…)'. Jurajda and Harmgart (2007) find that in 1995 the experience 
profile was considerably flatter in East than in West Germany, which is confirmed 
by Franz and Steiner (2000) based on data through 1997. Gathmann (2005) extended 
the analysis through 2000 and found that the relative East-West wage difference 
was largest for experienced workers. Thus even 10 years after unification the flat 
wage-experience profile of the socialist economy had not disappeared. 
A possible explanation for the different developments in the returns to human 
capital inherent in schooling and in labour market experience might be related to 
the specific adjustment coinciding with economic transition: if schooling were a 
valid signal for innate individual productivity it could be remunerated immedi-
ately. In contrast, socialist labour market experience may have been only of limited 
value and it took time for labour market experience in the market economy to accu-
mulate value. This might explain why the adjustment in returns to experience lags 
behind the adjustment in returns to education. 
In this study we compare the East and West German wage structures almost 
two decades after unification. We investigate whether systematic differences in the 
returns to experience and tenure in the two regional labour markets, which derive 
from differences in past wage setting mechanisms, have disappeared over time. 
This complements the literature on the transition process in East Germany, where </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>optimistic studies from the early 1990s have been replaced by more sombre assess-
ments. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Our study contributes to the literature in various ways: first, in contrast to most 
analyses which study labour market adjustments of former socialist countries on 
their way to becoming market-oriented economies, in the case of Germany we can 
take advantage of a benchmark economy. East and West Germany, since 1990, 
share labour market institutions in addition to history and language. Therefore, 
East Germany is adjusting to an institutional setting which at the same time and 
identically determines West German labour market outcomes. This allows us to 
identify the consequences of a socialist heritage in a comparative perspective, 
which is not available for other countries. Second, we improve on the least squares 
approach which predominates in studies of wage structures in transition economies 
and account for the endogeneity of tenure and experience. We apply the more 
advanced estimators of Altonji and Shakotko (1987) and Topel (1991). The former 
uses an instrumental variables technique while the latter identifies returns to tenure 
and experience in a two-step procedure, assuming exogenous job changes. Esti-
mates based on these procedures at times differ vastly from biased least squares 
results and in our case the biases may well differ for East and West Germany. 
Third, we take advantage of recent and representative panel data on life-cycle wage 
structures. Finally, as Gö rzig et al. (2008) point to shifts in the sectoral and occupa-
tional employment structure as the main determinant of differences in wage levels 
in East and West Germany, we control for such composition effects. 
Our results are of immediate policy relevance: German active labour market 
policies spend large amounts to create public employment opportunities for the 
East German labour force (for a survey, see Fertig et al., 2006). If there are no or only 
low returns to experience then the payoff of expensive public employment is much 
lower than expected. In addition, prior analyses of transition economies' labour 
market adjustments may have been too optimistic when they built their conclusions 
on the increasing returns to schooling only. Taking returns to experience and tenure 
into account the transition processes in labour markets may be much slower than 
has been assumed so far. 
After first confirming the results of prior studies on wage structures since unifica-
tion with our data, we focus on the most recent surveys of the German Socioeconomic 
Panel (SOEP Group, 2001) to analyse East and West German wage structures. We pro-
vide evidence on returns to tenure and experience and investigate whether socialist 
labour market institutions continue to characterize East German wages. Numerous 
commentators interpreted the previously observed lack of returns to experience in 
East Germany as a consequence of the obsolescence of general human capital </p>

<p>2 For recent contributions, see Snower and Merkl (2006) or Uhlig (2006, 2008). For accounts of German unifi-
cation and its labour market aspects, see, for example, Steiner and Bellmann (1995), Burda and Schmidt 
(1997), Franz and Steiner (2000), Burda and Hunt (2001), Hunt (2001), Spitz-Oener (2007), or Burda (2006, 
2008). </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>following reunification. We test whether these findings are due to a cohort effect that 
disappears when only those cohorts who entered the labour market after 1990 are 
considered. Moreover, we compare wage structures of East German workers in both 
regions of the country. As wage structures are generally heterogeneous across skill 
groups we also study East and West German life-cycle wages by skill group. 
Our key results are that the returns to tenure are small but similar in East and 
West Germany, while the experience profiles still differ substantially even after 
controlling for potential biases and composition effects. Particularly for medium-
and high-skill workers returns to experience are significantly higher in West than 
in East Germany. Additional analyses suggest that the difference between returns 
to general human capital may result from differences in the average quality of this 
human capital rather than from differences in its regional prices. We discuss possi-
ble interpretations of this evidence, which suggests that it takes at least one genera-
tion to leave the socialist heritage behind. </p>

<p>2. Estimation approach </p>

<p>The key challenge in identifying the causal returns to tenure and experience in a 
wage model is to account for the potential endogeneity of the measures of human 
capital. This problem has been neglected in the transition economics literature on 
the development of wage structures so far. Assume that for person i in employment 
j and period t </p>

<p>W ijt ¼ b 1 T ijt þ b 2 E ijt þ e ijt ; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where W represents the log real hourly wage, and T and E represent (polynomials 
of) tenure and experience, respectively. Other control variables may enter equation 
(1) but are ignored here for ease of exposition; b k are coefficients to be estimated; e ijt 
is the error term, which is assumed to combine fixed individual effects (e i ), fixed job 
match effects (e ij ) and a random term g ijt : </p>

<p>e ijt ¼ e i þ e ij þ g ijt : 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>There are several reasons why T or E may be correlated with components of the 
error term, which, unless accounted for, causes biased and inconsistent least 
squares estimates of the return parameters b k : tenure may be correlated with e i if 
person-specific characteristics affect the stability of employment relationships as 
well as wages. Furthermore, job match-specific unobservables e ij are likely to affect 
the probability of quits and thereby of observed tenure. In addition, we observe 
only those selected new employment relationships which improve individual out-
comes. An overall positive correlation between tenure and the unobservables 
would lead to an overestimation of the least squares coefficient. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Experience may be correlated with e ij as matching and job search processes 
increase the probability of a good match, the longer an individual is active in 
the labour market. This may generate a positive correlation between experience 
and the match-specific error component e ij . If individuals with specific unob-
served characteristics such as motivation spend more time in the labour market, 
this correlation between experience and e i may yield an overestimate of the 
returns to experience. 
Two classic approaches to deal with these potential endogeneities are suggested 
by Altonji and Shakotko (1987) (AS) and Topel (1991). Altonji and Shakotko (1987) 
address the endogeneity of tenure using an instrumental variables approach. They 
instrument all tenure indicators based on the difference between the period-specific 
value and the average value 
T ij for a given job match j of person i: </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>T ijt ¼ T ijt À 
T ij : 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>This instrument is correlated with T and uncorrelated with person-and match-
specific unobservables, thus solving the endogeneity problem. 
4 The endogeneity of 
experience both with respect to e i and e ij is not accounted for in this approach, 
which is why b 2 may be biased upward. Since tenure and experience are generally 
positively correlated, overestimated returns to experience generate underestimated 
returns to tenure. 
As a second estimator, we apply Topel's (1991) two-step procedure. Step 1 esti-
mates average within-job annual wage growth for individuals who did not change 
jobs: </p>

<p>W ijt À W ijtÀ1 ¼ ðb 1 þ b 2 Þ þ e ijt À e ijtÀ1 : 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>If we estimate a model for annual wage growth the constant term reflects the sum 
of the returns to seniority (b 1 ) and to experience (b 2 ), because over the period of 1 year </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>DT ¼ DE ¼ 1: 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>3 There may be more than one tenure indicator because of higher order polynomial and interaction terms. 
4 Dustmann and Pereira (2008) discuss an alternative approach introduced by Finnie (1993), which corrects 
only for the correlation between tenure and person-specific error terms. Their estimates for West German 
data show that the returns to tenure based on this approach (which uses the difference between T ijt and the 
average of T i ) are between those generated by OLS and AS. 
5 Equation (5) describes changes in tenure and experience for individuals who are employed full year and 
who are re-interviewed after exactly 1 year. In the GSOEP data interview, dates vary. Therefore DT and DE 
also take on values other than exactly 1 year (for example, with a first interview in August of 2002 and a 
second interview in February of 2003 we obtain 6 months). As we are able to take advantage of the precise 
information on tenure, experience and the interview date, we can consider the actually observed changes in 
tenure and experience when estimating (b 1 + b 2 ). Thus our results are not affected. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>The procedure generalizes to nonlinear specifications of tenure and experience, 
where we applied second-and third-order polynomials. Step 2 then investigates 
the earnings of workers who started new jobs. As they have not yet accumulated 
seniority, a cross-sectional estimation of the returns to experience of individuals 
with zero tenure identifies their returns to general labour market experience: </p>

<p>W ijt ¼ b 2 E ij0 þ e ijt : 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>Here E ij0 reflects the initial experience of workers starting a new job. The returns to 
seniority are then approximated as the difference in the returns found in steps 1 
and 2 of the analysis. 
To obtain these estimates, we follow the literature in rewriting total experience 
as the sum of initial experience on the new job and current tenure, </p>

<p>E ijt ¼ E ij0 þ T ijt ; 
ð7Þ </p>

<p>which then generates the following wage equation </p>

<p>W ijt ¼ ðb 1 þ b 2 ÞT ijt þ b 2 E ij0 þ e ijt : 
ð8Þ </p>

<p>The second step regression thus uses </p>

<p>W ijt À T ijt b 
Ã ¼ b 2 E ij0 þ e ijt ; 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>where b* is the estimated value of (b 1 + b 2 ) from step 1 (see equation 4). We addi-
tionally consider changes in a large set of control variables when estimating b*. 
Unbiased estimators result only if the groups of individuals who did not change 
jobs and those who started a new job are randomly selected and if their characteris-
tics are not correlated with the unobservables. As this is unlikely to be the case, 
Topel (1991) interprets his estimate of b 2 (returns to experience) as an upper bound 
such that the resulting estimate of b 1 (returns to tenure) is a lower bound of the 
returns to seniority. While both the AS and the Topel estimators rely on restrictive 
assumptions, both improve on the least squares approach to estimate the returns to 
tenure and experience and are frequently applied in this literature (see, for exam-
ple, Parent, 2000; Luchsinger et al., 2003; or Dustmann and Pereira, 2008). </p>

<p>3. Data and descriptive analysis </p>

<p>3.1 Data, sample and definition of variables </p>

<p>We use data taken from the German Socio-Economic Panel (SOEP Group, 2001), a 
representative dataset on German households. The focus of our analysis is on the </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>years 2002-2006, yet we also discuss the evidence for earlier years, starting with 
German unification. We consider fulltime employed males, aged 25-60, who are 
not self-employed, not in vocational training, not in marginal jobs and who work in 
the private sector. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Since there were some missing values in the observed gross wage, hours and 
education measures we generated 10 complete multiply imputed datasets which 
we use for all analyses. The imputation procedure fills missing values of certain 
variables in several steps. First, a value is drawn randomly out of the distribution 
of observed values. Then the random draw is replaced by predicted values which 
are obtained successively in 20 iteration steps (following a recommendation of van 
Buuren et al., 1999). The process is repeated 10 times with different random draws 
of the starting values and generates 10 complete datasets without missing values. 
All 10 are used in the analysis and inference procedures are adjusted following 
Rubin's rule (Little and Rubin, 1987; Rubin, 1987). 
The dependent variable measures log hourly wages in 2002 Euros. Wages are 
calculated based on current gross monthly incomes, which we divided by hours 
worked in the month of the interview. We apply current working hours because 
monthly income includes overtime pay and thus likely varies with the actual num-
ber of hours worked. 
7 This allows for a more precise measurement compared with 
studies based, for instance, on the Panel Study of Income Dynamics (PSID), which 
only provides annual incomes or studies based on German unemployment insur-
ance data, which have no information on hours worked at the individual level 
beyond fulltime or part-time status. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Figure 1 characterizes the age-earnings profiles observed for workers in East 
and West Germany. It immediately suggests that the regional difference is not only 
one of levels but also of life-cycle patterns. Figure 2A presents the life-cycle wage 
structures for medium skill, that is, with completed vocational education, and high-
skill groups with completed tertiary education. It confirms the difference in wage 
levels across age groups for the two regions. To focus on the difference in the slopes 
of wage profiles, Figure 2B depicts life-cycle wages relative to the wage level 
obtained by the youngest age group, again separately for both regions and skill 
groups. The difference in relative wage increases between the two regions appears 
to begin with the age group of the 35-39 year olds. This may suggest that there is a </p>

<p>6 In future work we will investigate the determinants of the wage structure of female workers. Females, who 
make up the smaller part of the private sector workforce, are omitted here in order to generate a homoge-
neous sample and to avoid sample selection issues. 
7 Only if the respondent did not provide the number of current hours worked, were the contractual working 
hours applied. 
8 Additional disadvantages of the data available from the German unemployment insurance (UI) are that: (i) 
earnings are censored at about the 80th percentile of the wage distribution; (ii) the data are much less infor-
mative than the GSOEP in measures such as overtime hours or education; and (iii) work experience may be 
underestimated, as periods in self-employment or as a civil servant are not reflected in the UI data (for a 
discussion see, for example, Gernandt and Pfeiffer, 2007). </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>cohort effect at work, which causes different valuations for labour force participa-
tion experience under the communist and the market-oriented regimes. This 
hypothesis is tested below. 
Our key explanatory variables are tenure and experience. Tenure measures the 
time spent with the current employer over all possible jobs at the monthly level. 
Experience measures the sum of total fulltime and part-time work experience. 
9 Both 
tenure and experience are measured at the same time as wages, that is, at the 
annual interview. When someone participates in the GSOEP for the first time the 
individual is asked about tenure at the current job and retrospectively about work 
experience. This initial information is updated with every subsequent interview on 
an annual basis. The tenure of individuals who change jobs is calculated based on </p>

<p>2.1 </p>

<p>2.2 </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.6 </p>

<p>2.7 </p>

<p>2.8 </p>

<p>2.9 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>25-29 
Age groups (years) </p>

<p>ln w </p>

<p>West </p>

<p>East </p>

<p>30-34 
35-39 
40-44 
45-49 
50-54 
55-60 </p>

<p>Figure 1. Life-cycle wage structure in East and West Germany </p>

<p>Note: Real hourly wages are deflated to 2002 prices. Estimates were obtained by regressing real log hourly 
wages on a set of indicator variables for age group and year. The thin lines are pointwise 95 percent confi-
dence intervals obtained from least squares standard errors adjusted for multiple imputation. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>9 Recent studies (for example, Parent, 2000) consider industry-specific experience. In our case it would be 
interesting to separately control for East or West German experience. Unfortunately, our data do not provide 
information at this level of detail for the full sample. When respondents join the survey they are asked about 
their total prior work experience, but not about the region where the experience was acquired, nor about 
industry or occupation. Information on experience and tenure by region, occupation or industry could be 
coded for the time individuals participate in the panel survey, but is not available for the period prior to join-
ing the survey. Less than one-third of our East German observations joined the GSOEP at the time of unifica-
tion. For these it would be possible to check whether they moved between East and West Germany and 
gathered different types of experience. For the majority of our East German observations we do not know 
where they worked in the past. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>observed behaviour. To obtain the level of experience at the start of an ongoing job 
we calculate the difference between current experience and tenure: cases where 
reported tenure was more than 2 years longer than reported experiences were 
dropped. 
10 As the data do not provide the exact date of job terminations, the exact </p>

<p>Log real hourly wages by region and skill group </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>2.20 </p>

<p>2.40 </p>

<p>2.60 </p>

<p>2.80 </p>

<p>3.00 </p>

<p>3.20 </p>

<p>3.40 </p>

<p>55-60 
Age-group (years) </p>

<p>West-Skill 
West-High skill 
East-Skill </p>

<p>East-High skill </p>

<p>Log real hourly wages indexed to age-group 25-29 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.05 </p>

<p>1.10 </p>

<p>1.15 </p>

<p>1.20 </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>55-60 </p>

<p>Age-group (years) </p>

<p>West-Skill </p>

<p>West-High skill </p>

<p>East-Skill </p>

<p>East-High skill </p>

<p>25-29 
30-34 
35-39 
40-44 
45-49 
50-54 </p>

<p>25-29 
30-34 
35-39 
40-44 
45-49 
50-54 </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>Figure 2. Life-cycle wage structure by region and skill group: log-level and group-
wise indexed to wages of age group 25-29 </p>

<p>Note: Skill stands for workers with completed vocational training. High skill represents those with com-
pleted tertiary degree. The wage development of workers without vocational training is not presented 
because of small sample sizes. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>10 This affected about 4.5 percent of our observations. In addition, in cases where the measured experience 
was slightly smaller than tenure, initial experience was replaced by the value of tenure and then updated 
based on subsequent observations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>initial work experience when taking on a new job cannot be determined. 
11 As only 
individuals who are observed in at least two subsequent periods can be considered 
in the Topel estimator, we censor observations in the first year of data (which is 
missing due, for instance, to panel attrition). 
Figure 3 illustrates the distribution of tenure and experience outcomes in East 
and West Germany for the period 2002 to 2006: the share of East German employees 
with tenure above 15 years is visibly smaller than that in the West. This is exactly 
the pattern we would expect as a consequence of German unification and of the 
economic shifts starting in 1989. We find a somewhat lower share of workers with 
many years of work experience in the East, which is likely to be a consequence of 
intensive early retirement programmes initiated at unification. 
Our specification of the wage model considers cubic terms in tenure and experi-
ence, a set of six indicators of highest educational attainment, immigrant status, </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
10 
30 
0 
20 
40 
10 
30 </p>

<p>East Germany 
West Germany </p>

<p>Tenure </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>Experience </p>

<p>Figure 3. Tenure and experience in East and West Germany </p>

<p>Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>11 We added half of the uncertain period as additional experience and considered the other half as unem-
ployment. For example, if a person started a new job in October and was observed to be employed on the 
old job in March the termination date of the old job could be at any point between March and October. We 
added half of this uncertain period (three of the six months from April to September) to the prior experience 
value, on average two months. This uncertainty affected about 5 percent of all person-year observations. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>federal state of residence (nine for West and six for East Germany), 12 industry 
indicators as well as calendar year fixed effects. The variables are described in 
Table 1 by subsample. </p>

<p>3.2 Descriptive analysis </p>

<p>Before we investigate the German wage structure in most recent times, we estimate 
the returns to tenure and experience in East and West Germany in earlier periods 
to replicate the results from studies cited in the Introduction. Using the specification </p>

<p>Table 1. Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>West Germany, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>East Germany, 
mean (SD) </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Log real hourly wage 
2.82 (0.0013) 
2.41 (0.0026) 
Explanatory variables 
Tenure 
10.79 (0.0275) 
8.26 (0.0423) 
Experience 
19.73 (0.0301) 
20.36 (0.0561) 
Education: Lower Sec. School 
0.3934 (0.0015) 
0.1400 (0.0021) 
Education: Intermediate Sec. School 
0.2034 (0.0013) 
0.5609 (0.0030) 
Education: Upper Sec. School 
0.0850 (0.0009) 
0.0470 (0.0013) 
Education: University, Technical College 
0.2224 (0.0013) 
0.2345 (0.0026) 
Education: Other/Missing 
0.0958 (0.0009) 
0.0175 (0.0008) 
Born in Germany 
0.8268 (0.0012) 
0.9800 (0.0008) 
Industry: Not Applicable 
0.0102 (0.0003) 
0.0288 (0.0010) 
Industry: Agriculture 
0.0438 (0.0006) 
0.0438 (0.0012) 
Industry: Energy 
0.2945 (0.0014) 
0.2068 (0.0024) 
Industry: Mining 
0.1524 (0.0011) 
0.1156 (0.0019) 
Industry: Manufacturing 
0.1019 (0.0010) 
0.1662 (0.0022) 
Industry: Construction 
0.1120 (0.0010) 
0.1344 (0.0021) 
Industry: Trade 
0.0988 (0.0009) 
0.0758 (0.0016) 
Industry: Transport 
0.0872 (0.0009) 
0.0971 (0.0018) 
Industry: Bank, Insurance 
0.0207 (0.0004) 
0.0387 (0.0012) 
Industry: Services 
0.0455 (0.0007) 
0.0488 (0.0013) 
Industry: Other 
0.0025 (0.0002) 
0.0022 (0.0003) 
Industry: Missing 
0.0306 (0.0005) 
0.0418 (0.0012) 
No. person-year observations 
10,087 
2746 </p>

<p>Note: Region indicators not presented to save space. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>described above, we estimated wage regressions for East and West German sam-
ples, separately for moving 5-year windows (1992-1996, 1993-1997 and so on). We 
used these results to predict the wage effects of tenure and experience. They are 
presented in Table 2 for two non-overlapping periods and in Figure 4 for six mov-
ing and overlapping 5-year windows. Based on Figure 4 we confirm prior evidence 
in that the returns to experience in East Germany (depicted for predictions of 0 vs. 
5 and 0 vs. 10 years) have always been below those in the West. The returns to ten-
ure (see Table 2) have been stable in West Germany, while in East Germany they 
increased from the early to the late 1990s. 
Next, we extend the analysis to more recent periods and present in Table 3 
the least squares results of our wage model for the time period from 2002 to 
2006. For both regions the third-order polynomials in tenure and experience are 
jointly significant mostly at the 1 percent level. We applied these estimates to 
predict the wage effects of 10-year tenure and experience. They are presented 
in Table 4, in columns 1 and 4 for West and East Germany. A comparison 
of the predicted effects yields very similar associations between seniority and </p>

<p>Table 2. Development of predicted least squares returns to tenure and experience 
in West and East Germany </p>

<p>West Germany (1992-1996) 
(1997-2001) </p>

<p>East Germany (1992-1996) 
(1997-2001) </p>

<p>5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0899*** 
0.0819*** 
0.0417* 
0.1332*** 
(0.0143) 
(0.0120) 
(0.0240) 
(0.0235) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1468*** 
0.1454*** 
0.0627** 
0.2035*** 
(0.0191) 
(0.0166) 
(0.0298) 
(0.0322) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.0917*** 
0.0996*** 
0.0128 
0.0519 
(0.0186) 
(0.0186) 
(0.0444) 
(0.0452) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.1538*** 
0.1668*** 
0.0245 
0.0803 
(0.0283) 
(0.0281) 
(0.0653) 
(0.0664) 
20 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2038*** 
0.2228*** 
0.0411 
0.0779 
(0.0316) 
(0.0313) 
(0.0659) 
(0.0684) </p>

<p>Notes: (a) ***, ** and * indicate statistical significance at the 1, 5 and 10 percent level, respectively. 
(b) Standard errors are generated by block-bootstrap of the observations in the unbalanced panel using 100 
replications based on 10 multiply imputed datasets (e.g. Little and Rubin, 1987; Rubin, 1987). 
(c) The underlying regression models control for cubic terms in tenure and experience, a set of six indicators 
of highest educational attainment, immigrant status, federal state of residence, 12 industry indicators and 
calendar year fixed effects. 
(d) The returns were predicted based on regressions with 7561 and 9272 person-year observations for West 
Germany and 2697 and 3007 person-year observations for East Germany in two considered periods, respec-
tively. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (1992-2001), own calculations. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>wages in East and West Germany: staying with the same employer for 10 years 
is associated with 14 percent higher wages in both regions. This indicates a sta-
ble pattern for West Germany and a drop in returns to tenure for East Ger-
many (see Table 2 column 4). The predicted returns to experience are 
somewhat larger in West than in East Germany. We tested the hypothesis that 
the ordinary least squares (OLS) parameter estimates of tenure and experience 
differ significantly between East and West Germany. These tests yield similar 
returns to tenure but significantly different returns to experience in a fully 
interacted model. Figure 5 plots the wage-experience profiles in East and West 
Germany. Figure 5A shows the levels of predicted wages. In Figure 5B pre-
dicted wages are indexed to one at 5 years of experience: the patterns predicted 
based on least squares results differ substantially between the two regions with 
much steeper profiles in West Germany. In addition, we tested whether pre-
dicted tenure and experience effects (in Table 4) are identical in East and West 
Germany. The hypothesis is rejected at the 10 percent significance level for the 
highest experience values. </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>92-96 
94-98 
95-99 
96-00 
97-01 
93-97 
Predicted change in log wage </p>

<p>Survey year (5 year intervals) </p>

<p>5 vs. 0 year experience (West) 
10 vs. 0 year experience (West) </p>

<p>5 vs. 0 year experience (East) 
10 vs. 0 year experience (East) </p>

<p>Figure 4. Returns to experience in East and West Germany over time </p>

<p>Notes: The lines represent the returns to experience in East and West Germany, both for 5 vs. 0 (dashed 
lines) and for 10 vs. 0 years (full lines) of experience. The returns were estimated in linear regression models, 
which controlled for cubic terms in tenure and experience, a set of six indicators of highest educational 
attainment, immigrant status, federal state of residence, 12 industry indicators, and calendar year fixed 
effects. The samples were gathered from moving observation windows of five subsequent calendar years. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (1992-2001), own calculations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table 3. OLS regression results -dependent variable: log wages </p>

<p>West Germany 
East Germany </p>

<p>Tenure/10 
0.1651*** 
0.1349 
[0.0447] 
[0.0930] 
Tenure </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/100 
)0.0229 
0.0140 
[0.0319] 
[0.0718] 
Tenure </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/1000 
)0.0008 
)0.0099 
[0.0062] 
[0.0142] 
Exp/10 
0.4842*** 
0.4446*** 
[0.0669] 
[0.1453] 
Experience 
2 /100 
)0.1781*** 
)0.2162*** </p>

<p>[0.0361] 
[0.0767] 
Experience 
3 /1000 
0.0211*** 
0.0292** 
[0.0057] 
[0.0120] 
Educ: Intermediate 
0.1272*** 
0.0143 
[0.0162] 
[0.0391] 
Educ: Upper secondary 
0.2837*** 
0.2008*** 
[0.0236] 
[0.0750] 
Educ: Univ., techn. College 
0.5017*** 
0.3952*** 
[0.0168] 
[0.0462] 
Educ: Other/Missing 
0.0156 
)0.0787 
[0.0211] 
[0.1278] 
Born in Germany 
0.0926*** 
0.2630** 
[0.0175] 
[0.1226] 
2003 
0.0420*** 
0.0213* 
[0.0068] 
[0.0121] 
2004 
0.0469*** 
0.0552*** 
[0.0076] 
[0.0145] 
2005 
0.0501*** 
0.0631*** 
[0.0087] 
[0.0160] 
2006 
0.0642*** 
0.0776*** 
[0.0089] 
[0.0184] 
Constant 
2.0718*** 
1.6786*** 
[0.0394] 
[0.1470] 
State of residence 
Yes 
Yes 
Industry 
Yes 
Yes </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table 3. (cont) OLS regression results -dependent variable: log wages </p>

<p>West Germany 
East Germany </p>

<p>Observations 
10,087 
2746 
R-squared 
0.38 
0.33 </p>

<p>Notes: (a) ***, ** and * indicate statistical significance at the 1, 5 and 10 percent level, respectively. 
(b) The coefficients of the indicators for state of residence, industry and calendar year are not presented to 
save space. Standard errors are calculated based on Rubin's rule for multiply imputed data using <rs type="software">Stata</rs>'s 
micombine command. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>Table 4. Predicted returns to tenure and experience in East and West Germany with 
alternative estimators -full sample </p>

<p>West Germany 
East Germany </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
OLS 
AS 
Topel 
OLS 
AS 
Topel </p>

<p>5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0767*** )0.0079 
0.0452* 
0.0697** 
)0.0298 
0.0497 
(0.0150) 
(0.0178) 
(0.0243) 
(0.0312) 
(0.0282) 
(0.0493) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1413*** 
0.0055 
0.0704 
0.1390*** )0.0639 
0.1378 
(0.0204) 
(0.0307) 
(0.0493) 
(0.0419) 
(0.0513) 
(0.0933) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2002*** 
0.1993*** 0.2249*** 
0.1719*** 
0.1631** 0.1424* 
(0.0237) 
(0.0281) 
(0.0433) 
(0.0551) 
(0.0725) 
(0.0830) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.3273*** 
0.3353*** 0.4372*** 
0.2576*** 
0.2709 
0.2175 
(0.0353) 
(0.0450) 
(0.0868) 
(0.0822) 
(0.3003) 
(0.1669) 
20 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.4223*** 
0.4639*** 0.8301*** 
0.2576*** 
0.3666 
0.2871 
(0.0381) 
(0.0615) 
(0.1804) 
(0.0868) 
(0.2338) 
(0.3478) </p>

<p>Notes: (a) ***, ** and * indicate statistical significance at the 1, 5 and 10 percent level, respectively. 
(b) Shaded cells indicate a significant difference in the predicted wage effects between East and West Ger-
many at least at the 10 percent level. Assuming no correlation between the predicted wage effects, the z-test 
statistic divides the difference in predicted wage values (DW) by the square root of the sum of their vari-
ances: 
Z = (DW West ) DW East )/[var(DW West ) + var(DW East )] </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>. 
(c) Standard errors are generated by block-bootstrap of the observations in the unbalanced panel using 100 
replications based on ten multiply imputed datasets (e.g. Little and Rubin, 1987; Rubin, 1987). 
(d) The underlying regression models are specified as in Table 3. 
(e) The OLS and AS returns were predicted based on regressions with 10,087 person-year observations for 
West and 2746 person-year observations for the East German sample. The first step of the Topel-estimator 
used 9300 and 2479 person-year observations, the second step is based on 10,087 and 2746 person-year 
observations in West and East Germany, respectively. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1 Main results </p>

<p>Least squares results can be biased due to the correlation between covariates and 
error terms. Based on the discussion in Section 2 it is plausible that these biases can 
affect East and West German estimates in different ways. East and West German </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>Predicted log wages indexed at the level of five years of experience </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.1 </p>

<p>2.2 </p>

<p>2.3 </p>

<p>2.4 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>2.6 </p>

<p>2.7 </p>

<p>2.8 </p>

<p>2.9 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>25 
Experience </p>

<p>WEST(OLS) 
EAST(OLS) 
WEST(IV) 
EAST(IV) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.02 </p>

<p>1.04 </p>

<p>1.06 </p>

<p>1.08 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>1.12 </p>

<p>Experience </p>

<p>WEST(OLS) </p>

<p>EAST(OLS) </p>

<p>WEST(IV) </p>

<p>EAST(IV) </p>

<p>5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 </p>

<p>25 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Predicted log wages </p>

<p>Figure 5. Estimated polynomials in experience in East and West Germany based on 
least squares and instrumental variables estimation (AS) </p>

<p>Note: The wages were predicted for individuals with 5 years tenure, born in Germany, observed in 2006, 
employed in the energy sector with intermediate education, and residing either in Saxony or NRW. The pre-
dictions are based on the OLS and AS estimates. (B) Ratio of predicted wage at every value of experience 
over the predicted wage at 5 years of experience. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>labour markets differ in terms of job stability (Boockmann and Steffes, 2008), 
dynamics of industrial adjustment (Gö rzig et al., 2008) and overall unemployment. 
This may affect the correlation between individual unobservables and job stability, 
the relevance of job-match characteristics, search behaviour and the patterns of 
search outcomes. As these mechanisms determine the potential biases of the least 
squares estimator, the biases for East and West Germany may well differ in such a 
way that the least squares results may not hold up to more advanced estimation 
approaches. 
We apply the approaches of Altonji and Shakotko (1987) and Topel (1991) to the 
model specification of Table 3. The predicted impact of the first 5 and 10 years of 
tenure and experience are presented in Table 4 separately for the two regions. Over-
all, the results confirm expectations. As in much of this literature we obtain for both 
regions vastly reduced returns to tenure when the AS estimator is applied, they 
even turn negative for East Germany. The predictions are not significantly different 
from zero. 
12 The returns to experience obtained with the AS estimator are very sim-
ilar to the least squares results in both cases, confirming higher returns to experi-
ence in West Germany. The wage-experience profile in Figure 5 yields a somewhat 
dampened curvature with the AS estimator compared with OLS, while the key con-
clusion of flatter returns in the East than in the West remains. However, the 
difference between East and West German returns to experience and tenure are not 
statistically significant based on the AS estimator. 
Next, we apply the Topel estimator which identifies the causal returns to tenure 
and experience if job changes are exogenous (columns 3 and 6 in Table 4). 
13 The 
resulting returns to tenure lie between the OLS and AS results but are hardly statis-
tically significant: we obtain a return of 7 percent to 10 years of tenure for West Ger-
many and 13.8 percent for East Germany. The returns to experience for the West 
German sample are significantly different from zero throughout and much above 
the levels obtained for East Germany: while 10 years of work experience in West 
Germany yield a return of 44 percent, it increases East German wages only by 
22 percent. Thus, the results of the AS and Topel estimators confirm that even 
20 years after reunification the life-cycle earnings patterns are substantially flatter 
in East than West Germany. Mostly likely due to the lack of precision in the 
estimates for East Germany we do not obtain statistically significant differences in 
the predicted returns to experience (or tenure) between the two German labour 
market regions for either of the two estimators. </p>

<p>12 In their analysis for Switzerland, Luchsinger et al. (2003) similarly observed a drop from a significant 7.5 
percent wage increase with 10 years of tenure based on OLS to an insignificant 1.7 percent when they 
applied the AS estimator. Dustmann and Pereira (2008) find a drop from a significant 12.8 percent to a small 
negative value for West German data from 1984-1999, as well. 
13 The regression results of the first and second step Topel estimation for the West German case are pro-
vided in Table A1 in the Appendix. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>According to the literature, wage structures may differ substantially across 
skill groups. Dustmann and Meghir (2005) found that skilled workers benefit 
much more from general labour market experience than unskilled workers. So, 
if the average worker in East Germany was less skilled than his West German 
counterpart this might have caused the observation of different returns to 
experience. </p>

<p>Table 5. Returns to tenure and experience in East and West Germany according to 
alternative estimators -by skill group </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
OLS 
AS 
Topel 
OLS 
AS 
Topel </p>

<p>(A) Medium-skilled (person-year observations West: 6508, East: 1953) 
5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0829*** )0.0125 
0.0424* 
0.0873*** )0.0213 
0.1125*** 
(0.0105) 
(0.0236) 
(0.0243) 
(0.0252) 
(0.0341) (0.0393) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1501*** )0.0143 
0.0936** 
0.1585*** )0.0526 
0.1959*** 
(0.0180) 
(0.0452) 
(0.0422) 
(0.0433) 
(0.0640) (0.0652) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.0917*** 
0.1399** 
0.1514*** 0.0360 
0.1533 
0.0440 
(0.0148) 
(0.0707) 
(0.0305) 
(0.0262) 
(0.1321) (0.0473) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.1673*** 
0.2650* 
0.2926*** 0.0608 
0.2814 
0.0983 
(0.0260) 
(0.1402) 
(0.0611) 
(0.0459) 
(0.2628) (0.0946) 
20 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2698*** 
0.4710 
0.5443*** 0.0768 
0.4620 
0.2371 
(0.0391) 
(0.2779) 
(0.1270) 
(0.0666) 
(0.5224) (0.1952) 
(B) Highly skilled (person-year observations West: 2244, East: 643) 
5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0258 
)0.0255 
0.0130 
0.1097** )0.0865* 
0.1472 
(0.0253) 
(0.0351) 
(0.0353) 
(0.0472) 
(0.0486) (0.0937) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0623 
)0.0166 
0.0334 
0.1919*** )0.1875** 0.2795** 
(0.0416) 
(0.0639) 
(0.0626) 
(0.0737) 
(0.0934) (0.1363) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2298*** 
0.2321*** 0.2974*** 0.0978* 
0.0743 
0.1784** 
(0.0322) 
(0.0607) 
(0.0484) 
(0.0522) 
(0.2748) (0.0890) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.4013*** 
0.4058*** 0.5648*** 0.1627* 
0.1414 
0.3331* 
(0.0553) 
(0.1140) 
(0.0962) 
(0.0899) 
(0.5486) (0.1744) 
20 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.5696*** 
0.5779*** 1.0091*** 0.1939 
0.2544 
0.5710 
(0.0755) 
(0.2038) 
(0.2021) 
(0.1239) 
(1.0973) (0.3579) </p>

<p>Notes: (a) See notes below Table 4. 
(b) The underlying regression models follow the specification in Table 3, where we use second instead of 
third order polynomials in tenure and experience in order to avoid overfitting. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>We repeated our analyses separately for three skill subsamples, defining skill 
groups following the literature: 
14 workers without a vocational education are con-
sidered as low-skill workers. We observe 5 and 13 percent of our East and West 
German samples in that group. Medium-skill workers are those who completed a 
vocational degree (more than 72 and 64 percent of the East and West German sam-
ples, respectively) and high-skill workers are those who hold a tertiary education 
degree, which is observed for about 22 percent in both regions. The mere skill dis-
tribution in the two regional subsamples does not seem to support the skill-based 
explanation of differences in life-cycle wage structures. 
The predicted returns to experience and tenure for medium-and high-skill 
groups are presented in Table 5. While Dustmann and Pereira (2008) added skill 
interaction terms to their specification we estimate separate equations for the differ-
ent skill groups to flexibly account for potential differences in composition effects 
across skill groups. We do not present the results for low-skill workers because they 
are based on very small samples which do not yield informative results. For the 
other skill groups the returns to tenure are somewhat mixed: returns to tenure in 
the East exceed those in the West; in the West they are higher for medium-skill 
workers, in the East they are higher for high-skill workers. 
Now, we find significantly lower returns to experience in the East than in the 
West for all subgroups. 
15 The returns to experience are higher for those with high 
than with medium skills. Generally, the higher returns to experience in West Ger-
many appear to be driven by high-skill workers, whose relative wage gains due to 
experience are about twice as high as those observed for medium-skill workers. </p>

<p>4.2 Robustness tests </p>

<p>We complement the above analyses by two immediate tests. First, we repeated all 
analyses after adding six categorical firm-size indicators to the specification. Even 
though the firm-size effects were jointly significant in almost all estimations they 
did not affect the predicted returns to tenure and experience. Second, we evaluated 
whether the results for East Germany in Table 4 are sensitive to controlling for 
third-order polynomials. As the sample size is small this might have caused some 
overfitting. We redid the analysis for East Germany using only second-order 
polynomials and obtained returns to experience that were even smaller than those 
presented in Table 4. 
As an additional test of whether the results presented above are indicative of a 
different wage structure in the two German regions, we repeated the analysis con-
sidering only the birth cohorts born 1970 or later. These individuals' labour market </p>

<p>14 See, for example, Dustmann and Meghir (2005), Dustmann and Pereira (2008), or Fitzenberger (1999). 
15 At first it seems surprising that the experience differences by skill group are more significant than in the 
overall sample. This appears to go back to the much smaller conditional variance of the dependent variable 
when skill group-specific effects are considered. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>history should not be affected by personal employment experience under the East 
German socialist regime. If we find subdued returns to experience even for them, it 
suggests ongoing differences in the earnings structures rather than cohort effects. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>We applied the same estimation and prediction procedure as above, only now 
omitting cubic tenure and experience terms from the specification to avoid overfit-
ting. 
17 The results are presented in Table 6. Our main conclusions hold when the 
younger sample is considered: under least squares the returns to tenure are similar 
across regions, and the returns to experience are significantly higher in the West 
compared with the East. Under the AS estimator the returns to tenure diminish. 
The predictions based on the Topel procedure yield larger returns to tenure in the 
East and substantially larger returns to experience in the West. This suggests that </p>

<p>Table 6. Predicted returns to tenure and experience in East and West Germany with 
alternative estimators -sample of individuals born after 1969 </p>

<p>West Germany 
East Germany </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
OLS 
AS 
Topel 
OLS 
AS 
Topel </p>

<p>5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0963*** 
0.0279 
0.0827* 
0.1034* 
)0.1116 
0.0598 
(0.0284) 
(0.0401) 
(0.0430) 
(0.0560) 
(0.0763) 
(0.0670) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1561** 
0.0611 
0.1216 
0.1344** )0.1589 
0.1520 
(0.0348) 
(0.0753) 
(0.0840) 
(0.0667) 
(0.1378) 
(0.1702) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2142*** 
0.2251*** 
0.1891*** )0.0381 
0.1474* 
0.0212 
(0.0408) 
(0.0549) 
(0.0672) 
(0.1039) 
(0.0843) 
(0.1390) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.3366*** 
0.3665*** 
0.3229** 
0.0315 
0.2800** 
0.1220 
(0.0559) 
(0.0955) 
(0.1376) 
(0.1422) 
(0.1307) 
(0.2888) </p>

<p>Notes: (a) See notes below Table 4. 
(b) The underlying regression models follow the specification in Table 3, where we use second instead of 
third order polynomials in tenure and experience in order to avoid overfitting. 
(c) The predicted returns to 20 years of experience are not presented because they are out of sample predic-
tions for this subsample. 
(d) The OLS and AS returns were predicted based on regressions with 2069 person-year observations for 
West and 534 person-year observations for the East German sample. The first step of the Topel estimator 
used 1752 and 448 person-year observations, the second step is based on 2069 and 534 person-year observa-
tions in East and West Germany, respectively. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>16 In addition to grouping subsamples based on the regime under which they gathered work experience it 
would be interesting to distinguish between those who received their education under the communist sys-
tem vs. those who were educated in the market economy. The latter group includes the birth cohorts since 
the mid-1980s. It seems to be too early to evaluate these individuals' returns to experience. 
17 For this sample we observed mean values of tenure of 4.2 years in the East and 4.7 years in the West. 
Mean experience amounted to 7.6 years in the East and 8.3 years in the West. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>the different returns to experience are not due to cohort effects but instead to sys-
tematic regional differences in the wage structure. </p>

<p>4.3 Aggregate wage trends </p>

<p>One might argue that with respect to the development of individual earnings low 
returns to work experience can be complemented and balanced by high overall real 
wage increases over time. Thus if general wage trends have steeper slopes in East 
Germany than in the West the impact of lower returns to experience were amelio-
rated. 
As our estimations control for the overall development in real wages we can 
inspect the evidence on this point. The year indicators in the least squares estimates 
in Table 3 illustrate ceteris paribus real average wage increases between 2002 and 
2006 of 6.4 percent in West and 7.8 percent in East Germany, which implies annual 
increases of about 1.6 and 1.9 percent, respectively. While eastern wages generally 
grow somewhat faster this cannot balance the lower returns to experience of about 
20 percentage points in 10 years (cf. Tables 4 and 6). 
When we compare the aggregate wage trends across skill groups, we find larger 
wage increases in the regressions for high-skilled than for medium-or low-skilled 
workers. While this differs from Dustmann and Pereira's (2008) finding for the 
1990s it agrees well with the overall widening of the income distribution in recent 
years (Dustmann et al., 2007; Gernandt and Pfeiffer, 2007). Thus, overall secular 
wage growth is somewhat larger in East than in West Germany. Yet in the individ-
ual life cycle this effect is too small to make up for subdued returns to experience in 
East Germany. </p>

<p>4.4 Returns to East and West German experience compared </p>

<p>After we established that the difference in East-West German wage structures still 
exists many years after unification it is an open question why this might be the case. 
One possible explanation could be the selective East-West migration of individuals, 
with particularly high expected wage growth. 
18 A rigorous test of the hypothesis of 
selective East-West migration requires counterfactual evidence on potential wages 
for migrants in the East or for stayers in West Germany, which is beyond the focus 
of our analyses. 
We concentrate instead on the potential mechanisms behind the returns to expe-
rience differentials. Higher returns to experience in West compared with East 
Germany may result from two mechanisms: first, they may go back to different eval-
uations of the homogenous good 'experience' in the two regions, that is, identical </p>

<p>18 Brü cker and Trü bswetter (2007) use data through 1997 and confirm that East-West migrants are positively 
selected based on unobserved abilities. For a more general analysis of East-West migration patterns, see 
Hunt (2006). </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>labour market experience may receive a higher price in the West than in the East. 
Second, the type of experience which is generally available in the East German 
labour market may differ from the type of experience predominantly available in 
West Germany. In that case homogeneous experience could well receive the same 
price in both regions. However, we observe different returns to experience because 
the average quality of experience is heterogeneous between East and West Gemany. 
We can test whether one or both of these mechanisms are at work if we accept 
two assumptions. First, we assume that within a given regional labour market East 
and West German experience earns an identical price if their quality is identical. In 
that case we can compare the returns to East and West German experience in a 
given regional labour market and test whether they differ significantly. If they do 
we conclude that there must be differences in quality. If we accept as a second 
assumption that the experience of West (or East) Germans is of identical quality 
independent of where it is applied we can compare East and West German returns 
to an identical good and thus learn about regional price differences. 
We re-estimated our wage models to test the hypothesis of quality differences in 
experience of East vs. West German origin. Unfortunately, our data do not allow us 
to clearly measure, for every individual year of experience, the region of the coun-
try in which the data were gathered. Therefore, we proxy East and West German 
experience using an indicator of whether an individual originally, that is, in the 
year prior to unification (1989), resided in East or West Germany. 
Table 7 presents the predicted returns to tenure and experience in panel (A) for 
East Germans working in the West and in panel (B) for East Germans working in 
the East. A comparison of the returns to experience for East Germans in West Ger-
many (Table 7A) with those of the overall West German workforce (see Table 4, col-
umns 1-3) shows that East Germans in West Germany receive lower returns to 
experience than the average worker in West Germany. 
19 In addition, the coefficients 
on the experience interaction terms for individuals with East German origin in the 
West German sample are jointly significantly different from zero at the 1 percent 
level. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>An investigation of West Germans in East Germany yields similar results. 
Table 7B presents the predicted returns to experience for East Germans in East 
Germany. These can be compared with the returns in Table 4 (columns 4-6) for the 
entire East German workforce to learn about the wage structure of West Germans 
in East Germany. As East Germans receive lower returns in East Germany than the 
entire East German workforce, West German experience must earn higher returns 
in East Germany than East German experience. This is confirmed by the joint statis-
tical significance of experience interaction terms for West Germans in the wage </p>

<p>19 This differs from the finding of Gernandt and Pfeiffer (2008), who conclude that for East German migrants 
in the West wages have fully converged. 
20 Generally, we do not present the estimated coefficients and tests of joint statistical significance referred to 
in this subsection in order to avoid clutter. The results are available from the authors. </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table 7. Returns to East and West German experience </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
OLS 
AS 
TO </p>

<p>(A) East Germans in West German Employment 
5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0756*** 
)0.0124 
0.1865** 
(0.0155) 
(0.0172) 
(0.0746) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1344*** 
)0.0068 
0.3425*** 
(0.0212) 
(0.0282) 
(0.0962) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.1548 
0.1885*** 
0.0816 
(0.1012) 
(0.0764) 
(0.1189) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2208 
0.3003*** 
0.1652 
(0.1424) 
(0.1130) 
(0.1189) 
(B) East Germans in East German Employment 
5 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.0732** 
)0.0421 
0.0567 
(0.0307) 
(0.0307) 
(0.0547) 
10 vs. 0 year Tenure 
0.1378*** 
)0.0932 
0.1470 
(0.0408) 
(0.0577) 
(0.0990) 
5 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.1393** 
0.1201 
0.1353 
(0.0549) 
(0.0873) 
(0.0826) 
10 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.2028** 
0.2061 
0.2084 
(0.0824) 
(0.1631) 
(0.1658) 
20 vs. 0 year Experience 
0.1858** 
0.3027 
0.2861 
(0.0888) 
(0.3031) 
(0.3454) </p>

<p>Notes: (a) ***, ** and * indicate statistical significance at the 1, 5 and 10 percent level, respectively. 
(b) We do not present the predicted returns to 20 years of East German experience in West Germany because 
this involves out of sample predictions. 
(c) The standard errors were obtained via block-bootstrap using 100 replications based on ten multiply 
imputed datasets. 
(d) The underlying regression models are specified as in Table 3. In addition, we considered interaction 
terms on the experience polynomials for East Germans in West Germany in Panel (A) and for West Germans 
in East Germany in Panel (B). For the Topel estimator the interaction terms were considered at the second 
stage only, which implies that experience gathered in the ongoing employment yields the same returns for 
all employees. Heterogeneity in returns to experience is thus limited to experience accumulated on prior 
employments. The coefficients of the interaction terms in combination with the main effects were always 
jointly significant at the one percent level, except for the AS estimator in Panel (A) where they were insignifi-
cant. 
(e) The OLS and AS returns were predicted based on regressions with 9870 person-year observations for the 
West and 2694 person-year observations for the East German sample. The first step of the Topel estimator 
used 7225 and 1910 person-year observations, the second step is based on 9870 and 2694 person-year obser-
vations in Panels (A) and (B), respectively. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>regressions for all of East Germany. Both panels of Table 7 as well as the tests for 
statistical significance therefore support the conclusion that in both regional labour 
markets experience from the two regions earns different returns. Under assumption 
1 we interpret this as indicative of quality differences between East and West Ger-
man experience. 
Under assumption 2 we can investigate whether there is evidence for price dif-
ferences. If East (or West) German experience is a homogenous good we can com-
pare its price in both regions of the country. A comparison of returns to East 
German experience in panels (A) and (B) of Table 7 yields no clear answer: based 
on the OLS and AS estimators returns to East German experience are higher in the 
West; based on the Topel estimator they are higher in the East. In a wage regression 
for all East Germans the experience interaction terms for those who now work in 
West Germany are jointly significant at the 5 percent level if quadratic experience 
terms are used and jointly insignificant with a cubic specification. Thus we find no 
clear evidence in favour of true price differences with respect to the East German 
experience. 
21 In addition, one may well question the underlying assumption that 
the experience of East German workers now working in the West is on average still 
of the same quality as that of East German workers working in the East. Finally, in 
a wage regression for all West Germans a joint significance test does not reject the 
null hypothesis that the returns to West German experience are identical in East or 
West Germany. 
In sum, our initial analyses yielded that the returns to experience earned in East 
Germany are lower than those earned in West Germany. Further tests provided in 
this subsection show that this is unlikely to be due to true differences in the price 
for homogenous experience. Instead, the evidence is stronger for the alternative 
explanation that the type of experience earned in the East German labour market 
differs in character or quality from that earned in the West German labour market. 
As we found above that returns to experience differ already for young workers in 
East vs. West Germany this implies that even the type of experience gathered in 
East Germany since unification earns lower returns than work experience gathered 
in the West. It is left for future research to determine the mechanisms behind this 
intriguing phenomenon. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>The literature on the adjustment of wage structures in transition economies suffers 
from two major shortcomings: first, it concentrates almost exclusively on the 
returns to schooling and disregards the life-cycle perspective of wage structures; </p>

<p>21 This result would be expected in a scenario of convergence between the two German regional labour mar-
kets (see Gernandt and Pfeiffer, 2008). </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>second, it generally relies on least squares estimation which does not account for 
important biases in the estimation of wage determinants. 
This paper contributes to that literature by studying the returns to tenure and 
experience based on more appropriate estimators. We analyse the wage structure 
of a transition economy and compare East German life-cycle wage patterns to those 
in West Germany, a region with the same institutional framework but no heritage 
of a centrally planned economy. Previous studies found flat age-earnings profiles 
in East Germany immediately after unification in the early 1990s. We first corrobo-
rate that these differences existed in the 1990s and then investigate the wage pat-
terns between 2002 and 2006, almost two decades after the fall of the iron curtain. 
Our results confirm that not much has changed since the early 1990s, and 
that the wage-experience profile in East Germany is still substantially flatter 
than in the West. The East-West differences in returns to experience are statisti-
cally significant for the high-and medium-skilled in most specifications. The 
low East German returns to experience might be due to a cohort effect and 
could be determined by workers whose experience became obsolete at the eco-
nomic transition. These individuals may be more likely to be employed in posi-
tions that do not match their 'at times outdated' qualifications. To test whether 
this drives our results we estimate our models separately only for those birth 
cohorts who gathered their entire labour market experience after unification. 
However, even for these individuals we find significantly lower returns to expe-
rience in East than in West Germany. This confirms that until today returns to 
experience are lower in East than West Germany. In a separate analysis we 
compared the returns to experience for subsamples of different regions of ori-
gin. These results indicate that former East Germans earn lower returns to expe-
rience in the West German labour market than West Germans and vice versa 
that West Germans earn higher returns in the East than East Germans. Since 
the returns to West German experience do not differ significantly across the 
two labour markets we conclude that it may be the character of East German 
experience rather than general price differences which are behind the observed 
patterns. 
This opens the intriguing research question of why the returns to human capital 
and the character of experience differ systematically and significantly between the 
two regions, even after controlling for composition effects related to education, 
industry, firm size and region. In a recent contribution Fuchs-Schü ndeln and Izem 
(2008) emphasize that productivity differentials between East and West Germany 
are not due to worker characteristics but instead must be explained by differences 
in firm characteristics, regional public policy, or the cooperation between firms (see 
also Uhlig, 2006, 2008). This corroborates our conclusion that there are indeed sys-
tematic regional 'rather than individual' differences between East and West Ger-
many affecting the wage structure. In future research we plan to consider the 
following potential explanations: (i) possibly, the value of experience depends on 
the type and quality of formal education and workers with formal East German </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>training are systematically disadvantaged. This can be tested, when younger East 
German cohorts, who received their complete education under the market economy 
system, enter the labour market. (ii) Possibly, continued educational activities are 
predominantly used in West Germany. In that case different life-cycle wage devel-
opments reflect systematically different additions to productivity over time, which 
might be complemented by different deferred compensation patterns in the two 
regions. (iii) Employees in the two regions might be differently affected by collec-
tive bargaining. We know that East German employers are less likely to be mem-
bers of employer associations (Kohaut and Schnabel, 2003). This could explain the 
observed results if union contracts tend to prescribe age-based wage structures. (iv) 
Independent of institutional differences in the collective bargaining frameworks, 
life-cycle wage structures might be affected by differences in the negotiating power 
of older workers in East and West Germany. One way to learn about any such dif-
ferences could be to compare wage curves in East and West Germany by age group. 
Buscher (2003) finds unusually high wage elasticities in East Germany, overall. It 
would be interesting to compare this evidence for different age groups and to test 
the hypothesis of monopsonistic labour markets for older employees in East Ger-
many. (v) Finally, Mü nich et al. (2005) find heterogeneous wage structures across 
industries in the Czech Republic. If such heterogeneities in returns to experience 
and tenure exist in Germany as well, we might be observing simple differences in 
the composition of the workforce in the two regions. 
This research yields three conclusions. First, even today East German workers 
could on average gain substantially over the life-cycle by moving West and accu-
mulating Western type work experience. Second, there appears to be little benefit to 
using public funds to keep otherwise unemployed East German workers in subsi-
dized employment, as the East German labour market does not seem to reward 
work experience. This is particularly relevant as Lechner and Wunsch (2009) point 
to this mechanism as the main justification for otherwise ineffective and at times 
even counterproductive active labour market policies in East Germany. 
22 Third, 
studies which celebrate the arrival of market economies based on an analysis of 
returns to schooling neglect that the impact of socialism may still be present in the 
returns to experience and tenure. Based on a comparison with the West German 
benchmark we find evidence for substantially weaker life-cycle wage structures in 
the transition economy of East Germany, even close to 20 years after unification 
and even for those workers who entered the labour force after unification. There-
fore, the transition process might be much more protracted than had been assumed 
so far and, to the extent that returns to tenure and experience reflect real productiv-
ity differentials, the productivity gap between economic systems may have been 
larger than assumed so far. 
An intriguing question for future research is to investigate the mechanisms 
behind the differential developments of returns to experience across transition </p>

<p>22 For similar results, see also Caliendo et al. (2006), or Fitzenberger and Vö lter (2007). </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>economies over time, with rising returns to experience in Estonia (Noorkoiv et al., 
1997), constant levels in the Czech Republic (Mü nich et al., 2005) and weakly rising 
returns in East Germany. </p>



<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>





<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>



<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Table A1. Regression results of the Topel estimator for West Germany </p>

<p>Topel estimation (1st step) 
Topel estimation (2nd step) </p>

<p>Dtenure/10 
0.5775*** 
initial exper./10 
0.4634*** 
0.1080 
0.0486 
Dtenure 
2 /100 
0.0088 
initial exper. 
2 /100 
)0.0283 
0.0479 
0.0404 
Dtenure 
3 /1000 
0.0020 
initial exper. 
3 /1000 
0.0021 
0.0101 
0.0089 
Dexper. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/100 
)0.0877 
educ_intermediate 
0.1843*** 
0.0587 
0.0183 
Dexper. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>/1000 
0.0071 
educ_upper sec. 
0.3848*** 
0.0091 
0.0263 
Deduc_Sec.School 
)0.0911 
educ_university 
0.5879*** 
0.1049 
0.0197 
Deduc_intermed. 
)0.1958* 
educ_other/missings 
)0.0011 </p>

<p>0.1068 
0.0279 
Deduc_upper sec. 
)0.1854 
state_Schleswig-Hols. 
)0.0848** </p>

<p>0.4702 
0.0386 
Deduc_university 
)0.0755 
state_Hamburg 
)0.0618 
0.1064 
0.0598 
Deduc_other 
)0.0974 
state_Lower Saxony 
)0.0249 
0.0940 
0.0265 
Dstate_Schleswig-H. 
0.1251 
state_Bremen 
)0.0366 
0.0803 
0.0794 
Dstate_Hamburg 
)0.0294 
state_N-Rhein-Westfa. 
)0.0303 
0.0523 
0.0206 
Dstate_Lower Saxony 
)0.0816 
state_Hessen 
)0.0110 
0.0889 
0.0267 
Dstate_Bremen 
0.1827*** 
state_R-Pfalz,Saarl. 
)0.0199 
0.0049 
0.0259 
Dstate_N-Rhein-Westfa. 
0.1720 
state_Baden-Wuertt. 
0.0655*** 
0.1982 
0.0216 
Dstate_Hessen 
)0.0175 
Born in Germany 
0.0753*** 
0.0534 
0.0214 </p>



<p>Orlowski and Riphahn </p>

<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

<p>Table A1. (cont) Regression results of the Topel estimator for West Germany </p>

<p>Topel estimation (1st step) 
Topel estimation (2nd step) </p>

<p>Dstate_R-Pfalz,Saarl. 
)0.1984 
ind_Not Applicable 
)0.3294*** </p>

<p>0.2089 
0.0869 
Dstate_Baden-Wuertt. 
)0.0556*** 
ind_Agriculture 
)0.1036*** </p>

<p>0.0176 
0.0357 
Dstate_Bavaria 
)0.0836 
ind_Mining 
0.0167 
0.0569 
0.0199 
Dind_Not Applicable 
)0.2604* 
ind_Manufacturing 
)0.0674*** </p>

<p>0.1542 
0.0211 
Dind_Agriculture 
)0.0552 
ind_Construction 
)0.1140*** 
0.0510 
0.0219 
Dind_Energy 
)0.0327 
ind_Trade 
)0.0313 
0.0343 
0.0256 
Dind_Mining 
0.0162 
ind_Transport 
0.0334 
0.0264 
0.0274 
Dind_Manufacturing 
)0.0755* 
ind_Bank,Insurance 
0.0013 
0.0453 
0.0427 
Dind_Construction 
0.0065 
ind_Services 
)0.0573** 
0.0402 
0.0276 
Dind_Trade 
)0.0773* 
ind_Other 
)0.0629 </p>

<p>0.0415 
0.0938 
Dind_Transport 
0.0287 
ind_Missing 
)0.0504* </p>

<p>0.0443 
0.0300 
Dind_Bank,Ins. 
)0.0399 
y2003 
0.0319*** 
0.0324 
0.0068 
Dind_Services 
)0.0114 
y2004 
0.0339*** 
0.0499 
0.0078 
Dind_Other 
0.0712 
y2005 
0.0325*** 
0.0930 
0.0092 
Dind_Missing 
)0.0372 
y2006 
0.0315*** 
0.0644 
0.0092 
Constant 
1.8676*** 
0.0304 </p>

<p>Note: The results are based on 10 multiply imputed datasets for West Germany. The first step estimation 
uses 9300 and the second step 10,087 observations. 
Source: Germany Socio-Economic Panel (2002-2006), own calculations. </p>

<p>The East German Wage Structure after Transition </p>



<p>Ó 2009 The Authors 
Journal compilation Ó 2009 The European Bank for Reconstruction and Development </p>

</text></tei>