<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F17421772.2011.647058" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT Spatial heterogeneity, spatial dependence and spatial scale constitute key features of 
spatial analysis of housing markets. However, the common practice of modelling spatial dependence as 
being generated by spatial interactions through a known spatial weights matrix is often not satisfactory. 
While existing estimators of spatial weights matrices are based on repeat sales or panel data, this paper 
takes the approach to a cross-section setting. Specifically, based on an a priori definition of housing 
submarkets and the assumption of a multifactor model, we develop maximum likelihood methodology 
to estimate hedonic models that facilitate understanding of both spatial heterogeneity and spatial 
interactions. The methodology, based on statistical orthogonal factor analysis, applied to the urban 
housing market of Aveiro (Portugal) at two different spatial scales, provides exciting inferences on the 
spatial structure of the housing market. </p>

<p>Interactions spatiales dans des modèles de prix hédoniques : le marché de 
l'immobilier urbain à Aveiro, Portugal </p>

<p>RÉ SUMÉ L'hétérogénéité spatiale, la dépendance spatiale et l'échelle spatiale sont des caractéristiques clé 
de l'analyse spatiale dans les marchés de l'immobilier. Toutefois, la pratique habituelle de la modélisation 
de la dépendance spatiale comme étant le résultat d'interactions spatiales par le biais d'une matrice de poids 
spatiaux n'est souvent pas satisfaisante. Alors que les estimateurs existants des matrices de poids spatiaux 
sont basés sur des données de panel ou des ventes répétées, la présente communication adopte le principe 
d'un cadre transversal. Plus spécifiquement, sur la base d'une définition à priori des sub-marche´s de </p>

<p>Arnab Bhattacharjee (to whom correspondence should be sent)l'immobilier, et de l'hypothe`se d'un mode`le multifactoriel, nous cre´ons une me´thodologie de probabiliteḿ 
aximale pour estimer des mode`les hédoniques qui facilitent les connaissances de l'he´te´roge´ne´ite´spatiale et 
des interactions spatiales. Cette me´thodologie, base´e sur une analyse des facteurs orthogonaux, applique´e 
au secteur de l'immobilier urbain a`Aveiro (Portugal) a`deux e´chelles spatiales diffe´rentes, fournit des 
infe´rences excitantes en ce qui concerne la structure spatiale du secteur de l'immobilier. </p>

<p>Interacciones espaciales en modelos hedó nicos de fijació n de precios: El mercado de 
la vivienda urbana de Aveiro, Portugal </p>

<p>EXTRACTO La heterogeneidad, dependencia y escala espaciales constituyen características clave del 
análisis espacial de los mercados de la vivienda. No obstante, la práctica común de modelar la 
dependencia espacial como algo generado por interacciones espaciales a través de una matriz conocida de 
pesos espaciales, a menudo, no es satisfactoria. Aunque los estimadores existentes de matrices de pesos 
espaciales se basan en ventas repetidas o datos de panel, este estudio lleva el planteamiento a un marco 
de corte transversal. Específicamente, basados en una definición a priori de los submercados de la 
vivienda y en la presuposicio´n de un modelo de mu´ltiples factores, desarrollamos una metodología de 
probabilidad ma´xima para estimar modelos hedo´nicos, que facilita la comprensio´n de la heterogeneidad 
espacial y las interacciones espaciales. La metodología, basada en el ana´lisis estadístico de factores 
ortogonales y aplicada al mercado de la vivienda urbana de Aveiro (Portugal) en dos escalas espaciales 
diferentes, proporciona interesantes inferencias sobre la estructura espacial del mercado de la vivienda. </p>

<p>This paper examines the role of space in housing markets within the context of a 
spatial hedonic pricing model applied to the city of Aveiro, Portugal. The above 
application is based on a methodological contribution, namely maximum like-
lihood inference for an unknown spatial weights matrix in a pure cross-section 
setting, for a given a priori characterization of housing submarkets. Specifically, the </p>



<p>paper modifies the methodology developed in Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler  (2011) for estimation of a symmetric spatial weights matrix in a panel data setting, 
to the current context of cross-section data, admitting a factor structure and 
structural spatial dependence arising from a spatial error model. The estimated 
spatial weights matrix is not constrained by restrictive assumptions relating to 
drivers of spatial diffusion, and offers unique opportunities to understand the nature 
of interactions in urban space. 
Our framework and applications pay special attention to three related but 
distinct aspects of spatial analyses relating to housing markets*spatial hetero-
geneity, spatial dependence and spatial scale. The former two spatial aspects have 
been extensively discussed in the spatial econometrics literature (see, for example, 
Anselin, 1988a, 1988b, 1999, 2002). To quote: 'Spatial dependence may be caused 
by different kinds of spatial spill-over effects, while heteroscedasticity could easily 
result from the heterogeneity inherent in the delineation of spatial units and from 
contextual variation over space' (Anselin, 1988b, p. 1). Spatial scale is not so much 
an econometric, but an important empirical issue, and has been discussed widely in 
the housing economics literature, for example in Malpezzi (2003). Whether an 
urban scale is the most suitable, or whether the appropriate scale for analysis should 
be peri-urban (including an urban centre, adjoining suburbs and the countryside), 
regional or national, depends on both the spatial phenomenon under analysis and 
the specific spatial context. 
In our framework, analysis proceeds as follows. First, a suitable spatial scale is 
fixed. Next, at the above chosen scale, we begin by segmenting the housing market 
into submarkets, based on a combination of several criteria: administrative 
boundaries, hedonic substitutability and socio-cultural segmentation. </p>

<p>1   Given the above segmentation into submarkets, spatial dependence relates to 
inferences on spatial weights representing spillovers across different submarkets, and 
those between houses within the same submarket. For the former, the methodology 
in Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) can be adapted, provided we can estimate 
the cross-submarket spatial autocovariance matrix of the errors; for this purpose, we 
use a methodology based on the cross-section factor model. For the second, we 
develop maximum likelihood methodology, where we assume for simplicity that 
the within-submarket spatial weights are the same across all submarkets. 
Following the spatial econometrics literature (see, for example, Anselin, 1988b,  1999), spatial heterogeneity is used to inform spatially varying coefficients, spatial 
structural change and heteroscedasticity. In our framework, this is achieved by 
allowing for heterogeneity across submarkets in intercepts and slopes of the factor-
based hedonic housing price model, as well as the error variance. </p>

<p>2   As mentioned above, the proposed methodology is based on statistical factor 
analysis on housing and location characteristics. Applied to the housing market of 
Aveiro segmented into submarkets at two different spatial scales, the method provides 
a description of urban spatial structure based on spatial heterogeneity, spatial 
interactions and spatial scale. The resulting spatial model is useful for understanding 
relative importance of various elements*housing characteristics and access to central 
and local amenities, as well as interactions within and between housing submarkets* 
and provides useful inferences on residential location, urban planning and policy. 
Substantial gains are also obtained with regard to house price prediction. 
In several ways, the proposed framework offers improved understanding of 
space in housing markets. First, we represent spatial heterogeneity through a factor-
based hedonic pricing model estimated at the submarket level. In the process, we </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 135 </p>

<p>follow the literature, beginning with Archer &amp; Williamson (1973) and Davies  (1974), on the use of statistical factor analysis to aggregate hedonic characteristics 
into interpretable behavioural categories. These orthogonal factors are then used as 
explanatory variables in a hedonic pricing regression model in log-linear form. The 
model allows for spatial heterogeneity in the form of different preferences for 
housing and access characteristics in different submarkets and submarket-specific 
fixed effects. Substantial spatial heterogeneity is observed, providing useful 
interpretation for urban spatial structure. 
Second, following the emerging econometric literature on unknown spatial 
weight matrices (Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly, 2009, 2011; Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen- Butler, 2011), we develop methodology to estimate spatial interactions within and 
across housing submarkets under the structural assumption of symmetry. As Anselin  &amp; Lozano-Gracia (2008) and Anselin et al. (2010) demonstrate, it is important in 
hedonic models to allow for interactions modelled by a spatial econometric model. 
At the same time, there is explicit acknowledgement in the literature of 
considerable uncertainty regarding real drivers of spatial diffusion, and that 
assuming spatial weights based on geographic distances or contiguity is far too 
simplistic (Giacomini &amp; Granger, 2004; Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler, 2011). Our 
work extends the literature on estimation of the spatial weights matrix to a pure 
cross-section setting under the structural assumption of symmetry; for a critical 
review of some recent methods in the panel data setting, see Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly  (2011). 
Third, in conducting analyses and obtaining inferences on heterogeneity and 
interactions at two different spatial scales, our work emphasizes the importance of 
spatial scale. In our view, studying spatial structure of housing markets from all the 
above dimensions is important not only for understanding residential location but 
also for urban planning and housing policy; see Maclennan (2010) and 
Bhattacharjee et al. (2010) for further discussion. 
Finally, our conceptual framework, combining unknown spatial interactions 
with unrestricted spatial heterogeneity, has important connections to philosophical 
views in geography and urban studies. Spatial heterogeneity relates to the idea of 
distinctive identity of spatial units or 'unique spaces' (Hartshorne, 1939) and 
emphasizes neighbourhood effects. Further, our representation of spatial depen-
dence in terms of an unknown spatial weights matrix is closely wed to the idea of 
abstract and endogenously produced space in Lefebvre (1974 [1991]). At the same 
time, our spatial weights matrices acknowledge the notion of distance decay 
inherent in logical positivism (Schaefer, 1953), while abstracting from the Cartesian 
characterization of space emphasized in exogenous and given spatial weights 
matrices based on distance or contiguity. 
The rest of the paper is organized as follows. In Section 2, we discuss our 
methodology and place it within the context of the emerging literature on 
inferences relating to unknown spatial interactions. Following this, in Section 3, we 
apply our methods to a spatial hedonic price model for the city of Aveiro, using a 
small but very rich dataset on hedonic characteristics of properties sold through the 
leading real estate agency in 2007. Next, we extend the analysis to the peri-urban 
spatial scale including neighbouring parishes with potentially substantial spillovers 
with Aveiro, based on data for all properties put on the market between 2000 and 
2010 (Section 4). With both datasets, we find important evidences on spatial 
heterogeneity and dependence that inform our understanding of the urban spatial </p>



<p>structure of the housing markets in Aveiro, as well as the importance of spatial scale. 
Section 5 concludes. </p>

<p>2. Methodology </p>

<p>Our proposed methodology combines spatial hedonic analysis based on orthogonal 
factors with a method for inferences on unknown spatial weights matrices under 
the structural constraint of symmetric spatial weights. Below, we discuss our 
methodology in further detail. </p>

<p>2.1. Hedonic Pricing Model </p>

<p>Building on the early work of Lancaster (1966) and Rosen (1974), hedonic pricing 
models continue to be actively used in housing studies. In particular, valuation of 
access to central and local services and other housing attributes, and construction of 
price indices based on single sales data, have been addressed through hedonic 
specifications; see Maclennan (1977) for a classic and critical discussion, and 
Chattopadhya (1999), Malpezzi (2003) and Palmquist (2005) for recent reviews. 
In hedonic pricing models, dwelling unit values (or proxies such as prices or 
rents) are regressed on a bundle of characteristics of the unit that determine the value: </p>

<p>P ¼ f S; N ; L; C; T 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>where P denotes the value of the house (price, or price per unit area), and S, N, L, 
C and T denote, respectively, structural characteristics of the dwelling (living space, 
type of construction, tenure, etc.); neighbourhood characteristics (and local 
amenities); location within the market (or access to employment/business centre); 
other characteristics (access to utilities and public services, such as clean water 
supply, electricity, central heating, etc.); and the time (date, month) when the value 
is observed. 
Estimating the hedonic price function using a collection of observed housing 
values and dwelling unit characteristics yields a set of implicit prices for housing 
characteristics that are essentially willingness-to-pay estimates. This allows analysis 
of various upgrading scenarios, targeted to specific subgroups, defined either by 
socio-economic characteristics or by location. Thus, the model facilitates under-
standing of residential location, and therefore urban structure, and provides 
valuable input towards urban planning and housing policy. 
Theory provides no guidance for the functional form appropriate for hedonic 
regression. However, a nonlinear hedonic function is useful for recovering the 
underlying structural demand curve from estimates of the hedonic relationship (the 
reduced form). This and several other important advantages motivated Follain &amp;  Malpezzi (1980) to recommend the semi-log form; for further discussion, see 
Follain &amp; Malpezzi (1980) and Malpezzi (2003). 
In this paper, we estimate the hedonic model with a small modification to the 
semi-log form, where logarithm of price per square meter of living space is 
regressed on logarithm of house area, conditioning on several other hedonic 
housing characteristics. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 137 </p>

<p>2.2. Factor Structure and Multivariate Dimension Reduction </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>There are literally hundreds of potential housing characteristics that could be 
included on the right hand side of a hedonic regression model. Unfortunately, 
coefficient estimates are not robust to the omitted variables problem (Butler, 1982;  Ozanne &amp; Malpezzi, 1985). However, the same correlation between omitted and 
included variables that biases individual coefficient estimates often aids better 
prediction from a 'sparse' model (Malpezzi, 2003). 
This feature of the hedonic pricing model enhances the possibility of exploiting 
the factor structure to obtain parsimonious estimates and improved predictions. 
Several studies, beginning with Kain &amp; Quigley (1970) and Archer &amp; Wilkinson  (1973), have taken this approach, and Davies (1974) combined factor analysis with 
the regression approach. In a critical review, Maclennan (1977) suggests that the 
researcher needs to make sure that the extracted factors do not reflect solely 
statistical properties but behavioural collections of housing characteristics. 
In this paper, we employ a hybrid approach, combining factor analysis with 
regression. Initially, we identify a small collection of leading factors from a large 
number of potentially important hedonic characteristics, using factor analysis with 
varimax orthogonal rotations. For both the datasets used in this paper, these 
(orthogonal) factors are clearly identified with interpretable collections of housing 
characteristics, such as structural dimensions, access to utilities, centrality and access 
to local services. At the second stage, we predict factor values for all properties, 
including those for which some hedonic characteristics are missing, and use these 
predicted factors to estimate the hedonic regression model in semi-log form. 
In this way, we address the Davies (1974) and Maclennan (1977) critiques. 
Further, the assumed factor model is absolutely crucial for our proposed inference 
methods for the spatial weights matrix; we will discuss this issue in Section 2.4. In 
addition, the factor-based hedonic housing price model offers three potential 
advantages. 
First, in building a hedonic model based on a small number of factors, rather 
than a large collection of housing characteristics, we build a parsimonious model 
with more precise estimation that offers better interpretation of the regression 
coefficients (implicit prices). More importantly, in including all potential economic 
factors affecting prices, the factor-based regression model is less susceptible to the 
omitted variables problem. Second, hedonic regression based on factors allows a 
unique opportunity to reduce missing value problems, where factors can be 
predicted (imputed) using the information available on only a selection of included 
characteristics, under the assumption that the missing data are allocated randomly 
across the properties conditional on the values of observed features. This leads to 
considerably larger sample sizes for estimation of the hedonic model, with benefits 
of improved precision in the estimates. Third, the approach based on orthogonal 
factors is not subject to multicollinearity, and could therefore contribute to higher 
efficiency, which in turn can lead to better prediction of housing prices; see 
Malpezzi (2003) for further discussion. Besides, the orthogonality of factors is also 
important for estimating the spatial weights, which we discuss later in Section 2.4. 
Finally, and most importantly, the factor-based approach is absolutely crucial 
for our methodology for estimating spatial weights. Thus, it is very useful for 
studying spatial dependence in urban housing markets driven by an unknown 
spatial weights matrix. </p>



<p>2.3. Spatial Issues in Hedonic Pricing Estimates </p>

<p>The recent literature has discussed the potential bias and loss of efficiency that can 
result when spatial effects are ignored in the estimation of hedonic models; see, for 
example, Pace &amp; LeSage (2004), Anselin &amp; Lozano-Gracia (2008) and Anselin et al.  (2010). Spatial patterns in the housing markets arise from a combination of spatial 
heterogeneity and spatial dependence (Anselin, 1988a). Additionally, as discussed 
before, choice of an appropriate spatial scale is important (Malpezzi, 2003). We 
now turn to a discussion of spatial issues in the construction of our hedonic pricing 
models, including all of the three above aspects of space. </p>

<p>2.3.1. Spatial scale and housing submarkets. Definition of submarkets is important at 
both conceptual and empirical levels. Housing markets are local and diverse, and 
hedonic price estimation requires careful delineation of these markets (Malpezzi,  2003). The definition of submarkets in practice ranges from the national or regional 
scale (Linneman, 1981; Mills &amp; Simenauer, 1996), through metropolitan areas 
(Follain &amp; Malpezzi, 1980), to below the metropolitan level (Straszheim, 1975;  Gabriel, 1984; Grigsby et al., 1985; Rothenberg et al., 1991; Maclennan &amp; Tu,  1996; Bourassa et al., 1999). 
Malpezzi (2003) argues that one reason why the metropolitan area is appealing 
as the unit of analysis is that these areas are usually thought of as labour markets, 
which may therefore be approximately coincident with housing markets. On the 
other hand, submarkets below the metropolitan level can be segmented by location 
(central city/suburb), or by housing quality, or even by race or income levels. Such 
segmentation facilitates both understanding of residential neighbourhood choice 
and devising appropriate urban housing policy. However, the empirical literature 
does not suggest an unambiguous definition of a unique spatial scale. 
In this paper, we conduct our analysis at two different spatial scales, both 
disaggregated to a relatively fine spatial level. In the first, we consider administrative 
regions (parishes) within the city of Aveiro as submarkets, and pool the suburban 
area together into a single submarket. This definition aids understanding of spatial 
heterogeneity and interactions within the urban area, but does not provide 
satisfactory analysis in terms of spillovers between the city and the suburban area. 
Second, we extend our analysis to a finer spatial scale within the suburban area, 
constructing submarkets with careful consideration to the principles of segmenta-
tion discussed above. Our analysis reflects some advantages of using a flexible spatial 
scale, since processes of agglomeration and dispersion operate differently at different 
scales (Arbia et al., 2010, 2012). </p>

<p>2.3.2. Spatial heterogeneity and neighbourhood effects. The conceptual notion behind 
spatial submarkets discussed above implies that the price determining (hedonic) 
mechanism can be heterogeneous over space. This spatial heterogeneity can 
originate from demand and supply factors, institutional barriers or discrimination, 
each of which can cause differentials across neighbourhoods in the way housing 
attributes are valued by consumers and house prices determined (Anselin et al.,  2010). However, if spatial heterogeneity is present and ignored, an average price 
across all submarkets is estimated that ignores submarket heterogeneity. Worse still, 
the error term of the regression can then be correlated with the included regressors 
and ordinary least squares (OLS) will produce biased estimates. 
The standard urban model in the AlonsoÁMuthÁMills tradition predicts a 
generally declining pattern of prices with distance from the centre of the city, though </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 139 </p>

<p>there may be spatial variation in relative preference for centrality. Other models based 
on localized amenities or multiple centres imply a stronger impact of access to local 
amenities. Like distances, the implicit prices for dwelling characteristics and size may 
also vary spatially, reflecting either supply constraints or residential sorting. Follain &amp;  Malpezzi (1980), Mozolin (1994), Adair et al. (2000) and Soderberg &amp; Janssen (2001), 
among others, have examined intra-urban variation in the price of housing using 
hedonic models. We follow the above line of literature in allowing coefficients in our 
hedonic pricing model to vary across submarkets, and use the estimated variation to 
infer on residential neighbourhood choice and urban spatial structure. </p>

<p>2.3.3. Spatial dependence and spatial weights matrix. In contrast to spatial hetero-
geneity, spatial dependence leads to spatial autocorrelation, implying that prices of 
nearby houses tend to be more similar than those of houses that are farther apart. 
Likewise, average price of houses in nearby or related submarkets may be correlated 
more strongly. A common explanation for spatial autocorrelation is spatial 
spillovers or other forms of contagion effects. However, incorrectly modelled 
spatial heterogeneity, measurement problems in explanatory variables, omitted 
variables, and unmodelled features having a spatial pattern can also lead to spatial 
autocorrelation (Anselin &amp; Griffith, 1988). Recent empirical literature has 
addressed issues of bias and loss of efficiency that can result when spatial effects 
are ignored in the estimation of hedonic models (see, for example Pace &amp; LeSage,  2004; Anselin &amp; Lozano-Garcia, 2008) and the use of spatial econometric models 
to address spatial autocorrelation is becoming increasingly standard. </p>

<p>4   The usual approach to the representation of spatial interactions is to define a 
spatial weights matrix, denoted W, which typically represents a theoretical and a priori 
characterization of the nature and strength of spatial interactions between different 
submarkets or dwellings. 
5 These spatial weights represent patterns of diffusion of 
prices and unobservables over space, and thereby provide a meaningful and easily 
interpretable representation of spatial interaction (spatial autocorrelation). The spatial 
weights are typically modelled as functions of geographic or economic distance. The 
distance between two spatial units reflects their proximity with respect to prices or 
unobservables, so that the spatial interaction between a set of units (dwellings) can be 
represented as a function of the economic distances between them. 
Given a particular choice of the spatial weights matrix, there are two important 
and distinct ways in which spatial dependence is modelled in spatial regression 
analysis*the spatial lag model and the spatial error model. In the former, 
the hedonic regression includes, as an additional regressor, the spatial lag of the 
dependent variable y (which in our case is price), represented by Wy, and the 
regression errors (o) are completely idiosyncratic. By contrast, in the spatial error 
model, the regression errors are spatially dependent on their spatial lag, Wo. 
The implications of spatial interaction on estimation of these two models are 
different. In the spatial lag model, the endogenous spatial lag implies that OLS 
estimates not accounting for spatial interaction would be biased, while in the spatial 
error model, they will be unbiased but inefficient. However, though different in 
interpretation, the above two models are very difficult to distinguish empirically 
(Anselin, 1999, 2002). In line with current practice in the area of spatial 
econometrics, we first estimate the hedonic pricing model under the spatial error 
assumption. Next, to judge whether endogenous spatial lags are relevant, we 
perform a test for spatial lag dependence by nesting the spatial error model within a 
hybrid model incorporating both spatial lag and spatial error dependence; for more </p>



<p>discussion on sequential model selection in the spatial context, see Born &amp; Breitung  (2011). 
The choice of appropriate spatial weights is a central component of spatial 
models as it imposes a priori a structure of spatial dependence, which may or may 
not closely correspond to reality. Further, the accuracy of these measures affects 
severely the estimation of spatial dependence models (Anselin, 2002; Fingleton,  2003). Spatial contiguity or suitable functions of geographic distances are frequent 
choices. However, spatial data may be anisotropic, where spatial autocorrelation is a 
function of both distance and the direction separating points in space (Simon, 1997;  Gillen et al., 2001). Further, spatial interactions may be driven by other factors, such 
as trade weights, transport cost, travel time and socio-cultural distances. The choice 
typically differs widely across applications, depending not only on the specific 
economic context but also on availability of data. The problem of choosing spatial 
weights is a key issue in many applications. 
Given the above ambiguities regarding measurement of spatial weights, and in 
line with the notion that factors different from geographic distance or contiguity 
may potentially drive spatial interactions, we consider the spatial weights matrix 
(W) as an unknown symmetric matrix with zero diagonal elements. We allow 
spatial interactions to be potentially negative, often implying segmented housing 
markets or asynchronous housing cycles. 
6 Based on a given definition of urban 
submarkets (or a fixed set of spatial locations) and panel data on these spatial units, 
Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly (2009, 2011) and Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011)  developed several methods to estimate the spatial weights matrix between the 
submarkets. 
7 Here, we extend the panel estimation methodology in Bhattacharjee 
&amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) under the structural assumption of symmetric spatial 
weights to a purely cross-section setting. 
Specifically, we consider a cross-section Gaussian factor regression model 
(Liu &amp; Rubin, 1998) where each housing property i (01, . . ., n) belongs to a single 
submarket M j , where M j is one of J mutually exclusive and exhaustive submarkets 
M 1 , M 2 , . . ., M J . The price of the dwelling y i depends on a (q )1) vector of 
unobserved orthonormal Gaussian factors F i of housing and locational hedonic 
characteristics (the (p )1) vector x i , q Bp), where the effects of the factors 
potentially vary across the submarkets. The corresponding regression error o i is 
uncorrelated with the factors, but may be spatially related to the errors for other 
houses through an unknown spatial weights matrix, W. In other words, we 
consider a spatial error model with a cross-section heterogeneous factor structure 
across the submarkets, where the effects of the factors are potentially different across 
submarkets and there may be submarket-specific fixed effects: </p>

<p>X i F i ; c; W 
ð 
ÞÂ 
indep N P aþc </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>F i ; W 
À 
Á 
; i ¼ 1; 2;:::; n; </p>



<p>W ¼ diag w </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 ; :::; w </p>

<p>2 
p </p>



<p>; F i Â 
iid N q 0; I 
ð Þ; </p>

<p>y i ¼ b 0j þ b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j F i þ e i ; e ¼ kW e þ t; i 2 M j 
t i Â N 0; r </p>

<p>2 
j </p>



<p>independent; Cov t i ; F i 
ð 
Þ ¼ 0: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>Here e ¼ e i ; e 2 ; . . . ; e n 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>, the vector of the random errors, has a spatial error 
structure with an unknown spatial weights matrix W (n)n) having zero diagonal 
elements, and the zero mean Gaussian idiosyncratic errors (y i s) are potentially 
heteroscedastic across submarkets but independent over the cross-section and </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 141 </p>

<p>uncorrelated with the random factors F i . Equation (1) describes a simplified version 
of the cross-section factor model with heterogeneous group effects discussed in 
Andrews (2005), with additional Gaussian assumptions. These distributional 
assumptions are useful in our case for drawing inferences by maximum likelihood 
on the intra-submarket spatial weights. 
The spatial weights matrix W is the row-standardized version of W </p>

<p>0 
nÂn 
ð </p>

<p>Þ , which 
is assumed to be symmetric and have a block-structure as follows: </p>

<p>W </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>ij ¼ </p>

<p>0 if 
i ¼ j 
x o if i; j 2 M k ; k ¼ 1; :::; J 
x kl if i 2 M k ; j 2 M l ; M k \ M l ¼ /: </p>

<p>8 
&lt; </p>

<p>: 
(2) </p>

<p>The above weights matrix is unknown and quite general, allowing for unknown 
but fixed spatial weights between properties in the same submarket, and similarly 
unknown spatial weights between properties in any pair of submarkets. 
8 For 
identification in the reduced form, it is required that (IÁlW) is nonsingular. 
Further structural assumptions are required for identification. Following 
Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011), we assume symmetric spatial weights within 
and between submarkets </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>*a standard assumption in the spatial econometrics 
literature. However, spatial weights are allowed to be negative. 
In this paper, we assume a spatial error model. Because of endogeneity, 
estimating the spatial weights matrix under the spatial lag model is a more difficult 
problem. However, we can perform specification tests against the spatial lag model 
under the assumption that the same spatial weights matrix W describes both spatial 
lag dependence and error dependence. For this purpose, we nest the above 
spatial error model within the following model that includes both spatial lag and 
spatial error, with different autoregressive coefficients: </p>

<p>y ¼ qW y þ b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>j F i þ e i ; 
i ¼ 1; 2; . . . ; n; 
i 2 M j ; </p>

<p>e ¼ kW e þ t; 
t i Â N 0; r </p>

<p>2 
j </p>



<p>independent; Cov t i ; F i 
ð 
Þ ¼ 0: 
(3) </p>

<p>Born &amp; Breitung (2011) propose a regression-based test, where at the first stage, 
the spatial error model (1) is estimated. At the second stage, the test evaluates 
whether there is any residual spatial dependence that can be explained by spatial lag 
effect. We use this test to verify whether the spatial error model is adequate for our 
empirical applications. The test is simple to apply and has several advantages over 
standard LM tests; see Born &amp; Breitung (2011) for further details. </p>

<p>2.4. Estimation of Symmetric Spatial Weights Matrix </p>

<p>As discussed before, our main methodological contribution is to estimate unknown 
spatial weights within a factor-based cross-section spatial error model. Next, we 
describe our estimation methodology in three steps: first, the cross-market spatial 
interaction matrix W 
+ (defined in Equation (4) below); second, the cross-
submarket spatial autocovariance matrix G; and finally, the within-submarket 
spatial weight v 0 . </p>

<p>2.4.1. Estimation of cross-market spatial interaction matrix. In the panel data setting, the 
methodology in Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) is based on a given 
consistent estimator for the underlying hedonic regression model with spatial </p>



<p>errors as in Equation (1). Based on residuals from the above estimation, a consistent 
estimatorĈ (with asymptotically normally distributed elements) is first obtained for 
the J)J cross-submarket spatial autocovariance matrix </p>

<p>C ¼ I À W </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>ð 
Þ 
À1 R I À W </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>ð 
Þ; </p>

<p>W 
Ã ¼ k </p>

<p>0 x 12 . . . x 1J 
x 12 
0 . . . x 2J </p>

<p>. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. 
. . 
. </p>

<p>x 1J x 2J . . . 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 
6 
6 
6 
6 
4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>7 
7 
7 
7 
7 
5 </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>and R ¼ diag r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 ; r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ; . . . ; r </p>

<p>2 
J </p>

<p>Â 
Ã 
: </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>Let us assume that such an estimatorĈ has been obtained. Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen- Butler (2011) show how this estimatorĈ can then be used to estimate the 
unknown cross-submarket spatial weights matrix W </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>. Without any structural 
constraints on the weights matrix, the estimation problem is only partially 
identified, up to an orthogonal transformation of interactions. Specifically, they 
show that the matrix </p>

<p>V ¼ I À W </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>ð 
Þ:diag </p>

<p>1 
r 1 </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>1 
r 2 </p>

<p>; . . . ; </p>

<p>1 
r J </p>

<p>h 
i </p>

<p>is consistently estimated, up to an arbitrary orthogonal transformation, bŷ </p>

<p>C 
À1=2 ¼Ê:K 
À1=2 :Ê 
0 ; </p>

<p>whereÊ: andK contain the eigenvectors and eigenvalues, respectively, of the 
estimated spatial autocovariance matrixĈ. 
10 In other words,Ĉ 
(1/2 is a consistent 
estimator of VT for some unknown square orthogonal matrix T. Since T is an 
arbitrary orthogonal matrix, it has precisely J( JÁ1)/2 free elements. Hence, the 
spatial weights matrix W 
+ can be precisely estimated only under additional 
structural constraints. Symmetry of the spatial weights matrix constitutes one set of 
valid identifying restrictions, 
11 which is the structural assumption we make here. 
Under the symmetry assumption, Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011)  describe inference methods and an algorithm for estimating the unknown spatial 
weights matrix. Estimation requires application of the 'gradient projection' 
algorithm (Jennrich, 2001) which optimizes an objective function over the group 
of orthogonal transformations of a given matrix; standard errors are obtained using 
the bootstrap. 
This method can be readily applied to our spatial hedonic pricing model 
provided an initial consistent estimator can be found for the cross-submarket spatial 
autocovariance matrix G. In this paper, we propose a maximum likelihood method 
to estimate this autocovariance matrix. </p>

<p>2.4.2. Estimation of cross-submarket spatial autocovariance matrix. In the panel data 
setting, Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) estimated the underlying regression 
model and obtained residuals, and then estimatedĈ as the sample covariance matrix </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 143 </p>

<p>of the cross-market residuals. This step was relatively simple because, for each time 
period, there was a residual uniquely identified with each submarket. 
In the current pure cross-section setting, the situation is more complex because 
a priori there is no natural way to associate a house in any one submarket with a 
corresponding house in any other submarket. For this matching problem, we use an 
analogy of the current cross-section factor model (Andrews, 2005) with the 
multifactor error structure of cross-sectionally dependent panel data inherent in the 
common correlated effects methodology of Pesaran (2006). 
In the common correlated effects approach (Pesaran, 2006), linear combina-
tions of unobserved common factors are approximated by cross-section averages of 
the dependent and explanatory variables, which are then included in the panel 
regression model in addition to the other regressors. The cross-section averages 
vary over time and not over the cross-section, and represent omitted time-specific 
common factors. Clearly, an alternative to these cross-section averages would be 
including a full set of time fixed effects. 
Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) use residuals across spatial units for the 
same time period to estimate the spatial error autocovariance matrix. The 
multifactor spatial error model provides a clear justification for this approach. 
Residuals for the same period are matched because the corresponding observations 
on different spatial units align perfectly along the dimension of the unobserved 
latent factors*in the panel data setting, the time-specific common shocks. Taking 
this intuition to the pure cross-section setting, it is therefore natural to match 
housing property i in submarket M j with the dwelling j in another submarket M j 
that bears the closest correspondence in the vector of latent factors; in our case F i 
and F j . Thus, the proposed methodology proceeds as follows. 
In the first stage, we estimate a suitable set of orthogonal factors based on 
hedonic characteristics. Using these estimated factors, we consistently estimate the 
hedonic regression model in Equation (1) separately for each submarket. This 
estimation allows for full spatial heterogeneity, but ignores the spatial error 
structure. Based on these submarket-specific regression estimates, we obtain 
residuals for each property. 
We match properties across submarkets in the second stage. Specifically, to the 
residual for an index dwelling i in submarket M i , we match the residual for that 
house j in submarket M j that has the closest match in the vector of estimated factors; 
in other words, </p>

<p>j ¼ arg min </p>

<p>j Ã 2M j </p>

<p>F i À F j Ã </p>

<p>0 
F i À F j Ã </p>



<p>In the third stage, based on matched residuals across the different submarkets, 
the cross-submarket spatial autovariance matrix is estimated simply by the sample 
covariance matrixĈ. Finally, estimation of W 
+ follows using the Bhattacharjee &amp; 
Jensen-Butler (2011) methodology outlined in the previous subsection. 
The assumption of the multifactor model is crucial for this estimation 
procedure. 
12 First, residuals from an estimated hedonic pricing model would be 
extremely susceptible to the potential omitted variables problem. In practical terms, 
it is very difficult to avoid this problem, even if a large number of hedonic 
characteristics are included in the estimation. By contrast, in estimating the factor 
model, it is simpler to minimize this problem by including factors corresponding to 
all notional features that theory and past studies have identified as determinants of </p>



<p>house prices. One can then make the reasonable assumption that what remains in 
the error is uncorrelated with the included factors. 
Second, and as discussed above, the factor model is conceptually very closely 
related to the critical distinction between spatial strong and weak dependence 
(Pesaran &amp; Tosetti, 2011), and therefore to the common correlated effects approach 
(Pesaran, 2006). Specifically, in the panel data setting, the theoretical justification 
for matching residuals corresponding to different spatial units for the same time 
period is that they match on the strong spatial dependence (or, unobserved factor) 
dimension. Matching against estimated factors provides an exact conceptual 
counterpart to this argument in our cross-section factor model setting. </p>

<p>13   Third, since our estimated factors are orthogonal by construction, it is 
straightforward to match two properties in different submarkets by the inner 
product (sum of squares) of the vector of difference of their corresponding 
estimated factors. 
Finally, under the assumptions of the factor model (1),Ĉ estimated as above is 
the maximum likelihood estimator of the spatial autocovariance matrix (see also 
Andrews, 2005) under the maintained factor model and Gaussian error assumption. 
Since there is a unique relation between G and the corresponding W </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, the 
corresponding cross-submarket symmetric spatial weights matrix is a maximum 
likelihood estimate as well. </p>

<p>2.4.3. Estimation of within-submarket spatial weight. What remains now is to estimate 
the within-submarket spatial weight v 0 . Since dwellings within a submarket are in 
general located closer to each other than those across different submarkets, it is 
expected that v 0 will be large compared to the cross-submarket spatial weights. We 
propose maximum likelihood to conduct this estimation. Specifically, for any 
candidate value of v 0 , we construct the corresponding row-standardized spatial 
weights matrix W, estimate the spatial error model using maximum likelihood, and 
evaluate the value of the maximized likelihood. In this way, we construct spatial 
weights matrices using various candidate values for v 0 , estimate the corresponding 
spatial error models by maximum likelihood using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Geoda</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Anselin</rs>, 2005), and 
maximize the likelihood over all such candidate values. Standard errors are 
estimated by numerical approximation to compute the Fisher information at this 
maximized value for v 0 . </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Finally, as discussed earlier, we use the Born &amp; Breitung (2011) regression test 
to examine the validity of spatial error dependence against a hybrid model 
including a spatial lag. </p>

<p>3. Empirical Analysis at the Urban Spatial Scale </p>

<p>3.1. Data </p>

<p>The proposed methodology is applied to the housing market of Aveiro, a city 
located in the Centro Region of Portugal. The urban agglomeration of Aveiro 
includes the municipality with the same name and the neighbouring municipality 
of Ílhavo and it had a population of 114,000 inhabitants in 2006. Our first empirical 
analysis refers only to the city, which corresponds to six of the 14 parishes of the 
municipality of Aveiro (Table 1). The dataset includes 166 properties sold through 
one of the leading real estate agencies in Aveiro in 2007. 
15 The spatial distribution 
of the properties is presented in Figure 1, where each house is indicated by a dot. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 145 </p>

<p>This dataset is quite different from the one analysed in the following section. 
One potential limitation is the reduced number of available observations, covering 
only the urban and suburban areas of Aveiro municipality. However, this is 
compensated by availability of data at a finer detail, including specific location of 
each house (so that exact distances can be computed) and greater detail of hedonic 
characteristics recorded for each house, but especially the availability of true 
transaction prices (rather than listing prices as in the second dataset). Most 
importantly, the small sample size enables us to obtain ML estimates of spatial 
econometric models using alternate definitions of spatial weights and thereby 
compare the adequacy of different specifications. 
The data cover single unit housing (12.3%) and flats (87.7%), both newly built 
(11.8%) and used (88.2%), located in different urban and suburban areas. Data on 
several physical and location attributes of each house were collected, as well as exact 
location of each house. Location attributes were defined by geographic distances 
from each property to several amenities and services available within the city, 
constructed using Geographic Information System (GIS). These represent the 
desirability of each neighbourhood. </p>

<p>Table 1. Population and density of housing sample </p>

<p>Parishes 
Population 
Density 
Sample 
Houses </p>

<p>Aradas 
7,628 
15% 
854 
22 
13.3% 
Esgueira 
12,262 
24% 
691 
42 
25.3% 
Glória 
9,917 
19% 
1,445 
27 
16.3% 
Santa Joana 
8,652 
17% 
225 
11 
6.6% 
São Bernardo 
4,079 
8% 
1,037 
9 
5.4% 
Vera Cruz 
8,652 
17% 
1,273 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>55 
33.1% 
Total 
51,190 
100% 
368 
166 
100% </p>

<p>Notes: 
+ Including the lagoon area. Population (in number of inhabitants), density (in inhabitants per km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>). </p>

<p>Vera Cruz </p>

<p>Esgueira </p>

<p>Aradas </p>

<p>Glória </p>

<p>São Bernardo </p>

<p>Santa Joana </p>

<p>Figure 1. Location of housing sample. </p>



<p>The dependent variable used in hedonic price models is usually the transaction 
price. We use a more scale neutral normalized measure*logarithm of price per 
square meter (p/m 
2 ). Housing prices are explained by a wide set of variables (see 
Table 2). Some location attributes are defined as minimum distances to services 
such as high schools or pharmacies; the others are defined as gravity type measures 
of potential, generated by distances to services like restaurants, sport centres or 
public administration offices. For this purpose, we define the potential (P i ) 
generated by a given set of services of type S (S 1 ,S 2 ,. . .,S n ) at a given location (i) by: </p>

<p>P i S 
ð Þ ¼ 
X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>S j </p>

<p>d ij 
; </p>

<p>where S j denotes the service located at the point j and d ij the distance between 
locations i and j (see Stewart, 1947). 
Descriptive statistics presented in Table 2 reflect large variation in the physical 
and location attributes across the sample as well as missing value problems. Missing 
values for total area were imputed, under the standard assumption of conditionally 
missing at random, using the method of conditional mean imputation based on 
values of x and y; see Little (1992) for further discussion. 
The dependent variable in our hedonic regression is price per square meter. All 
other physical and location attributes (including total area) are treated as 
explanatory variables. Observations with missing values in the other physical 
characteristics were omitted from the factor analysis. </p>

<p>3.2. Factor Analysis </p>

<p>The explanatory variables were subjected to factor analysis followed by varimax 
rotations to extract orthogonal factors with maximum explanatory power. The 
leading factors were identified by maximum likelihood factor analysis on the 
original housing attributes. The scree plot suggested five leading factors, which 
were then optimally rotated by a orthogonal varimax procedure. Taken together, 
the five factors explain 63.4% of the variance of all the data. The extracted 
orthogonal factor loadings are reported in Table 3; for visual clarity, we exclude 
from the table estimated loadings below the cut-off of 0.35. Based on these 
loadings, predicted factor scores were computed for use in subsequent analysis. 
The five factors provide a clear interpretation in terms of behavioural 
collections of housing characteristics. Factor 1 corresponds to several indicators 
of centrality related to the city centre*the loadings being higher for amenities that 
are closer to the CBD. The loadings are positive on characteristics measured in 
minimum distances, and negative on those measured in gravitational potential. 
Factor 2 also describes centrality, in this case negatively related to access to local 
amenities such as shopping malls, railway stations, supermarkets or motorway 
connections. 
By contrast, factors 3, 4 and 5 represent the internal characteristics of dwellings. 
Factor 3 is related to a combination of attributes which, in the case of Aveiro, are 
strongly correlated: being a flat or a single unit housing, having a gas connection 
and cable TV infrastructure 
16 (high values of the factor correspond to flats with gas 
and cable TV). Factor 4 represents housing space, combining house size with the </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 147 </p>

<p>number of rooms, while factor 5 refers to additional desirable characteristics such as 
living room and kitchen area and the provision for a garage. 
Thus, the extracted factors represent behavioural collections of housing 
characteristics rather than statistical quantities with ambiguous interpretations 
(Maclennan, 1977). </p>

<p>Table 2. Descriptive statistics of variables, urban scale </p>

<p>Variable 
Units of measurement N Minimum Maximum Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Internal physical characteristics </p>

<p>d 
Type 
(Single unit 01, 
Flat 00) </p>

<p>166 
1.00 
2.00 
1.13 
0.34 </p>

<p>d 
Duplex 
(Yes 01; No 00) 
162 
1.00 
2.00 
1.20 
0.40 
d 
Balcony 
(Yes 01; No 00) 
166 
0.00 
1.00 
0.19 
0.40 
d 
Terrace 
(Yes 01; No 00) 
166 
0.00 
1.00 
0.10 
0.30 
d 
Provision for garage (Yes 01; No 00) 
166 
0.00 
1.00 
0.59 
0.49 
d 
Cable TV 
(Yes 01; No 00) 
166 
0.00 
1.00 
0.26 
0.44 
d 
Gas (natural) 
(Yes 01; No 00) 
166 
0.00 
1.00 
0.38 
0.49 
Number of 
bedrooms </p>

<p>(Number) 
165 
1.00 
5.00 
2.32 
0.84 </p>

<p>d 
Build and age 
(Used 01, New 00) 
165 
0.00 
1.00 
0.88 
0.32 
Floors 
(Number) 
166 
1.00 
12.00 
3.46 
2.16 
ln 
Kitchen area 
(m 
2 ) 
139 
1.70 
3.21 
2.48 
0.31 
ln 
Living room area 
(m 
2 ) 
147 
2.12 
3.35 
2.53 
0.19 
ln 
Price 
(Euros/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
166 
5.98 
8.01 
7.11 
0.34 
ln 
Total area </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(m 
2 ) 
166 
3.50 
5.52 
4.67 
0.39 </p>

<p>Location characteristics </p>

<p>ln 
Central amenities 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
4.51 
8.58 
7.19 
0.74 
ln 
Local amenities 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
8.35 
9.26 
8.72 
0.17 
ln 
CBD Aveiro 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
5.54 
8.63 
7.30 
0.68 
ln 
Local commerce 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
3.49 
7.96 
6.14 
0.93 
ln 
Primary schools 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
3.16 
6.76 
5.48 
0.69 
ln 
High schools 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
3.14 
8.23 
6.39 
0.95 
ln 
University 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
6.06 
8.70 
7.49 
0.58 
ln 
Hospital 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
4.96 
8.37 
7.08 
0.62 
ln 
Health centres 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
5.32 
8.60 
7.31 
0.66 
ln 
Pharmacies 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
3.39 
7.83 
5.86 
0.88 
ln 
Parks and gardens 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
5.17 
8.20 
6.81 
0.72 
ln 
Rail station 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
4.88 
8.21 
6.90 
0.70 
ln 
Access node 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
5.41 
8.31 
7.19 
0.51 
ln 
Gas station 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
2.08 
7.67 
6.07 
0.95 
ln 
Police 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
166 
3.57 
8.41 
7.11 
0.67 
p 
Administration 
(Potential) 
166 
5.49 
9.09 
6.89 
0.72 
p 
Cultural centre 
(Potential) 
166 
6.04 
8.66 
7.19 
0.50 
p 
Specialised 
commerce </p>

<p>(Potential) 
166 
6.56 
8.75 
7.71 
0.43 </p>

<p>p 
Restaurants 
(Potential) 
166 
7.80 
10.15 
8.90 
0.54 
p 
Hotels and hostels 
(Potential) 
166 
5.48 
8.15 
6.72 
0.65 
p 
Monuments 
(Potential) 
166 
7.95 
10.90 
8.71 
0.48 
p 
Banks, ATMs, Post (Potential) 
166 
7.87 
10.19 
8.85 
0.47 
p 
Sports 
(Potential) 
166 
7.04 
8.81 
7.88 
0.38 </p>

<p>Notes: d 0dummy variable; ln0in logarithms; p 0gravitational potential. </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>: includes 56 imputed missing values. </p>



<p>3.3. Spatial Heterogeneity </p>

<p>Next, ordinary least squares (OLS) regression was used to estimate hedonic pricing 
models allowing for spatial heterogeneity across the urban submarkets of Aveiro. 
Predicted orthogonal factors obtained above, including imputations for missing 
values, were used as explanatory variables. Of the 166 housing properties in the 
dataset, there were complete data for only 118 houses. The possibility of 
imputation for missing values in the factors marks one of the advantages of the 
factor-based approach taken in this paper. </p>

<p>Table 3. Factor loadings for urban scale, varimax rotated (absolute value !3.5) </p>

<p>Factor 1 
Factor 2 
Factor 3 
Factor 4 
Factor 5 </p>

<p>Location attributes </p>

<p>University 
0.930 
Central amenities 
0.921 
CBD Aveiro 
0.912 
Parks and gardens 
0.876 
Local amenities 
0.839 
(0.413 
Local commerce 
0.790 
Hospital 
0.788 
Health centres 
0.778 
High schools 
0.733 
Pharmacies 
0.640 
0.367 
Police 
0.580 
0.426 
Gas station 
0.397 
0.374 
Primary schools 
0.391 
Specialised commerce 
(0.473 
(0.814 
Administration 
(0.784 
(0.416 
Monuments 
(0.809 
Banks, ATMs, Post 
(0.860 
Sports 
(0.919 
Hotels and hostels 
(0.923 
Restaurants 
(0.940 
Cultural centre 
(0.953 
Railway station 
0.785 
Access node 
0.593 </p>

<p>Physical attributes </p>

<p>Gas (natural) 
0.740 
Cable TV 
0.736 
Floors 
0.585 
Type (Single unit 01, Flat 00) 
(0.473 
Duplex 
Total area 
0.794 
Number of bedrooms 
0.749 
Living room area 
0.630 
Provision for garage 
0.575 
Terrace 
0.478 
Balcony 
0.434 
Kitchen area 
0.432 
Build and age (Used 01, New00) 
(0.362 </p>

<p>Percentage of variance explained 
37.60% 
8.21% 
6.48% 
5.65% 
5.45% </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 149 </p>

<p>The total area of the house was also included as a regressor. Since the dependent 
variable is logarithm of price per unit area, the coefficient on this regressor (b s ) is 
expected to lie between zero and negative unity (0 and (1), with the 
interpretation that 1'b s is the price elasticity of house area. 
These regression models were estimated for the full sample as well as for each of 
the four submarkets defined by boundaries of administrative areas (parishes): 
Submarket 1 (Suburban: São Bernardo, Aradas and Santa Joana); Submarket 2 
(Esgueira); Submarket 3 (Glória); and Submarket 4 (Vera Cruz). The final two are 
the most central areas encompassing the CBD of Aveiro, Glória being mostly 
residential while Vera Cruz caters to both the residential and service sector. 
Esgueira is partly urban and partly suburban. The estimated hedonic models 
reported in Table 4 are parsimonious and offer good scope for interpretation, both 
in terms of individual coefficients and their variation across the submarkets. The 
variation in price elasticity of housing space and shadow prices of the factors capture 
our notion of spatial heterogeneity. 
In the aggregate model, the explained variation (in terms of adjusted R 
2 ) is 
quite high and all the regressors are highly significant, with the exception of 
factor 2. The signs of the coefficients agree with a priori expectations. The price per 
square meter decreases with distance to CBD (factor 1) and increases with factor 4 
(housing space) and factor 5 (size of living room and kitchen and provision for 
garage). The negative coefficient on factor 3 implies a single unit housing is 
preferable even if it implies absence of cable TV or gas infrastructure; the relatively 
low shadow price of this factor conceals heterogeneity across submarkets. 
Substantial spatial heterogeneity is observed across the four submarkets in terms 
of shadow prices for different factors related to physical and location characteristics, 
as well as the price elasticity of total area. Analysis by submarkets shows important 
differences in the explanatory factors across the different parts of the city. 
Importantly, there is a substantial contrast between Vera Cruz and the other areas, 
showing that the traditional core of the city has a distinctive housing market. The </p>

<p>Table 4. Estimated factor based hedonic model with heterogeneity (urban scale) </p>

<p>Aggregate model Submarket 1 Submarket 2 Submarket 3 Submarket 4 
Explanatory variables 
(All submarkets) 
(Suburban) 
(Esgueira) 
(Glória) 
(Vera Cruz) </p>

<p>Intercept 
11.49 
12.05 
10.22 
10.64 
11.34 
(28.64) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(10.90) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(11.18) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(13.93) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(11.43) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Log total area 
(0.94 
(1.05 
(0.70 
(0.71 
(0.90 
((10.93) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((4.66) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((3.51) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((4.39) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((4.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 1 
(0.06 
(0.03 
0.01 
0.09 
(0.23 
(Access to city centre) 
((3.76) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((0.59) 
(0.18) 
((1.58) 
((1.36) 
Factor 2 
(0.00 
(0.03 
(0.06 
(0.06 
0.26 
(Access to local amenities) 
((0.13) 
((0.77) 
((1.23) 
((1.22) 
(1.49) 
Factor 3 
(0.05 
(0.09 
(0.07 
(0.03 
0.02 
(Type of dwelling) 
((3.17) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((2.14) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((2.17) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((0.83) 
(0.31) 
Factor 4 
0.20 
0.26 
0.05 
0.16 
0.16 
(Housing space) 
(6.49) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(2.25) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((0.52) 
(2.68) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(1.63) 
Factor 5 
0.21 
0.26 
0.27 
0.15 
0.19 
(Additional desirable features) 
(10.92) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(4.49) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(8.79) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(4.57) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(3.65) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Number of observations 
166 
42 
42 
27 
55 
Adjusted R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.583 
0.587 
0.736 
0.587 
0.332 </p>

<p>Notes: t-statistics in parentheses; 
+++ significant at the 1% level, </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% </p>

<p>level. </p>



<p>estimates indicate that the elasticity of housing space is strongest in Glória and 
Esgueira, and weaker in Vera Cruz and the suburban area. 
While they are not statistically significant in any submarket, 
17 access to both the 
centre and to local amenities is valued relatively highly in Vera Cruz. The significant 
negative coefficient for factor 3 for the suburban area and Esgueira implies that 
detached houses are more valued even if they lack infrastructures facilities (like cable 
TV or gas); for the more central Vera Cruz and Glória such an effect is not observed. 
The effect of factor 4 is the most heterogeneous across the submarkets, indicating 
that the importance ascribed to the number of rooms differs from area to area. The 
additional desirable features (factor 5, representing living room and kitchen area and 
the provision for a garage) attracts similar premium in all four submarkets. 
We evaluated forecast performance of the various models by cross-validation 
analysis, that is, by comparing each observation against the predicted value based on 
leave-one-out sample estimates omitting the index dwelling. In line with 
arguments in Malpezzi (2003), our factor-based model generated better predictions 
compared to a model with a full set of hedonic characteristics. Based on the 118 
houses with full data, the estimated factor hedonic model without imputed factors 
has a cross-validation mean squared error (MSE) that is 16% lower than that of a 
model with full hedonics included. The cross-validation MSE using predicted 
factors is 30% higher, but based on a substantially larger sample of 166 observations. 
On the whole, the factor-based hedonic model has good predictive performance. </p>

<p>3.4. Spatial Interaction * Distance and Contiguity Based Spatial Weights </p>

<p>We now turn to an examination of spatial interaction between submarkets. First, 
we take the standard approach in spatial econometrics by constructing spatial 
weights based on distances and contiguity. Before estimating the hedonic price 
models with spatial effects, we explore whether properties with similar square 
meter prices were more spatially clustered than normally expected, using Moran's 
I test. This test statistic for the presence of spatial dependence is: </p>

<p>I ¼ 
n </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P 
j w ij ðx i À lÞðx j À lÞ 
P 
i ðx i À lÞ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; 
(5) </p>

<p>where n is the number of observations; x i and x j denote the observed prices (t/m 
2 ) 
at locations i and j, respectively; m denotes the mean price; w ij the (i, j)-th element 
of the spatial weights matrix W, and S denotes the sum of all spatial weights: 
S ¼ 
P </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>P 
j w ij : 
The above statistic is often used to analyse global spatial autocorrelation and is 
known to depend strongly on the assumed specification of the spatial weights 
matrix (Anselin, 1995). However, as discussed above, the choice of spatial weights 
in applications is often arbitrary and determined subjectively by the researcher, and 
there is usually very little formal evidence supporting such choice (Anselin, 2002). 
To ensure robustness with regard to choice of the spatial weights matrix, we 
explored several specifications: binary weights based on distances between houses 
ranging from within 100, 500, 1,000, 1,500, 3,000 and 5,000 meters, as well as 
rook and queen contiguity. Table 5 reports the estimated Moran's I statistic 
18 for 
these seven different specifications. Results for contiguity are visually illustrated in 
Figure 2. The four quadrants in the figure provide a classification of different types 
of spatial autocorrelation: highÁhigh (upper right) or lowÁlow (lower left) for </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 151 </p>

<p>positive spatial autocorrelation; and highÁlow (lower right) or lowÁhigh (upper 
left), for negative spatial autocorrelation. Positive spatial autocorrelation implies 
that a high (low) value in the current location is surrounded by high (low) values in 
neighbouring observations. The slope of the best-fitting regression line is Moran's I 
statistic (Anselin, 2005). While Moran's I index is useful for detecting the presence 
of spatial autocorrelation, it does not indicate the precise structure of spatial 
interactions (Anselin, 2005). 
Based on the above measures of contiguity or distance, Moran's statistics tend to 
be positive but are not significant, showing little evidence of spatial autocorrelation 
in housing prices. Taking this evidence on face value, we would be tempted to 
conclude that geographically adjacent observations have little or no influence on 
house prices*a rather unsatisfactory observation. 
Next, we used the <rs id="software-5" type="software">GEODA</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Anselin</rs>, 2005; Anselin et al., 2006) to 
perform a series of Lagrange Multipliers (LM) tests (Anselin, 2005) for both spatial 
lag dependence and spatial error dependence. Specifically, in addition to OLS, we 
estimated by maximum likelihood (ML) alternative spatial regression models and 
investigated whether a spatial error or a spatial lag model, or indeed a model </p>

<p>Table 5. Moran's I test for seven weighting matrices </p>

<p>Distances 
Square meter price (t/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>d100 
0.1669 
d500 
0.0952 
d1,000 
0.0954 
d1,500 
0.1001 
d3,000 
(0.0533 
d5,000 
0.2263 
Queen/Rook 
0.1032 </p>

<p>Figure 2. Moran scatter plot for residuals (contiguity weight matrix). 
Source: Results were produced using <rs id="software-6" type="software">GEODA</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Anselin</rs>, 2005). </p>



<p>without spatial effects, best fit the data. We report the results for a spatial weights 
matrix based on rook and queen contiguity in Table 6; results for other 
specifications of spatial weights are similar. 
Like Moran's I statistics, we find no evidence of spatial dependence. This is 
despite the fact that we have not accounted for spatial heterogeneity in these 
estimates*a feature that can contribute to spatial dependence. The Lagrange 
Multiplier (LM) test statistics are significant neither for the spatial error (p-value 0.41) 
nor the spatial lag (p-value 0.77) models. The null hypothesis of both tests, which is 
the lack of spatial dependence, cannot be rejected at the 5% significance level. 
Therefore, spatial dependence is either absent or not related to the geographical 
notions of distances and contiguity considered in the above seven specifications. 
This highlights an important limitation of spatial econometric methods for studying 
hedonic pricing models, arising from the treatment of spatial dependence as the 
outcome of spillover processes which are dependent on previously fixed and 
arbitrary spatial weights matrices (see also Giacomini &amp; Granger, 2004). In other 
words, such evidence may have generated from ill-specified definitions of spatial 
weights, which is an issue we will investigate further in this paper. </p>

<p>3.5. Estimated Spatial Weights Matrix </p>

<p>As discussed before, this paper extends an emerging area of research that takes a 
more general view of the nature and strength of spatial diffusion and cross-section 
interaction. Moving away from the usual practice of ex ante definition of spatial 
interactions, we estimate the unknown spatial weights matrix that is consistent with 
an observed pattern of spatial dependence and is therefore suitable for interpreta-
tion. Specifically, as proposed in Section 2, we use an extension of the 
Bhattacharjee &amp; Jensen-Butler (2011) estimator to the pure cross-section setting </p>

<p>Table 6. No spatial dependence, spatial lag and spatial error dependence estimates </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>No spatial 
dependence 
(OLS estimation) </p>

<p>Spatial lag model 
(ML estimation) </p>

<p>Spatial error model 
(ML estimation) </p>

<p>Intercept 
11.49 (28.64) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>11.31 (14.66) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>11.55 (29.28) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Log total area 
(0.94 ((10.93) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.94 ((11.18) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.95 ((11.26) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 1 
(0.06 ((3.76) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.06 ((3.28) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.06 ((3.42) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 2 
(0.00 ((0.13) 
(0.00 ((0.17) 
(0.00 ((0.13) 
Factor 3 
(0.05 ((3.17) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.05 ((3.18) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.05 ((3.08) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 4 
0.20 (6.49) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.20 (6.66) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.21 (6.60) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 5 
0.21 (10.92) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.21 (11.06) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.22 (11.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Lagrange multiplier (lag) 
0.08 (p-value 0.77) 
Robust LM (lag) 
0.27 (p-value 0.61) 
Lagrange multiplier (error) 
0.67 (p-value 0.41) 
Robust LM (error) 
0.86 (p-value 0.35) 
Lagrange multiplier 
0.94 (p-value 0.63) 
Number of observations 
166 
166 
166 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.598 
0.598 
0.600 
Log likelihood 
20.404 
20.442 
20.753 
Lag coefficient (r) 
0.026 (p-value 0.78) 
Lag coefficient (l) 
0.109 (p-value 0.37) </p>

<p>Notes: t-/z-statistics in parentheses; </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>significant at the 
10% level. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 153 </p>

<p>and obtain estimates of a symmetric spatial weights matrix under a spatial error 
model. The symmetry assumption adopted in this work is in line with the 
traditional practice in housing studies, and is a natural consequence of defining 
spatial weights based on distances. 
The first step is to estimate the spatial autocovariance matrix of residuals across 
the four submarkets. As discussed in Section 2, we use residuals across the four 
submarkets, matched by factors, to construct the cross-submarket error spatial 
autocovariance and autocorrelation matrix (Table 7). In contrast to the results 
above based on a priori fixed spatial weights, significant spatial autocorrelation can 
be observed between some submarkets. 
Table 8 reports the corresponding estimated symmetric spatial weights matrix 
for cross-submarket interactions. Results are consistent with the spatial structure of 
Aveiro, showing that Vera Cruz has a highly significant negative interaction with 
the suburban area, while Glória has a highly significant positive interaction with 
both the suburban area and Esgueira. 
These observations can be explained by the urban geography of Aveiro. Vera 
Cruz represents a distinct housing market in the CBD of Aveiro and draws its 
housing demand from a population quite different from the inhabitants in large 
detached houses in the suburban area. Such segmented markets imply that negative 
spatial interactions are likely between these two submarkets. On the other hand, 
Glória and Esgueira are largely residential submarkets close to the centre and are 
likely to offer positive spillovers; the same is true for Glória and the suburban area 
which are contiguous submarkets. 
However, the best test for how these spatial weights relate to the urban housing 
market in Aveiro would come from spatial econometric models based on these, to 
which we turn next. </p>

<p>3.6. Spatial Models with Estimated Spatial Weights Matrix </p>

<p>Finally, we estimate the within-submarket spatial weight v 0 and test the validity of 
the spatial error model with the spatial weights matrix estimated as above. The </p>

<p>Table 7. Cross-submarket spatial error autocovariance and autocorrelation matrix 
(variances reported on the diagonal, autocorrelations below diagonal) </p>

<p>Submarkets 
1 (Suburb) 
2 (Esgueira) 
3 (Glória) 
4 (Vera Cruz) </p>

<p>1 (Suburb) 
0.057 
2 (Esgueira) 
(0.042 
0.033 
3 (Gló ria) 
0.085 
0.142 
0.050 
4 (Vera Cruz) 
(0.150 
0.031 
(0.079 
0.045 </p>

<p>Table 8. Cross-submarket estimated symmetric spatial interaction matrix </p>

<p>Submarkets 
1 (Suburb) 
2 (Esgueira) 
3 (Glória) 
4 (Vera Cruz) </p>

<p>1 (Suburb) 
0.00 
2 (Esgueira) 
(0.024 
0.00 
3 (Gló ria) 
0.041 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.074 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 
4 (Vera Cruz) 
(0.072 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.017 
(0.037 
0.00 </p>

<p>Notes: 
+++ Significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% level. </p>



<p>estimates for the factor-based hedonic model (Table 9) and for a corresponding 
model based on selected hedonic characteristics (Table 10) are reported below. 
The factor-based model provides inferences on spatial heterogeneity that fall 
along the lines of the results discussed above. As expected, the estimated within-
submarket spatial weight,x 0 00.345, is much larger than any of the estimated 
cross-submarket spatial weights. With the corresponding estimated spatial weights 
matrixŴ , the data support spatial dependence through the spatial error model, but 
evidence in favour of the spatial lag model is not statistically significant. This 
inference is markedly different from the previous case where contiguity and 
distance based spatial weights were used. </p>

<p>Table 9. Estimated factor based hedonic spatial dependence models </p>

<p>Variables 
Spatial error model 
Spatial lag model </p>

<p>Intercept 
10.9248 (31.10) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>11.4615 (6.94) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Total area (in logarithms) 
(0.8128 ((10.85) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.8510 ((9.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 1 
(Access to city centre) 
)Suburban 
(0.0527 ((1.20) 
(0.0478 ((1.18) 
)Esgueira 
(0.1142 ((3.14) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.1072 ((2.09) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
(0.0581 ((1.46) 
(0.0230 ((0.50) 
)Vera Cruz 
(0.2695 ((2.38) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(0.2596 ((1.95) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>Factor 2 
(Access to local amenities) 
)Suburban 
(0.0204 ((0.74) 
(0.0211 ((0.86) 
)Esgueira 
(0.0077 ((0.18) 
(0.0141 ((0.27) 
)Glória 
(0.0076 ((0.15) 
(0.0253 ((0.48) 
)Vera Cruz 
0.2846 (2.20) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.2716 (1.96) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>Factor 3 
(Type of dwelling) 
)Suburban 
(0.0831 ((1.93) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>(0.0834 ((2.48) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>)Esgueira 
(0.0684 ((2.09) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(0.0675 ((1.77) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>)Glória 
(0.0111 ((0.27) 
(0.0135 ((0.33) 
)Vera Cruz 
0.0309 (0.65) 
0.0275 (0.53) </p>

<p>Factor 4 
(Housing space) 
)Suburban 
0.1756 (3.69) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1876 (3.67) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Esgueira 
0.0625 (1.26) 
0.0809 (1.37) 
)Glória 
0.1736 (3.93) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1898 (4.02) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Vera Cruz 
0.1307 (2.51) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1458 (2.46) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>Factor 5 
(Additional desirable features) 
)Suburban 
0.2379 (4.22) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.2409 (5.40) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Esgueira 
0.2791 (9.05) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.2796 (7.78) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
0.1782 (5.54) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1773 (5.46) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Vera Cruz 
0.1749 (5.44) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1815 (5.14) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Intra-market spatial weight, v 0 
0.345 (6.95) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.345 (6.95) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Spat. err. autoregression, l 
(15.7176 ((6.01) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>r 0(0.0500 ((0.23) 
Number of observations 
166 
166 
Wald (LR) test*no spatial effect 
36.08 
+++ (24.72 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) 
0.051 (0.052) 
Reg. test (spat. lag): r 00 
t 00.03 </p>

<p>Notes: z-statistics in parentheses; 
+++ significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% </p>

<p>level. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 155 </p>

<p>Furthermore, once spatial interaction through the spatial error model is 
accounted for, the Born &amp; Breitung (2011) regression test fails to reject the null 
hypothesis of no spatial lag. Thus, the spatial error model is appropriate for this 
application. This observation has important implications for inference and 
interpretation of spatial dependence in this application. 
In particular, it would appear that the cost of not accounting for spatial 
dependence lies mainly in efficiency. Predictions using the spatial model provide a 
cross-validation MSE that is 11% lower than the OLS hedonic factor-based model 
with full spatial heterogeneity. This suggests substantial efficiency gains in terms of 
prediction. </p>

<p>Table 10. Estimated hedonic spatial models using housing characteristics </p>

<p>Variables 
Spatial error model 
Spatial lag model </p>

<p>Intercept 
9.9553 (13.97) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>42.1409 (3.58) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Total area (in logarithms) 
(0.7703 ((10.03) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.6850 ((9.08) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 1 
(Log*distance from CBD) 
)Suburban 
0.0099 (0.11) 
(0.0581 ((0.80) 
)Esgueira 
(0.1039 ((1.56) 
(0.1863 ((2.55) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
(0.1091 ((1.09) 
(0.1288 ((1.85) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>)Vera Cruz 
(0.0276 ((0.35) 
0.0657 (0.99) </p>

<p>Factor 2 
(Log*distance from superstore) 
)Suburban 
(0.0342 ((0.61) 
(0.0086 ((0.19) 
)Esgueira 
0.0447 (0.72) 
(0.0007 ((0.01) 
)Glória 
0.0872 (1.25) 
0.0788 (1.39) 
)Vera Cruz 
(0.0140 ((0.29) 
(0.0137 ((0.30) </p>

<p>Factor 3 
(Dummy*house, not flat) 
)Suburban 
0.3884 (3.71) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.3395 (4.18) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Esgueira 
0.5792 (6.07) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.5724 (6.62) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
0.3772 (1.41) 
0.3139 (1.48) 
)Vera Cruz 
0.4568 (3.87) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.4659 (4.07) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 4 
(Number of bedrooms) 
)Suburban 
0.0827 (1.16) 
0.0773 (1.39) 
)Esgueira 
0.1503 (2.91) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1352 (2.72) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
0.1947 (4.05) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1670 (3.72) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Vera Cruz 
0.2093 (4.99) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1948 (4.75) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 5 
(Dummy*provision for garage) 
)Suburban 
0.2512 (2.83) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.2119 (3.08) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Esgueira 
0.2179 (3.46) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1828 (2.84) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Glória 
0.3698 (3.53) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.3317 (4.06) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>)Vera Cruz 
0.2089 (2.75) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.1643 (2.26) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>Intra-market spatial weight, v 0 
0.472 (3.69) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.472 (3.69) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Spat. err. autoregression, l 
(16.5915 ((5.29) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>r 0(4.5554 ((2.74) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Number of observations 
166 
166 
Wald (LR) test*no spatial effect 
28.02 
+++ (25.02 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) 
7.52 
+++ (11.00 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>) 
Reg. test (spat. lag): r 00 
t 00.00 </p>

<p>Notes: z-statistics in parentheses; 
+++ significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% </p>

<p>level. </p>



<p>Inferences were largely similar when selected hedonic characteristics were used. 
In this case, both the spatial error model and the spatial lag model were individually 
supported by the data. However, the Born &amp; Breitung (2011) regression test fails to 
reject the null hypothesis that there is no spatial lag evidence after spatial error 
dependence is accounted for. 
Overall, our analysis points to important benefits in terms of understanding the 
spatial structure of the housing market in Aveiro at a finer urban scale. Both issues 
relating to spatial heterogeneity and spatial interactions are prominent in the urban 
submarkets defined by administrative boundaries. The empirical analysis provides 
an illustration of the proposed framework and methods for understanding spatial 
heterogeneity and dependence. In particular, whereas traditional measures of spatial 
weights based on distance or contiguity support the counterintuitive impression of 
insignificant spatial dependence, the estimated spatial weights matrix is useful for 
modelling interactions and spillovers more appropriately. The sample size was 
somewhat limited, but provided the opportunity for ML estimation of spatial 
econometric models. 
However, some inferences from our analysis are weak, particularly those related 
to factors representing access and centrality. On the one hand, coefficients are not 
significant in most cases (see Tables 4 and 9); on the other hand, the restriction of 
the analysis to a limited number of parishes does not provide a general 
understanding of the housing market of Aveiro and its connection with the 
spatially heterogeneous social and economic conditions. 
The consideration of the urban agglomeration corresponding to the munici-
palities of Aveiro and Ílhavo is more in line with the concept of metropolitan area 
discussed in Malpezzi (2003). Hence, following arguments in Maclennan &amp; Tu  (1996), we extend our analysis to a broader spatial scale, using submarkets 
segregated by location, housing quality and income levels. </p>

<p>4. Analysis at the Peri-urban Scale </p>

<p>Now, we extend our analysis to the housing market of the peri-urban area 
combining the municipalities of Aveiro and Ílhavo and the surrounding areas, using 
data for several years. This dataset covers a more heterogeneous area with more 
submarkets which, in addition to providing inferences on spatial dependence, 
enables a richer interpretation of the interaction pattern and of its underlying drivers. 
Seven submarkets were selected, using a combination of criteria in line with 
Maclennan &amp; Tu (1996) and Malpezzi (2003): administrative boundaries, urban 
structure, demographic features and history of urban development. Spatial 
contiguity of submarkets was generally preserved, but not always. 
19 A short 
description of the selected submarkets is as follows (see Figure 3). </p>

<p>. Aveiro inner city: the core of Aveiro city, including the administrative and 
service centre, as well as high density housing. This area has a higher 
concentration of more affluent residents. 
. City of I´lhavo: the administrative centre of a separate municipality, 
corresponding to the second centre of the urban agglomeration of Aveiro. 
. Gafanhas: a mixture of residential and industrial areas, including the most 
important port of Centro Region; the residential market combines older and 
consolidated settlements with detached houses spread in semi-urban areas, </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 157 </p>

<p>with a marked predominance of working class and lower middle class 
residents. 
. Beaches: an area with a high population density, corresponding to a strip of 
land stretching between the sea and the lagoon; most houses are either 
second residences or used for rent in the high season. 
. Suburban Type A: a group of small areas not very far away from Aveiro inner 
city. New planned residential areas dominate, being either blocks of flats or 
clusters of detached houses; these areas attract people from the Aveiro inner 
city looking for more affordable housing. Traditional social groups of people 
owning a small agricultural property and working either in manufacturing or 
in low skill service jobs have been gradually substituted by the above urban 
inhabitants. 
. Suburban Type B: a combination of isolated new houses or blocks, typical of 
Suburban Type A, with old rural settlements; the proportion of urban 
incomers, relative to traditional social groups, is lower than in Suburban 
Type A. 
. Suburban Type C: similar to Suburban Type B but with a higher proportion 
of old rural settlements and traditional social groups. </p>

<p>The database used was provided by the biggest real estate agency of Portugal 
(Casa Sapo/Janela Digital) and includes a set of hedonic and location characteristics 
similar to, but less detailed than, those presented in Section 3. However it covers all 
the municipalities of Aveiro and Ílhavo and includes a much larger number of cases 
(12,467 dwellings) sold over a time span of about 10 years (October 2000ÁMarch  2010). </p>

<p>Aveiro 
inner city 
B e a c h e s </p>

<p>B e a c h e s </p>

<p>Suburban Type A </p>

<p>City of 
Ílhavo </p>

<p>Legend </p>

<p>Lagoon </p>

<p>Suburban Type B </p>

<p>Suburban Type C 
Gafanhas </p>

<p>Figure 3. Housing submarkets for AveiroÁÍlhavo at the peri-urban spatial scale. </p>



<p>An important difference relative to Section 3 is that the price data here refer to 
listing prices, rather than selling prices. We compensate for the wedge between 
listing and selling prices by including in our regressions the logarithm of time on 
the market (in days). In addition, we include time (yearly) fixed effects to control 
for aggregate cyclical and political factors. 
Similar to the analysis presented in Section 3, GIS tools were used to compute 
the proximity of each house to a number of central and local amenities. The 
variables and descriptive statistics are reported in Table 11. 
Following an identical methodology, we use maximum likelihood factor 
analysis with orthogonal varimax rotation. Following the arguments in Davies  (1974) and Maclennan (1977), we verify that the resulting five leading factors align 
well with housing characteristics related to behavioural patterns (Table 12). The 
factors are as follows: </p>

<p>. Factor 1: access to the centre or to central amenities. 
. Factor 2: access to local services and amenities (health centres, parks/gardens, 
etc.), also implying proximity to the traditional local centres within the area 
under study. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>. Factor 3: access to beaches, schools and local commerce. 
. Factor 4: housing space. 
. Factor 5: additional facilities (garage, balcony, central heating, etc.). </p>

<p>The estimated hedonic model with spatial heterogeneity based on factors is 
reported in Table 13. The results show substantial heterogeneity across the 
submarkets. Several important observations follow. 
First, Beaches is quite a distinct housing market from the others, in terms of 
estimated factor prices that are very different from the rest of the submarkets. 
Second, and in particular, the price elasticity of house area is the least for Beaches 
(0.129) and highest for the inner city of Aveiro (0.429). This implies that the size of 
houses designed for holidays and weekend purposes is not particularly valued, while 
the demand in the most affluent area (CBD of Aveiro) is considerably more 
sensitive to size. 
Third, while the general model shows that prices increase with access to the 
city centre, there is large variation across the different submarkets. In the CBD of 
Aveiro or suburban areas close to the city, the negative value attached to poor 
access to the city centre is highly significant, while access is most valuable in 
Beaches, which is the submarket located farthest from the centre. The same does 
not apply for the more remote Suburban Type C or submarkets such as Ílhavo or 
Gafanhas. This is explained by the different social profiles of inhabitants in these 
areas. 
Fourth, access to local facilities has a heterogeneous effect on prices. However, 
by contrast to access to the centre, it is valued significantly, with the expected signs, 
only in Suburban Type A, B and C submarkets. This means that proximity to local 
centres is valued in the suburban areas, but not in CBD Aveiro, and even negatively 
valued in Ílhavo and Gafanhas. This is because local centres in the more urbanized 
locations tend to produce negative externalities such as noise or lack of parking 
space, while in the suburban areas they tend to be associated with better urban 
layouts and access to local amenities, different from that of unqualified suburban 
sprawl. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 159 </p>

<p>Table 11. Descriptive statistics of variables, peri-urban scale (N012,467) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Units of 
measurement 
Minimum Maximum Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Internal physical characteristics </p>

<p>d 
Type 
(Single unit 01, 
Flat 00) </p>

<p>0.00 
1.00 
0.28 
0.45 </p>

<p>ln 
Number of bedrooms 
(Number) 
0.00 
2.48 
1.23 
0.33 
d 
Duplex 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.12 
0.33 
d 
Build and age: new building 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.31 
0.46 
d 
Build and age: under 
construction </p>

<p>(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.25 
0.43 </p>

<p>d 
Build and age: restored 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.06 
d 
Build and age: used building, less 
than 10 years </p>

<p>(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.34 
0.47 </p>

<p>d 
Build and age: used building, 10Á 
25 years </p>

<p>(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.08 
0.27 </p>

<p>d 
Build and age: used building, 
more than 25 years </p>

<p>(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.01 
0.11 </p>

<p>d 
Build and age: not restored 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.00 
0.03 
ln 
Price 
(Euros/m 
2 ) 
5.18 
8.65 
6.98 
0.32 
ln 
Total area 
(m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
3.00 
6.40 
4.88 
0.48 
ln 
Time on the market (TOM) 
(Days) 
0.00 
7.76 
5.00 
1.64 
d 
Balcony 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.39 
0.49 
d 
Terrace 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.18 
0.39 
d 
Provision for garage 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.16 
0.37 
d 
Garage 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.64 
0.48 
d 
Central heating 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.43 
0.50 
d 
Fireplace 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.29 
0.45 </p>

<p>Location characteristics </p>

<p>ln 
Central amenities 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.42 
11.97 
8.02 
0.83 
ln 
Local amenities 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.04 
11.95 
7.33 
0.63 
ln 
CBD Aveiro 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.23 
11.98 
8.08 
0.80 
ln 
Local commerce 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
4.07 
9.16 
6.58 
1.15 
ln 
Primary schools 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
3.65 
7.59 
5.60 
0.83 
ln 
Intermediate schools 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
4.38 
8.80 
6.57 
1.01 
ln 
University 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.46 
9.38 
8.12 
0.63 
ln 
Hospital 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.39 
9.34 
7.84 
0.88 
ln 
Health centres 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
4.78 
9.16 
7.15 
0.87 
ln 
Pharmacies 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
3.60 
8.61 
5.99 
0.95 
ln 
Parks and gardens 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
3.97 
8.84 
7.04 
0.95 
ln 
Rail station 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
4.41 
9.22 
7.55 
0.99 
ln 
Access node 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.96 
8.62 
7.47 
0.54 
ln 
Gas station 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
3.37 
8.79 
6.53 
0.96 
ln 
Police 
(Min. dist.-meters) 
5.39 
11.97 
7.84 
0.81 
p 
Administration 
(Potential) 
2.02 
8.71 
6.28 
1.10 
p 
Culture 
(Potential) 
5.24 
8.05 
6.46 
0.69 
p 
Specialised commerce 
(Potential) 
5.31 
8.50 
6.59 
0.72 
p 
Restaurants 
(Potential) 
6.92 
10.12 
8.44 
0.64 
p 
Hotels and hostels 
(Potential) 
5.79 
9.41 
7.25 
0.69 
p 
Monuments 
(Potential) 
7.37 
9.90 
8.35 
0.45 
p 
Banks, ATMs, Post 
(Potential) 
6.64 
9.80 
8.41 
0.68 
p 
Sports 
(Potential) 
6.39 
8.54 
7.53 
0.44 
d 
Sea/beaches 
(Yes 01; No00) 
0.00 
1.00 
0.07 
0.25 </p>

<p>Notes: d 0dummy variable; ln0in logarithms; p 0gravitational potential. </p>



<p>Fifth, additional facilities such as garage, balcony and central heating are 
positively valued with high significance everywhere, except in Beaches, where such 
attributes do not matter. Finally, living space is positively valued, and in largely 
equal measure, across all seven submarkets. 
In general, spatial heterogeneity is in line with the urban geography of Aveiro 
and reflects the dynamics of urban development, and its analysis is important for 
understanding the spatial nature of the urban housing market and to provide 
guidelines for urban planning and housing policy. The unique character of the 
housing submarket in Beaches is related to its evolution as the destination for 
second homes and rental properties for holiday makers. Likewise, the high price 
elasticity for house area in the centre of Aveiro reflects scarcity rents. In turn, this 
shortage of housing space in the centre has led to migration from the city to the 
suburban areas, which have a larger price sensitivity to access. It would thus appear </p>

<p>Table 12. Factor loadings at peri-urban scale, varimax rotated (absolute value!3.5) </p>

<p>Factor 1 
Factor 2 
Factor 3 
Factor 4 
Factor 5 </p>

<p>Location attributes </p>

<p>Centrality, central amenities 
0.913 
CBD Aveiro 
0.907 
Hospital 
0.853 
University 
0.851 
0.368 
Police 
0.818 
Railway station 
0.646 
0.521 
Access node 
0.460 
Restaurants 
(0.702 
0.548 
Culture 
(0.752 
Sports 
(0.819 
(0.376 
Hotels and hostels 
(0.844 
0.443 
Monuments 
(0.889 
Specialised commerce 
(0.924 
Health centres 
0.878 
Parks and gardens 
0.858 
Gas station 
0.432 
0.520 
Intermediate schools 
0.494 
0.518 
Pharmacies 
0.363 
0.399 
Administration 
(0.563 
(0.601 
Banks, ATMs, Post 
(0.421 
(0.759 
Sea/beaches 
0.849 
Primary schools 
0.373 
0.690 
Local commerce 
0.390 
(0.785 </p>

<p>Physical attributes </p>

<p>Total area 
0.815 
Type (Single unit 01; Flat 00) 
0.353 
0.759 
Number of rooms 
0.753 
Build and age: used building, less than 10 years 
(0.446 
Garage 
0.779 
Balcony 
0.614 
Central heating 
0.575 
Fireplace 
0.458 
Provision for garage 
0.427 </p>

<p>Percentage of variance explained 
25.02% 
10.10% 
8.03% 
5.88% 
4.91% </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 161 </p>

<p>Table 13. Estimated factor based hedonic model with heterogeneity (peri-urban spatial scale) </p>

<p>Variables 
Aggregate model 
CBD Aveiro 
CBD Ílhavo 
Gafanhas 
Suburban Type A Suburban Type B Suburban Type C 
Beaches </p>

<p>Intercept 
9.890 
9.786 
10.638 
10.560 
10.567 
10.016 
10.375 
15.122 
(236.87) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(101.66) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(55.36) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(72.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(86.53) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(115.73) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(89.63) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((16.56) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Log total area 
(0.598 
(0.571 
(0.685 
(0.761 
(0.762 
(0.614 
(0.693 
(0.871 
((70.79) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((30.14) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((22.20) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((29.30) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((29.83) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((34.61) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((29.28) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((25.66) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Log time on the 
0.005 
0.006 
0.016 
0.003 
0.011 
0.004 
(0.003 
(0.007 
market 
(3.69) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(2.10) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(3.99) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.98) 
(3.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(1.30) 
((0.90) 
((1.53) 
Factor 1 
(0.043 
(0.036 
(0.164 
0.099 
(0.144 
(0.025 
0.001 
(1.761 
(Access to city centre) 
((19.77) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((3.65) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((1.57) 
(2.29) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((6.34) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((2.27) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(0.13) 
((4.46) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 2 
0.027 
0.010 
0.180 
0.042 
(0.079 
(0.098 
(0.029 
(0.146 
(Access to local 
amenities) </p>

<p>(14.65) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.97) 
(6.19) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(2.04) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((7.06) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((7.58) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((2.17) </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>((0.84) </p>

<p>Factor 3 
0.077 
(0.016 
(0.214 
0.015 
(0.120 
(0.016 
(0.005 
(0.745 
(Access to beaches) 
(38.21) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((1.62) 
((2.78) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.32) 
((4.31) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((1.29) 
((0.51) 
((5.48) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 4 
0.154 
0.199 
0.217 
0.209 
0.242 
0.162 
0.171 
0.211 
(Housing space) 
(40.12) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(19.51) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(15.64) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(21.25) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(20.65) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(20.01) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(15.60) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(7.34) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>Factor 5 
0.043 
0.061 
0.044 
0.028 
0.038 
0.025 
0.019 
(0.002 
(Additional facilities) 
(21.34) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(15.13) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(6.17) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(5.15) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(7.21) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(5.92) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(3.28) </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>((0.09) 
Time fixed effects 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
Number of obs. 
12,467 
3,296 
1,188 
1,765 
1,421 
2,480 
1,512 
805 
Adjusted R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.572 
0.359 
0.459 
0.483 
0.557 
0.498 
0.484 
0.557 </p>

<p>Notes: t-statistics in parentheses; </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% level. </p>

<p>162 A. Bhattacharjee et al. </p>

<p>that further development of quality housing and good local amenities and access to 
the centre would make the suburban areas both affordable and desirable for the 
urban population. 
The spatial structure of the urban agglomeration of Aveiro is also prominent in 
the analysis of spatial interaction based on the estimated cross-submarket symmetric 
spatial weights matrix (Table 14). The first striking conclusion is that spatial 
interaction is significant for 17 out of 21 cells of the matrix. The main drivers of 
spatial interactions are common patterns of response to stochastic shocks; if for 
example, houses with particular characteristics become preferable for given social 
groups, we expect to obtain positive interactions between places with similar social 
structures and negative interactions for places where contrasted social groups 
dominate. Positive interactions between submarkets are also related to spillovers 
between these areas in unobservable housing characteristics, which in turn are 
prominent for areas contiguous in geographical location. Further, housing 
preferences similar across all submarkets are expected to generate an overall pattern 
of positive interaction. 
As expected, contiguity or distance explains a number of the significant positive 
spatial weights across submarkets in Aveiro. These include: spatial weights between 
Beaches, Gafanhas and Suburban Type C; and between Suburban Type A and 
Suburban Type C on the one hand and CBD Aveiro, CBD Ílhavo and Suburban 
Type B on the other. 
However, the spatial weights between some pairs of contiguous regions are not 
statistically significant or even negative (for example, between CBD Aveiro and 
Suburban Type B), and some other significant weights relate to non-contiguous 
regions. In other words, many significant spatial weights appear to be driven by 
reasons other than geographic distance or contiguity. Specifically, for some of these 
submarkets positive spillovers appear to be related to a combination of the coreÁ 
periphery relationship and socio-cultural factors. Examples include: CBD Aveiro 
and CBD Ílhavo; Beaches and CBD Aveiro; and CBD Ílhavo and Gafanhas. 
Finally, Table 14 indicates significant negative spatial interactions between 
CBD Aveiro and Suburban Type B, and between Suburban Type A and Suburban 
Type C. Apparently, both of these are related to market segmentation, where each 
submarket is attractive to different population groups. </p>

<p>Table 14. Estimated symmetric spatial interaction matrix (peri-urban spatial scale) </p>

<p>Submarkets </p>

<p>CBD 
Aveiro </p>

<p>CBD 
Ílhavo 
Gafanhas </p>

<p>Suburban 
Type A </p>

<p>Suburban 
Type B </p>

<p>Suburban 
Type C 
Beaches </p>

<p>CBD Aveiro 
0.00 
CBD Ílhavo 
0.0231 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.00 
Gafanhas 
(0.0089 
0.0521 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 
Suburban 
Type A </p>

<p>0.0415 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0495 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>(0.0725 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Suburban 
Type B </p>

<p>(0.0190 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0047 
(0.0404 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0189 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Suburban 
Type C </p>

<p>0.0227 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0984 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0263 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>(0.0309 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.0427 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Beaches 
0.0674 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.0012 
0.0328 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.0062 
0.0274 </p>

<p>++ </p>

<p>0.0406 </p>

<p>+++ </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>Notes: 
+++ Significant at the 1% level, 
++ significant at the 5% level, 
+ significant at the 10% level. </p>

<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 163 </p>

<p>Admittedly, some of the above explanations are tentative, and would require 
further research to confirm and interpret. These developments are beyond the 
scope of the paper. However, what we clearly show is that the spatial weights 
matrix, estimated using our methodology, combined with the analysis of spatial 
heterogeneity, provides a very rich set of information which can be the basis for 
detailed analysis and for the disclosing of the causes underlying the observed spatial 
patterns. </p>

<p>21   Finally, the above analysis at a larger spatial scale, in combination with previous 
analysis (based on central parishes), provides some insights about the importance of 
spatial scale. Largely focusing at the urban scale, our previous analyses provided 
useful inferences with regard to spatial heterogeneity and interactions across 
parishes. However, understanding of spillovers between the urban and suburban 
parishes was somewhat limited by the fact that the suburban area contained a 
heterogeneous mix of neighbourhoods. This issue was addressed in the current 
analysis by dividing the suburban area into various notional submarkets that 
segregate the varieties of living space (Lefebvre, 1974 [1991]) in a more useful way. 
In this larger spatial scale too, very interesting inferences are drawn relating to 
spatial heterogeneity and interactions. This highlights the fact that, with regard to 
study housing submarkets, a single scale may not always be adequate (Whitehead,  2003). </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>In summary, our work here puts the connection between urban spaces and housing 
markets in a new framework and develops methodology for understanding urban 
housing markets in terms of three distinct but interconnected features of space* 
spatial heterogeneity, spatial dependence and spatial scale. Our methodology relies 
on factor-based hedonic pricing analysis and offers many advantages in terms of 
interpretation, improved prediction and the facility to develop understanding of 
spatial interactions in more general terms. 
Applied to the study of housing submarkets in the city of Aveiro, Portugal, the 
methodology offers a unique understanding of spatial aspects of the housing market. 
This is important for understanding neighbourhood choice, housing preferences, 
and the evolution of urban spatial structure. The implications of such studies on 
place-based urban planning and housing policy that is informed by a clear 
understanding of the links between space and housing is a subject of ongoing and 
further studies (see Maclennan, 2010; Bhattacharjee et al., 2010). </p>

<p>Notes </p>





<p>5. For a setting with n spatial units under study, W is an n )n matrix with zero diagonal elements. The off-
diagonal elements are typically either dummy variables for contiguity or inversely proportional to the distance 
between a pair of units, so that spillover between a pair of units that are farther apart is lower. 
6. An analogy with well-researched urban areas in the USA is illuminative. A city like Chicago, where house 
prices have risen in the CBD but grown even faster in the suburbs, would imply positive spatial interaction 
between the centre and the periphery. By contrast, in Detroit, where prices in the centre have declined at the 
same time as suburban housing prices have continued to rise, suggests negative spatial interaction. We are 
grateful to Steve Malpezzi for pointing out this connection with urban structure. 
7. See Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly (2011) for a review and discussion, as well as an application to network interactions 
within a committee. 
8. Note that, since the spatial weights matrix is unknown in our setting, it is necessary to row-standardize W to 
enable identification of both W and the autoregressive parameter (l) in Equation (1). The assumption that the 
intra-submarket spatial weight is the same across all submarkets is not necessary, but retained here for 
computational simplicity. 
9. That is, W 
0 is symmetric, which holds if v kl 0v lk for all l "k. W is the row-standardized version of W 
0 , and </p>

<p>therefore will not be symmetric in general. 
10. Here, A 
1/2 denotes the symmetric square root of a positive definite matrix A, and A 
(1/2 denotes its inverse. </p>

<p>In other words, A 
(1/2 has the same eigenvectors as A, but with the eigenvalues replaced by the reciprocal of </p>

<p>the square root of the corresponding eigenvalues of A. 
11. See Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly (2011) for further discussion on partial identification and structural constraints in 
this context. 
12. We thank an anonymous referee whose comments encouraged us to examine the special features of the factor 
model in the cross-section context, thereby improving upon the methodology and its discussion substantially. 
13. See Bhattacharjee &amp; Holly (2011) for further discussion of the conceptual distinction between strong and 
weak dependence and their connection to the spatial weights matrix. 
14. In principle, one can allow the within-submarket spatial weights to vary across submarkets. In our empirical 
exercise, we abstract from this issue for the sake of computational simplicity. 
15. The name of the agency is withheld because of a confidentiality agreement. 
16. Flats tend to be located in areas with high residential density, which in turn generate scale economies for the 
provision of these infrastructure facilities. 
17. Given the small sample sizes in each submarket, it is not surprising that many regression coefficients are not 
statistically significant. The estimates indicate that, despite small sample sizes, it is important to allow for spatial 
heterogeneity. Further, the limitation of sample size is counterbalanced by the benefits of estimating spatial 
econometric models (spatial error and spatial lag models) by maximum likelihood, which is computationally 
difficult on large datasets. 
18. The value of the Moran's I statistic ranges from 1 (perfectly positive spatial autocorrelation) to (1 (perfectly 
negative spatial autocorrelation), a value near zero indicating no spatial autocorrelation. 
19. Rothenberg et al. (1991) define submarkets in terms of bundle 'quality' (that is, close hedonic substitutability), 
and these sets of close substitute units may or may not have any spatial content. 
20. The consolidation of a single urban area corresponding to the municipalities of Aveiro and Ílhavo was built on 
a territory previously organized as a set of small urban and rural clusters, each with its own provision of small 
scale services. Factor 2 reflects the proximity to such local centres. 
21. Paradoxically, the main reason mitigating against more formal analysis of spatial structure using the estimated 
spatial weights matrix is large sample size. It is computationally very difficult to conduct ML-based inferences 
in spatial econometric models when sample size is large. Suitable ML computation for large sample 
applications, based perhaps on regularization or subsampling, is planned for the future. </p>



<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 165 </p>







<p>Spatial Interactions in Hedonic Pricing Models 167 </p>

</text></tei>