<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1468-0297.2008.02177.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:31+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>An earlier paper showed that an economy could be trapped in an equilibrium state in which the 
absence of the rule of law led to asset-stripping and the prevalence of asset-stripping led to the 
absence of a demand for the rule of law, highlighting a coordination failure. This article looks more 
carefully at the dynamics of transition from a non-rule-of-law state. The article identifies a commit-
ment problem as the critical feature inhibiting the transition: the inability, under a rule of law, to 
forgive theft. This can lead to the perpetuation of the non-rule-of-law state, even when it might seem 
that the alternative is Pareto-improving. </p>

<p>Why do dysfunctional institutions persist? It is now well understood that they persist if 
there are politically powerful losers from reform and no way to promise them com-
pensation credibly. There are two possible lines of attack on this problem. The first 
investigates whether the problem of commitment can be solved dynamically. The 
second asks how a society evolves when such commitment is not possible. We are 
concerned with the second question. The presumption has been that if a reform is 
Ôgood enoughÕ, then once a society understands the magnitude of its benefits, sufficient 
demand for the reform will emerge that it will occur. Creating the rule of law is an 
example of such a reform. The rule of law stops the few from stealing from the many. In 
this view, one would expect the rule of law to emerge. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Even though we believe that the rule of law creates a vast majority of winners, we see 
that many societies are not moving towards the rule of law. In Russia and many other 
post-communist countries, little progress towards either forming a strong constituency 
for the rule of law, or establishing the rule of law, has been made since the privatisation 
of most state enterprises. 
had on average slightly less adherence to the rule of law than the world as a whole but 
showed low dispersion. Between 1996 and 2005, a twin peaks pattern emerged for the 
post-communist countries and for the world: some post-communist countries achieved 
a good measure of rule of law, while for the majority, scores remained low or deteri-
orated. Holmes (2002) reflects a widely shared view (see fn. 2) when he writes that in 
Russia the central obstacle to the emergence of the rule of law is the lack of demand: </p>

<p>No well-organised constituency for a rule-of-law system exists in Russia today. 
Putin may sincerely want to introduce the rule of law. He may repeatedly 
announce that he is going to create it. . . .These subjective intentions are 
irrelevant, however. The rule of law is going to emerge only if there are strong 
constituencies supporting it. (p. 87) </p>

<p>One possible explanation for this puzzle is that the rule of law is not such a great 
thing. Perhaps we have overestimated its ability to increase income or underestimated 
its distributional consequences, in particular, those that cannot be undone by credible 
commitments to redistribute. For example, the traditional view of the enclosure of the 
commons in England was that it created large, dispersed benefits. Yet Weitzman (1974)  showed that most people could be worse off under the efficient enclosure than under 
inefficient free access rights. 
4 The establishment of the rule of law in a lawless state is a 
more compelling example of a reform that should engender widespread support, since 
it is a movement from the jungle to order. Political philosophers from Hobbes to 
Nozick clearly viewed this kind of reform as an improvement. Economists have argued 
that although private, relation-based governance may suffice for a middle-income 
country, the rule of law is necessary to make the transition to a high-income country 
(Rodrik, 2003, p. 17; Dixit, 2004, p. 82). Yet, as Figure 1 illustrates, many societies do 
not seem to be moving towards the rule of law. 
In this article we offer an alternative explanation. We assume that the rule of law is an 
institutional change that permits higher levels of welfare to everyone because of the 
greater incentives to production. We also assume that individuals are forward-looking, 
with expectations that are consistent with the properties of the underlying model. But 
we allow individuals who do not believe that a quick transition to the rule of law will 
occur to adapt their economic activities accordingly. Costs of exiting the lawless state arise 
endogenously from these adaptive behaviours and engender resistance to reform. 
We show this in a simple, dynamic model that builds on our earlier static model of 
coordination. 
5 In the earlier model, agents with control rights over enterprises face two 
choices: one economic, whether to build the value of their assets or strip them; and one 
political, whether to adopt the rule of law or not. Given the static nature of that model, 
only those who choose to build value benefit from the rule of law. Thus, the probability 
distribution of the political outcome depends on the fraction of the population that 
chooses to build value, which itself depends on the probability distribution of the 
political outcome. We showed that self-fulfilling Pareto-inferior equilbria may exist in 
which few agents build value and thus few demand the rule of law. </p>

<p>6   [ A U G U S T 2008 ] 
1475 </p>

<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>4 Subsequently, Allen (1982) challenged the view that the enclosure movement enhanced efficiency. 
5 See Hoff and Stiglitz (2004a), which also provides a brief review of the transition from communism in 
Russia. For a diagrammatic exposition, see Hoff and Stiglitz (2004b). 
6 For another example of political-economic links with self-fulfilling equilibria, see Chang (2006). </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>In the dynamic setting that we explore here, all individuals obtain a future benefit 
from the establishment of the rule of law. Therefore, individuals who strip assets in the 
current period may vote for creating the rule of law. Their choice depends on the trade-
off between the loss from the expected recapture of part of their stripping income in 
the transition to the rule of law and the gain with respect to future economic activities. 
Asset stripping in our model is like getting Ôblood on one's handsÕ, in that it makes an 
individual vulnerable to a loss in the transition to the rule of law. We do not assume 
that the blood is never washed away. On the contrary, we make the minimalist 
assumption that only the current period's return from asset stripping is vulnerable to 
recapture. However, as long as the non-rule-of-law state persists, some agents may 
choose to strip assets, period after period. Thus the blood on their hands would be 
fresh when the rule of law state was created and so they would gain from the estab-
lishment of the rule of law only after they began to build value -that is, with a time lag. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>This can that delay the establishment of the rule of law or even lock the society out of it. 
Our results highlight a coordination problem that an elected policy maker cannot solve 
because of a commitment problem inherent in the rule of law. 
All that we require to generate the possibility of losers from institutional reform 
endogenously is that, under the rule of law, society cannot commit itself to zero 
recapture of income from asset stripping. 
8 This commitment problem arises from what 
scholars take to be key features of any system that provides impartial third party 
enforcement of property rights and contracts: </p>

<p>(a) Such a legal system should be viewed as a self-enforcing equilibrium between 
political officials and citizens, and </p>

<p>0 -2 
0 
2 </p>

<p>Rule of law score </p>

<p>0 
Kdensity -rule of law </p>

<p>-2 
0 
2 </p>

<p>Rule of law score </p>

<p>World </p>

<p>Post-communist countries </p>

<p>1996 </p>

<p>Kdensity -rule of law </p>

<p>Post-communist countries </p>

<p>World </p>

<p>2005 </p>

<p>Poor 
Good 
Poor 
Good </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Distribution of World Bank Rule of Law Scores for Post-communist Countries and All 
Countries, 1996 and 2005 
Note. Indicators are scaled so that the world average and median are zero and the standard 
deviation is one. </p>

<p>7 This result is reminiscent of Adsera and Ray (1998), who assume that, for all agents, the benefits of 
coordination come with an exogenous delay. Our article explores a mechanism that can generate (for some 
agents) the delay that Adsera and Ray model as a reduced form. 
8 Or, more precisely, that the risk of recapture will not increase under the rule of law. </p>

<p>1476 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>(b) Only if the distribution of power is such that conflicting actors seek to resolve 
their conflicts by recourse to law does law rule. </p>

<p>Following from these two properties is a third, namely, </p>

<p>(c) The contents of the rule of law are subject to interrogation and reform, rather 
than capable of being frozen at a moment in time. </p>

<p>9   In other words, one cannot simultaneously have the rule of law and fence it in so 
as to commit a society not to capture illegitimate gains obtained before some time t. 
In Section 4, we sketch a simple mechanism underlying the commitment problem 
in a rule-of-law governed democracy: Politicians have incentives to appropriate ille-
gitimately obtained income and to redistribute it to their supporters, whereas they do 
not have such incentives with respect to legitimately obtained income. 
As in our earlier static model, we have chosen to develop our points in a specific 
context -post-communist countries after the privatisation of many state enterprises. 
But the framework of our article illuminates a very general problem and thus may serve 
as a basis for integrating the literature. Starting with a society in which theft is allowed 
but allowing theft is not in anyone's self-interest, can we explain the creation of third 
party enforcement of property rights, which makes it costly for individuals to steal? </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Our framework shows why it is difficult to create a demand for the rule of law from scratch, e.g. 
without norms that limit theft. Our framework is Markov; i.e. current and future out-
comes are conditioned only on the current state. If, more realistically, we allow that 
outcomes also depend on history, then the difficulty of exiting the lawless state after 
asset-stripping will be greater than our model would suggest, as we show in Section 2. In 
the conclusion, we suggest additional applications of our framework. 
Our article contributes to the rapidly growing literature on the positive economics of 
institutional change (see references in fn. 1). Our departure from the existing work on 
the problem of credible commitment to compensate losers from reform is that we treat 
individualsÕ economic interests as endogenous, whereas existing work 
11 treats them as 
parametric. That modelling approach is appropriate when economic institutions are 
stable with regard to the political transitions that the model tries to explain, e.g. the 
case of the transitions from authoritarianism of Latin America and Southern Europe 
(O'Donnell et al., 1986). What is historically distinct about the post-communist tran-
sitions is the possibility of simultaneous deep change in both the economy and the 
polity. These transitions have been compared to Ôrebuilding the ship the seaÕ: ÔHardly 
any of the institutional elements of the old order can be relied upon, i.e., is consid-
ered. . .worthy of preservation for more than a transitory period or recognised as a 
worthy legacyÕ (Elster et al., 1998, p. 18, emphasis in original). In this context it is 
appropriate to treat economic interests as endogenous. Our article focuses on the costs 
of exiting a lawless state created by two kinds of problems: (1) the coordination of </p>

<p>9 See, e.g. on (a) Weingast (1997) and Basu (2000) and on (b,c), Maravall and Przeworski (2003). 
Regarding point (c), it is worthwhile to quote from the Supreme Court decision in the case of Nebbia vs. New 
York (1934), where the Court declared that Ôthere is no closed case or category of business affected with the 
public interest. . .Õ (cited in North, 1981, p. 198). 
10 Basu (1997, p. 248) observes that ÔSince this exercise. . .has not been done thus far, we do not really know 
whether the model of the market, abstracted from its social and political moorings, can ever be realized.Õ 
11 As Acemoglu and Robinson (2006, p. 316) emphasise. Acemoglu et al. (2005) outline the desiderata for 
a yet-to-be-built general theory of institutional change. </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>economic and political choices and (2) the constraints that the rule of law imposes on 
the content of laws. 
Our article also contributes to the literature on privatisation. Studies of privatisation all 
over the world have concluded that privatisation is unlikely to improve performance when 
corporate governance institutions are weak. 
12 While noting in that case the absence of any 
benefit from privatisation, these studies overlook a cost that we emphasise here: by wid-
ening the scope for asset stripping, privatisation may create political forces opposed to 
establishing the rule of law. Not surprisingly, scholars have enjoined developing countries 
before privatising firms to Ôembrace a corporate governance perspective. . .that can con-
strain the grabbing hands of public and private actorsÕ (Dyck, 2001, p. 59). In Section 3, we 
extend our model to consider two policies that affect the demand for the rule of law -the 
sequencing and pacing of the post-communist transition and macroeconomic policy. 
Our framework of binary choices in the economy and the polity is too simple to 
capture the institutional path of any real post-communist country. In our concluding 
Section, we emphasise the need in future work to incorporate changes over time in the 
distribution of power. </p>

<p>1. A Dynamic Model of the Demand for the Rule of Law </p>

<p>1.1. The Agents </p>

<p>There is a continuum one of forward-looking agents with control rights over enter-
prises. Time is divided into an infinite number of periods. In every period, each agent 
has a choice between two economic actions: </p>

<p>Building value: Making an irreversible investment to increase the enterprise's value, or 
Stripping assets: Stripping the assets of the enterprise by appropriating corporate value 
for themselves and expropriating minority investors, sometimes also 
referred to as ÔtunnellingÕ. </p>

<p>The assumption behind this setup is that agents are not constrained by norms, other 
informal institutions or corporate institutions such as boards. 
13 In choosing their 
strategies, agents look at the entire future stream of returns, where d 2 (0,1) is the 
discount factor. 
Agents differ in their ability to strip assets. h denotes an agent's type, and a higher 
value of h corresponds to a greater ability to strip assets. h has a continuous distribution 
H(h) and density function h(AE). </p>

<p>1.2. The Political Environment </p>

<p>There are two possible political institutions. Initially the polity is a Ônon-rule-of-law 
stateÕ. 
14 The alternative political institution is Ôthe rule of lawÕ, by which we mean well-</p>

<p>12 See Dyck (2001), Djankov and Murrell (2002), and Megginson (2005). 
13 For an interesting case study of the institutional vacuum in one Russian firm, see Gray and Hendley  (1997). 
14 A typical characterisation of the institutional environment in which the first wave of Russian privatisation 
occurred was a Ôsystemic vacuum. . .[without] effective regulations and controlsÕ (Kolodko, 2000, p. 196), 
permitting Ôa sort of Hobbesian capitalismÕ (Freeland 2000, p. 21). </p>

<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>defined and enforced property rights, broad access to those rights and predictable rules 
for resolving rights disputes. The gain from the rule of law is that it makes property 
rights effective. We assume that for every agent, this is a gain: the profit incentives of a 
private firm under the rule of law are stronger than the rent-seeking incentives in the 
non-rule-of-law state (see inequality (4)). The question we address in this article is 
whether this assumption is sufficient to ensure a demand for establishing the rule of law. 
In each period, individuals have to express a political preference, e.g. by voting over 
policies that would create the rule of law. Voting is a metaphor for the myriad ways, 
such as lobbying an elected policy maker, that individuals influence the collective 
choice over institutions. We assume that the probability p t of transition to the rule of 
law in period t is a decreasing function of the fraction of agents, denoted x t , who vote 
against the establishment of the rule of law: </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>p t ¼ pðx t Þ; p 
0 ðÁÞ &lt; 0 for x 2 ð0; 1Þ; 0 ¼ pð1Þ &lt; pð0Þ ¼ 1: 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>Equation (1) means that the probability that the rule of law will be established rises 
from zero to one as the proportion of agents opposed to its establishment falls from 
100% to zero. 
We also assume that the rule of law is an absorbing state: once it is established, the 
society continues in that state forever. Similar results would hold if there were a small 
probability of reversion to the non-rule-of-law state. </p>

<p>16   1.3. The Payoffs </p>

<p>For simplicity, we model the process of building the value of an asset as requiring a 
given level of investment. An individual who builds value in a period obtains an income 
flow f per unit asset and makes an investment I 
j &lt; f per unit asset, where j is the state 
of the world (N or L) at the end of the period, and I 
N &gt; I </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>. 
17 One way to motivate this 
is to suppose that if N is the end-of-period state, then the firm must invest in the private 
enforcement of property rights to obtain a return on its investment. 
Let b 
j denote the net flow from building value: </p>

<p>b 
j ¼ f À I </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>for j ¼ N ; L: 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>Building value increases the asset to a proportiong &gt; 1 of its former size. We 
assume dg &lt; 1 so that asset values are finite. 
The model makes an important simplification that leads to an underestimation of 
the value of the rule of law -the model abstracts from direct externalities across firms. 
In the real world, if a large fraction of the economy is engaged in asset stripping, then 
(as in Russia in the 1990s) overall production suffers. We abstract from these exter-
nalities in order to focus on externalities mediated by the political environment. </p>

<p>15 A part of the economy does not have control rights over firms. A premise of the analysis is that those who 
do are the decisive ÔvotersÕ over whether to create impartial third-party enforcement of property rights and 
contracts. 
16 It would be easy to model such a reversion within our Markovian framework, and it is clear from Figure 1 
that reversion occurs. Our assumption of no reversion increases the gains from transition to the rule of law 
and, thus, makes it more surprising that a strong demand for rule of law may not emerge. 
17 Alternatively, as in Hoff and Stiglitz (2004a), we could model the rule of law as entailing an increased 
return from the same level of investment -e.g. because it reduces the costs of distribution. Nothing depends 
on the choice between these two simplifications. </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>Consider next the payoff to stripping assets. An agent who strips will increase the flow 
of income per unit asset at the cost of reducing the asset to a proportionz &lt; 1 of its 
former size. Let s 
j denote the payoff per unit asset to an agent of type h, where j is the 
state of the world at the end of the period: </p>

<p>s 
N ðhÞ ¼ h; s 
L ðh; kÞ ¼ ð1 À kÞh with k &gt; 0: 
ð3Þ </p>

<p>In this expression, k represents the diminution in the ability to strip after the 
imposition of the rule of law, which circumscribes certain actions used by strippers. k 
also measures the expected recapture of current income from stripping if the transition 
to the rule of law occurs in a given period. Thus, an agent of type h who is stripping 
assets suffers a loss hk in expected value in the transition period. This is his cost of 
exiting the lawless state. 
As discussed above, we assume that for all agents, building value under the rule of law 
yields a higher lifetime utility than stripping assets under non-rule-of-law, i.e. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>1 À g 
! 
h 
1 À z 
ð4Þ </p>

<p>for all h and with strict inequality for some h, where g dg and z dz. One way to 
view the rule of law is that it suppresses the inferior, stripping technology -analogous 
to pulling a ship apart at sea -in favour of the superior, value-creating technology -
rebuilding the ship. Below, we consider agentsÕ choice of economic strategy in the 
initial state N -that is, in the wreckage of the central planned economy. </p>

<p>1.4. The Choice of Economic Strategy </p>

<p>If the initial state is N, individual economic choices are predicated on the path of 
aggregate political behaviour, x t , x tþ1 , x tþ2 . . .. Each agent has an expectation concern-
ing these values, and in the equilibria explored here the expectation is correct. We will 
investigate a subset of possible equilibrium paths such that, as long as non-rule-of-law 
state prevails, the fraction of agents opposed to reform remains the same: x t ¼ x tþ1 ¼ 
x tþ2 ¼ Á Á Á x. We will derive the economic switch line as those combinations of (x, h) for 
which the agent is indifferent in state N between building value and stripping assets. 
An agent of type h has expected income per unit asset of 
bðxÞ ¼ pðxÞb 
L þ ½1 À pðxÞb </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>if he builds value in a given period, and sðx; h; kÞ ¼ h ½1 À pðxÞk if he strips assets. We 
write utility recursively. We denote it by V N (x) if the initial state is N and the individual 
chooses to build value, and similarly for V L . Thus, </p>

<p>V L 
b </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>1 À g 
: 
ð5Þ </p>

<p>If the initial state is N, then an individual of type h will choose to build value in every 
period if and only if </p>

<p>V N ðxÞ 
bðxÞ þ g fpðxÞV L þ ½1 À pðxÞV N ðxÞg 
ð6Þ </p>

<p>! sðx; h; kÞ þ zfpðxÞV L þ ½1 À pðxÞ V N ðxÞg: 
ð7Þ </p>

<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>The inequality in (6) and (7) is equivalent to the condition, </p>

<p>1 À z½1 À pðxÞ 
f 
g 
bðxÞ À 1 À g ½1 À pðxÞ 
f 
g sðx; h; kÞ þ pðxÞðg À zÞV L Dðx; h; kÞ ! 0 ð8Þ </p>

<p>The sign of D(x, h; k), defined in the right-hand side of (8), is positive if and only if the 
individual is better off building value than stripping assets if the initial state is N. Since 
D is strictly decreasing in the agent's ability to strip, i.e. </p>

<p>@Dðx; h; kÞ 
@h 
¼ À½1 À pðxÞk 1 À g ½1 À pðxÞ 
f 
g &lt; 0; 
ð9Þ </p>

<p>there is a critical value of h for each value of x, which is denoted by h a (x ;k) and 
implicitly defined by </p>

<p>Dðx; h a ; kÞ 0: Economic switch line 
ð10Þ </p>

<p>Agents with h 
h a build value in every period and have utility equal to (6) or, 
equivalently, </p>

<p>V N ðxÞ ¼ </p>

<p>
b þ pg 
b </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>1 À g 
1 À ð1 À pÞg 
¼ </p>

<p>b 
1 À g 
þ 
pg 
1 À g 
V L À V N ðxÞ 
½ 
: 
ð11Þ </p>

<p>Agents with h &gt; h a strip assets until the transition to state L occurs, and have utility </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>S N ðx; h; kÞ ¼ </p>

<p>s þ pz 
b </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>1 À g 
1 À ð1 À pÞz 
¼ 
s 
1 À z 
þ 
pz 
1 À z 
½V L À S N ðx; h; kÞ: 
ð12Þ </p>

<p>In Figure 2, the switch line is negatively sloped because an increase in x lowers 
b and 
raises s. Greater constraints on stripping (higher k) shift up the switch line because they 
make stripping less profitable. Formally, we have: </p>

<p>Proposition 1. </p>

<p>ðaÞ 
@h a ðx; kÞ 
@x 
&lt; 0 and ðbÞ 
@h a ðx; kÞ 
@k 
&gt; 0: </p>

<p>Proof. Differentiating (10) gives 
@h a 
@x 
¼ Àp 
0 @Dðx; h a ; kÞ=@p 
@Dðx; h a ; kÞ=@h 
, where </p>

<p>@Dðx; h a ; kÞ 
@p 
¼ ðb 
L À b 
N Þ½1 À ð1 À pÞz þ h a k½1 À ð1 À pÞg </p>

<p>þ ðg À zÞV L À g sðx; h a ; kÞ þ z 
bðxÞ 
½ 
: 
ð13Þ </p>

<p>The first two terms of (13) are positive by construction. We prove in the Appendix that 
the final bracketed term is also positive. Part (a) then follows immediately from (9). 
Similarly we obtain @h a =@k ¼ ÀpðxÞh a f1 À g ½1 À pðxÞg=@Dðx; h a ; kÞ=@h &gt; 0, which 
proves part (b). </p>

<p>18 The bracketed terms on the right-hand side of (11) and (12) are the capital gains from transition to the 
rule of law. </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>1.5. Preferences over Political Institutions </p>

<p>In each period, agents express a political preference, e.g. by voting, over the rule of law. 
Those who build value demand the rule of law, since it would increase their incomes 
currently and in the future. Those who strip assets face an intertemporal trade-off. 
Their lifetime income is (1 À k)h þ zV L if the transition to the rule of law occurs at the 
end of the current period, and h þ zS N (x, h; k) otherwise. 
Let b denote an asset-stripper's benefit (which could be positive or negative) if state 
N persists one more period: </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>bðx; h; kÞ ¼ kh À z½V L À S N ðx; h; kÞ: 
ð14Þ </p>

<p>b is a strictly increasing function of h because those who strip better have a greater cost 
of exiting the lawless state: </p>

<p>@b 
@h 
¼ k þ 
ð1 À pkÞz 
1 À ð1 À pÞz 
&gt; 0 
ð15Þ </p>

<p>and so there exists a switch point, which we denote by h p , at which b ¼ 0. The switch 
point has the following properties, as one can easily check: </p>

<p>Proposition 2. h p is decreasing in k and is invariant to aggregate political behaviour, x. </p>

<p>ðaÞ 
@h p 
@k 
¼ À 
@b=@k 
@b=@h 
&lt; 0; ðbÞ 
@h p 
@x 
¼ À 
@b=@x jb¼0 
@b=@h 
¼ 0: 
ð16Þ </p>

<p>The intuition for (16a) is that since the higher is k, the greater an asset stripper's cost 
of exiting the lawless state, more agents will oppose the establishment of the rule of law </p>

<p>1 
0 </p>

<p>II 
strip assets and 
oppose establishment 
of the rule of law </p>

<p>III 
strip assets and demand 
the rule of law 
I 
build value and 
demand the rule of law </p>

<p>Increasing opposition to the rule of law </p>

<p>θ 
λ 
a (1; ) </p>

<p>θ p </p>

<p>θ 
λ 
a (0; ) </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>Fig. 2. The Switch Lines </p>

<p>19 We treat (14) as if it is defined over all h, but it affects behaviour only through (17), i.e. it is relevant only 
to asset-strippers. </p>

<p>1482 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>(h p is decreased). For (16b), the intuition is that when b ¼ 0, individuals are indifferent 
between states, and so a marginal change in x has a zero first-order effect on an 
individual's ÔvoteÕ. 
We are now ready to define the political switch line, denoted h 
Ã (x; k), as those com-
binations of (x, h) for which the individual is indifferent between states N and L: </p>

<p>h 
Ã ðx; kÞ Maxðh a ; h p Þ: Political switch line 
ð17Þ </p>

<p>Agents of type h O h 
Ã demand legal reform (the rule of law) and agents of type 
h &gt; h 
Ã oppose it. Figure 2 depicts an example of a political switch line. It coincides with 
the economic switch line for h a &gt; h p , and otherwise, corresponds to h p . As shown in the 
Figure, some asset-strippers support the rule of law even though its establishment will 
make them vulnerable to the recapture of illegitimate gains from asset stripping; the 
long-run benefits from the rule of law exceed the Ôexit costÕ of transition. These agents 
fall in Region III of the Figure, where h a &lt; h &lt; h p . 
There are also two possible polar configurations. The first occurs if k is so high -
and thus h p is so low -that no asset stripper demands the rule of law. The second 
configuration, depicted in Figure 3, occurs if k ¼ 0. (In the Figure, h max denotes the 
maximum ability to strip among agents, which is implicitly defined by writing (4) as 
a strict equality.) With no risk of recapture of stripping returns, there is no exit cost 
from the lawless state and so all asset strippers demand the rule of law. We will 
argue in Section 4 that the rule of law, by constraining the content of laws, bars setting 
k ¼ 0. </p>

<p>1.6. The Stripping Ability Curve </p>

<p>To analyse the equilibrium demand (x) for the rule of law, one additional curve is 
needed that reflects the distribution of types in the population. We denote by the </p>

<p>1 
0 </p>

<p>III </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>θ p (x;0) 
θ max </p>

<p>θ a (x;0) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The Switch Lines When There is No Risk of Recapture of Stripping Returns </p>

<p>2008 ] 
1483 </p>

<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>stripping ability curve the function x(h) ¼ 1 À H(h). For each value of h, the stripping 
ability curve gives the fraction of agents whose ability to strip is greater than or equal to 
that value. If the distribution of h is approximately normal, then the stripping ability 
curve will have the shape of the dotted line in Figure 4; another example is in Figure 
5(a). </p>

<p>1.7. Equilibrium Paths </p>

<p>An equilibrium path in the lawless state depends on the fraction of agents x 
Ã who 
oppose the establishment of the rule of law, where x 
Ã solves </p>

<p>x 
Ã ¼ 1 À H ½h 
Ã ðx 
Ã ; kÞ: 
ð18Þ </p>

<p>An interior equilibrium is a pair of values (x, h) that satisfy the political switch line and 
the stripping ability curve. Since both curves are downward sloping, they can have more 
than one intersection. Figure 4 depicts the case of two stable values of x 
Ã (at 0 and x 
00 ). 
Figure 4 also depicts an unstable equilibrium, at x 
0 . At that point, the political switch 
line is steeper than the stripping ability curve. This means that the response along the 
political switch line to a perturbation in x will be greater than the perturbation itself. So 
if there is a perturbation at x 
0 , the ÔswitchedÕ agents do not wish to switch back. The 
perturbation changes the way agents believe the system will evolve, which lowers h a by 
so much that some agents change their economic strategy and, having done that, face 
sufficiently high exit costs that their preference ordering over political institutions changes. 
Thus the path along which a fraction x 
0 opposes the establishment of a rule of law in 
each period is unstable. 
The model could have two corner solutions: x 
Ã ¼ 0 is always an equilibrium (though 
it need not be stable), since at x ¼ 0 the political switch line lies above, or is coincident 
with, the stripping ability curve. x 
Ã ¼ 1 is also an equilibrium if the political switch line lies </p>

<p>1 
0 
x' 
x'' </p>

<p>Stripping ability curve </p>

<p>Political switch line, </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>λ 
*(x; ) </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Multiple Equilibria </p>

<p>1484 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>below the stripping ability curve at x ¼ 1. If this point is an equilibrium, then the society 
is trapped in the non-rule-of-law state. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>The model clarifies the effect of changes in the expected recapture fraction, k. 
21 A 
decrease in k makes asset stripping more attractive (the economic switch line shifts down) 
but also increases the demand for rule of law by asset strippers (the political switch line 
shifts up). The net effect on support for the establishment of the rule of law thus 
depends on the nature of the original equilibrium. Starting from a stable equilibrium 
in which the marginal ÔvoterÕ is a wealth-creator, 
22 a reduction in k increases the opposition 
to the establishment of the rule of law, since it increases the fraction of agents who strip 
assets. However, starting from a stable equilibrium in which the marginal ÔvoterÕ is an 
asset stripper, the effect is the opposite: a reduction in k increases the demand for the rule 
of law, since it lowers exit costs from a lawless state. </p>

<p>1.8. A Numerical Example </p>

<p>In the standard model of Ôpolitical and economic losersÕ who block reform (see ref-
erences in fn. 1), dysfunctional institutions serve the interests of narrow groups at the 
expense of everyone else. In our model, in contrast, the victims of the dysfunctional 
institutions include those who choose them. To illustrate this, we present a numerical 
example. In the example, we assume: </p>

<p>(a) a transition probability equal to the squared demand for the rule of law: p(x) ¼ 
(1 À x) 
2 , 
(b) a set of values of the parameters, 
23 and 
(c) a distribution of stripping abilities in which two-thirds of the agents have h ¼ 
h max and among the remainder, h is uniformly distributed on [0.65, h max ]. </p>

<p>Figure 5(a) shows that the stable equilibria of x* are 0 and 0.75. In the first case, no 
one opposes the establishment of the rule of law, and reform occurs in period 1. In the 
second case, three-fourths of the agents oppose the rule of law, and reform is delayed 
on average for 16 periods. 
24 Figure 5(b) depicts the growth paths of agentsÕ expected 
aggregate lifetime income in these two cases. 
25 Expected aggregate income is 20% 
lower along the path of delayed reform. Every agent is strictly worse off. </p>

<p>20 As emphasised by Greif (1994), culture is an equilibrium selection device and so it is interesting to 
consider within this model the role that culture might have played in Russia. Two facts suggest that the ÔgoodÕ 
corner equilibrium, with x 
Ã ¼ 0, would not be a focal point: (a) managers commonly engaged in asset 
stripping well before the mass privatisation of 1992-4 (Grigoriev, 1992) and (b) most beneficiaries of the mass 
privatisation of large state enterprises in Russia were the managers. For instance, Varese (2001, Appendix B), 
finds in his survey of one Russian city in 1993 that 51% of the 92 full-time officials of the Communist Party in 
1988 were top managers of economic enterprises. 
21 We discuss other comparative statics results in Hoff and Stiglitz (2004a). 
22 Or, more accurately, if the intersection of h 
Ã (x; k) and the stripping ability curve lies along h a , not h p . 
23 f ¼ 0.05, I 
L ¼ 0.01, I 
N ¼ 0.0475,g ¼ 1:05,z ¼ 0:9, k ¼ 0.3, and d ¼ 0.945. Using (4), these values imply 
h max ¼ 0.8. The <rs id="software-0" type="software">EXCEL</rs> program is available at <rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://www.econ.worldbank.org/staff/khoff</rs>. 
24 One can show by standard methods that given a transition probability p per period, the expected 
number of periods before reform is 1/p. If x 
Ã ¼ 0.75, then p(x 
Ã ) ¼ 0.0625 and the expected delay is 16 
periods. 
25 When x 
Ã ¼ 0.75, 87% of agents build value (the marginal asset-stripper demands the rule of law). To 
compute aggregate income, we assume that each agent has control rights over an equal share of aggregate 
assets. This implies that the fraction of agents who strip assets equals the fraction of assets that are stripped. </p>



<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>2. Sources of Historical Dependence </p>

<p>In the Markovian model we have constructed, actions do not depend on history. In this 
Section, we consider sources of historical dependence. </p>

<p>2.1. History-dependent Payoffs </p>

<p>An important example of history dependence are endogenous shifts in the distribution 
of types H(h). Consider a set of societies with initially similar distributions of types </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>x* = 0.75 
x* = 0 </p>

<p>Stripping ability curve </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
Time period 
Agents' aggregate expected income 
x* = 0.75 </p>

<p>x* = 0 </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>θ </p>

<p>a (0; 0.3) </p>

<p>θ a (1; 0.3) </p>

<p>θ p </p>

<p>Fig. 5. (a) A Numerical Example (b) Paths of AgentsÕ Aggregate Expected Income </p>

<p>1486 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>among which, for some reason, one subset began with an initially high level of asset 
stripping and another subset with an initially low level. If stripping assets was charac-
terised by learning-by-doing, then behaviour would be self-reinforcing. The distribution 
of types would diverge over time, as would the degree of support for the rule of law. As 
Holmes (2003, pp. 20-1) states, </p>

<p>Bullies and plunderers -who could never flourish if the rules of the game were 
crystal clear and reliably enforced -cannot be expected to promote or enforce 
a system that will radically devalue the rude skills of acquisition and domina-
tion they have perfected in the state of nature. </p>

<p>Efficiency in stripping may also increase as it becomes more institutionalised (and 
similarly, the ability to engage in growth-enhancing investments may increase with use, 
or atrophy without it). 
An offsetting factor would be that as the stock of assets goes down, the returns from 
further stripping decline. When assets to strip run out, everyone would support the rule 
of law. However, in natural resource-rich economies, such as Russia's, this would not 
happen quickly. 
A further source of history dependence are labour adjustment costs if hired labour is 
specialised to either stripping assets or building value, e.g. mobsters vs. engineers. 
A formal model is Krugman (1991). </p>

<p>2.2. History-dependent Beliefs </p>

<p>The experience of the transition may reinforce one or another view of man; one 
can learn to trust, or not to. A history of corruption may influence a social group's 
norms in ways that would make it harder to achieve a rule of law state (Fisman and  Miguel, 2006). The following response of a Russian minister to allegations of cor-
ruption illustrates that the abuse of power can come to be publicly perceived as 
legitimate: </p>

<p>Vladimir Rushaylo has flatly denied the allegations that 70 per cent of all 
Russian officials are corrupted . . .ÔOnly those who have links with the organised 
criminal gangs can be regarded as corrupted officials. Do not mistake bribe-
taking for corruption,Õ the Russian Interior Minister stressed. </p>

<p>(RIA news agency, Moscow, March 13, 2001/BBC Monitoring Ó BBC) </p>

<p>2.3. Cumulative Exit Costs </p>

<p>We assumed that only those assets stripped in the transition period were subject to 
recapture, whereas assets stripped in earlier periods were ÔgrandfatheredÕ -time had 
gained them legitimacy. In reality, it is the cumulative stock of asset stripping that is at 
risk of recapture. As the stock increases over time, the costs of exiting the non-rule-
of-law state also increase. This effect would be even larger if, as the amounts taken 
mount, demands that more of the assets be recaptured increase, i.e. k increases. 
Recapture may not be the only exit cost. Asset strippers who have engaged in 
criminal activity may also face a risk of retroactive criminal prosecution. Recognising </p>



<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>the huge cost associated with the transition to the rule of law, they may ÔinvestÕ a great 
deal in the maintenance of the non-rule-of-law state, including murdering those who 
work to establish the rule of law. Not only are some individuals locked in by their past 
but others who might wish to support the rule of law may incur tremendous risks in 
doing so. </p>

<p>26   3. Policies that Change the Political/Economic Dynamics </p>

<p>A better understanding of barriers to institutional reform can serve as a guide to what 
conditions might be changed in order to achieve success. We will consider first the 
sequencing and pacing of reform, and then macroeconomic policy. </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>3.1. The Sequencing and Pacing of Reform </p>

<p>The model in Section 1 analysed how, after privatisation, asset-stripping affects the 
demand for the rule of law. Here we develop a very simple model that links what 
happens before and during formal privatisation -and what happens after. The extended 
model captures aspects of the debate in the 1990s between advocates of Ôgradualist 
policiesÕ and proponents of a ÔBig BangÕ approach to privatisation. (In the end, only 
Russia and the Czech Republic followed the latter approach.) A gradualist approach 
postpones privatisation until corporate governance institutions are in place, whereas a 
Big Bang, sometimes called Ôshock therapyÕ, privatises as rapidly as possible. </p>

<p>28   At the outset of the transition from communism, a central rationale for rapid pri-
vatisation was to avoid the diminution of wealth within the state from asset stripping 
and inefficiency. Let Y G denote output per period from the initial stock of assets in the 
public sector. If wastage reduces the assets each period to a proportion l of their 
former size, and if the assets are privatised at time T, then the assets will have dimin-
ished by a factor l 
T . 
Gradualism entails creating corporate governance mechanisms that reduce the 
ability of an agent to strip assets after privatisation. Such mechanisms shift down the 
stripping ability curve. 
29 We parameterise the shift by a function x(AE). The faster the 
privatisation, the weaker is corporate governance. </p>

<p>26 The assassination in of V. Golovlyov, a member of the Duma, is one of a long list of assassinations, nearly 
all unsolved, of Russian public officials. It was believed that ÔMr. Golovlyov was killed by former cronies 
because he had jumped [from a criminal past] to the side of the law helping the investigators.Õ (Michael  Wines, New York Times, August 24, 2002). 
27 On the uses of political-economic models for posing normative questions with regard to aspects of policy 
that are treated as exogenous, see Rodrik (1993). Besides the two policies considered in this Section, another 
key influence on the demand for rule of law are controls on international capital flows; see e.g. Qian (1999), 
Hoff and Stiglitz (2004a) and Braguinsky and Myerson (2007). 
28 This policy choice also has implications, which we do not discuss here, for the manner of privatisation 
(its perceived legality and the ability to transfer state enterprises to outsider, not insider, owners, with large 
consequences for privatisation's success) and also for employment losses and fiscal costs; see Roland (1994), 
Dewatripont and Roland (1995) and Frydman et al. (1999). An engaging overview of the debate is McMillan  (2002, ch. 15). 
29 One measure of this is in Atanasov et al. (2007), which shows that following a change in Bulgarian 
securities law to restrict the scope for financial tunnelling, share prices jumped in a high-risk-of-tunnelling 
group of firms relative to share prices in a low-risk control group. </p>

<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>Given the initial stock of assets in the public sector, I let W [x 
Ã (x,k),x(T),k(T)] 
denote the maximised value after privatisation of expected future income as of time 
T. The model of Section 1 maps into this function. W(AE) depends on the constit-
uency against the rule of law, x 
Ã (x, k) and also depends directly on the extent of 
corporate governance mechanisms x and on k through their influence on stripping. 
The value of expected future income at time zero can be written as </p>

<p>Y G 
1 À dl 
ð1 À d 
T l 
T Þ þ d 
T l 
T W ½x 
Ã ðx; kÞ; xðT Þ; kðT Þ: 
ð19Þ </p>

<p>Equation (19) captures several effects of delaying privatisation. First, delay means 
greater dissipation of value while assets remain in the public sector. But transferring 
property to the private sector does not eliminate agency problems. 
30 Strengthening 
corporate governance institutions increases the value of the assets in the hands of the 
private sector. A third set of effects relates to the political dynamics. Creating better 
corporate governance institutions before privatising large state enterprises reduces the 
incentives and scope for asset stripping and so influences the constituency for reform. 
Thus, if one plots social welfare in (19) as a function of the speed of privatisation, it 
may be that some delay in official privatisation trades off optimally the agency costs of 
state ownership with the agency costs and political risks (given weak corporate gover-
nance) of private ownership. Figure 6 depicts this case. 
But whether a comparison of gradualism and the Big Bang is a relevant comparison 
for Russia is contentious. In one view, no reform-minded government existed to 
ÔengineerÕ the transition. As the Russia historian Stephen Kotkin (2001) writes: </p>

<p>The idea that the collapse suddenly ended in December 1991 and that a handful 
of new ÔdemocratsÕ or Ôradical reformersÕ had come to power, was silly. (p. 7) </p>

<p>. . .[W]ho was supposed to have implemented [the criticsÕ] suggested state-led 
ÔgradualistÕ policies -the millions of officials who had betrayed the Soviet state 
and enriched themselves in the bargain? No Russian leadership, rising to 
power by virtue of the spiraling collapse of central (Soviet) state institutions, 
could have prevented the ensuing total appropriation of bank accounts and 
property that . . .were in the hands of unrestrained actors. (p. 116, emphasis in 
original) </p>

<p>A second perspective is that Yeltsin enjoyed enormous authority in the autumn and 
winter of 1991-2. That authority gave him the opportunity to change the political forces in 
place before implementing privatisation. Had he made those changes, he could have </p>

<p>30 In both the public and the private sectors, deadweight losses arise because information is asymmetric, 
incentives are not aligned and controllers take distortionary actions to divert assets and income from the ÔtrueÕ 
owner (the state or the corporation) to themselves (Stiglitz, 2000). Two recent developments shed light on 
the importance of agency costs in privatised firms in Russia: (a) A study finds that oligarchs who controlled 
state enterprises reported twice as much income as those who controlled private enterprises, Ôpresumably 
because it was more difficult to hide incomes in those businessesÕ (Braguinsky, forthcoming). The less income 
that is hidden, the less income that is likely diverted, with consequent deadweight losses. (b) One can 
interpret actions of Putin to limit the ability of privatised Russian firms to sell reserves of natural resources as 
reflecting his belief that this will reduce the diversion of assets (see The Russia Journal, ÔKremlin eyes Russia's 
natural resources,Õ Aug. 2-8, 2002 repr. in Johnson's Russia List). </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>implemented gradualism. He chose not to do this and to focus instead on economic 
reforms first. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>A third view is that while gradualism was not politically feasible in Russia because it 
would have expropriated powerful stakeholders, Big Bang privatisation was both fea-
sible and also favourable to the progress of Russia towards a free market economy 
because it would change the interests of the key political players. Fast privatisation, moreover, 
would constrain the policy options of future governments that might oppose capitalism 
(Boycko et al., 1995; Shleifer and Treisman, 2000). </p>

<p>32   History cannot readily resolve counterfactual questions. However, Poland provides 
an example where advocates of Big Bang privatisation had argued that gradualism was 
not politically feasible but privatisation was delayed and wealth within the state was 
preserved (the rate of wastage l was low). Given Poland's success in preserving wealth 
and in moving towards the rule of law, 
33 there is a strong presumption that Big Bang 
privatisation would have been inferior to the gradual privatisation strategy that Poland 
adopted. It is also plausible that Russia could have preserved a large fraction of its 
principal assets, natural resources, within the public sector: In extractive industries, one 
can at worst steal the flow. If the right to sell assets does not exist, no one can steal the 
capital value. </p>

<p>3.2. Macroeconomic Policy </p>

<p>Macroeconomic policy can also change the political/economic dynamics that we 
investigate in this article. In post-communist countries, rapid price liberalisation led to </p>

<p>0 
Timing of privatisation </p>

<p>Social welfare 
at time 0 </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Social Welfare When Delaying Privatisation Lowers Private Sector Agency Costs </p>

<p>31 This view is held with various nuances by Fish (1994), McFaul (1995, pp. 225-7), Dewatripont and  Roland (1995), Black et al. (2000), Reddaway and Glinski (2001) and Goldman (2003). 
32 Biais and Perroti (2002) and Hoff (2003) discuss the limits of the strategic use of privatisation. 
33 See Belka et al. (1993) and Grzymala-Busse (2003). </p>

<p>1490 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>high inflation, which led to tight monetary policy to dampen the inflation. We will 
slightly modify the model of Section 1 to capture a link between macroeconomic policy 
and institutional change. 
We relax our assumption in (1) about the probability p(AE) of transition to the rule of 
law. We assume here that a particular typeĥ is decisive, as in the case of a median voter 
model, 
34 so that we can direct attention at how policy affects him. We also assume thatĥ 
is sufficiently high that if an individual of typeĥ strips, he will oppose the establishment 
of the rule of law in the current period, i.e.ĥ &gt; h p . Thus, if he strips, p ¼ 0 and his 
utility is S N ðĥ; r Þ ¼ s 
N ðĥ; r Þ þ zS N ðĥ; r Þ, where r denotes the interest rate. If he builds 
value, then p ¼ 1 and his utility is V L (r) ¼ b </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>(r) þ gV L (r). Under plausible circum-
stances, raising r lowers the relative return to building value: at a higher value of r, the 
cost of capital is higher, the likelihood of credit rationing is greater and future profits 
obtained from current investments are more heavily discounted. </p>

<p>35   Government chooses a level of public spending, G, and through monetary policy 
influences the level of the interest rate. 
36 The rule of law will be established if </p>

<p>s 
N ðĥ; r Þ </p>

<p>1 À z </p>

<p>b 
L ðr Þ </p>

<p>1 À g 
: Rule-of -Law constraint 
ð20Þ </p>

<p>Equating the two sides of (20) implicitly defines a critical valuer . Only if the interest 
rate is below it will the rule of law be established. 
Suppose that social welfare depends on growth, the level of social expenditures, and 
inflation and, in turn, these three variables depend on r and G. In any given state (N or 
L), welfare is an indirect function of these two government policies. In Figure 7, in the 
traditional approach, the social optimum is at point P. That approach takes the 
political institutions as given but in this article we have emphasised their endogeneity. 
Suppose that social welfare under the rule of law is so much higher than under no 
rule of law that under any policy, the rule-of-law state provides greater welfare than the 
non-rule-of-law state. Then fr,Gg should be chosen so that the rule of law emerges as 
part of the political equilibrium, i.e. r 
r . The iso-welfare curves are dashed in the 
policy region where the rule of law is unattainable. Maximum social welfare is obtained 
at point P 
0 , not P. </p>

<p>4. Is It Possible to Have Secure But Illegitimate Rights to Income? </p>

<p>All that we require to generate the possibility of losers from reform is that society 
cannot commit to k ¼ 0. Some defenders of Big Bang privatisation have argued that 
the reason for the failures is the fear of renationalisation, and that all that is required to 
turn defeat into victory is to guarantee that there will be no recapture of assets even 
from those who have engaged in stripping of corporate value or in other respects </p>

<p>34 Suppose that the establishment of the rule of law depends on a majority voting rule: p ¼ 0 if x &gt; 1/2 
and otherwise p ¼ 1. The Ôtipping pointÕ at which the rule of law is established is a population fraction 
x ¼ 1=2. Associated with the tipping point is a critical value of stripping ability, which we denote byĥ, such 
that half of the population has a stripping ability above the critical value and half below it. 
35 This result can be derived by positing in our basic model that the discount factor is a function of r. 
36 For simplicity, suppose that the level of G does not affect the relative return to building value. </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>defrauded investors or the state. In this Section, we explain why it may be neither 
desirable, nor feasible, to provide such a guarantee. 
It may actually be functional for society that some recapture of past theft is expected. 
A key limit on the extent of opportunistic behaviour in a lawless state is that such 
behaviours are punished under a future regime. If self-interested individuals perceived 
k to be zero, then, until the moment of the establishment of the rule of law, each would 
be trying to steal as much as he could. On such grounds, Adam Smith (1759, Part II, ii, 
3.3) argued that justice was necessary to the existence of society. 
The sina qua non of the rule of law or any rule-governed state is the effective 
restriction on arbitrary power. Our article focuses on a limited range of theft -that of 
corporate assets. It is difficult to see how a society could commit itself to totally for-
giving corporate theft (if its costs were viewed as high), while not doing so for other 
forms of theft. And the latter, both theory and history suggest a rule-governed state 
cannot do. 
37 Instead of reviewing this vast literature, we suggest one mechanism that 
would make such a commitment impossible in a democracy. 
The consequences of the state's seizing illegitimately taken property are markedly 
different from the consequences of the state's taking or redistributing legitimately 
obtained wealth. It is rational for politicians seeking to increase their share of the 
electorate to argue for the first and not the second and for redistributing the illegiti-
mately obtained wealth to voters. Nationalising stolen wealth does not harm investment 
incentives. On the contrary, it improves them. </p>

<p>Interest 
rate, r </p>

<p>Government spending, G </p>

<p>Rule-of-law constraint </p>

<p>Iso-welfare curves in 
the rule-of-law state 
Direction of 
increasing 
social 
welfare </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P' 
r </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Rule-of-law Constraint </p>

<p>37 See fn. 9 and Elster (2004), who finds that attempts to design institutions to protect once politically 
powerful groups from justice under successor regimes have never succeeded. Such protection was denied not 
only to past elites, but even to ordinary people who Ô[a]lthough not wrongdoers. . . were the beneficiaries of 
wrongdoingÕ (Elster, p. 39). </p>

<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>In contrast, in a democratic society, what stops nationalisation of legitimate wealth 
and its distribution to voters by politicians is that doing that would discourage invest-
ment, which would leave most citizens worse off. By the same token, what may stop 
nationalisation of illegitimately taken wealth is that beliefs about its unfairness change, 
or that the new owners are more efficient than the old owners and so better able to 
command power and to benefit society. </p>

<p>38   Myths have a role to play in changing a political consensus but inventing myths takes 
time. In Russia, there is evidence that rights' holders have some but limited ability -
through investing in the firms and providing public goods -to change the perceived 
legitimacy of their property rights (Frye, 2006). 
It is at times of transition that new myths and beliefs are created. At the beginning of 
the transition, not everyone believed that privatisation and the creation of a market 
economy would, at least by themselves, improve the well-being of most citizens. Support 
for the Coasian position that, in the absence of transaction costs, any distribution of 
property rights under a rule of law is efficient and therefore should be respected, 
depends on the fact that it actually does lead to efficient outcomes. There is an equi-
librium in which this is not believed and justifiably so, because it does not produce the 
promised results if it is not believed. Distrust in this proposition undermines the 
legitimacy of rights directly and, indirectly, weakens property rights through the 
mechanism outlined in our model, by undermining the demand for the rule of law. 
Our article has investigated this type of coordination failure and the Ôexit costsÕ from a 
non-rule-of-law state to which the coordination failure gives rise. </p>

<p>5. Avenues for Future Research </p>

<p>Our model leaves open a wide range of problems for future work: </p>

<p>5.1. The Evolution of Inequality </p>

<p>As is well known, in Russia many of the asset-strippers evolved into oligarchs and the 
loans-for-shares programme in 1995-7 consolidated the oligarchic structure of power. 
The dysfunctional institutions in Russia led to a vast increase in inequality of wealth and 
power; an interesting discussion is Colloudon (2002). This development lies completely 
outside our model. Moreover, as economic historians have established, high inequality 
is itself a key factor in the creation and persistence of dysfunctional institutions; see e.g. 
Engerman and Sokoloff (1997, 2003) and Acemoglu et al. (2002). An important 
problem for future research is thus to incorporate the modelling of changes in 
inequality with that of changes in institutions. This should shed further light on why 
attempts to jumpstart capitalist institutions are hazardous. </p>

<p>5.2. Bayesian Dynamics </p>

<p>Not only do we see that the distribution of power coevolves with institutions. A similar 
process occurs with respect to beliefs. In the post-communist countries, individuals </p>

<p>38 For historical examples, see Rajan and Zingales (2003, ch. 6). </p>

<p>2008 ] </p>

<p>
E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>update their beliefs about whether privatisation leads to efficiency on the basis of the 
economic outcomes of the privatisation and also the incentives of the advocates of 
particular positions. The fact that short-run outcomes were so poor in many of the post-
communist economies and that those advocating rapid privatisation enriched them-
selves by it so greatly, 
39 would increase doubts about the validity of the view that a 
market economy is broadly beneficial (Denisova et al., 2007). An analysis of the 
Bayesian dynamics, in which agents update their beliefs about the truth of the Coasian 
view, might help to explain differences across countries in the paths of institutional 
development. </p>

<p>5.3. International Policy as a Coordination Device </p>

<p>We have explored the role of national policies (e.g. macroeconomic policy) in limiting 
the economic behaviour that can reinforce bad institutions. What role can international 
organisations, such as the World Trade Organisation, play in facilitating coordination? 
In the case of the Eastern European countries, the opportunity to join the European 
Union made a particular set of rules focal and led individuals to anticipate large 
rewards from coordinating on them, which helps to explain the successful transitions in 
those economies; see Elster et al. (1998) and Roland and Verdier (2003). </p>

<p>5.4. Other Applications of the Model </p>

<p>We have focused on the transition from communism but our analysis has three other 
applications. Without change, the model can be applied to the problem of post-conflict 
states in which economic and political structures have collapsed. A second application 
is to post-colonial countries in which the legitimacy of inherited law is contested. To 
those currently in possession of assets, there is a risk that another claimant to the 
property will appear and have the backing of law. This lowers the relative return to 
investing (relative to asset stripping). Stripping affects the political dynamics. It creates 
an additional obstacle to the movement towards the rule of law based on any 
conceivable criteria of legitimacy of property rights. 
A third application is to oil field unitisation. Imagine that a number of individuals 
own an oil reservoir in common; that is, none has the right to exclude any of the 
others. Overexploitation makes extraction inefficient for each individual by prema-
turely depleting subsurface pressure. But because no one pays for the use of the field, 
no one takes this cost fully into account in deciding how to exploit the field. The 
problem disappears if one individual owns the whole field and charges each individual 
for his use (Libecap 1989). However, anticipation of delay in unitisation leads to 
individual drilling. Imagine that every period of individual drilling gives a leaseholder 
private information about the value of his lease. Then he may gain from a delay in 
unitisation if his private information is favourable. Delay, by making the information 
public and so increasing his rental share under unitisation, offsets the impact on him </p>

<p>39 Of the 296 businessmen in Russia ranked by experts as most influential in 1995-9, one-third either came 
from the ranks of former reformist politicians or their close personal assistants, or became elected politicians 
or office-holders at some point after becoming wealthy. The Russian media in 1999 named virtually all of 
these 296 as warranting criminal investigation for asset stripping (Braguinsky, forthcoming). </p>

<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

<p>of the damage to the reservoir. This can lead to opposition to unitisation, period after 
period. 
We hope that some of these issues will be pursued in future research. </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>We use the following property of the economic switch line in the proof of Proposition 1. </p>

<p>Lemma. ðg À zÞV L À g sðx; h a ; kÞ þ z bðxÞ ! 0 </p>

<p>Proof of Lemma. Rearranging terms in (8) and using (10) gives </p>

<p>ðg À zÞV L ¼ 
sðx; h a ; kÞ À 
bðxÞ À ð1 À pÞ½g sðx; h a ; kÞ À z 
bðxÞ 
pðxÞ 
: 
ð8 
0 Þ </p>

<p>By substituting for (gÀz)V L from (8 
0 ) and rearranging terms, we can write the left-hand side of 
the lemma as </p>

<p>ðg À zÞV L À g sðx; h a ; kÞ þ z 
bðxÞ ¼ 
1 
p 
ð1 À g Þð1 À zÞ 
sðx; h a ; kÞ 
1 À z 
À </p>

<p>bðxÞ 
1 À g </p>



<p>¼ ðg À zÞ½V L À V N ðxÞ </p>

<p>where the last expression is obtained by substituting for 
b=ð1 À g Þ from (11) and for s=ð1 À zÞ 
from (12) and by recognising that V N (x) S N (x,h a ;k). Since g &gt; z and V L ! V N (x), the Lemma is 
proved. </p>

<p>The World Bank 
Columbia University and NBER </p>

<p>Submitted: 23 March 2003 
Accepted: 17 October 2007 </p>



<p>2008 ] 
1495 </p>

<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>



<p> 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>





<p>E X I T I N G A L A W L E S S S T A T E </p>

<p>Ó The Author(s). Journal compilation Ó Royal Economic Society 2008 </p>

</text></tei>