<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10818-017-9252-0" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract A two-species bioeconomic model is analyzed, but in contrast to most 
similar models, there is no biological interaction between the species, only economic. 
The interaction takes place in the market where the quantity of either species may affect 
the price of the other. The effects of cross-price elasticities on the optimal steady state 
and on the optimal paths in the sole-owner case are investigated both analytically 
(steady states) and numerically (optimal paths). First, it is shown that if the harvest of 
one species has impact on the price of another species, then this has a positive effect on 
its steady-state stock. The effect increases with the stock-elasticity in the cost function. 
Further, in the case of linear demand functions, the steady state outcome depends solely 
on the sum of the cross-price parameters and not their individual values. Secondly, in 
the investigation of optimal paths, it is shown that if the harvest of one species has 
impact on the price of the other, optimal trajectories reach steady state faster for itself 
and slower for the other species. Further, when cross-price elasticities are sufficiently 
high, the paths go from being monotonic to feature over-or undershooting. </p>

<p>Analysis of multi-species and ecosystem models has been common in the bioeconomic 
literature at least since the 70s, whether it has been for the purpose of studying open </p>

<p>B Stein Ivar Steinshamn </p>

<p>stein.steinshamn@nhh.no </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Business and Management Science, Norwegian School of Economics, Bergen, 
Norway </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>access, maximum yield or economic rent; see e.g. Anderson (1975), Silvert and Smith  (1977) and May et al. (1979). More recent contributions include Kasperski (2015) and 
Wang and Ewald (2010). In these articles, however, the interaction between species has 
always been biological, ecological and sometimes technical, but rarely in the market. 
Most articles that take market-interactions into account, are empirical studies, and 
many, if not most of them, seem to deal with interaction between aquaculture and wild 
caught fish (Anderson 1985; Ye and Beddington 1996). 
Analysis of substitutes and complements in demand is fundamental in economics 
and well known from basic textbooks as well as numerous empirical studies, e.g. 
Meng (2014) and Garcia and Raya (2011) to mention a couple of recent ones. This 
phenomenon also applies to natural resources such as fish products (Vignes and Etienne  2011). However, there are only a few studies that systematically investigate implica-
tions of cross-price effects on optimal management of renewable resources from a 
conceptual and theoretical angle, probably because such models have a tendency to 
become very messy. There are, however, some recent exceptions to this rule, and Quaas  et al. (2013) is one such. Their results are based on the assumption that there are two 
stocks with identical regeneration functions. Using this assumption they investigate 
the effect on resilience of substitutability and complementarity. Quaas and Requate  (2013) study the effects of preferences for diversity in a model with an arbitrary number 
of fish species. An older example is Ruseski (1999) who uses a two-stage, two-period 
model to analyze the behavior of two agents, one regulated and one unregulated, who 
harvest identical products from two separate stocks. He finds that trade in the presence 
of market power and divergent management regimes may produce unexpected results. 
Related problems have also been srtudied in the literature on the interplay between 
international trade and renewable resources like, for example, Chichilnisky (1994), 
Brander and Taylor (1997) and Bulte and Barbier (2005) None of these, however, 
deal with the same problem as studied here. 
In this article a continuous time two-species bioeconomic model is applied to 
investigate the effects of economic (market) interaction between species on opti-
mal management from a sole-owner perspective. That is, the owner, or manager, 
of both species is one and the same who maximizes the combined revenue from 
the two stocks. This may seem far-fetched if the term sole-owner is taken literally. 
But here the more common interpretation of the term sole-owner is used, namely 
that it represents the managing authority of a nation who behave as a sole-owner on 
behalf of its inhabitants in order to maximize the aggregated resource rent. There 
may, for example, exist two stocks in different parts of the country's EEZ, but with 
certain similar characteristics making them substitutes in the market. Such charac-
teristics can be that both species are "white fish" or that they are used for fish-meal 
or fish-oil production. This sole-owner exploits a certain degree of direct and indi-
rect market power, and the demand functions are assumed to be stationary over 
time. 
The biological model is a surplus growth model, but the only interaction between 
the species is in the market where the quantity of each species may affect the price 
of the other. The aim of this study is to investigate implications of market interaction 
upon the optimal steady state and on the paths leading to the steady state. Revenue 
and costs for each species are separable, but the harvest of one species enters the </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>inverse demand function for the other. There are several possibilities, for example 
that one species affects the price of the other, but not vice versa. The most realistic 
assumption is probably that they are true substitutes such that both species affect the 
other species' price. Somewhat facetiously, we can say that they predate on each others 
price. No technical or biological interactions are considered, but the two stocks can 
have completely different growth functions. No artificial assumptions about symmetry 
are made. 
The analysis is divided in two parts, first a steady state analysis and then a dynamic 
analysis. Each of these parts are again divided in two, based on whether the net revenue 
function depends on the state variable(s) or not. This is because the state variables turn 
out to play an important role for the results. In the steady state analysis, the results 
are derived analytically from the mathematical model. In the dynamic analysis, on the 
other hand, numerical methods are resorted to as it is beyond realistic expectations 
to hope for closed-form solutions of a highly non-linear system of four differential 
equations. </p>

<p>2 The generic model </p>

<p>The model is a continuous-time, bioeconomic model of the surplus-growth type, with 
two species, x and y, but with no biological interaction. The two species are assumed 
to be substitutes in the market implying that the cross-price elasticities are negative. In 
other words, the price of one species may depend on both own supply and the supply 
of the other species, and therefore there exist certain degrees of market power that are 
exploited. The generic inverse demand functions look as follows: </p>

<p>p x = p x (h x , h y ) 
p y = p y (h x , h y ) </p>

<p>where p i is price of species i and h i is harvest of species i. Technically it is assumed 
that ∂ p i /∂h j &lt; 0 for i, j ∈ (x, y). The net revenue function, in its most generic form, 
is then defined as </p>

<p>R(x, y, h x , h y ) = p x (h x , h y )h x + p y (h x , h y )h y − κ x (x, h x ) − κ y (y, h y ) 
(1) </p>

<p>where x and y denote the size of the respective stocks, and κ x and κ y are cost functions. 
The separability of the cost functions rule out technical interactions. 
The net revenue function is the objective function to be maximized with respect to h x 
and h y as control variables, whereas x and y are the state variables. The state and control 
variables are all functions of time, t. In addition there are two separate biological 
surplus growth functions, one for each species: f (x) and g(y). The infinite horizon 
dynamic optimization problem resulting from this leads to the following discounted 
Hamiltonian: </p>

<p>H = e 
−δt R(x, y, h x , h y ) + λ[ f (x) − h x ] + γ [g(y) − h y ] </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>where λ and γ are costate variables, also functions of t, and δ is the discount rate. The 
first-order conditions for this general case are given by 1 </p>

<p>∂ H/∂h x = ∂ H/∂h y = 0 
( 2 ) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>dλ/dt = −∂ H/∂ x, dγ /dt = −∂ H/∂ y </p>

<p>together with the dynamic constraints </p>

<p>dx/dt = f (x) − h x 
(3) </p>

<p>dy/dt = g(y) − h y 
(4) </p>

<p>and initial conditions x(0) = x 0 and y(0) = y 0 . Now let R with subscripts represent the 
first and second partial derivatives with respect to its respective arguments as defined in 
Eq. (1). For example R 1 ≡ ∂ R/∂ x and R 12 ≡ ∂ 2 R/∂ x∂ y. From the general definition 
of R it is seen that </p>

<p>R 12 = R 14 = R 21 = R 23 = R 32 = R 41 = 0. </p>

<p>The first-order conditions solved with respect to the discount rate yield the following 
two criteria: </p>

<p>δ = f (x) + 
R 31 
R 3 </p>

<p>dx 
dt 
+ 
R 33 
R 3 </p>

<p>dh x 
dt 
+ 
R 34 
R 3 </p>

<p>dh y 
dt 
+ 
R 1 
R 3 
(5) </p>

<p>δ = g (y) + 
R 42 
R 4 </p>

<p>dy 
dt 
+ 
R 43 
R 4 </p>

<p>dh x 
dt 
+ 
R 44 
R 4 </p>

<p>dh y 
dt 
+ 
R 2 
R 4 
. 
(6) </p>

<p>The two equations in (2) can be used to find explicit solutions for the costate variables 
and hence their time derivatives. Taking the first-order conditions and solving for 
dx/dt, dy/dt, dh x /dt and dh y /dt by eliminating the costate variables and their time 
derivatives, yields the following system of non-linear first-order differential equations: </p>

<p>dh x /dt = 
R 34 A − R 44 B 
C </p>

<p>dh y /dt = 
−R 33 A + R 43 B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>where 2 </p>

<p>1 It is assumed that H is continuous, strictly concave and twice differentiable in the control variables h x 
and h y . Concavity in H is fulfilled when demand is downward sloping and the cost functions are convex. 
2 It is worth noticing that A depends on y and h y whereas B depends on x and h x . </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>A = R 4 (g − δ) + R 42 (g − h y ) + R 2 </p>

<p>B = R 3 ( f − δ) + R 31 ( f − h x ) + R 1 
C = R 33 R 44 − R 34 R 43 . </p>

<p>Together with the dynamic constraints (3) and (4), using R 32 = R 41 = 0, this consti-
tutes a system of four differential equations. In the following we assume decreasing 
marginal return on harvest, that is R 33 &lt; 0 and R 44 &lt; 0. If, in addition, we assume 
C &gt; 0, then R will be partially convex in the control variables. This is fulfilled if the 
direct price effect is stronger than the cross-price effect, which seems to be a reason-
able assumption. Restricting the search for optimal steady states to the closed intervals 
0 ≤ h i ≤ M SY i , and x and y to be between zero and the natural carrying capacity, 
will guarantee the existence of both a maximum and minimum in the control variables 
on this interval. In the following, focus will be on interior solutions when they exist. 
Finding closed form solutions for the time paths x(t), y(t), h x (t) and h y (t) for this 
system is far too optimistic, even in the simplest case. In stead, in the section Dynamic 
Analysis the system will be solved numerically. But first we will look at steady states. </p>

<p>3 Steady state analysis </p>

<p>In this section the properties of steady states are analyzed, and it is all based on the 
fairly general formulation of the net revenue function found in (1). By setting all time 
derivatives equal to zero, it is seen that the criteria (5) and (6) simplify to the following 
in steady state: </p>

<p>δ = f (x) + 
R 1 
R 3 
(7) </p>

<p>δ = g (y) + 
R 2 
R 4 
(8) </p>

<p>These two equations together with h x = f (x) and h y = g(y) yield four equations to be 
solved for x, y, h x and h y . The following analysis is divided in two parts, namely when 
the net revenue (in practice costs) depends on the state variables x and y, and when 
it does not. These two cases can be thought of as representing purse seine technology 
and trawl technology, respectively. With purse seine technology there is usually little 
or no relationship between total stock size and costs of harvest whereas for trawl 
technology it is believed to be a strong relationship between stock size and costs. In 
reality, stock-dependence of costs varies along a continuum for both technologies. This 
dependence has been studied empirically by a number of authors, for example Harley  et al. (2001) and Sandberg (2006). In this article, I focus on the extreme cases where 
the stock-elasticity is either zero or one, in order to isolate the most interesting results. </p>

<p>3.1 State-independent net revenue </p>

<p>When costs do not depend on the stock size, all costs can technically be integrated in 
the demand function by defining the price as a price net of costs. Then an interesting </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>conclusion can be made directly from observing the two simple expressions (7) and 
(8). This is stated in the following proposition: </p>

<p>Proposition 1 If there is no stock-dependece of any kind in the revenue function, the 
optimal steady state stock and harvest levels will not be affected by own-or cross-price 
parameters. </p>

<p>Proof If the stock levels are not explicitly included in the revenue function, or the 
derivatives are zero, the last terms in (7) and ( 8) will disappear as R 1 = R 2 = 0. Then 
these two equations will be two independent equations in x and y, and the steady state 
will only depend on biological parameters and the discount rate </p>

<p>The implication of Proposition 1 is that without stock-dependence the Golden Rule, 
as stated, for example, in Grafton et al. (2004, p. 113) is exactly the same in a two-
species model with market interactions as it would be with two single-species models, 
namely that the marginal biological productivity of each stock should equal the alter-
native rate of return represented by the discount rate. As such, this is a generalization 
of the same result from single-species models. Mathematically it may look simple, 
but thinking about it, this is a fairly strong and far from obvious observation. Let us 
put it this way: If the quantity of herring in the market affects the price of mackerel 
and vice versa, this will not affect the optimal standing stock levels of mackerel or 
herring, nor their corresponding harvest levels, as the technology in these two fish-
eries are purse seine technology. If, on the other hand, the quantity of haddock in the 
market affects the price of cod and vice versa, this will affect the optimal standing 
stock and corresponding harvest levels as the fisheries in question are characterized 
by bottom trawl technology where the size of the stock has strong impact on the cost 
of harvesting. The intuition behind this is much the same as in the single-species case 
with downward sloping demand. 
But even in the case where the optimal steady state is not affected by the cross-
price parameters, the paths towards the steady will typically be affected irrespective 
of technology, as we shall see later. In practice, the way stock levels affect net revenue 
is through the cost functions. More specifically, therefore, if the cost functions are 
stock independent, optimal steady states will be characterized by the condition that 
marginal biological growth should equal the discount rate. In the special case that 
the discount rate is zero, the optimal steady states will correspond to the maximum 
sustainable yield levels. One practical implication of this is that cross-price effects 
do not make any difference with respect to steady states in schooling (purse seine) 
fisheries whereas they may make a difference in demersal (trawl) fisheries. </p>

<p>3.2 State-dependent net revenue </p>

<p>With state-dependent net revenue, the last terms in Eqs. (7) and (8) come into play as 
R 1 and R 2 are no longer zero. The cross-price parameters enter the equations through 
the denominator of the last term, namely R 3 and R 4 . From (1) it is seen that these are 
given as </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>R 3 = 
∂ p x 
∂h x 
h x + p x + 
∂ p y 
∂h x 
h y − 
∂κ x 
∂h x 
(9) </p>

<p>R 4 = 
∂ p x 
∂h y 
h x + p y + 
∂ p y 
∂h y 
h y − 
∂κ y 
∂h y 
. 
(10) </p>

<p>It is the cross-price parameters that are of interest here, and these are </p>

<p>∂ p y 
∂h x </p>

<p>&lt; 0 in (9) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>∂ p x 
∂h y </p>

<p>&lt; 0 in (10). Let us concentrate on R 4 , as the analysis of R 3 is equivalent. As 
the two species are supposed to be substitutes, the cross-price elasticities are negative 
implying that R 4 is smaller when the cross-price effect is taken into account than if 
the species are economically independent, that is </p>

<p>∂ p x 
∂h y </p>

<p>= 0. This will unambiguously 
lead to a higher steady state stock and a more conservative harvest policy. This can be 
stated in the following proposition: </p>

<p>Proposition 2 Assuming strictly concave growth functions and net revenue that 
depends positively on the stock level for one of the stocks, then if the harvest of one 
species reduces the price of the other species, this implies a higher optimal steady 
state stock for the affecting stock. </p>

<p>Proof Assume that the only cross-price effect present is from h y to p x . Then it is 
seen from (10) that having such a cross-price effect compared to not having it, will 
reduce R 4 through the term </p>

<p>∂ p x 
∂h y </p>

<p>&lt; 0. As R 2 &gt; 0, reducing R 4 will make the fraction 
R 2 /R 4 larger. From (8) it is seen that making R 2 /R 4 larger has to be compensated by 
a smaller g (y) for a given δ. R 4 and g (y) therefore goes in the same direction. As 
g is assumed to be concave, smaller g (y) implies going to the right (higher stock). 
Exactly the same reasoning applies to (9). </p>

<p>Proposition 2 says that if the harvest of y affects the price of x negatively, then this 
will imply a higher optimal standing stock of y, and vice versa, compared to when 
there is no such effect. The intuition is that the downward pressure on revenue from the 
other species can be regarded as an addition to the marginal cost for the sole owner, and 
therefore we have the well-known phenomenon that higher costs have a conservative 
effect. The interesting thing is that this only comes into effect when net revenue also 
depends on the stock. In practice, it implies that for demersal fisheries, where we expect 
high stock dependence of costs, cross-price relationships play a conservative role 
whereas for schooling fish stock (typical pelagic fisheries) cross-price relationships 
have little or no effect. This is an important result as it adds to the well-known fact 
that schooling species are already most vulnerable and exposed to extinction and 
collapse due to the technology in the fishery, which usually is purse seine. Demersal 
species caught by trawl, on the other hand, is to large extent naturally protected by 
their behavior (uniform distribution in the ocean) which makes it extremely costly to 
harvest on very small stocks even under open access regimes. </p>

<p>Corollary The steady state stock for one of the species, for example x, may depend on 
the harvest of the other, y, even if the opposite is not true. This happens when R 1 = 0 
but R 2 = 0 or vice versa. </p>

<p>Proof This follows directly from (7) and (8) </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>Even though (7) and (8) are easy to relate to conceptually, closed-form solutions 
for the steady state levels are almost impossible to find except for the simplest spec-
ifications of demand and cost functions, and even in these cases the expressions tend 
to become too long and messy to be of any practical value. 
In the case of linear demand functions, that is when </p>

<p>p x (h x , h y ) = a x − b x h x − c x h y 
(11) </p>

<p>p y (h x , h y ) = a y − b y h y − c y h x 
(12) </p>

<p>where a i is the constant term, b i is the sensitivity to own harvest and c i is the cross-price 
sensitivity, the following statement is proposed: </p>

<p>Proposition 3 If demand functions are linear, the steady-states are determined exclu-
sively by the sum of the cross-price parameters. </p>

<p>Proof It is seen from the analysis above and Eqs. (7) and (8) that the cross-price 
parameters only affect the steady state through the terms R 3 and R 4 . In the linear case 
these terms can be written </p>

<p>R 3 = a x − 2b x h x − (c x + c y )h y 
R 4 = a y − 2b y h y − (c x + c y )h x . </p>

<p>Thus it is seen that the cross-price parameters enter the equations that determine the 
steady state in the form of the sum of the two parameters. </p>

<p>In other words, no matter how asymmetric the economic and biological submodels 
are with respect to demand, cost structure and surplus growth function, if the cross-
price parameters change value such that their sum remains the same, the steady state 
will remain unchanged. In practice this means that the two fish stocks can be quite 
different regarding economic, biological and technological aspects, if we let the cross-
price parameters change values such that for example c x = 3 and c y = 7 instead of 
the other way around, it will not change the steady state. </p>

<p>4 Dynamic analysis </p>

<p>Not only the steady state, but also the optimal paths leading to the steady state are 
of interest, and, in particular, how they are affected by the cross-price parameters. 
As in the previous section, the case with stock-independent net revenue, in practice 
stock-independent costs, will be analyzed first. Thereafter the case where net revenue 
depends on the stocks, is investigated. </p>

<p>4.1 State-independent net revenue </p>

<p>Here we let net revenue depend on harvest only and not on the stock size. This is 
representative of fisheries with purse seine technology targeting schooling fish, and </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>only the extreme case is investigated, that is no trace of the stocks in the net revenue 
function whatsoever, which implies that, in addition to R 32 = R 41 = 0, from earlier, 
we also have </p>

<p>R 1 = R 2 = R 31 = R 42 = 0 </p>

<p>just like in Sect. 3.1. The first-order conditions corresponding to (5) and (6) then 
simplifies to: </p>

<p>δ = f (x) + 
R 33 
R 3 </p>

<p>dh x 
dt 
+ 
R 34 
R 3 </p>

<p>dh y 
dt </p>

<p>δ = g (y) + 
R 43 
R 4 </p>

<p>dh x 
dt 
+ 
R 44 
R 4 </p>

<p>dh y 
dt </p>

<p>This system can be solved for the time derivatives of the control variables yielding </p>

<p>dh x /dt = 
R 4 R 34 (g − δ) − R 3 R 44 ( f − δ) 
C 
(13) </p>

<p>dh y /dt = 
R 4 R 33 (g − δ) − R 3 R 34 ( f − δ) 
C 
(14) </p>

<p>and C denotes the determinant as earlier, assumed to be positive. It is immediately 
seen that in the case with stock independent net revenue, although the steady states 
are unaffected by the cross-price parameters, the optimal paths are affected. 
Together with the dynamic constraints, (3) and (4), the equations (13) and (14) 
constitute a system of four non-linear first-order differential equations. In principle, 
this is a solvable system yielding the optimal time paths for h x (t), h y (t), x(t) and y(t). 
Due to the non-linearities, meaningful closed-form solutions are beyond expectation. 
The only approach, therefore, is to solve the system numerically. 
In order to perform numerical analysis, special functional forms must be deter-
mined. Here linear inverse demand functions will be applied where the price of each 
species depends on both own harvest and the harvest of the other species as specified 
by Eqs. (11) and (12). In addition it is assumed that the growth functions, f and g, 
are standard logistic surplus growth functions: </p>

<p>f (x) = r x x 1 − 
x 
K x </p>

<p>g(y) = r y y 1 − 
y 
K y </p>

<p>where r i and K i have the conventional interpretations as intrinsic growth rate and 
carrying capacity for i = (x, y), see Clark (2010). The numerical specification of the 
above equations is given in appendix. The numbers are not meant to represent any real 
fisheries, rather they are meant to describe completely hypothetical, but still possible, 
fisheries with meaningful characteristics; in other words fisheries that very well might 
have existed. </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>First, the optimal steady state is found: From Proposition 1 we know that in this </p>

<p>x 
60 
y 
332.5 
h x 
9 
h y 
74.8125 </p>

<p>case the steady state is independent of the cross-price parameters c i . In a non-linear 
four-dimensional system, there are multiple possible solutions, but fortunately, for the 
cases considered here, there is only one possible solution within the feasible region 
x ∈ [0, K x ], y ∈ [0, K y ] and h i ∈ 0, </p>

<p>r i K i </p>

<p>4 . Remember that with the logistic model </p>

<p>r K </p>

<p>4 represents maximum sustainable yield. 
In order to investigate the effect of cross-price parameters on the optimal time paths, 
we start by looking at the development of x with (c x = 0.08 ) and without (c x = 0) 
cross-price effect in the case without stock-dependence. This is illustrated in Fig. 1. 3 
The stock is assumed to be overexploited initially (like so many fish stocks around 
the world), and it is seen that the approach to the steady state is asymptotic due to the 
non-linearity [as opposed to the bang-bang approach resulting from linear models, see 
Clark (2010)]. The boundary conditions applied here are x 0 = 45 and h x at t = 65 
equal to the optimal steady state harvest. It is reassuring to see that with these initial 
conditions the stock level approaches the independently calculated steady states even 
when they are not restricted to it. I take this as a confirmation that the paths are really 
optimal. It is seen that without cross-price effect both stock and harvest approach 
their steady state values monotonically. With cross price effect from the harvest of y 
on the price of x, on the other hand, the stock development of x goes down initially 
(undershooting) and reaches its steady state more slowly. The harvest is first higher 
than the steady state level, then goes below and then gradually approaches it. This is 
both an interesting, and very robust result. 
The corresponding stock and harvest development for y is illustrated in Fig. 2. Here 
the initial stock is y 0 = 300. 
The most noticeable feature is that the effect on species x, whose price is affected by 
the other species, is more pronounced than for species y, which causes the effect. The 
stock of y approaches its steady state faster with cross-price effect than without.This 
is the opposite of the x-stock development which even goes down initially. In other 
words, the behavior of the x-stock is less bang-bang like and the y-stock more bang-
bang like with cross-price effect from y on x. </p>

<p>4.2 State-dependent net revenue </p>

<p>In the section "Steady state analysis" there was significant difference between the cases 
with and without stock-dependent net revenue, in practice costs. It may therefore be </p>

<p>3 The numerical solutions have been found using dsolve (numeric) in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Maple</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">18</rs>. </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
6 0 
7 0 </p>

<p>hx 
x 
hx-c 
x-c </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Stock and harvest development for species x with (x-c and hx-c) and without (x and hx) cross price 
effect when there is no stock-dependence. Harvest of y affects price of x </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
6 0 
7 0 </p>

<p>hy 
y 
hy-c 
y-c </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Stock and harvest development for species y with (y-c and hy-c) and without (y and hy) cross price 
effect when there is no stock-dependence. Harvest of yaffects price of x </p>

<p>interesting to investigate whether there is any noticeable difference in the dynamics 
case also. In this section the standard cost function derived from the Schaefer produc-
tion is applied: </p>

<p>κ x (h x , x) = 
C x h x 
x </p>

<p>κ y (h y , y) = 
C y h y 
y </p>

<p>where the values for the parameters C x and C y are given in Appendix. </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>Table 1 Results from the 
dynamic analysis and 
state-dependent costs </p>

<p>c x = 0 
c x = 0.08 
c x = 0 
c x = 0.08 
c y = 0 
c y = 0 
c y = 0.01 
c y = 0.01 </p>

<p>x 
77.1 
110.6 
78.7 
121.1 </p>

<p>y 
409.6 
413.4 
410.2 
413.0 </p>

<p>h x 
9.4 
7.3 
9.4 
5.8 </p>

<p>h y 
75.5 
75.4 
75.5 
75.4 </p>

<p>First, the long-term optimum is calculated, and this is affected by the cross-price 
parameters as shown earlier. The steady state for the case without cross-price effects 
and for some combinations of parameter values are reported in Table 1. 
According to Proposition 2, x will increase when c y increases and vice versa, 
everything else equal. This is confirmed by the table. Typically the stock will also 
increase when the own price-parameter increases, but not necessarily so, as seen when 
c y increases from 0 to 0.01 for c x = 0.08. In this case the stock y decreases slightly. 
Figures 3 and 4 illustrate the time-paths for x and y, respectively, with and without 
cross-price effects, but this time with stock-dependent costs. 
It is seen that the paths increase monotonically and approach the steady state asymp-
totically without any sign of over-or undershooting when there is no cross-price effect. 
And, just like in Figs. 1 and 2, it is seen that the introduction of market interaction leads 
to over-and undershooting for the species whose price is affected by the other species. 
The effect, however, is not very pronounced. It is further confirmed that the steady 
states themselves are affected by the stock-dependence, but this is almost negligible 
for the affecting stock. 
Thus, it is seen that whether net revenue is stock-dependent or not does not have any 
significant impact on the shape of the optimal time paths although it has significant 
impact on the steady states. The shape of the time-paths are mainly affected by the 
cross-price parameters. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
6 0 
7 0 
hx 
x 
hx-c 
x-c </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Stock and harvest development for species x with (x-c and hx-c) and without (x and hx) cross price 
effect when there is stock-dependence in costs. Harvest of y affects price of x </p>



<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
6 0 
7 0 </p>

<p>hy 
y 
hy-c 
y-c </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Stock and harvest development for species y with (y-c and hy-c) and without (y and hy) cross price 
effect when there is stock-dependence in costs. Harvest of y affects price of x </p>

<p>5 Summary and conclusions </p>

<p>This article is about a two-species bioeconomic model where the only interaction 
between the species is in the market. In other words, there is no technical or biological 
interaction between the species. This may be relevant for a social planner, for example 
the managing authorities in a country, who has to deal with several species around the 
coast. These species may be located in different geographical areas and therefore do 
not interact biologically, but their products are sold in the same market. 
The article is structured in two parts, first steady-state analysis and then dynamic 
optimal path analysis. These parts again are divided in two sections, with and with-
out state-dependent costs. Steady states are studied both analytically and numerically 
whereas optimal paths are studied numerically. The main result from the steady-state 
analysis is that if the harvest of one species has impact on the price of another species, 
then this has a positive effect on its stock. The effect increases with the stock-elasticity 
in the cost function. In other words, whether cross-price elasticities have impact on the 
steady state or not, depends on the technology in the respective fisheries. In fisheries 
where effort and costs are independent of the total stock size, cross-price elasticities 
have no such effect. This is typically relevant for fish species with schooling behavior, 
and therefore harvested using purse seine technology. For demersal species, which 
typically are caught using bottom trawl, the cross-price elasticities actually affect the 
optimal size of standing stocks and corresponding harvest. More precisely, the qualita-
tive effect is such that the presence of cross-price elasticities have a conservative effect 
on the stocks. In other words, the presence of a substitute in the market reduces the 
price and thereby profitability, and hence has a conservational effect on the stock. This 
was shown analytically in the section Steady State Analysis. This is a generalization 
of the same result from single-species models. A novel result found here is that, in 
the case of linear demand functions, it is the sum and only the sum of the cross-price 
parameters that affect the steady states, and not their composition or individual values. </p>



<p>S. I. Steinshamn </p>

<p>In the section Dynamic Analysis it is shown that optimal paths towards steady 
state are affected by cross-price elasticities whether costs depend on stock or not. If 
harvest of one species has impact on the price of another species, optimal trajectories 
reach steady state faster for itself and slower for the other species. Further, when the 
cross-price influence is sufficiently strong, the stock and harvest paths go from being 
monotonically increasing or decreasing to exhibit over-or undershooting. Overshoot-
ing is defined as the case where the stock is induced to increase initially even though the 
initial stock is above the target. Undershooting is defined as the case where the stock 
is induced to decrease although it already under the target steady state. In other words, 
over-and undershooting refer to regions where the variables make an initial departure 
from the target before they come "back on the track". No trace of over-or undershoot-
ing have been found when the cross-price effects are removed. It is the indirect gain 
made by the cross-price effects that make over-and undershooting optimal. 
The results presented here are fairly novel, and therefore there is scope for quite 
a bit of future research. This may include the combination of biological and mar-
ket interaction, the combination of technological interaction and market interaction. 
And it may, of course, include other numerical examples, numerical analysis of other 
functional forms, and not least empirical investigation of particular cases. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The author is thankful for financial support from the Norwegian Research Council 
throgh Grant No. 255530 (MESSAGE). </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Interna-
tional License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the 
source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>

<p>6 Appendix </p>

<p>In this appendix the numerical specification applied in the analysis is summarized in 
the following table </p>

<p>r x 
K x 
r y 
K y 
δ 
0.25 
150 
0.4 
760 
0.05 
a x 
b x 
c x 
10 
0.1 
0.08 
a y 
b y 
c y 
15 
0.02 
0.01 
C x 
C y 
200 
1500 </p>





<p>Predators in the market: implications... </p>







</text></tei>