<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecoj.12114" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>There is a widespread belief that peer effects are important in charitable giving but little evidence on 
how donors respond to their peers. Analysing a unique data set of donations to online fund-raising 
pages, we find positive and sizeable peer effects: a £10 increase in the mean of past donations 
increases giving by £2.50, on average. Donations respond to both very large and very small amounts 
and to changes in the mode. We find little evidence that donations signal charity quality -our 
preferred explanation is that donors use information on earlier donations to decide what is 
appropriate for them to give. </p>

<p>have raised more than £1 billion for a wide range of different charities through the 
biggest individual online fund-raising website, and this has been growing over time. 
1 The 
way that individual online fund-raising typically works is as follows: Individual fund-
raisers decide on a fund-raising activity to raise money for their chosen charity (these 
activities often involve a sporting event such as running a marathon or swimming the 
English Channel but novelty activities such as head shaving are also popular). The fund-
raisers then set-up personalised web pages on a fund-raising website and invite people to 
make donations to their chosen charities. Most of the donations come from the fund-
raiser's friends, family and colleagues. 
2 Almost all are made online via the fund-raising 
page and are passed directly by the fund-raising website to the charity. The online 
donations are listed on the fund-raising page, with the most recent first. 
3 Information on 
how much has been given and by whom, 
4 is then visible to each donor who arrives at the 
fund-raising page. When donors go to the page to make a donation they can see all the 
previous online donations that have been made; we exploit this set-up to look at whether 
donors are influenced by how much other people have given. 
Of course, donations made to the same page will be correlated because of the 
common characteristics of the peer group -the fund-raiser's friends, family and work 
colleagues. Our identification strategy relies on the within-page variation in the 
observed history of donations that arises as a result of donors arriving at the website at 
different times. 
5 In essence, we argue that there is plausibly exogenous variation in the 
set of donations observed by each donor because exactly when donors make their 
donation is subject to random factors, such as when they turn on their computer and 
find time to log on to the fund-raising website to make a donation. We further discuss 
our identification strategy in Sections 3 and 4. 
We provide direct evidence on the direction and magnitude of peer effects in giving. In 
principle, it is possible that other people's donations could 'crowd out' giving (Warr, 1982;  Roberts, 1984) but we show that higher (average) donations cause people to increase the 
amount that they give -a £10 increase in the mean of past donations causes people to give 
£2.50 more on average. One potential criticism of a simple 'linear-in-means' specification is 
thatitcan mask the potentiallydiversewaysinwhich peereffects can work(Sacerdote,2011). </p>

<p>1 For comparison, total donations from individuals in the UK were estimated to be £13 billion in 2010-11. 
2 We do not have direct information on the identity of the donors or their relationship with the fund-
raiser. However, we have supporting evidence that they are mainly friends, family and colleagues from a 
separate survey of approximately 19,000 Justgiving donors (Payne et al., 2011). Of those who had been asked 
to give to a fund-raising page, 84% had been asked by a family member (of whom 87% said that they always 
gave when asked); 96% had been asked by a friend (67% always gave); 89% had been asked by a colleague 
(48% always gave); 70% had been asked by a charity representative (only 9% always gave). 
3 Donors can see up to 30 or 50 past donations by scrolling down without having to click through. As the 
median number of donations is 33, this means that most donors can see all previous donations in one go. 
4 Donors can choose to donate anonymously. Unfortunately, whether or not a donation was given 
anonymously was miscoded for more than half our sample, which means that we cannot do a full analysis on 
the effects of anonymity. Where we do have information, we find that 11% of donations are made 
anonymously. Large and small donations are more likely to be made anonymously as might be expected. We 
find that the effect of large and small donations is not affected by whether or not the donation was made 
anonymously. We also find that the probability of giving anonymously does not change after a large or small 
donation. 
5 Mas and Moretti (2009) provide perhaps the closest study to our study in terms of identification. They 
look at the effect of peers' productivity in the context of supermarket checkouts, exploiting randomness 
arising from the scheduling of checkout operatives. They estimate individual-specific fixed effects; we do not 
have sufficient observations to allow us to do this. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>1054 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>We are able to shed light on the nature of peer effects in giving and show that the amount 
given is affected both by 'shining knights' (very large donations) and by 'widows' mites' (very 
small donations), as well as there being 'herd behaviour' (donations following the mode). 
We also exploit the richness of our data to explore some of the underlying 
mechanisms that might explain why donors respond positively to how much their peers 
have given. We find no evidence that peer donations provide a signal about the quality 
of a charity (Vesterlund, 2003), or that peer effects are only related to fund-raising 
targets (Andreoni, 1998). The explanation that is most consistent with observed 
behaviour is that donors use information on (the distribution of) past donations as a 
benchmark in deciding how much it is appropriate for them to give. 
The plan of the remainder of the study is as follows. The next Section provides 
information on our data -a subset of fund-raising pages set-up by runners in the 2010 
London marathon. Section 2 discusses our empirical strategy. Section 3 explores the 
effect of other donations and the nature of the peer effects by looking at the effect of 
large and small donations and changes in the mode, whereas Section 4 contains our 
main econometric analysis. Section 5 explores alternative explanations of why donors 
might respond to their peers and Section 6 concludes. </p>

<p>1. The Setting -Online Fund-raising </p>

<p>In this study, we focus on fund-raising pages set-up by people who raised money for 
charity by running in the 2010 London marathon and who fund raised via the two largest 
fund-raising websites in the UK -Justgiving (www.justgiving.co.uk) and Virgin Money 
Giving (http://uk.virginmoneygiving.com/giving/). The London marathon claims to 
be the biggest single fund-raising event in the world and, of the approximately 35,000 
runners who line up each year, an estimated 20,000 are raising money for charity. 
Our initial sample contained information from more than 12,000 fund-raising pages. 
The data were captured on 30 April 2010, five days after the marathon took place. For 
each page we have all the information that is publicly available (examples of fund-
raising pages are shown in online Appendix B). This includes the fund-raiser's name, 
the charity they were fund-raising for, their target amount (if they had one), the total 
amount raised offline at the time the data were captured, the full history of donations 
to the website, the donors' names (where available) and the amount given. 
Table 1 provides a basic sample summary. Each fund-raiser gets an average of 34.5 
donations and raises an average of £1,093 in online donations and £335 in reported 
offline donations. 
6 Donations are spread over time. The typical page is set-up just over 
two months before the marathon. Some fund-raisers create pages up to six months 
before the event. Over this period, fund-raisers may sequentially target different sets of 
people within their wider peer group. In this case, any observed change in donation 
amounts (e.g. following a large or small donation or a change in the mode) may simply 
reflect the arrival of a new donor group. When we look at amounts donated in Section 4, 
we test for changes in arrival rates; we also carry out an additional robustness check 
focusing only on donations made within the same day. </p>

<p>6 These totals exclude the value of UK Gift Aid tax relief, which is additionally passed to the charity by the 
tax authorities. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>The mean online donation is £30.31. The distribution of donations is heavily 
concentrated with spikes at £10 and £20 (and to a lesser extent other rounded 
amounts) with just over half of all donations at exactly £10 or £20. 
The distributions of donation amounts and the number of donations per page are 
skewed by the presence of a few very successful fund-raisers 
7 and generous donors. In 
our analysis, we exclude pages which have single donations of more than £1,000. We 
also exclude pages with fewer than 10 donations (1,783 pages) or more than 100 
donations (212 pages). With these exclusions, our sample is 10,597 pages. </p>

<p>2. Empirical Strategy </p>

<p>A commonly estimated model in the peer effects literature is a linear-in-means model. 
In our case, this can be written as: </p>

<p>Table 1 
Sample Summary Statistics </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Minimum </p>

<p>1st 
percentile Median </p>

<p>99th 
percentile Maximum </p>

<p>Full sample 
Number of donations per 
page </p>

<p>34.5 
25.4 
1 
1 
29 
114 
370 </p>

<p>Number of days 
74.8 
50.7 
0 
0 
67 
204 
225 
Online donations -all 
£30.31 
£66.02 
£1 
£5 
£20 
£200 
£10,000 
Total raised online per 
page </p>

<p>£1,093 £1,401 
£1 
£20 
£778 
£5,710 
£40,326 </p>

<p>Total raised offline per 
page </p>

<p>£335 
£1,115 
£0 
£0 
£0 
£3,077 
£53,000 </p>

<p>Proportion of pages with 
target </p>

<p>0.803 </p>

<p>Proportion of pages with 
target achieved </p>

<p>0.395 </p>

<p>Target amounts 
£99,985 £9.9 m 
£0.01 
£200 
£1,500 
£9,000 
£1 bn 
Number of fund-raisers 
12,750 </p>

<p>Estimation sample 
Number of donations per 
page </p>

<p>36.7 
19.7 
10 
10 
33 
91 
100 </p>

<p>Number of days 
79.5 
49.5 
2 
6 
73 
205 
225 
Online donations 
£29.81 
£46.58 
£1 
£5 
£20 
£200 
£1,000 
Total raised online per 
page </p>

<p>£1,115 
£916 
£53 
£136 
£892 
£4,458 
£12,260 </p>

<p>Total raised offline per 
page </p>

<p>£310 
£827 
£0 
£0 
£0 
£2,725 
£43,897 </p>

<p>Proportion of pages with 
target </p>

<p>0.823 </p>

<p>Proportion of pages with 
target achieved </p>

<p>0.420 </p>

<p>Target amounts 
£1,511 
£832 
£200 
£200 
£1,500 
£5,000 
£7,000 
Number of fund-raisers 
10,597 </p>

<p>7 The biggest individual fund-raisers include Richard Branson who raised more than £35,000 for Virgin 
Unite, including a single donation of £6,550, and popstar Natalie Imbruglia, also running for Virgin Unite 
who raised more than £32,000, including a single donation of £10,000. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>1056 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>d in ¼ a þ c 
d i;nÀ1 þ u in ; </p>

<p>where the donation amount, d, given by donor n to page i is estimated as a function of 
the mean of all past donations to the same page up to that point 
d i;nÀ1 . 
There are well-known problems in identifying peer effects (Brock and Durlauf, 2001;  Manski, 2003). In our case we can rule out the reflection problem as the amount given 
by the nth donor will not affect the donations made by previous donors. Correlated 
effects are a clear concern. Donors to a page will share socio-economic and 
demographic characteristics because they are likely to be drawn from a fund-raiser's 
network of friends, family and work colleagues. They will also be subject to the 
common influence of the same fund-raiser who may be more or less effective at 
encouraging people to give. 
Our identification strategy therefore relies on within-page variation in observed past 
donations arising as a result of donors arriving at a page at different times to make 
their donation. Of course there is likely to be some endogenous sorting within a page: 
close family and friends will be among the first to give, as well as people with a strong 
connection to the cause -and both these groups are likely to give more. This is clear 
from the observed decline in mean donation size over the first few donations to a page 
(see Figure 1a). In our analysis, we run regressions excluding the first three donations 
to a page -this is both to allow for some donation history for subsequent donors to 
respond to and also because the first three donations are systematically higher than the 
rest and may possibly behave differently to those that follow (e.g. because they are from 
the donor's closest friends/family). Our main findings are not sensitive to this sample 
selection. It is clear from a randomly selected sub-sample of pages (Figure 1b) that 
there is also non-systematic variation in the size of donations within a page that causes 
the within-page mean to vary. We exploit this variation to identify peer effects. 
As a number of studies have pointed out (see discussion in Sacerdote, 2011), a 
limitation of the linear-in-means model is that it may over-simplify -and potentially 
obscure -the many different ways in which peer effects work in practice. Following 
Sacerdote (2011), who presents a typology of potential peer effects in relation to 
education, we can distinguish a number of different ways in which peer effects might 
affect giving. 
First, donations may be affected by 'shining knights', i.e. by large donations to a 
page. A large donation is likely to place upwards pressure on amounts given among 
donors who want to signal their wealth (Glazer and Konrad, 1996) or generosity 
(Harbaugh, 1998) or the closeness of their relationship with the fund-raiser by being 
among the biggest donors. This would be likely only to affect the upper end of the 
distribution among donors competing to give the most. Large donations may, however, 
have a wider effect on all donors to the extent that they crowd out other giving, 
assuming standard public good giving (Warr, 1982; Roberts, 1984) or crowd it in if 
there is a threshold for the provision of the public good (Andreoni, 1998). Large 
donations may also provide a signal about the quality of the charity (Vesterlund, 2003)  or affect individuals' beliefs about how much it is appropriate to give, assuming such 
beliefs are based on the observed distribution of amounts given. 
Second, donations may be affected by 'widows' mites', i.e. by small donations to a 
page. Becker (1974) emphasised that donations might be motivated by the desire to </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>avoid social stigma as well as to gain social prestige. Some donors will want to get away 
with giving as little as possible and a small donation will allow them to reduce how 
much they give. This is likely to affect donations at the lower end of the distribution. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Mean of Amount </p>

<p>£ </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 25 </p>

<p>Amount Donated </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>Mean of Previous Donations £ </p>

<p>10 
20 
30 
Order of Donations on Page </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. (a) Mean Amount by Order of Donation on Page (full sample). (b) Within-page 
Variation in Past Mean (randomly selected sub-sample) </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>More generally, a small donation may also affect all others in ways similar to a large 
donation -i.e. through crowd out/crowd in, signalling effects or benchmarking. 
Third, there may be 'herd behaviour'. Donors with a desire to conform may try to 
target how much they give on the modal amount (Bernheim, 1994). In this case, the 
amount given may be affected by (changes in) the mode of donations to a page. As 
with small and large donations, a change in the mode may affect only some donors or 
all other donors to a page. 
Table 2 summarises the different ways in which donations by peers might influence 
giving. The online fund-raising data allow us to explore these different types of peer 
effects. In particular, we can look directly at the effect of 'shining knights' and 'widows' 
mites' and of changes in the mode on amounts given. We also look at whether large 
and small donations affect only some donors (in the upper/lower end of the 
distribution) and/or whether the effects appear to be more general. </p>

<p>3. Estimates of Peer Effects -A Natural Experiment Approach </p>

<p>To look at the effects of 'large' and 'small' donations and changes in the modal 
amount we estimate the following specification: </p>

<p>d in ¼ a þ bT in þ z </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>in d þ u in ; 
where d in refers to the nth donation to fund-raising page i (in pounds) and T in is a 
'treatment' indicator equal to 1 if the donation follows a large/small donation or a 
change in the mode, or equal to 0 otherwise. We define a 'large' donation as being 
at least twice the page mean (and more than £50). The mean 'large' donation is £102. 
A 'small' donation is defined as half the page mean. The mean 'small' donation is 
£8.61. We look separately at increases and decreases in the mode. 
8 z in is a vector of 
controls for the systematic component of the timing of donations -the order on the 
page and the date of donation respectively. The error term is decomposed into a </p>

<p>Table 2 
Nature of Peer Effects in Giving </p>

<p>Donation will have an effect on ÁÁÁ </p>

<p>Type of donation 
… only some donors if there is: 
… all donors if there is: </p>

<p>Large donations 
('Shining knights') </p>

<p>Competition to be the 
top donor </p>

<p>Crowding in/out 
Signalling quality 
Benchmark for appropriate amount </p>

<p>Small donations 
('Widows' mites') </p>

<p>Desire to avoid being the 
bottom donor </p>

<p>Crowding in/out 
Signalling quality 
Benchmark for appropriate amount </p>

<p>Modal donations 
('The herd') </p>

<p>Following the herd; giving 
what other people give </p>

<p>Crowding in/out 
Signalling quality 
Benchmark for appropriate amount </p>

<p>8 Where there is more than one mode, we look at increases in the maximum of the modes and decreases 
in the minimum of the modes. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>constant page-specific effect that will pick up common differences in donations across 
pages and a pure random error term: u in = g i + v in . We estimate this model using a 
fixed-effects regression that removes the effect on donations of the page-specific 
unobservable factors. We drop pages where a large or small donation occurs within the 
first three donations; we also restrict the first change in the mode to occur after the 
first three donations. 
Our identifying assumption is that there is random variation in the timing of 
donations, after controlling for systematic within-page variation, such that the random 
error term, v in , is uncorrelated with the 'treatment' variable, T in . We would argue that 
this assumption is plausible, at least within a narrow window of donations, given that 
the exact timing of when people make an online donation will be subject to a number 
of exogenous factors. Exactly when donors arrive at the page -and hence whether they 
arrive just before or just after a large/small donation -will be influenced by a number 
of random factors such as when they turn on their computer and when they find a 
moment to log on to the fund-raising website to make an online donation. Under our 
identifying assumption, the coefficient b will identify the average causal effect of a 
large/small donation on the amount subsequently given. 
There are two possible violations of this identifying assumption. One is if large/small 
donations affect the extensive margin -i.e. the probability that donors make a 
donation. In this case, the observed donations before and after would be subject to a 
differential selection process. A second is if fund-raisers sequentially target different 
groups of donors -in which case the first large/small donation would herald the 
arrival of a new group of donors. We have no information on visits to the websites, or 
on donor characteristics that allow us to test for these effects directly. However, we can 
look at the arrival rate of donations (i.e. the number of donations made to a page per 
day) to give some indication of whether either of these is likely to be material. Both a 
change in the extensive margin and the arrival of a new group of donors would be 
associated with a change in the arrival rate. 
Figure 2 plots the distributions of the arrival rates (i.e. the number of donations per 
day) on the days before and after each of the four treatments we look at. There is little 
obvious change in the distributions and this is confirmed by Kolgomorov-Smirnov 
tests. The p-values for the equality of distributions before/after large and small 
donations are 0.219 and 0.352, respectively, whereas the p-values for the equality of 
distributions before/after increases and decreases in the mode are, respectively, 0.094 
and 0.668. In all four cases we fail to reject that the distributions of arrival rates are the 
same. 
By contrast, Figure 3 provides clear evidence of effects on amounts given after each 
of the four 'treatments'. Donations increase after both a large donation and an 
increase in the mode, whereas donations fall after both a small donation and a 
decrease in the mode. These findings are confirmed by regression results, summarised 
in Table 3. We vary the size of the window before and after -looking at a very narrow 
window of one donation before/after and also five donations before/after and five 
before and ten after. We do a further robustness check where we restrict the before 
and after donations to lie within the same day, making it less likely that they have been 
made by different groups of (sequentially targeted) donors. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>The results in panels (a)-(d) confirm that there is a change in how much subsequent 
donors give following each of the four treatments. The coefficients indicate fairly 
sizeable effects. Within a narrow window of one donation either side, large donations 
are associated with a £12.49 increase in donation size, compared to a previous donation 
level around £20, whereas a small donation reduces donation size by a similar 
magnitude. The effects also appear to be fairly persistent affecting at least 10 donations 
that follow; this is likely to work not just through the first large/small donation or 
change in mode but also through changes in subsequent donations. 
As discussed in the previous Section, large and small donations may affect amounts 
given either by triggering competition among some donors (other large/small 
donations) or, more generally, by influencing all other donors through crowd out/in, 
signalling or benchmarking effects. We shed light on this by looking at the effect on 
subsequent amounts given, excluding other large and small donations. This will tell us 
whether the effect is (just) to trigger other large/small donations or whether it goes 
wider than this. The results, shown in panels (e) and ( f ), indicate that large and small 
donations do indeed trigger other similar-sized donations (the coefficients are smaller 
than in panels (a) and (b)) but that there are effects even on 'regular-sized' donations. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Arrivals </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Arrivals </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Arrivals </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Arrivals </p>

<p>Before 
After </p>

<p>Before 
After </p>

<p>Before 
After </p>

<p>Before 
After </p>

<p>Kernel = Epanechnikov, 
Bandwidth = 0.3174 </p>

<p>Number of Donations Per Day 
Number of Donations Per Day </p>

<p>Number of Donations Per Day 
Number of Donations Per Day </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>Kernel = Epanechnikov, 
Bandwidth = 0.3089 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>Kernel = Epanechnikov, 
Bandwidth = 0.3404 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>Kernel = Epanechnikov, 
Bandwidth = 0.3246 </p>

<p>p-value = 0.219 
p-value = 0.352 </p>

<p>p-value = 0.094 
p-value = 0.668 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(c) 
( d) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Distributions of Arrivals. Before/After: (a) A 'Large' Donation; (b) A 'Small' Donation; (c) An 
Increase in Mode; and (d) A Decrease in Mode 
Notes. A large donation is defined as twice the page mean and at least £50. A small donation is 
half the page mean. We focus on the first large/small donation or change in mode to occur on a 
page, excluding those within the first three donations. p-value is for test of equality of 
distributions (Kolgomorov-Smirnov). </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>The coefficients in panels (a)-(d) indicate that the peer effects are increasing in 
amount size -a large donation is associated with a bigger effect than an increase in the 
mode. We explore this further by looking at the effects of different-sized large 
donations (twice previous mean, three times previous mean, five times previous mean 
and more than ten times previous mean). As in previous studies (Shang and Croson,  2009) we find that larger donations produce a greater response from subsequent 
donors, at least up to very large donations of ten or more times the page mean. 
Combined with our results on the effects of large/small donations and changes in the 
mode, this supports our use of a linear-in-means model in the next Section. 
Finally, we look at whether there is evidence of spillover effects from donors giving 
more in response to a large donation on one fund-raising page to how much they 
give on other fund-raising pages. We do this by exploiting the fact that, within 
the Justgiving sample, we can identify donors who give to more than one fund-raising 
page. We construct a donor-level panel of amounts given sequentially across different 
pages. </p>

<p>9   We estimate an equation of the following form: </p>

<p>d sj ¼ a þ b 1 T sj þ b 2 T ðsÀ1Þj þ g j þ x sj ; </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Mean of Amount </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Mean of Amount </p>

<p>Mean Amount -Donations Before/After 
Mean Amount -Donations Before/After </p>

<p>Mean Amount -Donations Before/After 
Mean Amount -Donations Before/After </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Mean of Amount </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Mean of Amount </p>

<p>-5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 4 5 
-5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>-5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 4 5 
-5 -4 -3 -2 -1 0 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>(a) 
( b) </p>

<p>(c) 
( d) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Mean Amounts Given Before/After: (a) A 'Large' Donation; (b) A 'Small' Donation; 
(c) An Increase in Mode; and (d) A Decrease in Mode (all donations measured in £) 
Notes. A large donation is defined as twice the page mean and at least £50. A small donation is 
half the page mean. We focus on the first large/small donation or change in mode to occur on a 
page, excluding those within the first three donations. </p>

<p>9 We drop 4% of donations which were made on the same day as we cannot identify donation order. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>where d sj refers to the sth donation of donor j. T sj is an indicator equal to 1 if there has 
been a large donation (within ten donations) to the page currently visited, whereas 
T (sÀ1)j is an indicator equal to 1 if the previous page visited by the donor had a large 
donation. b 1 captures the own-page effect and b 2 any spillover effect of a large 
donation on a previously visited page. We estimate this equation on the full sample of 
( Justgiving) donors but the own-page and spillover effects are identified from donors 
who give to multiple pages. We include a trend to allow for the fact that donors may 
reduce their donations as they are asked to sponsor more people. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Effect of Large/Small Donation and Change In Mode </p>

<p>One before/ 
one after </p>

<p>One before/one 
after (same day) </p>

<p>Five before/ 
five after </p>

<p>Five before/ 
ten after </p>

<p>(a) Effect of a 'large' donation 
After 
12.458** 
13.392** 
12.611** 
12.134** 
(0.789) 
(2.609) 
(0.661) 
(0.496) 
N 
15,508 
6,464 
68,926 
102,492 </p>

<p>(b) Effect of a 'small' donation 
After 
À11.411** 
À9.493** 
À11.169** 
À10.232** 
(0.911) 
(2.090) 
(0.770) 
(0.550) 
N 
14,499 
6,600 
58,858 
91,422 </p>

<p>(c) Effect of an increase in the mode 
After 
À0.424 
1.755 
0.887 
1.137* 
(1.211) 
(2.818) 
(0.961) 
(0.671) 
N 
11,394 
7,137 
55,272 
80,104 </p>

<p>(d) Effect of a decrease in the mode 
After 
À3.250* 
À2.195 
À2.732** 
À4.142** 
(1.290) 
(3.772) 
(0.959) 
(0.666) 
N 
12,665 
8,754 
55,114 
87,904 </p>

<p>(e) Effect of a large donation -excluding other large donations 
After 
2.541** 
2.724** 
3.051** 
2.793** 
(0.348) 
(1.001) 
(0.278) 
(0.208) 
N 
14,690 
6,079 
6,5386 
9,6125 </p>

<p>(f ) Effect of a small donation -excluding other small donations 
After 
À2.050* 
À1.214 
À0.610 
À1.014* 
(1.124) 
(2.751) 
(0.830) 
(0.606) 
N 
12,399 
5,546 
4,8705 
7,2011 </p>

<p>Twice 
mean </p>

<p>Three times 
mean </p>

<p>Five times 
mean </p>

<p>Ten times 
mean </p>

<p>(g) Effect of different-sized large donations (five donations before/five after) 
After 
11.154** 
10.663** 
17.396** 
20.327** 
(1.043) 
(0.973) 
(1.825) 
(3.155) 
N 
27,647 
24,585 
12,285 
4,409 </p>

<p>Notes. Dependent variable = £ amount given. A large donation is twice the page mean and at least £50. A 
small donation is half the page mean. All regressions include fund-raising page fixed effects. Columns (III) 
and (IV) in panels (a)-( f ) and all columns in panel (g) include additional controls for place within page 
(linear trend), indicators for days since page was set-up (capped at 100) and indicator variables for two days 
and one day before the marathon, the day of the marathon and (any) days after the marathon. *p &lt; 0.10; 
**p &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>Our results confirm the own-page crowd-in effect. Our estimate is 5.91 (SE 3.11) 
which is significant at the 10% level. The estimated spillover effect is also positive 
(5.60), but insignificant (SE 1.80), suggesting that there is no crowd out of a large 
donation to one page on donations to other fund-raising pages. </p>

<p>4. Econometric Analysis </p>

<p>In this Section we present estimates from a linear-in-means model. The attraction of 
the mean is that it provides a simple summary statistic of the distribution of 
donations that donors appear to be responding to. We have shown in the previous 
Section that donors respond to large and small donations and to the mode. The 
linear-in-means model provides a parsimonious specification to capture these 
behaviours, particularly when we come to test for heterogeneity of effects in the 
next Section. 
We estimate the following specification: </p>

<p>d in ¼ a þ c 
d i;nÀ1 þ z </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>in d þ u in ; 
where d in refers to the nth donation to fund-raising page i and 
d i;nÀ1 is the mean of all 
donations made online to the fund-raising page up to the point at which the nth donor 
arrives at the page. 
10 As before, z in is a set of indicators for the order in which the 
donation occurs on the page and date controls, including indicators for the days since 
the page was set-up (capped at 100) and also for the days in the immediate run up to 
the day of the marathon. 
We are interested in the coefficient c which measures the extent to which a higher 
level of past donations across the page is associated with people giving more or less. The 
OLS estimate of c is likely to be biased upwards by unobservable factors that affect all 
donations to a page that can be captured in a page-specific error term, i.e. u in = g i + v in 
These factors will include both shared (unobserved) characteristics of the donors to a 
page, such as their income, as well as (unobserved) characteristics of the fund-raiser, 
such as their persuasive power or their personal connection to a particular cause. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Because of the latter factor, we cannot identify the effect of past donations from within-
donor variation across pages but only from variation within pages over time. 
Estimating a fixed-effects model using a within-groups specification, however, will 
lead to a downwards-biased estimate of c because the mean-differenced error term, 
u in À ð1=N À 1Þ 
P N 
j¼2 u ij , will be negatively correlated with the mean-differenced 
lagged dependent variable, 
d i;nÀ1 À ð1=N À 1Þ 
P N À1 </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>
d ij . In the case of estimating the 
effect of the past mean of all donations, this bias will not be negligible even though we 
have a long panel (the average number of donations per page in our analysis is 37 and 
we observe many pages with 50 or more donations), unlike the standard case of 
'Nickell bias' (Nickell, 1981). We show this formally in online Appendix C. </p>

<p>10 The donor will also see the amount raised offline up to the point at which they arrive at the website, 
whereas we only know the total amount raised offline at the time the data were captured. As a robustness 
check, we run the regressions only on pages with no offline donations. 
11 The fact that fund-raiser characteristics may influence all donations to a page means that exploiting 
information on multiple donations by the same donor to different pages is unlikely to lead to an unbiased 
estimate. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>Our preferred approach, therefore, is to estimate c using the Arellano and Bond  (1991) GMM estimator.   12   First, the page-specific effect g i is eliminated by first differencing: </p>

<p>Dd in ¼ cD 
d i;nÀ1 þ Dz </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>in d þ Dv in : 
In this first-differenced model there is, however, an endogeneity problem due to the 
correlation between 
d i;nÀ1 and v i,nÀ1 . As shown in online Appendix C, the bias of the 
OLS estimator in this first-differenced model does not decrease with N. In our main 
specification we use the two-period lag and the three-period lag of the page mean as 
instruments for the (change in) mean of past donations, with different reduced form 
coefficients per donation order. The Arellano-Bond test for serial correlation does not 
reject the null of no second-order serial correlation, implying that the two-period lag is 
valid as an instrument. The Hansen test does not indicate that the instrument set is not 
valid. 
Our main results are presented in Table 4. For comparison, we show both 
the upwards-biased OLS and the downwards-biased fixed-effects results for all 
specifications. Our preferred GMM results lie between these two for all specifications. 
We also present results for the effect of the last donation and the effect of the mean of 
the past five and ten donations. As demonstrated in online Appendix C, the extent of 
downwards bias to the fixed-effects estimator is greater when looking at the past mean 
of all donations to a page than for the simple lagged dependent variable. 
In our main specification, the GMM estimate of c is positive and significant, implying 
positive peer effects. This finding is robust to a number of robustness checks, 
presented in Appendix A. In our main specification we drop the first three 
observations from each page -we also show results dropping no and five observations. 
We also vary the instrument set, using different lags as instruments for the past mean. 
The estimated coefficient indicates that a £10 increase in the mean of past 
donations leads to people giving £2.50 more on average. To illustrate the magnitude of 
this, the effect of a £150 donation following three donations of £20 would be to 
increase giving by £8.13, whereas the effect of a £150 donation following six donations 
of £20 would be to increase giving by £4.64 (in both cases, the effect on giving in the 
case of the lagged dependent variable would be to increase giving by £2.86). This 
highlights an important feature of estimating the effect of the past mean -that the 
effect of a single donation diminishes, the later it occurs on a page. This is intuitively 
plausible as a donor may give less weight to a single large donation if there are more 
other donations on the page. We also find further empirical support for this finding by 
repeating the analysis from the previous Section and looking at the effect of a single 
'large' donation made after 10 donations and after 15 donations to a page (compared 
with a large donation that occurs between five and ten donations). The estimated 
effect of a large donation is reduced by £1.19 when it occurs after 10 or more donations 
and by £2.50 when it occurs after 15 or more donations. This lends further support to 
including the past mean of all donations as the preferred empirical specification and 
we focus on this specification in the next Section. </p>

<p>12 We estimate the GMM model using xtabond2, see Roodman (2006). </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>5. Inside the Black Box -Exploring Why Peers Matter </p>

<p>We would like to understand why peers matter. As discussed in Section 3, there are 
several potential explanations. On the basis of our findings so far, we can rule out that 
donors are (just) aiming to be the most generous donor to a page as both small 
donations and changes in the mode matter; large donations also have a wider effect 
than simply triggering similar-sized donations. By analogous reasoning, we can also 
rule out that donors are (just) trying to avoid being the least generous donor to a page. 
The observed effects of large and small donations also imply that donors do not just try 
to follow the herd and match the mode. 
Table 2 summarised a number of potential explanations of why large/small 
donations and changes in the mode may affect all donations that follow. Our 
estimates of peer effects are positive, ruling out classic crowd out. Andreoni (1998)  discusses the case in which threshold contribution levels, such as a minimum level of 
funding required before the public good can be produced, can result in crowd in -</p>

<p>Table 4 
Main Regression Results </p>

<p>(I) 
(II) 
(III) </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>Page fixed 
effects </p>

<p>Difference 
GMM </p>

<p>(a) Past_mean (£) 
0.525** 
À0.359** 
0.250** 
(0.013) 
(0.023) 
(0.028) 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(1), p-value 
0.000 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(2), p-value 
0.322 
Hansen test, p-value 
(217 over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.864 </p>

<p>(b) Mean, last ten (£) 
0.458** 
À0.114** 
0.202** 
(0.012) 
(0.012) 
(0.019) 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(1), p-value 
0.000 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(2), p-value 
0.313 
Hansen test, p-value 
(217 over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.397 </p>

<p>(c) Mean, last five (£) 
0.361** 
À0.047** 
0.116** 
(0.011) 
(0.007) 
(0.010) 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(1), p-value 
0.000 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(2), p-value 
0.348 
Hansen test, p-value 
(217 over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.771 </p>

<p>(d ) Past_donation (£) 
0.125** 
0.003 
0.022** 
(0.005) 
(0.003) 
(0.001) 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(1), p-value 
0.000 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(2), p-value 
0.051 
Hansen test, p-value 
(217 over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.630 </p>

<p>Notes. Dependent variable: donation amount (£). Sample size: I = 10,597, NI = 364,286. Instruments are the 
second and third-period lag of the (level) independent variable. All regressions include additional controls 
for place within page (linear trend), indicators for days since page was set-up (capped at 100) and indicator 
variables for two days and one day before the marathon, the day of the marathon and (any) days after the 
marathon. **p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>essentially large donations make it more likely that the threshold will be reached, 
which can encourage other donations. The potential effects of thresholds are relevant 
to the London marathon fund-raising pages, the majority of which have fund-raising 
targets. We find that peer effects are stronger for pages with a target but we also find a 
positive and significant effect for pages without a target (Table 5, column (I)). This 
indicates that targets do not provide the full explanation of the observed peer effects. 
There are further interesting differences in behaviour around the target. Regression 
analysis, summarised in Table 6, columns (I) and (II) shows, first, that the size of the 
first donation to take the total over the target donation is significantly higher and 
second that donations are lower on average after the target than before. Assuming as 
before that there is some random variation in exactly when donors arrive at a page 
(and that they are equally likely to arrive before or after the target, within a narrow 
window), this could be interpreted as a negative effect of hitting the target on 
donations. One important caveat to this is that it is possible for fund-raisers to change 
their target (e.g. to increase the target amount once it has been reached). We have no 
evidence on the extent to which this happens in practice. 
Finally, column (III) of Table 6 provides the results from a further GMM regression 
in which the past mean of donations is interacted with an indicator for the donor 
arriving after the target has been reached. This tests whether the crowd-in effect of past 
donations is the same on either side of the target. We find that the coefficient on the 
interaction term is negative and similar in magnitude to the coefficient on the past </p>

<p>Table 5 
Testing for Heterogeneous Effects </p>

<p>(I) 
(II) 
(III) 
(IV) 
(V) </p>

<p>Past_mean (£) 
0.104** 
0.160** 
0.098** 
0.264** 
0.214** 
(0.042) 
(0.041) 
(0.031) 
(0.032) 
(0.034) 
Past_mean 9 page with target 
0.158** 
(0.050) 
Past_mean 9 medium charity 
À0.043 
(0.057) 
Past_mean 9 large charity 
0.078 
(0.056) 
Past_mean 9 major charity 
0.085 
(0.054) 
Past_mean 9 charity age &gt; 10 years 
0.127** 
(0.047) 
Past_mean 9 charity age &gt; 20 years 
0.018 
(0.047) 
Past_mean 9 overseas charity 
À0.079 
(0.045) 
Past_mean 9 young donors 
0.020 
(0.046) 
Number of observation = NI 
364,286 
183,619 
280,660 
260,362 
364,286 
Number of pages = I 
10,597 
5,248 
8,208 
8,194 
10,597 </p>

<p>Notes. Difference GMM: Dependent variable = donation amount (£). All regressions include additional 
controls for place within page (linear trend), indicators for days since page was set-up (capped at 100) and 
indicator variables for two days and one day before the marathon, the day of the marathon and (any) days 
after the marathon. Instruments are the two-period and three-period lag of the past mean. **p &lt; 0.01. 
Medium, large and major charities have incomes of £1 m-£5 m, £5 m-£50 m and £50 m+ respectively. 
Young donors are defined by the fund-raiser being &lt;40. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>mean implying that there is no crowd-in effect of past donations once the target has 
been reached. 
Another possibility is that donations may be important as a signal of the quality of the 
charity, with higher (lower) donations indicating that the particular cause is more (less) 
worthy of support (Vesterlund, 2003). To explore this empirically we adopt an idea, 
proposed by Heutel (2013), that the information content of past donations should be 
more important for smaller charities and for younger charities, for charities operating 
overseas whose activities are less easy to observe directly and for younger donors. To 
implement this we match data from the Charity Commission Register, comprising all 
registered charities in England and Wales. We are able to find a match in the case of 78% 
of fund-raising pages (some of those we cannot match are Scottish and Irish charities), 
although information is not always available for all charities even where a match is made. 
Table 5 summarises the results from a set of regressions that include interaction 
terms, allowing the effect of the past mean to vary by, respectively -the size of the 
charity, the age of the charity, the location of charitable activity (UK or overseas) and 
the age of the fund-raiser (which proxies for the age of donors, defined by a cut-off of 
40). The results provide little support for this particular signalling story. The effect of 
past donations is actually stronger for larger charities and for older charities, although 
the differences are not statistically significant. We find no difference in peer effects 
between overseas and UK-based charities. We find no evidence of statistically 
significant differences by age. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Table 6 
Donations Around the Target Amount </p>

<p>(I) 
(II) 
(III) 
Fixed 
effects </p>

<p>Difference 
GMM </p>

<p>Difference 
GMM </p>

<p>Target donation 
53.988** 
47.506** 
50.554** 
(3.957) 
(3.455) 
(1.490) 
Reached target 
À3.517** 
À2.563 
3.588** 
(0.564) 
(1.482) 
(1.398) 
Past_mean (£) 
0.262** 
0.268** 
(0.040) 
(0.030) 
Past_mean 9 reached target 
À0.191** 
(0.030) 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(1), p-value 
0.000 
0.000 
Arellano-Bond test for AR(2), p-value 
0.940 
0.943 
Hansen test, p-value 
(over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.669 
0.898 
(205) 
(395) 
Number of observation = NI 
139,201 
135,308 
135,308 
Number of pages = I 
3,893 
3,893 
3,839 </p>

<p>Notes. Dependent variable = donation amount (£). All regressions include additional controls for place 
within page (linear trend), indicators for days since page was set-up (capped at 100) and indicator variables 
for two days and one day before the marathon, the day of the marathon and (any) days after the marathon. 
Target donation is the first donation to take the total over the target amount. Reached target is an indicator 
variable if the total is greater than the target. Instruments are the two-period and three-period lag of the past 
mean. **p &lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>13 We obtain information on the age of the fund-raiser by matching to the marathon results. Age of 18-40 
is the youngest category given in this database. We obtain similar results if we use older cut-offs. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>Instead of signalling charity quality, past donations may alternatively signal to donors 
how much it is socially appropriate for them to give. This is our preferred explanation 
of why past donations affect the amount given. When they arrive at a page, donors 
observe the distribution of past donations and use this to form -or update -their 
beliefs about how much they should give. These beliefs are likely to be donor (and 
possibly fund-raiser) specific; donors will have some idea of where they should locate 
within the distribution depending on their characteristics relative to those of other 
donors, including the proximity of their relationship with the fund-raiser, their 
support for a particular charity and their income (and possibly what their peers know 
about their income). Large/small donations and the mode will all affect amounts 
donated subsequently because they will be used to inform donors' beliefs. We cannot 
test this benchmarking story explicitly but it is consistent with the observed pattern of 
behaviour, including both donor responses to past donations and the fact that, 
individually, past donations have less effect if they occur later on in the page. </p>

<p>6. Discussion </p>

<p>This study adds to the empirical literature on what Andreoni has referred to as 'the 
inherent sociality of giving' by providing new evidence on the importance of peer 
effects in charitable giving in the context of online individual fund-raising. 
Online fund-raising is important to look at in its own right as a sizeable -and 
growing -channel for raising money for charities in the UK and elsewhere. It also 
provides an excellent setting to look at peer effects as it offers an environment in which 
donors observe donations from people within their naturally occurring peer groups 
(i.e. their friends, family and colleagues). 
There is an inevitable issue about the extent to which our findings can be 
generalised beyond this particular setting. The online fund-raising context in which 
donors can see all other donations -and know that their donations will be seen -is 
arguably quite distinctive. However, it is one that is potentially relevant to practitioners 
and policy makers interested in whether they can exploit the power of peer effects by 
providing similar levels of publicity to donations in other settings. Furthermore, by 
looking at data that span more than 1,000 different charities, we have been able to 
demonstrate that peer effects are not limited to particular charities or groups of 
donors, suggesting that the effects are likely to be more broadly generalisable. 
The richness of the data also allows us to explore potential explanations of why peers 
matter. We can reject that donors systematically compete to be the top, or strive to 
avoid being the bottom or align themselves with the mode or median. Our preferred 
explanation, which is consistent with the empirical findings, is that donors give what 
they think that they personally are expected to give where the distribution of the 
donations of their peers (along with other factors, such as income and specific cause) 
feed into the formation of that expectation. 
In this study we have analysed only a small sub-sample of the population of online 
fund-raising pages that are potentially available. Going forward, information from 
online fund-raising pages, particularly matched with social network data, has the 
potential to yield even further insights into how donors behave in social settings. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



<p>Appendix A. Robustness Checks </p>

<p>(I) </p>

<p>(II) </p>

<p>(III) </p>

<p>(IV) </p>

<p>(V) </p>

<p>(VI) </p>

<p>(VII) </p>

<p>(VIII) </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Excluding no 
observation 
Excluding first </p>

<p>5 observations </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Excluding first </p>

<p>3 observations </p>

<p>Past_mean (£) </p>

<p>0.250** </p>

<p>0.143** </p>

<p>0.358** </p>

<p>0.283** </p>

<p>0.188** </p>

<p>0.151** </p>

<p>0.216** </p>

<p>0.256** </p>

<p>(0.028) </p>

<p>(0.015) </p>

<p>(0.043) </p>

<p>(0.078) </p>

<p>(0.031) </p>

<p>(0.049) </p>

<p>(0.025) </p>

<p>(0.039) </p>

<p>Instruments </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>
d </p>

<p>i;nÀ4 </p>

<p>
d 
i;nÀ2 ; </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>i;nÀ3 </p>

<p>Collapsed </p>

<p>Collapsed </p>

<p>One-step </p>

<p>Arellano-Bond test </p>

<p>for AR(1), p-value </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>Arellano-Bond test </p>

<p>for AR(2), p-value </p>

<p>0.322 </p>

<p>0.275 </p>

<p>0.539 </p>

<p>0.325 </p>

<p>0.327 </p>

<p>0.332 </p>

<p>0.325 </p>

<p>0.326 </p>

<p>Hansen test, p-value 
(over-ID restrictions) </p>

<p>0.864 </p>

<p>0.768 </p>

<p>0.865 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.811 </p>

<p>0.209 </p>

<p>0.547 </p>

<p>0.864 </p>

<p>(217) </p>

<p>(217) </p>

<p>(217) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(217) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(323) </p>

<p>(218) </p>

<p>Notes. Difference GMM: Dependent variable = 
donation amount (£). All regressions include additional controls for place within page (linear trend), indicators for days </p>

<p>since page was set-up (capped at 100) and indicator variables for two days and one day before the marathon, the day of the marathon and (any) days after the marathon. 
**p &lt; </p>

<p>0.01. </p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L 
[ J U N E </p>

<p>University of Bristol 
University of Bristol 
University College London </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix B. Online Fund-raising. 
Appendix C. Bias of Fixed-effects Estimator. </p>

<p><rs type="software">Stata</rs></p>

<p>© 2013 The Author(s). 
The Economic Journal Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of the Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2015] </p>

<p>P E E R E F F E C T S I N C H A R I T A B L E G I V I N G </p>



</text></tei>