<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1467-8462.2013.12010.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs><rs id="software-2" type="software">Stata 
SE/MP</rs><rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Version 11</rs><rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs>For many years, social scientists the world over 
have been using large-scale, longitudinal data-
sets that are available to them to answer 
research-driven questions using evidence-
based analyses. This was first started in 1968 
on a large scale with the American Panel Study 
of Income Dynamics (PSID), housed at the 
University of Michigan. Indeed, this dataset 
continues to provide invaluable data on gen-
erations of individuals in households concern-
ing topics, such as educational attainment, 
housing situations and income and employment 
dynamics, and was described in detail by Hill 
(1991). 
Following the US lead, in 1984 the German 
Socio-Economic Panel Study (SOEP) was 
established at the German Institute for Eco-
nomic Research in Berlin, Germany. It built 
upon many ideas that had been established in 
the American PSID and introduced a hierarchi-
cal data structure to manage the complicated 
data at different levels, such as person, 
household, roster and sampled and over time. 
This structure is documented in Haisken-
DeNew and Frick (2005). In 1991, the British 
Household Panel Study (BHPS) was intro-
duced to cover the population of Great Britain. 
Taylor et al. (2010) document this study 
in many hundreds of pages of detailed 
information. 
Following the tradition of their American, 
German and British counterparts, in 2001 the 
Australian household panel dataset, House-
hold, Income and Labour Dynamics in 
Australia (HILDA) Survey, was released for 
the first time for academic and government use. </p>

<p>* Hahn: Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and 
Social Research, The University of Melbourne, Victoria 
3010 Australia; Haisken-DeNew: Melbourne Institute of 
Applied Economic and Social Research, The University of 
Melbourne, Victoria 3010 Australia; IZA, Bonn 53113 
Germany; and Department of Economics, McMaster 
University, Ontario L8S 4L8 Canada. Corresponding 
author: Haisken-DeNew, email &lt;johnhd@unimelb.edu. 
au&gt;. The authors wish to thank Simon Freidin for helpful 
comments. </p>

<p>The Australian Economic Review, vol. 46, no. 3, pp. 379-86°C </p>

<p>2013 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research 
Published by Wiley Publishing Asia Pty Ltd </p>

<p>Watson and Wooden (2002) and Wooden, 
Freidin and Watson (2002) document this first 
release. From the PSID to the HILDA Survey, 
the content of longitudinal datasets remained 
largely similar, although the data structure and 
variable naming schemes in which the data 
were stored could not be more heterogeneous 
between datasets. 
The key to retrieving data from a dataset is 
to understand the data file and variable naming 
scheme. The PSID system used a simple 
variable-naming scheme, in which variables 
were sequentially numbered (that is, v1 
followed by v2 and v3). This reached a 
limit in 1993 with the variable v23363 and, 
in 1994, the 'early release' (er) files started 
a new variable name scheme with er2001, 
which was followed by er2002 and so on. 
Due to the sequential naming of the variables, 
a range of variables was found in the family 
file for 1968, another range of variables for 
1969 and so on. However, one had no way of 
knowing the variable name of another year, 
given the variable name of a particular year. 
When the German SOEP addressed the issue 
of variable names, it followed the hierarchical 
structure of the data. Thus, the variable name 
ap3301 referred to the 'a' wave (1984), 'p' at 
the person level and the 33rd question of 
the person questionnaire, but specifically 
the first part of that multi-part question. 
However, there was no guarantee that the 
next year would follow suit in the variable 
naming. The BHPS went first into 'speaking 
variable names', in which the variable 
names no longer identified the order of the 
variable in a dataset, but rather the content and 
the year in which this content was collected. 
For instance, the variable rmovjb asked in the 
'r' wave refers to 'moved for employment 
reasons'. 
The Australian HILDA Survey follows the 
scheme outlined by the BHPS to a large extent 
and prefaces every single variable with a two-
letter category code. For instance, 'ws' refers to 
'wages and salaries'. The variable jwscmg 
asked in the 'j' wave (or 2010) deals with wages 
and salaries (ws) but specifically addresses 
'Main job, current weekly gross wages &amp; 
salary'. Indeed, the same variable 1 year </p>

<p>previously ('i' wave) is called deterministically 
iwscmg. By adding a wave indicator, a broad 
category indicator and 'speaking names', 
the HILDA Survey's variable names are 
moderately identifiable in content, even if 
one has never seen the specific question or 
questionnaire before. Clearly, data structure 
and variable-naming schemes have evolved 
over time. 
However, no previous dataset has changed 
its data structures or naming schemes to keep up 
with international longitudinal dataset 'best 
practice'. If one could have a tool to find the 
common denominators of the various panel 
datasets and create a simple, yet effective, 
manner of dealing with all datasets in the same 
way, then this would be useful to researchers of 
all datasets, especially those interested in 
comparative research. Indeed, the creators of 
the Cross-National Equivalent File, run out of 
Cornell University, New York, were faced 
immediately with this issue, as they attempted 
to deal with data from the American PSID, 
German SOEP, British BHPS and Australian 
HILDA Survey. The common redefining of 
variable names and content is described in Frick 
et al. (2007). 
Although the Australian HILDA Survey was 
the first large-scale, longitudinal dataset to 
establish itself in Australia, there are now many 
more datasets, as described in Table 1, address-
ing populations such as children in Australia, 
Aboriginal children, youths, recent immigrants, 
doctors and the homeless. All of the datasets 
have different instruments or questionnaires, 
different data structures and variable-naming 
schemes and little has changed since Haisken-
DeNew (2001). Thus, left alone, each dataset 
would require substantial investment in under-
standing the dataset before one could start to do 
any analyses. 
One software solution to the many of the 
issues raised here is a tool called '<rs id="software-4" type="software">PanelWhiz</rs>' 
&lt;<rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://www.panelwhiz.com</rs>&gt;, which is writ-
ten in and for the statistical package called <rs id="software-5" type="software">Stata</rs> 
&lt;<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://www.stata.com</rs>&gt;. For the German 
SOEP, its functionality is summarised in 
Haisken-DeNew and Hahn (2010). <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> 
was initially developed to deal specifically with 
the complexity of the German SOEP structure </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
September 2013°C </p>

<p>2013 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p>on variable naming, but has since expanded to 
cover all of the world's major household panel 
datasets. 
<rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> is a graphical user interface that 
allows users to extract data from known 
datasets in a controlled manner, without having 
to write data extraction code oneself. The 
structure of the data is in fact embedded into the 
data itself and is called up and read by 
<rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> to allow it to use this structure 
automatically, without the user having to 
delve further in the data structure. In terms 
of the amount of <rs type="software">Stata</rs> programming code, it 
is the largest-ever user-written collection of 
add-ons for <rs type="software">Stata</rs>. <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> provides in 
<rs type="software">Stata</rs> an analogous platform to what the 
<rs type="software">Integrated Public Use Microdata Series</rs> (for 
more information, see Minnesota Population 
Center 2001) does at the browser level. This 
article outlines the features of <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> in 
conjunction with Australian datasets that are 
listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>2. Issues of Structure in Australian Panel 
Data </p>

<p>The Australian HILDA Survey, in its simplest 
version, contains one single 'combined' file per 
wave or year, starting in 2001, such that any 
household-level information has been added to 
every person in that household. In addition, 
there is a master file which contains entries for 
each person who has ever entered into the 
HILDA Survey sample. The master file allows 
one to use this as a starting point and define the 
sample immediately (that is, a sample of only 
men, from 2001 to 2004). The (longitudinal) 
person identifier xwaveid is consistent over 
time and data files. The HILDA Survey, on the 
other hand, has no concept of a longitudinal 
household. All persons aged 15 and over are 
interviewed directly. Longitudinal identifiers 
for spouses, mothers, fathers etc. are also 
available, such that one could retrieve data on 
individual wages and of the spouse and use the </p>

<p>Table 1 Key Information on Major Economic Longitudinal Datasets in Australia </p>

<p>Dataset 
Information </p>

<p>HILDA Survey 
The Household, Income and Labour Dynamics in Australia Survey 
Website 
&lt;http://www.melbourneinstitute.com/hilda/&gt; 
References 
Watson and Wooden (2002) and Wooden, Freidin and Watson (2002) 
MABEL 
Medicine in Australia: Balancing Employment and Life 
Website 
&lt;https://mabel.org.au/&gt; 
References 
Joyce et al. (2010) and Yan et al. (2011) 
LSAC 
Growing Up in Australia: The Longitudinal Study of Australian Children 
Website 
&lt;http://www.growingupinaustralia.gov.au/&gt; 
References 
Gray and Smart (2009) and Commonwealth of Australia (2012b) 
LSIC 
Footprints in Time-The Longitudinal Study of Indigenous Children 
Website 
&lt;http://www.fahcsia.gov.au/about-fahcsia/publications-articles/research-publications/longitudinal-
data-initiatives/footprints-in-time-the-longitudinal-study-of-indigenous-children-lsic&gt; 
References 
Mullan and Redmond (2012) and Commonwealth of Australia (2012a) 
CASiE 
Consumer Attitudes, Sentiments &amp; Expectations in Australia 
Website 
&lt;http://www.melbourneinstitute.com/macro/CASiE/&gt; 
Reference 
Lim et al. (2012) 
Journeys Home 
A Longitudinal Study of Factors Affecting Housing Stability </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Website 
&lt;http://www.melbourneinstitute.com/journeys_home/&gt; 
Reference 
Scutella and Johnson (2012) 
LSAY 
The Longitudinal Surveys of Australian Youth </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Website 
&lt;http://www.lsay.edu.au/&gt; 
Reference 
Marks and Rothman (2003) 
LSIA 
The Longitudinal Survey of Immigrants to Australia </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Website 
&lt;http://www.immi.gov.au/media/research/lsia/&gt; 
Reference 
&lt;http://www.immi.gov.au/media/research/lsia/&gt; </p>

<p>Note: (a) Not currently supported by PanelWhiz, but under consideration for support.°C </p>



<p>Hahn and Haisken-DeNew: PanelWhiz and the Australian Longitudinal Data Infrastructure 381 </p>

<p>variables in the same regression. See Wooden 
and Watson (2007) and Wooden, Freidin and 
Watson (2002) for more information. 
Following this structure, the dataset 'Medi-
cine in Australia: Balancing Employment and 
Life' (MABEL), labour market survey of 
doctors, also uses a longitudinal person 
identifier xwaveid and also a one-letter wave 
indicator and a two-letter classification scheme 
for each variable. Thus, the variable ajshw 
refers to the 'a' wave (2008) and 'js' to 'job 
satisfaction' and the remaining 'hw' refers to 
'hours of work'. This variable is called bjshw in 
the following wave and so on. See Joyce et al. 
(2010) and Yan et al. (2011) for an overview. 
The Longitudinal Survey of Australian 
Children (LSAC) is a survey that started in 
2004 and contains two cohorts of children: the 
(K) kids cohort of 4-to 5-year olds and the (B) 
0-to 1-year-old baby cohort. The children are 
followed generally every year, along with 
detailed information on the mother, father or 
other guardians, as outlined in Commonwealth 
of Australia (2012b). The major identifiers are 
hicid: household identification number, the 
cohort and the wave. The focus is on the study 
child (SC) in a particular family, in which 
Parent 1 (P1) and Parent 2 (P2) are identified. 
Parents living elsewhere (PLEs) are also 
identified. In the LSAC, the variable names 
start with the wave letter (a-d), use a one-or 
two-letter code to reflect the topic area, such as 
'LC' for 'Learning and cognition outcomes', 
followed by a question or sub-question number. 
There are physically separate data files for each 
cohort and year. See also Gray and Smart 
(2009) for more detailed information. 
In a similar manner, the Longitudinal Survey 
of Indigenous Children (LSIC) addresses 
indigenous children, with an albeit smaller 
sample of under 2,000 children, but also 
focusing on two cohorts: the (K) kids cohort 
of 3.5-to 4.5-year olds and the (B) 16-to 18-
month-old baby cohort. The data use the 
xwaveid and wave to identify the children 
over time and also focus on the study child (SC) 
as in the LSAC. Mullan and Redmond (2012) 
provide a scientific overview of the LSIC, while 
Commonwealth of Australia (2012a) outlines 
the data content and reports some basic findings. </p>

<p>The Consumer Attitudes, Sentiments &amp; 
Expectations in Australia (CASiE) is an 
exceptional dataset, in that it is not a 
longitudinal dataset like the HILDA Survey, 
but rather is a series of repeated cross-sections, 
and has been available-monthly-since 1995, 
consisting of approximately 1,200 respondents 
every month. Thus, if one were interested in 
general movements from month to month, this 
dataset is of particular interest. Men and women 
aged from 16 to 65 years are asked primarily 
questions on economic expectations and con-
sumer sentiment. Each respondent is charac-
terised by gender, age, occupation, education, 
political party preference, home ownership, 
household income and post-code, in addition 
to many other time-changing indicators. The 
file structure has one file per year, with all 
12 months of a year put into the one file. 
Needless to say, there are very differing file 
structures and relational dependencies between 
files and datasets. The HILDA Survey, 
MABEL, LSAC, LSIC and CASiE are all 
similar in many dimensions, yet different 
enough to pose a challenge even for hardened 
empirical economists. </p>

<p>3. Common Interface for Australian Data </p>

<p>The obvious advantage of using <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> is 
the power of the common interface. Every 
survey supported by <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs>, regardless of 
original structure, is integrated into the system 
in a similar manner. The entire dataset is 
scanned for critical pieces of information: 
(i) which physical data files belong together 
in a data year; (ii) variable names and how they 
correspond to each other over time; and (iii) 
keywords associated with variable labels. 
In contrast to standard statistical software, 
one does not open a data file and select one 
single variable, but rather one can select an 
entire vector of variables belonging to each 
other. As all words used in variable labels are 
scanned, one can compile a total list of all used 
words from the labels and create an index of 
keywords or dictionary, linking each known 
keyword to a particular variable, which in turn 
can be related to an entire vector of variables 
which belong together over time.°C </p>

<p>2013 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
September 2013 </p>

<p>To start off, one selects the dataset of interest 
(in this case, HILDA Survey). Assuming that 
one were to start a data project from scratch, as 
in Figure 1, one would first be interested in 
opening either a specific wave or a keyword list. 
Here, we will examine a specific wave. The 
HILDA Survey contains information from 
2001 to 2011, and correspondingly, there are 
clickable links for each year's wave. A browse 
page is created when clicking on a year. 
However, many datasets contain thousands of 
variables, making the creation of browse pages 
a relatively slow process. <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> creates a 
browse page once when needed, and if the page 
already exists, <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> simply uses it. The 
browse page is valid for a given distribution of 
data. It may become necessary to delete and 
recreate the browse pages if, for instance, there 
is a new release or revised version of the data. 
In Figure 1, we select the 2010 wave [j -
2010]. In the HILDA Survey, for the 'j' wave 
(or 2010), the respondent is asked whether he 
has a long-term health condition, as indicated 
by the variable jhelth in Figure 2. However, one </p>

<p>can simply click on the 'item' called helth, 
which would represent all the years' informa-
tion from wave 'a' to wave 'k'. 
If one were to click on 'N' (that is, notes), one 
would see the following vector of variables in 
Figure 3, all associated with the item called 
'helth'. Clicking on 'S' would produce summary 
statistics and 'T' would produce tabulations. 
All words used in item labels become part of 
the keyword dictionary and can be searched. 
Thus, searching or clicking on the word 'unable' 
would produce output like in Figure 4. PanelWhiz 
would list all items having the word 'unable' in 
the item label. Items could then be immediately 
selected, regardless of the wave or year. 
After having selected several items and 
having stored the <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> project under a 
name, such as 'myproject', the Project Page 
would look something like in Figure 5. 
The items selected would be sorted by their 
categories, such as 'AN' for 'Ancestry'. Add-
ing any new items to the project would create 
additional entries in the Project Page. Here, in 
this particular view of the Project Page, we see </p>

<p>Figure 1 The PanelWhiz 'Start Page' </p>

<p>Start Page &gt; H 
HILDA [default] 
&lt;Project Page&gt; 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
┌──────────┬───────┬─────────────────────────┐ 
| Projects | W 
Waves | Specials | Help | About | 
───────────────┘ 
└──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>┌───────────────┐ 
────┘ S Select a wave └─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>[a -2001] 
[b -2002] 
[c -2003] 
[d -2004] </p>

<p>[e -2005] 
[f -2006] 
[g -2007] 
[h -2008] </p>

<p>[i -2009] 
[j -2010] 
[k -2011] </p>

<p>[Delete ALL Browsepages] 
[Generate ALL Browsepages] </p>

<p>┌─────────────────────┐ 
────┘ W Waves keyword index └───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>[*****] [a] [b] [c] [d] [e] [f] [g] [h] [i] [j] [k] [l] </p>

<p>[m] [n] [o] [p] [q] [r] [s] [t] [u] [v] [w] [x] [y] [z] </p>

<p>Figure 2 Browse Page Entries </p>

<p>┌────────────┐ 
──────┘ HE: Health └────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>[jhelth] 
( S T K N ) 
K1 Long term health condition 
X w p i 
helth: Long term health condition </p>

<p>°C 2013 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p>Hahn and Haisken-DeNew: PanelWhiz and the Australian Longitudinal Data Infrastructure 383 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Variable Notes </p>

<p>┌────────┐ 
──────┘ jhelth └───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>Itemname 
helth 
Itemlabel 
Long term health condition 
Category 
HE: Health 
Itemvector 
ahelth bhelth chelth dhelth ehelth fhelth ghelth hhelth ihelth jhelth khelth 
Iteminfo 
K2 | K1 | K1a | K1a | K1a | K1a | K1a | K1a | K5a | K1 | K1 | </p>

<p>────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>Figure 4 Keyword Browse Page </p>

<p>Start Page &gt; Entries for U 
&lt;Project Page&gt; 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
HILDA Keyword Browse Page for [ U ] 
PanelWhiz HILDA (5.0) Dec 2010 &lt;john@panelwhiz.eu&gt; 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
[*****] [a] [b] [c] [d] [e] [f] [g] [h] [i] [j] [k] [l] </p>

<p>[m] [n] [o] [p] [q] [r] [s] [t] [u] [v] [w] [x] [y] [z] 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
unable 
unchanged 
under 
undergraduate 
understanding 
undertake 
undertaking 
unemployed 
unemployment 
unhappy 
unincorporated union 
unit 
units 
unknown 
unmarried 
unpaid 
unrelated 
unsocial 
unsuccessful 
unsuitab 
unsuitable 
unsure 
until 
up 
ups 
us 
use 
used 
useful 
uses 
using 
usual 
usually 
uterine 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>[ unable ] 
TOP </p>

<p>X N J -f 
fiprbuh 
Was unable to heat home 
X N J -h 
hepuwrk 
Long term health conditions impacts on employment -Permanently unable to w 
X N J -j 
jbperm 
Permanently unable to work 
X N J -r 
rpnopay 
During last 12 mths have you been unable to meet a repayment on house </p>

<p>Figure 5 Project Page </p>

<p>Start Page &gt; H 
HILDA [myproject] 
&lt;Project Page&gt; 
──────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
┌─────────┬──────────────────────────────────────────────────────┐ 
| P 
Project | Prefs | Retrieved Data | Library | Help | Header | _ | 
────┘ 
└───────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
┌───────┬─────────────────────────────────────────────────┐ 
| S 
Start | Plugins | Update | Recover | Undo | Refresh | _ | 
┌───┘ 
└─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── 
| Add Items | New | Open | Save, As | Retrieval 
└─────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>┌─────────────────────────┬──────────────────┬───────┐ 
| Items [37] | Items+Vars | Items+Vars+Files | ? | _ | 
──────────────────────────────┘ 
└────────────────────────────────────────────────────── </p>

<p>AN: Ancestry </p>

<p>[ X _ _ w i ] ancob 
Country of birth 
a 
a-aancob 
b 
b-bancob 
c 
c-cancob 
d 
d-dancob 
e 
e-eancob 
f f-fancob 
g 
g-gancob 
h 
h-hancob 
i 
i-iancob 
j j-jancob 
k 
k-kancob </p>

<p>ED: Education </p>

<p>[ X _ _ W i ] edagels 
Age left school 
a 
a-aedagels 
b 
b-bedagels 
c 
c-cedagels 
d d-dedagels 
e 
e-eedagels 
f f-fedagels 
g 
g-gedagels 
h 
h-hedagels 
i 
i-iedagels 
j j-jedagels 
k 
k-kedagels </p>

<p>[ X _ _ W i ] edfts 
Full-time student 
a 
a-aedfts 
b 
b-bedfts 
c 
c-cedfts 
d 
d-dedfts 
e 
e-eedfts 
f f-fedfts 
g 
g-gedfts 
h 
h-hedfts 
i 
i-iedfts 
j j-jedfts 
k 
k-kedfts </p>

<p>°C 2013 The University of Melbourne, Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
September 2013 </p>

<p>the underlying variable names associated with 
each item. Thus, the variable in 2002 bancob is 
the 2002 ('b' wave) entry for the item ancob. 
By clicking on 'Retrieval', the data retrieval 
is started. File by file, the data files are opened, 
the selected variables are kept and possibly 
renamed, sub-sets of the files are stored in 
temporary files and then they are pieced 
together to create one rectangularised file in 
<rs type="software">Stata</rs> 'long' format (observations stacked on 
each other, year by year). </p>

<p>4. Conclusions </p>

<p><rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> is a tool written entirely in <rs type="software">Stata</rs>'s 
own programming language, which facilitates 
easy data extraction using a graphical user 
interface. Users are not required to write data 
retrieval programs, as <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> generates and 
runs extraction code on the fly, based on the 
variables selected. Due to its common interface 
and implementation for many datasets, it is 
useful for international comparative work and 
allows for an easy introduction to a new dataset 
for first-time users. As the data retrievals are 
standardised and used by many researchers, the 
chance of mistakes in the initial data-creation 
phase of any research is virtually reduced to 
zero. Updates to <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> are pushed to users 
and are installed in the same manner as <rs type="software">Stata</rs> 
itself. <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> currently has more than 300 
users and currently supports international data-
sets such as the German SOEP, the British BHPS 
(or its successor, the UK Understanding Society 
study), the American PSID and Current Popula-
tion Survey-National Bureau of Economic 
Research, the American Survey of Income and 
Program Participation, the South African Na-
tional Income Dynamics Study, in addition to 
the HILDA Survey, MABEL, LSAC, LSIC and 
CASiE. <rs type="software">PanelWhiz</rs> runs in Windows, Mac and 
Linux, but needs at least <rs id="software-28" type="software">Stata SE/MP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-28" type="version-number">11</rs> or later 
to run. </p>

<p>January 2013 </p>





<p>Hahn and Haisken-DeNew: PanelWhiz and the Australian Longitudinal Data Infrastructure 385 </p>



<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
September 2013 </p>

</text></tei>