<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs11166-011-9127-z" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Many experiments have demonstrated that when evaluating payoffs, 
people take not only their own payoffs into account, but also the payoffs of 
others in their social environment. Most of this evidence is found in settings 
where payoffs are riskless. It is plausible that if people care about the payoffs 
of others, they do so not only in a riskless context, but also in a risky one. This 
suggests that an individual's decision making under risk depends on the risks 
others in his or her environment face. This paper is the first to test whether 
individuals' risk attitudes are affected by the risks others face. The results show 
that risk attitudes appear to be less affected by others' risks than expected, 
even though the same subjects do show concerns for inequality in a riskless 
setting. Interestingly, we find that people prefer risks to be independent across 
individuals in society rather than correlated. </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>Many experiments have demonstrated that people show concerns for the 
fairness of income allocations. In general, people especially dislike being worse 
off than others: they try to 'keep up with the Joneses' (Galí 1994). In line 
with prospect theory (Kahneman and Tversky 1979) these results suggest that 
people evaluate their own payoffs relative to a reference point, where in these 
social contexts the payoffs of others serve as a reference point. 
Most studies showing that people care about the income of others in society, 
assume that the incomes of all involved are certain, i.e. they abstract from risk. 
Extrapolating the results of these studies to a risky context suggests that people 
also care about the payoffs of others when payoffs are risky. It is therefore to 
be expected that payoffs of others serve as a reference point not only in a risk 
free context, but also in a risky one. 
From prospect theory in individual decision making we know that if an 
individual is asked to choose between two lotteries, his choice will depend on 
his reference point: a different reference point may lead to a different choice. 
Translating this to a social context, and assuming that the reference point is at 
least partly determined by the payoffs of others, we expect that the payoffs of 
others have an impact on the choices people make between lotteries that affect 
only themselves. Thus, we posit that people's choices between lotteries are not 
only affected by the lotteries themselves, but also by the payoffs and lotteries 
others face. In other words, people's risk attitudes are likely to depend on the 
payoffs and lotteries others face. To stress this dependency, we refer to risk 
attitudes as social risk attitudes. In this paper we do a first test to analyze to 
what extent risk attitudes indeed are social risk attitudes. 
Knowing how individuals' attitudes towards risk are affected by the payoffs 
and risks faced by people around them may yield important insights into be-
havior in financial markets, and, for instance, behavior in times of a pandemic. 1 
If risk attitudes are affected by risks faced by the environment, financial booms 
and crises do not only directly affect investment behavior, but also indirectly, 
through their impact on risks faced by others. Similarly, a pandemic will not 
only have a direct, but also an indirect impact on behavior. 
In an experiment we let subjects make risky choices in a social context. 
The risky social context is operationalized by letting subjects choose between 
allocation lotteries that determine both the lottery they themselves face and 
the lotteries the other ten participants in the experimental session face. We 
ask subjects to choose between two lotteries for themselves, while keeping 
the other subjects' lotteries fixed. By repeating the same question for various 
lotteries for the other subjects, we can explore whether the lotteries that others 
face affect the decision maker's choices. We hypothesize that varying those 
lotteries will affect choices. We refer to these questions as individual risk 
questions. We also included questions where subjects choose between lotteries </p>

<p>1 Evidence suggests that in financial markets and in pandemics, risk attitudes are influenced by a 
type of social contagion (e.g. see Christakis and Fowler 2007; Shiller 2008). </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>for the other subjects while keeping their own lottery fixed. We refer to these 
questions as peer risk questions. 
An attractive feature of our individual risk questions is that they allow us 
to investigate how distributions of risks and payoffs for the other subjects 
influence risky choice, by excluding any emotions and motives related to social 
interactions, such as group compliance or avoiding the feeling of guilt. The 
choices in this type of question are not confounded by adherence to social 
norms, feelings of social pressure, or fear for reciprocal behavior. 
In the peer risk questions subjects choose between, for instance, (1) an 
allocation where every 'other subject' receives an independent lottery yielding 
20 euro with 30% probability and 10 euro otherwise, and (2) an allocation 
yielding 20 euro to 30% of the other subjects and 10 euro to the rest of 
the other subjects. We refer to the first option as a "lottery" and to the 
latter as the "corresponding allocation." The expected value and the possible 
outcomes are the same in both options. There is one crucial difference between 
the options, though: in the "lottery" risks are perfectly independent across 
subjects, whereas in the "allocation" risks are correlated. A choice between 
these options sheds light on our experience of facing risks of natural disasters, 
influenza pandemics, terrorist attacks, and airplane crashes, where risks show 
a strong correlation with others in our environment, compared to events with 
similar, but uncorrelated risks. 
Our results are mixed. We find relatively weak evidence for the lotteries 
of others to influence a subject's choice between lotteries for himself even 
though almost all subjects exhibit behavior consistent with social preferences 
when they can only influence others' payoffs. Nevertheless, the evidence does 
suggest several behavioral patterns, such as avoidance of inequality whenever 
possible. The results of the peer risk questions are striking and show a 
clear preference for the lottery rather than for the corresponding allocation, 
suggesting that subjects prefer situations where risks are independent rather 
than correlated. 
The paper proceeds as follows. Section 1 introduces our experimental design 
to measure risk preferences in a social context. Sections 2 and 3 discuss the 
experiment and report its results. Finally, Sections 4 and 5 provide a discussion 
and interpretation of the results of the experiment and a conclusion. </p>

<p>1 Experimental design </p>

<p>The experiment consists of two types of questions: peer risk questions and 
individual risk questions. Subjects make choices between allocation lotteries. 
An allocation lottery is a lottery over allocations of money over a group of 
subjects. </p>

<p>1.1 Individual risk questions </p>

<p>Individual risk questions are designed to study social risk attitudes. We con-
sider a group of subjects and let each person choose between two lotteries </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>while fixing the lotteries that the others in the group receive, i.e. we let each 
subject choose between allocation lotteries that differ only in the lottery the 
subject himself receives. Thus, when choosing, the decision maker cannot 
influence the payoffs and risks of the other subjects in the group. While the 
payoffs and risks of other subjects cannot be influenced, this does not mean 
that they play no role. From the literature on social preferences (Sobel 2005) 
we know that people evaluate allocations of money by taking into account not 
only their own payoffs, but also the payoffs of others, often their peers. This 
finding suggests that, when evaluating lotteries for themselves, people do take 
into account the lotteries others face. Our individual risk questions will allow 
us to analyze the extent to which risk attitudes depend on the lotteries others 
face. </p>

<p>1.2 Peer risk questions </p>

<p>In order to ensure sufficient variation in questions and to reduce the risk 
of subjects ignoring lotteries of others merely to reduce cognitive burden 
during the experiment, we also included another type of questions where 
the decision maker could influence only the lotteries of others. In peer risk 
questions we fix the lottery that the decision maker will receive and let him 
choose between allocation lotteries for the other individuals in the group. In 
these questions we mostly focus on different types of allocation lotteries. Each 
type of allocation lottery can be seen as a different allocation rule, where 
the decision maker acts as a social planner. We let subjects choose between, 
for instance, an allocation where each 'other subject' receives an independent 
lottery yielding 20 euro with 30% probability and 10 euro otherwise, and an 
allocation yielding 20 euro to 30% of the other subjects and 10 euro to the 
rest of the other subjects. We refer to the first option as a lottery and to the 
latter as the corresponding allocation. In the latter, the subjects receiving a 
particular payoff will be randomly determined, so that every subject still has 
30% probability of receiving 20 euro and 70% probability of receiving 10 
euro. The resolution of the latter lottery, however, is not independent across 
subjects. The appeal of this type of question is that it indicates how subjects 
care about the correlation of their payoffs and risks with the payoffs and risks 
of others. 
This type of question also indicates how concerns for procedural fairness 
may arise. If subjects would prefer the lottery to the corresponding allocation, 
then they prefer to let fate determine the final payoffs as much as possible 
and prefer to give everybody an equal chance on payoffs, independently of 
what the others receive. A preference for the lottery over the corresponding 
distribution received considerable attention in the literature on social risk 
analysis in the 1980's (e.g. Broome 1982; Fishburn 1984; Hammerton et al. 
1982; Keeney 1980; Keller and Sarin 1988). Our peer risk questions allow us to 
test whether the mentioned findings in the 1980's are robust to real incentives. 
A nice illustration of preferences over allocation rules is the following case 
in the Supreme Court of the United States: Holmes v. United States (Broome </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>1984). In 1841, an American ship struck an iceberg close to Newfoundland. The 
crew and half of the passengers managed to escape in two available lifeboats. 
One of these lifeboats was overcrowded. In a desperate attempt to keep this 
lifeboat from sinking, the crew members threw persons overboard by using the 
criteria that no woman would be thrown overboard and that no couples would 
be separated. Crewman Alexander Holmes was later on convicted of 'unlawful 
homicide' and was sentenced to jail by the judge. The interesting aspect of 
this story is that Holmes was not convicted because of the manslaughter but 
rather because of the fact that he had not cast lots: "In no other than this or 
some like way are those having equal rights put upon equal footing ..." The 
council, however, argued that the principle of selection the crewman used was 
more humane than using lots. The council and the crewman, thus, had different 
preferences over allocation rules than the judge. </p>

<p>2 Experiment </p>

<p>All experimental sessions were conducted at the Behavioral and Experimental 
Economics laboratory Maastricht (BEELab) with 121 (65 male, 56 female) 
students from Maastricht University. The vast majority (88%) were students 
from Economics and Business Administration. The other subjects were stu-
dents from Law, Cultural Sciences, and from University College Maastricht. 
They were recruited through email announcements and announcements on 
the students' intranet. Each subject participated in only one session. The 
experiment was programmed in <rs id="software-1" type="software">Z-tree</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Fischbacher</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2007</rs>). 
In every session, exactly 11 subjects participated. They all received a show-
up fee of 4 euro. The average earnings per subject, including this show-up 
fee, were 12.98 euro. The experiment lasted 70 min on average. Between 
20 and 35 min were spent on reading the instructions. At the end of the 
instructions there was a short questionnaire to test whether subjects under-
stood the instructions. The experiment would continue only after all subjects 
understood the instructions. The instructions can be found in Appendix B. At 
the end of the experiment subjects were asked to answer some demographic 
questions. 
In reality individuals compare themselves with many others: friends, col-
leagues, neighbors, family, etc. In order to replicate the situation of one 
individual comparing himself with many others, we let subjects compare 
themselves not with only one other subject, but with all other subjects in the 
same session. Thus, when a subject makes a decision, there are ten others. 
The experiment consisted of 40 questions where subjects had to make 
choices between allocation lotteries. There were 28 individual risk questions 
and 12 peer risk questions. At the start of the experiment three practice 
questions were given. The order of the other 40 questions was randomized. We 
also randomized the left-right presentation on the screen. To determine the 
earnings of all subjects, at the end of each session one of the subjects and one 
of his questions was chosen at random. If this implied that the other subjects </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>would receive a lottery, the lottery was played for each of these subjects 
independently. 
The allocation lotteries to choose from were displayed on the computer 
screen as in Fig. 3 in Appendix A. The allocation lotteries are displayed as a 
2 × 2 matrix. The columns represent the different allocation lotteries, where 
the upper half shows the lottery for the decision maker. In order to avoid 
biases, we randomize the order of all 40 questions. </p>

<p>2.1 Individual risk questions </p>

<p>The 28 individual risk questions are given in Tables 3, 4, and 5 in Appendix A. 
The columns 'lottery 1' and 'lottery 2' give the two lotteries between which 
the decision maker has to choose given that the other 10 subjects receive 
the lottery described in the third column. The subjects are offered 4 types of 
choices. In the first type of choice the subject chooses between (30% : 23, 70% 
: 3) 2 and 10 for sure for himself. As in this question one of the lotteries is a 
payoff to be received with certainty, we label this type of question 'Certainty'. 
The second type of choice is between (40% : 13, 60% : 8) and (50% : 20, 50% 
: 0) for the decision maker. Here the latter is a mean preserving spread (MPS) 
of the former, which is why we label these questions 'MPS'. The third type of 
choice is between (80% : 12, 20% : 2) and (80% : 7, 20% : 22). Neither of these 
two is a MPS of the other. An important difference between these lotteries is 
the minimum payoff attainable, which the subjects may choose to maximize. 
Therefore, we label this type of question 'Maximin'. We added two questions 
with higher stakes where the subjects choose between (20% : 60, 80% : 0) and 
(40% : 13, 60% : 8). We label these two questions 'Maximin High Stakes'. 
For each of the four types of questions we varied the lotteries that the other 
subjects received in order to check whether this would influence decisions. 
Some lotteries would ensure the same payoff as the decision maker, others 
would ensure the same lottery. Furthermore, we varied the lotteries the others 
would receive with respect to the probabilities and payoffs. By varying the 
lotteries the others receive, we can infer whether the levels of risk and the 
levels of payoffs others receive influence the decision maker's risk attitude. 
We ask different types of questions in order to obtain richness in the data that 
allows us to explore the basic patterns of behavior that can be observed in a 
risky social environment. 
As a benchmark, in each of the three categories, Certainty, MPS, and Max-
imin, we have one question where the other subjects receive the same payoff as 
the decision maker. In that question, the resulting allocation would always be 
constant, i.e. without any inequality. This question, therefore, reveals subjects' 
risk attitudes in isolation, i.e. if there would be no others. A similar question, </p>

<p>2 ( p : x, 1 − p : y) denotes the lottery yielding x with probability p and y with probability 1 − p. </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>which does allow for inequality in final allocations, is the one where the other 
subjects receive the same lottery as the decision maker, but where this lottery is 
independently resolved for each subject. A subject only concerned with ex ante 
opportunities of others would not behave differently in this question compared 
to the benchmark question. Subjects who are concerned with the equality of 
final allocations might behave differently, though. 
For the other questions we varied the payoff and risks of the other subjects' 
lottery. In some questions the others would always receive more than the 
decision maker. In other questions, they would always receive less. There are 
also questions where the others would receive outcomes that are between the 
maximum and the minimum of what the decision maker would get. Finally, 
there are questions, like C6, that are of the lottery type as discussed in the 
description of peer risk questions and there are questions of the corresponding 
allocation type, like C7. Note that in C7 the subjects who would receive 15 
would be determined randomly. </p>

<p>2.2 Peer risk questions </p>

<p>Table 6 in Appendix A lists the peer risk questions. In questions P1, P3, and 
P7 subjects are asked to choose between a lottery and the corresponding 
allocation. Questions P2, P4, and P5 illustrate whether the lotteries of the 
decision maker in P1, P3, and P7 are considered to be better or worse than 
the lottery that guarantees equality. We added P6 to test for consistency, as 
the answer in P5 and P7 would, together with transitivity, predict the answer in 
P6. P8, P9, and P10 test whether subjects are concerned with equality among 
the others. Finally, P11 and P12 test whether subjects like to be ahead of others 
and whether they dislike others being ahead. </p>

<p>2.3 Demographic questions </p>

<p>At the end of the experiment, we asked subjects for their age, gender, 
number of brothers, and number of sisters. We also asked what kind of study 
programme they are enrolled in: Economics, Psychology, Healthcare, or other. 
Finally, we asked whether they are a member of a study-or student association, 
whether they are a member of a sports club, and how many subjects in their 
session they know. </p>

<p>2.4 Relation with Dictator and Ultimatum games </p>

<p>In most of the literature the way to analyze social preferences is to let people 
play a game such as a dictator game or an ultimatum game (Bolton et al. 2005; 
Charness and Rabin 2002; Karni et al. 2008; Sebald 2007; Trautmann 2009). 
The driving forces of decisions in the ultimatum game are not only preferences 
over final allocations, but also reciprocity concerns: people may behave in a </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>certain way to induce others to behave in a certain way. It may well be that 
a social norm and reciprocity concerns conflict with a person's preferences 
over final allocations, which makes it impossible to disentangle preferences 
over final allocations from reciprocity concerns in the existing experiments. 
Reciprocity is not present in one-stage games. Therefore, one can argue that in 
the dictator game reciprocity plays no role. As we are interested in preferences 
over final allocations rather than reciprocity concerns, the dictator game might 
be more suitable for our purposes than the ultimatum game. 
The decisions subjects make in dictator games, however, always simulta-
neously influence both their own payoff and the payoff of at least one other 
player. Therefore, these dictator games and their risky versions (e.g. Bohnet 
and Zeckhauser 2004; Bohnet et al. 2008; Boles and Messick 1995; Bolton and 
Ockenfels 2010) would only allow us to analyze the tradeoff subjects make 
between (1) individual risks and payoffs and (2) others' risks and payoffs, 
and would not allow us to study the impact of risks and payoffs of others 
on attitudes towards individual risks and payoffs. This is why we deliberately 
chose not to implement a risky version of the dictator game. </p>

<p>3 Results </p>

<p>3.1 Individual risk questions </p>

<p>In the Certainty and MPS questions, the majority of the choices (79.75% and 
82.19%, respectively) are in accordance with risk aversion, and in the Maximin 
questions the majority of choices (73.56%) is in accordance with maximin. The 
exact percentages of the choices for each question can be found in Table 7 
in Appendix A. These results are in accordance with the choices we would 
expect from subjects in an isolated context. Thus, the social context provided 
here does not seem to strongly influence subjects' risk attitudes. 
Although in the Certainty, MPS, and Maximin questions subjects often 
chose one particular lottery, they did not always choose that lottery. This 
suggests that there were questions that made subject's preferences switch when 
changing the lottery that others would receive. These switches can be caused 
by random error, but also by the social component of preferences being strong 
enough to make preferences between lotteries switch. In order to test whether 
switches are mainly random or clearly in favor of one or the other lottery, we 
used a sign test. Figure 1 shows which switches are significant and in which 
direction. An arrow from C1 to C4 indicates that most switches from C1 to 
C4 were from lottery 1 to lottery 2. Thick arrows indicate significance at a 5% 
level (one-sided), and the other arrows indicate significance at the 10% level. 
Table 1 gives the corresponding p-values. 
We also examined the effects of demographic and individual characteristics 
on the choice behavior. For each characteristic, we calculated per block (i.e. C, 
MPS, MM, MMH) the number of times one particular lottery was chosen, </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>(a) Certainty 
(c) Maximin 
(b) Mean Preserving Spread </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Significant switches from lottery 1 to lottery 2 </p>

<p>and ran a Mann Whitney U test on these values. We found no significant 
effects, except for male subjects choosing lottery 1 significantly more often 
than female subjects in MMH (MWU: p = 0.001, two-sided). Thus, men seem 
more sensitive to higher stakes than women. </p>

<p>3.2 Peer risk questions </p>

<p>The choices in questions P1, P3, and P7 reveal that subjects have a significant 
preference for the lottery rather than the corresponding allocation (signtest: 
p &lt;0.001, two-sided). This holds for all three questions. In P1, 67.77% of the 
subjects choose the lottery. In P3 and P7 these percentages are 67.77% and 
82.64%, respectively. The exact percentages of the choices for all peer risk 
questions can be found in Table 8 in Appendix A. 
For each subject, we counted the number of times he or she chose the lottery 
in P1, P3, and P7. Figure 2 summarizes the results. We observe that a vast 
number of subjects chose the lottery in a majority of the questions. In order to </p>

<p>Table 1 Significance of switches (one-sided p-values) </p>

<p>Significant switches from lottery 1 to lottery 2 
Certainty 
Mean preserving spread 
Maximin 
Switch 
p-value 
Switch 
p-value 
Switch 
p-value </p>

<p>C1→ C4 
0.095 
MPS2→ MPS6 
0.073 
MM1→ MM5 
0.067 
C1→ C8 
0.068 
MPS2→ MPS7 
0.067 
MM1→ MM6 
0.084 
C2→ C4 
0.058 
MPS2→ MPS8 
0.058 
MM3→ MM2 
0.067 
C2→ C8 
0.032 
MPS3→ MPS6 
0.033 
MM3→ MM5 
0.014 
C5→ C4 
0.032 
MPS3→ MPS7 
0.047 
MM3→ MM6 
0.035 
C5→ C8 
0.013 
MPS3→ MPS8 
0.032 
MM4→ MM5 
0.072 
C6→ C8 
0.095 
MM7→ MM5 
0.084 
MM8→ MM5 
0.084 </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Consistency of choices </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Percentage of Subjects </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
Number of times Lottery is chosen </p>

<p>get a more detailed picture, Table 2 shows in which questions subjects chose 
the lottery rather than the corresponding allocation. 
As we can see, 47.93% of the subjects always prefer to give a lottery rather 
than the corresponding allocation to the other subjects, whereas only 6.61% 
prefer the exact opposite. Moreover, 28.92% and 16.53% prefer the lottery to 
the allocation twice and once, respectively. Thus, we indeed observe a clear 
regularity in the preferences for the lottery over the corresponding allocation. 
P2, P4, and P5 test whether the lotteries and corresponding allocations in 
P1, P3, and P7 are considered to be better or worse than the lottery that 
guarantees equality. Interestingly, we do not observe an overall preference for 
the lottery that guarantees equality. In P4 and P5 subjects clearly prefer to give 
the same as they will receive to the other subjects (signtest: p &lt; 0.001, two-
sided). The percentages are 69.42%, and 88.43%, respectively. However, in P2 
69.42% of the subjects prefer to give the others the allocation rather than the 
same payoff as they themselves will receive. Overall, subjects prefer the lottery 
over the corresponding allocation no matter whether this allocation or lottery 
is considered to be better or worse than the lottery which would guarantee 
equality. In P6 subjects clearly prefer to give the same as they will receive to 
the other subjects (signtest: p &lt; 0.001, two-sided), which is consistent with the 
findings in P5 and P7. </p>

<p>Table 2 Patterns in choices 
between lotteries and their 
corresponding allocations </p>

<p>Lottery preferred P1 
P3 
P7 
% of subjects </p>

<p>Always 
x 
x 
x 
47.93% 
Twice 
x 
x 
4.96% 
x 
x 
13.22% 
x 
x 
10.74% 
Once 
x 
1.65% 
x 
4.13% 
x 
10.74% 
% of subjects 
67.8% 67.8% 82.6% </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>P8, P9, and P10 test whether subjects are concerned with the equality of 
allocations among other subjects. Subjects did not significantly prefer one 
allocation over the other in these questions, suggesting that they, on average, 
were not concerned with the equality of the allocation among other subjects. 
Finally, in P11 and P12, the subjects preferred to give the others the 
highest possible outcome in 87.60% and 85.95% of the cases, which was highly 
significant. This illustrates that subjects are willing to maximize the payoff of 
others, even if this leads to being worse off than these other subjects. Thus, 
the results of the individual risk questions cannot be driven by subjects being 
purely selfish, which we will discuss further in Section 4. 
Again, we found no significant influence of the demographic variables on 
the choices made by subjects. </p>

<p>4 Interpretation and discussion </p>

<p>4.1 Further interpretation </p>

<p>We will now further interpret the findings reported in Fig. 1 and Table 1. 
Overall, not many switches were observed in Fig. 1, suggesting that choices are 
not strongly affected by the payoffs and risks of others. One could argue that 
the subjects therefore do not care about the payoffs of others. This argument, 
however, is contradicted by the fact that at least 85% of the subjects chose to 
maximize others' payoffs in P11 and P12. These findings are in line with the 
results from the debriefings, where subjects had to indicate how they made 
their decisions. Subjects indicated having lexicographic preferences, whereby 
they first choose the best lottery for themselves, and only then care about the 
lotteries of others. 
We will now investigate whether the few switches that are observed, though, 
do suggest consistent behavioral patterns. First, consider the Certainty ques-
tions. The interesting feature of the lotteries in these types of questions is 
that subjects can avoid the standard risk by choosing lottery 2, which gives 
them a certain payoff of 10. On top of that, in C4 and C8 they can even 
avoid another type of risk by choosing lottery 2, namely the risk of facing an 
unequal allocation. Choosing lottery 1 in C4, could lead to inequality as the 
others will face the exact same lottery. Choosing lottery 1 in C8 would lead to 
inequality anyhow. Figure 1 shows that in C4 and C8 lottery 2 is significantly 
more chosen in comparison to the questions where the other subjects receive 
a certain payoff. 
In C2 and C5, lottery 1 is significantly more chosen. In both these questions, 
subjects can never end up being worse off than other subjects. In C2 strict 
equality will arise no matter which lottery is chosen. In C5, the worst possible 
payoff for a subject in the risky lottery is the payoff that all other subjects 
receive. Choosing the risky lottery, therefore, will not lead to disadvantageous 
inequality in the sense of the decision maker being worst off. </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>In C1, a subject will for sure face inequality by choosing lottery 2, as he 
would then receive a payoff of 10, whereas all others would receive a payoff of 
16. A subject might therefore be induced to choose lottery 1 as there he still 
faces the chance of being better off than the other subjects. The certainty in the 
other subjects' payoff leads to a relatively higher choice of the risky lottery 1. 
In the MPS and Maximin questions certainty can never be assured, as no 
payoff is given for sure to the decision maker. Certainty in terms of equality 
can only be assured in MPS10 and MM3 where the other subjects receive the 
same outcome as the decision maker. The results of the MPS and Maximin do 
not show a clear choice pattern. 
The results of the peer risk questions are striking. Subjects appear to have a 
strong preference for one allocation rule over the other. They prefer the lottery 
to the corresponding distribution. This result suggests that subjects are not 
willing to be held responsible for determining the allocation of payoffs. They 
would rather have fate determine the actual payoffs of the other subjects. In 
that sense, they are decision averse. Interestingly, we observe this preference 
irrespective of whether the other subjects face a higher, an equal or a lower 
expected value than the decision maker. However, we do observe significantly 
more subjects choosing the lottery when the expected value for the other 
subjects is lower than the expected value for the decision maker (signtest P1 vs 
P3: p = 0.001, one-sided, and signtest P3 vs P7: p = 0.003, one sided). 
Two possible explanations can be given for the fact that in P4, P5 and 
P6 subjects prefer to give the same payoff to the others as they will receive 
themselves, while this preference is not present in P2. Subjects seem to be max-
imizing the expected values of the other subjects. However, this interpretation 
does not explain why we find a significant preference for 'the same payoff as 
you' in case where the expected values of all subjects are identical. This brings 
us to the second possible explanation. In all questions where subjects prefer 
to choose the same payoff as themselves for the other subjects, the lottery or 
allocation they would otherwise get contains the worst possible outcome in 
comparison to the lowest possible outcome in their own lottery. Maximizing 
the other subjects' worst possible outcome, therefore seems to be another 
plausible motive. Both motives are actually confirmed by the results found 
for P11 and P12. In these two questions the lottery which maximizes the other 
subjects' (worst possible) payoff is significantly more often chosen (signtest: 
p &lt; 0.001 for both questions). Subjects are thus willing to maximize the (worst 
possible) payoff of others, even if this may lead to being worse off than these 
other subjects. In P11, 87.60% and in P12, 85.95% of the subjects behaved in 
this way. </p>

<p>4.2 Discussion </p>

<p>We are aware of three studies that are close in spirit to ours. Brennan et al. 
(2008) did an experiment in the spirit of our experimental design. They 
considered two lotteries: a risky and a sure one, which gives the expected 
payoff of the risky one for sure. Every subject was paired with another subject. </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>The authors considered four allocation lotteries: (1) both subjects receive the 
lottery, (2) both subjects receive the sure payoff,(3) one subject receives the 
lottery and the other the sure payoff, and (4) the reverse. Then they elicited the 
willingness to pay (WTP) and the willingness to accept (WTA) of the decision 
maker for each of these allocation lotteries, given that the other player does 
not pay or receive anything. Thus, strictly speaking, in the WTA treatment 
the decision maker chooses between an allocation lottery and an allocation 
where he receives the WTA and his partner receives nothing. Therefore, in 
the choice the lottery of the other player is not kept fixed. When choosing (or 
determining the WTA or WTP) the player thus simultaneously determines his 
own and his partner's payoff. In the analysis of the results, though, Brennan et 
al. compare the WTP and WTA from the four allocation lotteries. In that sense 
their experiment is close in spirit to ours. Interestingly, Brennan et al. (2008) 
also find no significant effect of the risk of others on individual behavior. 
Another experiment in the spirit of ours is Linde and Sonnemans (2009). 
Linde and Sonnemans studied whether risk attitudes depend on whether 
others receive more or less than the decision maker. They show that subjects 
are relatively more risk averse when they are guaranteed to earn less than 
their partner, though the vast majority of subjects behaves according to risk 
aversion. Linde and Sonnemans' study differs from ours in some important 
aspects. First, they only consider others' payoffs to be riskless. Second, their 
experiment includes a large proportion of questions where the decision maker 
simultaneously influences his own and the other's payoff. Third, subjects are 
randomly paired with one other subject in their study, while we consider all 
subjects in one session as one group. Fourth, each subject first had to play 
several Bertrand games against the subject he was paired with. Only after 
these Bertrand games did the subjects answer the questions in the spirit of 
our experimental design. Between the Bertrand games and the next questions 
every subject was shown the picture of his partner. 
The experiment by Kroll and Davidovitz (2003) is in a similar spirit as our 
peer risk questions P1, P3, and P7 in the sense that it concerns allocation rules. 
They let children choose between two allocation lotteries. The first allocation 
lottery, which they call 'common game', would give the decision maker a 
particular lottery and the others would receive the same as the decision maker. 
In the second allocation, which they call 'individual game' the lottery was 
the same, but it was resolved for every subject independently. They found a 
significant preference for the first lottery. This finding predicts that C2, MPS10, 
and MM3 are perceived to be different than C4, MPS4, and MM7, respectively. 
We only find a significant switch in a particular direction between C2 and C4, 
though. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>In order to examine how risks and payoffs of others influence risk attitudes, we 
conducted an experiment. The key feature of our experiment is to keep either </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>the lottery of the decision maker or the lottery that others receive fixed, and to 
vary the other lottery. Then repeating the questions for a different fixed lottery 
allows us to explore risk attitudes in a social context. It allows us to analyze 
whether risk attitudes depend on the lotteries others face. Since the decision 
makers do not influence the payoffs of others in this context, choices cannot 
be driven by intentions, social pressure or reciprocity. Thus, our results are not 
confounded by reciprocity and fully reflect preferences over allocations. 
The results show that risk attitudes are not so much affected by the risks 
others face. Since a large majority of the subjects did choose to maximize 
others' payoffs if this would not influence their own payoffs, we can never-
theless not conclude that they are purely selfish. Combined with the results 
from the debriefing, these results suggest that subjects have lexicographic 
social preferences whereby they first maximize their own utility and only then 
the utility of others. Striking is the finding that subjects prefer lotteries to 
their corresponding allocations, where risks are perfectly independent across 
subjects. This suggests that they prefer risks to be independent across members 
of the population rather than correlated. It also indicates that subjects prefer 
everybody to undergo the same procedure, thereby avoiding the possibility to 
be held responsible for bad outcomes of others. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited. </p>

<p>Appendix A </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Screenshot </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>Table 3 Individual risk questions: certainty </p>

<p>Certainty 
Lottery 1 
Lottery 2 
Lottery others </p>

<p>C1 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
16 
C2 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
same payoff as you 
C3 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
(20%: 25, 80%: 5) 
C4 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
same lottery as you 
C5 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
3 
C6 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
(50%: 15, 50% 5) 
C7 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
15 for 50% of subjects 
5 for 50% of subjects 
C8 
(30%: 23, 70%: 3) 
10 
10 </p>

<p>Note that the expected value of lottery 1 is 9, while the expected value of lottery 2 is 10. We chose 
this expected value of 9, because we expected the social context to have a strong impact on risk 
attitudes. Thus, we expected that subjects would be risk seeking in this context, so as to still be 
able to get more than the other subjects in at least some instances. As the results show, though, 
the impact of the social context on choices appeared not to be that strong </p>

<p>Table 4 Individual risk questions: Mean Preserving Spread </p>

<p>Mean Preserving 
Lottery 1 
Lottery 2 
Lottery others 
Spread </p>

<p>MPS1 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
10 
MPS2 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
13 
MPS3 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
(50%: 25, 50%: 5) 
MPS4 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
same lottery as you 
MPS5 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
20 
MPS6 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
8 
MPS7 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
0 
MPS8 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
(20%: 20, 80%: 0) 
MPS9 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
20 for 20% of subjects 
0 for 80% of subjects 
MPS10 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(50%: 20, 50%: 0) 
same payoff as you </p>

<p>Table 5 Individual risk questions: Maximin </p>

<p>Lottery 1 
Lottery 2 
Lottery others </p>

<p>Maximin 
MM1 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
MM2 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
MM3 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
same payoff as you 
MM4 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
12 for 80% of subjects 
2 for 20% of subjects 
MM5 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
7 for 80% of subjects 
22 for 20% of subjects 
MM6 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
10 
MM7 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
same lottery as you 
MM8 
(80%: 12, 20%: 2) 
(80%: 7, 20%: 22) 
(50%: 11, 50%: 9) 
Maximin High 
Stakes 
MMH1 
(20%: 60, 80%: 0) 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(33%: 33, 67%: 0) 
MMH2 
(20%: 60, 80%: 0) 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
11 </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>Table 6 Peer risk questions </p>

<p>You 
Others 1 
Others 2 </p>

<p>P1 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
(30%: 20, 70%: 10) 
20 for 30% of subjects 
10 for 70% of subjects 
P2 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
same payoff as you 
20 for 30% of subjects 
10 for 70% of subjects 
P3 
(30%: 17, 70%: 7) 
(50%: 15, 50%: 5) 
15 for 50% of subjects 
5 for 50% of subjects 
P4 
(30%: 17, 70%: 7) 
(50%: 15, 50%: 5) 
same payoff as you 
P5 
(50%: 16, 50%: 4) 
(20%: 20, 80%: 0) 
same payoff as you 
P6 
(50%: 16, 50%: 4) 
same payoff as you 
20 for 20% of subjects 
0 for 80% of subjects 
P7 
(50%: 16, 50%: 4) 
(20%: 20, 80%: 0) 
20 for 20% of subjects 
0 for 80% of subjects 
P8 
(20%: 20, 80%: 8) 
13 for 40% of subjects 
14 for 20% of subjects 
8 for 60% of subjects 
12 for 20% of subjects 
10 for 30% of subjects 
6 for 30% of subjects 
P9 
(20%: 20, 80%: 8) 
13 for 40% of subjects 
13 for 40% of subjects 
8 for 60% of subjects 
10 for 30% of subjects 
6 for 30% of subjects 
P10 
(20%: 20, 80%: 8) 
13 for 40% of subjects 
14 for 20% of subjects 
8 for 60% of subjects 
12 for 20% of subjects 
8 for 60% of subjects 
P11 
(40%: 13, 60%: 8) 
13 
8 
P12 
10 
13 
8 </p>

<p>Table 7 Percentage choice Lottery 1 across different questions </p>

<p>Certainty 
Mean Preserving Spread 
Maximin 
Question 
Percentage 
Question 
Percentage 
Question 
Percentage </p>

<p>C1 
22.3% 
MPS1 
83.5% 
MM1 
28.1% 
C2 
23.1% 
MPS2 
85.1% 
MM2 
24.8% 
C3 
20.7% 
MPS3 
86.0% 
MM3 
31.4% 
C4 
16.5% 
MPS4 
83.5% 
MM4 
27.3% 
C5 
24.0% 
MPS5 
81.8% 
MM5 
21.5% 
C6 
20.7% 
MPS6 
80.2% 
MM6 
22.3% 
C7 
19.8% 
MPS7 
78.5% 
MM7 
28.1% 
C8 
14.9% 
MPS8 
78.5% 
MM8 
28.1% 
MPS9 
82.6% 
MMH1 
55.4% 
MPS10 
83.5% 
MMH2 
53.7% </p>

<p>Table 8 Percentage choice Others 1 across different questions </p>

<p>Question 
Percentage 
Question 
Percentage </p>

<p>P1 
67.8% 
P8 
47.9% 
P2 
30.6% 
P9 
52.1% 
P3 
67.8% 
P10 
47.1% 
P4 
30.6% 
P11 
87.6% 
P5 
11.6% 
P12 
86.0% 
P6 
87.6% 
P7 
82.6% </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>Appendix B: Instructions </p>

<p>Introduction </p>

<p>Welcome to this decision-making experiment. In this experiment you can earn 
money. How much you earn depends on your decisions and the decisions of 
other participants and random events. At the end of the experiment your 
earnings will be paid out privately and confidentially in cash. </p>

<p>It is important that you have a good understanding of the rules in the 
experiment. Therefore, please read these instructions carefully. In order to 
check that the instructions are clear to you, you will be asked a few questions at 
the end of the instructions. The experiment will start only after everybody has 
correctly answered those questions. At the end of the experiment you will be 
asked to fill in a short questionnaire. Thereafter you will receive your earnings. </p>

<p>During the whole experiment, you are not allowed to communicate with 
other participants. </p>

<p>If you have a question, please raise your hand. We will then come to you 
and answer your question in private. </p>

<p>Explanation of experiment </p>

<p>During this experiment there are eleven participants, which means that there 
are ten other participants. The other participants answer the same questions as 
you do, only in a different order. 
The experiment consists of 40 questions. In each question you will be 
asked to choose between two allocations of lotteries for the participants in 
this experiment. Your choices will be anonymous. There is no wrong or 
right answer. We are only interested in your own preferences. During the 
experiment, you will not receive any information about the choices of the other 
participants. They will also not receive any information about your choices. </p>

<p>You will encounter three types of allocations. We will now explain these 
three types of allocations. Note that in each question you will have to choose 
between two allocations. </p>

<p>Independent lotteries In the first type of allocation everyone receives a lottery. 
You may receive a different lottery than all the other participants, but all other 
participants receive a common lottery. An example of such an allocation is as 
follows 
Allocation I 
You receive 
17 euro with probability 1/5 
18 euro with probability 4/5 </p>

<p>The others receive 
15 euro with probability 2/5 
19 euro with probability 3/5 </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>In this allocation a lottery is played for you, which yields 17 euro with probabil-
ity 1/5 and 18 euro with probability 4/5. For each other participant a lottery is 
played, which yields 15 euro with probability 2/5 and 19 euro with probability 
3/5. The lotteries of different participants are thus independent and do not 
necessarily yield the same payoff. This means that when your lottery turns out 
to yield 17 euro, this does not increase or decrease the probability of another 
person getting 15 euro. Moreover, if the lottery of one other participant, called 
participant A, turns out to yield 15 euro, then the probability that another 
participant, called participant B, also gets 15 euro remains 2/5. Participant 
B does not necessarily then also receive 15 euro. For him the lottery is also 
played, and he also gets 15 euro with the probability 2/5. Thus the lottery is 
played for each player separately, not only once for all "others" at the same 
time. 
Let's consider another allocation: 
Allocation II 
You receive 
17 euro with probability 1/5 
18 euro with probability 4/5 </p>

<p>The others receive 
17 euro with probability 1/5 
18 euro with probability 4/5 </p>

<p>In this allocation everybody receives the same lottery. Depending on the 
realizations of the lotteries, it is likely that not everybody will receive the same 
payoff, because the lottery is played for each player separately, not only once 
for all "others" at the same time. </p>

<p>Others receive the same as you In the second type of allocation you receive 
a lottery and all other participants will receive the same payoff as you. An 
example is as follows: </p>

<p>Allocation III 
You receive 
10 euro with probability 1/5 
18 euro with probability 4/5 </p>

<p>The others receive 
the same as you </p>

<p>In this lottery you receive 10 euro with probability 1/5 and 18 euro other-
wise. If it turns out that you receive 10 euro, then all other participants will 
also receive 10 euro. If it turns out that you receive 18 euro, then all other 
participants will also receive 18 euro. In this sense your outcome will determine 
what the others get. </p>

<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>



<p>Others receive dif ferent payof fs with certainty In the third type of allocation 
you receive a lottery and one part of the other participants gets one payoff 
and the other participants get another payoff for sure. Consider the following 
example: </p>

<p>Allocation IV 
You receive 
25 euro with probability 1/5 
8 euro with probability 4/5 </p>

<p>The others receive 
3 persons receive 15 euro 
7 persons receive 19 euro </p>

<p>In this allocation you receive the lottery, which yields a payoff of 25 euro with 
probability 1/5 and a payoff of 8 euro with probability 4/5. From the other 
participants the computer will randomly select 3 people who will receive 15 
euro and the others will receive 19 euro. </p>

<p>During the experiment we will repeatedly ask you to make a choice between 
two allocations. The screen you will see during the experiment looks as follows. </p>

<p>In the two boxes you see two different allocations, called option A and 
option B, from which you have to choose. The circles show a graphical 
representation of the corresponding allocations. After selecting one of the two 
allocations, you can press the "OK" button. </p>

<p>The first 3 questions will be "practice questions". The next questions all 
may determine your payoff at the end of this experiment. At the end of the 
experiment the computer will select one person out of the 11 participants </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>

<p>at random. From that selected person one of the questions will randomly 
be selected and played out for real money, to determine the payoff of all 
participants. Note that this does not mean that the others will not receive 
anything. If you are the one selected, one of the questions you answered will be 
randomly selected and your chosen lottery will be played for you. Afterwards, 
the option you chose in that question will also be used to calculate the payoff 
of the others by playing the allocation you chose for them. The person who is 
selected thus determines the payoffs for all participants. 
Thus, every time you answer a question, keep in mind that this question 
may be the one that will determine your payoff and the payoffs of the others 
in the end. Every allocation we describe may be the one you and the other 
participants really end up with. 
Everybody will be paid his or her payoff from the experiment plus four euro 
for showing up. </p>



<p>J Risk Uncertain (2011) 43:205-225 </p>





</text></tei>