<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fjors.12298" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT. From 1940 to 1960 across 20 large U.S. cities, rental housing's price fell, renters' in-
comes rose, rent's share in household budgets fell, and, as expected, renters' real housing consumption 
increased. From 1970 to 2010, rental housing's price increased, renters' incomes decreased, but, un-
expectedly, renters' real housing consumption increased. We find neither demographics nor housing 
supply factors account for the anomalous post-1970 increase in renters' housing consumption. We 
conclude that after 1970 there was a nationwide increase in renters' preferences for housing consump-
tion. With incomes falling, renters increased housing consumption by decreasing consumption of other 
necessities including food, clothing, and transportation. </p>

<p>Virtually all Americans have been renters in the housing market at some point in 
their lives-as young adults starting out, during life transitions such as divorce or job 
change, or as senior citizens downsizing from the family home. For low-and moderate-
income Americans, rental housing is often the only viable option available because their 
incomes and savings are insufficient to finance the purchase of a home and to pay the 
costs of upkeep over time. As the subprime mortgage crisis underscores, homeownership 
is not for everyone. According to the 2010 Census, just over a third of all U.S. households 
lived in rented dwellings. 
For most renters, like most homeowners, the cost of housing absorbs a significant 
portion of household income. In this paper, we explore the changing circumstances of 
renters in 20 of the largest U.S. urban housing markets over the past seven decades, with 
special attention to the past four decades. We focus on providing a unique, long-term view 
of changes in the income of renters, the rents they pay, and the quantity of housing they 
consume. Decennial census data reveal that from 1930 to 1970, most renters' incomes rose 
while the price of rental housing services fell. In contrast, from 1970 to 2010, most renters' 
incomes fell and the price of rental housing services rose. We break down the post-1970 
changing distribution of rents into changes in the price of rental housing services and </p>

<p>*This research benefited from several years of support from the MacArthur Foundation. Outstanding 
research assistance was provided by Qasim Mahmood, Guoqing Sun, and Nick Kinnon, whose work was 
supported by grants from the Rockefeller Foundation and Bates College. We have also benefited from 
comments on drafts of this work by Robert Buckley, Rosanne Ducey, George Galster, Edward Glaeser, Ingrid 
Ellen, Edgar Olsen, Stuart Rosenthal, Nathan Tefft, Andreas Waldkirch, John Weicher, and Christine 
Whitehead. The authors alone are responsible for the analysis and conclusions provided in this paper. 
Received: March 2015; revised: January 2016; accepted: March 2016. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1111/jors.12298 </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>changes in quantity of rental housing services consumed. Here we encounter a striking 
puzzle that has not been documented in the existing literature. Despite falling renter 
incomes and increasing prices of rental housing services, since 1970 renters have markedly 
increased their consumption of rental housing services, which leads us to ask whether 
demographic changes might have driven changes in consumption separately from changes 
in incomes and prices. The answer is mixed: an estimated demand function confirms 
that demographics do matter-most notable, renting baby-boomers and their successors 
consume markedly more housing than do people born prior to World War II-but there 
remain large increases over time in housing consumption that are not accounted for by 
incomes, prices, or demographics. Do supply factors account for the increased housing 
consumption of renters? Our evidence suggests that supply considerations do not provide 
an explanation. 
The budget constraint implies that changes in rent's budget share must be accom-
panied by offsetting changes in other goods' budget shares. We turn in the last section 
of the paper to documenting these changes in other goods' budget shares over the past 
eight decades using the Consumer Expenditure Survey (CEX). Examining expenditure 
shares of renters from 1935 to 2011, we find that rent's budget share generally increases 
over the time span, peaking in 2011. From 1935 through the early 1970s the increases in 
rent's budget share are offset by declines in food's share. Since the 1970s, food's budget 
share has largely flattened. From the early 1970s through 2011, increases in rent's bud-
get share and similar increases in "Other" spending are offset by decreases in the budget 
shares of food, transport, and clothing. Our evidence suggests that the usual suspects 
(demographics, supply factors) do not explain the increase in the housing consumption of 
renters. While there is certainly room for more research to explain the phenomenon, our 
analysis suggests that there has been a fundamental change in the tastes of renters; they 
have a stronger preference for housing consumption. </p>

<p>2. TWO MODELS OF HOUSING </p>

<p>With our focus on the long-term changes in renter incomes, rents paid, and housing 
services consumed, this paper builds on the extensive housing affordability literature. In 
a widely cited paper, Quigley and Raphael (2004) summarize the evidence that between 
1960 and 2000, lower income renters sharply increased the fraction of their income spent 
on rent. 
1 While some analysts bemoan rental housing's unaffordability, 
2 some note that 
the increased spending has brought a reduction in the numbers of households living in </p>

<p>1 The Harvard Joint Center for Housing Studies reports that "the share of US households unable to 
find affordable rentals has been on the rise for a half-century, with an especially large jump in the last 
decade" and "affordability is likely to deteriorate further over the next few years" (Joint Center for Housing 
Studies, 2011). For many years there was much concern about the "adequacy" of rental housing; prior to 
1960, many units lacked basic plumbing and heating or were markedly overcrowded. For example, in 1949 
many large families lived in small quarters and more than 40 percent of units lacked complete indoor 
plumbing (Gabriel, 1996). In the mid-1980s, U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) 
analysts began counting the number of very poor households with what came to be known as "worst case 
housing needs." HUD found that substandard and crowded housing had become very infrequent problems, 
while housing expenditures in excess of 50 percent of income was the most often-faced problem among 
these households. For example, by 1993 HUD found that 95 percent of worst housing needs cases were due 
to rents in excess of 50 percent of income, while substandard or overcrowded housing occurred in only 9 
percent of the worst housing needs cases (HUD, 1996, p. 13). 
2 Among the many older papers in this vein: Clay (1987), cited by Nelson (1994) as an early voice 
worrying about declines in the stock of affordable housing; Apgar et al. (1991); Bogdon et al. (1994); 
Malpezzi and Green (1996); Orr and Peach (1999); and, more recently, Vandenbroucke (2007). </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>substandard housing (Weicher, 1991; Malpezzi and Green, 1996). Malpezzi and Green 
argue "America's poor are spending more to get better housing." 
Our approach to measuring rents and housing consumption is based on an extensive 
literature. Urban economists rely on two primary models of housing: the housing services 
model and the hedonic price model. In the housing services model, housing is treated 
as a composite commodity in which attributes of housing are collapsed into a single 
homogeneous good. In the hedonic price model, housing is represented as a bundle of 
distinct attributes, each with its own pricing. Prices in the housing services model are 
generally measured by price indices. The quantity of housing services is then defined 
as rent divided by price. The best known rental housing price index is the contract rent 
index of the Bureau of Labor Statistics (BLS). Prices in the hedonic price model are 
generally measured by regressions of rent (or house value) on a vector of housing units' 
characteristics. The American Housing Survey (AHS) has provided the richest source of 
attribute information for hedonic price estimation. 
Murray (1978) offers theoretical and empirical arguments that indicate that nei-
ther the housing services nor the hedonic price model is uniformly more general than 
the other. In this light, the choice of model depends largely on what question is being 
asked and what data are available. For example, if the question asked is about the ben-
efits accruing to households from living in public housing, as in Murray (1975), then 
the housing services model can suffice, while if the question asked is about changes in 
the quality of rental housing units over time, as in Gordon and vanGoethem (2007), then 
the hedonic price model can prove especially powerful. In this analysis, we rely chiefly 
on the housing services model, though we do present some data from the AHS on specific 
housing attributes. </p>

<p>3. THE PRICE AND QUANTITY OF RENTAL HOUSING SERVICES </p>

<p>The BLS contract rent index is a central component of our analysis. The BLS provides 
rent indices for the nation, census regions, and large metropolitan areas dating back as 
early as 1915. This long, time series provides a rich source of information on rents and is 
the best source of rent and quantity information for our purposes. The BLS index is not 
perfect and many researchers have addressed biases in these indices (biases we address in 
our analysis of the BLS data). Crone et al. (2010) report that prior to 1977 the BLS omitted 
from its contract rent sample units that had a change of tenant or that were vacant. Their 
paper presents a national contract rent index that corrects for the consequent downward 
bias in the BLS. They find that rental housing's price rose considerably more between 
1940 and 1985 than indicated by the BLS index. Gordon and vanGoethem (2007) argue 
that unmeasured quality changes are a primary driver of the bias identified by Crone et al. 
Using a mix of data sources, Gordon and vanGoethem estimate for the period 1935-1985 
a somewhat smaller bias than did Crone et al. 
For the period 2000-2010, Ambrose et al. (2015) provide another alternative to the 
BLS rent index. They restrict attention to new tenants in properties handled by property 
management companies. Ambrose et al. use their data to estimate city-specific rent indices 
from 2000 to 2010 for more cities than are covered by the BLS data; they find smaller 
rent increases and many more rent decreases than in the BLS contract rent data for that 
decade. 
Gordon and vanGoethem caution against using national rent indices for subnational 
analyses. This poses a challenge for us because there are no bias-corrected, city-specific 
rent indices for most of the period of interest to us. Fortunately, our central results prove </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>robust to choosing between the BLS city-specific indices and the national bias-corrected 
index of Crone et al. 
The city-specific price indices of the BLS and of Ambrose et el. share a limitation of 
all city-specific Consumer Price Index (CPI) price indices: they do not allow comparison of 
price levels across cities. Instead, the index is arbitrarily set to 100 in all cities in a chosen 
base year. However, a BLS analysis, "Three Budgets for an Urban Family of Four" (U.S. 
Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1972), prices a fixed bundle of consumption goods, including 
rental housing, across some 40 cities in 1970. These fixed-bundle prices, coupled with the 
BLS rent indices and CPI price indices, reveal differences in price levels across cities over 
time. 
Another problematic feature of the BLS rent indices has been their treatment of 
depreciation. For years prior to 1988, the BLS national and city-specific rent indices do 
not account for depreciation of housing units. Randolph notes that until 1988 the BLS 
indices' implied rates of change are consequently biased downward by the depreciation 
rate. Lowry (1982), Apgar et al. (1987), and Randolph (1988) report that the literature 
contains estimates from 0.3 to 0.9 percent per annum for rental housing's depreciation 
rate. 
A further problem with the BLS rent index, shared with the other indices men-
tioned above, is their reliance on contract rent, i.e., on rents paid to landlords. Contract 
rents often include some utilities while excluding others; indeed, contract rents some-
times exclude utilities altogether. Which utilities are included in contract rent has varied 
considerably over time and across cities. Consequently, contract rents do not provide a 
measure of expenditure on a consistently defined mix of housing and utilities. The oil 
crises of the 1970s and early 1980s increased gross rents appreciably, but these increases 
are missed in contract rents for units in which utilities are not included in rent. Moreover, 
Integrated Public Use Microsamples (IPUMS) data reveal that in the 1970s and 1980s, 
many landlords responded to higher utility costs by excluding utilities from rent when 
renegotiating rents, exacerbating the downward bias in the BLS contract rent index as 
a gross rent index. The U.S. Census and the American Community Survey (ACS) collect 
data on both contract rent and expenditure on utilities not included in rent. These data 
do not suffice for separating housing and utility expenditures, but they do permit the 
construction of "gross rent," which is the sum of housing expenditure and total utility 
expenditure. Appendix 1 reports how we use city-specific contract rent indices, the city-
specific CPI utility price indices, the BLS 1970 budget data, and census and ACS data 
on contract rents and gross rents to construct city-specific "gross rent" price indices ap-
propriate to measuring real gross rents. 
3 We then adopt the housing services model and 
define the quantity of rental housing services a household consumes to be the household's 
gross rent divided by the city-specific gross rent price index for that consumer's location. 
Figure 1 shows both the BLS rent index and our gross rent price index relative to 
the CPI price index for all goods less shelter. 
4 The BLS relative prices from 1935 to 2010 
are indicated by the closely spaced symbols in Figure 1. Our relative gross rent prices 
for 1970-2010 are indicated by the widely spaced symbols. The bases for the two indices </p>

<p>3 When using the BLS contract rent index to construct an "equivalent rent" for homeowners for use 
in the CPI, the BLS makes an adjustment for utilities in the contract rent index. But it is the unadjusted 
contract rent index that is used for the renter shelter price index in the CPI (Poole et al., 2005, pp. 20-22, 
29). 
4 Since Gordon and vanGoethem (2007) caution against using national indices for subnational anal-
yses, we rely on the BLS city-specific rent indices to construct our gross indices for most analyses here. 
However, in our regression analysis, we check for the robustness of our results to using a national gross 
rent index grounded in the national contract rent indices of Crone et al. (2010). </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>FIGURE 1: Relative BLS Contract Price Index and Relative Gross Rent Price Index. </p>

<p>FIGURE 2: Mean Rent-to-Income Ratios by Income Quintile. </p>

<p>are set so that the relative prices coincide in 1970. The sharpest difference in relative 
price changes between the two series are for the 1970s, when the contract-rent-based 
BLS measure fails to capture the sharp 1970s increases in utility expenditures and in the 
proportion of "utilities not included" rents among contract rents. </p>

<p>4. TWO EPOCHS FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>

<p>A glance at rent-to-income ratios across time reveals two epochs for rental housing: 
1940-1960 and 1970-2010. Figure 2 shows for each of five renter income quintiles, 
5 us-
ing census and ACS data, the ratios of mean gross rent (i.e., rent inclusive of utilities) 
to household income for 1940-2010. Rent-to-income ratios fell for all income quintiles </p>

<p>5 Throughout, individuals are assigned to quintiles within their city-specific renters' income distri-
bution with individuals with negative incomes excluded from consideration. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>from 1940 to 1960, 
6 and, until 1970, continued to fall slightly for the wealthiest quintiles; 
the poorest quintiles began to see increases in their rent income ratios by 1970. Since 
1970, rent income ratios have risen. Clearly, the post-1970 increases have been sharpest 
for renters in the poorest quintiles of the renter income distribution 
7 ; but even the wealth-
iest renters have seen the share spent on rent rise from 12 percent in 1970 to 18 percent 
in 2010. 
8 What has driven the changes in rent-income ratios over time? We first consider 
the period of increasing affordability, 1940-1960. Then we examine the period of declining 
affordability, 1970-2010. </p>

<p>1940-1960 </p>

<p>The story from 1940 to 1960 is simple: renters' incomes rose dramatically and the 
price of rental housing services fell substantially. Census data reveals that renters' real 
incomes rose 110 percent between 1940 and 1960. Because housing is income inelastic, 
renters opted to reduce their rent to income ratios over this period. 
9 Moreover, a BLS 
index of the price of rental services and the CPI reveal a dramatic 33 percent drop in the 
relative price of rental housing services from 1935 to 1950 that has only been partially 
undone subsequently. </p>

<p>6 The 1950 Census did not collect data on rents. The ratios observed in 1940 are not simply a reflection 
of the end of the Depression or pre-World War II buildup conditions; the ratio of median rent to estimated 
median income was about the same when the Depression started as when it was ending. The 1930 Census 
did not gather income data, but U.S. Department of Commerce (DOC) estimates imply that real per capita 
income in 1940 was 15.4 percent above that of 1930 (U.S. Bureau of the Census, 1975, Series F-4, p. 224) 
and 1930 Census data and CPI data indicate that real rents were 6 percent lower in 1940 than in 1930. 
These changes indicate a ratio of median rent to median income, rent-income, of 0.27 in 1930; that ratio 
was 0.25 in 1940, which is equal to the ratio observed in 1990 and well above the 0.19 observed in both 
1960 and 1970. 
7 Our computations are based upon households' census and ACS data for 20 of the largest U.S. cities 
compiled by the IPUMS project (Ruggles et al., 2010). For 1930 and 1940 we use the IPUMS 1 percent 
samples; for 1970 we use the IPUMS form 1 and form 2 1 percent metro samples; for 1980 we use the 
IPUMS 5 percent state sample; for 1990 and 2000 we use the IPUMS 5 percent samples; and for 2005, 
2008, and 2010 we use the IPUMS ACS samples. The 20 cities we study are: Atlanta, Baltimore, Boston, 
Cleveland, Chicago, Dallas, Detroit, Houston, Los Angeles, Miami, New York, Philadelphia, Pittsburgh, 
Phoenix, Riverside, San Diego, San Francisco, Seattle, Tampa, and Washington DC. Two constraints 
limited the sample of cities: first, it is for these 20 cities that we have consistently measured geographic 
boundaries for the metropolitan areas across time; second, for these cities we have needed city-specific price 
data. Individuals with negative incomes are excluded; for 1970-2000, individuals with rents at or above the 
IPUMS top codes are excluded from analyses of rents; for 2000-2010, individuals with the highest 1 percent 
of rents are excluded for comparability with the earlier top-coded samples. See appendix 1.1 of DiPasquale 
and Murray (2008) for the geographic definitions of these metropolitan areas. A complete list of household 
variables available from IPUMS by census year is provided at http://ipums.org/usa/hhold.html; the list 
of person variables available each year is provided at: http://ipums.org/usa/person.html. A bibliography 
of references to publications, presentations, and works in progress that use the Integrated Public Use 
Microdata Series projects is available at http://bibliography.ipums.org. 
8 In contrast, Quigley and Raphael (2004) report little change among renters in upper income quin-
tiles. The difference in results stems from our use of income quintiles for the distribution of renters' 
incomes, while Quigley and Raphael relied on income quintiles for the entire population. There are rela-
tively few renters in the uppermost national income quintiles because renters tend to have lower incomes 
than homeowners. 
9 Mayo (1981) reviews an extensive literature that estimates the income and price elasticities of 
demand. There is considerable consensus that both income and price elasticities are less than one for 
both renters and owners, though there are dissenters, e.g., Davis and Ortalo-Magne (2011). The range of 
uncertainty is considerable, with a lack of consensus beyond saying both elasticities are in the range of 
0.3-0.7. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>TABLE 1: Home Ownership Rates 1930-2010 </p>

<p>Year 
1930 
1940 
1950 
1960 
1970 
1980 
1990 
2000 
2005 
2008 
2010 </p>

<p>% owning 
47.8 
43.6 
55.0 
61.9 
62.9 
64.4 
64.2 
66.2 
68.9 
67.8 
65.1 </p>

<p>Source: Decennial census data (https://www.census.gov/newsroom/releases/archives/2010_census/cb11-
cn188.html) for all years except 2005 and 2008. 2005 and 2008 are the average of the four quarters reported 
in the Current Population Survey/Housing Vacancy Survey, Series H-111 Reports. </p>

<p>TABLE 2: An Index of Mean Real Renter Income by Local Income Quintile and Year </p>

<p>Year 
Quintile 1 
Quintile 2 
Quintile 3 
Quintile 4 
Quintile 5 </p>

<p>1970 
0.34 
0.88 
1.41 
2.00 
3.52 
1980 
0.33 
0.77 
1.25 
1.85 
3.17 
1990 
0.33 
0.85 
1.40 
2.06 
3.77 
2000 
0.33 
0.84 
1.38 
2.09 
4.44 
2005 
0.29 
0.73 
1.24 
1.91 
3.84 
2008 
0.31 
0.77 
1.30 
2.02 
4.17 
2010 
0.29 
0.72 
1.22 
1.91 
3.95 
% '70-'10 
−14.7 
−18.2 
−13.5 
−4.5 
12.2 </p>

<p>Note: See footnotes 7 and 10 for data sources, quintile definitions, and index base. </p>

<p>As shown in Table 1, the decline in the price of rental housing services coincides 
with a dramatic increase (11.4 percentage points) in the homeownership rate between 
1940 and 1950 and a 6.9 percentage point increase from 1950 to 1960. As the demand 
for new, owner-occupied, single-family homes in the suburbs increased, the price of inner 
city rental housing fell. Incomes for both renters and homeowners grew in the post-World 
War II economy. 
Because housing demand is price inelastic, the lower price of housing services induced 
a further decline in the rent-to-income ratio. Higher incomes and a lower price of rental 
housing led to increased housing consumption; for example, the proportion of rental units 
without plumbing fell from nearly half in 1940 to about one in six by 1960. </p>

<p>1970-2010 </p>

<p>Renters' fortunes reversed following 1970. Table 2 provides by year and income quin-
tile an index of mean real income for renters in the 20 cities for which we have consistent 
geographic boundaries and city-specific CPI price indices from 1970 to 2010; an index 
value of one indicates a household could just afford the bundle of goods described by 
the BLS in its 1970 budget for a renter family with four members. 
10 Between 1970 and 
2010, incomes fell appreciably for renters in all but the highest income quintile. That the 
decline in renters' incomes was a widespread phenomenon is evidenced by column 1 of 
Table 3, which reports the percentage change in median renter real income for each of 
our 20 cities. 
11 Between 1970 and 2010, the relative price of rental housing services rose </p>

<p>10 The data sources for Table 2 are those noted in footnote 7. The 1960 Census does not report 
metropolitan area identifiers, so we do not report statistics for 1960. The base (index = 1) for the index is 
the cost of the BLS low-income budget for an urban family of four in 1970 (U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, 
1972) adjusted over time by the local CPI. Table 2 omits 2 of our 20 cities, Tampa and Phoenix, for these 
we lack local CPI data for some years. 
11 Some care is needed in reading Table 3. The data are changes in medians, not means, though this 
makes only modest differences in the reported changes. Also, the price indices for real income changes </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>TABLE 3: Percentage Changes 1970-2010 in Renters' Median Real Income, the Relative 
Price of Rental Housing, and Renters' Median Real Housing and Real Nonhousing 
Consumptions for Local Third Income Quintiles </p>

<p>City 
% Real Income </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>% Relative Rental Price </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>% Real Housing </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>% Real Nonhousing </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Atlanta 
−15.2% 
6.9% 
39.6% 
−25.6% 
Baltimore 
−0.8% 
-
25.1% 
-
Boston 
−8.2% 
30.9% 
18.1% 
−17.3% 
Chicago 
−27.2% 
23.1% 
16.5% 
−33.1% 
Cleveland 
−42.4% 
−2.2% 
27.3% 
−47.6% 
Dallas 
−10.9% 
10.0% 
24.2% 
−20.4% 
Detroit 
−37.0% 
7.4% 
18.7% 
−49.0% 
Houston 
−12.4% 
24.3% 
29.1% 
−11.9% 
Los Angeles 
−7.4% 
53.3% 
19.7% 
−13.6% 
Miami 
−24.8% 
40.7% 
1.9% 
−32.4% 
New York 
−14.9% 
50.2% 
21.8% 
−22.9% 
Philadelphia 
−14.6% 
29.4% 
29.3% 
−26.2% 
Pittsburgh 
−31.5% 
4.3% 
17.8% 
−36.5% 
Riverside 
−7.5% 
54.0% 
21.6% 
−15.0% 
San Diego 
−13.7% 
43.4% 
23.8% 
−5.8% 
San Francisco 
10.7% 
58.3% 
10.5% 
12.2% 
Seattle 
−5.7% 
24.4% 
19.3% 
−3.1% 
Washington DC 
15.2% 
-
21.3% 
-
Average 
−13.8% 
28.7% 
21.4% 
−21.8% </p>

<p>Notes: 
a Incomes deflated by local CPI. 
b Gross Rent Index divided by local less-shelter CPI. 
c Rent deflated by Gross Rent Price Index. 
d Incomes less rent deflated by local less-shelter CPI. 
See footnote 7 for data sources. </p>

<p>28.7 percent, on average, across the 16 cities for which we have such price data. 
12 The 
changes in the price of rental housing services varied considerably across the cities be-
tween 1970 and 2010, as evidenced by the percentage changes in that price reported in 
Column 2 of Table 3. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Since renters' incomes fell and the price of housing services rose, it is natural to expect 
that real housing consumption fell between 1970 and 2010. But it did not. The median 
quantity of housing services renters consumed rose more than 20 percent between 1970 
and 2010, and mean real housing consumption rose in every renter income quintile, as 
evidenced by Table 4, which reports the national level of real housing consumption for 
each quintile in each of our sample years. (A value of one in Table 4 corresponds to the </p>

<p>are the local CPI, which include an owners' shelter component which is much more heavily weighted than 
the renters' shelter component. The real housing changes are created using our gross rent index. The real 
changes in nonhousing consumption are created using the CPI local nonshelter indices. Where owners' 
shelter costs rose more markedly than renters' shelter costs, the real income changes and real consumption 
changes can fail to match up as one might expect. 
12 Baltimore, Phoenix, Tampa, and Washington DC lack some local all goods less shelter CPI data. 
13 Table 3's columns should be compared with care. First, the price indices used across the columns 
are not the same. Incomes (in column 1) are deflated by the local CPI, which includes both a shelter 
component driven largely by the cost of owned homes and a nonshelter component; nonhousing expenditure 
(in column 4) are deflated by the local nonshelter CPI; and rent expenditure is deflated by our gross rent 
index. Furthermore, the table reports medians, not means; some relationships that would of necessity hold 
among means need not hold among medians. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>TABLE 4: Mean Renter Household Real Housing Services Consumed 
a , by Local Income 
Quintile and Year </p>

<p>Year 
Quintile 1 
Quintile 2 
Quintile 3 
Quintile 4 
Quintile 5 </p>

<p>1970 
0.84 
0.95 
1.04 
1.14 
1.42 
1980 
0.84 
1.00 
1.13 
1.24 
1.46 
1990 
0.88 
1.10 
1.25 
1.40 
1.69 
2000 
0.92 
1.12 
1.26 
1.41 
1.77 
2005 
0.94 
1.12 
1.26 
1.42 
1.71 
2008 
0.92 
1.11 
1.25 
1.41 
1.72 
2010 
0.96 
1.13 
1.27 
1.43 
1.76 
% Change 
Nation 
14.3% 
18.9% 
22.1% 
25.4% 
23.9% 
Regions: 
East 
5.0% 
16.3% 
20.8% 
23.7% 
22.0% 
Midwest 
20.0% 
17.3% 
22.9% 
21.7% 
25.8% 
South 
27.7% 
12.7% 
29.2% 
31.9% 
28.5% 
West 
14.3% 
17.0% 
20.8% 
24.5% 
24.8% </p>

<p>Notes: 
a Housing services equal to 1.00 correspond here to the housing services rendered by a specific rental 
housing unit deemed "suitable" for a low-income family of four in 1970 in U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (1972). 
See footnote 7 for data sources. </p>

<p>housing services rendered by a specific rental housing unit that BLS deemed "suitable" 
for a low-income family of four in 1970 (U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics, 1972).) Table 4 
also presents the regional rates of change in real housing consumption between 1970 and 
2010. Clearly, the increase in real housing consumption is a nationwide phenomenon. 
Such increases occurred even in the cities in which falling incomes were accompanied 
by the largest increases in the relative price of rental housing services. This is evidenced 
by the 18 
14 city-specific percentage changes from 1970 to 2010 in median real housing 
consumption for renters in the local third income quintile that are reported in Column 3 
of Table 3, The relative price changes and real housing consumption measures reported 
in Tables 3 and 4 are based on our gross price index and the local CPI for all goods less 
shelter. Had we relied solely on the BLS rent index, the real housing consumption changes 
would have appeared much larger than those we report. 
Substantial increases in real housing consumption when incomes are falling and 
rental housing's price is rising are very surprising. Do we see evidence of such increases 
in data that do not require price indices for calculating quantity? We do. The AHS has 
tracked the size of rental units since 1985. Table 5 reports the median square footage of 
rental units in 1985 and 2011. Nationally, renters occupied units 4.5 percent larger in 
2011 than in 1985. The median size of rental units had grown steadily from 1985 until 
2007; at that peak, units were 8 percent larger than in 1985. However, regions differed 
sharply in how the sizes of units changed. Rental units in the West grew steadily into 2011 
(up 10.9 percent from 1985), and units in the South grew until 2008 or 2009 (and in 2011 
were still up by 17.4 percent over 1985). But rental units in the Northeast and Midwest 
have never again been as large as they were in 1985, falling 14.1 percent and 10.6 percent, 
respectively, by 2011. Why do we not see in Table 4 declines in real housing consumption 
for renters in the Northeast and Midwest? The answer lies in housing's amenities. 
The AHS has tracked numerous housing amenities since 1985, and a few since 1973. 
Table 5 reports the frequencies of five housing amenities in 1985 and in 2011: having two </p>

<p>14 We do not have the needed housing price indices for Phoenix and Tampa. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>TABLE 5: Renters' Space and Amenities 1985 and 2011 </p>

<p>Year 
Nation 
Northeast 
Midwest 
South 
West </p>

<p>Square feet per unit 
1985 
1,245 
1,629 
1,454 
1,103 
1,262 
2011 
1,301 
1,400 
1,300 
1,295 
1,400 
Square feet per person 
1985 
458 
619 
537 
414 
436 
2011 
500 
576 
544 
500 
500 
% with 2+ baths 
1985 
11.7% 
4.2% 
5.7% 
17.0% 
18.2% 
2011 
27.1% 
9.8% 
17.0% 
37.4% 
34.1% 
% with clothes washer 
1985 
40.5% 
35.2% 
38.1% 
46.4% 
39.9% 
2011 
56.5% 
38.3% 
54.5% 
68.2% 
56.2% 
% with clothes dryer 
1985 
30.0% 
19.0% 
33.3% 
33.0% 
33.3% 
2011 
53.2% 
32.9% 
53.3% 
64.0% 
54.1% 
% with dishwasher 
1985 
28.0% 
15.4% 
20.8% 
35.9% 
37.3% 
2011 
49.7% 
31.8% 
43.2% 
57.7% 
57.6% 
% with central air 
1985 
26.9% 
8.5% 
23.3% 
48.3% 
19.3% 
2011 
53.1% 
19.4% 
53.1% 
80.8% 
41.6% </p>

<p>Source: 1985 and 2011 American Housing Survey National Summaries. </p>

<p>or more bathrooms, having a clothes washer, having a clothes dryer, having a dishwasher, 
and having central air conditioning. The proportion of units with two or more baths more 
than doubled between 1985 and 2011, and such increases were ubiquitous across the 
country. Similarly, in every region the proportion of units with central air doubled or 
nearly doubled over the period. The proportions of units with various appliances grew 
comparably in number, but from higher initial bases. Renters in the South and West 
have been renting more and better housing; renters in the Northeast and Midwest have 
been renting smaller, but better units. These trends were already underway before 1985. 
Between 1973 and 1985, the percentage of renters with two or more baths rose from 
6.2 percent to 11.7 percent, and the percentage with central air rose from12.9 percent to 
26.9 percent; the increases occurred in all regions. 
There is a vast literature spanning decades estimating hedonic prices of dwelling 
and location attributes. Sirmans et al. (2006) offer a meta-analysis of hedonic prices 
for numerous owner-occupied single-family dwelling characteristics. Using the models in 
81 studies, coefficients on traits in semilog specifications with the log of house value as 
the dependent variables prove rather stable over time (with the exception of lot size) 
but vary somewhat with region. The meta-analysis indicates that apart from substantial 
changes in square footage and lot size, a change in any one specific characteristic has only 
a modest effect on value. 
With this evidence before us how are we to account for renters consuming more 
housing despite lower incomes and more costly housing? Have other determinants of 
demand driven this result? Have supply constraints somehow forced greater consumption? 
We turn first to demand. </p>

<p>5. THE DETERMINANTS OF HOUSING DEMAND </p>

<p>Prices and incomes are not the only determinants of housing demand. Mankiw and 
Weil (1989) emphasize the potential impact of demographic trends on housing demand in 
the owner-occupied market. Demographics are equally likely to matter for rental housing 
markets. Moreover, the demographic composition of renter households changed markedly 
after 1970 (DiPasquale and Murray, 2008). In 2010, more renter households were female 
headed, more were black, and more (almost three times as many) were Hispanic. Renter 
households were generally slightly smaller, though in some places, such as Los Angeles, </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>they were larger. The changes in female headship and family size occurred chiefly in the 
1970s; changes in racial and ethnic makeup have occurred more steadily over time. 
Differences in ages of household heads across cities in any year are much sharper 
than the differences across time. For example, the mean ages of household heads in Dallas 
and New York differ by almost eight years, while the ages of all heads of households in 
1970 and 2010 differ by only 1.3. However, there was an appreciable (two-year) drop in 
renter household heads' mean age in the 1970s that reflects both the first appearance of 
the very large baby-boom generation into cities' rental housing markets and the shrinking 
numbers of the late 19th century and early 20th century cohorts. Cohort effects might 
dramatically affect housing consumption. The baby-boomers grew up in the post-World 
War II housing boom; the generations born in the early 20th century grew up in housing 
far more modest than the stock built in the mid-20th century. People's early shelter 
experiences might shape their expectations about what constitutes adequate housing 
which would mean that boomers and their elders would always have very different ideas 
about what constitutes adequate housing. 
To ascertain whether changes in income, prices, or demography can account for the 
rise in real housing consumption reported in Tables 3 and 4, we estimate a log-log demand 
function for housing with detailed demographic variables, as well as prices and incomes. 
Table 6, column 1 reports the results from a 16 metropolitan area 
15 fixed effects OLS re-
gression with robust standard errors clustered by city-year. The dependent variable is the 
quantity of housing services consumed: gross rent in current dollars divided by the local 
current price of housing services. The housing price index used in column 1 is our gross 
rent index grounded in the BLS contract rent index (see appendix 1 for the steps required 
to turn a contract rent index into a gross rent index). Column 2 contains comparable re-
gression results based on a gross rent index grounded in the national contract rent index 
of Crone et al. (2010). The goods for which prices are included in the demand equations 
are housing, food, medical care, transportation, and apparel, plus a price for "all other 
goods." 
16 Food is the numeraire good: income and the prices of nonfood goods are divided 
by the price of food. Since demand functions are homogeneous of degree zero in prices and 
income, we constrain the numeraire good's cross-price elasticity with housing to be minus 
the sum of the estimated coefficients on income and the other prices. 
17 The regression also </p>

<p>15 Footnote 7 details the sources for our data in Tables 6-8. The OLS regressions are for only 16 of the 
20 cities in our original sample. Baltimore, Phoenix, Tampa, and Washington DC lack some of the required 
price data for each year. Miami and Pittsburgh lack some required data for some years. While using a 
balanced panel would ensure that the year dummies cannot reflect year-to-year changes in the geographic 
composition of the sample, we include Miami and Pittsburgh in the OLS regressions because doing so 
changes almost all estimated coefficients, including the key parameters (year dummies and housing's 
income and own-price elasticities) only in the third decimal place-and changes no parameter appreciably. 
The larger sample is more nationally representative and the added observations increase efficiency. We 
exclude households reporting negative or zero incomes or rents. 
16 We rely on the metropolitan-specific CPI indices to construct our nonhousing price variables. The 
exceptions are two: (i) the food price in 1970, for which only a national index is available, and (ii) the 
price for "other goods," which we construct from the local CPI for all goods but shelter, local CPI's for 
food, medical care, transportation, and apparel, and the annual national relative importance of the CPI 
components reported by the Department of Labor. The local CPI's only track local rates of price change, 
not intercity price differences. To make cross-city comparisons, we relied on the BLS "Three Budgets for an 
Urban Family of Four Persons" U.S. Bureau of Labor Statistics (1972) which in 1970 tracked the prices of 
specific quantities of goods across 40 U.S. cities, thereby providing cross-city goods-price indices for 1970. 
One of the BLS budgets was specifically for renters and provides a base from which local prices then grew 
in accord with the local CPIs. Using city-specific fixed effects and the logs of prices absorbs the intercity 
differentials. 
17 We fail to reject this null hypothesis of homogeneity at a 5 percent significance level. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>TABLE 6: The Demand for Rental Housing Using Household Observations 1970-2010 
(Dependent Variable: Natural Log of Gross Rent Divided by Price) </p>

<p>Variable 
OLS 
OLS 
OLS 
IV </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Dummy for 1980 
0.058 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>−0.023 
0.038 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.023 
(0.020) 
(0.033) 
(0.022) 
(0.027) 
Dummy for 1990 
0.193 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.161 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.179 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.110 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.030) 
(0.064) 
(0.038) 
(0.045) 
Dummy for 2000 
0.206 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.133 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.176 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.074 
(0.043) 
(0.081) 
(0.056) 
(0.068) 
Dummy for 2005 
0.269 
0.227 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.250 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.183 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.050) 
(0.101) 
(0.066) 
(0.078) 
Dummy for 2008 
0.271 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.235 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.238 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.138 
(0.055) 
(0.105) 
(0.072) 
(0.087) 
Dummy for 2010 
0.300 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.261 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.270 
0.200 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.056) 
(0.108) 
(0.073) 
(0.088) 
ln(real income) 
0.182 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.183 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.182 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.005) 
(0.012) 
ln(real housing price) 
−0.341 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>−1.008 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>−0.374 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>−0.387 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.052) 
(0.179) 
(0.054) 
(0.180) 
ln(real apparel price) 
0.018 
−0.057 
0.028 
0.012 
(0.041) 
(0.072) 
(0.053) 
(0.049) 
ln(real medical price) 
−0.038 
0.127 
−0.026 
−0.026 
(0.049) 
(0.095) 
(0.048) 
(0.068) 
ln(real transport price) 
0.218 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.368 
0.220 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.204 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(0.079) 
(0.206) 
(0.090) 
(0.065) 
ln(real other good price) 
−0.006 
−0.001 
0.018 
0.050 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(0.015) 
(0.032) 
(0.020) 
(0.017) 
R 
2 : 
0.289 
0.289 
0.287 
-
Observations: 
1,856,311 
1,856,311 
1,593,616 
1,593,616 
With metro fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
With demographics 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
(robust estimated standard errors clustered by city-year in parentheses) </p>

<p>Notes: 
a Instruments for price and income: building cost index, construction cost index, household head's 
education. The IV regression is only for the 11 cities with instrument data. See footnote 21. 
*Significant at 0.01 level. **Significant at 0.05 level. ***Significant at 0.10 level. </p>

<p>includes variables for year, household size and composition, and the household head's eth-
nicity, race, age group, and birth cohort. The omitted category is two-parent households 
with a white head of prime working age born during the baby boom. The demographic 
variables' estimated coefficients and standard errors are reported in Appendix 1.1. The 
regression's R 
2 is 0.28. 
The central message of Table 6, first seen in columns 1 and 2 and then repeated 
in columns 3 and 4, is found in the significance and magnitudes of the coefficients on 
the year dummies (collectively the coefficients are highly statistically significant in both 
the OLS and IV regressions, with P-values less than 0.00005): even allowing for taste 
differences among cohorts, prices, income, and demographics, rental housing demand has 
risen markedly between 1970 and 2010. (Had we used the lower contract rent index 
of Ambrose et al. (2015) for 2000-2010, we would have calculated even larger demand 
increases over that decade.) 
The OLS price and income elasticity estimates, −0.34 and 0.18, reported in column 1 
of Table 6 are at the low end of estimates found in the literature (Mayo, 1981). The price 
elasticity estimated using the national Crone et al.-based gross rent index, reported in </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>column 2 of Table 6, is considerably larger in magnitude, −1.0. Despite this difference in 
price elasticity estimates, the key year-dummies' estimated coefficients in columns 1 and 
2 are quite similar-our central result about a shift in demand over time is robust to the 
choice of gross rent index. 
The OLS estimated price elasticities might suffer from simultaneity bias, as housing 
demand and housing supply are jointly determined. The price elasticity might also suffer 
attenuation bias as the price is imperfectly measured. To shield our estimates from such 
biases we employ two instruments for the price of rental housing 
18 : a year-and-city-specific 
building cost index and a year-and-city-specific construction cost index, both tracked by 
Engineering News Report and obtained from their website. 
19 Construction and building 
costs' correlations with the rental price index are 0.35 and 0.18, respectively. The national 
gross rent index grounded in Crone et al. (2010) lacks the regional variation of the city-
specific measures and proves too weak for sensible instrumental variables estimation. We 
do not report those results. 
Mayo notes that income elasticity estimates based on current income tend to be 
smaller than those based on permanent income. Our income elasticity may have a further 
downward bias due to measurement error inherent in the census asking people about 
current rent, but last year's income. 
20 We use the household head's education as an 
instrument for income; education is correlated with permanent income and, we assume, 
uncorrelated with transient income and errors from using lagged income. Column 4 of 
Table 6 reports the results from a 2SLS IV estimation of the demand function of column 1. 
The IV-estimated price elasticity, −0.39, is only slightly larger than the OLS estimate, 
but the IV-estimated income elasticity, 0.53, is much higher than the OLS estimate. These 
estimates are more in line with past studies than were the OLS estimates. 
21 Because the </p>

<p>18 The dependent variable in our demand equations is the natural log of reported rent less the natural 
log of price. In our log-log specification, subtracting the log of price from both sides alters only the coefficient 
on the log of price. In particular, it has no effect on the disturbances. Consequently, any instrument valid 
for estimating a rent regression is also valid for estimation when the dependent variable is the log of rent 
less the log of price. It is tempting to look for land price data to use as an instrument, given the importance 
of land's cost in supply. However, a valid instrument cannot be correlated with the part of an endogenous 
explanatory that is correlated with the disturbance term (Murray, 2006). Land values are largely locally 
driven, so shocks to local housing demand are likely to be reflected in local land prices. We would need 
an instrument with both temporal and cross-sectional variation that is uncorrelated with the endogenous 
component of land price. Such is hard to come by. 
19 The construction cost index (http://enr.construction.com/economics) is based on "200 hours of com-
mon labor at the 20-city average of common labor rates, plus 25 cwt of standard structural steel shapes at 
the mill price prior to 1996 and the fabricated 20-city price from 1996, plus 1.128 tons of Portland cement 
at the 20-city price, plus 1,088 board-ft of 2 × 4 lumber at the 20-city price." The building cost index is 
based on "68.38 hours of skilled labor at the 20-city average of bricklayers, carpenters and structural iron 
workers rates, plus 25 cwt of standard structural steel shapes at the mill price prior to 1996 and the 
fabricated 20-city price from 1996, plus 1.128 tons of Portland cement at the 20-city price, plus 1,088 board 
ft of 2 × 4 lumber at the 20-city price." Many of the components of the index are determined in regional 
markets, but labor's cost is determined more locally. Since rent is one determinant of local wages among 
many, there remains room for concern about the construction cost index as a valid instrument. 
20 The incomes in the regression have been adjusted for price differences between the census year 
and the preceding year, but not for any growth or fall in incomes. 
21 The P-values of the F-statistics for the relevance of the instruments in the rental-housing price and 
income reduced form equations are 0.053 and less than 0.0005, respectively. While the instruments appear 
relevant, we find that the instruments are weak for rental housing's price (using Finlay and Magnuson's 
2009 riv test routine in <rs type="software">STATA</rs>, which is robust to clustered disturbances, and conditioning on the IV 
estimate of the income elasticity). The instruments' weakness arises because fixed-effects for city and year 
in the model absorb much of the variation in both the cost indices and the price of rental housing, leaving </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>IV estimates are only for a sample of 11 cities, 
22 we also report, in column 3 of Table 6, 
the results of an OLS regression for those 11 cities. Note that the 11-city income and price 
elasticities, −0.37 and 0.18, are very close to the full sample OLS estimates; the time 
dummies also have similar coefficients in the two regressions. The similar estimates in 
columns 1 and 3 encourage us to consider the IV estimates from the 11 cities as instructive 
for the 16 cities. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>The estimated demographic effects are unsurprising and almost all are statistically 
significant. Larger households consume more housing; single-parents living with no other 
adult consume more housing than households with two or more adults; non-Hispanic 
whites consume more housing than other groups; cross-price elasticities are generally 
small and often statistically insignificant, though the estimate of 0.18 for transportation 
strikes us as unduly large; the implicit OLS estimate of the cross-price elasticity of housing 
with respect to the price of food is −0.31 and statistically significant; and the baby-boomers 
and their successors consume more housing than earlier birth cohorts. This last result 
is consonant with the basic theme of this paper: tastes for housing change over time. 
Household heads born prior to World War II have a substantially different view of what 
constitutes suitable housing than do household heads from the baby-boom generation and 
their successors; prewar households consume about 10 percent less housing than baby-
boomers, ceteris paribus. (We experimented with several variants of the age variable 
specification. The estimated cohort effects were robust to these.) 
Tables 4 and 5 indicate that the largest shifts in demand occurred in the South. 
Regression analyses confirm that finding. Table 7 reports OLS and IV estimated coeffi-
cients for year dummies by region from regressions that again control for income, prices, 
demographics, and metropolitan area. The reported coefficients estimate how much the 
intercept term for a given decade and region differs from the 1970 intercept term for that 
same region. In both OLS and IV regressions, 23 of 24 estimated differences are positive. 
The largest estimated effects are for the southern region; the other three regions appear 
to have similarly smaller increases in demand. We reject at conventional significance 
levels the hypotheses that demand has been unchanging, either everywhere or in some 
one specific region. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>Implicit in the estimates reported in Tables 6 and 7 is a story about when the shifts 
in renters' demands for housing occurred. Table 8 makes this story explicit by reporting 
the changes in the estimated coefficients of Table 6 from one time period to the next. </p>

<p>little variation in either for estimating the price elasticity. In the model specified without city fixed-effects, 
we find the instruments for rental housing's price, as well as for income, are not weak. The resulting price 
and income elasticities are −0.55 and 0.53, respectively, very like estimates elsewhere. The IV estimates 
for the year dummies are little affected by dropping the city fixed-effects, though they become slightly 
larger after 2000 without fixed-effects. The weak instrument robustness of our estimation and inference 
about exogenous variables is consonant with the discussion of Andrews and Stock (2007) who report 
several alternative criteria for such robustness-one of which our data satisfy. Since our interest in these 
regressions is in exogenous variables-specifically whether controlling for demographics (in addition to 
prices and income) eliminates the seeming effects of time on renters' demands-the possible weakness of 
the price instruments is not a particular problem for us. 
22 The IV regressions are for only 11 cities because, in addition to the four cities that lack needed 
price data, Houston, Miami, Pittsburgh, Riverside, and San Diego lack construction index data. 
23 2SLS is generally not robust to weak instruments. It is therefore heartening that Fuller's approxi-
mately unbiased IV estimator (Fuller, 1977), which has been shown in numerous Monte Carlos to be weak 
instrument robust as a point estimator (e.g., Hahn et al., 2004; Andrews and Stock, 2007) yields essentially 
the same price and income elasticities as 2SLS does in our sample. For more about instrument weakness 
and our analysis, see footnote 22. 
24 The census and ACS surveys are drawn independently across the years. Consequently, each year's 
data offers independent information about changes in housing demand over time. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>TABLE 7: Regional Rental Housing Demand Changes from 1970 Controlling for Income, 
Prices, and Demographics (Dependent Variable: Natural Log of Gross Rent Divided by 
Price) </p>

<p>Northeast 
Midwest 
South 
West </p>

<p>Year 
OLS 
IV 
OLS 
IV 
OLS 
IV 
OLS 
IV </p>

<p>1980 
0.017 
0.023 
−0.006 
0.022 
0.095 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.028 
0.043 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>−0.003 
1990 
0.133 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.079 
0.075 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.075 
0.199 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.132 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.182 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.066 
2000 
0.130 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.048 
0.052 
0.011 
0.228 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.085 
0.131 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.013 
2005 
0.197 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.118 
0.143 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.139 
0.305 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.206 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.196 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.073 
2008 
0.154 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.048 
0.120 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.092 
0.290 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.172 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.193 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.043 
2010 
0.184 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.104 
0.167 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.177 
0.331 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.260 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.206 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.091 </p>

<p>Notes: *Statistically significant at 0.01; **statistically significant at 0.05; ***statistically significant at 0.10. </p>

<p>TABLE 8: Shifts in Demand by Period after Controlling for Incomes, Prices, 
Demographics, and Location (Changes in Table 6 Estimated Year Dummies' Coefficients) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
Period 
OLS 
OLS 
IV </p>

<p>1970-1980 
5.8% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>3.8% </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.3% 
1980-1990 
13.5% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>14.1% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>8.7% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1990-2000 
1.3% 
−0.3% 
−3.7% 
2000-2005 
6.3% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>7.4% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>11.0% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>2005-2008 
0.2% 
−1.2% 
−4.5% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>2008-2010 
2.9% </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>3.2% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>6.2% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1970-2010 
30.0% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>27.0% </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>20.0% </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Notes: *Statistically significant at 0.01; **statistically significant at 0.05; *** statistically significant at 0.10. </p>

<p>Qualitatively, the OLS and IV results are in accord that the largest shifts in renters' 
demand for housing occurred in the 1980s and between 2000 and 2005. The IV results 
expose statistically significant changes in every period but the 1970s and 1990s. 
25 A 
similar pattern is seen for each region using the results of Table 7, but the IV estimates 
are less precise for the year-by-region results. </p>

<p>6. CHANGING CHARACTERISTICS OF HOUSING SUPPLY </p>

<p>Since conventional demand analysis does not account for the increase in renters' 
housing consumption, we turn to supply considerations. If housing were a conventional 
good and unaffected by government policies, the price of housing services would suffice 
for capturing the effects of supply on people's consumption of housing. In that case, our 
instrumental variables estimates would properly account for the interactions of supply 
and demand. However, housing is not conventional good and housing markets are targets 
of government policy. </p>

<p>25 The 1970s and 1990s were the only two periods of increased income equality (the 1970s) or lessened 
increasing income inequality (the 1990s) in our sample years (Autor et al., 2008). We, therefore, examined 
whether increased income inequality might spur renters' housing consumption by increasing the amount 
of housing the less wealthy renters would need to "keep up" with the wealthier, home-owning "Jones'." 
Including in our model one or another of various city-and-year-specific measures of income inequality had 
only small effects on the time dummy coefficients reported in Table 6. Inequality's estimated coefficients 
were always small, generally insignificant, and of mixed signs. Keeping up with the Jones' is not the root 
of the observed shift in renters' housing demand. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>Housing services' unconventional character is that they are delivered by discrete, 
long-lived but physically depreciating dwellings. As housing units depreciate, they tend 
to become occupied by less wealthy tenants. This filtering process is a centerpiece of the 
housing literature. Governments' intervention in housing markets comes in two primary 
forms: the provision of subsidies for housing supply or demand and land use and building 
regulations. 
Lowry (1960) provides a clear intuitive account of the filtering process. Sweeney 
(1974) provides a definitive theoretical framework for analyzing this filtering process. 
Empirical work on filtering is scarce, but Rosenthal (2014) provides evidence describing 
the connections among housing's depreciation rate, households' price and income elastici-
ties of demand, changes in the market price of housing, and the path of dwellings through 
the income distribution. Unfortunately, Rosenthal's work, rooted in housing demand, does 
not reveal the empirical structure of the dynamic interaction between housing supply and 
housing demand that might ideally inform our work. At the core of Sweeney's model of 
filtering is the notion of hierarchies of dwellings. New dwellings tend to sit at the top 
of the hierarchy since they tend to be of above average quality. Suppliers of these new 
dwellings are responsive to the housing demands of wealthier households. Households a 
little lower on the wealth ladder tend to choose from the slightly depreciated dwellings 
now abandoned by the occupants of new dwellings. 
Since housing quality is correlated with housing's age, housing markets with a larger 
share of younger units are apt to afford renters at each wealth level with better housing 
opportunities. In our data, when the proportion of units less than 10 and between 10 and 
20 years of age and the proportion of the stock built before 1950 are added to the regression 
of column 1, Table 6, they prove collectively insignificant and the estimated coefficients on 
the year dummies are only modestly reduced. Besides recent new construction, another 
possibility for filtering raising renters' consumption is through increased homeownership. 
Often, becoming a homeowner means leaving an apartment to buy a house. Many rental 
units left behind by such (usually) higher income renters become available to lower income 
tenants. As seen in Table 1, homeownership rates were rising over much of our sample 
period. Did units newly available to the growing number of renters simply provide much 
more housing than the units occupied in 1970, leaving renters no choice but to occupy 
such units? The local homeownership rate, when added to the regressions in column 1 
of Table 6, proves only marginally statistically significant, with an unexpectedly positive 
coefficient, while other coefficients are not much changed. Shifting homeownership rates 
do not account for the conundrum of increasing real housing consumption as renters' 
incomes fall and rental housing's price rises. 
Filtering might deny some renters the lower quality units they would prefer, but it 
would not drain from the stock already existing lower quality units. In 1970, 33 percent 
of rental units in the 17 cities for which we have housing price data were of the quality 
that subsequently rented for $675 or less in 2010 Baltimore housing dollars. By 2010, the 
number of units of such quality had fallen by a fifth, despite falling incomes of renters 
and growing numbers of renters in all of these cities. The lost low-quality units may 
have been removed from the stock or they may have been upgraded to serve higher 
income households. While gentrification has replaced or upgraded low-end units in many 
neighborhoods in many cities, the scale of gentrification across 17 cities and across the four 
decade time span of our study seems too small to explain the changes we observe in the 
low-rent stock. 
26 If renters are pressed by limits on supply to consume more housing than </p>

<p>26 Maciag (2015) estimates that only 8 percent of census tracts in the 50 largest cities experienced 
gentrification between 2000 and 2010. The evidence presented suggests that gentrification increased </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>they would like, why would the low-quality units leave the stock? 
27 A filtering account 
of renters' increased housing consumption is inconsistent with the documented loss of 
low-end units. 
One might also speculate that increases in the stock of subsidized housing might 
account for the increased housing consumption we observe at the lower end of the renter 
income distribution. This is not the case. We measure the "quantity" a dwelling provides 
as the ratio of the unit's gross rent paid to the price of housing. We underestimate the real 
housing services of units with subsidized rents below the units' market value. Since such 
units have grown over time as a proportion of the rental stock, correcting our measure to 
account for the actual services of subsidized units would result in even higher estimates 
of the growth in real housing consumption than we report. 
Many authors have worried that government regulations have made the available 
supply of housing less affordable for both owners and renters (e.g., Downs, 1991; U.S. De-
partment of Housing and Urban Development, 2007; Glaeser and Gyourko, 2003; Glaeser 
et al., 2005, 2006; Saks, 2008). 
28 Quigley and Raphael (2004, p. 211) argue that the 
affordability problems facing renters could be eased by removing the regulatory bar-
riers that impede the construction of affordable rental housing. However, Quigley and 
Raphael also note that there are no studies that explicitly measure the impact of land 
use regulations on the increases in rent burdens over time presented in their analysis 
(2004, p. 208). In fact, there is limited data measuring the extent of land use regu-
lation by locality and there is no data on changes over time. Saiz (2010) and Turner 
et al. (2014) provide compelling evidence that regulation, as well as local geographic 
constraints, impact housing supply and, further, that regulatory regimes are endoge-
nous, changing with local housing market conditions. One question facing us, then, is 
whether the observed rise in rental housing's income share for renters is attributable to 
changing regulatory conditions between 1970 and the present. Saiz (2010) and Turner 
et al. (2014) argue convincingly that housing regulation variation across cities has consid-
erable effect on supply. If regulation varies as much over time as it does over space, 
then changing regulation might account for renters' increased housing consumption. 
Lacking an intertemporal measure of regulation, Saiz (2010) and Turner et al. (2014) </p>

<p>between 2000 and 2010 with 20 percent of tracts with low incomes and low house values experiencing gen-
trification compared with just 9 percent in the 1990s. While some of our cities appear to have experienced 
gentrification in the study, there are no estimates of the impact on the size and quality of the housing 
stock. (Gentrification is measured by increases in house values, incomes, and share of the population 
25 years and older with bachelor's degrees.) Nonetheless, gentrification might have contributed to renters' 
increased consumption in some cities. However, the increase in demand we observe is ubiquitous, while 
gentrification is not. 
27 It is also possible that the rents on these units rose more than average. We know of no evidence on 
the correlation of housing quality and changes in rents over time. An assumption of the BLS price index, 
and hence of ours, is that the law of one price applies to housing services. 
28 In 1990, Congress mandated that HUD report annually the number of households facing worst case 
housing needs, including affordability problems (e.g., U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, 
2007). HUD subsequently formed a commission to study regulatory barriers to affordable housing (Downs, 
1991). More recently, DiPasquale and Murray (2008) document a sharp decline in the number of low-rent 
housing units available in American cities, despite growing numbers of renters. Numerous studies have 
focused on the dynamics of such changes, asking why, as time passes, do some units disappear from the 
affordable stock and others appear in it (e.g., Nelson and Vandenbroucke, 1996; Somerville and Holmes, 
2001; Somerville and Mayer, 2003). These many studies rely chiefly on the AHS and most limit attention 
to a single decade or less. Some offer national numbers, others regional numbers, while still others report 
outcomes for a small number of cities. Only Nelson and Vandenbroucke (1996) report on a large number 
of cities (41), but they observe each of those cities for only four years. Where these studies' time periods 
overlap with DiPasquale and Murray's longer, census-based work, the results are in basic agreement. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>implicitly assume regulation has not changed over time-they apply the 2005 city-specific 
regulation measure (Gyourko et al., 2008) across several decades. 
Without an intertemporal measure of regulation, it is difficult to assess the claim 
that it is increased regulation that accounts for renters' markedly increased real housing 
consumption since 1970. However, there is some suggestive evidence that points away 
from changing regulation as the cause. Table 3 reveals that for all but the first income 
quintile, most of renters' increase in real housing consumption occurred between 1970 
and 1990. (The increase in the lowest quintile has occurred more smoothly over time.) 
The 1970 and 1990 censuses identified households as "urban" or "rural," where "urban" 
denotes any city or incorporated place of more than 2,500 inhabitants. Rural households 
made up 11 percent of all renter households in 1970. Anderson (2012) argues that county 
governments were very slow to adopt land use controls in rural areas and rural land 
remains less regulated than urban land. 
29 Because housing market regulation is markedly 
more extensive in urban areas and their surroundings than in truly rural areas, we expect 
that between 1970 and 1990 the renters designated as rural experienced less regulation-
driven increased housing consumption than did urban renters. Did these rural renters 
increase their real housing consumption less than urban renters did? 
Unfortunately, there is no rural analog to the BLS rent index data, so we cannot in 
the BLS data compare the real housing consumptions of rural and urban renters. What 
we can compare in the census data are rural and urban rent income ratios and how those 
changed between 1970 and 1990. If changes in regulation between 1970 and 1990 pressed 
urban renters, but not rural renters, to increase their rent income ratios, we would not, 
ceteris paribus, see rural rent-income ratios rise as urban rent-income ratios did. What 
do we observe? The median ratio of gross rent to income for rural renters in 1970 was 
0.169; for urban renters it was 0.206. The corresponding ratios in 1990 were 0.241 and 
0.283. 
30 The increases in housing expenditure as a fraction of income were much the same 
for rural and urban households. 
But ceteris is not always paribus. Shifts in incomes and prices in rural areas relative 
to urban areas could account for rural rent-income ratios rising as urban ratios did with-
out the pressure of sharply increased regulation. Between 1970 and 1990 rural renters' 
incomes fell by 3 percent relative to urban renters' incomes. Given the income inelasticity 
of housing demand, this relative shift would tend to make rural household's rent-income 
ratios rise relative to those for urban households by about 1.5 percent. Thus, differential 
urban-rural income changes are not sufficient to account for rural rent-income ratios 
keeping up with supposedly regulation-driven increases in urban areas. 
Since we do not have a rental housing services price index for the rural sector, we 
cannot empirically assess such price changes. However, such differential price changes 
would have to have been quite substantial given housing's price inelasticity and the large 
increases in urban rent-income ratios induced by substantial quantity increases in urban 
areas. Moreover, such a marked differential change in prices would have to have involved 
rural housing services' price rising markedly from 1970 to 1990 relative to the urban price. </p>

<p>29 Anderson (2012) argues that the lack of land use control at the urban fringe in unincorporated 
rural areas contributed to urban sprawl over time. While she acknowledges that data on rural land use 
regulation is scarce, she argues land use controls were largely adopted by urban municipalities not county 
governments from the 1930s through the late 1970s and 1980s. Regional planning efforts became more 
common in county government in the 1970s and 1980s which brought some land use controls but the fiscal 
needs of county government encouraged prodevelopment positions and weak land use controls (Anderson, 
2012, p. 377). 
30 These ratios are for renters with strictly positive incomes and rents for real income and rent levels 
not top-coded in either 1970 or 1990. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>1935 1960-61 1972-73 1984 
1994 
2001 
2011 </p>

<p>Budget Share </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3: Gross Rent's Budget Share in the CEX by Expenditure Quintiles. </p>

<p>Such a large increase in the rural rental-housing services' price relative to the urban price 
strikes us as implausible. 
Thus, unless housing market regulation changed equally dramatically in both urban 
and rural areas between 1970 and 1990, the comparable rent-income ratio increases in 
rural and urban areas argue against changes in regulation being the cause of the observed 
increase in real housing consumption between 1970 and 1990. </p>

<p>7. HOUSING AND NONHOUSING EXPENDITURE SHARES </p>

<p>The 21.4 percent increase in renters' median real housing consumption that occurred 
between 1970 and 2010, coupled with an accompanying 13.8 percent fall in renters' median 
income and a 28.7 percent increase in the relative price of rental housing, forced renters 
into difficult decisions. Real nonhousing consumption fell 21.8 percent. Changes in rent's 
budget share must be accompanied by offsetting changes in other goods' budget shares. 
Which goods would renters cut most, and which least? We employ the CEX to analyze the 
changing composition of renters' household budgets from 1935 to 2010. Figure 3 reports 
the gross rent share of total household expenditures for 1935-2011 for each of the five 
total expenditure quintiles using the CEX. 
31 While the patterns over time of the rent-
to-income ratios shown in Figure 2 and the rent-to-expenditure ratios in Figure 3 are 
similar, there are some differences: (i) the spike in rent to expenditure ratio in 1973-
1974; (ii) the much lower rent ratios for households in the lowest quintile; and (iii) the 
increase in that quintile's rent ratio from 1935 to 1960. 
32 The spike might be due to 
sharply increased utility expenditures during the first oil shock of the 1970s. The higher 
rent-to-income ratios for the first quintile are probably due to substantial numbers of </p>

<p>31 We obtained the 1935, 1961, and 1973 CEX data from ICPSR. We obtained the 2011 CEX data from 
the BLS CEX website. The other years' CEX data were obtained from NBER's CEX website. Those who 
wish to replicate our findings using our code will need first to obtain the raw data from ICPSR, NBER, 
and BLS. Combining the data from the several years required numerous small judgments about categories 
across the years; our code reflects those judgments. 
32 The CEX contains income data. The rent-to-income ratios using the CEX data look very much like 
Figure 2 except that, as in Figure 3, the first quintile's rent share rises from 1935 until 1960 or 1973. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>1935 1960-61 1972-73 1984 
1994 
2001 
2011 </p>

<p>Budget Share </p>

<p>Year </p>

<p>Rent </p>

<p>Food </p>

<p>Trans </p>

<p>Medical </p>

<p>Clothing </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>FIGURE 4: Mean Budget Shares by Spending Category, CEX 1935-2011. </p>

<p>TABLE 9: Changes in Budget Shares CEX 1935-2011 </p>

<p>Change 1935-2011 
Change 1972-2011 
Change 2001-2011 </p>

<p>Rent 
0.134 
0.057 
0.053 
Food 
−0.125 
−0.022 
0.008 
Transport 
0.045 
−0.028 
−0.013 
Medical 
0.000 
−0.005 
0.000 
Clothing 
−0.068 
−0.057 
−0.015 
Other 
0.014 
0.055 
−0.033 </p>

<p>reported low incomes that stem from including substantial transitory financial losses in 
income, coupled with the high rents paid in accord with usually much higher incomes. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>With declines in renter income as housing's expenditure share is increasing, renters 
are decreasing their consumption of other things; column 4 of Table 3 reports the percent-
age change from 1970 to 2010 in median real nonhousing consumption for the 16 cities 
for which we have a local all goods but shelter CPI. Real nonhousing consumption fell in 
12 of the cities and by 21.9 percent overall. The CEX allows us to detail the distribution 
of this reduced spending across budget items. 
Figure 4 shows the trends in mean budget shares by spending category from 1935 to 
2011. The spending categories were chosen to indicate budget shares devoted to necessi-
ties. In 2011, the largest components of the "Other" category are insurance, pensions, and 
entertainment. As shown in Figure 4, rent's budget share increases over most of the time 
span, peaking in 2011. Food's budget share declines significantly until the early 1970s 
then flattens out through 2011. As shown in Table 9, the total change in budget shares 
from 1935 through 2011 is dominated by increases in rent budget share (13.4 percentage 
point increase) that are largely offset by declines in the food budget share (12.5 percent-
age point decrease). However, since 1972-1973, the size of the rent share increase is two 
and a half times the size of the food share decrease. The rent share increase and similar 
increase in the "Other" spending share are offset by declines in budget shares for food, 
transport, and clothing. The rise in rent budget share between 2001 and 2011 is offset 
with decreases in shares for transport, clothing, and other spending. </p>

<p>33 Using Current Population Survey and CEX data, Cutler and Katz (1992) document comparable 
differences between the first income quintile's shares of income and expenditure for other years. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>8. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In this paper, we document the changing fortunes of renter over eight decades with 
detailed attention to the past four decades. From 1940 to 1970, American renters shared in 
the growing prosperity of other Americans. Renters spent less of their incomes on housing 
while increasing the quantities of housing consumed. Since 1970, renter incomes fell, the 
price of rental housing services rose, but renters consumed more housing. With declining 
incomes, renters have faced tough choices. Their increase in housing consumption was 
accompanied by decreases in spending on clothing, food, and transport. 
The increase in renters' housing consumption while incomes fell and rents rose is 
a confounding puzzle. Our results show that the increases in housing consumption are 
far from fully explained by demographic changes in the U.S. renter population. While 
lack of data limit our ability to provide definitive analysis of the impact of supply fac-
tors on the increase in renters' housing consumption, the evidence we do have indicate 
that the increases in housing consumption among renters are not due to commonly sug-
gested supply factors. Filtering as measured by the age composition of the stock does 
not account for the increase in housing consumption. A lack of time series data on reg-
ulation by city precludes us from directly assessing the role of regulation in increased 
housing consumption, but indirect evidence suggests that regulation has not driven those 
increases. Our analysis supports the claim that in the years since 1970 there has been a 
fundamental change in the tastes of renters-they have a stronger preference for housing 
consumption. </p>

<p>APPENDIX 1. </p>

<p>A Gross Price Index for Rental Housing Services </p>

<p>Because our analyses focus on the gross rents (that is, rents including utilities) 
reported in IPUMS, we need gross rent price indices to separate prices and quantities. 
The BLS rent index is not a gross rent price index; the BLS index is based on a sample of 
contract rents, some of which include utilities and some of which do not. From 1970 to 2010, 
the role of utilities has changed significantly. Utility costs have increased substantially 
and the portion of units where rents include utilities has decreased. We construct city-
specific gross rent indices from the BLS city-specific contract rent indices. The IPUMS 
census and ACS data allow us to estimate the fraction of rents in the BLS sample that are 
gross rents and the fraction where contract rents do not include utilities (using numbers 
of households with contract rents and the numbers of households with gross rents not 
equal to contract rent). The IPUMS data also allow us to estimate the ratio of utility 
expenditures to gross rent (using those households for which reported contract rent and 
reported gross rent differ to infer utilities expenditures). 
We use the IPUMS data on the ratio of utilities to gross rent for those whose contract 
rents do not include utilities and on the fraction of renters whose utilities are not included 
in rent to convert the contract rents BLS observes into gross rents. 
The standard practice in building price indices is to fix the quantities in a bundle and 
to then track the cost of that fixed quantity over time. We track the cost of a fixed bundle 
of utilities by identifying a bundle of utilities in 1970 (specifically, the utilities included by 
the BLS in determining 1970 gross rent for the low-income budget) and increasing that 
cost over time in accord with the local fuel CPI. So, in this second role of utilities in our 
work, real utility consumption is held fixed. (We would have preferred fixing quantities in 
the housing bundle at some midpoint of the period under study, but the last BLS cross-city 
budget study was done in 1970.) </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>

<p>We fix the quantity of rental housing whose cost we track over time by examining 
hypothetical renters with the BLS 1970 low-income budget. The gross rent for this unit in 
1970, GR 70 , is provided by the BLS budget data. We assume that in 1970 contract rents 
that included utilities did so correctly, on average. Consequently, across units like the unit 
in the BLS budget, the mean contract rent observed by BLS would have been </p>

<p>CR 70 = GR 70 − f 70 U 70 , </p>

<p>where f 70 is the fraction of renters whose rent does not include utilities in 1970 and U 70 
is the cost of utilities in the BLS 1970 budget. We use an estimate for U 70 : </p>

<p>U 70 = p 70 GR 70 , </p>

<p>where p 70 is the fraction of 1970 gross rent that is utilities for those households in the 
IPUMS for whom contract rent does not equal gross rent. (These estimates overlook 
the endogeneity of utilities' inclusion in rent that might result in utility costs differing 
between units including utilities in rent and units not including utilities in rent.) 
The BLS rent index implies that contract rents changed between 1970 and 1980 at 
some rate g 80 , so that CR 80 = (1 + g 80 )CR 70 and </p>

<p>GR 80 = CR 80 + f 80 U 80 = (1 + g 80 ) CR 70 + f 80 U 80 . 
(A1) </p>

<p>From the IPUMS, we estimate that </p>

<p>GR 80 = U 80 / p 80 . 
(A2) </p>

<p>Solving (1) and (2) for U 80 yields </p>

<p>U 80 = 
p 80 (1 + g 80 ) CR 70 
(1 − p 80 f 80 ) 
(A3) </p>

<p>which, by (2), implies that </p>

<p>GR 80 = 
(1 + g 80) CR 70 
(1 − p 80 f 80) 
. 
(A4) </p>

<p>Iterating this procedure from year to year yields a series of gross rent estimates. 
However, these gross rent estimates do not hold the quantity of utilities fixed. The IPUMS 
ratios of utilities to gross rent reflect changes in the prices of utilities and changes in the 
quantities of utilities. A proper gross rent index would be based upon a fixed quantity of 
utilities. To obtain such a fixed quantity series of gross rents, we obtain the evolving cost 
of a fixed quantity of utilities,Ũ t , by inflating U 70 over time using the local CPI fuel price 
index. We then subtract (A3) from (A4) and addŨ t to obtain the time path of the gross 
rent of the housing service embodied in the 1970 BLS budget rental unit,R t . 
In constructing its rent index, BLS began accounting for depreciation of the units in 
1988. We account for depreciation from 1970 to 1987. For years prior to 1988, we adjust the 
quantity of housing absent utilities to reflect a 0.7 percent annual decline in the quantity 
of housing services provided by the BLS units. This rate of decline is in the mid-range 
of 0.5-0.9 percent per annum that Apgar et al. (1987), DiPasquale and Wheaton (1992), 
and Lowry (1982) report as estimates found in the literature for rental housing's annual 
depreciation rate. We have also computed gross rent price indices assuming depreciation 
rates of 0.5 and 0.9 percent; our qualitative results persist if these indices are used in lieu 
of the index based upon a 0.7 percent depreciation rate. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>



<p>APPENDIX 2. </p>

<p>Demographic Effects in the Demand for Housing Equations of Table 6 </p>

<p>Variable 
OLS 
OLS 
OLS 
IV </p>

<p>Elderly (over 65) 
−0.144 
−0.141 
−0.146 
0.036 
(0.013) 
(0.013) 
(0.014) 
(0.030) 
Young (18-29) 
−0.019 
−0.018 
−0.016 
0.066 
(0.004) 
(0.005) 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
Midage (45-65) 
−0.041 
−0.040 
−0.043 
−0.014 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.010) 
Born pre-1920 
−0.117 
−0.119 
−0.122 
−0.082 
(0.018) 
(0.019) 
(0.020) 
(0.027) 
Born 1920-1929 
−0.117 
−0.119 
−0.120 
−0.108 
(0.011) 
(0.011) 
(0.013) 
(0.021) 
Born 1930-1939 
−0.080 
−0.082 
−0.083 
−0.080 
(0.009) 
(0.009) 
(0.010) 
(0.014) 
Born 1940-1945 
−0.034 
−0.035 
−0.037 
−0.048 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.012) 
Born after 1964 
0.041 
0.041 
0.046 
0.041 
(0.010) 
(0.010) 
(0.011) 
(0.012) 
Single head 
−0.110 
−0.110 
−0.107 
0.074 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
Female head 
0.026 
0.026 
0.024 
0.101 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.008) 
Number of kids 2 parent hhd 
0.017 
0.018 
0.016 
0.030 
(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.003) 
Number of kids 1 parent hhd 
0.028 
0.027 
0.026 
0.043 
(0.003) 
(0.003) 
(0.004) 
(0.003) 
Second adult 1 parent hhd 
0.082 
0.082 
0.083 
−0.090 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
(# of adults-2) in 2 parent hhd 
0.022 
0.022 
0.022 
−0.022 
(0.003) 
(0.003) 
(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(# of adults-2) in 1 parent hhd 
0.066 
0.066 
0.065 
−0.047 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.006) 
(0.005) 
Black head 
−0.231 
−0.231 
−0.233 
−0.084 
(0.008) 
(0.008) 
(0.009) 
(0.011) 
Hispanic head 
−0.202 
−0.203 
−0.206 
−0.064 
(0.009) 
(0.009) 
(0.010) 
(0.012) 
Hispanic black head 
0.155 
0.155 
0.159 
0.062 
(0.012) 
(0.011) 
(0.013) 
(0.017) 
Race neither white or black 
−0.084 
−0.080 
−0.085 
−0.009 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.005) 
(0.006) </p>



<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 57, NO. 1, 2017 </p>



<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>DIPASQUALE AND MURRAY: THE SHIFTING DEMAND FOR RENTAL HOUSING </p>





<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

</text></tei>