<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.26.3.87" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>pollution: groundwater toxins, acid rain, air pollution, global warming, and so on. 
pollution: groundwater toxins, acid rain, air pollution, global warming, and so on. 
Indeed, given the great linguistic generality of the term "pollution" (including noise 
Indeed, given the great linguistic generality of the term "pollution" (including noise 
pollution, light pollution, and others), it can be diffi cult for economists to fi nd an 
pollution, light pollution, and others), it can be diffi cult for economists to fi nd an 
example of a negative externality that 
example of a negative externality that cannot be described as a form of pollution. Our 
be described as a form of pollution. Our 
two favorite nonpollution externalities for teaching are traffi c congestion and spam. 
two favorite nonpollution externalities for teaching are traffi c congestion and spam. 
Of course, a similar externality has been present for decades in other forms of 
Of course, a similar externality has been present for decades in other forms of 
unsolicited advertising, including junk mail, telemarketing, and billboards. These 
unsolicited advertising, including junk mail, telemarketing, and billboards. These 
intrusive activities also impose claims on consumer attention without offering 
intrusive activities also impose claims on consumer attention without offering 
compensation or choice. However, email spam is breathtakingly larger in magni-
compensation or choice. However, email spam is breathtakingly larger in magni-
tude, with quantities in the absence of automated spam fi lters equal to hundreds of 
tude, with quantities in the absence of automated spam fi lters equal to hundreds of 
emails per user per day-if our email inboxes stood unguarded, they would quickly 
emails per user per day-if our email inboxes stood unguarded, they would quickly 
become totally useless. (In contrast, junk mail has not yet reduced our unguarded 
become totally useless. (In contrast, junk mail has not yet reduced our unguarded 
postal mailboxes to this fate.) One can purchase unsolicited email delivery on the 
postal mailboxes to this fate.) One can purchase unsolicited email delivery on the 
black market for a price at least a thousand times less than that to send bulk postal 
black market for a price at least a thousand times less than that to send bulk postal 
mail. Spam has become such a widespread phenomenon that trademark holder 
mail. Spam has become such a widespread phenomenon that trademark holder 
Hormel fi nally stopped objecting to the use of the term to refer to unsolicited email 
Hormel fi nally stopped objecting to the use of the term to refer to unsolicited email 
(Templeton, undated). 
(Templeton, undated). 
Spam also seems to be an extreme externality in the sense that the ratio of 
Spam also seems to be an extreme externality in the sense that the ratio of 
external costs to private benefi ts is quite high. We estimate that American fi rms and 
external costs to private benefi ts is quite high. We estimate that American fi rms and 
consumers experience costs of almost $20 billion annually due to spam. Our fi gure 
consumers experience costs of almost $20 billion annually due to spam. Our fi gure 
is more conservative than the $50 billion fi gure often cited by other authors, and we 
is more conservative than the $50 billion fi gure often cited by other authors, and we 
also note that the fi gure would be much higher if it were not for private investment 
also note that the fi gure would be much higher if it were not for private investment 
in anti-spam technology by fi rms, which we detail further on. On the private-benefi t 
in anti-spam technology by fi rms, which we detail further on. On the private-benefi t 
side, based on the work of crafty computer scientists who have infi ltrated and moni-
side, based on the work of crafty computer scientists who have infi ltrated and moni-
tored spammers' activity (Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 2011; Kanich 
tored spammers' activity (Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 2011; Kanich 
et al. 2008; Kanich et al. 2011; Caballero, Grier, Kreibich, and Paxson 2011), we 
et al. 2008; Kanich et al. 2011; Caballero, Grier, Kreibich, and Paxson 2011), we 
estimate that spammers and spam-advertised merchants collect gross worldwide 
estimate that spammers and spam-advertised merchants collect gross worldwide 
revenues on the order of $200 million per year. Thus, the "externality ratio" of 
revenues on the order of $200 million per year. Thus, the "externality ratio" of 
external costs to internal benefi ts for spam is around 100:1. 
external costs to internal benefi ts for spam is around 100:1. 
In this paper, we start by describing the history of the market for spam, 
In this paper, we start by describing the history of the market for spam, 
highlighting the strategic cat-and-mouse game between spammers and email 
highlighting the strategic cat-and-mouse game between spammers and email 
providers. We discuss how the market structure for spamming has evolved from 
providers. We discuss how the market structure for spamming has evolved from 
a diffuse network of independent spammers running their own online stores to 
a diffuse network of independent spammers running their own online stores to 
a highly specialized industry featuring a well-organized network of merchants, 
a highly specialized industry featuring a well-organized network of merchants, 
spam distributors (botnets), and spammers (or "advertisers"). Indeed, email 
spam distributors (botnets), and spammers (or "advertisers"). Indeed, email 
service provision has become more concentrated in part because the high fi xed 
service provision has become more concentrated in part because the high fi xed 
costs and economies of scale of fi ltering spam offer a signifi cant advantage to 
costs and economies of scale of fi ltering spam offer a signifi cant advantage to 
large service providers. We then put the spam market's externality ratio of 100 
large service providers. We then put the spam market's externality ratio of 100 
into context by comparing it to other activities with negative externalities, such as 
into context by comparing it to other activities with negative externalities, such as 
pollution associated with driving an automobile, for which we estimate a ratio of 
pollution associated with driving an automobile, for which we estimate a ratio of 
about 0.1, and for nonviolent property crime such as automobile theft, for which 
about 0.1, and for nonviolent property crime such as automobile theft, for which 
we estimate a ratio of 7-30. Lastly, we evaluate various policy proposals designed 
we estimate a ratio of 7-30. Lastly, we evaluate various policy proposals designed 
to solve the spam problem, cautioning that these proposals may err in assuming 
to solve the spam problem, cautioning that these proposals may err in assuming 
away the spammers' ability to adapt. 
away the spammers' ability to adapt. </p>

<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 89 </p>

<p>The History of Spam: Cat-and-Mouse Games </p>

<p>Email is sent via a "sender push" technology called Simple Mail Transfer Protocol 
Email is sent via a "sender push" technology called Simple Mail Transfer Protocol 
(SMTP). Other examples of sender-push transfer include postal mail, text messaging, 
(SMTP). Other examples of sender-push transfer include postal mail, text messaging, 
and voice mail. (In contrast, the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) used in web 
and voice mail. (In contrast, the Hypertext Transfer Protocol (HTTP) used in web 
browsing is "receiver pull"-nothing shows up in your web browser until you specify 
browsing is "receiver pull"-nothing shows up in your web browser until you specify 
a URL.) SMTP was designed in the early 1980s when the trust level across what was 
a URL.) SMTP was designed in the early 1980s when the trust level across what was 
then called the "Arpanet" was quite high. Accordingly, senders were not required 
then called the "Arpanet" was quite high. Accordingly, senders were not required 
to authenticate their emails. SMTP servers all over the world were programmed to 
to authenticate their emails. SMTP servers all over the world were programmed to 
cooperate in relaying messages. In many respects, SMTP replicates the "transfer 
cooperate in relaying messages. In many respects, SMTP replicates the "transfer 
protocol" of the U.S. Postal Service. Anyone in the United States can anonymously 
protocol" of the U.S. Postal Service. Anyone in the United States can anonymously 
drop a letter in a mailbox and, provided it has proper postage, have it delivered, 
drop a letter in a mailbox and, provided it has proper postage, have it delivered, 
without any requirement for the sender to provide an authentic return address. 
without any requirement for the sender to provide an authentic return address. 
Spammers fi rst developed technology to automate the sending of bulk email 
Spammers fi rst developed technology to automate the sending of bulk email 
in the mid 1990s by opportunistically tapping into mail relay servers and anony-
in the mid 1990s by opportunistically tapping into mail relay servers and anony-
mously fl oating a deluge of spam from phony domains (Goodman, Cormack, and 
mously fl oating a deluge of spam from phony domains (Goodman, Cormack, and 
Heckerman 2007). In 1994, the attorneys Canter and Siegel hired a programmer to 
Heckerman 2007). In 1994, the attorneys Canter and Siegel hired a programmer to 
automate a posting to every USENET newsgroup in existence, so that thousands of 
automate a posting to every USENET newsgroup in existence, so that thousands of 
discussion groups devoted to every topic from 
discussion groups devoted to every topic from Star Trek to board games were inun-
to board games were inun-
dated with advertisements for services to help immigrants apply for the green-card 
dated with advertisements for services to help immigrants apply for the green-card 
lottery. This software soon evolved into the fi rst automated bulk emailer (Zdziarski 
lottery. This software soon evolved into the fi rst automated bulk emailer (Zdziarski 
2005, pp. 10 -13). In 1995, the fi rst commercial "spamware," aptly titled Floodgate, 
2005, pp. 10 -13). In 1995, the fi rst commercial "spamware," aptly titled <rs type="software">Floodgate</rs>, 
appeared for sale at a price of $100. <rs type="software">Floodgate</rs> advertised its ability to harvest email 
appeared for sale at a price of $100. Floodgate advertised its ability to harvest email 
addresses from a variety of sources including newsgroups, CompuServe classifi ed 
addresses from a variety of sources including newsgroups, CompuServe classifi ed 
ads, AOL Member Directory, and other sources. Then, via the included companion 
ads, AOL Member Directory, and other sources. Then, via the included companion 
software Goldrush, it promised an ability to send out thousands of emails per 
software Goldrush, it promised an ability to send out thousands of emails per 
hour (Zdziarski 2005, p. 16; Everett-Church 1999). Such software, crude by today's 
hour (Zdziarski 2005, p. 16; Everett-Church 1999). Such software, crude by today's 
standards, enabled spammers to send email at a cost on the order of $0.0001 per 
standards, enabled spammers to send email at a cost on the order of $0.0001 per 
message. Since then, the spam market has been shaped by the technological cat-
message. Since then, the spam market has been shaped by the technological cat-
and-mouse game between spammers and email service providers. 
and-mouse game between spammers and email service providers. </p>

<p>Anti-spam Filtering Techniques 
As an early response to spam, Internet administrators developed authentica-
As an early response to spam, Internet administrators developed authentica-
tion protocols: where previously one only had to type a password to collect one's 
tion protocols: where previously one only had to type a password to collect one's 
incoming mail, now most had to authenticate themselves by providing a password to 
incoming mail, now most had to authenticate themselves by providing a password to 
send outgoing mail. To prevent domain spoofi ng-using the domain of a well-known 
send outgoing mail. To prevent domain spoofi ng-using the domain of a well-known 
company to make an email seem more legitimate -domain authentication routines 
company to make an email seem more legitimate -domain authentication routines 
check that the IP address listed in the Domain Name System matches the sending 
check that the IP address listed in the Domain Name System matches the sending 
IP. However, many SMTP servers remained unauthenticated for a long time, and the 
IP. However, many SMTP servers remained unauthenticated for a long time, and the 
default mail delivery protocol is still to deliver email from any sending IP address. 
default mail delivery protocol is still to deliver email from any sending IP address. 
After authentication, the arsenal of fi ltering technologies consists of machine 
After authentication, the arsenal of fi ltering technologies consists of machine 
learning, crowdsourcing, and IP blacklisting. Such screening devices detect suspected 
learning, crowdsourcing, and IP blacklisting. Such screening devices detect suspected 
spam messages and either reject them from being delivered, or send them to a junk-
spam messages and either reject them from being delivered, or send them to a junk-
mail folder. 
mail folder. </p>



<p>The machine-learning approach dates from the late 1990s (Sahami, Dumais, 
The machine-learning approach dates from the late 1990s (Sahami, Dumais, 
Heckerman, and Horvitz 1998; Androutsopoulos, Koutsias, Chandrinos, Paliouras, 
Heckerman, and Horvitz 1998; Androutsopoulos, Koutsias, Chandrinos, Paliouras, 
and Spyropoulos 2000). A typical machine-learning implementation uses "ground 
and Spyropoulos 2000). A typical machine-learning implementation uses "ground 
truth" data on a subset of observations to learn rules to classify the remaining data. 
truth" data on a subset of observations to learn rules to classify the remaining data. 
With spam, the ground truth is given by human-labeled examples of spam versus 
With spam, the ground truth is given by human-labeled examples of spam versus 
non-spam emails and the algorithm is trained to recognize features of the email 
non-spam emails and the algorithm is trained to recognize features of the email 
that predict whether it is spam. For example, one can have the classifi er examine 
that predict whether it is spam. For example, one can have the classifi er examine 
the predictive power of all words and word pairs in the subject lines of the emails, 
the predictive power of all words and word pairs in the subject lines of the emails, 
which might lead to dummy variables for the presence of "Viagra," "Nigeria," and 
which might lead to dummy variables for the presence of "Viagra," "Nigeria," and 
"Free Money" being included as key predictors. Other examples of heavily weighted 
"Free Money" being included as key predictors. Other examples of heavily weighted 
features include unusual punctuation common to spam, such as "!!!", and nouns 
features include unusual punctuation common to spam, such as "!!!", and nouns 
associated with spam-advertised products, such as "Rolex". Every URL contained 
associated with spam-advertised products, such as "Rolex". Every URL contained 
in a message could also be treated as a possible predictor as spam emails nearly 
in a message could also be treated as a possible predictor as spam emails nearly 
always include the URL of the website to place orders for the advertised product. 
always include the URL of the website to place orders for the advertised product. 
Any machine-learned fi lter can have false positives -that is, legitimate mail that is 
Any machine-learned fi lter can have false positives -that is, legitimate mail that is 
fi ltered to the junk folder (for instance, spam fi lters might make it hard to converse 
fi ltered to the junk folder (for instance, spam fi lters might make it hard to converse 
legitimately about bank transfers in Africa). 
legitimately about bank transfers in Africa). 
Spammers responded with creative misspellings designed to avoid the fi lters, 
Spammers responded with creative misspellings designed to avoid the fi lters, 
such as "V1agra," created many unique URLs all mapping to the same order form, 
such as "V1agra," created many unique URLs all mapping to the same order form, 
and included attachments of graphical images of text messages, which became 
and included attachments of graphical images of text messages, which became 
popular with spammers when they realized that text-based classifi ers could not fi nd 
popular with spammers when they realized that text-based classifi ers could not fi nd 
the text in the form of a GIF or JPEG image. Spammers also include irrelevant text 
the text in the form of a GIF or JPEG image. Spammers also include irrelevant text 
passages, such as excerpts of news stories that are common in legitimate conver-
passages, such as excerpts of news stories that are common in legitimate conver-
sations, or create random permutations of words from one email to the next to 
sations, or create random permutations of words from one email to the next to 
throw classifi ers off track. Of course, over time the anti-spam classifi ers continued 
throw classifi ers off track. Of course, over time the anti-spam classifi ers continued 
to improve and adapt, too. Goodman, Cormack, and Heckerman (2007) present a 
to improve and adapt, too. Goodman, Cormack, and Heckerman (2007) present a 
nice introduction to such anti-spam technology for nonexperts. 
nice introduction to such anti-spam technology for nonexperts. 
Crowdsourcing represents a way to collect additional data to improve the 
Crowdsourcing represents a way to collect additional data to improve the 
predictive power of machine-learning models. Large webmail providers such as 
predictive power of machine-learning models. Large webmail providers such as 
Yahoo! Mail collect data when users press the "mark as spam" button to move email 
Yahoo! Mail collect data when users press the "mark as spam" button to move email 
from the inbox to the junk mail folder. Data from such marked spam can be used, as 
from the inbox to the junk mail folder. Data from such marked spam can be used, as 
soon as that same day, to retrain the spam classifi er. However, most users just delete 
soon as that same day, to retrain the spam classifi er. However, most users just delete 
irrelevant emails rather than marking them as spam. We took a random sample of 
irrelevant emails rather than marking them as spam. We took a random sample of 
six months of mail activity for 1.3 million active Yahoo! Mail users and found that 
six months of mail activity for 1.3 million active Yahoo! Mail users and found that 
only 6 percent of users ever marked any email as spam, but the vast majority deleted 
only 6 percent of users ever marked any email as spam, but the vast majority deleted 
messages without reading them. 
messages without reading them. 
Spammers have developed a strategic response to the spam voting system. In 
Spammers have developed a strategic response to the spam voting system. In 
addition to the "spam" button in the inbox, webmail services also provide a "not 
addition to the "spam" button in the inbox, webmail services also provide a "not 
spam" button to mark false-positive messages in the junk mail folder. In four months 
spam" button to mark false-positive messages in the junk mail folder. In four months 
of 2009 Yahoo! Mail data, our Yahoo! colleagues found that (suspiciously) 63 percent 
of 2009 Yahoo! Mail data, our Yahoo! colleagues found that (suspiciously) 63 percent 
of all "not spam" votes were cast by users who never cast a single "spam" vote. After 
of all "not spam" votes were cast by users who never cast a single "spam" vote. After 
examining additional data on these accounts, such as IP address, position in the 
examining additional data on these accounts, such as IP address, position in the 
network of users, and repeatedly casting not-spam votes on a variety of emails that 
network of users, and repeatedly casting not-spam votes on a variety of emails that 
were receiving multiple "spam" votes from legitimate users, the authors concluded 
were receiving multiple "spam" votes from legitimate users, the authors concluded </p>

<p>The Economics of Spam 91 </p>

<p>that the vast majority of these accounts were created by spammers to cast strategic 
that the vast majority of these accounts were created by spammers to cast strategic 
votes in order to help their campaigns beat the spam fi lters (Cook, Hartnett, 
votes in order to help their campaigns beat the spam fi lters (Cook, Hartnett, 
Manderson, and Scanlan 2006; Ramachandran, Dasgupta, Feamster, and Wein-
Manderson, and Scanlan 2006; Ramachandran, Dasgupta, Feamster, and Wein-
berger 2011). The researchers discovered 1.1 million of these sleeper accounts, and 
berger 2011). The researchers discovered 1.1 million of these sleeper accounts, and 
Yahoo! inserted a detection algorithm to mitigate the effects of this strategic voting. 
Yahoo! inserted a detection algorithm to mitigate the effects of this strategic voting. 
The single most effective weapon in the spam-blocking arsenal turns out to 
The single most effective weapon in the spam-blocking arsenal turns out to 
be blacklisting an email server (Cook, Hartnett, Manderson, and Scanlan 2006; 
be blacklisting an email server (Cook, Hartnett, Manderson, and Scanlan 2006; 
Ramachandran, Feamster, and Vempala 2007). In 2011, 80 percent of all emails 
Ramachandran, Feamster, and Vempala 2007). In 2011, 80 percent of all emails 
received by Yahoo! Mail were rejected by their servers through IP blacklisting. Fortu-
received by Yahoo! Mail were rejected by their servers through IP blacklisting. Fortu-
nately, just as the postmark from the sending post offi ce limits the ability to spoof 
nately, just as the postmark from the sending post offi ce limits the ability to spoof 
one's return address, Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) makes it impossible to 
one's return address, Transmission Control Protocol (TCP) makes it impossible to 
spoof the IP address of the mail server from which the message was sent. Therefore, 
spoof the IP address of the mail server from which the message was sent. Therefore, 
if email administrators noticed that their users were receiving tremendous amounts 
if email administrators noticed that their users were receiving tremendous amounts 
of mail from one server, they could "blacklist" such a server. Sharing blacklist infor-
of mail from one server, they could "blacklist" such a server. Sharing blacklist infor-
mation enables multiple organizations to shut down spam activity more quickly. 
mation enables multiple organizations to shut down spam activity more quickly. 
For example, the Spamhaus Block List, founded in 1998 by Steve Linford, now 
For example, the Spamhaus Block List, founded in 1998 by Steve Linford, now 
protects nearly 1.8 billion email inboxes from spam ( 
protects nearly 1.8 billion email inboxes from spam (〈 〈http://www.spamhaus.org http://www.spamhaus.org 
/organization/index.lasso /organization/index.lasso⟩ ⟩, accessed February 9, 2012). 
, accessed February 9, 2012). 
An unintended side effect of blacklisting occurs when a single user starts 
An unintended side effect of blacklisting occurs when a single user starts 
sending spam and causes their email server to be blacklisted. At that point, everyone 
sending spam and causes their email server to be blacklisted. At that point, everyone 
else using the same email server will suddenly fi nd their outbound emails being 
else using the same email server will suddenly fi nd their outbound emails being 
blocked. This situation could arise within any large organization, like a college, a 
blocked. This situation could arise within any large organization, like a college, a 
corporation, or a shared Internet service provider (ISP). Of course, information 
corporation, or a shared Internet service provider (ISP). Of course, information 
technology professionals can then sort out the problem, and organizations such 
technology professionals can then sort out the problem, and organizations such 
as Spamhaus strive to act quickly in unblocking any email server who was falsely 
as Spamhaus strive to act quickly in unblocking any email server who was falsely 
accused or who corrects the problem with its users, but blacklists still routinely cause 
accused or who corrects the problem with its users, but blacklists still routinely cause 
reliability problems for users trying to send email. 
reliability problems for users trying to send email. 
The larger email services such as Yahoo! Mail, Microsoft Hotmail, and Google 
The larger email services such as Yahoo! Mail, Microsoft Hotmail, and Google 
Gmail have large, dedicated anti-spam and customer support teams. The high fi xed 
Gmail have large, dedicated anti-spam and customer support teams. The high fi xed 
costs of anti-spam technologies and benefi ts of crowdsourced data have made it 
costs of anti-spam technologies and benefi ts of crowdsourced data have made it 
diffi cult for small email providers to compete, which has contributed to signifi cant 
diffi cult for small email providers to compete, which has contributed to signifi cant 
increases in concentration in email provision since the mid 1990s. We obtained 
increases in concentration in email provision since the mid 1990s. We obtained 
market share data (from comScope) for the top 50 largest consumer web-based email 
market share data (from comScope) for the top 50 largest consumer web-based email 
services (including home Internet service providers) for the period 2006 -2012. The 
services (including home Internet service providers) for the period 2006 -2012. The 
data show that webmail provision has become increasingly concentrated in the "Big 
data show that webmail provision has become increasingly concentrated in the "Big 
Three" of Hotmail, Yahoo! Mail, and Gmail. The three-fi rm concentration ratio in 
Three" of Hotmail, Yahoo! Mail, and Gmail. The three-fi rm concentration ratio in 
this market has increased from 55 percent to nearly 85 percent over the last six years; 
this market has increased from 55 percent to nearly 85 percent over the last six years; 
we believe that spam is a signifi cant contributor to this increase in concentration. 
we believe that spam is a signifi cant contributor to this increase in concentration. </p>

<p>Botnets 
Blacklists gradually made it impossible for spammers to use their own servers 
Blacklists gradually made it impossible for spammers to use their own servers 
(or others' open relay servers) with fi xed IP addresses. Spammers responded with a 
(or others' open relay servers) with fi xed IP addresses. Spammers responded with a 
"Whack-a-Mole" strategy, popping up with a new computer IP address every time the 
"Whack-a-Mole" strategy, popping up with a new computer IP address every time the 
old one got shut down. This strategy was observed and named as early as 1996, and 
old one got shut down. This strategy was observed and named as early as 1996, and </p>



<p>eventually became considerably cheaper with another major innovation in spam: 
eventually became considerably cheaper with another major innovation in spam: 
the botnet. 
the botnet. 
A botnet is a network of "zombie" computers infected by a piece of malicious 
A botnet is a network of "zombie" computers infected by a piece of malicious 
software (or "malware") designed to enslave them to a master computer. The 
software (or "malware") designed to enslave them to a master computer. The 
malware gets installed in a variety of ways, such as when a user clicks on an ad 
malware gets installed in a variety of ways, such as when a user clicks on an ad 
promising "free ringtones." The infected computers are organized in a militaristic 
promising "free ringtones." The infected computers are organized in a militaristic 
hierarchy, where early zombies try to infect additional downstream computers and 
hierarchy, where early zombies try to infect additional downstream computers and 
become middle managers who transmit commands from the central "command 
become middle managers who transmit commands from the central "command 
and control" servers down to the frontline computers ( John, Moshchuk, Gribble, 
and control" servers down to the frontline computers ( John, Moshchuk, Gribble, 
and Krishnamurthy 2009; Caballero, Poosankam, Kreibich, and Song 2009; Cho, 
and Krishnamurthy 2009; Caballero, Poosankam, Kreibich, and Song 2009; Cho, 
Caballero, Grier, Paxson, and Song 2010). 
Caballero, Grier, Paxson, and Song 2010). 
The fi rst spamming botnets appeared in 2003. Static blacklists are power-
The fi rst spamming botnets appeared in 2003. Static blacklists are power-
less against botnets. In a botnet, spam emails originate from tens of thousands 
less against botnets. In a botnet, spam emails originate from tens of thousands 
of IP addresses that are constantly changing because most individual consumers 
of IP addresses that are constantly changing because most individual consumers 
have their IP addresses dynamically allocated by Dynamic Host Control Protocol 
have their IP addresses dynamically allocated by Dynamic Host Control Protocol 
(DHCP). Dynamic blacklisting approaches have since been developed; Stone-Gross, 
(DHCP). Dynamic blacklisting approaches have since been developed; Stone-Gross, 
Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna (2011) document that 90 percent of zombie computers 
Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna (2011) document that 90 percent of zombie computers 
are blacklisted before the end of each day. However, if the cable company assigns 
are blacklisted before the end of each day. However, if the cable company assigns 
a zombie computer a new IP address each day, that computer gets a fresh start and 
a zombie computer a new IP address each day, that computer gets a fresh start and 
can once again successfully send out spam. 
can once again successfully send out spam. 
In response to botnets, many Internet service providers, such as Comcast, 
In response to botnets, many Internet service providers, such as Comcast, 
began to prevent their users' computers from operating as send-mail servers. This 
began to prevent their users' computers from operating as send-mail servers. This 
meant that individuals and small businesses could no longer run their own mail 
meant that individuals and small businesses could no longer run their own mail 
servers, as in the original, decentralized vision of the Internet, and now had to rely 
servers, as in the original, decentralized vision of the Internet, and now had to rely 
on larger commercial email vendors. 
on larger commercial email vendors. 
A second generation of botnets makes use of accounts at large commercial email 
A second generation of botnets makes use of accounts at large commercial email 
providers. For example, a zombie could be programmed to sign up for hundreds 
providers. For example, a zombie could be programmed to sign up for hundreds 
of thousands of free email accounts at Gmail, and then send spam email through 
of thousands of free email accounts at Gmail, and then send spam email through 
these accounts. Email providers have implemented sending thresholds designed to 
these accounts. Email providers have implemented sending thresholds designed to 
detect and prevent this sort of spamming. If a user exceeds these limits, the system 
detect and prevent this sort of spamming. If a user exceeds these limits, the system 
may refuse to send out the email, or it may ask the user to solve a CAPTCHA (as 
may refuse to send out the email, or it may ask the user to solve a CAPTCHA (as 
discussed in the next subsection). Such rules cut down on outbound spam, but 
discussed in the next subsection). Such rules cut down on outbound spam, but 
also impose negative side effects on users who happen to be high-volume senders 
also impose negative side effects on users who happen to be high-volume senders 
of legitimate email. In 2011, Yahoo! Mail experienced an average of 2.5 million 
of legitimate email. In 2011, Yahoo! Mail experienced an average of 2.5 million 
sign-ups for new accounts each day. The anti-spam team deactivated 25 percent of 
sign-ups for new accounts each day. The anti-spam team deactivated 25 percent of 
these immediately, because of clearly suspicious patterns in account creation (such 
these immediately, because of clearly suspicious patterns in account creation (such 
as sequentially signing up account names JohnExample1, JohnExample2, . . .) and 
as sequentially signing up account names JohnExample1, JohnExample2, . . .) and 
deactivated another 25 percent of these accounts within a week of activation due to 
deactivated another 25 percent of these accounts within a week of activation due to 
suspicious outbound email activity. 
suspicious outbound email activity. 
In 2009, six botnets accounted for over 90 percent of botnet spam (Symantec 
In 2009, six botnets accounted for over 90 percent of botnet spam (Symantec 
2010; John, Moshchuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009). The largest botnet on 
2010; John, Moshchuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009). The largest botnet on 
record, known as Rustock, infected over a million computers and had the capacity 
record, known as Rustock, infected over a million computers and had the capacity 
to send 30 billion spam emails per day before it was taken down in March 2011. 
to send 30 billion spam emails per day before it was taken down in March 2011. 
Microsoft, Pfi zer, FireEye network security, and security experts at the University 
Microsoft, Pfi zer, FireEye network security, and security experts at the University </p>

<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 93 </p>

<p>of Washington collaborated to reverse engineer the Rustock software to determine 
of Washington collaborated to reverse engineer the Rustock software to determine 
the location of the command servers. They then obtained orders from federal 
the location of the command servers. They then obtained orders from federal 
courts in the United States and the Netherlands allowing them to seize Rustock's 
courts in the United States and the Netherlands allowing them to seize Rustock's 
command-and-control computers in a number of different geographic locations. 
command-and-control computers in a number of different geographic locations. 
(Microsoft fi nancially supported the operation presumably because Rustock sent 
(Microsoft fi nancially supported the operation presumably because Rustock sent 
its emails through Windows Live Hotmail accounts, while Pfi zer participated 
its emails through Windows Live Hotmail accounts, while Pfi zer participated 
because a Rustock spam often advertised counterfeit versions of Pfi zer's patent-
because a Rustock spam often advertised counterfeit versions of Pfi zer's patent-
protected Viagra.) If the servers had been located in less-friendly countries, it is 
protected Viagra.) If the servers had been located in less-friendly countries, it is 
not clear whether the takedown could have been successful. The takedown of this 
not clear whether the takedown could have been successful. The takedown of this 
single botnet coincided with a one-third reduction in global email spam-and 
single botnet coincided with a one-third reduction in global email spam-and 
hence a one-quarter reduction in global email traffi c (Thonnard and Dacier 2011; 
hence a one-quarter reduction in global email traffi c (Thonnard and Dacier 2011; 
Microsoft 2011). Thus, the efforts of these private fi rms produced a remarkably 
Microsoft 2011). Thus, the efforts of these private fi rms produced a remarkably 
large large positive externality. externality. </p>

<p>CAPTCHA: Screening Humans from Bots 
To avoid spammers setting up many commercial email accounts, services 
To avoid spammers setting up many commercial email accounts, services 
like Yahoo! Mail have implemented a screening device called a CAPTCHA, which 
like Yahoo! Mail have implemented a screening device called a CAPTCHA, which 
is an acronym for "Completely Automated Public Turing test to tell Computers 
is an acronym for "Completely Automated Public Turing test to tell Computers 
and Humans Apart." This test will be familiar to most readers as a set of twisty, 
and Humans Apart." This test will be familiar to most readers as a set of twisty, 
distorted text characters. Spammers turned to visual-recognition software to break 
distorted text characters. Spammers turned to visual-recognition software to break 
CAPTCHAs, and in response email providers have created progressively more 
CAPTCHAs, and in response email providers have created progressively more 
diffi cult CAPTCHAS, to the point where many legitimate human users struggle to 
diffi cult CAPTCHAS, to the point where many legitimate human users struggle to 
solve them. 
solve them. 
However, the big breakthrough in CAPTCHA breaking arose when spammers 
However, the big breakthrough in CAPTCHA breaking arose when spammers 
fi gured out how to employ human labor to break CAPTCHAs for them. In this 
fi gured out how to employ human labor to break CAPTCHAs for them. In this 
idea's fi rst incarnation, a spammer would set up a pornography site, offering to 
idea's fi rst incarnation, a spammer would set up a pornography site, offering to 
display a free photo to any user who could successfully type in the text characters 
display a free photo to any user who could successfully type in the text characters 
in a CAPTCHA image. In the background, their software had applied for a mail 
in a CAPTCHA image. In the background, their software had applied for a mail 
account at a site like Hotmail, received a CAPTCHA image, and relayed it to the 
account at a site like Hotmail, received a CAPTCHA image, and relayed it to the 
porn site; they would obtain text from a user interested in free porn and relay this 
porn site; they would obtain text from a user interested in free porn and relay this 
back to the Hotmail site (Kotadia 2004). 
back to the Hotmail site (Kotadia 2004). 
More formal labor markets subsequently developed for CAPTCHA breaking 
More formal labor markets subsequently developed for CAPTCHA breaking 
(Motoyama, Levchenko, Kanich, McCoy, Volker, and Savage 2010). A market maker 
(Motoyama, Levchenko, Kanich, McCoy, Volker, and Savage 2010). A market maker 
typically operates one website for interacting with buyers of CAPTCHA-breaking 
typically operates one website for interacting with buyers of CAPTCHA-breaking 
services, and another for interacting with workers who sell their labor. For example, 
services, and another for interacting with workers who sell their labor. For example, 
one can purchase CAPTCHA-breaking services from the DeCaptcher website, which 
one can purchase CAPTCHA-breaking services from the DeCaptcher website, which 
transmits each CAPTCHA to a worker at the PixProfi t website for breaking, then 
transmits each CAPTCHA to a worker at the PixProfi t website for breaking, then 
back to the customer at DeCaptcher. The customer may use a separate piece of soft-
back to the customer at DeCaptcher. The customer may use a separate piece of soft-
ware (such as GYCAutomator, which specializes in Gmail, Yahoo! Mail, and Craigslist 
ware (such as GYCAutomator, which specializes in Gmail, Yahoo! Mail, and Craigslist 
CAPTCHAs) to transmit the CAPTCHA and its solution. The entire process takes 
CAPTCHAs) to transmit the CAPTCHA and its solution. The entire process takes 
less than 30 seconds. The market wage advertised for CAPTCHA-breaking laborers 
less than 30 seconds. The market wage advertised for CAPTCHA-breaking laborers 
declined from nearly $10 per thousand CAPTCHAs in 2007 to $1 per thousand in 
declined from nearly $10 per thousand CAPTCHAs in 2007 to $1 per thousand in 
2009. These labor markets started with Eastern European labor and then moved to 
2009. These labor markets started with Eastern European labor and then moved to 
locations with lower wages: India, China, and Southeast Asia. 
locations with lower wages: India, China, and Southeast Asia. </p>



<p>In February 2012, Kotalibablo.com was advertising to workers that they could 
In February 2012, Kotalibablo.com was advertising to workers that they could 
earn wages starting at $0.35 per thousand. The same company operates the buyer-
earn wages starting at $0.35 per thousand. The same company operates the buyer-
facing website Antigate.com, which at that time advertised a price of $0.70 per 
facing website Antigate.com, which at that time advertised a price of $0.70 per 
thousand to customers wanting to break CAPTCHAs. Motoyama, Levchenko, 
thousand to customers wanting to break CAPTCHAs. Motoyama, Levchenko, 
Kanich, McCoy, Voelker, and Savage (2010) measured typical response times of 
Kanich, McCoy, Voelker, and Savage (2010) measured typical response times of 
around 10 -15 seconds per CAPTCHA, with accuracy rates around 90 percent. 
around 10 -15 seconds per CAPTCHA, with accuracy rates around 90 percent. 
(During one peak-load period, they experimentally measured a labor supply elas-
(During one peak-load period, they experimentally measured a labor supply elas-
ticity of approximately one: increasing their bid amount from $2 per thousand 
ticity of approximately one: increasing their bid amount from $2 per thousand 
to $5 per thousand increased quantity solved from 8 to 18 per second.) Several 
to $5 per thousand increased quantity solved from 8 to 18 per second.) Several 
websites can provide more than ten CAPTCHAs per second, putting total industry 
websites can provide more than ten CAPTCHAs per second, putting total industry 
capacity (at a price of $1 per thousand) at over a million broken CAPTCHAs per 
capacity (at a price of $1 per thousand) at over a million broken CAPTCHAs per 
day. These services market themselves as "Image to Text" providers and operate in 
day. These services market themselves as "Image to Text" providers and operate in 
the light of day -as of 2012 U.S. law, there does not appear to be anything illegal 
the light of day -as of 2012 U.S. law, there does not appear to be anything illegal 
about the services they offer. 
about the services they offer. 
CAPTCHAs are also used to authenticate senders in what are known as 
CAPTCHAs are also used to authenticate senders in what are known as 
"challenge-response systems." Such a service will intercept messages from anyone 
"challenge-response systems." Such a service will intercept messages from anyone 
not in a preset contact list, sending an autoreply before allowing the message to be 
not in a preset contact list, sending an autoreply before allowing the message to be 
delivered. The autoreply requires that the sender solve a CAPTCHA, thus authenti-
delivered. The autoreply requires that the sender solve a CAPTCHA, thus authenti-
cating the sender as human. Such systems have been available for at least seven years, 
cating the sender as human. Such systems have been available for at least seven years, 
but the market has for the most part rejected this technology, and with good reasons 
but the market has for the most part rejected this technology, and with good reasons 
(Isacenkova and Balzarotti 2011). First, the autoreply "challenge" itself often gets 
(Isacenkova and Balzarotti 2011). First, the autoreply "challenge" itself often gets 
caught in a spam fi lter because it contains stock text and a link, and is sent frequently 
caught in a spam fi lter because it contains stock text and a link, and is sent frequently 
from the same sender-which are all strong signals in machine-learned spam fi lters. 
from the same sender-which are all strong signals in machine-learned spam fi lters. 
Second, it requires that receivers maintain a continually updated contact list. Third, 
Second, it requires that receivers maintain a continually updated contact list. Third, 
spammers can use the challenge-response system to spoof messages from unsus-
spammers can use the challenge-response system to spoof messages from unsus-
pecting "senders," who receive the spammers' message as "backscatter spam" when 
pecting "senders," who receive the spammers' message as "backscatter spam" when 
they fail the challenge and get bounced to the apparent sender. 
they fail the challenge and get bounced to the apparent sender. </p>

<p>Hijacking Accounts from Legitimate Users 
Another recent strategy of botnets has been to hijack existing email accounts 
Another recent strategy of botnets has been to hijack existing email accounts 
from legitimate users. (These same techniques can be used for even more nefarious 
from legitimate users. (These same techniques can be used for even more nefarious 
purposes, such as hijacking a bank account; for more details about this form of 
purposes, such as hijacking a bank account; for more details about this form of 
online crime, we refer readers to Moore, Clayton, and Anderson 2009, in this 
online crime, we refer readers to Moore, Clayton, and Anderson 2009, in this 
journal.) For example, "phishing" occurs when the culprit sends an email posing as 
journal.) For example, "phishing" occurs when the culprit sends an email posing as 
a legitimate institution-say, "Hotmail user account services," often including the 
a legitimate institution-say, "Hotmail user account services," often including the 
actual logo of the institution being spoofed-and asks the victim to visit a website to 
actual logo of the institution being spoofed-and asks the victim to visit a website to 
"verify your account password." In the practice of "keylogging," a type of malware 
"verify your account password." In the practice of "keylogging," a type of malware 
records keystrokes and transmits information (especially suspected passwords) to 
records keystrokes and transmits information (especially suspected passwords) to 
the spammer. The practice of "packet sniffi ng" takes advantage of small companies 
the spammer. The practice of "packet sniffi ng" takes advantage of small companies 
and colleges who still transmit user passwords over the Internet in unencrypted text, 
and colleges who still transmit user passwords over the Internet in unencrypted text, 
and so a spammer "listening" at a login page can not only hijack that account, but 
and so a spammer "listening" at a login page can not only hijack that account, but 
also any other accounts (such as Yahoo! Mail) for which the user has conveniently 
also any other accounts (such as Yahoo! Mail) for which the user has conveniently 
chosen the exact same password. This technique was recently used to obtain access 
chosen the exact same password. This technique was recently used to obtain access 
to 93,000 accounts on the Sony Playstation Network (Gross 2011). 
to 93,000 accounts on the Sony Playstation Network (Gross 2011). </p>

<p>The Economics of Spam 95 </p>

<p>In 2005, an industry consortium established a technology standard called 
In 2005, an industry consortium established a technology standard called 
Domain Keys Identifi ed Mail (DKIM) as a new weapon in the war against both 
Domain Keys Identifi ed Mail (DKIM) as a new weapon in the war against both 
spamming and phishing. Now adopted by a number of fi rms, including Yahoo! 
spamming and phishing. Now adopted by a number of fi rms, including Yahoo! 
Mail, Gmail, PayPal, and eBay, this standard creates a digital signature that email 
Mail, Gmail, PayPal, and eBay, this standard creates a digital signature that email 
senders can adopt. For example, if a phisher pretends to be PayPal asking a user to 
senders can adopt. For example, if a phisher pretends to be PayPal asking a user to 
verify their account password, Yahoo! Mail will immediately notice that the message 
verify their account password, Yahoo! Mail will immediately notice that the message 
does not have the correct digital signature (based on public-key encryption) and 
does not have the correct digital signature (based on public-key encryption) and 
will therefore reject the forged email without delivering it. Unfortunately, spam-
will therefore reject the forged email without delivering it. Unfortunately, spam-
mers have already responded to this strategy by trying to hijack the account of a 
mers have already responded to this strategy by trying to hijack the account of a 
corporate user that has been "whitelisted" via DKIM. In March 2011, a number of 
corporate user that has been "whitelisted" via DKIM. In March 2011, a number of 
accounts became compromised at Epsilon, an email service provider who handles 
accounts became compromised at Epsilon, an email service provider who handles 
the sending of legitimate bulk email for a number of corporate clients, such as TiVo, 
the sending of legitimate bulk email for a number of corporate clients, such as TiVo, 
Capital One, U.S. Bank, and the Kroger grocery chain (Moyer 2011). 
Capital One, U.S. Bank, and the Kroger grocery chain (Moyer 2011). 
On the whole, anti-spam efforts at large companies have mitigated the nuisance 
On the whole, anti-spam efforts at large companies have mitigated the nuisance 
of spam to customers. However, the cat-and-mouse moves seem certain to continue. 
of spam to customers. However, the cat-and-mouse moves seem certain to continue. </p>

<p>Spammers and the Field of Dreams 
From a spammer's perspective, any online platform delivering eyeballs is 
From a spammer's perspective, any online platform delivering eyeballs is 
a natural target. In other words, as Kevin Costner's character in 
a natural target. In other words, as Kevin Costner's character in Field of Dreams 
famously heard, "If you build it, they will come." 
famously heard, "If you build it, they will come." 
Spam is prevalent on social bookmarking sites 
Spam is prevalent on social bookmarking sites 1 1 (Krause, Schmitz, Hotho, 
(Krause, Schmitz, Hotho, 
and Stumme 2008) and online classifi eds (Tran, Hornbeck, Ha-Thuc, Cremer, and 
and Stumme 2008) and online classifi eds (Tran, Hornbeck, Ha-Thuc, Cremer, and 
Srinivasan 2011). On Twitter, spam takes the form of inserting a spammy link to 
Srinivasan 2011). On Twitter, spam takes the form of inserting a spammy link to 
an ongoing conversation between users ( Yardi, Romero, Schoenebeck, and boyd 
an ongoing conversation between users ( Yardi, Romero, Schoenebeck, and boyd 
2009), using Twitter's hashtag feature. Twitter spam also occurs when an ostensible 
2009), using Twitter's hashtag feature. Twitter spam also occurs when an ostensible 
fan of a celebrity writes a message including the characters "@LadyGaga," in hopes 
fan of a celebrity writes a message including the characters "@LadyGaga," in hopes 
of getting it exposed to her fans. Facebook suffers relatively less from spam because 
of getting it exposed to her fans. Facebook suffers relatively less from spam because 
of the way it requires users to verify connections with each other, but spammers 
of the way it requires users to verify connections with each other, but spammers 
continue to invent new techniques, from malicious apps to friend requests from 
continue to invent new techniques, from malicious apps to friend requests from 
fi ctitious identities, that keep Facebook's anti-spam team quite busy (Warren 2011; 
fi ctitious identities, that keep Facebook's anti-spam team quite busy (Warren 2011; 
Cohen 2012; Ghiossi 2010). Text-messaging spam has become a serious problem in 
Cohen 2012; Ghiossi 2010). Text-messaging spam has become a serious problem in 
certain countries: one source estimated that 30 percent of text messages in China are 
certain countries: one source estimated that 30 percent of text messages in China are 
now spam. However, in the United States the relatively high price of SMS messaging 
now spam. However, in the United States the relatively high price of SMS messaging 
(often $0.10 per message, orders of magnitude higher than in China) has kept text 
(often $0.10 per message, orders of magnitude higher than in China) has kept text 
message spam rates below 1 percent (Gómez Hidalgo, Bringas, Sánz, and García 
message spam rates below 1 percent (Gómez Hidalgo, Bringas, Sánz, and García 
2006). Text spam is aggressively fi ltered by cell phone providers, especially for text 
2006). Text spam is aggressively fi ltered by cell phone providers, especially for text 
messages from a computer to a phone through a webmail client (Almeida, Gómez, 
messages from a computer to a phone through a webmail client (Almeida, Gómez, 
and Yamakami 2011). Providers of online instant message software also struggle to 
and Yamakami 2011). Providers of online instant message software also struggle to 
block spam. 
block spam. 
Next to email spam, the most prominent form of spam is known as "web spam" 
Next to email spam, the most prominent form of spam is known as "web spam" 
or "black-hat search-engine optimization." A typical web-spam implementation mines 
or "black-hat search-engine optimization." A typical web-spam implementation mines </p>

<p>1 Social bookmarking, also known as "tagging," is a way to share webpages with a community of users. </p>



<p>news feeds for headlines and automatically creates pages with snippets of popular 
news feeds for headlines and automatically creates pages with snippets of popular 
stories. The article snippet is used under a "fair use" exception to copyright law, 
stories. The article snippet is used under a "fair use" exception to copyright law, 
and the remainder of the page is typically saturated with advertisements. Such web 
and the remainder of the page is typically saturated with advertisements. Such web 
spam can deceive search engines into featuring these ad-laden pages prominently 
spam can deceive search engines into featuring these ad-laden pages prominently 
in search results about popular topics, thereby annoying users, but it is not illegal. It 
in search results about popular topics, thereby annoying users, but it is not illegal. It 
differs fundamentally from all the other forms of spam discussed in this paper in that 
differs fundamentally from all the other forms of spam discussed in this paper in that 
it is not sender-push: One only sees a web spam page if one voluntarily clicks. Web 
it is not sender-push: One only sees a web spam page if one voluntarily clicks. Web 
spam has been combated through machine learning about the credibility of poten-
spam has been combated through machine learning about the credibility of poten-
tial links and the downgrading of low-credibility links in search results (Caverlee 
tial links and the downgrading of low-credibility links in search results (Caverlee 
and Liu 2007; Zhou, Burges, and Tao 2007; see also Ntoulas, Najork, Manasse, and 
and Liu 2007; Zhou, Burges, and Tao 2007; see also Ntoulas, Najork, Manasse, and 
Fetterly 2006, and Castillo, Donato, Gionis, Murdock, and Silvestri 2007). 
Fetterly 2006, and Castillo, Donato, Gionis, Murdock, and Silvestri 2007). </p>

<p>Market Structure </p>

<p>Most spam is illegal under the United States CAN-SPAM Act of 2003, which 
Most spam is illegal under the United States CAN-SPAM Act of 2003, which 
requires unsolicited emails to have valid return addresses and opt-out provisions. 
requires unsolicited emails to have valid return addresses and opt-out provisions. 
While many people use "spam" to refer to the (sometimes annoyingly frequent) 
While many people use "spam" to refer to the (sometimes annoyingly frequent) 
messages they receive from businesses with which they have previously transacted, 
messages they receive from businesses with which they have previously transacted, 
for the purposes of this paper we defi ne spam to be messages from economic agents 
for the purposes of this paper we defi ne spam to be messages from economic agents 
who do not have a previous relationship with the customer and who do not offer 
who do not have a previous relationship with the customer and who do not offer 
opt-out provisions. 
opt-out provisions. 
The spam market does have some similarities to the market for legitimate 
The spam market does have some similarities to the market for legitimate 
online advertising (whose institutions have been described in this journal by Evans 
online advertising (whose institutions have been described in this journal by Evans 
2009) in the sense that spam attempts to generate a sale. However, while in legiti-
2009) in the sense that spam attempts to generate a sale. However, while in legiti-
mate advertising the whole point is to promote awareness (of a fi rm or a product), 
mate advertising the whole point is to promote awareness (of a fi rm or a product), 
spam typically uses obfuscation to get its message through. Spam-based advertising 
spam typically uses obfuscation to get its message through. Spam-based advertising 
is dominated by "affi liate marketing," in which a merchant recruits intermediaries 
is dominated by "affi liate marketing," in which a merchant recruits intermediaries 
known as affi liates (a.k.a. spammers) to advertise on its behalf, in return for a share 
known as affi liates (a.k.a. spammers) to advertise on its behalf, in return for a share 
of the fi nal purchase amount (Levchenko et al. 2011; Samosseiko 2009; Kanich et al. 
of the fi nal purchase amount (Levchenko et al. 2011; Samosseiko 2009; Kanich et al. 
2011; Kanich et al. 2008). Thus, a merchant advertising via spam generally shrouds 
2011; Kanich et al. 2008). Thus, a merchant advertising via spam generally shrouds 
its identity, hiding behind an array of cookie-cutter storefronts, in order to increase 
its identity, hiding behind an array of cookie-cutter storefronts, in order to increase 
the chances of getting its offer through to users. 
the chances of getting its offer through to users. 
The supply (or "publishing") side of the spam market has become dominated by 
The supply (or "publishing") side of the spam market has become dominated by 
botnets, as discussed earlier. Several teams of computer scientists have demonstrated 
botnets, as discussed earlier. Several teams of computer scientists have demonstrated 
that botnets are distinct economic entities from the merchants on the demand side 
that botnets are distinct economic entities from the merchants on the demand side 
of the spam market ( John, Moschuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009; Kanich 
of the spam market ( John, Moschuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009; Kanich 
et al. 2011; Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 2011). Major merchants are 
et al. 2011; Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 2011). Major merchants are 
advertised by multiple botnets, and botnets compete with each other for clients 
advertised by multiple botnets, and botnets compete with each other for clients 
(Thonnard and Dacier 2011). A botnet may either rent out its services to indepen-
(Thonnard and Dacier 2011). A botnet may either rent out its services to indepen-
dent spammers, or send its own spam while acting as an affi liate for a merchant. 
dent spammers, or send its own spam while acting as an affi liate for a merchant. 
Both business models appear to be widely practiced ( John, Moschuk, Gribble, and 
Both business models appear to be widely practiced ( John, Moschuk, Gribble, and 
Krishnamurthy 2009; Kanich et al. 2011; Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 
Krishnamurthy 2009; Kanich et al. 2011; Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 
2011). The market structure appears to be an oligopoly (Zhao et al. 2009). The 
2011). The market structure appears to be an oligopoly (Zhao et al. 2009). The </p>

<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 97 </p>

<p>Stone-Gross team infi ltrated the Cutwail botnet and documented its offerings, which 
Stone-Gross team infi ltrated the Cutwail botnet and documented its offerings, which 
range from a bare bones rental of computation time on the compromised machines 
range from a bare bones rental of computation time on the compromised machines 
all the way to a user-friendly interface allowing a customer to create a mass mailing 
all the way to a user-friendly interface allowing a customer to create a mass mailing 
and test it against open-source spam fi lters before sending. Like publishers in the 
and test it against open-source spam fi lters before sending. Like publishers in the 
legitimate advertising market, botnets invest in signifi cant fi xed costs of ad serving, 
legitimate advertising market, botnets invest in signifi cant fi xed costs of ad serving, 
match advertisers with potential customers, and offer large reach. 
match advertisers with potential customers, and offer large reach. 
To probe the demand side of the spam market, Levchenko et al. (2011), a team 
To probe the demand side of the spam market, Levchenko et al. (2011), a team 
of 14 coauthors based at the University of California at San Diego and the University 
of 14 coauthors based at the University of California at San Diego and the University 
of California at Berkeley, developed spam feeds to identify examples of spam, a 
of California at Berkeley, developed spam feeds to identify examples of spam, a 
web crawler to follow advertised URLs, and botnet infi ltration and botnet detection 
web crawler to follow advertised URLs, and botnet infi ltration and botnet detection 
algorithms (see also John, Moschuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009) to monitor 
algorithms (see also John, Moschuk, Gribble, and Krishnamurthy 2009) to monitor 
botnet activity. Table 1 presents statistics on the merchants tracked through this 
botnet activity. Table 1 presents statistics on the merchants tracked through this 
technique. The fi rst row shows that spam for only 45 merchants included 365 million 
technique. The fi rst row shows that spam for only 45 merchants included 365 million 
distinct URLs during the data collection period. The second row of the table shows 
distinct URLs during the data collection period. The second row of the table shows 
that there are more than 5,000 times as many URLs as domain names used by 
that there are more than 5,000 times as many URLs as domain names used by 
spammers. For example, a spammer might register the domain pharma.com and 
spammers. For example, a spammer might register the domain pharma.com and 
then host thousands of identical pages with different URLs on the same domain: 
then host thousands of identical pages with different URLs on the same domain: 
"pharma.com/buy123.html," "pharma.com/purchase01.html," and so on. There 
"pharma.com/buy123.html," "pharma.com/purchase01.html," and so on. There 
are also more than 1,000 domain names per merchant. A merchant may be repre-
are also more than 1,000 domain names per merchant. A merchant may be repre-
sented by several affi liate spammers, each of whom might register multiple domains. 
sented by several affi liate spammers, each of whom might register multiple domains. 
Large, reputable registrars generally reject applications for spammy-sounding 
Large, reputable registrars generally reject applications for spammy-sounding 
domain names, such as those containing "med" or "pharm" (Kanich et al. 2008), 
domain names, such as those containing "med" or "pharm" (Kanich et al. 2008), 
but hundreds of registrars are willing to look the other way (Levchenko et al. 2011). 
but hundreds of registrars are willing to look the other way (Levchenko et al. 2011). 
Row three gives the number of "store-front styles" that represent individual user 
Row three gives the number of "store-front styles" that represent individual user 
interfaces, each with a distinct look and feel. When law enforcement tries to shut 
interfaces, each with a distinct look and feel. When law enforcement tries to shut 
down illegal sales, they look for identical storefronts and try to take them down all 
down illegal sales, they look for identical storefronts and try to take them down all 
at once, so store-front variation helps a merchant avoid complete shutdown. For 
at once, so store-front variation helps a merchant avoid complete shutdown. For 
each pharmaceutical merchant, there are approximately 30 distinct store fronts; 
each pharmaceutical merchant, there are approximately 30 distinct store fronts; 
this fi gure is much lower for software and replicas. The fi nal row of the table shows 
this fi gure is much lower for software and replicas. The fi nal row of the table shows 
the number of merchants anchoring the market. Despite the large numbers of 
the number of merchants anchoring the market. Despite the large numbers of 
domains, URLs, and store fronts, only 100 merchants had a measurable market 
domains, URLs, and store fronts, only 100 merchants had a measurable market 
share of spam activity, and fewer than ten merchants account for over 80 percent of 
share of spam activity, and fewer than ten merchants account for over 80 percent of 
the market (Levchenko et al. 2011; Kanich et al. 2011). 
the market (Levchenko et al. 2011; Kanich et al. 2011). </p>

<p>Table 1 
Breakdown of the Spam Supply Chain </p>

<p>Stage 
Pharmacy 
Software 
Replicas 
Total </p>

<p>Unique URLs 
346,993,046 
3,071,828 
15,330,404 
365,395,278 
Domains 
54,220 
7,252 
7,530 
69,002 
Store-front styles 
968 
51 
20 
1,039 
Merchants 
30 
5 
10 
45 </p>

<p>Source: From a study of 45 merchants tracked by Levchenko et al. (2011). </p>



<p>After tracking the merchants via the botnets, Levchenko et al. (2011) placed 
After tracking the merchants via the botnets, Levchenko et al. (2011) placed 
120 orders for the advertised goods, spread across the 100 identifi ed merchants. 
120 orders for the advertised goods, spread across the 100 identifi ed merchants. 
The affi liated spammer usually hosts the entire consumer storefront experience; 
The affi liated spammer usually hosts the entire consumer storefront experience; 
that is, the spammer generally collects payment information and then hands the 
that is, the spammer generally collects payment information and then hands the 
transaction to the merchant before credit card authorization. Payment processing 
transaction to the merchant before credit card authorization. Payment processing 
services for these merchants are quite concentrated: a total of only 17 banks serve 
services for these merchants are quite concentrated: a total of only 17 banks serve 
the 100 merchants, with just three banks (from Latvia, Azerbaijan, and St. Kitts 
the 100 merchants, with just three banks (from Latvia, Azerbaijan, and St. Kitts 
and Nevis) processing the payments for more than 75 percent of the transactions. 
and Nevis) processing the payments for more than 75 percent of the transactions. 
Postage stamps on the packages revealed the physical locations where the goods 
Postage stamps on the packages revealed the physical locations where the goods 
originated: nearly all the pharmaceuticals came from India, for example, while 
originated: nearly all the pharmaceuticals came from India, for example, while 
replica watches generally came from China. 
replica watches generally came from China. 
Overall, while spammers have nearly free entry in registering domains and 
Overall, while spammers have nearly free entry in registering domains and 
renting services from botnets, merchants appear to face more signifi cant fi xed 
renting services from botnets, merchants appear to face more signifi cant fi xed 
costs, especially in obtaining payment processing services. Only a small number of 
costs, especially in obtaining payment processing services. Only a small number of 
banks appear willing to take the risk of associating with gray-market merchants. This 
banks appear willing to take the risk of associating with gray-market merchants. This 
may explain why a relatively small number of merchants supply most of the market 
may explain why a relatively small number of merchants supply most of the market 
for these spam-advertised goods. 
for these spam-advertised goods. </p>

<p>Assessing the Externality </p>

<p>What are the costs of spam to users, and how does it compare with the return 
What are the costs of spam to users, and how does it compare with the return 
to spammers? A widely cited report from Ferris Research (2005) placed the world-
to spammers? A widely cited report from Ferris Research (2005) placed the world-
wide cost of spam in 2005 at $50 billion; Ferris raised its estimate to $100 billion in 
wide cost of spam in 2005 at $50 billion; Ferris raised its estimate to $100 billion in 
2007 and $130 billion in 2009 ( Jennings 2009). However, the Ferris reports did not 
2007 and $130 billion in 2009 ( Jennings 2009). However, the Ferris reports did not 
describe how they estimated such key parameters as the amount of time per worker 
describe how they estimated such key parameters as the amount of time per worker 
spent deleting spam; indeed, one of the authors of that report indicated to us that 
spent deleting spam; indeed, one of the authors of that report indicated to us that 
their work was "not a scientifi c survey," but that it attempted to be a lower-bound 
their work was "not a scientifi c survey," but that it attempted to be a lower-bound 
estimate. Regarding the returns to spammers, the most common estimate of profi ts 
estimate. Regarding the returns to spammers, the most common estimate of profi ts 
involves the phrase "millions of dollars a day," which in turn apparently originated 
involves the phrase "millions of dollars a day," which in turn apparently originated 
in a widely cited IBM press release. 
in a widely cited IBM press release. 2 2 In this next section, we fi nd these widely cited 
In this next section, we fi nd these widely cited 
estimates of user costs and spammer profi ts are somewhat exaggerated, but of the 
estimates of user costs and spammer profi ts are somewhat exaggerated, but of the 
right order of magnitude. 
right order of magnitude. </p>

<p>Measuring the Diffuse Costs of Spam 
The negative externalities imposed by spam include wasted time for consumers: 
The negative externalities imposed by spam include wasted time for consumers: 
both wading through irrelevant advertisements in one's inbox and missing an 
both wading through irrelevant advertisements in one's inbox and missing an 
important message that went to the junk mail folder. They also include the costs 
important message that went to the junk mail folder. They also include the costs </p>

<p>2 See Malik (2008), "IBM Says Storm Worm Creators Making Millions Daily," 〈http://gizmodo.com 
/354741/ibm-says-storm-worm-creators-making-millions-daily⟩. Phishing for account information in 
order to steal money is a form of online crime representing less than 0.3 percent of all email traffi c. 
Researchers at Microsoft found that conventional wisdom was an overestimate by 50 of the true profi ts to 
phishing (Herley and Florêncio 2009). </p>

<p>The Economics of Spam 99 </p>

<p>of server hardware, which requires more than fi ve times as much capacity as would 
of server hardware, which requires more than fi ve times as much capacity as would 
be required in the absence of spam, as well as the costs of spam prevention services 
be required in the absence of spam, as well as the costs of spam prevention services 
provided by fi rms to reduce the burden on end users. 
provided by fi rms to reduce the burden on end users. 
The chief challenge in totaling up the social cost is credibly estimating the 
The chief challenge in totaling up the social cost is credibly estimating the 
number of hours lost by people dealing with spam. Estimating the amount of spam 
number of hours lost by people dealing with spam. Estimating the amount of spam 
that beats spam fi lters is diffi cult -after all, if we knew it was spam, we would have 
that beats spam fi lters is diffi cult -after all, if we knew it was spam, we would have 
fi ltered it. We choose to examine success rates of spam in infl uencing consumer 
fi ltered it. We choose to examine success rates of spam in infl uencing consumer 
behavior, and use these to infer how many spam messages must have gotten 
behavior, and use these to infer how many spam messages must have gotten 
through. Here we rely on the work of Kanich et al. (2008), who observed that out 
through. Here we rely on the work of Kanich et al. (2008), who observed that out 
of 347 million attempted mailings for an online pharmacy, about 83 million were 
of 347 million attempted mailings for an online pharmacy, about 83 million were 
accepted for delivery rather than bounced; our question is how many arrived in the 
accepted for delivery rather than bounced; our question is how many arrived in the 
inbox versus the spam box. The 83 million messages accepted for delivery resulted in 
inbox versus the spam box. The 83 million messages accepted for delivery resulted in 
10,500 clicks by consumers; we can estimate the number of spam messages reaching 
10,500 clicks by consumers; we can estimate the number of spam messages reaching 
the inbox with an educated guess about the clickthrough rate for spam campaigns. 
the inbox with an educated guess about the clickthrough rate for spam campaigns. 
We know legitimate email marketing for medical products has a clickthrough rate of 
We know legitimate email marketing for medical products has a clickthrough rate of 
about 1.1 percent (Email Marketing Metrics Report, 2011), while untargeted display 
about 1.1 percent (Email Marketing Metrics Report, 2011), while untargeted display 
advertising on Yahoo! usually has clickthrough rates of 0.1 percent or less. The 
advertising on Yahoo! usually has clickthrough rates of 0.1 percent or less. The 
clickthrough rate for spam email should be lower than the former but higher than 
clickthrough rate for spam email should be lower than the former but higher than 
the latter, because spam targets consumers more indiscriminately than legitimate 
the latter, because spam targets consumers more indiscriminately than legitimate 
email marketing, while email that reaches the inbox attracts more attention than 
email marketing, while email that reaches the inbox attracts more attention than 
the average web graphical ad. Using a clickthrough rate of 0.25 percent for spam, 
the average web graphical ad. Using a clickthrough rate of 0.25 percent for spam, 
we estimate that about 4,200,000 messages (10,500 clicks divided by 0.0025 clicks/ 
we estimate that about 4,200,000 messages (10,500 clicks divided by 0.0025 clicks/ 
message) reached inboxes, out of 347 million messages sent. That is, we estimate 
message) reached inboxes, out of 347 million messages sent. That is, we estimate 
that only about 1.2 percent of sent spam messages actually reach user inboxes. 
that only about 1.2 percent of sent spam messages actually reach user inboxes. 
As a consistency check on this estimate, we look at spammers' costs and revenues. 
As a consistency check on this estimate, we look at spammers' costs and revenues. 
Given the free entry of spammers (as opposed to botnets or merchants), we should 
Given the free entry of spammers (as opposed to botnets or merchants), we should 
expect them to earn zero profi ts. Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna (2011) 
expect them to earn zero profi ts. Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna (2011) 
estimate that spammers pay around $30 per million unblocked message deliveries (or 
estimate that spammers pay around $30 per million unblocked message deliveries (or 
fi ve million emails sent, 80 percent of which were blocked by blacklisting). Spammers 
fi ve million emails sent, 80 percent of which were blocked by blacklisting). Spammers 
appear to earn about $50 per purchase (Kanich et al. 2011), so to break even each 
appear to earn about $50 per purchase (Kanich et al. 2011), so to break even each 
spammer will have to generate 8.3 million email sends. 
spammer will have to generate 8.3 million email sends. 3 3 Knowing that spammers earn 
Knowing that spammers earn 
about one purchase per 375 clicks (Kanich et al. 2008) and assuming as before a click-
about one purchase per 375 clicks (Kanich et al. 2008) and assuming as before a click-
through rate of 0.25 percent, we estimate that 150,000 emails must reach inboxes in 
through rate of 0.25 percent, we estimate that 150,000 emails must reach inboxes in 
order to generate one purchase. That gives us an estimate of 1.8 percent of attempted 
order to generate one purchase. That gives us an estimate of 1.8 percent of attempted 
spams reaching user inboxes (0.15 million out of 8.3 million messages). This estimate 
spams reaching user inboxes (0.15 million out of 8.3 million messages). This estimate 
is slightly higher than our original estimate, but in the same ballpark. 
is slightly higher than our original estimate, but in the same ballpark. 
Given this fi gure, we can arrive at an estimate of the total user cost of spam. 
Given this fi gure, we can arrive at an estimate of the total user cost of spam. 
Ninety billion spam messages were sent each day worldwide in 2010 (Symantec 2010; 
Ninety billion spam messages were sent each day worldwide in 2010 (Symantec 2010; 
MAAWG 2011); we just estimated that 1.2 percent of these 90 billion get through to 
MAAWG 2011); we just estimated that 1.2 percent of these 90 billion get through to 
the consumer. (These 2010 fi gures ignore the subsequent 30 percent decrease in 
the consumer. (These 2010 fi gures ignore the subsequent 30 percent decrease in 
global spam due to the Rustock botnet takedown described above, though anecdotal 
global spam due to the Rustock botnet takedown described above, though anecdotal </p>

<p>3 The Kanich group found 1 conversion per 12.3 million emails sent, which is in the right ballpark. </p>



<p>evidence suggests that other botnets have been growing to fi ll the void.) A large 
evidence suggests that other botnets have been growing to fi ll the void.) A large 
fraction of this spam targets the United States: more than 90 percent of this spam 
fraction of this spam targets the United States: more than 90 percent of this spam 
was in English (Symantec, 2010), and Kanich et al. (2008) observe nearly 100 times 
was in English (Symantec, 2010), and Kanich et al. (2008) observe nearly 100 times 
as much spam going to the United States as to any other country. Suppose, then, 
as much spam going to the United States as to any other country. Suppose, then, 
that the average value of a user's time is $25 per hour, and that each piece of spam 
that the average value of a user's time is $25 per hour, and that each piece of spam 
takes an average of fi ve seconds to deal with. (False positives in the spam box are 
takes an average of fi ve seconds to deal with. (False positives in the spam box are 
more costly, but so rare that we ignore them in this estimate.) This brings the total 
more costly, but so rare that we ignore them in this estimate.) This brings the total 
worldwide end-user cost of spam to nearly $14 billion per year. 
worldwide end-user cost of spam to nearly $14 billion per year. 
As to the costs of anti-spam technology and hardware, Jennings (2009) in a 
As to the costs of anti-spam technology and hardware, Jennings (2009) in a 
report published by Ferris Research estimated the costs at approximately $6.5 billion 
report published by Ferris Research estimated the costs at approximately $6.5 billion 
worldwide, based on surveys of fi rms purchasing anti-spam solutions. This seems 
worldwide, based on surveys of fi rms purchasing anti-spam solutions. This seems 
roughly correct, given that the largest anti-spam service provider, Symantec, had 
roughly correct, given that the largest anti-spam service provider, Symantec, had 
$6.2 billion in annual revenues in 2011, although it is hard to know exactly how 
$6.2 billion in annual revenues in 2011, although it is hard to know exactly how 
much of the revenue for this fi rm was due to spam as opposed to network security. 
much of the revenue for this fi rm was due to spam as opposed to network security. 
Other fi rms providing anti-spam services to corporate clients include McAfee, Trend 
Other fi rms providing anti-spam services to corporate clients include McAfee, Trend 
Micro, and Barracuda. Our total should also include the labor costs of the staff 
Micro, and Barracuda. Our total should also include the labor costs of the staff 
who install and maintain the anti-spam solutions, and the costs of additional server 
who install and maintain the anti-spam solutions, and the costs of additional server 
capacity required by spam email. We believe $6.5 billion is a reasonable estimate for 
capacity required by spam email. We believe $6.5 billion is a reasonable estimate for 
the total, which represents approximately $30 per user for just over a billion users. 
the total, which represents approximately $30 per user for just over a billion users. 4 4 
If fi rms were not investing in anti-spam technology, end users would be receiving 
If fi rms were not investing in anti-spam technology, end users would be receiving 
100 times as much spam, which given our estimate of the current time loss due to 
100 times as much spam, which given our estimate of the current time loss due to 
spam, would put the total economic loss at over $1 trillion. However, without any 
spam, would put the total economic loss at over $1 trillion. However, without any 
spam fi ltering it is unlikely that email would be a popular means of communication, 
spam fi ltering it is unlikely that email would be a popular means of communication, 
so while one cannot take this number literally, it does give a feel for the magnitude 
so while one cannot take this number literally, it does give a feel for the magnitude 
of user time savings resulting from private investment in anti-spam technology. 
of user time savings resulting from private investment in anti-spam technology. 
Taken together, the total costs of spam worldwide today appear to be approxi-
Taken together, the total costs of spam worldwide today appear to be approxi-
mately $20 billion, in round numbers. Our estimate is half that of the widely cited 
mately $20 billion, in round numbers. Our estimate is half that of the widely cited 
Ferris Research (2005) number, because we use a lower value of end-user time, we 
Ferris Research (2005) number, because we use a lower value of end-user time, we 
ignore help-desk support for users struggling with spam, and we use a lower estimate 
ignore help-desk support for users struggling with spam, and we use a lower estimate 
of the number of spams that reach user inboxes. 
of the number of spams that reach user inboxes. </p>

<p>Measuring the Private Returns to Spam 
Researchers have used three tactics to estimate the revenues of botnets and 
Researchers have used three tactics to estimate the revenues of botnets and 
merchants: 1) monitor botnet activity and infi ltrate spot markets for spam services, 
merchants: 1) monitor botnet activity and infi ltrate spot markets for spam services, 
2) hijack a botnet to estimate the number of purchases generated by a merchant 
2) hijack a botnet to estimate the number of purchases generated by a merchant 
through a spam campaign, and 3) estimate order volume through periodically placing 
through a spam campaign, and 3) estimate order volume through periodically placing 
one's own orders and examining the gaps in the sequential order ID numbers. 
one's own orders and examining the gaps in the sequential order ID numbers. 
As an example of the fi rst approach, Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 
As an example of the fi rst approach, Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, and Vigna 
(2011) infi ltrated the (then prolifi c) Cutwail botnet. They were able to monitor 
(2011) infi ltrated the (then prolifi c) Cutwail botnet. They were able to monitor 
every advertising campaign run on the botnet, recording message volume, purpose, 
every advertising campaign run on the botnet, recording message volume, purpose, 
and associated merchants. Next, the team infi ltrated a private web forum operated 
and associated merchants. Next, the team infi ltrated a private web forum operated </p>

<p>4 For reference, Yahoo! Mail incurs anti-spam costs of approximately $55 million per year for 500 million 
active email accounts, a cost of $0.10 per account per year. </p>

<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 101 </p>

<p>by the botnet masters as a market for spam services. The authors document two ways 
by the botnet masters as a market for spam services. The authors document two ways 
to publish spam through the Cutwail botnet. Retail spam services were offered at 
to publish spam through the Cutwail botnet. Retail spam services were offered at 
$100 to $500 per million emails in this market. "Wholesale" spam service involves 
$100 to $500 per million emails in this market. "Wholesale" spam service involves 
separately acquiring email address lists and renting time on the botnet's spam-send 
separately acquiring email address lists and renting time on the botnet's spam-send 
infrastructure. A monthly rental, capable of pumping out 10 million unblocked 
infrastructure. A monthly rental, capable of pumping out 10 million unblocked 
messages per day, was priced at $10,000, or about $33 per million emails. A 
messages per day, was priced at $10,000, or about $33 per million emails. A 
more premium wholesale spam product, sending all messages through webmail 
more premium wholesale spam product, sending all messages through webmail 
accounts (and therefore incurring the higher cost of having to break CAPTCHAs), 
accounts (and therefore incurring the higher cost of having to break CAPTCHAs), 
cost about one-third more. The authors estimate that the Cutwail botnet earned 
cost about one-third more. The authors estimate that the Cutwail botnet earned 
$1.7-4.2 million in profi t during the 14-month period of study. 
$1.7-4.2 million in profi t during the 14-month period of study. 
In Table 2, we convert the cost estimates for spam from the fi rst research tech-
In Table 2, we convert the cost estimates for spam from the fi rst research tech-
nique (Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, Vigna 2011; Motoyama, Levchenko, Kanich, 
nique (Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, Vigna 2011; Motoyama, Levchenko, Kanich, 
McCoy, Voelker, and Savage 2010) to the standard unit used in the advertising 
McCoy, Voelker, and Savage 2010) to the standard unit used in the advertising 
industry: cost per thousand impressions (CPM). For spam email, an impression will 
industry: cost per thousand impressions (CPM). For spam email, an impression will 
be a "successful connection"-an email that is not screened out by IP blacklisting 
be a "successful connection"-an email that is not screened out by IP blacklisting 
and so lands in either the inbox or spam folder. To put the fi gures in perspective, 
and so lands in either the inbox or spam folder. To put the fi gures in perspective, 
we also include estimates for the cost of sending consumers messages via direct 
we also include estimates for the cost of sending consumers messages via direct 
mail, Super Bowl advertising, or legitimate online advertising. We next suppose 
mail, Super Bowl advertising, or legitimate online advertising. We next suppose 
the average transaction, or "conversion" in online-advertising parlance, to produce 
the average transaction, or "conversion" in online-advertising parlance, to produce 
profi ts of $50. Given this assumption, Column 3 gives the conversion rate necessary 
profi ts of $50. Given this assumption, Column 3 gives the conversion rate necessary 
to break even on each form of advertising. For legibility, Column 4 restates the 
to break even on each form of advertising. For legibility, Column 4 restates the 
breakeven conversion rates in units of conversions per 100,000 ads. 
breakeven conversion rates in units of conversions per 100,000 ads. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Cost of Spam Advertising Relative to Other Advertising Media 
(cost per thousand impressions (CPM)) </p>

<p>Breakeven conversion 
with marginal profi t = $50.00 </p>

<p>Advertising vector 
CPM 
Percent 
Per 100,000 deliveries </p>

<p>Postal direct mail 
$250-1,000 
2-10% a 
2000 
Super Bowl advertising 
$20 
0.04% 
40 
Online display advertising 
$1-5 
0.002-0.006% 
2 
Retail spam 
$0.10-0.50 
0.001-.0002% 
0.3 
Botnet wholesale spam 
$0.03 
0.00006% 
0.06 
Botnet via webmail 
$0.05 b 
0.0001% 
0.1 </p>

<p>Sources: For direct mail, U.S. Postal Service website, For Super Bowl advertising, 〈http://money.cnn.com 
/2011/02/03/news/companies/super_bowl_ads?index.hrm⟩. For retail spam and botnet wholesale 
spam, Stone-Gross, Holz, Stringhini, Vigna (2011); for botnet via webmail, Motoyama, Levchenko, 
Kanich, McCoy, Voelker, and Savage (2010). 
Notes: Cost per thousand impressions (CPM) is the standard unit of measurement in the advertising 
industry. For spam email, an impression will be a "successful connection"-an email that is not screened 
out by IP blacklisting and so lands in either the inbox or spam folder. 
a Direct Marketing Association (2012) reports 2.2%. 
b Assumes botnet rental is delivery method. </p>



<p>Direct mail is the most expensive form of advertising, due to printing and 
Direct mail is the most expensive form of advertising, due to printing and 
postage costs; this medium thus requires high breakeven conversion rates of at 
postage costs; this medium thus requires high breakeven conversion rates of at 
least 2 percent. For the case of $50 profi t per sales, standard online display adver-
least 2 percent. For the case of $50 profi t per sales, standard online display adver-
tising can be profi table down to a conversion frequency of 2 per 100,000 ads, while 
tising can be profi table down to a conversion frequency of 2 per 100,000 ads, while 
"premium display" would require 10 per 100,000 ads. Retail spam is profi table 
"premium display" would require 10 per 100,000 ads. Retail spam is profi table 
down to 0.2 conversions per 100,000. Bulk spam through wholesale botnet rental is 
down to 0.2 conversions per 100,000. Bulk spam through wholesale botnet rental is 
sustainable with a mere 0.06 conversions per 100,000 ads, or about 1 in 2,000,000. 
sustainable with a mere 0.06 conversions per 100,000 ads, or about 1 in 2,000,000. 
Clearly, spam can be orders of magnitude less effective than traditional forms of 
Clearly, spam can be orders of magnitude less effective than traditional forms of 
advertising and still remain profi table. 
advertising and still remain profi table. 
The second research technique, hijacking a botnet, appears in the infl uential 
The second research technique, hijacking a botnet, appears in the infl uential 
2008 "Spamalytics" paper (Kanich et al. 2008), in which the researchers co-opted a 
2008 "Spamalytics" paper (Kanich et al. 2008), in which the researchers co-opted a 
portion of the Storm botnet by modifying the software instructions given to a set of 
portion of the Storm botnet by modifying the software instructions given to a set of 
downstream zombie computers. The modifi ed instructions replaced the link to the 
downstream zombie computers. The modifi ed instructions replaced the link to the 
spammer's storefront with a link to their own replica storefront. Users could place 
spammer's storefront with a link to their own replica storefront. Users could place 
an order at the replica storefront, but would then receive an error message. The 
an order at the replica storefront, but would then receive an error message. The 
researchers could thus measure how many conversions would have been generated 
researchers could thus measure how many conversions would have been generated 
by the spam emails with their modifi ed instructions. 
by the spam emails with their modifi ed instructions. 
In total, the group modifi ed 345 million pharmaceutical emails sent from botnet 
In total, the group modifi ed 345 million pharmaceutical emails sent from botnet 
zombies. Three-quarters of these were blocked through blacklisting, and the remaining 
zombies. Three-quarters of these were blocked through blacklisting, and the remaining 
82 million emails led to a scant 28 conversions, or about 1 in 3,000,000. This conver-
82 million emails led to a scant 28 conversions, or about 1 in 3,000,000. This conver-
sion rate is far lower than what could be profi table for a retail spam campaign. We 
sion rate is far lower than what could be profi table for a retail spam campaign. We 
suspect that the reason for this lack of success is that a large portion of this major spam 
suspect that the reason for this lack of success is that a large portion of this major spam 
campaign went to large email providers like Yahoo! and Gmail and failed to evade their 
campaign went to large email providers like Yahoo! and Gmail and failed to evade their 
spam fi lters. We hypothesize that small-scale spammers can beat spam fi lters more easily 
spam fi lters. We hypothesize that small-scale spammers can beat spam fi lters more easily 
and can spend time crafting creatively targeted campaigns; meanwhile, large-scale bulk 
and can spend time crafting creatively targeted campaigns; meanwhile, large-scale bulk 
campaigns spray email like a fi rehose, but the vast majority of it is blocked by fi lters. 
campaigns spray email like a fi rehose, but the vast majority of it is blocked by fi lters. 
The same research group also introduced the third estimation technique: 
The same research group also introduced the third estimation technique: 
placing sequential orders and drawing inferences from order ID numbers (Kanich 
placing sequential orders and drawing inferences from order ID numbers (Kanich 
et al. 2011). They began by making multiple purchases only a few seconds apart. 
et al. 2011). They began by making multiple purchases only a few seconds apart. 
Ten merchants were determined to use simple ascending rules for order IDs; for 
Ten merchants were determined to use simple ascending rules for order IDs; for 
these merchants, the researchers placed a series of orders spaced over a period of 
these merchants, the researchers placed a series of orders spaced over a period of 
six weeks. The order IDs fully revealed the quantity of other orders placed in the 
six weeks. The order IDs fully revealed the quantity of other orders placed in the 
intervening time periods. The researchers also learned that one spammer hosted 
intervening time periods. The researchers also learned that one spammer hosted 
the images for its storefronts on a server belonging to someone else, which the 
the images for its storefronts on a server belonging to someone else, which the 
spammer had hijacked through malware. The researchers notifi ed the server's 
spammer had hijacked through malware. The researchers notifi ed the server's 
owner, who in turn gave them permission to monitor requests for the relevant 
owner, who in turn gave them permission to monitor requests for the relevant 
image URLs, which provided reliable data on average order size and the basket of 
image URLs, which provided reliable data on average order size and the basket of 
goods purchased. Each of these ten large spam-oriented merchants earned between 
goods purchased. Each of these ten large spam-oriented merchants earned between 
$500,000 and $1.5 million per month in revenue-of course, profi ts would be 
$500,000 and $1.5 million per month in revenue-of course, profi ts would be 
lower. The researchers project that, in total, spam-oriented merchants receive gross 
lower. The researchers project that, in total, spam-oriented merchants receive gross 
revenues of about $180-360 million dollars annually. 
revenues of about $180-360 million dollars annually. 
We can check this revenue estimate using estimates of the prices and quantities 
We can check this revenue estimate using estimates of the prices and quantities 
of spam emails sent. As noted earlier, Symantec (2010) estimates the volume of 
of spam emails sent. As noted earlier, Symantec (2010) estimates the volume of 
spam at 90 billion attempted connections per day, 80 percent of which are refused 
spam at 90 billion attempted connections per day, 80 percent of which are refused </p>

<p>The Economics of Spam 103 </p>

<p>due to blacklisting. Similarly, the Yahoo! Mail team told us that in October 2011, 
due to blacklisting. Similarly, the Yahoo! Mail team told us that in October 2011, 
they received approximately 30 billion attempted connections per day, 80 percent 
they received approximately 30 billion attempted connections per day, 80 percent 
of which were bounced, just under 10 percent of which went to the spam folder, and 
of which were bounced, just under 10 percent of which went to the spam folder, and 
just over 10 percent of which went to a user's inbox. If the unblocked 20 percent 
just over 10 percent of which went to a user's inbox. If the unblocked 20 percent 
of spam is priced at $50 per million ("premium bulk" rates), this would amount 
of spam is priced at $50 per million ("premium bulk" rates), this would amount 
to $600,000 worth of spam being sent to Europe and North America each day-so 
to $600,000 worth of spam being sent to Europe and North America each day-so 
perhaps $750,000 worldwide. This fi gure seems a bit high given our previous esti-
perhaps $750,000 worldwide. This fi gure seems a bit high given our previous esti-
mate of just under $1 million per day in revenues for the entire supply chain (which 
mate of just under $1 million per day in revenues for the entire supply chain (which 
must also include the cost of goods sold), but it is of the right order of magnitude. 
must also include the cost of goods sold), but it is of the right order of magnitude. 
Overall, we feel comfortable with an estimate of total industry revenue for 
Overall, we feel comfortable with an estimate of total industry revenue for 
spam-advertised goods on the order of $300 million per year. One might, in prin-
spam-advertised goods on the order of $300 million per year. One might, in prin-
ciple, want to include consumer surplus in a calculation of the total benefi ts of 
ciple, want to include consumer surplus in a calculation of the total benefi ts of 
spam. However, because consumers who wanted these goods would likely be able to 
spam. However, because consumers who wanted these goods would likely be able to 
fi nd them via online searches in the absence of spam, we assume that the consumer 
fi nd them via online searches in the absence of spam, we assume that the consumer 
benefi ts are less than the total revenues earned by the spam industry. Since we have 
benefi ts are less than the total revenues earned by the spam industry. Since we have 
estimated the revenues rather than the profi ts of the spam industry, and we know 
estimated the revenues rather than the profi ts of the spam industry, and we know 
there are marginal costs to the goods sold, we will assume for convenience that the 
there are marginal costs to the goods sold, we will assume for convenience that the 
revenues represent approximately the total surplus generated by spam, including 
revenues represent approximately the total surplus generated by spam, including 
both producer and consumer surplus. 
both producer and consumer surplus. </p>

<p>The "Externality Ratio" of Spam in Context 
The "Externality Ratio" of Spam in Context 
Spam to end users costs around $20 billion annually, compared with approxi-
Spam to end users costs around $20 billion annually, compared with approxi-
mately $200 million in surplus generated by the spam to these same users. The 
mately $200 million in surplus generated by the spam to these same users. The 
ratio of the cost of this externality to society relative to the ratio of private benefi ts 
ratio of the cost of this externality to society relative to the ratio of private benefi ts 
it generates is about 100:1. 
it generates is about 100:1. 
To put this magnitude into context, Table 3 provides estimates for the externality 
To put this magnitude into context, Table 3 provides estimates for the externality 
ratios associated with 1) the air pollution from driving a vehicle, and 2) the (nonvio-
ratios associated with 1) the air pollution from driving a vehicle, and 2) the (nonvio-
lent) stealing of automobiles. For driving, we use a low value for the benefi t accrued to 
lent) stealing of automobiles. For driving, we use a low value for the benefi t accrued to 
a driver, a fi gure just above the operation cost per mile. In reality, people make many 
a driver, a fi gure just above the operation cost per mile. In reality, people make many 
inframarginal trips, valued by the consumer well over the marginal cost. The cost esti-
inframarginal trips, valued by the consumer well over the marginal cost. The cost esti-
mate comes from Delucchi (1998), who does a nice job of accounting for the social cost 
mate comes from Delucchi (1998), who does a nice job of accounting for the social cost 
of the various air pollutants emitted by an automobile; time congestion externalities are 
of the various air pollutants emitted by an automobile; time congestion externalities are 
not measured so this estimate should be viewed as the cost of driving on an uncongested 
not measured so this estimate should be viewed as the cost of driving on an uncongested 
roadway. (Interested readers are directed to Parry, Walls, and Harrington 2007, who 
roadway. (Interested readers are directed to Parry, Walls, and Harrington 2007, who 
survey the literature more broadly, including the matter of congestion costs.) Delucchi's 
survey the literature more broadly, including the matter of congestion costs.) Delucchi's 
preferred estimate for the social cost per mile was $0.06; using this fi gure gives an exter-
preferred estimate for the social cost per mile was $0.06; using this fi gure gives an exter-
nality ratio of about 0.1, three orders of magnitude less than the value we obtain for 
nality ratio of about 0.1, three orders of magnitude less than the value we obtain for 
spam. By contrast, stealing automobiles has a much higher externality ratio, as demon-
spam. By contrast, stealing automobiles has a much higher externality ratio, as demon-
strated by Field (1993). The societal costs include uninsured losses to victims, insurance 
strated by Field (1993). The societal costs include uninsured losses to victims, insurance 
premiums, law enforcement patrol costs, and the cost of prosecuting and incarcerating 
premiums, law enforcement patrol costs, and the cost of prosecuting and incarcerating 
offenders who are caught. Adding it all up, the costs imposed on society by auto thieves 
offenders who are caught. Adding it all up, the costs imposed on society by auto thieves 
are a whopping 7 to 30 times the revenue extracted from the vehicle theft. 
are a whopping 7 to 30 times the revenue extracted from the vehicle theft. 
In certain ways, nonviolent auto theft turns out to be a fairly close analogue to 
In certain ways, nonviolent auto theft turns out to be a fairly close analogue to 
spam. The costs of both auto theft and spam are high, and are distributed diffusely 
spam. The costs of both auto theft and spam are high, and are distributed diffusely </p>



<p>across the majority of the population (because insurance rates and law enforcement 
across the majority of the population (because insurance rates and law enforcement 
costs account for the bulk of the costs of auto theft, as in Field 1993). Relative to 
costs account for the bulk of the costs of auto theft, as in Field 1993). Relative to 
other types of crime with poor insurance coverage, both have particularly diffuse 
other types of crime with poor insurance coverage, both have particularly diffuse 
costs. Unlike most crime, spam has no specifi cally identifi able victim, no especially 
costs. Unlike most crime, spam has no specifi cally identifi able victim, no especially 
wronged persons inspiring law enforcement to vigorously bring spammers to 
wronged persons inspiring law enforcement to vigorously bring spammers to 
justice. In fact, some of the "victims" of spam, those who voluntarily make purchases 
justice. In fact, some of the "victims" of spam, those who voluntarily make purchases 
from illegal advertising, arguably exert large negative externalities on the rest of 
from illegal advertising, arguably exert large negative externalities on the rest of 
society. Accounting for how much spam actually reaches the inbox, we estimate 
society. Accounting for how much spam actually reaches the inbox, we estimate 
that only about 1 in 25,000 people needs to succumb to the temptation to make a 
that only about 1 in 25,000 people needs to succumb to the temptation to make a 
grey-market purchase to make it profi table for spammers to inundate everyone with 
grey-market purchase to make it profi table for spammers to inundate everyone with 
advertisements at current levels. From an economic perspective, one could view a 
advertisements at current levels. From an economic perspective, one could view a 
law enforcement system as providing disincentives to make such purchases. 
law enforcement system as providing disincentives to make such purchases. 
While the externality ratio of spam is large, the cost comes in the form of atten-
While the externality ratio of spam is large, the cost comes in the form of atten-
tion and time, not disease and death as in the case of air pollutants. We are not aware 
tion and time, not disease and death as in the case of air pollutants. We are not aware 
of any estimates of the externality ratio of violent crime, but if we use $10,000,000 as 
of any estimates of the externality ratio of violent crime, but if we use $10,000,000 as 
the value of a life and say that a victim of a violent crime has one chance in 1,000 of 
the value of a life and say that a victim of a violent crime has one chance in 1,000 of 
death, then the expected value of the loss of life would be $10,000. For comparison, 
death, then the expected value of the loss of life would be $10,000. For comparison, 
the gains to an armed robber may have greater utility than the losses to a victim 
the gains to an armed robber may have greater utility than the losses to a victim 
because of differences in the marginal utility of income, but any plausible estimate 
because of differences in the marginal utility of income, but any plausible estimate 
of this social welfare gain from this typical armed robbery places the externality ratio 
of this social welfare gain from this typical armed robbery places the externality ratio 
far higher than our estimates for spam. Thus, there are examples of externality 
far higher than our estimates for spam. Thus, there are examples of externality 
ratios higher than that of spam, though these tend to have their harm concentrated 
ratios higher than that of spam, though these tend to have their harm concentrated 
in a small number of people. Various forms of air pollution are similarly diffuse to 
in a small number of people. Various forms of air pollution are similarly diffuse to 
spam, and may have much larger social costs than spam, but their externality ratios 
spam, and may have much larger social costs than spam, but their externality ratios 
are much smaller. 
are much smaller. </p>

<p>Policy Proposals </p>

<p>Considerable effort has gone into anti-spam measures. We already discussed 
Considerable effort has gone into anti-spam measures. We already discussed 
many of the private (and cooperative) technological solutions that have been 
many of the private (and cooperative) technological solutions that have been </p>

<p>Table 3 
Extracted Revenue, Imposed Costs, and Externality Ratios </p>

<p>Activity 
Revenue/benefi t 
Cost 
Externality ratio </p>

<p>Driving automobiles 
$0.60 per mile 
$0.02-0.25 per mile a 
0.03 -0.41 
Stealing automobiles 
$400 -1200 million per year 
$8 -12 billion per year 
6.7-30.3 
Email spam 
$160 -360 million per year 
$14 -18 billion per year b 
39 -112 </p>

<p>Sources: The source for the fi rst row is Delucchi (1997), for the second row, Field (1993). (The FBI 
Uniform Crime Report (2010) places the vehicle value extracted by criminals in the same range as Field 
1993.) The fi nal row is based on the authors' calculations. 
a Air pollution costs. 
b Cost to end users. </p>

<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 105 </p>

<p>adopted by fi rms in an attempt to reduce the social cost of spam. Here we consider 
adopted by fi rms in an attempt to reduce the social cost of spam. Here we consider 
public policy proposals from the legal and economic perspectives. 
public policy proposals from the legal and economic perspectives. </p>

<p>Legal Interventions 
American spam legislation began in earnest with the Telephone Consumer 
American spam legislation began in earnest with the Telephone Consumer 
Protection Act (TCPA) of 1991, which, as a response to rising fax machine spam, 
Protection Act (TCPA) of 1991, which, as a response to rising fax machine spam, 
required fax marketing to be opt-in. 
required fax marketing to be opt-in. 5 5 The legislation also required phone telemar-
The legislation also required phone telemar-
keters to offer an opt-out. In 2003, a consumer challenge to unsolicited email was 
keters to offer an opt-out. In 2003, a consumer challenge to unsolicited email was 
unsuccessful; the Pennsylvania Superior Court ruled in 
unsuccessful; the Pennsylvania Superior Court ruled in Aronson vs. Bright-Teeth Now 
(2003 Pa. Super 187, 824 A.2d 320) that email transmission, without the tangible costs 
(2003 Pa. Super 187, 824 A.2d 320) that email transmission, without the tangible costs 
of paper and toner, was legally different from fax transmission. The TCPA did little 
of paper and toner, was legally different from fax transmission. The TCPA did little 
to stop telemarketing, especially with the 
to stop telemarketing, especially with the Aronson decision, because opting out on a 
decision, because opting out on a 
fi rm-by-fi rm basis was diffi cult and time consuming. However, the National Do-Not-
fi rm-by-fi rm basis was diffi cult and time consuming. However, the National Do-Not-
Call Registry adopted in 2003 allowed consumers to opt out of all telemarketing (with 
Call Registry adopted in 2003 allowed consumers to opt out of all telemarketing (with 
some exemptions for nonprofi ts and politicians) by fi lling out a single form. 
some exemptions for nonprofi ts and politicians) by fi lling out a single form. 
The fi rst national legislation directed at email spam was the Controlling the 
The fi rst national legislation directed at email spam was the Controlling the 
Assault of Non-Solicited Pornography and Marketing Act of 2003. The cumbersome 
Assault of Non-Solicited Pornography and Marketing Act of 2003. The cumbersome 
title created the catchy acronym "CAN-SPAM." The law requires unsolicited email 
title created the catchy acronym "CAN-SPAM." The law requires unsolicited email 
to have a valid return address, to offer a simple opt-out option, and to identify 
to have a valid return address, to offer a simple opt-out option, and to identify 
itself as advertising in the subject line. The CAN-SPAM Act does not appear to have 
itself as advertising in the subject line. The CAN-SPAM Act does not appear to have 
markedly affected the illegal advertising market (Sipior, Ward, and Bonner 2004). 
markedly affected the illegal advertising market (Sipior, Ward, and Bonner 2004). 
One reason is that much of spamming activity was already illegal, including the sale 
One reason is that much of spamming activity was already illegal, including the sale 
of counterfeit goods infringing on trademarks and intellectual property rights, or 
of counterfeit goods infringing on trademarks and intellectual property rights, or 
pharmaceuticals that are illegal to dispense without a prescription in many jurisdic-
pharmaceuticals that are illegal to dispense without a prescription in many jurisdic-
tions (or even to ship across state lines to a consumer with a valid prescription). In 
tions (or even to ship across state lines to a consumer with a valid prescription). In 
addition, jurisdictional boundaries hamper spam prosecutions. A spammer may be 
addition, jurisdictional boundaries hamper spam prosecutions. A spammer may be 
based in Latvia, work for a merchant in Moscow, send spam to the United States 
based in Latvia, work for a merchant in Moscow, send spam to the United States 
from a botnet with zombie computers all over the world, and have the fi nal goods 
from a botnet with zombie computers all over the world, and have the fi nal goods 
shipped from India. Governments around the world have not been willing to strain 
shipped from India. Governments around the world have not been willing to strain 
diplomatic relations with other countries over spammers. 
diplomatic relations with other countries over spammers. 
A different legal tactic has been proposed by Levchenko et al. (2011). Recall that 
A different legal tactic has been proposed by Levchenko et al. (2011). Recall that 
they found a potential choke point for spammers: the small number of banks willing 
they found a potential choke point for spammers: the small number of banks willing 
to process payment for the merchants. American authorities might seek penalties 
to process payment for the merchants. American authorities might seek penalties 
for U.S. banks who transact with spammers in places like Azerbaijan, Latvia, and St. 
for U.S. banks who transact with spammers in places like Azerbaijan, Latvia, and St. 
Kitts &amp; Nevis. Indeed, some of the basis for such legislation could come from the 
Kitts &amp; Nevis. Indeed, some of the basis for such legislation could come from the 
war on drugs, since a fair number of spam purchases are for controlled narcotic 
war on drugs, since a fair number of spam purchases are for controlled narcotic 
substances such as oxycodone. 
substances such as oxycodone. </p>

<p>Economic Policy Proposals 
To correct problems created by a negative externality, the standard solution in 
To correct problems created by a negative externality, the standard solution in 
the economist's toolkit is to levy a Pigouvian tax on the externality-causing activity. 
the economist's toolkit is to levy a Pigouvian tax on the externality-causing activity. </p>

<p>5 Some illegal fax spam continued. Horror stories from recipients are documented at 〈http://www 
.junkfax.org/fax/stories/Kirsch.html⟩. </p>



<p>In the case of spam, the popular economic solution is to require a "postage stamp," 
In the case of spam, the popular economic solution is to require a "postage stamp," 
costing perhaps a tenth of a cent, for delivery of an unsolicited email advertise-
costing perhaps a tenth of a cent, for delivery of an unsolicited email advertise-
ment, and transfer that postage amount to the receiver to compensate them for 
ment, and transfer that postage amount to the receiver to compensate them for 
their attention (for example, Kraut, Morris, Telang, Filer, Cronin, and Sunder 2002; 
their attention (for example, Kraut, Morris, Telang, Filer, Cronin, and Sunder 2002; 
and Bill Gates at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, in January 2004 
and Bill Gates at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Switzerland, in January 2004 
as reported in Jesdanun 2004). However, pricing all email in order to disincentivize 
as reported in Jesdanun 2004). However, pricing all email in order to disincentivize 
the irrelevant material is highly ineffi cient: many legitimate and useful emails, such 
the irrelevant material is highly ineffi cient: many legitimate and useful emails, such 
as fl ight reminders and nonprofi t newsletters, might well cease to exist. 
as fl ight reminders and nonprofi t newsletters, might well cease to exist. 
A related option would be to levy penalties on consumers who purchase 
A related option would be to levy penalties on consumers who purchase 
goods from spammers, on the grounds that every purchase goes a long way toward 
goods from spammers, on the grounds that every purchase goes a long way toward 
increasing the profi tability of spam to U.S. consumers. However, enforcing such 
increasing the profi tability of spam to U.S. consumers. However, enforcing such 
a law would be quite diffi cult without severe restrictions on privacy-like giving 
a law would be quite diffi cult without severe restrictions on privacy-like giving 
government the ability to monitor purchase receipts sent to webmail clients. 
government the ability to monitor purchase receipts sent to webmail clients. 
Instead, economic authors generally prefer the a variant of the Pigouvian tax 
Instead, economic authors generally prefer the a variant of the Pigouvian tax 
called "attention bonds" (Loder, Van Alstyne, and Walsh 2004). The idea is to have 
called "attention bonds" (Loder, Van Alstyne, and Walsh 2004). The idea is to have 
the sender of an email pay the receiver for attention. The sender sends a bond--for 
the sender of an email pay the receiver for attention. The sender sends a bond--for 
example, say fi ve cents--along with each email. When the recipient reads the mail, the 
example, say fi ve cents--along with each email. When the recipient reads the mail, the 
recipient gets the sender's fi ve cents deposited in a bank account (or the recipient 
recipient gets the sender's fi ve cents deposited in a bank account (or the recipient 
can choose to accept the email without payment, returning the money to the sender). 
can choose to accept the email without payment, returning the money to the sender). 
The recipient can also "whitelist" a sender to receive all of future emails from that 
The recipient can also "whitelist" a sender to receive all of future emails from that 
sender, even those with zero posted bond price. This whitelisting option is designed 
sender, even those with zero posted bond price. This whitelisting option is designed 
to avoid penalizing useful automatic emails like newsletters and fl ight-change notifi -
to avoid penalizing useful automatic emails like newsletters and fl ight-change notifi -
cations: solicited (whitelisted) emails have a zero price, which is effi cient given the 
cations: solicited (whitelisted) emails have a zero price, which is effi cient given the 
near-zero cost of transmission, while unsolicited emails have a positive price designed 
near-zero cost of transmission, while unsolicited emails have a positive price designed 
to compensate recipients for the imposition on their attention. Any (non-whitelisted) 
to compensate recipients for the imposition on their attention. Any (non-whitelisted) 
messages without the required bond never reach the recipient's mailbox. Ideally, 
messages without the required bond never reach the recipient's mailbox. Ideally, 
consumers would have the ability to set individual thresholds for the price of their 
consumers would have the ability to set individual thresholds for the price of their 
attention; for example, a high-school student might be willing to look at any unso-
attention; for example, a high-school student might be willing to look at any unso-
licited email whose bond exceeded half a cent, while a busy lawyer might require 
licited email whose bond exceeded half a cent, while a busy lawyer might require 
at least $20. Internalizing the attention externality in this way would give advertisers 
at least $20. Internalizing the attention externality in this way would give advertisers 
incentives to make sure they were targeting their emails only to those consumers most 
incentives to make sure they were targeting their emails only to those consumers most 
likely to be interested in the advertised products, thus increasing economic effi ciency. 
likely to be interested in the advertised products, thus increasing economic effi ciency. 
While we admire the elegance of attention bonds, we wish to sound a note of 
While we admire the elegance of attention bonds, we wish to sound a note of 
caution. No method currently exists to link email accounts with payment mecha-
caution. No method currently exists to link email accounts with payment mecha-
nisms. Should adoption of the attention bond proposal eventually become feasible, 
nisms. Should adoption of the attention bond proposal eventually become feasible, 
how might spammers respond? With attention bonds, a cybercriminal could earn 
how might spammers respond? With attention bonds, a cybercriminal could earn 
the size of the bond per email, say $0.05 (a fi gure often suggested, see for example 
the size of the bond per email, say $0.05 (a fi gure often suggested, see for example 
Van Alstyne 2007), by hijacking a legitimate account and sending mail to his own 
Van Alstyne 2007), by hijacking a legitimate account and sending mail to his own 
account to collect the bond. Account hijacking is already a serious problem, and the 
account to collect the bond. Account hijacking is already a serious problem, and the 
incentives to hijack would increase by at least three orders of magnitude if one could 
incentives to hijack would increase by at least three orders of magnitude if one could 
steal $500 by sending 10,000 emails from a hijacked account. Of course, counter-
steal $500 by sending 10,000 emails from a hijacked account. Of course, counter-
measures could then be taken, but our point is that the attention bond system will 
measures could then be taken, but our point is that the attention bond system will 
surely produce attempts to exploit the new system for profi t. By the time one takes 
surely produce attempts to exploit the new system for profi t. By the time one takes 
into account the transactions costs of setting up an attention bond system, along 
into account the transactions costs of setting up an attention bond system, along </p>

<p>The Economics of Spam 107 </p>

<p>with a much heightened incentive to hijack accounts, the overall welfare effects of 
with a much heightened incentive to hijack accounts, the overall welfare effects of 
such a change are unclear to us. 
such a change are unclear to us. 
There are two key ineffi ciencies at work with the sender-push property right 
There are two key ineffi ciencies at work with the sender-push property right 
of SMTP. This paper has thus far focused on the fi rst: unsolicited email imposes 
of SMTP. This paper has thus far focused on the fi rst: unsolicited email imposes 
an externality on user attention. The second is that spam has arguably created a 
an externality on user attention. The second is that spam has arguably created a 
stigma for legitimate email marketers, destroying potential surplus that could be 
stigma for legitimate email marketers, destroying potential surplus that could be 
created by legitimate players who would, in the absence of such stigma, offer some 
created by legitimate players who would, in the absence of such stigma, offer some 
well-targeted emails to consumers who would mostly appreciate them. This inef-
well-targeted emails to consumers who would mostly appreciate them. This inef-
fi ciency has presented an arbitrage opportunity for middlemen, including "daily 
fi ciency has presented an arbitrage opportunity for middlemen, including "daily 
deal" sites like Groupon and LivingSocial. A daily deal site collects email addresses 
deal" sites like Groupon and LivingSocial. A daily deal site collects email addresses 
via consumers opting in. If the deals turn out not to be of suffi ciently high quality, 
via consumers opting in. If the deals turn out not to be of suffi ciently high quality, 
consumers can easily opt out with a single action (which is much easier than opting 
consumers can easily opt out with a single action (which is much easier than opting 
out of unsolicited emails from hundreds of individual merchants). Merchants reach 
out of unsolicited emails from hundreds of individual merchants). Merchants reach 
consumers through the transmission rights of the middleman, and pay a substantial 
consumers through the transmission rights of the middleman, and pay a substantial 
fee to do so. As of this writing in mid 2012, Groupon's market valuation exceeds 
fee to do so. As of this writing in mid 2012, Groupon's market valuation exceeds 
$5 billion and it has about $1.8 billion in annual revenue, which gives one an idea 
$5 billion and it has about $1.8 billion in annual revenue, which gives one an idea 
of the size of this second ineffi ciency. The other major daily deal site, LivingSocial, 
of the size of this second ineffi ciency. The other major daily deal site, LivingSocial, 
is a private company, so revenue fi gures are not available, but the company controls 
is a private company, so revenue fi gures are not available, but the company controls 
a comparable market share to Groupon. There are many other competitors in 
a comparable market share to Groupon. There are many other competitors in 
this space, ranging from big players such as Google, to local newspapers. We view 
this space, ranging from big players such as Google, to local newspapers. We view 
$5 billion as a reasonable estimate of the daily deal market. 
$5 billion as a reasonable estimate of the daily deal market. 
In contrast to the high-level market-design interventions that have been 
In contrast to the high-level market-design interventions that have been 
proposed, we feel the most promising economic interventions are those that raise 
proposed, we feel the most promising economic interventions are those that raise 
the cost of doing business for the spammers by cutting into their margins and thus 
the cost of doing business for the spammers by cutting into their margins and thus 
making many campaigns unprofi table. As mentioned, one fruitful avenue is to put 
making many campaigns unprofi table. As mentioned, one fruitful avenue is to put 
legal pressure on domestic banks that process payments from foreign banks known 
legal pressure on domestic banks that process payments from foreign banks known 
to act on behalf of spam merchants. This could put downward pressure on conver-
to act on behalf of spam merchants. This could put downward pressure on conver-
sion rates and with them, profi ts. Another proposal comes from our colleague 
sion rates and with them, profi ts. Another proposal comes from our colleague 
Randall Lewis, who imagines "spamming the spammers" by identifying spam emails 
Randall Lewis, who imagines "spamming the spammers" by identifying spam emails 
and placing fake orders on spam-advertised stores. This step would increase the 
and placing fake orders on spam-advertised stores. This step would increase the 
merchants' costs dramatically, as they would fi nd it much more diffi cult to fi ll 
merchants' costs dramatically, as they would fi nd it much more diffi cult to fi ll 
orders, and their banks may raise their fees if they submit many invalid payment 
orders, and their banks may raise their fees if they submit many invalid payment 
authorization requests. Of course, an unintended consequence is that from time to 
authorization requests. Of course, an unintended consequence is that from time to 
time a legitimate merchant will be inundated with bogus product orders. 
time a legitimate merchant will be inundated with bogus product orders. 
Email-spam advertising has evolved over the past 15 years from a handful of 
Email-spam advertising has evolved over the past 15 years from a handful of 
independent spam kings to a well-organized, sophisticated market. The spam supply 
independent spam kings to a well-organized, sophisticated market. The spam supply 
chain includes merchants at the top, affi liate spammers downstream, and a relatively 
chain includes merchants at the top, affi liate spammers downstream, and a relatively 
concentrated market of botnets producing the majority of the spam emails. Nearly 
concentrated market of botnets producing the majority of the spam emails. Nearly 
40 trillion spam emails per year advertise a variety of products, including pharmaceu-
40 trillion spam emails per year advertise a variety of products, including pharmaceu-
ticals, gambling, counterfeit watches, gray-market job opportunities, pornography, 
ticals, gambling, counterfeit watches, gray-market job opportunities, pornography, 
software, and dating services. The costs of spam to consumers outweigh the social 
software, and dating services. The costs of spam to consumers outweigh the social 
benefi ts by an enormous margin, on the order of 100:1. While we admire high-level 
benefi ts by an enormous margin, on the order of 100:1. While we admire high-level 
economic proposals to introduce Pigouvian taxes on spam, our research on the 
economic proposals to introduce Pigouvian taxes on spam, our research on the 
cat-and-mouse games played by spammers leads us to be cautious about the possible 
cat-and-mouse games played by spammers leads us to be cautious about the possible </p>



<p>unintended consequences of these proposals. Instead, we advocate supplementing 
unintended consequences of these proposals. Instead, we advocate supplementing 
current technological anti-spam efforts with lower-level economic interventions at 
current technological anti-spam efforts with lower-level economic interventions at 
key choke points in the spam supply chain, such as legal intervention in payment 
key choke points in the spam supply chain, such as legal intervention in payment 
processing, or even spam-the-spammers tactics. By raising spam merchants' oper-
processing, or even spam-the-spammers tactics. By raising spam merchants' oper-
ating costs, such countermeasures could cause many campaigns no longer to 
ating costs, such countermeasures could cause many campaigns no longer to 
be profi table at the current marginal price of $20-50 per million emails. These 
be profi table at the current marginal price of $20-50 per million emails. These 
proposals are no panacea, but could bring about a signifi cant reduction in spam. 
proposals are no panacea, but could bring about a signifi cant reduction in spam. </p>

<p>■ Both of us completed this work while working at Yahoo! Research. We thank Yahoo! for 
giving us an unprecedented opportunity to pursue research with academic freedom and access 
to corporate data. We are grateful to our former Yahoo! colleagues Carlo Catajan, Raghav 
Jeyeraman, and Gareth Shue for taking time to help us understand the institutional details 
of this market. Anirban Dasgupta, Randall Lewis, Preston McAfee, Kunal Punera, Michael 
Schwarz, and Andy Skrzypacz provided helpful discussions. We thank JEP editors David 
Autor, John List, Chiang-Tai Hsieh, and especially managing editor Timothy Taylor, for 
advice and support in structuring and revising this paper. </p>



<p>Justin M. Rao and David H. Reiley 109 </p>







</text></tei>