<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2F089533002320951064" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs><rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs><rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs><rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs>available in AEA's Econlit and other databases. Each article in every Elsevier journal 
is provided with a citation history (cited by) building up over time, so it is possible 
to see how an article was later cited within the <rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs> journals. 
<rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs> license agreements are individually tailored to the needs of 
participating universities and consortia of libraries. Depending upon the additional 
desired contents and functionalities, there is a maximum surcharge of 15 percent. 
It is becoming clear through such collaborations that Elsevier journals are increas-
ingly used by readers. Thomas Sanville (2001), Executive Director of OhioLINK, 
has recently described their experience over four years with the usage of electronic 
journals. In that article, he provides an independent description of the real-life 
experience of libraries in an electronic consortium for the state of Ohio and, 
supported by facts and figures, probes the value element of electronic resource 
sharing within library consortia. 
As a result of consortial deals and other forms of electronic availability, the 
actual price paid by a library for access to a journal can vary greatly below the 
quoted list price. It is possible to obtain electronic access at large discounts to 
nonsubscribed titles within the economics subject collection. A hypothetical Sci-
enceDirect customer subscribing to 40 economics titles could gain electronic access 
to the remaining 37 economic journals as listed on ͗http://www.economicsdirect. 
com͘ at a discount of as much as 85 percent. 
There are also significant savings in administration and storage for a library 
that licenses <rs type="software">ScienceDirect</rs>. (On average, a library spends less than 30 percent of its 
total budget on journal/book material; over 70 percent goes to staff and the costs 
associated with housing, staff and administering the collection). Moreover, the 
essay does not factor in the significant benefits in convenience and time for faculty 
and students arising from the availability of all Elsevier journals from one electronic 
platform on the basis of IP-domain recognition. No passwords are required. </p>

<p>Prices for Individuals 
The essay suggests that the average subscription price for individuals is $360. 
This is misleading with respect to the Elsevier Science journals, which make up 
seven of the top ten commercial journals on Bergstrom's list. The average personal 
subscription price for the year 2002 for the Elsevier journals referred to is $167. 
Each subscription averages 1,740 pages. Not taken into account are other reduced 
prices such as for members of the European Economic Association receiving the 
European Economic Review (2000 pages) at a cost of $48, various student subscrip-
tion prices and other discount arrangements such as "subscribe by submission" 
options. </p>

<p>Publishing Costs 
The article makes a distinction between first copy costs and marginal subscrib-
ers' costs. However, it ignores the additional costs that arise for electronic versions. 
Today's market requires dual publication of both paper journals and electronic 
delivery, and electronic formats with added functionalities are increasing first copy 
costs significantly. </p>



<p>A key element of the essay is the calculation of the "excessive profits of 
commercial publishers," which comes up with figures that bear no relation to 
reality. Bergstrom bases his calculations of the profits of a commercial journal upon 
the studies of Tenopir and King (2000), which provide an accurate cost model for 
journal publishing. Bergstrom makes the assumption that first copy costs of eco-
nomics journals are $100 per page; nowhere in his article is this choice explained 
or justified. He also applies marginal subscriber costs of $0.02 per subscriber per 
page. 
Let us apply the Tenopir and King model to the journals of the American 
Economic Association for the year 2000, as reported in the May 2001 issue of the 
American Economic Review. Total publication costs quoted in the statement are 
$3,349,000. Cumulative number of pages published in the AER, JEL and JEP is 
4,346. Total number of members/subscribers is 24,448. Using the Tenopir and 
King model (0.02 ϫ 4,346 ϫ 24,448), we arrive at a total marginal costs of 
$2,125,000. The total first copy costs can then be calculated as $3,349,000 Ϫ 
$2,125,000 ϭ $ 1,224,000. On a page basis, this amounts to $1,224,000/4,346 ϭ 
$281 per page. This estimate is probably low, since general organizational expenses 
of the AEA that help to support the journals are not fully allocated to the journals, 
and the AEA can draw on a considerable amount of volunteer time related to the 
production of these journals. 
There have been many studies on first copy costs of the publishing system. The 
figures quoted by both Odlyzko (1995, 1997) and Tenopir and King (1997) give 
$4,000 per article as the median figure, with an upper limit of $8,000. Assuming 
20 pages per article, these estimates would imply first copy costs of $200 to $400 per 
page. Given these figures and our own calculation of the AEA first copy cost as $281 
per page, Bergstrom's choice of $100 per page as an "average" for first copy costs 
appears far too low, which means that his estimates of profits to be earned from 
journal publication are far too high. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
In general, Bergstrom's essay is based on an outdated print-based view of the 
publishing industry. It does not recognize the benefits of desk-top access to a wide 
array of journals from one integrated electronic source, as opposed to readers 
scrambling over a single paper copy in a library reading room. 
Data from the Association of Research Libraries indicate that the index of total 
U.S. research spending as measured in constant U.S. dollars has increased from 100 
in 1976 to 243 in 1995, while average library expenditure increased only to 158. If 
library spending continues to increase at a much slower pace than R&amp;D budgets 
(which drive the volume of articles produced), tensions will continue to exist. It can 
be alleviated by new business models only. As per year-end 2001, worldwide, over 
2,000 academic institutions are using full ScienceDirect functionalities, and this 
number is increasing monthly. Hence, it can be conceivably argued that the 
tailor-made offerings meet the needs of many libraries. 
In the meantime, most of the Elsevier journals and other commercial journals 
mentioned were started at a time when university presses and other "not-for-profit" </p>

<p>Comments 229 </p>

<p>organizations were not prepared to assume the entrepreneurial risks. Elsevier 
recognized an opportunity. In cooperation with editors, it responded to market 
demands from readers and authors and started publishing these journals at its own 
expense and risk. Judging from the authors published, the highly respected edito-
rial boards and the citation levels of the published papers, these Elsevier journals 
serve the economics community exceptionally well. 
It would be peculiar for economists to object to firms earning a profit through 
risk taking and foresight in an industry that has traditionally had relatively low 
barriers to entry. </p>

<p>Joop Dirkmaat 
Publisher, Elsevier Science 
P.O. Box 1991 
1000 BZ Amsterdam, The Netherlands 
͗j.dirkmaat@elsevier.com͘ </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Odlyzko, Andrew. 1995. "Tragic Loss or Good 
Riddance? The Impending Demise of Tradi-
tional Scholarly Journals." International Journal of 
Human-Computer Studies. 42:1, pp. 71-122. 
Odlyzko, Andrew. 1997. "The Economics of 
Electronic Journals." First Monday. August, 2:8. 
Sanville, Thomas J. 2001."A Method Out of the 
Madness: OhioLINK's Collaborative Response to 
the Serials Crisis." Serial. July, 14:2, pp. 163-78. 
Tenopir, Carol and Donald W. King. 1997. </p>

<p>"Trends in Scientific Scholarly Publishing in the 
U.S." Journal of Scholarly Publishing. 48:3, pp. 137-
70. 
Tenopir, Carol and Donald W. King. 2000. 
Towards Electronic Journals: Realities for Scientists, 
Librarians, and Publishers. Washington, D.C.: Spe-
cial Libraries Association. 
Tenopir, Carol and Donald W. King. 2001. 
"Lessons for the Future of Journals." Nature. Oc-
tober 18:413, pp. 672-73. </p>

<p>* 
* 
* </p>

<p>With respect to the "price-gouging" by commercial journals, I agree with 
Theodore C. Bergstrom (Fall 2001, pp. 183-198) that economists should encour-
age their "libraries to cancel these journals and spend the money on something 
more cost-effective." However, I suggest a different alternative, one that he men-
tions in passing but does not include among his "substitution possibilities." With the 
powerful search engines that are available, researchers are often able to come up 
with relevant articles from so extensive a range of journals that most libraries would 
not have the space, much less the funding, to subscribe to them all; the access to 
interlibrary loan has become indispensable. Although interlibrary loan may be 
slower than recovering articles from actual journals in the library, downloading 
them from the Online Computer Library Center (OCLC) on a personal or library </p>



<p>computer does save the effort and expense of manual photocopying. As the 
researcher becomes more experienced with search engines and downloading, he or 
she becomes attuned to the idea of electronic publishing. 
It never occurred to me, until I read Professor Bergstrom's paper, that some 
economists may be "refus[ing] to do free refereeing for any of the overpriced 
journals," which may in part explain why I have had some horrible silences and 
unconscionable waits for decisions from several in his "rogue's gallery of the world's 
most expensive economics journals"-that, and perhaps the malaise of some edi-
tors that he describes under "Defections by Editors and Editorial Boards." Although 
other journals on Professor Bergstrom's lists of commercial publishers, to which I 
have submitted manuscripts, are exceptionally well managed, answer my e-mail 
queries promptly and provide quick decisions, I do think that in general the 
turnaround is quicker with the nonprofit journals. If, by refusing to referee, 
economists are intent on "Punishing Overpriced Journals," they are at the same 
time punishing other economists. 
Professor Bergstrom observes that "the established elite journals tend to prefer 
articles of general interest and to reject more specialized articles, even though they 
may be of great interest to a relatively small group of readers." It makes sense that 
suppliers to "specific subfields of economics" would be monopolists and that social 
welfare might be greater in the presence of those monopolists than it would be in 
their absence. I am able to subscribe, at a reasonable price, to several of the 
commercial journals that Bergstrom lists because I am a member of their sponsor-
ing societies. Those publishers took a chance on these journals when their special-
ized areas seemed more marginal than they turned out to be. In fact, over the years 
that I have subscribed to them, these journals have expanded, one of them from 
four to six issues per year, the other from four to twelve issues per year, which says 
something about the service they are providing in their subfields. 
Commercial journals that fill specialized niches deserve higher prices. It is not 
obvious that "huge rents to owners of commercial journals" are translating into 
excessive current profits, because in one way or another, those profits are likely to 
have been capitalized into fixed costs. However, that may explain why many of the 
commercial journals are continuing to raise their prices to libraries, some by 
15 percent or more a year. I agree with Professor Bergstrom that "price gouging" 
publishers who "have been draining huge amounts of money from university 
budgets" need to be restrained. Economists should support the strategic cancella-
tions by their library of those expensive journals that others in the OCLC consor-
tium prefer to keep. For those who take pride in seeing their articles displayed in 
the libraries they use, and who feel like freeloaders when publishers of their articles 
write them personal letters urging them to pressure their libraries to subscribe, this 
adversarial strategy will be painful. Perhaps it will motivate the commercial journals 
to rely more on their reasonably priced society subscriptions. 
Intensifying the use of interlibrary loan may cause commercial journals to 
increase their prices and even seek to prevent the libraries from disseminating 
their articles electronically. But as hard copies of the journals become more rare 
and their contents less accessible, economists will be increasingly attracted to </p>

<p>Comments 231 </p>

<p>the "innovative and reasonably priced new electronic economics journals" that 
Professor Bergstrom heralds. As electronically published articles become acces-
sible via the search engines and are found to download as easily as convention-
ally printed articles, economists who take pleasure in citing relevant articles and 
who measure their own effectiveness by the number of times their papers are 
cited will become more open to publishing in and citing from the new elec-
tronic journals. Instead of trying to punish the commercial journals, as Profes-
sor Bergstrom urges, economists should be moved by his rhetoric to get past 
their former biases in favor of bound volumes in library stacks and respond to 
calls, that some of us have regrettably ignored, to participate in that next 
revolution in scholarly publishing. The commercial journals helped pave the 
way for that revolution and deserve credit for that, but they can only play a small 
part in what the future has to offer. </p>

<p>Robert E. Kohn, Professor-Emeritus 
Southern Illinois University at Edwardsville 
Edwardsville, Illinois </p>

<p>Response from Theodore Bergstrom </p>

<p>I am grateful to Joop Dirkmaat of Elsevier Science and to Professor Robert 
Kohn for raising some interesting issues that received little attention in my article, 
and I am pleased to have a chance to carry the discussion a little further. </p>

<p>Electronic Access 
Mr. Dirkmaat suggests that my essay is "based on an outdated print-based view 
of the publishing industry" and fails to "recognize the benefits of desk-top access." 
There is no doubt that electronic access is an important breakthrough in delivery 
technology and a great timesaver for scholars. But how have these changes affected 
costs, and how have nonprofit and commercial publishers priced these improved 
products? A year ago, when I wrote my article, several major publications had not 
yet gone on-line, and it was not clear to me that pricing policies had settled into a 
stable configuration. Now, all of the top economics journals have on-line versions, 
and systematic pricing patterns seem to have emerged. Let us have a look at the 
data. 
Almost all of these journals bundle the print edition with a university-wide site 
license allowing any user on campus to access the on-line version. These licenses 
also allow faculty and students to access the journal from their home computers via 
a proxy server. Prices for print and on-line versions of the ten most cited nonprofit 
and ten most cited commercial economics journals are reported in Tables 1 and 2. 
In my article in the Fall 2001 issue, I reported that the average price of an 
institutional subscription in 2001 for the ten most cited nonprofit journals was 
$0.15 per page, while the average price per page for the ten most cited commercial 
journals was $0.82. Tables 1 and 2 show that the picture for subscriptions that </p>



<p>include on-line access is very similar. The average price per page for an institutional 
electronic site license bundled with a paper edition was $0.16 for nonprofit journals 
and $0.96 for commercial journals. 
1 The only exception among the top economics 
journals is Econometrica, which offers on-line access to individual subscribers, but 
does not yet offer an institutional site license. 
Publishers have incurred costs in setting up a system of electronic access and </p>

<p>1 Some journals offer small discounts for subscribers who choose to take only the electronic version. 
Kluwer Publishing adds a 20 percent surcharge for subscribers who take both print and electronic 
versions. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Library Prices of Nonprofit Journals in 2002 for Print and Electronic Versions </p>

<p>Journal Title </p>

<p>Print 
Subscription </p>

<p>On-line Plus 
Print </p>

<p>Price Per Page </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>On-line Plus Print </p>

<p>AEA Journals </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>$150 
$300 
$0.07 
Econometrica 
$267 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Polit Ec 
$207 
$207 
$0.16 
Quarterly J Ec 
$168 
$168 
$0.12 
J Finance 
$250 
$250 
$0.09 
J Consumer Res 
$99 
$99 
$0.19 
Ec Journal </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>$338 
$338 
$0.15 
Rev Ec Studies 
$180 
$180 
$0.22 
Rev Ec Stats 
$180 
$180 
$0.28 
Am J Ag Ec 
$150 
$150 
$0.14 
Average 
$202 
$211 
$0.16 </p>

<p>a Prices are for 2002, page count is for 2001. 
b American Ec Review, J of Ec Perspectives, and J of Ec Literature 
c Economic Journal subscription includes Journal of Econometrics. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Library Prices of Commercial Journals in 2002 for Print and Electronic Versions </p>

<p>Journal Title </p>

<p>Print 
Subscription </p>

<p>On-line Plus 
Print </p>

<p>Price Per Page 
On-line Plus Print </p>

<p>J Financial Economics 
$1522 
$1522 
$0.77 
J Economic Theory 
$2070 
$2070 
$1.04 
J Econometrics 
$2152 
$2152 
$1.08 
J Monetary Ec 
$1427 
$1427 
$1.08 
J Public Ec 
$1647 
$1647 
$1.20 
World Development 
$1649 
$1649 
$0.77 
European Ec Review 
$1225 
$1225 
$0.61 
J Env Ec Mgmt 
$748 
$748 
$1.07 
J Health Ec 
$921 
$921 
$0.81 
Ec Letters 
$1696 
$1696 
$1.13 
Average 
$1506 
$1506 
$0.89 </p>

<p>Note: Page count is for 2001, price for 2002. </p>

<p>Comments 233 </p>

<p>bear recurring costs of converting articles from print to electronic media and of 
administering contracts with electronic subscribers. Moreover, the availability of 
desk-top access through university site licenses is likely to reduce publishers' 
revenue from individual subscriptions. Since nonprofit journals price approxi-
mately at their average cost, we can get a rough estimate of the cost of going on-line 
by looking at library subscription prices of nonprofit journals before and after the 
introduction of electronic access. All of the top-cited nonprofit journals have 
introduced on-line access since 1998. The average per-page price of the top-cited 
nonprofit economics journals (measured in 2002 dollars) rose from $0.10 in 1998 
to about $0.12 in 2002. Thus, for the nonprofit journals, a price increase of about 
2 cents per page has sufficed to pay the costs of going on-line. During the same time 
period, the top-cited commercial journals increased their prices by an average of 
about 10 cents per page, from $0.79 to $0.89. 
Mr. Dirkmaat points out that Elsevier now offers "package deals" to libraries. 
By paying some multiple of its current total expenditure on Elsevier journals, a 
library can subscribe electronically to Elsevier journals that it doesn't currently 
hold. The net price of these additional journals can be substantially lower than 
their list price. With electronic site licenses, commercial publishers, who tradition-
ally charged a uniform institutional price for paper editions, have found ways to 
price discriminate between large and small universities by offering negotiated 
group rates to consortia of smaller libraries. There is reason to be pleased that price 
discrimination will extend access to work published in Elsevier journals beyond the 
largest and richest universities. On the other hand, once commercial journals are 
able to price discriminate, they can relax a significant constraint on prices charged 
to large universities. Price discrimination enables them to raise prices to the largest 
universities without fearing that they will lose the subscriptions of the middle-sized. 
Carl Bergstrom and I (Bergstrom and Bergstrom, 2001) present a theoretical case 
that the introduction of university site licenses by profit-maximizing publishers is 
likely to reduce rather than increase the consumers' surplus of the academic 
community. </p>

<p>Prices for Individuals 
Mr. Dirkmaat suggests that my data on the average price of personal subscrip-
tions is "misleading with respect to the Elsevier Science Journals, which make up 
seven of the top ten commercial journals on Bergstrom's list." (Actually, with recent 
acquisitions, all ten journals on this list are published by Elsevier. The Journal of 
Economic Theory and Journal of Environmental Economics and Management, formerly 
published by Academic Press, now belong to Elsevier, as does World Development, 
formerly published by Pergamon.) But even when we account for discounts to 
members of professional societies, we see from Tables 3 and 4 that, on average, 
personal subscriptions to the top Elsevier journals are more than twice as expensive 
as for the top nonprofit journals. Even more striking is the fact that all of the 
leading nonprofit journals bundle electronic access with print subscriptions at little 
or no extra charge, while only one commercial journal offers electronic access to </p>



<p>individuals. 
2 In addition to providing free online access to individual subscribers, 
all but one of the nonprofit journals give them access to the complete backlist of 
previous volumes (via JSTOR) at little or no extra charge. None of the commercial 
journals includes electronic access to old volumes with private subscriptions. Al-
though it does not sell on-line subscriptions to individuals, Elsevier does allow </p>

<p>2 The exception is the Journal of Environmental Economics and Management, the official organ of the 
Association of Environmental and Resource Economists. According to the AERE newsletter (Kolstad, 
2001), after protracted negotiations, in which the association threatened to found its own journal, the 
publisher agreed to reduce prices to members, to offer individual electronic subscriptions and to triple 
its financial support of the editorial office of JEEM. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Personal Subscriptions for Nonprofit Journals: Paper Editions, On-line Access 
and On-line Back Issues </p>

<p>Journal Title 
Paper 
On-line 
Back Issues </p>

<p>AEA Journals 
$86 
included 
$10 extra 
Econometrica 
$60 
included 
included 
J Polit Ec 
$48 
included 
included 
Quarterly J Ec 
$44 
included 
$50 extra 
J Finance 
$80 
included 
included 
J Consumer Res 
$45 
included 
included 
Ec Journal 
$65 
included 
included 
Rev Ec Studies 
$54 
included 
included 
Rev Ec Stats 
$50 
included 
$50 extra 
Am J Ag Ec 
$90 
included 
n.a. 
Average 
$62 </p>

<p>Table 4 
Personal Subscriptions for Commercial Journals: Paper Editions, On-line Access 
and On-line Back Issues </p>

<p>Journal Title 
Paper 
On-line 
Back Issues </p>

<p>J Financial Economics 
$95 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Economic Theory </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>$1035 ($75) 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Econometrics 
$160 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Monetary Ec 
$95 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Public Ec 
$180 
n.a. 
n.a. 
World Development 
$257 
n.a. 
n.a. 
European Ec Review </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>$74 
n.a. 
n.a. 
J Env Ec Mgmt </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>$449 ($80) 
$105 
n.a. 
J Health Ec 
$85 
n.a. 
n.a. 
Ec Letters 
$300 
n.a. 
n.a. 
Average 
$273 ($140) </p>

<p>a Personal subscription available to members of European Economic Association. 
b The higher prices are those quoted by publisher for individual subscribers. By joining an associated 
society, one can obtain the lower price listed in parentheses. </p>

<p>Comments 235 </p>

<p>nonsubscribers to view web-based articles on a "pay-per-view" basis at a price of $30 
per article. 
Mr. Dirkmaat asks us to notice that members of the European Economic 
Association can receive the European Economic Review at reduced rates. I am sur-
prised that he brings this to our attention. The EER has been the official journal of 
the EEA, but this relationship is about to end. Because of discontent with Elsevier's 
pricing policies, the EEA Council voted unanimously to terminate its agreement 
with Elsevier with effect from January 1, 2003. I expect that the EEA will demon-
strate over the next few months that it is possible to break free from an exploitative 
publishing arrangement and to offer an improved and reasonably priced alterna-
tive. Other professional societies whose journals have been captured by commercial 
publishers will find this a useful lesson. </p>

<p>Publishing Costs 
Mr. Dirkmaat is concerned that my article doesn't explain the basis of my 
estimate of $100 per page for first copy costs of journal articles. Fair enough. Here 
is where it comes from. Tenopir and King (2000, pp. 256 -259) offer detailed 
estimates of first copy costs for journal articles. Their estimate (p. 259) is $130 per 
page (which includes $60 per page for "special graphics," a figure that seemed to 
me high for economics papers). By pestering several economics journal editors and 
their staffs, I obtained rough breakdowns of production costs for a few journals and 
thus estimated marginal, per subscriber costs. For other journals, I had data on total 
costs and the number of subscriptions sold. With this data, I made estimates of first 
copy costs for about 20 journals. While my estimates varied quite widely across 
journals, the median was close to $100. 
Dirkmaat attempts his own estimate of first copy costs, using data from the May 
2001 AER, which reports total publication costs for each of the three AEA journals. 
Based on the assumption that marginal costs are $0.02 per page per subscriber, he 
estimates that the average first copy cost per page is $281. I applaud Dirkmaat's 
efforts to argue from actual data. His method is reasonable in principle, but 
(understandably for someone not familiar with AEA publications) he did not 
realize that the publication expenses reported for the Journal of Economic Literature 
also include the cost of producing EconLit, an electronic bibliography of economic 
literature. EconLit is produced in a separate office from the office that handles the 
JEL articles and book reviews. EconLit is marketed separately from the AEA journals 
and maintains separate accounts. The staff of the JEL provided me with a break-
down of expenditures between the two offices. Of the $1.57 million reported as JEL 
expenses, only about $700,000 are attributable to the articles and book reviews. 
When we apply Dirkmaat's method, but exclude the EconLit costs, the resulting 
estimate of average first copy costs for the three AEA journals is $84 per page. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Since the May issue of the AER reports total publication expenses separately for </p>

<p>3 This calculation accounts for the fact that 500 of the 1,254 pages in the 2001 Journal of Economic 
Literature consist of material, such as annotated book listings, that is prepared in the EconLit office. 
These are excluded from the pages credited to the JEL office in calculating costs per page, but are </p>



<p>each of the three journals, it is possible to estimate their costs separately. If we 
assume marginal costs of $0.02 per page, the estimated per page first copy costs are 
$55 for the AER, $154 for the JEP and $134 for the JEL (with EconLit costs 
excluded). However, because circulation of the AEA journals is so large, these 
estimates are highly sensitive to the assumption made about marginal cost per page. 
For example, if it is assumed that marginal costs are $0.015 per page instead of 
$0.02, the estimated first copy cost for the AER is $177 per page, and the average 
for the three journals is $222. 
Whether first copy costs are $100 or $200 per page, it appears that the leading 
commercial journals are priced far above average cost and enjoy very large profits 
at the expense of the academic community. (Of course, I cannot disprove the 
alternative explanation that large commercial publishers operate much less effi-
ciently than the nonprofits and thus have higher first copy costs and lower profits 
than my calculations suggest.) Consider a journal with 1,700 pages (the average 
number of pages in the journals in Table 2) and 850 institutional subscribers, with 
first copy costs of c per page and marginal costs of $0.02 per page per subscriber. 
Its average cost per subscriber will be given by </p>

<p>AC ϭ c 
1700 
850 
ϩ $0.02 ϫ 1700 ϭ 2c ϩ $34. </p>

<p>Its average costs are $234 per subscriber if c ϭ $100 and $434 if c ϭ $200. The 
average price of journals listed in Table 2 is $1500 per subscriber. At this price, the 
journal's profits per subscriber are $1266 with the low-cost estimate and $1066 with 
the high estimate. </p>

<p>Conclusion 
As Kohn and Dirkmaat point out, most of the current top commercial eco-
nomics journals were founded in the 1970s, at a time when the nonprofit journals 
failed to expand their capacity to match the growth in economic research. The new 
journals served an important purpose, and even in their early years, their publishers 
seem to have been handsomely rewarded with profits. In 1985, the average insti-
tutional price of the commercial journals listed in Table 2 was about $0.30 per page 
(measured in 2002 dollars). There is good evidence that this price was well above 
average cost. Four well-known nonprofit specialty economics journals were founded 
at roughly the same time as the "new" commercial journals: the Journal of Labor 
Economics, Journal of Money, Credit, and Banking, Journal of Human Resources and the 
Journal of Law and Economics. Institutional subscription prices for these four non-
profit journals ranged from $0.09 to $0.12 per page (in 2002 dollars), only about 
one-third the price of the new commercial journals. Since 1985, the large commer-
cial publishers have not been content with prices merely three times those of </p>

<p>included in our calculation of printing and distribution costs. Details of the calculation are available 
from the author. </p>

<p>Comments 237 </p>

<p>comparable nonprofit journals. They have managed to raise their prices per page 
to almost six times the prices of nonprofit journals. Just how far should our gratitude 
extend? 
The profession has fallen into an unfortunate equilibrium in which many able 
authors, editors and referees donate their time and effort to overpriced journals 
that sap resources from the academic community 
4 and severely limit access to 
research by setting prices far above average cost. Several recent developments 
suggest that electronic technology is likely to help us break out of this bad 
equilibrium and to distribute and certify our research papers without monopolistic 
exploitation. In addition to the European Economics Association's departure from 
the Elsevier fold, three distinct electronic journals projects have made encouraging 
headway. Two of these projects got underway in 2001. These are Economic Bulletin, 
which is available on-line for free and is an effective substitute for Elsevier's pricey 
Economic Letters, and the Berkeley Electronic Press series of journals in theoretical 
economics, macroeconomics and economic analysis and politics. The Electronic 
Society for Social Scientists (ELSSS), which plans to introduce a series of low-
priced, high-quality, technologically advanced economics journals, has recently 
acquired the necessary working capital for initiating the first of this series, the 
Review of Economic Theory, and is currently assembling an editorial board. These 
developments suggest that we are well on our way to fulfilling Professor Kohn's 
prophecy that although the commercial journals "helped pave the way for a 
revolution in scholarly publishing, they can only play a small part in what the future 
has to offer." </p>

<p>Theodore C. Bergstrom 
University of California at Santa Barbara 
Santa Barbara, California </p>



<p>4 As my previous paper pointed out, a library that subscribed to all economics journals would spend 
about 90 percent of its budget on commercial journals, though these journals receive only about 
38 percent of all citations. </p>





</text></tei>