<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fcoep.12177" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Eliminating or reducing the federal charitable deduction can have serious impacts 
on the level of charitable donations. Tax price elasticity estimates from a multivari-
ate sample selection model indicate that changing the deduction to a 12% tax credit 
would have reduced individual donations in 2012 by 18.9% if applied to itemizing 
taxpayers and by 10.5% if extended to nonitemizers. Elimination of the deduction 
would have led to a 35% reduction in individual charitable donations. Even if cou-
pled with cuts in marginal tax rates, eliminating the charitable deduction will still 
likely result in substantial reductions given the inelastic income elasticities of chari-
table donations. The estimates justify the ardent opposition of many in the nonprofit 
sector to the more radical proposals for changing the tax treatment of charitable 
contributions. (JEL D34, C34) </p>

<p>The empirical literature on charitable dona-
tions is comprised largely of studies that examine 
total giving (e.g., Andreoni, Gale, and Scholz 
1996; Bakija and Heims 2011; Brown and 
Lankford 1992; Jones 2006; Yörük 2009) and/or 
religious and secular giving (e.g., Brooks 2005; 
Brown and Ferris 2007; Brown and Lankford 
1992; Helms and Thornton 2012; Vaidyanathan, 
Hill, and Smith 2011; Yen and Zampelli 2014). 
The "secular" category combines donations 
across all charitable organizations other than 
churches, mosques, and synagogues. Few stud-
ies disaggregate secular donations by purpose. 
Some exceptions stand out. Brooks (2007) and 
Ottoni-Wilhelm and Hungerman (2007) examine 
both total giving and giving by purpose in the 
United States, focusing on estimates of tax price 
elasticities and their implications for income 
tax policy. 1 Using Canadian data, Hossain and 
Lamb (2012) assess the effects of tax incentives </p>

<p>Zampelli: Professor, School of Business and Economics, The 
Catholic University of America, Washington, DC 20064. 
Phone 202-319-6683, Fax 202-319-4426, E-mail zam-
pelli@cua.edu 
Yen: Senior Economist, STY Health Econometrics, 
Knoxville, TN 37931. 
Phone 865-769-4769, Fax 
865-769-4769, E-mail syen04@gmail.com 
1. Ottoni-Wilhelm (2010) examines charitable donations 
to the needy but does not include a tax price in his model, 
focusing rather on the impact of religious denomination. </p>

<p>on donations across charitable categories. To 
overcome the econometric problems that arise 
when the dependent variable is censored at zero 
for a non-negligible portion of the sample, the 
Tobit model, single-(Tobin 1958) or multiequa-
tion (Amemiya 1974), is normally relied upon. 2 
There are, however, important shortcomings 
with the Tobit parameterization upon which we 
elaborate in the sections below. 
In this article, we use Yen's (2005) multi-
variate sample selection model (MSSM) which 
extends Heckman's (1979) bivariate selection 
model to a three-good system. Like all selection 
models, the procedure allows the binary (selec-
tion) and level outcomes to be determined by sep-
arate stochastic processes and relaxes the Tobit 
parameterization restrictions noted above and 
discussed below. It also allows correlations of the 
error terms among all equations, accommodating 
feedback among all binary and level decisions on 
donations. To the extent that unobserved factors </p>

<p>2. Hossain and Lamb (2012) estimate separate Tobit 
models for donations to religious and international organi-
zations. They use the bivariate selection model to inves-
tigate total donations and donations to health and social 
service organizations. </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>CP&amp;IA: Combined Purpose and International Aid 
MSSM: Multivariate Sample Selection Model 
OPPS: Center on Philanthropy Panel Study 
PSID: Panel Study on Income Dynamics </p>

<p>113 
Contemporary Economic Policy (ISSN 1465-7287) 
Vol. 35, No. 1, January 2017, 113-124 
Online Early publication April 20, 2016 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/coep.12177 
© 2016 Western Economic Association International </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>such as household and institutional character-
istics can affect donation activities jointly, the 
MSSM constitutes an improvement over single 
equation and bivariate models and multiequation 
two-step procedures by enhancing the statistical 
efficiency of the estimates. 
The article is intended as a contribution to 
the literature on charitable giving by purpose 
in the spirit of Brooks (2007) and Hossain and 
Lamb (2012). 3 We develop and estimate a model 
of charitable donations to organizations that 
help people in need, combined purpose and 
international aid (CP&amp;IA) organizations, and 
all other organizations. The primary objective is 
to provide estimated tax price elasticities which 
can be used to predict the impacts of changes 
in the tax treatment of charitable contributions 
on the levels of individual monetary donations 
to charity. 4 For example, how would changing 
the charitable deduction to a 12% tax credit, as 
proposed by the National Commission on Fiscal 
Responsibility and Reform, impact individual 
contributions to charity? 5 The answer to this 
question is of enormous importance to nonprofits 
given that over 70% of all charitable donations 
comes from individuals. 6 
Below in Section II, we detail the short-
comings of the Tobit model and present the 
MSSM. Data and variables are described in 
Section III. Results are presented and discussed 
in Section IV. Section V provides the discussion 
and conclusions. </p>

<p>II. ECONOMETRIC MODEL </p>

<p>A large body of the charitable donation liter-
ature is based on the Tobit model (Tobin 1958). 
The Tobit model is known to be restrictive in 
that any variable which positively (negatively) 
impacts the level of a dependent variable is </p>

<p>3. Ottoni-Wilhelm and Hungerman (2007) estimate 
panel data model using data for households making 
positive charitable contributions. Households with zero 
contributions are excluded, resulting in a great loss 
of information. 
4. Charitable donations to combined purpose and interna-
tional aid organizations are included in the analysis because 
some of these contributions are certainly directed toward the 
poor and needy. We choose to treat them separately since con-
tributions to these types of charities may also be directed to a 
myriad of other purposes. 
5. For a listing of proposals to reform the tax treatment of 
charitable contributions, the reader is referred to the Indepen-
dent Sector (2016). 
6. The National Philanthropic Trust (2016) reported 
that, in 2014, 72% of all donations to charity came 
from individuals. </p>

<p>forced to have a positive (negative) impact on 
the probability of a positive outcome (Lin and 
Schmidt 1984). 7 Further, the relative effects of 
two continuous explanatory variables on the 
probability, conditional mean, and unconditional 
mean of the dependent variable are identical and 
equal to the ratio of the corresponding coeffi-
cients. Such presumptions are questionable in 
the context of charitable donation and, in fact, 
of most empirical applications. Recently, Brooks 
(2007) estimates tax price elasticities across 
six nonprofit subsectors using the log-Tobit 
model, with the logarithmic transformation for 
the dependent variable. Apart from the afore-
mentioned parametric restrictions, an additional 
issue with the log-Tobit model is that maximum-
likelihood estimates are not invariant with respect 
to scaling of the dependent variable. Further, a 
common approximation to the relative marginal 
effects of unconditional level of the dependent 
variable can have a poor property, because 
the unconditional mean of the dependent vari-
able (c) is E(c) = E[exp(log c)] ≥ exp[E(log c)] 
by Jensen's inequality. Using property of the 
truncated log-normal distribution for the error 
term (Johnson, Kotz, and Balakrishnan 1994, 
241), the unconditional mean for the log-Tobit 
model is E(c) = exp(x ′ β + σ 2 /2)Φ(σ + x ′ β/σ), 
where x ′ β is the mean of the latent regression 
function, σ is error standard deviation, and Φ(·) 
is cumulative distribution function of the unit 
normal (see Appendix S2, Supporting Infor-
mation). This suggests that interpreting the 
coefficient of a log-transformed variable (i.e., 
an element of β) as the elasticity based on the 
exponential term of the expression can result in 
substantial error as the remaining (probability) 
term is ignored. We demonstrate the lack of 
invariance of log-Tobit estimates and proper 
calculation of elasticity estimates by estimating 
a log-Tobit model for donation for the needy, 
a category considered in this article. Further 
details of (issues with) the log-Tobit model are 
presented in Appendix S2 and estimation results 
in Table S1. 
When households are not necessarily poten-
tial consumers of the donated goods, the Tobit 
model cannot properly handle zero observa-
tions of the dependent variables. The sample </p>

<p>7. Recent studies by Forbes and Zampelli (2011, 2013) 
provide formal hypothesis tests which demonstrate the gen-
eral superiority of sample selection models, for example, 
Cragg's (1971) "single-hurdle" model and Heckman's (1979) 
bivariate selection model, over Tobit specifications for both 
time and money donations. </p>

<p>ZAMPELLI &amp; YEN: CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE NEEDY </p>



<p>selection model (Heckman 1979) offers a 
richer behavioral explanation and more flexi-
ble parameterization to accommodate the zero 
observations. For this analysis of joint dona-
tion activities, we use the MSSM (Yen 2005), 
which is an extension of Heckman's (1979) 
bivariate sample selection model to the mul-
tivariate case. The outcome for each type of 
contribution (c i ) is governed by a binary sample 
selection rule (observation subscript suppressed 
for brevity) </p>

<p>(1) 
log c i = x 
′ β i + σ i v i if z 
′ α i + u i &gt; 0 </p>

<p>c i = 0 
i f z 
′ α i + u i ≤ 0, </p>

<p>i = 1, 2, 3, </p>

<p>where z and x are vectors of explanatory vari-
ables with conformable parameter vectors α i 
and β i , σ i is a scale parameter, and (u i , v i ) are 
random error terms. In contrast to the Tobit 
model in which one stochastic process deter-
mines both the binary and level outcomes, the 
binary outcome for each good i is governed by 
a sample selection process and level by another. 
The logarithmic transformation of the dependent 
variables also accommodates potential non-
normality and heteroscedasticity of the error 
terms (Yen and Rosinski 2008). Assuming the 
error terms (u 1 , u 2 , u 3 , v 1 , v 2 , v 3 ) are distributed 
as six-dimensional standard normal with zero 
means and a finite correlation matrix, the system 
can be estimated by the method of maximum 
likelihood. The sample likelihood function is 
presented in Yen (2005) but is much simplified 
for a three-good system, which we present in 
Appendix S1. 
The MSSM nests two restricted specifica-
tions: (1) an independent system in which all 
unique error correlations are zeros; (2) a pairwise 
selection system in which only the correlation 
between each selection equation and its corre-
sponding level equation is allowed (Yen 2005). 
Tests against these nested specifications can be 
done with the Wald, likelihood ratio, or Lagrange 
multiplier test. 
Marginal effects of probabilities, conditional 
levels, and unconditional levels allow in-depth 
analysis of the effects of explanatory variables. 
Denote the cumulative distribution function 
of the unit normal as Φ(·) and the correlation 
between the selection and level equations for 
each good as ρ i . Then, for each i, the probability 
of a positive c i and conditional mean (Yen and 
Rosinski 2008, 5) are </p>

<p>(2) 
Pr 
( 
c i &gt; 0 
) 
= ϕ 
( 
z 
′ α i 
) 
, </p>

<p>E 
( 
c i | c i &gt; 0 
) 
= exp 
( 
x 
′ β i + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i ∕2 </p>

<p>) 
(3) </p>

<p>× Φ 
( 
z 
′ α i + ρ i σ i 
) 
∕Φ 
( 
z 
′ α i 
) 
. </p>

<p>Given E(c i ) = Pr (c i &gt; 0)E(c i | c i &gt; 0), the 
unconditional mean of c i is </p>

<p>(4) 
E 
( 
c i 
) 
= exp 
( 
x 
′ β i + σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i ∕2 </p>

<p>) 
Φ 
( 
z 
′ α i + ρ i σ i 
) 
. </p>

<p>This multiplicative relationship also implies 
that the elasticities of probability and conditional 
mean with respect to a variable add up to the elas-
ticity of the unconditional mean. Differentiating 
(differencing) Equations (2)-(4) with respect to 
explanatory variables x and z yields the marginal 
effects of continuous (discrete) explanatory 
variables. Unlike the restrictions imposed by 
Tobit parameterization, these expressions and 
the resulting marginal effects (Yen and Rosinski 
2008, 5) suggest that though the marginal effect 
of a common variable in the selection and level 
equations (say x k = z k with coefficients β ik = α ik ) 
on the probability of positive c i is determined 
exclusively by the coefficients α ik , the marginal 
effects on the conditional and unconditional 
means of c i are functions of both α ik and β ik , 
which can take either sign. This, again, shows the 
advantage of the sample selection parameteriza-
tion over the Tobit. We calculate elasticities with 
respect to tax price, for all observations and aver-
aged over the sample. For statistical inference, 
standard errors of elasticities are calculated by 
a mathematical approximation procedure known 
as the delta method. </p>

<p>III. DATA AND VARIABLE DESCRIPTIONS </p>

<p>Our empirical analysis uses data from the 
2009 Center on Philanthropy Panel Study 
(COPPS) and Panel Study on Income Dynamics 
(PSID). The COPPS is the philanthropy module 
of the PSID and contains data on charitable 
donations by purpose, religious affiliation, and 
a number of important economic, demographic, 
and cultural characteristics for a sample of 8,690 
American families. Additional data are extracted 
from the PSID 2009 family file and merged 
with the COPPS data. Importantly, because the 
PSID has a low-income oversample, all analyses 
are weighted. The weights account for unequal 
sampling probabilities of families in the PSID as 
well as for differential attrition (Gouskova 2007). 
Also noted is that the COPPS data on monetary </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>giving by households which itemize charitable 
contributions are similar to tax return data except 
for the very top of the income distribution. The 
COPPS data have a distinct advantage in exam-
ining the charitable behavior of nonitemizers 
as such data are unavailable from tax returns. 
For more details regarding COPPS and the 
PSID, the reader is referred to Wilhelm (2005, 
2008a, 2008b). 
From the total sample, we dropped house-
holds with a head residing in a foreign country 
(43 observations), for which the respondent was 
not the head or the wife (206) or the philan-
thropy module questions were not asked (6), 
cohabitating (772), or with a separated or unclear 
marital status (367). Additionally, we dropped 
observations with missing values on important 
variables: 342 on educational level, 30 on race, 
12 on life satisfaction, and one on age, all of 
the household head. Finally, 153 "borderline 
itemizer" households (explained below) were 
eliminated. This left us with an estimation sam-
ple of 6,758 households whose marital status is 
married with husband and wife living together, 
single head of household, or single. All variable 
definitions and weighted sample statistics are 
provided in Table 1. 
The dependent variables are donations to 
organizations who help people in need of food, 
shelter, or other basic necessities (needy), to 
CP&amp;IA/peace organizations, and to all other 
charities (all other). These data were taken 
directly or calculated from the COPPS database 
which identifies monetary donations to charita-
ble organizations by purpose. 8 Federal and state 
marginal tax rates are estimated using Internet 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">TAXSIM</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">Version 9</rs>, the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">NBER</rs>'s FORTRAN pro-
gram for calculating liabilities under U.S. federal 
and state income tax laws from individual data. 9 
These rates are estimated presuming zero char-
itable contributions so that they represent "first 
dollar" tax rates. 10 This ameliorates the potential 
endogeneity problem with actual marginal tax 
rates that arises because large donation amounts </p>

<p>8. The all other categories include religious organiza-
tions, health and medical research, education, neighborhood 
and community improvement, youth and family services, the 
arts, the environment, and other organizations. 
9. For a complete description, readers are directed to 
the TAXSIM website at http://users.nber.org/~taxsim/ and 
Feenberg and Coutts (1993). 
10. The term "first dollar" tax rate refers to the tax rate 
that would be applied to the first dollar the individual con-
tributes to charity. Correspondingly, the "first dollar" tax price 
refers to the cost to the individual of the first dollar the indi-
vidual contributes to charity. </p>

<p>may reduce taxable income enough to lower the 
household's marginal tax bracket. The first dollar 
tax price of monetary donations is calculated as 
P = (1 − Iτ) = 1 − I 
[( 
τ f + d s τ s − d f τ s τ f 
(5) </p>

<p>−d s τ s τ f 
) 
∕ 
( 
1 − d f τ s τ f 
)] 
, </p>

<p>where I = 1 for itemizers and 0 otherwise, τ is 
the marginal tax rate, τ f is the marginal fed-
eral tax rate, τ s is the marginal state tax rate, 
d s = 1 if contributions are deductible on the state 
return and 0 otherwise, and d f = 1 if federal taxes 
are deductible on state returns (Bradley, Holden, 
and McClelland 2005). 11 We note, however, that 
even the first dollar tax price can be suscepti-
ble to omitted variables bias due to unobserved 
heterogeneity across states, that is, differences 
across states that are correlated with both tax rates 
and the philanthropic behavior of its citizenry. 
As a precaution, therefore, we include a set of 
state dummy variables to reduce the likelihood of 
such bias. 
The formulation of the tax price in Equation 
(5) presumes that an itemizing household remains 
an itemizing household even in the absence of the 
charitable deduction, that is, that itemization sta-
tus is itself exogenous to charitable giving. For 
borderline itemizers, such is not the case; as with-
out the charitable deduction, they would choose 
the standard deduction, so that their itemization 
status is endogenous to giving. In our sample, 
such borderline itemizers are identified as house-
holds which itemize and make positive monetary 
donations to charity but face a tax price of one. 
Following Clotfelter (1980) and as noted above, 
we exclude these households. 
Similar to Brooks (2007), our measure of 
income is pretax family income. We use this 
broad measure of income because it is likely to 
be much less responsive to variations in marginal 
tax rates (Saez, Slemrod, and Giertz 2012). Both 
tax price and income are included in the natural 
log form. 
Remaining variables are taken directly or 
calculated from the COPPS and/or PSID data </p>

<p>11. Most taxpayers are allowed a choice between the 
itemized deductions and the standard deduction. They can 
itemize their deductions (from a list of allowable items) and 
subtract those itemized deductions (and any applicable per-
sonal exemption deductions) from their adjusted gross income 
to arrive at the taxable income. Alternatively, they can elect 
to subtract the standard deduction for their filing status and 
any applicable personal exemption deduction. In other words, 
the taxpayer may generally deduct the total itemized deduc-
tion amount, or the standard deduction amount, whichever 
is greater. Those choosing the former are "itemizers" while 
those choosing the latter are "non-itemizers." </p>

<p>ZAMPELLI &amp; YEN: CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE NEEDY </p>



<p>TABLE 1 
Variable Definitions and Sample Statistics </p>

<p>Variable 
Definition 
Mean </p>

<p>Dependent variables: annual charitable contribution in dollars, 2008 
Needy 
To the needy 
182.86 
(936.36) 
Among donors (28.54% of sample) 
570.15 
(1585.49) 
CP&amp;IA 
To combined purpose and international/peace orgs 
186.86 
(1016.55) 
Among donors (25.73% of sample) 
648.03 
(1812.78) 
All other 
To all other charities 
1206.15 
(3253.39) 
Among donors (54.92% of sample) 
2002.37 
(3997.40) 
Continuous explanatory variables 
Tax price 
First dollar tax price (defined in text) 
0.89 
(0.14) 
For itemizers (41.4% of sample) 
0.74 
(0.08) 
Income 
Total family income 2008, in $10,000 
7.73 
(12.19) 
Wealth 
Wealth excluding home equity in $10,000 
26.64 
(179.09) 
Home equity 
Home equity in $1,000 
95.55 
(20.41) 
Kids 
Number of children under 18 years of age 
0.55 
(1.01) 
Age young child 
Age of youngest child 
2.17 
(4.45) 
Binary explanatory variables (household head characteristics): yes = 1, no = 0 
No high school 
Did not complete high school (reference) 
0.14 
High school 
Has a high school diploma 
0.31 
Some college 
Completed some college work 
0.24 
College 
Has a college degree 
0.19 
Some grad school 
Has some graduate work or graduate degree 
0.12 
Catholic 
Religion is Catholic 
0.24 
Jewish 
Jewish 
0.03 
Protestant 
Protestant 
0.55 
Other relig. 
Greek/Russian/Eastern Orthodox 
0.00 
No relig. 
Espouses no religion, is agnostic or atheist (reference) 
0.18 
Same relig. 
Has same religion as spouse 
0.35 
Married 
Is married 
0.52 
Working 
Working now 
0.68 
Retired 
Retired 
0.18 
Disabled 
Disabled 
0.04 
Other labor status 
Unemployed, student, homemaker, other (reference) 
0.10 
Work (both) 
Head and wife both work 
0.27 
Retired (both) 
Head and wife both retired 
0.05 
African Amer. 
Race is African American 
0.15 
Hispanic 
Hispanic 
0.07 
Other race 
Neither African American nor Hispanic (reference) 
0.78 
Large metro. 
Resides in large metro area 
0.40 
Small metro. 
Resides in small metro area 
0.34 
Large urban 
Resides in large urban area 
0.07 
Small urban 
Resides in small urban area 
0.15 
Rural 
Resides in completely rural area (reference) 
0.04 
Farm 
Grew up on a farm or in the country 
0.13 
Small town 
Grew up in a small town or suburb 
0.45 
City 
Grew up in a large city 
0.37 
Elsewhere 
Grew up elsewhere 
0.05 
Satisfied 0 
Not satisfied with life at all (reference) 
0.02 
Satisfied 1 
Not very satisfied with life 
0.04 
Satisfied 2 
Somewhat satisfied with life 
0.31 
Satisfied 3 
Very satisfied with life 
0.43 
Satisfied 4 
Completely satisfied with life 
0.20 
Sample size 
6,758 </p>

<p>Notes: Standard deviations in parentheses. All sample statistics are weighted. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>sets and are considered rather standard fare in 
most empirical studies of philanthropic behavior. 
These include wealth measures, homeownership, 
age, gender, race, marital status, labor market 
status, education, religious affiliation, life satis-
faction, and the rural/urban character of place 
of residence. 
Finally, unlike two-step estimation which 
requires exclusion restrictions, that is, explana-
tory variables unique to the selection equations 
and excluded from the levels equations, for 
parameter identification, such restrictions are 
unnecessary for maximum-likelihood estimation 
because the parameters are identified through the 
nonlinearity inherent in the error distributional 
assumptions. However, to avoid relying entirely 
on the distributional assumption for identifi-
cation, we do impose exclusion restrictions. 
Given the limitations of the data, we include in 
the selection equations three binary variables 
indicating whether the household head grew up 
on a farm, in a small city, or in a large city. These 
are intended to capture the effects of the social 
ties, norms, and diversity that are identified with 
the geographic area where the household head 
was raised (Bekkers 2006; Putnam 2000; Steblay 
1987). 12 Use of these instruments is supported 
by statistical tests below. </p>

<p>IV. RESULTS </p>

<p>Weighted maximum-likelihood estimates 
for the instruments and error correlations are 
presented in Table A1 (see Table S1 for all 
estimates). The three instrumental variables 
(farm, small town, and city) are individually 
significant in all selection equations with one 
exception and jointly significant in the selection 
equations for needy (Wald = 7.02, p = .071), 
CP&amp;IA (Wald = 10.26, p = .016), and all other 
(Wald = 8.83, p = .032), with df = 3, rejecting 
the null hypothesis of weak instruments. Based 
on a specification with no exclusion restrictions, 
Wald test results suggest the three variables are 
jointly insignificant in the level equations for 
the needy (Wald = 1.40), CP&amp;IA (Wald = 2.74), 
and all other (Wald = 1.94), all with df = 3 and a 
p &gt; .40, supporting their excludability from the 
level equations. In sum, our test results provide 
evidence of adequate instrumentation. </p>

<p>12. Initially, the exclusion restrictions included the four 
educational variables. Subsequent test result, however, did not 
support their exclusion from the level equations. It is worth 
noting, however, that the tax-price elasticities are found to be 
fairly robust with respect to exclusion restrictions. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Estimated Tax Price Elasticities (Full Sample) </p>

<p>Probability </p>

<p>Conditional 
Level </p>

<p>Unconditional 
Level </p>

<p>Needy 
−1.375 
(0.129)*** </p>

<p>−0.972 
(0.192)*** </p>

<p>−2.347 
(0.235)*** 
CP&amp;IA 
−1.333 
(0.143)*** </p>

<p>−0.091 
(0.185) </p>

<p>−1.423 
(0.227)*** 
All other 
−1.050 
(0.076)*** </p>

<p>−1.671 
(0.147)*** </p>

<p>−2.720 
(0.173)*** </p>

<p>Note: Asymptotic standard errors in parentheses. 
Statistical significance *** at the 1% level. </p>

<p>Individually, 9 of the 15 error correlation 
coefficients are statistically significant at the 
1% level. By Wald tests, the three error corre-
lations (df = 3) are jointly significant among 
the selection equations (Wald = 1153.96) and 
level equations (Wald = 113.58). The two nested 
specifications, the pairwise selection system 
(Wald = 1552.75, df = 12) and independent sys-
tem (Wald = 2466.83, df = 15), are both rejected. 
Lagrange multiplier and likelihood-ratio tests 
produce similar results. These test results, all 
with a p &lt; .0001, support both joint estimation 
and the use of the MSSM over the two nested 
specifications. Finally, using Vuong's (1989) 
non-nested test, the Tobit system (Amemiya 
1974) is rejected in favor of the MSSM (standard 
normal statistic Z = 12.73, p &lt; .0001). As we are 
primarily concerned with tax price elasticities, 
we tabulate and discuss only these results, with 
the remaining marginal effect estimates available 
upon request. 
By the adding-up property of elasticities noted 
above, the price elasticity of each probability 
of a positive donation and of the corresponding 
conditional mean add up to the price elasticity 
of the unconditional mean. The total impact of 
a tax price change on the unconditional mean 
giving level, therefore, derives from two distinct 
sources: the impact on the likelihood of giving, 
or equivalently, on the proportion of households 
that donate and the impact on the amount that 
donors give. 
Table 2 reports the tax price elasticities of 
probabilities, conditional levels, and uncondi-
tional levels for the three donation categories, 
for the full sample. With only one exception, all 
are highly statistically significant. For both needy 
and all other, changes in tax prices precipitate 
changes in both the probability of donating and 
in the amounts that donors give. In contrast, a tax 
price change works largely through its impact on 
the likelihood of giving to CP&amp;IA organizations. </p>

<p>ZAMPELLI &amp; YEN: CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE NEEDY </p>



<p>In all cases, the tax price elasticities of uncon-
ditional levels are statistically greater than unity 
in absolute value, indicating that the charitable 
deduction is fiscally or treasury efficient, that 
is, the foregone tax revenue is more than offset 
by the greater amount of monetary donations to 
charity (Andreoni 2008). 
These estimates are well within historical 
bounds that run from zero to −7.07 as reported 
by Peloza and Steel (2005) in their meta-analysis 
of 69 studies on charitable giving. These bounds, 
however, are specific largely to total charitable 
donations. A more relevant comparison is to tax 
price elasticities of donations to our particular 
categories of charity. In this regard, we can 
compare our estimates only to those reported 
by Brooks (2007). 13 Brooks (2007) reports a 
tax price elasticity of donations to the needy 
of −1.33, statistically indistinguishable from 
minus unity. In contrast, our higher estimate 
of −2.347 strongly supports the alternative 
hypothesis that donation to the needy is tax-price 
elastic (p &lt; .0001). For combined purpose giv-
ing, Brooks estimates a price elasticity of −2.68 
in comparison with our much lower estimate 
of −1.423 for CP&amp;IA donations which, again, 
is significantly greater than unity in absolute 
value (with a one-tail p = .03). 14 For Canada, 
Hossain and Lamb (2012) report price elasticity 
estimates in the range of −0.81 for religious 
donations to −2.25 for donations to international 
organizations. Except for the religious category, 
their price elasticity estimates are statistically 
greater than unity. 
The range of tax price elasticity estimates 
reported in Table 2 (along with those from 
Brooks and Hossain and Lamb) is at the higher 
end of the historical spectrum. Indeed, one might 
suspect that the estimates are unrealistically 
high for a number of reasons. For example, it is 
hypothesized that the response of donations to 
temporary (short-run) tax changes is greater than 
to permanent (long-run) tax changes. If so, then 
tax prices calculated in the year of donation will 
likely contain a large transitory component and 
hence lead to artificially higher price elasticities </p>

<p>13. Ottoni-Wilhelm and Hungerman (2007) estimate tax 
price elasticities for specific categories of donations, none 
of which match ours. Their reported (significant) elasticity 
estimates range from −1.80 to −2.50. 
14. Though Brooks (2007) does not include giving for 
peace and international relief services in the combined pur-
pose category as we do, the difference in definition is unlikely 
to be a major source of the difference in magnitudes as dona-
tions to combined purpose organizations make up about 90% 
of total CP&amp;IA giving. </p>

<p>than estimates calculated over a number of years. 
Similarly, because cross-sectional studies are 
likely to reflect short-term donor responses, they 
are hypothesized to yield higher price elasticities 
than results from panel data analysis. Though 
acknowledging such possibilities, we note that 
the (only) meta-analyses of historical tax price 
elasticity estimates conducted by Peloza and 
Steel (2005) do not support either of these 
claims. Their analysis does suggest, however, 
that our estimates may be higher because of 
the use of survey data rather than tax-filer data. 
Unfortunately, tax-filer data are not conducive 
to investigation of differences among different 
types of cash contributions. 
The policy implication of our tax price elastic-
ity estimates is fairly straightforward. Changing 
the tax treatment of charitable contributions 
can have substantial impacts on the amounts 
contributed. We consider a simple proposal put 
forth by the National Commission on Fiscal 
Responsibility and Reform (Bowles-Simpson 
Commission) empaneled by President Obama 
to change the charitable deduction into a nonre-
fundable tax credit of 12% under two alternative 
scenarios. Scenario 1 maintains current law and 
allows only itemizers to take advantage of the 
credit, while Scenario 2 extends the credit to 
the charitable donations by taxpayers who do 
not itemize deductions. The latter scenario is 
consistent with the Commission's recommen-
dation. Under this proposal, the tax price is 
equal to 0.88, with a one dollar contribution to 
charity costing the tax payer $0.88. As such, 
this exercise can also be viewed as at least a 
partial evaluation of the proposed changes to the 
charitable deduction included in the Tax Reform 
Act of 2014 put forth by former House Ways 
and Means Committee Chairman Representative 
David Camp. Those proposed changes have been 
estimated by Rosenberg et al. (2014) to yield an 
average tax price of $0.88. 15 
For the predictions, we presume that the three 
types of households in our sample-married, 
single with children, and single-map into the 
three tax filing statuses of married filing jointly, 
single head of household, and single. Table 3 </p>

<p>15. We note that our evaluation does not incorporate the 
Bowles-Simpson Commission's accompanying recommen-
dation that the credit apply only to contributions above 2% 
of adjusted gross income. Nor does it account for any other 
changes recommended by Camp's tax reform act. Possible 
macroeconomic effects of these changes are also ignored. The 
evaluation is partial in nature focusing solely on the effects of 
a change in tax price on cash donations to charity. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Tax-Price Elasticities by Itemization and Marital Status </p>

<p>Itemizers 
Nonitemizers </p>

<p>Donation 
Probability </p>

<p>Conditional 
Level </p>

<p>Unconditional 
Level 
Probability </p>

<p>Conditional 
Level </p>

<p>Unconditional 
Level </p>

<p>Married = 1 (n = 1,906) 
Married = 1 (n = 1,794) </p>

<p>Needy 
−0.990 (0.088)*** −0.977 (0.195)*** −1.968 (0.215)*** −1.491 (0.151)*** −0.970 (0.195)*** −2.461 (0.252)*** 
CP&amp;IA 
−0.918 (0.094)*** −0.079 (0.184) 
−0.997 (0.201)*** −1.413 (0.162)*** −0.094 (0.187) 
−1.507 (0.241)*** 
All other 
−0.499 (0.033)*** −1.423 (0.144)*** −1.922 (0.147)*** −1.080 (0.092)*** −1.727 (0.149)*** −2.807 (0.189)*** </p>

<p>Married = 0 &amp; Kids &gt; 0 (n = 126) 
Married = 0 &amp; Kids &gt; 0 (n = 808) </p>

<p>Needy 
−1.233 (0.109)*** −0.973 (0.191)*** −2.207 (0.223)*** −1.829 (0.178)*** −0.966 (0.207)*** −2.795 (0.280)*** 
CP&amp;IA 
−1.237 (0.128)*** −0.090 (0.185) 
−1.328 (0.218)*** −1.827 (0.202)*** −0.102 (0.192) 
−1.928 (0.272)*** 
All other −0.899 (0.061)*** −1.654 (0.146)*** −2.553 (0.163)*** −1.807 (0.139)*** −1.912 (0.152)*** −3.719 (0.229)*** </p>

<p>Married = 0 &amp; Kids = 0 (n = 473) 
Married = 0 &amp; Kids = 0 (n = 1,651) </p>

<p>Needy 
−1.118 (0.094)*** −0.975 (0.191)*** −2.092 (0.215)*** −1.672 (0.161)*** −0.968 (0.201)*** −2.640 (0.263)*** 
CP&amp;IA 
−1.086 (0.107)*** −0.086 (0.183) 
−1.171 (0.205)*** −1.673 (0.183)*** −0.099 (0.190) 
−1.772 (0.257)*** 
All other −0.741 (0.042)*** −1.586 (0.145)*** −2.327 (0.152)*** −1.533 (0.116)*** −1.853 (0.151)*** −3.386 (0.209)*** </p>

<p>Note: Asymptotic standard errors are in parentheses. 
Statistical significance *** at the 1% level. </p>

<p>provides estimated tax price elasticities for each 
of the three types by itemizing status. Note that in 
all cases, the unconditional tax price elasticities 
for all categories are higher for nonitemizers than 
for itemizers. This is consistent with Peloza and 
Steel (2005) whose meta-analysis tests the usual 
claim that tax price elasticities will be higher 
for itemizers than for nonitemizers and finds the 
exact opposite. Such differences are important 
when analyzing policies that propose extending 
the preferential treatment of charitable donations 
to nonitemizing taxpayers. We use sample mean 
tax prices and unconditional contribution levels 
for each household group to calculate changes in 
donations per household. Using data from Table 
1.3 of the 2012 Individual Income Tax Returns 
available from the Internal Revenue Service, we 
multiply the per household donation change by 
the total number of returns filed under each filing 
status to get estimates of the total change in 
donations (in billions of 2012 dollars). 16 For the 
interested reader, details of the calculations are 
provided in the Tables A2-A4. 
For Scenario 1, the reduction in contributions 
is large and comes mostly from the all other 
category. Summing across the donation types, 
the total reduction is estimated to be almost 
$43.3 billion. In 2012, this would have amounted 
to a 18.9% reduction in individual charitable 
contributions and a 13.7% reduction in total </p>

<p>16. Table 1.3 for 2012 can be downloaded at http://www. 
irs.gov/uac/SOI-Tax-Stats-Individual-Income-Tax-Returns-
Publication-1304-(Complete-Report). </p>

<p>charitable contributions. 17 For Scenario 2 which 
extends the credit nonitemizers, the reduction 
is almost $24 billion, amounting to a 10.5% 
reduction in individual contributions and a 7.6% 
reduction in total contributions. 18 The difference 
indicates clearly that the moderating impact of 
extending the credit to nonitemizing taxpayers 
is substantial. Such estimated impacts are far 
larger than those that were and would be pre-
dicted by Congressional Budget Office (CBO) 
(2011), Cordes (2011), and Galle, Colinvaux, and 
Steurle (2012) as these studies assumed a low tax 
price elasticity of −0.5 and a high tax price elas-
ticity of only −1.0. Indeed, using these elasticity 
estimates, we would have predicted reductions 
in individual (total) contributions ranging from 
2.3% to 7.5% (1.7%-5.4%). </p>

<p>V. SUMMARY AND CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>We estimated an MSSM of charitable dona-
tions to organizations that help people in need, 
to CP&amp;IA organizations, and to all other orga-
nizations. The methodology relaxes some of the </p>

<p>17. Giving USA (2013) estimated individual charitable 
contributions of $228.9 billion and total contributions of 
$316.2 billion for 2012. 
18. The substantial change in donations resulting from 
the switch from deduction to credit is contrary to the Canadian 
experience where a change from deduction to credit was 
estimated to have very little impact on charitable donations. 
In Canada, however, as Duff (2001) acknowledges, this was 
to be expected since their two-tier "credit" still depended on 
income as did the previous deduction. </p>

<p>ZAMPELLI &amp; YEN: CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE NEEDY </p>



<p>restrictions of the Tobit model that is often used 
when the dependent variable takes on zero val-
ues for a non-negligible portion of the sample. 
Our primary objective was to provide efficient 
and unrestricted estimates of the tax price elastic-
ities of charitable donations with which we could 
predict the impact of proposed changes in the tax 
treatment of charitable contributions on the level 
of contributions. 
The estimated tax price elasticities all exceed 
one in absolute value and are therefore consis-
tent with the argument that the deductibility of 
charitable contributions is a fiscally efficient 
subsidy, that is, the amount of tax revenue lost 
from the deduction is accompanied by an even 
greater increase in amount of private charitable 
donations (Andreoni 2008). Of course, fiscal 
efficiency is a double-edged sword. Proposals 
prompted primarily by deficit worries regard-
ing elimination of or reduction in the subsidy 
for charitable contributions (Cordes 2011) will 
have serious consequences for charitable dona-
tions with price elasticities exceeding unity. For 
example, we predicted that changing the deduc-
tion to a 12% tax credit would have reduced total 
donations in 2012 by $43.3 billion if applied only 
to itemizing taxpayers and by almost $24 billion 
if extended to nonitemizers. These losses could 
not have been offset fully even in the (highly 
unlikely) case where the government used the 
entire increase in tax revenues to do so. 
Given our price elasticity estimates, complete 
elimination of the deduction, as proposed by the 
Bipartisan Policy Center Panel and Republican 
Presidential Candidate Ben Carson, could have 
serious consequences for monetary donations </p>

<p>to charitable organizations. We estimate that in 
2012, elimination of the deduction, by itself, 
would have led to a 35% reduction in individual 
charitable donations and a 25% reduction in total 
charitable donations. 
Proposals to eliminate the charitable deduc-
tion, however, are often coupled with proposed 
deep cuts in marginal income tax rates. For 
example, the Carson plan calls for elimination of 
the charitable deduction with a flat 15% income 
tax rate. Proponents of such plans argue that 
reductions in charitable donations would be min-
imal at worst, given that the cuts in marginal tax 
rates will raise incomes along with the rate of eco-
nomic growth. Such optimism may be misplaced. 
Specifically, estimates of the income elasticity 
of charitable donations are usually well below 
one. Our (unreported) income elasticity estimates 
range from a low of 0.299 for donations to the 
needy to a high of 0.956 for donations to CP&amp;IA. 
Using our price elasticity estimates, the percent-
age reduction in donations from eliminating the 
charitable deduction range from a low of 35% 
for CP&amp;IA to a high of 85% for the all other 
category. Given the income inelastic nature of 
charitable donations, to offset completely or even 
substantially these reductions would require any 
marginal tax rate reduction to yield percentage 
increases in incomes that are simply not believ-
able. This remains true even with a presumed 
low price elasticity of −0.50. Fundamentally, our 
results provide justification for the ardent oppo-
sition expressed by many in the nonprofit sector 
and philanthropic community to the more radical 
proposals for changing the tax treatment of char-
itable contributions. </p>

<p>APPENDIX 
TABLE A1 
Weighted Maximum-Likelihood Estimates: Coefficients of Instruments and Error Correlations </p>

<p>Selection Equations 
Level Equations </p>

<p>Variable 
Needy 
CP&amp;IA 
All Other 
Needy 
CP&amp;IA </p>

<p>Instruments 
Farm 
−0.129 (0.074)* 
−0.201 (0.078)** 
−0.133 (0.075)* 
Small town 
−0.171 (0.067)** 
−0.156 (0.069)** 
−0.087 (0.069) 
City 
−0.164 (0.068)** 
−0.212 (0.070)*** −0.159 (0.070)** 
Error correlations 
Selection: CP&amp;IA 
0.270 (0.019)*** 
Selection: all other 
0.506 (0.018)*** 
0.387 (0.020)*** 
Level: needy 
0.046 (0.494) 
−0.112 (0.098) 
−0.111 (0.192) 
Level: CP&amp;IA 
−0.073 (0.072) 
−0.110 (0.380) 
−0.116 (0.107) 
0.384 (0.042)*** 
Level: all other 
−0.183 (0.019)*** −0.114 (0.020)*** −0.674 (0.033)*** 0.231 (0.070)*** 0.246 (0.031)*** </p>

<p>Notes: Asymptotic standard errors are in parentheses. All donation amounts, the dependent variables, are expressed in $100. 
Not reported are estimates of common regressors (see Table 1) and state dummy variables. 
Statistical significance *** at the 1% level; ** at the 5% level; * at the 10% level. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>TABLE A2 
Calculation of Changes in Contributions to the Needy from Policy Changes </p>

<p>Tax Price </p>

<p>Tax Price 
with Credit </p>

<p>% tax 
Price </p>

<p>Tax-Price 
Elasticity </p>

<p>% 
Donation </p>

<p>Avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>No. of 
Returns 
Donations </p>

<p>Married 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−1.968 
−37.2 
371 
−138 
25,887,574 
−3.576 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−2.461 
29.5 
83 
25 
27,830,822 
0.682 
Head of household 
Itemizers 
0.75 
0.88 
17.3 
−2.207 
−38.3 
259 
−99 
3,877,508 
−0.384 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−2.795 
33.5 
48 
16 
17,936,676 
0.289 
Single 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−2.092 
−39.6 
319 
−126 
14,635,170 
−1.848 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−2.640 
31.7 
49 
16 
52,020,685 
0.808 
Totals 
Scenario 1 
−5.808 
Scenario 2 
−4.029 </p>

<p>Notes: ΔAvg. donation in dollars; ΔDonations in billions of dollars. Totals may not add up due to rounding. </p>

<p>TABLE A3 
Calculation of Changes in Contributions to CP&amp;IA from Policy Changes </p>

<p>Tax Price </p>

<p>Tax Price 
with Credit </p>

<p>% tax 
Price </p>

<p>Tax-Price 
Elasticity </p>

<p>% 
Donation </p>

<p>Avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>No. of 
Returns 
Donations </p>

<p>Married 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−0.997 
−18.9 
418 
−79 
25,887,574 
−2.041 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−1.507 
18.1 
97 
18 
27,830,822 
0.488 
Head of household 
Itemizers 
0.75 
0.88 
17.3 
−1.328 
−23.0 
319 
−73 
3,877,508 
−0.285 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−1.928 
23.1 
24 
6 
17,936,676 
0.100 
Single 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−1.171 
−22.2 
213 
−47 
14,635,170 
−0.691 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−1.772 
21.3 
49 
10 
52,020,685 
0.542 
Totals 
Scenario 1 
−3.016 
Scenario 2 
−1.887 </p>

<p>Notes: ΔAvg. donation in dollars; ΔDonations in billions of dollars. Totals may not add up due to rounding. </p>

<p>TABLE A4 
Calculation of Changes in Contributions to All Other Charities from Policy Changes </p>

<p>Tax Price </p>

<p>Tax Price 
with Credit </p>

<p>% tax 
Price </p>

<p>Tax-Price 
Elasticity </p>

<p>% 
Donation </p>

<p>Avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>avg. 
Donation </p>

<p>No. of 
Returns 
Donations </p>

<p>Married 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−1.922 
−36.4 
2,608 
−948 
25,887,574 
−24.550 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−2.807 
33.7 
831 
280 
27,830,822 
7.790 
Head of household 
Itemizers 
0.75 
0.88 
17.3 
−2.553 
−44.3 
1,230 
−544 
3,877,508 
−2.111 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−3.719 
44.6 
198 
88 
17,936,676 
1.585 
Single 
Itemizers 
0.74 
0.88 
18.9 
−2.327 
−44.0 
1,209 
−532 
14,635,170 
−7.790 
Nonitemizers 
1.00 
0.88 
−12.0 
−3.386 
40.6 
332 
135 
52,020,685 
7.017 
Totals 
Scenario 1 
−34.450 
Scenario 2 
−18.057 </p>

<p>Notes: ΔAvg. donation in dollars; ΔDonations in billions of dollars. Totals may not add up due to rounding. </p>



<p>ZAMPELLI &amp; YEN: CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTIONS TO THE NEEDY </p>







<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>Yörük, B. "How Responsive Are Charitable Donors to 
Requests to Give?" Journal of Public Economics, 
93(9), 2009, 1111-17. </p>

<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Appendix S1. The sample likelihood function </p>

<p>Appendix S2. Invariance issue and marginal effects for 
the log-Tobit model 
Table S1. Weighted maximum-likelihood estimates of 
sample selection system of charitable giving 
Table S2. Maximum-likelihood estimates of log-Tobit 
model for donation to the needy (partial) </p>

</text></tei>