<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fbf00163432" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Comparing analytical approaches is crucial when important policy decisions of corporations or government agencies 
may be influenced by results that depend on the methodologies certain disciplines customarily use. Technical 
efficiency can be measured by a full-frontier production function model or by linear programming specifications. 
By using these modeling approaches observations pertaining to three lmerboard manufacturing facilities arc classified 
as efficient, inefficient, scale inefficient, and other. However, observations may or may not be consistently classified 
into these four groups when employing the two modeling approaches. In order to validate the efficiency designa-
tions of the two modeling approaches and to determine the uniqueness of observations, a fuzzy K-means cluster-
ing approach that uses a modified hat matrix H* as a similarity or information matrix is employed. This ap-
proach permits observations to be allocated to clusters in a fuzzy way by defining a membership function from 
0 to 1. As the degree of fuzziness increases, a sensitivity analysis with respect to individual observations belong-
ing to some cluster can be evaluated. At the same time, this fuzzy approach assists the analyst to assess the incon-
sistencies that can arise when using the mathematical programming and full-frontier modeling approaches of 
technical efficiency. </p>

<p>Organizations can use a number of criteria to evaluate, control and improve the perfor-
mance of an organization's production processes. Sink [1985], among others, discusses 
seven such criteria: efficiency, productivity, product quality, innovation, quality of work 
life, effectiveness, and profitability. In order to compute or estimate these performance 
criteria various modeling approaches have been proposed in the literature (e.g., Dogramaci 
[ 19811). However, the acceptance of these criteria is in part determined by the consistency 
and accuracy of the results provided by the different modeling approaches. 
Charnes et al. [1988] suggested that checking analytical approaches is crucial when im-
portant policy decisions of corporations or government agencies may be influenced by results 
that depend on the methodologies certain disciplines customarily use. This implies that 
different methodologies can lead to inconsistent conclusions. If agreement of results does </p>

<p>*The refereeing process of this paper was handled through Rolf Fare. The majority of this research work was 
completed when Bill Seaver was at the Department of Management Information Resources, College of Business 
Administration, Western Illinois University, Macomb, IL 61455. </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>not prevail, statistical diagnostic procedures could be used to isolate and confirm the in-
consistent observations. Once these observations are identified, their inconsistencies can 
be in part explained by the specific modeling difficulties that arise when attempting to ac-
curately represent production processes. 
In the spirit of the above concerns, the prime objective of this study is to introduce a 
fuzzy modification of the K-clustering procedure of Gray and Ling [ 19841 in order to clarify 
inconsistent and validate consistent efficiency designations, and to obtain some understand-
ing of the fuzziness associated with belonging to derived efficiency groups. The efficiency 
designations are obtained by using the full-frontier production function (Afriat [1972], 
Greene [1980], Kopp [1981]) and Fare, Grosskopf, and Lovell's [1985] linear programming 
models of technical efficiency when analyzing the efficiency performance of three liner-
board manufacturing facilities (Triantis [1984]). These two modeling approaches are con-
ceptually similar in their representation of technical efficiency. However, they differ in the 
way technical efficiency is estimated or computed. Inconsistent efftciency designations can 
be derived for a variety of reasons such as, the accuracy of the modeling approaches in 
representing the underlying complex production processes, the precision with which the 
data depict the assumed independent input/output measures and the impact of each obser-
vation on the remaining observations during the estimation or computational procedures. 
Triantis [ 19841 in analyzing the efficiency performance of three linerboard manufactur-
ing facilities, identified four groups of observations, i.e., the strongly technically efficient,' 
the strongly technically inefficient? the scale inefficientP and observations that did not belong 
clearly to the three previous groups." These derived groups for the most part corresponded 
closely with the descriptive production information found in the mills' monthly operating 
statements, i.e., observations within each group exhibited efficient or nonefficient behavior 
due to normal or unusual production situations,5 or due to external environmental condi-
tions (see Seaver and Triantis [1989]). It is believed that by identifying the unique produc-
tion characteristics of the various groups of efficient or nonefficient observations, that specific 
improvement programs could be defined so as to facilitate efficiency improvement. 
Subsequently, Seaver and Triantis [1989] used outlier diagnostics, and in specific, the 
external studentized residual, that also identified strongly efficient or inefficient observa-
tions. However, it was observed that a methodology was necessary that would be able to 
identify observations that represented unusual production situations, observations for which 
efficiency designation discrepancies existed and observations that were neither strongly 
technically efficient or inefficient but somewhere between these two extremes. Such an 
approach could then facilitate the evaluation of the derived technical efficiency measures. 
In this study, a fuzzy K-means clustering approach is introduced to evaluate the efficiency 
measures obtained from the full-frontier production frontier and linear programming ap-
proaches and to obtain some understanding of the fuzziness associated with belonging to 
the previously defined efficiency groups. 
Therefore, the intent of this study is to evaluate plant output increasing technical effi-
ciency measures (Fare and Lovell[1978]) for three pulp and linerboard facilities. The financial 
and production data were obtained for a 25-month period during which no technological 
developments were observed so as to avoid confusing technical efficiency and technological 
progress. The input/output data used in this study are given by Seaver and Triantis [ 19891. 
The input/output relationship to be examined by the full-frontier and the linear programming </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>models depicts linerboard production (LPR) as a function of capital (CAP), manufacturing 
labor (LAB), net raw material (NMAT), and energy (ENE) usage. In order to ensure brevity 
of this presentation the results primarily pertaining to one of the three mills will be discussed. 
The full-frontier and the linear programming models estimate the frontier based on which 
observations are isolated as efficient and inefficient, with the efficient observations being 
on the frontier and the inefficient ones being off the frontier. However, given the existence 
of modeling issues such as, correct variable specification and measurement errors and com-
putational difficulties such as collinearity among independent variables, outliers and leverage 
points, it was anticipated that observations would exhibit fuzziness in belonging to any one 
of the previously defined four efficiency groups. As Bellman and Zadeh [ 19701 have noted: 
"By fuzziness, we mean a type of imprecision which is associated with fuzzy sets, that 
is, classes in which there is no sharp transition from membership to nonmembership."6 
As a result, a fuzzy modification of the K-clustering procedure of Gray and Ling [1984] 
that helps detect influential subsets in regression models will be used to compare and evaluate 
the efficiency measures of the full-frontier and linear programming modeling approaches. 
Overall, it is anticipated that there will be even more verification that the full-frontier and 
linear programming model approaches provide similar results in the study of technical effi-
ciency as was noted by &amp;aver and Triantis [ 19891. The focus of this paper is not to compre-
hensively include and test all possible production function specifications and their respective 
estimating techniques nor allthe statistical methodology pertaining to cluster analysis. We 
concentrate on representative models and techniques and discuss our experience. 
In the following section, the terminology and background used in this paper are introduced. 
Section 3 describes the fuzzy K-means methodology and highlights a number of issues 
such as, the choice of H* as the similarity measure, the choice of the specific parameter 
value m that defines the degree of fuzziness associated with observations belonging to specific 
clusters and the reasons for choosing an initial value for the number of clusters. Addi-
tionally, an illustrative example is presented in Section 3.3 to clarify the use of the fuzzy 
K-means clustering technique. The results pertaining to the three linerboard facilities are 
discussed in Section 4. In the final section, conclusions are drawn and methodological 
extensions recommended. </p>

<p>2. Terminology and background </p>

<p>The study of technical efficiency measures evaluated in this paper uses the isoquant (Isoq 
P(Xi))7 and the weak efficient subset Weff P(X")8 of the output correspondence set P(Xi) 
as defined by Fare et al. [1985]. They show how the output increasing Farrell technical </p>

<p>efficiency measure, denoted as F,($, Xi), uses the isoquant subset Isoq P(x") as its refer-
ence set. This output increasing technical efficiency measure F&amp;J', Xi) shows by how </p>

<p>much output yi can be increased when a productive unit uses the input vector X'. The weak 
cone output increasing efficiency measure IV,"@, Xi) uses the constant returns to scale 
technology of P(x") as its reference set and represents by how much output 3 can be in-
creased when a productive unit uses the input vector Xi in a constant returns to scale 
technological environment. Additionally, the weak measure of technical efficiency denoted 
as WO(yi, Xi) uses the weak efficient subset Weff P(X') as its reference set and denotes </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>the maximum amount by which output $ can be increased and still be produced by an 
input vector no larger than Xi. 
Fare et al. [1985] define the linear programming formulations that have been used in 
this study to calculate the weak cone W,"(y", Xi) and the weak IV,@, X') output increas-
ing technical efficiency measures for the ith observation (Seaver and Triantis [1989]).p Scale </p>

<p>inefficiency for the ith observation is given by S,(yi, Xi) = W,k(y', Xi)lWo(yi, Xi). Addi-</p>

<p>tionally, a single equation production function specification of the Cobb-Douglas type and 
the COLS (Afriat [1972], Greene [1980], Kopp [1981]) methodology were used to derive 
the Farrell output increasing full-frontier technical efficiency measures (Seaver and Triantis 
[1989]). 
The empirical results presented in this paper pertain to linerboard manufacturing facilities. 
A brief description of the linerboard technology is given subsequently. For a more detailed 
description, refer to Britt [ 19701. From a papermaker's point of view, paper is an engineering 
structure composed of cellulose fibers. The main source of this fiber is the pulpwood which 
may arrive at the mill in the form of sawdust, logs, wood chips or whole trees. Most of 
this wood fiber must be converted into suitable chip form in order for it to be cooked. 
The chips are subsequently steam-cooked within a chemical solution in a pressure vessel 
or digester. The mills under investigation use the Kraft or alkaline pulping process that 
uses an alkaline solution of caustic soda and sodium sulfide. The products of the cooking 
process are the pulp and blackliquor that contains the original pulping chemicals and the 
dissolved wood substances. Even though the ratio of pulpwood to chemicals present in the 
digester is 4:1, the cost of the chemicals is almost three times that of pulpwood. This 
necessitates the chemical recovery processi 
In order to prepare the pulp for paper processing, refining is undertaken first and subse-
quently chemicals are added to the pulp to alter its chemical properties. Refining is defined 
as the mechanical action or beating of the fiber that increases its flexibility and internal 
bonding capability. Once the pulp has been prepared, it is distributed at a paper machine 
where the pulp is transformed into linerboard. Based on the transformation process of the 
linerboard technology and the availability of the cost accounting data from the mill operating 
statements, the following input/output specification was used by Triantis [ 19841 and Seaver 
and Triantis [ 19891 to estimate the frontier either using the full-frontier production func-
tion or the linear programming models, i.e., </p>

<p>LPR = f(CAP, LAB, NMAT, ENE). 
(1) </p>

<p>LPR represents linerboard production, CAP stands for capital, LAB is manufacturing labor, 
NMAT stands for net raw material usage (primarily chemical and fiber usge) and ENE 
represents energy usage (primarily electricity, steam, fuel oil, gas, and black liquor usage). 
For a comprehensive discussion concerning the definition of these variables refer to Trian-
tis [1984]. </p>

<p>3. Methodology </p>

<p>Observations that are clearly efficient or inefficient are expected to be classified into distinct 
groups. It is this hypothesis that Seaver and Triantis [1989] investigated with regression </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>outlier diagnostics for observation subset sizes, ranging from one to three. While these 
researchers were successful in identifying subsets of only efficient and inefficient observa-
tions, they also found subsets that were mixed with both types of observations. It is very 
likely, as they suggested, that dominant observations in the dataset can mask the true effi-
ciency performance of other observations in a subset. 
Additionally, further support for the methodological approach used in this paper is pro-
vided by examining for example, the output increasing technical efficiency measures of 
mills 1,2, and 3. These measures are given in Table 1 and Tables Al and A2 of Appendix 
A, respectively. These are (a) the full-frontier measures obtained by assuming a Cobb-
Douglas production function form for relation (1) and using corrected ordinary least squares </p>

<p>methodology; (b) the weak; and (c) the scale technical efficiency measures. RI and R2 indi-</p>

<p>cate the ranking of each observation based on the full-frontier and weak technical efficiency 
measures, respectively. </p>

<p>Table 1. Output increasing technical measures for mill 1. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
23 
24 
25 </p>

<p>Full-frontier efficiency 
measure@ </p>

<p>0.942 
0.901 
0.922 
0.901 
0.953 
0.894 
0.920 
0.985 
0.960 
0.891 
0.899 
0.903 
0.961 
0.891 
0.910 
0.901 
0.970 
0.881 
0.986 
0.955 
0.963 
0.968 
1 .ooo 
0.986 
0.953 </p>

<p>e 
w,u', xy 
K+ 
s,u', Xi), </p>

<p>13 
0.980 
20 
0.969 
20 
0.982 
19 
0.971 
14 
1.000 
1 
0.946 
19 
0.940 
24 
0.987 
11 
1 .oOO 
1 
1.000 
22 
1 .oOO 
1 
0.897 
15 
1 .oOo 
1 
1.000 
4 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
9 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
23 
0.916 
25 
0.988 
21 
0.954 
22 
0.990 
17 
0.958 
21 
1.000 
8 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
24 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
16 
0.943 
23 
0.985 
18 
0.991 
17 
0.992 
5 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
25 
1.000 
1 
0.847 
3 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
10 
1.000 
1 
0.999 
7 
1.000 
1 
0.993 
6 
0.989 
18 
0.998 
1 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
2 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
12 
1.000 
1 
0.991 </p>

<p>a These efficiency measures are based on the following standard: LPR = (0.184) X (CAP)0.2s6 X (LAB)o.34o 
x (ENE)0.543 X (NMAT)'.tz9. </p>

<p>bR, is the ranking based on the full-frontier technical efficiency measure using four significant digits. </p>

<p>' W&amp;J', Xi) represents weak output increasing technical efficiency measure. </p>

<p>d R2 is the ranking based on II',@, X') using four significant digits. </p>

<p>e S,($, X') represents the output increasing scale efficiency measure. </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Given these technical efficiency measures, one would be interested in isolating the ex-
tremely efficient and inefficient observations so as to formulate efficiency performance 
improvement strategies. In this case, three measures were used to determine these obser-
vations. More specifically, Table 2 presents the output increasing technical efficiency pro-
file for the three mills. The observations have been classified into five groups according 
to the efficiency performance as designated by the full-frontier, the weak, and the scale 
efficiency measures. An observation was classified as efficient if both the full-frontier and 
weak efficiency measures were greater than or equal to 95 % and inefficient if both measures 
were less than or equal to 92 % . If the difference between the full-frontier and weak effi-
ciency measures were greater than or equal to 0.08, then these observations were classified 
as representing discrepant efficiency performance. For the discrepant observations it was 
difficult to classify an observation either as efficient/inefficient or as an observation be-
tween the two efficiency extremes. If observations did not fall in any of the previous three 
categories, then they were classified as exhibiting neither a strong efficient or inefficient 
behavior. Last, scale inefficient observations were classified as those for which the scale 
efficient performance measure was less than or equal to 97 %. The rules for classifying 
observations could change depending on the type of technology being studied. In this case, 
managers have indicated that they would investigate more than an 8% inefficient perfor-
mance, whereas more than a 95 % performance was considered good. Given this efficiency 
profile, it became apparent that the efficiency performances of mills 1 and 2 were clearer 
than that of mill 3. At this point it became apparent that there was a need to first verify 
this efficiency profile and second if possible, to explain it. </p>

<p>Table 2. Output increasing technical efficiency profile for the three mills. </p>

<p>Mill 1 
Mill 2 
Mill 3 </p>

<p>Efficient observationsa 
5,8,9,13,17,19,20,21,22 
23,24,25 </p>

<p>Inefficient observationsb 
10 </p>

<p>Discrepant 
2,6,7,14,16,18 
observations' </p>

<p>Observations that do 
1e,3d 4' 11' 12' 15' 
f&gt; 
, , 
not exhibit strong 
efficient or inefficient 
behaviorf </p>

<p>Scale inefficient 
1,3,6,18,25 
observation@ </p>

<p>1,6,9,13,16,19,21,22 
1,3,16,21,22 
23,24 </p>

<p>3,12 
9,14,15,17,20 </p>

<p>20 
2,4,5,8,11,19,24,25 </p>

<p>2',4,5,7,8',10,11,14', 
6,7,10e,12,13i,18,23 
15,17,18' </p>

<p>19,22 
7,8,19,22,25 </p>

<p>a Full-frontier output increasing measure (FFJ) 2 0.95 A WJy', Xi) 2 0.95. </p>

<p>bFFoi 5 0.92 A W,cv', Xi) I 0.92. </p>

<p>' WJy', X') -FF; 2 0.08. </p>

<p>d This observation can be interpreted as exhibiting somewhat discrepant behavior according to FFi and W,$, Xi). </p>

<p>e This observation can be interpreted as exhibiting somewhat efficient behavior according to FFi and W&amp;v', X 3. </p>

<p>f The observation is not efficient, inefficient, or discrepant. </p>

<p>gsooi,, X') 5 0.97. </p>

<p>i This observation can be interpreted as exhibiting somewhat inefficient behavior according to FFi and W,G, Xi). </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>3.1. Clustering: stage one </p>

<p>In order to identify efficiency groups, cluster analysis can be used to identify observations 
that merge together on the basis of some natural relationship. The mutually exclusive groups 
called clusters should either have a low variance within each cluster but a high variance 
between clusters or high similarities within a cluster but low similarities between clusters. 
There are many different clustering strategies (Cormacck [1971], Hartigan [1975], F'unj and 
Stewart [1983], Dillow and Goldstein [1984], Seaver and Lee [1987]). However, the essence 
of the methodology for hierarchical clustering schemes is to take p variables on each of 
the n observations, compute an n x rz matrix of distances between each pair of observations 
using the p variables, and to cluster on the distance measure of similarity and dissimilarity 
for n -1 groups down to two groups. However, while there is some initial simplicity when 
using cluster analysis methodology, there are some issues that make its implementation 
less straightforward. These issues include items such as which similarity measure and cluster-
ing algorithm to use, the existence of correlated variables and outliers, the determination 
of the number of clusters, the hard identification of cluster boundaries, and set consistency?' 
(Milligan [1980], Punj and Stewart [1983], Wong and Lane [1983]). 
The K-clustering procedure of Gray and Ling [1984] can be used to detect influential 
subsets in regression. They advocate using the elements (ha) of a modified hat matrix, 
H*, where X is appended with Y such that Q = (XIY) and </p>

<p>H* = Q(Q'Q)-'Q' 
= H + ee'le'e. 
(2) </p>

<p>The matrix H* represents one way of combining the leverage of H1* (Hoaglin and Welsch, 
1978) and the residual information. I3 The matrix H* could be viewed as a type of a distance 
matrix that differs from the usual distance matrix. First, for the usual distance matrix, 
the distance of an observation from itself would be zero. For H*, (h$) represents the dis-
tance from the main mass of points when i = j. The sum of the main diagonal elements 
of H* is equal to the number of the estimated regression coefficients plus one?4 Individual 
values of (h$) 2 (2*[number of the estimated coefficients + l])ln, represent an observa-
tion that is influential (as to its remoteness of distance from the main mass of points) in 
its own right in the (XIY) space. 
Second, large positive or negative (h$) elements for i # j represent distinctly different 
types of influence (in their relationship to one another) as to be shown in Figure 1. They 
indicate a distance from the main mass of data, but more importantly joint influence. Large 
positive or negative values of (h/J for i # j could be highlighted visually, but the large 
number of combinations of submatrices of H* that contain several influential observations 
necessitates the use of the clustering procedures. Gray and Ling [1984] referred to H* as 
a type of similarity matrix. Hadi [1990] did not use this terminology in describing H* 
but labeled it as an information matrix. In the ensuing discussion, H* will be referred to 
as a type of similarity matrix. 
In order to clarify the different types of joint influence, consider Figure 1 with scenarios 
(a), (b), and (c). For scenario (a), the subset of observations indexed by i and j which 
are both on approximately the same line away from the centroid of the observations 
and relatively remote, would have large positive value of (ha). In scenario (b), where </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>*++* 
** 
* 
*** 
** 
* 
**** </p>

<p>**** </p>

<p>*i </p>

<p>** 
*i </p>

<p>x 
(a) </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>*i 
Y" </p>

<p>Y 
*k -K,,, </p>

<p>*I 
*Z 
** * 
*** 
** * 
**** 
* 
** 
* 
** 
ci i </p>

<p>I 
x 
Id </p>

<p>figure 1. Three scenarios of joint influence. </p>

<p>observations indexed by i and j are on opposite sides of the data mass but on a line passing 
through the centroid of the data, the (h$) would have a large negative value. Scenario (c) 
would have several large positive and negative values for the submatrix of H* indexed by 
i, j, k, 2, and m (Gray and Ling [1984]).r5 
Gray and Ling suggested lh$l and --I$ as additional measures of similarity to be ex-
amined. To take into account the off-diagonal information of H or H*, Hadi [1985] sug-
gested the following two measures of similarity:16 </p>

<p>S = (Sij) = eiejhij/I(l -hii)(l -hjj) -$j] 
(3) </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>or </p>

<p>S" = (siTi&gt; = -(l -h$(l -h;) -h;;. 
(4) </p>

<p>However, a rejoinder by Gray and Ling [Hadi, 1985) still supported H* as the better measure 
of similarity. Subsequent research by Hadi [ 19901 suggests that the diagonal elements and 
off-diagonal elements of H* satisfying the following two inequalities, respectively, would 
be aberrant or would constitute influential subsets: </p>

<p>(A$) 2 2 (no. param. est. + 1)/n 
(5) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>where Wi is the mean of ith row or column of H* omitting h$ and v is 2, 2.5, or 3. 
In light of Hadi's recent findings and those of Seaver and Triantis [1989] which found 
that outlier diagnostics for pairs did well in identifying strongly efficient and inefficient 
observations, H* will be the similarity measure used in this research. It needs to be empha-
sized that the similarity measure represented by H* reflects similarity in leverage (outlying-
ness in X) and outliers (outlyingness in y)?' 
With the similarity measure resolved, the Km nearest neighbor (Wang and Lane [1983])'* 
clustering method is used in the first stage to avoid problems associated with set consis-
tency and distribution form. Set consistency is critical since the analyst may not want to 
impose a priori information on the number of efficiency clusters and their respective sizes. 
Generally, the analyst will have no preconceived idea relating to the shape or size of the 
efftciency clusters and would want to be confident that the initialization stage of the clustering 
procedure used will also not have any preconceived automated shapes. For example, some 
clustering procedures always produce clusters of a spherical shape with approximately equal 
number of observations per cluster. The Kth nearest-neighbor approach avoids these two 
problems plus provides some procedures for assessing and testing the number of clusters 
from the sample data (Wang and Schaack [1982]) if needed. 
Since the Kth nearest-neighbor approach uses nonparametric probability density estimates, 
it does not deteriorate in the presence of outliers as some clustering procedures do (Milligan 
[1980]). In general, the analyst will not know if the outliers that impact technical efficiency 
measurement are single observations or subsets of observations. The Kth nearest-neighbor 
approach avoids this dilemma since its computation procedure will not be affected by outliers 
even though this approach highlights them. In addition, the use of a nonparametric prob-
ability density function does not impose any a priori assumptions with respect to the distribu-
tion of technical efficiency. 
The major limitation of the Kth nearest-neighbor approach, as far as this research is 
concerned, is the hard placement or mutually exclusive placement of observations in a 
cluster. In general, it is anticipated that some observations will be obviously efficient or 
inefficient (i.e., hard placement in an efficiency category). However, some observations 
will not necessarily fall into those two extremes. This necessitates a procedure at a subsequent </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>stage that allows for vagueness in belonging to an efficiency category (i.e., a nonhard place-
ment in a cluster). The candidate number of clusters and centroids of each cluster obtained 
from stage one using the Kth nearest-neighbor method are used as inputs to the second 
stage clustering procedure. The fuzzy K-means clustering method, which is the second 
stage, allows the analyst to study the vagueness of belonging to an efficiency cluster for 
each observation (Seaver and Lee [1987]). 
To summarize, the approach used in the first stage entails the following: (a) compute 
H*; (b) perform a Kth nearest-neighbor clustering (Appendix B); and (c) use the number 
of clusters as an input to the second-stage procedure which is the fuzzy K-means approach. </p>

<p>3.2. Fuzzy clustering: stage two </p>

<p>The second stage of the methodology was motivated by several considerations. First, since 
an observation may not be uniquely classified into one of the four hard clusters (efficient, 
inefficient, scale inefficient, and other), a clustering approach that would allow the possibility 
of partial membership in a cluster or clusters was needed. Second, Rousseeuw and van 
Zomeren [ 19901 recently noted that detecting outliers and leverage points in multivariate 
scenarios is very difficult because of a masking effect, i.e., one observation or group of 
observations hides the extremeness of another single observation or group. They specifically 
point out that the H matrix is affected by this masking effect. One would expect that H* 
is also affected. In light of this possibility, a clustering approach that is capable of some 
sensitivity analysis is necessary. Third, since Hadi suggests the use of means for the diagonal 
and off-diagonal elements of H* in order to obtain a clearer visual identification (equation 
(6)), there is a need to use a clustering approach that employs means. Finally, the second 
stage clustering approach, that can avoid the masking effect, be capable of performing a 
sensitivity analysis, uses means and permits partial memberships in clusters, needs to be 
initialized with a first-stage clustering solution such as the Kth nearest-neighbor solution. 
This is the reason for the two-stage clustering approach. 
A generalization of the K-means clustering algorithm (called fuzzy K-means clustering) 
which allocates observations to clusters in a fuzzy way will compensate for these considera-
tions. The fuzzy K-means clustering approach allows construction of a membership fimc-
tion whose (i, g)th elements represent the degree of belonging or grade of membership 
of the ith observation to the gth cluster (Bezdek [ 19811, Kandel [ 19821). This membership 
matrix U is initialized by the first stage solution. In addition, the degree of fuzziness can 
be increased to see if the degree of belonging changes (in the case of this research, if an 
efficient observation stays efficient or moves to an inefficient cluster, or vice versa) or if 
there is some masking effect. 
Letting Z be the IZ x p data matrixi where zi is the ith observation with p dimensions 
and letting U = (u,) be the n x c membership matrix where c is the number of clusters, 
the elements uig must satisfy the following conditions: </p>

<p>uig E K4 11 for every i, g, </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>2 uig = 1 </p>

<p>g=l </p>

<p>for every i, 
(8) </p>

<p>2 uig &gt; 0 </p>

<p>i=l </p>

<p>for every g. 
(9) </p>

<p>The ith row vector of U(uil, ui2, . . . , uiC) represents the memberships of the ith observa-
tion where Uig can be interpreted as the degree of belonging of the ith observation to the 
gth cluster. Grades of membership or degrees of belonging near 1 or 0 represent full mem-
bership and nonmembership in a fuzzy set, respectively. On the other hand, grades of 
membership that are not close to the extremes of 0 and 1 would be candidates for partial 
membership in several clusters. If the restriction, Uis = 1 or 0 is added to equations (7), 
(8), and (9) this results in the usual partitioning of n observations into c hard clusters. 
Let T = (tt, tz, . . ., t,) be the set of prototype value vectors for cluster centers, ini-
tially determined from stage one with the Kth nearest-neighbor clustering approach, and 
let d, be the distance measure for observation Zi from tg. One can define d, as the familiar 
Euclidean distance, i.e., </p>

<p>(jig = d(q, tg) = [(Zi -tg&gt; '(Zi -tN2* 
(10) </p>

<p>Given dig, the degrees of belonging can be computed with the following formulation: </p>

<p>With the computation of the degrees of belonging or grades of membership, there is a re-
estimate of the cluster centroids in a fuzzy way according to the following relationship: </p>

<p>tg = 
2 
(Uig~mZi/~ 
CUiglm9 </p>

<p>15glc. </p>

<p>(12) </p>

<p>i=l 
i=l </p>

<p>Successive computational repetitions of equations (10) through (12) lead to the minimiza-
tion of the following objective function with respect to U and T (Bezdek, 1981): </p>

<p>JW, T) = 2 2 (u,)"+, l&lt;m&lt;oo. </p>

<p>i=l 
g=l </p>

<p>(13) </p>

<p>These successive repetitions continue until the differences between successive member-
ship matrices are less than some preassigned value (in this case 0.01). </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Figure 2 represents the flowchart for the two-stage K-means clustering procedure. One 
begins with the computation of H* and then uses the Kth nearest-neighbor approach to 
obtain the hard membership matrix Ua, the number of clusters and their cluster centers. 
Subsequently, the fuzzifier m is initialized as is the additional membership matrix Ui. The 
outer do loop defines the maximum number *O of iterations the computation of equations 
(lo), (1 l), and (12) can take place which is contingent on the absolute value of the dif-
ference between the two matrices to be greater than some preassigned value.*' The inner 
do loop adjusts the cluster centers (equation (12))) computes the distances from the cluster 
centers (equation (10)) and adjusts the membership matrix (equation (11)). Once the com-
putations have been completed, Dunn's normalized partition coefficient and Dunn's nor-
malized partition entropy are computed. As described subsequently, these partitioning coef-
ficients evaluate the fuzziness of the partitioning. Lastly, the final membership matrix and 
cluster centers are part of the program's output?* 
This algorithmic formulation is the K-means fuzzy clustering procedure which is an 
iterative procedure that minimizes the mth degree of belonging and the squared distances 
from the cluster centers. In equation (13), m is a smoothing constant, sometimes called 
a fuzzifier, that controls the fuzziness of the clusters. If m = 1, relation (13) reduces to 
the hard K-means clustering. As m increases, the degree of individual belongings are fuz-
zier. Dunn [ 19741, Ohashi [1984], and others have suggested the use of m = 2. The pres-
ent authors have looked at values of m = 1.5, 2.0, and 2.5 for this research. Changes in 
m are used to determine the uniqueness of efficient or inefficient observations. However, 
the criterion of looking at different values of m is not to focus on m itself but to enable 
the analyst to observe the movement of observations or the change in the degrees of </p>

<p>Figure 2. Flowchart of the fuzzy K-means clustering algorithm. </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>belonging. Bezdek [1981] comments that no optimal choice for m has emerged for data 
belonging to a certain type of cluster as m increases. Some fuzzy clusterings are going 
to be more fuzzy than others. When each observation has equal membership in all clusters, 
the degree of belonging is l/c. In this case, there is complete fuzziness. However, when 
each observation has a membership of 1 in some cluster (and zero in all others), the clustering 
is entirely hard. Observations that are outliers or leverage points would be expected to belong 
to a group or groups with a high degree of belonging or they would have a very fuzzy 
degree of belonging across groups. Dunn's normalized partition coefficient. </p>

<p>F = c trace [UU 'l/n 
c 
c-l 
' 
0 I F, 5 1, </p>

<p>or Dunn's normalized partition entropy. </p>

<p>EC = 
-c;==, c;+ a&amp;, log&amp;j&amp;J/n 
1 -cln 
for 2 I c 5 n, </p>

<p>(14) </p>

<p>(15) </p>

<p>evaluate this fuzziness and partitioning. Values of F, and EC close to zero reflect very fuzzy 
solutions while values close to 1 are near hard solutions. There are other functions of the 
membership matrix U that can be used to construct a fuzziness index (Bezdek [1981], Kauf-
man and Rousseeuw [1990]). However, there is no justification that would determine the 
optimal number of clusters. The recent paper by Rousseeuw and von Zomeren [ 19901 sug-
gested that the maximum number of clusters of observations to be concerned about is 6 
in a linear model contaminated with outliers and leverage points. In this research, there 
was an examination of the number of clusters in close proximity to 6, taking into account 
the information from the normalized fuzziness indexes. However, the expectation was that 
four classes would be identified, i.e., the efficient, inefficient, scale inefficient, and other. </p>

<p>3.3. A hypothetical example </p>

<p>To illustrate the basics of this two-stage clustering approach, which will group observa-
tions into efficiency clusters and at the same time highlights their degree of belonging to 
other clusters of efficiency or inefficiency, only two variables will be used, a dependent 
variable (the natural logarithm of production, LNPROD) and an independent variable (also 
in natural logarithmic form, LNINDEP)F3 The data for this hypothetical firm is shown 
in Table 3. The matrix Q = (XlY) is a 12x2 matrix for this example. The scatter plot 
in Figure 3 reveals that there would be a very strong linear relationship between LNPROD 
and LNINDEP if it were not for observations 4, 5, 10. 
The matrix H*, given in Table 4 for this hypothetical firm, is found by solving equation 
(2) using the previously defined matrix Q. Utilizing the criterion of Hadi [1990] for the 
main diagonal elements of H* (equation (5) and Table 4), only observation 10 is identified 
as a high leverage point since (hzT) is greater than the value designated by equation (5) </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Table 3. Original data for example. </p>

<p>Observation 
Y(LNPROD) 
X(LNINDEP) </p>

<p>1 
9.806 
5.593 
2 
9.900 
5.697 
3 
9.491 
5.245 
4 
10.580 
5.343 
5 
10.370 
5.380 
6 
9.658 
5.325 
7 
9.497 
5.252 
8 
9.358 
5.098 
9 
9.826 
5.615 
10 
9.443 
6.296 
11 
9.781 
5.461 
12 
10.509 
6.369 </p>

<p>10.6 
. 
4 
. 
12 
10.4 
. 
5 </p>

<p>10.2 </p>

<p>g 
10 </p>

<p>E 
. 
5 
2 
9.8 
:1 </p>

<p>0.9 
' </p>

<p>9.6 
'6 </p>

<p>#7 
3 
9.4 
*lo </p>

<p>'8 </p>

<p>9.2 
5 
5.2 
5.4 
5.6 
5.8 
6 
6.2 
6.4 </p>

<p>LNINDEP </p>

<p>Figure 3. Scatter plot for example. </p>

<p>which is 2(2 + 1)/12 = 0.50. Observations 4 and 5 with diagonal elements (hg) of 0.304 
and 0.209 respectively mask the influence of each other since each is less than 0.50 as 
found by equation (5). 
This masking effect is evident as the off-diagonal elements of H* are inspected. The 
largest off-diagonal elements h$ are 0.322 (for observations 10 and 12), 0.250 (for obser-
vations 4 and 5), -0.242 (for observations 4 and lo), and -0.162 (for observations 5 
and 10). Using equation (6)) only the pair [4,5] would not be found to be influential because 
of the masking effect created by observation 10. The h$ value for observations 10 and 12 
is similar to Figure la as is that for the pair of observations 4 and 5. On the other hand, </p>

<p>EVALUATING </p>

<p>TECHNICAL 
EFFICIENCY 
MEASURES 
IN MANUFACTURING </p>

<p>Table 4. H* for example*. </p>

<p>351 </p>

<p>Observation 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 </p>

<p>1 
.085 
.088 
,076 
,066 
2 
.092 
.074 
.050 
3 
,083 
.121 
4 
.304 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 </p>

<p>.070 
,077 
.076 
,058 
,074 
,074 
,110 
,085 
,083 
,250 
,127 
.119 
.209 
.115 
,109 
.087 
.085 
.083 </p>

<p>.072 
,068 
,086 
.144 
,127 
,089 
,086 
.092 </p>

<p>.085 
.088 
,076 
,063 
,066 
,076 
,076 
,071 
.086 </p>

<p>,115 
,043 
,022 
-.242 
-.162 
,016 
.024 
-.017 
,121 
,593 </p>

<p>,080 
,080 
.082 
,106 
.lOO 
.084 
.082 
,083 
,080 
.053 
,083 </p>

<p>.105 
,118 
,061 
-.055 
-.019 
,059 
,061 
,042 
108 
,322 
,076 
,203 </p>

<p>'Since matrix H* is symmetrical, 
only the upper triangular portion is shown. In addition, only 3 significant 
digits are shown but at least 10 were used in the computations. </p>

<p>the pair [5, lo] as well as the pair [4, lo] are on opposite sides of the data mass and have 
large negative h$ values as in Figure lb. Hadi's rules of thumb that find influential pairs 
are suitable, but a clustering approach is necessary to capture the essence of joint influence 
for any combination of observations. 
The Kth nearest-neighbor initialization stage determined three modal clusters: (4, 5)) 
(8, 3, 7,6, ll}, and {1,9,2, 10, 12). For this example, one would not necessarily find 
this clustering solution intuitively acceptable. However, this solution is found using a hard 
placement criterion. Therefore it is necessary to use an approach that allows observations 
to belong to clusters in a fuzzy way. 
Table 6 shows the K-means fuzzy clustering results using m = 2 for eight to three clusters. 
The initial and final membership matrix for the three clusters after 11 iterations of equa-
tions (10) through (12) is shown in Table 5. It is important to note in Table 5 that the three 
cluster solution is different than the initial Kih nearest-neighbor clustering results. The three 
fuzzy K-means clusters are {4, 5)) (1, 2, 3, 6, 7, 8, 9, 1 l}, { 10, 12). However, in the 
cluster of observations (10, 12)) observation 12 also has a strong belonging to cluster 1, 
the major cluster that shows a linear relationship between y and x. This three cluster fuzzy 
solution is viable given the scatter plot of Figure 3. 
Dunn's normalized partition coefficient is highest (i.e., closest to hard partitions) at six 
clusters and lowest at three and four clusters (i.e., more fuzzy). The normalized partition 
entropy coefficient is fuzzier for five and six clusters. As the number of clusters increaases 
above 5 and 6 for Dunn's normalized partition coefficient and the normalized partition en-
tropy coefficient respectively, the solutions in Table 6 suggest a harder placement of obser-
vations. This is to be generally expected as the number of clusters increases. However, 
for efficiency evaluation purposes, as suggested by this research, one would look for the 
number of clusters to be 6 or less. 
In terms of efficiency, observations 4 and 5 would be efficient and observation 10 very 
inefficient. The uniqueness of these two subsets could have been found from the three-, </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Table 5. Degree of belonging matrices for initial and final iterations for three clusters using the fuzzy K-means 
clustering procedure. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
I 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0 
1 
0 
0 
1 
1 
1 
0 
0 
1 
0 </p>

<p>UInitial </p>

<p>Cluster </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
1 
0 
1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
1 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>.97 
.92 
.96 
.02 
.02 
.94 
.96 
.83 
.96 
.Ol 
1.0 
.39 </p>

<p>UFinal </p>

<p>Cluster </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>.Ol 
.04 
.Ol 
.oo 
.oo 
.Ol 
.Ol 
.02 
.02 
.98 
.oo 
.52 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>.02 
.04 
.03 
.98 
.98 
.OS 
.03 
.15 
.02 
.Ol 
.oo 
.09 </p>

<p>Table 6. Highest degree of belonging for different number of clusters. </p>

<p>Number of clustersa </p>

<p>Observation 
Eight 
Seven 
Six 
Five 
Four 
Three </p>

<p>1 
.95(2) 
.97(2) 
.98(2) 
.99(2) 
.88(2) 
.97(l) 
2 
.93(2) 
.95(Z) 
.97(2) 
.97(2) 
l.OO(2) 
.92(l) 
3 
.90(l) 
.96(l) 
.99(l) 
.99(l) 
1.00(l) 
.96(l) 
4 
.99(5) 
.99(4) 
.99(3) 
.96(3) 
.97(3) 
.98(3) 
5 
.99(6) 
.99(5) 
.99(4) 
.92(3) 
.94(3) 
.98(3) 
6 
.91(l) 
.84(l) 
.99(l) 
.99(l) 
1.00(l) 
.94(l) 
7 
.90(l) 
.96(l) 
.99(l) 
.99(l) 
1.00(l) 
.96(l) 
8 
.95(4) 
.97(3) 
.87(l) 
.90(l) 
.91(l) 
.83(l) 
9 
.98(2) 
.99(2) 
.99(2) 
.99(2) 
.92(2) 
.96(l) 
10 
1.00(8) 
1.00(7) 
l.OO(6) 
1.00(5) 
l.OO(4) 
.98(2) 
11 
.93(3) 
.79(l) 
.81(l) 
.81(l) 
.90(l) 
1.00(l) 
12 
l.OO(7) 
l.OO(6) 
l.OO(5) 
l.OO(4) 
.54(2)b 
.52(Z)' </p>

<p>Dunn's normalized 
partition coefficient 
,893 
,896 
,923 
,910 
,828 
,805 
Normalized 
partiton entropy 
,699 
,490 
,308 
,291 
,399 
,351 </p>

<p>aCluster to which an observation has the highest degree of belonging is shown in parentheses. </p>

<p>bOther degrees of belonging are 0.22(4), 0.18(l), and 0.06(3). </p>

<p>'Other degrees of belonging are 0.39(l) and 0.09(3). </p>

<p>EVALUATING </p>

<p>TECHNICAL 
EFFICIENCY 
MEASURES 
IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>four-, five-, or six-cluster scenarios (see Table 6), especially for larger values of m. In 
the four cluster groupings, observation 12 has a mixed degree of belonging, i.e., to the 
cluster of observations { 1, 2, 9, 12) and cluster of observation {lo}, but that is what 
would be anticipated with the K-means fuzzy clustering approach. Finally, it needs to be 
clarified that the fuzzy clustering results by themselves do not identify whether a subset 
contains efficient, inefficient, discrepant, unique observations in terms of their produc-
tion characteristics or observations that do not exhibit strong efficient or inefficient behavior. 
However, it is anticipated that observations do group in a natural way according to these 
efficiency subset designations. The K-means fuzzy clustering approach identifies these 
efficiency subsets in a fuzzy way. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>The Kth nearest-neighbor clustering methodz4 determined five modal clusters: (2, 7, 11, 
16}, (6, 18, 17}, {l, 8, 13}, {3,4, 5,9, 10, 12, 15,25}, (14, 19,20, 21,22,23,24}. 
This initial solution was obtained for K = 2, using (/z$)*~ as the similarity measure and 
applying the diagnostic procedures of Wong and Schaack [1982]. This was not much dif-
ferent than the minimum expected number of clusters, 4. This initial Kth nearest-neighbor 
solution was used as an input to the fuzzy K-means clustering analysis for which the number 
of clusters was varied from 5 to 12. However, the results for the smallest but most stable 
number of clusters, 9, will be shown and explained for mill 1. 
The K-means fuzzy clustering algorithm with m = 1.5,2.0, and 2.5 generated the degrees 
of belonging shown in Table 7 for the nine clusters. The observations for which the degree 
of belonging varied considerably as the fuzziness increased from 1.5 to 2.5 are highlighted. 
The most noteworthy changes occurred for observations 19 and 21 for which the highest 
degree of belonging was associated with cluster 2 for m = 2.0 and 2.5. 
For mill 1 there are five clusters of subset size 3 or greater. In cluster 1, observations 
10, 12, 4, 15 have a strong degree of belonging for this cluster when m = 1.50 and are 
inefficient or somewhat inefficient observations according to Table 2. As m increases, the 
second highest degree of belonging is associated with cluster 4 for observations 10, 12, 
and 4. Cluster 4 contains an inefficient observation 11 and two discrepant observations, 
i.e., 2 and 16 for m = 1.50. Additionally, it is interesting to note that the second highest 
degree of belonging when m = 2.00 and m = 2.50 is for cluster 1 for all observations 
of cluster 4. This indicates that the discrepant observations 2 and 16 exhibit more ineffi-
cient than efficient behavior. This is confirmed from the efficiency results of Table 1. 
Cluster 3 comprises efficient observations for m = 1.50. As the degree of fuzziness 
increases, all observations in this cluster move toward cluster 2 which consists of one 
efficient (observation 9) and one discrepant (observation 7) observation. Additionally, obser-
vation 9 of cluster 2 has a highest and second highest degree of belonging for clusters 
5 and 3 respectively when m = 2.0 and 2.5. Cluster 5 also comprises two efficient and 
one almost discrepant observations. The point to be made is that efficient observations 
move toward other efficient observations as indicated by the shifts in degree of belonging 
as m increases. </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.F'. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Table % Fuzzy K-means clustering for mill 1. </p>

<p>Cluster 
Observations </p>

<p>M = 1.50 </p>

<p>Second 
Highest 
HighesP </p>

<p>M = 2.00 </p>

<p>Second 
Highest= 
Highesta </p>

<p>M = 2.50 </p>

<p>Seconda 
Highesta 
Highest </p>

<p>4i* </p>

<p>.90 
-
.58 
.20(4) 
.39 
.24(4) 
10' 
.99 
.83 
.05(4) 
.57 
.11(4) 
12i* 
1.00 
.94 
.02(4,5) 
.84 
.04(4) 
15i* 
.82 
-
.33 
.27(5) 
.50(5) 
.24 
7d 
1.00 
-
.23(4) 
.18(5) 
.18(4) 
.16(5) 
9e 
.27 
.20(3) 
.34(5) 
.19(3) 
.27(5) 
.16(3) 
19e 
.98 
-
.82(2) 
.lO 
.63(2) 
.14 
20e 
.72 
.13(4) 
.38 
.18(2) 
.31 
.16(2) 
21e 
.96 
.83(2) 
.09 
.57(2) 
.16 
22e 
1.00 
-
.88 
.08(2) 
.91 </p>

<p>J4c-9 </p>

<p>23e 
.98 
-
.50 
.28(2) 
.31 
.26(2) 
24e 
.99 
-
.71 
.17(2) 
.41 
.24(2) 
2d 
.99 
-
.82 
.07(l) 
.55 
.12(l) 
11i* 
.95 
.82 
.09(l) 
.78 
.07(l) 
16d 
.95 
-
.59 
.10(l) 
.34 
.13(l) 
3d*,s 
.96 
.03(l) 
.51 
.16(l) 
.28 
.18(l) </p>

<p>5e 
.65 
.17(3) 
.81 
.07(3) 
.86 
.04(3) 
25e,S 
.93 
.02(l) 
.29 
.13(1,2,3,7) 
.21 
.13(1,2,3) 
1e*,s 
.85 
.05(l) 
.43 
.13(l) 
.27 
.14(l) 
ge 
.98 
-
.88 
-
.92 
-</p>

<p>13e 
.95 
-
.52 
.08(l) 
.29 
.10(1,4) </p>

<p>6d,S </p>

<p>.94 
.02(l) 
.32 
.14(l) 
.21 
.14(l) 
lgdaS 
.96 
-
.96 
-
.96 
-
14d 
1.00 
-
1.00 
-
.98 
-</p>

<p>17e 
1.00 
-
1.00 
.98 </p>

<p>a The cluster other than the one indicated by the left-hand column of the Table is noted in parentheses. </p>

<p>d Discrepant observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>d* This observation exhibits somewhat discrepant behavior according to Table 2. </p>

<p>e Efficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>e* This observation exhibits somewhat efficient behavior according to Table 2. </p>

<p>i Inefficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>i* This observation exhibits somewhat inefficient behavior as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>' Scale inefficient observation. </p>

<p>Cluster 6 is comprised of efficient and mostly efficient observations 1, 8, and 13. Cluster 
7 has identified two discrepant and scale inefficient observations 6 and 18. As the degree 
of fuzziness increases, observation 6 has the second highest degree of belonging for cluster 
1. Interestingly, according to the full-frontier efficiency measure, observation 6 does ex-
hibit inefficient behavior. 
Cluster 9 contains observation 17 that is classified as an efficient observation by all 
measures. However, it has no degree of belonging to cluster 3. Seaver and Triantis [1989] </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>noted that this is an unusual observtion where the mill experienced 82% idle time due 
to a lack of orders. Thus, while this observation is exhibiting efficient behavior, it is very 
different from the remainder of the data set. The fuzzy K-means clustering approach iden-
tified this uniqueness. 
Finally, discrepant observations as indicated by Table 2 are found in clusters 2, 4, 7, 
8. It is noteworthy that observations 14, 6, and 18 which have been isolated as belonging 
to clusters 7 and 8, represent situations during which the mill exhibited unusual production 
situations. For observations 6 and 18, the mill was idle 63 % and 65 % of the time respec-
tively. Whereas, for observation 14, bad weather conditions led to increased fiber losses 
and excess energy usage. The question that remains unanswered is, given the external con-
ditions represented by the mill idle time and the bad weather conditions, did the mill operate 
efficiently or inefficiently? The answer to this question can be found by visiting with the 
production managers and production workers who can subsequently disclose more infor-
mation about the specifics of the production situation during these months. An additional 
yet relevant question that needs to be addressed is, if these observations represent a dif-
ferent type of production scenario and therefore should not be compared with the remainder 
of the data set. It is encouraging however, that the K-means clustering approach was able 
to identify these observations. 
These results suggest the following general observations. First, the fuzzy K-means cluster-
ing analysis provides confirmation of the efficiency results of Tables 1 and 2. Thus, it enables 
the analyst to isolate the observations that are strongly efficient or inefficient and those 
that are between the two extremes. From a managerial perspective this finding allows 
managers to define their efficiency improvement strategies on the observations that exhibited 
strongly inefficient behavior. From a conceptual perspective, this finding suggests that ef-
ficiency performance should not be viewed as discrete but as fluctuating over a some type 
of continuum. Second, the two approaches used to study efficiency in this research are 
indeed very similar in their representation of efficiency. However, discrepant observations 
in terms of efficiency designations can be found. For some of these discrepant observa-
tions, their efficiency tendencies can be found as the degree of fuzziness is varied. Third, 
the fuzzy K-means clustering approach isolates observations that represent unique produc-
tion characteristics and scale inefficient behavior. 
These observations are consistent with the results that were obtained for the other two 
mills as indicated by Tables 8 and 9. For mill 2, cluster 3 represents inefficient or somewhat 
inefficient behavior, whereas clusters 5 and 6 efficient behavior. Cluster 7 isolates the unusual 
observation 20. For this observation, the mill was idle 90% of the time. This is consistent 
with the findings reported by Seaver and Triantis [ 19891 using multiple outlier diagnostics. 
In addition for mill 2, as the fuzziness increases, there is movement of nondominant 
observation+ to the clusters with similar efficiency characteristics (e.g., observations 6 and 
9 in cluster 1 to the efficient cluster 5 or observation 14 in cluster 2 to the inefficient cluster 
3 as shown in Table 8). 
On the other hand, for mill 3 it is expected from the efficiency profile of Table 2, that 
the clustering results would be less clear. This is confirmed by Table 9. For example, cluster 
3 comprises three types of observations, i.e., efficient (observations 3,21), discrepant (obser-
vations 11,24), and observations that do not exhibit strong efficient or inefficient behavior 
(observation 12). Additionally, cluster 5 is comprised of inefficient observations (9, 14, </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Table 8. Fuzzy K-means clustering for mill 2. </p>

<p>Cluster 
Observations </p>

<p>M = 1.50 </p>

<p>Second 
Highest 
Highesta </p>

<p>M = 2.00 </p>

<p>Second 
Highesta 
High&amp;' </p>

<p>M = 2.50 </p>

<p>Second 
Highesta 
Highesta </p>

<p>1 
4 
.99 
.92 
.04(3) 
.67 
.12(3) 
5 
.87 
lO(3) 
.81 
lO(3) 
.70 
.12(3) 
6e 
.65 
.11(4) 
.29 
.20(5) 
.22 
.19(5) 
1 
7 
.91 
.07(3) 
.82 
.09(3) 
.67 
.13(3) 
9e 
.96 
.02(5) 
.51 
.14(5) 
.32 
.17(5) 
I 
2 
141* 
.89 
.09(3j 
.39 
.20&lt;3j 
.28 
i9i3j 
17 
.96 
.02(5) 
.94 
.02(5) 
.91 
.03(5) 
18'* 
.98 
.87 
.04(5) 
.62 
lO(5) </p>

<p>2i* </p>

<p>.95 
.03(2) 
.59 
.12(1,2) 
.38 
.17(l) 
3' 
.97 
.02(l) 
.75 
.13(l) 
.56 
.18(l) </p>

<p>*i* </p>

<p>.34 
.30(2) 
.23 
.2 l(2) 
.20 
.19(l) 
12' </p>

<p>1 
.99 
-
.87 
.07( 1) 
.77 
.09( 1) 
4 
10 
1.00 
-
.95 
.83 
.04(l) 
11 
1.00 
-
.95 
-
.78 
.05&amp; 
5 
15 
.52 
.20(l) 
.31 
.21(l) 
.25 
.19(l) 
1 
5 
16e 
.98 
.01(l) 
.79 
.07(l) 
.60 
.10(1,2) 
19CJ 
.81 
.11(l) 
.55 
.14(l) 
.42 
.16(2) 
23e 
.99 
.79 
.09(2) 
.54 
.17(2) 
24e 
.90 
.04(2) 
.52 
.15(2) 
.35 
.18(2) 
6 
1e 
.49 
.24(l) 
.30 
.22(l) 
.39 
.16(l) 
1 
13e 
.95 
.02(l) 
.66 
.10(l) 
.86 
.03(1,3) 
21e 
.45 
.16(2,5) 
.27 
.17(5) 
.17 
.17(2,5) 
1 
22exs 
.97 
-
.72 
.06(1,3) 
.31 
.13(1,3) 
7 
20d 
1.00 
1.00 
-
.99 
-</p>

<p>a The cluster other than the one indicated by the left-hand column of the Table is noted in parentheses. </p>

<p>d Discrepant observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>e Efficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>i Inefficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>i* This observation exhibits somewhat inefficient behavior as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>' Scale inefficient observation. </p>

<p>15, and 20), discrepant observations (8 and 19), and observations that do not exhibit strong 
efficient or inefficient behavior (observation 7). Finally, as the degree of fuzziness increases 
from 1 SO to 2.50 more clarity in identifying the efficiency characteristics of observations 
is achieved for mills 1 and 2 but not for mill 3. It is interesting to note that mill 3 has 
consistently shown differences when compared to mills 1 and 2 as far its efficiency perfor-
mance is concerned as indicated by Seaver and Triantis [1991] .3 One might explain these 
dissimilarities in part by the differences in the collinearity structure of the independent 
variables of mill 3. It is encouraging that the fuzzy K-means clustering approach is sen-
sitive to these differences. </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>Table 9. Fuzzy K-means clustering for mill 3. </p>

<p>Cluster 
Observations </p>

<p>M = 1.50 </p>

<p>Second 
Highest 
HighesP </p>

<p>M = 2.00 </p>

<p>Second 
Highesta 
Highesta </p>

<p>M = 2.50 </p>

<p>Second 
High&amp; 
HighesP </p>

<p>16e 
1.00 
-
.20 
.18(31 
.18 
.16(3) </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>4d 
.95 
.02(3) 
.54 
.12;1:3) 
.34 
.14?1:3) 
5d 
.94 
.04(3) 
.61 
.14(3) 
.40 
.16(3) 
6 
.98 
-
.94 
-
.82 
.05(l) 
10e* 
.92 
.06(3) 
.75 
.09(l) 
.55 
.13(l) 
13i* 
.64 
.17(3) 
.25 
.22(l) 
.20(6) 
.17 
3e 
.74 
.19(2) 
.31 
.25(2) 
.22 
.22(2) 
lid 
.77 
.12(2) 
.66 
lO(2) 
.47 
.13(2) 
12 
Sl 
.34(2) 
.88(l) 
.03 
.72(l) 
.05 
21e 
.27 
.23(2) 
.19(l) 
.16 
.16(l) 
.15 
24d 
.96 
.03(2) 
.90 
.03(1,2) 
.73 
.07(l) 
1e 
.89 
.05(2) 
.37 
.18(2) 
.24 
.17(2) 
18 
.97 
.55 
.10(1,2) 
.32 
.13(1,2,5,6) </p>

<p>c 
c </p>

<p>23 
.86 
.06(2) 
.89 
.03(1,2) 
.96 
7s 
.44 
.25(3) 
.22(l) 
.21 
.17 
.17(l) </p>

<p>8d,S </p>

<p>.66 
.16(2) 
.43(l) 
.17 
.24(l) 
.19 
9' 
.89 
.04(3,6) 
.31 
.25(l) 
.26(6) 
.25 
14' 
.45 
.27(6) 
.24 
.22(6) 
.19 
.18(6) 
15' 
.59 
.14(6) 
.33 
.18(l) 
28 
.22(6) 
19d,S 
.26 
.26(7) 
.20 
.17(7) 
.16 
.16(6) 
20' 
.92 
.04(6) 
.76 
.07(6) 
.28 
.23(6) 
2d 
.93 
.42 
.19(3) 
.22(3) 
.16 
17' 
.98 
.83 
.05(5) 
.20(5) 
.19 
22eJ 
.96 
.02(l) 
.44 
.15(l) 
.28 
.16(1,2,4) 
1 
25dJ 
.97 
.92 
.88 
.03(4) </p>

<p>a The cluster other than the one indicated by the left-hand column of the Table is noted in parentheses. </p>

<p>d Discrepant observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>e Efficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>e* This observation exhibits somewhat efficient behavior according to Table 2. </p>

<p>i Inefficient observation as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>i* This observation exhibits somewhat inefficient behavior as indicated by Table 2. </p>

<p>' Scale inefficient observation. </p>

<p>6. Conclusions </p>

<p>Initially, by studying the efficiency performance measures of Tables 1, Al, and A2 one 
could conclude that there are some inconsistencies between the full-frontier and linear 
programming measures. This can prove disturbing for a decision maker who might base 
efficiency performance improvement programs on these findings, especially since one would 
expect the two approaches to lead to similar conclusions. Therefore, a two-stage fuzzy 
clustering approach that uses a modified hat matrix was implemented to confirm the 
technical efficiency profile of Table 2. </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>In fact, it was found that the two approaches essentially provide consistent results for 
observations that have been consistently designated as efficient or inefficient by the two 
approaches. By varying the degree of fuzziness, one can obtain some understanding of 
the degree of belonging to derived efficiency clusters. For instance, consistently designated 
efficient and inefficient observations remained in their original clusters as the degree of 
fuzziness increased. However, observations that were not efficient or inefficient generally 
moved to clusters with a similar efficiency characteristics as the degree of fuzziness in-
creased. This suggests that relying only on estimated or computed technical efficiency 
measures can lead to misleading conclusions if additional sensitivity analyses are not per-
formed. The fuzzy K-means clustering analysis improves the evaluation capability of the 
analyst as far as the technical efficiency measures are concerned. 
Additionally, observations that represent extreme or unusual operating conditions or scale 
inefficiencies were for the most part highlighted by the clustering analysis. These observa-
tions are also responsible for the efficiency designation discrepancies. There are a number 
of reasons why the two approaches might lead to discrepant conclusions. First, the full-
frontier approach assumes a specific functional form whereas, the linear programming 
approaches do not. Second, any data set can be plagued with a number of data problems 
such as outliers, measurement errors, collinearity among independent variables. The ex-
istence of these data problems could cause both approaches to determine inaccurate effi-
ciency measures. Third, there might be an input and/or output specification error that could 
again lead to incorrect efficiency designations. Fourth, the single error specification of 
technical efficiency could adversely impact the estimation and or computational accuracy 
of the two approaches. In this case, the composed error approach should be employed. 
These issues are interrelated and their singular and joint impact needs to be studied further. 
Given the sensitivity of the efficiency measures to observations that represent unusual 
operating conditions, one might be tempted to augment the existing full-frontier methodology 
by incorporating very robust and collinearity-resistant procedures. While robust statistical 
procedures provide a good but complicated estimation alternative, incorporating fuzzy 
regression analysis may prove more worthwhile. Additionally, it might be necessary to pro-
vide a comprehensive sensitivity analysis with respect to the linear programming measures. 
This analysis could specifically address the measurement problems associated with ob-
taining accurate representations of the input/output factors. 
Finally, the measurement and evaluation of technical efficiency should not be performed 
in a vacuum. There is a need to link the measurement results to specific improvement 
strategies. The clustering analysis presented in this paper provides the decision maker with 
a vehicle to ensure that the measurement-improvement link is made. The common and 
unique operating characteristics of the efficient, inefficient, scale inefficient and unusual 
groups need to be studied. Based on these operating characteristics, improvement strategies 
can be formulated. Finally, the accuracy and consistency of an organization's measurement 
system will in part enhance the success of the efficiency performance improvement programs, </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>



<p>Appendix A </p>

<p>Table AZ. Output increasing technical efficiency measures for mill 2. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>Full-frontier efficiency 
measuresa </p>

<p>1 
0.974 
7 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
2 
0.883 
23 
0.923 
21 
0.995 </p>

<p>3 
0.906 
20 
0.909 
24 
0.999 
4 
0.940 
14 
0.967 
13 
0.985 
5 
0.934 
15 
0.943 
14 
0.976 
6 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
1 
0.983 
7 
0.928 
16 
0.931 
19 
0.986 </p>

<p>8 
0.894 
21 
0.935 
17 
0.993 
9 
0.975 
6 
1 .ooo 
1 
1 .ooo 
10 
0.961 
11 
0.932 
18 
0.991 </p>

<p>11 
0.951 
12 
0.914 
22 
0.998 
12 
0.866 
24 
0.912 
23 
0.997 </p>

<p>13 
0.992 
3 
1.000 
1 
0.984 
14 
0.884 
22 
0.936 
16 
0.980 
1.5 
0.945 
13 
0.972 
12 
0.990 
16 
0.978 
5 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
17 
0.921 
17 
0.937 
15 
1.000 
18 
0.906 
19 
0.928 
20 
0.997 
19 
0.965 
10 
0.978 
10 
0.970 
20 
0.919 
18 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
21 
0.981 
4 
1.000 
1 
0.996 
22 
0.972 
8 
1.000 
1 
0.749 
23 
0.966 
9 
0.978 
11 
0.992 
24 
0.995 
2 
1.000 
1 
1.000 </p>

<p>a These efficiency measures are based on the following standard: LPR = (0.996) X (CAP)0.3q' x (LAB)'.lW 
x (ENE)'.&amp;l 
x (NMAT)0.084. </p>

<p>bRt is the ranking based on the full-frontier technical efficiency measure using four significant digits, </p>

<p>' W&amp;J', X') represents weak output increasing technical efficiency measure. </p>

<p>d R, is the ranking based on I+'&amp;, Xi) using four significant digits. </p>

<p>e SJ$, Xi) represents the output increasing scale efficiency measure. </p>



<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p>Table A2 Output increasing technical efficiency measures for mill 3. </p>

<p>Observation </p>

<p>Full-frontier efficiency 
measuresa 
e 
WJy', Xi), 
@ 
s,(y', Xi)' </p>

<p>1 
0.988 
2 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
2 
0.845 
22 
0.984 
16 
0.996 </p>

<p>3 
0.969 
4 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
4 
0.909 
13 
1.000 
1 
0.993 
5 
0.918 
10 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
6 
0.937 
7 
1 .ooo 
1 
1.000 
7 
0.900 
15 
0.972 
17 
0.950 </p>

<p>8 
0.899 
16 
0.987 
15 
0.963 </p>

<p>9 
0.864 
21 
0.920 
21 
0.990 
10 
0.948 
6 
0.995 
13 
0.999 
11 
0.904 
14 
0.992 
14 
0.991 
12 
0.920 
9 
0.968 
18 
0.996 </p>

<p>13 
0.892 
17 
0.931 
20 
0.985 
14 
0.793 
25 
0.818 
25 
0.999 
15 
0.878 
19 
0.905 
22 
0.997 </p>

<p>16 
1.000 
1 
1.000 
1 
1.000 </p>

<p>17 
0.826 
24 
0.891 
23 
0.989 </p>

<p>18 
0.932 
8 
1.000 
1 
0.978 </p>

<p>19 
0.887 
18 
1 .oOO 
1 
0.905 </p>

<p>20 
0.843 
23 
0.855 
24 
1.000 </p>

<p>21 
0.970 
3 
1.000 
1 
1.000 </p>

<p>22 
0.951 
5 
1.000 
1 
0.904 </p>

<p>23 
0.916 
11 
0.945 
19 
0.997 </p>

<p>24 
0.913 
12 
1.000 
1 
0.999 </p>

<p>25 
0.877 
20 
1.000 
1 
0.856 </p>

<p>a These efficiency measures are based on the following standard: LPR = (0.245) X (CAP)'."* 
X (LAB)'.*" 
x (ENE)0.500 x (NMAT)0.329. </p>

<p>bRtisthernk' a mg based on the full-frontier technical efficiency measure using four significant digits. </p>

<p>' W,($, Xi) represents weak output increasing technical efficiency measure. </p>

<p>d R, is the ranking based on W,y, X') using four significant digits. </p>

<p>e S&amp;v', Xi) represents the output increasing scale efficiency measure. </p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>







<p>B.L. SEAVER AND K.P. TRIANTIS </p>

<p><rs type="software">IML SAS</rs><rs type="software">SAS</rs></p>

<p>EVALUATING TECHNICAL EFFICIENCY MEASURES IN MANUFACTURING </p>





</text></tei>