<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1468-0297.2011.02449.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:51+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Recent substantive reforms to the English National Health Service expanded patient choice and 
encouraged hospitals to compete within a market with fixed prices. This study investigates whether 
these reforms led to improvements in hospital quality. We use a difference-in-difference-style esti-
mator to test whether hospital quality (measured using mortality from acute myocardial infarction) 
improved more quickly in more competitive markets after these reforms came into force in 2006. We 
find that after the reforms were implemented, mortality fell (i.e. quality improved) for patients living 
in more competitive markets. Our results suggest that hospital competition can lead to improve-
ments in hospital quality. </p>

<p>Across the developed world, health care spending accounts for a large and growing 
share of most countriesÕ gross domestic product (GDP). 1 In an effort to slow the rate of 
spending growth and improve health system performance, a number of countries have 
enacted market-based health care reforms that have centred on increasing user choice 
and promoting competition between health care providers. 2 These reforms have been 
primarily designed to create financial incentives in a sector that has typically been more 
state-directed and centrally controlled than others. However, there is not a consensus 
on how health care markets should be structured and the evidence on the impact of 
choice and competition on clinical quality is inconclusive (Dranove and Satterthwaite, 
1992, 2000; Gaynor and Haas-Wilson, 1999; Sage et al., 2003; Gaynor, 2004). This article 
evaluates one recent set of market-based health reforms introduced in the English 
National Health Service (NHS) from 2002 to 2008, which focused on introducing 
patient choice and provider competition. We take advantage of the explicit introduc-
tion of choice and competition into the NHS in 2006 to create a quasi-natural experi-
ment where we can examine whether greater exposure to competition prompted 
hospitals to improve their performance. </p>

<p>The recent English NHS reforms had three central elements (Department of Health, 
2003). First, patients were given the ability to select the hospital they attend for surgery 
and the government provided publicly assessable information on provider quality to 
inform patientsÕ choices. Second, the government liberalised the hospital sector in 
England by giving publicly owned hospitals additional fiscal and managerial autonomy 
and encouraging private sector providers to enter the market and deliver care to 
publicly funded patients. Third, the government introduced a new case-based hospital 
reimbursement system that paid providers a fixed, centrally determined price for every 
procedure that they carried out. In sum, policy makers in the NHS hoped that their 
efforts to encourage patient choice would create quality competition between hospitals 
in England, which would prompt providers to improve their clinical performance 
(Department of Health, 2004). 
In order to assess the impact of the recent NHS market-based reforms, we exploit the 
fact that the choice-based reforms will create sharper financial incentives for hospitals 
in markets where choice is geographically feasible. Specifically, we use a difference-
in-difference (DiD) style estimator to test whether patient outcomes in more potentially 
competitive markets have improved at a significantly faster rate post-reform than in less 
competitive markets after all patients in England were formally given the ability to 
select their hospital in 2006. We measure these improvements in quality by examining 
changes in 30-day mortality rates for patients diagnosed with an acute myocardial 
infarction (AMI). Thirty-day AMI mortality is an appealing quality indicator because 
AMIs are easily clinically identifiable, AMI mortality is not subject to gaming or 
manipulation like many elective outcomes, and for patients with an AMI, there is a 
clear link between appropriate treatment and good outcomes (Bradley et al., 2006; Jha 
et al., 2007). Indeed, 30-day AMI mortality is frequently used in the literature assessing 
the relationship between competition and overall hospital quality. 3 
This work adds to the existing literature examining the impact of public sector 
reform on service quality. To evaluate the reforms, we use a DiD estimator and (a) 
develop a range of concentration measures and illustrate that our results are robust 
across each; (b) calculate concentration using elective patient flows and measure quality 
using outcomes for an emergency procedure (AMI), which mitigates the selection bias 
inherent in using quality measures based on the outcomes of elective procedures; (c) 
develop an instrument for market competition that exploits the variability in distance 
between a patientÕs GP and their nearest four hospitals (which is largely a historical 
artefact) as an exogenous source of variation in the underlying market structure; and 
(d) present various tests of robustness that indicate that our estimates arise post-2005 
are consistent across various alternative specifications of our estimator and are driven by 
hospital market structure and not by spurious associations with urban density. 
Ultimately, we find that after the introduction of these reforms in 2006, our marker 
for service quality (AMI mortality) improved more quickly for patients living in more 
competitive hospital markets. Compared to the mean, AMI mortality has fallen 
approximately 0.31 percentage points per year faster in places that were one standard 
deviation higher on our market structure index (on a base mortality of 13.82% during </p>

<p>3 See Kessler and McClellan (2000); Propper et al. (2004, 2008); Kessler and Geppert (2005); Gaynor et al. 
(2010). </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>[ A U G U S T 2011 ] 
F229 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>the 2002-8 period). As a result we conclude that hospital competition within a market 
with fixed prices can improve patient outcomes. 
This article is structured as follows. Section 1 examines the existing literature on the 
impact of hospital competition on quality. Section 2 outlines the recent NHS market-
based reforms and presents our estimation strategy. Section 3 outlines our data, marker 
for service quality and the various measures of competition to define the ÔtreatedÕ groups 
in our DiD estimations. Section 4 presents our results. Section 5 contains our conclusions. </p>

<p>1. Evidence on the Relationship Between Hospital Competition and Hospital 
Quality </p>

<p>There is a growing US literature analysing the impact of hospital competition on 
hospital quality and efficiency; however, the evidence for England is only just emerging 
(Propper et al., 2004, 2008; Cooper et al., 2010a,b; Gaynor et al., 2010). Comprehensive 
reviews of this literature can be found in Gaynor (2004), Romano and Mutter (2004), 
Propper et al. (2006), Vogt and Town (2006), Cooper et al. (2010b). 
A key trend emerging from this literature is that greater competition in markets with 
fixed prices generally leads to improvements in hospital performance (Gaynor, 2004, 
2006). Examining competition in a fixed price market in the US, Kessler and McClellan 
(2000) looked at the impact of hospital competition on AMI mortality for Medicare 
beneficiaries from 1985 to 1994. They find that in the 1980s, the impact of competition 
was ambiguous but, in the 1990s, higher competition led to lower mortality. Related 
work by Kessler and Geppert (2005) also found that competition reduced AMI mor-
tality and that it also led to more intensive treatment for sicker patients and less 
intensive treatment for healthier patients. However, Gowrisankaran and Town (2003) 
found that increased competition in a fixed price market led to an increase in 
mortality, but argue that their results stem from the fact that hospitals in California 
were underpaid for treating Medicare patients with AMI. This hypothesis is consistent 
with research, which found that lower Medicare reimbursement rates led to increases in 
mortality, particularly in competitive markets (Shen, 2003). 4 
Nearly, all of the English literature on hospital competition examines an earlier set of 
NHS reforms -the 1990s internal market. This market allowed hospitals to compete on 
quality and price for bulk purchasing contracts but, in general, there is a near uniform 
consensus that the internal market never created significant financial incentives for 
hospitals to change their behaviour (Le Grand et al.1998; Klein, 1999; Le Grand, 1999). 
There is some evidence that prices fell during the internal market (Propper, 1996; 
Soderlund et al., 1997; Propper et al., 1998); however, Soderlund et al. (1997) suggest 
that higher competition was not associated with lower prices. Propper et al. (2004, 
2008) examined the impact of competition on clinical performance during this period. 
Both studies find that competition (measured using counts of hospitals within markets </p>

<p>4 Looking at competition in a market with unregulated prices, Gowrisankaran and Town (2003) found 
that higher competition led to lower AMI mortality, which served as a proxy for overall quality. Likewise, Sari 
(2002) uses hospital complication rates as a proxy for quality, and finds that higher hospital competition 
led to improvements in quality. Hamilton and Ho (2000) looked at competition in a variable priced market by 
examining hospital mergers and found that there was no significant relationship between competition and 
mortality. Volpp et al. (2003) examine price competition in New York and find that it is associated with 
significant increases in AMI mortality. </p>

<p>F230 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>defined by 30 minute isochrones) was associated with lower hospital quality, as 
measured by AMI mortality, possibly because hospitals shifted resources towards 
reducing waiting times and improving other easily observed measures of performance. 
More recently, several working articles, including Bloom et al. (2010), Cooper et al. 
(2010a,b), and Gaynor et al. (2010) have investigated the most recent set of post-2006 
NHS reforms. In a study on management practice, Bloom et al. (2010) find a 
correlation between competition and hospital management quality, and a correlation 
between higher management quality and lower AMI mortality. To address concerns 
about endogeneity between market structure and management performance in their 
cross-sectional analysis, they use a measure of local political vulnerability as an instru-
ment for the number of hospitals, based on the idea that politically vulnerable juris-
dictions tend not to impose unpopular hospital closures. Several studies look more 
directly at patient outcomes during the post-2006 period of reform, including an earlier 
version of our work on AMI mortality (Cooper et al., 2010b), and a study of the effects 
of competition on patientsÕ length of stay in hospital (Cooper et al., 2010a). Gaynor 
et al. (2010) also look at the effect of competition on AMI mortality and trust-level 
overall mortality. These latter articles use DiD related methodologies and find that 
higher competition is associated with better hospital performance. </p>

<p>2. Patient Choice and Hospital Competition Reforms and Our Estimation 
Strategy </p>

<p>2.1. Competition in the English NHS </p>

<p>The English NHS is a publicly funded health system that is free at the point of use. In the 
20 years prior to the reforms, patients had little choice over where they received care. 
From 1997 to 2002, the buyers of care (local government organisations) and providers of 
care (NHS-owned facilities) were tasked with working ÔcooperativelyÕ to organise care for 
their local communities (Klein, 2006). In practice, this involved coordinating care 
packages and negotiating annual contracts that were based on quality, volume and price. 
The recent wave of NHS reforms were introduced in several stages from 2002 to 2008 
and focused on increasing patient choice and hospital competition in order to create 
financial incentives for providers to improve their quality and efficiency (Department 
of Health, 2004, 2009b). The reforms involved changes to the demand side and supply 
side, as well as additional reforms to fundamentally restructure how hospitals in Eng-
land were funded. Broadly, the reforms were designed to give patients choice over 
where they went for care, together with a reimbursement system where money followed 
the usersÕ choices, so that hospitals only received funding if they were able to attract 
patients. Hospitals were given increased managerial and fiscal autonomy, encouraged 
to compete on non-price elements of service and care and paid a fixed price based on a 
national tariff for different diagnoses that were drawn up by the Department of Health. 
In effect, the reforms created an incentive for hospitals to attract patients and compete 
with each other for volume in a market that only allowed providers to differentiate 
themselves on quality rather than price. 
Figure 1 is a timeline of the key elements of the reforms. The market-based reforms 
occurred during a period when there was a significant surge in NHS spending and </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F231 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>succeeded a wave of heavy performance management that focused on shortening 
waiting times. However, these funding changes and the performance management 
programme likely had a general effect across England, whereas the impact of the 
market-based reforms, which we study, will be much more market dependent. 
Prior to 2002, patients themselves could not select where they went for secondary 
care and were largely confined to providers within their own Primary Care Trust. From 
2002 to 2006, a small subset of patients who were waiting for long periods of time were 
allowed to opt to travel further for care but the majority of patients were largely con-
fined to attending their local hospital and providers had no financial incentive to 
expand their market share. On 1 January 2006, all patients in England were formally 
given the ability to choose where they received elective care (Department of Health, 
2009b; Dixon et al., 2010). However, it did take some time for the policy to bed in and 
for NHS Choose and Book, the electronic referral system, to become fully active (Dixon 
et al., 2010). Therefore, we take mid-2006 after the beginning of the new financial year 
as the key point when hospitals in England were significantly exposed to the financial 
incentives created by competition. 
To create an environment that would support competition, beginning in 2002, the 
health service began paying for NHS patients to receive care in private sector facilities 
and attempted to diversify the hospital sector (Department of Health, 2002). The NHS 
helped to coordinate the development of Independent Sector Treatment Centres 
(ISTCs), which were to compete against traditional NHS hospitals to provide elective 
surgery and diagnostic services). Furthermore, in an effort to encourage local inno-
vation, the government gave high performing hospitals additional fiscal, clinical and 
managerial autonomy. Hospitals that earned additional autonomy were referred to as 
ÔFoundation TrustsÕ (FTs) (Department of Health, 2005). 
In 2004 and 2005, the government implemented a new fixed-price funding mechan-
ism called ÔPayment By ResultsÕ (PBR), which was a case-based payment system modelled 
on the diagnosis-related group (DRG) system from America (Department of Health, </p>

<p>2001 
2002 
2003 
2004 
2005 
2006 
2008 
2007 </p>

<p>Choice 
Pilots Begin 
for Heart 
Disease and 
Elective 
Patients in 
London </p>

<p>April 2004: 
'Payment by 
Results' for 
20 
Foundation 
Trusts </p>

<p>Jan 2006: All 
Patients can 
Choose from 
4-5 
Providers. </p>

<p>'Choose and 
Book' 
System for 
Online 
Bookings. </p>

<p>NHS Choice 
Website 
goes Online. 
Website has 
Provider 
Quality 
Information </p>

<p>Patients can 
Choose to 
Attend Any 
Provider in 
England for 
Care </p>

<p>Consistent Increases in NHS-wide Funding </p>

<p>Private Sector Hospitals Increasingly Enter the Market to Offer Elective Care to NHS Patients </p>

<p>Patients 
Waiting &gt; 6 
Months can 
Choose 
Provider with 
Shorter Wait </p>

<p>April 2005: 
'Payment by 
Results' for 
All NHS 
Providers </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Timeline for the Second Wave of NHS Market-based Reforms (2001-8) </p>

<p>F232 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2009a). Under PBR, hospitals were rewarded for increasing their activity and attracting 
more patients. The new reimbursement system allowed money to follow patientsÕ choices 
so providers were paid for their elective care based on the number of patients they were 
able to attract. Ultimately, since GPs are highly active in informing the destination of 
most referrals, GPs now play a substantial role dictating how money flows around the 
post-2005 NHS. 
Along with giving patients a formal choice of where they receive secondary care in 
2006, the government also introduced a paperless referral system (Department of 
Health, 2009a). The booking interface included the ability to search for hospitals based 
on geographic distance and see estimates of each hospitalÕs waiting times that were 
based on the last 20 appointments at each facility. The ÔChoose and BookÕ system was 
rolled out as patients in the NHS were given a choice of their secondary care provider. 
In addition, the government also created a website to provide additional quality 
information to inform patientsÕ choices. The hope was that providing information to 
patients would help them to make informed choices based on quality. The website 
currently includes detailed information on various aspects of provider performance, 
including risk-adjusted mortality rates, hospital activity levels, waiting times and infec-
tion rates sorted by procedures (Department of Health, 2009c). </p>

<p>2.2. Hypothesis </p>

<p>From mid-2006 onwards, faced with fixed price reimbursements, increased elasticity of 
demand and the start of a new financial year, we expect that hospitals located in more 
competitive markets to take steps to differentiate themselves from one another on non-
price aspects of their care, and in particular, by improving their clinical performance. 
The existing literature from the US suggests that fixed price hospital competition can 
prompt hospitals to improve their performance (Kessler and McClellan, 2000; Kessler 
and Geppert, 2005). We expect a similar response from English providers. 
There are reasons to expect that NHS providers should be particularly responsive to 
this type of quality competition. First, NHS hospital managers face significant pressure 
to maintain annual financial surpluses, which would quickly be eroded if they failed to 
attract sufficient market share in the market for elective care and lost ground to other 
competing providers. Indeed, the NHS has embedded explicit rewards for high per-
forming providers that maintain surpluses and rewards them with greater financial and 
managerial autonomy in the form of granting them FT status. In contrast, poorly 
performing hospitals have, in the past, actually had their senior management removed 
by the central government. Second, the incentives during the second period may be 
particularly sharp because GPs, who serve as patientsÕ agents, can now more easily refer 
patients to a wider range of hospitals. Elsewhere, Klein and Leffler (1981), Shapiro 
(1983) and Allen (1984), have found that even in markets with imperfect information, 
there is likely to be an equilibrium with optimal quality if consumers can perceive 
quality ex post and providers have an interest in attracting repeat business. Since GPs 
serve as agents for different patients for the same set of conditions on an ongoing basis, 
they are well positioned to observe quality ex post and use that information to advise 
future patients. In effect, despite the fact that patients seldom attend hospitals for the </p>

<p> 
F233 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>same procedures twice, GPs will be able to take advantage of their knowledge of their 
previous patientsÕ experiences and outcomes to inform future referrals. 
Therefore, we expect that AMI mortality will decrease more quickly in more com-
petitive markets from mid-2006 onwards after hospitals were exposed to competition 
created from the new NHS reimbursement system and the expansion of patient choice. 
While providers are not explicitly competing for AMI patients because competition in 
the NHS is limited to the market for elective care, we expect the market-based reforms to 
result in across-the-board improvements in hospital performance, which in turn will 
result in lower AMI death rates. To that end, Bloom et al. (2010) looked at NHS hos-
pitals and found that better managed hospitals had significantly lower AMI mortality 
and that greater hospital competition was associated with better hospital management. 
Indeed, they observed that a one standard deviation improvement in a hospitalÕs overall 
management quality was associated with 0.66-percentage point reduction in AMI mor-
tality and that better managed providers were able to attain more revenue per hospital 
bed and had higher patient satisfaction. Consistent with their findings, we expect that 
competition will prompt providers to improve their overall hospital management, which 
will result in across-the-board improvements in clinical performance. We capture these 
across-the-board improvements using risk-adjusted 30-day AMI mortality, our measure 
of hospital quality (which we discuss in more detail below). </p>

<p>2.3. Specification of Our Empirical Model </p>

<p>Our analysis centres on using regressions based on changes in AMI mortality trends to 
test whether hospitals located in more competitive markets improved their perform-
ance post mid-2006, relative to hospitals located in less competitive markets. Whereas, 
the bulk of the research on hospital competition relies on analysing a cross-sectional 
relationship between measured competition and quality, we use our estimates of 
market structure to determine which hospital markets were ÔtreatedÕ and therefore 
exposed to the full force of the NHS market-based reforms after they were introduced. 
Our research design is therefore DiD in style. However, the NHS market-based 
reforms that we are investigating do not fit neatly within the traditional DiD framework. 
In particular, every area in England was exposed, to some degree, to the reforms so, in 
principle, there are no distinct treatment and control groups. In practice, however, the 
NHS choice reforms will have had varying impact intensity across the country 
depending on the underlying geographical relationships between hospitals and res-
idential areas. We assume that hospitals located in areas where choice is not geo-
graphically feasible will be subjected to less sharp financial incentives created from 
competition in comparison to hospitals located in areas where patients have consid-
erable potential choice. Our DiD identification strategy is therefore based on the 
premise that the incentives from hospital competition are more intense in the period 
after the introduction of the NHS choice reforms and increasingly so for hospitals 
located in less concentrated markets. Similar DiD estimation strategies have been used 
to evaluate the employment effects of minimum wage increases (Card, 1992) and to 
study the 1990s internal market NHS reforms (Propper et al., 2008). 
The second modification to the standard DiD setup is that, rather than comparing 
the levels of quality in the pre and post-policy periods, we estimate the effects of the </p>

<p>F234 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>reforms from a break in the time trend in AMI mortality after the mid-2006 Ôpolicy-onÕ 
date. In our preferred empirical specification, we implement this using two-part, 
quarterly splines, split at the end of the second quarter in 2006 and interacted with our 
measure of potential market structure. We adopt this approach to illustrate explicitly 
that there are no differences in trends between high and low competition markets prior 
to the reforms. Note, there is no theoretical reason to expect a discrete jump in 
hospital quality in the first quarter after the policy-on date in the context of the NHS 
reforms and our spline specification imposes this restriction whilst allowing for a more 
gradual improvement in quality as the reforms begin to bite. However, as described 
below, we test and relax this restriction in our robustness tests. 
Our general empirical regression specification is therefore: </p>

<p>death ijkt ¼b 1 t þ b 2 I t À ~ 
tjt ! ~ 
t 
f 
gþb 3 z jt t þ b 4 z jt I t À ~ 
tjt ! ~ 
t 
f 
g 
þ b 5 z jt þ b 6 I t ! ~ 
t 
f 
gþ b 7 z jt I t ! ~ 
t 
f 
gþ c 0 controls ijkt þ error ijkt 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>Here, death ijkt is an indicator for whether patient i, from GP market j, treated at hospital 
site k died within 30 days of admission for AMI in period t. Subscript t indicates a 
running counter of quarters since quarter 1, 2002 (the first period in our data), and ~ 
t is 
the break point in the spline, corresponding to our policy-on period starting the end of 
the second quarter of 2006. Variable z jt is the market structure index of GP market j at 
time t, which we describe in Section 3.3 below. 5 
We can estimate various alternative specifications by imposing restrictions on 
these parameters. Setting b 1 = b 2 = b 3 = b 4 = 0 gives rise to a standard DiD specifi-
cation with continuous treatment variable, in which coefficient b 7 is the estimated 
effect of the policy on the change in death rates between the pre and post-policy 
periods. Imposing the restrictions b 7 = b 6 = 0 instead gives our preferred spline-
based difference-in-trends estimator in which b 4 is the effect of the policy on the 
annual rate of change in death rates. Relaxing all these restrictions gives a combi-
nation of these two estimators, allowing for a step change at the policy-on date and 
a change in trends. 
Our preferred specification is the one that imposes b 7 = b 6 = 0, but we report on the 
others in our robustness checks. In this preferred specification, coefficient b 1 captures 
the baseline rate of decline in AMI mortality prior to the 2006 reforms, for locations in 
which our index of market structure is zero (a monopoly). Coefficients b 1 + b 2 capture 
the baseline rate of mortality decline in these low-competition places after reform. 
Now consider a comparator place where there is high competition. The sum of 
b 1 + b 3 equals the time trend in mortality in these areas before the reform. The sum 
b 1 + b 2 + b 3 + b 4 is the time trend in mortality in highly competitive areas after the 
2006 reform. The second partial derivate of the death rate trend with respect to dif-
ferences in competition in the post-policy period is b 4 . This is our coefficient of interest 
and is a DiD estimate of the effect of competition on the trends in mortality. 6 </p>

<p>5 This index is calculated from data for the whole calendar year, rather than the quarter. 
6 This is easily deduced since: </p>

<p>Treatment effect ¼ ½ðb 1 þ b 2 þ b 3 Dnlhhi þ b 4 DnlhhiÞ À ðb 1 þ b 3 DnlhhiÞ À ½ðb 1 þ b 2 Þ À b 1  
¼ b 4 Dnlhhi: </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F235 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>The coefficient b 3 is also informative, in that it provides the basis to test for the exis-
tence of pre-policy differences in trends between high and low competition places 
b 3 6 ¼ 0. The existence of pre-policy differences in trends would undermine the credi-
bility of the DiD strategy. 
We estimate (1) using Ordinary Least Squares and cluster our standard errors at the 
GP level to allow for error correlation across patients within GP markets. Note that the 
specification in equation (1) includes a vector of control variables as discussed in the 
data section and can be generalised to include hospital and GP fixed effects. Our 
specifications further include an interaction between Strategic Health Authorities 
(SHAs) and time trends, controlling for trends associated with local SHA policies and 
changes in regional funding. 7 </p>

<p>3. Data, Our Measures of Competition, Our Quality Indicator and the 
Instrumental Variable Strategy </p>

<p>3.1. Data Sources and Setup </p>

<p>Our article relies on patient-level Hospital Episodes Statistics (HES) data from 2002 to 
2008. In addition to observations for patients with an emergency AMI, our analysis 
contains data on patients undergoing elective hip replacement, knee replacement, 
knee arthroscopy, cataract repair and hernia repair, which we use in the construction of 
our competition indices. At the hospital level, we know hospital site postcodes, the NHS 
trust to which the site belongs, and we have indicators of the hospital type (teaching 
hospitals, FTs status) and hospital size. Our work improves on previous research by 
using the hospital site-specific locations, rather than the trust headquarters. There are 
typically multiple treatment sites for each trust, separated by distances of up to 50 km, 
so using Trust locations provides only a very approximate indicator of the location at 
which treatment is carried out. 8 
We use GP and hospital site postcodes to calculate distances between patientsÕ GPs 
and the hospital where care was delivered. This distance is a key component in our 
analysis and is used as an input into most of our competition measures. For our main 
analysis, we use matrices of straight-line distances between GPs and NHS sites. For some 
of our supplementary results, we calculate origin-destination matrices from minimum 
road travel times along the primary road network. 9 </p>

<p>7 There are ten NHS Strategic Health Authorities (SHAs) in England; each represents a different region of 
the country. SHAs are responsible for implementing the policy that is set by the Department of Health and 
managing local health care provision. Increasingly, over the period we study, policy making has been devolved 
to local SHAs. 
8 In addition, our data includes information on NHS funded patients who received elective surgery from 
privately owned providers. However, as it has been well documented, HES data has poor coverage of care 
delivered in private settings. This does not present a problem for our analysis, since during our period of 
analysis, private providers accounted for less than 3% of total NHS volume. Approximately 5% of our sample 
received elective surgery in privately owned facilities. In addition, consistent with other research (Gaynor 
et al., 2010; Propper and van Reenen, 2010), and NHS data cleaning rules, we limit our analysis to providers 
who treat over 99 AMIs per year. 
9 This generalised network was provided by the Department of Transport and is populated with road link-
specific travel speeds derived from their National Transport Model for 2003. We generated the GP hospital 
origin-destination matrix using the Network Analysis tools from the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">ESRI</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">ArcGIS</rs> software package. </p>

<p>F236 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>3.2. Measures of Health Care Quality </p>

<p>Our measure of hospital quality is the 30-day mortality rate for patients with an AMI. 10 
In our analysis, we include every patient who had a main International Classification of 
Disease 10 code of I21 or I22 and only include emergency AMI admissions and 
admissions where the patientsÕ length of stay was three days or more (unless the patient 
died within the first three days of being admitted) (World Health Organization, 
2009). 11 
We chose to use AMI mortality as our measure of performance for four primary 
reasons. First, AMIs are a relatively frequent, easily observable medical occurrences that 
are clinically identifiable and have a substantial mortality rate. For example, in 2008 the 
overall, 30-day mortality rate for emergency AMI was 11.7% compared to a mortality 
rate of 0.20% for elective hip replacement. Second, with AMIs, there is a clear link 
between timely and high-quality medical intervention and patientsÕ survival (Bradley 
et al., 2006; Jha et al., 2007). Contrast this with a quality indicator such as readmissions 
for elective hip replacements, where a patient failing to stick to a rehabilitation pro-
gramme after they were discharged could produce poor outcomes or lead to a read-
mission. Third, unlike other measures of performance, like hospital waiting times, AMI 
mortality (and death rates in general) are not subject to gaming or manipulation by 
hospitals. Fourth, AMIs are an emergency procedure where patients are generally taken 
directly to their nearest provider for care with little discretion over which hospital they 
attend, which mitigates hospitals ability to risk-select healthier patients for care. The 
fact that AMI is a non-elective procedure also mitigates biases due to the endogeneity of 
market structure to elective quality. This point is illustrated in Appendix A. 
A further impetus for using AMI mortality is that it is frequently used by governments 
and private organisations to rank and compare hospital performance (including by the 
UK government). 12,13 Consequently, 30-day AMI mortality is also often used in the 
academic literature as a measure of overall hospital performance in the UK and the US 
(Kessler and McClellan, 2000; Volpp et al., 2003; Propper et al., 2004, 2008; Kessler and 
Geppert, 2005; Bloom et al., 2010; Gaynor et al., 2010; Propper and van Reenen, 2010). 
Consistent with its use as a measure of hospital performance, a recent study assessing 
the relationship between hospitalsÕ management quality and their overall performance 
found a statistically significant relationship between overall hospital management </p>

<p>10 Our mortality measure only includes deaths that occurred within the hospital. While there are 30-day all 
cause AMI mortality figures, they rely on linking HES data to data on deaths provided by the Office for 
National Statistics (ONS). Unfortunately, those data linkages were not reliable for the years in our analysis 
and we find that when using them, the number of deaths in the hospital are equal to the number of total 
deaths out of the hospital Given that during the period we investigate, length of stay for patients with an AMI 
only reduced by less than 2% (from 9.43 to 9.26 days), itÕs unlikely our results were driven by hospitals 
discharging patients Ôsicker and quickerÕ. 
11 We choose to limit our analysis to patients with a length of stay of over two days or patients who died in 
the first two days of their admission in order to avoid possible up-coding, whereby patients with other 
conditions were coded as having an AMI in order to generate larger reimbursements. Up-coding may have 
been prevalent during this period as the government shifted to a fixed-price, prospective reimbursement 
system (Street and Maynard, 2007). 
12 As Davies et al. (2001) note, 30-day AMI quality is used for hospital rankings by healthgrades.com, the 
Michigan Hospital Association (where itÕs aggregated with congestive heart failure and angina), the UK 
Department of Health, the California Hospital Outcomes Project, the Greater New York Hospital Association, 
and the University Hospital Consortium. 
13 See http://2008ratings.cqc.org.uk/findcareservices/informationabouthealthcareservices.cfm </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F237 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>performance and hospital level 30-day AMI mortality (Bloom et al., 2010). Likewise, 
according to data made publicly available by Dr. Foster Health, despite accounting for 
less than 3% of total hospital deaths, standardised AMI mortality in English hospitals 
was positively correlated (r = 0.33) with overall hospital mortality for the financial year 
beginning in 2009. 14 Likewise, in our administrative data, we have found that raw AMI 
mortality is positively correlated with elective hip and knee replacement waiting times 
(r = 0.33) and positively correlated with length of stay for elective hip and knee 
replacement (r = 0.11 and r = 0.22, respectively). 
While 30-day AMI mortality is a frequently used measure of hospital quality, there are 
several issues with its use. First, as with all quality measures, despite being correlated 
with other dimensions of performance, there is a question of whether or not a single 
measure can capture the multi-dimensional nature of health care quality (McClellan 
and Staiger, 1999). A second issue with 30-day mortality is the noise inherent with this 
type of measure. This noise is particularly acute when researchers use hospital level 
data, where it is difficult to suitably risk adjust and hospital performance can vary from 
year to year. Our use of patient-level data, which allows for controls for patientsÕ 
socioeconomic status, age and co-morbidities, mitigates this problem. In our estima-
tion, we control for co-morbidities using the Charlson co-morbidity index (Charlson 
et al., 1978) and control for patientsÕ socio-economic status using the income vector of 
the 2007 Index of Multiple Deprivation, which we include at the Census Output Area 
level (Communities and Local Government Department, 2009). 15,16 </p>

<p>3.3. Market Measures and Estimates of Market Structure </p>

<p>Identifying the impact of competition in the wake of NHS reforms requires accurately 
measuring market structure. In this article, we estimate market structure in the English 
NHS using both counts of providers and Herfindahl-Hirschman Indexes (HHIs) cal-
culated using actual and predicted patient flows. Our aim in developing a range of 
measures of market structure is to illustrate that our results are robust across a number 
of measures of market structure, since there is not a single, agreed upon measure that 
is immune to each and every form bias. 
The debate over measuring market structure centres around thwarting potential 
endogeneity between hospital quality and market structure, avoiding measures of 
market structure that simply reflect urban population density and defining a market 
size that accurately reflects the choice sets available to NHS users. Concerns over the 
endogeneity between measures of market structure and firm performance have been </p>

<p>14 Dr Foster is a commercial company that measures provider performance in the the NHS; see http:// 
www.drfosterhealth.co.uk, last accessed March 1, 2011. 
15 For confidentiality reasons, the patient home addresses are not available for use in our analysis. 
However, we do have access to codes that identify the patientÕs GP and GP postcode. There are around 7600-
7700 GP postcodes in each year in our data. Patients can usually (at the time relevant for our study) only 
register at a GP practice if they live in the catchment area of that GP, so GPs serve as a strong proxy for 
patientsÕ home addresses. 
16 The Charlson index of co-morbidities is a zero to six ranking of illness severity, which predicts the 
probability of a patients' one-year mortality based on the presence of certain co-morbidities. It is calculated 
based on the presence of illnesses described in the secondary diagnosis field within the HES dataset. </p>

<p>F238 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>frequently cited in the literature and stem from three aspects of the construction of the 
market structure measures. 
These different forms of bias could positively or negatively affect our estimates. First, 
the physical market size itself could be associated with hospital performance, which 
would bias our estimates upwards. For example, a high-quality provider might attract 
patients from a larger area, and hence appear to be operating in a less concentrated 
market. Second, the actual patient flows that are used to estimate market shares (and 
form the key component of the HHI) could be associated with quality because high 
quality providers could attract all the local business and as a result appear to be 
operating in more concentrated markets and bias our estimates downwards. Third, the 
actual location of hospitals and of new market entrants may be associated with per-
formance. For example, if new hospitals were reluctant to locate near high quality 
providers, this would artificially show high quality providers to be operating within 
concentrated markets and bias our estimates of the treatment effect downwards. 
In addition to concerns about endogeneity, there are also fears that the various 
measures of market structure will be spuriously correlated with urban population 
density, which stem from two causes. First, densely populated cities have more hospitals 
within smaller geographic areas, and as a result, urban areas will likely appear more 
competitive. Second, measures of market structure that are calculated within fixed 
geographic markets may be biased because the time it takes to travel 30 km in an urban 
area will differ significantly from the time it takes to travel 30 km in a rural area. 
In our estimates of market structure, we calculate competition within the market for 
elective secondary care for NHS funded patients. We focused on competition for elective 
care because this was the only hospital market where competition occurred during the 
time period we are studying. We study five high volume procedures -hip replacement, 
knee replacement, arthroscopy, hernia repair and cataract repair -and develop com-
posite measures of market structure, which are weighted averages of the competition 
measures that we calculated for each of the individual procedures. The bulk of our 
measures of market structure are based on actual patient flows. However, Kessler and 
McClellan (2000) have suggested that any measures of market structure based on actual 
patient flows could be endogenous to hospital quality because they may be correlated 
with various unobserved characteristics of either patients or providers. As a result, in 
addition to using an instrumental variable strategy, we also estimate a measure of market 
structure, similar to the measure used in Kessler and McClellan (2000), which is based on 
predicted patient flows generated from models of patient choice. 
We centre all of our markets on GP practices, rather than on hospitals, because this 
mirrors the post-2005 NHS market structure, where patients select their hospital in 
conjunction with their GP (Dixon et al., 2010). In addition, were we to centre our 
measures of market structure on hospitals, then there is the risk that if unobserved 
determinants of hospital choice are correlated with patient characteristics, there could 
be spurious and problematic associations between health status and market structure. 
To measure market concentration using actual patient flows, we calculate the neg-
ative natural logarithm of an HHI (nlhhi) based on hospitalsÕ market shares. This 
transformation is convenient because the nlhhi increases with competition, with zero 
corresponding to monopoly and infinity to perfect competition. In addition, this 
measure is equivalent to the natural log of the number of equal size firms in the </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F239 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>market, which makes interpreting the index more intuitive. Thus, for given market area 
j, our concentration index is: </p>

<p>nlhhi j ¼ À ln 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>n ^ </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>N j </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>¼ ln 
1 
hhi j </p>



<p>¼ lnðequivalent number of equal sized providersÞ 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>Here, n k is the number of procedures carried out at hospital k within market j and N j 
is the total number of procedures carried out in market j. Note that n k includes pro-
cedures performed at hospital k that were not referred from market j. 
We construct our preferred market definition as follows: consider an elective proce-
dure, e.g. hip replacements, in one year, e.g. 2002. We use matrices of patient flows from 
GP practices to hospitals for hip replacement in 2002 to deduce GP-centred markets. 
Specifically, we find the radius that represents the 95th percentile of distance travelled 
from a GP practice to hospitals for hip replacements in 2002. This defines the feasible 
choice set for patients at this GP practice in 2002. We then compute the HHI based on all 
hospitals providing hip replacements within this GPÕs market, regardless of whether 
this GP actually refers patients to all of these hospitals. This process is repeated for all GPs, 
for all years 2002-8 and for all five key elective procedures. A single elective HHI is 
calculated for each GP per year as a weighted average of the procedure-specific HHIs with 
weights proportional to the volume of patients in each procedure category. 17 
In addition to calculating this HHI within a variable radius market, we also compute 
a number of alternative HHIs using other market definitions. These include an HHI 
measured within a fixed radius market, which is derived in a similar way to the variable 
radius HHI described above, except that we use a fixed 30 km radius drawn around 
each GP practice in the country to delineate the market boundaries. The second 
alternative index is an HHI based on travel times along the primary road network from 
each GP. Here, we include hospitals in our relevant markets if they fall within a 30-min 
car ride from a referring GP. A third alternative is based on our 95% variable radius 
market but it does not treat sites within the same trust as competitors and only views 
sites from a different Trust as viable alternatives in the calculation of our HHI. We have 
also calculated our preferred purchaser-perspective measures using the count of hos-
pitals within each market in lieu of using HHIs. In addition, we calculate one measure 
of market concentration from the providerÕs perspective, where the market is centred 
on hospitals and the market is defined a fixed radius of 20 km drawn around each site. 
Alongside the HHIs we generated using actual patient flows, we also created an 
HHI derived from predicted patient flows that is based on the strategy used in Kessler 
and McClellan (2000). Building our predicted patient flow HHI is a two-step pro-
cedure. The first step involves estimating a patient choice model based on hospital 
and GP locations, and hospital and patient characteristics. 18 From this step we predict 
the number of patients each GP refers to their local hospitals, controlling for patient </p>

<p>17 It is important to note that GPs do not need to refer patients to a particular hospital within their market 
for the hospital to be included in the nlhhi associated with the GP. 
18 Patient characteristics included age, gender, socio-economic status and severity of illness. Provider 
characteristics included indicator dummies for teaching status, public or private ownership and FT status. 
Distance was measured as the straight-line distance from GPs to hospital sites. </p>

<p>F240 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>and provider characteristics and GP-hospital differential distances. We then use these 
numbers to generate the HHIs. 19 However, whereas Kessler and McClellan (2000) 
used a conditional logit to model patient choices, we use a Poisson regression on 
aggregate GP-hospital flows, which is equivalent but is simpler to compute (Gui-
maraes et al., 2003). 
As Table 1 illustrates, all these measures of GP-centred competition are moderately 
correlated. The indices from fixed radius and time-based market definitions are highly 
correlated. Indices based on market definitions using GP hospital flows are quite highly 
correlated with each other and only moderately correlated with the fixed distance and 
time-based indices. We favour the variable radius methods that infer markets from 
de-facto patient choices over hospitals, not least because this is less correlated with 
urban density. 20 
As a further check of robustness, we estimate (1) substituting an indicator variable 
for our competition measure, which is equal to one if a patientÕs GP practice is located 
in an urban area. 21 For further robustness, we also reconstruct the competition index </p>

<p>19 Following Kessler and McClellan (2000), we used these predicted counts (count jk ), which is the expected 
number of patients each GP j refers to hospital k in a given year to generate market shares, denoted a jk , for all 
hospitals k = 1,…,K, located within 100 km of j: </p>

<p>b a jk ¼ 
d 
count jk 
P K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>d 
count jk 
: </p>

<p>We then used these predicted market shares generated from the predicted count of patients referred from j 
to k to create GP-level HHIs. These GP-level HHIs were the sum of the squares of the predicted market shares 
of providers within 100 km of j: </p>

<p>HHI j ¼ 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>^ a 2 
jk : </p>

<p>This measure would be similar to our fixed radius HHIs centred on GP practices, except that the market 
shares used to create the HHI j would be based on predicted patient flows. Consistent with Kessler and 
McClellan (2000), we weight these GP HHIs by b jk , which is the share of patients from GP j which comprise 
the total activity of hospital k, in order to generate hospital level HHIs that are vary based on the competi-
tiveness of the various GP markets served by hospital k, such that </p>

<p>^ 
b jk ¼ 
d 
count jk 
P J </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>d 
count jk </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>and, </p>

<p>HHI k ¼ 
X J </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>^ 
b jk 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>^ a 2 </p>

<p>jk </p>

<p>! </p>

<p>¼ 
X J </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>^ 
b jk HHI j : </p>

<p>However, as Kessler and McClellan (2000) noted, since there is potential that unobserved determinants of 
patientsÕ hospital choice could be correlated with patientsÕ underlying health status, we assign HHI k back to 
GP practices based on the shares of patients from GP j treated at all hospitals k = 1,…, k located within a 
100 km radius of j: </p>

<p>HHI j Ã ¼ 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>^ a jk 
X J </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>^ 
b jk 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>^ a 2 </p>

<p>jk </p>

<p>! 
" 
# </p>

<p>¼ 
X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>^ a jk HHI j </p>

<p>This HHI j* is calculated for all years and for all five procedures and then averaged across the five procedures 
weighted by the total volume of each procedure performed per year. Thus, this measure varies both by year 
and by GP. 
20 This is easily seen when our various concentration measures are superimposed onto a map of England. 
These mappings are available from the authors on request. 
21 A GP is located in an urban area if the local output area falls within urban settlements with a population 
of 10,000 or more, according to the UK Office of National Statistics -available at http://www.statistics.gov.uk/ 
geography/census_geog.asp. </p>

<p> 
F241 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>using the shares of secondary school pupils in schools within our GP-centred markets 
(defined by the 95% referral radius during the pre-policy period) for use in a placebo 
test. These tests are designed to confirm that our results are driven by competition, 
rather than spurious associations with urban density. </p>

<p>3.4. Instrumental Variable Estimation </p>

<p>In an effort to thwart the endogeneity that we described earlier, in addition to creating 
HHIs from predicted patient flows, we have also developed an instrument for com-
petition. Our preferred instrument takes advantage of the historically determined 
hospital locations in England and is based on the variation in distance to a patientÕs 
nearest four hospitals. Specifically, our instrument for market structure is the standard 
deviation of distances from GPs to their nearest four hospitals, conditional the on the 
distance to the patient's nearest hospital (a control which we introduce in order to 
control for potential urban ⁄ rural differences in GP location). This IV strategy rests on 
the fact that NHS hospital and GP relative positions are unrelated to hospital quality, 
which is supported by the fact that hospital locations in England are largely a historical 
artefact which have not changed substantially since the NHS was founded in 1948 
(Klein, 2006). 
To illustrate our IV strategy, imagine two hospital markets centred on two indi-
vidual GP practices (A and B). The nearest provider in the area of GP A is located at 
5 km, and the remaining three at 15, 20 and 30 km. The nearest provider to GP B is 
also at 5 km, but with the remaining three all within 10 km (in different directions). 
In this situation, while the distance to the nearest provider is the same in both 
cases, the alternatives available to patients of GP B are much more substitutable than 
the alternatives available to patients of GP A because they are all within a similar 
travel distance, so patients of GP A are much more likely to attend the nearest 
provider. We therefore assume that GP-centred markets characterised by a high 
dispersion in distances to local providers are low choice and therefore low com-
petition markets. 
In practice, we have three instrumented variables, which include the baseline meas-
ure of market structure, the pre-policy time trend interacted with market structure and 
the post-policy time trend interacted with market structure. We perform our IV with a 
2SLS estimator and include GP and hospital fixed effects. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Correlations Between Different Measures of Market Structure </p>

<p>Àlog(HHI)À 
95% </p>

<p>Àlog(HHI)À 
30 km </p>

<p>Àlog(HHI)À 
30 min </p>

<p>Àlog(HHI)-
predicted 
flows 
Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Àlog(HHI)-95% 
1.00 
0.7483 
0.5639 
Àlog(HHI)-30 km 
0.48 
1.00 
1.4860 
0.9053 
Àlog(HHI)-30 min 
0.43 
0.92 
1.00 
1.2686 
0.8081 
Àlog(HHI)-predicted flows 
0.47 
0.92 
0.86 
1.00 
1.0458 
0.5930 </p>

<p>Notes. HHI, Herfindahl-Hirschman Indexes. </p>

<p>F242 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>4. Results </p>

<p>4.1. Empirical Results </p>

<p>Our estimation sample contains 433,325 patients who had an AMI between 2002 and 
2008. There are 227 hospital sites providing care for AMI for patients who were 
registered at 7,742 GP practices. Hospital quality, measured by 30-day AMI in-hospital 
mortality, improved consistently from 2002 to 2008, as shown in Table 2. Likewise, 
the number of AMIs treated per year also fell. This reduction in mortality and 
reduction in overall AMI occurrences is consistent with international trends and is 
driven, in part, by increasing adoption of new technology in the treatment of AMI 
and improvements in public health (Committee on Second Hand Smoke Exposure 
and Acute Coronary Events, 2009; Meyers et al., 2009; Schroeder, 2009; Walker et al., 
2009). The coefficient of variation in 30-day mortality rates between hospitals was 
approximately 30% per year, suggesting that there is significant variation in outcomes 
between providers. 
Table 3 provides OLS estimates of the DiD specification of (1) using our pre-
ferred empirical specification and index of market structure (the nlhhi using the 
95% GP market described in Section 3.3 and restricting b 6 = b 7 = 0 as discussed in 
Section 2.3). The variables of interest in our sample are described in Appendix B. 
Our main interest is in the coefficient on the interaction between the 2006-8 trend 
and our market structure index. This coefficient is b 4 in (1) and it estimates the 
impact of our policy by measuring the effect of greater competition on the quar-
terly reduction in AMI mortality after patient choice and competition were intro-
duced in 2006. 
Table 3 reports several versions of our preferred specification, where we have 
included and excluded patient characteristics, hospital and GP fixed effects. The 
results presented in Table 3 illustrate that our main finding is not highly sensitive to 
the control variables we include in our estimator. In each specification in Table 3, we 
find that after the formal introduction of choice in 2006, mortality decreased more 
quickly in more competitive markets. The coefficient of our interaction term is nearly </p>

<p>Table 2 
Thirty-day Patient-level AMI Mortality from 2002 to 2008 </p>

<p>Year 
Population treated 
Mean mortality 
Standard deviation </p>

<p>2002 
64933 
0.1563 
0.3631 
2003 
64776 
0.1506 
0.3576 
2004 
66226 
0.1415 
0.3485 
2005 
62433 
0.1396 
0.3465 
2006 
59760 
0.1309 
0.3373 
2007 
59017 
0.1247 
0.3304 
2008 
56180 
0.1196 
0.3245 
2002-8 
433,325 
0.1381 
0.3451 </p>

<p>Notes. Observations are limited to patients between 39 and 100 years of age with a length of stay greater than 
two days, treated at sites that treated more than 99 AMIs per year. Unlike the regressions that we present, we 
do not limit the distance that patients travelled for care. AMI, acute myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F243 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>identical in all specifications and it remains negative and significant with and without 
GP and hospital fixed effects or the exclusion of patient characteristics. Column (5) is 
our overall preferred specification and includes both GP and hospital fixed effects, 
which control for the possibility of changing GP, patient and hospital composition in 
high competition and low competition areas. Based on the coefficient of interest in 
Column (5) from Table 3, taking a one standard deviation gap in nlhhi (=0.565) as our 
benchmark, 30-day AMI mortality fell 0.31 percentage points faster per year after the 
reforms for patients treated in more competitive markets (=0.564 Â 0.0014 Â 4, 
because the time trends are quarters). Framed differently, the shift from a market with 
two equally sized providers to one with four equally sized providers after the reforms 
would have resulted in a 0.39 percentage point faster reduction in AMI mortality per 
year from 2006 onwards. 
An essential observation from Table 3 is that the pre-policy trend in AMI mortality in 
areas with uncompetitive market structures is not statistically different from the trend 
in markets with competitive structures once we control for patient characteristics. The 
coefficient on the 2002-5 Trend Â nlhhi interaction is near zero and statistically insig-
nificant in all specifications other than Column (1), which includes no control vari-
ables. This shows that these different markets were balanced in terms of the mortality 
trends pre-reform, and allays fears that the DiD results simply pick up pre-existing 
differences in trends. The full set of results from our overall preferred specification are 
presented in Appendix C. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Least Squared Estimates of (1) with Market Structure Measured as the nlhhi Within a 
Market That Captures all Hospitals Within the 95th Percentile of each GP's Maximum 
Travel Distance </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend 
À0.0018*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0026 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0024*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0023*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0024*** 
(0.0002) 
2006-8 Trend 
À0.0004** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0004) 
2002-5 Trend Â nlhhi 
0.0004* 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0003 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0002 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0001 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0002 
(0.0002) 
2006-8 Trend Â nlhhi 
À0.0013** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0013** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0013** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014*** 
(0.0005) 
nlhhi 
À0.0017 
(0.0023) </p>

<p>0.0020 
(0.0022) </p>

<p>À0.0015 
(0.0028) </p>

<p>À0.0014 
(0.0027) </p>

<p>À0.0015 
(0.0028) </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
No 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Hospital fixed effects 
No 
No 
Yes 
No 
Yes 
GP fixed effects 
No 
No 
No 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
422,350 
422,350 
422,350 
422,350 
R 2 
0.036 
0.105 
0.126 
0.125 
0.126 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Dependent variable = 1 if patient 
died within 30 days of their admission to hospital following an emergency AMI. Hospital characteristics: 
hospital type (foundation trust, teaching hospital or traditional acute hospital), number of AMIs treated at 
the hospital per year. Patient characteristics: age, gender, Charlson comorbidity score and patient socio-
economic status measured using the income component of the 2004 Index of Multiple Deprivations at the 
output area. Standard errors are clustered on GP-practices. AMI, acute myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>F244 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Table 4 shows that the results we observed in Table 3 are not highly sensitive to 
the choice of which market structure index we use to define the treated groups. 22 It 
presents OLS estimates of (1) using seven separate measures of market structure. Our 
findings remain consistent and significant across the seven different measures of 
market structure. The coefficient on the interaction between market structure and the 
2006-8 trend is always negative and significant, illustrating that higher competition was 
associated with higher quality (lower mortality), regardless of how we quantified market 
structure. Column 3 includes estimates of competition where we fix the nlhhi in time as 
the average of the 2002-5 nlhhis, which uses pre-reform patient flows from a time 
period where patients had no choice over their provider (hence the patient flows are 
likely unrelated to quality). In addition, in Column (6) we have also presented a </p>

<p>Table 4 
Least Squared Estimates of (1) Using Seven Alternative Measures of Market Concentration </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend 
À0.0024*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0024*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0022*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0026*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0026*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0023*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0028*** 
(0.0002) 
2006-8 Trend 
À0.0018*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0016*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0020*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0012** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0015** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>0.0005 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0014** 
(0.0005) 
2002-5 Trend Â nlhhi 
0.0002 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0003 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0000 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>0.0003* 
(0.0001) </p>

<p>0.0003* 
(0.0001) </p>

<p>0.0002 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0006** 
(0.0002) 
2006-8 Trend Â nlhhi À0.0012* 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0015** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0017* 
(0.0007) </p>

<p>À0.0009** 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>À0.0009** 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>À0.0009** 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>À0.0012** 
(0.0004) 
nlhhi 
-
À0.0026 
(0.0032) </p>

<p>À0.0022 
(0.0042) </p>

<p>0.0036 
(0.0070) </p>

<p>0.0013 
(0.0067) </p>

<p>0.0099 
(0.0061) </p>

<p>0.0091 
(0.0073) </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Hospital fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
GP fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
422,350 
382,026 
439,365 
437,185 
421,094 
461,508 
R 2 
0.126 
0.126 
0.127 
0.126 
0.126 
0.126 
0.124 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Column (1) nlhhi = negative ln of 
HHI within 95% variable market with competition measured as the average HHI between 2002 and 2005 prior to 
the reforms; column (2) nlhhi = negative ln of HHI within 95% variable market where competition is measured 
between hospital trusts, not sites; column (3) nlhhi = negative ln of HHI within 75% variable radius market; 
column (4) nlhhi = negative ln of HHI within fixed 30 km radius market; column (5) nlhhi = negative ln of HHI 
within market defined by 30-min drive time from each GP practice; column (6) nlhhi is centred on hospitals and 
defined within a 20 km fixed radius; column (7) nlhhi = negative log of HHI based on predicted patient flows. 
Dependent variable = 1 if patient died within 30-days of their admission to hospital following an emergency AMI. 
Hospital characteristics: hospital type (foundation trust, teaching hospital or traditional acute hospital), 
number of AMIs treated at the hospital per year. Patient characteristics: age, gender, Charlson comorbidity score 
and patient socioeconomic status measured using the income component of the 2004 Index of Multiple 
Deprivations at the output area. 
Standard errors are clustered on GP-practices. HHI, Herfindahl-Hirschman Indexes; AMI, acute myocardial 
infarction. </p>

<p>22 Note that we limit observations in our analysis to patients who travelled for care within their relevant 
geographic market. For example, if we measured competition within fixed 30 km markets, we limited our 
observations who travelled less than 30 km for care. We introduced this limit so that if a patient had a heart 
attack away from home, it would not indicate that their local market structure was associated with the location 
where they received care. This is why the number of observations in our analysis varies according to the 
measure of market structure used in the particular estimation. </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F245 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>measure of market structure centred on hospitals. Finally, Column (7) includes 
estimates of our treatment effect where market concentration is measured using pre-
dicted patient flows similar to those used by Kessler and McClellan (2000). 
In addition to using HHIs, in Table 5 we also present least squares estimates of (1) 
using logged hospital counts within each market definition to calculate market struc-
ture across the country. While counts are not as sensitive to the underlying market 
characteristics as an HHI, they do not rely on patient flows and serve as a robustness 
check on our HHI estimations. We calculate count measures of competition in four 
market definitions -two separate variable radius markets, a fixed radius market and a 
time-based radius market. The counts are logged so our estimates are more easily 
comparable to the nlhhis. Regardless of the count-based market structure measure that 
we use, we consistently find that the interaction term of interest is negative and sig-
nificant, indicating that a competitive market structure was associated with a statistically 
significant reduction in AMI mortality after 2006 with estimates that are a similar 
magnitude to those we generated measuring market structure using HHIs. 
To illustrate that our findings are the result of changes in hospital quality, rather 
than the by-product of different patient populations living in high versus low compe-
tition regions, we estimated (1) using hospital Â year fixed effects. Hospital interactions 
on year fixed effects should capture improvements in quality from hospitals year to 
year. When we estimated (1) and included hospital Â year fixed effects interactions, as 
anticipated, it washes out the effect of competition. </p>

<p>Table 5 
Least Squared Estimates of (1) with Market Concentration Measured as the Natural Log 
of the Count of Hospitals Within Four Market Definitions </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend 
À0.0025*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0023*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0026*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0027*** 
(0.0002) 
2006-8 Trend 
À0.0013** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0015*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0012* 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>À0.0013* 
(0.0005) 
2002-5 Trend Â count 
0.0002 
(0.0001) </p>

<p>0.0001 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>0.0002* 
(0.0001) </p>

<p>0.0003* 
(0.0001) 
2006-8 Trend Â count 
À0.0009** 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>À0.0016*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0008** 
(0.0003) </p>

<p>À0.0008** 
(0.0003) 
count 
À0.0031 
(0.0019) </p>

<p>À0.0006 
(0.0027) </p>

<p>0.0049 
(0.0058) </p>

<p>0.0032 
(0.0058) </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Hospital fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
GP fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
382,026 
439,365 
433,699 
R 2 
0.126 
0.127 
0.126 
0.126 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Column (1) 95% variable market; 
column (2) 75% Variable market; column (3) Fixed 30 km radius market; column (4) market defined 30-min 
travel time from each GP. Dependent variable = 1 if patient died within 30-days of their admission to hospital 
after an emergency AMI. Hospital characteristics: Hospital type (foundation trust, teaching hospital or tra-
ditional acute hospital), number of AMIs treated at the hospital per year and patient characteristics: age, 
gender, Charlson comorbidity score and patient socioeconomic status measured using the income compo-
nent of the 2004 Index of Multiple Deprivations at the output area. Standard errors are clustered on GP-
practices. AMI, acute myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>F246 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>4.2. Test of Functional Form </p>

<p>Table 6 presents additional estimates of our treatment effect using different function 
functional forms discussed in Section 2.3, and shows some tests on the various 
parameter restrictions in the general model of (1). In addition to our preferred esti-
mator, we estimate the treatment effect using a traditional DiD regression (Column 1), 
added the post-policy dummy and a post-policy * market structure interaction to our </p>

<p>Table 6 
Alternative Regression Specification with Market Structure Measured as the nlhhi Within a 
Market that Captures all Hospitals Within the 95th Percentile of each GP's Maximum 
Travel Distance </p>

<p>Standard difference-in-
difference </p>

<p>Time trend interactions &amp; 
post * nlhhi interaction </p>

<p>Year-post 
dummies * nlhhi </p>

<p>Post 
À0.0267*** 
(0.0020) </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend 
À0.0023*** 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>2003_Post 
À0.0072* 
(0.0032) 
Post Â nlhhi 
À0.0038* 
(0.0019) </p>

<p>2006-8 Trend 
À0.0013** 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>2004_Post 
À0.0123*** 
(0.0031) 
Nlhhi 
À0.0030 
(0.0022) </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend Â nlhhi 
0.0000 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>2005_Post 
À0.0097** 
(0.0032) 
2006-8 Trend Â nlhhi 
À0.0015** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>2006_Post 
À0.0091** 
(00033) 
nlhhi 
0.0004 
(0.0035) </p>

<p>2007_Post 
À0.0027 
(0.0035) 
Post 
À0.0024 
(0.0029) </p>

<p>2008_Post 
À0.0082* 
(0.0036) 
Post Â nlhhi 
0.0029 
(0.0031) </p>

<p>2003_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>À0.0023 
(0.0036) 
2004_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>0.0027 
(0.0034) 
2005_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>0.0025 
(0.0035) 
2006_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>À0.0015 
(0.0038) 
2007_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>À0.0077* 
(0.0038) 
2007_Post Â 
nlhhi </p>

<p>À0.0018 
(0.0037) 
nlhhi 
À0.0001 
(0.0031) 
F-test p-value 
All time trends 
0.0000 
Trends * nlhhi 
0.0018 
Post &amp; post * nlhhi 
0.4470 </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Hospital fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
GP fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
422,350 
422,350 
R 2 
0.125 
0.126 
0.126 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Dependent variable = 1 if patient 
died within 30-days of their admission to hospital following an emergency AMI. Hospital characteristics: 
Hospital type (foundation trust, teaching hospital or traditional acute hospital), number of AMIs treated at 
the hospital per year. Patient characteristics: age, gender, Charlson comorbidity score, patient socioeconomic 
status measured using the income component of the 2004 Index of Multiple Deprivations at the output area. 
Standard errors are clustered on GP-practices. AMI, acute myocardial infarction. </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F247 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>preferred spline estimator (Column 2), and shown the most general specification with 
year dummies and year dummies interacted with market structure (Column 3). Note 
the specification in Column 3 is set up so that the coefficients show the marginal 
change from the previous year. 
As Table 6 illustrates, our estimates of the treatment effect of competition are not 
substantively dependent on the functional form of our estimator. The simple DiD 
estimator in column 1 shows a fall in mortality in high competition areas relative to low 
competition areas after the policy-on date. The estimates presented in the second 
column of Table 6 suggest that there was not a discrete jump in performance in 2006 
and provides support for our preferred spline specification that is predicated on the 
presence of a more gradual improvement in performance. We provide some formal 
tests for these restrictions in Column 2. The joint test of significance of all the spline 
coefficients gives a p-value less than 0.01, the test for the two coefficients on the 
interaction between the splines and market structure index is 0.001. In contrast, the 
joint test of the coefficients on the post-policy dummy and post-policy Â market structure 
interaction gives a p-value of 0.447. These tests provide evidence in favour of our spline-
based, difference-in trends specification. 
In the third column, with the most flexible non-parametric specification, the coef-
ficients of interest on the year Â market structure interactions are negative in 2006, 2007 
and 2008. Although these last semi-parametric estimates are imprecise, the drop in the 
2007 period is significant at 5% and the general pattern of point estimates is broadly in 
line with our main results. 
Figure 2 plots the predicted mortality rates over time using the point estimates from 
this semi-parametric procedure, by way of illustrating the general pattern, which our 
estimates are trying to uncover. The dashed line shows the prediction for concentrated 
market structure locations (i.e. with the market structure index set to zero, 
corresponding to one hospital), which represent the counterfactual of what would have 
happened to AMI mortality in the absence of the reforms. The solid line shows the </p>

<p>-0.03 </p>

<p>-0.02 </p>

<p>-0.01 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 2008 </p>

<p>1 Site 
90th Percentile </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Changes in Predicted Mortality Rates Over Time in Monopoly Markets with One-Site Providing 
Care and in Markets in the Most Competitive Decile of Our Market Structure Index </p>

<p>F248 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>pattern for competitive market structures, with the index set to the top decile 
(nlhhi = 1.55). Both plots are normalised to zero in 2006. The plots show clearly that 
the trends tracked together prior to the reform date, but diverged from 2005 ⁄ 6 on. The 
picture supports our main finding that locations with less concentrated markets that 
were most exposed to the effects of the reforms sustained a higher and improved rate 
of decline in mortality rates than the counterfactual areas that remained less exposed 
to competition. </p>

<p>4.3. Other Tests of Robustness and Instrumental Variables Estimates </p>

<p>Table 7 presents robustness checks to illustrate that the effect we identify in our 
interactions between our post-2006 time trend and our measure of market structure are 
not simply spurious associations with urban density or driven by problematic (endo-
genous) associations between market structure and firm performance. In Column (1), 
we present interactions between the time trends and an indicator variable for whether 
or not the patientÕs local hospital market is located in a city, substituted for the measure 
of market structure. 23 The interaction term between the city indicator and our 
post-policy trend is not significant and is approximately half as large as our main </p>

<p>Table 7 
Additional Robustness Tests </p>

<p>Test of urban 
effect </p>

<p>School competition 
falsification test </p>

<p>Instrumental 
variable estimate </p>

<p>2002-5 Trend 
À0.0025*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0028*** 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>À0.0030*** 
(0.0005) 
2006-8 Trend 
À0.0004 
(0.0007) </p>

<p>0.0003 
(0.0008) </p>

<p>À0.0017 
(0.0010) 
2002-5 Trend Â 
market structure </p>

<p>0.00034 
(0.0004) </p>

<p>0.0002 
(0.0001) </p>

<p>0.0011 
(0.0006) 
2006-8 Trend Â 
market structure </p>

<p>À0.0007 
(0.0008) </p>

<p>À0.0002 
(0.0002) </p>

<p>À0.0031* 
(0.0014) 
Market structure 
-
-
0.0107 
(0.0261) </p>

<p>Patient characteristics 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Hospital fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
GP fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
414,230 
425,408 
R 2 
0.126 
0.126 
0.105 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Dependent variable = 1 if patient 
died within 30-days of their admission to hospital following an emergency AMI. Hospital characteristics: 
Hospital type (foundation trust, teaching hospital or traditional acute hospital), number of AMIs treated at 
the hospital per year. Patient characteristics: age, gender, Charlson comorbidity score, patient socioeconomic 
status measured using the income component of the 2004 Index of Multiple Deprivations at the output area. 
Standard errors are clustered on GP-practices for the IV and falsification test. Standard errors are clustered on 
hospitals for the hospital centred fixed-radius HHI. AMI, acute myocardial infarction; HHI, Herfindahl-
Hirschman Indexes. </p>

<p>23 Within our HES data, the area is defined as a city if the population within the hospitalÕs output area is 
greater than 10,000. We also estimated an interaction between our time trends and a London dummy and this 
was also not significant. </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F249 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>estimate. In Column (2), we present a Ôplacebo ⁄ falsificationÕ test in which we replace 
hospital market structure with a measure of market structure amongst state secondary 
schools. Clearly, if choice and competition in the health service drive our results, we 
would not expect to see a significant impact from schooling structure on AMI mortality 
rates in response to the NHS choice reforms. In contrast, if we are simply picking up 
changes in mortality trends in dense versus less dense places, then the market structure 
in schooling is just as likely to produce a Ôfalse positiveÕ result. Reassuringly, the coef-
ficient on the interaction between post-reform trends and schooling structure is near 
zero and insignificant. 
The third column of Table 7 presents our instrumental variables estimates. We 
instrument market structure using variation of the straight-line distance from each GP 
to the nearest four elective providers, controlling for the distance to the patient's 
nearest provider. The F-tests on our instrumented variables are significant (p &lt; 0.001) 
with F-statistics of 207.32, 209.76 and 75.41, respectively for the 2002-5 Â market 
structure term, the 2006-2008 Â market structure term and the baseline market structure. 
In addition, the signs on the standard deviation coefficients in the first stage are 
negative suggesting that higher standard deviations are associated with lower nlhhis. 
The IV estimates show a similar pattern to the OLS results in Table 3. The point 
estimate on our coefficient of interest is more than double that in the equivalent OLS 
specification, although the standard errors are also higher and the Hausman test 
indicates no statistically significant difference between the IV and OLS coefficient. 
There is no evidence from the IV estimates that it is the endogeneity of market 
structure to health service quality that drives our findings. Appendix D. includes the 
first stage estimates from our IV estimator. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>There has been significant debate over the potential for hospital competition to 
improve hospital quality. This debate has been particularly intense in England, where 
two successive UK governments have experimented with introducing hospital competi-
tion into the tax-funded English NHS. Previous experience with hospital competition 
in England has not been positive. Looking at the 1990s internal market, Propper et al. 
(2004, 2008) found that higher competition was associated with higher AMI mortality. 
This is consistent with speculation that in markets where hospitals can compete on 
price and quality, price is likely to decrease but so too is quality (Gaynor, 2004). 
This article looks at the more recent wave of market-based reforms in the English 
NHS. In the latest wave of reforms, patients were given the ability to select their 
secondary care provider, prices were regulated by the UK Department of Health, and 
hospitals could only compete on quality. We exploit the introduction of patient choice 
in 2006 to determine whether increases in hospital competition in a market with fixed 
prices led to improvements in hospital quality. Consistent with previous work exam-
ining the relationship between competition and quality, we measure hospital quality 
using 30-day mortality from AMI. 
In our analysis, we find that higher competition was associated with a faster decrease 
in 30-day AMI mortality after the formal introduction of patient choice in January 2006. 
Our results are robust to a number of specifications and definitions of market con-</p>

<p>F250 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>centration and consistent with our tests of the counterfactuals. The title of our article 
asked whether or not hospital competition saved lives. Judging from the impact of the 
reforms on 30-day AMI mortality, the reforms did save lives. Based on the results from 
our preferred specification, we can provide an indicative estimate that the reforms 
resulted in approximately 300 fewer deaths per year after the reforms were introduced 
in 2006 (based on a mean nlhhi of 0.748, an average 70,000 AMI cases in each year, and 
the coefficient in Table 3 Column (4): 70,000 Â 4 Â 0.0014 Â 0.748). Crucially, this 
estimates is for lives saved by reducing AMI mortality alone and ultimately, AMI mor-
tality only accounts for approximately 0.5% of total NHS hospital admissions. So, given 
that we postulate that AMI mortality is correlated with quality across hospitals, in 
practice, the lives saved from the reforms when estimated across the NHS and all 
dimensions of service provision are likely to be significantly higher. 
We posit that the improvements we observe in hospital quality were driven by 
increases in competition for elective care. Competition in the elective market in 
England likely prompted hospitals to take a number of steps to improve clinical 
performance, such as undertaking clinical audits, tightening clinical governance, 
making investments in new technology and improving hospital management. Those 
improvements spurred on by elective competition likely resulted in across-the-board 
improvements in hospital quality. These general quality improvements, we argue, are 
likely captured by our chosen indicator of quality, 30-day AMI mortality, where there is 
a close link between timely and effective medical interventions and patient survival 
(Bradley et al., 2006; Jha et al., 2007). 
Thus, our results suggest that, in contrast to what Propper et al. (2008) observed for 
the 1990s internal market, competition in the current fixed price market did save lives. 
These results are consistent with Kessler and McClellan (2000) and Kessler and 
Geppert (2005) that were focused on hospital competition in the US and found that 
hospital competition within a market with fixed prices led to an increase in hospital 
quality, as indicated by a reduction in AMI mortality. Our results add support to current 
efforts in England to increase the amount of publicly available information on quality 
and promote hospital competition in the absence of price competition. 
The conclusion, then, is that hospital competition, introduced in a fixed priced 
market, can lead to an increase in the quality of hospital services, as economic 
theory would predict. The rise in quality we have observed in the wake of the most 
recent NHS reforms has undoubtedly increased consumer welfare. We postulate that 
given the level of quality improvements that can be attributed to these reforms these 
results are consistent with an overall improvement in social welfare. However, more 
research needs to be carried out to evaluate this latter assertion empirically. </p>

<p>Appendix A: Bias Mitigation from Using Non-elective Outcomes When 
Competition is Measured by Elective Procedures </p>

<p>The pervasive problem in studies of the effects of elective market structure on hospital quality is that 
the measures of market structure are endogenous to quality in cross-sectional analysis. Our main 
strategy in this article for solving this problem is to use the timing of the NHS reforms interacted with </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F251 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>measures of market structure to provide an exogenous source of variation in competition over time. 
We back this up with estimates based on market structure indices predicted from exogenous char-
acteristics (the Kessler and McClellan (2000) index) and instrumental variables based on dispersion 
in GP-hospital distances. We also argue that using non-elective AMI procedure mortality as a 
quality indicator mitigates (though does not eliminate) the potential bias from the endogeneity of 
market structure indices to elective health care quality. Our reasoning is set out below. 
The underlying parameter we would like to estimate is the causal effect of the market structure 
for electives comp_e on latent hospital quality q. Note, by definition, choice is only operational for 
electives, so it is only elective procedures that provide any quality incentives to hospitals. For 
simplicity, assume that quality is influenced by elective market structure and by an exogenous 
quality component u: </p>

<p>q ¼ b comp e þ u 
ðA:1Þ </p>

<p>There are possibly many potential measures of hospital quality q based on different procedures j. 
Shock v_j captures idiosyncratic procedure-specific quality differences and v_j is assumed 
uncorrelated with q and uncorrelated with v_k, for j 6 ¼ k: </p>

<p>q j ¼ q þ v j </p>

<p>so substituting in (A.1) </p>

<p>q j ¼ b comp e þ u þ v j </p>

<p>An inherent endogeneity issue arises in estimating this equation for elective procedures </p>

<p>q e ¼ b comp e þ u þ v e 
ðA:2Þ </p>

<p>The measured market structure comp_e is dependent partly on exogenous geographical factors 
w, but also partly on patient choices in response to observed elective quality e.g.: </p>

<p>comp e ¼ c q e þ w 
ðA:3Þ </p>

<p>or in reduced form </p>

<p>comp e ¼ p ðu þ v eÞ þ n </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>p ¼ c=ð1 À cbÞ and n ¼ w=ð1 À cpÞ </p>

<p>So the bias in using elective procedures as a quality measure in (A.2) is: </p>

<p>cov½comp e; ðu þ v eÞ=varðcomp eÞ ¼ p varðu þ v eÞ=varðcomp eÞ 
¼ p varðuÞ=varðcomp eÞ þ p varðv eÞ=varðcomp eÞ </p>

<p>Now, suppose we have an alternative measure of quality from non-elective AMI outcomes: </p>

<p>q a ¼ q þ v a </p>

<p>So what we estimate now is: </p>

<p>q a ¼ b comp e þ u þ v a </p>

<p>Now the bias is: </p>

<p>cov½comp e; ðu þ v aÞ=varðcomp eÞ ¼ p varðuÞ=varðcomp eÞ </p>

<p>&lt; p varðuÞ=varðcomp eÞ þ p varðv eÞ=varðcomp eÞ </p>

<p>(as long as Var(v_e) &gt; 0, and c &gt; 0 in (A.3)). </p>

<p>F252 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Put simply, the bias in using elective procedures includes an additional bias induced by people 
choosing hospitals based on all dimensions of elective quality (general and idiosyncratic). For 
AMIs, this bias is reduced since individuals do not generally have a choice over where they receive 
care and the bias is only attributable to the components of AMI quality that are shared with 
elective quality, not to the idiosyncratic part of elective quality. </p>

<p>Appendix B: Key Summary Statistics </p>

<p>Variable name 
Variable description 
Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation Minimum Maximum </p>

<p>Death_30 
Death_30 is a binary indicator that 
equals 1 if the patient died within 
30-days of being admitted with 
an AMI </p>

<p>0.1369 
0.3437 
0 
1 </p>

<p>Age 
Age is the age of the patient 
71.4371 
12.8655 
40 
99 
Female 
Female is an indicator that equals 1 
if the patientÕs gender is female </p>

<p>0.3813 
0.4857 
0 
1 </p>

<p>IMD_Income_2007 
IMD_Income_2007 is score of 1-5 
based on the income component 
of the 2007 index of multiple 
deprivations. </p>

<p>3.1607 
1.3982 
1 
6 </p>

<p>Tradiditional_NHS* Traditional_NHS is an indicator that 
equals 1 if the hospital where the 
patient received care is not a 
foundation trust or teaching hospital </p>

<p>0.7239 
0.4471 
0 
1 </p>

<p>Teaching* 
Teaching is an indicator variable that 
equals 1 if the hospital where the 
patient is treated is a teaching 
hospital </p>

<p>0.1458 
0.3529 
0 
1 </p>

<p>FT* 
FT is an indicator variable that equals 
1 if the hospital where the patient is 
treated is a foundation trust </p>

<p>0.1605 
0.3671 
0 
1 </p>

<p>Charlson_Score 
The Charlson comorbidity score is an 
index ranging from 0 to 6, based on 
the patientÕs co-morbidities. Six is 
the most severe. </p>

<p>1.7047 
1.0543 
0 
12 </p>

<p>Angioplasty 
Angioplasty is an indicator variable 
that equals 1 if the patient 
underwent an angioplasty during 
his ⁄ her admission </p>

<p>0.0543 
0.2267 
0 
1 </p>

<p>Negloghhi 30 km 
Negloghhi30 km is the negative log of 
the HHI measured using a 
fixed radius that is centred on each 
GP practice and averaged across 
2002 to 2005 </p>

<p>1.4768 
0.9186 
0 
3.6085 </p>

<p>Negloghhi 30 band 
Negloghhi30band is the negative log 
of the HHI measured using a 
variable radius that is defined by the 
30-min travel time surrounding each 
GP practice and averaged across 
2002 to 2005 </p>

<p>1.2526 
0.8141 
0 
3.2266 </p>

<p>Negloghhi 95 
Negloghhi95 is the negative log of the 
HHI measured using a variable 
radius that captures the 95th 
percentile of travel for each GP 
practice </p>

<p>0.7349 
0.5561 
0 
3.728348 </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F253 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Appendix B: (Continued) </p>

<p>Variable name 
Variable description 
Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
deviation Minimum Maximum </p>

<p>Neglohhhi 20 
Negloghhhi20 is the negative log of 
the HHI measured using a fixed 
radius of 20 km drawn around each 
hospital and averaged across 2002 to 
2005 </p>

<p>1.0069 
0.9292 
0 
3.3369 </p>

<p>Log G_Count_30mins Log G_Count_30Band is the logged 
count of hospitals within a variable 
radius that captures a 30-min travel 
time surrounding each GP practice 
and averaged across 2002 to 2005 </p>

<p>1.5651 
0.8600 
0.0000 
3.4657 </p>

<p>Log G_Count_30km 
Log G_Count_30 km is the logged 
count of hospitals within a fixed 
radius that extends 30 km around 
each GP practice </p>

<p>1.7806 
0.9723 
0.0000 
3.8501 </p>

<p>Log G_Count_95sh 
Log G_Count_95 is the logged count 
of the hospitals within a radius 
defined by the distance that captures 
the 95th percentile of travel for each 
GP practice and averaged across 2002 
to 2005 </p>

<p>1.3985 
0.7113 
0.0000 
3.7992 </p>

<p>Distance 
Distance is the straight-line distance 
that each patient travelled for care 
measured in kilometres </p>

<p>13.3152 
28.4493 
0.0000 
607.5968 </p>

<p>Site Activity 
The number of heart attack patients 
each hospital treats annually. </p>

<p>483.9835 233.7503 100 
1,312 </p>

<p>Notes. *The cumulative sum of Traditional NHS, FT and Teaching is greater than 1.00 because hospitals can 
be both teaching hospitals and foundation trusts. Observations are limited to patients between 39 and 
100 years of age with a length of stay greater than two days, treated at sites that treated more than 25 AMIs per 
year. Unlike the regressions that we present, we do not limit the distance that patients travelled for care. AMI, 
acute myocardial infarction; NHS, National Health Service; FT, foundation trust; HHI, Herfindahl-Hirsch-
man Indexes. </p>

<p>Appendix C: Least Squared Estimates of (1) with Competition Measured as the 
Negative ln of the HHI Within a Market That Captures All Hospitals Within the 
95th Percentile of each GPÕs Maximum Travel Distance </p>

<p>Coefficient 
Standard error </p>

<p>2002-2005 Trend 
À0.0024*** 
0.0002 
2006-2008 Trend 
0.0014** 
0.0004 
2002-2005 Trend Â nlhhi 
0.0002 
0.0002 
2006-2008 Trend Â nlhhi 
À0.0014** 
0.0005 
Negloghhi95 
À0.0014 
0.0028 
Female 
0.0124*** 
0.0012 
Charlson2 
0.0361*** 
0.0013 
Charlson3 
0.0776*** 
0.0021 
Charlson4 
0.1242*** 
0.0034 
Charlson5 
0.1399*** 
0.0055 
Charlson6 
0.1928*** 
0.0071 
IMD Income 2 
0.0011 
0.0018 
IMD Income 3 
0.0055* 
0.0018 
IMD Income 4 
0.0046* 
0.0019 
IMD Income 5 
0.0059* 
0.0021 </p>

<p>F254 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Appendix C: (Continued) </p>

<p>Coefficient 
Standard error </p>

<p>Age 45-49 
À0.0016 
0.0022 
Age 50-54 
0.0053* 
0.0021 
Age 55-59 
0.0125*** 
0.0021 
Age 60-64 
0.0263*** 
0.0021 
Age 65-69 
0.0446*** 
0.0022 
Age 70-75 
0.0741*** 
0.0023 
Age 75-79 
0.1157*** 
0.0023 
Age 80-84 
0.1539*** 
0.0024 
Age 85-89 
0.1974*** 
0.0027 
Age 90+ 
0.2564*** 
0.0035 
Teaching 
À0.0056 
0.0123 
FT 
0.0050* 
0.0022 
Site Activity (150-300) 
À0.005 
0.0037 
Site Activity (300-450) 
À0.0180*** 
0.0039 
Site Activity (450 + ) 
À0.0254*** 
0.0042 
Distance 
0.0008*** 
0.0002 
Angioplasty 
À0.0460*** 
0.0023 
February 
À0.0042 
0.0026 
March 
À0.0093*** 
0.0025 
April 
À0.0060* 
0.0025 
May 
À0.0100*** 
0.0025 
June 
À0.0120* 
0.0025 
July 
À0.0110*** 
0.0025 
August 
À0.0103*** 
0.0026 
September 
À0.0109*** 
0.0026 
October 
À0.0068** 
0.0025 
November 
À0.0044 
0.0026 
December 
À0.0025 
0.0025 
Tuesday 
À0.0062*** 
0.0018 
Wednesday 
0.0000 
0.0018 
Thursday 
À0.0027 
0.0018 
Friday 
À0.0234*** 
0.0017 
Saturday 
0.0910*** 
0.0025 
Sunday 
0.2400*** 
0.0035 
North East Â Year 
À0.0003 
0.0001 
Yorkshire and Humber Â Year 
À0.0001 
0.0001 
North West Â Year 
0.0001* 
0.0000 
East Midlands Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
West Midlands Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
East of England Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0001 
South East Coast Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
South Central Â Year 
À0.0001 
0.0001 
South West Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Hospital Fixed Effects 
Yes 
GP Fixed Effects 
Yes </p>

<p>N 
422,350 
R 2 
0.126 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 10% level. ** Significant at 5%. *** Significant at 1%. Dependent variable = 1 if patient 
died within 30-days of their admission to hospital. Standard errors are clustered on GP-practices. Reference 
categories: Male, Charlson1, IMD-Income1, Age 40-44, Traditional NHS Trust, Site Activity (0-150), January, 
London SHA. FT, foundation trust; HHI, Herfindahl-Hirschman Indexes; SHA, Strategic Health Authorities. </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F255 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Appendix D: First Stage of IV Estimate -Dependent Variable: 2002-2005 Â nlhhi </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
Standard error </p>

<p>2002-2005 Trend 
1.0261*** 
0.0153 
2006-2008 Trend 
0.4037*** 
0.0222 
Female 
À0.0063 
0.0183 
Charlson 2 
À0.0061 
0.0197 
Charlson 3 
À0.0300 
0.0295 
Charlson 4 
À0.0376 
0.0436 
Charlson 5 
0.0223 
0.0734 
Charlson 6 
À0.1546 
0.0878 
IMD Income Vector -2 
À0.0018 
0.0302 
IMD Income Vector -3 
À0.0029 
0.0309 
IMD Income Vector -4 
À0.0044 
0.0318 
IMD Income Vector -5 
À0.0374 
0.0339 
Age 45-49 
À0.0564 
0.0725 
Age 50-54 
À0.0259* 
0.0676 
Age 55-59 
À0.1098 
0.0646 
Age 60-64 
À0.0393 
0.0628 
Age 65-69 
À0.0669 
0.0617 
Age 70-74 
À0.0172 
0.0629 
Age 75-79 
À0.0222 
0.0620 
Age 80-84 
À0.0135 
0.0615 
Age 85-89 
À0.0046 
0.0640 
Age 90 + 
À0.0487 
0.0681 
Teaching Hospital 
À0.6379 
0.3280 
Foundation Trust 
À1.7376*** 
0.1669 
Angioplasty 
À0.0564 
0.0729 
Hospital Volume (150 AMIs -299) 
À0.0381 
0.1715 
Hospital Volume (300 AMIs -449) 
À0.2220 
0.1899 
Hospital Volume (450 AMIs +) 
0.5298* 
0.2155 
Distance to Nearest Provider 
À0.0002 
0.0001 
Distance to Second Nearest Provider 
0.0000 
0.0000 
Distance to Third Nearest Provider 
0.0000 
0.0000 
Distance to Fourth Nearest Provider 
À0.0001*** 
0.0000 
February 
À0.0533 
0.0366 
March 
À0.0574 
0.0356 
April 
À0.0607 
0.0375 
May 
À0.0900* 
0.0370 
June 
À0.0003 
0.0370 
July 
À0.1184* 
0.0391 
August 
À0.0663 
0.0398 
September 
À0.1409*** 
0.0396 
October 
À0.2610*** 
0.0419 
November 
À0.2006*** 
0.0413 
December 
À0.2095*** 
0.0406 
North East Â Year 
À0.0180 
0.0125 
Yorkshire and Humber Â Year 
À0.0085 
0.0066 
North West Â Year 
0.0062 
0.0042 
East Midlands Â Year 
À0.0028 
0.0003 
West Midlands Â Year 
0.0018 
0.0006 
East of England Â Year 
À0.0004 
0.0010 
South East Cost Â Year 
0.0032 
0.0004 
South Central Â Year 
À0.0042 
0.0006 
South West Â Year 
À0.0039 
0.0046 
Tuesday 
À0.0478 
0.0273 
Wednesday 
À0.0637 
0.0284 
Thursday 
0.0076 
0.0269 
Friday 
À0.0181 
0.0266 
Saturday 
À0.0034 
0.0332 
Sunday 
À0.0369 
0.0414 </p>

<p>F256 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>AppendixD:FirstStageoftheIVEstimates-DependentVariable:2006-2008 Â nlhhi </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
Standard error </p>

<p>2002-2005 Trend 
0.0375*** 
0.0025 
2006-2008 Trend 
1.0843*** 
0.0120 
Female 
0.0048 
0.0070 
Charlson 2 
À0.0035 
0.0073 
Charlson 3 
À0.0094 
0.0111 
Charlson 4 
À0.0176 
0.0166 
Charlson 5 
0.0084 
0.0280 
Charlson 6 
À0.0299 
0.0344 
IMD Income Vector -2 
À0.0004 
0.0114 
IMD Income Vector -3 
0.0041 
0.0116 
IMD Income Vector -4 
0.0110 
0.0118 
IMD Income Vector -5 
À0.0062 
0.0123 
Age 45-49 
À0.0040 
0.0267 
Age 50-54 
À0.0020 
0.0249 
Age 55-59 
À0.0345 
0.0236 
Age 60-64 
À0.0059 
0.0231 
Age 65-69 
À0.0076 
0.0227 
Age 70-74 
0.0103 
0.0229 
Age 75-79 
0.0015 
0.0229 
Age 80-84 
0.0058 
0.0224 
Age 85-89 
0.0124 
0.0238 
Age 90 + 
À0.0091 
0.0258 
Teaching Hospital 
À0.7666*** 
0.1115 
Foundation Trust 
À0.6250*** 
0.0626 
Angioplasty 
À0.0998** 
0.0299 
Hospital Volume (150 AMIs -299) 
À0.3386*** 
0.0681 
Hospital Volume (300 AMIs -449) 
À0.3902*** 
0.0744 
Hospital Volume (450 AMIs +) 
À0.0083 
0.0821 
Distance to Nearest Provider 
À0.0001 
0.0000 
Distance to Second Nearest Provider 
0.0000 
0.0000 
Distance to Third Nearest Provider 
0.0000 
0.0000 
Distance to Fourth Nearest Provider 
0.0000*** 
0.0000 
February 
0.0032 
0.0120 
March 
À0.0085 
0.0117 
April 
0.0305* 
0.0127 
May 
0.0095 
0.0128 
June 
0.0275* 
0.0126 
July 
0.0317 
0.0140 
August 
0.0470** 
0.0141 
September 
0.0246 
0.0140 
October 
0.0287 
0.0154 
November 
0.0560*** 
0.0150 
December 
0.0587*** 
0.0145 
North East Â Year 
À0.0089 
0.0054 
Yorkshire and Humber Â Year 
À0.0048 
0.0038 
North West Â Year 
0.0018 
0.0013 
East Midlands Â Year 
À0.0013 
0.0001 
West Midlands Â Year 
0.0012 
0.0003 
East of England Â Year 
0.0001 
0.0003 
South East Cost Â Year 
0.0015 
0.0002 
South Central Â Year 
À0.0010 
0.0002 
South West Â Year 
À0.0030 
0.0030 
Tuesday 
À0.0133 
0.0106 
Wednesday 
À0.0184 
0.0107 
Thursday 
0.0003 
0.0103 
Friday 
À0.0014 
0.0101 
Saturday 
0.0125 
0.0128 
Sunday 
À0.0121 
0.0154 </p>

<p>2011 ] 
F257 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>Appendix D: First Stage of the IV Estimates -Dependent Variable: nlhhi </p>

<p>Variable 
Coefficient 
Standard error </p>

<p>2002-2005 Trend 
À0.0023** 
0.0007 
2006-2008 Trend 
0.0173*** 
0.0012 
Female 
À0.0018 
0.0010 
Charlson 2 
À0.0020 
0.0011 
Charlson 3 
À0.0043* 
0.0016 
Charlson 4 
À0.0036 
0.0023 
Charlson 5 
0.0022 
0.0039 
Charlson 6 
À0.0104* 
0.0045 
IMD Income Vector -2 
À0.0006 
0.0016 
IMD Income Vector -3 
0.0000 
0.0017 
IMD Income Vector -4 
À0.0025 
0.0017 
IMD Income Vector -5 
À0.0028 
0.0019 
Age 45-49 
À0.0053 
0.0040 
Age 50-54 
À0.0022 
0.0038 
Age 55-59 
À0.0027 
0.0037 
Age 60-64 
À0.0012 
0.0035 
Age 65-69 
À0.0044 
0.0035 
Age 70-74 
À0.0019 
0.0035 
Age 75-79 
À0.0034 
0.0035 
Age 80-84 
À0.0030 
0.0035 
Age 85-89 
À0.0026 
0.0035 
Age 90 + 
À0.0044 
0.0038 
Teaching Hospital 
0.0176 
0.0252 
Foundation Trust 
0.0388* 
0.0070 
Angioplasty 
0.0068 
0.0033 
Hospital Volume (150 AMIs -299) 
0.0018 
0.0092 
Hospital Volume (300 AMIs -449) 
0.0155 
0.0103 
Hospital Volume (450 AMIs +) 
0.0126 
0.0115 
Distance to Nearest Provider 
0.0000* 
0.0000 
Distance to Second Nearest Provider 
0.0000*** 
0.0000 
Distance to Third Nearest Provider 
0.0000 
0.0000 
Distance to Fourth Nearest Provider 
0.0000*** 
0.0000 
February 
À0.0036 
0.0021 
March 
À0.0031 
0.0021 
April 
À0.0067 
0.0022 
May 
À0.0071 
0.0021 
June 
À0.0005 
0.0021 
July 
À0.0095*** 
0.0022 
August 
À0.0104*** 
0.0022 
September 
À0.0127*** 
0.0023 
October 
À0.0164*** 
0.0023 
November 
À0.0145*** 
0.0023 
December 
À0.0135*** 
0.0023 
North East Â Year 
0.0001 
0.0004 
Yorkshire and Humber Â Year 
0.0003 
0.0003 
North West Â Year 
0.0005 
0.0003 
East Midlands Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
West Midlands Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
East of England Â Year 
À0.0001 
0.0001 
South East Cost Â Year 
0.0001*** 
0.0000 
South Central Â Year 
0.0000 
0.0000 
South West Â Year 
0.0004 
0.0004 
Tuesday 
0.0012 
0.0015 
Wednesday 
0.0011 
0.0016 
Thursday 
0.0015 
0.0015 
Friday 
0.0000 
0.0015 
Saturday 
À0.0006 
0.0018 
Sunday 
À0.0007 
0.0023 </p>

<p>Notes. * Significant at 5% level. ** Significant at 1%. *** Significant at 0.1%. Error terms are clustered on GP 
practices. </p>

<p>London School of Economics </p>

<p>F258 
[ A U G U S T </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p> 
F259 </p>

<p>D O E S H O S P I T A L C O M P E T I T I O N S A V E L I V E S ? </p>

<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>Ó 2011 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>F260 
[ A U G U S T 2011] </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

</text></tei>