<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.20151404" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Almost all firms in developing countries have fewer than ten work-
ers, with a modal size of one. Are there potential high-growth entre-
preneurs, and can public policy help identify them and facilitate 
their growth? A large-scale national business plan competition in 
Nigeria provides evidence on these questions. Random assignment 
of US$34 million in grants provided each winner with approximately 
US$50,000. Surveys tracking applicants over five years show that 
winning leads to greater firm entry, more survival, higher profits and 
sales, and higher employment, including increases of over 20 per-
centage points in the likelihood of a firm having ten or more workers. 
 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>countries with the ability to grow a firm beyond this 10-worker threshold, and if so, 
whether policy can identify such individuals in advance and overcome their con-
straints to growth. 
I investigate these questions through the context of an evaluation of the impact 
of a national business plan competition in Nigeria. The YouWiN! competition was 
launched in late 2011 by the president of Nigeria, and in its first year attracted almost 
24,000 applications aiming to start a new business or expand an existing one. The 
top 6,000 applications were selected for a 4-day business plan training course, and 
then winners were chosen to receive awards averaging US$50,000 each, paid out in 
four tranche payments conditional on achieving basic milestones. The top-scoring 
plans overall and within region were chosen as winners automatically, and then 
729 additional winners were randomly selected from a group of 1,841 semifinalists, 
providing experimental variation from US$34 million in grants that enables causal 
estimation of the program's impact. Three annual follow-up surveys enable tracking 
the trajectory of impacts, with the third survey occurring 27 months after winners 
received their first grant payment and 12 to 18 months after the last payment. A final 
survey round conducted during an economic crisis in 2016 enables examination of 
impacts three years after all payments. 
I find that winning this competition has large positive impacts on both applicants 
looking to start new firms as well as those aiming to expand existing firms. Three 
years after applying, new firm applicant winners were 37 percentage points more 
likely than the control group to be operating a business and 23 percentage points 
more likely to have a firm with ten or more workers (relative to a control mean of 
11 percent), while existing firm winners were 20 percentage points more likely 
to have survived, and 21 percentage points more likely to have a firm with ten 
or more workers (relative to a control mean of 17 percent). The winners are also 
innovating more, and are earning higher sales and profits. There continue to be sig-
nificant impacts more than three years after all payment, during an economic crisis, 
although the magnitudes are smaller. Examining the channels of impact, I find the 
grants enabled firms to purchase more capital and hire more labor, with no changes 
in business networks, mentors, self-efficacy, or uses of other sources of finance. 
The results show there is a group of constrained entrepreneurs with the ability to 
grow their businesses beyond a small scale, and that the business plan competition 
was successful in both attracting such individuals, and in helping them overcome 
their constraints. 
This paper contributes to three main literatures. The first addresses the sources 
and constraints to job growth, which is one of the most fundamental concerns of 
policymakers globally. An increasing body of work examines which types of firms 
create more jobs, with recent evidence highlighting the importance of business start-
ups and young firms in job creation. 
2 Related work has found that a small number 
of firms, variously termed "gazelles," "high-growth entrepreneurs," or "high-impact 
firms" represent a tiny fraction of the overall firm population, but make a dispropor-
tionately large contribution to job growth. 
3 New job creation by firms is of particular </p>

<p>2 See, for example, Haltiwanger, Jarmin, and Miranda (2013) for the United States, and Ayyagari, 
Demirguc-Kunt, and Maksimovic (2014) for evidence from a range of developing countries. 
3 See reviews by Henrekson and Johannsson (2010) and the OECD (2010). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>importance in sub-Saharan Africa given that it currently has the lowest share of the 
labor force in wage work of any region in the world, and that demographic forces 
result in the working-age population growing 2.8 percent per year (ILO 2012). A 
long literature suggests that a perceived lack of high-growth entrepreneurship in 
many African countries (e.g., Elkan 1988; Omidyar Network 2013) may be in part 
due to multiple market failures that prevent individuals with good ideas from fund-
ing them. This paper provides empirical evidence that there are such potential high 
growth entrepreneurs who can grow rapidly if funded. 
Business plan competitions are starting to become one popular tool that seeks to 
foster high growth entrepreneurship. They seek to identify individuals with prom-
ising ideas and the aspiration to grow, help these individuals formalize these ideas 
through getting them to develop a detailed business plan, and then spur the devel-
opment of some of these potentially high growth firms through providing financing 
to the winners. While the first such competitions were held for business school stu-
dents in the United States they are now increasingly being used in developing coun-
tries. 
4 Examples include the MENA 100 business plan competition in 14 countries 
in the Middle East and North Africa since 2009, the GIST/I-Dare business plan 
competition for individuals from 28 developing countries, launched in 2011; and 
business plan competitions run by Technoserve throughout Central America since 
2002 (Klinger and Schündeln 2011). They are also starting to be used by the World 
Bank in several sub-Saharan African countries, including Côte d'Ivoire, Gabon, 
Guinea-Bissau, Rwanda, Senegal, Somalia, South Sudan, Tanzania, and Uganda. 
However, there is very little evidence as to the effectiveness of these programs. 
Many of the programs are small in nature, awarding fewer than ten prizes in any 
given year, limiting the sample size for evaluation. Programs explicitly try to select 
entrepreneurs with the best growth prospects, so that any comparison of winners and 
losers is likely to overstate the effects of the program due to selection bias. Klinger 
and Schündeln (2011) and Fafchamps and Quinn (forthcoming) attempt to address 
these issues by pooling together competitions run in multiple countries to get larger 
sample sizes of winners (although still fewer than 40 cash winners in either study), 
and use a regression-discontinuity approach to compare winners to those who just 
finished below them in rank. Both studies find impacts on business start-up or expan-
sion, and Fafchamps and Quinn (forthcoming) also find increased job creation in the 
first six months. In the one experimental study we are aware of, Fafchamps and 
Woodruff (2016) run a small business plan competition in Ghana, in which winners 
are selected to receive individualized training, but not cash. They find no significant 
impact of this individualized training on firm growth. This paper builds on this lit-
erature through experimental evaluation of a much larger sample, with substantial 
prizes, detailed surveys, and a longer time period for tracking winners. 
Finally this paper adds to a literature on how to generate entrepreneurship in 
developing countries, and in particular the role of capital in alleviating constraints. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The vast majority of this work has focused on microenterprises, typically with no </p>

<p>4 Lora Kolodny, "How to Win a Business Plan Competition," New York Times, June 10, 2009, http://www. 
nytimes.com/2009/06/11/business/smallbusiness/11competition.html (accessed March 18, 2014). 
5 The paper also contributes to a related debate in the literature as to whether a lack of capital constrains entre-
preneurs from growing and hiring employees, or whether it is other factors such as labor regulations, management 
ability, and the possibility that "transformational" entrepreneurs who aim to create large, vibrant businesses that </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>employees, with the emphasis on starting such businesses, and/or growing the 
incomes of their owners. This is the case with work testing small grants of US$100 
to US$200 to existing businesses (e.g., De Mel, McKenzie, and Woodruff 2008; 
McKenzie and Woodruff 2008; Fafchamps et al. 2014; Karlan, Knight, and Udry 
2015); ultra-poor programs providing grants and training to get very poor people to 
start businesses (e.g., Banerjee et al. 2015; Bandiera et al. 2017); and business train-
ing programs for microenterprises (reviewed in McKenzie and Woodruff 2014). 
Blattman, Fiala, and Martinez (2014) considers a program in Uganda where groups 
received grants of approximately US$382 per member, and finds this generates 
increases in skilled self-employment and in incomes for the recipients, but only 
minor increases in employment in these firms. Fafchamps and Quinn (forthcoming) 
provide grants of US$1,000 to their 39 winners. The grants studied here of almost 
US$50,000 per recipient are 50 to 500 times as large as the grants in these earlier 
studies. 
This difference in size is important for two reasons. First, even a standard concave 
production function with a low steady-state optimal size can exhibit high returns to 
capital for the first few dollars invested, so the fact that marginal returns from small 
grants have been high need not imply that capital is the constraint to growing larger 
firms who hire workers. Second, since the lending cost per dollar lent falls with loan 
size, credit market frictions are expected to be particularly binding for small loans, 
and one therefore might expect credit constraints to be less binding for larger invest-
ments. If credit constraints don't bind, then theory would predict the grants would 
merely supplement the wealth of business owners without changing their production 
decisions. Even with credit constraints, there is a question as to whether diminishing 
returns to capital results in grants of this size being far more than is needed to move 
businesses to their efficient size. The results in this paper show that the business 
plan competition is successful in identifying entrepreneurs with the potential to use 
these large amounts of capital, and that with this capital, they are able to generate 
enterprises that hire employees and exhibit rapid growth. </p>

<p>I. The Business Plan Competition </p>

<p>The Youth Enterprise With Innovation in Nigeria (YouWiN!) program is a busi-
ness plan competition for young entrepreneurs in Nigeria. 
6 It is a collaboration 
between the Ministry of Finance, the Ministry of Communication Technology, 
and the Ministry of Youth Development with support from the Department for 
International Development (DFID) and the World Bank. It has the stated objec-
tive of encouraging innovation and job creation through the creation of new busi-
nesses and expansion of existing businesses. It was formally launched on October 
11, 2011 by President Goodluck Jonathan in a ceremony aired live over the National 
Television network, and advertised through a variety of media events, roadshows, </p>

<p>grow and hire workers are fundamentally different from owners of microenterprises (Schoar 2010). The evidence 
here shows that there are individuals for whom capital is the key constraint. 
6 The business plan competition was run in four consecutive years. My analysis uses the first year of the pro-
gram, which was the only year a randomized experiment was implemented. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>and small and medium enterprise (SME) outreach events. Online Appendix 1 details 
the timeline of the project. 
The program provides a four-day training course on preparation of a business 
plan to applicants who make it through a first stage, and then grants to the winning 
1,200 submissions, with each winner eligible for an amount up to 10 million naira 
(approximately US$64,000), with the amount any winner getting varying between 1 
and 10 million naira depending on the funding needs identified in their business plan 
and the assessment of independent consultants of what the actual needs are. Winners 
also receive ongoing monitoring as the grant is paid in four tranches, coupled with 
some potential mentoring and two additional two-day group training events. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Figure 1 provides a schematic of the different phases of the competition. I sum-
marize the key aspects of these in the text, with additional details provided in online 
Appendix 2. </p>

<p>A. Eligibility and the First Stage Application </p>

<p>To be eligible for the program, applicants had to be Nigerian citizens aged 40 
or younger, proposing the creation of a new or expansion of an existing business 
venture within Nigeria that would employ Nigerians, and which did not involve the 
production or distribution of weapons, alcohol, tobacco, or gambling. They then 
needed to register on a website and submit an application by November 25, 2011. 
This application included basic personal information, proof of age and nationality, 
the proposed location of the business, along with information about their business 
idea (online Appendix 2 provides further details). Applicants were divided into 
six regional pools on the basis of the geopolitical zone in which they wanted to 
do business, with training also taking place in these different regional locations. 
23,844 applications were received, of which 3,614 (15 percent) were for existing 
business expansions and 20,230 were for new businesses. A minority of applicants 
were female: 18.5 percent of new business applicants and 14.9 percent of existing 
business applicants were female. </p>

<p>B. Application Scoring </p>

<p>Applications were scored by the Enterprise Development Center (EDC) of the 
Pan-African University, a sister institution of the Lagos Business School. Names 
and other identifying information were removed before scoring to increase the 
impartiality of this process. Marks were given for the quality and viability of the 
business idea, the amount of job creation likely, the abilities and market understand-
ing of the applicant, and the passion and commitment displayed in the application, 
and the likelihood of the proposed business succeeding. This first stage marking was 
a rapid assessment (taking approximately ten minutes per plan) given the vast num-
ber of applications and the short window for assessment before training was to start. 
There was a conscious decision to favor existing businesses over new businesses </p>

<p>7 A pool of volunteer mentors were available, although as we will see, the winners appear to have received no 
more mentoring than the control group. The additional training consisted of two 2-day bootcamps run by the UK 
school for start-ups covering cash-flow management, sales, purchasing, and team management. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>throughout the competition given the assumption that they had at least made the first 
step of establishing a business. An algorithm was then used to select 6,000 candi-
dates for the business plan training on the basis of location, type of business (new 
or existing), and score. </p>

<p>C. Business Plan Training </p>

<p>Business plan training took place between December 6 and December 20, 2011. 
Each of the six regions had a local training location. Of the 6,000 individuals selected 
to attend training, 4,873 attended (81 percent). The rapid rollout of the program and 
short amount of time (1-2 weeks) between notification of selection into the 4-day 
training session and it taking place is a likely reason for nonattendance. Biometric 
data (iris scans and fingerprints) were collected on all attendees to enable accu-
rate identification of individuals. Candidates who did not attend training were not </p>

<p>Figure 1. Competition Stages and Treatment Assignment </p>

<p>Notes: Regression-discontinuity sample of firms around the cutoff for being chosen for business plan training not 
shown. Non-experimental winner sample is only used for matching estimates in online Appendix 5. Survey num-
bers are for having data on firm operation. Online Appendix 8 provides other data on attrition. </p>

<p>First round application 
23,844 firms (3,614 existing, 20,230 new) </p>

<p>Top 6,000 chosen for 4-day business plan training with 
scoring cutoffs varying by region and new/existing 
6,000 firms (1,254 existing, 4,746 new) 
4,873 attend training </p>

<p>Submit detailed business plan for scoring 
4,510 firms (981 existing, 3,529 new) </p>

<p>Semi-finalists chosen on basis of score, with thresholds varying 
by region and new/existing 2,400 firms 
(596 existing, 1,804 new) </p>

<p>Non-experimental winners 
(selected on highest scores 
overall and within region, with 
preference for existing) 
475 firms 
357 existing 
118 new </p>

<p>Experimental Sample 
Dropped if score &lt;30 
79 firms 
disqualified 5 firms 
(randomly selected within 
strata defined by region, gender, 
and new/existing) 
1,841 firms (541 existing, 1,300 new) 
729 treatment (278 existing, 451 new) 
1,112 control (263 existing, 849 new) </p>

<p>Follow-up surveys 
Follow-up 1: 396 firms 
Follow-up 2: 439 firms 
Follow-up 3: 417 firms </p>

<p>Follow-up surveys 
Follow-up 1: 617 treat, 836 control 
Follow-up 2: 645 treat, 917 control 
Follow-up 3: 674 treat, 1011 control </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>eligible to submit a business plan. Online Appendix 2 provides detail on the content 
of the course. </p>

<p>D. Business Plan Submission and Business Plan Scoring </p>

<p>Applicants who had attended the training had until January 22, 2012 to sub-
mit the business plan. The business plan required much more detail than the first 
round concept note. In total 4,510 business plan applications were received, which 
is 92.5 percent of those who attended the training. The business plans were then 
scored by a joint EDC/PricewaterhouseCoopers team, with a team of 20 markers 
split evenly between the two organizations. Marking criteria were developed which 
focused on the market, management skills, business experience, articulating the 
risks and financing needs of the business, and job creation and cash flow prospects. 
A typical plan took 30-45 minutes to mark. </p>

<p>E. Selection of Winners </p>

<p>The business plans were narrowed down to 2,400 semifinalists by first selecting 
the highest scoring 450 existing businesses and highest scoring 150 new businesses 
nationwide, and then selecting the top scoring 300 plans per region after taking out 
these national top scores. Then from these 2,400 semifinalists, the following groups 
of winners were selected: </p>

<p>• 300 National Merit Winners: The 225 top-scoring existing business plans and 
75 top-scoring new business plans nationwide were selected as national win-
ners. This was done to ensure the highest-scoring proposals on pure merit were 
selected. 
• 180 Zonal Merit Winners (30 per region): After removing the 300 national merit 
winners, the highest-scoring 45 existing business plans and 15 new business 
plans per zone were selected as zonal finalists. Their proposals were reviewed 
by panelists of local entrepreneurs and local business leaders in each zone, who 
identified the best 30 out of the 60 zonal finalists to be zonal merit award win-
ners. The zonal finalists who were not selected were then placed back into the 
pool and were eligible to be selected as ordinary merit winners. 
• 720 Ordinary Merit Winners (120 per region): 120 ordinary winners per region 
were randomly selected from among the remaining 1,920 semifinalists using 
the lottery procedure described below. </p>

<p>F. Randomization Algorithm </p>

<p>Random selection of the ordinary winners was done for two main reasons. First, 
from an operational point of view, a competition run at this scale is not feasible 
to do with presentations in front of judges, and it was recognized that there would 
be inherent uncertainty in the scoring as to which applicants were best amongst 
the semifinalists. Moreover, in many developing countries there are concerns 
that programs get captured by individuals with certain political or ethnic ties, 
and it was felt randomizing gives people a fair chance and is less subject to this </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>perception risk. 
8 Second, random assignment enabled rigorous measurement of 
the program's impacts. 
The randomization procedure was designed as follows. First, among the semifi-
nalists, all those with business plan total scores below 30 were dropped, to maintain 
a minimum standard. This reduced the pool from 1,920 to 1,841 firms. Then a 
two-step stratified randomization was conducted by the author in <rs type="software">STATA</rs> to choose 
the ordinary winners: </p>

<p>(i) First, within each region, half of the existing firm business plans were ran-
domly chosen to be ordinary winners, with this selection stratified by gender. 
This reflected the preference of the government to again oversample existing 
business plans. </p>

<p>(ii) Then, the number of slots for new firm business plans was calculated per 
zone as 120 minus the number of existing business ordinary winners. This 
was subdivided into a number of slots for new businesses operated by men 
and new businesses operated by women in proportion to the share of women 
among new businesses in the pool in each region. Then the number of new 
firms dictated by the number of remaining slots was randomly chosen from 
the number of new firm semifinalists in each region and gender strata. </p>

<p>This gives an ordinary winner treatment group of 720 firms and an ordinary win-
ner control group of 1,121 firms. After quality checking which disqualified some 
winners, and redrawing of replacements (see online Appendix 2), of the 1,841 firms 
in the ordinary winner pool, we have a treatment group of 729 randomly assigned 
to treatment (of which 13 were disqualified). The control group consists of the 
1,112 firms randomly assigned to the control group (after the random replacement), 
of which 9 were nonrandomly selected to actually receive treatment. In terms of the 
impact evaluation, this will be handled through assignment to treat analysis. </p>

<p>G. Award Amounts and Payment </p>

<p>The amounts awarded were payable in four tranche payments. The first pay-
ment was typically around 10 percent of the total amount, with a second tranche 
payment averaging 45 percent of the total then payable for the purpose of physi-
cal capital acquisition and working capital. The third and four tranche payments 
were made conditional on employment and sales turnover triggers that were set 
individually for each firm based on their business plan projections. These triggers 
were deliberately set to be quite low, and were intended to ensure the business was 
set up and producing. The third tranche payment required sales turnover to have 
reached 25 percent of the first-year target annualized turnover set out in the business 
plan, with firm-specific employment triggers that averaged 3.7 workers. The fourth 
tranche payment required sales turnover to have reached 40 percent of the first-year </p>

<p>8 However, the fact that the ordinary winners were randomly chosen from amongst semifinalists was not 
announced to applicants; but rather was information that could be used in case of a complaint. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>annualized turnover goal, with firm-specific employment triggers that averaged 
5.5 workers. 
Online Appendix 3 summarizes the award amounts received by the winners. The 
mean (median) winner received a total award of US$49,000 (US$57,000). Only 6 
of the 1,200 winners received no payment (due to being disqualified, or in one case, 
withdrawing). A total of 1,168 winners (97.3 percent), including 96.8 percent of 
the experimental winners, received all four tranche payments, but the length of time 
taken to receive all four tranches varied across firms: 748 of the firms received their 
last tranche payment in June or July 2013, while the last 33 recipients got their last 
tranche in January 2014. </p>

<p>II. Verification of Random Assignment and Data Collection </p>

<p>A. Verification of Randomization and Characteristics of Winning Firms </p>

<p>Table 1 presents summary statistics for the treatment and control groups accord-
ing to assignment to treatment status for new and existing firms, as well as the 
characteristics of the non-experimental winners. The goal of the randomization is 
to ensure that the treatment and control groups are similar in terms of average char-
acteristics. This is tested formally through an F-test of joint orthogonality, which 
tests whether the observable characteristics in Table 1 are jointly unrelated to treat-
ment status. We cannot reject this null hypothesis, confirming that randomization 
has delivered balanced groups. In contrast the test rejects that the observable char-
acteristics of the national and zonal winners are similar to those of the experimental 
sample, even when excluding the business plan scores used to separate the groups. 
Table 1 is also useful for showing some basic characteristics of the experimen-
tal sample. We see the average existing firm owner is male, aged 32, with 4 years 
of business experience and running a business with a median of 5 workers. Half 
are married, and 10 percent have previously worked or lived abroad, and 65 per-
cent have university education. Only 7 percent have ever had a formal loan before 
for their business. New applicants are slightly younger, with an average age of 29, 
70 percent have university education, and they have higher business plan scores 
than the existing firm applicants on average, reflecting the preference for existing 
firm applicants at each stage. We see they come from relatively well-off households, 
with 85 percent having a computer at home and two-thirds having a satellite dish. 
The most common business sectors are manufacturing and crop and animal produc-
tion, sector is looked at in more detail below. The mean (median) annual turnover 
for existing businesses in the experimental sample is 5.6 million naira (1.5 million 
naira). The maximum grant of 10 million naira thus represents two years of turnover 
for the mean firm and more than six years for the median firm. 
Online Appendix 4 summarizes the main sectors that YouWiN! winners propose 
to operate their businesses in, based on the self-classification of applicants at the 
time of submitting their business plans. Agricultural production activities is the 
largest sector, accounting for one-third of winning new business applications and 
20 percent of existing business applications. Typical examples include plans to set 
up or expand poultry or catfish farms, and production of cashews, palm oil, and 
cassava. The second most common sector for existing firms is IT and computer </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>services, comprising 17 percent of existing firm winners, but only 7 percent of new 
firm winners. Typical examples include software and website development, repairs 
and installation, and computer training courses. Manufacturing is the second most 
common sector for new firms, comprising 13 percent, and third most common for 
existing firms, comprising 14 percent of winners. The products being manufactured 
are very heterogeneous, and include processed food products, books and media, 
metal products, chemicals and detergents, and a range of other products. Other 
industries includes a variety of different activities such as advertising, teaching, 
event management, photography, and filmmaking, as well as some activities that 
were a mix of other categories. </p>

<p>B. Data Collection </p>

<p>The follow-up surveys targeted the 729 individuals selected as ordinary win-
ners of the competition (the experimental treatment group), the 1,112 individu-
als in the experimental control group, as well as also surveying the 475 national </p>

<p>Table 1-Baseline Characteristics and Balance of Experimental Sample </p>

<p>Existing firms 
New firms </p>

<p>Non-
experimental 
winners </p>

<p>Treatment 
group </p>

<p>Control 
group </p>

<p>Non-
experimental 
winners </p>

<p>Treatment 
group </p>

<p>Control 
group </p>

<p>Applicant characteristics 
Female 
0.17 
0.18 
0.17 
0.19 
0.17 
0.18 
Age 
32.5 
32.0 
31.8 
30.1 
29.3 
29.6 
Married 
0.60 
0.50 
0.56 
0.42 
0.34 
0.36 
High school or lower 
0.10 
0.13 
0.12 
0.06 
0.11 
0.10 
University education 
0.71 
0.63 
0.67 
0.79 
0.69 
0.71 
Postgraduate education 
0.12 
0.08 
0.12 
0.13 
0.05 
0.06 
Lived abroad 
0.14 
0.10 
0.11 
0.18 
0.06 
0.09 
Choose risky option 
0.59 
0.56 
0.52 
0.63 
0.57 
0.55 
Have internet access at home 
0.68 
0.57 
0.61 
0.60 
0.47 
0.48 
Own a computer 
0.94 
0.87 
0.88 
0.92 
0.84 
0.86 
Satellite dish at home 
0.74 
0.67 
0.71 
0.64 
0.68 
0.64 
Freezer at home 
0.64 
0.57 
0.61 
0.63 
0.51 
0.55 </p>

<p>Business characteristics 
Crop and animal sector 
0.14 
0.16 
0.16 
0.22 
0.22 
0.22 
Manufacturing sector 
0.28 
0.28 
0.26 
0.23 
0.28 
0.24 
Trade sector 
0.05 
0.06 
0.05 
0.06 
0.04 
0.04 
IT sector 
0.14 
0.15 
0.14 
0.04 
0.07 
0.06 
First round application score 
59.0 
57.2 
56.6 
59.9 
59.9 
59.9 
Business plan score 
61.7 
45.8 
45.4 
74.4 
53.7 
55.5 
Number of workers 
9.11 
7.35 
7.73 
Ever had formal loan 
0.11 
0.06 
0.09 </p>

<p>Sample size 
357 
278 
263 
118 
451 
849 
Joint orthogonality test: treatment 
versus control </p>

<p>0.920 
0.884 </p>

<p>Joint orthogonality test: non-experimental 
versus treatment </p>

<p>0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>Joint orthogonality test: non-experimental 
versus treatment (no score) </p>

<p>0.012 
0.000 </p>

<p>Notes: p-values shown for joint orthogonality tests. Test for comparison of treatment and control conditions on 
regional strata. Existing firms and new firms refer to status at time of application. (no score) indicates the joint 
orthogonality test is conducted excluding the first round application score and business plan score. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>and zonal winners (excluding the 5 disqualified), and a sample of 823 applicants 
who had scores just on either side of the cutoff used to select people to attend the 
4-day business training course. These latter two groups are used for propensity 
score matching analysis of the impact of the program on non-experimental win-
ners (online Appendix 5), and regression-discontinuity analysis of the impact of the 
business plan training alone (online Appendix 6). 
Three annual follow-up surveys were taken, followed by a fourth, longer-term 
follow-up which is discussed in Section VI. Surveys took place nationwide via 
face-to-face interviews, supplemented by telephone interviews and web interviews 
when security concerns prevented travel, and to boost response rates. Surveys were 
conducted by TNS RMS Nigeria. In addition, an attempt was made through proxy 
interviews and two question interviews with refusals to ascertain whether individu-
als who could not be contacted or had refused were currently operating a business, 
and if so, the number of employees they had. Online Appendix 7 discusses the 
survey methodology in more detail and shows robustness of results to controls for 
survey type. 
The first follow-up survey took place between November 2012 and May 2013. 
This corresponds to approximately one year after individuals had first applied to 
the program, 8 months or more after the winners had been announced, and an aver-
age of 5 to 6 months since the winners received their first tranche payment. The 
median firm had received 4,000,000 naira ($US25,000) by the time of this survey. 
The response rate for the experimental sample was 75.6 percent (81.2 percent for 
treatment, 71.9 percent control). 
The second follow-up survey took place between October 2013 and February 
2014, approximately two years after application and just as firms had received their 
last tranche payments. This was an even more intensive effort in data collection, 
and achieved an 88.9 percent response rate (91.5 percent for treatment, 87.2 per-
cent for control). 
9 The third follow-up survey took place between September 2014 
and February 2015. This corresponds to 3 years after application, and between 12 
and 18 months after firms had received their last tranche payment from the pro-
gram. The response rate was 83.1 percent (87.0 percent for treatment, 80.5 percent 
for control). 
Online Appendix 8 reports further breakdowns on attrition by applicant type 
and treatment status. It then examines robustness to attrition in several ways. First, 
it shows that the responding sample remains balanced on baseline observable 
characteristics. Then it shows robustness to three different bounding approaches, 
to controlling for the application and business plan score, and to filling in missing 
data based on past operating status. The main results are robust to all but the worst 
case bounds, and even these bounds, which assume that all attritting control firms 
would be operating and all attritting treated firms would be closed, still show 
a positive treatment impact on business operation and on having more than ten 
employees. </p>

<p>9 Moreover, some of those not interviewed in round 2 were interviewed in round 1, so there are only 4 percent 
of the experimental sample for which we have no follow-up data in either of the first two rounds. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>III. Measuring the Impact of the Business Plan Competition: 
Theory and Empirical Approach </p>

<p>The main objective of the YouWiN! program was to generate jobs by encouraging 
and supporting aspiring entrepreneurial youth in Nigeria to develop and execute 
business ideas. I discuss first what theory suggests the likely impacts of the program 
will be, and then the empirical approach to measuring these impacts. Both the theory 
and empirical approach set out here were prespecified in advance through a regis-
tered pre-analysis plan. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>A. Theory: How Might Participating in the YouWiN! Program Lead 
to More Jobs and Higher Profits? </p>

<p>I consider a simple partial equilibrium model that provides a framework for 
understanding how the YouWiN! program might affect the performance of individ-
ual firms. This model is intended as a vehicle for organizing thoughts, rather than 
a fully specified model to calibrate. In complementary work, Buera, Kaboski, and 
Shin (2014, 2016) specify and calibrate macro models of occupational choice and 
entrepreneurship which they use to attempt to explain the impacts of different asset 
grant interventions (including this paper). Their results point to the importance of 
heterogeneity in talent, and financial frictions, but they are unable to explain the 
sustained increases in income seen amongst grants to microenterprises, nor changes 
in the size distribution of firms. 
Consider a simple model where a firm's production Y is a function f ( · ) of their 
productivity A, their capital stock K, the owner's entrepreneurial skill E, and outside 
labor L. 
11 The firm owner's problem is to choose K and L given A and E: </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>Y = f (A, K, E, L) . </p>

<p>With complete markets the firm production decision will be separable from the 
household consumption decision and firms will choose capital and labor such that 
their marginal products are equal to the market interest rate and market wage rate, 
respectively, </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>f K (A, K </p>

<p> *  , E, L </p>

<p> *  ) = r , </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>f L (A, K </p>

<p> *  , E, L </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>) = w . </p>

<p>10 See https://www.socialscienceregistry.org/docs/analysisplan/25/document. 
11 This model focuses on the implications for firm size, conditional on running a firm. For a model of the firm 
entry decision, see the online Appendix of Blattman, Fiala, and Martinez (2014). Similar to the model here, they 
note that an unrestricted grant will have no effect on the entry decision, and there is no permanent impact of a con-
ditional grant on occupational choice without credit constraints. 
12 In this simple model A, E, and f ( · ) are exogenous. However, some components of these can be chosen by 
firms by purchasing new technologies, hiring consultants to implement new processes, etc. For the purposes of this 
simple model, I consider these part of the choice of capital stock, and then the implications of the model are similar 
for these. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>In such a model, firm size is then completely determined by the talents of the firm 
owner, as in the seminal model of Lucas (1978). The answer in this simple model to 
the puzzle of why there are so many one-person firms in developing countries and 
so few larger firms (Hsieh and Olken 2014) is then that single person enterprises are 
the optimal scale given the talent of most of those engaging in entrepreneurship in 
these countries. I then examine the predictions of such a model for how YouWiN! 
should affect the production and firm size of winners. </p>

<p>Case 1 (Perfect Markets, YouWiN! Program Is Just a Grant): If firms are not 
credit-constrained and the program just changes the resources firm owners have 
available to them, then there is no change in the first-order conditions (2) and (3), 
and so no change in employment or output. The grant will merely make the owner 
richer, but not change their production decisions. This possibility is often a key 
concern of policymakers in any grants program, and is referred to as a lack of addi-
tionality, with the program just funding activities firms were going to do anyway. </p>

<p>Case 2 (Perfect Markets, YouWiN! Program Is a Conditional Grant): The 
YouWiN! program does not make a single lump sum grant to firm owners, but instead 
is payable in tranches, conditional on the firm owner taking certain actions-with 
the first and second tranches typically paying for more working capital and invest-
ment, and the third and fourth tranches being triggered by reaching jobs and turn-
over triggers. This conditionality does not fundamentally change the equilibrium 
first-order conditions, but can be viewed as causing a temporary increase in the 
returns to capital and labor in the firm. Therefore we would predict a short-term 
increase in capital and labor, which would then dissipate once all the tranche pay-
ments have been received. Once the final payments are received, we should see no 
difference between treatment and control firms as the treated firms reduce capital 
and labor to get back to the equilibrium levels. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Case 3 (YouWiN! Program is More Than Just a Grant): It is possible that par-
ticipating in, and especially winning, the YouWiN! program may also have other 
impacts on the productivity of the firm (A), and the skills of the owner (E ). The 
training offered could increase the entrepreneurial skills of the owner, although 
since the business plan training was also provided to the control group, this should 
change the first-order conditions similarly for both groups, and it would only be if 
the small amount of additional training increased skills that we should see a treat-
ment effect. If winning enables firm owners to meet other business owners or gain 
mentors, this could increase A and E. Winning might also change the confidence 
and attitudes, spurring the self-belief of the owner in the business and causing them 
to work harder; or alternatively, may dent the confidence of the control group. If </p>

<p>13 An exception to this prediction will occur if there is a flypaper effect, as in Fafchamps et al. (2014). In this 
case, firm owners may have suboptimally low levels of capital invested in their business as a result of self-control 
problems or external pressure, and the program may overcome these issues by directing capital into mental accounts 
for business use. In this case, there may be a long-term level effect on capital and profits. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>individuals invest on the basis of their beliefs about their talent (as in Jovanovic 
1982) rather than actual talent, this will change the first-order conditions. </p>

<p>Case 4 (YouWiN! Program with Capital and Labor Market Constraints): If firms 
are credit-constrained, then they invest less in their firms than optimal according to 
(2). Winning the YouWiN! program could reduce credit constraints in three ways: </p>

<p>(i) Directly by providing a grant to the firm; </p>

<p>(ii) Indirectly, through providing a signal of quality that leads to more bank lend-
ing and </p>

<p>(iii) Indirectly, through providing co-financing and a signal of quality that leads to 
more outside investments from partners. </p>

<p>The impact of these channels will be to increase capital stock. This may increase 
or decrease labor depending on the shape of the production function-a heavily 
credit-constrained firm may have previously substituted capital for labor, and so 
reduces workers once it can buy machines to replace them. Conversely, if capital and 
labor are complements in production, more capital will enable the firm to hire more 
workers. Profits should increase in either case. 
This simple model offers a lens through which to interpret the results of the exper-
iment, and highlights key mechanisms to examine in understanding these results. If 
either markets are complete, or the competition is not very good at identifying a 
group of high-ability entrepreneurs who are constrained, then we should expect no 
impact of the program unless it succeeds in increasing A and E for participants. In 
contrast, if capital constraints are important and the competition is able to attract 
entrepreneurs of sufficient ability, it should induce larger firm sizes for those who 
win. </p>

<p>B. Experimental Estimation </p>

<p>The main approach used for evaluating the impact of the program is to use the 
randomized controlled trial (RCT) based on the random selection of ordinary win-
ners from among the semifinalists. This is done separately for the new and existing 
business applicants, and involves regressions of the following form: </p>

<p>(4) 
Outcom e i = a + b × AssignTrea t i + c × Region × Gende r i + ε i . </p>

<p>Here AssignTreat denotes whether or not applicant i was randomly cho-
sen as an ordinary winner from among the semifinalist experimental pool, and 
region × gender controls for the randomization strata. Robust (Huber-White) 
standard errors are used. The coefficient b then gives the average effect of being 
assigned to receive a grant, the ITT estimate of the program's impact for firms in 
the experimental sample. Recall that 13 of the 729 winners were disqualified and 
so did not receive a grant, while 9 of the 1,112 control firms were nonrandomly 
selected to replace them. Since these compliance rates with treatment are so high, </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>the local average treatment effects of actually receiving the grant are similar to the 
intent-to-treat effects, and so we report just the ITTs. In order to estimate the trajec-
tory of impacts, I estimate the treatment effects separately by year. </p>

<p>IV. Results of the Impacts of the Business Plan Competition </p>

<p>The business plan competition had the stated objective of encouraging innovation 
and job creation through the creation of new businesses and expansion of existing 
businesses. I examine its success in achieving these outcomes by considering the 
impact on start-up and survival, the impact on innovation and employment, and then 
also examine how this translates into profitability and sales. 
Online Appendix 9 provides details on how key outcomes were measured. My 
main approach to deal with multiple hypothesis testing is to group the outcomes 
into domains or families, and then examine the impact on a natural aggregate 
(e.g., total employment, total capital stock) or standardized index measure (e.g., 
index of standardized z-scores for profit and sales outcomes) within each domain. 
In online Appendix 10, I also provide sharpened q-values that hold constant the 
false discovery rate when reporting results for specific outcomes-all outcomes in 
Tables 2-8 that have p-values below 0.10 also have sharpened q-values below 0.05. </p>

<p>A. Impacts on Start-Up and Survival </p>

<p>Table 2 examines the impact of the competition on whether applicants for new 
enterprises set up a business and have it subsequently survive (panel A), and whether 
applicants with existing enterprises have these businesses survive (panel B). The 
first three columns show the extensive margin of whether a firm operates or not, 
while the remaining three columns combine the extensive and intensive margins to 
consider how many hours a week the owner works in his or her own firm. Consider 
first the impacts on new enterprises. Fifty-five percent of those in the control group 
were operating a business at the time of the first follow-up survey, and 56.9 percent </p>

<p>Table 2-Impact on Start-Up and Survival </p>

<p>Operates a firm at time of survey </p>

<p>Weekly hours worked in 
self-employment </p>

<p>Round 1 
Round 2 
Round 3 
Round 1 
Round 2 
Round 3 </p>

<p>Panel A. New firms 
Experimental treatment effect 
0.215 
0.359 
0.373 
13.538 
21.699 
19.526 
(0.029) 
(0.023) 
(0.024) 
(1.961) 
(1.704) 
(1.748) </p>

<p>Sample size 
1,021 
1,181 
1,085 
993 
1,071 
927 
Control mean 
0.550 
0.569 
0.540 
24.9 
23.9 
19.4 </p>

<p>Panel B. Existing firms 
Experimental treatment effect 
0.083 
0.130 
0.195 
9.058 
8.643 
11.687 
(0.027) 
(0.025) 
(0.031) 
(2.653) 
(2.552) 
(2.492) </p>

<p>Sample size 
432 
505 
477 
423 
458 
409 
Control mean 
0.871 
0.844 
0.759 
43.3 
40.9 
31.6 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Existing and new refers to firm status at time of application. Rounds 1, 
2, and 3 are 1, 2, and 3 years after application. Regressions control for randomization strata. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>at the time of the second follow-up survey, and 54 percent in the last survey. The 
experimental estimate of the impact is 21.3 percentage points at the time of the first 
survey, 35.8 percentage points by the second survey, and 37.3 percentage points 
by the third survey. These effects are also large, positive, and strongly statistically 
significant ( p &lt; 0.000001). By the second and third follow-ups, the new applicant 
winners are spending twice as many hours a week working in self-employment than 
the control group. 
Panel B shows that winning also increases the survival rates of existing firm own-
ers. Eighty-seven percent of the control firms survived 1 year, 84.4 percent two 
years, and 75.9 percent three years. Winners had 8 percentage point higher survival 
rates in the first year, 13 percentage point higher survival rates in the second year, 
and 20 percentage point higher survival rates in the third year, with these results 
again strongly statistically significant. Winners are spending almost 12 more hours 
per week working in self-employment than the control group after 3 years. </p>

<p>B. Impacts on Employment </p>

<p>Generating employment was one of the main goals of the program. Our main 
measures of employment come from survey reports. The surveys asked detailed 
questions on employment in different categories, and questions on the most recent 
workers hired. Online Appendix 11 compares these reports to administrative data on 
the winners that came from program reports at around the same time as the second 
survey. The employment reported to the program is larger than that reported to our 
surveys in the majority of cases, and appears that the administrative data suffers 
from over-reporting biases. In contrast, comparison of our survey measures with 
physical observation where available suggests more confidence in the survey mea-
sures. I also return to this issue in further robustness checks in Section VII. 
Table 3 reports the impact of winning on key employment outcomes, while 
Figure 2 shows quantile treatment effect estimates of the impact on total employ-
ment in round 3. These are unconditional estimates, which code employment as zero 
for individuals not operating firms. Online Appendix 11 shows the descriptive com-
parison that treated firms are also hiring more workers than the control conditional 
on being in operation. 
The first column of Table 3 shows a positive impact on the employment status 
of the owner. The difference between these estimates and the impacts on start-up 
and survival in Table 2 reflects that some individuals would have been employed 
as wage workers had they not started or continued with their firms. Column 2 then 
considers total employment in the firm, which is the sum of the owner's employment 
in the firm, the number of wage and salary workers, and the number of daily and 
casual workers in the firm. The average control group firm among new applicants 
has 3.7 workers by the time of the third survey, with the treatment effect of 5.2 work-
ers more than doubling this average. The average control group firm among existing 
firm applicants has 5.6 workers by the time of the third survey, with the treatment 
effect of 4.4 workers representing an 80 percent increase. Impacts are larger in the 
second and third years once all the grants had been received than in the first year. 
The quantile treatment effect regressions show positive and significant effects across 
most of the distribution, with the effect size similar in magnitude to the regression </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>estimates between the thirtieth and ninetieth percentiles for new firms and the twen-
tieth and ninetieth percentiles for existing firms. Online Appendix 11 shows these 
increases in employment come from both more wage and salary workers, and from 
more casual and daily workers, with little change in unpaid workers. 
Our survey data asks more detailed questions on the three most recently hired 
workers each year. Only 5 percent of these are related to the owner, 33 percent 
are female, 45 percent have post-secondary education, and their average wage is 
22,400 naira/month (approximately US$143). The third-round survey also asked 
what these workers were doing before getting hired. Only 36 percent were working 
in another job, with the rest either unemployed or students. 
Column 3 examines the extent to which winning the competition has enabled 
firms to surpass the ten worker threshold. 
14 Amongst new firm applicants, we see 
that only 11 percent of the control group had reached this size three years after </p>

<p>14 Note this variable was not included in the pre-analysis plan. It was motivated by the definition of ten workers 
as a cutoff between micro and small businesses in many countries, and by the work of Hsieh and Olken (2014) 
noting this threshold as one that few firms in developing countries exceed. The results would be similar if we instead 
chose another binary threshold under 15 or 20 workers. </p>

<p>Table 3-Impact on Employment and Innovation </p>

<p>Own 
employment </p>

<p>Total 
employment </p>

<p>Firm of 10+ 
workers </p>

<p>Firm of 25+ 
workers </p>

<p>Innovation 
index </p>

<p>Panel A. New firms 
First follow-up 
0.074 
1.426 
0.024 
0.007 
0.099 
(0.025) 
(0.732) 
(0.020) 
(0.008) 
(0.019) </p>

<p>Second follow-up 
0.128 
6.012 
0.288 
0.022 
0.270 
(0.017) 
(0.412) 
(0.026) 
(0.009) 
(0.018) </p>

<p>Third follow-up 
0.119 
5.227 
0.229 
0.025 
0.219 
(0.018) 
(0.469) 
(0.028) 
(0.011) 
(0.019) </p>

<p>Control mean: first follow-up 
0.787 
3.618 
0.083 
0.010 
0.225 
Control mean: second follow-up 
0.841 
3.305 
0.088 
0.009 
0.214 
Control mean: third follow-up 
0.831 
3.773 
0.114 
0.014 
0.181 
Sample size: first follow-up 
1,021 
987 
987 
987 
995 
Sample size: second follow-up 
1,181 
1,159 
1,159 
1,159 
1,071 
Sample size: third follow-up 
1,085 
1,044 
1,044 
1,044 
927 </p>

<p>Panel B. Existing firms 
First follow-up 
0.047 
1.512 
0.057 
0.007 
0.105 
(0.019) 
(0.795) 
(0.041) 
(0.019) 
(0.029) </p>

<p>Second follow-up 
0.066 
2.556 
0.215 
0.009 
0.126 
(0.018) 
(1.388) 
(0.041) 
(0.018) 
(0.028) </p>

<p>Third follow-up 
0.070 
4.425 
0.208 
0.028 
0.141 
(0.022) 
(0.673) 
(0.040) 
(0.015) 
(0.029) </p>

<p>Control mean: first follow-up 
0.938 
6.852 
0.212 
0.032 
0.390 
Control mean: second follow-up 
0.922 
8.134 
0.231 
0.038 
0.407 
Control mean: third follow-up 
0.906 
5.571 
0.170 
0.014 
0.341 
Sample size: first follow-up 
432 
422 
422 
422 
423 
Sample size: second follow-up 
505 
500 
500 
500 
458 
Sample size: third follow-up 
477 
461 
461 
461 
409 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Regressions control for randomization strata. Existing and new refers 
to firm status at time of application. Rounds 1, 2, and 3 are 1, 2, and 3 years after application. Innovation index is 
an index of standardized z-scores of 12 different measures of innovative activity. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>applying, with treatment increasing this by 22.9 percentage points. Among existing 
firms, 17 percent of the control group were at this size after three years, with the 
treatment taking a further 20.6 percent to this level. Few firms have grown to the size 
of having 25 workers, but columns 4 and 8 of Table 3 show that by the third round 
the treatment has had a statistically significant 2.5-2.7 percentage point increase in 
this likelihood, relative to a control mean of only 1.4 percent. 
In online Appendix 11, I combine the estimates of the total employment effects 
per firm with the number of winning firms to generate an estimate of the overall 
difference in employment created between the winners and the control group. The 
experimental treated firms report a total of 6,858 workers employed at the time of the 
round 3 survey, of which I estimate that 3,579 are the program impact (95 percent CI 
is 3,061, 4,161), whereas the remaining workers would have been employed anyway. 
Adding in the propensity-score matching estimates for the impact on the national and 
zonal winners then gives a total of 7,027 jobs created from all winning firms. </p>

<p>C. Cost Effectiveness for Employment Generation </p>

<p>The first round gave the winners 9,240 million naira (US$58 million) in grants. 
The cost of administering the first round of programs, including scoring the applica-
tions, running the 4-day business plan training, and administering the tranche pay-
ments, is estimated at $2 million. At the end of the third year, the estimate from 
online Appendix 11 is that 7,027 jobs were directly generated in the treated firms as a 
result of the program. Thus the cost per job created in the winning firms is US$8,538 
(or $9,600 for just the firms in the experimental sample). Online Appendix 12 dis-
cusses the additional assumptions needed for this to represent net job creation for </p>

<p>Figure 2. Quantile Treatment Effects on Total Employment in Round 3 </p>

<p>Notes: New firms and existing firms refer to status at time of application. Round 3 is 3 years after application and 
12-18 months after all grants have been received. </p>

<p>−5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Total employment </p>

<p>−5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Total employment </p>

<p>5 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 95 
5 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 95 </p>

<p>Percentile </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>Quantile treatment </p>

<p>95% CI </p>

<p>Panel A. New firms </p>

<p>Percentile </p>

<p>Panel B. Existing firms </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>the economy as a whole, and compares this cost to other job creation policy efforts 
in developing countries. </p>

<p>D. Impact on Innovation </p>

<p>The other stated objective of the program was to encourage innovation. I measure 
12 different types of innovative activities and aggregate these into an index. The last 
column of Table 3 shows that winners are also innovating more. By the final survey 
round there is a 22 percentage point increase in innovative activities for experimen-
tal winners among new firms, and 14 percentage point increase for existing firms. 
Online Appendix 13 shows that the new applicants are innovating more in multiple 
dimensions, introducing new products, processes, pricing methods, quality control 
systems, using the internet, and using new channels for selling goods. As is standard 
in developing countries, most of this innovation involves moving toward the world 
frontier by introducing new products or processes that are new for the firm and often 
its city or neighborhood, but that are available elsewhere in the country or in the 
world. As such, they are similar to capital inputs, for which the alleviation of credit 
constraints allows more of these innovation inputs to be purchased. </p>

<p>E. Impacts on Profits and Sales </p>

<p>Table 4 reports the treatment impact on several measures of sales and profitabil-
ity, and Figure 3 shows quantile treatment effects on profits. The quantile treatment 
effects for the last survey round show positive and significant impacts on firm profits 
for all quantiles between the twentieth and the eighty-fourth for new firm appli-
cants, and for all quantiles between the twelfth and the seventy-sixth for existing 
firm applicants. However, there is zero effect at the bottom of the distribution (since 
profits are zero for firms that don't operate), and very wide standard errors for the 
top quantiles (reflecting a long upper tail). This results in low statistical power for 
looking at impacts on the levels of profits. 
I use three prespecified approaches to deal with these issues, and in online 
Appendix 14 also examine robustness to several alternative approaches. The first 
prespecified approach was to truncate monthly profits and sales at the ninety-ninth 
percentile to reduce the influence of outliers. This transform still leaves a very dis-
persed long tail, and a standard deviation of profits that is two to three times the 
mean, resulting in low power. The second alternative prespecified approach was to 
consider the inverse hyperbolic sine transformation of profits, which is similar to a 
log transformation, but allows for zeros and negative values. Third, I use an overall 
index of standardized z-scores which considers multiple profit and sales measures, </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>with this latter measure also providing a summary measure to account for multiple 
hypothesis testing. </p>

<p>15 These include other measures like asking for annual sales, whether sales were higher than one year ago, and 
profits in the best month. In the first two rounds we also asked for the number of customers and details of sales of 
the main product. Firms found these questions difficult to answer, and they were dropped for the third survey round 
and are not included in the aggregate index here (but are reported in online Appendix 14). </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>The first four columns of Table 5 show the impact for new firms. In the first year 
the impact on the inverse hyperbolic sine of profits is positive and significant, but the 
impact on the other measures is not statistically significant. The impacts are larger 
in the second and third year follow-ups and both the inverse hyperbolic sine and </p>

<p>Table 4-Impacts on Business Sales and Profits </p>

<p>New firms 
Existing firms </p>

<p>Truncated 
sales </p>

<p>Truncated 
profits </p>

<p>Inverse 
hyperbolic 
sine 
profits </p>

<p>Aggregate 
index of 
sales and 
profits </p>

<p>Truncated 
sales </p>

<p>Truncated 
profits </p>

<p>Inverse 
hyperbolic 
sine 
profits </p>

<p>Aggregate 
index of 
sales and 
profits </p>

<p>Experimental impacts 
First follow-up 
36.160 −24.512 
2.156 
0.016 
50.805 
0.074 
0.972 
0.080 
(49.884) (26.330) 
(0.369) 
(0.047) 
(85.662) (49.416) 
(0.373) 
(0.070) </p>

<p>Second follow-up 
297.783 
69.061 
4.154 
0.298 
346.304 
69.234 
2.183 
0.237 
(56.494) (15.150) 
(0.326) 
(0.036) 
(134.728) (35.420) 
(0.401) 
(0.060) </p>

<p>Third follow-up 
64.541 
20.137 
3.962 
0.167 
349.228 
32.035 
2.580 
0.211 
(92.338) (21.635) 
(0.346) 
(0.042) 
(143.729) (40.956) 
(0.464) 
(0.070) </p>

<p>Control mean: first follow-up 
271.467 167.705 
6.583 
−0.005 
509.699 257.025 
10.772 
−0.045 
Control mean: second follow-up 278.177 
91.061 
6.161 
−0.096 
660.535 206.305 
9.646 
−0.117 
Control mean: third follow-up 
438.490 114.099 
5.775 
−0.050 
509.975 192.151 
8.565 
−0.108 
Sample size: first follow-up 
995 
995 
995 
995 
423 
423 
423 
423 
Sample size: second follow-up 
1,151 
1,150 
1,150 
1,152 
497 
497 
497 
497 
Sample size: third follow-up 
1,063 
1,063 
1,063 
1,063 
468 
469 
469 
470 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Experimental estimates are ITT estimates and control for randomiza-
tion strata. Sales and profits are in 1,000s of real naira per month. Aggregate index of outcomes includes monthly 
sales, truncated monthly sales, annual sales, sales higher than one year ago, monthly profits, truncated monthly prof-
its, profits in the best month, and inverse hyperbolic sine of profits. Existing and new refers to firm status at time of 
application. Rounds 1, 2, and 3 are 1, 2, and 3 years after application. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Quantile Treatment Effects on Profits in Round 3 </p>

<p>Notes: Profits are in thousands of real naira per month. New firms and existing firms refer to status at time of appli-
cation. Round 3 is 3 years after application and 12-18 months after all grants have been received. </p>

<p>−150 </p>

<p>−100 </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>Total profits 
Total profits </p>

<p>510 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 95 </p>

<p>Percentile </p>

<p>510 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 95 </p>

<p>Percentile </p>

<p>Panel A. New firms </p>

<p>−250 </p>

<p>−100 
−50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Panel B. Existing firms </p>

<p>OLS </p>

<p>Quantile treatment effect </p>

<p>95% CI </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>summary index are significant in both years, while the impact on profits and sales 
is only statistically significant in the second year. The last four columns of Table 5 
show the impacts for existing firms. As with the new firms, the impacts are stronger 
in years 2 and 3 than in year 1, and are again significant for the inverse hyperbolic 
sine and summary index measures in both years. The impact on the level of sales is 
also significant in years 2 and 3, while the impact on profits is only significant in the 
second year. Online Appendix 14 shows the round 3 impacts on profits and sales are 
also significant for both new and existing firms if we use any of several alternative 
transforms that reduce the influence of the top tail of the distribution, as well as 
examining robustness to other measures of profits and sales. 
The estimated effect size is approximately 0.2 to 0.3 standard deviations in terms 
of the aggregate index. The quantile treatment effect on monthly profits in round 3 
at the fiftieth percentile is 69,000 naira for new firms and 51,000 naira for new 
firms, while the regression estimates of the ITT are 69,000 naira (round 2) and 
20,000 naira (round 3) for new firms, and 69,000 naira (round 2) and 32,000 naira 
(round 3) for existing firms. Relative to the monthly profit round 3 control means 
of 114,000 naira (new firms) and 192,000 naira (existing firms), these estimates are </p>

<p>Table 5-Impact on Capital </p>

<p>Took a 
formal 
loan </p>

<p>Received 
equity 
investment </p>

<p>Value of 
inventories </p>

<p>Made 
large 
K purchase </p>

<p>Value of 
capital 
purchases </p>

<p>Value 
of capital 
stock </p>

<p>Panel A. New firms 
First follow-up 
−0.003 
−0.005 
349 
0.289 
1,062 
1,448 
(0.006) 
(0.010) 
(123) 
(0.031) 
(128) 
(196) </p>

<p>Second follow-up 
0.003 
0.026 
1,869 
0.404 
1,543 
4,568 
(0.009) 
(0.012) 
(350) 
(0.029) 
(143) 
(464) </p>

<p>Third follow-up 
0.015 
0.001 
697 
0.103 
155 
3,489 
(0.012) 
(0.010) 
(196) 
(0.031) 
(122) 
(324) </p>

<p>Control mean: first follow-up 
0.011 
0.029 
721 
0.211 
345 
1,024 
Control mean: second follow-up 
0.018 
0.017 
925 
0.206 
252 
1,290 
Control mean: third follow-up 
0.022 
0.020 
713 
0.206 
292 
984 
Sample size: first follow-up 
995 
995 
991 
995 
991 
995 
Sample size: second follow-up 
1,071 
1,071 
1,013 
1,071 
1,013 
956 
Sample size: third follow-up 
857 
857 
771 
857 
771 
809 </p>

<p>Panel B. Existing firms 
First follow-up 
−0.025 
0.026 
729 
0.369 
1,356 
2,050 
(0.017) 
(0.019) 
(268) 
(0.046) 
(185) 
(335) </p>

<p>Second follow-up 
−0.039 
0.030 
1,320 
0.242 
1,018 
3852 
(0.020) 
(0.023) 
(579) 
(0.045) 
(202) 
(744) </p>

<p>Third follow-up 
0.001 
0.001 
845 
0.115 
221 
4,295 
(0.025) 
(0.018) 
(486) 
(0.052) 
(340) 
(713) </p>

<p>Control mean: first follow-up 
0.042 
0.026 
1,223 
0.358 
537 
1,759 
Control mean: second follow-up 
0.063 
0.045 
2,226 
0.434 
596 
3,190 
Control mean: third follow-up 
0.061 
0.031 
1,645 
0.362 
668 
2,536 
Sample size: first follow-up 
423 
423 
422 
423 
423 
422 
Sample size: second follow-up 
458 
458 
453 
458 
453 
381 
Sample size: third follow-up 
372 
372 
360 
372 
360 
331 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Experimental estimates are ITT estimates and control for randomiza-
tion strata. Inventories and capital values are in 1,000s of real naira per month. Existing and new refers to firm sta-
tus at time of application. Rounds 1, 2, and 3 are 1, 2, and 3 years after application. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>equivalent to a 17 to 60 percent increase (new firms) and 17 to 36 percent increase 
(existing firms). </p>

<p>V. Mechanisms </p>

<p>The results show that winning the competition resulted in sizable increases in 
employment which persisted after all grant money had been received, and that this 
increase in employment was profitable for firms. This contrasts with case 1, which 
predicted no employment effect, and case 2, which predicted that any effect would 
reverse once all grant money had been received. I therefore turn to examining the 
impacts on intermediate channels to help understand the mechanisms behind this 
employment effect. </p>

<p>A. Conditionality </p>

<p>The fact that the grants were payable in four tranches, with the third and fourth 
tranches requiring progress on sales and hiring workers, may make the impact 
different from that of an unrestricted grant. I can rule out the mechanism in case 2, 
whereby conditionality only acts by inducing a short-term increase in the return 
to labor and capital, since the impacts persist after all payments were received. 
Moreover, if conditionality were the reason for hiring, it would not explain why 
the majority of winners hire more workers than needed to be hired to receive the 
tranche payment. Seventy-eight percent of the winning firms have more employees 
than required at the time of the second survey, and 73 percent at the time of the third 
survey. Even without the conditionality, paying the grant in four installments over 
time may have different impacts to a single lump-sum grant and I am unable to say 
if the impact would be different if paid in a single one-time grant. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>B. Changes in A and E </p>

<p>Next, consider the evidence for case 3, whereby the impact of the program comes 
from changing the productivity and entrepreneurial skill of those operating busi-
nesses. Online Appendix 15 provides results. There is no significant change in entre-
preneurial self-efficacy, which measures the owner's self-confidence in their ability 
to carry out 12 business-related actions such as "estimate customer demand for a 
new product," and "identify good employees who can help the business grow." This 
also helps rule out the concern that the control group has become less self-confident 
as a result of not winning. There is also no change in the likelihood the firm owner 
has a business mentor, or in the number of other firm owner's they discuss business 
with. These suggest the main mechanisms are not through more confidence and 
connections. There is a minor improvement in business practices for the new firms 
operating, but the magnitude of the effect is likely to explain only a 0.2 percent 
increase in the likelihood of operating, and a 4 percent change in profits. There is no </p>

<p>16 For example, recipients facing borrowing and saving constraints may be less able to buy larger value items if 
the payment is made in tranches, but payment in tranches may help them overcome self-control problems and take 
longer to plan their investments. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>increase in business practices for existing firms. This set of results suggest that the 
impact is not coming through the mechanisms of increasing A and E. </p>

<p>C. Changes in Capital </p>

<p>Table 5 examines how winning affected the firm's use of capital. The first two 
columns consider the use of outside finance in the form of formal loans and equity 
investment, respectively. The use of both forms of finance is very low, with fewer 
than 3 percent of the new firm applicants in the control group receiving either form 
of financing in a given year, and only 6 percent of existing firm applicants having 
received a formal loan in any given year, and fewer than 5 percent receiving equity 
investments. We see relatively little impact on crowd-in or crowd-out of these other 
sources of financing. New firm applicants were 2.6 percentage points more likely to 
receive equity financing in round 2, and existing firm applicants were 3.9 percentage 
points less likely to receive a formal loan in round 2. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>The remaining columns of Table 5, in contrast, show that the grants greatly 
increased the amount of capital in the winning firms. Treated firms have higher 
inventory levels, are more likely to have made a purchase of business equipment, 
land, or buildings of over 100,000 naira, and have spent more on such purchases. 
The result is that the total capital stock of the treated firms is 3.5 million naira higher 
than the 800,000 naira control mean among new applicants at the time of round 3, 
and 4.3 million naira higher than the 2.5 million naira control mean among existing 
applicants. The winning firms are therefore substantially higher in terms of capital 
stock, as well as in terms of employment. 
These results suggest that the main effect of winning is to allow firms to overcome 
credit constraints by using the capital grants to purchase more capital inputs, hire 
more labor, and use this to produce a wider variety of inputs. In online Appendix 16, 
I examine two more pieces of evidence for capital being the main driver of impact. I 
use the heterogeneity in the amount of grant received among the experimental win-
ners and find those winners who received larger grants were able to grow larger. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>I also consider heterogeneity in impacts with respect to the potential importance of 
capital constraints to the firm at the time of application, finding modest evidence that 
more capital-constrained firms benefited more from the grants, but also that almost 
everyone says they are capital-constrained. 
Under the assumption that the additional workers are paid their marginal product 
of labor, and that the only impact of the grants on profits is through the increase in 
capital stock, the implied return to capital can be obtained by estimating the follow-
ing equation: </p>

<p>(5) 
Profit s i = a + b × Capita l i + c × Region × Gende r i + ε i , </p>

<p>17 Online Appendix 16 shows that informal financing from moneylenders, family, and friends is also rare, and 
likewise does not appear to have been crowded out by the receipt of the grant. 
18 Online Appendix 18 considers two other prespecified dimensions of heterogeneity: gender and business plan 
score. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>where capital is instrumented with assignment to treatment. I do this first in levels, 
and then in a log formulation. Table 6 reports the implied return on capital. 
19 The 
estimated real return to capital for new firms is 1.3 to 3.4 percent per month, while 
for existing firms it is 0.4 to 3.3 percent per month. As a comparison, real interest 
rates for SME finance are around 20 percent per annum. So the average return on 
capital is at the level needed to pay for a loan were credit available. However, these 
average returns will include higher returns for some firms and lower returns for 
others (including those whose businesses fail). Since loan financing does not allow 
banks to capture the high returns in the upside, but results in losses to the bank in 
the case of lower returns, in the absence of a way to distinguish well who is likely to 
succeed, banks will be reluctant to lend. Moreover, given this variability in returns, 
firms may be reluctant to borrow at prevailing interest rates. 
20 This is seen in the 
data, with few control group firms receiving loans. </p>

<p>D. How Do the Additional Businesses Induced to Operate Compare 
to the Control Firms? </p>

<p>Winning the competition resulted in many additional firms operating in the treat-
ment group than the control group. If scarce credit is allocated first to the most 
productive firms, we might expect the marginal firms to be induced to operate by 
the competition to be less efficient and run by less talented individuals than the 
firms operating in the control group. Online Appendix 17 examines whether this is 
the case. The observable baseline characteristics of the winners operating a firm in 
round 3 are similar to the control, with no changes in the sector, nor in the education 
of the owner. Using data from the first follow-up survey, I also show owners are 
similar in terms of ability measures (digitspan and Raven test), and grit. Finally, in </p>

<p>19 Note that firms that answered a shortened version of the survey have data on profits, but not capital stock, 
available. As a result, the Wald ratio of the impact on profits in Table 4 to the impact on capital in Table 5 will not 
be exactly equal to the implied return on capital in Table 6, since Table 6 restricts to a common sample. This also 
means the results in Table 6 are specific to those firms answering the full survey. 
20 Indeed, equity, rather than debt, may be a more suitable way to fund these types of firms, but few firms receive 
equity-financing in this market either. </p>

<p>Table 6-Estimated Monthly Real Return on Capital </p>

<p>New firms 
Existing firms </p>

<p>Round 2 
Round 3 
Round 2 
Round 3 </p>

<p>Panel A. Levels specification: real monthly profits (truncated at 99th percentile) 
Capital stock (truncated at 99th percentile) 
0.017 
0.013 
0.023 
0.004 
(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.010) 
(0.010) </p>

<p>Panel B. logs specification: log (real monthly profits + 1) 
log (capital stock + 1) 
0.410 
0.423 
0.446 
0.411 
(0.026) 
(0.030) 
(0.057) 
(0.052) </p>

<p>Implied monthly real return (percent) 
3.03 
3.38 
3.34 
2.45 
Sample size 
956 
806 
381 
331 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Capital stock is instrumented by assignment to treatment. Implied 
monthly return for log specification estimated at median profit to capital ratio. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>terms of labor productivity, the marginal firms that only operate as a result of win-
ning are not all less productive than the control group firms, but rather come from 
across the control group productivity distribution. Moreover, these additional firms 
are larger in size than most firms in Nigeria, and are run by youth with human capital 
levels that greatly exceed national averages-and as such are expected to be more 
productive than the average Nigerian firm. </p>

<p>VI. Longer-Term Impacts during a Time of Recession </p>

<p>In 2016, Nigeria suffered its worst economic performance in 30 years, driven by 
a contraction in the oil sector which is the main export and accounts for 70 percent 
of government revenues. The government imposed currency controls and import 
restrictions, which led to a parallel exchange rate and inflation reaching 18.5 per-
cent, the highest in over a decade. In this difficult environment for firms, I went back 
and conducted a longer-term follow-up survey between July and November 2016. 
The survey was answered by 79.7 percent of treatment and 74.5 percent of control 
firms, and operating status was obtained for 92.5 percent of treatment and 90.9 per-
cent of control firms. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Table 7 summarizes the impacts of the program during this time period, which is 
five years after applying and more than 3 years since all money has been received 
from the program. New firm applicants are still 24.1 percentage points more likely 
to be operating a firm, report 2.6 more workers, and are 11.1 percentage points more 
likely to have 10 or more workers than control firms. Existing firms are 9.5 percent-
age points more likely to be operating, have 3.0 more workers, and are 12.7 percent-
age points more likely to have 10 or more workers. These impacts are all significant 
at the 1 percent levels and large relative to the control means. The impact on the </p>

<p>21 A joint orthogonality test can not reject balance on baseline characteristics for the sample answering the 
survey for either new firms ( p = 0.857) or existing firms (0.985). </p>

<p>Table 7-Longer-Term Impacts during a Time of Recession </p>

<p>New firms 
Existing firms </p>

<p>Outcome </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Control 
mean </p>

<p>Treatment 
effect </p>

<p>Sample 
size </p>

<p>Control 
mean </p>

<p>Treatment 
effect </p>

<p>Operates a firm at time of survey 
1,198 
0.529 
0.241 
487 
0.761 
0.095 
(0.028) 
(0.036) </p>

<p>Total employment 
1,125 
3.810 
2.596 
462 
5.206 
2.997 
(0.458) 
(0.756) </p>

<p>Firm of 10+ workers 
1,125 
0.117 
0.111 
462 
0.154 
0.127 
(0.024) 
(0.038) </p>

<p>Truncated profits 
1,085 
84.625 −0.866 
450 
108.978 
26.111 
(14.970) 
(24.526) </p>

<p>Inverse hyperbolic sine of profits 
1,085 
5.055 
2.368 
450 
7.768 
1.551 
(0.378) 
(0.521) </p>

<p>Aggregate index of sales and profits 
1,085 −0.019 
0.081 
450 
−0.046 
0.102 
(0.047) 
(0.070) </p>

<p>Notes: Impacts from round 4 survey taken in July through November 2016, more than three years after all payments 
had been received. Regressions control for randomization strata. Robust standard errors in parentheses. Regressions 
control for randomization area. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>level of profits is insignificant, but there is a positive and significant impact on the 
inverse hyperbolic sine of profits for both new and existing firms, and on the aggre-
gate index of sales and profits for new firms. Online Appendix 19 shows the quantile 
treatment effect estimates are positive for profits in the middle of the distribution, 
but at the lower tail there is no impact with firms closed, and at the upper tail the 
variance is large. 
These results show that the program has continued to have positive impacts over a 
longer time horizon. However, the estimated impacts on firm operation and employ-
ment are smaller in magnitude than seen in round 3. This may reflect some of the 
additional firm growth achieved by treated firms being constrained by the weak 
economy. </p>

<p>VII. Robustness to Common Concerns about Firm Experiments </p>

<p>There are several general issues that affect almost all firm experiments in devel-
oping countries: the use of self-reported data, the extent to which impacts arise from 
general equilibrium factors, and the extent to which the results generalize. I discuss 
each in turn. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>A. Self-Reporting </p>

<p>While the use of self-reported data from surveys is standard for firm experiments 
in developing countries, readers may be concerned whether such data are reliable. 
A first point to note is that administrative data on firms are rare in most developing 
countries, and there is a growing body of evidence to show that firms systemati-
cally misreport their revenues, costs, and wages to the authorities (Pomeranz 2015; 
Carrillo, Pomeranz, and Singhal 2017; Kumler, Verhoogen, and Frías 2015), so that 
it is not clear that one should prefer administrative data over survey data even if it 
were available. Indeed the analysis in online Appendix 11 suggests that the admin-
istrative data on employment for the business plan competition winners is unreliable 
in our specific case. 
Second, the survey was designed and conducted in a manner to reduce reporting 
bias. It was conducted by a well-known independent market research company (TNS 
RMS Nigeria) and participants were told its "purpose is to help better understand 
the growth process of enterprises being run by Nigerian youth, as well as the devel-
opment process of youths thinking about starting a business," with participants told 
the results would be kept confidential and used for research purposes only. The first 
round survey asked about a variety of government programs, and not just YouWiN! 
Together these features are likely to make the survey responses less biased than if 
the data were collected in an official capacity by the government program imple-
menters. Online Appendix 14 shows treatment does not have significant impacts on 
errors in reporting sales and profits. 
Finally, although I need to rely on survey data for the majority of the analysis, 
there are a couple of checks of business size that are not based on self-reports. In </p>

<p>22 Note that these robustness checks were not included in the pre-analysis plan, but are a response to commonly 
occurring comments raised for almost all firm experiments. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>the first and second round follow-ups, approximately 50 percent of the in-person 
surveys took place in the business (the rest taking place at the home or at a third 
location). In the third round, more emphasis was put on trying to interview at the 
business premises, and 90 percent of the in-person surveys of those operating busi-
nesses took place at the business. 
23 Likewise, in the long-term follow-up round in 
2016, 97 percent of the in-person surveys for those operating a business took place 
at the business location. For this subsample the interviewers physically counted how 
many employees they observed at the place of business. This is an undercount of 
true employment because it misses workers who are working in another location 
(e.g., in the homes of clients, in other stores, traveling, etc.) or who are temporarily 
absent. Nevertheless, it does provide a check of whether observed employment is 
larger for the treated firms. Second, throughout the survey rounds information was 
collected on whether the firms have a website, along with the URL. On October 4, 
2015, and January 10, 2017 I tested to see whether each firm had a functioning URL. 
Having a functioning website is a proxy for being of a larger size three-and-a-half 
years and five years after winning. 
Table 8 reports the results of these checks. YouWiN! winners have significantly 
more observed workers and are more likely to have a functioning website for 
both new and existing applicants. This is true for both the third follow-up and the 
long-term survey round. At the time of the third follow-up, new firms have approx-
imately three times as many employees observed at the premises among the experi-
mental winners than the control group, and existing firms have almost twice as many 
employees observed. While the absolute levels are smaller, these ratios are similar to 
those in Table 3. Both new and existing firms are twice as likely to have a function-
ing website among the experimental winners as in the control group. While limited, 
these checks do help provide assurance that there is a genuine increase in firm sizes 
for the treated firms. </p>

<p>23 Those whose business had closed down or who had not started businesses were surveyed at their home or in 
a third location. </p>

<p>Table 8-Impacts on Non-Self-Reported Outcomes </p>

<p>New firms 
Existing firms </p>

<p>Employees 
counted </p>

<p>Functioning 
website </p>

<p>Employees 
counted </p>

<p>Functioning 
website </p>

<p>Impact at third follow-up 
2.044 
0.040 
1.746 
0.081 
(0.263) 
(0.014) 
(0.439) 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Long-term impact 
1.173 
0.022 
1.051 
0.097 
(0.253) 
(0.013) 
(0.370) 
(0.028) </p>

<p>Sample size: third follow-up 
860 
1,300 
398 
541 
Sample size: long term follow-up 
908 
1,300 
386 
541 
Control mean: third follow-up 
1.077 
0.047 
2.175 
0.099 
Control mean: long term follow-up 
1.220 
0.045 
2.209 
0.072 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in parentheses. Long-term follow-up is five years after applying, and more than three 
years after all funding has been received. </p>

<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>

<p>B. Competition and Spillovers </p>

<p>A second potential concern may be whether the growth of the winners came at the 
expense of other firms. There are two elements of this concern. The first is a concern 
about internal validity: if the growth of the winners came at the expense of firms in 
the control group, the control group would no longer provide a valid counterfactual. 
This seems unlikely to be an important concern in our case, since the experimental 
sample is widely scattered over a country of 170 million people, and is not heavily 
concentrated in any single industry. As a check, online Appendix 20 shows that there 
is no heterogeneity in treatment effect, nor difference in control outcomes, with the 
number of other firms selected as winners in the same state and industry. As a result, 
the estimates should be internally valid, and are informative for showing the con-
straints facing individual businesses. 
The second aspect of this concern is then whether the gains to winners came from 
taking business from other firms in the economy. 
24 Often this is seen as a concern in 
thinking about scaling up small pilots, whereas here YouWiN! is operating at a scale 
of $60 million per year, and is larger than all the other business plan competitions 
discussed in the introduction. It seems unlikely that such a program would have 
the intensity randomized at the regional level as in the labor market intervention of 
Crépon et al. (2013), precluding a randomization approach to measuring these spill-
overs. Rotemberg (2015) uses detailed firm data from India and finds a small busi-
ness subsidy program there did result in competitors losing market share, but not for 
those producing internationally traded markets. In the United States, Bronnenberg 
and Ellickson (2015) note that online sales have had a market expansion effect, by 
increasing convenience and product variety, so that gains to new entrants need not 
come from taking market share from incumbents, and they speculate that such chan-
nels may be more important in developing country markets. 
We have seen that winners have indeed increased innovation, adding new prod-
ucts and new locations. For example, one of the winners set up a dry-cleaning chain, 
which expanded into locations where dry-cleaning services weren't readily avail-
able. Given how underdeveloped many product markets are in Nigeria, it seems 
plausible that the gain in sales is coming from growing the size of the market, not 
just undercutting competitors. As an additional check on this, online Appendix 20 
shows that winners were no more likely to reduce their product prices than the con-
trol group, suggesting that the channel for expansion was not taking market share 
through price competition. This evidence is admittedly indirect and limited, but the 
absence of detailed data on other firms in Nigeria precludes any further analysis of 
changes for nonprogram firms. </p>

<p>24 Of course even if the gains to winners all come from taking business from other firms, aggregate efficiency 
can still increase if the business plan competition reduces misallocation by taking sales from small, unproductive 
firms and directing it toward more efficient firms. Section VD argues that the winners are likely to be more efficient 
than the average firm in the economy. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AUGUST 2017 </p>

<p>C. External Validity </p>

<p>A final critique that can be raised about any impact evaluation is the extent to which 
its results may generalize. The program studied here is a nationwide program to a 
large number of firms in Africa's largest country, and hence should be of intrinsic 
interest. Moreover, the competition has already been run in three more rounds in 
Nigeria. Nevertheless, there are reasons to believe the findings may generalize beyond 
Nigeria. As noted in the introduction, these types of business plan competitions have 
become increasingly common, particularly in sub-Saharan Africa. While the amounts 
offered in Nigeria are high, they are far from unique-the average grant sizes in the 
Somalia business plan competition were $58,000 in round 1 and $67,000 in round 
2, and awards of $25,000 were given in Côte d'Ivoire. The key difference here is the 
large number of winners and randomized selection provide the ability to evaluate and 
learn from this competition, which has not been possible in the other cases. It seems 
likely that these competitions in other countries are also inducing applications from 
entrepreneurs with high growth potential. Whether such entrepreneurs can be identi-
fied in alternative ways to business plan competitions and/or be supported through 
alternative policy instruments to grants are interesting questions for future research. </p>

<p>VIII. Conclusions </p>

<p>The YouWiN! business plan competition has had large impacts on the rate of 
business start-up, survival of existing firms, employment, profits, and sales of win-
ning firms. It has succeeded in generating more firms with ten or more employees, 
and provides the first experimental evidence of how direct policy action can spur the 
growth of such firms. The impacts are not consistent with a model of no market fail-
ures in which the grants would be predicted to increase the incomes of the business 
owners without changing their production decisions. Examination of the interme-
diate channels suggests that a main effect of the program has been to enable firms 
to buy more capital, innovate more, and hire more workers, with little impact on 
business practices, mentoring, or networking. The business plan competition seems 
an effective tool for identifying entrepreneurs with much greater scope for growth 
than the typical microenterprise. </p>



<p> 
McKenzie: identifying and Spurring entrepreneurShip 
VOL. 107 nO. 8 </p>



</text></tei>