<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1590%2Fs0034-71402003000400011" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Summary: 1. Introduction; 2. The NAIRU and the natural rate 
of unemployment; 3. The data and the estimated models; 4. The 
estimation procedures; 5. The model's estimation results; 6. The 
estimated NAIRU and the response of ∆π to cyclical unemploy-
ment; 7. Conclusions. </p>

<p>This paper estimates the Brazilian NAIRU (Nonaccelerating In-
flation Rate of Unemployment) and investigates several empirical 
questions: the stability of coefficients of the Brazilian price Phillips 
curve, the behavior of the NAIRU along time, and error bands for 
the NAIRU. This article innovates, with respect to previous re-
search work done for Brazil, because it estimates error bands for 
the NAIRU and adopts econometric models that, in our judgment, 
deal more adequately with the still recent instability of the Brazil-
ian economy. We estimate two different state-space models: one 
with a time-varying NAIRU and another in which the NAIRU is 
changing over time according to a hidden Markov chain specifica-
tion. </p>

<p>The study presents some new evidence on several questions. It 
shows that while the slope of the Brazilian price Phillips curve is 
stable the NAIRU has not been stable. It concludes that there is 
a statistically significant relationship, with correct sign, between 
deviations of unemployment from the NAIRU and inflation. It 
also shows that, after the second semester of 1995, there is no 
significant evidence that the NAIRU has been different from the 
observed unemployment rate. </p>

<p>Neste artigo estima-se a NAIRU (a taxa de desemprego que mantém </p>

<p>* This paper was RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>estável a taxa de inflação) do Brasil e investiga-se diversas questões 
empíricas: a estabilidade dos coeficientes da Curva de Phillips (para 
preços) brasileira , o comportamento da NAIRU ao longo do tempo, 
e os intervalos de confiança para a NAIRU. </p>

<p>O presente trabalho inova, em relação aos anteriores, ao adotar 
modelos econométricos que, acredita-se, são mais adequados para 
lidar com as instabilidades defrontadas pela economia brasileira em 
período recente. Estimam-se dois modelos diferentes em espaço-
de-estados: um com uma NAIRU que muda ao longo do tempo e 
outro no qual a NAIRU muda, ao longo do tempo, de acordo com 
a especificação de uma cadeia de Markov oculta. </p>

<p>Obtém-se novas evidências sobre diversas questões empíricas. Mos-
tra-se que a inclinação da Curva de Phillips do Brasilé estável 
mas que a NAIRU brasileira vem se alterando ao longo do tempo. 
Conclui-se que existe uma relação estatisticamente significante, e 
com o sinal correto, entre os desvios da taxa de desemprego em 
relaçãoà NAIRU e a taxa de inflação. No entanto, devidoà impre-
cisão das suas estimativas, não há evidência significativa de que a 
NAIRU, depois do segundo trimestre de 1995, tenha sido diferente 
da taxa de desemprego observada. </p>

<p>In this article we estimate the Brazilian Phillips curve aiming to obtain the 
Nonaccelerating Inflation Rate of Unemployment (NAIRU) for Brazil. We investi-
gate the stability of coefficients of the Brazilian Phillips curve and the relationship 
between the rate of inflation and the deviation of the observed rate of unemploy-
ment from the NAIRU. We also estimate error bands for the NAIRU in order to 
determine whether there is any significant difference between the NAIRU and the 
observed unemployment rate. 
Estimating the relationship between nominal and real variables in Brazil is a 
very hard task due to the instability experienced by the Brazilian economy in its 
recent past. The macroeconomic models are estimated using information provided 
by time series data, and the number of required observations outnumbers what 
is available for the most recent period of stability after the Real Plan. This is a 
challenge for anyone who works with Brazilian macroeconomic data. The great 
instability of the Brazilian economy, especially when the nominal side is modeled, 
makes it crucial to deal with structural breaks. The strong nominal shocks faced 
by the economy at different periods and at the beginning of the many stabilization </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>plans point in the direction of using models that allow for large breaks and frequent 
alternations of the states of the economy. 
Portugal et al. (1999) estimate two different models for the Brazilian NAIRU. 
The first model is a traditional Phillips curve with constant intercept, autoregres-
sive residuals and dummies to allow for structural breaks. The second model is 
a univariate structural model with trend and cycle, Harvey (1989), in which the 
NAIRU is defined as the trend component. The definition of the NAIRU, used in 
the second model, is questionable and in the literature (Staiger et al., 2001, Cogley  and Sargent, 2001, Hall, 1999) there is a distinction between the natural rate of 
unemployment, usually defined as the unemployment trend, and the NAIRU. 
In Corseuil et al. (1996) there are no calculations for the NAIRU but there is a 
careful analysis of the components of unemployment (trend and cycle), for the main 
metropolitan regions of Brazil. They test the relative importance of aggregate and 
regional shocks in the determination of unemployment and conclude that there is 
evidence in favor of a strong influence of aggregate factors. 
We believe that the structural breaks in the models for the Brazilian NAIRU 
cannot be dealt with by models with dummies and autoregressive residuals (Por- tugal et al., 1999), thresholds [TAR model, (Tong, 1990)] or with time-varying 
smooth transitions between states [STAR model, Teräsvirta (1994) or TV-STAR 
model, Lundbergh et al. (2002)]. Fortunately, since the beginning of the '90s there 
has been a variety of theoretical developments in time series analysis that enable 
us to extract information from data even when instabilities, like the ones observed 
for Brazilian data, are present [Hamilton (1989); Kim (1994); Kim and Nelson  (1999); Sims (1999); Sims and Zha (2002)]. These developments allow us to deal 
with a larger set of data. 
Our research innovates, when compared to other research work done for Brazil, 
because it adopts some of these developments which, in our view, deal more ade-
quately with abrupt structural breaks in the model's equation and frequent alter-
nations of the states of the economy. We estimate two different models to calculate 
the natural rate of unemployment and its confidence interval: one model with a 
time-varying NAIRU and another model in which the NAIRU is changing over 
time according to a hidden Markov chain specification. The first model allows 
for the presence of ARCH residuals; the second model allows for persistent het-
eroscedasticity 1 as well as a richer pattern of time variation for the NAIRU. We </p>

<p>1 Sims (1999), using monthly data on a short term interest rate and a commodity price index 
for a considerably more stable country like the USA, has found evidence of the presence of 
persistent heteroscedasticity in the model. Kim and Nelson (1999), using quarterly data for the 
1962.I -1985.IV period, found very strong ARCH effects in estimates of a fixed coefficient version </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>could not reject the absence of ARCH residuals in the first model under the main-
tained hypothesis of a time-varying NAIRU. Under the specification for the second 
model, we could not reject the presence of both Markov-switching heteroscedas-
ticity and a time-varying NAIRU. A detailed description of both models and of 
the estimation methods can be found in Kim and Nelson (1999). The models 
were estimated using quarterly data for the average rate of open unemployment 
in six Metropolitan Regions and for the rate of inflation measured by the national 
consumer price index (INPC) in eleven Metropolitan Regions (including the six 
regions where unemployment is measured), both collected by IBGE for the period 
1982:1 -2001:4. 
Following Staiger et al. (2001), the recent theories that have been proposed 
to explain the relationship between inflation and unemployment can be classified 
into two groups: theories in which "the Phillips curve is alive and well but..." and 
those that proclaim the "the Phillips curve is dead". The theories in the first 
group ((Staiger et al., 1997, 2001); Gordon (1982, 1997, 1998);King and Watson  (1994); Blanchard and Katz (1997)) conclude that the Phillips curve continues to 
have the same negative slope but it has been shifting. A good survey of these 
theories can be found in Katz and Krueger (1999). The theories in the second 
group interpret the recent events as a change in the slope of the Phillips curve 
(Akerlof et al. (1996, 2000) ; Taylor (2000)). For Brazil, the most recent study 
(Portugal et al., 1999) can be classified in the first group. This study did not find 
evidence that the slope of the Brazilian Phillips curve has changed, but it could 
not reject that the curve has been shifting. 
The article is organized as follows: In section 2, we describe the data used, 
how the monthly data were transformed into quarterly data and the estimated 
models; in section 3, we present the estimation procedures adopted, and in the 
appendix, we describe the Kim filter and its use in the estimation of one of the 
models; in section 4, we show the estimation results and discuss some statistical 
tests; in section 5, we conclude. </p>

<p>2. The NAIRU and the Natural Rate of Unemployment </p>

<p>For many researchers, the NAIRU is a synonym for the natural rate of unem-
ployment. However, we find it convenient to separate these two concepts, just as 
do many others (Staiger et al. (2001), Cogley and Sargent (2001), Hall (1999)). 
The idea of a natural rate of employment was first proposed in Friedman's </p>

<p>of the U.S. monetary growth function. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>(1968) presidential address to the American Economic Association: "The natural 
rate of unemployment is the level which would be ground out by the Walrasian 
system of general equilibrium equations, provided that there is embedded in them 
the actual structural characteristics of the labor and commodity markets, includ-
ing market imperfections, stochastic variability in demands and supplies, the cost 
of gathering information about job vacancies and labor availabilities, the costs of 
mobility, and so on". The main point of Friedman's address was to argue that 
there was no permanent (long-run) tradeoff between inflation and unemployment. 
His definition does not require the existence of a short-run inflation-unemployment 
tradeoff. Therefore, there is a natural rate of unemployment, even in the absence of 
any short-run unemployment-inflation tradeoff. Besides, as pointed out by Roger- son (1997), his definition is not inconsistent with the natural rate of unemployment 
being equal to the low frequency (trend) movements in unemployment. 
The NAIRU concept, on the other hand, needs the view (a view which is 
very prominent among central bankers and monetary economists) that there is a 
short-run inflation-unemployment tradeoff. Even though, for many economists, 
the existence of this short-run tradeoff is purely speculative, its existence is one 
of the most enduring ideas in macroeconomics: shocks in monetary policy push 
inflation and unemployment in opposite directions in the short run. If this trade-
off is admitted, there must be some level of unemployment (NAIRU) consistent 
with constant inflation. Therefore, if a contractionary shock in monetary policy 
increases unemployment above the NAIRU, the inflation rate will decrease, and 
if an expansionary monetary shock decreases the unemployment rate below the 
NAIRU, the inflation rate will increase. 
One simple model for the relationship between unemployment (u), inflation 
change (∆π) and the NAIRU (ū) is given by ∆π t = β(u t −ū)+ t = −βū+βu t + t = 
α + βu t + t , where α = −βū and t is the error term. In this model the NAIRU 
(ū) is −α/β. This relationship for Brazil, from 1982:I-2001:IV, is illustrated by 
the scatterplot in figure 1. The horizontal axis shows the average rate of open 
unemployment in quarter t and the vertical axis shows the difference between the 
monthly inflation rate in quarter t and the monthly inflation rate in quarter t-1. 
Figure 1 also plots the OLS, ordinary least squares, regression line -the simple 
model -estimated over the full sample. The regression line shows a negative 
relationship between unemployment and inflation change, and its intersection with 
the unemployment axis is the ordinary least squares estimate of the NAIRU. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Inflation Change x Unemployment </p>

<p>Dp = -0.6873*U + 3.7 </p>

<p>(0.549) 
(3.1) </p>

<p>R 
2 = 0.0197 </p>

<p>NAIRU= 5.4% </p>

<p>-50.00% </p>

<p>-40.00% </p>

<p>-30.00% </p>

<p>-20.00% </p>

<p>-10.00% </p>

<p>0.00% </p>

<p>10.00% </p>

<p>20.00% </p>

<p>2% 
3% 
4% 
5% 
6% 
7% 
8% 
9% </p>

<p>Open Unemployment </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>The problem with this estimate of the NAIRU is that it does not control for 
other factors that may affect the relationship between inflation and unemploy-
ment, such as inflation stabilization plans, seasonal effects and lagged effects of 
unemployment and inflation. This lack of control for other factors may explain 
why both coefficient of the regression line are not significantly different from zero. 
Figure 2 is identical to figure 1 but shows data from 1995:1-2001:IV, which 
is the period after the Real Plan with much lower inflation. Figure 2 shows no 
evident relationship between inflation change and unemployment. One possible 
explanation is the absence of the short-run tradeoff between inflation and unem-
ployment under low inflation. However, we will show that this relationship can 
still be recovered from the most recent data if a more complicated model, one with 
time-varying parameters, is adopted. </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Inflation Change x Unemployment </p>

<p>-1.5% </p>

<p>-1.0% </p>

<p>-0.5% </p>

<p>0.0% </p>

<p>0.5% </p>

<p>1.0% </p>

<p>2% 
3% 
4% 
5% 
6% 
7% 
8% 
9% </p>

<p>Open Unemployment </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>It should be emphasized that the models used to estimate the NAIRU need 
more than the existence of the short-run tradeoff. They need the notion that 
monetary policy affects the price level by first affecting unemployment, which, 
then, via a Phillips Curve, affects inflation. In the next section we describe the 
specification adopted to identify the Brazilian NAIRU. </p>

<p>3. The Data and the Estimated Models </p>

<p>The basic data comprise the national consumer price index (INPC) of IBGE 
from 1981:12 to 2002:01 and the average rate of open unemployment of IBGE 
from 1982:1 to 2001:12. These monthly data were averaged into quarterly data 
resulting in a sample size of 80 observations. The model was estimated using only 
quarterly data, from the first quarter of 1982 to the last quarter of 2001. The 
monthly data was transformed into quarterly data as follows: </p>

<p>π t = (1/3).log(P t,f /P t−1,f ) = monthly geometric average of the quarterly rate 
of inflation; </p>

<p>P t,f = centered INPC ( national consumer price index) of IBGE for the last 
month of quarter t; </p>

<p>U t = quarterly average of the monthly average rate of open unemployment of 
IBGE. </p>

<p>3.1 The basic model </p>

<p>Our basic model for the relationship between the change of the rate of inflation 
and the rate of unemployment can be represented by the following equations: 2 </p>

<p>∆π t = µ t + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st (u t−s −ū t−s ) + Z t γ t + t 
(1) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=0 </p>

<p>µ t+s = 0 (restriction that allows for the identification of u t ) 3 
(2) </p>

<p>2 This is the standard specification used for the Phillips curve (Staiger et al. (1997, 2001), 
Gordon (1997), etc.). Vector and matrixes are bold faces. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>µ t = α 0t + α 1t D 1t + α 2t D 2t + α 3t D 3t 
(3) </p>

<p>D it = seasonal dummy of quarter i; </p>

<p>u t−1 = NAIRU at t − 1; </p>

<p>Z t = is a row vector of control variables with the two first lags of ∆π t ; 4 </p>

<p>t ∼ N (0, σ 2 ) </p>

<p>Equation (1) can also be represented in the following form: </p>

<p>∆π t = µ t + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st u t−s − </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>ξ st ∆ū t−s − ξ 0tūt−1 + Z t γ t + t 
(1') </p>

<p>where ξ 1t = −β 1t − β 2t , ξ 2t = −β 3t , ξ 0t = β 1t + β 2t + β 3t and ∆ū t−s =ū t−s −ū t−s−1 . </p>

<p>If the NAIRU slowly changes over time then </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>ξ s ∆ū t−s ∼ = 0 5 Furthermore, </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=0 </p>

<p>µ t+s = 0 implies that α 0t = −α 1t /4 − α 2t /4 − α 3t /4. Therefore, </p>

<p>∆π t = </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>(D st − 1/4) α st + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st u t−s − </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>ξ st ∆ū t−s − ξ 0tūt−1 + Z t γ t + t </p>

<p>∼ = </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>(D st − 1/4) α st + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st u t−s − ξ 0tūt−1 + Z t γ t + t </p>

<p>∆π t = β 0t + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>(D st − 1/4)α st + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st u t−s + Z t γ t + t 
(4) </p>

<p>4 We use two lags of ∆π because the basic model is one of the equations of a three lags VAR 
on inflation and unemployment in which the sum of coefficients of lagged inflation is equal to 1. 
Sargent (1971) has pointed out that, under rational expectations, this restriction is only valid 
if inflation has a unit root. We tested and did not reject that inflation in Brazil is I(1). This 
restriction is necessary for the existence of the NAIRU and implies the absence of any long-run 
trade off between inflation and unemployment. 
5 We are using here the same restriction adopted by Staiger et al. (2001). Alternatively, this 
restriction can be justified, if the initial model is similar to the one in King et al. (1995) and is </p>

<p>given by ∆πt = µt + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>βst (ut−s −ūt−1) + Ztγt + t. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>where β 0t ≡ −ξ 0tūt−1 ≡ −(β 1t + β 2t + β 3t )ū t−1 . </p>

<p>If (β 1t +β 2t +β 3t ) &lt; 0 and β 0t &gt; 0, for all t, then we can obtainū t−1 estimating 
the model and using the last equation: </p>

<p>u t−1 = −β 0t /(β 1t + β 2t + β 3t ) 
( 5 ) </p>

<p>The inflation stabilization plans adopted by Brazil (Cruzado (1986:1 and 
1986:2), Bresser (1987:3), Verão (1989:1), Collor I (1990:2), Collor II (1991:2) 
and Real (1994:3)) have produced, in the quarters of their implementation, an 
abrupt reduction of the rate of inflation. To deal with these shocks, interventions 
were made in the model at each quarter of implementation of each stabilization 
plan. The basic model with interventions at each stabilization plan is described 
by the following equation: </p>

<p>∆π t = β 0t (1 + θ tτ ) + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>[D st − (1/4)  *  (1 + θ tτ )] α st + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β st u t−s + Z t γ t + t (6) </p>

<p>θ tτ = 0, if there was no stabilization plan at quarter t; 
θ tτ = θ τ = nonlinear intercept intervention parameters when stabilization plan 
"τ " happens at period t τ = 1 (Cruzado and Collor II Plans), τ = 2 (Bresser and 
Verão Plans), τ = 3 (Collor I and Real Plans) 
To simplify the description of the model we summarize the representation of 
the model as follows: </p>

<p>Let </p>

<p>y t = ∆π t ; x t = (1 + θ tτ ) (D 1t − (1/4) (1 + θ tτ )) (D 2t − (1/4) (1 + θ tτ )) </p>

<p>(D 3t − (1/4) (1 + θ tτ )) u t−1 u t−2 u t−3 Z t </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t = [β 0t α 1t α 2t α 3t β 1t β 2t β 3t γ t ] 
therefore the model can be represented, in a compact form, by </p>

<p>y t = x t (θ tτ )β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t + t 
(7) </p>

<p>In its recent past, the Brazilian economy has experienced a period of great 
economic instability and the above equation may show structural breaks in its </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>parameters. To deal with possible structural breaks we estimate two different 
versions of the above model: the TVP model (which allows for parameter change 
over time and ARCH residuals); the MSR model (which allows for parameter 
change over time and Markov-switching regimes). </p>

<p>3.2 The TVP and the MSR models </p>

<p>The TVP Model </p>

<p>The TVP model is a state-space model with ARCH residuals and is a simplified 
version of the model proposed by Harvey et al. (1992): </p>

<p>y t = x t (θ tτ )β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t + Λ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t + t , measurement equation 
(8) </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t = β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t−1 + ω t transition equation 
(9) </p>

<p>t ∼ N 0, σ 
2 , 
ω t ∼ N (0, Q) 
and </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t /ψ t−1 ∼ N (0, h 1t ) </p>

<p>where ψ t−1 = [y t−1 , y t−2 , ...., y 1 ] , information available up to time t − 1; Λ,  *  
t and 
σ are scalars and Q is, by hypothesis, diagonal and 9 x 9. 
The ARCH effect is introduced through the scalar residual  *  
t . The variance of </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t is given by </p>

<p>h 1t = 1 + γ 0 </p>

<p> * 2 
t−1 </p>

<p>(10) </p>

<p>The MSR Model </p>

<p>The MSR model is a state-space model with a Markov-switching regime. It is 
a simplified version of the model suggested by Kim and Nelson (1999): </p>

<p>y t = x t (θ tτ )β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t + t , measurement equation 
(11) </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t = β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t−1 + ω t , transition equation 
(12) </p>

<p>t ∼ N (0, σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>St ) 
, 
ω t ∼ N (0, Q St ) </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>The subscript St denotes that σ 2 and the parameters at the diagonal of ma-
trix Q take values that depend on a discrete, nonobserved variable, that follows a 
Markov-switching process with 2 different states (regimes). The transition proba-
bilities are given by </p>

<p>P = 
p 11 p 12 
p 21 p 22 
(13) </p>

<p>where, p iJ = probability of state J, at period t, given state i at period t − 1 and </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>J=1 </p>

<p>p iJ = 1, 
i= 1, 2 
(14) </p>

<p>4. The Estimation Procedures </p>

<p>4.1 The TVP model estimation procedure </p>

<p>Harvey et al. (1992) substitute the  * 2 
t−1 variable in equation (10) , which is 
nonobserved, by its conditional expectation, h 1t = 1 + γE  * 2 
t−1 /ψ t−1 . Therefore, 
the algorithm is an approximation. To get E  * 2 
t−1 /ψ t−1 , Harvey, Ruiz and 
Sentana augmented the original state vector in the transition equation (9) in the 
following way: </p>

<p>β  *  </p>

<p>t 
 *  
t </p>

<p>= 
I 9 
0 </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>β  *  </p>

<p>t−1 
 *  
t−1 </p>

<p>+ 
I 9 
0 </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>ω t </p>

<p> *  
t </p>

<p>where I 9 is the identity matrix with 9x9 dimension. Therefore, the measurement 
equation (8) is replaced by </p>

<p>y t = [x t (θ t ) Λ] 
β  *  </p>

<p>t 
 *  
t </p>

<p>+ t </p>

<p>It is not hard to show that </p>

<p>E </p>

<p> * 2 </p>

<p>t−1 /ψ t−1 = E </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t−1 /ψ t−1 
2 + E </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t−1 − E( </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t−1 /ψ t−1 ) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The two expectations at the right-hand side of the last equation can be com-
puted, recursively, using the Kalman filter. The first expectation is equal to the 
recursive estimation of the second element of the state vector (  *  
t−1 ) squared and 
the second expectation is equal to its recursively estimated covariance matrix. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Given the intercept intervention parameters θ τ [τ = 1, 2 and 3] , σ, Λ, γ 0 and Q, 
it is possible to obtain the model's likelihood value and β  *  
t through the Kalman Fil-
ter recursions. That is, we can concentrate the likelihood with respect to β  *  
t , using 
the Kalman filter and, with the help of a numerical optimization routine, estimate </p>

<p>the value of the other parameters θ τ (τ = 1, 2 and 3), σ, Λ, γ 0 and the elements </p>

<p>at the diagonal of matrix Q that maximizes the likelihood. </p>

<p>To arrive at a more parsimonious model the following restrictions were imposed 
a priori: </p>

<p>Q(2, 2) = Q(3, 3) = Q(4, 4), equality between parameters, at the diagonal of ma-
trix Q, which controls for the time change of seasonal dummies coefficients; </p>

<p>Q(5, 5) = Q(6, 6) = Q(7, 7), equality between parameters, at the diagonal of ma-
trix Q, which controls for the time change of lag unemployment coefficients; </p>

<p>Q(8, 8) = Q(9, 9), equality between parameters, at the diagonal of matrix Q, 
which controls for the time change of lag ∆π t coefficients. </p>

<p>With these restrictions matrix Q has only 4 unknown parameters. Therefore, 
the TVP model has, if we exclude the parameters of β  *  
t from the counting, a total 
of 10 parameters to be estimated. In section 5.1 we describe how, departing from 
this more general model and using a few statistical tests, we are able to reduce, 
from 10 to 5, the number of parameters to be estimated. </p>

<p>4.2 The MSR model estimation procedure </p>

<p>In order to estimate the MSR model, it is necessary to make inferences about 
both the unobserved states and the latent Markov state. The regime shifts of the 
MSR model imposes a nonlinearity that precluded the estimation of this type of 
model until the estimation methods by Albert and Chib (1993), Shephard (1994)  and Kim (1994) were developed. I use the Kim's method to estimate the MSR 
model. The Kim filter is an optimal estimator in the sense that no other estimator, 
based on a linear function of the information set, yields a smaller mean squared 
error (Smith and Makov, 1980). In the appendix we describe the Kim filter and 
its use in the MSR model estimation. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>We adopt the same restrictions for the MSR model -on the parameters of 
the diagonal of matrix Q i (state i = 1, 2) -which were imposed on the TVP 
model in section 3.1. Furthermore, equation (15) shows that we can estimate 
only p 11 and p 21 in order to obtain the entire matrix P. Therefore, given p 11 , p 22 , 
θ τ (τ = 1, 2, 3), σ i (the measurement equation residual's standard deviation at state 
i, i = 1, 2), and the 4 parameter in the diagonal of matrix Q i , at each state, we 
can use Kim's filter and smoothing algorithm (Kim and Nelson, 1999) to estimate 
β  *  
t and calculate the value of the likelihood of the MSR model. The Kim's filter 
obtains the nonlinear mapping from the hyperparameters (σ i and Q i ; i = 1, 2), the 
parameters in P, and the intervention parameters θ τ (τ = 1, 2, 3) to the likelihood 
value. We use this mapping to estimate the likelihood maximizing values of these 
hyperparameters and parameters using a numerical optimization routine. That is, 
the likelihood can be concentrated with respect to β  *  
t making it easier to estimate 
p 11 , p 22 , θ τ (τ = 1, 2, 3) , σ 1 , σ 2 and the parameters at the diagonal of matrix Q, 
at each state, with the help of a numerical optimization routine. The results of 
this estimation are presented in section 5.2. 
The MSR model has 15 parameters to be estimated through the numerical 
optimization routine 6 . Therefore, there is an excessive number of parameters. We 
show, in the next section, how departing from this more general model and using 
a few statistical tests, we impose some restrictions and end up with a model with 
only 8 parameters to be estimated through the numerical optimization routine. </p>

<p>5. The Model's Estimation Results </p>

<p>The two models were estimated using computer programs developed with the 
help of the "<rs type="software">Matlab</rs>" software. The log likelihood for the two models, and for a 
variety of alternative hypothesis, is presented in table 1. </p>

<p>6 The parameter of β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t do not enter explicitly in the numerical optimization routine. They 
are concentrated out by the Kim filter. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Table 1 
Log likelihood and alternative hypothesis </p>

<p>TVP Model </p>

<p>Initial Model (10 parameters) 
112.07 </p>

<p>Simplified Models (Q(j, j) = 0, for j = 1, Λ = 0 and γ0 = 0) </p>

<p>Q(1, 1) = 0 (5 parameters) 
111.43 
(selected model) 
Q(1, 1) = 0 (4 parameters) 
107.87 </p>

<p>MSR Model </p>

<p>Initial Model (15 parameters) 
121.27 </p>

<p>Simplified Models (Qi(j, j) = 0, for j = 1 and i = 1, 2) </p>

<p>Q1(1, 1) = Q2(1, 1) (regime dependent) (9 par.) 
121.26 
Q1(1, 1) = Q2(1, 1) (regime independent) (8 par.) 
121.06 
Q1(1, 1) = 0 and Q2(1, 1) = 0 (regime dependent) (8 par.) 
121.09 
(selected model) 
Q1(1, 1) = 0 and Q2(1, 1) = 0 (regime dependent) (8 par.) 
119.33 
Q1(1, 1) = Q2(1, 1) = 0 (regime independent) (7 par.) 
113.14 </p>

<p>Note : the parameter count, in this table, does not include the parameters of β </p>

<p> *  
t </p>

<p>(β </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t has 9 other parameters) </p>

<p>5.1 The TVP model results and the stability of coefficients of the 
brazilian price Phillips curve </p>

<p>The TVP model was initially estimated with 10 parameters if we exclude from 
the counting the parameters that belong to β  *  
t and which were concentrated out of 
the likelihood using the Kalman filter. We could not reject -at a significance level 
higher than 10% and using the likelihood ratio test -that Λ, γ 0 and the parameters 
of the diagonal of matrix Q, which controls for the time variation of coefficients 
of the dummy variables, of the rate of unemployment and of the lags of the rate 
of inflation, are all equal to zero. The log likelihood values with and without the 
restrictions are presented in table 1. Therefore, we could not reject the stability 
of the Brazilian price Phillips Curve. The TVP model, without ARCH residual in 
the measurement equation, with a time-varying intercept (time-varying NAIRU) 
and with intercept intervention at the stabilization Plans, has only 5 parameters to 
be estimated through the numerical optimization routine. This simplified version 
of the TVP model fits the data as well as the initial less parsimonious model 
with 10 parameters. Table 1 shows that the model with 10 parameters has a 
log likelihood value of 112.07 and the simplified model with 5 parameters has a 
likelihood value of 111.43. We can also reject the hypothesis of a stable NAIRU. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>If we add this hypothesis to the already simplified 5 parameters TVP model, the 
number of parameters drops from 5 to 4, but the log likelihood drops from 111.43 
to 107.87. The estimated values of the 5 parameters of the selected TVP model 
and those of the one-step ahead Theil-U 7 can be found in table 2. The one-step 
ahead forecast and fitted values of the TVP model are presented in figure 3. The 
estimated NAIRU and its confidence interval are presented in section 6. </p>

<p>Table 2 
TVP model 
log likelihood = 111.43, Theil-U = 0.28 </p>

<p>Hyperparameters 
Parameter 
S.D. </p>

<p>Q(1, 1) 
0.0086 
0.0045 
σ( t standard deviation) 
0.0156 
0.0032 
Intercept Intervention Parameters </p>

<p>Cruzado and Collor II Plans (θ1) 
−0.8320 
0.1798 
Bresser and Verão Plans (θ2) 
−1.5427 
0.2287 
Collor I and Real Plans (θ3) 
−3.9380 
0.6404 </p>

<p>5.2 The MSR model results and the stability of coefficients of the 
price Phillips curve </p>

<p>The MSR model was initially estimated, in its more general version, with 15 
parameters, if we exclude from the counting the parameters belonging to β  *  
t . It 
could not be rejected -at a significance level higher than 10% and using the 
likelihood ratio test -that all the parameters at the diagonal of matrix Q are 
equal to zero at state 2 and that these parameters (with the exception of the 
parameter that controls for the time variability of the intercept) are also equal to 
zero at state 1. With these restrictions, the MSR model has 8 parameters to be 
estimated through the numerical optimization routine. </p>

<p>7 The one-step ahead Theil-U statistic is equal to </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t=k+1 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t / </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t=k+1 </p>

<p>(∆πt − ∆πt−1) 2 , where </p>

<p>et is the one-step ahead forecast error, k is the number of parameters of the model and T is 
the sample size. The one-step ahead forecast is obtained using the full sample to estimate the 
parameters that enter the numerical optimization routine (5 parameters for the TVP model and 
8 parameters for the MSR model). Fixing the parameters, that enters the optimization routine, 
at their maximizing levels, the other 9 parameters used in the one-step ahead forecast for period 
t use, in their estimation, only observations up to t − 1. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Table 1 presents the log likelihood for the simplified selected MSR model (with 
the above restrictions)as 121.09 and for the initial MSR model (without these re-
strictions)as 121.26. Furthermore, as table 1 shows, if we impose the additional 
restriction of no time-varying intercept in state 1 (stable NAIRU), the number 
of parameters drops from 8 to 7 but the log likelihood drops from 121.09 to 
113.14. Therefore, we cannot reject the stability of coefficients of the Brazilian 
price Phillips curve but, given this stability, we can reject a constant NAIRU. </p>

<p>Figure 3 </p>

<p>TVP Model -One Step Ahead Forecast of Dp </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>-0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>83.IV 
86.IV 
89.IV 
92.IV 
95.IV 
98.IV </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>Forecast </p>

<p>01.IV </p>

<p>MSR Model -One Step Ahead Forecast of Dp </p>

<p>-0.50 </p>

<p>-0.40 </p>

<p>-0.30 </p>

<p>-0.20 </p>

<p>-0.10 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>83.IV 
86.IV 
89.IV 
92.IV 
95.IV 
98.IV 
01.IV </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>Forecast </p>

<p>TVP Model -Fitting Dp </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>-0.3 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>83.IV 
86.IV 
89.IV 
92.IV 
95.IV </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>Forecast </p>

<p>01.IV </p>

<p>MSR Model -Fitting Dp </p>

<p>-0.50 </p>

<p>-0.40 </p>

<p>-0.30 </p>

<p>-0.20 </p>

<p>-0.10 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>83.IV 
86.IV 
89.IV 
92.IV 
95.IV 
98.IV </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp </p>

<p>Forecast </p>

<p>01.IV </p>

<p>In table 3 we present the estimated values of these 8 parameters. The estimated 
transition probability matrix (P) can be found in table 4. The one-step ahead 
forecast and fitted values of the MSR model are presented in figure 3. The state 1 
probability, at each period, can be viewed in figure 4. The estimated NAIRU and 
its confidence interval are presented in section 6. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>Table 3 
MSR model 
log likelihood = 121.09, Theil-U= 0.29 </p>

<p>Hyperparameters 
Parameter 
S.D. </p>

<p>Q(1, 1) at state 1 
0.0054 
0.0015 
σ1( t standard deviation at state 1 ) 
0.0066 
0.0015 
σ2( t standard deviation at state 2 ) 
0.0337 
0.0065 
Transition Probabilities </p>

<p>p11 [P r(St = 1|St − 1 = 1)] 
0.9600 
0.0280 
p21 [P r(St = 1|St − 1 = 2)] 
0.1290 
0.0800 
Intercept Intervention Parameters </p>

<p>Cruzado and Collor II Plans (θ1) 
−1.2873 
0.3302 
Bresser and Verão Plans (θ2) 
−2.2231 
0.4464 
Collor I and Real Plans (θ3) 
−5.9764 
1.3193 </p>

<p>Figure 4 </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Table 4 
Transition probability matrix (P) </p>

<p>St = 1 St = 2 
St − 1 = 1 
0.960 
0.040 </p>

<p>St − 1 = 2 
0.129 
0.871 </p>

<p>Steady -State 
probabilities 
0.763 
0.237 </p>

<p>5.3 The comparison between the TVP and MSR models and some 
additional statistical tests </p>

<p>Table 1 shows that the maximizing value of log likelihood for the selected MSR 
model is 121.09 and the same value for the selected TVP model is 111.43. The 
TVP model is more parsimonious than the MSR model, since it has 3 parameters 
less. It is also true that the TVP model (without ARCH residuals) is nested in 
the MSR model. Nevertheless, as it has been pointed out by Engel and Hamilton  (1990), if the information matrix is singular in the region of the parameter space 
where the MSR model becomes the TVP model, then the standard regularity con-
ditions needed to establish asymptotically valid hypothesis tests are not satisfied. 
Therefore, we cannot test, using the usual tests, which of the models better fits 
the data and the results, for both models are going to be presented. </p>

<p>The MSR model, as can be seen in table 5, satisfactorily passes two tests: one 
test, suggested by Engel and Hamilton (1990), designed to test if the measurement 
equation residuals are homoscedastic without regime switching (p 11 = 1− p 22 ) but 
with a time-varying intercept in the measurement equation at state 1; another 
to test if there is no time-varying intercept at state 1 (Q 1 (1, 1) = 0) when the 
hypothesis of Markov-switching, for the standard deviation of the residual of the 
measurement equation, is in place. When the hypothesis p 11 = 1 − p 22 is imposed 
to the MSR model, there is no longer a Markov-switching process and the rate 
of inflation is an i.i.d. sequence with individual densities given by a mixture of 
two normals. We are able to reject both hypotheses, at a significance level smaller 
than 1%, using the likelihood ratio and Wald tests. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>Table 5 
Additional hypothesis tests -MSR model </p>

<p>Ho 
 *  : p11 = 1 − p22 
Ho : Q1(1, 1) = 0 
Wald test 
179.15 
12.58 </p>

<p>Likelihood Ratio test 
12.50 
15.90 </p>

<p>Log Likelihood (under Ho) 
114.84 
113.14 </p>

<p> *  Suggested by Engel and Hamilton (1990)   We did not detect significant serial correlation, in the MSR model, for either 
the standardized one-step ahead forecast error or the squares of the standardized 
one-step ahead forecast errors. Nevertheless, the same is not true for the TVP 
model. Tables 6 and 7 present these tests. </p>

<p>Table 6 
Tests for serial correlation of standardized forecast errors </p>

<p>MRS MODEL 
TVP MODEL 
Autocorrelation Partial Q-Statistic Probability Autocorrelation Partial Q-Statistic Probability 
Correlation 
Correlation 
1 
0.210 
0.210 
3.5391 
0.060 
0.112 
0.112 
1.0071 
0.316 
2 
−0.016 
−0.063 
3.5591 
0.169 
−0.218 
−0.234 
4.8715 
0.088 
3 
−0.106 
−0.094 
4.4819 
0.214 
−0.185 
−0.137 
7.6755 
0.053 
4 
−0.056 
−0.014 
4.7397 
0.315 
0.159 
0.161 
9.7834 
0.044 
5 
−0.069 
−0.063 
5.1400 
0.399 
0.029 
−0.086 
9.8529 
0.080 
6 
−0.190 
−0.186 
8.2412 
0.221 
−0.222 
−0.203 
14.078 
0.029 
7 
−0.001 
0.072 
8.2414 
0.312 
−0.056 
0.051 
14.350 
0.045 
8 
0.021 
−0.017 
8.2814 
0.406 
0.062 
−0.049 
14.694 
0.065 
9 
−0.083 
−0.141 
8.9036 
0.446 
−0.053 
−0.160 
14.948 
0.092 
10 
−0.064 
−0.026 
9.2744 
0.506 
−0.092 
0.001 
15.714 
0.108 
11 
0.058 
0.068 
9.5794 
0.569 
0.023 
0.005 
15.763 
0.150 
12 
−0.144 
−0.266 
11.525 
0.485 
−0.158 
−0.342 
18.102 
0.113 
13 
−0.069 
0.014 
11.975 
0.530 
−0.029 
0.053 
18.183 
0.151 
14 
−0.030 
−0.011 
12.064 
0.601 
0.015 
−0.023 
18.206 
0.198 
15 
0.133 
0.042 
13.797 
0.541 
0.080 
−0.156 
18.839 
0.221 
16 
0.011 
−0.085 
13.809 
0.613 
−0.108 
−0.110 
20.004 
0.220 
17 
−0.026 
0.023 
13.878 
0.676 
−0.068 
−0.008 
20.472 
0.251 
18 
0.294 
0.271 
22.807 
0.198 
0.287 
0.155 
28.992 
0.048 
19 
0.135 
−0.024 
24.729 
0.170 
0.179 
0.004 
32.365 
0.028 
20 
−0.038 
−0.066 
24.885 
0.206 
−0.114 
−0.054 
33.760 
0.028 
21 
−0.180 
−0.071 
28.394 
0.129 
−0.172 
−0.053 
36.982 
0.017 
22 
−0.105 
−0.077 
29.612 
0.128 
0.006 
−0.137 
36.987 
0.024 
23 
−0.022 
0.014 
29.668 
0.159 
0.099 
0.001 
38.091 
0.025 
24 
−0.171 
−0.139 
33.017 
0.104 
−0.128 
−0.156 
39.983 
0.021 </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Table 7 
Tests for serial correlation of squared standardized forecast errors </p>

<p>MRS MODEL 
TVP MODEL 
Autocorrelation Partial Q-Statistic Probability Autocorrelation Partial Q-Statistic Probability 
Correlation 
Correlation 
1 
0.203 
0.203 
3.2996 
0.069 
0.055 
0.055 
0.2379 
0.626 
2 
0.016 
−0.026 
3.3215 
0.190 
0.218 
0.215 
4.0756 
0.130 
3 
−0.071 
−0.072 
3.7315 
0.292 
0.166 
0.153 
6.3475 
0.096 
4 
−0.070 
−0.043 
4.1399 
0.387 
0.016 
−0.042 
6.3685 
0.173 
5 
0.057 
0.084 
4.4096 
0.492 
0.041 
−0.029 
6.5077 
0.260 
6 
0.169 
0.145 
6.8681 
0.333 
0.287 
0.289 
13.582 
0.035 
7 
−0.062 
−0.144 
7.2053 
0.408 
−0.019 
−0.033 
13.615 
0.058 
8 
−0.074 
−0.037 
7.6944 
0.464 
0.146 
0.024 
15.498 
0.050 
9 
−0.145 
−0.098 
9.5824 
0.385 
−0.076 
−0.171 
16.015 
0.067 
10 
0.066 
0.139 
9.9768 
0.443 
−0.026 
−0.028 
16.078 
0.097 
11 
0.067 
−0.008 
10.386 
0.496 
0.000 
0.032 
16.078 
0.138 
12 
0.118 
0.071 
11.689 
0.471 
0.047 
0.030 
16.286 
0.178 
13 
0.005 
−0.009 
11.692 
0.553 
−0.107 
−0.125 
17.377 
0.183 
14 
−0.047 
−0.014 
11.906 
0.614 
−0.018 
−0.104 
17.409 
0.235 
15 
−0.092 
−0.050 
12.728 
0.623 
−0.019 
0.115 
17.445 
0.293 
16 
−0.005 
−0.027 
12.730 
0.692 
0.012 
0.106 
17.459 
0.356 
17 
0.051 
0.055 
12.997 
0.736 
−0.005 
−0.005 
17.462 
0.423 
18 
0.222 
0.188 
18.060 
0.452 
0.185 
0.134 
21.002 
0.279 
19 
−0.021 
−0.081 
18.106 
0.515 
−0.105 
−0.097 
22.152 
0.277 
20 
0.012 
0.048 
18.122 
0.579 
−0.041 
−0.092 
22.331 
0.323 
21 
−0.042 
−0.008 
18.310 
0.629 
−0.051 
−0.049 
22.614 
0.365 
22 
−0.074 
−0.080 
18.916 
0.651 
−0.107 
−0.082 
23.889 
0.353 
23 
0.025 
0.006 
18.987 
0.702 
−0.033 
−0.041 
24.009 
0.403 
24 
0.037 
−0.038 
19.144 
0.744 
−0.063 
−0.154 
24.463 
0.435 </p>

<p>6. The Estimated NAIRU and the Response of ∆π to Cyclical 
Unemployment </p>

<p>Figure 5 shows the smoothed estimates of the NAIRU for the TVP and MSR 
models, as defined in section 2, and its confidence intervals computed from the 
smoothed estimates of β  *  and of Var(β  *  ), at each period t. The confidence inter-
vals for the NAIRU were computed from 1,000 extractions of the distribution of 
the estimator of β  *  and, in each extraction, the NAIRU was computed as explained 
in section 2. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>Figure 5 </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>TVP Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>93.IV 
95.IV 
97.IV 
99.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>TVP Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>93.IV 
95.IV 
97.IV 
99.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MSR Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MSR Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Nairu </p>

<p>---</p>

<p>Confidence Intervals </p>

<p>Error Bands for Nairu </p>

<p>Smoothed Estimations -95% confidence Intervals (1,000 simulations at each date) </p>

<p>After the Real Plan, there is growing evidence of the presence of seasonality 
in the unemployment data. Therefore, we also have estimated both previously 
selected models, with seasonally adjusted unemployment data 8 . The estimated 
NAIRU and its confidence intervals for both models, with seasonally adjusted 
unemployment data, are presented in figure 6. 
The cyclical unemployment is defined as the difference, at each date t, between 
the observed rate of unemployment and the estimated NAIRU. If we consider as 
given the cyclical unemployment then, from equation (1), we get: </p>

<p>8 The unemployment rate was seasonally adjusted using the <rs type="software">x12-arima</rs> software. The presence 
of seasonality in ∆π is dealt with, in our model, by the seasonal dummies. Nevertheless, if we 
exclude these dummies from the model, the results do not change in any significant way. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>∆π t = µ t + </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>β s C t−s + </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s=1 </p>

<p>γ s ∆π t−s + t 
(1") </p>

<p>where C t = u t − u t = cyclical unemployment. </p>

<p>Figure 6 </p>

<p>........ </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MSR Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>93.IV 
95.IV 
97.IV 
99.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>MSR Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>TVP Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>93.IV 
95.IV 
97.IV 
99.IV 
01.IV 
2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>TVP Model </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>Seasonally adjusted Unemployment 
Nairu </p>

<p>---</p>

<p>Confidence Intervals </p>

<p>Error Bands for Nairu -with seasonally adjusted unemployment data </p>

<p>Smoothed Estimations -95% confidence Intervals (1,000 simulations at each date) </p>

<p>The response of ∆π t (the first difference of inflation) to a permanent +0.5% 
cyclical unemployment, which has started at period t-h, can be computed through 
the following recursions: </p>

<p>θ(1) = 1 and θ(n) = </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i=2 </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p> </p>

<p>min{i−1,2} </p>

<p>k=1 </p>

<p>[γ k .θ(i − k)] </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p> 
; n = 1, 2, . . . </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>

<p>921 </p>

<p>R(0) = 0 and R(h) = 0.5  *  12  *  </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>k=1 </p>

<p>min{k−1,3} </p>

<p>m=0 </p>

<p>β m θ(k − m), 
h= 1, 2, .... </p>

<p>R(h) is the annualized percent response of ∆π to a 0.5% cyclical unemployment 
that has been persistent for the last h quarters. Given the distributions of the pa-
rameters of equation (1 ), we can construct error bands for R(h) through Monte 
Carlo simulations. Figure 7 presents the cyclical unemployment, R(h) and its error 
bands for the TVP and MSR models with nonseasonally adjusted unemployment. 
Figure 8 presents the same results for the TVP and MSR models when both are 
estimated using seasonally adjusted unemployment. </p>

<p>Figure 7 </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment -MSR </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment -TVP </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 </p>

<p>-25 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Response to +0.5% Cyclical Unemployment -MSR </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp 
(%) </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 </p>

<p>-25 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Response to +0.5% Cyclical Unemployment -TVP </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp 
(%) </p>

<p>Estimated Value 
--------
95% Confidence Intervals (1000 simulations) </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment and the Response of the Change in 
Annual Inflation Rate ( ) to Cyclical Unemployment 
Dp </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Figure 8 </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment -TVP </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 
-25 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Response to +0.5% Cyclical Unemployment -TVP </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp 
(%) </p>

<p>85.IV 
89.IV 
93.IV 
97.IV 
01.IV 
-6 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment -MSR </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>1 
3 
5 
7 
9 
11 
-25 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>-15 </p>

<p>-10 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Response to +0.5% Cyclical Unemployment -MSR </p>

<p>quarters </p>

<p>Dp 
(%) </p>

<p>Estimated Value 
--------
95% Confidence Intervals (1000 simulations) </p>

<p>Cyclical Unemployment and the Response of the Change in Annual 
Inflation Rate ( ) to Cyclical Unemployment (with seasonally adjusted unemployment data) 
Dp </p>

<p>The main conclusions are as follows: There is a statistically significant rela-
tionship between cyclical unemployment and the change in inflation rate; if the 
TVP model is considered, a permanent 0.5% cyclical unemployment, after 3 quar-
ters, reduces by 7.5% the annualized monthly inflation rate; if the MSR model is 
considered a permanent 0.5% cyclical unemployment, after 1 quarter, reduces by 
5% the annualized monthly inflation rate. </p>

<p>7. Conclusions </p>

<p>In our analysis of the results we emphasize two main aspects: Is there a sta-
tistically significant relationship between an upward (downward) deviation of the 
rate of unemployment from our estimated value of the NAIRU and a reduction 
(increase) in the rate of inflation? To what degree our measure of the NAIRU is </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>significantly different from the observed rate of unemployment across time? 
The first question can be easily answered by observing the response of inflation 
to cyclical unemployment, presented in section 5. There is a significant and neg-
ative response of inflation to an increase in cyclical unemployment. Nevertheless 
the effect is not measured with high precision if we consider model uncertainty. 
The response of annual inflation to 0.5% cyclical unemployment that is persistent 
for 3 quarters belongs, with a 95% degree of confidence, to the (−11%, −7.5%) 
interval for the TVP model and to the (−6%, −4%) interval for the MSR model. 
The two models do not allow for time-varying coefficients for lag unemployment 
and lag inflation. Therefore, it cannot be rejected that the deviations of the rate 
of unemployment from the NAIRU can have a significant effect, with correct sign, 
on the rate of inflation. Nevertheless, it is also true that the above estimates of 
the effect are not very precise. If we consider the uncertainty with respect to what 
the right model is, then any value between −11% and −4% cannot be rejected. 
The answer to the second question depends on the degree of precision with 
which the NAIRU is estimated. Observing figures 5 and 6 we can conclude that 
the estimates of the NAIRU, considering both models, are very imprecise and that 
from the second quarter of 1995 the estimated value of the NAIRU is contained 
within its error bands and therefore it cannot be rejected that the observed rate 
of unemployment was equal to the NAIRU. 
Despite what we have said, one cannot conclude that our estimates of the 
NAIRU are useless. It should be pointed out that, during a good part of the period 
of high inflation faced by Brazil, the rate of unemployment was systematically 
below the error bands estimated for the NAIRU. Therefore, there was a continuous 
uptrend in the rate of inflation, whose upward trajectory was only broken by the 
stabilization plans. This is true for the MSR model from the beginning of 1985 
until the second semester of 1995. For the TVP model, this is true from the 
beginning of 1986 to the beginning of 1991. It is also interesting to note that the 
two models indicate that there was a decrease in the NAIRU from 1994 until the 
middle of 1995, when it started increasing again until it reached values next to its 
previous 1994 level by 1999. The NAIRU has been decreasing since the year 2000. 
Unfortunately, there is not a large number of articles with different models and 
with estimates of the NAIRU for Brazil. The degree of confidence in the results 
depends critically on the increase of research in this area. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>



<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>





<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>



<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Let, 
ψ t−1 = [y t−1 , y t−2 , ...., y 1 ] , information available up to time t-1; </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = E(β  *  
t ψ t−1 , S t = j, S t−1 = i) ; </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = E[(β  *  
t − β  *  
t/t−1 )(β  *  
t − β  *  
t/t−1 ) /ψ t−1 , S t = j, S t−1 = i] ; </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 = E(β  *  
t−1 /ψ t−1 , S t−1 = i); </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 = E[(β  *  
t−1 − β  *  
t−1/t−1 )(β  *  
t−1 − β  *  
t−1/t−1 ) /ψ t−1 , S t−1 = i]; </p>

<p>Pr [S t = j, S t−1 = i] = p iJ ; </p>

<p>P = [p ij ] = matrix of transition probabilities; </p>

<p>Pr [S t = i|ψ t ] = probability of state i , at period t, given information up to 
time t. </p>

<p>The objective of Kim's nonlinear filter is to obtain estimates of the unob-
served state vector (β  *  
t ) and its associated mean squared error matrix (Σ t ), and 
of the marginal probability of the latent Markov state variable S t , at each date 
t. The estimates are based on information available up to time t. That is, at 
each date t, given β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 , </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 , Pr[S t−1 = i|ψ t−1 ], y t , Q j , σ j , (for i = 1, 2 
and j = 1, 2), θτ (τ = 1, 2 and 3) and the matrix of transition probabilities (P) 
the Kim's filter allows us to obtain approximate estimations of β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>t|t , Σ </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>t|t , and 
Pr[S t = j|ψ t ](j = 1, 2). To start the filter we need the initial values of β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>0|0 , 
Σ </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>0|0 and Pr[S 0 = i/ψ 0 ](i = 1, 2). We set β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>0|0 = 0 , Σ </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>0|0 = Ix100.000 and 
Pr[S 0 = i/ψ 0 ] (i = 1, 2) equal to the ergodic distribution of the Markov chain (the 
steady-state marginal distribution of the states). What we have called Kim filter 
is actually a combination of the Kalman filter, Hamilton filter and a collapsing 
procedure. We describe the Kim filter below 9 . </p>

<p>9 A detailed discussion of the Kim's filter can be found in Kim (1994) and Kim and Nelson 
(1999). </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>Part I of Kim Filter -The Kalman Filter </p>

<p>Given β </p>

<p> * (i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 , </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 , y t , Q i , σ i , ( for i = 1, 2) and θτ (τ = 1, 2, 3), 
the Kalman Filter gives β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t , the conditional one-step prediction er-
ror (η </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 ), and the conditional variance of the one-step prediction error, f </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>( for i = 1, 2 and j = 1, 2). The algorithm estimates 2 (number of different pos-
sible regimes) state vectors for each possible value of S t−1 . Therefore, at each 
date t, the algorithm estimates 4 state vectors. The Kalman filter recursions are 
presented below: </p>

<p>Prediction equations: </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = β </p>

<p> * (i) 
t−1|t−1 </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = </p>

<p>(i) </p>

<p>t−1|t−1 +Q j </p>

<p>Updating equations: </p>

<p>η </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = y t − β </p>

<p> * (i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 x t </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 = x t </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 x t + σ 2 </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>= β </p>

<p> * (i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 + </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 x t f </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>η </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t = (I − </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 x t f </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>x t ) </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>Part II of Kim Filter -The Hamilton Filter </p>

<p>Given Pr [S t−1 = i|ψ t−1 ],P, η </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 , f </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 , the Hamilton Filter obtains 
Pr[S t−1 = i, S t = j|ψ t ] and Pr[S t = i| t ]. The Hamilton Filter is presented 
below: </p>

<p>Pr [S t = j, S t−1 = i|ψ t−1 ] = Pr [S t = j, S t−1 = i] Pr [S t−1 = i|ψ t−1 ] , (i, j = 1, 2) </p>

<p>Pr [S t−1 = i, S 1 = j|ψ t ] = 
f (y t |S t−1 = i, S t = j, ψ t−1 ) Pr [S t−1 = i, S t = j|ψ t−1 ] 
f (y t |ψ t−1 ) </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

<p>The NAIRU, Unemployment and the Rate of Inflation in Brazil </p>



<p>Pr [S t = j|ψ t ] = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>Pr [S t−1 = i, S t = j|ψ t ] </p>

<p>Where, </p>

<p>f (y t |S t−1 = i, S t = j, ψ t−1 ) = (2π) </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 f </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t−1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 exp − 
1 
2 
η </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 , f </p>

<p>(i,j) −1 </p>

<p>t|t−1 η </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t−1 (i, j = 1, 2) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>f (y t |ψ t−1 ) = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>f (y t |S t = j, S t−1 = i, ψ t−1 ) Pr [S t = j, S t−1 = i|ψ t−1 ] </p>

<p>Part III of Kim Filter -The Collapsing </p>

<p>Given β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>(both estimated by the Kalman filter) , Pr S t−1 = i , 
S t = j|ψ t , Pr [S t = i|ψ t ] (both estimated by the Hamilton filter) and P, the filter </p>

<p>collapses β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>into β </p>

<p> * (j) </p>

<p>t|t and </p>

<p>(i,j) </p>

<p>t|t into </p>

<p>(j) </p>

<p>t|t . The collapsing is of crucial impor-
tance because without it the number of filter evaluations is multiplied by 2, at each 
date t, and it is computationally unfeasible to estimate the model. The collaps-
ing is an approximation based on the work of Harrison and Stevens (1976). The 
approximation consists of a weighted average of the updating procedures by the 
probabilities of the Markov state, in which the mixture of 4 Gaussian densities is 
collapsed, after each observation, into a mixture of 2 densities. It is done as follows: </p>

<p>Collapsing equations: </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (j) </p>

<p>t|t = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>Pr [S t−1 = i, S t = j|ψ t ] β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>Pr [S t = j|ψ t ] </p>

<p>(j) </p>

<p>t|t = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>Pr[S t−1 =i,St=j|ψt] </p>

<p>(i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>+ β </p>

<p> * (i) 
t|t </p>

<p>−β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (i) 
t|t </p>

<p>−β </p>

<p> * (i,j) 
t|t </p>

<p>Pr[St=j|ψt] </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>



<p>Elcyon Caiado Rocha Lima </p>

<p>The Likelihood </p>

<p>The likelihood is given by : L = </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>f (y t /ψ t−1 ) </p>

<p>The Recursive Estimates </p>

<p>β  *  
t|t = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>β </p>

<p> * (j) </p>

<p>t|t Pr [S t = j|ψ t ] </p>

<p>Σ t|t = </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>Σ </p>

<p>(j) </p>

<p>t|t Pr [S t = j|ψ t ] </p>

<p>Therefore, given p 11 , p 22 , θτ (τ = 1, 2, 3) , σ i (the measurement equation 
residual's standard deviation at state i, i = 1, 2), and the 4 parameter at the 
diagonal o matrix Q i at each state, we can use the Kim's filter to estimate β  *  
t|t , 
Σ t|t , Pr [S t = j|ψ t ] and calculate the value of the likelihood of the MSR model. The 
Kim filter obtains the nonlinear mapping from the hyperparameters (σ i and Q i ; i = 
1, 2), the parameters in P, and the intervention parameters θτ (τ = 1, 2, 3) to the 
likelihood value. We use this mapping to estimate the likelihood maximizing values 
of these hyperparameters and parameters using a numerical optimization routine. 
Given the output of the Kim filter we can use Kim's smoothing algorithm (Kim 
and Nelson, 1999) to estimate -using all the sample information -β  *  
t and its 
covariance matrix. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro 57(4):899-930 OUT/DEZ 2003 </p>

</text></tei>