<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10614-011-9257-z" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract We present an algorithm and a corresponding <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> numerical 
toolbox to solve any form of infinite-planning horizon affine linear quadratic open-loop 
differential games. By rewriting a specific application into the standard framework one 
can use the toolbox to calculate and verify the existence of both the open-loop non-
cooperative Nash equilibrium (equilibria) and cooperative Pareto equilibrium (equi-
libria). In case there is more than one equilibrium for the non-cooperative case, the 
toolbox determines all solutions that can be implemented as a feedback strategy. Alter-
natively, the toolbox can apply a number of choice methods in order to discriminate 
between multiple equilibria. The user can predefine a set of coalition structures for 
which they would like to calculate the non-cooperative Nash solution(s). It is also 
possible to specify the relative importance of each player in any coalition structure. 
Furthermore, the toolbox offers plotting facilities as well as other options to analyse 
the outcome of the game. For instance, it is possible to disaggregate each player's 
total loss into its contributing elements. The toolbox is available as a freeware from 
the authors of this paper. </p>

<p>Many situations in, for example, economics and management are characterised by 
multiple decision makers/players who can enforce decisions that have enduring 
consequences. This often invokes coordination problems and so a natural frame-
work to analyze these kinds of problems involves dynamic game theoretical set-
tings. Dynamic game theory tries to arrive at appropriate models describing a 
dynamic process affected by different players. Depending on the specific problem 
such models can sometimes be used by an individual decision maker to opti-
mise her performance. In other cases it may serve as a starting point to intro-
duce new communication lines which may help to improve upon the outcome of 
the current process. Furthermore it is possible to analyze the robustness of play-
ers' strategies w.r.t. worst-case scenarios. To this end one can introduce "nature" 
as an additional player which tries to work against the other decision makers in a 
process. 
In, for example, policy coordination problems two basic questions usually arise: 
(i) whether policies are coordinated and, (ii) which information the participating par-
ties have. Both these points are rather unclear and, therefore, strategies for differ-
ent possible scenarios are calculated and compared with each other. Often, one of 
these scenarios is the so-called open-loop scenario. In this open-loop information sce-
nario it is assumed that all players know just the initial state of the process and the 
model structure. More specifically, it is assumed that players simultaneously deter-
mine their actions for the whole planning horizon of the process before it starts. 
Next they submit their actions to some central authority who then enforces these 
plans as binding commitments. In other words, players cannot react on any devi-
ations occurring during the evolution of the process. Obviously, since according 
to this scenario the participating parties can not react to each other's policies, its 
economic relevance is mostly rather limited. However, as a benchmark to see how 
much parties can gain by playing other strategies, its role is fundamental. Due to its 
analytic tractability the open-loop Nash equilibrium strategy is in particular very pop-
ular for problems where the underlying model can be described by a (set of) linear 
differential equation(s) and the individual objectives can be approximated by func-
tions that quadratically penalise deviations from some (equilibrium) targets. Exam-
ples and additional references of differential games in economics and management 
science can be found e.g. in Dockner et al. (2000), Jørgensen and Zaccour (2003) 
and Plasmans et al. (2006). 
Under the assumption that the parties have a finite-planning horizon, the linear 
quadratic differential game was first modeled and solved in a mathematically rigorous 
way by Starr and Ho (1969a,b). A recent exposition (and additional references) on lin-
ear quadratic differential games can be found in Engwerda (2005), whereas Başar and 
Olsder (1999) give a good overview and introduction on dynamic games in general. 
In the rest of this paper we will concentrate on the case that the players base 
their decisions on a performance criterion that has an infinite-planning horizon. We 
will present an algorithm and a corresponding <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> numerical toolbox which 
solves any form of an infinite-planning horizon affine linear quadratic open-loop 
differential game. The software, called <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs>, is available as a freeware </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>from the authors of this paper. 1 By rewriting a specific application into the standard 
framework, one can use the toolbox to calculate and verify the existence of both the 
open-loop non-cooperative Nash equilibrium (equilibria) and cooperative Pareto equi-
librium (equilibria) of any infinite-planning horizon affine linear quadratic open-loop 
differential game. In case there is more than one equilibrium for the non-cooperative 
case, the toolbox determines all solutions that can be implemented as a state-feed-
back strategy that is a common assumption in most of the applications. 2 Alternatively, 
the toolbox can apply a number of choice methods in order to discriminate between 
multiple equilibria. For instance, one can choose to report only Pareto-undominated 
solutions or only those that are characterised by the lowest combined loss of all the 
players. In order to determine the cooperative solution, the user is asked to specify the 
relative importance of each player in the cooperative game. Moreover, the user can 
predefine a set of coalition structures for which they would like to calculate the non-
cooperative Nash solution(s). Conversely, a coalition structure generator is provided 
that automatically creates a whole space of coalition structures for a given number 
of players. Furthermore, the toolbox offers plotting facilities as well as other options 
to analyze the outcome of the game. For instance, it is possible to disaggregate each 
player's total loss into its contributing elements, which correspond to the quadratic 
expressions constituting the player's loss function. 
The paper is organised as follows. In Sect. 2 we will outline the model considered 
and present both necessary and sufficient conditions under which there will exist a 
unique equilibrium, a number of multiple equilibria or an infinite number of these. 
The basic algorithm underlying the numerical toolbox that is presented in Sect. 4 is 
discussed in Sect. 3. In Sect. 4 we will discuss the toolbox that has been constructed 
to verify in typical applications whether there will be a unique equilibrium, multiple 
equilibria or infinite number of these and how to obtain the solution in the first two 
cases. In Sect. 5 we illustrate the use and capabilities of this software with a number 
of examples. Section 6 concludes. </p>

<p>2 The Open-Loop Game </p>

<p>In this section we consider two players who control a different set of inputs v i to the 
single system described by the structural (simultaneous) form model: </p>

<p>y(t) = P 1ṗ (t) + P 2 p(t) + P 3 y(t) + P 41 v 1 (t) + P 42 v 2 (t) + P 5 c, 
(1) </p>

<p>p(t) = P 6ṗ (t) + P 7 p(t) + P 8 y(t) + P 91 v 1 (t) + P 92 v 2 (t) + P 10 c, p(0) = p 0 , (2) </p>

<p>where p is the n-dimensional state of the system; v i is an m i -dimensional (con-
trol) vector that player i, i = 1, 2, can manipulate; y is a b-dimensional vector of </p>

<p>1 A dedicated webpage will be available on-line soon. Mean while contact T. Michalak for obtaining the 
software. 
2 A state-feedback strategy can be expressed as a linear function of the state variables of the model. 
Specifically, if we denote a vector of state variables by x, a state-feedback strategy can be written as F x, 
where F is a real valued function of appropriate dimension. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>endogenous variables; c is a constant (that can be chosen without loss of generality 
equal to 1) and p 0 is the initial state of the system. We assume that all variables can 
be observed at any point of time and that n, m i ≥ 1 and b ≥ 0. Model (1,2) is a 
formulation which one frequently encounters in economic modeling. Since we like 
to stay close to the original equations formulated by the modeler we choose for this 
formulation instead of the standard state-space formulation. Notice that, by choos-
ing P 1 = P 3 = P 6 = P 8 = 0, our formulation includes the standard state-space 
formulation. 
The performance criterion player i likes to minimise is: </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt ( i1 w(t) − f ) 
T L i1 ( i1 w(t) − f ) + 2( i2 w(t) − g) 
T L i2 e dt, (3) </p>

<p>where w T (t) := [ṗ T (t) p T (t) y T (t) v T 
1 (t) v T 
2 (t)]; f and g are some constant vec-
tors in IR 2n+b+m 1 +m 2 ; e := [1, . . . , 1] T ∈ IR 2n+b+m 1 +m 2 and θ is a non-negative 
discounting factor. In this formulation the introduction of the i j matrices makes 
it possible to deal with several interpretations of the model. For instance by choos-
ing in (3) i1 = i2 and f = g the vector i j w(t) can be interpreted as an out-
put vector of the system player i likes to track towards some specific value. 
By choosing a specific column of the i j, j = 1, 2, matrices equal to zero, e.g., 
one can express the fact that some variable is not an important variable for 
player i. The matrices L i1 are (without loss of generality) assumed to be sym-
metric. Later on additional assumptions will be made w.r.t. some of the above 
matrices. 
It is assumed that the players act non-cooperatively and that their information struc-
ture about the game is of the open-loop type. More specifically, we suppose that the 
players choose their actions from the following set of actions: </p>

<p>U s = v ∈ L 2 | J i (x 0 , v) exists in IR ∪ {−∞, ∞}, lim </p>

<p>t→∞ </p>

<p>x(t) = 0 . </p>

<p>The assumption that both players simultaneously use stabilizing controls introduces 
the cooperative meta-objective to stabilise the system (see e.g. Engwerda (2005), for 
a discussion). 
We are looking for the Nash equilibria of this game. That is, for the combinations 
of actions of all players which are secure against any attempt by one player to uni-
laterally alter her strategy, or, stated differently, for such sets of actions that if one 
player deviates she will only lose. In the literature on dynamic games this problem 
is known as the open-loop Nash non-zero-sum linear quadratic differential game and 
has been analyzed by several authors (see e.g. Starr and Ho 1969a; Simaan and Cruz 
1973; Başar and Olsder 1999; Abou-Kandil and Bertrand 1986; Feucht 1994; Kremer 
2002; Engwerda 2005). To avoid cumbersome notation, we restrict the analyses in 
this section to the two-player case. The algorithm is, however, implemented for the 
general N -player case. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>To analyze the question under which conditions this game will have a unique equi-
librium we first rewrite the model into the standard framework considered in Engwerda 
(2008). 3 
Assuming that I − P 6 is invertible, we have from (2) thaṫ </p>

<p>p(t) = (I − P 6 ) 
−1 (P 7 p(t) + P 8 y(t) + P 91 v 1 (t) + P 92 v 2 (t) + P 10 c) . 
(4) </p>

<p>Substitution of this into (1) and, under the assumption thatP 1 := I − P 1 (I − P 6 ) −1 P 8 − 
P 3 is invertible we can perform a number of elementary operations in order to arrive 
at the following reduced form of the model: </p>

<p>p(t) =Â p(t) +B 1 v 1 (t) +B 2 v 2 (t) +Ê 1 c, p(0) = p 0 , 
(5) 
y(t) =Ĉ p(t) +D 1 v 1 (t) +D 2 v 2 (t) +Ê 2 c, 
(6) </p>

<p>withĈ </p>

<p>:=P </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 (P 1 (I − P 6 ) 
−1 P 7 + P 2 ), 
(7) </p>

<p>D 1 :=P </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 (P 1 (I − P 6 ) 
−1 P 91 + P 41 ), 
(8) </p>

<p>D 2 :=P </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 (P 1 (I − P 6 ) 
−1 P 92 + P 42 ), 
(9) </p>

<p>E 2 :=P </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 (P 1 (I − P 6 ) 
−1 P 10 + P 5 ), 
(10) </p>

<p>A := (I − P 6 ) 
−1 (P 8Ĉ + P 7 ), 
(11) 
B 1 := (I − P 6 ) 
−1 (P 8D1 + P 91 ), 
(12) </p>

<p>B 2 := (I − P 6 ) 
−1 (P 8D2 + P 92 ), 
(13) 
E 1 := (I − P 6 ) 
−1 (P 8Ê2 + P 10 ). 
(14) </p>

<p>Next, introduce z T := p T c v T 
1 v T 
2 . Substitutingṗ and y from (5) and (6), respec-
tively, into w yields: </p>

<p>w = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ÂÊ </p>

<p>1B1B2 </p>

<p>I 0 0 
0 
CÊ 2D1D2 
0 0 
I 
0 
0 0 0 
I </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ 
z =: N z. 
(15) </p>

<p>Using this, J i can be rewritten as: </p>

<p>J i = </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt z 
T (t)( i1 N − [0 f 0 0]) 
T L i1 ( i1 N − [0 f 0 0])z(t) </p>

<p>+2z 
T (t)( i2 N − [0 g 0 0]) 
T L i2 [0 e 0 0]z(t) dt </p>

<p>3 See also Engwerda (2005, Chap. 7). </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt z 
T (t) ( i1 N − [0 f 0 0]) 
T L i1 ( i1 N − [0 f 0 0]) </p>

<p>+ ( i2 N − [0 g 0 0]) 
T L i2 [0 e 0 0] + [0 e 0 0] 
T L </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>i2 ( i2 N − [0 g 0 0]) z(t)dt </p>

<p>=: </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt z 
T (t)M i z(t)dt. 
(16) </p>

<p>Finally, we introduce the extended state variable x T (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt [ p T (t) c] and con-
trol variable u i (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt v i (t) so that the state of the system isn = n + 1-dimen-
sional. Now, the game can be rewritten into the standard form. Players minimise: </p>

<p>J i (u 1 , u 2 ) := </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>[x 
T (t), u </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 (t), u </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 (t)]M i </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>x(t) 
u 1 (t) 
u 2 (t) </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ dt, 
(17) </p>

<p>where x(t) is the solution to the linear differential equation: </p>

<p>x(t) = Ax(t) + B 1 u 1 (t) + B 2 u 2 (t), x 
T (0) = p </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0 c , 
(18) </p>

<p>with: </p>

<p>A := 
Â − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ IÊ 1 
0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>; and B i := 
B i 
0 
. 
(19) </p>

<p>Now, factorise M i as follows: </p>

<p>M i =: </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ 
Q i V i W i 
V T </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>R 1i N i 
W T </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>N T </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>R 2i </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ , </p>

<p>with Q i ∈ IRn ×n , R 1i ∈ IR m i ×m i , V i ∈ IRn ×m 1 , W i ∈ IRn ×m 2 and N i ∈ IR m 1 ×m 2 . 
In the rest of the paper we will assume that the matrices R ii are positive definite 
and matrix G (see Appendix A for some additional notation including matrix G) is 
invertible. In the solution of this game the next algebraic Riccati equations play an 
important role: </p>

<p>A 
T K 1 + K 1 A − (K 1 B 1 + V 1 )R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 K 1 + V </p>

<p>T 
1 </p>

<p>+ Q 1 = 0, 
(20) 
A 
T K 2 + K 2 A − (K 2 B 2 + W 2 )R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>22 B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 K 2 + W </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 + Q 2 = 0, </p>

<p>as well as the set of (coupled) algebraic Riccati equations: </p>

<p>0 = A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2P +P A −P BG 
−1 B 
TP + Q, 
(21) </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>or, equivalently: </p>

<p>0 = A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2P +P A − P B + </p>

<p>Z 1 
Z 2 
G 
−1 ( B 
TP + Z ) + Q. </p>

<p>In particular, the existence of a so-called strongly stabilizing solution of (21) plays 
an important role. A solutionP T =: (P T 
1 ,P T 
2 ), withP i ∈ IRn, of (21) is called a 
strongly stabilizing solution if both σ Ã − BG −1B TP and σ Ã T 
2 −P BG −1B T 
⊂ C − . 4 
The next relationship between certain invariant subspaces of matrix: </p>

<p>M := 
Ã −BG −1B T </p>

<p>−Q 
−Ã T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(22) </p>

<p>and the solutions of the Riccati equations (21) are well-known (see e.g. Engwerda 
2007). This property will also be used to calculate the strongly stabilizing solutions 
of (21). </p>

<p>Lemma 1 Let V ⊂ IR 3n be ann-dimensional invariant subspace of M, and let X i ∈ 
IRn ×n , i = 0, 1, 2, be three real matrices such that: </p>

<p>V = im X </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0 , X </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 , X </p>

<p>T 
2 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>. 
(23) </p>

<p>If X 0 is invertible, thenP i := X i X </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 , i = 1, 2, solves (21) and σ (A − BG −1 (Z + 
B TP )) = σ (M| V ). Furthermore, (P 1 ,P 2 ) is independent of the specific choice of a 
basis of V . </p>

<p>When X 0 is invertible, then-dimensional invariant subspace V in (23) is called a 
graph subspace. The next lemma provides a characterisation of the strongly stabilizing 
solution of (21): </p>

<p>Lemma 2 1. The set of algebraic Riccati equations (21) has a strongly stabilizing 
solutionP if and only if matrix M has ann-dimensional stable graph subspace 
and M has 2n eigenvalues (counting algebraic multiplicities) with a real part 
larger than or equal to zero. 
2. If the set of algebraic Riccati equations (21) has a strongly stabilizing solution, 
then it is unique. </p>

<p>A proof of both this lemma and the next theorem follow directly from Engwerda 
(2008). </p>

<p>Theorem 3 Consider the differential game (17-18) with symmetric M i , R ii &gt; 0, 
invertible matrix G and (A, B i ) stabilizable. 
This game has a unique open-loop Nash equilibrium for every initial state if and only if </p>

<p>4 σ (H ) denotes the spectrum of matrix H ; C − = {λ ∈ C | Re(λ) &lt; 0}. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>1. The set of coupled algebraic Riccati equations (21) has a strongly stabilizing 
solution, and 
2. the two algebraic Riccati equations (20) have a (strongly) stabilizing solution. </p>

<p>Moreover, in case this game has a unique equilibrium, the equilibrium actions are 
given by: </p>

<p>u  *  
1 (t) 
u  *  
2 (t) </p>

<p>= −G 
−1 Z +B 
TP ˜ (t, 0)x 0 , 
(24) </p>

<p>where˜ (t, 0) is the solution of the transition equation: </p>

<p>(t, 0) = A − BG 
−1 Z +B TP 
˜ (t, 0);˜ (0, 0) = I. </p>

<p>The costs by using the actions (24) for the players are: </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0L i x 0 , i = 1, 2, 
(25) </p>

<p>where, with A cl := A− BG −1 Z +B TP ,L i is the unique solution of the Lyapunov 
equation: </p>

<p>I, −G 
−1 Z +B </p>

<p>TP </p>

<p>M i I, −G 
−1 Z +B </p>

<p>TP 
T </p>

<p>+ A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>clL i +L i A cl = 0. </p>

<p>In case the game has more than one equilibrium, generically, there exists an infi-
nite number of equilibria (see Engwerda 2005; Kremer 2002). However, usually for 
a finite number of them only, the corresponding actions can be implemented as a 
state-feedback strategy (i.e., such strategy that can be written as a linear function of 
the state variables of the model like, for instance, in Theorem 3; see also footnote 1 
in this paper). In economics it is often argued that actions by policymakers have a 
(state-)feedback structure (Taylor rule etc.). For that reason, in case there is more than 
one equilibrium, the algorithm will determine only those that can be implemented as 
a (state-)feedback rule. From Engwerda (2005) we recall the following result. </p>

<p>Theorem 4 The differential game (17-18), with M i symmetric, R ii &gt; 0, matrix G 
invertible and (A, B i ) stabilizable, has for every initial state an open-loop Nash set 
of equilibrium actions (u  *  
1 , u  *  
2 ) which permit a feedback synthesis if and only if 
1. The set of coupled algebraic Riccati equations (21) has a stabilizing solution, and 
2. the two algebraic Riccati equations (20) have a stabilizing solution. </p>

<p>Moreover, ifP is stabilizing solution of (21), the actions (24) yield an open-loop 
Nash equilibrium that can be synthesised as a state feedback. The corresponding costs 
are given by (25). </p>

<p>Finally, if one would like to consider the game (17-18) without a constant that, in 
particular, allows for a zero discount rate, the state variable should not be extended, </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>i.e., x T (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt p T (t) is to be used instead of x T (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt p T (t) c . The 
system in (18) becomes: </p>

<p>x(t) = Ax(t) + B 1 u 1 (t) + B 2 u 2 (t), x 
T (0) = p </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0 , 
(26) </p>

<p>where: </p>

<p>A :=Â − 
1 
2 
θ I ; 
(27) </p>

<p>B i :=B i . 
(28) </p>

<p>The rest of the above analysis remains valid but withn = n. </p>

<p>3 The Computational Framework </p>

<p>To verify the existence, the number and numerical values of equilibria in the game 
(17-18), in the numerical toolbox we use the following algorithm 5 : </p>

<p>Algorithm 5 </p>

<p>Step A1: Verify whether R ii &gt; 0, G is invertible and (A, B i ) are stabilizable. If this 
is not the case, go to Step A6. 
Step A2: Calculate the eigenstructure of: </p>

<p>H 1 := 
A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V 1 
−S 1 </p>

<p>−Q 1 
− A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V 1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>H 2 := 
A − B 2 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>22 W 2 
−S 2 </p>

<p>−Q 2 
− A − B 2 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>22 W 2 </p>

<p>T . </p>

<p>If H i , i = 1, 2, has ann-dimensional stable graph subspace, then proceed. 
Otherwise there is not an equilibrium and go to Step A6. 6 </p>

<p>Step A3: Calculate matrix M := 
Ã −BG −1B T </p>

<p>−Q 
−Ã T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>If M has s ≥n stable eigenvalues and u ≤ 2n unstable eigenvalues (count-
ing algebraic multiplicities) then proceed to Step A4. Otherwise, i.e., if 
s &lt;n, the game has no equilibrium and go to Step A6. 
Step A4: The number of equilibria equals the number of differentn-dimensional sta-
ble invariant graph subspaces of matrix M. In particular this implies that if </p>

<p>5 Notice that we just present those equilibria that can be synthesized as a feedback strategy. </p>

<p>6 With an equilibrium we mean everywhere in the algorithm an equilibrium that can be synthesized as a 
state feedback. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>matrix M has eigenvalues that have a geometric multiplicity that is larger 
than one, it may happen that there are an infinite number of equilibria (see 
e.g. Engwerda 2005, Example 7.11). The algorithm does not elaborate this 
case because (i) it is numerically more involved to decide whether an eigen-
value has a geometric multiplicity that is larger than one; (ii) the occurrence 
of such cases requires a more detailed inspection of how many different 
n-dimensional subspaces can be generated; and (iii) generically, the alge-
braic multiplicity of the eigenvalues is one. If s ≥n and there is at least 
one eigenvalue that has an algebraic multiplicity larger than one, then the 
algorithm terminates and the user is informed about the possibility that in 
the simulation an infinite number of equilibria might occur. It is then up to 
the user either to choose some parameters that differ a little bit from the 
previous choice (yielding probably a simulation that produces no difficul-
ties), or to take a serious look at the eigenstructure of matrix M and draw 
own conclusions. Therefore the algorithm proceeds as follows: 
A4.1: If at least one eigenvalue has an algebraic multiplicity larger than 
one then the game may have an infinite number of equilibria if s &gt;n. 
If s =n there probably exists a unique equilibrium, but this has to 
be verified using the generalised eigenspace(s). For both cases: go 
to Step A6. Otherwise proceed with Step A4.2. 
A4.2: All stable eigenvalues have an algebraic multiplicity of one. 
A4.2.1: Case s =n. Let λ s denote the set of all stable eigenvalues 
andṼ s denote the matrix which columns consist of the 
eigenvectors corresponding with these stable eigenvalues. 
A4.2.1.1: If λ s contains no complex eigenvalues then the 
image ofṼ s represents then-dimensional sta-
ble invariant subspace of M. Go to Step A5. 
A4.2.1.2: If λ s contains complex eigenvalues then replace 
every pair of conjugate complex eigenvectors 
x + iy and x − iy inṼ s by the real part of 
this eigenvector, x, and the imaginary part, y, 
respectively (see Example 6 below for further 
details). The image of this modified real matrix 
represents then then -dimensional stable invari-
ant subspace of M. Go to Step A5. 
A4.2.2: If s &gt;n and: 
A4.2.2.1: If there are no complex eigenvalues then: 
• Calculate the set Cn λ s of all </p>

<p>s! </p>

<p>(s−n)!n!n -element 
combinations from s stable eigenvalues; 
• For every combination λ s 
i ∈ Cn λ s : (i) letṼ s 
i be 
the matrix which columns consist of eigenvec-
tors corresponding with eigenvalues from the 
set λ s 
i ; (ii) go to Step A5. 
A4.2.2.2: If there are complex eigenvalues then: 
• Calculate the set Cn λ s of all </p>

<p>s! </p>

<p>(s−n)!n!n -element 
combinations from s stable eigenvalues that </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>have the property where if λ s 
i contains a com-
plex eigenvalue it contains the complex conju-
gate of this eigenvalue too. 
• For every such combination λ s 
i ∈ Cn λ s : (i) let 
V s 
i be the matrix constructed in a similar way 
as in item A4.2.1.2; (ii) go to Step A5. 
Step A5: For every matrix of eigenvectorsṼ s 
i calculate the corresponding M-invari-
ant graph subspace P. To that end proceed as follows: 
A5.1: Let X 1 , X 2 and X 3 be such that </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ 
X 1 
X 2 
X 3 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ =Ṽ </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>i . </p>

<p>Verify whether matrix X 1 is invertible. If not then ImṼ s 
i is not a graph 
subspace and there is no equilibrium corresponding with this set of 
eigenvalues. Choose another matrixṼ s 
i from the set of potential can-
didates and return to the beginning of the current step (Step A5.1). 
If there are no other candidates left, go to Step 6. 
 *  DenoteP 1 := X 2 X </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 andP 2 := X 3 X </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 . 
 *  Then: </p>

<p>u  *  
1 (t) 
u  *  
2 (t) </p>

<p>:= −G 
−1 (Z + B 
TP )x 
 *  (t), </p>

<p>where withP T := P T </p>

<p>1P </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 is the open-loop Nash equilibrium 
strategy. Here x  *  (t) is the solution of the differential equatioṅ 
x(t) = (A − BG −1 (Z + B TP ))x(t), x(0) = x 0 . 
 *  The spectrum of the corresponding closed-loop matrix A cl equals 
λ s 
i . 
 *  Players' losses can be computed from J i = p T 
0L i p 0 whereL i 
solves the following Lyapunov equation: </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C LL i +L i A C L + </p>

<p>1 
2 
I, F 
T M i 
I 
F 
= 0. 
(29) </p>

<p>Step A6: End of algorithm. </p>

<p>Step A2 in the above algorithm verifies whether the algebraic Riccati equations 
(20) have a stabilizing solution. Of course one can use here <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> to verify this. 
Concerning the numerical stability of Algorithm 5 we notice that various sugges-
tions have been made in the literature to calculate solutions of Riccati equations in 
a numerically reliable way (see e.g. Laub (1979, 1991), Paige and van Loan (1981), 
van Dooren (1981), Mehrmann (1991) and Abou-Kandil and Bertrand (1986) for a 
more general survey on various types of Riccati equations). These methods can also be </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>used to improve the numerical stability of Algorithm 5. In particular, if one considers 
the implementation of large scale models one should consult this literature. 
As already indicated one can also try to solve the (set of coupled) algebraic Riccati 
equations (20) iteratively. In particular, for large scale systems one might hope that 
such algorithms will be more efficient. For that reason various iteration schemes have 
been suggested in literature (see e.g. Abou-Kandil and Bertrand 1986 or Engwerda 
2007). However, since Eq. 20 may admit several solutions, convergence of any game 
is quite difficult to obtain under general conditions (see Azevedo-Perdicoúlis and Jank 
(2005), for a result on positive solutions). An important problem with these algorithms 
is related to the a priori verification of the system's strong stabilizability. If one does 
not want to do it there is an open question how to proceed in case the algorithm 
terminates at a non-stabilizing solution. </p>

<p>4 <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> </p>

<p>Next we proceed with an outline of the numerical toolbox. The software verifies the 
existence of and, provided that a finite number of equilibria exists, calculates the 
outcome of the N -player extension of the game (1-3). The scheme presenting all 
the components of the toolbox software is displayed in Fig. 1. The main file, called 
<rs type="software">LQDGsolver.exe</rs>, solves the LQDG which is to be defined in the input. The input file 
can be created by the user using an intuitive input interface provided (file <rs type="software">TBXinput-
GUI.exe</rs>). Alternatively, more proficient users might choose to create the input file 
directly (in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> or text formats). <rs type="software">LQDGsolver</rs> produces the following output 
for every coalition structure considered: </p>

<p>• number of equilibria, intermediate matrices constructed during the solution process 
(H 1 , H 2 , H 3 and M) and eigenvalues; 
• output actions; 
• closed-loop matrices A cl ; 
• solution of Lyapunov equationsL i for every player; and 
• loss J i for every player. </p>

<p>The above output is saved in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> and text formats in a directory that corre-
sponds to the chosen name of the project. The following output files are created: </p>

<p>• PROJECT_NAME_model.txt: text file containing the structural and reduced form 
of the dynamic system; 
• inputPROJECT_NAME.m: binary <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> file containing (processed) input to 
the project; 
• PROJECT_NAME_validation.txt: text file containing all the information about the 
various stages of model validation; 
• PROJECT_NAME_output.txt: text file containing all the output produced; and 
• outputPROJECT_NAME.m: binary <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> file containing all the project's 
output. </p>

<p>The plotting tool is provided that uses the above output to draw the dynamics of 
every variable in the model for a chosen coalition structure and equilibrium. Less 
advanced users can use a simple output interface (file <rs type="software">TBXoutputGUI.exe</rs>) that allows </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>Fig. 1 Scheme of the <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> software </p>

<p>both to edit the toolbox output and to plot the graphs required. Conversely, more 
advanced users can directly analyse output of all numerical simulations and create 
graphs. 
The input for the toolbox is the following model: </p>

<p>y(t) = P 1ṗ (t) + P 2 p(t) + P 3 y(t) + </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>P 4i v i (t) + P 5 , 
(30) </p>

<p>p(t) = P 6ṗ (t) + P 7 p(t) + P 8 y(t) + </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>P 9i v i (t) + P 10 , p(0) = p 0 , (31) </p>

<p>where p is the n-dimensional state of the system, v i is the m i -dimensional (control) 
vector player i (where i = 1, . . . , |N |) can manipulate (with 
m i =: m), y is the 
b-dimensional vector of endogenous variables and p 0 is the initial state of the sys-
tem. Defining z(t) := [ p(t)ṗ(t) y(t) v(t) c] 
T , the general form of the performance 
criterion that player i likes to minimise is: </p>

<p>J i = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>z 
T (t) i z(t) e 
−θ(t−t 0 ) dt, 
(32) </p>

<p>where: </p>

<p>i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,1),i 
φ (1,2),i 
. . . φ (1,2n+b+m+1),i 
φ (2,1),i 
φ (2,2),i 
. . . φ (2,2n+b+m+1),i 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b+m+1,1,i) φ (2n+b+m+1,2),i . . . φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+m+1),i </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ . </p>

<p>Matrix i can be factorised as follows: </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>p 2 ,i 
pṗ,i 
py,i 
pv,i 
pc,i </p>

<p>ṗ p,i 
ṗ 2 ,i 
ṗy,i 
ṗv,i 
ṗc,i </p>

<p>yp,i 
yṗ,i 
y 2 ,i 
yv,i 
yc,i </p>

<p>vp,i 
vṗ,i 
vy,i 
v 2 ,i 
vc,i </p>

<p>cp,i 
cṗ,i 
cy,i 
cv,i 
c 2 ,i </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ 
. </p>

<p>with all submatrices .,i defined in Appendix B. Furthermore, in Appendix C it is 
shown how, using the appropriate notation, it is possible to define any linear qua-
dratic loss function containing the variables from vector z(t) in the input file (if 
the user chooses to create this file by himself not using the provided interface). Of 
course, the user is supposed to define only those coefficients φ (i.e., elements of 
matrix˜ i ) that are different from zero. The cost criterion (32) can be rewritten as 
follows: </p>

<p>J i := 
1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎨ </p>

<p>⎩ 
p(t) c v(t) </p>

<p>T 
i </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>p(t) 
c 
v(t) </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎬ </p>

<p>⎭ 
e 
−θ(t−t 0 ) dt </p>

<p>:= 
1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎨ </p>

<p>⎩ 
p(t) c v(t) M i </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>p(t) 
c 
v(t) </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎬ </p>

<p>⎭ 
e 
−θ(t−t 0 ) dt, </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>:= </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>I n×n 0 n×1 0 n×m n×(n+m+1) 
Â 1Ê1B 
ĈÊ 2D 
0 m×n 0 m×1 I m×m m×(n+m+1) 
0 1×n 1 0 1×m 1×(n+m+1) </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>(33) </p>

<p>and M i := T i . 
The toolbox also offers the possibility to analyze equilibria for different coa-
lition structures which are formally defined as divisions of all the players in the 
game into exhaustive and disjoint coalitions. That is, if, for instance, five players 
participate in the game and players 1, 3, 4 and players 2, 5 decide to cooper-
ate, then the toolbox offers the possibility to calculate the open-loop Nash equi-
librium for the resulting two-player game. Obviously the outcome depends on the 
relative weight of every players' performance criterion within the coalition. There-
fore, the user is asked to specify both the coalition structure and these relative 
weights. 
The number of coalitions structures that can be created from even a small number 
of players is a non-trivial issue. More in detail, let denote the set of all possible 
coalition structures. The number of all possible coalition structures is a function of 
the number of players N and equals the so-called Bell number B |N | . The Bell number 
is the number of ways a set of |N | elements can be partitioned into non-empty subsets. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>The following Dobinsky's formula is one way to compute Bell numbers (Comtet 
1974): B |N | = </p>

<p>1 
e </p>

<p>∞ 
j=0 </p>

<p>j |N | </p>

<p>j! . 7 
To simplify the presentation of coalition structures we will use the following short-
hand notation: [C 1 |C 2 | . . . |C m ] where C 1≤k≤m is represented by the sequence of 
players that belong to this coalition. For example: [123|4|56] stands for a coalition 
structure where players 1, 2, 3 and players 5, 6 cooperate, respectively and player 4 
remains single. </p>

<p>Example 6 Let N = {1, 2, 3, 4}. Listing all the possible partitions of the set N into 
coalitions, we obtain: [1234], [123|4], [124|3], [134|2], [1|234], [12|3|4], [13|2|4], 
[14|2|3], [23|1|4], [24|1|3], [1|2|34], [12|34], [13|24], [14|23], [1|2|3|4]. Indeed, 
using simple recursive software to compute Dobinsky's formula we obtain: B 4 = 15. 
The number of possible partitions increases exponentially when n increases linearly. 
For |N | = 1, 2, . . . , 15, we have the following numbers of coalitions according to 
Dobinski's formula: B 1 =1, B 2 = 2, B 3 = 5, B 4 = 15, B 5 = 52; B 6 =203, B 7 =877, 
B 8 =4140;B 9 =21147,B 10 =115975,B 11 =678570, B 12 =4213597, B 13 =27644437; 
B 14 = 190899322, and B 15 = 1382958545. </p>

<p>It is clear that an examination of all possible coalition structures is not always inter-
esting for the user. Usually, the researcher should choose and restrict her attention to a 
subset of coalition structures. In the sequel we will use the notation F for the full set 
of feasible coalition structures and R for a reduced set of relevant feasible coalition 
structures. 
We will now briefly discuss the various steps the user is confronted with while 
using the toolbox. </p>

<p>Step T1: <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> Initialisation To define the LQDG problem the user is sup-
posed to provide a number of compulsory components of the model. As it has been 
mentioned before, it is the most convenient to use the interface provided in order to 
create the project. The main window of the user interface is shown in Fig. 2. More 
proficient users also may create the input file directly in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> or text formats. 
Compulsory components of the LQDG problem include: 
• the name of the new project; 
• number of players, number of state and output variables, whether the model include 
constant or not; 
• the number of control instruments per player; 
• the nonzero P i and P i j matrices from the structural form model (30-31); 
• the parameters from the performance criterion (32); 
• the initial condition p 0 ; and 
• the coalition structures to be considered. 8 
• If the model includes constants, i.e., at least one element of matrices P 5 and P 10 
is non-zero, then it is mandatory to specify a strictly positive discount rate. </p>

<p>7 See Chapter 5 of Plasmans et al. (2006) for more details on this issue. </p>

<p>8 For less than 6 players <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> has predefined sets of all coalition structures so that the user does 
not have to define them himself. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Main window of the User Input Interface </p>

<p><rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> offers an opportunity to control and verify every important 
intermediate step of the solution process as well as the results obtained. The list of all 
the available options can be edited in the user interface. </p>

<p>Step T2: Model Validation by <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> Based on the input that is provided in 
Step A1, the toolbox verifies various regularity conditions: </p>

<p>1. The invertibility of the matrices I − P 3 and I − P 7 (I − P 3 ) −1 P 1 − P 5 ; 
2. Positive definiteness of the matrices R ii ; 
3. Invertibility of G; and stabilizability of (A, B i ); and 
4. The final validation step that is performed checks whether the algebraic Riccati 
equations (20) have a stabilizing solution. </p>

<p>If conditions 1 or 2 fail the toolbox terminates. If conditions 3 and 4 fail then it 
means that no equilibrium can be found for the particular coalition structure and the 
toolbox considers the next coalition structure in the queue. </p>

<p>Step T3: Calculation of Equilibria In this phase, open-loop Nash equilibria as out-
lined in Theorem 3 are calculated for every specified coalition structure (if such equi-
libria exists). </p>

<p>5 Examples </p>

<p>In this section we illustrate the various steps of the algorithm in three simple exam-
ples. Firstly, we analyze a dynamic duopoly game with sticky prices as considered by 
Fershtman and Kamien (1987); secondly, we present the solution of the problem used 
in Example 7.10 by Engwerda (2005), where a multiple finite number of equilibria </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>emerges; thirdly, we present the solution of the problem used in Example 7.12 by 
Engwerda (2005) characterised by complex eigenvalues. </p>

<p>5.1 A Game on Dynamic Duopolistic Competition from Fershtman and Kamien 
(1987) </p>

<p>The problem we address here is to find the open-loop Nash equilibria of the game 
defined by the revenue functions: </p>

<p>J i (v 1 , v 2 ) = </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt p(t)v i (t) − c v v i (t) − 
1 
2 
v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i (t) dt, 
(34) </p>

<p>subject to the dynamic constraint: </p>

<p>p(t) = s{a − (v 1 (t) + v 2 (t)) − p(t)}, p(0) = p 0 . 
(35) </p>

<p>Recall that, in this model, θ &gt; 0 denotes the discount rate of future profits and 
s ∈ (0, ∞) is the adjustment speed parameter of the market price, p(t), towards the 
price dictated by the demand function. That is, for larger values of s the market price 
adjusts more quickly along the demand function. The cost functions of the compa-
nies are assumed to be C(v i ) := c v v i + </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 v 2 
i , where c v ∈ (0, a) is a fixed parameter. 
Furthermore, the inverse demand function is assumed to be given byp = a −(v 1 +v 2 ). 
To determine the open-loop equilibrium actions for this game (34-35) we proceed 
along the steps outlined in Sect. 3. To that end we first notice that the maximisation 
of (34) can be rewritten as the minimisation of −J i . </p>

<p>Step T1: <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> Initialisation The above maximisation problems can be 
rewritten in terms of (32) as: </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 1 </p>

<p>J 1 (v 1 , v 2 ) = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>−θt </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ 
z 
T (t) </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0 0 −2 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 1 0 2c v 
0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>z(t) </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ 
dt and </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 2 </p>

<p>J 2 (v 1 , v 2 ) = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>−θt </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ 
z 
T (t) </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0 0 0 −2 0 
0 0 0 0 
0 
0 0 0 0 
0 
0 0 0 1 2c v 
0 0 0 0 
0 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>z(t) </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎪ ⎭ 
dt, </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>subject to the dynamics (35), where z T (t) := [ p(t)ṗ(t) v 1 (t) v 2 (t)c]. 
The model fits into our standard model (30-31) if we specify the various parameters 
in the input file of the toolbox as follows: </p>

<p>P 1 = P 2 = P 3 = P 4i = P 5 = P 6 = P 8 = 0, P 7 = −s, P 9i = −s and P 10 = c. </p>

<p>Notice that in this example n = m 1 = m 2 = 1 (and therefore m = 2) and b = 0. In 
the performance specification all parameters are zero for both players except the next 
ones. For player 1 we have φ (1,3),1 = −2, φ (3,3),1 = 1, and φ (3,5),1 = 2c v , whereas 
for player 2 φ (1,4),2 = −2, φ (4,4),2 = 1 and φ (4,5),2 = 2c v . 
There are two players in the game. Hence B 2 = 2 and F = {[1|2], [12]}. As 
already mentioned before, the user can either choose to compute the Nash equilibria 
for all coalition structures (if such equilibria exist) or only for some elements of F 
by creating own set of feasible coalition structures R . We choose in this example to 
calculate analytically the equilibrium for non-cooperative CS [1|2]. </p>

<p>Step T2: Model Validation by <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> With this input the toolbox next cal-
culates the standard form (17-18) by considering the new variables: </p>

<p>x 1 (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt p(t), x 2 (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt and u i (t) := e </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θt v i (t), i = 1, 2. (36) </p>

<p>With these variables the problem (34-35) can be rewritten as finding the open-loop 
Nash equilibrium of </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>u i (.) </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>[x 1 (t) x 2 (t) u 1 (t) u 2 (t)]M i </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>x 1 (t) 
x 2 (t) 
u 1 (t) 
u 2 (t) </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ dt, 
(37) </p>

<p>subject to the dynamicṡ </p>

<p>x(t) = 
−s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ as 
0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>x(t) + 
−s 
0 
u 1 (t) + 
−s 
0 
u 2 (t). 
(38) </p>

<p>where M i = T i as in (33) with i defined by the user in Step T1. 9 
Following the notation in Sect. 2 the toolbox generates the following matrices: </p>

<p>A = 
−s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ as 
0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>, B i = 
−s 
0 
, Q i = 
0 0 
0 0 
, R ii = 1, R i j = 0 (i = j), </p>

<p>V 1 = W 2 = 
−1 
c v 
, W 1 = V 2 = 
0 
0 
, and N i = 0. </p>

<p>9 Note that y(t) is not taken into account in vector z(t) in the cost criteria in Step T1 as y(t) := 0. Toolbox 
automatically extends matrices 1 and 2 by two appropriate zero vectors. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>So, clearly R ii &gt; 0 and (A, B i ) is stabilizable. Furthermore: </p>

<p>G := 
1 0 
0 1 
, B := 
−s −s 
0 
0 
, Z 1 := 
−1 0 
c v 0 
, Z 2 := 
0 −1 
0 c v 
, </p>

<p>Z := 
−1 c v 
−1 c v 
,B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 := </p>

<p>−s 0 
0 0 
,B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 := </p>

<p>0 0 
−s 0 
,B 
T := 
−s 0 0 0 
0 0 −s 0 
. </p>

<p>and from this: </p>

<p>M = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>−3s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ s(a + 2c v ) 
−s 2 
0 
−s 2 
0 
0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
−c v 
2s + </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
0 
0 
−c v 
c 2 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>−s(a + c v ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
0 
1 
−c v 
0 
0 
2 s + </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
−c v 
c 2 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>0 
0 −s(a + c v ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>=: 
Ã 
−S 
−Q −Ã T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Following Sect. 2 the game has, for all p 0 , a unique open-loop Nash equilibrium if 
the following sets of algebraic Riccati equations have a (strongly) stabilizing solution 
P i and K i , (where i = 1, 2, respectively): </p>

<p>1. The set of coupled Riccati differential equations: </p>

<p>0 = −Ã </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 P − PÃ + P BG 
−1B T P −Q. 
(39) </p>

<p>2. The two Riccati equations: </p>

<p>0 = −A 
T K 1 − K 1 A + (K 1 B 1 + V 1 )R 11 B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 K 1 + V </p>

<p>T 
1 </p>

<p>− Q 1 , 
(40) </p>

<p>0 = −A 
T K 2 − K 2 A + (K 2 B 2 + W 2 )R 22 B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 K 2 + W </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 − Q 2 . (41) </p>

<p>To verify whether, e.g., the algebraic Riccati equation (40) has a stabilizing solution 
it is sufficient to check whether the following equation satisfies this property: </p>

<p>A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V </p>

<p>T 
1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>K + K A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V </p>

<p>T 
1 </p>

<p>− K S 1 K + Q 1 − V 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 = 0. 
(42) </p>

<p>It is easily verified that the Hamiltonian matrix associated with this Riccati equation: </p>

<p>A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>−S 1 </p>

<p>−Q 1 + V 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>− A − B 1 R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>11 V T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>−2s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ s(a + c v ) 
−s 2 
0 
0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
0 
1 
−c v 
2s + </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ 
0 
−c v 
c 2 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>−s(a + c v ) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>has a two-dimensional stable graph subspace. Thus, Eq. 40 has a stabilizing solution. 
In a similar way one can verify whether (41) has a strongly stabilizing solution. The 
procedure to verify whether (39) has a strongly stabilizing solution is presented in the 
next step. </p>

<p>Step T3: Calculation of Equilibria Again, following Algorithm 5, the toolbox first 
computes the eigenvalues of matrix M to determine whether (42) has a strongly sta-
bilizing solution. These eigenvalues are − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ, − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 λ 1 , </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ, </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ, </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ + 2s, − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 s 
+ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 λ 1 , where: </p>

<p>λ 1 = 17s 2 + 10sθ + θ 2 . </p>

<p>Clearly, matrix M has 2 stable and 4 unstable eigenvalues. Therefore, the only 
open-loop Nash equilibrium candidate is obtained by considering the eigenspaces 
of M corresponding with the eigenvalues − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ and − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 λ 1 . The eigenspaces 
corresponding with these eigenvalues are: </p>

<p>T 1 = Span{T 1 } where </p>

<p>T 1 = [−(2c v θ + 2c v s + θa + 2sa), −(3θ + 4s), a − c v , 
(a − c v )(as − c v s − c v θ)/θ, a − c v , (a − c v )(as − c v s − c v θ)/θ] 
T , and </p>

<p>T 2 = Span{T 2 } where </p>

<p>T 2 = [−5s − θ − λ 1 , 0, 2, v, 2, v] 
T , </p>

<p>respectively, with v := − </p>

<p>(s+θ−λ 1 )(2sa−3sc v −c v θ−c v λ 1 ) 
4s(2s+θ) </p>

<p>. In particular we see that for the 
values − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ, − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 λ 1 the corresponding eigenspace is a graph subspace (i.e., 
V s 
i = Span{T 1 , T 2 }). 
Since (A, B i ), where i = 1, 2, are stabilizable, R ii &gt; 0, G is invertible, M has 
a 2-dimensional stable graph subspace and 4 unstable eigenvalues, and the algebraic 
Riccati equations (39-40) have a stabilizing solution, then all conditions are satisfied 
for the game to have a unique open-loop Nash equilibrium. The corresponding actions 
are: </p>

<p>u  *  
1 (t) 
u  *  
2 (t) </p>

<p>= − 
−1 c v 
−1 c v 
+ 
−s 0 
−s 0 
P x(t), 
(43) </p>

<p>whereP </p>

<p>1 =P 2 = 
a − c v 
2 </p>

<p>(a−c v )(as−c v s−c v θ) 
θ </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>−(2c v θ + 2c v s + θa + 2sa) −5s − θ − λ 1 
−(3θ + 4s) 
0 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>=: 
f o g o 
h o l o 
, i = 1, 2. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>Using the equilibrium actions: </p>

<p>u </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>i (t) = (1 + s f 0 )x 1 (t) + (sg 0 − c v )x 2 (t), </p>

<p>the resulting closed-loop system is: </p>

<p>x(t) = 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 s − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 λ 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 (s − θ + λ 1 ) </p>

<p>as+(a+2c v )(θ+s) 
3θ+4s </p>

<p>0 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 θ </p>

<p>x(t). </p>

<p>Next, we reformulate this result in terms of our original model parameters. From 
the above differential equation in x, one obtains the next differential equation for the 
equilibrium price path p(t): </p>

<p>p(t) = 
1 
2 
(θ − s − λ 1 ) p(t) − 
as + (a + 2c v )(θ + s) 
3θ + 4s 
. </p>

<p>The equilibrium actions are: </p>

<p>v </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>i (t) = (1 + s f 0 ) p(t) + sg 0 − c v , i = 1, 2. </p>

<p>For the parameters' values: a = 4, s = 0.1, c v = 1.5, θ = 0.05 and initial condition 
p 0 = [3] , the toolbox produces the following numerical values (N e non-cooperative 
and C e cooperative equilibrium between players): </p>

<p>1. The equilibrium actions: </p>

<p>C L 
 *  (N 
e ) = 
0.8042 −1.4385 
0.8042 −1.4385 
and C L 
 *  (C 
e ) = 
0.6559 −1.2898 
0.6559 −1.2898 
; </p>

<p>2. The closed-loop system: </p>

<p>A </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>cl (N 
e ) = 
−0.2858 
0.6877 
0 −0.0250 
and A </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>cl (C 
e ) = 
−0.2562 
0.6580 
0 −0.0250 
; </p>

<p>3. Lyapunov equations' solutions (see Eq. 29 in Step A5 of the algorithm) 10 : </p>

<p>L </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 (N 
e ) = 
−0.8411 
0.5327 
0.5327 −7.8099 
,L </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1 (C 
e ) = 
−0.8603 
0.5255 
0.5255 −8.2266 
; </p>

<p>L </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 (N 
e ) = 
−0.8411 
0.5327 
0.5327 −7.8099 
,L </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>2 (C 
e ) = 
−0.8603 
0.5255 
0.5255 −8.2266 
; </p>

<p>10 These matrices can be used to calculate players' losses for any given initial condition p 0 . </p>



<p>396 </p>

<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Control variables in the duopoly game (non-cooperative equilibrium) </p>

<p>4. The optimal losses of players 11 : J  *  
1 (N e ) = p T 
0L 1 (N e ) p 0 = J  *  
2 (N e ) = p T 
0L 2 (N e ) 
p 0 = − 12.1836; and J  *  
1 (C e ) = p T 
0L 1 (C e ) p 0 = J  *  
2 (C e ) = p T </p>

<p>0L 
 *  </p>

<p>2 (C e ) p 0 = 
− 12.8162. </p>

<p>The toolbox offers a possibility to plot graphs of control, state and output vari-
ables' dynamics. To plot graphs for a particular equilibrium the toolbox command 
plot_graph should be used. 12 Figure 3 shows the dynamics of the control variables 
for both players (i.e., output of both firms) for the assumed parameter values, whereas 
Fig. 4 shows the dynamics of the state variables (i.e., market price as well as a constant, 
which is added to the state variables of the system as outlined in Sect. 2). 
Furthermore, as it has been already mentioned, the toolbox offers an option to 
decompose the loss function of every player into its linear components showing what 
is each element's contribution to the total outcome. It is especially useful in both model 
calibration and analysis. When disaggregate losses option is chosen the toolbox creates 
a dummy player j for every non-zero element φ (a,b),i of matrix i in the loss function 
of player i. Player j s matrix j has φ (a,b), j as the only non-zero entry. Furthermore, 
every dummy player is assigned a control variable added to the first state equation of 
the system with a coefficient 0 so that it does not have any influence on the system. The 
weight of dummy players' control variables in their loss functions can be defined by 
the user using the (advanced) option dummy_control_instrument_multiplier (δ) whose 
default value is 1. 
In the above example, there are 3 non-zero entries in each i matrix, namely, 
φ (1,3),1 , φ (3,3),1 , and φ (3,5),1 in 1 and φ (1,4),2 , φ (4,4),2 and φ (4,5),2 in 2 . 
Consequently, the toolbox creates 6 dummy players j = 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 and 8 with: </p>

<p>11 Note that it is not possible to calculate the analytic solution of the corresponding Lyapunov equations, 
so it is not possible to calculate the analytic formulas for players' losses. 
12 See the toolbox manual for more details. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>Fig. 4 State variable and constant in the duopoly game (non-cooperative equilibrium) </p>

<p>3 = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0 0 −2 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 δ 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>and analogous 4 , 5 , 6 , 7 and 8 . 
Furthermore, the toolbox adds 6 new control variables to the model and solves the 
following game 13 : </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v i </p>

<p>J i (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v i </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt − p(t)v i (t) + c v v i (t) + 
1 
2 
v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i (t) dt, </p>

<p>for i = 1, 2 and </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 3 </p>

<p>J 3 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 3 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt {− p(t)v 1 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 (t)}dt, </p>

<p>13 Note that dummy players which corresponds to elements that involve a constant are always positioned 
last. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 4 </p>

<p>J 3 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 4 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt 1 
2 
v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 (t) dt, </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 5 </p>

<p>J 5 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 5 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt {− p(t)v 2 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 (t)}dt, </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 6 </p>

<p>J 6 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 6 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt 1 
2 
v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>6 (t) dt, </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 7 </p>

<p>J 7 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 7 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt {c v v 1 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>7 (t)}dt, </p>

<p>− min </p>

<p>v 8 </p>

<p>J 8 (v 1 , v 2 , . . . , v 8 ) = − min </p>

<p>v 8 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>e 
−θt {c v v 2 (t) + v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>8 (t)}dt, </p>

<p>subject to dynamics: </p>

<p>p(t) = s{a − (v 1 (t) + v 2 (t)) − p(t)} + 0v 3 + · · · + 0v 8 , p(0) = p 0 . </p>

<p>Since dummy players have no influence on the system then their optimal strat-
egy is to never use the control instrument as it cannot improve their loss. Conse-
quently, all the obtained results will be the same up to additional dimensions in 
losses corresponding to dummy players. These losses can be always interpreted 
in terms of the losses of real players. In our example, since v 2 
3 (t) and v 2 
5 (t) are 
always zero, J 3 and J 5 can be interpreted as the loss from </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 e −θt {− p(t)v 1 (t)}dt 
and </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 e −θt {− p(t)v 2 (t)}dt obtained by players 1 and 2, respectively. Thus, J  *  </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>and J  *  
5 are revenues from sales, whereas J  *  
4 + J  *  
7 and J  *  
6 + J  *  
8 are costs func-
tions of both oligopolistic firms. For the parametrisation assumed above the tool-
box produces the following disaggregation of optimal losses in both regimes: </p>

<p>N e 
C e 
Interpretation 
J  *  </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>−39.4144 
−34.2076 
Revenue (player 1) 
J  *  </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5.3650 
3.5454 
Cost (player 1) 
J  *  </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>−39.4144 
−34.2076 
Revenue (player 2) 
J  *  </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5.3650 
3.5454 
Cost (player 2) 
J  *  </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>21.8658 
17.8460 
Cost (player 1) 
J  *  </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>21.8658 
17.8460 
Cost (player 2) </p>

<p>which has the following interpretation: while non-cooperating the first/second com-
pany has a revenue with an equilibrium of −J  *  
3/5 (N e ) = 39.4144 while it incurs a 
cost of J  *  
4/6 (N e ) + J  *  
7/8 (N e ) = 5.3650 + 21.8658 = 27.2308. Total profit for each 
company is −J  *  
3/5 (N e ) − J  *  
4/6 (N e ) − J  *  
7/8 (N e ) = 12.1836 = J  *  
1/2 (N e ). In contrast, 
when companies cooperate, their production is much smaller J  *  
4/6 (C e ) &lt;&lt; J  *  
4/6 (N e ) </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>but due to a degree of monopolistic power they are able to obtain higher profits: 
J  *  
1/2 (C e ) = 12.8162. </p>

<p>5.2 Example 7.10 of Engwerda (2005) With Multiple Equilibria </p>

<p>A two-player Example 7.10 from Engwerda (2005) can be rewritten using the notation 
outlined in Sect. 2 as follows: </p>

<p>A = 
−0.1 0 
0 
−2 
, B 1 = 
1 0 
0 1 
, B 2 = 
1 
0 
, Q 1 = 
1 0 
0 0.1 
, Q 2 = 
1 1 
1 2 
, </p>

<p>R 1 = 
2 −1 
−1 1 
, R 2 = 1, R i j = 0 (i = j), V 1 = V 2 = W 1 = W 2 = 
0 
0 
and N i = 0. </p>

<p>Step T1: <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> Initialisation We can rewrite the above example to fit our 
standard model (30-31) by specifying: </p>

<p>P 1 = P 2 = P 3 = P 4i = P 5 = P 6 = P 8 = 0, P 7 = A, P 9i = B i and P 10 = 
0 
0 
. </p>

<p>Notice that in this example n = m 1 = 2, m 2 = 1 (and therefore m = 3) and b = 0. In 
the performance specification all parameters are zero for both players, except for 
φ (1,1),1 = 1; φ (2,2),1 = 0.1; φ (5,5),1 = 2; φ (5,6),1 = −1; φ (6,5),1 = −1; and φ (6,6),1 = 1, 
for the first player, and: φ (1,1),2 = 1; φ (2,1),2 = 1; φ (1,2),2 = 1; φ (2,2),2 = 2; and 
φ (7,7),2 = 1 for the second player. In this example, we specify the discount rate to 
be 0. </p>

<p>Step T2: Model Validation by <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> With this input the toolbox next calcu-
lates the standard form (17-18). Clearly, (i) R ii &gt; 0; (ii) (A, B i ) is stabilizable; and 
(iii) G is invertible (see Appendix A for a definition of G). </p>

<p>Step T3: Calculation of Equilibria Again, we will follow Algorithm 5 for the non-
cooperative case where matrix M is: </p>

<p>M = − </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0.1 0 
1 
1 
1 
0 
0 
2 
1 
2 
0 
0 
1 
0 −0.1 0 
0 
0 
0 0.1 
0 
−2 
0 
0 
1 
1 
0 
0 −0.1 0 
1 
2 
0 
0 
0 
−2 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In Step A4 of the algorithm, the toolbox determines the spectrum of M. Numeri-
cal calculations show that M = T J T −1 , where J is a diagonal matrix with entries 
λ = {2; −2.2073; −1.0584; 2.0637; −0.1648; 1.4668} and </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>T = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0 0.2724 −0.6261 −0.0303 −0.1714 
0.3326 
0 0.7391 
0.5368 −0.0167 
0.3358 
0.0633 
0 0.1181 −0.5405 
0.0154 −0.6473 −0.2433 
0 0.0176 
0.0176 
0.0262 
0.0155 
0.0119 
0 0.4384 −0.0771 
0.0239 
0.6207 −0.2897 
1 0.4161 
0.1463 
0.9987 
0.2311 
0.8614 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Let us factorise matrix T into [T 1 T 2 T 3 T 4 T 5 T 6 ]. Matrix M has six different eigen-
values, where three of them are negative, i.e., λ s = {−2.2073; −1.0584; −0.1648}. 
They correspond to eigenvectors T 2 , T 3 and T 5 . Since no eigenvalue has an 
algebraic multiplicity higher than one and there are no complex eigenvalues, 
the toolbox determines in Step A4.2.2.1 of the algorithm that there are at most 
3 
2 
= 3 different equilibrium strategies that permit a feedback synthesis, i.e., </p>

<p>Cn λ s = {(−2.2073, −1.0584), (−2.2073, −0.1648), (−1.0584, −0.1648)} orṼ s ∈ 
{(T 2 , T 3 ), (T 2 , T 5 ), (T 3 , T 5 )}. For all three combinations of two eigenvectorsṼ s the 
toolbox executes Step A5. 
Consider P 1 := Im[T 2 T 3 ]. The first 2 × 2 block of this matrix equals 
0.2724 −0.6261 
0.7391 0.5368 
. This matrix is invertible. P 1 is an element of P pos and </p>

<p>σ (M| P 1 ) = {−2.2073, −1.0584}. In a similar way it can be verified that P 2 := 
Im[T 2 T 5 ] and P 3 := Im[T 3 T 5 ] are also appropriate graph subspaces. On the whole, 
all three M-invariant subspaces satisfy all conditions. 
As an example, we will calculate the equilibrium strategy that permits a feedback 
synthesis resulting from P 3 . To that end we factorise P 3 as follows: </p>

<p>P 3 = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>−0.6261 −0.1714 
0.5368 
0.3358 
−0.5405 −0.6473 
0.0176 
0.0155 
−0.0771 0.6207 
0.1463 
0.2311 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>=: </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>X 
Y 
Z </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ , </p>

<p>where X, Y and Z are 2 × 2 matrices. We obtain then: </p>

<p>P 1 := Y X 
−1 = 
−0.5405 −0.6473 
0.0176 
0.0155 </p>

<p>−0.6261 −0.1714 
0.5368 
0.3358 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>P 2 := Z X 
−1 = 
−0.0771 0.6207 
0.1463 0.2311 </p>

<p>−0.6261 −0.1714 
0.5368 
0.3358 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>The corresponding open-loop Nash strategy is u  *  
i (t) := −R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>i B T 
iP i e A cl t x 0 . Here the 
closed-loop matrix A cl := A − S 1P1 − S 2P2 is 
−1.7538 −0.8112 
1.3622 0.5305 
. It is easily </p>

<p>verified that the spectrum of this matrix A cl indeed equals {−1.0584, −0.1648}. The 
cost for both players in this equilibrium is obtained by solving the corresponding </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>Lyapunov equation (29). This gives a cost: </p>

<p>J 1 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>3 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>10.2694 12.6875 
12.6875 16.1956 
x 0 and J 2 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>3 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>15.7425 18.3929 
18.3929 21.7370 
x 0 . </p>

<p>The other two non-cooperative equilibria are: </p>

<p>J 1 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>0.3207 −0.0476 
−0.0476 
0.0221 
x 0 and J 2 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>0.1708 0.1065 
0.1065 0.2636 
x 0 </p>

<p>as well as </p>

<p>J 1 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>2 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>7.9338 −2.7856 
−2.7856 
1.0062 
x 0 and J 2 (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>2 ) = x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>8.1006 −3.2333 
−3.2333 
1.6482 
x 0 . </p>

<p>Thus, there are altogether 3 non-cooperative equilibria N e 
1 , N e 
2 and N e 
3 . Assum-
ing x 0 = 
1 
1 
we obtain the following optimal losses of players in this regime: </p>

<p>N e </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N e </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>N e </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>J 1 
0.2476 
3.3688 
51.8401 
J 2 
0.6473 
3.2821 
74.2653 </p>

<p>The key question is whether it is possible to discriminate between multiple equi-
libria of a particular coalition structure. It is especially important in more complex 
games, where a practically intractable number of equilibria can be obtained. One of 
the widely accepted solution concepts to discriminate between various equilibria of 
a game is Pareto-domination. An equilibrium is said to be Pareto-dominated if it is 
possible to find another equilibrium in which all the players in the game will not be 
worse off and at least one of them will be better off. If option discriminate between 
equilibria using Pareto domination is chosen, the toolbox is going to report a list of 
Pareto-undominated equilibria. In the above case, it is clear that in the non-cooperative 
regime equilibrium N e 
1 dominates the other two as J 1 (N e 
1 ) &lt; J 1 (N e 
2 ) &lt; J 1 (N e 
3 ) and 
at the same time J 2 (N e 
1 ) &lt; J 2 (N e 
2 ) &lt; J 2 (N e 
3 ). Consequently, apart from all the equi-
libria, the toolbox is going to report also a set of Pareto-undominated equilibria which 
consists of N e 
1 . 
The particular advantage of the Pareto concept is based on the fact that it is in the 
interest of all the players to play only Pareto -undominated equilibria. However, the 
downside is that there can be a whole spectrum of them. Because of this, we propose 
another two ways to discriminate between multiple equilibria. The first method is based 
on the concept of so called social optimum, i.e., such an equilibrium is chosen that mini-
mises the sum of all the players' losses, or, in our two-player game: J 1 (N e 
1 ) + J 2 (N e 
1 ). 
In our example J 1 (N e 
1 ) + J 2 (N e 
1 ) &lt; J 1 (N e 
2 ) + J 2 (N e 
2 ) &lt; J 1 (N e 
3 ) + J 2 (N e 
3 ) so the 
first equilibrium is chosen when this option is on. The other method we propose to 
discriminate between multiple equilibria refers to the adjustment speed of the equilib-
rium closed-loop system towards its long-term equilibrium, measured by the smallest </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>absolute value of the eigenvalues of the A cl matrix that are located in the left half of 
the complex plane. In our example: </p>

<p>A cl (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1 ) = </p>

<p>−1.7538 −0.8112 
1.3622 
0.5305 
, λ 
s (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>1 ) = {−1.0584, −2.2073}; </p>

<p>A cl (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>2 ) = </p>

<p>−1.0212 −0.4372 
−2.3234 −1.3510 
, λ 
s (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>2 ) = {−0.1648, −2.2073}; and </p>

<p>A cl (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>3 ) = </p>

<p>−1.7538 −0.8112 
1.3622 
0.5305 
, λ 
s (N </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>3 ) = {−1.0584, −0.1648}. </p>

<p>Consequently, the toolbox will choose the equilibrium such that their graph sub-
space consists of eigenvector corresponding to −1.0584, −2.2073, i.e., N e 
1 . </p>

<p>5.3 Example 7.12 of Engwerda (2005) With Complex Eigenvalues </p>

<p>A two-player Example 7.12 from Engwerda (2005) can be rewritten in terms of nota-
tion outlined in Sect. 2 as follows: </p>

<p>A = 
− </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>0 
0 − </p>

<p>1 
4 </p>

<p>, B 1 = B 2 = 
1 0 
0 1 
, Q 1 = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1 1 
1 3 
, Q 2 = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>2 − </p>

<p>7 
9 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>7 
9 </p>

<p>1 
, </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>1 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>7 
90 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>90 1 </p>

<p>, R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>2 = </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>1 
10 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 
10 </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>V 1 = V 2 = W 1 = W 2 = 
0 
0 
, and N i = 0. </p>

<p>Step T1: <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> Initialisation We can rewrite the above example to fit our 
standard model (30-31) by specifying: </p>

<p>P 1 = P 2 = P 3 = P 4i = P 5 = P 6 = P 8 = 0, P 7 = A, P 9i = B i and P 10 = 
0 
0 
. </p>

<p>Notice that in this example n = m 1 = m 2 = 2 (and therefore m = 4) and b = 0. 
In the performance specification, all parameters are zero for both players, except for 
φ (1,1),1 = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , φ (1,2),1 = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , φ (2,1),1 = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , φ (2,2),1 = </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 , φ (5,5),1 = r 11 , φ (5,6),1 = 
r 12 , φ (6,5),1 = r 21 , φ (6,6),1 = r 22 , φ (1,1),2 = 1, φ (1,2),2 = − </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>18 , φ (2,1),2 = 
− </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>18 , φ (2,2),2 = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 , φ (7,7),2 = s 11 , φ (7,8),2 = s 12 , φ (8,7),2 = s 21 , and φ (8,8),2 = s 22 , 
where: </p>

<p>r 11 r 12 
r 21 r 22 
= 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>7 
90 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>7 
90 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>and 
s 11 s 12 
s 21 s 22 
= 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>1 
10 </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>1 
10 </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>for the first and second players, respectively. Also in this example, we specify the 
discount rate to be 0. </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>Step T2: Model Validation by <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> With this input, the toolbox next cal-
culates the standard form (17-18) and checks that both Q i and R i are positive definite, 
(A, B i ) are stabilizable and G is invertible. </p>

<p>Step T3: Calculation of Equilibria Again, we will follow Algorithm 5 for the non-
cooperative case. We have that: </p>

<p>M = − </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0.5000 
0.0000 
0.5000 −0.0389 
0.5000 −0.0500 
0.0000 
0.2500 −0.0389 
0.5000 −0.0500 
0.3750 
0.5000 
0.5000 −0.5000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.5000 
1.5000 
0.0000 −0.2500 
0.0000 
0.0000 
1.0000 −0.3889 
0.0000 
0.0000 −0.5000 
0.0000 
−0.3889 
0.5000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 −0.2500 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>In Step A4 of the algorithm the toolbox determines the spectrum of M. Numeri-
cal calculations show that M = T J T −1 , where J is a diagonal matrix with entries 
λ = {−1.0004 + 0.0227i; −1.0004 − 0.0227i; 0.2525; 0.4983; 1; 1} and </p>

<p>T = </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>0.1358 + 0.4406i 
0.1358 − 0.4406i −0.0045 −0.0002 
0.3848 
0.0003 
0.4499 − 0.1379i 
0.4499 + 0.1379i 
0.0005 
0.0026 
0.0134 −0.3767 
0.1966 + 0.0979i 
0.1966 − 0.0979i −0.0080 
0.7063 −0.3982 
0.3764 
0.5940 
0.5940 
0.5979 −0.0156 −0.2833 
0.7531 
−0.0211 + 0.3297i −0.0211 − 0.3297i −0.0189 −0.7077 −0.7593 −0.2935 
0.1341 − 0.1946i 
0.1341 + 0.1946i −0.8013 −0.0056 
0.1906 
0.2513 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Matrix M has two (complex) eigenvalues with a negative real part. Let x be the 
real part of the eigenvector corresponding with the eigenvalue −1.0004 + 0.0227i and 
y the imaginary part of this eigenvector </p>

<p>x 
T := [0.1358, 0.4499, 0.1966, 0.5940, −0.0211, 0.1341] and </p>

<p>y 
T := [0.4406, −0.1379, 0.0979, 0, 0.3279, −0.1964]. </p>

<p>The invariant subspace corresponding with eigenvalues {−1.0004 + 0.0227i; 
−1.0004 − 0.0227i} is S =Im[x y]. According to Sect. 2, the unique equilibrium 
actions are u  *  
i (t) = −R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>i B T 
iP i x(t), where: </p>

<p>P 1 = 
0.1966 0.0979 
0.5940 0 </p>

<p>0.1358 0.4406 
0.4499 −0.1379 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>= 
0.3280 0.3380 
0.3776 1.2063 
and </p>

<p>P 2 = 
−0.0211 0.3297 
0.1341 −0.1964 </p>

<p>0.1358 
0.4406 
0.4499 −0.1379 </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>= 
0.6703 −0.2493 
−0.3183 
0.3942 
. </p>

<p>The with these actions corresponding closed-loop system matrix is then: </p>

<p>A cl := 
−1.0004 0.0222 
−0.0231 −1.003 
. </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>The eigenvalues of this matrix are {−1.0004 + 0.0227i; −1.0004 − 0.0227i}. The 
corresponding equilibrium costs are </p>

<p>J 1 (N 
e ) = x </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0L 1 (N 
e )x 0 = 
1 
2 
x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>0.2990 0.3715 
0.3715 1.1344 
x 0 and </p>

<p>J 2 (N 
e ) = x </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>0L 2 (N 
e )x 0 = 
1 
2 
x </p>

<p>T 
0 </p>

<p>0.6479 −0.2644 
−0.2644 0.2936 
x 0 . </p>

<p>6 Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>In this paper we considered a dynamic linear affine structural form model that is 
affected by different players who all like to minimise their own performance criterion 
that is a quadratic affine function of the variables occurring in the model. The costs 
are assumed to be discounted over time and the considered planning horizon by the 
players is assumed to be infinite. Under the assumption that in the minimisation of 
their performance the players do not cooperate, we presented both necessary and suffi-
cient conditions under which this problem has a unique open-loop Nash equilibrium, a 
multiple but finite number of equilibria and or an infinite number of equilibria. A com-
putational framework was provided for how one can numerically solve the problem. 
The algorithm has been implemented in a form of a numerical toolbox available on 
the internet. Users, starting from the structural model, can calculate for their specific 
application the equilibrium strategies and involved cost (if they exist). The toolbox 
also provides the possibility to calculate for different coalition structures whether the 
corresponding game will have an open-loop Nash solution. For that purpose the user 
has to define which coalition structures they like to analyze and what the relative 
importance is of each player within a certain coalition. We demonstrated both theoret-
ically and numerically in a worked example on dynamic duopolistic competition the 
use of the toolbox. 
<rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> is implemented in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs>. In particular, it uses some standard 
functions of <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> to calculate the eigenstructure of a (|N |n) × (|N |n) matrix, 
where |N | is the number of involved players andn is the state dimension of the model. 
Since no additional efforts are taken to calculate this eigenstructure in a numerically 
efficient way, the practical use of the current toolbox is limited to some extent. This is 
because for either a large number of players and/or a large state dimension, the accu-
racy and efficiency is restricted by that of the implemented <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> functions. So 
for large N and/orn the user should look for an own code to implement the algorithm. 
Another way one might choose to calculate the equilibrium strategies is by using iter-
ative algorithms. In the literature a number of iterative schemes have been suggested 
(see e.g. Engwerda 2007). A disadvantage of these schemes is that on the one hand 
they do not provide an answer to the question whether the game will have a unique 
equilibrium. On the other hand these schemes may converge without providing the 
appropriate equilibrium strategy. If this happens one is stuck with the question how to 
proceed. 
For the corresponding problem with a finite planning horizon, at least from a the-
oretical point, it is clear under which conditions there exists a unique equilibrium </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>(see e.g. Engwerda 2005). From a computational point it is also clear how one can 
calculate this equilibrium. Either one can solve the involved set of nonlinear differen-
tial two-point boundary-value equations directly using standard <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> functions. 
Another possibility is to transform the involved set of Riccati differential equations 
(in the spirit of Reid (1972)) to a set of linear differential equations and then solve 
this set first (see e.g. Tabak 1975; Engwerda 2007). Since the calculations require 
the numerical solution of a set of (nonlinear) differential equations the dimension of 
the games for which one can still calculate the equilibrium actions (using standard 
<rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> functions) without problems is usually smaller than in the infinite horizon 
case. 
In the literature, also different equilibrium concepts have been studied for games 
considered above. Probably the most well-known is the feedback Nash concept. Unfor-
tunately, for this case there are no general conditions known, except for the scalar case, 
i.e.,n = 1 (see e.g. Engwerda 2005) under which the game has a unique feedback 
Nash equilibrium. 
Finally, we would like to mention that for discrete time systems much work has 
been done by <rs corresp="#software-58" type="creator">Neck et al.</rs>. in the development of the numerical software OPTGAME 
for the calculation of Nash equilibria in (non-)linear systems in case the performances 
of players are quadratic (see e.g. Neck et al. 2001). </p>

<p>Acknowledgments Tomasz Michalak acknowledges support from (a) the EPSRC under the project 
ALADDIN (Autonomous Learning Agents for Decentralised Data and Information Systems) project and 
is jointly funded by a BAE Systems and EPSRC strategic partnership; and (b) the FWO (Fonds voor 
Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek Vlaanderen, Belgium). </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncom-
mercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original author(s) and source are credited. </p>

<p>Appendix A: Notation </p>

<p>The following shorthand notation is used: </p>

<p>S i := B i R </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>ii B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>i , G := </p>

<p>[0 I 0] M 1 
[0 0 I ] M 2 </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>0 0 
I 0 
0 I </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ = 
R 11 N 1 
N T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>R 22 
, </p>

<p>where we assume throughout that this matrix G is invertible. Furthermore: </p>

<p>A 2 := 
A 0 
0 A 
, B := [B 1 , B 2 ], B 
T := 
B T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
0 B T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>1 := </p>

<p>B T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 
, B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 := </p>

<p>0 
B T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>Q := 
Q 1 
Q 2 
, Z := 
[0 I 0] M 1 
[0 0 I ] M 2 </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>I 
0 
0 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ = 
V T </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>W T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>Z i := [I 0 0]M i </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>0 0 
I 0 
0 I </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ = [V i , W i ], i = 1, 2, </p>

<p>A := A − BG 
−1 Z , A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 := A </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>2 − </p>

<p>Z 1 
Z 2 
G 
−1 B 
T , </p>

<p>Q i := Q i − Z i G 
−1 Z , Q := 
Q 1 
Q 2 
, S i := BG 
−1 B </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>i , </p>

<p>S := [ S 1 , S 2 ], and M := 
A 
− S 
− Q − A T </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Notice that: </p>

<p>M = H 1 + H 2 G 
−1 H 3 , </p>

<p>where: </p>

<p>H 1 := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>A 
0 
0 
−Q 1 −A T 
0 
−Q 2 
0 
−A T </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ , H 2 := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎣ </p>

<p>−B 
Z 1 
Z 2 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎦ and H 3 := Z ,B T 
1 ,B T 
2 . </p>

<p>Matrices H 1 , H 2 , H 3 and G to construct the M are stored in the <rs type="software">LQDG Toolbox</rs> output 
file. </p>

<p>Appendix B: Cost Function Submatrices </p>

<p>p 2 ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,1),i p 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>φ (1,2),i p 1 p 2 . . . φ (1,n),i p 1 p n 
φ (2,1),i p 2 p 1 φ (2,2),i p 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. . . φ (2,n),i p 2 p n 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n,1),i p n p 1 φ (n,2),i p n p 2 . . . φ (n,n),i p 2 </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>ṗ p,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (n+1,1),iṗ1 p 1 φ (n+1,2),iṗ1 p 2 . . . φ (n+1,n),iṗ1 p n 
φ (n+2,1),iṗ2 p 1 φ (n+2,2),iṗ2 p 2 . . . φ (n+2,n),iṗ2 p n 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n+n,1),iṗn p 1 φ (n+n,2),iṗn p 2 . . . φ (n+n,n),iṗn p n </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>yp,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,1),i y 1 p 1 φ (2n+1,2),i y 1 p 2 . . . φ (2n+1,n),i y 1 p n 
φ (2n+2,1),i y 2 p 1 φ (2n+2,2),i y 2 p 2 . . . φ (2n+2,n),i y 2 p n 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b,1),i y b p 1 φ (2n+b,2),i y b p 2 . . . φ (2n+b,n),i y b p n </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>vp,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,1),i v 1 p 1 φ (2n+b+1,2),i v 1 p 2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,n),i v 1 p n 
φ (2n+b+2,1),i v 2 p 1 φ (2n+b+2,2),i v 2 p 2 . . . φ (2n+b+2,n),i v 2 p n 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b+m,1),i v m p 1 φ (2n+b+m,2),i v m p 2 . . . φ (2n+b+m,n),i v m p n </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>cp,i := φ (2n+b+m+1,1),i cp 1 φ (2n+b+1,2,i) cp 2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,n,i) cp n , </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>pṗ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,n+1),i p 1ṗ1 φ (1,n+2),i p 1ṗ2 . . . φ (1,n+n),i p 1ṗn 
φ (2,n+1),i p 2ṗ1 φ (2,n+2),i p 2ṗ2 . . . φ (2,n+n),i p 2ṗn 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n,n+1),i p nṗ1 φ (n,n+2),i p nṗ2 . . . φ (n,n+n),i p nṗn </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>ṗ 2 ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (n+1,n+1),iṗ </p>

<p>2 
1 </p>

<p>φ (n+1,n+2),iṗ1ṗ2 . . . φ (n+1,n+n),iṗ1ṗn 
φ (n+2,n+1),iṗ2ṗ1 φ (n+2,n+2),iṗ </p>

<p>2 
2 </p>

<p>. . . φ (n+2,n+n),iṗ1ṗn 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n+n,n+1),iṗnṗ1 φ (n+n,n+2),iṗnṗ2 . . . φ (n+n,n+n),iṗ </p>

<p>2 
n </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>yṗ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,1,i) y 1ṗ1 φ (2n+1,2,i) y 1ṗ2 . . . φ (2n+1,n),i y 1ṗn 
φ (2n+2,1,i) y 2ṗ1 φ (2n+2,2,i) y 2ṗ2 . . . φ (2n+2,n),i y 2ṗn 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b,1,i) y bṗ1 φ (2n+b,2,i) y bṗ2 . . . φ (2n+b,n),i y bṗn </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>vṗ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,n+1,i) v 1ṗ1 φ (2n+b+1,n+2,i) v 1ṗ2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,n+n),i v 1ṗn 
φ (2n+b+2,n+1,i) v 2ṗ1 φ (2n+b+2,n+2,i) v 2ṗ2 . . . φ (2n+b+2,n+n),i v 2ṗn 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b+m,n+1,i) v mṗ1 φ (2n+b+m,n+2,i) v mṗ2 . . . φ (2n+b+m,n+n),i v mṗn </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>cṗ,i := φ (2n+b+m+1,n+1),i cṗ 1 φ (2n+b+1,n+2,i) cṗ 2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,n+n,i) cṗ n , </p>

<p>py,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,2n+1),i p 1 y 1 φ (1,2n+2),i p 1 y 2 . . . φ (1,2n+b),i p 1 y b 
φ (2,2n+1),i p 2 y 1 φ (2,2n+2),i p 2 y 2 . . . φ (2,2n+b),i p 2 y b 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n,2n+1),i p n y 1 φ (n,2n+2),i p n y 2 . . . φ (n,2n+b),i p n y b </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>ṗy,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (n+1,2n+1),iṗ1 y 1 φ (n+1,2n+2),iṗ1 y 2 . . . φ (n+1,2n+b),iṗ1 y b 
φ (n+2,2n+1),iṗ2 y 1 φ (n+2,2n+2),iṗ2 y 2 . . . φ (n+2,2n+b),iṗ2 y b 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n+n,2n+1),iṗn y 1 φ (n+n,2n+2),iṗn y 2 . . . φ (n+n,2n+b),iṗn y b </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>y 2 ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,2n+1),i y 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,2n+2),i y 1 y 2 . . . φ (2n+1,2n+b),i y 1 y b 
φ (2n+2,2n+1),i y 2 y 1 φ (2n+2,n+2),i y 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. . . φ (2n+2,2n+b),i y 2 y b 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b,2n+1),i y b y 1 φ (2n+b,2n+2),i y b y 2 . . . φ (2n+b,2n+1),i y 2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>vy,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,2n+1,i) v 1 y 1 φ (2n+b+1,2n+2,i) v 1 y 2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,2n+b),i v 1 y b 
φ (2n+b+2,2n+1,i) v 2 y 1 φ (2n+b+2,2n+2,i) v 2 y 2 . . . φ (2n+b+2,2n+b),i v 2 y b 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b+m,2n+1,i) v m y 1 φ (2n+b+m,2n+2,i) v m y 2 . . . φ (2n+b+m,2n+b),i v m y b </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>cy,i := φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+1,i) cy 1 φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+2,i) cy 2 . . . φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b),i cy b , </p>

<p>pv,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,2n+b+1),i p 1 v 1 φ (1,2n+b+2),i p 1 v 2 
. . . φ (1,2n+b+m),i p 1 v m 
φ (2,2n+b+1),i p 2 v 1 φ (2,2n+b+2),i p 2 v 2 
. . . φ (2,2n+b+m),i p 2 v m 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n,2n+b+1),i p n v 1 φ (n+n,2n+b+2),i p n v 2 . . . φ (n,2n+b+m),i p n v m </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>ṗv,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (n+1,2n+b+1),iṗ1 v 1 φ (n+1,2n+b+2),iṗ1 v 2 . . . φ (n+1,2n+b+m),iṗ1 v m 
φ (n+2,2n+b+1),iṗ2 v 1 φ (n+2,2n+b+2),iṗ2 v 2 . . . φ (n+2,2n+b+m),iṗ2 v m 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (n+n,2n+b+1),iṗn v 1 φ (n+n,2n+b+2),iṗn v 2 . . . φ (n+n,2n+b+m),iṗn v m </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>



<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>

<p>yv,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,2n+b+1),i y 1 v 1 φ (2n+1,2n+b+2),i y 1 v 2 . . . φ (2n+1,2n+b+m),i y 1 v m 
φ (2n+2,2n+b+1),i y 2 v 1 φ (2n+2,2n+b+2),i y 2 v 2 . . . φ (2n+2,2n+b+m),i y 2 v m 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b,2n+b+1),i y b v 1 φ (2n+b,2n+b+2),i y b v 2 . . . φ (2n+b,2n+b+m),i y b v m </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>v 2 ,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,2n+b+1),i v 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,2n+b+2),i v 1 v 2 . . . φ (2n+b+1,2n+b+m),i v 1 v m 
φ (2n+b+2,2n+b+1),i v 2 v 1 φ (2n+b+2,2n+b+2),i v 2 v 2 . . . φ (2n+b+2,2n+b+m),i v 2 v m 
. . . 
. . . 
. . . . . . 
φ (2n+b+m,2n+b+1),i v m v 1 φ (2n+b+m,2n+b+2),i v m v 2 . . . φ (2n+b+m,2n+b+m),i v 2 </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>cv,i := φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+1,i) cv 1 φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+2,i) cv 2 . . . φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+m),i cv m , </p>

<p>pc,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (1,2n+b+m+1),i p 1 c 
φ 2,2n+b+m+1),i p 2 c 
. . . 
φ n,2n+b+m+1),i p n c </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , ṗc,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (n+1,2n+b+m+1),iṗ1 c 
φ n+2,2n+b+m+1),iṗ2 c 
. . . 
φ n+n,2n+b+m+1),iṗn c </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>yc,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+1,2n+b+m+1),i y 1 c 
φ 2n+2,2n+b+m+1),i y 2 c 
. . . 
φ 2n+m,2n+b+m+1),i y b c </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , vc,i := </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+1,2n+b+m+1),i v 1 c 
φ 2n+b+2,2n+b+m+1),i v 2 c 
. . . 
φ 2n+b+m,2n+b+m+1),i v n c </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎥ 
⎦ , and </p>

<p>c 2 ,i := φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+m+1),i c 2 . </p>

<p>Appendix C: Defining Linear Quadratic Loss Function in the Input File </p>

<p>If the user chooses to create by themselves the input file, the linear-quadratic loss of 
every player in the game should be defined as follows. According to the definition of 
vector z(t), i.e., z(t) := [ p(t)ṗ(t) y(t) v(t) c] 
T , coefficient φ (in the loss of player i) 
that regards: </p>

<p>(i) variable p 1≤k≤n has an index (k, .), i, i.e. , φ (k,.),i ; 
(ii) variableṗ 1≤k≤n has an index (n + k, .), i, i.e., φ (n+k,.),i ; 
(iii) variable y 1≤k≤b has an index (2n + k, .), i, i.e., φ (2n+k,.),i ; 
(iv) variable v 1≤k≤m has an index (2n + b + k, .), i, i.e., φ (2n+b+k,.),i ; and 
(v) variable c has an index (2n + b + m + 1, .), i, i.e., φ (2n+b+m+1,.),i . </p>

<p>For example, to define in the toolbox the following loss function of player i: </p>

<p>J i = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>1 
2 
p 2 p 6 + α 1ṗ3 ( p 3 +ṗ 2 ) + v 2 ( p 3 + 2v i ) + 
√ 
3v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i + 4 e 
−θt dt, </p>

<p>where α 1 is some parameter, we need to simplify it first into linear quadratic form: </p>

<p>J i = 
1 
2 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 − </p>

<p>1 
2 
p 2 p 6 + α 1 p 3ṗ3 + α 1ṗ2ṗ3 + p 3 v 2 + 2v i v 2 + 
√ 
3v </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i + 4 e 
−θ t dt, </p>



<p>A Numerical Toolbox to Solve N -Player Affine LQ Open-Loop Differential Games </p>



<p>and set: </p>

<p>φ (1,1),i = 5, φ (2,6),i = − 
1 
2 
, φ (3,n+3),i = α 1 , φ (n+2,n+3),i = α 1 , φ (3,2n+b+2),i = 1, </p>

<p>φ (2n+b+i,2n+b+2),i = 2, φ (2n+b+i,2n+b+i),i = 
√ 
3, and φ (2n+b+m+1,2n+b+m+1),i = 4. </p>

<p>Of course, instead of φ (2,6),i = − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 one might as well set φ (6,2),i = − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 or φ (2,6),i = 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 and φ (6,2),i = − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 or any other linear combination that sums up to − </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 . </p>





<p>T. Michalak et al. </p>





</text></tei>