<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2F1467-8462.12246" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Over and above the current Australia's official national statistical agency, the 
Australian Bureau of Statistics (ABS), provides 
academics and researchers access to microdata 
by way of the widely known confidential unit 
record files (or CURFs) via CD-ROM, the 
Remote Access Data Laboratory (RADL) and 
the ABS Data Laboratory (ABSDL, onsite). The 
ABS also provides two TableBuilder products, 
online tools for creating tables, graphs and maps 
using ABS microdata. These microdata files 
are 'licensed', as opposed to 'public use', as each 
organisation, and its individual staff, is required 
to sign relevant undertakings assuring it will 
abide by prescribed conditions of use (under 
the Census and Statistics Act 1905 (Cwlth) and 
the Statistics Determination 1983). Recently the 
ABS has expanded its microdata product suite 
by offering the DataLab protected research 
environment, which for the first time allows 
researchers to have unparalleled access to pro-
tected ABS datasets. </p>

<p>2. The DataLab </p>

<p>Essentially, the DataLab is a data analysis solut-
ion for high-end data users who want to extract 
full value from ABS microdata in an interactive 
(real time) environment. All ABS microdata files, 
ranging from basic and expanded CURFs through 
to detailed and integrated files, are accessible via 
the DataLab, providing a more responsive and 
interactive environment than that offered by 
RADL and TableBuilder. The DataLab can be 
accessed securely on-site at ABS offices or as part 
of the virtual DataLab trial program. 
The DataLab was designed in late 2015 to 
improve access to ABS microdata, enhance </p>

<p>* Customised and Microdata Delivery Section, Dissemi-
nation Branch, Australian Bureau of Statistics, Australian 
Capital Territory 2617 Australia; email &lt;talei.parker@ 
abs.gov.au&gt;. </p>

<p>The Australian Economic Review, vol. 50, no. 4, pp. 478-83°C </p>

<p>2017 Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>user experience and advance research outcomes 
to inform policy design and delivery, as well 
as increase the use of statistics within the 
research community. The development areas to 
be addressed included: </p>

<p>the costs and security risks associated with 
the maintenance of ageing technologies (for 
example, RADL); </p>

<p>the substantial changes in user requirements 
and the increased sophistication of researcher 
skills (for example, programming skills asso-
ciated with <rs type="software">SAS</rs> as opposed to improved 'point 
and click' functionality, and open source 
coding packages such as R and Python); and </p>

<p>importantly the increased risk of re-identifi-
cation posed by making more detailed as 
well as integrated microdata available. </p>

<p>While the RADL allows analysis of micro-
data in a secure and controlled environment, it 
does not allow 'remote' access as implied by its 
name. Instead it provides a remote execution 
service, whereby authorised users submit 
queries in <rs id="software-5" type="software">SAS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">9.1</rs>, <rs id="software-6" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">11.5</rs> or <rs id="software-7" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">10</rs> 
analytical languages against expanded CURFs 
(see Figure 1). A range of automated processes 
monitor data requests and either release or 
withhold results where there is a possible 
confidentiality/disclosure risk. The number of </p>

<p>unit records that can be seen at any one point in 
time is restricted in the RADL. 
In comparison, the DataLab environment 
provides users with their own virtual workspace 
within the secure ABS cloud (see Figure 2). 
These workspaces can be accessed remotely, 
using a two-factor authentication over an 
encrypted internet connection using Citrix. 
While the microdata files remain in the secure 
environment, users can view and analyse unit 
record information using the latest analytical 
software with no code restrictions. All analyti-
cal outputs are subject to a principles-based, 
manual vetting process to evaluate disclosure 
risks and apply confidentiality measures where 
required before being released. 
The storage of files and running of analyses 
occurs on dedicated ABS servers housed in a 
secure data centre. The DataLab environment 
is a self-contained environment (that is, there is 
no email or internet connection, no copy and 
paste functionality in or out of the environ-
ment, no print facility and data cannot be 
copied to removable media). All file movement 
in and out of the DataLab is performed and 
managed by the ABS Customised and Micro-
data Delivery (CaMD) team through a dedi-
cated administrative portal following a strict 
auditing and sign-off process. All sessions 
within the DataLab environment are recorded 
allowing for real-time monitoring and subse-
quent playback. </p>

<p>Figure 1 RADL Login and Query Screens </p>

<p>Parker: The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics 
479°C </p>

<p>2017 Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>3. DataLab Access and Approval Process </p>

<p>Access to the DataLab is managed under a 
'Trusted Access' model using the principles 
from the 'Five Safes Framework' (FSF) (Desai, 
Ritchie and Welpton 2016). The ABS has 
adopted this model in order to significantly 
improve and more effectively manage micro-
data access and disclosure risk. Users are at 
the core of this model, which is built on the value 
of partnerships, shared accountability and the 
mutual benefits that result from researcher access 
to data. By carefully assessing people, projects, 
settings, data and output, necessary controls 
can be put in place to increase public value 
from national statistics whilst protecting privacy 
and confidentiality. The FSF (see Table 1) allows 
the ABS to better enable authorised users to work </p>

<p>directly with the data without infringing on 
their academic independence. 
Each of the 'five safes' is considered indepen-
dently on a sliding scale, as well as jointly, 
to evaluate whether a particular method of 
data access meets these requirements. Once 
researchers are trained, authorised and have 
signed relevant undertakings to comply with 
privacy and confidentiality obligations, the level 
of direct treatment applied to the data can be 
reduced. Similarly, technology settings and 
output review further protect data access and 
results. The benefit of this approach is that steps 
taken to protect privacy and confidentiality 
are designed to be both reasonable collectively 
and adequate to minimise the overall risk of 
disclosure. 
In order to use the DataLab, researchers 
must first be 'accredited'. The accreditation </p>

<p>Figure 2 DataLab Login and Home Screens </p>

<p>Table 1 The Five Safes (FSF) Applied to Trusted Access </p>

<p>Principle 
Criteria 
In practical terms </p>

<p>Safe People Appropriate personal authorisation 
to access and use the data </p>

<p>An undertaking on how the data will be used is signed after 
engagement with the researcher. Training is provided so 
that users understand their responsibilities and are able to 
use the microdata effectively. 
Safe Projects Data to be used for an appropriate 
purpose </p>

<p>Users demonstrate that they will use the data for legitimate 
statistical research purposes. 
Safe Settings The access environment prevents 
unauthorised use </p>

<p>The data cannot be exported from the environment. 
The login is secure. 
Safe Data 
The data have been appropriately 
and sufficiently protected </p>

<p>Directly identifying information has been removed and the data 
are treated appropriately with respect to the other four 
'safes'. 
Safe Outputs The statistical results do not disclose 
identifying information </p>

<p>Outputs are checked for disclosure risk and treated if deemed 
necessary°C </p>

<p> 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
December 2017 </p>

<p>process generally takes 12-14 working days 
(after training attendance) and once approved, 
researchers are notified via email. Each of the 
steps involved are outlined below. </p>

<p>(i) Researchers must be employed by an org-
anisation that has a Responsible Officer 
Undertaking (ROU) signed by the relevant 
delegate (Safe people). This is a legislative 
requirement (Statistics Determination 
1983). The ABS cannot disclose microdata 
unless a 'responsible officer'-one that acts 
'within the scope of authority exercisable 
by him/her in accordance with arrange-
ments approved by that organisation'-
assures their staff will act appropriately. </p>

<p>(ii) Researchers need to be able to demon-
strate the appropriate knowledge and 
experience necessary for handling confi-
dential information, and demonstrate 
a commitment to protecting and main-
taining the confidentiality of data (Safe 
people; Safe projects). It is expected that 
researchers understand the need to respect 
the privacy and confidentiality of data 
providers and behave accordingly. </p>

<p>(iii) Researchers must be experienced in the 
use of one or more of the analytical 
software languages available within the 
DataLab. This is important as the Data-
Lab is a self-service system and the ABS 
does not provide training or assistance to 
users for coding and methodological 
issues related to their research. Software 
available in the DataLab include <rs id="software-8" type="software">SAS 
Enterprise Guide</rs> <rs corresp="#software-8" type="version-number">7.1</rs>, <rs id="software-9" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-9" type="version-number">13</rs>, <rs id="software-10" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version-number">24</rs>, R 
3.1.2, <rs type="software">Microsoft Word</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2010</rs>, <rs id="software-1" type="software">Microsoft 
Excel</rs> 2010, <rs type="software">Ultraedit</rs> and <rs type="software">Adobe Acrobat 
Reader DC (PDF</rs>). Updates to these 
statistical packages will be made available 
as they are released. The addition of 
further packages is open to discussion as 
the DataLab is envisioned to be a product 
that evolves and adapts to user needs and 
requirements. </p>

<p>(iv) Researchers need to have successfully 
completed the mandatory face-to-face </p>

<p>DataLab training and quiz (Safe people). 
The training session is intended to ensure 
users understand their legal and ethical 
responsibilities and to assist them with 
understanding Statistical Disclosure Con-
trol (SDC) when using the DataLab. The 
session is presented in three modules. The 
first explains the new 'shared account-
ability' approach and how the five safes 
apply to assessing access requests. The 
second focuses on a researcher's legal and 
ethical responsibilities when using the 
DataLab, and the final module focuses 
on SDC and is made up of a number of 
interactive exercises designed to help 
users understand confidentiality require-
ments from the ABS perspective and how 
outputs are vetted for release. </p>

<p>(v) Researchers are required to have signed 
an Individual Undertaking and Declara-
tion of Compliance (Safe people). This is 
a legislative requirement under ABS 
legislation. Depending on the microdata 
being accessed users will be required 
to sign either a Clause 7 or 7A (under the 
Statistics Determination 1983) or Section 
16A (secondment under the Australian 
Bureau of Statistics Act 1975 (Cwlth)) 
undertaking. </p>

<p>(vi) Researchers must complete and submit a 
project proposal (Safe project). The 
proposal needs to outline the research 
objectives and any associated ethics/ 
grants approvals, the microdata products 
to be used, and any anticipated outcomes 
and project timeframes. </p>

<p>4. Using the ABS DataLab </p>

<p>Once researchers have completed the accredi-
tation process they are provided with a 
username and password. Researchers in the 
virtual DataLab trial are also supplied with a 
secure two-factor authentication Fortitoken 
1 to 
enable access from their desktop in their own 
workplace environments. 
Once logged into the system, researchers are 
made aware that session recording is used in°C </p>

<p>2017 Commonwealth of Australia. Australian Economic Review°C 2017 The University of Melbourne, 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Parker: The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics </p>

<p>
the system and they must indicate agreement to 
this. Session recording is a part of the required 
DataLab auditing process and all sessions are 
viewed by CaMD staff. The use of a virtual 
environment has been provided to enable the 
researcher complete flexibility in how they 
approach their analytical/project work. </p>

<p>5. DataLab Drives </p>

<p>A total of four drives are provided within 
the DataLab for each user in a Windows 
environment. 
The H: drive is the researcher's personal 
drive. It contains an 'Application' folder and a 
'Clearance' folder. The 'Application' folder is 
for the researcher to save and access any code, 
project information and output files in the 
course of their work. If the researcher has any 
pre-prepared code files, Word/PDF documents 
or public data files they may wish to use then 
these will be accessible in this folder once they 
have been cleared and loaded by CaMD. The 
'Clearance' folder is where the researcher 
places analytical results that require vetting. 
Those microdata files that the researcher 
has been given approval to use can be found in 
the V: drive. Project teams have access to a 
shared project space-the S: drive-within 
their individual virtual workspaces. The shared 
project spaces have been designed to facili-
tate collaboration and enable the team to 
complete their research/project end to end 
before requesting a release of outputs to be 
used for public dissemination. 
The L: drive is a read-only drive designed to 
mimic 'Google' in a way. As the DataLab is a 
contained environment with no internet access, 
this drive has been created to house analytical 
reference material, publicly available code and 
any other material that researchers may 
routinely use or search for in the normal course 
of their work. 
In relation to package add-ons, researchers 
can request for CaMD to have these loaded on 
their behalf. For example, a researcher who is 
using <rs type="software">STATA</rs> may need an add-on, such as 
'svr', that is not available in the ABS licensed 
package within the DataLab. A request can be 
made to CaMD to have this added into the </p>

<p>DataLab environment and once loaded it will 
be available for all DataLab users via this drive. </p>

<p>6. Clearance Process (Safe Outputs) </p>

<p>Output checking is standard practice in 
countries that use the FSF (for example, Stats 
NZ 2017 and Office for National Statistics 
2017) and is a mechanism to protect against 
statistical disclosure, that is, the release of 
information that could lead to the identification 
of an individual, household or organisation in 
data. As microdata files in the DataLab have 
lower levels of 'confidentialisation' applied, 
they carry an increased risk of disclosure, 
compared to other products. Output checking 
helps to mitigate reasonably this risk and guard 
against mistakes. 
Once researchers are ready to have an output 
file released, they save it to their 'Clearance' 
folder and CaMD team members will vet the 
request. The turn-around time for the vetting 
process is 1-2 business days. 
CaMD uses a 'principles'-based approach to 
output checking (Ritchie and Elliot 2015) and 
utilises 'rules of thumb'. Practical guidelines 
on adhering to the safe output standard are 
provided to users as part of the face-to-face 
DataLab training session. Once output has been 
cleared, it is released to the researcher via 
email. </p>

<p>7. Improved Microdata Offering </p>

<p>The full suite of basic and expanded CURFs 
(ABS 2017) are available in the DataLab, 
removing the need for researchers to use CD-
ROMs (basic CURFs) and/or the RADL 
(expanded CURFs). With the implementation 
of the FSF and the development of the 
DataLab, the ABS now also offers access to 
detailed microdata files (ABS 2017). These 
files have been designed specifically for the 
DataLab, have direct identifiers removed and 
are confidentialised within the context of the 
DataLab's security features. The following are 
examples of such files. </p>

<p>(i) Australian Census Longitudinal Dataset 
(ACLD): The ACLD is a 5 per cent°C </p>

<p> 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p> 
The Australian Economic Review 
December 2017 </p>

<p>sample of data from the 2006 Census 
linked to the 2011 Census. It enables large-
sample longitudinal analysis of transitions 
in the economic and social conditions of 
Australians. </p>

<p>(ii) Business Longitudinal Analysis Data Envi-
ronment (BLADE): The BLADE is an 
integrated data environment and was 
developed by the ABS and the Department 
of Industry, Innovation and Science. It 
contains detailed information drawing on 
several years of ABS business survey data 
and administrative data from the Australian 
Tax Office (ATO), on the characteristics 
and finances of Australian businesses. This 
allows for longitudinal analysis of business 
and investigatory analyses of the 'micro-
economic factors driving productivity, 
performance, innovation and job crea-
tion' in the Australian economy (ABS 
2016-17) </p>

<p>(iii) Multi-Agency Data Integration Project 
(MADIP): MADIP is an on-going part-
nership project that brings ABS Census 
data together with administrative data 
from the ATO, Department of Human 
Services, Department of Social Services, 
Department of Health and, most recently, 
the Department of Education. Currently in 
an evaluation phase, it creates a valuable 
data resource with significant potential 
for research and policy analysis (ABS 
2016-17). </p>

<p>8. Conclusion </p>

<p>The ABS DataLab research environment offers 
researchers greater flexibility in accessing and 
analysing unit record data whilst ensuring 
essential confidentiality processes are main-
tained. Up-to-date technology and trusted 
access based risk management mean the 
system is streamlined, responsive to user needs 
and provides microdata access in a reliable 
and safe manner. The DataLab delivers ease </p>

<p>of use, enhanced opportunity for collaboration 
and a modernised approach to dissemination. 
Researchers can better inform public decisions 
and develop policy. These outcomes are 
achieved in a manner that respects privacy 
and confidentiality of those who provide their 
data. </p>

<p>September 2017 </p>

<p>Endnote </p>

<p>1. See &lt;https://www.fortinet.com/products/identity-access-
management.html&gt;. </p>



<p> 
Melbourne Institute of Applied Economic and Social Research Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd </p>

<p>Parker: The DataLab of the Australian Bureau of Statistics </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>