<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fkykl.12110" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Over the last 15 years, China has become a major economic partner of sub-Saharan 
African countries. 
1 China is now Africa's largest trade partner and the largest devel-
oping country to invest in Africa. Apart from that, China provides increasing financial 
and technical assistance to African countries. Over the same period of time, Africa's 
growth performance has improved significantly. Following two decades of negative 
growth rates in the 1980s and 1990s, Africa's Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per 
capita grew by an annual average of 2.4 percent in 2000-2009, while the growth rate 
in 2010-2012 amounted to 1.8 percent (World Bank, 2014a). Obviously, various fac-
tors have contributed to Africa's better growth performance, including a marked 
improvement in institutions, education and infrastructure and a decrease in conflicts 
and macroeconomic distortions (AfDB et al., 2013; UNECA, 2013). Still, the ques-
tion arises as to whether China's engagement has also made a significant contribution 
to economic growth in Africa. This is the main focus of this paper. 
We single out the impact of Sino-African economic linkages on the African 
growth performance for two main reasons. Firstly, starting from a relatively low base, 
China has become Africa's largest trading partner and largest (developing country) 
investor within only a couple of years. This acts as a classical economic shock that 
should have an impact on growth rates. Secondly, China's approach towards African 
countries differs from high-income countries in terms of trade structure and technol-
ogy spillovers through Foreign Direct Investment (FDI). As a consequence, we could 
expect diverging economic effects. At the same time, China also differs from other 
developing (or emerging market) economies, such as India or Brazil, that engage in 
Africa. China's trading and investment links with Africa are much more intensive </p>

<p>* Matthias Busse (Corresponding author), Ruhr-University Bochum, Faculty of Management and Economics, 
Chair of International Economics, GC 3/145, Universitaetsstr. 150, 44780 Bochum, Germany, E-mail 
matthias.busse@rub.de, Tel. +49-234-32-22902, Fax +49-234-32-14520; Ceren Erdogan, Ruhr-University 
Bochum, Faculty of Management and Economics, Chair of International Economics, E-mail: ceren. 
erdogan@rub.de; Henning Muehlen, University of Hohenheim, Institute of Economics, Economics: Interna-
tional Economics, E-mail: LHenning.Muehlen@uni-hohenheim.de 
1. Hereafter referred to as African countries or Africa. </p>

<p>KYKLOS ,Vol. 69 -May 2016 -No. 2, 228-262 </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>than those of other developing countries. Apart from a few countries, for example, in 
Eastern Africa, the economic activities of non-Chinese developing countries are sim-
ply not large enough to have the same potential economic impact on African coun-
tries at a macro level (Morrissey and Zgovu, 2011). 
In theory, China's activities in Africa could have positive or negative conse-
quences for African countries. To begin with, it is important to note that China's eco-
nomic activities have resulted in an overall increase of trade, FDI, and aid in Africa 
rather than a diversion of existing flows from third countries. In principle, this should 
have positive effects. An expansion of international trade with a new partner like 
China could boost growth rates by increasing demand for African products (mainly 
raw materials). Also, the diversification of Africa's traditional trading partners could 
reduce export volatility, thereby decreasing output volatility and thus boosting long-
run growth rates (Hnatkovska and Loayza, 2004). Furthermore, China's enormous 
demand for raw materials has led to higher world market prices for raw materials, 
improving the terms-of-trade of African exporters of natural resources (Zafar,  2007). Consumers in Africa could benefit from (additional) imports of manufactured 
goods from China, allowing them to cut their expenses by consuming low-cost Chi-
nese products or increasing the variety of consumer goods available to them. Like-
wise, African producers could take advantage of low-cost Chinese inputs in their 
production process rather than importing goods and technologies from "Northern" 
countries that may be too expensive or advanced (He, 2013). 
Similar to trade, foreign investment from China could also have positive 
growth effects for Africa. It is expected to enlarge the capital stock in African 
countries, to increase productivity levels through higher competition intensities, 
and it is associated with higher tax revenues (UNCTAD, 2006). Also, foreign 
investment could foster productivity spillovers to African firms. In contrast to 
North-South FDI, spillovers from South-South FDI could be even larger, as 
Chinese firms use technologies that may be more appropriate for African firms. 
Finally, Chinese economic cooperation projects establish and improve much 
needed infrastructure in Africa, which lowers transaction costs and thus enhances 
(internal and external) trade and growth rates. 
In contrast to these positive effects, China's engagement in Africa could also 
have negative consequences for economic growth. China's strong demand for 
raw materials paired with African economies' high dependence on the primary 
(resource) sector enhances the risk of encountering (or deepening) the resource 
curse (Carmignani and Chowdhury, 2012). An exchange rate overvaluation 
due to increasing exports of natural resources could crowd out manufacturing 
products. Extracting and exporting natural resources could lead to rent-seeking 
and corruption (Busse and Gröning, 2013). Corruption, on the other hand, may 
lower the level of investment and the productivity of capital stock in an economy 
(Swaleheen, 2007). In addition, African countries with high corruption and weak 
institutions may not be able to fully reap the benefits of investment for growth as </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>investment increases growth more in countries with high institutional quality 
(Dort et al., 2014). This matters as most African countries have already weak 
institutions and China, with its "non-interference" policy, does not tie trade 
and investment to any reform conditions. 
Additionally, Chinese manufactured firms could displace their African 
competitors in case they produce similar goods. Both exchange rate overvaluations 
and low-cost competition from China threaten African suppliers in manufacturing. 
Depending on the country considered, this applies in particular to textiles, furni-
ture, footwear, or ceramic products (Morrissey and Zgovu, 2011). Either the home 
market of African suppliers could be contested by Chinese firms or African exports 
to third markets, for instance in Europe or America, could be displaced 
(Giovannetti and Sanfilippo, 2009). Summing up, there are opportunities and risks 
that arise from China's various activities in Africa. This calls for an empirical anal-
ysis of the growth effects in African countries. 
To the best of our knowledge, there has not yet been an econometric analysis 
on the impact of China's activities on African growth including the three chan-
nels, trade, FDI and aid, at the same time. The existing literature provides strong 
evidence for the relevance of each of these channels for African growth. Conse-
quently, our analysis accounts for all three channels of interaction in order to 
obtain a comprehensive picture of China's impact on Africa. In terms of method-
ology, we use panel data for 43 sub-Saharan African countries, the period 1991-
2010, a simple Solow-type growth model and two different econometric 
methods, including an instrumental variable approach. 
The paper is structured in the following way. Section II summarizes the related 
literature on Sino-African trade, FDI and aid relations. Section III explains the 
methodology employed in our empirical analysis and introduces the variables 
and the data used. The main results as well as various robustness checks and lim-
itations are discussed in Section IV. Finally, Section V discusses the policy 
implications of our analysis and concludes. </p>

<p>II. LITERATURE REVIEW </p>

<p>Although China's engagement in Africa has received considerable attention in pol-
icy publications (Goldstein et al., 2006; Broadman, 2007; Kaplinsky et al., 2007;  Asche and Schüller, 2008; Morrissey and Zgovu, 2011), there are very few econo-
metric analyses on this topic. This is mainly due to the fact that economic relations 
between China and Africa have only picked up since 2000 and data is not easily 
available at country level. The study at hand focuses on the three transmission chan-
nels, trade, FDI and aid from China to Africa. Contrary to our approach, the existing 
literature does not include all channels at once but rather looks closer at the determi-
nants and effects of each of the channels individually. This literature review com-
prises the most important econometric analyses for each of the respective channels. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>A first group of studies investigates the trade relations between China and 
Africa. For instance, Meyersson et al. (2008) investigate the impact of African 
resource exports to China on African economic and political development. The 
authors find that African resource exports to the world have no effect on African 
growth, but exporting natural resources to China as compared to the rest of the 
world has large positive effects on economic growth and investment in Africa. 
Baliamoune-Lutz (2011) also finds that African countries exporting primary prod-
ucts to China benefit more in terms of growth and that imports from China have a 
positive effect on African growth, contradicting the wide held belief of resource 
curse and displacement effects. However, Giovannetti and Sanfilippo (2009) find 
evidence that Chinese exports displace African exports in third markets, including 
the European Union and the United States. On the other hand, Drummond and Liu  (2013) argue that rising trading links with China have allowed African countries to 
diversify their export base across countries, away from advanced "Northern" econ-
omies, which can be viewed as a positive development. However, the authors also 
find that the increasing dependence on China may lead African countries to become 
more susceptible to spillovers from China's domestic economy. For instance, based 
on the authors' estimations an increase (decline) in China's domestic investment 
growth is associated with an increase (decline) in African countries' export growth, 
with the impact being greater for resource-rich economies. 
A second group of studies concentrates on determinants and effects of Chinese 
FDI in Africa. To begin with, Kolstad and Wiig (2011) find that Chinese FDI pre-
dominantly flows to African countries with large natural resource endowments. 
Cheung et al. (2012) confirm China's resource-seeking investment motive and also 
find market potential, trade intensity and the presence of Chinese contracted pro-
jects to attract Chinese FDI to Africa. While Sanfilippo (2010) supports market size 
and resource endowment to be the main drivers of Chinese FDI, he finds that these 
same motives attract Chinese economic cooperation projects in Africa even more. 
Finally, Biggeri and Sanfilippo (2009) argue that Chinese economic activities in 
Africa are not only driven by a country's resource endowment or market size but 
also by the strategic interaction of trade, FDI and aid. For instance, Chinese infra-
structure projects in a particular country increase Chinese FDI to that country, while 
Chinese FDI in a former period increases trade with that country in the present (or 
vice versa). Similar to our approach Biggeri and Sanfilippo (2009) also concentrate 
on the three dominant economic channels, trade, FDI and aid. However, they rather 
analyse how the three channels are intertwined, whereas our paper analyses the 
respective channels' effects on growth. Moreover, Whalley and Weisbrod (2012)  analyse the impact of Chinese FDI on African growth by employing Solow growth 
accounting methods. Their results suggest that a significant portion of the acceler-
ated growth in some African countries in the years immediately before and after 
the financial crisis can be attributed to Chinese FDI inflows. Zhang et al. (2014) also 
employ a growth accounting approach to examine the impact of Chinese FDI on </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>African GDP growth. Contrary to Whalley and Weisbrod (2012), Zhang et al.  (2014) find that neither total net FDI inflows nor inflows from China alone have 
a significant impact on African growth. Moreover, Seyoum et al. (2015) conduct 
a case study on Chinese FDI spillovers in Ethiopia. They find that Chinese firms 
are more productive than Ethiopian ones and that there are positive productivity 
spillovers from Chinese FDI into the Ethiopian manufacturing sector provided 
that absorptive capacity is high. Kaplinsky and Morris (2009b) argue that the 
developmental effect of Chinese FDI in Africa largely depends on strategic 
negotiations and the quality of governance on the part of African governments. 
Finally, there is some evidence that FDI from private Chinese enterprises is 
steadily increasing in Africa (Gu, 2009; Shen, 2013). Shen (2013) also finds that 
private Chinese FDI is positive for job creation but there is negative perception 
regarding technological transfer and mixed perception in terms of local 
industrialization. 
Finally, a third group of studies provides evidence on Chinese aid in Africa. 
Although, numerous qualitative studies on the topic of Chinese economic and devel-
opment cooperation in Africa exist (Bräutigam, 2009, 2011a, 2011b), opportunities 
for econometric analyses were quite limited due to severe data constraints regarding 
Chinese aid. However, recent efforts to create a database of Chinese official finance to 
Africa has resulted in a number of empirical papers on the topic (Strange et al., 2013). 
Overall, the existing literature establishes that although Chinese aid cannot be easily 
compared with Western aid, it cannot be ruled less effective or "rogue" (Dreher et al.,  2014). Moreover, Dreher et al. (2015) argue that it is necessary to distinguish between 
official development assistance from China to Africa, which is driven by foreign pol-
icy agendas, and more commercially-oriented less concessional forms of Chinese fi-
nancing to Africa, which is primarily driven by economic interests. Related to that, 
McCormick (2008) analyses the impact of aid from China compared to India, on 
the development of Africa. The author finds that, compared to India, China offers a 
wider range of financial and technical assistance to Africa. The effects of Chinese 
and Indian aid seem significant for African development but do depend to a large 
extent on the institutional and structural conditions in the recipient country. </p>

<p>III. MODEL AND DATA </p>

<p>3.1. Descriptive Overview </p>

<p>Before embarking upon the empirical analysis it is worthwhile to analyse 
descriptive statistics of trade, FDI and aid between China and Africa over the last 
two decades. This also lends support to our approach to single out China's 
impact compared to other major economies that have economic relations with 
Africa. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Trade While Sino-African trade volumes were negligible before 2000, bilateral 
trade increased significantly in the last decade from $3 billion in 1995 to $125 
billion in 2012 (see Figure 1). Figure 1 presents African trade with its major trad-
ing partners over the last twenty years. It is evident that no other trading partner 
has increased its trade volume in the same period as much as China did. 
With regards to trade structure Sino-African trade is largely concentrated on a 
few countries and product groups. In 2012 natural resources accounted for 66 
percent of Africa's exports to China. 
2 Major resource exporters to China in 
2012 were Angola, South Africa, the Republic of Congo, the Democratic Repub-
lic of Congo, and Zambia. With the exception of South Africa, resource exports 
accounted for well over 90 percent of the aforementioned countries total exports 
to China, reflecting the high concentration of trade in natural resources. When 
looking at African imports from China, the trade pattern is mirror-inverted, that 
is, African countries import mainly non-resource products from China (97 per-
cent of total imports in 2012). Africa's heavy concentration on resource exports 
and non-resource imports reflects a traditional Heckscher-Ohlin-type trade pat-
tern. Africa concentrates on the export of natural resources where it has a com-
parative advantage, and in turn imports labour-intensive manufactured goods 
from China which is labour-abundant. Interestingly, South Africa's trade with </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Africa's Trade with Major Trading Partners, 1995-2012. Notes: Figures refer to total merchandise trade 
(exports + imports) in billion US$. Data source: UNCTADStat (2014) </p>

<p>2. Percentages are authors' calculations based on disaggregated trade data from UN Comtrade (2014). </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>China differs from that of other African countries in the sense that both South 
African exports to and imports from China concentrate mainly on non-resource 
goods. In terms of resource trade, Angola was China's most important African 
trading partner in 2012 (42 percent of total Sino-African resource trade). </p>

<p>FDI In terms of foreign investment, Chinese FDI flows to Africa increased from just 
$200 million in 2000 to $2.2 billion in 2012, making China the largest developing 
country to invest in Africa (UNCTAD, 2013; MOFCOM, Various Years b). 
Although Chinese FDI to Africa is low relative to FDI flows from other countries, 
its growth over the last decade has been remarkable. Figure 2 illustrates this upward 
trend of Chinese FDI to Africa since 2000. 
3 However, despite the fast growth in Chi-
nese FDI flows, the actual volumes are fairly small, both in terms of African GDP and 
total FDI inflows in Africa. Average Chinese FDI flows to Africa in 2000-2012 
accounted for just about 4 percent of total FDI inflows to Africa. 
Major African host countries in terms of Chinese FDI stock are South Africa, 
Sudan, Nigeria, and Zambia. As is the case with Sino-African trade, Chinese 
FDI in Africa is also concentrated on resource-rich African economies with the 
exception of South Africa. Moreover, Chinese FDI is promoted by strategic 
national policy objectives, such as the Going Global Policy or the Forum on China 
Africa Cooperation, resulting in large and long-term oriented investments, com-
plicating a comparison between Chinese FDI with FDI from the rest of the world. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Economic Cooperation (Aid) Additionally, Chinese aid initiatives in Africa in the 
form of economic or technical cooperation have also increased remarkably in the last 
decade. According to China's National Bureau of Statistics (NBS, 2013), the turnover 
on economic cooperation projects in Africa reached $35 billion in 2012 compared to 
$1.2 billion in 2000. The Chinese government supports economic cooperation pro-
jects in Africa and often links them with FDI and trade activities further reflecting 
its political objectives on the continent (Biggeri and Sanfilippo, 2009; Sanfilippo,  2010). Areas of economic cooperation where China is most active in Africa include 
infrastructure (railways, roads, telecommunication) and facility construction projects 
(government buildings, stadiums, hospitals, schools) (Biggeri and Sanfilippo, 2009). </p>

<p>3. The sharp decline in 2009 may suggest that Chinese FDI flows decreased after the financial crisis. In 
fact, it is rather due to an exceptionally large investment in South Africa's Standard Bank in 2008 mak-
ing South Africa the country with the largest Chinese FDI stock in Africa. 
4. The importance of Africa in China's foreign policy culminated in the establishment of the Forum on 
China-Africa Cooperation (FOCAC) in 2000. The forum holds ministerial conferences every three years 
and is an important platform to implement specific economic policy programs with Africa. Moreover, 
China's "Going-Global" policy, announced in 2001, also contributed to the rise in Sino-African eco-
nomic relations. In order to encourage foreign trade and outward FDI, the policy provides Chinese firms 
with easy access to loans, foreign exchange and preferential policies for taxation, imports and exports 
(UNCTAD and UNDP, 2007). </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Furthermore, China provides financial aid in the form of grants, zero-interest loans, 
debt relief, and concessional loans as well as preferential export credits, market-rate 
export buyers' credits, and commercial loans from Chinese banks (Bräutigam,  2011b). Although China publishes annual data on the turnover of economic cooper-
ation projects at a country-level, it is difficult to compare with aid disbursements from 
Western donors. 
5 On the other hand, China's main objectives in Africa are not pri-
marily geared towards financial aid but rather towards a form of South-South Coop-
eration. Chinese companies often work on contracted projects in Africa as a result of a 
greater finance or trade deal the Chinese government agreed upon with the govern-
ment of a particular African country which entails some sort of economic or technical 
cooperation. In the absence of other appropriate data sources, we argue that data on 
economic cooperation may serve as an adequate proxy for the level of Chinese devel-
opment cooperation activities in Africa. </p>

<p>3.2. Empirical Model, Variables and Data </p>

<p>To assess the impact of the various Chinese activities on economic growth in 
Africa, we use a simple Solow-type growth model. We exploit the times-series 
dimension in the data by using a panel data approach. In line with large parts 
of the relevant literature, for example, Mankiw et al. (1992), Islam (1995) and </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>FDI inflows to Africa by Major Investors, 2001-2012. Note: FDI inflows to Africa in billion US$. Data 
source: UNCTAD (2014) </p>

<p>5. As Bräutigam (2011b) points out, economic cooperation data does not refer to something provided by 
the Chinese government, but rather to revenues earned by Chinese firms in contracted economic coop-
eration projects abroad, and should therefore not be confused with data on financial flows from the Chi-
nese government. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Hoeffler (2002), we use real GDP per capita growth rates as our dependent var-
iable, that is, changes in the log of real income per capita y in country i over time 
t, or lny it -lny it-1 . Essential independent variables in this growth model are initial 
income per capita (lny it-1 ), the population growth rate n, changes in technology g, 
the depreciation rate of the capital stock δ, and the savings rate s. We add further 
control variables and the variables of interest X it explained below. The basic 
model reads as follows: </p>

<p>lny it -lny it-1 ¼ α þ βlny it-1 þ γlns it þ ϕln n it þ g þ δ 
ð 
Þþφ'lnX it </p>

<p>þλ t þ μ i þ ε it </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>The model includes period-specific effects λ t (for example, technology shocks 
affecting all countries), country-specific fixed-effects μ i and an independent and 
identically distributed error term ε it . In line with Mankiw et al. (1992), we assume 
that changes in technology and the depreciation rate of the capital stock are con-
stant over time and equal to 0.05. Equation 1 can then be rewritten as: </p>

<p>lny it ¼ α þ β þ 1 
ð 
Þlny it-1 þ γlns it þ ϕln n it þ 0:05 
ð 
Þþφ'lnX it </p>

<p>þλ t þ μ i þ ε it </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>To test this model empirically, we use GDP per capita for income levels and 
the share of investment in GDP for the savings rate. In line with the predictions 
of the Solow model and the results of previous empirical growth papers, we 
expect a negative impact of income levels in the previous period on growth rates 
(due to convergence effects), a positive impact of investment and a negative 
effect of an increase in the population. 
For our main variables of interest -trade, FDI and aid -we distinguish between 
flows from China and the rest of the world (ROW). To control for Sino-African 
trade flows, we use two different sets of variables. Firstly, we employ total Afri-
can exports to (and imports from) China and control for respective African trade 
with the rest of the world. These variables are meant to capture the effects of total 
African trade with China, though we distinguish between imports and exports, 
which can have different effects. Secondly, we differentiate between natural 
resource exports and imports, and non-resource exports and imports. Due to the 
importance of natural resources in Sino-African trade, we are interested in the 
effects of trade in different commodities. Natural resource exports comprise, 
among others, fuel, various mineral products, and non-ferrous metals. 
6 We nor-
malised all trade variables by the GDP of the respective African country. </p>

<p>6. See Appendix A for an exact definition of natural resource trade and all other variables as well as data 
sources. Descriptive statistics are displayed in Appendix B. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>For foreign investment, we again differentiate between Chinese FDI and FDI 
from the ROW to African countries, both normalized by the host country's 
GDP. Chinese outward FDI data at the country-level is available from 1991. 
There are two sets of Chinese FDI data: (1) Chinese Approved Overseas Invest-
ment data for 1991-2005, and (2) Chinese Outward FDI data reported in IMF-
OECD format since 2003. 
7 We combine the two sets of data by using the first 
set for the years 1991-2002 and the second set for the years 2003-2010. Even though 
the data in the two datasets could differ at a country level, the deviations are fairly 
small. This allows us to exploit a longer time series since 1991. To include as many 
observations as possible, we fill missing values with zero assuming that there was no 
FDI in that case (and add one before taking the log). 
8 To control for FDI from the 
ROW, we subtract Chinese FDI flows from total FDI flows to African countries. 
Finally, we test for the effects of Chinese economic cooperation projects in 
African countries, again, normalized by the respective country's GDP. Data is 
taken from various issues of the China Statistical Yearbook published by China's 
National Bureau of Statistics. Following Biggeri and Sanfilippo (2009) and 
Sanfilippo (2010), we use data on economic cooperation as a proxy for Chinese 
aid due to the lack of other official data. Although there have been Chinese eco-
nomic cooperation projects in Africa for several decades, country-level data on 
economic cooperation has only been published since 1998. In order to keep the 
time frame of our analysis as long as possible, we computed data at a country 
level for 1991-1997. More specifically, we assume that the country breakdown 
of China's total economic cooperation before 1998 is similar to that in the period 
1998-2001. As China's economic cooperation projects started soaring after the 
Going Global Policy in 2001, we find it reasonable to assume that in the years 
before 2002 the level of economic cooperation in Africa as compared to the 
ROW was more or less constant. Importantly, this procedure does not affect 
the main results reported below. If we exclude the years before 1998, the results 
do not change much in terms of the sign and significance of the main variables of 
interest. Besides China's economic cooperation, we control for foreign aid 
received by African countries from the ROW. 
The additional control variables include changes in the terms-of-trade, the 
inflation rate for macroeconomic distortions, and the number of battle deaths 
for the occurrence and intensity of conflicts. The latter variable has been included 
to control for the relatively high conflict intensity in sub-Saharan Africa. We take 
logs of all variables but changes in the terms-of-trade, as there are many negative 
observations for this variable. Changes in the terms-of-trade should have a </p>

<p>7. For a discussion of China's FDI data see Cheung et al. (2012). 
8. We inserted a zero in 47 out of 151 observations. While excluding the zero observations does not affect 
the results reported below, it would reduce the sample significantly. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>positive impact of growth, whereas the opposite is expected for the inflation rate 
and conflict intensity. 
Due to lack of adequate data for many African countries, we do not include 
measures for education. 
9 With regards to institutional quality we also face issues 
as measures are either not available for the majority of the sampled countries or 
for the whole period in question (1991-2010). 
10 In order to keep our sample as 
large as possible we do not include these measures in our main regressions. How-
ever, we control for institutional quality in additional regressions (robustness 
checks) by using the rule of law indicator of the World Bank (2014b) Good Gov-
ernance indicators, which covers basically all African countries and is available 
from 1996. 
11 At the same time, we use the rule of law indicator to explore coun-
try heterogeneity by using interactive terms with our FDI and aid variables. 
The period under consideration in the baseline regressions is restricted to 
1991-2010 by the availability of Chinese investment and economic cooperation 
data. To control for business cycle effects, we compute five-year averages for 
all variables, which results to four observations for the period 1991 to 2010. 
For the lagged dependent variable, we also use information for the previous 
period 1986 to 1990. In further regressions, we use four-year averages (five 
observations for 1991 to 2010). 
12 The sample consists of 43 sub-Saharan African 
countries, that is, all 48 countries in that region apart from Liberia, Sao Tome 
and Principe, Seychelles, Somalia, and South Sudan. While trade figures for 
Liberia are highly distorted, the last four had to be excluded due to missing 
data for key variables such as GDP per capita or investment, or simply did 
not exist as a country for the larger part of the period under consideration. 
In extensions and robustness checks, we both enlarge the sample by including 
North African countries and reduce the sample by excluding sub-Saharan 
African islands. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>In terms of the methodology, we use a standard OLS fixed-effects model. This 
approach allows a robust estimation of the various linkages and ensures to control 
for unobserved time-invariant country fixed-effects. In a dynamic fixed-effects </p>

<p>9. The sample would decline by more than one third if we included, for instance, the Barro and Lee (2013)  educational attainment variables. Data on gross or net school enrolment ratios are fairly incomplete and 
of heterogeneous quality for African countries which would also lead to a decreased sample. 
10. The International Country Risk Group data (PRS Group, 2014) for political risk, is available for the 
period in question but only covers around 30 African countries. Using this data would imply cutting 
our sample by one third. 
11. Using the rule of law indicator in our main regressions would cut our time series by five years or 25 
percent of the total. 
12. While we do have data for Chinese FDI and economic corporation data available until 2012, that is not 
sufficient to compute an additional five-or four-year period. 
13. See Appendix C for the country sample. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>model, it is well known that the inclusion of the lagged dependent variable can 
lead to biased estimates (Nickell, 1981). This bias mainly affects the lagged 
income per capita variable, which is not the variable of principle interest in our 
paper. Still, the size of the impact of the various trade, FDI and aid variables of 
main interest could be affected, for example, by using the lagged dependent var-
iable to calculate the long-run effects. More worryingly, there might be another 
bias due to the endogeneity of some of the explanatory variables. Depending on 
the partner country or product type, trade, FDI and aid are likely to be endogenous 
with respect to economic growth. To mitigate both concerns, we also use the sys-
tem Generalized Methods of Moments (GMM) estimator, introduced by Arellano  and Bover (1995) and Blundell and Bond (1998). </p>

<p>IV. RESULTS </p>

<p>4.1. Main Results </p>

<p>Baseline Regressions We begin by reporting fixed-effects regressions using 
five-year averages in Table 1. Column 1 presents our baseline specification in-
cluding only the basic Solow model variables. The results are predominantly in 
line with the theoretical model predictions suggesting that the Solow model fits 
well for the African economies' dataset employed. The lagged dependent vari-
able has a positive and highly significant coefficient of 0.868. Our estimate is 
close to other findings of Solow growth regressions where African countries 
are explicitly included, for example, Hoeffler (2002). 
14 As expected, the invest-
ment variable is positive and highly significant. Contrary to the theory, the esti-
mate for population growth is positive, albeit, not significant and relatively small 
in size. Finally, regarding the within R-squared (which is at 0.75), we find that 
the regressors explain a high portion of the within country variation in GDP 
per capita growth -meaning that the model fits relatively well. 
In the next step, we extend our model by including the variables of principle inter-
est in Column 2. Namely, the specification includes the terms-of-trade growth rate of 
African countries, FDI flows from China and the ROW, the presence of Chinese eco-
nomic cooperation projects, aid flows from the ROW as well as total imports from 
and total exports to China and the ROW, respectively. By including these additional 
variables, we lose 18 observations due to missing data for these measures. Neverthe-
less, the data loss is small, the sign and significance levels of the main controls do not 
change much and the model fit increases to 0.85 for the within R-squared. </p>

<p>14. In order to assess the effect of the lagged GDP per capita variable on GDP per capita growth, we have 
to correct the estimated coefficient by subtracting 1 and obtain -0.132. In a corresponding fixed-effects 
regression, Hoeffler (2002, p. 147) finds a coefficient which is equal to -0.230. The difference in mag-
nitude is likely to be due to the fact that her study includes 85 developing countries including also a set 
of non-African countries. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Both estimates for FDI have a positive sign while those for foreign aid from 
the ROW and Chinese economic cooperation have a negative sign. Yet all four 
coefficients are insignificant indicating that these factors do not play a big role 
in explaining the within variation of African countries growth rates. Turning 
towards the trade measures, we find effects that matter for economic growth. 
While the coefficient of Africa's total exports to China is positive but insignifi-
cant, total imports from China have a significant and negative impact on growth 
rates. At the same time, we analyse the trade relations with the ROW. The effects 
are somehow contrary to those with China. Again, the exports' estimate has a 
positive sign and the imports' coefficient has a negative sign, but the statistical 
significance has changed. Total African exports to the ROW are significant 
whereas total imports from the ROW are insignificant indicating that exports to 
the ROW might foster economic growth in Africa. 
15 For the moment, however, 
these results should be treated as correlations rather than causations. 
In Column 3 we include further variables to control for macroeconomic distor-
tions as well as for the occurrence and intensity of conflicts. The estimates of the 
two measures enter with the expected negative sign in our specification, but they 
are statistically insignificant. Most notably regarding this regression, the outcome 
for the other estimates -in particular those for our variables of principle interest -
are not affected by including the inflation rate and the number of battle deaths 
although we lose four further observations. 
Finding evidence for potential growth effects related to our trade measures, we 
next differentiate between resource and non-resource trade (Column 4). We 
replace the four total trade variables by eight disaggregated imports/exports var-
iables for resource and non-resource trade. Only one of the eight coefficients is 
statistically significant indicating a correlation with economic growth, that is, 
non-resource imports from China which has a negative sign. The negative corre-
lation between total imports from China and economic growth across Africa, as 
shown in Columns 2 and 3, seems to arise from imports in non-resource sectors. 
Given the dominance of non-resource goods in total imports from China (97 per-
cent in 2012), this result is hardly surprising. Still it points to potential displace-
ment effects of African firms by their Chinese competitors. Though the findings 
in Columns 2 and 3 indicate a significant positive effect of total exports to the 
ROW, the disaggregated results for resource and non-resource exports to the 
ROW are not significant. 
The terms-of-trade growth's estimate is positive and significant at the five per-
cent level (or better), indicating that African exporters of natural resources have 
benefited from higher world market prices for their export products. This out-
come is in line with the results of Zafar (2007) who showed that demand from </p>

<p>15. T-tests confirm that each flow from China is significantly different from the corresponding flow from 
the ROW. This applies to all other regressions as well. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>China has contributed considerably to the increase in prices of raw materials, par-
ticularly for oil and metals from Africa, which then led to an increase in the 
terms-of-trade. This result is supported by Farooki and Kaplinsky (2013), who 
also analysed the (positive) impact of China on various commodity prices. At 
the same time, the improvements in the terms-of-trade of African countries could 
also arise from lower import prices, for example, from low-cost Chinese 
manufactured goods, as imports of these goods increased significantly over the 
last 15 years. What matters is the positive correlation of changes in the terms-
of-trade and economic growth in African countries. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>To analyse the terms-of-trade effects in more detail, we computed interaction 
terms, that is, we multiply changes in the terms-of-trade with all respective trade 
variables, to examine non-linear effects. While most interaction terms, whether at 
an aggregated or disaggregated level are not significant, two exceptions stand 
out: the interaction terms with total exports to China and resource exports to 
China, respectively, which are positive and highly significant at the one percent 
level (Columns 5 and 6). This outcome is robust to including all respective inter-
action terms at the same time (not reported) and indicates that exporting natural 
resources to China indeed is associated with higher growth rates. But this result 
shows up either directly through changes in the terms-of-trade or indirectly 
through the interaction term. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>System-GMM Results Next, we replicate all six specifications using (two-step) 
system GMM regressions in order to address endogeneity concerns (and the bias 
due to the inclusion of the lagged dependent variable). In these regressions we 
treat the lagged dependent variable, investment, population growth, inflation, 
all four total import and export variables, all non-resource import and export var-
iables, as well as FDI and aid from the ROW as endogenous. To reduce the num-
ber of endogenous variables (and thus the number of instruments used), we set 
changes in the terms-of-trade, battle deaths, and all natural resource export vari-
ables as exogenous. We assume that African countries are too small to have an 
impact on world market prices (that is, their terms-of-trade) and that conflicts 
mainly have an impact on economic growth but not vice versa. Yet switching 
the status of both variables from exogenous to endogenous hardly affects the 
results. Natural resource exports are mainly driven by the fact whether a country 
has natural resource endowments or not. Reverse causality is less of an issue in 
this case. Again, the main results are not affected by declaring all trade variables </p>

<p>16. It is beyond the scope of this paper to analyze the impact of China on prices of manufacturing goods 
and raw materials in detail. See Section 4.3 for a discussion of the limitations of our approach. 
17. Columns 5 and 6 are our preferred model specifications. As they include all controls, the various aggre-
gated and disaggregated trade variables and the two interaction terms. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>as endogenous. 
18 We also treat Chinese aid and FDI to Africa as exogenous. As 
pointed out by Kolstad and Wiig (2011), Chinese FDI to Africa is not attracted 
by GDP as soon as South Africa is excluded from the sample. Predominately, 
Chinese FDI (and aid) is concentrated in African countries with large resource 
endowments, which is exogenous. 
Using a large number of instruments may overfit endogenous variables and 
may weaken the Hansen J-test of the instruments' joint validity. To keep the 
number of instruments at a minimum, we use the collapse option in <rs id="software-1" type="software">STATA</rs> in 
all regressions (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Roodman</rs>, 2009).  19 This ensures that the number of instruments 
is always well below the number of countries. Overall, the results, reported in 
Table 2, are broadly in line with the fixed-effects results. The lagged dependent 
variable is always significant at the one percent level. Depending on the model 
specification, the estimated coefficient is slightly above or below one, implying 
no strong evidence for convergence in sub-Saharan African countries. This find-
ing is in line with the results of McCoskey (2002), who also found no conver-
gence for economic growth in sub-Saharan Africa, although smaller 
"convergence clubs" do exist. 
In five out of six model specifications, investment has a positive and signifi-
cant impact on economic growth. In contrast to the fixed effects results, total 
African exports to the ROW are not significant. Importantly, total imports from 
China and non-resource imports from China have -as before -a negative and 
significant impact on growth. This implies that we do observe displacement 
effects of African products by Chinese imports, even if we control for endogeneity. 
While changes in the terms-of-trade are no longer positively associated with growth 
(apart from one model specification), both interaction terms with terms-of-trade 
growth are positive and significant at the five or ten percent level. This result under-
lines the importance of changes in the terms-of-trade with respect to economic 
growth when looking at African exports of natural resources to China. 
The test statistics for the system GMM estimator (Hansen J-test) indicate that 
the instruments used are valid. However, we do have econometric problems 
regarding autocorrelation. The system GMM estimator requires high first-order 
but no second-order autocorrelation. While the p-values for the AR(2) indicate 
that, indeed, we do not have second-order autocorrelation, the corresponding 
p-values for the AR(1) show that we cannot reject the null hypothesis, in three 
out of six model specifications, though the p-values are only slightly above 
0.10 in two model specifications. These results thus have to be viewed with 
caution. Still, all test statistics for our preferred model specifications (Columns 
5 and 6) indicate that the estimations are valid. </p>

<p>18. All non-reported results can be obtained from the authors upon request. 
19. In all system GMM regressions, we use the Windmeijer (2005) finite-sample correction to the reported 
standard errors in the two-step estimation. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>China's Impact on African Economic Growth, Baseline Regressions, Fixed Effects and Five-year Averages </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Lagged Dep. Var. </p>

<p>0.868 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(16.34) 0.747 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(9.495) </p>

<p>0.735 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(10.54) </p>

<p>0.756 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.09) </p>

<p>0.755 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(10.69) </p>

<p>0.785 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.51) </p>

<p>ln Investment </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.239) 0.170 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.235) </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.613) </p>

<p>0.135 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.473) </p>

<p>0.173 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.249) </p>

<p>0.159 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.243) </p>

<p>ln Population Growth </p>

<p>0.056 (0.842) </p>

<p>0.044 (0.477) </p>

<p>-0.052 (-0.619) </p>

<p>-0.101 (-1.158) </p>

<p>-0.051 (-0.622) </p>

<p>-0.074 (-0.847) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>0.205 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.361) </p>

<p>0.208 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.257) </p>

<p>0.176 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.322) </p>

<p>0.233 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.588) </p>

<p>0.295 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(2.935) </p>

<p>ln FDI China </p>

<p>0.0017 (0.428) </p>

<p>0.0016 (0.363) </p>

<p>0.0014 (0.285) </p>

<p>0.0010 (0.268) </p>

<p>0.0019 (0.541) </p>

<p>ln FDI ROW </p>

<p>0.0001 (0.00841) </p>

<p>-0.005 (-0.326) </p>

<p>-0.0103 (-0.554) </p>

<p>-0.0040 (-0.271) </p>

<p>0.0020 (0.131) </p>

<p>ln Aid China </p>

<p>-0.0254 (-0.803) </p>

<p>-0.0329 (-1.179) </p>

<p>-0.0269 (-0.875) </p>

<p>-0.0278 (-1.141) </p>

<p>-0.0175 (-0.705) </p>

<p>ln Aid ROW </p>

<p>-0.0689 (-1.574) </p>

<p>-0.0572 (-1.291) </p>

<p>-0.0703 (-1.243) </p>

<p>-0.0446 (-1.190) </p>

<p>-0.0437 (-1.127) </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0170 (1.476) </p>

<p>0.0171 (1.483) </p>

<p>0.0115 (1.243) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from </p>

<p>-0.0751 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.376) </p>

<p>-0.0707 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.186) </p>

<p>-0.0674 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.311) </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to ROW </p>

<p>0.102 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.013) </p>

<p>0.0908 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.180) </p>

<p>0.0658 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(2.009) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0091 (-0.217) </p>

<p>-0.0116 (-0.260) </p>

<p>0.0081 (0.197) </p>

<p>ln Inflation </p>

<p>-0.0018 (-0.0870) </p>

<p>-0.0077 (-0.341) </p>

<p>0.0034 (0.191) </p>

<p>0.0018 (0.0981) </p>

<p>ln Battle Deaths </p>

<p>-0.0043 (-1.135) </p>

<p>-0.0037 (-0.828) </p>

<p>-0.00353 (-1.111) </p>

<p>-0.0027 (-0.845) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0627 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.526) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0061 (0.785) </p>

<p>0.0072 (1.204) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports from China </p>

<p>-0.0612 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.616) </p>

<p>-0.0547 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.407) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0051 (0.658) </p>

<p>0.0025 (0.404) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from China </p>

<p>0.00061 (0.0478) </p>

<p>-0.0091 (-0.723) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0167 (-0.552) </p>

<p>-0.0192 (-0.652) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports from ROW </p>

<p>0.0498 (0.777) </p>

<p>0.0375 (0.718) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to ROW </p>

<p>0.0082 (0.526) </p>

<p>0.0090 (0.537) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0322 (-1.464) </p>

<p>-0.0166 (-0.761) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Res. Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0557 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.000) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>169 </p>

<p>151 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 1. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>R-squared (within) </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.84 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions include country-and period-specific dummies. t-values 
obtained from (cluster-)robust standard errors in parentheses. *significant at the 10% </p>

<p>level; **significant at the 5% level; ***significant at the 1% level. </p>

<p>Table 2 </p>

<p>China's Impact on African Economic Growth, System GMM and Five-year Averages </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Lagged Dep. Var. </p>

<p>1.060 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(18.22) 1.015 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(13.18) 0.964 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(12.01) 0.988 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(6.657) </p>

<p>0.960 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.27) </p>

<p>0.955 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(5.838) </p>

<p>ln Investment </p>

<p>0.313 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.048) 
0.101 (0.841) </p>

<p>0.236 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(1.995) </p>

<p>0.230 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.412) </p>

<p>0.268 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.563) </p>

<p>0.217 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.440) </p>

<p>ln Population Growth </p>

<p>0.148 (0.876) </p>

<p>-0.129 (-1.070) </p>

<p>0.010 (0.0738) </p>

<p>0.022 (0.0915) </p>

<p>-0.032 (-0.256) </p>

<p>-0.095 (-0.534) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>0.089 (1.039) </p>

<p>0.050 (0.635) </p>

<p>0.018 (0.144) </p>

<p>0.151 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(1.691) 
0.124 (1.064) </p>

<p>ln FDI China </p>

<p>0.0603 (1.172) </p>

<p>0.0347 (0.716) </p>

<p>0.0009 (0.0264) </p>

<p>0.0134 (0.425) </p>

<p>0.0144 (0.402) </p>

<p>ln FDI ROW </p>

<p>-0.0508 (-0.783) -0.0682 (-1.430) -0.0872 (-0.957) </p>

<p>-0.0666 (-1.099) </p>

<p>-0.0636 (-0.618) </p>

<p>ln Aid China </p>

<p>0.0086 (0.904) 
-0.0004 (-0.0250) 0.0020 (0.297) </p>

<p>0.0030 (0.289) </p>

<p>0.0037 (0.427) </p>

<p>ln Aid ROW </p>

<p>0.0361 (1.569) </p>

<p>0.0255 (1.614) </p>

<p>0.0330 (1.157) </p>

<p>0.0047 (0.301) </p>

<p>0.0222 (1.063) </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0123 (0.719) </p>

<p>0.0069 (0.601) </p>

<p>-0.0005 (-0.0389) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from China </p>

<p>-0.162 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.323) </p>

<p>-0.102 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.745) </p>

<p>-0.0315 (-0.557) </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0677 (-0.718) </p>

<p>0.0163 (0.209) </p>

<p>-0.0372 (-0.460) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from ROW </p>

<p>0.119 (1.553) </p>

<p>0.0467 (0.698) </p>

<p>-0.0087 (-0.158) </p>

<p>ln Inflation </p>

<p>-0.0125 (-0.379) -0.0243 (-0.700) </p>

<p>-0.0009 (-0.0280) -0.0463 (-1.386) </p>

<p>ln Battle Deaths </p>

<p>-0.0037 (-0.586) </p>

<p>0.0035 (0.252) </p>

<p>-0.0071 (-0.978) </p>

<p>-0.0015 (-0.0971) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.111 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.119) </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 2. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to China 
ln Non-resource Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0101 (0.285) </p>

<p>-0.0081 (-0.215) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports from China </p>

<p>-0.130 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.019) </p>

<p>-0.0937 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.723) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0020 (0.0964) </p>

<p>0.0074 (0.316) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from China </p>

<p>0.0145 (0.620) </p>

<p>0.0066 (0.286) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0120 (-0.195) </p>

<p>-0.0171 (-0.273) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports from ROW </p>

<p>0.173 (1.140) </p>

<p>0.147 (1.223) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to ROW </p>

<p>0.0020 (0.0889) </p>

<p>-0.0083 (-0.302) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0323 (-0.729) </p>

<p>-0.0293 (-0.595) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.0383 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Res. Exp. to China </p>

<p>(1.814) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>169 </p>

<p>151 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>147 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>Instruments </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>AR (1), p-value </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.09 </p>

<p>AR (2), p-value </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>Hansen J-test, </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions include country-and period-specific dummies. We always use the two-step system GMM with Windmeijer's (2005)   finite sample correction. t-</p>

<p>values reported in parentheses The p-values </p>

<p>reported for AR(1) and AR(2) refer to 
first-and second-order autocorrelated disturbances in the </p>

<p>first differences equations. </p>

<p>*significant at the 10% level; 
**significant at the 5% level; 
***significant at the 1% level. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>By using the system GMM technique, we can calculate the size of the impact 
of our variables of principal interest on economic growth. For example, an 
increase in the volume of non-resource imports from China divided by total 
GDP (Table 2, Column 6) by one percent is associated with a decrease in GDP 
per capita growth of 0.1 percent over a period of five years across countries. 
The quantitative effect of importing more non-resource goods from China on 
economic growth is thus modest but by no means negligible. 
Our results for a negative impact of non-resource imports from China are at 
odds with those reported by Baliamoune-Lutz (2011) who found a positive 
impact of imports from China on African growth. We believe that this can be 
partly explained by the fact that Baliamoune-Lutz (2011) does not distinguish be-
tween resource and non-resource goods. At the same time we use a longer period 
of time (1991-2010 instead of 1995-2008) and a different methodology. On the 
other hand, our results for displacement effects are more in line with those of 
Giovannetti and Sanfilippo (2009). Yet they concentrate on displacement effects 
for African exports in third markets but do not investigate these effects in African 
countries' domestic markets. 
For the growth effects of foreign investment, we cannot confirm the positive 
effects found by Whalley and Weisbrod (2012). Again, this can be explained 
by the different methodologies employed. Since they use Solow growth account-
ing methods to analyse the impact of Chinese FDI on African economic growth, 
they are more likely to investigate (and find evidence for) the short-run growth 
impact of Chinese investment. Also, their methodology allows them to account 
for the impact of even relatively small changes in FDI and its impact on eco-
nomic growth. </p>

<p>4.2. Robustness Checks </p>

<p>In order to examine the robustness of the obtained results, we run numerous addi-
tional regressions. In terms of the methodology, we prefer to present the results for 
the fixed-effects estimator only. In fact, we have tested the validity of the system 
GMM estimator in numerous additional regressions. Using different model spec-
ifications, different lag structures, taking different time periods or annual aver-
ages, the test statistics never ensure a proper specification in all six models at 
the same time. Partly, this is due to the relatively small number of countries as 
well as the short time period. While the results for the principle variables of inter-
est are not much affected, the fixed-effects model seems to be more robust than the 
GMM estimator. Still, the fixed-effects estimator does not control for the potential 
endogeneity of some of the explanatory variables. But since the GMM estima-
tions support the basic outcome for the various trade variables, we are still con-
vinced that endogeneity issues are not a major problem and that our findings 
can be viewed as causal effects as well. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>China's Impact on African Economic Growth, Sample Variations, Fixed Effects and Five-year Averages </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>Total Africa </p>

<p>Total Africa </p>

<p>Excl. Islands </p>

<p>Excl. Islands </p>

<p>Excl. South Africa </p>

<p>Excl. South Africa </p>

<p>Lagged Dep. Var. </p>

<p>0.764 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.40) </p>

<p>0.792 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(12.31) </p>

<p>0.726 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(10.26) </p>

<p>0.756 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.76) </p>

<p>0.755 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(10.67) </p>

<p>0.785 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(11.30) </p>

<p>ln Investment </p>

<p>0.173 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.321) </p>

<p>0.158 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.377) </p>

<p>0.167 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.069) </p>

<p>0.153 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(2.986) </p>

<p>0.173 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.213) </p>

<p>0.160 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.177) </p>

<p>ln Population Growth </p>

<p>-0.075 (-1.020) </p>

<p>-0.091 (-1.166) </p>

<p>-0.002 (-0.0242) </p>

<p>-0.023 (-0.251) </p>

<p>-0.050 (-0.583) </p>

<p>-0.075 (-0.812) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>0.228 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.608) </p>

<p>0.288 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(2.890) </p>

<p>0.240 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.520) </p>

<p>0.310 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.039) </p>

<p>0.233 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.582) </p>

<p>0.295 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(2.937) </p>

<p>ln FDI China </p>

<p>0.0007 (0.220) </p>

<p>0.0013 (0.448) </p>

<p>0.0023 (0.586) </p>

<p>0.0030 (0.746) </p>

<p>0.0010 (0.264) </p>

<p>0.0020 (0.546) </p>

<p>ln FDI ROW </p>

<p>-0.0035 (-0.251) </p>

<p>0.0021 (0.137) </p>

<p>-0.0060 (-0.371) </p>

<p>-0.0020 (-0.113) </p>

<p>-0.0039 (-0.261) </p>

<p>0.0018 (0.111) </p>

<p>ln Aid China </p>

<p>-0.0252 (-1.132) </p>

<p>-0.0164 (-0.720) </p>

<p>-0.0243 (-1.066) </p>

<p>-0.0139 (-0.588) </p>

<p>-0.0278 (-1.140) </p>

<p>-0.0174 (-0.700) </p>

<p>ln Aid ROW </p>

<p>-0.0374 (-1.093) </p>

<p>-0.0356 (-1.017) </p>

<p>-0.0578 (-1.302) </p>

<p>-0.0592 (-1.287) </p>

<p>-0.0445 (-1.188) </p>

<p>-0.0438 (-1.125) </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to China </p>

<p>0.0097 (1.139) </p>

<p>0.0147 (1.455) </p>

<p>0.0115 (1.242) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from 
China </p>

<p>-0.0652 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.295) </p>

<p>-0.0785 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.327) </p>

<p>-0.0673 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.294) </p>

<p>ln Total Exports to ROW </p>

<p>0.0646 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(2.011) </p>

<p>0.0672 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(1.905) </p>

<p>0.0658 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(2.006) </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from 
ROW </p>

<p>0.0017 (0.0442) </p>

<p>0.0173 (0.364) </p>

<p>0.0081 (0.196) </p>

<p>ln Inflation </p>

<p>0.0039 (0.224) </p>

<p>0.0024 (0.135) </p>

<p>0.0054 (0.294) </p>

<p>0.0039 (0.209) </p>

<p>0.0034 (0.188) </p>

<p>0.0018 (0.0993) </p>

<p>ln Battle Deaths </p>

<p>-0.0033 (-1.067) </p>

<p>-0.0023 (-0.743) </p>

<p>-0.0026 (-0.748) </p>

<p>-0.0015 (-0.432) </p>

<p>-0.0035 (-1.108) </p>

<p>-0.0027 (-0.845) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0633 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.452) </p>

<p>0.0635 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.511) </p>

<p>0.0627 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.521) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to China </p>

<p>0.0055 (0.992) </p>

<p>0.0086 (1.408) </p>

<p>0.0072 (1.149) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>-0.0510 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.414) </p>

<p>-0.0657 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.330) </p>

<p>-0.0546 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.400) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports 
to China </p>

<p>0.0019 (0.347) </p>

<p>0.0066 (0.919) </p>

<p>0.0025 (0.404) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>-0.0105 (-0.822) </p>

<p>-0.0134 (-1.015) </p>

<p>-0.0093 (-0.703) </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 3. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>Total Africa </p>

<p>Total Africa </p>

<p>Excl. Islands </p>

<p>Excl. Islands </p>

<p>Excl. South Africa </p>

<p>Excl. South Africa </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0177 (-0.677) </p>

<p>-0.0207 (-0.689) </p>

<p>-0.0192 (-0.654) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>0.0360 (0.694) </p>

<p>0.0559 (0.877) </p>

<p>0.0374 (0.715) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports 
to ROW </p>

<p>0.0091 (0.555) </p>

<p>0.0086 (0.502) </p>

<p>0.0091 (0.536) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0192 (-0.951) </p>

<p>-0.0144 (-0.618) </p>

<p>-0.0166 (-0.761) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Res. Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0555 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.003) </p>

<p>0.0546 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.089) </p>

<p>0.0558 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(2.985) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>165 </p>

<p>165 </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>144 </p>

<p>144 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>49 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>42 </p>

<p>R-squared (within) </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions include country and period-specific dummies. t-values </p>

<p>obtained from (cluster-)robust standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p>*significant at the 10% level; 
**significant at the 5% level; 
***significant at the 1% level. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>In the interest of saving space, we restrict the presentation of our extensions 
and robustness checks to four dimensions: different country samples, different 
period averages, lagged effects of aid and FDI as well as country heterogeneity 
in terms of institutional quality. We begin with the sample variations, presented 
in Table 3. First, we extend our sample and add six North African countries (Col-
umns 1 and 2). 
20 This allows us to examine whether our results are sensitive to a 
larger sample size that includes basically all African countries for which we have 
data. Although North African countries differ from those below the Sahara, they, 
too, have considerable trade and investment links with China. 
In Columns 3 and 4, we refer to the initial sub-Saharan Africa sample again 
but exclude all four African islands. It can be argued that small islands, such 
as Cape Verde, the Comoros or Mauritius, differ from the sub-Saharan African 
mainland. Arguably, this may apply to Madagascar as well. Historically, Mada-
gascar and Mauritius have had a large Asian diaspora which may influence the 
effect of Chinese economic interactions in the present. What is more, the island 
economies' trade composition is very different from mainland Africa. For exam-
ple, Mauritius has higher trade/GDP levels and exports much more manufactured 
goods than the rest of sub-Saharan Africa (Subramanian, 2013). 
Finally, in Columns 5 and 6 we exclude South Africa from our sub-Saharan 
Africa sample. As explained in Section 2, China's motives for trade and invest-
ment in South Africa differ compared to other Chinese trading partners and 
investment destinations in Africa. Partly due to higher income levels, South Africa 
is a larger market for Chinese exports of manufacturing products. This may affect 
our results, in particular the trade variables. Moreover, Chinese decisions to invest 
in South Africa are also more likely to be driven by horizontal motives in contrast 
to other African countries. 
To facilitate a comparison of the results, Columns 1, 3 and 5 (2, 4 and 6) in 
Table 3 refer to our preferred specifications, that is, Column 5 (6) in Table 1. 
The sample variations in Table 3 clearly confirm our baseline findings as we 
are able to almost replicate the results. Throughout the six regressions we have 
the same qualitative outcome for all significant measures. This applies to the var-
ious trade variables as well as the two interaction terms with changes in the 
terms-of-trade. Furthermore, not only are the same variables significant at a com-
parable level, the magnitude of these estimates is also similar. 
Turning towards the robustness checks with different period averages, we 
re-run the regressions for our two preferred specifications, using four-year aver-
ages. While this procedure may not fully control for business cycle effects, it allows 
us to exploit more variation in the data over time (Columns 1 and 2 in Table 4). 
Additionally, the larger T allows us to conduct two additional robustness checks with 
variables that are only available for a shorter time period. First, we lag all FDI and aid </p>

<p>20. The included North African countries are Algeria, Djibouti, Egypt, Libya, Morocco, and Tunisia. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>China's Impact on African Economic Growth, Fixed Effects and Four-year Averages </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>Baseline Specifications </p>

<p>Lagged FDI and Aid </p>

<p>Institutional Quality </p>

<p>Lagged Dep. Var. </p>

<p>0.827 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(25.32) </p>

<p>0.852 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(30.56) </p>

<p>0.776 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(16.02) </p>

<p>0.770 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(17.14) </p>

<p>0.692 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(25.82) </p>

<p>0.724 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(32.00) </p>

<p>ln Investment </p>

<p>0.125 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.763) </p>

<p>0.119 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(4.314) </p>

<p>0.0635 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.360) </p>

<p>0.0665 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.540) </p>

<p>0.0542 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.024) </p>

<p>0.0410 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(1.763) </p>

<p>ln Population Growth </p>

<p>0.00854 (0.121) </p>

<p>-0.014 (-0.168) </p>

<p>0.0948 (1.606) </p>

<p>0.103 (1.659) </p>

<p>-0.0976 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.707) 
-0.0832 (-1.284) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>0.209 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.190) </p>

<p>0.256 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.177) </p>

<p>0.174 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(4.083) </p>

<p>0.205 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.698) </p>

<p>0.194 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.375) </p>

<p>0.187 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.503) </p>

<p>ln FDI China </p>

<p>0.0033 (1.256) </p>

<p>0.0055 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(1.795) 
-0.0004 (-0.124) </p>

<p>0.0001 (0.0395) </p>

<p>0.0037 (1.378) </p>

<p>-0.0165 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.065) </p>

<p>ln FDI ROW </p>

<p>0.0065 (0.719) </p>

<p>0.008 (0.832) </p>

<p>0.004 (0.626) </p>

<p>0.0075 (1.116) </p>

<p>0.0015 (0.217) </p>

<p>0.0321 (1.598) </p>

<p>ln Aid China </p>

<p>-0.0137 (-1.080) </p>

<p>-0.0189 (-1.230) </p>

<p>0.0303 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(1.811) 
0.0301 (1.549) </p>

<p>-0.0036 (-0.130) </p>

<p>-0.0008 (-0.0769) </p>

<p>ln Aid ROW </p>

<p>-0.0238 (-0.957) </p>

<p>-0.0217 (-0.900) </p>

<p>-0.0015 (-0.104) </p>

<p>-0.0153 (-0.896) </p>

<p>-0.0790 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.847) 
-0.0034 (-0.200) </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0104 (1.137) </p>

<p>0.0018 (0.314) </p>

<p>ln Total Imp. from China </p>

<p>-0.0556 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(-2.975) </p>

<p>-0.0553 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.892) </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to ROW </p>

<p>0.0246 (0.807) </p>

<p>-0.0165 (-0.550) </p>

<p>ln Total Imp. from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0168 (-0.520) </p>

<p>-0.0578 (-1.483) </p>

<p>ln Inflation </p>

<p>-0.0258 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.421) </p>

<p>-0.0251 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.477) -0.0336 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.451) </p>

<p>-0.0289 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.085) </p>

<p>-0.023 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(-3.016) </p>

<p>-0.0161 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.092) </p>

<p>ln Battle Deaths </p>

<p>-0.0019 (-0.601) </p>

<p>-0.0034 (-1.380) 
-0.0004 (-0.132) -0.00017 (-0.0391) </p>

<p>0.00001 (0.0293) </p>

<p>0.0007 (0.202) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Total Exp. to China </p>

<p>0.0662 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(4.306) </p>

<p>0.0496 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.522) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to China </p>

<p>-0.0005 (-0.135) </p>

<p>0.0049 (1.035) </p>

<p>0.0009 (0.210) </p>

<p>-0.0004 (-0.0878) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>-0.0431 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.310) </p>

<p>-0.0627 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(-2.094) -0.084 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(-2.743) </p>

<p>-0.076 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(-2.734) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports 
to China </p>

<p>0.0068 (1.093) </p>

<p>-0.0034 (-0.691) </p>

<p>-0.0013 (-0.343) </p>

<p>0.0002 (0.0460) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>-0.0109 (-1.168) </p>

<p>-0.0085 (-1.167) </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(-1.740) 
-0.0059 (-1.016) </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 4. </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>Dependent Variable: ln GDP per capita </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Independent Variables </p>

<p>Baseline Specifications </p>

<p>Lagged FDI and Aid </p>

<p>Institutional Quality </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0187 (-0.689) </p>

<p>-0.0241 (-1.133) </p>

<p>0.0042 (0.198) </p>

<p>0.001 (0.0482) </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>0.0357 (0.665) </p>

<p>-0.0036 (-0.0793) </p>

<p>0.0313 (0.711) </p>

<p>0.0361 (0.797) </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports 
to ROW </p>

<p>-0.0183 (-1.377) </p>

<p>-0.0128 (-1.259) </p>

<p>-0.0103 (-1.415) </p>

<p>-0.0143 (-1.527) </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>-0.0218 (-1.573) </p>

<p>-0.0128 (-1.082) </p>

<p>-0.0105 (-1.033) </p>

<p>-0.0127 (-1.221) </p>

<p>Terms-of-Trade Growth </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0.0503 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(3.677) </p>

<p>0.0384 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.0387 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.0376 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>ln Res. Exp. to China </p>

<p>(3.654) </p>

<p>(3.749) </p>

<p>(3.785) </p>

<p>ln Rule of law </p>

<p>0.0502 (1.155) </p>

<p>0.147 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(5.310) </p>

<p>ln Rule of law </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Aid China </p>

<p>0.0017 (0.221) </p>

<p>ln Rule of law </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln Aid ROW </p>

<p>0.0266 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.098) </p>

<p>ln Rule of law </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Ln FDI China </p>

<p>0.0058 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(2.507) </p>

<p>ln Rule of law </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>ln FDI ROW </p>

<p>-0.0097 (-1.565) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>174 </p>

<p>174 </p>

<p>143 </p>

<p>143 </p>

<p>146 </p>

<p>146 </p>

<p>Countries </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>R-squared (within) </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>0.94 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions include country-and period-specific dummies. t </p>

<p>values obtained from (cluster-)robust standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p>*significant at the 10% level; 
**significant at the 5% level; 
***significant at the 1% level. In Columns 3 and 4 the variables ln FDI China, ln FDI ROW, ln Aid China </p>

<p>and ln Aid ROW 
are lagged by one period. Institutional </p>

<p>quality in Columns 5 and 6 is proxied by the rule of law. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>variables by one period (Columns 3 and 4). 
21 It could be argued that both foreign 
investment and aid could have growth effects but that these effects occur with a time 
lag, for example, countries may need some time to benefit from technology spillovers 
or improvements in infrastructure, institutions or education. Second, we explore the 
heterogeneity of African countries by including interaction terms. While there are 
many possible variables for interaction terms, we focus on the interaction of the fun-
damental institutional indicator (rule of law) with all four FDI and aid variables (Col-
umns 5 and 6). </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>As with sample variations, using four-year averages provide clear support for 
our main results (Columns 1 and 2 in Table 4). Sign and significance levels of all 
control variables are not affected much. The exception is the inflation rate, which 
is now negatively associated with growth rates. Regarding the variables of prin-
ciple interest, we still find displacements effects for (non-resource) imports from 
China. Yet, total exports to the rest of the world are no longer positively corre-
lated with growth. In contrast to the previous section, we find FDI inflows from 
China to be positive and significant at the ten percent level when including dis-
aggregated trade variables (Column 2). Yet this result is not robust if we use 
more aggregated trade variables or lagged FDI (Columns 1, 3 and 4). Once we 
lag all FDI and aid variables, we obtain a positive (and significant) coefficient 
for aid from China (Column 3), which is, however, not robust to including the 
disaggregated trade indicators (Column 4). Since the estimated coefficient just 
falls short of the conventional ten percent significance level, there is some evi-
dence that FDI from China could have positive growth effects but that it takes 
time to materialise. Lagging the aid variables indicates that aid from the ROW 
could be negatively associated with economic growth, but this outcome, again, 
is not robust to different model specifications. 
With regards to institutional quality, we find that countries with a stronger rule 
of law may benefit from aid from the ROW while countries with low levels of 
rule of law may be adversely affected (Column 5). 
23 These results support the 
effectiveness of Western aid conditional on strong institutions. Furthermore, Chi-
nese FDI benefits African countries with a stronger rule of law (Column 6). </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>This outcome is in accordance with the findings of Dort et al. (2014) that invest-
ment increases growth more in countries with high institutional quality. </p>

<p>21. As FDI and aid values are only available since 1991, including lags for FDI and aid in the baseline 
regressions with five-year averages would reduce our dataset to three periods and only 115 observa-
tions. The corresponding results would be less reliable. 
22. We tested numerous interaction terms of all three main variables (trade, FDI and aid) with various 
institutional indicators (corruption, government effectiveness, regulatory quality, and democracy). 
The coefficients of most interaction terms were either not significant or not robust to changes in the 
model specification. The exception is the interaction term with rule of law, which we display in Table 4. 
23. The net impact from aid from the ROW on growth is slightly positive (-0.079 + 0.0266*3.00 = 0.0008). 
24. Again, the net impact of Chinese FDI on growth is positive (0.0009). </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>4.3. Limitations </p>

<p>Due to our empirical approach and the topic at hand our analysis is restricted by 
certain limitations. Broadly, they fall into two main categories. First of all, our 
modelling framework only accounts for the direct effects of trade, FDI and aid 
on growth. The indirect effects that arguably exist are much harder to quantify. 
Chinese trade, FDI and aid can very well have an impact on African capital for-
mation (investment) and/or the terms-of-trade of African economies which in 
turn can affect economic growth rates. 
China's economic activity is often seen as having a large impact on world 
commodity prices which in turn can affect inflation and the terms-of-trade at 
the global level. These changes can have possibly large effects on other emerging 
and developing economies (Roache, 2012). For instance, Villoria (2009) finds 
that the economic rise of China has resulted in a decrease in world prices for 
manufacturing goods. In addition to rising commodity prices due to China's 
considerable demand for raw materials, this has had a positive impact on the 
terms-of-trade of African resource exporters (Kaplinsky, 2009). But even African 
countries that are not major exporters of raw materials haven been able to take 
advantage of lower prices of manufactured goods. 
With regards to indirect effects through investment, Chinese FDI and aid are 
seen as important sources of capital for African economies, and also trade can 
increase a country's capital stock. China is very active in infrastructure and facil-
ity construction and provides increasing foreign direct investment to Africa. One 
may argue that these efforts can improve the capital stock and hence domestic 
investment in African economies which in turn may improve GDP per capita 
growth rates. The empirical evidence on the relationship between FDI and 
domestic investment is mixed. Morrissey and Udomkerdmongkol (2012) find 
that FDI crowds out domestic investment whereas Al-Sadig (2012) shows that 
FDI stimulates private domestic investment in developing host economies. 
We check for potential indirect effects through investment and/or terms-of-
trade in two ways. First, we drop investment and terms-of-trade and related inter-
action variables (both separately as well as simultaneously) from the model and 
analyse whether our main results change. Second, we follow Baron and Kenny  (1986) and analyse whether the effects of Chinese trade, FDI and aid on African 
growth are mediated by domestic investment and terms-of-trade. 
25 Both exten-
sions confirm the robustness of the significant negative growth effects of (non-re-
source) imports from China, the positive terms-of-trade interaction effects with 
(resource) exports to China, and positive growth effects of exports to the ROW 
from our baseline regressions. In fact, dropping investment and/or terms-of-trade 
and related interaction terms lead to very small changes in the significance or </p>

<p>25. Due to space constraints, we do not display results for these extensions. </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>magnitude of the variables in question. In addition, the mediator analysis con-
firms that the significant effects from these variables are not intervened (medi-
ated) by investment or terms-of-trade. At the same time, we gain an additional 
result from the mediator analysis that exports to China are positively mediated 
by investment's effect on growth, i.e., revenues from rising exports to China 
increase capital in African economies which in turn can be invested to increase 
economic growth. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>A detailed assessment of whether China's effect on African growth is direct or 
indirect through variables such as investment and terms-of-trade is an important 
area for further research but beyond the scope of this paper. Although we do not 
account for the effects of trade, FDI and aid on investment and terms-of-trade, we 
did include interaction variables of terms-of-trade with our trade variables. These 
terms show how improved terms-of-trade, for various reasons that we cannot 
account for, enlarge the growth effects of total (resource) exports to China, that 
is, resource exports to China are positive for African growth, even more so if 
the country's terms-of-trade are favourable. 
The second major limitation of our approach concerns the time frame. In our 
analysis, we include a period of just 20 years, half of which has seen a major 
increase in China's economic activities and engagement in Africa. It could very 
well take a much longer period of time before changes in the volume, structure 
and pattern of African trade, FDI and aid due to China's economic rise will have 
a more profound impact on African economies. Such an investigation of the 
long-run effects would require data for at least another couple of decades. Still, 
our analysis, which refers more to short-to mid-run, can be highly useful when 
it comes to averting the potentially negative effects (for example, in non-resource 
imports) and to enlarge the positive impacts in exports of natural resources. </p>

<p>V. DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>In this paper we investigated how Chinese trade, FDI and aid in Africa affect 
African economic growth. Contrary to other empirical studies in this context, 
we examine the impact of the three main channels of China's activities simulta-
neously. Our empirical findings can be summarised as follows. Generally, FDI 
flows from China and the rest of the world, Chinese economic cooperation, 
and foreign aid from other countries seem to play no major role for African coun-
tries' economic development. Although we do find some positive effects of Chi-
nese economic corporation when using lagged aid flows, these results are not 
robust. Sino-African trade, however, has an important impact. Our results </p>

<p>26. In fact, dropping investment from the model also yields a positive significant growth effect of total ex-
ports to China, confirming the result of the mediator analysis. </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>indicate that African imports from China, particularly non-resource imports, 
have a negative impact on economic growth in Africa. This finding is robust 
to using different samples and period averages as well as an instrumental vari-
able approach. Although not robust in all specifications, African exports to the 
world (excluding China) are positively associated with growth in Africa. We 
also find that African economies that export natural resources benefit from 
China's rising demand for raw materials due to both positive changes in their 
terms-of-trade and increasing exports of natural resources to China, when using 
interaction terms. Finally, our results indicate that there is some heterogeneity 
in the country sample. African countries with a stronger rule of law benefit 
more from aid from the ROW and from Chinese FDI. 
In terms of policy implications, these results clearly demonstrate the opportunities 
and challenges that African countries are facing when dealing with a new partner like 
China. African exports of natural resources are an obvious example for both. The 
opportunities arise due to higher (total) export earnings of resource-rich African coun-
tries. These additional funds have to be spent well, for example, on development pur-
poses, such as improvements in infrastructure or education. The downside and thus 
the main challenge is to escape the resource curse that arises too often in African 
countries with weak institutions (Carmignani and Chowdhury, 2012). 
Likewise, African consumers benefit from low-cost imports of non-resource goods 
from China. This applies to African producers importing low-cost intermediate goods 
from China as well. Therefore, welfare levels of consumers rise and producers can be 
more competitive. In contrast, we find strong evidence for displacement effects, as 
African producers might not be able to compete with their Chinese counterparts. This 
applies in particular to specific labour-intensive manufactured goods, such as textiles, 
footwear or furniture, where African producers have had a considerable market share 
in local markets so far (Morrissey and Zgovu, 2011). While a temporary increase in 
trade protection levels (tariffs and non-tariff trade barriers) could allow African pro-
ducers to keep market shares, a suitable (long-run) policy option must be grounded 
on an increase in competitiveness levels. In this regard, African firms are far behind 
their Chinese competitors. These displacement effects have to be seen in perspective 
as Chinese firms dominate many sectors/product categories where there are no Afri-
can competitors. Still, the question arises whether China's rise on world markets may 
obstruct export opportunities for African firms in (other) labour-intensive products, 
partly by export diversification or by moving up the value chain. So far, the evidence 
is not that favourable for African countries, as China (and other Asian countries) may 
block that market segment (Kaplinsky and Morris, 2009a). 
In terms of foreign direct investment, many developing countries have 
benefited greatly from FDI, especially China. The insignificant results from our 
regressions concerning FDI from both China and the rest of the world may point 
to an insufficient FDI environment in African countries rather than a display of 
FDI not playing a role for African growth. So far, most foreign investment in </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Africa has been resource-seeking FDI with few linkages to other sectors. African 
governments should thus focus on attracting efficiency-seeking (or vertical) FDI 
by creating a better environment for the private sector. This could be achieved by 
providing a simpler and more transparent regulatory environment, building and 
upgrading infrastructure, enhancing educational levels and/or offering invest-
ment incentives, such as tax exemptions or the establishment of Special Eco-
nomic Zones that have worked in other developing countries, most notably 
China. African governments have to ensure that they harness the potentially pos-
itive effects of foreign investment. So far, Chinese investment is often isolated 
from the rest of the local economy. Improving linkages between foreign firms 
and the domestic economy is thus vital to improve the growth effects of foreign 
investment. This could improve technology spillovers to domestic firms. Similar to 
trade, African governments should target specific sectors that are important for eco-
nomic development and then direct foreign investment to these sectors. This could 
enhance productive capacity and domestic investment, boost local employment 
levels, and foster the integration of African firms into the global economy 
(UNCTAD, 2010). Importantly, a coherent regional integration policy and frame-
work would be highly important to both increase FDI flows and enhance the spillover 
effects. 
Although we could not find any significant growth effects of Chinese aid to 
Africa, it is nevertheless an important part of China's Africa Policy and its "pack-
age deals" to Africa. Chinese economic cooperation projects in Africa are 
steadily growing, particularly in the field of infrastructure, but its effects on 
African growth may still need some years to emerge. Although widely criticized 
by Western donors for its aid practices in African countries (with poor human 
rights and/or governance records), China's economic cooperation projects pro-
vide a viable alternative for many African countries. This implies that Western 
donors may have to adjust their aid policies in Africa to a growing Chinese pres-
ence on the continent. For African policymakers, on the other hand, it implies 
that they could be less dependent on Western aid and the conditions attached. 
No matter the source, in general the effect of aid on economic growth is contro-
versial and depends a great deal on how the host country utilizes it. 
Up to now, most African governments lack a clear and coherent strategy when 
dealing with a new partner such as China. Unfortunately, that implies that they 
are not taking full advantage of the opportunities that arise from China's activi-
ties in Africa. </p>



<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>





<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>





<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>





<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>APPENDIX </p>

<p>Table A.1. Definition of Variables and Data Sources </p>

<p>Variable 
Definition 
Source </p>

<p>GDP per capita 
Gross Domestic Product (GDP) per 
capita, const. US$ 2005 </p>

<p>World Bank (2014a) </p>

<p>Investment 
Gross capital formation, % of GDP World Bank (2014a) 
Population Growth 
Population growth rate in % 
World Bank (2014a) 
Terms-of-Trade Growth 
Changes in the terms-of-trade in %, 
based on an index 2000 = 100 </p>

<p>World Bank (2014a) </p>

<p>Battle Deaths 
Number of Battle Deaths 
PRIO (2009) for the years 1991-
2008; UCDP (2013) for the 
years 2009-2011 
Rule of Law 
Good Governance Indicator. Rule 
of law measures, among others, the 
quality of contract enforcement 
and the functioning of the police 
and the courts. Standardised 
indicator ranging from 0 to 100, 
with higher values corresponding to 
better outcomes. </p>

<p>World Bank (2014b) </p>

<p>Inflation 
GDP deflator, annual change in % 
World Bank (2014a) 
Aid ROW 
Total official development 
assistance (ODA) from the rest of 
the world (non-Chinese sources), 
% of GDP </p>

<p>World Bank (2014a) </p>

<p>Aid China 
Turnover on Chinese economic 
cooperation with foreign countries, 
% of GDP </p>

<p>NBS (2013) </p>

<p>FDI ROW 
Inflows of Foreign Direct 
Investment from the rest of the 
world (total FDI inflows less 
inflows of FDI from China), % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UNCTADstat (2014) </p>

<p>FDI China 
Inflows of FDI from China, 
measured as China's approved 
overseas investment flow and 
China's outward FDI flow, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>MOFTEC and MOFCOM (a): 
1991-2002; MOFCOM (b): 
2003-2011 </p>

<p>Total Exports to ROW 
Total exports to the ROW, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Total Exports to China 
Total exports to China, % of GDP 
UN Comtrade (2014) 
Total Imports from ROW Total imports from the ROW, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Total Imports from China Total imports from China, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Resource Exports to 
ROW </p>

<p>Total exports of natural resources to 
the ROW, % of GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Resource Exports to 
China </p>

<p>Total exports of natural resources to 
China, % of GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Resource Imports from 
ROW </p>

<p>Total imports of natural resources 
from the ROW, % of GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Resource Imports from 
China </p>

<p>Total imports of natural resources 
from China, % of GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>Table 0. (Continued) </p>

<p>Variable 
Definition 
Source </p>

<p>Non-resource Exports to 
ROW </p>

<p>Total exports minus natural 
resource exports to the ROW, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Non-resource Exports to 
China </p>

<p>Total exports minus natural 
resource exports to China, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Non-resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>Total imports minus natural 
resource imports from the ROW, % 
of GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Non-resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>Total imports minus natural 
resource imports from China, % of 
GDP </p>

<p>UN Comtrade (2014) </p>

<p>Table A.1 </p>

<p>APPENDIX </p>

<p>Table B.1. Descriptive Statistics </p>

<p>Variable 
Observations 
Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
Deviation 
Minimum 
Maximum </p>

<p>ln GDP per capita 
147 
6.42 
1.02 
4.82 
9.51 
ln Investment 
147 
2.91 
0.49 
1.56 
4.45 
ln Population Growth 
147 
-1.74 
0.24 
-2.75 
-1.23 
ln Inflation 
147 
2.19 
1.37 
-3.44 
8.86 
ln Battle Deaths 
147 
2.58 
3.52 
0 
10.64 
Terms-of-Trade Growth 
147 
0.01 
0.26 
-1.29 
0.65 
ln Aid ROW 
147 
2.07 
1.11 
-1.09 
4.09 
ln Aid China 
147 
-0.60 
1.44 
-4.95 
2.24 
ln FDI ROW 
147 
0.63 
1.51 
-4.42 
4.39 
ln FDI China 
147 
-4.68 
2.95 
-11.22 
0.33 
ln Total Exports to ROW 
147 
2.82 
0.84 
0.37 
4.25 
ln Total Exports to China 
147 
-1.75 
2.67 
-9.03 
3.37 
ln Total Imports from 
ROW </p>

<p>147 
3.10 
0.64 
1.41 
5.07 </p>

<p>ln Total Imports from 
China </p>

<p>147 
0.03 
1.27 
-2.95 
3.70 </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to 
ROW </p>

<p>147 
1.14 
2.04 
-4.01 
4.20 </p>

<p>ln Resource Exports to 
China </p>

<p>147 
-3.29 
3.76 
-10.94 
3.37 </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from 
ROW </p>

<p>147 
0.58 
1.13 
-2.83 
3.24 </p>

<p>ln Resource Imports from 
China </p>

<p>147 
-5.63 
2.16 
-10.94 
-1.56 </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to ROW </p>

<p>147 
2.04 
0.87 
-0.47 
3.77 </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Exports 
to China </p>

<p>147 
-3.77 
2.44 
-10.31 
0.88 </p>

<p>CHINA'S IMPACT ON AFRICA </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



<p>SUMMARY </p>

<p>This paper investigates the impact of Chinese activities in sub-Saharan African countries with respect to 
the growth performance of economies in that region. Using a Solow-type growth model and panel data </p>

<p>for the period 1991 to 2010, we find that African economies that export natural resources have benefited </p>

<p>from positive terms-of-trade effects. In addition, there is evidence for displacement effects of African 
firms due to competition from China. On the other hand, Chinese foreign investment and aid in Africa </p>

<p>does not appear to have a significant impact on African growth. </p>

<p>Table 0. (Continued) </p>

<p>Variable 
Observations 
Mean </p>

<p>Standard 
Deviation 
Minimum 
Maximum </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from ROW </p>

<p>147 
2.99 
0.62 
1.35 
4.93 </p>

<p>ln Non-resource Imports 
from China </p>

<p>147 
0.02 
1.27 
-2.95 
3.70 </p>

<p>ln Rule of Law 
146 
3.00 
0.99 
-0.04 
4.39 </p>

<p>Table B.1 </p>

<p>APPENDIX C: </p>

<p>Country Sample </p>

<p>Algeria, Angola, Benin, Botswana, Burkina Faso, Burundi, Cameroon, Cape Verde, Central African 
Republic, Chad, Comoros, Dem. Rep. of Congo, Rep. of Congo, Cote d'Ivoire, Djibouti, Egypt, 
Equatorial Guinea, Eritrea, Ethiopia, Gabon, Gambia, Ghana, Guinea, Guinea-Bissau, Kenya, 
Lesotho, Libya, Madagascar, Malawi, Mali, Mauritania, Mauritius, Morocco, Mozambique, 
Namibia, Niger, Nigeria, Rwanda, Senegal, Sierra Leone, South Africa, Sudan, Swaziland, Tanzania, 
Togo, Tunisia, Uganda, Zambia, Zimbabwe </p>

<p>MATTHIAS BUSSE/CEREN ERDOGAN/HENNING MÜHLEN </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. </p>



</text></tei>