<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10683-017-9548-x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Studies of experimental and betting markets have shown that markets are 
able to efficiently aggregate information dispersed over many traders. We study 
information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets using a novel information 
structure. Compared to previous studies, the information structure is more complex, 
allows for heterogeneity in information among traders-which provides insights 
into the way in which information is gradually disseminated in the market-and 
generates situations in which all traders hold identical beliefs over the traded assets' 
values, thus providing a harsh stress test for belief updating. We find little evidence 
for information aggregation and dissemination in early rounds. Nonetheless, after 
traders gain experience with the market mechanism and structure, prices converge 
to reveal the true state of the world. Elicited post-market beliefs reveal that markets 
are able to efficiently aggregate dispersed information even if individual traders 
remain uninformed, consistent with the marginal trader hypothesis. </p>

<p>The idea that markets can aggregate dispersed private information into prices is 
central to much of economic thinking. 
1 When some traders are fully informed about 
the true state of the world, competitive bidding will push prices to reflect the true 
state, thus revealing the information to uninformed traders. A more challenging case 
is when each trader only holds partial information about the true state. If traders 
understand how the different pieces of information affect behaviour, the movement 
of prices eventually reveals the information held by other traders. Furthermore, if 
traders continuously condition their market demands on their own information, then 
market prices should continuously move until no trader can learn any more from the 
prices. 
2 Naturally, whether equilibrium market prices fully reveal the true state 
depends on the information structure. Radner (1979) showed that prices converge to 
an equilibrium as if each trader openly and truthfully communicates his own private 
information. This result, however, requires that traders hold diverse or heteroge-
neous partial private information and that the true state is in the unique element 
within the intersect of at least two different private information. 
3 This analysis 
equates the states of the world with beliefs over the traded assets' possible 
valuations. It remains an open question, therefore, whether market prices are able to 
fully reveal the true state even when traders hold identical or homogeneous partial 
private information, in the sense that it induces the same beliefs over asset 
valuations. This paper studies the information aggregation properties of markets in a 
novel design that allows us to clearly distinguish between situations where traders 
hold homogeneous and heterogeneous partial private information about the true 
state of the world. 
Empirical studies suggest that the intricate process of information aggregation 
(e.g., learning about the information of others through price movements) postulated 
by theory often places too many demands on the abilities of the traders [see De- Bondt and Thaler (1985), Thaler (1988), Hirshleifer (2001) and Shleifer (2000)]. 
However, identifying 'who knows what' is often challenging in empirical market </p>

<p>1 The idea often builds upon the early discussions by Hayek (1945) and was subsequently development 
further by Grossman (1976). It is also the central theme of the ''efficient market hypothesis'' (Fama 1970). 
2 Alternatively, some traders could seek to learn more about the true event at a cost. However, Grossman  and Stiglitz (1980) challenged the notion that traders will be willing to incur such costs if market prices 
will eventual reveal what they learnt. 
3 For example, consider the state space f1; 2; 3; 4; 5; 6g, where the true state is 4. Suppose that trader A 
knows that the true state is in f1; 2; 3; 4g and trader B knows that the true state is in f4; 5; 6g. Combining 
both pieces of information through open communication, both traders will realise that the true state must 
be 4. Conversely, if trader B's partition is such that she knows the true state to be in f3; 4; 5g, then the 
combined information can only reveal that the true state is either 3 or 4. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>research. Controlled experimental environments complete the picture by studying 
market behaviour in a highly structured environment, where the experiment 
designer controls the information structure. Laboratory experiments study the 
general principles underpinning economic behavior with extraordinary control over 
independent variables, and generally generalise well to various field environments 
(Camerer 2015). Market experiments, in particular, yield similar results with student 
and businessmen populations (e.g., Porter and Smith 1994). 
In a study of information dissemination in experimental single-period markets, 
Plott and Sunder (1982) found that asset prices converge to fully reveal the true state 
even when only a subset of the traders had full information about the true state. </p>

<p>4   Markets where traders have partial information pose a greater challenge to 
successful convergence, as market prices have a double role of information 
aggregation and dissemination (e.g., Plott and Sunder 1988; Forsythe and  Lundholm 1990; Copeland and Friedman 1987; Camerer and Weigelt 1991;  O'Brien and Srivastava 1991). 
5 Plott and Sunder (1988) pioneered the laboratory 
study of information aggregation in single-period markets structured as event-
contingent assets. In their experiments, the true state of the world can either 
be X, Y or Z with some known probabilities. For each state other than the true state, 
half of the traders are informed of the false state. For example, let the true state 
be Y. In this case, half of the traders know the true state to be either X or Y (i.e., 
not Z), and the other traders know the true state to be either Y or Z (i.e., not X). 
Thus, traders have heterogeneous information that, if aggregated efficiently, is 
enough to fully reveal the true state. In the treatments closest to our design, the 
market consists of three types of assets x, y and z, which pay a positive dividend for 
the states X, Y, and Z, respectively (e.g., asset x pays a positive dividend if and only 
if the true state is X). 
6 The results of Plott and Sunder (1988) show that market 
prices converge to the true value of the asset-thereby revealing the true state-
even when there is no immediate incentive for any trader to reveal their private 
information. However, the information structure used in the experiments greatly 
facilitates information dissemination and aggregation. For example, if the true event 
is Y, then the distribution of private information implies that demand for asset y will 
easily outstrip those for assets x and z. 
7 As such, the market demand for asset 
y relative to those of assets x and z will immediately reveal the true event to be Y. 
In this paper, we study a more complex and asymmetric information structure. 
This structure allows us to test an environment where information aggregation 
requires counterfactual reasoning, and to test gradual aggregation and dissemination 
of information. The information structure we employ differs from that of Plott and   4 Developments in uses of predictions markets (e.g., Wolfers and Zitzewitz 2004; Chen and Plott 2002)  are often inspired by the success of markets in this respect. 
5 For a broader summary of market experiments on information aggregation, see surveys by Sunder  (1995), Duxbury (1995) and Noussair and Tucker (2013). 
6 Subsequent studies have used a similar design to study price manipulation (e.g., Hanson et al. 2006;  Veiga and Vorsatz 2010) and the interplay between trading performances and overconfidence (Biais et al.  2005). 
7 The not X traders will have positive demands for assets z and y, whilst the not Z traders will have 
positive demands for assets x and y. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>Sunder (1988) in two important ways. First, it relaxes the one-to-one relation of 
states of the world to profitable assets (Arrow-Debreu securities) by allowing 
different states to map onto the same asset. Second, while the states of the world are 
symmetric and equiprobable, the different possible asset evaluations are not. This 
asymmetry in information translates to asymmetry with regards to the information 
held by different types of traders. 
These two design innovations raise two new issues, respectively. First, as 
different states of the world map to the same asset value, we generate a situation 
where, in some states, all of the traders hold exactly the same beliefs over the assets' 
values despite having diverse information regarding the underlying state of the 
world. In previous studies, such as Plott and Sunder (1988), traders always 
potentially observe some market activity (asks, bids, or transactions) that is 
inconsistent with some state of the world that they consider possible. Such market 
activity reveals that there exist other traders who hold different information, and 
thus conveys new information about the true state. In our setting, in contrast, the 
different information held by different traders translates to the same beliefs and the 
same market activity, hence the observed market activity does not provide any new 
information regarding the true state. The diverse information held by different 
traders, if aggregated successfully, is nonetheless sufficient to fully reveal the true 
state. To do so requires counterfactual reasoning: traders should realize that all 
observed market activity is consistent with their own beliefs about the assets' 
values, and consequently eliminate the states of the world in which some of the 
other traders hold differing beliefs. Our experiment tests whether this feature of the 
market impedes, or even prevents, successful aggregation of information. 
Second, in states of the world where different traders do hold different beliefs, we 
can identify a minority of traders who hold different beliefs to those held by the 
majority traders. Since the majority traders dominate the market and the price 
setting, the minority traders stand to better learn new information from the initial 
movement of prices. Accordingly, we test whether these minority traders become 
better informed about the true state of the world and about the true value of the 
assets, and whether they can leverage this knowledge for profit. </p>

<p>8   Finally, previous studies have focused on aggregate outcomes in the market. Our 
experimental design introduces yet another new feature. To test individual belief 
updating and information dissemination, we elicit traders' post-market beliefs about 
the true asset-relevant event. This allows us to test whether individual revelation of 
the true state is a necessary condition for information revelation in market prices. 
We present a simple fully revealing rational expectations equilibrium (FRE) 
model, which shows that information aggregation and full revelation of the true 
state is possible in our setup both when traders' beliefs over the assets' values are 
heterogeneous and homogeneous. Furthermore, when traders hold heterogeneous 
private information, the model predicts that a minority subset of traders (the </p>

<p>8 Plott and Sunder (1988) included several treatments where a single asset was traded, which valuations 
depend on the state of the world. This induces some asymmetries, not in the information structure as in 
the present study, but in the asset valuations. As (with a limited supply of the asset) the price reveals the 
highest valuation in the market, traders who hold lower valuations are potentially better informed. Plott 
and Sunder (1988) did not explore the implications of such differences between trader types in their data. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>minority traders) will learn about the true state before the others and will be 
instrumental in driving prices towards the FRE. Against this backdrop, three 
questions are investigated: </p>

<p>RQ1: Can Arrow-Debreu markets be successful at aggregating private 
information about the true event into prices, even when traders are endowed 
with homogeneous beliefs, such that information aggregation is challenging 
and requires traders to employ sophisticated counterfactual reasoning? 
RQ2: Are minority traders better informed about the true event, can they leverage 
this knowledge for profit, and are they instrumental in driving prices to 
reveal the true state? 
RQ3: Can individuals in the market learn the true event from the movement of 
prices, and is individual learning a necessary condition for information 
aggregation in the prices? </p>

<p>To measure success at information aggregation in the experimental setting, we 
benchmark the FRE model against a prior-information equilibrium (PIE) model. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The PIE model assumes that the traders update their beliefs given their private 
information, but fail to take market activity into account. Thus, we test the ability of 
the market to aggregate dispersed information by comparing the observed final 
market prices to the FRE and PIE predictions. The post-market beliefs allow us to 
test the role of individual beliefs in market prices convergence to the true values and 
the dissemination of information throughout the market. By repeating the market 
game, we are able to test the role of market experience in information aggregation 
and dissemination. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Our findings can be summarised as follows. Markets are successful at 
aggregating dispersed information in the prices when traders are experienced, but 
not in early rounds. Although market prices reflect the true state, traders largely 
remain ignorant in the post-market stage. This finding is consistent with the 
marginal trader hypothesis (e.g., Forsythe et al. 1992), which posits that efficiency 
in market prices only require a small population of sophisticated traders, who are 
influential in driving prices to the competitive equilibrium. We observe successful 
price convergence even in the more challenging case of homogeneous beliefs. That 
is, we do not find any significant differences in the information aggregation 
properties of markets when traders are endowed with homogeneous or heteroge-
neous private information. Finally, we find some evidence suggesting that minority 
traders learn about the true event before others and are instrumental in driving prices 
towards the FRE. There is no evidence, however, that the better-informed minority 
traders are able to extract a higher share of the surplus. </p>

<p>9 This builds on prior experimental research on the issue of information aggregation (e.g., Banks 1985; 
Barner et al. 2005; Camerer and Weigelt 1991; Copeland and Friedman 1987; Forsythe and Lundholm 
1990; O'Brien and Srivastava 1991; Plott and Sunder 1982, 1988). 
10 Plott (2000) found that prices converge fairly efficiently to the FRE when subjects have some 
experience (i.e., after three rounds or more). </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>2 Experimental design </p>

<p>We conducted 7 experimental sessions involving 12 subjects each. Participants 
were recruited from the subject pool of the experimental economics laboratory at 
Ben-Gurion University of the Negev using the recruitment software <rs id="software-2" type="software">ORSEE</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Greiner</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2015</rs>). All sessions were programmed with the <rs id="software-3" type="software">z-Tree</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Fischbacher</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">2007</rs>)  software. Subjects in each session were first given 45 min to familiarise themselves 
with the instructions, complete an accompanying set of control questions and 
participate in two non-paying practice rounds (see the ''supplementary Appendix'' 
for the translated instructions). The experiment itself included 10 rounds. All 
payoffs were stated in ECU (Experimental Currency Unit), and converted to New 
Israeli Shekels (NIS) at the end of the experiment at a conversion rate of 15 ECU = 
1 NIS. The final payoff consisted of the payoff of one randomly chosen round in 
addition to a show-up fee of 25 NIS. The average payment including show-up fee 
was 73.33 NIS (approximately 21 USD). Average session duration was 
approximately 120 min. </p>

<p>2.1 Market structure and procedure </p>

<p>The twelve traders are randomly allocated into three groups of four traders each. 
Each group k 2 f1; 2; 3g is randomly assigned to be of type X or type O with equal 
probabilities. Thus, there are eight equally probable states of the world 
s 2 S Â k H k , where H k 2 fX; Og denotes group k's type. 
11 Let the event xðsÞ 2 
f0; 1; 2; 3g denote the total number of type X groups at state s (e.g., xðsÞ ¼ 1 iff 
s 2 fXOO; OXO; OOXg). At each state s 2 S, traders observe the type of the two 
other groups, but not their own group's type. For example, in the case where 
s ¼ XXO, the first two groups observe one X and one O, hence only events 1 and 2 
are possible. The third group observes two X's, hence only events 2 and 3 are 
possible. 
For the true state s 
Ã 2 S, we define the event xðs 
Ã Þ as the corresponding true 
event. This distinction is necessary as market prices will convey information about 
the true event rather than the true state. The information structure is commonly 
known and endows traders with private and partial information over the true event. 
For example, if s 
Ã ¼ XXX, then all traders will observe two other type X groups, 
implying that they each know the true event xðs 
Ã Þ to be either 2 or 3. 
Trade involves four ''types'' of Arrow-Debreu assets, indexed by a 2 f0; 1; 2; 3g. 
The value of asset a given the true event xðs 
Ã Þ is given by </p>

<p>dðxðs 
Ã Þ; aÞ ¼ 
100 
if a ¼ xðs 
Ã Þ; </p>

<p>0 
otherwise: </p>



<p>Each trader is endowed with a working capital loan of 5000 ECU and six units of 
each of the four assets. There are four simultaneous markets, one for each asset. 
Trade is conducted using the Continuous Double Auction (CDA) mechanism for a </p>

<p>11 The eight states are XXX, OXX, XOX, XXO, XOO, OXO, OOX and OOO, where the first, second and 
third coordinates of each state denote the type of groups 1, 2 and 3, respectively. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>duration of 300 s. Short sales are prohibited, and a price ceiling of 200 ECU is 
imposed on the bid and ask prices to limit potential negative profits. Note that 
traders at the start of the markets do not know the value of each asset (i.e., they 
don't know which assets are valued at 0 or 100). Instead, they only know that the 
value of each asset can be either 100 or 0, depending on the true event xðs 
Ã Þ. 
After 300 s, the CDA market closes and traders enter the post-market stage. 
Here, traders are asked to guess how many type X groups were in the market. The 
response b i 2 f0; 1; 2; 3g is taken to be participant i's elicited belief. 
12 The payment 
for beliefs is given by </p>

<p>gðxðs 
Ã Þ; b i Þ ¼ 
200 
if b i ¼ xðs 
Ã Þ; </p>

<p>À 200 
otherwise: </p>



<p>At the end of the round, traders receive feedback on the true state, the unit value and 
number of units owned for each of the four assets, and their detailed final round 
payoff. The round payoff consist of the total value of owned assets and remaining 
capital, minus the initial loan of 5000 ECU, plus payment for the submitted 
beliefs. 
13 Denote by L i ! 0 and e </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>i ! 0 trader i's inventory of capital and asset a, 
respectively. Thus, each trader i's payoff is given by: </p>

<p>P i ¼ ðL i À 5000Þ þ 
X 3 </p>

<p>a¼0 </p>

<p>dðxðs 
Ã Þ; a i Þe </p>

<p>a 
i </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>marketpayoff </p>

<p>þ gðxðs 
Ã Þ; b i Þ; 
zfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl}|fflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{ </p>

<p>postÀmarketpayoff </p>

<p>where the first term captures the consequences of the trader's market decisions and 
the second his submitted beliefs. </p>

<p>3 Theoretical analysis </p>

<p>3.1 Preliminaries </p>

<p>We shall refer to the events xðs 
Ã Þ 2 f1; 2g as the heterogeneous events, given that 
they induce different beliefs in different traders. That is, the private information 
held by traders in one group, the minority traders, induces different beliefs over the 
assets' valuations than for the other traders. For example, if s 
Ã ¼ XXO, groups </p>

<p>12 Eliciting a (modal) point belief is sufficient for the purpose of assessing individuals' ability to learn the 
true state from the observed market prices. The alternative of eliciting a full belief distribution would 
require an incentive compatible scoring rule, which is likely to be confusing for experimental subjects. 
13 Because the loan of 5000 ECU is to be returned at the end of the round, there were some instances of 
bankruptcy (13% of all observations). In the first five rounds, these appeared to be distributed rather 
uniformly across all subjects. In the last five rounds, bankruptcies were concentrated in a handful of 
subjects, suggesting that the initial bankruptcies were part of the learning process. See the 
''supplementary Appendix'' for more details. Note that the limited liability doesn't impact the theoretical 
analysis, as it doesn't bias trading decisions with respect to the true asset, but may impede information 
aggregation by increasing risky and/or noisy investments. Thus, if anything, we are underestimating the 
market's true ability to aggregate information without limited liability. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>1 and 2 know that the true event is either 1 or 2, while group 3 (the minority 
traders) knows that the true event is either 2 or 3. In the complementary events 
xðs 
Ã Þ 2 f0; 3g, all traders observe the same number of X's, and therefore hold the 
same beliefs over the events x(s). We therefore refer to these events as the 
homogeneous events. For example if s 
Ã ¼ XXX, all traders know that the true event 
is either 2 or 3. Naturally, it follows that there are no minority traders in 
homogeneous events. </p>

<p>3.2 The FRE and PIE models </p>

<p>The experimental design endows traders with partial and private information about 
the true event. Because the complexity of the CDA mechanism makes it extremely 
difficult to analyse with standard game theoretical methods, we evaluate the 
market's success at aggregating information by comparing market prices against the 
fully revealing rational expectations equilibrium (FRE) and the prior-information 
equilibrium (PIE) described in full below. Table 1 details the FRE and PIE 
predicted prices of each asset a in the market and the corresponding implied 
proportion of submitted beliefs in the post-market stage. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>The PIE describes the market clearing prices when risk-neutral traders use Bayes' 
rule to update their posteriors about the true event given their own private 
information and condition their demands upon such posteriors. However, there is no 
belief updating following trade, and consequently the true event is only partially 
revealed in prices. For example if s 
Ã ¼ XXO, then traders in groups 1 and 2 will 
assign equal posteriors to the events 1 and 2, whilst those in group 3 will assign 
equal posteriors to the events 2 and 3. As traders condition their demand for assets 
on their posteriors, the corresponding market clearing prices are 0, 50, 50 and 0 for 
assets a ¼ 0, a ¼ 1, a ¼ 2 and a ¼ 3, respectively. 
15 Uniformed of the true event, 
traders in groups 1 and 2 will uniformly randomise between the responses b ¼ 1 
and b ¼ 2. Similarly, those in group 3 will randomise between the responses b ¼ 2 
and b ¼ 3. 
In contrast to the PIE, the FRE describes an outcome where risk-neutral traders 
not only use Bayes' law to update their posteriors but also continuously learn about 
the private information of others from market prices. This endogenous process 
continues until no trader can learn any more from prices and the true event is fully 
revealed in the prices. Since all traders are fully informed about the true event by 
definition, this should be reflected in their submitted beliefs. 
In many respects, both equilibria describe some form of market aggregation. 
Where they differ is on the issues as to whether the true event is partially (PIE) or 
fully (FRE) revealed in prices. The expected market payoff in both PIE and FRE is 
600. The expected post-market payoff is 0 and 200 for the former and latter, 
respectively. </p>

<p>14 The models assume that prices are set only by the expected values of the assets given the traders' 
beliefs. That is, we assume that traders are risk neutral and have no other motivations for trading other 
than divergent beliefs. 
15 Traders from groups 1 and 2 are willing to sell asset a ¼ 3 at zero. Given group 3 traders are the 
minority in the population, the only market clearing price for asset 3 is zero. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>How prices might actually converge to the FRE remains an open question. There 
is an extensive literature that discusses the dynamic behaviours of traders (e.g., 
Dubey et al. 1987; Hellwig 1982; Ostrovsky 2012; Radner 1979). However, the 
complexity of such models are largely beyond the scope of our experimental design. 
Furthermore, Biais and Pouget (1999) show that given the information asymmetry 
in our design, there should be no trade in equilibrium, except at the FRE prices. Yet 
without trade at non FRE prices, it is difficult to see how traders learn about the true 
state. 
In the following subsection, we present a simple reasoning model describing the 
convergence process supporting the FRE prices. 
16 As we later elaborate, counter-
factual reasoning by traders will play in integral role in the convergence process. </p>

<p>3.3 The reasoning model </p>

<p>The model builds on Jordan's (1982) discussion of the way in which prices may first 
converge to some 'pre-equilibrium' on the path to the FRE. 
17 Trade takes place over 
t ¼ 1; 2; 3; 4 hypothetical periods. Traders are risk-neutral, not capital constrained, 
always seek to maximise payoffs and are non-strategic in the sense that they trade in 
each period as if it were the last. Denote p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t as the period t price of asset a. Given the 
above, the model assumes that behaviours at each period t are described by the 
following four stages: </p>

<p>Table 1 Predicted prices and 
beliefs </p>

<p>p 
a denotes the predicted price of 
asset a and B 
j denotes the 
predicted proportion of traders 
submitting beliefs b ¼ j </p>

<p>True event Market prices 
Submitted beliefs </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Panel A: Fully revealing equilibrium rational expectations (FRE) </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 0 
100 
0 
0 
0 1.00 0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 1 
0 100 
0 
0 0 
1.00 0 
0 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2 
0 
0 100 
0 0 
0 
1.00 0 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 3 
0 
0 
0 100 0 
0 
0 
1.00 </p>

<p>Panel B: Prior-information equilibrium (PIE) </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 0 
50 
50 
0 
0 0.50 0.50 0 
0 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 1 
0 
50 
50 
0 0.17 0.50 0.33 0 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2 
0 
50 
50 
0 0 
0.33 0.50 0.17 </p>

<p>xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 3 
0 
0 
50 
50 0 
0 
0.50 0.50 </p>

<p>16 We introduce the reasoning model to highlight the challenges and complexities in convergences to the 
FRE. The model is not based on a game theoretic analysis of double auction market structure, does not 
incorporate risk-aversion and does not include other motivations to trade other than differences in 
opinion. 
17 Jordan (1982) model is sometimes known as the 'Jordan Path'. Copeland and Friedman (1987) and 
Plott and Sunder (1988) have noted that the convergence of asset prices to the FRE in their data is 
consistent with the Jordan Path. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>Stage 1. Traders observe the period t À 1 prices of each asset (i.e., p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>tÀ1 ). 
Stage 2. Traders update their beliefs regarding the true event. 
Stage 3. Traders condition their demands for assets given their updated posteriors 
or beliefs. 
Stage 4. The market clears and period t prices are established. </p>

<p>To see how convergence to the FRE occurs in the reasoning model, first consider 
the case where s 
Ã ¼ XXX or xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 3 (homogeneous event). Here, all traders 
observe two type X groups and therefore assign equal posteriors to the events 
2 and 3. At period t ¼ 1, traders condition their asset demands on such posteriors. 
This results in the market clearing prices: p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 ¼ p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 ¼ 50 and p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ¼ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ¼ 0 (the PIE 
prices). At period t ¼ 2, traders observing the previous period prices will reason the 
true event to be 3. The reasoning is as follows. If the true event were 2, some traders 
would have observed one X and one O. Such traders would assign a posterior 
probability of 0.5 to the event 1, driving p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 up to 50. Since p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ¼ 0, this must mean 
that no trader observes only one other X ruling out event 2. Conditioning their 
demands on the updated beliefs now results in the market clearing prices: p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 ¼ 100 
and p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ¼ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 ¼ p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ¼ 0 (the FRE prices). Since the true event is fully revealed in 
t ¼ 2, there should be no revisions to the prices in periods t ¼ 3 and t ¼ 4. This 
process of information aggregation holds by symmetry for the s 
Ã ¼ OOO case. 
Now consider the case where s 
Ã ¼ XXO or xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2 (heterogeneous event). 
Here, traders in groups 1 and 2 observe one type X group and therefore assign equal 
posteriors to the events 1 and 2. Conversely, the minority traders in group 3 observe 
two type X groups and therefore assign equal posteriors to the events 2 and 3. At 
period t ¼ 1, traders condition their asset demands on such posteriors, resulting in 
the market clearing prices: p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ¼ p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 ¼ 50 and p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 ¼ p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1 ¼ 0 (the PIE prices). 
18 At 
period t ¼ 2, the minority traders, having observed non-zero prices for asset 1, can 
deduce that some of the other traders observed a type O group. This rules out 
event 3 from being the true event, hence the true event must be xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2. In 
contrast, the non-minority traders (those in groups 1 and 2), who already knew that 
there is at least one type O group receive no new information from the prices, and 
therefore remain uninformed. Given the updated beliefs, there is still excess demand 
for asset 1 by groups 1 and 2, leading to market clearing prices of p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 ¼ p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 ¼ 50 and 
p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 ¼ p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 ¼ 0. 
19 However, given their higher valuations, the market mechanism will 
allocate asset 2 to the minority traders. At period t ¼ 3, groups 1 and 2 again 
remain uninformed of the true event. Given that the trade of asset 2 will now mostly 
involve group 3 traders, though, the subsequent market clearing prices will be: 
p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 ¼ p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 ¼ 0, p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 ¼ 50 and p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 ¼ 100. 
20 At period t ¼ 4, the non-minority traders </p>

<p>observing that p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 [ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 , should conclude that the true event is xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2. As traders </p>

<p>18 Although group 3 traders value asset 3 at 50, those in groups 1 and 2 value asset 3 at 0. The excess 
supply therefore drives the market clearing price of asset 3 towards 0. 
19 If leveraged short-sales are permitted, then p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 may converge to 0 as traders in group 3 act to short the 
asset. 
20 The intuition here is that because asset 2 is all held by the group 3 traders, 'Bertrand' like competition 
between informed traders drive the price of asset 2 up to 100. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>condition their asset demands on their updated beliefs, we arrive at the market 
clearing prices: p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 ¼ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 ¼ p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 ¼ 0 and p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 ¼ 100, the FRE prices. 
21 This process of 
information aggregation holds by symmetry for all states where xðs 
Ã Þ 2 f1; 2g. 
The main results of the reasoning model are as follows. Firstly, convergence to 
the FRE prices is possible for all states and events. Secondly, on the path of 
convergence towards the FRE, prices go through the PIE prices. Finally, minority 
traders (heterogeneous event) learn about the true event before the other traders and 
are 'instrumental' in driving prices towards the FRE. </p>

<p>3.3.1 Some comments </p>

<p>The model assumes that traders only update their beliefs on observed prices. In 
CDA markets, traders can also learn from the volume of transactions or the unfilled 
bid and ask prices. Will these additional elements influence the information 
aggregation process? Suppose that traders only update their beliefs on observed 
transaction volumes. When s 
Ã ¼ XXX, transactions should be concentrated on assets 
2 and 3. So again, traders will only learn about the true event through reasoning 
about why transactions for asset 1 is relatively low. When s 
Ã ¼ XXO, transactions 
should be concentrated on assets 1 and 2. 
22 As such, minority traders should still 
learn about the true state before the others. Consequently, transaction volumes for 
asset 2 will increase relative to those for asset 1 as minority traders concentrate their 
purchases on the true asset. Non minority traders will thus learn the true event to be 
2. Thus, the additional elements do not seem to alter the information aggregation 
process in any substantial way. 
The model suggests that convergence to the FRE might be more challenging for 
the heterogeneous information events given that minority subjects must first be 
informed about the true event and be instrumental at driving prices towards the 
FRE. 
23 At the same time, convergence to the FRE also requires agents to employ 
counterfactual reasoning. In heterogeneous information events, agents make 
inferences from actual observed trade. In the homogeneous information events, in 
contrast, agents deduce the true event from not observing trade on an asset, which 
would have been traded in some counterfactual event. Recognising that empirical 
(experimental and otherwise) data are often noisy, and some trade is likely to 
happen, it is not clear whether low volumes or prices are enough for agents to be 
confident at ascertaining the true event. Even complete market inactivity is 
somewhat ambiguous, as it is not clear how much time should be allowed to elapse 
before concluding that there is no demand for the asset. Lack of trade may be 
explained, for example, by agents concentrating on other parts of the market. For </p>

<p>21 An interesting corollary of the model is that if there is only one minority trader, as opposed to group of 
traders, prices may never converge to the FRE. 
22 The population of group 3 traders (minority traders) who will purchase asset 3 is substantially smaller 
than those in groups 1 and 2, who will mainly transact in assets 1 and 2. 
23 Note that because t refers to hypothetical periods, it does not necessarily imply that convergence to the 
FRE is slower for the heterogeneous relative to homogeneous information states. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>these reasons, convergence to FRE prices may depend on the information structure, 
with homogeneous beliefs leading to slower convergence. </p>

<p>4 Experimental results </p>

<p>To study prices in dynamic CDA markets, we partition the market data into time 
windows of 30 seconds, each indexed by t ¼ ð1; 2; 3; . . .; 10Þ. Denote by p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t the 
mean transaction price for asset a in window t. For example, p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 corresponds to the 
mean transaction price of asset 3 within the 30-60 s time window. Where p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t cannot 
be computed as there are no transactions in the time window, we employ the carry 
forward rule, substituting p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t with the last known computed price. 
24 As such, p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t will 
always reflect the most recent price for asset a. Where appropriate, we will also 
consider the prices without the carry forward rule, denoted by p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t . That is, p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t ¼ 0 if 
no transactions are observed. 
Since all events of the form x(s) are a one-to-one mapping to assets, we will 
sometimes use both terms interchangeably. For any true event xðs 
Ã Þ, define the 
alternative event as the non-true event to which traders assign a positive posterior 
given their private information at the start of the market. Since this will differ 
amongst the minority and non-minority traders, we use Alt-M and Alt-NM to denote 
the alternative event for the former and latter, respectively. Finally, for any true 
event, define the implausible events as those which all traders assign zero posterior 
to given their private information at the start of the market. For example if 
xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 2, then assets 0, 1, 2 and 3 are the implausible, Alt-NM, true, and Alt-M 
assets, respectively. If xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 0, then assets 0 and 1 are the true and Alt-NM assets, 
respectively, while assets 2 and 3 are the implausible assets. 
Figures 1 and 2 present the median p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t and submitted beliefs for homogeneous 
and heterogeneous private information events, respectively. The rows in each 
figure correspond to prices for the true, Alt-NM, Alt-M, and implausible assets. The 
header of each panel details the round, followed by the number of sessions which 
data is pooled from and the corresponding mean submitted belief in parenthesis. The 
solid and dash horizontal lines on each panel detail the FRE and PIE prices, 
respectively. For example, the top left panel of Fig. 1 corresponds to the the median 
p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t of the true asset over the first round. The header shows that the round-1 true event 
was homogeneous in three of the seven sessions, and that 42% of subjects' 
submitted beliefs corresponded to the true event. 
There are several indications of learning over the ten rounds. We first consider 
purchases at a price of above 100 ECU. Such purchases might seem 'irrational' 
given that the maximum value of any asset is 100 ECU. Note, however, that this is 
not necessarily the case. For example, a trader might be willing to buy an asset she 
knows to be worthless at a price of 120 ECU, if she believes that this will influence </p>

<p>24 The carry forward rule is performed recursively until a price is determined. That is, we first set 
p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t ¼ p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>tÀ1 . If this cannot be determined, we then set p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t ¼ p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>tÀ2 and so forth. If no transaction of the asset 
occurred since the beginning of trader, we set p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>1 ¼ 0. It was rather rare that an asset was not traded at all 
in t ¼ 1, occurring for only 24 of 280 (8.6%) of traded assets, 15 instances of which pertain to an asset 
that all traders can rule out as the true asset at the beginning of trade (e.g., a ¼ 0 in s 
Ã ¼ XXO). </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>the beliefs of other traders and enable her to sell five units of the same asset at a 
price of 30 ECU, or if she believes that she will be able to resale the asset at a higher 
price. We find that 19% of all purchases in the first five rounds were at a price of 
above 100 ECU, decreasing to 9% of all purchases in the last five rounds. 
Furthermore, whilst 79% of subjects made a seemingly irrational purchase at least 
once in the first five rounds, only 35% did so in the last five rounds. See the 
''supplementary Appendix'' for more details. 
25 Importantly, the persistence of such 
purchases suggests that there are still some subjects who behave like noise traders 
(e.g., De-Long et al. 1990). 
Turning our attention to price dynamics, we observe that the true asset often 
transacted at close to 100 ECU. Consistent with the FRE and PIE predictions, prices 
of the implausible and Alt-M assets are converging towards zero, but only in rounds 
6-10. Finally, prices for the Alt-NM asset seem to converge towards 100 ECU in 
rounds 1-4, 50 ECU in rounds 5-6 and finally, 0 ECU in rounds 7-10. To </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 </p>

<p>True </p>

<p>Alt-NM </p>

<p>Implausible </p>

<p>1, 3, (0.42) 
3, 2, (0.21) 
4, 1, (0.50) 
5, 1, (0.58) 
6, 4, (0.56) 
7, 2, (0.54) 
8, 1, (1.00) 
9, 2, (0.71) 
10, 1, (0.83) </p>

<p>1,3, (0.56) 
3, 2, (0.75) 
4, 1, (0.50) 
5, 1, (0.42) 
6, 4, (0.40) 
7, 2, (0.42) 
8, 1, (0.00) 
9, 2, (0.29) 
10, 1, (0.17) </p>

<p>1, 3, (0.03) 
3, 2, (0.04) 
4, 1, (0.00) 
5, 1, (0.00) 
6, 4, (0.04) 
7, 2, (0.04) 
8, 1, (0.00) 
9, 2, (0.00) 
10, 1, (0.00) </p>

<p>median p t 
FRE price 
PIE price </p>

<p>Price </p>

<p>30 seconds time windows (t) </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Prices and submitted beliefs for homogeneous information events. The first, second and third rows 
correspond to median prices for the true, Alt-NM and implausible assets, respectively, aggregating over 
all sessions. The header of each panel details the round, followed by the number of sessions and finally, 
the corresponding submitted beliefs in parenthesis. The solid and dash horizontal lines denote the FRE 
and PIE prices, respectively </p>

<p>25 In fact, one of these subjects-call her subject A-was responsible for nearly 25% of all purchases 
above 100 ECU in the last 5 rounds. However, all of such purchases for subject A pertained to the true 
asset. Furthermore, irrational purchases were often between the range of 101-120. Perhaps, subject 
A might be using the prices to signal the true event to others. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>acknowledge the role of experience, we separate the data in the following analyses 
into 'Inexperienced' (rounds 1-5) and 'Experienced' (rounds 6-10) subjects. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>In the following, we will first address RQ1, investigating whether Arrow-Debreu 
markets can be successful at aggregating dispersed private information into prices 
and revealing the true event. Orthogonal to this, we will also investigate whether the 
nature of information aggregation might be dependent on the information structure, 
more specifically, whether price and belief convergence differ between homoge-
neous and heterogeneous events. Finally, we study the behaviours of minority 
subjects to investigate RQ2. </p>

<p>4.1 Information aggregation </p>

<p>Our approach seeks to investigate the question of information aggregation from 
three different angles. Since relative asset prices can be interpreted as the markets' 
prediction about the true event, we will first investigate whether the markets are 
often correct (i.e., the true asset is priced higher than the other assets). Thereafter, 
we will focus on the issue of arbitrage opportunities, such as when prices of the </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 150 200 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 910 </p>

<p>True </p>

<p>Alt-NM </p>

<p>Alt-M </p>

<p>Implausible </p>

<p>1, 4, (0.50) 
2, 7, (0.58) 
3, 5, (0.57) 
4, 6, (0.65) 
5, 6, (0.71) 
6, 3, (0.64) 
7, 5, (0.68) 
8, 6, (0.71) 
9, 5, (0.72) 
10, 6, (0.86) </p>

<p>1, 4, (0.31) 
2, 7, (0.31) 
3, 5, (0.32) 
4, 6, (0.21) 
5, 6, (0.18) 
6, 3, (0.31) 
7, 5, (0.25) 
8, 6, (0.21) 
9, 5, (0.18) 
10, 6, (0.11) </p>

<p>1, 4, (0.13) 
2, 7, (0.08) 
3, 5, (0.08) 
4, 6, (0.14) 
5, 6, (0.10) 
6, 3, (0.06) 
7, 5, (0.07) 
8, 6, (0.08) 
9, 5, (0.08) 
10, 6, (0.03) </p>

<p>1, 4, (0.06) 
2, 7, (0.02) 
3, 5, (0.03) 
4, 6, (0.00) 
5, 6, (0.01) 
6, 3, (0.00) 
7, 5, (0.00) 
8, 6, (0.00) 
9, 5, (0.02) 
10, 6, (0.00) </p>

<p>median p t 
FRE price 
PIE price </p>

<p>Price </p>

<p>30 seconds time windows (t) </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Prices and submitted beliefs for heterogeneous information events. The first, second, third and 
fourth rows correspond to median prices for the true, Alt-NM, Alt-M and implausible assets, respectively, 
aggregating over all sessions. The header of each panel details the round, followed by the number of 
sessions and finally, the corresponding submitted beliefs in parenthesis. The solid and dash horizontal 
lines denote the FRE and PIE prices, respectively </p>

<p>26 As noted by Forsythe and Lundholm (1990), experience with the trading mechanism or experimental 
design is crucial in giving markets a better chance at succeeding. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>various assets do not sum up to 100 ECU. The intuition here is that subjects may 
learn about the true event at different t, resulting in disagreements and consequently 
arbitrage opportunities. However, such arbitrage opportunities should also be 
eliminated if information aggregation is successful. Finally, we will benchmark the 
FRE against the PIE to examine if prices are relatively closer to either equilibria. </p>

<p>4.1.1 Relative prices </p>

<p>From Figs. 1 and 2, we note that prices for the Alt-M and implausible assets are 
consistently lower than those for the Alt-NM and true assets. Indeed, transactions of 
the former two assets are also relatively less frequent. These observations are 
helpful since they suggest that markets often excluded the Alt-M and implausible 
assets as candidates for the true event. In this case, our analysis can focus on the 
relative prices of the Alt-NM and true assets. </p>

<p>To make such comparisons, we will define assets A and B as the highest and 
second highest priced assets at time window t, respectively, with the corresponding 
prices p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>t and p </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>t . 
27 We derive the following two frequencies for some b ! 1: </p>

<p>f t : The frequency to which p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>t ! bp </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>t at window t. 
f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t : The frequency to which p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>t ! bp </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>t conditional on A being the true asset at 
window t. </p>

<p>For b ¼ 1, f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t reflects the proportion of markets in which the true asset was priced 
higher than the other assets. Thus, f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 measures the proportion of times in which the 
final prices reveal the true event. This happens overall in 52 of the 70 (74.3%) 
markets included in the experiment, or 29 of the 35 (82.86%) markets with 
experienced subjects. In each of the final four rounds, final prices revealed the true 
event in six of the seven sessions. 
Values of b larger than 1 capture the extent to which asset A is priced higher than 
asset B. Intuitively, f t captures the markets' candidate true asset at time t given the 
criterion b. For example when b ¼ 2, then f t details the ratio of observations which 
the price of asset A is at least twice that of asset B in window t-data aggregated 
over all sessions. In this case, f </p>

<p>Ã 
t </p>

<p>f t can be interpreted as the frequency to which the 
markets are correct (e.g., the frequency to which the true asset is priced at least b 
times higher than the Alt-NM asset at time t). Inversely, ðf t À f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t Þ details the 
frequency to which the markets are incorrect. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Figure 3 details the f t and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t for b ¼ 1; 1:5; 2; 2:5; 3. 
29 A few observations are 
apparent from the figure. First, for b [ 1, f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t is very close to f t , implying that traders 
are sometimes incorrect in identifying the true asset, but rarely by a large margin. 
Alternatively, when markets clearly favour one asset over the others, they are almost 
always correct. </p>

<p>27 Prices for assets A and B here are derived applying the carry forward rule. </p>

<p>28 The FRE predicts that f t and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t are unity for all b ! 1. In contrast, the PIE predicts that f t and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t are 
zero for all b [ 1. 
29 See the ''supplementary Appendix'' for f t and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t for b ¼ 1; 1:1; 1:2; 1:3; 1:4; 1:5. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>Second, experience has a strong effect on information aggregation. When 
subjects are inexperienced, f 10 is approximately 0.35 and 0.10 when b ¼ 1:5 and 
b ¼ 2, respectively, suggesting that final trading prices do not discriminate between 
the assets by much. Furthermore, the plots are rather flat, indicating that 
discrimination doesn't improve by much across the trading period. For experienced 
subjects, in contrast, f t and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t are very close to each other. Discrimination clearly 
develops as trade proceeds, as reflected in the upwards trends in the plots, 
culminating in f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>10 at approximately 0.60 and 0.51 when b ¼ 1:5 and b ¼ 2, 
respectively. The markets were, therefore, quite efficient in discriminating between 
the true asset and the other assets, with the true asset priced at at least twice the 
other asset in 51% of all observations. </p>

<p>4.1.2 Arbitrage opportunities </p>

<p>To study arbitrage opportunities, we define SUM t ¼ 
P 
a p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t as the sum of al prices at 
window t. 
30 The thick black line on Fig. 4 plots the median SUM t over all sessions. 
Here, we clearly observe SUM t to be decreasing with t for both inexperienced and </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 </p>

<p>Inexperienced, =1 Inexperienced, =1.5 Inexperienced, =2 Inexperienced, =2.5 Inexperienced, =3 </p>

<p>Experienced, =1 
Experienced, =1.5 
Experienced, =2 
Experienced, =2.5 
Experienced, =3 </p>

<p>f t = `"Freq.( p A </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>p B 
t )"' </p>

<p>f t * = `"Freq.( [p A </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>p B 
t ] &amp; [p A is the true asset] )"' 
(Aggregated over all rounds and sessions) </p>

<p>Observed Frequencies </p>

<p>30 Seconds time block (t) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Highest and second highest price assets. Assets A and B are the highest and second highest price 
assets at window t, respectively, with correspond prices p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>t and p </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>t . The constant b ! 1 captures the extent 
to which p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>t is higher than p </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>t . For a given b, f t shows the frequency to which the market has ''picked a 
true event'' and f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t the frequency to which the market is correct. Specifically, for b ¼ 1, f </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>t is the 
proportion of time in which the prices reveal the underlying true event </p>

<p>30 Neglecting the carry forward rule here to avoid double counting. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>experienced subjects, indicating that arbitrage opportunities are reduced with t. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>Are they 'eliminated' at the end of the market? 
To study this, we focus on the prices at window t ¼ 10. Panel A of Table 2 
details the mean SUM 10 apportioned by sessions and experience. We clearly observe 
SUM 10 to be higher than 100 for inexperienced subjects. Indeed, aggregating over 
all sessions, we find SUM 10 to be significantly greater from 100 (Signrank, 
q\0:001, n ¼ 35 observations) for inexperienced subjects. This clearly suggests 
that arbitrage opportunities are still apparent at the end of the market. 
The picture is nuance for experienced subjects. Firstly, we observe some 
heterogeneity amongst the sessions, with SUM 10 be noticeably different from 100 
for sessions 1, 4 and 5 and less so for sessions 3, 6 and 7. Aggregating over all 
sessions, we do not find SUM 10 to be significantly different from 100 for 
experienced subjects (Signrank, q ¼ 0:13, n ¼ 35). 
32 We thus cannot exclude the 
possibility that arbitrage opportunities are eliminated at the end of the market. </p>

<p>0 
100 200 300 400 </p>

<p>0 
100 200 300 400 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>All events 
Homogenous event only 
Heterogeneous event only 
(aggregated over all sessions) 
Median SUM </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>30 seconds time window (t) </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Median SUM t over all sessions. The header of each panel details the round. The variable SUM t ¼ 
P 
a p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t describes the sum of all prices at window t. Arbitrage opportunities are defined to arise when 
SUM t 6 ¼ 100 </p>

<p>31 Notice that SUM t for inexperienced subjects are frequently above 100 ECU. This is mainly due to the 
activities of those subjects who purchased assets at prices above 100 ECU. 
32 For further robustness checks, we also regressed SUM 10 on a constant-fixed effect regression model. 
For inexperienced subjects, the constant is positive and significantly different from 100 at the 1% level. 
For experience subjects, the constant is positive but not significantly different from 100 at the 5% level. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>4.1.3 Deviations of prices from the FRE and PIE </p>

<p>To benchmark the FRE against the PIE, we compute the mean absolute deviations 
of p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t from the former and latter, henceforth known as MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t and MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t , 
respectively. 
33 Note that the symmetrical nature of the FRE and PIE imply that 
MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t and MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t will often be close and at times even identical. 
Given the above, we define DIFF t ¼ MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t À MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t as the difference between 
both mean absolute deviations at window t. Interpretations here should be 
straightforward: A positive (negative) DIFF t implies that prices at window t are 
relatively closer to the FRE (PIE). This relationship also implies that DIFF t will </p>

<p>Table 2 Summary statistics for SUM 10 and DIFF 10 </p>

<p>Variables: SUM 10 ¼ 
P 
a p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10 and DIFF 10 ¼ MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>10 À MAD </p>

<p>F 
10 </p>

<p>Variable 
Inexperienced 
Experienced </p>

<p>SUM 10 
DIFF 10 
SUM 10 
DIFF 10 </p>

<p>Panel A: Data aggregated by sessions </p>

<p>Session 1 (mean) 
248 
-1 
143 
4 </p>

<p>Session 2 (mean) 
134 
6 
80 
13 </p>

<p>Session 3 (mean) 
98 
3 
86 
4 </p>

<p>Session 4 (mean) 
353 
-4 
183 
-6 </p>

<p>Session 5 (mean) 
314 
0 
141 
-1 </p>

<p>Session 6 (mean) 
190 
-3 
103 
13 </p>

<p>Session 7 (mean) 
175 
-16 
98 
10 </p>

<p>All sessions (mean) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>216** (n = 35) 
-3 (n = 35) 
119(n = 35) 
5* (n = 35) </p>

<p>Wilcoxon Signrank Null </p>

<p>SUM 10 ¼ 100 
q \ 0:01 
q ¼ 0:13 </p>

<p>Null: DIFF 10 ¼ 0 
q ¼ 0:09 
q ¼ 0:02 </p>

<p>Panel B: Data aggregated by homogeneous and heterogeneous events </p>

<p>Homogeneous (mean) 
277 (n = 7) 
-3 (n = 7) 
112 (n = 10) 
0 (n = 10) </p>

<p>Heterogeneous (mean) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>201 (n = 28) 
-2 (n = 28) 
122 (n = 25) 
7 (n = 25) </p>

<p>Mann-Whitney (Homo vs. Hetero) 
q ¼ 0:13 
q ¼ 0:83 
q ¼ 0:66 
q ¼ 0:12 </p>

<p>The variable SUM t ¼ 
P 
a p </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t describes the sum of all prices at window t. The variable DIFF t ¼ 
MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t À MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t describes the difference between the mean absolute deviation of prices from the PIE 
(MAD 
P ) and FRE (MAD 
F ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Aggregating over all sessions, we use the fixed effect model to regress SUM 10 (DIFF 10 ) over a constant, 
where ÃÃ and Ã imply that the constant is significantly different from 100 (0) at the 1 and 5% levels, 
respectively 
b Aggregating over all sessions, we use the fixed effect model to regress the dependent variable (SUM 10 or 
DIFF 10 ) over a constant and a situation dummy for Heterogeneous information events. ÃÃ and Ã imply 
that the situation dummy is significantly different from zero at the 1 and 5% levels, respectively </p>

<p>33 More formally, MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t ¼ 
P 
a jp </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t À p 
a j=4 and MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t ¼ 
P 
a jp </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>t Àp 
a j=4, where p 
a andp 
a are the FRE 
and PIE prices, respectively. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>converge to 25 (-25) as prices converge to the FRE (PIE). Therefore, any relative 
measure between the FRE and PIE only needs to focus on the sign of DIFF t . 
Information aggregation is also expected to be a dynamic process from traders 
continuously about the true event from prices. Furthermore, the reasoning model in 
Sect. 3.3 predicts that the path of convergence to the FRE will also go through the 
PIE. In this case, we should typically expect DIFF t to start in the negative region 
and increase with t towards the positive region. However, the rate of increase is also 
expected to decrease with t. 
The construct of DIFF t is also convenient given that variations will only depend 
on the prices of the true and Alt-NM assets, the two most frequently traded asset 
types. That is, for fixed prices of the true and Alt-NM assets, variations to the 
implausible and Alt-M assets will not influence DIFF t given that such variations 
shift the MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t and MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t by the same magnitude. 
The thick solid line on Fig. 5 details the median DIFF t , aggregating over all 
sessions. For inexperienced subjects, we observe DIFF t to often be zero (i.e., prices 
are not getting closer to the FRE nor the PIE with t.) This is consistent with the 
observations in Sect. 4.1.1, where we find that prices for the true and Alt-NM assets 
are often not very different. For experienced subjects, we often observe DIFF t to be 
negative at the start of the round and increase progressively over t. To see the 
evolution of prices more formally, we regress DIFF t on the time trend t and t 
2 . The </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 
1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>6 
7 
8 
9 
10 </p>

<p>All events 
Homogenous event only 
Heterogeneous event only 
(aggregated over all sessions) 
Median MAD </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>30 seconds time window (t) </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Median DIFF t over all sessions. The header of each panel details the round. The variable 
DIFF t ¼ MAD </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>t À MAD </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>t describes the difference between the mean absolute deviation of prices from 
the PIE (MAD 
P ) and the mean absolute deviation of prices from the FRE (MAD 
F ). A positive and 
negative DIFF t indicate that prices are relatively closer to the FRE and PIE, respectively </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>fixed-effects coefficient estimates for experienced and inexperienced subjects are 
reported as follows (robust standard errors in parenthesis) 
34 : </p>

<p>DIFF t ¼ À 6:31 </p>

<p>ð1:49Þ </p>

<p>þ 0:92 </p>

<p>ð0:64Þ </p>

<p>t À 0:06 </p>

<p>ð1:49Þ </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>n ¼ 350 ðInexperienceÞ </p>

<p>DIFF t ¼ À 7:48 </p>

<p>ð1:73Þ </p>

<p>þ 1:69 </p>

<p>ð0:72Þ </p>

<p>t À 0:05 </p>

<p>ð0:06Þ </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>n ¼ 350 ðExperienceÞ </p>

<p>The negative intercept term in both regressions imply that prices towards the start of 
the round are significantly closer to the PIE. For inexperienced subjects, the coef-
ficient estimates for t and t 
2 are not significant at the 10% level. In contrast, the t 
coefficient for experienced subjects is both significant (q ¼ 0:02) and positive. The 
t 
2 coefficient for experience subjects is negative but not significant (q ¼ 0:42). The 
estimates therefore suggest that only for experienced subjects do prices seem to 
move away from the PIE towards to the FRE. 
To test whether markets are indeed successful at aggregating dispersed private 
information and revealing the true event through the equilibrium prices, we now focus 
on the end of the markets (i.e., window t ¼ 10). Panel A of Table 2 details the mean 
DIFF 10 apportioned by sessions and experience. Aggregating over all sessions, we do 
not find DIFF 10 to be significantly different from zero (Signrank, q ¼ 0:093, n ¼ 35). 
In contrast, we find DIFF 10 to be positive and significantly (Signrank, q ¼ 0:027, 
n ¼ 35) different from zero for experienced subjects. 
35 Together with the observations 
from Sects. 4.1.1 and 4.1.2, the evidence here leads us to our first result. </p>

<p>Result 1 For experienced subjects we find that (1) Markets frequently price the true asset 
significantly higher than the other assets, (2) There is no significant evidence of arbitrage 
opportunities at the end of the round, (3) Prices move towards the FRE and away from the 
PIE within a round, and (4) End of round prices are significantly closer to the FRE relative to 
the PIE. These observations do not hold for inexperienced subjects. The evidence therefore 
suggests that markets can be successful at information aggregation, even when the task is 
challenging and requires market participants to employ counterfactual reasoning, but only 
when market participants have experience with the trading mechanism or market design. </p>

<p>For further robustness checks, we also employ the approach of Plott and Sunder  (1988) and Forsythe and Lundholm (1990) where only the last (P1 price) and last 5 
(P5 prices) transactions prices of each asset are considered. For inexperienced 
subjects, we find P1 (Signrank, q ¼ 0:859, n ¼ 35) and P5 (Signrank, q ¼ 0:022, 
n ¼ 35) prices to be somewhat closer to the PIE. In contrast, P1 (Signrank, 
q ¼ 0:044, n ¼ 35) and P5 (Signrank, q ¼ 0:025, n ¼ 35) prices are significantly 
closer to the FRE for experienced subjects. </p>

<p>34 To setup our panel data model, we defined each round as an ''independent'' market, with the time 
variable t. Therefore, we estimated the fixed-effects model, clustering the standard errors at the session 
level. We also considered the estimates from GLLAMM (Rabe-Hesket et al. 2005) linear regression 
model, a class of Multilevel mixed models, which allows for a hierarchy of random effects for windows 
nested in rounds nested in sessions. The conclusions are similar. 
35 For further robustness checks, we also regressed DIFF 10 on a constant-fixed effect regression model. 
For inexperienced subjects, the constant is negative but not significantly different from zero at the 5% level. 
For experience subjects, the constant is positive and significantly different from zero at the 5% level. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>4.1.4 Homogeneous versus heterogeneous information events </p>

<p>Building on Result 1, we now investigate whether the information aggregation 
properties of markets depend on the information structure (i.e., homogeneous or 
heterogeneous events). </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>First consider those instances where the true and Alt-NM assets are the highest 
(A) and second highest (B) priced assets at window t. Focusing on window t ¼ 10, 
we compute the ratio p </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>10 =p </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>10 , the relative price of the true over the Alt-NM asset. 
This ratio does not differ significantly between homogeneous and heterogeneous 
events for inexperienced (Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:412, n ¼ 35) and for experienced 
(Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:372, n ¼ 35) subjects. 
Turning our attention to arbitrage opportunities, Fig. 4 details the median SUM t 
for homogeneous and heterogeneous events, apportioned by rounds. With the 
exception of round 4, there does not seem to be any obvious differences in SUM t for 
both events. Restricting our analysis to prices at the end of the round, Panel B of 
Table 2 details the mean SUM 10 apportioned by events and experience. Aggregating 
over all sessions, we do not find SUM 10 for homogeneous and heterogeneous events 
to be significantly different amongst inexperienced (Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:13, 
n ¼ 35) and experienced (Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:66, n ¼ 35) subjects. Similarly, 
we do not find SUM 10 for experienced subjects to be significantly different from 100 
for homogeneous (Signrank, q ¼ 0:54, n ¼ 10) and heterogeneous (Signrank, 
q ¼ 0:20, n ¼ 23) events. 
Finally, Fig. 5 details the DIFF t for homogeneous and heterogeneous events, 
apportioned by rounds. Now with the exception of round 5, there does not seem to 
be any differences in DIFF t amongst both events. Panel B of Table 2 also provides 
some summary statistics for DIFF 10 over the homogeneous and heterogeneous 
events. We again do not find any significant differences in DIFF 10 for inexperienced 
(Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:83, n ¼ 35) and experienced (Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:12, 
n ¼ 35) subjects. This leads us to the second result. </p>

<p>Result 2 For inexperienced and experienced subjects, we find that homogeneous 
and heterogeneous events do not result in significant end of round differences in (1) 
The ratio of highest and second highest priced assets, (2) Arbitrage opportunities, 
and (3) Differences in the mean absolute deviation of prices from the PIE and FRE. 
This suggests that the information aggregation properties of markets are 
independent of whether traders are endowed with homogeneous or heterogeneous 
private information about the true event. </p>

<p>4.2 Post-market stage </p>

<p>Turning our attention to the post-market stage, we define a subject to be correct if 
her submitted beliefs correspond to the true event, i.e., b ¼ xðs 
Ã Þ. The corresponding </p>

<p>36 For inexperienced subjects, there were 7 and 28 occurrences of homogeneous and heterogeneous 
information events, respectively. For experienced subjects, the corresponding occurrences are 10 and 23, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>proportions of correct inexperienced and experienced subjects are 0.51 and 0.71, 
respectively. 
Given that both PIE and FRE make precise predictions as to the submitted beliefs 
of minority and non-minority traders, it seems natural to investigate how such 
predictions match subjects' submitted beliefs. To do so, we compute the mean 
absolute deviations of the submitted beliefs from the PIE and FRE beliefs. </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>Submitted beliefs for inexperienced subjects are significantly closer to the PIE 
prediction (Signrank, q\0:01, n ¼ 35). This may not be surprising given that 
Result 1 suggests that the true event is unlikely to be reflected in prices. It is perhaps 
more surprising that beliefs submitted by experienced subjects are not significantly 
closer to either the FRE or the PIE prediction (Signrank, q ¼ 0:79, n ¼ 35) despite 
the fact that subjects could learn the true event by looking at the closing market 
prices. This result reveals that individual learning is not a necessary condition for 
successful information aggregation in prices. That is, it is possible for market prices 
to reflect the true event even when a sizeable proportion of traders remain 
uninformed of the true event. 
This result is consistent with the marginal trader hypothesis (e.g., Forsythe and  Lundholm 1990), which posits that it is sufficient to have a few sophisticated traders 
that understand how market prices are related to the states of the world in order to 
drive prices towards the FRE. We explore this possibility by using the post-market 
stage to identify the 'sophisticated' traders independent of their market behaviour. 
We define expert traders to be those who submitted a correct belief in at least nine 
out of the ten markets they participated in. This categorization yields 24% (20 of 84) 
expert traders. 
38 Table 3 presents mixed-effects regressions comparing the expert 
traders with the other traders. Columns (1) and (2) reveal that expert traders made 
larger profits, and held higher share of the true asset at the end of trade. Looking at 
the expert traders' purchase decisions, we see in Columns (3) and (4) that experts 
were more judicious in their purchase decisions, making fewer purchases, and being 
more likely to purchase the true asset compared to non-experts. The MAD in 
column (6) of the table, defined as the mean absolute deviation of the trader's 
purchases from the FRE, shows that the experts' mean purchase price is indeed 
significantly closer to the FRE price. To further test whether expert traders were 
more likely to push prices closer to the FRE, we look at how prices move with each 
purchase made by the trader. 
39 We define convergent purchases to be purchases 
made at a price that is at least as close to the FRE price as in the preceding 
transaction of the same asset. 
40 Column (5) in Table 3 details the share of </p>

<p>37 For example if xðs 
Ã Þ ¼ 1, then the FRE predicts that all 4 minority subjects and all 8 non-minority 
subjects will submit beliefs b ¼ 1. In contrast, the PIE predicts that beliefs b ¼ 0 and b ¼ 1 will be each 
submitted by 2 minority subjects. In addition, beliefs b ¼ 1 and b ¼ 2 will each be submitted by 4 
minority subjects. 
38 Only four traders submitted correct beliefs in all ten rounds. The results are robust to setting the 
criterion at 7, 8, or 10 correct beliefs. 
39 Selling decisions are more difficult to analyse since even traders who are informed about the true event 
should seek to sell assets at prices away from the FRE. 
40 Suppose that the sequence of purchase prices for an asset is 75, 79, 122, 60, 89 and 89 with the FRE 
price being 100. Then only the second, fifth and sixth purchases will be defined as convergent as they are </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>convergent purchases out of the trader's total purchases in the round. Close to 61% 
of non-experts' purchases do not move the price away from the FRE compared to 
65% for expert traders. This difference increases to nine percent points and becomes 
significant at the 10% level if we restrict the analysis to experienced traders only. 
Returning to the comparison of homogeneous and heterogeneous events, we find 
that inexperienced subjects are more likely to submit a correct belief in a 
heterogeneous event than in a homogeneous event (0.69 vs. 0.39, Fisher exact, 
q\0:001). With experience, however, we see a substantial improvement even in the 
homogeneous events. Experienced subjects are roughly equally likely to be correct 
in both event types, submitting correct beliefs in 0.73 and 0.65 of instances for the 
heterogeneous and homogeneous events, respectively (Fisher exact, q ¼ 0:152). 
41 It 
thus appears that homogeneous events pose greater difficulty for traders to discover 
the true state of the world. Notwithstanding, this does not impede price 
convergence. This conclusion should be taken cautiously, however, as the post-
market beliefs may be influenced by the ex-ante low probability of the 
homogeneous events. 
42 Result 3 summarises: </p>

<p>Table 3 Expert traders </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
Profits 
True in 
inventory </p>

<p>Total 
purchases </p>

<p>Proportion 
true </p>

<p>Proportion 
convergent </p>

<p>MAD </p>

<p>EXPERT 196.048 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(86.193) </p>

<p>9.814 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(3.946) </p>

<p>-2.429 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>(1.325) </p>

<p>0.161 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.040) </p>

<p>0.044 (0.029) 
-8.651 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(2.240) </p>

<p>Round 
-0.038 
(0.157) </p>

<p>-0.481 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.107) </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(0.004) </p>

<p>0.004 (0.004) 
-4.650 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.290) </p>

<p>Constant 553.322 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(24.561) </p>

<p>22.254 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.836) </p>

<p>12.940 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(1.333) </p>

<p>0.352 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.040) </p>

<p>0.584 
a (0.031) 
73.898 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(3.099) </p>

<p>N 
840 
840 
840 
553 
768 
768 </p>

<p>Mixed-effects regressions with random effects for subjects and robust standard errors clustered at the 
session level. Note that profits do not change across rounds as trade is zero-sum </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>q\0:01 
b q\0:05 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>q\0:10 </p>

<p>Footnote 40 continued 
no further away from 100 than the preceding purchase. If the FRE price is instead 0, then only fourth and 
sixth can be defined as convergent purchases. 
41 Alternatively, we can also consider the mean absolute deviations of submitted beliefs from the FRE 
predictions. For inexperienced subjects, submitted beliefs are closer to the FRE predictions in 
heterogeneous relative to homogeneous information events (Mann-Whitney, q\0:001, n ¼ 35). In 
contrast, we find no significant differences for experienced subjects (Mann-Whitney, q ¼ 0:328, n ¼ 35). 
42 This explanation implies a failure to properly apply Bayes' rule. To see why, first consider the case 
where s 
Ã ¼ OOO (homogeneous event). By Bayes' rule, each uninformed subject should assign equal 
probability to the events 0 and 1. However, the prior probability of nature choosing event 1 is also three 
times more than 0. Thus, the failure to properly apply Bayes' rule will lead to uninformed subjects 
incorrectly assigning greater weights to the event 1. Now consider the case where s 
Ã ¼ XXO 
(heterogeneous event). Traders in groups 1 and 2 should believe that events 1 and 2 are possible. Since </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>Result 3 Inexperienced traders remain uninformed about the true state of the 
world. Although with experience market prices converge to the FRE prices, traders 
remain largely uninformed. There is some evidence that a few sophisticated traders 
both succeed in discovering the true state and are instrumental in driving prices 
towards the FRE. </p>

<p>4.3 Minority report </p>

<p>The reasoning model of Sect. 3.3 predicts that minority traders in the heterogeneous 
events learn about the true state before the non-minority traders, and are influential 
at driving prices towards the FRE. In this section we test these predictions using the 
market behaviour and submitted beliefs of minority traders. 
Table 4 provides some evidence supporting the model's predictions. Comparing 
behaviour in the heterogeneous events within subjects, we find that when 
(exogenously) placed in the minority role, traders are better informed, as measured 
by post-market beliefs (p\0:05 for the marginal effect in the regression reported in 
Column (1)). Column (4) shows that minority traders are more active, making 9% 
more purchases than non-minorities. They are, however, not more likely to purchase 
the true asset or to make a convergent purchase, as seen in Columns (5) and (6). 
Notwithstanding, Column (7) reveals that minority traders buy at closer to the FRE 
price, suggesting that when minority traders do make a convergent purchase, their 
purchase price moves a larger distance from the preceding traded price towards the 
FRE price. Finally, Columns (2) and (3) show that, at the end of trade, minority 
traders hold a larger share of the true asset in their inventory, but do not make a 
larger profit overall compared to rounds in which they are cast in the non-minority 
role. Result 4 summarises these observations. </p>

<p>Result 4 Relative to non-minority subjects, minority subjects (1) Are significantly 
more likely to be correct, (2) Hold a significantly greater proportion of the true 
asset in their inventory and (3) Purchase additional assets at prices significantly 
closer to the FRE. This provides some tentative evidence that minority subjects are 
informed about the true event before the others and are influential at driving prices 
towards the FRE. </p>

<p>If minority traders are better informed, why are they unable to leverage their 
knowledge to purchase the true asset at a discount and thus improve their payoffs? A 
central claim of the efficient market hypothesis (e.g., Fama 1970) is that if markets 
are strong-form efficient, then any trader seeking to exploit his private information 
immediately reveals the same information from his demand of assets, thus negating 
any possible gains. Furthermore, competitive bidding between minority subjects 
might also reduce the scope for such gains. </p>

<p>Footnote 42 continued 
nature chooses events 1 and 2 each with probability 3 / 8, such subjects should not weight one event 
more than the other, even when they fail to properly apply Bayes rule. However, for traders in group 3, 
the failure to properly apply Bayes' rule will lead them to put greater weights on event 2, given that the 
prior probability on event 3 is 1/8. Thus, the proportion of correct subjects will be more than 1/2. </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>The above suggests that whilst minority traders may initially be able to profit 
their knowledge of the true event, such gains will eventually be eroded over time. 
To study the development of minority gains over time , we compute the liquidation 
value (i.e., how much the portfolio of cash and assets is worth after the loan of 5000 
ECU is returned) of the trader's portfolio at window t. We then regress for each 
window t, the liquidation value on the minority subjects, using fixed subject effects 
with session level clustering. The minority dummy coefficient, b 1;t , thus captures 
the expected difference in liquidation value between the minority and non-minority 
roles at window t. Figure 6 plots the estimate for b 1;t at each window t. The hump 
shape distribution of b 1 suggests that the liquidation value of a minority trader 
increases during the early periods of the round (i.e., between windows 2-5), with the 
gap disappearing as trade proceeds. However, the differences are not significant at 
the 5% level. </p>

<p>5 Conclusion </p>

<p>This study is motivated by the question as to whether markets are able to aggregate 
dispersed private information about the true state of the world into prices. We 
consider an experimental design which allows us to endow traders with homoge-
neous and heterogeneous private information about the true event. With this 
framework, we advance a simple model which shows that markets converge to the 
fully revealing rational expectations equilibrium for both homogeneous and 
heterogeneous cases, indicating that the true event will be reflected in prices. 
However, the process of convergence to the FRE is challenging and requires traders 
to perform counterfactual reasoning. A post-market stage allows us to estimate </p>

<p>Table 4 Minority traders </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
Correct 
beliefs </p>

<p>Profits 
True in 
inventory </p>

<p>Total 
purchases </p>

<p>Proportion 
true </p>

<p>Proportion 
convergent </p>

<p>MAD </p>

<p>Minority 0.106 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>(0.045) </p>

<p>-6.006 
(30.259) </p>

<p>2.204 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(0.815) </p>

<p>2.928 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.441) </p>

<p>0.002 
(0.020) </p>

<p>-0.009 
(0.023) </p>

<p>-6.672 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(2.033) </p>

<p>Round 
0.031 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>(0.009) </p>

<p>0.022 
(0.189) </p>

<p>-0.462 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.080) </p>

<p>0.006 
(0.004) </p>

<p>0.003 (0.005) -4.835 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(0.246) </p>

<p>Constant 0.459 
(0.047) </p>

<p>602.002 
(10.086) </p>

<p>23.789 
(1.125) </p>

<p>11.653 
(0.414) </p>

<p>0.401 
(0.024) </p>

<p>0.594 (0.026) 72.497 
(1.507) </p>

<p>N 
636 
636 
636 
636 
405 
581 
581 </p>

<p>OLS regressions with subject fixed effects and robust standard errors clustered at the session level. Only 
data from the heterogeneous events is included. Note that profits do not change across rounds as trade is 
zero-sum </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>q\0:01 
b q\0:05 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>q\0:10 </p>

<p>Information aggregation in Arrow-Debreu markets: an... </p>



<p>individual learning independent of market activity, and to correlate learning and 
market behaviour. 
We find that markets can be successful at aggregating information, but only when 
market participants have experience with the trading mechanisms. When traders are 
experienced, the market prices successfully aggregate and reflect the true state, even 
when traders start out with induced homogeneous beliefs. The requirement for 
counterfactual reasoning does not appear to impede market convergence. Although 
the prices reveal the true state, individual learning is strongly constrained. 
Consistent with the marginal trader hypothesis, we find that a limited number of 
sophisticated traders is sufficient to drive market prices towards the rational 
expectations equilibrium. The role traders play in price convergence depends both 
on endogenous characteristics and on information asymmetries. The last point 
suggests that even when some traders gain insider knowledge, markets can 
efficiently price this knowledge. 
Taken together, this paper extends the pioneering work by Plott and Sunder  (1988) on information aggregation in an environment which we believe to be 
significantly more complicated. The new design allows us to explore questions of 
information structure complexity and symmetry, and compare market results to 
directly elicited post-market beliefs. We conclude that markets composed of 
experienced traders are able to successfully aggregate dispersed information even in 
a challenging environment, and even if only a minority of the traders become fully 
informed in the process. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We thank Ariel Levy, Emma-Riikka Myllymäki, and participants at the ESA 2016 
international meeting in Jerusalem, Experimental Finance 2015 in Nijmegen, Exeter Prize 2016 workshop </p>

<p>-100 -75 -50 -25 0 25 50 75 100 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
30 second time block (t) </p>

<p>1,t </p>

<p>Coef. Estimate for </p>

<p>1,t </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Coefficient estimate of b 1;t . We regress subjects' liquidation value at window t on a constant and 
situation dummy for minority subjects (b 1;t coefficient). The above details the estimate of b at each t </p>

<p>L. Choo et al. </p>



<p>and World Finance Conference 2017 in Sardinia for helpful comments and discussion. The authors would 
like to thank Shyam Sunder whose suggestions motivated this experimental research. </p>

<p>Funding Funding was provided by University of Exeter. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original 
author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were 
made. </p>









</text></tei>