<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fsjpe.12150" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Recent studies on the effects of anti-smoking policies on subjective well-being 
present mixed results and do not account for potential externalities, especially 
among couples. We contribute to the literature by evaluating the impact of 
smoking bans on well-being externalities among smokers and non-smokers as 
well as couples of different types of smokers. We exploit the policy experiment 
provided by the timing of the UK public smoking bans and measure well-being 
via the GHQ. We employ matching techniques combined with flexible difference-
in-differences fixed effects panel data models on data from the British Household 
Panel Survey. The joint use of matching with fixed effects specifications allows 
building more comparable treatment and control groups, producing less model-
dependent results and accounting for individual-level unobserved heterogeneity. 
We find that public smoking bans appear to have a statistically significant short-
term positive impact on the well-being of married individuals, especially among 
women with dependent children. These effects appear to be robust to alternative 
specifications and placebo tests and are discussed in the light of the economic 
theory and recent evidence. </p>

<p>the introduction of smoking bans appear to present higher levels of life satis-
faction. The author suggests that this may imply that current smokers are 
time-inconsistent and might benefit from anti-smoking policies. Odermatt and  Stutzer (2015) used data from 40 European countries and also suggested that 
smokers who would like to quit smoking report higher levels of life satisfac-
tion after the implementation of smoking bans. However, they do not find sig-
nificant effects of smoking bans on SWB. Hinks and Katsaros (2010)  employed UK data and found that smokers who reduce their intake of cigar-
ettes after the ban report significantly lower levels of life satisfaction if com-
pared to individuals who did not reduce their amount of tobacco intake (and 
smoked the same pre-ban amount of cigarettes). Leicester and Levell (2016)  also exploited UK data and found that while tobacco excise taxes increase 
smokers' well-being, the impact of smoking bans appears to be weaker. Over-
all, these papers tend to overlook potential intra-household well-being exter-
nalities and appear to present conflicting results. 
3 Furthermore, most of these 
studies do not appear to fully exploit the longitudinal nature of their data and 
do not explicitly account for the presence of individual-level unobserved 
heterogeneity. 
The main objective of this paper is to evaluate the intra-couple well-being 
externalities of public smoking bans among couples of different types of 
smokers. We employ UK longitudinal data from the British Household 
Panel Survey (BHPS) and exploit the policy experiment provided by the dif-
ferential timing of the introduction of public smoking bans in Scotland and 
England. We combine matching techniques with a series of flexible differ-
ence-in-differences fixed effects panel data models to estimate the impact of 
public smoking bans on the SWB of smokers, non-smokers and couples of 
different types of smokers. We find that the UK public smoking bans appear 
to have a positive and statistically significant short-term effect on the well-
being of married individuals, especially among women with dependent chil-
dren. These effects appear to be robust to alternative specifications and pla-
cebo tests. Our results appear to suggest that public smoking bans may 
produce short-term positive externalities by increasing the SWB of individu-
als in couples with dependent children, especially women. We discuss and 
interpret these results also in the light of the economic theory and recent 
evidence. 
This paper provides several contributions to the literature. First, we build 
upon and extend previous analyses on the impact of smoking bans by focus-
ing on well-being externalities. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first 
paper that focuses on bans driven well-being externalities among couples of 
smokers and non-smokers by employing a policy experiment. Secondly, we 
combine matching methods with difference-in-differences to build more com-
parable treatment and control groups, produce less model-dependent results 
and thus increase the reliability of our identification strategy. Finally, we </p>

<p>3 It might be argued that some of the measures of overall life satisfaction used in these 
studies may indirectly account for potential intra-household externalities. However, previous 
studies do not seem to focus on well-being externalities, especially among couples. </p>

<p>. More specifically, the GHQ is a summary mea-
sure of psychological distress based on 12 questions concerning both positive 
and negative recent emotional experiences (Gardner and Oswald, 2007). 
7 In this 
study, we use the GHQ measured on the Likert scale with values ranging from 0 
to 36 (computed by taking the sum of the responses to the 12 questions and 
assigning values of 0 to the ones corresponding to the highest levels of well-being 
and 3 to the ones corresponding to lowest levels of well-being). The resulting 
measure is a summary index of well-being that is increasing in psychological dis-
tress: higher GHQ values correspond to lower levels of well-being. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>As our main objective was to identify variations in well-being driven by 
smoking bans within a relatively short period of time, the use of the GHQ 
appears to be appropriate as it is often employed to define short-term fluctua-
tions of emotional distress (for a discussion see Powdthavee and van den  Berg, 2011). More general measures of 'total' or 'global' well-being such as 
life satisfaction might be less prone to detect temporary affective changes. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Furthermore, we exploit intra-couple information on well-being to define </p>

<p>7 The 12-item version includes questions on: concentration; loss of sleep; playing a useful 
role; being capable of making decisions; being constantly under strain; having problems over-
coming difficulties; enjoying day-to-day activities; ability to face problems, unhappiness/de-
pression; losing confidence; believing in self-worth; and general happiness. For each item/ 
question, respondents are asked to choose between four answers ranging from 1 to 4, with 
higher scores reflecting lower levels of well-being. Therefore, higher scores of the GHQ reflect 
lower levels of SWB. An example of the GHQ question is as follows: 'Have you recently 
been able to concentrate on whatever you're doing?' followed by the answers 'Better than 
usual (1)', 'same as usual (2)', 'less than usual (3)' and 'much less than usual (4)'. 
8 We have also estimated models using the 12 items from the GHQ separately. Results are 
available upon request. 
9 We have also considered the use of a measure of life satisfaction in an earlier version of 
the paper. However, this measure is only present in selected waves of the BHPS, leading to 
small sample sizes of treated individuals for most of the sub-samples employed in our analy-
sis. This produced imprecise point estimates with large standard errors. </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>externalities. More specifically, we focus on changes in well-being among 
spouses of different types of smokers as we expect externalities to be more rel-
evant for these sub-groups of individuals. </p>

<p>Covariates and descriptive statistics </p>

<p>The BHPS contains rich information on demographic and socioeconomic indi-
vidual-level characteristics that we include in our panel data models. Our 
models control for age (age and age squared); gender (by estimating separate 
models for men and women); employment status (self-employed, unemployed; 
retired; family care; student; long-term sick/disability status; government train-
ing or in other jobs; all contrasted against being employed as an employee); 
marital status (by estimating separate models for individuals married or in a 
couple vs. single/divorced/widowed); and household related variables including 
household size and the number of dependent children living within the house-
hold (if present). </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>In the BHPS, information on smoking prevalence and intensity is based 
on the questions 'Do you smoke cigarettes?' and 'Approximately, how 
many cigarettes a day do you usually smoke?' respectively. For the purpose 
of our analysis, we define two types of individuals: potential smokers and 
never smokers. Potential smokers are individuals who report being a smo-
ker at least once during the survey period (i.e. individuals who answered 
'yes' to the question on smoking prevalence at least once). Never smokers 
are defined as individuals who always reported being non-smokers through-
out the entire period of the survey. Our definition of potential smokers 
allows us to go beyond current smoking status that might be affected by 
the introduction of the smoking bans while also including individuals with 
a propensity to smoke. Robustness checks provide key results for alterna-
tive definitions of smokers. 
Table 1 presents summary statistics of the main variables in our analysis. 
These variables are presented for males and females separately. As our analy-
sis will focus on the effects of smoking bans on intra-couple well-being exter-
nalities, descriptive statistics are both presented for the overall unmatched 
sample (i.e. married and single individuals together) and are broken down by 
marital status (married/living with a partner vs. unmarried/single). 
11 Overall, 
there is a higher prevalence of smoking among men in all samples, especially 
among single men with an average of around 29%. Smoking intensity also 
appears to be larger among men with the highest mean value of daily number 
of cigarettes among married male individuals (16.5 cigarettes per day). 
Throughout all samples, women appear to present slightly lower levels of 
SWB (higher GHQ levels) if compared to men and the highest levels of </p>

<p>10 An earlier version of this paper included health status via self-assessed health and the 
presence of breathing and heart related problems. To avoid any potential issues around bad 
controls and post-treatment bias, we have removed these variables from our analysis. 
11 To avoid changes in the composition of treated and control groups over time, we 
include in our sub-samples of married vs. single only those individuals who do not change 
marital status and are either married or single throughout waves 9-16. </p>

<p>distress seem to be concentrated among single women. A higher proportion of 
men appear to be married or in a couple, yet women appear to show a gener-
ally higher average number of children. </p>

<p>IV ECONOMETRIC METHODS </p>

<p>We estimate the impact of smoking bans on SWB by exploiting the differ-
ent timing of the introduction of the Scottish and English smoking bans. 
As an identical public smoking ban was implemented in England 1 year 
later than in Scotland, we can identify our treatment effect by computing 
differences in well-being between Scottish and English individuals before 
and after the implementation of the ban in Scotland via difference-in-differ-
ences (DD) models (Ashenfelter, 1978; Ashenfelter and Card, 1985; Heck- man and Robb, 1985). We first employ standard two-way fixed effects 
models (2FE) using Scotland and England as treated and control groups 
respectively, and then use a more flexible model with fixed effects and 
country-specific time trends that allows for different policy effects by region 
and time. We also combine our DD models with matching techniques to 
pre-process the data and enhance comparability between treatment and 
control groups while improving the overall credibility of our identification 
strategy (Ho et al.Matching </p>

<p>We first use matching to pre-process the data before the estimation of our 
DD models in order to produce more accurate and less model-dependent esti-
mates. The pre-processing approach matches the pre-treatment observable 
characteristics of individuals in treated and control groups to increase their 
comparability. The approach was proposed by Ho et al. (2007) and further 
discussed and applied in a number of recent studies (e.g. Blackwell et al.,  2009; Hainmueller and Xu, 2011; Iacus et al., 2011; Jones and Rice, 2011;  King et al., 2011). In this case, the main goal of matching is to ensure that 
individuals in treatment (Scotland) and control (England) groups are as simi-
lar as possible in terms of covariate distribution. An advantage of this com-
bined approach is that it is 'doubly robust' in that under weak conditions 
(and excluding extreme cases where matching would lead to non-identification 
even when the subsequent parametric models are correctly specified) if either 
the matching or parametric models are correct, causal estimates should be 
consistent (Bickel and Kwon, 2001; Ho et al., 2007). 
In order to pre-process the data, we have applied a series of alternative 
matching methods such as nearest neighbour, kernel and Mahalanobis dis-
tance matching. The DD estimates presented in our result section are based 
on kernel matching. 
12 In this case, kernel matching is preferred as it 
exploits a wider range of information on individuals in the control group 
to achieve a lower variance. 
Table 2 shows the reduction in bias on observables obtained through kernel 
matching based on the pre-treatment (smoking ban) wave (i.e. wave 15). The 
matched sample used for the subsequent empirical analysis includes 2220 indi-
viduals from Scotland and 6227 individuals from England. The first four col-
umns present statistics based on the unmatched sample, while columns five to 
eight are based on the matched sample. The table displays mean values of 
each variable and provides standard t-test statistics to measure differences 
between mean values of the observables between treated and control groups. 
It appears that a number of variables are significantly different across treat-
ment and control groups based on the unmatched sample (e.g. age, household 
size and income; employment status such as working in family care and being 
a student), while none of these covariates appear to show significant differ-
ences after the matching. This underlines that in this case kernel matching </p>

<p>12 Results based on nearest neighbour and Mahalanobis distance matching are similar and 
available upon request. Kernel matching builds the counterfactual outcome using weighted 
averages of all individuals in the control group, with higher weights being placed on the 
untreated individuals with scores closer to the treated. We impose common support condi-
tion and use a bandwidth of 0.01. We have also used alternative bandwidth values (e.g. 
0.005, 0.0025 and 0.00125); however, in our case lower bandwidths lead to a smaller sample 
size and do not appear to improve the overall quality of the matching. Hence, we present 
our results based on a 0.01 bandwidth. While the results presented here are based on obser-
vations included in the pre-treatment wave (wave 15), we have also tested kernel matching 
using observations throughout waves 9-15. Results are virtually identical and available upon 
request. </p>

<p>appears to have reduced differences in the observables of individuals in treated 
and control groups. </p>

<p>Two-way fixed effects models </p>

<p>We estimate the impact of the smoking bans on the GHQ of smokers, 
non-smokers and couples using 2FE. These models exploit differences in 
reported SWB between England and Scotland from 1999 to 2007 (waves 9-
16) while controlling for observed individual characteristics, time effects 
and time-invariant individual-level unobserved heterogeneity. Our basic 2FE 
model is: </p>

<p>y it ¼ a þ s s ðS i P t Þ þ X it ; þ v t þ u i þ e it 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where y it is SWB measured by the GHQ of an individual i at time t. S i is 
a dummy variable defining whether an individual resides in Scotland 
(S i = 1) while P t is an indicator for the post-ban period (i.e. P t = 1 if the 
smoking ban is in force at survey time t, 0 otherwise). The treatment effect 
is identified by s s , an interaction between country of residence and the 
post-ban period. X it is a vector of individual observed characteristics at 
time t (age and age squared, marital status, household characteristics, 
income and employment status) and u i represents individual fixed effects. 
The inclusion of fixed effects allows capturing individual-level unobservable 
confounders and more specifically to ease concerns around the potential 
correlation between treatment status and error terms driven by unobserved 
characteristics (provided that this correlation is confined to the unobserved 
effects). 
13 The time dummies m t account for time trends common to both 
the treatment and control groups. e it is an idiosyncratic error term. This is 
a DD estimator with one of the differences corresponding to the within-
individual difference of a standard fixed effects estimator (Jones and Rice,  2011). </p>

<p>Country-specific time trends models </p>

<p>As an alternative to the basic 2FE model, we also estimate a more flexible 
specification with fixed effects and country-specific time trends (CSTT). This is 
a more general specification which nests model (1) as a special case and identi-
fies the impact of the UK smoking bans by disentangling the treatment effect 
by countries and different time periods: </p>

<p>Y it ¼ a þ S i </p>

<p>X T </p>

<p>t¼1 </p>

<p>s St m t þ E i 
X T </p>

<p>t¼2 </p>

<p>s Et m t þ X it ; þ u i þ e it 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>The impact of the bans on SWB is captured by the parameters s St and s Et 
on the interactions between being resident in Scotland (S i = 1) or England 
(E i = 1), and the time dummies m t . Here, changes in SWB related to the </p>

<p>13 Specifications without fixed effects appear to produce similar results. Estimates are avail-
able upon request. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>

<p>V RESULTS </p>

<p>Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>Identification of the average treatment effect on the treated through DD mod-
els relies on the parallel trend assumption so that values of our outcome of 
interest, well-being defined via the GHQ, should follow similar pre-treatment 
time trends in both Scotland and England. To examine whether this assump-
tion holds, we display GHQ trends by country of residence, gender, marital 
status and the presence of dependent children in Figure 1. For the overall 
population (which includes both married and single individuals with and with-
out children, upper part of Figure 1), GHQ trends appear to be broadly simi-
lar in Scotland and England before the introduction of the bans. More 
specifically, while for Scottish and English women GHQ trends appear to 
slightly converge between waves 14 and 15 (i.e. 1 year before the introduction 
of the ban in Scotland, although this change amounts to less than a half 
GHQ point), pre-Scottish ban trends appear very similar for male individu-
als. 
15 Both graphs show that in the year when the Scottish ban was introduced 
(between waves 15 and 16), GHQ levels in Scotland appear to decrease (im-
plying a small increase in SWB), especially among women. Still for the overall 
population sample of men, SWB also appears to somewhat increase in Eng-
land after the smoking ban. Graphs for married individuals of both genders 
(second row of Figure 1) appear to display GHQ trends comparable to the 
ones of the overall population. Single women in Scotland and England (third 
row of Figure 1) show virtually identical self-reported GHQ trends, also dur-
ing the introduction of the two bans with slight increases in SWB between 
waves 15 and 16 (Scottish ban) followed by decreases in SWB between waves 
16 and 17 (English ban). However, SWB reported by single men seem to vary 
during the pre-Scottish ban period, although only between GHQ scores of 10 
and 11. Men and women with children (fourth row of Figure 1) exhibit rela-
tively stable differences in GHQ levels between England and Scotland before 
the Scottish ban with increases in SWB during the Scottish ban and simulta-
neous slight decreases in England. However, the very stable GHQ levels </p>

<p>14 In this case, we use England in wave 9 as a baseline country-specific time trend as no 
public smoking ban was in place at that time. Treatment effects are computed using differ-
ences between estimated interaction terms, i.e. interactions between country of residence and 
time dummies, before and after the Scottish ban in England and Scotland. More specifically, 
the corresponding treatment effect reported in each table is the one obtained by the following 
double difference: (Scotland*wave 16 -England*wave 16) -(Scotland*wave 15 -Eng-
land*wave 15) where waves 15 and 16 are the pre-and post-Scottish ban waves in the BHPS 
respectively. Standard errors for these treatment effects are obtained using the lincom com-
mand in <rs type="software">Stata</rs>. 
15 The presence of anticipation effects on well-being is explored using placebo tests in 
Table 7. </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 
GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Overall population -Men </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 
GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Overall population -Women </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Married -Men </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Married -Women </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Single -Men </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>Single -Women </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>With child -Men </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>With child -Women </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>No child -Men </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>9 
1 0 
1 1 
1 2 
1 3 
1 4 
1 5 
1 6 
1 7 
1 8 </p>

<p>GHQ likert scale </p>

<p>Waves </p>

<p>No child -Women </p>

<p>Scotland </p>

<p>England </p>

<p>Figure 1. GHQ trends in Scotland and England (after kernel matching). 
The continuous vertical lines indicate the Scottish smoking ban, while the dashed lines 
represent the English bans. All graphs are based on matched samples of individuals obtained 
using kernel matching. GHQ trends based on unmatched samples are similar and available 
upon request. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>among men and women without children (last row) do not appear to be 
affected by the introduction of the smoking bans. Overall, we observe mostly 
stable pre-treatment trends and increases in SWB in the year of the implemen-
tation of the Scottish ban, especially among women. Yet, specific sub-groups 
display some, although limited, variation in pre-treatment GHQ trends (e.g. 
single men) while others present no apparent changes in GHQ levels in the 
presence of the bans (e.g. men with no children). </p>

<p>Estimates </p>

<p>In order to examine whether there are any intra-couple well-being externalities 
driven by the public smoking bans, we first present estimates separately by 
gender (men vs. women), marital status (married/living with a partner vs. sin-
gle) and smoking status (overall population, potential smokers and never 
smokers), see Table 3. Furthermore, to identify potential well-being externali-
ties within couples of different types of smokers, we present estimates also 
broken down by the smoking status of spouses (whether spouses are potential 
smokers vs. spouses of never smokers), see Table 4, and whether these couples 
have cohabiting dependent children, see Table 5. 
Estimates of both 2FE and CSTT models are produced by combining ker-
nel matching with DD linear fixed effects models. All treatments effects should 
be interpreted as point changes on the GHQ Likert scale. Table 3 displays 
estimates of the impact of the Scottish public smoking ban on well-being pro-
duced by 2FE and CSTT models. The majority of treatment effects for mar-
ried men and women appear to be negative and statistically significant in both 
models. As lower GHQ scores correspond to higher levels of well-being, this 
suggests that the Scottish ban had a positive and statistically significant 
impact on the SWB of married individuals. For married male individuals 
(overall population, that is potential smokers and never smokers together), 
the ban led to a decrease in the GHQ (increase in well-being) of around 
between 0.4 and 0.5 points on the Likert scale (0.438, 2FE model, and 0.506, 
CSTT model at 5% significance level), while for married females (overall pop-
ulation) the decrease in the GHQ appears to be well-over half a point (be-
tween 0.543 and 0.708). The ban does not appear to have had a statistically 
significant effect among single men or women. Married male and female never 
smokers also appear to experience statistically significant increases in well-
being (around 0.5 points and 0.46-0.80 points, respectively). Therefore, the 
ban appears to have led to an increase in well-being among married men and 
women, and larger impacts have been found among married individuals who 
are never smokers compared to those who are potential smokers. 
Table 4 reports treatment effects from 2FE and CSTT models broken down 
by gender, type of smokers and 'smoking type' of each spouse. We observe nega-
tive and statistically significant effects for both genders among the overall popu-
lation and never smokers. Although presenting similar size and signs, treatments 
effects among potential smokers do not appear to be statistically significant. 
However, this may be partly due to the increased standard errors potentially </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>driven by the relative small amount of observations available to estimate these 
models (especially the ones for women who are potential smokers and married/ 
living with a never smoker). The largest statistically significant improvements in 
well-being following the ban are observed among males who are never smokers 
and married/living with potential smokers (with a decrease of around 0.97 GHQ 
points and statistically significant at 5% level in the 2FE model) while, although 
sizeable (0.76-1.8 GHQ points), the effects for the corresponding female sub-</p>

<p>Table 3 
The impact of the Scottish ban on well-being </p>

<p>ATET Scotland 
2FE 
CSTT </p>

<p>Overall population 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.438 (0.184)** 
À0.506 (0.205)** 
N 
17,385 
17,385 
Single 
0.236 (0.372) 
À0.101 (0.453) 
N 
4833 
4833 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
À0.543 (0.194)*** 
À0.708 (0.227)*** 
N 
19,003 
19,003 
Single 
À0.039 (0.313) 
0.094 (0.369) 
N 
7366 
7366 </p>

<p>Potential smokers 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.283 (0.346) 
À0.552 (0.385) 
N 
6022 
6022 
Single 
0.259 (0.671) 
À0.442 (0.819) 
N 
1749 
1749 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
À0.708 (0.390)* 
À0.484 (0.434) 
N 
5976 
5976 
Single 
0.225 (0.552) 
0.426 (0.634) 
N 
2746 
2746 </p>

<p>Never smokers 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.522 (0.214)** 
À0.482 (0.238)** 
N 
11,363 
11,363 
Single 
0.389 (0.393) 
0.272 (0.478) 
N 
3084 
3084 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
À0.459 (0.222)** 
À0.795 (0.264)*** 
N 
13,027 
13,072 
Single 
À0.190 (0.372) 
À0.079 (0.449) 
N 
4620 
4620 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses. Statistical significance: ***1% level; **5% level; *10% level. This table 
reports average treatment effects on the treated (ATET) obtained from panel data difference-in-differences 
models (2-way fixed effects model, 2FE, and country-specific time-trends models, CSTT). Subjective well-
being is defined using the GHQ12. Models were estimated using linear fixed effects specifications on 
matched samples obtained using kernel matching. All models include individual fixed effects, the full bat-
tery of controls and dummies for the time trend. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>samples are only weakly significant. There appears to be statistically significant 
improvements in well-being also among never smokers married/living with a 
never smoker, among both males and females (around 0.5-0.6 GHQ points for 
males, around 0.7 for females, though only for the CSTT model). This implies 
that the ban appeared to have had a positive impact especially among never 
smokers, regardless of the smoking status of their partners. </p>

<p>Table 4 
The impact of the Scottish ban on well-being externalities among couples </p>

<p>2FE 
CSTT </p>

<p>Overall population 
Men 
Men 
Spouse: potential smoker 
À0.662 (0.357)* 
À0.551 (0.399) 
N 
5033 
5033 
Spouse: never smoker 
À0.350 (0.224) 
À0.492 (0.252)* 
N 
11,122 
11,122 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Spouse: potential smokers 
À0.732 (0.384)* 
À0.852 (0.445)* 
N 
5588 
5588 
Spouse: never smoker 
À0.384 (0.251) 
À0.623 (0.295)** 
N 
10,697 
10,697 </p>

<p>Potential smokers 
Men 
Men 
Spouse: potential smoker 
À0.605 (0.505) 
À0.809 (0.564) 
N 
3213 
3213 
Spouse: never smoker 
0.244 (0.523) 
À0.120 (0.570) 
N 
2321 
2321 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Spouse: potential smoker 
À0.666 (0.587) 
À0.577 (0.606) 
N 
3217 
3217 
Spouse: never smoker 
À0.428 (0.659) 
À0.306 (0.785) 
N 
1739 
1739 </p>

<p>Never smokers 
Men 
Men 
Spouse: potential smoker 
À0.970 (0.476)** 
0.271 (0.542) 
N 
1820 
1820 
Spouse: never smoker 
À0.520 (0.247)** 
À0.615 (0.281)** 
N 
8801 
8801 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Spouse: potential smoker 
À0.759 (0.458)* 
À1.179 (0.651)* 
N 
2371 
2371 
Spouse: never smoker 
À0.380 (0.271) 
À0.694 (0.317)** 
N 
8958 
8958 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses. Statistical significance: ***1% level; ** 5% level; * 10% level. This table 
reports average treatment effects on the treated (ATET) obtained from panel data difference-in-differences 
models (2-way fixed effects model, 2FE, and country-specific time-trends models, CSTT). Subjective well-
being is defined using the GHQ12. Models were estimated using linear fixed effects specifications on 
matched samples obtained using Kernel matching. All models include individual fixed effects, the full bat-
tery of controls and dummies for the time trend. </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>Table 5 </p>

<p>The impact of the Scottish ban among couples with and without dependent children </p>

<p>Men </p>

<p>Women </p>

<p>Overall population </p>

<p>Potential smokers </p>

<p>Never smokers </p>

<p>Overall population </p>

<p>Potential smokers </p>

<p>Never smokers </p>

<p>Without children 
Spouse: overall population </p>

<p>À0.263 (0.245) </p>

<p>À0.558 (0.470) </p>

<p>À0.184 (0.279) </p>

<p>0.059 (0.280) </p>

<p>À0.504 (0.587) </p>

<p>0.248 (0.302) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>8545 </p>

<p>2690 </p>

<p>5855 </p>

<p>9145 </p>

<p>2687 </p>

<p>6458 </p>

<p>Spouse: potential smoker </p>

<p>À0.499 (0.446) </p>

<p>À0.809 (0.682) </p>

<p>À0.570 (0.503) </p>

<p>À0.087 (0.553) </p>

<p>0.152 (0.848) </p>

<p>À0.392 (0.563) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>2550 </p>

<p>1526 </p>

<p>1024 </p>

<p>2672 </p>

<p>1495 </p>

<p>1177 </p>

<p>Spouse: never smoker </p>

<p>À0.090 (0.295) </p>

<p>À0.185 (0.635) </p>

<p>À0.079 (0.330) </p>

<p>0.146 (0.333) </p>

<p>À0.705 (0.830) </p>

<p>0.267 (0.350) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>5918 </p>

<p>1134 </p>

<p>4784 </p>

<p>5878 </p>

<p>971 </p>

<p>4907 </p>

<p>With children 
Spouse: overall population </p>

<p>À0.568 (0.387) </p>

<p>À0.074 (0.732) </p>

<p>À0.835 (0.432)* </p>

<p>À1.162 (0.401)*** </p>

<p>À1.711 (0.743)** </p>

<p>À0.882 (0.478)* </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>4397 </p>

<p>1703 </p>

<p>2691 </p>

<p>4762 </p>

<p>1530 </p>

<p>3232 </p>

<p>Spouse: potential smoker </p>

<p>À0.711 (0.744) </p>

<p>À0.001 (0.975) </p>

<p>À1.853 (1.261) </p>

<p>À1.556 (0.692)** </p>

<p>À2.344 (0.986)** </p>

<p>À0.606 (0.969) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>1379 </p>

<p>935 </p>

<p>444 </p>

<p>1717 </p>

<p>957 </p>

<p>760 </p>

<p>Spouse: never smoker </p>

<p>À0.605 (0.433) </p>

<p>À0.373 (1.132) </p>

<p>À0.705 (0.456) </p>

<p>À0.677 (0.536) </p>

<p>0.183 (1.351) </p>

<p>À0.850 (0.597) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>2978 </p>

<p>739 </p>

<p>2239 </p>

<p>2701 </p>

<p>441 </p>

<p>2260 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses. Statistical significance: </p>

<p>***1% level; </p>

<p>**5% level; 
*10% level. This table reports average treatment effects on the treated (ATET) obtained from </p>

<p>panel data difference-in-differences models (2-way fixed effects model, 2FE). 
Subjective well-being is defined using the GHQ12. Models were estimated using linear fixed effects </p>

<p>specifications on matched samples obtained using kernel matching. All models include individual fixed effects, the full battery of controls and dummies for the time trend. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>To further investigate the presence of well-being externalities induced by 
the public smoking bans, we look at the impact of the Scottish ban among 
couples with and without the presence of dependent children in the household 
(Table 5). Although still mostly negative, all treatments effects for both mar-
ried men and women without children do not appear to be statistically signifi-
cant. For specific sub-samples, this could also be the result of relatively small 
sample sizes and thus imprecisely estimated effects. However, the magnitude 
of several of the treatments effects for individuals without children appear to 
be smaller if compared to the effects of their counterparts with children, espe-
cially among women. Conversely, we observe statistically significant improve-
ments in well-being mostly among married women with children (lower right-
hand side part of Table 5). Larger effects are observed among female individ-
uals with dependent children who are potential smokers and whose partners 
are also potential smokers (2.3 GHQ points). 
In order to further appreciate the extent of the variation induced by the 
ban on the GHQ scale, it might be useful to consider our estimates in the 
light of the ones of previous studies. For example, Gardner and Oswald  (2006) used data from the BHPS and the GHQ on the Likert scale and find 
that unemployment is associated with an increase of nearly 1.9 GHQ points 
while marriage is correlated with a decrease of 1.3 points. Furthermore, Clark  and Oswald (2002) and Gardner and Oswald (2007) found that widowhood, 
the life event thought to have the largest negative effect on well-being observ-
able in standard datasets, is associated with a decrease in well-being of around 
5 GHQ points. While this may suggest that our effects are sizeable, we 
should avoid comparing these estimates directly because of differences in the 
empirical approaches and the temporary nature of the treatment effects in our 
analysis. </p>

<p>Robustness checks and placebo tests 
We also explore the effects of the public smoking bans using alternative defini-
tions of smokers. Table 6 presents estimates on the impact of the Scottish ban 
on individuals who smoke throughout the survey (always smokers); respon-
dents who report smoking at the time of the ban regardless of their previous 
smoking status (current smokers); as well as individuals who were smoking 
before the ban and quit smoking after the ban (quitters). These are broken 
down by gender and marital status and were produced using 2FE models. 
The ban appears to have increased SWB for women who are married and 
either always or current smokers, although the latter treatment effect is only 
weakly statistically significant. We find a larger and statistically significant 
increase in SWB (around 3.6 GHQ points) among married males who are 
quitters. As quitters are a sub-group of our potential smokers, this may imply 
that changes in SWB for male potential smokers who are married might be 
partly driven by the effects of quitters. However, it should be kept in mind 
that the sub-samples presented in this table are relatively limited if compared 
to the ones based on similar models which employ previous definitions of 
smokers (Table 3, which overall does not appear to present significant effects </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>for men potential smokers). For this reason, we were not able to further dis-
entangle treatment effects by spouses' smoking type. 
Table 7 shows results from placebo tests assuming that the Scottish ban was 
implemented in 2004 and 2005 (i.e. 2 and 1 year before its actual implementation 
respectively). These should further explore the robustness of our results as well as 
the presence of potential anticipation effects. Results are broken down by gender, 
type of smokers and marital status. Apart from weakly statistically significant 
coefficients for married men who are potential smokers and among married 
women who are never smokers, all remaining estimated treatment effects do not 
appear to be statistically different from zero. Furthermore, the direction of these 
effects appears to be undetermined with a mixture of positive and negative signs. 
This also seems to provide some further support to our main results. </p>

<p>VI CONCLUSION AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We exploit the natural experiment provided by the timing of the introduction 
of the UK smoking bans to identify the impact of public smoking bans on 
SWB. We extend the literature by focusing on well-being externalities among 
smokers and non-smokers as well as couples of different types of smokers. We 
employ kernel matching combined with fixed effects panel data difference-in-
differences models and placebo tests. We find statistically significant effects of 
public smoking bans on well-being, especially among married female individu-
als with dependent children. </p>

<p>Table 6 
Robustness checks: alternative definitions of smokers </p>

<p>ATET Scotland 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Always smokers 
Married 
À0.248 (0.585) 
À1.240 (0.601)** 
N 
1600 
1831 
Single 
1.138 (1.034) 
À0.754 (0.880) 
N 
574 
888 </p>

<p>Current smokers 
Married 
0.0996 (0.454) 
À0.782 (0.474)* 
N 
3014 
3168 
Single 
0.085 (0.805) 
À0.024 (0.702) 
N 
1191 
1675 </p>

<p>Quitters 
Married 
À3.578 (1.420)** 
À0.182 (2.091) 
N 
427 
361 
Single 
1.690 (3.090) 
3.435 (5.719) 
N 
106 
170 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses. Statistical significance: ***1% level; **5% level; *10% level. This table 
reports average treatment effects on the treated (ATET) obtained from panel data difference-in-differences 
models (2-way fixed effects model, 2FE). Subjective well-being is defined using the GHQ12. Models were 
estimated using linear fixed effects specifications on matched samples obtained using kernel matching. All 
models include individual fixed effects, the full battery of controls and dummies for the time trend. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>Our estimates might be interpreted via a number of potential mechanisms. For 
example, the positive well-being externalities among individuals with dependent 
children may indicate the presence of parental altruism. Individuals with altruistic 
preferences towards their children would benefit more from the introduction of 
public smoking bans than non-altruistic parents, mainly for the expected reduction 
of their children's exposure to second-hand smoke, at least in public places. How-
ever, our findings appear to show statistically significant increases in SWB only for </p>

<p>Table 7 
Placebo tests: the impact of the Scottish ban on well-being in 2004 and 2005 </p>

<p>ATET Scotland 
2004 
2005 </p>

<p>Overall population 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.251 (0.170) 
0.035 (0.171) 
N 
12,656 
15,053 
Single 
0.345 (0.417) 
0.253 (0.394) 
N 
3279 
4078 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
0.120 (0.203) 
0.203 (0.197) 
N 
13,872 
16,471 
Single 
0.156 (0.340) 
À0.046 (0.301) 
N 
5183 
6301 </p>

<p>Potential smokers 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.569 (0.296)* 
0.271 (0.300) 
N 
4365 
5204 
Single 
À0.544 (0.749) 
0.647 (0.743) 
N 
11,86 
1477 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
0.256 (0.371) 
À0.296 (0.382) 
N 
4362 
5181 
Single 
0.649 (0.621) 
À0.082 (0.492) 
N 
1926 
2343 </p>

<p>Never smokers 
Men 
Men 
Married 
À0.075 (0.205) 
À0.103 (0.209) 
N 
8291 
9849 
Single 
0.773 (0.498) 
0.043 (0.433) 
N 
2093 
2601 </p>

<p>Women 
Women 
Married 
0.071 (0.243) 
0.427 (0.231)* 
N 
9510 
11,290 
Single 
À0.161 (0.385) 
À0.055 (0.382) 
N 
3257 
3958 </p>

<p>Standard errors in parentheses. Statistical significance: ***1% level; **5% level; *10% level. This table 
reports average treatment effects on the treated (ATET) obtained from panel data difference-in-differences 
models (2-way fixed effects model, 2FE). Subjective well-being is defined using the GHQ12. Models were 
estimated using linear fixed effects specifications on matched samples obtained using kernel matching. All 
models include individual fixed effects, the full battery of controls and dummies for the time trend. </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>

<p>married women with children while the same estimates for men do not appear to 
show notable improvements. As our models and data do not allow testing directly 
this hypothesis, we cannot exclude that these results may partly reflect broader 
gender based differences in reporting well-being. 
Furthermore, our robustness checks also find an increase in SWB among 
married males who are quitters, i.e. individuals who quit smoking after the 
introduction of the ban. This might suggest that the effects for this sub-sample 
of married men could be to some extent driven by the ban leading individuals 
to quit or reduce smoking also at home. This would be in line with the recent 
empirical literature indicating that public smoking bans may also increase the 
likelihood of voluntary smoking restrictions at home (e.g. Cheng et al., 2015)  and the use of anti-smoking policies as self-control devices (e.g. Leicester and  Levell, 2016). Overall, further research and larger datasets might be needed to 
more precisely establish the causal pathways leading to the observed increase 
in well-being following public smoking bans. Yet, our placebo tests, showing 
mainly insignificant changes whose direction is undetermined in the 2 years 
prior the introduction of the ban, appear to suggest that our findings should 
be mainly the result of the Scottish ban. 
It should be noted that through our data and methods, we are only capable 
of identifying the short-term effects of public smoking bans on intra-couple 
well-being externalities. In the medium and long-run, individuals could adapt 
to the presence of public smoking bans and as a result their reported well-
being could also change over time. Although our estimated treatment effects 
on well-being appear to be non-negligible in size, we should be cautious in 
comparing them with the ones identified by previous studies (for instance 
those of important life events such as marriage and divorce on well-being, see 
Clark and Oswald, 2002; and Gardner and Oswald, 2007), also because of 
their transitory nature. 
Overall, our findings appear to suggest that the welfare impact of public 
smoking bans should not be limited solely to smokers but could also be 
extended to partners and family members of smokers. From a policy perspec-
tive, while public smoking bans may have a limited effect on active smoking 
and some potential adverse effects on passive smoking (e.g. Adda and Cor- naglia, 2010; Carpenter et al., 2011), they may also produce positive short-
term well-being externalities, especially among couples living with young chil-
dren. This additional information could be exploited by governments con-
cerned with the overall impact evaluation of their anti-smoking policies 
alongside standard findings on smoking prevalence and intensity. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Bruce Hollingsworth, Andrew Jones, Giuseppe Migali, Luigi Sedda, 
Ian Walker, members of the Health Economics at Lancaster (HEAL) 
Research Group, Lancaster University (UK), and participants to seminars at 
the University of York (UK), for helpful discussions. We also thank two 
anonymous referees for their useful comments. </p>

<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>





<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>



<p>SMOKING BANS AND WELL-BEING EXTERNALITIES </p>



<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>



<p>Date of receipt of final manuscript: 14 September 2017 </p>

<p>Scottish Journal of Political Economy 
© 2017 Scottish Economic Society </p>



<p>MIAOQING YANG AND EUGENIO ZUCCHELLI </p>

</text></tei>