<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.31.1.49" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>The first section of this paper will review what factors have propelled China's 
economic growth in the past, and explain why they are unlikely to provide the same 
kind of boost going forward. 
Future growth in China has to come mostly from the growth of labor produc-
tivity. Since China's investment-to-GDP ratio was already a remarkable 43.3 percent 
in 2015, it is hard to expect a high growth rate of productivity from continued 
physical investment. Indeed, Bai and Zhang (2014) estimated that the returns to 
investment have shown signs of decline since 2008. Some productivity increase 
could come from reducing resource misallocation (Hsieh and Klenow 2009), which 
could be accomplished by further reforms in the factor and product markets, 
including reforms of state-owned enterprises. However, the pace of reform in the 
future is unlikely to be as aggressive as in the past, partly because interest groups 
across China now have more means to block reforms than in the past and partly 
because the low-hanging fruit in the area of institutional reforms has been picked. 
Thus, productivity growth from this source also faces a limit. 
Since the onset of the global financial crisis in 2008, the external demand for 
Chinese products has weakened, and wages in China have meanwhile increased 
faster than in almost all other major economies. A growth model based on exploiting 
the use of cheaper labor is no longer viable. While a strict family planning policy 
implemented since the early 1980s once produced an unnaturally low birth rate and 
therefore an unusually favorable dependence ratio for China, the same force has 
now produced relatively few people entering the labor force today relative to the 
new retirees, hence yielding an unusually unfavorable dependence ratio. 
Facing rising labor costs and weak external demand, China's firms have to 
make a tough choice: in, out, up, or down. "In" is to move factories to inland areas 
where the wage is lower than coastal China. Given the pace of convergence within 
the country and the cost of logistics facing firms inland, this is at best a temporary 
strategy. "Out" means engaging in outbound direct investment, combining Chinese 
know-how with low wages in other countries. "Up" means innovation and upgrading, 
so that the firms no longer need to depend on low-paying unskilled labor. "Down" 
means closing the business; it is an option for individual firms, but not for the 
country as a whole. While a portfolio of these strategies will be employed by firms, 
a decisive factor for China's economic future is whether its firms can innovate and 
upgrade and how fast they can do so. In the next section, we focus on innovation 
and quality upgrading, and ask the question: Is China investing enough and wisely 
in research and development, and can it transition to a more innovative economy? 
We study three questions in particular. First, how strong is China's national 
investment in research and development (R&amp;D)? We do so by comparing the 
Chinese trajectory in recent years with international experiences. 
Second, what is the growth of innovation by Chinese firms? To answer this ques-
tion, we make use of data on patents from China State Intellectual Property Office 
(SIPO), the United States Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO), and World Intel-
lectual Property Office (WIPO). We use the data on patents to compare China's 
rate of innovation as compared to other BRICS (that is, Brazil, Russia, India, and </p>

<p>Shang-Jin Wei, Zhuan Xie, and Xiaobo Zhang 51 </p>

<p>South Africa) economies and high-income economies (such as the United States, 
Germany, Japan, and the Republic of Korea). We will use patent applications and 
patents granted by firms both at home and in the United States as proxies for inno-
vative activities. China's performance on innovative activities as measured by patent 
data has been strong, especially in recent years, but China may well have some 
lessons to learn from India and in particular from the Republic of Korea. We will 
argue that rising wages and expanding markets are among the important drivers 
behind China's patent explosion. 
Third, because the Chinese economy continues to have a nontrivial share 
of state-owned enterprises, we investigate possible resource misallocation in the 
innovation space. Although state-owned enterprises have received more subsidies 
from the government, their performance in innovation is lackluster compared to 
private enterprises. Furthermore, the elasticity of patent filing or patents granted 
with respect to expenditures on research and development is significantly higher 
for private sector firms than for state-owned enterprises. We interpret these data 
patterns as existence of misallocations in public fiscal resources. Interestingly, we 
find that China's state-owned enterprises often face higher realized tax burdens 
(the sum of corporate income tax and value-added tax as a share of sales or value 
added). To improve the efficiency of resource allocation, the direction of policy 
reforms should perhaps put weight on leveling the playing fields for firms across all 
ownership types with simultaneous reductions in discretionary subsidies and taxes. </p>

<p>Sources of China's Growth since 1980 and the Moderation of 
Growth since 2012 </p>

<p>China's rapid growth in the past several decades has been driven by a 
combination of two sets of factors: a) market-oriented policy reforms to let market-
determined output prices and factor prices replace administrative prices, to 
introduce and strengthen property rights, and to reduce barriers to international 
trade and investment; and b) economic fundamentals, including in particular a 
favorable demographic structure and a low initial level of labor cost. Here, we offer 
an overview of these factors and how they have evolved in the last 36 years. 
The Chinese growth miracle started with the rural sector reform known as 
the "rural household responsibility system" in the early 1980s. Instead of collec-
tive farming and selling all output to a national procurement plan at a price set 
by the plan (usually substantially below the would-be market price), farmers were 
granted land user rights and allowed to sell what they produced in excess of the offi-
cial quota at a market price. Agricultural production and rural incomes witnessed 
a dramatic increase in the ensuing years (Lin 1992). In a few years, hundreds of 
millions of farmers were released from their land and many started to work in 
factories, providing the nonfarm sector with a seemingly unlimited labor supply. In 
the 1980s, China's labor cost was among the lowest in developing countries, lower 
than in India and the Philippines and indeed lower than 114 out of 138 non-OECD </p>



<p>economies. The vast majority of these workers were restricted to living in rural areas 
by the hukou system, with many working during the 1980s for township and village-
owned enterprises, which were manufacturing firms located in rural areas. These 
enterprises provided a way for a reallocation of labor from low-productivity farm 
activities to higher-productivity manufacturing activities, at a time before restric-
tions on internal migrations were relaxed. 
During the 1990s, the government launched reforms of the township and village 
enterprises and of the state-owned enterprise sector. Most township and village enter-
prises were privatized, de jure or de facto. By 2011, the township and village enterprise 
sector had almost disappeared, with employment plummeting from 129 million in 
1995 to merely 6 million in 2011 (Xu and Zhang 2009). Among state-owned enter-
prises, which were overwhelmingly in urban areas, employment fell by about half from 
113 million in 1995 to 67 million in 2011. The number of state-owned firms declined 
from 1,084,433 (or 24 percent of the total number of firms) in 1995 to 521,503 (or 3 
percent of the total) in 2014 (according to our tabulations based on the China Firm 
Registry database in Table 1). The much larger drop in the number of state-owned 
enterprises than in their employment was part of a deliberate policy of "grasping the 
large and letting go of the small"-that is, privatizing small state-owned enterprises 
and consolidating bigger ones (Hsieh and Song 2015). 
The reform was painful in the short run, in that tens of millions of urban 
workers had to leave their former state-owned employers. Remarkably, the country 
avoided a big spike in the unemployment rate. The key is that the de facto priva-
tization was accompanied by aggressive reforms to lower entry barriers faced by 
private sector entrepreneurs. The inefficiency of the previously centrally planned, 
state-dominated economic system, together with very high barriers to entry, meant 
huge unexplored or underexplored profitable opportunities. As a result, almost all </p>

<p>Table 1 
Number of Registered Firms in China (1995-2014) </p>

<p>Firm count 
at year end 
Private (%) </p>

<p>State-owned 
firms (%) 
Foreign (%) </p>

<p>1995 
4,598,604 
71 
24 
5 
2000 
5,875,706 
76 
19 
5 
2005 
7,980,991 
85 
10 
5 
2010 
11,150,201 
90 
5 
5 
2014 
18,178,921 
94 
3 
3 </p>

<p>Annual growth rate (%) </p>

<p>1995-2005 
6 
8 
−3 
5 
2005-2014 
10 
11 
−5 
3 
1995-2014 
8 
9 
−4 
4 </p>

<p>Source: Tabulated by authors based on China Firm Registry Database. 
Note: Firms ownership classification is based on the ownership information on firm 
registration. Foreign-invested firms include both fully foreign-owned and sino-foreign 
joint ventures. All firm ownership types other than "state" or "foreign" are grouped 
in "private." </p>

<p>From "Made in China" to "Innovated in China": Necessity, Prospect, and Challenges 53 </p>

<p>of the lost jobs in township and village enterprises and state-owned enterprises were 
offset by new job opportunities in the dynamic private sector. As shown in Table 1, 
the number of private enterprises increased by nearly five-fold to about 17 million 
(18,178,921 × .94) in the period 1995-2014. By 2011, 193 million people worked 
in private enterprises (including self-employed) (CNBS 2012). This represents the 
largest de facto privatization program in world history in terms of the number of 
workers who move from state-sector to private sector employment, and one that was 
accomplished without massive unemployment. 
Through this period, the growth in the Chinese economy has become driven 
overwhelmingly by the growth in the private sector aided by an expansion in the 
number of entrepreneurs. This pattern is especially true for the manufacturing sector, 
which has been growing faster than either the agricultural or service sectors. Indeed, 
Wei and Zhang (2011b) have documented two "70 percent rules" using manufacturing 
firm census data in 1994 and 2005: First, approximately 70 percent of the growth in 
industrial value added came from private sector firms between these two census years. 
Second, approximately 70 percent of private sector growth in value added came from 
growth in the count of new private sector firms (the extensive margin), while the 
remaining 30 percent came from growth of existing firms (the intensive margin). 
China also carried out a number of other reforms intended to incentivize 
local governments to pursue growth-friendly policies. For example, under the fiscal 
arrangement introduced in the early 1980s, local governments and the central 
government follow a pre-determined revenue formula (though varying across 
regions as a function of local bargaining power), which stimulates the incentives 
of local officials to create a more business-friendly environment. More generally, 
in spite of the political centralization by the Communist Party, the country has 
implemented a system of fiscal and economic decentralization that grants local 
governments sufficient decision-making power-and more importantly incen-
tives-to compete with each other. The local economic growth rate is used as a 
key performance indicator for the career advancement of officials. The delegation 
of economic policy authority to local governments, which have better knowledge 
of local information, and competition for investment and tax base among local 
governments in the Chinese style of federalism have provided a useful check on the 
temptation of local government officials to expropriate local firms. As a result, firms 
acquire some de facto security of property rights, even if the formal property rights 
institutions are problematic (Qian and Weingast 1997; Xu 2011). 
China's government also set up numerous special economic zones and special 
development zones in the coastal provinces to attract foreign direct investment in 
the 1980s and 1990s. These zones help the government to meet two challenges. 
First, public funding for infrastructure was limited, especially in the early days of 
the reform era. The government was able to concentrate limited public funding to 
provide adequate roads, power supply, waste treatment and other infrastructure to 
the firms within the zones, even when it was not able to improve the infrastructure 
nationally at the same speed. Second, policy reforms within these zones were politi-
cally easier than doing the same things on a national scale. The success in these </p>



<p>zones in terms of economic growth, employment, and tax revenues in turn facili-
tated similar market-oriented reforms outside the zones. Foreign direct investment 
rose rapidly in China, especially since 1992, and these zones played an important 
role in attracting international firms. Foreign-invested firms were and continue to 
be an important channel for transfer of technology and management ideas from 
advanced economies to China. 
China's integration with the global economy was accelerated after the country 
joined the World Trade Organization in December 2001. Foreign-invested firms 
have often accounted for half of the country's total exports. China's trade expanded 
fast: While China's GDP approximately doubled once every seven years, its export 
value in US dollar terms doubled once every four years. By 2004, China had come to 
be known as the World's Factory, a label describing not only the sheer volume of its 
cross-border trade, but also the breadth of its sector coverage (as discussed in Feen-
stra and Wei 2010). China's growth in both imports and exports, along with foreign 
investment coming to the country, is also an important channel for domestic firms 
to acquire technological knowhow. 
While the deep cause of growth and development is institutional changes engen-
dered by policy reforms and embrace of globalization, the proximate drivers of 
economic growth include improvement in productivity as a crucial component. The 
increase in productivity stems from innovations within sectors and the reallocation of 
resources (mainly workers) from lower-productivity to higher-productivity sectors, such 
as from the state sector to the private sector and from the agricultural sector to nonag-
ricultural sectors (Zhu 2012). Sectoral productivity and structural change accounted 
for 42 and 17 percent of economic growth during 1978-1995 (Fan et al. 2003). 
For three decades following the start of market-oriented reforms, China 
appeared to have an inexhaustible amount of "surplus labor" (which can be thought 
of as conceptually the same as low-productivity labor in rural areas). But signs of 
labor shortage started to emerge in the first decade of the 2000s. According to Cai 
and Du (2011) and Zhang, Yang, and Wang (2011), wages for unskilled workers 
showed double-digit growth starting in 2003-2004. The exact timing of a sharp 
increase in the wage rate of unskilled workers is subject to debate. Wang, Huang, 
Zhang, and Rozelle (2011) report a turning point as early as 2000. On the other 
hand, Knight, Deng, and Li (2011) and Golley and Meng (2011), for example, 
point out that barriers to internal migration, especially a rigid household registra-
tion system that prevents rural households from moving freely to urban areas, imply 
additional scope for rural-to-urban migration if and when the remaining barriers 
can be dismantled. In any case, China is a low-wage country no more. 
Two features of demographic transition have also been a powerful driver of 
China's growth in the past three and a half decades. The first feature is a favorable 
dependency ratio. China's sharp decline in fertility rate has meant fewer young 
dependents to support for a given size of the working cohort. The fraction of prime-
age people in total population rose steadily for three decades, creating an unusually 
large demographic dividend, which in turn contributed to economic growth (Cai 
and Wang 2008; Wei 2015). </p>

<p>Shang-Jin Wei, Zhuan Xie, and Xiaobo Zhang 55 </p>

<p>The second feature of demography that affects growth is the gender ratio 
imbalance of the premarital cohort. This less-studied factor may have a quanti-
tatively significant effect as well. The one-child policy has yielded an unintended 
consequence in distorting the sex ratio in favor of boys. As the one-child generation 
enters the marriageable age, young men face a very competitive marriage market. 
In order to attract potential brides, families with sons choose to work harder, save 
more, and take on more risks, including exhibiting a higher propensity to be entre-
preneurs (Wei and Zhang 2011a, b; Chang and Zhang 2015; Wei, Zhang, and Liu 
forthcoming). It is estimated that increasing marriage market competition due to 
sex ratio imbalances has contributed to about two percentage points of economic 
growth per year (Wei and Zhang 2011b). 
It is important to point out that the additional growth due to an unbalanced 
sex ratio is of an immiserizing type: social welfare is likely to have become lower 
even though the GDP growth accelerated. The logic is explained in Wei and Zhang 
(2011b): The extra work effort and extra risk-taking that produce a higher GDP 
growth rate are motivated by a desire to improve one's chance (or one's children's 
chance) of success in the marriage market. Yet the fraction of young men who will 
not get married in the aggregate is determined by the sex ratio, and not by the econ-
omy-wide work effort, risk-taking, or GDP growth rate. In this sense, the extra work 
effort and risk-taking are futile; households collectively would have been willing to 
give up this part of income growth in exchange for no sex ratio imbalance. 
Thus, from 1980 to 2011, China was experiencing a relatively low wage, a large 
workforce with a favorable dependency ratio, and an increasingly unbalanced sex 
ratio in the premarital cohort. But starting in 2012, China's age cohort of 15-60 
started to shrink in absolute size. Policy changes to postpone the official retirement 
age or to encourage more female labor force participation will at best moderate the 
resulting decline in the workforce. Because the female labor force participation was 
very high under the central planning regime before the 1980s, higher than most 
non-Communist countries in the world, such as the United States, Japan, Germany, 
India, and Indonesia, the participation rate of women in the labor force has in 
fact come down over time. The recent relaxation of the family planning policy in 
November 2015 from the limit of one child per couple to two children per couple, 
while motivated by a desire to improve the demographic pattern for the economy, 
will make the dependency ratio worse for the next decade-and-a-half rather than 
better by adding to the number of children without altering the size of the work-
force. After all, no couple can produce a 16-year old right away (Wei 2015). The sex 
ratio at birth started to become less unbalanced in 2009, and the contribution to 
growth from an unbalanced sex ratio will become weaker over time. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 Beside a moderation of growth since 2012, China has to deal with challenges associated with income 
inequality, regional disparity, environmental degradation, and corruption. For perspectives on these 
challenges, see Fan, Kanbur, Wei, and Zhang (2014). </p>



<p>Evolution of Aggregate Productivity </p>

<p>To see how the growth of physical capital, human capital (workforce adjusted for 
average years of schooling), and total factor productivity each contributes to China's 
GDP growth, we perform a simple decomposition based on an aggregate produc-
tion function approach. 
2 Figure 1 summarizes the result. A few features are worth 
noting. First, investment in physical capital has always been important for China's 
growth, accounting for 67.9 percent on average throughout this period. The relative 
share of contribution from physical investment increased to 107 percent after 2009, 
which resulted from the government stimulus package in response to the global 
financial crisis. Second, the contribution from the growth of human capital has 
been positive, at 12.5 percent during 1999-2008 and 16 percent during 2009-2015. </p>

<p>2 The computation method and data sources are explained in online Appendix Part A, available with 
this paper at http://e-jep.org. </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Contributions to GDP Growth of Physical Capital, Human Capital, and 
Total Factor Productivity, 1979-2015 
(share) </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations based on the methodology and data sources detailed in Online Appendix A. 
Note: See Appendix for details of the estimation. </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>−0.2 </p>

<p>−0.4 </p>

<p>−0.6 </p>

<p>Capital Human Capital 
Total factor productivity </p>

<p>1 
9 
7 
9 </p>

<p>1 
9 
8 
1 </p>

<p>1 
9 
8 
3 </p>

<p>1 
9 
8 
5 </p>

<p>1 
9 
8 
7 </p>

<p>1 
9 
8 
9 </p>

<p>1 
9 
9 
1 </p>

<p>1 
9 
9 
3 </p>

<p>1 
9 
9 
5 </p>

<p>1 
9 
9 
7 </p>

<p>1 
9 
9 
9 </p>

<p>2 
0 
0 
1 </p>

<p>2 
0 
0 
3 </p>

<p>2 
0 
0 
5 </p>

<p>2 
0 
0 
7 </p>

<p>2 
0 
0 
9 
2 0 1 1 
2 0 1 3 
2 0 1 5 </p>

<p>From "Made in China" to "Innovated in China": Necessity, Prospect, and Challenges 57 </p>

<p>Because of the outsized role of physical investment in the Chinese economy, the 
contribution of human capital is smaller than what one typically finds from growth 
decomposition for an OECD economy. Third, the growth of total factor produc-
tivity was a major contributor to GDP growth before 2008, often accounting for 20 
percent or more to the total growth. (An exception was the period of 1989-1991, a 
time of domestic political turbulence and international sanctions.) 
Strikingly, the contributions from the growth of total factor productivity have 
turned persistently negative since 2009. 
3 Upon reflection, this is perhaps not overly 
surprising. The Chinese government's response to the global financial crisis that 
started in 2008 was to encourage physical investment through an aggressive fiscal 
(and bank lending) program, but there were no ambitious structural reforms 
pursued during this period that could have raised aggregate efficiency, and yet GDP 
growth started to moderate after 2012-and this combination is a recipe for nega-
tive growth in total factor productivity. 
The Chinese economy is at a crossroads. Structural factors in the form of less-
favorable demographics and a higher cost of labor imply a lower potential growth 
rate. To achieve robust future growth, raising the growth of total factor productivity 
is a must. 
One way to raise future productivity growth is to pursue more structural reforms. 
These include removing barriers to labor mobility from rural to urban areas (the 
hukou system) and leveling uneven access to bank loans by firms of different owner-
ship. Another way to raise productivity growth is via innovation. Innovation can 
take the form of creating new products, new ways of using existing products, new 
designs, new processes for producing existing products that are more efficient 
and cost-effective, new ways of organizing business, and new ways of branding and 
marketing the products or services. 
Can China transition from a world assembly line to an innovation powerhouse? 
It's easy to list reasons to be skeptical. There is no shortage of news stories of intel-
lectual property rights violations by Chinese companies. 
4 There is criticism that the </p>

<p>Chinese school system puts too much weight on rote learning and not enough on 
creative and critical thinking. On the other hand, more optimistic examples are 
available, too. Tencent, the company that provides the popular communication 
tool, <rs type="software">WeChat</rs>, which combines group chat, voice calls, video sharing, and financial 
exchanges, is generally regarded as among the most innovative internet companies 
in the world. Huawei, the telecom equipment producer, is said to take out more </p>

<p>3 The baseline calculation assumes a capital income share of 0.50. We vary the share from 0.4 and 0.55 
and find that the broad pattern of the evolution of total factor productivity stays the same. Our finding 
is broadly consistent with Wu and Conference Board China Center (2014). For example, they reported 
negative total factor productivity from 2007 to 2012, while our estimate indicates such a decline from 2009 
to 2014. One difference between their study and our growth decomposition is that they obtain a larger 
contribution from human capital, which may be related to the way the schooling adjustment is made. 
4 Fang, Lerner, and Wu (2016) provide evidence that regional variations in the strength of intellectual 
property rights protection in China are correlated with propensity to innovate for privatized formally 
state-owned firms. </p>



<p>patents a year than either Apple or Cisco. The world's first quantum satellite was 
launched by China in August 2016. To address whether such examples of innovation 
are exceptions or the norm, we offer a systematic look at the data in the next section. 
It is hard to quantify with precision the relative contributions to total factor 
productivity growth from different sources. From the China Statistical Yearbook on 
Science and Technology, we compute and compare investment made by firms in the 
survey in (a) importing and digesting foreign technologies, (b) buying and digesting 
technologies from other domestic firms, and (c) developing their own in-house tech-
nological improvement. In 2000, the survey firms collectively spent nearly 20 percent 
of their technology improvement budget on importing and digesting foreign tech-
nology, about 2 percent on buying technologies from other domestic sources, and 78 
percent on developing their own in-house technological improvement. Over time, 
the share of the first item declines, whereas the last two items expand. By 2014, the 
survey firms collectively spent 11 percent of their technological improvement budget 
on importing and digesting international technologies, about 5 percent on buying 
technologies from domestic sources, and the remaining 84 percent on developing 
their own in-house technological advancement, with the last two categories showing a 
significant increase over the shares in 2000 (see online Appendix Figure A1). These 
numbers indicate in an indirect way the improvement in the domestic innovation 
capacity in China's manufacturing sector. </p>

<p>Research and Development: Investment and People </p>

<p>Innovative leaders at both the corporate and national levels tend to invest 
heavily in research and development. The United States, Japan, and Germany, 
the largest three rich economies, invested more than 2.7 percent of their GDP in 
research and development in 2014, which is almost 50 percent more than an average 
OECD country (about 1.9 percent in 2014), and about three times as much as most 
developing countries. If China makes the transition to a more innovative economy, 
it needs to make a commitment to research and investment spending as well. 
In 1991, when systematic data on this subject started to be collected, China 
invested 0.7 percent of GDP in research and development. This was much lower 
than technological leaders like the United States, Japan, and Germany, but not out 
of line with big developing economies such as India, Brazil, or South Africa. Indeed, 
because China's competitiveness at this time was based on exploiting its vast cheap 
labor and making use of technologies developed elsewhere, domestic research and 
development and innovation were not an imperative at this time. 
A comparison of research and development spending between China and 
other economies is provided in Figure 2. For all countries in the world other than 
China, we plot research and development expenditure as a share of GDP in the 
latest possible year (which is 2014 for most countries). Clearly, higher-income coun-
tries tend to have a higher ratio of research and development spending to GDP. 
For China, we plot the same ratio using corresponding data for China from 1995 to </p>

<p>Shang-Jin Wei, Zhuan Xie, and Xiaobo Zhang 59 </p>

<p>2014. By 2010, China had reached the median value of research and development 
as a share of GDP. By 2012, its spending had caught up with the OECD average (at 
1.88 percent of GDP in that year) even though China's income level was still less 
than one-fifth of the OECD average. By 2014, China's research and development 
spending had reached 2.05 percent of GDP. From an aggregate R&amp;D spending 
viewpoint, China is an overachiever. 
Another indicator of innovation effort is the share of researchers in the popu-
lation. In 1996, China had 443 researchers per million people. In comparison, the 
shares for the United States, Japan, and Korea were 3,122, 4,947, and 2,211 per 
million, respectively. The Chinese ratio in 1996 was comparable to Brazil (420 per 
million in 2000) and better than India (153 per million in 1996), though much lower 
than Russia (3,796 per million in 1996). By 2014, the share in China had grown to 
1,113 researchers per million population. 
5 Because China's research and develop-</p>

<p>ment expenditure has grown faster than the number of researchers, research and 
development expenditure per researcher has grown over time as well. </p>

<p>5 For more cross-country comparisons, see online Appendix Figure A2, available with this paper at 
http://e-jep.org. </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Research and Development Intensity Comparison </p>

<p>Source: World Bank, OECD database (https://data.oecd.org/rd/gross-domestic-spending-on-r-d.htm). 
Note: Data for China are from 1995 to 2014, and data for all other countries are for 2014 or the latest 
year available. </p>

<p>R&amp;D/GDP in percent </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1,000 
GDP per capita (USD in 2005) </p>

<p>3,000 
8,000 
22,000 
60,000 </p>

<p>NOR </p>

<p>LUX </p>



<p>The Pace of Innovation as Measured by Growth in Patents </p>

<p>Not all dimensions of innovation are equally well measured. The output of 
innovation can take the form of patents, commercial secrets, improvement in busi-
ness processes or business models, and others. Innovation can also take place in 
areas outside the commercial space, such as culture. Since innovation in the form of 
patents is relatively well measured, we will pay special attention to patents by firms. 
Our conjecture is that innovation across all dimensions is positively correlated. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The number of Chinese patents has exploded. Table 2 presents some summary 
statistics. The number of patent applications filed in China's State Intellectual Prop-
erty Office (SIPO) rocketed from 83,045 in 1995 to more than 2.3 million in 2014, 
at an annual growth rate of 19 percent (column 1). In 2011, China overtook the 
United States as the country with the most patent filings in the world that year 
(based on data from WIPO). 
What explains the explosion of Chinese patents? Could it be easy approval or 
low-quality patents? Some straightforward comparisons across countries suggest not. 
One simple metric for judging ease of patent approval is the ratio of the number 
of patents granted in year t to the number of patent applications in year t − 1, which 
we will call the patent approval rate. Based on data from the World Intellectual 
Property Organization, the patent approval rate in China in recent years is 30-40 </p>

<p>6 A simple regression of firm-level total factor productivity (estimated using the Olley-Pakes method 
based on data from the Annual Survey of Manufacturing Firms) on the cumulative number of patents 
yields a positive slope coefficient. In other words, firm-level total factor productivity and the stock of 
patents are positively correlated. Fang, He, and Li (2016) also show a positive association between 
firm-level total factor productivity and patent count. They interpret this as patent innovation raising 
productivity; such an interpretation would need an instrumental variable approach to back it up. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Patent Applications and Patents Granted (1995-2014) </p>

<p>Number of patent applications 
at China's State Intellectual 
Property Office (SIPO) </p>

<p>Number of 
patents 
granted by 
China's SIPO </p>

<p>Distribution of patents 
grantedby type of patents 
(3) </p>

<p>Share of patents 
granted to 
applicants from 
outside China 
(%) </p>

<p>Number of patents 
granted by foreign 
patent offices 
to China-based 
applicants 
Invention 
(%) </p>

<p>Utility 
model (%) </p>

<p>Design 
(%) 
Year 
(1) 
(2) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>1995 
83,045 
45,064 
8 
68 
25 
8 
75 
2000 
170,682 
105,345 
12 
52 
36 
10 
88 
2005 
476,264 
214,003 
25 
37 
38 
20 
398 
2010 
1,222,286 
814,825 
17 
42 
41 
9 
2,587 
2014 
2,361,243 
1,302,687 
18 
54 
28 
7 
10,603 </p>

<p>Annual growth rate in different periods (%) 
1995-2005 
19 
17 
31 
10 
22 
28 
18 
2005-2014 
19 
22 
18 
27 
18 
9 
44 
1995-2014 
19 
19 
25 
18 
20 
18 
30 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' tabulation based on data from China's State Intellectual Property Office's webpage 
(http://www.sipo.g ov.cn/tjxx/) for columns 1-4 and the World Intellectual Property Office for Column 5. </p>

<p>From "Made in China" to "Innovated in China": Necessity, Prospect, and Challenges 61 </p>

<p>percent, which is essentially in the middle of the approval rates across countries. For 
example, the Chinese approval rate is higher than those in India and Brazil, which 
are close to 20 percent, but lower than those in the United States and Korea, which 
are in the range of 50-60 percent. Therefore, the Chinese patent approval ratio 
does not seem to be unusually high. 
Among the three types of patents (invention, utility model, and design), the 
fraction of approved invention patents, arguably the most technically intensive cate-
gory, rose from 8 percent in 1995 to 18 percent in 2014 (column 2 of Table 2). In 
2005, patents granted to foreign applicants accounted for more than 20 percent of 
China's total approved patents, but dropped to 7 percent in 2014, suggesting an 
increasing role of indigenous innovations in the Chinese economy since 2005. As 
Table 2 shows, both total Chinese patents filing and approvals show a rapid growth. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>One way to consider the quality of Chinese patents is to examine patents applied 
by and granted to Chinese firms in other countries. As noted earlier, the rate of 
patents approved by China's patent office grew at an annual rate of 19 percent from 
1995 to 2014. During that period, the number of patents granted to Chinese appli-
cants by patent offices in developed countries was rising even faster at 30 percent 
per year (see last column in Table 2). 
Of particular interest is a comparison of the number of patents granted by the 
US Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO) to Chinese firms with those to firms from 
other countries. As shown in Table 3, the number of patents granted by the USPTO 
to Chinese corporate applicants rose from 62 in 1995 to 7,236 in 2014. The annual 
growth rate was 21 percent in the first half of the period (1995-2005) but accelerated </p>

<p>7 The online Appendix available with this paper at http://e-jep.org includes more detail on patent data. 
For example, Appendix Tables A2 and A3 provide more detail on Chinese patent filings and approvals, 
while Appendix Figure 3 provides more details on cross-country comparisons of patent approval rates. </p>

<p>Table 3 
Number of Patents Granted by the US Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO) to 
International Corporate Applicants </p>

<p>Year 
China 
Brazil 
India 
Russia </p>

<p>South 
Africa 
Germany 
Japan </p>

<p>Republic 
of Korea </p>

<p>1995 
62 
63 
37 
98 
123 
6,600 
21,764 
1,161 
2000 
119 
98 
131 
183 
111 
10,234 
31,296 
3,314 
2005 
402 
77 
384 
148 
87 
9,011 
30,341 
4,352 
2010 
2,657 
175 
1,098 
272 
116 
12,363 
44,814 
11,671 
2014 
7,236 
334 
2,987 
445 
152 
16,550 
53,849 
16,469 </p>

<p>Annual growth rate in different periods (%) 
1995-2005 
21 
2 
26 
4 
−3 
3 
3 
14 
2005-2014 
38 
18 
26 
13 
6 
7 
7 
16 
1995-2014 
28 
9 
26 
8 
1 
5 
5 
15 </p>

<p>Note: Computed by authors based on data from the United States Patent and Trademark Office 
(USPTO). </p>



<p>to 38 percent a year during the latter half of the period (2005-2014). Of the compar-
ison countries-Brazil, Russia, India, South Africa, German, Japan, and Korea-only 
India had a similar rate of growth in corporate patents in the United States. 
Two natural adjustments are to consider a country's population size and 
income level. To this end, we run cross-country regressions with log number of 
patents granted to applicants from various comparison countries by the US Patent 
and Trademark Office as the dependent variable. As explanatory variables, we use 
the log of population, squared log of population, and country times year (country 
× year) fixed effects. Figure 3 plots the estimated coefficients for the interaction 
term between county and year fixed effects for selected counties. These coefficients 
can be interpreted as how a given country does relative to the average interna-
tional experience based on its population size. China shows steady gains in patents 
even with these adjustments. Of the comparison countries, India also shows gains 
over time after these adjustments, but Japan, Germany, the Republic of Korea, the 
Russian Federation, Brazil, and South Africa do not. Overall, Chinese firms collec-
tively do better in their patent count than what the country's population size and 
income level would have suggested. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>8 Details of the regressions are available in an online Appendix available with this paper at http://e-jep. 
org. See Appendix Table A5. </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Patents Granted in US Patent and Trademark Office (USPTO) to Different Countries </p>

<p>Source: Authors using data from World Intellectual Property Office (WIPO). 
Note: Conditional plot by controlling for population, population squared, and country and year fixed 
effects. One can interpret the coefficients indicated on the y-axis as showing how a given country does 
relative to the average international experience based on its population size. 
Coef cient of (country × year) dummy </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>−4 </p>

<p>−2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1,000 
GDP per capita (USD in 2005) </p>

<p>3,000 
8,000 
22,000 
60,000 </p>

<p>Shang-Jin Wei, Zhuan Xie, and Xiaobo Zhang 63 </p>

<p>One can also look at foreign citations of Chinese patents (granted by China's 
State Intellectual Property Office). The count of foreign citations of Chinese inven-
tion patents grew at the rate of 33 percent a year during 1995-2005, but accelerated 
to 51 percent a year from 2005 to 2014. The growth of citations of Chinese utility 
model patents is similar, at 36 percent per year during 1995-2014. After adjusting for 
population size and income, Chinese firms perform well. 
9 This pattern is consistent </p>

<p>with international recognition of rising scientific and innovative ideas out of China. 
Overall, not only has the number of Chinese patents exploded, but a variety 
of comparisons suggest that Chinese patent quality also exhibits a real and robust 
improvement over time that is quite favorable relative to international experi-
ence. There is no reason to be pessimistic about the intrinsic ability for Chinese 
firms to innovate. </p>

<p>Patterns of Innovation Growth </p>

<p>By looking at patterns of patents across different categories of industries, we can 
gain insight into some of the factors as potential drivers of innovation, including the 
rise in relevant market size, industrial competition, market size, and change in relative 
prices (such as rising wages). We merge the Chinese patent database with the Annual 
Survey of Industrial Enterprises in China (ASIEC). The ASIEC database covers all 
the state-owned enterprises and private firms with sales exceeding 5 million yuan 
from 1998 to 2009, including ownership information. 
10 The patent database contains </p>

<p>all patents granted by China's State Intellectual Property Office between 1985 and 
2012. One pattern that emerges is that state-owned enterprises in general perform 
worse than private firms in generating patents. During the period 1998-2009, the 
number of patents granted to private firms in China grew by 35 percent per year, 
overtaking the number of patents given to state-owned and foreign firms by a comfort-
able margin. The drop in the share of patents by state-owned enterprises is partly due 
to the shrinkage of that sector, as described earlier. In 1998, state-owned enterprises 
accounted for 30 percent of total firms in the ASIEC database, while they dropped to 2 
percent by 2009. Clearly, private firms have become the engine of innovation in China. 
Market size has been regarded as a key driver of innovation in the literature 
(Acemoglu and Linn 2004). In other words, firms aiming at larger global markets 
should be more innovative. In past decades, the Chinese economy has become </p>

<p>9 We perform cross-country regressions similar to those described in Figure 3 with the forward citation of 
Chinese firms' patents by all patent applicants in the United States as the dependent variable. The online 
Appendix Table A5 provides more detail on the extent of forward citation across countries regression 
analysis, and Appendix Figure A4 shows the coefficients on the interaction term between country and 
year fixed effects against log income. Overall, relative to a country's population size and income level, 
the Chinese firms do well in terms of forward citations of their patents. See also Xie and Zhang (2015) 
for an analysis of the growth of patents in China. 
10 While ASIEC data for 2010-2014 seem to be available on the gray market, the quality appears suspect. 
To be conservative, we do not use these data in this paper. </p>



<p>increasingly integrated with the world economy, in particular since China joined 
the World Trade Organization in 2001. In this data, exporting firms in China are 
indeed more innovative than nonexporting firms. 
Since 2003, real wages in China have grown by more than 10 percent a year. 
Some reckon that China has passed the so-called "Lewis turning point," which 
means that an era of ultra-low-wage production is over (for example, Zhang, Yang, 
and Wang 2011). While patents are rising for both capital-and labor-intensive firms, 
the fraction of patents granted to labor-intensive firms increased from 55 percent 
in 1998 to 66 percent in 2009. Rising labor costs may have induced labor-intensive 
sectors to come up with more innovations to substitute for labor. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>We can connect the discussions on total factor productivity and on innovation. 
We separate all firms in the ASIEC sample into those with no patents during 1998-
2007, those with a cumulative patent count of 1-4 patents during the same period, 
and those with a cumulative count of more than 4 patents. We compute the growth 
of total factor productivity for each individual firm. We find that firm-level produc-
tivity tends to grow faster in the group that engages in more innovation. This suggests 
that to reverse China's negative levels of total factor productivity, it would be helpful 
for China to facilitate conditions that expand both the number of firms that engage 
in innovative activities and the intensity of innovation per innovating firm. </p>

<p>Misallocation of Innovation Resources </p>

<p>The innovation gap between China and leading advanced economies such as 
the United States, Japan, and even Korea is still wide. On the list of 2015 Thomson 
Reuters' Top 100 Global Innovators, Japanese and US firms lead the way, while no 
single Chinese firm makes the list. More systematic data confirms the continued gap 
in innovation (Shen, Wang, and Whalley 2015). The numbers of US patents received 
by either Japanese, German, or Korean firms are still more than twice as many as those 
obtained by Chinese firms in spite of their smaller population size (as shown earlier 
in Table 3). Part of the gap reflects different stages of development: as we have shown, 
both investment in R&amp;D and innovation measured by patent count are strongly posi-
tively related to GDP per capita. However, another contributor to the gap could be 
resource misallocation in the innovation space. We turn to this topic next. 
Following China's reforms in the late 1990s, the share of state-owned enter-
prises in total firms dropped significantly from 24 percent in 1995 to 3 percent in 
2014, as discussed earlier. However, most of the surviving state-owned enterprises 
are relatively big, and are in upstream industries or strategically important sectors </p>

<p>11 The descriptions in these paragraphs are based on bivariate correlations, and as such are, of course, 
only suggestive. In order to evaluate the relative importance of these factors' contributions to firm inno-
vations in a more rigorous manner, we run multivariate regressions using a hybrid binomial estimation 
method proposed by Allison (2005). The details are available in the online Appendix, Part B, available 
with this paper at http://e-jep.org (see Appendix Tables A7-A11). Overall, the findings confirm the 
importance of rising labor cost. </p>

<p>From "Made in China" to "Innovated in China": Necessity, Prospect, and Challenges 65 </p>

<p>(Hsieh and Song 2015). They are typically subject to less competition than private 
enterprises. Thus, China's state-owned firms both absorb nontrivial resources, 
including government subsidies, and still command nontrivial political weights. 
Part of China's move to becoming an innovative economy must be to improve the 
efficiency of resource allocation between state-owned and private firms. China's 
state-owned firms continue to receive considerable financial support from the 
government, including access to low-cost bank loans and research and development 
subsidies. In the aftermath of both the 1997 Asian financial crisis and the 2008 
global financial crisis, the Chinese government launched stimulus packages which 
often involved credit expansion and which disproportionately went to state-owned 
enterprises. The more favorable policies and injection of massive stimulus funds 
have reduced the returns to capital of state-owned enterprises since 2008 (Bai and 
Zhang 2014), caused a decline in their total factor productivity (Wu 2013), and 
provided a lifeline for inefficient zombie firms (Tan, Huang, and Woo 2016). The 
returns to capital of state-owned enterprises are much lower than their private coun-
terparts (Hsieh and Song 2015). Moreover, state-owned enterprises lagged behind 
private firms in total factor productivity (Brandt 2015). These patterns suggest a 
misallocation of government support between state-owned and private enterprises. 
Government subsidies for research and development can promote firm innova-
tions in China (as reviewed in Boeing 2016 and confirmed by our own firm-level 
regressions). Government subsides can be defended on the ground that research 
and development by firms generate positive externalities. Indeed, most advanced 
countries subsidize research and development as well. The question is not whether 
subsidies can be justified at all, but rather whether China's allocation of such subsi-
dies is consistent with economic efficiency. 
Based on simple averages, it would appear that a greater fraction of state-
controlled firms are innovative (that is, they have patents) than domestic private 
sector firms. Indeed, some state-controlled firms receive many patents in a year. But 
the simple averages are misleading both because state-controlled firms are much 
larger on average (and larger firms tend to invest more in research and develop-
ment), and because they tend to receive more subsidies from various levels of the 
government. Subsidies from local governments to local government-controlled 
firms are especially noteworthy. 
We examine firm-level data for evidence of effectiveness of research and devel-
opment spending in generating innovations. Based on firms in the ASIEC sample 
during 2005-2007, for every 10 million yuan of firm-level investment in research and 
development, domestic private-sector firms and foreign-invested firms generate 6.5 
and 7.6 patents, respectively. In comparison, the same investment by state-owned 
firms yields a more meager 2.2 patents. We may obtain a more informative picture by 
sorting firms by size and ownership. In Figure 4, on the horizontal axis, all Chinese 
firms are sorted into ten size deciles based on the sum of the sales during the period, 
with the first decile being the smallest and the 10th being the largest. Within each size 
decile, firms are then sorted by ownership. "State" refers to all firms in which the state 
(either the central or the local governments) have controlling shares (50 percent or </p>



<p>more); "foreign" refers to all firms in which foreign entities, including investors from 
Taiwan, Hong Kong, or Macao, have a 10 percent share or more but the state has no 
more than 50 percent of the shares. All other firms are in the "private" category. 
Table 4 presents statistics on domestically granted patents by firm ownership and 
size during 2005-2007 when all relevant data are available. In most of the size catego-
ries, domestic private sector firms and foreign-invested firms invest more in research 
and development and generate more patents than their state-owned counterparts. 
Inspecting Figure 4 and Table 4, several patterns are especially noteworthy. First, 
the returns to research and development spending-as measured by the number of 
patents per million yuan of research and development spending on the vertical 
axis-tend to decline with firm size. Because large firms tend to spend more on 
research and development, this pattern is consistent with the idea that diminishing 
returns apply to investment in innovation. Second, across most size deciles, we see 
that foreign-invested firms and domestic private sector firms tend to have higher 
returns to investment in research and development. Third, we do not observe a 
connection between firm subsidies (relative to sales) and effectiveness at converting 
research and spending into innovative outcome as measured by patents. Instead, we </p>

<p>Figure 4 
Patent Count per Million Yuan of R&amp;D Investment as a Function of Ownership 
and Size </p>

<p>Source: Data from Annual Surveys of Above-Scale Manufacturing Firms, 2005-2007. 
Notes: We used a 2005-2007 sample. Firms are first sorted by size (sales) deciles, and, within each size 
decile, are subdivided into three ownership groups: "State" refers to firms for which the state (central 
or local governments) has 50 percent share or more; "Foreign" refers to firms for which foreign entities 
have at least 10 percent of the share and the state has less than 50 percent share; "Private" includes all 
other firms. Firms that report positive patents but no R&amp;D spending (or spending of less than 100 yuan) 
are excluded. 
Patent count per million RMB investment in R&amp;D </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>Private </p>

<p>Foreign </p>

<p>State </p>

<p>5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
Size by sales (deciles) </p>

<p>Smaller 
Larger </p>

<p>Shang-Jin Wei, Zhuan Xie, and Xiaobo Zhang 67 </p>

<p>see that state-controlled firms tend to have much higher subsidies (relative to sales) 
than either domestic private firms or foreign-invested firms. Interestingly, because 
small and medium state-owned firms are mostly owned by local governments, they 
receive more subsidies from the local governments than large state-owned firms. 
König, Song, Storesletten, and Zilibotti (paper in progress) argue that, in 
theory, the most productive firms should pursue innovation and less-productive 
firms should just imitate. Against this theoretical benchmark and also compared 
to the data patterns in Taiwan, they find that less-productive firms in China engage 
in too much research and development spending-and the more-productive firms 
may not do enough. Based on their calibrations, if the R&amp;D misallocation can be 
reduced (so that the association between productivity and R&amp;D spending resem-
bles that in Taiwan), the aggregate productivity growth in Chinese manufacturing 
during 2001-2007 could have grown by about one-third to one-half. 
In sum, there is prima facie evidence that the pattern of subsidies across 
China's firms represents resource misallocation. China's economy-wide innovative 
outcomes would have been higher if the subsidies were more evenly spread across 
firm ownership. 
12 The sensible policy reforms would be to provide subsidies only </p>

<p>12 The Appendix available online with this paper at http://e-jep.org offers some exploratory regres-
sions that tend to confirm the intuition in the text. In particular, we regress patent count on firm R&amp;D 
expenditure by controlling for firm sales, firm fixed effects, and year fixed effects. In order to evaluate 
whether private firms and state-owned enterprises have different elasticity regarding R&amp;D expenditure, 
we interact firm ownership with R&amp;D expenditure in the regressions. The interaction term between the 
state-owned enterprise dummy and R&amp;D variable is statistically negative, indicating that the elasticity of </p>

<p>Table 4 
Patents, Research and Development Expenditure, and Subsidies by Firm Type 
and Size </p>

<p>Size by sales quantile </p>

<p>Firm type 
0-20% 
20-40% 
40-60% 
60-80% 80-100% </p>

<p>Number of patents 
Private 
1,107 
2,630 
4,003 
7,585 
64,586 
Foreign 
226 
579 
876 
3,031 
44,178 
State 
46 
87 
177 
351 
9,116 </p>

<p>R&amp;D expenditure (million 
RMBs) </p>

<p>Private 
769 
1,763 
3,335 
7,933 
143,848 
Foreign 
122 
312 
760 
2,333 
86,946 
State 
41 
112 
210 
595 
51,172 </p>

<p>(Subsidies/sales) × 100 
Private 
0.22 
0.25 
0.25 
0.24 
0.31 
Foreign 
0.13 
0.11 
0.11 
0.11 
0.11 
State 
0.84 
0.86 
0.71 
0.74 
0.27 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculation based on Annual Surveys of Above-Scale Manufacturing Firms, 2005-2007. 
Note: We used a 2005-2007 sample; divided into 5 groups by sales; and drop observations that invest less 
than 100 Yuan but have positive patents. "Foreign" refers to firms for which foreign entities have at least 
10 percent of the share and the state has less than 50 percent share. "Private" includes all other firms. </p>



<p>in cases where the social returns exceed private returns (such as certain innovative 
activities) without regard to firm ownership. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>China's past success in economic growth means that its real manufacturing wage 
has increased by about 14-fold from 1980 to 2015. In addition, China's shrinking 
workforce since 2012 has added to the wage pressure. By necessity, China has to 
move to a growth model that is based more on innovation and productivity increase 
than in the past. 
Can China rise to the challenge? One sometimes hears an argument for the 
"middle-income trap hypothesis," which claims that only in exceptional cases can 
a middle-income country ever manage to become an innovative high-income 
economy. Indeed, the challenges facing China have often been expressed in the 
context of a possible middle-income trap by both the government of the country 
and some scholars (for example, OECD 2013; Ma 2016). Han and Wei (2015) do 
not find support for an unconditional notion of the middle-income trap hypothesis, 
using both a transition matrix analysis and a nonparametric analysis (by regres-
sion trees). Nonetheless, they identify certain conditions under which growth in a 
middle-income country could stagnate or even regress. 
We have argued that Chinese firms have demonstrated a capacity to become 
more innovative in response to wage pressure and global opportunities. The data 
on Chinese patents, both from a quantity and a quality perspective, appear encour-
aging enough that we should not be that pessimistic about China's prospects for a 
successful transition to a more innovation-based growth model. 
If China finds effective ways to embrace a shift to a more innovative economy, 
it can realize faster its dream of moving into the high-income club. The govern-
ment subsidies tend to favor state-owned firms, and yet both domestic private sector 
firms and foreign-invested firms are more effective in converting investment in 
R&amp;D to innovation outcomes as measured by patents. One meaningful step along 
those lines would be for China to reduce its apparent misallocation of innovation 
resources by leveling the playing field for firms of all ownership types, limiting the 
government's discretion in subsidies for research and development, and assuring 
that private sector firms have a fair chance at receiving those subsidies. This will be 
a helpful structural reform that will complement the reforms in stronger protection 
of intellectual property rights and in the education system. </p>

<p>patents granted with respect to R&amp;D expenditures is significantly higher for private firms than for SOEs. 
This finding is consistent with the view that state-owned enterprises have not spent R&amp;D resources as 
efficiently as private firms. </p>

<p>From "Made in China" to "Innovated in China": Necessity, Prospect, and Challenges 69 </p>

<p>■ We thank the editors Gordon Hanson, Enrico Moretti, and especially Timothy Taylor 
for very helpful comments and suggestions. We are also grateful for comments received at 
seminars/conferences held in Hong Kong Baptist University, New York University, University 
of Michigan, and University of Western Australia, and support from the Natural Science 
Foundation of China (Approval number 71350002), the National Science Foundation 
(Approval number 7675172), and the key research base of China Ministry of Education 
(14JJD790027). We thank Lea Sumulong and Joy Glazener for excellent editorial assistance 
and Lintong Li for outstanding research assistance. The paper represents the personal views of 
the authors and not necessarily those of the institutions with which they are affiliated. </p>







</text></tei>