<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1086%2Fma.20.3585423" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Eight years ago, two Macroeconomics Annual papers-Goodfriend 
and King (1997) and Rotemberg and Woodford (1997)-played a cen-
tral role in stimulating a burgeoning research program regarding the 
monetary policy implications of macroeconomic models with explicit 
microeconomic foundations.1 This research program incorporates two 
crucial elements compared with more traditional monetary policy anal-
ysis. First, reflecting the influence of the Lucas (1976) critique, the em-
phasis on explicit microeconomic foundations is intended to ensure 
that the resulting structural equations are reasonably invariant to the 
choice of monetary policy. Second, this research follows the standard 
public finance approach of determining the policy regime that maxi-
mizes household welfare and then evaluating the performance of alter-
native policies relative to this benchmark. 
After initially focusing on small stylized models, this line of research </p>

<p>has subsequently proceeded to analyze micro-founded macroeconometric </p>

<p>models that incorporate an expanded set of nominal and real rigidities 
and hence can be matched more closely to observed aggregate data. 
For example, Christiano, Eichenbaum, and Evans (2005) (henceforth 
CEE) specified a dynamic general equilibrium model with a number of 
distinct structural features: staggered wage and price setting with par-
tial indexation, habit persistence in consumption, endogenous capital 
accumulation with higher-order adjustment costs, and variable capac-
ity utilization.2 Smets and Wouters (2003a) (henceforth SW) later </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>applied full-information Bayesian methods to estimate essentially the 
same specification (augmented by a larger set of structural distur-
bances) and found that the model is competitive with an unrestricted 
Bayesian vector autoregression (VAR) in terms of goodness-of-fit and 
out-of-sample forecasting performance.3 
In this paper, we investigate the design of monetary policy when 
the central bank faces uncertainty regarding the true structure of the 
economy. Of course, a long-established literature has considered this 
topic using traditional structural macroeconomic models, building on 
the seminal work of Brainard (1967).4 Nevertheless, recent analysis 
of small stylized micro-founded models has demonstrated that the 
implications of uncertainty can be markedly different when the policy-
maker's goal is to maximize household welfare because the welfare 
function itself depends on the specification and parameter values of 
the model.5 
By using a micro-founded macroeconometric modeling framework, 
we can examine the policy implications of several aspects of uncer-
tainty that may be more difficult to consider in a small stylized model. 
First, by applying Bayesian methods, we can use the posterior distribu-
tion of the model parameters to determine whether simple rules that 
perform well in the baseline economy are robust to parameter uncer-
tainty, that is, to the range of parameter values that are reasonably con-
sistent with the observed data. Second, we can gauge the degree of 
innovation uncertainty by evaluating the extent to which the policy con-
clusions are sensitive to alternative assumptions regarding the nature 
and incidence of the structural shocks to the model. Finally, we can 
explore the implications of specification uncertainty by changing specific 
features of the model such as the role of money balances or the struc-
ture of nominal contracts.6 
As the baseline specification for our analysis, we use a micro-
founded macroeconometric model similar to those studied by CEE and 
SW. Applying a Bayesian procedure to estimate this model with post-
war U.S. data, we set the baseline values of the model parameters using 
the mean of the posterior distribution. We employ Lagrangian meth-
ods to determine the optimal policy under commitment in the baseline 
economy. Finally, we use second-order perturbation to solve the model </p>

<p>and compute the level of welfare under the optimal policy as well as 
for alternative simple rules.7 
We find that a simple interest rate rule that responds solely to nomi-
nal wage inflation and the lagged interest rate yields a welfare out-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>come that nearly matches that under the fully optimal policy.8 Because 
this rule involves only observable variables and does not require a 
measure of the output gap, the natural rate of interest, or forecasts of 
variables, the rule can be implemented without assuming that the poli-
cymaker knows the correct specification of the model or the true values 
of the model parameters. 
The near-optimality of the simple wage stabilization rule is directly 
attributable to the overriding importance of nominal wage inertia in 
determining the welfare costs of aggregate fluctuations in the base-
line economy. This inertia reflects the relatively long duration of nomi-
nal wage contracts as well as the nearly uniform degree of indexation 
to lagged inflation. Furthermore, under our baseline specification of 
Calvo-style contracts with an exogenous probability of reoptimization, 
many wage contracts remain in effect much longer than the one-year 
average duration. Thus, as emphasized by Erceg, Henderson, and 
Levin (2000), stabilizing aggregate wage inflation helps alleviate the 
degree of cross-sectional dispersion in real wages and thereby mini-
mizes the associated inefficiencies in employment of differentiated 
labor services and in the allocation of leisure across households. 
The simple wage stabilization rule is robust to parameter uncertainty 
and innovation uncertainty and to some modifications of the baseline 
model specification. For example, this rule yields near-optimal perfor-
mance for variations of model parameters based on the estimated pos-
terior distribution, a finding consistent with earlier work regarding the 
importance of parameter uncertainty.9 However, this rule is not robust 
across the full range of estimates of model parameters seen in the 
literature, which often lie in the extreme tails of our estimated pos-
terior distribution. Thus, research that reduces this type of uncer-
tainty regarding certain key parameter values could be used to design 
monetary policy that yields a significant increase in welfare. The 
performance of the wage stabilization rule is also relatively insensi-
tive to various assumptions regarding the nature and incidence of the 
innovations and to augmenting the model to incorporate monetary 
frictions. 
Nevertheless, this rule is not robust to alternative specifications of 
the wage-contracting mechanism. In particular, the welfare costs of </p>

<p>nominal wage variability are much smaller when wages are deter-
mined by Taylor-style contracts with the same average duration as in 
our baseline specification of Calvo-style contracts.io Thus, the simple 
wage stabilization rule is no longer nearly optimal, and better welfare </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>outcomes are provided by other simple rules that respond to price in-
flation and real economic variables. Of course, as Hall (2005) empha-
sizes, neither Calvo-style nor Taylor-style contracts provide the ideal 
microeconomic foundations for the determination of nominal wages 
and employment. Thus, our results should be interpreted as highlight-
ing the extent to which additional research regarding the structure of 
labor markets is likely to have substantial benefits for the design of 
monetary stabilization policy. 
The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. Section 2 pro-
vides an overview of the baseline model specification. Section 3 briefly 
describes the estimation procedure and the posterior distribution of the 
model parameters. Section 4 characterizes the optimal policy in the 
baseline economy and compares the performance of alternative simple 
rules. Sections 5 and 6 analyze the implications of parameter uncer-
tainty and innovation uncertainty, respectively. Section 7 considers 
several types of specification uncertainty. Section 8 concludes. The ap-
pendix contain some additional derivations and results. </p>

<p>2 The Model </p>

<p>As in CEE and SW, our baseline model incorporates a number of 
mechanisms that can induce intrinsic persistence in the propagation of 
shocks, including habit persistence in consumption, costs of adjust-
ment for investment and capacity utilization, and staggered nominal 
wage and price contracts with partial indexation. The model also 
includes a number of exogenous disturbances (assumed to be mutually 
uncorrelated) that account for the stochastic variation in the observed 
data used in our estimation procedure. </p>

<p>2.1 Household Preferences 
The economy has a continuum of infinitely lived households. The 
conditional welfare of a given household h e [0, 1] at a given time t is 
defined as the discounted sum of expected period utility: </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>Wt(h) 
= Et E8flj Vt+j(h), 
(4.1) </p>

<p>j=0 </p>

<p>where the subjective discount factor is ft 
= 
/Ztb and we define +j 
= </p>

<p>I=0o t+s. Thus, the steady-state subjective discount factor is given by </p>

<p>the parameter 0 &lt; p &lt; 1, while stochastic variation in the rate of time </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>preference is induced by the exogenous disturbance Zb; we assume 
that the logarithm of this disturbance follows an AR(1) process. 
The period utility function of a given household h at time t is speci-
fied as follows: </p>

<p>V(h) (Ct(h) -OCt-(h))1-" ZL(Lt(h))'+x </p>

<p>zn(Mt(h))1-K </p>

<p>Vt(h) = </p>

<p>-
+y </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(4.2) 
1-a 
1+X </p>

<p>1-K </p>

<p>where Ct(h) denotes the household's total consumption, Lt(h) denotes 
its labor hours, and Mt(h) denotes its real cash balances."1 The prefer-
ence parameters, a, x, K, and o, are strictly positive, while 0 lies in the 
unit interval. The exogenous disturbance ZfL induces stochastic varia-
tion in household preferences for leisure relative to consumption, and </p>

<p>Zn 
is an exogenous shock to money demand; the logarithm of each 
shock is assumed to follow an AR(1) process. 
Habit persistence in consumption is an important but somewhat 
controversial feature of this specification. In particular, for positive 
values of 0, the household's lagged consumption effectively serves as 
a reference value in determining the period utility generated by cur-
rent consumption.12 Recent empirical analysis of aggregate data has 
obtained substantial evidence of habit persistence; for example, CEE 
emphasize its role explaining the hump-shaped behavior of aggregate 
consumption in response to a monetary policy shock. Nevertheless, it 
should be noted that micro-level studies have occasionally obtained 
results that directly conflict with the macro evidence.13 
Of course, the curvature parameters of the utility function also re-
main quite controversial. Some studies have argued that a is around 
unity, while others find much larger values.14 Furthermore, microeco-
nometric studies have typically obtained estimates of x that are signifi-
cantly greater than unity, whereas some macroeconomists have argued 
that the aggregate data are consistent with a near-zero value of X, cor-
responding to a very high intertemporal elasticity of leisure for the rep-
resentative household.'5 
Finally, while this specification allows real money balances to di-
rectly influence household utility, most of our analysis will focus on 
the cashless economy emphasized by Woodford (2003) and others; this 
economy corresponds to the limiting case in which po becomes arbi-
trarily small. Later in the paper, however, we will revisit this issue and </p>

<p>examine the policy implications of incorporating a nontrivial role for 
money into the model. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>2.2 Production and Prices </p>

<p>The final composite good-used for both consumption and invest-
ment-is obtained by bundling together a continuum of differentiated 
intermediate goods using a Dixit-Stiglitz aggregator function. As in 
SW, we allow the elasticity of substitution between different goods </p>

<p>to exhibit exogenous temporal variation; that is, 
AP-</p>

<p>= ZPp. The pa-</p>

<p>rameter AP &gt; 0 determines the steady-state markup rate, while the </p>

<p>exogenous disturbance Z p (assumed to have an i.i.d. log-normal distri-
bution) shifts the desired markup at each point in time. A given firm, 
indexed by i e [0, 1], as the sole producer of intermediate good i, faces 
a downward-sloping demand curve, and its elasticity of demand </p>

<p>-(1 + ; P)/;ltp is invariant to the firm's level of production.16 </p>

<p>Interestingly, the steady-state markup parameter AP does not influ-</p>

<p>ence the first-order dynamics of the model economy and hence cannot 
be estimated using the methods employed in this paper. Nevertheless, 
this parameter does affect the second-order properties of the model, 
including the welfare performance of monetary policy rules. In light of </p>

<p>the available evidence from disaggregated data, we set AP = 0.20 in the </p>

<p>baseline version of the model, and then consider alternative values </p>

<p>from 0.1 to 0.5.17 </p>

<p>Every intermediate-goods producer has an identical production 
function that determines the gross output of good i as a Cobb-Douglas 
function of the firm's employment of labor services Nt(i), its rental of 
capital services Kt(i), and the exogenous economy-wide productivity 
factor At: </p>

<p>Yt(i) = AtKt (i) *Nt(i)1' -(D 
(4.3) </p>

<p>where the parameter a represents the share of capital in gross output, 
and we assume that the logarithm of the productivity factor follows 
an AR(1) process. As in CEE and SW, every firm hires its capital and 
labor services on competitive economy-wide markets and hence has 
the same marginal cost of production. 
The firm's net output Yt(i) reflects the presence of the fixed overhead 
cost (. This fixed cost induces locally increasing returns to scale for 
each individual firm and generates procyclical total factor productivity 
at the aggregate level. Thus, inferences about the value of ( can be 
made using both micro-level and macro-level data. </p>

<p>In the baseline version of the model, we assume that prices are deter-
mined by Calvo-style nominal contracts with partial indexation.18 In </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>particular, every firm faces a constant probability 1 -~p of reoptimiz-
ing its price contract in any given period, where ep e [0, 1]; thus, price 
contracts have an average duration 1/(1 -p). Whenever the contract 
is not reoptimized, the firm's price is adjusted automatically by the 
lagged rate of inflation raised to the power yp 
~ [0, 1]. 
This specification of price-setting behavior provides formal under-
pinnings for the hybrid New Keynesian Phillips curve.19 In particu-
lar, the indexation parameter yp determines the relative weight on the 
backward-looking versus forward-looking terms in the hybrid Phillips 
curve. While the magnitude of these weights is subject to ongoing 
controversy, recent analysis of aggregate data seems to be largely con-
sistent with the available microeconomic evidence indicating that in-
dexation is not a typical characteristic of price adjustment.20 
Under the assumption that all firms have the same marginal cost, 
the responsiveness of inflation to current marginal cost is determined 
solely by the parameter ?p. Typically, as in SW, the estimated value of 
?p tends to imply a relatively long average duration of price contracts 
that is inconsistent with recent microeconomic evidence.21 Several re-
cent studies have shown that incorporating additional real rigidities-
such as quasi-kinked demand and firm-specific capital-yields 
more plausible estimates of the degree of nominal rigidity.22 Neverthe-
less, analyzing the second-order implications of these mechanisms 
poses some technical challenges that remain to be addressed in the 
literature. </p>

<p>2.3 Investment and Capacity Utilization 
Households own the entire stock of physical capital Kt. Capital accu-
mulation is subject to adjustment costs that are assumed to be propor-
tional to the squared growth rate of investment rather than the more 
traditional formulation involving the squared level of investment. As 
emphasized by CEE, this specification of adjustment costs can gen-
erate a hump-shaped response of aggregate investment to a monetary 
policy shock, consistent with the implications of an identified vector 
autoregression. While the formal microeconomic foundations of this 
mechanism were initially opaque, Basu and Kimball (2003) have sub-
sequently shown that very similar implications can be obtained in a 
framework with planning delays in investment. </p>

<p>Thus, the capital stock owned by a given household h E [0, 1] evolves 
as follows: </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Kt(h) </p>

<p>= (1 -6)Kt-1(h) + [1 -1(z[It(h) </p>

<p>1)2] (h) 
(4.4) </p>

<p>where Kt(h) denotes the household's beginning-of-period capital stock, 
and It(h) denotes the gross investment during period t. The deprecia-
tion rate is given by 6, and the parameter C gauges the magnitude of 
investment adjustment costs.23 Finally, the exogenous disturbance Z[ 
acts as an economy-wide shock to investment demand; its logarithm 
follows an AR(1) process. 
In each period, the aggregate flow of capital services Kt to the inter-
mediate goods sector is defined as the capacity utilization rate Ut mul-
tiplied by the predetermined level of the physical capital stock, Kt-1. 
The capacity utilization rate can vary from its steady-state value of 
unity, but such variations are associated with a real resource cost. In 
particular, we specify the resource cost It(h) incurred by a given 
household h as a constant elasticity of substitution (CES) function of its 
capacity utilization Ut(h): </p>

<p>Ut 
(h)l+1 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>Ut(h) 
= </p>

<p>1 + </p>

<p>(4.5) </p>

<p>1+ -</p>

<p>where &gt; ? 0 and u &gt; 0.24 
As emphasized by CEE, variable capacity utilization can effectively 
enhance the short-term flexibility of the economy in response to aggre-
gate shocks. Nevertheless, the magnitude of the utilization cost param-
eter / is currently subject to a great deal of uncertainty due both to the 
scarcity of microeconomic evidence and to conflicting results from re-
cent macroeconometric analysis. For example, CEE find that variations 
in capacity utilization play an important role in explaining the sluggish 
response of inflation to a monetary policy shock, whereas the results of 
Altig, Christiano, Eichenbaum, and Linde (2004) suggest that the ag-
gregate effects of a technology shock are consistent only with relatively 
limited variations in capacity utilization. 
Finally, following SW, we include an external finance premium 
shock Zq (assumed to have an i.i.d. log-normal distribution), which 
acts as a wedge between the risk-free real interest rate and the required 
expected rate of return on physical capital. Recent analysis of firm-level 
data has obtained precise estimates of the magnitude and cyclical </p>

<p>behavior of the external finance premium (see Levin, Natalucci, and 
Zakrajsek 2004). However, further theoretical and empirical research is </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>clearly needed to elucidate the underpinnings and implications of this 
mechanism. </p>

<p>2.4 Employment and Wages 
Households provide a continuum of differentiated labor services, 
which are bundled together using a Dixit-Stiglitz aggregator function 
and then rented to the intermediate sector. As in SW, we allow the 
elasticity of substitution between different types of labor services to 
exhibit exogenous temporal variation; that is, At-= ZIlw. The parame-
ter i" &gt; 0 determines the steady-state markup of real wages over the 
marginal rate of substitution between consumption and leisure. The 
exogenous disturbance Zw' (assumed to have an i.i.d. log-normal distri-
bution) shifts the desired wage markup at each point in time. Given 
this specification, a given household h e [0, 1], as the sole provider of 
the labor service of type h, faces a downward-sloping labor demand </p>

<p>curve with elasticity -(1 + At )/t w. </p>

<p>In the baseline version of the model, we assume that wages are de-
termined by Calvo-style nominal contracts with partial indexation. </p>

<p>In particular, each household faces a constant probability 1 -~, of </p>

<p>reoptimizing its wage contract in any given period, where w, e [0, 1]. 
Whenever the contract is not reoptimized, the household's wage is 
automatically adjusted by the lagged rate of price inflation raised to 
the power yw 
e [0, 1]. 
The steady-state markup parameter ;w and the contract wage pa-
rameter r, cannot be identified independently from the log-linear 
dynamics of the model. Given the scarcity of disaggregated evidence </p>

<p>on these two parameters, we proceed by calibrating AW = 0.20 (the 
same baseline value as for AP) and estimating the value of W,.25 We </p>

<p>will then gauge the policy and welfare implications of alternative com-
binations of these two parameters that yield the same first-order be-
havior of the model. 
Because the wage-setting mechanism has crucial implications for 
the design of optimal monetary policy, we will also consider two 
modifications to the baseline specification, namely, indexation of 
wages to lagged wage inflation instead of lagged price inflation 
and the use of fixed-duration Taylor-style wage contracts instead of 
Calvo-style contracts. As we will see, these alternative specifica-</p>

<p>tions yield significantly different implications for monetary policy and 
welfare. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>2.5 Fiscal and Monetary Policy 
We assume that government spending is exogenously determined and 
exhibits persistent variations; in particular, its logarithm follows an 
AR(1) process. As is evident from the previous discussion, government 
spending has no direct effects on either utility (through purchases of 
public goods) or production (perhaps via a stock of public capital); 
consideration of these channels, as well as automatic fiscal stabilizers, 
is deferred to future research. 
Furthermore, we assume that the government offsets the steady-state 
effects of monopolistic distortions by enacting the appropriate magni-
tude of production and employment subsidies, which are financed via 
a constant level of lump-sum taxes. Thus, the deterministic steady state 
is Pareto-optimal in the baseline model with a zero inflation rate. Un-
der these assumptions, we can focus our analysis on the stabilization 
task of monetary policy, abstracting from the complications that would 
arise if the central bank also played a role in trying to offset the effects 
of steady-state distortions.26 
In estimating the model, we use a fairly simple monetary policy rule 
in which the short-term nominal interest rate responds to the lagged 
interest rate as well as to deviations of aggregate price inflation from 
target and of actual output from the level that would prevail in the 
absence of nominal inertia. This specification includes two additional 
exogenous shocks, namely, persistent AR(1) shifts in the inflation objec-
tive and transitory white-noise shocks to the current policy rate. In our 
normative analysis, of course, we consider the full Ramsey policy as well 
as alternative specifications of simple policy rules, and we assume that 
monetary policy does not exhibit any exogenous stochastic variation. </p>

<p>3 Model Estimation </p>

<p>We employ Bayesian methods to estimate the log-linearized version of 
the model, using quarterly U.S. data over the period 1955:1 through 
2001:4.27 In particular, we treat seven aggregate variables as directly 
observed: real consumption, real investment, real gross domestic prod-
uct (GDP), real wages, total hours, GDP price inflation, and the federal 
funds rate.28 Because the rest of the model variables (such as the capital 
stock) are treated as unobserved, we use the Kalman filter in comput-</p>

<p>ing the likelihood function of the model. 
As widely recognized in earlier work, certain structural parameters 
are not well-identified from the cyclical dynamics of the data. There-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>fore, we use long-term historical averages to specify the values of these 
parameters: the capital share parameter a = 0.36, the discount factor </p>

<p>fl = 0.99 (corresponding to a steady-state real interest rate of about 4 </p>

<p>percent), and the depreciation parameter = 0.025 (corresponding to 
an annual rate of about 10 percent). Similarly, we calibrate the out-
put shares of consumption, investment, and government spending at 
cy = C/Y = 0.56, iy = 0.24, and gy = 0.20, respectively.29 Finally, we </p>

<p>set the wage and price markup parameters 'w = AP = 0.2; in the fol-</p>

<p>lowing section, we will consider the implications of alternative values 
for these two parameters. 
We formulate independent prior densities for each of the other 
thirty-one parameters of the model, namely, ten parameters related to 
preferences and technology, five coefficients of the empirical interest 
rate reaction function, and sixteen parameters of the data-generating 
processes for the disturbances. Overall, our prior is consistent with 
the previous literature and is relatively uninformative for most of the 
parameters; details are given in the appendix.30 Given these priors, 
we characterize the posterior distribution using a Metropolis-Hastings 
Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm. Our estimation meth-
odology is broadly similar to that of Lubik and Schorfheide (2005); fur-
ther details are provided in the appendix.31 
In the remainder of this section, we focus on characterizing the pos-
terior distribution of the key structural parameters. Table 4.1 reports 
the posterior means and the 5 percent and 95 percent bounds for each 
of these parameters. Corresponding results for the parameters of the 
shock processes may be found in the appendix. 
As depicted in figure 4.1, the macroeconomic data are quite informa-
tive regarding the parameters related to price and wage determination. 
In light of recent micro-based evidence obtained by Bils and Klenow 
(2004) and Golosov and Lucas (2003), we specify a prior mean of 0.38 
for the Calvo price-setting parameter cp, corresponding to an average 
contract duration of about 1.5 quarters; we employed the same prior 
mean for the Calvo wage parameter ,. In contrast, the posterior mean 
estimates for these two parameters imply an average contract duration 
of about five quarters, similar to the findings of CEE and SW.32 Fur-
thermore, the posterior probability intervals of these estimates are rela-</p>

<p>tively narrow, suggesting a fairly clear disconnect between the micro 
and macro evidence. 
We impose relatively uninformative priors on the degree of price 
and wage indexation. The estimate of the degree of price indexation is </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.1 
Estimation Results </p>

<p>Posterior 
90% Probability 
Parameter 
Mean 
Interval </p>

<p>cp Calvo prices 
0.83 
0.81-0.86 </p>

<p>w, Calvo wages 
0.79 
0.72-0.85 </p>

<p>yp Price indexation 
0.08 
0.00-0.21 </p>

<p>,w Wage indexation 
0.79 
0.43-1.00 
C Investment adjustment 
0.56 
0.27-0.86 
a Consumption utility 
2.19 
1.68-2.74 
0 Consumption habit 
0.29 
0.20-0.38 </p>

<p>X Labor utility 
1.49 
0.95-2.12 
Fixed cost 
1.09 
1.06-1.11 </p>

<p>40 Capital utilization </p>

<p>0.21 
0.12-0.31 </p>

<p>near 0 and relatively precisely estimated; in contrast, the degree of 
wage indexation is found to be substantial but very imprecisely esti-
mated. The lack of price indexation differs from SW but is consistent 
with the findings of Ireland (2001) and Edge, Laubach, and J. Williams 
(2003). 
The macroeconomic data are somewhat less informative regarding 
other structural parameters. Figure 4.2 repeats the previous figure for 
the structural parameters not related to price and wage determination. 
Overall, the resulting estimates are consistent with estimates from the 
literature. Except for the parameters determining capacity utilization 
costs and habit persistence, the posteriors do not differ greatly from 
the respective priors. The finding of a relatively tight posterior dis-
tribution for the capacity utilization cost parameter occurs despite the 
imposition of a relatively loose prior and contrasts with the wide dis-
persion of estimates of this parameter in the literature. 
One structural parameter that deserves further discussion is the 
returns to scale in production, 0. We chose a relatively tight prior cen-
tered on 1.08 for this parameter, based on the estimates of Basu (1996) 
and Basu and Fernald (1997), who find fixed costs of between 3 and 10 
percent. Our resulting mean estimate is 1.09. By comparison, when we 
imposed an uninformative prior, the mode estimate exceeded 2, a re-
sult consistent with the findings of SW but contrary to the micro evi-
dence. Despite this difference in point estimates, in fact the data were 
not terribly informative about this parameter, as seen in the figure. 
Interestingly, imposing our prior on q resulted in a small estimate of </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Calvo Price (?p) 
Calvo Wage (4w) 
30 
12 </p>

<p>-
Posterior 
25 
--Prior 
10 </p>

<p>20 
8 </p>

<p>C 15 
6 </p>

<p>2E 0 </p>

<p>0 
4 
. </p>

<p>0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 </p>

<p>Price Indexation (y,) 
Wage Indexation (yw) 
20 
5 </p>

<p>4 
15 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>C 10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5----------1-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>Parameter 
Parameter </p>

<p>Figure 4.1 </p>

<p>Estimated Posterior Distributions (Solid Lines) and Prior Distributions (Dashed) for the 
Price and Wage Parameters </p>

<p>investment adjustment costs. Our estimate of investment adjustment 
costs are noticeably lower than SW but more in line with those re-
ported by Altig, Christiano, Eichenbaum, and Linde (2004). 
For the monetary policy reaction function, we obtain the following 
estimation results: </p>

<p>rt = 0.84rt-_ + 0.16[2.7(rt_1 -;t-1) + 0.10yt-1] </p>

<p>(0.03) 
(0.3) 
(0.07) </p>

<p>+ 0.26Arrt + 0.51Ayt + r? </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.07) </p>

<p>where the estimated standard error of each coefficient is enclosed in 
parentheses. This reaction function exhibits a high degree of inertia, a </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Investment Adjustment Costs (?) 
Preferences (a) 
2.5 
1.5 </p>

<p>-
Posterior 
2 ----
Prior </p>

<p>i 
" 
\ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>S0.5 
I% </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
0 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Capacity Utilization (w) 
Labor Disutility (X) 
8 
1.5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 
0 
1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Returns to Scale (&lt;) 
Habit (0) 
35 
8 
30 
I </p>

<p>SI </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Returns to Scale 
Habit ( </p>

<p>315 
30 
2 </p>

<p>15 
;/ 
" </p>

<p>10 
0 </p>

<p>1 
1.05 
1.1 
1.15 
1.2 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 
Parameter 
Parameter </p>

<p>Figure 4.2 
Estimated Posterior Distributions (Solid Lines) and Prior Distributions (Dashed) for 
Structural Parameters </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>strong long-run response to inflation, modest sensitivity to the level of 
the output gap, and a sizeable response to changes in the output gap. 
As for the monetary policy shocks, we find that the inflation target 
t7r has significant variation and exhibits very high persistence ap-
proaching that of a random walk, while the transitory disturbance 
rq/ 
has negligible variance. It should be noted that our modeling frame-
work does not provide any rationale or potential benefits from a time-
varying inflation target or from idiosyncratic disturbances to the 
policy rule. Thus, given our focus on policies that maximize social 
welfare, we henceforth eliminate these two shocks by setting their var-
iances to 0. </p>

<p>4 Optimal Monetary Policy </p>

<p>In this section, we characterize the monetary policy implications of the 
baseline model at the posterior mean values of the estimated parame-
ters, abstracting from uncertainty about the true structure of the econ-
omy. We start by considering the optimal policy under commitment 
that maximizes conditional expected welfare and then compare the 
performance of simple rules in which the short-term interest rate is 
adjusted in response to one or more observable variables. </p>

<p>4.1 The Optimal Policy Problem 
The optimal policy under commitment can be computed by formulat-
ing an infinite-horizon Lagrangian problem in which the central bank 
maximizes conditional expected social welfare subject to the full set of 
nonlinear constraints implied by the private sector's behavioral equa-
tions and the market-clearing conditions of the model economy.33 The 
first-order conditions of this problem are obtained by differentiating 
the Lagrangian with respect to each of the endogenous variables (in-
cluding the policy instrument) and setting these derivatives to 0. Of 
course, performing these derivations by hand would be extremely 
tedious; thus, we utilize the symbolic <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> procedures developed by 
Levin and Lopez-Salido (2004).34 
We then proceed to analyze the behavior of the economy under 
optimal policy by combining the central bank's first-order conditions 
together with the private sector's behavioral equations and the market-</p>

<p>clearing conditions. Thus, the size of the model is much larger under 
the optimal policy because these first-order conditions take the place 
of a single interest rate reaction function, while the set of Lagrange </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>multipliers is added to the list of model variables. Nevertheless, it 
should be emphasized that no new parameters have been added to the 
model because the central bank's first-order conditions involve the 
same structural parameters as in the behavioral equations and market-
clearing conditions. 
Because this set of nonlinear equations involves rational expecta-
tions, numerical methods are required to characterize the equilib-
rium properties of the stochastic economy.35 Furthermore, while the 
first-order dynamics can be investigated by log-linearizing the model, 
higher-order methods are needed to evaluate conditional expected 
welfare.36 Therefore, we employ the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Dynare</rs> software package of Juil-
lard (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-date">2001</rs>) to compute the second-order approximation of the model 
economy.37 
Finally, as in Levin and Lopez-Salido (2004), our analysis is focused 
on evaluating the welfare cost of business cycles; that is, for each mone-
tary policy regime, we measure how conditional expected welfare 
changes in response to the stochastic variation of the model econ-
omy.38 Throughout the paper, welfare costs are expressed in terms of 
the equivalent percentage decline in steady-state consumption. </p>

<p>4.2 Characteristics of Optimal Policy 
The deterministic steady state of the baseline economy is characterized 
by a 0 inflation rate. In particular, as noted above, we assume that 
fiscal subsidies offset the steady-state monopolistic distortions to pro-
duction and employment, while money is essentially absent from the 
baseline specification. Thus, in the absence of stochastic shocks, the 
central bank's sole task is to choose the constant inflation rate that min-
imizes the degree of cross-sectional dispersion in prices and wages; in-
deed, by maintaining a 0 inflation rate, monetary policy succeeds in 
implementing the Pareto-optimal equilibrium in steady state. 
The first-order implications of the optimal policy are shown in figure 
4.3, which depicts the response of selected macro variables to an exog-
enous rise in the productivity factor.39 The optimal policy (solid line) 
yields a path of short-term real interest rates that closely resembles 
that of the real business cycle (RBC) economy with flexible wages and 
prices (dotted line); in contrast, real interest rates are nearly constant 
under the empirical reaction function (dashed line). In the RBC econ-</p>

<p>omy, real wages initially rise about 0.75 percent; with a constant price 
level, this adjustment occurs solely through a surge in nominal wage 
inflation. In contrast, the optimal policy for the baseline economy is </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Nominal Interest Rate 
Real Interest Rate 
0.1 
0.1 </p>

<p>0 
0-
S-0.1 
-0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-0.2 
-0.2 </p>

<p>-0.3 
-0.3 </p>

<p>-0.40 
5 
10 
15 
20 -0.4 0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Price Inflation 
Wage Inflation 
0.05 
0.8 </p>

<p>0 --</p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>C -0.05 -</p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>-0.1-0 </p>

<p>_____________ </p>

<p>-0.15 </p>

<p>.-0.2 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Labor Hours 
Consumption 
0.2 
0.5 </p>

<p>.......... ............... ........ 
0.45 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>............. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>II </p>

<p>-0.6 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>Figure 4.3 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Positive Shock to Productivity: Optimal 
Policy (Solid Lines), Empirical Reaction Function (Dashed), RBC Economy (Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>mainly oriented towards minimizing cross-sectional dispersion in wage 
rates and hence permits a noticeable decline in prices while nominal 
wage inflation remains close to 0. 
Under the optimal policy (as in the RBC economy), the positive 
shock to productivity induces a substantial decline in aggregate labor 
hours that is gradually reversed over the subsequent year. Under the 
empirical reaction function, labor hours decline only for a single quar-
ter and then rise above baseline. These findings relate to the debate re-
garding the empirical evidence of the response of hours to productivity 
shocks and the sensitivity of these results to monetary policy. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.2 
The Welfare Cost of Business Cycles </p>

<p>Empirical reaction function 
-2.57 </p>

<p>Optimized price inflation rule 
-2.60 </p>

<p>Optimized wage inflation rule 
-2.13 </p>

<p>Optimal policy 
-2.01 </p>

<p>We now compare the welfare implications of these policies for the 
baseline economy with stochastic variation in all of the exogenous dis-
turbances except the monetary policy shocks. For each policy, table 4.2 
reports the welfare cost of business cycles in terms of the equivalent 
percentage point change in steady-state consumption; this table also 
indicates welfare outcomes for two simple rules that are discussed fur-
ther below. 
Under the empirical reaction function, the welfare cost of business 
cycles in the baseline model is equivalent to a permanent 2.6 percent 
reduction in household consumption. The optimal policy is associated 
with a markedly lower cost of business cycles, equivalent to about 2 
percent of steady-state consumption. It should be noted that these wel-
fare costs are an order of magnitude larger than in the results empha-
sized by Lucas (2003) mainly because staggered contracts induce 
substantial cross-sectional dispersion in relative prices and wages.40 
To gauge these welfare results more concretely, we note that U.S. 
personal consumption expenditures were about $28,000 per person 
in 2004; thus, switching from the empirical reaction function to the 
optimal policy would permanently raise welfare by about $160 per 
person, while eliminating all stochastic variation in the economy 
would generate a permanent welfare gain exceeding $700 per person. 
As we will see below, however, the magnitude of the welfare costs can 
be quite sensitive to the parameter values of the model as well as to the 
specification of the innovations and the determination of wages and 
prices. </p>

<p>4.3 Simple Policy Rules 
We now consider the performance of simple policy rules with coeffi-
cients chosen to maximize welfare in the baseline model.41 In particu-
lar, we examine rules with the following form: </p>

<p>rt = rirt-1 + r7rt + ro,cot 
(4.6) </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>where the nominal interest rate rt responds to the price inflation rate </p>

<p>7rt and the nominal wage inflation rate wt as well as to the lagged 
nominal interest rate. This type of rule is operational in the sense of 
McCallum (1999): the policy instrument is determined only by observ-
able variables and not by model-specific constructed data such as the 
natural rates of interest and output, and forecasts of variables (which 
require knowledge of the economy).42 Furthermore, it is equivalent to 
targeting a deterministic path for the level of wages or prices; such pol-
icies have been shown to perform very well in the presence of the 0 
lower bound on nominal interest rates.43 
Given the role of wage dispersion in determining the welfare cost of 
business cycles, it is useful to consider policy rules that respond di-
rectly to nominal wage inflation, as suggested by Erceg, Henderson, 
and Levin (2000).44 Therefore, we consider a hybrid rule that responds 
differentially to both price and wage inflation, as well as rules that re-
spond to price inflation alone. Optimizing the coefficients of the hybrid 
rule to maximize welfare in the baseline model, we find that r,, = 3.2 
while r,, = 0. Thus, given that the optimized rule does not actually re-
spond to price inflation, we simply refer to this rule as the benchmark 
wage inflation rule. We then compare its performance to an alternative 
rule that does not respond to wages-henceforth referred to as the 
benchmark price inflation rule-for which welfare optimization yields </p>

<p>r, = 2.1. </p>

<p>As indicated in table 4.2, the benchmark wage inflation rule 
yields a welfare outcome nearly identical to the optimal policy; indeed, 
following this simple wage inflation rule rather than the optimal policy 
would incur a welfare cost equivalent to less than $35 per person 
per year. In contrast, the benchmark price inflation rule yields a 
welfare loss that is roughly the same as under the empirical reaction 
function. 
The impulse responses to the technology shock under the bench-
mark wage inflation rule mimics closely those of the optimal policy, as 
seen in figure 4.4. One difference is that the benchmark wage inflation 
rule initially tightens monetary policy, causing a slightly excessive 
fall in labor hours and consumption at the onset of the shock. After a 
few quarters, however, the benchmark wage inflation rule gets back </p>

<p>on track, and the paths of labor hours, consumption, and price and 
wage inflation are virtually identical to those obtained under the opti-
mal policy. In contrast, the benchmark price inflation rule is overly </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Nominal Interest Rate 
Real Interest Rate 
0.4 
0.4 </p>

<p>, 
0.2 
0.2 </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>-0.2 
-0.2 </p>

<p>-0.4 
-0.4 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Price Inflation 
Wage Inflation 
0.05 
0.1 </p>

<p>0 
-" "' 
0.05 </p>

<p>.o.o.s </p>

<p>:-</p>

<p>, . ...... </p>

<p>. 
-0.05-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-0.1 .. 
-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.15 
-0.1 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Labor Hours 
Consumption 
1 
0.8 </p>

<p>0. 
0.6 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>-0.5 
04 </p>

<p>-1 
0.2 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>Figure 4.4 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Positive Shock to Productivity: Optimal 
Policy (Solid Lines), Optimized Wage Inflation Rule (Dashed Lines), and the Optimized 
Price Inflation Rule (Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>stimulative at the onset of the shock, keeping price inflation near base-
line but generating excessive nominal wage inflation. </p>

<p>5 Parameter Uncertainty </p>

<p>In this section, we explore the sensitivity of household welfare to varia-
tions in the parameters under the wage inflation policy rule optimized 
to the baseline parameters discussed in Section 3. We evaluate the per-
formance of this rule in comparison with that of the optimal policy de-
termined using the true values of the model parameters. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>5.1 Estimated Parameters 
We start by considering the effect of uncertainty as measured by our 
estimated posterior distribution. We compute the welfare losses associ-
ated with joint parameter uncertainty of the ten structural parameters 
together.45 For this purpose, we randomly select 5,000 draws of the 
parameter vector from the posterior distribution described above. For 
each draw, we compute welfare under the optimal policy for the 
true set of parameters and under the benchmark wage inflation policy. 
Note that this method incorporates the covariance between the model 
parameters, allowing for the possibility that particular combinations of 
parameter realizations may have sizeable effects on outcomes. Figure 
4.5 reports the results from this exercise; the upper panel shows the 
resulting distributions of welfare losses under the two policies, and the 
lower panel shows the distribution of the relative welfare loss equal to 
the difference in welfare between the optimal policy and the bench-
mark wage inflation rule. 
Uncertainty about the structural parameters implies a great deal of 
uncertainty regarding the welfare loss associated with fluctuations, 
but far less uncertainty regarding the performance of the benchmark 
wage inflation rule relative to the optimal policy. As seen in the upper 
panel of the figure, the distribution of welfare losses under either pol-
icy is wide with a relatively long left tail. Under the optimal policy, the 
median welfare loss is 2.1 percent, just 0.1 percentage point larger than 
for the posterior mean estimates, but the 90 percent confidence interval 
for the welfare loss ranges from 4.3 percent to 0.9 percent. The results 
under the benchmark wage inflation rule are comparable. Thus, pa-
rameter uncertainty can easily make the welfare costs of fluctuations 
more than double what we estimate, or half as large, for that matter. 
However, as the lower panel of the figure shows, the performance of 
the benchmark wage inflation rule relative to the optimal policy is re-</p>

<p>markably robust to parameter uncertainty. Indeed, the mean relative 
welfare loss, evaluated over the posterior distribution, is 0.14 percent, </p>

<p>compared to 0.12 percent assuming no uncertainty, and the 90 percent 
probability interval for the relative welfare loss is fairly narrow, rang-
ing from 0.06 to 0.35 percent. 
Because the benchmark rule performs so well across the posterior </p>

<p>distribution, it is not surprising that taking account of parameter un-
certainty as measured by the posterior distribution has almost no effect 
on the parameters or expected performance of the optimized wage in-
flation rule. We computed the coefficient of a wage inflation rule that </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-
Optimal policy 
0.4 
---Wage inflation rule </p>

<p>S0.3 </p>

<p>0 0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
8 
7 
6 
5 
4 
3 
2 
1 
0 </p>

<p>Welfare Loss </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>c 4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.6 
0.5 0.4 0.3 0.2 0.1 
0 </p>

<p>Welfare Loss Relative to Optimal Density </p>

<p>Figure 4.5 
The Distribution of Welfare Losses for the Estimated Posterior Distribution 
Note: The top panel represents welfare losses relative to the steady state for the optimal 
policy tuned to each parameter draw (solid line) and the benchmark wage inflation rule 
(dashed line). The bottom panel represents the difference in welfare loss between the op-
timal and benchmark wage inflation rule. </p>

<p>maximizes expected welfare integrating over the posterior distribution 
as above. The optimal coefficient equals 2.9, slightly lower than the 
value of 3.2 in the case of no uncertainty. But this rule yields an in-
crease in expected welfare relative to the benchmark wage inflation 
rule of only 0.0004 percent. Thus, the existence of parameter uncer-
tainty, as measured by the posterior distribution, is nearly irrelevant 
for designing policy in this model. Of course, a significant reduction in 
this uncertainty could have implications for the design of policy and 
welfare, as we examine next. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>The degree of parameter uncertainty represented by the posterior 
distribution likely understates the true degree of uncertainty that poli-
cymakers face. As discussed in Onatski and N. Williams (2003) and 
Lubik and Schorfheide (2005), the mean and spread of the posterior 
distributions are highly sensitive to the assumed prior distributions. 
Point estimates and their standard errors are sensitive to estimation 
methodology, sample, and the values of calibrated parameters.46 This 
sensitivity is illustrated by the wide range of point estimates for 
various model parameters found in what are nearly identical models 
studied in CEE, SW, and this paper. 
Given this concern that the degree of parameter uncertainty may ex-
ceed that implied by the posterior distribution, we now examine the 
robustness of the benchmark wage inflation rule to a much wider set 
of parameter values. A second goal of this analysis is to uncover which 
parameters entail costly consequences when an estimate is far from the 
true value. To facilitate our analysis, we vary specific parameters one 
at a time, holding all other parameters at their respective mean esti-
mates. We focus our analysis on the difference in welfare between that 
found under the benchmark wage inflation rule and the optimal policy 
for the specified parameter. Again, we measure the potential loss in 
switching from the optimal policy (assuming that the true parameter 
value is known) to the benchmark wage inflation rule (optimized for 
the baseline parameters). 
We start with the parameters describing price and wage determina-
tion. Figure 4.6 plots the differences in the consumption-equivalent 
welfare losses between the optimal policy and the benchmark wage in-
flation rule as the four parameters related to price-and wage-setting 
are varied. The results for the Calvo parameters are shown in the 
upper panels; the results for the indexation parameters are shown in 
the lower panels. The vertical lines indicate the 5 percent and 95 per-
cent posterior bounds for the parameters calculated from the MCMC 
simulations. If the resulting plotted line is horizontal, estimation error 
for that parameter has no welfare costs, while a steeply sloped line 
indicates that parameter estimation error carries high costs and that 
better estimates could have a large social benefit. 
Although uncertainty regarding the wage and price parameters 
based on the estimated probability intervals has very modest impli-</p>

<p>cations for the performance of the benchmark wage inflation rule, 
looked at from a broader or an explicitly min-max perspective, reduc-
ing uncertainty about price-and wage-setting parameters could yield </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Calvo Price (,p) 
Calvo Wage (w,) 
0 
0 </p>

<p>-0.2 
' 
0-0.2 </p>

<p>-I -0.4 wo-0.4 </p>

<p>-0.6 
-0.6 </p>

<p>-0.8 
-0.8 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
0 
0.5 
1 </p>

<p>Price Indexation (Yp) 
Wage Indexation (,w) </p>

<p>0 
0' </p>

<p>-0.2 
-0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>--0.4 
-0.4 </p>

<p>-
-0.6 
-0.6 </p>

<p>-0.8 
-0.8 </p>

<p>-1 
-1 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
0 
0.5 
Parameter 
Parameter </p>

<p>Figure 4.6 
Parameter Uncertainty: Price and Wage Setting 
Note: The difference in welfare between the benchmark wage inflation rule and the opti-</p>

<p>mal policy. The two vertical lines indicate the 5 and 95 percent bounds from the posterior </p>

<p>distributions. </p>

<p>moderate benefits in terms of monetary policy design and welfare. The 
relative performance of the benchmark wage inflation rule is sensitive 
to very high values of the Calvo wage parameter. For the other Calvo </p>

<p>price and indexation parameters, the performance of the benchmark 
wage inflation policy drops off if prices are reoptimized very fre-
quently or if a high share of contracts is indexed, neither of which is 
likely according to the posterior distribution. For example, consider 
the case that the true Calvo price parameter, cp, is as low as some of 
the micro evidence suggests. According to the posterior distribution, 
such a low value is extremely unlikely. But if true, knowledge of this </p>

<p>parameter could be used to design a monetary policy that yields a 
moderate improvement in welfare. The same applies for the Calvo </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Investment Adjustment Costs ( ) 
Preferences (a) </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>.J </p>

<p>-
-0.5-
-0.5 </p>

<p>-1 
-1 </p>

<p>0 
2 
4 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Capacity Utilization (V) 
Preferences (X) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.J </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-0.5-</p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-1L 
-1 
0 
2 
4 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Returns to Scale ( ) 
Preferences (0) </p>

<p>.J </p>

<p>2 -0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-1 -*----1 
0.8 
1 1.2 1.4 1.6 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
Parameter 
Parameter </p>

<p>Figure 4.7 
Parameter Uncertainty: Other Structural Parameters 
Note: The difference in welfare between the benchmark wage inflation rule and the opti-
mal policy. The two vertical lines indicate the 5 and 95 percent bounds from the posterior 
distributions. </p>

<p>wage and price indexation parameters. Although the degree of wage 
indexation is imprecisely estimated, the relative welfare loss is nearly 
invariant to the value of this parameter. 
Figure 4.7 plots the results for the parameters related to preferences 
and technology. Given the estimated precision of these parameter esti-
mates, parameter uncertainty has trivial implications for welfare and 
therefore for policy. For example, although x, the parameter measuring 
the disutility of labor, is imprecisely estimated, it has only a modest 
effect on relative welfare. 
It should be noted that the parameter 0, which measures the degree 
of increasing returns, does have a significant effect on relative welfare </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>under the benchmark wage rule. With a loose prior, we would esti-
mate a value for this parameter near 2. Assuming that the results of 
the literature indicating at most modest increasing returns are true, the 
resulting reduction in uncertainty has a large effect on welfare in this 
model, assuming policy is designed to be optimal at the baseline esti-
mates. Moreover, our estimate of the habit persistence parameter is on 
the low side of recent estimates, which tend to find values in the 0.5-
0.7 range. Once again, we find such values to be unlikely, but we find 
a significant drop in the performance of the benchmark wage inflation 
rule when the habit parameter increases past 0.5. Finally, knowledge of 
the true magnitude of investment adjustment costs would be valuable 
for policy design. </p>

<p>5.2 Steady-State Markups 
As noted above, we cannot estimate the steady-state price and wage 
markups using the first-order dynamics of the model but instead cali-
brate both to be 20 percent. Given the uncertainty regarding the values 
of these parameters, we briefly explore the implications of alternative 
calibrations of the steady-state markups for monetary policy. 
The magnitude of welfare losses depends on the steady-state price 
markup, but the performance of the benchmark wage inflation rule rel-
ative to the optimal policy is insensitive to this parameter. We evaluate 
the welfare losses under four representative monetary policies ana-
lyzed above as AP is varied from 0.1 to 0.5, holding all other parameters 
fixed. Recall that the steady-state price markup does not affect the first-
order properties of the system.47 The results are shown in the upper 
part of table 4.3. Welfare losses are larger when the steady-state price 
markup is smaller, reflecting the effect of greater dispersion when 
goods are more highly substitutable. The relative performance of the 
various policies is insensitive to the value of the steady-state price 
markup. 
The welfare losses are highly sensitive to the value of the steady-
state wage markup, and for very high values of this parameter, the 
performance of the benchmark price inflation policy rule approaches 
that of the benchmark wage inflation rule. In considering the effects of </p>

<p>variations in 2", we vary the value of Calvo wage parameter, ?,, so </p>

<p>that the first-order properties of the model are constant.48 We hold all </p>

<p>other parameter values fixed at baseline values. Note that even with a 
high steady-state wage markup, the benchmark wage inflation policy 
rule performs well, although the difference between it and the rules </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Table 4.3 
Welfare Losses and the Steady-State Markups </p>

<p>Benchmark Benchmark 
Wage 
Price 
Optimal 
Empirical 
Inflation 
Inflation 
Experiment 
Policy 
Reaction 
Rule 
Rule </p>

<p>Price markup: )P 
0.10 
-2.13 
-2.72 
-2.23 
-2.64 
0.20 
-2.01 
-2.57 
-2.13 
-2.60 
0.50 
-1.92 
-2.48 
-2.07 
-2.57 </p>

<p>Wage markup: A" 
0.05 
-4.91 
-7.94 
-6.05 
-7.90 
0.10 
-3.18 
-4.43 
-3.47 
-4.44 
0.20 
-2.01 
-2.57 
-2.13 
-2.60 
0.50 
-1.15 
-1.42 
-1.30 
-1.45 </p>

<p>that respond to price inflation is much smaller than in the baseline 
model. </p>

<p>6 Innovation Uncertainty </p>

<p>We now consider alternative assumptions regarding the set of shocks 
in the model. In computing welfare, we have had to take a stand on 
each shock as to whether it reflects shifts in fundamentals, the effects 
of distortions, or measurement error. In particular, we have assumed 
that the wage and price shocks and the shocks to the external finance 
premium are distortionary, while the remaining shocks reflect shifts in 
fundamentals. We now revisit these assumptions and evaluate the per-
formance of the various monetary policies under alternative assump-
tions regarding the nature of innovations. 
The baseline model is admittedly profligate in specifying shocks. In 
particular, the external finance premium has a large estimated variance 
and may be important for welfare according to the model but arguably 
lacks micro-foundations. It is important to note that we have assumed 
that this shock does not affect fundamentals but instead represents 
inefficient fluctuations in an external finance premium or a type of 
"animal spirits" that monetary policy should counteract. Therefore, we 
consider an alternative model specification in which these shocks do 
not exist; that is, Tobin's Q strictly follows fundamentals. We assume 
that these shocks represent measurement error evident in estimating </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.4 
Welfare Under Innovation Uncertainty </p>

<p>Benchmark Benchmark 
Wage 
Price 
Optimal 
Empirical Inflation Inflation 
Experiment 
Policy 
Reaction Rule 
Rule </p>

<p>Baseline specification 
-2.01 
-2.57 
-2.13 
-2.60 </p>

<p>Eliminate shocks to: 
External finance premium 
-2.00 
-2.55 
-2.11 
-2.57 
Price markup 
-1.95 
-2.51 
-2.04 
-2.48 </p>

<p>Wage markup 
-0.22 
-0.44 
-0.30 
-0.65 
Time preference 
-2.29 
-2.78 
-2.38 
-2.76 
Labor disutility 
-2.24 
-2.79 
-2.36 
-2.79 </p>

<p>Assume shocks distortionary 
Time preference 
-2.58 
-3.35 
-2.68 
-3.08 
Labor disutility 
-2.46 
-3.14 
-2.59 
-3.01 </p>

<p>the model but that they have no effects on the actual allocation of 
resources. We do not re-estimate the model, but rather we simply set 
the variance of the external finance premium shocks to 0.49 The second 
line of table 4.4 reports the results from this experiment. Eliminating 
the external finance premium shocks has little effect on welfare or on 
the relative performance of the various policy rules. 
We further examine how the policy rules perform under alternative 
assumptions regarding the nature of shocks to price and wage mark-
ups. In the baseline model, these shocks are viewed as being distortion-
ary movements in markups. We now consider the possibility that these 
disturbances simply reflect measurement error that the econometrician 
faces in estimating the model. In implementing this idea, we do not re-
estimate the model, but instead simply zero out the markup innova-
tions. We continue to assume that the policymaker is able to measure 
wage and price inflation accurately, that is, absent measurement error. 
(If the markup shocks in fact represented measurement error that the 
policymaker confronts, then the performance of the policy rules that 
we consider would deteriorate.) We consider each shock in isolation 
and the combined effect. The results are shown in the upper part of 
table 4.4. 
Eliminating either markup shock reduces the welfare costs of fluctu-
ations but does not alter the relative performance of the various policy 
rules. In either case, the welfare gap between the optimal policy and </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>the benchmark wage inflation rule is reduced relative to that in the 
baseline specification. The price shocks have relatively little effect on 
welfare; the wage shocks, however, are an important source of welfare 
loss under both the optimal and the benchmark policies but neverthe-
less have little effect on the relative performance of the benchmark 
wage inflation policy rule. 
Finally, we consider the nature of disturbances to preferences. In the 
baseline model, we have assumed that shocks to time preference and 
the disutility of labor reflect fundamental movements in the economy 
that monetary policy should accommodate. We consider two alterna-
tive assumptions. First, we assume that the shocks merely reflect mea-
surement error and evaluate the four policies under the assumption 
that the preference shock does not exist. As before, we consider each 
shock in isolation. Eliminating either preference shock increases wel-
fare under the various policies by about 0.25 percentage point; that is, 
stochastic shocks to preferences are welfare-enhancing in our baseline </p>

<p>model.50 The performance of the benchmark wage inflation rule rela-
tive to the optimal policy is almost unchanged. Second, we consider 
the assumption that the preference shocks reflect nonfundamentals, 
such as changes in tax rates. The results are shown in the lower section 
of table 4.4. In this case, the welfare losses are significantly higher than 
in the baseline model, but again the performance of the benchmark 
wage inflation rule relative to the optimal policy does not deteriorate. 
Regardless of the assumption about the nature of these shocks, the 
benchmark wage inflation rule is nearly optimal and outperforms the 
estimated and benchmark price inflation rules by a significant margin. 
In summary, although innovation uncertainty exacerbates the already 
significant uncertainty about the magnitude of the welfare costs of 
fluctuations, the benchmark wage inflation rule is remarkably robust 
to changes in assumptions regarding the nature of shocks hitting the 
economy. </p>

<p>7 Specification Uncertainty </p>

<p>We now proceed to consider the broader problem of specification un-
certainty in the sense of Leamer (1978).51 In specifying the baseline 
model, we made numerous choices that affect the parameter estimates, </p>

<p>the structure of the model, and the determinants of welfare. In this 
section, we analyze the sensitivity of optimal policies to alternate 
assumptions regarding the model specification and evaluate the </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>marginal benefit of reducing uncertainty of each of the key specifica-
tion issues in terms of social welfare. As in the preceding section, this 
analysis provides information on the value, from the perspective of 
monetary policy, of improving our knowledge of specification issues 
and suggests where the highest payoffs are for further research in this 
area. While the list of specifications we consider is far from exhaustive, 
it provides some examples of the type of specification uncertainty that 
may be important for policy analysis. </p>

<p>7.1 Monetary Frictions and Working Capital 
Our baseline model can be viewed as a cashless economy that com-
pletely abstracts from monetary frictions. We now investigate the 
policy implications of incorporating household demand for money as 
well as working-capital considerations for firms. First, we permit the </p>

<p>scale parameter po to have a nontrivial value, so that real money </p>

<p>balances have direct effects on household utility. Second, following 
CEE, we assume that firms must borrow from financial intermediaries 
to cover their wage bill and then repay the loan at the end of the 
period. Thus, assuming that these funds can be obtained at the gross 
risk-free nominal interest rate, firms' total labor costs are now given by 
RtWtLt. 
Since we specify that policy is conducted via an interest rate rule, 
we do not need to concern ourselves with market clearing in the loan 
market. This would only serve to pin down the value of broad money. 
Instead, we simply append the portfolio allocation decision to deter-
mine the household's cash balances (which now affect welfare), and 
we incorporate the effects of working capital on firms' labor demand 
and marginal costs. We then re-estimate the model, using data on cash 
balances in addition to the seven variables noted above.52 The mode 
estimate of the preference parameter K is 11.4, while the mode esti-
mates of all other model parameters are nearly the same as in the base-
line specification.53 
The modified model has two key implications for policy. First, owing 
to the effects of nominal interest rates on costs and money balances, the 
optimal inflation rate is no longer 0 but is instead slightly below 0. 
Second, there is a cost to highly variable nominal interest rates that is </p>

<p>absent in the baseline model and a resultant benefit to smoothing inter-
est rates. As a result, the optimal wage inflation policy rule responds 
less aggressively to wage inflation, with a coefficient of 1.5, compared 
to 3.2 in the baseline model.54 The benchmark wage inflation rule </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>yields a welfare loss of 0.07 percentage points in terms of permanent 
consumption greater than a rule optimized for this alternative model 
with monetary frictions and working capital. </p>

<p>7.2 Alternative Models of Wage Setting 
A key result in our analysis is the importance of stabilizing wages 
owing to the distortions associated with wage dispersion under Calvo-
style contracts. Given the central role of this channel, we consider alter-
native specifications of wage setting that have significant effects on 
the welfare implications of sticky wages and on optimal policy. In par-
ticular, we consider two alternative specifications in which the effects 
of wage dispersion on welfare are muted relative to the Calvo-style 
model.55 
We first consider a modest modification to the indexation of wages 
in the model and assume that nonoptimized wages are indexed to last 
period's wage inflation rate, as opposed to the rate of price inflation. 
This modification reduces the effects of fluctuations in wage inflation 
on wage dispersion and thereby on welfare.56 Table 4.4 reports the 
results from this specification for four specifications of monetary pol-
icy. Not surprisingly, the consumption-equivalent loss in conditional 
welfare under the optimal policy is somewhat smaller than in the base-
line model. 
The relative performance of the benchmark wage inflation rule is 
considerably worse, however, under this form of wage indexation and 
is dominated by the rule that responds only to price inflation. Under 
the benchmark wage inflation policy rule, the consumption-equivalent 
loss in conditional welfare is 0.6 percentage points larger than under 
the optimal policy and 0.3 percentage points higher than under the 
benchmark price inflation rule. In fact, with this specification of wage 
indexation, the benchmark wage inflation policy rule does slightly 
worse than the estimated policy rule. Evidently, the result that a simple 
policy rule designed to maximize welfare should respond exclusively 
to wage inflation is not robust to changes in the model of wage de-
termination, even to this seemingly innocuous change in the model 
specification. 
We now consider a more substantive change in the specification of 
wage and price determination, and assume that contracts have fixed </p>

<p>duration as in Taylor (1980); see also Chari, Kehoe, and McGrattan </p>

<p>(2000).57 Compared with the baseline specification of Calvo-style 
contracts with random duration, this alternative specification limits </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.5 
Welfare Under Uncertainty Regarding Wage Setting </p>

<p>Benchmark Benchmark 
Wage 
Price 
Optimal 
Empirical Inflation 
Inflation 
Experiment 
Policy 
Reaction 
Rule 
Rule </p>

<p>Baseline specification 
-2.01 
-2.57 
-2.13 
-2.60 </p>

<p>Wage-wage indexation 
-1.85 
-2.34 
-2.46 
-2.15 
Taylor contracts 
-0.35 
-0.41 
-0.85 
-0.50 </p>

<p>the degree of price and wage dispersion-and the associated welfare 
costs-resulting from the presence of some prices and wages that have 
not been reoptimized for many periods. 
We suppose that nominal wages and prices are determined by 
staggered contracts that are reset every M periods. Thus, at t the </p>

<p>distribution of wages is given by {Wt, j} where j = 1,... ,M denotes </p>

<p>the number of periods since the last reset. In particular, we assume 
that all price and wage contracts last for four quarters, implying mean 
contract durations somewhat shorter than implied by our posterior 
mean estimates of the Calvo update parameters, ?p and 5,. We do not 
change any other parameter estimates and revert to the baseline as-
sumption that wages are indexed to past price inflation. The results 
are reported in table 4.5. As expected, replacing Calvo-style wage and 
price setting with Taylor-style contracts significantly reduces wage 
and price dispersion and hence the welfare costs associated with 
fluctuations. 
With Taylor-style staggered wages and prices, the relative perfor-
mance of the benchmark wage inflation rule falls dramatically, while 
the estimated policy rule is nearly optimal. The benchmark price infla-
tion rule outperforms the benchmark wage inflation rule but falls 
behind the estimated rule. With Taylor price and wage contracts, the 
welfare costs associated with price and wage dispersion are relatively 
modest and therefore the optimal policy focuses on coming close to 
the real allocation in the flexible wage and price economy. The esti-
mated rule accomplishes this balance very well, while the benchmark 
price inflation rule is somewhat less effective owing to a lack of re-
sponse to the output gap. The performance of the benchmark wage 
inflation rule suffers more significantly because it implicitly puts far 
too much emphasis on stabilizing nominal wage inflation relative to 
achieving the flexible wage and price real allocation.58 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Finally, it should be noted that the welfare cost of business cycles 
and the performance of alternative monetary policies are sensitive not 
only to the structure of nominal contracts but to the specification of 
household preferences. For example, as in CEE and SW, our analysis 
has followed Erceg, Henderson, and Levin (2000) in assuming that 
each individual household provides a distinct labor service, whereas 
Schmitt-Grohe and Uribe (2004) assume that each household has a con-
tinuum of members providing all types of labor services and that 
the household's utility depends only on its total hours of work. While 
such assumptions might seem to be merely technical details, in fact 
these differences have fairly dramatic consequences for the first-
order dynamics of wage inflation, the second-order effects of cross-
sectional wage dispersion, and the design of welfare-maximizing 
policy rules.59 </p>

<p>8 Conclusion </p>

<p>Over the past decade, there has been remarkable progress in devel-
oping empirical micro-founded macroeconomic models for monetary 
policy analysis. In this paper, we have drawn on and extended this 
literature to consider the design of policy under uncertainty. By con-
fronting a fully specified dynamic stochastic general equilibrium 
model with the data, we can directly gauge the uncertainty associated 
with the model parameters as well as the implications of alternative 
assumptions about the model specification. 
Our analysis indicates that the welfare cost of business cycles is quite 
large-an order of magnitude larger than the findings emphasized by 
Lucas (2003)-and arises mainly due to inefficiencies associated with 
cross-sectional dispersion in wages and employment. As a direct con-
sequence, we find that the welfare outcome associated with optimal 
policy under commitment is closely matched by a very simple rule 
that responds solely to nominal wage inflation. Furthermore, the per-
formance of this benchmark wage inflation rule is robust to uncertainty 
about the structural parameters and the particular shocks hitting the 
economy. The performance of this rule, however, is very sensitive to 
the specification of wage and price determination, suggesting that a 
hybrid rule involving both wage and price inflation might be more </p>

<p>robust across a broader class of models. 
These findings underscore the central importance of labor markets 
for analyzing the welfare costs of macroeconomic fluctuations and the </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>design of monetary policy. Of course, the crucial role of wage setting 
and employment dynamics has long been recognized, and recent re-
search has refocused interest on these issues; see Hall (2005). Thus, 
further progress in formulating micro-founded specifications of labor 
market behavior and comparing the empirical performance of these 
specifications is likely to have substantial payoffs for the design of 
monetary policy. 
Finally, while our analysis has emphasized the implications of poli-
cymaker uncertainty regarding the true structure of the economy, we 
have abstracted completely from the role of learning by policymakers 
or private agents. Nevertheless, we recognize that the learning mecha-
nism is crucial for understanding the evolution of the economy in re-
sponse to changes in the monetary policy regime-such as the Volcker 
disinflation-and to other aggregate disturbances.60 Thus, incorporat-
ing learning in micro-founded macroeconometric models and reconsi-
dering the policy implications represents a natural direction for future 
research.61 </p>

<p>9 Appendix </p>

<p>9.1 The Nonlinear Model </p>

<p>9.1.1 The Baseline Model The text describes the household side, 
and we now fill in some detail on the firm side. Define the capacity uti-
lization cost function from equation (4.5) by: </p>

<p>1+,-1 </p>

<p>1 + </p>

<p>where / is the inverse of the elasticity of utilization cost with respect to 
utilization, and y is chosen so that steady state utilization costs are 0. 
Also define the investment adjustment cost function from equation 
(4.4) by: </p>

<p>S(Z/It(i)/Itl(i)) = -1 
ZI(iIt(i) </p>

<p>1)2 </p>

<p>Note that adjustment costs are assumed to be 0 at the steady state, </p>

<p>S(1) = 0, and are only of second-order at the steady state. 
Index households by h and firms by i. Then denote by Nt(i) the labor 
input of plant i, given by: </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Nt(i) = [i Lt(i, </p>

<p>h)l/(l+t) </p>

<p>dhi </p>

<p>where Lt(i, j) is the input of labor of type j at plant i. The plant's out-
put is given by equation (4.3). 
Aggregate final good output, Yt is created by (costlessly) combining 
a continuum of intermediate goods, Yt(i), indexed by i: </p>

<p>F1r </p>

<p>1+ </p>

<p>Y= oJ Y(i) </p>

<p>P di 
(4.7) </p>

<p>Final goods output is equal to consumption; aggregate investment, It; 
government spending, Gt; and capital utilization costs: </p>

<p>Yt = Ct + Gt + It + P(Ut)Kt-1 
(4.8) </p>

<p>9.1.2 Equilibrium Allocation and Prices In the following, we omit 
household and plant indices where no confusion will result. The house-
hold's budget constraint is standard, and households trade in a com-
plete market to allocate their consumption over time. Let MUCt denote 
the marginal utility associated with an incremental increase in con-
sumption in period t, accounting for its effect on period utility in the 
period t + 1: </p>

<p>MUCt = Zb(ct -Ctl)-a 
flOEtZb+ Ct+-</p>

<p>t)-</p>

<p>(4.9) </p>

<p>The consumption Euler equation summarizes the representative house-
hold's optimal saving behavior: </p>

<p>MUCt = Et[MUCt+lR tPt/Pt+1] </p>

<p>(4.10) </p>

<p>where Rt is the gross nominal interest rate and Pt is the price level. 
Households set wages subject to their individual labor demand 
curves, which arise from the firms' input demands. The evolution of 
the aggregate nominal wage index is: </p>

<p>Wt/t' </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>-/wWt/1 
P-2 
+ (1 -w)tl/' 
(4.11) </p>

<p>Here, z?t is the optimal nominal wage chosen by those households that 
can optimize in the period, which satisfies: </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>~t +i </p>

<p>lwnt+i 
,bi-</p>

<p>zt (Lt+i(h))x -0 </p>

<p>(4.12) </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>As in usual in Calvo pricing models, equation (4.12) incorporates 
forward-looking expectations of future nominal wages but now in-
cludes lagged inflation via the partial indexation. 
Households own the capital stock, Kt, which they accumulate using 
the capital accumulation technology and rent to firms at rental rate Rt. 
This leads to three key relationships. First, we let Qt be the real share 
value per unit of capital, which is determined by an asset pricing Euler 
equation from equation (4.10): </p>

<p>Qt -Et[l </p>

<p>M 
(Qt+l(1 -6) + Ut+1l </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>T(Ut-+)) 
(4.13) </p>

<p>where Zq is the i.i.d. external finance premium shock. The optimal in-
vestment decision leads to an investment Euler equation: </p>

<p>(Z It Z It l </p>

<p>MUCt+l 
Z 
iS' 
ZIt+l 
ZlIt+l 
It+ </p>

<p>1 -QtS' ,It 
-Et 
Qt+1 S' 
t+i It+ </p>

<p>It-1)It-1 MUCt it It It </p>

<p>(4.14) </p>

<p>This equation balances the costs and benefits of investment, with 
lagged investment and the shocks showing up through the effects of 
the costs of adjustment. Finally, the first order condition for utilization 
gives: </p>

<p>Rt 
= </p>

<p>I'(Ut) </p>

<p>(4.15) </p>

<p>On the production side, the firms' cost-minimization conditions are 
symmetric and are given by: </p>

<p>WtLt </p>

<p>1 -
. 
-
(4.16) </p>

<p>RkUtKtl 
X </p>

<p>Thus, firms equate the marginal rate of transformation between labor 
and effective capital (UtKt-1) 
to the relative factor prices, and the 
capital-labor ratio is identical across firms. Marginal costs are then 
given by: </p>

<p>At </p>

<p>The evolution of the aggregate nominal price index is: </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>Pt-l+ 
+-</p>

<p>(1 -</p>

<p>p)Pt1i </p>

<p>(4.18) </p>

<p>pt 
pp?_,i </p>

<p>i 
~ </p>

<p>)f-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Here, Pt is the optimal price chosen by those firms that can optimize in 
the period, which satisfies: </p>

<p>Et 
-s </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>Pt (PtPt+s-1YP 
MC 
t+s </p>

<p>pt+s </p>

<p>EsZft+sSpsYt+s(i)MUCt+i </p>

<p>t-(1 + P+s) </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(4.19) </p>

<p>Finally, we close the model by specifying an empirical monetary 
policy reaction function. We specify policy in terms of a generalized 
Taylor-type rule, where the policy authority sets nominal rates in re-
sponse to inflation and the output gap. To do this, we define a model-
consistent output gap as the difference between actual and potential 
output, where potential output is defined as what would prevail under 
flexible prices and wages and in the absence of the three cost-push 
shocks (Z,,,Z , Zq) that cause variations in wage and price markups 
and the external finance premium. Thus, the model is supplemented 
with flexible-price versions of the key equations (4.10) through (4.18), 
which determine potential output Yt*. Then the policy rule is assumed 
to take the following form: </p>

<p>rt = rirt-1 + (1 -ri)(itt + r,(7t-1 -t7*1) + ry log(Yt-1/YW1)) </p>

<p>+ ra(7rt 
-7t-1) + ray{log(Yt/Yt*) 
-log(Yt-1/Y 1)1 + 
t+ 
(4.20) </p>

<p>Here, rt = log Rt is the short-term interest rate, 7rt = A In(Pt/Pt_1) is the 
inflation rate, 7r* is an AR(1) shock to the inflation objective, and q R is 
an i.i.d. policy shock. </p>

<p>9.1.3 The Model with Monetary Frictions In the model with mone-
tary frictions from Section 7.1, the household also has a portfolio allo-
cation decision. The first-order condition is: </p>

<p>ZtbCt(Mt/Pt)-K </p>

<p>= (Rt -1)MUCt 
(4.21) </p>

<p>The cost-minimization condition [equation (4.16)] now becomes: </p>

<p>RtWtLt 1 -a(4.22) 
v 
-(4.22) </p>

<p>RkUtKt-</p>

<p>In turn, the marginal cost changes from equation (4.17) to: </p>

<p>MCt = (RtWt) -(Rt) </p>

<p>-_(1 </p>

<p>-
" 
)1)-</p>

<p>(4.23) </p>

<p>At </p>

<p>Market clearing in the loan market then implies: </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>WtLt = At -Mt </p>

<p>where At represents the level of broad money after the infusion of 
money via the central bank. </p>

<p>9.1.4 The Model with Staggered Contracts In the model with stag-
gered contracts from Section 7.2, we must make a few alterations to the 
model. We again allow for partial indexation, so the evolution of an in-
dividual household's wage is given by: </p>

<p>Wej 
=Pt-l 
Wtl, 
j_1 
if j </p>

<p>-M 
Wifj'Pt_2) 
= wt 
if j=M </p>

<p>The aggregate wage index changes from equation (4.11) to: </p>

<p>W1/ 
1 
w1 
1/W 
(4.24) </p>

<p>Wt 1t, </p>

<p>j= 1 </p>

<p>Finally, the optimal wage choice satisfies: </p>

<p>EtM-1 </p>

<p>(PtPth)MUC 
t+i 
(Lt+i(h))z] 0 
(4.25) </p>

<p>Et 
t 
t </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>t S flt+inLti(h) </p>

<p>-Pt-it+i-</p>

<p>1 + tw </p>

<p>9.2 The Linearized Model </p>

<p>9.2.1 Baseline Model For much of the paper, we work with the log-
linearized version of the model described above, which we present 
here. We use lowercase letters to indicate the logarithmic deviations 
from steady state. In the case of shocks, e' and ' refer to the shocks 
normalized to the log-linear equations, with the e shocks being persis-
tent and the l shocks i.i.d. 
To save on notation, we define Rk as the mean real rate of return on 
capital, which is assumed to satisfy P = 1/(1 -6 + Rk), and 0 equals 
1 plus the share of fixed costs in production. Furthermore, we denote </p>

<p>cy, gy, and ky as the steady-state ratios of consumption, government </p>

<p>spending, and capital to output, respectively. 
The following ten equations in ten endogenous variables {ct, it, qt, </p>

<p>kt, rtk, Ut, it, yt, wt, t} are the linearized counterparts to the equations 
described in Section 9.1 of this appendix: </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>ct = Et </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>{ OCt-1 </p>

<p>+ (1 + 
fl02 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Po)Ct+l 
-
flOct+2 
1 
+--+ </p>

<p>flo2 </p>

<p>((1 -flO)(rt -lt+l) -E b 
+ (1 + 
eb+l </p>

<p>2)} </p>

<p>(4.26) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>qt -(rt -Et7rt+l) 
+1 -
{(1 -)Etqt+l </p>

<p>+ akEtrk+1} ?+ 1 </p>

<p>(4.27) </p>

<p>{t + </p>

<p>it-1 </p>

<p>+ fit+i + </p>

<p>-qt </p>

<p>+ f(l </p>

<p>+1 </p>

<p>-ei)} 
(4.28) </p>

<p>kt = (1 -6)kt-1 + ?it 
(4.29) </p>

<p>ut -= rk 
(4.30) </p>

<p>It -wt rtk + ut + kt-1 
(4.31) </p>

<p>yt = cyct + gyeg 
+ Rkyit + Rkkyut 
(4.32) </p>

<p>yt 0-/[e + a(ut + kt-1) + (1 -c)lt] </p>

<p>(4.33) </p>

<p>wt =1 
+-</p>

<p>Et 1wt+1 + wt-1 + rt+ -(1 + flyw)rt + ynrt-</p>

<p>AW (1 -kw) (1 -?W) Lt 8Lb _ 9 b 1w </p>

<p>(1w 
+ (1 + 
2,)X)w 
(wt-</p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>t </p>

<p>t+1)-</p>

<p>t </p>

<p>(1 -)(1 
) </p>

<p>((1 + </p>

<p>f02)ct -</p>

<p>OCt_1 </p>

<p>-lOct+l) </p>

<p>(4.34) </p>

<p>(1 -0) (1 -#0) </p>

<p>1 
(1 -</p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>p)_(1 </p>

<p>-p) 
7t -</p>

<p>+ flypflJEt7Et+1 </p>

<p>+ 
Y7pt-1 +p </p>

<p>1 
+ (1 -Jy-wt 
-E </p>

<p>+ 
?p </p>

<p>As shown in Onatski and N. Williams (2004), equation (4.32) corrects a </p>

<p>slight error in SW due to the capital utilization costs, which enter as the 
final term. 
In addition, there are ten equations for the shock processes, six of </p>

<p>which, {e , </p>

<p>Et El tb, e ) </p>

<p>Et , </p>

<p>}, </p>

<p>follow AR(1) processes of the form: </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>P 
4t-ttV </p>

<p>where vtx is a mean zero innovation with variance a2. The remaining 
four shocks, {,P, qW, i l[ ,}, are assumed to be i.i.d. with mean zero </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>and variance a4. The innovations are assumed to have zero contempo-</p>

<p>raneous correlation. 
The full model also includes counterparts to equations (4.26) through 
(4.33) that describe the log-linearized equations for the flexible-price 
allocation. In these equations, the shocks ilp, lq, and q, are set to 0, 
as is the inflation rate. The nominal interest rate is replaced by the 
flexible-price real interest rate, r*. This yields nine equations and nine 
additional variables, {cl, i , y , w*, I, 
qt*, rt*, rt*, 
kt }, where the asterisk 
superscript denotes the flexible-price value of the variable. 
We close the model by including the linearized counterpart to the 
policy rule: </p>

<p>rt = rirt-1 + (1 -ri)(rt + r,(7rt-1 -7r1_) + ry(yt-1 -
Yt-1)) </p>

<p>+ ran(rt -t-1) + ray(yt -Yt* -(yt-1 -Ye-1)) + r[ </p>

<p>(4.36) </p>

<p>9.2.2 Model with Monetary Frictions Here, we note the modifica-
tions to the expressions above when we consider the model with mon-
etary frictions. Linearizing equation (4.21) gives: </p>

<p>-K mtt </p>

<p>((1 + 
2)Ct --OCt_1 -flEtct+l) </p>

<p>R -1 </p>

<p>(1 -0)(1 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>--o) </p>

<p>fl (eb -Eteb+1) </p>

<p>(4.37) </p>

<p>1 -Ot 
t+ </p>

<p>where mt is the log-deviation of real cash balances. Here R is the </p>

<p>steady-state gross nominal rate that satisfies R = 1 + Rk -6. Lineariz-</p>

<p>ing equation (4.22), we see that we replace equation (4.31) with: </p>

<p>It = -Wt -rt + r + Zt + kt-1 </p>

<p>(4.38) </p>

<p>Linearizing equation (4.23), we see that we replace equation (4.35) with: </p>

<p>1 
(1 -XPp)(1 
-4p) </p>

<p>7rt = </p>

<p>+ flp </p>

<p>Ettt+l + yp7rt-1 + </p>

<p>x (ar + (1 -a)(wt 
+ rt) </p>

<p>--</p>

<p>e' + 
rp) </p>

<p>9.3 Estimation Details and Results </p>

<p>9.3.1 Specification of the Priors Table 4.6 reports the details of 
the specification of the prior for the model.62 For the parameters of </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Table 4.6 
Specification of Priors </p>

<p>Standard 
Parameter 
Distribution 
Mean 
Deviation </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Investment adjustment costs 
Normal 
0.5 
0.2 
a 
Consumption utility 
Normal 
2 
0.5 </p>

<p>0 
Consumption habit 
Beta 
0.7 
0.15 </p>

<p>X 
Labor utility 
Normal 
1.2 
0.5 
-1 Fixed cost-1 
Gamma 
0.075 
0.0125 </p>

<p>0-1 Capital utilization costs 
Log normal 
6.4 
5 </p>

<p>, 
Calvo wages 
Beta 
0.375 
0.1 </p>

<p>?p 
Calvo prices 
Beta 
0.375 
0.1 </p>

<p>Y, 
Wage indexation 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 </p>

<p>Yp 
Price indexation 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 
r, 
Policy, lagged inflation 
Normal 
2 
0.5 </p>

<p>ra7 </p>

<p>Policy, change in rc 
Normal 
0.2 
0.1 </p>

<p>ri 
Policy, lagged interest rate 
Normal 
1 
0.15 </p>

<p>ry Policy, lagged output gap </p>

<p>Gamma 
0.25 
0.25 </p>

<p>ray Policy, change in gap 
Gamma 
0.25 
0.25 </p>

<p>aa </p>

<p>Productivity 
Gamma 
0.6 
0.6 
an 
Inflation objective 
Gamma 
0.1 
0.1 
ab 
Preference 
Gamma 
0.3 
0.3 </p>

<p>ag 
Government spending 
Gamma 
0.3 
0.3 </p>

<p>al 
Labor supply 
Gamma 
3 
3 
ai 
Investment 
Gamma 
0.1 
0.1 
Ur 
Interest rate 
Gamma 
0.1 
0.1 </p>

<p>aq </p>

<p>External finance premium 
Gamma 
5 
5 </p>

<p>ap 
Price markup 
Gamma 
0.2 
0.2 </p>

<p>aw 
Wage markup 
Gamma 
0.2 
0.2 </p>

<p>Pa 
Productivity 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 
p, 
Inflation objective 
Beta 
0.85 
0.1 </p>

<p>Pb </p>

<p>Preference 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 </p>

<p>pg 
Government spending 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 </p>

<p>Pi </p>

<p>Labor supply 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 </p>

<p>Pi 
Investment 
Beta 
0.5 
0.25 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.7 </p>

<p>Estimation Results </p>

<p>90% Probability 
Parameter 
Posterior Mean 
Interval </p>

<p>aa Productivity 
0.5949 
0.5441-0.6490 </p>

<p>au Inflation objective 
0.1153 
0.0916-0.1430 
ab Preference 
0.1346 
0.0739-0.2171 </p>

<p>ag Government spending 
0.2873 
0.2635-0.3134 
a, Labor supply 
2.4625 
1.8121-3.2219 </p>

<p>ai Investment </p>

<p>1.0625 
0.8815-1.2570 </p>

<p>ar Interest rate </p>

<p>0.0001 
0.0000-0.0000 </p>

<p>aq External finance premium 
4.0198 
2.5531-6.4477 </p>

<p>ap Price markup 
0.2072 
0.1812-0.2363 </p>

<p>aw Wage markup 
0.3035 
0.2743-0.3351 </p>

<p>Pa Productivity 
0.9639 
0.9467-0.9794 
p, Inflation objective 
0.9950 
0.9871-0.9995 </p>

<p>Pb Preference 
0.9397 
0.8868-0.9835 </p>

<p>pg Government spending 
0.9443 
0.9147-0.9710 </p>

<p>p, Labor supply 
0.9833 
0.9652-0.9972 
Pi Investment 
0.7170 
0.5755-0.8356 
r, Policy, lagged inflation 
2.6951 
2.1525-3.2813 </p>

<p>ra~ Policy, change in 7 
0.2637 
0.1650-0.3612 </p>

<p>ri Policy, lagged interest rate 
0.8392 
0.7817-0.8921 </p>

<p>ry Policy, lagged output gap 
0.0968 
0.0086-0.2417 </p>

<p>ray Policy, change in gap 
0.5091 
0.4077-0.6386 </p>

<p>the shock processes, where we had little guidance from the literature, 
we set relatively loose priors. For the standard deviations, we used 
gamma distributions with standard deviations equal to the means. We 
gauged the relative magnitudes of the shocks from Onatski and N. 
Williams (2004) and SW. For all but one persistence parameter, we 
used a wide beta distribution. The exception was the inflation objective 
shock. Since it and the interest rate shock enter additively in the policy 
rule of equation (4.37), a tighter prior is necessary to distinguish be-
tween them. For the structural parameters, we chose the parameters of 
the distributions to cover the range of estimates we found in the litera-
ture with reasonably high probability. </p>

<p>9.3.2 Computation of the Posterior As in SW, we first look for a pa-
rameter vector that maximizes the posterior mode, given our prior and 
the likelihood based on the data. We took great efforts to explore the </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>ca </p>

<p>Y 
b 
Yg </p>

<p>10 
20 
20 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10\ 
10 </p>

<p>O 
0 
0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
0 
0.1 0.2 
0 
0.5 
1 
0 
0.5 </p>

<p>10r 
0.4 
500 
S0.5 
5 
0.2 </p>

<p>0 
5 
0 0.5 1 1.5 0 0.1 0.2 0 10 20 </p>

<p>Op 
Ow 
Pa </p>

<p>Pn </p>

<p>.20 
20 
40100 </p>

<p>S10 
10 
20 
50 </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>0.5 00 </p>

<p>0.5 o.5 </p>

<p>1 8.9 0.95 1 </p>

<p>Pb 
Pg 
PI 
Pi </p>

<p>10 
20 
4 </p>

<p>020 
5 
10 
20 
2 </p>

<p>0.5 
1 0.5 
1 0.9 0.95 1 0.5 
1 </p>

<p>Parameter 
Parameter 
Parameter 
Parameter </p>

<p>Figure 4.8 
Estimated Posterior Distributions (Solid Lines) and Prior Distributions (Dashed Lines) for </p>

<p>the Parameters Describing the Shock Processes </p>

<p>parameter space sufficiently to locate a global maximum. In particular, 
we sampled 200 values from the prior distribution and used these as </p>

<p>starting values for Chris Sims's optimization algorithms designed to 
avoid common problems with likelihood functions (these algorithms 
are available on his web page, http://www.princeton.edu/~sims). We 
reran it in combination with a standard hill-climber algorithm until it 
settled on the maximal value. We used the resulting mode as the start-</p>

<p>ing point for our MCMC sampling. 
We then sample from the posterior distribution using a Metropolis-</p>

<p>Hastings Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) algorithm in order 
to make small sample inferences about the parameters. We sampled 
ten separate chains for 45,000 periods each, discarding the first 15,000 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>Table 4.8 
Mode Estimates in the Baseline Specification and Alternative Specification with Monetary 
Frictions </p>

<p>Baseline 
Money 
Parameter 
Specification 
Frictions </p>

<p>C Investment adjustment 
0.5487 
0.6119 
a 
Consumption utility 
2.0445 
2.0433 
0 Consumption habit 
0.2935 
0.3219 </p>

<p>X Labor utility 
1.4051 
1.6037 </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>Money utility 
NA 
11.3822 
Fixed cost 
1.0824 
1.0805 </p>

<p>Capital utilization 
0.1981 
0.1769 </p>

<p>w, </p>

<p>Calvo wages 
0.8074 
0.8123 </p>

<p>cp Calvo prices 
0.8240 
0.8335 </p>

<p>,W Wage indexation 
0.7734 
0.8670 
yp Price indexation 
0.1159 
0.1957 </p>

<p>a, Productivity 
0.5942 
0.5791 </p>

<p>a, Inflation objective 
0.1067 
0.1030 </p>

<p>ab Preference 
0.1205 
0.1256 </p>

<p>ag Government spending </p>

<p>0.2847 
0.2878 
a/ Labor supply 
2.3217 
2.3597 
ai Investment 
1.0349 
1.0770 </p>

<p>ar Interest rate </p>

<p>0.0000 
0.0000 </p>

<p>aq External finance premium 
3.6781 
3.3857 </p>

<p>op Price markup </p>

<p>0.2048 
0.1653 
a, Wage markup 
0.2987 
0.2931 </p>

<p>Um Money demand 
NA 
19.8955 </p>

<p>Pa Productivity 
0.9611 
0.9562 
p, Inflation objective 
0.9944 
0.9993 </p>

<p>Pb Preference 
0.9443 
0.9392 </p>

<p>pg Government spending 
0.9418 
0.9486 
Pi Labor supply 
0.9803 
0.9853 </p>

<p>Pi Investment 
0.7309 
0.7221 
Pm Money demand 
NA 
0.9877 
r, Policy, lagged inflation 
2.7323 
2.7974 </p>

<p>ran Policy, change in r 
0.2847 
0.2586 
ri Policy, lagged interest rate 
0.8318 
0.8412 </p>

<p>ry Policy, lagged output gap 
0.0001 
0.0001 </p>

<p>ray Policy, change in gap 
0.4811 
0.5063 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Preferences 
Government 
Investment 
Labor Supply </p>

<p>( </p>

<p>1 
0.04 
0.5 
0.5 </p>

<p>0. 
0.020 
-0.5 
-0.5 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
x10 </p>

<p>" 
0.05 
5 
0.1 
0.05 </p>

<p>S 
-0.05 
-5 
-0.1 
-0.05 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
c 
0.2 
0.02 
0.2 
0.205 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0 
0 
0 
0 
. 
.---</p>

<p>-0.2 
-0.02 
-0.2 
-0.2 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0 
0.1 </p>

<p>.-0.4. </p>

<p>" -0.5 
0.05 
0.2 
-0. </p>

<p>CO </p>

<p>S-1 00...02. 
-0.2 
-0.2 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>01 
--0.1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-0.3 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.02 
0 </p>

<p>-0.4 
\ </p>

<p>.0 </p>

<p>S 
-1 
-0.03 
-1 
-0.5 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>Quarters 
Quarters 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>Figure 4.9 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Shocks: Optimal Policy (Solid Lines), 
Estimated Policy (Dashed Lines), and Flexible-Wage and Flexible-Price Equilibrium 
(Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>periods. Thus, we were left with 300,000 points from the posterior dis-
tribution. In order to assess convergence of the Markov chains, we use 
the potential scale reduction statistic described by Gelman, Carlin, 
Stem, and Rubin (2004), which gave clear indications of convergence 
for all the parameters. </p>

<p>9.3.3 Estimation Results for the Shocks and the Monetary Model 
The text reports the estimation results for the structural parameters. 
Table 4.7 reports the estimates of the parameters for the shock pro-
cesses. Figure 4.8 plots the prior and posterior distributions for the </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>External Finance Premium 
Price Markup 
Wage Markup 
2 
0.2 
10 </p>

<p>0 0 </p>

<p>-2 
-0.2 
-10 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0.05 
0.2 
0.1 </p>

<p>o 
" </p>

<p>S10 
20 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>. 0.051 
1 0.21 
1 1 </p>

<p>-0.05 
-0.2 
-1 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>i 
0.05 
0.2 
1 </p>

<p>0 
.. 
-
o0-
. 
... </p>

<p>1 
0.2 
5 </p>

<p>0.5 
0 
0 
.--</p>

<p>--------</p>

<p>L-</p>

<p>E 
0 
-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.5 
-0.2 
-5 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0.5 
0 
0uarters 
Qu------rters </p>

<p>E 
0 </p>

<p>................ </p>

<p>-0.05o-"' 
-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
Quarters 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>Figure 4.10 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Shocks: Optimal Policy (Solid Lines), 
Estimated Policy (Dashed Lines), and Flexible-Wage and Flexible-Price Equilibrium 
(Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>Preferences 
Government 
Investment 
Labor Supply </p>

<p>1 
0.05 
0.5 
0.0.5 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0.5 
0.0 .0.0 </p>

<p>0=. 
.. </p>

<p>-...0 
-0.05 
-0.5 
-0.5 </p>

<p>0 
10 20 0 
10 20 0 
10 20 0 
10 20 </p>

<p>x10-3 </p>

<p>S0.05 
0.05 
0.05 
0.05 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>C 
0 
0............. </p>

<p>0. </p>

<p>....... .. ...... </p>

<p>a--0.05 
-0.052 
-0.05 
-0.05 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>c0.051 
1 
00-3 </p>

<p>-
0 
0. 
2 
0.05 
-0.2 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
-0 
20 </p>

<p>E 
0.02-
0 
....1 
10 
0 
-0.43 </p>

<p>S.... 
"......" 
"0 </p>

<p>''. </p>

<p>S-0.05 
0 
-51 
-0.2-</p>

<p>0 
10 20 0 
10 20 0 
10 20 0 
10 20 </p>

<p>Quarters 
Quarters 
0.1 
1 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>S -1 
0-
-1 
-0.8 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>Quarters 
Quarters 
Quarters 
Quarters </p>

<p>Figure 4.11 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Shocks: Optimal Policy (Solid Lines), 
Optimized Wage Inflation Policy Rule (Dashed Lines), and the Optimized Price Inflation 
Rule (Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>parameters describing the shock processes. Our prior insures that ar 
never hits 0, but its modal value is only 4 x 10-6. Except for the invest-
ment shock, the AR(1) shocks are highly persistent, with the inflation 
objective shock in particular being nearly a unit root process. Table 4.8 
reports the estimates for the specification of the model with monetary 
frictions from Section 7.1. </p>

<p>9.4 Optimal Policy </p>

<p>Here, we report the impulse responses to other shocks. In response to 
positive shocks to wages and Tobin's Q, the optimal policy calls for a </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>External Finance Premium 
Price Markup 
Wage Markup 
2 
0.5 
10 </p>

<p>-2 
-0.5 
-10 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0.02 
0.2 
0.05 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>-0.02 
-0.2 
-0.05 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>S0.02 
0.2 
1 </p>

<p>0 0 . . . . 
0 </p>

<p>-----..... </p>

<p>.. . 0. </p>

<p>0 
0 </p>

<p>-0.02 
-0.2 
-1 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>S-1 
-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 </p>

<p>0.5 
.. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>..... </p>

<p>0. 
0. 
"' </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>0 
-0.2 I 
-1 </p>

<p>Quart 
10 
20 
0 
10 
20 
20 
10 
20 </p>

<p>Qlua rte rs </p>

<p>Q~ua rte rs 
Q~ua rte rs </p>

<p>Figure 4.12 
Impulse Responses for One Standard Deviation Shocks: Optimal Policy (Solid Lines), 
Optimized Wage Inflation Policy Rule (Dashed Lines), and the Optimized Price Inflation 
Rule (Dotted Lines) </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>sharp increase in interest rates that causes a large decline in consump-
tion. The contractionary policy response reduces the responses of 
wages. In contrast, the estimated policy rule accommodates the shocks 
to a greater degree and allows larger rises in wage inflation. The opti-
mal policy response to a transitory shock to prices, however, is to do 
almost nothing. The estimated policy rule reacts to the rise in inflation, 
sending real rates higher and reducing consumption and aggregate 
labor. See figures 4.9 through 4.12. </p>

<p>Endnotes </p>

<p>The views expressed herein are solely the responsibility of the authors and should not 
be interpreted as reflecting the views of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve 
System, the management of the Federal Reserve Bank of San Francisco, or anyone else 
associated with the Federal Reserve System. We appreciate comments and suggestions 
from the editors, Mark Gertler and Ken Rogoff, and from our two discussants, Giorgio 
Primiceri and Carl Walsh. This paper has also benefited from conversations with Klaus 
Adam, Michele Cavallo, Steve Cecchetti, Matt Canzoneri, Richard Dennis, Behzad Diba, 
John Fernald, John Leahy, David Lopez-Salido, and Lars Svensson. </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>properties of the model. By using an explicit definition of the adjustment cost function, 
we are able to analyze the second-order approximation of the model economy. </p>

<p>24. As with investment adjustment costs, this explicit specification incorporates the basic 
properties assumed by CEE and SW, while enabling us to analyze the second-order ap-
proximation of the model economy. </p>

<p>25. Taylor (1999b) provides an overview of the evidence on nominal wage inertia. For 
analysis of the elasticity of demand for differentiated labor services, see Griffin (1996a, 
1996b). </p>

<p>26. For analysis of optimal policy in economies with steady-state distortions, see Benigno 
and Woodford (2004) and Schmitt-Groh6 and Uribe (this volume). </p>

<p>27. A detailed description of the log-linearized model is provided in Section 9.2 of the 
appendix. </p>

<p>28. We use the same data set as in Altig, Christiano, Eichenbaum, and Linde (2004), 
obtained from Martin Eichenbaum's web page, http://www.faculty.econ.northwestem 
.edu/faculty/eichenbaum. The real wage is constructed as nonfarm wage rate adjusted 
by the GDP price deflator, while total hours are measured for the nonfarm business sec-
tor. The inflation rate and interest rate are demeaned and converted to quarterly rates; 
the other five variables are measured in logarithmic deviations from linear trends, in per-
centage points. </p>

<p>29. The mean ratio of net exports to GDP was zero to two decimal points over our 
sample. </p>

<p>30. In specifying these priors, we have drawn heavily on Smets and Wouters (2003a, 
2003b); Christiano, Eichenbaum, and Evans (2005); Altig, Christiano, Eichenbaum, and 
Linde (2004); and Onatski and N. Williams (2004). </p>

<p>31. Since the work of Schorfheide (2000) and especially after the original Smets and 
Wouters (2003a) paper, there have been a number of papers using Bayesian methods for 
models similar to ours; examples include Del Negro and Schorfheide (2004); Rabanal and 
Rubio-Ramirez (2003); Laforte (2003); Onatski and N. Williams (2004); and Del Negro, 
Schorfheide, Smets, and Wouters (2004). </p>

<p>32. For comparison, Taylor (1993b), using a staggered wage model, estimates an average 
wage contract duration of about 31 quarters. </p>

<p>33. See Kydland and Prescott (1980); King and Wolman (1999); and Khan, King, and 
Wolman (2003). </p>

<p>34. These procedures are available on the Dynare web site or on request from the 
authors. </p>

<p>35. Judd (1998) provides a general introduction and comparison of methods for solving 
nonlinear rational expectations models. </p>

<p>36. See Kim and Kim (2003); Kim, Kim, Schaumburg, and Sims (2003); and Woodford 
(2003). </p>

<p>37. Because perturbation methods provide a local approximation around the steady 
state, our analysis does not consider the implications of the zero lower bound on nominal 
interest rates. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>

<p>38. For this purpose, it is essential to utilize conditional mean-preserving spreads for the 
exogenous disturbances; see Levin and Lopez-Salido (2004) for further discussion. </p>

<p>39. Impulse responses for other structural shocks are reported in the appendix. </p>

<p>40. For related analysis and results, see Cho, Cooley, and Phaneuf (1997); Canzoneri, 
Cumby, and Diba (2004); and Paustian (2004). </p>

<p>41. For analysis and discussion of the rationale for simple rules, see Taylor (1993a) and 
Williams (2003). </p>

<p>42. McCallum (1999) also highlights the role of information lags; thus, while our specifi-
cation utilizes contemporaneous data, it will be useful to consider this issue further in 
subsequent research. </p>

<p>43. See Reifschneider and Williams (2000), Eggertsson and Woodford (2003), and others. </p>

<p>44. See also Erceg and Levin (2005) and Mankiw and Reis (2002). </p>

<p>45. We do not, however, vary the parameters associated with the shock processes or the 
calibrated parameters. </p>

<p>46. In addition, the welfare costs of fluctuations are very sensitive to the assumed degree 
of substitutability across types of labor and of goods, parameters that we take as fixed in 
this analysis. </p>

<p>47. Note that we do not impose a relationship between the fixed cost parameter and the 
markup implied by a zero-profit condition. </p>

<p>48. Thus, we isolate the effects of changing the substitutability of different types of labor 
on welfare from those on the sensitivity of wages to movements in the marginal rate of 
substitution. </p>

<p>49. In a previous version of this paper, we estimated an alternative model that included 
no external finance premium shocks. Estimates of most model parameters were nearly </p>

<p>identical to the baseline estimates. Exceptions included the estimate of C, which fell, </p>

<p>implying significantly higher costs of adjusting investment, and the investment adjust-
ment cost shock became more variable and less persistent. The effects on welfare of this 
specification were modest. </p>

<p>50. Because a shock to preferences affects only welfare and not the production possibil-
ities of the economy, with flexible wages and prices, welfare is nondecreasing to a mean-
preserving spread to preferences. </p>

<p>51. For some early analysis of specification uncertainty in structural models, see Becker, 
Dwolatsky, Karakitsos, and Rustem (1986) and Frankel and Rockett (1988). </p>

<p>52. The money data are available only from 1959 onward, so we shorten the sample by 
four years. Linearized expressions are given in the appendix. </p>

<p>53. Complete estimation results are reported in Section 9.3 of the appendix. </p>

<p>54. It is still the case that the optimal coefficient on price inflation is 0. </p>

<p>55. Although not considered here, another model of wage and price setting that does not 
yield dispersion effects on aggregate welfare is the quadratic adjustment costs model of 
Rotemberg (1982). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>



<p>56. We estimated a version of the baseline model where wage indexation depends on a 
combination of past price and wage inflation. We found that the weight is primarily on 
past price inflation, providing support for the baseline model specification. Nonetheless, 
one may not be convinced by this finding and remain concerned about uncertainty re-
garding the form of wage indexation. </p>

<p>57. As explained below, we have not formally estimated this alternative specification. 
The empirical performance of the model may be sensitive to which type of nominal rigid-
ity is assumed; see Chari, Kehoe, and McGrattan (2000); Kiley (2002); and Guerrieri 
(2001). </p>

<p>58. We also examined a version of the model with Taylor wage contracts and Calvo 
prices. The results were very similar to those found when both wages and prices are set 
by Taylor contracts. </p>

<p>59. The specification of Erceg, Henderson, and Levin (2000) implies a much flatter nomi-
nal wage Phillips curve; that is, nominal wage inflation is much less sensitive to the mar-
ginal rate of substitution between consumption and leisure. Furthermore, cross-sectional 
wage dispersion induces differences in labor across households that have substantial 
effects on social welfare. </p>

<p>60. Erceg and Levin (2003) analyze a DGE model roughly similar to the one in this paper 
and show that private agents' gradual learning about the Fed's inflation objective is cru-
cial for interpreting the effects of the Volcker disinflation, while Edge, Laubach, and J. 
Williams (2003) and Erceg, Guerrieri, and Gust (2005) highlight the role of learning in fit-
ting the stylized facts of the U.S. productivity growth boom of the late 1990s. </p>

<p>61. See Beck and Wieland (2002) for analysis of optimal learning and control in a small 
stylized economy with ongoing structural change. </p>

<p>62. For a brief survey of the literature on specification of priors, see Onatski and N. Wil-
liams (2004). This survey includes studies focusing on real models, such as King and 
Rebelo (1999) and Boldrin, Christiano, and Fisher (2001), as well as papers focusing on 
monetary policy in smaller models, such as Rotemberg and Woodford (1997), Judd and 
Rudebusch (1998), and Sack (1998). </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>





<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>





<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>



<p>Levin, Onatski, Williams, and Williams </p>



<p>Kim, J., and S. Kim (2003). "Spurious Welfare Reversals in International Business Cycle 
Models," Journal of International Economics, 60:471-500. </p>

<p>Kim, J., S. Kim, E. Schaumburg, and C. Sims (2003). "Calculating and Using Second 
Order Accurate Solutions of Discrete Time Dynamic Equilibrium Models," Princeton 
University, mimeo. </p>

<p>Kimball, M. S. (1995). "The Quantitative Analytics of the Basic Neomonetarist Model," 
Journal of Money, Credit and Banking, 27:1241-1277. </p>

<p>Kimura, T., and T. Kurozumi (2003). "Optimal Monetary Policy in a Microfounded 
Model with Parameter Uncertainty," Bank of Japan, manuscript. </p>

<p>King, R., and S. Rebelo (1999). "Resuscitating Real Business Cycles," in J. B. Taylor and 
M. Woodford (eds.), Handbook of Macroeconomics. Amsterdam: North-Holland, 927-1007. </p>

<p>King, R., and A. Wolman (1999). "What Should the Monetary Authority Do When Prices 
Are Sticky?" in J. B. Taylor (ed.), Monetary Policy Rules, University of Chicago Press, 
349-398. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>





<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>





<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

<p>Monetary Policy Under Uncertainty </p>





<p>Yun, T. (1996). "Nominal Price Ridigity, Money Supply Endogeneity, and Business 
Cycles," Journal of Monetary Economics, 37:345-370. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on May 18, 2018 15:06:12 PM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c) </p>

</text></tei>