<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Froie.12300" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>This paper shows that a strong comparative advantage is 
necessary for free trade and specialization in a 2 3 2 
symmetric Ricardian model to be achieved in a Nash equi-
librium. Governments strategically control labor distribution 
across industries, and representative agents maximize Cobb-
Douglas utilities. A Nash equilibrium with complete special-
ization is achieved if and only if relative productivity 
exceeds a key value of 3, which is considered a very large 
number based on previous empirical studies. This paper also 
introduces a two-stage game where each government choo-
ses labor distribution first and then tariffs. In this two-stage 
game, complete specialization is never achieved for any 
relative productivity level. Finally, by generalizing the 
Cobb-Douglas model into constant elasticity of substitution 
(CES) preferences, I show that if immiserizing growth 
effects exist, complete specialization could not be achieved 
for any level of relative productivity. </p>

<p>1 | IN TRO DUCT IO N </p>

<p>The two most important questions in international trade are the normative question of "why should 
nations pursue free trade?" and the positive question of "do nations have incentives to pursue free 
trade?" The former question is well explained by David Ricardo, in that comparative advantage is the 
source of mutual benefits from world trade. This paper indicates that the answer to the second question 
also relies on comparative advantage; a strong comparative advantage is necessary for nations to strate-
gically pursue free trade in a Ricardian model. Defining the degree of comparative advantage as the 
relative productivity between more and less competitive industries in a symmetric Ricardian model 
with Cobb-Douglas preferences, this paper shows that a Nash equilibrium with complete specialization 
is achieved if and only if the measure exceeds a key value of 3, a very large number based on previous 
empirical studies. This paper also shows that complete specialization cannot be achieved if the govern-
ment implements import tariffs in addition to labor distribution policies, or if there exist immiserizing 
growth effects. 
A rational government wants to manipulate the terms of trade by protecting the less competitive 
sector and controlling the more competitive one. However, protectionism under strong comparative </p>

<p>advantage results in a decrease in the domestic production size and consequently a decrease in its wel-
fare. Therefore, a strong mutual comparative advantage should be present in order to achieve free trade. 
Otherwise, the government would use trade policies such as export subsidies or import tariffs. Costinot, 
Donaldson, Vogel, and Werning (2015) explored the relationship between comparative advantage and 
optimal trade taxes. Their optimal trade taxes aim to control the production size of more competitive 
sectors with comparative advantage to manipulate the terms of trade. 
1 The difference between Costinot </p>

<p>et al. (2015) and this paper is that the former considered import tariff and export subsidy as their strat-
egies with a passive foreign government whereas the latter considers governments' intervention in 
labor distribution in a Nash equilibrium. 
Even though this paper assumes that governments directly control the labor distribution across 
industries rather than using indirect tools such as trade taxes, both Costinot et al. (2015) and this paper 
are based on the same main logic that welfare can be improved by manipulating the terms of trade. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>There are many examples of policies that effectively reallocate labor towards low productivity section. 
Governments use various types of assistance policies such as domestic subsidies, antidumping laws, 
and industry bailouts to help less competitive domestic industries. These polices potentially reallocate 
the labor distribution from high to low productive sectors. 
The main model of this paper uses a simplified framework of Ricardian models described in Dorn-
busch, Fischer, and Samuelson (1977) where Cobb-Douglas utility functions are used and the number 
of goods is two. In this paper, a representative agent in each country has a Cobb-Douglas utility func-
tion, which is considered to have a "medium" value of elasticity of substitution. 
3 The elasticity of sub-</p>

<p>stitution derived from the utility function is the main factor in determining the equilibrium prices, or 
equivalently, the terms of trade. To maximize the utility of the representative agent, each government 
strategically determines the quantities of labor in the two industries. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>A government's incentive for specialization primarily depends on how much the two countries 
have a mutual comparative advantage. To define a measure of comparative advantage, this paper intro-
duces a symmetric model in which one country's labor productivity of its more (less) competitive 
industry is equal to the other country's labor productivity in the more (less) competitive industry. With 
the help of the symmetric structure, the measure of comparative advantage is defined as the ratio of 
higher labor productivity to lower labor productivity, which is equal to the relative autarky price. The 
main results are that (1) the degree of specialization strictly increases in comparative advantage, and 
(2) only if comparative advantage exceeds or equals to the number 3 would a complete specialization 
be achieved in a Nash equilibrium. 
The value of relative productivity 3 is a very large number based on previous empirical evidence. 
Costinot, Donaldson, and Komunjer (2012) measured relative productivities across 21 countries and 13 
industries based on the year 1997. 
5 Normalizing all industries to the United States and in all countries </p>

<p>for the food industry, there is no single value of relative productivity among 260 values (20 countries 
3 13 industries) that is greater than 3 or less than 1/3. Among the 260 values, 253 of them are in the 
range of [0.5,2]. The maximum is 2.74, which is the relative productivity of the Korean chemicals 
industry relative to that of the United States. The minimum value is 0.49, which is the relative produc-
tivity of the Hungarian transport industry relative to that of the United States. Considering that 3 is an 
unrealistically large value of relative productivity, the main result in this paper may imply that it would 
be hard for countries to agree on free trade and complete specialization without any international 
organizations. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>The model in this paper is closely related to the theory of immiserizing growth developed by Bhag-
wati (1958), which indicates that export-biased growth might deteriorate the terms of trade sufficiently 
such as to decrease the welfare of the economy. 
7 In the context of the Ricardian model, export-biased </p>

<p>growth can be interpreted as the expansion of the more competitive industry without contraction of the </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>less competitive industry. However, the government's action on labor distribution not only has the 
expansion effect (i.e., immiserizing growth effect) but also the contraction effect. Therefore, this paper 
investigates how each effect, separately, affects the government's incentive to avoid complete 
specialization. 
It is well known that a lower elasticity of substitution increases the possibility of having immiseriz-
ing growth effects (see Bhagwati, Brecher, &amp; Hatta, 1983, 1984). Therefore, I extend the baseline 
model by including a constant elasticity of substitution (CES) utility function with a general elasticity-
of-substitution parameter. With the extended model, I show that if the elasticity of substitution is lower 
than 0.5, which is the condition for the existence of immiserizing growth effect, complete specializa-
tion could never be achieved for any value of relative productivity. Although this paper shows that 
there is no immiserizing growth effect with Cobb-Douglas utility functions, the other effects (including 
the direct effect and terms-of-trade effects from the contraction) prevents complete specialization if the 
relative productivity is smaller than 3. 
This paper also investigates how Nash equilibrium specialization is determined when governments 
are allowed to implement import tariffs. Specifically, I introduce a two-stage game where each govern-
ment first strategically chooses labor distribution and then optimal import tariffs. This paper shows that 
complete specialization can never be achieved in such a two-stage game. This result of missing com-
plete specialization is closely related to Kennan and Riezman (1988, 1990), where agents are endowed 
with goods. The two-stage game in this paper reproduces the results of Kennan and Riezman (1990), 
where the optimal tariffs are a function of the endowments. Kennan and Riezman (1990) show that a 
more equal (asymmetrical) distribution of endowments between the two sectors results in lower 
(higher) tariffs and thus higher (lower) utility in a Nash tariff war. In the two-stage game, "endow-
ments" are endogenously chosen by the government's strategic action on labor distribution. Govern-
ments know that if they choose more specialized labor distribution, which implies a more 
asymmetrical endowment distribution in Kennan and Riezman's (1990) model, it will end up with the 
Nash equilibrium with higher tariffs and thus lower utilities. To avoid this destructive tariff war under 
asymmetrical endowment distribution, governments would have incentives to avoid specialization of 
labor distribution in the two-stage game. The main results of this paper support this logic, as it shows 
that the degree of specialization under the two-stage game is strictly lower than that under the one-
stage game. 
The rest of the paper proceeds as follows. Section 2 introduces the Ricardian model with Cobb-
Douglas utility. Section 3 derives the best response functions of the labor inputs. Section 4 discusses 
how the degree of comparative advantage affects the Nash equilibrium trade specialization. Section 5 
introduces a two-stage game where each government strategically chooses labor distribution first and 
then tariffs. Section 6 investigates how the theory of immiserizing growth is related to the main model 
of this paper. Section 7 concludes the paper. </p>

<p>There are two terms in country A's utility function in Equation (13). The first term EX(a,a 
0 ) is the </p>

<p>utility contribution of the exporting sector, while the second term IM(a,a 
0 ) is that of the importing </p>

<p>FIGU RE 3 Comparative advantage and specialization in the two-stage game [Colour figure can be viewed at </p>

<p>wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>sector. The exporting-sector contribution EX(a,a 
0 ) is affected by both a and a 
0 . By the definition of the </p>

<p>immiserizing growth model, country A experiences the immiserizing growth effect if oEX(a,a 
0 )/oa &lt; 0, </p>

<p>which means that expansion of the exporting sector decreases welfare. With Cobb-Douglas utility 
function, we have oEX(a,a 
0 )/oa &gt; 0 (see Equation (14)), which implies that there is no immiserizing </p>

<p>growth effect. EX(a,a 
0 ) is also affected by a 
0 because the contraction of the import sector affects the rel-</p>

<p>ative price of the exporting good. As a 
0 increases, the relative price p/q decreases and thus, EX(a,a 
0 ) </p>

<p>decreases, i.e., oEX(a,a 
0 )/oa 
0 &lt; 0. oIM(a,a 
0 )/oa is equal to zero, where (a,a 
0 ) 5 (1,1), because of the </p>

<p>domestic production of the imported good where a 
0 5 1 is zero. Lastly, we have oIM(a,a 
0 )/oa 
0 &lt; 0, </p>

<p>because the lower production of imported goods negatively affects utility. 
Where (a,a 
0 ) 5 (1,1), we derive the following four effects from Equation (13): </p>

<p>oEXða; a 
0 Þ=oa5 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
=2; 
(14) 
oEXða; a 
0 Þ=oa 
0 521= 2 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p </p>

<p>
; 
(15) 
oIMða; a 
0 Þ=oa50; 
(16) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>oIMða; a 
0 Þ=oa 
0 521= 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
: 
(17) </p>

<p>If the sum of the four effects from Equations (14) to (17) (i.e., 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
=221= 2 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
À 
Á 
21= 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
is nega-
tive), country A would have an incentive to deviate from complete specialization. Similar to the result 
in Proposition 1, if k is smaller than 3, the sum is negative; the sum is zero if k 5 3; and the sum is pos-
itive if k &lt; 3. 
While there is no immiserizing growth effect with Cobb-Douglas utility functions, it would be inter-
esting to investigate the relationship between the immiserizing growth effect and strategic specialization 
under more general utility functions. As indicated in Bhagwati, Brecher, and Hatta (1983, 1984), the 
immiserizing growth effect can exist for low values of elasticity of substitution between export and 
import goods. Therefore, in this section, we generalize the utility function with CES parameters: </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>IMða;a 0 Þ </p>

<p>: </p>

<p>Under the same logic as the Cobb-Douglas utility case, we can investigate country A's incentive 
to deviate from complete specialization (i.e., (a,a 
0 ) 5 (1,1)) when country B is in the state of com-</p>

<p>plete specialization, i.e., b 5 1. The four different effects when (a,a 
0 ) 5 (1,1) and b 5 1 are as </p>

<p>follows: </p>

<p>oEXða; a 
0 Þ=oa5 
ð2112EÞ 
2E </p>

<p>ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
; 
(21) </p>

<p>oEXða; a 
0 Þ=oa 
0 52 
1 
2E 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p &lt;0; 
(22) </p>

<p>oIMða; a 
0 Þ=oa50; 
(23) 
and </p>

<p>oIMða; a 
0 Þ=oa 
0 52 
1 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p &lt;0: 
(24) </p>

<p>Equation (21) indicates that there exists an immiserizing growth effect if the elasticity of substitu-
tion (E) is smaller than or equal to 0.5. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Because the other effects in Equations (22) to (24) are smaller than or equal to zero, hav-
ing immiserizing growth effects is the sufficient condition for missing complete specialization 
in a Nash equilibrium for any level of DCA (k). This is summarized in the following 
proposition. </p>

<p>Proposition 3 If the immiserizing growth effect exists (i.e., the elasticity of substitution is lower than 
0.5), complete specialization is not achieved for any level of comparative advantage. (See the proof in 
Appendix (A8).) 
Letting the sum of the four effects from Equations (22) to (24) be zero, we have a simple 
relationship between E and k, E5 k11 
ð 
Þ= 2k22 
ð 
Þ, which is plotted in Figure 4. The area below 
the curve indicates nonspecialization parameter combinations of ðE; kÞ. For E&lt;0:5 a country 
will not fully specialize for any value of k. For the Cobb-Douglas case explored in this paper, 
where E51, k needs to be more than 3 for complete specialization. For E to 1 (perfect substi-
tutes), countries fully specialize for any k &gt; 1. Moreover, the graph shows that a country will 
not fully specialize if the immiserizing growth effect exists (i.e., the elasticity of substitution is 
lower than 0.5). </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>7 | CONC LUD IN G REM ARK S </p>

<p>The main finding of this paper is that when the government can control labor distribution, strong com-
parative advantage is necessary for complete specialization to be achieved in a Nash equilibrium. This 
paper also investigates how immiserizing growth effects are related to incomplete specialization in a 
CES framework. From the stylized model, this paper shows that the existence of immiserizing growth 
effects is the sufficient condition for missing complete specialization. Finally, this paper introduces a 
two-stage game where governments choose labor distribution and then optimal tariffs. In this two-stage 
game, complete specialization is never achieved for any degree of comparative advantage. All of these 
results imply that it would be difficult for countries to agree on free trade without any help from inter-
national organizations. 
The alternative explanation for incomplete specialization might be a commodity-aggregation prob-
lem. While 1-or 2-digit Standard International Trade Classification (SITC) results in a smaller degree 
of complete specialization across countries, finer digit levels (such as 3 or 4 digits) show different pat-
terns. For example, both the United States and China have strong manufacturing export industries but 
the United States is more specialized in transportation equipment while China is more specialized in 
electronic equipment. Another explanation for the missing complete specialization could be from the 
Ricardo-Viner model, in which there are immobile factor endowments such as land and capital. In 
contrast to the classical Ricardian model where labor productivity is constant, the marginal return of 
labor decreases as the quantity of labor input increases in the Ricardo-Viner model. This diminishing 
marginal-return effect prevents countries from completely giving up their less competitive industries. 
Another remaining question is how the elasticity of substitution between export and import goods 
affects the Nash equilibrium of specialization. The main reason why countries avoid specialization is 
that they want to improve the terms of trade through strategic labor distribution policy. Therefore, it is 
expected that for lower elasticity of substitution values, complete specialization is difficult to achieve, 
as shown in Section 6. However, under perfect substitutes utility, i.e., Uðx; yÞ5x1y, it is apparent that 
the Nash equilibrium with complete specialization would be achieved for any degree of comparative 
advantage, because the prices are not affected by labor distribution in this case. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENT </p>

<p>The author appreciates helpful comments from the two anonymous referees, Xiaoping Chen, 
Wilfred Ethier, Pinelopi Koujianou Goldberg, Karl Shell, and Lei Sandy Ye, and, in addition, </p>

<p>FIGU RE 4 The elasticity of substitution and complete specialization [Colour figure can be viewed at </p>

<p>wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>| </p>



<p>wishes to thank Linh My Ton for research assistance. The author gratefully acknowledges research 
support from Nanyang Technological University AcRF Tier-1 Grant (RG171/14). </p>

<p>NOTE S </p>

<p>1 Brunnermeier and Sannikov (2015) also indicated that government's capital control in undercapitalized countries can </p>

<p>recover the optimal terms of trade and, therefore, improve welfare because firms in those countries do not internalize 
the negative effects of too high investment on the terms of trade. 
2 Bagwell and Staiger (2011) and Broda, Limao, and Weinstein (2008) suggested empirical evidence that countries use </p>

<p>optimal tariffs in order to manipulate the terms of trade. 
3 Dornbusch, Fischer, and Samuelson (1977) and Eaton and Kortum (2002) used an identical Cobb-Douglas preference </p>

<p>in a Ricardian model with a continuum of goods. 
4 Many research papers have shown that the existence of protectionism such as tariffs, quota, and environmental regula-</p>

<p>tions is the state of Nash equilibrium because countries try to improve the terms of trade through protectionism. For 
Nash tariff wars, see Johnson (1950), Gorman (1958), Kennan and Riezman (1988), Gros (1987), Syropoulos (2002), 
Zissimos (2009), and Ogawa (2012). For Nash quota wars, see Rodriguez (1974) and Tower (1975). For strategic envi-
ronmental regulations, see Barrett (1994), Kennedy (1994), Burguet and Sempere (2003), and Bhattacharya and Pal 
(2010). 
5 The list of 13 industries is food, textiles, wood, paper, fuel, chemicals, plastic, minerals, metals, machinery, electrical </p>

<p>transport and manufacturing not elsewhere classified. The list of 21 countries is Australia, Belgium-Luxembourg, 
Czech Republic, Denmark, Spain, Finland, France, Germany, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Korea, the Nether-
lands, Poland, Portugal, Slovakia, Sweden, United Kingdom, and United States. The measures of relative productivity 
are computed using relative producer prices from the Groningen Growth and Development Centre (GGDC) Productiv-
ity Level Database. See Inklaar and Timmer (2008) for details. 
6 Depending on the choice of a country for normalization rather than the United States, some relative productivities might </p>

<p>exceed 3. However, considering U.S. markets share the largest portion in the world economy, using the United States 
as the standard country would be most appropriate. 
7 Also see Bhagwati and Johnson (1960), Bhagwati (1968, 1969), and Bhagwati et al. (1984). </p>

<p>8 Once the representative agent's smooth preferences are revealed, comparative advantage can be interpreted as differen-</p>

<p>ces in relative autarky prices between the two countries. Because of Cobb-Douglas utility functions, the measure of 
comparative advantage based on relative autkary prices is identical to that based on relative productivity. 
9 See the proof in Appendix (A5). </p>

<p>10 The Metzler paradox can also explain why the two countries have a mutual destructive tariff war under complete </p>

<p>specialization. The relative domestic price of the foreign good under complete specialization is </p>

<p>q 11t A 
ð 
Þ 
p 
5 
ð11t A Þð21t B Þ 
21t A 
: 
(10) </p>

<p>10 (It can be derived from Equation (B3) in Appendix B.) From Equation (10), we know that an increase in t A increases </p>

<p>the relative domestic price of the imported good. This is the Metzler paradox, in which the imposition of a tariff on 
imports decreases the relative internal price of that good. Under the paradoxical price changes, an increase in tariff will 
necessarily increase real purchasing power for domestic consumers. 
11 The <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> code is downloadable in mwkang.site11.com/code/rie2016. </p>

<p>12 The Ricardian model introduced in this paper has a combination of effects that include expansion and contraction, so it </p>

<p>is not obvious whether the condition oEX(a,a 
0 )/oa &lt; 0 clearly represents the immiserizing growth effect. To clarify this </p>

<p>issue, it is worth presenting a simple model of endowment economy. With the same CES utility functions as in Equa-
tion 18, country A's endowment for good (x, y) is 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
a; 0 
À 
Á 
and country B's endowment is 0; 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
. In this endow-
ment economy, there exists closed form solutions for the equilibrium allocations, and the condition for country A's 
welfare to decrease as a increases is that E &lt; 0.5 for any value of a 
0 &gt; 0, a ! a 
0 , and k &gt; 0, which is the same as the </p>

<p>condition in Equation (21). </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>



<p>Gros, D. (1987). A note on the optimal tariff, retaliation and the welfare loss from tariff wars in a framework with 
intra-industry trade. Journal of International Economics, 23(3), 357-367. </p>

<p>Inklaar, R., &amp; Timmer, M. P. (2008). GGDC productivity level database: International comparisons of output, 
inputs and productivity at the industry level (Technical Report). Groningen Growth and Development Centre, 
University of Groningen. </p>

<p>Johnson, H. G. (1950). Optimum welfare and maximum revenue tariffs. Review of Economic Studies, 19(1), 28-35. </p>

<p>Kennan, J., &amp; Riezman, R. (1988). Do big countries win tariff wars? International Economic Review, 29(1), 81-85. </p>

<p>Kennan, J., &amp; Riezman, R. (1990). Optimal tariff equilibria with customs unions. Canadian Journal of Economics, 
23(1), 70-83. </p>

<p>Kennedy, P. W. (1994). Equilibrium pollution taxes in open economies with imperfect competition. Journal of 
Environmental Economics and Management, 27(1), 49-63. </p>

<p>Ogawa, Y. (2012). The structure of Nash equilibrium tariffs. Economic Theory, 51(1), 139-161. </p>

<p>Rodriguez, C. A. (1974). The non-equivalence of tariffs and quotas under retaliation. Journal of International 
Economics, 4(3), 295-298. </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>| </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Syropoulos, C. (2002). Optimum tariffs and retaliation revisited: How country size matters. Review of Economic 
Studies, 69(3), 707-727. </p>

<p>Tower, E. (1975). The optimum quota and retaliation. Review of Economic Studies, 42(4), 623-630. </p>

<p>Zissimos, B. (2009). Optimum tariffs and retaliation: How country numbers matter. Journal of International 
Economics, 78(2), 276-286. </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Kang M. Comparative advantage and strategic specialization. Rev Int 
Econ. 2018;26:1-19. https://doi.org/10.1111/roie.12300 </p>

<p>APPENDIX A: PROOFS </p>

<p>A1 | Proof of property (i) </p>

<p>I A ðajbÞ is given by </p>

<p>I A ðajbÞ5 
1 
ffiffi ffi 
2 
p 
a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
12a ffiffi </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>p 1b 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p </p>

<p>a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
1 
12b ffiffi </p>

<p>k 
p </p>

<p>v 
u 
u 
t </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>Part A </p>

<p>1 
12a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
1 
12b ffiffi </p>

<p>k 
p </p>

<p>12a ffiffi </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>p 1b 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p </p>

<p>v 
u 
u 
t </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>Part B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B 
B 
B 
B 
B 
B 
@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
C 
A </p>

<p>: 
(A1) </p>

<p>The function (A1) is composed of two parts: A and B. I will show that each part is strictly concave 
in a where 0 &lt; a &lt; 1. Part A in (A1) can be expressed as </p>

<p>A5 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
a 2 11bk2a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>a1 </p>

<p>12b 
k </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>: 
(A2) </p>

<p>Replacing 11bk and </p>

<p>12b </p>

<p>k with t 1 (where 1&lt;t 1 &lt;11kÞ and t 2 (where 0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=kÞ, respectively, the 
second derivative of (A2) with respect to a is </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>a 2 t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ 
a1t 2 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>oa 2 
52 
ðt 1 1t 2 Þa 
3 t 2 4t 1 23a 
ð 
Þ 1at 1 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ 
2 a 2 
t 2 1a </p>

<p>
3=2 
t 2 1a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>: 
(A3) </p>

<p>Because the ranges for t 1 and t 2 are </p>

<p>1&lt;t 1 &lt;11k </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=k; </p>

<p>Equation (A3) is strictly negative. 
Part B in (A1) can be expressed as </p>

<p>B5 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi ffi 
12a 
ð 
Þ 
2 a1 </p>

<p>12b 
k </p>

<p>À 
Á </p>

<p>11bk2a </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>: 
(A4) </p>

<p>Replacing 11bk and </p>

<p>12b </p>

<p>k with t 1 and t 2 , respectively, the second derivative of (A4) with respect to 
a is </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>12a 
ð 
Þ 
2 a1t 2 
ð 
Þ 
t 1 2a </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>oa 2 
52 
ðt 1 1t 2 Þf3 t 2 1a 
ð 
Þðt 1 21Þ1 t 2 11 
ð 
Þðt 1 2aÞg </p>

<p>4 t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>4 t 2 1a 
t 1 2a </p>

<p>3=2 
: 
(A5) </p>

<p>Because 1&lt;t 1 &lt;11k and 0&lt;t 2 &lt;1=k, (A5) is strictly negative. Therefore, we have I </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>A ðajbÞ&lt;0. </p>

<p>A2 | Proof of property (ii) </p>

<p>From Appendix (A1), we know that I A ðajbÞ can be expressed in terms of t 1 and t 2 : </p>

<p>I A ðajbÞ5 
1 
ffiffi ffi 
2 
p </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
a 2 t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ 
a1t 2 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
12a 
ð 
Þ 
2 a1t 2 
ð 
Þ 
t 1 2a </p>

<p>s 
0 </p>

<p>@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>A ; 
(A6) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>t 1 511bk and t 2 5 
12b 
k 
: </p>

<p>Taking the derivative of (A6) with respect to a, we have </p>

<p>2 
ffiffi ffi 
2 
p 
I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ðajbÞ5 </p>

<p>2t 1 t 2 1t 1 a23t 2 a22a </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ð 
Þ </p>

<p>t 2 1a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>t 1 2a 
t 2 1a </p>

<p>q 
1 
t 1 1t 2 22t 1 t 2 23t 1 a1t 2 a12a </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ð 
Þ </p>

<p>t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>t 2 1a 
t 1 2a </p>

<p>q 
: 
(A7) </p>

<p>Where a 5 0, the first order condition of I A ðajbÞ with respect to a is </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ð0; bÞ5 </p>

<p>2t 1 ð12t 2 Þ1t 1 1t 2 </p>

<p>2t 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ffiffi ffi </p>

<p>t 2 
t 1 </p>

<p>q 
&gt;0; </p>

<p>which is strictly positive because t 2 &lt;1. </p>

<p>A3 | Proof of property (iii) </p>

<p>From Equation (A7), we can derive I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ð1; bÞ as </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ð1; bÞ5 </p>

<p>22ð11t 2 Þ 
2 221t 1 23t 2 12t 1 t 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
t 1 21 
t 2 11 </p>

<p>r 
ð11t 2 Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>5 
t 1 27t 2 12t 1 t 2 22t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 24 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
t 1 21 
t 2 11 </p>

<p>r 
ð11t 2 Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>(A8) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>t 1 511bk and t 2 5 
12b 
k 
: </p>

<p>The denominator in (A8) is strictly positive. Therefore, we need to show that the numerator in 
(A8) is strictly negative for all b 2 ½0; 1 and k 2 ½1; 3Þ. The numerator in (A8) can be expressed in 
terms of b and k as </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>| </p>



<p>hðb; kÞ5t 1 27t 2 12t 1 t 2 22t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 24 </p>

<p>5 11bk 
ð 
Þ 27 
12b 
k 
12 11bk 
ð 
Þ 
12b 
k 
22 
12b 
k </p>

<p>
2 
24 </p>

<p>5 bk23 
ð 
Þ1 
ðb21Þ 
k 
51 
2ð12bÞ 
k 
22bk </p>



<p>: </p>

<p>(A9) </p>

<p>h(b,k) is strictly increasing in k because we have </p>

<p>ohðb; kÞ 
ok 
5b1 
5 
k 2 1 </p>

<p> 
k 3 25 </p>

<p>b 
k 2 28 </p>

<p>b 
k 3 14 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>k 3 </p>

<p>5b1 
5 
k 2 ð12bÞ1 </p>

<p>4 
k 3 ð12bÞ 
2 &gt;0: </p>

<p>Therefore, the supreme of h(b,k) is achieved at k 5 3, where k 2 ½1; 3Þ. Where k 5 3, h(b,k) is </p>

<p>hðb; 3Þ5 
64 
9 
b2 
20 
9 
b 
2 2 
44 
9 
5 
4 
9 
16b25b 
2 211 
À 
Á 
: 
(A10) </p>

<p>From Equation (A10), we know that hðb; 3Þ is strictly increasing in b 2 ½0; 1. Where b 5 1, we 
have h(1,3) 5 0. Therefore, h(b,k) is strictly negative for all b 2 ½0; 1 and k 2 ½1; 3Þ. </p>

<p>A4 | Proof of properties (iv) and (v) </p>

<p>Referring to Equation (A8), we have </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ð1; bÞ5 </p>

<p>t 1 27t 2 12t 1 t 2 22t </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 24 
2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>t 1 21 
t 2 11 </p>

<p>q 
ð11t 2 Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>; 
(A11) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>t 1 511bk and t 2 5 
12b 
k 
: </p>

<p>Where ða; bÞ5ð1; 1Þ, we have t 1 5 1 1 k and t 2 5 0. Thus, from Equation (A11), we obtain </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ð1; 1Þ5 </p>

<p>k23 
2 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p ; 
(A12) </p>

<p>which is strictly positive if k &lt; 3 and strictly negative if k &gt; 3. </p>

<p>A5 | Proof of property (vi) </p>

<p>Referring to Equation (A7), we have </p>

<p>2 
ffiffi ffi 
2 
p 
I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ðajbÞ5 </p>

<p>2t 1 t 2 1t 1 a23t 2 a22a </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ð 
Þ </p>

<p>t 2 1a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>t 1 2a 
t 2 1a </p>

<p>q 
1 
t 1 1t 2 22t 1 t 2 23t 1 a1t 2 a12a </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ð 
Þ </p>

<p>t 1 2a 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffi </p>

<p>t 2 1a 
t 1 2a </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>t 1 511bk and t 2 5 
12b 
k 
: </p>

<p>Plugging t 1 5 1 1 ak and t 2 5 </p>

<p>12a </p>

<p>k ; we obtain </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffi ffi 
2 
p 
I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ðajaÞ5 </p>

<p>a1k23ak21 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
ð12a1akÞ 
1 
2k23ak1ak </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
12a1ak 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>5 
a13k26ak1ak 
2 21 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
ak2a11 
ð 
Þ 
: </p>

<p>(A13) </p>

<p>Solving the equation, I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ða 
Ã ja 
Ã Þ50 from Equation (A13), we have </p>

<p>a 
Ã 5 
3k21 
6k2k 2 21 
; 
(A14) </p>

<p>which is strictly increasing in k and reaches 1 where k 5 3. Where k&gt;3; (A14) exceeds 1. </p>

<p>A6 | Proof of property (vii) </p>

<p>In the Nash equilibrium, i.e., aðb 
Ã Þ5a 
Ã , we have the following equation: </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ðaðbÞjbÞ50: 
(A15) </p>

<p>Implicitly differentiating (A15) with respect to b, we acquire </p>

<p>a 
0 ðbÞ52 
oI </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ðajbÞ=ob 
I </p>

<p>00 </p>

<p>A ðajbÞ </p>

<p>: 
(A16) </p>

<p>Plugging ða; bÞ5 </p>

<p>3k21 </p>

<p>6k212k 2 into (A16), we have </p>

<p>a 
0 b 
ð Þ5 
11k 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>14k2k 2 21 
&lt;1; </p>

<p>which is strictly less than 1 where k 2 ½1; 3. </p>

<p>A7 | Proof of Property (viii) </p>

<p>Referring to Equation (A14), we have </p>

<p>a 
Ã ðkÞ5 
3k21 
6k2k 2 21 
; </p>

<p>which is a unique solution for I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ða 
Ã ja 
Ã Þ50. Where k &gt; 3, a*(k) exceeds 1. Thus, if k &gt; 3, there is no </p>

<p>solution for a* in the range of [0,1] for the equation I </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>A ða 
Ã ja 
Ã Þ50. </p>

<p>A8 | Proof of Proposition 2 </p>

<p>From Equation (21), we know that the necessary and sufficient condition for the existence of immise-
rizing growth effects is that E &gt; 0.5. From Equations (21) to (24), we know that I A increases as a 
decreases if a 5 a 
0 5 1. This means that if country B is in the state of complete specialization (i.e., </p>

<p>b 5 1), country A does not have an incentive to achieve complete specialization. The same logic is 
applied to country B. Therefore, they have mutual incentives to deviate from complete specialization. </p>

<p>APPENDIX B: ANALYSIS OF THE TWO-STAGE GAME 
In the economy described in Section 6, country A's consumption on goods x and y are </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>| </p>



<p>x A 5 </p>

<p>ð12aÞ1ak </p>

<p>p 
q </p>



<p>ð11t A Þ 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p p 
q 21t A 
ð 
Þ 
; y A 5 </p>

<p>ð12aÞ1ak </p>

<p>p 
q </p>



<p>
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
21t A 
ð 
Þ 
: 
(B1) </p>

<p>From (B1), country A's indirect utility is </p>

<p>I A 
p 
q 
; t A ; t B ; a; b </p>



<p>5 </p>

<p>ð12aÞ1ak 
p 
q </p>

<p>
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
11t A 
p </p>

<p>ffiffi ffi 
k 
p ffiffi ffi 
p 
q </p>

<p>r 
21t A 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>5 
12a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p ffiffi ffi 
p 
q </p>

<p>r 1a 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p ffiffi ffi 
p 
q </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>B 
B 
@ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C 
C 
A </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
11t A 
p </p>

<p>21t A 
: </p>

<p>(B2) </p>

<p>By the market clearing conditions and maximization, the relative world price of good x is </p>

<p>p 
q 
5 
bk 21t A 
ð 
Þ1 12a 
ð 
Þ 11t A 
ð 
Þ 21t B 
ð 
Þ 
ak 21t B 
ð 
Þ1 12b 
ð 
Þ 11t B 
ð 
Þ 21t A 
ð 
Þ 
: 
(B3) </p>

<p>Under complete specialization, i.e., (a,b) 5 (1,1), country A's utility is </p>

<p>I A 5 
ffiffi ffi 
k 
p 
1 
ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
21t B 
p </p>

<p>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi 
11t A 
21t A </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>; 
(B4) </p>

<p>which is strictly increasing in t A but strictly decreasing in t B . Therefore, under complete specialization, 
the Nash equilibrium for tariffs is ðt </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>A ; t </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>B Þ5ð1; 1Þ. 
Now, we assume that the economy is not in the state of complete specialization. Partially 
differentiating p/q with respect to t A , we have </p>

<p>FIGU RE B1 The best response functions where k 5 3 in the two-stage game [Colour figure can be viewed at </p>

<p>wileyonlinelibrary.com] </p>



<p>| </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>o p=q 
ð 
Þ 
ot A 
5 
11t B 
ð 
Þ 12b 
ð 
Þ 11t B 
ð 
Þ1ak 12a 
ð 
Þ 11t B 
ð 
Þ1abk 
2 2ð12bÞat B 
½ </p>

<p>
ð12bÞð21t A Þ 11t B 
ð 
Þ2akð21t B Þ 
½ </p>

<p>
2 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>12b 
ð 
Þ1ak 12a 
ð 
Þ1 
abk 
2 2ð12bÞa 11t B 
ð 
Þ 
21t B </p>

<p>ak2 
ð12bÞð21t A Þ 11t B 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>21t B 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>" 
# 2 
: </p>

<p>(B5) </p>

<p>From Equations (B2) and (B5), we can derive the best response tariff function t A (t B ;a,b), that 
maximizes country A's utility conditional on t B . In the same way, we can derive country B's best </p>

<p>response tariff function, t B (t A ;a,b). Plugging t A (t B ;a,b) and t B (t A ;a,b) into I A </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>q ; t A ; t B ; a; b </p>



<p>, we have </p>

<p>country A's indirect utility function in terms of (a,b), which is denoted as I </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>A ða; bÞ. From I </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>A ða; bÞ, 
we can derive the best response function a(b) that maximizes I </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>A ða; bÞ given b. In the same way, 
country B's best response function b(a) can be derived. For example, where k 5 3, the two best 
response functions, a(b) and b(a), are shown in Figure B1, where the Nash equilibrium is (a*, 
b*) 5 (0.62,0.62). 
From a(b) and b(a), we can derive the Nash equilibrium specialization (a*,b*) which satisfies a 
(b*) 5 a* and b(a*) 5 b*. By the symmetric structure of the model, we always have a* 5 b. From the 
derivations of t A ðt B ; a; bÞ and t B ðt A ; a; bÞ, I apply a numerical analysis using <rs type="software">Matlab</rs>. The Matlab code 
can be downloaded in mwkang.site11.com/code/rie2016. </p>

<p>KANG </p>

<p>| </p>



</text></tei>