<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.104.8.2456" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We show that isolated capital cities are robustly associated with 
greater levels of corruption across US states, in line with the view 
that this isolation reduces accountability. We then provide direct 
evidence that the spatial distribution of population relative to the 
capital affects different accountability mechanisms: newspapers 
cover state politics more when readers are closer to the capital, 
voters who live far from the capital are less knowledgeable and 
interested in state politics, and they turn out less in state elections. 
We also find that isolated capitals are associated with more money in 
state-level campaigns, and worse public good provision. (JEL D72, 
D73, H41, H83, K42, R23) </p>

<p>Corruption is widely seen as a major problem, in developing and developed coun-
tries alike, and much has been written on its determinants and correlates. This paper 
pursues the first systematic investigation of a hitherto underappreciated element in 
this story: the spatial distribution of the population in a given polity of interest, rela-
tive to the seat of political power. 
This spatial distribution might affect the incentives and opportunities for public 
officials to misuse their office for private gain. In particular, it may affect the degree 
of accountability, as has long been noted in the particular context of US state poli-
tics. For instance, Wilson's (1966) seminal contribution argued that state-level politics 
were particularly prone to corruption because state capitals are often far from the 
major metropolitan centers, and thus face a lower level of scrutiny by citizens and 
by the media: these isolated capitals have "small-city newspapers, few (and weak) </p>

<p>* ). We are grateful to three anonymous referees for 
many helpful suggestions. We also thank  
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>civic associations, and relatively few attentive citizens with high and vocal standards 
of public morality" (Wilson, p. 596). As a result, "it is no accident that state officials 
in Annapolis, Jefferson City, Trenton, and Springfield have national reputations for 
political corruption" (Maxwell and Winters 2005, p. 3). 
Our first contribution is to establish a basic stylized fact that is very much in 
line with this "accountability view": isolated US state capital cities are associ-
ated with higher levels of corruption. A simple depiction of that can be seen in 
Figure 1, where our baseline measure of corruption is plotted against our baseline 
measure of the isolation of a state's capital city. We show that this connection is very 
robust, despite the inherently small sample size, and consistently meaningful from 
a quantitative perspective. 
Quite importantly, we are also able to address the issue of endogeneity, which 
is evidently present since the location of the capital city is an institutional choice, 
and since it might itself affect the distribution of population. Fortunately, the his-
torical record documenting the designation of state capitals gives us a plausible 
source of exogenous variation: the location of the geographical centroid of each 
state. We develop instrumental variables based on that location, and find that the 
effect of an isolated capital city on corruption is again significant when estimated 
using this strategy. 
Our second contribution is to provide direct evidence that isolated capital cities 
are associated with lower accountability. We investigate two different realms of 
accountability, certainly among the most important: the roles of the media and 
of the electoral process. We find that they are indeed affected by the spatial distri-
bution of population. 
When it comes to the media, we show that newspapers give more coverage to 
state politics when their readership is more concentrated around the state capital 
city. This is matched by individual-level patterns: individuals who live farther from </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.4 
0.5 
0.6 
0.7 
0.8 </p>

<p>Average log distance </p>

<p>Corruption 
Fitted values </p>

<p>• RI 
• MA • CT 
• DE </p>

<p>• CO • UT • NH • VT </p>

<p>• MD 
• NJ </p>

<p>• IN 
• ME </p>

<p>• MN </p>

<p>• AR 
• NE </p>

<p>• MI • KS 
• NC 
• AZ 
• WA 
• OR </p>

<p>• WI </p>

<p>• WV • VA • KY </p>

<p>• OH 
• GA 
• SC • OK 
• PA 
• AL </p>

<p>• TN </p>

<p>• LA </p>

<p>• MS </p>

<p>• ND• MT 
• NY 
• IL 
• SD </p>

<p>• FL 
• NM 
• MO 
• ID • WY • NV 
• TX • CA </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Note: Corruption = Federal convictions of public officials for corruption-related crime (average 
1976-2002); independent variable: AvgLogDistance not (average 1920-1970). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>the state capital are less informed and display less interest in state politics, but not 
in politics in general. 
When it comes to elections, we find that voter turnout in state elections is greater 
in counties that are closer to the state capital. In addition, we also show that iso-
lated capital cities are associated with a greater role for money in state-level elec-
tions, as measured by campaign contributions, and that, in states with a relatively 
isolated capital, firms and individuals who are closer to it contribute dispropor-
tionately more. These are novel empirical regularities, all of which likely further 
distort accountability. 
Finally, we provide some evidence on whether this pattern of low accountability 
affects the ultimate provision of public goods: states with isolated capital cities also 
seem to spend relatively less, and get worse outcomes, on things like education, 
public welfare, and health care. This suggests that low accountability and corrup-
tion induced by isolation do have an impact in terms of government performance 
and priorities. 
The substantial quantitative literature looking at corruption across US states (e.g., 
Meier and Holbrook 1992; Fisman and Gatti 2002; Alt and Lassen 2003; Glaeser and 
Saks 2006), has pointed at factors ranging from education to historical and cultural 
factors to the degree of openness of a state's political system, but it has essentially 
not tested the idea that the isolation of the capital city is related to corruption. 
1 We 
also relate to the literature on media and accountability, particularly in the United 
States, such as Snyder and Strömberg (2010), and Lim, Snyder, and Strömberg 
(2014). Our evidence is very much consistent with their finding that a disconnect 
between media markets and political jurisdictions weakens accountability. 
Most directly, our paper belongs in the intersection between urban economics 
and economic geography, on one side, and political economy-such as Ades and 
Glaeser (1995); Davis and Henderson (2003); Campante and Do (2010); Galiani 
and Kim (2011); and Campante, Do, and Guimaraes (2013). A recent literature in 
political science has also dealt with the political implications of spatial distributions, 
as surveyed for instance by Rodden (2010). We add the idea that some places (e.g., 
capital cities) are distinctive. 
The paper is organized as follows: Section I presents the data, Section II discusses 
the empirical strategy to deal with endogeneity issues, Section III showcases the 
results, and Section IV discusses them. Section V concludes. </p>

<p>I. Data </p>

<p>We start by describing our data, focusing on the main variables of interest. Our 
choices for instrumental variables will be discussed later, within the context of our 
empirical strategy. All variables (including control variables), sources, and descrip-
tive statistics are documented in the online Appendix. </p>

<p>1 Some studies have found that population size is positively correlated with corruption (Meier and Holbrook 
1992, Maxwell and Winters 2005), although this relationship is not especially robust (Meier and Schlesinger 2002, 
Glaeser and Saks 2006). As for the spatial distribution of population, most effort has been devoted to looking at 
urbanization, under the assumption that corruption thrives in cities (Alt and Lassen 2003). There is some evidence 
for that assertion, but it is not robust (Glaeser and Saks 2006). </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>A. Isolation of the Capital </p>

<p>We get information on the spatial distribution of population for the 48 continental 
states with county-level data from the US Census, for all census years between 1920 
and 2000. We attribute the location of each county's population to the geographical 
position of the centroid of the county, and then calculate its distance to the State 
House or Assembly. 
2 From that we compute measures of isolation averaged over 
time, both because the effects of changes in the distribution of population would 
likely be felt over a relatively long period, and because, while autocorrelation turns 
out to be very high, there is nontrivial variation over time in a number of states. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Our preferred measure of isolation is the average of the log of the distance of the 
state's population to the capital city, AvgLogDistance for shorthand. Campante and 
Do (2010) show that this measure (uniquely) has a number of desirable properties. 
(See details and a brief discussion of properties in the online Appendix.) 
It is also rather easy to interpret. To fix ideas, consider an intuitive measure of 
isolation of a state's capital, namely the distance between the capital and that state's 
largest city. AvgLogDistance takes this intuition and applies it in a more comprehen-
sive and systematic fashion. First, instead of looking at the largest city only, it takes 
into account the entire state without arbitrarily discarding information. Second, it 
does so by weighing each place according to its population. Last but not least, the 
log transformation ensures that the measure is unbiased with respect to the measure-
ment error introduced by not having the exact location of individuals, and thus hav-
ing to approximate the actual spatial distribution (Campante and Do 2010). 
To further facilitate interpretation, we normalize the measure so that zero rep-
resents a situation of minimum isolation, in which all individuals live arbitrarily 
close to the State House. Conversely, we set at one the situation where the capital 
is maximally isolated, with all individuals living as far from it as possible in the 
context of interest. 
Given this basic framework, different choices can yield specific versions that 
highlight distinct aspects of isolation. We choose to adopt a relatively agnostic view 
and experiment with a few options. 
The first choice has to do with normalization and what it means to have "maxi-
mal" isolation. To fix ideas, consider that the salience of what happens in the state 
capital, for a given citizen, decreases with her distance from it. One possibility is that 
salience falls at the same rate across different states, so that distances are weighted 
in the same way in states large and small. In this case, we set maximum isolation as 
benchmarked by the highest possible level across all states: a measure of one would 
correspond to a situation where the entire population of the state is as far from its </p>

<p>2 While finer geographical subdivisions such as census tract and block are available, the focus on counties 
enables us to compute the measures for the years before the population data became consistently available at those 
more detailed levels for the entire United States in 1980. We start in 1920 because that is when detailed county data 
first becomes available. Alaska and Hawaii are left out as the data for them do not go as far back in time. 
3 We will use different averages depending on the relevant period of analysis but, quite importantly, our results 
are essentially unaltered if we use time-specific measures instead (see the online Appendix). Also importantly, we 
will leave aside the time variation in our estimation, because the very high autocorrelation in the isolation measures 
and the fluctuations over time in the baseline corruption variable, as we will note, make that variation very noisy, 
entailing severe econometric problems with standard methods and thus rendering its use unwarranted. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>capital as it is possible to be far from Austin while remaining in Texas. We denote 
this "unadjusted" measure by AvgLogDistanc e not . 
Another possibility is that this salience falls to zero beyond the state's borders. 
In this case, we would want to set the level of maximum isolation in each state to 
be a situation where the entire population lives as far from the capital as it is pos-
sible to be in that specific state. This would correspond to an "adjusted" version 
of our measure, AvgLogDistanc e adj , which automatically adjusts for the size of 
each state. 
An important point coming out of this distinction is that AvgLogDistanc e not is in 
practice highly correlated with the geographical size of the state. At the same time, 
we want to distinguish the impact of the distribution of population from a possible 
unrelated correlation with geographical size per se. We will do that by controlling for 
the size and shape of each state in all AvgLogDistanc e not specifications, by including 
(the log of) the state's area and (the log of) the maximum distance from county cen-
troids to state capital (i.e., the measure that benchmarks AvgLogDistanc e adj ). This 
will allow us to consider the hypothetical of comparing states with similar sizes but 
different degrees of isolation, which seems to be the relevant experiment. 
A second choice has to do with functional form. While AvgLogDistance has the 
notable advantage of unbiasedness, its concavity entails a view of accountability 
that gives disproportional weight to citizens living relatively close to the capital. 
For instance, in the limit, one could imagine a model in which all that matters is 
the population that lives within a certain range of the capital; concavity gives us 
a way to approximate this without attributing arbitrary limits. An alternative view 
would have individual weights decline linearly with distance, and to allow for 
this possibility we will consider AvgDistance, without the log transformation, as 
a robustness check. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>We will also consider a couple of well-known (inverse) measures of isolation: 
the share of population living in the state capital (as of 2010), CapitalShare, and a 
dummy for whether the capital is the largest city in the state, CapitalLargest. These 
are very coarse and rather unsatisfactory measures, relying on arbitrary definitions 
of what counts as the capital city and discarding all the spatial information beyond 
those arbitrary limits, but we will check them for the sake of completeness. </p>

<p>B. Corruption </p>

<p>Our baseline measure of corruption across US states is the oft-used number of 
federal convictions for corruption-related crime (relative to the size of the popula-
tion). (A detailed description of this measure can be found in Glaeser and Saks 
2006.) These refer to cases, typically prosecuted by US Attorneys all over the coun-
try, against public officials and others involved in public corruption, as surveyed and 
compiled by the Public Integrity Section (PIS) at the US Department of Justice in 
their "Report to Congress." Federal authorities can claim jurisdiction, for instance, 
over corruption-related crime that "affects interstate commerce," or in entities that 
receive more than $10,000 in federal funds-which yields them a lot of leeway </p>

<p>4 This measure has all of the other main properties of AvgLogDistance, as noted in the online Appendix. The 
correlation between the two in our sample is around 0.8. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>in pursuing cases related to state and local governments. The resulting measure 
has the substantial advantage of being relatively objective, and focusing on federal 
convictions alleviates concerns over the differences in resources and political bias 
that might affect the variation across states. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Because the measure is very noisy in terms of its year-on-year fluctuations, we 
focus attention on the average number of convictions, for the period 1976-2002. 
We use this sample of years to keep comparability with the existing literature (e.g., 
Glaeser and Saks 2006, Alt and Lassen 2008). 
The baseline measure aggregates state-, federal-, and local-level officials, plus 
"others involved." This adds noise to the extent that the accountability logic we 
focus on pertains most directly to state governments. However, it adds much rel-
evant information, both because state officials are only a fraction of those implicated 
in corruption at the level of state politics, and because one would expect that a cul-
ture of corruption arising at that level would spill over to other domains of govern-
ment in the state. 
6 Still, we consider as an alternative approach a measure restricted 
to state-level officials. These are not discriminated on a state-by-state basis in the 
PIS Report, but some of the information can be recovered from the Transactional 
Records Access Clearinghouse (TRACfed) at Syracuse University, a database com-
piling information about the federal government. We have gathered yearly data for 
each individual state and (fiscal) year between 1986 and 2011, and averaged them 
over the entire available period. 
7 We also normalize the measure, using the number 
of state government employees (as of 1980). 
For the sake of robustness, we will also look at different approaches to measur-
ing corruption. First, we follow Saiz and Simonsohn (2013) in building a measure 
from an online search, using the <rs type="software">Exalead</rs> tool, for the term "corruption" close to 
the name of each state (performed in 2009). 
8 Lastly, we consider additionally (in 
the online Appendix) the measure of corruption perceptions in state politics intro-
duced by Boylan and Long (2003), based on a set of questions posed to report-
ers covering State Houses, and the TRACFed-based measure of convictions of 
local officials. The former is less objective, but gives us another measure of state-
level corruption; the latter provides a measure of spillovers across different levels 
of government. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>5 Still, there obviously is variation related to the functioning of local District Attorney (DA) offices and federal 
agencies, introducing measurement error in the variable (Alt and Lassen forthcoming, Gordon 2009). 
6 As an illustration of the former, consider the case involving former Alabama governor Don Siegelman, who was 
convicted of corruption charges in 2006. As can be gleaned from the 2006 PIS Report, four people were convicted 
in addition to the governor, in relation to the same episode, and none of them were state officials. 
7 This restricted measure is much noisier, not the least because, since there are relatively few state-level officials 
compared to other levels, their share in aggregate convictions is relatively small-typically about 10 percent overall, 
as compiled in the PIS Report. The average number of convictions per state-year in the overall measure is about 14, 
whereas the number for the restricted measure constructed from TRACfed is just under one. 
8 The choice of <rs type="software">Exalead</rs> is due to its being one of the few engines offering reliable "proximity" searches (Saiz 
and Simonsohn 2013, p.138). They argue that this measure performs well in reproducing the standard stylized facts 
found by the literature on corruption, both at the state and country levels. 
9 These measures are typically significantly correlated with one another (see the online Appendix). In particular, 
the baseline measure of federal convictions is highly correlated with the measure restricted to state officials (just 
under 0.6), and somewhat less so with the measure restricted to local officials (about 0.4). The two restricted mea-
sures are significantly correlated with each other (0.33), consistent with the existence of spillovers. The <rs type="software">Exalead</rs> 
measure has a more tenuous correlation with the baseline (0.25, significant at the 10 percent level). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>C. "Placebo" Variables </p>

<p>We consider other features of the spatial distribution of population, beyond the 
role of the capital city, by looking at the isolation of the state's largest city (again 
measured by AvgLogDistance). We also check for outcome variables related to 
crime and federal prosecutorial efforts, apart from corruption. Here we resort 
to a measure of criminal cases brought by prosecutors to federal courts in each state 
(as of 2011) in relation to drug offenses, which are by far the most numerous type 
among the federal cases. </p>

<p>D. Accountability </p>

<p>Newspaper Coverage.-When it comes to the media as a source of accountability, 
we focus on state-level political coverage by newspapers, since they tend to provide 
far greater coverage of state politics in the United States than competing media such 
as TV (e.g., Vinson 2003, Druckman 2005). 
We look at newspapers whose print edition content is available online and search-
able at the website NewsLibrary.com-covering nearly four thousand outlets all 
over the United States. We search for the names of each state's then-current gover-
nors-as well as, alternatively, for terms such as "state government," "state budget," 
or "state elections," where "state" refers to the name of each state. 
10 We only con-
sider mentions to the state in which each newspaper is based. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>We also compute a state-level measure of political coverage. We take the first 
principal component of the four search terms for each newspaper (adjusted by size), 
and perform a weighted sum of this measure over all newspapers. 
12 We use two 
alternative sets of weights: the circulation of each newspaper in the state, which for 
its simplicity is our preferred option, and that circulation weighted by its geographi-
cal concentration, as captured by the ReaderConcentr variable described below. The 
latter would put more weight on circulation closer to the capital, allowing for the 
possibility that newspapers whose audience is more concentrated around the capital 
city might have a disproportionate effect on the behavior of state politicians. </p>

<p>Concentration of Readership around the Capital.-We use circulation data bro-
ken down by county, provided by the Audit Bureau of Circulations (ABC). We com-
pute the AvgLogDistance to the capital analogously to what we described before, 
only using newspaper readership instead of population. 
13 We then define the mea-
sure of readership concentration, ReaderConcentr, as 1 − AvgLogDistance: a larger </p>

<p>10 Similar procedures using NewsLibrary.com have been used, for instance, by Snyder and Strömberg (2010) 
and Lim, Snyder, and Strömberg (2012). We look for terms that are not necessarily related to corruption scan-
dals-though it can certainly be the case (and actually is, for some states) that governors are involved in a few of 
those-to guard against reverse causality-namely, the possibility that there is a lot of media coverage because 
of the existence of such scandals. 
11 We also run a search for a "neutral" term ("Monday"), following Gentzkow, Glaeser, and Goldin (2006), to 
control for newspaper size. 
12 This aggregate measure introduces a source of measurement error, due to the fact that the data do not cover 
the totality of a state's newspaper industry. There is no particular reason to believe that this measurement error is 
correlated with the underlying value of the variable we want to measure. 
13 We use the unadjusted version of AvgLogDistance, but normalization is immaterial here, because our estima-
tion will use state fixed effects. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>measure of ReaderConcentr implies that a given newspaper's audience is more 
concentrated around its home state's capital. The number of newspapers with ABC 
data available is considerably smaller than what NewsLibrary.com covers, so we 
end up with a total of 436 newspapers in our sample. We leave aside the circula-
tion of a newspaper outside of its home state, since we are focusing on coverage of 
home-state politics. </p>

<p>Citizens' Information.-We use data from the American National Election Studies 
(ANES). In the 1998 pre-election survey, a random sample of voting-age citizens 
were interviewed, in California, Georgia, and Illinois. As usual for the ANES up 
until 2000, the 1998 survey includes information about the county of each interview, 
which we use to compute distance (from the county centroid) to the state capital. 
Most interestingly and uniquely, it asks questions that directly measure knowledge 
of state politics and interest in news coverage related to state politics. 
We code a dummy for Knowledge that captures whether the individual respon-
dents are able to provide the correct name of at least one candidate in the upcoming 
gubernatorial elections. We also code a dummy for Interest in state political news: 
whether the respondent reports to care about newspaper articles about the guberna-
torial campaign, conditional on her reading newspapers, so as to focus on potential 
consumers of print media. Finally, we create a GeneralInterest dummy based on 
whether respondents follow public affairs in general, unconstrained to the state level. </p>

<p>Voter Turnout.-We look at turnout in all gubernatorial elections between 1990 
and 2012, at the county level, again attributing for simplicity the county's popula-
tion to its centroid, and computing the distance between each county's centroid and 
the state capital. </p>

<p>Money in State Politics.-We look at data on total contributions to electoral cam-
paigns, comprising all types of state-level office and aggregated at the state level. We 
focus on the period 2001-2010, as the state coverage of the data for previous elec-
toral cycles is somewhat inconsistent. In addition to total contributions, we also focus 
on county-level contributions coming from a specific industry, namely real estate, 
which we choose because it tends not to be spatially concentrated, and because it 
is one of the industries that contributes the most to state-level campaigns. 
14 This 
will let us look into whether distance from the capital affects contribution patterns 
within states. </p>

<p>E. Public Good Provision </p>

<p>We start with data on the pattern of expenditures by US states (in 2009). Most 
of state government expenditures that might be directly ascribed to public good 
provision fall under four categories: "Education," "Public Welfare," "Health," and 
"Hospitals." We take the share of these categories in total spending as a proxy for 
resources devoted to public good provision. We also compute the share devoted to </p>

<p>14 Out of the classification provided by our source, the National Institute on Money in State Politics, real estate 
falls behind only public sector unions and lawyers/lobbyists, which tend to be more naturally concentrated. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>"Government Administration," "Interest on General Debt," and "Other" as a proxy 
for what is not directly related to public good provision. 
These measures do not speak to how effectively resources are spent, so we check 
proxies for the ultimate provision of public goods. These are affected by many fac-
tors other than state-level policy, but should still provide useful information. We use 
three measures that capture aspects of what should be affected by the type of pub-
lic good expenditure we have defined: the "Smartest State" index (Morgan Quitno 
Corporation 2005), which aggregates different measures of educational inputs and 
outcomes, the percentage of the population that has health insurance, and the log of 
the number of hospital beds per capita. </p>

<p>II. Empirical Strategy </p>

<p>Our analysis sits on three pillars. First, we will look at the correlation patterns 
linking isolated capital cities and corruption; on the other hand, we will look at 
direct evidence on whether isolation relates to different accountability mechanisms. 
The third pillar is about addressing endogeneity concerns regarding those correla-
tion patterns, related to the facts that the location of the capital city is an institu-
tional decision and that it affects the spatial distribution of population. Both of these 
could be correlated with omitted variables that are also associated with corruption. 
For instance, corruption and the location of the capital city could be jointly deter-
mined-say, with relatively corrupt states choosing to isolate their capital cities. 
Alternatively, it could be the case that corruption affects the population flows that 
determine how isolated the capital city will ultimately be-say, by pushing eco-
nomic activity and population away from the capital. We now turn to the empirical 
strategy we use to address these confounding factors. </p>

<p>A. Source of Exogenous Variation </p>

<p>In the absence of something like a natural experiment on the location of capital 
cities, a source of exogenous variation in the isolation of the capital comes from a 
specific point of interest: each state's centroid. Defined as the average coordinate of 
the state, the centroid does not depend on the spatial distribution of population, but 
only on the state's geographical shape. 
The first crucial point is that the centroid is an essentially arbitrary location and 
should not affect any relevant outcomes in and of itself. This should be true at least 
once the territorial limits of each state are set. 
15 Because of that, we will eventually 
control, in all of our specifications, for the geographical size of the state, to guard 
against the possibility that a correlation between omitted variables and the expan-
sion or rearrangement of state borders might affect the results. 
The second crucial point is that there is a connection between the location of the 
centroid and the location of the capital city, which is obviously a necessary condi-
tion for the variation in the former to generate meaningful variation in the latter. As 
it turns out, the history of the designation of state (and federal) capitals in the United </p>

<p>15 State borders have been generally stable after establishment. For a history of those borders, see Stein (2008). </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>States strongly suggests exactly such a link. This is because concerns with equal 
representation led to strong pressures to locate the capital in a relatively central posi-
tion, particularly as state capital cities were typically chosen at a time when trans-
portation and communication costs were substantial (Zagarri 1987; Shelley 1996; 
Engstrom, Hammond, and Scott 2013). Consistent with that, a quick inspection 
of any map of the United States displaying all state capitals makes it immediately 
apparent that many of them are actually in relatively central locations. </p>

<p>B. Instrumental Variables </p>

<p>The key question is then how to turn this source of exogenous variation into an 
instrumental variable. The natural candidate is the isolation of the centroid in terms 
of population, CentroidAvgLogDistanc e not . We can check that there does seem to 
be a positive correlation between the isolation of the capital and the isolation of the 
centroid, as illustrated by Figure 2. 
This proposed instrument purges the direct influence of the endogenous location 
of the capital, as it does not depend directly on the latter. However, it is still a func-
tion of the distribution of population, and could thus still be contaminated by the 
influence of the capital city over the distribution of population across the state. 
In order to deal directly with that second potential source of exogeneity, we 
will combine the role of the centroid with a second source of exogenous variation 
affecting the spatial distribution of population: the spatial distribution of economic 
resources. More specifically, we use spatial data on land suitability for cultivation, 
aggregating data on soil and climate properties (Ramankutty et al. 2002). 
The idea is that the spatial distribution of land suitability would affect that of pop-
ulation, particularly in pre-industrial days, as people would be more likely to settle 
relatively close to places well-suited for agriculture. The persistence in population 
patterns would in turn suggest that this influence should persist as well. We would </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>AL </p>

<p>AZ 
AR </p>

<p>CA </p>

<p>CO 
CT </p>

<p>DE </p>

<p>FL </p>

<p>GA </p>

<p>ID </p>

<p>IL </p>

<p>IN </p>

<p>IA 
KS 
KY 
LA </p>

<p>ME </p>

<p>MD </p>

<p>MA </p>

<p>MI </p>

<p>MN </p>

<p>MS </p>

<p>MO </p>

<p>MT </p>

<p>NE </p>

<p>NV </p>

<p>NH </p>

<p>NJ </p>

<p>NM </p>

<p>NY </p>

<p>NC </p>

<p>ND </p>

<p>OH 
OK </p>

<p>PA </p>

<p>RI </p>

<p>SC </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>TN </p>

<p>TX </p>

<p>UT </p>

<p>VT </p>

<p>VA </p>

<p>WA </p>

<p>WV </p>

<p>WI </p>

<p>WY </p>

<p>-0.05 
0 
0.05 </p>

<p>• RI </p>

<p>• MA 
• CT </p>

<p>• DE 
• CO 
• UT 
• NH 
• VT </p>

<p>• NJ 
• IN 
• ME 
• MN 
• AR 
• NE 
• MI 
• KS 
• NC 
• AZ 
• OR 
• WV 
• VA 
• KY 
• GA 
• OK </p>

<p>• PA 
• AL 
• TN 
• LA 
• MS </p>

<p>• ND 
• MT 
• NY • IL 
• SD </p>

<p>• FL </p>

<p>• NM 
• MO 
• ID 
• WY 
• NV </p>

<p>Average log distance to capital 
(residuals) 
Fitted values </p>

<p>• </p>

<p>• CA </p>

<p>• WA 
• IA </p>

<p>• MD </p>

<p>• TX </p>

<p>• SC </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Notes: Average log distance to capital is AvgLogDistance not (average 1920-1970) and aver-
age log distance to centroid is CentroidAvgLogDistance not (average 1920-1970). Residuals are 
obtained from regressions of those variables on log Area and log Maximum Distance. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>thus expect that, in case the most suitable land is relatively far from the centroid, 
population would tend to be too-and the capital city would be more isolated, to the 
extent that it tends to be located close to the centroid. Crucially, it is eminently plau-
sible that spatial patterns in terms of climate and soil, relative to the state's centroid, 
would neither be meaningfully affected by current population patterns that could be 
correlated with corruption, nor likely to affect corruption through any means other 
than their impact on the isolation of the capital. 
We thus compute SuitCentroidAvgLogDistanc e not for the 48 states in the conti-
nental United States, and use it as an alternative instrumental variable. Its main 
drawback is that, quite naturally, it has a more tenuous correlation with our variable 
of interest, namely the isolation of the capital. </p>

<p>C. Validation </p>

<p>It is instructive to look at the correlation between our two proposed instrumental 
variables and a number of "predetermined" variables-namely variables that cannot 
be affected by contemporaneous levels of corruption or by its current covariates. We 
select variables that are essentially geographical in nature. 
16 One would expect that, 
if the instruments were to vary systematically with state characteristics that might 
correlate with current levels of corruption, thus threatening the exclusion restriction, 
this would be picked up by a few of those predetermined variables. 
Table 1 first displays the coefficients on these predetermined variables obtained 
by running separate regressions without additional controls (other than the afore-
mentioned geographical size controls). Columns 1 and 2 present the results for the 
population and suitability instrument, respectively. Both are uncorrelated with the pre-
determined variables, with p-values that are generally quite substantial. Alternatively, 
we show in columns 3 and 4 the results from a single specification containing all vari-
ables. There are essentially no significant coefficients (with one marginal exception), 
and the F-test for joint significance also fails to find any connection. 
States with population or land suitability highly concentrated around the centroid 
thus look ex ante rather similar to those with low concentration. Interestingly, col-
umn 5 shows this is not true for the basic measure of capital city isolation, for which 
we do see statistically significant correlations. </p>

<p>III. Empirical Results </p>

<p>A. A Stylized Fact </p>

<p>We first look at the basic correlation patterns between our baseline measures of 
corruption and the isolation of capital cities, in Table 2. 
In column 1, we see a strong positive correlation between corruption and 
AvgLogDistanc e not (measured as an average of the measures calculated up to 1970, 
i.e., before the time period for which corruption is measured), without any controls </p>

<p>16 We can also add a couple of historical variables measured far back in the past, as contained in the 1878 US 
Statistical Abstract, which have the drawback of further limiting our already small sample. These additional results 
are available in the online Appendix. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>Table 2-Corruption and Isolation of the Capital City: Avg log Distance </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
1.0477*** 1.1666*** 1.0307*** 0.7932*** 
[0.215] 
[0.247] 
[0.322] 
[0.276] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
0.8245*** 0.8383*** 0.8023*** 0.5734** 
[0.168] 
[0.190] 
[0.200] 
[0.223] </p>

<p>Basic control variables 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Control I 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Control II 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.257 
0.465 
0.532 
0.609 
0.232 
0.406 
0.525 
0.598 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. OLS regressions. Dependent variable: Corruption = Federal convictions for 
corruption-related crime relative to population, average 1976-2002. Independent variables as of 1970 (AvgLogDistance average 
1920-1970). All AvgLogDistance not specifications include log Area and log Maximum Distance. Basic control variables: log income, 
log population, percent college. Control I: Share of government employment, percent urban, census region dummies. Control II: 
racial dissimilarity, regulation index, Share of value added in mining. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p>Table 1-Correlations with Predetermined Variables </p>

<p>Centroid 
AvgLogDist not 
(population) 
Individual 
(1) </p>

<p>Centroid 
AvgLogDist not 
(suitability) 
Individual 
(2) </p>

<p>Centroid 
AvgLogDist not 
(population) 
Joint 
(3) </p>

<p>Centroid 
AvgLogDist not 
(suitability) 
Joint 
(4) </p>

<p>AvgLogDist not 
Individual 
(5) </p>

<p>AvgLogDist not 
Joint 
(6) </p>

<p>log total border 
0.0115 
0.0080 
0.0151 
0.0139 
−0.0363 
−0.0463 
[0.565] 
[0.418] 
[0.489] 
[0.343] 
[0.242] 
[0.147] </p>

<p>Latitude 
0.0004 
−0.0001 
0.0012 
−0.0004 
−0.0020 
0.0003 
[0.590] 
[0.810] 
[0.216] 
[0.444] 
[0.231] 
[0.883] </p>

<p>Longitude 
−0.0003 
0.0003 
−0.0003 
0.0006* 
−0.0009 
0.0003 
[0.539] 
[0.305] 
[0.725] 
[0.075] 
[0.254] 
[0.737] </p>

<p>log distance to DC 
−0.0027 
0.0009 
0.0060 
−0.0024 
−0.0140 
−0.0099 
[0.742] 
[0.834] 
[0.614] 
[0.556] 
[0.193] 
[0.441] </p>

<p>Date of statehood 
−0.0002 
0.0000 
−0.0001 
−0.0000 
−0.0004* 
−0.0001 
[0.177] 
[0.612] 
[0.380] 
[0.755] 
[0.090] 
[0.656] </p>

<p>log elevation span 
−0.0049 
0.0004 
−0.0074 
−0.0023 
−0.0257*** 
−0.0204* 
[0.307] 
[0.881] 
[0.175] 
[0.340] 
[0.009] 
[0.057] </p>

<p>Percentage of 
−0.0017 
−0.0004 
−0.0025 
−0.0002 
0.0001 
−0.0019 
water area 
[0.181] 
[0.682] 
[0.190] 
[0.851] 
[0.979] 
[0.542] </p>

<p>log navigable 
0.0016 
−0.0006 
0.0016 
−0.0007 
0.0071* 
0.0036 
waterways 
[0.287] 
[0.316] 
[0.464] 
[0.630] 
[0.087] 
[0.452] </p>

<p>Share of arable 
−0.0036 
−0.0116 
−0.0277 
−0.0112 
0.0478 
0.0151 
land (1950) 
[0.869] 
[0.354] 
[0.221] 
[0.498] 
[0.343] 
[0.756] </p>

<p>F-statistic 
1.04 
1.25 
1.46 
p-value 
0.428 
0.295 
0.200 </p>

<p>Notes: p-values in brackets. Columns 1, 2, 5: Coefficients from individual regressions of AvgLogDistance on log Area, log 
Maximum Distance, and reported variable. Columns 3, 4, 6: Coefficients from multiple regression of AvgLogDistance on 
log Area, log Maximum Distance, and all reported variables. F-statistic and p-value are for the joint hypothesis of significance 
of reported coefficients. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>other than geographical size. 
17 Column 2 then introduces a basic set of controls, as 
of 1970. The coefficient of interest is highly significant, and fairly stable in size. 
Columns 3 and 4 add as controls other correlates of corruption that are established in 
the literature, and our preferred specification is that of column 3, which essentially 
reproduces the basic specification in Glaeser and Saks (2006). While in column 4 
the size of the coefficient is slightly reduced, it is robustly statistically significant at 
the 1 percent level, quite remarkably in light of the small sample size. 
18 The same pat-
tern is also present for our first alternative measure of isolation, AvgLogDistanc e adj , 
as shown by columns 5-8 reproducing the four specifications. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>The effect is also meaningful quantitatively. Our preferred specification's coeffi-
cient (1.03) implies that an increase of one standard deviation in the isolation of the 
capital city (around 0.09, or roughly the increase experienced by Carson City, NV 
between 1920 and 2000), would yield a corresponding increase in corruption (0.10) 
of around 0.75 standard deviation. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Let us now consider the robustness of our results, beyond the different specifica-
tions in Table 2. We first consider alternative measures of corruption, in Table 3. 
Columns 1 and 2 reproduce the main specification from our baseline results (col-
umns 3 and 7 in Table 2), for the measure of corruption convictions restricted to 
state officials. 
21 They very much confirm the message from Table 2. Even quantita-
tively, the results are fairly similar, and especially so when we take into account that 
this is a noisier measure: an exercise along the lines of what we have done for the 
baseline results would yield an effect of just over 0.55 standard deviation. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>We then look at the alternative <rs type="software">Exalead</rs> measure of corruption. 
23 Columns 3 and 
4 again mimic the main baseline specifications, and again find very similar results. 
The estimated quantitative effect is now of about 0.7 standard deviation, once again 
very close to the baseline. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>The next step is to check for alternative measures of the isolation of the capital 
city. We find that the results are still present with both versions of AvgDistance, 
adjusted and unadjusted, as shown in columns 5 and 6. For the coarser measures, 
CapitalShare and CapitalLargest, we see negative coefficients in columns 7 and 8, </p>

<p>17 The online Appendix shows that the results are still present without the controls. 
18 The results are not sensitive to outliers: they are still present when we run the regressions excluding one census 
region at a time. They also survive measures of party competition and of the breakdown of state revenues between 
taxes and other sources. These can all be seen in the online Appendix. 
19 We do not include controls for geographical size, since this is built into the measure of concentration. The 
results are not sensitive to that choice (see the online Appendix). 
20 For the sake of comparison, Glaeser and Saks (2006) find in their sample an effect of about half of a standard 
deviation of a corresponding one-standard-deviation increase in education, a variable that has been consistently 
found to be (negatively) correlated with corruption (Alt and Lassen 2003, Glaeser and Saks 2006). 
21 We run weighted regressions, using yearly standard deviations of the measures of convictions for each state 
over the sample period of 1986-2011, in order to adjust for the fact that the small number of convictions entails 
noise in the measures. The results are essentially the same if we run unweighted regressions instead (see the 
online Appendix). 
22 A positive correlation also holds for a narrow measure restricted to convictions of local officials (see the online 
Appendix). This is consistent with the idea that a culture of corruption at the state level spills over to other levels 
of government within the state. 
23 Since the measure of corruption is computed over a more recent period, we use here the average of the mea-
sures of isolation up to 2000, and use the demographic control variables as of 2000 as well. 
24 The regression results are also robust when we use the Boylan and Long (2003) measure of corruption percep-
tions in state politics. They are also quantitatively very similar to our baseline: the estimated coefficient implies 
that an increase in AvgLogDistanc e not by one standard deviation is associated with an increase in the measure of 
corruption perception of about 0.75 standard deviation. (See the online Appendix.) </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>consistent with the baseline results. The quantitative implications, however, suggest 
in both cases a smaller effect, of about one-third of a standard deviation. This is 
consistent with a substantial measurement error being introduced by the use of these 
coarse measures. </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>We then probe the results with a few "placebo" regressions, meant to check 
whether the patterns we find in the data are actually related to the isolation of capi-
tal cities and its conjectured link with corruption and accountability. Columns 1-4 
in Table 4 use the isolation of the largest city-since the latter is also the capital 
city in 17 out of 50 states, one might wonder whether the measure of isolation of 
the capital could be in fact proxying for that. It has no independent effect, and its 
inclusion does not affect the significance or size of the coefficient on the isolation 
of the capital. 
From our basic hypothesis about accountability, one would not expect any par-
ticular connection between the isolation of the capital city and the prevalence of (or 
federal prosecutorial efforts in pursuing) other types of crime that are presumably 
unrelated to state politics. We see in columns 5-8 that indeed there is no connection 
between the number of drug cases and the isolation of the capital. </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>25 Note that we use the "Exalead" measure of corruption, in light of the time period for which we have the popu-
lation data at the city level. The coefficients are negative, but statistically insignificant, when we use the baseline 
measure of convictions, again consistent with substantial measurement error (see the online Appendix). 
26 To check that this is not driven by outliers, we also dropped the states on the Mexico border-which tend to 
have a disproportionate number of drug-related cases (especially Arizona and New Mexico). Columns 7 and 8 show 
the same pattern holds in that case. </p>

<p>Table 3-Corruption and Isolation of the Capital City: Robustness </p>

<p>State 
officials </p>

<p>State 
officials </p>

<p>Corruption 
(Exalead) </p>

<p>Corruption 
(Exalead) 
Corruption Corruption </p>

<p>Corruption 
(Exalead) </p>

<p>Corruption 
(Exalead) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
0.1311** 
0.0020** 
[0.064] 
[0.001] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
0.0741* 
0.0018** 
[0.043] 
[0.001] </p>

<p>AvgDistance not 
0.7733*** 
[0.284] </p>

<p>AvgDistance adj 
0.4710*** 
[0.091] </p>

<p>Capital share 
−0.0011** 
[0.0005] </p>

<p>Capital largest 
−0.0001* 
[0.0001] </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
50 
50 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.591 
0.551 
0.395 
0.398 
0.485 
0.553 
0.340 
0.328 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. OLS regressions; Columns 1-2: Weighted OLS regressions (Weight = 0.0000001 + stan-
dard deviation of conviction sample). Dependent variables: State Officials = Federal convictions of state public officials for cor-
ruption-related crime per 100 state government employees, average 1986-2011. Corruption (Exalead) = Number of search hits for 
"corruption" close to state name divided by number of search hits for state name, using Exalead search tool (in 2009). Corruption 
= Federal convictions for corruption-related crime relative to population, average 1976-2002. Independent variables as of 1970 
(AvgLogDistance average 1920-1970) in columns 1-2 and 5-6, as of 2000 (AvgLogDistance average 1920-2000) in columns 3-4 
and 7-8. Control variables: log Area and log Maximum Distance (for AvgLogDistance not specifications only), log income, log popu-
lation, percent college, share of government employment, percent urban, census region dummies. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>B. 2SLS Results </p>

<p>We can now check the two-stage least-squares (2SLS) results in Table 5, start-
ing in panel A with CentroidAvgLogDistance, the population-based instru-
ment. 
27 We start off in columns 1 and 2 by displaying the first-stage results for 
the full specification, i.e., with the full set of controls. (The results are similar 
for the other specifications.) We can see that it is indeed a significant predictor of 
AvgLogDistance. The F-statistic for the excluded instrument is reasonably high for 
both AvgLogDistanc e not and AvgLogDistanc e adj , but relatively close to standard 
thresholds for weak-instrument-robust inference. 
28 We thus show the p-values as 
given by the minimum distance version of the Anderson-Rubin (AR) test, which is 
robust to weak instruments. Columns 3-8 then reproduce in order, for comparison's 
sake, the specifications with controls from Table 2. We see confirmed the significant 
positive effect of having an isolated capital on corruption. 
Panel B in turn runs the same exercise using our second, land-suitability-based 
instrumental variable, SuitCentroidAvgLogDistanc e not . Unsurprisingly in light of the 
inherently weaker link between it and the isolation of the capital city, the first stage 
is weaker. The instrument is nevertheless still a significant predictor of the isolation </p>

<p>27 The adjusted measure CentroidAvgLogDistanc e adj turns out to be a very weak instrument, with a first-stage 
F-statistic under 3. Still, the 2SLS results are rather similar, and can be seen in the online Appendix. 
28 Specifically, the Cragg-Donald Wald F-statistics are 10.34 and 12.52, respectively, for AvgLogDistanc e not and 
AvgLogDistanc e adj . This lies between the 10 percent and 15 percent thresholds of the Stock-Yogo weak instrument 
maximal IV size critical values (Stock and Yogo 2005), meaning that the instrument would be considered weak if 
we were to limit the size of the conventional IV Wald test to at most 0.1 above its nominal value. We take this to 
mean that the instrument is not obviously weak, but in any case we choose to present the robust inference as well. </p>

<p>Table 4-"Placebo" Tests </p>

<p>Corruption Corruption Corruption Corruption </p>

<p>Drug 
Cases </p>

<p>Drug 
Cases </p>

<p>Drug 
Cases </p>

<p>Drug 
Cases 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
0.4817 
−0.0109 
(largest city) 
[0.298] 
[0.336] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
0.2564 
−0.2019 
(largest city) 
[0.222] 
[0.242] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
1.0366*** 
−4.4612 
−3.9185 
[0.378] 
[13.799] 
[9.765] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
0.8921*** 
1.0907 
−9.5891 
[0.236] 
[9.201] 
[8.288] </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
44 
44 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.422 
0.532 
0.370 
0.532 
0.339 
0.322 
0.394 
0.417 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. OLS regressions. Dependent variables: Corruption = Federal convictions for 
corruption-related crime relative to population, average 1976-2002; Drug Cases = Criminal defendants commenced in federal 
courts, 2011. Independent variables as of 1970 (AvgLogDistance average 1920-1970) for columns 1-4, as of 2000 (AvgLogDistance 
average 1920-2000) in columns 5-8. Control variables: log Area and log Maximum Distance (for AvgLogDistance not specifica-
tions only), log income, log population, percent college, share of government employment, percent urban, regional dummies. 
Columns 7-8 exclude Mexico border states (CA, AZ, NM, TX). 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>of the capital at the 5 percent level. Columns 3-8 show that we also find a generally 
significant effect of the isolation of the capital city on the measure of corruption. </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>C. Accountability and the Spatial Distribution of Population </p>

<p>We will now look for direct evidence that the accountability of state-level officials 
is affected by the spatial distribution of population. In particular, we will consider 
two possible versions of this hypothesis: the role of the media and the role of the 
electoral process. </p>

<p>29 Quite interestingly, the coefficients are remarkably consistent with those obtained in panel A, even if estimated 
a bit less precisely. This suggests that the potential bias stemming from our second source of endogeneity is not 
very important in practice. It is reassuring that the evidence for a causal impact of the isolation of the capital city on 
corruption seems robust to the different sources of endogeneity, and also in relation with the potential threat of the 
relative weakness of the land-suitability instrument. </p>

<p>Table 5-Corruption and Isolation of the Capital City: Addressing Causality </p>

<p>1st 
stage </p>

<p>1st 
stage 
2SLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>Panel A. Population: Centroid 
AvgLogDistance not 
0.8708*** 
1.8280*** 1.7360*** 1.5857*** 
[0.250] 
[0.583] 
[0.546] 
[0.567] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
1.0851*** 
1.4880*** 1.3880*** 1.2725*** 
[0.287] 
[0.489] 
[0.441] 
[0.458] </p>

<p>Basic Control 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control I 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control II 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.851 
0.677 
0.387 
0.463 
0.538 
0.398 
0.481 
0.551 
F-statistic 
12.15 
14.27 
-
-
-
-
-
-
AR p-value 
-
-
0.002 
0.002 
0.003 
0.002 
0.002 
0.003 </p>

<p>Panel B. Land suitability: Centroid 
AvgLogDistance not 
1.2427** 
1.1403 
1.7231** 
1.4375** 
[0.456] 
[0.976] 
[0.858] 
[0.681] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
1.4166** 
0.8999 
1.4495** 
1.2610** 
[0.530] 
[0.776] 
[0.734] 
[0.618] </p>

<p>Basic control 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control I 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control II 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
R 
2 (centered) 
0.828 
0.607 
0.465 
0.465 
0.562 
0.456 
0.469 
0.553 
F-statistic 
7.42 
7.15 
-
-
-
-
-
-
AR p-value 
-
-
0.333 
0.033 
0.014 
0.333 
0.033 
0.015 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. Dependent variable: Corruption = federal convictions for corruption-related crime rela-
tive to population, average 1976-2002. Independent variables as of 1970 (AvgLogDistance: average 1920-1970). Basic control 
variables: log income, log population, percent college, log area, log maximum distance. Control variables I: Share of government 
employment, percent urban, census region dummies. Control variables II: Racial dissimilarity, regulation index, share of value 
added in mining. IV: Centroid AvgLogDistance not of population (panel A) and land suitability (panel B). AR p-value: p-value from 
Anderson-Rubin (minimum distance) test. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>The Role of the Media.-Newspaper-Level Evidence: The basic hypothesis we 
check is that a newspaper's coverage of state politics is greater when its readers are 
on average closer to the state capital. For this we first run regressions of our different 
measures of state-level political coverage on the concentration of readership around 
the capital, ReaderConcentr, controlling for newspaper size, circulation and state 
fixed effects. We indeed find coefficients that are generally positive and significant, 
as we can see in Table 6. </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>We can also look at this question at an aggregate state level, as opposed to that 
of individual newspapers. The regression evidence, in Table 7, confirms that states 
with isolated capitals tend to display lower levels of media coverage of state poli-
tics. 
31 The effect is stronger for the AvgLogDistanc e adj measure, indicating that what 
matters most for the connection is how isolated the capital city is, not so much in 
terms of absolute distances, but rather relative to the geographical size of the state. </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>Similar results obtain with the measure of isolation of the state centroid in terms of 
population as an instrument for the isolation of the capital: we see a significant effect 
in the case of AvgLogDistanc e adj , and no effect for the case of AvgLogDistanc e not 
(columns 5 and 6). That said, statistical significance is sensitive to the exclusion of 
the states of South Dakota and Delaware, which calls for caution in the interpreta-
tion of the aggregate evidence. </p>

<p>30 Note that we would expect the kind of measurement error introduced by leaving aside out-of-state circulation 
to lead these estimates to be biased downward: newspapers with significant out-of-state circulation would likely 
have an incentive to provide less coverage of home-state politics, and the concentration of their circulation is being 
overestimated in our calculation. 
31 We include in our set of control variables a dummy for whether the state had an election for governor in one 
of the years to which our newspaper search refers (2008 and 2009), to account for coverage possibly reacting to the 
proximity of elections. 
32 The results are largely the same if we exclude Rhode Island, which turns out to be a positive outlier in the 
media coverage variable-about five standard deviations greater than the state with the next largest measure. This 
is because there is one newspaper, the Providence Journal, that far outstrips the circulation of all other RI-based 
newspapers in the sample, This newspaper had a very large measure of coverage of state politics, and is idiosyncrati-
cally driving the state-level measure. </p>

<p>Table 6-Newspaper Coverage of State Politics and the Concentration of Circulation 
around the Capital </p>

<p>Number of search hits </p>

<p>State 
elections </p>

<p>State 
budget </p>

<p>State 
government </p>

<p>Governor's 
name 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>ReaderConcentr 
884.057*** 
983.524*** 
1,164.911** 
1,377.846*** 
[304.295] 
[254.500] 
[555.114] 
[239.350] </p>

<p>Observations 
431 
436 
436 
436 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.783 
0.770 
0.789 
0.716 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets, clustered by state. OLS regressions. Dependent variable: Number of 
search hits for each term in NewsLibrary.com (January 1, 2008 to December 31, 2009). Control variables: log of 
daily circulation, Number of search hits for "Monday," state fixed effects. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>Individual-Level Evidence: We now look at whether individuals display lower 
levels of interest and information regarding state politics when they are farther away 
from the state capital. Table 8 shows the results of probit specifications, with our sur-
vey dummy variables for Knowledge and Interest as dependent variables, and (the 
log of) distance to the state capital being the main independent variable of interest. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Columns 1 and 2 show a robust, significant pattern: individuals who are farther 
from the state capital are substantially less likely to be informed about state politics. 
Columns 3 and 4 show the same goes for the level of interest in state campaign 
news, within the subset of newspaper readers. Quantitatively, our preferred speci-
fications with all individual-and county-level controls imply substantial marginal 
decreases of about 8 percentage points (from a mean probability around 66 per-
cent), and 6 percentage points (off a 40 percent mean probability), respectively. 
Finally, columns 5 and 6 display a placebo test: the correlation with distance is 
distinctly absent when it comes to the level of GeneralInterest in government and 
public affairs. </p>

<p>The Role of Voters.-We now check whether citizens who are farther away 
from the capital are also less likely to vote in state elections. Table 9 (panel A) 
runs county-level regressions, with data from all gubernatorial elections between 
1990 and 2012, controlling for county demographics (in the preceding census, 
for each year), and with state-year fixed effects so as to focus on within-state and 
within-election variation. </p>

<p>33 For all dependent variables, we first show the specification with county-level controls only, and then include 
individual-level controls. In all specifications we cluster the standard errors at the county level and include state 
fixed effects, and marginal effects are reported. We also control for the surveyor's assessment of the respondent's 
general level of information about politics and public affairs, so that we look at the effect of distance conditional on 
the respondents' level of information beyond the confines of state politics. </p>

<p>Table 7-Media Coverage and Isolation of the Capital City </p>

<p>Media coverage </p>

<p>Circ. 
weighted </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance 
weighted </p>

<p>Circ. 
weighted </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance 
weighted </p>

<p>Circ. weighted 
2SLS 
population </p>

<p>Circ. weighted 
2SLS 
population 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
−2.3921 
−2.1841 
−4.4325 
[3.379] 
[3.285] 
[2.730] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
−4.7810* 
−5.2566** 
−3.6317* 
[2.529] 
[2.589] 
[2.169] </p>

<p>Observations 
47 
47 
47 
47 
46 
46 
AR p-value 
-
-
-
-
0.115 
0.115 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.460 
0.451 
0.246 
0.237 
0.554 
0.570 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. OLS regressions except where noted. Dependent variable: First principal component of 
weighted search hits for each of the terms in Table 7 (weighted by newspaper circulation or AvgLogDistance-weighted newspaper 
circulation, as indicated), divided by hits for "Monday." Independent variables as of 2000 (AvgLogDistance average 1920-2000). 
Control variables: log Area and log Maximum Distance (for AvgLogDistance not specifications), log income, log population, per-
cent college, share of government employment, regional dummies, dummy for election in 2008-2009. Columns 5-6 exclude Rhode 
Island. The state of Montana is missing from the media coverage sample. Instrument: centroid AvgLogDistance not of population. AR 
p-value: p-value from Anderson-Rubin (minimum distance) test. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>Table 8-Distance to the Capital and Individual Engagement with State Politics </p>

<p>Knowledge 
Knowledge 
Interest 
Interest 
Gen. interest Gen. interest 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>log distance to 
−0.0623*** −0.0836*** 
−0.0326 
−0.0649** 
−0.0001 
−0.0120 
capital 
[0.0205] 
[0.0252] 
[0.0227] 
[0.0288] 
[0.0218] 
[0.0275] </p>

<p>State fixed effects 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
County controls 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Individual controls 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
780 
780 
652 
648 
780 
776 
Mean of dependent 
variable </p>

<p>0.662 
0.662 
0.403 
0.403 
0.590 
0.590 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.033 
0.172 
0.021 
0.160 
0.014 
0.207 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets, clustered by county. Probit regressions, marginal effects reported. 
Dependent variables: Knowledge = dummy for knowing name of at least one candidate in gubernatorial elections; 
Interest = dummy for caring "a great deal," "quite a bit," or "some" about newspaper articles regarding gubernato-
rial elections (conditional on reading newspapers); General interest = dummy for reporting interest in government 
and public affairs "most of the time" or "some of the time." County controls: population, percent urban, popula-
tion density, percent non-White, median age, median income, and median schooling (from 1990 Census); Individual 
controls: dummies for age, occupation, sex, income, and political party identification, and number of children and 
general level of information (from ANES). All columns include state fixed effects. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p>Table 9-Distance to the Capital and Turnout in State Elections </p>

<p>All years 
All years 
Presidential years 
Off years 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Panel A. All electoral cycles 
log distance to capital 
−0.0180*** 
−0.0191*** 
−0.0053 
−0.0341*** 
[0.002] 
[0.003] 
[0.003] 
[0.005] </p>

<p>log distance to centroid 
−0.0031 
[0.002] </p>

<p>State fixed effects 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control variables 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
18,518 
18,518 
3,471 
2,288 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.819 
0.814 
0.768 
0.770 </p>

<p>Dep. var.: Turnout in state 
1990-1992 
1993-1996 
1997-2000 
2001-2004 
2005-2008 
2009-2012 
elections 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) 
(9) 
(10) </p>

<p>Panel B. Individual cycles 
log distance to capital 
−0.0176*** 
−0.0169*** 
−0.0180*** 
−0.0171*** 
−0.0192*** −0.0149*** 
[0.003] 
[0.003] 
[0.003] 
[0.002] 
[0.003] 
[0.002] </p>

<p>State fixed effects 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Control variables 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
2,956 
3,073 
3,069 
3,117 
3,073 
3,230 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.845 
0.800 
0.823 
0.840 
0.836 
0.846 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets, clustered by state. OLS regressions. Dependent variable: turnout in state election, 
county-level (1990-2012). Independent variables: log distance to capital, log distance to centroid. Control variables: log density of 
population over 18, percent high school and above, percent college and above, log median household income, poverty rate, shares of 
population under 5, 5-17, 18-24, 25-44, 45-64, 65-74, 75-84, 85 and above, shares of census-defined races, all from the preceding 
census, and Gini coefficient, racial fractionalization, religious fractionalization from 1990. All columns include state fixed effects. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>We see a negative effect of distance to the capital on turnout in column 1 that 
is statistically significant and quantitatively nontrivial: doubling the distance from 
the capital would reduce turnout by around 1.5 percentage points (or one-sixth of the 
within-state standard deviation), from a mean around 45 percent. Column 2 further 
shows that the result is related to the special role of the capital: a placebo variable 
(distance to state centroid) is insignificant and barely affects the main coefficient. 
Interestingly, column 3 shows the effect is much weaker, and statistically insig-
nificant, for state elections that coincided with presidential elections. In contrast, the 
same regression restricted to the sample of "off "-years where no federal election 
took place yields a coefficient that is three times as large (column 4)-we can reject 
the equality of coefficients at the 1 percent level. 
Panel B (columns 5-10) then shows that the result is unaltered if we consider each 
of the separate six election cycles covered by our data separately: the coefficient is 
remarkably consistent, although it gets smaller in the most recent cycle. </p>

<p>34 </p>

<p>D. Money in Politics </p>

<p>We now ask whether there is a link between the spatial distribution of population 
around the state capital and the amount of campaign money in state-level politics. 
Table 10 shows a robust positive relationship, at the aggregate state level, between 
the isolation of the capital and campaign contributions (controlling for population 
and income). 
Columns 1 and 2 show that the result holds for the basic OLS specifications, 
which reproduce our preferred specifications for corruption, but with campaign 
contributions as our dependent variable. It is also substantial quantitatively: a one-
standard-deviation increase in the isolation of the capital would be associated with a 
30 percent increase in contributions. Columns 3 and 4 then show the result survives 
unscathed when we control for presidential campaign contributions (in the 2008 
election cycle), which helps capture other factors leading to a high general propen-
sity to engage in this form of political activity (the raw correlation is 0.87). Finally, 
columns 5-8 show similar results when we again instrument for AvgLogDistance 
using the isolation of the centroid with respect to population, although the same is 
not true with the alternative instrument. 
In light of this aggregate pattern, we then ask whether, within states, individuals 
or firms who are located closer to the capital have a different propensity to contrib-
ute money to state politics. We look at this question by focusing on one specific 
industry whose location is not particularly concentrated spatially, namely real estate. 
We see in columns 1 and 2 in Table 11 that individuals and firms located in counties 
that are farther from the capital spend less in campaign contributions, both in abso-
lute terms and controlling for income per capita. Columns 3-5 show that the results 
stay remarkably consistent when controlling for additional county demographics, </p>

<p>34 Note that assuming that the relationship that emerges from the county-level data would necessarily aggregate 
up to a link between state-level turnout and the isolation of the state capital would be incurring in the well-known 
ecological fallacy. As it turns out, there is a weak negative link between turnout and the isolation of the capital, 
that is borderline statistically significant (at the 10 percent level) once states with presidential-year elections are 
excluded from the sample. (See the online Appendix.) The difference between presidential and off-years is also true 
for every election cycle taken in isolation (see the online Appendix). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>when leaving aside counties that report no contributions, and even if we look at 
contributions at the zip code level, using within-county variation only. Quite inter-
estingly, columns 6 and 7 show that this pattern comes exclusively from states with 
relatively isolated capital cities (above median AvgLogDistanc e not ). </p>

<p>Table 10 -Campaign Contributions and Isolation of the Capital City </p>

<p>OLS 
OLS 
OLS 
OLS </p>

<p>2SLS 
Population </p>

<p>2SLS 
Population </p>

<p>2SLS 
Land 
suit. </p>

<p>2SLS 
Land. 
suit. 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
3.0146*** 
2.4782** 
5.0364*** 
1.6361 
[0.942] 
[1.080] 
[1.679] 
[2.339] </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance adj 
2.4241*** 
1.9627** 
4.0473*** 
1.3751 
[0.788] 
[0.856] 
[1.372] 
[1.988] </p>

<p>log presid. contributions 
0.3171 
0.3407* 
0.1854 
0.2163 
0.3605** 0.3670** 
[0.207] 
[0.200] 
[0.216] 
[0.206] 
[0.173] [0.171] </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.903 
0.899 
0.910 
0.907 
0.897 
0.896 
0.909 
0.907 
AR p-value 
-
-
-
-
0.002 
0.002 
0.505 
0.505 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. Dependent variable: log of campaign contributions to state-level campaigns, 
2001-2010. Independent variables as of 2000 (AvgLogDistance: average 1920-2000). Control variables (as of 2000): log of cam-
paign contributions to presidential campaigns (2008): log Area and log Maximum Distance (AvgLogDistance not specifications 
only), log income, log population, percent college (all columns), share of government employment, percent urban, regional dum-
mies (except for columns 1 and 4). IV: centroid AvgLogDistance not of population and land suitability. AR p-value: p-value from 
Anderson-Rubin (minimum distance) test. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p>Table 11-Distance to the Capital and Campaign Contributions from Real Estate Industry </p>

<p>By county 
By county 
By county </p>

<p>Counties 
with 
positive 
contribs. </p>

<p>By 
zip code </p>

<p>Counties in 
low avg. 
logdist. 
states </p>

<p>Counties in 
high avg. 
logdist. 
states 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>log distance to capital 
−1.2649*** −0.1797** −0.2052** −0.2146*** −0.3093*** 
0.0001 
−0.3678*** 
[0.181] 
[0.081] 
[0.083] 
[0.049] 
[0.112] 
[0.100] 
[0.119] </p>

<p>Basic controls 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
County controls 
X 
X 
X 
X 
Zero-contrib excluded 
X 
County fixed effects 
X 
State fixed effects 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X 
X </p>

<p>Observations 
3,105 
3,104 
3,050 
2,207 
40,347 
1,199 
1,851 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.334 
0.688 
0.708 
0.736 
0.311 
0.730 
0.700 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets, clustered by state. Observation unit: County (zip code in column 5). Dependent vari-
able: log of campaign contributions to state-level campaigns, 2001-2010, from the real estate industry based in each county (zip-
code in column 5). Counties with zero contribution excluded in column 4. Column 6 sample is restricted to states below median 
AvgLogDistance not , column 7 sample is restricted to states above median AvgLogDistance not . Independent variables: log distance 
to capital. Basic control variables: log population over 18, log median household income. County control variables: percent high 
school and above, percent college and above, poverty rate, log land area, shares of population under 5, 5-17, 18-24, 25-44, 45-64, 
65-74, 75-84, 85, and above, shares of census-defined races, all from 2000 census, and Gini coefficient, racial fractionalization, 
religious fractionalization from 1990. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>E. Isolated Capital Cities and the Provision of Public Goods </p>

<p>Last but not least, we look at whether isolated capital cities are associated with 
distinct patterns of public good provision. Table 12 displays the results, using 
AvgLogDistanc e not as an independent variable of interest. </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Columns 1 and 2 show isolated capital cities are significantly correlated with lower 
spending on public good provision, and with more spending on items not directly 
related to it. Column 3 then shows a correlation, significant at the 10 percent level, 
with lower levels of public good provision, summarized by the first principal com-
ponent of our three measures. The estimates are quantitatively meaningful: a one-
standard-deviation increase in isolation is associated with a drop of around 0.25-0.3 
standard deviation in the distribution of spending, and similarly for public good 
provision. Columns 4-6 then display 2SLS specifications, with the isolation of the 
centroid with respect to population as the instrument. The results are broadly con-
sistent, although the coefficient for public good provision is now essentially zero. </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>IV. Discussion </p>

<p>The main message from our results is the substantial evidence of a link between 
isolated capital cities and greater levels of corruption across US states. This link is 
robust to different specifications and measures of both concepts, and seems to be </p>

<p>35 We use the control variables from our preferred specification for the baseline results in Table 1, except that 
we add ethnic fractionalization in order to take into account the standard result that it seems to affect the provision 
of public goods. 
36 Results are similar if we use AvgLogDistanc e adj instead (see the online Appendix). </p>

<p>Table 12-Public Goods and Isolation of the Capital City </p>

<p>OLS 
OLS 
OLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
2SLS 
PG exp. 
Oth. exp. 
PG prov. 
PG exp. 
Oth. exp. 
PG prov. 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>AvgLogDistance not 
−0.478*** 
0.319*** 
−2.690* 
−0.552** 
0.330** 
−0.405 
[0.137] 
[0.102] 
[1.533] 
[0.217] 
[0.149] 
[2.517] </p>

<p>Observations 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
48 
AR p-value 
-
-
-
0.021 
0.041 
0.874 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.451 
0.593 
0.877 
0.448 
0.593 
0.871 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors in brackets. Dependent variables: PG exp. (public good expenditures) = share 
of state expenditures on education, public welfare, health, and hospitals in 2008; Oth. exp. (other expenditures) 
= share of state expenditures on government administration, interest on debt, and "other" in 2008; PG prov. (pub-
lic good provision) = first principal component of "Smart State" Index (2005), percent of population with health 
insurance (2008-2009), and log of hospital beds per capita (2009). Independent variables: AvgLogDistance not aver-
age 1920-2000. Control variables: log area and log maximum distance, log income, log population, percent col-
lege, share of government employment, racial dissimilarity, percent urban, regional dummies (all specifications). 
IV: centroid AvgLogDistance not of population. AR p-value: p-value from Anderson-Rubin (minimum distance) test. 
*** Significant at the 1 percent level. 
** Significant at the 5 percent level. 
* Significant at the 10 percent level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>specific about corruption, and about the role of the capital city. 
37 In addition, while 
we are short of a true natural experiment where state capitals would have been ran-
domly assigned, plausible sources of exogenous variation indicate that our stylized 
fact is not driven by confounding factors related to the endogeneity of that choice 
and its impact on the spatial distribution of population. 
This is very much in line with what we have termed the accountability view: the 
idea that isolated capitals may see corruption fester because of reduced accountabil-
ity. We have also found direct evidence for that view, as different mechanisms are 
related to the spatial distribution of population. </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>First, we saw that newspapers whose audience is on average farther from the state 
capital provide less coverage of state politics. Such a pattern could be expected, to 
the extent that media outlets are at least partly trying to provide content that inter-
ests their audience (e.g., Mullainathan and Shleifer 2005, Gentzkow and Shapiro 
2010), and to the extent that media consumers are at least somewhat more interested 
(ceteris paribus) in what happens close to where they live. We also found some 
evidence that states with more isolated capitals have less intense media coverage of 
state politics. 
This lower level of media scrutiny could very well lead to, and be reinforced by, 
a less informed and less engaged citizenry. Consistent with that, we find that living 
farther from the capital substantially decreases the level of interest in state cam-
paigns among individuals with comparable demographic characteristics and with 
a comparable level of information about policy in general. In contrast, it does not 
affect the level of interest in public affairs in general. Put together, these pieces 
suggest that where individuals are located matters substantively for media account-
ability at the state level. 
It is thus natural to conjecture that other forms of holding state officials account-
able could also be linked to the spatial distribution of population. In particular, one 
might expect that disengagement to be reflected in lower voter turnout, and hence 
less accountability via the electoral process. We find that turnout in state elections is 
indeed lower farther from the state capital-an empirical regularity that is novel, to 
the best of our knowledge, in the US context. 
39 Notably, the logic of our hypothesis 
would predict a weaker link between turnout and distance to the state capital for 
presidential-year elections, where presumably turnout would be more affected by 
forces unrelated to state politics. This is exactly what we find. 
Still in the realm of the electoral process, we find a strong positive relationship 
between the isolation of the state capital and the amount of money in state-level 
campaigns. We can thus speculate that, with lower media scrutiny and reduced 
involvement by voters, an isolated capital opens the way for a stronger role of money 
in shaping political outcomes. </p>

<p>37 In particular, that the results do not extend to other types of federal crime helps alleviate the concern that they 
might be driven by differences in the ability, zeal, or resources available to federal prosecutors-at least to the extent 
that these differences apply across different types of cases. 
38 We also find that politicians earn higher salaries in states with more isolated capitals, as proxied by governor 
compensation (as a share of per capita income and controlling for the relative desirability of living in the capital, as 
captured by relative housing prices). This is consistent lower accountability, in that one would expect politicians to 
be able to extract rents both legally as well as illegally (see the online Appendix). 
39 Similar effects have been detected elsewhere (Hearl, Budge, and Pearson 1996). </p>

<p> 
campante and do: Isolated capItal cItIes and corruptIon 
Vol. 104 no. 8 </p>

<p>This interpretation is bolstered by the evidence that firms or individuals who are 
located closer to the capital city contribute more, and that this is true only in states 
with relatively isolated capitals. These empirical patterns, which are also novel (to 
the best of our knowledge), indicate that the aggregate relationship is not driven 
by those who are farther from the capital spending money so as to compensate 
for lower influence in other dimensions. In short, isolation seems associated with 
money in politics, and in ways that further distort the political process toward those 
isolated capitals. 
This evidence is particularly interesting as it goes against an alternative hypothesis 
linking isolated capitals and corruption, in the opposite direction from the account-
ability view-what we may call the "capture view." This conjecture, prominently 
featured in the historical records on the debate over the location of US state capitals 
(Shelley 1996), would posit that a capital city removed from the major centers of 
population and economic activity poses a smaller risk of political capture by special 
interests. Insofar as such capture would be reflected in a greater role of money in 
politics, our results undermine the hypothesis, at least in a contemporaneous setting. 
Our last piece of evidence is that isolated capital cities are also associated with 
diminished public good provision. Along with our previous results, this paints a 
picture of isolated capital cities associated with low accountability and corrup-
tion, with important detrimental effects on the state's performance as a provider of 
public goods. 
As a final note, the direct evidence linking isolated capital cities to lower account-
ability also gives us a fresh perspective on the basic stylized fact that links them 
to greater corruption. One important limitation shared by all of our measures of 
corruption is that they capture not only what they are meant to capture, but also 
accountability, to one degree or another. This is certainly a source of measurement 
error, but the evidence on accountability suggests that the true extent of corruption 
in states with isolated capitals is relatively underestimated by our measures. This 
would work against our stylized fact. </p>

<p>V. Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>It is interesting to speculate about the connection between isolated capitals, 
accountability, and corruption, going into the future: could the "death of distance" 
mean that the isolation of capital cities would become relatively less important? In 
addition, the associated retreat of newspapers could also weaken the specific media 
accountability mechanism we detect. This is an interesting topic for future research, 
but it certainly need not be the case: casual observation suggests that online media 
is not immune from a bias toward local coverage-consistent with demand-driven 
bias-and there could also be countervailing forces. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>More broadly, our work sheds light on the long-run implications of institutional 
choices and their spatial content. The importance of the location of the capital city 
is highlighted both by the historical record in the United States, where the issue was </p>

<p>40 As an illustration: conversations with people in the newspaper industry suggest that coverage of state politics is 
often the first to be cut, and likely more so when the capital is isolated, because newspapers need to focus on what is 
most interesting for their dwindling readership, or because it is easier to lay off someone who is in a distant capital. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2014 </p>

<p>prominently discussed and fought over both at the state and federal levels, and by 
the many instances of countries relocating their capitals. We have shown one rea-
son that makes it important, as it affects institutional performance along important 
dimensions even in a fully democratic context. In terms of policy, one is led to con-
clude that polities with isolated capital cities require extra vigilance, to counteract 
their tendency toward reduced accountability. Put simply, watchdogs need to bark 
louder when there is a higher chance that people are not paying much attention. </p>



<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>