<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.20150592" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Hayek (1945) argues that local information is key to understanding 
the efficiency of alternative economic systems and whether production 
should be centralized or decentralized. The Chinese experience of 
decentralizing SOEs confirms this insight: when the distance to the 
government is farther, the SOE is more likely to be decentralized, and 
this distance-decentralization link is more pronounced with higher 
communication costs and greater firm-performance heterogeneity. 
However, when the Chinese central government oversees SOEs in 
strategic industries, the distance-decentralization link is muted. We 
also consider alternative agency-cost-based explanations, and do 
not find much support. </p>

<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>over the merits of market socialism in the first half of the last century involved 
influential economists such as Oscar Lange, Abba Lerner, Ludwig von Mises, and 
Friedrich Hayek, and has continued in recent decades (Bardhan and Roemer 1992,  1993; Shleifer and Vishny 1994; Stiglitz 1994). The two key arguments for why 
capitalism is more efficient than planned economy are: stronger incentives under the 
more secure protection of private property rights and the efficiency of using specific 
information dispersed among individuals and plants (Boettke 2005). This second 
point originates from Hayek (1945), one of the most influential papers of all time. </p>

<p>2   The critical importance of incentives, ownership, and property rights for explaining 
performance in socialist and transitional economies is one of the most active areas 
of research (Megginson and Netter 2001; Djankov and Murrell 2002; Estrin et al.  2009). However, the importance of local information for the management of state-
owned enterprises is rarely empirically explored. 
We examine the causes of decentralization of state-owned enterprises (SOEs) 
in China, focusing on the role of local information. We rely on the Annual Survey 
of Industrial Firms (ASIF) 1998-2007, which covers all SOEs. Decentralization is 
defined as the oversight status of an SOE shifting from a higher-to a lower-level 
government. The availability of local information is captured by the physical dis-
tance between an SOE and the oversight government. A larger distance implies that 
the government has fewer direct observations on firm-specific information. This 
interpretation of distance is consistent with the recent literature in which the dis-
tance is found to capture information asymmetry in financial markets (Coval and  Moskowitz 1999), to explain a headquarter's investment across its plants in differ-
ent locations (Giroud 2013), and to shed light on the lending relationship between 
banks and firms (Petersen and Rajan 1994). 
Hayek (1945) implies it is more efficient for an oversight government with a 
greater distance from the SOE to decentralize the control rights to a lower gov-
ernment closer to the SOE. Moreover, when firms' performance heterogeneity is 
greater, and hence local information figures more prominently, the same distance 
results in a stronger tendency to decentralize in order to utilize local information. 
Furthermore, when the communication costs are lower, the oversight government 
has less difficulty finding out what is going on in the SOE, and the same distance 
may lead to a weaker tendency to decentralize (Bloom et al. 2014). 
Hayek's insight does not imply that SOEs should always be decentralized. Tilting 
the balance toward centralization are considerations such as internalizing the exter-
nality of SOEs, or putting top-notch experts that specialize in complex problems in 
charge of sophisticated SOEs (Garicano 2000). Moreover, the central government 
may have incentives to control key elements of the economy, that is, what Vladimir 
Lenin called in 1922 the "commanding heights." 
Indeed, most governments of the world have engaged in controlling these com-
manding heights since the end of World War II (Yergin and Stanislaw 1998). 
3 Strong 
state intervention in western economies largely started with the UK Attlee Labour </p>

<p>2 As of January 27, 2017, Hayek (1945) has been cited about 14,000 times in <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Google</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Scholar</rs>, and it is viewed 
by a panel of top economists as one of the top 20 articles published in the AER in its first 100 years' history (Arrow  et al. 2011). 
3 Most historical material on commanding heights across countries in this paper comes from Yergin and  Stanislaw (1998). </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>government in 1945, which promoted government planning and nationalization of 
industries. The General de Gaulle government in France followed suit, declaring 
that the state "must hold the levers of command." Similarly, after the independence 
of India, Prime Minister Nehru often evoked the commanding-heights metaphor. 
Typically, these countries, as well as Germany, Korea, Japan, many Latin American 
countries, and of course, all socialist countries, had strong state control/ownership 
over strategic sectors such as defense, iron and steel, railroads, ship-building, util-
ities, and telecom. In these sectors, the key consideration for decentralization is 
likely not to utilize local information but to ensure the benefits of "strategic control." 
Here the force of distance in decentralization should naturally be more muted. 
We find support for the above conjectures. Consistent with Hayek (1945), the 
larger the SOE-to-government distance, the more likely the SOE is decentral-
ized. Moreover, the positive distance-decentralization link is stronger with greater 
firm-performance heterogeneity and higher communication costs. Consistent with 
the commanding-heights conjecture, for SOEs in strategic industries under the 
direct oversight of the central government, the distance-decentralization relation-
ship is muted. This strategic segment is nontrivial but not large, about 5 percent of 
the total value added of all sample industrial firms. 
To ensure correct interpretation for the distance-decentralization link, we conduct 
several checks. To exclude the possibility that distance to the government serves as a 
proxy of the distance to an agglomeration center, we construct a placebo distance to 
the alternative agglomeration city, and do not find this measure to be correlated with 
decentralization. To address distance's potential endogeneity, we rely on exogenous 
sources of variation of the distance to identify its effect on decentralization. In the 
1960s and 1970s, a large number of SOEs were relocated to China's inland areas in 
anticipation of wars with the United States and the Soviet Union. As a result, their 
distances to oversight governments were determined historically and had nothing to 
do with decentralization decisions decades later. The instrumental variable results 
are qualitatively similar to those in our base specification. 
We also consider two alternative hypotheses on decentralization. The first is the 
oversight agency conjecture, which posits that decentralization originates from 
considerations of rent seeking by the oversight government. Like the Hayek con-
jecture, it predicts a positive distance-decentralization link, and a stronger link 
when communication costs are high. However, only the Hayek conjecture pre-
dicts a higher distance-decentralization link in the presence of greater performance 
heterogeneity. Furthermore, the finding of the lack of relationship between the 
distance-decentralization link and the rent environment is consistent with the Hayek 
conjecture, but inconsistent with the oversight agency conjecture. Also supporting 
the Hayek conjecture is that the government initiated SOE reforms to turn around 
SOE performance in the mid-1990s. 
The second alternative hypothesis is the local capture conjecture, which posits that 
decentralization is determined by lower governments' lobbying. Perhaps because of 
its information and other advantages, the lower government is better able to collude 
with SOE for rents (Bardhan and Mookherjee 2000). This view implies a negative 
relationship between decentralization and the SOE-to-lower-government distance, 
and this relationship being more pronounced with higher rents. We find support for 
such a negative relationship (which is also consistent with the information-based </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>Hayek conjecture). However, we do not find the distance-decentralization rela-
tionship to be stronger when rents are higher, and this inconsistency with the local 
capture conjecture makes the Hayek conjecture relatively more appealing. Also sup-
porting the Hayek conjecture is the fact that the decentralization decision could not 
be refused by lower governments. 
We contribute to two threads of literature. First, this is the first empirical paper 
that links and tests Hayek's idea of the fundamental importance of local information 
in understanding SOE decentralization. We are not the first to examine how local 
information affects decentralization of firms in a market economy (e.g., Acemoglu  et al. 2007; Bloom et al. 2014; Bloom, Sadun, and Van Reenen 2012; Giroud 2013). </p>

<p>4   However, we differ from these previous studies in two aspects. First, we focus on 
the role of local information in SOE decentralization, and speak directly to Hayek's 
attempt to understand how local information shapes the choices of centralization ver-
sus decentralization for socialist firms. In the literature of socialist firms, there have 
been numerous studies of incentives and ownership (Megginson and Netter 2001;  Djankov and Murrell 2002; Estrin et al. 2009), but none documents the key aspect of 
how the lack of local information affects the governance of socialist firms (Boettke  2005). In addition, we add to the general literature of local information and firm 
decentralization by offering evidence that, in the state sector, commanding-heights 
considerations can overrule the force of local information. 
Related to the literature above, we also add to the empirical literature on the ben-
efits and costs of decentralization in firms (Bardhan 2016). The theoretical literature 
on decentralization of firms is large. Aghion and Tirole (1997) show it is efficient to 
delegate when the information advantage of agents is significant and the conflict of 
interest is not large. Garicano (2000) suggests that it makes sense to create a hier-
archy of knowledge production (see also Bolton and Dewatripont 1994). Dessein  (2002) and Alonso, Dessein, and Matouschek (2008) argue that when agents report 
information strategically, it is often desirable for an uninformed principal to dele-
gate. These theoretical papers greatly enrich the insights of Hayek (1945) by pro-
viding further rationales for decentralization, both highlighting factors that Hayek 
considered, such as agent information advantage (Aghion and Tirole 1997), and 
those that Hayek did not consider, such as specialization in information acquisi-
tion, hierarchy of knowledge production, conflicts of interest between principals and 
agents (Aghion and Tirole 1997), and strategic reporting by agents (Dessein 2002;  Alonso, Dessein, and Matouschek 2008). In contrast to the large theoretical litera-
ture on decentralization, the empirical literature is limited. Thus, while we cannot 
directly test the implications of these new models, by testing the simple yet powerful 
implications of Hayek (1945), we contribute to the emerging empirical literature on 
decentralization of firms (Acemoglu et al. 2007; Bloom et al. 2014; Bloom, Sadun,  and Van Reenen 2012; Giroud 2013; Aghion et al. 2017). </p>

<p>4 Acemoglu et al. (2007) show that the availability of public information to the headquarters reduces the need 
to delegate controls to the manager. Bloom et al. (2014) provide evidence that the information technology facili-
tates, while the communication technology hinders, decentralization within a firm. Bloom, Sadun, and Van Reenen 
(2012) find that competition and trust foster greater decentralization. Giroud (2013) examines how the within-firm 
distance between headquarters and their plants affect plant performance, and finds that the proximity of the head-
quarters to a plant increases the plant's investment and productivity. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>Second, we contribute to an ignored area, that of SOE decentralizations in the 
literature of SOE reforms. This literature largely focuses on privatization (World 
Bank 1995; Yergin and Stanislaw 1998; Megginson and Netter 2001; Djankov and  Murrell 2002; Bai, Lu, and Tao 2009; Estrin et al. 2009), but SOE decentralization 
has been widespread and important. Indeed, local governments are playing increas-
ingly important roles in governing SOEs (Bardhan 2002; 2016), which remain 
important in many countries. In China, for instance, the share of the state sector in 
the value of industrial output, while dropping precipitously from 78 percent in 1978, 
has stabilized at a high level of 22 percent in 2014. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>I. Institutional Background </p>

<p>The formal hierarchy of Chinese government consists of the central, provincial, 
municipal, and county governments. Each government of a specific level is in charge 
of all the SOEs affiliated with that government. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Decentralization of Chinese SOEs became an important option for SOE reforms 
as the government confronted SOE losses and tried to improve SOE performance. 
After China began its economic reform in 1978, market competition quickly inten-
sified coincident with a rise of the private sector (Brandt and Rawski 2008). As a 
result, the profits and taxes per unit of net capital stock and working capital in indus-
trial SOEs had fallen from 24 percent in 1978 to 7 percent in 1996 (Qian 2000), and 
more than one-third of SOEs had losses in 1996. Realizing the necessity of further 
reforms, some oversight governments experimented with decentralizing SOEs in 
order to improve efficiency. 
7 For instance, State Economic and Trade Commission  et al. (1994) stated that "the adjustment of the oversight status of SOEs should aim 
for … optimizing the allocation of state assets, and improving operating efficiency 
of capital." 
8 Partly due to its local-experiment nature, the decentralization process 
proceeded unevenly. Based on our sample, which includes all SOEs, decentraliza-
tion happened throughout our sample period: the annual numbers of SOEs being 
decentralized from 1999 to 2007 are 235, 200, 250, 149, 204, 280, 102, 59, and 37, 
respectively. We focus on decentralizations after 1998, which is the earliest year 
with detailed data of all SOEs. 
Decentralization was one of many methods for SOE reforms beginning in the 
second half of the 1990s. The slogan of overall SOE reform then was "grab the big 
and let go of the small" (Xu, Zhu, and Lin 2005; Hsieh and Song 2015). With limited 
attention span and information processing ability, the upper government decided to 
focus its attention on key SOEs. To "grab the big," many large SOEs were merged 
to form industrial conglomerates, and the control rights over such firms were con-
solidated to the central government. To "let go of the small," many SOEs were pri-
vatized, or went through internal restructuring, bankruptcy, employee shareholding, </p>

<p>5 This measure has changed into the share in total industrial sales since 2012, and it does not include the share 
of collective firms. 
6 Online Appendix Figure B-1 shows the distribution of SOE affiliations in terms of the number of firms, 
employment and output in 1998. 
7 This readiness to experiment with various reform options at the local level is a key advantage of the M-form 
governance in China (Qian, Roland, and Xu 2006). 
8 See online Appendix C for all government documents cited in the paper. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>auctions, leasing, and joint ventures (Garnaut et al. 2005, Chapter 3); others were 
delegated to lower-level governments, i.e., decentralized. In implementing SOE 
reforms, the central government offered general guidelines but left significant room 
for the oversight governments to experiment (Qian, Roland, and Xu 2006; Brandt  and Rawski 2008). The State Reform Commission (1996), for instance, stated that 
the reform of small SOEs should respect local conditions of each region, and that the 
local government was encouraged to experiment with various means. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>The decentralization decision, once made by the oversight government, could not 
be refused by its lower governments. Because of its power to appoint government 
officials, the higher-level government had total control over its lower levels, and the 
decentralization decision was thus made by the incumbent oversight government. 
Some provinces explicitly stated that no city had the right to resist the implementa-
tion of SOE decentralization (e.g., Chongqing Government 1997). 
Decentralization in general did not change the objectives and responsibilities of 
the oversight government. Delivering growth and/or tax revenues have been the key 
priority of different levels of governments under China's political system of yard-
stick competition (Maskin, Qian, and Xu 2000; Li and Zhou 2005; Shih, Adolph, and  Liu 2012). Thus, the lower-level government, after taking over decentralized SOEs, 
would still strive for high growth rates and/or tax revenues, and try to improve its 
SOEs' performance in order to maintain good promotion prospects. An exception 
could be made with SOEs of strategic importance to the government. For them, the 
government might have different objectives that we shall consider later. 
China's decentralization featured a full transfer of both cash flow and control 
rights, which likely reduced the extent of agency costs. Like a decentralized western 
corporation, the decision-making authority in China's state sector moves down the 
hierarchy after decentralization. While the plant manager in a corporation, after del-
egation, may take sub-optimal actions at the cost of the firm (Alonso, Dessein, and  Matouschek 2008; Dessein 2002), China's SOE decentralization partly alleviated 
this problem. Because cash flow rights were also transferred to the local government 
after decentralization, the Chinese local government would partially internalize the 
costs and benefits of governing the decentralized SOEs. 
10 The complete delega-
tion in various rights is well-documented. State Council (1998), for instance, states 
that, "after decentralization, all rights regarding the SOE's finance, labor, wage, 
social welfare, and personnel are transferred to the local government; also trans-
ferred include state asset, liability, equity … further transferred are the loss and sub-
sidy quotas … ; after decentralization, all income taxes are … turned to local public 
finance." </p>

<p>9 Some provinces explicitly listed decentralization as an option. In Shandong province, the explicit reform meth-
ods were franchising, privatization, transfer, decentralization, merger and acquisition, and bankruptcy (Shandong  Government 2003). In Jiangxi province, decentralization was also listed as one of several reform methods (Jiangxi 
Government 2007). 
There were no strict geography-based rules but some broad guidelines about which level of government should 
be in charge of an SOE. In general, if an SOE is delegated, it would be under the oversight of the lower government 
of its location (e.g., Hubei Government 2003; Shaanxi Government 2005). 
10 To the extent that local government officials pursue pure private rents and that the delegated cash flow rights 
are not sufficient to induce efficient behavior, agency costs at the local government level remain. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>II. Conceptual Framework of Determinants of SOE Decentralization </p>

<p>Consider an economy with two layers of government, upper and lower. Either 
can have de facto control rights of SOEs, and whichever layer has the control rights 
benefits as follows. First, it obtains a significant share of the taxes that the SOE 
pays, such as the value added tax and the corporate income tax (Wong and Bird  2008). It also has discretion over the SOE's profit. Second, it has discretion over the 
SOE's strategic decisions such as preventing bankruptcies to maintain employment 
and social stability, a key criterion in evaluating local government officials. Third, it 
appoints personnel to key, well-paying positions in the SOE, which engenders rents. 
Oversight rights also entail costs in shouldering subsidies when the SOE takes a loss. 
What prompts the oversight government to decentralize? The immediate motive 
during our sample period was to turn around SOE performance. Over time, many 
SOEs had experienced declining profitability, which increased the cost of control. 
With less rent to share and more subsidies to shoulder, poorly-performing SOEs are 
likely to be decentralized first. </p>

<p>The Hayek Conjecture.-The literature, starting from Hayek (1945) and includ-
ing Aghion and Tirole (1997), suggests that one way to improve SOE performance 
is to take advantage of local information. When the government cares about effi-
ciency improvement, there is a tendency for the government to decentralize those 
SOEs in which the government has less local information. Hayek (1945, p. 524) is 
illustrative: </p>

<p>If we can agree that the economic problem of society is mainly one of rapid 
adaptation to changes in the particular circumstances of time and space, it 
would seem to follow that the ultimate decisions must be left to the people 
who are familiar with these circumstances, who know directly of the rele-
vant changes and of the sources immediately available to meet them. We 
cannot expect that this problem will be solved by first communicating all 
this knowledge to a central board, which, after integrating all knowledge, 
issues its orders. We must solve it by some form of decentralization. </p>

<p>How much the oversight government is privy to local information depends on 
the distance between the SOE and the government (Giroud 2013). With a shorter 
distance, the time-constrained official is more likely to have first-hand knowledge, 
or through denser social networks to hear, about how the SOE performs and whether 
the manager is diligent or competent. Realizing this, the manager is more likely to 
report honestly, which further improves the quality of knowledge received by the 
government (Alonso, Dessein, and Matouschek 2008). A shorter distance should 
then result in a higher likelihood of centralized control. In contrast, the greater 
the distance between the SOE and the oversight government, the larger the loss 
of useful (and truthful) local information critical for efficient allocation decisions, 
and the more likely the SOE is decentralized to preserve efficiency. Interestingly, 
Chinese governments were aware of this relationship between distance and need for 
decentralization. For instance, an SOE being "located far away" from the oversight 
government was explicitly listed as a reason to push forward its decentralization 
(Shandong Government 2003). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>Distance, nevertheless, is a crude measure of information asymmetry. Given 
the distance, the extent of information asymmetry depends on publicly available 
information and communication costs (Acemoglu et al. 2007; Bloom et al. 2014). 
Centralized control relies on information available to the principal, a good indicator 
of which is publicly available information about similar technologies. When the 
principal faces higher performance heterogeneity, firm-specific local information 
becomes more important and the oversight rights should be given to the government 
closer to the firm. The positive distance-decentralization link should thus be stronger 
for firms with greater firm-performance heterogeneity. Similarly, when communi-
cation costs between the SOE and its oversight government are higher, the principal 
faces more information asymmetry (Bloom, Sadun, and Van Reenen 2012; Garicano  2000; Giroud 2013). There is then a greater loss of information in communication 
between the principal and the agent. When communication costs are higher, the pos-
itive distance-decentralization link should thus be stronger. To summarize, our first 
key conjecture is as follows. </p>

<p>The Hayek Conjecture: When the government cares about efficiency 
improvement, the greater the physical distance between the SOE and the over-
sight government, the more likely the SOE is decentralized. Moreover, the 
positive distance-decentralization link should be stronger for SOEs with greater firm-
performance heterogeneity and facing higher communication costs. </p>

<p>The Commanding-Heights Conjecture.-Since many SOEs feature strategic con-
cerns and nonprofit objectives (Bai et al. 2000; Bardhan 2016), other noneconomic 
factors also shape SOE decentralization decisions. In 1922, Lenin proposed that the 
state should control the "commanding heights," or key segments of the economy. 
Many governments have since followed this philosophy, strengthening direct con-
trol of the economy, most notably during the period from the Great Depression to 
the collapse of the Soviet Union. Such governments included the Attlee Labour gov-
ernment in the United Kingdom, the de Gaulle government in France (both imme-
diately after World War II), as well as India, Germany, Korea, Japan, many Latin 
American countries, and of course, all socialist countries. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>The Chinese central government has always maintained a strong control of its 
commanding heights. Indeed, "national interests" have often been mentioned in 
Chinese government's documents about SOEs. In 2006, the State Council's docu-
ment on the reorganization of SOEs (State Council 2006) stated, "the state should 
maintain absolute control over important industries that are related to national secu-
rity and national economic growth." A priori, several features make strategic objec-
tives more salient for the central rather than for local governments. For example, 
relative to their local counterparts, central government officials have a longer tenure. 
While the central regime's legitimacy depends on popular support, local govern-
ment officials owe their appointment entirely to the upper government. Only the </p>

<p>11 Even earlier than the Soviet Union, Japan adopted the heavy-handed SOE-dominated industrialization strat-
egy and directly controlled the commanding heights in the Meiji Restoration period in the 1870s (Morck and 
Nakamura 2016), which quickly failed. The government then adopted laissez-faire policies that spurred its first 
industrialization from 1870s to 1920s. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>Table 1-Variable Descriptions </p>

<p>Firm-level and industry-level variables </p>

<p>Decentralized 
Dummy variable which equals to one if a firm's affiliation-level is changed to a lower 
level of the government, zero otherwise. Source: Annual Survey of Industrial Firms 
(ASIF). </p>

<p>Different city 
Dummy variable which equals to one if being located in a different city from the seat of 
the government with which it is affiliated, and zero otherwise. </p>

<p>Distance 
The logarithm of the physical distance (in kilometers) between the firm and the seat of 
the oversight government. Sources: ASIF and Geographic Information System. </p>

<p>Placebo distance 
Distance from Shanghai for central SOEs; distance from the largest non-capital city 
within the province for provincial SOEs, and distance from the largest non-municipal-
seat county-level city within the same municipality for municipal SOEs. Sources: ASIF 
and GIS. </p>

<p>Restructured 
Dummy variable equals to one if the state share falls below 30 percent or exit from the 
database. </p>

<p>Firm asset 
Log of firm asset. </p>

<p>ROS 
Ratio of before-tax profit on sales, winsorized at tail 0.5 percents. </p>

<p>TFP 
Total factor productivity (see online Appendix K for details). Three methods are used, 
including OLS, Olley-Pakes, and the index number. </p>

<p>Firm importance 
Ratio of the SOE's valued added to the total value added of the SOEs under the same 
oversight government. </p>

<p>Fully state-owned 
Dummy variable which equals to one if the state share in the firm's equity equals 100 
percent. </p>

<p>Average wage 
Log of the average wage (in thousand yuan) within the firm. </p>

<p>Industry-level HHI 
Herfindahl index at the three-digit industry level. </p>

<p>TFP dispersion 
Standard deviation of the firm's TFP in the three-digit-industry-year level. </p>

<p>ROS dispersion 
Standard deviation of the firm's ROS in the three-digit-industry-year level. </p>

<p>TFC 
Dummy variable equals to one if the firm was established during 1964-1966 or  1969-1971 in the Third Front Construction Area (see online Appendix I). </p>

<p>Fiscal, economic, and institutional variables at province, municipal, and county levels </p>

<p>Provincial (municipal, 
county) GDP per 
capita </p>

<p>Log of annual per capita GDP in the firm's province (municipality, or county), in con-
stant price of year 2000. Source: China Statistical Yearbooks (CSYs) (1998-2007). </p>

<p>Provincial state sector 
share </p>

<p>Share of SOE employment in total urban employment in the firm's province. Source: 
CSYs. </p>

<p>Provincial unemp. rate 
The annual urban unemployment rate in the firm's province. Source: CSYs. </p>

<p>Provincial (municipal, 
county) fiscal revenue 
per capita </p>

<p>Log of the annual fiscal revenue per capita in the firm's province (municipality and 
county), in constant price of year 2000. Sources: CSYs and Financial and Statistical 
Materials of Municipalities, Cities, and Counties (FSMPCCs) (1998-2007). </p>

<p>Provincial (municipal, 
county) fiscal 
autonomy </p>

<p>The ratio of fiscal revenue to fiscal expenditure in the firm's province (municipality and 
county). Source: CSYs and FSMPCCs. </p>

<p>Road mileage 
Road distance (in kilometers) per thousand people at the province level. Different levels 
of roads and railway mileage are translated into the equivalent of second-level road 
mileage according to transport capacity. Sources: CSYs and FSMPCCs. </p>

<p>Entertainment and 
travel cost </p>

<p>The average ratio of the firm's entertainment and travel cost to sales in a province. A 
higher value means more corruption. Source: World Bank Enterprises Survey for China, 
2005. </p>

<p>Corruption cases 
Graft cases filed per thousand people. Source: Procuratorial Yearbooks of China. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>central government cares about strategic issues such as ensuring a strong defense or 
cultivating "national champions" (Bardhan and Mookherjee 2000). 
The central government likely has a greater stake in controlling the strategic SOEs 
for which multiple objectives/tasks feature prominently. Indeed, when conflicts of 
interest between the principal and the agent become severe, the principal is less 
likely to delegate (Aghion and Tirole 1997). It then becomes important to directly 
control these SOEs in pursuit of the central government's objectives. Otherwise, 
decentralizing SOEs in these commanding-heights segments may result in the local 
government ignoring the central government's "strategic considerations" and ulti-
mately hurting the central government. For these strategic SOEs, efficiency and the 
force of local information thus become less important, and the balance tilts toward 
centralized control. </p>

<p>The Commanding-Heights Conjecture: The positive distance-decentralization 
link should be weaker for SOEs with strategic importance to the government, espe-
cially for those under central government control. </p>

<p>Agency Cost Considerations.-We have implicitly assumed that the Chinese gov-
ernment intended to improve SOE performance in decentralizing SOEs due to either 
fiscal reasons or other embedded incentives. Now we consider additional conjec-
tures presuming self-interested government officials. 
When the SOE-government distance is shorter, the rents from directly controlling 
the SOE are likely greater. Proximity magnifies the private benefits associated with 
being directly in charge, partly due to greater trust between the SOE and its over-
sight-government officials. As a result, the government wants to keep nearby SOEs, 
which lowers the chance of their decentralization. Moreover, when communication 
costs are higher, rent extraction from distant SOEs would be more difficult, and 
direct control of these distant SOEs becomes less enticing, resulting in a higher 
chance of decentralization for SOEs at a greater distance. Thus, the positive dis-
tance-decentralization link should be stronger for SOEs facing higher communica-
tion costs. Similarly, under the assumption of easier rent extraction in nearby SOEs, 
when SOE rents are higher, rent extraction from nearby SOEs is relatively more 
appealing, resulting in a stronger distance-decentralization link in high-rent envi-
ronments. We call these predictions the oversight agency conjecture. 
Because decentralization in general could not be refused by lower governments, 
lobbying for decentralization by lower governments was unlikely to be a key factor 
behind decentralization. However, we cannot rule it out. Moreover, prevailing lit-
erature worries about local capture. If lower-level governments (denoted as Lower 
here) can lobby for decentralization, what are the testable implications? 
In recent literature highlighting the specter of local capture (Bardhan 2002, 2016;  Mookherjee 2015), local governments are often presumed to be better able to col-
lude with the SOEs for personal rents. 
12 Presumably the ability to collude depends 
crucially on the distance. When the distance is short, collusion is more likely and 
sustainable. Physical proximity enables more interaction, trust, channels of mutual </p>

<p>12 Bardhan and Mookherjee (2000) offer instructive discussions of when local or national capture is more likely. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>influence, and ultimately, sustained collusion. The key factor in local capture is the 
SOE-Lower distance; where this distance is shorter, it is easier for Lower and the 
SOE manager to collude for rents. Lower thus lobbies for decentralization. As a 
result, decentralization becomes more likely with a shorter SOE-to-Lower distance. 
Moreover, when the SOE has abundant rents to share, Lower finds it more enticing 
to collude with the SOE, and is more motivated to lobby for decentralization. Thus, 
the negative relationship between decentralization and the distance to Lower should 
be more pronounced when the rents are higher. In sum, the local capture conjec-
ture predicts a negative link between decentralization and the distance to Lower, 
and a negative interaction term between the distance to Lower and proxies of rents. 
Interestingly, the Hayek conjecture also predicts a negative link between decentral-
ization and the distance to Lower: the efficiency gain is higher when the distance 
between the SOE and Lower is shorter. The Hayek conjecture, however, does not 
speak directly to the relationship between the decentralization-distance link and the 
rent environment. </p>

<p>Distinguishing Alternative Conjectures.-We examine the relevancy of the alter-
native conjectures by their ability to explain key empirical facts that we shall present 
later. Each has some unique predictions. First, only the Hayek conjecture predicts 
that the distance-decentralization link hinges on firm-performance heterogeneity. 
Second, only the commanding-heights conjecture predicts that the distance-decen-
tralization link should be weaker for central SOEs in strategic industries. Third, the 
oversight agency conjecture uniquely predicts a positive interaction term between 
rents and distance to the oversight government, while the local capture conjecture 
predicts a negative interaction term between rents and SOE-to-Lower distance. 
Overall, the conjecture that predicts better and that finds support for its unique pre-
diction(s) should be more relevant. Table 2 lists predicted signs of these conjectures 
to facilitate comparison. 
Aside from these empirical tests, two facts favor the Hayek conjecture over the 
oversight agency conjecture: Due to the prevalence of SOE losses in the mid-1990s, 
the main motive for decentralization then was to improve SOE performance; and 
local governments had strong motivation for growth or tax revenues. Similarly, the 
fact that decentralization decisions were made by the oversight government and 
could not be refused by lower governments reduces the plausibility of the local 
capture conjecture. </p>

<p>III. Basic Results </p>

<p>Our dataset is the Annual Survey of Industrial Firms (ASIF) from 1998 to 
2007. It includes all SOEs and all non-state firms with sales exceeding five mil-
lion yuan. Since we are only concerned with SOE decentralization, in our baseline 
regressions we only keep the SOE sample (defined as the share of state ownership 
exceeding 30 percent); we also drop all post-decentralization observations. 
13 The 
30 percent threshold is chosen because it indicates relative state control based on </p>

<p>13 We further drop the first year because decentralization needs two years' data to establish. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>available government documents. 
14 In alternative specifications when other SOE 
restructurings (apart from decentralizations) are considered jointly with decentral-
izations, we keep the sample up to the restructuring year. 
For our baseline regressions, we restrict the sample as follows. First, starting 
with 79,438 SOEs with non-missing oversight information, we drop those at the 
bottom of the hierarchy, i.e., those under county-or-below oversight governments 
(43,898 firms), which cannot be decentralized. Second, we drop SOEs without at 
least three continuous years of data (17,682 firms). This condition is imposed so as 
to take into account two periods of lagged information in determining decentraliza-
tion; that is, decentralization was likely determined based on more than one peri-
od's information. 
15 Finally, we drop SOEs whose oversight status changed and then 
reversed back within two years (312 firms), which likely represent coding errors. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Our final sample consists of 17,546 SOEs. See online Appendix A for details on 
various stages of the sample choice. 
Decentralization is defined to be one once an SOE experiences a change in its 
oversight status to a lower level; it remains one afterwards. Some may view this 
zero-one measure as inadequate, that is, its value of one may reflect a different 
extent of decentralization in various rights at each oversight level, and it may thus 
be more accurate to measure decentralization as a continuous variable. However, it 
is reasonable to adopt the zero-one measure in our context: decentralization in fact 
means a complete transfer of all cash flow and control rights for most SOEs, and the 
proportion of rights decentralized is largely close to one. 
In 1998, our initial sample year, the shares of SOEs under the oversight of the 
central, provincial, and municipal governments in all these SOEs are approximately </p>

<p>14 Several key government documents (State Asset Management Bureau and State Reform Commission 1994;  1997) state that there are two types of state control, namely, absolute control (i.e., state share exceeding 50 percent) 
and relative control (i.e., the state share between 30 percent and 50 percent, and being the largest shareholder). We 
do not classify ownership based on a firm's registered ownership type because some former SOEs do not change 
their registered ownership type even after ownership restructuring (Dollar and Wei 2007). We extensively check the 
sensitivity of our results to alternative definitions of state ownership later. 
15 Assuming that a change in the covariates will have an immediate effect on decentralization decisions, one 
can also include SOEs with only two years of consecutive observations and use once-lagged explanatory variables. 
We have conducted a sensitivity check as above, and we get similar results (see Table G-1 in the online Appendix). 
16 Retaining them does not change our key results. See a sensitivity check in Table G-1 in the online Appendix. </p>

<p>Table 2-Summary of Predictions from Key Hypotheses </p>

<p>Predictions from the hypotheses </p>

<p>Hayek 
information </p>

<p>Commanding 
heights </p>

<p>Oversight 
agency </p>

<p>Local 
capture </p>

<p>Distance to the oversight government (Dis OS-gov ) 
Positive </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Dis OS-gov × firm heterogeneity 
Positive </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Dis OS-gov × communication costs 
Positive </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Dis OS-gov × strategic industries × central government 
Negative </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Dis OS-gov × rents 
Positive </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Distance to lower government (Dis Lower ) 
Negative </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>YES </p>

<p>Dis Lower × rents 
Negative </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>Notes: YES: results consistent with predictions. NO: results inconsistent with predictions. Empty cell: no prediction. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>16 percent, 29 percent, and 55 percent, respectively. In total, 1,516 SOEs, or about 
9 percent of the sample, experienced decentralization. Among these decentralized 
SOEs, there are 455, 543, and 518 SOEs whose original oversight governments 
were the central, provincial, and municipal governments, respectively. </p>

<p>A. Specification </p>

<p>We estimate the following probit equation of the determinants of decentralization: </p>

<p>(1) Pr( Decen ijkt = 1) = Pr( Distance ik δ + X ijk,lag β + Z lag α + θ j + ρ k </p>

<p>+ γ t + ε ijkt &gt; 0). </p>

<p>Here, Pr means probability; Decen ijkt is a dummy variable that equals one when firm 
i in industry j under the oversight government k at year t is decentralized; Distance ik 
measures the logarithm of (one plus) the physical distance (in km) between firm i 
and the city in which the oversight government is located. 
17 The vector X includes 
lagged firm characteristics including the firm size (i.e., the logarithm of the firm 
assets), performance (i.e., returns on sales, or ROS), Firm Importance (i.e., the 
share of the firm's value added in the total value added of all manufacturing SOEs 
within the jurisdiction of the oversight government), and the dummy variable of full 
(i.e., 100 percent) state ownership. The vector Z lag measures lagged province-level 
variables: GDP per capita, unemployment rate, and share of SOEs in total urban 
employment. When computing the lag of a variable, we use the average of its once-
and twice-lagged values to take into account multiple periods' information. Besides 
the industry and the year dummies, we also control for the 363 dummy variables 
indicating the oversight government of the SOE to hold constant oversight-specific 
tendency to decentralize. 
18 To allow for correlation of the error term across time and 
space, we cluster the standard errors at the initial oversight government level. 
Since decentralization is mostly irreversible in our sample, we delete those obser-
vations after Decen has turned one. We consider the possibility of multiple decen-
tralizations per firm later. Our main parameter of interest is the marginal effect of 
Distance. Its estimate is based on comparison between SOEs with different dis-
tances to the original oversight government. </p>

<p>B. Baseline Results </p>

<p>We first compare the basic characteristics of decentralized and non-decentral-
ized SOEs using the data from the pre-decentralized periods (see Table B-3 in the 
online Appendix). 
19 Relative to the non-decentralized SOEs, the decentralized ones </p>

<p>17 We obtain the distance based on GIS. We do not have the exact longitude and latitude of the firm within a 
county (or district/county-level city), and use the county center in which the firm was located as the approximate 
location. 
18 That is, the central government, one of the 31 provincial governments, or one of the 331 municipal 
governments. 
19 Table 1 contains the definitions of the variables. Table B-2 in the online Appendix presents the means and the 
standard deviations for the key control variables. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>in their pre-decentralized years have a greater logarithm of the distance to the over-
sight government (4.2 versus 2.7), their average asset size is smaller, their profit-
ability and TFP are worse, their relative importance (i.e., Firm Importance) and the 
per capita GDP in their location are lower. Thus, the oversight government tends to 
decentralize SOEs that are far away, smaller, less important, and worse-performing. 
Columns 1 to 4 of panel A of Table 3 present the baseline probit results for all 
the SOEs, the central, the provincial, and the municipal SOEs, respectively. When 
examining decentralization by each oversight, we address the concern that the extent 
of decentralization at each oversight level could differ, in which case it is unclear 
if the decentralization dummy captures similar extent of delegation for SOEs under 
different oversight levels. We find that distance is robustly and positively correlated 
with decentralization whether using the full or the oversight-specific samples. Using 
the pooled sample estimates, increasing the distance by one standard deviation (SD, 
here 2.40) would increase the probability of decentralization by 1.3 percentage 
points, or 9 percent of the SD of the dependent variable. For the central, the pro-
vincial, and the municipal SOEs, increasing the distance by 1 SD (1.66, 1.74, and 
1.57) would increase the probability of decentralization by 0.78, 0.64, and 0.71 per-
centage points, or 4 percent, 4 percent, and 6 percent of the SD of the dependent 
variable. In addition, decentralization is more likely for smaller, poorly-performing, 
and less important firms (see column 1). </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Restructuring Options.-In our baseline estimation, we focus on decentraliza-
tion. But an SOE could face other restructuring options (including privatizations). </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>For those SOEs that were eventually restructured, some observations are left out of 
our previous estimation: in the case of SOEs being restructured but never decentral-
ized, all the restructuring years; in the case of SOEs being restructured after decen-
tralization, all the post-decentralization years. This could be problematic if ignoring 
simultaneous choices of decentralization and restructuring might bias the estimate 
of the distance effect. We thus examine whether our results hold when considering 
both decentralization and restructuring. 
We need to bear in mind that measuring privatizations with our data is difficult. 
An SOE's privatization is manifested in several ways: staying in the sample with the 
state share dropping sufficiently; becoming privatized but exiting the sample due to 
its sales being below five million yuan; going bankrupt and exiting the sample; and 
being merged with private firms and exiting the sample. The number of SOEs dis-
appearing from the sample ("exit") in the middle of the survey (7,183) far exceeds 
that experiencing explicit privatization (4,060). Because we cannot capture most 
privatizations, in this check we lump explicit privatizations with "exit" and call such 
SOEs Restructured. Because our objective is to understand decentralization and to </p>

<p>20 Another issue is whether the probit model is the right specification. Alternatively we could use the duration 
model since the structure of the outcome is {0, 0, … , 0} or {0, 0, … , 0, 1}. The literature has shown that the esti-
mates from a discrete-time binary-choice model converge to those obtained from a continuous-time duration model 
(Allison 1982). Thus not surprisingly, we reach qualitatively similar results in column 5 using the Cox proportional 
hazard model (see online Appendix D for further results using the hazard model). 
21 In the rest of this paper, restructuring means all restructuring options including privatization but excluding 
decentralizations. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>ensure the robustness of the distance-decentralization link, modeling all restructur-
ing options as thoroughly as possible is beyond the scope of this paper. 
In a given year an SOE faces three options: unchanged (base), decentralized, and 
Restructured. We use the multinomial logit framework. The incumbent government 
maximizes among the utility levels associated with all the options, and chooses the </p>

<p>Table 3-Determination of Decentralization </p>

<p>Probit 
Hazard 
Multinomial logit </p>

<p>Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Central 
SOEs </p>

<p>Provincial 
SOEs </p>

<p>Municipal 
SOEs 
Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Decentralized (t) 
Decentralized (t) Restructured (t) </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>Panel A. Baseline results 
Distance lag 
0.0054 
0.0047 
0.0037 
0.0044 
0.3059 
0.0053 
0.0011 
(0.0007) 
(0.0017) 
(0.0008) 
(0.0005) 
(0.0434) 
(0.0008) 
(0.0010) </p>

<p>log(firm asset lag ) 
−0.0029 −0.0049 
−0.0030 
−0.0017 
−0.1454 
−0.0025 
−0.0109 
(0.0005) 
(0.0009) 
(0.0010) 
(0.0009) 
(0.0320) 
(0.0006) 
(0.0011) </p>

<p>ROS lag 
−0.0102 −0.0171 
−0.0129 
−0.0044 
−0.5428 
−0.0074 
−0.0683 
(0.0015) 
(0.0065) 
(0.0029) 
(0.0017) 
(0.0801) 
(0.0015) 
(0.0065) </p>

<p>Firm importance lag 
−0.0466 −0.2243 
−0.1461 
−0.0248 
−2.5841 
−0.0399 
−0.0716 
(0.0203) 
(0.5033) 
(0.1049) 
(0.0152) 
(1.1532) 
(0.0187) 
(0.0200) </p>

<p>Fully state-owned lag 
−0.0069 −0.0129 
−0.0147 
0.0001 
−0.3387 
−0.0059 
−0.0264 
(0.0013) 
(0.0051) 
(0.0023) 
(0.0013) 
(0.0723) 
(0.0013) 
(0.0045) </p>

<p>GDP per capita lag 
0.0061 −0.0026 
−0.0094 
0.0620 
0.3009 
0.0045 
0.0007 
(0.0044) 
(0.0050) 
(0.0331) 
(0.0224) 
(0.2421) 
(0.0043) 
(0.0154) </p>

<p>State sector share lag 
−0.0062 −0.0958 
0.0765 
0.0620 
−0.2776 
−0.0140 
0.2086 
(0.0309) 
(0.0239) 
(0.0625) 
(0.0470) 
(1.6584) 
(0.0270) 
(0.1069) </p>

<p>Unemployment rate lag 
−0.1128 
0.2042 
−0.1744 
−0.1104 
−7.2925 
−0.0558 
−0.8459 
(0.1100) 
(0.2195) 
(0.4464) 
(0.2980) 
(7.1847) 
(0.1222) 
(0.4227) </p>

<p>Government, year, and 
industry dummy </p>

<p>YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
69,785 
11,171 
20,356 
38,258 
69,785 
83,700 
83,700 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.115 
0.085 
0.111 
0.189 
0.077 </p>

<p>Central 
SOEs </p>

<p>Provincial 
SOEs </p>

<p>Municipal 
SOEs </p>

<p>Full state 
ownership </p>

<p>Partial state 
ownership </p>

<p>Panel B. Robustness checks: probit 
Distance lag 
0.0045 
0.0025 
0.0047 
0.0062 
0.0046 
(0.0017) 
(0.0010) 
(0.0006) 
(0.0008) 
(0.0014) </p>

<p>Controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Additional controls 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
11,171 
19,562 
32,974 
54,161 
15,624 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.086 
0.116 
0.194 
0.113 
0.143 </p>

<p>Notes: Standard errors clustered at the oversight-government level are reported in the parentheses. Columns 1−4 of 
panel A report the marginal effect from the probit regressions. Column 5 reports the results from a Cox proportional 
hazard model. Columns 6-7 report results from a multinomial logit (MLogit) model: for each firm in year t, there 
are three possible outcomes, with "neither restructured nor decentralized" being the base. The two columns report 
the marginal effect of each explanatory variable on the probability of being Decentralized and being Restructured, 
respectively. When computing the lag of a variable, we use the average of its once-and twice-lagged values to take 
into account multiple periods' information. The samples used in the probit and MLogit specifications differ in two 
ways. First, for those eventually-restructured SOEs, the MLogit model contains observations in their first year after 
restructuring, while the probit model does not. Second, the MLogit model also includes the post-decentralization 
years for the central and provincial SOEs, because once decentralized, they still face the choice of being further 
decentralized (and being restructured). Panel B performs robustness checks using the probit model. Columns 1-3 
are the results for the subsamples of the central, the provincial, and the municipal SOEs, respectively, with addi-
tional controls for per capita GDP, fiscal revenue, and fiscal autonomy of both the incumbent oversight government 
and the lower-level government. Columns 4-5 use the subsamples of fully state-owned and of partially-privatized 
SOEs, respectively. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>optimal one. For this exercise we keep the post-decentralization observations and 
expand the sample up to the restructuring years for the SOEs that were eventually 
restructured during the sample years. </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>The results are in columns 6 and 7 of panel A of Table 3. 
23 The coefficient of log 
distance remains positive and statistically significant, with a marginal effect on the 
probability of decentralization of 0.0053, similar to our baseline estimate. Our result 
on the distance-decentralization link thus remains robust. In contrast, the distance 
coefficient for Restructured is small and statistically insignificant. </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>A related check is to delete those SOEs that were eventually restructured. Now 
the choices are "no change" and "decentralization." We re-estimate the base specifi-
cation using this smaller sample, and the coefficient of log distance remains positive 
and statistically significant (see Table E-2 in online Appendix E). </p>

<p>Omitted Variables.-In columns 1 to 3 of panel B of Table 3, we deal with the 
concern that the estimates may be affected by the omitted circumstances faced by 
both the original and the lower governments. To address this, we examine decen-
tralization by each oversight and include additional controls that may affect decen-
tralizations: fiscal revenue per capita, GDP per capita, and fiscal autonomy (i.e., 
the ratio of fiscal revenues to fiscal expenditures). For the provincial and municipal 
SOEs, we add these controls for both the original oversight government and the 
lower government. For the central government, we only add these controls at the 
lower government level. 
25 The results on distance remain similar. </p>

<p>Full versus Partial SOEs.-Columns 4 and 5 of panel B of Table 3 distinguish the 
case of full (i.e., 100 percent) and of partial (i.e., 30-99 percent) state ownership. 
In the case of partial state ownership, there are other corporate governance mecha-
nisms to obtain information, and the direct information available to the government 
that is captured by distance is thus less important. We therefore expect a weaker 
distance-decentralization link under partial state ownership. That is confirmed: the 
coefficient is larger in full than in partial SOEs. </p>

<p>Additional Checks.-First, we consider various ways to define an SOE: using the 
50 percent threshold of state ownership (i.e., absolute state control), or using the 
definition of Brandt, Van Biesebroeck, and Zhang (2012), or that of Hsieh and Song  (2015) (see online Appendix F). Second, we add back the 312 SOEs whose over-
sight status changed and then immediately reverted back within two years. Third, 
we keep post-decentralization observations, which allow us to add 26 SOEs with a 
second decentralization. Fourth, we loosen the requirement of having at least three </p>

<p>22 An exception is municipal SOEs, which drop out of the sample after decentralization. This is because after 
decentralization, the municipal SOEs become county SOEs, and no longer face the same three options as other 
SOEs (i.e., they cannot be further decentralized). 
23 Again, we report marginal effects on the probability of each option. 
24 The distance-decentralization result remains robust when we split the Restructured option into Explicit 
Privatization (i.e., when the state share falls below 30 percent), and Exit (i.e., when the firm exits the sample). 
We again find a positive and statistically significant effect of distance on decentralization, and no effect on either 
Explicit Privatization or Exit (see Table E-1 in online Appendix E). 
25 For the central SOEs sample, we do not include these additional variables for the original oversight government 
because there is only one central government, and these additional variables would be perfectly collinear with the 
year dummies, which we have already controlled for. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>consecutive years of data for an SOE, and require only two years of consecutive 
observations and use once-lagged covariates (see Table G-1 of online Appendix G). 
In all the checks, our key results remain robust. </p>

<p>Centralization.-Some SOEs also experienced centralization (i.e., the over-
sight status changing to a higher level). Does the distance matter symmetrically 
in determining centralization as in determining decentralization? To see this, we 
define centralization to be one (and stay so) after the oversight status changing 
into a higher-level government, and zero otherwise. We then modify the sample 
by dropping central SOEs, which cannot be centralized further, and adding the 
20,273 county SOEs, 
26 which can be centralized. A much smaller share of SOEs 
experienced centralization than decentralization: among the provincial and munici-
pal SOEs, 2 percent experienced centralization; among the county SOEs, 3.5 percent 
did. For centralization, the key distance measure is that to the upper government, 
which captures informational gains from centralization. 
In online Appendix H, we estimate the centralization equation with the baseline 
covariates. The results are symmetric to the case of decentralization: SOEs located 
closer to the upper government are more likely to be centralized. The magnitude of 
this distance measure (in absolute value) is significantly smaller than in column 1 of 
Table 3 with respect to decentralizations. </p>

<p>C. Agglomeration and Endogeneity </p>

<p>Agglomeration.-In China, political and economic centers overlap. Beijing is 
also a key agglomeration center, and a provincial capital is usually the largest city 
in the province. The distance to the oversight government could then reflect the dis-
tance to an economic center. A priori the proximity to economic centers matters for 
SOE decentralization because such SOEs are more viable thanks to this geograph-
ical advantage, and retaining control of them might be beneficial to the oversight 
government. If this concern is valid, the distance between an SOE and the other 
agglomeration center in the oversight region should also have a positive association 
with decentralization. 
To verify, we create a placebo distance measure (Placebo Distance). For central 
SOEs, Placebo Distance is the distance to Shanghai, the other agglomeration center 
on par with Beijing. For noncentral SOEs, Placebo Distance is to the largest non-
capital city within the jurisdiction. We then re-run our baseline regressions using 
Placebo Distance to replace the distance variable. If its coefficient is positive and 
statistically significant, we might worry that our distance variable may simply cap-
ture economic agglomeration. Reassuringly, the results in column 1 of Table 4 show 
that the coefficient of Placebo Distance is statistically insignificant and only about 
one-eleventh the size of the coefficients in Table 3. 
We also consider the possibility that the "other largest city" could be far smaller 
than the capital city. We repeat the exercise using the subsample that excludes the 
regions whose capital city's GDP is more than 50 percent larger than that of the </p>

<p>26 Again we impose the restriction of three years of consecutive observations. See Table A-2 for the evolution of 
sample with various restrictions by oversight level. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>second largest city. The results in column 2 of Table 4 remain similar. Thus, our 
result on the positive distance-decentralization link does not reflect the agglomera-
tion effect. </p>

<p>Endogeneity.-Although we have controlled for many variables that capture key 
confounding factors, such as the SOE's importance and lagged firm performance, 
the distance may still capture something other than the quality of information. The 
distance could then be endogenous: unimportant or less profitable SOEs may be 
located further away. 
To deal with endogeneity, we rely on an instrumental variable (IV) that captures 
exogenous variations in the SOE-government distance. We take advantage of the 
fact that, being worried about potential wars with the United States and the Soviet 
Union during the 1960s and 1970s, China relocated many SOEs to her hinterland. 
This migration of firms is called the Third Front Construction program (TFC, see 
online Appendix I), which covered a large area in China. The relocation sites were 
chosen to be far away from external threats. It is implausible that, other than through 
the channel of the distance to the government, the TFC affiliation would affect SOE 
decentralization three to four decades later-after all, China's central leadership 
had changed several times, and the new leaders had distinct objectives. Because 
TFC covered 13 provinces and 5.9 percent of firms in our sample, this instrument 
is likely a relevant one. We thus construct a dummy variable TFC, which is one if a 
firm was established during the TFC period (i.e., 1964-1966 and 1969-1971) and 
in the TFC regions. </p>

<p>Table 4-Determinants of Decentralization: Placebo Test and Third Front Construction as IV </p>

<p>Placebo test 
2SLS </p>

<p>Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Excluding small 
placebo city </p>

<p>First stage 
Distance </p>

<p>Second stage 
Decentralized (t) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Placebo distance lag 
0.0005 
0.0002 
(0.0009) 
(0.0012) 
Distance lag 
0.0240 
(0.0124) 
TFC 
0.2416 
(0.1018) 
Controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
69,785 
56,742 
69,785 
69,785 </p>

<p>Kleibergen-Paap F-statistic 
5.627 </p>

<p>Anderson-Rubin F-statistic 
3.83 </p>

<p>( p-value) 
(0.0504) 
90 percent confidence interval 
[0.0050, 0.0537] </p>

<p>Notes: Standard errors clustered at the oversight-government level are reported in the parentheses. Columns 1-2 
report results on placebo distance using the probit model. Placebo distance is defined as the distance from Shanghai 
for the central SOEs, the distance from the largest city within the province (except for the provincial capital) for pro-
vincial SOEs, and the distance from the largest county-level city within the municipality (except for the municipal 
seat) for municipal SOEs. Column 2 excludes the provincial and municipal SOEs located in the same jurisdiction 
with the jurisdictional capital as the sole agglomeration city. Columns 3-4 report results using TFC as the instru-
ment. Column 3 reports the first stage results. Column 4 reports the linear probability IV estimates (i.e., 2SLS) and 
the associated test statistics. The control variables are the same as in Table 3. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>A key concern for a valid IV is that it is correlated with the unobserved factors 
behind the outcome. One way to shed light on (but not prove) the excludability is to 
examine if the IV is related to other known determinants of the outcome in sensible 
ways (Altonji, Elder, and Taber 2005). To see this, we regress TFC on other covari-
ates in the decentralization decision (see Table J-1 of online Appendix J). The coef-
ficients of the firm size, full state ownership, and income are statistically significant, 
not surprisingly since we know that TFC moved larger SOEs to inland (and thus 
lower-income) regions. In contrast, the coefficients of the key current determinants 
of decentralization, profitability, and Firm Importance, are statistically insignificant. 
These results, along with the historical origin of TFC, suggest that TFC is indeed 
likely excludable. 
Columns 3 to 4 of Table 4 report the IV regression results based on the 2SLS 
specification. 
27 Our IV seems to be relevant. In the first stage (column 3), TFC has a 
positive and statistically significant effect on the distance: a TFC affiliation increases 
the SOE-oversight-government distance by 24 log points. Moreover, based on the 
Anderson-Rubin test under the 2SLS model with the clustered standard errors (col-
umn 4), which provide valid inference on the coefficient of the endogenous variable 
even in the presence of a weak instrument (Finlay and Magnusson 2009), the test 
statistic is significantly different from zero with a p-value of 0.0504. The 90 percent 
confidence interval is [0.005, 0.054], suggesting that the coefficient of distance is 
positive and statistically significant even if the IV is weak. 
In the second-stage, the coefficient of distance remains positive and statistically 
significant. Once corrected for endogeneity, the distance's coefficient increases from 
0.0054 to 0.024. The larger magnitude of the IV estimate relative to the OLS/pro-
bit estimate likely reflects the endogeneity bias associated with the latter. In online 
Appendix J, we examine whether the difference in the magnitudes could reflect 
special characteristics of the complier group since the IV estimate reflects the local 
average treatment effect of that group (Angrist and Pischke 2009). We show that the 
compliers group (i.e., the SOEs that change their distance statuses due to the switch 
on TFC) is a small share of the population, but the distributions of the characteristics 
of the complier group and the population are similar (Table J-2). These two findings 
offer cautious optimism about extending the IV estimate to the population. </p>

<p>IV. Distinguishing between Alternative Hypotheses </p>

<p>Now we try to distinguish between the alternative hypotheses about decentral-
ization by allowing the distance-decentralization link to depend on communication 
costs, firm-performance heterogeneity, and rents. </p>

<p>Measurements.-We proxy communication costs by the provincial road mileage 
per capita. We proxy firm-performance heterogeneity by measures of the dispersion 
of firm performance within the firm's industry-year cell. Since we use three methods 
to compute TFP (i.e., the OLS production function, the Olley-Pakes, and the index 
function methods; see online Appendix K), we present three sets of results when we </p>

<p>27 The results based on the IV-probit specification are qualitatively similar to the 2SLS results. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>interact the distance with the TFP dispersion. In addition, we also present the disper-
sion in return on sales (ROS, that is, before-tax profit over sales), a more transparent 
and intuitive measure. </p>

<p>Communication Costs.-Based on columns 1 and 2 in panel A of Table 5, the 
effect of distance on decentralization is statistically significantly higher when 
the road density is lower. 
28 Increasing the road density at the mean by one SD is 
associated with a reduction in </p>

<p>∂ Decen </p>

<p>______ </p>

<p>∂ Distance </p>

<p>by 28 percent. This supports both the Hayek 
and the oversight agency conjectures (see Table 2). </p>

<p>Firm-Performance Heterogeneity.-Relative to the other conjectures, the Hayek 
conjecture increases its appeal once considering the interaction of the distance with 
firm-performance heterogeneity. The results in columns 3 to 6 show robustly that the 
distance-decentralization link is significantly stronger when firm-performance het-
erogeneity is greater. Based on the estimates, increasing the dispersion of industry 
TFP (by the Olley-Pakes method) by one SD at the mean would increase </p>

<p>∂ Decen </p>

<p>______ </p>

<p>∂ Distance </p>

<p>by 23 percent, a large effect. This confirms a unique prediction of the Hayek con-
jecture (see Table 2). </p>

<p>The Commanding-Heights Conjecture.-To capture strategic concerns for certain 
types of SOEs, we first construct a subsample of strategic industries (denoted as 
Strategic Industries I (or II), see online Appendix L for details). We then interact the 
distance measure with the Strategic Industries I (or II) dummy, and re-estimate the 
baseline model with the pooled sample and by oversight. 
Consistent with the commanding-heights conjecture, the coefficient of the inter-
action term between Strategic Industries I and distance is negative and statistically 
significant for central SOEs (panel B of Table 5). In contrast, it is statistically insig-
nificant for the noncentral SOEs. 
29 The result is robust with Strategic Industries II. 
Also consistent with the commanding-heights conjecture, the share of SOEs that 
were decentralized is higher for the non-strategic than for the strategic SOEs among 
those under the central government oversight: 16.7 percent (17.4 percent) versus 
11.0 percent (12.1 percent) under Strategic Industries I (II). 
When relying on the Strategic Industry I definition, the group of central strategic 
SOEs, 490 in 1998 and 407 in 2007, represents a nontrivial share of the Chinese 
industrial economy. Their relative importance in the sample industrial firms had 
dropped from 1998 to 2007 (see Table L-1): in terms of the share in the total number 
of firms, from 0.3 percent to 0.1 percent; 
30 in terms of the share in the total number 
of employees, from 2.5 percent to 1.3 percent; in terms of the total value added, 
from 6.2 percent to 4.4 percent. </p>

<p>31 </p>

<p>28 Columns 1 and 2 use the lagged road density and the road density in 1998 to see if the result is sensitive to 
the lagging structure of the road density. 
29 Result on provincial and municipal SOEs separately are similar and available upon request. 
30 This is based on calculation from our sample, that is, it excludes non-SOE firms with sales below five million 
yuan. So the share can be roughly viewed as in large and medium industrial firms. See Table L-1 for these statistics. 
31 The relative importance of the central strategic SOEs in the sample SOEs, however, had increased significantly 
from 1998 to 2007: in terms of the share in the total number of SOEs, from 0.9 percent to 3.0 percent; in terms of 
the share in the total number of employees, from 4.7 percent to 8.9 percent; in terms of the total value added, from 
14.1 percent to 23.5 percent. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts  Vol. 107 no. 8   Rents.-To further shed light on the various conjectures, we interact the distance 
with the two proxies of rents: the local corruption level and the firm-level rents. To 
accommodate all the conjectures, we use two distance measures: that between the SOE </p>

<p>Table 5-Determinants of Decentralization: Testing Alternative Hypotheses </p>

<p>Province 
road 
mileages lag </p>

<p>Province 
road 
mileages 1998 </p>

<p>ROS 
dispersion lag </p>

<p>TFP OLS 
dispersion lag </p>

<p>TFP 
Olley-Pakes 
dispersion lag </p>

<p>TFP Index 
Number 
dispersion lag 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Panel A. Key indicators of communication costs or firm performance heterogeneity 
Distance lag 
0.0086 
0.0077 
0.0032 
0.0016 
−0.0021 
0.0009 
(0.0010) 
(0.0011) 
(0.0009) 
(0.0019) 
(0.0020) 
(0.0018) </p>

<p>Distance lag × Key indicators 
−0.0021 
−0.0017 
0.0117 
0.0026 
0.0048 
0.0032 
(0.0004) 
(0.0006) 
(0.0045) 
(0.0011) 
(0.0012) 
(0.0011) </p>

<p>Key indicators 
0.0132 
0.0113 
−0.0654 
−0.0116 
−0.0152 
−0.0141 
(0.0033) 
(0.0040) 
(0.0277) 
(0.0059) 
(0.0066) 
(0.0061) </p>

<p>Controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
69,785 
69,785 
69,785 
69,784 
61,660 
69,784 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.118 
0.116 
0.116 
0.116 
0.114 
0.116 </p>

<p>Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Central 
SOE </p>

<p>Provincial &amp; 
Municipal SOE </p>

<p>Whole 
sample </p>

<p>Central 
SOE </p>

<p>Provincial &amp; 
Municipal SOE 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Panel B. Interactions of distance with strategic industries 
Distance lag 
0.0055 
0.0048 
0.0046 
0.0056 
0.0056 
0.0046 
(0.0007) 
(0.0017) 
(0.0005) 
(0.0006) 
(0.0017) 
(0.0005) </p>

<p>Strategic industries I 
× Distance lag 
−0.0011 
−0.0047 
0.0008 
(0.0007) 
(0.0016) 
(0.0011) </p>

<p>Strategic industries II 
× Distance lag 
−0.0011 
−0.0052 
0.0002 
(0.0006) 
(0.0018) 
(0.0007) </p>

<p>Controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
69,785 
11,171 
58,614 
69,785 
11,171 
58,614 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.116 
0.088 
0.135 
0.115 
0.087 
0.134 </p>

<p>Key indicators of corruption 
being: </p>

<p>Key indicators of firm rents 
being: </p>

<p>Entertainment 
and travel cost </p>

<p>Corruption 
cases lag </p>

<p>Firm 
ROS lag </p>

<p>Firm average 
wage lag </p>

<p>Industry-level 
HHI lag </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Panel C 
Distance to oversight gov lag 
0.0055 
0.0082 
0.0048 
0.0054 
0.0060 
0.0056 
(0.0007) 
(0.0022) 
(0.0016) 
(0.0006) 
(0.0011) 
(0.0006) </p>

<p>Distance to oversight gov lag 
× Key indicators 
−0.2031 
0.0140 
−0.0074 
−0.0002 
−0.0082 
(0.1520) 
(0.0465) 
(0.0033) 
(0.0005) 
(0.0229) </p>

<p>Distance to Lower gov lag 
−0.0010 
0.0006 
0.0009 
−0.0010 
−0.0011 
−0.0011 
(0.0004) 
(0.0012) 
(0.0022) 
(0.0003) 
(0.0010) 
(0.0006) </p>

<p>Distance to Lower gov lag 
× Key indicators 
−0.1177 
−0.0608 
−0.0008 
−0.0001 
0.0024 
(0.0753) 
(0.0620) 
(0.0009) 
(0.0004) 
(0.0305) </p>

<p>Key indicators 
2.1216 
−0.0647 
0.0002 
−0.0032 
0.0586 
(0.9606) 
(0.3534) 
(0.0011) 
(0.0021) 
(0.0591) </p>

<p>Controls 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES </p>

<p>Observations 
69,785 
69,785 
66,173 
69,785 
69,157 
69,785 </p>

<p>Pseudo R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.116 
0.116 
0.117 
0.116 
0.117 
0.116 </p>

<p>Notes: Standard errors clustered at the oversight-government level are reported in the parentheses. This table reports 
the marginal effect from probit regressions. The control variables are the same as in Table 3. In panel B, Strategic 
industries I includes (i) oil and gas, petroleum; (ii) nuclear fuel, aviation and aerospace, arms and ammunition; (iii) 
electricity, heat, gas, and water supply. Strategic industries II includes: Strategic industries I, plus (iv) automobile, 
locomotive, and ship. See online Appendix L for details about the construction of strategic industries. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>

<p>and the oversight government, which is needed for the oversight agency conjecture; or 
that between the SOE and the lower government, which is needed for the local capture 
conjecture. We choose two proxies for corruption: the number of graft cases filed per 
thousand people (similar to Aghion et al. 2016); and the provincial share of enter-
tainment and traveling costs over sales, which has been shown to be a good proxy for 
corruption at the local level (Cai, Fang, and Xu 2011). 
32 We proxy the firm-level rents 
with the firm's profitability, its average wage level, and its market power (as measured 
by the Herfindahl index at its three-digit industry). The results are in panel C of Table 5. 
The results are against both the oversight agency and the local capture conjectures. 
In column 1, the coefficient of the distance to the oversight government is positive and 
statistically significant, consistent with both the Hayek and the oversight agency cost 
conjectures. The coefficient of the distance to the lower-level government is negative 
and statistically significant, consistent with both the Hayek and the local capture con-
jectures. However, in nine out of the ten columns, the coefficients of the interaction 
terms between the proxies of rents and the two distance measures are statistically insig-
nificant, inconsistent with both the oversight agency and the local capture conjectures. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Overall Plausibility.-Table 2 shows the match of the empirical results and the 
predictions from the conjectures. Among all the facts to be explained, the Hayek 
conjecture appears to explain the most about decentralization for the vast majority 
of the SOEs. The commanding-heights conjecture contributes to understanding cen-
tral SOEs in strategic industries. Some key predictions of the oversight agency and 
the local capture conjectures are not confirmed empirically. </p>

<p>V. Conclusions </p>

<p>China's decentralization of SOEs provides a unique opportunity to test the impli-
cations of Hayek's insight on the importance of local information for designing eco-
nomic systems. As the quote from Hayek suggests, when a society experiences rapid 
changes, the ultimate decisions should be left to those familiar with the particular 
circumstances, and "some form of decentralization" is needed. Indeed, we find that 
a larger information asymmetry between the SOE and the original oversight govern-
ment, as proxied by their physical distance, is associated with a greater likelihood 
of decentralization. Moreover, the positive effect of distance on decentralization is 
larger where SOE performance is more heterogeneous and the communication costs 
are higher. Our findings suggest that Hayek's insight on local information is indeed a 
key for understanding both the organization of firms and the working of economic sys-
tems. Our findings also suggest that when the central government decides to control 
the commanding heights, the Hayek conjecture loses much of its explanatory power. 
This group of commanding-heights SOEs represented about 5 percent of industrial </p>

<p>32 See Table 1 for definition. Some may question whether the provincial proxy of corruption would work for 
the central SOEs. We do not think this is an issue because the central SOEs are physically located in their specific 
provinces, and their rent-seeking tendency would be influenced by the local norms of corruption (Fisman and  Miguel 2007). We have tried dropping the central SOEs to ensure our proxy of local corruption is accurate, and the 
key results remain similar. 
33 The negative and statistically significant coefficient of the interaction term between the distance to the over-
sight government and lagged firm ROS is in fact opposite to what the oversight agency conjecture predicts. </p>

<p> 
huang et al.: hayek, local InformatIon, and commandIng heIghts 
Vol. 107 no. 8 </p>

<p>output in China. The Chinese experience of managing its SOEs thus demonstrates 
the dual goals of the government: efficiency and controlling commanding heights. We 
also consider, but do not find strong support for, the agency-costs-based explanations. </p>





<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
AugusT 2017 </p>



</text></tei>