<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.15.4.29" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A </p>

<p>regression model is censored when the recorded data on the dependent 
variable cuts off outside a certain range with multiple observations at the 
endpoints of that range. When the data are censored, variation in the 
observed dependent variable will understate the effect of the regressors on the 
"true" dependent variable. As a result, standard ordinary least squares regression 
using censored data will typically result in coefficient estimates that are biased 
toward zero. 
Traditional statistical analysis uses maximum likelihood or related procedures 
to deal with the problem of censored data. However, the validity of such methods 
requires correct specification of the error distribution, which can be problematic in 
practice. In the past two decades, a number of semiparametric alternatives for 
dealing with censored data have been proposed. In a semiparametric approach, 
part of the functional form of the model-usually the regression function-is 
parametrically specified by the researcher based upon plausible assumptions, while 
the rest of the model is not parameterized. 
1 While the theoretical literature has 
produced several semiparametric estimators for the censored data model, pub-
lished applications of these estimators to empirical problems in economics have 
lagged far behind. 
This paper reviews the intuition and computation of a handful of semipara-
metric estimators proposed for the censored regression model. The various esti-
mators are used to examine changes in black-white earnings inequality during the </p>

<p>1 In this issue, the paper by DiNardo and Tobias offers further discussion of nonparametric and 
semiparametric analysis. </p>

<p>1960s, around the time of the passage of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, based on 
longitudinal Social Security Administration (SSA) earnings records. These earnings 
records are censored at the taxable maximum; that is, anyone earning more than 
the maximum that was taxable under Social Security is recorded as having earned 
at the maximum. Thus, above the maximum, the data on earnings do not accu-
rately reflect actual earnings. Ordinary least squares analysis of these data implies 
little convergence in the earnings of black and white workers during the 1960s. On 
the other hand, the estimates from the semiparametric models that account for 
censoring suggest that significant black-white earnings convergence did occur after 
1964. Comparisons of the results from parametric and semiparametric procedures 
help pinpoint sources of misspecification in the parametric approach. </p>

<p>Censored Regression Models and Estimators </p>

<p>The Social Security Administration data set that we analyze suffers from the 
simplest form of data censoring, interval censoring, for which the values of the "true" 
dependent variable, y*, are observed only if they fall within some known, often 
one-sided, interval [a, b]. Otherwise, the closest endpoint of the interval is ob-
served instead of y*. Tobin (1958) used this model to analyze consumer expendi-
tures on automobiles, with a ϭ 0 and b ϭ ϱ, and economists generally refer to 
regression models with nonnegativity constraints as Tobit models. Other typical 
applications of these censored regression models are to right-censored data, where 
a ϭ Ϫϱ and b represents a maximum recordable value for the dependent variable. 
Such models arise for top-coded data, where sufficiently large values of the true 
variable y* are recorded as "at least equal to b." In our primary empirical applica-
tion, the dependent variable, the logarithm of annual earnings, is "top-coded," or 
censored from above, with b equal to the logarithm of the maximum annual 
earnings subject to Social Security taxes in a given year. 
Algebraically, the model for the observed dependent variable y under interval 
censoring is </p>

<p>y ϭ ͭ </p>

<p>a 
if xЈ␤ ϩ Ͻ a, 
b 
if xЈ␤ ϩ Ͼ b, 
xЈ␤ ϩ otherwise, </p>

<p>where y is the observed value of the dependent variable, x is a vector of observed 
explanatory variables, ␤ is a vector of unknown regression coefficients to be 
estimated, is an unobserved error term, and a and b are the censoring interval 
endpoints. While the true dependent variable y* satisfies a standard linear regres-
sion model, the observed variable y clearly does not when y* lies outside [a, b]. 
Because y does not vary with the regressors x when it is censored (unlike the true </p>



<p>variable y*), standard least squares regression will underestimate the magnitude of 
the regression slope coefficients. 
If the distribution of the error terms given the regressors has a known 
parametric form-for example, normally distributed and homoskedastic errors-it 
is straightforward to derive and maximize the likelihood function. This provides a 
consistent and approximately normal estimator of the regression coefficients ␤ 
(see, for example, Amemiya, 1985, chapter 10). However, in many empirical 
problems, the distribution of the errors is not known or is subject to heteroskedas-
ticity of unknown form. In such cases, the maximum likelihood estimator will not 
provide a consistent estimate (Goldberger, 1983; Arabmazar and Schmidt, 1981, 
1982). Also, for censored panel data with fixed effects-that is, censored data with 
repeated observations on individuals over time and intercept terms that are allowed 
to vary freely across individuals-maximum likelihood estimation methods will 
generally be inconsistent even when the parametric form of the conditional error 
distribution is correctly specified (Honoré, 1992). 
Thus, it is important to develop estimation methods that provide consistent 
estimates for censored data even when the error distribution is nonnormal or 
heteroskedastic. Here, we focus on describing three particular semiparametric 
estimators for the censored regression model, with acronyms CLAD, SCLS and 
ICLAD. All three estimators can be computed by alternating between a "recensor-
ing" step, in which the data are "trimmed" (using the current parameter estimates) 
to compensate for the censoring problem, and a "regression" step using the 
trimmed data to obtain coefficient estimates. More complete algebraic derivations 
and discussions of the various alternatives are available in Powell (1994, section 
5.3). Further details on large-sample properties and standard error formulae can be 
found in the cited references. 
The censored least absolute deviations (CLAD) estimation method was proposed 
by Powell (1984). For the linear model, the method of least absolute deviations 
obtains regression coefficient estimates by minimizing the sum of absolute residu-
als. It is a generalization of the sample median to the regression context just as least 
squares is a generalization of the sample mean to the linear model. If the true 
dependent variable y* were observed, then its median would be the regression 
function xЈ␤ under the condition that the errors have a zero median. Least 
absolute deviations could then be used to estimate the unknown coefficients. 
When the dependent variable y is censored, its median is unaffected by the 
censoring if the regression function xЈ␤ is in the uncensored region (that is, if xЈ␤ 
is in the interval [a, b]). However, if the regression function xЈ␤ is below the lower 
threshold a (or above the upper threshold b), then more than 50 percent of the 
distribution will "pile up" at a (or b). In this case, the median of y is that interval 
endpoint, which does not depend on xЈ␤. Thus, computation of the CLAD esti-
mator alternates between deleting observations with estimates of the regression 
function xЈ␤ that are outside the uncensored region [a, b] (the "recensoring" step) 
and estimating the regression coefficients by applying least absolute deviations to </p>

<p>Kenneth Y. Chay and James L. Powell 31 </p>

<p>the remaining observations (the "regression" step), as described by Buchinsky 
(1994). </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>The symmetrically censored least squares (SCLS) estimation method, proposed by 
Powell (1986b), is based on a "symmetric trimming" idea. For simplicity, suppose 
that a ϭ Ϫϱ, so that the data are "top-coded" at b (as in our empirical application), 
and assume that the true dependent variable y* is symmetrically distributed around 
the regression function xЈ␤. Due to the censoring, the observed dependent vari-
able y has an asymmetric distribution, since its upper tail is "piled up" at the 
censoring point b. This situation is illustrated in Figure 1. However, symmetry can 
be restored by "symmetrically censoring" the dependent variable y from below at 
the point 2xЈ␤ Ϫ b. Now the regression function is equidistant from both censor-
ing points. Since this new "recensored" dependent variable is symmetrically distrib-
uted around the regression function, the regression coefficients can be estimated 
by least squares. Iterating between this "symmetric censoring" of the dependent 
variable using the current estimates (which drops observations with values of the 
regression function above b) and least squares estimation of the regression coeffi-
cients using the "symmetrically trimmed" data yields the SCLS estimator. 
Finally, the identically censored least absolute deviations (ICLAD) and identically 
censored least squares (ICLS) estimation methods were proposed by Honoré and 
Powell (1994). The motivation for these estimators is similar to the "symmetric 
trimming" idea used to derive the SCLS estimator, but involves recensoring the 
dependent variable for pairs of observations so that their density functions have the 
same shape. Suppose that the dependent variables for two observations, y 1 and y 2 , 
are censored from above at b, as depicted in Figure 2. While the shape of the 
densities for these two observations would be the same in the absence of censoring, 
the censored densities have different shapes. Also, the distances from the regres-
sion functions, xЈ 1 ␤ and xЈ 2 ␤, to the censoring point b are different. 
However, the second observation y 2 , which has the smaller regression function 
xЈ 2 ␤, can be artificially "recensored" at the point xЈ 2 ␤ Ϫ xЈ 1 ␤ ϩ b ϵ ⌬xЈ␤ ϩ b. The 
resulting "identically censored" density for y 2 will have the same shape as the 
density for y 1 . Further, the difference between the two identically censored vari-
ables will be symmetrically distributed around the difference in their regression 
functions, ⌬xЈ␤. As a result, the regression coefficients can be estimated by finding 
the value of ␤ that minimizes the sum of absolute (ICLAD) or squared (ICLS) 
differences of the "identically censored" residuals across all distinct pairs of obser-
vations. As with the estimators discussed above, the ICLS and ICLAD estimators can </p>

<p>2 Quantile regression, as discussed by Koenker and Hallock in this issue, is based on a weighted version 
of the least absolute deviations approach (Koenker and Bassett, 1978). Indeed, it is straightforward to 
extend the CLAD approach to analyze the case of censored quantile regression (CRQ) estimation, as 
proposed by Powell (1986a). </p>



<p>be calculated by repeated application of linear least squares or least absolute 
deviations regression programs. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Honoré (1992) originally proposed the concept behind the ICLAD and ICLS 
estimators for censored panel data with individual-specific intercepts (also known 
as "fixed effects"). Instead of identically censoring observations for pairs of indi-
viduals, the approach can be applied to pairs of observations across time periods for </p>

<p>3 In the empirical application, we focus on the least absolute deviations version of the estimator-
ICLAD-rather than the least squares version (ICLS), since simulation evidence suggests that it 
performs better in small samples (Honoré and Powell, 1994). </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Density of y and "Symmetrically Censored" Density </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Densities of y 1 and y 2 and "Identically Censored" Densities </p>

<p>Semiparametric Censored Regression Models 33 </p>

<p>each individual. Differencing the identically censored observations for a fixed 
individual eliminates the fixed effect, just as time differences eliminate fixed effects 
in the standard linear panel data model. In fact, this approach yields consistent 
estimates even when correctly specified maximum likelihood would not. 
Each of these estimation procedures imposes a particular assumption on the 
underlying error distribution. The SCLS estimator is based on the assumption that 
the error terms are symmetrically distributed around zero, which implies that their 
median (and mean) is zero. While compatible with the traditional assumption of 
normally distributed and homoskedastic errors, the symmetry assumption is less 
restrictive and provides consistent estimates when these parametric conditions fail 
to hold. However, it is stronger than the "zero median" restriction exploited by the 
CLAD estimator, which permits nonnormal, heteroskedastic and asymmetric er-
rors. The ICLAD and ICLS estimators assume that the error terms are identically 
(but not necessarily symmetrically) distributed, ruling out heteroskedasticity, but 
permitting asymmetry of the error distribution. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>As with the choice of regressors, it is ultimately up to the empirical researcher 
to determine which assumption is most plausible for the particular application. In 
practice, though, computation of several parametric and semiparametric estimators 
provides a useful guide to the sensitivity of the results to the identifying assump-
tions, either through casual comparison of the coefficient estimates and standard 
errors or more formal specification tests of the kind described by Newey (1987). In 
other words, the different estimation approaches give the researcher additional 
ways to "cut the data" to see which results are robust to alternative specifications. 
The interval censored regression model is a special case of the more general 
censored selection model, in which the dependent variable y is generated as </p>

<p>y ϭ d ϫ ͑xЈ␤ ϩ ͒, </p>

<p>where d is an observable binary ("dummy") variable indicating whether the true 
dependent variable y* ϭ xЈ␤ ϩ is observed (d ϭ 1) or "censored" (d ϭ 0). For 
the special case of interval censoring considered above, d is an indicator for 
whether the true variable y* is in the uncensored region [a, b]. More generally, 
though, d will depend on regressors and error terms that are related to, but distinct 
from, those in the equation for y*. For example, market wages may only be 
observed for individuals with positive labor supply, which is a different form of 
censoring than top coding in wages. 
In such selection models, parametric estimation methods for the coefficients ␤ 
are typically based on maximum likelihood (Gronau, 1973) or the "two-step" 
strategy proposed by Heckman (1976, 1979). When the error distribution is not 
parametrically specified, however, semiparametric estimation of the regression </p>

<p>4 Much of the theoretical literature on semiparametric estimation of censored regression models has 
focused on this assumption. However, some simulation evidence suggests that heteroskedasticity causes 
greater bias in standard maximum likelihood estimation than nonnormality (Powell, 1986b). </p>



<p>coefficients generally involves explicit nonparametric estimation of density or 
regression functions, unlike the simpler methods for interval censored data de-
scribed above. 
5 Also, semiparametric identification of the censored selection model 
generally requires an "exclusion restriction"-that is, a regressor that is included in 
the set of regressors for the binary variable d must be excluded from the list of 
regressors x in the equation of interest. This exclusion restriction (or instrumental 
variable), which is not required for the interval-censoring model, may not be 
plausible in many empirical applications. Due to these difficulties, empirical appli-
cations of semiparametric selection models are even less common than applications 
of the semiparametric censored regression models described above. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>An Empirical Application: Relative Earnings of Black Men in the 
South During the 1960s </p>

<p>Title VII of the Civil Rights Act of 1964, which went into effect on July 2, 1965, 
outlawed discrimination against black and female workers and established the 
Equal Employment Opportunity Commission to monitor compliance with Title VII 
and to enforce its statutes. Executive Order 11246, signed by President Johnson on 
September 24, 1965, prohibited discrimination by federal contractors and created 
its enforcement arm, the Office of Federal Contract Compliance, to monitor 
contractors. Many states had also adopted their own fair employment practice laws 
before 1964 forbidding discrimination among employers located within the state. 
These laws were similar to Title VII and established state-level commissions to hear 
individual discrimination claims. However, none of the 21 states with enforceable 
state laws before the passage of the 1964 Civil Rights Act were in the South. 
We use longitudinal data on earnings to estimate the impact of these civil 
rights policies. In a joint project of the Census Bureau and the Social Security 
Administration (SSA), respondents to the 1973 and 1978 March Current Popula-
tion Surveys were matched by their Social Security numbers to their Social Security 
earnings histories. The resulting files contain survey responses on race, gender, 
education, age and region of residence as of the survey year for persons in the 
March surveys linked to any earnings for which they paid Social Security taxes. 
We examine the pooled data containing earnings information from 1958 to 
1974, with a particular focus on the years 1963, 1964, 1970 and 1971. We use a 
sample of black and white men living in southern states who were born in the 
period 1910 -1939 (the youngest man in the sample was 24 in 1963, while the oldest 
was 61 in 1971). We focus on men in the South because none of the states in the 
South had fair employment practice laws before 1965, and Title VII enforcement </p>

<p>5 An exception is given by Honoré, Kyriazidou and Udry (1997). 
6 One example of an early implementation is provided by Newey, Powell and Walker (1990), which 
applied semiparametric estimation methods to the Mroz (1987) data on the labor supply of married 
women. </p>

<p>Kenneth Y. Chay and James L. Powell 35 </p>

<p>activity was primarily directed at racial discrimination in the South. A within-cohort 
analysis is used to control for the changing composition of workers over time. The 
final sample consists of 10,105 men, and our analysis uses all men with nonzero 
earnings in a given year. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>A significant shortcoming of the earnings data is that many records are 
censored at the Social Security maximum taxable earnings level. In addition, the 
real value of the tax ceiling changed substantially during the time period of 
interest, rising from a little over $15,000 (in 1982-1984 dollars) in 1963-1964 to 
about $20,000 in 1970 -1971. At least 32 percent of the sample is classified as 
earning the top-coded amount from 1958 to 1974, and this share fluctuates 
considerably during the key periods, reaching a peak of 54 percent in 1965. 
Consequently, any estimates of the impact of Title VII on the black-white earnings 
gap that do not explicitly account for censoring at the tax ceiling and changes in 
it could be severely biased. 
We use several approaches to estimate the interval censoring model. The 
dependent variable in each case is the natural logarithm of annual taxable earn-
ings, and the explanatory variables are race, level of education, age and age-
squared. Table 1 presents the estimation results for the race and education coef-
ficients based on the various estimators. The first column, headed OLS1, contains 
the ordinary least squares estimates based on all of the data. The second column, 
headed OLS2, presents the least squares results using only the observations that are 
not censored. The third column contains the Tobit maximum likelihood estimates 
under the assumption that the errors are normally distributed and homoskedastic. 
The remaining columns present the results for the three semiparametric estima-
tors: CLAD, SCLS and ICLAD. The Tobit, CLAD and SCLS estimators were imple-
mented using the <rs type="software">Stata</rs> software package, while the ICLAD estimator was calculated 
using the <rs type="software">Gauss</rs> package. For each estimator, we have created <rs type="software">Stata</rs> "ado" files that 
are available at ͗http://elsa.berkeley.edu/ϳkenchay͘. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>It is clear from Table 1 that the least squares and maximum likelihood 
estimates of the black-white log-earnings gap and the returns to education are 
extremely biased when compared to the semiparametric estimators. We think of 
the CLAD estimator as the natural benchmark, since it is consistent under the 
normality of errors assumption justifying the maximum likelihood estimator, under 
the independence of errors assumption justifying the ICLAD estimator, and under 
the conditional symmetry of errors assumption justifying the SCLS estimator. When 
compared to the CLAD benchmark, the least squares estimator based on all of the 
data (OLS1) actually does better than the maximum likelihood estimator. For this </p>

<p>7 Over 84 percent of the men in the sample have positive earnings in 1963-1964. This figure is 
83 percent in 1970 -1971. 
8 The standard errors for OLS, MLE and ICLAD were calculated using standard approximations. The 
standard errors for CLAD and SCLS were calculated using the bootstrap techniques discussed by 
Brownstone and Valletta in this issue. It is much more efficient to calculate the ICLAD estimator using 
<rs type="software">Gauss</rs> instead of <rs type="software">Stata</rs>. </p>



<p>application, it appears that misspecifying the errors as being normally distributed 
and using maximum likelihood estimation results in more biased estimates than 
ignoring the censoring problem entirely and using least squares estimation. A more 
formal test of the normality assumption also suggests that it is violated for the 
log-earnings model. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>There are sizeable differences in the estimated effects of education on earn-
ings across the three semiparametric estimators. While the ICLAD and SCLS 
estimators of the education premium are similar, they are always greater than the 
CLAD estimator. These differences are significant given the precision of the 
estimates and range from 17 percent to 43 percent for the ICLAD estimator and </p>

<p>9 Chay and Honoré (1998) calculate the test statistics for nonnormality and for heteroskedasticity in 
censored regression models discussed by Chesher and Irish (1987). The test statistic for detecting 
nonnormality ranges from 900.47 to 1200.68. Under the null, this statistic has an (asymptotic) 
2 (2) 
distribution with a 1 percent critical value of 9.21. Therefore, we easily reject the hypothesis that the 
errors are normally distributed. The test for heteroskedasticity yields statistics between 84.71 and 90.85. 
Under the null, these have (asymptotic) 
2 (12) distributions with a 1 percent critical value of 26.22. We 
therefore also reject the null of no heteroskedasticity. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Estimated Effects of Race and Education on Log-Earnings 
(estimated standard errors in parentheses) </p>

<p>OLS1 
OLS2 
MLE 
CLAD 
SCLS 
ICLAD </p>

<p>Black-White Gap 
1963 
Ϫ0.355 
Ϫ0.183 
Ϫ0.629 
Ϫ0.416 
Ϫ0.444 
Ϫ0.474 
(0.033) 
(0.038) 
(0.044) 
(0.027) 
(0.031) 
(0.032) 
1964 
Ϫ0.349 
Ϫ0.154 
Ϫ0.674 
Ϫ0.428 
Ϫ0.444 
Ϫ0.473 
(0.032) 
(0.038) 
(0.044) 
(0.033) 
(0.036) 
(0.031) 
1970 
Ϫ0.262 
Ϫ0.115 
Ϫ0.508 
Ϫ0.278 
Ϫ0.302 
Ϫ0.338 
(0.032) 
(0.037) 
(0.044) 
(0.020) 
(0.031) 
(0.029) 
1971 
Ϫ0.242 
Ϫ0.111 
Ϫ0.486 
Ϫ0.244 
Ϫ0.287 
Ϫ0.312 
(0.031) 
(0.038) 
(0.044) 
(0.022) 
(0.032) 
(0.031) 
Returns to Education 
1963 
0.041 
0.012 
0.102 
0.051 
0.068 
0.073 
(0.003) 
(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.007) 
(0.003) 
1964 
0.040 
0.013 
0.103 
0.064 
0.079 
0.075 
(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.004) 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
(0.003) 
1970 
0.037 
0.003 
0.101 
0.055 
0.066 
0.071 
(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.004) 
(0.003) 
(0.006) 
(0.003) 
1971 
0.035 
0.002 
0.100 
0.054 
0.065 
0.070 
(0.002) 
(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.003) 
(0.005) 
(0.003) </p>

<p>Notes: The dependent variable is the natural logarithm of annual taxable earnings. Regressions also 
include a constant and age and age-squared as explanatory variables. Observations with nonpositive 
earnings are dropped from the analysis. The sample sizes for 1963, 1964, 1970 and 1971 are 8525, 8529, 
8391 and 8275, respectively. The OLS2 specification also drops top-coded observations, leading to 
sample sizes of 4632, 4267, 4485 and 4163. MLE is Tobit maximum likelihood; CLAD is censored least 
absolute deviations; SCLS is symmetrically censored least squares; ICLAD is identically censored least 
absolute deviations. </p>

<p>Semiparametric Censored Regression Models 37 </p>

<p>20 percent to 33 percent for the SCLS estimator. The differences in the estimates 
of the black-white earnings gap are smaller, with the CLAD estimator about 
11 percent to 28 percent and 4 percent to 18 percent smaller in magnitude than the 
ICLAD and SCLS estimators, respectively. Strikingly, the semiparametric ap-
proaches all result in more precise estimates of the race coefficient than maximum 
likelihood estimation. For example, the standard errors of the CLAD estimator are 
25 percent to 55 percent smaller than the standard errors of the Tobit estimator. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>The differences in the coefficient estimates across the various estimators can 
be used as a sort of specification check, similar in spirit to the Newey (1987) 
specification analysis mentioned earlier. For the education coefficient, the large 
differences between the maximum likelihood and semiparametric estimates sug-
gest that nonnormal errors are an important source of bias in the Tobit estimator. 
Further, the significant differences among the semiparametric estimates imply that 
heteroskedasticity and asymmetry of the errors are also sources of misspecification 
in the maximum likelihood estimator of the education premium. Conversely, for 
the black-white earnings gap, the smaller differences among the semiparametric 
estimates suggest that nonnormality is the biggest source of bias in the Tobit 
estimator, with heteroskedasticity and asymmetry playing smaller roles. 
To examine the question of specification in more detail, we estimated the 
distribution of the error terms derived from the CLAD estimates, using the Kaplan 
and Meier (1958) estimator. The resulting estimated error distribution for log-
earnings has fatter tails than does a normal distribution. The maximum likelihood 
estimator is sensitive to values in the tails, while the least absolute deviations 
estimator, which focuses on the median value, is unaffected by extreme observa-
tions. Since black men are more likely to be in the left-hand tail of the distribution, 
fat tails can explain the consistently larger (in magnitude) maximum likelihood 
estimates of the race coefficient. They can also explain the larger sampling errors 
of the Tobit estimator relative to the semiparametric estimators. Thus, abnormally 
long tails in the log-earnings distribution may be the major source of misspecifica-
tion in the maximum likelihood estimates of the black-white earnings gap (Chay, 
1995; Chay and Honoré, 1998). 
Based on the series of cross-sectional estimators for the four years shown in 
Table 1, the maximum likelihood and semiparametric approaches yield very similar 
estimates of changes in black-white relative earnings during the late 1960s. The 
maximum likelihood and semiparametric estimates all imply that the black-white 
earnings gap narrowed about 0.15 log points from 1963-1964 to 1970 -1971. We 
conclude from this that while there is bias in the Tobit estimator of the race 
coefficient, this bias is fixed over time. Thus, it is "differenced out" when one 
examines changes in the estimated race coefficient. However, the two ordinary least </p>

<p>10 The standard errors for the CLAD and SCLS estimators were calculated using 500 bootstrap replica-
tions. Applying the bootstrap to the Tobit maximum likelihood estimator results in standard errors that 
are nearly identical to those presented in Table 1, which are based on the asymptotic approximation. 
Thus, the bootstrap technique is not the source of the differences in the estimated standard errors. </p>



<p>squares estimators imply that relative earnings only converged between 0.06 
(OLS2) and 0.10 (OLS1) log points during the period of interest. Not accounting 
for the severe censoring in the earnings data results in downwardly biased estimates 
of the impact of Title VII. Also, although the CLAD estimator imposes the weakest 
stochastic restrictions on the error terms, it results in the most precise estimates of 
the policy effects. 
Figures 3A and 3B provide a more detailed picture of the various estimators. 
The top panel shows the percentage of workers in the sample recorded as earning 
at the taxable maximum (the top-code rate) from 1958 to 1974, separately by race. 
The bottom panel plots the estimated black-white log-earnings gaps from the OLS1, </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Top-Code Rate and Estimates of Black-White Log-Earnings Gap, 1958 -1974 </p>

<p>Kenneth Y. Chay and James L. Powell 39 </p>

<p>OLS2, MLE and CLAD estimators for the series of cross-sections from 1958 -1974. 
There is a striking correspondence between changes in the top-code rate in the top 
panel and changes in the ordinary least squares estimates in the bottom panel. 
Indeed, it seems that most of the changes in the ordinary least squares estimates 
over time are being driven by changes in the amount of censoring varying by race. 
This results in a severe understatement of the racial earnings convergence in the 
late 1960s. The time series of the CLAD and maximum likelihood estimates, on the 
other hand, have no association with the top-code rates, although, as noted earlier, 
the maximum likelihood estimates systematically overstate the size of the black-
white earnings gap when compared to the CLAD estimates. The maximum likeli-
hood and CLAD estimates imply substantial black economic progress in the South 
after 1964; a result that is masked by the ordinary least squares estimates. 
Finally, Table 2 presents the fixed-effects estimation results based on the 
ICLAD estimator for each of the six possible pairs of time periods in our panel data. 
The table entries give the estimated change in the race and education coefficients 
between the two specified periods. The analysis includes age and age-squared as 
explanatory variables. To compare the parameter estimates across the six columns, 
the sample is restricted to the 7,435 men with positive earnings in all four years. 
This reduces the sample size by about 10 percent to 13 percent relative to the 
cross-sectional samples. 
The black-white earnings gap narrowed substantially during the period of 
interest, even after accounting for individual-specific fixed effects. The relative 
earnings of black men increased about 0.12-0.14 log-points from 1963 to 1971. 
These estimates are similar to those implied by the series of maximum likelihood 
and semiparametric estimates of the cross-sectional censored regression model in 
Table 1. A key assumption underlying the fixed-effects ICLAD estimator is that the 
distribution of the unobservables is the same in all time periods for a given 
individual. A formal specification test did not reject the restrictions implied by this 
assumption at conventional levels of significance (Chay and Honoré, 1998). </p>

<p>Table 2 
Fixed-Effects ICLAD Estimates of Effects of Race and Education 
(estimated standard errors in parentheses) </p>

<p>1963-64 
1963-70 
1963-71 
1964-70 
1964-71 
1970-71 </p>

<p>Change in 
Black-White Gap 
0.011 
0.102 
0.136 
0.095 
0.108 
0.015 
(0.007) 
(0.017) 
(0.021) 
(0.020) 
(0.019) 
(0.007) 
Returns to Education 
0.002 
0.001 
0.000 
0.000 
Ϫ0.003 
0.000 
(0.001) 
(0.002) 
(0.003) 
(0.003) 
(0.002) 
(0.001) </p>

<p>Notes: See notes to Table 1. The sample is the 7,435 men with positive earnings in all four years. For each 
pair of years, the absolute error loss function was used to estimate the identically censored panel data 
model with fixed effects. The estimates represent the change in the coefficients between the two years. </p>



<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>When data are censored, ordinary least squares regression can provide mis-
leading estimates. The results from the semiparametric models show that there was 
significant earnings convergence among black and white men in the American 
South after the passage of the 1964 Civil Rights Act, a result that was masked by least 
squares analysis. The semiparametric methods can also provide information on the 
sources of misspecification in parametric estimation approaches. In the log-
earnings model, it appears that abnormally long tails are the major source of bias 
in the Tobit maximum likelihood estimates. </p>

<p>y We thank Bo Honoré, David Lee, and especially Alan Krueger, Timothy Taylor and </p>

<p>Michael Waldman for their helpful comments. Marcelo Moreira provided outstanding research 
assistance. Support from the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation and the Center for Advanced Study 
in the Behavioral Sciences is gratefully acknowledged. </p>



<p>Semiparametric Censored Regression Models 41 </p>





<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



</text></tei>