<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10614-017-9706-4" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract The importance of network externalities for the development of technol-
ogy and industry structure has been recognized in evolutionary economic for a long 
time. However, network externalities are no isolated phenomena. They are based on 
competing standards in a comprehensive network of technology lines that are based 
on one another and remain to various degrees interoperable or compatible. As some 
evidence from the ICT sector inparticular shows, compatibility and tying or bundling 
of standards may be employed as strategic tools. The present paper investigates the 
economic role of tied standards for the dynamics of competition between standards. 
A replicator model operating on an aggregated level is complemented by an agent-
based simulation with explicit representation of the network structure among users. A 
variety of effects are studied, including the role of initial usage share, manipulation of 
compatibility, expansion of vendors into other segments, as well as the network struc-
ture and central or peripheral positioning of agents. The agent-based model contrasts 
a complete network and a regular ring network with asymmetric network structures 
derived from Barabàsi and Albert's preferential attachment mechanism and triadic 
closure. </p>

<p>When users-both corporate and private-consider employing a new technology, say 
Voice-over-IP telephony (VoIP), their choice between different available standards or 
products implementing this technology may be severely limited. While many stan-
dards 1 may be available in theory, practical usability depends on which standard 
predominates the users' direct environment, which ones are used by their business part-
ners etc. This effect, network externalities, has extensively been investigated (David 
1985; Katz and Shapiro 1985; Arthur et al. 1987). However, there is a second constraint, 
introduced by compatibility to other standards already employed by the respective 
users; they may for instance need to consider, if the desired VoIP software works well 
with the used operating system, office software, computer and network hardware, etc. 
Network externalities will then develop not only within but also across segments. 
Vendors of standards have been known to use this to their advantage: Microsoft's 
breakthrough famously came with agreements to couple their software with IBM 
hardware. Another well-known case linked to the company is the bundling of its 
operating system Windows with its web browser Internet Explorer. Today, many large 
companies in the ICT (information and communication technology) sector maintain 
extensive portfolios of partly bundled or integrated products. While the phenomenon 
is by no means limited to the ICT sector, the strength of network externalities in ICT 
makes examples in this sector both more numerous and more obvious. 2 
Obvious strategies to gain an advantage for a competing standard in such a setting 
include increasing the compatibility with major competitors in other segments, 3 intro-
ducing spin-off standards in other segments, and reducing compatibility with weaker 
competitor's products in order to drive them out of business. 
Can strategic exploitation of network effects of this type be demonstrated in a simple 
evolutionary model? 4 Can it be demonstrated for (1) the initial usage share in either 
segment (putting incumbants at an advantage) (2) the compatibility between standards 
across segments (3) the positioning of initial adopters? Is there a point beyond which 
reduction of compatibility is desirable for a competitor? Is it wise to expand into 
another segment to control the standard in that segment directly-given the capacity 
to do so? 
The present contribution offers a replicator dynamic model of standard competition 
with cross-segment ties. A standard replicator equation is used in which the compat-
ibility with and the usage shares of standards in one or several other segments take 
the role of the evolutionary fitness. The replicator model yields a first-order dynamic </p>

<p>1 This may include, e.g., skype, Google and Facebook's Videochats, tox, as well as the products of a wealth 
of other providers operating predominantly on the national level in different countries. 
2 For more examples, see Sect. 5. </p>

<p>3 This seems important for small competitors, with Microsoft's initial contract with IBM falling in this 
category. 
4 Evolutionary model in this context refers to a model that emphasizes the development and the dynamics 
remaining agnostic towards the existence of an equilibrium. It will become clear in Sect. 2 that much of the 
relevant literature in the field of competition with network externalities comes from evolutionary economics. 
It will also become clear, that evolutionary techniques such as replicator dynamics and agent-based modeling 
are well-suited to approach these questions. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>system that allows to investigate the impact of initial conditions and of compatibility 
terms. These would be what governs the strategic actions of major competitors in sec-
tors with densely interconnected standards such as the information and communication 
technology. 
Direct interaction between agents on the micro-level sometimes leads to the emer-
gence of non-trivial macro-level dynamics. Therefore, it is necessary to show that 
benchmark models operating at an aggregated level will still work if a micro-layer of 
massive numbers of interacting agents is included. For this, an agent-based version 
of the model is added. The deterministic dynamics resulting from the (aggregated 
level) replicator model are replaced by transition probabilities between user groups 
of standards. 5 For the trivial network structure of a complete graph, this results in a 
stochastic dynamic system which is equivalent to the macro-level model in its behav-
ior while for other network structures, the probabilities change locally, i.e. between 
agents, depending on their neighborhood. 
Section 2 gives a brief literature overview before the model is discussed in Sect. 3. 
Section 4 discusses simulations and results. These analyses are contrasted with some 
evidence of strategic use of standard tying in the ICT (information and communication 
technology) sector in Sects. 5, 6 concludes. </p>

<p>2 Literature Review </p>

<p>While there were some earlier considerations of increasing returns in economic theory 
(see, e.g. Sraffa 1926; Young 1928), the specific role of increasing returns to the number 
of consumers, and thus the phenomenon of network externalities, was only analyzed 
in detail starting in the 1980s. 6 
There are two major schools to approach the modeling of network externalities: 
One relies on game theory and the analysis of equilibria for rational agents in a 
game theoretic setting. This approach was pioneered by Katz and Shapiro (1985, 
1986). It received much attention and drew a large number of contributions in the 
subsequent years; Farrell and Klemperer (2007) provide an overview. The other line 
of research emphasized path dependence, self-reinforcing feedbacks, and dynamics. 
Nelson's (1968) and Fisher and Pry's (1971) models of technological change may, 
without directly focusing on network externalities, have been the first predecessor 
of this class of models. The tradition of literature fully developed in the 1980s with 
David's (1985, 1992) historical analyses and Arthur et al.'s (1983[1982], 1987, 1988, 
1989) urn scheme (Eggenberger-Pólya process) models. The consensus among the 
two traditions holds that network effects tend to lead to a lock-in with only one alter-
native as the uncontested standard which may bring certain disadvantages in the form </p>

<p>5 Transition probabilities here refers to the probabilities that a user will continue using or switch to a certain 
standard (thus becoming part of its user group). 
6 Though Demsetz (1968) quotes an 1859 paper by Chatwick who may have been the first who realized 
the strategic consequences for commercial vendors of standards in sectors with network externalities when 
he distinguished between "competition in a market" and "competition for a market". </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>of technological alternatives that are not viable any more because the user base con-
centrates on another, potentially inferior technology. 7 
As the body of literature and evidence grew, scholars turned to further details 
including tying of standards across sectors, or rather across subsectors/segments within 
a larger sector. As an example, this may be thought of as an operating system, an office 
software package, a web browser, a database system and numerous other categories of 
software and hardware products that require a certain compatibility with one another 
in order to work properly. 8 Many of the larger vendors are active in several or almost all 
of these subsectors. It is obvious that network externalities may also unfold indirectly 9 
across sectors and that it opens a large variety of strategic options to any commercial 
vendor. The idea of tied standards was initially proposed by Choi (2004) and analyzed 
in a game theory framework. Later, an evolutionary replicator model was put forward 
(Heinrich 2014); this model will be used and extended for the analysis in the present 
article. 
With recent advances of network theory (Watts and Strogatz 1998; Barabási and 
Albert 1999; Vázquez 2003) and their application to the field of technology diffusion 
and network externality models, it became clear that the result of swift and complete 
lock-in and monopolization relied crucially on the implicitly assumed network struc-
ture of a complete network. The properties of other network structures in this respect 
including lattice networks, Watts-Strogatz random graphs (i.e., small world networks), 
and scale free networks (both Barabàsi-Albert preferential attachment networks and 
and Vazquez' connect nearest neighbor (CNN) networks) were investigated subse-
quently (Delre et al. 2007; Lee et al. 2006; Frenken et al. 2008; Uchida and Shirayama 
2008; Pegoretti et al. 2009). It was found that networks with large diameter effectively 
inhibited complete lock-in (Uchida and Shirayama 2008). Small world networks on 
the other hand 10 resemble the findings of the complete network (Delre et al. 2007; 
Lee et al. 2006; Pegoretti et al. 2009). Some of the findings by Uchida and Shirayama 
(2008) also hint that clustering (CNN instead of BA scale free networks) may reduce 
the probability of a lock-in as well. 
However, comprehensive studies of mechanisms and market-strategic and eco-
nomic consequences of complex (tied multi-sector or multi-segment) network 
externality systems have yet to be conducted. One difficulty of this is the dimen-
sion of the resulting problems with many free variables the effect of which would 
need to be systematically analyzed. This and the need to take the network structure 
into account suggests simulation as the best option for this analysis which will form 
the centerpiece of the present article. This allows not only to investigate the effect of </p>

<p>7 Aside from these asymptotically stable equilibria, the complete monopolization of the sector for just one 
alternative, there are also one or more unstable tipping-point equilibria between the basins of attraction of 
the stable equilibria. 
8 More concrete examples are given in Sect. 5. </p>

<p>9 Note that this is not the same as Katz and Shapiros's (1985) indirect network effect, which is a network 
effect that unfolds not directly via the number of users but by means of another mechanism, perhaps reduced 
costs. 
10 That is, Watts-Strogatz random graphs with more than a certain threshold of rewired edges, values of 
around 20% are suggested. However, the threshold for this phase transition may depend on other environment 
variables. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>neighborhood structures but also the possible role and plausibility of strategic use of 
tying and network externalities. </p>

<p>3 A Model of Network Externalities and Tied Standards </p>

<p>3.1 Replicator Dynamic Model with Implicit Network Structure </p>

<p>The present study will be based on a replicator model that largely follows the model 
proposed in Heinrich (2014). The numerical study below requires assuming specific 
parameter sets. Different values for several of the more interesting parameters (with 
otherwise plausible parameter settings) will be considered in order to study the sensi-
tivity of the system with respect to those parameters. 
The starting point of the model is a replicator equation 11 </p>

<p>p i, j,t+1 = p i, j,t (1 + f i, j,t − φ j,t ) </p>

<p>where p i, j,t are the usage shares of standard i in segment 12 j at time t, f i, j,t is the 
evolutionary fitness term of this standard, and φ j,t is the average evolutionary fitness 
in segment j at time t. </p>

<p>φ j,t = f </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>j ,t p j ,t </p>

<p>where f j ,t = </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎝ 
f 1, j ,t 
f 2, j ,t 
... </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎠ and p j ,t = </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎝ 
p 1, j ,t 
p 2, j ,t 
... </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎠ are vectors with components for </p>

<p>each standard of the segment j and T denotes the transpose. The fitness term must 
include measures of the size of the standard's network or usage share and, if tying 
between standards across segments is to be taken into account, also such measures 
for compatible standards in other segments. Compatibility denotes the interoperability 
between two standards. Can files created with program 1 be opened with program 2? 
Is program 1 available for operating system 3 on mobile device 4? Is it usable in the 
same way as former industry standard program 5? In reality, there are many cases of 
limited interoperability, therefore it seems fitting to to denote interoperability between 
any two standards i and i as a real valued number between 0 and 1, a i i ∈ [0, 1] (if in 
the same segment) or c i i ∈ [0, 1] (if in different segments). </p>

<p>11 This is a discretization of the canonical form </p>

<p>dp i, j </p>

<p>dt = p i, j,t ( f i, j,t − φ j,t ). 
12 This refers to a subsector or one of several types of goods within the same sector such that interacting 
network externalities can be expected (as in the above example of operating systems, office software, 
web browsers etc.). Of course, in reality the sector association of these segments would not be unique or 
homogeneous, but different segments and even different standards within segments would align only to 
varying degrees. This is reflected in the compatibility matrices A and C in the present model, which allow 
the level of interaction of network externalities to be fine-tuned or investigated. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>Consider the vector of the fitnesses of standards in segment j at time t, f j ,t </p>

<p>f j ,t = w j , j A j p j ,t + </p>

<p>j = j </p>

<p>w j , j C j , j p j,t . </p>

<p>where p j,t is the vector of the corresponding population shares, w j , j are parameters 
indicating the weight 13 of the compatibility with standards in segment j on the fitness 
terms in segment j , and A and C are matrices of the compatibilities of standards in 
two segments (C j , j between segments j and j ) or between standards in the same 
segment (A). Let the elements of those matrices be denoted a i i and c i i respectively and 
hold values between 0 and 1 which indicate to what degree standard i is compatible 
to standard i from the point of view of a user of standard i . Note that for most 
technologies, this compatibility structure would be assumed to be symmetric 14 but 
there may be exceptions. 15 
Consider for illustrative purposes a system with one segment and two standards. 
The above function would become </p>

<p>f 1,1,t 
f 2,1,t 
= w 1,1 
a 11,1,t a 12,1,t 
a 21,1,t a 22,1,t </p>

<p>p 1,1,t 
p 2,1,t 
. </p>

<p>and would not have to contain any cross-segmental compatibility matrices C. In case 
of a two-segment system with two standards in each segment, the fitness function for 
standards in segment 1 would read </p>

<p>f 1,1,t 
f 2,1,t 
= w 1,1 
a 11,1,t a 12,1,t 
a 21,1,t a 22,1,t </p>

<p>p 1,1,t 
p 2,1,t 
+w 1,2 
c 11,1,2,t c 12,1,2,t 
c 21,1,2,t c 22,1,2,t </p>

<p>p 1,2,t 
p 2,2,t 
. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>Note that this is still a very general model except for two aspects: First, the fitness 
terms resulting from compatibilities across different segments are additive in this 
model. They could also 16 be connected multiplicatively, but this would lead to a very 
strong effect of single segments in a very large model, 17 while an additive model 
allows the effects to be tuned with the parameters w. Second, no standalone-fitness </p>

<p>13 This allows to weight different tied segments differently, especially the segment the evolutionary fitness 
of which is being computed with the above equation. 
14 In formal terms, A would be a symmetric matrix and C j, j would be the transpose of C j , j , C j, j = </p>

<p>C T </p>

<p>j , j </p>

<p>. Since a standard should be perfectly compatible with itself, all main diagonal elements of A should 
further equal 1. 
15 For instance, a software may offer to read, open, and transform but not to write file types of a competing 
software. 
16 It is unlikely that all network effects follow the same functional form, therefore an approach was chosen 
that seemed relatively universal and flexible yet integrates easily with the evolutionary model and the 
simulation below. For a comprehensive account of proposed functional forms of network externalities, see 
Swann (2002). 
17 Incompatibility with all standards in one segment would lead to the fitness term being multiplied by 
zero for this segment and, thus, to the overall fitness also being reduced to zero. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>term (one without relation to network externalities) is included. This would only add 
additional variables without contributing substantially to the purpose of the model, 
to investigate and illustrate the effect of compatibility on the development of usage 
shares and market power. 
For this model, the direct effects of different variables can now be studied; partic-
ularly of interest is whether the compatibility terms have a positive or a negative 
effect. 18 This is derived in "Appendix 1". For the terms of matrix A, this yields </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 11,1 </p>

<p>≥ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 12,1 </p>

<p>≥ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 21,1 </p>

<p>≤ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 22,1 </p>

<p>≤ 0. If A is to be symmetric, </p>

<p>hence α = a 12,1 = a 21,1 and 0 &lt; p 1,1,t &lt; 0.5, we further derive that </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂α </p>

<p>&gt; 0. 
For the direct influence of the terms of the inter-segmental compatibility martix C, it 
is obtained that </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 11,1,2 </p>

<p>≥ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 12,1,2 </p>

<p>≥ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 21,1,2 </p>

<p>≤ 0, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 22,1,2 </p>

<p>≤ 0. However, in 
the inter-segmental case, there may be irreducible indirect effects that work by first 
influencing the usage shares in the other segment and then taking an indirect effect by 
means of these. This will be discussed in more detail in Sect. 4.2. 
The proper way to analyze this is by computing the attractors in this dynamical 
system and assessing their stability. For a single segment with two standards with 
symmetric A and α &lt; 1, this unsurprisingly yields the result that there are two stable 
equilibria (the monopolization of the segment by the two standards respectively) and 
one unstable tipping equilibrium (for detailed derivation, see "Appendix 2"). 
This is in agreement with the present analysis and the previous literature: network 
externalities must, if present, have a very strong effect towards asymmetric market 
power and usage shares and ultimately towards monopolization. </p>

<p>3.2 Agent-Based Simulation Model with Explicit Network Structure </p>

<p>Macro-level models like the replicator dynamics above and like many of the network 
externality models in the literature generally assume a complete network between the 
agents and often also-sometimes depending on the interpretation-generally homo-
geneous agents. This does not live up to accurately representing what is observed in the 
real world. The purpose of those models, creating simplified mathematical representa-
tions of the real world in order to identify general characteristics, should therefore be 
complemented by analyses that drop these simplifications, that allow for heterogene-
ity and, perhaps more importantly, for a greater variety of network structures. It must 
be shown that the general characteristics identified in macro-level models continue 
to hold there. Further, the effect of network structures can be investigated as can be 
mechanisms that rely on their characteristics (the friendship paradox is addressed as 
an example in a simulation in Sect. 4.3). 
The proper tool for such an analysis is agent-based modeling and simulation (Pyka 
and Fagiolo 2005; Elsner et al. 2015; Gräbner 2015). Specifically, the aggregated 
level development equations from the above replicator model are dropped; agents are 
modelled explicitly and are periodically allowed to reconsider their adoption decision. </p>

<p>18 The partial derivatives of the replicator equation with respect to the variables in question is used to assess 
this. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>Adoption decisions may be assumed to be costly (perhaps requiring new equipment), 
and are therefore not taken lightly or reconsidered frequently. In making adoption 
decisions, agents do take network externalities into account but only those that arise 
from their direct neighbors. That is, connections indicate nothing more and nothing less 
than the potential need to interact by making use of the standard in question such that the 
choice of the connected neighbor causes an external effect on the agent. 19 This would, 
in turn, prompt the agent to take her information about previous adoption decisions 
by neighbors into account in her own adoption decision. It is reasonable to assume 
that agents are perfectly informed about their neighbor's adoption decisions, since 
the network externality gives incentive to try to be coordinated and neighbors would 
therefore have an incentive to announce their adoption decisions both immediately and 
truthfully. In order to keep the model close and comparable to the aggregated level 
replicator model above, the future population shares p i, j,t+1 in the replicator model 
are used as probabilities for the agent to adopt the respective technologies, hence </p>

<p>p i, j,t+1 = p </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>i, j,t (1 + f </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>i, j,t − φ </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j,t ) </p>

<p>with </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j ,t = w j , j A j p </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j ,t + </p>

<p>j = j </p>

<p>w j , j C j , j p </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j,t . </p>

<p>φ </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j,t = ( f </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>j ,t ) 
T p </p>

<p>L 
j ,t </p>

<p>where the variables with superscript L indicates quantities in the immediate neigh-
borhood of the respective agent that are not necessarily constant across the network. 
Furthermore the usage shares p L 
j ,t are absolute, not relative, usage shares, that is non-
adopters count as a seperate share which means that agents who encounter no adopters 
in their neighborhood will also not adopt any technologies (since all adoption probabil-
ities are then multiplied with 0), agents with a small share of adopters in their vicinity 
will also only have a small (but positive) share to join a standard's usage network. 
Five network structures will be studied: </p>

<p>1. Complete network All agents are direct neighbors of all other agents. This should 
correspond most directly to the aggregated level replicator model above (with 
only minor changes, such as a stochastic term for the agent's technology adoption 
decision instead of deterministic development equations for the shares). It is meant 
as a mere benchmark case. 
2. Regular 1-d grid Agents are arranged in a circle and directly connected to n 
neighbors (out of a total of N agents) to both sides. For the following simulations 
the parameter setting n = 30, N = 1000 are used. Grid networks are known to have 
constant betweenness centrality, high clustering, and a large diameter relative to the 
number of vertices. As discussed in the literature review above, they tend to cancel 
out monopolization effects in network externality models of technology diffusion. </p>

<p>19 A potential extension for a more elaborate model would be to consider links of different strength; the 
present model considers just one type and strength of links, hence a non-weighted network. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>3. Barabàsi-Albert preferential attachment networks Starting with one agent, new 
agents are added and connected to k nodes with a probability proportional to their 
current degree (number of direct neighbors). This produces a heavily asymmetric 
degree distribution which is, in fact, scale free; such networks are known to also 
have a small diameter. The parameter settings used below are k = 2, N = 1000. 
4. Barabàsi-Albert preferential attachment networks with triadic closure Since real-
world networks tend to be highly clustered, something which is not the case for 
Barabàsi-Albert networks, clustering is increased here by using triadic closure. 
m open triads, unconnected nodes which have a common neighbor, are randomly 
selected and closed. The parameter setting used in the simulations below is k = 1, 
N = 1000, m = 1000 which gives the network as many edges as network (3) but 
a larger diameter. Note that triadic closure is similar to Vázquez' (2003) connect 
nearest neighbor (CNN) network generating mechanism: as nodes of higher degree 
are more likely to be selected, this should increase the asymmetry of the degree 
distribution (and indeed combine two power-law generating mechanisms). 
5. Barabàsi-Albert preferential attachment networks with triadic closure like net-
work (4) but with parameters k = 2, N = 1000, m = 1000 which gives the 
network a diameter similar to that of network (3) but higher density. </p>

<p>These five structures cover both basic benchmark cases for comparison with the 
simple aggregated level replicator (the complete network, and, to a lesser extent, the 
grid network) and network structures that include many realistic features also observed 
in real life networks including clustering (grid network, preferential attachment with 
triadic closure) and small diameter (small-world property) as well as scale-free degree 
distribution (preferential attachment networks). The literature discussed in Sect. 2 
offers some guidance on what to expect in models with these network structures: 
clustering should tend to reduce network externalities and subsequent monopoliza-
tion effects, high density and scale-free degree distributions may counteract this 
reduction. </p>

<p>4 Simulation Analysis </p>

<p>Simulation offers a convenient and reliable method to study the behavior of complex 
systems at least in parts of their potentially vast possibility space. With the limits of 
analytical tractability of the general model exhausted in the face of a large number 
of free parameters, this section first turns to Monte Carlo simulation to study the 
development of some representatives of the general class of models before proceeding 
to agent-based simulation in order to analyze effects of the network structure and to 
verify that the general characteristics derived for the aggregated level model continue 
to hold with an agent-based micro-level. </p>

<p>4.1 Experimental Design </p>

<p>Most of the following simulation studies will consider two segment models with 
two standards in each of them (hence quadratic 2 × 2 matrices A and C for both </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>segments). It is further assumed that all standards are "tied" to one other standard in 
the other segment, hence having higher compatibility with this than with the other 
one; for convenience the first standard in both segments and the second standard in 
both segments are considered "tied". 20 Matrices C 1,2 and C 2,1 are assumed to be 
transposes, i.e. inter-segmental compatibility is symmetric. 21 
The specific effects that are to be studied with either aggregated level Monte Carlo 
simulation (MC) or agent-based simulation (ABM) are listed in Table 1 with the 
resulting developments shown in more detail in the respective figures as indicated in 
the table. Some aspects are discussed in more detail in the next sections. 
The simulation study starts by investigating effects 1 through 5 in one-, two-, 
and three-segment replicator models. These are fully deterministic, hence a single-
run Monte Carlo simulation suffices. For this part of the study, the variable of 
interest as indicated in the table is varied while the other parameters are kept 
constant. 
For comparison to the two-segment models below, a one-segment Monte Carlo 
simulation 22 with variations in the initial usage share (left panel) and intra-segmental 
compatibility (right panel) is shown in Fig. 1. As predicted analytically, it is shown that 
a high one-way compatibility (a 12 but not a 21 ) can help recovering from an inferior 
position with low usage share but only if a 12 exceeds a certain threshold. 23 From the 
theoretical analysis in Sect. 3.1 and Appendices "1" and "2" it becomes clear that this 
must be the case for all models of this type. For the multi-segment models, however, 
this is less easy to assess. 
If not indicated otherwise, the parameters for the following two-and three-segment </p>

<p>Monte Carlo simulations are set as follows: A = 
1 0.9 
0.9 1 
, C = 
0.1 0 
0 0.1 
, </p>

<p>w 1,1 = w 2,2 = 1, w 1,2 = w 2,1 = 2; the settings for the initial usage shares vary 
according to the scenario needed for the study of the respective effect. 
The agent-based simulation follows the same principle (just one effect or variable is 
varied ceteris paribus) but with 100 runs per effect and setting with all studies repeated 
for all five network types under investigation. The illustrations in Figs. 8 through 13 
show the average and the 90% intervals. The most central purpose of the agent-based 
simulation is to confirm that the findings of the aggregated level models persist in 
the agent-based version. Further, the effects of the network structure etc. are to be 
assessed. </p>

<p>20 Hence c 11 will for instance generally be larger than c 12 except in runs in which variation of these terms 
is studied. 
21 The parameters for the fitness weight of the two segments will be set to 1 for intra-segmental influence, 
w 1,1 = w 2,2 = 1, and 2 for inter-segmental influence, w 1,2 = w 2,1 = 2 but some of the runs will be 
contrasted by runs without intra-segmental network effect (hence, w 1,1 = w 2,2 = 0) in order to show a 
more pronounced inter-segmental effect. </p>

<p>22 Panel 1a with A = 
1 0.9 
0.9 1 
, varying usage share p 1 ; Panel 1b with A = 
1 0.9 
a 12 1 
, p t=0 = </p>

<p>0.3 
0.7 
and varying a 12 . </p>

<p>23 Which is between 0.4 and 0.5 for the current settings. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>Table 1 
Investigated effects 
Explanation </p>

<p>MC/ABM </p>

<p>Result </p>

<p>Figure(s) </p>

<p>1 
Increased initial usage share of standard i </p>

<p>in segment j, p 
i, j,0 , on the same </p>

<p>segment j 
(traditional network externality w/o tied standards) </p>

<p>MC </p>

<p>p 
i, j,t incr., (⇒ p </p>

<p>=i, j,t decr.) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
Increased initial usage share of standard i </p>

<p>in segment j, p </p>

<p>i, j,0 , on a </p>

<p>standard i </p>

<p>segment j 
that is tied to i </p>

<p>in j </p>

<p>MC </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>i 
, j </p>

<p>,t incr. </p>

<p>2, 7a </p>

<p>3 
Improved inter-segmental compatibility c </p>

<p>ii, j, j of tied standards i </p>

<p>and i </p>

<p>in </p>

<p>segments j </p>

<p>and j </p>

<p>MC </p>

<p>p 
i, j,t incr., p </p>

<p>i 
, j </p>

<p>,t incr. </p>

<p>3, 7b, 5 </p>

<p>4 
Improved inter-segmental compatibility c </p>

<p>ii, j, j of standard i </p>

<p>in segment j </p>

<p>with standard i </p>

<p>in segments j 
which is/was tied (has higher </p>

<p>compatibility to) standard i </p>

<p>0 in segment i </p>

<p>MC </p>

<p>p 
i, j,t incr., p </p>

<p>i 
, j </p>

<p>,t incr. or decr., p </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>0 , j,t decr. </p>

<p>4, 7b </p>

<p>5 
Expanding into another segment j </p>

<p>by the vendor of standard i </p>

<p>in segment j </p>

<p>establishing a new standard i  *  
with higher inter-segmental compatibility </p>

<p>with i, c 
ii * , j, j , (with a very small but positive initial usage share) </p>

<p>MC </p>

<p>p 
i, j,t decr. in short term, put possibly incr. in long term </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>6 
Interaction of the network structure with the effects of initial usage shares 
(effects 1 and 2) </p>

<p>ABM 
Effects persist under all network structures </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>7 
Interaction of the network structure with the effect of inter-segmental 
compatibility (effects 3 and 4) </p>

<p>ABM 
Effect persists under all network structures, but less 
pronounced with asymmetric network structures </p>

<p>9, 11 </p>

<p>8 
Initial total usage share versus uncommited agents </p>

<p>ABM 
Network externality effects stronger with more 
uncommited agents </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>9 
Effect of selection of initial adopters by one standard i </p>

<p>(Feld's friendship </p>

<p>paradox) </p>

<p>ABM 
Higher usage shares of standard i </p>

<p>and standards tied to </p>

<p>this one </p>

<p>13 </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>Shares </p>

<p>p(1,j,0)=0.9 
p(1,j,0)=0.8 
p(1,j,0)=0.7 
p(1,j,0)=0.6 
p(1,j,0)=0.5 
p(1,j,0)=0.4 
p(1,j,0)=0.3 
p(1,j,0)=0.2 
p(1,j,0)=0.1 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time </p>

<p>Shares </p>

<p>a(12)=0.7 
a(12)=0.6 
a(12)=0.5 
a(12)=0.4 
a(12)=0.0 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 1 One-segment model. a Effect of initial usage share p 1, j,0 on the development of usage shares p 1, j,t 
in time t. b Effect of intra-segmental compatibility a 12 on the development of usage shares p 1, j,t , given 
the initial usage share p 1, j,0 = 0.3 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>p(1,j,0)=0.5 
p(1,j,0)=0.4 
p(1,j,0)=0.3 
p(1,j,0)=0.2 
p(1,j,0)=0.1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>p(1,j,0)=0.5 
p(1,j,0)=0.4 
p(1,j,0)=0.3 
p(1,j,0)=0.2 
p(1,j,0)=0.1 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Two-segment model: effect of initial usage share. a Effect of initial usage share of standard 1 in 
segment 1 on future usage shares of standards 1 in both segments. b Setup (as in subfigure 2a) without 
intra-segmental effects. Note that the development is similar but slower </p>

<p>4.2 Monte Carlo Simulation of the Replicator Dynamic Model </p>

<p>4.2.1 Initial Usage Shares (Effects 1, 2) </p>

<p>Higher initial usage shares of a standard i have a direct positive effect on future usage 
shares of the standard itself, i.e. the direct network externality effect (Fig. 1). It will also 
have a positive effect on future usage shares of any standards that have a high two-way 
compatibility with standard i-be it in the same or other segments. The direct effect 
of higher compatibility of a standard i to any other standards will also be beneficial 
for the future usage shares of i (Fig. 2). There can, however, be indirect effects similar 
to the ones discussed in relation to cross-segmental compatibility below. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>c(11)=0.16 
c(11)=0.14 
c(11)=0.135 
c(11)=0.13 
c(11)=0.12 
c(11)=0.10 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>c(11)=0.16 
c(11)=0.14 
c(11)=0.135 
c(11)=0.13 
c(11)=0.12 
c(11)=0.10 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Two-segment model: effect of inter-segmental compatibility between tied partner standards, c 11 . a 
Effect of inter-segmental compatibility c 11 between two standards 1 in different segments 1 and 2 on the 
development of usage shares of these standards p 1,1,t and p 1,2,t . b Setup without intra-segmental effects, 
otherwise identical </p>

<p>4.2.2 Inter-Segmental Compatibility (Effects 3, 4) </p>

<p>As seen already in the one-segment case in Fig. 1, compatibility also has a direct 
positive effect on the future usage shares of the involved standards, though it may be 
desirable to have low compatibility to weaker competitors in order to drive them out 
of business. This is also true for cross-segmental compatibility as shown in Figs. 3 and 
4. Figure 3 demonstrates that sufficiently high compatibility even between minority 
standards will help to expand usage shares and eventually establish a position of 
dominance in both segments. 24 Note that the same effects can be shown for cases with 
higher numbers of segments. 25 </p>

<p>4.2.3 When Is it Time to Reduce Compatibility? (Effects 3, 4) </p>

<p>Let there be two pairs of tied standards 26 across two segments; one pair has low usage 
shares, the other one is dominant. A standard i in the pair with comparatively low 
usage shares may try to improve its position by establishing compatibility with the 
other standard in the other segment (i.e. increasing c 12 . This standard in the other 
segment is then temporarily highly compatible both standard i and its competitor in 
the same segment. If standard i, as would be expected, increases its usage share-is </p>

<p>24 Initial usage shares in the shown case are p 1,0 = 
0.3 
0.7 
, p 2,0 = 
0.6 
0.4 
; the compatibility term of </p>

<p>the first (tied) standards in both segments is varied; about c = 0.135 is sufficient for the pair to become 
dominant. 
25 A three-segment model as shown in Fig. 7 uses the same matrices A for all segments and the basic </p>

<p>inter-segmental compatibility matrices C = 
0.1 0 
0 0.1 
between segments 1 and 3 and between segments </p>

<p>2 and 3 while only varying c 12 between segments 1 and 2. (w 1,1 = w 2,2 = w 3,3 = 1, w 1,2 = w 2,1 = 
w 3,1 = w 1,3 = w 3,2 = w 2,3 = 2). 
26 For instance, both standards of each pair might be offered by the same respective vendor. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0.65 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>c(12)=0.10 
c(12)=0.05 
c(12)=0.00 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0.65 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.95 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>c(12)=0.10 
c(12)=0.05 
c(12)=0.00 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Two-segment model: effect of inter-segmental compatibility between other standards (i.e. standards 
that are members of different tied pairs of standards), c 12 . a Setup with high inter-segmental compatibility 
of standards 1 in both segments, c 11 = 0.1 and standards 2 in both segments, c 22 = 0.1. Effect of additional 
inter-segmental compatibility c 12 between standard 1 in segment 1 and 2 in segment 2 on the development 
of usage shares of standards 1in both segments, p 1,1,t and p 1,2,t . b Setup without intra-segmental effects, 
otherwise identical </p>

<p>there a threshold beyond which it is better to end this temporary engagement, reduce 
c 12 again and return to the initial two-pair situation? Fig. 5 hence shows a setting </p>

<p>with a compatibility matrix C = 
0.103 0.05 
0 0.1 
and assumes that a standard's vendor </p>

<p>is theoretically capable to reduce compatibility terms by inserting artificial obstacles 
preventing interaction between the standards. In these simulation runs, c 12 is reduced 
to 0 if the usage share of standard 1 in segment 1, p 1,1,t reaches a threshold level of 
th × max( p 2,t ). 27 The result is a direct effect that decreases the standard's usage share 
growth (upper panel), which is, however, offset by an indirect effect after some time. 
The indirect effect works through the shifts in the other segment (lower panel). 
The answer to the question-should the compatibility be reduced-consequently 
depends on the time frame across which the standard vendor attempts to maximize their 
usage shares. In the immediate future, the direct effect dominates (thus, compatibility 
should be decreased), after some time, this may be offset by indirect effect (thus, 
compatibility should be left as high as it is if this time frame is the relevant one). 
Given that competition between standards in reality is much less stylized with frequent 
new developments, innovations etc., many vendors may prefer to choose shorter time 
frames as the basis for their decisions. </p>

<p>4.2.4 Expansion into the Other Segment (Effect 5) </p>

<p>The commercial vendor of a standard in segment 1, standard i = 1, dissatisfied with 
her standard's compatibility with standards in segment 2, may consider to expand into </p>

<p>27 Note that p 2,t (with indices for segment and time, but without an index for the standard) denotes the 
vector of usage shares of segment 2 at time t. max( p 2,t ) thus denotes the highest usage share in this segment 
at this time. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>none 
th=1.5 
th=1.1 
th=1.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Effect of inter-segmental compatibility reduction. Depicted are the developments of usage shares 
of standards 1 in both segments where the compatibility between standard 1 in segment 1 and standard 2 in 
segment 2 is initialized as c 12 = 0.05, but is reduced to c 12 = 0 as soon as the usage share of standard 1 
in segment 1 reaches p 1,1,t = th × max( p 2,t with different threshold values th </p>

<p>this segment. She would thereby create a standard with a higher compatibility with 
her standard in segment 1. Starting with the basic setup as introduced above, a new 
standard in segment 2 is created with an initial usage share of p 3,2,t = 0.01 and the 
compatibility matrices are changed to accommodate this additional standard. 28 Both 
the effect of the usage share of standard i in segment 1 (with c 13 = 0.2) and that of the 
compatibility term with the new standard c 13 (with p 1,1,0 = 0.45) are studied (Fig. 6). 
In both experiments, the remainder of the second segment is initially shared equally 
between the other two standards in this segment. It is shown that the newly introduced 
standard is quickly able to corner the second segment, if the usage of standard i in 
the first segment was large enough before expanding into the second segment. This 
improves the position of standard i in the first segment further . </p>

<p>4.3 Agent-Based Simulation </p>

<p>4.3.1 Network Structure and Initial Usage Share (Effect 6) </p>

<p>The agent-based simulation is conducted in two steps: First, it is to be shown that the 
characteristic effects found for the macro-level replicator model either in the analytical 
setup or in the Monte Carlo simulations above, are still present in the agent-based 
version (otherwise they might be accidental results of the macro-level model). Second, </p>

<p>28 I.e. matrix A 2 now has to be a 3 × 3 matrix, C has to be a 2 × 3 matrix: A 2 = </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎝ </p>

<p>1 0.9 0.9 
0.9 1 0.9 
0.9 0.9 1 </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎠ , </p>

<p>C = 
0.1 0 c 13 
0 0.1 0 
. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>p(1,j,0)=0.60 
p(1,j,0)=0.55 
p(1,j,0)=0.45 
p(1,j,0)=0.40 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
200 
400 
600 
800 
1000 
1200 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>c(13)=0.5 
c(13)=0.4 
c(13)=0.3 
c(13)=0.2 
c(13)=0.1 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Effect of expansion into the second segment: an additional standard 3 is introduced in segment 2 
by the vendor of standard 1 in segment 1 (and has therefore high compatibility to standard 1 in segment 1). 
a Effect of initial usage share of standard 1 in segment 1 on usage shares p 1,1,t (upper panel), p 1,2,t and 
p 3,2,t (lower panel). b Effect of inter-segmental compatibility c 13 on usage shares p 1,1,t (upper panel), 
p 1,2,t and p 3,2,t (lower panel) </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.2 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.3 </p>

<p>p(1,j,0)=0.9 
p(1,j,0)=0.8 
p(1,j,0)=0.7 
p(1,j,0)=0.6 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.1 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.2 </p>

<p>c(12)=0.15 
c(12)=0.10 
c(12)=0.05 
c(12)=0.00 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 
300 
400 
500 
600 
700 
0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Time 
Shares S.3 </p>

<p>(a) 
(b) </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Three segment simulation run; depicted are the developments of usage shares of standards 1 in 
all three segments. a Effect of initial usage share of standard 1 in segment 1. b Effect of inter-segmental 
compatibility between standard 1 in segment 1 and standard 2 in segment 2 (other inter-segmental compati-
bilities are 0.1 between all standards 1 and between all standards 2 across all three segments, 0.0 otherwise) </p>

<p>the impact of the network structure and that of the initial share of total adopters 
( i p i, j,t ) can be investigated. 
Where not indicated otherwise, the agent-based simulations use the same parameter 
setup as the Monte Carlo simulations with 75% early adopters in each segment (25% 
of the agents as non-adopters). 29 A single time step indicates one agent reevaluating </p>

<p>29 The early adopters are randomly chosen from without regard of their specific position in the network. 
This may serve as a neutral benchmark case in which no strategic use of the positioning in the network is 
made; effect 9 changes this assumption and studies an example of strategical use of the network structure 
for the positioning of early adopters. The share of early adopters is more closely studied in effect 8. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>0 
2000 4000 6000 8000 10000 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0 
2000 4000 6000 8000 10000 
Time </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.2 </p>

<p>0 
2000 4000 6000 8000 10000 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0 
2000 4000 6000 8000 10000 
Time </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Development of usage shares in a two-segment model with two standards each, complete network, 
initial total usage shares 0.75. Absolute shares on the left hand side (blue curve: shares of standard 1, p 1 , 
the green curve gives 1 − p 2 , i.e. if read with an inverted scale the shares of standard 2), relative shares on 
the right hand side. (Colour figure online) </p>

<p>her adoption decisions, i.e. with N = 1000 agents and t max = 10000 time steps, the 
average agent will reevaluate her decision 10 times. As seen below, this leads to a 
rather slow development compared to what is to be expected in the real world and 
compared to the replicator dynamic above. 
Figure 10 shows the result of 9 example runs in a complete network for 9 differ-
ent initial relative shares of the second segment while the first segment is divided </p>

<p>p 1,0 = 
0.6 
0.4 
for all 9 runs. The simulations show that the monopolization towards </p>

<p>the pair of tied standards with the larger overall usage share as predicted above does 
occur and that it does occur in both segments. This was to be expected since the 
complete network was used in this case. Results for all network structures under con-
sideration here (for 100 runs per setting) are shown in a more compressed form (not 
the entire development, just the final usage shares) in Fig. 8. As would be expected, 
the resulting curve is s-shaped with very asymmetric starting distributions converg-
ing to monopolization much quicker; the effect can be reproduced for all network 
structures. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>p1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>Fig. 9 Initial relative usage shares: final usage share of standard 1, p 1 , depending on its initial relative usage 
shares, average and 90% interval of 100 runs for each setting. Network structures: a complete network, b 
regular ring grid, c Barabàsi-Albert d k = 1 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure, e k = 2 Barabàsi-Albert 
with triadic closure </p>

<p>4.3.2 Network Structure and Inter-segmental Compatibility (Effect 7) </p>

<p>To a lesser degree, this does also hold for the effects of inter-segmental compatibility 
as analyzed above and as shown in the results of agent-based studies in Figs. 9 and 
11. Considerable variation remains for some parameter values and some network 
structures; for the k = 1 preferential attachment network with triadic closure (diagram 
D in Figs. 9, 11), the effects are much less pronounced than for the other network 
types, but they certainly remain detectable. The effects are strongest in the case of the 
complete network (diagrams A) and the regular grid (diagrams B). Interestingly, this 
can also be said for values between p 1 = 0.2 and p 1 = 0.8 in the effect of the initial 
usage share in Fig. 8. Here too, the preferential attachment networks (and to a lesser 
degree the grid network in diagram B) lead to slightly less pronounced effect. The 
effect is clearly detectable but with a lot of variation. In the center, the clear s-shape of 
the curve does not appear to emerge in these cases. Asymmetric network structures (C 
through E) allow for more isolated (even clustered in cases D and E) subcommunities 
and consequently tend to preserve initial usage shares compared to any outside effects 
homogenizing the network. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.10 
0.15 
0.20 
0.25 
0.30 </p>

<p>c11 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>Fig. 10 Inter-segmental compatibility: final usage share of standard 1, p 1 , depending on inter-segmental 
compatibility with the tied partner standard, average and 90% interval of 100 runs for each setting. Network 
structures: a complete network, b regular ring grid, c Barabàsi-Albert, d k = 1 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic 
closure, e k = 2 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure </p>

<p>4.3.3 Initial Non-Adopters (Effect 8) </p>

<p>The effect of the initial total usage share ( i p i, j,0 ) is given in Fig. 12. Starting from </p>

<p>an initial equal sharing p j,0 = 
0.5 
0.5 
between the standards, the shares of the </p>

<p>then largest standard are studied after t max = 10,000 time steps. While the complete 
network leads to an asymmetric final distribution, particularly if the initial total usage 
share was low, this is not so much the case for the other network structures; particularly 
network structure D (k = 1 preferential attachment network with triadic closure) does </p>

<p>not deviate far from the initial distribution p j,0 = 
0.5 
0.5 
and also has a markedly </p>

<p>lower standard deviation. This is probably also a result of the presence of multitudes 
of isolated clusters. </p>

<p>4.3.4 Positioning of Initial Adopters (Effect 9) </p>

<p>This section considers Feld's (1991) friendship paradox as an example to demonstrate 
the potential of positioning in networks in this context. Many other effects of this family </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.00 
0.05 
0.10 
0.15 
0.20 
0.25 </p>

<p>c12 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>Fig. 11 Inter-segmental compatibility: final usage share of standard 1, p 1 , depending on inter-segmental 
compatibility with standards other than the tied partner, average and 90% interval of 100 runs for each setting. 
Network structures: a complete network, b regular ring grid, c Barabàsi-Albert, d k = 1 Barabàsi-Albert 
with triadic closure, e k = 2 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure </p>

<p>are conceivable. The "paradox" refers to the phenomenon that an agent's neighbors 
("friends") in a network with asymmetric degree distribution do on average have more 
neighbors and are thus more central. To study this effect, the competition between two 
standards, one with and one without the benefits of this phenomenon, is considered. The 
standard with the benefits of this effect selects random neighbors of arbitrarily chosen 
agents as initial adopters (Fig. 13). Unsurprisingly, it is found to have no effect in 
the network structures with homogeneous degree distributions (complete network and 
regular grid, A and B). For all other network structures, this leads to the s-shaped curve 
being changed to a concave one with the lower end (low initial shares) being inflated 
upwards. Hence, a network of moderately high to high final usage shares results from 
well-connected initial adopters. It should be noted that commercial vendors frequently 
seek to employ such a strategy (trying to win over more well-connected individuals 
first) by approaching institutions like universities with favorable contracts etc. </p>

<p>5 Evidence from the ICT Sector </p>

<p>While the literature does not offer any previous models on strategic use of network 
externalities and market power in the case of tied standards, there is a small literature 
tradition on product bundling (Choi 2004; Nalebuff 2004; Miao 2010; Eisenmann et al. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>Initial Share of Adopters </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>Fig. 12 Initial total usage shares: final usage share of largest standard in segment 1, max( p 1 , p 2 ), depending 
on initial total usage shares, average and 90% interval of 100 runs for each setting. Network structures: a 
complete network, b regular ring grid, c Barabàsi-Albert, d k = 1 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure, e 
k = 2 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure </p>

<p>2011) and there are some empirical observations that strongly imply the systematic 
employment of such strategies. This section will discuss a few examples from the ICT 
sector. 
Luksha (2008) recounts several cases of cooptation of organizational networks 
(supplier networks, user networks) by a dominant firm for its own purposes. His 
examples include Microsoft as the dominant player in the PC operating systems' 
segment forcing cooperation between the two major competitors in the PC processor 
segment (which is clearly tied to PC operating systems), Intel and AMD. Luksha also 
identifies firms that actively shape and coordinate their user networks, namely Sun 
(then the vendor of a wide array of IT products including <rs type="software">Java</rs>, <rs type="software">StarOffice</rs>, <rs type="software">MySQL</rs>, 
<rs type="software">Solaris</rs>), Google, and Intel. Luksha does not go into detail on this, but it is clear that this 
activity is targeted on entrenching and extending the dominant position and the usage 
shares of the various products. This can be done by bundling products (across tied 
segments), particularly, in case of firms that offer a wide variety of related products 
like Sun (at the time), Google, Apple, and Microsoft. It can also be accomplished 
by acquiring more well-connected users (say, university students and faculty) and 
perhaps by coercing the help of prominent institutions (say, by offering special deals 
to universities)-in fact, aggressive marketing to otherwise privileged user groups is 
rather common. The case of Sun's Java offers a prime example of a huge marketing </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Shares Segm.1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>p1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1.0 </p>

<p>p1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>(d) </p>

<p>(e) </p>

<p>Fig. 13 Friendship paradox: final usage share of standard 1, p 1 , depending on its initial relative usage shares 
with (left hand side) and without (left hand side) more central initial adopters for standard 1 (friendship 
paradox), average and 90% interval of 100 runs for each setting. Network structures: a complete network, b 
regular ring grid, c Barabàsi-Albert, d k = 1 Barabàsi-Albert with triadic closure, e k = 2 Barabàsi-Albert 
with triadic closure </p>

<p>campaign that was run to position the new standard in the mid 1990s, probably in full 
awareness of the intricacies of network externalities (Garud et al. 2002). 
Further, many successful commercial ICT standards started out by securing a tem-
porary bundling or at least a licensing cooperation with one of the major players in a 
tied subsector: Microsoft's success in the 1980s came after (and as a direct consequence 
of) its alliance with IBM in the 1970s; one of the first strategic actions of Sun's deploy-
ment of Java in 1995 was a licensing agreement with Microsoft (Garud et al. 2002); 
the three successful mobile operating systems (Android, iOS, Windows Mobile) were 
established by major vendors of other (tied) standards, the Google search engine (in 
combination with other Google online services) in case of Android and PC operating 
systems in case of Apple's iOS and Microsoft's Windows Mobile. Sure enough, they 
swiftly displaced the early mobile operating systems by less well-positioned vendors, 
such as Blackberry and Symbian (West and Mace 2010). 30 </p>

<p>30 Note that there is a strand of literature that analyzes technological change as successive emergence of 
sectors and segments within sectors (see e.g. Saviotti and Pyka 2008, 2013)-with all implications for tying 
between the respective standards; for the ICT sector, this is discussed by Bass and Bass (2001). </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>More recently there has been speculation about which segment is likely to determine 
the future development of the ongoing mobile device platform competition with some 
scholars arguing that attracting third-party developers is the most important aspect 
(Ghazawneh and Henfridsson 2013) while others contend that mobile online services 
(app stores, integration with social networks) play a crucial role compared to more 
traditional (software and hardware) segments (Kenney and Pon 2011). Specifically, 
the platforms that emerged as superior, Apple iOS, Google Android, and Windows 
Mobile were identified as those able to generate revenue in those services. An inter-
esting strategy may be that of Google, which generates its revenue and the network 
externalities crucial in keeping the platform competitive in entirely different segments 
(Kenney and Pon 2011). Note, however, that this particular analysis in Kenney and 
Pon (2011) does not place too much value on the integration of and compatibility 
among the segments; as the simulations above suggest, this may be another cru-
cial effect, which may be at the bottom of the success of the tightly closed Apple 
platform. </p>

<p>6 Conclusions </p>

<p>One of the open problems of the economic analysis of information and communication 
technologies is the problem of "tied" segments, i.e. in segments that are subject not 
only to network externalities originating in the same segments but also to those that 
unfold in other, connected segments. A practical example is provided by the large 
number of integrated software products in the ICT sector with the vendors of these 
products partly locked in fierce battles for dominance of one segment or another, and 
partly engaged in quests of integrating their products across segments and cementing 
their commanding position in those markets. 
The present article proposed a model for the analysis of standards in tied seg-
ments. In a simple replicator-dynamic model, the feasibility for commercial vendors 
of standards of making strategic use of network externalities acting within and across 
segments has been demonstrated. While initial usage share is-as variously pointed 
out by previous literature-crucially important for the success or failure of standards, 
it was shown that compatibility with other standards does have a considerable direct 
effect which may offset a low usage share. Compatibility is in this context understood 
as the interoperability between standards, the potential for users and groups of users 
to make efficient use of both standards at the same time. 
It was also shown, however, that there is a second, indirect effect of intersegmen-
tal compatibility which may make it desirable for sufficiently strong competitors to 
reduce certain compatibility terms. This may serve to extend the dominating position 
in one segment or to expand into another while displacing other standards there on the 
compatibility of which the earlier success of this competitor relied. It has been shown 
that the time scope of the consideration is one crucial element in choosing between 
reducing and maintaining compatibility-in the very short term, the direct effect will 
prevail. 
Nevertheless, a replicator model must remain at a fairly high level of abstraction. 
It derives its legitimacy from its claim of being an aggregated version of micro-level </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>dynamics-but does the micro level, if modelled explicitely actually follow this behav-
ior? For the present model, it could be shown in Sect. 3.2 that all results derived for 
the aggregated replicator dynamic version can be recovered in a fully agent-based 
model. Five different network structures were studied; the effects under considera-
tion could be found in all of them, though the effect of compatibility terms is much 
less pronounced in user network structures with asymmetric degree distributions and 
especially in those with local clusters (introduced in this case by triadic closure), 
and many network structures tend to preserve at least isolated niches of competing 
standards. 
Finally, the agent-based model also allowed an assessment of the potential role 
of the positioning of initial adopters in the network structure-as an example of this 
potentially vast class of effects, the strategic use of Feld's friendship paradox has been 
investigated-he effect is considerable for all network structures with asymmetric 
degree distribution (it cannot exist in regular grid networks). 
Unsurprisingly, ample evidence of strategic use of network effects along various 
lines can be found as well as detailed in Sect. 5. While the section focussed on the 
effects also studied on a theoretical level in this paper, it would be expected that most 
practical strategies would be more intricate, making use of not just the initial market 
share and interference with compatibility but also the network structure itself: The 
positioning of initial adopters can be manipulated through targeted advertisement. 
Strategic approaches would also not attempt positioning in the entire network (hence, 
the entire world) at once but focus on specific niches, niches that are large enough to 
form an installen base but clustered to withstand outside influences by other competi-
tors. With the rise of social media and big data, the knowledge about the social network 
structure has developed immensely and commercial vendorsm may soon develop the 
capability of influencing the network structure itself. 31 This would not only have a 
huge potential of upsetting established industry and market structures but would also 
entail pressing ethical questions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements For many helpful and instructive comments and discussions, I am grateful to Sidonia 
von Proff, Ben Vermeulen, Claudius Gräbner, Wolfram Elsner, to the participants of the Annual Meeting of 
the Evolutorischen Ausschuss of the Verein für Socialpolitik 2015, the Annual Conference of the European 
Association for Evolutionary and Political Economy 2015, and the Conference on Complex Systems 2015, 
as well as to two anonymous reviewers. All remaining errors are my own. </p>

<p>Compliance with Ethical Standards </p>

<p>Conflicts of interest There are no conflicts of interest. </p>

<p>Ethical Standard The research presented in this paper is in compliance with accepted ethical standards 
for good science. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Interna-
tional License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, </p>

<p>31 Aggressive attempts by social networks like Facebook and Linkedin to connect users that seem to isolated 
or too passive may represent first attempts of doing exactly that. Their practical merits may, however, seem 
questionable. </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>



<p>Appendix 1: Derivation of the Marginal Effects of the Compatibility 
Terms in the 2-Segment Replicator Model </p>

<p>From Eq. (1) the evolutionary fitness of standard 1 in segment 1 follows as </p>

<p>f 1,1,t = w 1,1 a 11,1 p 1,1,t + w 1,1 a 12,1 p 2,1,t + w 1,2 c 11,1,2 p 1,2,t + w 1,2 c 12,1,2 p 2,2,t </p>

<p>(and analogously that for standard 2 in segment 1). The average fitness in segment 
1 is </p>

<p>φ 1,t = w 1,1 a 11,1 p 2 
1,1,t + w 1,1 a 12,1 p 2,1,t p 1,1,t + w 1,1 a 21,1 p 1,1,t p 2,1,t 
+ w 1,1 a 22,1 p 2 
2,1,t + w 1,2 c 11,1,2 p 1,2,t p 1,1,t + w 1,2 c 12,1,2 p 2,2,t p 1,1,t 
+ w 1,2 c 21,1,2 p 1,2,t p 2,1,t + w 1,2 c 22,1,2 p 2,2,t p 2,1,t </p>

<p>and the usage share of standard 1 in segment 1 at time t + 1 follows as </p>

<p>p 1,1,t+1 = p 1,1,t + w 1,1 a 11,1 p 2 
1,1,t + w 1,1 a 12,1 p 2,1,t p 1,1,t + w 1,2 c 11,1,2 p 1,2,t p 1,1,t 
+ w 1,2 c 12,1,2 p 2,2,t p 1,1,t − w 1,1 a 11,1 p 3 
1,1,t − w 1,1 a 12,1 p 2,1,t p 2 </p>

<p>1,1,t </p>

<p>− w 1,1 a 21,1 p 2 
1,1,t p 2,1,t − w 1,1 a 22,1 p 2 
2,1,t p 1,1,t − w 1,2 c 11,1,2 p 1,2,t p 2 </p>

<p>1,1,t </p>

<p>− w 1,2 c 12,1,2 p 2,2,t p 2 
1,1,t − w 1,2 c 21,1,2 p 1,2,t p 2,1,t p 1,1,t 
− w 1,2 c 22,1,2 p 2,2,t p 2,1,t p 1,1,t . </p>

<p>and for p 2,1,t+1 analogously. The direct effects of different variables can now be 
studied; particularly the compatibility terms are of interest. For the terms of matrix A, </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 11,1 
= w 1,1 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t − a 11,1 p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1,1,t ≥ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 12,1 
= w 1,1 p 2,1,t p 1,1,t − w 1,1 p 2,1,t p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t ≥ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 21,1 
= −w 1,1 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t p 2,1,t ≤ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂a 22,1 
= −w 1,1 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2,1,t p 1,1,t ≤ 0 </p>

<p>and, specifically if A is to be symmetric, hence α = a 12,1 = a 21,1 , </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂α 
= w 1,1 p 2,1,t p 1,1,t − 2w 1,1 p 2,1,t p </p>

<p>2 
1,1,t </p>

<p>which is </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂α </p>

<p>&gt; 0 if, and only, if 0 &lt; p 1 , 1, t &lt; 0.5. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>

<p>The direct influence of the terms of the inter-segmental compatibility matrix C are 
obtained in the same way as </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 11,1,2 
= w 1,2 p 1,2,t p 1,1,t − w 1,2 p 1,2,t p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t ≥ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 12,1,2 
= w 1,2 p 2,2,t p 1,1,t − w 1,2 p 2,2,t p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t ≥ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 21,1,2 
= −w 1,2 p 1,2,t p 2,1,t p 1,1,t ≤ 0 </p>

<p>∂ p 1,1,t+1 
∂c 22,1,2 
= −w 1,2 p 2,2,t p 2,1,t p 1,1,t ≤ 0. </p>

<p>Appendix 2: Equilibrium and Stability Analysis of the Symmetric 2-
Segment Replicator Model </p>

<p>In this case, we have </p>

<p>A = 
1α 
α1 
p 1,1,t+1 = p 1,1,t + w 1,1 p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t + w 1,1 α(1 − p 1,1,t ) p 1,1,t − w 1,1 p </p>

<p>3 
1,1,t </p>

<p>− w 1,1 α(1 − p 1,1,t ) p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t − w 1,1 αp </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t (1 − p 1,1,t ) 
− w 1,1 (1 − p 1,1,t ) 
2 p 1,1,t </p>

<p>= p 1,1,t + w 1,1 p 1,1,t (1 − p 1,1,t )( p 1,1,t + α − αp 1,1,t − αp 1,1,t </p>

<p>− (1 − p 1,1,t )) = p 1,1,t + w 1,1 p 1,1,t (1 − p 1,1,t )(2 p 1,1,t 
− 2αp 1,1,t − 1 + α) </p>

<p>= p 1,1,t + w 1,1 p 1,1,t (1 − p 1,1,t )(1 − α)(2 p 1,1,t − 1) </p>

<p>= −2w 1,1 (1 − α) p </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>1,1,t + 3w 1,1 (1 − α) p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t + (1 − (1 − α)w 1,1 ) p 1,1,t </p>

<p>which has the equilibrium set (most easily seen from the second-to last form) </p>

<p>0 = w 1,1 p 1,1 (1 − p 1,1 )(1 − α)(2 p 1,1 − 1) </p>

<p>with solutions (assuming w 1,1 = 0) </p>

<p>p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1,1,1 = 0 
p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1,1,2 = 1 
p </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>1,1,3 = 0.5 </p>

<p>and stability conditions following from the system's eigenvalue λ (linearized for the 
equilibria) with the equilibrium being stable if, and only if, |λ| &lt; 1. </p>

<p>λ = 
∂ p 1,1,t+1 ( p 1,1,t ) 
∂ p 1,1,t 
= −6w 1,1 (1 − α) p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1,1,t + 6w 1,1 (1 − α) p 1,1,t </p>

<p>+ (1 − (1 − α)w 1,1 ), </p>



<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>

<p>thus </p>

<p>λ( p  *  
1,1,1 ) = λ(0) = 1 − (1 − α)w 1,1 
λ( p  *  
1,1,2 ) = λ(1) = 1 − (1 − α)w 1,1 
λ( p  *  
1,1,3 ) = λ(0.5) = </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 (1 − α)w 1,1 + 1. </p>

<p>The first two equilibria are thus stable if w 1,1 is small enough in comparison to α, 32 
specifically if 2 &gt; (1 − α)w 1,1 . These are the monopolization equilibria. The third 
equilibrium, the tipping point, is never stable. An equilibrium and stability anal-
ysis for the continuous form of the system for specific numerical examples with 
non-vanishing inter-segmental compatibility matrix (but vanishing intra-segmental 
compatibility term) is conducted in Heinrich (2014) with very similar results (i.e. 
stable monopolization equilibria but unstable tipping point equilibrium). </p>



<p>32 If w 1,1 is too large, the discrete system is not an adequate discretization to the continuous system from 
which it is derived above as the discrete form would in this case not only destabilize the equilibria but also 
likely violate the restrictions of 0 ≤ p i, j,t ≤ 1 which must hold since the p i, j,t are usage shares. </p>



<p>T. Heinrich </p>





<p>Network Externalities and Compatibility Among Standards... </p>





</text></tei>