<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.31.2.211" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Definition and History 
We define "fake news" to be news articles that are intentionally and verifiably 
false, and could mislead readers. We focus on fake news articles that have political 
implications, with special attention to the 2016 US presidential elections. Our defi-
nition includes intentionally fabricated news articles, such as a widely shared article 
from the now-defunct website denverguardian.com with the headline, "FBI agent 
suspected in Hillary email leaks found dead in apparent murder-suicide." It also 
includes many articles that originate on satirical websites but could be misunder-
stood as factual, especially when viewed in isolation on Twitter or Facebook feeds. 
For example, in July 2016, the now-defunct website wtoe5news.com reported that </p>



<p>Pope Francis had endorsed Donald Trump's presidential candidacy. The WTOE 5 
News "About" page disclosed that it is "a fantasy news website. Most articles on wtoe-
5news.com are satire or pure fantasy," but this disclaimer was not included in the 
article. The story was shared more than one million times on Facebook, and some 
people in our survey described below reported believing the headline. 
Our definition rules out several close cousins of fake news: 1) unintentional 
reporting mistakes, such as a recent incorrect report that Donald Trump had 
removed a bust of Martin Luther King Jr. from the Oval Office in the White House; 
2) rumors that do not originate from a particular news article; 
1 3) conspiracy theo-</p>

<p>ries (these are, by definition, difficult to verify as true or false, and they are typically 
originated by people who believe them to be true); 
2 4) satire that is unlikely to be </p>

<p>misconstrued as factual; 5) false statements by politicians; and 6) reports that are 
slanted or misleading but not outright false (in the language of Gentzkow, Shapiro, 
and Stone 2016, fake news is "distortion," not "filtering"). 
Fake news and its cousins are not new. One historical example is the "Great 
Moon Hoax" of 1835, in which the New York Sun published a series of articles about 
the discovery of life on the moon. A more recent example is the 2006 "Flemish 
Secession Hoax," in which a Belgian public television station reported that the 
Flemish parliament had declared independence from Belgium, a report that a 
large number of viewers misunderstood as true. Supermarket tabloids such as the 
National Enquirer and the Weekly World News have long trafficked in a mix of partially 
true and outright false stories. 
Figure 1 lists 12 conspiracy theories with political implications that have circu-
lated over the past half-century. Using polling data compiled by the American 
Enterprise Institute (2013), this figure plots the share of people who believed each 
statement is true, from polls conducted in the listed year. For example, substantial 
minorities of Americans believed at various times that Franklin Roosevelt had prior 
knowledge of the Pearl Harbor bombing, that Lyndon Johnson was involved in the 
Kennedy assassination, that the US government actively participated in the 9/11 
bombings, and that Barack Obama was born in another country. 
The long history of fake news notwithstanding, there are several reasons to 
think that fake news is of growing importance. First, barriers to entry in the media 
industry have dropped precipitously, both because it is now easy to set up websites 
and because it is easy to monetize web content through advertising platforms. 
Because reputational concerns discourage mass media outlets from knowingly 
reporting false stories, higher entry barriers limit false reporting. Second, as we 
discuss below, social media are well-suited for fake news dissemination, and social </p>

<p>1 Sunstein (2007) defines rumors as "claims of fact-about people, groups, events, and institutions-that 
have not been shown to be true, but that move from one person to another, and hence have credibility 
not because direct evidence is available to support them, but because other people seem to believe 
them." 
2 Keeley (1999) defines a conspiracy theory as "a proposed explanation of some historical event (or events) 
in terms of the significant causal agency of a relatively small group of persons-the conspirators--acting 
in secret." </p>

<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 215 </p>

<p>media use has risen sharply: in 2016, active Facebook users per month reached 1.8 
billion and Twitter's approached 400 million. Third, as shown in Figure 2A, Gallup 
polls reveal a continuing decline of "trust and confidence" in the mass media "when 
it comes to reporting the news fully, accurately, and fairly." This decline is more 
marked among Republicans than Democrats, and there is a particularly sharp 
drop among Republicans in 2016. The declining trust in mainstream media could 
be both a cause and a consequence of fake news gaining more traction. Fourth, 
Figure 2B shows one measure of the rise of political polarization: the increasingly 
negative feelings each side of the political spectrum holds toward the other. 
3 As we </p>

<p>3 The extent to which polarization of voters has increased, along with the extent to which it has been 
driven by shifts in attitudes on the right or the left or both, are widely debated topics. See Abramowitz 
and Saunders (2008), Fiorina and Abrams (2008), Prior (2013), and Lelkes (2016) for reviews. </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Share of Americans Believing Historical Partisan Conspiracy Theories </p>

<p>Note: From polling data compiled by the American Enterprise Institute (2013), we selected all 
conspiracy theories with political implications. This figure plots the share of people who report 
believing the statement listed, using opinion polls from the date listed. </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 </p>

<p>Share of people who believe it is true (%) </p>

<p>2010: Barack Obama was born in another country </p>

<p>2007: US government actively planned or 
assisted some aspects of the 9/11 attacks </p>

<p>2007: US government knew the 9/11 attacks were 
coming but consciously let them proceed </p>

<p>2003: Bush administration purposely misled the public 
about evidence that Iraq had banned weapons </p>

<p>2003: Lyndon Johnson was involved in the 
assassination of John Kennedy in 1963 </p>

<p>1999: The crash of TWA Flight 800 over Long Island 
was an accidental strike by a US Navy missile </p>

<p>1995: Vincent Foster, the former aide to 
President Bill Clinton, was murdered </p>

<p>1995: US government bombed the government building 
in Oklahoma City to blame extremist groups </p>

<p>1995: FBI deliberately set the Waco re 
in which the Branch Davidians died </p>

<p>1994: The Nazi extermination of millions 
of Jews did not take place </p>

<p>1991: President Franklin Roosevelt knew Japanese 
plans to bomb Pearl Harbor but did nothing </p>

<p>1975: The assassination of Martin Luther King 
was the act of part of a large conspiracy </p>



<p>Figure 2 
Trends Related to Fake News </p>

<p>Note: Panel A shows the percent of Americans who say that they have "a great deal" or "a fair 
amount" of "trust and confidence" in the mass media "when it comes to reporting the news fully, 
accurately, and fairly," using Gallup poll data reported in Swift (2016). Panel B shows the average 
"feeling thermometer" (with 100 meaning "very warm or favorable feeling" and 0 meaning "very 
cold or unfavorable feeling") of Republicans toward the Democratic Party and of Democrats 
toward the Republican Party, using data from the American National Election Studies (2012). </p>

<p>A: Trust in Mainstream Media </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Percent Great deal/Fair amount </p>

<p>1998 
2002 
2006 
2010 
2014 </p>

<p>Overall </p>

<p>B: Feeling Thermometer toward Other Political Party </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Feeling thermometer </p>

<p>(0 = least positive, 100 = most) </p>

<p>1980 
1984 
1988 
1992 
1996 
2000 
2004 
2008 
2012 </p>

<p>Republicans' feeling thermometer 
toward Democratic Party </p>

<p>Democrats' feeling thermometer 
toward Republican Party </p>

<p>Democrats </p>

<p>Republicans </p>

<p>Hunt Allcott and Matthew Gentzkow 217 </p>

<p>discuss below, this could affect how likely each side is to believe negative fake news 
stories about the other. </p>

<p>Who Produces Fake News? 
Fake news articles originate on several types of websites. For example, some 
sites are established entirely to print intentionally fabricated and misleading 
articles, such as the above example of denverguardian.com. The names of these 
sites are often chosen to resemble those of legitimate news organizations. Other 
satirical sites contain articles that might be interpreted as factual when seen out 
of context, such as the above example of wtoe5news.com. Still other sites, such as 
endingthefed.com, print a mix between factual articles, often with a partisan slant, 
along with some false articles. Websites supplying fake news tend to be short-lived, 
and many that were important in the run-up to the 2016 election no longer exist. 
Anecdotal reports that have emerged following the 2016 election provide 
a partial picture of the providers behind these sites. Separate investigations by 
BuzzFeed and the Guardian revealed that more than 100 sites posting fake news 
were run by teenagers in the small town of Veles, Macedonia (Subramanian 2017). 
Endingthefed.com, a site that was responsible for four of the ten most popular 
fake news stories on Facebook, was run by a 24-year-old Romanian man (Townsend 
2016). A US company called Disinfomedia owns many fake news sites, including 
NationalReport.net, USAToday.com.co, and WashingtonPost.com.co, and its owner 
claims to employ between 20 and 25 writers (Sydell 2016). Another US-based 
producer, Paul Horner, ran a successful fake news site called National Report for 
years prior to the election (Dewey 2014). Among his most-circulated stories was 
a 2013 report that President Obama used his own money to keep open a Muslim 
museum during the federal government shutdown. During the election, Horner 
produced a large number of mainly pro-Trump stories (Dewey 2016). 
There appear to be two main motivations for providing fake news. The first 
is pecuniary: news articles that go viral on social media can draw significant adver-
tising revenue when users click to the original site. This appears to have been the 
main motivation for most of the producers whose identities have been revealed. The 
teenagers in Veles, for example, produced stories favoring both Trump and Clinton 
that earned them tens of thousands of dollars (Subramanian 2017). Paul Horner 
produced pro-Trump stories for profit, despite claiming to be personally opposed to 
Trump (Dewey 2016). The second motivation is ideological. Some fake news providers 
seek to advance candidates they favor. The Romanian man who ran endingthefed. 
com, for example, claims that he started the site mainly to help Donald Trump's 
campaign (Townsend 2016). Other providers of right-wing fake news actually say 
they identify as left-wing and wanted to embarrass those on the right by showing that 
they would credulously circulate false stories (Dewey 2016; Sydell 2016). </p>

<p>A Model of Fake News 
How is fake news different from biased or slanted media more broadly? Is 
it an innocuous form of entertainment, like fictional films or novels? Or does it </p>



<p>have larger social costs? To answer these questions, we sketch a model of supply 
and demand for news loosely based on a model developed formally in Gentzkow, 
Shapiro, and Stone (2016). 
There are two possible unobserved states of the world, which could represent 
whether a left-or right-leaning candidate will perform better in office. Media firms 
receive signals that are informative about the true state, and they may differ in the 
precision of these signals. We can also imagine that firms can make costly invest-
ments to increase the accuracy of these signals. Each firm has a reporting strategy 
that maps from the signals it receives to the news reports that it publishes. Firms 
can either decide to report signals truthfully, or alternatively to add bias to reports. 
Consumers are endowed with heterogeneous priors about the state of the world. 
Liberal consumers' priors hold that the left-leaning candidate will perform better in 
office, while conservative consumers' priors hold that the right-leaning candidate 
will perform better. Consumers receive utility through two channels. First, they want 
to know the truth. In our model, consumers must choose an action, which could 
represent advocating or voting for a candidate, and they receive private benefits if 
they choose the candidate they would prefer if they were fully informed. Second, 
consumers may derive psychological utility from seeing reports that are consistent 
with their priors. Consumers choose the firms from which they will consume news 
in order to maximize their own expected utility. They then use the content of the 
news reports they have consumed to form a posterior about the state of the world. 
Thus, consumers face a tradeoff: they have a private incentive to consume precise 
and unbiased news, but they also receive psychological utility from confirmatory 
news. 
After consumers choose their actions, they may receive additional feedback 
about the true state of the world-for example, as a candidate's performance is 
observed while in office. Consumers then update their beliefs about the quality of 
media firms and choose which to consume in future periods. The profits of media 
firms increase in their number of consumers due to advertising revenue, and media 
firms have an incentive to build a reputation for delivering high levels of utility 
to consumers. There are also positive social externalities if consumers choose the 
higher-quality candidate. 
In this model, two distinct incentives may lead firms to distort their reports in the 
direction of consumers' priors. First, when feedback about the true state is limited, 
rational consumers will judge a firm to be higher quality when its reports are closer 
to the consumers' priors (Gentzkow and Shapiro 2006). Second, consumers may 
prefer reports that confirm their priors due to psychological utility ( Mullainathan 
and Shleifer 2005). Gentzkow, Shapiro, and Stone (2016) show how these incen-
tives can lead to biased reporting in equilibrium, and apply variants of this model to 
understand outcomes in traditional "mainstream" media. 
How would we understand fake news in the context of such a model? Producers 
of fake news are firms with two distinguishing characteristics. First, they make no 
investment in accurate reporting, so their underlying signals are uncorrelated with 
the true state. Second, they do not attempt to build a long-term reputation for </p>

<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 219 </p>

<p>quality, but rather maximize the short-run profits from attracting clicks in an initial 
period. Capturing precisely how this competition plays out on social media would 
require extending the model to include multiple steps where consumers see "head-
lines" and then decide whether to "click" to learn more detail. But loosely speaking, 
we can imagine that such firms attract demand because consumers cannot distin-
guish them from higher-quality outlets, and also because their reports are tailored 
to deliver psychological utility to consumers on either the left or right of the polit-
ical spectrum. 
Adding fake news producers to a market has several potential social costs. First, 
consumers who mistake a fake outlet for a legitimate one have less-accurate beliefs 
and are worse off for that reason. Second, these less-accurate beliefs may reduce 
positive social externalities, undermining the ability of the democratic process to 
select high-quality candidates. Third, consumers may also become more skeptical 
of legitimate news producers, to the extent that they become hard to distinguish 
from fake news producers. Fourth, these effects may be reinforced in equilibrium by 
supply-side responses: a reduced demand for high-precision, low-bias reporting will 
reduce the incentives to invest in accurate reporting and truthfully report signals. 
These negative effects trade off against any welfare gain that arises from consumers 
who enjoy reading fake news reports that are consistent with their priors. </p>

<p>Real Data on Fake News </p>

<p>Fake News Database 
We gathered a database of fake news articles that circulated in the three 
months before the 2016 election, using lists from three independent third parties. 
First, we scraped all stories from the Donald Trump and Hillary Clinton tags on 
Snopes (snopes.com), which calls itself "the definitive Internet reference source for 
urban legends, folklore, myths, rumors, and misinformation." Second, we scraped 
all stories from the 2016 presidential election tag from PolitiFact (politifact.com), 
another major fact-checking site. Third, we use a list of 21 fake news articles that 
had received significant engagement on Facebook, as compiled by the news outlet 
BuzzFeed (Silverman 2016). 
4 Combining these three lists, we have a database of </p>

<p>156 fake news articles. We then gathered the total number of times each article was 
shared on Facebook as of early December 2016, using an online content database 
called BuzzSumo (buzzsumo.com). We code each article's content as either pro-
Clinton (including anti-Trump) or pro-Trump (including anti-Clinton). 
This list is a reasonable but probably not comprehensive sample of the major 
fake news stories that circulated before the election. One measure of comprehen-
siveness is to look at the overlap between the lists of stories from Snopes, PolitiFact, 
and BuzzFeed. Snopes is our largest list, including 138 of our total of 156 articles. As </p>

<p>4 Of these 21 articles, 12 were fact-checked on Snopes. Nine were rated as "false," and the other three 
were rated "mixture," "unproven," and "mostly false." </p>



<p>a benchmark, 12 of the 21 articles in the BuzzFeed list appear in Snopes, and 4 of 
the 13 articles in the PolitiFact appear in Snopes. The lack of perfect overlap shows 
that none of these lists is complete and suggests that there may be other fake news 
articles that are omitted from our database. </p>

<p>Post-Election Survey 
During the week of November 28, 2016, we conducted an online survey of 
1208 US adults aged 18 and over using the <rs type="software">SurveyMonkey</rs> platform. The sample 
was drawn from SurveyMonkey's Audience Panel, an opt-in panel recruited from 
the more than 30 million people who complete SurveyMonkey surveys every month 
(as described in more detail at https://www.surveymonkey.com/mp/audience/). 
The survey consisted of four sections. First, we acquired consent to participate 
and a commitment to provide thoughtful answers, which we hoped would improve 
data quality. Those who did not agree were disqualified from the survey. Second, 
we asked a series of demographic questions, including political affiliation before 
the 2016 campaign, vote in the 2016 presidential election, education, and race/ 
ethnicity. Third, we asked about 2016 election news consumption, including time 
spent on reading, watching, or listening to election news in general and on social 
media in particular, and the most important source of news and information about 
the 2016 election. Fourth, we showed each respondent 15 news headlines about the 
2016 election. For each headline, we asked, "Do you recall seeing this reported or 
discussed prior to the election?" and "At the time of the election, would your best 
guess have been that this statement was true?" We also received age and income 
categories, gender, and census division from profiling questions that respondents 
had completed when they first started taking surveys on the Audience panel. The 
survey instrument can be accessed at https://www.surveymonkey.com/r/RSYD75P. 
Each respondent's 15 news headlines were randomly selected from a list of 
30 news headlines, six from each of five categories. Within each category, our list 
contains an equal split of pro-Clinton and pro-Trump headlines, so 15 of the 30 arti-
cles favored Clinton, and the other 15 favored Trump. The first category contains 
six fake news stories mentioned in three mainstream media articles (one in the New 
York Times, one in the Wall Street Journal, and one in BuzzFeed) discussing fake news 
during the week of November 14, 2016. The second category contains the four 
most recent pre-election headlines from each of Snopes and PolitiFact deemed to 
be unambiguously false. We refer to these two categories individually as "Big Fake" 
and "Small Fake," respectively, or collectively as "Fake." The third category contains 
the most recent six major election stories from the Guardian's election timeline. 
We refer to these as "Big True" stories. The fourth category contains the two most 
recent pre-election headlines from each of Snopes and PolitiFact deemed to be 
unambiguously true. We refer to these as "Small True" stories. Our headlines in 
these four categories appeared on or before November 7. 
The fifth and final category contains invented "Placebo" fake news headlines, 
which parallel placebo conspiracy theories employed in surveys by Oliver and Wood 
(2014) and Chapman University (2016). As we explain below, we include these </p>

<p>Hunt Allcott and Matthew Gentzkow 221 </p>

<p>Placebo headlines to help control for false recall in survey responses. We invented 
three damaging fake headlines that could apply to either Clinton or Trump, then 
randomized whether a survey respondent saw the pro-Clinton or pro-Trump 
version. We experimented with several alternative placebo headlines during a pilot 
survey, and we chose these three because the data showed them to be approxi-
mately equally believable as the "Small Fake" stories. (We confirmed using Google 
searches that none of the Placebo stories had appeared in actual fake news arti-
cles.) Online Appendix Table 1, available with this article at this journal's website 
(http://e-jep.org), lists the exact text of the headlines presented in the survey. The 
online Appendix also presents a model of survey responses that makes precise the 
conditions under which differencing with respect to the placebo articles leads to 
valid inference. 
Yeager et al. (2011) and others have shown that opt-in internet panels such 
as ours typically do not provide nationally representative results, even after 
reweighting. Notwithstanding, reweighting on observable variables such as educa-
tion and internet usage can help to address the sample selection biases inherent in 
an opt-in internet-based sampling frame. For all results reported below, we reweight 
the online sample to match the nationwide adult population on ten character-
istics that we hypothesized might be correlated with survey responses, including 
income, education, gender, age, ethnicity, political party affiliation, and how often 
the respondent reported consuming news from the web and from social media. The 
online Appendix includes summary statistics for these variables; our unweighted 
sample is disproportionately well-educated, female, and Caucasian, and those who 
rely relatively heavily on the web and social media for news. The Appendix also 
includes additional information on data construction. </p>

<p>Social Media as a Source of Political Information </p>

<p>The theoretical framework we sketched above suggests several reasons why social 
media platforms may be especially conducive to fake news. First, on social media, 
the fixed costs of entering the market and producing content are vanishingly small. 
This increases the relative profitability of the small-scale, short-term strategies often 
adopted by fake news producers, and reduces the relative importance of building a 
long-term reputation for quality. Second, the format of social media-thin slices of 
information viewed on phones or news feed windows-can make it difficult to judge 
an article's veracity. Third, Bakshy, Messing, and Adamic (2015) show that Facebook 
friend networks are ideologically segregated-among friendships between people 
who report ideological affiliations in their profiles, the median share of friends with 
the opposite ideology is only 20 percent for liberals and 18 percent for conserva-
tives-and people are considerably more likely to read and share news articles that 
are aligned with their ideological positions. This suggests that people who get news 
from Facebook (or other social media) are less likely to receive evidence about the 
true state of the world that would counter an ideologically aligned but false story. </p>



<p>One way to gauge the importance of social media for fake news suppliers is to 
measure the source of their web traffic. Each time a user visits a webpage, that user 
has either navigated directly (for example, by typing www.wsj.com into a browser) 
or has been referred from some other site. Major referral sources include social 
media (for example, clicking on a link in the Facebook news feed) and search 
engines (for example, searching for "Pope endorsed Trump?" on Google and 
clicking on a search result). Figure 3 presents web traffic sources for the month 
around the 2016 US presidential election (late October through late November) 
from Alexa (alexa.com), which gathers data from browser extensions installed 
on people's computers as well as from measurement services offered to websites. 
These data exclude mobile browsing and do not capture news viewed directly on 
social media sites, for example, when people read headlines within Facebook or 
Twitter news feeds. 
The upper part of the graph presents referral sources for the top 690 US news 
sites, as ranked by Alexa. The lower part of the graph presents web traffic sources for 
a list of 65 major fake news sites, which we gathered from lists compiled by Zimdars 
(2016) and Brayton (2016). For the top news sites, social media referrals represent 
only about 10 percent of total traffic. By contrast, fake news websites rely on social </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Share of Visits to US News Websites by Source </p>

<p>Note: This figure presents the share of traffic from different sources for the top 690 US news 
websites and for 65 fake news websites. "Other links" means impressions that were referred from 
sources other than search engines and social media. "Direct browsing" means impressions that did 
not have a referral source. Sites are weighted by number of monthly visits. Data are from Alexa. </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 
Weighted average of percentage (%) </p>

<p>Fake news sites </p>

<p>Top news sites </p>

<p>Other links </p>

<p>Other 
links 
10.6 </p>

<p>Other 
links 
5.7 </p>

<p>Direct 
browsing 
48.7 </p>

<p>Direct 
browsing 
30.5 </p>

<p>Search 
engines 
30.6 </p>

<p>Search 
engines 
22.0 </p>

<p>Social 
media 
10.1 </p>

<p>Social 
media 
41.8 </p>

<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 223 </p>

<p>media for a much higher share of their traffic. This demonstrates the importance 
of social media for fake news providers. While there is no definitive list of fake news 
sites, and one might disagree with the inclusion or exclusion of particular sites in 
this list of 65, this core point about the importance of social media for fake news 
providers is likely to be robust. 
A recent Pew survey (Gottfried and Shearer 2016) finds that 62 percent of US 
adults get news from social media. To the extent that fake news is socially costly and 
fake news is prevalent on social media, this statistic could appear to be cause for 
concern. Of this 62 percent, however, only 18 percent report that they get news from 
social media "often," 26 percent do so "sometimes," and 18 percent do so "hardly 
ever." By comparison, the shares who "often" get news from local television, national 
broadcast television, and cable television are 46 percent, 30 percent, and 31 percent 
respectively. Moreover, only 34 percent of web-using adults trust the information 
they get from social media "some" or "a lot." By contrast, this share is 76 percent for 
national news organizations and 82 percent for local news organizations. 
The results of our post-election survey are broadly consistent with this picture. 
For the month before the 2016 election, our respondents report spending 66 
minutes per day reading, watching, or listening to election news. (Again, these and 
all other survey results are weighted for national representativeness.) Of this, 25 
minutes (38 percent) was on social media. Our survey then asked, "Which of these 
sources was your most important source of news and information about the 2016 
election?" The word "important" was designed to elicit a combination of consump-
tion frequency and trust in information. Figure 4 presents responses. In order, the 
four most common responses are cable TV, network TV, websites, and local TV. 
Social media is the fifth most common response, with 14 percent of US adults listing 
social media as their most "important" news source. 
Taken together, these results suggest that social media have become an impor-
tant but not dominant source of political news and information. Television remains 
more important by a large margin. </p>

<p>Partisanship of Fake News </p>

<p>In our fake news database, we record 41 pro-Clinton (or anti-Trump) and 115 
pro-Trump (or anti-Clinton) articles, which were shared on Facebook a total of 
7.6 million and 30.3 million times, respectively. Thus, there are about three times 
more fake pro-Trump articles than pro-Clinton articles, and the average pro-Trump 
article was shared more on Facebook than the average pro-Clinton article. To be 
clear, these statistics show that more of the fake news articles on these three fact-
checking sites are right-leaning. This could be because more of the actual fake news 
is right-leaning, or because more right-leaning assertions are forwarded to and/or 
reported by fact-checking sites, or because the conclusions that fact-checking sites 
draw have a left-leaning bias, or some combination. Some anecdotal reports support 
the idea that the majority of election-related fake news was pro-Trump: some fake </p>



<p>news providers reportedly found higher demand for pro-Trump (or anti-Clinton) 
fake news, and responded by providing more of it (Sydell 2016). 
There could be several possible explanations for a preponderance of pro-
Trump fake news. The more marked decline of trust in the mainstream media 
among Republicans shown in Figure 2 could have increased their relative demand 
for news from nontraditional sources, as could a perception that the mainstream 
media tended to favor Clinton. Pro-Trump (and anti-Clinton) storylines may have 
simply been more compelling than pro-Clinton (and anti-Trump) storylines due to 
particulars of these candidates, perhaps related to the high levels of media attention 
that Trump received throughout the campaign. Or, it could theoretically be that 
Republicans are for some reason more likely to enjoy or believe fake news. 
Some prior evidence argues against the last hypothesis. McClosky and Chong 
(1985) and Uscinski, Klofstad, and Atkinson (2016) find that people on the left 
and right are equally disposed to conspiratorial thinking. Furthermore, Bakshy, 
Messing, and Adamic (2015) find that conservatives are actually exposed to more 
cross-cutting news content than liberals, which could help conservatives to be better 
at detecting partisan fake news. Below, we present further evidence on this hypoth-
esis from our survey. </p>

<p>Figure 4 
Most Important Source of 2016 Election News </p>

<p>Notes: Our post-election survey asked, "Which of these sources was your most important source 
of news and information about the 2016 election?" This figure plots responses. Observations are 
weighted for national representativeness. </p>

<p>Radio </p>

<p>Print </p>

<p>Social 
media </p>

<p>Local TV </p>

<p>Website </p>

<p>Network TV </p>

<p>Cable TV </p>

<p>6.2% </p>

<p>8.0% </p>

<p>13.8% </p>

<p>14.5% </p>

<p>14.8% </p>

<p>19.2% </p>

<p>23.5% </p>

<p>Hunt Allcott and Matthew Gentzkow 225 </p>

<p>Exposure to Fake News </p>

<p>How much fake news did the typical voter see in the run-up to the 2016 elec-
tion? While there is a long literature measuring media exposure (for example, Price 
and Zaller 1993), fake news presents a particular challenge: much of its circulation 
is on Facebook (and other social media) news feeds, and these data are not public. 
We provide three benchmarks for election-period fake news exposure, which we 
report as average exposure for each of the 248 million American adults. 
First, we can use prior evidence to predict the number of times the articles 
in our database were read based on the number of times they were shared. The 
corporate website of Eventbrite (2012) reports that links to its events on Facebook 
generate 14 page visits per share. A blog post by Jessica Novak (undated) reports 
that for a set of "top performing" stories on Facebook the ratio of visits to shares 
was also 14. Zhao, Wang, Tao, Ma, and Guan (2013) report that the ratio of views to 
shares for videos on the Chinese social networking site Renren ranges from 3 to 8. 
Based on these very rough reference points, we consider a ratio of 20 page visits per 
share as an upper bound on the plausible range. This implies that the 38 million 
shares of fake news in our database translate into 760 million page visits, or about 
three visits per US adult. 
Second, we can use web browsing data to measure impressions on fake news 
websites. For the month around the 2016 election, there were 159 million impres-
sions on the 65 websites in the bottom part of Figure 3, or 0.64 impressions per 
adult. This is dwarfed by the 3 billion impressions on the 665 top news websites over 
the same period. Furthermore, not all content on these 65 sites is false: in a random 
sample of articles from these sites, we categorized just under 55 percent as false, 
either because the claim was refuted by a mainstream news site or fact-checking 
organization, or because the claim was not covered on any other sites despite being 
important enough that it would have been covered on other sites if it were true. 
When comparing these first two approaches to estimating election-period fake news 
exposure, remember that the first approach uses cumulative Facebook shares as 
of early December 2016 for fake news articles that were fact-checked in the three 
months before the election, while the second approach uses web traffic from a one 
month period between late October to late November 2016. 
Third, we can use our post-election survey to estimate the number of articles 
respondents saw and remembered. The survey gave respondents 15 news head-
lines-three headlines randomly selected from each of the five categories detailed 
earlier-and asked if they recalled seeing the headline ("Do you recall seeing this 
reported or discussed prior to the election?") and if they believed it ("At the time of 
the election, would your best guess have been that this statement was true?"). 
Figure 5 presents the share of respondents that recalled seeing (left bar) and 
seeing and believing (right bar) headlines, averaging responses across all the head-
lines within each of our main categories. Rates of both seeing and believing are 
much higher for true than fake stories, and they are substantially higher for the 
"Big True" headlines (the major headlines leading up to the election) than for the </p>



<p>"Small True" headlines (the minor fact-checked headlines that we gathered from 
Snopes and PolitiFact). The Placebo fake news articles, which never actually circu-
lated, are approximately equally likely to be recalled and believed as the Fake news 
articles which did actually circulate. This implies that there is a meaningful rate of 
false recall of articles that people never actually saw, which could cause the survey 
measure to significantly overstate true exposure. On the other hand, people likely 
forgot some of the Fake articles that they were actually exposed to, which causes the 
survey responses to understate true exposure. 
In summary, one can think of recalled exposure as determined both by actual 
exposure and by the headline's perceived plausibility-people might think that if a 
headline is plausible, they probably saw it reported somewhere. Then, we show that 
if the Placebo headlines are equally plausible as the Fake headlines, the difference 
between recall of Fake and Placebo headlines represents the rate of true exposure that 
was remembered. The Appendix available online with this paper at http://e-jep.org 
presents additional theoretical and empirical discussion of false recall in our data. </p>

<p>Figure 5 
Percent of US Adult Population that Recall Seeing or that Believed Election 
News </p>

<p>Notes: In our post-election survey, we presented 15 headlines. For each headline, the survey asked 
whether respondents recall seeing the headline ("Do you recall seeing this reported or discussed 
before the election?") and whether they believed it ("At the time of the election, would your best 
guess have been that this statement was true?"). The left bars present the share of respondents who 
recall seeing the headlines in each category, and the right bars present the share of respondents 
who recall seeing and believed the headlines. "Big True" headlines are major headlines leading up 
to the election; "Small True" headlines are the minor fact-checked headlines that we gathered from 
Snopes and PolitiFact. The Placebo fake news headlines were made-up for the research and never 
actually circulated. Observations are weighted for national representativeness. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Percent of US Adult population </p>

<p>Recalled seeing 
Recalled seeing and believed </p>

<p>Small true 
Fake 
Placebo 
Big true </p>

<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 227 </p>

<p>After weighting for national representativeness, 15 percent of survey respon-
dents recalled seeing the Fake stories, and 8 percent both recalled seeing the story 
and said they believed it. 
5 By comparison, about 14 percent of people report seeing </p>

<p>the placebo stories, and about 8 percent report seeing and believing them. We esti-
mate that the average Fake headline was 1.2 percentage points more likely to be 
seen and recalled than the average Placebo headline, and the 95 percent confi-
dence interval allows us to exclude differences greater than 2.9 percent. 
We can use these results to provide a separate estimate of fake news exposure. 
The average Fake article that we asked about in the post-election survey was shared 
0.386 million times on Facebook. If the average article was seen and recalled by 
1.2 percent of American adults, this gives (0.012 recalled exposure)/(0.386 million 
shares) ≈ 0.03 chance of a recalled exposure per million Facebook shares. Given 
that the Fake articles in our database had 38 million Facebook shares, this implies 
that the average adult saw and remembered 0.03/million × 38 million ≈ 1.14 fake 
news articles from our fake news database. 
All three approaches suggest that election-period fake news exposure was on 
the order of one or perhaps several articles read per adult. We emphasize several 
important caveats. First, each of these measures excludes some forms of exposure 
that could have been influential. All of them exclude stories or sites omitted from 
our database. Estimated page visits or impressions exclude cases in which users saw 
a story within their Facebook news feed but did not click through to read it. Our 
survey-based recall measure excludes stories that users saw but did not remember, 
and may be subject to other biases associated with survey-based estimates of media 
exposure (Bartels 1993; Prior 2009; Guess 2015). </p>

<p>Who Believes Fake News? </p>

<p>It is both privately and socially valuable when people can infer the true state 
of the world. What factors predict the ability to distinguish between real and fake 
news? This analysis parallels a literature in political science measuring and inter-
preting correlates of misinformation, including Lewandowsky, Oberauer, and 
Gignac (2013), Malka, Krosnick, and Langer (2009), and Oliver and Wood (2014). 
We construct a variable C ia , that takes value 1 if survey respondent i correctly 
identifies whether article a is true or false, 0.5 if respondent i is "not sure," and value 
0 otherwise. For example, if headline a is true, then C ia takes value 1 if person i 
responded "Yes" to "would your best guess have been that this statement was true?"; 
0.5 if person i responded "Not sure"; and 0 if person i responded "No." We use C ia </p>

<p>5 These shares are broadly consistent with the results of a separate survey conducted by Silverman and 
Singer-Vine (2016): for a set of five fake news stories, they find that the share of respondents who have 
heard them ranges from 10 to 22 percent and the share who rate them as "very accurate" ranges from 
28 to 49 percent. </p>



<p>as the dependent variable and a vector X i of individual characteristics in a linear 
regression: </p>

<p>C ia = α 1 X i + α 0 + ε ia . </p>

<p>Table 1 reports results. Column 1 includes only false articles (both Fake and 
Placebo), and focuses only on party affiliation; the omitted category is Independents. 
In these data, it is indeed true that Republicans were statistically less likely than 
Democrats to report that they (correctly) did not believe a false article. Column 2 
includes only true articles (both Big True and Small True categories). This suggests 
that Republicans are also more likely than Democrats to correctly believe articles 
that were true ( p = 0.124). These results suggest that in our data, Republicans were 
not generally worse at inference: instead, they tended to be more credulous of both 
true and false articles. Of course, it is possible that this is simply an artifact of how 
different respondents interpreted the survey design. For example, it could be that 
Republicans tended to expect a higher share of true headlines in our survey, and 
thus were less discerning. 
Another possible explanation is that the differences between parties hide 
other factors associated with party affiliation. Columns 3 and 4 test this possibility, 
including a vector of additional covariates. The differences between the Democrat 
and Republican indicator variables are relatively robust. Column 5 includes all arti-
cles, which weights true and false articles by the proportions in our survey sample. 
Given that our survey included a large proportion of fake articles that Republicans 
were less likely to recognize as false, Democrats are overall more likely to correctly 
identify true versus false articles. Three correlations tend to be statistically signifi-
cant: people who spend more time consuming media, people with higher education, 
and older people have more accurate beliefs about news. As with Republicans rela-
tive to Democrats, people who report that social media were their most important 
sources of election news were more likely both to correctly believe true headlines 
and to incorrectly believe false headlines. 
The association of education with correct beliefs should be highlighted. Flynn, 
Nyhan, and Reifler (2017) argue that education could have opposing effects on 
political misperceptions. On the one hand, education should increase people's 
ability to discern fact from fiction. On the other hand, in the presence of motivated 
reasoning, education gives people better tools to counterargue against incon-
gruent information. To the extent that the association in our data is causal, it would 
reinforce many previous arguments that the social return to education includes 
cognitive abilities that better equip citizens to make informed voting decisions. For 
example, Adam Smith (1776) wrote, "The more [people] are instructed, the less 
liable they are to the delusions of enthusiasm and superstition, which, among igno-
rant nations, frequently occasion the most dreadful disorders." 
A common finding in the survey literature on rumors, conspiracy theories, 
and factual beliefs is that partisan attachment is an important predictor of beliefs 
(for example, Oliver and Wood 2014; Uscinski, Klofstad, and Atkinson 2016). </p>

<p>Hunt Allcott and Matthew Gentzkow 229 </p>

<p>For example, Republicans are more likely than Democrats to believe that Presi-
dent Obama was born outside the United States, and Democrats are more likely 
than Republicans to believe that President Bush was complicit in the 9/11 attacks 
(Cassino and Jenkins 2013). Such polarized beliefs are consistent with a Bayesian 
framework, where posteriors depend partially on priors, as well as with models of 
motivated reasoning (for example, Taber and Lodge 2006, or see the symposium 
in the Summer 2016 issue of this journal). Either way, the ability to update one's 
priors in response to factual information is privately and socially valuable in our 
model, and polarized views on factual issues can damage society's ability to come </p>

<p>Table 1 
What Predicts Correct Beliefs about News Headlines? </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>Democrat 
0.029 
-0.004 
0.028 
-0.010 
0.015 
(0.020) 
(0.023) 
(0.019) 
(0.021) 
(0.013) </p>

<p>Republican 
-0.024 
0.040 
-0.037* 
0.021 
-0.018 
(0.024) 
(0.027) 
(0.020) 
(0.023) 
(0.014) </p>

<p>ln(Daily media time) 
-0.002 
0.042*** 
0.013*** 
(0.007) 
(0.008) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>Social media most 
-0.066*** 
0.065*** 
-0.023 
important 
(0.025) 
(0.024) 
(0.016) </p>

<p>Use social media 
0.014 
-0.023 
0.002 
(0.030) 
(0.038) 
(0.019) </p>

<p>Social media 
-0.027 
0.028 
-0.008 
ideological segregation 
(0.036) 
(0.046) 
(0.024) </p>

<p>Education 
0.014*** 
0.004 
0.011*** 
(0.004) 
(0.004) 
(0.003) </p>

<p>Undecided 
-0.011 
0.006 
-0.005 
(0.017) 
(0.022) 
(0.013) </p>

<p>Age 
0.002*** 
0.000 
0.002*** 
(0.000) 
(0.001) 
(0.000) </p>

<p>N 
12,080 
6,040 
12,080 
6,040 
18,120 </p>

<p>p-value 
0.029 
0.124 
0.004 
0.207 
0.035 
(Democrat = Republican) 
Articles in sample 
False 
True 
False 
True 
All </p>

<p>Note: This table presents estimates of a regression of a dependent variable measuring correct 
beliefs about headlines on individual characteristics. Columns 1 and 3 include only false 
headlines, columns 2 and 4 contain only true headlines, and column 5 contains all headlines. 
All columns include additional demographic controls: income, race, and gender. "Social media 
most important" means social media were the respondent's most important sources of election 
news. "Social media ideological segregation" is the self-reported share (from 0 to 1) of social 
media friends that preferred the same presidential candidate. "Undecided" is an indicator 
variable for whether the respondent decided which candidate to vote for less than three months 
before the election. Observations are weighted for national representativeness. Standard errors 
are robust and clustered by survey respondent. 
*, **, *** indicate statistically significantly different from zero with 90, 95, and 99 percent 
confidence, respectively. </p>



<p>to agreement on what social problems are important and how to address them 
(Sunstein 2001a, b, 2007). 
Given this discussion, do we also see polarized beliefs with respect to fake news? 
And if so, what factors moderate ideologically aligned inference-that is, what 
factors predict a lower probability that a Republican is more likely to believe pro-
Trump news than pro-Clinton news, or that a Democrat is more likely to believe 
pro-Clinton than pro-Trump news? To gain insight into this question, we define B ia 
as a measure of whether individual i believed article a, taking value 1 if "Yes," 0.5 
if "Not sure," and 0 if "No." We also define D i and R i as Democrat and Republican 
indicators, and C a and T a as indicators for whether headline a is pro-Clinton or 
pro-Trump. We then run the following regression in the sample of Democrats and 
Republicans, excluding Independents: </p>

<p>B ia = β D D i C a + β R R i T a + γ D D i + γ R R i + ε ia . </p>

<p>The first two independent variables are interaction terms; their coefficients β D 
and β R measure whether a Democrat is more likely to believe a pro-Clinton head-
line and whether a Republican is more likely to believe a pro-Trump headline. The 
second two independent variables control for how likely Democrats or Republicans 
are as a group are to believe all stories. Since headlines are randomly assigned to 
respondents, with equal balance of true versus false and pro-Trump versus pro-
Clinton, the estimated β parameters will measure ideologically aligned inference 
Table 2 presents the results. Column 1 presents estimates of β D and β R . Demo-
crats and Republicans, respectively, are 17.2 and 14.7 percentage points more likely 
to believe ideologically aligned articles than they are to believe nonaligned articles. 
Column 2 takes an intermediate step, constraining the β coefficients to be the same. 
Column 3 then allows β to vary by the same vector of X i variables as reported in 
Table 1, except excluding D i to avoid collinearity. In both columns 1 and 3, any 
differences between Democrats and Republicans in the magnitude of ideologically 
aligned inference are not statistically significant. 
Three variables are strongly correlated with ideologically aligned inference. 
First, heavy media consumers are more likely to believe ideologically aligned arti-
cles. Second, those with segregated social networks are significantly more likely to 
believe ideologically aligned articles, perhaps because they are less likely to receive 
disconfirmatory information from their friends. The point estimate implies that a 
0.1 (10 percentage point) increase in the share of social media friends that preferred 
the same presidential candidate is associated with a 0.0147 (1.47 percentage point) 
increase in belief of ideologically aligned headlines relative to ideologically cross-
cutting headlines. Third, "undecided" adults (those who did not make up their 
minds about whom to vote for until less than three months before the election) are 
less likely to believe ideologically aligned articles than more decisive voters. This 
is consistent with undecided voters having less-strong ideologies in the first place. 
Interestingly, social media use and education are not statistically significantly associ-
ated with more or less ideologically aligned inference. </p>

<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 231 </p>

<p>One caveat to these results is that ideologically aligned inference may be exag-
gerated by respondents' tendency to answer expressively or to want to "cheerlead" 
for their party (Bullock, Gerber, Hill, and Huber 2015; Gerber and Huber 2009; 
Prior, Sood, and Khanna 2015). Partisan gaps could be smaller in a survey with 
strong incentives for correct answers. </p>

<p>Table 2 
Ideological Alignment and Belief of News Headlines </p>

<p>(1) 
(2) 
(3) </p>

<p>Democrat × Pro-Clinton 
0.172*** 
(0.021) </p>

<p>Republican × Pro-Trump 
0.147*** 
(0.023) </p>

<p>Aligned 
0.161*** 
0.096 
(0.016) 
(0.140) </p>

<p>Aligned × Republican 
0.000 
(0.027) </p>

<p>Aligned × ln(Daily media time) 
0.024*** 
(0.009) </p>

<p>Aligned × Social media most important 
-0.031 
(0.037) </p>

<p>Aligned × Use social media 
-0.068 
(0.050) </p>

<p>Aligned × Social media ideological segregation 
0.147*** 
(0.046) </p>

<p>Aligned × Education 
-0.004 
(0.007) </p>

<p>Aligned × Undecided 
-0.099*** 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Aligned × Age 
0.001 
(0.001) </p>

<p>N 
10,785 
10,785 
10,785 </p>

<p>Notes: This table presents estimates of a regression of a variable measuring belief of news headlines 
on the interaction of political party affiliation indicators and pro-Clinton or pro-Trump headline 
indicators. The sample includes all news headlines (both true and false) but excludes survey 
respondents who are Independents. "Social media most important" means social media were the 
respondent's most important sources of election news. "Social media ideological segregation" is 
the self-reported share (from 0 to 1) of social media friends that preferred the same presidential 
candidate. "Undecided" is an indicator variable for whether the respondent decided which 
candidate to vote for less than three months before the election. Observations are weighted 
for national representativeness. Standard errors are robust and clustered by survey respondent. 
*, **, ***: statistically significantly different from zero with 90, 95, and 99 percent confidence, 
respectively. </p>



<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>In the aftermath of the 2016 US presidential election, it was alleged that fake 
news might have been pivotal in the election of President Trump. We do not provide 
an assessment of this claim one way or another. 
That said, the new evidence we present clarifies the level of overall exposure 
to fake news, and it can give some sense of how persuasive fake news would need 
to have been to have been pivotal. We estimate that the average US adult read and 
remembered on the order of one or perhaps several fake news articles during the 
election period, with higher exposure to pro-Trump articles than pro-Clinton arti-
cles. How much this affected the election results depends on the effectiveness of 
fake news exposure in changing the way people vote. As one benchmark, Spenkuch 
and Toniatti (2016) show that exposing voters to one additional television campaign 
ad changes vote shares by approximately 0.02 percentage points. This suggests that 
if one fake news article were about as persuasive as one TV campaign ad, the fake 
news in our database would have changed vote shares by an amount on the order 
of hundredths of a percentage point. This is much smaller than Trump's margin of 
victory in the pivotal states on which the outcome depended. 
Of course there are many reasons why a single fake news story could have been 
more effective than a television commercial. If it were true that the Pope endorsed 
Donald Trump, this fact would be significantly more surprising-and probably 
move a rational voter's beliefs by more as a result-than the information contained 
in a typical campaign ad. Moreover, as we emphasize above, there are many ways in 
which our estimates could understate true exposure. We only measure the number 
of stories read and remembered, and the excluded stories seen on news feeds but 
not read, or read but not remembered, could have had a large impact. Our fake 
news database is incomplete, and the effect of the stories it omits could also be 
significant. 
We also note that there are several ways in which this back-of-the-envelope 
calculation is conservative, in the sense that it could overstate the importance of 
fake news. We consider the number of stories voters read regardless of whether they 
believed them. We do not account for diminishing returns, which could reduce 
fake news' effect to the extent that a small number of voters see a large number of 
stories. Also, this rough calculation does not explicitly take into account the fact 
that a large share of pro-Trump fake news is seen by voters who are already predis-
posed to vote for Trump-the larger this selective exposure, the smaller the impact 
we would expect of fake news on vote shares. 
To the extent that fake news imposes social costs, what can and should be done? 
In theory, a social planner should want to address the market failures that lead to 
distortions, which would take the form of increasing information about the state of 
the world and increasing incentives for news consumers to infer the true state of the 
world. In practice, social media platforms and advertising networks have faced some 
pressure from consumers and civil society to reduce the prevalence of fake news on 
their systems. For example, both Facebook and Google are removing fake news sites </p>

<p>Hunt Allcott and Matthew Gentzkow 233 </p>

<p>from their advertising platforms on the grounds that they violate policies against 
misleading content (Wingfield, Isaac, and Benner 2016). Furthermore, Facebook 
has taken steps to identify fake news articles, flag false articles as "disputed by 3rd 
party fact-checkers," show fewer potentially false articles in users' news feeds, and 
help users avoid accidentally sharing false articles by notifying them that a story is 
"disputed by 3rd parties" before they share it (Mosseri 2016). In our theoretical 
framework, these actions may increase social welfare, but identifying fake news sites 
and articles also raises important questions about who becomes the arbiter of truth. </p>

<p>■ We thank David Deming, Brendan Nyhan, Craig Silverman, Aaron Smith, Joe Uscinski, 
David Vannette, and many other colleagues for helpful conversations and feedback. We are 
grateful to Chuan Yu and Nano Barahona for research assistance, and we thank Stanford 
University for financial support. Our survey was determined to be exempt from human 
subjects review by the NYU and Stanford Institutional Review Boards. </p>







<p>Social Media and Fake News in the 2016 Election 235 </p>





</text></tei>