<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs00191-017-0548-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract The emergence of profit-based online platforms related to the Sharing 
Economy, such as <rs type="software">BlaBlaCar</rs> and <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs>, provides new means for end users to create 
an income from their possessions. With this opportunity, participants have to make 
strategic economic decisions despite limited formal expertise and information. Decen-
tralization (using digital technologies) and reputation (using user reviews) are the core 
mechanisms chosen by these platforms to mitigate these limitations and to work 
efficiently as online matchmakers. We test the performance of these two mechanisms 
by studying the allocative efficiency (in terms of value and volume of transactions) of 
simulated marketplaces under different types of motivation from the participants and 
control from the platforms. As a result, we find an inverted-U relationship between the 
decision-making leeway available to the participants and the platform's allocative 
efficiency. From the participants' perspectives, too much freedom or too many barriers 
lead to market failures affecting specific participants: low-end consumers are banned 
from the marketplace while high-end providers experience lower levels of activity. As 
governance advice for these platforms, we show the limitations of promoting these 
platforms on the sole motive of monetary rewards. </p>

<p>The Internet has dramatically changed the production and distribution of consumer goods 
and services. Users have seized these new opportunities to bypass well-established busi-
nesses for production and trade. In this research, we focus on those online platforms that give 
anyone an opportunity to share their possessions for profit -such as airbnb.com, blablacar. 
com and turo.com. These platforms operate in a grey area between traditional marketplaces 
(supplied by formal firms) and the not-for-profit part of the Sharing Economy (Belk 2014). 
Consequently, specific forms of market governance have to be found in order to provide an 
efficient platform that would embed both profit motive and the willingness to share. 
Due to its rapid growth, this sector has been largely scrutinized in the media and in the 
academic literature. Codagnone et al. (2016) provide an extensive literature review show-
ing how the potential of these platforms is widely assumed to be correlated with regulatory 
matters. In the same line, Frenken (2017) sketches three potential futures of sharing based 
on different institutional decisions by the markets, governments and the public. Here, we 
take a different approach by showing how economic governance at the platform level alone 
can provide predictions of the potential successes and failures of the platforms. By doing 
so, we question the ability to provide economic governance by relying only on interme-
diation technologies. We show that the online platforms of the profit-based sharing 
economy are not neutral technologies. Only specific forms of governance over the 
transactions can help the platform to meet the expectations of the sharing economy to 
benefit all participants. The focus on internal governance supplements the widely discussed 
external factors of platform success and failure, e.g., the different levels of government 
regulation, the competition with other platforms or incumbents, and their social legitimacy. 
Our interest in this issue comes from the emergence of a hybrid form of governance 
between intermediation and community building. On the one hand, these platforms define 
themselves as 'intermediaries', creating an apparent proximity with other online interme-
diaries such as eBay.com, <rs type="software">Craigslist</rs> or <rs type="software">Facebook</rs>, because of a strong technological 
integration with the Web 2.0 (including social networks and user reviews) (Belk 2014). 
The main difference between intermediaries and merchants is the distribution of control 
between the platform and the participants (Hagiu 2007). While the merchants keep full 
control over the sale (e.g. pricing, quantities), intermediaries only control the affiliation to 
their platform, taking the form of a two-sided platform connecting independent sellers and 
buyers. On the other hand, by putting forward the idea of sharing, these platforms position 
themselves in a moral system interested in social welfare (Botsman and Rogers 2011). 
Assuming that learning and enforcing morality is the result of both individual attributes and 
social relations (Hodgson 2014), decentralized platforms do not provide the structure for 
this kind of social enterprise. For instance, we can observe this ambiguity in the governance 
of <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs>, in which the platform emphasizes its role of intermediary by describing itself as 
"a trusted community marketplace" 
1 rather than a company or a merchant. Yet, on 
September 8th 2016, Brian Chesky, CEO and co-founder of <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> addressed an email 
to the entire community of users entitled "Discrimination and Belonging". 
2 The core of the </p>

<p>1 https://www.airbnb.com/about/about-us (last visited on August 7, 2017) 
2 Full email available at http://blog.airbnb.com/fighting-discrimination-and-creating-a-world-where-anyone-
can-belong-anywhere/ (last visited on August 7, 2017) </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>email consists in the acknowledgment of discrimination on the platform, and the descrip-
tion of new platform policies implementing stronger control over the users' behaviors. 
In this paper, we study the interaction of platform governance and participants' behavior 
using an agent-based simulation model. The model consists in the formal representation of 
a marketplace where we simulate pricing and purchasing decisions by the participants. Our 
objective is to study the specific conditions under which the online platforms of the sharing 
economy can approach the allocative efficiency of a clearing house (i.e. a fully-informed 
and fully-centralized intermediary that generates the maximum value and volume of 
transactions). As an intermediary, the platform governs the diffusion of information 
between the participants. This is the central component of the model that simulates it via 
mechanisms controlling what information is accessible to the participants so as to copy the 
search engines available for the buyers to find a seller. In addition, we assume that 
purchases and user reviews are the main sources of information available to the sellers. 
At the individual level, the model implements behaviors by assuming that actions are 
motivated by monetary or non-monetary incentives, also known as extrinsic and intrinsic 
motivations (Benkler 2004). The original work by Frey and Jegen (2001) studies the 
positive and negative influences of extrinsic motivation (monetary incentives or punish-
ments) when the action was originally performed using intrinsic motivation. This paper 
aims to provide a better picture of the potential evolution of the platforms, in line with the 
recent concerns that emerged about the predatory or greedy nature of the for-profit 
platforms of the sharing economy (e.g. Frenken and Schor 2017; Slee 2016). 
As a result, this modelling framework gives us the opportunity to study the interplay 
of specific structures of platform control and individual motivation. For each structure, 
the simulation shows patterns of allocative efficiency from two perspectives: the 
platform perspective (aggregated level) and the participant perspective (individual 
level). In a nutshell, the limited information generates local market frictions. The 
individual adaptation to these frictions leads to specific types of failures at the aggre-
gated platform level, depending on the participants' motivations. From the platform 
perspective, the market failure is more systematic when participants are only extrinsi-
cally motivated and when control is either too constraining or completely absent. From 
the participant perspective, we are able to specify which categories of participants and 
transactions are banned from the platform: the low-end of the demand side cannot 
access the marketplace due to the overpricing of the low-end of the supply side, and the 
high-end of the supply side is undervalued. The simulation results also give us the 
opportunity to discuss insights for platform policies to increase successful trading. This 
view of platform control and individual motivation is based on Landini (2016), who 
describes this evolution as a key characteristic of the evolution of the digital economy 
toward one equilibrium of high control and extrinsic motivation. However, our mech-
anisms of control are more limited: platform owners can never achieve full information 
about the participants. They cannot control the timing of purchases, they can only 
influence the information available for that decision. </p>

<p>2 Literature review </p>

<p>In this paper, we limit our analysis to the sharing of consumer goods that Benkler (2004)  describes as 'shareable goods'. Those goods are 'lumpy', which is equivalent in economics </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>to 'indivisible', to the extent that once acquired, the utility or functions provided by these 
goods cannot be changed gradually. In addition, they are 'mid-grained', meaning that 
"there will be relatively widespread private ownership of these goods and that these 
privately owned goods will systematically exhibit slack capacity relative to the demand 
of their owners" (Benkler 2004: 276). Accommodations and cars are examples of shareable 
goods that can be found on platforms such as airbnb.com (renting accommodation), 
blablacar.com (ridesharing) and turo.com (car sharing). On all these platforms, 
individuals can share their under-utilized possessions with other individuals in a peer-to-
peer system. Other examples include household goods (such as bikes, power tools or 
ladders) that can be rented on neighborgoods.org or parking spaces on justpark.com. 
According to Rachel Botsman, 
3 a platform belongs to the 'sharing economy' when: 
(1) the under-utilized assets are used more efficiently by users who specifically value 
access over ownership; and (2) the platform owner / designer and the participants 
exhibit values such as transparency, respect or belonging. Botsman does not limit the 
sharing economy to the profit-based platforms: under-utilized assets can be traded for 
monetary or non-monetary benefits. By focusing our own research on platforms using 
monetary transactions, we want to understand the behavioral interplay between mon-
etary incentives (sharing for a price) and non-monetary incentives (e.g. sharing for the 
public good) that emerge on these platforms. </p>

<p>2.1 The motivations to join and participate in the sharing economy </p>

<p>Shareable goods are probably as old as private property. Sharing practices also pre-date the 
Internet: homeowners renting spare rooms, cooperatives, etc. (Belk 2014; Frenken and  Schor 2017). Yet, with the commoditization of the Internet, the extent of sharing entered a 
new phase of evolution. According to Benkler (2004: 278), "technology does not determine 
the level of sharing. But it does set threshold constraints on the effective domain of sharing 
as a modality of economic production. Within the domain of the feasible, the actual level of 
sharing practices will be culturally driven and cross-culturally diverse." Technology has 
reduced the transaction costs of sharing, making peer-to-peer transactions more attractive. 
From an economic perspective, the literature on two-sided platforms (e.g. 
Eisenmann et al. 2006; Rochet and Tirole 2006) provides a major contribution to the 
understanding of the economic issues faced by online platforms. Even if not limited to 
the Internet, it addresses the classic 'chicken and egg problem', i.e. the indirect network 
effect of two-sided platforms: to grow, the platform needs sellers to attract buyers, and 
vice versa (Caillaud and Jullien 2003). Firmly embedded in Industrial Organization, the 
strategic decisions are located at the platform level: the success of a nascent online 
platform relies on its ability to compete efficiently against other platforms or against 
brick-and-mortar incumbents. The solution to these issues is typically achieved by 
pricing structures, or rules and regulations. The pricing structure can take different 
forms. One side of the platform can be subsidized, while the loss is compensated by the 
other side, e.g. 'divide-and-conquer' (Caillaud and Jullien 2003). One can separate the 
price of access and the price of usage: e.g. by using fixed fees and variable fees (Rochet  and Tirole 2006). The rules and regulations can be at the platform level, for instance, by </p>

<p>3 http://www.fastcoexist.com/3046119/defining-the-sharing-economy-what-is-collaborative-consumption-
and-what-isnt (last visited on August 7, 2017) </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>regulating multi-homing (Armstrong 2006), or the bundling of complements 
(Eisenmann et al. 2006). The regulations can also be public, for instance, platforms 
can face antitrust concerns (Rysman 2009). However, as Levin (2013: 57) puts it, this is 
a 'high-level view' of Internet platforms, "focusing on platform pricing and user 
decisions to join a platform, but not addressing how platforms try to structure economic 
or social activity in ways that create value." For instance, Bailey and Bakos (1997) find 
in the literature four reasons to use online intermediaries: aggregation, trust, facilitation 
and matching. Here, joining the platform would only be one aspect of aggregation. 
Even if the rest of this literature review will be moving toward a more disaggregated 
view of online platforms, we must acknowledge the contribution of the two-sided platforms 
literature for our research question. By looking at the network effect and externality, this 
literature put forward how individual decisions (such as joining a platform) have conse-
quences that we must include in the analysis of the platform strategy. In addition, even if 
pricing is only one instrument for the platforms to regulate individual behaviors and 
prevent market failures (Boudreau and Hagiu 2009), we still make pricing an important 
mechanism in our model. The major difference is that, on the peer-to-peer platforms of the 
sharing economy, pricing decisions are in the hands of participants and relate to individual 
transactions, not to the access and usage prices of the platform. 
This change of focus corresponds to a different historical stage of the online platforms: 
while the two-sided market literature was interested in the attractiveness of nascent 
platforms (bringing more participants), we are interested in the sustainability of the 
platforms (keeping the participants satisfied). Hence, we supplement the analyses in terms 
of growth, competition and external regulation by looking at the framework surrounding 
the individual decisions once on the platform. This particular question does not benefit 
from the same level of empirical investigations and theoretical discussions, probably 
because of the focus on centralized platforms where individual decisions are mostly 
influenced by profit. A common denominator in this very small literature is to assess the 
behavior in terms of monetary versus non-monetary motivations. An early attempt by 
Benkler (2004) consists in identifying (1) the non-monetary motivations to perform 
specific actions in a sharing organization, and (2) the interplay between monetary and 
non-monetary motivations. The latter has been studied in behavioral economics by Frey  and Jegen (2001) who report evidence of both positive and negative interplay of the two 
motivations, named intrinsic (non-monetary) and extrinsic (monetary). 
Among the few studies collecting data on participants in profit-based platforms of 
the sharing economy, we note (1) a coexistence of intrinsic and extrinsic motivations, 
and (2) extrinsic motivation is what motivates the decision to join the platform, while 
intrinsic motivation explains the actions performed on the platforms. If the two types 
of motivation seem to reinforce each other positively, there are several views on their 
relative power. Bellotti et al. (2015) find that owner / designers of the platform are 
intrinsically motivated, unlike the participants who are extrinsically motivated. In the 
same line, for Codagnone et al. (2016), intrinsic motivation is mostly a characteristic 
of the early not-for-profit platforms. Lampinen and Cheshire (2016) observe that 
intrinsic and extrinsic motivations are adjusted by the participant depending on their 
current context, and even when the original motivation was not intrinsic, ancillary or 
unexpected intrinsic benefits are discovered once on the platform. Hamari et al. (2016)  observe a predominance of intrinsic motivation, while Möhlmann (2015) finds first an 
extrinsic motivation (money saving) followed by trust (an intrinsic motivation). </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>Böcker and Meelen (2017) provide a more precise picture of the diversity of motiva-
tions by accounting for different types of shared goods: quite intuitively, car-sharing is 
more environmentally-motivated, while sharing meals has a strong social motivation 
and sharing accommodations is economically motivated. Finally, Hellwig et al. (2015)  identify four clusters of sharing consumers (idealists, opponents, pragmatists, norma-
tives) whose motivations correspond to articulated beliefs rather than simple demo-
graphics. This is supported by Möhlmann's observation (2015) that the decision to 
participate in a sharing experience involves rationalization and complex decision 
processes. This diversity encouraged us to model different scenarios regarding the 
relative hierarchy of motivations. </p>

<p>2.2 The design of a decentralized matching market </p>

<p>By focusing on the individual participants rather than the platform, we need to adopt a 
performance measure that will reflect this perspective (instead of plaform market shares 
or winner-take-all competition). We do so by adopting the concept of "allocative 
efficiency" (Gode and Sunder 1993, 1997). In its most generic form, "allocative 
efficiency is the ratio of the actual to the potential gains from trade" (Gode and Sunder  1997: 603). The upper bound of the "potential gains" is reached when the participants 
can make all the transactions they desire, either as suppliers when they share their 
possessions, or as customers by accessing the shared goods. Concretely, on the demand 
side, <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> is functioning efficiently if the guests find a room when they desire to 
travel or <rs type="software">BlaBlacar</rs> is efficient when there is a seat available for one's desired journey. 
On the supply side, both the revenue and the efficient utilization of our shareable 
possessions are impacted if an <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> host or a <rs type="software">BlaBlaCar</rs> traveler cannot find a buyer. 
From the public good perspective, such a failure can be seen as proof that profit-based 
platforms cannot provide the basic level of service required by Universal Service 
obligations (Slee 2016) or provided by incumbent firms (Cusumano 2015). 
To achieve allocative efficiency, these marketplaces rely on decentralized governance 
using platform rules and complex peer-to-peer mechanisms designed to facilitate and 
control the transactions. However, both sides are affected by information scarcity, due 
not to the opportunism of the participants, but because of the difficulty to assess the exact 
content of the transaction (Benkler 2004). Usually, such uncertainty is reduced by encour-
aging the homogenization of products (norms, expectations of distribution channels or 
externalization of components) and the homogenization of tastes (marketing and confor-
mity). In a peer-to-peer market, the variety of products and tastes might be overwhelming 
(Lu and Kandampully 2016), making it very difficult (1) for the buyers to assess the quality 
of each product, and (2) for the sellers to assess the size of the demand. If it is not possible to 
change the level of information or the degree of heterogeneity, versioning is the solution 
(Shapiro and Varian 1999): the pricing should reflect the heterogeneity by proposing 
different levels of price for different matches. Bhargava and Choudhary (2004) discuss 
how a menu of differentiated services (such as "freemium") improves the allocative 
efficiency in a market characterized by heterogeneous users. However, if the versions are 
not clearly differentiated, efficiency diminishes due to the cannibalization of higher 
versions by lower versions. Marketing strategies can be used to magnify the product 
differentiation (for instance, by promoting exclusive or private access to specific categories 
of users), creating artificial search frictions. The interplay of search frictions and product </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>differentiation is well understood in the industrial organization literature (Wolinsky 1986): 
product differentiation can cause imperfect competition if it creates an unequal distribution 
of market power among the providers and search frictions can exacerbate this by 
diminishing artificially the substitutability between products. As a consequence, search 
frictions provide a rational explanation of price dispersion (Chade et al. 2017; Kim et al.  2010; Levin 2013). However, the dispersion can reflect the improved allocative efficiency 
of versioning, as well as reflect uncompetitive pricing (Anderson and Renault 1999;  Armstrong et al. 2009; Weber and Zheng 2007). 
The objective of the literature on two-sided matching (Roth 1982) is to solve this 
matching problem in a more inclusive fashion. A matching problem arises when one 
attempts to match agents from two disjoints groups. Different algorithms or institutional 
arrangements can be used in order to perform the matching. This branch of research has 
contributed to the advance of solutions to the matching problem: theoretically (e.g. 
decentralized decision-making, information disclosure or bounded rationality) and with 
concrete applications (e.g. organ donors, assignment of children to schools). However, only 
a very limited amount of research has been conducted on situations where the available 
information and the preferences of the agents are still evolving (Chakraborty et al. 2010). In 
this study, the authors find that the interdependency between available information and 
preferences prevents stability in matching mechanisms. Such a situation is characteristic of 
emerging markets when product categories have to be invented and adopted by stake-
holders, thanks to the experience gathered after repeated matchings (Suarez et al. 2015). 
Using the case of labor economics, Anderson and Smith (2010) study a matching 
problem where the hidden characteristics of individuals are approximated via a reputation 
system. The reputation is updated by learning the individual characteristics through 
matchings. They discuss the necessary conditions and potential deviations of a perfect 
matching. A striking result is that, even if a stable matching can emerge, the matching 
mechanisms fail for specific levels of individual characteristics. However, they assume that 
reputation converge toward the real value of the characteristics. This limitation is inherent 
in some assumptions of the matching literature, such as the existence of a social planner and 
the use of delays (e.g. clearinghouses or deferred acceptance). Chade (2006) provides a 
solution to the absence of social planner or auctioneer by using two-player games, in a 
context of experience-based information and search frictions. He also finds a correlation 
between the player's characteristics and its ability to find a match. This result is central to 
our own research: exclusion does not happen randomly, yet this author uses a marriage 
analogy limiting the reusability of information for repeated matching. (Post-marriage 
reviews are not available and the matched partners exit the market.) 
The tradition of micro-founded market simulations (Gode and Sunder 1993; Kirman  and Vriend 2001) provides an alternative set of solutions to this problem. This approach 
differs from the classic hypotheses of profit maximization, Walrasian auctioneer and 
perfect information, due to their lack of plausibility (Axtell 2005). Instead, heteroge-
neous agents learn, adapt and interact repeatedly, leading to the emergence of aggregate 
dynamics that cannot be entirely deduced from individual behaviors (Delle Gatti et al.  2012). Gode and Sunder (1993: 120) build on Vernon Smith's work to establish that the 
"performance of an economy is the joint result of its institutional structure, market 
environment, and agent behavior. Institutional structure is defined by the rules that 
govern exchange, market environment by agents' tastes and endowments of informa-
tion and resources, and agents' behavior by their trading strategy". The implication is </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>that the standard microeconomic assumptions (e.g. Walrasian auctioneer, profit maxi-
mization) can be implemented as a specific case within this framework. 
A caveat is that this literature is mostly interested in testing different auction mecha-
nisms (Marks 2006; Phelps et al. 2008) giving an extra emphasis on the negotiation phase, 
at the expense of the search phase. However, this stream of research provides results 
qualitatively similar to our research. Zhan and Friedman (2007) study a continuous double 
auction mechanisms where individual participants strategically adjust their profit motives 
(via markups and markdowns on their bids and asks) over repeated auctions. They find that 
market efficiency increases when there is a moderate markup by buyers and markdown by 
sellers and it decreases when it is more or less than moderate. Their explanation is that "in 
increasing the markup, traders face a tradeoff between greed (larger profit if there is a 
transaction) and fear (a greater probability of failing to transact)" (Zhan and Friedman  2007: 3000). Rud and Rabanal (2016) compare posted prices and decentralized (random) 
matching using the previous model. Posted prices do not achieve the same level of 
allocative efficiency as auctions. This result matters because posted prices are now the 
main form of pricing in the for-profit platforms of the sharing economy, auction systems 
being progressively replaced (Slee 2016) due to higher transaction costs (Levin 2013). 
Taking a more global perspective, Phelps et al. (2008) advise designing the market 
mechanisms very specifically taking into account the co-evolution of traders' structure / 
characteristics and the matching problem. 
Because both the matching market and the micro-founded literatures ignore search 
frictions, they have some limitations for our own research. The latter takes bounded-
rationality and limited information as granted and, therefore, decisions are made using 
learning mechanisms. Yet these learning mechanisms are intended to improve the 
quality of the information used for the decision, in the same way that matching markets 
require information disclosure. In addition, both literatures assume the existence of a 
clearing-house, all transactions being processed synchronously. An alternative model of 
a "bazaar economy" with asynchronous transactions has been proposed by Miller and  Tumminello (2015), establishing that search frictions are a secondary problem if one 
can control the distribution of traders' characteristics. Such a possibility is not imple-
mented in our model, but this form of control appears in the discussion. </p>

<p>2.3 Trust and reputation </p>

<p>Kirman and Vriend (2001) -in their analysis of the dynamics and emergent properties of 
Marseille's fish market -use the concept of loyalty to facilitate coordination and learning 
over repeated transactions. Loyalty is particularly relevant for the sharing economy, where 
social and non-anonymous relationships shape the transactions. However, with the Internet, 
the online platforms extend sharing to individuals outside our social circle and networks 
(Schor 2016). Most of the transactions involve new participants who are not going to enter 
a cycle of repeated transactions with the same partners and goods that cannot be examined 
before the transaction (Levin 2013). As Einav et al. (2016: 616) put it: "peer-to-peer 
businesses usually have to tradeoff between two important objectives: designing market 
mechanisms that efficiently elicit and incorporate dispersed information, and minimizing 
search and deliberation to keep the user experience convenient." 
The solution adopted by most platforms consists in asking the participants to write a 
post-transaction review. The aggregation of user reviews provides a basis for the creation </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>and sharing of market information. This is a solution to some of the requirements of the 
matching problem (revealing preferences and hidden characteristics) using a simple 
mechanism. Also, the platforms depend heavily on user reviews because they help to build 
trust and reputation. Users are expected to give credit and contribute to reviews, mostly to 
determine the quality of goods that would be considered as 'experience goods' and, 
therefore, to oppose opportunism. Facing imperfect information about quality, the literature 
predicts various nuisances for customers: market concentration, limited incentives to 
supply the highest quality, overpricing. (See for instance Shapiro 1982 and Allen 1984.)  Other solutions could address these nuisances. For instance, auctions are meant to punish 
greedy behaviors and misrepresentations of information to improve trustworthiness (Phelps  et al. 2008). In the same line, an insurance system can be designed to prevent agency 
problems (e.g. moral hazard) when the content of the transaction can be strategically altered 
(Roger and Vasconcelos 2014; Weber 2014). However, these mechanisms expect the 
motivations to be purely monetary, i.e., the participants only fear a loss of profit. User 
reviews are more appropriate in the sharing economy because they also embed pieces of 
information that can be used for the non-monetary aspects of the transaction. 
However, due to their simplicity, user reviews might not always prevent market frictions 
and they can sometimes aggravate them. In particular, user reviews produce similar 
concerns as product differentiation on the imperfect pricing of products (Armstrong et al.  2009). Reasons can be found in the literature review by Dellarocas (2003) who finds a 
rather general consensus that positive reviews lead to higher prices. At the same time, he 
shows how reviews have to be handled cautiously, because (i) a critical mass of reviews is 
necessary to derive a strategy, (ii) platforms control how the reviews are provided, and (iii) 
reviews lack context. The importance of the critical mass has been confirmed by Duan et al.  (2008). They put forward "the dual nature of online user reviews": (i) "consumer's 
assessment of product quality", and (ii) "product awareness among consumers". They find 
that higher ratings do not affect the sales, while the number of reviews is correlated with 
sales (cf. bandwagon effect). For Hu et al. (2006), reviews are bimodal and give a true 
picture only when everyone answers. At the same time, user reviews reflect the opinion of a 
given person at a given time. This is the reason why, for Benkler (2004), user reviews 
incorporate the social aspect of sharing, but remain vague in terms of information 
processing. We assume that user reviews are central components in the moral system of 
the sharing economy, by providing the social structure for the "inculcation and enforce-
ment" of values in the group together with individual preferences (Hodgson 2014). 
In a nutshell, the profit-based online platforms of the sharing economy make the 
promise to build functioning marketplaces relying mostly on technology and values. 
The technologies behind the marketplaces use decentralization and user reviews as a 
form of control, information processing and gathering. In the rest of this work, we will 
analyze the conditions under which those technologies decrease or amplify the local 
frictions generated by the participants' behavior. </p>

<p>3 Model </p>

<p>Our model captures the operation of a peer-to-peer marketplace guided by decentralized 
decision-making and user reviews. Our objective is to compare the performance of 
different motivations when the peers try to complete transactions. </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>We present our model as an online platform for accommodations (such as <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs>): 
the customers are 'guests' who want to find a 'host' for a night at a given location. 
Below, we describe the model in three blocks / sub-sections: </p>

<p>1. the governance of the marketplace; 
2. the guests selecting an accommodation and writing a review; 
3. the hosts adjusting their pricing decision. </p>

<p>Figure 1 gives an overview of the simulation by showing the five sequential substeps 
happening during every time step of a simulation. </p>

<p>3.1 The marketplace </p>

<p>Gode and Sunder (1993) summarize some assumptions of micro-founded market 
simulations that we use in our model: </p>

<p>&amp; demand and supply functions can be derived from simple budget constraints rather 
than maximization-behavior based on costs; 
&amp; the budget constraints being private, the demand and supply functions are unknown 
to the participants; 
&amp; the transactions occur on single units only. </p>

<p>By giving the opportunity to anyone of supplying consumer goods, peer-to-peer 
platforms encourage individuals to make a profit from their existing possessions. Even 
if the platform policies may advise them to mimic professional standards and norms, 
supplier costs are mostly opportunity costs related to the willingness to make transac-
tions with strangers (Zervas et al. 2017). This is why we adopt the following assump-
tions about the marketplace: </p>

<p>&amp; the quantity is capped (e.g. number of guests in an accommodation, number of seats 
in a car traveling a specific route); 
&amp; the quality is fixed (we assume that the possessions are not acquired solely for the 
purposes of being shared; they are under-utilized possessions); 
&amp; the price is related to personal motivations or constraints more than production 
costs; 
&amp; there is no bargaining; price adjustments are made sequentially, via experimenta-
tions made outside the transactions. </p>

<p>Fig. 1 A typical time step of the simulation </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>The marketplace comprises two categories of agents: a set of hosts (H) and a set of 
guests (G). Each agent is initialized with a fixed personal characteristic: for a guest, this is 
her budget (b), i.e. the limit of the monetary price she is willing (or able) to pay for the 
accommodation; for a host, this is the quality level of his accommodation (q) (this includes 
the characteristics of the host, too). Both b and q are distributed uniformly in [1100]. Our 
objective is to provide the platform participants with a personal and ordinal characteristic. 
Besides wealth and quality, this characteristic can be replaced to study the distributions of 
other critical characteristics, such as the distance from the city center or the willingness to 
pay for or to supply any service. By setting b and q with the same values, an omniscient 
matchmaker could centrally achieves a full matching where each guest could find a host 
with p = q = b (assortative matching where guests with budget b are matched with hosts of 
quality b = q). This full and centralized matching will be used as a benchmark to compare 
the allocative efficiency of the decentralized governance and differently motivated behav-
iors. We also assume that, at each simulation time step t, the exact same number of hosts 
and guests look for an accommodation: |H| = |G|. Consequently, all the hosts and guests are 
active at every time step, i.e., there is neither systemic shortage nor surplus on either side of 
the platform. This assumption is necessary for the platform to achieve full matching in the 
case of a centralized and assortative matchmaker. 
For the guests, in our simple design, the fair price of an accommodation is p = q (i.e. 1 unit 
of price = 1 unit of quality). For individuals whose motivation is non-monetary, this simple 
assumption is also a social norm that is part of the non-monetary reward: visiting a host where 
p ≤ q will be seen at the individual guest level as a sign of respect and socially as a shared 
understanding of the social norms. This is the source of the interplay between monetary and 
non-monetary motivations in the model. The motivations of the participants are implemented 
via four scenarios described in Table 1. A given scenario connects a guest strategy (i.e. the 
type of motivation involved in choosing a host) with a host strategy (i.e. the type of motivation 
involved in adjusting the price). For tractability of the results, we assume that within a 
scenario all the hosts follow the same host strategy and all the guests follow the same guest 
strategy. Relaxing this assumption, for instance, by allowing a mix of strategies in a given 
period or over time, would require the comparison of a much larger number of scenarios. 
When the simulation starts (at time step t = 1), the hosts do not know how to evaluate 
their accommodations. Hence, they randomly set a starting price p 1 = (1 − γ) × q + γ  *  
p R where p R ∼U 1; 100 
ð 
Þis a random component of the price, q is the fair price and γ 
balances the repartition between random and fully informed pricing. Then, at every 
simulation time step t, each guest will try to find an accommodation (substeps 1 and 2, 
see Fig. 1). If she succeeds, she will write a review regarding her experience of the 
accommodation quality (substep 3). Once the time steps are over, the hosts have the 
opportunity to adjust their price (substeps 4 and 5). </p>

<p>Table 1 Scenarios based on host and guest strategies </p>

<p>Guest strategy </p>

<p>Quality 
Price </p>

<p>Host strategy 
Satisfaction 
Scenario I 
Scenario II 
Occupancy 
Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>3.2 Demand side: Booking and reviewing </p>

<p>The process of finding an accommodation takes the first two substeps described in 
Fig. 1, for each guest (more details follow): </p>

<p>&amp; substep 1: guest g ∈ G reduces the set of hosts H to a subset H g , limited to the hosts 
who are not already booked and whose current price is within her budget con-
straints (i.e. a given price range). 
&amp; substep 2: if H g ≠ ∅, i.e. one or more hosts match the criteria of substep 1, she 
selects one host based on its attributes. The selection process follows one of two 
strategies: Price Strategy or Quality Strategy. 
If H g = ∅, no hosts match with this condition, she is considered unmatched and 
her search ends. The simulation returns to substep 1 with another guest. </p>

<p>In more detail, we learned from the literature on user reviews that reviews contribute to 
reputation building and are being used as a proxy rather than a fair source of information. 
For instance, Fradkin (2014) analyzed search data from <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> and shows that potential 
customers filter the listings based on objective variables (mostly the location and maximum 
price) before browsing the remaining listings and evaluating more subjective characteristics 
(including the number and text of reviews). Such a distinction can be found in the model of 
an online market with a self-selection bias of user reviews built by Li and Hitt (2008). In 
their model, they distinguish two classes of attributes: the 'search attributes', which can be 
inspected before the transaction, and the 'experience attributes', which are specific to each 
customer based on its experience of the product. 
Our model follows a similar approach with substep 1 using objective information 
and substep 2 being more subjective. We have two objective search attributes available 
for the guests to make a decision during substep 1: b g is the available budget of the 
guest g, and for each host h ∈ H, the guest can observe the price p h, t , i.e., the price 
requested to reserve the accommodation owned by h during night t. Using these 
attributes, during substep 1, all the guests sequentially try to find a host whose price 
is below their budget constraint and within a certain price range (r). The price range r 
gives us the opportunity to create some variations inside the scenarios, by looking at the 
effect of guests deviating more or less from their budget. For simplicity, r is the same 
for every guest inside a simulation. At the end of substep 1, for each guest g, H g is the 
subset of hosts from hosts H who are not yet booked and whose prices are below the 
budget b g , but not lower than b g − r: </p>

<p>H g ¼ h∈Hjbooked h ¼ false; b g −r ≤ p h;t ≤ b g 
È 
É </p>

<p>Then, the specificity of our platforms of interest is that quality is both a search 
attribute (the quality described by the host) and an experience attribute (the quality 
experienced by the guest and assessed in the user review). Based on the literature 
reviewed above, we make the following assumptions about the quality q h of each host: </p>

<p>&amp; the hosts are unable to assess their own quality because shared accommodations are 
heterogeneous, non-standard and include the characteristics of the host; </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>&amp; the guests are able to observe the quality once they visit the accommodation; 
&amp; this observation leads to subjective individual reviews. </p>

<p>This is the reason why, during substep 2, we implement two selection strategies, 
related to the concept of "lexicographic preferences" and developed by Valente (2012). 
Both strategies are based on an algorithm of product selection including empirically-
validated hypothesis on the behavior of boundedly rational and adaptive customers. We 
implement it in its simplest version: products are defined by two characteristics (quality 
and price). Customers have an order of preference for these characteristics, in line with 
their motivation (monetary and / or non-monetary). For both strategies, if H g ≠ ∅ after 
substep 1, then substep 2 has two components (substep 2.1 and substep 2.2), one for 
each characteristic. During substep 2.1, each guest creates a subset H ġ ⊆H g by selecting 
the hosts with the best performance in her first characteristic of interest. Then, during 
substep 2.2, if H ġ </p>



<p>&gt; 1, each guest creates a subset € 
H g ⊆H ġ ⊆H g by selecting the best 
performance in her second characteristic of interest. If € 
H g </p>



<p>&gt; 1, the host is chosen </p>

<p>randomly from € 
H g . 
The selection strategies are the concrete implementation of the behavioral 
decision making made by the agents using their specific form of motivation. 
The quality strategy reflects an agent whose motivations are mostly non-mon-
etary: the quality q reflects the objective characteristics of the accommodation, 
but in the case of the sharing economy, the quality includes immaterial char-
acteristics related to the hosts such as friendliness, shared values and so on. 
The price strategy is only monetary, in the sense that the guest value the 
savings provided by the platform. 
Based on the information available about the accommodations' characteristics, we 
implement two different strategies for the guests to select an accommodation: </p>

<p>&amp; Quality Strategy: the only way for guests to approximate the quality of an 
accommodation is to use the price as a proxy of quality, provided that the host 
has priced his accommodation adequately: </p>

<p>-substep 2.1: among the hosts in H g , guest g selects the host(s) with the highest 
reputation (number of positive reviews) within a margin of tolerance (τ reputation ), hence 
creating the subset H ġ ¼ h∈H g 
È </p>

<p>Pos h;t ≥ max Pos i;t 
À 
Á 
Â 1−τ reputation 
À 
Á 
; ∀i∈H g g. 
-substep 2.2: among the hosts in H ġ , guest g selects the host(s) with the highest 
price (as a proxy of the highest quality) within a margin of tolerance (τ price ), hence </p>

<p>creating the subset € 
H g ¼ h∈H ġ 
È </p>

<p>p h;t ≥ max p j;t </p>

<p>Â 1−τ price 
À 
Á 
; ∀ j∈H ġ g. </p>

<p>&amp; Price Strategy: Zervas et al. (2017) point up how <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> has affected a specific 
segment of the hospitality industry, the lower-end hotels. Hotels offering business 
services do not suffer from the emergence of this platform. Guttentag (2015)  observes that <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> is attractive to the low end of the market and covers a demand 
that is unattractive for the incumbents of the hospitality industry. <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> provides 
accommodations cheaper than hotels. Our understanding is that saving money is a 
strong motivation on these platforms: </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>-substep 2.1: among the hosts in H g , guest g selects the cheapest accommodation(s) 
within a margin of tolerance (τ price ), hence creating the subset 
H ġ ¼ h∈H g 
È </p>

<p>p h;t ≤ min p i;t 
À Á 
Â 1 þ τ price 
À 
Á 
; ∀i∈H g g. 
-substep 2.2: among the hosts in H ġ , guest g selects the host(s) with the highest 
reputation (number of positive reviews) within a margin of tolerance (τ reputation ), 
hence creating the subset € 
H g ¼ h∈H ġ 
È </p>

<p>Pos h;t ≥ max Pos j;t 
À 
Á 
Â 1−τ reputation 
À 
Á 
; ∀ 
j∈H ġ g where Pos h,t is the number of positive reviews for host h at the current 
simulation time step t. </p>

<p>Both strategies address the user reviews in the same way: they count the number of 
positive review as a way to distinguish between reputable and less reputable hosts 
(substep 2.2 of price-oriented strategy and substep 2.1 of quality-oriented). The differ-
ences are: the reversed lexicographic preferences between price and reputation, and the 
quality-oriented guests use the price as a proxy of quality while the price-oriented 
guests are focused on saving money. The tolerances τ price and τ reputation give us an 
opportunity to create some variations inside the scenarios, in the same way as r (the 
price range) does in substep 1, as did Valente (2012). 
Once all the guests have had an opportunity to find an accommodation, the guests 
who have found a match move to substep 3. During substep 3, the strategies make no 
difference and no additional parameter is used. Each matched guest visits her host and 
she reviews the quality of the accommodation. The content of the review depends on 
the similarity between the price paid and the quality observed while staying. The 
platform stores the review as a binary grade. </p>

<p>M h;t ¼ 
0 if quality q h &lt; price p h;t 
1 if quality q h ≥ price p h;t </p>

<p>&amp; </p>

<p>In other words, 0 means that the guest was 'unsatisfied' by the value for money of 
the accommodation, while 1 means 'satisfied' or 'positive review'. We use these simple 
grades in order to account for the difficulty to transfer valuable information from one 
guest to another (e.g. specific preferences, limited trust in strangers). Yet, following Hu  et al. (2006), a bimodal system of user reviews is still efficient when every participant 
contributes a review. So the potential frictions initiated by user reviews are not the 
result of their incompleteness, but come from the manner in which they are used by the 
supply side. </p>

<p>3.3 Supply side: Sharing profitably </p>

<p>Once substeps 1 to 3 are performed by the guests, the hosts have the opportunity to 
adjust their price. At substep 4, the hosts assess their individual successes and failures 
according to their own strategies. Reviews and occupancy form the only source of 
information they have to evaluate their accommodations. However, the guests had 
surveyed the market for their own selection process and, therefore, the selection 
outcome informs the hosts about their own market position. Depending on their 
strategy, they will define a success (m s,h,t ) and a failure (m f,h,t ) differently: </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>&amp; Satisfaction Strategy: receiving a bad grade (M h, t = 0) is a failure equivalent to not 
hosting a guest at all. 
&amp; Occupancy Strategy: the content of reviews have no influences on the host's 
decisions, the only thing that matters is the number of hosted guests. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows how successes (m s,h,t ) and failures (m f,h,t ) are computed. On these peer 
to peer platforms, we assume that the motivations of hosts and guests follow very 
similar logics. Consequently, hosts who are only motivated by monetary rewards will 
focus their decision strategy only on 'occupancy', while hosts who also value the social 
dimension of the platform will take into account the more qualitative 'guest satisfac-
tion' in their strategy. 
At substep 5, the hosts make a final decision about price adjustment. They compute 
the probability to adjust the price </p>

<p>Prob adjust price 
ð 
Þ h;t ¼ 
m s;h;t −m f ;h;t </p>





<p>a h;t 
Â ε </p>

<p>where a h, t ∈ ℤ 
+ is the number of steps since the last price adjustment (by definition, 
m s,h,t + m f,h,t = a h,t , i.e. successes and failures are measured since the latest price </p>

<p>adjustment only). If m s,h,t = m f,h,t , </p>

<p>m s;h;t −m f ;h;t </p>

<p>j 
j </p>

<p>a h;t </p>

<p>¼ 0, this means that, if successes equal </p>

<p>failures, the host receives a mixed signal and doesn't take action. If m s,h,t = a h,t or </p>

<p>m f,h,t = a h,t , </p>

<p>m s;h;t −m f ;h;t </p>

<p>j 
j </p>

<p>a h;t </p>

<p>¼ 1, this means that the host has the clearest signal possible that </p>

<p>maximizes the probability of adjusting price. The rationale is that agents make 
decisions using all the (limited) information they receive from the environment. The 
probability captures the strength of the signal they receive: the more evidence points in 
the same direction, the more chance to follow this lead. This follows the minimalist 
modelling of cognitive reasoning used by Epstein's (2014) agent_zero. Following 
Epstein, such a minimalist approach is still more realistic than giving the agents the 
ability to estimate the right price using a Bayesian approach, for instance. Consequent-
ly, the hosts try to estimate the probability of two events (overpricing, underpricing) 
using only the information accumulated since their latest action. Any older memory 
would be counterproductive in this minimalist setting since the information relates to a 
decision that has been changed. 
ε, 0 ≤ ε ≤ 1, is a parameter to control the frequency of actions in the simulation. Its 
function is to prevent hasty decisions by forcing the hosts to delay actions. A random 
value is drawn from the uniform distribution between 0 and 1; if Prob(adjust price) h, t is 
above this random value, the price is adjusted: </p>

<p>Table 2 Computation of m s,h,t and m f,h,t , using the information accumulated since the last price adjustment </p>

<p>Failure 
Success </p>

<p>Host Strategy 
Satisfaction 
m f,h,t = number of steps without 
positive reviews </p>

<p>m s,h,t = number of positive reviews </p>

<p>Occupancy 
m f,h,t = number of steps without guests 
m s,h,t = number of guests </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>&amp; if m s,h,t − m s,h,t &gt; 0 (i.e. successes &gt; failures), the price increases of 1 unit, 
&amp; if m s,h,t − m s,h,t &lt; 0, (i.e. failures &gt; successes), the price decreases of 1 unit, 
&amp; and, reminder, if m s,h,t = m f,h,t (i.e. successes = failures), no adjustment is made. </p>

<p>4 Results </p>

<p>The results discussed below are based on the following parameters: population P = 200, 
ε = 0.2, host population H = 100, guest population G = 100. The results are recorded at 
t = 2000 time steps and they show the average over 40 repetitions of the simulation to 
control for the stochastic processes (i.e., host's initial price, order of guest's queue, 
host's tiebreakers and host's price adjustment). 
4 The degree of randomness of the initial 
price γ is 0.5 for brevity of the results and following the observation of its effects 
detailed in the Appendix. Inside the four scenarios (see Table 1 above), the price range 
(r = {1, 2, 5,10,15,50} for the aggregated data and r = {1, 5, 15, 50} for the individual 
data) and the tolerances (τ price = {0.05,0.25} and τ reputation = {0.05,0.25}) provide ad-
ditional insights about the potential successes and failures of the platforms for 
|r| × |τ price | × |τ reputation | = 6 × 2 × 2 = 24 combinations of parameter values. </p>

<p>4.1 Centralization versus decentralization of platform governance </p>

<p>We begin by analyzing the performance at the platform level. Taking the host perspec-
tive, we consider the aggregated value of all the transactions completed during the 
simulation, i.e., how much revenue was created for the hosts from their under-utilized 
possessions. Taking the guest perspective, we consider the aggregated volume, i.e., how 
many accommodations were booked and visited by the guests. 
Figure 2 shows the performances of the different scenarios, using the 24 possible 
combinations of parameters r (price range delimiting the budget constraint) and τ price 
and τ reputation (tolerances). The value and volume of the transactions are compared to 
the centralized assortative matching, where p = q = b. Such a benchmark has two 
meanings: (i) there is a perfect matching between hosts and guests providing a full 
and constant occupancy of the accommodations, maximizing the aggregated volume 
and value of the transactions (perfect allocative efficiency); (ii) the hosts have been able 
to adjust their price in order to reflect the actual quality of the accommodation. As a 
reminder, this requires a fully centralized market, where a fully informed matchmaker 
would assortatively match the guest with a budget b to the host with a quality q = b, as 
well as command the host to charge a price p = q. This is theoretically reachable in this 
decentralized model, because there is no shortage or surplus on either side of the 
market: H = G, as well as q and b have the same values among the hosts and guests, 
respectively. The challenge is for the hosts to discover the right price p of their 
accommodation via step-by-step incremental adjustments. </p>

<p>4 Other parameter values have been tested to guarantee the robustness of our results. The results are collected 
once the platform has stabilized (large t); ε does not affect the relative results of the scenarios. The number of 
repetitions (40) is large enough to stabilize the coefficient of variation of the variables of interest. See the 
Appendix for a more detailed analysis of these values. </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>We make the assumption that the main objective of platform governance is to lead the 
participants closer to this benchmark. Figure 2 shows that Scenario I is the most 
successful means to reach this goal. In this scenario, hosts and guests are both motivated 
by the non-monetary signal embedded in the user reviews and they reach the highest 
levels of transactions in value and volume. Hosts receive 92-93% of the revenue and 
guests rent 95-96% of the accommodations they would have rented in a fully centralized 
system. In addition to the non-monetary motivation, the other condition is a wide price 
range and a greater tolerance for lower reputation (i.e. r = {10,15,50}, τ price = 0.05 and 
τ reputation = 0.25 identified in Scenario I by the significant group "a"). 
The interplay of different forms of motivations, implemented via the hosts' and guests' 
strategies, is not one-sided. The level of performance of a given strategy is highly 
interdependent with the strategy adopted on the other side of the market. For instance, 
in terms of value, the Satisfaction Strategy by the hosts (Scenarios I and II) seems to be the 
most successful Strategy. However, a decision by the guest to adopt a Price Strategy 
(Scenario II), together with a wide price range, can lead the hosts to endure the lowest 
level of revenue (45-49%), while the guests still find 71-74% of accommodations. In 
terms of volume, the Occupancy Strategy by the hosts (Scenarios III and IV) bans nearly 
50% of the guests from finding an accommodation. The individual search attributes </p>

<p>j 
i c d b 
b b c </p>

<p>j 
g 
b 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>j 
i d e c d e 
f </p>

<p>j 
g c d d e f 
h </p>

<p>l efg 
ab 
cd 
abc a ab </p>

<p>m gh def cde 
bc 
de </p>

<p>ab 
cde </p>

<p>l efg def gh ij 
j </p>

<p>m g fg hi jk k </p>

<p>k 
h b c f g 
i 
m </p>

<p>j d e a b e f 
i 
m </p>

<p>jk gh ab c ef 
l </p>

<p>j 
d 
a 
c f g 
l </p>

<p>h ab e 
i 
k 
n </p>

<p>i c d f g 
j 
l 
n </p>

<p>h 
a 
a b c e f m </p>

<p>i bc abc de g m </p>

<p>Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II </p>

<p>1 
2 
5 1 0 1 5 5 0 
1 
2 
5 10 15 50 </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>Price Range (r) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>70% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>Value of transactions 
(% of similarity and significant groups) </p>

<p>m k gh de cd bc </p>

<p>lm j 
f 
b 
a 
a </p>

<p>lm k hi ef ef ef </p>

<p>l 
j g h f 
g 
i </p>

<p>bc 
de </p>

<p>ab 
cd </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>bc 
de 
abc 
ab 
cd </p>

<p>g 
a cde 
cd 
ef </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>bc 
de </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>ab 
cd </p>

<p>cd 
ef 
fg fg efg </p>

<p>g ab 
de 
fg 
fg efg efg </p>

<p>m 
j bc d 
f no </p>

<p>l 
h 
a c d f g o </p>

<p>mn i ab ab d 
k </p>

<p>lm g ab b 
e 
l </p>

<p>ab 
cd 
ab def g 
ij 
k </p>

<p>ef a 
f gh j 
k </p>

<p>bc 
def 
abc 
cd 
ef 
ef 
cd 
ef 
hi </p>

<p>f 
a 
bc 
de 
f 
e f h i </p>

<p>Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II </p>

<p>1 
2 
5 1 0 1 5 5 0 
1 
2 
5 10 15 50 </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>Price Range (r) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>70% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>Volume of transactions 
(% of similarity and significant groups) </p>

<p>j 
i c d b 
b b c </p>

<p>j 
g 
b 
a 
a 
a </p>

<p>j 
i d e c d e 
f </p>

<p>j 
g c d d e f 
h </p>

<p>l efg 
ab 
cd 
abc a ab </p>

<p>m gh def cde 
bc 
de </p>

<p>ab 
cde </p>

<p>l efg def gh ij 
j </p>

<p>m g fg hi jk k </p>

<p>k 
h b c f g 
i 
m </p>

<p>j d e a b e f 
i 
m </p>

<p>jk gh ab c ef 
l </p>

<p>j 
d 
a 
c f g 
l </p>

<p>h ab e 
i 
k 
n </p>

<p>i c d f g 
j 
l 
n </p>

<p>h 
a 
a b c e f m </p>

<p>i bc abc de g m </p>

<p>Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II </p>

<p>1 
2 
5 1 0 1 5 5 0 
1 
2 
5 10 15 50 </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>Price Range (r) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>70% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>Value of transactions 
(% of similarity and significant groups) </p>

<p>m k gh de cd bc </p>

<p>lm j 
f 
b 
a 
a </p>

<p>lm k hi ef ef ef </p>

<p>l 
j g h f 
g 
i </p>

<p>bc 
de </p>

<p>ab 
cd </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>bc 
de 
abc 
ab 
cd </p>

<p>g 
a cde 
cd 
ef </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>bc 
de </p>

<p>cd 
ef </p>

<p>ab 
cd </p>

<p>cd 
ef 
fg fg efg </p>

<p>g ab 
de 
fg 
fg efg efg </p>

<p>m 
j bc d 
f no </p>

<p>l 
h 
a c d f g o </p>

<p>mn i ab ab d 
k </p>

<p>lm g ab b 
e 
l </p>

<p>ab 
cd 
ab def g 
ij 
k </p>

<p>ef a 
f gh j 
k </p>

<p>bc 
def 
abc 
cd 
ef 
ef 
cd 
ef 
hi </p>

<p>f 
a 
bc 
de 
f 
e f h i </p>

<p>Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II </p>

<p>1 
2 
5 1 0 1 5 5 0 
1 
2 
5 10 15 50 </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>(.05;.05) </p>

<p>(.05;.25) </p>

<p>(.25;.05) </p>

<p>(.25;.25) </p>

<p>Price Range (r) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>70% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>Volume of transactions 
(% of similarity and significant groups) </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Aggregated value and volume of transactions at the platform level. For all the combinations of 
scenarios and parameter values, the figure compares the allocative efficiency relative to the benchmark (i.e, the 
centralized assortative matching) in terms of "similarity" with the benchmark. The efficiency is analyzed at the 
aggregated level for all the hosts in terms of "Value of transactions" and for all the guests in terms of "Volume 
of transactions". The efficiency is analyzed using the data from the simulation ("% of similarity") and a post-
hoc analysis of this data ("Significant groups"). "% of similarity" (graduated color scale from black to white): 
Percentage of similarity with the benchmark. For instance, a Value of transactions of 90% means that this 
specific configuration of scenarios and parameters has achieved to accumulate 90% of the value that would 
have been achieved by centralized assortative matching. "Significant groups" (letters "a" to "o"): For each 
scenario, percentages of similarity are compared in terms of statistical difference (ANOVA). Because they are 
significantly different, a post-hoc analysis is conducted to rank and group the similarities, using Tukey's 
comparison of means at 99% confidence level. Two consecutive groups in the alphabetical order are 
significantly different at level 99%. For instance, "a" achieves a statistically significantly higher percentage 
of similarity than "b". When the figure shows a string of more than one group in a single cell (e.g. "ab" or 
"cdef"), it means that the configuration of parameters of this cell does not produces a percentage of similarity 
significantly different from other cells in the same group(s) </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>(tolerance and price range) cannot influence this result. Yet, this strategy is not too 
detrimental for the hosts who receive up to 75% of the available revenue. 
The price range r is the second most important factor explaining the performance of 
the platform. 
5 When r = 1, the guests potentially reveal they budget b by avoiding 
accommodations below their budget. In the two-sided matching literature, revealing 
this kind of information is essential for successful matchmakings. For this reason, 
platform owners might be willing to control the accommodation search in this way to 
mimic an omniscient matchmaker. However, Fig. 2 shows the poor result of this 
solution. In fact, we observe in many places an inverted-U relationship between r 
and performance (both value and volume of transactions). In most cases, both in value 
and in volume, the best performance is obtained for intermediate values (r = {2, 5, 10}). 
While r = 1 is clearly outperformed by r = 50 in Scenarios I and III, the reverse is true 
for Scenarios II and IV. The signal is clear for the platform governance: when the 
motivation is mostly monetary, it is better to limit the price scope during the guest 
search for accommodation, for instance, by putting the most expensive accommoda-
tions higher in the search results. Interestingly, the best performance described earlier 
includes r = 50. Consequently, there is a very fine line between the instrumentation of 
successful control and failed control. 
Finally, the tolerances (τ price and τ reputation ) provide small but significant insights. The 
effect of τ price is correlated with the guest motivation. When the motivation is not just 
monetary (Scenario I), increasing it reduces both the value and volume of transactions. 
On the contrary, when the motivation is purely monetary, a greater tolerance improve 
both the value and volume in Scenario II and the value in Scenario IV. The effect of a 
greater τ reputation is positive when hosts are not just motivated by their occupancy. 
However, the benefits of tolerating a wider range of reputation decreases with the price 
range r. Consequently, a certain leeway is important on their first source of motivation 
observed on the platform, wherever the motivation is located in terms of side. </p>

<p>4.2 Frictions among individuals on each side of the marketplace </p>

<p>Additional insights about the performance of platforms are to be found in the frictions 
between participants inside the platform. In Figs. 3 and 4, the performance of the 
platforms (value and volume) is broken down by individual participants. For each host, 
ordered by quality level q, we individualize how much revenue (sum of values of 
transactions) received during the simulation, in percent of the revenue of full occupancy 
at p = q (i.e. centralized assortative matching, when the host accommodates a guest 
paying p = q = b at every time step). For each guest, ordered by budget level b, we 
individualize how many accommodations they are able to book, in percent of the full 
occupancy (i.e. centralized assortative matching, when the guests find an accommoda-
tion at every time step). 
For every scenario, the simulation produces two trends: when the host quality 
increases, his ability to earn an adequate income decreases (Fig. 3) and the guest's 
ability to book all the needed accommodations decreases with her budget (Fig. 4). 
While these results relate to the simple behavioral assumptions of the model, the range </p>

<p>5 The point can be verified in the Appendix. The Tables 5 and 6 show that the price range r has the highest 
main effect, by comparison to the other variables in the model. </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>of strategies and parameter values offers us several options to assist the platform and 
avoid such extreme outcomes. 
First, on our platforms of interest, matches are exclusive during one time step: e.g., 
accommodations are booked for a given date and they become unavailable for concur-
rent use. This process creates local shortages on specific segments of the marketplace, 
particularly when hosts are still assessing the quality or price of their accommodations. 
These shortages can be seen in our simulation by the allocative inefficiency in Figs. 3 
and 4. In details, we observe that, when the price range r increases, the value and 
volume improve for some participants (hosts with intermediate quality in Fig. 3 and 
guests with high budget in Fig. 4). In fact, increasing the price range reduces the local 
shortages and, therefore, it increases the number of transactions, since guests are less 
likely to be without a host after substep 1 (i.e. when they look for a host within a range r 
of their budget). While the volume of transactions in Fig. 4 cannot exceed 100% (i.e. 
maximum potential allocative efficiency, when each guest achieve exactly one </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II 
Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>r: 1 </p>

<p>r: 5 </p>

<p>r: 15 </p>

<p>r: 50 </p>

<p>25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>200% </p>

<p>500% </p>

<p>1,000% </p>

<p>2,000% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>200% </p>

<p>500% </p>

<p>1,000% </p>

<p>2,000% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>200% </p>

<p>500% </p>

<p>1,000% </p>

<p>2,000% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>200% </p>

<p>500% </p>

<p>1,000% </p>

<p>2,000% </p>

<p>Host Quality q 
Similarity (with centralized assortative matching) (log </p>

<p>10) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>(0.05;0.05) 
(0.05;0.25) 
(0.25;0.05) 
(0.25;0.25) </p>

<p>Value of transactions 
(% of similarity) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Value of transactions at the individual level for each Scenario. For each scenario, the graphs depict 
how much the marketplaces deviate from the centralized assortative matching in terms of value, depending on 
the tolerance and on the price range (r = {1, 5, 15, 50}, stacked vertically). Hosts are ordered by their unique 
and fixed quality q </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>transaction at every time step), a value of transaction above 100% in Fig. 3 means that 
hosts can overcharge their accommodations leading to a revenue exceeding what would 
happen by assortative matching. 
Second, increasing the price range of search has a counterpart: the additional 
pressure on the cheapest accommodation and the devaluation of the most expensive 
ones. As observed at the aggregated level, regarding the value of transactions (Fig. 3), 
these phenomena are particularly visible for Scenarios I, II and IV. At the individual 
level, when the price range r increases, we observe an increasing value for the hosts 
with the lowest quality levels and decreasing revenue for the hosts with the highest 
quality. The value being a direct result of pricing, these results also means that the 
lowest quality hosts overprice their accommodations (p &gt; q) while the highest quality 
hosts underprice their accommodations (p &lt; q). The tolerances from the guests can 
slightly alter these phenomena as noticed at the aggregated level. We can see now that 
the effect of τ price is limited to the intermediate and high ends of the supply side. 
Third, these phenomena of overpricing and underpricing also have a direct effect on 
the volume of transactions (Fig. 4), leading to the exclusion of the guests with the </p>

<p>Scenario I 
Scenario II 
Scenario III 
Scenario IV </p>

<p>r: 1 </p>

<p>r: 5 </p>

<p>r: 15 </p>

<p>r: 50 </p>

<p>25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 
25 
50 
75 
100 </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>25% </p>

<p>50% </p>

<p>75% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>Guest Budget b </p>

<p>Similarity (with centralized assortative matching) </p>

<p>Tolerance (τprice;τreputation) </p>

<p>(0.05;0.05) 
(0.05;0.25) 
(0.25;0.05) 
(0.25;0.25) </p>

<p>Volume of transactions 
(% of similarity) </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Volume of transactions at the individual level for each Scenario. Same as Fig. 3, in terms of 
volume. Guests are ordered by their unique and fixed budget b </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>lowest budget. The exclusion increases with the price range r and is more limited for 
Scenario I and II than for Scenario III and IV where we observe a clear cutoff around 
the guest budget b = 50. The tolerance has an interesting effect in Scenario III and IV 
that was invisible at the aggregated level: a higher tolerance for reputation slightly 
smooths the inequality of successful matching between lower and higher budgets. </p>

<p>5 Discussion </p>

<p>With the simulations, we have shown how the local frictions emerging on decentralized 
platforms create specific patterns of aggregated market failure that we have measured in 
terms of allocative inefficiency (equivalent to underactivity and exclusion). In fact, 
agent-based simulations help us to understand the conditions for "non-transactions", 
which are more difficult to capture empirically than the transactions. Transactions can 
only measure what is working, when the traders benefit from the transaction. However, 
to assess the potential evolution of the platform, it matters to understand the platforms' 
failures, too. Following the three components of our theoretical framework, we will 
now discuss how the extent and the shape of market failures are influenced by (i) the 
interplay of forms of motivation (the scenarios), (ii) the instruments of governance 
(stylized by the tolerances and price range during search), and (iii) the imperfect 
information created by the user reviews. </p>

<p>5.1 The motivations of sharing </p>

<p>If one assumes that the profit-based online platforms of the sharing economy provides 
an opportunity to make a profit and / or contribute to the public good by sharing idle 
possessions, one can also assume that achieving just one transaction improves the 
social welfare (Botsman and Rogers 2011). Looking at the patterns of exclusion for 
specific participants that we just described, the threshold between success and failure is 
to be discussed. A certain level of underactivity is intrinsically linked to our assump-
tions: absence of negotiation (search is directed using posted prices) and absence of 
stock (only one unit is available per trader). In this context, Chade et al. (2017: 34)  establish that the solution can only by a trade-off where "sellers that post lower prices 
will attract more potential buyers and will therefore sell with a higher probability. 
Buyers who pursue lower-priced goods must accept lower trade probabilities since 
there are more competing buyers. With two-sided heterogeneity and complementarity, 
this trade-off plays an important role in the determination of the equilibrium sorting 
patterns." Clearly, the motivations of the participants influences the direction of the 
trade-off between economic profitably (value) and social activity (volume). 
Underactivity may be acceptable, because the platforms exhibit the characteristics of 
a 'long tail', as observed in e-commerce (Einav et al. 2016). This can also be seen in our 
simulation, via the strong inequality in revenue and activity among members. Partici-
pants may react to this inequality via two behavioral patterns, as identified by Ikkala &amp;  Lampinen (2014: 175): increasing the price as the number of positive reviews grows 
larger to filter the demand or, on the contrary, underpricing the listing to increase its 
visibility. By capturing these behaviors in our model, we show how the unequal demand 
cannot be reduced to a long tail phenomenon, since it has consequences on the price </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>structure of the marketplace leading to the exclusion of categories of users. The long tail 
can be seen as an opportunity for participants who do not value visibility because they 
cater to the needs of specific participants. However, the other side of the coin is that the 
visibility can be captured by the "superstar effect", where successful suppliers benefit 
from the reinforcement learning until price and quality become disconnected (Levin  2013). This effect can be exacerbated by user reviews, as we will discuss below. 
Conversely, underactivity can be detrimental to the platform, either by increasing the 
complexity of search due to the profusion of unverified sellers or by generating a 
negative word-of-mouth about the platform. The hypothesis that participants keep using 
the platform even if it is not efficient is at odds with other models, such as Einav et al.  (2016). However, by assuming that the sharing economy provides goods to individuals 
who cannot afford transactions on traditional marketplaces, we simulate the emergence 
of an overpriced low-end market for captive users. By offering more consumption 
opportunities to individuals who were excluded from the traditional marketplaces, the 
profit-based sharing economy may produce its own failures by excluding or 
overcharging its participants. These failures are contradictory with some of the non-
monetary expectations of the sharing economy, such as improving social capital and 
trust, or helping less advantaged groups (Codagnone et al. 2016). In addition, due to the 
winner-takes-all nature of two-sided platforms (Caillaud and Jullien 2003), these failures 
can have dreary consequences once a platform monopolizes the market (Frenken and  Schor 2017). By identifying the specific locations of failure, our simulations show why 
buyers on the lower end and sellers on the higher end should join alternative platforms or 
encourage forms of governance that would be less detrimental to them. </p>

<p>5.2 The instruments of platform governance </p>

<p>The main challenge established at the individual motivation level is that the trade-off 
between volume and value affect different sides of the platform, unlike Zhan and 
Friedman's model (Zhan and Friedman 2007) where the auctions help to balance greed 
(increase the profitability of the transaction) and fear (limit the chance to achieve a 
transaction). This result put forward the complex design decisions made at the platform 
level. For instance, with the occupancy strategy in Scenarios III and IV, sellers who are 
motivated by monetary rewards make decisions that are detrimental to their competitors, 
customers and the platform as a whole. Concretely, this form of motivation from the sellers 
excludes a large part of the potential buyers (only 50% to 53% of allocative efficiency in 
volume), yet they manage to receive up to 75% of the value. This means high revenue per 
transaction. If we assume that the sharing activities are a side-activity for the participants, it 
seems fair that the participants want to limit their commitment to the most profitable 
transactions. However, this strategy fails to provide a Universal Service (Slee 2016) and it 
can be easily taken over by incumbents who propose a wider scope of products (Cusumano  2015). The platform owners can also share those concerns. If they receive a percentage of 
the transaction value and they are willing to reduce the costs related to an increased activity 
on the platform, they might favor Scenarios III or IV. 
By contrast, owners interested in attaining a critical mass of participants to compete with 
the incumbents or achieve Universal Service would like to recreate the conditions of 
Scenario I. As exemplified by Brian Chesky email, platform policies can be implemented 
to encourage the adoption of non-monetary motivations. Put in terms of motivation, </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>platform owners can use strategically their market environment to crowd out or crowd in 
participation on their platforms (Frey and Jegen 2001). Using the literature on two-sided 
matching, obtaining information about the motivations of users can be useful ex ante to 
create the behavioral conditions represented by the scenarios. In the same line, information 
about the user characteristics (such as their budget and quality in our model) can also give 
an opportunity to the platform owner to limit the entry of participants who will systemat-
ically be excluded. By studying a few simple governance instruments in our model 
(tolerance and price range), we have shown that these instruments have non-linear and 
strongly interdependent effects. Designing these instruments of governance is difficult, 
which can explain the numerous changes and experiments performed by the platforms, as 
well as the misalignment between the motivations of the designers and those of the 
participants, as observed by Bellotti et al. (2015). 
From the participant perspective, our results echo the work of Lauermann et al.  (2017) showing that decentralized mechanisms can achieve allocation efficiency 
even when the participants ignore the exact market condition (including their own 
characteristics), provided that the search frictions are small. To diminish the search 
friction, the platform should use all the governance mechanisms (monetary, non-
monetary and informational) at its disposal (Boudreau and Hagiu 2009; Phelps  et al. 2008). For instance, Gode and Sunder (1997) face a similar problem when 
their double auction system cannot prevent the allocative inefficiency resulting 
from the displacement of intramarginal traders by extramarginal traders (who do 
not value the goods as much as the intramarginal traders). As a solution, they 
sketch an alternative market governance that almost mimics the mechanism of 
centralized assortative matching (e.g., bids and asks closer to actual constraints, 
delayed decisions queuing in a clearing house). In the same line, Anderson and  Renault (1999) use search costs to explain the emergence of "tourist traps", i.e., 
options with similar characteristics and largely overpriced, because "buyers do not 
shop around". Different mechanisms can be tested to achieve such results. In 
addition to the non-monetary instruments proposed above and following the 
lessons from the two-sided market literature, the platform can regulate the behav-
iors monetarily by subsidizing the underactive participants using fees collected 
from their overpriced counterpart. The platform can also modify how the infor-
mation is displayed, for instance, to alter the tolerance and the price range of the 
participants. In fact, <rs type="software">Airbnb</rs> uses such a mechanism in the search ranking of 
accommodations. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5.3 User reviews and reputation </p>

<p>In this research, we have made the assumption that user reviews are a major piece 
of information for participant decisions on the platforms. By implementing user 
reviews in only three of the four scenarios (Scenario IV is extrinsically-motivated 
on both sides), we were interested in testing the complex interactions of user 
reviews and decentralization. The main difference between Scenarios III and IV is 
the use (or not) of user reviews by the users. We observe only a very small </p>

<p>6 https://www.airbnb.com/help/article/39/what-factors-determine-how-my-listing-appears-in-search-results 
(last visited on August 7, 2017) </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>difference: with user reviews, the high-end hosts are slightly more rewarded. Yet 
the user review alone is unable to prevent unsatisfactory transactions. On the other 
side, with Scenarios I and II, the user review is a very efficient tool to help the 
hosts in assessing the quality of their accommodations. Even if our results are 
slightly more positive toward the user reviews (since every guest has to write one), 
it also confirms that user reviews have a limited value without context and 
quantity (Benkler 2004; Dellarocas 2003), the reason being that user reviews 
can exacerbate the artificial prominence of some participants in a complex way. 
In line with our results, we expect search frictions to create captive users, leading 
the prominent supplier to increase its price, while the competitors have to reduce 
theirs (Armstrong et al. 2009). If we try to diminish the search frictions, the 
situation can deteriorate because the improved substitutability between products 
might make the participants even more dependent on user reviews for their 
decision and therefore reinforce the market power of the prominent suppliers 
(Kim et al. 2010). 
Finally, in our model, user reviews are written regarding an identifiable and fixed 
quality of the accommodation. Yet, on other platforms, the quality of the transactions 
can be based on more subjective characteristics. For instance, with carpooling, the 
characteristics of the car and seats have a minor importance for the transaction, by 
comparison to the driver's behavior. We assumed earlier that user reviews are a way to 
enforce and inculcate the values, moral system and expectations of the social group; 
consequently a feedback can exist between the user review and the behavior being 
reviewed. In an extreme form of control, the platform can use the reviews to select the 
best participants. The implementation of this strategy would again depend on the 
position of the platform and its participants regarding the trade-off between higher 
volume of transactions versus higher value (or quality) of transactions. </p>

<p>6 Limitations and possible extensions </p>

<p>Using an agent-based model mimicking the emergence of a profit-based platform for 
sharing consumer goods, we show how much these platforms must balance motiva-
tions, as well as control. Even if the individual simulations involve agents with 
homogeneous strategies, they give some clear insights about the platform governance, 
particularly to the platform owners interested in avoiding such extreme outcomes. In 
addition to the insights developed above, this research also contributes to an assessment 
of a theoretical framework that can be used to monitor the real evolution of these 
platforms and, therefore, contributes to the empirical understanding of the profit-based 
sharing economy. For instance, the collection of data should not be limited to the 
successful transactions: failed transactions involve specific profiles of participant that 
reduce the universality of these platforms. 
In this current version, the simulations are performed on a closed platform with a 
population of agents having immutable characteristics. A dynamic version of the model, 
introducing the entry of new users depending on platform success and the exit of 
unsatisfied agents, would be a particularly interesting extension of the model. More than 
an extension, adding dynamics in the population of participants relate to a different set of 
empirical and theoretical questions. The type of motivations / actions discussed here </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>would have to be replaced by an analysis of the mechanisms triggering actions. Such a 
setting could also be used to understand the competition between platforms of the sharing 
economy, for instance, between profit-based and not-for-profit in line with the existing 
work between proprietary and open source approach in software programming. 
Along those lines, a limitation of the existing model is the simple and homogeneous 
representation of the population. This choice was motivated by our focus on the 
interplay between monetary and non-monetary motivations, as well as the efficiency 
of user reviews. Consequently, this model could be used to study some other aspects of 
the platform governance, particularly when the participants' characteristics are not 
uniformly distributed or when the platform has to deal with seasonal activity. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments I would like to thank two anonymous referees and the participants in WCSS2015 and 
IWSE2015 for their helpful comments. I am also grateful to John Miller for his excellent suggestions on 
previous versions of this work. </p>

<p>Data availability statement The datasets generated during and/or analyzed during the current study are 
available from the corresponding author upon request. The simulation model is also available and can be run 
using <rs id="software-27" type="software">NetLogo</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-27" type="creator">Wilensky</rs> <rs corresp="#software-27" type="version">1999</rs>). </p>

<p>Compliance with ethical standards </p>

<p>Conflict of interest The author declares that he has no conflict </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>In the following, we explain the choice of parameter values. Table 3 gives an overview 
of the variables of interest available in the model. </p>

<p>Table 3 Summary of variables, factors and ranges used for the simulations and sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>Name 
Type 
Range </p>

<p>Value of transactions 
Independent 
[0;1], i.e. percentage of centralized assortative matching 
Volume of-transactions Independent 
[0;1], i.e. percentage of centralized assortative matching 
Population P 
Control 
200 
Time steps t 
Control 
2000 
Repetitions 
Control 
40 
Scenario 
Dependent (complex factor) I (Satisfaction &amp; Quality), II (Satisfaction &amp; Price), 
III (Occupancy &amp; Quality), IV (Occupancy &amp; Price) 
Randomness ratio γ 
Dependent 
Base = 0.5, FF = OAT = [0;1] (5) 
Frequency of action ε Dependent 
Base = 0.2, FF = [0.18;0.22], OAT = [0.1;0.3] (5) 
Price range r 
Dependent 
Base = 2, FF = [1;15], OAT = [0;50] (10) 
Tau price 
Dependent 
Base = 0.1, FF = [0.05;0.25], OAT = [0.00;0.25] (5) 
Tau reputation 
Dependent 
Base = 0.1, FF = [0.05;0.25], OAT = [0.00;0.25] (5) </p>

<p>Base, Base value; FF, range of full factorial design; OAT, range for Morris' Elementary effect (number of 
levels between brackets) </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>i. Number of time steps and number of repetitions </p>

<p>Using the base values of the parameters, we study the evolution of the independent 
variables over a long period of 3000 time steps. Its evolution is shown in Fig. 5 by 
reporting the variables themselves (top panel) and the evolution of the variables during 
periods of 50 steps. When t = 2000, we consider that the variation of the results is 
almost null. As a trade-off between computational costs and quality of data, we limit 
the simulation to 2000 time steps. 
Following Lorscheid et al. (2012), we control for the stochasticity of the results by 
using a number of repetitions that stabilizes the coefficient of variation of the indepen-
dent variables. This stabilization can be observed on Fig. 6 around 40 repetitions. </p>

<p>ii. Local sensitivity analysis: the relative importance of variables </p>

<p>Following Thiele et al. (2014), we perform a local sensitivity analysis by 
looking at the effect of the dependent factors (or variables) on the independent </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 </p>

<p>Step (t) 
% of centralized assortative matching </p>

<p>Volume of transactions </p>

<p>0.68 </p>

<p>0.72 </p>

<p>0.76 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>0.84 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 </p>

<p>Step (t) 
% of centralized assortative matching </p>

<p>Scenarios </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>Value of transactions </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 </p>

<p>Step (t) </p>

<p>Variation (%) </p>

<p>Scenarios </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>(variation over 50 steps) </p>

<p>Value of transactions </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>0 
1000 
2000 
3000 </p>

<p>Step (t) </p>

<p>Variation (%) </p>

<p>(variation over 50 steps) </p>

<p>Volume of transactions </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Effect of the number of time steps </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>variables, one factor at a time. Due to the number of inputs and the high-
computational cost of the model, we follow the Morris method, which offers 
the best trade-off between information quality and computational costs. The 
results are reported on Fig. 7, and the parameter space is created from the full 
factorial design described in Table 3. 
The top panel of Fig. 7 gives an overview of the effect of the factors on the 
independent variables. This is achieved by the comparison of the two measures μ 
(average effect of each factor using values sampled from the factorial design) and μ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>(similar to μ, using the absolute value of the effect). μ 
 *  shows the influence from the 
factors on the independent variable, while the comparison between μ 
 *  and μ tells us 
if the influence is monotonic. First, the importance of each factor varies with the 
scenarios, making it difficult to pin down a single factor of interest. For instance, the 
degree of randomness of the initial price seems to have a strong influence of 
Scenario IV, but this factor is almost non-influential in other scenarios. Second, the 
difference of scale between μ 
 *  and μ lets us suspect the existence of non-monotonic 
relationships. For instance, τ price shows a strong influence on the value of transactions 
in Scenario I, as measured by μ </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>. Since its value on the μ axis is almost null, we 
suspect a nonlinear relationship. 
On the bottom panel, we observe the interaction between factors measured 
by σ (the standard deviation of the effect μ). Again, the sensitivity varies 
between scenarios. In addition, many factors exhibit a relatively high σ, show-
ing the existence of interactions between factors. </p>

<p>iii. Global sensitivity analysis: main effect and interaction effect </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 </p>

<p>Repetitions </p>

<p>Coefficient of Variation </p>

<p>Scenarios </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality </p>

<p>Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>(coefficient of variation with increasing number of repetitions) </p>

<p>Value of transactions </p>

<p>0.0025 </p>

<p>0.0050 </p>

<p>0.0075 </p>

<p>0.0100 </p>

<p>0.0125 </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 </p>

<p>Repetitions </p>

<p>Coefficient of Variation </p>

<p>(coefficient of variation with increasing number of repetitions) </p>

<p>Volume of transactions </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Number of repetitions and coefficient of variation </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>Using the effect analysis method proposed by Lorscheid et al. (2012) and 
implemented by Thiele et al. (2014), we quantify the effect of the different 
variables, in interaction. For the following work, we use the extremes of the 
full factorial design shown in Table 3. 
The first step of the effect analysis consists in a factorial ANOVA. The Table 4 
reports the levels of significance, looking at the main effects by individual 
factors and the interaction effects of pairs of factor on the two independent 
variables for the four scenarios. As expected, the variables with limited main 
effects such as ε and τ reputation have limited interaction effects when coupled with 
other variables. The second step consists in measuring the strength of the effects 
(main and interaction). Table 5 reports the effects on the value of transactions 
and Table 6 reports the effects on the volume. The diagonal (in bold) shows the 
main effects. </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality 
Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality 
Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>0.05 
0.10 
0.05 
0.10 </p>

<p>−0.12 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>−0.12 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>Factor </p>

<p>init−price−randomness </p>

<p>price−range−search </p>

<p>proba−action </p>

<p>tau−price </p>

<p>tau−reputation </p>

<p>Value of transactions </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality 
Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality 
Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>0.03 
0.06 
0.09 
0.12 
0.03 
0.06 
0.09 
0.12 </p>

<p>−0.09 </p>

<p>−0.06 </p>

<p>−0.03 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>−0.09 </p>

<p>−0.06 </p>

<p>−0.03 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>Factor </p>

<p>init−price−randomness </p>

<p>price−range−search </p>

<p>proba−action </p>

<p>tau−price </p>

<p>tau−reputation </p>

<p>Volume of transactions </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality 
Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality 
Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>0.05 
0.10 
0.05 
0.10 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>Value of transactions </p>

<p>Sc.III:Occupancy&amp;Quality 
Sc.IV:Occupancy&amp;Price </p>

<p>Sc.I:Satisfaction&amp;Quality 
Sc.II:Satisfaction&amp;Price </p>

<p>0.03 
0.06 
0.09 
0.12 
0.03 
0.06 
0.09 
0.12 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>μ </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>σ </p>

<p>Volume of transactions </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Morris screening method </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>Table 4 Levels of significance of main effects and interaction effects measured by factorial ANOVA </p>

<p>I Satisfaction 
&amp; Quality </p>

<p>II Satisfaction 
&amp; Price </p>

<p>III Occupancy 
&amp; Quality </p>

<p>IV Occupancy 
&amp; Price </p>

<p>Factors 
value 
volume 
value 
volume 
value 
volume 
value 
volume </p>

<p>γ (initial randomness) 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
ε (action frequency) 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
* 
*** 
r (price range) 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
τ price 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
τ reputation 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
γ: ε 
** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
** 
γ: r 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
** 
*** 
*** 
ε: r 
* 
** 
γ: τ price 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
* 
ε: τ price 
* 
* 
r: τ price 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
γ: τ reputation 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
* 
** 
ε: τ reputation 
* 
* * * 
* * 
r: τ reputation 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
*** 
** 
τ price : τ reputation 
*** 
*** 
** </p>

<p>*for p-value &lt;0.05 </p>

<p>**for p-value &lt;0.01 </p>

<p>***for p-value &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>Table 5 Effect matrix for value of transactions </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>Scenario I Satisfaction &amp; Quality 
γ 
−0.0200 
0.0024 
0.0185 
0.0032 
−0.0097 </p>

<p>ε 
0.0026 
−0.0011 
−0.0019 
0.0016 </p>

<p>r 
0.0732 
−0.0239 
−0.0160 </p>

<p>τ price 
−0.0253 
−0.0109 </p>

<p>τ rep 
0.0273 </p>

<p>Scenario II Satisfaction &amp; Price 
γ 
−0.0177 
0.0037 
0.0211 
0.0035 
−0.0099 </p>

<p>ε 
0.0010 
−0.0013 
−0.0002 
0.0029 </p>

<p>r 
−0.0316 
0.0327 
−0.0238 </p>

<p>τ price 
0.0325 
−0.0014 </p>

<p>τ rep 
0.0210 </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

<p>Table 6 Effect Matrix for Volume of transactions </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>Scenario I Satisfaction &amp; Quality 
γ 
-0.0297 
0.0026 
0.0087 
0.0011 
−0.0061 </p>

<p>ε 
0.0026 
−0.0005 
−0.0011 
0.0006 </p>

<p>r 
0.1012 
−0.0102 
−0.0153 </p>

<p>τ price 
−0.0113 
−0.0061 </p>

<p>τ rep 
0.0191 </p>

<p>Scenario II Satisfaction &amp; Price 
γ 
−0.0323 
0.0037 
0.0070 
0.0038 
−0.0075 </p>

<p>ε 
0.0019 
−0.0007 
−0.0005 
0.0016 </p>

<p>r 
0.0459 
0.0088 
−0.0195 </p>

<p>τ price 
0.0102 
−0.0017 </p>

<p>τ rep 
0.0144 </p>

<p>Table 5 (continued) </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>Scenario III Occupancy &amp; Quality </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>γ 
−0.0057 
0.0003 
−0.0031 
−0.0047 
0.0002 
ε 
−0.0013 
−0.0006 
−0.0001 
0.0001 </p>

<p>r 
0.0011 
−0.0060 
0.0024 
τ price 
−0.0052 
−0.0002 </p>

<p>τ rep 
−0.0062 </p>

<p>Scenario IV Occupancy &amp; Price 
γ 
−0.0067 
0.0007 
−0.0030 
−0.0038 
−0.0002 </p>

<p>ε 
−0.0006 
−0.0008 
−0.0002 
0.0005 </p>

<p>r 
−0.0490 
0.0429 
0.0021 
τ price 
0.0440 
−0.0002 </p>

<p>τ rep 
−0.0064 </p>

<p>Main effects in bold font, interaction effects elsewhere </p>

<p>A. Querbes </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a 
link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>Table 6 (continued) </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>Scenario III Occupancy &amp; Quality </p>

<p>Factors 
γ 
ε 
r 
τ price 
τ rep </p>

<p>γ 
0.0026 
−0.0001 
−0.0009 
−0.0014 
−0.0007 </p>

<p>ε 
−0.0052 
0.0001 
−0.0001 
0.0001 </p>

<p>r 
−0.0031 
−0.0002 
−0.0004 </p>

<p>τ price 
−0.0006 
0.0001 
τ rep 
0.0004 </p>

<p>Scenario IV Occupancy &amp; Price 
γ 
0.0013 
−0.0002 
−0.0015 
−0.0006 
−0.0008 </p>

<p>ε 
−0.0047 
0.0004 
−0.0004 
0.0002 </p>

<p>r 
−0.0084 
0.0056 
−0.0008 </p>

<p>τ price 
0.0058 
−0.0001 </p>

<p>τ rep 
0.0004 </p>

<p>Main effects in bold font, interaction effects elsewhere </p>

<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>



<p>Banned from the sharing economy: an agent-based model of a... </p>

</text></tei>