<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecoj.12284" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Credence goods markets suffer from inefficiencies caused by superior information of sellers about 
the surplus-maximising quality. While standard theory predicts that equal mark-up prices solve the 
credence goods problem if customers can verify the quality received, experimental evidence indicates 
the opposite. We identify a lack of robustness with respect to heterogeneity in social preferences as a 
possible cause of this and conduct new experiments that allow for parsimonious identification of 
sellers' social preference types. Our results confirm the assumed heterogeneity in social preferences 
and provide strong support for our explanation of the failure of verifiability to increase efficiency. </p>

<p>A central topic in the field of information economics is the design of institutions or 
contracts that mitigate market inefficiencies resulting from the presence of 
asymmetric information. Almost all contributions to the literature build on the 
assumption of common knowledge that agents are rational own-money maximisers 
who behave as desired when kept indifferent in own-money terms -see Bolton and  Dewatripont (2005) for a textbook coverage of this approach. In this article, we argue 
that while this assumption is harmless in some applications -because it results in 
institutions that are almost optimal if preferences are almost as assumed -it is 
misleading in others. 
Specifically, we study markets for credence goods where inefficiencies result from 
superior information of sellers about the optimal quality for consumers. In such 
markets, theory predicts that equal-mark-up prices solve the problem if customers can 
verify the quality received (Dulleck and Kerschbamer, 2006). However, this prediction 
is refuted by existing experimental evidence which indicates that markets with 
verifiability perform no better than markets without (Dulleck et al., 2011). We identify 
a lack of robustness of institutional design with respect to heterogeneity in social 
preferences as a possible cause. By social preferences, we mean that subjects may not 
only care for their own material pay-off but may consider the pay-offs of others as well, 
when making decisions. 
To provide support for our explanation for the failure of verifiability to increase 
efficiency, we design a simple and intuitive test that allows for parsimonious 
identification of a seller's social preference type. The results obtained in an </p>

<p>implementation of the test indicate that less than a fourth of the experimental sellers 
behave in accordance with the standard assumption on preferences. The rest behave 
either in line with other forms of selfish preferences or in accordance with different 
variants of non-selfish social preferences. Taken together our experimental findings 
provide strong support for heterogeneity in social preferences and for our explanation 
of the failure of verifiability to increase efficiency. Based on this observation, we argue 
that future research should search for an institutional design that is robust against 
preference heterogeneity. Such research seems especially important for markets 
for credence goods where inefficient institutions potentially cause huge economic 
costs. </p>

<p>1   The next subsection describes the main problems emerging from the asymmetric 
information in markets for credence goods and explains how verifiability helps to solve 
them in theory. The subsequent subsection summarises the experimental evidence 
showing that verifiability fails empirically and sketches our explanation for the failure. </p>

<p>0.1. Credence Goods Markets, Informational Asymmetries and the Role of Verifiability </p>

<p>Credence goods markets are characterised by informational asymmetries between 
expert sellers and customers because customers are unable to identify the quality they 
need, whereas expert sellers are able to do so (Darby and Karni, 1973). Typical 
examples include: </p>

<p>(i) health care services, where the doctor is better informed than the patient on 
the disease the latter has and on the treatment he needs; 
(ii) car repair services, where the mechanic knows more about the type of service 
the vehicle needs than the owner; and 
(iii) taxicab rides in an unknown city, where the driver is better informed about the 
shortest route to the destination than the tourist. </p>

<p>A second informational problem in markets for credence goods arises when the 
customer is unable to observe and verify the quality of service he has received. For 
example, in the market for medical treatments a patient might be unable to distinguish 
a cheap from an expensive drug infusion. In the car repair market, the owner might be 
unable to observe whether a broken part has been repaired or replaced. 
The informational asymmetries on credence goods markets may cause a variety of 
problems and inefficiencies. Expert sellers may provide unnecessarily high quality 
(a case referred to as 'overtreatment'), or insufficiently low quality ('undertreatment'), 
or they may charge for a higher quality than provided ('overcharging'). Such cases are 
not only a theoretical possibility but are well documented in the literature. Empirical 
evidence for considerable market inefficiencies is available, among others, for the 
health care sector (Hughes and Yule, 1992; Gruber and Owings, 1996; Gruber et al., </p>

<p>1 Economically important credence goods markets include the market for medical care and that for car 
repair services. For the former the data in the WHO World Health Statistics (2009) -online available at 
http://www.who.int/whosis/whostat/2009/en/ -indicate that health care expenditures account for 
approximately 15% of GDP in the US and are still rising. For the latter the online site researchandmar-
kets.com reports annual revenues of about $90 billion for the US auto repair industry, of which 70% 
originate from mechanical repair. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>394 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>1999; Iizuka, 2007), for car repairs (Wolinsky, 1993; Hubbard, 1998; Schneider, 2012)  and for taxi rides (Balafoutas et al., 2013). 
An important finding in the theoretical literature is that verifiability ensures efficiency 
on markets for credence goods. 
2 Verifiability applies if consumers are able to observe 
and verify the quality they receive, so that expert sellers cannot charge for a quality that 
has not been provided. If verifiability applies, experts are predicted to choose equal-
mark-up prices. With such prices an expert earns the same profit independently of the 
quality she provides (sellers are referred to as she and consumers as he throughout to 
make the reference clear although in practice they can both be of either sex). Thus, 
under the mentioned standard assumption on preferences, such prices induce the 
expert to provide the appropriate quality of the credence good. As a consequence, 
consumers -inferring experts' incentives from posted prices -are predicted to interact 
and the market is predicted to reach the maximal level of efficiency. </p>

<p>0.2. The Limits of Verifiability and a Potential Explanation for Its Failure </p>

<p>Experimental data in Dulleck et al. (2011) indicate that -contrary to theoretical 
prediction -verifiability fails to promote efficiency on credence goods markets. Indeed, 
the relative frequencies of market interaction, undertreatment and overtreatment do 
not differ significantly between two experimental treatments that are identical except 
that verifiability applies to one but not the other. The observed aggregate performance 
in both treatments is better in terms of efficiency than the standard prediction for a 
market without verifiability but considerably worse than the prediction for a market with 
verifiability. These findings raise two questions whose answers are important for the 
understanding of -and the optimal design of institutions for -credence goods markets: 
why is the performance of credence goods markets so poor in the presence of 
verifiability when all theoretical approaches predict verifiability to ensure efficiency? 
And why do markets without verifiability perform so much better than predicted? 
In this article, we argue that heterogeneity in the social preferences of credence 
goods sellers can provide an answer to both questions. Key to our argument are the 
following two observations: </p>

<p>(i) the standard solution to the credence goods problem for the case where the 
quality of the good is verifiable -equal-mark-up prices -is robust against the 
presence of sellers with pro-social other-regarding preferences but non-robust 
against the presence of sellers with anti-social other-regarding concerns. By 
pro-social (anti-social) other-regarding preferences we mean a willingness to 
give up own material pay-off to increase (decrease) the material pay-off of the 
trading partner; 
(ii) for the prediction for markets without verifiability the opposite is true -it is 
robust against the presence of sellers with anti-social other-regarding 
preferences but non-robust against the presence of sellers with pro-social 
other-regarding concerns. </p>

<p>2 See Emons (1997, 2001), Pesendorfer and Wolinsky (2003), Alger and Salani e (2006) and Dulleck and 
Kerschbamer (2009) for research articles on the role of verifiability and Dulleck and Kerschbamer (2006) for 
a unifying model and a survey of the literature. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>

<p>395 </p>

<p>A key ingredient in our explanation in the previous paragraph is heterogeneity in 
social preferences in the (experimental) seller population. To provide support for 
heterogeneity, we design new experiments intended to identify a seller's social 
preferences from her provision behaviour. Our main theoretical innovation is the 
construction of a simple and intuitive test that allows us to identify a seller's social 
preference type without making any specific assumptions on the form of her utility 
function. This distinguishes our approach from most of the rest of the literature on 
elicitation of type and intensity of social preferences, which uses test designs that rely 
on strong assumptions regarding the form of the utility function. </p>

<p>3;4 </p>

<p>We then implement our test for social preferences in new credence goods markets 
experiments. Our main findings are that: </p>

<p>(i) only a minority (of less than a quarter) of subjects behave according to the 
standard assumption of lexicographic maximisation of first the own and then 
the other's material pay-off; 
(ii) the behaviour of a sizeable minority of subjects is consistent with other forms 
of selfish preferences; 
(iii) the behaviour of a large majority of sellers is consistent with either a taste for 
efficiency (in the spirit of Andreoni and Miller (2002) or Charness and Rabin  (2002)) or inequality aversion (in the tradition of Fehr and Schmidt (1999) or 
Bolton and Ockenfels (2000)); and 
(iv) a minority of subjects behaves spitefully or competitive ( a la Levine (1998) or 
Charness and Rabin (2002)). </p>

<p>Hence, our empirical findings provide strong support for heterogeneity in social 
preferences and therewith for our explanation for the surprisingly low level of 
efficiency on credence goods markets in the presence of -and the surprisingly high 
efficiency level in the absence of -verifiability. 
The remainder of the article is organised as follows. Section 1 first introduces a 
simple model of a credence goods market, then presents predictions based on 
standard assumptions and finally reports the results from two experimental treatments 
in Dulleck et al. (2011). Section 2 presents our explanation for the low level of 
efficiency in credence goods markets in the presence and the high level of efficiency in 
the absence of verifiability in the data of Dulleck et al. (2011). Section 3 develops the 
test for identifying social preferences in a credence goods experiment and Section 4 
presents the results from an implementation of the test. Section 5 concludes with a 
discussion of our results and their implications for institutional design and for agent 
selection. </p>

<p>3 Typical assumptions made in the economic literature on social preferences are linearity (the ring-test -
employed by Offerman et al. (1996) and Brandts et al. (2009), among others -is based on the assumption of 
linear preferences), piecewise linearity (the tests implemented by Cabrales et al. (2010), Blanco et al. (2011) 
and Iriberri and Rey-Biel (2013) are based on a piecewise linear model of social preferences), or specific 
forms of convexity (Andreoni and Miller (2002) and Fisman et al. (2007) check consistency of behaviour with 
the maximisation of a CES utility function). 
4 An exception is Kerschbamer (2015) who develops a test for social preferences that shares many features 
with the one proposed here. We discuss the relationship further in Section 2. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>396 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>1. Verifiability in Credence Goods Markets: Model, Standard Predictions and 
Experimental Evidence </p>

<p>1.1. Basic Model </p>

<p>Consumers are ex ante identical. They need a high quality, q 
1 , of a particular 
(credence) good with probability h, and a low quality, q 
0 , with probability 1 À h. Each 
consumer (he) is randomly matched with one seller (she) who sets prices p 
1 and p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>for the high, respectively low, quality (with p 
1 ! p 
0 ). The seller has costs c 
1 (c 
0 , 
respectively) for the high (low) quality, with c 
1 [ c 
0 . 
The consumer only knows the prices for the different qualities but not the quality he 
needs when he makes his decision whether or not to interact with the seller. In case of 
interaction, the seller gets to know which quality the customer needs. Then, she 
provides one of the two qualities and charges one of the two prices. 
Customers in need of the low quality are sufficiently treated in either case, both if 
the seller chooses q 
0 and if she chooses q 
1 . However, if the customer needs the high 
quality, then only q 
1 is sufficient. A sufficient quality yields a value v &gt; 0 for the 
customer, an insufficient quality yields a value of zero. If the customer 
decides against interaction then both, the customer and the seller, receive an 
outside option of o ≥ 0. In case of an interaction, the monetary pay-off for the 
consumer is the value from the quality received minus the price to be paid. The 
seller receives the monetary pay-off of the price charged minus the costs of the 
quality provided. More formally, let h 2 {0,1} be the index of a customer's need in 
terms of quality, l 2 {0,1} the index of the quality provided and j 2 {0,1} the 
index of the quality charged for. Then the material pay-off of the seller under price-
vector ðp 
0 ; p 
1 Þ is </p>

<p>p s ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; l; jÞ ¼ p 
j À c 
l ; 
(1) </p>

<p>while the customer receives </p>

<p>p c ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; h; l; jÞ ¼ v À p 
j ; if h l, and À p 
j otherwise. 
(2) </p>

<p>Figure 1 presents this game. Note that this simple game captures all the idiosyncratic 
problems of credence goods markets discussed in the introduction. If a customer 
needs q 
1 and the seller provides q 
0 , we have undertreatment; if the customer needs q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>and the seller provides q 
1 ; we have overtreatment; and if the seller charges p 
1 when q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>is provided, we have overcharging. </p>

<p>1.2. Experimental Design </p>

<p>In the following, we introduce the experimental parameterisation of the basic model 
used in Dulleck et al. (2011) which are also used in our new experiments below. 
5 We 
refer to two treatments in Dulleck et al. (2011), one without verifiability (treatment </p>

<p>5 Dulleck et al. (2013) address in a similar framework the question whether a seller's price-posting 
behaviour is indicative of her intentions regarding provision and charging behaviour. Huck et al. (2007, 2010,  2012) have interesting experiments on the effect of prices and opportunities to build up a reputation on the 
performance of markets for experience (rather than credence) goods. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>N-Endo) and one with verifiability (treatment V-Endo). 
6 Treatment N-Endo corre-
sponds to the game shown in Figure 1. Implementing verifiability means that 
consumers are able to observe and verify ex post the quality of the provided good 
(without knowing, however, whether this quality is the appropriate one). Therefore, in 
treatment V-Endo the last stage in Figure 1 is degenerate because the expert has to 
charge the price for the provided quality. Hence, with verifiability overcharging is 
precluded, while over-and undertreatment are still possible. 
In both treatments the customer's probability of needing the high quality is h = 0.5, 
and the value of a sufficient quality is v = 10. The costs of providing the low (high) 
quality are c 
0 ¼ 2 (c 
1 ¼ 6). The prices posted by the sellers, p 
0 and p 
1 (with p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>p 
1 ), 
have to be chosen in integer numbers from the interval {1, . . . , 11}. The outside 
option if no trade takes place between the seller and the customer is set to o = 1.6. 
Matching groups of eight subjects each were implemented, with four subjects as 
customers and four subjects as sellers. Role assignment was random at the 
beginning and fixed for all 16 periods in the experiment. In order to prevent 
attempts to build up a reputation as a reliable seller, there was random rematching </p>

<p>in 
out </p>

<p>h 
1-h </p>

<p>q 1 
q 0 
q 0 
q 1 </p>

<p>p 1 
p 0 
p 1 </p>

<p>Undertreatment 
Overtreatment </p>

<p>Overcharging 
Overcharging </p>

<p>p 0 </p>

<p>p 1 , p 0 </p>

<p>p 1 
p 0 
p 1 
p 0 </p>

<p>seller provides </p>

<p>seller charges </p>

<p>seller posts prices </p>

<p>consumer enters or not </p>

<p>nature det. severity of prob </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The Credence Goods Game 
Notes. The term undertreatment refers to providing q 
0 when the consumer needs q 
1 ; 
overtreatment refers to providing q 
1 when the consumer needs q 
0 ; and overcharging refers to 
charging p 
1 when q 
0 has been provided. </p>

<p>6 Dulleck et al. (2011) have a total of 16 experimental treatments (on the role of liability, verifiability, 
competition and reputation) of which we discuss only two here (and add two new ones). The main difference 
in experimental design between the new treatments and those in Dulleck et al. (2011) is our reliance on 
(carefully designed) exogenously given prices for different qualities of the good rather than letting sellers 
endogenously decide on prices. To emphasise this difference, we refer to the treatments B/N and B/V in 
Dulleck et al. (2011) as treatments N-Endo and V-Endo here, while the new treatments have names ending 
in -Exo. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>398 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>of customers and sellers within each matching group after each period. All 
experimental sessions were run computerised using <rs id="software-2" type="software">zTree</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Fischbacher</rs>, 2007) and 
recruiting was done via <rs id="software-3" type="software">ORSEE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Greiner</rs>, 2004). A total of 184 subjects participated 
in treatments N-Endo and V-Endo. </p>

<p>1.3. Standard Prediction for the Role of Verifiability </p>

<p>PREDICTION 1. (Standard Prediction for the Role of Verifiability). Under the assumption that 
subjects have standard preferences, in treatment N-Endo no interaction will take place, yielding no 
efficiency gains in the market. By contrast, in treatment V-Endo the expert will post p 
0 ¼ 6 and 
p 
1 ¼ 10 and the consumer will choose to enter the market and he will get the appropriate quality, 
yielding full efficiency in the market. </p>

<p>The following considerations lead to this prediction. Consider treatment N-Endo 
first. Under the standard assumption of common knowledge that all agents are 
rational, risk-neutral and exclusively interested in their own material pay-off, the expert 
will always charge the higher price p 
1 and always provide the cheaper quality q 
0 . 
Anticipating this, a consumer will then only accept if p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>ð1 À hÞv À o ¼ 3:4. But 
with such a p 
1 the seller earns less than the value of her outside option (because 
ð1 À hÞv À c 
0 \ 2o). Thus, no interaction is predicted for N-Endo. In treatment 
V-Endo, the expert cannot charge for a quality other than the provided one and the 
quality provided depends on the mark-up p 
l À c 
l ; l 2 {0,1}. An equal-mark-up price-
vector is defined as one that satisfies p 
1 À c 
1 ¼ p 
0 À c 
0 . Under the standard 
assumption on preferences (that if indifferent in own-money terms the expert will 
provide in the best interest of the customer) an equal-mark-up price-vector is predicted 
to induce provision of appropriate quality. An undertreatment (overtreatment) price-
vector satisfies p 
1 À c 
1 \ p 
0 À c 
0 (p 
1 À c 
1 [ p 
0 À c 
0 ) and is predicted to induce 
provision of low (high) quality independently of the customer's need. 
Figure 2 shows in the space of price-vectors the set of equal-mark-up price-vectors as 
a straight line with slope 1. The set of undertreatment price-vectors is indicated as the 
dark area below the equal-mark-up line and the set of overtreatment vectors is shown as 
the light area above the equal-mark-up line. Anticipating how an expert's provision 
behaviour depends on the price-vector under which the transaction takes place, a 
consumer will accept an equal-mark-up vector iff p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10, an undertreatment vector iff 
p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3, and an overtreatment vector iff p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>8. Thus, to maximise profits, the expert 
will post the equal-mark-up vector ðp 
0 ; p 
1 Þ ¼ ð6; 10Þ; which will be accepted by an own-
money-maximising, risk-neutral consumer. </p>

<p>1.4. Experimental Results of Dulleck et al. (2011)   OBSERVATION 1. (Experimental Results for the Role of Verifiability). Compared to treatment 
N-Endo, verifiability has no significant impact on the frequency of interaction, the undertreatment 
rate, the overtreatment rate and overall efficiency. The overall performance in both treatments is 
better than the standard prediction for treatment N-Endo but worse than the standard prediction 
for treatment V-Endo. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>Table 1, as well as Figures 3 and 4 support this observation, leading us to reject both 
parts of Prediction 1: contrary to the prediction efficiency gains and interaction rates 
are not significantly different between the two treatments and they are significantly 
higher than 0 and significantly lower than 1 in both. </p>

<p>p 1 </p>

<p>c 1 -c 0 </p>

<p>Always high quality </p>

<p>Always low quality </p>

<p>p 0 </p>

<p>p 1 = p 0 + (c 1 -c 0 ) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Standard Prediction for Provision Behaviour under Verifiability 
Notes. Under the standard assumption on preferences an expert's provision behaviour under 
verifiability is determined exclusively by her material incentives: if c 
1 À c 
0 [ p 
1 À p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(c 
1 À c 
0 \ p 
1 À p 
0 ) the expert earns more by selling q 
0 (q 
1 ) and is therefore predicted to 
always provide the low quality (high quality); if c 
1 À c 
0 ¼ p 
1 À p 
0 the expert is indifferent in 
material terms and in this case standard theory predicts that she will provide the appropriate 
quality. </p>

<p>Table 1 
Summary Statistics for N-Endo and V-Endo </p>

<p>Averages per period 
N-Endo* 
V-Endo* </p>

<p>Interaction 
0.45 
0.50 
Undertreatment </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>0.53 
0.60 
Overtreatment </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>0.06 
0.05 
Overcharging </p>

<p> § </p>

<p>0.88 
-
Profit seller 
2.69 
2.58 
Profit customer 
1.00 
1.06 
Number of subjects 
96 
88 
(independent matching groups) 
(12) 
(11) </p>

<p>Notes. *None of the variables is significantly different between the two treatments (using two-sided Mann-
Whitney U-tests with matching groups of eight subjects as independent observations). </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>Customer needs q 
1 , 
but seller provides q 
0 . </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>Customer needs q 
0 but seller provides q 
1 . 
 § Seller provides q 
0 but charges p 
1 (with 
p 
1 [ p 
0 and customer needs q 
0 ). </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>A possible explanation for the relatively high interaction rate and the relatively low 
undertreatment rate in N-Endo is experts having a taste for efficiency. Another possible 
explanation is that experts care for equitable pay-offs. Support for the latter hypothesis 
comes from the analysis of price-posting behaviour. Contrary to the theoretical 
prediction, equal-mark-up prices are very rare in V-Endo. They are chosen in less than 
5% of all transactions. Table 2 reports the frequencies of the five most popular price-
vectors posted by sellers in the two treatments. It is interesting to note that in treatment 
V-Endo only one equal-mark-up vector is among the top five price-vectors but it is not the </p>

<p>Interaction </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 
Period </p>

<p>V-Endo </p>

<p>N-Endo </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Relative Frequency of Interaction in N-Endo and V-Endo 
Notes. The Relative Frequency of Interaction is calculated as (no. accepted transactions)/ 
(no. possible interactions) averaged over all sessions for a given treatment. </p>

<p>Undertreatment </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>V-Endo </p>

<p>N-Endo </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 
Period </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Relative Frequency of Undertreatment in N-Endo and V-Endo 
Notes. The Relative Frequency of Undertreatment is calculated as (no. cases where the customer 
needs q 
1 but receives q 
0 )/(no. cases where the customer needs q 
1 ) averaged over all sessions for 
a given treatment. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>predicted one. In both treatments, the price-vector (6, 8) is by far the most frequently 
posted price-vector. If the seller always provided the appropriate quality and charged for 
it, then this price-vector would split the gains from trade equally between the consumer 
and the seller both when the consumer needs the low and when he needs the high 
quality. The prominence of this price-vector therefore suggests that a concern for relative 
pay-offs plays a role for aggregate behaviour in the experiment. 
Of course, these observations provide only a rough indication that social preferences 
may shape sellers' behaviour. In Section 3, we develop a simple parsimonious test for 
social preferences within the framework of a credence goods market which is then 
implemented in new experiments in Section 4. Before doing so we argue (in Section 2) 
that heterogeneity in social preferences can explain why markets with verifiability 
perform worse than in the standard prediction and why markets without verifiability 
perform better. </p>

<p>2. Heterogeneity in Social Preferences and Robustness of Institutions </p>

<p>In this Section, we explain in more detail how heterogeneity in social preferences of 
sellers can explain the relatively bad performance of credence goods markets with 
verifiability and the relatively good performance of markets without verifiability. Our 
discussion here and in the next Section relies on the assumption that (experimental) 
credence goods sellers are heterogeneous and that the preferences of each seller can 
be represented by a utility or motivation function U ðp s ; p c Þ satisfying the following 
three conditions: </p>

<p>(i) @U =@p s [ 0; 
(ii) signð@U =@p c Þ depends (only) on whether p s ! p c ; or p s \p c ; and 
(iii) @U =@p s [ @U =@p c : </p>

<p>The first condition requires that -holding the monetary pay-off of the customer 
constant -the seller's utility increases in her own monetary pay-off. This assumption is 
satisfied by all empirically relevant social preference types discussed in the economics 
literature. 
The second assumption states that whether a seller is selfish, pro-social or anti-social 
depends only on whether the customer has more or less monetary pay-off than the 
seller. On the one hand, this assumption is generous because it allows for all </p>

<p>Table 2 
Most Popular Price-vectors in N-Endo and V-Endo </p>

<p>Treatment N-Endo 
Treatment V-Endo </p>

<p>ðp 
0 ; p 
1 Þ 
Absolute no. 
Relative frequency (%) 
ðp 
0 ; p 
1 Þ 
Absolute no. 
Relative frequency (%) </p>

<p>(6,8) 
176 
22.92 
(6,8) 
265 
37.64 
(4,8) 
84 
10.94 
(7,8) 
89 
12.64 
(5,7) 
50 
6.51 
(5,8) 
46 
6.53 
(5,8) 
44 
5.73 
(4,8) 
17 
2.41 
(4,7) 
39 
5.08 
(8,8) 
15 
2.13 
393 (of 768) 
51.17 
432 (of 704) 
61.36 </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>402 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>empirically relevant types of social preferences that have been discussed in the 
economics literature. On the other hand, this assumption is strong because it implies </p>

<p>(i) that the seller's general attitude towards the customer only depends on the 
pay-off allocation implied by a decision; and 
(ii) that the reference point for the evaluation of pay-off allocations is an outcome 
with equal pay-offs for both sides of the market. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The third assumption states that a seller values changes in own material pay-off more 
than equivalent or smaller changes in the customer's pay-off. This assumption is fairly 
innocent for allocations with p s \ p c but might be regarded as somewhat restrictive for 
allocations with p s [ p c ; its main purpose is to get a unique 'switching point' in the test 
proposed below, though, and it can be relaxed without changing results qualitatively. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Given our three assumptions on the utility or motivational function U ðp s ; p c Þ, it 
seems natural to distinguish between the five archetypes of social preferences defined 
in Table 3. 
9 What can we say about the market behaviour of credence goods sellers 
exhibiting those types of social concerns? 
Consider markets without verifiability (N-markets) first. For such markets the 
standard prediction -undertreatment and overcharging under each price-vector -is 
already a worst case scenario that leaves no room for deterioration. This follows from 
the observation that by behaving according to the standard prediction a seller not only 
maximises her material pay-off but also minimises the pay-off of the customer. An 
immediate consequence is that anti-social other-regarding preferences do not manifest 
themselves in a worse outcome than predicted under standard preferences. On the 
other hand, pro-social other-regarding preferences easily manifest themselves in a 
better market outcome than predicted. To see this, consider an EL expert who finds </p>

<p>Table 3 
Social Preference Types and Implied Provision Behaviour </p>

<p>Social preference type </p>

<p>Derivative of U w.r.t. p c 
Provision behaviour under Ω </p>

<p>For p s ! p c 
For p s \ p c 
Cust. needs q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Cust. needs q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>SE (selfish) 
=0 
=0 
q 
0 or q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>q 
0 or q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>EL (efficiency loving) 
&gt;0 
&gt;0 
q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>SP (spiteful) 
&lt;0 
&lt;0 
q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>IA (inequality averse) 
&gt;0 
&lt;0 
q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>IL (inequality loving) 
&lt;0 
&gt;0 
q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>q </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>7 See Kerschbamer (2015) for a more detailed discussion of this assumption. 
8 The test proposed by Kerschbamer (2015) relies on the somewhat weaker assumption dU(z,z)/dz &gt; 0 for 
all z &gt; 0. This assumption only rules out more extreme variants of spite while the condition in the text 
excludes both extreme variants of altruism and extreme variants of spite. 
9 In online Appendix A, we discuss those archetypes and their relation to different variants of social 
preferences discussed in the literature in some detail. There we also present a Figure that displays typical 
indifference curves for the five archetypes in ðp s ; p c Þ space. By focusing on the five 'pure' types defined in 
Table 3 we omit preference types that are selfish in one of the two domains and pro-or anti-social in the 
other. In the experimental section (Section 5), we allow for such hybrid types. In online Appendix A, we 
explain how this is done. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>out that the customer needs q 
1 . By providing q 
0 instead of q 
1 she increases her material 
pay-off by c 
1 À c 
0 at a cost of v [ c 
1 À c 
0 to the customer. Thus, if the additional 
profit the seller receives from providing q 
0 instead of q 
1 (i.e. c 
1 À c 
0 ) is small 
compared to the loss arising from undertreatment (i.e. v) and if the weight on p c in her 
utility function is sufficiently high relative to the weight on p s , she will refrain from 
undertreatment. The same is true for IA experts in the domain of advantageous 
inequality and for IL experts in the domain of disadvantageous inequality. 
In sum, in N-markets experts with anti-social other-regarding preferences behave 
exactly like experts with standard preferences while experts with pro-social other-
regarding preferences tend to behave better than predicted by standard theory. 
For the standard solution for markets with verifiability (V-markets), by contrast, we 
get the opposite result. To see this, note that the standard prediction for equal-mark-
up prices -appropriate quality independent of the level of the mark-up -is already a 
best-case scenario that leaves no room for improvement. Consider an EL expert, for 
instance. Since the material pay-off of the customer enters positively in her utility 
function, she will act in the interest of the consumer along the equal-mark-up line, 
where helping the customer involves no cost. Furthermore, since @U =@p c [ 0 in both 
domains (i.e. in the domain of advantageous inequality and in the domain of 
disadvantageous inequality) the EL expert will provide the appropriate quality even 
under price-vectors that deviate (slightly) from the equal-mark-up rule. Thus, EL 
experts necessarily provide appropriate quality in a corridor along the equal-mark-up 
line -as shown in Figure 5 -but they do not perform better than SE experts at the 
equal-mark-up line. 
10 The same is true for other experts with pro-social other-
regarding preferences -under equal-mark-up prices they behave as predicted but do 
not behave better than predicted. However, anti-social other-regarding preferences 
easily manifest themselves in a worse market outcome than predicted under standard 
preferences because hurting the customer involves no cost under equal-mark-up 
prices. Consider a SP expert, for instance. Since the material pay-off of the customer 
enters negatively in her utility function, she necessarily provides q 
1 to a consumer who 
needs q 
0 ; and q 
0 to a consumer who needs q 
1 , along the equal-mark-up line where 
hurting the customer involves no cost. Furthermore, since @U =@p c \ 0 in both 
domains the SP expert will always provide the wrong quality even under price-vectors 
that deviate (slightly) from the equal-mark-up rule. The same is true for other experts 
with negative attitudes towards customers -most importantly for IA experts in the 
domain of disadvantageous inequality. 
Together these observations not only explain the poor performance of equal-mark-
up prices in V-Endo, they also explain why equal-mark-up prices are very rarely chosen 
in this treatment. More importantly, there is no cheap repair for this problem in the 
sense that there is simply no price-vector that induces a SP expert, for instance, to 
provide the appropriate quality in a V-market. Her provision behaviour is rather 
(qualitatively) like the one shown in Figure 5 with the important difference that she 
will necessarily always provide the wrong (instead of the appropriate) quality in a 
corridor along the equal-mark-up line. </p>

<p>10 Point Ω and the other price-vectors indicated by bullet points in Figure 5 are not important for the 
arguments in this section -we will refer to them in the next section. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>3. Identification of Social Preferences in Markets for Credence Goods </p>

<p>The discussion in the previous section assumes that there is heterogeneity in social 
preferences in the (experimental) expert population. The challenge is, of course, to 
show that empirically. Based on the three primitive assumptions on preferences 
introduced in the previous section we now derive a parsimonious test for the 
identification of social preferences in the framework of a credence goods market with 
verifiability. Our starting point in deriving the test is the following observation: in the 
space of possible price-vectors there is exactly one (and only one) that allows for a neat 
discrimination between the above defined preference types from the provision 
behaviour in a credence goods market. Looking at Figure 5 it is the price-vector 
referred to as 'Point Ω'. It is defined as follows: </p>

<p>DEFINITION 1. The price-vector X ¼ ðp </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X ; p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>X Þ has p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X ¼ ðv þ c 
1 Þ=2 À ðc 
1 À c 
0 Þ and 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>X ¼ ðv þ c 
1 Þ=2. </p>

<p>To discuss the properties of this price-vector, we have first to define and discuss the 
location of the three dashed lines in Figure 5: </p>

<p>The upward sloping dashed line is the equal-mark-up line. It connects all price-
vectors with p 
1 À p 
0 ¼ c 
1 À c 
0 , implying that the expert receives exactly the 
same material pay-off independently of whether she provides q 
0 or q 
1 at points 
on this line. </p>

<p>always high 
quality </p>

<p>always 
appro-
priate 
quality </p>

<p>always low 
quality </p>

<p>Point </p>

<p>p 1 = p 0 +(c 1 -c 0 ) </p>

<p>p 0 = (v+c 0 )/2 </p>

<p>c 1 -c 0 </p>

<p>p 1 = (v+c 1 )/2 </p>

<p>p 1 </p>

<p>p 0 </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Provision Behaviour of an EL Expert Under Verifiability 
Notes. An EL expert is willing to give up own material pay-off to increase the material pay-off of 
the customer. Thus, she will necessarily provide the appropriate quality in a corridor along the 
equal-mark-up line (where helping the customer involves no cost). </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>The horizontal dashed line connects all price-vectors where the expert and the 
customer receive exactly the same material pay-off if the expert (correctly or 
incorrectly) provides q 
1 . Thus, this line is defined by p s ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; l ¼ 1; 
j ¼ 1Þ ¼ p c ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; h ¼ 1; l ¼ 1; j ¼ 1Þ ¼ p c ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; h ¼ 0; l ¼ 1; j ¼ 1Þ 
() p 
1 ¼ ðv þ c 
1 Þ=2: </p>

<p>The vertical dashed line connects all price-vectors where the expert and the 
customer receive exactly the same material pay-off if the expert correctly 
provides q 
0 . Thus, this line is defined by p s ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; l ¼ 0; j ¼ 0Þ ¼ 
p c ðp 
0 ; p 
1 ; h ¼ 0; l ¼ 0; j ¼ 0Þ () p 
0 ¼ ðv þ c 
0 Þ=2: </p>

<p>Since Point Ω is at the intersection of the upward sloping and the horizontal dashed 
line it has p 
0 ¼ ðv þ c 
0 Þ=2 À ðc 
1 À c 
0 Þ=2; implying that this point is necessarily to the 
left of the vertical dashed line -where we have p 
0 ¼ ðv þ c 
0 Þ=2. 
Now, suppose we (as the experimentalists) impose the price-vector in Point Ω and 
look at an expert's provision behaviour. First, assume the customer needs the cheaper 
quality, q 
0 . If the expert provides the appropriate quality, she induces a pay-off 
allocation ðp s ; p c Þ with disadvantageous inequality. This is so because Point Ω is strictly 
to the left of the vertical dashed line along which both parties get exactly the same 
material pay-off if the expert correctly provides q 
0 . If the expert provides the expensive 
quality instead, she induces an equal-material-pay-offs allocation -that is, an allocation 
with p s ¼ p c . This follows from the fact that Point Ω is on the horizontal dashed line. 
Furthermore, since Point Ω is on the equal-mark-up line, the expert's own material 
pay-off is the same in both allocations. 
What does this imply for provision behaviour? An EL expert and an IL expert will 
necessarily decide for the asymmetric allocation -by providing q 
0 to a customer who 
needs q 
0 . By contrast, an SP and an IL expert necessarily decide for the symmetric 
allocation -by providing q 
1 to a customer who needs q 
0 . This is so because the own 
material pay-off is the same in both allocations, while the customer's pay-off is higher in 
the asymmetric than in the symmetric allocation (relevant for EL and SP) respectively 
because disadvantageous inequality is present in the asymmetric but absent in the 
symmetric allocation (relevant for IA and IL). 
Now assume that the customer needs the expensive quality, q 
1 . If the expert provides 
q 
1 , then she induces the equal-material-pay-offs allocation discussed in the previous 
paragraph. This follows from the fact that the material pay-off of both parties is 
independent of the quality needed by the customer when the expensive quality is 
provided. If the expert provides q 
0 instead, she induces a pay-off allocation ðp s ; p c Þ with 
advantageous inequality. This follows from the fact that Point Ω has 
p 
0 ¼ ðv þ c 
0 Þ=2 À ðc 
1 À c 
0 Þ=2 which exceeds c 
0 =2 because v [ ðc 
1 À c 
0 Þ. Further-
more, since Point Ω is on the equal-mark-up line, the expert's own material pay-off is 
the same in both allocations. 
From these considerations it follows that an EL expert and an IA expert will 
necessarily decide for the symmetric allocation -by providing q 
1 to a customer who 
needs q 
1 -while a SP and an IL expert necessarily decide for the asymmetric allocation 
-by providing q 
0 to a customer who needs q 
1 . This is so because the own material 
pay-off is the same in both allocations while the customer's pay-off is higher in the 
symmetric than in the asymmetric allocation (relevant for EL and SP) respectively </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>because advantageous inequality is present in the asymmetric but absent in the 
symmetric allocation (relevant for IA and IL). 
In sum, if we observe the decision of an expert under the price-vector located at 
Point Ω in Figure 5 twice, once combined with the consumer needing the low quality 
and once combined with the consumer needing the high quality, then we can infer her 
social preference type with some precision -see Table 3. To formulate a more precise 
statement, we call the strategy of providing the appropriate quality in both cases 'always 
appropriate quality' and the strategy of providing the expensive quality in both cases 
'always high quality'; moreover, we denote the strategy of providing the cheap quality 
in both cases 'always low quality' and the strategy of providing the expensive quality 
when the cheap quality is needed and the cheap quality when the expensive one is 
needed 'always wrong quality'. Using those terms, we can state the following 
Proposition: </p>

<p>PROPOSITION 1. (Impartial Social Preferences). Consider the price-vector Ω as defined in 
Definition 1. Under this price-vector: </p>

<p>(a) 'always appropriate quality' is consistent with SE and EL preferences but inconsistent 
with IA, SP and IL; 
(b) 'always high quality' is consistent with SE and IA preferences but inconsistent with EL, 
SP and IL; 
(c) 'always low quality' is consistent with SE and SP preferences but inconsistent with IA, 
SP and EL; 
(d) 'always wrong quality' is consistent with SE and SP preferences but inconsistent with IA, 
EL and IL. </p>

<p>Proof. Follows immediately from the text preceding the result. </p>

<p>Testing the provision behaviour under the price-vector Ω is like eliciting impartial 
social preferences, because under this price-vector a seller compares two allocations 
that yield the same material pay-off for her but different pay-offs for the customer. 
Thus, deciding for the 'fair' allocation (whatever is considered fair) does not 
involve any costs here. Based on the predictions for Point Ω we now change p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>slightly, while keeping p 
1 constant, in order to test whether (experimental) sellers 
are willing to give up their own material pay-off to help or hurt the customer. From 
Figure 5, an increase (decrease) in p 
0 corresponds to a move along the horizontal 
dashed line to the right (left) of Point Ω implying that we increase (decrease) the 
expert's pay-off from providing q 
0 at the cost (for the benefit) of the consumer's 
pay-off. At the same time, the pay-offs for both parties from providing q 
1 remain 
constant at the equal-material-pay-offs allocation ðp s ; p c Þ ¼ ½ðv À c 
1 Þ=2; ðv À c 
1 Þ=2: 
Given our three assumptions on the utility function, what are the implications of 
changing p 
0 for the provision behaviour of sellers with different types of social 
preferences? First, we get the following monotonicity result: </p>

<p>LEMMA 1. (Monotonicity). Consider two price-vectors, the price-vector Ω from Definition 1 and 
a second vector, Ψ, which has the same p 
1 as Ω (i.e. p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>W ¼ p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>X ) but a different p 
0 (i.e. p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X 6 ¼ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>W ). </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>If p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X \ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>W (p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X [ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>W respectively) then -keeping the consumer's need with respect to quality 
constant -an expert who provides q 
0 (q 
1 ) under Ω must provide q 
0 (q 
1 )under Ψ. </p>

<p>Proof. See online Appendix B. </p>

<p>Proposition 1 and Lemma 1 together imply: </p>

<p>PROPOSITION 2. (Partial Social Preferences). Consider the price-vectors Ω and Ψ from 
Lemma 1. Then observing </p>

<p>(a) 'always appropriate quality' under Ω and Ψ is only consistent with EL preferences (but 
inconsistent with SE, IA, SP and IL); 
(b) 'always high quality' under Ω and 'always high quality', 'always appropriate quality' or 
'always wrong quality' under Ψ with p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X \ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>W is only consistent with IA preferences (but 
inconsistent with SE, EL, SP and IL); 
(c) 'always low quality' under Ω and 'always low quality', 'always appropriate quality' or 
'always wrong quality' under Ψ with p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>X [ p </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>W is only consistent with IL preferences 
(but inconsistent with SE, IA, SP and EL); 
(d) 'always wrong quality' under Ω and 'always wrong quality' under Ψ is only consistent 
with SP preferences (but inconsistent with SE, IA, EL and IL). </p>

<p>To understand Proposition 2, the test to be applied in the next Section, and the term 
'partial social preferences', consider an IA seller, for instance. From the arguments 
above, we know that such an expert will always provide the high quality under price-
vector Ω. Increasing p 
0 slightly, while keeping p 
1 constant, creates a tension between a 
higher own monetary pay-off and more inequality. By deciding for 'always high quality' 
or switching to 'always appropriate quality' (or 'always wrong quality') the seller reveals 
a positive willingness to pay for reducing inequality, because own-money-maximisation 
would ask for 'always low quality'. The argument for sellers with other kinds of social 
preferences is similar. </p>

<p>4. Implementing the Test in Lab Experiments </p>

<p>4.1. Experimental Parameters and Procedures </p>

<p>To test for and classify the social preferences of sellers, we ran new experiments using a 
design based on the theoretical results derived in the previous Section. The timing of the 
game was exactly the same as in the game described in Section 1, except for the first 
stage: instead of letting sellers post their prices themselves, the price-vector in a given 
period was chosen exogenously -through the software -with equal probability from the 
set {(3,8), (4,8), (5,8), (6,8), (7,8)}. This set of vectors has two characteristics: 
First and foremost, it includes the equal-mark-up vector Ω characterised in 
Proposition 1 -it is the vector (4,8). Starting from this price-vector it then varies 
p 
0 as described in Lemma 1 and Proposition 2. The allocations implied by the equal-
mark-up vector Ω and by the other price-vectors in the set are displayed in Figure 6. 
Second, this set of price-vectors includes the four most frequently chosen price-
vectors in treatment V-Endo (see Table 2). We call the experimental treatment with </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>408 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>SE 
7 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-7 </p>

<p>IA </p>

<p>(3,8) </p>

<p>(4,8) </p>

<p>(5,8) </p>

<p>(6,8) </p>

<p>(7,8) </p>

<p>EL </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>π 3 </p>

<p>π c </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Possible Combinations of Buyer's and Seller's Material Pay-offs (for different price-vectors and 
depending on whether the buyer needs q 
0 or q 
1 ) 
Notes. Providing q 
1 induces the equal-material-pay-offs outcome ðp s ; p c Þ ¼ ð2; 2Þ independently of 
the needed quality under each of the considered price-vectors. If the customer needs q 
0 , the seller 
implicitly chooses between this allocation (by inefficiently providing q 
1 ) and the allocation 
corresponding to the respective price-vector on the line (with slope À1) above the equal-material-
pay-offs allocation (by efficiently providing q 
0 ). If the customer needs q 
1 the choice is between the 
equal-material-pay-offs point (by efficiently providing q 
1 ) and the respective point on the line 
(with slope À1) below the equal-material-pay-offs allocation (by inefficiently providing q 
0 ). </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>this (exogenously given) set of price-vectors V-Exo1. In order to check whether the 
inclusion of the price-vector (3,8) -which was not among the most frequently posted 
price-vectors in treatment V-Endo -has any impact on behaviour, we also ran an 
experimental treatment where the exogenously determined price-vector was chosen 
with equal probability only from the four most frequently chosen price-vectors (4,8), 
(5,8), (6,8) and (7,8). We call this treatment V-Exo2. 
We ran four sessions with 16 subjects each both for V-Exo1 and for V-Exo2, yielding 
eight independent matching groups per treatment. Overall, a total of 128 subjects 
participated in the new experiments (with no subject having participated in the 
experiment reported in Section 1). Sessions lasted less than 1.5 hours. </p>

<p>4.2. Experimental Results </p>

<p>Tables 4 and 5 present the data for the two new treatments with exogenously imposed 
price-vectors, that is, for V-Exo1 and for V-Exo2. From Table 4, it is clear that -except 
for overtreatment -there are no significant differences between those treatments 
(using the overall average for a particular variable within a matching group of eight 
subjects as the independent observation, yielding eight independent observations per 
treatment). For overtreatment, the Table indicates significantly higher rates in V-Exo1 </p>

<p>Table 4 
Overview of Results in V-Exo1 and V-Exo2 (periods 7-16) </p>

<p>V-Exo1 
V-Exo2 
p-value </p>

<p>Interaction 
0.54 
0.58 
0.40 
Undertreatment 
0.53 
0.46 
0.71 
Overtreatment 
0.35 
0.22 
0.05* 
Profit seller 
2.27 
2.35 
0.40 
Profit buyer 
1.29 
1.29 
0.60 
Number of subjects 
64 
64 
(independent matching groups) 
(8) 
(8) </p>

<p>Notes. *However, we do not find a significant difference in overtreatment between V-Exo1 and V-Exo2 if we 
control for the price-vector (see Table 5): the provision behaviour under the price-vector (3,8) -which is 
present in V-Exo1 but absent in V-Exo2 -seems to be responsible for the difference in overtreatment 
between V-Exo1 and V-Exo2. </p>

<p>Table 5 
Undertreatment (UT) and Overtreatment (OT) Rates Conditional on Price-vectors (periods 7-16) </p>

<p>p I ; p II </p>

<p>UT </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>UT </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>p-value 
OT </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>OT </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>p-value 
V-Exo1 
V-Exo2 
(UT) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>V-Exo1 
V-Exo2 
(OT) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>(3,8) 
0.048 
n.a. 
-
0.913 
n.a. 
-
(4,8) 
0.100 
0.243 
0.07 
0.333 
0.529 
0.17 
(5,8) 
0.737 
0.778 
1.00 
0.000 
0.100 
0.24 
(6,8) 
0.882 
0.765 
0.23 
0.077 
0.000 
0.28 
(7,8) 
0.818 
0.636 
0.41 
0.000 
0.000 
n.a. </p>

<p>Notes. *Undertreatment: customer needs q 
1 , but seller provides q 
0 . 
 † Overtreatment: customer needs q 
0 , but 
seller provides q 
1 . </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>410 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>than in V-Exo2. A closer look at the data reveals that the difference is entirely due to 
the provision behaviour under the price-vector (3,8), which is present in V-Exo1 but 
absent in V-Exo2. In fact, Table 5 shows that -controlling for price-vectors -there is no 
significant difference between V-Exo1 and V-Exo2, both with respect to overtreatment 
and undertreatment. This also implies that, conditional on the price-vector and the 
quality needed by the consumer, there is no difference in the likelihood of appropriate 
treatment across treatments. 
11 These results allow us to pool the data from the two 
treatments in the following analysis of social preference types. 
In order to classify sellers according to their social preferences, we first look at 
violations of monotonicity according to Lemma 1. It turns out that 45 out of 64 sellers 
(70%) behave in line with the statement over all 16 periods of the experiment. Taking 
into account that some learning may go on in early periods, we decided to focus on the 
final 12 periods only (i.e. on periods 5-16). In those periods the behaviour of 56 out of 
64 sellers (88%) respects the monotonicity condition. This high degree of consistent 
behaviour is encouraging, because it suggests that stable (non-standard) preferences, 
rather than noise or any kind of confusion of subjects, drives our findings. Of the 56 
sellers whose behaviour is consistent with Lemma 1, we had to exclude three from 
further analysis due to lack of data caused by customers' opting out. 
12 Our data analysis 
is therefore based on 53 sellers. </p>

<p>OBSERVATION 2. (Identification of Social Preferences). </p>

<p>(a) Less than a quarter of the experimental sellers act in accordance with the standard 
assumption on preferences -they provide appropriate quality if and only if they are held 
indifferent in own-money terms; 
(b) About a quarter of the seller population displays behaviour that is consistent with a 
strong taste for efficiency. They provide appropriate quality even if own-money 
maximisation calls for over-or undertreatment; 
(c) About a fifth of sellers show behaviour that is consistent with strong inequality aversion. 
They over or under-treat customers if this behaviour reduces inequality (or turns 
disadvantageous into advantageous inequality) even if it also reduces their own 
monetary pay-off; 
(d) Adding up strong and weak forms of social preferences indicates that about half of the 
sellers display behaviour that is consistent with a taste for efficiency, while little more 
than a quarter of the sellers display behaviour consistent with (strong or weak) 
inequality aversion. </p>

<p>11 Table 5 includes data for the equal-mark-up price-vector (4,8). In treatment V-Endo, where prices are 
chosen by sellers this price-vector is observed extremely rarely -specifically in only 17 of the 704 possible 
cases. In two of the 17 cases, no interaction took place. The overtreatment rate in the remaining cases is 
37.5%, which is in the range that is observed in V-Exo1 and V-Exo2. The undertreatment rate is zero in 
V-Endo under this price-vector but it is based on only seven cases, which prevents meaningful testing of 
whether the provision behaviour under equal-mark-up price-vectors depends on whether the price-vector has 
been chosen endogenously or determined exogenously. 
12 We included all experts who under price-vector Ω had treated at least one customer needing q 
0 AND at 
least one customer needing q 
1 ; 50 of the 56 sellers were included under this rule. From the remaining six 
sellers, we included those where the data were consistent with exactly one of the social preference types 
introduced in Section 3. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>Table 6 provides a summary of the data. 
13 To read it properly, note that sellers who 
are classified as either weak EL, weak IA, weak SP or weak IL are also classified as weak 
SE. This has to be the case because weak EL, IA, SP and IL behave exactly as the strong 
version of the respective type as 'impartial spectators' (i.e. when there is no trade-off 
between own material pay-off and a fairness standard), that is at price-vector (4,8) in 
Figure 6. Once p 
0 varies, weak EL, IA, SP and IL act exactly like (strong) SE, because 
their own material pay-off is at stake. 
14 It follows that for relative frequencies (given in 
parentheses in Table 6) to add up to 100%, one has to add up either the strong non-SE 
types and the total number of SE types or the total number of non-SE types and the 
number of strong SE types. 
It is important to recall that the results displayed in Table 6 allow for 'mistakes' in 
early rounds. If we do not allow for learning in early periods then we lose eight of the 
53 observations. Interestingly, we do not lose a single experimental seller who reveals a 
willingness to give up own material pay-off to change the material pay-off of the 
customer. 
15 This suggests that selfish sellers do need some time to find out the own-
money-maximising strategy while strong EL and strong IA 'know how they want to 
behave' from the beginning. Since strong EL and strong IA reveal a willingness to give 
up own material pay-off to change the material pay-off of the customer, while the other 
types appearing with non-zero entries in Table 6 do not, one would expect that the 
former two types earn less -on average -than the rest. This is indeed what we find in 
the data. Tables C4 and C5 in the online Appendix C display -for the seller types in 
Table 6 -the average profits per period conditional on an interaction having taken 
place. While the entries for strong EL and strong IA are 2.37 and 2.22 respectively the 
other types earn 2.48, on average. If we put strong EL and strong IA sellers in one tub 
and all the other sellers in a second tub then the difference across tubs in average 
profits per period (conditional on an interaction having taken place) is significant at 
the 5% level (p = 0.03, Mann-Whitney U-test, N = 53). </p>

<p>Table 6 
Classification of Individual Behaviour in V-Exo </p>

<p>Social preference type 
Strong 
Weak 
Total </p>

<p>EL (efficiency loving) 
13 (24.5%) 
13 (24.5%) 
26 (49.0%) 
IA (inequality averse) 
10 (18.9%) 
3 (5.7%) 
13 (24.5%) 
SP (spiteful) 
0 (0%) 
3 (5.7%) 
3 (5.7%) 
IL (inequality loving) 
0 (0%) 
2 (3.8%) 
2 (3.8%) 
SE (selfish) 
9 (17.0%) 
21 (39.6%) 
30 (56.6%) </p>

<p>Notes. Note that sellers who are classified as either weak EL, weak IA, weak SP or weak IL are also classified as 
weak SE. Thus, for relative frequencies (given in parentheses) to add up to 100%, one has to add up either 
the strong non-SE types and the total number of SE types or the total number of non-SE types and the 
number of strong SE types. </p>

<p>13 Again, we pool the data from V-Exo1 and V-Exo2, because a Fisher exact test reveals that there are no 
significant differences in the distribution of social preference types between the two treatments (with p &gt; 0.5). 
14 Formally, the reason is that the weak SE type is the limit of all kinds of social preference types when the 
weight on the distributional part of the utility function approaches zero. Note, however, that the limiting 
behaviour is different for the four non-SE types! 
15 Table C3 in the online Appendix C displays a Table equal to Table 6 but based only on the 45 sellers 
who respect the monotonicity condition throughout the 16 periods of play. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>412 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>4.3. Discussion of Heterogeneity of Preferences </p>

<p>An important insight from our experimental results is that the behaviour of only a 
minority of individuals (those in the category 'weak EL') is consistent with the 
standard assumption on preferences -that is that sellers always follow their monetary 
incentives and in case of indifference they act in the interest of customers. This 
insight is important for several reasons. First, it is important for the current 
application -institutional design for credence goods markets under verifiability -
because it provides an explanation for both, why equal-mark-up price-vectors do not 
work as predicted by theory and why such vectors were not chosen in the 
endogenous pricing conditions of Dulleck et al. (2011). Second, it is important for 
institutional design for markets plagued by asymmetric information more generally, 
because it suggests that institutional design based on the standard assumption on 
preferences might yield bad incentives for some or even many agents. The results 
reported in Table 6 also confirm the heterogeneity in social preferences on which 
our discussion in Section 2 is based. Some sellers care for efficiency, some for 
equality of pay-offs, and some do not care for the well-being of others (or for 
efficiency) at all. 
Heterogeneity in preferences and behaviour is a well-established finding, of course. 
Indeed, it has been observed in many other games, for instance in public goods games 
(Fischbacher et al., 2001; Fischbacher and G€ achter, 2010) or in gift-exchange games 
(Fehr et al., 1993 1997). Also, in the literature on identification of the type and 
intensity of social preferences, heterogeneity is well known (Andreoni and Miller,  2002; Charness and Rabin, 2002; Engelmann and Strobel, 2004; Fisman et al., 2007). 
The current article contributes to the existing literature in two important ways: </p>

<p>(i) our identification procedure depends only on a small set of primitive 
assumptions on preferences, which is in contrast to much of the previous 
literatures; and 
(ii) our test for social preferences is completely nested in a market for credence 
goods. </p>

<p>This latter feature might help to alleviate the concern that the results of elicitation 
procedures based on dictator games are not robust and not easy to extend to other 
important economic situations. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>This study argues that heterogeneity in social preferences provides an explanation for 
both, why credence goods markets with verifiability fail to reach efficient outcomes and 
why markets without verifiability perform considerably better than predicted by 
standard theory. Key to our argument are the following two observations: first, the 
standard prediction for markets without verifiability is non-robust against the presence 
of agents with pro-social other-regarding preferences. Second, the standard solution to 
the credence goods problem for the case where the quality of the goods is verifiable -
equal-mark-up prices -is non-robust against the presence of agents with anti-social 
other-regarding preferences. </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>



<p>To provide support for our explanation, we design a test that allows for a clean 
discrimination between different preference types from the provision behaviour in an 
experimental market for credence goods. An important feature of our experimental 
design is that the discrimination does not depend on any specific assumptions on the 
form of the utility function of the expert. The experimental design rather 
directly tests the key characteristics of different variants of social preferences that 
have been discussed in the economics literature. A second important design feature is 
that our test for social preferences is completely nested in a market for credence goods. 
Important conclusions for credence goods markets and, more generally, for markets 
with asymmetric information can be drawn from our experimental results. Specifically, 
we have found in an implementation of our test that less than a quarter of the 
experimental sellers behave according to the standard assumption on preferences 
(that all agents are rational own-money maximisers who behave as desired if held 
indifferent in own-money terms). The rest behave either in line with other forms of 
selfish or in accordance with different variants of non-selfish other-regarding 
preferences. An immediate implication is that institutional design based on the 
standard assumption of lexicographically maximising agents yields bad incentives for 
some or possibly many agents. Another implication of our experimental results is that 
there are agents that behave appropriately, independent of the institutional design. 
Taken together these two observations have two important consequences, one for 
institutional design and the other for agent selection. </p>

<p>5.1. Designing the Right Institutions </p>

<p>What is needed for a well-performing market is not a perfect institution for one type of 
agent but rather an institution that is robust against the coexistence of different types 
of agents. Our results indicate that verifiability is not such an institution (nor is a 
market where verifiability does not apply). By contrast, as Dulleck et al. (2011) have 
shown, 'liability' is a quite robust institution in markets for credence goods. 'Liability' 
requires verifiability of 'outcomes', while 'verifiability' requires only verifiability of 
'inputs'. Thus, securing verifiability of outcomes, where possible, might solve credence 
goods problems more effectively in some markets. </p>

<p>5.2. Selecting the Right Agents </p>

<p>Designing robust institutions might be difficult, especially for markets for credence 
goods. Imposing liability, for instance, generates other problems or may be impossible 
to achieve. 
16 As a consequence, selecting the 'right' agents for jobs involving experts' </p>

<p>16 On the one hand, liability requires a form of verifiability of success. Especially in the medical realm 
success is often impossible or very costly to measure for a court, while still being observed by the consumer. 
On the other hand, even in cases where success is verifiable strict liability might pose problems. For instance, 
an insufficiently repaired car may work for some time before it breaks down. To mitigate the undertreatment 
problem in such a situation the liability needs to cover a longer period. But during this longer period the car 
may stop working for reasons unrelated to the expert's behaviour. Also, an extended liability period may 
induce fraudulent behaviour on the side of the customer as he may not put in the required maintenance 
effort -a problem that has previously been discussed by Taylor (1995). </p>

<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>414 </p>

<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H </p>

<p>services becomes particularly important. Instead of choosing doctors, mechanics or 
computer specialists exclusively according to their training, customers or their 
representatives should also take into consideration the attitudes of these experts 
towards their customers. Selecting the right agents may also help to solve problems 
created by uncertainty over input costs: with cost uncertainty standard theory would 
predict that verifiability cannot solve the problems on credence goods markets -a 
problem ignored in the formal literature on credence goods thus far. Our results 
suggest that verifiability can solve this problem if the 'right' agents are selected: 
Efficiency loving experts provide appropriate treatment in a corridor along the equal-
mark-up line; that is, even if monetary incentives are not perfectly in line. Hence, the 
crucial task of potential employers or buyers is to identify experts with the right social 
preferences. Public policy might step in here, for instance, by screening applicants for 
particular jobs (like in the health care sector, for instance) not only after their 
performance in entry examinations but also in accordance with their social track 
record. Since the 'effort cost' for performing social activities is arguably lower for more 
'consumer-friendly' types, a CV featuring an impressive track record of volunteer work 
might well act as a screening device. </p>

<p>University of Innsbruck 
University of Cologne and University of Innsbruck 
Queensland University of Technology </p>

<p>Submitted: 9 May 2013 
Accepted: 25 February 2015 </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix A. Social Preference Types. 
Appendix B. Proof of Lemma 1. 
Appendix C. Additional Experimental Results. 
Appendix D. Experimental Instructions for the -Exo Treatments. 
Data S1. </p>



<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>

<p>2017] </p>

<p>S O C I A L P R E F E R E N C E S I N G O O D S M A R K E T S </p>





<p>© 2015 The Authors. 
The Economic Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of Royal Economic Society. </p>



<p>T H E E C O N O M I C J O U R N A L </p>

<p>[ M A R C H 2017] </p>

</text></tei>