<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecin.12386" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>I collect data on how subjects acquire information about risky choices in both real 
and hypothetical settings using process-tracing software called <rs type="software">Mouselab</rs>. On average, 
there are no significant differences across settings in the amount of time subjects take to 
make a choice or the completeness of the information they acquire. Subjects also acquire 
information in sequences consistent with an integration model of decision-making, such 
as expected utility theory or prospect theory. I do not find significant differences in risk 
preferences across settings, on average, but I do find that subjects' risk preferences are 
related to the completeness of the information that they acquire and where they start 
their information acquisition. (JEL C91, D80, D83) </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>cognitive ability tend to make choices exhibiting 
hypothetical bias. 2 
These contradictory results have yet to be 
explained. Camerer and Hogarth (1999) illustrate 
that real incentives are likely to alter behavior 
when the task involved depends on the subject's 
effort level. But the choices that are typically used 
to measure risk aversion are designed to measure 
preferences, not effort. Moreover, while it is clear 
how economic incentives can cause individuals 
to misrepresent their willingness to pay for clean 
air in a survey that could influence environmental 
policy, there is not an obvious economic moti-
vation for why individuals would systematically 
misrepresent their risk preferences so that they 
appear more risk tolerant when they make choices 
with hypothetical consequences. 3 
This study uses a method of process tracing 
to explore whether individuals acquire informa-
tion about the risky choices in the commonly used 
Holt and Laury multiple-price list (HL MPL) 
differently when the choices have hypothetical 
monetary consequences rather than real monetary 
consequences (Holt and Laury 2002). It is pos-
sible that individuals may attend to the informa-
tion in hypothetical choices differently than real 
choices, and several studies have demonstrated 
that how individuals acquire information can be 
related to their decision-making. For instance, 
Costa-Gomes and Crawford (2006) show that 
simplified searches are correlated with deviations 
from equilibrium in a two-person guessing game, 
and Caplin, Dean, and Martin (2011) find that 
search patterns can affect subjects' decisions con-
ditional on choice complexity. 
There is no doubt that subjects are willing to 
devote at least some time to the consideration of 
hypothetical choices. Psychologists frequently 
rely exclusively on hypothetical decisions to 
study behavior. Some of these studies have 
used <rs type="software">Mouselab</rs> or other process-tracing tech-
niques, and they demonstrate that individuals 
do spend time considering hypothetical choices 
(Willemsen and Johnson 2010). The question of 
interest here, however, is whether information </p>

<p>2. Taylor (2013) focuses on the relationship between 
cognitive ability, risk aversion, and incentives using data from 
this same experiment. 
3. Murphy and Stevens (2004) discuss the lack of the-
oretical reasoning for hypothetical bias with respect to 
willingness-to-pay elicitation and their case is actually more 
applicable to risk preference elicitation. Carson and Groves 
(2007) consider the incentive properties of "inconsequen-
tial" survey questions in the context of valuation studies, but 
their conclusion that "economic theory makes no predictions" 
about respondent behaviour is equally relevant here. </p>

<p>acquisition behavior is significantly different for 
hypothetical and real risky choices. 
Wilcox (1993) is the only other study that 
explores a similar question. In particular, it tests 
whether subjects spend different amounts of time 
on decisions when there is variability in the frac-
tion of subjects who will be paid. This mecha-
nism, known as the random lottery mechanism 
(RLM), adds additional uncertainty to an experi-
ment from the perspective of the subject because 
only a portion of subjects will be paid based on 
their decisions. Wilcox finds that subjects spend 
more time on higher-yielding decisions, where 
"higher-yielding" implies a greater probability 
that the subject will be selected to have at least 
one of her choices have real consequences. Like 
Wilcox (1993), I also observe the amount of time 
subjects spend on each choice, but I also observe 
what types of information subjects acquire, how 
much information they collect before making a 
decision, and the sequences in which they collect 
that information. 
Observing the sequences in which informa-
tion is acquired also allows me to test whether 
these patterns are more consistent with an inte-
grative model of decision-making or a heuristic 
model. Integration theories of decision-making 
maintain that individuals integrate probabilis-
tic information and potential outcomes when 
making decisions. In contrast, heuristic models 
of decision-making hypothesize that the com-
plexity of many choices leads many individu-
als to resort to "rules of thumb" to simplify the 
decision-making process (Gigerenzer and Gaiss-
maier 2011; Gigerenzer, Todd, and the ABC 
Research Group 1999; Kahneman and Tversky 
1982; Newell and Simon 1972; Payne, Bettman, 
and Johnson 1993). 
The few early studies that explored how 
individuals acquired information about risky 
choices suggested that strategies consistent 
with a heuristic tended to dominate information 
acquisition behavior (Ford et al. 1989; Johnson, 
Payne, and Bettman 1988; Payne, Bettman, 
and Johnson 1988). However, the tasks and the 
presentation of the risky choices in these studies 
differ significantly from the tasks economists 
typically use to elicit risk preferences today. 4 </p>

<p>4. Payne, Bettman, and Johnson (1988) and Johnson, 
Payne, and Bettman (1988) are rare examples of early studies 
that used real payoffs. The subjects who participated in the 
experiments included in Payne, Bettman, and Johnson (1988) 
had the potential to win up to $9.99, which is approximately 
$19.00 in 2011 dollars. However, the choice structure and the 
tasks were atypical relative to the types of task that are used 
to elicit risk preferences from individuals today. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>More recent studies that have explored this ques-
tion employed tasks and choices more akin to the 
types of choices typically used by economists to 
measure risk preferences (Arieli, Ben-Ami, and 
Rubinstein 2011; Glöckner and Herbold 2011; 
Johnson, Schulte-Mecklenbeck, and Willem-
sen 2008). 5 Interestingly, these studies have 
reached contradictory conclusions. For example, 
Johnson, Schulte-Mecklenbeck, and Willemsen 
(2008) and Glöckner and Herbold (2011) find 
information acquisition patterns consistent with 
integration models, but Arieli, Ben-Ami, and 
Rubinstein (2011) do not. The conflicting results 
are not due to differences in how the process data 
were collected. All three studies used hypothet-
ical payoffs, and Glöckner and Herbold (2011) 
and Arieli, Ben-Ami, and Rubinstein (2011) 
used eye-tracking technology, while Johnson, 
Schulte-Mecklenbeck, and Willemsen (2008) 
used <rs type="software">Mouselab</rs>. 
I find that there are not significant differ-
ences in individuals' information acquisition or 
their risk preferences, on average, across real and 
hypothetical settings. Subjects also acquire infor-
mation in a manner consistent with the implicit 
calculation of expected utility or another integra-
tive model. In other words, when individuals face 
the choices presented to them in the HL MPL, 
they do not merely make decisions "as if" they 
are integrating probabilities and outcomes, their 
search patterns suggest that they actually do. 
Subjects are not more likely to be inconsistent 
when their choices were made in the hypothetical 
setting, and, unsurprisingly, subjects who do not 
acquire enough information to compute expected 
value for most of their decisions the first time they 
complete the task are more likely to make incon-
sistent choices. Interestingly, subjects who are 
willing to make these decisions without acquiring 
sufficient information to compute expected value 
also tend to make choices that imply that they are 
significantly less risk averse than the rest of the 
sample, even after controlling for the number of 
inconsistent choices. 
The following section briefly describes the 
method used to observe subject information 
acquisition, as well as provides a detailed 
explanation of the experimental design and the </p>

<p>5. Glöckner and Betsch (2008) used a method that they 
call the "open <rs type="software">mouselab</rs> method," which does not actually 
mask the information and, instead, asked a subject to move the 
mouse to the piece of information about which she is thinking. 
They find that information search is more consistent with an 
integrative model using this method. </p>

<p>protocol. Section II outlines the measures of 
information acquisition considered in the anal-
ysis. The results are presented and discussed in 
Section III and Section IV concludes. </p>

<p>I. EXPERIMENTAL DESIGN </p>

<p>A. Observing Information Acquisition </p>

<p>I use a software program called <rs type="software">Mouselab</rs> to 
observe how subjects acquire information about 
risky choices. <rs type="software">Mouselab</rs> is a method of process-
tracing used by psychologists for nearly three 
decades, and economists more recently, because 
it is lower-cost alternative to eye-tracking and 
provides analogous measures (Costa-Gomes 
and Crawford 2006; Costa-Gomes, Crawford, 
and Broseta 2001; Gabaix et al. 2006; Johnson 
et al. 2002; Payne, Bettman, and Johnson 1988; 
Reutskaja et al. 2011). The software enables the 
researcher to "mask" selected information so 
that a subject must move the computer pointer 
over the attribute to reveal it. In this experiment, 
the probabilities and payoffs (the attributes) of 
each gamble were masked and the individual was 
required to "unmask" the attributes by scrolling 
over the cell to view it. Once the mouse pointer 
leaves the cell, the attribute is hidden again. 
By requiring a subject to unmask the gambles' 
attributes and allowing them to view only one 
piece of information at a time, individuals' 
strategies for acquiring information about risky 
choices is observable in this stylized context. 6 
An example of how each pair of gambles was 
presented to subjects in the experiment is shown 
in Figure 1. 7 </p>

<p>B. The Task </p>

<p>The task used to measure risk preferences is a 
version of the multiple price list format pioneered 
by Holt and Laury (2002). The HL MPL presents 
ten pairs of gambles, or lotteries, to the subject 
and asks her to choose the more-preferred gamble 
in each pair. Columns (1) through (4) of Table 1 
illustrate the conventionally ordered HL MPL 
format. The payoffs of the gambles are struc-
tured so that Gamble B is more risky than Gamble </p>

<p>6. Subjects were required only to "mouseover" an 
attribute to reveal it and were not required to "click" on the 
attribute. Requiring a click is a design feature that could have 
been employed, but I believe that it would have increased the 
differences between our design and an eye-tracking design 
without an obvious benefit. 
7. The experiment was presented in color. </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>FIGURE 1 
Choice Example </p>

<p>A because the differences in the potential pay-
offs are larger. In the example shown in Table 1, 
Gamble A has possible payoffs of $40 and $32, 
and Gamble B has higher-variance payoffs of $77 
and $2. The probabilities are adjusted progres-
sively down the list of decisions so that the dif-
ference in the expected value between Gamble A 
and Gamble B, calculated in columns (5) through 
(7) but not shown to the subject, is monotoni-
cally decreasing. 
Because the focus of this study is on how indi-
viduals acquire information about the gambles 
presented to them, in addition to masking the 
attributes of the gambles and requiring subjects 
to unmask them, I modified the conventional HL 
MPL design in four other important ways. 
(a) Randomized order of the choices. First, the 
order of the choices was randomized and sub-
jects were presented with only one pair of gam-
bles at a time. Conventionally, subjects are pre-
sented with all ten gamble pairs simultaneously 
and in the order shown in Table 1. Facing this 
conventional order, once an individual switches 
from the safe gamble to the risky gamble, it would 
be inconsistent (according to expected utility the-
ory) to switch back to the safe gamble in sub-
sequent decisions. In fact, several studies simply 
show subjects all ten choices at the same time and 
ask them to identify the gamble pair at which they </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Multiple Price List </p>

<p>HL 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
Decision Gamble A 
Gamble B </p>

<p>Number p($40) p($32) p($77) p($2) EV A EV B EV A − EV B </p>

<p>1 
0 .1 
0 .9 
0.1 
0.9 32.80 9.50 
23.30 
2 
0 .2 
0 .8 
0.2 
0.8 33.60 17.00 
16.60 
3 
0 .3 
0 .7 
0.3 
0.7 34.40 24.80 
9.90 
4 
0 .4 
0 .6 
0.4 
0.6 35.20 32.00 
3.20 
5 
0 .5 
0 .5 
0.5 
0.5 36.00 39.50 
−3.50 
6 
0 .6 
0 .4 
0.6 
0.4 36.80 47.00 
−10.20 
7 
0 .7 
0 .3 
0.7 
0.3 37.60 54.50 
−16.90 
8 
0 .8 
0 .2 
0.8 
0.2 38.40 62.00 
−21.60 
9 
0 .9 
0 .1 
0 .9 
0.1 39.20 69.50 
−30.30 
10 
1 
0 
1 
0 
40.00 77.00 
−37.00 </p>

<p>Notes: All currency units are in 2011 U.S. dollars. Subjects were 
not presented with the information in columns (5) through (7). The 
probabilities and payoffs are averages since the probabilities were 
randomly perturbed by up to 2 percentage points and payoffs were 
randomly varied between 19, 20, and 21 times the "low" payoffs used 
in Holt and Laury (2002). </p>

<p>would switch. 8 That structure was not imposed 
here. This randomized design allows me to dis-
entangle (a) how individuals acquire information 
about more difficult choices in terms of the differ-
ence in their expected values, from (b) learning 
effects that may occur as subjects become more </p>

<p>8. Harrison, Lau, and Rutström (2007) employ this strat-
egy, as do Tanaka, Camerer, and Nguyen (2010) in various 
multiple-price list versions. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>familiar with the experimental design. The order 
in which a subject actually completed a choice is 
referred to as the Position Number, while the con-
ventional HL MPL order is referred to as the HL 
Decision Number. For example, if a subject was 
presented with the sixth decision in the HL MPL 
as her first choice, then the HL Decision Num-
ber for that choice is six and the Position Number 
is one. 
(b) Random perturbations in probabilities. 
Second, the probabilities of each gamble were 
randomly perturbed, dynamically, by up to 2 per-
centage points, so that the probabilities for the 
two gambles in each choice were not identical. 
For example, consider HL Decision 3 in the con-
ventionally ordered MPL. Rather than seeing a 
30% chance of the high payoff in both the safe 
and risky gambles, a subject could be presented 
with a 31% chance of the high payoff in Gamble 
A and a 28% chance of the high payoff in Gam-
ble B. Two percentage points is large enough to 
keep the probability information valuable, while 
preserving the monotonically decreasing rela-
tionship in the difference in expected values of 
the gambles. 
(c) Random scaling of the payoffs. Third, the 
scale of the payoffs was varied because subjects 
might begin to ignore this information after mak-
ing just a few choices if they were constant. 
Specifically, payoffs of each pair of gambles were 
randomly scaled by a multiple of 19, 20, or 21 
times the "low" payoffs used in Holt and Laury 
(2002). In that study, the low payoffs for the safe 
gamble were $2 and $1.60 and the low payoffs 
for the risky gamble were $3.85 and $0.10. In this 
experiment, if the payoffs for a gamble pair were 
scaled by 19, then a subject saw safe payoffs of 
$38 and $32 and risky payoffs of $73 and $1.90 
for that particular pair of gambles. The "20 times" 
scale is shown in Table 1. 
(d) Randomization of the choice format 
across subjects. Finally, to address concerns 
about possible left-to-right and top-to-bottom 
bias in subjects' attention to different areas in 
a choice display (Reutskaja et al. 2011), the 
presentation of the gambles was randomized 
along three different dimensions: (1) whether the 
probabilities or the payoffs were presented in 
the top row, (2) whether the safe gamble or the 
risky gamble was on the left, and (3) whether 
the high payoff or low payoff was on the left 
within each gamble. This randomization was 
by subject, and not across choice scenarios for 
any one subject. The instructions for each sub-
ject were designed so that the tutorial material </p>

<p>was presented in the same format as the actual 
choice scenarios that were later displayed for 
that subject. </p>

<p>C. Protocol </p>

<p>The experiment was computer-based, and 
a typical session included about four subjects, 
but never more than six, who were isolated by 
dividers. Before subjects began the experiment, 
they were read instructions that explained that 
they would be asked to make some choices and 
that there were no correct choices. They were 
also told that they were not competing against 
one another. 9 The remainder of the instructions, 
including a tutorial that explained the choices to 
the subjects and tested their understanding, were 
all presented via the computer. 
Each subject made choices in both the real 
and hypothetical settings, and the setting of the 
first task was randomly assigned. Subjects were 
not aware at the beginning of the experiment 
that they would make choices in both settings, 
only that there would be two sections, and in 
each section they would be asked to make some 
choices. All subjects received the same instruc-
tions and the same tutorial. The computer-based 
tutorial explained the gambles to the subjects 
using a vignette in which they were asked to 
imagine that there were two opaque jars filled 
with green balls and red balls and that the prob-
ability and payoff associated with drawing each 
color from each jar would be masked but that 
they would be able to unmask this information by 
moving the computer mouse over the cell with the 
information. They were then instructed that they 
would be asked to choose the jar from which they 
would prefer to draw a ball. 
After the tutorial, subjects randomly selected 
to make choices in the real setting were informed 
that they would make ten choices, one of which 
would be selected to determine their payoff. 
These subjects were reminded that, although only 
one choice would be selected, each choice was 
equally likely to be selected. Those designated to 
complete the hypothetical choices in the first task 
were informed that they would make ten choices, 
one of which would be selected, and they would 
then be shown how much their payoff would have 
been had the outcome counted toward their pay-
off. These subjects were then asked to consider 
these choices as if they would count toward their 
actual payoff. </p>

<p>9. Appendix S1, Supporting Information, includes the 
full script of these instructions. </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>Once subjects completed the first task, they 
then saw the instructions for whichever treatment 
they had not yet completed. After the subjects 
completed the second task, the results from both 
tasks were revealed to them in the order in which 
the subject completed the tasks. After comple-
tion of the choice tasks, a subject's payoff was 
revealed to her, and she was then asked to com-
plete a test that measured both numeracy and 
cognitive ability (Frederick 2005; Weller et al. 
2013). The final section of the experiment was 
a debriefing questionnaire that inquired whether 
subjects had been distracted during the experi-
ment, whether they were liquidity constrained, 
the income level of their household, their educa-
tion level and educational aspirations, the extent 
of their math and probability training, their aca-
demic major, and their gender. </p>

<p>II. MEASURES OF INFORMATION ACQUISITION </p>

<p>An individual's information acquisition can 
be measured in terms of its breadth and its 
depth. A search index that measures whether the 
sequences in which a subject acquires informa-
tion suggests she is using an integrative decision-
making model, like expected utility, or a heuristic 
to make her choices can also be computed. </p>

<p>A. Breadth </p>

<p>Breadth is defined here to be the complete-
ness of an individual's information set. One mea-
sure of information set breadth used here is 
whether a subject viewed at least one proba-
bility in each gamble and all four payoffs in a 
given choice scenario. This measure acknowl-
edges that some subjects may recognize the com-
plementary nature of the probabilities and the fact 
that they can compute expected value without 
opening both probabilities in each gamble. This 
measure is called 1(EV-Sufficient), and it takes a 
value of zero or one for each choice depending 
on whether the subject viewed sufficient infor-
mation to compute expected value. A second 
measure of information breadth is how many 
unique attributes a subject opened for a given 
choice, Unique Attributes. Since each choice has 
eight pieces of information, this measure ranges 
from zero to eight for each choice. 10 Given </p>

<p>10. To account for the possibility that subjects may "ac-
cidentally" unmask a cell only acquisitions for which a cell is 
unmasked for at least 100 ms are included (Payne, Bettman, 
and Johnson 1993). However, the results are not qualitatively 
different if a 50 ms threshold is used. </p>

<p>that the results are not substantively different 
for the two measures, I present the results for 
1(EV-Sufficient) below. </p>

<p>B. Depth </p>

<p>An alternative way to think about information 
acquisition behavior is in terms of its depth. The 
depth of a subject's information acquisition was 
measured by the number of cells that he opened 
(including repetitions) before making a choice, 
which is referred to as # Acquisitions, as well 
as how much time he spent making a choice, the 
Decision Duration. </p>

<p>C. Search Index </p>

<p>The sequences in which a subject acquires 
information acquisition can be used to construct 
an index to indicate whether those sequences are 
consistent with an integrative decision-making 
model or a heuristic. Such indices are designed 
to measure whether the transitions that sub-
jects use to acquire information about a choice 
are dominated by interdimensional transitions 
or intradimensional transitions. Interdimensional 
transitions are transitions among the dimensions 
of a particular option, each option has four dimen-
sions in this experiment, and they are consistent 
with an individual integrating the components 
of an option into a single value, like expected 
value. Intradimensional transitions are transitions 
across options to the same dimension. These 
types of transitions are consistent with an individ-
ual using a heuristic. For instance, someone may 
always choose the option with the highest poten-
tial payoff. The search metric (SM Index) intro-
duced by Böckenholt and Hynan (1994) is one 
index that indicates whether information acquisi-
tion is dominated by interdimensional transitions 
or intradimensional transitions, and it takes the 
following form: </p>

<p>(1) SM = </p>

<p>√ 
N 
( 
(AD∕N) 
( 
r a − r d 
) 
− (D − A) 
) </p>

<p>√ 
A 2 (D − 1) + D 2 (A − 1) </p>

<p>where r a denotes the number of interdimensional 
transitions, r d denotes the number of intradimen-
sional transitions, N is the total number of transi-
tions a subject makes while considering a choice, 
D is the number of dimensions in the choice, and 
A is the number of alternatives. The SM index is 
structured so that the mean value generated by 
random search behavior is equal to zero, and posi-
tive numbers are consistent with integrative mod-
els of decision-making and negative numbers are </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>consistent with the use of a heuristic. Although 
there are other search indices, the SM index is the 
preferred index because it is independent of the 
alternative-dimension ratio and it can be used to 
test whether information acquisition patterns are 
different from random search behavior (Schulte-
Mecklenbeck, Kuhberger, and Ranyard 2011). </p>

<p>III. RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 98 subjects participated in exper-
imental sessions conducted during March and 
April of 2011. The subjects were recruited 
primarily from undergraduate chemistry, eco-
nomics, and environmental studies courses at 
the University of Oregon. Subjects earned an 
average total payoff of $52.68, with a maximum 
of $86.00 and a minimum of $6.90. Nearly all 
subjects finished within 40 minutes. 
Ninety-seven subjects are included in the anal-
ysis because one subject was dropped since she 
did not unmask a single attribute in seven of the 
ten real choices and eight of the ten hypotheti-
cal choices. 11 As shown in Table 2, 48 subjects 
completed the real choices in the first task; the 
remaining 49 completed the hypothetical choices 
first. More than half of the subjects had com-
pleted a course in which at least 2 weeks were 
spent on probability and statistics. The average 
score on the nine-item cognitive ability test was 
approximately six, and just under one-third claim 
to have been liquidity constrained. Unlike many 
experiments that primarily use economics and 
psychology majors, this sample consists of a 
wider range of majors. Based on tests of equal-
ity of proportions, if the sample is partitioned by 
whether a subject completed the real or hypo-
thetical choices first, the individuals randomly 
assigned to each treatment are not statistically 
different along these dimensions. </p>

<p>A. Information Acquisition </p>

<p>The mean number of cells unmasked per 
choice, # Acquisitions, and mean Decision Dura-
tion per choice in each of the four task-setting 
treatments is shown in Table 3, along with the 
percentage of choices for which subjects viewed 
enough information to compute expected value, 
1(EV-Sufficient), and the SM Index. A simple 
comparison of means suggests that informa-
tion acquisition was nearly identical in the real </p>

<p>11. In other words, she made 17 out of 20 choices with 
no information about the choice she was making. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Summary Statistics </p>

<p>1(Real×1st Task) and 1(Hypot×1st Task) Indicate That 
Subjects Completed the Real Choices or the 
Hypothetical Choices in the First Task, Respectively </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>1(Real× 
1st Task) </p>

<p>1(Hypot× 
1st Task) 
p value </p>

<p>N 
48 
49 
-
Female 
0.46 
0.35 
.263 
Stats/Prob. course 
0.58 
0.55 
.748 
Ability score 
5.98 
5.55 
.222 
Liquidity constrained 
0.31 
0.27 
.608 
Major 
Economics 
0.10 
0.10 
.973 
Environmental science 
0.21 
0.16 
.568 
Science 
0.23 
0.22 
.957 
Business 
0.21 
0.18 
.760 
Other 
0.25 
0.33 
.410 </p>

<p>Notes: Values shown are proportions, except for N and 
Ability Score. Depending on the variable, p values are shown 
for either tests of equal proportions or tests of equal means. </p>

<p>and hypothetical settings in the first task. For 
example, mean # Acquisitions is 16.13 in the first 
task for both the real and hypothetical settings 
(p = .999). Decision Duration, the percentage of 
EV-Sufficient choices, and the SM Index are also 
nearly identical. 12 
The SM Index is positive and significantly 
different from zero in all four treatments, which 
indicates subjects used an integrative decision-
making model for this task. Out of the 1,939 
choices made, there are only ten choices in which 
the SM Index was less than zero. 13 
In the second task, by contrast, in addition 
to a substantial decline in information acquisi-
tion relative to the first task, average information 
acquisition appears to differ across settings. Sub-
jects unmasked approximately three fewer cells 
in the hypothetical setting relative to the real set-
ting (p = .001). Subjects also spent significantly 
less time per decision on the hypothetical choices </p>

<p>12. All p values are adjusted for within-subject 
correlations. 
13. It is possible that the spatial separation of the gambles 
may have biased subjects toward using within-gamble tran-
sitions to acquire information. In other words, because it is 
more "work" to make a same-attribute transition relative to 
a within-gamble transition subjects could, conceivably, make 
fewer same-attribute transitions. However, it is not obvious 
how the information can be presented to subjects in this type 
of choice context in a way that will both avoid this bias and 
not increase the difficulty of the choices with an unintuitive 
arrangement of the information. Moreover, Johnson, Schulte-
Mecklenbeck, and Willemsen (2008) also find that subjects 
tend to make transitions consistent with an integrative model 
when each gamble is presented horizontally in a row rather 
than in a "block" like this experiment. </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>TABLE 3 
Mean Information Acquisition Comparisons </p>

<p># Acquisitions Per Choice 
Decision Duration (in Seconds) 
Percent 1(EV-Sufficient) 
SM Index </p>

<p>Real 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Real 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Real 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Real 1st 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 1st 
Task 
16.13 
16.13 
13.78 
13.22 
85 
85 
3.11 
3.18 
Real 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Real 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Real 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Real 2nd 
Task </p>

<p>Hypot 2nd 
Task 
14.21 
11.03 
10.97 
9.28 
78 
63 
2.91 
2.52 </p>

<p>than the real choices in the second task-9.28 s 
compared to 10.97 s (p = .085)-and only 63% 
of the choices in the hypothetical setting satisfied 
the EV-Sufficient criteria (p = .007). 
Table 4 presents the estimates from parametric 
models for the four measures shown in Table 3. 14 
The models include controls for each task set-
ting separately, as well as their interactions with 
Position Number, HL Decision Number, and HL 
Decision Number 2 .These models also include 
controls for gender, cognitive ability, and whether 
the subject indicated that any of the following 
three conditions were true: completed a course 
in probability or statistics, is a business or eco-
nomics major, or is liquidity constrained. 
There are not significant differences in 
information acquisition across settings. The 
coefficient estimates for 1(Hypot×1st Task) in all 
four specifications are effectively zero and sta-
tistically insignificant. The coefficient estimates 
for 1(Real×2nd Task) and 1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
for both information depth measures shown 
in columns (1) and (2) indicate that subjects 
spent approximately one-third less time and 
made fewer acquisitions on each choice in the 
second task compared to choices in the first 
task. But there is not a statistically significant 
difference across settings in the second task-a 
Wald test of the null hypothesis that these two 
estimates are equal fails to reject the null for all 
four specifications. 
The coefficient estimates on Position Number 
in the information depth models indicate subjects </p>

<p>14. Although the panel structure of the data allows fixed-
effects models to be estimated, the experimental design 
imposes a constraint on fixed-effects models that prevent us 
from using them to appropriately address the primary ques-
tion of this study. A more detailed explanation is provided in 
Appendix S1. Fortunately, a fixed-effects model is not nec-
essary. Table A1 in Appendix S1 shows results from fixed-
effects specifications that are consistent with the main results 
discussed below, and Table A2 in Appendix S1 shows that 
coefficient estimates and standard errors generated from ordi-
nary least squares (OLS), fixed-effects, and random-effects 
models for Decision Duration are nearly identical. </p>

<p>spent less time on each choice, approximately 
5% less, and made fewer acquisitions, as they 
progressed through the first task in the real set-
ting. This is congruent with the expectation that 
individuals will spend more time on the choices 
they see earlier and will decrease the amount of 
time on each choice as they become more famil-
iar with the format. Somewhat counterintuitively, 
however, the coefficient estimates on the interac-
tion of Position Number and treatment imply that 
subjects who faced hypothetical choices in both 
tasks and real choices in the second task reduced 
time spent on choices at a slower rate than sub-
jects who faced real choices in the first task. 
Figure 2 reveals the reasons for this result. 
First, subjects who faced real choices in the 
first task spent significantly more time on the 
first choice. These subjects spent more than 
22 seconds on their first choice, on average, 
while subjects who faced hypothetical choices in 
the first task spent approximately 16.4 seconds on 
their first choice (p = .025, adjusted for within-
subject correlation). After the first choice in the 
first task the amount of time subjects spent on 
each choice is comparable across settings-the 
two lines for the first task overlap and they do 
not significantly diverge in the second task. If the 
first choice that subjects completed is excluded 
and an identical model is estimated there is no 
difference between the slopes. 15 Second, subjects 
spent significantly less time on the first choice in 
the second task because they were repeating the 
same task, regardless of the setting. 
While subjects reduced the depth of the infor-
mation they acquired as they progressed through 
the tasks, they did not reduce the breadth of their 
information. The coefficient on Position Num-
ber in the 1(EV-Sufficient) specification shown 
in column (3) is not statistically different from 
zero. Subjects acquired nearly the same breadth </p>

<p>15. A model that includes a dummy for the first choice 
and the other covariates shown in Table 4 produces compara-
ble results. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Information Acquisition </p>

<p>Information Acquisition Measure Used as Dependent Variable Is Shown at the Top of Each Column 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
ln(Duration) 
# Acquisitions 
1(EV-sufficient) 
SM Index 
OLS 
Poisson 
Logit 
OLS </p>

<p>1(Hypot×1st Task) 
−0.002 
0.015 
0.334 
0.001 
(0.126) 
(0.143) 
(0.794) 
(0.290) 
1(Real×2nd Task) 
−0.375*** 
−0.247* 
0.180 
−0.394 
(0.121) 
(0.129) 
(0.786) 
(0.254) 
1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
−0.316*** 
−0.288*** 
−0.184 
−0.484** 
(0.111) 
(0.102) 
(0.720) 
(0.213) 
Position Number 
−0.061*** 
−0.049*** 
−0.046 
−0.081*** 
(0.008) 
(0.010) 
(0.064) 
(0.019) 
… × 1(Hypot×1st Task) 
0.021** 
0.035*** 
0.004 
0.064** 
(0.010) 
(0.012) 
(0.078) 
(0.026) 
… × 1(Real×2nd Task) 
0.037*** 
0.021* 
−0.030 
0.041* 
(0.011) 
(0.012) 
(0.077) 
(0.023) 
… × 1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
0.027** 
0.017 
−0.052 
0.037 
(0.011) 
(0.011) 
(0.074) 
(0.025) 
HL Decision Number 
0.127*** 
0.189*** 
0.500*** 
0.267*** 
(0.032) 
(0.036) 
(0.168) 
(0.070) 
… × 1(Hypot×1st Task) 
−0.021 
−0.079 
−0.158 
−0.121 
(0.049) 
(0.051) 
(0.201) 
(0.097) 
… × 1(Real×2nd Task) 
0.038 
0.026 
−0.182 
−0.001 
(0.045) 
(0.053) 
(0.249) 
(0.104) 
… × 1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
−0.053 
−0.035 
−0.261 
−0.083 
(0.036) 
(0.042) 
(0.212) 
(0.077) 
HL Decision Number 2 
−0.011*** 
−0.017*** 
−0.049*** 
−0.023*** 
(0.003) 
(0.003) 
(0.014) 
(0.006) 
… × 1(Hypot×1st Task) 
0.001 
0.007 
0.014 
0.011 
(0.004) 
(0.005) 
(0.018) 
(0.009) 
… × 1(Real×2nd Task) 
−0.005 
−0.003 
0.015 
0.000 
(0.004) 
(0.005) 
(0.021) 
(0.010) 
… × 1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
0.002 
0.000 
0.017 
0.004 
(0.003) 
(0.004) 
(0.018) 
(0.007) 
Constant 
9.180*** 
2.331*** 
0.320 
2.429*** 
(0.168) 
(0.162) 
(0.864) 
(0.350) 
Log-likelihood 
−1437.200 
−7938.942 
−951.993 
−2850.431 
1(Real×2nd Task) = 1(Hypot ×2nd Task) η 
0.651 
0.745 
0.549 
0.704 
HL Decision×1(Real×2nd Task) = HL 
Decision×1(Hypot ×2nd Task) η </p>

<p>0.050 
0.271 
0.736 
0.444 </p>

<p>HL Decision 2 ×1(Real×2nd Task) = HL 
Decision 2 ×1(Hypot ×2nd Task) η </p>

<p>0.114 
0.540 
0.909 
0.716 </p>

<p>N 
1,939 
1,939 
1,939 
1,923 </p>

<p>Notes: Standard error estimates clustered on subject. Models include controls for gender, if a subject completed a course in 
statistics or probability, if a subject is a business or economics major, if the subject is liquidity constrained, and cognitive ability. 
*p &lt;.10. **p &lt;.05. ***p &lt;.01. 
η p values of Wald test shown. </p>

<p>of information for the first choice as they did 
for the tenth choice, which implies that subjects 
remained engaged throughout the entire task, 
again, regardless of the setting. 
The statistically significant coefficient esti-
mates on HL Decision Number and HL Decision 
Number 2 for all four specifications indicate that 
subjects were more likely to acquire a greater 
breadth of information, spend more time, and 
unmask cells in sequences more consistent with 
an integrative decision-making model when the 
choices are more "difficult." Recall from Table 1 
that the difference in expected values between the 
two gambles initially decreases, it is the smallest </p>

<p>for HL Decision Numbers 4 and 5, and then 
begins to increase again. If the time spent on each 
choice is plotted against the HL Decision Num-
ber, then an inverted u-shape is formed. This pat-
tern is consistent with the results of Glöckner and 
Herbold (2011), who also find that decision dura-
tions increase when the difference in the expected 
values of the options decreases. 
The interactions of 1(Hypot×1st Task) with 
HL Decision Number and HL Decision Number 2 
are not statistically significant, which indicates 
that subjects responded to the changes in diffi-
culty similarly for both the real and hypothetical 
choices in the first task. In contrast, a Wald test of </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>FIGURE 2 
Mean Decision Duration by Position Number in Which It Was Viewed by the Subject </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Mean Decision Duration (in seconds) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
Position Number </p>

<p>Real x 1st Task 
95% CI, Real x 1st Task 
Hypot x 1st Task 
95% CI, Hypot x 1st Task 
Real x 2nd Task 
95% CI, Real x 2nd Task 
Hypot x 2nd Task 
95% CI, Hypot x 2nd Task </p>

<p>Note: 95% confidence intervals are shown. </p>

<p>the null hypothesis that the coefficient estimates 
on HL Decision Number×1(Real×2nd Task) and 
HL Decision Number×1(Hypot×2nd Task) are 
equal is rejected in the model for Decision Dura-
tion (p=.050). In other words, subjects are less 
responsive to changes in the difficulty of the 
choices when the choices are hypothetical than 
when they are real, but only in the second task. 
Figure 3 shows this pattern visually. For 
each treatment, Decision Duration is fit with a 
quadratic with respect to the HL Decision Num-
ber. The two thin lines plot the real and hypo-
thetical settings in the first task, and both follow 
very similar paths. The thick-dashed line plotting 
Decision Duration for the hypothetical choices in 
the second task, however, diverges dramatically 
from the thick-solid line plotting the time spent 
on each decision in the real choices, and this 
explains the difference in unconditional means 
shown in Table 3. Indeed, in the second task, sub-
jects appear to be almost completely insensitive 
to the narrowing of expected value between the 
two options when the choices are hypothetical. </p>

<p>B. Where Do Subjects Begin Their Searches? </p>

<p>Probabilities or Payoffs. Given that subjects are 
spending more time on the choices in which the 
difference in expected value is narrower and that 
their search patterns are consistent with an inte-
grative decision model, if subjects realize that the </p>

<p>information about the difficulty of the choice is 
revealed via the probability cells, then we should 
expect them to begin their searches in the proba-
bility cells more often because the payoffs pro-
vide no information about the difficulty of the 
choice. The complementary nature of the prob-
abilities allows a subject to infer the difficulty 
of the choice by opening any of the probability 
cells, and, in fact, there was a slight tendency 
for subjects to begin their searches in a probabil-
ity cell-more than 53% of searches started in a 
probability cell-but the percentage is not signif-
icantly different from 50% (p=.135). 16 </p>

<p>Location. Similar to Caplin, Dean, and Martin 
(2011) who find that subjects tend to use a 
top-down search pattern, I find a clear left-to-
right search pattern in the data and a tendency to 
start searches in the top-left corner of a choice. 17 
Subjects demonstrated a clear tendency to start 
their searches in the option on the left-they </p>

<p>16. A linear probability model with standard error esti-
mates clustered on subject was used to estimate the prob-
ability that a subject started to search in a probability cell. 
Figure A1 in Appendix S1 demonstrates that subjects did not 
reveal a tendency to start in a cell with any particular attribute, 
other than the tendency not to start in the low-payoff cell in 
the risky option. 
17. The tasks in Caplin, Dean, and Martin (2011) were 
laid out along a vertical axis, whereas the options in the tasks 
for the present experiment were laid out horizontally. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 3 
Decision Duration by HL Decision Number </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Mean Decision Duration (in seconds) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
HL Decision Number </p>

<p>Real x 1st Task 
Hypot x 1st Task 
Real x 2nd Task 
Hypot x 2nd Task </p>

<p>began in the left option in more than 75% of 
choices. 18 The most common cell in which sub-
jects began searches was in the top left corner of 
the option on the left. More than 26% of searches 
began in this cell, although a random search 
pattern would result in about 12.5% of searches 
beginning in any particular cell (p=.000, pro-
portion test that probability equals 12.5%). The 
second most common cell in which subjects 
began their searches was in the cell at the bottom 
right of the option on the left-the cell in the 
option on the left closest to the "Submit" button. 
Subjects began nearly 21% of their searches in 
this cell (p=.000, proportion test that probability 
equals 12.5%). 
In contrast, subjects rarely started searches in 
the far right cells. Only about 6.5% of searches 
begin in the far right column, although we would 
expect 25% of searches to begin in the far right 
column if subjects were choosing to start their 
information acquisition in a random cell. 19 </p>

<p>C. Information Acquisition, Consistency, and 
Risk Aversion 
Inconsistency. How subjects acquire information 
is mostly unrelated to the consistency of their </p>

<p>18. Figure A2 in Appendix S1 demonstrates this strong 
tendency for subjects to start in cells on the left. 
19. Coefficient estimates from logit models indicate that 
the start location does not differ by setting. Results are not 
shown, but available from the author upon request. </p>

<p>choices. Table 5 shows the estimation results 
from logit regressions in which the dependent 
variable equals one if a subject made at least one 
inconsistent choice, 1(Inconsistent). 
The coefficient estimates on Number of 
Choices Viewed and 1(EV-Sufficient All Choices) 
in columns (1) and (2) imply that it was not 
necessary for subjects to view EV-Sufficient 
information for all of their choices to make 
consistent choices. However, it appears unlikely 
that a subject who does not acquire enough 
information to compute expected value for most 
of their choices would be able to make consistent 
choices in this task. If the model is re-estimated 
using only data from the first task, as shown in 
columns (3) and (5), the coefficients on Num-
ber of Choices Viewed and 1(EV-Sufficient All 
Choices) indicate that subjects who acquired 
EV-Sufficient information for more choices 
were less likely to make an inconsistent choice. 
The coefficient on Number of Choices Viewed 
indicates that each choice that is viewed reduces 
the likelihood of an error by more than 20%. In 
contrast, these measures are unrelated to con-
sistency in the second task, which is reasonable 
given that all subjects had just completed the 
entire task. 20 </p>

<p>20. As an additional robustness check, the models in 
columns (3) and (4) were also estimated using an indicator 
variable that equals one if the subject unmasked at least six 
Unique Attributes, on average, during the task (nearly 90% 
do). Again, the results were substantively unchanged. </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>TABLE 5 
Inconsistency and Information Acquisition </p>

<p>Logit Models in Which the Dependent Variable Equals One if the Subject Made One or More Inconsistent Choices. 
Sample Included in the Specification Shown at the Top of Each Column 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
Both 
Tasks </p>

<p>Both 
Tasks </p>

<p>1st 
Task </p>

<p>2nd 
Task </p>

<p>1st 
Task </p>

<p>2nd 
Task </p>

<p>1(Hypot×1st Task) 
0.151 
0.162 
0.150 
-
0.156 
-
(0.493) 
(0.494) 
(0.486) 
(0.501) 
1(Real×2nd Task) 
−0.354 
−0.316 
-
-
-
-
(0.512) 
(0.516) 
1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
−1.257** 
−1.185* 
-
−1.003* 
-
−1.016* 
(0.628) 
(0.607) 
(0.604) 
(0.593) 
Number of choices viewed 
−0.140 
-
−0.205* 
−0.101 
-
-
(0.093) 
(0.116) 
(0.167) 
1(EV-Sufficient All Choices) 
-
−0.639 
-
-
−1.124** 
0.120 
(0.441) 
(0.534) 
(0.717) 
Ln(Mean decision duration) 
0.467 
0.427 
0.463 
0.635 
0.517 
0.395 
(0.690) 
(0.692) 
(1.032) 
(1.163) 
(1.106) 
(1.176) 
Mean SM index 
−0.028 
−0.105 
−0.061 
−0.011 
−0.140 
−0.207 
(0.347) 
(0.345) 
(0.488) 
(0.762) 
(0.466) 
(0.708) 
(Started left≥9) 
0.227 
0.210 
0.240 
0.340 
0.376 
0.300 
(0.414) 
(0.408) 
(0.514) 
(0.926) 
(0.535) 
(0.871) 
Freq. started probability 
0.015 
0.007 
0.015 
−0.027 
0.010 
−0.025 
(0.069) 
(0.070) 
(0.103) 
(0.110) 
(0.108) 
(0.107) 
Constant 
−1.691 
−2.158 
−0.980 
−3.634* 
−2.197 
−3.265* 
(1.461) 
(1.455) 
(2.098) 
(1.862) 
(2.140) 
(1.847) 
Log-likelihood 
−93.828 
−93.832 
−54.554 
−33.751 
−53.736 
−33.909 
1(Real×2nd Task) = 1(Hypot ×2nd Task) a 
0.158 
0.163 
-
-
-
-
N 
194 
194 
97 
97 
97 
97 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors shown. Models include controls for gender, if a subject completed a course in statistics or 
probability, if a subject is a business or economics major, if a subject is liquidity constrained, and cognitive ability. 
*p &lt;.10, **p &lt;.05. 
a p values of Wald test shown. </p>

<p>Subjects also appear to have learned as they 
progressed through the experiment and this 
resulted in more consistent choices in the second 
task. The coefficient estimates on 1(Hypot×2nd 
Task) indicate subjects who faced hypothetical 
choices in the second task were significantly 
less likely to make an inconsistent choice-less 
than half as likely or approximately 17% points 
less likely, even though these subjects spent 
less time on the more difficult choices. Fur-
thermore, although it is possible that shorter 
Decision Durations could increase the likelihood 
that a subject makes an error, the insignificant 
coefficients on Ln(Mean Decision Duration) 
indicate that subjects were not significantly less 
likely to make an inconsistent choice if they 
spent more time on their decisions. 
Where subjects started their searches does not 
impact choice consistency. An indicator variable 
equal to one if a subject started in the left option 
for at least nine choices, 1(Started Left ≥ 9), was 
included in the model because subjects started 
their searches in the option on the left for at least 
nine choices nearly half the time (48.5%) and the </p>

<p>coefficient on this variable is insignificant. The 
coefficient estimate on Freq. Started Probability, 
which is the number of times that a subject started 
in a probability cell, is also insignificant. 21 </p>

<p>Risk Aversion. I do not find that average risk pref-
erences are significantly different across settings 
in this experiment. The mean Last Safe Choice 
(i.e., the switch point) was 6.68 in the real set-
ting and 6.47 in the hypothetical setting. The 
distributions of subjects' switch points in each 
setting is shown in Figure 4, and a Wilcoxon 
rank-sum test fails to reject the null hypothesis </p>

<p>21. As shown in Section III.B, subjects did not demon-
strate such a strong tendency to start their searches in proba-
bility cells compared to payoff cells. The median number of 
choices that subjects started on the left in a task is eight, while 
the median number of choices that they started in a probability 
cell is five. A Shapiro-Wilk test rejects the null hypothesis that 
Freq. Started Left is normally distributed (p &lt;.001), and fails 
to reject the null that Freq. Started Probability is normally 
distributed (p=.963). The results are nearly identical if Freq. 
Started Left is used instead; log-likelihoods are slightly lower 
using 1(Started Left≥9) for all three specifications suggesting 
a slightly better fit. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 4 
Distribution of Subject Switch Points </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Number of Subjects </p>

<p>0 
1 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 </p>

<p>Distribution of Subject Switch Points </p>

<p>by Last Safe Choice </p>

<p>Hypothetical 
Real </p>

<p>that these distributions come from the same pop-
ulation (p=.453). The standard deviations are 
also very similar and do not significantly dif-
fer (σ r =.201, σ h =.197, p value =.639, Levene's 
test of equal variances). 22 Furthermore, although 
the tasks in this experiment were more challeng-
ing because the probabilities and payoffs were 
masked, subjects' switch points in these exper-
iments are comparable to the average switch 
points of subjects who face the conventional HL 
MPL. For instance, Holt and Laury (2005) report 
average safe choices that range from 4.9 to 7.1 for 
subjects in three different experiments who faced 
10 or 20 times the "baseline" payoffs. 
Significantly, it appears that how subjects 
acquire information about these choices is related 
to their apparent risk preferences. Table 6 shows 
the results of Poisson regressions used to model 
risk aversion as measured by a subject's switch 
point. The regressors in the models are identi-
cal to the specification used to model consistency 
that is shown in column (1) of Table 5, except for 
the inclusion of an additional control for the num-
ber of reversals. </p>

<p>22. These results are substantively the same if these mea-
sures are compared within task. The mean Last Safe Choice in 
the first task was 6.77 in the real setting and 6.69 in the hypo-
thetical setting (p=.781, Wilcoxon rank-sum test, σ r =.300; 
σ h =.277, p value = .639, Levene's test). The means in the 
second task were 6.59 and 6.25 in the real and hypotheti-
cal settings, respectively (p=.417, Wilcoxon rank-sum test; 
σ r =.273, σ h =.280, p value = .835, Levene's test). </p>

<p>Subjects who acquire EV-Sufficient informa-
tion for very few choices make decisions that 
make them appear less risk averse. The coef-
ficient estimate on Number of Choices Viewed 
implies that subjects who do not typically 
acquire enough information to compute expected 
value may be revealing their risk preferences by 
demonstrating that they are willing to make these 
decisions with significantly less information. The 
magnitude of this effect is displayed in Figure 5, 
which shows the predicted number of safe 
choices conditional on the Number of Choices 
Viewed. A subject who views all ten choices 
is predicted to make approximately seven safe 
choices, while subjects who view three or fewer 
are expected to make approximately five safe 
choices. 23 If we assume utility is described by 
the constant relative risk aversion utility function 
U(x) = x 1 − r /1 − r, a subject who makes seven 
safe choices is willing to pay no more than $12 
to play a gamble with a 50-50 chance of paying 
$100 or $0, while someone who makes only five 
safe choices would be willing to pay up to $44 
to play. 24 </p>

<p>23. These predicted values are calculated using the 
variable means. 
24. These dollar values are the certainty equivalents that 
would make an individual indifferent between the gamble 
and a certain amount of money using the coefficient of risk 
aversion on the lower bound. For example, an r of .15 implies 
a certainty equivalent of $44.20. </p>

<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>



<p>TABLE 6 
Research Aversion and Information Acquisition </p>

<p>Poisson Model in Which the Dependent Variable Is the 
Subject's Last Safe Choice, That Is, the Switch Point 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>1(Hypot×1st Task) 
0.022 
0.019 
(0.055) 
(0.055) 
1(Real×2nd Task) 
−0.020 
−0.026 
(0.059) 
(0.060) 
1(Hypot×2nd Task) 
−0.054 
−0.079 
(0.064) 
(0.063) 
Number of choices viewed 
0.039*** 
-
(0.013) 
1(EV-Sufficient All Choices) 
-
0.110** 
(0.044) 
Ln(Mean decision duration) 
−0.144* 
−0.113 
(0.081) 
(0.075) 
Mean SM index 
−0.029 
0.003 
(0.040) 
(0.038) 
1(Started left≥9) 
−0.129*** −0.119*** 
(0.041) 
(0.043) 
Freq. started probability 
0.013 
0.013 
(0.009) 
(0.009) 
Reversals 
0.120*** 0.109*** 
(0.031) 
(0.034) 
Constant 
2.022*** 2.111*** 
(0.185) 
(0.180) 
Log-likelihood 
−412.903 −414.867 
1(Real×2nd Task) = 1(Hypot ×2nd 
Task) a </p>

<p>0.584 
0.383 </p>

<p>N 
194 
194 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors shown. Model includes 
controls for gender, if a subject completed a course in statistics 
or probability, if a subject is a business or economics major, 
if a subject is liquidity constrained, and cognitive ability. 
*p &lt;.10, **p &lt;.05, ***p &lt;.01. 
a p values of Wald test shown. </p>

<p>The specification shown in column (2) demon-
strates that the relationship between risk prefer-
ences and the number of choices that subjects 
viewed is robust, regardless of how it is included 
in the model. This specification also indicates 
that the coefficient estimate on Ln(Mean Deci-
sion Duration), which is relatively large and 
statistically significant at the 8% level in the spec-
ification shown in column (1), does not appear to 
be robust. 
Interestingly, where a subject starts acquiring 
information is significantly related to her risk 
aversion. The coefficient estimate on 1(Started 
Left ≥ 9) implies that subjects who always, or 
nearly always start on the left, make choices that 
suggest that they are approximately 13% less risk 
averse than subjects who do not. 
On the whole, these results provide evidence 
that some characteristics of information acquisi-
tion are related to apparent risk aversion. In par-
ticular, subjects who tend to not acquire enough 
information to compute expected value and those </p>

<p>who systematically begin on the left tend to 
appear less risk averse. Thus, if subjects acquired 
information differently for hypothetical choices 
compared to real choices then it is possible these 
differences could have been a source of the hypo-
thetical bias in some prior studies. However, the 
evidence in Section III.A indicates that infor-
mation acquisition did not significantly differ 
across settings, except under very specific con-
ditions (i.e., repeating a task under hypotheti-
cal conditions that they just completed under 
real conditions). </p>

<p>IV. DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSION </p>

<p>I used process-tracing software called Mouse-
lab, which tracks how individuals acquire 
information while making choices, to test 
whether differences in information acquisition 
across real and hypothetical settings can explain 
the "hypothetical bias" in risk preferences that 
some studies have identified (Harrison 2006; 
Holt and Laury 2002, 2005). I do not find major 
differences in information acquisition or risk 
aversion across settings, on average, despite 
using relatively large potential payoffs in the 
experiment, ranging from $1.90 to $81, in the 
context of a modified HL MPL. 
The process-tracing data generated in this 
experiment does not provide evidence that indi-
viduals acquire information for hypothetical 
choices differently than real choices. However, 
similar to Caplin, Dean, and Martin (2011), I 
also find that how subjects acquire information 
is related to their decisions. Subjects who fre-
quently fail to acquire enough information to 
compute expected value for the choices in a task 
tended to make more errors, and they also appear 
to be less risk averse, even after controlling for 
the number of errors. Additionally, subjects who 
start their information acquisition on the left tend 
to be less risk averse. 
There are two subtle differences in how sub-
jects acquire information in hypothetical settings 
that could be important in some research settings. 
First, subjects who made choices in the real set-
ting in the first task spent 30% more time on the 
first choice than subjects who made choices in the 
hypothetical setting. After this first choice, infor-
mation acquisition is very similar, but this differ-
ence for the first choice suggests that researchers 
relying on a single choice should be wary of 
assuming a hypothetical choice will receive the 
same attention as a real choice. Second, subjects 
who faced the hypothetical choices in the second </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 5 
Predicted Switch Points by the Number of Choices for Which a Subject Viewed EV-Sufficient 
Information </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Predicted Last Safe Choice </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
Number of Choices Viewed </p>

<p>task did not respond to an increase in choice dif-
ficulty by increasing the amount of time spent 
to the same degree as those subjects who faced 
the real choices in the second task. This should 
make researchers who are seeking to conduct 
within-subject analysis cautious about whether it 
is appropriate to use a research design in which 
some subjects complete the real choices before 
the hypothetical choices. Depending on the task, 
the order may significantly affect the effort put 
forth by subjects in each task. In this case, it 
does not appear that this difference in duration 
in the second task affected choices, but it should 
be considered when designing an experiment that 
asks subjects to repeat a task in both real and 
hypothetical settings. 
Hypothetical scenarios in surveys and 
experiments are valuable because they allow 
economists to explore questions that would be 
extremely costly or impractical with real conse-
quences. In some cases, the only way to proceed 
with research is to use hypothetical choice scenar-
ios. This study finds that some measures of infor-
mation acquisition are related to risk aversion, but 
on the whole individuals do not acquire informa-
tion about hypothetical choices in a significantly 
different way than they do about real choices, 
and that risk preferences are not significantly dif-
ferent across settings in this context. Considered </p>

<p>in conjunction with several prior studies that do 
not find differences in risk preferences across 
settings (Beattie and Loomes 1997; Kühberger, 
Schulte-Mecklenbeck, and Perner 2002; Wise-
man and Levin 1996), there is evidence to 
suggest risk preferences obtained via hypothet-
ical choices are not necessarily biased and that 
economists should not reflexively dismiss them. </p>



<p>TAYLOR: INFORMATION ACQUISITION UNDER RISKY CONDITIONS </p>





<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Appendix S1. Instructions Read Aloud and Supporting 
Analysis </p>

</text></tei>