<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Flabr.12083" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. This paper analyses the relationship between wage distribution and educational 
attainment of the workforce. Wage inequality in Turkey decreased over 2002-10; a period over which 
it also saw an increase in the supply of educated workers. Our findings suggest that decreasing 
inequality in the bottom half of the distribution was largely due to decreasing returns to education 
and experience; whereas the moderate decline in inequality in the upper tail of the wage distribution 
is explained by a fall in returns to the 'routine' occupational tasks. The effect of changes in the 
composition of workers was found to be moderate. </p>

<p>Following the dramatic increase in wage inequality observed across several countries, 
there has been a considerable interest in studying the distribution of wages, over the last 
three decades. In particular, the steep increase in the wage gap between the college and the 
high school graduates in the United States has been documented by many authors, starting 
with Katz and Murphy (1992) and Bound and Johnson (1992). Besides the United States, 
an increasing educational premium has also been documented for many OECD countries 
(Berman et al., 1997; Machin and Reenen, 1998). In line with these studies, most of the 
analysis in the literature has subsequently focused on wage inequality between workers 
with high and low educational qualifications. In these studies, the increasing wage inequal-
ity is mostly explained by the supply-demand approach and attributed to increasing skill 
demand. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Two most popular theories used to explain increase in the relative demand for skilled 
workers are the Stolper-Samuelson effects and the skill biased technological change 
(SBTC). The first theory argues that competition with labour-abundant countries decreases 
the relative price of labour-intensive goods and accordingly reduces the real wages of less 
educated workers in both relative and absolute terms (Hanson and Harrison, 1999). The 
SBTC theory argues that in accordance with the diffusion of higher technologies of infor-
mation and communication, the labour demand has shifted in favour of skilled workers 
and increased the skill premiums (Acemoglu, 2002). Although there is no clear agreement, </p>

<p>We are grateful to the Turkish National Statisitics Institute for making the data available. We 
would like to thank the participants at the 33rd IARIW General Conference, Rotterdam, Nether-
lands, August 2014, for their useful comments. We would also like to thank Sarah Brown, Ken Clark, 
Jonathan Perraton, Peter Wright, the editor, and an anonymous referee for their helpful comments. 
All responsibility for the analysis and interpretation of these data lies with the authors. 
1 Department of Economics, University of Sheffield, 9 Mappin Street, Sheffield S1 4DT, UK 
2 Department of Economics, Bartın University, A gdacı Campus, Merkez, Bartin, 74110, Turkey 
Email: oyilmaz@bartin.edu.tr </p>

<p>LABOUR 31 (1) 73-104 (2017) 
DOI: 10.1111/labr.12083 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>JEL J31, J82, I24 </p>

<p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License, which permits use 
and distribution in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, the use is non-commercial and no modifications or 
adaptations are made. </p>

<p>it is generally believed that SBTC is the main reason for increasing wage inequality. Most 
of the initial explanations for the increasing demand for skilled workers centred on the 
argument that the new and efficient technology that is embodied in the new capital equip-
ment complimented the high skilled workers, thus depressing the relative demand for less 
skilled workers (Berman et al., 1994; Caselli, 1999; Galor and Tsiddon, 1997; Krusell et al.,  2000). 
More recently a number of papers (using evidence from both the United States and Eur-
ope) nuance this argument further and link the earnings inequality to job polarization, 
routinization and changes in returns to specific 'tasks' all linked with evolving technology 
and globalization (Acemoglu and Autor, 2011; Firpo et al., 2011; Goos et al., 2009, 2014). 
The argument here is that the changing nature of technology has resulted in the depression 
of returns to (and eventual loss of jobs in) 'routine' tasks that can now be performed by 
technologies. As these routine tasks are performed by the medium skilled workers, this in 
turn leads to wage polarization where, relative to middle of the wage distribution, the 
wages at the upper and the lower tail grow faster; this in turn then results in an increases 
in inequality in the top half of the distribution but a decrease in inequality in the bottom 
half of the distribution (Naticchioni et al., 2014). 
Although a number of studies have looked at the evidence from developed countries, to 
a lesser extent, evolution of wage distribution has also been analysed for developing coun-
tries. Using cross-sectional household data for Argentina, Chile, Costa Rica, Colombia, 
Malaysia, Mexico, Philippines, Chinese Taipei and Uruguay, Robbins (1996) found that 
trade liberalization was accompanied by rise in relative wages and the demand for skilled 
workers. Hanson and Harrison (1999) examined the effects of Mexican trade reforms on 
wage inequality and they asserted that the rising wage gap was associated with changes 
internal to industries and could not be explained by the Stolper-Samuelson type effects. 
Galiani and Sanguinetti (2003) analysed the trade liberalization process which took place 
in Argentina during 1990s; their results show that trade openness explained only a small 
proportion of the increase in wage inequality. Berman and Machin (2000) analysed SBTC 
for developing countries and found evidence that demand for skilled labour increased in 
middle income countries and this increase was mainly due to skill upgrading within indus-
tries rather than a reallocation of employment from low-to high-skill industries. 
In the recent years a number of Latin American countries have witnessed a decline in 
wage inequality (Campos et al., 2012; Lustig et al., 2013). The reasons given for the declin-
ing wage inequality echo those for rising wage inequality, in reverse. The observed fall in 
wage inequality has been largely attributed to fall in skill premiums and more robust gov-
ernment transfers; further much of the fall in the skill premiums is attributed to increases 
in educational attainments and fall in the demand for the skilled labour (Lustig et al.,  2013). Naticchioni et al. (2008) in their paper analysed the stable wage inequality in Italy 
over 1993-2004 and found that the increasing educational attainment of the workforce was 
countervailed by the stable skill demand. 
This paper analyses the relationship between wage distribution and changing educational 
attainment of the workforce. For our analysis we focus on the Turkish labour market, 
which experienced a substantial decrease in wage inequality between 2002 and 2010; a per-
iod over which it also saw a rapid increase in the educational attainment of the workforce. 
We explore the link between the changes in the relative supply of skilled labour, fall in the 
returns to education and decrease in wage inequality. Within this context we also check if 
there was any evidence of job polarization and its impact on wage inequality for Turkey; </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>where job polarization is captured at the individual level by using the occupational task 
measures classification suggested by Goos et al. (2009).   2   To understand the factors affecting wage inequality in Turkey over this period, the 
change in wage distribution between 2002 and 2010 is, as a first step, decomposed into 
three components: effect of returns to human capital (changes in coefficients); effect of 
changes in the composition of human capital (changes in covariates); and changes in resid-
ual distribution (price and composition of unmeasured human capital characteristics). To 
do this we use the decomposition method proposed by Lemieux (2002); furthermore, in 
order to correct for the possible selection bias related to the participation in wage employ-
ment, a two-step procedure, proposed by Dubin and McFadden (1984), is also used within 
this decomposition. The analysis is done for both men and women separately. 
Next we use the Firpo et al. (2009) decomposition which allows us to identify, for the 
entire distribution, the composition effect of the different covariates used in the analysis. 
This then allows us to look at the role played by education in explaining the decreasing 
inequality; it also allows us to look at the contribution of occupations to the observed 
changes, i.e., whether or not job polarization played any role in the changing wage distri-
bution. 
Our paper contributes to the existing literature in two main ways. First, it provides the 
most recent and rigorous detailed decomposition analysis of wage inequality in Turkey; 
where we look closely at the impact of increase in education of the labour force on wage 
inequality. Second, it is the first paper to look at occupational task measures and see how 
they might contribute to changes in the distribution of wages in Turkey. 
The key findings of the paper suggest that the increasing supply of educated labour, 
which was due to an increase in the number of universities and the reform to the education 
system which increased the years of compulsory education, had a significant effect on the 
wage distribution in Turkey between 2002 and 2010. Wage inequality in Turkey decreased 
over this period with much of the decline happening in the lower tail of the wage distribu-
tion. Decomposition results reveal that decreasing wage inequality in the bottom half was 
mainly due to decreasing returns to education and experience. It is also found that the 
decrease in residual wage dispersion was mainly due to the decreasing price of unmeasured 
human capital. The moderate decline in inequality in the upper tail of the wage distribu-
tion is explained by fall in returns to 'routine' occupational tasks. Finally, the effect of 
changes in the composition of workers is found to be moderate. 
The structure of the paper is as follows; Section 2 reviews the existing literature on the 
empirical work for Turkey and discusses the education reforms and the macroeconomic 
environment for the Turkish economy. Section 3 presents the underlying hypothesis and 
outlines the methodology used in this paper. Section 4 presents the data and descriptive 
statistics; wage regression estimations, and decomposition results are discussed in Sec-
tion 5; and finally Section 6 concludes. </p>

<p>2. Turkish economy </p>

<p>2.1 Wage inequality in Turkey </p>

<p>Studies on the wage inequality in Turkey are few. Kizilirmak (2003) analysed the 
increase in relative demand for skilled labour and wage inequality in the Turkish </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
manufacturing sector for the 1988-2000 period and argued that the change in relative 
demand for skilled workers was primarily due to the within-industry skill upgrading (which 
in part she attributed to trade). Elveren and Galbraith (2009) examined the sub-sectors of 
Turkish manufacturing and found an increase in the sector premiums between 1980 and 
2001. Meschi et al. (2011) investigate the relationship between trade openness, technology 
adoption and relative demand for skilled workers in the Turkish manufacturing sector 
using firm-level data covering the period 1980-2001. They find evidence of skill upgrading 
within firms as a direct result of increased trade openness; thus lending support to the 
argument of SBTC in a middle income country like Turkey. 
Tansel and Bodur (2012) use the quantile regression technique to analyse the evolution 
of male wage inequality over the 1994-2002 period, using the Household Budget Survey 
(HBS). The authors find that there was an overall decline in wage inequality in Turkey; 
where inequality declined at the lower end of wage distribution while it increased at the 
top end. Their results indicated that education contributed to higher wage inequality 
through both within and between dimensions; and finally they find evidence of decreasing 
returns to education which they attribute to increase in the educational attainment of the 
labour forces, combined with a relatively stable demand for skilled workers. 
Bakis and Polat (2015) study the evolution of wage inequality in Turkey over the period 
2002-10, using the Labour Force Survey (LFS) data. The authors do a supply-demand 
analysis, as in Katz and Murphy (1992). They find a steep increase in the supply of college 
educated workers relative to both, workers with some college level education and workers 
with high school education; and the relative wages for the college educated workers over 
this period decreased. The aggregate decomposition of wage inequality 
3 further revels that 
it is the changing returns to covariates, and not the changing composition, that explain 
much of the observed change in inequality. The authors provide institutional changes, espe-
cially the sharp increase in minimum wage as an explanation for the observed decline in 
wage inequality. 
Our analysis uses the same data set and covers the same period as the Bakis and Polat  (2015) paper. However, we differ from their analysis in three key ways: (1) we do the aggre-
gate decomposition, similar to them, however, we decompose the changes in the distribu-
tion of residuals as well; (2) we do a detailed decomposition to look at the specific 
covariates which might contribute to the changing trends in the wage inequality; and (3) 
given the evidence of Meschi et al. (2011) of potential SBTC in Turkey we look at the dif-
ferent occupational task measures to see if they contribute to wage inequality in Turkey. </p>

<p>2.2 Education system and composition of labour force </p>

<p>The education system in Turkey has seen numerous changes in the last few decades. First 
of these was the reform to the compulsory education system in 1997. Before the reform the 
education system in Turkey was organized as compulsory primary school (5 years), middle 
(or secondary) school (3 years), high school and vocational high school (3 years) and uni-
versity education (2-6 years). With the reform in the education system, compulsory pri-
mary education was extended to 8 years and middle school was abolished. </p>

<p>4   The second important development was the rapid increase in the number of universities. 
The establishment of new universities began with the second Five Year Development Pro-
gram which was put in practice in 1968 (State Planning Organization, 1967). Over the fol-
lowing years, the number of universities increased gradually with the establishment of 20 
universities between 1971 and 1991. In 1991, there were only 29 universities in Turkey. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>However, in the following years the number of universities increased dramatically, particu-
larly in 1992 when 24 new universities were established in 1 year. Finally, with the 'a uni-
versity in each city' policy (starting in 2000) and growing private sector participation, in 
2011 the number of universities reached 165. As a consequence of these new universities, 
the number of university students also increased substantially. For instance, from 1994 to 
2011, number of students in formal university education increased by more than 300 per 
cent and rose from 1.2 to 3.7 million (Turkey National Statistics Institute; TurkStat hence-
forth). 
The fast increase in the number of universities in Turkey has been accompanied by a ris-
ing difference between the old and the new universities in terms of equipment, funding and 
resources which can be expected to lead differences in the quality of education. Hatake- naka (2006) argued that the new universities which are not located in metropolitan centres 
find it difficult to recruit qualified people because they are unwilling to relocate to outer 
regions even though several measures were tried in the past to address these issues. 
5 In 
addition, due to the central university entrance examination system, more successful stu-
dents have the chance of studying with other successful students in the universities with 
better resources and this leads to further skill differences between university graduates. </p>

<p>6   Considering these two developments, it can be argued that the supply of educated labour 
in labour force (employed and unemployed) continuously increased starting from the early 
1990s. According to TurkStat web database, between 1988 and 2011 the share of individu-
als with university education in labour force increased from 4 to 21 per cent for women 
and 5-15 per cent for men. For the same period, the share of individuals with education 
less than high school in labour force decreased for both men and women. Similar patterns 
are also observed in the composition of the employed and the unemployed. Based on these 
observations, a decrease in educational premium can be expected; the increasing supply of 
workers with higher education is likely to decrease the upward pressure on the wages of 
university graduates, whereas decreasing the share of workers with low level of education 
moderates the downward pressure on their wages. </p>

<p>2.3 Macroeconomic environment </p>

<p>Turkey experienced several major economic crises starting from the 1990s. The first crisis 
occurred with the Gulf war in 1991. The second crisis, which was triggered by the fiscal 
and external imbalances, occurred in 1994 and a GDP growth rate of negative 6.1 per cent 
was witnessed. After a short period of recovery, due to the adverse effects of the Asian, 
Russian and Brazilian crises, the Turkish economy experienced a slowdown in 1998 with a 
growth rate of 3.1 per cent, and then contracted in 1999 at the rate of negative 3.4 per 
cent. Even though the economy was in boom in 2000 with a 7.3 per cent growth rate, the 
heaviest crisis of Turkey's recent history, mainly due to the major capital outflows, 
occurred in November 2000 and February 2001 when the GDP declined by 5.7 per cent in 
2001 in real terms (Tansel and Bodur, 2012). 
In terms of growth rates, the post-2001 period can be defined as the recovery period for 
Turkey. The real growth rate was 6.2 per cent in 2002 and the economy grew by 6 per cent 
on average until 2007 when the recent global economic crises first showed its effects on 
Turkey. On the other hand, in contrast to the fast growth performance across sectors, addi-
tional employment could not be generated. The rate of unemployment was 6.5 per cent in 
2000 and it increased to 10.4 per cent in 2002. The unemployment rate remained high and 
never fell below 10 per cent despite the rapid surges in the GDP and exports. This </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
observation is defined as jobless-growth in the literature, characterized by a contraction of 
formal jobs and increased informalization of economic activities (Telli et al., 2007; Yeldan,  2006). </p>

<p>3. Hypothesis and methodology </p>

<p>3.1 Hypothesis </p>

<p>In his seminal paper, Mincer (1974) proposed an earnings function in which wages are 
defined as a function of human capital, where individuals who make higher investment in 
human capital receive higher returns from the labour market. The wage function can 
accordingly be written as: </p>

<p>y i ¼ X i b þ e i ; 
ð1Þ </p>

<p>where y i is log wage of individual i, X i is the vector of individual characteristics that 
determine wages; b is the coefficient vector giving the marginal returns to the covariates in 
X i ; and e i is the random error term. The key individual characteristics that Mincer stressed 
were education (schooling) and experience (years in the labour market, including but not 
restricted to, on-the-job training). However, in subsequent empirical work vector X i has 
included a wide range of wage-determining characteristics. 
Although higher levels of education provide higher earnings at the individual level, an 
increase in the educational attainment of the whole population does not necessarily mean 
an increase in returns to education. Pritchett (2001) argued that the marginal return to 
adding an additional year of schooling in whole population can be substantially different 
from average returns estimated with a Mincerian regression at a single point in time 
depending on the shifts in skill demand; he asserted that marginal returns to education 
decrease as the supply of educated labour expands if the demand remains stagnant. 
In their seminal paper, Katz and Murphy (1992) analysed the changes in wage inequality 
in the United States during the 1963-87 period. Their results show that the college wage 
premium decreased in the 1971-79 period in which there was a large increase in the supply 
of college graduates. On the other hand, the college wage premium increased in the 1979-
87 period in which the growth of the supply of graduates was very small. Accordingly, they 
argued that, combined with the smooth increase in skill demand, the fluctuations in the 
growth of the supply of college graduates as a fraction of the labour force played an 
important role in explaining the large differences in the relative wages of college graduates 
between these two decades. Based on the findings of Pritchett (2001) and Katz and Mur- phy (1992), it can be argued that the education premium and wage inequality can increase 
or decrease depending on the differences between the relative growth rate of the supply 
and demand for the skills. 
Another important implication of estimating the Mincerian regression is that if the 
demand for skill increases, returns to the unmeasured human capital such as unobservable 
skills linked to school quality, intrinsic ability and effort, which are the main reasons why 
workers with the same level of education and experience have different wages, increase as 
well. In particular, the rate of increase in returns to unmeasured characteristics is greater 
for individuals who have more education. In econometric terms, residuals in Mincerian-
type equations are empirically heteroskedastic. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>Lemieux (2002) and Martins and Pereira (2004) also note that school quality differences 
are more likely to be prevalent at higher schooling levels, because those are the stages that 
exhibit greater heterogeneity in schooling paths and school quality. Moreover, differences 
in school quality and the variance of residuals increase even more dramatically if admis-
sions to schools get more selective at higher levels of education (as is in the case of Tur-
key). Therefore, changes in skill premiums affect wage inequality in two ways 
simultaneously; first, it affects the wage gap between workers with lower and higher educa-
tion levels which causes an increase in the between-group inequality component. Second, it 
affects the wage dispersion within workers who have the same level of education but stud-
ied at schools with different qualities, which causes an increase in the within-group inequal-
ity component. </p>

<p>7   The argument of technological changes leading to polarization in wages and jobs 
requires a distinction between skills and tasks. Based on the models proposed by Acemoglu  and Autor (2011) and Firpo et al. (2011), the tasks content of individual jobs can be deter-
mined by the occupations. These occupation-based task categories can then be incorpo-
rated in the standard Mincerian wage regressions to determine the impact of changes in 
the composition of these tasks categories and returns to them on wage distribution. In gen-
eral it is argued that routine tasks are more vulnerable to technological changes compared 
with non-routine tasks; this is due to the fact that routine tasks require repeated physical 
strength and motions which computer and machines can perform (Goos et al., 2014). Job 
polarization would require the share of workers in the routine jobs to fall and the share of 
workers in the non-routine jobs to increase. </p>

<p>3.2 Decomposition method </p>

<p>In our paper we do both an overall decomposition, also called the aggregate decomposi-
tion, and a detailed decomposition which looks at the contribution of different covariates 
to the overall change in the distribution of wages. 
The literature on decomposition of wage inequality goes back to the seminal papers of 
Oaxaca (1973) and Blinder (1973). In their models the change in average wage between 
two time periods can be decomposed into two components: (1) the 'explained' effect, 
which is the effect of changes in the distribution of covariates (also referred to as the com-
position effect); and (2) the 'unexplained' effect, which is the effect of changes in the 
regression coefficients (changes in the returns to the covariates), this is often also referred 
to as the 'wage structure' effect. 
Following the seminal work of Blinder and Oaxaca, various other decomposition meth-
ods have been developed over the last few decades. One of the methods is that proposed 
by Juhn et al. (1993, JMP hereafter) in which they extended the Blinder-Oaxaca decompo-
sition of the mean wages by taking the distribution of residuals into account. In the JMP 
framework the changes in the distribution over time can be decomposed into three compo-
nents: (1) changes in the distribution of observable covariates; (2) changes in the regression 
coefficients (returns to the observable covariates); and (3) changes in the distribution of 
residuals. However, the JMP decomposition does not account for changes in the distribu-
tion of covariates; their method thus ignores the problem of heteroscedasticity. 
For the aggregate decomposition we use the decomposition method proposed by 
Lemieux (2002), which unifies the residual imputation method proposed by JMP and the 
re-weighting factor method proposed by DiNardo et al. (1996). The Lemieux approach 
has several advantages compared with the other decomposition methods. First, like JMP it </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
allows for the decomposition of changes in the entire distribution of wages rather than the 
decomposition of the change in the mean wages only. Second, unlike JMP it accounts for 
distribution of covariates, therefore, it can account for the problem of heteroskedasticity. 
Finally, it is also possible to decompose the changes in the residual distribution into the 
effect of the changes in unobservable characteristics and the effect of changes in returns to 
those characteristics. This then allows us to test the hypothesis of the human capital 
approach which asserts that a positive change in returns to observable skills exerts a posi-
tive impact on returns to unobservable skills. 
Once we have the aggregate decomposition, to look at the contribution of different 
covariates we do a detailed decomposition, for this we use the recentered influence function 
(RIF ) regression method proposed by Firpo et al. (2009). This method is an extension of 
the Blinder-Oaxaca decomposition where in the first step we run a regression where the 
dependent variable, instead of being log wages, is RIF of the statistic of interest, say the 
s 
th -quantile (q s ) of the log wages, RIF ðy; q s Þ. Once the RIF regression has been estimated 
we can do a detailed decomposition, in a way similar to the Blinder-Oaxaca decomposi-
tion, for any distributional parameter. 
Full econometric specification of different decompositions that we use in our empirical 
analysis is provided in Appendix A. </p>

<p>3.3 Selection bias </p>

<p>By definition, wage estimations are performed for the individuals who have reported 
their wages. However, selection into wage-earning sector cannot be assumed as random, 
resulting in a selection bias. The consequence of ignoring this problem is that the estima-
tors of the wage regressions are biased (Heckman, 1979). 
According to TurkStat, nearly 30 per cent of working men in Turkey were self-employed 
in the year 2000. This share decreased to 23 per cent in 2010. The considerable share of 
self-employed is an indicator of non-random participation into the wage sector. The selec-
tion bias problem becomes even more crucial in wage estimations for women. Over the last 
50 years, Turkey's female labour force participation has been decreasing (Goksel, 2012). 
According to the Global Gender Gap Report 2013 (World Economic Forum, 2013), the 
female labour force participation rate in Turkey is 30 per cent and this ratio puts Turkey 
in the 123rd place out of 136 countries. Another problem that may cause selection bias is 
that there is a substantial share of unpaid family workers who traditionally work in the 
agricultural sector and are recorded as employed in employment statistics. According to 
TurkStat, for the year 2002, 49 per cent of total female employment consists of unpaid 
workers. However, these individuals do not report any form of labour income and so they 
are automatically omitted from the sample. Given the above issues we take into account 
the selection bias in our analysis. 
In the first step, following Dubin and McFadden (1984), a multinomial logit model is 
estimated separately for men and women. An individual i is characterized as having three 
options; these options are different for men and women. The sample of woman is grouped 
into following three categories: fw i ¼ 2 if working in the wage sector; fw i ¼ 1 if she is an 
unpaid family worker; and fw i ¼ 0 if she is economically inactive (non-participant). The 
categories for men are: fw i ¼ 2 if working in the wage sector; fw i ¼ 1 if self-employed; and 
fw i ¼ 0 if he is economically inactive (non-participant). The predicted probabilities from 
the multinomial logit model (estimated separately for men and women) are then used to 
construct a selection correction term, k ij , by using the formula provided by Hill (1983). </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>In the second step, augmented wage equations are estimated separately for men and 
women by including correction term as an additional regressor: </p>

<p>y ij ¼ X ij b j þ h j k ij þ e ij ; 
ð2Þ </p>

<p>where y ij is the log wage of individual i in sector j; X ij is the vector of sector specific indi-
vidual characteristics; b j is the vector of returns to characteristics in sector j; h j is the 
unknown coefficient related with the selection correction term; and e ij is the independent 
residual term. The augmented wage equation estimation results are then used in decompo-
sition of the change in wage distributions of men and women over time. 
Details of the estimation of the selection-corrected wage regressions, including the 
econometric specification of the multinomial logit model and how the correction term is 
estimated, are given in Appendix A. </p>

<p>4. Data </p>

<p>4.1 Sample selection </p>

<p>Data sources are the two waves of Household Labour Force Survey (LFS), which is con-
ducted by TurkStat, for the years 2002 and 2010. The LFS has the largest sample of Turk-
ish labour force and contains information on both the workers' demographic 
characteristics and characteristics of the main job for each individual within the house-
hold. </p>

<p>8   For our analysis we create two cross-sections of workers. The details of the exclusion cri-
terion used and the observations lost as a result are given in Table 1. The number of indi-
viduals surveyed by TurkStat increased between 2002 and 2010 (first row, 'full sample', 
Table 1). We exclude from our analysis all workers outside the ages of 20 and 64. 
9 We also 
drop from our analysis all those who are coded as students, ill, disabled and retired. As 
LFS does not provide any information on the wages that are earned from the second job, 
individuals who have more than one job are also dropped. A very small proportion of the 
women (men) are self-employed (unpaid family workers) so these are also dropped from 
the sample. The remaining observations are classified as economically inactive, self-
employed (only for men), unpaid family workers (only for women) and wage earners. 
Labour Force Survey contains information on net monthly wages. In order to get hourly 
wages, monthly wages are first divided by 4.3 and then divided by the usual hours of work 
per week. Finally, hourly wages are deflated by the consumer price index, which is pro-
vided by TurkStat, to obtain real hourly wages. </p>

<p>4.2 Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>Tables with the descriptive statistics of the variables for each sample year for women and 
men are presented in Appendix B (Tables B1 and B2). 
Wage-earning women are the most educated, with 40 per cent having a university educa-
tion in 2010. Unpaid family workers are the least educated, with a third of them having no 
formal education. Between 2002 and 2010 there has been a shift in the distribution of edu-
cation for the wage earners, with a fall in the wage earners with primary (high school) </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
education by 6 percentage points (4 percentage points), and an increase in the university 
educated women by 8 percentage points. Compared with other groups, wage-earning 
women are more likely to be heads of their household, more likely to come from house-
holds where other members of the household are also wage earners; and are less likely to 
have children present in the household. Women in unpaid work tend to come predomi-
nantly from rural households (where other members of the household are more likely to 
be self-employed). Although a majority of wage-earning women are younger than 35 years, 
economically inactive and unpaid worker group mainly consist of women who are older 
than 35. 
Wage-earning men are more educated relative to other two groups (economically inactive 
and self-employed). There has been a shift in the distribution of education between 2002 
and 2010, towards university-educated workers in the wage sector; the share of workers 
with primary education decreased by 8 percentage points, whereas the share of workers 
with a university degree increased by 5 percentage points. There is not much difference in 
the mean values of the variables that represent presence of children in the household 
between self-employed men and wage earning men; for the economically inactive men on 
the other hand values of these variables are smaller. Self-employed men have a high pro-
portion of other members of the household who do unpaid family work (possibly women </p>

<p>Table 1. Exclusion criterion for the sample </p>

<p>2002 
2010 </p>

<p>All 
Men 
Women 
All 
Men 
Women </p>

<p>Full sample 
300,689 146,836 153,853 522,171 255,053 267,118 
Exclusion observations 
Age over 64 or &lt;20 
135,422 
67,780 
67,642 227,112 112,765 114,347 
Students 
3,252 
1,969 
1,283 
6,190 
3,401 
2,789 
Disabled or ill 
2,838 
1,639 
1,199 
10,691 
4,678 
6,013 
Retired 
10,987 
8,249 
2,738 
18,426 
14,159 
4,267 
More than one job 
1,259 
1,148 
111 
4,747 
4,344 
403 
Employers 
5,370 
5,082 
288 
7,602 
7,032 
570 
Self-employed (women) 
2,552 
-
2,552 
5,835 
-
5,835 
Unpaid family workers (men) 
2,765 
2,765 
-
4,024 
4,024 
-
Sample for analysis </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>136,244 
58,204 
78,040 237,544 104,650 132,894 
% of the full sample 
45% 
40% 
51% 
45% 
41% 
50% 
Economically inactive </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>72,237 
11,426 
60,811 115,298 
17,704 
97,594 
(53%) 
(20%) 
(78%) 
(49%) 
(17%) 
(73%) 
Self-employed (men) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>14,007 
14,007 
-
23,869 
23,869 
-
(10%) 
(24%) 
-
(10%) 
(23%) 
-
Unpaid family workers (women) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7,787 
-
7,787 
15,220 
-
15,220 
(6%) 
-
(10%) 
(6%) 
-
(11%) 
Wage earners </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>42,213 
32,771 
9,442 
83,157 
63,077 
20,080 
(31%) 
(56%) 
(12%) 
(35%) 
(60%) 
(15%) 
Sample for wage equations </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>41,205 
32,039 
9,166 
77,701 
59,131 
18,570 </p>

<p>Notes: 
a This is the sample used in sample selection equation. 
b The % in the () are % of the sample for analysis. 
c Any further losses in observations from the row above (wage earners) are for following reasons: reported 
extreme values of experience (inconsistent with age); reported zero wage; and exclusion of Skilled agricul-
tural and fishery workers occupational category. We lose 212 observations in 2002 and 639 observations in 
2010 due to exclusion of this occupation. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>in the family). Self-employed men are the oldest group with 70 per cent of them over 
35 years old; on the other hand, more than half of the inactive and wage worker groups 
are younger than 35. 
From the descriptive statistics, it can be seen that the change in compulsory education 
system and the increasing number of universities caused a substantial change in the edu-
cational composition of wage workers (and workforce in general). The new education sys-
tem, which abolished the primary school and made secondary education compulsory, 
reduced the number of workers with only primary education for both men and women; 
whereas with the increasing accessibility of university education, the number of workers 
with a university degree increased for both genders. Based on these observations, it can 
be argued that the supply of educated labour in Turkey increased between 2002 and 
2010. 
To capture job polarization, following Goos et al. (2009), occupations are classified into 
three task categories: abstract, routine and service. Details of the occupation classifications 
used are given in Appendix B, Table B3. Women, relative to men are over represented in 
the abstract jobs, i.e., among professionals and technicians. This could be due to the selec-
tion process as only very high skilled women enter the labour force (40 per cent of the 
wage earning women have university education). Women are underrepresented in the rou-
tine jobs, such as plant and machine operators and assemblers. For both men and women, 
over time share of wage earners in abstract category has not changed; whereas the share of 
workers in the routine category has decreased. </p>

<p>4.3 Wage dynamics </p>

<p>Table 2 presents the wage dynamics for men and women over time. The mean log 
wages for both men and women have increased over time; with a higher increase in the 
mean wages of women. The mean wage for men is higher than the mean wage for women 
in 2002 and this relationship reverses in 2010. This observation does not necessarily imply 
positive discrimination towards women. For instance, using the Structure of Earnings Sur-
vey 2006 conducted by the TurkStat, Kaya (2010) shows that on average women earn 2.5 
percentage points more than men. She also argues that the higher average wage for 
women is a consequence of a composition effect as most of the female employees have a 
university degree, whereas male employees mostly have only primary education. By 
exploiting a quantile decomposition method, she finds that although the composition 
effect had a narrowing effect on the gender wage gap (favouring women), the effect of 
differences in the returns to characteristics had an increasing effect on the gender wage 
gap (favouring men) showing that the human capital characteristics of women are 
rewarded less than the characteristics of their male counterparts. Considering Kaya's  (2010) findings, the reversal of relative wages between men and women between 2002 and 
2010 can be explained by the higher increase in the share of university graduates among 
female wage workers. 
Wage inequality over this period decreased with a fall in inequality reflected in the fall 
in the 90-10 wage gap which has fallen by 21 per cent for women and almost 18 per cent 
for men. For both men and women, much of the fall in inequality has been in the lower 
tail of the distribution (the 50-10 wage gap), with inequality in the upper tail (90-50 wage 
gap) showing only a moderate decline. The changing pattern of inequality seems to be con-
sistent with the job polarization argument. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
5. Empirical results </p>

<p>5.1 Wage regressions </p>

<p>The first step in our empirical investigation is to look at the multinomial logit model for 
labour market status. 
10 Tables 3 and 4 show the relative risk ratios (RRR) from the maxi-
mum likelihood estimation of the multinomial logit model for women and men, respec-
tively. The omitted category in the model is the group of economically inactive men and 
women. The RRR tells us how the probability of choosing wage employment or unpaid 
family work (self-employment in the case of men) relative to being economically inactive 
changes if we increase the independent variable by one unit. If the RRR is &gt;1, it means 
that the individual is more likely to be in wage employment or unpaid family work (self-
employment for men) and accordingly, if it is lower than 1, the individual is more likely to 
be economically inactive. 
Table 3 shows that for women education at all levels increases the probability of choos-
ing wage employment. Having other members of the household in the wage sector, being 
head of the household and (for the year 2002) having a grandmother in the household also 
increases the probability of being in wage employment. The presence of children in the 
household aged 5 or less and between 5 and 11, being married, and presence of self-
employed members in the household all have a decreasing effect on wage employment. 
Table 4 shows that for men education at all levels, the presence of children in the house-
hold aged 5 or less, other members of the household in the wage sector, and being the 
head of the household increase the probability of choosing wage employment. Living in 
rural area and the presence of unpaid family workers in the household all increase the like-
lihood of being self-employed. For both men and women (Tables 3 and 4), the RRRs for 
educational categories are much smaller in 2010 than they were in 2002. This indicates that 
education does not increase the probability of being a wage worker (as opposed to being 
economically inactive) in 2010 as much as it did in 2002. 
To see the changes in the returns to the human capital characteristics the wage regres-
sions are estimated for each year, for men and women separately. The regression results 
(Table 5) show that the coefficients for the education variables decreased from 2002 to 
2010 for men and women. The percentage decrease is more at lower education levels than </p>

<p>Table 2. Wage dynamics </p>

<p>Mean log wages </p>

<p>Log wage differentials </p>

<p>90-10 
90-50 
50-10 </p>

<p>Women 
2002 
5.38 (0.91) 
2.169 
1.139 
1.030 
2010 
5.65 (0.78) 
1.792 
1.099 
0.693 
Total change 
0.27 
À0.377 
À0.041 
À0.336 
% 
5.0 
À21.1 
À3.7 
À48.5 
Men 
2002 
5.42 (0.80) 
1.902 
1.091 
0.811 
2010 
5.61 (0.67) 
1.617 
1.020 
0.597 
Total change 
0.19 
À0.285 
À0.071 
À0.214 
% 
3.5 
À17.6 
À6.9 
À35.8 </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>Table 3. Relative risk ratios (women) </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Unpaid family 
worker </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Unpaid family 
worker </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Education 
Primary school 
1.10 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1.74 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.30 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.56 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.05) 
(0.11) 
(0.04) 
(0.06) 
Secondary school 
0.68 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>3.01 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.20 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.42 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.09) 
(0.23) 
(0.07) 
(0.11) 
High school 
0.66 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>5.54 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.92 
4.21 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.08) 
(0.38) 
(0.08) 
(0.18) 
Vocational high school 
0.69 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>8.13 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.92 
5.41 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.13) 
(0.60) 
(0.09) 
(0.24) 
University 
1.13 
33.58 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.85 
21.26 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.26) 
(2.38) 
(0.10) 
(0.90) 
Presence of children in the household 
Age ≤4 
0.69 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.03) 
(0.02) 
(0.02) 
(0.01) 
5 ≤ Age &lt; 11 
0.97 
0.81 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.98 
0.76 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.02) 
11 ≤ Age &lt; 15 
0.88 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.99 
0.92 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1.02 
(0.04) 
(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
Other members of the household 
Presence of wage workers 
0.72 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.08 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.63 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.04) 
(0.07) 
(0.03) 
(0.04) 
Presence of self-employed 
14.23 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.85 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>12.21 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.80) 
(0.05) 
(0.42) 
(0.03) 
Presence of unpaid family workers 
4.91 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.88 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.23) 
(0.08) 
(0.18) 
(0.05) 
Marital status 
Married 
1.31 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.70 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.10) 
(0.02) 
(0.10) 
(0.01) 
Divorced 
0.37 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.99 
0.55 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.39 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.13) 
(0.09) 
(0.09) 
(0.08) 
Widowed 
0.47 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.85 
0.40 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.08) 
(0.04) 
(0.11) 
(0.03) 
Age 
25-35 
1.57 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.53 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.82 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.55 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.11) 
(0.07) 
(0.11) 
(0.05) 
35-45 
1.81 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.44 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.74 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.72 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.14) 
(0.07) 
(0.17) 
(0.07) 
45-65 
1.80 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.51 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.62 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.14) 
(0.04) 
(0.16) 
(0.03) 
Head of household dummy 
0.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.56 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.01) 
(0.13) 
(0.03) 
(0.07) 
Grandmother 
1.67 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.20 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.26 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.07 
(0.11) 
(0.08) 
(0.06) 
(0.05) 
Rural 
9.70 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.00 
8.16 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.88 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.41) 
(0.04) 
(0.24) 
(0.03) 
Constant 
0.00 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.00) 
(0.01) 
(0.00) 
(0.01) 
Observations 
7,787 
9,442 
15,220 
20,080 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors are reported in (). *** p &lt; 0.01, ** p &lt; 0.05, * p &lt; 0.1. Omitted category: econom-
ically inactive. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
Table 4. Relative risk ratios (men) </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Self-employed Wage worker Self-employed Wage worker </p>

<p>Education 
Primary school 
1.35 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.10 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.19 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.58 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.09) 
(0.14) 
(0.06) 
(0.07) 
Secondary school 
1.39 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>3.23 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.22 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.11) 
(0.23) 
(0.08) 
(0.10) 
High school 
1.19 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>3.67 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.09 
2.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.10) 
(0.26) 
(0.07) 
(0.11) 
Vocational high school 
0.90 
4.27 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.15 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>3.31 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.08) 
(0.32) 
(0.08) 
(0.17) 
University 
0.63 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.96 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>3.96 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.36) 
(0.05) 
(0.19) 
Presence of children in the household 
Age ≤ 4 
0.99 
0.96 
1.00 
1.02 
(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
5 ≤ Age &lt; 11 
0.90 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.93 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.92 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.00 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.02) 
11 ≤ Age &lt; 15 
0.90 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.95 
0.92 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.96 
(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.02) 
Other members of the household 
Presence of wage workers 
0.68 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.43 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.73 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.30 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.03) 
(0.04) 
(0.02) 
(0.03) 
Presence of self-employed 
0.17 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.83 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.99 
(0.02) 
(0.04) 
(0.02) 
(0.03) 
Presence of unpaid family workers 
23.91 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.06 
25.43 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.35 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(1.74) 
(0.08) 
(1.31) 
(0.07) 
Marital status 
Married 
2.19 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.06 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.19) 
(0.10) 
(0.14) 
(0.08) 
Divorced 
1.32 
1.13 
1.28 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1.01 
(0.24) 
(0.15) 
(0.14) 
(0.08) 
Widowed 
1.62 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.96 
2.42 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.05 
(0.30) 
(0.18) 
(0.41) 
(0.18) 
Age 
25-35 
2.33 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.62 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.72 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.46 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.20) 
(0.07) 
(0.20) 
(0.05) 
35-45 
2.85 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.35 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>3.69 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.20 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.27) 
(0.07) 
(0.29) 
(0.05) 
45-65 
3.03 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.00 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.62 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.29) 
(0.04) 
(0.31) 
(0.03) 
Head of household dummy 
2.71 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.53 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.39 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>2.13 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.19) 
(0.11) 
(0.11) 
(0.07) 
Rural 
1.66 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>1.63 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.02) 
(0.05) 
(0.02) 
Constant 
0.07 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.01) 
(0.02) 
(0.00) 
(0.03) 
Observations 
14,007 
32,771 
23,869 
63,007 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors are reported in (). *** p &lt; 0.01, ** p &lt; 0.05, * p &lt; 0.1. Omitted category: econom-
ically inactive. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>Table 5. Wage regression estimations </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>2002 
2010 
2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Education 
Primary school 
0.04 
À0.09 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.00 
(0.05) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.01) 
Secondary school 
0.10 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>À0.02 
0.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.01) 
High school 
0.25 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.01) 
Vocational high school 
0.18 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.01 
0.45 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.06) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.01) 
University 
0.56 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.79 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.07) 
(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.02) 
Tenure 
0.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.00) 
(0.00) 
(0.00) 
(0.00) 
Tenure squared (10 </p>

<p>À3 </p>

<p>) 
À0.51 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.76 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.77 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.29 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.11) 
(0.06) 
(0.06) 
(0.03) 
Presence of children in the household 
Age ≤ 4 
0.06 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.02 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>À0.01 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.00) 
5 ≤ Age &lt; 11 
À0.02 
0.01 
À0.02 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>À0.02 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.00) 
11 ≤ Age &lt; 15 
À0.03 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>À0.03 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.02 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>À0.03 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
Marital status dummies 
Married 
0.11 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
Divorced 
0.08 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>À0.01 
0.04 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>(0.04) 
(0.02) 
(0.05) 
(0.02) 
Widowed 
0.13 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0.04 
À0.06 
0.09 
(0.05) 
(0.03) 
(0.10) 
(0.06) 
Age 
25-35 
0.12 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
35-45 
0.16 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.02) 
(0.01) 
45-65 
0.21 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.04) 
(0.02) 
(0.02) 
(0.01) 
Member of social security system 
0.55 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
Occupational categories 
Service 
0.16 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.01 
À0.05 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>À0.07 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.03) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
Abstract 
0.43 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.03) 
(0.02) 
(0.01) 
(0.01) 
Λ (selection term) 
0.15 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.04) 
(0.03) 
(0.03) 
(0.02) 
Constant 
3.79 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.81 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.06 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>4.88 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>(0.09) 
(0.05) 
(0.06) 
(0.03) 
Industry dummies 
YES 
YES 
YES 
YES 
Observations 
9,166 
18,570 
32,039 
59,131 
R-squared 
0.61 
0.63 
0.49 
0.56 </p>

<p>Notes: Robust standard errors are reported in (). *** p &lt; 0.01, ** p &lt; 0.05, * p &lt; 0.1. Details of the industry 
dummies used are given in Appendix B, Table B4. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
at higher education levels. For example, although returns to high school education for 
women (men) decreased by 76 per cent (65 per cent) over time, considering 2002 as the 
base year, the returns to university education decreased by 51 per cent (36 per cent). The 
coefficient for the abstract dummy is positive for both men and women; compared with the 
base category of routine workers, workers in the occupations classified as abstract earn 
more, ceteris paribus. For women, however, the premium of being in abstract jobs has fal-
len over time. The coefficient for the service dummy is negative (except for the 2002 female 
sample) showing that workers in the service group earn less than the workers in the routine 
occupations, ceteris paribus. For men, there has been no change in the returns to service 
sector jobs, whereas for women these returns have fallen over time. 
According to the wage regression results, compared with the base category of never mar-
ried, being married has a positive effect on wages. Also, working in the formal sector 
(which is captured by the membership of social security system) has a positive effect on 
wages. The coefficient for the selection term is positive for men and women and statistically 
significant in each year, which means that the unobservable factors that affect selection 
into wage employment are positively correlated with the unobservable factors that affect 
wages. 
The descriptive statistics and the regression results show that composition of the wage 
earners and returns to their characteristics changed significantly over time. However, it is 
not possible to see to what extent these changes were responsible for the changes in the 
wage distribution without decomposing the changes in wage inequality. </p>

<p>5.2 Decompositions </p>

<p>Table 6 reports the results of the aggregate decomposition using the method proposed 
by Lemieux. Looking at the 90-10 wage gap columns, for both men and women, the 
decomposition results indicate that the systematic part of the wage equation (sum of the 
covariate and the coefficient effects) explains about 58 and 55 per cent of the fall in </p>

<p>Table 6. Aggregate decomposition of changes in wage distribution </p>

<p>Inequality measure </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>90-10 
90-50 
50-10 
90-10 
90-50 
50-10 </p>

<p>2002 
2.169 
1.139 
1.030 
1.902 
1.091 
0.811 
2010 
1.792 
1.099 
0.693 
1.617 
1.020 
0.597 
Total change % 
À0.377 
À0.041 
À0.336 
À0.285 
À0.071 
À0.214 
(À21.1) 
(À3.7) 
(À48.5) 
(À17.6) 
(À6.9) 
(À35.8) 
Effect of coefficients 
À0.174 
0.003 
À0.178 
À0.121 
À0.031 
À0.091 
(À46.2) 
(8.5) 
(À52.9) 
(À42.7) 
(À43.0) 
(À42.5) 
Pricing function 
À0.099 
À0.080 
À0.019 
À0.141 
À0.065 
À0.075 
(À26.2) 
(À196.0) 
(À5.6) 
(À49.4) 
(À92.3) 
(À35.2) 
Covariates 
À0.046 
À0.020 
À0.026 
À0.034 
0.016 
À0.050 
(À12.3) 
(À50.1) 
(À7.7) 
(À12.1) 
(22.2) 
(À23.4) 
Unexplained 
À0.058 
0.056 
À0.114 
0.012 
0.009 
0.002 
(À15.3) 
(137.6) 
(À33.9) 
(4.1) 
(13.1) 
(1.1) </p>

<p>Notes: Table presents results from the Lemieux (2002) decomposition. 
Percentage shares of each effect in total change are shown in parentheses. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>inequality for women and men, respectively. Changes in returns to the observed character-
istics (effect of coefficients) had a substantial share in explaining the decreasing inequality 
both at the upper tail (90-50 gap) and the lower tail (50-10 gap) of the wage distribution 
for men. For women, however, the changes in the coefficients was inequality increasing at 
the upper tail, and inequality decreasing in the lower half of the wage distribution. 
The effect of covariates, for men, is inequality increasing in the upper tail but inequality 
decreasing in the lower tail of the wage distribution. For women, the effect of covariates is 
negative and relatively small in the lower tail of the distribution but larger in the top tail 
of the wage distribution. Part of the explanation for the differences in these findings for 
men and women could be due to the fact that the proportion of women with university 
education (who are more likely to be in the upper tail) working in the wage sector is much 
higher than the proportion of men in the wage sector with university education. A further 
increase in the supply of educated women dampens the returns to them, whereas for men it 
does not. 
For women, around 26 per cent of the fall in inequality is explained by returns to the 
unmeasured characteristics (pricing function), this rises to almost 50 per cent for men. The 
pricing function has a considerable share in explaining the declining inequality at the top 
end of the distribution, whereas the size of this effect is found to be relatively small in the 
lower tail of the distribution, for both men and women. 
Table 7 presents the decomposition of changes in wage residuals. The skill pricing func-
tion explains almost all of the variation in the change in dispersion of wage residuals in 
the top half of the distribution; and almost 80-90 per cent of the variation in the bottom 
part of the distribution. This provides evidence that decreasing returns to human capital 
were accompanied by a decrease in pricing function of unmeasured characteristics. 
Next we do the detailed decomposition using the method proposed by Firpo et al.  (2009); the results are presented in Table 8; Panel A reports the aggregate decomposition 
and Panels B and C report the detailed composition and coefficient effects, respectively, for 
the main factors: education, experience (age dummies, tenure, 
11 and tenure square) and the 
occupational categories (routine, service and abstract). </p>

<p>12   From Panel A we can see that, for both men and women, there is a bigger fall in 
inequality in the bottom half (50-10) of the wage distribution and most of this is explained 
by the coefficient effect. For women, the covariate (composition) effect is negative and </p>

<p>Table 7. Decomposition of changes in wage residuals </p>

<p>Inequality measure </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>90-10 
90-50 
50-10 
90-10 
90-50 
50-10 </p>

<p>2002 
1.262 
0.646 
0.616 
1.270 
0.652 
0.618 
2010 
1.047 
0.514 
0.534 
1.031 
0.523 
0.509 
Total change % 
À0.215 
À0.132 
À0.082 
À0.239 
À0.130 
À0.109 
(À20.5) 
(À25.7) 
(À15.5) 
(À23.2) 
(À24.9) 
(À21.4) 
Effect of covariates 
À0.002 
0.009 
À0.006 
À0.015 
À0.003 
À0.018 
(À1.1) 
(6.5) 
(À7.4) 
(À6.4) 
(À2.2) 
(À16.7) 
Pricing function 
À0.217 
À0.141 
À0.076 
À0.224 
À0.133 
À0.091 
(À98.9) 
(À106.5) 
(À92.6) 
(À93.6) 
(À97.8) 
(À83.3) </p>

<p>Notes: Table presents results from the Lemieux (2002) decomposition. 
Percentage shares of each effect in total change are shown in parentheses. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
relatively more effective in the top half of the distribution; for men, the total composition 
effect is positive (inequality increasing) on the top half of the distribution and negative 
(inequality decreasing) in the bottom of the distribution. This is consistent with the 
Lemieux decomposition results. </p>

<p>13   In Panel B of Table 8 we have detailed composition effect. Overall the changes in the 
composition of educated workers, where there are more of them in the labour market, has </p>

<p>Table 8. Detailed decomposition of changes in wage distribution </p>

<p>Inequality measure </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>90-10 
90-50 
50-10 
90-10 
90-50 
50-10 </p>

<p>Panel A: Aggregate decomposition 
2002 
2.151 
1.160 
0.991 
1.874 
1.092 
0.782 
2010 
1.808 
1.152 
0.656 
1.632 
1.038 
0.594 
Total change 
À0.344 
À0.008 
À0.335 
À0.241 
À0.054 
À0.188 
% change 
À16.0 
À0.7 
À33.9 
À12.9 
À4.9 
À24.0 
Composition effect 
À0.042 
À0.023 
À0.020 
À0.012 
0.036 
À0.048 
(À12.3) 
(À269.0) 
(À5.9) 
(À4.9) 
(67.3) 
(À25.6) 
Specification error 
À0.014 
À0.001 
À0.013 
0.034 
À0.011 
0.045 
(À4.1) 
(À8.9) 
(À4.0) 
(14.0) 
(À21.1) 
(24.0) 
Coefficient effect 
À0.244 
0.030 
À0.274 
À0.258 
À0.075 
À0.182 
(À70.9) 
(354.0) 
(À81.5) 
(À106.8) 
(À140.5) 
(À97.1) 
Reweighting error 
À0.044 
À0.015 
À0.029 
À0.005 
À0.003 
À0.002 
(À12.7) 
(À176.2) 
(À8.6) 
(À2.3) 
(À5.6) 
(À1.3) </p>

<p>Panel B: Detailed composition effect: Main factors 
Education 
0.038 
À0.014 
0.052 
0.052 
0.027 
0.025 
(10.9) 
(À168.2) 
(15.4) 
(21.7) 
(50.2) 
(13.6) 
Experience 
À0.018 
0.002 
À0.020 
À0.017 
0.009 
À0.026 
(À5.3) 
(25.6) 
(À6.0) 
(À7.2) 
(16.1) 
(À13.8) 
Occupation categories 
Routine 
0.003 
À0.002 
0.005 
0.002 
0.001 
0.001 
(0.9) 
(À26.5) 
(1.6) 
(1.0) 
(2.7) 
(0.4) 
Service 
À0.007 
À0.004 
À0.003 
À0.002 
À0.001 
0.000 
(À2.1) 
(À45.4) 
(À1.0) 
(À0.7) 
(À2.6) 
(À0.2) 
Abstract 
À0.001 
0.000 
À0.001 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
(À0.2) 
(À1.1) 
(À0.2) 
(0.2) 
(0.6) 
(0.1) </p>

<p>Panel C: Detailed coefficient effect: Main factors 
Education 
À0.042 
0.046 
À0.088 
0.001 
À0.006 
0.007 
(À12.2) 
(544.7) 
(À26.2) 
(0.6) 
(À10.6) 
(3.8) 
Experience 
À0.055 
0.201 
À0.256 
À0.069 
0.123 
À0.192 
(À15.9) 
(2,509.2) 
(À76.3) 
(À28.7) 
(227.1) 
(À102.0) 
Occupation categories 
Routine 
À0.042 
À0.015 
À0.027 
0.012 
À0.021 
0.034 
(À12.3) 
(À181.2) 
(À8.1) 
(5.1) 
(À39.8) 
(18.0) 
Service 
0.099 
0.002 
0.097 
À0.016 
0.000 
À0.016 
(28.6) 
(23.5) 
(28.8) 
(À6.7) 
(À0.2) 
(À8.5) 
Abstract 
0.009 
0.031 
À0.022 
0.002 
0.012 
À0.011 
(2.6) 
(365.6) 
(À6.5) 
(0.7) 
(22.9) 
(À5.6) </p>

<p>Notes: Table presents results from the Firpo et al. (2009) decomposition. 
Percentage shares of each effect in total change are shown in parentheses. 
Education: Primary school, secondary school, high school, vocational high school and university. 
Experience: age dummies, tenure, tenure square. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>been inequality increasing. The only exception is the top tail of the wage distribution for 
women. So, although it seems that for women, holding the returns to education constant, 
an increase in the educational qualification lowers difference between the workers who 
are in the top end of the distribution and those who are around the median of the distribu-
tion, the same cannot be said for men. This could be as women have had much big-
ger gains in university education relative to men. Composition effect of experience has 
been inequality decreasing for both men and women in the lower tail of the distribution 
but inequality increasing in the upper tail. Changes in the composition of workers in differ-
ent occupation-based task categories contribute very little to the overall changes in 
inequality. 
Most of the change in inequality has happened in the bottom half of the distribution; the 
inequality has fallen in the top half but very little. Focusing on the bottom half (50-10), here 
most of the decrease in inequality is attributed to the coefficient effect, which explains more 
than 80 per cent of the fall in inequality for women and almost 97 per cent of the fall in 
inequality for men. Looking at the detailed coefficient effect, for women much of this is due 
to fall in returns to education and experience, which together explain almost all of the fall in 
inequality in the bottom tail; followed by changes in the returns to routine occupations which 
explain 8 per cent of the fall in inequality. For men, returns to education and returns to rou-
tine tasks are inequality increasing in the bottom tail of the distribution. Much of the 
decrease in inequality for men is explained by the changes in returns to experience. </p>

<p>6. Conclusion </p>

<p>This paper investigates the decrease in wage inequality observed in Turkey between 2002 
and 2010, by looking at the relationship between the distribution of wages and the educa-
tional attainment of the workforce. To understand the factors behind the changes in the 
wage distribution we do an aggregate decomposition using the Lemieux (2002) method, 
which allows us to look at the residuals, and a detailed decpomposition using the Firpo  et al. (2009) method. 
The results of the analysis show that the increasing supply of educated labour, which is 
attributed to the increase in the number of universities and the reform in the education 
system which increased the years of compulsory education, had a substantial effect on the 
wage distribution in Turkey between 2002 and 2010. As a result of the increase in supply, the 
wage inequality decreased in both the top and the bottom half of the wage distribution. The 
decrease in wage inequality was relatively low in the top half of the wage distribution, with 
most of the decline being concentrated in the lower half of the wage distribution. 
Using the decomposition methodology proposed by Lemieux, it is found that the 
decreasing wage inequality observed in Turkey between 2002 and 2010 was mainly due to 
two factors: (1) the decreasing between group inequality which is related to decreasing 
coefficients for education, a finding confirmed by the Firpo et al. decomposition; and (2)  the decreasing within-group inequality due to decreasing skill pricing function of unmea-
sured skills. The second finding is in accordance with the skill price theory of Lemieux  (2002) who argued that negative changes in the coefficient component exerts a negative 
impact on the residual component along the wage distribution, providing a measure for 
unmeasured skills pricing. Substantial change in skill pricing function may be linked to 
high-quality differences between universities. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
Using the Firpo et al. detailed decomposition we find that for women much of the 
decrease in inequality in the lower tail is explained by the coefficient effect with falling 
returns to education and experience explaining almost all of the fall in inequality. For 
men, the fall in inequality in the bottom tail is mainly explained by the changing returns 
to experience. We also look at job polarization: there is little role for it in the composition 
effect. In the coefficient effect, changes in the returns to routine tasks explain the fall in 
inequality in the upper tail of the wage distribution for both men and women. This is con-
trary to what we expect from the job polarization hypothesis. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>1 The impact of institutional factors such as, unionization, minimum wages and collective bargain-
ing practices, on the wage distribution has also been investigated (Lee, 1999; Card et al., 2003). 
2 The task content of work is determined at the occupational level, making occupation a key chan-
nel via which technology affects the wage structure (Firpo et al., 2011). 
3 The authors use the DiNardo et al. (1996) and Juhn et al. (1993) decomposition methods. 
4 Turkish education system was reformed again in 2012 and a more complex system known as the 
'4+4+4 system' has been adopted. 
5 For instance, there was a requirement for academics to 'serve' in outer areas before being pro-
moted. Today, there is a salary supplement to provide incentives for people to work in universities in 
the outer areas. 
6 There is also teaching quality differences between high schools in Turkey. Apart from vocational 
high schools, there are three different types of public high schools in Turkey, namely science high 
schools, Anatolian high schools and general high schools which have different levels of selectiveness 
in their admissions. 
7 Card and Krueger (1992) provided evidence that men who are educated at higher quality schools 
have higher return to an additional year of schooling; and returns are also higher for individuals who 
studied with better educated teachers. 
8 Previous studies on Turkey have used HBS. The main aim of HBS is to collect consumption and 
expenditure information, although it has some information on the labour market. LFS has numerous 
advantages over HBS: in particular, it has a much wider coverage and more observations which allow 
us to look at women, who are underrepresented in the labour market; all the national statistics are 
based on LFS, and these are used for policy analysis; and lastly, the main aim of LFS, unlike HBS, 
is to look at the labour market. 
9 The reason of choosing this age band is that decision to pursue higher education is endogenous 
as it depends on the returns to higher education. However, individuals who are at the age of 20 or 
older are likely to have already made their educational decisions. We exclude those above 64, as that 
is when the retirement decisions are made. 
10 Selection procedure requires the availability of valid instruments, i.e., variables which affect the 
labour market status but do not affect wages. For identification the following variables are included 
in the multinomial logit model. Three dummies to capture the labour market status of other members 
of the household: presence of wage workers, presence of self-employed and presence of unpaid family 
workers in the household; a dummy for the head of the household; a dummy for whether the worker 
lives in rural or urban area; and finally, only for women, whether or not there is a grandmother pre-
sent in the household. Justification for using these variables, along with the full econometric specifi-
cation, is discussed in Appendix A of the paper. 
11 Tenure is obtained by using the question 'year that you started your latest job/occupation'. 
12 Detailed decomposition for all other variables used in the wage regression is available on request 
from the authors. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>13 The Lemieux decomposition method decomposes the change in the observed (actual) gap; 
whereas the Firpo et al. decomposition method decomposes the predicted gap. 
14 Unless the number of observations are equal in the two periods, it is not possible to match resid-
uals exactly. Lemieux (2002) suggested a solution to this problem. His idea is to discretize the distri-
bution of residuals in h intervals which contain the same number of observations and replace the 
actual residuals by the average residual in each interval. In this analysis h is chosen as 500. 
15 We use selection correction in both the wage regressions underlying Lemeiux decomposition and the 
RIF regressions underlying the Firpo et al. decomposition. This is done to ensure consistency of analysis 
and results across the two decomposition methods. As a robustness check analysis was done without selec-
tion correction for the male sample, the results were qualitatively similar to those presented in the paper. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>



<p>
© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>



<p>Appendix A Econometric specification </p>

<p>1. Decompositions </p>

<p>1.1 Lemieux (2002) </p>

<p>Consider the wage determination equation for period t: </p>

<p>y it ¼ X it b t þ u it ; 
[A1] </p>

<p>where y it is the log wage of individual i at time period t; X it is the vector representing skills 
(human capital), tasks (based on occupations) and other individual characteristics; b t is 
the vector of estimated coefficients for returns to all elements in X it ; and u it is the regres-
sion residual. There is a similar wage determination equation for period s. 
The decomposition method developed by Lemieux (2002) unifies the residual imputation 
method proposed by Juhn et al. (1993; JMP hereafter) and the re-weighting factor method </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
proposed by DiNardo et al. (1996; DFL hereafter). As a first step, for the Lemieux decom-
position, we estimate a separate wage regression for each period (t and s) as given by equa-
tion [A1]. To compute the effect of changes in the prices of characteristics, following JMP, 
we construct a counterfactual wage vector that would prevail in period s (the base year; in 
our empirical analysis s ¼ 2002) if the price of human capital were the same as they were 
in period t (in our empirical analysis t ¼ 2010). To get the counterfactual wage vector, the 
coefficients from period s wage regression are replaced with coefficients from period t such 
as: </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is ¼ X is b t þ u is : 
[A2] </p>

<p>Once the counterfactual wages y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is are constructed, we can obtain the share of effect of 
changes in prices in total change in wage distribution by comparing any inequality measure 
(such as percentile wage gaps) for y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is and empirical wages for period s (y is ). 
The second step of the method is to estimate the re-weighting factor which will then be 
used to modify the original sample weights and calculate the effect of changes in covari-
ates. The concept of modifying sample weights, which are used to calculate sample statis-
tics representative of the population, was originally proposed by DFL. This method 
attaches a new counterfactual weight to each individual to keep the distribution of charac-
teristics constant and thereby makes it possible to account for changes in covariates. Their 
idea is to pool the samples of two periods and estimate a logit or probit model for the 
probability of being in the base year, using the same covariates as in the wage regression. 
The re-weighting function is defined as: </p>

<p>w i ¼ 
1 À P is 
P is </p>

<p>P s 
1 À P s 
; 
[A3] </p>

<p>where P is ¼ Prðperiod ¼ sjx is Þ is the predicted probability that an individual in the pooled 
sample comes from the base year s conditional on covariates; and P s is the unconditional 
probability that the observation is in period s. The new sample weights are then computed 
by multiplying the original sample weights for period s (w is ) with the re-weighting factor: 
w </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is ¼ w i w i . Following Lemieux (2002) notation, the counterfactual values of wages that 
can be generated by using the new sample weights are summarized in Table A1. 
The difference between the distributional statistics (e.g. percentile wage gaps) of y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is and 
y is (both using the original sample weights) gives the coefficient effect. This corresponds to 
the comparison of the distributions presented in the second and the first rows of the 
Table A1. On the other hand, the distribution statistics that are calculated by using y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is and 
the new re-weighted sample weights, w </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is , contain the effect of covariates as well as the coef-
ficients. Accordingly, the covariates effect is calculated as the difference between the distri-
butional statistics that are obtained by using y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is with the original sample weights w is and 
y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is with the new sample weights w </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is . This corresponds to the comparison of the distribu-
tions presented in the fourth and the second rows of Table A1. 
The final stage of the decomposition is to calculate the effect of changes in the residuals 
on the change in the wage distribution between the two periods; here Lemieux (2002) uses 
the residual imputation method which is provided by JMP. Consider the following linear 
form of the model for wage residuals: </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>u is ¼ p s g is þ e is ; </p>

<p>[A4] </p>

<p>where g is is the unmeasured human capital, p s is the return to the unmeasured human capi-
tal and e is is a random error term not linked with skills. Then, the variance of residuals 
can be calculated as: </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s ¼ p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g;s þ r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e;s ; </p>

<p>where r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g;s ¼ Varðg is Þ and r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e;s ¼ Varðe is Þ. In this model, with the assumption that the distribu-
tion of unmeasured skills is constant (r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g;s ¼ r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g;s ¼ r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g ), and r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>e;s is zero or stable over time, 
changes in skill prices are the only source of any change in residual wage inequality: </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t À r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s ¼ ðp </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>t À p </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>s Þr </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g : </p>

<p>The main disadvantage of this form (equation [A4]) is that the residuals are assumed to 
be a linear function of unmeasured skills. To understand the effect changes in unmeasured 
human capital prices have on wage distribution, JMP propose a more general setting in 
which a non-linear pricing scheme is applied: </p>

<p>u is ¼ p s ðg is Þ þ e is ; 
[A5] </p>

<p>where p s ðÁÞ is a monotonic and continuous function; and for simplicity e is is assumed to be 
zero. 
The JMP model, as given in equation [A5], is more general compared with the form in equa-
tion [A4] as it provides more flexibility by making it possible to generate any distribution of u is 
from an arbitrary distribution of skills g is . For instance, assume without loss of generality, that 
the g is follows a uniform distribution over the interval of ½0; 1: g is ¼ F s ðu is Þ; where F s ðÁÞ is the 
cumulative distribution function of u is . Following which equation [A5] can be written as: </p>

<p>u is ¼ p s ðg is Þ ¼ F </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>s ðu is Þ; </p>

<p>where g is can be interpreted as the rank of observation i in the distribution of residuals, 
whereas the non-linear skill pricing function p s ðÁÞ is the inverse cumulative distribution of u is . 
Using the skill pricing function, the counterfactual wages in equation [A2] can be rewritten as: </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is ¼ X is b t þ u is ¼ X is b t þ p s ðg is Þ: 
[A6] </p>

<p>The decomposition is finalized by replacing the residuals in period s with the residuals 
that would prevail if the skill pricing function was p t ðÁÞ instead of p s ðÁÞ such that: </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is ¼ X is b t þ p t ðg is Þ ¼ X is b t þ u </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>is ; 
[A7] </p>

<p>where u </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>is ¼ p t ðg is Þ ¼ F </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>t F s ðu is Þ is the counterfactual residual for the observation i. To com-
pute the counterfactual residuals, JMP suggest the following procedure: first, the rank 
g is ¼ F s ðu is Þ is computed from the empirical residual distribution in period s and then the 
residual at the same rank in the residual distribution in period t is picked. </p>



<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
The obtained counterfactual wages now can be used to decompose the changes in wage 
inequality. Extending JMP, they can also be combined with counterfactual weights to con-
trol for the distribution of covariates. In addition, having the counterfactual wage vectors, 
it is also possible to calculate any measure of inequality to see the effects of different fac-
tors on different parts of wage distribution. 
Last but not the least an important feature of this decomposition method is that it is 
also possible to decompose the changes in wage residuals. As sample weights are used to 
calculate indices that are representing the population, comparison of variances of residual 
wages using the original sample weights and counterfactual weights provides information 
about how much of the change in residual distribution is due to the change in covariates 
and the change in the skill pricing function. </p>

<p>1.2 Firpo, Fortin and Lemieux (2009)   To get the detailed decomposition we estimate the Re-centred Influence Function (RIF) 
regression, proposed by Firpo et al. (2009). The RIF for the s-quantile (q s ) of log wages y t , 
at time t, is given as (to keep notation simple we suppress the index i for the individual): </p>

<p>RIF ðy t ; q s Þ ¼ q s þ ½s À d t;s =f Y t ðq s Þ; 
[A8] </p>

<p>where f Y t ðq s Þis the density distribution function of y t computed at the quantile q s and d t ; 
is the dummy variable taking value one if y t q s and zero otherwise. 
Following Fortin et al. (2011) we assume RIF to be a linear function of covariates in 
vector x t , such that: </p>

<p>RIF ðy t ; q s Þ ¼ X t b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t þ u t ; 
[A9] </p>

<p>where b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t is the vector of coefficients for the s-quantile. Equation [A9] is also referred to as 
the unconditional quantile regression; it is estimated for each year, t and s.The changes in 
the s-quantile can then be decomposed as: </p>

<p>q s;t À q s;s ¼ 
X t b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t À 
X s b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>s ¼ ð 
X t À 
X s Þb </p>

<p>s 
s </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>composition effect </p>

<p>þ 
X s ðb </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t À b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>s Þ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>coefficient effect </p>

<p>: 
[A10] </p>

<p>The first term on the right hand side of equation [A10] reflects the change in the distri-
bution of observed covariates (composition effect), and the second term reflects the 
changes in the regression coefficients (returns to the observed covariates). Equation [A10] </p>

<p>Table A1. Counterfactual distributions </p>

<p>Variable 
Weight 
Resulting distribution </p>

<p>y is 
w is 
Distribution at period s 
y </p>

<p>a 
is </p>

<p>w is 
Distribution at period s with b of period t 
y is 
w </p>

<p>a 
is </p>

<p>Distribution at period s with covariates of period t 
y </p>

<p>a 
is </p>

<p>w </p>

<p>a 
is </p>

<p>Distribution at period s with covariates and b of period t </p>

<p>Notes: The base year is s:w is are the original sample weights from the year s. 
w </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>is ¼ w i w i are the counterfactual weights, where w i is the re-weighting factor. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>can then be used to obtain the detailed decomposition, similar to the Blinder-Oxaca 
method, such as: </p>

<p>q s;t À q s;s ¼ </p>

<p>X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>ðx k;t À x k;s Þ b b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>k;s þ </p>

<p>X K </p>

<p>k¼1 </p>

<p>x k;t ð b b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>k;t À b b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>k;s Þ; 
[A11] </p>

<p>where x k;t is the mean of the k 
th component of the vector X t , and b b </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>k;t is the corresponding 
coefficient. 
The RIF regressions can be biased as the assumption of linearity (equation [A9]) 
holds true only locally. To correct for the specification error the RIF regression is com-
bined with the DFL re-weighting function. This requires estimating the RIF regres-
sion for period s with the re-weighting function such that the covariates of period s 
have the same distribution as in period t. Let the re-weighted period s covariates be X </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>s , 
and the estimated coefficients be b b </p>

<p>cs </p>

<p>s . The composition effect can then be further 
decomposed as: </p>

<p>ð 
X </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>s À 
X s Þb </p>

<p>s 
s </p>

<p>|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>pure composition effect </p>

<p>þ 
X s ðb </p>

<p>cs </p>

<p>s Àb </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>s Þ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>specification error </p>

<p>; 
[A12] </p>

<p>where the first term of equation [A12] is the pure composition effect and the second term 
is the specification error. Similarly the coefficient effect is decomposed into pure coefficient 
effect and the re-weighting error component, given as: </p>

<p>
X t ðb </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>t Àb </p>

<p>cs </p>

<p>s Þ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl ffl} </p>

<p>pure coefficient effect </p>

<p>þ ð 
X t À 
X </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>s Þb </p>

<p>cs </p>

<p>s Þ 
|fflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl{zfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflfflffl} </p>

<p>reweighting error </p>

<p>; 
[A13] </p>

<p>where the first term of equation [A13] is the pure coefficient effect and the second term is 
the re-weighting error term. 
Further, within the decomposition analysis we use the normalization suggested by Yun  (2005) such that the results are not sensitive to the omitted category for the categorical 
variables. 
In our empirical application we use the <rs type="software">STATA</rs> ado file 'RIFREG' written by Firpo et al.  (2009), downloaded from: http://faculty.arts.ubc.ca/nfortin/datahead.html. </p>

<p>2. Selection bias </p>

<p>To estimate the correction term a multinomial logit model (Dubin and McFadden, 1984)  is estimated separately for men and women. An individual i is characterized as having 
three options; these options are different for men and women. The sample of women is 
grouped into the following three categories: fw i ¼ 2 if working in the wage sector; fw i ¼ 1 
if she is an unpaid family worker; and fw i ¼ 0 if she is economically inactive (non-partici-
pant). The categories for men are: fw i ¼ 2 if working in the wage sector; fw i ¼ 1 if self-
employed; and fw i ¼ 0 if he is economically inactive (non-participant). The probability of 
being in group j is obtained by: </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
P ij ¼ Pðfw i ¼ jjZ i Þ ¼ </p>

<p>expðZ i a j Þ </p>

<p>1 þ 
P 2 
j¼0 expðZ i a j Þ </p>

<p>for j ¼ 0; 1; 2; 
[A14] </p>

<p>where the numerator is normalized to 1 for j ¼ 0; P ij ¼ Pðfw i ¼ jjZ i Þ is the conditional prob-
ability of individual i belonging to sector j, conditional on Z i , a vector of covariates; and a j is 
a column vector of coefficients corresponding to the j 
th sector. The predicted probabilities 
from the multinomial logit model (estimated separately for men and women) are then used to 
construct a selection correction term, k ij , by using the formula provided by Hill (1983): </p>

<p>k ij ¼ 
6 
p 2 </p>

<p>
ðÀ1Þ 
Jþ1 J À 1 
J 
ln b 
P ij </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>k6 ¼j </p>

<p>b 
P ik ln b 
P ik </p>

<p>1 À b 
P ik </p>

<p>! 
" 
# </p>

<p>for j ¼ 0; 1; 2: 
[A15] </p>

<p>In the second step, augmented wage equations are estimated separately for men and 
women by including correction term as an additional regressor: </p>

<p>y ij ¼ X ij b j þ h j k ij þ e ij ; 
[A16] </p>

<p>where y ij is the log wage of individual i in sector j; X ij is the vector of sector specific indi-
vidual characteristics; b j is the vector of returns to characteristics in sector j; h j is the 
unknown coefficient related to the selection correction term; and e ij is the independent 
residual term. The augmented wage equation estimation results are then used in decompo-
sition of the change in wage distributions of men and women over time. </p>

<p>15   Selection procedure requires the availability of valid instruments, i.e., variables which 
affect the labour market status but do not affect the wages. This means there should exist 
at least one element in vector Z (equation [A14]) which is excluded from vector X (equa-
tion [A16]). For identification, the following variables are included in the multinomial logit 
model. Three dummies to capture the labour market status of other members of the house-
hold: the presence of wage workers, the presence of self-employed and the presence of 
unpaid family workers in the household; a dummy for the head of the household; a 
dummy for whether the worker lives in rural or urban area; and finally, only for women, 
whether or not there is a grandmother present in the household. 
Justification for using the labour market status of other members of the household in 
the participation equation comes from the well documented evidence on the importance of 
social networks in determining the labour market outcomes (Calvo-Armengol and Jackson,  2004; Montgomery, 1991). Presence of other household members in a specific sector is 
likely to influence the probability of employment within the sector. For instance, Calvo-
Armengol and Jackson (2004) argue that, when information about jobs arrives individuals 
who are unemployed and directly hear of a job use the information to obtain a job; on the 
other hand, individuals who are already employed, depending on whether the job is more 
attractive than their current job, might take the job or else might pass information to one 
(or more) of their direct connections in the network. In accordance with this argument, it 
is possible that a wage worker (or a self-employed) may share the information about a 
waged employment (or self-employment) opportunity with his or her household members 
who are unemployed or self-employed. 
Increasingly there is evidence that the labour supply decisions are more dependent on 
individuals' 'role in the household' and 'composition of the household' rather than </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>individuals' 'sex' (Cunningham, 2001). The head of the household must enter the labour 
force as she or he is often perceived as the main bread earner; this status within the house-
hold is unlikely to have any effect on the wage of the individual. 
The presence of other adults in the household can aid in the labour force participation 
(LFP) of women, by providing child care; however, it can also be detrimental, as other adults 
may be either considered as labour market substitutes for women or additional care responsi-
bilities for women. In this case a dummy for the presence of a grandmother in the household 
can aid in LFP of women by providing child care, but at the same time can be a deterrent for 
LFP as an elderly relative in the household may be an additional care responsibility for the 
women. For instance, using US data, Ettner (1996) shows that caregiving responsibilities for 
elders is a significant detriment to LFP for women. Similar results are echoed using the UK 
data by Heitmueller and Inglis (2007) and Heitmueller (2007). In case of China, on the other 
hand, Maurer-Fazio et al. (2011) found that co-residence with elders had a positive effect on 
the LFP of women, especially married women. Similarly Marenzi and Pagani (2005) found 
that in Italy, the presence of elderly parents in the house can be beneficial for the LFP of 
women, especially those with pre-school children. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
Appendix B Additional tables </p>

<p>Table B1. Descriptive statistics for women </p>

<p>2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Economically 
inactive </p>

<p>Unpaid 
family 
worker </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Economically 
inactive </p>

<p>Unpaid 
family 
worker </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Education dummies 
No formal education 
0.22 
0.33 
0.04 
0.25 
0.32 
0.06 
Primary school 
0.58 
0.63 
0.28 
0.47 
0.55 
0.22 
Secondary school 
0.07 
0.02 
0.07 
0.10 
0.07 
0.08 
High school 
0.08 
0.02 
0.17 
0.08 
0.03 
0.13 
Vocational high school 
0.04 
0.01 
0.11 
0.05 
0.02 
0.11 
University 
0.02 
0.00 
0.32 
0.04 
0.01 
0.40 
Tenure 
-
19.55 
6.42 
-
15.27 
5.07 
-
(0.15) 
(0.07) 
-
(0.11) 
(0.05) 
Presence of children in the household 
Age ≤ 4 years 
0.33 
0.31 
0.18 
0.33 
0.27 
0.18 
5 ≤ Age &lt; 11 years 
0.41 
0.42 
0.29 
0.39 
0.38 
0.27 
11 ≤ Age &lt; 15 years 
0.22 
0.28 
0.17 
0.21 
0.25 
0.16 
Other members of the household 
Presence of wage 
workers </p>

<p>0.50 
0.12 
0.64 
0.57 
0.21 
0.64 </p>

<p>Presence of self-
employed </p>

<p>0.21 
0.93 
0.10 
0.16 
0.87 
0.10 </p>

<p>Presence of unpaid 
family workers </p>

<p>0.05 
0.55 
0.02 
0.04 
0.42 
0.02 </p>

<p>Marital status dummy 
Never married 
0.10 
0.13 
0.38 
0.10 
0.09 
0.35 
Married 
0.83 
0.85 
0.56 
0.83 
0.89 
0.57 
Divorced 
0.01 
0.002 
0.04 
0.02 
0.01 
0.06 
Widowed 
0.05 
0.01 
0.02 
0.05 
0.01 
0.02 
Age 
20-24 
0.16 
0.16 
0.24 
0.13 
0.10 
0.18 
25-34 
0.32 
0.26 
0.43 
0.30 
0.23 
0.42 
35-44 
0.24 
0.22 
0.24 
0.24 
0.26 
0.28 
45 and above 
0.27 
0.35 
0.08 
0.32 
0.41 
0.11 
Member of social 
security system </p>

<p>-
0.01 
0.73 
-
0.06 
0.77 </p>

<p>Head of household 
dummy </p>

<p>0.07 
0.00 
0.10 
0.08 
0.00 
0.10 </p>

<p>Grandmother 
0.05 
0.13 
0.05 
0.06 
0.13 
0.05 
Rural 
0.30 
0.92 
0.18 
0.23 
0.86 
0.13 
Observations 
60,811 
7,787 
9,442 
97,594 
15,220 
20,080 </p>

<p>Note: Standard errors for continuous variables are reported in (). Sample weights are used. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

<p>Table B2. Descriptive statistics for men </p>

<p>2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Economically 
inactive </p>

<p>Self-
employed </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Economically 
inactive </p>

<p>Self-
employed </p>

<p>Wage 
worker </p>

<p>Education dummies 
No formal education 
0.06 
0.10 
0.02 
0.09 
0.09 
0.03 
Primary school 
0.52 
0.70 
0.43 
0.39 
0.62 
0.35 
Secondary school 
0.12 
0.09 
0.14 
0.18 
0.13 
0.16 
High school 
0.14 
0.06 
0.15 
0.13 
0.07 
0.12 
Vocational high 
school </p>

<p>0.09 
0.03 
0.12 
0.09 
0.06 
0.13 </p>

<p>University 
0.08 
0.02 
0.15 
0.11 
0.04 
0.20 
Tenure 
-
17.81 
8.00 
-
15.07 
6.20 
-
(0.12) 
(0.04) 
-
(0.08) 
(0.03) 
Presence of children in the household 
Age ≤ 4 years 
0.27 
0.32 
0.35 
0.25 
0.28 
0.34 
5 ≤ Age &lt; 11 years 
0.35 
0.43 
0.42 
0.33 
0.39 
0.38 
11 ≤ Age &lt; 15 years 
0.22 
0.27 
0.21 
0.21 
0.25 
0.19 
Other members of the household 
Presence of wage 
workers </p>

<p>0.30 
0.12 
0.29 
0.34 
0.18 
0.34 </p>

<p>Presence of self-
employed </p>

<p>0.18 
0.07 
0.08 
0.13 
0.08 
0.08 </p>

<p>Presence of unpaid 
family workers </p>

<p>0.06 
0.48 
0.03 
0.04 
0.44 
0.03 </p>

<p>Marital status 
Never married 
0.40 
0.05 
0.18 
0.39 
0.06 
0.22 
Married 
0.58 
0.93 
0.81 
0.58 
0.92 
0.77 
Divorced 
0.01 
0.01 
0.01 
0.02 
0.01 
0.01 
Widowed 
0.01 
0.01 
0.002 
0.003 
0.01 
0.001 
Age 
20-24 
0.30 
0.03 
0.12 
0.22 
0.02 
0.11 
25-34 
0.33 
0.24 
0.43 
0.33 
0.19 
0.40 
35-44 
0.20 
0.29 
0.29 
0.21 
0.29 
0.30 
45 and above 
0.17 
0.43 
0.15 
0.23 
0.49 
0.18 
Member of social 
security system </p>

<p>-
0.42 
0.73 
-
0.39 
0.78 </p>

<p>Head of household 
dummy </p>

<p>0.50 
0.89 
0.76 
0.51 
0.85 
0.71 </p>

<p>Rural 
0.36 
0.66 
0.24 
0.27 
0.56 
0.17 
Observations 
11,426 
14,007 
32,771 
17,704 
23,869 
63,077 </p>

<p>Notes: Standard errors for continuous variables are reported in (). Sample weights are used. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Educational Attainment and Wage Inequality </p>

<p>
Table B3. Occupation categories: Sample proportions for the wage earners </p>

<p>Sample proportions </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>2002 
2010 
2002 
2010 </p>

<p>Abstract 
0.39 
0.39 
0.22 
0.23 
Legislators, senior officials and managers 
0.04 
0.03 
0.04 
0.05 
Professionals 
0.21 
0.21 
0.10 
0.10 
Technicians and associate professionals 
0.14 
0.14 
0.08 
0.08 
Service 
0.45 
0.50 
0.39 
0.41 
Clerks 
0.20 
0.20 
0.09 
0.09 
Service workers and shop and market sales workers 
0.11 
0.14 
0.16 
0.16 
Elementary occupations 
0.14 
0.16 
0.14 
0.16 
Routine 
0.15 
0.11 
0.37 
0.35 
Craft and related trades workers 
0.11 
0.05 
0.22 
0.19 
Plant and machine operators and assemblers 
0.04 
0.06 
0.15 
0.16 </p>

<p>Note: Sample weights are used. </p>

<p>Table B4. Industry dummies: Sample proportions for the wage earners </p>

<p>2002 
2010 
2002 
2010 
Women 
Women 
Men 
Men </p>

<p>Industry categories 
Agriculture, Hunting, Forestry and Fishing (Base category) 
4.7 
3.6 
1.9 
2.2 
Mining and Quarrying 
0.2 
0.1 
1.2 
1.1 
Manufacturing 
25.0 
20.3 
26.3 
25.4 
Electricity, Gas and Water 
0.3 
0.2 
1.3 
1.1 
Construction 
1.3 
1.4 
9.8 
8.8 
Wholesale and Retail Trade and Restaurants and Hotels 
13.6 
16.0 
18.9 
19.6 
Transport, Storage and Communication 
3.0 
3.1 
7.7 
7.2 
Financing, Insurance, Real Estate and Business Services 
7.8 
12.0 
4.6 
8.7 
Community, Social and Personal Services 
44.0 
43.3 
28.3 
25.9 </p>

<p>Note: Sample weights are used. </p>

<p>© 2016 The Authors LABOUR published by Fondazione Giacomo Brodolini and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p> 
Gurleen Popli -Okan Yilmaz </p>

</text></tei>