<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1108%2Fjes-04-2014-0055" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Purpose -The purpose of this paper is to combine multidimensional welfare analysis and entropy 
metrics to derive not only the best relative weights but also substitution degree among different 
attributes to construct multidimensional indices of well-being with Chinese Household Income Project 
Survey 2002 data. 
Design/methodology/approach -The authors follow Maasoumi's two-step measures of multivariate 
inequality to calculate the inequality for three social groups in China, urban residents, migrants, and rural 
residents. The two-step approach provides an aggregation formula which is numerically identified in this 
paper based on a metric entropy distance measure between the distribution of the aggregate well-being 
functions, on the one hand, and the distribution of the self-reported "happiness" indicator. The authors 
compare the differences in relative weights and substitution degree for the three groups, and link them to 
some institutional factors. 
Findings -The authors find that incorporating substitution among attributes, and taking into 
consideration group heterogeneity are very important in multidimensional analysis of well-being. 
Originality/value -The two-step approach provides an aggregation formula which is numerically 
identified in this paper based on a metric entropy distance measure between the distribution of the aggregate 
well-being functions, on the one hand, and the distribution of the self-reported "happiness" indicator. 
Journal of Economic Studies 
Vol. 42 No. 1, 2015 
pp. 4-19 
Emerald Group Publishing Limited 
0144-3585 
DOI 10.1108/JES-04-2014-0055 </p>

<p>The current issue and full text archive of this journal is available on Emerald Insight at: 
www.emeraldinsight.com/0144-3585.htm </p>

<p>© Asian Development Bank. The views expressed in this publication are those of the authors and 
do not necessarily reflect the views and policies or the Asian Development Bank (ADB) or its 
Board of Governors or the governments they represent. ADB does not guarantee the accuracy of 
the data included in this publication and accepts no responsibility for any consequence of their 
use. By making any designation of or reference to a particular territory or geographic areas, or by 
using the term "country" in this document, ADB does not intend to make any judgments as to the 
legal or other status of any territory or area. 
JEL Classification -I31, C43 
The authors would like to thank Le Wang and anonymous referees and Almas Heshamti for 
comments and suggestions. The usual disclaimer applies. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>which is to infer information on weights based on self-reported "happiness." Nardo  et al. (2005) proposed a regression of life satisfaction on various variables to derive 
the relative weights. However, this approach suffers from a number of disadvantages. 
First, there is over reliance on self-reported indicator of "happiness." Second, it is 
complex to take into consideration explicit non-linear relationships in regressions. 
Third, this approach does not handle the substitution relationship among different 
attributes in a satisfactory manner. In this paper we propose a different strategy. 
First, we adopt ideal aggregation functions that combine different attributes so as to 
minimize general entropic divergence between the aggregate's distribution, and 
the distributions of the constituent attributes. This procedure leaves the parameters 
of the aggregator function undetermined. But these parameters can be obtained 
to, again, minimize the entropic divergence between the distribution of the aggregates 
and the distribution of any desired measure of "happiness." A metric entropy 
measure is a proper measure of "distance" and suitable to compare two or more 
distributions, with a minimand that identifies weights and other parameters 
uniquely. This offers an aggregation formula, as in Maasoumi (1986), which is 
extended in this paper by a numerical optimization routine to identify suitable 
numerical values for weights and other parameters. These numerically identified 
well-being measures provide a basis for multidimensional consideration of poverty 
and inequity. 
The structure of this paper is as follows. In Section 2, we introduce Maasoumi's 
two-step measures of multivariate well-being and inequality; In Section 3, we introduce 
the two metric entropy measures; Section 4 describes the numerical optimization 
procedures; Section 5 contains the empirical results based on CHIPS; and Section 6 
provides the conclusion and potential future research directions. </p>

<p>2. Multivariate measure of well-being and inequality 
It has been widely accepted that only using one attribute (usually income or GDP) to 
measure individuals' or countries' welfare is insufficient. We should incorporate more 
attributes (especially non-tradable ones) to obtain more comprehensive information. 
However, including more attributes brings in the problem of aggregation, that is how to 
aggregate different indicators of well-being to represent the welfare level. Maasoumi  (1986) proposed a two-step measure of multivariate inequality. In the first step, he used 
different attributes to construct a welfare aggregate or "average," and in the second 
step, he calculated the inequality index using each person's welfare evaluation obtained 
in the first step. We now describe this two-step measures of multivariate inequality 
method in detail. 
In the first step, we address the aggregation problem using the generalized entropy 
measure to have a representation of the divergence between the multiple distribution of 
the attributes, on the one hand, and the distribution of the latent aggregator index, on 
the other. Let S i be the individual i's aggregate welfare, which can be seen as 
individual's utility evaluation or welfare assessment. Let X ij be individual i's amount 
of jth attribute. Then we can define the multivariate generalized entropy measure of 
closeness as follows: </p>

<p>D b S; X ; a 
ð 
Þ¼ 
X m </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>a j 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>S i S i =X ij 
À 
Á b À1 
h 
i 
=b bþ 1 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>where α j 's are the relative weights of each attributes ð 
P m 
j¼1 a j ¼ 1Þ. By minimizing the 
D β function regarding S i 's, which are subject to restriction that 
P n 
i¼1 S i ¼ 1, that is: </p>

<p>min </p>

<p>S i 
f g </p>

<p>D b S; X ; a 
ð 
Þmin </p>

<p>S i 
f g </p>

<p>X m </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>a j 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>S i S i =X ij 
À 
Á b À1 
h 
i 
=b bþ 1 
ð 
Þ </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>s:t: 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>S i ¼ 1 </p>

<p>we can get our welfare or aggregate function: </p>

<p>S i p 
X m </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>a j X </p>

<p>Àb 
ij </p>

<p>! À1=b </p>

<p>; b a 0; À1; 
(3) </p>

<p>S i p 
Y m </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>a j </p>

<p>ij ; b ¼ 0; 
(4) </p>

<p>S i p 
X m </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>a j X ij ; b ¼ À1: 
(5) </p>

<p>These are different averages of the attributes for each person, and the elasticity of 
substitution between different attributes is 1/(1+β). By minimizing the "divergence 
measure" D β , we make the welfare vector S ¼ (S 1 , S 2 , …, S n ) as close to their 
corresponding multivariate attributes as possible. From Information Theory, the vector S 
absorbs all the objective information from data, and any deviation from S will cause some 
distortion. The underlying assumption in this step is that we know the exact weights for 
different attributes(α j 's) and substitution degree between attributes( β). However, in 
reality, we do not know. Finding out the parameters is one main issue in this paper, and 
we will discuss it later. There is also a welfare theoretic basis for this conundrum. Every 
scalar aggregator endows individual attributes with weights, and levels of substitution, 
that reflect social valuations. Arrow's impossibility theorems speak to the difficulty of 
reaching consensus. Generalized entropy measures are equivalent, up to monotonically 
increasing transformations, very flexible welfare functions. But this merely identifies a 
family of aggregator functions. The choice of a metric entropy which satisfies the 
triangularity property of distances resolves some of this indeterminacy, but not all. Here 
"calibrating" toward the distribution of observed "happiness" will find parameter values 
that would be required to "match" the underlying attributes and their valuations to the 
"happiness" observation. No more, and no less. 
In the second step (Maasoumi, 1986), adopted the generalized entropy index on 
inequality for the S i distribution as the measure of multidimensional inequality, that is: </p>

<p>M g S 
ð Þ ¼ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>p i S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i =p i </p>

<p>À 
Á 1 þ g À1 
h 
i 
=g 1 þ g 
ð 
Þ; g a 0; À1 
(6) </p>

<p>M 0 S 
ð Þ ¼ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i log S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i =p i </p>

<p>À 
Á 
; Theil's first index 
(7) </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>M À1 S 
ð Þ ¼ 
X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>p i log p i =S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>À 
Á 
; Theil's second index 
(8) </p>

<p>where p i is individual i's population share (usually ¼ 1/n), and S </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>i is normalized S i which 
is divided by the total K ¼ 
P n 
i¼1 S i . </p>

<p>3. Two metric entropy measures 
The entropy measures of similarity or association we will introduce below are 
supported by a set of desirable axiomatic properties. These include invariance to 
non-linear (monotone) transformations, invariance to dimensionality, capability 
to reproduce correlation and other linear measures of linear association (when that is 
appropriate as for jointly Gaussian variables), metricness, normalization, and others. 
In Maasoumi and Racine's (2002) and Granger et al.'s (2004) paper, they proposed 
a metric entropy to test dependence of two univariate variable X and Y, which is 
"Matusita-Bhattacharya-Hellinger measure of dependence" (we call it metric entropy 
measure 1 later) given by: </p>

<p>S r ¼ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Z þ 1 </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>Z þ 1 </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>f 
1=2 x; y 
ð ÞÀf </p>

<p>1=2 
1 </p>

<p>x 
ð Þf </p>

<p>1=2 
2 </p>

<p>y 
ð Þ </p>

<p>
2 
dxdy 
(9) </p>

<p>where f(x, y) is the joint pdf of X and Y, f 1 (x) is the marginal pdf of X, and f 2 (y) is the 
marginal pdf of Y. This metric is able to measure the non-linear dependence 
relationship between X and Y, with the range [0, 1). S ρ is zero when X and Y are 
independent variables and is positive but less than one otherwise. Because it is a metric, 
we can say the larger it is, the farther the two variables are from independence. For 
discrete or categorical variables, suppose X∈{x 1 , x 2 , …, x m }, Y∈{y 1 , y 2 , …, y n }, joint 
probability mass function is P xy (i, j) ¼ Prob(X ¼ x i , Y ¼ y j ) and the corresponding 
marginal probability mass functions are P x (i) ¼ Prob(X ¼ x i ) and P y ( j) ¼ Prob(Y ¼ y j ), 
then we can rewrite (9) as: </p>

<p>S r ¼ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>X m </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>j¼1 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>1=2 </p>

<p>xy i; j 
ð ÞÀP </p>

<p>1=2 
x </p>

<p>i 
ð ÞP </p>

<p>1=2 
y </p>

<p>j 
ð Þ </p>

<p>h 
i 2 
: 
(10) </p>

<p>This metric can also be used to measure the distance between the distributions of X 1 
and X 2 if we write it in the following form (we call it metric entropy measure 2 later): </p>

<p>S r ¼ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>Z þ 1 </p>

<p>À1 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>1=2 
1 </p>

<p>x 
ð ÞÀf </p>

<p>1=2 
2 </p>

<p>x 
ð Þ </p>

<p>
2 
dx: 
(11) </p>

<p>Equation (11) measures the closeness of random variables X 1 and X 2 's distributions. S ρ 
equals zero if they have identical distribution, and it is positive and less than one 
otherwise. Larger S ρ means that the difference between their distributions is larger. 
For discrete or categorical variables, suppose X 1 , X 2 ∈{x 1 , x 2 , …, x n }[1], and the 
corresponding probability mass functions are P 1 (i) ¼ Prob(X 1 ¼ x i ) and P 2 (i) ¼ Prob 
(X 2 ¼ x i ), and then we can rewrite (11) as: </p>

<p>S r ¼ 
1 
2 </p>

<p>X n </p>

<p>i¼1 </p>

<p>P 1 i 
ð Þ 
1=2 ÀP 2 i 
ð Þ </p>

<p>1=2 </p>

<p>h 
i 2 
: 
(12) </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>4. Numerical procedure 
4.1 Data 
In this paper, we use Chinese Household Income Project Survey (CHIPS) 2002[2], which 
is provided by Shi (2009). CHIPS2002 is a countrywide survey conducted in the year 
2002, containing samples from urban residents, migrants, and rural residents. We treat 
urban residents, migrants (in cities) and rural residents as separate groups[3], and we 
only keep urban residents with local hukou and migrants with rural hukou. After 
deleting observations with missing values, the final sample contains 6,553 urban 
residents, 5,035 migrants, and 8,533 rural residents. </p>

<p>4.2 Variables 
In attribute selection, we include five attributes proxying in four types. The first and 
second attributes are household per capita income (income for short later)[4] and 
household per capita net asset (net asset for short later), which represent "economic" 
conditions. For income, it is net income, and we adjust it for provincial CPI and 
household composition (children count as one half). In Maasoumi and Nickelsburg  (1988) and Pasha et al.'s (2005) papers, they both used annual nominal income. And 
because in CHIPS there is information about assets and debts, we also choose 
household per capita net asset to capture "permanent income." For urban residents, 
CHIPS has information about annual personal income, and we calculate household per 
capita income by taking the average of personal incomes in the same household. For 
migrants, we calculate household per capita income by dividing the answer to "total 
household income from working in cities and family production in 2002" by the size of 
household. For rural residents, we use total annual household income divided by family 
size. For net asset, we first calculate the household net asset by total household 
financial asset (for rural residents, we also include fixed productive assets) minus total 
household debt and then divide it by household size. The third attribute is household 
per capita usable house area (house area for short later)[5], which reflect the housing 
conditions. In Pasha et al.'s (2005) paper, they used building area. In this paper, we use 
usable house area for two reasons. First, usable house area reflects better how much 
space the person can use and live in. Second, most migrants cannot afford buying or 
renting a whole apartment in cities so they share apartments or rooms with other 
people. Thus, CHIPS only has data on usable house area for migrants. To calculate 
household per capita usable house area, we divide the usable house area by family size 
for urban residents and by the number of family members living together for migrants 
and rural residents. The fourth attribute is health. It is the answer to body conditions, 
which contains five categories, "Worst," "Worse," "Just so-so," "Good," and "Very 
good," and we assign number 1-5 to them, respectively. The fifth attribute is years of 
education (education for short later), which represent human capital (Maasoumi and  Nickelsburg, 1988). Statistical summaries are in Table I. 
In calculating the individual's welfare S, the weights indicate the relative importance 
of different attributes. To eliminate the effects of the scale difference in attributes, we 
normalize them by calculating the "shares" of attributes to the total amount in their 
group, i.e. dividing individuals' attribute amount by the total amount in their group. 
This is also consistent with research in happiness, which finds that relative amount 
plays an important role in determining happiness or subjective well-being. One 
exception is net asset because for some observations the values of net asset are 
negative. We add the absolute value of the minimal net asset (which is negative) in the 
group to each person within the group and then calculate their share of net asset. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Obs. 
Income (RMB) 
Net asset (RMB) </p>

<p>House area (m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
Health (scale) </p>

<p>Education (year) </p>

<p>Age (year) </p>

<p>Married (percent) </p>

<p>Urban </p>

<p>6,553 </p>

<p>9,050.61 </p>

<p>13,264.27 </p>

<p>18.86 </p>

<p>3.74 </p>

<p>10.83 </p>

<p>46.74 </p>

<p>93.68 </p>

<p>(5,874.49) </p>

<p>(41,809.52) </p>

<p>(10.19) </p>

<p>(0.86) </p>

<p>(3.18) </p>

<p>(11.28) </p>

<p>Migrant </p>

<p>5,035 </p>

<p>6,979.73 </p>

<p>7,233.45 </p>

<p>10.73 </p>

<p>4.21 </p>

<p>6.60 </p>

<p>28.69 </p>

<p>68.51 </p>

<p>(6,278.85) </p>

<p>(42,146.60) </p>

<p>(10.58) </p>

<p>(0.68) </p>

<p>(3.50) </p>

<p>(14.06) </p>

<p>Rural </p>

<p>8,533 </p>

<p>3,176.11 </p>

<p>3,262.13 </p>

<p>30.34 </p>

<p>3.95 </p>

<p>7.12 </p>

<p>45.13 </p>

<p>95.47 </p>

<p>(2,615.35) </p>

<p>(5,780.14) </p>

<p>(21.28) </p>

<p>(0.78) </p>

<p>(2.56) </p>

<p>(10.63) </p>

<p>Table I. 
Statistical 
description for 
attributes </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Another variable we use is the happiness level. The question for interviewees is 
"Generally speaking, do you feel happy?" and their answers can be categorized 
into "very happy," "happy," "so-so," "not very happy," "not happy at all," and "don't 
know"[6]. We keep observations with the first five answers and assign values 5, 4, 3, 2, 
and 1, respectively, to interviewees' reported happiness. Table II shows the reported 
happiness distributions in the three groups. </p>

<p>4.3 Choosing parameters 
In assessing the multidimensional welfare of individuals, one critical issue is to choose 
the parameters, i.e. weights for different attributes α j 's and the substitution degree β. 
Given the data, the choice of parameters determines everyone's welfare and then the 
distribution, which can be used to conduct some research on inequality or implement 
some policy analysis. However, there is no wide consensus on how to choose these 
parameters. In this paper, we will choose the parameters using a method similar to 
calibration, which can be included in the category "Hedonic Weights" in Decancq and  Lugo's (2013) paper. Simply speaking, we search the whole parameter space to find the 
set of parameters making the distance of reported happiness and objective measures of 
individual welfare smallest. To measure the distance between reported happiness and 
welfare, we adopt the two methods mentioned in Section 3. 
Given individuals' attributes and parameters, we can calculate individuals' welfare S i 's, 
which can be seen as continuous variables across observations. To compare the 
individuals' welfare with their reported happiness, we transform individuals' welfare into 
discrete variables. The procedure is as follows: first, we normalize S i into the range [0, 1] by: </p>

<p>normalized S i ¼ 
S i ÀS min 
S max ÀS min 
(13) </p>

<p>where S min and S max are the minimal and maximal values among S i 's; second, we assign 
values 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5 to individuals' welfare if their normalized S 's are in the range [0, 0.2], 
(0.2, 0.4], (0.4, 0.6], (0.6, 0.8], or (0.8, 1]. 
It is possible to be economical in searching the parameter space[7], we adopt 
algorithms to reduce the computation burden and time, as follows. 
4.3.1 Step 1: rough search. First, we go through the parameter space roughly and 
record 50 best parameter sets. Parameter sets are judged by the smallest distance 
between reported happiness and welfare given the parameter set in different measures. 
For the first measure of Section 3, that is (9) and (10), the larger the value the smaller 
the distance between reported happiness and calculated welfare because it indicates the 
dependence of reported happiness and welfare in the individual level. We call it "Metric 
entropy measure 1" and denote it as S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r. For the second measure of Section 3, that is (11) 
and (12), the smaller the value the smaller the distance between reported happiness and 
calculated welfare because it indicates the difference between reported happiness 
and individual welfare in the distribution level. We call it "Metric entropy measure 2" and </p>

<p>Not happy at all 
Not very happy 
So-so 
Happy 
Very happy </p>

<p>Urban 
2.23 
10.21 
31.39 
49.02 
7.15 
Migrant 
1.65 
9.22 
44.83 
37.97 
6.34 
Rural 
1.02 
7.98 
29.02 
46.58 
15.40 </p>

<p>Table II. 
Happiness 
distribution (percent) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>denote it as S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r . In this rough search, we set the interval of weights α j 's as 0.05[8] and the 
interval of substitution degree β as 0.01, and we let α j 's change in {0, 0.05, 0.10, …, 0.95, 
1.00} with 
P 5 
j¼1 a j ¼ 1 and β change in {0, 0.01, 0.02, …, 0.99, 1.00}. Then we record 50 
best-performed parameter sets in each measure for future use. 
4.3.2 Step 2: refinement. After we get results from the rough search in the step 1, we 
conduct some refinement and obtain best parameter sets with α j s' change interval as 0.01. 
Due to the huge computation burden, we only make more accurate search around the 
best 50 results from step 1[9]. Let us denote any of the results from step 1 as 
b 
1 ; a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 ; a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 ; a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 ; a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>4 ; a </p>

<p>1 
5 </p>

<p>À 
Á 
. In the refinement step, we let β change in the range [ β </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>−0.01, 
β </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>+0.01] with interval 0.01 and each α j change in the range a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>j À0:05; a </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>j þ 0:05 </p>

<p>h 
i 
with </p>

<p>interval 0.01, and α j 's also need to satisfy 
P 5 
j¼1 a j ¼ 1. And after comparing the 
distances between happiness and different parameter sets, we record best-performed 100 
parameter sets in this step. 
4.3.3 Step 3: bootstrap. In a sense, the best S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r and S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r can be regarded as an estimate 
based on a specific data sample. To report some degree of reliability, we bootstrap non-
parametrically from the data set to test the performance of the 100 parameter sets 
recorded in step two. We record the percentage of each parameter set performing best 
in the bootstrap procedure. </p>

<p>5. Numerical results 
The main task above is to find out relative weights for different attributes and their 
degree of substitution. Then we can interpret the findings in two contexts. The first is 
welfare analysis, which focusses on multidimensional index of well-being and, we use 
certain parameter sets to investigate the inequality in different groups. The second 
examination is a form of utility analysis, which explains the relative weights as 
contributions to utility for each attribute. We consider some historical and family 
characteristics to shed light on findings that help policy decisions. </p>

<p>5.1 Welfare analysis 
Table III shows the best parameter sets for metric entropy measures 1 and 2 in different 
groups after refinement. The second column is entropy metric S ρ , the third one is β, the 
fourth to the eighth columns are relative weights for income, net asset, house area, 
health, and education. However, the refinement results may be not robust in the 
statistical sense. We give the best parameter sets in bootstrap procedure (having 
the highest percentage to be the best parameter sets) in Table IV for different metrics 
with the bootstrap number 999. The second column is the percentage of performing 
best for the parameter sets. Because there are some very similar parameter sets, so the </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education 
Urban 
0.01045 
−0.23 
0.19 
0.15 
0.10 
0.55 
0.01 
Migrant 
0.00818 
−0.23 
0.29 
0.26 
0.11 
0.34 
0.00 
Rural 
0.00950 
−0.24 
0.03 
0.09 
0.01 
0.87 
0.00 
S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education 
Urban 
0.00418 
−0.02 
0.06 
0.03 
0.05 
0.84 
0.02 
Migrant 
0.00163 
−0.13 
0.01 
0.00 
0.10 
0.86 
0.03 
Rural 
0.00089 
−0.63 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.76 
0.24 </p>

<p>Table III. 
Best parameter set 
in refinement for 
S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r and S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>percentage is not very high. The third to ninth columns are the same to the second to 
eighth columns in Table III. And also we can see that the percentage in metric entropy 
measure 2 is higher than in metric entropy measure 1, which means parameter sets 
perform more stable in metric entropy measure 2. 
In addition, we can obtain the desired parameter sets by taking the percentage-
weighted average of the bootstrap results (in Table V). In this way, how much weight 
we give to different parameter sets is the percentage they become the best parameter 
set in bootstrap procedure, so we give larger weights to parameter sets which perform 
better in the statistical sense. 
Another way to calculate the relative weight from the data is using the (normalized) 
metric entropy measures between each attribute and happiness as their respective 
relative weights. The results are in Table VI. However, this results are not consistent 
with other results. The possible reason is that this method does not take into 
consideration of substitution effects in different attributes, i.e. β. So it may provide </p>

<p>% 
S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education 
Urban 
5.3 
0.01028 
0.00 
0.24 
0.13 
0.02 
0.38 
0.23 
Migrant 
9.7 
0.00770 
−0.20 
0.20 
0.28 
0.13 
0.39 
0.00 
Rural 
12.0 
0.00920 
−0.51 
0.05 
0.00 
0.01 
0.94 
0.00 
% 
S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education 
Urban 
11.5 
0.00441 
−0.09 
0.06 
0.11 
0.03 
0.74 
0.06 
Migrant 
20.0 
0.00163 
−0.13 
0.01 
0.00 
0.10 
0.86 
0.03 
Rural 
41.7 
0.00089 
−0.63 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
0.76 
0.24 </p>

<p>Table IV. 
Best parameter 
set in bootstrap 
for S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r and S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Urban 
−0.170 
0.209 
0.164 
0.075 
0.490 
0.062 
Migrant 
−0.235 
0.267 
0.284 
0.089 
0.360 
0.000 
Rural 
−0.331 
0.044 
0.038 
0.015 
0.899 
0.004 
S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Urban 
−0.032 
0.058 
0.052 
0.047 
0.813 
0.030 
Migrant 
−0.133 
0.005 
0.006 
0.105 
0.848 
0.036 
Rural 
−0.587 
0.016 
0.001 
0.000 
0.815 
0.167 </p>

<p>Table V. 
Weighted average 
parameter set 
in bootstrap for 
S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r and S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Urban 
0.253 
0.027 
0.114 
0.466 
0.140 
Migrant 
0.112 
0.174 
0.281 
0.297 
0.136 
Rural 
0.064 
0.077 
0.069 
0.717 
0.073 
S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Urban 
0.354 
0.212 
0.371 
0.013 
0.050 
Migrant 
0.377 
0.253 
0.270 
0.058 
0.042 
Rural 
0.339 
0.266 
0.312 
0.009 
0.074 </p>

<p>Table VI. 
Relative weights by 
calculating S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r and 
S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>r between 
attributes and 
happiness </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>some evidence for the importance of adding attribute substitution into the 
multidimensional indices of well-being. 
Next, we calculate the inequality based on the parameter sets we obtained above. Here 
we use the best and weighted average parameter sets in bootstrap to calculate individuals' 
welfare without discretizing them, and then we calculate Theil's first and second indices 
and generalized entropy index with γ ¼ −1/2 using R package "<rs type="software">ineq</rs>." Here we use 
generalized entropy index with γ ¼ −1/2 because the metric entropy measure we use is the 
same entropy metric with γ ¼ −1/2. The results are in Table VII. The second column is the 
inequality in reported happiness, where happiness is a discrete variable. The third and 
fourth columns are inequality of welfare S calculated through the best and weighted 
average parameter sets in the bootstrap, using metric entropy measure 1. The fifth and 
sixth columns are inequality of welfare S calculated through the best and weighted 
average parameter sets in the bootstrap, using metric entropy measure 2. The results for 
discrete individual welfare are in Table VIII. When we analyze inequality results, we 
should focus more on results from metric entropy measure 2 because it focusses on the 
similarity of two distributions. It is interesting to note from Tables VII and VIII, that 
inequality in self-reported "happiness" is always higher than that in multidimensional 
welfare based on entropy metric 2. One possible explanation is that this is due to the </p>

<p>Happiness 
Best in S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Average in S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Best in S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Average in S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Theil's 1st index 
Urban 
0.03310635 
0.02096783 
0.01882967 
0.01938336 
0.02362107 
Migrant 
0.02997603 
0.02424105 
0.02820155 
0.01788124 
0.01882405 
Rural 
0.0297519 
0.02066842 
0.01913168 
0.01961511 
0.01907011 
Theil's 2nd index 
Urban 
0.03863011 
Inf </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.01963884 
0.02109975 
0.0265901 
Migrant 
0.0335238 
0.02364874 
0.02687041 
0.0197093 
0.02074389 
Rural 
0.03345007 
0.02405269 
0.02212287 
0.022138 
0.02167807 
GE (γ ¼ −1/2) 
Urban 
0.03546201 
0.04373861 
0.01915617 
0.02013176 
0.02487101 
Migrant 
0.0314595 
0.02378915 
0.02732712 
0.01866831 
0.01965113 
Rural 
0.03133147 
0.02212602 
0.02042914 
0.02071965 
0.02021248 
Note: 
a Inf comes from the fact that some person's welfare equals to zero </p>

<p>Table VII. 
Inequality indices 
for happiness and 
original individual 
welfare S </p>

<p>Happiness 
Best in S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Average in S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>Best in S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Average in S </p>

<p>2 
r </p>

<p>Theil's 1st index 
Urban 
0.03310635 
0.02214269 
0.02716573 
0.02494992 
0.02496797 
Migrant 
0.02997603 
0.04447686 
0.0621958 
0.02500336 
0.02569485 
Rural 
0.0297519 
0.02979672 
0.02786803 
0.02747622 
0.02431393 
Theil's 2nd index 
Urban 
0.03863011 
0.02415579 
0.02813996 
0.02798481 
0.02833565 
Migrant 
0.0335238 
0.04900813 
0.0639305 
0.02733607 
0.02806306 
Rural 
0.03345007 
0.03405223 
0.03188229 
0.03125789 
0.02858245 
GE (γ ¼ −1/2) 
Urban 
0.03546201 
0.02299552 
0.02753501 
0.02624043 
0.02639708 
Migrant 
0.0314595 
0.04646297 
0.06276656 
0.02599023 
0.02670232 
Rural 
0.03133147 
0.03159864 
0.02957278 
0.02909023 
0.02613244 </p>

<p>Table VIII. 
Inequality indices 
for happiness and 
discrete individual 
welfare S </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>substitution between different attributes. Individuals may report based on the most 
pressing needs and dimensions, as perceived by them at a moment in time. Even though 
our approach aggregates different dimensions "toward' this self-reported indicator, it still 
allows for formal consideration of other objective indicators. Another possible explanation 
is that there exist some hidden factors such as personality which affect happiness and are 
not captured by the variables used in this paper[10]. </p>

<p>5.2 Utility analysis 
The other way to interpret the best parameter sets we get is to explain them as the 
utility of different groups, and we can compare the difference across groups. In this 
sense, parameter sets obtained by metric entropy measure 1 may be more suitable, 
since using it implicitly imposes a correspondence relationship between reported 
happiness and aggregated welfare. Thus, we will mainly use the S </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>r 's results to 
represent the utilities in different groups. And because some parameter sets are very 
close in the results, we group them up. The principle is that substitution degree is 
within 0.1 from the group mean and the sum of distance of relative weights to group 
mean is &lt;0.2. The results are in Table IX. For the weighted average parameter sets, the 
numbers in the parenthesis are the standard errors, and for grouped parameter sets, the 
numbers in the bracket are the ranges. To gain greater intuition, we plot the absolute 
value of β and α j 's in Figures 1 and 2. 
By comparing the parameter values of the three groups, we find some similarities and 
differences. First, it seems the average substitution degrees across different attributes in 
different groups are relatively similar, and they are different from perfect substitution, 
which suggests that it may be problematical assuming perfect substitution (as in linear 
aggregators and regressions). Second, migrants' preference is very similar to urban 
residents other than for education. Education does not contribute to migrants' utility. 
A possible explanation is that this phenomenon is related to the Household Registration 
(Hukou) system in China. There are segregated labor markets in Chinese cities, and 
migrants are discriminated against for entry in mainly the "good" industries, where 
"good" means higher wages combined with higher demand for education and skills (Chen  et al., 2009, 2012; Meng and Zhang, 2001). Thus, the contribution of migrants' education to 
welfare is nearly zero. Third, compared with urban residents and migrants, rural residents </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education </p>

<p>Weighted average 
Urban 
−0.170 
0.209 
0.164 
0.075 
0.490 
0.062 
(0.097) 
(0.023) 
(0.090) 
(0.036) 
(0.085) 
(0.100) 
Migrant 
−0.235 
0.267 
0.284 
0.089 
0.360 
0.000 
(0.054) 
(0.037) 
(0.061) 
(0.028) 
(0.053) 
(0.000) 
Rural 
−0.331 
0.044 
0.038 
0.015 
0.899 
0.004 
(0.162) 
(0.012) 
(0.038) 
(0.008) 
(0.026) 
(0.005) 
Grouped 
Urban 
−0.005 
0.240 
0.120 
0.020 
0.377 
0.243 
[−0.01,0.00] 
[0.24,0.24] 
[0.11,0.13] 
[0.02,0.02] 
[0.37,0.38] 
[0.23,0.25] 
Migrant 
−0.234 
0.287 
0.255 
0.096 
0.362 
0.000 
[−0.31,−0.18] 
[0.20,0.34] 
[0.21,0.34] 
[0.04,0.13] 
[0.29,0.45] 
[0.00,0.00] 
Rural 
−0.567 
0.035 
0.041 
0.010 
0.912 
0.002 
[−0.65,−0.50] 
[0.03,0.05] 
[0.00,0.06] 
[0,0.02] 
[0.90,0.94] 
[0.00,0.01] </p>

<p>Table IX. 
Weighted average 
and grouped 
parameter set in 
bootstrap for S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>put most of their weights on health and less on economic factors (income, net asset, and 
house area) and education. On the one hand, from happiness literature (Clark et al., 2008;  Luttmer, 2005), relative income matters a lot for happiness, which means people would like 
to compare their income and asset with others. Rural residents are less exposed to external 
world due to lack of media so they are less likely to compare their income or property with 
others[11]. Thus, economic factors matter relatively less to their utility. On the other hand, 
the relatively poor medical conditions and lack of medical security in rural area may be 
another reason why rural residents care more about health[12]. </p>

<p>5.3 Control for marital status 
One concern of the above method is that it only includes five attributes due to data 
limitations, and many other characteristics correlated with happiness are omitted, such </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
beta(abs) income 
asset 
house 
health education </p>

<p>Urban 
Migrant 
Rural </p>

<p>Figure 2. 
Grouped 
parameter set </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 
beta(abs) income 
asset 
house 
health education </p>

<p>Urban 
Migrant 
Rural </p>

<p>Figure 1. 
Weighted average 
parameter set </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>as age and marital status. Here we adopt cell decomposition method to address this 
issue[13]. As is shown in Table AI in the Appendix, the subgroup/cell differences in 
characteristics mainly come from marital status rather than age. This is based on 
summary statistics, including quantiles. Thus, we divide the sample further according 
to marital status within each group in order to isolate its potential impact. 
Table X shows the weighted average parameter set for married and unmarried within 
each group, respectively. We can see that substitution degrees are different between the 
married and unmarried within each group, but especially for urban and rural residents. 
Although there also exist differences in weights for different marital status, the differences 
are not very large. It should be noted that migrant group is youngest and most single. </p>

<p>6. Conclusion 
In this paper,with CHIPS2002 data, we combine multidimensional welfare analysis and 
entropy metrics to identify the best relative weights and substitution degree among 
five attributes which make individuals' welfare have the smallest distance to reported 
happiness for three social groups, urban residents, migrants, and rural residents. We 
use the obtained parameter sets to calculate inequality in the three groups. In addition, 
we compare the differences among the three groups and attempt to link them to 
institutional factors. Main findings in this paper are as follows: first, substitution 
among attributes matters for multidimensional indices of well-being; second, there are 
significant group differences in relative weights of attributes in China, which may be 
related to some social and institutional factors; third, inequality in calculated welfare 
from metric entropy measure 2 is less than reported happiness inequality. From this 
study, we learn that we should incorporate substitution among attributes and take into 
consideration group heterogeneity in multidimensional assessments of well-being and 
poverty. This would seem to suggest that one size-fits-all policies are not appropriate 
for China, and perceptions of well-being, objectively and as self-reported, reflect very 
different concerns, requiring very different approaches. For example, health issues 
dominate rural perceptions of well-being, whereas education and income are more 
prominent among other groups. Based on finite and different substitution values, it is 
safe to assume that different groups place very different monetary values on non-
monetary attributes. This is quite significant for policy analysis going forward. 
There are several potential future research directions. First, we can search more 
precisely in our numerical algorithms. Second, we can further investigate the role of 
attribute substitution in multidimensional well-being. Third, we can adopt clustering 
techniques to identify unique attribute dimensions and reduce double counting 
(Hirschberg et al., 1991, 2001). Fourth, when CHIPS2007 releases specific data on asset </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>1 
r </p>

<p>β 
Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education </p>

<p>Married 
Urban 
−0.097 
0.250 
0.060 
0.115 
0.461 
0.115 
Migrant 
−0.256 
0.263 
0.313 
0.071 
0.318 
0.035 
Rural 
−0.260 
0.044 
0.042 
0.020 
0.893 
0.002 
Unmarried 
Urban 
−0.334 
0.134 
0.053 
0.174 
0.193 
0.446 
Migrant 
−0.443 
0.186 
0.075 
0.098 
0.639 
0.002 
Rural 
−0.764 
0.183 
0.206 
0.099 
0.470 
0.041 </p>

<p>Table X. 
Weighted average 
parameter set in 
bootstrap for 
married and 
unmarried </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>and housing, we can investigate how the relative weights and substation degree change 
over time. </p>

<p>Notes 
1. In this case, we need the two random variables in the same support. </p>

<p>2. We cannot use panel data to control individual fixed effect because CHIPS data is cross-
sectional. However, the focus of this paper is not on investigating the causality of happiness 
but on the methodology of constructing a mapping from self-reported happiness to a 
number of objectively measured attributes. </p>

<p>3. On the one hand, we expect the welfare functions of different groups to be different due to 
the great disparity in their living environment, opportunities, and life style (Meng and  Zhang, 2001), and we wish to compare their differences. On the other hand, if we combine all 
the groups into one, we will get a biased result for welfare function or distribution because 
we lack an accurate and reliable proportion of the three groups, most of which comes from 
the lack of exact data on migrants. </p>

<p>4. We use income rather than consumption for two reasons. First, consumption data are 
not available for CHIPS. Second, income is a generally broader indicator of economic 
opportunity. </p>

<p>5. Due to data limitation, we cannot impute housing expenses for people who live in their own 
houses. However, our computation is mainly based on each group (urban residents, 
migrants and rural residents) so it partly alleviates this problem. </p>

<p>6. We treat answers in the category "don't know" as missing values, and the fractions are &lt;1 
percent in all the three samples. </p>

<p>7. In theory, it is very intensive to search all of the parameter space because it is continuous. </p>

<p>8. If we reduce the α j 's' interval to 0.01, the computation time will increase approximately 
5 
4 ¼ 625 times. </p>

<p>9. The implicit assumption is that there is continuity with respect to parameter intervals. We 
make some trials and find that this holds for well-performed parameters after refinement. 
With more powerful computation ability, we can let parameters change in smaller intervals, 
and then the continuity assumption is more plausible. </p>

<p>10. We thank anonymous referee for this explanation. </p>

<p>11. Another possible explanation is that rural residents conduct self-consumed production, and 
that is not included in the income variable. Thus, income is not relatively important for rural 
residents. We thank anonymous referee for pointing this out. </p>

<p>12. From Table I, we can see that average age of rural residents is not larger than that of urban 
residents, so age should not be the reason why rural residents care more about health. </p>

<p>13. Another method is regression-or model-based method to adjust all the attributes for age 
and marital status. One problem is that it is hard to adjust category variables such as 
happiness and health with this method, another challenge is specification issues for proper 
modeling for each attribute, and jointly. </p>



<p>18 </p>

<p>JES 
42,1 </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Corresponding author 
Professor Esfandiar Maasoumi can be contacted at: esfandiar.maasoumi@emory.edu </p>

<p>Income 
Net asset 
House area 
Health 
Education 
Happiness 
Obs. 
(RMB) 
(RMB) 
(m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
(scale) 
(year) 
(scale) </p>

<p>Age o30 and unmarried 
Urban 
88 
9,771.57 
12,429.08 
18.93 
4.15 
12.92 
3.50 
(9,940.64) 
(19,314.31) 
(14.15) 
(0.78) 
(2.60) 
(0.82) 
Migrant 
1,513 
6,698.52 
7,338.93 
10.50 
4.26 
4.38 
3.37 
(5,956.73) 
(51,368.19) 
(10.34) 
(0.60) 
(3.91) 
(0.80) 
Rural 
111 
2,610.78 
2,497.21 
31.50 
4.18 
7.97 
3.60 
(1,709.03) 
(3,450.37) 
(21.44) 
(0.56) 
(2.83) 
(1.01) 
Age o30 and married 
Urban 
167 
7,920.34 
7,361.50 
17.76 
4.16 
12.44 
3.62 
(4,968.59) 
(16,387.08) 
(8.81) 
(0.79) 
(2.66) 
(0.89) 
Migrant 
744 
7,002.45 
5,045.39 
10.05 
4.28 
8.64 
3.37 
(4,192.52) 
(11,531.09) 
(8.25) 
(0.67) 
(2.37) 
(0.80) 
Rural 
329 
2,738.15 
2,874.91 
24.44 
4.12 
7.77 
3.61 
(2,727.24) 
(4,238.83) 
(14.50) 
(0.72) 
(2.25) 
(0.98) 
30 ⩾ Age ⩽ and unmarried 
Urban 
168 
8,330.37 
12,709.83 
21.06 
3.68 
11.09 
3.02 
(5,168.96) 
(28,324.24) 
(15.60) 
(0.90) 
(3.09) 
(0.99) 
Migrant 
41 
7,173.61 
8,843.88 
13.48 
4.12 
6.63 
2.95 
(5,056.30) 
(20,823.30) 
(11.08) 
(0.64) 
(3.37) 
(0.74) 
Rural 
123 
3,090.98 
1,969.45 
33.13 
3.84 
6.85 
3.10 
(2,832.77) 
(4,201.32) 
(29.86) 
(0.92) 
(2.80) 
(1.11) 
30 ⩾ Age ⩽ 50 and married 
Urban 
3,953 
8,972.41 
13,071.21 
17.82 
3.82 
11.17 
3.46 
(6,040.24) 
(48,764.71) 
(9.20) 
(0.84) 
(2.90) 
(0.86) 
Migrant 
2,460 
7,227.42 
7,877.01 
10.78 
4.21 
7.50 
3.40 
(6,815.61) 
(43,474.59) 
(10.95) 
(0.68) 
(2.68) 
(0.79) 
Rural 
5,288 
3,339.56 
3,393.75 
29.50 
4.06 
7.48 
3.68 
(2,711.24) 
(6,318.62) 
(21.06) 
(0.72) 
(2.44) 
(0.85) 
Age W50 and unmarried 
Urban 
158 
9,167.59 
13,077.64 
25.37 
3.45 
8.81 
3.46 
(5,712.32) 
(18,172.00) 
(14.61) 
(0.93) 
(4.01) 
(0.84) 
Migrant 
27 
6,789.93 
10,641.35 
9.32 
3.70 
4.15 
3.37 
(10,917.96) 
(36,551.89) 
(8.04) 
(1.14) 
(3.52) 
(0.88) 
Rural 
152 
3,010.61 
2,848.60 
32.01 
3.44 
5.31 
3.39 
(1,935.27) 
(5,665.93) 
(22.70) 
(0.96) 
(2.84) 
(1.07) 
Age W50 and married 
Urban 
2,014 
9,322.74 
14,243.70 
20.31 
3.54 
10.09 
3.57 
(5,416.78) 
(29,771.28) 
(10.57) 
(0.86) 
(3.44) 
(0.81) 
Migrant 
236 
6,090.95 
5,883.73 
12.84 
3.83 
5.55 
3.33 
(7,303.52) 
(24,484.50) 
(11.49) 
(0.97) 
(3.35) 
(0.88) 
Rural 
2,510 
2,931.13 
3,168.23 
32.56 
3.72 
6.36 
3.73 
(2,422.56) 
(4,857.50) 
(21.56) 
(0.84) 
(2.60) 
(0.83) </p>

<p>Table AI. 
Statistical 
description for 
attributes by cells </p>

<p>For instructions on how to order reprints of this article, please visit our website: 
www.emeraldgrouppublishing.com/licensing/reprints.htm 
Or contact us for further details: permissions@emeraldinsight.com </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Weights and 
substitution 
degree </p>

<p>Downloaded by University of Texas Libraries At 10:13 30 March 2018 (PT) </p>

</text></tei>