<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs00191-010-0188-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Firms increasingly rely upon external actors for their innovation 
process. Interaction with these actors may occur formally (i.e. through a 
collaboration agreement) or informally (i.e. external actors acts as sources of </p>

<p>I. M. B. Freitas (B) 
Recent theoretical and empirical contributions in the literature on innovation 
have highlighted the importance of establishing external linkages to improve 
the innovation potential of firms. Theoretical papers have argued that external 
actors represent important sources of information for innovation and thus a 
positive relationship between the extent of reliance upon external linkages and 
firm R&amp;D performance should exist (Chesbrough 2003). Empirical research 
has instead looked at the nature of the linkages distinguishing between the 
role played by specific actors such as suppliers, customers (von Hippel 1988), 
and universities (Cohen et al. 2002; Laursen and Salter 2004) as sources of 
information or as partners in formal linkages such as technological agreements 
and R&amp;D joint ventures (Freeman 1991; Hagedoorn 2002). However, the 
analysis of the role played by external linkages in the innovation process goes 
beyond the acknowledgement of their impact on firm performance and/or their 
nature and entails several aspects not all equally well explored in the existing 
literature. 
The first aspect relates to the determinants of the choice of setting up 
external linkages. Although firms' reliance upon external linkages depends on 
internal research capabilities as well as on innovative investments (Cabagnols 
and Le Bas 2002), a relatively neglected aspect is the issue of what drives firms' 
selection of which actors to interact with both formally and/or informally. In 
this respect, it is important to understand whether or not the choice is specific 
to firms' innovation strategies (i.e. doing product or process innovation). 
Recent contributions (Shrolec and Verspagen 2008) suggest that significant 
differences exist with regard to firms' innovative strategies and highlight 
how interacting with different actors contributes to the definition of these 
strategies. The first aim of this paper is to understand whether and to what 
extent firms' reliance upon external linkages is influenced by their innovation 
strategies. By focusing on two types of external linkages-informal linkages 
(i.e. when actors are a source of information for innovation) and formal </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>linkages (i.e. when actors are formal partners in R&amp;D projects)-we will look 
at whether specific innovation strategies lead to interact with specific actors. 
The second aspect concerns the choice of an 'appropriate mix' of formal 
and informal external linkages. Given the complexity of innovative activity, 
we should expect firms to draw upon several information sources and/or 
to combine formal and informal interactions. However, in the literature, 
linkages have generally been examined in isolation (the notable exception 
being Laursen and Salter 2006) or separately from formal partnerships (Bönte 
and Keilbach 2005, being the exception in this case), which provides a rather 
simple view of the innovation process. As a consequence, we know little about 
whether or not firms use linkages and information from different sources in 
a certain combination to carry out a specific innovative outcome. A better 
understanding of the role of external linkages in the innovation process 
should therefore result from taking into account the possibility that firms may 
simultaneously use many information sources as 'inputs' and also cooperate 
with several actors to carry out their innovative projects. 
This perspective opens up the possibility that complementarity or substi-
tution relationships exist between different actors. Indeed, prior research has 
found a significant relation between reliance on external information sources 
and the decision to engage in formal cooperative R&amp;D agreements (Cassiman 
and Veugelers 2002). However, these researches have not examined the issue 
of substitution versus complementarity in a context in which firms can decide 
to use several external sources and at the same time cooperate with several 
actors. In this paper, we will look at the extent to what the use of formal and 
informal external linkages characterized by complementarity or substitution. 
It should be noted that we will control for firm level differences in innova-
tion strategies, and examine complementarity and substitution relationships 
between informal and formal information sources. 
The third aspect concerns whether firms' reliance upon external linkages in 
the innovation process could be specific to the institutional and/or industrial 
context in which they operate. Indeed, the literature on both national (Nelson 
1993) and sectoral (Malerba 2002) systems of innovation stresses the notion 
that the institutional context shapes the pattern of innovation at the firm 
level. However, very few studies analyze whether national differences in the 
institutional and economic structures lead to systematic differences in the 
use of external partners, both as sources of information for innovation and 
as partners for collaboration. By considering four countries with different 
institutional organizations and market structures, we explore to what extent 
reliance upon formal and informal linkages is consistent across countries or 
whether systematic differences exist. 
To address the aspects described above, we employ data from the Com-
munity Innovation Survey (CIS 3). The sample consists of firms that have 
innovated during the period 1998-2000 in four European countries: the 
Netherlands, Norway, Sweden and the UK. We consider the impact of the 
innovative strategies of firms on their reliance upon several external ac-
tors (viz. other enterprises of the group, suppliers, customers, competitors, </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>universities, governmental institutes) as sources of information for innovation 
and as partners for innovation development. To account for the possibility that 
firms rely simultaneously upon several partnerships and sources as 'inputs' 
to the innovation process, a Multivariate Probit analysis is carried out for 
each country separately and then compared. The paper shows that firms 
with different innovative strategies rely upon different portfolios of formal or 
informal sources of information. At the national level, we find that innovative 
strategies seem to be more important for establishing formal links, while 
reliance on informal information sources varies across countries and industries, 
consistent with the view that national and industrial contexts shape the uses of 
information sources. 
The paper is organized as follow. Section 2 reviews the literature on the 
role of formal and informal linkages for the firms' innovative activities. In 
Section 3, we describe the data and the methodology. Section 4 presents the 
results. Section 5 concludes this study. </p>

<p>2 Background literature </p>

<p>Innovative activity does not take place in a business world in which firms are 
isolated from each other and from other organizations. Both institutional and 
technological contexts shape the organizational context in which innovation 
occurs (Whitley 2000). Indeed, industrial innovation can be understood as a 
process that involves search for information and interaction with both market 
based actors (i.e. customers, suppliers, competitors) and research institutions 
(i.e. universities and government) (Salter and Martin 2001). These interactions 
may be the consequence of formal alliances and/or cooperation agreements 
or they may occur in a more informal way. In both cases, they usually entail 
some form of knowledge and/or information exchange between the partners 
involved. Information acquired from external linkages differs in the form of 
access (i.e. informal or formal) as well as on the content being transferred 
(Swann 2002; Monjon and Waelbroeck 2003). In particular, informal use of 
sources is associated with the internal capabilities of firms to access and to 
absorb the information produced by other market or research organizations 
immediately. Instead, the knowledge derived from formal collaborations is 
associated with the use of ideas and developments resulting from access to 
infrastructures, human capital, and innovative capabilities of partners. 
Concerning the content, the capability to translate external information 
inputs into successful innovations has been traditionally associated with the 
presence of high absorptive capacity at the firm level (Cohen and Levinthal 
1989; Cohen et al. 2002). However, high absorptive capacity can be considered 
just a prerequisite. The development of a specific type of innovation is not 
accidental, but reflects the innovative strategies of firms (Swann 2002; Tether 
2002). The capabilities required to innovate successfully vary depending on 
the type of innovation that firms want to develop. As a consequence, firms </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>may choose to interact with specific actors in order to introduce specific 
innovations. 
User-producer interaction, for instance, is widely acknowledged as crucial 
for carrying out product innovation (von Hippel 1988). To develop and to 
market a novel product, getting knowledge and collaborating with customers 
is as important as performing internal R&amp;D investments, since customers 
are an important source of information that may boost product innovation 
(Levin and Reiss 1988; Belderbos et al. 2004a, b). When product innovation 
is based on a recent scientific discovery, it often entails a formal collaboration 
with universities (Beise and Stahl 1999; Tether 2002; Monjon and Waelbroeck 
2003). Firms that mainly pursue an imitation strategy instead seem to prefer 
horizontal technological information from competitors (Baldwin et al. 2002; 
Cabagnols and Le Bas 2002). Firms pursuing process innovation, which entails 
investments in machinery and equipment, seem to require mainly interaction 
with suppliers (Pavitt 1984; Malerba 1992). Swann (2002) finds that British 
process innovators tend to use universities both as a source of information 
and as R&amp;D partners when compared to product innovators. Reinchstein and 
Salter (2006) further find that knowledge from suppliers enhances process 
innovations in firms with a cost-focus strategy, while the probability of doing 
process innovation is negatively associated with the use of customers as a 
source of knowledge. 
Acknowledging the presence of a positive correlation between establishing 
one specific linkage and pursuing a specific innovation is just one part of 
the whole picture. Innovation is a complex phenomenon and typically firms 
tap several sources of information at the same time. In their investigation of 
innovative strategies for a sample of European firms based on the CIS survey 
Shrolec and Verspagen (2008) have identified the presence of three possible 
approaches toward the use of external sources: a 'science based' approach, 
which combines reliance upon both universities and research institutes; a 
'client and industry based' approach, which combines information from cus-
tomers, competitors and other firms of the same group; and a 'supplier based' 
approach, which mainly relies upon information from suppliers. Each of these 
approaches is then linked in one or more types of innovation, with 'science 
based' firms participating more to joint projects with external organizations, 
'client and industry based' firms doing more product innovation and 'supplier 
based' firms relatively more involved in the acquisition of machinery and 
equipment. 
Complementarity may even exist between formal and informal linkages as 
reliance upon several informal sources can also occur in combination with the 
establishment of formal partnerships for innovation, in particular, the intensive 
use of external sources of information seems to enhance cooperation with 
public research organizations (Cassiman and Veugelers 2002), or with external 
actors that are already considered to be an important source of knowledge for 
innovation (Belderbos et al. 2004a, b). 
Finally, besides being related to specific innovation strategies, the need to 
develop specific external linkages may also depend on the type of industry and </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>technology (Pavitt 1984; Marsili 2001). Firms active in science-based industries 
generally tend to benefit most from interactions with public research organiza-
tions and focus on (novel) product innovation (Cabagnols and Le Bas 2002). In 
technological complex and uncertain environments, informal interaction is also 
considered to be beneficial, even in intermediate and mature industry stages 
(Pyka 2000). In supplier-dominated industries, firms rely mainly on suppliers 
as source of process-innovations (Leiponen 2002). Specialized-suppliers rely 
mainly on customers as sources of information to develop customized product-
innovation and to solve technological problems for their clients (Riggs and 
von Hippel 1994). In scale-intensive activities, which are also high-capital-
intensive, firms achieve competitive advantage by exploiting economies of 
scale, and firms tend to innovate more in product than in process (Martínez-
Ros and Labeaga 2002). 
Altogether, existing contributions hint at the following. When innovating is 
complex, firms require the integration of several specific types of knowledge 
and therefore they need to interact with several actors at the same time. On 
the one hand, the need to interact might be the consequence of the presence of 
a relationship of complementarity or substitution between several information 
sources. In other words, different information sources reinforce each other (i.e. 
complementarity) or firms tap different sources to acquire information that is 
difficult to access such as, for example, information possessed by competitors 
(i.e. substitution). On the other hand, interaction with several actors might be 
the consequence of the fact that firms may do several types of innovation which 
differ in terms of novelty and integration of market and production. In other 
words, firms pursue different 'innovation strategies'. In this paper, we analyze 
both the impact of different innovation strategies on the use of formal and 
informal information sources, as well as the complementarity and substitution 
relationship among the sources. </p>

<p>3 Method and data </p>

<p>The discussion in the previous section has highlighted the presence of a 
relationship between firms' innovative strategies and reliance upon external 
linkages. A key objective in this paper is then to analyze whether different 
innovation strategies go together with the use of informal and formal in-
formation sources. 
1 We have, in addition, stressed that firms seem to rely 
upon several external linkages at the same time. In the analysis we will 
therefore examine whether a substitution or complementarity relationship 
exists between informal and formal sources, and within each type of source. </p>

<p>1 A brief note on terminology is in order here. CIS questionnaires ask about 'innovation cooper-
ation' and 'information sources' not about formal or informal sources. Throughout the paper we 
term as 'formal' those linkages with external actors that result from cooperation and 'informal' 
those that involved exchange of information not based on cooperation. </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Our analysis is done separately for each country, following a system of 
simultaneous equations: 
⎧ 
⎨ </p>

<p>⎩ </p>

<p>Pr Inf ij = f i 
k = j Inf kj , k For kj , X i 
Pr For ij = f i 
k Inf kj , k = j For kj , X i </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>where Pr indicates the probability that a (formal or informal) source is used 
by the firm, Inf indicates informal information sources, For indicates formal 
cooperation linkages, j subscripts for the actor relationships we identify (other 
enterprises part of the same group, suppliers, customers, competitors, universi-
ties, government research institutes), k indicates a set including the elements 
subscripted by k, X is a vector of explanatory variables, i = 1, ..., N indicates 
the individual firm, and f indicates a function that we will approximate by the 
probit model. Thus, the model states that the probability for each (formal or 
informal) linkage is a function of the other linkages and a set of explanatory 
variables. For estimation purposes, we append an error term to each equation, 
and we allow these error terms to be correlated between the equations. 
Our dependent variables are binary and have been constructed on the basis 
of two questions contained in the CIS 3 survey. Firms were asked to evaluate 
the importance of the sources of information used for technological innovation 
in the 3 years preceding the survey. We employ this question to identify the 
informal linkages (Inf). 
2 The second question asked firms whether they had 
any co-operation arrangements on innovation activities with other enterprises 
or institutions during the same time period and to indicate the type of partner. 
We employ this question to identify the formal linkages (For). Among the 
several sources, we focus on those that appeared both as sources of information 
and as partners in R&amp;D (i.e. collaboration with consultants and in-house 
sources of information were excluded). Hence, we focus on Other enterprises 
within the group (Inf_oth, F_oth), Suppliers (Inf_sup, For_sup), Customers 
(Inf_cust, F_cust), Competitors (Inf_comp, F_comp), Universities or other 
higher education institutes (Inf_uni, F_uni), and Government research orga-
nizations (Inf_gov, F_gov). 
As explanatory variables, we use four sets of covariates. Our first set de-
scribes the innovation strategy of the firms. New_pdt is a dummy equal to one 
if the firm introduced a product that was new to the market (i.e. it is a 'novel 
innovator'). Imp_pdt is a dummy equal to one if the firm only introduced a 
product that was new to the firm (i.e. it is an imitator). Firms that declared to 
have introduced only process innovation are the reference category. Pdt_prc 
is a dummy equal to one if the firm introduced both a new product and a new </p>

<p>2 The question asked firms to evaluate the importance on a four item scale ('not used', 'low 
importance', 'medium importance', 'high importance'). Responses were recoded into a binary 
variable equal to zero if the source was not used or rated as having a low importance and equal to 
1 if it was considered of medium or high importance. </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>process. Since we consider the introduction of specific innovation a proxy for 
firms' strategy, we treat the innovation types as independent variables that 
reflect firms' choices, rather than dependent variables. 
We expect that the development of innovations with certain characteristics, 
in terms of degree of product novelty and integration between process and 
product innovation, requires specific learning and R&amp;D efforts. Consequently, 
different innovation strategies are expected to rely on different external link-
ages to access specific information and knowledge to innovate. In particular, 
as suggested by our literature review, when compared to firms that make 
process innovations only, we expect 'novel product innovators' to rely more on 
formal and informal linkages with Customers, Universities and Governmental 
research institutes. Innovators with improved products instead should rely 
more on informal linkages with Customers and Competitors. Finally, we 
expect firms that made both product and process innovations to rely relatively 
more than 'only process innovators' on formal linkages with Suppliers and 
Customers, and more on formal and/or informal linkages with public research 
organizations. 
Our second set of variables accounts for the fact that firms carry out 
different types of investments. Several studies have found that firms with 
different investment portfolios might develop different learning processes 
(Noteboom 1999), forge different types of external linkages for innovating 
(Becker and Dietz 2004) and engage in specific types of innovation. The 
variable inv_int is the total share of innovative expenditures (i.e. expenditures 
in intramural, extra-mural R&amp;D, other knowledge, design and training) on the 
turnover of the firm. The variable inv_mac is the share of total expenditures 
on machinery on the total turnover. 
3 Inv_int controls for the firm's efforts in 
building internal capabilities to improve internal efficiency and to respond to 
markets. Inv_mac controls for the impact of 'embodied innovation' on the 
probability to set up external linkages. To capture better the differentiation 
of innovative investment strategy of firms, we also created a variable inv_var 
that is a count variable of the different types of investment activities in which 
the firm has been involved. This variable varies between 0 and 5. 
To these variables we add a set of industry and firm level controls. It 
is widely acknowledged that firms in different industries seem to engage 
in diverse types of technical change and innovative activities, and focus on 
a variety of potential learning processes (Malerba 1992). Thus, the specific 
industrial activity of firms might influence the reliance upon use of specific 
sources of information, both formal and informal. Firms are grouped into 
five categories of industries, according to the taxonomies proposed by Pavitt 
(1984) and Marsili (2001): fundamental process (fund), complex-product </p>

<p>3 Investment strategies reflect the two factor loadings obtained when running a factor analysis on 
the intensity of expenditure in each innovative activity surveyed. </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>(compx), product-engineering (pdt_eng), science-based (scie), and continuous 
process. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Firm level controls include firm size and an indication of the largest market 
in which the firm operates. Size is measured as the logarithm of total the 
number of employees. Large firms, which invest highly in innovative activities, 
are expected to search more for information, to rely relatively more upon 
university research, and to cooperate relatively more with several actors to 
innovate (Cohen et al. 2002; Leiponen 2002; Fontana et al. 2006). Finally, Mkt 
is a dummy variable equal to one if the largest market of the firm is perceived 
to be international. The list of variables and their description is summarized in 
Table 1. 
The estimation method is a Multivariate Probit maximum likelihood in 
which the decisions to engage in formal and informal linkages with a set 
of external organizations are estimated simultaneously. 
5 Formal or informal 
linkages data are binary but they have as many 'dimensions' as the number of 
external partner/ sources. The choices are not mutually exclusive. This method 
allows the simultaneous estimation of more than one binary probit equation 
with correlated disturbances. By allowing disturbances across equations to 
be freely correlated, the method allows to test for the correlation between 
dependent variables conditional on a certain number of common explanatory 
variables (Galia and Legros 2004, p. 1193), thus providing insights into the 
extent of complementary of substitution between them. A positive (negative) 
correlation of the error terms between two equations is taken as an indication 
of complementarity (substitution) between the two dependent variables. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>3.1 Data </p>

<p>The data used in this paper come from the Community Innovation Survey 3 
(CIS 3) that investigates the process of innovation development by firms in 
the period 1998-2000, in four European countries: The Netherlands, Norway, 
Sweden and the UK. The CIS survey asks firms about the type of innovation 
introduced in the 3 years preceding the survey, the sources of information 
they drew upon, their formal collaborative arrangements in order to innovate, 
as well as their expenditures and investments in several types of innovation 
activities. The process of innovation in services and in manufacturing has been </p>

<p>4 Fundamental-process activities include chemicals, plastic and rubber industries. Complex-
products include transport equipment. Product-engineering include machinery and equipment 
industries. Science-based activities include represented pharmaceutical and electrical and optical 
industries. Continuous-process includes all the other manufacturing activities. This is also the 
reference category. 
5 More specifically, the estimation method employed here is based on the 'recursive conditioning 
simulator' implemented for <rs type="software">STATA</rs> by Cappellari and Jenkins (2003). 
6 As a robustness check we have also performed for each country 12 separate Probit regressions 
one for each type of linkage. Results in terms of sign and significance of the estimators of 
multivariate and binary Probit are very similar. These results are available upon request from 
the corresponding author. </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Table 1 Variable description </p>

<p>Variable name 
Description </p>

<p>Dependent variables 
Inf_ot 
Rated as medium or highly important Other Enterprises 
of the same group as source of information to innovate 
Inf_sup 
Rated as medium or highly important Suppliers 
as source of information to innovate 
Inf_cust 
Rated as medium or highly important Customers 
as source of information to innovate 
Inf_comp 
Rated as medium or highly important Competitors 
as source of information to innovate 
Inf_uni 
Rated as medium or highly important Universities 
as source of information to innovate 
Inf_gov 
Rated as medium or highly important Governmental 
research institutes as source of information to innovate 
F_ot 
Did a co-operation arrangement 
with Other enterprises of the same group 
F_sup 
Did a co-operation arrangement with Suppliers 
F_cust. 
Did a co-operation arrangement with Customers 
F_comp 
Did a co-operation arrangement with Competitors 
F_uni. 
Did a co-operation arrangement with Universities 
F_gov 
Did a co-operation arrangement with Governmental 
research institutes 
Explanatory variables 
Innovation 
New_pdt 
The firm introduced a product that was new 
strategy 
to the market 
Imp_pdt 
The firm introduced only a product that was new 
to the firm 
Pdt_prc 
The firm introduced both a product and a process 
innovation 
Investment 
Inv_int 
Total share of innovative expenditures (i.e. expenditures 
type 
in intramural, extra-mural R&amp;D, other knowledge, 
design and training) on the turnover 
Inv_mac 
Share of total investment in machinery on 
the total turnover 
Inv_var 
Count of the different types of investment activities 
the firm has been involved in (Max 5-Min 0) 
Industry 
Fdt 
Fundamental process firm 
controls 
Compx 
Complex-product firm 
Pdt_eng 
Product-engineering firm 
Scie 
Science-based firm 
Firm controls Size 
Logarithm of the total number of employees 
Mkt 
Firm's largest market is international </p>

<p>found to be quite different (Miozzo and Soete 2001; Cainelli et al. 2006). 
Therefore, the analysis undertaken in this paper focuses on manufacturing 
firms with more than nine employees. As the CIS survey does not collect 
data on the sources of information and collaborative arrangements for non-
innovators, we cannot proceed, as we wished, with the analysis for the non-
innovative firms. Thus all the firms in our sample are innovative in the sense 
that they have introduced at least one innovation in the period covered by 
the survey. Our sample includes a total of 3963 firms (1633 firms for The 
Netherlands, 1005 firms for the UK, 559 for Sweden, and 766 for Norway). </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>These firms have established at least 11,245 linkages with external actors 
between 1998 and 2000. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The majority of linkages are established with customers (28.35% of the 
total), followed by suppliers (24.15%), other firms of the same group (15.99%), 
and competitors (15.46%). Fewer linkages are established with universities 
(9.27%) and governmental research institutions (7.00%). The Netherlands is 
the country with the highest number of total established linkages; it accounts 
for slightly more than one third of the total. The UK follows with a share of 
25.37%. The two Scandinavian countries account for the remaining 41.15%. It 
has to be noted that, in general, firms in our sample established more informal 
than formal linkages. 
Statistically significant differences across countries are found in terms of 
the average number of linkages established by innovative firms. Firms in our 
sample established on average 2.84 linkages with different types of external 
actors. Swedish firms established the highest number of linkages on average 
(3.67) followed by Norwegian (3.39), British (2.84) and Dutch (2.31) firms. 
Swedish firms tended to establish the highest number of formal linkages on 
average (1.05), as well as the highest number of informal linkages on average 
(2.63). 
Finally we look at the distribution of linkages by country and by innovation 
strategy. The majority of the linkages (60.33%) were established by firms 
pursuing both product and process strategy. Firms that introduced improved 
products (i.e. a product that was new to the firm) followed with 14.92% of 
total linkages. The rest of the other linkages were distributed across firms that 
introduced novel products (i.e. a product that was new to the market) (13.68%) 
and firms that introduced only process innovation (11.07%). Figure 1 depicts 
the distribution of the linkages by innovation strategies across countries. 
Concerning Dutch firms, the majority of the linkages were established by 
firms doing both product and process innovation, followed by firms intro-
ducing new products (both novel and improved ones). The same applies to 
Norwegian firms. A slightly different pattern emerges for UK and Sweden. In 
the case of the UK, a large majority of linkages were established by firms doing 
process innovation only. In the case of Swedish firms, those introducing novel 
products showed the highest share of the total linkages followed closely by firm 
doing process innovation only. 
All in all, our descriptive results point to the presence of some heterogeneity 
across countries concerning both the type of linkages (formal vs. informal) 
and the pattern of innovative strategies. In the remaining section of the paper 
we will look at the ways in which different innovation strategies impact on 
the choice of specific types of linkages. We will estimate the system of Eq. 1 
for each of the four countries individually, and compare the results across </p>

<p>7 CIS questionnaires provide information on whether or not a linkage with a specific partner is 
established. They do not provide information on the exact number of linkages. Thus, based on this 
information we can infer that at least 11,245 linkages have been established. </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>0.00% 5.00% 10.00% 15.00% 20.00% 25.00% 30.00% 35.00% 40.00% 45.00% 50.00% 55.00% </p>

<p>NL </p>

<p>UK </p>

<p>NW </p>

<p>SW </p>

<p>Only process 
Product &amp; process 
Improved product 
Novel product </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Distribution of linkages by innovation strategies. Each colour sums up to 100% </p>

<p>countries. Then we analyze the estimated correlation matrices for the error 
terms in the equations in each country. Each matrix provides information on 
the complementary or substitutive relation between each type of linkages in 
the country. In the end, we will comment about cross-country similarities and 
differences. </p>

<p>4 Informal and formal linkages and firms' innovative strategy </p>

<p>Estimates (marginal effects) are reported in four separate Tables 2, 3, 4 and 
5, one for each country. 
8 For simplicity and for the purpose of cross country 
comparison, we will focus on the results for each set of explanatory variables 
across the tables. </p>

<p>8 Restrictions concerning data accessibility from National Statistical Offices prevent us from 
pooling the data. This is the main reason why we are estimating four separate sets of regressions. 
The marginal effects reported refer to the single equation for which they are documented (i.e. they 
reflect the increase in probability of a positive outcome in the single equation that is the result of 
the direct effect of a change in the exogenous variable to which the marginal effect refers). The 
marginal effects are calculated as is usual in Probit models. The standard errors of the marginal 
effects are calculated using the estimated variance-covariance matrix of parameters in the single 
equation. </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Table 2 Multivariate Probit estimations (marginal effects) of reliance upon formal and informal external linkages </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust 
Inf_comp Inf_uni </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>F_uni </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt </p>

<p>−0.0006 </p>

<p>−0.0293 </p>

<p>0.0255 </p>

<p>−0.0467 </p>

<p>−0.0040 </p>

<p>0.0151 </p>

<p>0.0571 </p>

<p>0.0314 </p>

<p>0.1284 </p>

<p>0.0578 </p>

<p>0.0872 </p>

<p>0.0462 </p>

<p>0.0503 </p>

<p>0.0503 </p>

<p>0.0336 </p>

<p>0.0503 </p>

<p>0.0415 </p>

<p>0.0324 </p>

<p>0.0323 a </p>

<p>0.0407 </p>

<p>0.0403 c </p>

<p>0.0226 b </p>

<p>0.0381 b </p>

<p>0.0260 a </p>

<p>Imp_pdt </p>

<p>0.1131 </p>

<p>0.0187 </p>

<p>0.0570 </p>

<p>0.0002 </p>

<p>−0.0819 </p>

<p>0.0018 </p>

<p>0.0117 </p>

<p>−0.0199 </p>

<p>0.0970 </p>

<p>0.0202 </p>

<p>0.0034 </p>

<p>0.0165 </p>

<p>0.0665 a </p>

<p>0.0631 </p>

<p>0.0339 a </p>

<p>0.0643 </p>

<p>0.0498 a </p>

<p>0.0437 </p>

<p>0.0459 </p>

<p>0.0549 </p>

<p>0.0636 </p>

<p>0.0346 </p>

<p>0.0539 </p>

<p>0.0398 </p>

<p>Pdt_prc </p>

<p>0.0517 </p>

<p>0.0263 </p>

<p>0.0207 </p>

<p>−0.0488 </p>

<p>0.0154 </p>

<p>0.0082 </p>

<p>0.0164 </p>

<p>0.0751 </p>

<p>0.1268 </p>

<p>0.0186 </p>

<p>0.0772 </p>

<p>0.0248 </p>

<p>0.0510 </p>

<p>0.0502 </p>

<p>0.0340 </p>

<p>0.0506 </p>

<p>0.0428 </p>

<p>0.0333 </p>

<p>0.0317 </p>

<p>0.0421 a </p>

<p>0.0415 c </p>

<p>0.0193 </p>

<p>0.0388 b </p>

<p>0.0260 </p>

<p>Inv_int </p>

<p>−0.0027 </p>

<p>−0.0069 </p>

<p>0.0124 </p>

<p>−0.0003 </p>

<p>0.0051 </p>

<p>0.0021 </p>

<p>0.0042 </p>

<p>0.0063 </p>

<p>0.0013 </p>

<p>0.0011 </p>

<p>0.0074 </p>

<p>0.0037 </p>

<p>0.0033 </p>

<p>0.0035 b </p>

<p>0.0053 b </p>

<p>0.0031 </p>

<p>0.0025 b </p>

<p>0.0019 </p>

<p>0.0017 b </p>

<p>0.0025 b </p>

<p>0.0027 </p>

<p>0.0009 </p>

<p>0.0022 c </p>

<p>0.0015 b </p>

<p>Inv_mac </p>

<p>−0.0016 </p>

<p>0.0129 </p>

<p>0.0016 </p>

<p>0.0030 </p>

<p>−0.0015 </p>

<p>−0.0031 </p>

<p>0.0007 </p>

<p>0.0006 </p>

<p>0.0047 </p>

<p>0.0016 </p>

<p>−0.0111 </p>

<p>−0.0031 </p>

<p>0.0075 </p>

<p>0.0085 </p>

<p>0.0038 </p>

<p>0.0047 </p>

<p>0.0059 </p>

<p>0.0058 </p>

<p>0.0046 </p>

<p>0.0060 </p>

<p>0.0036 </p>

<p>0.0010 </p>

<p>0.0093 </p>

<p>0.0052 </p>

<p>Inv_var </p>

<p>0.0184 </p>

<p>0.0371 </p>

<p>0.0264 </p>

<p>0.0271 </p>

<p>0.0256 </p>

<p>0.0173 </p>

<p>0.0236 </p>

<p>0.0525 </p>

<p>0.0408 </p>

<p>0.0037 </p>

<p>0.0483 </p>

<p>0.0208 </p>

<p>0.0127 </p>

<p>0.0131 c </p>

<p>0.0099 c </p>

<p>0.0130 b </p>

<p>0.0107 b </p>

<p>0.0080 b </p>

<p>0.0076 c </p>

<p>0.0102 c </p>

<p>0.0098 c </p>

<p>0.0040 </p>

<p>0.0092 c </p>

<p>0.0060 c </p>

<p>Scie </p>

<p>0.1069 </p>

<p>−0.0418 </p>

<p>0.0097 </p>

<p>0.1084 </p>

<p>−0.0530 </p>

<p>−0.0480 </p>

<p>−0.0406 </p>

<p>0.0084 </p>

<p>−0.0086 </p>

<p>−0.0050 </p>

<p>0.0186 </p>

<p>−0.0250 </p>

<p>0.0603 a </p>

<p>0.0592 </p>

<p>0.0408 </p>

<p>0.0592 a </p>

<p>0.0468 </p>

<p>0.0331 </p>

<p>0.0303 </p>

<p>0.0474 </p>

<p>0.0457 </p>

<p>0.0201 </p>

<p>0.0436 </p>

<p>0.0239 </p>

<p>Compx </p>

<p>0.2099 </p>

<p>0.0479 </p>

<p>−0.0167 </p>

<p>−0.1290 </p>

<p>−0.1879 </p>

<p>−0.1111 </p>

<p>−0.0606 </p>

<p>0.1527 </p>

<p>0.1014 </p>

<p>0.1177 </p>

<p>−0.1350 </p>

<p>0.0205 </p>

<p>0.1054 b </p>

<p>0.1017 </p>

<p>0.0730 </p>

<p>0.0974 </p>

<p>0.0379 c </p>

<p>0.0272 c </p>

<p>0.0372 </p>

<p>0.1003 </p>

<p>0.0898 </p>

<p>0.0707 a </p>

<p>0.0343 c </p>

<p>0.0530 </p>

<p>Pdt_eng </p>

<p>0.0034 </p>

<p>−0.1020 </p>

<p>0.0922 </p>

<p>0.1587 </p>

<p>0.0175 </p>

<p>−0.0469 </p>

<p>−0.0596 </p>

<p>0.0167 </p>

<p>0.0303 </p>

<p>0.0103 </p>

<p>0.0222 </p>

<p>−0.0340 </p>

<p>0.0689 </p>

<p>0.0693 </p>

<p>0.0361 b </p>

<p>0.0672 b </p>

<p>0.0571 </p>

<p>0.0346 </p>

<p>0.0298 b </p>

<p>0.0570 </p>

<p>0.0552 </p>

<p>0.0263 </p>

<p>0.0521 </p>

<p>0.0245 </p>

<p>Fdt </p>

<p>0.1357 </p>

<p>−0.0452 </p>

<p>0.0572 </p>

<p>−0.0438 </p>

<p>0.0301 </p>

<p>0.0078 </p>

<p>−0.0591 </p>

<p>0.0453 </p>

<p>−0.0182 </p>

<p>0.0397 </p>

<p>0.0767 </p>

<p>−0.0333 </p>

<p>0.0900 </p>

<p>0.0868 </p>

<p>0.0442 </p>

<p>0.0831 </p>

<p>0.0767 </p>

<p>0.0569 </p>

<p>0.0387 </p>

<p>0.0760 </p>

<p>0.0659 </p>

<p>0.0431 </p>

<p>0.0792 </p>

<p>0.0354 </p>

<p>Size </p>

<p>0.1000 </p>

<p>0.0201 </p>

<p>−0.0013 </p>

<p>0.0281 </p>

<p>0.0785 </p>

<p>0.0455 </p>

<p>0.0583 </p>

<p>0.0293 </p>

<p>0.0297 </p>

<p>0.0111 </p>

<p>0.0894 </p>

<p>0.0403 </p>

<p>0.0150 c </p>

<p>0.0152 </p>

<p>0.0107 </p>

<p>0.0150 a </p>

<p>0.0126 c </p>

<p>0.0093 c </p>

<p>0.0095 c </p>

<p>0.0121 b </p>

<p>0.0116 b </p>

<p>0.0047 b </p>

<p>0.0121 c </p>

<p>0.0078 c </p>

<p>Mkt </p>

<p>0.0430 </p>

<p>−0.0946 </p>

<p>0.1145 </p>

<p>0.1087 </p>

<p>−0.0300 </p>

<p>−0.0352 </p>

<p>0.0209 </p>

<p>−0.0206 </p>

<p>−0.0058 </p>

<p>−0.0049 </p>

<p>0.0157 </p>

<p>0.0084 </p>

<p>0.0456 </p>

<p>0.0463 b </p>

<p>0.0325 c </p>

<p>0.0462 b </p>

<p>0.0398 </p>

<p>0.0306 </p>

<p>0.0286 </p>

<p>0.0380 </p>

<p>0.0366 </p>

<p>0.0155 </p>

<p>0.0341 </p>

<p>0.0228 </p>

<p>Results for Sweden 
Obs: 559; Wald Chisq, 533.40 (significant at 1%); Log likelihood, </p>

<p>−2,620.06 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at 10% </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Significant at 5% </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Significant at 1% </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Table 3 Multivariate Probit estimations (marginal effects) of reliance upon formal and informal external linkages </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust 
Inf_comp Inf_uni </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>F_uni </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt </p>

<p>0.0189 </p>

<p>−0.0273 </p>

<p>0.0089 </p>

<p>−0.0450 </p>

<p>0.0331 </p>

<p>−0.0067 </p>

<p>0.0510 </p>

<p>0.0825 </p>

<p>0.0887 </p>

<p>0.0077 </p>

<p>0.0742 </p>

<p>0.0137 </p>

<p>0.0401 </p>

<p>0.0411 </p>

<p>0.0365 </p>

<p>0.0403 </p>

<p>0.0305 </p>

<p>0.0311 </p>

<p>0.0262 a </p>

<p>0.0307 c </p>

<p>0.0311 c </p>

<p>0.0127 </p>

<p>0.0269 c </p>

<p>0.0260 </p>

<p>Imp_pdt </p>

<p>0.0578 </p>

<p>−0.0965 </p>

<p>0.1409 </p>

<p>0.1101 </p>

<p>0.0227 </p>

<p>−0.0346 </p>

<p>0.1301 </p>

<p>0.0168 </p>

<p>0.0629 </p>

<p>0.0233 </p>

<p>0.0968 </p>

<p>0.1015 </p>

<p>0.0734 </p>

<p>0.0724 </p>

<p>0.0455 c </p>

<p>0.0735 </p>

<p>0.0631 </p>

<p>0.0548 </p>

<p>0.0762 a </p>

<p>0.0638 </p>

<p>0.0704 </p>

<p>0.0418 </p>

<p>0.0724 </p>

<p>0.0727 </p>

<p>Pdt_prc </p>

<p>0.0421 </p>

<p>0.0774 </p>

<p>0.1646 </p>

<p>0.1542 </p>

<p>0.0634 </p>

<p>0.0404 </p>

<p>0.0908 </p>

<p>0.0590 </p>

<p>0.0696 </p>

<p>0.0308 </p>

<p>0.0887 </p>

<p>0.1044 </p>

<p>0.0491 </p>

<p>0.0501 </p>

<p>0.0470 c </p>

<p>0.0483 c </p>

<p>0.0364 a </p>

<p>0.0376 </p>

<p>0.0284 c </p>

<p>0.0357 a </p>

<p>0.0358 a </p>

<p>0.0152 b </p>

<p>0.0294 c </p>

<p>0.0303 c </p>

<p>Inv_int </p>

<p>0.0022 </p>

<p>−0.0078 </p>

<p>−0.0028 </p>

<p>0.0004 </p>

<p>0.0059 </p>

<p>0.0066 </p>

<p>0.0026 </p>

<p>0.0016 </p>

<p>0.0012 </p>

<p>−0.0034 </p>

<p>0.0028 </p>

<p>0.0041 </p>

<p>0.0020 </p>

<p>0.0024 c </p>

<p>0.0017 </p>

<p>0.0020 </p>

<p>0.0014 c </p>

<p>0.0016 c </p>

<p>0.0011 b </p>

<p>0.0013 </p>

<p>0.0013 </p>

<p>0.0017 b </p>

<p>0.0010 c </p>

<p>0.0011 c </p>

<p>Inv_mac </p>

<p>−0.0126 </p>

<p>0.0038 </p>

<p>0.0006 </p>

<p>−0.0049 </p>

<p>0.0016 </p>

<p>−0.0078 </p>

<p>0.0013 </p>

<p>−0.0077 </p>

<p>−0.0013 </p>

<p>−0.0035 </p>

<p>0.0009 </p>

<p>0.0020 </p>

<p>0.0071 a </p>

<p>0.0036 </p>

<p>0.0038 </p>

<p>0.0043 </p>

<p>0.0027 </p>

<p>0.0050 </p>

<p>0.0022 </p>

<p>0.0047 </p>

<p>0.0027 </p>

<p>0.0042 </p>

<p>0.0023 </p>

<p>0.0025 </p>

<p>Inv_var </p>

<p>−0.0100 </p>

<p>0.0076 </p>

<p>0.0368 </p>

<p>0.0215 </p>

<p>0.0203 </p>

<p>0.0334 </p>

<p>0.0209 </p>

<p>0.0489 </p>

<p>0.0476 </p>

<p>0.0069 </p>

<p>0.0307 </p>

<p>0.0534 </p>

<p>0.0113 </p>

<p>0.0117 </p>

<p>0.0107 c </p>

<p>0.0113 a </p>

<p>0.0083 b </p>

<p>0.0086 c </p>

<p>0.0068 c </p>

<p>0.0081 c </p>

<p>0.0081 c </p>

<p>0.0037 a </p>

<p>0.0069 c </p>

<p>0.0072 c </p>

<p>Scie </p>

<p>0.0806 </p>

<p>−0.0200 </p>

<p>0.1462 </p>

<p>0.0932 </p>

<p>−0.0585 </p>

<p>−0.0617 </p>

<p>−0.0537 </p>

<p>−0.0154 </p>

<p>−0.0305 </p>

<p>0.0180 </p>

<p>−0.0385 </p>

<p>−0.0194 </p>

<p>0.0617 </p>

<p>0.0606 </p>

<p>0.0433 c </p>

<p>0.0597 </p>

<p>0.0350 a </p>

<p>0.0372 a </p>

<p>0.0262 b </p>

<p>0.0396 </p>

<p>0.0380 </p>

<p>0.0247 </p>

<p>0.0292 </p>

<p>0.0331 </p>

<p>Compx </p>

<p>−0.1771 </p>

<p>−0.0692 </p>

<p>0.1175 </p>

<p>−0.0261 </p>

<p>−0.1345 </p>

<p>−0.1166 </p>

<p>−0.0912 </p>

<p>−0.1165 </p>

<p>−0.1073 </p>

<p>−0.0030 </p>

<p>−0.0482 </p>

<p>−0.1163 </p>

<p>0.0883 b </p>

<p>0.1116 </p>

<p>0.0772 </p>

<p>0.1054 </p>

<p>0.0347 c </p>

<p>0.0538 b </p>

<p>0.0304 c </p>

<p>0.0405 c </p>

<p>0.0454 b </p>

<p>0.0330 </p>

<p>0.0504 </p>

<p>0.0240 c </p>

<p>Pdt_eng </p>

<p>−0.0383 </p>

<p>−0.0273 </p>

<p>0.1240 </p>

<p>0.0258 </p>

<p>−0.0260 </p>

<p>−0.1047 </p>

<p>−0.0754 </p>

<p>−0.0243 </p>

<p>0.0660 </p>

<p>−0.0008 </p>

<p>−0.0179 </p>

<p>0.0150 </p>

<p>0.0553 </p>

<p>0.0582 </p>

<p>0.0427 c </p>

<p>0.0581 </p>

<p>0.0389 </p>

<p>0.0330 c </p>

<p>0.0238 c </p>

<p>0.0380 </p>

<p>0.0480 </p>

<p>0.0184 </p>

<p>0.0330 </p>

<p>0.0380 </p>

<p>Fdt </p>

<p>−0.0076 </p>

<p>−0.1491 </p>

<p>−0.0986 </p>

<p>−0.1943 </p>

<p>−0.0898 </p>

<p>−0.0347 </p>

<p>−0.0951 </p>

<p>−0.0333 </p>

<p>0.1083 </p>

<p>−0.0110 </p>

<p>0.0068 </p>

<p>−0.0044 </p>

<p>0.0892 </p>

<p>0.0902 a </p>

<p>0.0895 </p>

<p>0.0780 b </p>

<p>0.0501 a </p>

<p>0.0638 </p>

<p>0.0274 c </p>

<p>0.0622 </p>

<p>0.0883 </p>

<p>0.0229 </p>

<p>0.0626 </p>

<p>0.0618 </p>

<p>Size </p>

<p>0.1262 </p>

<p>0.0276 </p>

<p>0.0116 </p>

<p>0.0290 </p>

<p>0.0446 </p>

<p>0.0351 </p>

<p>0.0502 </p>

<p>0.0349 </p>

<p>0.0336 </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>0.0351 </p>

<p>0.0517 </p>

<p>0.0165 c </p>

<p>0.0165 a </p>

<p>0.0147 </p>

<p>0.0161 a </p>

<p>0.0116 c </p>

<p>0.0122 c </p>

<p>0.0096 c </p>

<p>0.0115 c </p>

<p>0.0115 c </p>

<p>0.0051 </p>

<p>0.0095 c </p>

<p>0.0099 c </p>

<p>Mkt </p>

<p>0.0329 </p>

<p>−0.0415 </p>

<p>0.0721 </p>

<p>0.0257 </p>

<p>0.0798 </p>

<p>−0.0011 </p>

<p>0.0249 </p>

<p>−0.0444 </p>

<p>−0.0271 </p>

<p>−0.0292 </p>

<p>0.0747 </p>

<p>0.0201 </p>

<p>0.0397 </p>

<p>0.0414 </p>

<p>0.0380 a </p>

<p>0.0408 </p>

<p>0.0292 c </p>

<p>0.0315 </p>

<p>0.0246 </p>

<p>0.0297 </p>

<p>0.0298 </p>

<p>0.0144 b </p>

<p>0.0240 c </p>

<p>0.0251 </p>

<p>Results for Norway 
Obs, 766; Wald Chisq, 523.92 (significant at 1%); Log likelihood, </p>

<p>−3,741.53 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at 10% </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Significant at 5% </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Significant at 1% </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Table 4 Multivariate Probit estimations (marginal effects) of reliance upon formal and informal external linkages </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>F_uni </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt </p>

<p>−0.010 </p>

<p>−0.036 </p>

<p>0.124 </p>

<p>−0.029 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.028 c </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.017 a </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.014 b </p>

<p>0.015 c </p>

<p>0.018 a </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>Imp_pdt </p>

<p>0.067 </p>

<p>−0.058 </p>

<p>0.197 </p>

<p>0.090 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.068 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.098 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.038 c </p>

<p>0.044 b </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.034 b </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.040 b </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>Pdt_prc </p>

<p>0.034 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.120 </p>

<p>0.062 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>0.062 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.031 c </p>

<p>0.030 b </p>

<p>0.018 b </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 c </p>

<p>0.019 c </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.008 b </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>Inv_int </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 b </p>

<p>0.001 c </p>

<p>0.001 c </p>

<p>0.001 b </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 a </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.001 c </p>

<p>Inv_mac </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 b </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 a </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 b </p>

<p>Inv_var </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.006 b </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.003 c </p>

<p>0.003 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.002 c </p>

<p>0.002 c </p>

<p>0.002 c </p>

<p>Scie </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>−0.159 </p>

<p>0.049 </p>

<p>0.067 </p>

<p>0.086 </p>

<p>−0.007 </p>

<p>−0.040 </p>

<p>−0.013 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>−0.011 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.068 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.040 c </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p>0.045 </p>

<p>0.034 b </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.013 c </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.026 c </p>

<p>Compx </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>−0.015 </p>

<p>0.133 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>−0.014 </p>

<p>0.049 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.056 </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.055 b </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.034 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.029 a </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>Pdt_eng </p>

<p>−0.066 </p>

<p>−0.076 </p>

<p>0.104 </p>

<p>0.053 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>−0.021 </p>

<p>−0.027 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>−0.027 </p>

<p>−0.022 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.034 a </p>

<p>0.036 b </p>

<p>0.037 c </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.014 a </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.011 b </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>Fdt </p>

<p>0.132 </p>

<p>−0.059 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>−0.007 </p>

<p>−0.020 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>−0.013 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.037 c </p>

<p>0.036 a </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.026 a </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.019 a </p>

<p>Size </p>

<p>0.076 </p>

<p>−0.011 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.010 c </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.010 c </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.007 c </p>

<p>0.005 c </p>

<p>0.005 c </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.002 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>Mkt </p>

<p>0.101 </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>0.062 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>−0.018 </p>

<p>−0.023 </p>

<p>−0.017 </p>

<p>−0.007 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.026 c </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.025 b </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>Results for The Netherlands 
Obs, 1,633; Wald Chisq, 696.12 (significant at 1%); Log likelihood, </p>

<p>−6,981.42 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at 10% </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Significant at 5% </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Significant at 1% </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Table 5 Multivariate Probit estimations (marginal effects) of reliance upon formal and informal external linkages </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>F_uni </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>−0.130 </p>

<p>0.126 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>−0.014 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.067 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>−0.009 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.037 c </p>

<p>0.035 c </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.026 c </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.012 b </p>

<p>Imp_pdt </p>

<p>−0.062 </p>

<p>−0.182 </p>

<p>0.059 </p>

<p>0.131 </p>

<p>−0.019 </p>

<p>−0.024 </p>

<p>−0.038 </p>

<p>−0.035 </p>

<p>0.062 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.014 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.047 c </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.046 c </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.014 c </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.036 a </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>Pdt_prc </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.017 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>−0.022 </p>

<p>−0.012 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>−0.019 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.011 a </p>

<p>Inv_int </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 a </p>

<p>0.001 b </p>

<p>0.001 b </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>Inv_mac </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.003 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>Inv_var </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 b </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.011 c </p>

<p>0.010 b </p>

<p>0.007 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.004 c </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.007 c </p>

<p>0.003 b </p>

<p>0.005 c </p>

<p>0.002 c </p>

<p>Scie </p>

<p>0.051 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>−0.041 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>−0.024 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.045 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.040 c </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.008 c </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>Compx </p>

<p>0.096 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.108 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.061 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>−0.020 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>−0.035 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.057 a </p>

<p>0.049 </p>

<p>0.050 b </p>

<p>0.053 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>Pdt_eng </p>

<p>−0.019 </p>

<p>0.096 </p>

<p>0.080 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>0.158 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.034 </p>

<p>−0.026 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.061 </p>

<p>0.047 b </p>

<p>0.054 </p>

<p>0.057 </p>

<p>0.054 c </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.006 c </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>Fdt </p>

<p>0.122 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>−0.035 </p>

<p>−0.090 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>−0.008 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.011 </p>

<p>0.075 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>0.057 b </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.054 </p>

<p>0.049 a </p>

<p>0.044 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.037 b </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>Size </p>

<p>0.098 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.013 c </p>

<p>0.011 a </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.012 a </p>

<p>0.009 c </p>

<p>0.005 c </p>

<p>0.005 c </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.003 a </p>

<p>0.005 b </p>

<p>0.003 c </p>

<p>Mkt </p>

<p>0.051 </p>

<p>−0.076 </p>

<p>0.059 </p>

<p>0.126 </p>

<p>0.104 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>−0.011 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.074 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.037 b </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.038 c </p>

<p>0.044 b </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.059 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.069 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.062 </p>

<p>Results for the UK 
Obs, 1,005; Wald Chisq, 547.34 (significant at 1%); Log likelihood, </p>

<p>−4,094.64 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Significant at 10% </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Significant at 5% </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Significant at 1% </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Results for innovative strategies We start by looking at the relationship 
between firms' innovation strategies and reliance upon formal and informal 
linkages. Concerning novel product innovators (New_pdt), our results suggest 
that firms pursuing this strategy were relatively more likely than only process 
innovators (the reference category) to set up linkages with customers, and to 
a lesser extent with research organizations. This result holds across countries, 
although for Scandinavian firms only in the case of formal linkages. Swedish 
novel product innovators were also relatively more likely to engage in formal 
collaborations with competitors. Norwegian and Dutch novel product innova-
tors also tended to rely upon (formal) collaborations with suppliers and other 
firms of the group. 
Firms that introduced improved products (Imp_pdt) present a different 
profile. Still, customers are important for these firms (both as a source of 
information and as formal partners). However, our marginal effects show that 
other actors matter as well. British and Dutch firms in this category tended to 
draw knowledge informally from competitors (the magnitude of the effect is 
the highest in the case of British firms) reflecting the importance of following 
an imitation strategy. 'Improved product innovators' were also less likely to 
tap informally into suppliers in the UK. Norwegian and Dutch firms that 
introduced improved products seemed relatively more likely to engage in 
formal collaboration with other enterprises of the group, in contrast to British 
firms. 
Finally, we find heterogeneity in behavior for firms that introduced both 
a new product and a process (Pdt_prc). Again customers and public research 
organizations (governmental institutes in Norway and the UK, universities in 
Norway, Sweden, and the Netherlands) were important mainly as partners 
in formal collaborations. In the case of cooperation with customers, the 
effect seems to have been particularly strong for Sweden. Competitors were 
also an important source of information for all firms, except for British and 
Swedish product and process innovators. (Formal) interaction with suppliers 
was relevant for Dutch firms in this group and to a lesser extent for Swedish 
and Norwegian firms. Informal linkages with customers were important for 
product and process innovators in Norway and the Netherlands. In this case, 
a standard deviation increase around the mean increases the probability of 
tapping into customers of 16.6% and 12.3% for Norwegian and Dutch product 
and process innovators respectively. </p>

<p>Results for investment type Firms' investments are captured by three vari-
ables. In the case of innovative investment intensity (Inv_int), our marginal 
effects are generally positive suggesting a direct correlation with reliance upon 
some informal and formal external actors in each of the four countries. For 
instance, the greater the firms' expenditures in internal innovative capabilities, 
the more firms were able to interact (either formally or informally) with gov-
ernmental institutes and universities particularly in the Scandinavian countries. 
The more firms invested in innovative activities, the more they interacted 
with competitors in the Netherlands. Negative and significant coefficients were </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>instead found for formal interactions with customers in UK, competitors in 
Norway and informal interactions with suppliers in Norway. When significant, 
marginal effects are generally low. 
Concerning investment in machinery (Inv_mac), our results indicate that, in 
a few cases the share of total expenditures in machinery on the total turnover 
significantly increased the likelihood of engaging in formal linkages. When 
we look at informal relationships though, firms with a relatively higher share 
of investment in machinery were less likely to tap universities as source of 
information in The Netherlands. Higher investment in machinery relatively 
increases the likelihood of interacting with other enterprises of the group 
as well as with suppliers in the UK, in contrast to Norway. These results 
suggest that that in some countries (i.e. The Netherlands) information acquired 
from research organizations may substitute for investment in machinery. One 
explanation is that universities may allow firms to use specific equipment for 
their innovation. 
Finally, marginal effects for investment variety (inv_var) are generally 
positive indicating that the more diversified the investment portfolio, the more 
likely firms were to rely upon external actors both as source of information 
(except for suppliers) and as cooperation partners. In this case, the magnitude 
of the marginal effect is higher than in the previous cases and similar across 
countries. </p>

<p>Results for industry controls When looking at the impact of industrial control 
variables, results reveal some similarities but also important cross country 
differences. 
Concerning firms pursuing science-based activities (scie), our marginal 
effects are positive and particularly strong for British and Norwegian firms 
setting up informal linkages with customers. Norwegian science-based firms 
were also less likely to collaborate with enterprises of the group. Dutch 
and British science-based firms tended to establish formal relationships with 
governmental research institutes. Dutch science-based firms were also more 
likely to use informal linkages with universities. Consequently, science-based 
activities seemed to be more R&amp;D intensive and more dependent on public 
research in the Netherlands, and carried on in a more 'market-oriented' way 
in the UK and in Norway. 
The picture appears more variegated in the case of complex-product firms 
(compx). In the UK and the Netherlands, these firms tapped customer in-
formation to innovate. In Sweden, by contrast, these firms set up relatively 
fewer formal collaborations with universities. Norwegian firms in complex-
product activities were less likely to collaborate with other enterprises of the 
group, suppliers and clients. Dutch firms active in this sector seemed instead to 
collaborate with competitors. All in all, our results indicate that the nature of 
the activity of complex product firms was so different across the four countries 
that they needed to integrate in different ways different bundles of knowledge, 
and also outsource different steps of the production process. </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Concerning firms active in product-engineering industries (pdt_eng) mar-
ginal effects are positive and relatively higher in the case of British firms that 
interacted informally with universities and suppliers, and with customers both 
in Norway, Sweden, and the Netherlands. Instead, firms relied less on informal 
linkages suppliers in the Netherlands, and less on informal linkages with public 
research organizations in Norway. Thus, product-engineering firms seemed to 
rely more on public research results in the UK, while they relied more on 
customer-relationships in the Netherlands and the Scandinavian countries. 
Finally, our results suggest that British and Dutch firms active in 
fundamental-process activities (Fdt) relied more than firms in continuous-
process activities upon relationships with other enterprises of their group to 
innovate. We find the opposite for Norwegian firms. Swedish firms active 
in fundamental-process activities did not differ much on the reliance on 
informal linkages with firms in continuous-process activities. Fundamental-
process activities seems to present a similar pattern of reliance upon external 
linkages across the four countries. </p>

<p>Results for control variables Results for the impact of control variables, 
capturing the organizational and market characteristics of firms, are quite con-
sistent with previous results from the existing literature. In the four European 
countries analyzed, large firms were generally more likely than smaller ones 
to engage in formal collaborations as suggested by the positive and significant 
coefficient of size. This relationship holds for any actor, except for supplier and 
customers in the UK, and for competitors in Norway. Moreover, the larger 
the firm, the higher is the probability of drawing upon informal sources of 
information from all actors, except for suppliers and customers. 
Concerning the location of the largest market (mkt), firms whose largest 
market is international had a relatively higher propensity to interact with 
public research organization (universities) in Norway and UK and with cus-
tomers (UK and Netherlands). Also imitating competitors seems to have been 
important for these firms especially in UK and Sweden. </p>

<p>4.1 Complementarity and substitution among external linkages </p>

<p>Our empirical method allows us to produce, from each estimate, a matrix of 
correlation coefficients of the error terms in the equations for each dependent 
variable. Looking at the sign of the coefficients provides an indication as 
to whether the external linkages are complementary (positive coefficient) or 
substitutes (negative coefficient) for the firms in the sample. In this section, 
we comment upon the relationships. Tables reporting the coefficients for each 
country separately are contained in the Appendix. 
In all countries we do not find evidence of a significant relationship of 
substitution among any actor. Coefficients for formal linkages are generally 
significant and positive, thus complementarity exists between these external 
sources of information. In other words, firms that established formal col-
laborations tended to do so with more than one actor. Complementarity is </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>also found for informal linkages with competitors, suppliers and customers 
and between informal linkages with competitors and informal linkages with 
governmental research institutes and universities, though to a lesser extent. 
This result suggests that interactions with competitors may be more efficient if 
combined with interactions with public research organizations. 
Complementarity is stronger in the case of formal collaborations, and 
weaker in the case of informal linkages especially with customers and com-
petitors. In Norway, we also find strong complementarity between formal and 
informal linkages with other enterprises of the group and formal collaboration 
with universities. 
Consistently with previous findings (Belderbos et al. 2004a, b), firms in our 
sample tended to collaborate with actors that they also used as sources of 
information. However, in our case complementarity between formal and in-
formal linkages with the same actor was generally weak except for interactions 
involving governmental research institutes and universities. In Norway, formal 
and informal linkages with competitors were not significantly complementary. 
Interestingly, linkages with research organizations tended to exhibit the 
highest number of significant complementarities, reflecting the notion that 
firms relied upon information from research organizations to improve their 
access to an even wider pool of sources. The Netherlands is the country in 
which we found the highest number of complementarities among all types of 
external linkages, except for informal linkages with other enterprises of the 
group and government research institutes, as well as for collaboration with cus-
tomers and competitors. Norway instead had the smallest number of significant 
correlations, followed by Sweden. In particular, in Sweden, the number of 
complementarities was the smallest for interactions among universities and 
governmental research institutes and other informal sources. In Norway, the 
number of complementarities was the smallest for informal interactions with 
suppliers and Customers. These results suggest that Norwegian and Swedish 
firms were eventually more able to absorb external information from informal 
interactions without the need to collaborate with these actors or access other 
sources. Dutch and British firms instead needed to use a wider mix of external 
sources and strategies to innovate effectively. </p>

<p>4.2 Highlighting cross-country similarities and differences </p>

<p>The final step of our analysis involves the identification of cross-country 
similarities and/or differences in the determinants of the choice of formal and 
informal external linkages. To achieve this goal, we decided to synthesise our 
previous results in two separate tables, one summarizing results for formal 
linkages and the other for informal linkages. In order to keep our exposition 
clear, we only focus on whether or not a specific variable was found significant 
in the previous analysis. Thus, the signs in each table correspond to the 
countries in which each coefficient was found to be significantly different from 
zero. 
Table 6 below reports the results for the subset of formal linkages. </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Table 6 Cross country similarities and differences for the use of formal linkages </p>

<p>F_ot 
F_sup 
F_cust 
F_comp. 
F_uni. 
F_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt 
+ + + 
++ 
+ + ++ 
+ 
++ 
++ 
Imp_pdt 
+ + − 
++ 
Pdt_prc 
+ 
+ + + 
+ + + 
+ 
+ + + 
++ 
Inv_int 
+ + + 
+ 
− 
− + + 
+ + + 
+ + + 
Inv_mac 
− 
− 
Inv_var 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + + 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
Scie 
−− 
− 
− 
+ 
Compx 
− 
− 
− 
+ + 
− 
− 
Pdt_eng 
− − − 
−− 
Fdt 
− 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Size 
+ + ++ 
+ + + 
+ + + 
+ + + 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
Mkt 
− 
+ </p>

<p>Reported signs are for those countries whose corresponding marginal effect is significantly 
different from zero </p>

<p>The emerging evidence in this case points to cross country similarity al-
though some dissimilarities exist at the firm level. For instance, in almost every 
country the larger the firm size, the higher the probability of cooperation. Sim-
ilarly, the more varied the firm investment portfolio, the higher the probability 
of cooperation. 
Concerning the impact of innovation strategy, our results suggest that, 
in every country, firm cooperation with customers was the outcome of an 
innovative strategy involving novel product introduction. Similarly, a strategy 
based on novel product introduction was always pursued by firms cooperating 
with universities or governmental research institutes. Both results are consis-
tent with previous findings (Beise and Stahl 1999; Tether 2002) discussed in 
Section 2. In terms of investment, some similarities at the firm level can be 
found, too. In three countries out of four, the share of innovative expenditures 
was positively and significantly associated to the probability of cooperating 
with other firms of the same group, universities, and governmental research 
institutes. Few similarities are found instead concerning the impact of invest-
ments in machinery as well as concerning industry specific effects. 
Our results for the subset of informal linkages are instead reported in 
Table 7. 
In this case, the evidence is more mixed. Again, firm size and investment 
variety are, when significant, always positively associated to the probability of 
relying upon any external source of information. The biggest difference with 
respect to the previous results concerns the role of both innovative strategies 
and investment. In these cases, our results suggest the following. First, correla-
tion is weaker when compared to the case of formal interactions since relatively 
fewer coefficients turn out to be significantly different from zero. Second, in 
those cases in which correlation is significant, there is no single strategy which 
can be pursued to tap any source of information. On the contrary, tapping 
each information source seems to require the implementation of a different 
mix of strategies. Third, the implementation of a specific mix is mainly country </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Table 7 Cross country similarities and differences for the use of informal linkages </p>

<p>Inf _ot 
Inf _sup 
Inf _cust 
Inf_comp 
Inf_uni 
Inf_gov </p>

<p>New_pdt 
− 
+ + 
+ 
Imp_pdt 
+ 
− 
+ + + 
++ 
− 
Pdt_prc 
++ 
++ 
++ 
Inv_int 
−− 
+ 
+ 
+ + + 
++ 
Inv_mac 
−+ 
+ 
− 
Inv_var 
++ 
++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
Scie 
+ 
− 
+ + 
+ 
− + 
− 
Compx 
+ − + 
++ 
−− 
−− 
Pdt_eng 
− 
−+ 
+ + + 
+ 
+ 
− 
Fdt 
++ 
−− 
−− 
− 
Size 
+ + ++ 
++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
+ + ++ 
Mkt 
+ 
−− 
+ + + 
++ 
++ </p>

<p>Reported signs are for those countries whose corresponding marginal effect is significantly 
different from zero </p>

<p>specific, as no strategy (or mix of) exists that is common to every country (as it 
happened with novel product introduction in the case of formal linkages). 
All in all, the previous considerations point to the following conclusions. 
No clear cut pattern seem to emerge concerning the relative importance of 
firm specific effect vis-à-vis country effects in the establishment of formal 
and informal external linkages. However, the establishment of formal linkages 
seems to be the consequence of firm specific characteristics especially related 
to innovation strategies, and, to a lesser extent, investment, rather than of 
country specific characteristics. This finding is consistent with the results of 
Shrolec and Verspagen (2008), who pointed to the role of firms strategies in 
explaining pattern of innovation rather than sectoral and national factors. The 
establishment of informal linkages instead seems to depend relatively less on 
firm characteristics. In this case, differences across national and sectoral inno-
vation systems are so strong that differences still remain even after controlling 
for firm strategies and other characteristics. </p>

<p>5 Conclusions </p>

<p>This paper has started from the observation that firms tend to rely upon 
the contribution of different external actors in their innovation process. 
This empirical fact may either be due to the presence of a relationship of 
complementarity or substitution between several information sources or a 
consequence of the fact that firms undertake several types of innovations 
that differ in terms of novelty and integration of market and production (i.e. 
firms have different innovation strategies). In this paper, we have empirically 
analyzed both these possibilities using a sample of innovating firms from four 
European countries (Norway, Sweden, the Netherlands and the UK). 
Concerning the complementarity/ substitutability issue, our estimation ap-
proach allowed us to account for the simultaneous use of several external 
linkages. In this respect, our results suggest that few cross-countries differences </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>exist and that there are no substitution relations across different external 
actors. In other words, in all the countries in our sample firms tend to cooperate 
formally with actors that they also use to screen on the market. This result 
confirms previous findings in the literature (Belderbos et al. 2004a, b), though 
in our case complementarity between formal and informal linkages with the 
same actor seems comparatively much weaker. 
Concerning the role of different innovation strategies, our results have 
shown that firms with different innovation strategies tend to rely on different 
mixes of external actors and that some differences exist across countries. In 
particular, novel product innovators tend to have formal and informal interac-
tion with customers and with research organizations to a lesser extent. Firms 
that introduce only improved products seem to regard informal linkages with 
competitors (both formal and informal) and with customers as more important 
in the innovation process. In comparison, firms that innovate in both product 
and process tend to rely relatively more on customers and public research 
organizations. We have also found differences in the portfolio of external 
linkages across firms active in different industrial and technological contexts. 
At the national level, our analysis points to the important role played by firm 
characteristics and innovative strategies particularly in the establishment of 
formal linkages with external actors. In the case of informal linkages firms 
specific characteristics tend to matter less. 
All in all, our results provide novel insights into the role of firms' in-
novative strategies in establishing external linkages in different sectoral as 
well as national contexts. These results, although preliminary and in need of 
further corroboration, suggest some managerial and policy implications. On 
the managerial side, if firms' capabilities to use certain types of linkages and 
the adequacy of knowledge provided by external actors differ across countries 
and sectors, then the decision to enter into new markets (internationalization, 
delocalization or diversification) may create problems of identification, access 
and process of external sources of information. Therefore, firms may need to 
complement these decisions with investment in wider search and collaborative 
activities, as well as in new routines for enhancing the processing of external 
information. On the policy side, our results suggest not only that public 
research organizations in different countries have different capabilities to 
provide specific relevant innovative knowledge, but also that their capabilities 
depend on the quality and function of the interaction among different market 
actors. It should be the task of policy makers to nurture and to reinforce these 
interactions. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements A previous version of this paper has been presented at the 12th Interna-
tional J. A. Schumpeter Society Conference in Rio de Janeiro. We thank the participants for the 
useful comments received. We also thank the editors of this special issue and two anonymous 
referees for their comments on previous drafts of the paper. The usual disclaimers apply. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited. </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Table 8 Correlation matrix for the use of informal and formal linkages: results for Sweden </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>F_comp. </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.37 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.62 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.59 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_cust. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.43 </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 . 5 5 </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Only correlation coefficients significant at least at 5% are reported </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Table 9 Correlation matrix for the use of informal and formal linkages: results for Norway </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>F_comp. </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.46 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.44 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.33 </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.26 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.34 </p>

<p>0.44 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_cust. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>0.26 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.39 </p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 . 5 7 </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Only correlation coefficients significant at least at 5% are reported </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>

<p>Table 10 Correlation matrix for the use of informal and formal linkages: results for the Netherlands </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>F_comp. </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.08 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.41 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.55 </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.65 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>0.11 </p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>F_cust. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.64 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.28 </p>

<p>0.51 </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 . 3 3 </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Only correlation coefficients significant at least at 5% are reported </p>

<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>



<p>Table 11 Correlation matrix for the use of informal and formal linkages: results for the UK </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>F_cust </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>F_comp. </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>Inf_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.27 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.24 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.17 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_ot </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.48 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.49 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.45 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.36 </p>

<p>Inf_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.14 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.18 </p>

<p>F_sup </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.13 </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.66 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>Inf_cust </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>0.47 </p>

<p>0.22 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.21 </p>

<p>0.32 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>F_cust. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.74 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.19 </p>

<p>0.61 </p>

<p>Inf_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.16 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>F_comp </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.44 </p>

<p>0.23 </p>

<p>0.54 </p>

<p>Inf_uni </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.57 </p>

<p>0.38 </p>

<p>0.31 </p>

<p>F_uni. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.29 </p>

<p>0.58 </p>

<p>Inf_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 . 6 8 </p>

<p>F_gov </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Only correlation coefficients significant at least at 5% are reported </p>



<p>I.M.B. Freitas et al. </p>



<p>External linkages and firms' innovative strategies </p>





</text></tei>