<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10797-018-9484-5" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract Contrary to frequent recommendations of the public finance literature and 
international institutions, a persistently high tax wedge on labor is observed in Europe. 
Simultaneously, the scope for shifting taxes to more growth-friendly revenue sources 
appears underused. This motivates our simulation of a tax shift from labor to property 
for Germany, a country where property tax revenues are particularly low and the tax 
wedge on labor income is among the highest in industrialized countries. We simulate a 
reform where property is no longer taxed by its (often) outdated cadastral value but by 
its market value, using the additional revenue to reduce social insurance contributions 
(SIC). To make such a simulation possible, we match property-related information 
with the input data of the tax-benefit microsimulation model EUROMOD. We find 
a considerable increase in property tax revenues, allowing to reduce the implicit tax 
rate on labor from 37.2 to 36.5%. Distributive effects tend to be modest and depend 
on the design of the SIC reduction. Overall, our results suggest that more households 
would gain than lose from the tax shift, with gainers mostly situated in the middle of 
the income distribution. </p>

<p>A high implicit tax rate on labor is often said to be detrimental to growth and employ-
ment (e.g., Arnold et al. 2011; Myles 2009). In general, the literature suggests that 
taxes levied on consumption or property are less distortionary and growth-harming 
than those levied on corporate or labor income (Mankiw et al. 2009; Slemrod 1990). 
Despite these findings, the scope for shifting taxes to more growth-friendly revenue 
sources appears underused in many countries. For instance, various institutions have 
frequently advised European governments to augment growth potentials by shifting 
the tax burden away from labor to other tax bases such as property (e.g., European 
Council 2015; OECD 2014; IMF 2013). Germany in particular has been identified as 
a country which makes only little use of property taxes, 1 while having a high implicit 
tax rate on labor (see Fig. 1). At the same time, the distribution of income and wealth 
has become more uneven in many advanced economies (including Germany) over the 
past few decades, and finding better ways to tax affluent households is back on the 
policy agenda of many governments (Atkinson and Piketty 2010; Peichl et al. 2010; 
Bach et al. 2009). Property constitutes the quantitatively most important wealth asset 
of German households, and the development of real estate prices has been found a 
crucial component of observed wealth inequalities (Lindner 2015). 
The use of outdated cadastral values to determine property tax liabilities is com-
monly said to be an important reason why revenues from taxing property are so low 
in Germany (Spahn 2004). Indeed, the current valuation of real estate defining the 
property tax base dates back to 1964 in Western Germany and to 1935 in Eastern 
Germany. Various scholars have argued for a revaluation of such cadastral values, but 
no reform has been carried out (e.g., Blöchliger 2015; Färber et al. 2014). Similar 
situations with very outdated cadastral values determining property tax liability can 
be found in several other European countries (Andrews et al. 2011). 
Our study first simulates a property tax reform for Germany in which the tax base is 
no more defined by the cadastral value but by the market value of the property. To assess 
distributional consequences, we study changes in pre-and post-reform property tax 
liabilities as well as in disposable income across the income distribution. This relates 
to the literature recommending to look at both income and wealth when interested in 
distributive effects (e.g., Peichl and Pestel 2013). 2 Further, we simulate two revenue-
neutral scenarios in which the additional tax receipts are used to finance a reduction 
in social insurance contributions on labor income. 
Simulating such a policy reform is difficult since there exists no data source which 
provides information on both current property tax liability and the actual market value 
of the property. 3 However, the HFCS (Household Finance and Consumption Survey) </p>

<p>1 "Property taxes " in this paper describe recurrent levies on immovable real estate owned by private 
households, i.e., excluding transaction taxes as well as property taxes on corporate assets. 
2 Please note that we desist from constructing a multidimensional measure as an indicator for affluence 
or living standards but combine detailed information of a household's property wealth with disaggregated 
income measures in order to conduct our policy simulations. 
3 Only in its survey of 1988, the German Socio-Economic Panel (SOEP) asked respondents about the 
cadastral and market values of their main household residence. However, three shortcomings make the use </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>of the ECB provides extensive information regarding the value of properties owned. 
In addition, the EU-SILC survey (European Union Statistics on Income and Living 
Conditions) contains information on property taxes currently paid. In order to conduct 
our simulation, we match the two representative survey microdatasets. Performing a 
number of validity checks we show that especially on a more aggregate level such as 
household income deciles, the matched dataset preserves the properties of the original 
HFCS dataset sufficiently well. 
The matched dataset is then used to simulate a property tax reform that applies 
current market values instead of cadastral values. In a first scenario, we assess the 
potential revenue gain induced by the use of up-to-date property values. Next, we 
simulate a revenue-neutral scenario in which the additional revenue is used to lower 
social insurance contributions (SIC) via a lump sum SIC credit. As a third scenario, 
we simulate a proportional reduction of social insurance contributions, again under 
revenue neutrality. All simulations are carried out using <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs>-the tax-benefit 
microsimulation model for EU member states. It allows us to evaluate changes in 
households' disposable income induced by the different scenarios. Our baseline sim-
ulations focus on first-order effects of the three reform scenarios. In addition, we also 
discuss the relevance of second-order effects in our context, and provide robustness 
checks in the Appendix accounting for potential labor supply responses. 
From a budgetary perspective, our simulations suggest that the revenue from prop-
erty taxation would rise from currently e 5.8 bil. to e 16.3 bil. This additional revenue 
would allow a reduction of the implicit tax rate on labor from currently 37.2 to 36.5%. 
Examining distributive effects, our results first indicate that the (average) percentage 
increase in the property tax liability is roughly constant across the income distribution 
of property owners. Hence, the relative size of the property tax liability across the 
income distribution of homeowners is by and large preserved. Second, when examin-
ing the effect of the proposed update of cadastral values (again without redistributing 
the additional revenue) across the entire income distribution, we find that the relative 
change in disposable income varies little across income deciles. Thus, an update of 
cadastral values without using the additional revenue to lower the tax burden on labor 
would render such a reform virtually neutral in terms of redistribution. 
Finally, we turn toward the two revenue-neutral scenarios in which the additional 
tax receipts are used to lower the tax burden on labor income. We find that when 
a lump sum SIC credit is granted, all household deciles would gain in disposable 
income except for the top three ones. In contrast, when using the additional revenue 
for a proportional reduction of social insurance contributions, the effect on disposable 
income is small and relatively similar across the income distribution. In sum, we find 
for both scenarios that more households would gain than lose from the tax shift, with 
gainers mostly situated in the middle of the income distribution. </p>

<p>Footnote 3 continued 
of this joint observation impractical. First, the information dates back to 1988, and property values have 
changed substantially since then. Second, SOEP only collected ordinal measures of market value. Third 
and most importantly, information on property is only available for the main household residence and not 
for any other real estate owned. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Our results relate to the existing literature in a number of ways. First, several pro-
posals have been made to increase tax revenues from wealth and property (e.g., Bach 
et al. 2014; Piketty 2014). Our paper adds to this literature by assessing the revenue 
potential of an important policy tool, namely an up-to-date valuation of the property tax 
base. As mentioned above, outdated cadastral values determine property tax liability 
not only in Germany but also in several other European countries, making our results 
also relevant for other jurisdictions (see OECD 2014; Andrews et al. 2011). Further-
more, previous authors have pointed out that the redistributive element of the German 
property tax in its current form is rather limited (Bach and Schratzenstaller 2013). 
Our results support this view and indicate that this would not be substantially different 
once cadastral values are updated. In fact, our findings suggest that the potential for 
redistribution (if desired by the legislator) depends on the simultaneous reduction of 
the tax burden on labor. 
In addition, our results speak to the literature analyzing the distributive effects of tax 
shifts from labor income toward other tax bases such as consumption (e.g., Pestel and 
Sommer 2017). So far, little empirical work has been dedicated to property tax related 
simulations, mostly driven by data limitations. A notable exception is Moscarola et al. 
(2015), assessing labor market reactions to a property and labor tax reform in Italy. In a 
similar vein, Figari et al. (2017) investigate the fiscal and distributional consequences of 
including homeowners' imputed rent in personal taxable income as a kind of property 
tax for six European countries. Using up-to-date property values to determine property 
taxes could be regarded as an important complement (and maybe even as a substitute 
depending on the specific design) to housing income taxation. Finally, Kuypers et al. 
(2017) currently create a <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> input database directly from the HFCS dataset. 
Their approach aims at broadening the scope of <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> by including information 
on wealth from HFCS, but they do not combine this with EU-SILC data. The novelty of 
our paper is the creation of a new dataset via statistical matching that allows analyses 
regarding two variables which have never been jointly observed, namely the current 
property tax liability and the actual market value of the property. Our approach may 
potentially be extended to other European countries covered by <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs>, providing 
a fruitful avenue for further research. 
The remainder of this paper is organized as follows: Sect. 2 illustrates the insti-
tutional background of property taxes in Germany. Section 3 describes the matching 
procedure which combines the two datasets. An analysis of the quality and validity 
of the matched dataset is provided in Sect. 4. The simulated tax reform and its dis-
tributional and revenue effects are described in Sect. 5. The final section contains a 
conclusive discussion of our results. </p>

<p>2 Motivation and institutional background </p>

<p>As stressed above, Germany appears to have considerable scope to reform the valuation 
of property used for property taxation. Basic cross-country comparable descriptives 
underpin this view. Figure 1 illustrates large disparities across EU-28's member states 
with regard to revenue from property taxes and the implicit tax rate (ITR) on labor. 
Revenues from property taxes are comparatively low for Germany (0.44% of GDP </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Revenue from recurrent property taxes to GDP </p>

<p>GB </p>

<p>FR </p>

<p>DK </p>

<p>BE </p>

<p>PL </p>

<p>ES </p>

<p>IE </p>

<p>SE </p>

<p>LT </p>

<p>RO </p>

<p>FI </p>

<p>CY </p>

<p>NL </p>

<p>PT </p>

<p>IT </p>

<p>SL </p>

<p>DE </p>

<p>GR </p>

<p>SK </p>

<p>LV </p>

<p>EE </p>

<p>HU </p>

<p>BG </p>

<p>CZ </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>LU </p>

<p>HR </p>

<p>MT </p>

<p>EU member states </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 </p>

<p>ITR on labor </p>

<p>BE </p>

<p>IT </p>

<p>AT </p>

<p>SE </p>

<p>FI </p>

<p>HU </p>

<p>CZ </p>

<p>FR </p>

<p>DE </p>

<p>NL </p>

<p>EE </p>

<p>NO </p>

<p>SL </p>

<p>DK </p>

<p>LV </p>

<p>ES </p>

<p>SK </p>

<p>LU </p>

<p>LT </p>

<p>GR </p>

<p>HR </p>

<p>PL </p>

<p>RO </p>

<p>CY </p>

<p>IE </p>

<p>GB </p>

<p>PT </p>

<p>BG </p>

<p>MT </p>

<p>EU member states </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Revenue from property taxation to GDP and implicit tax rate on labor, EU-28 member states 2010. 
Notes: The left bar chart shows in descending order the percentage of national revenues collected from 
recurrent property taxes (as % of GDP). The right bar chart compares percentage points of implicit tax rate 
(ITR) on labor. The ITR is defined as the ratio of all direct and indirect taxes, including social security 
contributions levied on labor income to total compensation of the employee. Source: Commission (2013) </p>

<p>vs. 1.5% in EU-28). At the same time, the ITR on labor in Germany is above average 
(37.2 vs. 36.1% in EU-28). 
So far, several attempts to reform German property taxation have been made, e.g., 
an overhaul of the Grundsteuer was part of the national Reform Program 2014 and 
2015 but put on hold hitherto. As a consequence, the current valuation of property 
dates back to 1964 in Western Germany and to 1935 in Eastern Germany. Back then, 
rateable values 4 were assessed on the basis of capitalized gross returns (i.e., rental 
income) or, in the case of owner-occupied dwellings, on the basis of construction 
costs (for details see Spahn 2004). The original intention of the legislature was to 
update the property value on a regular basis, but this was never put into practice. 5 
To make cadastral values comparable, even new buildings, sales or improvements in 
existing buildings are rated as if they were built several decades ago. Hence, the tax </p>

<p>4 Please note that we use the term "cadastral value" and "rateable value" interchangeably. </p>

<p>5 To partly offset these nominally fixed cadastral values, municipalities started to raise local tax multipliers 
in addition to the federal rate. However, the multipliers are set on municipality level only, and hence do 
not account for heterogenous developments of property values within a given municipality. In addition, the 
increase in multipliers over time does not match inflation adjustment (see Sect. 5.2 for details). </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>valuations of German properties differ substantially from current market values. 6 In 
sum, the link between the property tax liability based on outdated cadastral values 
and the actual market value of the real estate is very weak (Wissenschaftlicher Beirat 
BMF 2010). 
From a policy perspective, two reasons render a reform of the current property 
tax system in Germany important and hence our simulation relevant. First, a sunset 
clause in the German Finanzausgleich-an equalization payment in the German multi-
level government-makes its reorganization inevitable by the end of 2018. Since it 
is often argued that reforms of property tax regimes should be linked to reforms of 
intergovernmental fiscal frameworks (e.g., Devereux et al. 2007), we consider the 
sunset clause as a window of opportunity for an overhaul of property taxation in 
Germany. Second, two pertinent constitutional complaints (BvR 639/11 and 1 BvR 
889/12) are currently pending before the Federal Constitutional Court. The court has 
to decide whether the continued failure to conduct a general reassessment of property 
values violates the equality-of-treatment clause of the constitution. </p>

<p>3 Description of the data used for the simulation </p>

<p>This paper is based on HFCS and EU-SILC data. The European Union Statistics 
on Income and Living Conditions (SILC) is a representative survey coordinated by 
Eurostat that encompasses rich information on income, benefits and taxes, including 
property taxes paid. Its main limitation is the lack of information on household wealth. 
In contrast, the Eurosystem Household Finance and Consumption Survey (HFCS) 
provides detailed data on assets and liabilities, including the (self-assessed) value of 
real estates households own. 7 In line with Lindner (2015) and Zhan (2015), we find real 
estate as the quantitatively most important wealth component of German households. 
Summary statistics on the two main variables of interest are presented in Table 1. 
Finally, both surveys contain a number of overlapping variables which we will use 
below for the matching procedure. </p>

<p>3.1 Methodology of statistical matching </p>

<p>Statistical matching aims to create a dataset from different sources which do not contain 
the same units. The difference to record linkage, which uses, e.g., social security 
numbers to link identical units, is that statistical matching combines similar ones 
(Rässler 2002). Statistical matching in our context allows for imputing the property 
value Y from HFCS (donor) to SILC (recipient) via a number of appropriate matching </p>

<p>6 Already in 1992 German fiscal authorities executed a comparison of selling prices with underlying 
cadastral values and found a ratio of ca. 5 to 1 (Bach and Bartholmai 2002). 
7 Due to non-response, the most affluent households are likely to be underrepresented in the HFCS. This 
issue can be addressed by assuming that the upper tail of the wealth distribution approximates a Pareto 
distribution (Vermeulen 2016). However, this approach is not applicable for subordinate wealth components 
such as real estate. Importantly, real estate has been found one of the most accurately reported subordinate 
wealth components in HFCS, with a ratio of reported values in HFCS compared to national accounts 
amounting to 86% (Eurosystem Household Finance and Consumption Network 2013). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>Table 1 Summary statistics of SILC and HFCS </p>

<p>SILC 
HFCS </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Median 
Mean 
SD 
Median </p>

<p>Tax liability 
e 345 
e 494 
e 250 </p>

<p>Main residence 
e 220,432 
e 190,058 
e 180,000 </p>

<p>Other property 
e 264,924 
e 678,954 
e 115,000 </p>

<p>"Tax liability" stands for the annual property tax liability paid for all owned immovable properties. "Main 
residence" displays the value of the main household residence. "Other property" represents the value of 
other properties than the main residence. Source: Own calculations based on sample of property owners in 
German HFCS and SILC, respectively </p>

<p>variables. These matching variables should be strongly correlated with the merger 
variable Y and be jointly observed with (Y ) as well as (X ), i.e., appear in both datasets. 
Although EU-SILC does not contain property values, it does provide information 
on whether a household owns property and how much property tax it pays. Through 
the careful selection of matching variables, we can assign respondents of EU-SILC 
(who do own property) the approximate market value of their property. Appendix A 
provides a detailed description regarding the choice of appropriate matching variables 
we use. 8 
We apply a so-called hot deck matching procedure which assigns each observation 
in HFCS to at least one "nearest neighbor unit" in SILC that is most similar with respect 
to the matching variables. "Nearest" is defined as the associated observational unit that 
shows the smallest distance metric based on the set of matching variables. Specifically, 
we transform the data into uncorrelated, standardized variables with variance equal to 
1 and then compute the Euclidean distance between two vectors x and y (McLachlan 
2004). Let C denote covariance matrix and the superscript T the matrix transpose, 
the distance between a HFCS observation x = x 1 , x 2, x 3, . . . , x N 
T and a SILC </p>

<p>observation y = y 1 , y 2, y 3, . . . , y N 
T is then defined as: </p>

<p>d x, y = 
x − y </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>C −1 x − y 
(1) </p>

<p>Since our recipient dataset (EU-SILC) is more than three times larger than our 
donor dataset, donor units may be used for different recipient units repeatedly. Such a 
marriage algorithm is known as polygamy (Rässler 2002). If the marriage is restricted 
to a single spouse (monogamy), we would lose almost three quarters of our SILC 
observations. Hence, we opted for a n &gt; 1 nearest neighbor match with multiple use 
of donor units (from HFCS). The final matched dataset we generate consists of 13,079 
household observations, among which the 6629 households liable for property taxes 
are enriched by the market value of their properties. In the next section, we will assess </p>

<p>8 Before applying statistical matching it is important to make sure that the data collection and survey design 
of HFCS and SILC are comparable. In Appendix A.1, we discuss coherence requirements such as reference 
period, target population and collection process of the two datasets. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>the quality of the matched dataset by comparing its properties, marginal, and joint 
distributions to the original HFCS dataset. </p>

<p>4 Assessment of the matching result </p>

<p>In order to assess the validity of our matching procedure, we start with analyzing 
the consistency of the overall marginal distribution. Therefore, we follow established 
literature and compare the mean value of property owned per property decile between 
the matched dataset and the original HFCS dataset (Rässler 2002). Visual inspection of 
Fig. 2 shows quite similar distributions of our matched property values. More formally, 
we perform a two-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test comparing the equality of the 
weighted distributions. Using this test, we cannot reject the null hypothesis that the 
distribution of property values in the HFCS and the matched dataset are equal. 
As a next step, we analyze the joint distributions of the matching variables and the 
merger variable in the original HFCS dataset and the matched dataset. Figure 10 in 
Appendix separately depicts the joint distribution of our merger variable-property 
value-with each matching variable. Visual inspection of Fig. 10 indicates similar 
joint distributions in both datasets. Furthermore, we perform parametric tests to detect </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 k </p>

<p>400 k </p>

<p>600 k </p>

<p>800 k 
1000 k 1200 k </p>

<p>EUR </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
1 0 </p>

<p>property deciles </p>

<p>original HFCS 
matched </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Marginal distribution of original HFCS values and matched data. Notes: The figure displays mean 
property values per property decile from the original HFCS as well as the matched dataset. The figure is 
restricted to survey respondents who own property. The white bars represent the distribution of the original 
HFCS property values. The gray-shaded bars display the distribution of property values in the matched 
dataset </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>Table 2 Assessing preservation of joint distribution </p>

<p>Matching variables 
Wald test </p>

<p>Mean regression 
.75 quantile regression </p>

<p>Prob &gt; χ 2 
Prob &gt; χ 2 </p>

<p>Household size 
0.6824 
0.6129 </p>

<p>Tenure status 
0.6037 
0.1551 </p>

<p>Self-employed 
0.9039 
0.1218 </p>

<p>Total income 
0.8655 
0.2747 </p>

<p>Private pension contribution 
0.3472 
0.0742 </p>

<p>Working hours 
0.2727 
0.0345 </p>

<p>Max age 
0.6854 
0.5948 </p>

<p>Years in residence 
0.7232 
0.3726 </p>

<p>Higher education 
0.3201 
0.7101 </p>

<p>Mortgage dummy 
0.3547 
0.0520 </p>

<p>Years worked 
0.4526 
0.1632 </p>

<p>Rental income dummy 
0.9839 
0.8015 </p>

<p>Public pension income 
0.8475 
0.1050 </p>

<p>This table tests whether the coefficients of regressing property value on each matching variable differ 
between the original HFCS dataset and the matched dataset. Specifically, it displays p values of a Wald test 
on the equality of the coefficients. The null hypothesis is that the coefficients obtained from these regressions 
do not differ between the original HFCS dataset and the matched dataset. The first column shows results 
from mean regressions, while the second column is based on quantile regressions. See text for details </p>

<p>significant differences in the joint distributions of the matching variables and the 
merger variable. First, we run two separate univariate regressions of property value 
on each matching variable. One regression uses the original HFCS dataset, while the 
other regression uses the matched dataset. We then perform a Wald test on the equality 
of the two estimated coefficients from both datasets, testing the hypothesis: </p>

<p>H 0 : coefficient HFCS − coefficient matched = 0 </p>

<p>In order to not only compare means but get a deeper understanding whether the 
joint distribution is preserved in the matched dataset, the same procedure is conducted 
using quantile regression. We estimate quantile regressions with coefficients for the 
75th quantile. 9 The first column of Table 2 shows that for the mean regression, the 
H 0 cannot be rejected across all matching variables. Looking at the results based on 
quantile regressions (the second column), we continue to find no significant differences 
in the distribution for most of the matching variables. In sum, our results suggest that 
both the marginal and joint distributions in the original HFCS are sufficiently preserved 
in the matched dataset. 
As a final step, we make use of auxiliary information to assess the quality and 
validity of the matched dataset. Specifically, we use the variable property (market) </p>

<p>9 Using quantile regressions on the .50 and .95 quantile, we receive similar results. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>value at time of acquisition (which we only observe in HFCS) as an instrument for 
the current property tax liability (which we only observe in SILC). The idea is that 
for survey respondents who acquired their property around the year of the last general 
assessment in 1964, the variable property value at time of acquisition should be highly 
correlated with the cadastral value of this property and thus with the current property 
tax liability. Hence, we can assess the quality of our matched dataset by comparing 
the (post-match) rank position of the property value at the time of acquisition with the 
rank position of the current property tax liability of these respondents. 10 To make this 
quality assessment valid, we restrict our analysis to households who acquired their 
property around the year of the last assessment, since the (market) value at the time 
of acquisition should come very close to the cadastral value of the property (we set 
an interval of ± 5 years around 1964). 11 Further, we only use households whose only 
property is their main residence, since property value at time of acquisition is only 
inquired for the dwelling the household lives in. We find around 600 households in 
our sample who meet these restrictions, close to 10% of our total sample. 
Figure 3 presents a binned scatterplot of the mean rank position of the property value 
at time of acquisition versus the rank position of the current property tax liability. 
The rank-rank relationship is almost perfectly linear, suggesting that our matching 
procedure assigns the underlying property value to the current tax liability reasonably 
well. The relationship between the two ranks is measured via a Spearman's rho and 
yields ρ = 0.74. Given that we have no information about improvements made to 
the property since 1964 (which would change the cadastral value of the respective 
property and hence its property tax liability), we consider this a sufficiently high 
degree of similarity. In sum, we conclude that our matched dataset should allow for 
valid inferences, especially on a more aggregated level such as income deciles. In the 
next section, we will run our simulations on this matched dataset. </p>

<p>5 Simulation of a property tax reform </p>

<p>5.1 The tax-benefit model <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>

<p>Our policy reform simulations are performed on <rs id="software-5" type="software">EUROMOD</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">version G2.0</rs>), the 
tax-benefit microsimulation model designed for EU member states. It applies national 
tax-benefit policy rules to harmonized microdata and calculates their effects on house-
hold disposable income (Sutherland and Figari 2013). Unlike computable general 
equilibrium (CGE) approaches, the only assumptions we impose concern our pro-
posed reform scenarios, or the elasticity of labor supply. Our approach is in the spirit 
of recent research, for instance on fiscal sustainability (Dolls et al. 2017), income dis-
tribution analysis (Bargain et al. 2015), or mortgage interest deductibility (Figari et al. 
2017). Thus, we follow well-established simulation techniques using EUROMOD, </p>

<p>10 In contrast, for property bought in more recent years, the link between the property value at time of 
acquisition and its cadastral value is weaker. 
11 Please note that in 1964 the legislator defined cadastral values as "the price that could be realized […] 
in the case of a sale" (see Spahn 2004). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>percentile rank of property value at time of acquisition </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 </p>

<p>percentile rank of current property tax liability </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Post-match relationship between current property tax liability and property value at time of acquisi-
tion for a subsample of households. Notes: This figure is based on a subsample of households which acquired 
the property around the year of the last assessment of cadastral values (1964). It presents a binned scatterplot 
of the relationship between a household's rank position of the property value at time of acquisition and a 
household's rank position of the current property tax liability using our matched dataset. To construct the 
figure, we split observations into 20 equal-sized bins based on the rank position of the current property tax 
liability and plot the mean rank position of the property value at time of acquisition within each bin (the 
y-axis). See text for details </p>

<p>allowing for inferences about the distributional and revenue effects of a tax shift from 
labor to property. 
The German component of <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> reproducing the 2010 German tax-benefit 
system has been validated through comparison with aggregate statistics provided by 
fiscal authorities (Ochmann and Granados 2011). We run all tax-benefit policy rules at 
their 2010 setting and then augment the model with a simulated change in property and 
labor taxation. Hence, our simulation model calculates household disposable income 
under the current as well as the reformed tax-benefit rules holding everything else 
constant and, therefore, avoiding endogeneity problems (Bourguignon and Spadaro 
2006). 
In general, our analysis focuses on first-order effects of the simulated reform. How-
ever, there may also be second-order responses to the proposed tax policy changes. 
For instance, it seems plausible that the proposed reduction in social insurance con-
tributions on labor income affects labor supply. Therefore, we provide an additional 
analysis in Appendix B which takes such behavioral responses into account. 12 Finally, </p>

<p>12 Figures 14 and 15 in Appendix B contrast our first-order results with results when taking labor sup-
ply responses into account. Overall, our findings do not qualitatively change. This seems not surprising, </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>we abstract from potential shifts of the property tax from owners onto tenants. Löffler 
and Siegloch (2015) find that in the short run, the incidence of the German property tax 
is borne by landlords. Other scholars argue that this might also be the case in the long 
run (Broer 2013). More importantly, two-thirds of the property tax collected stems 
from owner-occupied housing, which cannot be shifted onto a third party. In addition, 
it has been proposed that a reformed property tax should use legal requirements to 
prevent shifting of the tax onto tenants (Fuest 2016). </p>

<p>5.2 Current property taxation and the reform scenarios </p>

<p>In this section, we provide details regarding property taxation in Germany and our 
proposed policy reform. In our analysis, we focus on property taxes levied on (non-
agricultural) land, buildings and improvements. All legal regulations of the German 
property tax, i.e., the definition of the tax base, federal tax rates as well as legal norms 
regarding the property assessment are set at the federal level. Specifically, the German 
property tax is calculated as the product of three components: the cadastral value of the 
property, the federal tax rate and a municipality tax multiplier. Equation (2) formally 
shows the calculation of the property tax liability: </p>

<p>Property tax = tax multiplier local  *  tax rate federal  *  rateable value 
(2) </p>

<p>The tax multiplier is set by the local municipality and has been raised by most Ger-
man municipalities over time (Löffler and Siegloch 2015). This reflects the attempt to 
at least partly offset the nominally fixed cadastral values. However, using municipality 
tax multipliers to offset nominally fixed cadastral values does not provide a compre-
hensive remedy against outdated rateable values. For instance, any adjustment of the 
tax multiplier occurs on the municipality level only, and hence does not account for 
heterogenous developments of property values within a given municipality. 13 
Federal tax rates have rarely been changed over the last decades and range from 0.26 
to 0.35% for West Germany and from 0.5 to 1% for East Germany. The main reason 
why the federal tax rate differs between West and East Germany lies in the different 
reference year regarding the last assessment of rateable values (1964 for West and 
1935 for East Germany, respectively). 
Simulated property tax reform We simulate a property tax reform in which the taxable 
base-the rateable value-is no more defined by the cadastral value of the property 
but by its current market value. Since the introduction and rise of the municipality 
multiplier after 1964 mostly reflects the fact that cadastral values were not adjusted to 
inflation, we do not apply them when calculating the new property tax liability. This is 
consistent with the idea to simulate a situation in which current market values (instead 
of cadastral values) determine property taxes due, which makes the use of inflation-</p>

<p>Footnote 12 continued 
given that estimated labor supply responses in Germany are modest, and the SIC reduction in our simulations 
is small. 
13 In addition, the increase in weighted average multipliers since 1974 only accounts for 58% of inflation 
adjustment (Source: own calculations based on data from the Federal Statistical Office). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>offsetting multipliers redundant. Using current multipliers and current market values 
would lead to extremely inflated estimates of the new property tax liability. In contrast, 
not using multipliers when calculating the new property tax liability means that our 
simulation presents a more conservative estimate of the potential revenue effects of 
such a reform. Please note that we apply federal tax rates for West Germany to our 
entire sample, since the reason for the higher federal rate in East Germany is the 
different reference year regarding the last assessment (1935 instead of 1964), which 
becomes obsolete when using current market values for all German properties. </p>

<p>Three reform scenarios We simulate three different scenarios in conjunction with the 
proposed property tax reform. While the first simulation updates the cadastral values 
without changing any other taxes, the other two scenarios seek to shift part of the tax 
burden from labor to property: </p>

<p>-(1) The update of cadastral values is non-revenue neutral: In this first scenario, we 
estimate the additional tax revenue collected from the update of cadastral values 
irrespective of budget neutrality. 
-(2) Revenue neutrality through a lump sum SIC credit: The extra revenue from 
the update of cadastral values is offset by a nonrefundable lump sum SIC credit 
granted to all employees (all employees with positive SIC). 
-(3) Revenue neutrality through a proportional reduction of employees' SIC: Under 
this scenario, the additional revenue is used to grant a rebate that is proportional 
to the SIC payment of an employee. 14 </p>

<p>The first scenario functions as a gauge for the distributive effects from the sole 
update of cadastral values. The second reform scenario provides a simulation that 
especially benefits employees at the lower end of the income distribution, where the 
current tax wedge is particularly large. In the third scenario, the size of the SIC rebate 
is more closely tied to the current SIC payment of the employee. </p>

<p>6 Simulation results </p>

<p>6.1 Revenue effects </p>

<p>We start with the overall revenue effect of the proposed property tax reform. The 
current annual property tax liability for German households owning property equals 
e 345 on average. The proposed property tax reform changing from cadastral values 
to market values would raise this average property tax liability to e 967. This would 
increase the total revenue collected from property taxes substantially from currently 
e 5.8 bil. to e 16.3 bil. 15 The extra revenue of e 10.5 bil. raised by the proposed 
property tax reform represents around 1.9% of total tax revenue Germany collected in 
2010. In our second scenario (2), we use this additional revenue to grant a credit on </p>

<p>14 In the case of joint filers, the simulated tax reduction (i.e., the lump sum SIC credit and SIC rate reduction, 
respectively) is granted at the household level. 
15 Please note that our analysis ceteris paribus focuses on property taxes paid by private households exclud-
ing corporations. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>0 
150 300 
450 600 750 900 </p>

<p>1,050 1,200 </p>

<p>1,350 1,500 </p>

<p>(mean) property tax liability, EUR </p>

<p>poorest 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>) 
s 
e 
u 
l 
a 
v 
t 
e 
k 
r 
a 
m 
n 
o 
d 
e 
s 
a 
b 
( 
m 
r 
o 
f 
e 
r 
d 
e 
s 
o 
p 
o 
r 
p 
) 
s 
e 
u 
l 
a 
v 
l 
a 
r 
t 
s 
a 
d 
a 
c 
n 
o 
d 
e 
s 
a 
b 
( 
o 
u 
q 
s 
u 
t 
a 
t 
s </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Pre-and post-reform property tax liability across disposable income deciles (property owners only). 
Notes: This figure shows property tax liabilities across disposable income deciles for property owners only. 
The dark gray bars display the mean pre-reform property tax liability. The light gray bars show the mean 
post-reform property tax liability. Source: Own calculations based on EUROMOD </p>

<p>SIC in the amount of maximum e 233 per employee, guaranteeing revenue neutrality. 
For the average household, this would reduce annual social insurance contributions 
from e 6245 to e 5920. In our third scenario (3), we apply the additional revenue 
to grant a 5.2% rebate on the SIC payment of every employee, again under revenue 
neutrality. </p>

<p>6.2 Distributive effects </p>

<p>Now we want to analyze in greater detail how the reform of the property tax and 
the different scenarios would affect groups of taxpayers differently. Specifically, we 
examine how the burden of the update of cadastral values is distributed across income 
deciles of (i) property owners only and (ii) the overall population. 16 
(i) We start with examining changes in household budgets following the increase in 
property tax liability for proprietors only. Figure 4 shows pre-and post-reform property 
tax liabilities across income deciles of property owners. It is evident from the figure </p>

<p>16 In the following analysis, we use equivalized disposable income calculated as market income plus public 
transfers minus taxes and social insurance contributions. In accordance with established practice, we do 
account for differences in household size by applying the modified OECD equivalence scale. For details, 
see OECD (2013). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>-1.2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-.8 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-400 -350 -300 -250 -200 -150 </p>

<p>-100 -50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR 
% </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Change in average household disposable income per decile under scenario (1). Notes: This figure 
displays the change in disposable income under reform scenario (1), which is the non-revenue-neutral 
simulation. The figure is based on the entire population, regardless of being a homeowner or not. Households 
are put into deciles according to their pre-reform disposable income. Bars show the change in disposable 
income in monetary values (EUR); triangles display the percentage change in disposable income. Source: 
Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>

<p>that the increase in the property tax liability is relatively constant across the income 
distribution of proprietors with an only slightly more pronounced increase in the top 
five deciles. The post-reform property tax liability for each household income decile 
is approximately three times larger, compared to a pre-reform situation. Hence, the 
relative size of the property tax liability across the income distribution of homeowners 
is by and large preserved under the proposed reform. 
(ii) Next we want to study the effect of the proposed update of cadastral values across 
the entire income distribution (regardless of being a homeowner or not). We start with 
scenario (1), which is the non-revenue-neutral simulation. The bars in Fig. 5 show 
the change in disposable income in absolute monetary values (EUR) by disposable 
income decile. The negative change in income increases with household income, which 
is expected given that ownership rates in Germany rise substantially with income (see 
Fig. 11 in Appendix). 
When displaying the relative income change, a different picture emerges. The tri-
angles in Fig. 5, representing the percentage change in disposable income under the 
reform scenario (1), vary little across the distribution. 17 Hence, poorer households are </p>

<p>17 The second decile stands out with a similar absolute increase in tax burden of proprietors and an only 
slightly higher ownership rate, but a considerably higher income than the first decile. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>-.8 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 -150 -100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR 
% </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Change in average household disposable income per decile under scenario (2). Notes: This figure 
displays the change in disposable income across deciles of disposable income under reform scenario (2), 
which is the lump sum SIC credit simulation. The figure is based on the entire population, regardless of being 
homeowner or not. Households are put into deciles according to their pre-reform disposable income. Bars 
show the disposable income change in absolute monetary values (EUR); triangles display the percentage 
change in disposable income. Source: Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>

<p>in relative terms as affected by the update of cadastral values as richer ones. Thus, an 
update of cadastral values without redistributing the additional revenue would render 
such a reform virtually neutral in terms of redistribution. Previous authors have noted 
that the redistributive element of the German property tax is limited (e.g., Bach and 
Schratzenstaller 2013; Broer 2013). Our findings suggest that this would not change 
when cadastral values are updated. This motivates the analysis of our revenue-neutral 
reform scenarios (2) and (3), where the additional tax revenue is used to lower the tax 
burden on labor. 
Scenario (2) is a simulation in which the additional tax revenue of the proposed 
update of cadastral values is offset by a nonrefundable lump sum SIC credit. Such 
a lump sum SIC credit corresponds with a relatively high tax relief for low-income 
earners, whose contribution rate is reduced to a relatively greater extent. Figure 6 
displays the income change by deciles of household disposable income under reform 
scenario (2). The figure shows that all household deciles would gain in disposable 
income except for the top three ones. 18 The total yearly gains range between e 20 and </p>

<p>18 The reason why the first decile gains relatively little has to do with the fact that households in this 
decile are disproportionately more likely to be unemployed, out of the labor force, or self-employed, which 
corresponds with zero SIC payments. The same holds for the first decile of scenario (3). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>-.8 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 -150 -100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR 
% </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Change in average household disposable income per decile under scenario (3). Notes: This figure 
displays the change in disposable income under reform scenario (3), which is the proportional rebate 
simulation. The figure is based on the entire population, regardless of being a homeowner or not. Households 
are put into deciles according to their pre-reform disposable income. Bars show the disposable income 
change in absolute monetary values (EUR). Triangles display the percentage change in disposable income. 
Source: Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>

<p>e 60 on average across the household income deciles, whereas the three top deciles 
loose between e 15 and e 209 on average. The triangles in Fig. 6 display the income 
change relative to disposable household income, ranging between + 0.43 and − 0.40% 
for the single deciles. 
As a next step, we turn to our third reform scenario (3), in which the additional 
revenue is used to grant a rebate that is proportional to the SIC payment of an employee. 
Specifically, we simulate a 5.2% rebate on the social insurance contribution paid by the 
employee. The impetus for scenario (3) is that employees should enjoy a proportional 
reduction of their SIC payments. Figure 7 displays the income change relative to deciles 
of disposable household income under reform scenario (3). The figure indicates that 
the proportional rebate would have only small effects in terms of redistribution. With 
exception of the first decile, which clearly suffers, the average losses and gains per 
income decile do not exceed 0.2% of income. Similarly, absolute changes in disposable 
income across income deciles do not exceed e 50. In sum, it seems that middle-income 
households would profit to some extent from this reform scenario, whereas low-and 
high-income households slightly suffer. 
Figure 8 provides additional insights into the distributional effects of our simu-
lations. For each of our two revenue-neutral scenarios, we now display the share of 
gainers and losers per disposable income decile. A household is defined as a gainer </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>share of gainers and losers, % </p>

<p>poorest 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>share of gainers and losers, % </p>

<p>poorest 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest </p>

<p>disposable income decile </p>

<p>losers 
gainers </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Shares of gainers and losers per disposable income decile under reform scenarios (2) (above) and 
(3) (below). Notes: This figure shows the share of gainers and losers for the reform scenarios (2) and (3). 
Gainers (losers) are defined as households with a positive (negative) change in disposable income under 
the respective reform scenario. Source: Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>(loser) when experiencing a positive (negative) change in disposable income. The 
upper part of Fig. 8 shows the result for reform scenario (2). We find more gain-
ers than losers, with the share of losers increasing steadily with the income level. In 
contrast, the share of gainers is much more evenly distributed across income deciles. 
Turning toward scenario (3), we find again more gainers than losers, but this time 
losers are less concentrated in the upper part of the income distribution than under 
scenario (2). This mirrors our results of Fig. 7, suggesting that the proportional rebate 
would have only small effects regarding the income distribution. Please note the share 
of gainers generally exceeds the share of losers across all income deciles, except for 
the top income decile under scenario (2). In contrast, the mean change in disposable 
income is negative for three income deciles under scenario (2) (see Fig. 6) and for five 
income deciles under scenario (3) (see Fig. 7). Thus, we conclude that gains of the tax 
shift are modest but widespread, whereas losses tend to be bigger but less frequent. 
Finally, we want to assess overall changes in inequality associated with our 
three reform scenarios. For this purpose, we employ two widely used inequality 
indices, namely the Gini and the Atkinson with A ε = 1. In line with our pre-
vious results, we find the non-revenue-neutral scenario (1) to barely change the 
distribution of income (see Table 3). Regarding scenario (2), we observe a small 
reduction in income inequality. In contrast, scenario (3) would widen the income 
distribution, though only very slightly. Looking at changes in poverty thresholds 
(set at 60% of median disposable income), we barely find any effect of the three 
reform scenarios. However, this does not rule out that the proposed tax shift may 
generate significant gainers and losers. As the comparison of extensive margin (see 
Fig. 8) with the intensive margin (see Figs. 6, 7) already suggests, the worst off 
1% might be affected by a considerable income shock in both scenarios (2) and 
(3). These scenarios could therefore potentially face opposition from asset-rich but 
income-poor households, which might ask for mitigating measures. This seems 
to be pertinent especially to the political acceptance of such a reform, given that 
the issue of property taxation can affect election outcomes (Bosch and Solé-Ollé 
2007). </p>

<p>7 Conclusion </p>

<p>The idea of higher taxes on land, capital and wealth to finance mounting public 
debt has gained ground in several OECD countries. At the same time, the scope 
for shifting taxes to more growth-friendly revenue sources appears underused in 
many European countries. This seems to be especially true for Germany, a coun-
try which makes only little use of property taxes, while at the same time having a 
high implicit tax rate on labor. Against this backdrop, we simulate a property tax 
reform for Germany which increases revenues from the taxation of property while 
simultaneously lowering the tax burden on labor. Changing the current property tax 
scheme based on outdated cadastral values to one based on market property val-
ues, we find substantial revenue effects of the proposed reform. Specifically, tax 
collection from private household property would increase from currently e 5.8 
bil. to e 16.3 bil., allowing for an overall reduction of the implicit tax rate on </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Table 3 
Revenue and distributive effects of the three scenarios. Source: </p>

<p>Own calculations based on EUROMOD </p>

<p>Status Quo </p>

<p>Non-revenue neutral (1) 
SIC lump sum credit (2) </p>

<p>Proportional SIC rebate (3) </p>

<p>Budgetary 
Private property tax revenue </p>

<p>e 5.8 bil. </p>

<p>e 16.3 bil. </p>

<p>e 16.3 bil. </p>

<p>e 16.3 bil. </p>

<p>ITR on labor </p>

<p>37.2% </p>

<p>37.2% </p>

<p>36.5% </p>

<p>36.5% </p>

<p>Distributive </p>

<p>Gini </p>

<p>0.268 </p>

<p>0.268 </p>

<p>0.267 </p>

<p>0.268 </p>

<p>Atkinson (1) </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>0.114 </p>

<p>0.115 </p>

<p>Poverty threshold </p>

<p>e 950 </p>

<p>e 936 </p>

<p>e 950 </p>

<p>e 949 </p>

<p>Worst off 1% </p>

<p>− 13.6% income </p>

<p>− 14.4% income </p>

<p>Best off 1% </p>

<p>+ 4.5% income </p>

<p>+ 2.6% income </p>

<p>"Status Quo" represents the pre-reform situation. "Private property tax revenue"depicts property tax revenues collected from private households, "worst/best off 1 %" depicts </p>

<p>the mean percentage loss/gain in disposable income of the 1% most affected households </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>labor from 37.2 to 36.5%. Using EU-28 cross-country levels as a comparison, this 
equates to an improvement of the implicit tax rate on labor by three positions. In 
contrast, the increase in the ratio of property tax revenue to GDP would change 
Germany's position by 13 places, with an after-reform level similar to Denmark's 
(compare Fig. 1). Examining the distributional effects of the reform on the household 
level, we find the update of cadastral values without using the additional revenue 
to lower SIC to be virtually neutral in terms of redistribution. As rich and poor 
households show comparable increases in the (relative) property tax burden, any 
potential redistribution under the proposed reform depends crucially on the design 
of the revenue-neutral SIC reduction. While a SIC reduction via a lump-sum tax credit 
would especially benefit low-income households, a SIC rebate proportional to house-
holds' current contributions would barely alter the overall distribution of disposable 
income. This gives policy-makers considerable scope via the specific design of such 
a reform. 
In light of the controversial nature of the outdated taxation of property in 
Germany and the apparent reluctance of policy-makers to tackle it, our paper 
reduces uncertainty about both revenue and distributional effects of such a reform. 
Depending on the exact design, our results suggest that low-and median income 
households could be made better off when reducing the overall tax burden on 
labor. 
We are aware that shifting taxes from labor to property is not easy to implement, 
especially in a federal system like Germany where property taxes accrue to local 
municipalities, and social insurance contributions to federal budgets. In addition, 
mass appraisal can be both expensive and perceived as intrusive. However, our anal-
ysis aims to inform about the fiscal and distributional effects of such a shift, which 
can then be mapped against institutional costs and legal constraints. While such an 
analysis is beyond the scope of our paper, it provides a fruitful avenue for future 
research. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements Open access funding provided by Paris Lodron University of Salzburg. Parts of the 
paper were written during a research visit of Markus Tiefenbacher at the University of Essex and University 
of Antwerp. We would like to thank numerous seminar participants at Essex, Antwerp, Salzburg, WIFO 
Vienna and the IIPF Annual Congress 2016 for helpful comments and discussions. Financial support from 
the Humer Foundation and the Salzburg Centre for European Union Studies (SCEUS) is gratefully acknowl-
edged. The research leading to these results has also received support from the European Commission's 
7th Framework Programme (FP7/2013-2017) under Grant Agreement No. 312691 (InGRID-Inclusive 
Growth Research Infrastructure Diffusion). The results presented here are based on EUROMOD version 
G2.0. <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> is maintained, developed and managed by the Institute for Social and Economic Research 
(ISER) at the University of Essex, in collaboration with national teams from the EU member states. We 
are indebted to the many people who have contributed to the development of <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs>. The process 
of extending and updating <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> is financially supported by the European Union Programme for 
Employment and Social Innovation "Easi" (2014-2020). The results and their interpretation are the authors' 
responsibility. They make use of microdata for Germany from the EU Statistics on Incomes and Living 
Conditions (EU-SILC) and the Eurosystem Household Finance and Consumption Survey (HFCS). </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 Interna-
tional License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, 
and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the 
source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>A. Appendix A: Construction of the matched dataset </p>

<p>The following sections provide a detailed description of the different steps taken to 
construct the matched dataset. </p>

<p>A.1 Coherence check of datasets </p>

<p>Before applying statistical matching, it is important to make sure that data collection 
and survey design of HFCS and SILC are comparable. As a matter of fact, HFCS and 
EU-SILC have the same target reference population, namely all private households 
in Germany. Both surveys exclude all institutionalized population, i.e., people living 
in retirement homes, health care, religious, correctional and penal institutions. The 
reference units are defined as all age 16+ members currently living in the same house-
hold. Reference point for balance sheet items is in both surveys the date of interview. 
Interviews for EU-SILC were held between May 2010 and November 2010. The field 
work for HFCS data was conducted from September 2010 to July 2011. Both surveys 
use the same income reference period, which is 2009. Finally, due to the potential non-
response bias, HFCS tries to oversample wealthier households. In contrast, SILC does 
not apply such oversampling. However, it is important to note that for Germany, we 
find one of the best data coherence between HFCS and EU-SILC among the 15 euro 
area countries regarding potential matching variables. For instance, the median annual 
gross income differs by less than e 100. This small difference in median annual gross 
income despite oversampling might reflect the very limited oversampling of HFCS 
in Germany. Oversampling in Germany was only based on geographic information 
about the distribution of taxable income, whereas other countries applied much more 
rigorous oversampling based on, e.g., wealth tax records. In sum, we conclude that 
regarding target population, household definition and reference period, the two survey 
designs appear to be sufficiently coherent to allow statistical matching. </p>

<p>A.2 Identification of matching variables </p>

<p>As mentioned in the main text, the careful selection of the matching variables is crucial 
when using statistical matching (Little and Rubin 2014). In the spirit of the stepwise 
approach of Leulescu and Agafitei (2013), we apply the following three key steps to 
choose appropriate matching variables: 
First, we carry out a data reconciliation process to correct variable discrepancies of 
HFCS and SILC due to the use of different technical definitions or variable concepts. 
For instance, we harmonize potential matching variables when their scale of measure 
differs. Sometimes such harmonization is not possible when the level of detail and 
accuracy lie far apart. In such cases, we do not consider these variables for the matching 
procedure. 19 </p>

<p>19 To give an example, HFCS inquired total welfare benefit transfers on household level, whereas SILC 
collected at an individual level old-age benefits, survivor benefits, sickness pay, disability benefits and 
education-related allowances separately. As a consequence, we had to eliminate gross cash income from 
regular social transfer from the potential set of matching variables. </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>Table 4 
Reconciliation process of common variables-HFCS 2010 and SILC 2010 </p>

<p>Raw data </p>

<p>Recoded household data </p>

<p>Coarsened </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Month and year of birth </p>

<p>Average age in household </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>Average age </p>

<p>Age of oldest household member </p>

<p>Max age </p>

<p>Gender, age </p>

<p>Number of females per household </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>Number of females </p>

<p>Number of children per household </p>

<p>Number of children </p>

<p>Absolute household size </p>

<p>Household size </p>

<p>Relationship status </p>

<p>Household's family structure </p>

<p>In HFCS </p>

<p>Marital status </p>

<p>Country of birth, citizenship </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if any household member with 
migration background </p>

<p>In HFCS </p>

<p>Any migrant </p>

<p>Duration of stay in host 
country </p>

<p>Maximum number of years spent in 
Germany by any household member </p>

<p>In HFCS </p>

<p>Years in country </p>

<p>Self-defined economic status </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if at least two persons are active </p>

<p>on labor market (one if single-person 
household or lone) </p>

<p>In HFCS </p>

<p>Employment status </p>

<p>Highest ISCED level attained </p>

<p>Dummy =1 if any household member has a 
higher education degree </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>Higher education </p>

<p>Occupation (ISCO-88) </p>

<p>Dummy for each ISCO group </p>

<p>= 1 if any </p>

<p>household member' occupation fits to the 
respective group </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>ISCO-88 </p>

<p>Economic activity (NACE) </p>

<p>Dummy for each NACE group </p>

<p>= 1 if any </p>

<p>household member' economic activity fits </p>

<p>to the respective group </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>NACE </p>

<p>Type of labor contract </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if all active household members </p>

<p>have a permanent contract </p>

<p>In SILC </p>

<p>Work contract </p>

<p>Labor force experience </p>

<p>Maximum number of years spent in paid 
work by any household member </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Years worked </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>continued </p>

<p>Raw data </p>

<p>Recoded household data </p>

<p>Coarsened </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Number of hours worked per 
week </p>

<p>Maximum number of hours worked by any 
household member </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Working hours </p>

<p>Individual gross employee 
income </p>

<p>Aggregated household's cash employee 
income </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Employee income </p>

<p>Individual gross 
self-employed income 
Aggregated household's cash self-employed 
income </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Self-employed income </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if any household member 
receives self-employed income </p>

<p>Self-employed dummy </p>

<p>Individual income from 
public pension </p>

<p>Aggregated household's income from public 
pension scheme </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Public pension income </p>

<p>Individual income from 
unemployment benefit </p>

<p>Aggregated household's income from 
unemployment benefit </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Unemployment benefit </p>

<p>Income from financial 
investment </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Income from financial investment </p>

<p>Income from other public 
transfers </p>

<p>Aggregated household's income from other 
public transfers </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Other benefits </p>

<p>Contribution to private 
pension plan </p>

<p>Aggregated household's contribution to 
private pension plans </p>

<p>No coarsen </p>

<p>Private pension contribution </p>

<p>Household main residence 
mortgage principle 
payment, mortgage interest </p>

<p>rate </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>in HFCS </p>

<p>Mortgage </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if there are any mortgages using 
household main residence as collateral </p>

<p>Mortgage dummy </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>Table 4 </p>

<p>continued </p>

<p>Raw data </p>

<p>Recoded household data </p>

<p>Coarsened </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Rental income </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Rental income </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if any household member 
receives rental income </p>

<p>Income rental dummy </p>

<p>Intra-household cash transfer </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Intra-household income </p>

<p>Total gross income </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Total income </p>

<p>Tenure status </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Tenure status </p>

<p>Rental payment </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Rent </p>

<p>Years living in main 
household residence </p>

<p>Originally on household level </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Years in residence </p>

<p>Possession of vehicle </p>

<p>Dummy 
= 1 if any household member owns </p>

<p>a car </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Vehicle </p>

<p>Income from regular social 
transfer </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Incoherent </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Non-collateralized debt </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Incoherent </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Other self-employed income </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Incoherent </p>

<p>-</p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Table 4 provides a comprehensive summary of the reconciliation process and a list 
of the common set of variables from both surveys. 
Second, it is important that the common set of variables (i.e., our potential matching 
variables), which appear both in HFCS and SILC, show similar distributions. We apply 
Hellinger Distance (HD), a measure to evaluate similarity of variable distribution of 
two different datasets (Webber and Tonki 2013; Eurostat 2013). Equation (3) assesses 
the similarity/dissimilarity between donor HFCS and recipient SILC for each potential 
matching variable. A HD value of 0 can be interpreted as perfect similar and a value 
of 1 as perfect discrepancy. As commonly stated in the literature, an HD of over 
5% raises concerns about the similarity in marginal distributions (e.g., Leulescu and 
Agafitei 2013). </p>

<p>HD V, V = </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>n Di 
N D 
− 
n Ri 
N R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>V is the donor dataset (HFCS) and V the recipient dataset (SILC), K is the total 
number of cells in a contingency table, n Di is the frequency of cell i in donor data D, 
n Ri is the frequency of cell i in recipient data R, and N is the total size of the specific 
contingency table. 
We calculate HD metrics on a truncated dataset. To be more precise, only HFCS 
units that own property are taken into account as only this subsample is liable to 
property taxation. This restriction reduces noise as it prevents the matching of property 
values to households not liable for property taxation. In a similar vein, we also restrict 
the recipient file to observations liable to property taxes. 
Figure 9 indicates that for quite some variables, the HD metric is below 5%. For 
instance, most of the demographic variables from both surveys show a strong degree of 
similarity regarding their distributions. Furthermore, total household (gross) income 
and contributions to private pension plans are very similar across both surveys. More 
importantly, variables capturing whether a person has rental income or tenure status 
are very evenly distributed in both surveys. Unsurprisingly, relatively low similarity 
is found for variables measuring welfare transfers. All other variables exceeding the 
5% threshold are not used for the matching, as this would introduce noise to our 
analysis. Additional tests comparing weighted means by using simple t tests confirm 
our selection of suitable variables based on the HD metrics (results available upon 
request). 
As a third step, we want to test the explanatory power of the set of common variables 
which fulfill the condition of coherence and similarity of distributions (i.e., all vari-
ables not exceeding the 5% threshold in Fig. 9). According to D'Orazio et al. (2006), 
common variables for matching should be selected on the basis that they significantly 
explain the variation in the merger variable Y , that is the value of properties owned. 
As standard in the literature, the null hypothesis of no association between common 
variables and market value of property is tested. We run Rao-Scott tests, a correction 
of Chi-squared tests for contingency tables when the estimated cell proportions are 
derived from survey data (Rao and Scott 1981). In order to also provide a measure 
of strength of association between two variables, the Pearson correlation coefficients </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>0 .025 .05 .075 </p>

<p>.1 .125 .15 .175 </p>

<p>.2 .225 .25 .275 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>household size </p>

<p>number of children 
tenure status </p>

<p>number of females 
average age </p>

<p>work contract 
self-employed dummy 
total income </p>

<p>private pension contribution 
employment status 
working hours 
max age </p>

<p>years in residence 
higher education 
mortgage dummy 
years worked 
marital status </p>

<p>rental income dummy 
public pension income </p>

<p>income from financial investment </p>

<p>mortgage 
ISCO-88 </p>

<p>self-employed income 
employee income </p>

<p>vehicle 
NACE </p>

<p>years in country </p>

<p>rent </p>

<p>any migrant 
inter-household income 
unemployment benefits 
rental income 
other benefits </p>

<p>Fig. 9 Comparing extensive margins of common variables. Notes: Hellinger Distance metrics for common 
coherent variables with reference line at 0.05. For further information on variables abbreviations, we refer 
to Table 4 in Appendix. Source: Own calculations based on sample of property owners in German HFCS 
and SILC, respectively </p>

<p>Table 5 Rao-Scott test and Pearson correlation coefficients common variables </p>

<p>Common variables 
Test of independence 
Pairwise correlation </p>

<p>Max age 
Pearson 
0.0481 
0.0504* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0451 </p>

<p>Average age 
Pearson 
0.0951 
0.0641 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.1093 </p>

<p>Number of females 
Pearson 
0.0353 
0.0533 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0224 </p>

<p>Number of children 
Pearson 
0.2612 
−0.0238 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.2859 </p>

<p>Household size 
Pearson 
0.0029 
0.0376* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0016 </p>

<p>Marital status 
Pearson 
0.0897 
0.0308 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.08765 </p>

<p>Employment status 
Pearson 
0,1281 
0.0967 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0,1145 </p>

<p>Higher education 
Pearson 
0.2731 
0.1473** </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.2659 </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Table 5 continued </p>

<p>Common variables 
Test of independence 
Pairwise correlation </p>

<p>Work contract 
Pearson 
0.0000 
0,1154 </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Years worked 
Pearson 
0.0962 
0.0665* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.1496 </p>

<p>Working hours 
Pearson 
0.0004 
0.0568* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Self-employed dummy 
Pearson 
0.0003 
0.1545* * </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0003 </p>

<p>Public pension income 
Pearson 
0.04557 
0.0951* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0180 </p>

<p>Private pension contribution 
Pearson 
0.0000 
0.1092* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Mortgage dummy 
Pearson 
0.0033 
0.0513* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0027 </p>

<p>Rental income dummy 
Pearson 
0.0000 
0.2975** </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Total income 
Pearson 
0.0000 
0.3296** </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Tenure status 
Pearson 
0.0000 
0.0280* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Years in residence 
Pearson 
0.0311 
0.0068* </p>

<p>Likelihood ratio 
0.0304 </p>

<p>Tests of independence-dichotomized for continuous variables-cover Pearson's and likelihood-ratio Chi-
squared, both corrected for the survey design with the second-order correction of Rao and Scott (1981). 
Pairwise correlation coefficients are calculated allowing for sample design. Significance levels are based 
on survey-based variance estimates, with * and ** indicating significance at 5 and 1% levels, respectively </p>

<p>are calculated. Table 5 shows results for the Rao-Scott test and Pearson correlation 
coefficient. 20 As depicted, 13 of the 19 variables that have been found to be simi-
larly distributed across both surveys are also significantly correlated with our merger 
variable Y . When regressing the market value of property owned (= Y ) on such 13 vari-
ables, we obtain a R 2 of 0.64. Hence, based on overall coherence, similar distributions 
and sufficient predictive power, we select these 13 variables for statistical matching. 
Table 6 provides an overview of all variables considered for statistical matching, with 
the 13 variables finally selected for statistical matching shaded in gray (Figs. 10, 11). </p>

<p>20 Our results stay qualitatively the same when applying multivariate statistics such as stepwise regressions 
(results available upon request). </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>0 
200000 
400000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>&gt; = 5 </p>

<p>household size </p>

<p>0 
100000 200000 300000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>owner=0 </p>

<p>owner=1 </p>

<p>tenure status </p>

<p>0 
200000 400000 600000 
(mean) property value 
self-employed=0 </p>

<p>self-employed=1 </p>

<p>self-employed dummy </p>

<p>0 
200000 400000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>total income quintiles </p>

<p>total income </p>

<p>0 
200000 
400000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>private pension contribution quinties </p>

<p>private pension contribution </p>

<p>0 
200000 
400000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0-35 </p>

<p>36-40 </p>

<p>41-45 </p>

<p>&gt;=46 </p>

<p>working hours </p>

<p>0 
100000 200000 300000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>&lt;=40 </p>

<p>41-50 </p>

<p>51-60 </p>

<p>61-70 </p>

<p>&gt;=71 </p>

<p>max age </p>

<p>0 
100000 200000 300000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>years in residence </p>

<p>0 
200000 
400000 
(mean) property value 
higher education=0 </p>

<p>higher education=1 </p>

<p>higher education </p>

<p>0 
100000 200000 300000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>mortgage =0 </p>

<p>mortgage=1 </p>

<p>mortgage dummy </p>

<p>0 
100000 200000 300000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>0-20 </p>

<p>21-32 </p>

<p>33-44 </p>

<p>&gt;45 </p>

<p>years worked </p>

<p>0 
500000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>rental income=0 </p>

<p>rental income=1 </p>

<p>rental income dummy </p>

<p>0 
200000 
400000 
(mean) property value </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1-20000 
20001-30000 
30001-40000 
&gt;=40001 </p>

<p>public pension income </p>

<p>original HFCS </p>

<p>matched </p>

<p>Fig. 10 
Joint distribution of merger variable with each matching variable for original HFCS values and matched results </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>Table 6 Summary of matching variables </p>

<p>Variable name 
Coherence 
Distributional 
similarity </p>

<p>Explanatory 
power </p>

<p>Max age </p>

<p>Average age 
× </p>

<p>Number of females 
× </p>

<p>Number of children 
× </p>

<p>Household size </p>

<p>Marital status 
× </p>

<p>Any migrant 
× </p>

<p>Years in country 
× </p>

<p>Employment status 
× </p>

<p>Higher education </p>

<p>ISCO-88 
× </p>

<p>NACE 
× </p>

<p>Work contract 
× </p>

<p>Years worked </p>

<p>Working hours </p>

<p>Employee income 
× </p>

<p>Self-employed income 
× </p>

<p>Self-employed dummy </p>

<p>Public pension income </p>

<p>Unemployment benefit 
× </p>

<p>Income from financial investment 
× </p>

<p>Other benefits 
× </p>

<p>Private pension contribution </p>

<p>Mortgage 
× </p>

<p>Mortgage dummy </p>

<p>Rental income 
× </p>

<p>Rental income dummy </p>

<p>Intra-household income 
× </p>

<p>Total income </p>

<p>Tenure status </p>

<p>Rent 
× </p>

<p>Years in residence </p>

<p>Vehicle 
× </p>

<p>B Appendix B: Second-order effects </p>

<p>B.1 Accounting for labor supply responses </p>

<p>This section provides an additional analysis which incorporates labor supply responses 
into our simulation. Therefore, we follow the approach of Bargain et al. (2015) and </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.3 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.7 </p>

<p>ownership rate </p>

<p>poorest 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest </p>

<p>equivalised disposable income decile </p>

<p>Fig. 11 Ownership rates across disposable income deciles. Notes: Ownership rate comprises main house-
hold residence and/or other properties. Source: Own calculations based on SILC </p>

<p>use stylized values of labor supply elasticities estimated for Germany in order to 
account for second-order distributional consequences. We use values of 0.25 for female 
couples, 0.15 for male couples and 0.2 for singles, as reported in Bargain et al. (2014). 
The elasticities are estimated applying a flexible discrete choice model where couples 
are assumed to maximize a joint utility function over a discrete set of working hour 
choices. The utility function is specified to account for fixed costs of work, labor 
market restrictions, and preference heterogeneity with respect to age, the presence 
and number of children as well as unobserved heterogeneity components. We draw on 
their elasticity estimates, distinguished by sex and marital status. We then apply these 
elasticities in our simulations to infer the additional labor supply (and hence, labor 
income) of German households for our reform scenarios (2) and (3). 21 For the sake 
of simplicity and due to missing estimates, we assume the responses to be constant 
across income groups. 
Figures 12 and 13 replicate Figs. 6 and 7 from the main text, this time account-
ing for labor supply second-order adjustments. Since both reform scenarios lower the 
tax burden on labor, we find that on average households respond positively in terms 
of labor supply and gross income. For instance, when accounting for second-order 
effects, also the third highest income decile now gains on average reform scenarios 
(2) (see Fig. 6 and 6 for comparison). Overall, however, the differences to our baseline </p>

<p>21 In scenario (1), social insurance contributions on labor income do not change and hence we do not expect 
changes in labor supply. </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>-.8 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 -150 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR 
% </p>

<p>Fig. 12 Change in average household disposable income per decile when accounting for second-order 
effects (scenario (2)). Notes: This figure displays the change in disposable income under reform scenario 
(2) when accounting for second-order effects regarding labor supply responses. The figure is based on 
the entire population, regardless of being homeowner or not. Bars show the disposable income change in 
absolute monetary values (EUR). Triangles display the percentage change in disposable income. Source: 
Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>

<p>estimates are small. The additional gain in disposable income when accounting for 
second-order responses ranges between 0.01 and 0.12% across income deciles. Hence, 
the differences between our first-and second-order results appear to be small and do 
not qualitatively change our interpretation. This seems not surprising, given that esti-
mated labor supply responses for Germany are modest (Bargain et al. 2014), and the 
SIC reduction in terms of annual income in our simulation is small. 22 If anything, 
accounting for labor supply responses turns more households into gainers when simu-
lating our reform scenarios, making our first-order baseline a somewhat conservative 
estimate. 
Finally, Figs. 14 and 15 summarize the main distributional results under reform 
scenario (2) and (3). They contrast first-order results as depicted in Figs. 6 and 7 
with results when accounting for behavioral responses as shown in Figs. 12 and 13, 
respectively. </p>

<p>22 For instance, first-order effects only for reform scenario (2) range between + 0.43% and − 0.40% across 
income deciles. </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>-.8 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 -150 -100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR 
% </p>

<p>Fig. 13 Change in average household disposable income per decile when accounting for second-order 
effects (scenario (3)). Notes: This figure displays the change in disposable income under reform scenario 
(3) when accounting for second-order effects regarding labor supply responses. The figure is based on 
the entire population, regardless of being homeowner or not. Bars show the disposable income change in 
absolute monetary values (EUR). Triangles display the percentage change in disposable income. Source: 
Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>



<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>

<p>,4 </p>

<p>,6 </p>

<p>,8 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-.2 </p>

<p>-.4 </p>

<p>-.6 </p>

<p>-.8 
(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 </p>

<p>-150 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
richest 
poorest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR (first-order) 
EUR (second-order) </p>

<p>% (first-order) 
% (second-order) </p>

<p>Fig. 14 Change in average household disposable income per decile: first-order versus second-order (sce-
nario (2)). Notes: This figure contrasts first-and second-order change in disposable income under reform 
scenario (2). The figure is based on the entire population, regardless of being homeowner or not. (Dark) 
gray bars show the disposable income change in absolute monetary values (w/o) accounting for second-
order effects. Triangles display first-order percentage change in disposable income, while diamonds display 
second-order percentage change. Source: Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>



<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>

<p>-,8 </p>

<p>-,6 </p>

<p>-,4 </p>

<p>-,2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>,2 </p>

<p>,4 </p>

<p>,6 </p>

<p>,8 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, % </p>

<p>-200 -150 </p>

<p>-100 </p>

<p>-50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>(mean) change in disposable income, EUR </p>

<p>2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
poorest 
richest </p>

<p>disposable income deciles </p>

<p>EUR (first-order) 
EUR (second-order) </p>

<p>% (first-order) 
% (second-order) </p>

<p>Fig. 15 Change in average household disposable income per decile: first-order versus second-order (sce-
nario (3)). Notes: This figure contrasts first-and second-order changes in disposable income under reform 
scenario (3). The figure is based on the entire population, regardless of being homeowner or not. (Dark) 
gray bars show the disposable income change in absolute monetary values (w/o) accounting for second-
order effects. Triangles display first-order percentage change in disposable income, while diamonds display 
second-order percentage change. Source: Own calculations based on <rs type="software">EUROMOD</rs> </p>





<p>J. Paetzold, M. Tiefenbacher </p>





<p>Effects of a tax shift from labor to property </p>





</text></tei>