<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.15.4.157" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>T </p>

<p>he great workhorse of applied econometrics is the least squares model. 
This is a natural choice, because applied econometricians are typically 
called upon to determine how much one variable will change in response 
to a change in some other variable. Increasingly however, econometricians are 
being asked to forecast and analyze the size of the errors of the model. In this case, 
the questions are about volatility, and the standard tools have become the ARCH/ 
GARCH models. 
The basic version of the least squares model assumes that the expected value 
of all error terms, when squared, is the same at any given point. This assumption is 
called homoskedasticity, and it is this assumption that is the focus of ARCH/ 
GARCH models. Data in which the variances of the error terms are not equal, in 
which the error terms may reasonably be expected to be larger for some points or 
ranges of the data than for others, are said to suffer from heteroskedasticity. The 
standard warning is that in the presence of heteroskedasticity, the regression 
coefficients for an ordinary least squares regression are still unbiased, but the 
standard errors and confidence intervals estimated by conventional procedures will 
be too narrow, giving a false sense of precision. Instead of considering this as a 
problem to be corrected, ARCH and GARCH models treat heteroskedasticity as a 
variance to be modeled. As a result, not only are the deficiencies of least squares 
corrected, but a prediction is computed for the variance of each error term. This 
prediction turns out often to be of interest, particularly in applications in finance. 
The warnings about heteroskedasticity have usually been applied only to 
cross-section models, not to time series models. cross-section relationship between income and consumption in household data, 
one might expect to find that the consumption of low-income households is more 
closely tied to income than that of high-income households, because the dollars of 
savings or deficit by poor households are likely to be much smaller in absolute value 
than high income households. In a cross-section regression of household consump-
tion on income, the error terms seem likely to be systematically larger in absolute 
value for high-income than for low-income households, and the assumption of 
homoskedasticity seems implausible. In contrast, if one looked at an aggregate time 
series consumption function, comparing national income to consumption, it seems 
more plausible to assume that the variance of the error terms doesn't change much 
over time. 
A recent development in estimation of standard errors, known as "robust 
standard errors," has also reduced the concern over heteroskedasticity. If the 
sample size is large, then robust standard errors give quite a good estimate of 
standard errors even with heteroskedasticity. If the sample is small, the need for a 
heteroskedasticity correction that does not affect the coefficients, and only asymp-
totically corrects the standard errors, can be debated. 
However, sometimes the natural question facing the applied econometrician is 
the accuracy of the predictions of the model. In this case, the key issue is the 
variance of the error terms and what makes them large. This question often arises 
in financial applications where the dependent variable is the return on an asset or 
portfolio and the variance of the return represents the risk level of those returns. 
These are time series applications, but it is nonetheless likely that heteroskedasticity 
is an issue. Even a cursory look at financial data suggests that some time periods are 
riskier than others; that is, the expected value of the magnitude of error terms at 
some times is greater than at others. Moreover, these risky times are not scattered 
randomly across quarterly or annual data. Instead, there is a degree of autocorre-
lation in the riskiness of financial returns. Financial analysts, looking at plots of 
daily returns such as in Figure 1, notice that the amplitude of the returns varies over 
time and describe this as "volatility clustering." The ARCH and GARCH models, 
which stand for autoregressive conditional heteroskedasticity and generalized autore-
gressive conditional heteroskedasticity, are designed to deal with just this set of 
issues. They have become widespread tools for dealing with time series heteroske-
dastic models. The goal of such models is to provide a volatility measure-like a 
standard deviation-that can be used in financial decisions concerning risk analy-
sis, portfolio selection and derivative pricing. </p>

<p>ARCH/GARCH Models </p>

<p>Because this paper will focus on financial applications, we will use financial 
notation. Let the dependent variable be labeled r t , which could be the return on an 
asset or portfolio. The mean value m and the variance h will be defined relative to 
a past information set. Then, the return r in the present will be equal to the mean </p>



<p>value of r (that is, the expected value of r based on past information) plus the 
standard deviation of r (that is, the square root of the variance) times the error 
term for the present period. 
The econometric challenge is to specify how the information is used to forecast 
the mean and variance of the return, conditional on the past information. While 
many specifications have been considered for the mean return and have been used 
in efforts to forecast future returns, virtually no methods were available for the 
variance before the introduction of ARCH models. The primary descriptive tool was 
the rolling standard deviation. This is the standard deviation calculated using a 
fixed number of the most recent observations. For example, this could be calcu-
lated every day using the most recent month (22 business days) of data. It is 
convenient to think of this formulation as the first ARCH model; it assumes that the 
variance of tomorrow's return is an equally weighted average of the squared 
residuals from the last 22 days. The assumption of equal weights seems unattractive, 
as one would think that the more recent events would be more relevant and 
therefore should have higher weights. Furthermore the assumption of zero weights 
for observations more than one month old is also unattractive. The ARCH model 
proposed by Engle (1982) let these weights be parameters to be estimated. Thus, 
the model allowed the data to determine the best weights to use in forecasting the 
variance. 
A useful generalization of this model is the GARCH parameterization intro-
duced by Bollerslev (1986). This model is also a weighted average of past squared 
residuals, but it has declining weights that never go completely to zero. It gives 
parsimonious models that are easy to estimate and, even in its simplest form, has 
proven surprisingly successful in predicting conditional variances. The most widely 
used GARCH specification asserts that the best predictor of the variance in the next 
period is a weighted average of the long-run average variance, the variance </p>

<p>Figure 1 
Nasdaq, Dow Jones and Bond Returns </p>

<p>Robert Engle 159 </p>

<p>predicted for this period, and the new information in this period that is captured 
by the most recent squared residual. Such an updating rule is a simple description 
of adaptive or learning behavior and can be thought of as Bayesian updating. 
Consider the trader who knows that the long-run average daily standard 
deviation of the Standard and Poor's 500 is 1 percent, that the forecast he made 
yesterday was 2 percent and the unexpected return observed today is 3 percent. 
Obviously, this is a high volatility period, and today is especially volatile, which 
suggests that the forecast for tomorrow could be even higher. However, the fact 
that the long-term average is only 1 percent might lead the forecaster to lower the 
forecast. The best strategy depends upon the dependence between days. If these 
three numbers are each squared and weighted equally, then the new forecast would 
be 2.16 ϭ ͌ (1 ϩ 4 ϩ 9)/3. However, rather than weighting these equally, it is 
generally found for daily data that weights such as those in the em-
pirical example of (.02, .9, .08) are much more accurate. Hence the forecast is 
2.08 ϭ ͌ .02*1 ϩ .9*4 ϩ .08*9. 
To be precise, we can use h t to define the variance of the residuals of a 
regression r t ϭ m t ϩ ͌ h t t . In this definition, the variance of is one. The GARCH 
model for variance looks like this: </p>

<p>h tϩ1 ϭ ϩ ␣͑r t Ϫ m t ͒ 
2 ϩ ␤h t ϭ ϩ ␣h t t 
2 ϩ ␤h t . </p>

<p>The econometrician must estimate the constants , ␣, ␤; updating simply requires 
knowing the previous forecast h and residual. The weights are (1 Ϫ ␣ Ϫ ␤, ␤, ␣), 
and the long-run average variance is ͌ /(1 Ϫ ␣ Ϫ ␤). It should be noted that this 
only works if ␣ ϩ ␤ Ͻ 1, and it only really makes sense if the weights are positive, 
requiring ␣ Ͼ 0, ␤ Ͼ 0, Ͼ 0. 
The GARCH model that has been described is typically called the GARCH(1,1) 
model. The (1,1) in parentheses is a standard notation in which the first number 
refers to how many autoregressive lags, or ARCH terms, appear in the equation, 
while the second number refers to how many moving average lags are specified, 
which here is often called the number of GARCH terms. Sometimes models with 
more than one lag are needed to find good variance forecasts. 
Although this model is directly set up to forecast for just one period, it turns 
out that based on the one-period forecast, a two-period forecast can be made. 
Ultimately, by repeating this step, long-horizon forecasts can be constructed. For 
the GARCH(1,1), the two-step forecast is a little closer to the long-run average 
variance than is the one-step forecast, and, ultimately, the distant-horizon forecast 
is the same for all time periods as long as ␣ ϩ ␤ Ͻ 1. This is just the unconditional 
variance. Thus, the GARCH models are mean reverting and conditionally het-
eroskedastic, but have a constant unconditional variance. 
I turn now to the question of how the econometrician can possibly estimate an 
equation like the GARCH(1,1) when the only variable on which there are data is r t . 
The simple answer is to use maximum likelihood by substituting h t for 
2 in the 
normal likelihood and then maximizing with respect to the parameters. An even </p>



<p>simpler answer is to use software such as <rs type="software">EViews</rs>, <rs type="software">SAS</rs>, <rs type="software">GAUSS</rs>, <rs type="software">TSP</rs>, <rs type="software">Matlab</rs>, <rs type="software">RATS</rs> 
and many others where there exist already packaged programs to do this. 
But the process is not really mysterious. For any set of parameters , ␣, ␤ and 
a starting estimate for the variance of the first observation, which is often taken to 
be the observed variance of the residuals, it is easy to calculate the variance forecast 
for the second observation. The GARCH updating formula takes the weighted 
average of the unconditional variance, the squared residual for the first observation 
and the starting variance and estimates the variance of the second observation. This 
is input into the forecast of the third variance, and so forth. Eventually, an entire 
time series of variance forecasts is constructed. Ideally, this series is large when the 
residuals are large and small when they are small. The likelihood function provides 
a systematic way to adjust the parameters , ␣, ␤ to give the best fit. 
Of course, it is entirely possible that the true variance process is different from 
the one specified by the econometrician. In order to detect this, a variety of 
diagnostic tests are available. The simplest is to construct the series of { t }, which 
are supposed to have constant mean and variance if the model is correctly specified. 
Various tests such as tests for autocorrelation in the squares are able to detect 
model failures. Often a "Ljung box test" with 15 lagged autocorrelations is used. </p>

<p>A Value-at-Risk Example </p>

<p>Applications of the ARCH/GARCH approach are widespread in situations 
where the volatility of returns is a central issue. Many banks and other financial 
institutions use the concept of "value at risk" as a way to measure the risks faced by 
their portfolios. The 1 percent value at risk is defined as the number of dollars that 
one can be 99 percent certain exceeds any losses for the next day. Statisticians call 
this a 1 percent quantile, because 1 percent of the outcomes are worse and 
99 percent are better. Let's use the GARCH(1,1) tools to estimate the 1 percent 
value at risk of a $1,000,000 portfolio on March 23, 2000. This portfolio consists of 
50 percent Nasdaq, 30 percent Dow Jones and 20 percent long bonds. The long 
bond is a ten-year constant maturity Treasury bond. 
1 This date is chosen to be just 
before the big market slide at the end of March and April. It is a time of high 
volatility and great anxiety. 
First, we construct the hypothetical historical portfolio. (All calculations in this 
example were done with the <rs type="software">EViews</rs> software program.) Figure 1 shows the pattern 
of returns of the Nasdaq, Dow Jones, bonds and the composite portfolio leading up 
to the terminal date. Each of these series appears to show the signs of ARCH effects 
in that the amplitude of the returns varies over time. In the case of the equities, it 
is clear that this has increased substantially in the latter part of the sample period. 
Visually, Nasdaq is even more extreme. In Table 1, we present some illustrative </p>

<p>1 The portfolio has constant proportions of wealth in each asset that would entail some rebalancing over 
time. </p>

<p>GARCH 101: The Use of ARCH/GARCH models in Applied Econometrics 161 </p>

<p>statistics for each of these three investments separately and for the portfolio as a 
whole in the final column. From the daily standard deviation, we see that the 
Nasdaq is the most volatile and interest rates the least volatile of the assets. The 
portfolio is less volatile than either of the equity series even though it is 80 percent 
equity-yet another illustration of the benefits of diversification. All the assets show 
evidence of fat tails, since the kurtosis exceeds 3, which is the normal value, and 
evidence of negative skewness, which means that the left tail is particularly extreme. 
The portfolio shows substantial evidence of ARCH effects as judged by the 
autocorrelations of the squared residuals in Table 2. The first order autocorrelation 
is .210, and they gradually decline to .083 after 15 lags. These autocorrelations are 
not large, but they are very significant. They are also all positive, which is uncom-
mon in most economic time series and yet is an implication of the GARCH(1,1) 
model. Standard software allows a test of the hypothesis that there is no autocor-
relation (and hence no ARCH). The test p-values shown in the last column are all 
zero to four places, resoundingly rejecting the "no ARCH" hypothesis. 
Then we forecast the standard deviation of the portfolio and its 1 percent 
quantile. We carry out this calculation over several different time frames: the entire 
ten years of the sample up to March 23, 2000; the year before March 23, 2000; and 
from January 1, 2000, to March 23, 2000.  Consider first the quantiles of the historical portfolio at these three different 
time horizons. To do this calculation, one simply sorts the returns and finds the 
1 percent worst case. Over the full ten-year sample, the 1 percent quantile times 
$1,000,000 produces a value at risk of $22,477. Over the last year, the calculation 
produces a value at risk of $24,653-somewhat higher, but not enormously so. 
However, if the 1 percent quantile is calculated based on the data from January 1, 
2000, to March 23, 2000, the value at risk is $35,159. Thus, the level of risk 
apparently has increased dramatically over the last quarter of the sample. Each of 
these numbers is the appropriate value at risk if the next day is equally likely to be 
the same as the days in the given sample period. This assumption is more likely to 
be true for the shorter period than for the long one. 
The basic GARCH(1,1) results are given in Table 3. Under this table it lists the 
dependent variable, PORT, and the sample period, indicates that it took the 
algorithm 16 iterations to maximize the likelihood function and computed stan-</p>

<p>Table 1 
Portfolio Data </p>

<p>NASDAQ 
Dow Jones 
Rate 
Portfolio </p>

<p>Mean 
0.0009 
0.0005 
0.0001 
0.0007 
Std. Dev. 
0.0115 
0.0090 
0.0073 
0.0083 
Skewness 
Ϫ0.5310 
Ϫ0.3593 
Ϫ0.2031 
Ϫ0.4738 
Kurtosis 
7.4936 
8.3288 
4.9579 
7.0026 </p>

<p>Sample: March 23, 1990 to March 23, 2000. </p>



<p>dard errors using the robust method of Bollerslev-Wooldridge. The three coeffi-
cients in the variance equation are listed as C, the intercept; ARCH(1), the first lag 
of the squared return; and GARCH(1), the first lag of the conditional variance. 
Notice that the coefficients sum up to a number less than one, which is required to 
have a mean reverting variance process. Since the sum is very close to one, this 
process only mean reverts slowly. Standard errors, Z-statistics (which are the ratio of 
coefficients and standard errors) and p-values complete the table. 
The standardized residuals are examined for autocorrelation in Table 4. 
Clearly, the autocorrelation is dramatically reduced from that observed in the 
portfolio returns themselves. Applying the same test for autocorrelation, we now </p>

<p>Table 2 
Autocorrelations of Squared Portfolio Returns </p>

<p>AC 
Q-Stat 
Prob </p>

<p>1 
0.210 
115.07 
0.000 
2 
0.183 
202.64 
0.000 
3 
0.116 
237.59 
0.000 
4 
0.082 
255.13 
0.000 
5 
0.122 
294.11 
0.000 
6 
0.163 
363.85 
0.000 
7 
0.090 
384.95 
0.000 
8 
0.099 
410.77 
0.000 
9 
0.081 
427.88 
0.000 
10 
0.081 
445.03 
0.000 
11 
0.069 
457.68 
0.000 
12 
0.080 
474.29 
0.000 
13 
0.076 
489.42 
0.000 
14 
0.074 
503.99 
0.000 
15 
0.083 
521.98 
0.000 </p>

<p>Sample: March 23, 1990 to March 23, 2000. </p>

<p>Table 3 
GARCH(1,1) </p>

<p>Variable </p>

<p>Variance Equation </p>

<p>Z-Stat 
P-Value 
Coef 
St. Err </p>

<p>C 
1.40E-06 
4.48E-07 
3.1210 
0.0018 
ARCH(1) 
0.0772 
0.0179 
4.3046 
0.0000 
GARCH(1) 
0.9046 
0.0196 
46.1474 
0.0000 </p>

<p>Notes: Dependent Variable: PORT. 
Sample (adjusted): March 23, 1990 to March 23, 2000. 
Convergence achieved after 16 iterations. 
Bollerslev-Woodridge robust standard errors and covariance. </p>

<p>Robert Engle 163 </p>

<p>find the p-values are about 0.5 or more, indicating that we can accept the hypothesis 
of "no residual ARCH." 
The forecast standard deviation for the next day is 0.0146, which is almost 
double the average standard deviation of 0.0083 presented in the last column of 
Table 1. If the residuals were normally distributed, then this would be multiplied by 
2.327, because 1 percent of a normal random variable lies 2.327 standard deviations 
below the mean. The estimated normal value at risk ϭ $33,977. As it turns out, the 
standardized residuals, which are the estimated values of { t }, are not very close to 
a normal distribution. They have a 1 percent quantile of 2.844, which reflects the 
fat tails of the asset price distribution. Based on the actual distribution, the 
estimated 1 percent value at risk is $39,996. Notice how much this value at risk has 
risen to reflect the increased risk in 2000. 
Finally, the value at risk can be computed based solely on estimation of the 
quantile of the forecast distribution. This has recently been proposed by Engle and 
Manganelli (2001), adapting the quantile regression methods of Koenker and  Basset (1978) and Koenker and Hallock in this symposium. Application of their 
method to this data set delivers a value at risk ϭ $38,228. 
What actually did happen on March 24, 2000, and subsequently? The 
portfolio lost more than $1000 on March 24 and more than $3000 on March 27. 
The biggest hit was $67,000 on April 14. We all know that Nasdaq declined 
substantially over the next year. The Dow Jones average was much less affected, 
and bond prices increased as the Federal Reserve lowered interest rates. Fig-
ure 2 plots the value at risk estimated each day using this methodology within 
the sample period and the losses that occurred the next day. There are about 
1 percent of times the value at risk is exceeded, as is expected, since this is 
in-sample. Figure 3 plots the same graph for the next year and a quarter, during </p>

<p>Table 4 
Autocorrelations of Squared Standardized Residuals </p>

<p>AC 
Q-Stat 
Prob </p>

<p>1 
0.005 
0.0589 
0.808 
2 
0.039 
4.0240 
0.134 
3 
Ϫ0.011 
4.3367 
0.227 
4 
Ϫ0.017 
5.0981 
0.277 
5 
0.002 
5.1046 
0.403 
6 
0.009 
5.3228 
0.503 
7 
Ϫ0.015 
5.8836 
0.553 
8 
Ϫ0.013 
6.3272 
0.611 
9 
Ϫ0.024 
7.8169 
0.553 
10 
Ϫ0.006 
7.9043 
0.638 
11 
Ϫ0.023 
9.3163 
0.593 
12 
Ϫ0.013 
9.7897 
0.634 
13 
Ϫ0.003 
9.8110 
0.709 
14 
0.009 
10.038 
0.759 
15 
Ϫ0.012 
10.444 
0.791 </p>



<p>which the equity market tanks and the bond yields fall. The parameters are not 
reestimated, but the formula is simply updated each day. The computed value 
at risk rises substantially from the $40,000 initial figure as the volatility rises in 
April 2000. Then the losses decline, so that the value at risk is well above the 
realized losses. Toward the end of the period, the losses approach the value at 
risk again, but at a lower level. In this year and a quarter, the value at risk is 
exceeded only once; thus, this is actually a slightly conservative estimate of the 
risk. It is not easy to determine whether a particular value-at-risk number is 
correct, although statistical tests can be formulated for this in the same way they 
are formulated for volatilities. For example, Engle and Manganelli (2001) 
present a "dynamic quantile test." </p>

<p>Figure 2 
Value at Risk and Portfolio Losses In-Sample </p>

<p>Figure 3 
Value at Risk and Portfolio Losses Out of Sample </p>

<p>GARCH 101: The Use of ARCH/GARCH models in Applied Econometrics 165 </p>

<p>Extensions and Modifications of GARCH </p>

<p>The GARCH(1,1) is the simplest and most robust of the family of volatility 
models. However, the model can be extended and modified in many ways. I will 
briefly mention three modifications, although the number of volatility models that 
can be found in the literature is now quite extraordinary. 
The GARCH(1,1) model can be generalized to a GARCH( p,q) model-that 
is, a model with additional lag terms. Such higher-order models are often useful 
when a long span of data is used, like several decades of daily data or a year of 
hourly data. With additional lags, such models allow both fast and slow decay of 
information. A particular specification of the GARCH(2,2) by Engle and Lee 
(1999), sometimes called the "component model," is a useful starting point to this 
approach. 
ARCH/GARCH models thus far have ignored information on the direction of 
returns; only the magnitude matters. However, there is very convincing evidence 
that the direction does affect volatility. Particularly for broad-based equity indices 
and bond market indices, it appears that market declines forecast higher volatility 
than comparable market increases do. There is now a variety of asymmetric GARCH 
models, including the EGARCH model of Nelson (1991), the TARCH model-
threshold ARCH-attributed to Rabemananjara and Zakoian (1993) and Glosten, 
Jaganathan and Runkle (1993), and a collection and comparison by Engle and Ng  (1993). 
The goal of volatility analysis must ultimately be to explain the causes of 
volatility. While time series structure is valuable for forecasting, it does not 
satisfy our need to explain volatility. The estimation strategy introduced for 
ARCH/GARCH models can be directly applied if there are predetermined or 
exogenous variables. Thus, we can think of the estimation problem for the 
variance just as we do for the mean. We can carry out specification searches and 
hypothesis tests to find the best formulation. Thus far, attempts to find the 
ultimate cause of volatility are not very satisfactory. Obviously, volatility is a 
response to news, which must be a surprise. However, the timing of the news 
may not be a surprise and gives rise to predictable components of volatility, such 
as economic announcements. It is also possible to see how the amplitude of 
news events is influenced by other news events. For example, the amplitude of 
return movements on the United States stock market may respond to the 
volatility observed earlier in the day in Asian markets as well as to the volatility 
observed in the United States on the previous day. Engle, Ito and Lin (1990) call 
these "heat wave" and "meteor shower" effects. 
A similar issue arises when examining several assets in the same market. Does 
the volatility of one influence the volatility of another? In particular, the volatility 
of an individual stock is clearly influenced by the volatility of the market as a whole. 
This is a natural implication of the capital asset pricing model. It also appears that 
there is time variation in idiosyncratic volatility (for example, Engle, Ng and 
Rothschild, 1992). </p>



<p>This discussion opens the door to multivariate modeling where not only the 
volatilities but also the correlations are to be investigated. There are now a large 
number of multivariate ARCH models to choose from. These turn out often to be 
difficult to estimate and to have large numbers of parameters. Research is continu-
ing to examine new classes of multivariate models that are more convenient for 
fitting large covariance matrices. This is relevant for systems of equations such as 
vector autoregressions and for portfolio problems where possibly thousands of 
assets are to be analyzed. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>ARCH and GARCH models have been applied to a wide range of time series 
analyses, but applications in finance have been particularly successful and have 
been the focus of this introduction. Financial decisions are generally based 
upon the tradeoff between risk and return; the econometric analysis of risk is 
therefore an integral part of asset pricing, portfolio optimization, option pric-
ing and risk management. This paper has presented an example of risk mea-
surement that could be the input to a variety of economic decisions. The 
analysis of ARCH and GARCH models and their many extensions provides a 
statistical stage on which many theories of asset pricing and portfolio analysis 
can be exhibited and tested. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Bollerslev, Tim. 1986. "Generalized Autore-
gressive Conditional Heteroskedasticity." Journal 
of Econometrics. April, 31:3, pp. 307-27. 
Bollerslev, Tim and Jeffrey M. Wooldridge. 
1992. "Quasi-Maximum Likelihood Estimation 
and Inference in Dynamic Models with Time-
Varying Covariances." Econometric Reviews. 11:2, 
pp. 143-72. 
Engle, Robert F. 1982. "Autoregressive Condi-
tional Heteroskedasticity with Estimates of the 
Variance of United Kingdom Inflation." Econo-
metrica. 50:4, pp. 987-1007. 
Engle, Robert and Gary G. J. Lee. 1999. "A 
Permanent and Transitory Component Model 
of Stock Return Volatility," in Cointegration, Cau-
sality, and Forecasting: A Festschrift in Honour of 
Clive W. J. Granger. Robert F. Engle and Halbert </p>

<p>White, eds. Oxford: Oxford University Press, pp. 
475-97. 
Engle, Robert F. and Simone Manganelli. 
1999. "CAViaR: Conditional Autoregressive 
Value at Risk by Regression Quantiles." Depart-
ment of Economics, University of California, San 
Diego, Working Paper 99 -20. 
Engle, Robert F. and Simone Manganelli. 
2001. "CAViaR: Conditional Autoregressive 
Value at Risk by Regression Quantiles." Manu-
script, University of California, San Diego. Re-
vision of NBER Working Paper No. W7341 
(1999). 
Engle, Robert F. and Joseph Mezrich. 1996. 
"GARCH for Groups." RISK. 9:8, pp. 36 -40. 
Engle, Robert F. and Victor Ng. 1993. "Mea-
suring and Testing the Impact of News on </p>

<p>Robert Engle 167 </p>

<p>Volatility." Journal of Finance. December, 48:5, 
pp. 1749 -78. 
Engle, Robert, Takatoshi Ito and Wen-Ling 
Lin. 1990. "Meteor Showers or Heat Waves? Het 
eroskedastic Intra-Daily Volatility in the Foreign 
Exchange Market." Econometrica. May, 58:3, pp. 
525-42. 
Engle, Robert, Victor Ng and M. Rothschild. 
1992. "A Multi-Dynamic Factor Model for Stock 
Returns." Journal of Econometrics. April/May, 52: 
1-2, pp. 245-66. 
Glosten, Lawrence R., Ravi Jagannathan and 
David E. Runkle. 1993. "On the Relation Be-</p>

<p>tween the Expected Value and the Volatility of 
the Nominal Excess Returns on Stocks." Journal 
of Finance. 48:5, pp. 1779 -801. 
Koenker, Roger and Gilbert Bassett. 1978. 
"Regression Quantiles." Econometrica. January, 
46:1, pp. 33-50. 
Nelson, Daniel B. 1991. "Conditional Het-
eroscedasticity in Asset Returns: A New Ap-
proach." Econometrica. 59:2, pp. 347-70. 
Rabemananjara, R. and J. M. Zakoian. 1993. 
"Threshold Arch Models and Asymmetries in 
Volatility." Journal of Applied Econometrics. Janu-
ary/March, 8:1, pp. 31-49. </p>



<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



<p>123. Teresa Serra. 2013. Time-series econometric analyses of biofuel-related price volatility. Agricultural 
Economics 44:s1, 53-62. [Crossref] </p>

<p>124. Ulrich Oberndorfer, Peter Schmidt, Marcus Wagner, Andreas Ziegler. 2013. Does the stock market 
value the inclusion in a sustainability stock index? An event study analysis for German firms. Journal 
of Environmental Economics and Management 66:3, 497-509. [Crossref] </p>

<p>125. Monica Singhania, Jugal Anchalia. 2013. Volatility in Asian stock markets and global financial crisis. 
Journal of Advances in Management Research 10:3, 333-351. [Crossref] </p>

<p>126. H. Evren Damar, Césaire A. Meh, Yaz Terajima. 2013. Leverage, balance-sheet size and wholesale 
funding. Journal of Financial Intermediation 22:4, 639-662. [Crossref] </p>

<p>127. Kyungwon Kim. 2013. Modeling financial crisis period: A volatility perspective of Credit Default 
Swap market. Physica A: Statistical Mechanics and its Applications 392:20, 4977-4988. [Crossref] </p>

<p>128. Kyungjin Yoo, Youah Lee, Eunnyeong Heo. 2013. Economic effects by merger and acquisition types 
in the renewable energy sector: An event study approach. Renewable and Sustainable Energy Reviews 
26, 694-701. [Crossref] </p>

<p>129. Vinodh Madhavan. 2013. Nonlinearity in investment grade Credit Default Swap (CDS) Indices of US 
and Europe: Evidence from BDS and close-returns tests. Global Finance Journal . [Crossref] </p>

<p>130. David E. Allen, Ron Amram, Michael McAleer. 2013. Volatility spillovers from the Chinese stock 
market to economic neighbours. Mathematics and Computers in Simulation 94, 238-257. [Crossref] </p>

<p>131. Gianluca Benigno, Pierpaolo Benigno, Salvatore Nisticò. 2013. Second-order approximation of 
dynamic models with time-varying risk. Journal of Economic Dynamics and Control 37:7, 1231-1247. 
[Crossref] </p>

<p>132. William R. Parke, George A. Waters. 2013. ON THE EVOLUTIONARY STABILITY OF 
RATIONAL EXPECTATIONS. Macroeconomic Dynamics 1-26. [Crossref] </p>

<p>133. Pat Obi, Shomir Sil. 2013. VaR and time-varying volatility: a comparative study of three international 
portfolios. Managerial Finance 39:7, 625-640. [Crossref] </p>

<p>134. Marco Lippi, Matteo Bertini, Paolo Frasconi. 2013. Short-Term Traffic Flow Forecasting: An 
Experimental Comparison of Time-Series Analysis and Supervised Learning. IEEE Transactions on 
Intelligent Transportation Systems 14:2, 871-882. [Crossref] </p>



</text></tei>