<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1017%2Fs1365100515000619" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>I examine whether an RBC model can generate a higher volatility of consumption relative 
to output, a strong negative correlation between output and the trade balance, and a weak 
countercyclicality of the real interest rate, phenomena that have been observed in the 
business cycles of emerging economies, including Korea. From an RBC model with 
recursive utility, I show that it is not the degree of relative risk aversion, but the elasticity 
of intertemporal substitution (EIS), that governs the movements of the variables of the 
model in the log linearized environment. The Bayesian estimation results based on Korean 
data from the period 1987 to 2013 suggest that there are some elements of success in 
describing the Korean economy based on the simple RBC model both with the EIS larger 
than one and with an error term for the real interest rate equation. An EIS larger than one 
improves the performance of the simple RBC model mainly in the direction of raising the 
volatility of consumption relative to output. Simulation results show that the error term for 
the real interest rate process mostly reflects the endogenous channel of financial frictions 
where the domestic real interest rate depends negatively on the expected (transitory) 
productivity shock. </p>

<p>Some researchers have recently observed that business cycles in emerging eco-
nomies can be characterized very differently from those in advanced economies. 
For example, in emerging economies, consumption is relatively more volatile 
than output, the trade balance is strongly countercyclical, and the cost of foreign 
borrowing is countercyclical. 
1 I will call these the stylized facts in emerging-
economy business cycles. 
Notably, Aguiar and Gopinath (2007; henceforth AG) showed that the standard 
RBC model with a growth shock can successfully explain the stylized facts in 
emerging-economy business cycles. AG argue that a shock to the growth rate 
leads to an even larger increase in future income, implying that consumption 
responds more than current period income, reducing savings and generating a </p>

<p>I benefited from helpful comments by two anonymous referees, Sungbae An, Hong-Ki Bahng, Yongsung Chang, 
Yongseung Jung, Jinill Kim, Siwon Ryu, Myung-Soo Yi, Tack Yun, and seminar participants at the 2012 JSIE 
meeting. Any errors are mine. Address correspondence to: Wooheon Rhee, Department of Economics, Kyung Hee 
University, 25 Kyungheedae-ro, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 130-701, Korea; e-mail: wrhee@khu.ac.kr. </p>

<p>c 2016 Cambridge University Press 
1365-1005/16 </p>

<p>599 </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>large trade deficit. In contrast, if the shock is transitory, agents will increase 
savings. Consumption will increase by less and the trade balance will deteriorate 
by less or even improve. 
Previous research on emerging-economy business cycles examines Korean data 
when pointing out the stylized facts, but estimations and discussions mainly focus 
on Latin American economies such as Mexico and Argentina. Thus, examining 
the issue based explicitly on Korean data both in calibration and in estimation 
would fill a gap in the literature, which is one of the aims of this paper. 
In order to examine the issue, I employ the recursive utility of Epstein and  Zin (1991) and Weil (1989) instead of the CRRA utility function commonly 
used in the literature on emerging-economy business cycles. It is well known 
that the degree of relative risk aversion equals the inverse of the elasticity of 
intertemporal substitution (EIS hereafter) in the CRRA utility function, and they 
are not disentangled. If we stick to the conventional interpretation of the CRRA 
utility function, and if we set the degree of relative risk aversion at two to four, 
commonly used in the literature, we have a situation where the discount factor 
is greater than one in the Korean data. Specifically, as I show in Section 3, the 
CRRA utility function implies that the real interest rate (1 + r) in the steady state 
equals g 
γ /β, where γ denotes the degree of relative risk aversion, and g represents 
the steady state value of the (gross) growth rate. Put differently, β = g 
γ /(1 + r). 
Unless the mean growth rate is far less than the steady state value of the real interest 
rate, β (the discount factor) is greater than one. Unfortunately in the Korean data, 
the mean growth rate of real GDP is slightly less than the highest measure of the 
mean real interest rate for the sample period. 
2 Therefore, we should fix γ at one in 
order to have β less than one, if we stick to the conventional interpretation of the 
CRRA utility function. Even in this case, β turns out to be 0.9985 in the Korean 
data, which is virtually one. 
The recursive utility (RU) of Epstein and Zin (1991) and Weil (1989) separates 
the degree of relative risk aversion from the EIS. Log linearization of the model 
with recursive utility shows that it is not the degree of relative risk aversion but 
the elasticity of intertemporal substitution that governs the movements of the log 
linearized system of the model. It is the EIS that governs the movements of the 
stochastic discount factor. The steady state value of the real interest rate and all the 
log linearized equations are governed by the EIS-not by the measure of relative 
risk aversion. This means that the RBC model with recursive utility is seemingly 
equivalent to the same model with the CRRA utility function in the log linearized 
environment. However, the interpretation of the model parameter γ , the degree of 
relative risk aversion in the CRRA utility function, might be different: it represents 
not the degree of relative risk aversion but the inverse of the EIS. This allows us to 
set γ , conventionally interpreted as the meaure of relative risk aversion, to a value 
less than one, implying an EIS greater than one. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>I calibrate a model based on Korean data for the period 1987-2013 and do a 
Bayesian estimation of the model. The estimation and simulation results suggest 
that it is fair to say that a simple RBC model both with the EIS greater than one </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>and with an error term for the real interest rate equation can reasonably explain 
the business cycle stylized facts in the Korean economy despite its simplicity. It 
explains the excess volatility of consumption relative to output. The simulated 
volatility of consumption relative to output is 1.22, and close to the actual number 
from the data, 1.25. It also shows a weak countercyclicality (or acyclicality) of the 
real interest rate. 
I set the prior mean of the EIS at 2.3 in the Bayesian estimation of the model 
with recursive utility, which is equivalent to setting γ to 1/2.3 in the log linearized 
model with the CRRA utility function. The relative success of the RBC model 
with recursive utility, coupled with the EIS larger than one, or, equivalently, the 
model with the CRRA utility function, combined with γ less than one, suggests 
that it is the EIS, not the coefficient of relative risk aversion, that contributes 
most to the increase in the relative volatility of consumption in the model. We 
can understand this easily if we recall that the degree of risk aversion reflects 
intratemporal substitution across states, whereas the EIS reflects the intertemporal 
substitution across time. A higher EIS implies a higher volatility of consumption 
if other things are equal. 
I also include an error term for the real interest rate equation. It can be interpreted 
as either reflecting some aspects of financial frictions or representing a measure-
ment error independent of them. Some researchers argue for the importance of 
incorporating some aspects of financial frictions into the standard RBC model 
in order to explain the stylized facts in emerging-economy business cycles. For 
example, Neumeyer and Perri (2005), Uribe and Yue (2006), Garcia-Cicco et al.  (2010), and Chang and Fernandez (2013) argue for the importance of interest rate 
shocks and financial frictions in explaining the stylized facts in emerging-economy 
business cycles. The estimation results confirm that this is also the case in Korea. 
Interest rate shocks are important in explaining the stylized facts in Korean busi-
ness cycles. The error term for the real interest rate equation turns out to reflect 
mostly the endogenous channel of financial frictions, where the domestic real 
interest rate depends negatively on the expected (transitory) productivity shock. 
The estimation results further imply that the contribution of the trend component 
is small (about six percent) in explaining the movements of output. 
In Section 2, I discuss some aspects of the Korean business cycles along with 
fluctuations in productivity. The data show that the excess volatility of consumption 
relative to output is mainly due to market conditions in the 1990s and 2000s. In 
Section 3, I introduce the simple RBC model with a growth shock proposed 
by AG and Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) and discuss some issues in matching the 
implications of the model with the Korean data. I then incorporate the recursive 
utility of Epstein and Zin (1991) and Weil (1989) into the simple RBC model 
in order to show that it is the EIS, not the degree of relative risk aversion, that 
governs the movements of the log linearized system of the model. In Section 4, I 
describe the Korean data, present the Bayesian estimation results from the baseline 
RBC model, both with the EIS larger than one and with an error term for the real 
interest rate equation, and discuss the importance of the trend component. In order </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>-0.15 </p>

<p>-0.1 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>1970 1 
1971 1 
1972 1 
1973 1 
1974 1 
1975 1 
1976 1 
1977 1 
1978 1 
1979 1 
1980 1 
1981 1 
1982 1 
1983 1 
1984 1 
1985 1 
1986 1 
1987 1 
1988 1 
1989 1 
1990 1 
1991 1 
1992 1 
1993 1 
1994 1 
1995 1 
1996 1 
1997 1 
1998 1 
1999 1 
2000 1 
2001 1 
2002 1 
2003 1 
2004 1 
2005 1 
2006 1 
2007 1 
2008 1 
2009 1 
2010 1 
2011 1 
2012 1 
2013 1 </p>

<p>GDP per capita </p>

<p>ConsumpƟon per capita </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Business cycles in Korea. </p>

<p>to examine whether the error term for the real interest rate equation reflects some 
aspects of financial frictions, or whether it represents a simple measurement error 
independent of them, I do some additional analyses on RBC models with various 
aspects of financial frictions in Section 5. I examine whether the main message of 
this paper-that the higher EIS can explain the excess volatility of consumption 
relative to output-can be applied to the Argentine economy in Section 6. I also 
examine whether taking the risky steady state into consideration can improve 
the performance of the simple RBC model in explaining the excess volatility of 
consumption relative to output in Section 7. Section 8 briefly concludes. </p>

<p>2. SOME REMARKS ON KOREAN BUSINESS CYCLES </p>

<p>Previous research shows that the Korean economy exhibits excess volatility of 
consumption relative to output, as do other emerging economies. For example, 
AG's Table 2B reports that the volatility of consumption relative to output is 
1.23 in the case of Korea. However, it is worthwhile to note that consumption is 
not always more volatile than output throughout the AG's sample period (79:IV-
03:II). The excess volatility of consumption relative to output is due to the fact 
that consumption is more volatile than output only for the latter part of the sample, 
the 1990s and 2000s. More specifically, the volatility of consumption relative to 
output is 0.82 (0.85) for the sample period between 79:IV and 86:IV (95:IV). It 
increases and becomes higher than one as the latter part of the sample is included. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows log GDP per capita and log consumption per capita in Korea for 
the period 1970:I-2013:IV, for which official GDP data published by the Bank of 
Korea are available. The source of the data will be discussed in Subsection 4.1. Log 
GDP per capita and log consumption per capita are HP-filtered with a smoothing 
parameter of 1600. One thing we have to note in Figure 1 is that consumption is no 
longer more volatile than output for the sample period as a whole. The volatility 
of consumption relative to output is 0.88. However, when the sample covers the 
period between 87:I (93:I) and 13:IV, it rises to 1.25 (1.33). </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>TABLE 1. Business cycle reference dates and the average growth rates of TFP 
in Korea: 1970-2013 </p>

<p>Length Average of TFP 
Cycle 
Trough 
Peak 
Trough 
(months) 
growth rates </p>

<p>1 
Mar. 1972 
Feb. 1974 Jun. 1975 
39 
0.07 
2 
Jun. 1975 
Feb. 1979 Sep. 1980 
63 
−0.04 
3 
Sep. 1980 
Feb. 1984 Sep. 1985 
60 
0.26 
4 
Sep. 1985 
Jan. 1988 Jul. 1989 
46 
0.26 
5 
Jul. 1989 
Jan. 1992 Jan. 1993 
42 
0.28 
6 
Jan. 1993 
Mar. 1996 Aug. 1998 
67 
−0.05 
7 
Aug. 1998 
Aug. 2000 Jul. 2001 
35 
0.17 
8 
Jul. 2001 
Dec. 2002 Apr. 2005 
45 
0.31 
9 
Apr. 2005 
Jan. 2008 Feb. 2009 
46 
0.33 
10 
Feb. 2009 
Aug. 2011 2nd half of 2012 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>0.44 
11 
2nd half of 2012 </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  This is preliminary and not yet officially confirmed by Statistics Korea. </p>

<p>This fact suggests that we would best use a shorter sample rather than the 
whole sample as far as the Korean data are concerned in examining whether RBC 
models can explain the stylized facts in emerging-economy business cycles such as 
excess volatility of consumption relative to output. Another reason we should use 
a shorter rather than the whole sample is that we have little official data on interest 
rates, reflecting market conditions until the 1990s. Almost no official interest rate 
data are available for the earlier part of the sample. The Bank of Korea does not 
publish interest rate data for the earlier period, mainly because both deposit and 
lending interest rates were controlled by the government and do not reflect market 
conditions. One interest rate that provides the longest series and, at the same time, 
reflects market conditions is the rate for AA-rated corporate bonds [CB(AA-)], 
and data on this interest rate are available only since 1987. 
There is a cost in using a shorter rather than the whole sample, however. There 
may not be enough trend (or business) cycles to analyze in the short data sample. 
Statistics Korea is in charge of dating the official business cycle reference dates 
in Korea. They are reported in Table 1. There were eleven business cycles for the 
period between 1970 and 2013, and seven cycles for the period between 1987:I 
and 2013:IV. It suggests that if we use the data for the period between 1987:I and 
2013:IV, we have data for seven business cycles (fourth to eleventh cycles since 
1970). 
In order to have some idea about the fluctuations in productivity in Korea for 
the sample period, I calculate total factor productivity (henceforth, TFP) for the 
period 1970 to 2011. The TFP is obtained as 
TFP t = log(Y t ) − α log(K t ) − (1 − α) log(h t ), 
(1) 
where Y t and h t denote output and work hours in period t, and K t denotes the 
capital stock at the beginning of period t. The parameter α denotes the capital share </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>-1.5 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.5   1971  1973  1975  1977  1979  1981  1983  1985  1987  1989  1991  1993  1995  1997  1999  2001 
2003 
2005 
2007 
2009 
2011 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>g TFP </p>

<p>business cycle average of TFP </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Growth rates of TFP (g TFP ): 1971-2011. </p>

<p>in output. All the data used to calculate TFP are annual, in 2000 prices, and are 
available from the Korea Productivity Center (http://www.kpc.or.kr/productivity/). 
Of course, TFP measured in this way includes both the transitory and growth 
components of productivity. I do not try to separate them here using a time series 
estimation technique such as that in King et al. (1991). Instead, I report the 
importance of the growth component in Subsection 4.3 based on the Bayesian 
estimation results of the model. 
Figure 2 shows the growth rates of total factor productivity (TFP) for the period 
1971-2011 and the averages of TFP growth rates for each business cycle reported 
in Table 1. Growth rates of TFP fluctuate a lot and the average of TFP growth rates 
falls below zero during the second (75:II-80:III) and sixth (93:I-98:III) business 
cycles. The fall in the second business cycle seems to be related to the first and 
second oil shocks and the fall in the sixth business cycle seems to be related to the 
occurrence of the Asian currency crisis in 1997. After the first fall, the average TFP 
growth rate goes up and fluctuates around 0.26% during the third to fifth business 
cycles. After the second fall, it continuously increases from 0.17% during the 
seventh cycle to 0.44% during the tenth business cycle. Thus, there appear to be 
about five trend cycles for the whole sample for which official national accounting 
data are available and three trend cycles for the shorter sample (87:I-11:IV) in 
terms of the average growth rates of TFP. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>3. THE MODEL </p>

<p>3.1. The Standard RBC Model </p>

<p>Here, I introduce the simple RBC model with a growth shock proposed by AG 
and Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010), among others. The production function takes a </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>Cobb-Douglas form with the labor-augmenting technology </p>

<p>Y t = a t K </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>t (X t h t ) 
1−α . 
(2) </p>

<p>The natural logarithm of the transitory productivity shock, a t , follows a first-order 
autoregressive process, </p>

<p>ln a t = ρ A ln a t−1 + ε At , −1 &lt; ρ A &lt; 1, 
(3) </p>

<p>with ε At ∼ N(0, σ A ). The natural logarithm of the growth rate, g t ≡ </p>

<p>X t 
X t−1 </p>

<p>, of the 
trend component, X t , follows an AR(1) process, </p>

<p>ln(g t+1 /g) = ρ g ln(g t /g) + ε gt+1 , −1 &lt; ρ g &lt; 1, 
(4) </p>

<p>where g denotes the mean of g t and ε gt ∼ N(0, σ g ). The equation of motion for 
the capital stock is given by </p>

<p>K t+1 = (1 − δ)K t + I t , 
(5) </p>

<p>where I t and δ denote investment in period t and the depreciation rate, respectively. 
The budget constraint of a representative agent is given by </p>

<p>D t + C t + I t + 
κ 
2 </p>

<p>K t+1 
K t 
− g </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>K t = Y t + 
D t+1 
1 + r t 
, 
(6) </p>

<p>where D t+1 denotes the bond issued in period t at a discount rate of r t . C t is 
consumption in period t. The parameter κ measures the level of adjustment costs. 
The domestic real interest rate, r t , is the sum of the foreign interest rate (r 
 *  ) and 
the risk premium, φ(exp( D t /X t − d) − 1), and </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>t ≡ 1 + r t = 1 + r 
 *  + φ(exp( D t /X t − d) − 1), 
(7) </p>

<p>where D t is the aggregate level of external debt per capita, which the agent takes 
as exogenous. At equilibrium, D t = D t . The parameter d represents the mean 
external debt per capita. I assume that r </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>t is constant, following Otsu (2008) and 
Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010). The variable Q t is defined as the inverse of the gross 
real interest rate. 
The representative agent's utility function takes the Cobb-Douglas form and 
she solves the following problem subject to the budget constraint (6): </p>

<p>Max E 0 </p>

<p>∞ </p>

<p>t=0 </p>

<p>β 
t C </p>

<p>1−γ 
t </p>

<p>− 1 
1 − γ 
, 
(8) </p>

<p>where γ represents both the degree of relative risk aversion and the inverse of the 
elasticity of intertemporal substitution. Note that the utility function in (8) does 
not have work hours in it. I will explain why I do not consider work hours in this 
paper in detail in Subsection 3.3. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>The first-order conditions with respect to c t , d t , k t+1 in stationary forms (divided 
by X t−1 , and expressed in lowercase letters) are </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>−γ 
t </p>

<p>= λ t , 
(9) </p>

<p>λ t = β </p>

<p>1 + r 
 *  + ψ(e 
d t −d − 1) </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>γ 
t </p>

<p>E t λ t+1 , 
(10) </p>

<p>1 + κ 
k t+1 
k t 
g t − g λ t </p>

<p>= 
β 
g </p>

<p>γ 
t </p>

<p>E t λ t+1 </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>1 − δ + αa t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 h t+1 
k t+1 </p>

<p>1−α </p>

<p>+κ </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 − g − </p>

<p>κ 
2 </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 − g </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎦ , </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>where λ t represents the Lagrange multiplier for the budget constraint facing the 
household. Equation (9) states that the Lagrange multiplier represents the marginal 
utility of consumption. Equations (10) and (11) are the usual Euler equation and 
the capital Euler equation, respectively. 
The remaining equilibrium conditions are </p>

<p>d t + c t + i t + 
κ 
2 </p>

<p>k t+1 
k t 
g t − g </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>k t = y t + 
d t+1 
1 + r t 
g t , 
(12) </p>

<p>r t = r 
 *  + ψ(e 
d t −d − 1), 
(13) </p>

<p>k t+1 g t = (1 − δ)k t + i t , 
(14) </p>

<p>y t = a t k </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>t (g t h t ) 
1−α . 
(15) </p>

<p>For later use, trade balance (tb) is defined as </p>

<p>tb t = d t − 
d t+1 
1 + r t 
g t . 
(16) </p>

<p>3.2. Real Interest Rates in Korea </p>

<p>Before we proceed, let me point out that, in order to explain movements in the 
real interest rate in Korea, we need to assume a relatively lower discount rate (or 
relatively higher value of β) than for other emerging economies such as Mexico 
and Argentina, which have been the main focus of the recent literature. We need 
to make this supposition because the sample mean (gross) growth rate, g, is large 
relative to the sample mean (gross) real interest rate (1 + r). </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>-2.0 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>6.0 </p>

<p>8.0 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>12.0 </p>

<p>14.0 </p>

<p>1987 1 
1988 1 
1989 1 
1990 1 
1991 1 
1992 1 
1993 1 
1994 1 
1995 1 
1996 1 
1997 1 
1998 1 
1999 1 
2000 1 
2001 1 
2002 1 
2003 1 
2004 1 
2005 1 
2006 1 
2007 1 
2008 1 
2009 1 
2010 1 
2011 1 
2012 1 
2013 1 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>CB(AA-) </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. The real interest rate in Korea. </p>

<p>From equations (10) and (13), we know that the (net) real interest rate in the 
steady state is given by </p>

<p>r = r 
 *  = 
g </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>β 
− 1. 
(17) </p>

<p>This can be rewritten as </p>

<p>β = 
g </p>

<p>γ </p>

<p>1 + r 
. 
(18) </p>

<p>Equation (18) suggests that the discount factor β should be greater than one if the 
steady state value of the mean (gross) growth rate, g, is large relative to the steady 
state (gross) real interest rate, (1 + r). Other things equal, the lower the steady 
state value of the real interest rate, the higher the discount factor. Thus we need a 
measure of the real interest rate that is large relative to the steady state value of 
the mean (gross) growth rate, g, in order to avoid a situation where the discount 
factor β is larger than one. 
Figure 3 plots the real interest rate in Korea for the sample period 1987:I-
2013:IV. In the figure, the real interest rate is calculated as the difference between 
the nominal interest rate for AA-rated corporate bonds [CB(AA-)] and the 
four-quarter moving average of the GDP deflator inflation rates. This choice is 
restricted by the availability of data for the sample and the representativeness of 
market conditions. This measure of the real interest rate fluctuates between 6% 
and 13% during the first half of the sample and peaks in the second quarter of 
1998, during which time the IMF and the Korean government agreed to switch 
from a high-interest-rate policy to a more modest interest-rate policy. After that it 
tends to go down and stays below 4% for most of the period, except for the credit 
crunch in 2002 and the initial stage of the financial crisis in 2008. The average 
annual real interest rate is 5.47% for the sample period. 
We should note that even this measure of the average quarterly real interest rate 
(1.37%) reported in Figure 3 is much lower than the values implied by AG (the 
quarterly rate of 3.4% for Mexico) and Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) (the annual rate </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>of 9.5% for Argentina). This restricts our choice of values for γ , which measures 
the degree of relative risk aversion. The most commonly accepted values for γ 
range from two to four in the business cycle research. It is thought to be much 
larger than that if our main focus is on explaining movements in financial variables. 
The fact that the sample mean of the real interest rate is relatively low in Korea 
restricts the choice of the value for γ to one or less. More specifically, the average 
quarterly (gross) growth rate of GDP per capita, g, for the sample is 1.0122, and 
the average quarterly gross real interest rate, 1 +r, is 1.0137. If the exponent of the 
preference, γ , equals two, then the discount factor (β) calculated from equation 
(18) is 1.01 and is larger than one. Thus, I need to fix the parameter γ at one or a 
value less than one in order not to have the discount factor be larger than one and to 
let β be determined at the level that satisfies the steady state equilibrium condition 
(18). Even in the case of γ = 1, β turns out to be 0.9985. This is virtually one. </p>

<p>3.3. The Model with Recursive Utility </p>

<p>Unlike the previous research in this area, I employ the recursive utility of Epstein  and Zin (1991) and Weil (1989) in explaining the stylized facts in emerging-
economy business cycles. One advantage of using this type of utility is that we 
can separate the degree of (relative) risk aversion from the EIS. As is well known, 
the CRRA utility function does not disentangle the two parameters. The degree of 
relative risk aversion equals the inverse of the EIS in the CRRA utility function. 
I assume that the agent's objective function is given by </p>

<p>V t = (1 − β)C </p>

<p>1−γ 
θ </p>

<p>t </p>

<p>+ β E t V </p>

<p>1−γ 
t+1 </p>

<p>1 
θ </p>

<p>θ 
1−γ </p>

<p>, 
(19) </p>

<p>where θ ≡ </p>

<p>1−γ 
1−1/ψ </p>

<p>, and the parameters γ and ψ represent the degree of relative risk 
aversion and the EIS, respectively. If γ = </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>, and θ = 1, the objective function V t 
collapses to the usual CRRA utility fuction. The specific form of the value function 
in (19) is borrowed from Dew-Becker (2012) and Chen et al. (2013), among others, 
though their main focus is not (emerging-economy) business cycles. 
The stochastic discount factor and the Euler equation in stationary forms are 
given by </p>

<p>m t,t+1 ≡ βE t </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎩ </p>

<p>c t+1 
c t 
g t </p>

<p>1−γ −θ 
θ </p>

<p>v t+1 g t </p>

<p>(θ −1)(1−γ ) 
θ </p>

<p>E t v t+1 g t </p>

<p>1−γ </p>

<p>θ −1 
θ </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎭ 
(20) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>1 = E t </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎩ 
β 
c t+1 
c t 
g t </p>

<p>1−γ −θ 
θ </p>

<p>v t+1 g t </p>

<p>(θ −1)(1−γ ) 
θ </p>

<p>E t v t+1 g t </p>

<p>1−γ </p>

<p>θ −1 
θ </p>

<p>(1 + r t ) </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎭ 
, 
(21) </p>

<p>respectively. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>Note that the value function in (19) does not have work hours in it. The reason 
I do not consider the labor market in this paper is that it is known that the simple 
RBC model with a growth shock presented in Subsection 3.1 does not satisfactorily 
explain the stylized facts in emerging-economy labor markets: large fluctuations 
in wages and subdued fluctuations in employment. Refer to Bahng (2012) and Boz  et al. (2012) for the detailed discussions and references therein. Another reason 
I do not include work hours in the utility function is to remove the interaction 
between consumption and labor. If the period utility depends nonseparably on 
both consumption and labor, the marginal utility of consumption depends on labor. 
Furthermore, even if consumption and labor are separable in the period utility, the 
stochastic discount factor is affected by labor through the value function for the 
next period, V t+1 , as noted in Dew-Becker (2014). 
The main purpose of this paper is to examine whether the simple RBC model 
with recursive utility can generate a higher volatility of consumption relative 
to output, a strong negative correlation between output and the trade balance, 
and a weak countercyclicality of the real interest rate-phenomena that have been 
observed in Korean business cycles. For that reason, I assume that the labor supply 
is inelastically fixed at unity. Then the production function (15) is given by </p>

<p>y t = a t k </p>

<p>α </p>

<p>t (g t ) 
1−α . 
(22) </p>

<p>The use of recursive utility also changes the capital Euler equation: </p>

<p>1 + κ 
k t+1 
k t 
g t − g </p>

<p>= E t </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎪ ⎨ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎩ 
m t,t+1 </p>

<p>⎡ </p>

<p>⎢ 
⎣ </p>

<p>1 − δ + αa t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 
k t+1 </p>

<p>1−α </p>

<p>+κ </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 − g − </p>

<p>κ 
2 </p>

<p>k t+2 
k t+1 </p>

<p>g t+1 − g </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>⎤ </p>

<p>⎥ 
⎦ </p>

<p>⎫ 
⎪ ⎬ </p>

<p>⎪ ⎭ 
. </p>

<p>(23) </p>

<p>The remaining equilibrium conditions are equations (12)-(14). I will call the 
model described in this subsection the baseline model. 
For later use, let us derive the real interest rate in the steady state when we 
employ recursive utility. From the Euler equation (21), we know that the steady 
state level of the (net) real interest rate is given by </p>

<p>r = r 
 *  = 
g </p>

<p>(γ +θ−1)/θ </p>

<p>β 
− 1, 
(24) </p>

<p>which implies that </p>

<p>β = 
g </p>

<p>1+(γ −1)/θ </p>

<p>1 + r 
= 
g </p>

<p>1/ψ </p>

<p>1 + r 
. 
(25) </p>

<p>The second equality follows from the definition of θ . From this equation, we know 
that the steady state value of the real interest rate is not governed by the degree of </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>relative risk aversion but by the EIS. This implies that we do not have to set the 
value of γ at a very restrictive value of one in order to calibrate the model with 
the Korean data. 
In addition, the log linearization of the model reveals an interesting feature that 
has not been emphasized in previous work. For example, the log linearization of 
the stochastic discount factor (20) is given by </p>

<p>E t m t,t+1 = E t − 
1 
ψ 
( c t+1 − c t + g t ) , 
(26) </p>

<p>and the log linearization of the Euler equation (21) is given by </p>

<p>E t m t,t+1 − q t = 0, 
(27) </p>

<p>where q t denotes the log linearized Q t ≡ </p>

<p>1 
1+r t </p>

<p>. This shows that it is not the 
degree of relative risk aversion but the EIS that governs the movements of the log 
linearized system of the model. 
The conventional log linearized stochastic discount factor in the case of the 
CRRA utility function simply replaces </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>with γ in equation (26). Thus, the log 
linearized RBC model with recursive utility is seemingly equivalent to the same 
model with the CRRA utility function. However, the interpretation of the model 
parameter γ , the degree of relative risk aversion and, at the same time, the inverse 
of the EIS, in the CRRA utility function might be different: it represents the 
inverse of the EIS, not the degree of relative risk aversion in the log linearized 
environment. This allows us to set γ , conventionally interpreted as the measure of 
relative risk aversion, to a value less than one, implying that the EIS is larger than 
one. I will come back to this point in Subsection 4.2. </p>

<p>4. DATA AND ESTIMATION RESULTS </p>

<p>Now I turn to a discussion of the Korean data and the estimation methods. </p>

<p>4.1. Data and Calibration </p>

<p>All the national accounting data are from the Economic Statistics System of the 
Bank of Korea (http://ecos.bok.or.kr). As measures of real output, consumption, 
investment, and the trade balance, I use the logarithm of real GDP net of gov-
ernment spending, the logarithm of private consumption, the logarithm of total 
capital formation, and the level of the trade balance, respectively. They are all 
in the series 10.4.2.2 of the Economic Statistics System of the Bank of Korea. 
As is well known, Korea has experienced dramatic changes in demography over 
the sample period. The population growth rate is falling, and the society is aging 
very rapidly. However, the model in Section 3 does not consider labor supply, 
let alone population growth. Examining the effect of population dynamics on 
the Korean economy is itself a very important issue and it is beyond the scope </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>of this paper. Thus, I transform all the variables into per capita variables. All 
the relevant variables are divided by the population measure used by the Bank 
of Korea to get the per capita values. The population data are from the Korean 
Statistical Information Service (KOSIS). All the data are HP-filtered in order to 
have stationary series and the smoothing parameter is set to 1600. 
The sample period is 1987:I-2013:IV. As explained in Section 2, this period 
is chosen for several reasons. First, the excess volatility of consumption relative 
to output is not a prominent phenomenon in Korean business cycles before the 
Asian currency crisis of 1997. The volatility of consumption relative to output for 
the period 1970-1995 is just 0.51. Consumption was much smoother than output 
for the period, as it is in advanced economies. Second, the Korean government 
liberalized the financial market in the early 1990s and has let the interest rate be 
determined in the market step by step since 1992. Before then, interest rates were 
controlled by the government. The longest market interest rate series that the Bank 
of Korea officially publishes is the rate for AA-rated corporate bonds; this series 
has been available since January 1987. Third, the period includes two crises: the 
Asian currency crisis in 1997 and the global financial crisis in 2008. The two crises 
contributed to the excess volatility of consumption relative to output. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>For the sample period, the average quarterly growth rate (g) of real GDP net of 
government spending in Korea is set to 1.2%. The average quarterly net real interest 
rate (r) for the sample period is set to 1.4%. Real interest rates are constructed 
as the difference between the AA-corporate bond yields (series 4.2.2.1) and the 
four-quarter moving average of the GDP deflator inflation rate (series 10.4.3.2). I 
set the capital coefficient at α = 0.4, based on the fact that the labor income share 
(series 10.1.1) in the Korean economy, measured as the ratio of compensation 
for employees to GDP for the period 1987 to 2013, fluctuates around 60%. I set 
the depreciation rate at δ = 0.025, implying an annual depreciation rate of 10%, 
which is commonly used in the literature. I set the steady state value of the trade 
balance (tb)-to-GDP ratio (tby) to 0%, which is based on the sample mean of 
−0.03%. 
As explained in Section 3, it is not the degree of relative risk aversion but the 
EIS that governs the movements of the variables in the model, and the model 
with the CRRA utility function and the model with recursive utility are seemingly 
equivalent in the log linearized environment. Thus, just for purposes of compari-
son, I set the value of γ to unity in the case of the model with the CRRA utility 
function, which virtually means setting the EIS to unity. In the case of the model 
with recursive utility, the parameter γ actually plays no role, because it does not 
appear in the log linearized system of the model. Thus, I simply set it to two. </p>

<p>4.2. Bayesian Estimation and Simulation Results </p>

<p>For the estimation and simulation, I do a Bayesian estimation. I execute the 
Bayesian estimation in <rs id="software-0" type="software">Dynare</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.2.2</rs>. Readers who are interested in the 
details of the estimation are referred to Griffoli's (2007-2008) Dynare User Guide. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>One thing that I should note here is that this version of <rs type="software">Dynare</rs> does not allow the 
higher-order approximation of the model for the estimation. However, it is well 
known that log linearization is good enough if the main focus of the research is 
not on welfare analysis or investigation of the financial market but on examining 
the business cycle. 
Table 2 reports the parameter values, both calibrated and estimated from the 
Bayesian estimation. The model data are simulated 300,000 times. The measure-
ment equations for Y t , C t , I t , and TBY t are given by </p>

<p>g Y t = log Y t </p>

<p>observed </p>

<p>= log(y t ) − log(y t−1 ) + log(g t−1 ) </p>

<p>model </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>g Ct = log C t </p>

<p>observed </p>

<p>= log(c t ) − log(c t−1 ) + log(g t−1 ) </p>

<p>model </p>

<p>, 
(28) </p>

<p>g I t = log I t </p>

<p>observed </p>

<p>= log(i t ) − log(i t−1 ) + log(g t−1 ) </p>

<p>model </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>TBY t = TB t /Y t </p>

<p>observed </p>

<p>= tb t /y t </p>

<p>model </p>

<p>= tby t . </p>

<p>For the estimation, I use g Y , g C , g I , TBY, and r as observed variables, and 
consider a measurement error in each of them. I set the prior distribution for the 
AR(1) parameters for the shock process as a beta distribution, and the parameters 
with positive values as a gamma distribution. 
8 I set the prior distribution for the 
standard deviation of shock processes and the measurement errors for g Y , g C , g I , 
TBY, and r as an inverse gamma distribution. I set the prior mean of the EIS at 2.3, 
which is close to the values used in the literature. For example, Tallarini (2000)  and Piazzesi and Schneider (2006) set ψ at 1, and Bansal and Yaron (2004) set 
it at 1.5. Chen et al. (2013) estimate it to be ≈ 2, and Binsbergen et al. (2012)  estimate it to be 1.72. 
Table 3 reports the key moments simulated from the estimation. In Table 2, I 
set the prior mean of the EIS (ψ) at 2.3 in the case of the model with RU, whereas 
I implicitly set it to unity in the case of the model with the CRRA utility function, 
because it equals the inverse of γ . The log data density from the model with the 
CRRA utility function is 1,454 and that from the model with RU is 1,386. This 
implies that the overall performance of the model with the CRRA utility function 
is slightly better than that of the model with RU. However, the adoption of an EIS 
greater than one improves the performance of the simple RBC model at least in 
one important direction. It primarily raises the volatility of consumption relative to 
output. A higher EIS implies larger fluctuations in expected consumption growth 
given fluctuations in real interest rates. As far as the other second-order moments 
are concerned, the model with an EIS of unity performs better in explaining the 
correlations of investment with output, and both the autocorrelations of the trade 
balance and the real interest rate. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>TABLE 2. Parameter values both calibrated and estimated 
from Bayesian estimation of the Korean economy </p>

<p>Calibrated parameters 
α 
0.4 
g 
1.012 
1 + r 1.014 
γ, ψ γ = 1/ψ =1 (CRRA) γ =2, ψ =see below (RU) </p>

<p>β 
0.998 ⇐ β = </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>1+r </p>

<p>(CRRA), 0.991 ⇐ β = </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>1+r </p>

<p>(RU) 
TB/Y 0.0 
δ 
0.025 
Prior 
Posterior 
90 % C.I. 
Prior 
mean 
mean 
distribution </p>

<p>Estimated parameters (CRRA) 
κ 
3.0 
3.42 
3.25 
3.60 
gamma 
φ 
0.01 
0.003 
0.002 
0.004 
gamma 
ρ A 
0.8 
0.978 
0.970 
0.986 
beta 
ρ g 
0.8 
0.853 
0.785 
0.910 
beta 
σ A 
0.01 
0.029 
0.024 
0.034 
inverse gamma 
σ g 
0.01 
0.006 
0.004 
0.008 
inverse gamma 
σ g Y 
0.01 
0.011 
0.007 
0.015 
inverse gamma 
σ g C 
0.01 
0.015 
0.013 
0.018 
inverse gamma 
σ g I 
0.01 
0.017 
0.007 
0.027 
inverse gamma 
σ TBY 
0.01 
0.005 
0.003 
0.006 
inverse gamma 
σ r 
0.01 
0.004 
0.004 
0.005 
inverse gamma 
Estimated parameters (RU) 
κ 
3.0 
4.07 
3.80 
4.44 
gamma 
φ 
0.01 
0.002 
0.002 
0.002 
gamma 
ψ 
2.3 
2.30 
2.28 
2.32 
gamma 
ρ A 
0.8 
0.943 
0.914 
0.973 
beta 
ρ g 
0.8 
0.851 
0.755 
0.956 
beta 
σ A 
0.01 
0.016 
0.013 
0.019 
inverse gamma 
σ g 
0.01 
0.004 
0.002 
0.005 
inverse gamma 
σ g Y 
0.01 
0.009 
0.006 
0.012 
inverse gamma 
σ g C 
0.01 
0.012 
0.010 
0.014 
inverse gamma 
σ g I 
0.01 
0.021 
0.015 
0.026 
inverse gamma 
σ TBY 
0.01 
0.005 
0.003 
0.006 
inverse gamma 
σ r 
0.01 
0.014 
0.012 
0.016 
inverse gamma </p>

<p>Note: Observed variables in the estimation: g Y , g C , g I , TBY, and r. </p>

<p>Having an EIS greater than one is a controversial issue in macroeconomics. The 
90% confidence interval of the EIS, ψ, ranges from 2.28 to 2.32. This interval does 
not include one. If the 90% confidence interval includes one, we cannot strongly 
exclude the possibility of the EIS being one. This is indirect evidence that we 
cannot reject the hypothesis that the EIS should be greater than one in order to 
explain Korean business cycles. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>TABLE 3. The key moments from Bayesian 
estimation of the Korean economy </p>

<p>Model </p>

<p>Moments 
Data 
CRRA 
RU </p>

<p>σ (c)/σ (y) 
1.25 
0.94 
1.22 
σ (i)/σ (y) 
2.11 
1.23 
2.05 
corr(tb, y) 
−0.66 
−0.01 
0.09 
corr(r, y) 
−0.14 
−0.25 
−0.02 
corr(c, y) 
0.84 
0.97 
0.74 
corr(i, y) 
0.81 
0.94 
0.45 
corr(y, y −1 ) 
0.78 
0.99 
0.97 
corr(c, c −1 ) 
0.84 
0.99 
0.82 
corr(i, i −1 ) 
0.85 
0.95 
0.51 
corr(tb, tb −1 ) 
0.76 
0.59 
0.25 
corr(r, r −1 ) 
0.59 
0.46 
−0.00 
Log data density 
1,454 
1,386 </p>

<p>In sum, we can say that there are, to say the least, some elements of success in 
describing the Korean economy based on the simple RBC model both with EIS 
larger than one and with an error term for the interest rate process. It explains the 
relative volatility between consumption (investment) and output rather well. In 
addition, it can explain the acyclicality or the weak countercyclicality of the real 
interest rate. </p>

<p>4.3. Importance of the Trend Component </p>

<p>The relative importance of the trend (growth) component can be measured as </p>

<p>var [(1 − α)g t ] 
var ( log TFP t ) 
= 
(1 − α) 
2 σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g /(1 − ρ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>g ) 
2σ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>A /(1 + ρ A ) + (1 − α) 2 σ 2 
g /(1 − ρ 2 
g ) </p>

<p>. 
(29) </p>

<p>From Table 2, we can figure out that it is 0.061 in the case of the model with 
CRRA utility (γ = </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>= 1) and 0.063 in the case of the model with RU (prior 
mean of the EIS, ψ = 2.3). This means that the trend component explains a small 
fraction (about 6% ) of the movements of output. 
Table 4 reports the variance decomposition of the RBC model with RU. From 
the variance decomposition, we can confirm that most fluctuations of output are 
due to the transitory technology shock. However, fluctuations in consumption 
and investment are affected by both transitory and growth components. It is also 
noticeable that most of the fluctuations in the trade balance and the real interest 
rates are due to the error term for the interest rate process, ε r . Thus, we can say 
that different shocks are responsible for the movements of different variables. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>TABLE 4. Variance decomposition of 
the RBC model with recursive utility </p>

<p>Variables/shocks 
ε A 
ε g 
ε r </p>

<p>y 
90.4 
9.4 
0.2 
c 
39.9 
44.7 
15.4 
i 
32.8 
25.7 
41.5 
tb 
2.2 
29.4 
68.4 
r 
0.1 
0.2 
99.8 </p>

<p>Then what is the error term for the interest rate process, ε r ? In order to answer 
this question, I turn to discussions of models with financial frictions. </p>

<p>5. MODELS WITH FINANCIAL FRICTIONS </p>

<p>Neumeyer and Perri (2005), Uribe and Yue (2006), Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010), 
and Chang and Fernandez (2013), among others, argue that the AG-type model 
supplemented with financial frictions does a better job of explaining the stylized 
facts in emerging-economy business cycles. Thus, I add various financial frictions 
to the baseline AG-type model from the preceding section and see whether they 
improve the performance of the baseline model. 
There are many types of financial frictions in the literature. The so-called 
endogenous risk premium channel assumes that the country risk premium is en-
dogenously related to the domestic state of the economy. For example, the country 
risk premium goes down if the market expects higher productivity or higher growth 
in the future. Specifically, I will consider the following case: </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>r t = r 
 *  + φ[exp(d t − d) − 1] − ηE t exp(a t+1 − 1) + ε rt . 
(30) </p>

<p>Here, the country risk depends inversely on the expected productivity, a t+1 . This 
case is considered in Neumeyer and Perri (2005) and Faia and Monacelli (2007)  in a different context, and in Chang and Fernandez (2013), among others. One 
advantage of this type of risk premium is that we can have a countercyclical risk 
premium; the risk premium goes down if the market expects higher productivity 
in the future. 
Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) considers a different formulation of the risk premium: </p>

<p>r t = r 
 *  + φ[exp(d t − d) − 1] + exp(μ t − 1) − 1, 
(31) </p>

<p>where 
ln μ t = ρ μ ln μ t−1 + ε μt , −1 &lt; ρ μ &lt; 1, 
(32) </p>

<p>with ε μt ∼ N(0, σ μ ). I call this the exogenous risk premium channel, because it 
simply adds another shock, μ t , to the baseline model of the risk premium. It may 
stem from financial imperfections, which lead to stochastic shifts in the country </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>TABLE 5. Key moments, variance decom-
position of the RBC model with endoge-
nous risk premium channel </p>

<p>Moments 
Data 
Model </p>

<p>σ (c)/σ (y) 
1.25 
1.07 
σ (i)/σ (y) 
2.11 
2.18 
corr(tb, y) 
−0.66 
−0.28 
corr(r, y) 
−0.14 
−0.74 
corr(c, y) 
0.84 
0.91 
corr(i, y) 
0.81 
0.71 
corr(y, y −1 ) 
0.78 
0.87 
corr(c, c −1 ) 
0.84 
0.85 
corr(i, i −1 ) 
0.85 
0.76 
corr(tb, tb −1 ) 
0.76 
0.73 
corr(r, r −1 ) 
0.59 
0.50 </p>

<p>Variance decomposition (%) 
Variables/shocks 
ε A 
ε g 
ε r </p>

<p>y 
89.7 
10.3 
0.0 
c 
63.0 
36.0 
1.1 
i 
79.2 
19.0 
1.8 
tb 
41.3 
51.5 
7.2 
r 
61.8 
0.3 
38.0 
Log data density 
1,430 </p>

<p>premium that are uncorrelated with the state of domestic fundamentals such as a t 
and g t . 
Among the various types of financial frictions, I report only the case of the 
endogenous risk premium channel in Table 5. The exogenous risk premium chan-
nel cannot be differentiated from the baseline model with an error term for the 
real interest rate process, so the estimation results turn out not to be qualitatively 
different. Table 5 reports the log data density, the key moments simulated from the 
estimation, and the variance decompositon of the RBC model with the endogenous 
risk premium channel. 
11 The log data density is 1,430, which is in between the 
model with the CRRA utility function and the model with RU. Compared with the 
RBC model with RU, the RBC model with the endogenous risk premium channel 
better explains the autocorrelations of each variable and the correlations of each 
variable with output except the correlation of r and y. The RBC model with the 
endogenous risk premium channel implies a too strong countercyclicality of the 
real interest rate. If we compare the variance decompostions reported in Tables 
4 and 5, the contribution of ε r in explaining the movements of each variable be-
comes significantly smaller in Table 5, where I take the endogenous risk premium 
channel into consideration. It is almost negligible except the case of r, where ε r 
still explains about 38% of the movements in r. Table 5 implies that ε r represents </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>mostly the endogenous risk premium channel reflected in equation (30). As a 
result, the contribution of the transitory productivity shock, ε A , in explaining the 
movements of each variable significantly increases. </p>

<p>6. APPLICATION TO THE ARGENTINE DATA </p>

<p>Some readers may wonder whether the main message of this paper-that the higher 
EIS can better explain the excess volatility of consumption relative to output in 
Korean business cycles-can also be applied to other emerging economies such as 
Argentina or Mexico. Thus, I do a Bayesian estimation of the Argentine economy 
as an example in this section. 
Several remarks are in order before I report the estimation results for the Ar-
gentine economy. First, I follow Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) except that I adopt 
the Cobb-Douglas utility function instead of Greenwood et al.'s (1988) utility 
function. The estimation results do not change qualitatively when I use exactly 
the same model as Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) where Greenwood et al.'s (1988)  utility function is used instead of the Cobb-Douglas utility function. Second, 
Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) use g Y , g C , g I , and TBY as observed variables and do 
Bayesian estimation. They do not use the real interest rate data in the estimation, 
whereas I use them as one of the observed variables in the estimation of the Korean 
economy. It is because the original motivation of this paper is to explain the excess 
volatility of consumption relative to output combined with both a relatively large 
mean growth rate of output and low real interest rates in Korea. Here, I use the 
same data used for Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010), because I do not have the real 
interest rate data for Argentina. 
For the estimation, I use exactly the same calibrated values as in Table 2 of 
Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010); I set α = 0.32, β = 0.9224, δ = 0.1225, φ (their 
ψ) = 0.001, d = 0.007. I use g Y , g C , g I , and TBY as observed variables, and 
consider a measurement error in each of them. I set the prior distribution of each 
parameter to those values reported in Table 3 of Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010). In 
order to see what happens when the EIS gets larger, I set the value of γ at 2, 1, 
and 1/2 for the purpose of comparison, which corresponds to the EIS of 1/2, 1, 
and 2, respectively, in the model with RU. 
Table 6 reports the key second moments simulated from the estimation. As the 
EIS becomes larger, or equivalently, the parameter γ becomes smaller, the correla-
tion between the output growth and the trade balance to output ratio (tby) becomes 
more negative, the volatility of tby becomes smaller, and the correlation between 
consumption (investment) growth and tby becomes more negative. There are no 
significant changes in the volatilities and autocorrelations of variables: g Y , g C , g I . 
This can be explained as follows: As the EIS becomes larger, consumption fluc-
tuates more to smooth consumption, and the trade balance tends to move more in 
the direction opposite to output. This makes both the correlation between output 
growth and tby and the correlation between consumption (investment) growth and 
tby more negative. However, a higher EIS does not lead to the increased volatility </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>TABLE 6. The key moments from Bayesian estimation of 
the Argentine economy </p>

<p>Moments 
Data 
γ = 2 
γ = 1 
γ = 1/2 </p>

<p>σ (g Y ) 
5.3 
5.5 
5.5 
5.5 
σ (g C ) 
7.5 
10.3 
10.3 
10.0 
σ (g I ) 
20.4 
12.0 
12.1 
12.1 
σ (TBY) 
5.2 
56.7 
39.1 
28.6 
corr(g Y , g C ) 
0.72 
0.42 
0.42 
0.43 
corr(g Y , g I ) 
0.67 
0.57 
0.57 
0.57 
corr(g Y , TBY) 
−0.04 
−0.09 
−0.14 
−0.19 
corr(g C , TBY) 
−0.27 
−0.12 
−0.17 
−0.22 
corr(g I , TBY) 
−0.19 
−0.16 
−0.23 
−0.31 
corr(g Y , g Y −1 ) 
0.11 
0.63 
0.63 
0.63 
corr(g C , g C−1 ) 
−0.01 
0.00 
0.00 
0.00 
corr(g I , g I −1 ) 
0.32 
0.11 
0.11 
0.11 
corr(TBY, TBY −1 ) 
0.58 
0.99 
0.97 
0.94 </p>

<p>Note: The model data were simulated 300,000 times. Calibrated parameter values 
and estimated posterior medians used for the simulations are from Tables 2 and 3 
of Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010). </p>

<p>of consumption relative to output (or the volatility of consumption growth) in the 
Argentine data. This may be because Garcia-Cicco et al.'s (2010) parameterization 
and estimation are best suited to explaining the second moments of the growth 
variables. The volatility of consumption relative to output depends not only on 
the EIS but also on the other parameters such as ρ A , ρ g , and φ, as discussed 
in Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010). Another possibility is that the estimation does not 
include the real interest rate data as one of the observed variables. Or it may be 
because of something else. Unfortunately, I do not have the answer to this issue, 
and I leave it for future research. </p>

<p>7. RISKY STEADY STATE </p>

<p>Most previous business cyle research takes the approach of log linearizing the 
RBC (and/or DSGE) models around the deterministic steady state. However, 
Coeurdacier et al. (2011) show that taking the stochastic steady state into con-
sideration may improve the performance of a model, especially in welfare and/or 
portfolio decision analyses. They explicitly define the risky steady state as "the 
point where agents choose to stay at a given date if they expect future risk and if the 
realizations of shocks is zero at this date." Thus, I examine whether considering the 
risky steady state can be an alternative to the EIS being larger than one in the log 
linearized model with the CRRA utility function in explaining the excess volatility 
of consumption relative to output in emerging-economy business cycles. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>It is not clear whether taking the risky steady state into account will increase 
the volatility of consumption relative to output. Let us suppose that there is a </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>positive income shock. The more persistent the shock is, the more consumption will 
increase. It will exacerbate the trade balance and increase foreign borrowing and 
the risk premium. A higher risk premium will then discourage foreign borrowing 
and stabilize consumption. At the same time, the risky steady state leads to a 
precautionary motive for savings. The precautionary motive for savings will reduce 
consumption in the risky steady state. Thus, it is difficult to say a priori whether 
considering the risky steady state will increase the volatility of consumption 
relative to output. 
Following de Groot (2014), I solve a first-order approximation of the RBC 
model in Subsection 3.1 around a second-order approximation of the model's 
risk-adjusted steady state. 
13 The risk-adjusted correction terms appear in the 
forward-looking equations: the definition of the stochastic discount factor, the 
Euler equation (10), and the capital Euler equation (11). More specifically, these 
three equations are modified at the risky steady state as follows: </p>

<p>m ≡ 
β 
g γ + M 1 , </p>

<p>1 = 
β 
g γ · r + M 2 , 
(33) </p>

<p>1 = 
β 
g γ 1 − δ + α </p>

<p>g 
k </p>

<p>1−α </p>

<p>+ M 3 , </p>

<p>where the lowercase m denotes the stochastic discount factor and the capital Ms 
the risk-adjusted steady state correction terms (the second-order terms). 
Table 7 reports the parameter values used for the simulation, the volatility of 
consumption (investment) relative to output, and the correlation between the trade 
balance (the real interest rate) and output. I set most of the parameter values close 
to the posterior mean of the RBC model with the CRRA utility function reported in 
Table 2, except κ and φ. I set κ = 1 and φ = 0.1. 
14 The volatility of consumption 
relative to output is 0.93 in the case of the risky steady state, which is slightly 
larger than that in the deterministic steady state, and the volatility of investment 
relative to output is 1.35, which is slightly smaller than that in the deterministic 
steady state. Thus, we can say that considering the risky steady state does not 
significantly improve the performance of the log linearized RBC model with the 
CRRA utility function around the deterministic steady state as far as the excess 
volatility of consumption relative to output is concerned. </p>

<p>8. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Previous studies considered Korean data in pointing out the stylized facts in 
emerging-economy business cycles: excess volatility of consumption relative to 
output, a strong negative correlation between output and the trade balance, and a 
negative correlation between output and the real interest rate. However, their main 
focus is on Latin American economies such as Mexico and Argentina. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>TABLE 7. Calibration and the key moments from 
the RBC model with the risky steady state </p>

<p>Calibrated parameters 
α 
0.4 
g 
1.012 
1 + r 
1.014 
γ, ψ 
γ = 1/ψ =1 </p>

<p>β 
0.998 ⇐ β = </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>1 
ψ </p>

<p>1+r </p>

<p>(CRRA) 
TB/Y 
0.0 
δ 
0.025 
κ 
1.0 
φ 
0.1 
ρ a 
0.95 
ρ g 
0.85 
σ a 
0.025 
σ g 
0.006 
σ g Y 
0.010 
σ g C 
0.015 
σ g I 
0.02 
σ TBY 
0.005 
σ r 
0.004 </p>

<p>Estimated risk-adjusted correction terms 
M 1 
0.00009516 
M 2 
0.00003254 
M 3 
0.00002680 
Deterministic 
Risky 
Moments 
Data 
steady state 
steady state </p>

<p>σ (c)/σ (y) 
1.25 
0.82 
0.93 
σ (c)/σ (y) 
2.11 
1.52 
1.35 
corr(y, tb) 
−0.66 
−0.29 
−0.28 
corr(y, r) 
−0.14 
−0.75 
−0.77 </p>

<p>This paper explicitly focuses on describing and estimating the Korean economy. 
In order to do that, I incorporated a recursive utility into an AG-type RBC model 
in order to circumvent a situation where the discount factor becomes larger than 
one when the Korean economy is calibrated. This situation is due to the fact that 
the sample mean of the real interest rate is relatively low and the sample mean 
growth rate is relatively large. Recursive utility allows us to separate the degree 
of relative risk aversion from the EIS. The log linearization of the model with 
recursive utility shows that it is not the degree of relative risk aversion but the 
EIS that governs the movements of the variables in the model. This makes room 
for setting γ , conventionally interpreted as the degree of relative risk aversion in 
the case of the CRRA utility function, to be less than one, because it can be now </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>



<p>interpreted as the inverse of the EIS. It also suggests that the model with the CRRA 
utility function, combined with γ less than one, can produce the same results as 
the model with recursive utility where the EIS is larger than one. 
Bayesian estimation based on Korean data shows that there are some elements 
of success in describing the Korean economy based on the simple RBC model, 
both with the EIS larger than one and with an error term for the real interest rate 
process. It explains the relative volatility between consumption (investment) and 
output fairly well. It also shows acyclicality or a weak countercyclicality of the 
real interest rate observed in the Korean data. The estimation results further imply 
that the contribution of the trend component is small (about 6% ) in explaining the 
movements of output. 
I also examined whether the same model supplemented with some aspects 
of financial frictions can account for the success of the baseline model with an 
error term for the real interest rate process. As a simple way to reflect financial 
frictions, I follow previous research and assume that the domestic real interest 
rate depends negatively on the expected (transitory) productivity shock. I call this 
the endogenous risk premium channel. Simulation results suggest that the error 
term for the real interest rate process mostly reflects the endogenous risk premium 
channel. The endogenous risk premium channel further implies that the output 
and the trade balance are negatively correlated. 
Though the results are encouraging, they are not very satisfactory. In particular, 
the correlation between output and the trade balance is not strongly countercycli-
cal, and the autocorrelations of the trade balance and the real interest rate are 
not satisfactorily explained. Thus, in future research it would be interesting to 
introduce various mechanisms and/or frictions into the model to see if they can 
improve the explanatory power of the simple RBC model. 
To see whether the main message of this paper-that the higher EIS can better 
explain the excess volatility of consumption relative to output in Korean busi-
ness cycles-can also be applied to other emerging economies, I do Bayesian 
estimation of the Argentine economy as an example. Unfortunately, the results 
are not encouraging. A higher EIS does not lead to the increased volatility of 
consumption relative to output (or the volatility of consumption growth) in the 
Argentine data. It may be because Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010)'s parameterization 
and estimation are best suited to explaining the second moments of the growth 
variables. The volatility of consumption relative to output depends not only on the 
EIS but also on the other parameters such as ρ A , ρ g , and φ. Another possibility 
is that the estimation does not include the real interest rate data as one of the 
observed variables, whereas I include it as one of the observed variables in the 
case of Korea. Or it may be because of something else. Unfortunately, I do not 
have the answer to this issue and leave it for future research. 
Finally, I examined whether considering the risky steady state can improve 
the performance of the simple RBC model in explaining the excess volatility 
of consumption relative to output in emerging-economy business cycles. It does 
not significantly improve the performance of the simple RBC model. It is not </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>



<p>WOOHEON RHEE </p>

<p>surprising in the sense that the second-order approximation in general does not 
qualitatively change the results from the business cycle analyses that are based on 
log linearization of a model. </p>

<p>NOTES </p>

<p>1. In the Korean data, the real interest rate is acyclical or weakly countercyclical, depending on 
measures of the real interest rate. 
2. This is not surprising in view of the fact that Korea was the fastest-growing economy in the 
world from the 1960s to the early 1990s. 
3. An and Li (2013), in an independent work, also notice that the log linearization of the model 
with recursive utility collapses to the model with the CRRA utility function. However, they do not 
explicitly show that it is not the degree of relative risk aversion but the EIS that governs the movements 
of the log linearized system of the model. Their main focus is on explaining the movements of both 
macroeconomic and financial variables, and they concentrate on the second-order approximation of 
the model with recursive utility. 
4. AG's Korean data can be obtained at http://scholar.harvard.edu/gopinath/pages/data-and-codes. 
These data cover the period 1979:IV-2003:II. 
5. Here GDP is measured as GDP net of government spending, because the model in Section 3 
does not include government spending. If I use GDP including government spending, the volatility of 
consumption relative to output is higher than one for the whole sample period. Of course, even in this 
case, the excess volatility of consumption relative to output arises from the latter part of the sample. 
6. Detrending log GDP per capita with a cubic trend as was done in Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010)'s 
Figure 1 also produces about five trend cycles for the whole sample. 
7. Previous empirical studies, Garcia-Cicco et al. (2010) among others, also include crisis periods 
of Latin American economies. Theoretically, Boissay et al. (2013) suggest an RBC model that can 
generate banking crises. 
8. For convenience, I simply call the error term for the interest rate process "measurement error." 
I will discuss later whether it reflects some aspects of financial frictions or represents a measurement 
error independent of them. 
9. The model with the CRRA utility function in which γ is set to the inverse of the EIS, ψ (=2.3), 
should produce the same results as those reported in Table 3 under the column of the model with RU. 
This is actually the case. 
10. I also considered g t+1 instead of a t+1 , but the results do not change qualitatively from those 
reported in Tables 2 to 4. 
11. I set the prior distribution for η in equation (30) as a gamma distribution with prior mean of 0.1. 
12. This analysis was suggested by an anonymous referee. 
13. I am grateful to O. de Groot for making his codes available. 
14. Otherwise, the model has difficulty in convergence, especially when I set φ to a value less than 
0.1. </p>



<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>CAN RBC MODELS EXPLAIN BUSINESS CYCLES IN KOREA? </p>





<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S1365100515000619 </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 16:59:10, subject to the Cambridge </p>

</text></tei>