<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fecin.12279" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This study examines whether informal sector jobs are a source of training for young 
less-educated workers. Controlling for worker and job characteristics, it is found that, 
in the early years of workers' careers in Mexico, wage growth in the informal sector 
is higher than in the formal sector. This result is consistent with general human capital 
investment on-the-job if the informal labor market is more competitive than the formal 
labor market due to frictions generated by labor regulations. (JEL O17, J24, J310) </p>

<p>This study explores the role of informal jobs 
in the formation of human capital among young 
less-educated workers. An informal job is a job 
that fails to comply with some or all of the labor 
regulations. 1 The set of all informal jobs con-
stitute what is typically known as the informal 
sector. Due to the lack of compliance with the 
labor laws, informal jobs are not registered with 
the authorities. 2 However, it is often argued that 
compliance with these laws is of great signifi-
cance in developing countries to ensure social 
justice for workers (Berg and Kucera 2008) and 
to protect them against the forces of reallocation 
in the labor market (Inter-American Develop-
ment Bank 2003). In spite of these arguments, the 
lack of compliance with these mandates in devel-
oping countries is common practice, leading to 
the existence of sizable informal labor markets, 
especially among the youth and the less edu-
cated. 3 Hence, the importance of understanding 
what role the informal sector is playing in the 
lives of young less-educated workers. </p>

<p>Cano-Urbina: Assistant Professor, Department of Eco-
nomics, Florida State University, Tallahassee, FL 
32306-2180. Phone (850) 644-7090, Fax (850) 644-4535, 
E-mail jcanourbina@fsu.edu </p>

<p>1. These regulations are usually designed to protect work-
ers, for example, minimum wage, health insurance, severance 
pay, and retirement pension. 
2. Nevertheless, it is important to note that the informal 
sector is not about the black or the illegal market. 
3. According to the statistics of the Socio-Economic 
Database for Latin America and the Caribbean (published by 
CEDLAS and The World Bank), the proportion of male work-
ers ages 15-24 years with informal jobs ranges from 30.6% in 
Chile to 90% in Bolivia (information obtained in September 
2012). According to the same source, in Mexico, this propor-
tion is 79%. </p>

<p>The traditional views of the informal sector 
in the literature are that of a sector that is the 
last resort for many workers who are rationed out 
of the protected and better paid jobs in the for-
mal sector (e.g., Ozorio de Almeida et al. 1995), 
or that it is the disadvantaged sector in a seg-
mented labor market (e.g., Fields 1975; Harris 
and Todaro 1970). 4 The support for these views 
of the informal sector is mixed in the litera-
ture. The work of Maloney (1999), Amaral and 
Quintin (2006), and Galiani and Weinschelbaum 
(2012) suggests that the existence of informal 
labor markets is not necessarily evidence of seg-
mentation and that could be an equilibrium out-
come in a competitive labor market. However, the 
work of Arias and Khamis (2008) presents some 
evidence that is consistent with the rationing of 
formal-salaried jobs and with segmentation in the 
labor market. 5 </p>

<p>4. Harris and Todaro (1970) were concerned with urban 
unemployment and explained this in the context of a model 
of labor markets with segmentation between rural and urban 
jobs. The full connection with the informal sector is in the 
model developed by Fields (1975). I would like to thank an 
anonymous referee from Economic Inquiry for pointing this 
out to me. 
5. Also, the results from household surveys in Argentina, 
Bolivia, Colombia, and the Dominican Republic presented by 
Arias and Maloney (2007) appear to suggest that an important 
fraction of informal-salaried workers are rationed out of the 
better paid formal-salaried jobs (see Table 2.9 of Arias and 
Maloney 2007). </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>ENEU: Encuesta Nacional de Empleo Urbano 
ENOE: Encuesta Nacional de Ocupación y Empleo 
IMSS: Instituto Mexicano del Seguro Social 
IPW: Inverse Probability Weights </p>

<p>25 
Economic Inquiry 
(ISSN 0095-2583) 
Vol. 54, No. 1, January 2016, 25-43 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/ecin.12279 
Online Early publication October 15, 2015 
© 2015 Western Economic Association International </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>Despite the ongoing debate, informal jobs 
play an important role in the work lives of less-
educated workers. Maloney (1999) argues that 
informal-salaried jobs serve as the main point 
of entry for young poorly educated workers 
into paid employment. The current study further 
explores this idea focusing on the group of 
young less-educated workers in Mexico. The 
study explores the extent to which less-educated 
workers in the informal sector experience wage 
growth and how wage growth in the informal 
sector compares with wage growth in the formal 
sector. The basic question is whether informal 
jobs offer wage growth and skill accumulation 
to less-educated workers, and how it compares 
with formal jobs. 
The empirical analysis uses a household 
survey from Mexico, the ENOE (acronym in 
Spanish for Encuesta Nacional de Ocupación 
y Empleo). The panel structure of the survey 
allows the construction of measures of wage 
growth and continuing sector participation. The 
results indicate that young less-educated workers 
in the informal sector experience faster wage 
growth than their peers in the formal sector. 
Based on existing models of on-the-job training 
(Acemoglu and Pischke 1999a, 1999b; Becker 
1993; Stevens 1994), this result suggests that 
informal jobs offer valuable general training 
opportunities to young less-educated workers. 
The literature provides little evidence on 
wage growth in the informal sector or on how it 
compares with wage growth in the formal sector. 
There is some evidence on the wage gain (or loss) 
from informality. For example, Maloney (1999) 
and Alcaraz et al. (2011) provide estimates of the 
wage change associated with transitions between 
the formal and informal sectors in Mexico. The 
results in both studies indicate that informal-to-
formal transitions are associated with positive 
wage changes, while transitions in the opposite 
direction are associated with negative wage 
changes. However, none of these two studies 
provide evidence on wage growth experienced 
by workers in the informal sector or how it 
compares to wage growth in the formal sector. 
The present study contributes to the literature on 
the informal sector by providing evidence and 
some suggestive ideas of the mechanisms behind 
these results. 
The study is organized as follows. The follow-
ing section describes the sample used for the anal-
ysis and the criteria used to classify employed 
respondents as formal or informal sector work-
ers. Next, evidence from wage data is presented </p>

<p>in Section III and the economic interpretations of 
this evidence are presented in Section IV. The last 
section concludes and discusses future research. </p>

<p>II. DATA </p>

<p>The empirical analysis is based on data from 
a household survey in Mexico called the Occu-
pation and Employment Survey, ENOE. The 
ENOE is a rotating panel where households 
are visited five times over the course of a year, 
one visit every 3 months. 6 The ENOE collects 
demographic data from each family member as 
well as job-related data for members who are 12 
years of age or older. Job-related data include 
information on the individual's occupation, size 
of the firm and industry of occupation, earnings 
per hour, as well as work-related benefits. I used 
data from the ENOE from the first quarter of 
2005 to the fourth quarter of 2012. Appendix A 
provides more details on this survey. 
The sample used in the analysis includes male 
workers only. 7 Also, as the arguments made on 
this article are based on the employer-worker 
relationship and on who bears the cost of train-
ing, the sample is limited to workers who are 
employees. Self-employment is treated as a job 
category different from informal-salaried and 
formal-salaried as in Arias and Maloney (2007) 
or Arias and Khamis (2008). I restrict the sample 
to individuals who have less than 12 years of 
education and did not attend school during the 
five visits to the household in an effort to focus 
on less-educated workers who are committed to 
the labor market. As this study focuses on young 
workers, the main sample used in the analysis 
only includes workers between the ages of 16 and 
25 years. 8 However, to get a better understanding 
of the results, the analysis also considers samples 
of older workers. </p>

<p>6. For example, a household visited for the first time in 
January 2005 will be visited the second time in April 2005, the 
third time in July 2005, the fourth time in October 2005, and 
the fifth time in January 2006. Not all households are visited 
for the first time in January, they could be visited for the first 
time in any other month of the year. 
7. Some authors have found that women may have dif-
ferent reasons for joining the informal sector, for example, 
job flexibility to balance work and child rearing (Arias and 
Maloney 2007). 
8. Age 16 is the minimum age at which a worker can be 
hired according to Mexican Labor Law (see Articles 22, 173, 
and 174 of the Ley Federal del Trabajo). And so I set it as 
the lower bound for the sample. Age 26 is when the transition 
rate from informal to formal sector reaches a maximum (see 
Figure 1(b) below). And so I choose age 25 as the upper bound 
to focus on the first 10 years of the workers' careers. </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>Finally, because the informal sector is mainly 
an urban phenomenon, the sample is restricted 
to the urban areas. In principle, I include all the 
cities that are statistically self-represented in the 
sample of the ENOE. This includes 32 cities. In 
all of these cities, except for one, the population 
is larger than 100,000 people. 9 It is important to 
mention that there are communities in the sam-
ple with a population lower than 100,000 people, 
but that are assigned to a self-represented city. 
That is the case of small communities located 
in the outskirts of large cities. In those cases, I 
include observations from individuals living in 
the smaller communities even when the commu-
nity where they live is not larger than 100,000 
people. 10 Finally, I also include in the sample 
individuals who live in cities that are not self-
represented in the sample but that are larger than 
100,000 people. 
During the period of observation, males 
account for 49.70% of the respondents with 
less than 12 years of education and not attend-
ing school. Among these less-educated males, 
15.57% were between the ages of 16 and 25 years 
at the time of the first interview, and 91.70% of 
them were employed. 11 Among these young 
less-educated employed respondents, 79.38% 
worked as paid employees, while 8.67% were 
self-employed, 10.60% were unpaid employees, 
and 1.35% were employers. Finally, among 
these young less-educated workers working 
as paid employees, 28.98% attended primary 
school and no more (years 1-6), and 71.24% 
of those who attended graduated from primary 
school. Whereas 58.34% attended middle school 
but went no further, and 84.14% of those who 
attended graduated from middle school. The pro-
portion of workers in the sample who attended 
high school but did not graduate is 10.09%. 12 </p>

<p>9. The one self-represented city that is not larger than 
100,000 people is the city of Tlaxcala. It is classified as a 
city with a population between 15,000 and 99,999 people. 
According to the INEGI, the Statistics Bureau in Mexico in 
charge of the Census (and the ENOE), in 2010 the population 
of the city of Tlaxcala was 89,795 people (see http://www3 
.inegi.org.mx/sistemas/mexicocifras/default.aspx). 
10. In those cases, these "smaller" communities will be 
very much urbanized as the larger city, or even attached to the 
larger city. And in many cases individuals may in fact work 
in the big city. 
11. Note that 92.19% of the less-educated workers 
between the ages of 26 and 65 are employed. This proportion 
is very similar to the proportion of younger workers, suggest-
ing that the vast majority of the young less-educated workers 
included in the sample are already committed to the labor mar-
ket in spite of not having completed high school. 
12. Notice that this low percentage is a result of only 
including workers with less than 12 years of education in the </p>

<p>To determine informal sector status of a 
worker, I use the labor laws in Mexico. When 
a worker is hired in Mexico, labor regulations 
mandate that the employer register the worker in 
the Mexican Institute of Social Security, IMSS 
(acronym in Spanish for Instituto Mexicano 
del Seguro Social). This institution provides a 
bundle of benefits to its affiliates, such as health 
insurance, day-care services for children, life 
insurance, disability pensions, work-risk pen-
sions, sports and cultural facilities, retirement 
pensions, and housing loans (Levy 2007). Both 
the employer and the worker pay fees to fund this 
institution, but the employer fees are higher than 
the worker fees. If a firm is caught not complying 
with this regulation, it incurs a penalty. Once 
a worker is registered in the IMSS, the work 
relationship must abide by the labor regulation 
in Mexico. 13 
The questionnaire of the ENOE does not ask 
the individual whether he is a formal or an infor-
mal worker, but whether his job gives him access 
to medical services provided by IMSS or other 
institutions. 14 In this study, I consider a worker 
to belong to the formal sector if he is a paid 
employee and his job gives him access to any kind 
of medical services, and to belong to the informal 
sector if he is a paid employee and his job does 
not give him access to medical services. 15 
In the remainder of the study, I will focus 
on male workers with less than 12 years of 
education and employed as paid employees 
(salaried). Following the aforementioned defini-
tions of informal and formal sectors, Figure 1(a) 
presents the proportion of workers employed </p>

<p>sample. The proportion of workers who attend high school 
and went no further among male individuals between ages 
16 and 25 years who were paid employees is 26.74%, where 
64.09% graduated from high school. A bit more than 10% 
attended college. 
13. A salient mandate of the labor laws in Mexico is the 
severance pay. Workers in Mexico are entitled to severance 
pay either when they are fired or when they resign. Firing a 
worker "with just cause," in order to avoid severance pay, is 
difficult; and even if the employer is able to fire the worker 
with just cause, the worker is still entitled to a reduced 
severance pay. The severance pay is mandatory even if the 
firm is closing its business (see Gordon and Williams 2002). 
14. Other institutions could be the ISSSTE, the military 
or navy hospital, or the PEMEX hospital. ISSSTE is an 
institution similar to IMSS but for State employees only. 
PEMEX is the state-owned petroleum company in Mexico. 
Given the link between the State and these institutions, all 
workers entitled to medical services from these institutions 
will be hired formally. 
15. As mentioned before, self-employed and unpaid 
employees are not included in this definition of the infor-
mal sector. That is, they are neither formal nor informal 
sector workers. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 
Less-Educated Salaried Workers in Mexico by Age </p>

<p>Informal Sector </p>

<p>Formal Sector </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>percent (%) </p>

<p>16 
26 
36 
46 
56 
66 
age </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>27 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>FS 
IS (%) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>IS 
FS (%) </p>

<p>16 
26 
36 
46 
56 
66 
age </p>

<p>IS 
FS (left axis) 
FS 
IS (right axis) </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>Notes: Author's calculations using ENOE from Q1:2005 to Q4:2012. The calculations for panel (a) of the figure use only the 
information at the time of the first interview. The calculations for panel (b) of the figure pool all the ENOE panels (28 panels) 
over the period of observation and used the transitions over the course of a quarter. The samples include employed males with 
less than 12 years of education and not attending school. Both graphs use statistics calculated using the ENOE sampling weights. </p>

<p>in the formal or informal sectors at the time of 
the first interview for different age groups. The 
figure shows that 90.42% of those aged 16 at the 
time of the first interview were informal salaried, 
while the rest were formal salaried. Notice that 
the proportion of informal salaried decreases 
with the age groups between the ages of 16 and 
46 years. Figure 1(b) presents, also for different 
age groups, the transitions between the informal 
and formal sectors as a fraction of the size of the 
initial sector. These are the transitions over the 
course of a quarter (from one interview to the 
next) and pool all panels from the ENOE that 
are available over the period of observation. The 
figure shows that the likelihood of moving from 
the informal into the formal sector increases 
from 3.51% for workers of age 16 to 13.99% 
for workers of age 26 and that the likelihood 
of moving in the opposite direction decreases 
monotonically by age between workers aged 16 
and those aged 26. 
Note that the U-shaped age profile presented 
in Figure 1(a) could be contaminated by genera-
tional effects. More specifically, to the extent that 
the "older" workers in the ENOE's 2005-2012 
belong to a different generation, it could be 
that the graph reflects a generational pattern 
rather than a life-cycle one. There is however 
evidence that such a pattern is indeed a life-
cycle one. In particular, Duval-Hernández and 
Orraca-Romano (2011) show that after removing 
cyclical and cohort effects, the life-cycle partic-
ipation of unskilled males as informal salaried 
workers is U-shaped (see their Figure 6-B). </p>

<p>The change in the proportion of formal and 
informal workers, presented in Figure 1(a), 
and the increase in the likelihood of making a 
transition from the informal to the formal sector, 
presented in Figure 1(b), are consistent with a 
pattern in which less-educated workers enter the 
labor market through the informal sector with a 
tendency to move to the formal sector as they 
grow older. These patterns suggest that young 
less-educated workers employed in the infor-
mal sector may have expectations of eventually 
moving to the formal sector. 
The final sample used for the analysis below 
only includes individuals who do not have miss-
ing values in key variables used in the analysis 
below. These are: age, education, earnings, size 
of firm where the worker is employed, as well as 
the industry where the firm operates. 16 Appendix 
A provides more details on the measure of 
earnings that I used. Also, as the analysis below 
focuses on wage growth, I drop the top and 
bottom 0.5 percentiles of wage growth in the 
formal and informal sectors. 17 
Table 1 presents the summary statistics for the 
individuals in the sample at the time of the first </p>

<p>16. In the analysis below, I also use geographical vari-
ables and minimum wage variables, because this information 
is provided for all respondents in the sample, no respondent 
is drop for missing this information. 
17. In the analysis below, I will focus on measures of 
one-, two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth. For each of 
these four measures, and separately for each sector, I locate 
the top 0.5 percentile and the bottom 0.5 percentile and drop 
observations that are above the top or below the bottom 0.5 
percentiles separately for each sector. </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>TABLE 1 
Sample Descriptive Statistics by Sector: Mean 
(Standard Error) </p>

<p>Variable 
Formal Sector 
Informal Sector </p>

<p>Age 
21.853 
20.887 
(0.034) 
(0.043) 
Years of education 
8.708 
7.842 
(0.024) 
(0.033) 
Married 
0.233 
0.135 
(0.006) 
(0.005) 
Hourly earnings 
22.593 
20.282 
(0.141) 
(0.247) 
Minimum wage (proportion) 
Zone A 
0.381 
0.429 
(0.008) 
(0.009) 
Zone B 
0.232 
0.141 
(0.005) 
(0.004) 
Zone C 
0.387 
0.430 
(0.006) 
(0.007) 
Industry (proportion) 
Construction 
0.077 
0.268 
(0.004) 
(0.007) 
Manufacturing 
0.399 
0.192 
(0.007) 
(0.006) 
Commerce 
0.221 
0.175 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
Services 
0.302 
0.365 
(0.007) 
(0.008) 
Firm size (proportion) 
1−5 
0.056 
0.662 
(0.003) 
(0.008) 
6−50 
0.387 
0.296 
(0.007) 
(0.007) 
51+ 
0.556 
0.042 
(0.007) 
(0.003) 
No. of observations 
12,664 
12,203 </p>

<p>Notes: Sample statistics using the ENOE sampling 
weights. Male paid-employees with less than 12 years of edu-
cation and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Individ-
ual and job characteristics at the time of the first interview. 
Hourly earnings are in Mexican pesos as in the second half of 
December of 2010. The ranking of minimum wages by zone 
is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in zone k. </p>

<p>interview. About 50% of the individuals in the 
sample were employed in the formal sector at the 
time of the first interview. Even though workers 
in the formal sector are, on average, older, more 
educated, and have higher hourly earnings than 
those in the informal sector, the differences in 
these individual characteristics are not extreme. 
The proportion of workers who are married, how-
ever, is bigger in the formal sector. Notice the 
stark difference in the distribution of workers by 
firm size in the formal and informal sectors. In the 
formal sector, most of the workers are employed 
in large firms, whereas in the informal sector, 
most of the workers are employed in small firms. 
Also notice the differences in the distribution of 
workers by industry. The proportion of workers 
employed in the construction industry is larger </p>

<p>in the informal sector, whereas the proportion of 
workers employed in the manufacturing industry 
is larger in the formal sector. The services indus-
try is important in both sectors, although the pro-
portion of workers employed in that industry is 
slightly larger in the informal sector. </p>

<p>III. EVIDENCE FROM WAGE DATA </p>

<p>Figure 2(a) presents the empirical distribu-
tion of log wages in the formal and informal 
sectors in the sample. Wages are in Mexican 
Pesos of the second half of December 2010. 18 
Both distributions are more or less symmetric 
around their means, but the distribution of log 
wages in the formal sector is to the right of the 
distribution of log wages in the informal sector. 
A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test indicates that the 
distribution of log wages in the formal sector first 
order stochastically dominates the distribution 
of log wages in the informal sector. 19 This result 
is consistent with the study by Arias (2007), 
who finds that informal-salaried workers have 
an earnings disadvantage with respect to formal-
salaried workers at all points of the pay scale in 
the case of Argentina and Bolivia. This feature 
appears to be true for less-educated workers in 
Mexico. Log-wage regressions by sector have 
been estimated time and again in different papers 
in the literature; hence, I defer this discussion 
to Appendix B. 
Figure 2(b) shows the empirical distribution 
of the one-quarter wage growth for the formal 
and informal sectors, where one-quarter wage 
growth is defined as the exact percentage change 
in wages Δ 1 w it = [(w it − w it − 1 )/w it − 1 ] × 100, and 
t is in quarters. Wage growth in both sectors is 
right-skewed, but none of the distributions appear 
to first order stochastically dominate the other. 
A Kolmogorov-Smirnov test indicates that there 
is no ranking of any of these two distributions. 20 </p>

<p>18. I used the Consumer Price Index base 2nd half Dec 
2010 to deflate wages. 
19. The p value associated with the hypothesis that the 
empirical distribution function of ln(w) in the formal sector 
is "smaller" is 0.448, whereas the p value associated with the 
hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of ln(w) in 
the informal sector is "smaller" is 0.000, indicating that the 
distribution of ln(w) in the formal sector first order stochasti-
cally dominates that distribution in the informal sector. 
20. The p value associated with the hypothesis that the 
empirical distribution function of Δ 1 w in the formal sector 
is "smaller" is 0.000, whereas the p value associated with 
the hypothesis that the empirical distribution function of Δ 1 w 
in the informal sector is "smaller" is 0.000, indicating no 
ranking between these two distributions in terms of first order 
stochastic dominance. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 
Distribution of Log Hourly Earnings and Wage Growth by Sector </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.25 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>.75 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>1. </p>

<p>a 
b </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>density </p>

<p>−5 
0 
5 
10 
log hourly earnings </p>

<p>Informal Sector 
Formal Sector </p>

<p>kernel = epanechnikov, bandwidth = 0.0424 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.005 </p>

<p>.01 </p>

<p>.015 </p>

<p>density </p>

<p>−200 
0 
200 
400 
600 
one−quarter wage growth (%) </p>

<p>Informal Sector 
Formal Sector </p>

<p>kernel = epanechnikov, bandwidth = 4.7843 </p>

<p>Notes: Author's calculations using ENOE from Q1:2005 to Q4:2012. The sample includes males with less than 12 years of 
education and not attending school. The sample includes all wage observations, and so it can include multiple observations for 
each respondent. For panel (b), the top and bottom 0.5% of the one-quarter wage growth is dropped from the sample. </p>

<p>However, the distribution of wage growth in the 
informal sector appears to be slightly more dis-
perse than in the formal sector, suggesting that 
wages are more flexible in the informal sector, 
both for wage increases and wage decreases. A 
traditional variance ratio test rejects the hypothe-
sis that the variance of Δ 1 w in the formal sector is 
equal to the variance of Δ 1 w in the informal sec-
tor in favor of an alternative that the variance of 
Δ 1 w in the formal sector is smaller. 21 However, 
this test is sensitive to the assumption that the 
data are drawn from a Normal distribution. Using 
a test for the equality of variances that is robust 
when dealing with skewed distributions (Brown 
and Forsythe 1974; Levene 1960) also rejects the 
null hypothesis that the variances are equal. 22 
Next, I explore how wage growth in the infor-
mal sector compares to wage growth in the formal </p>

<p>21. For the variance ratio test, I used the <rs type="software">Stata</rs> command 
sdtest. The null hypothesis of this test is that the ratio r = 
σ 2 </p>

<p>FS </p>

<p>∕σ 2 </p>

<p>IS </p>

<p>equals 1, i.e. H 0 : r = 1. The calculated test statistic 
is f = 0.6605, which is distributed as F (32172,27221) , where 
the degrees of freedom in the numerator and denominator 
are (n FS − 1) and (n IS − 1), respectively. This null is rejected 
against the alternative H 1 : r &lt; 1 with a p value of 0.0000, and 
against the alternative H 1 : r ≠ 1 with a p value of 0.0000, but 
cannot be rejected against the alternative H 1 : r &gt; 1 with a p 
value of 1.0000. 
22. To test the hypothesis of equal variances, I used the 
<rs type="software">Stata</rs> command robvar which provides three alternative test 
statistics that vary the measure of central tendency used to 
calculate the test. The first one uses the mean of each group 
under comparison, the second uses the median of each group, 
and the third uses the 10% trimmed mean of each group. 
The first variant of the test is the one proposed by Levene 
(1960), the other two are the ones proposed by Brown and </p>

<p>sector conditional on individual and firm charac-
teristics and for different time spans. To this end, I 
estimate the following wage-growth regressions: </p>

<p>(1) 
Δ k w it = β k IS k 
it + x ′ 
it γ k + ξ k 
it , for k = 1, 2, 3, 4 
where t is defined in quarters and Δ k w it = 
[(w it − w it − k )/w it − k ] × 100, for k = 1, 2, 3, 4, that 
is, one-quarter, two-quarters, three-quarters, 
and four-quarters wage growth equations, 
respectively. For each of the four wage growth 
regressions in Equation (1), the variable IS k </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>is an indicator that equals 1 if the worker was 
employed (k + 1) consecutive quarters in the 
informal sector, and equals 0 if the worker was 
employed (k + 1) consecutive quarters in the for-
mal sector. That is, let I it be an indicator variable 
equal to 1 if individual i is employed in the infor-
mal sector in quarter t and 0 otherwise, and let F it 
be an indicator variable equal to 1 if individual 
i is employed in the formal sector in quarter t 
and 0 otherwise. Then, for the one-quarter wage 
growth regression IS 1 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>is defined as: </p>

<p>IS 1 
it = </p>

<p>{ 
1 if I it = I it−1 = 1 
0 if F it = F it−1 = 1 
. </p>

<p>Forsythe (1974), and which are more robust than Levene's test 
when dealing with skewed distributions. The calculated test 
statistics are: W 0 = 603.806 for the mean, W 50 = 448.425 for 
the median, and W 10 = 481.202 for the 10% trimmed mean. 
In each case, the test statistic is distributed as F (1,59393) , where 
the degrees of freedom in the denominator are (n FS + n IS − 2), 
and in all three cases the p value is 0.0000. </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Excluding Firm Characteristics </p>

<p>One-Quarter 
Two-Quarters 
Three-Quarters 
Four-Quarters </p>

<p>IS 
5.6786 
7.1109 
9.3467 
7.3511 
(0.8966) 
( 1.4177) 
( 1.9904) 
( 3.2308) 
Primary School Grad 
0.3394 
1.5640 
3.1785 
0.6612 
(1.7987) 
( 3.1738) 
( 3.4110) 
( 5.3259) 
Middle School Grad 
−0.1910 
0.5542 
3.3316 
2.5878 
(1.9484) 
( 3.2717) 
( 3.7138) 
( 5.4214) 
Experience 
−0.1255 
−0.3178 
−0.4230 
−0.2658 
(0.1572) 
( 0.2374) 
( 0.2813) 
( 0.4294) 
Minimum wage zone 
Zone B 
5.9182 
9.0389 
−16.9915 
17.1680 
(6.2530) 
( 12.5428) 
( 12.2333) 
( 14.9479) 
Zone C 
16.3610 
17.9894 
−21.0586 
31.5773 
(9.2845) 
( 17.7632) 
( 14.0026) 
( 17.2688) 
No. of observations 
61,211 
35,322 
19,074 
7,977 
R 2 
0.0254 
0.0292 
0.0411 
0.0827 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with 
less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 6}, Middle School 
Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in Zone k. The 
omitted category for the minimum dummy is Z one A. All specifications include year dummies, city dummies, and city-size 
dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-
White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis. </p>

<p>Similarly, for the two-, three-, and four-quarter 
wage growth regression IS k </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>is defined as: </p>

<p>IS k 
it = </p>

<p>{ 
1 if I it = · · · = I it−k = 1 
0 if F it = · · · = F it−k = 1 
for k = 2, 3, 4. </p>

<p>Notice that the definition of the indicator 
variables IS k </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>implies that, in the estimation of 
Equation (1) for each of the four time spans 
(k = 1, 2, 3, 4) I can only use the observations 
from individuals that were employed in the 
formal or informal sectors for at least (k + 1) 
consecutive quarters. For example, consider the 
one-quarter wage growth of a worker who was 
employed in the informal sector in quarters t 
and (t + 1), but employed in the formal sector in 
quarters (t + 2), (t + 3), and (t + 4). The estima-
tion sample will include the one-quarter wage 
growth between quarters t and (t + 1) as informal 
sector wage growth, but will not include the one-
quarter wage growth between quarters (t + 1) and 
(t + 2) because this is neither informal sector nor 
formal sector wage growth, it is the wage growth 
associated with the transition from informal to 
formal sectors. Then, the sample will also include 
the one-quarter wage growth between quarters 
(t + 2) and (t + 3) and between quarters (t + 3) 
and (t + 4) as formal sector wage growth. Now, 
consider the same individual for the two-quarter </p>

<p>wage growth. The sample will not include a 
measure of two-quarter wage growth for this </p>

<p>particular worker because the worker does not 
have a two-quarter wage growth in the informal 
sector. However the sample will include the two-
quarter wage growth between quarters (t + 2) 
and (t + 4) as formal sector wage growth. 
This restriction in the sample is to avoid 
β k from picking up the wage gains (or losses) 
associated with switching sectors. Then, the 
sample used for estimation can include "switch-
ers," but will not include the wage growth of 
the period when the worker switches sectors. A 
similar procedure would be applied for three-
and four-quarters wage growth and for consec-
utive formal sector employment. In this way, 
the parameter of interest, β k , summarizes how 
wage growth of an individual employed in the 
informal sector compares with wage growth 
of an individual employed in the formal sector 
conditional on x it . 
Tables 2 and 3 present the results from esti-
mation of Equation (1) for the different spans of 
wage growth. Table 2 presents estimation results 
excluding firm characteristics, mainly industry </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Including Firm Characteristics </p>

<p>One-Quarter 
Two-Quarters 
Three-Quarters 
Four-Quarters 
(k = 1) 
(k = 2) 
(k = 3) 
(k = 4) </p>

<p>IS 
6.4348 
10.1931 
10.9430 
8.6221 
(1.3510) 
( 2.1342) 
( 2.5570) 
( 3.9360) 
Primary School Grad 
−0.4403 
0.6469 
0.7347 
0.0085 
(1.9068) 
( 3.3122) 
( 3.4873) 
( 5.5391) 
Middle School Grad 
−1.3726 
−0.6968 
0.6823 
2.8297 
(2.0377) 
( 3.4458) 
( 3.7914) 
( 5.7344) 
Experience 
−0.1991 
−0.3757 
−0.4433 
−0.4033 
(0.1624) 
( 0.2482) 
( 0.2893) 
( 0.4393) 
Minimum wage zone 
Zone B 
7.2470 
10.8565 
−17.0079 
17.1709 
(6.2222) 
( 12.5631) 
( 11.9502) 
( 15.6764) 
Zone C 
19.5064 
20.9731 
−18.4204 
26.2562 
(9.5167) 
( 19.3186) 
( 13.4798) 
( 17.6474) 
Industry 
Manufacturing 
−4.0296 
−3.5441 
−2.3396 
−15.0508 
(1.4744) 
( 2.3128) 
( 2.7794) 
( 5.4999) 
Commerce 
−1.9194 
−3.8126 
−3.1344 
−14.4347 
(1.5668) 
( 2.3592) 
( 2.7493) 
( 5.4577) 
Services 
1.4914 
−0.3148 
2.4452 
−12.0859 
(1.4428) 
( 2.4641) 
( 2.5989) 
( 5.5296) 
Firm size 
6−50 
0.4679 
4.5489 
2.2367 
0.0441 
(1.3709) 
( 2.1889) 
( 2.5570) 
( 3.6977) 
51+ 
3.8702 
6.8607 
5.5254 
6.1962 
(1.6909) 
( 2.4795) 
( 2.8157) 
( 4.3931) 
No. of observations 
57,480 
33,188 
17,890 
7,476 
R 2 
0.0275 
0.0332 
0.0442 
0.0944 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with 
less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 6}, Middle School 
Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in zone k. The 
omitted categories for the dummy variables are: minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 2-5 employees. 
All specifications include year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the measure of hourly 
earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at the individual level 
are in parenthesis. </p>

<p>and firm size, whereas Table 3 presents estima-
tion results including these firm characteristics. 
From the perspective of a worker maximizing 
intertemporal earnings, the wage growth that 
matters is the wage growth unconditional on firm 
characteristics, hence the estimation in Table 2 
does not control for them. 23 Then for Table 2 the 
vector of covariates includes: education dum-
mies, labor market experience, minimum-wage 
zone dummies, year dummies, city dummies, 
and a dummy variable that indicates whether the 
individual wage used to compute wage growth 
was imputed (see Appendix A). For Table 3, 
the vector of covariates includes in addition 
dummies for the industry in which the worker is </p>

<p>23. An unskilled young worker choosing among jobs 
would look across industries and firm sizes to find the one 
that maximizes his expected discounted income. Hence, the 
wage growth that he would be looking at is the one for which 
there are no controls. </p>

<p>employed, and dummies for the size of the firm 
where the worker is employed. These indicators 
refer to the industry and size of the firm in the 
final period used to compute the wage growth. 24 
The first column of Tables 2 and 3 presents 
estimation results for one-quarter wage growth. 
In this case, the dependent variable is Δ 1 w it = 
[(w it − w it − 1 )/w it − 1 ] × 100, and the indicator for 
informal-sector participation is IS 1 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>as defined 
above. The positive estimate for the coefficient of 
IS 1 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>in both tables indicates that one-quarter wage 
growth is faster in the informal sector than in the 
formal sector. 
Notice the important role played by the indus-
try and firm size controls in Table 3. If firms of </p>

<p>24. To compute wage growth Δ k w it two periods are 
involved, an initial period (t − k) and a final period t. The 
industry and firm size indicators are those of period t, which 
is the final period used to compute the wage growth. </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>different sizes, or operating in different indus-
tries, are systematically different with respect to 
productivity, then these differences in produc-
tivity may lead to differences in wage growth as 
well as wage levels. For instance, larger firms 
invest more in technology than small firms, 
which may require more worker training, in 
turn resulting in higher wage growth. Similarly, 
one could argue that firms in industries with 
higher opportunities for human capital accu-
mulation for young less-educated workers will 
experience on average faster wage growth than 
other industries. 25 
Recall that formal sector workers are mostly 
employed in large firms, whereas informal sec-
tor workers are mostly employed in small firms 
(see Table 1). Similarly, the fraction of workers 
employed in the manufacturing and commerce 
industries is higher among formal sector work-
ers, whereas the fraction of workers employed in 
the construction and services industries is higher 
among informal sector workers (see Table 1). 
Then, however, not including firm-size controls 
would result in a downward-biased estimate of 
β k because wage growth is faster in larger firms 
and working in a large firm is negatively corre-
lated with being informal salaried worker. How-
ever, not including industry controls would result 
in an upward-biased estimate of β k because work-
ers in the construction industry experience faster 
wage growth than those in other industries, and 
working in the construction industry is positively 
correlated with being informal salaried worker. 
The opposite directions of the biases are reflected 
in the estimates of Table 3 that are larger than the 
estimates in Table 2 but the differences are not 
large and the conclusion is the same. 
Note that Table 3 indicates higher wage 
growth in the construction industry than in the 
manufacturing industry. This suggests that those 
workers who stayed in the construction industry 
and those who moved from another industry 
into construction experienced a higher wage 
growth than those who stayed in manufacturing 
or moved into manufacturing. The log-wage 
regressions in Appendix B indicate that less-
educated workers in the construction industry </p>

<p>25. Even though the sample excludes the wage growth 
associated with sector switching, the sample can include wage 
growth associated with employer switching within the same 
sector. The economic interpretations presented below refer to 
general human capital and the degree of competitiveness of 
the labor market. As general human capital is portable and 
difficulties finding jobs are related with labor market frictions, 
I decided not to restrict the sample to those workers who 
would stay with the same employee. </p>

<p>have on average higher wages than those in any 
of the other three industries which helps explain 
part of these estimation results. 
Finally, notice that neither education nor expe-
rience appear to have a significant effect on wage 
growth. The log-wage regressions presented in 
Appendix B indicate that these variables are 
important to determine wages in both the for-
mal and informal sectors. However, it appears 
that once the market accounts for differences in 
these individual features in the wage determina-
tion, wage growth is not greatly affected by them. 
The second, third, and fourth columns of 
Tables 2 and 3 present the estimation results 
for two-, three-, and four-quarter wage growth 
regressions, respectively. That is, the sec-
ond column presents the estimation results 
when the dependent variable is Δ 2 w it = 
[(w it − w it − 2 )/w it − 2 ] × 100, and the indicator 
of informal sector participation is IS 2 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>as defined 
above. Similarly for the third and fourth columns. 
In all three regressions, the conclusion is the 
same. That is, wages in the informal sector grow 
at a faster rate than wages in the formal sector. 
Notice that in the analysis presented above, 
there is no explicit treatment of unobserved het-
erogeneity or selection, and so the estimates 
on the indicator of informal sector participation 
could be biased. However, if unobserved hetero-
geneity, or "ability," has a similar effect on wage 
levels in two or three consecutive quarters, then 
its effect should cancel out when looking at wage 
growth. 26 Also, recall that educational achieve-
ment does not have a significant effect on wage 
growth (as indicated by the estimates in Table 3), 
and so it appears unlikely that unobserved het-
erogeneity would have a crucial role, given the 
strong correlation between education and abil-
ity. With respect to worker selection, one can 
argue that those workers continuously employed 
in the informal sector are negatively selected, and 
so, if high-ability workers experience faster wage 
growth than low-ability workers, the estimate of 
the coefficient of IS k </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>would be downward-biased. 
If this is the case, then we can consider the esti-
mate of β k provided in this study as a lower 
bound for the true value, and so the conclusion </p>

<p>26. Suppose that log-wages are given by: ln w it = z ′ </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>δ + 
μ i + ε it where z it is a vector of individual and firm observed 
characteristics, μ i represents a worker's unobserved abil-
ity, and ε it is a well-behaved error term. Wage-growth is 
given by Δ k w it = [(w it − w it − k )/w it − k ] × 100, where w it = 
exp 
{ 
z ′ </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>δ + μ i + ε it 
} 
, and exp{·} is the exponential function. 
Then, it is easy to see that the worker's unobserved ability, μ i , 
will cancel out. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Pattern of Sample Attrition in ENOE, 2005-2012 </p>

<p>Number in 
Sample </p>

<p>As Percentage of 
Interview 1 </p>

<p>Number of 
Attritors </p>

<p>Attrition 
Rate </p>

<p>Number Back 
from Nonresponse </p>

<p>Interview 1 
343,519 
-
-
-
-
Interview 2 
339,653 
98.87 
3,866 
1.13 
-
Interview 3 
316,925 
92.26 
26,057 
7.67 
3,329 
Interview 4 
301,391 
87.74 
19,452 
6.14 
3,918 
Interview 5 
289,213 
84.19 
15,818 
5.25 
3,640 </p>

<p>Notes: ENOE 2005-2012. Males ages 16-65 years living in urban areas. </p>

<p>would be the same, that is informal sector work-
ers experience faster wage growth than formal 
sector workers. </p>

<p>A. Attrition </p>

<p>It is important to note that by looking at 
wage growth, nonrandom sample attrition in the 
panel may grow for longer spans. Based on 
the results from Table 3, this could represent a 
problem if most of the attriters are individuals 
employed in the informal sector with low wage 
growth or employed in the formal sector with 
high wage growth. Antman and McKenzie (2007) 
and Duval-Hernández (2007) highlight the prob-
lem of attrition in the ENEU (Encuesta Nacional 
de Empleo Urbano), which is the predecessor 
of the ENOE and had the same sampling struc-
ture. Antman and McKenzie (2007) find that for 
the period 1987-2001, 10% of the households 
in the ENEU were observed for only one quar-
ter, and approximately 65% of the households 
could be followed for all five quarters. Similarly, 
Duval-Hernández (2007) finds that for the period 
1987-2002, 50% of the sample of interest in the 
ENEU was missing from the panel, most of them 
due to attrition. Hence, the concern is that the 
ENOE may also suffer from attrition. 
Table 4 presents the pattern of attrition in 
the ENOE during the period of 2005-2012. 27 
As Table 4 indicates, the problem of attrition 
appears less serious in the ENOE compared to the 
ENEU. For example, the attrition rate after the 
first interview is only 1.13%, and some of these 
individuals may come back from nonresponse 
at later interviews. The attrition rate is higher 
between the third and fourth interviews, but by 
the fifth interview 84.19% of the individuals 
who started are still in the sample. Next, Table 5 </p>

<p>27. Tables 3 and 4 are motivated by the work of Fitzgerald 
et al. (1998). </p>

<p>TABLE 5 
Characteristics in First Interview by Attrition 
Status </p>

<p>Always In 
Ever Out </p>

<p>Working hours per week 
48.55 
49.30 
Hourly earnings 
34.82 
35.62 
Age 
36.41 
32.19 
Married (%) 
56.28 
44.08 
Informal salaried (%) 
31.60 
35.00 
Attending school (%) 
4.54 
5.10 
Education (%) 
0 years 
1.69 
1.26 
Elementary: 1-6 years 
18.92 
17.38 
Middle school: 7-9 years 
31.95 
32.79 
High school: 10-12 years 
24.87 
23.97 
College+: 13+ 
22.45 
24.44 
Missing 
0.13 
0.18 
Minimum wage zone (%) 
Zone A 
45.37 
45.11 
Zone B 
15.95 
15.64 
Zone C 
38.68 
39.25 
Industry (%) 
Construction 
10.51 
12.30 
Manufacturing 
24.78 
22.12 
Commerce 
16.31 
17.73 
Services 
48.40 
47.85 
Firm size (%) 
1−5 
2 3 .13 
23.90 
6−50 
32.83 
35.00 
51+ 
44.04 
41.10 
No. of observations 
148,713 
35,616 </p>

<p>Notes: Sample statistics using the ENOE sampling 
weights. ENOE 2005-2012. Males ages 16-65 years living 
in urban areas. Hourly earnings are in Mexican pesos as in the 
second half of December of 2010. The ranking of minimum 
wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum 
wage in zone k. </p>

<p>presents the characteristics in the first interview 
by attrition status. There are some small but clear 
differences between those who were always 
in the sample and those who ever came out, 
almost all of these differences are statistically 
significant. For example, those who were always 
in the sample have less hours of work, lower 
hourly earnings, and are older than those who </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>were ever out. Equally important for this study 
are the differences in the distribution by industry 
of occupation and firm size. Overall, the numbers 
in Table 5 suggest that sample attrition could 
bias the regression results presented in Table 3. 
To have a more precise idea about the problem 
of attrition bias, I performed a variable addition 
test as suggested by Verbeek and Nijman (1992). 
The test consists in building a variable that sum-
marizes the pattern of attrition, adding this vari-
able to the regression being estimated and testing 
for its significance. Following the implementa-
tion of this test by Jones et al. (2013), I construct 
three variables: (1) an indicator of whether the 
individual is in the next interview, 28 (2) an indi-
cator of whether the individual is in the balanced 
panel, and (3) a variable measuring the number 
of interviews each individual is in the sample. 
Intuitively, if attrition is random, then conditional 
on the covariates, none of these variables should 
be correlated with the outcome variable, that 
is, with Δ k w it for k = 1, 2, 3. Note that I cannot 
perform this test on the four-quarter wage growth 
regression, Δ k w it for k = 4, because the variable 
for consecutive informal sector participation IS 4 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>equals one if the individual is informal salaried 
for all five interviews and zero if he is formal 
salaried for all five interviews. Hence, for all 
observations with IS 4 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>= 1 or IS 4 </p>

<p>it </p>

<p>= 0 the three 
additional variables have no variance at all. 
In the process of building each of these three 
variables, I follow Wooldridge (2002) and I 
assume that attrition is an absorbing state, that 
is, once the individual is out of the sample he 
never comes back. The results for this test are 
presented in Table 6. The numbers in the table 
are the estimated coefficient and standard error 
for the additional variable the same sample and 
the specifications as those used in Table 3. Each 
number in the table is taken from a separate 
regression. Except for one case, the additional 
variable is significant, which suggests that 
nonresponse is not random. </p>

<p>28. Recall that the dependent variable is wage growth. 
Let t = 1 be the time period for the first interview, t = 2 for 
the second interview, and so on. If individual i is in all five 
interviews, we have five wage measures w i1 , … , w i5 , but only 
four one-quarter wage growth measures Δ 1 w i2 , … , Δ 1 w i5 . 
Then, the indicator variable for whether individual i is in the 
next interview is irrelevant for t = 1, takes the value 1 for t = 2, 
t = 3, and t = 4 and it is irrelevant for t = 5. If individual i is 
only in the first four interviews, then, the indicator variable 
is irrelevant for t = 1, takes the value 1 for t = 2 and t = 3, 
takes the value 0 for t = 4, and is irrelevant for t = 5. An 
analogous explanation can be applied for the two-and three-
quarter wage growth. </p>

<p>TABLE 6 
Additional Variable Test for Attrition (Verbeek 
and Nijman 1992) </p>

<p>Wage Growth Span </p>

<p>Additional Variable </p>

<p>One-
Quarter </p>

<p>Two-
Quarters </p>

<p>Three-
Quarters 
(k = 1) 
(k = 2) 
(k = 3) </p>

<p>In next interview 
−2.3637 
−2.0769 
−4.2058 
(1.0227) 
(1.7424) 
(2.5778) 
In balanced panel 
−0.5454 
−1.3227 
−2.7628 
(0.2479) 
(0.5821) 
(1.2918) 
Total number of 
interviews </p>

<p>−1.5464 
−3.4012 
−4.0960 </p>

<p>(0.7524) 
(1.3114) 
(1.9483) </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sam-
pling weights. The table presents the estimated coefficient on 
the additional variable and its standard error in parenthesis. 
Each estimated coefficient is obtained from a separate regres-
sion. The samples and the regressions are comparable to the 
samples and regressions in Table 3. </p>

<p>To gage the effect of sample attrition in 
the estimates of Table 3, I re-estimate the 
wage-growth regressions for one-, two-, and 
three-quarters wage growth, using an inverse 
probability weight estimation as suggested by 
Wooldridge (2002) and Jones et al. (2013). The 
inverse probability weighting is based on the 
assumption of selection on observables intro-
duced by Fitzgerald et al. (1998). The inverse 
probability weights are computed separately for 
each of the three wage-growth regressions, the 
details of the calculation are given in Appendix C. 
The results are presented in Table 7. From the 
results in Table 6, it was expected that the esti-
mate on the consecutive informal sector partici-
pation was going to be lower, but the drop in the 
estimated coefficient is moderate. Moreover, the 
estimates for the one-quarter, two-quarters, and 
three-quarters wage growth regressions are all 
statistically significant and suggest the same con-
clusions as the results in Table 3, that is, informal 
sector workers experience faster wage growth. 
Given these estimates for the one-, two, and three-
quarter wage growth regressions, it appears plau-
sible that the estimate in Table 3 for four-quarter 
wage growth is not severely affected by attrition. </p>

<p>B. Evidence for Older Workers </p>

<p>The findings on wage growth for the group 
of young less-educated workers suggest that 
workers in the informal sector experience, on 
average, faster wage growth than formal-sector 
workers conditional on observable individual and </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 7 
One-, Two-, and Three-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions Using the Inverse Probability Weight </p>

<p>One-Quarter 
Two-Quarters 
Three-Quarters 
(k = 1) 
(k = 2) 
(k = 3) </p>

<p>IS 
5.8731 
7.6472 
8.0878 
(0.9183) 
(1.3279) 
(1.8228) 
Primary School Grad 
−0.8325 
−0.9636 
−5.5755 
(1.4968) 
(2.0654) 
(3.0870) 
Middle School Grad 
−2.0440 
−2.8833 
−7.1254 
(1.5320) 
(2.1588) 
(3.1965) 
Experience 
−0.2927 
−0.5863 
−0.8307 
(0.1078) 
(0.1514) 
(0.2021) 
Minimum wage zone 
Zone B 
9.8894 
28.0627 
−23.1000 
(14.6395) 
(6.0677) 
(10.9884) 
Zone C 
12.6085 
29.1531 
−24.8511 
(16.4483) 
(18.0704) 
(13.3383) 
Industry 
Manufacturing 
−2.2855 
−3.1559 
−2.1271 
(1.0331) 
(1.4326) 
(1.9525) 
Commerce 
−0.8760 
−2.5495 
−2.2613 
(1.0599) 
(1.4873) 
(2.0169) 
Services 
1.5879 
0.0611 
1.7940 
(1.0194) 
(1.3904) 
(1.9100) 
Firm size 
6−50 
0.6421 
4.0280 
2.2988 
(0.9885) 
(1.3128) 
(1.6873) 
51+ 
2.3657 
5.3698 
5.9189 
(1.1068) 
(1.4962) 
(1.9945) 
No. of observations 
44,390 
26,984 
15,701 
R 2 
0.0221 
0.0195 
0.0287 </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions are weighted using the inverse probability weight. The samples include male paid-employees with 
less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 6}, Middle School 
Grad = í µíµ {E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in Zone k. The 
omitted categories for the dummy variables are: minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 2-5 employees. 
All specifications include a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if the 
measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered at 
the individual level are in parenthesis. </p>

<p>job characteristics. At this point, it is natural to 
ask whether faster wage growth in the informal 
sector would also hold for older age groups. If 
older workers employed in the informal sector 
also experience faster wage growth than similar 
workers employed in similar jobs in the formal 
sector, then one can argue that workers would 
never want to leave their informal sector jobs, 
and that the formal sector would eventually 
disappear. On the contrary, the data suggest that 
for the group of young less educated workers, 
the number of workers (and the proportion of 
workers) employed in the formal sector increases 
with age (see Figure 1). 
How does wage growth in the informal sector 
compare with wage growth in the formal sector 
for older groups? Table 8 presents the estimate of 
β k for k = 1, 2, 3, 4, the coefficient on consecutive 
informal sector participation, for different age 
groups and for different wage-growth spans. </p>

<p>For ease of comparison, the first column of the 
table replicates the first row of Table 3, which 
are the estimates for young workers, those aged 
16-25 years. The estimation results indicate that 
informal sector workers experience significantly 
faster one-quarter wage growth in all age groups, 
but the same is not true for two-, three-, and 
four-quarter wage growth, with a few exceptions. 
The second youngest group, aged 26-35 years, 
experiences significantly faster wage growth 
for one-, two-, and three-quarters. Overall, the 
results indicate that the faster wage growth of 
informal sector workers is concentrated in the 
younger groups both in terms of the magnitude 
of wage growth and its statistical significance. </p>

<p>IV. ECONOMIC INTERPRETATIONS OF EVIDENCE </p>

<p>This section argues that the evidence from 
wage data is consistent with general human </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>TABLE 8 
One-, Two-, Three-, and Four-Quarters Wage Growth Regressions for Different Age Groups 
(Coefficient of Consecutive Informal Sector Participation) </p>

<p>Wage Growth 
Age 16-25 
Age 26-35 
Age 36-45 
Age 46-55 
Age 56-65 </p>

<p>One-quarter 
6.4348 
3.6825 
5.2406 
4.1891 
8.5961 
(1.3510) 
( 1.1655) 
( 1.2763) 
( 1.8945) 
( 2.6211) 
Two-quarters 
10.1931 
6.7597 
3.1237 
6.6653 
3.2306 
(2.1342) 
( 1.8116) 
( 1.7116) 
( 2.5365) 
( 3.4138) 
Three-quarters 
10.9430 
6.9986 
2.6828 
2.2499 
0.0209 
(2.5570) 
( 2.5206) 
( 2.5336) 
( 3.7573) 
( 4.9094) 
Four-quarters 
8.6221 
9.0234 
4.7516 
9.9983 
1.9499 
(3.9360) 
( 4.7700) 
( 3.7452) 
( 6.2769) 
( 6.1229) </p>

<p>Notes: All regressions are weighted using the ENOE sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees with less 
than 12 years of education and not attending school. All specifications include all the covariates used in the regressions of Table 3. 
That is, dummies for education, a variable for labor market experience, dummies for the different minimum wage zones, dummies 
for industry, dummies for firm size, a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, and city-size dummies, and a dummy equal to 1 if 
the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard errors clustered 
at the individual level are in parenthesis. </p>

<p>capital investment on-the-job. 29 First, consider 
the model of general on-the-job training in a 
competitive labor market provided by Becker 
(1993). In this model, the wage is determined 
by the worker's productivity in the current firm 
but also by the productivity in other firms. A 
distinctive feature of a competitive labor market 
is that productivity increases with general train-
ing equally in the firm providing it as well as in 
other firms. Consequently, firms cannot capture 
any of the returns from the investment in general 
training because the worker can move freely to 
another firm once training is finished. As a result, 
in a competitive labor market, workers capture 
all the returns from investment in general skills 
and bear the cost of general training through 
lower wages. Which implies a substantial wage 
growth after training is over. 
Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b) argue that 
because of labor market imperfections, worker's 
productivity in the current firm increases more 
with training than in other firms. Hence, when 
workers change jobs, they do not get paid their 
full marginal product, and as a result productivity 
increases faster with training than wages. Conse-
quently, firms' profits increase with training, and 
for this reason firms are willing to sponsor gen-
eral training. As a result, wage growth after train-
ing is over is not as substantial as in the case in 
which the workers bear all the costs of training. 
Acemoglu and Pischke also provide mechanisms </p>

<p>29. General training increases a worker's productivity at 
any firm, contrary to firm-specific training, which increases 
productivity more in firms providing it. See Becker (1993), 
chapter III. </p>

<p>that produce this distorted structure of wages 
as an equilibrium outcome of the model. Two 
of these mechanisms are: job-search frictions, 
and labor market institutions, such as minimum 
wages and unions. Furthermore, Acemoglu and 
Pischke show that the higher the distortion on the 
wage structure due to the labor market frictions, 
the more the firm will sponsor general training. 
The models of Becker (1993) and Acemoglu 
and Pischke (1999b) can be used together with 
the institutional differences that exist between the 
formal and the informal labor markets to inter-
pret the evidence from wage data presented in 
the previous section. The features of the infor-
mal and the formal labor markets suggest that 
the informal labor market operates like a com-
petitive labor market whereas the formal labor 
market operates like a frictional labor market. 
First, the informal labor market is not directly 
affected by labor market institutions, whereas, by 
definition, the formal labor market is affected by 
these institutions. Second, job search frictions are 
likely to be higher in the formal labor market 
than in the informal labor market. A market fric-
tion is defined as "the costly delay in the process 
of finding trading partners and determining the 
terms of trade … " (see Mortensen and Pissarides 
1999, 2571). The institutional features of the for-
mal labor market, such as unions or hiring and 
firing costs, generate frictions that delay the pro-
cess of job matching. Because the informal labor 
market, by definition, is not subject to these insti-
tutional features, job matching in the informal 
sector, while not perfect, is less complicated than 
in the formal sector. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>According to the model of Acemoglu and 
Pischke (1999b), frictions in the labor market 
allow firms to reap some of the returns from 
general training which leads firms to pay at least 
part for the costs of training. And so, if the formal 
labor market is a frictional labor market, firms 
in the formal sector will pay at least part of the 
costs of training, so that wages are not heavily 
discounted during the training period. However, 
according to the model of Becker (1993), in 
a competitive labor market, workers reap the 
returns from training but also bear the costs of 
training. And so, if the informal labor market is a 
competitive labor market, wages are discounted 
more heavily during the training period. As a 
consequence, even if both sectors have the same 
amount of investment on training, wage growth 
in the informal sector should be faster than wage 
growth in the formal sector. Which is the result 
found in the previous section? 30 
The notion that the informal labor market 
is competitive while the formal labor market is 
frictional has been used in previous studies. For 
example, Zenou (2008) develops an equilibrium 
model of the informal and formal sectors to eval-
uate various policies to reduce unemployment. In 
Zenou's model, the formal labor market is charac-
terized by search frictions, whereas the informal 
labor market is competitive. Equally important 
is the fact that labor market institutions generate 
frictions, and that labor market institutions are 
directly related with the existence and the level 
of informality in the labor market. In fact, one of 
the most cited causes of large informal sectors 
is the existence of rigidities in the labor market 
due to excessive regulation (see Schneider and 
Enste 2000). This link between labor regulations 
and the existence of informal sectors has been 
studied and documented. For example, Rauch 
(1991) develops a model in which the size of the 
informal sector is directly related to the degree 
of labor regulation. 31 Bosch et al. (2007) find </p>

<p>30. It is natural to ask if 3-12 months (one-to four-
quarters) are enough for a worker to accumulate the skills 
necessary for work. Employers' reports in the surveys for the 
Employer Opportunity Pilot Projects (EOPP) for year 1982, 
and the survey funded by the Small Business Administration 
(SBA) for 1992, suggest that the unconditional mean length 
of time for a worker "to become fully trained and qualified" 
is about 21 weeks, and that the median is about 6 weeks (see 
Barron et al. 1997, Table 3.4). 
31. Labor regulation by Rauch (1991) is implemented 
as a minimum wage. Acemoglu and Pischke (1999b) argue 
that this is one of the mechanisms that result in the 
structure of wages in which productivity increases faster 
with training than wages, and that leads to firm-sponsored 
general training. </p>

<p>that the main driving force behind the increase 
in informality in Brazil during the 1990s was 
the reduction of formal sector hirings mainly 
explained by changes in labor market legislation. 
More recently, Albrecht et al. (2009) built an 
equilibrium search and matching model to study 
the effects of changes of severance and payroll 
taxes; their simulations suggest that increases in 
both severance and payroll taxes shift employ-
ment from the formal to the informal sector. 
Once agreed that it is possible that human 
capital accumulation takes place while workers 
are employed in the informal sector, one could 
also say that it is possible that informal sector 
workers invest more in human capital than formal 
sector workers. Figure 2 shows that, on average, 
wages in the informal sector are lower than in the 
formal sector. The difference in intercepts in the 
log-wage regressions presented in Appendix B 
suggests that there is still a gap after controlling 
for worker and firm observable characteristics. 
Finally, Figure 1 suggests that, during the first 
years of the workers' careers, workers are more 
likely to move from the informal to the formal 
sector as they age. If wages and productivity are 
lower in the informal sector and informal sector 
workers expect to move to the formal sector 
eventually, investment in human capital may be 
greater in the informal sector than in the formal 
sector. That is, if workers face a lower price for 
their skills in the informal sector in the present, 
and expect a higher price for their skills when 
they move to the formal sector in the future, then 
the opportunity cost of human capital investment 
is lower in the informal sector, which will induce 
informal sector workers to invest more in human 
capital. Formal sector workers, however, do not 
face this lower opportunity cost. 
Faster wage growth in the informal sector 
could also arise in a model of on-the-job training 
with different levels of specificity of training in 
the formal and informal sectors. In the study by 
Becker (1993), when firms provide firm-specific 
on-the-job training, firms bear the cost of training 
because if the worker moves to another firm, all 
productivity gains from training will be lost. If 
most of the training in the formal sector involves 
firm-specific human capital, whereas most of the 
training in the informal sector involves general 
human capital, wages in the informal sector 
will exhibit greater growth than wages in the 
formal sector. 
Finally, recall that Table 8 indicates that 
faster wage growth in the informal sector is 
concentrated in the youngest groups, mainly </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>ages 16-25 years, but also ages 26-36 years. 
This is also consistent with theories of human 
capital accumulation, because it is mostly young 
workers who invest in accumulating skills on 
the job (e.g., Ben-Porath 1967; Rosen 1972). 
If most training takes place during the early 
stages of workers' careers, and if informal sector 
workers invest in human capital just as formal 
sector workers, or perhaps more, then we should 
only observe faster wage growth in the informal 
sector during the early stages of the workers' 
careers. This is what the evidence presented in 
Table 8 suggests. 
Evidently there are alternative explanations to 
the result that wages grow faster in the informal 
than in the formal sector presented in Table 3. 
Two alternative explanations are wage flexibility 
and job switching. It is possible that the results 
in Table 3 just reflect the fact that wages are 
more flexible in the informal sector than in the 
formal sector, particularly since previous stud-
ies have found that it is common that nomi-
nal wages remain constant from year to year in 
IMSS-registered firms (Castellanos et al. 2004). 
However, the results presented in Table 8 indicate 
that change in wages is not consistent across age 
groups, which does not support the wage flexibil-
ity explanation. That is, if the finding that wage 
growth is faster in the informal sector due to wage 
rigidity in IMSS-registered firms, this should be 
true for older workers too. Table 8 indicates that 
while this is true for one-quarter wage growth, 
it is not true for two-, three-, and four-quarter 
wage growth. Hence, the results in Table 8 dis-
card this possibility. 
Similarly, it is possible that the results in 
Table 3 are due to informal sector workers switch-
ing jobs more frequently than formal sector work-
ers. That is, if informal sector workers switch 
jobs very frequently and the wide range of infor-
mal sector job opportunities induce them to have 
higher reservation wages, then we could observe 
wages growing faster in the informal than in 
the formal sector. However, the range of hourly 
wage changes in Figure 2 is very large for both 
informal and formal sector wages, and for both 
wage increases and wage decreases. This sug-
gests that some workers are not staying with the 
same employer both in the informal and formal 
sectors, hence it is not very likely that the results 
in Table 3 are driven by more job switching in the 
informal sector. 
The ENOE allows for a more careful analy-
sis of this competing hypothesis. Table 9 presents 
the number of individual changes in job-related </p>

<p>characteristics for the sample used in the estima-
tion of Table 3. I consider three job-related char-
acteristics: occupation (job position), industry, 
and firm size. Changes in these characteristics are 
considered separately for the four different time 
spans: one-, two-, three-, and four-quarters. The 
table also shows, in parenthesis, the proportion of 
individual changes relative to the total number of 
observations by sector, presented in the first row. 
Recall that there can be multiple wage growth 
observations by individuals, and so there can also 
be multiple changes by individuals for each of the 
three categories. The results are mixed: there is a 
larger proportion of workers switching job posi-
tion and firm size within the formal sector, but 
there is a larger proportion of workers switching 
industry within the informal sector. The last two 
rows present the number of changes in "at least 
one" category without double counting switch-
ers and, in parenthesis, the proportion of these 
changes relative to the total number of observa-
tions in each sector. That is, if a worker changes 
both occupation and industry this is only counted 
as one change. In this case, the numbers show 
that the proportion of changes in the formal sector 
is larger than in the informal sector. Overall the 
table suggests that workers in these age and edu-
cation categories employed in the informal sector 
are not more likely than formal sector workers in 
the same categories to change jobs. 
A third possible explanation is that formal sec-
tor workers in small firms are hired at the mini-
mum wage, which would be above their market 
clearing wage, and that informal salaried catch 
up over time. However, this implies that wages 
in the informal sector grow, because they are 
catching up, and that the wage growth is due 
to the accumulation of human capital. That is, 
if employers behave optimally, they would only 
increase a worker's wage if there is an increase 
in that worker's productivity, and worker pro-
ductivity increases because workers accumulate 
human capital. </p>

<p>V. FINAL REMARKS </p>

<p>The traditional view of the informal sector 
assumes that jobs in this sector offer little beyond 
a make-shift or temporary job for workers that are 
waiting for a "better" formal sector job. However, 
this study shows that informal jobs are not dead 
end jobs, and that these jobs appear to offer wage 
growth similar to formal sector jobs for young 
less-educated workers entering the labor market. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>TABLE 9 
Workers Switching Job Position, Industry, and Firm Size by Sector </p>

<p>One-Quarter 
Two-Quarter 
Three-Quarter 
Four-Quarter </p>

<p>FS 
IS 
FS 
IS 
FS 
IS 
FS 
IS </p>

<p>Total observations by sector 
35,627 
30,223 
21,831 
16,905 
12,318 
8,768 
5,281 
3,520 
Switchers by: 
Job position 
8,613 
5,996 
5,645 
3,541 
3,344 
1,859 
1,501 
756 
(0.24) 
(0.20) 
(0.26) 
(0.21) 
(0.27) 
(0.21) 
(0.28) 
(0.21) 
Industry 
4,959 
5,511 
3,222 
3,282 
1,896 
1,753 
813 
737 
(0.14) 
(0.18) 
(0.15) 
(0.19) 
(0.15) 
(0.20) 
(0.15) 
(0.21) 
Firm size 
25,111 
11,864 
15,283 
6,529 
8,626 
3,312 
3,713 
1,372 
(0.70) 
(0.39) 
(0.70) 
(0.39) 
(0.70) 
(0.38) 
(0.70) 
(0.39) 
Any change 
27,712 
16,116 
16,969 
9,023 
9,587 
4,677 
4,142 
1,917 
(0.78) 
(0.53) 
(0.78) 
(0.53) 
(0.78) 
(0.53) 
(0.78) 
(0.54) </p>

<p>Notes: FS, formal sector; IS, informal sector. Number of workers who switch job position, industry, or firm size between 
interviews. The row "Any Change" avoids double counting of switchers for the three categories. The numbers in parenthesis 
are the proportion of switchers with respect to the total number of observations by sector presented in the first line. The One-
Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 1. The Two-Quarter columns correspond 
to workers who switched between interviews in t and t + 2. The Three-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched 
between interviews in t and t + 3. The Four-Quarter columns correspond to workers who switched between interviews in t and 
t + 4. The samples include male paid-employees with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, ages 16-25 years. </p>

<p>The present study provides an analysis of the 
informal and formal sectors using data from 2005 
to 2012 from a longitudinal household survey 
from Mexico, the ENOE. The analysis suggests 
that less-educated workers start their careers in 
the informal sector, and move to the formal sector 
as they grow older. More important, it is found 
that for young less-educated workers, wages in 
the informal sector grow faster than wages in 
the formal sector, conditional on worker and firm 
observable characteristics. 
If the labor market in the informal sector is 
a competitive labor market whereas the formal 
sector is a frictional labor market, models of 
on-the-job training in competitive and in non-
competitive labor markets predict that formal sec-
tor employers sponsor at least part of the training 
costs, while informal sector employers pass these 
costs onto the workers. The evidence from wage 
growth data presented in this study is consistent 
with these theories of human capital accumula-
tion, which, in turn, supports the possibility that 
young less-educated workers accumulate skills 
while employed in the informal sector. 
Informal-salaried workers may even invest 
more in human capital than formal-salaried work-
ers. This is because informal-salaried workers 
have lower wages and expect to eventually move 
to a formal-salaried job. Another mechanism con-
sistent with the evidence on wage data is based on 
systematic differences in the specificity of train-
ing between the informal and the formal sectors. 
Even though all these mechanisms lead to the </p>

<p>same conclusion in terms of investment in human 
capital in the informal sector, they may have dif-
ferent implications for the design of labor mar-
ket policies, and so ideally one could distinguish 
between them. That exercise would require more 
than just analyzing wage data. 
If informal jobs do indeed provide training to 
young less-educated workers, those who start in 
the informal sector and move to the formal sector 
later on in their careers, will have a career path 
different from the career path of less-educated 
workers who start in the formal sector. These 
differences could be used to distinguish between 
the proposed mechanisms discussed above. How-
ever, to study these differences, it is necessary to 
have access to a longer panel than the one used in 
this study, which only follows individuals during 
12 months. 
Equally important, if informal jobs provide 
training opportunities to young less-educated 
workers, then it is possible that these workers 
opt for an informal job instead of queuing longer 
for a formal job, in order to accumulate skills. 
Given the arguments provided before, it could 
also be possible that training costs could help in 
closing the gap between earnings in the formal 
and informal sectors, which appear to persist 
after controlling for observable characteristics. </p>

<p>APPENDIX A: THE ENOE </p>

<p>The ENOE is a rotating panel where households are 
visited five times during 12 months, one visit every 3 months. </p>

<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>



<p>After the fifth visit, the household is replaced with another 
household that is also visited five times in the course of a year. 
The ENOE collects demographic data of each family member 
as well as job-related data for members who are 12 years of 
age or older. Job-related data include working hours, earnings, 
benefits, firm size, job position, and industry of occupation. 
These data refer to the job held by the individual the week 
prior to the interview. I used data from the first quarter of 2005 
to the fourth quarter of 2012. During this period, it is possible 
to identify 28 different panels of individuals. 
Hourly earnings are obtained from a variable constructed 
by the ENOE called "ING_X_HRS" which provides average 
earnings per working hour. 32 To construct this variable, the 
ENOE records (1) how often the respondent receives his or her 
income (i.e., daily, weekly, monthly, etc.) and (2) what is the 
amount of money received. With these two pieces, the ENOE 
computes a measure of monthly income. Income reported by 
the respondent is only net income, that is, income received by 
the worker after paying taxes, social security fees, or union 
fees. All this information is with respect to the job held by the 
individual the week prior to the interview. 
In a separate sequence of questions, the ENOE collects the 
days of the week prior to the interview in which the worker 
attended his or her job and the number of hours worked on 
each day. With this information, a measure of monthly hours is 
constructed which is then used to obtain the average earnings 
per working hour provided by the variable "ING_X_HRS." 
Finally, I used the CPI base second half of December 2010 to 
deflate nominal hourly wages. 
The ENOE also indicates the minimum-wage zone in 
which an individual in the survey is located and the corre-
sponding minimum wage in that zone. In Mexico, there are 
three different minimum-wage zones: zones A, B, and C. 
Zone A pays the highest minimum wage, and zone C pays the 
lowest minimum wage. As this information is determined by 
the geographical location of the individual, it is provided for 
all individuals in the survey and so it can be used to impute 
individual earnings when this information is missing in the 
ENOE variable ING_X_HRS. The ENOE asks the individual 
if his or her earnings are between: (1) 0 and 1 minimum wage, 
(2) 1 and 2 minimum wages, (3) 2 and 3 minimum wages, 
(4) 3 and 5 minimum wages, and (5) more than 5 minimum 
wages. I used this information to impute earnings of workers 
who reported having worked but for whom the information 
on the ENOE variable ING_X_HRS is missing. Let w k be 
the minimum wage in zone k ∈ {A, B, C}. The following table 
describes the imputation procedures: </p>

<p>TABLE A1 
Imputation Procedures </p>

<p>Range of Minimum Wage 
Imputation </p>

<p>0-1 
0.5 × w k 
1-2 
1.5 × w k 
2-3 
2.5 × w k 
3-5 
4 × w k 
5 or more 
5.5 × w k </p>

<p>I also create an indicator variable for the observations for 
which earnings are imputed and include this variable in the </p>

<p>32. I constructed a similar variable using the information 
on the questions of the ENOE related to income and working 
hours and following standard procedures and obtained the 
same results. Hence, I decided to use the variable already 
constructed by the ENOE. </p>

<p>regression analysis below. In the final sample, only 4.77% of 
the earnings were imputed. </p>

<p>APPENDIX B: LOG-WAGE REGRESSIONS </p>

<p>Table 10 presents log-wage regressions for each salaried 
sector on a set of worker and firm observable characteristics. 
The estimation results indicate that graduation from primary 
school is an important factor to explain differences in earnings 
in the informal sector, but not in the formal sector. The effect 
of middle school graduation, however, is an important factor 
to explain differences in earnings in both sectors as well 
as labor market experience. Note that the indicators for the 
minimum wage zones are only significant in the formal sector. 
On average, those workers employed in cities with the highest 
minimum wage have higher earnings than those employed in 
cities in the minimum wage zones B and C. 
In both sectors, the industry of occupation is very impor-
tant in explaining differences in earnings. In both the formal 
and informal sectors, workers employed in manufacturing, </p>

<p>TABLE 10 
Log-Wage Regressions by Sector </p>

<p>Formal Sector Informal Sector </p>

<p>Primary School Grad 
0.0451 
0.1390 
(0.0254) 
( 0.0213) 
Middle School Grad 
0.1329 
0.2064 
(0.0263) 
( 0.0225) 
Experience 
0.0189 
0.0240 
(0.0014) 
( 0.0017) 
Minimum wage zone 
Zone B 
−0.1349 
−0.0763 
(0.1523) 
( 0.1629) 
Zone C 
−0.0878 
0.0329 
(0.1673) 
( 0.1763) 
Industry 
Manufacturing 
−0.2085 
−0.1492 
(0.0127) 
( 0.0121) 
Commerce 
−0.2489 
−0.2338 
(0.0133) 
( 0.0125) 
Services 
−0.1712 
−0.1318 
(0.0133) 
( 0.0120) 
Firm size 
6−50 
0.0167 
0.1104 
(0.0118) 
( 0.0105) 
51+ 
0.0378 
0.1218 
(0.0124) 
( 0.0218) 
Const 
2.9510 
2.5670 
(0.1716) 
( 0.1794) 
Number of obs. 
49,110 
45,403 
R 2 
0.1697 
0.2063 </p>

<p>Notes: Both regressions are weighted using the ENOE 
sampling weights. The samples include male paid-employees 
with less than 12 years of education and not attending school, 
ages 16-25 years. Primary School Grad = 1{E ≥ 6}, Middle 
School Grad = 1{E ≥ 9}. The ranking of minimum wages by 
zone is: w A &gt; w B &gt; w C , where w k is the minimum wage in 
Zone k. The omitted categories for the dummy variables are: 
minimum wage zone A, Construction industry, and firm size 
2-5 employees. Both specifications include a time trend, year 
dummies, city dummies, city-size dummies, and a dummy 
equal to 1 if the measure of hourly earnings was imputed using 
the minimum wage in the zone. Huber-White robust standard 
errors clustered at the individual level are in parenthesis. </p>



<p>ECONOMIC INQUIRY </p>

<p>commerce, or services have on average lower earnings than 
those employed in the construction industry. Interestingly, the 
estimates in both sectors are fairly similar and have a similar 
pattern. Also, those employed in larger firms earn on average 
higher wages than those in smaller firms. The differences in 
firm size are more important to explain wages in the informal 
sector than in the formal sector, as indicated by the statistical 
significance of the estimated coefficients. Both specifications 
include a time trend, year dummies, city dummies, city-size 
dummies, and a dummy equal to one if the measure of hourly 
earnings was imputed using the minimum wage in the zone, 
as I explained in the previous section. </p>

<p>APPENDIX C: COMPUTING THE INVERSE 
PROBABILITY WEIGHTS </p>

<p>The inverse probability weights (IPW) are calculated fol-
lowing the procedure described by Wooldridge (2002). A 
detailed implementation of this procedure is provided by 
Jones et al. (2013). See Wooldridge (2002, 587-88) and Jones 
et al. (2013, 283-87) for the details. For individual i define an 
indicator variable s ik as: </p>

<p>s ik = 1 { In Sample at Interview k } , 
k = 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. </p>

<p>IPW FOR ONE-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH </p>

<p>For the one-quarter wage growth regression, the first rel-
evant interview is the second interview, that is, k = 2, because 
at the first interview there is no measure of wage growth. For 
individual i, define the vector of characteristics z i0 as: </p>

<p>z ′ 
i0 = </p>

<p>( 
Δ 1 w ik , x ′ </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>) , k = 2, </p>

<p>where x ik is the vector of covariates used in the estimation of 
the wage growth regressions presented in Table 2. That is, z i0 
is the value of wage growth and of the covariates at the first 
relevant interview, which is the second interview. 
To compute the IPW for the one-quarter wage growth, I 
estimate three separate probit models for the indicator vari-
able s ik for k = 3, 4, 5 and from each estimation I obtain the 
predicted probability of being in the sample at interview k. 
The inverse of this predicted probability is the IPW for each 
interview. The following diagram describes the estimation of 
the IPW: </p>

<p>Probit of s i3 on z i0 ⇒ Obtain ̂ p ⇒ IPW i3 = 1∕̂ p i3 </p>

<p>Probit of s i4 on z i0 ⇒ Obtain ̂ p ⇒ IPW i4 = 1∕̂ p i4 </p>

<p>Probit of s i5 on z i0 ⇒ Obtain ̂ p ⇒ IPW i5 = 1∕̂ p i5 </p>

<p>Then, the IPW i3 is used to weight the observations of 
individual i at the third interview, the IPW i4 is used to weight 
the observations of individual i at the fourth interview, and the 
IPW i5 is used to weight the observations of individual i at 
the fifth interview. Observations for individual i at the second 
interview have a weight of 1. The same weighting is done for 
all individuals. </p>

<p>IPW FOR TWO-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH </p>

<p>For the two-quarter wage growth regression, the first 
relevant interview is the third interview, that is, k = 3, because </p>

<p>at the first and second interviews there is no measure of wage 
growth. Similar to what I did for the one-quarter wage growth, 
define the vector of characteristics z i0 as: </p>

<p>z ′ 
i0 = </p>

<p>( 
Δ 2 w ik , x ′ </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>) , k = 3. </p>

<p>To compute the IPW for the two-quarter wage growth, I 
estimate two separate probit models for the indicator variable 
s ik for k = 4, 5 and from each estimation I obtain the predicted 
probability of being in the sample at interview k as in the 
diagram presented above. The inverse of this predicted prob-
ability is the IPW for each interview. The IPW i4 is used to 
weight the observations of individual i at the fourth interview, 
and the IPW i5 is used to weight the observations of individual 
i at the fifth interview. Observations for individual i at the third 
interview have a weight of 1. The same weighting is done for 
all individuals. </p>

<p>IPW FOR THREE-QUARTER WAGE GROWTH </p>

<p>Finally, for the three-quarter wage growth regression the 
first relevant interview is the fourth interview, that is, k = 4, 
because at the first, second, and third interviews there is no 
measure of wage growth. Similar to what I did above, define 
the vector of characteristics z i0 as: </p>

<p>z ′ 
i0 = </p>

<p>( 
Δ 3 w ik , x ′ </p>

<p>ik </p>

<p>) , k = 4. </p>

<p>To compute the IPW for the three-quarter wage growth, 
I estimate one probit model for the indicator variable s ik for 
k = 5 and from this estimation I obtain the predicted probabil-
ity of being in the sample at interview k as in the diagram pre-
sented above. The inverse of this predicted probability is the 
IPW for each interview. The IPW i5 is used to weight the obser-
vations of individual i at the fifth interview, and the weight 
at the fourth interview is 1. The same weighting is done for 
all individuals. </p>



<p>CANO-URBINA: INFORMAL SECTOR AND ON-THE-JOB TRAINING </p>





</text></tei>