<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10824-015-9248-3" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract We conduct an analysis of 1835 pledges to 10 music production pro-
jects hosted on the largest Brazilian crowdfunding platform, namely the Catarse 
Web site, and we assess the relation between the fundraising accumulation period, 
the donor-entrepreneur distance and the propensity of donors to back projects. Our 
results suggest a significantly negative association between distance and the value of 
capital pledged to projects, which is consistent with the notion that the en-
trepreneur's network of close contacts might play a central role in funding. Fur-
thermore, our results contradict the idea that crowdfunding reduces the inhibiting 
effect of donor-entrepreneur distance. In addition, the results show that a long 
project exposure is associated with higher values of pledges. These results suggest 
practical implications for the study of crowdfunding as a financing platform. This </p>

<p>study contributes to the literature on the use of crowdfunding as an alternative 
funding source in a major emerging market. </p>

<p>Brazil is one of the major music producing and consuming regions worldwide, and 
it had the 11th largest market in 2009 (IFPI 2010). Although 58 % of the market 
was national and 90 % of the best-selling albums were by local musicians in 2009 
(IFPI 2014), music production differs little from the world market, as a few record 
companies compose the local market (Cassiolato et al. 2008). As such, the cost of 
entry for budding musicians is high (Cameron 2015). Although there is often 
demand from Brazilian artists for financing their activities (Lucas 2000), access to 
resources for beginners is scarce. Indeed, if we consider musicians as entrepreneurs, 
at the outset of their initiatives they find it difficult to attract external capital. The 
problem of accessing specific financing sources is inherent to their initial stage 
(Berger and Udell 1998; Cosh et al. 2009). This difficulty places a limiting factor on 
the entrepreneur's chances of survival and growth, especially given the lack of true 
guarantees and what potential investors would view as sufficient cash flows or good 
reputation. It should also be noted that investors are faced with asymmetric 
information. According to Cosh et al. (2009), entrepreneurs requiring smaller 
amounts of capital are unable to access venture capital, private equity or banks, 
which may be available in other stages. Hence, these entrepreneurs tend to find 
backing from: (1) their own resources, (2) their family and (3) their circle of close 
friends (Parker 2009; Sheng and Mendes-da-Silva 2014). 
Crowdfunding has become an innovative method for bringing investors and those 
requiring capital closer together, especially when the latter are developing artistic, 
cultural, social or other types of initiatives (Shiller 2013). This method has enabled 
relatively small sums pledged by a large number of people to make businesses 
viable in a more flexible and less costly way that does not require intermediate 
financiers. A large number of platforms for raising funds through crowdfunding 
have appeared as a result of this phenomenon. One example is Kickstarter (https:// 
www.kickstarter.com/), which is currently the largest platform in the world. Kick-
starter is a North American website hosting projects including films, games, music, 
design and technology. Since its launch in 2009, it has attracted more than R$ 1.5 
billion from 5.1 million people to finance more than 50,000 creative projects (Qiu 
2013). 
Although the World Bank (2013) and specialized consultants point to the rapid 
growth of this financing mode, it still tends to be highly concentrated in North 
America and Europe (59 and 35 % of the total value around the world, respectively) 
with a negligible presence in developing continents. South America, for example, </p>

<p>76 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>represented only 0.03 % of this market and that portion exceeded only the 
corresponding one for the African continent, which represented just 0.003 % 
(Massolution 2013). In addition to the social impact of crowdfunding and its interest 
from the financial media, and more recently, the academic business community 
(Shiller 2013; Mollick 2014; Bruton et al. 2015), various governments have 
recognized its relevance to developing countries (Royal and Windsor 2014), and 
consequently, they have given attention to regulating this activity (Agrawal et al.  2014). For example, the US Government recently approved legislation entitled the 
Jumpstart Our Business Startups Act (JOBS Act), which has the main objective of 
stimulating access by companies in the emerging growth stage (Stemler 2013). 
In finance, investors tend to demand relatively more information from embryonic 
businesses, given the high level of risk when dealing with new businesses (Berger  and Udell 1998). Investors in startups also tend to prefer businesses that are 
physically closer, as they are motivated by the wish to reduce the information 
asymmetry (Lee et al. 2008). However, crowdfunding allows an unlimited number 
of geographically dispersed people to be reached for the purpose of obtaining small 
amounts of money for financing a project or enterprise. It also allows business 
activities to be monitored as they progress, and this monitoring can occur over large 
distances, which will reduce information asymmetries. Moreover, in their mode of 
pledges, creative entrepreneurs like musicians can overcome problems of market 
capitalism as a delivery mechanism (Cameron 2015). 
This article examines the associations that exist between the fundraising period, 
geographic distances, socioeconomic factors and the pledges made to projects 
financed through crowdfunding in an emerging economy. For this purpose, the data 
that were analyzed are related to 1835 pledges toward ten music production projects 
that were judged to be successful on the main Brazilian crowdfunding platform in 
2013: Catarse. This work is organized in five sections. Section 2 presents 
background material about crowdfunding, its uses and the hypotheses tested in 
this study. Then, Sect. 3 sets out the methodology we used. The results are 
discussed in Sect. 4, and our conclusions are given in Sect. 5. </p>

<p>2 Background </p>

<p>The so-called subprime crisis was the worst financial crisis since the Great 
Depression according to Shiller (2013). This crisis has been perceived as due to 
failings intrinsic to the financial system and the people running it. In particular, 
financial agents have been seen as one of the principal causes of the crisis for 
working excessively for their own benefit. According to Shiller (2013), the financial 
industry needs time to rebuild its reputation with society, and this process is 
characterized by the emergence of financial innovations, e.g., social impact bonds 
and crowdfunding. In this sense, crowdfunding is frequently identified as one of the 
most relevant modern financial innovations (Kuti and Madarász 2014). This 
financing method has emerged as a novel way of raising capital for entrepreneurial 
ventures (Macht 2014), and it frequently occurs through the internet. Crowdfunding 
has enabled different business types, such as agribusiness, social projects, </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
77 </p>



<p>technological innovation projects and particularly cultural production, without the 
pitfalls of traditional methods of financing (Braet et al. 2013; Lehner 2013;  Schwartz 2013; Agrawal et al. 2014). We focus on this novel funding method in the 
case of music. </p>

<p>2.1 Definition and uses of crowdfunding </p>

<p>Crowdfunding has been seen as a tool that enables the democratization of financing 
(Brabham 2008; Kim and Hann 2014) and as an innovative method of financing. It 
is normally enabled through the internet by means of social media (Lehner 2013), 
and it allows entrepreneurs to reach geographically dispersed people around the 
globe who are willing to support the project (Saxton and Wang 2014). 
Crowdfunding has been described as the accumulation of small investments in 
individual projects by a large number of individuals who are supported by a 
platform (Royal and Windsor 2014). One of the characteristics of crowdfunding 
projects is the existence of a funding target. Often a campaign exceeds 100 % of its 
funding target, which is known as ''overfunding,'' entrepreneurs are not required to 
take investment but reserve the right to accept any amount beyond 100 %. In the 
particular case of this research, the excess funds are delivered to the entrepreneur's 
musical project. According to Royal and Windsor (2014), the platform allows 
project initiators to upload projects to the platform online for others worldwide with 
similar interests to contribute financially. 
According to Mollick (2014), the most basic variations in crowdfunding relate to 
the objectives pursued by the entrepreneurs and investors, called ''donors'' 
hereafter. As in the specific case of this article, the people who are interested in 
music production projects are not necessarily interested in financial returns, as 
discussed by Kuti and Madarász (2014) and Royal and Windsor (2014). By means 
of these platforms, the entrepreneur can seek a small sum, e.g., a few thousand 
Brazilian reals or less, to fund a specific project that is motivated by their own 
dream or objective. Usually, these types of projects receive the majority of their 
funding from the entrepreneur's social network, i.e., his or her network of personal 
contacts (family and friends) (Agrawal et al. 2011; Sheng and Mendes-da-Silva  2014). These social networks provide additional support that such funding does not 
customarily receive from angel investors, such as advice, governance and prestige 
(Ferrary and Granovetter 2009). From this starting point, recent studies have 
highlighted these aspects as pertinent to a relevant research agenda on the theme of 
crowdfunding (Lehner 2013). 
As crowdfunding has evolved, it has reached a growing segment of the public 
and is no longer restricted to being an alternative way for entrepreneurs or startups 
to attract funding for their projects. It has evolved so that crowdfunders can perform 
support roles. By way of illustration, in certain circumstances crowdfunding may be 
used to achieve the simple objective of raising awareness about a new project as part 
of a marketing campaign that directly involves consumers (Cameron 2015). The 
interested company is able to gauge whether there is demand and how much demand 
there is for a specific product (Schwienbacher and Larralde 2012). </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>Although crowdfunding can be used with the intention of participating in the 
equity of the company, this research focused on projects without this characteristic. 
Among these projects, Agrawal et al. (2014) highlighted seven characteristics in 
their review: (1) the funding is not geographically concentrated; (2) the values of 
pledges are highly asymmetric; (3) the propensity to invest increases as capital 
accumulates during the fundraising period of the project, with the risk that investors 
will follow herd behavior; (4) friends and family play a key role in the initial stages 
of the fundraising process; (5) the funding follows concentrations that already 
existed; (6) entrepreneurs and investors tend to be highly optimistic at the outset 
about the results of the project seeking investment; (7) lastly, the capital attracted by 
means of crowdfunding might replace traditional financing sources. 
In addition to these peculiarities, just as the objectives pursued by entrepreneurs 
vary, the motivations of the investors may also vary according to the nature of the 
project (Belleflamme et al. 2014). There are essentially four models for how 
individuals provide their sponsorship to projects (Kuti and Madarász 2014; Royal  and Windsor 2014). The first model is donation-our case in this research, which 
applies mainly to projects that are characterized as artistic, humanitarian and socio-
environmental. The sponsorship is in many cases virtually philanthropic. In other 
words, the investor does not expect a direct personal return from the donation. The 
second model is based on credit: The funds are provided to the entrepreneur as a 
loan with an expected return rate. This model does not (currently) exist in Brazil, as 
this activity is restricted to financial institutions by law. The third and most 
widespread crowdfunding model to date is based on nonfinancial compensation: 
Investors receive something in exchange for sponsoring the project. Individuals 
usually receive the product that was the objective of the appeal, such as books, CDs, 
DVDs, show tickets or a wide variety of other things. Finally, there is equity 
crowdfunding, in which the sponsors are effectively investors and receive a share in 
the equity of the company they finance. This practice is still rarely found in active 
use worldwide due to regulatory obstacles (Heminway and Hoffman 2011; Ahlers  et al. 2012), and it represented just 5 % of the total volume of funds managed 
through crowdfunding platforms globally in 2013, according to Massolution (2013). </p>

<p>2.2 Literature review and hypotheses </p>

<p>Due to the possibilities offered by the internet, geographic dispersion is probably 
one of the most common characteristics of crowdfunding operations. Lee et al.  (2008) suggest that the arrival of Web 2.0 simplified the sharing of information 
within the environment of large social networks at reduced costs. This simplification 
has contributed to establishing governance mechanisms for the enterprise. Put 
another way, the arrival of online crowdfunding platforms provided a tool to bring 
the investor and entrepreneur closer together and to share information with greater 
transparency for project budgets and the necessary details on the destination of the 
raised funds. Additionally, it became possible: (1) to monitor the whole process 
(with entrepreneurs having access at any time to all of the investors in the project), 
(2) to see the percentage of the fundraising target already achieved and (3) to see the 
remaining time the fundraising period had to run. </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
79 </p>



<p>From this point of view, based on data covering the period from August 2006 
until September 2009, Agrawal et al. (2011) analyzed 34 projects that received 
24,862 donations (representing 73 % of the total amount invested in the website) in 
the Dutch platform Sellaband (https://www.sellaband.com), which is a site for 
musicians wanting to raise funds to launch their albums, to investigate whether 
crowdfunding is sensitive to the investor-entrepreneur geographic distance. The 
average investor-entrepreneur distance found by Agrawal et al. (2011) was ap-
proximately 4,828 km, which is greater than the distance between the most southern 
and northern parts of Brazil (about 4300 km). In their study, the data indicate that 
the greater the investor's proximity to the entrepreneur is, the greater the value of 
the donations will be. According to Agrawal et al. (2011), although crowdfunding 
suggests a reduced role for spatial proximity, it does play a role. 
Regarding the works on crowdfunding, it should be noted that often works found 
in the literature do not discuss with proper depth, statistical significance in relation 
to the magnitude of the economic impact of the variables, as discussed by 
Drummond and O'Brienm (1993) and Miller and Rodgers (2008). In this regard, 
Agrawal et al. (2011), using models of binary response, indicate that investment 
propensity increases with funds raised. And relative to an entrepreneur with 
\$10,000 investment, an investor is 2.1 percentage points more likely to invest in a 
given week if the entrepreneur has $10,000-$20,000 and 8.4 points more likely to 
invest if they have more than $40,000. 
The authors argue that this geographical effect is driven by investors who likely 
have a personal connection with the artist-entrepreneur, e.g., family and friends, 
although they do not present empirical evidence about these social relations. They 
conclude that the online platform seems to eliminate most distance-related 
economic frictions, such as monitoring progress, providing input and gathering 
information; however, it does not eliminate social frictions. In the same line of 
thinking, a set of studies, e.g., Sorenson and Stuart (2001), Zook (2002), Mason  (2007) and Martins (2015), assumes that investors in enterprises in their initial 
stages tend to demand more information, monitor the business's progress and also 
participate in decisions about how the business is run. 
These activities result in costs that are sensitive to the investor-entrepreneur 
distance. Based on a sample of American Venture Capitalism Firms, Sorenson and  Stuart (2001) found that the probability of investing in a new venture falls with 
increasing geographical distance. Zook (2002) also found similar results to these 
authors' analysis for the American internet industry between 1994 and 2000. 
According to these authors, although communication technologies and the global 
financial market have geographically expanded the scope of economic interactions, 
they tend to occur regionally. Martins (2015) points out that when there are cases of 
investment outside the domestic sphere, for example, investment in projects in the 
BRIC countries (Brazil, Russia, India and China), the risks and costs tend to be 
mitigated through arrangements established between venture capitalists. 
The results of these studies show that the greater the distance between investors 
and the project is, the less likely the investors are to invest, and furthermore, they 
will probably invest less. However, in the musical production context, we must 
examine the mechanisms underlying the proximity of the donor and the amount </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>donated. Crowdfunding in the music industry cannot be seen only as an 
intermediary agent, as it is also the locus where social connections between fans 
and musicians occur (Zheng et al. 2014; Colombo et al. 2015). These fans do not 
just invest in the project of a singer or a band: They are meeting the request of 
people who are part of their social network (Saxton and Wang 2014) or are feeling 
motivated to act prosocially (Ariely et al. 2009). For these reasons, we advocate that 
the mechanisms inherent in the social capital of musicians and the behavioral 
aspects of donors simultaneously affect the relationship between the geographic 
distance and the value of a pledge. 
According to Nahapiet and Ghoshal (1998, 243), social capital can be defined as 
''the sum of the current and potential resources embedded within, available through, 
and derived from the social contacts of an individual or an organization.'' In the 
crowdfunding context, these personal contacts, such as friends, intense fans and 
family, often tend to be closer to the authors of the projects (see McPhearson et al.  2001). Moreover, because the contacts are parts of the authors' real social networks, 
it is likely that these contacts are direct targets of funding campaigns. Indeed, using 
data from Sellaband, Agrawal et al. (2011) found that not only did most of the 
donations occur in the same geographical area or in nearby areas, but these 
donations also had the highest value. Although they have not considered the 
distance of ties between donors and musicians, Mollick (2014) and Zheng et al.  (2014) identified a positive relationship between the number of social contacts 
identified on Facebook or other social networks (e.g., Weibo Page, a Chinese social 
network) with the amount donated and with the musical project's performance. 
These results are also supported by Saxton and Wang (2014), who found that 
nonprofit organizations with more Facebook fans receive more donations, and by 
Colombo et al. (2015), who found that greater numbers of contacts on Linkedin 
were associated with both the number of supporters and the volume of capital raised 
in 669 projects on the Kickstarter platform. 
In addition to this evidence that more frequent and more valuable donations come 
from people with personal ties who are geographically closer, it should be noted that 
relations' networks are also mechanisms of coercion (Coleman 1990; Matzat 2004)  in which socially closer donors to the entrepreneur who are more densely grouped 
tend to feel more motivated or morally obliged to donate larger amounts. The 
donors can include even the most avid fans appealing for recognition by the 
musicians. 
1 This behavior in the act of giving to musical projects in crowdfunding 
happens not only for personal reasons or for direct benefits (for example, received 
gifts), but also because donors want to obtain a good image or desire the respect and 
approval of the connected community that is raising money (Ariely et al. 2009). 
These networks of relations (as we have said) tend to be geographically close to the 
entrepreneurs. From these arguments, it is relevant to test hypothesis H 1 : </p>

<p>H 1 There is a negative association between the geographic distance separating the 
entrepreneur and the donor and the value of the music crowdfunding investments. </p>

<p>1 The authors thank Editor Samuel Cameron for having pointed the role of fans. </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
81 </p>



<p>In addition to evidence of the relationship between the proximity and pledge 
value, Agrawal et al. (2011), Zhang and Liu (2012) and Kuppuswamy and Bayus  (2014) assumed that the volume of accumulated pledges grows as the fundraising 
time increases. Accordingly, these authors suggest that the propensity for a potential 
donor/investor to sponsor a project increases, which might suggest some type of 
herd behavior by investors. Burtch et al. (2013) identified crowd's herding behavior 
as a possible influencing factor for participation in crowdfunding. 
The herding behavior acts as an uncertainty reduction mechanism and may result 
in greater density in the project supporters' network. The reason is that with an 
increase in the number of donors, it is more likely that these donors will have links 
between themselves, which would make them more visible to each other (see Burt  2005). Indeed, the increased redundancy enables the network to operate as a 
coercive apparatus (Matzat 2004), as those who have not yet supported an endeavor 
feel increasingly obliged to contribute (Ariely et al. 2009). In addition, this sense of 
obligation, which grows with the project exposure, should affect not only the 
likelihood of contributing, but also the value of the donation. As Ariely et al. (2009)  discussed, in the desire to be socially approved, donors feel morally obligated to 
contribute a proportional or greater value. It should be considered that this behavior 
is reinforced in social networks, as one of its key features is the reciprocity in trade 
(Mendes-da-Silva et al. 2008; Zheng et al. 2014). 
Still, there is another element to consider: the relationship between the exposure 
time (time from the announcement of project) and a donation's value. As indicated 
by Colombo et al. (2015), social capital is important to raising money. Thus, we 
investigate whether the origin of the actors that promote this social capital matters. 
At this point, we divide the social capital into two types: (1) external social capital, 
which is derived from social relations outside of the crowdfunding community, such 
as friends, family or intense fans; (2) internal social capital, involving those 
relationships that are established within the crowdfunding community, usually 
composed by donors and fans and enthusiasts with weaker relationships with 
entrepreneurs. Colombo et al. (2015) showed that the internal social capital 
significantly affects the number and value of donations in the early stages. These 
actors belong primarily to the internal network community, and they tend to have 
faster access to new campaigns in crowdfunding platforms, which increases the 
chance of them donating in a project's early stages. In the case of external social 
capital, which is designed by the friends, family and intense fans of the proponents, 
these contacts are commonly not connected to crowdfunding platforms. Thus, it is 
expected that the investors who are not socially connected to the entrepreneurs tend 
to take longer amounts to donate than others. Nevertheless, donors with close ties to 
the musicians tend to donate larger amounts (Saxton and Wang 2014). Given the 
above reasons, we believe that the greater the exposure time of the project is, the 
greater the value of the donations will be. This line of thinking leads to testing 
hypothesis H 2 : </p>

<p>H 2 There is a positive association between the fundraising accumulation period 
via crowdfunding and the value of the new pledges received by the music 
entrepreneur. </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>3 Methodology </p>

<p>In this section, we describe the data collection procedures, we present the platform 
used in the study and we present the empirical strategy that we adopted. </p>

<p>3.1 Data collection </p>

<p>In November 2013, when the data analyzed in this study were collected, Brazil had 
40 crowdfunding platforms that were listed on specialized sites, e.g., (http:// 
mapadocrowdfunding.tumblr.com). Among the different types of projects spon-
sored, the majority were creative and predominantly cultural projects, although 
there were other more specific objectives, e.g., financial support for soccer clubs at 
(http://vascodividazero.com.br). The dominant site among the 40 crowdfunding 
platforms is Catarse, which was the focus of this study. Only the Catarse website 
was considered, and all of the projects meeting the following criteria were selected: 
(1) The entrepreneurs were musicians who were using the platform to seek funds for 
financing the first album of their artistic career, and (2) the target funding was 
between R$ 10,000 and R$ 30,000 (US$ 1,00 = R$ 2,80); indeed, 95 % of the 
projects hosted on the platform fall in this range value. Because of that, this range 
was considered. 
The data collection required for constructing the variables under consideration 
took place in two main phases. The first phase focused on the Catarse platform 
(http://catarse.me), where two types of data were obtained: data from browsing the 
website directly and data provided by the platform's founders to its entrepreneurs 
and sponsors through the privacy policy for the platform. The second data collection 
phase examined socioeconomic data for the municipalities where the 1835 pledges 
considered in the research originated. These data were obtained from the Brazilian 
Institute for Geography and Statistics (IBGE-Instituto Brasileiro de Geografia e 
Estatística), and we drew on the most recent Brazilian Census, which was con-
ducted in 2010. 
The geographic distance between the entrepreneurs and the donors was 
obtained for the cities where they were located, and we used Google Maps APIs 
(http://code.google.com/apis/maps/) to identify the coordinates of each location. 
The distance was calculated using the procedure adopted by Nichols (2003) with 
the tool <rs id="software-1" type="software">ArcGIS ArcMap</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">10.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">ESRI</rs> 2010). The motivation for using these 
types of tools comes from the argument that when the data's spatial distribution 
is related to the phenomena occurring in the territory, one has a modern way to 
clarify questions related to various fields of knowledge (Ebner et al. 2009). The 
use of these techniques in the business field is in an embryonic stage (Good-
child 2010), especially in studies of collaborative phenomena (Sui et al. 2013). 
In addition, geographical information systems (GISs) could be a tool toward 
providing a spatial explanation of governance, population and cultural assets 
(Redaelli 2012). </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>

<p>
3.2 The website studied: Catarse </p>

<p>The Catarse website (http://catarse.me) was launched in January 2011, and it was 
one of the first crowdfunding platforms in Brazil. It is currently the largest collective 
financial community in the country and has already raised more than R$ 12 million 
to finance around 800 projects. The way it works is relatively simple and common to 
most competing sites: The entrepreneur uses the platform as a means to present their 
idea to the public, specifying the total investment required and the cutoff date for 
evaluating whether or not it has been achieved. To be able to use this platform for 
fundraising, the entrepreneur must meet the requirements given in Table 1. 
Figure 1 shows a typical project page on the platform we studied. On the right, 
observe: (1) the number of sponsors already attracted to the project, (2) the total 
pledged so far, (3) the total requested, (4) the remaining fundraising period, (5) the 
project description and (6) rewards and other relevant information. Table 2 shows a 
summary of the profiles of the ten projects selected for this study. Notice that these 
projects raised nearly R$ 200,522.00 from 1835 pledges that originated from 151 
different municipalities. The second column of the table shows the project that 
received the greatest number of investment pledges (377 pledges) achieved its target 
(through the Catarse platform) of R$ 29,400. Project No. 1 originated from the city 
of Curitiba in Paraná State, Southern Brazil. We do not highlight the pledge rewards 
because they were extremely similar and had the same pattern. These projects 
started with online distribution albums after physical distribution and evolved to 
give autographs and invitations to release shows. </p>

<p>Table 1 List of requirements for projects hosted on the Catarse website </p>

<p># Requirement </p>

<p>1 The project must be complete and have a clear objective or it will not be accepted on the platform </p>

<p>2 The project must present a realistic fundraising target and account for all of the costs and rates 
involved in a campaign on the platform; all projects must specify a budget that justifies the 
fundraising target given </p>

<p>3 Together with the target, projects must have a defined fundraising duration (with a maximum of 60 
days </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>4 The fundraising system is ''all or nothing'': if the given target is not achieved within the specified 
timescale, the sponsors receive a credit to back other projects, or if they prefer, a refund of their 
money; additionally, the project receives nothing </p>

<p>5 All projects must offer rewards as consideration to donors for their sponsorship. For example: copies 
of the work, CDs of music, innovative experiences, limited editions and exclusive benefits. Any 
form of financial return is prohibited </p>

<p>6 All projects must provide certain information that indicates what it is, what will be done and how the 
money will be spent </p>

<p>7 A high-quality video explaining the project must be produced </p>

<p>a Until September 30, 2013, the Catarse platform offered creators of projects that did not achieve their 
funding the possibility of having a ''Second Chance'' on the platform if they met certain requirements, 
with a new fundraising period opening once the project had been redesigned to correct any problems with 
it. This practice resulted in fundraising periods longer than the 60-day limit. This opportunity was 
abolished on October 01, 2013 </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>Note that Project No. 1 reached this total after 37 days of fundraising. Figure 2 
shows the geographic distribution of the 377 pledges made to Project No. 1 via the 
Catarse platform, as given in Table 2. </p>

<p>3.3 Model estimation </p>

<p>The variables investigated in this study are described in Table 3 and were selected 
by considering the literature on utilizing crowdfunding as a means to fund music 
production (Agrawal et al. 2011). The empirical model we tested is represented in 
(1). The four control variables were designed to assess the persistence of the 
coefficients estimated for the variables of interest, which are intended to test H 1 and 
H 2 . 
The control variables were selected by considering both the availability of the 
data provided by the Catarse website and the arguments in the literature, which 
indicate that it is possible for the dependent variable to be influenced by the control 
variables (Mason 2007; Agrawal et al. 2011, 2014). Thus, if the control variables 
have significant correlations with some of the other variables but are not considered </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Schematic view of the Catarse website. Source: adapted by the authors from the Catarse website 
(http://catarse.me/pt/andreadosguimaraes) </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
85 </p>



<p>in the model, the relationship between the variables of interest would not be 
adequately demonstrated. The errors e i are assumed uncorrelated, and E(e|X) = 0. </p>

<p>Value i ¼ b 0 þ b 1 Da i þ b 2 Dist i þ b 3 GdpCap i þ b 4 Literacy i þ b 5 HDI i þ b 6 Area i þ e i ð1Þ </p>

<p>To test the hypothesis, we used linear regression models based on the ordinary 
least-squares method (OLS model). To check the robustness, first we checked 
whether the dependent variable had an approximately normal distribution. Because 
the symmetry and kurtosis were relatively high, we also tested the models with 
standard errors of the patch through the bootstrapping procedure (Preacher and  Hayes 2008) and ran the model with the natural logarithm of the variable. In both 
cases, the results were consistent with the original template. Second, we evaluated 
the most appropriate functional form for the regression variables. In all of the cases, 
the linear function was adequate in other ways that did not significantly increase the 
fit. 
Third, we evaluated whether the errors held heteroscedasticity problems through 
the White test. Fourth, we assessed whether the models had multicollinearity 
problems by assessing the tolerances, which were not \0.2, and for the variance 
inflation factor (VIF), which did not show values [5. Fifth, we evaluated whether </p>

<p>Table 2 Profile of pledges made to the projects included in the research </p>

<p>Project </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Total raised (in R$) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>No. of pledges 
made to the project </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>City of the project 
headquarters </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>No. of 
fundraising days </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Project No. 1 
29,400 
377 
Curitiba 
37 </p>

<p>Project No. 2 
26,060 
112 
São Paulo 
60 </p>

<p>Project No. 3 
24,185 
189 
Niterói 
6 0 </p>

<p>Project No. 4 
21,180 
80 
Itapema 
56 </p>

<p>Project No. 5 
20,710 
266 
São Paulo 
51 </p>

<p>Project No. 6 
20,280 
129 
São Paulo 
60 </p>

<p>Project No. 7 
15,615 
190 
Rio de Janeiro 
101 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>Project No. 8 
15,452 
113 
São Paulo 
39 </p>

<p>Project No. 9 
15,070 
278 
Florianópolis 
60 </p>

<p>Project No. 10 12,570 
101 
Curitiba 
35 </p>

<p>This table provides information on the profile of each project included in this research. Observe that the 
project that attracted the largest number of donors raised a total of R$ 29,400 </p>

<p>Source: Developed by the authors from the data provided by the crowdfunding platform Catarse (http:// 
catarse.em) 
a Name omitted for confidentiality reasons </p>

<p>b Total sum in R$ raised by the project over the fundraising period </p>

<p>c Number of pledges received by the project during the fundraising period </p>

<p>d City in which the candidate project for funds is based </p>

<p>e Number of days that the project was visible on the platform to receive pledges (i.e., investments and 
donations) 
f One of the projects was resubmitted as a ''Second Chance,'' and it reached the funding target 101 days 
after the start of fundraising </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>the influential observations and atypical cases (cases with standardized residuals 
[2.5) generated overestimations of the model. To this end, we tested the model 
after discarding cases where the residue was [2.5. The direction of the relationship 
between the variables and the significance remained the same. Sixth, we generated 
models by replacing the independent variables with their natural logarithms, and the 
results remained very close to the original model. Seventh, to see whether there was 
any significant influence of the projects on the relationship between the variables, 
we ran a model with nine dummy variables (n-1 projects) as a control. The results 
still remained close to what was found in the original model. 
Finally, because most of the donations occurred in the municipality in which the 
project was realized (56.3 %), there is a chance of having a selection bias. </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Presentation of the geographic distribution of the pledges received by Project No. 1. Source: 
produced by the authors from data obtained from the Catarse platform using the tool ArcGIS ArcMap 
10.0 (ESRI 2010). This figure shows the geographic distribution of donors pledging capital to Project No. 
1, which attracted 396 pledges for a total of R$ 29,400. The most distant donor in Project No. 1, which is 
located in Curitiba/PR, was in the city of Manaus (Amazonas State); this donor corresponds to a distance 
of *2825 km. Country: Brazil </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>

<p>
Therefore, we also used the Heckman's Two-Step Selection Method (Heckman  1979). In the first step, we specified as the selection variable the donor-entrepreneur 
distance with a probit model, where the value one was assigned to all of the 
donations that came from distant cities (802 cases) and zero was assigned to the 
donations originated from the same city project (1.033 cases). At this step, we 
included the control variables as predictors. In the second step, we included the 
inverse Mills ratio variable in the OLS model, which controls the potential effect of 
selection bias, together with the independent and control variables. It should also be 
noted that because we observed no data from unsuccessful projects, it was not 
possible to assess empirically whether there was a selection bias in the projects. 
However, we believe that the relationship between the distance and the exposure 
time with respect to the value of donations is similar to corresponding relationship 
of successful projects. </p>

<p>4 Empirical results </p>

<p>Table 4 shows the general characteristics of the set of projects included in this 
study. The full initial sample consisted of 1954 pledges to the ten projects. 
However, this figure included 119 anonymous pledges, which are allowed by the 
Catarse platform but do not provide information on the municipality from where the 
pledge was made. Thus, anonymous pledges were excluded, which left 1835 
pledges that composed 94 % of the original sample. 
As indicated on Table 4, the entrepreneurs received on average more than 183 
pledges during the fundraising period. This period lasted an average of 56 days, 
though one of the projects was submitted as a ''Second Chance'' and reached the 
target funds 101 days after the start of fundraising. Another project achieved its 
target funding level in just 35 days. The projects attracted on average R$ 19,180.70, 
with total funds between R$ 10,000 and R$ 30,000, which is in accordance with the 
inclusion criteria adopted for this study. The average pledge was R$ 104.50, and the 
pledges varied from R$ 10.00 to R$ 5000.00. The average distance was 0 km, given 
that the majority of the sponsors (1033 of the total) were located in the same 
municipality as the project. The most distant sponsor was in Bonfim in Roraima 
(North of Brazil) for a project based in São Paulo (financial center of Brazil, in the </p>

<p>Table 3 Variables in the model </p>

<p>Value i 
=Value in R$ of the i-th pledge </p>

<p>Da i 
=Number of days from the start of the fundraising period when the i-th pledge was made </p>

<p>Dist i 
=Geographic distance in kilometers between the entrepreneur-artist and the donor </p>

<p>GdpCap i 
=GDP per capita in the donor's municipality (in R$) </p>

<p>Literacy i 
=% literacy in the donor's municipality </p>

<p>HDI i 
=HDI in the donor's municipality </p>

<p>Area i 
=Area of the donor's municipality (in km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>Southeast), which represents a distance of 3297.7 km. In accordance with the study 
conducted by Agrawal et al. (2011) on the Sellaband site, the propensity of sponsors 
to invest increased as the funds raised by the entrepreneur increased. 
From Fig. 3, one can see that the distribution of pledges is very homogeneous 
during the typical project period (up to 60 days). However, a positive correlation 
between the project maturing and the value of the pledge made is evident; this 
correlation is observed mainly in the final fundraising phase (50-60 days), with the 
average pledge made growing by nearly 70 % in comparison with the period of 
10-20 days (the period with the second-largest average pledge). The pledges after 
60 days occurred when the projects were in a ''Second Chance'' phase, that is, they 
were more mature and still had the potential to reach the fundraising target if they 
were given the opportunity to review some of the problems encountered and make 
any necessary corrections. In this period, a drastic increase in the average pledge 
made can be greater than R$ 250.00, which again suggests the importance of project 
maturity on the sponsors' decision with regard to the value to be invested. This 
behavior supports the results obtained by Agrawal et al. (2011). However, we used 
OLS models, not models of binary response (such as Agrawal et al. 2011). </p>

<p>4.1 Geographic distribution of pledges </p>

<p>In the present research, the ten sample projects are based in six cities: four in São 
Paulo (SP), two in Curitiba (Paraná State), one in Florianópolis (Santa Catarina 
State), one in Itapema (Santa Catarina State), one in Niterói (Rio de Janeiro State) </p>

<p>Table 4 Descriptive statistics for the variables included in the research </p>

<p>Average Median Min. 
Max. 
Standard 
deviation </p>

<p>Panel A: number of enterprises (N = 10) </p>

<p>No. of pledges considered as received 
183.5 
159 
80 
377 
96.5 </p>

<p>Total funds raised (R$) 
19,180.7 18,940 
10,810 28,450 
5538.8 </p>

<p>No. of fundraising days 
56 
58 
35 
101 
18.9 </p>

<p>Panel B: number of pledges (N = 1835) </p>

<p>No. of Donors = 1575 </p>

<p>Value of investment (R$) 
104.5 
50 
10 
5.000 
322.3 </p>

<p>Geographic distance (km) 
236.7 
0 
0 
3297.7 
456.4 </p>

<p>GDP per capita in the donor's 
municipality (R$) </p>

<p>31,298.0 30,400.5 5441.7 115,319.9 10,920.0 </p>

<p>Literacy in the donor's municipality (%) 89.9 
90.3 
73.1 
92.0 
1.9 </p>

<p>HDI in the donor's municipality 
0.807 
0.805 
0.625 
0.847 
0.029 </p>

<p>Area of the donor's municipality (km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 1,100.8 
675 
30.8 
34,096.4 
1420.0 </p>

<p>This study considered 10 different music production projects that received 1835 pledges (from across 
Brazil) </p>

<p>Source: Catarse Website. Demographic indicators: IBGE (Brazilian Institute of Geography and Statistics) </p>

<p>HDI human development index </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
89 </p>



<p>and one in Rio de Janeiro (Rio de Janeiro State). Pledges were made from 151 
Brazilian municipalities and two foreign countries: Paris, France, and Neuchatel, 
Switzerland; these pledges were not included in the analysis. The average distance 
of the pledges was slightly over 236 km. 
As discussed previously, empirical studies suggest that entrepreneurial initiatives 
tend to be funded by local donors for a range of reasons, such as the following: The 
monitoring costs are lower, there is better access to information, and active 
participation in decisions is possible. However, in the study conducted by Agrawal  et al. (2011), the majority of pledges made to the projects studied were distant: The 
average distance between the entrepreneurs and donors was 3000 miles (or about 
4828 km), and the donations originated from more than 80 different countries 
around the world. Figure 4 shows the geographic distribution of all of the pledges. 
The lines represent each sponsor-entrepreneur connection. Table 5 shows the 
geographic distribution of these pledges. 
As seen in Fig. 4, the majority of the pledges originate in regions closer to the 
project site. Specifically, most pledges are located within a radius of 50 km from the 
entrepreneur's location, and notably, the majority are within a distance of 5 km. 
Local investments are also on average greater than more distant ones, suggesting 
that the shorter the distance to the entrepreneur is, the greater the propensity to 
invest larger sums will be, which agrees with the negative coefficient found for the 
distance variable in the regression we performed (see Table 6). This pattern 
indicates a negative association with the pledge value. In addition, it is worth noting 
the similar average pledge in the ten projects from a distance of more than 2500 km. 
These data suggest that in Brazil, contrary to the evidence found in the European 
crowdfunding market (Agrawal et al. 2011), the financing of projects from artists at </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>20000 </p>

<p>30000 </p>

<p>40000 </p>

<p>50000 </p>

<p>60000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>350 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>450 </p>

<p>0-10 days 10-20 days 20-30 days 30-40 days 40-50 days 50-60 days &gt;60 days </p>

<p>N 
Average Pledge (R$) 
Total Invested (R$) </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Evolution of pledges over the fundraising period. Source: produced by the authors based on data 
collected on Catarse platform. Note this table shows how the average pledge values changed as the 
fundraising period progressed. Disregarding the project value of donations over 60 days, observe that as 
the hosted project matured, the value of the average pledge made via the platform appeared to increase </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>the start of their careers predominantly revolves around their network of close 
contacts. The Catarse platform states on its website that at least 50 % of the funds 
directed at projects come from the entrepreneur's own network of contacts. 
As a consequence of this perception, the administrator of the platform has 
advised the managers of hosted projects that in parallel to posting on the platform, 
they should also aim to create a page for the project on a social network. The 
motivation is the expectation that the page followers could help increase the size of 
the managers' networks of close contacts, which a priori will be more disposed to 
financially support the project hosted on the platform. Still, it is fundamental that 
more than 22 % of the total investment comes from distances [50 km, which 
represents a significant amount and suggests that the best-prepared and most </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Geographic distribution of all pledges (to projects hosted on the Catarse website). Source: 
produced by the authors from the data they collected using the tool ArcGIS ArcMap 10.0 (ESRI 2010). 
Note this figure shows the geographic spread of the 1835 pledges made to the 10 projects we examined, 
which are based in six different Brazilian cities: Curitiba (2), Florianópolis (1), Itapema (1), Niterói (1), 
Rio de Janeiro (1) and São Paulo (4) </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>

<p>
attractive entrepreneurs on the platform might benefit from the availability of these 
more distant resources by expanding their funding possibilities. Thus, it is more 
likely that these entrepreneurs will achieve their fundraising targets. 
The existence of associations between the value of a pledge, the fundraising days 
and the donor-entrepreneur distance was tested by hypotheses H 1 and H 2 . To that 
end, tests were conducted with respect to model (1), whose parameters were 
estimated using the OLS and Heckman selection model and are given in Table 6. 
Model I produced the results obtained for the two variables of interest: Days from 
the start of the fundraising period and Donor-entrepreneur distance. It can be 
confirmed from Model I that H 2 is supported, as Days from the start of the 
fundraising period gave a positive and significant parameter (b 1 ffi 1:193; p value 
\0.01). Thus, there appears to be a significant association within the values pledged 
to the hosted projects. In addition to statistical significance, about the economic 
importance, as recommended by Miller and Rodgers (2008), note that the effect of 
another day on the value of each donation is small, around R$ 1.2 (around US $ 
0.35), and this value seems to vary little, even considering the other controls 
adopted. However, as the average value of donations is approximately R$ 50.00, a 
period of 20 days of exposure could mean an increase of nearly 50 % in the value, 
which is economically relevant. 
These results support the arguments and findings of Agrawal et al. (2011), Zhang  and Liu (2012) and Kuppuswamy and Bayus (2014) that greater accumulated time 
in the fundraising period for the hosted project implies a greater propensity for 
donors to pledge larger capital sums. This correlation is due to decreases in the 
uncertainty of the project. 
The parameters estimated in Model I support hypothesis H 1 , as the parameter 
obtained for the donor-entrepreneur distance was negative and significant 
ðb 2 ffi À0:026;;p value \0.05). This result suggests that there are associations 
between the donor-entrepreneur distances and the values of pledges made to the 
hosted project, where the increase in one standard deviation in the distribution is 
related to a decrease of R$ 11.90 on the value of donations, which is also 
economically relevant. That is, more distant donors will be less disposed to invest 
larger sums in the project. This finding does not support the arguments that in the 
context of an emerging market, crowdfunding can be a sufficiently developed </p>

<p>Table 5 Frequency of investments by geographic distance </p>

<p>Distance (km) 
N 
Average pledge (R$) 
Total invested (R$) 
% of Total invested (%) </p>

<p>0-5 
1033 
109.09 
112,694 
58.8 </p>

<p>5-50 
218 
166.95 
36,395 
19.0 </p>

<p>50-500 
246 
63.81 
15,698 
8.2 </p>

<p>500-1500 
294 
79.54 
23,385 
12.2 </p>

<p>1500-2500 
34 
60.88 
2070 
1.1 
[2500 
10 
156.50 
1565 
0.8 </p>

<p>Total 
1835 
104.53 
191,807 
100 </p>

<p>Source: produced by the authors from the data they collected </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>Table 6 
Estimated regression parameters (dependent variable: Value of pledges) </p>

<p>Model I </p>

<p>Model II </p>

<p>Model III </p>

<p>Model IV </p>

<p>Model V </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Constant </p>

<p>73.057*** 
(11.348) </p>

<p>64.953** 
(26.685) </p>

<p>657.359* 
(352.548) </p>

<p>531.138 
(339.560) </p>

<p>318.649 
(521.386) </p>

<p>1. Days from the start of the fundraising period </p>

<p>1.193*** 
(0.442) </p>

<p>1.203*** 
(0.453) </p>

<p>1.218 
(0.454) </p>

<p>1.185 
(0.453) </p>

<p>0.937 
(0.492) </p>

<p>2. Donor-entrepreneur distance (in km) </p>

<p>-0.026** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>-0.025** 
(0.011) </p>

<p>-0.039** 
(0.016) </p>

<p>-0.047** 
(0.017) </p>

<p>-0.047* 
(0.022) </p>

<p>3. GDP per capita in the donor's municipality (in R$) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.001) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.001) </p>

<p>0.001 
(0.001) </p>

<p>-0.002** 
(0.001) </p>

<p>4. % Literacy in the donor's municipality </p>

<p>-8.271* 
(5.023) </p>

<p>-6.081 
(4.903) </p>

<p>7.764 
(10.024) </p>

<p>5. HDI in the donor's municipality </p>

<p>196.436 
(267.697) </p>

<p>111.506 
(272.065) </p>

<p>-1250.150 
(1174.970) </p>

<p>6. Area of the donor's municipality (in km </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>0.009*** 
(0.003) </p>

<p>0.014*** 
(0.006) </p>

<p>7. Inverse mills ratio (lambda) </p>

<p>149.640** 
(59.863) </p>

<p>F (d.f. = 1834) </p>

<p>5.369*** </p>

<p>3.747** </p>

<p>2.323** </p>

<p>3.130*** </p>

<p>Akaike criterion </p>

<p>26,393.80 </p>

<p>26,395.67 </p>

<p>26,398.01 </p>

<p>26,397.81 </p>

<p>Adjusted R-squared </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 
93 </p>



<p>Table 6 </p>

<p>continued </p>

<p>Model I </p>

<p>Model II </p>

<p>Model III </p>

<p>Model IV </p>

<p>Model V </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Wald Chi-square </p>

<p>17.74*** </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>1835 </p>

<p>1835 </p>

<p>1835 </p>

<p>1835 </p>

<p>802 </p>

<p>This table gives the parameters estimated for the empirical model adopted in this study. It is possible to see from the parameters obtained in the four models that the 
distance between the investors and the artist-entrepreneurs and the maturity of the fundraising period for the project have a marginally significant effect on the value of the 
investment made for each i-th 
pledge. This effect can be seen as an indication that being geographically closer to donors induces a greater propensity to attract them. </p>

<p>N 
= 1835 investment operations, i.e., pledges to one of the ten music production projects considered in this study. The regressions were conducted with robust standard 
error (HC1). The standard errors of the estimated coefficients are given in parentheses 
Source: 
Calculated by the authors from the data they collected from the site http://cartase.me and IBGE </p>

<p>*** p 
value \0.01; </p>

<p>** p 
value \0.05; </p>

<p>* p 
value \0.1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Only donations originated abroad. Heckman two-step selection model: 1033 censored cases (56.3 %) = zero donor-entrepreneur distance. The inverse Mills ratio (IMR) 
computed by Stata's heckman command, and used in the second-stage regression, is lambda </p>

<p>¼ f x 
ð Þ=F x 
ð Þ, where f(x) 
is the probability density function, and F(x) </p>

<p>is the </p>

<p>complementary cumulative distribution function </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>channel to supplant the information asymmetry imposed by the physical donor-
entrepreneur distance, as argued by Lee et al. (2008); at a minimum, no support for 
those arguments was found based on the data gathered from the main crowdfunding 
platform operating in Brazil. Conversely, the existence of concrete social relations 
networks between musicians and donors matter when deciding the amount of 
donation (Saxton and Wang 2014; Zheng et al. 2014; Colombo et al. 2015), as even 
these virtual relationships are, in many cases, supported in person (Wellman 1996). 
After testing H 1 and H 2 separately in Model I, the aim was to confirm the effect 
of the control variables related to the profile of the sponsor's municipality in Models 
II, III and IV. Model II shows that the wealth produced in the donor's municipality 
does not appear to influence the disposition of donors to pledge, i.e., the GDP per 
capita of the municipality is not a significant parameter ðb 1 ffi 0; p value [0.1). 
However, Model III produced a counterintuitive result that suggests less awareness 
among public donors with a higher level of education. Indeed, larger numbers of 
literate inhabitants imply lower pledges ðb 4 ffi À827:082; p value \0.1). However, 
this may be a spurious result, as it was not significant in the other models. We note 
that in Model III, the marginal effects of the variables of interest for the literate 
group were stronger than the corresponding effects included in Model I. In Model 
IV, the results suggest that the largest municipalities in terms of area appear to 
generate larger sums of investment (b 6 ffi 0:009; p value \0.01). 
In turn, the empirical model we tested (1) suggests that in all of the simulations, 
there are associations between the donor-entrepreneur distance and the value of 
each pledge received by the music production projects hosted on the Catarse 
crowdfunding platform, which is currently the largest in Brazil. In addition, 
significant indications of the effect of the fundraising time on the values of pledges 
were found when we considered the profile of the donor's municipalities. Finally, as 
most of the donations occurred within the municipality where the project was 
located, in Model V we simulated the relationship between the variables after 
excluding local donations. The results of the Heckman selection model, which 
served as a robustness check, corroborate the previous results, especially in the 
relationship between the variables the donor-entrepreneur distance and a donation's 
value: The greater the distance is, the lower the donated amount will be (b 1 ffi 0:041 
p value \0.1). </p>

<p>5 Conclusions </p>

<p>Crowdfunding is an evolving method for securing funds without the use of 
conventional equity markets. This financial innovation has enabled sources of 
funding for projects for a wide range of purposes, including cultural production 
projects, social projects and new technologies (Shiller 2013; Mollick 2014). 
Because it is supported by the internet, crowdfunding has the potential to make 
investment possible without the donors being close to the entrepreneurs. Even when 
dealing with small and medium investments in companies that are not listed on a 
stock exchange or in startups, it is only necessary for the entrepreneur to be able to </p>

<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>

<p>
provide relevant information to the donor, which reduces the information 
asymmetry, and therefore, the risks associated with the project. This fact increases 
the propensity of donors to pledge capital to the project. 
However, evidence worldwide has suggested that such a project is dependent on 
the entrepreneur's network of personal contacts, including friends and family 
(Parker 2009; Agrawal et al. 2011; Sheng and Mendes-da-Silva 2014). In other 
words, even though crowdfunding has the potential to attract capital from donors 
who are more distant from the entrepreneur, the maturity level of the crowdfunding 
industry in particular situations and institutional environments may not provide the 
necessary conditions for this pattern to happen. 
Because Brazil is a relevant emerging economy that seems to lack studies on how 
crowdfunding operates as a source of funding for small and medium projects, this 
article examined the existence of associations between the donor-entrepreneur 
distance and the propensity of donors to sponsor music production projects. In line 
with the notion that networks of close contacts might play a central role in funding, 
and simultaneously contradicting the idea that crowdfunding reduces the inhibiting 
effect of the geographic distance between donors and entrepreneurs, the results point 
to a significant, negative effect of distance on the amount of capital pledged to 
projects. These results corroborate hypothesis H 1 , which stated that there is a 
negative association between the donor-entrepreneur distances and the values of 
pledges to music production projects financed by crowdfunding. 
These results support the arguments of Sorenson and Stuart (2001), Zook (2002), 
Stuart and Sorenson (2005), Mason (2007) and Martins (2015). In addition, they 
contradict the ideas proposed by Lee et al. (2008), for whom the internet performs a 
sufficiently expressive role to make the distance between the entrepreneur and donor 
insignificant in terms of the ability of entrepreneurs to receive pledges for their 
projects. The data showed that although the internet allows donations in a wider 
geographical range, this fact does not impact the values of donations. In addition, 
the results suggest that as the fundraising period progresses, the pledges to projects 
tend to increase in value; this pattern corroborates hypothesis H 2 , namely that there 
is a positive association between the time the project has spent on the platform and 
the value of the investment received by the entrepreneur. This result supports the 
arguments made by Zhang and Liu (2012) and by Kuppuswamy and Bayus (2014), 
for whom donors tend to have a greater propensity to invest in projects that they find 
hosted for a longer period of time on a crowdfunding platform. 
The design of this research imposed limits on the work, which may restrict any 
generalizations that could be made from the results and point to a noteworthy set of 
issues: (1) the work only considered music projects, (2) the study was restricted to 
Brazil, (3) the time when the data were collected could have coincided with specific 
behavior for the variables studied, and (4) there were no individual-level data for 
donors. The issues investigated in this study add to the contemporary agenda for 
research into crowdfunding given by Lehner (2013), which appears to provide a 
promising field of business research. In addition, the results of this study suggest 
that crowdfunding requires new approaches that could help with the issues of 
attracting external capital, flexibility and financing costs, and asymmetric informa-
tion on the part of donors. Accordingly, we encourage effort to be put into </p>

<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>



<p>researching topics related to the development of the crowdfunding industry, e.g., (1) 
business and corporate governance models, (2) relationships with donors, (3) 
networks and the role performed by crowdfunding platforms, (4) discussions of the 
legitimacy of crowdfunding, (5) financial metrics, (6) legal and regulatory barriers 
and (7) recognition of opportunities. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The authors would like to thank the owner of the Catarse website, which granted 
access to the data that enabled this research. The authors must also thank the Fundação Getulio Vargas 
Business School at São Paulo (FGV/SP) and the Brazilian Institute of Financial Innovation (IBRIF) for 
their financial support. Finally, we would like to thank Dr. Andrea Maria Accioly Fonseca Minardi for her 
valuable comments at the ANPAD annual meeting 2014 in Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, two anonymous 
reviewers, and especially editor Sam Cameron for dedication to the development of the paper. The 
findings and conclusions expressed are the sole responsibility of the authors and do not necessarily 
represent the position of the institutions to which they are attached. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 
International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, dis-
tribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) 
and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>







<p> 
J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>





<p>J Cult Econ (2016) 40:75-99 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>