<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.26.2.189" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">Monster.com</rs><rs type="software">Amazon.com</rs><rs type="software">eBay</rs><rs type="software">Facebook</rs><rs type="software">Twitter</rs></p>

<p>The second main section of the paper then considers online experiments. This 
The second main section of the paper then considers online experiments. This 
category includes experiments that the economic researcher observes but does not 
category includes experiments that the economic researcher observes but does not 
control-for example, when <rs type="software">Amazon</rs> or eBay alters site design or bidding rules. It 
control-for example, when Amazon or eBay alters site design or bidding rules. It 
also includes experiments in which a researcher participates in design, including 
also includes experiments in which a researcher participates in design, including 
researcher-designed experiments; experiments conducted in partnership with 
researcher-designed experiments; experiments conducted in partnership with 
a company or website; and online versions of laboratory experiments. Finally, I 
a company or website; and online versions of laboratory experiments. Finally, I 
discuss certain limits to this type of data collection, including both "terms of use" 
discuss certain limits to this type of data collection, including both "terms of use" 
restrictions on websites and concerns about privacy and confi dentiality. 
restrictions on websites and concerns about privacy and confi dentiality. 
A wealth of data exists online mainly because the general public wants access 
A wealth of data exists online mainly because the general public wants access 
to it. With so much data readily accessible, researchers often need not obtain any 
to it. With so much data readily accessible, researchers often need not obtain any 
special permission to obtain the data they seek. Furthermore, easy data availability 
special permission to obtain the data they seek. Furthermore, easy data availability 
helps avoid selection bias: data providers tend to decline researcher requests for 
helps avoid selection bias: data providers tend to decline researcher requests for 
data that (they believe) refl ect unfavorably on them, but comprehensive online 
data that (they believe) refl ect unfavorably on them, but comprehensive online 
postings sometimes reveal surprisingly detailed information. The panorama of avail-
postings sometimes reveal surprisingly detailed information. The panorama of avail-
able online data may especially benefi t researchers early in their careers. Online 
able online data may especially benefi t researchers early in their careers. Online 
data is often available without delay and thus allows the preparation of original 
data is often available without delay and thus allows the preparation of original 
empirical research under tight time constraints-particularly helpful for students 
empirical research under tight time constraints-particularly helpful for students 
writing papers within the constraint of an academic term. Unrestricted access also 
writing papers within the constraint of an academic term. Unrestricted access also 
assists anyone whose credentials might fail to satisfy the gatekeepers who evaluate 
assists anyone whose credentials might fail to satisfy the gatekeepers who evaluate 
requests for internal data from companies and organizations. Meanwhile, the costs 
requests for internal data from companies and organizations. Meanwhile, the costs 
and diffi culty of collecting such data are modest. Most undergraduate computer 
and diffi culty of collecting such data are modest. Most undergraduate computer 
science students can design a basic system to collect data from a website, using tools 
science students can design a basic system to collect data from a website, using tools 
as basic as macros or scripts, so lack of advanced programming skills need not stand 
as basic as macros or scripts, so lack of advanced programming skills need not stand 
in the way. 
in the way. 
Online data can speak to almost every fi eld of economics, including subjects 
Online data can speak to almost every fi eld of economics, including subjects 
well beyond software, networks, and information technology. The next section iden-
well beyond software, networks, and information technology. The next section iden-
tifi es representative examples, focusing on novel data sources while fl agging useful 
tifi es representative examples, focusing on novel data sources while fl agging useful 
tools and techniques as well as recurring challenges. 
tools and techniques as well as recurring challenges. </p>

<p>Scraping the Internet to Collect Data </p>

<p>Consumers and competitors push websites to post remarkable amounts of 
Consumers and competitors push websites to post remarkable amounts of 
information online. For example, most retail booksellers would hesitate to share 
information online. For example, most retail booksellers would hesitate to share 
information about which items they sold. Yet eBay posts the full bid history 
information about which items they sold. Yet eBay posts the full bid history 
for every item offered for sale, and Amazon updates its rankings of top-selling 
for every item offered for sale, and Amazon updates its rankings of top-selling 
items every hour. Surveying job seekers can be time consuming, but sites like 
items every hour. Surveying job seekers can be time consuming, but sites like 
Monster.com organize available jobs, making it easier and quicker to track job 
Monster.com organize available jobs, making it easier and quicker to track job 
search among narrower groups. Researchers in many fi elds of economics have 
search among narrower groups. Researchers in many fi elds of economics have 
discovered the benefi ts of online data collection. Table 1 presents papers, each 
discovered the benefi ts of online data collection. Table 1 presents papers, each 
using online data, drawn from every top-level category in the 
using online data, drawn from every top-level category in the Journal of Economic 
Literature classifi cation system. Below, I turn to specifi c methods of online data 
classifi cation system. Below, I turn to specifi c methods of online data 
collection, with details on their respective applications as well as representative 
collection, with details on their respective applications as well as representative 
research using each method. 
research using each method. </p>

<p>Benjamin Edelman 191 </p>

<p>Table 1 
Diverse Papers Grounded in Online Data </p>

<p>History of Economic Thought 
Azar, Ofer H. 2007. "The Slowdown in First-Response Times of Economics Journals: Can it Be 
Benefi cial?" Economic Inquiry 45(1): 179-87. </p>

<p>Examines trends in the timing of journals' responses to submitted manuscript, collecting response 
time data from journals websites. 
Microeconomics 
Bajari, Patrick, and Ali Hortacsu. 2003. "The Winner's Curse, Reserve Prices, and Endogenous Entry: 
Empirical Insights from eBay Auctions." RAND Journal of Economics 34(2): 329-55. </p>

<p>Bid data from coin sales on eBay reveal bidder behavior in auctions, including the magnitude of the 
winner's curse. 
Macroeconomics and Monetary Economics 
Cavallo, Alberto. 2011. "Scraped Data and Sticky Prices." January 27. http://www.mit.edu/~afc 
/papers/Cavallo-Scraped.pdf. </p>

<p>Daily price data from online supermarkets reveal price adjustment and price stickiness. 
International Economics 
Philipp Maier. 2005. "A 'Global Village' without Borders? International Price Differentials at eBay." 
DNB Working Paper No. 044, De Nederlandsche Bank. </p>

<p>Purchases at eBay reveal differences in real prices between countries, including differences between 
countries without currency friction. 
Financial Economics 
Antweiler, Werner, and Murray Z. Frank. 2004. "Is All That Talk Just Noise? The Information Content of 
Internet Stock Message Boards." Journal of Finance 59(3): 1259-94. </p>

<p>Finds that online discussions help predict market volatility; effects on stock returns are statistically 
signifi cant but economically small. 
Public Economics 
Ellison, Glen, and Sara Fisher Ellison. 2009. "Tax Sensitivity and Home State Preferences in Internet 
Purchasing." American Economic Journal: Economic Policy 1(2): 53-71. </p>

<p>At a comparison shopping service, click patterns reveal users' efforts to avoid sales taxes. 
Health, Education, and Welfare 
Ginsberg, Jeremy, Matthew H. Mohebbi, Rajan S. Patel, Lynnette Brammer, Mark S. Smolinski, and 
Larry Brilliant. 2009. "Detecting Infl uenza Epidemics Using Search Engine Query Data." Nature, 
February 19, Volume 457(7232): 1012-14. </p>

<p>Trends in users' web searches identify infl uenza epidemics. 
Labor and Demographic Economics 
Edelman, Benjamin. Forthcoming. "Earnings and Ratings at Google Answers." Economic Inquiry. </p>

<p>Measures labor market outcomes in an online research service, including higher earnings for 
experience, fl exibility, and disfavored work schedules. 
Law and Economics 
Bhattacharjee, Sudip, Ram D. Gopal, Kaveepan Lertwachara, and James R. Marsden. 2006. "Impact of 
Legal Threats on Online Music Sharing Activity: An Analysis of Music Industry Legal Actions." Journal 
of Law and Economics 49(1): 91-114. </p>

<p>Observes the prevalence of users sharing music fi les via peer-to-peer networks, and analyzes users' 
response to an increased likelihood of litigation. 
Industrial Organization 
Chevalier Judith, and Austan Goolsbee. 2003. "Measuring Prices and Price Competition Online: 
Amazon.com vs. BarnesandNoble.com." Quantitative Marketing and Economics 1(2): 203-222. </p>

<p>Uses publicly available price and rank data to estimate demand elasticities at two leading sellers of 
online books, fi nding greater price sensitivity at Barnes &amp; Noble than at Amazon. </p>



<p>The Basics of Online Data Collection 
For a researcher seeking to collect data from the Internet, the simplest 
For a researcher seeking to collect data from the Internet, the simplest 
approach is typically a one-time collection of structured information from a single 
approach is typically a one-time collection of structured information from a single 
site. For example, Roth and Ockenfels (2002) retrieve data from about 480 eBay and 
site. For example, Roth and Ockenfels (2002) retrieve data from about 480 eBay and 
Amazon auctions, fi nding that Amazon's automatic extension of auction closing 
Amazon auctions, fi nding that Amazon's automatic extension of auction closing 
time obviated the incentive for late bidding (which was observed much more often 
time obviated the incentive for late bidding (which was observed much more often 
at eBay). Carlton and Chevalier (2001) retrieve data about prices of fragrances, 
at eBay). Carlton and Chevalier (2001) retrieve data about prices of fragrances, 
DVD players, and refrigerators from an array of retail sites to explore the relation-
DVD players, and refrigerators from an array of retail sites to explore the relation-
ship between retail promotion, online availability, and price dispersion. They fi nd 
ship between retail promotion, online availability, and price dispersion. They fi nd </p>

<p>Business Administration and Business Economics; Marketing; Accounting 
Brynjolfsson, Erik, Yu (Jeffrey) Hu, and Duncan Simester. 2011. "Goodbye Pareto Principle, Hello 
Long Tail: The Effect of Search Costs on the Concentration of Product Sales." Management Science 
57(8): 1373-86. </p>

<p>Data from an online clothing store show that the Internet reduces product search times and 
enables successful niche products. 
Economic History 
Michel, Jean-Baptiste, Yuan Kui Shen, Aviva Presser Aiden, Adrian Veres, Matthew K. Gray, The Google 
Books Team, Joseph P. Pickett, Dale Hoiberg, Dan Clancy, Peter Norvig, Jon Orwant, Steven Pinker, 
Martin A. Nowak, and Erez Lieberman Aiden. 2011. "Quantitative Analysis of Culture Using Millions of 
Digitized Books." Science, January 14, 331(6014): 176-82. </p>

<p>Analyzing approximately 4 percent of all books ever printed, as scanned by Google Books, the 
authors profi le changes in word choice and grammar, the duration of celebrity, and the problems of 
censorship and suppression. 
Economic Development, Technological Change, and Growth 
Seamans, Robert, and Feng Zhu. 2010. "Technology Shocks in Multi-Sided Markets: The Impact of 
Craigslist on Local Newspapers." NET Institute Working Paper 10-11. </p>

<p>Explores the response of local newspapers to entry by Craigslist, including increase in subscription 
price, decreasing advertising price, and decreasing classifi ed price. 
Economic Systems 
Hsieh, Chang-Tai, Edward Miguel, Daniel Ortega, and Francisco Rodríguez. 2011. "The Price of 
Political Opposition: Evidence from Venezuela's Maisanta." American Economic Journal: Applied 
Economics 3(2): 196-214. </p>

<p>Drawing on a "punishment list" published by Hugo Chavez, containing the names of people who 
signed a petition against him, this paper estimates the "price of political opposition"-the lost 
earnings of disfavored persons. 
Agricultural and Natural Resource Economics 
Camacho, Adriana, and Emily Conover. 2011. "The Impact of Receiving Price and Climate Information 
in the Agricultural Sector." IDB Working Paper IDB-WP-220. </p>

<p>Finds that farmers who received SMS (text message) information about price and weather had a 
narrower dispersion in expected price of their crops and a signifi cant reduction in crop loss. 
Urban, Rural, and Regional Economics 
Kroft, Kory, and Devin G. Pope. 2008. "Does Online Search Crowd Out Traditional Search and 
Improve Matching Effi ciency? Evidence from Craigslist." http://faculty.chicagobooth.edu/devin.pope 
/research/pdf/JPE_Final_with_fi gures.pdf. </p>

<p>Measures the number of Craigslist posts in metropolitan areas to observe Craigslist's effect on 
classifi ed ads, apartment and housing rental vacancy, and unemployment. </p>

<p>Table 1-continued </p>

<p>Using Internet Data for Economic Research 193 </p>

<p>that manufacturer websites tend to charge higher prices than retail websites, and 
that manufacturer websites tend to charge higher prices than retail websites, and 
that manufacturers who limit distribution of their product in the physical world also 
that manufacturers who limit distribution of their product in the physical world also 
tend to avoid having their product appear on websites that offer especially deep 
tend to avoid having their product appear on websites that offer especially deep 
discounts. Freedman and Jin (2011) retrieve data about lenders and borrowers at 
discounts. Freedman and Jin (2011) retrieve data about lenders and borrowers at 
the microfi nance person-to-person lending site Prosper.com, assessing the magni-
the microfi nance person-to-person lending site Prosper.com, assessing the magni-
tude of asymmetric information, efforts to mitigate information asymmetry, and 
tude of asymmetric information, efforts to mitigate information asymmetry, and 
pricing of risk. They fi nd that early lenders apparently did not understand the risks 
pricing of risk. They fi nd that early lenders apparently did not understand the risks 
involved, and as the lenders learned to evaluate these risks, high-risk borrowers 
involved, and as the lenders learned to evaluate these risks, high-risk borrowers 
found themselves unable to receive loans through this mechanism. 
found themselves unable to receive loans through this mechanism. 
Online data collection typically calls for a three-step procedure: A fi rst compo-
Online data collection typically calls for a three-step procedure: A fi rst compo-
nent retrieves web pages from a web server, often checking an input fi le for a list of 
nent retrieves web pages from a web server, often checking an input fi le for a list of 
pages to retrieve, terms to search for, or similar instructions. Next, a parser receives 
pages to retrieve, terms to search for, or similar instructions. Next, a parser receives 
web server replies and extracts the data elements of interest to the researcher, storing 
web server replies and extracts the data elements of interest to the researcher, storing 
this data in an output fi le. Finally, a researcher can use standard tools to import 
this data in an output fi le. Finally, a researcher can use standard tools to import 
and analyze the output fi le. Of course numerous refi nements on this approach are 
and analyze the output fi le. Of course numerous refi nements on this approach are 
possible, and subsequent sections present some of the variations. 
possible, and subsequent sections present some of the variations. 
Researchers can implement data collection systems in a number of program-
Researchers can implement data collection systems in a number of program-
ming languages. When demonstrating data collection in a classroom or assignment, 
ming languages. When demonstrating data collection in a classroom or assignment, 
I often offer <rs type="software">Visual Basic for Applications (VBA</rs>) code that stores data directly in 
I often offer Visual Basic for Applications (VBA) code that stores data directly in 
<rs type="software">Excel</rs>-letting Excel handle storage of both inputs and outputs. Figure 1 presents 
Excel-letting Excel handle storage of both inputs and outputs. Figure 1 presents 
sample code from this approach. For larger projects, researchers often choose Perl, 
sample code from this approach. For larger projects, researchers often choose Perl, 
PHP, or Python. 
PHP, or Python. </p>

<p>Long-Term Data Retrieval 
It is sometimes helpful to collect data over an extended period, which yields 
It is sometimes helpful to collect data over an extended period, which yields 
a larger sample as well as insight into changes over time. When data collection is 
a larger sample as well as insight into changes over time. When data collection is 
repeated periodically-a step that can be programmed to occur at preset time inter-
repeated periodically-a step that can be programmed to occur at preset time inter-
vals-a one-time script can be converted into a system for continued data retrieval. 
vals-a one-time script can be converted into a system for continued data retrieval. 
For example, Ellison and Ellison (2009) collect data on consumers making 
For example, Ellison and Ellison (2009) collect data on consumers making 
online purchases of computer memory modules. They examine hourly data over a 
online purchases of computer memory modules. They examine hourly data over a 
year, using the Pricewatch.com search engine, which displays lists of products being 
year, using the Pricewatch.com search engine, which displays lists of products being 
sold by participating online retailers at their own website. To measure users' incen-
sold by participating online retailers at their own website. To measure users' incen-
tive to buy from out-of-state online sellers (often thereby avoiding state sales tax), 
tive to buy from out-of-state online sellers (often thereby avoiding state sales tax), 
Ellison and Ellison need variation in users' choice sets to draw conclusions about 
Ellison and Ellison need variation in users' choice sets to draw conclusions about 
user preferences. Because choices change as online sellers adjust their prices, more-
user preferences. Because choices change as online sellers adjust their prices, more-
frequent data improves the power of the analysis. They fi nd that states with higher 
frequent data improves the power of the analysis. They fi nd that states with higher 
sales taxes for off-line purchases tend to have more online purchases-with buyers 
sales taxes for off-line purchases tend to have more online purchases-with buyers 
thereby often avoiding the state sales tax. 
thereby often avoiding the state sales tax. 
Long-term data collection can be particularly important for analysis of price 
Long-term data collection can be particularly important for analysis of price 
levels and infl ation. Cavallo (2011) collected daily prices of 80,000 supermarket 
levels and infl ation. Cavallo (2011) collected daily prices of 80,000 supermarket 
products taken from the public web pages of online retailers in four countries over 
products taken from the public web pages of online retailers in four countries over 
a period of three years. This price data is then used to explore patterns in price 
a period of three years. This price data is then used to explore patterns in price 
stickiness. Cavallo fi nds a bimodal pattern of price changes-that is, price changes 
stickiness. Cavallo fi nds a bimodal pattern of price changes-that is, price changes 
are signifi cantly positive or negative but few changes are close to zero, confi rming 
are signifi cantly positive or negative but few changes are close to zero, confi rming </p>



<p>Figure 1 
Sample Worksheet and Script for Basic Online Data Collection </p>

<p>A 
B 
1 
ISBN 
Rank 
2 
0300151241 
3 
0691143285 
4 
0195340671 </p>

<p>Sub GetAmazonDataDemo() 
'retrieves sales ranks from Amazon 
'INPUT: 
sheet1 column A --gives a list of ISBN-10 numbers 
'OUTPUT: 
sheet 1 column B --reports Amazon sales ranks </p>

<p>Dim curcell As Range, htmlresponse As String 'required variables </p>

<p>'iterate through rows of the fi rst column 
For Each curcell In ActiveWorkbook.Sheets("Sheet1").Range("A:A") 
'leave the loop when encounter a blank value in column A 
If curcell.Value = "" Then Exit For </p>

<p>'row 1 is the header row --don't do anything there 
If curcell.Row &gt; 1 Then 
'get Amazon product detail page with this ISBN 
htmlresponse = GetURL("http://www.amazon.com/o/ASIN/" &amp; Trim(curcell.Value)) </p>

<p>parse1 = GetBetween(htmlresponse, "Sales Rank:", " in") 
rankval = GetAfter(parse1, "#") </p>

<p>'store rank in column B 
curcell.Offset(0, 1).Value = rankval 
End If 
Next curcell 
'proceed to next row 
End Sub </p>

<p>Function GetURL(url) 
'INPUT: a URL to be retrieved 
'OUTPUT: the HTTP body at the specifi ed URL 
'REQUIREMENTS: 
a HTTP object: Winhttp, Xmlhttp, Winhttprequest, or Serverxmlhttp 
'ERROR HANDLING: 
none --should be added for production use! </p>

<p>On Error Resume Next 
Set objHTTP = CreateObject("WinHttp.WinHttpRequest.5.1") 
If objHTTP Is Nothing Then Set o = CreateObject("Microsoft.xmlhttp") 
If objHTTP Is Nothing Then Set o = CreateObject("winhttp.winhttprequest") 
If objHTTP Is Nothing Then Set o = CreateObject("MSXML2.ServerXMLHTTP") 
objHTTP.Open "GET", url, False 
objHTTP.send 
GetURL = objHTTP.responsetext 
End Function </p>

<p>Function GetBetween(s, s1, s2) 
'INPUT: s -string to search; 
s1 -string that marks start of retrieval 
s2 -string that marks end of retrieval 
'OUTPUT: the portion of s that comes strictly between s1 and s2 
'ERROR HANDLING: if s1 or s2 is not found, returns a blank string </p>

<p>p1 = InStr(s, s1) 
If p1 = 0 Then Exit Function 
's1 was not found 
p2 = InStr(p1 + Len(s1), s, s2) 
If p2 = 0 Then Exit Function 
's2 was not found 
GetBetween = Mid(s, p1 + Len(s1), p2 -p1 -Len(s1)) 
End Function </p>

<p>Function GetAfter(ByVal s As String, ByVal s1 As String) 
'INPUT: s -string to search; s1 -string that marks start of retrieval 
'OUTPUT: the portion of s that comes strictly after s1; if s1 is not found, all of s 
p1 = InStr(s, s1) 
If p1 = 0 Then GetAfter = s: Exit Function 
GetAfter = Mid(s, p1 + Len(s1), Len(s) -p1 -Len(s1) + 1) 
End Function </p>

<p>Benjamin Edelman 195 </p>

<p>the predictions of menu cost models. He also fi nds synchronization of prices for 
the predictions of menu cost models. He also fi nds synchronization of prices for 
goods that are close competitors within product categories. 
goods that are close competitors within product categories. </p>

<p>Multistep Data Retrieval 
More complex data retrieval systems can monitor multiple sources and adjust 
More complex data retrieval systems can monitor multiple sources and adjust 
their confi gurations based on what occurs. For example, in Edelman (2002), I use 
their confi gurations based on what occurs. For example, in Edelman (2002), I use 
a two-step process to measure the effects of recommendations by Amazon's edito-
a two-step process to measure the effects of recommendations by Amazon's edito-
rial staff. A fi rst system identifi es which books Amazon's editorial staff recommend, 
rial staff. A fi rst system identifi es which books Amazon's editorial staff recommend, 
running repeatedly to uncover new books soon after the recommendations begin. 
running repeatedly to uncover new books soon after the recommendations begin. 
Then a second system tracks the sales rank of each such book-allowing measure-
Then a second system tracks the sales rank of each such book-allowing measure-
ment of the sales increase attributable to Amazon's recommendation. This approach 
ment of the sales increase attributable to Amazon's recommendation. This approach 
allows examination of interaction between multiple economic actors, and if one set 
allows examination of interaction between multiple economic actors, and if one set 
of events is at least locally exogenous, this approach can identify causal effects. 
of events is at least locally exogenous, this approach can identify causal effects. 
To measure users' sharing on peer-to-peer networks, Bhattacharjee, Gopal, 
To measure users' sharing on peer-to-peer networks, Bhattacharjee, Gopal, 
Lertwachara, and Marsden (2006) also rely on a multistep collection process. A 
Lertwachara, and Marsden (2006) also rely on a multistep collection process. A 
fi rst system searches for randomly selected genres to retrieve a list of users sharing 
fi rst system searches for randomly selected genres to retrieve a list of users sharing 
music. For selected users, a second system then activates a "Find More From Same 
music. For selected users, a second system then activates a "Find More From Same 
User" function to retrieve information about the total number of songs that user 
User" function to retrieve information about the total number of songs that user 
is sharing. The authors collect weekly data for a year, yielding a measurement 
is sharing. The authors collect weekly data for a year, yielding a measurement 
of users' response to threatened litigation by the recording industry. Notably, 
of users' response to threatened litigation by the recording industry. Notably, 
Bhattacharjee et al. collect data not from sites presented to users in browsers such as 
Bhattacharjee et al. collect data not from sites presented to users in browsers such as 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> and <rs type="software">Firefox</rs>, but rather from <rs type="software">Kazaa</rs> and <rs type="software">WinMx</rs>, two fi le-sharing 
Internet Explorer and Firefox, but rather from Kazaa and WinMx, two fi le-sharing 
programs users can install on their computers. Data collection in this context calls 
programs users can install on their computers. Data collection in this context calls 
for scripting to operate programs' menus and buttons and to capture results from 
for scripting to operate programs' menus and buttons and to capture results from 
program windows. 
program windows. </p>

<p>Collecting Data from Secondary Sources 
For some purposes, researchers may fi nd it preferable to collect data from 
For some purposes, researchers may fi nd it preferable to collect data from 
aggregators that assemble data from multiple underlying sources. For example, 
aggregators that assemble data from multiple underlying sources. For example, 
Baye, Morgan, and Scholten (2004) examine retailers' prices at a comparison shop-
Baye, Morgan, and Scholten (2004) examine retailers' prices at a comparison shop-
ping service (a website that lists prices of selected items at multiple retailers) to 
ping service (a website that lists prices of selected items at multiple retailers) to 
measure the breadth of price dispersion. Baye, Morgan, and Scholten fi nd substan-
measure the breadth of price dispersion. Baye, Morgan, and Scholten fi nd substan-
tial price dispersion and little evidence of "the law of one price." 
tial price dispersion and little evidence of "the law of one price." 
For any researcher needing information about the history of a website-
For any researcher needing information about the history of a website-
whether on a one-off basis or for large-sample analysis-the Internet Archive is 
whether on a one-off basis or for large-sample analysis-the Internet Archive is 
the natural choice. With copies of 150 billion pages dating back to 1996 (Internet 
the natural choice. With copies of 150 billion pages dating back to 1996 (Internet 
Archive 2011), the Internet Archive provides no-charge access to prior versions of 
Archive 2011), the Internet Archive provides no-charge access to prior versions of 
most online materials, facilitating all manner of historic analysis. Seamans and Zhu 
most online materials, facilitating all manner of historic analysis. Seamans and Zhu 
(2010) use the <rs type="software">Internet Archive</rs> to gather historic data on <rs type="software">Craigslist</rs> postings to 
(2010) use the Internet Archive to gather historic data on Craigslist postings to 
explore relationships between the entry of Craigslist into a market and newspaper 
explore relationships between the entry of Craigslist into a market and newspaper 
circulation and pricing. 
circulation and pricing. 
While <rs type="software">Internet Archive</rs> preserves historic materials, certain secondary sources 
While Internet Archive preserves historic materials, certain secondary sources 
analyze and tabulate 
analyze and tabulate current user behavior. For example, <rs type="software">Google Trends</rs> reports 
user behavior. For example, Google Trends reports 
the frequency of particular searches at Google. Using Google Trends data, Choi 
the frequency of particular searches at Google. Using Google Trends data, Choi </p>



<p>and Varian (2009) predict future fi lings for unemployment benefi ts, fi nding an 
and Varian (2009) predict future fi lings for unemployment benefi ts, fi nding an 
improvement over offi cial government forecasts. Wu and Brynjolfsson (2009) use 
improvement over offi cial government forecasts. Wu and Brynjolfsson (2009) use 
Google searches to predict housing prices and sales, while Ginsberg, Mohebbi, 
Google searches to predict housing prices and sales, while Ginsberg, Mohebbi, 
Patel, Brammer, Smolinski, and Brilliant (2009) use data from Google searches to 
Patel, Brammer, Smolinski, and Brilliant (2009) use data from Google searches to 
detect infl uenza epidemics. 
detect infl uenza epidemics. </p>

<p>Web 2.0 Data Sources 
The term "Web 2.0" denotes the Internet's change from simple screens of 
The term "Web 2.0" denotes the Internet's change from simple screens of 
unchanging information to interactive communications in which users contribute 
unchanging information to interactive communications in which users contribute 
ever more content-often making sharply more information available to the 
ever more content-often making sharply more information available to the 
general public and to researchers. Facebook and Twitter are prominent examples 
general public and to researchers. Facebook and Twitter are prominent examples 
in this vein. 
in this vein. 
Researchers seeking to study activity at Facebook benefi t from default privacy 
Researchers seeking to study activity at Facebook benefi t from default privacy 
settings that let the general public view each user's name, friends, networks, 
settings that let the general public view each user's name, friends, networks, 
wall posts, photos, likes, and more. The resulting data can facilitate research on 
wall posts, photos, likes, and more. The resulting data can facilitate research on 
myriad topics. For example, Baker, Mayer, and Puller (2011) use Facebook to 
myriad topics. For example, Baker, Mayer, and Puller (2011) use <rs type="software">Facebook</rs> to 
assess the diversity effects of randomized dormitory assignment. They fi nd that 
assess the diversity effects of randomized dormitory assignment. They fi nd that 
students randomly exposed to persons of a different race have more friends of 
students randomly exposed to persons of a different race have more friends of 
that race within the dormitory, but no greater diversity in social networks outside 
that race within the dormitory, but no greater diversity in social networks outside 
that environment. 
that environment. 
Iyengar, Han, and Gupta (2009) look at data from Cyworld, a social 
Iyengar, Han, and Gupta (2009) look at data from <rs type="software">Cyworld</rs>, a social 
networking site in Korea, in which users often decorate their mini-homepages 
networking site in Korea, in which users often decorate their mini-homepages 
with items like wallpaper or music purchased from Cyworld. Using 10 weeks of 
with items like wallpaper or music purchased from Cyworld. Using 10 weeks of 
purchase and nonpurchase data from 208 users, they identify a low-status group 
purchase and nonpurchase data from 208 users, they identify a low-status group 
that is not affected by the purchases of others; a medium-status group that has a 
that is not affected by the purchases of others; a medium-status group that has a 
positive correlation with the purchases of others; and a high-status group that has 
positive correlation with the purchases of others; and a high-status group that has 
a negative correlation with the purchases of others. Acquisti and Gross (2006) 
a negative correlation with the purchases of others. Acquisti and Gross (2006) 
examine demographic and behavioral differences in users' views of privacy. They 
examine demographic and behavioral differences in users' views of privacy. They 
fi nd that privacy concerns expressed in survey results did not seem to limit which 
fi nd that privacy concerns expressed in survey results did not seem to limit which 
people joined Facebook nor how much information they revealed-in part, 
people joined Facebook nor how much information they revealed-in part, 
because those who joined did not fully understand what data was public. Default 
because those who joined did not fully understand what data was public. Default 
privacy settings at the short-message service <rs type="software">Twitter</rs> also facilitate research: with 
privacy settings at the short-message service Twitter also facilitate research: with 
few exceptions, Twitter messages are public, and Twitter also publishes the list of 
few exceptions, Twitter messages are public, and Twitter also publishes the list of 
all authors each Twitter user is "following." While few researchers have embraced 
all authors each Twitter user is "following." While few researchers have embraced 
Twitter data, Vincent and Armstrong (2010) assess high-frequency trading strate-
Twitter data, Vincent and Armstrong (2010) assess high-frequency trading strate-
gies grounded in messages on Twitter, fi nding a profi t opportunity in fast-breaking 
gies grounded in messages on Twitter, fi nding a profi t opportunity in fast-breaking 
Twitter discussions. 
Twitter discussions. 
The Internet's newest services also facilitate research on users' views of 
The Internet's newest services also facilitate research on users' views of 
companies and organizations. Every company and organization page on Facebook 
companies and organizations. Every company and organization page on Facebook 
includes a "like" button, and Facebook, Google, and others now let sites present 
includes a "like" button, and Facebook, Google, and others now let sites present 
"like," " 
"like," "+ +1," and similar buttons to garner user endorsements. The number and/or 
1," and similar buttons to garner user endorsements. The number and/or 
identity of users clicking these buttons is often available to researchers and the 
identity of users clicking these buttons is often available to researchers and the 
interested public-facilitating research about trends and trendsetters, reaction to 
interested public-facilitating research about trends and trendsetters, reaction to 
news, and more. 
news, and more. </p>

<p>Using Internet Data for Economic Research 197 </p>

<p>Monitoring Network Activity 
The computer science literature features papers that analyze users' network 
The computer science literature features papers that analyze users' network 
traffi c to draw conclusions about online activity. For example, Saroiu, Gribble, 
traffi c to draw conclusions about online activity. For example, Saroiu, Gribble, 
and Levy (2004) monitor the online activity of students at a university to identify 
and Levy (2004) monitor the online activity of students at a university to identify 
computers infected with "spyware"-software like <rs type="software">Gator</rs>, <rs type="software">Cydoor</rs>, <rs type="software">SaveNow</rs>, and 
computers infected with "spyware"-software like Gator, Cydoor, SaveNow, and 
<rs type="software">eZula</rs> that gathers information about computer use and relays it to a third party, 
eZula that gathers information about computer use and relays it to a third party, 
often without the consent (or informed consent) of the computer user. The authors 
often without the consent (or informed consent) of the computer user. The authors 
monitor infections to identify types of users and behaviors particularly likely to 
monitor infections to identify types of users and behaviors particularly likely to 
suffer from spyware. Karagiannis, Broido, Brownless, claffy, and Faloutsos (2004) 
suffer from spyware. Karagiannis, Broido, Brownless, claffy, and Faloutsos (2004) 
observe network activity at two Internet service providers to measure the prevalence 
observe network activity at two Internet service providers to measure the prevalence 
of peer-to-peer fi le-sharing software, fi nding that contrary to a common belief at 
of peer-to-peer fi le-sharing software, fi nding that contrary to a common belief at 
that time, peer-to-peer fi le sharing was not declining in response to concerns over 
that time, peer-to-peer fi le sharing was not declining in response to concerns over 
its legality, but was in fact continuing to increase. In principle, economists could use 
its legality, but was in fact continuing to increase. In principle, economists could use 
similar methods. As Saroiu, Gribble, and Levy (2004) and Karagiannis et al. (2004) 
similar methods. As Saroiu, Gribble, and Levy (2004) and Karagiannis et al. (2004) 
demonstrate, network monitoring systems are notable for the breadth of data they 
demonstrate, network monitoring systems are notable for the breadth of data they 
can observe-in principle, every online activity of users on the corresponding 
can observe-in principle, every online activity of users on the corresponding 
networks. They are also notable for their ability to collect data no individual site 
networks. They are also notable for their ability to collect data no individual site 
can, or cares to, assemble. 
can, or cares to, assemble. 
On a larger scale, commercial services analyze network traffi c to identify trends 
On a larger scale, commercial services analyze network traffi c to identify trends 
in user behavior and site popularity. Best known is comScore (2011), which offers a 
in user behavior and site popularity. Best known is comScore (2011), which offers a 
two-million member panel of users recruited to install tracking software that moni-
two-million member panel of users recruited to install tracking software that moni-
tors their browsing, purchasing, and other online activities. Compete offers a similar 
tors their browsing, purchasing, and other online activities. Compete offers a similar 
service, also via a panel of participating users, while Hitwise collects data from both 
service, also via a panel of participating users, while Hitwise collects data from both 
users and Internet service providers. 
users and Internet service providers. </p>

<p>What Types of Data are Abundant or Scarce? 
Online data collection projects tend to reveal certain data far more readily 
Online data collection projects tend to reveal certain data far more readily 
than others. For example, researchers seeking prices are easily satisfi ed; myriad sites 
than others. For example, researchers seeking prices are easily satisfi ed; myriad sites 
post product price information as they offer items for purchase. But a researcher 
post product price information as they offer items for purchase. But a researcher 
needing sales quantities faces greater diffi culty: while a few sites, most notably eBay, 
needing sales quantities faces greater diffi culty: while a few sites, most notably eBay, 
post substantial information about each sale, most sites have no business need to 
post substantial information about each sale, most sites have no business need to 
distribute sales information systematically and publicly. 
distribute sales information systematically and publicly. 
Work-arounds can yield quantity data. Some sites report the quantity of in-stock 
Work-arounds can yield quantity data. Some sites report the quantity of in-stock 
inventory available for each listed product. Slow decreases in this quantity are typi-
inventory available for each listed product. Slow decreases in this quantity are typi-
cally interpreted as indicating items sold. Large increases are understood to refl ect 
cally interpreted as indicating items sold. Large increases are understood to refl ect 
arrival of additional inventory. By checking suffi ciently frequently, a researcher can 
arrival of additional inventory. By checking suffi ciently frequently, a researcher can 
infer purchases. 
infer purchases. 
Other sites report sales ranks, which offer insight into sales quantities. Best 
Other sites report sales ranks, which offer insight into sales quantities. Best 
known in this area is Amazon, where many an author diligently tracks sales rank. 
known in this area is Amazon, where many an author diligently tracks sales rank. 
Chevalier and Goolsbee (2003) pioneered procedures for converting Amazon 
Chevalier and Goolsbee (2003) pioneered procedures for converting Amazon 
sales ranks to sales quantities using multiple methods including cross-checks with 
sales ranks to sales quantities using multiple methods including cross-checks with 
publishers (who report that a given sales rank in a given week matches a given 
publishers (who report that a given sales rank in a given week matches a given 
quantity), controlled experiments (purchasing and/or returning a given quantity 
quantity), controlled experiments (purchasing and/or returning a given quantity 
of books and monitoring changes in rank), and fi tting a portion of the distribution 
of books and monitoring changes in rank), and fi tting a portion of the distribution </p>



<p>using publicly known sales quantities (for example, for bestsellers whose sales are 
using publicly known sales quantities (for example, for bestsellers whose sales are 
occasionally revealed to the public). Depending on available data, these approaches 
occasionally revealed to the public). Depending on available data, these approaches 
can be u sed to extract quantities from other ranking systems. 
can be u sed to extract quantities from other ranking systems. 
In certain contexts, researchers may be able to infer useful information about 
In certain contexts, researchers may be able to infer useful information about 
sales from other materials that are posted at sites, such as "top sellers," "recom-
sales from other materials that are posted at sites, such as "top sellers," "recom-
mended items," or "people who bought this also bought . . ." suggestions. However, 
mended items," or "people who bought this also bought . . ." suggestions. However, 
such methods are not yet well developed. 
such methods are not yet well developed. </p>

<p>Data Requiring Company or Site Cooperation 
While the preceding sections identify data that researchers can collect directly 
While the preceding sections identify data that researchers can collect directly 
from websites, some research questions require data that sites decline to publish to 
from websites, some research questions require data that sites decline to publish to 
the public. In this context, it has proven fruitful to request additional data from the 
the public. In this context, it has proven fruitful to request additional data from the 
companies and organizations that run such sites. For example, Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and 
companies and organizations that run such sites. For example, Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and 
Ariely (2010) obtained records from an online dating site revealing all aspects of users' 
Ariely (2010) obtained records from an online dating site revealing all aspects of users' 
activities, including browsing, viewing photos, and sending and receiving messages. 
activities, including browsing, viewing photos, and sending and receiving messages. 
This data is necessary for Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and Ariely's evaluation of the quality of 
This data is necessary for Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and Ariely's evaluation of the quality of 
users' matches; they fi nd that at the dating site, "the actual matches are approximately 
users' matches; they fi nd that at the dating site, "the actual matches are approximately 
effi cient." Data providers are often concerned about distribution of their internal 
effi cient." Data providers are often concerned about distribution of their internal 
records. Below, I discuss methods to address such concerns and protect privacy. 
records. Below, I discuss methods to address such concerns and protect privacy. </p>

<p>Online Experiments </p>

<p>Scraping the web for existing data can raise concerns about whether observed 
Scraping the web for existing data can raise concerns about whether observed 
changes can be treated as exogenous or endogenous. After all, when users and sites 
changes can be treated as exogenous or endogenous. After all, when users and sites 
make decisions based on changing external circumstances to advance their respec-
make decisions based on changing external circumstances to advance their respec-
tive objectives, it can be diffi cult to draw inferences about what factor caused what 
tive objectives, it can be diffi cult to draw inferences about what factor caused what 
outcome. An experimental method can yield better insight into causation. Online 
outcome. An experimental method can yield better insight into causation. Online 
experiments can also observe long-run behavior changes, whereas most short-run 
experiments can also observe long-run behavior changes, whereas most short-run 
experiments risk overemphasizing short-run substitution effects. 
experiments risk overemphasizing short-run substitution effects. 
In the taxonomy of List (2011) in this journal, online experiments can take 
In the taxonomy of List (2011) in this journal, online experiments can take 
four forms: "Natural experiments" arise from exogenous changes created by third 
four forms: "Natural experiments" arise from exogenous changes created by third 
parties (or nature) that mimic the conditions of an experiment. "Laboratory experi-
parties (or nature) that mimic the conditions of an experiment. "Laboratory experi-
ments" place the agents in an artifi cial game-like setting to see how they react. "Field 
ments" place the agents in an artifi cial game-like setting to see how they react. "Field 
experiments" present agents with randomized variation in conditions-changes 
experiments" present agents with randomized variation in conditions-changes 
agents experience while carrying out their usual online activities in their homes 
agents experience while carrying out their usual online activities in their homes 
or at work, though they are aware that an experiment is being conducted. Finally, 
or at work, though they are aware that an experiment is being conducted. Finally, 
"natural fi eld experiments" present agents with randomized variation in natural 
"natural fi eld experiments" present agents with randomized variation in natural 
settings without informing agents that they are involved in an experiment. 
settings without informing agents that they are involved in an experiment. </p>

<p>Natural Experiments 
Sometimes, a site or service changes design parameters arbitrarily or in a time 
Sometimes, a site or service changes design parameters arbitrarily or in a time 
or manner unlikely to be correlated with other outcomes. Such circumstances can 
or manner unlikely to be correlated with other outcomes. Such circumstances can 
create a natural experiment yielding insight into lines of causation. 
create a natural experiment yielding insight into lines of causation. </p>

<p>Benjamin Edelman 199 </p>

<p>For example, Roth and Ockenfels (2002) point out that system designers set 
For example, Roth and Ockenfels (2002) point out that system designers set 
the ending rules for <rs type="software">eBay</rs> and <rs type="software">Amazon</rs> auctions without consideration of implica-
the ending rules for eBay and Amazon auctions without consideration of implica-
tions for bidder behavior. Thus, these sites provide a reasonable context to assess 
tions for bidder behavior. Thus, these sites provide a reasonable context to assess 
the effect of such rules. At the time of their study, eBay auctions closed at a fi xed 
the effect of such rules. At the time of their study, eBay auctions closed at a fi xed 
time, while Amazon auctions continued until ten minutes had gone by without a 
time, while Amazon auctions continued until ten minutes had gone by without a 
bid. Bidders reacted to such rules, submitting a higher fraction of late bids on eBay. 
bid. Bidders reacted to such rules, submitting a higher fraction of late bids on eBay. 
Other exogenous variation comes from unexpected changes. For example, 
Other exogenous variation comes from unexpected changes. For example, 
Miller (2011) relies on a large increase in the amount of information available about 
Miller (2011) relies on a large increase in the amount of information available about 
borrowers on <rs type="software">Prosper.com</rs>, a change which made lenders more selective among 
borrowers on Prosper.com, a change which made lenders more selective among 
high-risk borrowers. Chiou and Tucker (2011) note a 2009-2010 dispute between 
high-risk borrowers. Chiou and Tucker (2011) note a 2009-2010 dispute between 
Google and Associated Press that led to the temporary removal of AP stories from 
Google and Associated Press that led to the temporary removal of AP stories from 
<rs type="software">Google News</rs> (which aggregates news content from many sources). During that 
Google News (which aggregates news content from many sources). During that 
period, Google News referred fewer users to 
period, Google News referred fewer users to all traditional news sites, compared to 
traditional news sites, compared to 
other news aggregators that continued to host AP articles. 
other news aggregators that continued to host AP articles. </p>

<p>Researcher-Designed Experiments 
Some researchers participate in online markets in order to build what are, in 
Some researchers participate in online markets in order to build what are, in 
essence, online fi eld experiments. For example, Hossain and Morgan (2006) list 
essence, online fi eld experiments. For example, Hossain and Morgan (2006) list 
items on eBay with varying listing prices and shipping prices, showing that users 
items on eBay with varying listing prices and shipping prices, showing that users 
undervalue shipping cost relative to item price. By varying reserve policies in list-
undervalue shipping cost relative to item price. By varying reserve policies in list-
ings at <rs type="software">eBay</rs>, Katkar and Reiley (2006) fi nd that secret reserve prices deter bidder 
ings at eBay, Katkar and Reiley (2006) fi nd that secret reserve prices deter bidder 
entry and reduce the likelihood of a listing resulting in a sale. Resnick, Zeckhauser, 
entry and reduce the likelihood of a listing resulting in a sale. Resnick, Zeckhauser, 
Swanson, and Lockwood (2006) auction matched pairs of items on eBay, some 
Swanson, and Lockwood (2006) auction matched pairs of items on eBay, some 
using a seller's well-established identity and others using new identities, thereby 
using a seller's well-established identity and others using new identities, thereby 
identifying the willingness of buyers to pay for seller reputation. 
identifying the willingness of buyers to pay for seller reputation. 
Many companies have recognized the benefi t of experiments in improving 
Many companies have recognized the benefi t of experiments in improving 
their own operations. For example, online marketers test dozens of alternative 
their own operations. For example, online marketers test dozens of alternative 
advertisements. Tools like <rs type="software">Optimizely</rs> and Visual Website Optimizer let a designer 
advertisements. Tools like Optimizely and <rs type="software">Visual Website Optimizer</rs> let a designer 
evaluate user behavior in multiple variants of a site-testing alternative layout, color, 
evaluate user behavior in multiple variants of a site-testing alternative layout, color, 
text, and more. Varian (2010) discusses the benefi ts Google has achieved through 
text, and more. Varian (2010) discusses the benefi ts Google has achieved through 
comprehensive experiments to evaluate possible changes to its services. 
comprehensive experiments to evaluate possible changes to its services. 
In lieu of a researcher running experiments, Einav, Kuchler, Levin, and 
In lieu of a researcher running experiments, Einav, Kuchler, Levin, and 
Sundaresan (2011) fl ag the possibility of a researcher identifying experiments others 
Sundaresan (2011) fl ag the possibility of a researcher identifying experiments others 
are already running. If an <rs type="software">eBay</rs> seller is testing variations in item listing (perhaps 
are already running. If an eBay seller is testing variations in item listing (perhaps 
which format, description, or pricing achieves the highest price), a researcher can 
which format, description, or pricing achieves the highest price), a researcher can 
fi nd these variations, retrieve data about both the experimenter's changes and the 
fi nd these variations, retrieve data about both the experimenter's changes and the 
public's response, and thereby draw conclusions about the effect of the changes at 
public's response, and thereby draw conclusions about the effect of the changes at 
issue. Einav et al. fi nd that of the 100 million listings on eBay each day, more than half 
issue. Einav et al. fi nd that of the 100 million listings on eBay each day, more than half 
will reappear on the site, often with differing parameters for the sale. Assembling 
will reappear on the site, often with differing parameters for the sale. Assembling 
a dataset with hundreds of thousands of such matching pairs during a single year, 
a dataset with hundreds of thousands of such matching pairs during a single year, 
these authors examine questions about price dispersion, bidding under different 
these authors examine questions about price dispersion, bidding under different 
sets of rules, and customers' reaction to shipping fees. Practitioners' experiments 
sets of rules, and customers' reaction to shipping fees. Practitioners' experiments 
can offer a vastly larger sample than researcher-implemented experiments-in turn, 
can offer a vastly larger sample than researcher-implemented experiments-in turn, 
yielding more precise estimates. Practitioners' experiments also often occur across 
yielding more precise estimates. Practitioners' experiments also often occur across </p>



<p>product categories, whereas practical concerns often limit researcher-implemented 
product categories, whereas practical concerns often limit researcher-implemented 
experiments to narrow categories, impeding inferences about other areas. 
experiments to narrow categories, impeding inferences about other areas. </p>

<p>Experiments in Partnership with a Company or Site 
Some kinds of online fi eld experiments tend to require cooperation from a 
Some kinds of online fi eld experiments tend to require cooperation from a 
company or site operator. For example, Chen, Harper, Konstan, and Li (2010) look 
company or site operator. For example, Chen, Harper, Konstan, and Li (2010) look 
at <rs type="software">MovieLens</rs>, an online site that offers recommendations for movies. Submitting 
at MovieLens, an online site that offers recommendations for movies. Submitting 
movie recommendations is a public good-benefi ting all other users of the site, 
movie recommendations is a public good-benefi ting all other users of the site, 
at some cost to the specifi c user who makes time to contribute. Many movies had 
at some cost to the specifi c user who makes time to contribute. Many movies had 
too few recommendations for the software to match them with potential users, but 
too few recommendations for the software to match them with potential users, but 
Chen et al. fi nd that when MovieLens subscribers are informed of their standing 
Chen et al. fi nd that when MovieLens subscribers are informed of their standing 
in terms of how many recommendations they make relative to other users, they 
in terms of how many recommendations they make relative to other users, they 
tend to contribute more recommendations. Chen et al. partnered with Movielens in 
tend to contribute more recommendations. Chen et al. partnered with Movielens in 
order to provide such notifi cations to a random set of users. Online advertising has 
order to provide such notifi cations to a random set of users. Online advertising has 
proven particularly well suited to experiments with company cooperation. Reiley, 
proven particularly well suited to experiments with company cooperation. Reiley, 
Li, and Lewis (2010) change the number of advertisements presented at the top of 
Li, and Lewis (2010) change the number of advertisements presented at the top of 
the page at an Internet search engine, fi nding that when more such advertisements 
the page at an Internet search engine, fi nding that when more such advertisements 
are presented, users click more often on the top-most advertisement. Ostrovsky and 
are presented, users click more often on the top-most advertisement. Ostrovsky and 
Schwarz (2011) adjust reserve prices in <rs type="software">Yahoo</rs>! auctions for online advertisements, 
Schwarz (2011) adjust reserve prices in Yahoo! auctions for online advertisements, 
fi nding large revenue increases when reserve prices are set optimally. 
fi nding large revenue increases when reserve prices are set optimally. 
With additional technical complexity, researchers may be able to conduct 
With additional technical complexity, researchers may be able to conduct 
experiments entailing modifi cation of a website even without participation by or 
experiments entailing modifi cation of a website even without participation by or 
cooperation from that site. In Edelman and Gilchrist (2010), my coauthor and I 
cooperation from that site. In Edelman and Gilchrist (2010), my coauthor and I 
build a proxy that presents some users with modifi ed search result pages showing 
build a proxy that presents some users with modifi ed search result pages showing 
hypothetical alternative advertisement labels: in place of the usual "sponsored link" 
hypothetical alternative advertisement labels: in place of the usual "sponsored link" 
or "ad" labels, some users instead saw labels reading "paid advertisement." Users 
or "ad" labels, some users instead saw labels reading "paid advertisement." Users 
with low education or little online experience benefi t most from the "paid adver-
with low education or little online experience benefi t most from the "paid adver-
tisement" label, which the Federal Trade Commission has sought in other media. 
tisement" label, which the Federal Trade Commission has sought in other media. 
Similarly, Schechter, Dhamija, Ozment, and Fischer (2007) present varying secu-
Similarly, Schechter, Dhamija, Ozment, and Fischer (2007) present varying secu-
rity warnings as users attempt to access online banking applications, fi nding that 
rity warnings as users attempt to access online banking applications, fi nding that 
few users recognize the warnings intended to fl ag possible attacks. They also fl ag 
few users recognize the warnings intended to fl ag possible attacks. They also fl ag 
the importance of realistic experimental conditions: users who participated in the 
the importance of realistic experimental conditions: users who participated in the 
experiments as role players were far less concerned with security than those who 
experiments as role players were far less concerned with security than those who 
used their own actual passwords. 
used their own actual passwords. </p>

<p>Online Lab Experiments 
Online experiments can address many of the questions historically explored 
Online experiments can address many of the questions historically explored 
in real-world economics laboratories. For example, Horton, Rand, and Zeckhauser 
in real-world economics laboratories. For example, Horton, Rand, and Zeckhauser 
(2011) replicate three classic lab experiments in an online lab: the extent of coop-
(2011) replicate three classic lab experiments in an online lab: the extent of coop-
eration in a one-shot prisoners' dilemma game; playing the prisoners' dilemma 
eration in a one-shot prisoners' dilemma game; playing the prisoners' dilemma 
game after being "primed" by reading various religious or nonreligious texts (which 
game after being "primed" by reading various religious or nonreligious texts (which 
tends to reduce rates of defection); and testing the "framing" result of Kahneman 
tends to reduce rates of defection); and testing the "framing" result of Kahneman 
and Tversky(1979) that choices will differ depending on how questions are framed, 
and Tversky(1979) that choices will differ depending on how questions are framed, 
because people are risk averse in the domain of gains but risk seeking as to losses. 
because people are risk averse in the domain of gains but risk seeking as to losses. </p>

<p>Using Internet Data for Economic Research 201 </p>

<p>Horton, Rand, and Zeckhauser also conducted a natural fi eld experiment in which 
Horton, Rand, and Zeckhauser also conducted a natural fi eld experiment in which 
subjects were offered the opportunity to be paid to transcribe a simple passage of 
subjects were offered the opportunity to be paid to transcribe a simple passage of 
text in return for a compensation that had been randomly determined-demon-
text in return for a compensation that had been randomly determined-demon-
strating an upward-sloping supply of labor. Mason and Suri (2011) argue that online 
strating an upward-sloping supply of labor. Mason and Suri (2011) argue that online 
lab experiments using Mechanical Turk (which allows hiring people anywhere in 
lab experiments using Mechanical Turk (which allows hiring people anywhere in 
the world to carry out tasks that can be performed online) can offer important 
the world to carry out tasks that can be performed online) can offer important 
benefi ts over traditional laboratory experiments, including easier access to a large 
benefi ts over traditional laboratory experiments, including easier access to a large 
and diverse subject pool, low cost, and faster deployment of new experiments. 
and diverse subject pool, low cost, and faster deployment of new experiments. 
Online lab experiments also present potential downfalls. As in physical 
Online lab experiments also present potential downfalls. As in physical 
economics laboratories, participants who sign up to participate are unlikely to be 
economics laboratories, participants who sign up to participate are unlikely to be 
representative of the population as a whole, and their differences might be corre-
representative of the population as a whole, and their differences might be corre-
lated with some treatments. Online subjects can exit a study more readily than 
lated with some treatments. Online subjects can exit a study more readily than 
subjects in a lab, which may be a concern if certain treatments disproportionately 
subjects in a lab, which may be a concern if certain treatments disproportionately 
prompt early exit. Communication between online subjects may be possible, both 
prompt early exit. Communication between online subjects may be possible, both 
during an experiment and between experiments, depending on a researcher's 
during an experiment and between experiments, depending on a researcher's 
method of recruiting subjects. To deter communication among subjects, Horton, 
method of recruiting subjects. To deter communication among subjects, Horton, 
Rand, and Zeckhauser (2011) suggest running online experiments quickly and 
Rand, and Zeckhauser (2011) suggest running online experiments quickly and 
avoiding notoriety. 
avoiding notoriety. 
If researchers so choose, online experiments can blur the boundaries between 
If researchers so choose, online experiments can blur the boundaries between 
the lab and the fi eld. For example, Centola (2010) builds an online social network 
the lab and the fi eld. For example, Centola (2010) builds an online social network 
where participants can see the health behaviors of selected other participants 
where participants can see the health behaviors of selected other participants 
assigned to be their "health buddies." From one perspective, this appears to be a 
assigned to be their "health buddies." From one perspective, this appears to be a 
natural fi eld experiment: users participate from home or work, for an extended 
natural fi eld experiment: users participate from home or work, for an extended 
period, not knowing that they are subject to randomized variation in an academic 
period, not knowing that they are subject to randomized variation in an academic 
research project. Yet participants are interacting in an environment constructed 
research project. Yet participants are interacting in an environment constructed 
from scratch specifi cally for research purposes. Just as designers of a lab experiment 
from scratch specifi cally for research purposes. Just as designers of a lab experiment 
design the rules of their system, Centola controlled most aspects of what partici-
design the rules of their system, Centola controlled most aspects of what partici-
pants could see, say, and do. With the right design, online experiments may be able 
pants could see, say, and do. With the right design, online experiments may be able 
to combine positive aspects of lab and fi eld experiments. 
to combine positive aspects of lab and fi eld experiments. </p>

<p>Limits to Internet-Based Data Collection </p>

<p>Terms of Use and Similar Restrictions 
Most websites present a "Terms of Use" or similar document that purports to 
Most websites present a "Terms of Use" or similar document that purports to 
restrict the methods and purposes of data access. Such statements are widespread; 
restrict the methods and purposes of data access. Such statements are widespread; 
for example, Amazon, eBay, and Google all include provisions stating that users 
for example, Amazon, eBay, and Google all include provisions stating that users 
must not copy data from their sites. A series of court cases hold that such agree-
must not copy data from their sites. A series of court cases hold that such agree-
ments are enforceable against competitors seeking to copy data for reasons courts 
ments are enforceable against competitors seeking to copy data for reasons courts 
view as improper. For example, in 
view as improper. For example, in eBay vs. Bidders' Edge (100 F.Supp.2d 1058 [N.D. 
(100 F.Supp.2d 1058 [N.D. 
Cal. 2000]), Bidders' Edge sought to copy eBay data to build an auction aggrega-
Cal. 2000]), Bidders' Edge sought to copy eBay data to build an auction aggrega-
tion service-a service which, if successful, would have undercut eBay's competitive 
tion service-a service which, if successful, would have undercut eBay's competitive 
advantage. eBay could therefore offer a cogent notion of harm-not just a few extra 
advantage. eBay could therefore offer a cogent notion of harm-not just a few extra 
requests for its web server to answer, but a genuine business loss. 
requests for its web server to answer, but a genuine business loss. </p>



<p>In contrast, researchers are far less disruptive to the site whose data is being 
In contrast, researchers are far less disruptive to the site whose data is being 
copied. For example, researchers' activities are usually limited to analyzing data but 
copied. For example, researchers' activities are usually limited to analyzing data but 
not republishing or redistributing-and certainly not reselling-the information 
not republishing or redistributing-and certainly not reselling-the information 
they collect. Furthermore, most researchers access online data that sites produce 
they collect. Furthermore, most researchers access online data that sites produce 
and distribute incidental to other activity, and researchers' activities do not inter-
and distribute incidental to other activity, and researchers' activities do not inter-
fere with sites' core business models. In this context, researchers typically perceive 
fere with sites' core business models. In this context, researchers typically perceive 
that they have strong defenses to any claims that data providers might bring. Finally, 
that they have strong defenses to any claims that data providers might bring. Finally, 
for lack of an urgent business harm, a target site is less likely to press the point. 
for lack of an urgent business harm, a target site is less likely to press the point. 
In practice, sites most often respond to researchers' activities not by fi ling 
In practice, sites most often respond to researchers' activities not by fi ling 
lawsuits, but by blocking access from computers that send too many requests. Seeing 
lawsuits, but by blocking access from computers that send too many requests. Seeing 
many requests from a single IP address (roughly, a single computer), it is usually 
many requests from a single IP address (roughly, a single computer), it is usually 
straightforward for a site to confi gure its web server to deny further requests from 
straightforward for a site to confi gure its web server to deny further requests from 
that computer. Such a blockage often suffi ces to prompt a researcher to scale back 
that computer. Such a blockage often suffi ces to prompt a researcher to scale back 
data collection. That said, many researchers nonetheless continue requesting data 
data collection. That said, many researchers nonetheless continue requesting data 
even after a blockage-for example, using a different computer or a different IP 
even after a blockage-for example, using a different computer or a different IP 
address. Excessive requests could slow access by others and invite further bans, 
address. Excessive requests could slow access by others and invite further bans, 
but most researchers' data requirements can be adequately addressed using a data 
but most researchers' data requirements can be adequately addressed using a data 
collection system that operates at a rate similar to an ordinary user, sending perhaps 
collection system that operates at a rate similar to an ordinary user, sending perhaps 
one request every few seconds. 
one request every few seconds. 
To date, to the best of my knowledge, no data provider has fi led suit against 
To date, to the best of my knowledge, no data provider has fi led suit against 
a researcher collecting data that is available, in smaller quantities, to the general 
a researcher collecting data that is available, in smaller quantities, to the general 
public without charge. Of course a researcher facing notable problems-perhaps 
public without charge. Of course a researcher facing notable problems-perhaps 
accessing data that is otherwise made available only under a paid license-might do 
accessing data that is otherwise made available only under a paid license-might do 
well to seek guidance from a qualifi ed attorney. 
well to seek guidance from a qualifi ed attorney. </p>

<p>Privacy and Confi dentiality 
A researcher collecting online data must also consider privacy concerns. 
A researcher collecting online data must also consider privacy concerns. 
If collecting data about individuals, a researcher should consult the appropriate 
If collecting data about individuals, a researcher should consult the appropriate 
human subjects committee. That said, many human subjects committees will readily 
human subjects committee. That said, many human subjects committees will readily 
give the researcher permission for an online data collection project to proceed 
give the researcher permission for an online data collection project to proceed 
quickly and without conditions. In particular, human subject committees often give 
quickly and without conditions. In particular, human subject committees often give 
blanket permission or even waivers for studies that involve observation of public 
blanket permission or even waivers for studies that involve observation of public 
behavior, analysis of existing data, and gathering information in a way that that 
behavior, analysis of existing data, and gathering information in a way that that 
presents minimal risk to subjects. 
presents minimal risk to subjects. 
When collecting data from a secure or semisecure site or when analyzing 
When collecting data from a secure or semisecure site or when analyzing 
company data or other internal data, researchers may want to shield themselves 
company data or other internal data, researchers may want to shield themselves 
from user-specifi c data. Sometimes, researchers need not even receive sensitive 
from user-specifi c data. Sometimes, researchers need not even receive sensitive 
information. For example, when Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and Ariely (2010) analyzed user 
information. For example, when Hitsch, Hortaçsu, and Ariely (2010) analyzed user 
behavior at a dating website, they analyzed user data that contained no names, 
behavior at a dating website, they analyzed user data that contained no names, 
contact information, or images. But other research requires at least limited analysis 
contact information, or images. But other research requires at least limited analysis 
of sensitive information or data derived from sensitive information. For example, 
of sensitive information or data derived from sensitive information. For example, 
Ian Larkin and I analyzed working paper downloads at the SSRN (Social Science 
Ian Larkin and I analyzed working paper downloads at the SSRN (Social Science 
Research Network) website to investigate whether the numbers were being "gamed" 
Research Network) website to investigate whether the numbers were being "gamed" 
by authors downloading their own papers repeatedly to increase reported download 
by authors downloading their own papers repeatedly to increase reported download </p>

<p>Benjamin Edelman 203 </p>

<p>counts. In doing this analysis, we did not want to see the names of the authors 
counts. In doing this analysis, we did not want to see the names of the authors 
whose papers were most downloaded in circumstances suggesting gaming, but 
whose papers were most downloaded in circumstances suggesting gaming, but 
we did seek to analyze relationships between gaming and authors' professional 
we did seek to analyze relationships between gaming and authors' professional 
standing, coauthors, and peers. To limit data in this way, we kept author names in 
standing, coauthors, and peers. To limit data in this way, we kept author names in 
a restricted table with limited access rights. When we needed analysis of authors' 
a restricted table with limited access rights. When we needed analysis of authors' 
resumes and biographical information, we provided our research assistants with 
resumes and biographical information, we provided our research assistants with 
access to authors' names, but our assistants could not view information about paper 
access to authors' names, but our assistants could not view information about paper 
downloads, and they did not know the purpose of our study. These procedures 
downloads, and they did not know the purpose of our study. These procedures 
prevented anyone, including us, from connecting particular download data to a 
prevented anyone, including us, from connecting particular download data to a 
particular author. We found limited evidence of gaming due to demographic factors 
particular author. We found limited evidence of gaming due to demographic factors 
and career concerns, but strong evidence of gaming driven by social comparisons 
and career concerns, but strong evidence of gaming driven by social comparisons 
with various peer groups (Edelman and Larkin 2009). 
with various peer groups (Edelman and Larkin 2009). 
When requesting data from companies, additional protections can help address 
When requesting data from companies, additional protections can help address 
concerns about confi dentiality and about the possibility of readers uncovering 
concerns about confi dentiality and about the possibility of readers uncovering 
company identity. It is routine to describe a corporate data source in general terms 
company identity. It is routine to describe a corporate data source in general terms 
(like sector and approximate size) but to decline to name the specifi c company. 
(like sector and approximate size) but to decline to name the specifi c company. 
But creative researchers can do more to protect data details. For example, when 
But creative researchers can do more to protect data details. For example, when 
analyzing effectiveness of an online advertising campaign performed by Yahoo! and 
analyzing effectiveness of an online advertising campaign performed by Yahoo! and 
a major retailer, Lewis and Reiley (2011) created a database of over one million 
a major retailer, Lewis and Reiley (2011) created a database of over one million 
customers matched in the databases of the two companies. However, they then 
customers matched in the databases of the two companies. However, they then 
hired an outside vendor to render the data anonymous by merging together all of 
hired an outside vendor to render the data anonymous by merging together all of 
the personally-identifying information about users' online and offl ine activities. In 
the personally-identifying information about users' online and offl ine activities. In 
addition, the vendor multiplied actual sales amounts by an undisclosed number 
addition, the vendor multiplied actual sales amounts by an undisclosed number 
between 0.1 and 10-preventing readers, or even the researchers, from learning 
between 0.1 and 10-preventing readers, or even the researchers, from learning 
the true amount of the company's advertising costs, incremental revenue, or other 
the true amount of the company's advertising costs, incremental revenue, or other 
dollar fi gures. 
dollar fi gures. 
Even data not intended to identify individuals may prove easily linked to 
Even data not intended to identify individuals may prove easily linked to 
specifi c persons. For example, in 2006 AOL's research division posted search data 
specifi c persons. For example, in 2006 AOL's research division posted search data 
from 650,000 users-a dataset AOL intended to offer for academic research by 
from 650,000 users-a dataset AOL intended to offer for academic research by 
anyone interested. AOL believed users' privacy was adequately protected because 
anyone interested. AOL believed users' privacy was adequately protected because 
AOL published only users' search requests, not their names, usernames, or e-mail 
AOL published only users' search requests, not their names, usernames, or e-mail 
addresses. But some users could be identifi ed from their unusual searches-
addresses. But some users could be identifi ed from their unusual searches-
including searches for their own names, value of their homes, and the like (Barbaro 
including searches for their own names, value of their homes, and the like (Barbaro 
and Zeller 2006). Indeed, even a narrow range of possibilities for users' Social Secu-
and Zeller 2006). Indeed, even a narrow range of possibilities for users' Social Secu-
rity numbers can be inferred based on birthplace and date of birth, which are often 
rity numbers can be inferred based on birthplace and date of birth, which are often 
publicly available (Acquisti and Gross 2009). With re-identifi cation of individuals 
publicly available (Acquisti and Gross 2009). With re-identifi cation of individuals 
possible in unexpected circumstances, protecting privacy requires careful planning 
possible in unexpected circumstances, protecting privacy requires careful planning 
and ongoing vigilance. 
and ongoing vigilance. </p>

<p>Opportunities </p>

<p>Opportunities for research using the Internet expand every year. New sites 
Opportunities for research using the Internet expand every year. New sites 
and services collect and retain ever more data, while mobile devices collect data 
and services collect and retain ever more data, while mobile devices collect data </p>



<p>even more widely. Sites and users have been remarkably willing to share much of 
even more widely. Sites and users have been remarkably willing to share much of 
their data with anyone interested, and the opportunities for economic research 
their data with anyone interested, and the opportunities for economic research 
are limited primarily by researcher time and creativity. Furthermore, with certain 
are limited primarily by researcher time and creativity. Furthermore, with certain 
kinds of data increasingly widely available, future researchers may be able to repli-
kinds of data increasingly widely available, future researchers may be able to repli-
cate results with similar methods and different datasets rather than using different 
cate results with similar methods and different datasets rather than using different 
methods on the same sections. 
methods on the same sections. 
Meanwhile, in the realm of experiments, online data offers advances on ques-
Meanwhile, in the realm of experiments, online data offers advances on ques-
tions of exogeneity and identifi cation. A website design change is often plausibly 
tions of exogeneity and identifi cation. A website design change is often plausibly 
exogenous, whereas real-world events like government policies are typically corre-
exogenous, whereas real-world events like government policies are typically corre-
lated with other events. Online systems also make it particularly easy-and, in some 
lated with other events. Online systems also make it particularly easy-and, in some 
contexts, increasingly routine-for different users to receive different treatments 
contexts, increasingly routine-for different users to receive different treatments 
on a widespread and ongoing basis. These circumstances combine the identifi cation 
on a widespread and ongoing basis. These circumstances combine the identifi cation 
offered by experiments with the realism of naturally occurring data-potentially 
offered by experiments with the realism of naturally occurring data-potentially 
giving researchers the best of both methodologies. 
giving researchers the best of both methodologies. </p>

<p>■ ■ I thank Paul Kominers and Xiaoxiao Wu for excellent research assistance. </p>



<p>Using Internet Data for Economic Research 205 </p>







<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



</text></tei>