<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fjems.12141" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:07+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The lion's share of retail traffic through search engines originates from organic (natural) rather 
than sponsored (paid) links. We use a dataset constructed from over 12,000 search terms and 
2 million users to identify drivers of the organic clicks that the top 759 retailers received from search 
engines in August 2012. Our results are potentially important for search engine optimization 
(SEO). We find that a retailer's investments in factors such as the quality and brand awareness 
of its site increases organic clicks through both a direct and an indirect effect. The direct effect 
stems purely from consumer behavior: The higher the quality of an online retailer, the greater the 
number of consumers who click its link rather than a competitor in the list of organic results. 
The indirect effect stems from our finding that search engines tend to place higher quality sites in 
better positions, which results in additional clicks because consumers tend to click links in more 
favorable positions. We also find that consumers who are older, wealthier, conduct searches from 
work, use fewer words, or include a brand name product in their search are more likely to click a 
retailer's organic link following a product search. Finally, the quality of a retailer's site appears 
to be especially important in attracting organic traffic from individuals with higher incomes. The 
beneficial direct and indirect effects of an online retailer's brand equity on organic clicks, coupled </p>

<p>We thank the editor and two referees for helpful comments, and 7 </p>

<p>with the spillover effects on traffic through other online and traditional channels, leads us to 
conclude that investments in the quality and brand awareness of a site should be included as part 
of an SEO strategy. </p>

<p>Search engines are an important way of obtaining information on the Internet. According 
to Alexa Traffic Rank, Google.com is the most popular web site in the United States 
as well as in the world, and in May 2011, it was the first web site to achieve one 
billion monthly unique visitors. 
1 Many people use search engines as a starting point for 
navigating the Web, making search engines a crucial link in connecting content providers 
and users. This has spurred a sizable literature on search marketing that studies clicking 
behavior at search engines. To date, most of this literature has concentrated on the 
sponsored links that are typically displayed alongside organic links when consumers 
conduct searches. 
Although most of the economics and marketing literature on search engines has 
focused on paid clicks, the bulk of the traffic retailers receive through search engines 
is actually through unpaid clicks on organic links (Jerath et al., 2014). 
2 For this reason, 
more advertisers engage in search engine optimization (SEO) to improve organic clicks 
than purchase sponsored links to get paid clicks (Berman and Katona, 2013). To the 
best of our knowledge, the present paper is the first to provide search marketers with 
information on drivers of organic clicks to aid in SEO. 
Existing studies of sponsored search are typically based on a modest number of 
search terms and the corresponding number of paid clicks received by a single retailer. 
Our research complements these studies by focusing on the organic clicks that 759 retail 
sites received from more than 12,000 search terms. There is considerable cross-sectional 
variation in our data: It includes Web-only retailers as well as traditional retailers and 
covers 15 different retail segments including apparel, electronics, and mass merchants. 
For each of these search terms, we observe which retail sites received organic clicks as 
well as the number of clicks. We also obtained data from the first five pages of search 
results on <rs type="software">Google</rs> and <rs type="software">Bing</rs> for each search term, and this ultimately permits us to 
quantify the impact on organic clicks of a site's rank (position) in the search results. 
Our data also include several different measures of the accumulated brand equity of 
online retailers. These data allow us to determine whether consumers are more likely 
to click the link of a retailer who is perceived to operate a high-quality site (as a result 
of the retailer's current and past investments in advertising, the depth and breadth of 
offerings, secure payments, one-click purchases, returns policies, and so on). Ultimately, 
this permits us to quantify the benefits of SEO strategies that attempt to gain traffic by 
improving a retailer's rank in organic search results, versus gaining traffic by improving 
the quality and brand awareness of a site. 
Not surprisingly, we find that a retailer's rank on a results page is an important 
driver of its organic clicks: Exclusion from the first five pages of results for a search leads 
to a 90% reduction in organic clicks. For retailers that are listed on the first five pages of 
results, a 1% improvement in rank leads to 1.3% more organic clicks for that search. </p>

<p>1. <rs type="software">Alexa Traffic Rank</rs> is calculated by combining a web site's average number of daily visitors and page 
views over the past month. 
2. Our data are consistent with this finding. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Importantly, however, we also find that the brand equity of an online retailer is an 
important driver of organic clicks and that it is easy for search marketers to overlook the 
benefits of including investments in the quality and brand awareness of its site as part of 
an SEO strategy. The direct benefit of these and other investments in brand equity is an 
increase in the number of consumers clicking one retailer's link instead of a competing 
link on results pages. Moreover, investments in brand equity have an additional indirect 
effect: Search engines tend to place retailers with stronger brands in better positions, 
which results in additional increases in organic clicks. Finally, estimated effects of rank 
on organic clicks are keyword specific, whereas improvements in the brand equity of an 
online retailer increases clicks associated with all relevant searches. Taking all of these 
effects into account, we find that brand equity is as important as rank in determining 
organic clicks. 
We also point out that investments that improve site quality and consumer aware-
ness (and more broadly, that enhance an online retailer's brand equity) are likely to have 
spillover benefits in other channels that are not accounted for in this or other studies of 
organic and sponsored search. These benefits include increases in clicks through other 
online channels (such as price comparison sites), increases in the number of direct visits 
to a retailer's web site, increases in visits through navigational searches at search engines, 
and increases in traffic at the retailer's physical stores. These considerations-coupled 
with the fact that position is a zero-sum game and thus a retailer is unlikely to obtain a 
sustainable advantage through direct efforts to improve its ranking-lead us to conclude 
that brand equity is one of the more important components of retailers' SEO strategies. 
We also find that a retail site's brand equity is especially important in attracting 
organic traffic from individuals with higher incomes. Our results indicate that consumers 
who are older, wealthier, conduct searches from work, use fewer words, or include a 
brand-name product in their search are more likely to click a retailer's organic link 
following a product search. 
The remainder of this section provides an overview of SEO and the related litera-
ture. Section 2 discusses our data and describes the econometric methodology underly-
ing our analysis. Section 3 presents our empirical findings, whereas Section 4 provides 
robustness checks and some additional results. Finally, we conclude in Section 5 with 
some additional managerial implications of our findings for SEO. </p>

<p>1.1. Search Engine Optimization </p>

<p>Figure 1 highlights the avenues that retailers have for gaining traffic through search 
engines. This screenshot shows the search results that appear following a search for 
"shoes online" using <rs type="software">Google Search</rs>. In this particular example, three different types of 
links appear: top ads, side ads, and organic results. 
3 The top ads (marked by the red 
box in Figure 1), if any, are the highest listed search results and appear against a yellow 
background. For this particular search there are three top ads; the maximum number of 
top ads that may be displayed is four. The organic results (marked by the blue box) are 
listed below the top ads. Up to ten organic results can appear on a search result page. 
Finally, the side ads (purple box) appear on the right-hand side of the screen; Google 
allows for up to eight side ads to be shown on a result page. </p>

<p>3. Depending on the search term, up to four bottom ads may appear as well. For the search term "shoes 
online" no bottom ads were shown. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>FIGURE 1. SEARCH RESULTS </p>

<p>One way retailers obtain traffic is through the paid links that appear in top or side 
ads. Unlike organic links, retailers can directly influence the position of ads, which are 
displayed and ranked according to the results of an auction that is run in real time. 
Retailers identify keywords they want to bid on and specify how much they are willing 
to spend. <rs type="software">Google</rs> determines the ad rank using a site's maximum bid specified for 
the keyword and a quality score, which includes factors like click-through rates and 
relevance. Advertisers only pay when the link is clicked; the cost per click is equal to the 
minimum amount needed to get a specific position (generalized second-price auction 
mechanism). There is an extensive literature (discussed below) examining this avenue 
for obtaining clicks. 
A second way retailers obtain traffic through the search engine channel is through 
clicks on organic results, and this is the focus of our analysis. 
4 A site's position in <rs type="software">Google's</rs> 
organic search results depends on the site's relevance to a given search term. The exact </p>

<p>4. Although our main focus is on organic (non-paid) links, we do take the presence of sponsored links 
(ads) into account, because they may affect organic clicking behavior. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>algorithm that Google uses to determine a site's ranking is proprietary; according to 
Google, it depends on thousands of factors. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Although the goal of SEO is to optimize the organic traffic a retailer receives through 
product searches on search engines, the ultimate goal of retailers is presumably to 
maximize their profits. One of the initial steps in this optimization process is identifying 
the benefits and costs of different strategies for increasing traffic. 
6 Our paper represents 
a first attempt to examine the benefits side of the ledger, and in particular, to quantify 
the drivers of retailers' organic clicks. 
The first, and most common, SEO strategy is to tweak a site in an attempt to 
increase the rank of a retailer's organic link on the results pages for a given search term. 
The presumption is that higher ranks result in more organic clicks, but SEO requires 
quantifying the effects of rank on clicks. This is one objective of our paper. 
One myopic tactic for improving position, known as a "black-hat" strategy, is 
designed to "trick" search engines into elevating a retailer's rank in the results. Search 
engines are themselves players, and have incentives to adapt algorithms to ensure that 
search engine users receive relevant results. Consumers are players too, and may favor 
links of retailers they know and trust: SEO strategies that focus exclusively on rank 
(such as spamming links or hiding keywords) might improve the position of a retailer's 
link but not impact its clicks. For this reason, SEO strategies based on "tricking" or 
"spamming" engines are unlikely to yield sustainable improvements in rankings, may 
not result in additional clicks, and can even backfire as a result of negative effects on 
reputation. Furthermore, it is important to recognize that rankings are effectively a zero-
sum game: One retailer can move up on a particular results page only by pushing down 
the link of another retailer. Thus, although it makes sense for online retailers to ensure 
that their sites include page titles that accurately describe content, make use of head 
tags, are free of dead links, and so on, these efforts alone are unlikely to give a particular 
retailer a sustainable rank advantage because other retailers have incentives to engage 
in these strategies as well. 
A second and more costly SEO strategy-but one that is more likely to yield 
sustainable improvements in a retailer's organic traffic from search engines-focuses on 
improving site quality and brand awareness, or more broadly on enhancing the online 
retailer's brand equity (which embodies current and past investments in advertising, 
service and return policies, depth and breadth of offerings, prices, etc.). This strategy 
recognizes that consumers tend to click retailers that are more recognized, trusted, have 
reputations for providing value (in terms of prices, product depth or breadth), service 
(well-designed web sites, return policies, secure payment systems), and so on. This 
SEO strategy is alluded to by Google, which advises businesses to base "...optimization 
decisions first and foremost on what's best for the visitors of your site. They're the main 
consumers of your content and are using search engines to find your work. Focusing 
too hard on specific tweaks to gain ranking in the organic results of search engines may 
not deliver the desired results." </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Although it may be tempting to dichotomize rank-improving and brand-building 
SEO strategies, these two strategies are not mutually exclusive. Indeed, brand-building </p>

<p>5. See http://www.google.com/explanation.html. One of these factors is Google PageRank, which is an 
algorithm that uses the number of incoming links to measure the relative importance of a web site. 
6. SEO is based on the premise that more clicks translates into more sales, thus making organic clicks a 
useful intermediate metric. 
7. See Google's Search Engine Optimization Starter Guide, 2013, p. 2. A link to this guide is available online 
at http://support.google.com/webmasters/bin/answer.py?hl=en&amp;answer=35291 </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>activities may indirectly result in better positions. Furthermore, unlike direct invest-
ments in position, brand-building investments are not a perfect zero-sum game because 
consumers always have an option not to click on any organic search results. For exam-
ple, some consumers using the search phrase "tennis shoes" might not recognize any 
retailers in the list of search results, and hence not click on any links. If these retailers 
all invest in the brand awareness of their sites, they each may receive additional clicks 
because consumers are less likely to exercise the outside option. </p>

<p>1.2. Related Literature </p>

<p>Our paper is connected to several different literatures, including a handful of academic 
papers on SEO which provide important theoretical insights into SEO (Sen, 2005; Xing 
and Lin, 2006; Berman and Katona, 2013). These papers highlight several features of the 
equilibrium interaction between web sites and search engines that we take into account 
in our empirical analysis, including the endogeneity of the rank of organic links and the 
position of sponsored links in search results. To the best of our knowledge, there is no 
antecedent empirical research on SEO. 
There is, however, a sizeable theoretical and empirical literature on search engines 
that focuses on the sponsored links that appear alongside the organic results. The theo-
retical literature has in particular focused on the auction mechanism behind these paid 
results (e.g., Edelman et al., 2007; Varian, 2007). Earlier studies took user behavior as 
given; more recent work by Chen and He (2011) as well as Athey and Ellison (2012) 
take into account that users search optimally. White (2013) and Xu et al. (2012) focus on 
trade-offs between organic and sponsored search results. 
The empirical research on search engines has mostly focused on sponsored search 
as well. Yao and Mela (2011) develop a dynamic structural model of keyword advertising 
that takes optimal consumer behavior into account. Animesh et al. (2010) focus on quality 
uncertainty in sponsored search markets and find some evidence of adverse selection, 
but only for unregulated sponsored search markets. Ghose and Yang (2009) focus on 
ad placement and its effects on profitability and find a negative relationship between 
position and click-through rate as well as conversion rates. Agarwal et al. (2011) also 
find a negative relationship between position and click-through rates but find a positive 
relationship with conversion rates, which means that the top position is not necessarily 
the most profitable. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Our paper is also related to three recent papers that focus on the relationship 
between sponsored and organic search results. Yang and Ghose (2010) find organic clicks 
to be positively related to the presence of sponsored links, and vice versa. However, the 
presence of an organic link increases the utility of a sponsored listing more than the other 
way around. Similarly, Agarwal et al. (2015) find the presence of a link in the organic 
search results to be positively related to the click-through rate for sponsored links, but 
negatively related to conversions. A third paper by Jerath et al. (2014) uses clicks data 
based on 120 keywords to examine how the "popularity" of different keywords impacts 
clicking behavior. Their results suggest that less popular keywords are "more targetable" 
for sponsored search advertising than more popular keywords. </p>

<p>8. Other contributions to the literature on sponsored search include Jeziorski and Segal (2015) and Blake 
et al. (2015), among others. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Finally, our research is related to a very large literature documenting the impor-
tance of screen position and a seller's reputation or brand equity 
9 for retailers selling 
through other online channels including price comparison sites, shopbots, and auction 
sites (Brynjolfsson and Smith, 2000; Melnik and Alm, 2002; Dellarocas, 2003; Baye and 
Morgan, 2009; Baye et al., 2009; De los Santos et al., 2012). Although the broad message 
is that branding, screen position, consumer attributes, and retailer characteristics are 
all important determinants of click-through behavior in these channels, to date, little is 
known about their impact on organic clicks through search engines. </p>

<p>2. Data Description and Econometric Model </p>

<p>2.1. Data Description </p>

<p>Our main dataset is assembled using data from <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">comScore</rs> <rs id="software-3" type="software">Search Planner</rs> and contains 
information on the number of organic clicks web sites received for search terms and 
phrases entered at main search engines (i.e., <rs type="software">Google</rs>, <rs type="software">Bing</rs>, <rs type="software">Yahoo</rs>, <rs type="software">AOL</rs>, and <rs type="software">ASK</rs>) 
during August 2012. <rs type="software">Search Planner</rs> uses the comScore panel, which contains all online 
browsing activity of around two million U.S. users. Because our goal is to analyze the 
drivers of organic traffic following product searches, we restrict our sample to only 
include web sites that are Internet retailers. For this we make use of Internet Retailer's 
Top 500 Guide, which contains a ranking of North America's 500 largest e-retailers 
based on annual Web sales. Although not all of these retailers appeared in the comScore 
Search Planner database, some e-retailers (e.g., Amazon) operate multiple web sites 
(e.g., Amazon.com and Zappos.com), resulting in a total of 759 retail sites for which 
we have click-through data. For each of these 759 retailers, we used Search Planner to 
identify all search terms that generated traffic from <rs type="software">Google</rs> to the retailer. There is some 
overlap in search terms: as shown in Figure 1, Onlineshoes.com as well as Zappos.com 
appear relatively high in the organic results for the term "shoes online," which means 
that for both retailers this term is part of the set of search terms that generated traffic 
from Google. In total we end up with 12,184 distinct search terms that led users to the 
759 online retailers. The third dataset we use contains all the links that appeared on the 
first five search results pages on <rs type="software">Google Search</rs> and Bing Search for each of the 12,184 
search phrases. We collected these data using a scraper written in <rs type="software">Java</rs>; the data contain 
organic search results as well as paid links. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Not all 759 online retailers are relevant for each of the search terms in our data. 
For instance, Best Buy is not relevant for individuals searching for shoes and is therefore </p>

<p>9. Aaker (1991) defines brand equity as "a set of brand assets and liabilities linked to a brand, its name 
and symbol, that add to or subtract from the value provided by a product or service to a firm and/or to that 
firm's customers." Brand equity is based on factors like brand loyalty, name awareness, and quality. See Keller 
and Lehmann (2006) for a recent survey of the branding literature. 
10. Given the time required to query Bing and Google with the 12,184 search terms, our Java program 
retrieved position results only once. Given the intervening time between clicks and the collection of rank data, 
two potential issues arise: (a) endogeneity of position, which we address in Section 2.2, and (b) the stability of 
ranks over time. The limited data we have suggest that ranks for product searches are likely to be fairly stable 
over the relatively short window of time that is at issue here. For example, an examination of rank data we 
collected for two different projects reveals that, for the 3,599 overlapping observations in these two datasets, 
the (pooled) correlation between each firm's rank for searches conducted in July 2012 with its rank for the 
searches conducted in September 2012 is 0.80. Although we do not have more frequent (e.g., daily or weekly) 
data on ranks, the relatively high correlation in ranks over this 2-month period suggests that ranks are likely 
to be reasonably stable within the span of a single month. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>unlikely to show up in the search results for "shoes online." 
11 Given that a retail site 
must be listed on the search results pages to receive organic clicks, we only include a 
retailer as an observation for a specific search term if we observe the retail site in our 
search results data. Because we only captured the first five pages of search results, this 
does not rule out that a site that did not appear in these search results did in fact get 
clicks; we therefore also include a retail site if the site received organic clicks for the 
search term according to the Search Planner database. 
Our measure of a retail site's brand equity is based on the methodology devel-
oped in Baye et al. (2012) to overcome challenges in measuring the "prominence" of 
online retailers' names. These authors point out that the standard approach, which uses 
historical advertising data to measure accumulated brand equity and the strength of 
a firm's name, is not useful in the case of online retailers. Among other things, many 
online retailers are privately held and do not disclose advertising expenditures; the 
parent companies of publically traded online retailers do not typically report monthly 
advertising expenditures at the URL level. They further argue that the number of prod-
uct searches on <rs type="software">Google</rs> (or <rs type="software">Bing</rs>) that include the retailer's name or URL in the search 
query-navigational searches, in industry parlance-is a useful measure of a retailer's 
brand equity. Intuitively, the inclusion of "Amazon" in a product search indicates the 
consumer recognizes the company and can recall its name. This may be the result of 
past advertising campaigns, recommendations from friends, knowledge of Amazon's 
pricing practices, product depth, return policies, and so on. And in contrast to adver-
tising expenditures, it is possible to use data from comScore to measure the number of 
navigational searches Amazon received in a given month. 
Based on a revealed preference argument, Baye et al. conclude that the number of 
navigational searches for a retailer in a given month embodies more than name recog-
nition or recall; the inclusion of a retailer's name in a product search indicates that the 
consumer values the attributes associated with its name (e.g., its reputation, product 
breadth, product depth, and service quality), and that search results with links to that 
particular retailer are desirable. Baye et al. provide evidence that this measure works 
well in both retail and education contexts. 
12 For example, they show that there is a 
strong relationship between navigational searches for universities and external rank-
ings of their quality: Universities with stronger brand names (e.g., Harvard University) 
receive significantly more navigational searches than universities with weaker brand 
names (e.g., Indiana University). Moreover, they provide evidence that the prestige of a 
university-not its size-is the main driver of the navigational searches it receives. 
For these reasons, we use navigational searches to measure a firm's brand equity. 
Navigational searches are essentially a shortcut for typing in the URL of a specific retailer 
and then searching its site. Thus, our measure of brand equity is the total number of 
organic clicks a particular retailer received in August 2012 from searchers who navigated </p>

<p>11. Indeed, Best Buy did not show up in at least the first 30 pages of search results on <rs type="software">Google</rs> for the search 
term "shoes online" (checked on February 26, 2013). 
12. Although many of the general branding principles carry over to retailers, the measurement of retail 
brand equity provides some unique challenges; Ailawadi and Keller (2004) identify some unique issues to the 
measurement of retail brand equity. For our purposes, the key is that this measure is related to the overall 
image of an online retailer and its attributes, which includes factors like name recognition, product breadth 
and depth, shopping experience, and reputation (prices, quality, shipping, return policy, etc.). </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>to its site by including the retailer's name as a search term, including misspellings; 
examples include "Amazon," "Amazn," and "Buy camera at Amazon." </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Although we use navigational searches to construct our measure of brand equity, 
our dependent variable excludes organic clicks from navigational searches. We seek to 
understand why searchers choose to click on Amazon (or some other link) following a 
non-navigational search like "Levis Jeans," and not why they click on an Amazon link 
following a navigational search like "Amazon." Thus, in our econometric analysis of 
organic clicks, we exclude all search terms (and hence organic clicks based on searches) 
containing the name of one of the 759 retail sites. This results in 40,117 observations, 
where each observation is the number of clicks for each search term-retailer. 
In addition to the number of organic clicks per retail site, the Search Planner data 
also contain information on the demographics of searchers using each of the search terms, 
including the percentage of searchers by age, income, and location (home or work). We 
also used data from Internet Retailer's Top 500 Guide to identify each retailer's retail 
segment (e.g., mass merchant, apparel and accessories, sporting goods, etc.), whether the 
retailer has a presence on social media (Facebook or Twitter), the year in which the retail 
site began operating online, and whether the retailer has a brick-and-mortar presence. 
Table I provides summary statistics of these variables, as well as the other variables we 
use in our analysis. 
Finally, we analyzed each search term and constructed search-term specific vari-
ables based on the content of the search term. The first variable is the number of words 
in the search term. The second variable, denoted branded search term, is an indicator 
variable for whether the search terms include the brand name of a product (e.g., Nike or 
Adidas) in the product search. Note that, in our sample, this is different from the brand 
associated with a particular retailer's site (e.g., Zappos or Amazon). These two search-
term specific variables may tell us something about the intent of search. For instance, an 
individual searching for "Nike running shoes" is more specific in what she is looking 
for than someone searching for "shoes online," and this may affect clicking behavior. </p>

<p>2.2. Econometric Model </p>

<p>Our main objective is to study the drivers of organic clicks arising from searches for 
products on search engines. 
14 Let Clicks ik denote the total number of organic clicks 
retailer i received from individuals searching for search term k. Because of the presence 
of substantial positive skewness in organic clicks data, we use a log-normal regression 
model to analyze the relationship between organic clicks and the explanatory variables, 
that is, </p>

<p>ln(Clicks ik ) = γ 0 + γ 1 (RNO ik ) + γ 2 ln(Ra nk ik ) + γ 3 Sponsor ed ik + γ 4 ln(BE i ) </p>

<p>+γ 5 X ik + ε ik , 
( 1 ) </p>

<p>13. Baye et al. (2012) show that the utility of this measure is invariant to whether one uses a narrow 
definition of a navigational search (e.g., "Amazon" ) or this broader measure that includes both the retailer's 
name and product-related (e.g., "Buy camera at Amazon"). 
14. As a referee notes, clicks for some search terms may be more valuable (in terms of conversions, margins, 
or other performance measures) than others. Our focus here is on clicks; unfortunately, our data do not permit 
us to examine the differential effects of rank and other variables on these alternative measures of retailer 
performance. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>Table I. 
Descriptive Statistics (N = 40,117) </p>

<p>Variable 
Mean 
Std. Dev. 
Min 
Max </p>

<p>Google Related Data 
Organic clicks 
2,039 
10,809 
0 
752,296 
Brand Equity (thousands) 
3,412 
5,746 
0 
18,000 
Rank 
20.480 
17.564 
1 
52 
Rank not observed 
0.114 
0.317 
0 
1 
Sponsored Link on first page 
0.311 
0.463 
0 
1 
Bing Related Data 
Rank 
35.895 
20.652 
1 
52 
Rank not observed 
0.574 
0.494 
0 
1 
Sponsored Link on first page 
0.064 
0.244 
0 
1 
Alexa Related Data 
Sites Linking In (thousands) 
186 
395 
0 
1,183 
Demographics 
Age 18-24 
0.097 
0.166 
0 
1 
Age 25-34 
0.176 
0.220 
0 
1 
Age 35-44 
0.213 
0.235 
0 
1 
Age 45-54 
0.252 
0.249 
0 
1 
Age 55-64 
0.157 
0.219 
0 
1 
Age 65+ 
0.105 
0.186 
0 
1 
Income &lt;25k 
0.168 
0.218 
0 
1 
Income 25-50k 
0.217 
0.232 
0 
1 
Income 50-75k 
0.211 
0.231 
0 
1 
Income 75-100k 
0.153 
0.207 
0 
1 
Income &gt;100k 
0.251 
0.271 
0 
1 
Home 
0.792 
0.278 
0 
1 
Children 
0.649 
0.291 
0 
1 
Search Term Characteristics 
Branded Search Term 
0.141 
0.348 
0 
1 
Number of words 
2.367 
1.025 
1 
12 
Retailer Characteristics 
Social network presence 
0.944 
0.230 
0 
1 
Site age 
13.710 
2.827 
2 
24 
Web only retailer 
0.323 
0.468 
0 
1 
Retail Segment 
Apparel/accessories 
0.217 
0.412 
0 
1 
Automotive parts/accessories 
0.006 
0.075 
0 
1 
Books/music/video 
0.020 
0.139 
0 
1 
Computers/electronics 
0.128 
0.334 
0 
1 
Flowers/gifts 
0.005 
0.070 
0 
1 
Food/drug 
0.012 
0.110 
0 
1 
Hardware/home improvement 
0.042 
0.201 
0 
1 
Health/beauty 
0.022 
0.148 
0 
1 
Housewares/home furnishings 
0.032 
0.176 
0 
1 
Jewelry 
0.005 
0.074 
0 
1 
Mass merchant 
0.363 
0.481 
0 
1 
Office supplies 
0.019 
0.136 
0 
1 
Specialty/non-apparel 
0.054 
0.225 
0 
1 
Sporting Goods 
0.047 
0.211 
0 
1 
Toys/hobbies 
0.028 
0.166 
0 
1 </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>where RNO ik (short for rank not observed) is a dummy variable that equals 1 if retailer i 
is not observed on the first five pages of search results for search term k, Ra nk ik is the 
rank (or position) of retailer i on the first five pages of search results for search term k, 
Sponsor ed ik is a dummy for whether the retailer had a sponsored link on the first results 
page for search term k, B E i a measure of retailer i's brand equity, and X ik is a vector of 
other controls including demographic variables, search term specific variables, retailer 
characteristics as well as retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>There are two primary concerns with estimating this equation: (i) it is likely that 
some of the explanatory variables are endogenous (correlated with ε i j ); and (ii) owing 
to the nature of the Search Planner data, we only observe the dependent variable in 
equation (1) when clicks exceed a certain threshold. Below we discuss how we deal with 
these concerns. </p>

<p>2.2.1. Endogeneity </p>

<p><rs type="software">Google</rs> continuously updates its rankings of search results to generate the most relevant 
search results, which means that our rank variable will depend on past clicks. It is 
therefore likely that rank is correlated with the error term and thus endogenous. A 
similar effect may be at work for the ads variable: Ad positions are based on the outcome 
of a second-price auction that takes the relevance of the bidder with respect to the search 
term into account, again making it likely that ad positions are based on past clicking 
behavior on Google. 
The standard approach in the literature on clicks at platforms (e.g., clicks at price 
comparison sites or sponsored clicks at search engines) is to assume that such positions 
are exogenous. Using the Wu-Hausman test for endogeneity, however, we reject the 
hypothesis that rank and ad positions are exogenous in our data ( p = 0.0023 and p = 
0.0116, respectively). To account for the potential endogeneity of these variables, we use 
information about rank and ads on <rs type="software">Bing</rs> as instruments. These instruments are correlated 
with the endogenous regressors, but are unlikely to be correlated with the error term, 
because <rs type="software">Bing's</rs> decisions on search result rankings and ad positions are not based on 
past clicks on <rs type="software">Google</rs>. Indeed, using the Sargan test for overidentifying restrictions, we 
cannot reject the hypothesis that these are valid instruments for rank and ad positions 
on Google ( p = 0.3795). 
One might also worry that our measure of brand equity is correlated with the error 
in equation (1). For example, if users begin searching for products with generic search 
phrases and end their searches with a navigational search, navigational searches may 
be driven by organic search results, and thus endogenous. Based on the Wu-Hausman 
test, however, we cannot reject the hypothesis that our measure of brand equity is 
exogenous. 
16 Our main results thus treat only position and ads as endogenous. Section 4 
shows that our results are robust to the use of three alternative measures of brand equity 
that are also unlikely to be correlated with the errors. </p>

<p>2.2.2. Sample Selection </p>

<p>As we explained in Section 2.1, a retail site is included as an observation if it appears on 
the first five pages of the <rs type="software">Google</rs> search result page for a specific search term, independent </p>

<p>15. Retail segment fixed effects control for systematic differences in clicks across, for example, mass 
merchants who may receive many clicks owing to product breadth effects and specialty retailers who receive 
fewer clicks. Although this specification assumes the marginal impact of brand equity and rank is identical 
across retail segments, we show in Section 4 that the results are similar when one excludes mass merchants 
such as Amazon and Walmart. 
16. The p-value for this test, which uses navigational searches on <rs type="software">Bing</rs> as an instrument, is p = 0.1692. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>of whether the retailer received organic clicks according to Search Planner. Complicating 
matters, <rs type="software">Search Planner</rs> only reports the number of organic clicks if those clicks exceed 
a certain threshold, which means we do not know whether sites receiving zero organic 
clicks according to Search Planner really received no click-throughs for the search term 
in question or whether they were censored. 
What makes our setting different from a standard censoring environment is that 
the selection rule depends on total clicks (including paid clicks) rather than just organic 
clicks. This means that a different probability mechanism generates both the zero clicks 
and the positive clicks, and this cannot be captured by a standard Tobit censoring 
model. For this reason, we estimate a Heckman-type selection model. As we argued in 
the previous subsection, endogeneity is likely to be important in our data, so we allow 
for endogenous explanatory variables. Estimation of the model consists of two stages. In 
the first stage we regress a dummy for having positive clicks on all exogenous variables 
(including instruments) z. Here, it is important to include at least one more instrument 
than is necessary for dealing with the endogeneity problem (otherwise identification is 
purely based on the parametric form of the inverse Mills ratio). This additional exclusion 
restriction should relate to the probability of observing positive organic clicks. Because 
this probability relates to the number of total clicks, we use additional variables in 
the selection equation that are important for getting paid clicks: We add dummies for 
whether a sponsored link was displayed on each of pages 2 through 5 in the <rs type="software">Bing</rs> search 
results. We obtain the inverse Mills ratio, given byλ = λ(zδ) = φ(zδ)/ (zδ) from the 
selection equation, and add this to the second stage to obtain </p>

<p>ln(Clicks ik ) = γ 0 + γ 1 (RNO ik ) + γ 2 ln(Rank ik ) + γ 3 Sponsored ik + γ 4 ln(BE i ) + γ 5 X ik </p>

<p>+γ 6λ + ε ik 
(2) </p>

<p>We estimate this equation using the selected subsample (for which we observe organic 
clicks), that is, by two-stage least squares using instruments (z,λ) for the endogenous 
variables RNO ik , Ra nk ik , and Sponsor ed ik . </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>Table II provides results for the specification in equation (2), which regresses the loga-
rithm of organic clicks on explanatory variables that account for the impact on clicks of 
rank, brand equity, retailer characteristics, as well as characteristics including searcher 
demographics and the nature of search terms. Recall that these results control for poten-
tial endogeneity as well as censoring, and include a constant and retail segment fixed 
effects to account for potential differences in clicks across the 15 retail segments iden-
tified in Table I. All statistical tests are based on the reported robust standard errors, 
which account for potential heteroskedacity. 
The estimated coefficient for the inverse Mills ratio is significantly different from 
zero at the 1% level, which indicates that it is indeed appropriate to control for censoring 
of the data. We discuss the other estimated parameters of the model below. </p>

<p>3.1. Rank </p>

<p>As discussed earlier, one potential goal of SEO is to increase the ranking (or position) of 
a retailer's links in organic search results. But just how important is position in driving a 
retailer's organic clicks following a product search? The first two estimated coefficients </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table II. 
Main Results </p>

<p>Dependent variable: log of organic clicks on <rs type="software">Google</rs> </p>

<p>ln(Rank) 
−1.347 (0.252) *** 
Rank not observed 
−2.335 (0.616) *** 
Sponsored link on first page 
0.317 (0.150) ** 
ln(Brand Equity) 
0.084 (0.030) *** 
Age 18-24 
−0.109 (0.124) 
Age 25-34 
0.088 (0.108) 
Age 35-44 
0.141 (0.103) 
Age 55-64 
0.223 (0.107) ** 
Age 65+ 
0.181 (0.132) 
Income &lt;25k 
−0.708 (0.107) *** 
Income 25-50k 
−0.211 (0.100) ** 
Income 75-100k 
0.337 (0.111) *** 
Income &gt;100k 
0.773 (0.122) *** 
Home 
−1.451 (0.149) *** 
Children 
−0.191 (0.074) ** 
Branded search term 
0.101 (0.057) * 
Number of words 
−0.138 (0.035) *** 
Social network presence 
0.056 (0.144) 
Site age 
0.012 (0.009) 
Web only retailer 
0.127 (0.053) ** 
Inverse Mills ratio 
0.851 (0.286) *** 
Observations 
40,117 
Censored 
5,681 
Uncensored 
34,436 
Selection 
Yes 
Endogeneity 
Yes </p>

<p>Notes: * significant at 10%; ** significant at 5%; *** significant at 1%. Robust standard errors in parentheses. All specifications include a constant 
and retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>in Table II provide an answer. The estimated coefficient for rank not observed captures the 
effect of a retailer's link not being included on the first five pages of search results for a 
given search term. The estimated coefficient of −2.335 is significant in both an economic 
and statistical sense, and implies that a firm not appearing on the first five pages receives 
90% fewer clicks for a given search term. For a retailer whose link is observed on the 
first 5 pages, the estimated coefficient of −1.347 for ln(Rank) implies that a 1% decline in 
rank induces a 1.3% reduction in organic clicks for a given search term. For example, a 
retailer moving from the fifth to the sixth position in a search for "jeans" experiences a 
27% reduction in organic clicks for that search term, whereas moving from the sixth to 
the seventh position results in a 22% decline. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Although these results indicate that rank is a very important driver of organic 
clicks following product searches, it is important to stress that the unit of observation 
underlying these results is Ra nk i,k ; that is, retailer i's position in the results for search 
term k. Thus, these rank coefficients measure the effect of improving a retailer's position 
for a single search term. Consequently, SEO efforts that are term specific (e.g., designed to 
elevate a retailer's rank following a search for "jeans" but that have no effect on positions 
following other product searches), will result in a much smaller percentage improvement </p>

<p>17. We also ran specifications with position bins rather than the log-linear specification and the results 
were qualitatively similar. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>in that retailer's total organic clicks. By way of example, the average retailer in our sample 
was relevant for about 60 search terms, so the corresponding effect on total organic clicks 
is about 1/60 
th of the rank coefficients in Table II. For example, the estimated coefficient 
of −1.347 for ln(Rank) implies that a 1% improvement in rank following a given keyword 
search results in a 0.02% (= 1.347/60) increase in total organic clicks. 
These results indicate that the returns to term-specific SEO critically depend on 
the breadth and depth of a retailer's product offerings and hence the number of search 
terms in which its link is relevant. </p>

<p>3.2. Retailer Brand Equity </p>

<p>Table II also reports estimates of the direct effect of a retailer's brand equity on the clicks 
it receives following a product search. The estimated coefficient for the logarithm of 
brand equity is positive and very precisely estimated, indicating that the direct effect 
of brand equity of a retailer's site is an important determinant of the organic clicks it 
receives following a product search. It is important to note that, unlike rank, brand 
equity is not search-term specific. As such, the estimated impact of brand equity in 
Table II captures the impact on a retailer's total organic clicks: Holding rank and the 
other factors influencing clicks constant, a 1% increase in a site's brand equity results 
in a 0.084% increase in a retailer's total organic clicks. These results, coupled with those 
discussed above for rank, indicate that a marginal improvement in a retailer's brand 
equity has a larger direct effect on its organic clicks than SEO efforts resulting in a 
marginal improvement in its position associated with a particular search term. 
Notice that the estimated coefficient for brand equity in Table II, which corresponds 
to γ 4 in equation (2), measures the direct effect of retailer i's brand equity on its organic 
clicks. However, because search engines' algorithms determine rankings or positions of 
listings, in part, on past clicking behavior, there is also an indirect effect of brand equity 
on clicks: Retailers with greater brand equity and stronger brand names enjoy more 
clicks, which results in better future ranks. Figure 2, which graphs the average number 
of times retail sites appear on the first page of search results for different sextiles of brand 
equity, shows that online retailers with stronger brands in our data tend to have better 
ranks on results pages following non-navigational searches. The total effect of brand 
equity on clicks includes the direct effect identified in Table II as well as the indirect 
effect through rank. 
We identify the total effect of brand equity on clicks by using a standard two-step 
procedure (Alwin and Hauser, 1975). In the first step we regress the rank variables 
on the logarithm of brand equity to obtain brand-equity adjusted ranks to determine 
the impact of brand equity on rank. In the second step, we proceed as in equation (2) 
but using these brand equity adjusted ranks. This regression yields an estimate of the 
total effect of brand equity on organic clicks, including both the direct effect shown in 
Table II as well as the indirect effect stemming from the impact of brand equity on 
position. As shown in Figure 3, the indirect effect of brand equity on clicks (through 
its impact on rank) is slightly larger than the direct effect, resulting in a total effect on 
organic clicks of 0.185-roughly twice the direct effect. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>18. Note that this procedure does not impact any of the other parameter estimates in Table II, nor does it 
impact the overall fit of the model. The estimated total effect is significant at the 1% level; the robust standard 
error for the point estimate of 0.185 is 0.047. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Number of 
Times on First Page </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>Worst 
Poor Below Median Median Above Median 
Best </p>

<p>Sextiles of Brand Equity </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. PAGE RANK (POSITION) AND BRAND EQUITY </p>

<p>Elasticity and 95% </p>

<p>confidence interval </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>Direct 
Indirect 
Total </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. ELASTICITY OF CLICKS WITH RESPECT TO BRAND EQUITY </p>

<p>From the standpoint of SEO, these results highlight an important interaction be-
tween brand equity and rank. A 1% improvement in a retailer's brand equity directly 
increases its total organic clicks by 0.084%, owing to the fact that consumers more fre-
quently click on its link instead of a competing one in the list of search results. Ultimately, 
this induces search engines to elevate the firm's position in all relevant searches, which 
results in an additional 0.101% increase in clicks. The total effect of a 1% improvement in 
a retailer's brand equity is therefore a 0.185% increase in total organic clicks. Unlike the </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>impact of rank, this percentage increase applies to a retailer's overall clicks rather than 
the clicks stemming from a single search phrase. To illustrate, suppose a relatively un-
known retailer gets 1,000 organic clicks from navigational searches and 30,000 through 
non-navigational searches. 
19 If the retailer makes an investment in brand equity suffi-
cient to increase its navigational searches by 10 clicks (1%), it gains an additional 55 
(= 30, 000 × 0.185%) organic clicks from non-navigational searches. </p>

<p>3.3. Consumer Characteristics </p>

<p>The specification in Table II indicates that consumer characteristics systematically influ-
ence organic clicks on search engines. These results are of potential interest to retailers 
engaging in SEO to attract customers within particular demographic groups. 
Notice that all of the income categories are statistically significant at the 5% or better 
levels: Consumers with higher incomes tend to more frequently click an organic link 
following a product search than do consumers with lower incomes. Although not all of 
the age categories are statistically significant, the general pattern suggests that younger 
individuals are less likely to click organic links than older individuals. Interestingly, the 
results also indicate that consumers searching from home are less likely to click following 
an organic search than individuals conducting a product search from the workplace. 
These patterns may stem from differences in search behavior across consumers with 
different demographic characteristics. For example, consumers with greater incomes 
may be more likely to conduct product searches on platforms such as Amazon rather 
than a search engine; individuals with lower incomes may be more likely to search using 
price comparison sites. </p>

<p>3.4. Keyword-Specific Effects </p>

<p>One might worry that the demographic effects documented above stem from differences 
in the sophistication of searchers with different demographic characteristics. To account 
for this, we include two controls for the nature of the keyword search: (1) branded search 
term, which is an indicator for whether the search phrase includes a brand-name product 
(e.g., "Levi's Jeans" ), and (2) number of words, which is simply a count of the number 
of words included in the search. The results indicate that searchers who include specific 
brands of products in their terms, or who use fewer words in their search, are more likely 
to click an organic link following a product search. These findings are consistent with 
Yang and Ghose (2010), who find a positive relationship between branded searches and 
paid clicks as well as a positive relationship between keyword length and paid clicks. 
Our results are consistent with longer search phrases resulting in organic results that 
contain less relevant links, which would result in fewer organic clicks but more paid 
clicks. </p>

<p>3.5. Other Retailer Characteristics </p>

<p>In addition to retail segment fixed effects, the results in Table II include controls for other 
retailer characteristics that might impact SEO. We discuss each of these in turn. </p>

<p>19. To put this hypothetical in perspective, electricgeneratorsdirect.com received 1,208 organic clicks from 
navigational searches and 31,955 organic clicks through non-navigational searches in August of 2012. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>First, note that retailers with a sponsored link on the first page of organic results 
receive 37% more organic clicks after controlling for rank, brand equity, and other drivers 
of clicks. This positive relationship is consistent with findings of Yang and Ghose (2010) 
and suggests that these sponsored links may provide searchers information about the 
retailer that increases the perceived value of clicking its organic link. For instance, such a 
link might lead searchers to conclude that the corresponding organic listing is relevant; 
alternatively, the sponsored link might have value as an advertisement that increases the 
brand equity of the retailer, making consumers more likely to click on organic as well 
as sponsored links. As with rank effects, however, Ads is a keyword specific variable so 
this 37% increase applies to the base of clicks from that keyword; it does not imply a 
37% increase in overall organic clicks. 
Second, the results in Table II indicate that Web-only retailers receive about 13% 
more total organic clicks than their bricks-and-clicks counterparts. This highlights that 
drivers of organic clicks through search engines may differ from those through other 
channels, such as price comparison sites. For example, Baye et al (2009) find that bricks-
and-clicks retailers selling on a leading price comparison site receive over 25% more 
clicks than their Web-only counterparts. 
Finally, notice that the specification in Table II also includes additional controls 
designed to capture other variables that potentially influence organic clicks. These in-
clude site age (a potential proxy for cumulative brand equity) and whether the site 
has a presence on social networks (Facebook and Twitter). Although the coefficients for 
these two controls have a positive effect on organic clicks, they are relatively small and 
not statistically significant at conventional levels. On balance, we view this as evidence 
that the effects discussed above are not the result of spurious correlation with excluded 
drivers of organic clicks. </p>

<p>4. Robustness Checks and Additional Results </p>

<p>In this section we demonstrate that our results are robust to a variety of alternative 
specifications, and offer some additional results that are of potential interest for SEO 
related to generating traffic from consumers in different income classes. </p>

<p>4.1. Results Based on Alternative Measures of Retailer Brand 
Equity </p>

<p>One may worry that our results stem from endogeneity issues related to our measure 
of brand equity. Although the Wu-Hausman test did not trigger any formal concerns 
about our measure of brand equity being correlated with the error in equation (2), one 
may wonder whether our results are sensitive to this particular measure of brand equity. 
Table III shows that our main findings are robust to using three alternative measures of 
brand equity that are unlikely to suffer from endogeneity concerns. 
The first specification in Table III uses navigational searches on Google from June 
rather than August to construct the measure of retailer brand equity. Because naviga-
tional searches in June were predetermined at the time searchers made their August click 
decisions, this lagged measure of brand equity mitigates concerns that an unobserved 
factor drives both navigational and non-navigational clicks in the August clicks data. 
As shown in column (1), all parameter estimates, including the brand equity coefficient, 
increase slightly in magnitude but are qualitatively similar to those reported in Table II. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>Table III. 
Robustness: Alternative Measures of Brand </p>

<p>Dependent variable: log of organic clicks on <rs type="software">Google</rs> </p>

<p>Lagged Brand 
<rs type="software">Bing</rs> 
Brand Equity on Alexa 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) </p>

<p>ln(Rank) 
−1.463 (0.263) *** 
−1.162 (0.227) *** 
−1.282 (0.237) *** 
Rank not observed 
−2.569 (0.655) *** 
−1.910 (0.554) *** 
−2.154 (0.594) *** 
Sponsored Link on first page 
0.422 (0.165) ** 
0.245 (0.138) * 
0.404 (0.160) ** 
ln(Brand Equity) 
0.091 (0.029) *** 
0.035 (0.017) ** 
0.124 (0.032) *** 
Age 18-24 
−0.068 (0.131) 
−0.151 (0.116) 
−0.116 (0.121) 
Age 25-34 
0.117 (0.114) 
0.066 (0.102) 
0.084 (0.105) 
Age 35-44 
0.162 (0.107) 
0.128 (0.097) 
0.138 (0.101) 
Age 55-64 
0.209 (0.112) * 
0.231 (0.101) ** 
0.229 (0.106) ** 
Age 65+ 
0.189 (0.140) 
0.180 (0.124) 
0.179 (0.131) 
Income &lt;25k 
−0.728 (0.113) *** 
−0.674 (0.099) *** 
−0.689 (0.104) *** 
Income 25-50k 
−0.231 (0.105) ** 
−0.199 (0.093) ** 
−0.205 (0.098) ** 
Income 75-100k 
0.339 (0.116) *** 
0.331 (0.105) *** 
0.342 (0.110) *** 
Income &gt;100k 
0.805 (0.130) *** 
0.721 (0.114) *** 
0.757 (0.119) *** 
Home 
−1.529 (0.159) *** 
−1.363 (0.138) *** 
−1.432 (0.147) *** 
Children 
−0.187 (0.077) ** 
−0.206 (0.069) *** 
−0.201 (0.072) *** 
Branded search term 
0.114 (0.060) * 
0.093 (0.054) * 
0.077 (0.057) 
Number of words 
−0.151 (0.037) *** 
−0.115 (0.032) *** 
−0.133 (0.034) *** 
Social network presence 
0.132 (0.155) 
0.030 (0.135) 
−0.042 (0.141) 
Site age 
0.015 (0.009) 
0.015 (0.009) * 
0.000 (0.009) 
Web only retailer 
0.143 (0.056) ** 
0.117 (0.050) ** 
−0.041 (0.054) 
Inverse Mills ratio 
1.011 (0.308) *** 
0.626 (0.251) ** 
0.817 (0.278) *** 
Observations 
40,117 
40,117 
40,117 
Censored 
5,681 
5,681 
5,681 
Uncensored 
34,436 
34,436 
34,436 
Selection 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Endogeneity 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Notes: * significant at 10%; ** significant at 5%; *** significant at 1%. Robust standard errors in parentheses. All specifications include a constant 
and retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>The second specification in Table III uses navigational searches from <rs type="software">Bing</rs> rather 
than Google to measure brand equity. Because <rs type="software">Bing</rs> has a different population of users 
and employs a different algorithm for returning search results, it is unlikely that un-
observed factors that affect clicks on Google are correlated with this measure of brand 
equity based on navigational searches on Bing. The results in column (2) show that our 
findings are robust to using this alternative measure of brand equity. 
The final specification in Table III is based on an alternative measure of brand equity 
pioneered by Animesh et al. (2010). This measure is constructed from data produced by 
the Web traffic reporting firm, Alexa, and measures the "Sites Linking In." It is based on 
the number of links to a web site from sites that are visited by individuals on Alexa's 
Web traffic panel. 
20 Animesh et al. use these data to measure seller quality, noting that 
links pointing to a web site can be viewed as a positive recommendation from the 
referring site. As shown in column (3) of Table III, our results are also robust to using 
this alternative measure of brand equity-as well as to interpreting the brand equity 
effect identified in our earlier results as purely capturing "seller quality." </p>

<p>20. According to Alexa.com, "Links that were not seen by users in the Alexa traffic panel are not counted. 
Multiple links from the same site are only counted once." See also Alexa.com. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table IV. 
Robustness: Alternative Censoring Models </p>

<p>Dependent variable: log of organic clicks on Google </p>

<p>Tobit with IV 
Tobit </p>

<p>ln(Rank) 
−2.887 (0.118) *** 
−2.800 (0.040) *** 
Rank not observed 
−5.544 (0.788) *** 
−4.199 (0.101) *** 
Sponsored Link on first page 
0.381 (0.296) 
−1.021 (0.064) *** 
ln(Brand Equity) 
0.232 (0.019) *** 
0.275 (0.017) *** 
Age 18-24 
0.775 (0.190) *** 
0.701 (0.190) *** 
Age 25-34 
0.335 (0.156) ** 
0.332 (0.156) ** 
Age 35-44 
−0.041 (0.149) 
−0.001 (0.149) 
Age 55-64 
−0.106 (0.159) 
−0.108 (0.159) 
Age 65+ 
− 0.498 (0.186) *** 
−0.456 (0.186) ** 
Income &lt;25k 
−0.606 (0.171) *** 
−0.620 (0.171) *** 
Income 25-50k 
−0.319 (0.157) ** 
−0.281 (0.158) * 
Income 75-100k 
0.197 (0.168) 
0.200 (0.168) 
Income &gt;100k 
0.765 (0.143) *** 
0.750 (0.143) *** 
Home 
−1.397 (0.110) *** 
−1.314 (0.110) *** 
Children 
0.166 (0.104) 
0.115 (0.104) 
Branded search term 
0.041 (0.085) 
0.168 (0.083) ** 
Number of words 
−0.202 (0.029) *** 
−0.175 (0.028) *** 
Social network presence 
0.232 (0.173) 
0.185 (0.169) 
Site age 
0.038 (0.013) *** 
0.034 (0.012) *** 
Web only retailer 
0.457 (0.070) *** 
0.518 (0.069) *** 
Observations 
40,117 
40,117 
Censored 
5,681 
5,681 
Uncensored 
34,436 
34,436 
Selection 
No 
No 
Endogeneity 
Yes 
No </p>

<p>Notes: * significant at 10%; ** significant at 5%; *** significant at 1%. Robust standard errors in parentheses. All specifications include a constant 
and retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>4.2. Alternative Censoring Models </p>

<p>Table IV shows that our main results are robust to using a Tobit censoring model rather 
than the Heckman selection model used in our main specification. The Tobit model 
can be interpreted as a constrained version of the selection model, with the selection 
and outcome equations being equivalent while not allowing for any selection bias. 
Column (1) reports results controlling for both selection and endogeneity, as in our 
main specification, whereas column (2) simply controls for selection. Comparing the 
parameter estimates to those in column (1) of Table II, most parameters increase in 
magnitude and are largely consistent with those reported in our main specification in 
Table II. </p>

<p>4.3. Brand Equity and Consumer Income </p>

<p>Our main specification in Table II assumes that the coefficients for the drivers of or-
ganic clicks are identical across consumers in different income groups. We conclude 
by showing that our qualitative results are not an artifact of pooling across searchers 
with different incomes. 
21 These results are potentially of independent interest, because 
different retailers may use SEO to target consumers in different income groups. </p>

<p>21. We also ran specifications that did not pool across searchers of different ages or conducting searches 
from different locations, but those results did not materially differ from those presented in Table II. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>Table V. 
Unpooled Results by Income </p>

<p>Dependent variable: log of organic clicks on Google (for income group) </p>

<p>Income &lt;25k 
Income 25-50k 
Income 50-75k Income 75-100k Income &gt;100k </p>

<p>In(Rank) 
−1.143 (0.212) *** −0.963 (0.243) *** −1.235 (0.238) *** −1.426 (0.222) *** −1.619 (0.244) *** 
Rank not 
observed </p>

<p>−1.887 (0.511) *** −1.166 (0.563) ** −1.818 (0.531) *** −1.877 (0.527) *** −2.526 (0.567) *** </p>

<p>Sponsored Link 
on first page </p>

<p>0.309 (0.174) * 
0.257 (0.187) 
0.283 (0.195) 
0.397 (0.210) * 
0.589 (0.245) ** </p>

<p>ln(Brand Equity) 
0.071 (0.033) ** 
0.046 (0.037) 
0.061 (0.036) * 
0.100 (0.044) ** 
0.130 (0.047) *** 
Age 18-24 
0.321 (0.165) * 
0.139 (0.164) 
0.090 (0.188) 
−0.365 (0.234) 
−1.240 (0.271) *** 
Age 25-34 
0.381 (0.151) ** 
0.441 (0.143) *** 
0.192 (0.173) 
−0.148 (0.212) 
−0.596 (0.224) *** 
Age 35-44 
0.305 (0.149) ** 
0.079 (0.144) 
0.268 (0.165) 
0.007 (0.206) 
−0.026 (0.185) 
Age 55-64 
0.057 (0.158) 
0.175 (0.153) 
0.306 (0.172) * 
−0.011 (0.203) 
0.115 (0.202) 
Age 65+ 
0.383 (0.183) ** 
0.083 (0.183) 
0.174 (0.194) 
−0.471 (0.237) ** 
0.013 (0.221) 
Home 
−0.030 (0.189) 
−0.460 (0.215) ** −0.979 (0.216) *** −0.729 (0.259) *** −1.337 (0.267) *** 
Children 
−0.182 (0.105) * 
−0.221 (0.107) ** −0.220 (0.120) * 
−0.542 (0.139) *** −0.414 (0.143) *** 
Branded search 
term </p>

<p>0.067 (0.070) 
0.076 (0.067) 
0.177 (0.073) ** 
0.182 (0.084) ** 
0.203 (0.089) ** </p>

<p>Number of 
words </p>

<p>−0.157 (0.053) *** −0.085 (0.055) 
−0.123 (0.056) ** −0.139 (0.070) ** −0.208 (0.079) *** </p>

<p>Social network 
presence </p>

<p>0.092 (0.157) 
0.023 (0.165) 
−0.072 (0.179) 
−0.059 (0.197) 
0.062 (0.225) </p>

<p>Site age 
0.010 (0.010) 
0.013 (0.010) 
0.011 (0.012) 
0.005 (0.013) 
0.012 (0.014) 
Web only retailer 
0.107 (0.064) * 
0.079 (0.065) 
0.104 (0.071) 
0.224 (0.084) *** 
0.291 (0.096) *** 
Inverse Mills 
ratio </p>

<p>0.820 (0.290) *** 
0.456 (0.332) 
0.730 (0.325) ** 
0.848 (0.364) ** 
1.323 (0.423) *** </p>

<p>Observations 
40,117 
40,117 
40,117 
40,117 
40,117 
Censored 
4,558 
4,602 
4,409 
3,800 
3,773 
Uncensored 
35,559 
35,515 
35,708 
36,317 
36,344 
Selection 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Endogeneity 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Notes: * significant at 10%; ** significant at 5%; *** significant at 1%. Robust standard errors in parentheses. All specifications include a constant 
and retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>Table V reports the results of estimation by income group, and shows that our main 
qualitative findings hold in the absence of pooling. Interestingly, however, these results 
suggest that brand equity has differential effects across individuals in different income 
classes. 
For the three lowest income groups, the elasticity of organic clicks with respect to 
brand equity is smaller than the 0.084 reported in Table II based on pooled data, whereas 
for the top two income groups the elasticity is greater. Although one of the brand equity 
coefficients is not estimated precisely enough to infer that it is significantly different from 
the excluded ($51 to $74 thousand income) category, the results on balance indicate that 
brand equity is a more important driver of organic clicks for richer than poorer searchers. 
This result is illustrated in Figure 4, where the dots represent the point estimates for the 
elasticity of organic clicks with respect to brand equity for the five income groups, and 
the lines represent the corresponding 95% confidence intervals. </p>

<p>4.4. Relevance of Results for Specialty Retailers </p>

<p>Finally, one might worry that our main results are driven by the fact that large mass 
merchants (such as Amazon) have high levels of brand equity because of the breadth and </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Elasticity and 95% </p>

<p>confidence interval </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>&gt; 100 
75 to 99 
50 to 74 
25 to 49 
&lt; 25 
Income (Thousands of Dollars) </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. ELASTICITY OF CLICKS WITH RESPECT TO BRAND EQUITY BY INCOME 
OF SEARCHER </p>

<p>depth of their offerings, and also tend to receive large numbers of clicks because of this; 
that is, our regressions could simply be picking up "large retailer" effects. Although this 
concern is mitigated to some extent by the fact that all of our specifications include retail 
segment fixed effects, our specifications assume that the coefficients for brand equity, 
rank, and other variables are the same for mass merchants and specialty retailers. 
Table VI reports our main results (column 1) along with the results obtained when 
we exclude Amazon (column 2), Amazon-Walmart-Target (column 3), and all mass 
merchants (column 4) from the data. Notice that the estimated coefficients are remarkably 
similar across these different samples. </p>

<p>5. Managerial Implications for SEO </p>

<p>Our results are intuitive: When confronted with a list of potentially "relevant" search 
results, consumers are more likely to click the link of the retailer with the greatest brand 
equity. That is, holding other drivers of clicks constant, consumers tend to click retailers 
that are more recognized, trusted, have reputations for providing value (in terms of 
prices, product depth, or breadth), service (well-designed web sites, return policies, 
secure payment systems), and so on. Unlike price comparison sites and other online 
channels where signals of these attributes may be separately observed (through displays 
that include user feedback ratings, third-party certification, prices, shipping costs, etc.), 
the only signals consumers observe in organic product search results are sites' names 
(which embody their brand equity) and their "relevance" (as proxied by the rank or 
position that the search engine's algorithm assigns each organic link). We also showed 
that our findings are robust to several alternative specifications and, importantly, to 
controls for censoring as well as the endogeneity of a retailer's rank or position in the 
list of organic results. We conclude by discussing implications of our analysis for SEO, 
and by providing a few caveats regarding their implementation. </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>Table VI. 
Robustness: Main Specification for Different Retailer 
Samples </p>

<p>Dependent variable: log of organic clicks on Google </p>

<p>All 
Excluding 
Excluding Amazon, 
Excluding All 
Retailers 
Amazon 
Walmart &amp; Target 
Mass Merchants 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>ln(Rank) 
−1.347 (0.252) *** −1.359 (0.289) *** 
−1.267 (0.293) *** 
−1.330 (0.290) *** 
Rank not observed 
−2.335 (0.616) *** −2.489 (0.777) *** 
−2.449 (0.880) *** 
−2.491 (0.900) *** 
Sponsored link on first page 
0.317 (0.150) ** 
0.189 (0.145) 
0.106 (0.137) 
0.029 (0.140) 
ln(Brand Equity) 
0.084 (0.030) *** 
0.074 (0.032) ** 
0.067 (0.032) ** 
0.061 (0.031) * 
Age 18-24 
−0.109 (0.124) 
−0.129 (0.133) 
−0.124 (0.133) 
−0.041 (0.141) 
Age 25-34 
0.088 (0.108) 
0.044 (0.121) 
0.047 (0.122) 
0.123 (0.129) 
Age 35-44 
0.141 (0.103) 
0.136 (0.113) 
0.159 (0.112) 
0.148 (0.114) 
Age 55-64 
0.223 (0.107) ** 
0.261 (0.117) ** 
0.268 (0.118) ** 
0.401 (0.124) *** 
Age 65+ 
0.181 (0.132) 
0.367 (0.147) ** 
0.395 (0.151) *** 
0.582 (0.163) *** 
Income &lt;25k 
−0.708 (0.107) *** −0.734 (0.118) *** 
−0.724 (0.118) *** 
−0.700 (0.118) *** 
Income 25-50k 
−0.211 (0.100) ** 
−0.311 (0.112) *** 
−0.296 (0.110) *** 
−0.292 (0.117) ** 
Income 75-100k 
0.337 (0.111) *** 
0.329 (0.121) *** 
0.304 (0.120) ** 
0.347 (0.127) *** 
Income&gt;100k 
0.773 (0.122) *** 
0.681 (0.135) *** 
0.709 (0.138) *** 
0.716 (0.142) *** 
Home 
−1.451 (0.149) *** −1.410 (0.167) *** 
−1.325 (0.157) *** 
−1.343 (0.162) *** 
Children 
−0.191 (0.074) ** 
−0.175 (0.079) ** 
−0.220 (0.080) *** 
−0.208 (0.085) ** 
Branded search term 
0.101 (0.057) * 
0.100 (0.064) 
0.085 (0.066) 
0.079 (0.068) 
Number of words 
−0.138 (0.035) *** −0.141 (0.041) *** 
−0.128 (0.041) *** 
−0.133 (0.040) *** 
Social network 
0.056 (0.144) 
0.029 (0.142) 
0.017 (0.138) 
−0.008 (0.140) 
Site age 
0.012 (0.009) 
0.015 (0.010) 
0.014 (0.010) 
0.016 (0.011) 
Web only retailer 
0.127 (0.053) ** 
0.108 (0.062) * 
0.094 (0.062) 
0.145 (0.068) ** 
Inverse Mills ratio 
0.851 (0.286) *** 
0.726 (0.305) ** 
0.622 (0.313) ** 
0.634 (0.305) ** 
Observations 
40,117 
35,384 
31,513 
25,572 
Censored 
5,681 
4,371 
3,957 
3,569 
Uncensored 
34,436 
31,013 
27,556 
22,003 
Selection 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Endogeneity 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Notes: * significant at 10%; ** significant at 5%; *** significant at 1%. Robust standard errors in parentheses. Allspecifications include a constant 
and retail segment fixed effects. </p>

<p>5.1. Rank or Position on Results Pages </p>

<p>Our results indicate that rank is an important determinant of clicks; it is hard for a 
retailer to get organic clicks from a specific product search if its link is not observed on 
the first five pages of results for that search. For retailer's above this virtual "fold," the 
elasticity of clicks with respect to rank is about unity: a 1% improvement in rank leads 
to a 1% increase in organic clicks (for that search). Our results thus suggest that there 
are returns to SEO efforts that make it easier for search engines to determine a site's 
relevance for a particular product search. This includes making effective use of anchor 
texts, descriptive headings and meta tags, robot.txt files, and using accurate and unique 
page titles. 
However, although these sorts of strategies for SEO are necessary and important, 
our analysis suggests that it would be a mistake to make them the exclusive focus of 
SEO. Rankings are a zero-sum game, and other retailers also have strong incentives to 
ensure that their sites contain the information needed to be properly indexed by search 
engines. In light of best responses by other sites, these efforts may prevent a retailer from 
losing ranks due to miscommunication with search engines, but are unlikely to result </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>in improvements in the equilibrium ranks of a particular retailer's link. Additionally, 
strategies designed to improve rank need not result in a long-run increase in organic 
clicks. This is particularly true of efforts to "trick" search engines into viewing a site to 
be relevant when it is not. 
It is also important for managers to recognize that estimates of the impact of rank 
on organic clicks are keyword specific, and that apples-to-apples comparisons of the 
benefits of rank versus other drivers of clicks require an adjustment for the importance 
of that search in generating organic clicks relative to all relevant searches. Among other 
things, this means that the returns to focusing on improving rank may be larger for a 
niche retailer (which sells a single product on a site with a single page) than a mass 
merchant with thousands of products and pages. </p>

<p>5.2. Site Branding </p>

<p>The benefits of including brand equity as part of an SEO strategy are high. Such in-
vestments include increasing consumer awareness (through traditional as well as online 
advertising), making the site more user-friendly (easier to navigate), providing quality 
content and service (such as one-click purchases, easy return policies, and using a secure 
payment system), and more generally, enhancing the value of the brand that underlies 
the retailer's link. A number of retailers-including both Amazon and Walmart-have 
successfully used these strategies. 
Investments in branding have both direct and indirect effects on organic clicks. 
The direct effect stems from our finding that consumers are more likely to click on links 
they know and trust-a finding that is consistent with evidence from other channels, 
including price comparison and auction sites. But brand equity has an equally sizeable 
indirect effect: Search engines want to provide users with relevant links, and the brand 
equity of a site is correlated with the relevance of links, which leads to better ranks and 
positions. Importantly, the brand equity of a site impacts organic clicks for all relevant 
keywords, not just those related to a particular search, so there is an amplification effect 
of SEO strategies targeted to improve the branding of a site. 
In addition to spillovers on organic clicks related to searches for other keywords, 
investments that enhance brand equity are likely to lead to benefits in other channels. 
These benefits are not accounted for in our estimates, nor in the benefits that other papers 
document regarding the impact of brand and reputation on sponsored clicks. For exam-
ple, our analysis focuses exclusively on drivers of non-navigational searches at search 
engines, so the regression coefficients in Table II do not include the benefits of increases 
in brand awareness or site quality on organic traffic from navigational searches at search 
engines. Likewise, improvements in a site's brand equity are likely to result in more 
direct visits to a retailer's site, as well as more clicks at other platforms including price 
comparison and auction sites. Finally, for retailers operating both online and physical 
stores, some investments (such as advertising) may result in positive spillovers into the 
physical channel. 
Our analysis indicates not only that investments in brand equity lead to signifi-
cantly more organic clicks, but also that these investments are more likely to be sus-
tainable than SEO efforts focused entirely on rank. Additionally, such investments have 
spillover benefits in other channels as well, as has already been documented in extensive 
research on other online markets as well as traditional retail channels. For all of these 
reasons, we conclude that site quality, brand awareness, and other investments that </p>

<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>



<p>enhance the brand equity of an online retailer are important components of an overall 
SEO strategy. </p>

<p>5.3. Search Term Considerations </p>

<p>Some search terms and phrases are more likely to generate clicks than other keywords, 
even when one accounts for differences in the brand equity of different retailers and 
their ranks in search results. This is potentially relevant for SEO as well. For example, 
our finding that searchers including the specific brand of a product (e.g., "Levi's Jeans" ) 
in a search are more likely to click an organic link suggests that retailers selling branded 
products benefit by ensuring that their sites present information about the brands in 
their portfolio in a way that allows search engines to properly index them. Likewise, 
searchers using longer keywords are less likely to click an organic link, so parsimony in 
this regard is also important for SEO. </p>

<p>5.4. Demographic Considerations </p>

<p>Our findings that individuals that are older, have higher incomes, or who conduct prod-
uct searches at work are more likely to click organic links also have ramifications for 
SEO. Among other things, these results suggest that SEO is more likely to be important 
for retailers targeting consumers with these demographic characteristics. In addition, 
because the elasticity of organic clicks with respect to brand equity is higher for indi-
viduals with higher incomes, the marginal benefits of SEO efforts targeted at improving 
the quality and brand awareness of a site are greater for retailers targeting individuals 
with higher incomes. More generally, the key implication is that the benefits of SEO vary, 
depending on the demographic characteristics of the consumers retailers are attempting 
to attract through this channel. </p>

<p>5.5. Retailer Considerations </p>

<p>The relationship between sponsored links and organic clicks identified in our data 
highlights yet another set of spillovers that complicates the calculus of SEO. Retailers 
attempting to increase traffic through organic links should recognize that there are 
possible spillovers from paid links: Consumers are more likely to click organic links 
associated with sponsored links. On the surface, this might seem like a pure win for 
retailers, because a sponsored link that results in an organic click rather than a paid click 
costs nothing. This is unlikely to be part of a sustainable strategy, however. Ultimately, if 
consumers click a retailer's organic rather than sponsored link, its prospects for winning 
that sponsored link in an auction will decline, because search engines have little incentive 
to allocate scarce ad space to retailers that do not receive sponsored clicks. </p>

<p>5.6. Concluding Caveats </p>

<p>Our analysis has focused on the potential benefits of SEO by focusing exclusively on 
the drivers of organic clicks. We have not taken into account the costs of improving 
these drivers, such as the costs of improving the meta tags associated with a particular 
keyword to improve rankings or advertising through traditional media to improve the 
brand awareness of a site. Costs are obviously an important component of optimization, 
and it would be a mistake to base SEO decisions purely on the drivers documented </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>above. Future research documenting the costs of different SEO strategies is therefore 
also important for the SEO literature. 
It is also important to recognize that search engines are only one of many online 
platforms where consumers conduct product searches. Baye et al. (2013) note that in June 
2012, consumers using browsers conducted 634 million product searches at retailer sites 
(such as Walmart.com), 134 million product searches at price comparison sites (such as 
Dealtime.com), and 877 million searches at marketplace sites (such as eBay.com). They 
also point out that 70% of eBay's listings were for new products, and over 60% of its 
listings were through posted prices rather than auctions. Unlike SEO efforts designed 
to improve rankings at a search engine, SEO efforts to improve a retailer's brand eq-
uity can improve the clicks it receives from searches in these other channels. Because 
these spillover benefits are difficult to quantify, it is easy for those engaging in SEO to 
underestimate the benefits of investing in the quality and brand awareness of a site. </p>



<p>Search Engine Optimization </p>





</text></tei>