<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.13.1.181" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:56+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>During the late 1970s and 1980s, the federal courts transformed antitrust rules 
and the federal enforcement agencies altered their case selection criteria in re-
sponse to theories developed by industrial organization economists. These devel-
opments in economic thinking, often associated with the Chicago school, led cur-
rent antitrust law and practice toward a greater skepticism about the relationship 
between market concentration and market power and a greater recognition of the 
possible efficiency-enhancing role of vertical agreements (contracts between firms 
and their customers or suppliers) than was present in the 1950s and 1960s. 1 This 
survey will begin where those developments leave off by highlighting more recent 
developments in antitrust economics that have influenced the way the federal an-
titrust enforcement agencies analyze five issues: efficiencies from mergers, entry 
conditions, practices facilitating coordination, exclusionary practices, and the uni-
lateral competitive effects of mergers. </p>

<p>1 For an introduction to the economic ideas behind antitrust's Chicago school revolution, see Bork 
(1978), Posner (1976) and the debates in Goldschmid, Mann and Weston (1974). </p>

<p>Jonathan B. Baker is Director, Bureau of Economics, Federal Trade Commission, Wash-
ington, D.C. </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 182 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>Many of these developments are reflected in the Department of Justice (DOJ) 
and Federal Trade Commission (FTC) Horizontal Merger Guidelines (U.S. De-
partment of Justice and Federal Trade Commission, 1997). These guidelines de-
scribe federal agency enforcement policy and have been influential in the courts, 
although judges are not required to follow them. They have been revised four times 
since originally promulgated in 1968 by Justice, and have grown in economic 
orientation and sophistication with each revision. </p>

<p>New Developments in Analyzing the Efficiencies from Mergers </p>

<p>How should antitrust enforcers take into account the potential for mergers to 
generate cost savings and other efficiencies when evaluating an acquisition's likely 
competitive effects? The old legal precedents were skeptical of an efficiency defense 
to mergers. But in the 1997 revision of the efficiencies section of the 1992 merger 
guidelines, the federal enforcement agencies adopted an approach consistent with 
Williamson's (1968) framework for the welfare analysis of mergers. 
The revised guidelines recognize that mergers can create conflicting incen-
tives: they can lead to higher prices if they facilitate the exercise of market power, 
or they can lead to lower prices if they generate cost savings that encourage the 
merged firm to compete more aggressively. (In a dynamic context, the merger 
guidelines are also concerned with the possibility that firms could exercise market 
power by slowing innovation, or the possibility that the efficiencies from merger 
could generate product improvements.) An acquisition's net effect on price in any 
market depends on which effect dominates. It is quite possible to have both a gain 
in productive efficiency (cheaper production) along with a loss in allocative effi-
ciency resulting from greater market power. The merger guidelines focus on price, 
and thus emphasize identifying the net effect of the merger on consumer's surplus 
within the markets where anticompetitive harm appears possible. Under some cir-
cumstances, there is flexibility for the enforcement agencies to take into account 
production efficiencies that are generated in other markets or that do not appear 
likely to be passed on to consumers. 
The need to assess the relative magnitude of the price-increasing and price-
reducing incentives of mergers calls attention to the pass-through rate; that is, the 
rate at which the merged firm would pass on cost changes into prices. The lower 
the pass-through rate, the greater must be any marginal cost reductions to overcome 
an anticompetitive incentive to raise price and generate a price reduction on net. 2 
Because the federal enforcement agencies consider only those efficiencies that are 
merger-specific-that is, efficiencies from the proposed merger unlikely to be </p>

<p>2 The emphasis is on marginal cost reductions, not fixed cost savings. While fixed cost savings may benefit 
the economy by allowing resources to flow to other industries, they do not create an incentive to lower 
price in the markets where the competitive harm appears likely. </p>

<p>Jonathan B. Baker 183 </p>

<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 183 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>achieved (or to be achieved as rapidly) absent the merger-and because merger-
specific efficiencies typically lead to firm-specific cost savings (that do not diffuse 
to the rest of the industry), the relevant pass-through rate for evaluating mergers 
is usually firm-specific. A firm-specific pass-through rate relates a change in the price 
a firm charges for a product to a change in the marginal cost of that product, 
holding constant the marginal cost of rivals' products. The firm-specific pass-
through rate is likely to be lower than the rate at which industry-wide cost changes 
are passed through to prices. Indeed, in the special case where a competitor is a 
price-taker, the firm will not alter price at all in response to firm-specific costs 
change though it will do so when industry-wide costs are affected. 3 
The distinction between firm-specific and industry-wide pass-through rates be-
came important in the Federal Trade Commission's recent court challenge to the 
proposed merger of Staples and Office Depot (Ashenfelter, Ashmore, Baker and 
McKernan, 1998). The empirical results presented by one FTC expert witness, Orley 
Ashenfelter, showed that Staples' firm-specific pass-through rate was only 15 per-
cent; much lower than the industry-wide rate. If so, the merger would lead to higher 
prices unless merger-specific efficiencies generated marginal cost reductions at least 
six or seven times the magnitude of the price increase that would otherwise occur. </p>

<p>New Developments in Analyzing Entry Conditions </p>

<p>One of the earliest and most far-reaching Chicago school successes came in 
convincing the courts to recognize that new competition-supply substitution or 
entry-could counteract or deter the exercise of market power. Recent develop-
ments in economic theory have helped clarify the significance of sunk expenditures 
in determining when this would occur. If the fixed costs of entry are not sunk, and 
entrants have variable costs comparable to incumbents, the market is ''contestable'' 
and performs competitively regardless of market concentration among incumbent 
sellers (Baumol, Panzar and Willig, 1982). But if entry requires sunk expenditures, 
and incumbents would be expected to react quickly to cut price in response to 
entry, entry may be deterred even if the pre-entry price exceeds competitive levels. 
This may occur because the prospective entrant, recognizing the prospect of post-
entry competition, will not expect to earn a contribution margin adequate to cover 
its sunk costs (Schwartz and Reynolds, 1983). 
In theory, even small sunk expenditures may be sufficient to protect incum-
bents' exercise of market power (Stiglitz, 1987). But the courts (and the merger 
guidelines) have acted as if relatively small sunk costs create a relatively small 
entry deterrent. For example, in 1984 an appellate court held that Waste Man-</p>

<p>3 A low firm-specific pass-through rate does not necessarily imply competitive behavior, however, because 
in general the rate depends on the ratio of the slope of the demand function to the slope of the marginal 
revenue function, and thus importantly on the curvature (second derivative) of demand (Bulow and 
Pfleiderer, 1983). </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 184 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>agement could acquire another trash hauler despite a high combined market 
share in Dallas after concluding that low fixed (and sunk) costs made entry into 
trash collection easy. 
The merger guidelines were revised in 1992 to describe how the federal en-
forcement agencies determine whether significant sunk expenditures would deter 
entry in response to an anticompetitive merger. The guidelines now ask whether a 
new competitor operating at ''minimum viable scale'' could secure pre-merger 
prices and thus be profitable (Salop, 1986; Willig, 1991; Ordover and Baker, 1992; 
Baker, 1997d). This question recognizes that if the entrant must operate at an 
output level too large for the market to absorb without depressing prices further, 
or if incumbents would keep the new producer from achieving the necessary output 
level by expanding sales in response to entry, then new competition sufficient to 
solve the competitive problem from merger would not be forthcoming. The guide-
lines test the entrant's profitability at pre-merger prices, notwithstanding the price 
increase expected as a result of an anticompetitive merger, because entry will solve 
the competitive problem only if it returns the market price to pre-merger levels. 
Hence, the potential entrants relevant for merger analysis-namely, those whose 
entry would solve the feared competitive problem-will evaluate the profitability 
of entry based on a forecast that price will be at the pre-merger level. </p>

<p>New Developments in Analyzing Practices Facilitating Coordination </p>

<p>Before George Stigler (1964) wrote about oligopoly, most antitrust commen-
tators took the view that in an industry characterized by a handful of firms, some 
form of tacit collusion was almost certain to arise and, in consequence, price would 
be elevated substantially above the competitive level. Stigler questioned the inevi-
tability of noncompetitive oligopoly behavior by highlighting the need for oli-
gopolists to identify a consensus and to deter deviation from it, thus raising the sort 
of informational and dynamic issues that have become central to contemporary 
oligopoly theory. For example, he observed that when firms make inferences about 
the strategies of rivals from changes in their own market share, an industry partic-
ipant's ability to cut price without detection by rivals, and thus its incentive to do 
so, increases as the market grows less concentrated. 
This line of thought led toward attempts to classify industry structures as more 
or less likely to facilitate coordination. (The term ''coordination'' is now frequently 
used in this context in preference to traditional terms ''collusion'' and ''coopera-
tion,'' since those terms may carry with them the legal idea of an agreement. Co-
ordination refers to any equilibria in which firms adopt, with or without discussion 
or communication with their rivals, strategies that recognize that they have inter-
acted in the past and will continue to do so in the future.) The resulting focus on 
the presence or absence of factors facilitating coordinated outcomes became par-
ticularly influential in merger analysis at the federal enforcement agencies following 
the promulgation of the 1982 Department of Justice Merger Guidelines. </p>

<p>Policy Watch: Developments in Antitrust Economics 185 </p>

<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 185 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>The key post-Stiglerian development in the economic theory of coordinated 
behavior is the recognition that repeated interactions can facilitate supracompeti-
tive pricing. Stigler had highlighted the difficulties of sustaining coordination with 
a focus on a one-shot prisoner's dilemma game, pointing out the difficulties firms 
face in achieving consensus and deterring deviation from it. But as has become 
well-known, in an infinitely repeated game-even the prisoner's dilemma-coor-
dinated outcomes (often including the repeated play of the cooperative outcome 
of the one-shot prisoner's dilemma) can readily be sustained. This result is broadly 
known as the ''folk theorem,'' and it suggests that deterring defection may not be 
as difficult as it appeared to Stigler. For example, Green and Porter (1984) showed 
that while uncertainty about whether rivals are cheating on the cartel consensus 
may lead to occasional price wars, it does not necessarily undermine the possibility 
of substantial periods of coordination. Moreover, the other Stiglerian cartel prob-
lem, of identifying an oligopolistic consensus, appears less daunting when firms 
have the opportunity to engage in ''cheap talk''-in the sense that term is used in 
Farrell and Rabin (1996)-as by announcing (indeed, negotiating) proposed price 
increases in the business press, without commitment, before they are implemented. 
In light of these developments in economic theory, it is not surprising that business 
strategists teach managers how to facilitate coordination, albeit in ways calculated to 
avoid reaching what antitrust law would term an agreement, through practices that 
help firms achieve consensus or deter deviation such as price leadership, unilateral 
signaling announcements, selective advertising to discipline recalcitrant rivals, and stan-
dardization to simplify industry decision variables and facilitate the identification of a 
consensus (Porter, 1980). 4 Yet Stigler's insight that coordination is not inevitable has 
not been undermined. Even when the number of firms is small, coordination among 
sellers may be unsustainable if buyers adopt large, widely spaced and randomly timed 
procurements, for example. Accordingly, a task force reviewing antitrust aspects of 
defense industry consolidation recommended that the Defense Department schedule 
its purchases in such a way as to reduce the risks of coordinated interaction by sellers 
(Defense Science Board Task Force, 1994). 
The implication of these recent developments in economic theory in calling re-
newed attention to the possibility of coordination is consistent with the empirical re-</p>

<p>4 Some of these practices may call to mind another set of post-Stiglerian oligopoly models: models that 
suggest ways that firms can achieve supracompetitive prices in one-shot play, through commitments to 
take strategic action that will discourage vigorous competition by horizontal rivals. For example, firms 
may achieve higher prices by committing to less aggressive conduct-reducing advertising or production 
capacity, perhaps-when rivals would predictably respond by acting less aggressively as well (that is, when 
the decision variables of rivals are ''strategic complements'') (Cooper, 1986; Fershtman and Judd, 1987; 
Bonanno and Vickers, 1988; Besanko and Perry, 1994; Rey and Stiglitz, 1995). Antitrust enforcers and 
courts have as yet made little use of these models, though they occasionally arise in merger enforcement. 
They raise litigation challenges of proving that a firm's acts are adopted with the goal and reasonable 
expectation of dampening competition, and, outside the merger setting, issues about the reach of the 
antitrust laws to the extent the commitments are unilateral. </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 186 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>search surveyed by Bresnahan (1989), which suggests that some concentrated indus-
tries possess a great deal of market power and that anticompetitive conduct is a signif-
icant cause of high price-cost margins. Moreover, the active criminal enforcement 
program of the Justice Department's Antitrust Division demonstrates that firms do 
indeed fix prices, notwithstanding that such agreements are not enforceable contracts. 
The contemporary perspective on coordination has helped shape a Depart-
ment of Justice investigation of collusion among the major airlines, which was set-
tled in 1993 and 1994 by consent decrees in federal court. DOJ alleged that the 
leading U.S. air carriers employed a computer system run by an airline joint venture 
to fix prices. The computer system collected each airline's actual and proposed price 
changes and sent them to computerized reservation systems used by travel agents. 
The computer also processed the price information and gave the airlines detailed 
reports that were unavailable to users of computerized reservations systems. Ac-
cording to Justice, the airlines used those detailed reports effectively to conduct 
negotiations, creating a language using fare relationships and footnote designators. 
They allegedly reached complex bargains across markets, such as trades where one 
carrier offered to increase fares on a route into a rival's hub in exchange for the 
rival's assenting to increase fares on a route into the first carrier's hub. The consent 
order prevents the airlines from using footnote designators and other methods to 
engage in costless quasi-public negotiations about price levels. These issues extend 
beyond airlines: the Federal Communications Commission recently altered its rules 
governing spectrum auctions to require bidding in round numbers, as a means of 
preventing bidders from costlessly communicating (and potentially coordinating) 
using the ''trailing digits'' in their bids. </p>

<p>New Developments in Analyzing Exclusionary Practices </p>

<p>Antitrust law has long been concerned with the anticompetitive potential of ex-
clusionary practices. Early 20th century antitrust litigation involving Alcoa, for example, 
arose in part out of that firm's efforts to deny potential rivals in aluminum production 
access to low cost electric power. Enforcement interest in exclusionary conduct waned 
as courts recognized that conduct that excludes rivals can also promote competition-
as when a deal for exclusive distribution discourages dealer free-riding on manufac-
turer promotional efforts. However, recent economic research, often relying on game-
theoretic modeling techniques, has clarified the logic by which exclusionary practices 
can harm competition, and thus brought a resurgence of interest in the ways firms can 
achieve market power by raising rivals' costs or through other non-price exclusionary 
conduct (Salop and Scheffman, 1987; Ordover, Saloner and Salop, 1990; Rasmusen, 
Ramseyer and Wiley, 1991; Bernheim and Whinston, 1998). 
One insight suggested by this literature is that exclusionary practices can harm 
competition by leading rivals to participate in, or accede to, what might be termed 
an ''involuntary'' cartel. Suppose, for example, firms A and B would like to collude 
with rival C, their only actual or potential competitor in a market protected from </p>

<p>Jonathan B. Baker 187 </p>

<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 187 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>entry, but they cannot do so because C would increase output (or enter) were A 
and B to raise price. If A could somehow raise C's marginal costs or otherwise make 
it more difficult for C to sell more, then C would be led to do what it would not 
have done previously: reduce its output. A might be able to accomplish this end by 
foreclosing C from access to low cost sources of supply or distribution, perhaps 
through exclusive contracts, or by making it more difficult for C to attract custom-
ers, perhaps by tying sales of its products together. Then, A and B could take ad-
vantage of the less aggressive competition from C to exercise market power. 
It is by no means a foregone conclusion that such a strategy would work for firm 
A. Firm C may have alternative means of obtaining supply or distribution. Firm B may 
not go along with A in reducing output once C is taken out of the picture. The strategy 
may be unprofitable for A given that it must bear the full costs of excluding C while 
sharing with firm B the benefit of any higher prices that result. Moreover, A's strategy 
may both disadvantage C and increase aggregate economic welfare. For example, a 
manufacturer may foreclose rivals from effective distribution by requiring the dealer 
not to handle the products of rival manufacturers, but the same practice may also lead 
the manufacturer to increase its promotional effort, reduce dealer free-riding, and 
result in better service to customers. Notwithstanding these caveats, it should be clear 
that it is possible for exclusionary deals with suppliers, distributors, or customers to 
impair horizontal rivalry and reduce aggregate surplus. 
In several recent cases, enforcement agencies have claimed that an attempt 
was made to raise the costs of rivals. The FTC recently found that Toys R Us con-
vinced toymakers not to provide certain merchandise to warehouse club stores, 
thereby reducing retailing competition from an alternative distribution channel. 
(The toy retailer's defense is in part that it was acting to prevent free-riding by rival 
dealers on its investments in promoting toys and the firm is likely to appeal.) The 
FTC's 1997 consent settlement with Time Warner resolving a complaint arising 
from its acquisition of Turner Broadcasting sought to address (among other things) 
concerns that Time Warner might have been able to reduce the competition facing 
its company-owned cable television systems by raising the price of CNN and other 
programming to satellite providers of broadcast video. Similarly, in several recent 
enforcement actions involving health care providers, the Department of Justice has 
challenged health insurance plans with high market shares that adopted ''most-
favored-customer'' provisions, which require affiliated dentists or other providers 
not to accept lower reimbursement rates from any other insurance plans they also 
join. Justice was concerned that such provisions would discourage entry by lower-
cost rival insurance plans, by making it difficult for those rivals to convince providers 
to join their networks. 5 
The Justice Department's 1995 consent decree with Microsoft also addressed 
practices that allegedly harm competition by raising rivals' costs. A key provision </p>

<p>5 The close scrutiny that most-favored-customer provisions receive from the federal enforcement agencies 
also derives from a concern that they may facilitate coordination by discouraging targeted price-cutting 
(Salop, 1986; or see the survey in Baker, 1996). </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 188 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>prevents Microsoft from receiving royalties from computer manufacturers on a per-
processor basis, regardless of whether Microsoft's Windows operating system was 
installed on those machines. Under this provision, a firm effectively pays twice for 
the operating system if it installs an operating system owned by a Microsoft rival-
once to the rival and once to Microsoft-but it pays only once for a computer with 
Microsoft's operating system installed. Gilbert and Shapiro (1997) characterize this 
provision as a ''penalty clause.'' It raises the costs for firms with rival operating 
systems seeking to induce computer manufacturers to adopt a competing operating 
system for some product lines, and could thus protect Microsoft's alleged monopoly 
power in operating systems. 
In the 1995 Microsoft case, the Justice Department was seeking to protect com-
petition in innovation as much as price competition. Protecting incentives for inno-
vation is a common recent theme at the antitrust enforcement agencies. Another ex-
ample occurred when two pharmaceutical producers, Ciba-Geigy and Sandoz, sought 
to merge in 1996. The FTC obtained a consent settlement requiring the merged firm 
(Novartis) to sell off one of the competing research and development efforts in genetic 
engineering to a third firm to protect competition in innovation. Moreover, in a new 
round of Microsoft litigation, the Justice Department is currently asking a court to 
determine whether Microsoft's integration of Internet browser software into Windows 
harms innovation and tends to create or maintain monopoly by excluding rivals selling 
browsers such as <rs type="software">Netscape</rs> (DOJ's view), or promotes innovation and competition by 
improving software design (Microsoft's position). 6 
The widely discussed possibility of network externalities-the benefit that users 
obtain when other customers use the same product, as with much computer soft-
ware-raises the stakes for antitrust enforcers in discriminating between harmful 
and beneficial exclusionary practices. 7 The possibility of network effects increases 
the efficiency benefits of having a single standard in the marketplace, but it may 
also entrench a firm and so allow it to exercise market power in a more damaging 
way. In consequence, antitrust enforcement decisions may be ineffective unless they 
are made early in an industry's development, before a standard becomes so secure 
as to make an antitrust remedy impractical. Yet it may be hard to make reliable 
judgments before uncertainties about the consequences of the challenged conduct 
have been fully resolved in the marketplace. </p>

<p>New Developments in Analyzing Unilateral Anticompetitive Effects 
of Mergers </p>

<p>Unilateral theories of the anticompetitive effect of mergers have become com-
mon in the internal analyses of antitrust enforcement agencies during the last de-</p>

<p>6 For a range of views on competitive issues raised by the Microsoft case, see the conference volume 
edited by Eisenach and Lenard (forthcoming); see also Carlton and Waldman (1998). 
7 For more discussion of network externalities, see Carlton and Klamer (1983); the Symposium on Net-
work Externalities in the Spring 1994 issue of this journal; and Shapiro and Varian (1999). </p>

<p>Policy Watch: Developments in Antitrust Economics 189 </p>

<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 189 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>cade. Instead of focusing on how a merger could make coordination more likely 
or more effective, the unilateral theories describe how a merger would make it 
profitable for the merged firm to raise price without assuming repeated play, as by 
taking rivals' reactions as given. 8 
Two developments in economics spurred the recent interest in unilateral the-
ories. The first was a theoretical literature that investigated the conditions under 
which oligopolists would find merger profitable even if the industry members were 
not coordinating their actions, but were instead taking each other's output or price 
as given, consistent with Cournot-Nash or Bertrand-Nash solution concepts (Salant, 
Switzer and Reynolds, 1983; Deneckere and Davidson, 1985; Perry and Porter, 1985; 
Farrell and Shapiro, 1990). The second was an empirical literature encouraged by 
the simultaneous development of new econometric tools and computerized point-
of-sale scanner data (Baker and Bresnahan, 1985; Berry and Pakes, 1993; Hausman, 
Leonard and Zona, 1994; Werden and Froeb, 1994; Baker, 1997a). These tools and 
data can make it possible to identify the extent to which buyers consider individual 
products to be close substitutes; the extent to which, in consequence, individual 
products constrain the pricing of rivals; and the extent to which mergers encourage 
higher prices by removing those constraints. The 1992 revisions to the DOJ and 
FTC Horizontal Merger Guidelines recognize these economic developments by de-
scribing several ways in which a merger can lessen competition through unilateral 
effects; see also Willig (1991). 
The most common unilateral theory can be illustrated by a hypothetical 
example in which many buyers of one firm's Crunchy cereal brand view a rival's 
Fruity brand as their second choice at current prices. A merger between the 
firms would provide an incentive to increase the price of the Crunchy brand. 
Before the merger, a higher Crunchy price would lead to some loss of sales to 
the Fruity firm. But if the Crunchy firm acquires the Fruity firm, then it will 
recapture some of the contribution to profit on the lost Crunchy sales through 
an increase in Fruity sales. Accordingly, the merger removes Fruity as a com-
petitive constraint on Crunchy pricing. This problem is the most serious if the 
Fruity and Crunchy brands are the closest substitutes for each other, but that is 
not necessary for competitive harm to occur. The merged firm has some unilat-
eral incentive to raise the Crunchy price even if most of the lost sales go to brands 
other than Fruity-as long as some of the lost sales go to Fruity. Moreover, the 
merger could lead to higher prices even if the merging firms account for small 
shares of the breakfast cereals category. 
The application of this unilateral theory of anticompetitive effect is contro-
versial; not because the economic theory is questioned, but because the results 
can be demonstrated through methods (such as the estimation of demand cross-
elasticities between only a few products) that do not necessarily require an over-</p>

<p>8 A merger that operates as a commitment to less aggressive conduct, leading to higher prices when 
rivals would predictably respond by acting less aggressively as well, would also harm competition unilat-
erally, though some might instead view this outcome as coordinated. </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 190 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>all definition of a market (Baker, 1997c). Under such circumstances, the tradi-
tional practice of not challenging mergers among firms with low market shares 
(memorialized in ''safe harbors'' based on market concentration in the Merger 
Guidelines) may be undermined. Some critics make this point by arguing that 
this approach is tantamount to reviving the concept of ''submarkets''-or very 
narrow definitions of markets-which Chicago school antitrust commentators 
had attempted to discredit. 
Although the merger in the hypothetical example leads to a higher price so 
long as Crunchy and Fruity have a non-zero demand cross-elasticity, this theory 
does not in fact imply that all mergers among sellers of differentiated products will 
harm competition. Other forces, recognized in the merger guidelines though ig-
nored in the above example, may undermine or counteract the merged firm's in-
centive to raise price. These include: product repositioning, in which a third firm, 
Oaties, responds to the Crunchy price rise by adding Crunchy Oaties to its product 
line; efficiencies, in which the merger may lower marginal cost, leading the post-
merger price to fall notwithstanding the loss of direct competition between the 
brands; and entry by other firms. 
In some cases it is possible to estimate demand cross-elasticities among the 
products of the merging firms; data limitations and the econometric problem 
of identification are the most common hurdles. Information on cross-elasticities 
can then be used-in combination with estimates of price and marginal cost for 
the relevant products-to make inferences about the strength of the merged 
firm's incentive to raise price. One approach for making such inferences reports 
the extent to which the demand curve faced by the firm will grow steeper as a 
result of the transaction (Baker and Bresnahan, 1985). Another approach sim-
ulates the profit-maximizing post-merger prices, thereby incorporating infor-
mation or assumptions about the non-local (and perhaps out-of-sample) behav-
ior of demand and marginal cost (Shapiro, 1996; Werden, 1996, 1997; Hausman 
and Leonard, 1997). 9 Even when quantitative estimates of the information 
needed to employ these techniques-such as demand cross-elasticities, marginal 
cost, the pass-through rate, or the oligopoly solution concept-are unavailable 
or imprecise, these methods can still inform the evaluation of qualitative infor-
mation. 
The unilateral theory based upon the loss of localized competition among 
sellers of differentiated products underlies a number of recent consent settle-
ments reached between merging firms and the FTC or Department of Justice in </p>

<p>9 These are not the only ways econometric methods are now used to demonstrate unilateral anticom-
petitive effects of mergers. In litigating its successful challenge to the Staples/Office Depot merger, for 
example, the FTC introduced an econometric study to show that head-to-head competition among office 
superstore chains within metropolitan areas lowered the price of consumable office supplies (Baker, 
forthcoming). This study related variation in Staples' prices to changes in the number and identity of 
rivals; it was not an effort to estimate demand cross-elasticities. Other econometric methods of measuring 
market power are surveyed in Bresnahan (1989) and Baker and Bresnahan (1992). </p>

<p>Jonathan B. Baker 191 </p>

<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 191 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>consumer product industries. For example, the FTC recently required two merg-
ing producers of distilled spirits, Grand Met and Guinness, to divest Dewars 
scotch and Bombay gin to resolve competitive problems arising from that trans-
action. Similarly, the Justice Department recently entered into a consent decree 
requiring Continental Baking Co., which markets Wonder Bread, to spin off a 
brand of white bread in each of several regions of the country before acquiring 
Interstate Bakeries Corp. 
This model also applies outside of industries selling branded consumer prod-
ucts. For example, antitrust enforcers analyzing a proposed merger of accounting 
firms might ask whether the merger partners have greater expertise in auditing 
firms in certain industries, making them closer substitutes than rival firms for that 
business. A different unilateral theory, involving an auction model, was employed 
by the FTC staff to analyze the competitive effects of a merger involving two large 
drug store chains (Baker, 1997b). </p>

<p>Concluding Comment </p>

<p>Three decades ago, antitrust law relied heavily upon ''per se'' rules, which 
took the broad brush approach of deeming certain classes of business practices 
anticompetitive without regard to their effects in any particular case. Today, a 
case-by-case analysis is more common, often under the judicial rubric of applying 
the ''rule of reason.'' For example, in 1997, the Supreme Court ruled that max-
imum resale price maintenance (a practice by which a manufacturer capped 
dealer resale prices) would no longer be considered illegal per se. Similarly, at 
one time any attempt among sellers of substitutes to engage in price-fixing or 
market division was universally condemned; today, these practices could be al-
lowed if they are necessary to create a valuable new product, as when separately 
owned teams create a sports league and set prices jointly or when separately 
owned moving companies in different cities adopt a common brand name. More-
over, antitrust enforcers and courts have shifted from relying primarily on mar-
ket share evidence to predicting the competitive consequences of business prac-
tices; today, market definition and market shares are increasingly treated as 
merely one element in a detailed economic analysis of the consequences of the 
particular conduct at issue. 
A benefit of this trend toward a more detailed economic analysis of individual 
practices is that it can reduce errors in determining the likely effects of business 
conduct. The FTC's successful challenge to the Staples/Office Depot merger, for 
example, might have come out differently under the old approach. The govern-
ment's case was probably weakest in the market definition question (in showing 
that office superstores were a relevant product market excluding other channels 
for the distribution of office supplies) and strongest in offering direct evidence 
(documentary and econometric) that the merger would probably lead to higher 
prices for consumers. However, better analysis of individual cases may come at the </p>



<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 192 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>

<p>expense of reducing the clarity of legal rules and the certainty of their application, 
which affects both judges evaluating antitrust claims and firms wondering whether 
a proposed course of conduct would violate the antitrust laws. The increased reli-
ance on case-specific economic analysis may also add to the cost and time involved 
in investigating and litigating cases. However this tradeoff is resolved-that is, re-
gardless of whether economic models are used to design ''per se'' rules or to pro-
vide insights to guide the evaluation of case-specific evidence-economic analysis 
remains central to antitrust practice. </p>

<p>The views expressed are not necessarily those of the Federal Trade Commission or any 
individual Commissioner. The author is indebted to Dennis Carlton, Malcolm Coate, David 
Reiffen, Daniel Rubinfeld, Steven Salop, Louis Silvia, Charles Thomas, Gregory Vistnes, 
Gregory Werden, and Robert Willig. </p>





<p>/ 300f ja01 Mp 194 Tuesday Dec 21 04:45 PM LP-JEP ja01 </p>







</text></tei>