<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs00148-011-0355-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract We study the effects of immigration on the diversity of consump-
tion choices. Data from California in the 1990s indicate that immigration is 
associated with fewer stand-alone retail stores and a greater number of large 
and in particular big-box retailers-evidence that likely contradicts a diversity-
enhancing effect of immigration. In contrast, focusing on the restaurant sector 
for which we can better identify the types of products consumed by customers, 
we find that immigration is associated with increased ethnic diversity of 
restaurants. This latter effect appears to come in part from the comparative 
advantage of immigrants in the production of ethnic goods. </p>

<p>The share of foreign-born workers in the US labor force increased from 6.5% 
in 1980 to 13.3% in 2007. Contemporaneous with the remarkable surge in 
immigration, a controversial debate has arisen on the economic consequences 
of immigration-in large part focused on whether immigrants compete with 
natives for jobs and hence reduce wages for US workers. Economic theory can 
be readily used to justify concerns over the effects of immigrant inflows on 
outcomes for natives who compete with immigrants for similar jobs (see, e.g., 
Borjas 2009; Davis and Weinstein 2002), and an extensive empirical literature 
assesses these effects. 
A much less studied question is the effect of immigration on the variety 
of consumption choices in the destination country. Because immigrants are 
consumers with potentially different demand characteristics and also may have 
a comparative advantage in the production of ethnic goods, their arrival may 
change the composition of products available to consumers. The sign of the 
effect of immigration on product diversity, which can result from both output 
demand and labor supply shifts, is ambiguous. To the extent that immigrants 
have higher price elasticities of demand and/or less attachment to brands, they 
may increase demand for low-cost, standardized goods such as those often 
thought to be offered by big-box retailers, potentially reducing diversity in 
consumption choices. On the other hand, because of the differentiated variety 
of products that immigrants consume and produce, an inflow of foreign-born 
individuals may increase the diversity of consumption choices available to 
natives in non-tradable services, such as retail trade and restaurants. Our 
research attempts to quantify some of these "composition/variety" effects-
which have been often mentioned in the immigration literature but hardly ever 
modeled or measured. 
To investigate the effects of immigration on product diversity, we focus 
on small areas that experienced different immigration inflows. The immigrant 
inflows would only be expected to have effects on local markets for goods and 
services that are locally produced and non-traded; hence, our focus is on these 
non-tradable sectors, in particular the retail trade and the restaurant sector. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>We use data from the National Establishment Time Series (NETS) database </p>

<p>1 The proportion of goods and services consumed by immigrants might be too small to affect 
the product demand curve for nationally-traded goods ("traded"); and goods that are traded 
nationally may also be traded internationally, so immigration does not necessarily change the 
demand or supply of these goods. Regardless, our identification strategy focuses on local markets, 
and it is not clear how one would identify the effects on national markets. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>matched with Census of Population data. The NETS covers essentially all es-
tablishments, and provides detailed information on both geographical location 
and industry. We use NETS data for the entire state of California, mapping 
each business establishment in the NETS to its Census tract and merging the 
NETS data with Census of Population data on changes in the total and foreign-
born population residing in each tract. California is an immigrant-rich area; in 
2000, the state was home to one third of all foreign-born individuals living 
in the USA. Our empirical evidence is based on the relationships between 
immigrant inflows into local areas and a number of dimensions of change in 
the employment and composition of businesses in these local areas. Strictly 
speaking, then, we do not measure output but infer the effects of immigration 
on the composition of output from changes in the composition of employment 
and businesses. </p>

<p>2 Prior research on the effects of immigration on product variety </p>

<p>In contrast to the extensive literature on immigration and natives' labor 
outcomes, there is far less work that investigates how immigration changes 
product diversity. There is, in fact, relatively little work that even tries to 
measure product demand shifts associated with immigration (Borjas 2009, 
footnote 8) or effects of immigration on prices, which might be viewed as 
prerequisites for immigration to have much effect on product diversity. As 
such, we start by briefly reviewing the available evidence on product demand 
shifts and price effects. 
Using store-level price data, Lach (2007) finds a large and significant 
reduction in prices following the unexpected arrival of a large number of 
immigrants from the former Soviet Union in Israel during 1990. The short-
run nature of the empirical analysis-restricted to changes in prices in 1990-
limits the extent to which the negative immigration effect can be explained 
by declines in retail costs stemming from an outward labor supply shift, and 
in fact the immigration-induced labor supply shocks were arguably small in 
light of the low labor force participation of the recently arrived immigrants. 
If interpreted as demand-side effects, Lach's results are consistent with new 
consumers having higher price elasticities and lower search costs than the 
native population. In addition, evidence for prices for different product cat-
egories is consistent with product demand shifts induced by immigration, as 
prices increased more for products representing a relatively larger share of 
expenditures for immigrants. 
Bodvarsson et al. (2008) analyze the effects of the inflow of Cuban immi-
grants into Miami after the Mariel Boatlift of 1980. They find a positive and 
significant impact of immigrant inflows on retail sales per capita, and interpret 
their findings as evidence of positive consumer demand effects. Finally, the 
study of Bodvarsson and Van den Berg (2006) of Hispanic immigration to 
Dawson County, Nebraska-a uniquely segmented economy where immi-
grants work exclusively in an export sector (the meatpacking industry) but, as </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>usual, consume locally-also suggests that immigration can substantially boost 
local consumer demand. 
Evidence consistent with the existence of immigration-induced product 
demand shifts is also available for the UK, where Frattini (2009) finds that 
immigrant inflows between 1995 and 2006 increased the prices of low-value 
and everyday grocery goods-a result interpreted as stemming from demand 
side effects and which parallels some of our later findings for the retail sector. 
Saiz (2007) and Cortes (2008) also study the effects of immigration on prices, 
but with a different focus. Saiz studies immigrants' demand for housing and 
subsequent changes in housing rents, while Cortes studies how immigration 
changes the price of domestically produced products through declines in labor 
costs. 
As this brief review indicates, empirical research on how immigration affects 
host countries has recently moved away from its almost exclusive focus on 
labor markets to include effects on product demand and prices. Changes in 
prices are important because-aside from reflecting product demand shifts-
they affect real income and its distribution, in ways that depend on natives' 
consumption patterns. However, what are still largely ignored in most empiri-
cal research are the potential benefits from immigration in terms of increasing 
the variety of consumption choices in the destination country. 
One of the commonly cited benefits of immigration is that the diversity of 
the population is enhanced. Although diversity is often touted as a benefit in 
and of itself, economic models can help explain why diversity might increase 
welfare. Lazear (2000), for example, builds a model in which the gains from 
diversity are greatest when groups have information sets that (1) are disjoint, 
(2) are relevant to one another, and (3) can be learned by the other group at 
low cost. He then empirically evaluates the argument in favor of immigration-
induced diversity using the 1990 Census and concludes that current immi-
gration policy fails to foster diversity, while balanced immigration, promoted 
through the sale of immigration slots, would enrich the diversity of the US 
population. In other analyses of the economic effects of ethnic diversity 
(Ottaviano and Peri 2006, 2008; Sparber 2008; Amuedo-Dorantes and de la 
Rica 2008; Peri and Sparber 2009), the gains from diversity arise from pro-
ductivity effects (e.g., because of the existence of complementarities between 
workers of different types). 
In this paper, we define and study a different kind of diversity that may be 
induced by immigration-namely, we ask whether immigrant inflows increase 
the variety of products available for consumption. This diversity effect can 
arise for two reasons. First, immigrants consume and hence increase demand 
for "ethnic" goods. And second, they may have a comparative advantage in 
producing ethnic goods, hence increasing the supply of these goods 
2 (a similar </p>

<p>2 See Chiswick (2009) for a formal treatment of the relevance of ethnicity for economic analysis 
through these two channels (that is, that ethnic groups differ in their consumption patterns as well 
as in their supply of resources). </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>effect can stem from any kind of frictions or preferences that lead immigrants 
to increase labor supply in industries producing ethnic goods). The increased 
diversity of goods in the product market generated by immigration may 
then lead to welfare improvements for natives that have relatively stronger 
preferences for ethnic goods. </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>In economics, there is a well-established trade literature modeling and esti-
mating the welfare gains from increased varieties of traded goods. Broda and 
Weinstein (2006), building on the seminal work of Krugman (1979) and on the 
methodology developed by Feenstra (1994), model international trade within a 
framework of differentiated goods and estimate the contribution of imports of 
new varieties to national welfare in the USA. Using disaggregated US import 
data, they find that US consumers have low elasticities of substitution across 
similar goods produced in different countries, and calculate the gain from the 
threefold increase in import varieties between 1972 and 2001 to be 2.6% of 
GDP. 
More closely related to what we do is the study by Ottaviano and Peri 
(2007), which adapts the concept of "consumption variety" effects to the study 
of the economic benefits of immigration. They develop a general equilibrium 
model for a small open economy where individuals are differentiated in 
terms of origin-home-born and foreign-born-and consume two goods-
a homogenous tradable good and a differentiated local non-tradable good. 
Individuals of different origin are assumed to be able to produce different 
varieties of the non-tradable good. In this setting, the non-tradable good 
can be thought of as a composite basket of local services whose supply 
particularly benefits from "ethno-cultural" diversity, such as restaurants, retail 
trade, and entertainment. We build on the approach and attempt to directly 
study the relationship between immigrant inflows and the composition of prod-
ucts available to consumers, focusing on the retail sector and the restaurant 
sector. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 Waldfogel (2008) presents evidence consistent with the idea that an individual consumer's welfare 
can be affected by the agglomeration of individuals with particular tastes in the same market. 
He studies the relationship between the distribution of consumer types and the distribution of 
restaurants, and concludes that "agglomeration of demographically similar persons brings forth 
private products ... preferred by the agglomerating group" (p. 580). Although this research does 
not pertain to immigration per se, it makes the point that the entry of immigrants with similar 
tastes to a subgroup of natives may increase the provision of products preferred by those natives 
and hence increase their welfare, and more generally that the distribution of tastes in the market 
can affect the types of products offered. In the immigration literature, see Hatton and Leigh (2011) 
for a review of the interaction between ethnic groups and the host society, and the process by which 
the non-immigrant community accepts, accommodates, and adapts to inflows from particular 
immigrant groups. 
4 In the model of Ottaviano and Peri (2007), it is instead assumed that immigration increases the 
ethnic diversity of some local services. When calibrating the model to conditions in the USA, the 
authors specify restaurants and entertainment as the two sectors where immigration may induce 
ethnic diversity. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>3 Empirical approach </p>

<p>We use establishment-level data for California to study the relationships 
between changes in the composition of employment and businesses in a Census 
tract or other local area and immigrant inflows into the same and surrounding 
tracts. Before plunging directly into the analysis of the effects of immigration 
on variety, we present some preliminary analysis of the effects of immigration 
on employment in locally produced, non-traded industries, to establish that 
immigration into a local area affects such industries-a prerequisite for immi-
gration to have effects on the variety of local output. 
When immigrants flow into an area, they increase the demand for locally 
produced, non-traded goods (Altonji and Card 1991). In addition, the out-
ward labor supply shift associated with immigration contributes to higher 
total employment in any industry in which labor supply increases, with the 
magnitude depending on how much the increase in labor supply lowers prices, 
how strongly native labor supply to the industry responds to potential wage 
declines, and the price elasticity of demand for products from which labor 
demand is ultimately derived (Borjas 2009). Of course, immigrant inflows may 
themselves be a response to outward demand shifts in industries that employ 
immigrants, so we have to be cautious about causal inferences. 
These considerations have a few implications. First, to the extent that 
we want to detect demand effects of immigration, we should focus on non-
tradables. Second, although the labor supply effect of immigration can increase 
employment in any industry, it is only for non-tradables that we can reliably 
attribute a change in local variety to local immigration, so, again, we are more 
interested in this sector. And third, the effects might be different in industries 
that are intensive in the use of immigrants. In particular, to the extent that the 
supply effects of immigration are important, we ought to see more of an effect 
of immigration on employment in non-tradable industries that are immigrant-
intensive. 
In addition to these considerations, given our focus on product variety 
we are most interested in industries in which we can infer something about 
variety based on employment patterns. We focus on the retail sector-which 
is non-traded and non-immigrant-intensive-and restaurants-which are also 
non-traded but are immigrant intensive. Much of our analysis in fact focuses 
on the restaurant industry, for which the link between establishments and 
consumption variety is most transparent; in particular, we study the ethnic 
variety of restaurants and how it is affected by immigration. 
We look at the effects of immigration on product diversity along a number 
of dimensions. First, for retail stores, we examine how immigrant inflows are 
associated with changes in the numbers of chain versus stand-alone establish-
ments, as well as establishments of different sizes. The idea behind this analysis 
is that a larger number of small and especially stand-alone establishments-
in contrast to large and/or chain stores-may be associated with increased 
diversity of consumption choices. Immigrant inflows might lead to a prolif-
eration of small or stand-alone establishments to cater to the specific tastes </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>of immigrants that might not be met by the larger, chain stores. On the other 
hand, if immigrants have greater price elasticities of demand (consistent with 
Lach 2007), or if they tend to consume the products in which the large chain 
stores specialize, their arrival could shift the composition of businesses in the 
opposite direction. 
We then take this analysis in a narrower direction that more definitively 
identifies the effects of immigration on the diversity of consumption choices. 
Specifically, we examine whether immigrant inflows and increases in ethnic 
diversity in the local population are associated with a higher share of ethnic 
restaurants and greater diversity of the ethnicity of restaurants in the local 
market. Our analysis is based on detailed ethnic classifications of restaurants 
and characterizations of variety based on Herfindahl-Hirschman indexes. 
Although the focus on restaurants is narrow, the advantage of looking at 
this sector is that we know what types of goods a restaurant's consumers are 
purchasing. In contrast, even if we suggested above that growth of large chain 
stores at the expense of small retailers implies less diversity in consumption, 
chain stores, in principle, could offer a variety of ethnic goods-although 
casual observation suggests that their offerings are in fact quite homogenous. 
Finally, we are generally not concerned with separating the effects of labor 
supply and labor demand shifts that immigration induces. Demand shifts can 
increase product diversity by changing the agglomeration of tastes in a market, 
and supply shifts may play a role in increasing the diversity of consumption 
choices under the likely assumption that immigrants have a comparative 
advantage at producing "ethnic" goods or because of price effects of increased 
labor supply to particular industries. However, some of our analysis attempts 
to assess whether the increased variety of ethnic restaurants that we find likely 
stems more from the demand or from the supply side. </p>

<p>4 Data </p>

<p>4.1 Employment and business establishment composition </p>

<p>Our dependent variables are constructed using data from the NETS database. 
The NETS is a longitudinal file created by Walls and Associates using Dun 
and Bradstreet (D&amp;B) data, which covers all business establishments in the 
USA between 1989 and 2004. The unit of observation in the NETS is a 
business establishment, which is a business or industrial unit at a single physical 
location that produces or distributes goods or provides services. Using the 
headquarters' DUNS number, we can tell whether an establishment is a stand-
alone firm or a branch of a multi-establishment firm. The data in the NETS 
do not come from a single survey. Rather, D&amp;B collects the underlying data 
through a massive data collection effort covering many sources, including 
over 100 million telephone calls to businesses each year, as well as obtaining 
information from legal and court filings, newspapers and electronic news 
services, public utilities, all US secretaries of state, government registries and </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>licensing data, payment and collections information, company filings and news 
reports, and the US Postal Service. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>The NETS database does not contain detailed information about establish-
ments, but it does include the business name, a unique D&amp;B establishment 
identifier (the DUNS number), the establishment location, detailed SIC in-
dustrial codes in each year (and a cross-walk to NAICS codes), the identifier 
of the firm's headquarters (also a DUNS number), and employment (as well 
as sales, which we do not use because it is usually imputed) in each year. 
The NETS has unique advantages for the purposes of this study. First, 
after geocoding business establishments' addresses, we can map employment 
at the detailed geographic level; in our case, we do this at the level of the 
Census tract. 
6 Second, the NETS is designed to capture the universe rather 
than a sample of establishments, and hence covers essentially all firms and 
establishments. Third, unlike other sources of data on individual business 
establishments available through the Census Bureau or the Bureau of Labor 
Statistics, the NETS data are not confidential. We are, therefore, able to 
identify specific businesses both in our own work with the data and in the 
reporting of results. Both of these uses of specific business names are important 
in the ensuing analysis; we use company names to identify certain big-box 
retailers and to refine the ethnic classification of restaurants. On the other 
hand, a limitation of the NETS is that it includes no information on the 
composition of employment with respect to skill, immigrant status, or any 
other dimension. 
We use an extract of the NETS data that covers all business establishments 
that were ever located in California between 1992 and 2002. 
7 Given that 
the Census of Population data that we use to measure immigrant inflows 
(discussed next) span a 10-year window ending in 2000, using 2002 as the 
ending year for our analysis makes sense. Moreover, evidence that the NETS 
sometimes detects business births with a lag (Neumark et al. 2007) implies 
that using a 10-year window that is shifted forward by a couple of years </p>

<p>5 The NETS data construction effort-including both the cross-sectional files and the longitudinal 
linking that tracks establishments over time-is a massive and complicated one. Details are 
provided in Neumark et al. (2007). For more information about the NETS and comparisons to 
other data sources, see http://www.youreconomy.org/nets/NETSDatabaseDescription.pdf (viewed 
December 17, 2008). Although the data extend back to 1989, the data prior to 1992 are less reliable 
because only beginning in 1992 was D&amp;B able to purchase Yellow Page information on business 
units. We therefore use data beginning in 1992. 
6 The establishment locations were mapped to Census tracts with GIS software using the Census 
2000 TIGER/Line files as our data source (downloaded from www.esri.com/data). The NETS 
contains the street address of each business establishment, but GIS mapping requires that these 
addresses be "geocoded" to latitude-longitude coordinates. We used a geocoded version of the 
NETS data that was constructed for another research project (Neumark and Kolko 2010). 
7 We only had access to the geocoded NETS data for California for this research. The results 
might not generalize to other states, especially those in which immigrant inflows are much smaller 
relative to the population. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>relative to the Census should provide more accurate measurement of changes 
in employment and the number and types of businesses associated with 
immigrant inflows. Census-tract level summary statistics of the variables used 
in the analysis are reported in Electronic Supplementary Material. </p>

<p>4.2 Total and foreign-born population </p>

<p>Data on total and foreign-born population by Census tract are from the 1990 
and 2000 Censuses of Population. One question is how to define the size of 
the market in which to measure the immigrant inflows that may influence 
the diversity of consumption choices or reflect the availability of choices to 
consumers. We can identify immigrant inflows at the Census tract level. Two 
extreme choices would be to consider the data at the Census tract level or 
instead to aggregate up to the metropolitan statistical area (MSA). 
8 However, 
neither Census tracts nor MSAs seem to provide the right level of aggregation 
to identify the potential pool of customers or establishments located in a given 
tract: the former tend to be too small and also vary widely in size; the latter may 
be too large. And both are based on arbitrary boundaries that are likely to be 
crossed on a daily basis by residents, especially for Census tracts in densely 
populated areas and along borders shared by MSAs. 
To circumvent these problems, we define the pool of potential customers 
for an establishment located in tract c in year t as the weighted sum of the 
population in tracts k (k = 1, . . . , K c ) located in area a(c)-an area that 
encompasses but is larger than c, and is not arbitrarily restricted to MSA 
boundaries: </p>

<p>Pop a(c)t = </p>

<p>k∈a(c) </p>

<p>w ck · Pop kt , 
(1) </p>

<p>8 Census tracts are designed to be relatively homogenous with respect to population characteristics, 
economic status, and living conditions. The spatial size of Census tracts varies widely depending 
on population density. In California there are 7,049 Census tracts, with an average population 
of 4,200 in 1990 and 4,800 in 2000. MSAs include counties that center on an urban core and are 
characterized by a high degree of social and economic integration (as measured by commuting 
to work) with the core. There are 25 MSAs in California, ranging from highly densely populated 
metro areas such as Los Angeles-Long Beach (including 2,054 tracts) to more sparsely populated 
areas such as Merced (including 47 tracts). The analyses reported in this paper exclude the 242 
tracts located outside any MSA, which lie along the sparsely populated northern and eastern 
borders of the State. 
Because Census geography changes over time, we must normalize 1990 and 2000 Census tract 
geographic definitions. Our primary data source is the Neighborhood Change Database (NCDB), 
which provides total and foreign-born population counts from each Census year for each year-
2000 Census tract, mapping the earlier data onto the current boundaries. In the analyses of the 
restaurant sector we also need figures on foreign-born population from different countries, which 
are not available in the NCDB. In this case, we use data from the Census Summary Files (SF4), 
and employ Census Bureau reports of tract level allocation factors to map 1990 tract variables 
to 2000 geography. We would like to thank Justin Marion and Nathaniel Baum-Snow for sharing 
their computer code to implement this procedure. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>where the weights w ck are functions of the distance between the center of tract 
c and the center of tract k, which we denote d c,k . </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Assuming that the likelihood that consumers shop in tract c decreases with 
the distance between c and the tract where they live, we could arbitrarily 
specify w ck as some decreasing function of d c,k . Instead, we define weights 
based on the distances consumers travel. In particular, using data from the 
2001 National Household Travel Survey, we calculate summary statistics on 
the number of miles that Californians travel to go shopping. Figure 1 shows 
smoothed distributions of shopping trips by miles traveled, separately for 
residents in the MSAs of Los Angeles, Orange County, and Riverside (Panel 
A) and for residents in the remainder of the urbanized areas of California 
(Panel B). 
10 We group trips shorter than 5 miles into 1-mile-length bins, trips 
between 5 and 30 miles into 5-mile-length bins, and trips between 30 and 
50 miles into one residual bin. We let δ index these 11 distance bins and 
denote by p δ the proportions of shopping trips in each bin. These proportions 
are graphed in Fig. 1 (piecewise line). For each tract c, we then calculate the 
number of tracts that are δ miles away from c (T cδ ) and set the weights in Eq. 1 
equal to: </p>

<p>w ck = </p>

<p>⎧ 
⎨ </p>

<p>⎩ </p>

<p>p δ 
T cδ 
if d c,k ∈ δ </p>

<p>0 if d c,k &gt; 50 </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>where the values of p δ vary depending on whether tract c is in the Los Angeles, 
Orange County-Riverside area, or elsewhere in the state. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>When characterizing consumption choices available to consumers, we apply 
the same weights to counts of establishments by type. Finally, since we have 
argued that the composition/variety effects of immigration may arise not only 
from immigrants' consumption choices but also from their labor supply; in 
some of our analyses of these latter effects, we also define weights that map 
the distribution of miles traveled by Californians to commute to work. In 
practice, these weights are constructed as in Eq. 2, where the p δ 's represent </p>

<p>9 In practice, the center of a tract is defined by its geometric center, or "centroid." Spherical coor-
dinates of Census 2000 tract centroids were downloaded from the US Census Bureau (http://www. 
census.gov/geo/www/gazetteer/places2k.html) and converted to planar coordinates using <rs type="software">ArcGIS</rs> 
software. 
10 We do not disaggregate further because the sample is small. 
11 The idea behind dividing by T cδ is the following. Suppose that tract c is distance d from tract 
k, and the travel data imply that the proportion p of the trips of those residing in tract k cover 
distance d. Residents of tract k can travel in multiple directions, and we would not expect all 
those traveling distance d to travel to tract c. Instead, we count the number of tracts that are 
distance d from tract c, which we denote T, and assume that 1/T of those who travel distance d 
will travel to tract c. In principle one could try to refine this by taking account of roads and other 
travel infrastructure. Furthermore, this is a simplification, because one would really want to do this 
calculation separately for each tract k within distance d of tract c, calculating the share of those 
from each tract k around tract c that would travel to tract c. The simplified calculation we use, 
however, will still capture the variation in potential inflow from a surrounding tract depending on 
whether tracts in the area are geographically small or geographically large. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>the proportions of work trips of different length (piecewise lines in Fig. 2). 
A comparison of Figs. 1 and 2 reveals that individuals tend to travel longer 
distances to go to work than to go shopping. </p>

<p>5 Econometric analysis </p>

<p>5.1 Preliminary evidence on effects of immigration on local industries </p>

<p>We begin with a brief preliminary analysis relating the growth in employment 
in establishments in industry groupings (indexed by i) located in a given 
Census tract to inflows of immigrant residents into the same and surrounding 
tracts. Following the literature on the effects of immigration (e.g., Card 2001; 
Card and DiNardo 2000; Ortega and Peri 2009), we denote by I t /Pop t−1 
the immigration rate, namely the change in the foreign-born population from 
(t − 1) to t relative to the total population in (t − 1) and estimate regression 
models of the form: </p>

<p>E ict /E ict−1 = α i + β </p>

<p>N 
i </p>

<p>N a(c)t /Pop a(c)t−1 + β </p>

<p>I 
i </p>

<p>I a(c)t /Pop a(c)t−1 + u ict , </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>where E ict is the employment in establishments located in Census tract c in year 
t. The equation also controls for the change in the native population N, which 
is treated symmetrically to the immigration rate and scaled as well relative to 
the initial total population. All population measures are defined in area a(c) 
around Census tract c using the weighting described in the previous subsection. 
Because the model is estimated in differences, it eliminates time-invariant 
Census tract characteristics that may be correlated with both employment and 
population. 
In Eq. 3, comparisons of the estimates of β </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i and β </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>i tell us how inflows 
of immigrants into a local area affect employment in industry i, compared to 
inflows of natives. As discussed earlier, we expect the inflow of immigrants 
(or natives) into an area to have more impact on product and hence labor 
demand in non-tradable industries. Moreover, to the extent that immigrants 
tend to work in particular (non-tradable) industries, those industries ought 
to experience larger employment increases stemming from the labor supply 
increase and hence the lowering of prices for that industry's output; therefore, 
we report results for non-tradable industries divided into those that are less 
and more immigrant-intensive. Finally, because our analysis of the effects of 
immigration on product diversity focuses on the retail sector and on restau-
rants, we also present preliminary evidence based on Eq. 3 for the retail sector 
and the accommodation and food services sector (which includes restaurants). 
For the first classification, we would ideally categorize industries on the 
basis of estimates of the fraction of output that is non-traded. Since these 
estimates are not easily obtained, we have to rely on a standard, but somewhat 
arbitrary, classification of industries. Services have traditionally been classified </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Distribution of shopping trips by miles in California, 2001. a Los Angeles, Orange County, 
and Riverside MSAs. b Rest of California. The figures plot smoothed distributions of shopping 
trips by distance traveled (miles). The distance is between the person's residence and the shopping 
destination. The piecewise lines plot the average frequencies in 1-, 5-or 20-mile distance bins. 
Sample: (a) is based on 1,328 trips made for shopping purposes (general retail, food purchase, 
and personal services) by residents in Los Angeles, Orange County and Riverside; (b) is based on 
1,628 shopping trips made by residents of urbanized areas in the rest of California. 2001 National 
Household Travel Survey </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Distribution of commuting-to-work trips by miles in California, 2001. a Los Angeles, 
Orange County, and Riverside MSAs. b Rest of California. The figures plot smoothed dis-
tributions of trips to work by distance traveled (miles). The distance is between the person's 
residence and the place of work. The piecewise lines plot the average frequencies in 1-, 5-or 
20-mile distance bins. Sample: (a) is based on 598 trips made to go to work by residents in 
Los Angeles, Orange County, and Riverside; (b) is based on 695 trips made to go to work by 
residents of urbanized areas in the rest of California. 2001 National Household Travel Survey </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>as non-tradable industries. More broadly, this is arguably an appropriate 
definition for retail trade, construction, educational services, health care, 
social assistance, food services, repair and maintenance, personal and laundry 
services, and private household services-and in what follows, we will refer 
to this set of industries as non-tradable. Industries including transportation, 
warehousing, accommodation services, and public administration, as well as 
information, and finance, insurance, and professional services, may more often 
serve a larger population than local residents (Jensen and Kletzer 2010), while 
agriculture, mining, manufacturing, utilities, and wholesale trade are more 
clearly classified as strictly traded sectors. 
With regard to immigrant intensiveness, we use information on the existing 
differences in the likelihood of employment of foreign-born individuals across 
industries. 
12 As shown in Table 1, in 2000, foreign-born individuals made up 
around 31% of the total labor force in California. However, foreign-born 
shares in the labor force of (NAICS) two-digit industries were as high as 65% 
in agriculture and as low as 12% in mining-both industries that we classify 
as strictly tradable. Most of the other strictly tradable industries-that is, the 
manufacturing sub-industries and wholesale trade-have higher-than-average 
intensity in the use of immigrant labor. On the contrary, among non-tradable 
industries, some are more immigrant-intensive and others are less so. Note 
in particular that retail is below average in immigrant intensiveness, although 
still fairly intensive in the use of immigrants, while accommodation and food 
services is among the most immigrant-intensive industries. We might, then, 
expect the supply of immigrants to this sector-and restaurants in particular-
to play more of a role in the effects of immigration. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Table 2 reports the estimates of Eq. 3 for different industry groups. Given 
the uneven distribution of employment by industry and tract, regressions are 
weighted by the number of employees in tract c and industry i in 1992. Standard 
errors are clustered at the MSA level to correct for heteroscedasticity and 
arbitrary correlation across tracts located in the same MSA. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>As shown in column 1, Panel A, a 1% increase in native population is 
associated on average with a statistically significant 1.4% increase in em-
ployment when looking at all industries, whereas a similar increase in the 
immigrant population is associated with a smaller (but still significant) em-
ployment increase of 0.95%; the difference between the effects of native 
versus immigrant population inflows is marginally significant ( p = 0.11). When </p>

<p>12 Of course, we cannot classify industries strictly on the basis of the immigrant-intensiveness of 
their labor input, in part because there is a continuum of characteristics, and in part because these 
characteristics are not immutable. For example, an industry that is non-intensive in immigrant 
labor can still absorb immigrant labor, and the composition of the labor input in different 
industries can change with immigration. 
13 Immigrant intensiveness in the restaurant sector (43.4%) is virtually the same as in the broader 
accommodation and food services sector (43.5%). 
14 The estimation results presented in the paper are robust to running unweighted regressions 
and to clustering the standard errors at a higher level (across the 17 Consolidated Metropolitan 
Statistical Areas in California). </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>Table 1 Immigrant shares in the California labor force, by industry (2000) </p>

<p>Immigrant 
Percentage of labor force 
share (%) 
Total 
Foreign-born </p>

<p>Overall average 
30.53 
Industry 
Above average 
Agriculture, forestry, fishing, and hunting 
TR 
65.16 
1.97 
4.04 
Manufacturing: food and textile 
TR 
61.75 
2.27 
4.63 
Accommodation and food services 
NT 
43.53 
6.06 
8.61 
Manufacturing: metal, electrical, 
TR 
43.08 
8.49 
12.07 
and electronic 
Admin., support, waste mgmt. services 
NT 
40.05 
4.12 
5.44 
Repair, personal, household services 
NT 
39.54 
5.04 
6.56 
Manufacturing: paper and chemical 
TR 
38.03 
2.42 
3.03 
Wholesale trade 
TR 
36.75 
4.02 
4.88 
Construction 
NT 
31.41 
6.24 
6.37 
Below average 
Mail and warehousing 
-
28.98 
1.28 
1.23 
Transportation 
-
28.43 
2.68 
2.50 
Retail trade: miscellaneous 
NT 
28.27 
7.12 
6.63 
Health care and social assistance 
NT 
28.10 
9.88 
9.11 
Retail trade: hobby and general 
NT 
24.86 
3.89 
3.17 
Real estate, rental, and leasing 
-
23.24 
2.13 
1.63 
Finance and insurance 
-
22.93 
4.63 
3.48 
Professional, scientific, and technical serv. 
-
22.59 
7.25 
5.39 
Management of companies/enterprises 
-
19.12 
0.04 
0.02 
Information 
-
19.11 
3.90 
2.48 
Arts, entertainment, and recreation 
-
18.73 
2.06 
1.25 
Educational services 
NT 
17.24 
8.41 
4.74 
Utilities 
TR 
14.70 
0.77 
0.38 
Public administration 
-
13.41 
5.16 
2.28 
Mining 
TR 
12.23 
0.16 
0.06 </p>

<p>NAICS two-digit industries ranked by the share of foreign-born in the labor force, from the most 
immigrant-intensive sector to the least 
2000 Census 
TR traded industries; NT non-traded industries </p>

<p>we restrict attention to non-tradable industries, in column (2), we see-as 
expected-larger effects of both types of population inflows. Again, the effect 
of immigrants is smaller than the effect of natives, although the difference is 
not significant. Nonetheless, the lower point estimates for immigrant inflows 
may reflect the fact that immigrants are on average lower earners, and remit 
some of their income to their home countries. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Columns (3) and (4) break up non-tradable industries into non-immigrant-
intensive and immigrant-intensive. Contrary to what we might expect if im-
migrants tend to push out labor supply in immigrant-intensive industries (and </p>

<p>15 Immigrants are also younger. In 2000 Census data for California, the share of prime-age 
individuals (25-44 years old) was 49% among the adult foreign-born population, but only 37% 
among natives. On the contrary, the shares over 65 were, respectively, 10% and 17%. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>Table 2 Percentage growth in employment across Census tracts and immigrant and native 
population growth in surrounding areas </p>

<p>Non-traded, 
Non-traded, 
All 
Non-
non-immigrant immigrant 
Accommodation 
industries traded intensive 
intensive 
Retail and food 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Percentage 
1.385 a 
1.893 b 2.654 a 
1.824 a 
2.997 a 5.281 a 
growth in 
(0.132) 
(0.210) (0.310) 
(0.510) 
(0.581) (0.917) 
native 
population 
Percentage 
0.945 a 
1.321 a 1.119 b 
0.690 
1.078 b 4.250 b 
growth in 
(0.232) 
(0.432) (0.451) 
(1.417) 
(0.437) (1.968) 
immigrant 
population 
Constant 
0.036 
0.085 c 0.250 a 
0.287 
0.257 a 
0.421 b 
(0.027) 
(0.050) (0.039) 
(0.207) 
(0.078) (0.158) 
Observations 
6,793 
6,789 
6,776 
6,782 
6,753 
5,960 
F-test 
2.711 
1.455 
6.528 
0.836 
9.982 
0.245 
(H 0 : β N = β I ) 
Probability &gt;F 
0.113 
0.240 
0.017 
0.370 
0.004 
0.625 </p>

<p>Dependent variable: 1992-2002 percentage change in the number of employees in establishments 
located in a Census tract in the industry or industries indicated. Immigrant and native population 
figures are defined as the weighted sum of the population in surrounding tracts in the 1990 
and 2000 Censuses, with weights reflecting the distribution of shopping trips from the National 
Household Travel Survey, 2001. The number of observations varies across columns because 
Census tracts with no observations in an industry in 1992 are dropped. The universe is 6,793 
populated Census tracts located within one of the 25 MSAs in California. Estimates are weighted 
by the tract-industry employment level in 1992. Standard errors (in parentheses) are clustered at 
the MSA level 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
c Significant at 10% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database, 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>

<p>this may not be what happens because of, for example, natives' employment 
responses), the estimated effect of immigration on employment in the 
immigrant-intensive industries is smaller (0.69 versus 1.12), and is imprecisely 
estimated. 
To focus more sharply on the sectors on which we concentrate in our main 
analysis of immigration and product diversity, columns (5) and (6) report 
results for the retail and the accommodation and food services industries. The 
results for retail are similar to those for non-traded industries overall and even 
more so to non-traded, non-immigrant-intensive industries (column (3)). In 
particular, the effect of immigrant inflows is substantially weaker than that of 
native inflows. In contrast, for accommodation and food services, the effects 
of both native and immigrant inflows are large, and the effect of immigrants 
is almost as large as (and not significantly different from) the effect of native 
inflows. 
This preliminary analysis leads to a couple of conclusions, as well as setting 
the stage for some of the analyses we report next. First, immigrant inflows are </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>associated with increased employment in both retail and accommodation and 
food services. This provides some prima facie evidence for studying the effects 
of immigration on the composition of output in these industries. Second, the 
effect is much greater in the latter industry, which is at least consistent with 
labor supply mattering more in the accommodation and food services industry. 
This is consistent with other evidence we report below on how immigrants 
affect product diversity in the restaurant sector. At the same time, we do not 
find similar evidence of a larger relative (or absolute) effect of immigration 
on non-traded, immigrant-intensive industries generally, perhaps because, in 
this case, immigrants move into industries that have not been as immigrant-
intensive in the past. The pattern could be different in the restaurant sector 
because of a comparative advantage of immigrants in the production of ethnic 
food corresponding to their country of origin. Below, we present evidence 
consistent with this as well. </p>

<p>5.2 Econometric analysis of the composition/diversity effects of immigration </p>

<p>We now turn to evidence on the effects of immigration on the variety of 
consumption choices available to natives. We estimate models that relate 
changes in measures of the composition of businesses (such as the share of 
establishments of a certain type K, e.g., defined by size) to measures of changes 
in the composition of the population by nativity and ethnicity (such as the 
share of immigrants over the total population). Our interest in this analysis is in 
how immigration affects the consumption options of residents of a particular 
Census tract. Because these residents may travel to surrounding tracts when 
they shop or go out to eat, and because the consumption choices in these 
surrounding tracts (as well as their own tract) are likely, in general, to be 
shaped in part by the role of immigrants as consumers, in this analysis both 
the dependent and independent variables are defined as aggregates of tracts 
that correspond to the shopping area centered on a given tract of residence 
c, using the weights defined in Eq. 2. We therefore estimate equations of the 
form: </p>

<p>logEstab 
typeK _share a(c)t = η + δ log(I/Pop) a(c)t + φ logPop a(c)t + ξ a(c)t . </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>The dependent variable is the change in the log of the share of establishments 
that are of type K. The coefficient δ captures the potential effect of the 
immigrant share of the population on the composition of businesses. Since 
size per se arguably leads to more diversity, 
16 the equation also controls 
for changes in the population. Because the equation is estimated in first 
differences with an intercept, the estimates are not influenced by aggregate </p>

<p>16 For example, in Krugman (1979), growth in the labor force (which may stem from immigration, 
as well as from other changes) increases varieties available in the market solely because of 
economies of scale in production. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>time-series relationships between structural changes in the economy-such as 
the advent of big-box retailing-and immigration. 
When we turn to the narrower analysis of restaurants, the consumption 
choices available to natives may also be shaped by the role of immigrants as 
workers, because immigrants may have a comparative advantage in the pro-
duction of ethnic goods. In this analysis, therefore, we also estimate equations 
where the immigrant share of the population is defined in area a(c) centered on 
c, but defined using weights that map the distribution of commuting-to-work 
trips, rather than the distribution of shopping trips. </p>

<p>5.3 Retail stores </p>

<p>We focus first on the retail sector. Table 3 looks at changes in the share or 
number of stores by size of the business, using three size categories: stores with 
1 to 9, 10 to 99, and 100 or more employees. As shown in Panel A, columns (1) 
through (3), growth in the share of the foreign-born population is associated 
with a decline in the share of very small retail establishments and increases in </p>

<p>Table 3 Growth of establishments of different sizes and growth in the foreign-born share across 
bundles of Census tracts </p>

<p>Retail stores 
All 
Food, clothing, general merchandise, 
miscellaneous 
Number of employees 
1-9 
10-99 
100+ 
1-9 
10-99 
100+ 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Panel A: Dependent variable: log share of stores 
log foreign share 
−0.041 b 
0.255 c 
0.390 
−0.048 b 
0.357 b 
0.280 
(0.017) 
(0.136) 
(0.258) 
(0.018) 
(0.156) 
(0.280) 
log population 
−0.030 c 
0.273 b 
0.280 
−0.019 
0.244 
0.409 c 
(0.015) 
(0.127) 
(0.214) 
(0.014) 
(0.152) 
(0.213) 
Panel B: Dependent variable: log number of stores 
log foreign share 
−0.374 b 
−0.078 c 
0.056 
−0.386 c 
0.019 
−0.059 
(0.141) 
(0.041) 
(0.194) 
(0.209) 
(0.108) 
(0.193) 
log population 
0.703 a 
1.006 a 
1.013 a 
0.804 a 
1.067 a 
1.232 a 
(0.151) 
(0.121) 
(0.176) 
(0.140) 
(0.138) 
(0.214) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: Change in the log of the share (Panel A) or the log of the number (Panel B) of 
retail establishments with one to nine employees, 10 to 99 employees, or 100 or more employees. 
Sample in columns (1)-(3) is restricted to establishments with NAICS two-digit codes 44 and 45 
(retail trade). Sample in columns (4)-(6) is restricted to establishments with NAICS 3-digit codes: 
445 (grocery stores); 448 (clothing stores, except luggage and leather goods); 452 (department and 
other general merchandise stores); and 453 (miscellaneous stores, except pet supplies stores and 
manufactured home dealers). Both dependent variables and population figures are defined for 
aggregates of tracts, with weights reflecting the distribution of shopping trips from the National 
Household Travel Survey, 2001. Observations: 6,807 tracts within MSAs. Estimates are weighted 
by the number of retail establishments across aggregates of tracts in 1992. Standard errors (in 
parentheses) are clustered at the MSA level 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
c Significant at 10% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database, 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>the shares of both medium-sized and large stores (although the latter effect is 
not statistically significant). As shown in Panel B, this compositional change 
stems from a drop in the number of small stores. The estimates imply that a 
10% increase in the share of the foreign-born population is associated with a 
4% drop in the number of small establishments. 
As suggested earlier, a decreasing share or number of small retail establish-
ments may be associated with less diverse consumption choices. This argument 
is more likely to hold for products such as food, clothes, or other consumption 
goods such as decorations and gifts but is likely less relevant for items such 
as auto parts, hardware, or electronics-because the latter are more likely to 
be uniform across stores of different sizes, and at any rate unlikely to display 
variation in the "ethnicity" of goods. Therefore, we next restrict the analysis to 
the subset of the retail sector in which it is more likely that more small stores 
implies greater diversity (possibly along ethnic lines); we define this subset to 
include grocery, clothing and general merchandise stores, as well as a series of 
miscellaneous stores that specialize in items such as art supplies, posters, coins, 
decorations, or collectibles. As shown in columns (4) through (6), in this case, 
also, growth in the share of the foreign-born population is associated with a 
drop in both the number and share of very small retail stores, and growth in 
the share of larger stores. 
In the next two tables, we look at the same question but characterizing the 
composition of retail stores differently. In Table 4, we study the differential 
growth in small businesses identified on the basis of the number of estab-
lishments in California with the same DUNS headquarter number. First, we 
identify stand-alone stores as those with no other establishments in California 
with the same DUNS headquarter number. We find that an increasing share 
of immigrants in the population is associated with both smaller shares of and 
fewer stand-alone stores (columns (1) and (4)). We find similar results when 
extending the analysis to a more broadly defined group of small businesses-
including not only stand-alone stores but also small chains, which are identified 
as stores for which no more than nine other stores share the same DUNS head-
quarter number (columns (2) and (5)). As it turns out, though, these findings 
are driven by the stand-alone stores; when we run the analysis separately for 
small chains but excluding the stand-alone stores (columns (3) and (6)), we 
find that an increasing share of immigrants in the population is associated 
with a larger share of stores in small chains (and no effect on the number of 
such stores). Thus, the sharpest result is that an increasing immigrant share is 
associated with declines in stand-alone retail stores. 
In Table 5, we look instead at large chains. Specifically, we exploit the non-
confidentiality of the NETS data to examine effects of immigrant inflows on 
particularly large and well-known big-box retailers. Columns (1) and (2) use 
a narrow list, including Wal-Mart, Kmart, Costco, Target, Lowe's, and Sears, 
while in columns (3) and (4) the list is expanded to also include Best Buy, 
Home Depot, Staples, Office Depot, Circuit City, and Fry's. The first list 
captures general big-box retailers, and the second includes more-specialized 
ones. In 1992, there was on average one big-box retailer from the short list for </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>Table 4 Growth of stand-alone or small-chain establishments and growth in the foreign-born 
share across bundles of Census tracts </p>

<p>Retail sector 
All 
Food, clothing, general merchandise, 
miscellaneous 
Number of stores with One 
1-10 
2-10 
One 
1-10 
2-10 
same headquarter 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>Panel A: Dependent variable: log share of stand-alone or small-chain stores 
log foreign share 
−0.092 a −0.066 a 
0.296 b −0.089 a −0.066 a 
0.335 b 
(0.022) 
(0.014) 
(0.124) 
(0.030) 
(0.021) 
(0.158) 
log population 
−0.059 b −0.051 a 
0.204 
−0.039 
−0.042 a 
0.073 
(0.024) 
(0.015) 
(0.144) 
(0.026) 
(0.014) 
(0.239) 
Panel B: Dependent variable: log number of stand-alone or small chain stores 
log foreign share 
−0.425 a −0.399 a −0.037 
−0.427 c −0.403 c −0.003 
(0.144) 
(0.137) 
(0.122) 
(0.222) 
(0.212) 
(0.128) 
log population 
0.674 a 
0.682 a 
0.937 a 
0.784 a 
0.780 a 
0.895 a 
(0.158) 
(0.149) 
(0.115) 
(0.148) 
(0.138) 
(0.210) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: Change in the log of the number of establishments with unique headquarter 
DUNS number in California (columns (1) and (4)), or whose headquarter DUNS number is 
shared by no more than nine other establishments in California, either including stand-alone stores 
(columns (2) and (5)) or excluding them (columns (3) and (6)). Both dependent variables and 
population figures are defined for aggregates of tracts, with weights reflecting the distribution of 
shopping trips from the National Household Travel Survey, 2001. Observations: 6,807 tracts within 
MSAs. Estimates are weighted by the number of retail establishments across aggregates of tracts 
in 1992. Standard errors (in parentheses) are clustered at the MSA level 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
c Significant at 10% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database, 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>

<p>every 13 Census tracts, and one big-box retailer from the long list for every 
nine tracts. For the two definitions, the average change in the number of big-
box stores between 1992 and 2002 is one more store for every 23 tracts (short 
list) or nine tracts (long list). Most of the establishments that belong to these 
chains are reported to belong to the retail sector, but there are some cases in 
which the sector of activity is wholesale trade (on average, fewer than 10%). 
In columns (1) and (3), we consider all establishments belonging to each chain, 
and in columns (2) and (4), we restrict attention to the retail stores only, as in 
the preceding analyses in this section. 
For these different definitions, we regress the change in the number of 
big-box retail establishments on the change in the share of the foreign-born 
population and the change in the log total population. 
17 The estimates indicate 
that increases in the immigrant share are associated with more big-box retail 
establishments. In particular, the estimates in columns (2) and (4) imply that 
a 10-percentage point increase in the foreign-born population (which is the 
standard deviation of the foreign-born share across tracts) is associated with </p>

<p>17 Note that in this case, because of the large number of tracts with no big-box outlets, the 
dependent variable is the change in levels rather than the change in logs. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>Table 5 Changes in the number of big-box retailers and changes in the foreign-born share across 
bundles of Census tracts </p>

<p>Big-box retailers 
Short list 
Long list 
Reported sector 
Wholesale and 
Retail trade 
Wholesale and 
Retail trade 
of activity 
retail trade 
only 
retail trade 
only 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Panel A: Dependent variable: number of big-box retailer establishments 
foreign share 
0.129 b 
0.168 b 
0.222 
0.247 c 
(0.062) 
(0.069) 
(0.150) 
(0.135) 
log population 
0.093 a 
0.085 a 
0.131 a 
0.126 a 
(0.017) 
(0.018) 
(0.028) 
(0.027) 
Panel B: Dependent variable: big-box retail/total retail establishments 
foreign share 
0.008 
0.019 c 
(0.006) 
(0.009) 
log population 
0.008 a 
0.010 a 
(0.002) 
(0.002) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: Change in the number or share of big-box retailers: Wal-Mart, Kmart, 
Costco, Target, Lowe's, and Sears (columns (1) and (2)); these as well as Best Buy, Home Depot, 
Staples, Office Depot, Circuit City, and Fry's (columns (3) and (4)). Both dependent variables and 
population figures are defined for aggregates of tracts, with weights reflecting the distribution of 
shopping trips from the National Household Travel Survey, 2001. Observations: 6,807 tracts within 
MSAs. Standard errors (in parentheses) are clustered at the MSA level 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
c Significant at 10% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database, 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>

<p>one more big-box store from the short list for every 59 tracts, and one more big-
box store from the long list for every 40 tracts. As shown in Panel B, increases 
in the share foreign-born are also associated with increases in the number of 
big-box retailers as a fraction of all retail establishments, although the estimate 
is significant only for the longer list of big-box chains. 
A potential issue in interpreting the estimates of the coefficients on the 
change in the foreign-born share of the population in this last analysis is 
the endogenous location of immigrants. Despite using first differences, we 
cannot rule out bias from time-varying local factors associated with changes 
in both the number or type of retail establishments and immigrant inflows. 
Big-box retailers may locate in areas where land values are increasing more 
slowly than in other areas, a factor that may also be associated with larger 
immigrant inflows. We cannot directly test this hypothesis, but we did find that 
between 1990 and 2000 the foreign-born population share did not grow faster 
in areas with a larger concentration of big-box retailers in 1992, providing some 
evidence against this particular non-causal interpretation of our estimates. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Moreover, recent evidence (Saiz 2003, 2007; Ottaviano and Peri 2007) suggests </p>

<p>18 We study the association (across tracts and aggregates of tracts) between the 1990-2000 changes 
in the share of the foreign-born population and the share of big-box retailers (in the total number 
of stores) in 1992. The association is negative across tracts, and positive, but not statistically 
significant, across aggregates of tracts based on the weights we use in the regression analysis. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>that immigrant inflows increase rather than decrease rents. This combined 
evidence appears to rule out the possibility that immigrants either flowed into 
areas of declining land values (which therefore would have already had more 
big-box retailers), or caused land values to decline, which could have led to a 
greater concentration of such retailers. 
If we assume that diversified products are more likely to be provided by 
a large number of stand-alone retail stores, and less likely to be provided by 
chain stores and especially big-box retailers, then the findings reported in this 
section suggest that, rather than increasing diversity, immigrants may have the 
opposite effect. This could be due to lower income levels, greater thrift, or 
greater price sensitivity that favors Wal-Marts over smaller outlets. 
19 However, 
an important caveat is that we have no information on the types of goods that 
consumers can buy at different stores. For example, one might associate a big-
box retail store with more uniformity of consumption choices than an equal 
volume of goods sold by numerous small stand-alone stores. But that may not 
always be true. It is possible that we need, for example, a Mexican, Indian, and 
Ethiopian grocery store in a local market in order to be able to buy tortillas, 
na'an, and injera, in addition to the white and whole wheat bread at the local 
Safeway or IGA. But it is also possible that large big-box retailers have the 
capacity to supply a greater variety of types of bread, including many ethnic 
choices. Moreover, many stand-alones are not necessarily purveyors of ethnic 
goods. For example, casual observation suggests that many of the bodegas in 
Manhattan carry similar inventories of food items. Because of this inherent 
limitation in being able to draw conclusions based simply on the number, size, 
and composition of retail outlets, in the next section we turn to the analysis of 
the restaurant sector, for which we can much more readily associate the type 
and variety of establishments with the nature of the consumption choices they 
offer. </p>

<p>5.4 Ethnic restaurants </p>

<p>The industrial classification of establishments in the NETS is extraordinarily 
rich: the dataset includes an 8-digit SIC code that in the case of eating places 
separately identifies restaurants of 15 different ethnicities. The full list of 
ethnic categories as well as other types of eating places is provided in Table 6. 
On the other hand, a shortcoming of the NETS data is that around 40% 
of establishments in the restaurant sector are generally classified as "eating 
places," without identification of a specific category. The availability of the 
company name, however, allows us to substantially refine the classification. 
For example, we can easily identify establishments that belong to well-known 
chains such as MacDonald's or Taco Bell (examples of fast-food places), </p>

<p>19 We are interested in the effects of immigrant inflows without conditioning on their income, as 
the relevant question is the effect of the immigrant inflows actually experienced by the areas we 
study, not what would have happened if there were inflows of immigrants with incomes the same 
as natives. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>Table 6 Distribution of eating places in California by 8-digit SIC categories, 1992 and 2002 </p>

<p>SIC 8-digit industry 
Reported % 
Recoded % 
1992 
2002 
1992 
2002 </p>

<p>Eating places 
42.26 
39.37 
24.30 
20.16 
Ethnic food restaurants 
0.83 
1.06 
0.37 
0.49 
American 
2.61 
1.91 
2.25 
1.65 
Cajun 
0.06 
0.07 
0.03 
0.04 
Chinese 
4.50 
4.17 
6.39 
5.80 
French 
0.61 
0.44 
1.48 
1.34 
German 
0.15 
0.11 
0.28 
0.21 
Greek 
0.16 
0.15 
0.30 
0.26 
Indian/Pakistan 
0.24 
0.38 
0.48 
0.65 
Italian 
2.79 
2.53 
4.21 
3.52 
Japanese 
1.43 
1.75 
1.97 
2.40 
Korean 
0.13 
0.16 
0.19 
0.25 
Lebanese 
0.02 
0.02 
0.02 
0.02 
Mexican 
4.42 
5.10 
8.24 
8.45 
Spanish 
0.07 
0.06 
0.04 
0.05 
Thai 
0.37 
0.57 
0.96 
1.20 
Vietnamese 
0.13 
0.21 
0.32 
0.45 
Other Asian 
0.30 
0.35 
Other Hispanic 
0.04 
0.06 
Other foreign (non-American) 
0.08 
0.07 
Ice cream and soft drink stands 
0.16 
0.32 
0.36 
0.35 
Concessionaire 
0.31 
0.24 
0.28 
0.21 
Frozen yogurt stand 
0.82 
0.32 
0.80 
0.31 
Ice cream stands 
1.69 
1.37 
1.73 
1.36 
Snow cone stand 
0.03 
0.05 
0.03 
0.04 
Soda fountain 
0.06 
0.06 
0.05 
0.05 
Soft drink stand 
0.04 
0.04 
0.03 
0.03 
Fast-food restaurants and stands 
1.92 
1.31 
2.21 
1.60 
Box lunch stand 
0.05 
0.04 
0.04 
0.03 
Carry-out only (except pizza) 
0.94 
0.83 
0.66 
0.54 
Chili stand 
0.02 
0.02 
0.01 
0.01 
Coffee shop 
1.66 
3.12 
2.34 
3.63 
Delicatessen 
1.43 
1.08 
1.34 
0.98 
Drive-in restaurant 
0.65 
0.44 
0.58 
0.39 
Fast-food, chain 
3.96 
7.75 
11.54 
18.81 
Fast-food, independent 
1.55 
1.33 
1.20 
0.98 
Food bars 
0.03 
0.03 
0.03 
0.02 
Grills 
0.49 
0.89 
0.46 
0.58 
Hamburger stand 
0.53 
0.54 
0.47 
0.39 
Hot dog stand 
0.35 
0.31 
0.32 
0.29 
Sandwiches shop 
2.30 
2.24 
1.81 
1.58 
Snack bar 
0.26 
0.22 
0.23 
0.18 
Snack shop 
0.13 
0.10 
0.11 
0.09 
Lunchrooms and cafeterias 
0.03 
0.35 
1.97 
2.18 
Automat 
0.01 
0.01 
0.01 
0 
Cafeteria 
0.42 
0.30 
0.36 
0.23 
Luncheonette 
0.07 
0.05 
0.07 
0.05 
Lunchroom 
0.01 
0 
0.01 
0 
Restaurant, lunch counter 
0.04 
0.05 
0.04 
0.04 
Family restaurants 
0.56 
0.77 
0.44 
0.55 
Family: chain 
0.97 
1.09 
1.19 
1.13 
Family: independent 
1.69 
1.12 
1.42 
0.94 </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>Table 6 (continued) </p>

<p>SIC 8-digit industry 
Reported % 
Recoded % 
1992 
2002 
1992 
2002 </p>

<p>Pizza restaurants 
3.68 
4.3 
4.23 
4.01 
Pizzeria, chain 
1.41 
1.00 
1.34 
1.84 
Pizzeria, independent 
1.40 
0.76 
1.29 
0.68 
Seafood restaurants 
1.13 
0.89 
1.16 
0.96 
Oyster bar 
0.01 
0 
0.01 
0 
Seafood shack 
0.04 
0.11 
0.03 
0.08 
Steak and barbecue restaurants 
0.04 
0.05 
0.17 
0.13 
Barbecue restaurant 
0.56 
0.61 
0.52 
0.56 
Steak restaurant 
0.78 
0.61 
0.53 
0.40 
Other 
Buffet 
0.12 
0.24 
0.10 
0.12 
Café 
2.27 
2.29 
2.07 
2.02 
Caterers 
3.69 
3.79 
3.57 
3.60 
Chicken restaurant 
0.42 
0.43 
0.21 
0.23 
Commissary restaurant 
0.02 
0.02 
0.01 
0.02 
Contract food services 
0.18 
0.18 
0.10 
0.11 
Diner 
0.17 
0.17 
0.16 
0.14 
Dinner theater 
0.03 
0.04 
0.03 
0.04 
Health food restaurant 
0.09 
0.08 
0.09 
0.07 
Total 
100 
100 
100 
100 
Number of establishments 
41,000 
47,608 
41,000 
47,608 </p>

<p>The sample is restricted to business establishments with SIC 4-digit industry 5812. The table 
reports the distribution of SIC 8-digit industries. Percentages shown for italicized entries are for 
restaurants that are not more finely classified. The recoding of establishments is based on the 
company name, as described in the text. For example, we can easily identify well-known chains 
(of fast-food, ice-cream places, and family restaurants). Ethnic restaurants of foreign ethnicity are 
identified based on the presence of foreign words in the company name 
NETS </p>

<p>Cold Stone or Baskin Robbins (examples of ice cream places), and Denny's 
or Sizzler (examples of family restaurants). More important, we can also 
use the company name to identify ethnic restaurants that may have been 
misreported as generic eating places. We do so by searching for words included 
in the business name that point to a specific ethnicity (e.g., "Chinese" or 
"Mandarin," "Japanese" or "Tokyo," "Italy" or "Milan"), or for words from 
the foreign language of reference (e.g., "wok," "samurai," or "trattoria"). Our 
re-classification reduced by nearly half the share of unclassified places and 
substantially increased the share of restaurants of foreign ethnicities. We also 
separately identify three more categories of foreign ethnic restaurants: other 
Asian, other Hispanic, and other foreign ethnic restaurants. 
Paralleling the analysis of the previous section, we are interested in explor-
ing whether the presence of a large (and diverse) foreign-born population 
increases the choices of restaurants available to natives. First, we study the 
relationship between changes in the foreign-born share of the population and 
changes in the share of foreign ethnic restaurants, as in: </p>

<p>logEthnic_share a(c)t = η + δ log(I/Pop) a(c)t + φ log Pop a(c)t + ζ a(c)t . (5) </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>Columns (1) and (2) of Table 7 present estimates of Eq. 5 for three different 
levels of aggregation: in Panel A we add up the number of restaurants and 
all population figures in tracts using the shopping weights defined in Eq. 2. 
In Panel B, we use shopping weights to define the growth of restaurants and </p>

<p>Table 7 Changes in the share of foreign ethnic restaurants and changes in the share of foreign-
born population across bundles of Census tracts </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Foreign ethnic restaurants/ 
Hispanic ethnic restaurants/ 
all eating places 
all eating places 
Excluding 
Excluding 
caterers, 
caterers, 
fast food, 
fast food, 
Excluding 
ice-cream 
Excluding 
ice-cream 
caterers 
places 
caterers 
places 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Panel A: Aggregation of all variables using weights from distribution of shopping trips 
log foreign share 
0.180 b 
0.229 a 
(0.066) 
(0.069) 
log foreign Hispanic share 
0.364 a 
0.359 a 
(0.048) 
(0.055) 
log foreign non-Hispanic share 
−0.130 
−0.114 
(0.092) 
(0.089) 
log population 
−0.058 
0.111 
0.201 
0.400 b 
(0.097) 
(0.101) 
(0.176) 
(0.187) 
Panel B: As in Panel A except foreign share defined using commuting weights 
log foreign share 
0.440 a 
0.407 a 
(0.108) 
(0.116) 
log foreign Hispanic share 
0.458 a 
0.384 a 
(0.079) 
(0.088) 
log foreign non-Hispanic share 
−0.105 
−0.093 
(0.159) 
(0.157) 
log population 
−0.087 
0.116 
0.217 
0.447 b 
(0.088) 
(0.094) 
(0.200) 
(0.213) 
Panel C: Aggregation of variables across MSAs 
log foreign share 
0.632 a 
0.584 a 
(0.089) 
(0.086) 
log foreign Hispanic share 
0.361 a 
0.274 b 
(0.093) 
(0.102) 
log foreign non-Hispanic share 
−0.050 
−0.012 
(0.145) 
(0.146) 
log population 
−0.857 a 
−0.645 a 
−0.378 
−0.068 
(0.233) 
(0.203) 
(0.344) 
(0.374) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: Share of foreign ethnic or Hispanic restaurants. All variables are aggregated 
across Census tracts, with weights reflecting the distribution of shopping trips from the 2001 
National Household Travel Survey (Panels A and B, except foreign share in Panel B defined 
using commuting-to-work weights), or across MSAs (Panel C). Observations: 6,807 tracts within 
MSAs (Panels A and B) and 25 MSAs (Panel C). Estimates are weighted by the 1992 number of 
restaurants, based on the same aggregation of tracts. Standard errors (in parentheses) in Panels A 
and B are clustered at the MSA level 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database and Summary Files (SF4), 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>of the total population, while we define the growth in the immigrant share 
of the population on areas centered on c using commuting-to-work weights, to 
more accurately capture changes in the immigrant share of the local workforce. 
Finally, in Panel C, we aggregate all variables across the 25 MSAs in California, 
which may also better capture the labor market than using shopping weights. 
Regardless of the level of aggregation, we find that an increase in the foreign-
born share of the population is associated with sizable increases in the share of 
ethnic restaurants. </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>The effects are larger when defining the immigrant share in an area that 
more closely represents the size of the labor market (Panels B and C), 
suggesting that labor supply shifts may play an important role in the growth of 
ethnic restaurants. For example, in column (1), when we define the dependent 
variable as the ratio of foreign ethnic restaurants to all eating places (except 
caterers), we find that a 1% increase in the foreign-born share in the shopping 
area centered on c is associated with a 0.18% increase in the share of ethnic 
restaurants in the same area, while a 1% increase in the foreign-born share 
in the commuting-to-work area centered on c is associated with a 0.44% 
increase in the share of ethnic restaurants in the reach of consumers residing 
in tract c. The results are robust to an alternative definition of the share 
of ethnic restaurants-the ratio of foreign ethnic restaurants to all eating 
places excluding not only caterers but also fast-food and ice-cream places 
(column (2)). 
If these positive associations are really an effect of immigration, then the 
ethnicity of the restaurants that "result" from immigration ought to be associ-
ated with the ethnicity of the immigrants. To test this prediction, we estimate 
the relationship between the growth in the share of Hispanic restaurants and 
the growth in both the share of Hispanic and non-Hispanic foreign-born in 
the population. 
21 We focus on Hispanic immigration because it was by far the 
largest immigrant inflow into California in our sample period. As shown in 
columns (3) and (4), we find that the within-ethnicity relationships are positive 
and significant, regardless of the level of aggregation, while the cross-ethnicity 
relationships are generally not significant, either economically or statistically 
(and are opposite-signed). In this analysis, though, it is only for the commuting 
weights (Panel B) that the positive relationship is stronger. </p>

<p>20 Given that ethnic restaurants are predominantly stand-alone, we would likely similarly find that 
immigration is associated with increases in the share of stand-alone restaurants. However, because 
there may be many non-ethnic stand-alone restaurants that do not add to product diversity (think 
of another diner), evidence on how immigration affects the share of stand-alone restaurants is less 
informative about how immigration affects product diversity than is evidence on how immigration 
affects the ethnic composition of restaurants. (This is a reflection of the same problem we discussed 
earlier, with regard to the limitations of drawing conclusions about how immigration affects 
product diversity from evidence on how immigration affects the size distribution, and the chain 
versus stand-alone and big-box composition of the retail sector.) 
21 Hispanic restaurants are those of Mexican, Spanish, or other Hispanic ethnicity. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>Finally, we ask whether increasing variety of ethnic groups is associated with 
increasing variety of ethnic restaurants. While studying the correlates of the 
share of foreign-born in the population has the advantage of analyzing the 
effects of immigration using a similar approach to the small number of previous 
studies, it is not informative about "diversity" per se. Likewise, the share of 
ethnic non-American restaurants is not necessarily an appropriate measure of 
the variety of choices available to those who decide to eat out. To measure 
diversity, we construct Herfindahl-Hirschman indexes (HHI) of concentration 
for the ten ethnic nativity groups (indexed by j) that are separately identified 
at the Census tract level (US born individuals, and individuals born in Europe, 
Mexico, the Caribbean, Central America, South America, Canada, Asia, 
Africa, and Oceania), and for the eighteen types of ethnic restaurants (indexed 
by m) coded in the NETS or by us (listed in Table 6): </p>

<p>HHI </p>

<p>pop </p>

<p>a(c) = </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>Pop j,a(c) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>j=1 Pop j,a(c) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>HHI </p>

<p>eat </p>

<p>a(c) = </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>m=1 </p>

<p># restaurants m,a(c) </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>m=1 # restaurants m,a(c) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>. 
(6) </p>

<p>Table 8 Changes in the Herfindahl-Hirschman index of concentration for ethnic restaurants and 
changes in the index of concentration for nativity groups </p>

<p>Aggregation 
Census tract, weighted sum 
Across MSAs 
of restaurants, and populations 
HH nativity index 
Shopping weights 
Commuting weights 
defined using 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) </p>

<p>HH index for 
0.042 
0.161 b 
0.316 a 
nativity groups 
(0.075) 
(0.060) 
(0.080) 
log population 
0.031 
0.035 c 
0.193 a 
(0.021) 
(0.019) 
(0.045) </p>

<p>Dependent variable: Changes in the Herfindahl-Hirschman index of concentration for ethnic 
restaurants, defined over 18 categories of ethnic restaurants (American, Cajun, Chinese, French, 
German, Greek, Indian/Pakistani, Italian, Japanese, Korean, Lebanese, Mexican, Spanish, Thai, 
Vietnamese, other Asian, other Hispanic, and other foreign). The independent variable capturing 
diversity is the change in the Herfindahl-Hirschman index of concentration for nativity groups, 
defined over 10 categories (US-born; born in Europe, Mexico, Caribbean countries, Central 
America, South America, Canada, Asia, Africa, or Oceania). All variables are aggregated across 
Census tracts, with weights reflecting the distribution of shopping trips from the 2001 National 
Household Travel Survey (columns (1) and (2), except the HH index for nativity groups in column 
(2) is defined using commuting-to-work weights) or across MSAs (column (3)). Observations: 
6,807 Census tracts within MSAs (columns (1) and (2)) and 25 MSAs (column (3)). Estimates are 
weighted by the 1992 number of restaurants, based on the same aggregation of tracts. Standard 
errors (in parentheses) adjusted for heteroscedasticity and (in columns (1) and (2)) clustering 
across MSAs 
a Significant at 1% level 
b Significant at 5% level 
c Significant at 10% level 
NETS; Neighborhood Change Database and Summary Files (SF4), 1990 and 2000 Censuses </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>Table 8 reports the relationship between changes in the two indexes defined 
above, and shows evidence of a positive association between the ethnic diver-
sity of the population and the ethnic diversity of restaurants, regardless of the 
level of aggregation. 
22 However, the positive association between population 
and restaurant diversity is only statistically significant, and is much stronger, 
when the diversity of the population (HHI 
pop ) is evaluated for areas that 
capture the extent of the relevant labor market (columns (2) and (3), using 
commuting-to-work weights and aggregation across MSAs, respectively), com-
pared to defining the index to capture the diversity of the more limited pool of 
consumers (column (1)). This suggests that the more varied the composition 
of the population across nativity groups becomes-in terms of the workforce-
the more varied is the composition of restaurants across ethnic lines, suggesting 
that the potential channel through which immigration delivers "consumption 
variety" is more likely to stem from a comparative advantage of immigrants in 
the production of ethnic food than from immigrants' consumption demands for 
ethnic food in restaurants (although we have little doubt that both channels are 
important.) This is consistent with the evidence that the restaurant labor force 
is strongly immigrant-intensive, as shown in Table 1, as well as the apparently 
greater effect of immigrant inflows in the restaurant sector than in retail, as 
shown in Table 2, which we interpreted as likely reflecting larger labor supply 
increases in the restaurant sector. 
Notice that in our equations, we control for changes in the population. So, 
even if size per se creates diversity (Krugman 1979), we are explicitly testing 
for the increased variety that may arise from diversity in the population, which 
can clearly be enhanced by immigration; the coefficient on the Herfindahl-
Hirschman index measures the relationship between diversity in the popula-
tion and diversity in the types of restaurants once changes in the size of the 
population are held constant. 
Of course, the mere presence of ethnically diverse restaurants does not 
mean that natives are better off. Although we do not attempt to estimate the 
actual welfare gains from diversity, a prerequisite for such gains would have 
to be that natives consume from the ethnic establishments that get created, 
rather than that these ethnic restaurants simply serve new immigrants from 
the corresponding ethnic group. Casual observation suggests that the clientele 
of ethnic restaurants is by no means limited to co-ethnics. And in fact a limited 
amount of research documents this. Liu and Jang (2009) collected data on 
customers of Chinese restaurants in a Midwestern US city and found that 
60.2% were Caucasian, while 32.0% were Asian. Josiam and Monteiro (2004) 
surveyed patrons of Indian restaurants in Minneapolis/St. Paul. Among their </p>

<p>22 The indexes are both inversely related to variety, so this conclusion follows from the positive 
regression coefficients. </p>

<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>



<p>respondents, 75% were classified as white American, and only 12% as South 
Asian. </p>

<p>23 </p>

<p>For given elasticities of substitution of demand across different types of 
restaurant meals, another reason why natives would benefit from increased 
variety is through reduced prices. The lack of detailed data on prices at the 
local level prevents us from pursuing an approach along the lines of the 
estimation of Broda and Weinstein (2006) of the gains from trade. </p>

<p>6 Conclusions </p>

<p>Most of the debate on the economic consequences of immigration focuses on 
whether immigrants take jobs away from natives and reduce wages for US 
workers. In this paper, we direct attention instead to the effects of immigration 
on the composition of output, stemming from the fact that immigrants are 
consumers with potentially different demand characteristics and also may have 
a comparative advantage in the production of ethnic goods. 
We look at these composition effects in a number of ways. First, we estimate 
the relationship between immigrant inflows and the size distribution and com-
position of business establishments. This analysis indicates that immigration is 
associated with fewer stand-alone retail stores, and a greater number of chains 
and in particular big-box retailers. This evidence would appear to contradict 
a diversity-enhancing effect of immigration, although we cannot draw firm 
conclusions because we do not have information on the types of goods that 
consumers buy at different stores. 
Consequently, we focus more of our attention on the relationship between 
immigration and the ethnic diversity of restaurants, for which we can much 
more readily identify the types of products consumed by customers. The 
evidence indicates quite clearly that immigration is associated with increased 
ethnic diversity of restaurants, and labor supply shifts appear to play an 
important role in the growth of ethnic restaurants. 
Our findings support the existence of some economic benefits of immigra-
tion that have rarely been documented in the literature. Although a state-
ment about welfare would require a more structural approach, the diversity 
effects of immigration in the restaurant sector expand natives' consumption 
choices and, as such, are potentially welfare-enhancing. We find that these 
effects likely stem in part from comparative advantage of immigrants in the </p>

<p>23 It would be ideal to know more about actual spending patterns of consumers. In his study of 
immigration to Israel, Lach (2007) infers something about spending patterns by looking at the 
association of immigrants from the former Soviet Union with prices for pork and vodka (given that 
their consumption demands for these products differ substantially from the rest of the population). 
But these are idiosyncratic cases. For the United States, the Consumer Expenditure Survey does 
not identify respondents who are immigrants, although it does identify Hispanic respondents. 
However, the survey does not identify spending at ethnic versus other restaurants, or spending 
on other goods that are strongly tied to ethnicity. </p>



<p>F. Mazzolari, D. Neumark </p>

<p>production of ethnic food from their country of origin. On the other hand, with 
respect to the composition of the retail sector, one might plausibly view our 
evidence as suggesting that immigrant inflows increase the homogeneity rather 
than the diversity of consumption choices. This latter result may reflect the fact 
that immigrants do not have any particular comparative advantage in retail 
work, and, for that sector, their effect may act more through the demand side. 
Perhaps because of generally low incomes of immigrants, as well as sensitivity 
to prices, the demand effects of immigrants on the retail sector may do less to 
increase consumption diversity. Of course, low-income natives may gain more 
from growth of larger, big-box retailers that lower prices, even at the cost of 
standardization, than from increases in diversity of consumption choices, so 
that once we account for heterogeneity of the native population, the mapping 
from diversity to welfare is not necessarily straightforward. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements We are grateful to the University of California Labor and Employment 
Research Fund and the United Nations for research support, to Daria Burnes for outstanding 
research assistance, to Giuseppe Ragusa for help with programming, and to Albrecht Glitz, Saul 
Lach, Ken Small, Klaus Zimmermann, three anonymous referees, and seminar participants at UCI 
and the University of Milan, for helpful comments. Any views are our own, and not those of 
the University of California, Confindustria, the United Nations, or the Public Policy Institute of 
California. This paper circulated earlier with the title "Beyond Wages: The Effects of Immigration 
on the Scale and Composition of Output." </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 
Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in 
any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited. </p>



<p>Immigration and product diversity </p>





</text></tei>