<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fcoep.12223" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>This research investigates two features of the Affordable Care Act that especially 
affect young adults, the young adult-dependent coverage (YAD) mandate and the 
requirement to cover contraception (CM). Both mandates were first enacted at the 
state level but have been studied only in isolation. We estimate a wide range of models 
allowing these mandates to have joint effects on insurance coverage, health-care access, 
health outcomes and fertility. We provide new evidence that helps settle the mixed 
findings from past state-level YAD and CM research and suggests the two mandates 
may combine to improve the well-being of young adults. (JEL I18, I12, H75) </p>

<p>Young adults are typically low-risk/low-cost 
users of health insurance who are also among 
the most likely to be uninsured. The Patient 
Protection and Affordable Care Act of 2010 
(ACA) targeted this group and contains two 
key mandates of particular benefit to young 
adults: (1) extending the provision of young 
adult-dependent coverage (YAD) on family 
insurance plans to age 26 and (2) requiring all 
Food and Drug Administration (FDA)-approved 
contraceptive methods to be available to women 
with no cost sharing (HRSA 2015). Both of these 
provisions were enacted at the state level prior 
to the national reform, thus providing a natural 
setting for researchers to test their effects (e.g., 
Depew 2015; Levine, McKnight, and Heep 2011;  Monheit et al. 2011 for YAD; Mulligan 2015;  Raissian and Lopoo 2015 for contraception man-
dates [CMs]). However, the key findings from </p>

<p> *  We would like to thank Elizabeth Nash from the 
Guttmacher Institute for providing information on state 
contraception policies, Joel Cantor for research on dependent 
coverage mandates, and Philip Levine for CPS data on health 
insurance. This paper has also benefited from the comments 
of Reagan Baughman, David Bradford, Anca Cotet-Grecu, 
Andrew Houtenville, Joanna Lahey, Robert Mohr, David 
Simon, and participants in presentations at APPAM, the 
University of Connecticut, Bowdoin College, the Eastern 
Economics Association Meetings, and iHEA Meetings, as 
well as those of three anonymous referees and the editor. 
Trudeau: Assistant Professor, Department of Business 
Economics, Sacred Heart University, Fairfield, CT 
06825. Phone 203-365-4156, Fax 203-365-7538, E-mail 
trudeauj@sacredheart.edu 
Conway: Professor, Department of Economics, University of 
New Hampshire, Durham, NH 03824. Phone 603-862-
3386, Fax 603-862-3383, E-mail karen.conway@unh.edu </p>

<p>this research are decidedly mixed. Moreover, no 
research has taken a comprehensive approach to 
studying these two mandates in tandem. 
Our research seeks to close this gap by 
studying the effects of both mandates on health 
insurance coverage, access to care, general health 
outcomes, and reproductive outcomes using a 
variety of datasets and empirical approaches. We 
make three contributions. First, ours is the first 
study to investigate the effects of both mandates. 
Our approach not only avoids the possible bias 
caused by ignoring a related health insurance 
policy but allows for the mandates to reinforce 
(or diminish) each other's effects. Such an inter-
action between the mandates appears plausible 
for young women. Given their typically low risk 
of serious health problems yet higher fertility, 
the costs because of pregnancy likely loom large. </p>

<p>ABBREVIATIONS </p>

<p>ACA: Affordable Care Act of 2010 
ASEC: Annual Social and Economic Supplement 
BRFSS: Behavioral Risk Factor Surveillance System 
CDC: Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 
CM: Contraception Mandate 
CPS: Current Population Survey 
DD: Difference-in-Difference 
DDD: Triple Difference 
EPICC: Equity in Prescription Insurance and 
Contraception Coverage Act 
ERISA: Employee Retirement Income Security Act 
ESI: Employer-Sponsored Insurance 
FDA: Food and Drug Administration 
HRSA: Health Resources and Services Administration 
MEPS: Medical Expenditure Survey 
NCSL: National Conference of State Legislatures 
YAD: Young Adult-Dependent Coverage </p>

<p>73 
Contemporary Economic Policy (ISSN 1465-7287) 
Vol. 36, No. 1, January 2018, 73-92 
Online Early publication March 16, 2017 </p>

<p>doi:10.1111/coep.12223 
© 2017 Western Economic Association International </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>Moreover, the cost of prescription contraception 
is relatively expensive, especially for young 
adults whose incomes tend to be lower than 
other groups. For example, Trussell et al. (2013)  estimates the average annual cost of short-acting 
prescription contraception to be $390.53 for 
injections, $654.30 for the birth control pill, 
and $1,023.86 for the birth control patch. 1 The 
reported spike in requests and <rs type="software">Google</rs> searches 
for intrauterine devices immediately after the 
2016 election is strong, although admittedly 
anecdotal, evidence of the importance women 
place on having the cost of their contraception 
covered (Ross 2016). 
Health insurance policies that include contra-
ception coverage are likely valued more highly by 
young women than policies that do not, which in 
turn may lead to greater take-up and strengthens 
the effects of a YAD mandate. Similarly, Raissian  and Lopoo (2015) note that CMs only help those 
women who have insurance; thus, a CM may have 
stronger effects in states where young women 
have better access to health insurance, such as 
provided by a YAD mandate. Even if these man-
dates do not combine to increase health insurance 
coverage, they could still combine to affect the 
care women receive and their health outcomes. 
For example, a woman covered by a YAD may 
not bother going to the doctor for routine care if 
she is using nonprescription contraception (e.g., 
condoms, spermicide); the addition of a CM may 
encourage her to seek prescription contraception 
and lead her to get such routine care, care which 
could potentially diagnose, treat, or prevent other 
health conditions (like depression). 
There are other, more indirect mechanisms 
too. Depew (2015) and Colman and Dave (2015)  find that YADs reduce labor supply; the latter 
also find a decrease in time spent waiting for 
or receiving health care and an increase in "so-
cializing." Such second-order effects could lead 
YADs to affect both care received and health 
outcomes (indeed, Colman and Dave 2015, find 
an increase in subjective well-being) as well as 
influence reproductive behavior and the desire 
for contraception. These scenarios suggest that 
the effects of these mandates can operate through </p>

<p>1. These estimates contain an initial physician visit cost 
of $41.45 taken from the 2011 Medicare fee schedule; how-
ever, other evidence from the Medical Expenditure Survey 
(MEPS) by Davis and Carper (2012) suggests that the aver-
age expense for a visit to a primary physician is closer to 
$145, or for an OB-GYN $235. For context, note that the aver-
age earnings for 18-24-year-old women in 2009 was $24,117 
according to the U.S. Census Bureau (2012). </p>

<p>multiple avenues and may be influenced by 
whether the other mandate exists, an interaction 
effect we model explicitly. 
A second contribution is the comprehensive 
set of outcomes we investigate in studying these 
two mandates. This approach allows us to both 
fill in the gaps left by existing research and bring 
new evidence to key outcomes for which past 
findings are mixed. Research on state-level YAD 
mandates (e.g., Levine, McKnight, and Heep  2011; Monheit et al. 2011) focuses on insurance 
coverage. 2 In contrast, research on CMs primar-
ily focuses on sexual activity and contraception 
use (Atkins and Bradford 2014; Magnusson et al.  2012; Raissian and Lopoo 2015) and birth and 
abortion rates (Dills and Cotet-Grecu 2016; Mul- ligan 2015). Possible effects on insurance cover-
age or on more general health-care utilization and 
health outcomes that may arise out of the com-
plementary consumption of health services have 
been mostly ignored. 3 Our study investigates the 
effects of both mandates, first in isolation and 
then allowing for joint effects, for health insur-
ance coverage; health-care access; general health 
outcomes; and pregnancies, births, and abortions. 
Drawing from several data sources also allows 
us to explore multiple independent measures of 
insurance coverage, general health, and repro-
ductive outcomes, bringing new evidence and a 
different kind of robustness check to past work. 
Finally, our study provides data and method-
ological updates to existing research on state-
level mandates. Six states adopted YADs in 2009 
alone, yet the two key studies observing their 
effect on coverage end in 2008 (Levine, McK- night, and Heep 2011; Monheit et al. 2011). 
Some recent YAD research emphasizes including 
narrower, more targeted age groups (e.g., Slusky 
2015), while Depew (2015) advocates for a wider 
age range such that eligibility can be based on age 
rather than marital or student status, which may 
be endogenous. Recent work also explores sen-
sitivity to including location-specific time trends 
and emphasizes the need to test for pretrends and 
conduct placebo tests (e.g., Depew 2015; Dills  and Cotet-Grecu 2016; Mulligan 2015; Slusky   2. Studies that investigate the broader effects of YAD 
reform on coverage, health-care utilization, and general health 
outcomes all consider only the ACA's mandate (Antwi,  Moriya, and Simon 2015a; Antwi et al. 2015b; Barbaresco,  Courtemanche, and Qi 2015; Chua and Sommers 2014; Som- mers et al. 2013). 
3. An exception is Raissian and Lopoo (2015), which 
investigates the effect of state-level CMs on private insurance 
and preventive care services. To our knowledge, no published 
study has investigated the causal effects of the ACA CM. </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>2015). We estimate every outcome with several 
difference-in-difference (DD) and triple differ-
ence (DDD) models and subject each one to sen-
sitivity and robustness checks. These exercises 
lend support to the emerging view that YADs did 
not significantly increase insurance coverage and, 
instead, led to a switch in the source of cover-
age. Our analyses also bring new evidence to the 
mixed findings regarding CMs' effects on fertility 
by finding that they reduce reported pregnancies. 
Finally, our joint models yield suggestive evi-
dence that the two mandates combine to improve 
the general well-being of young adults, although 
the precise mechanism for the effect is not clear. </p>

<p>II. BACKGROUND </p>

<p>In 1994, Utah adopted a provision for 
extended parental coverage of young adult 
dependents, allowing unmarried children under 
the age of 26 to enroll under their parents' 
insurance plan. 4 By 2009, more than 30 states 
had implemented their own variations of the 
YAD mandates, limiting dependency by age, 
student status, marital status, and whether or not 
the young adult has their own dependents. The 
2010 ACA extended parental coverage of health 
insurance to all young adults, without exceptions, 
under the age of 26 as of September 23, 2010. 
During the same time period, federal and 
state legislation began to challenge the equity 
of insurance coverage that does not provide free 
access to contraception. The issue first received 
national attention in the form of the Equity in 
Prescription Insurance and Contraception Cover-
age Act (EPICC) in 1997, yet Congress failed to 
enact the bill. States, however, seized the oppor-
tunity to establish their own initiatives, starting 
with Maryland in 1998, extending contraception 
coverage to women with insurance plans that 
covered other prescription drug benefits. By 
2009, more than 25 states had enacted similar 
CMs. The ACA extended outpatient contracep-
tive services and prescription drug benefits to all 
insured women starting August 1, 2012 at zero 
cost sharing (HRSA 2015). 
One complication in studying the effects 
of state-level mandates is that not all firms 
are subject to the mandates' reforms. In 1974,   4. Although Utah is commonly cited as the first adopter 
of YAD legislation, in our reading, we observe that North 
Dakota extended family coverage to students up to age 23 and 
nonstudents cohabitating with a parent through age 19 in 1985 
and then increased both age thresholds in 1995. See Table S2, 
Supporting Information. </p>

<p>the Employee Retirement Income Security 
Act (ERISA) set the minimum standards for 
firms extending employer-sponsored insurance 
(ESI) benefits to their employees and exempted 
self-insured firms from state-level insurance 
mandates. In 2009, 59% of ESI plans were 
issued by self-insured firms (Henry J. Kaiser  Family Foundations and Health Research and  Educational Trust [HRET] 2010), such that they 
are not covered by the mandates. 5 A second com-
plication is that the increased cost of the newly 
mandated benefits may decrease ESI offers. 
Unfortunately, data sources that have measures 
of care utilization and health outcomes, including 
those we employ here, do not have information 
on ESI offers or ERISA status. 
Research on these mandates, both at the 
state level and via the ACA, has exploded in 
recent years, and an expanded discussion of this 
research is available upon request. For the sake of 
brevity, Table 1 summarizes the research on each 
state-level mandate (two columns) across the 
three effects of interest (three rows)-coverage, 
care utilization, and health outcomes. 6 We briefly 
summarize the key insights and note that our 
study requires an additional column as it consid-
ers the effects of both mandates on all three types 
of outcomes for the first time. 
Research into state-level YAD mandates (left 
column of Table 1) focuses on the effects on 
insurance coverage (top panel); care utilization 
(middle panel) and health outcomes (bottom 
panel) are much less explored. Most studies 
examine the effect of state-level YAD mandates 
across all or most states, although a few focus 
only on the Massachusetts Health Reform in 
2006. Each employs quasiexperimental, DD, 
or DDD frameworks, using young adults not 
eligible for the mandates and/or living in states 
without mandates as control groups. The majority 
of studies of coverage use the Current Population 
Survey (CPS), which allows the identification of 
the source of coverage (own, dependent) and, for 
young adults living with their parents, whether 
the policy holders work for small employers who </p>

<p>5. Nonetheless, evidence provided by Sonfield et al.  (2004) suggests that CMs led to an increase of insurance plans 
including contraception coverage. 
6. We provide a similar summary table (Table S1) for 
ACA mandate research. However, it only has one column (for 
YAD) because, to our knowledge, no research yet exists with 
respect to the contraception mandate with the exception Finer,  Sonfield, and Jones (2014), a descriptive study that reports 
that the percentage of privately insured women paying zero 
out-of-pocket expenses for contraception increased after the 
ACA. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>TABLE 1 </p>

<p>Summary of Studies on the Independent Effects of State-Level YAD and Contraception Mandates on Insurance, Care, and Health </p>

<p>YAD Mandate </p>

<p>Contraception Mandate </p>

<p>Coverage 
Long, Yemane, and Stockley </p>

<p>(2010)-MA Health Reform </p>

<p>(CPS </p>

<p>2006-2009) </p>

<p>DD, 19-26 vs. all 27-33, minorities 27-33, childless 27-33 in 
MA: decreases uninsured rate by 5.0-6.5 pp. 
DDD, compare against NY: decrease uninsured rate 5.4-7.5 pp. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Blum et al. (2012)-State Level 
(BRFSS 2002-2004 vs. 2008-2009) </p>

<p>Descriptive 1 st 
Study, 19-23, 3 treatment states CO, NJ, SD v. 17 controls </p>

<p>0.2% increase in any insurance coverage. 
Descriptive 2 nd 
Study, nonstudents 19-23 v. 26-29 in CO and SD only </p>

<p>4.2% increase in coverage for 19-23-year-olds. 
Depew (2015)-State Level </p>

<p>(CPS 2001-2010) </p>

<p>DDD, 19-29, 2.3 pp increase in likelihood of dependent insurance 
coverage. Subsamples: 14.4% increase for females, 10% increase males 
relative to mean. </p>

<p>Hahn and Yang (2014)-State Level </p>

<p>(CPS 2001-2010) </p>

<p>DD, 19-24 in expansion states: 4.8 pp increase in dependent coverage, 
more than half because of decreases in own private insurance. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Raissian and Lopoo (2015) </p>

<p>(CPS 1989-2009) </p>

<p>DD, 15-44, includes indicator for mandates that cover services and 
supplies or suppliers only: no effect on probability of having private 
insurance coverage </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Levine, McKnight, and Heep </p>

<p>(2011)-State Level 
(CPS 2001-2009) </p>

<p>DDD, 19-24: 3.3 pp increase in any coverage, 4.4 pp increase in 
private insurance. Subsample, nonstudents: 5.1 pp increase in any 
insurance coverage. </p>

<p>DD, 19-24 and live with parents: 1.6 pp increase in any insurance 
(2.9 pp private). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Monheit et al. (2011)-State Level </p>

<p>(CPS 2001-2009) </p>

<p>DD, 19-29: No effect on overall uninsured, private or public coverage. 
Subsamples, by residence with parents and/or ages 19-25: decreases </p>

<p>in own ESI from 2.11 to 3.33 pp offset by increases in parents' coverage 
of 2.58-3.84 pp. </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>TABLE 1 
Continued </p>

<p>YAD Mandate </p>

<p>Contraception Mandate </p>

<p>Care Utilization </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Blum et al. (2012)-State Level 
(BRFSS 2002-2004 vs. 2008-2009) </p>

<p>Descriptive 1 st 
Study, 19-23, 3 treatment states CO, NJ, SD v. 17 controls: </p>

<p>0.9% increase in having primary physician, 4.6% increase in recent 
physical exam, 3.9% decrease in forgoing care because of cost. 
Descriptive 2 nd 
Study, nonstudents 19-23 v. 26-29 in CO and SD only: </p>

<p>3.8% increase in having primary physician, 2.1% increase in recent 
physical exam, 8.0% decrease in forgoing care because of cost. 
Atkins and Bradford (2014)-(BRFSS 1998-2010-limited, Family Planning 
Module) </p>

<p>DD, 18-44, Logit Regressions, Treatment: DE and IA; Controls: KY, NE, and 
SD: 5% more likely to report any prescription contraception use, 4% higher pill 
use in treatment states. 
Magnusson et al. (2012) </p>

<p>(NSFG 2006-2008) </p>

<p>DD, 15-44, Logit Regressions: 64% increased odds of consistent contraceptive 
use among privately insured women in mandate states relative to none; no 
effect on uninsured women's consistent use. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mulligan (2015) 
(BRFSS 1998-2010-limited, Family Planning Module) </p>

<p>DD, 18-44: 2.1 pp increase in probability of any contraceptive use; 
1.8 pp hormonal. Subsample, 20-29: 3.6 pp increase in shot/implant use. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Raissian and Lopoo (2015) 
(NSFG 1995, 2002, 2006-2010)   DD, 15-44 privately insured only, includes indicator for mandates that 
cover services and supplies or suppliers: no effect on contraception use, 8% 
increase in pill use by women with low education, driven by supply mandates. </p>

<p>DDD, 15-44, privately insured v. not privately insured: no differential effect on 
contraception use overall or among low educated; 15.9% (12.8%) increase </p>

<p>in pap smears (pelvic exams), driven by low-educated privately insured women. </p>

<p>Health Outcomes </p>

<p>Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) </p>

<p>(Vital Statistics 1998-2008) </p>

<p>DD for 18-19, 20-34, 35-44 by race: 4% decrease in births to Hispanic teens 
robust to inclusion of state-specific time trends and event-study specification. 
Other Outcomes: No effect on meconium release, precipitous labor, induced 
labor, or C-section. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mulligan (2015) 
(Vital Statistics 1993-2007, NSLY, CPS) </p>

<p>DD, 15-44: 6% decrease in state annual abortion rate, moderated by inclusion 
of state time trends; effects do not persist in long run for flexible time 
specification model. Births: 3% decline in state-and individual-level analyses, </p>

<p>not robust to state trends. </p>

<p>Notes: 
Studies typically follow a DD/DDD approach, identifying the effect of each mandate using variation across states and over time. For DDD specifications, the treatment and control </p>

<p>groups are also indicated. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Indicates that the study spans more than one row of the matrix. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Burgdorf (2014) conducts a sensitivity analysis of Monheit et al. 2011 and Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011), incorporating a distinction between the source of dependent coverage </p>

<p>(spouse or parent). See also Monheit, Cantor, and DeLia (2015)'s commentary and Burgdorf (2015)'s reply. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>are therefore more likely affected by state-level 
reforms (because of ERISA). There remains 
some debate about whether the overall uninsured 
rate decreases (Levine, McKnight, and Heep  2011) or is unaffected because of reverse crowd-
out from own to parent coverage (Monheit et al.  2011; Depew 2015, who also finds a decrease 
in young adult labor supply). These differences 
stem from differences in definition of controls 
(19-24 vs. 19-29) and identification of eligibil-
ity. Using CPS data and DD as well as the alter-
native DDD strategies of Levine, McKnight, and  Heep (2011) versus Depew (2015), we attempt 
to replicate past results, compare approaches, 
and explore the role that CMs may play. We also 
estimate these models using a health insurance 
measure from a different data source, the Behav-
ioral Risk Factor Surveillance System (BRFSS). 
Because the CPS has no information on care 
utilization and is limited to one measure of 
self-reported health status, research that investi-
gates health care or outcomes typically uses the 
BRFSS. To our knowledge, only one study (Blum  et al. 2012) considers the effect of state-level 
YADs on care utilization, and no study examines 
outcomes. 7 
Table 1 makes it clear that several gaps exist in 
studying the effects of CMs as well. These stud-
ies focus on contraceptive use (care utilization) 
and fertility and birth outcomes (reproductive 
health outcomes), with most finding a posi-
tive effect on contraceptive use. This research 
typically takes a DD approach and considers 
broader age groups than YAD research as all 
women of childbearing age may be potentially 
affected by CMs. Only Raissian and Lopoo  (2015) consider more general types of health 
care, finding an increase in pap smears for states 
that mandate contraceptive services and supplies. 
We consider a still broader set of care utilization 
variables that have not yet been investigated in 
CM research. Raissian and Lopoo (2015) also 
make the point that CMs may not have much 
impact because they only affect women with 
health insurance-which is precisely why we 
believe it is critical to investigate the joint effects 
of contraceptive and YAD mandates. </p>

<p>7. Using the BRFSS, Blum et al. (2012) provide descrip-
tive evidence of increased insurance coverage and care utiliza-
tion of individuals living in 3 treatment (YAD) states relative 
to those living in 17 control states. Additionally, two studies 
investigate the effects of the MA Health Reform on health care 
(Kolstad and Kowalski 2012) and outcomes (Courtemanche  and Zapata 2014), but neither focuses on young adults nor the 
YAD. </p>

<p>To our knowledge, only two economic studies 
address the direct effect of CMs on health out-
comes, and both investigate only reproductive 
outcomes with contradicting findings. Mulligan  (2015) uses state-level Vital Statistics data on 
fertility outcomes (births and abortions) and 
individual-level CPS Fertility Supplement data 
and finds a decline in both births and abortions, 
although the former is sensitive to including 
state-specific time trends. Dills and Cotet-Grecu 
(2016) conduct a similar analysis using the 
restricted-use Vital Statistics data but incorporate 
a more extensive set of individual-and state-level 
characteristics and policies. They find no robust 
effects on overall births with the exception of one 
subgroup, Hispanic teens (&lt;19), who experience 
a decline in births. 
Taken together, the research summarized in 
Table 1 reveals that CMs appear to increase con-
traceptive use but that evidence for the rest of 
the outcomes is lacking and/or mixed. Moreover, 
no study has considered the effects of both man-
dates together. Our analysis fills this gap and, as 
such, informs ACA research by providing the first 
evidence of how these two mandates combine to 
affect outcomes. </p>

<p>III. EMPIRICAL STRATEGY </p>

<p>We apply a quasiexperimental framework that 
takes advantage of variation in each mandate 
within states over time to two individual-level 
datasets (the CPS and the BRFSS) as well as 
state-level Vital Statistics data on births and abor-
tions (see Table 2 and Section IV for details). We 
begin with a DD framework because all women 
are potentially affected by a state's CM, so its 
variation is limited to the state level. We esti-
mate a DD model for each mandate separately 
and for one that allows for a joint effect. However, 
because most YAD studies exploit the fact that 
not all young adults are eligible and so employ a 
DDD approach, we also estimate two alternative 
DDD models that rely on different identification 
strategies. This comparison allows us to see if (1) 
our DD findings stand up to a DDD approach and 
(2) if controlling for CMs and addressing more 
recent methodological concerns affect existing 
YAD-DDD findings. </p>

<p>A. DD Models </p>

<p>Because CMs potentially apply to all women 
of childbearing age, past CM research has relied 
on variation over time and across states only, </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>TABLE 2 
Description of the Data Used: (A) Summary Statistics for Outcomes Studied and Eligibility Status by 
Age Group and (B) Description of Other Variables Included in the Models </p>

<p>Ages 19-24 
Ages 25-29 </p>

<p>(A) Summary Statistics 
N 
M 
SD 
N 
M 
SD 
Source </p>

<p>1. Insurance Coverage 
Insured a 
85,929 
0.72 
0.45 
75,674 
0.75 
0.43 
CPS 
HlthPlan 
77,841 
0.75 
0.43 
111,390 
0.81 
0.40 
BRFSS 
2. Care Utilization 
NotAfford 
64,857 
0.22 
0.41 
95,522 
0.20 
0.40 
BRFSS 
Checkup 
50,291 
0.70 
0.46 
76,126 
0.70 
0.46 
BRFSS 
3. Health Outcomes 
General 
Very Good + [CPS] a 
79,579 
0.74 
0.44 
70,069 
0.71 
0.45 
CPS 
Very Good + [BRFSS] 
78,019 
0.61 
0.49 
111,330 
0.65 
0.48 
BRFSS 
PhysHlth 
73,335 
2.37 
5.42 
105,788 
2.37 
5.67 
BRFSS 
MentalHlth 
73,350 
4.82 
8.07 
105,602 
4.32 
7.91 
BRFSS 
Reproductive 
Birth Rate [DD] 
686 
104.76 
18.80 
NA 
Vital Stats 
Birth Rate [DDD] 
3,822 
103.16 
24.75 
3,185 
120.09 
19.15 
Vital Stats 
Abortion Rate [DD] b 
546 
30.51 
12.81 
NA 
Abortion Surveil. 
Pregnant 
77,243 
0.08 
0.26 
102,057 
0.08 
0.27 
BRFSS 
4. Eligibility Used for DDDs 
"Levine" [CPS] 
85,929 
0.75 
0.44 
NA 
CPS 
"Levine" [BRFSS] 
78,115 
0.66 
0.48 
NA 
BRFSS 
"Depew" [CPS] 
85,929 
0.60 
0.49 
75,674 
0.21 
0.41 
CPS 
"Depew" [BRFSS] 
78,115 
0.56 
0.50 
111,479 
0.09 
0.28 
BRFSS </p>

<p>(B) Other Variables 
1. State-level Controls [Z] 
Medicaid eligibility, fraction of state receiving Medicaid assistance, receiving employer-sponsored insurance (ESI), state unemployment rate, 
indicator for availability of over-the-counter emergency contraception 
2. Sample-specific Controls [X, Z] 
BRFSS: Control for race, marital status, student status, and income bracket 
CPS: Control for marital status, student status, and a quadratic measure of the income to poverty ratio. Regressions use Levine, McKnight, and 
Heep's (2011) data, "maindata.dta," limited to women and expanded to include 2009. 
Vital Statistics/Abortion Surveillance: Control for fraction of state population that is married, non-White, that earned a high school diploma, that 
earned a college degree as well as log median income, average age, average number of children under 5 per household, average number of 
children under 18 per household by state, as in Mulligan (2015). </p>

<p>a CPS measures VeryGood + and Insured have different sample sizes because of survey questionnaire referencing current vs. prior year (see 
footnote 18). 
b Sample from Abortion Surveillance excludes AK, CT, FL, NH, and WY because of missing information. </p>

<p>that is, a DD approach. The typical CM model 
estimated is </p>

<p>CM Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>+ πZ st + β CM CM st + ε iast , </p>

<p>where the state (θ s ) and year (θ t ) fixed effects cap-
ture the "treatment" and "after" effects included 
in the most basic DD model. CM is a dummy vari-
able equal to one if the state has a CM in that year 
(and thus equals the standard "treatment*after" 
variable of interest). θ a , X, and Z are age fixed 
effects, other individual characteristics, and state 
characteristics, respectively. 
The effects of a YAD mandate can be esti-
mated in a similar way: </p>

<p>YAD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>+ πZ st + β YA YAD st + ε iast , </p>

<p>where all variables are as defined above, and YAD 
is a dummy variable equal to one if the state has a 
YAD mandate in that year. We combine these two 
models to allow for both effects, thus eliminating 
the potential omitted variable bias from focusing 
only on one mandate, and we also include an 
interaction term to capture any joint effects the 
mandates may have 8 : </p>

<p>Full Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iast </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>+ πZ st + β CM CM st + β YA YAD st </p>

<p>+ β CM * YA 
( 
YAD st  *  CM st 
) 
+ ε iast . </p>

<p>8. We also specify a simpler model that drops the interac-
tion term and so focuses only on the possible omitted variable 
bias created by considering each mandate in isolation; that 
is, we see how the estimates of β CM and β YA are affected by 
controlling for the other mandate. As a practical matter, how-
ever, the conclusions are similar to those drawn by comparing 
models 1-3, and so, we do not report them. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>The CM and YAD models commonly esti-
mated often include different controls (i.e., X and 
Z); as described in Section IV and Table 2, we 
include a broad set of controls that are represen-
tative of both. Likewise, CM models are typically 
estimated on a wider set of ages, whereas YAD 
models are limited to young adults. To be com-
parable across models and have a homogeneous 
sample, we limit all DD analyses to women aged 
19-24, the age group to which most YADs apply. 
A concern with DD models is that the trends 
in treatment and control groups/states may be dif-
ferent in the periods preceding the law. In our 
case, with two potentially interacting laws occur-
ring over a short time frame (13 years), the typical 
approaches (plotting trends before and after the 
law, estimating the pre-and post-effects of the 
law) greatly strain the data. 9 To our knowledge, 
no one has attempted these approaches in such 
a setting. Furthermore, these approaches become 
even more untenable-and less necessary-in 
the DDD models we consider next. 10 We instead 
address this concern in two ways, both of which 
can be applied to all models we estimate (single 
mandate and the full models, DD and DDD mod-
els alike). First, we subject all models to a placebo 
test in which each mandate variable is replaced 
with a dummy of whether the mandate was in 
place 3 years in the future. This test is a more 
parsimonious way of seeing if the different "treat-
ment" states behaved differently even before the 
mandate(s) was passed. It is also straightforward 
to apply to our more complicated DDD models. 
We are further reassured that, for our simpler one-
mandate DD models, estimating a dynamic spec-
ification with a full set of leads and lags of the 
policy typically yields similar conclusions to our 
3-year lead placebo. 11 Second, we estimate all 
DD models both with and without state-specific </p>

<p>9. To illustrate, consider an event time plot where there 
are now five potential types of treatment states: (1) those that 
only adopt a YAD, (2) those that only adopt a CM, (3) those 
that first adopt a YAD then a CM, (4) those that adopt a CM 
and then a YAD, and (5) those that adopt both at the same 
time. Not only does that split the data into six groups (five 
treatment + one control), but there are also two events ("time 
zero") to consider. Similarly, a dynamic regression, such as 
that estimated by Bellou and Bhatt (2013), would include 
thrice the number of lead and lag coefficients (one set for each 
mandate plus their interaction). 
10. As Depew (2015, 127) notes, the assumptions 
required for identification in DDDs are considerably weaker. 
11. Testing the joint statistical significance of the leads of 
the policy in these models yields a different conclusion from 
our placebo (3-year lead instead of current) less than 25% of 
the time. More importantly, these differences never occur in 
models that yield a key finding. </p>

<p>time trends and estimate DDD models that do and 
do not include state-specific time effects. 
Because many young adults in YAD states are 
not eligible for the mandate by virtue of their 
age, marital status, or student status, most YAD 
studies take a DDD approach, where eligible and 
ineligible young adults in both states are further 
compared. To be comparable to this past research, 
we adapt the above models to two alternative 
DDD approaches, described next. 12 </p>

<p>B. DDD Models </p>

<p>To estimate a YAD-DDD model, we must 
identify a group of young adults who are not eli-
gible for the YAD enacted in their state. Past YAD 
work differs on using age and/or marital/student 
status to identify eligibility, and both approaches 
have drawbacks. If one relies on age only, then 
to obtain a reasonable number of ineligible indi-
viduals, the age range of the sample must be siz-
able; typically, ages 19-29 are included (Depew  2015; Monheit et al. 2011). This approach pools 
together young adults at potentially very differ-
ent points in their lives and has been subject to 
strong criticism in studies of the ACA (which 
must rely on age; e.g., Slusky 2015). Put simply, 
adults aged 25-29 (who are ineligible in most 
YAD states) may not be an appropriate control 
group for those aged 19-24. If the analysis is 
instead limited to that narrower, more homoge-
neous age group, as Levine, McKnight, and Heep  (2011) does, then other, arguably endogenous, 
eligibility criteria such as marital and student sta-
tus must be used. Depew (2015) makes this point 
and provides evidence of possible endogeneity. 
We therefore estimate two different DDD 
models, one that is limited to 19-24 year olds 
and uses marital and student status (as well 
as age) to identify eligibility and another that 
includes 19-29 year olds and uses only age 
to identify eligibility. The first follows Levine,  McKnight, and Heep (2011), and the second 
follows Depew (2015). 13 These two studies also 
differ in controlling for location-specific time </p>

<p>12. We also try modifying our DD models by replacing 
the YAD dummy variable with a measure of the intensity of 
the law. Specifically, we re-estimate Equations (2) and (3) 
using the percentage of young adults aged 19-24 in a national 
CPS sample who would be eligible for the state's mandate 
(on the basis of age, marital status, and student status). The 
estimates are quite similar to those from the above equations 
and are available upon request. 
13. Monheit et al. (2011) is a hybrid of the two 
approaches, including 19-29-year-olds in many analyses but 
also using student and marital status as criteria as well. </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>effects. Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)  take a more restrictive approach and do not 
include state-specific time trends or effects, 
whereas Depew (2015) includes the full set of 
state*year fixed effects (as well as age*year and 
age*state fixed effects). As such, we view these 
two approaches as ideal bookends to the range 
of possible DDD approaches one could take, and 
we try to follow each one as closely as possible. 
Our "Levine" model continues with the 
19-24-year-old samples from the DD approach 
and defines Eligible as Levine, McKnight, and  Heep (2011) do: as a dummy variable equal to 
one if the individual, i, would be eligible for the 
YAD enacted (at some point in the sample) in 
their state, s, on the basis of age a, and mari-
tal/student status, m, e; for those living in a state 
without a YAD, it is equal to one if they are 
unmarried. Eligible is then interacted with every 
variable included in the model, </p>

<p>YAD-DDD Model ∶ Y iamest = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iamest + πZ st + β YA YAD st + α 
′ Eligible iames </p>

<p>(2a) </p>

<p>+ θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>s Eligible iames + θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>t Eligible iames + θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>a Eligible iames + γ 
′ X iamest Eligible iames </p>

<p>+ π 
′ Z st Eligible iames + β </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>YA YAD st Eligible iames + ε iamest , </p>

<p>and the DDD "treatment" effect is the coefficient 
on Eligible*YAD, or β ′ 
YA . This approach is akin to 
splitting the sample into eligible ("treated") and 
ineligible ("control") observations and estimat-
ing the difference in the effects of the YAD man-
date being implemented. Modifying this model to 
include CM's effects as well yields </p>

<p>Full-DDD Model ∶ Y iamest = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + γX iamest + πZ st + β CM CM st + β YA YAD st </p>

<p>(3a) </p>

<p>+ β CM * YA 
( 
YAD st  *  CM st 
) 
+ α 
′ Eligible iames + θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>s Eligible iames + θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>t Eligible iames + θ </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>a Eligible iames 
+ γ 
′ X iamest Eligible iames + π 
′ Z st Eligible iames + β </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>CM CM st Eligible iames + β </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>YA YAD st Eligible iames 
+ β </p>

<p>′ 
CM * YA </p>

<p>( 
YAD st  *  CM st 
) 
Eligible iames + ε iamest . </p>

<p>The baseline effect of a CM is β CM as 
before, and the special effect of having both 
mandates when one is YAD-eligible is now 
β ′ 
CM * YA . 
Depew (2015) uses only age to determine 
eligibility and expands the ages considered to 
29. Depew (2015) also includes the full set </p>

<p>of state-by-year, state-by-age, and year-by-age 
fixed effects. This full set of fixed effects allows 
the treatment and control groups to differ with 
respect to other factors in a very flexible way. 
It also includes location-specific time effects 
in an even less restrictive manner than state-
specific time trends. We adapt this specification 
to our three models (Equations (1)-(3)) by first 
expanding our sample to ages 19-29; note that 
this means that our "CM-only" model results 
are different for the "Depew" model because 
of the wider age group and richer set of fixed 
effects included. In contrast, the "Levine" CM-
only model is identical to the DD model without 
state-specific time trends. Second, eligibility is 
now equal to one if the individual is below the 
cut-off age for the YAD in the individual's state. 
Equations (1b)-(3b) (next page) reflect this dis-
tinction, with eligibility indexed by a and s, age 
and state, respectively, only. Finally, this model </p>

<p>requires adding the full set of age*state, age*year, 
and state*year fixed effects. However, the effect 
of a CM will be completely subsumed in the state-
by-year fixed effects. We therefore adapt our "De-
pew" model to include state-specific time trends 
instead. To explore the impact of this restriction, 
we also try including state-specific quadratic time </p>

<p>trends, and we re-estimate the YAD-only model 
including the full set of state*year fixed effects. 
The results are reasonably similar, lending sup-
port to our approach. 
Using our adapted "Depew" approach, 
the 
three 
models 
we 
estimate 
are 
then: </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>CM Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a + θ a * s </p>

<p>(1b) </p>

<p>+ θ a * t + θ s  *  time + γX iast + πZ st </p>

<p>+ β CM CM st + ε iast , </p>

<p>YAD-DDD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a </p>

<p>(2b) </p>

<p>+ θ a * s + θ a * t + θ s  *  time + γX iast + πZ st </p>

<p>+ β YA YAD st + β </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>YA YAD st Eligible as + ε iast , 
and </p>

<p>Full-DDD Model ∶ Y iast = α + θ s + θ t + θ a </p>

<p>(3b) </p>

<p>+ θ a * s + θ a * t + θ s  *  time + γX iast + πZ st </p>

<p>+ β CM CM st + β YA YAD st + β </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>YA YAD st Eligible as 
+ β CM * YA CM st YAD st </p>

<p>+ β′ CM * YA CM st YAD st Eligible as + ε iast , </p>

<p>where the DDD estimate of YAD's effect is β ′ 
YA , 
and the joint effect of having both a YAD and a 
CM is β ′ 
CM * YA . </p>

<p>IV. DATA </p>

<p>Our analyses use data from several datasets 
combined with information on state-level insur-
ance mandates and other characteristics. We first 
examine the variation in state-level insurance 
mandates and then discuss the different datasets 
we use: the CPS (coverage and health status), the 
BRFSS (coverage, care, and health and reproduc-
tive outcomes), and the Vital Statistics (reproduc-
tive outcomes). We conclude by discussing the 
individual-and state-level controls we include, as 
well as robustness checks and placebo tests. </p>

<p>A. State Mandates </p>

<p>The National Conference of State Legislatures 
(NCSL) website (National Conference of State 
Legislatures 2012) contains information on both 
the extended parental coverage and CMs. We 
cross-reference the NCSL indicators for YADs 
with Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011), Mon-
heit et al. (2011), Hahn and Yang (2014), Depew 
(2015), and Cantor et al. (2012), and the CM indi-
cators with the Guttmacher Institute (2014), Rais-
sian and Lopoo (2015), Dills and Cotet-Grecu 
(2016), and Mulligan (2015). This exercise is </p>

<p>summarized in Table S2 and reveals several dis-
crepancies across the different sources. For CMs, 
the differences are fairly minor 14 ; for YADs, 
however, they are much more widespread, and 
no two studies use the exact same list, a point 
also noted in Burgdorf (2014). The differences 
appear to be because of the use of implementa-
tion versus effective dates, states with multiple 
changes to extended coverage eligibility criteria, 
and the censoring of most samples in 2008. We 
arrive at our final list by cross-referencing the 
discrepancies with state legislation recorded in 
WestLaw. As is the convention, we omit Mas-
sachusetts from our analyses because of its per-
sonal mandate. 
Figure S1, Supporting Information, summa-
rizes the adoption of these mandates over time, as 
well as the state-specific requirements for YAD 
eligibility, and Figure S2 shows the geographic 
variation over time. While both reveal the accel-
erating adoption of both mandates during this 
short time period, they also suggest substantial 
independent variation in each one. We explore 
their correlation formally by estimating state-
year panel models in which the presence/absence 
of each mandate is regressed on the other as 
well as state and year fixed effects. This exercise 
reveals a statistically significant positive relation-
ship between the two, which suggests that con-
sidering each mandate in isolation could lead to 
bias. 15 At the same time, there appears to be suf-
ficient independent variation to identify the sepa-
rate and joint effects of each mandate. 16 </p>

<p>B. CPS-Health Insurance Coverage and 
General Health </p>

<p>The March Supplement of the CPS, also 
known as the Annual Social and Economic Sup-
plement (ASEC), provides measures of health 
insurance status and source of coverage: private, </p>

<p>14. Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) differ by excluding 
states in which legislation is enacted by Attorney General 
opinion in Michigan and Montana; the differences with Mul-
ligan (2015, Table 1) are almost all 1 year or less. When 
different, Mulligan (2015) tends to use the year prior to imple-
mentation. However, these differences may be compounded 
by combining these earlier dates with the year of birth rather 
than year of conception, as in Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016)  and in our analyses. 
15. A Chi-squared test of independence on whether each 
state eventually adopts each mandate similarly rejects the null 
hypothesis of independence. 
16. The R-squares of 0.608 and 0.703 obtained from the 
state-year panel models suggest that 29-39% of the variation 
remains even after controlling for the other mandate and for 
state and year fixed effects. </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>public, group, and nongroup. As noted above, 
it is the main data source for past YAD studies 
of insurance coverage. While the CPS contains 
no information on health-care access, it does 
have a general self-reported health measure as 
well as other individual characteristics, including 
age, marital, and student status. We employ 
Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)'s dataset 
and code submitted for publication in the AEJ: 
Economic Policy 17 to replicate and expand their 
analyses by (1) including state CMs; (2) using 
the revised list of YAD mandates; and (3) adding 
data for 1997-1999 and post-2008, 18 more ages 
(25-29), and the self-reported health measure. 
The year 2009, in particular, could be influential 
both because six states adopted YAD mandates 
in that year and because of the potentially wide-
reaching effects of the Great Recession. As 
discussed shortly, one robustness check is to 
drop 2009 from our analyses. The CPS sample 
spanning 1997-2009 is comprised of 85,929 
females aged 19-24 and 75,674 females aged 
25-29. Table 2 provides the summary statistics 
for each of our outcome variables across all three 
data sources; it also lists the control variables 
included. 19 </p>

<p>C. BRFSS-Insurance Coverage, Care Access, 
Health Outcomes, and Pregnancy </p>

<p>The BRFSS is an annual telephone survey on 
personal health behaviors administered by the 
states that includes measures of all four outcomes 
of interest here-if the individual has health 
insurance; their access to health care; their self-
reported general, physical, and mental health; and 
their reproductive outcomes (if they are currently 
pregnant). 20 As such, it allows us to explore, 
with one data source, the full range of outcomes 
shown in Table 1. It also allows us to bring </p>

<p>17. The dataset "maindata.dta" is available at http://www 
.aeaweb.org/articles.php?doi=10.1257/pol.3.1.129. 
18. The CPS questions often refer to the previous calen-
dar year; therefore, while Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011)  use 2001-2009 CPS data, their analyses actually refer to the 
years 2000-2008. However, the self-reported health measure 
refers to the current year (year of the survey), and so, we adjust 
the data accordingly for those analyses. 
19. All summary statistics and regression analyses 
include sample weights. 
20. Concern over the response rates of a landline sur-
vey, especially for young adults, led the BRFSS to include 
a cell phone survey in 2008 and modify its weighting pro-
cedures. Testing for raking began in 2007 and replaced post-
stratification entirely in 2011. These issues likely do not play 
a substantial role in our analyses as they end in 2009 (and in 
robustness checks, 2008). </p>

<p>new evidence for the two most heavily studied 
outcomes-health insurance coverage for YADs 
and reproductive outcomes for CMs. These two 
outcomes, as well as a self-reported general 
health status (similar to the one in the CPS), are 
available in every year. Table 2 shows that health 
insurance and general health are reasonably sim-
ilar across the CPS and the BRFSS, although the 
CPS respondents consistently report lower insur-
ance rates and better health. It also shows that 
about 8% of young women report being pregnant 
at the time of the survey. 
However, other access and health outcome 
measures are not reported in every year, as shown 
in Table S3. Not Afford (whether the individual 
had to forego care because they could not afford 
to see the doctor) is the most available access 
measure, missing only in 2002. Especially unfor-
tunate for our purposes is that routine care target-
ing females (pap smears and breast exams) and 
reported use of contraception methods are miss-
ing in too many years and/or states to be useful. 21 
Our health-care access measures are therefore 
limited to Not Afford and whether the woman had 
a routine physician visit in the last year (Check 
up, missing for most states in 2001-2004). 
Finally, in all years but 2002, the BRFSS con-
tains two measures indicating the number of days 
in the previous month in which the respondent's 
physical or mental health was "not good," which 
we also investigate in our analyses. </p>

<p>D. Vital Statistics and Abortion 
Surveillance-Reproductive Outcomes </p>

<p>Past CM research relies primarily on Vital 
Statistics data to investigate reproductive out-
comes, and we do as well, using the birth and 
abortion rates from the Centers for Disease Con-
trol and Prevention (CDC) aggregated to the 
state-year level. 22 The restricted-use Vital Statis-
tics records contain information on maternal and 
infant characteristics, including demographic and 
health indicators as well as geographic identifiers </p>

<p>21. Pap Smear and Breast Exam are missing for the vast 
majority of states for five of the more recent years (2001,  2003, 2005, 2007, and 2009), leading to relatively small 
sample sizes and less observed variation in the post mandate 
periods. The contraception questions are asked by all states in 
only 2002 and 2004 and by a very small number of states, if 
at all, in the remaining years. 
22. Our abortion data is the same as that used in Mul- ligan (2015). Our conception year, state-level births data are 
similar; Mulligan (2015) uses birth year and state-level births, 
whereas Dills and Cotet-Grecu (2016) use conception year 
(estimated using date of last menstrual period) and county-
level births. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>for state and county. Using the estimated length 
of gestation and counting back from the month 
of birth, pregnancies resulting in live births are 
aggregated to the state level by conception year 
and reported as the annual birth rate per 1,000 
women. The full sample of live births between 
1997 and 2009 is 19,457,946 births aggregated 
into 686 state-year observations. Abortion statis-
tics by state are reported annually in the CDC's 
"Morbidity and Mortality Weekly Report: Abor-
tion Surveillance" by age bracket (&lt;15, 15-19,  20-24, 25-29, 30-34, 35-39, 40+). 
These aggregate fertility measures preclude 
estimation of most DDD models. Neither the 
births nor abortion data contain the information 
needed to determine "Levine" eligibility (e.g., 
student status). In addition, the abortion data are 
already aggregated into broad age groups, and so, 
determining eligibility based solely on age (i.e., 
"Depew") is not possible either. This limitation 
highlights the benefits of the Pregnant variable 
we investigate from the BRFSS; to our knowl-
edge, we are the first to do so in this kind of 
research. At the same time, we note that Preg-
nant differs from these fertility measures because 
(1) it captures whether the woman is pregnant 
and knows it at the time of the survey (and so 
misses many pregnancies over the course of a 
year), and (2) it captures some eventual miscar-
riages (which are missed in aggregate fertility 
measures). Table 2 suggests that the former is 
larger than the latter as the 8% reported preg-
nancy rate in the BRFSS is substantially lower 
than the birth + abortion rates per 1,000 women 
observed in the Vital Statistics. </p>

<p>E. Other Data Choices and Robustness Checks </p>

<p>One challenge is choosing a set of control 
variables that are representative of both CM and 
YAD research. At the individual level, our choice 
is limited by what is available in the CPS ver-
sus the BRFSS; recall that our Vital Statistics 
analyses (state-level births and abortions) con-
tain no individual-level variables. An additional 
complication is that studies vary in the state-level 
variables they include. Most include the unem-
ployment rate and Medicaid eligibility levels, 
and CM studies emphasize controlling for emer-
gency contraception availability. To be compara-
ble across mandates and outcomes, we include all 
three state-level variables as well as the percent 
reporting ESI and percent receiving Medicaid; we 
also choose a broad set of individual-level vari-
ables (see panel B of Table 2). </p>

<p>Recent CM research (Dills and Cotet-Grecu  2016; Mulligan 2015) shows that the effects are 
sensitive to the inclusion of state-specific time 
trends. As noted in Section III, we estimate our 
DD models both with and without state-specific 
time trends and choose one DDD approach that 
does control for state-specific time effects ("De-
pew") and one that does not ("Levine"). 23 We 
also re-estimate all models excluding 2009 as it 
was an unusual year because of the Great Reces-
sion and the large number of states enacting 
YADs; the results are quite similar. Finally, we 
subject every model to a placebo test in which 
the current mandate variables are replaced with 
a 3-year lead-that is, whether or not they were 
enacted 3 years in the future. In the full model, 
this process involves four separate tests-the 
individual statistical significance of each man-
date coefficient (β CM , β YA , and β CM * YA ) as well 
as their joint statistical significance. </p>

<p>V. RESULTS </p>

<p>Our empirical analyses include three models 
(Equations (1)-(3) above) estimated with four 
different approaches (two DD and two DDD) 
on a wide set of outcomes from three different 
data sources. We also subject every model to a 
placebo test. We therefore report only the key 
coefficients from each of the models/approaches, 
and at the bottom of each one, we summarize 
whether the model "passed" the placebo test(s) 
at a 10% level. For the models including both 
mandates, we also report the p value for the 
joint test of the three key coefficients (for YAD, 
CM, and YAD*CM). To facilitate comparisons, 
we group the results by outcome rather than 
data source. </p>

<p>A. Health Insurance and Health-Care Access </p>

<p>Table 3 reports the results for health insurance 
coverage using data from both the CPS and the </p>

<p>23. Because the BRFSS data is gathered monthly, we 
include month fixed effects as well as year and state fixed 
effects in those models; their inclusion has no substantive 
impact on the results. Other sensitivity analyses explored but 
not reported include lagging the mandate indicators by 1 year 
(to allow for a delayed effect and/or variables that may capture 
behavior over more than one calendar year), including age-
specific time trends, reducing the individual-and state-level 
controls included, and estimating the dichotomous outcomes 
with probit and the count outcomes (i.e., days not healthy) 
with a negative binomial. None of these analyses affect the 
conclusions drawn from the core set of exercises. All results 
discussed are available upon request. </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>TABLE 3 </p>

<p>Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Having Any Insurance Coverage in the Last Year or Current Health Plan a </p>

<p>DD Models </p>

<p>DDD Models </p>

<p>Base </p>

<p>w/ State-Time Trends </p>

<p>By Status ("Levine") </p>

<p>By Age Only ("Depew") </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>1. Insured [CPS] 
CM </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>−0.009 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.011* </p>

<p>(−0.22) </p>

<p>(−0.48) </p>

<p>(−0.39) </p>

<p>(−0.30) </p>

<p>(−0.22) </p>

<p>(−0.69) </p>

<p>(0.72) </p>

<p>(1.90) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>0.019** </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.028* </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>(0.61) </p>

<p>(−0.50) </p>

<p>(2.30) </p>

<p>(−0.14) </p>

<p>(1.71) </p>

<p>(0.10) </p>

<p>(0.30) </p>

<p>(0.43) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.032** </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>−0.007 </p>

<p>(0.86) </p>

<p>(2.08) </p>

<p>(0.87) </p>

<p>(−0.28) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.7567 </p>

<p>0.0022 </p>

<p>0.0213 </p>

<p>0.2786 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P/P/P/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>2. HlthPlan [BRFSS] </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.015* </p>

<p>0.015* </p>

<p>0.0003 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>(0.03) </p>

<p>(0.48) </p>

<p>(1.67) </p>

<p>(1.70) </p>

<p>(0.03) </p>

<p>(−0.22) </p>

<p>(1.64) </p>

<p>(1.40) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.023* </p>

<p>−0.010 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>−0.0002 </p>

<p>−0.022 </p>

<p>−0.043 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.020* </p>

<p>(−1.86) </p>

<p>(−0.69) </p>

<p>(0.01) </p>

<p>(−0.01) </p>

<p>(−1.05) </p>

<p>(−1.16) </p>

<p>(0.79) </p>

<p>(1.77) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.020 </p>

<p>−0.001 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>−0.022 </p>

<p>(−1.21) </p>

<p>(−0.03) </p>

<p>(0.65) </p>

<p>(−1.37) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.1863 </p>

<p>0.3984 </p>

<p>0.6647 </p>

<p>0.1362 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F/P/F/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/F/P/F </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Each model uses sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in Table 2, Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; 
corresponding t-statistics 
are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is </p>

<p>not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β </p>

<p>CM , β 
YA , and β </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>* YA from the placebo regression. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>BRFSS. Using the CPS measure and the "Levine" 
YAD-DDD model, our results are close to those 
of Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011), despite 
including more years (1997-1999 and 2009), 
using slightly different mandate dates, and lim-
iting our analyses to women. 24 However, the 
rest of our analyses provide very little evidence 
that either mandate increased insurance coverage. 
Using the BRFSS insurance measure instead is 
especially damaging, often leading to estimated 
negative effects. Our results are therefore consis-
tent with the conclusion drawn by Depew (2015)  and Monheit et al. (2011), which state that YADs 
did little to increase overall insurance coverage 
and may have instead simply caused a shifting 
between group versus individual, parent versus 
own, and/or private versus public. The results for 
CMs and the joint effect of CM and YAD like-
wise suggest little consistent effect, although it 
is somewhat surprising that they are found to be 
positive and significant about as often as the much 
more heavily studied YAD. 
The health-care access measures from the 
BRFSS, Not Afford and Checkup, likewise 
yield no consistent evidence that either mandate 
expanded young women's access to general 
health care, and in fact, the estimated effects are 
just as likely to be detrimental as beneficial (see 
Table S4). Given that we find no evidence that 
these mandates expanded insurance coverage, 
it is not surprising to find little effect on these 
general measures of care received. It nonetheless 
remains possible that switching types of cover-
age (à la YADs) could affect access in subtler 
ways, such as the quality or convenience of care 
received. If YADs lead young adults to switch to 
their parents' insurance, then that new insurance 
may differ in its coverage of contraception if the 
state also has a CM. Likewise, as Depew (2015)  and Colman and Dave (2015) find, the switch 
in health insurance may have been accompanied 
by other changed behaviors. Such subtle mech-
anisms suggest that these mandates could still 
have effects on general health, and the avenue for 
CMs to affect reproductive outcomes-by 
expanding contraceptive use among the 
insured-remains. </p>

<p>B. General and Reproductive Health Outcomes </p>

<p>Table 4 reports results for several mea-
sures of general health. The first two panels </p>

<p>24. Specifically, Levine, McKnight, and Heep (2011) find 
a statistically significant increase of 0.033 (Table 5, Panel A, 
column 2 on p. 148), while ours suggests a 0.028 increase. </p>

<p>are the standard self-reported health variable 
(1 = poor to 5 = excellent) from the CPS and 
BRFSS, transformed to Very Good plus (=1 if 
excellent or very good, 0 otherwise) as com-
monly constructed. Neither mandate in isolation 
appears to have a consistent effect on Very Good 
plus, but the effect of having both mandates is 
consistently positive and, in the BRFSS data, 
almost always statistically significant. More-
over, while the individual coefficients vary, the 
estimated total effect of having both mandates 
is surprisingly close across the two very dif-
ferent datasets and DDD models, ranging from 
0.023 to 0.046. 
We explore this finding further by estimating 
the same models using the number of days out 
of the last 30 that physical (mental) health was 
"not good" from the BRFSS (see Table 5). These 
analyses suggest no effect of either mandate on 
physical health, with the exception of the "De-
pew" model, which suggests that YADs reduce 
the number of "not good" days. The results are 
marginally more suggestive for mental health, but 
the mechanisms appear to differ. The "Depew" 
model once again finds that YADs are beneficial 
and that CMs may be as well, although the lat-
ter is not statistically significant. The "Levine" 
model finds it is CMs and perhaps the joint effect 
(CM*YAD) that are beneficial and that YADs 
are harmful if anything. However, the net total 
effect is again quite similar across the two DDD 
models; both suggest that having both mandates 
reduces the number of "not good" mental health 
days by 0.546-0.584 days. 
Taken together with the results for Very Good 
plus, a broad measure of health, we conclude 
that there is some weakly suggestive evidence 
that these mandates are improving the subjective 
well-being of young women, although the path-
ways are not clear. Our findings therefore echo 
those of Colman and Dave (2015) for the ACA's 
YAD mandate; perhaps they derive from the 
same mechanisms (decreased time spent working 
and waiting for or receiving care, increased time 
socializing). It is also intriguing to link our "De-
pew" findings with the reductions in labor supply 
caused by YADs found by Depew (2015); per-
haps that reduced labor supply is associated with 
improvements in health. 
Finally, we turn to reproductive outcomes, 
reported in Table 6. The top two panels report 
estimates from the aggregate Vital Statistics mea-
sures typically used. Here, we find similar results 
to Mulligan (2015) that CMs appear to reduce 
fertility until location-specific time effects </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>TABLE 4 </p>

<p>Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Measures of Self-Reported Health a </p>

<p>DD Models </p>

<p>DDD Models </p>

<p>Base </p>

<p>w/ State-Time Trends </p>

<p>By Status ("Levine") </p>

<p>By Age Only ("Depew") </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>1. Very Good </p>

<p>+ [CPS] </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.025* </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>(1.47) </p>

<p>(1.08) </p>

<p>(0.73) </p>

<p>(0.89) </p>

<p>(1.47) </p>

<p>(1.80) </p>

<p>(1.07) </p>

<p>(0.48) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>−0.008 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>−0.014 </p>

<p>−0.013 </p>

<p>−0.030 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>−0.016 </p>

<p>(0.17) </p>

<p>(−0.73) </p>

<p>(0.42) </p>

<p>(−0.82) </p>

<p>(−0.79) </p>

<p>(−0.83) </p>

<p>(0.64) </p>

<p>(−0.77) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>(1.05) </p>

<p>(1.41) </p>

<p>(0.74) </p>

<p>(1.45) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.2106 </p>

<p>0.4902 </p>

<p>0.2146 </p>

<p>0.4503 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>2. Very Good </p>

<p>+ [BRFSS] </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>−0.012 </p>

<p>−0.012 </p>

<p>−0.010 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>−0.009 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>(−0.36) </p>

<p>(−0.93) </p>

<p>(−0.86) </p>

<p>(−0.69) </p>

<p>(−0.36) </p>

<p>(−0.52) </p>

<p>(0.25) </p>

<p>(0.18) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>−0.019 </p>

<p>−0.004 </p>

<p>−0.041** </p>

<p>0.040* </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>−0.037** </p>

<p>(0.69) </p>

<p>(−1.18) </p>

<p>(−0.19) </p>

<p>(−2.09) </p>

<p>(1.73) </p>

<p>(−0.04) </p>

<p>(1.27) </p>

<p>(−2.32) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.046** </p>

<p>0.056** </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.079*** </p>

<p>(2.52) </p>

<p>(2.46) </p>

<p>(1.40) </p>

<p>(4.44) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.0893 </p>

<p>0.0323 </p>

<p>0.1498 </p>

<p>0.0002 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F/P/P/P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Each model uses sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in Table 2, Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; 
corresponding t-statistics 
are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is </p>

<p>not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β </p>

<p>CM , β 
YA , and β </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>* YA from the placebo regression. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>TABLE 5 </p>

<p>BRFSS Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Measures of Self-Reported Physical and Mental Health a </p>

<p>DD Models </p>

<p>DDD Models </p>

<p>Base </p>

<p>w/State-Time Trends </p>

<p>By Status ("Levine") </p>

<p>By Age Only ("Depew") </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>1. PhysHlth 
CM </p>

<p>−0.018 </p>

<p>0.0001 </p>

<p>0.034 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>−0.018 </p>

<p>0.209 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>(−0.15) </p>

<p>(0.00) </p>

<p>(0.22) </p>

<p>(0.16) </p>

<p>(−0.15) </p>

<p>(1.59) </p>

<p>(0.35) </p>

<p>(0.43) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.007 </p>

<p>0.088 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>0.175 </p>

<p>−0.266 </p>

<p>−0.114 </p>

<p>−0.206* </p>

<p>−0.302* </p>

<p>(−0.05) </p>

<p>(0.52) </p>

<p>(0.47) </p>

<p>(0.72) </p>

<p>(−0.91) </p>

<p>(−0.37) </p>

<p>(−1.68) </p>

<p>(−1.87) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.131 </p>

<p>−0.106 </p>

<p>−0.160 </p>

<p>0.162 </p>

<p>(−0.70) </p>

<p>(−0.43) </p>

<p>(−0.37) </p>

<p>(0.73) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.8879 </p>

<p>0.9064 </p>

<p>0.2977 </p>

<p>0.2006 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P/P/P/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>2. MentalHlth </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>−0.251 </p>

<p>−0.243 </p>

<p>−0.081 </p>

<p>−0.088 </p>

<p>−0.251 </p>

<p>−0.820*** </p>

<p>−0.238 </p>

<p>−0.232 </p>

<p>(−1.30) </p>

<p>(−1.39) </p>

<p>(−0.31) </p>

<p>(−0.31) </p>

<p>(−1.30) </p>

<p>(−3.12) </p>

<p>(−1.27) </p>

<p>(−1.17) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.076 </p>

<p>−0.026 </p>

<p>0.276 </p>

<p>0.155 </p>

<p>0.527* </p>

<p>0.867** </p>

<p>−0.402* </p>

<p>−0.504*** </p>

<p>(−0.26) </p>

<p>(−0.09) </p>

<p>(0.73) </p>

<p>(0.50) </p>

<p>(1.66) </p>

<p>(1.97) </p>

<p>(−1.83) </p>

<p>(−3.08) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−0.028 </p>

<p>0.187 </p>

<p>−0.631 </p>

<p>0.190 </p>

<p>(−0.08) </p>

<p>(0.43) </p>

<p>(−1.11) </p>

<p>(0.70) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.5748 </p>

<p>0.8158 </p>

<p>0.0020 </p>

<p>0.0298 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/F/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Each model uses sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in Table 2, Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; 
corresponding t-statistics are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is </p>

<p>not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β </p>

<p>CM , β 
YA , and β </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>* YA from the placebo regression </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>TABLE 6 </p>

<p>Results of the Effect of State Mandates on Birth and Abortion Rates and Reported Pregnancies a </p>

<p>DD Models </p>

<p>DDD Models </p>

<p>Base </p>

<p>w/ State-Time Trends </p>

<p>By Status ("Levine") </p>

<p>By Age Only ("Depew") </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>1. Births [VS] 
CM </p>

<p>−2.223* </p>

<p>−2.571** </p>

<p>−0.594 </p>

<p>−0.52 </p>

<p>−0.411 </p>

<p>−0.88 </p>

<p>(−1.86) </p>

<p>(−2.16) </p>

<p>(−0.39) </p>

<p>(−0.34) </p>

<p>(−0.51) </p>

<p>(−0.75) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.270 </p>

<p>−0.91 </p>

<p>−0.538 </p>

<p>−1.35 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>0.329 </p>

<p>−0.377 </p>

<p>(0.22) </p>

<p>(−0.45) </p>

<p>(−0.53) </p>

<p>(−1.03) </p>

<p>(0.51) </p>

<p>(−0.35) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>2.104 </p>

<p>1.299 </p>

<p>0.689 </p>

<p>(0.94) </p>

<p>(0.86) </p>

<p>(0.49) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.1762 </p>

<p>0.7622 </p>

<p>0.8204 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>2. Abortions [AS] </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>−1.628** </p>

<p>−1.212* </p>

<p>−0.811 </p>

<p>−0.864 </p>

<p>(−2.24) </p>

<p>(−1.96) </p>

<p>(−1.31) </p>

<p>(−1.43) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>2.773** </p>

<p>−0.279 </p>

<p>0.266 </p>

<p>(0.06) </p>

<p>−2.05 </p>

<p>(−0.43) </p>

<p>−0.32 </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>NA </p>

<p>YAD×CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>−3.410** </p>

<p>−0.816 </p>

<p>(−2.32) </p>

<p>(−0.70) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.0548 </p>

<p>0.5029 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F/P/F/F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F/P/P/F </p>

<p>3. Pregnant [BRFSS] </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>YAD </p>

<p>YAD*CM </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>−0.008 </p>

<p>−0.016** </p>

<p>−0.016** </p>

<p>−0.006 </p>

<p>−0.013 </p>

<p>−0.013** </p>

<p>−0.015** </p>

<p>(−1.07) </p>

<p>(−1.49) </p>

<p>(−2.41) </p>

<p>(−2.28) </p>

<p>(−1.07) </p>

<p>(−0.98) </p>

<p>(−2.35) </p>

<p>(−2.46) </p>

<p>YAD (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>−0.008 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.016* </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>(1.13) </p>

<p>(−0.42) </p>

<p>(0.57) </p>

<p>(−0.84) </p>

<p>(1.24) </p>

<p>(1.26) </p>

<p>(1.78) </p>

<p>(0.83) </p>

<p>YAD × CM (× Eligible) </p>

<p>0.015* </p>

<p>0.018* </p>

<p>−0.018 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>(1.77) </p>

<p>(1.72) </p>

<p>(−0.69) </p>

<p>(0.82) </p>

<p>Joint Test (p value) </p>

<p>0.1987 </p>

<p>0.0401 </p>

<p>0.4806 </p>

<p>0.0273 </p>

<p>Placebo Test b </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P/F/P/F </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>P/P/P/P </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Each model uses sample weights and controls for state-level characteristics reported in Table 2, Panel B as well as age, year, and state fixed effects. Standard errors are clustered by state; 
corresponding t-statistics 
are reported in parentheses, and *, **, *** indicate 10, 5, and 1% significance levels, respectively. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>The placebo test replaces each mandate variable with a dummy for whether the mandate is in place 3 years in the future. P indicates whether the estimated coefficient passes, that is, is </p>

<p>not statistically significant at the 10% level; F indicates fails. The fourth indicator for the YAD*CM model is the joint test of β </p>

<p>CM , β 
YA , and β </p>

<p>CM </p>

<p>* YA from the placebo regression. </p>



<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>

<p>are included, which eliminate all significant 
effects. 25 Moreover, our placebo tests suggest 
that including those effects are necessary. We 
augment these previously studied measures with 
whether the young woman reports being pregnant 
(via the BRFSS), included in the bottom panel. 
These individual-level data allow us to estimate 
all four DD and DDD approaches, as we have 
for all of the other outcomes. These results are 
consistent with the aggregate data, suggesting 
that CMs have a negative effect on pregnancy. 
Now, however, including location-specific time 
effects appears less necessary, and their inclusion 
strengthens the impact of CMs. These analy-
ses are also weakly suggestive that YADs may 
increase pregnancy, which is not implausible, 
especially if YADs make it easier for women 
to get insurance from a source other than their 
employers and reduces their labor supply. </p>

<p>VI. CONCLUDING REMARKS </p>

<p>This research takes a comprehensive approach 
to studying the effects of insurance mandates 
on young adults by using contrasting empirical 
methodologies to estimate the individual and pos-
sibly joint effects of both YAD and contracep-
tion insurance mandates on a wide set of out-
comes spanning several different datasets. Our 
approach helps settle conflicting past findings as 
well as uncovers more complicated pathways for 
these mandates to have an effect. For YADs, our 
results support the more tepid findings of Depew  (2015) and others that such mandates do not sig-
nificantly increase overall insurance coverage. 
Rather, the strong effects of Levine, McKnight,  and Heep (2011) appear unique to their method-
ology and data source (the CPS). Using an alter-
native methodology (e.g., a DDD based on age 
only) or dataset (BRFSS) overturns the positive 
results we find using the CPS and their approach. 
Past research on the effect of CMs on fertil-
ity outcomes (as measured with aggregate births 
and abortions) has also been mixed, whereby 
strong negative effects are greatly diminished 
by the inclusion of location-specific time trends 
(e.g., Mulligan 2015). We use similar-yet not 
identical-aggregate data as this past work and 
find the same mixed results. However, we also </p>

<p>25. Recall that the "Depew" model includes state-specific 
time trends. Also recall that these aggregate Vital Statis-
tics datasets have no individual characteristics (precluding 
"Levine") and that the abortion data are already aggregated 
by broad age groups (precluding "Depew"). </p>

<p>bring new evidence by estimating the effects one 
or both mandates have on reported pregnancy 
using data from the BRFSS. These analyses also 
yield a negative effect of CMs on fertility, an 
effect that is stronger when location-specific time 
effects are included. When combined with the 
aggregate evidence, it strengthens the case that 
CMs reduce fertility. 
These findings for insurance coverage and 
reproductive outcomes are largely unaffected by 
allowing the other mandate to have an effect as 
well, despite the fact that we find the two man-
dates' enactments are positively correlated. We 
do find some evidence, however, that the two 
mandates combine to affect the general health 
and well-being of young adults, an effect that is 
mostly obscured if each mandate is considered 
in isolation. Such effects are plausible in light of 
past work that finds other pathways for YADs to 
have an effect (through a change in coverage type 
or reducing labor supply) and our results here that 
CMs appear likely to have an effect on reproduc-
tive behavior. 
This research is not without its shortcomings. 
Our results are not as definitive as we would like 
and are instead mostly suggestive. Our analyses 
face the difficulty of identifying the unique and 
joint effects of two mandates using the relatively 
small number of years and states in which pol-
icy changes take place. This challenge is com-
pounded by the fact that these mandates likely 
fail to reach a significant proportion of young 
women; that is, the gap between intent-to-treat 
(what we estimate) and treatment-on-the-treated 
estimates is large. This is especially true for our 
DD and age-based DDD YAD models because 
many young adults do not satisfy other eligi-
bility requirements. More broadly, neither man-
date is binding for those young adults who get 
their insurance from self-insured firms (because 
of ERISA) or who already receive such coverage 
prior to the law. As noted by Depew (2015), such 
attenuation bias is likely to lead to insignificant 
results and is why he uses the American Com-
munity Survey to study labor supply, a very large 
dataset that is nearly 20 times bigger than the 
CPS or BRFSS. While these challenges extend 
to all studies of state-level YADs and CMs, 
studying both in tandem and subjecting them to 
such substantial robustness checks (different data 
sources and empirical methodologies) appears 
almost certain to exacerbate them and makes the 
consistent findings that do emerge compelling. 
The ACA, with its much wider reach and 
fewer exemptions, avoids some of these </p>

<p>TRUDEAU &amp; CONWAY: INSURANCE MANDATES &amp; YOUNG WOMEN </p>



<p>limitations and has led to an explosion of 
research studying the effects of its YAD. As 
the full potential of the ACA's impact grows, 
with the CM and other mandates firmly in place, 
future work should consider the dual effects of 
both of these mandates on the coverage, care, 
and well-being of young adults. At the same 
time, the possible repeal of the ACA, an outcome 
that appears more likely with the 2016 elections, 
suggests that these state-level mandates may 
once again become relevant and therefore so too 
the estimated effects we explore here. </p>





<p>CONTEMPORARY ECONOMIC POLICY </p>



<p>SUPPORTING INFORMATION </p>

<p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the 
online version of this article: 
Table S1. Summary of Studies on the ACA-YAD mandate 
on insurance, care, and health 
Table S2. Comparison of timing of state mandates 
across studies 
Table S3. State level sampling of care utilization and 
health measures in the BRFSS 
Table S4. Results of the effect of state mandates on health-
care utilization 
Figure S1. Timing of individual state mandates on young 
adult-dependent coverage and contraception coverage 
Figure S2. Growth in state-level YADs and CMs over 
time (1997-2009) </p>

</text></tei>