<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1080%2F14631377.2016.1139301" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Over the past century European security has been strongly influenced by the dynamics of 
economic and military power, as well as by the use of economic warfare and sanctions to alter 
the balances between adversaries. 
1 The evolution of the Ukraine conflict and its outcomes 
during 2014-2016 are consistent with this rule, in that they have been affected by the per-
formances of the Russia and Ukraine economies, resource-driven changes in Russia-NATO 
(North Atlantic Treaty Organisation) conventional forces, imbalances between Russia and 
Ukraine in military capabilities, and energetic efforts to use economic sanctions to influ-
ence opponents. However, the defence economic dimension of the Ukraine crisis has been 
relatively neglected. 
The objectives of this article are to draw lessons from the defence economic history 
of Europe over the past century in order to address the following questions: what levels 
of resource commitments were required of NATO countries and the USSR to generate the 
military power that ensured nuclear and conventional deterrence in Europe in the Cold 
War period? What have been the unique defence economic institutions and policies that 
have enabled the USSR and Russia to produce military capabilities that have appeared to 
be more substantial than warranted by their economic power? Did the policies of national </p>

<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The evolution and outcomes of conflicts in Europe, including the 
current one in Ukraine, have been influenced by the dynamics of 
economic, technological and military balances, which in turn are 
affected by the economic warfare and sanctions that have been 
used to alter them. This article reviews defence economic concepts 
of relevance to the Ukraine conflict and then draws out lessons 
for the present concerning power balances, military capabilities, 
conventional deterrence, economic warfare and counter-measures 
against sanctions from experiences in Europe in the twentieth century. 
An evaluation is made of the impacts of economic sanctions on Russia 
and Ukraine in 2014-2016. </p>

<p>© 2016 the Author(s). Published by taylor &amp; Francis. 
this is an open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-nonCommercial-noDerivatives License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, 
provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. </p>

<p>KEYWORDS </p>

<p>Economic power; military 
capabilities; technology; 
economic warfare and 
sanctions; Russia; ukraine </p>

<p>ARTICLE HISTORY </p>

<p>Received 1 July 2015 
Accepted 5 December 2015 </p>

<p>CONTACT Christopher mark Davis 
christopher.davis@wolfson.ox.ac.uk </p>

<p>OPEN ACCESS </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>governments in Europe to achieve financial 'peace dividends' in the post-Cold War period 
adversely affect NATO's conventional military capabilities and thereby its deterrence of 
Russian actions related to Ukraine? Have the dynamics of economic, technological and mil-
itary balances influenced the general developments in security in Europe and the genesis 
of the Ukraine conflict? Did Western economic warfare and sanctions directed at the USSR/ 
Russia over the period 1917-2013 achieve established goals concerning the alteration of 
economic and military power balances? What have been the economic and military impacts 
on Russia of Ukraine-related economic sanctions during 2014-2016?  The analysis is divided into two inter-related components, both covering the period 1917-
2016. The first is concerned with the assessment of: the organisation and performance of 
the defence sectors in the economies of the USSR and Russia; trends in defence capabilities, 
economic and military balances, and conventional deterrence in Europe; the adequacy of 
resources allocated to support NATO, including its expansion in the 2000s; and comparison 
of the economic power and military capabilities of Russia and Ukraine in 2013-2016. The 
second section evaluates the causes and features of Western economic warfare directed at 
the USSR/Russia, as well as Russian responses and economic results in the periods 1917-1945,  1945-1991 and 1992-2013. it then describes Western economic sanctions imposed on Russia 
in connection with the Ukraine conflict and assesses their economic, military and political 
impacts. The remainder of this introduction reviews concepts related to these main sections. </p>

<p>Generation of military power by the economy, military balances in Europe, and 
conventional deterrence </p>

<p>The concept of economic power of relevance to national security concerns what Knorr (1957,  p. 8) called 'economic defense potential' , which is determined by the volume and rate of 
growth of GDP, the structure and flexibility of output at the sector level, and capabilities in sci-
ence and technology. Economic power is produced by an economic system that is governed 
by economic policies and functions in a multi-dimensional economic environment (Gregory  &amp; Stuart, 1999). OECD/NATO countries have had competitive and open market economies, 
which over time have performed well at macro and micro levels in the generation of eco-
nomic power. in contrast, the USSR/CMEA countries had centralised, state-owned, planned 
and closed economies. These developed the characteristics of a 'shortage economy' , which 
generated rapid extensive economic growth but inhibited efficiency and technological pro-
gress (Davis &amp; Charemza, 1989; Kornai, 1980, 1992). Following the collapse of the communist/ 
command systems in Europe, all countries engaged in the processes of economic transition. 
Those in East Europe and the Baltic region made rapid progress to market economies and 
joined the EU. But Russia, Ukraine and other states that emerged from the USSR developed 
hybrid economic systems (part market, part state) that performed poorly in the 1990s. 
The Soviet economy had obvious formal features (planning, price controls, state monopoly 
of foreign trade), but also had six important 'Hidden Processes' (HP) that influenced eco-
nomic performance and have been carried over into the contemporary market economies 
of Russia and Ukraine: HP 1, indirect bureaucratic control (Kornai, 1992); HP 2, pervasive 
second economies with related corruption networks (Davis, 1988); HP 3, negative value 
added in industry (e.g. obsolete factories in East Ukraine) (McKinnon, 1991); HP 4, a 'Rent 
Management System' (RMS) that involves the state redistributing the value obtained from 
energy exports through formal and informal channels (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2005, 2010); HP 5, </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>'implicit' subsidisation of allied East European states (e.g. low oil prices in trade with CMEA 
countries) (Marrese &amp; vanous, 1983); and HP 6, illegal acquisition of restricted foreign tech-
nologies (CiA (US Central intelligence Agency), 1985). 
2 in this article references will be made 
to the HP numbers as these processes are discussed. 
The inter-relationships between economic power and military developments in Europe 
have been studied thoroughly over the centuries (Goodwin, 1991). in his 1878 publication 
Anti-Dühring Engels (1970, pp. 184-185 cited in Davis, 1991a) wrote: </p>

<p>… the triumph of force is based on the production of arms, and this in turn on production in 
general -therefore on 'economic power' , on the 'economic order' , on the material means which 
force has at its disposal … Nothing is more dependent on economic pre-conditions than pre-
cisely the army and navy. </p>

<p>Similar points were made by Lenin and early Soviet defence economists (Davis, 1991a). 
During World War ii all major countries not only studied the problem of how to convert eco-
nomic power into military capabilities, but also implemented policies in their war economies 
to accomplish this, with varying degrees of success. in the post-war period Knorr (1957, p. 7,  1973) argued that 'defense potential' was dependent not only on economic power, but also 
on the efficiency of the utilisation of resources devoted to defence (organisational ability) 
and on the 'will to provide for military power' (e.g. share of GDP devoted to defence). Studies 
of economic power and security have been continued up to the present (Fels, Kremer, &amp;  Kronenberg, 2012). 
Military capabilities are determined not only by the general conversion of economic 
power to defence potential, but also by the performance of the defence sector, which is made 
up of six economic institutions (armed forces, defence industry, defence supply (logistics), 
military R&amp;D, military foreign trade, and the central defence bureaucracy) that function in 
specific economic systems (Davis, 1990b, 2002). Pozharov (1981, pp. 116-117) describes the 
interconnection as follows: </p>

<p>in order for economic power to be converted into military strength, it is necessary to provide for 
the production of armaments, combat technology and other items of a military nature, the cor-
rect distribution and timely delivery of them to the troops, and the creation of all the conditions 
for their effective utilization. A special social organism serves these goals -the military economy. 
The scale and effectiveness of the military economy characterizes the military-economic power 
of the state, that is, its actual capability to provide its armed forces and to support the necessary 
defensive capacity of the country. </p>

<p>in the case of the USSR, the defence sector was given a high priority status within the planned 
economy, which meant that it benefited from the preferential allocation of scarce resources 
and from the establishment of special organisations (e.g. the Military-industrial Commission) 
to ensure the accomplishment of the national security objectives of the state. Aspects of 
Soviet defence organisation have been maintained in the Russian Federation (Davis, 2002). 
Government policy makers take into account external and domestic threats (military, 
economic, political) when developing a national security strategy that includes both threat 
reduction programmes (diplomatic, propaganda, arms control, espionage) and the military 
capabilities generated by the defence sector (Davis, 1986a, 1986b, 1992). in the case of 
the USSR, the strategy of the Brezhnev regime placed heavy emphasis on military power, 
whereas the Gorbachev government shifted it to threat reduction (see quotation on p. 6). in 
the Russian Federation, the government of Yeltsin placed less emphasis on military power 
than has that of Putin. </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>A final concept used in this study concerns the impacts on nations of the relative dynamics 
of economic, technological and military balances. 
3 Kennedy (1988) argued that the rises and 
declines of major countries, empires and alliances in Europe in the twentieth century were 
strongly influenced by shifts in these balances and that an important skill in statecraft in 
the economic sphere is the maintenance of an appropriate distribution of national income 
between consumption, investment and defence. The adverse impacts of a sustained heavy 
defence burden on the USSR are evaluated in Davis (1990a). </p>

<p>Goals and features of economic warfare and sanctions </p>

<p>Economic warfare (including specific economic sanctions) is intended primarily to influence 
economic, technology and military power balances to the advantage of the country/alli-
ance conducting it. Punitive measures can relate to trade in commodities (embargo, denial 
of 'Most-Favoured Nation' (MFN) status, refusal of export licences, preclusive buying) and 
finance (freezing of assets, restrictions on lending, expropriation of property) (Baldwin, 1985,  p. 41). Even in periods with no overt economic warfare, countries that are leaders in tech-
nology maintain controls on exports that concern both the features of technologies (e.g. 
advanced encryption) and potential recipient countries (Joyner, 2006; Kabrt &amp; Jung, 2015;  MacDaniel, 1993; Rode &amp; Jacobsen, 1985). 
in this article economic warfare (including sanctions) is interpreted as a politico-economic 
process with a beginning, an end, and the following features in between: EWF (Economic 
Warfare Feature) 1, trigger (cause); EWF 2, establishment of objectives (economic, military, 
political); EWF 3, agreement on conditions for termination; EWF 4, decisions on specific 
measures (e.g. restrictions on trade and finance); EWF 5, comprehensiveness of participation; 
EWF 6, commitment to implementation (e.g. rigorous or symbolic); EWF 7, effectiveness of 
counter-measures; EWF 8, evaluation of impacts; and EWF 9, removal of restrictions/sanc-
tions. These nine features are discussed throughout the historical periods examined in the 
second section of this article, including the one related to the Ukraine conflict. Elements 
of this process (trigger, measures, counter-measures, economic impacts) are summarised 
in three historical tables covering Western economic warfare (sanctions) directed against 
the USSR/Russia during 1917-1945 (Table 6), 1949-1991 (Table 7) and 1992-2016 (Table 
8). A more detailed assessment of anti-Russia sanctions related to the Ukraine conflict is 
presented in Table 10, which considers specific measures, goals and impacts (economic, 
military, political) during 2014-2016. </p>

<p>Economic-military power balances in Europe from the Bolshevik Revolution 
in 1917 to the Ukraine conflict in 2016 </p>

<p>Economic power, military capabilities and conventional deterrence in the Soviet 
period </p>

<p>The underdeveloped and unbalanced economy of the Russian Empire experienced severe 
strains in supporting the country's intensive military involvement in WWi (e.g. supporting 
the largest army in the conflict), which contributed to the revolutions of 1917 (Davis, 1999;  Service, 2009). 
4 The Bolsheviks developed the War Communism economic system to mobilise 
all available resources to fight and win the Civil War. Following the victory Lenin recognised </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>the economic weakness of the revolutionary nation and introduced the New Economic 
Policy in the 1920s to stimulate an economic recovery and ease domestic political tensions. 
Although the large Red Army was demobilised and much of the defence industry was con-
verted to civilian production, the government understood the importance of providing a 
strong economic foundation for the military power of the socialist state in a threatening 
world (Davis, 1991a; Erickson, 1962; Pozharov, 1981). The adoption of the Stalinist economic 
programme, including the high priority status of defence, generated rapid industrialisation 
in the 1930s (Davis, 1996). This enabled the USSR to shift economic and military balances in 
its favour in peacetime and to convert quickly to a militarised economy during World War 
ii (Harrison, 1985). 
The Soviet Union emerged victorious from World War ii, but its economy was severely 
damaged and its structure was distorted in favour of the military sector. By the mid-1950s 
it had reduced the military burden and entered a period of rapid extensive growth with 
rising living standards that continued into the mid-1970s (Davis, 1999, 2014a). The index of 
USSR industrial production (1970=100.0) increased from 22.2 in 1950 to a peak of 189.1 in 
1988 (Figure 1). Despite Western economic warfare, the Soviet Union became the dominant 
economic power in Europe. Although the USSR introduced numerous economic reforms, it 
retained an inefficient shortage economy that was characterised by decelerating GDP growth 
and sluggish technological innovation (Ellman &amp; Kontorovich, 1992; Gregory &amp; Stuart, 2001). 
Soviet hard-currency trade through its state monopoly expanded dramatically in the 
1970s because of increases in world market prices for energy and in exports of oil and gas: 
energy earnings rose from $388 million in 1970 to $18,865 million in 1984. The government 
made use of its evolving 'Rent Management System' (RMS) (HP 4) to redistribute the growing 
energy 'rent' (value) to finance imports, to support the defence effort, and to subsidise inef-
ficient enterprises (HP 3) and East European countries (HP 5) (Davis, 2014a; Gaddy &amp; ickes,  2005; Marrese &amp; vanous, 1983). </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Index of Industrial Production, 1970 = 100 </p>

<p>Years </p>

<p>Industrial Production 
Index (1970 = 100) 
Year 
Index 
1950 
22.2 
1953 
29.5 
1957 
42.0 
1965 
73.8 
1970 
100.0 
1975 
133.2 
1980 
157.8 
1985 
174.0 
1988 
189.1 
1991 
169.2 </p>

<p>Late 
Stalin </p>

<p>Khrushchev Era 
Inter-
regnum </p>

<p>Mature Soviet Command Economy 
Perestroika </p>

<p>Figure 1. industrial production in the ussR, 1950-1991. source: Davis (1999, p. 347). </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>OECD economies grew at healthy rates during 1950-1973, experienced 'stagflation' in  1974-1980 due to oil price shocks, and then entered a period of sustained growth. Overall, 
from 1965 to 1985 Soviet economic power declined relative to the major OECD countries and 
the technology gap with the USA widened: 8-10 years for advanced microcircuits and 9-15 
years for mainframe computers in the mid-1980s (DOD (US Department of Defense), 1988). 
From the mid-1960s the Soviet leadership pursued an ambitious strategy to enhance 
national security that placed greater emphasis on military power than on threat reduction 
(Davis, 1992, 2002; Sapir, 1991). The allocation of resources to the defence sector rose sub-
stantially and by the 1980s the defence burden was around 15% of GDP. The increases in 
the armed forces and deployed weapons are shown in Table 1. Western economic warfare 
(discussed in the next main section) slowed the emergence of the USSR as the second super-
power, but did not prevent it (DOD, 1981 … 1990). 
However, by the mid-1980s the Soviet leadership recognised that the increments to Soviet 
military capabilities were generating diminishing returns to the security of the USSR and were 
undermining the economy and the living standards of the population, so it adopted a differ-
ent strategy. in a 1988 speech Gorbachev explained the 'new thinking' (Davis, 1990a, p. 94): </p>

<p>… it is now quite clear that building up military power makes no country omnipotent. What is 
more, one-sided reliance on military power ultimately weakens other components of national 
security … We are witnessing the emergence of a new historic reality -a turning away from the 
principle of super-armament to the principle of reasonable defence sufficiency. </p>

<p>During the late Cold War period NATO built up its conventional and strategic nuclear forces 
and achieved deterrence in Europe. This required substantial commitments of resources to 
defence: USA 6% of GDP, UK 5%, France 4% and Germany 3%. Although there were tensions 
in Europe during 1945-1989, there were no armed conflicts or changes in international 
borders. The USA did not recognise the 1940 annexations of Estonia, Latvia and Lithuania, 
but it treated this as a side-issue in order to manage its relations with the USSR for the sake 
of global stability. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Table 1. Developments in the soviet defence sector: 1965-1991.   sources: Author's calculations, 2015; Davis (2002, p. 157). </p>

<p>indicator 
Units  1965  1970  1975  1980  1985  1990  1991   Armed Forces Manpower 
total armed forces 
thousands 
3885 
3405 
3615 
3715 
3980 
3065 
2910 
strategic rocket forces 
thousands 
110 
350 
350 
385 
300 
260 
165 
Ground forces 
thousands 
1460 
1750 
1825 
1825 
1995 
1475 
1400 
Air forces 
thousands 
510 
330 
440 
550 
570 
420 
420 
Air defence forces 
thousands 
440 
500 
500 
520 
635 
500 
475 
navy 
thousands 
390 
475 
500 
435 
480 
410 
450 
Armed Forces Military Equipment 
tanks 
number 
28,000 
38,000 
42,000 
50,000 
52,600 
54,000 
54,400 
total artillery, mortars 
number 
19,000 
21,000 
26,100 
29,900 
50,200 
64,200 
64,200 
GF helicopters 
number 
300 
800 
1550 
2000 
4300 
4500 
4500 
Fighter/attack aircraft 
number 
2300 
2850 
3550 
5000 
5900 
4335 
4905 
submarines (ss/ssn) 
number 
190 
240 
265 
257 
203 
242 
221 
strategic bombers 
number 
118 
157 
157 
157 
160 
128 
100 
iCBms 
number 
281 
1472 
1469 
1338 
1371 
1378 
1006 
iCBm warheads 
number 
281 
1472 
2169 
5362 
6813 
6938 
6106 
ssB/ssBn 
number 
25 
44 
73 
85 
78 
60 
55 
sLBm warheads 
number 
72 
287 
828 
1558 
2264 
2900 
2792 
total warheads 
number 
882 
2327 
3565 
7488 
9997 
11,252 
10,164 </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>The USA and USSR became involved in numerous conflicts in the Third World, but it 
proved to be increasingly difficult for them to make effective use of traditional military 
force in unconventional warfare. 
6 The USA suffered several defeats involving large losses of 
US weapons that had been supplied to weak regimes threatened by revolutionary forces: 
Ethiopia in 1974, vietnam in 1975, and Nicaragua and iran in 1979. The USSR fought and lost 
a war in Afghanistan during 1979-1989.  Although the Gorbachev regime introduced reforms of the national security strategy 
and economy, its policies were not successful in either significantly lowering the defence 
burden or in closing the economic power gap (Davis, 1991b). Living standards deteriorated, 
technological innovation stagnated and the USSR continued to decline as a world power 
(Davis, 1990a; Ellman &amp; Kontorovich, 1992). The communist regimes in Eastern Europe col-
lapsed in 1989 and in the USSR in 1991. Economic warfare and sanctions played minor roles 
in bringing about these changes. </p>

<p>Declines in the economic and military power of Russia and Ukraine in the 1990s </p>

<p>Russia and Ukraine emerged as independent states in 1991 with similar inheritances of a 
malfunctioning shortage economy with newly revealed negative value-added components 
(HP 3) and the common challenge of establishing a market system in difficult politico-eco-
nomic circumstances. Due to the weakness of the state in Russia there was a break-down in 
the priority protection system and in central control of the RMS (HP 4), which had less rent 
(value) to distribute because of low energy prices ($22 per barrel). initial macroeconomic 
stabilisation efforts failed in both countries, which resulted in 40% declines in GDP and 
high inflation (EBRD (European Bank for Reconstruction and Development), 1994 … 1999). 
Microeconomic processes were dominated by barter between firms, build-ups of informal 
inter-enterprise debt, pervasive second economy activity and corruption (HP 2), ineffective 
privatisation, limited industrial restructuring, and little FDi (see Note 10). By the mid-1990s 
Russia had a 'virtual economy' in which the state pretended to promote market-oriented 
reform while using the RMS to transfer value from the energy sector to negative value-added 
industries (HP 1, HP 3) in order to avoid mass bankruptcies and political unrest (Gaddy &amp;  ickes, 1998, 2005). 
7 in 1998 Russia experienced a new financial crisis due to its large budget 
deficits and debt (GKO) levels and a 50% drop in the price of oil to $11 per barrel. 
Macroeconomic developments in Ukraine in the 1990s mirrored those in Russia. in the 
main industrialised region in East Ukraine the large Soviet-era firms were mostly unprofitable 
(HP 3), closely integrated with Russian ones, and supported by subsidies from Russia in the 
forms of low energy and raw material prices and guaranteed orders for products that were 
uncompetitive internationally (HP 5) (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2014a). 
in contrast, OECD economies experienced healthy growth, and technological progress 
accelerated. The East Europe and Baltic countries engaged successfully with necessary 
reforms and their economies recovered quickly. So the gaps in economic power widened 
between Russia/Ukraine and important countries in the world. 
Russia and Ukraine lowered the priorities of their military-industrial complexes and 
drastically reduced defence expenditures (Davis, 2002; international institute for Strategic  Studies (iiSS), 1992 … 2000). Their armed forces and defence industries operated in difficult 
circumstances and experienced deteriorations of their capabilities (Allison, 1997; Gaddy,  1996; Odom, 1998). Negligible progress was achieved in defence-related reforms. in 1993 </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>Ukraine agreed to give up its nuclear weapons and to lease military bases in Crimea to Russia 
in return for energy subsidies and guarantees of its territorial integrity. Although Russia and 
Ukraine moved apart in the political sphere, they remained closely integrated in defence 
industry and military R&amp;D (Cooper, 2013). 
The effectiveness of NATO armies remained high and new military technologies were 
introduced (stealth design, smart bombs, drones). However, due to the widespread per-
ception that there were no longer serious security threats in Europe, the NATO countries 
decided to obtain an economic 'peace dividend' by reducing defence expenditures, military 
personnel and weapon systems (see Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 2. Armed forces of ussR, Russia, ukraine, uK, usA in Europe, Germany: 1990, 2000, 2013.   sources: Author's calculations, 2015; iiss military Balances (1991, 2001, 2014). </p>

<p>indicator </p>

<p>Years </p>

<p>1990 
2000 
2013 </p>

<p>USSR 
military personnel 
3,988,000 
nA 
nA 
tanks 
61,500 
Artillery 
66,880 
Combat aircraft 
4335 
Helicopters 
4500 
Defence % GDP 
15.0 
Russia 
military personnel 
nA 
1,004,100 
845,000 
tanks 
21,820 
2550 
Artillery 
20,746 
5436 
Combat aircraft 
1455 
1389 
Helicopters 
2108 
392 
Defence % GDP 
2.8 
3.1 
Ukraine 
military personnel 
nA 
303,800 
129,950 
tanks 
3937 
1110 
Artillery 
3704 
1952 
Combat aircraft 
543 
139 
Helicopters 
247 
221 
Defence % GDP 
3.4 
1.3 
UK 
military personnel 
306,000 
210,940 
169,150 
tanks 
1330 
363 
227 
Artillery 
705 
418 
610 
Combat aircraft 
823 
504 
283 
Helicopters 
107 
228 
176 
Defence % GDP 
5.2 
2.4 
2.3 
USA in Europe 
military personnel 
299,200 
99,382 
67,463 
tanks 
5917 
657 
53 
Artillery 
2685 
326 
123 
Combat aircraft 
660 
237 
179 
Helicopters 
210 
134 
48 
Defence % GDP 
6.5 
3.4 
3.7 
Germany 
military personnel 
469,000 
321,000 
186,450 
tanks 
5045 
2815 
322 
Artillery 
2492 
2115 
272 
Combat aircraft 
697 
457 
205 
Helicopters 
210 
102 
22 
Defence % GDP 
3.2 
1.6 
1.2 </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>The table shows that the number of UK Main Battle (MB) tanks dropped from 1330 in 
1990 to 363 in 2000. Substantial withdrawals were made of the military forces of the USA, 
UK and France deployed in Germany. Despite these cutbacks, NATO engaged in bombing 
campaigns in 1995 in Bosnia-Herzogovina (against Bosnian Serb forces in the civil war) and 
in 1999 in Serbia (related to Kosovo). These actions were strongly opposed by Russia. in 1999 
the membership of NATO was expanded to include Czech Republic, Hungary and Poland. 
in the post-Cold War period through 2013 there was significant instability of the borders 
of countries in Europe with a total of 30 alterations. There were peaceful changes in 22 cases: 
reunification of Germany; fragmentation of the USSR into 15 successor states; division of 
Czechoslovakia; independence of Slovenia and FRY Macedonia; and Serbia and Montenegro 
splitting. Three states achieved independence following wars: Serbia-Montenegro, Bosnia-
Herzogovina and Croatia. in five other cases regions of a state with an aggrieved ethnic 
minority achieved autonomy through armed conflict with the support of a foreign power, 
and thereafter entered the category of 'frozen conflict': Transdniestria (1992), South Ossetia 
(1992), Abkhazia (1993), Nagorno-Karabakh (1994) and Kosovo (1999). The weakening of 
NATO's conventional deterrence influenced the development of several of these conflicts. </p>

<p>Recovery in Russia, stagnation in Ukraine, expansion of the EU and NATO, and 
power balances in Europe during 2000-2013 </p>

<p>vladimir Putin was elected President of Russia in 2000 and has remained the dominant 
leader since then. Despite slow progress with economic reforms in Russia, GDP grew by an 
average of 7% during 2000-2008 due to increases in earnings from energy exports (the oil 
price rose to a peak of $145 per barrel in 2008) and in consumption and investment. The 
greater resource rents available to the government through the RMS (HP 4) enabled it to 
support welfare programmes, subsidise negative-value added and loss-making industries 
(HP 3), and reduce domestic and international debt (Connolly, 2015a; Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2010). 
However, the RMS continued to allow substantial informal siphoning off of rents and the 
second economy (HP 2), with its related corruption networks, remained an important com-
ponent of the Russian economy (Kim &amp; Kang, 2009). The Global Financial Crisis (GFC) caused 
temporary negative growth, but the population and economy in Russia were protected by 
stabilisation funds built up prudently by imposing high taxes on energy exports. During 
2010-2013 GDP growth was a healthy 3.4%, inflation remained low, and surpluses were 
achieved in the state budget and current account (see Table 3 for 2012-2013). Russia's high 
growth rates enabled it to reduce the economic power gap in Europe. 
Russia deepened its integration into the global economy by joining the WTO in 2012 
and developing closer economic links with the EU, its most important trade partner. But 
Russia also attempted to enhance its economic relationships with Former Soviet Union (FSU) </p>

<p>Table 3. Performances of economies of Russia and ukraine: 2012-2016. </p>

<p>sources: Author's calculations, 2015; EBRD (2015), imF (2015a, 2015c) and World Bank (2015a, 2015b, 2015c). </p>

<p>Russia economy 
Ukraine economy </p>

<p>2012 2013 2014 2015 2016 2012 2013 2014 2015 
2016 
GDP growth (%) 
3.4 
1.3 
0.6 
-3.8 
-0.6 
0.2 
0.0 
-6.8 -12.0 
1.0 
inflation (average annual %) 
5.1 
6.8 
7.8 
15.5 
7.5 
-0.2 
0.5 
24.9 
50.0 
23.4 
Government balance/GDP (%) 
0.4 
-1.3 
-1.2 
-4.3 
-2.1 
-5.4 
-6.7 -10.3 -7.3 
-3.9 
Current account balance/GDP (%) 
3.6 
1.6 
3.2 
8.1 
6.9 
-8.2 
-9.2 
-4.1 
-1.1 
-1.4 
External debt/GDP (%) 
32.0 
34.8 
33.0 
29.2 
27.0 
76.6 
78.6 
97.6 
153.0 
134.2 </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>countries (Armenia, Belarus, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Ukraine) by establishing the Eurasian 
Economic Union (EEU), with a target start date of 2015. 
Ukraine has had a democratic political system, but one with instability due to the division 
of the population between pro-Europe segments in the West and pro-Russia ones in the 
East (Huntington, 1996). 
8 The peaceful Orange Revolution in 2005 promised political and 
economic reforms and reductions in the pervasive corruption in the economy (HP 2), but the 
pro-West government was ineffectual in promoting improvements in productivity (e.g. by 
closing down negative value-added industries in the East) and in eradicating corrupt hidden 
practices at all levels that severely distorted economic processes. in 2010 the population 
elected the more pro-Russian President Yanukovich. 
With respect to macroeconomic performance, growth of GDP in Ukraine recovered to 
an average of 7% over 2000-2008, but then contracted by 15% in 2009. During 2010-2013 
Ukraine had a low average growth rate of 2.4% (zero in 2013), chronic budget and current 
account deficits, and high foreign debt to GDP burdens (79% in 2013) (Table 3). Ukraine 
remained dependent on Russia for energy supplies and as a market for exports of uncom-
petitive industrial commodities (HP 5) (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2014a). </p>

<p>9   The EU economies grew at the modest rate of 2.3% during 2000-2008. The Baltic and 
Central East European countries benefited from inflows of FDi and completed their acces-
sions to the EU in 2004 and 2007.  10 However, the GFC caused recessions in most European 
countries, with average annual growth of -4.4% in 2009 and only 0.9% during the 2010-2013 
recovery period. The poor economic performances in Europe increased pressures on gov-
ernments to reduce public expenditures, including those on defence. The EU continued to 
expand, despite its economic problems and austerity policies in several countries (notably 
Greece), by granting membership to Croatia in 2012. it made efforts to involve FSU states 
through the European Neighbourhood Policy (ENP) and Europe Association Agreements. 
Russia changed its national security strategy in the 2000s to place more emphasis on 
military power, raised the priority of the defence sector, and adopted ambitious plans for 
weapons procurement and reforms of the armed forces (Davis, 2002, 2011; FOi (Swedish  Defence Research Agency), 2010; iiSS, 2000 … 2014; Monaghan, 2014; SiPRi (Stockholm 
international Peace Research institute), 2000…2014). The organisation of the Russian defence 
sector in the early 2000s is shown in Figure 2. 
The three key decision-making and management bodies were the Russian President, 
the Security Council, and the State Commission for Military-industrial issues. Real ($2011) 
defence spending increased from $31.1 billion in 2000 to $84.8 billion in 2013 (SiPRi Milex  Online Database, 2015). The defence share of GDP rose from 3.6% of GDP to 4.2%. The size 
of the armed forces was reduced from 1,004,100 to 845,000 and the number of MB tanks 
from 12,920 to 2550 as part of modernisation (Table 2). Limited progress was made in mil-
itary reforms through 2008, but efforts were intensified after the GFC. The Russian military 
engaged in counter-insurgency operations in the Caucasus (Chechnya, Dagestan) and was 
victorious in a war against Georgia over South Ossetia in 2008. 
Due to economic difficulties in Ukraine and the low priority its government awarded to the 
defence sector, military expenditure as a share of GDP fell from 3.6% in 2000 to 2.4% in 2013 
(SiPRi Milex Database, 2015). But it increased in real ($2011) terms from a low $2.4 billion to 
$4.4 billion. The number of troops was reduced from 303,800 to 130,000 and MB tanks from 
3895 to 1110 (Table 2). The malfunctioning of the Ukraine economy and the disregard of the </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>military by successive governments meant that in 2013 the armed forces suffered from low 
pay and poor conditions for officers and men, obsolete weapons, and inadequate training. 
in the 2000s NATO continued to withdraw conventional forces from forward-operating 
bases. By 2013 the USA had only 53 MB tanks and 48 helicopters in the Conventional Forces 
in Europe (CFE) zone. National armies were reduced. Germany cut the size of its armed forces 
from 321,000 to 186,450 and the number of MB tanks from 2815 to 322 (Table 2). From 1993 
to 2013 the number of combat aircraft in France was cut from 630 to 290. NATO defence 
spending rose after 11 September 2001, but most of the increment was devoted to War on 
Terror operations outside of Europe (iraq, Afghanistan). Defence expenditure was reduced 
significantly in most European countries after the GFC and by 2013 their average defence 
share of GDP was 1.6% (Table 4) (iiSS, 2014). 
Despite the cutbacks in armed forces and defence expenditures, NATO expanded its 
membership by including the Baltic and East Europe countries in 2004 (Bulgaria, Estonia, 
Latvia, Lithuania, Romania, Slovakia, Slovenia) and 2009 (Croatia) and developed closer rela-
tions with some FSU states (Georgia, Ukraine, Moldova). NATO Europe per capita defence 
expenditure in real terms ($2005) dropped from $715 in 1990 to $515 in 2000 to $401 in 
2013 (Table 4). </p>

<p>Armed Forces 
Military Supply System 
Defence Industry 
Military RDT&amp;E 
Military Foreign Trade </p>

<p>Non-MOD Units 
DI Institutes 
Civilian Firms </p>

<p>Units involved 
in the Storage, 
Distribution &amp; 
Maintenance 
of Other Goods 
Defence Firms </p>

<p>Units involved 
in the Storage, 
Distribution &amp; 
Maintenance 
of Weapons 
Export Firms 
Import Agencies 
Other Institutes 
MOD Units </p>

<p>y 
c 
a 
r 
c 
u 
a 
e 
r 
u 
B 
e 
c 
n 
e 
f 
e 
D 
l 
a 
r 
t 
n 
e 
C </p>

<p>Border Guards 
Ground Forces </p>

<p>Air Forces </p>

<p>Strategic 
Nuclear Forces </p>

<p>Internal Troops </p>

<p>Railway 
Troops </p>

<p>Spetsnaz 
Troops of 
GRU and 
Others </p>

<p>Navy </p>

<p>Rear Services 
Directorates of 
Food, Fuel, Trade, 
Clothing, Housing </p>

<p>Main Armaments 
Directorate, 
Armaments 
Directorates of the 
AF Services </p>

<p>Federal Security 
Service (FSB) </p>

<p>General Staff </p>

<p>GRU </p>

<p>Main Military 
Council </p>

<p>Civilian Firms 
with Military 
Output </p>

<p>Academy of 
Sciences RF </p>

<p>Federal Agency 
for Shipbuilding </p>

<p>Federal Agency 
for Munitions </p>

<p>Federal Agency 
for Control 
Systems </p>

<p>Russian 
Aviation-Space 
Agency </p>

<p>Federal Agency 
for Conventional 
Weapons </p>

<p>Chemical </p>

<p>Electrical and 
Electronics </p>

<p>Petroleum </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Internal Affairs </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Defence </p>

<p>Min of Civil 
Defence and 
Emergencies </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Industry, Science 
and Technology </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Economic 
Development and 
Trade </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Atomic Energy </p>

<p>State Comm for 
Military-Tech 
Co-operation </p>

<p>Research 
administrations of 
the civilian 
ministries, MOD, 
and AS RF </p>

<p>Research 
administrations of 
the defence 
industry agencies </p>

<p>Weapons import 
programmes </p>

<p>Spetsinformatsiya 
programme: SVR, 
GRU, MFERT, 
AS RF </p>

<p>2 
8 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Government of the 
Russian Federation </p>

<p>Russian Federation 
President </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 
12 
10 </p>

<p>Rosoboroneksport 
[Merger of 
Rosvooruzhenie, 
and PromEksport] </p>

<p>Independent 
weapons export 
programmes </p>

<p>5 
8 </p>

<p>2 
8 
13 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>9 
10 
5 </p>

<p>Security Council </p>

<p>Presidential 
Administration </p>

<p>FSB Troops </p>

<p>State Duma 
Federation Council </p>

<p>Construction 
Troops, FAPSI 
Troops and 
Other Troops </p>

<p>Committee on Defence 
Committee on Security 
and Defence </p>

<p>Federal Railway 
Troops Service </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Finance, Dept. of 
Defence Complex </p>

<p>Federal Agency for 
State Comms and 
Info (FAPSI) </p>

<p>Federal Border 
Guards Service </p>

<p>13 
10 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Committee on Industry </p>

<p>Foreign 
Intelligence 
Service (SVR) </p>

<p>Deputy PM for 
Defence Complex </p>

<p>State Commission for 
Military-Industrial Issues </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Federal Special 
Construction 
Service </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Main 
Penitentiary 
Directorate 
Troops </p>

<p>11 
6, 7 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Committee on Security </p>

<p>Ministry of 
Justice </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Figure 2. the organisation of the Russian defence sector in the early 2000s. source: Davis (2002, p. 161). </p>

<p>Table 4. nAto Europe defence expenditure: 1990, 2000, 2013. </p>

<p>note: the defence expenditure share of GDP in the 1990 column is the average of 1990-1994. 
sources: Author's calculations, 2015; nAto (2014). </p>

<p>1990 
2000 
2013 
total defence expenditures 
$ 2005 million 
274,923 
247,363 
225,767 
Defence expenditures as share of GDP 
% 
2.7 
2.0 
1.6 
Defence expenditures per capita 
$ 2005 
715 
515 
401 </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>Since spending by European countries after 2001 included significant 'out-of-area' com-
ponents, per capita expenditure of relevance to the defence of Europe was lower during 
the 2000s than is suggested by aggregate defence spending figures. NATO also proceeded 
with the development of a missile defence system in Europe. This was strongly opposed by 
Russia, which withdrew from the Conventional Forces in Europe Treaty in 2007 in retaliation. 
Overall, the sustained reductions in military expenditure and armed forces by NATO countries 
during 1991-2013 undermined conventional deterrence in Europe. </p>

<p>11   Over this period NATO countries also significantly scaled back intelligence efforts focussed 
on Russia (CiA/DiA in the USA and Mi6/Ministry of Defence in the UK), and redeployed expe-
rienced analysts with Russia/Ukraine area knowledge and language capabilities to the War 
on Terror in the Middle East and South Asia. in 2011-2012 the USA announced that it would 
be making a major shift in its strategic focus away from peaceful Europe to the Asia-Pacific 
region to deal with new threats. 
During 2000-2013 the USA augmented its poor record of supplying weapons to weak 
armed forces that either allowed weapons to be stolen on a large scale or were defeated and 
surrendered supplies to US opponents: Afghanistan army 2001 ongoing (to the Taleban); iraq 
army 2003-2010 (to Shia and Sunni insurgents); Georgia army 2008 (to Russia); iraq army 
2014 (to iSiS); Syria democratic forces 2015 (US anti-tank weapons to al-Nusra Front); and 
Yemen army 2015 (much of the $500 million in US military aid to al-Houthi and al-Qaeda 
rebels) (Whitlock, 2015). 
With respect to the military balance in Europe in 2013, both NATO and Russia had reduced 
numbers of personnel and weapons compared to 2000. NATO military equipment remained 
superior technologically to that of Russia and potentially provided a deterrent to conflict 
involving members of the alliance. However, the numbers of operational NATO conventional 
weapons in Europe were at such low levels (Table 2) that Russia did not need to take into 
account NATO actual capabilities when making national security decisions related to the 
Ukraine conflict. 
The differences between Russia and Ukraine with respect to economic performance, 
priority given to defence and military expenditure meant that the bilateral economic and 
military balances shifted strongly in favour of the former during 2000-2013. Table 5 shows 
that by 2013 Russia had three times the population and GDP Per Capita of Ukraine and 
nine times the GDP (PPP). in the military sphere, Russia had substantially greater numbers 
of armed forces personnel and weapons and devoted more resources to defence both in 
absolute terms and as a share of GDP. </p>

<p>Table 5. Russia-ukraine economic and military balances in 2013. </p>

<p>note: there is an inconsistency between the GDP (PPP) figures and those related to Defence expenditure/burden due to 
differences in methodologies and base years. 
sources: Author's calculations, 2015. Population: RF FsGs (Russian Federation, Federal'naya sluzhba Gosudarstvennoi statis-
tiki) (2014, p. 641); GDP (PPP): CiA World Factbook (2015); GDP (PPP) per capita calculated by dividing GDP by population; 
Armed forces, tanks: table 2; Defence expenditure and Defence burden: siPRi military Expenditure Database (2015). </p>

<p>indicator 
Units 
Russia 
Ukraine 
Ratio Russia to Ukraine 
Population 
thousands 
143.7 
45.2 
3.2 
GDP (purchasing power parity) 
Billion 2013 us$ 
3556 
399 
8.9 
GDP (PPP) per capita 
us$ 
24,746 
8830 
2.8 
Armed forces personnel 
number 
845,000 
129,950 
6.5 
tanks 
number 
2550 
1110 
2.3 
Defence expenditure (exchange rate) 
Billion 2011 us$ 
84.8 
4.4 
19.3 
Defence burden 
DE % GDP 
4.2 
2.4 
1.8 </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>Defence-economic aspects of the conflict in Ukraine 2013-2015 </p>

<p>The evolution, features and consequences of the Ukraine conflict have been fully docu-
mented elsewhere (e.g. UK House of Lords, 2015) and are only briefly reviewed below. This 
section focuses on the interconnections between economic and military developments in 
Ukraine and Russia. 
The crisis grew out of the need by Ukraine to obtain external support for its faltering 
economy either from the EU/iMF (requiring wide-ranging reforms and a Greece-style aus-
terity programme) or from Russia as a reward for participating in the new EEU. The decision 
by President Yanukovich in Autumn 2013 to pursue the latter course provoked the Maidan 
protest movement (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2014a). The government found that it had to rely primarily 
upon the highly-paid riot police (Berkut) in controlling the increasingly violent political dis-
pute because the ordinary police had divided loyalties and the underfunded armed forces 
made it clear that they would not get involved in an armed conflict involving Ukrainian 
citizens. Following the overthrow of the President in February 2014, the interim government 
reversed foreign economic policies to favour the EU and expressed an interest in joining 
NATO (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2014c). in response to these political changes and the growing prob-
lems in the economy, the iMF (international Monetary Fund), EC (European Commission) 
and USA have been providing Ukraine with substantial financial assistance, which is linked 
to economic reform and austerity programmes. </p>

<p>12   Russia disapproved of the revolutionary changes in Ukraine and perceived a risk that it 
would lose its important military bases in Crimea, which give it access through the Black Sea 
to the Mediterranean Sea (e.g. for naval transport of weapons systems and ammunition to 
Syria). Since the bilateral economic and military balances were in Russia's favour (Table 5) 
and conventional deterrence of NATO had degraded (Table 2), it implemented a covert oper-
ation to take control of Crimea that was effective because competent non-violent actions 
by pro-Russia units and Russian special forces were backed by the implicit threat of decisive 
military intervention by Russia. 
During Spring 2014 the insurrections by pro-Russian forces in East Ukraine (Luhansk, 
Donetsk) received hidden assistance from Russia (Allison, 2014; iiSS, 2014, 2015). in June 
the Ukraine government attempted to re-establish control in East Ukraine by sending in its 
armed forces (supplemented by nationalist militias), despite the weaknesses of the army 
(e.g. poor training and equipment, limited counter-insurgency skills), lack of international 
military support, superior Russian military capabilities, and the demonstration in Crimea that 
Russia was prepared to intervene militarily. The attempted re-occupation of East Ukraine 
was resisted successfully by the pro-Russian insurgents during two phases of war, but the 
conflict resulted in heavy civilian casualties because both sides used artillery, tanks, mortars 
and rockets in fighting in villages and cities. The armed combat was ended in February 2015 
by the Minsk ii Agreement and a relatively stable truce existed throughout the remainder 
of the year and into early 2016. 
in response to the annexation of Crimea, the war in the eastern regions and the shooting 
down of Malaysia Airlines Flight 17, economic sanctions were imposed on Russia by foreign 
countries, which are discussed in the next section. NATO has supplemented these sanctions 
with military ones. in recognition of the erosion over the past two decades of the conven-
tional deterrence provided by NATO in Europe, the USA and UK have redeployed troops, 
tanks and aircraft to 'front-line states' (notably the Baltic countries) for military exercises </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>and border patrols. Several NATO countries have provided the Ukrainian armed forces with 
military trainers and non-lethal military supplies. A couple of NATO European countries 
have made commitments to raise defence spending to the agreed low level of 2% of GDP. 
A controversial issue debated during 2014-2015 was whether or not NATO should directly 
provide weapons and military equipment to Ukraine. The poor performances of the Ukraine 
armed forces in the two active phases of the war reflected the sustained neglect of them 
by successive governments. Some pro-Ukraine politicians and security analysts in the West 
argued in favour of such supplies in order to turn the tide of battle. However, the prevailing 
opinion was that the current imbalance of military power in Ukraine in favour of the insur-
gents in the eastern regions and Russia could not be changed in the short-term by foreign 
powers providing more sophisticated weapons to Ukraine. Evidence was provided earlier in 
this article concerning the record of the repeated failures of the USA in supplying weapons to 
weak governments with poorly performing armies (see pp. 7 and 12). it has been clear that 
the armed forces of Ukraine would require extended intensive training before they could 
handle some of the systems (e.g. the AN/TPQ-53 mobile anti-artillery radar system) being 
proposed by supporters of arms supplies. Other drawbacks to this interventionist policy were 
the comprehensive penetration of Ukraine government organisations by Russian intelligence 
and Russian escalation dominance in conventional weapons (Allison &amp; Simes, 2015). Taking 
these factors into account, NATO probably was correct in deciding to not provide weapons 
directly to Ukraine during 2014-2015 (Monaghan, 2015). </p>

<p>Western economic warfare and its impacts on the USSR and Russian 
Federation, 1917-2016 </p>

<p>Western economic warfare, Soviet counter-measures and their impacts, 1917-1991 </p>

<p>Foreign countries waged economic warfare against the USSR from its creation because of 
both its revolutionary ideological threat and specific 'triggers' (EWF 1): Soviet Russia with-
drawing from World War i; attempted socialist revolutions in Western countries; Soviet 
espionage abroad; the USSR military build-up in the 1930s; and the Nazi-Soviet pact. The 
features of Western economic warfare and Soviet counter-measures during 1917-1945 are 
described in Table 6. </p>

<p>13   However, participation in anti-USSR economic warfare was uneven (EWF 5 
Comprehensiveness) due to competition between the leading capitalist nations in military 
and economic spheres. Germany covertly provided the USSR armed forces and defence 
industry with assistance in the 1920s (D'yakov &amp; Bushueva, 1992; Nekrich, Ulam, &amp; Freeze,  1997). Western firms, notably American ones, exported large quantities of machinery and 
equipment to Stalin's USSR in the 1930s, which assisted its rapid industrialisation (Sutton,  1971). Germany exported manufactured goods to the USSR during 1939-1941 in return for 
supplies of energy and raw materials needed to wage its war in the West, whereas the USA 
and Britain provided the Soviet Union with substantial economic and military assistance to 
fight Germany in the years 1941-1945 (Ericson, 1999; Nekrich et al., 1997). 
Soviet Russia developed economic warfare counter-measures (EWF 7) against the cap-
italist countries that involved secret cooperation (e.g. with Germany during 1922-1933), 
trade diversion and technological espionage (run by Cheka-OGPU-NKvD and military intel-
ligence) (HP 6). Secret Gosplan (State Planning Committee) 'control figures' for 1928-1929 </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>demonstrate that the covert acquisition of Western technology for branches of the defence 
industry was built into state plans (Davis, 2005, 2014b). 
14 Soviet intelligence ran many suc-
cessful operations during 1939-1945 to obtain secret Western technologies and blueprints 
of weapons systems (e.g. the atomic and hydrogen bombs) (Andrew &amp; Gordievsky, 1990;  Usdin, 2005). 
The growing power of Stalin's USSR impelled the newly formed (1949) NATO alliance to 
adopt containment policies that involved formalised economic warfare against the USSR 
under the supervision of the Coordinating Committee for Multilateral Export Control (CoCom) 
(Adler-Karlsson, 1968) (see Table 7). 
The objectives of the economic warfare were to restrain the development of the military 
and economic power of the USSR and Warsaw Pact (EWF 2). All important industrialised 
countries participated in these restrictions on trade and finance (EWF 5), which remained in 
effect to a diminishing degree until the end of the Cold War. Supplemental sanctions were 
introduced in response to unacceptable actions by the USSR (e.g. 1956 suppression of the 
uprising in Hungary, 1968 Warsaw Pact invasion of Czechoslovakia). 
Three cases of Cold War anti-Soviet economic sanctions have relevance to the current 
Ukraine crisis. The first case illustrates the problem of ending sanctions (EWF 3). in 1974 
the US Congress adopted the Jackson-Vanik Amendment to the Trade Act that imposed 
the sanction of not offering MFN status to any country with a non-market economy that 
restricted freedom of emigration and human rights (verona, 2012). This was a response to </p>

<p>Table 6. Western economic warfare and sanctions against the ussR: 1917-1945.   sources: Author's calculations, 2015. For 1917-1921: service (2009); 1918: D'yakov and Bushueva (1992); 1921-1928:  service (2009); 1928-1939: sutton (1971); 1939-1941: nekrich et al. (1997) and Ericson (1999); 1941-1945: Harrison  (1985). </p>

<p>Start date 
Trigger 
West actions 
Russian response 
Economic results 
1917-1921 
Bolshevik Revolution, 
withdrawal from WWi, 
renunciation of tsarist 
debts, civil war </p>

<p>West embargoes all 
trade and lending 
to ussR 1918-1921 
and tries to destroy 
Bolsheviks </p>

<p>Focus on survival, 
War Communism, 
requisitioning </p>

<p>survival of Bolshevik 
regime and socialist 
economy </p>

<p>1918 
Versailles treaty 
Restrictions on Ger-
many, soviet Russia 
excluded </p>

<p>secret ussR-Germany 
military and defence 
industry cooperation </p>

<p>Both ussR and 
Germany benefit from 
covert cooperation 
1919-1932 
1921-1928 
soviet revolutionary 
activities in foreign 
countries </p>

<p>Continuation of 
embargoes, but some 
businesses resume 
trade </p>

<p>Lenin's policy of con-
cessions, technologi-
cal espionage </p>

<p>nEP promotes recovery 
of economy, some 
foreign economic 
assistance 
1928-1939 
ussR revolutionary 
activities, military 
build-up, stalin purges </p>

<p>Attempts to continue 
economic warfare, 
but Great Depression 
stimulates exports 
of machinery and 
technology to ussR </p>

<p>ussR imports West 
technology and 
machinery, technolog-
ical espionage </p>

<p>Western technology 
helps with industriali-
sation of ussR in 1930s </p>

<p>1939-1941 
nazi-soviet Pact, 
invasion of Poland, 
war with Finland, 
occupation of Baltic 
states </p>

<p>trade embargoes, but 
Germany supplies 
machinery and equip-
ment to ussR </p>

<p>ussR ally of Germany 
and provides it with 
raw materials for war 
effort, technological 
espionage </p>

<p>soviet economy and 
military power develop 
in late 1930s </p>

<p>1941-1945 
invasion of ussR by 
Germany, attack on 
usA by Japan </p>

<p>usA/uK form alliance 
with ussR and provide 
it with substantial 
economic assistance </p>

<p>stalin regime accepts 
Western aid in return 
for fighting nazi 
Germany </p>

<p>Western aid and 
technology help ussR 
to win wars against 
Germany and Japan </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>the trigger of the Soviet Union's repression of dissidents and blocking of the attempts of 
citizens to emigrate. The Jackson-Vanik legislation remained in effect throughout the Cold 
War, even though the Gorbachev government removed the causes of it (see pp. 17 and 18 
for discussions of its continuation in the post-communist period). 
The second case relates to the comprehensiveness of participation in sanctions (EWF 5) 
and to divisions between the USA and Europe. in response to the invasion of Afghanistan in 
1979 by the USSR and the adoption of martial law in Poland in 1981, the USA imposed dra-
conian controls on the export to the USSR of energy-related technologies (as well as a 1980 
grain embargo) and asked its NATO partners to participate. However, West Europe decided 
to ignore the US sanctions and instead to cooperate with the USSR in building the 4500 km 
natural gas pipeline from the Urengoi gas fields to Ukraine during 1982-1984 (CiA, 1981). 
The third case illustrates the tendency for sanctions to be terminated in response to 
more important international developments (EWF 6 Commitment). in 1983 a Soviet fighter 
aircraft shot down Korean Airlines civilian passenger flight 007, which had strayed into Soviet 
airspace. The world community was appalled and additional sanctions were imposed on the 
USSR in response (Goodrich, 1988). But after 1985 the Western powers quietly removed them 
in order to work constructively with the new reformist Soviet leader, Mikhail Gorbachev. </p>

<p>Table 7. Western economic warfare and sanctions against the ussR: 1945-1991. </p>

<p>sources: Author's calculations 2015. For 1945-1991: Adler-Karlsson (1968), Rode and Jacobsen (1985) and Hunter (1991);  1956: Adler-Karlsson (1968); 1968: Hanson (1988); 1965-1979: Hunter (1991); 1979: Adler-Karlsson (1982), Hanson (1988)  and Hunter (1991); 1981: Hunter (1991); 1983: Goodrich (1988). </p>

<p>Start date 
Trigger 
West actions 
Russian response 
Economic results 
1945-1991 
Development of Cold 
War, arms race, con-
flicts in third World </p>

<p>West wages economic 
warfare using CoCom of 
nAto </p>

<p>ussR planned econ-
omy, high priority for 
defence and heavy 
industry, technology 
espionage </p>

<p>ussR develops econ-
omy and becomes 
military superpower </p>

<p>1956 
uprising in Hungary 
and suppression by 
soviet troops, Poland 
crisis </p>

<p>introduction of sup-
plemental economic 
sanctions </p>

<p>Develop CmEA and 
links with neutral 
countries, third World 
(india) </p>

<p>Limited, short-term 
economic impacts of 
West sanctions </p>

<p>1968 
Prague spring reform 
in Czechoslovakia 
suppressed by War-
saw Pact invasion </p>

<p>introduction of sup-
plemental economic 
sanctions </p>

<p>ussR improves CmEA 
and its military-
industrial complex 
(miC), technology 
espionage </p>

<p>Limited, short-term 
economic impacts of 
sanctions </p>

<p>1965-1979 
soviet repression 
of intellectuals and 
Jewish dissidents </p>

<p>1974 Jackson-Vanik limits 
mFn, 1978 restrictions on 
export of gas/oil drilling 
technology, but some 
relaxation of CoCom due 
to détente </p>

<p>ussR improves CmEA, 
miC, Spetsinformat-
siya </p>

<p>Limited, short-term 
economic impacts 
of sanctions, soviet-
West trade rises 
by a factor of 10 
1971-1979 due to oil 
prices 
1979 
soviet invasion of 
Afghanistan </p>

<p>us embargo on exports 
of grain and technology 
to ussR, limits on finance </p>

<p>ussR improves CmEA, 
miC, Spetsinformat-
siya </p>

<p>short-term disruption 
of soviet-West trade </p>

<p>1981 
Polish military 
imposes martial law 
to suppress solidarity </p>

<p>introduction of economic 
sanctions to block devel-
opment of gas fields </p>

<p>ussR develops miC, 
builds gas pipelines 
using Europe tech-
nology </p>

<p>Dramatic increase in 
natural gas exports to 
Europe benefits ussR 
economy 
1983 
shooting down of 
KAL 007 </p>

<p>Limits on Aeroflot in usA, 
suspension of cultural 
and scientific exchanges, 
deployment of Pershing 
missiles in Europe </p>

<p>ussR experiences 
minor disruptions 
to services, acts to 
improve East-West 
relations </p>

<p>Relaxation of con-
straints on East-West 
trade due to pere-
stroika from 1985 </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>By the 1960s the USSR had a well-organised and effective Spetsinformatsiya (special 
information) system that involved the intelligence services (KGB (Komitet Gosudarstvennoi 
Bezopasnosti), GRU (Glavnoe Razvedyvatel'noe Upravlenie)) covertly collecting restricted 
Western technologies on a large scale in accordance with detailed plans produced by the 
Military-Industrial Commission and KGB Directorate T (HP 6). According to the CiA (1985): </p>

<p>Each year Moscow receives thousands of pieces of Western equipment and many tens of thou-
sands of unclassified, classified, and proprietary documents as part of this campaign. virtually 
every Soviet military research project -well over 4,000 each year in the late 1970s and over 5,000 
in the early l980s -benefits from these technical documents and hardware. The assimilation 
of Western technology is so broad that the United States and other Western nations are thus 
subsidizing the Soviet military build-up. </p>

<p>The West learned about the full extent of the Soviet Spetsinformatsiya system from secret 
documents provided to French intelligence by an officer in KGB Directorate T, called Agent 
Farewell (Hanson, 1987; Kostin &amp; Raynaud, 2011). 
An evaluation of economic warfare and sanctions directed at the USSR in the Cold War 
period indicates that the NATO/OECD countries made a serious professional effort to impede 
the developments of Soviet defence-related economic power and military capabilities and 
achieved some success in slowing the emergence of the USSR as the second superpower. 
However, the economic warfare was undermined by divisions in the West (e.g. West Europe 
cooperating with the USSR in building the gas pipeline) and moderately effective coun-
ter-measures by the Soviet Spetsinformatsiya system. </p>

<p>Western economic sanctions, Russian counter-measures and their impacts in the 
transition period, 1992-2013 </p>

<p>Economic warfare and sanctions directed at Russia diminished markedly following the col-
lapse of the USSR (Table 8). The rationale for maintaining CoCom was undermined and the 
organisation was disestablished in 1994 (Joyner, 2006). it was replaced in 1996 by the new 
multilateral non-proliferation Wassenaar Agreement, which included Russia as a member. 
However, the USA, UK and other technology leaders maintained national Export Control 
Lists concerning military and dual-use technologies. Some categories of technologies 
were not approved for export to Russia in the 1990s. Although the justification for the 
1974 Jackson-Vanik Amendment had disappeared completely, the US Congress would not 
agree to its repeal due to anti-Russia sentiments, which meant that the Executive Branch 
(US President) had to grant Russia an annual waiver for it to obtain MFN status (EWF 3 End 
Conditions). 
As in the past, Russia attempted to circumvent foreign controls on technologies of rele-
vance to its defence efforts using a re-organised Spetsinformatsiya system (HP 6). The main 
agencies involved were the Ministry of Defence GRU and the successor to the foreign arm of 
the KGB, the SVR (Sluzhba Vneshnei Razvedki), notably its Directorate X: Scientific and Technical 
Intelligence. However, technological acquisition operations were adversely affected in the 
1990s by political changes in Russia (the shift to a democratic political system and an initial 
pro-West foreign policy) and tight budget constraints due to the collapse of the economy. 
The USA intensified its controls on exports of military and dual-use technologies post-
'9/11' (Table 8). 
15 Due to the military build-up by Russia in the 2000s and the worsening 
of bilateral relations, these controls increasingly inhibited high-technology trade between </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>the two countries. The Jackson-Vanik Amendment was repealed in 2012 (this was necessary 
for legal reasons because of Russia's entry to the WTO), but it was replaced by the Sergei 
Magnitsky Rule of Law Accountability Act of 2012, which imposed sanctions (visa bans, freez-
ing of assets) on Russian government officials who had been involved in the maltreatment 
of the Russian anti-corruption lawyer (this relates to EWF 3 on the difficulty in establishing 
End Conditions). 
Russia imposed restrictions on its own exports and imports from the West, such as its five-
month ban in 2010 on the import of poultry products from the USA (with a value of $760 
million in 2009), ostensibly because of health risks (EWF 7 Counter-measures). Throughout 
the 2000s Russian intelligence agencies (GRU, SVR) made efforts to obtain controlled mili-
tary and dual-use technologies in the OECD countries and achieved some successes (HP 6). 
in sum, the West continued to control high-technology trade with Russia in the post-com-
munist period and to maintain various outmoded sanctions (notably Jackson-Vanik). But 
these measures were fragmented and unevenly enforced across the Western alliance, and 
offset to some extent by Russian counter-measures. As a result, the impacts of Western 
economic warfare/sanctions on the economic and military power of the Russian Federation 
during 1992-2013 were rather minor compared to those of other determinants (e.g. world 
market price of oil). </p>

<p>Western economic sanctions and Russian counter-measures related to the Ukraine 
conflict </p>

<p>Economic sanctions were imposed on Russia by the EU, USA, Canada, Japan and several 
other countries in response to the annexation of Crimea, the war in the eastern regions and 
the shooting down of Malaysia Airlines Flight 17. 
16 The official measures included: (1) actions 
against individuals who played roles in the Crimea/Ukraine conflicts; (2) trade embargoes; </p>

<p>Table 8. Western economic warfare and sanctions against the Russian Federation: 1992-2015.   sources: Author's calculations, 2015. For 1992-2013: macDaniel (1993), Joyner (2006) and ussD (2015); 1992-2012: Verona 
(2012); 2012: Verona (2012); 2014-2015: Blackwill and simes (2014) and World Bank (2015a, Part 3). </p>

<p>Start date 
Trigger 
West actions 
Russian response 
Economic results 
1992-2013 
normal us/uK con-
cerns for technology 
security </p>

<p>usA and uK maintain 
export control lists, 
difficult for Russia to 
obtain some items </p>

<p>imposes its own 
export controls, tech-
nological espionage </p>

<p>Difficulty in obtaining 
high-tech, military-re-
lated technologies </p>

<p>1992-2012 
inertia and reluctance 
by us to remove even 
historic anti-soviet 
sanctions </p>

<p>Jackson-Vanik 
Amendment remains, 
but waived on annual 
basis. </p>

<p>Russians complain 
about Cold War relic </p>

<p>since Jackson-Vanik 
waived every year, no 
impact </p>

<p>2012 
Human rights abuses 
in Russia, death in 
prison of sergei 
magnitsky </p>

<p>Jackson-Vanik 
Amendment removed 
in return for passage 
of magnitsky Act that 
imposes sanctions on 
Russian officials </p>

<p>Russians dispute 
details of case and 
impose restrictions on 
usA officials </p>

<p>no significant impact </p>

<p>2014-2015 
ukraine conflict, 
annexation of Crimea 
by Russia </p>

<p>Restrictions on 
individuals involved 
in ukraine conflict, 
ban on business in 
Crimea, restrictions of 
high-tech trade and 
provision of loans </p>

<p>Russian sanctions 
(ban on food imports), 
trade diversion, 
technological espio-
nage, covert financial 
operations </p>

<p>Western sanctions 
have limited macro-
economic impact on 
Russia </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>and (3) restrictions on finance (see Table 10 below). in addition, the Ukraine government 
subjected Russia to both official sanctions (e.g. banning Russian planes from flying through 
Ukrainian airspace) and unofficial ones (e.g. toleration of the technically criminal actions of 
shadowy nationalist groups using explosives to destroy the four pylons that supported the 
cables delivering electricity to the population of Crimea in November 2015). 
Two features of anti-Russia economic sanctions have undermined their effectiveness: 
participation and outsourcing. The sanctions have had the support of important countries 
with a collective GDP of US$42.5 trillion. However, Table 9 shows that seven major industrial 
countries (Brazil, China, india, indonesia, iran, South Korea and Turkey) with collective GDP 
of US$31.5 trillion declined to participate. This indicates that there is a major problem with 
EWF 5 (Comprehensiveness) in that current sanctions are much leakier than the marginally 
effective ones of the Cold War CoCom period. </p>

<p>17   The second problem is that NATO countries have transferred much of their electronic and 
high-technology production to lower wage non-participating countries, unlike in the more 
controlled Cold War period. 
18 This globalisation of defence production and procurement 
has facilitated Russian trade diversion and covert acquisition of technology (EWF 7, HP 6). 
A global development that amplified the effects of anti-Russia sanctions was the coin-
cidental drop in the world market price of oil (OPEC crude oil basket) from $115 per barrel 
in June 2014 to $50 in January 2015 and around $31 in January 2016. This external shock 
lowered Russia's dollar earnings from energy exports, which weakened the financial positions 
of its banks, businesses and government. Russia has been able to use its RMS (HP 4) and sub-
stantial stabilisation funds (the Reserve Fund and Sovereign Wealth Fund), that were devel-
oped from past high taxation on energy exports, to buffer the adverse impacts of sanctions 
on the population, corporations and the financial sector. But the lower oil price has reduced 
revenue flows through the RMS and prevented the replenishment of the stabilisation funds. 
The Russian government has responded to sanctions by adopting numerous coun-
ter-measures (EWF 7). With respect to Ukraine, it imposed restrictions on exports of </p>

<p>Table 9. GDP of participant and non-participant countries in anti-Russia sanctions: 2013. </p>

<p>note: Gross domestic product based on purchasing power parity (PPP) valuation of country GDP in current us$. 
sources: Author's calculations, 2015; imF (2015c, accessed in november 2015). </p>

<p>Country 
GDP PPP US$ billions, current 2013 </p>

<p>Participants in Sanctions 
Eu countries 
17,578 
usA 
16,768 
Japan 
4,668 
Canada 
1,518 
Australia 
1,053 
switzerland 
432 
norway 
328 
new Zealand 
151 
total 
42,496 
Non-participants in Sanctions 
China 
16,149 
india 
6,776 
Brazil 
3,013 
indonesia 
2,389 
south Korea 
1,697 
turkey 
1,444 
iran 
1,244 
total 
31,467 </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>agricultural and industrial goods to Russia, cut energy subsidies and demanded pre-pay-
ment of gas supplies. 
19 it banned imports of food from the countries imposing sanctions and 
made efforts to find alternative suppliers in non-participating nations. in March 2015 Russia 
prohibited Western iT firms based in Russia from bidding for state contracts (about 70% of 
their in-country revenue) if they are observing Western restrictions on doing business in 
Crimea. in November 2015 the Russian government required all state agencies to purchase 
Russian-sourced software (e.g. for spreadsheets) instead of foreign products (e.g. <rs type="software">Excel</rs>) from 
the start of 2016. in an unrelated action, but one relevant to this article, Russia imposed 
economic sanctions on Turkey (restrictions of charter flights for tourists, removal of visa-free 
travel, suspension of investment projects, a ban on hiring Turkish citizens) in late November 
2015 in response to the Turkish air force using a US-supplied F-16 to shoot down a Russian 
bomber engaged in ground attacks against Turkomen insurgents in north Syria (BBC, 2015). 
Several Russian government import-substitution policies have been supported by large 
budget allocations. Russia proceeded with the formation of the EEU in January 2015 with 
the other member states of Armenia, Belarus, Kazakhstan and Kyrgyzstan. Russian institu-
tions have explored options for obtaining substitute finance in alternative financial centres 
in Asia (Singapore, Hong Kong, Shanghai). However, according to Connolly (2015b) Asia 
was the source of only 10% of loans to Russian businesses in 2015. in light of the Western 
embargo on exports of military equipment (e.g. helicopter carriers from France), Russia has 
been moving back toward self-sufficiency in defence. it has revived aspects of the priority 
protection system in the economy, as indicated by President Putin becoming Head of the 
State Commission for Military-Industrial Issues in September 2014 (see Figure 2). Russia has 
re-energised its Spetsinformatsiya system and relevant institutions are engaged in trade 
diversion and in the covert acquisition of banned technologies and finance (EWF 7). </p>

<p>Economic and military impacts of Western and Russian economic sanctions related 
to the Ukraine conflict, 2014-2016 </p>

<p>Developments in the economy of Russia in 2014-2015 were mainly negative (Table 3): decel-
eration of GDP growth to -3.8%; acceleration of inflation to 15.5%; increase in the budget 
deficit; wide-ranging budget cuts (usually 10%); rises in interest rates to a peak of 17%; a 
40% year-on-year depreciation of the ruble-dollar exchange rate; large outflows of capital; 
higher risk premiums on bonds; and increases in unemployment and poverty (EBRD, 2015;  iMF, 2015a, 2015c; RF MER (Russian Federation, Ministerstvo Ekonomicheskogo Razvitiya),  2015; World Bank, 2015b, 2015c). 
20 in the positive category were the substantial surplus in the 
current account (7% of GDP), increases of import substitution production in Russian industry 
and agriculture, and a sharp reduction in the external debt (to 29% of GDP). Forecasts of 
economic growth in 2016 were revised downward by the World Bank (to -0.7%) in December 
2015 and the RF Ministry for Economic Development (to -0.8%) in January 2016, primarily 
due to lower than anticipated world oil prices (Prokopenko, 2016; World Bank, 2015d). 
Numerous publications have claimed that the worsening economic situation in Russia 
has provided proof that the sanctions have been achieving their objectives. However, it is 
almost impossible to measure the economic impacts of sanctions because of the disruption 
caused by the drop in oil prices and lack of information of the effectiveness of Russian coun-
ter-measures. The World Bank (2015b) presented an interesting analysis of this topic, but it </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>had weaknesses concerning sources and methods, and almost every tentative conclusion 
had several qualifications following it. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Table 10. impacts of ukraine-related foreign sanctions on Russia during 2014-2015. </p>

<p>sources: Author's calculations, 2015; Gaddy and ickes (2014b), World Bank (2015a, Part 3; 2015b) and numerous current 
news articles and documents of institutions (e.g. us government, iiss, EC). </p>

<p>Type of sanction 
Goal 
Economic impacts 
Military impacts 
Political impacts </p>

<p>Actions against Individuals 
Bans on travel (no 
visas) </p>

<p>Punish participants 
in ukraine conflict 
and put pressure on 
Russian government 
to change policies </p>

<p>negligible from 
travel ban. But asset 
freezes and bans on 
business have micro 
impacts </p>

<p>negligible. Russia 
bans officials from 
foreign travel and 
accounts </p>

<p>negligible. Russians 
would boast not 
complain about 
sanctions </p>

<p>Freezing of assets 
Bans on business 
dealings 
Restrictions on Trade 
Bans on exports to 
or imports from 
Crimea </p>

<p>Disrupt economy 
of Crimea and force 
Russia to increase 
subsidies to it </p>

<p>sanctions disruptive 
and Russia forced to 
increase support </p>

<p>negligible 
Popular support 
for annexation, but 
complaints about 
subsidies could grow 
Bans on transactions 
by foreign busi-
nesses in Crimea 
Embargoes on 
exports to Russia 
of weapons 
and military 
equipment </p>

<p>Constrain Russian 
military power, 
discomfort national 
security elite </p>

<p>Cuts in spending on 
foreign arms/equip-
ment, funding of 
import substitution </p>

<p>Disruption of 
defence supply and 
industry </p>

<p>Pushes Russia back 
to self-sufficiency in 
defence </p>

<p>Embargoes on 
exports to Russia 
of dual-use 
technologies </p>

<p>Constrain Russian 
economic and 
military power </p>

<p>Limited due to 
trade diversion and 
espionage </p>

<p>Limited due to 
trade diversion and 
espionage </p>

<p>Russia tries for 
self-sufficiency and 
searches for new 
partners 
Embargoes on 
exports to Russia 
of energy explora-
tion technologies 
(deep-sea drilling, 
shale) </p>

<p>Constrain devel-
opment of new oil 
fields to limit export 
earnings </p>

<p>Limited in medi-
um-term due to 
stock-piling, trade 
diversion and espi-
onage </p>

<p>negligible 
Russia tries for 
self-sufficiency and 
searches for new 
partners </p>

<p>Restrictions on Finance 
Bans on loans to and 
transactions in 
Crimea </p>

<p>Disrupt economy 
of Crimea and force 
Russia to increase 
investment there </p>

<p>sanctions disruptive 
and Russia forced 
to increase financial 
support </p>

<p>negligible 
Leaders committed 
to covering costs 
of annexation, but 
public support could 
waver 
Restricted access 
by Russian 
state-owned/influ-
enced banks and 
enterprises to West 
capital markets </p>

<p>Limit new credit and 
complicate re-fi-
nancing to increase 
vulnerability and 
limit investment in 
Russia </p>

<p>sanctions have 
adverse direct 
effects on targets 
and indirect impacts 
on other Russian 
companies </p>

<p>some defence-re-
lated firms cannot 
pursue foreign 
projects </p>

<p>sanctions make 
banks and firms 
more vulnerable and 
therefore dependent 
on state. Helps con-
solidate regime 
Reduction in the 
period of loans in 
capital markets to 
30 days </p>

<p>increase vulnera-
bility of specified 
banks/companies </p>

<p>Foreign operations 
of some firms 
impeded </p>

<p>Freezing of the 
assets of specified 
Russian firms of 
individuals </p>

<p>Complicate interna-
tional transactions 
of target firms/banks 
(individuals) </p>

<p>some impacts until 
counter-measures 
in place </p>

<p>negligible 
Firms use sanctions 
as a plus to obtain 
state support </p>

<p>Actions Against Russia as a Country 
Expulsion of Russia 
from G8 </p>

<p>undermine status 
of leaders, exclude 
from important 
discussions </p>

<p>negligible 
negligible 
Viewed as insulting 
by Russian elite, but 
minor impacts </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>in assessing the macroeconomic impacts of sanctions on Russia, the counter-factual of 
the oil price not falling should be considered. if Russia had continued to receive payments 
of $115 per barrel from June 2014, then it is likely that many of the negative phenomena 
in the Russian economy (capital outflows, exchange rate depreciation, low FDi, negative 
growth, diminished stabilisation funds) would not have developed, even with sanctions. in 
reality the oil price did drop, so sanctions must be assessed in conjunction with the decline 
in Russia's hard-currency energy earnings. Table 10 summarises the impacts of sanctions on 
economic, military and political processes in Russia. 
The sanctions imposed on individuals in Crimea, Eastern Ukraine and Russia deny them 
visas and freeze their overseas assets. But many of these people come from modest socio-eco-
nomic backgrounds and would not have had external passports, foreign banks accounts or 
plans to travel abroad. Bans on Russian state officials are largely irrelevant because their own 
government has prohibited them (and close family members for security services employees) 
from having foreign bank accounts and has restricted their travel abroad in order to fight 
corruption and counteract the subversive efforts of foreign espionage agencies. However, 
the restrictions on business transactions with firms of wealthy Russians have caused some 
serious local complications. Overall, the targeted individual sanctions have had negligible 
macroeconomic, military or political impacts. 
Strict controls have been imposed on transactions involving Crimea (exports, imports, 
investment, loans, business operations). These have had significant direct and indirect 
negative local effects, in that companies have withdrawn from Crimea (e.g. McDonalds of 
Ukraine), avoided investment there, and have suspended services (e.g. licences for computer 
games and software). However, the experienced and pervasive Russian/Ukrainian 'second 
economy' (HP 2) has provided substitutes ('pirate' copies) for some withdrawn goods and 
services that cannot be measured by international organisations or US government analysts 
in Washington, DC. Furthermore, countries not participating in sanctions, such as Turkey up 
to November 2015, have been active in capital investment projects in Crimea. However, the 
Russian government has been forced to make investments in Crimea or related to it (e.g. 
infrastructure, tourist facilities) that might have been financed externally in the absence of 
sanctions. </p>

<p>22   The embargo on exports to Russia of weapons and military equipment has been effective 
in the official sphere. This has reduced Russia's spending on imports (e.g. warships from 
France), but has increased its investment in import substitution. Russia probably has acquired 
some smaller items of banned military equipment through trade diversion and military 
technologies (e.g. blueprints for reverse engineering) through economic espionage (EWF 7, 
HP 6). The sanctions have disrupted supply and production plans in the defence sector. The 
main political impact of these sanctions has been to encourage Russia to return to self-suf-
ficiency in the defence field. Several assessments suggest that these compensatory efforts 
(e.g. substitution of defence-related imports from Ukraine) will meet with limited success 
in the short-term, but could pay off in the medium/long-term. 
The bans on exports to Russia of dual-use and energy-related technologies have been 
partially successful in curtailing official trade in the specified commodities and services. But 
the economic impacts have been mitigated by stock-piling of the technologies in advance 
of the crisis and informal acquisition of them through trade diversion and technological 
espionage (HP 6). 
23 The Russian government, like other investors in the world, has delayed 
numerous capital investment projects (e.g. deep-sea drilling for oil) because of the low oil </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>price, which has lowered the demand for the banned technologies. 
24 These sanctions have 
impelled the Russian government to promote self-sufficiency in energy technologies and 
to search for alternative trading partners in China, india and South Korea. By 2015 there was 
some evidence that economic sanctions were disrupting general scientific R&amp;D in Russia (e.g. 
Western firms refusing to export scientific equipment out of concern that it might be used 
in the military sphere), although most of the problems were caused by the depreciation of 
the ruble and international organisations responding of new Russian legislation restricting 
the activities of NGOs (Dezhina, 2015). 
The financial sanctions have had negative impacts on the specifically targeted banks 
and firms (difficulties in obtaining new loans and rolling over existing ones) and indirect 
adverse consequences for other Russian firms because of uncertainty in markets. These 
restrictions have generated capital outflows because Russian firms have needed to convert 
ruble funds to cover foreign obligations and have reduced FDi in Russia (see Note 10). Some 
defence-related firms have found it impossible to pursue planned projects with foreign 
partners. However, the Russian government has assisted targets of sanctions and, in any 
event, much of Russian external debt obligations are with Russian entities (about one-half 
of repayments in 2015-2016) and can therefore be easily re-scheduled (Connolly, 2015b). 
Furthermore, informal channels (the well-documented Russian second economy) (HP 2) 
have been used to obtain financing in the complicated global financial system that has 
demonstrated clearly over the past five years that it cannot be regulated effectively by USA/ 
UK government agencies (e.g. uncontrolled sub-prime lending, tolerance of incompetent 
borrowing strategies of banks, fraudulent derivatives, cheating on LiBOR, swindling the 
population through unnecessary loan insurance, money laundering for drug cartels). it will 
be challenging for the hastily organised EU/USA compliance teams to ensure that financial 
sanctions are not comprehensively subverted by talented Russians working in the global 
financial sector and intelligence agencies. The most important impact of these Western 
financial sanctions probably has been to make the most market-oriented of Russian firms 
and banks become more dependent on the Russian state (Gaddy &amp; ickes, 2014b). 
A final category of sanctions relates to exclusions of Russia from membership in interna-
tional bodies (e.g. G8), as well as boycotts of events in Russia (e.g. vE Day celebrations). These 
symbolic gestures have not achieved the declared economic, military or political impacts. 
The Russian government initially responded by developing compensatory relationships with 
other major countries (e.g. the BRiCS). However, by the end of 2015 the terrorist actions of 
iSiS directed against France and Russia resulted in these two countries forming a tentative 
military alliance to combat the common terrorist threats. 
The economy of Ukraine has performed poorly during 2014-2015 (Table 3), but Russian 
sanctions have made only minor contributions to this. Adverse macroeconomic develop-
ments have been caused primarily by the intensification of long-standing performance prob-
lems (low productivity, large budget deficits and external debts), weak economic institutions, 
deeply ingrained corruption (HP 2), the direct economic effects of the crisis (disruption of 
industrial production and tax collection in East Ukraine by war) and reactions of foreign 
investors to geopolitical risk (currency depreciation). The loss of Russian subsidies (HP 5) 
has been offset by the iMF/EU/USA, which have taken on long-term financial responsibility 
for propping up the malfunctioning economy of Ukraine on the condition of adherence 
to a package of deep reforms and restructuring and financial austerity similar to the one 
developed to deal with the debt crisis in Greece. it is possible, though, that a new round of </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>bilateral sanctions in late 2015-early 2016 could cause greater problems for Ukraine in the 
future. These include Ukraine cutting off electricity supplies to Crimea, banning Russian 
airlines from flying through its airspace and restricting exports to Russia. in response Russia 
has banned additional Ukrainian imports, reduced deliveries of coal and natural gas, and 
refused to re-schedule bond repayments. 
Russian counter-sanctions have had negligible macroeconomic effects on EU countries 
because the affected commodities (food products) comprise only small shares of exports. 
However, there have been some negative microeconomic impacts (e.g. the bans on the 
exports to Russia of fruit from Greece and cheese from Lithuania). </p>

<p>Conclusions concerning defence-economic influences on the Ukraine 
conflict and the impacts of economic sanctions </p>

<p>This concluding section focuses on developing answers to the questions posed in the 
introduction concerning defence economics and economic warfare. There is no elaboration 
of points previously made concerning the wisdom of EU and NATO expansion eastward, 
causation in the Ukraine political and military conflict, and the merits of supplying arms to 
Ukraine. 
The first question concerns the commitments of resources made by both the USSR and 
NATO countries to achieve their security objectives and establish a military balance in Europe. 
Due to the traumatic experiences of World War ii, NATO countries and the USSR were com-
mitted to converting economic power into military capabilities and to maintaining combat 
readiness. These policies resulted in the USSR devoting around 15% of GDP to defence in the 
mid-1980s and in the leading NATO countries accepting relatively heavy defence burdens 
for democracies in peacetime: USA 6%, UK 5%, France 4% and Germany 3%. Although these 
military efforts strained economies (especially that of the USSR) and entailed significant 
opportunity costs, they contributed to peace in Europe, stability of borders, and nuclear 
and conventional deterrence. 
The USSR economy was significantly smaller than those of its NATO adversaries and its 
technological level was lower. However, the Soviet Union developed a unique, insulated 
military economic system (central planning and rationing, high priority, technological espi-
onage) that enabled it to mobilise its limited resources to become the dominant European 
industrial and military power (Figure 1, Table 2). However, the exceptionally heavy defence 
burden and well-known flaws in the general economic and political systems contributed 
to the collapse of the USSR. Most institutional features of the Soviet defence sector were 
carried over to the Russian Federation (Figure 2). However, in the 1990s the priority of the mil-
itary-industrial complex declined and the armed forces, defence industry and military R&amp;D 
experienced severe economic difficulties. The situation changed for the better in the 2000s 
as a result of economic recovery and the raised priority of national security programmes. 
As in the past, the top leadership is closely involved in managing the military-industrial 
complex (e.g. President Putin is head of both the Security Council and the State Commission 
for Military-Industrial Issues). The conflicts during 2013-2016 in Ukraine and Syria demon-
strate that the Russian economy can generate necessary military capabilities and that the 
leadership has the will to employ them. 
The answer to the third question concerning the consequences of the sustained drive by 
national governments in Europe to achieve financial 'peace dividends' in the post-Cold War </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>period is clear. The drastic cuts in defence spending, down to an average of 1.6% of GDP in 
NATO Europe, adversely affected NATO's conventional military capabilities and deterrence. 
This meant that Russia did not need to take NATO into account when it was formulating its 
military strategy to deal with the Ukraine crisis. The efforts by NATO to move troops and mili-
tary equipment closer to Eastern borders have been justified on the basis that they will deter 
Russia from future aggressive actions against NATO members. During 2014-2016 only the UK 
and Poland were meeting the agreed NATO defence burdens target of 2%, although several 
other countries (e.g. Estonia) made commitments to reach that target by 2020 (iiSS, 2015). 
Over the past century the dynamics of economic, technological and military balances 
have helped to explain the rise and fall of nations and alliances. This was evident in the case 
of World War ii. in the Cold War period the NATO countries had greater economic power 
and a higher average technological level than the USSR, but for several decades the latter 
was able to achieve military balance through its defence economic arrangements. in the 
post-communist period the NATO countries have maintained their economic power and 
technological superiority. However, as a result of continued NATO cuts in defence spending 
and the increased Russian defence effort the balance of deployed conventional military 
capabilities in Europe shifted in favour of Russia. Table 5 demonstrates that by 2013 Russia 
had overwhelming advantages over Ukraine in the local balance of economic and military 
power. These military imbalances contributed to Russia's annexation of Crimea and support 
for insurgents in eastern Ukraine. 
The USA, Japan and European countries conducted economic warfare (supplemented by 
sanctions) against the USSR throughout 1917-1991 (Tables 6 and 7). However, there were 
recurrent disagreements between participants with respect to perceptions of triggers, objec-
tives, termination conditions, and specific measures that limited the comprehensiveness of 
and commitments to economic warfare. The wide-ranging trade controls of CoCom achieved 
some successes. But the robust counter-measure Spetsinformatsiya system enabled the USSR 
to obtain controlled goods and secrets through trade diversion and technological espionage. 
Table 8 indicates that in the period 1992-2013 lower key and fragmented efforts were made 
by the West to control the flows of technology to Russia and to impose economic sanctions. 
These achieved some goals concerning specific products or sectors. Overall, the answer to 
question five is that Western economic warfare and sanctions directed at the USSR/Russia 
over the period 1917-2013 did not achieve intended ambitious objectives concerning the 
alteration of economic and military power balances, but did slow the development of the 
USSR into a superpower. 
The final question concerns Ukraine-related economic sanctions during 2014-2016. The 
assessments in Table 10 suggest that the sanctions imposed on Russia (bans on individuals, 
prohibitions of transactions in Crimea, embargoes on exports of military goods and some 
energy-related technologies, and restrictions on the availability of finance) have had rela-
tively minor impacts. The effectiveness of economic sanctions has been undermined by the 
limited participation by major economies (Table 9), restraints on the rigour of measures in 
order to maintain the USA-EU alliance, and the usual covert counter-measures by Russia. if 
world market prices of oil had not dropped by over 60% during 2014-2016, it is likely that 
anti-Russia sanctions would have had negligible macroeconomic impacts. But given actual 
economic developments, it is reasonable to conclude both that economic sanctions have 
imposed marginal microeconomic and macroeconomic costs on Russia and that they have </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>not influenced in a pro-Western manner either public opinion or the national security deci-
sion making of the elite in that country. </p>

<p>Notes </p>

<p>1. The close relationships between economic power and national security are recognised both in 
the academic literature (see below) and by contemporary European leaders. When introducing 
the Strategic Defence and Security Review in November 2015, UK Prime Minister David Cameron 
wrote: 'Economic security and national security go hand in hand. So at the heart of our strategy 
is our decision to see through our long-term economic plan and use our renewed economic 
strength to invest further in our security' (Cameron, 2015). in April 2015 German Finance 
Minister Wolfgang Schäuble stated that 'in the long term, the conflict with Putin's Russia will 
be decided only on the basis of economic strength … European sanctions are definitely having 
an impact on Putin's Russia. But we can afford these sanctions only because -and as long as 
-we have a strong economy' (Brookings institution, 2015). 
2. These hidden processes are described in more detail and evaluated by Davis (2014a, 2016). 
The latter paper shows the structural similarities in the mathematical equations representing 
the processes of Negative Value Added, Rent Extraction and Implicit Subsidisation of East Europe. 
3. Kennedy (1988) evaluates the general dynamics of the Russian Empire and the USSR, as well as 
specific issues related to Ukraine, such as Russia's annexation of Crimea in 1783 and its relations 
with Ukraine and Poland (see map on p. 109). 
4. Davis (1999) contains a comparative economic systems analysis of industrialisation and 
industrial policy in Russia/USSR, with sections on the Russian Empire, New Economic Policy, 
Stalin economy, Brezhnev period and the Russian Federation in the 1990s. 
5. The low-key USA treatment of the annexation of the Baltic States by the USSR in 1940 contrasts 
with its more robust current policies toward Russia in connection with the annexation of Crimea 
in 2014. 
6. The assessments of the ineffectiveness of arms transfers to weak governments by superpowers 
provides background evidence related to the debate over NATO arms supplies to Ukraine 
discussed on p.14. 
7. Connolly (2015a) correctly points out that the Russian economy possessed not only the two 
sectors identified in the virtual economy model of negative value-added heavy industry (A) and 
the rent-generating energy sector (B), but also a growing competitive private sector (services 
and industries) (C) with hard budget constraints and profit orientation. 
8. Huntington (1996, p. 165) claimed that Ukraine is a 'cleft country' that contains a 'civilizational 
fault line' between areas with backgrounds in Western empires and those rooted in Russian 
Orthodoxy and suggested that this could lead to the fragmentation of the country. See related 
maps on pp. 159 and 166. 
9. Russian energy-related subsidies of Armenia, Belarus and Ukraine were continuations into 
the transition period of the Soviet practice of implicitly subsidising East European countries 
(Marrese &amp; vanous, 1983) discussed above. 
10. Cumulative FDi inflows per capita over 1989-2008 were $4492 for Central Europe and the Baltic 
States, but only $899 for Ukraine and $304 for Russia (EBRD, 2009, p. 27), so foreign finance 
was of limited significance to Russia. 
11. Although in the period before the Ukraine crisis NATO would not accept the argument that 
the actions of its European member countries in reducing defence expenditures and military 
capabilities were undermining conventional deterrence, it is noticeable that since 2014 NATO 
has justified its redeployments of troops and weapon systems to East Europe and the Baltic 
states and calls for increased defence spending by claiming that these measures will help to 
deter future aggressive military moves by Russia. 
12. iMF (2014) announced a $17 billion support package in April 2014, and subsequently dispersed 
$4.5 billion of it. in February 2015 a new $17.5 billion conditional loan was approved to replace 
the initial one (iMF, 2015b). The EC provided Ukraine with Macro-Financial Assistance loans of (in </p>

<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>



<p>millions) €100 (May 2014), €500 (June 2014), €260 (November 2014), €500 (December 2014) and 
€250 (April 2015). it has approved an additional €1.5 billion in assistance for Ukraine (EC, 2015). 
13. President Putin has a historical perspective on economic sanctions that has similarities with 
the one presented in this paper. in his 2014 State of the Nation speech he stated: 'Speaking of 
the sanctions, they are not just a knee-jerk reaction on behalf of the United States or its allies 
to our position regarding the events and the coup in Ukraine, or even the so-called Crimean 
Spring. i'm sure that if these events had never happened … they would have come up with 
some other excuse to try to contain Russia's growing capabilities, affect our country in some 
way, or even take advantage of it. The policy of containment was not invented yesterday. it 
has been carried out against our country for many years, always, for decades, if not centuries. 
in short, whenever someone thinks that Russia has become too strong or independent, these 
tools are quickly put into use' (Putin, 2014). 
14. Davis (2005) presents at study of Soviet defence economics during 1917-1932, which is partially 
based on 133 formerly classified (mostly Sovershenno Sekretno) Soviet documents from the 
Russian State Archive of the Economy (RGAE). The cited document is Gosplan (1928) Kontrol'nye 
tsifry oborony na 1928/29 god, which is from RGAE Fond 4372, Opis' 91, Delo 256, pp. 83-111. This 
document was discussed at a seminar at Hitotsubashi University in October 2014 (Davis, 2014b). 
15. By 2013 the following USA government organisations were involved in export control efforts: 
US Department of State, Directorate of Defense Trade Controls and Bureau of international 
Security and Non-proliferation; US Department of Commerce, Bureau of industry and Security; 
US Department of Homeland Security, Project Shield America and Export Enforcement 
Coordination Center; US Department of Treasury, Office of Foreign Assets Controls; and US 
Department of Defense, Defense Threat Reduction Agency (USSD (US State Department), 2015). 
16. Although the legal adjudication of the responsibility for the shooting down of Malaysian Airlines 
Flight 17 has not been completed, the case of the more obvious shooting down of KAL 007 by a 
Soviet fighter jet in 1981 (see p. 16) suggests that any additional sanctions related to this action 
are likely to be diluted by Big Power compromises over foreign policy issues in the years ahead. 
17. Economic relations between Russia and Turkey deteriorated in November 2015 due to the latter 
shooting down a Sukhoi 24 bomber belonging to the former in Syrian airspace in November 
2015. in response to this incident Russia imposed wide-ranging economic sanctions on Turkey, 
which shifted the latter country into the anti-Russia sanctions category identified in Table 9. 
18. vernon and Kapstein (1991) edited a special issue of Daedalus that examined the break-down 
of the Cold War practice of maintaining national capabilities in defence industries as a result of 
the seemingly inexorable trend toward globalisation. Over the past 25 years no NATO defence 
sector has been able to sustain autonomous military R&amp;D and production capabilities. instead, 
many critical components of weapons/sensor production have been out-sourced to low-cost 
high-tech countries, such as the People's Republic of China. Russia and China have established 
close links in the technological espionage and weapons production spheres. 
19. Gaddy and ickes (2014a) point out that Russia is the sole market for many Ukrainian industrial 
goods because of historically-determined technological compatibilities and their uncompetitive 
characteristics. So Ukraine's embargo on exports of industrial products to Russia is likely to 
mean that its firms will not find alternative customers. Some Russian industrial firms face similar 
difficulties due to Ukrainian restrictions on imports. 
20. All statistics for Russia and Ukraine for 2015-2016 are the best estimates as of January 2016. 
21. in World Bank (2015b) Part 3. The Economic Impact of Sanctions the authors mention several 
quantitative methodologies that could be applied to study Russia sanctions, but are not used 
in the actual analysis. They attempt to draw out lessons for the current situation in Russia from 
the history of economic sanctions against South Africa in the 1980s. No references are made 
to the history of Western sanctions directed against the USSR and Russia or counter-measures 
(Tables 6, 7 and 8 of this article). No Russian language secondary or archive sources are cited 
in this study, which is typical for a product of an international organisation. 
22. in March 2015 former Russia Finance Minister Kudrin estimated the direct costs to Russia to 
that date of the support of Crimea to be about $7 billion and that the combination of direct </p>



<p>C. M. DAviS </p>

<p>and indirect costs (some generated by sanctions) over three years would amount to around 
$150 billion (TASS, 2015). 
23. Reuters (2015) reported that Gazprom Neft expects to double the production of oil in the 
Arctic Prirazlomnoe field in 2015 to 600,000 tons using offshore drilling technology, which 
is supposed to be restricted by sanctions. The Human Intelligence-bereft CiA has negligible 
capabilities to monitor visits to restricted remote territories in Russia by well-paid and suitably 
cautious Western energy engineers and technicians. 
24. According to an article by Pagnamenta (2016): 'BP cut 4,000 jobs from its exploration and 
production business, while Petrobas … has slashed its five-year investment programme by 
25 per cent' . </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>i would like to express my gratitude for the support of my research provided by Oxford University 
through sabbatical leaves and grants from my two departments (Economics and Area Studies), Wolfson 
College and the John Fell Fund. The development of this article benefited from the opportunities 
provided by six institutions to visit and present my ideas: Korea institute for international Economic 
Policy, Seoul (September 2014); Hitotsubashi University, institute of Economic Research, Tokyo (October 
2014); NATO Parliamentary Assembly, Economics and Security Committee, The Hague (November 2014); 
Elcano Royal institute for Strategic and international Studies, Madrid (February 2015); University of York, 
vOX Seminar on 'Economic Sanctions' , York (April 2015); and Wolfson College, Seminar on 'The Ukraine 
Conflict in 2014-15: Political, Economic, Military and international Dimensions' . i also appreciate the 
financing of my earlier research on international security and defence economics that was provided 
by grants from the Ford Foundation, Pew Charitable Trusts and volkswagen Foundation. </p>

<p>Disclosure statement </p>

<p>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author. </p>



<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>







<p>C. M. DAviS </p>



<p>POST-COMMUNiST ECONOMiES </p>







<p>C. M. DAviS </p>



</text></tei>