<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10842-016-0243-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract The paper analyses the role of regulation in the suppression of disruptive innovations 
and shows that this process might be explained by the dependance on the path of joint evolution 
of regulation and the mainstream technology. Industrial policy in highly regulated industries 
such as wireless telecommunications is able to support evolution of established technologies 
and adjust itself to sustaining innovations, while regulatory disconnection impedes disruptive 
technologies, and the market plays a quite secondary role in this process. We observe more 
innovations in those parts of telecommunications where regulator is less active, but the core, the 
physical layer, of the industry is changing in sustaining way of development of the technology. 
The paper argues that the problem of impediment to disruptive innovations could be alleviated 
if the crucial resources of the industry were accessible for a number of potential innovators and 
newcomers. The openness makes easier the appearance of disruptive technologies, and regu-
lation must facilitate it in order to promote opportunities for creative destruction. </p>

<p>Despite the different views in Economics on the relationships between innovation and 
competition, some aspects seem pretty obvious and even trivial. The best incentives for 
innovation activity is the Bthe difference in profit that a firm can earn … compared to what </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 
DOI 10.1007/s10842-016-0243-y </p>

<p>* Dmitrii Trubnikov 
d.trubnikov@uvt.nl </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Tilburg Institute for Law, Technology, and Society (TILT), Tilburg University, Tilburg, 
The Netherlands </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>CIRSFID, University of Bologna, Bologna, Italy </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>it would earn^otherwise (Gilbert 2006). Opportunity to escape competition and gain a 
monopoly and, thus, to charge prices higher than the competitive level is one of the main 
driving forces of innovations. 
1 Therefore, the conduct of a company that innovates is anti-
competitive by its nature, but it does not mean that such behaviour is undesirable from the 
point of view of social interests and, thus, is not considered in such a way by antitrust policy. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>What is really desirable is that competitors of the innovator also have opportunities to innovate 
and positively affect the innovative conduct of the leader. However, at this particular point the 
triviality of the problem disappears and we enter the field of different legal and economics 
concepts, tools and methods of dealing with issues related to allocation of exclusive privileges 
and antitrust investigations. 
The understanding that the aspiration of monopoly is the best incentive for innovation has 
moved the economics mainstream to the promotion of the idea that there are needs for 
government interventions that would provide exclusive rights for innovators. However, we 
can hypothesise that the market per se could be sufficient to the promotion of incentives for 
innovators 
3 and, at the same time, could, possibly, make obsolete any needs to antitrust 
interventions. Therefore, it is quite risky to make conclusions that reasons for the victory of 
the leaders are their best business practices without paying attention to the fact that regulation 
played certain role in this superiority. 
For instance, antitrust authorities might investigate the conduct of a company that had, 
allegedly, abused their intellectual property rights, inducing the discussion about the validity of 
such suspicion, but they can not affect the core of the problem, since the privileges to exclude 
others are precisely the main intention of the institution of intellectual property. They can be 
trying to assess the potential harm to consumers after a merger of some significant market 
players, but it is difficult to take into consideration that the structure of this market had been 
already transformed to the oligopolistic form by the regulatory policy and the real market 
forces have not already played a noticeable role in the field. Dogan and Lemley (2008) notice 
these shortcomings of antitrust law when they point out that Bthreats to competition do not 
come only from private conduct in unregulated industries, … [but] also come from govern-
ment regulation itself. … Where it is the state itself that decides upon an anticompetitive end, 
the antitrust laws have not intervened.M 
eanwhile, the problem becomes more complicated when the task of antitrust investigation 
is not only to develop the theory of harm to consumers, but to understand how the opportu-
nities of market participants for innovations might be harmed. 
4 However, it should be noticed 
that innovations very often come to our life in completely unpredictable ways, and, thus, it 
might be merely impossible to assess the potential harm for innovations if even the source of 
such unpredictable innovations is uncertain. What is more important is that the real threat for 
innovations comes not only from the conduct of leaders, but from the legal frameworks that 
determine such conduct and protect positions of incumbents. </p>

<p>1 Such arguments are very common in the justification of the institution of intellectual property. See, e.g., Posner 
(2005). 
2 Shelanski (2013), for example, notices that BInnovation inevitably leaves some firms behind and may confer 
market power on the innovating firm. … innovation greatly benefits consumers and should not be viewed as any 
more harmful to competition than when a firm cuts price and thereby leaves its rivals without customers^. 
3 Fritz Machlup (1958), commissioned by Congress of the United States to evaluate the country's patent system, 
concluded that BIf we did not have a patent system, it would be irresponsible, on the basis of our present 
knowledge of its economic consequences, to recommend instituting one. But since we have had a patent system 
for a long time, it would be irresponsible, on the basis of our present knowledge, to recommend abolishing it.4 
Some scholars pointed out that B[t]his calls for innovative theories of harm^(De Streel and Larouche 2015). </p>

<p>400 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>One of the popular theories dedicated to innovations that appeared in the middle of the 
1990s (Bower and Christensen 1995), and since that time has been embraced by many 
scholars, claims that Bleading firms almost always triumphed in battles of sustaining innova-
tion and that entrant firms typically beat the incumbent leaders when disruptive innovations 
emerged^(Christensen 2006). Disruptive innovation is one of those forces that can yield the 
real threats to established firms and Bgenerates the kind of 'creative destruction' described by 
Schumpeter^(De Streel and Larouche 2015). Shelanski (2013) points out that due to the 
importance of creative destruction, the Schumpeterian approach, despite its arguments about 
the negative relation between competition and innovations, does not exclude antitrust inter-
ventions in the regulatory policy. </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Meanwhile, for established firms the best way to protect their positions is to capture the 
control over innovations, and here both kinds of innovations, sustaining and disruptive, are 
equally important to be controlled. In highly regulated industries, such as telecommunications, 
the Banticompetitive end^might be the result of regulatory activity, and the opportunities for 
disruptive innovations might be harmed by regulation. 
Since the source of the disruptiveness is not always certain, the possible response to the 
attempts to control the development and innovations in telecommunications industry is the 
placement of the crucial resources of the field in the realm of Bcommons^. Lawrence Lessig 
(2001) uses the similar idea when he talks about the control over the physical layer of a 
communications system. The problem is that the most of them by their economic nature are 
classic examples of private goods, since they are both rivalrous and excludable. Possibly, we 
could base some hypothesis on the enormous potential of the capacity of fiber-optic infra-
structure, but since the access to this infrastructure has physical barriers, its exploitation in the 
way of an uncontrolled Bphysical layer^seems difficult. At the same time, the radio spectrum 
by its nature is Bcommon good^, and it is quite possible that technological solutions might 
alleviate the problem of the rivalry of this good, and, thereby, transform it into the economic 
realm of Bpublic goods^. Another crucial resource of telecommunications, that is also by its 
nature is non-rivalrous and non-excludable, is information and knowledge that are controlled 
by the incumbents through the institution of intellectual property. It is possible to assume that 
the mechanisms of control over these resources maintain the oligopolistic structure of the field 
and facilitate the development of the mainstream part of the industry. 
The purpose of this paper is to highlight the role of regulation in the suppression of 
disruptive innovations in telecommunications and to show that this process is explained not 
mainly by explicit actions of government in the interests of incumbents, but rather by the 
dependance on the path of joint evolution of regulation and the mainstream technology. In the 
beginning of the paper, I provide a brief analysis of disruptive innovations in telecommuni-
cations and distinguish WiMAX as a real life example of disruptive technology in the industry, 
explain this position and describe the economic model of the technology. Then I use this case 
to demonstrate that the failure of this disruption was determined by state interventions in 
market mechanisms that, eventually, did not allow to put into practice the economic model, 
and protected the established status quo of the area. In the final section I argue that the current 
paradigm, that justifies regulatory interventions, heavily depends on the previous way of </p>

<p>5 Shelanski (2013) claims that B[a] natural implication of the Schumpeterian argument is that a firm with market 
power would … have an incentive to interfere with the cycle of Bcreative destruction^by impeding rivals' ability 
to develop new products or services that threaten its dominance.Ĵ </p>

<p>Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
interaction of regulation and technology, and it locks the evolution of the industry on the 
mainstream technology, protecting business interests of incumbents. </p>

<p>2 The Disruptiveness in Wireless Communications </p>

<p>2.1 Disruptive Innovations in Telecommunications </p>

<p>According to the concept introduced by Christiansen and Bower in 1995, innovations 
could be classified on sustaining, when innovations take place within the existing 
market and Btend to maintain a rate of improvement [providing] customers something 
more or better in the attributes they already value^, and disruptive, when innovations 
Bintroduce a very different package of attributes from the one mainstream customers 
historically value^. The initial version of the concept claimed that in the first phase an 
innovation performs worse than the main product or services in the market but with 
lower prices, and only in the second phase, the quality of the innovation increases and 
attracts the mainstream consumers. However, in more general view, a disruption 
comes not only from the Blow end^, but also from the Bhigh end^(Govindarajan 
and Kopalle 2006) and from a Bnew market^(Christensen and Raynor 2003), and it 
might be claimed that one of the core features of disruptive innovations is their 
financial unattractiveness for the incumbents (Christensen 2006). 
We can find some noticeable examples of disruptive innovations in the telecommunications 
industry: <rs type="software">Skype</rs> that has gained the benefits of the market of long-voice telephony, numerous 
Internet messengers, that partly substituted SMS services or even traditional voice services, or 
Internet video streaming services such as <rs type="software">NetFlix</rs>. However, the majority of these examples 
shares one distinctive feature that, in general, does not entirely fit the concept of disruptive 
technologies: entering the telecommunications market from the outside they have not 
undermined the positions of the incumbents of the industry. 
Indeed, from this point of view these innovations of telecommunications services differ 
significantly from other examples of disruptiveness. The appearance of smartphones subverted 
the market of mobile phones and destroyed the business of the former leader of the market 
Nokia. The introduction of digital photo cameras ruined the business of Kodak. At the same 
time, the appearance of <rs type="software">Skype</rs>, despite of the undeniable significance of the innovation for the 
industry, has not destroyed the business of British Telecom, Deutsche Telecom or Telefonica. 
There are some concerns of the incumbents about Bcommodization^of their services 
(Larouche 2007; Kushida 2015), but it does not mean the loss of their places under the sun. 
The reasons for sustainability of the established players of telecommunications towards 
such kind of disruptive innovations are pretty apparent -these innovations did not attack the 
infrastructure layer of the industry. They have changed the structure and the models of the 
business of incumbents, substituting voice or video traffic by data traffic, but not their 
positions. We can also notice that they broadened the borders of the industry and triggered 
competition on some of its layers, but did not challenge the core. Moreover, even appearance 
of many of these innovations was determined by the development of this core and their 
commercial success was merely impossible before the infrastructure layer reached conditions 
that allowed their proliferation. 
However, even the infrastructure layer of the industry can also be challenged, and history 
shows us the case when the landscape of telecommunications could have been changed by </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>disruptive wireless technology. From this point of view, WiMAX 
6 might be to some extent 
considered as an attempt to construct an alternative infrastructure apart from the mainstream 
industry that could help to form an open and competitive environment in telecommunications. 
Nowadays the story of WiMAX has already almost evaporated from the discussions of 
telecommunications researchers and many of the main actors of this scene even disappeared 
from the list of active players of the field (Alvarion, Redline, Aperto Networks, Airspan, etc.). 
Nevertheless, it is impossible to deny that, firstly, this story has had a significant value for 
development of the field. Secondly, the entire project cost a lot for the participants and, 
possibly, might be considered as one of the most costly undertakings that has ever existed in 
telecommunications and has not achieved success. Only Intel alone invested a huge amount in 
this idea, and that money was spent not only on R&amp;D or production of WiMAX chipsets, but 
also on the deployment of wireless networks 
7 and even acquisition of radio frequencies 
(PCWorld, May 8, 2008). By 2011 there were deployed more than 500 WiMAX networks 
worldwide (Financial Times, August 16, 2010), and vendors of consumers electronics supplied 
their devices with WiMAX chipsets inside. 
8 Finally, this case might represent an interest for 
the empirical studies dedicated to the analysis of the impact that regulation has on development 
of technology, and to the analysis of the intersection of regulation and market mechanisms, that 
exposes that technological superiority or even first-mover advantage are not necessary condi-
tions for the victory in the competitive environment in the presence of regulation. </p>

<p>2.2 The Strategic Inflection Point in Telecommunications Industry </p>

<p>The theory of disruptive innovations initially appeared in management science (Bower and 
Christensen 1995) and then was adopted by researchers of other areas of social sciences. 
Similar ideas can be found in papers of Andrew S. Grove, who was among the chief executives 
of Intel Corporation from the time of the creation of the company, and it makes a particular 
sense for the purpose of this article, since this company is one of the main actors of the story. In 
his works dedicated to management, Grove introduced the concept of Bstrategic inflection 
point^that is trying to describe a situation Bwhen a major change takes place in [the firm's] 
competitive environment^and requires Ba fundamental change in business strategy^(Grove 
1998). 
The end of the XX century and the beginning of the XXI century might be considered as a 
Bstrategic inflection point^for many companies whose main business was in the fields of the 
new economy. Even those companies whose market positions seemed sustainable for the outer </p>

<p>6 For the purpose of this article the term WiMAX, that is an acronym for Worldwide Interoperability for 
Microwave Access, is used to refer to the IEEE 802.16 standard for wireless metropolitan area networks. The 
terms BWiMAX technology^or BWiMAX standard^in this paper describe the technology that complied with the 
sub-sets of IEEE 802.16 standard approved by the WiMAX Forum, the organisation that promoted the concept 
and coordinated certification of compliance with IEEE 802.16 and interoperability. 
7 The most noticeable example is Clearwire where the company lost about 1 billion according to its Preliminary 
Fourth-Quarter Financial Information published on 7 January 2009 (Available at http://www.intc. 
com/releasedetail.cfm?ReleaseID=357860), but there were also Orascom Telecom in Egypt, Worldmax in the 
Netherlands, PIPEX Wireless in the United Kingdom, Unwired in Australia, Neovia in Brazil, etc. (Intel News 
Release, May 22, 2006. Available at http://www.intel.com/pressroom/archive/releases/2006/20060522corp.htm). 
8 For example, in the list of WiMAX Certified products that were approved for the usage in the WiMAX network 
of Japaness company UQ Communication there are laptops and tablets produced by Lenovo, Acer, Sony, 
Panasonic, Toshiba, Fujitsu, etc. Information available at the website of the company http://www.uqwimax. 
jp/english/annai/certification/info.html </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
threats were under the risk to lose their business if their markets lose their attractiveness for 
consumers due to the technological advances and appearance of new solutions for the 
problems of human beings. The digital technologies of the XXI century provided opportunities 
for such disruptiveness and left entire markets in the annals of history. Examples are markets of 
tape recorders and cassette tapes, analog photo cameras and photographic films, cable radio, 
matrix printers, cathode ray tube technology, etc. Meanwhile, not only the digital world 
threatened positions of companies that achieved their success in the XX century -the 
development of digital technologies also threatened the status quo of the digital marketplace. 
Grove (1996) pointed out that Intel, whose main business was production of dynamic memory 
chips and who was one of the leaders of this market, in the middle of the 1980s had a real risk 
to lose everything and only the decision to change the business and to move the focus on 
manufacturing microprocessors allowed the company to protect its positions and to reach 
worldwide leadership in the growing market of personal computers. 
The threat to the positions of a company comes not only from the industry where it is 
active, but also from external markets, and in the case of personal computers, the threat could 
be expected, and now we observe its materialisation, from mobile devices. From the beginning 
of its appearance, the mobile phone has been more and more transforming to a device with 
computational capacity that allows to execute a big variety of different tasks. Modern tablet PC 
already might be considered as a real substitution for traditional personal computers, 
9 but the 
main players of the market of components for these mobile devices are not the same as were in 
the market of components for personal computers. The growing industry of mobile devices has 
been the real, albeit long-term, disruptive innovation for the established industry of personal 
computers, and the top-managers of the incumbents of the latter at the turn of the centuries 
could already understand it, and, moreover, it could be quite tempting for them to extend their 
business to the new area. 
Meanwhile, to become a leader of the new field was not easy even for such giants as 
Intel Corporation. The incumbents of this market controlled the field through numerous 
patents for the essential technologies. Qualcomm in 2000 was already Bemerging as a 
kind of Intel of the wireless era^(FORTUNE Magazine, May 15, 2000), and ARM 
Holdings, that licensed its processor designs to other chip-makers including Qualcomm, 
Apple, Samsung and others, has become a sort of standard in the growing industry of 
chipsets for mobile devices. We can find figures that show that in 2006 about 98% of all 
mobile phones already used ARM solutions on their motherboards, and, moreover, the 
company had plans to extend its business and to become Bthe architecture for the digital 
world^(CNET, April 3, 2006). 
The alternative to the entry to this field could be creation of a new technology and a 
new market based on this technology, that would be able to substitute the next stage of 
the current way of development of the industry. Therefore, the task could be to find ways 
for the creation of this market and alteration of the trajectory of the development of the 
industry towards the new technology. In other words, the task was creation of a disruptive 
technology for telecommunications in general. In order to protect its positions in the 
entire semiconductors industry where growing market of mobile devices threatened the 
established order, such companies as Intel had to introduce their own disruptive innova-
tion for the new field. </p>

<p>9 In 2010, Steve Jobs already proclaimed that the Post-PC era has arrived (TechRepublic, June 2, 2010) </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>2.3 The Disruptiveness in Different Layers of Telecommunications 
and the Economic Model of the Wireless Innovation </p>

<p>In general, WiMAX was not the only example of wireless technologies that could threaten the 
established telecommunications business at that time. 
10 Moreover, we can find information 
that before taking the leadership in the WiMAX Forum, Intel executives also considered the 
alternatives, but finally stopped their choice on the technology, because they saw that Bonly 
WiMAX drove the technology with economic model^(Fitchard 2008). 
When Intel took the leadership in the WiMAX Forum, the concept of the technology had 
been transformed from Ban access alternative^, that aimed to be as a wireless solution for the 
last mile problem, to Ba platform for mobile computing^(Fitchard 2008). The way of the 
development of telecommunications industry traditionally had in its core voice services, while 
data transfer had been gradually added to the technology. The opportunity for disruptiveness 
was to turn it upside down and to put the data transfer in the core of the system, while voice 
services could be just a part among other opportunities provided by the technology. </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Meanwhile, WiMAX was not an innovation that could be brought to the market with efforts 
of just one creative company, it was a concept that threatened the status quo of different 
markets and assumed joint actions of many players from various layers of telecommunications. 
The result of these actions could be expressed in alteration of all of these markets, formation of 
new business models and creation of new leaders. If Intel was seeking the ways to extend its 
semiconductor business in the new area, there were players in other fields that understood their 
possible benefits from new markets that could be created by the technology. 
From the perspective of telecommunications business, WiMAX was not attractive for incum-
bents of the mobile industry, especially for those who already invested in the creation of 3G 
infrastructure (Conti 2005). WiMAX did not assume the evolution of the networks of mobile 
providers, but instead required new investments in the creation of new networks that would operate 
separately from the cellular networks. Of course, some core parts of the networks infrastructure 
might be used for different kinds of networks, but, nevertheless, the adoption of WiMAX for mobile 
carriers could signify excessive investments in the equipment without returns from the previous 
undertakings (Weil 2009, 9). In other words, sunk costs associated with their current way of 
development made adoption of the non-mainstream innovation highly unattractive to their business 
models. From this point of view this technology perfectly fits one of the important features of 
disruptive innovations that was noticed by Christiansen and was highlighted in the beginning of this 
paper, namely, the financial unattractiveness for incumbents. However, it does not entirely mean that 
mobile service providers would never develop WiMAX networks. In order to preserve their 
positions and to broaden the spectrum of services they could not entirely reject WiMAX technology, 
but they were reluctant in their response to the emergence of this innovation and it was, definitely, 
not the best way of the development of the industry for their business models. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>10 We also can notice Mobile Broadband Wireless Access specification IEEE 802.20 or other subsets of IEEE 
802.16 such as WiBro. 
11 Intel fellow and CTO of Intel's wireless group Siavash Alamouti described these Intel's attempts to enter the 
wireless market in the following way: B…this is not an Intel-versus-the-wireless-industry situation… [but] the 
computing and electronic industry versus a telecom industry traditionally dominated by voice^. (Fitchard 2008). 
12 Moreover, even for the incumbents of the mobile world WiMAX still could be interesting as a strategy for 
entry in the new territories, and, as a result, we can find examples of deployment of WiMAX networks by the 
world leaders of mobile communications. For instance, there were networks of Vodafone under the brand 
Vodacom and the former French monopoly Orange in some African countries, but, again, it rather show the 
possibility of the usage of the technology for disruption of existing or creation of new markets. </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
The technology was not only unattractive for the established mobile operators, but also for 
the incumbents of the traditional wired telecommunications industry. Many of them already 
had assets in the mobile business and, thus, there were no reasons to create competition with 
other units within their companies. Reasons for the adoption of fixed WiMAX solutions were 
even weaker than the possible embracement of the mobile version of the technology: the 
implementation of fixed WiMAX for remote areas might be less attractive business than the 
monopolistic development of wired infrastructure through the government subsidisation of the 
universal service, while creation of such networks in parallel with their existing networks 
simply made no sense. 
Meanwhile, by the middle of 2010 the total number of deployment of WiMAX networks 
reached 500 in 147 countries (Financial Times, August 16, 2010). In some of these cases it was 
an attempt of provision of mobile services, but in many it was competition with incumbents of 
wired telecommunications and even a natural solution of the digital divide problem. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>WiMAX, despite of its unattractiveness for established players of the field, opened doors for 
newcomers or helped to solve the Blocal loop^problem for those who otherwise had to rely on 
the incumbents' infrastructure. 
In 2004, Intel executives claimed that WiMAX technology will Btruly usher in the 
broadband wireless revolution^and saw three phases of the deployment of the technology: 
1) outdoor solutions, 2) indoor solutions, 3) mobility (Intel News Release, Jan. 21, 2004). This 
three-phases evolution approach was included in the plans of certification of WiMAX 
equipment, and there were proposals that this upgrade on the higher phases might be done 
through the installation of new versions of software, while the hard core of the network would 
remain the same. The third mobile phase of the technology was later considered as one of the 
possible versions of 4G mobile telecommunications, however, this candidate for 4G was not 
an evolutionary path of the mobile technology, but the mobile version of the fixed wireless 
technology. 
There were several issues for those who considered to invest in this sort of business, and the 
economic model of WiMAX had to have a solution for these problems in order to find 
widespread adoption. First of all, the price of the network equipment and end-users terminals 
had to be significantly lower than those provided by competing technologies, and in different 
phases of the development of the technology different alternatives could be considered as 
rivals. 
Secondly, there was a necessity to avoid the high costs of installation of end-users 
equipment, and it was an issue in the first two steps of the development of the technology, 
that were based only on the solutions for the fixed broadband access. 
Thirdly, the technology must provide a cost-effective solution for the architecture of the 
network in the sense of the coverage area of a base station and required number of the base 
stations. It should take into account such aspects as the absence of a line of sight between base 
stations and end-users terminals and the necessity to arrange high speeds connections. 
Then, there should be a solution for the network infrastructure. The technology allowed to 
solve the problem of the last mile, but it was not less important to understand how the core of 
the network could be connected with other network elements and, moreover, how it could be 
interconnected with other networks. This task could not be solved solely by technological 
means, and required active participation of government in the promotion of development of </p>

<p>13 Some even considered WiMAX as a possible Bcost effective solution to answering the challenges posed by the 
digital divide^. (Yarali et al. 2007). </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>infrastructure and competition in this area. It was already clear by the time of the appearance of 
WiMAX that B[s]uccessful competition for infrastructure can reduce the needs for access 
regulation^(Canoy et al. 2003, 71). At the same time, the European approach that aimed to the 
promotion of service-based competition was not the best solution for infrastructure develop-
ment and some recent researches point out these shortcomings of European regulation (Yoo 
2014). </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Finally, maybe the most important issue that had to be solved for the attraction of investors 
and entrepreneurs is the creation of expectations that this technology will change the world of 
telecommunications. Investments in the creation of WiMAX networks for the provision of 
services in underserved areas could be a question for new adepts of the technology, but if to 
consider the outdoor solutions for the coverage of these areas as just a first stage in the 
formation of the future mobile business, then this activity is merely a necessary part of the 
whole business model where the desired pay-off will be achieved later. 
The leadership of such company as Intel in this project was a noticeable signal about the 
commitments of serious players towards the technology. Mo Shakouri, who was a vice 
president of WiMAX Forum, pointed out that Bwithout Intel's support the WiMAX industry 
never would have moved so fast^(Fitchard 2008), and this speed of the development of the 
project increased expectations of investors. In September 2007, Intel's WiMAX plans were 
more than ambitious: 150 million subscribers worldwide one year later in 2008; 750 million, 
more than 10% of the world population, in 2010; and 1.3 billion in 2012 (Gardiner 2007). Paul 
Otellini, CEO of Intel of that time, claimed that the industry is moving toward ultra mobility 
and BWiMAX … will be the network that provides that^(Gardiner 2007). 
To summarise, the success of the technology required its widespread adoption that could be 
achieved through interoperability, solution of the cost-effective network architecture issue, 
provision of expectations of the future alternative telecommunications market and assistance of 
governments in the creation of the backbone infrastructure, and would allow to decrease the 
prices of equipment and to eliminate the costs of installation. At the same time, these tasks 
were highly complicated by the issues of the allocation of radio frequencies and by the 
industrial policy, and, moreover, the failure in the finding of the solution for these problems 
merely signified that the primary goals would not also be achieved. </p>

<p>3 The Role of Regulation in the Development of Wireless Industry </p>

<p>Technological change is not an independent process as it is assumed by technological 
determinism, and the market is not the only social institution that influences technology 
(MacKenzie and Wajcman 1999). Regulation co-determines the development of technologies 
and even technologies that will be embraced by society, as well as technologies that would be 
thrown away from the main course of technological development. Butenko and Larouche 
(2015), for example, argue that Bregulation affects which inventions are made, which are 
developed, and which are not, as well as which take off, and which do not^. The interaction of 
technological change and regulation defines the actions of industry players and shape the 
architecture of the network and characteristics of the key technologies, and telecommunica-
tions provide us good examples of how Ball changes in regulation produce important </p>

<p>14 For the discussion about advantages of facilities-based competition see also Lemstra et al. (2015), De Bijl 
(2005). </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
consequences on the organization of the industry that in turn … have important consequences 
on the technology^(Antonelli 1995). What is more interesting here and what might be referred 
from the case of the WiMAX story is that in the current regulatory regime the market plays a 
quite secondary role in this process. The victory in the battle between the evolution of the 
mainstream technology and the disruptive technology proposed to the market from the outside 
was not determined by the superiority of technological solutions or even more sustainable 
business models of the established players, but was a consequence of regulatory decisions and 
legal norms in some key aspects. Eventually, the economic model of WiMAX could not solve 
the problems highlighted in the previous section and there is a clear relationship between this 
failure and the government interventions into the market. 
Indeed, among the studies dedicated to the comparison of mobile WiMAX and LTE we can 
find that LTE did not have technological superiority 
15 and, thus, earlier WiMAX appearance in 
the market could have played as a first-mover advantage. The business models of the 
mainstream operators could be threatened by the appearance of newcomers, but chances to 
succeed in the telecommunications marketplace for those who were eager to launch the new 
wireless business were significantly affected by the regulation of the field. 
The deployment of wireless networks heavily depends on the ability of telecommunications 
operators to get radio resources. Only very limited parts of the radio spectrum through out the 
world are accessible on the free basis, while mostly commercially interesting radio resources 
are under the control of governments everywhere, and, moreover, these resources have not 
been available for Btwo guys in a garage^1 
6 who could have brought the disruption into the 
markets of telecommunication services. On the contrary, the social utility from the economies 
of scale, and understanding of the best ways of its achievement incorporated in the economics 
mainstream, have always ruled the decision makings concerning the radio spectrum allocation, 
and instead of distribution of the radio spectrum for a number of entrepreneurs, it has always 
been allocated to small groups of big service providers. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>There is also another area of government interventions, that is very relevant to the field of 
wireless technology, as well as to the industries of the new economy in general, and this area is 
the institution of intellectual property. As it was mentioned in the beginning of the paper there 
is no consensus about the scope of necessary interventions and even a necessity to create 
incentives through the provision of exclusive rights. This section of the paper analyses the 
impact of both of these aspects, the government intervention in the area of radio spectrum use 
and allocation of exclusive rights to objects of the intellectual sphere on the eventual defeat of 
the disruptive wireless technology by the mainstream part of the industry, and, at the same 
time, discusses the possible positive role of regulation in the promotion of technological 
pluralism in the industry. </p>

<p>3.1 Radio Spectrum Allocation </p>

<p>One of the main aspects of the legal frameworks that has always influenced the development 
of the industry is regulation of the radio spectrum, and this is not limited to the market of 
telecommunications services, but also affects the market of manufacturers. The problem is not </p>

<p>15 Some even claims, that WiMAX performed better in some cases (Roodaki et al. 2014). 
16 The term here is adopted from Christensen et al. (2013), who notice that BDisruptive innovations are … 
products or services, often created by Btwo guys in a garage^.1 
7 Melody (2012), for example, notices that in the EU B[t]he liberalisation objective of stimulating competition 
and opening access apparently was not considered to be the cornerstone of spectrum policy^. </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>only that the state allocates rights to use radio waves, but it also determines how the spectrum 
should be used, and this particular issue makes innovation dependent also on policymakers, 
but not only on creative minds. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>The developers of the WiMAX standard from the very beginning had been struggling with 
the necessity to comply with spectrum regulation that was different in different places and, 
thus, availability of the parts of the spectrum for the future deployment of networks was also 
different. For example, the report of the OECD (2006) pointed that BMuch of the success of 
WiMAX hinges on the ability of operators to find appropriate and available spectrum^, and 
that Bwithout a globally recognized frequency band, the economies of scale will be reduced^. 
It was also clearly understood by the members of WiMAX Forum and was expressed in its 
official papers dedicated to the regulatory issues (WiMAX Forum 2004). 
19 Furthermore, the 
developers, in order to mitigate the problem and to find some intersections in the regulation of 
spectrum in different countries, were trying to adjust technical features of the technology to 
these common points by reducing, for example, the required bandwidth for a channel or the 
transmission power. However, at the same time, it limited the capacity of the technology. 
Even in the 3.5 GHz band the regulation of some countries (e.g., Sweden or the UK) directly 
prohibited mobility of telecommunications services Bother than 3G services^(OECD 2006, 21). 
Therefore, while in the higher band (5.7 GHz) mobility was limited by the laws of nature, in the band 
3.5 GHz there was allowed only the competition with DSL due to the legal rules. In some 
jurisdictions there were restrictions on the coverage area of base stations that reduced the benefits 
of the cost-efficiency of the network infrastructure. 
20 Regulation of the usage of radio spectrum in 
several countries prohibited real mobility in wireless broadband networks, restricting the speed of 
end-user devices of such networks to the speed of pedestrians (OECD 2006). Moreover, the most 
suitable radio band for the mobility of WiMAX specifications, 2.5 GHz, was reserved for the 
evolution of the mainstream technology by the International Telecommunications Union, an agency 
of the United Nations, under the IMT-2000 umbrella, and, thus, could not be used in many of the 
world countries before the inclusion of WiMAX in the IMT-2000 family (OECD 2006). 
The future rules were not determined and were unclear for those who considered to play 
this game, and, thus, increased risks of such investments. At the same time, for those who 
already had their business within the established order, such uncertainty was not a problem -
they had time to wait, to lobby their interests and to adjust their networks to the sustaining 
innovations of the mainstream technology. Even the disruptiveness of the technology could not 
provide enough incentives for investors if the future of the regulatory attitude towards the use 
of radio frequencies was so uncertain. The unclear situation with the possibility to use lower 
parts of radio spectrum (e.g. 2.5 GHz) on the third mobile phase of the technology significantly 
reduced the attractiveness of projects related to the first fixed phases for the potential investors. 
About all factors of the success of the technology highlighted in the previous section 
heavily depended on the decisions of policymakers: the price of technological solutions </p>

<p>18 The concept of technology neutrality is able to some extent alleviate the problem, but this principle was widely 
adopted by the industrial policy only after the mainstream of wireless technology defeated the main competitor, 
which at that moment was WiMAX. 
19 The paper notices Bthe uniform allocation of spectrum worldwide, is crucial to lowering equipment costs 
because radios are a major cost component in developing WiMAX Forum Certified systems^. 
20 For example, in Russia the coverage area of WiMAX base station in the 3.5 GHz radio band was restricted to 
3 km with the maximum power of radio transmitter -10 dBW. The same maximum power of radio transmitter 
was established for Wi-Fi (Decision of GRFC 28.11.05 № 05-10-01-001), and compliance with such rule merely 
made the economy of such networks quite doubtful. </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
required economies of scale that could not be achieved without global adoption of the 
standard, the limitations imposed on the usage of wireless networks affected the cost-
efficient architecture and the costs of installation, the uncertainty and the restrictive policies 
on the mobility decreased the expectations. Even solution of the problems of interconnections 
and backbones in many places of the world required government assistance and could not be 
solved independently from incumbents. In countries with a low level of concentration in the 
industry, with advanced fiber-optic infrastructure that was not totally under the control of 
incumbents and where there were possibility for its costs-efficient construction, like in Russia, 
the main problem to the entrance to the wireless market was a solution of radio frequencies 
allocation problem, while in those countries where telecommunications infrastructure was just 
recently opened for competition or was under the total control of incumbents the problem of 
entrance was more complicated. 
The WiMAX technology was unable to achieve global adoption, and the final stage of the 
life of the project began in 2010, when it already became apparent that the mobile version of 
the standard lost the battle with LTE. This period revealed some examples that show that 
expectations of those who invested in the WiMAX projects hoping to obtain in the future the 
broader parts of radio spectrum and to extend their services were wrong. Dutch company 
WorldMAX 
21 was forced to shutdown its WiMAX network in June 2010 because the 
government, in excuse of national security, put restriction on the license of the company 
regarding the usage of radio spectrum (Vos 2010). Just one month before, the company 
Freedom4 
22 left the market of telecommunications services in the UK because the regulatory 
policy did not permit provision of mobile services on the WiMAX network of the company 
(Baker 2010). However, strictly speaking, mobility in the radio band 3.5 GHz is limited also 
by economic rationales, but what is more relevant to the problem is that the company was also 
unable to get frequencies in the 2.6 GHz radio band (Baker 2010). 
The similar problem of impossibility to extend the radio resource of deployed fixed 
WiMAX networks into the radio band that allows mobility was observed in other parts of 
the World. The main explanation of this situation is that these radio resources were obtained by 
the mobile incumbents for the development of their networks, 
23 and for them, as described 
earlier, WiMAX was not the best alternative among WiMAX and LTE. </p>

<p>3.2 Issues of Intellectual Property Related to the Wireless Technology </p>

<p>As was noticed above, the economic model of the wireless technology requires a cost-effective 
network infrastructure. This could be achieved only if the technology incorporates the most 
advanced relevant technological achievements that existed in the industry at that time. In the 
world where ideas are not free and the owners of intellectual goods have rights to exclude 
others from the participation in the technological progress, the entities that were able to 
concentrate the rights on the most essential solutions for technological development have 
power to affect the total outcome of the industry. In the analysed case such Bintellectual </p>

<p>21 According to some estimations, Intel Capital and Enertel Holding jointly invested 37 million USD in the 
creation of this network in Amsterdam. (Higginbotham 2010) 
22 This company was also the project with investments of Intel Capital (Intel News Release, Feb. 11, 2008) 
23 Possibly, the most noticeable exceptions from this pattern were Clearwire in the US and Yota in Russia, but in 
the second case the company gained frequencies and got opportunities to deploy networks in most of the Russian 
regions when WiMAX was already doomed and the company turned its efforts towards LTE. </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>monopolists^2 
4 had very apparent interests in the promotion of the mainstream of the wireless 
telecommunications, rather than to allow disruptors to challenge their business positions. 
Ericsson, the leader of the market of mobile networks equipment, joined the WiMAX 
Forum in 2004 (Ericsson Press Release, Dec. 13, 2004). The company has had Bone of the 
industry's strongest intellectual property portfolios^(Ericsson Press Information, Feb. 2007), 
but has never been among the manufacturers of WiMAX equipment. Among those who were 
able to significantly benefit from the technology and who really produced certified WiMAX 
equipment were such companies as Alvarion, Airspan, Navini, Aperto Networks, etc. These 
companies might really be considered as outsiders of the market of wireless equipment and as 
disruptors of the established market. However, in the case of the victory of WiMAX in the 
competition for 4G standard they could get a portion of the pie. Some researchers argued that 
wide adoption of BWiMAX as a 4G standard would be crisis for Ericsson and Nokia Siemens 
Networks^, and, as a result, these companies had to adjust their strategies to the promotion of 
LTE, and intellectual property rights could be a powerful tool for the achievement of such goal 
(Seo 2013, 169-171). In 2006 Ericsson terminated its participation in the WiMAX project and 
devoted its resources to HSPA and LTE. WiMAX was rather the threat than the opportunity for 
the company that controlled about the third of the mainstream market. 
The most noticeable player in the sphere of mobile standards, Qualcomm, was also among those 
who had opportunities and incentives to determine the future of wireless technology, and, according 
to the claims of some experts, openly opposed the development of WiMAX (Bloomberg, September 
3, 2007). In 2005, The Economist, describing the role of Qualcomm in the third generation wireless 
networks, claimed that B[b]ecause its technology underlies the third-generation mobile-phone 
standard, Qualcomm has become a toll bridge that all equipment-makers must cross^(The 
Economist, Oct. 20, 2005). In 2005 -2006, Qualcomm significantly increased its patent portfolio 
concerning, inter alia, crucial solutions for WiMAX technology by the acquisition of the developer 
of MIMO technology 
25 Airgo and the pioneer and developer of OFDM technology 
26 Flarion, and 
became the holder of Bthe most widely licensed in the industry^patent portfolio that Bapplies to all 
existing 4G standards … including … LTE … and … WiMAX^(Qualcomm's LTE/WiMAX patent 
licensing statement, Dec. 2008). Some experts, commenting the acquisition of Flarion by 
Qualcomm, even claimed that BQualcomm has now got its hands on all future mobile technology^, 
and directly pointed out that, as a result of it, BWiMAX … might face problems^(Lewan 2005). 
From the perspectives of disruptiveness of the mainstream wireless business for the market of 
traditional PC and WiMAX for the mainstream telecommunications, such actors of the semicon-
ductors market as Qualcomm had clear reasons to be in favour of the wireless mainstream. 
In order to help to promote the WiMAX technology in the middle of 2008 Intel jointly with 
Cisco, 
27 Samsung, Alcatel-Lucent and telecommunications service providers Sprint Nextel and 
Clearwire formed the patent pool Open Patent Association. The primary goal of the organisa-
tion was proclaimed Bto foster a global ecosystem focused on delivering broader choice, 
competitive equipment and service costs for WiMAX technology, devices and applications^. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>However, they did not manage to attract to this patent pool all companies that possessed the </p>

<p>24 The term Bintellectual monopoly^here is adopted from Boldrin and Levine (2008). 
25 MIMO is an essential element of many modern wireless standards. 
26 OFDM is a method of encoding digital data that has also found wide application in the wireless standards. 
27 The company in 2007 for $330 million acquired noticeable player among WiMAX manufacturers Navini 
Networks (FORTUNE Magazine, Oct. 23, 2007). 
28 The website of the organisation is available through Internet archive https://web.archive. 
org/web/20110727151012/http://openpatentalliance.org/ </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
essential patents for the technology. The response of the mainstream industry was the commit-
ments of the main patent holders Bto a framework for establishing predictable and more 
transparent maximum aggregate costs for licensing intellectual property rights (IPR) that relate 
to 3GPP Long Term Evolution^(Ericsson Press Release, April 14, 2008). 
Qualcomm did not join any of these agreements, but introduced in the same year their own 
FRAND patent statement. Qualcomm put it in the way that LTE and WiMAX Bwill be used to 
complement existing 3G deployments to help address the growing demand for mobile data^, 
but the initial purpose of WiMAX was not the complementing of 3G deployments. The 
technological and logical continuation of 3G networks could be only LTE from these two 
alternatives, and it was clear for the senior executives of Qualcomm. Peter Lancia, Sr. Director 
in Marketing of Qualcomm, noticed that BLTE will provide a parallel evolution path to 3G, and 
will leverage 3G's scale and ecosystem of vendors, operators, consumers and application 
developers^(OnQ blog at the Qualcomm's website, May 25, 2010). </p>

<p>3.3 Promotion of Competition and Technological Pluralism in the Industry </p>

<p>Although the promotion of competition is among the priority goals of the industrial policy, the reality 
of modern days shows us that all layers of the industry have been becoming more and more 
concentrated, and this concentration takes place on the global level. By 2015, the major part of the 
market of mobile infrastructure equipment was already under the control of just four companies: 
Ericsson, Nokia, Alcatel-Lucent and Huawei, and nowadays, when Nokia finally gained control 
over Alcatel-Lucent, the oligopolistic structure has become even more prominent. The number of 
mobile service providers has also declined, and some European mobile markets have already 
changed their structure from four to three operators (Austria, Germany, Ireland, etc.). 
The analysis of this paper is drawing the link between the regulation and the ongoing 
process of concentration of the industry, but this does not mean that in the pure laissez-faire 
system we would not face the similar problem or a set of other issues. As it was noticed above, 
the success of WiMax was practically impossible without assistance of governments in the 
creation of the backbone infrastructure and efficient solutions of the problem of interconnec-
tion. These crucial resources were under the control of incumbents, and for them the alternative 
development of the industry was not the best possible option, while new entrants, who could 
bring the disruption in the market, were in a dependent position from the conduct of the giants, 
and only industrial policy aimed at the promotion of technological pluralism and competition 
could alleviate the problem. 
At the same time, if the aim of the competition policy is the promotion of competition 
between the main players, who already invested in development of the mainstream technology, 
but not facilitation of access for new entrants and opening doors for them for bringing new 
technologies, then we can hardly expect the appearance of innovations that threaten the 
mainstream course of the development due to the problem of sunk costs of the incumbents. 
Antonelli (1995) in his analysis of technological change in telecommunications points out that 
Bthe larger the variety of independent players, the larger the opportunities to generate new 
technologies^, and it has a particular sense for the recent story of the wireless industry. There 
were a number of sets of 2G standards, then there were just two 3G sets of standards, and there 
is the only one standard considered as 4G technology. However, if the technological pluralism 
was a target of the industrial policy, then we could expect not only to have the diversity, but 
also to observe the continuing process of creative destruction in this viable field of the new 
economy. </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>4 The Mutual Shaping of Technology and Regulation in Telecommunications </p>

<p>The regulation of telecommunications has evolved since the appearance of the industry, 
addressing its efforts to new issues that have been arising with the development of the 
technology. However, not only technology raises problems before policymakers and affects 
legal norms, but legal norms, in turn, affect the development of technology. In social sciences 
dedicated to regulatory issues this idea is expressed in the concept of mutual shaping of 
technology and society (e.g. MacKenzie and Wajcman 1999). Meanwhile, in a case of 
disruptive technology in highly regulated industries there could be an issue, because the law 
has been developing along with the mainstream of the industry and it has created the 
playground for the mainstream players, while for the technology that assumes an alternative 
way of the functioning of the field the old rules could be inappropriate or even hostile. 
In other words, law and technology not only mutually shape each other, this mutual shaping 
process is able to form the high level of dependence on the previous way of development and 
protect the mainstream course of the technology from external threats. Many scholars point to 
the problem of Bregulatory disconnection^(Brownsword and Goodwin 2012; Brownsword 
and Somsen 2009) or Bpacing problem^(Marchant et al. 2011), the situation when the pace of 
development of technology is faster than of the law that aims to regulate this technology 
(Butenko and Larouche 2015). The WiMAX case shows us that industrial policy in highly 
regulated industries is able to adjust itself to sustaining technologies, even if with the time lag, 
while this disconnection impedes disruptive innovations. As a result, the incumbents of the 
field might even benefit from this pacing problem. 
If, for example, there was no problem of interference, then there would not exist any need to 
solve this problem through regulation, but, at the same time, if this problem can be solved by 
means of legal tools and there are obvious beneficiaries of this mechanism, then the necessity 
to seek alternative ways of its solution is not so actual, unless it fits the aims of the main 
industry's actors. Moreover, even when technology is already able to provide such solution, 
and nowadays we can hear claims that this time has already come (e.g. Werbach 2004; Staple 
and Werbach 2004), the regulation is very reluctant to change its paradigm. The new 
technological paradigm might signify not only dramatic alteration of regulatory approaches 
without clear understanding of the final results, but also may have a significant negative impact 
on the business interests of current major players, and, thus, this regulatory shift is not 
desirable neither for the incumbents nor for the policymakers. 
This is not only the case of radio spectrum or industrial policy of telecommunications in 
general. It is the pattern that can be found in many cases when a regulated industry faces 
disruptive innovations. Uber or Airbnb, for instance, have also experienced numerous ob-
structions from the side of regulation. 
29 However, the attempts of policymakers to protect the 
established business interests is not necessarily a case of regulatory capture, but also their 
natural response to the threats to stability, since new technology might convey unpredictable 
consequences. 
It is also necessary to notice that some innovations, like, for example, implementation of 
BitTorrent protocol that has disrupted the copyright industry, or mentioned above Uber or 
Airbnb, have a crucial advantage compared to innovations in wireless telecommunications. </p>

<p>29 One of the Wikipedia articles is even dedicated to the BLegal status of Uber's service^. Airbnb also has the 
explicit opposition of regulation in many parts of the world: Canada (Montreal Gazette, April 29, 2015), 
Germany (Guardian, May 1, 2016), Russia (RBC, Oct. 8, 2015), and so on. </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
They provide more opportunities for their users to disobey the law, and, thus, have more 
chances to success, while in the case of wireless technology the deployment of a network 
might require a high level of investments without the possibility to dissolve this activity in the 
ocean of other radio pirates, and that increases risks of potential Bviolators^and enhance the 
opportunity for law enforcement. 
At the same time, the problem of impediment to disruptive innovations due to regulatory 
disconnection could be alleviated if the crucial resources of the field were accessible for a big 
number of potential newcomers. In the same way as the end-to-end principle of the Internet 
architecture facilitated growth of diverse online services (Lessig 2006), the physical layer of 
the industry could also make possible the appearance of new disruptive technologies and 
business models if the industrial policy were aimed to promote accessibility of the resources. 
Of course, there is no shortage of justifications of limitations of freedom of potential radio 
spectrum users from the positions of public interests, but it is also necessary to notice that more 
and more scholars nowadays claim that if we take into account the modern technologies, then 
many of these assumptions are obsolete (see Werbach 2004; Staple and Werbach 2004; 
Milgrom et al. 2011). Moreover, the ideas that radio spectrum, or, at least, some of its parts, 
represents a common resource that should be returned to the realm of commons have become 
popular among many scholars (e.g. Benkler 2002; Lessig 2001; Werbach 2001). However, it is 
also possible to admit, that, on the one hand, this discussion about openness of radio spectrum 
could be quite futile without robust economic models that could drive innovations in this field 
providing numerous benefits for various strata of society, but, on the other hand, it is difficult 
to expect the appearance of such models without understanding the possibility of their 
implementation due to the total control of the resource in the interests of major players. 
The idea of the open spectrum emerged before the appearance of WiMAX, and, indeed, the 
widespread implementation of this concept could become the significant part of the growing 
sharing economy. It is difficult to say now whether WiMAX or another wireless technology 
with the similar idea could really benefit from the openness of radio, but we can hypothesise 
that in this case this technology had more chances than the long term evolution of the 
mainstream. However, we can not truly say that WiMAX Forum aimed the efforts to promote 
the technology within the open spectrum concept, but the comparison with Wi-Fi, that mainly 
operates in the unlicensed frequencies, was one of the main parts of the leitmotif of the story 
(e.g. Intel News Release [Intel Outlines Broadband Wireless Vision], Jan. 21, 2004). Moreover, 
WiMAX camp considered the operation of WiMAX networks in the license-exempt parts of 
radio spectrum (Intel 2005). The license-exempt 5 GHz band was among the Binitial bands of 
focus^(WiMAX Forum 2004), but this radio band increases requirements of line of sight and, 
thereby, decreases the commercial attractiveness of the technology. 
Meanwhile, innovations in the unlicensed parts of radio spectrum are able even to change 
the core assumptions of the mainstream economic models. For example, the phenomenon of 
community networks, where the infrastructure is a common-pool resource, hardly fits the 
mainstream understanding of the economics of telecommunications. Such networks provide 
services for dozens of thousands of subscribers and compete with the giants (Baig et al. 2015), 
but, again, one of the problems of their development is the access to the resources that are 
necessary for creation of this common infrastructure. However, if the scenario of the WiMAX 
camp about the widespread adoption of the technology and significant reduction of prices of 
WiMAX equipment was fulfilled, then this technology could be a powerful tool for such 
innovative business models. Moreover, the mesh topology of network architecture, that 
Benkler (2002) described in the model of the BIdeal Open Wireless Network^, and that is </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>widely used in the wireless community networks, was placed in the agenda of the evolution of 
WiMAX (Wei et al. 2005). 
In the field of intellectual property WiMAX proponents promoted the idea about open 
patent system for the technology B[t]o help ensure product differentiation and interoperability 
at a more predictable cost^(Intel News Release, June 9, 2008), but they were not able to 
include in this pool the essential claims of the opposition of this technology, and again, it 
exposes the development of the mainstream institutions of our society that, even if uninten-
tionally, protect the established status quo. 
Although the institution of intellectual property and allocation of radio frequencies both 
represent the examples of government intervention in the mechanisms of the free market, they 
are quite different by their nature. In the case of radio spectrum distribution, the problem is 
based on physical characteristics of radio waves, that are expressed in the limitation imposed 
by the mother nature, while in the second case this is mainly an attempt to provide a utilitarian 
solution for economic issues, but not the problem imposed by the physical features of our 
world. 
If we consider regulation as the institution that forms the common playground for different 
actors, then we might expect to see the difference between institution of intellectual property 
and norms of allocation of radio frequencies. Government establishes the same rules for all 
members of society to get protection on the results of creativity of human minds, and, 
theoretically, anyone can use these mechanisms for his business purposes. There is a restriction 
for the usage of a particular idea, but not the restriction for the use of alternatives. 
30 At the 
same time, the allocation of radio frequencies a priori does not assume the pluralistic landscape 
of commercial wireless networks and allows to allocate these privileges only to a very limited 
number of actors. However, it is possible to argue that this difference in some cases is mostly 
theoretical. Inventions might be essential for the entire industry without possibilities to invent 
around, 
31 and, thus, it could be an analogy between property rights on such resource and 
property rights on an essential part of the radio spectrum, merely because it might be an 
absence of alternatives in both cases. Since the technological inventions are not the result of 
individual genius but the natural consequence of technological development of our civilisa-
tion, 
32 even patent races to some extent might be considered as an analogy of Braces^for radio 
frequencies, and, thus, both these institutions similarly promote the ongoing process of 
concentration of the field. 
The optimal design of the institution of intellectual property in economics is often consid-
ered as a proper balance between provision of incentives for innovations and resulting 
monopoly prices and deadweight losses (See e.g. Merges 2000). However, the effect on prices 
is not the only economic effect generated by this institution, and some argue that we must 
weigh the benefits of IPR Bagainst the costs of the centralization of economic decisionmaking 
and the creation of barriers to innovation and market entry^(Wu 2006). From this point of 
view, the most important economic effect of IPR is on industry structure and it reflects the idea 
that regulation, affecting the industry structure, also affects the architecture of the network. 
Centralisation of decision making about the technological development inevitably affects the 
process of technological change and expresses in the architecture of the network that is, as </p>

<p>30 It leads some to the conclusion that BIP rights are rarely if ever Bintellectual monopolies^.^(Lemley 2009). 
31 Some even claim that Bknowledge can be considered as an essential facility^(Antonelli 2007). 
32 Such position is quite common, and, for example, can be found in Scotchmer (1991). </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
Antonelli (1995) notices, Bstrongly influenced by the changing characteristics of clay 
technologies^. 
In their highly cited article of 1986 Sah and Stiglitz, analysing the process of decision 
making depending on architecture of an economic system, argue that, due to the imperfectness 
of decision making process and limited capabilities of human minds, polyarchical systems, 
whose architecture is represented by Ba market oriented economy^, provide more opportunities 
to accept Bgood^innovations, while in hierarchies, where decision making is centralised, the 
risk to sort out such projects is higher. At the same time, they claim that the advantage of 
hierarchical systems is that they better cope with Type II errors, when it would be more 
reasonable to reject some accepted projects. Tim Wu (2006) emphasises that since 
decentralised systems (polyarchies) are able to approve more projects than hierarchies, Bthey 
manage to capture the few available profitable ideas^. Following the logic of this literature and 
taking into account that the technological variety of the wireless industry presented in the 
market is not so diverse, it is possible to argue that facilitation of decentralised decision 
makings in the industry would provide more chances for valuable ideas to materialise in the 
technological solutions. 
Meanwhile, the decentralisation and pluralism are highly dependent on the institutional 
environment that, as it was highlighted above, requires active participation of the regulator. 
Access to radio frequencies, essential radio technologies, infrastructure and interconnection 
points are those issues which efficient solution, possibly, was able to change the course of the 
wireless industry. What is also interesting here, is that without regulatory participation in the 
solution of these issues even assured access to long term financial institutions, and in the 
WiMAX case we observe that Intel and others have invested a lot in the project, is not 
sufficient for the achieving success. Moreover, inability to get access to the industrial resources 
merely signifies that financial support of even a lucrative idea at an early stage of its 
development would be highly limited, and, again it plays as a discouraging factor for 
innovations in the field. 
Nowadays, when intellectual property rights on wireless technologies have become more 
concentrated, when the most interesting parts of radio spectrum have already been assigned to 
the mainstream, and, moreover, when they already have been propertisized by the incumbents, 
the entire future of the industry is totally in the hands of these proprietaries -proprietaries of 
technology, infrastructure and radio waves, and we do not have robust reasons to assume that 
such a system is able to better appreciate potential innovations than an open and competitive 
marketplace. As it was mentioned in the beginning of the paper, this is not the problem of 
market concentration that could be solved by the implementation of antitrust, but this is the 
problem of the exclusive rights that were granted by regulation and that finally created the 
barriers for the appearance of any disruptions. </p>

<p>5 Summary and Conclusions </p>

<p>The analysed initiative to change the established wireless industry was totally defeated by the 
incumbents of the field. The industry has become more concentrated than it was 15 years ago, 
and this tendency is observed in all layers of telecommunications. 
It is possible to draw some analogy of the WiMAX case with other cases of standard wars 
such as competition between Betamax and VHS. There were studies that claimed that Betamax 
was a superior standard, but, nevertheless, lost the battle, and, thus, it is possible to assume that </p>

<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>the choice of the market did not represent the best possible outcome (Liebowitz and Margolis 
1995). However, here is the crucial difference of these two cases. In the Betamax-VHS case 
the market played the superior role in the adoption of the technology, while in the WiMAX-
LTE case the role of the market was secondary and the outcome was mainly determined by 
regulation. Moreover, Sony, whose videotape format was defeated by JVC, was able to bring 
to the market the DVD format (in collaboration with Philips, Toshiba and Panasonic) and 
avoid the mistakes of the previous experience. The introduction of DVD was a clear disruption 
for VHS industry. The DVD format provided obvious advantages for participants of the home 
video market and, eventually, replaced VHS as a method of video distribution. On the one 
hand, these two examples show us, that the market does not exclude a risk to sort out superior 
technology and from this point of view it is impossible to argue that it solves the problem 
better than regulation, but, on the other hand, it leaves more chances for a technological shift at 
the later stages compared to the regulatory policy that creates opportunities for leaders to 
determine technological development. Moreover, even if the market outcome is not the best 
from short-term efficiency perspectives, industrial pluralism is able to be a basis for a future 
technological breakthrough. 
We observe more innovations in those parts of telecommunications where regulator is less 
active, but the core, the physical layer, of the industry is changing gradually in sustaining, not 
disruptive, way of development of the technology. Regulation has locked-in the future 
development of the industry on the mainstream technology and eliminated alternatives. 
Meanwhile, the WiMAX story shows us that not only that concentration in telecommunica-
tions is not a necessary condition for the innovative development, but also that disruptive 
technologies are able to attract investments in this field from newcomers and weak players of 
the industry, putting the mainstream under the pressure of competition, and fostering innova-
tions in their business. However, innovations require accessibility of the main resources and 
that might be achieved only if the resources are in the common domain. Even if WiMAX was 
not the technology that could benefit from this openness, it had chances to evolve to the 
version that could. The main advantage of the open access to the essential resources is that the 
openness makes easier the appearance of disruptive innovations, and regulation must facilitate 
this openness in order to promote the opportunities for creative destruction. 
The alternative viewpoint might be that the process of technological change should be 
governed in public interests by public agencies because they have abilities to weigh costs and 
benefits of different technological regimes and choose more suitable direction for social 
interests. In fact, this is an alternative representation of the old discussion about virtues of 
Bthe invisible hand^and the opinion, like of Stiglitz (2001), that this hand Bis simply not 
there^, and the diversity of the theories of modern economics does not provide us any 
uniformity. However, even if we assume that the problem of regulatory capture is not relevant 
to the issue, and that the regulator is able to understand social interests and bases its actions on 
this understanding, we still cannot escape from the problems of epistemological limitations, 
transaction costs and information asymmetry, and, thus, we do not have reasons to believe that 
public agencies are able to govern the process of technological change better than market 
mechanisms. 
The phenomenon of sunk costs has a deterring effect on the adoption of non-mainstream 
innovations by incumbents, while for potential new entrants this issue does not exist if they 
have not invested yet in currently presented technological solutions and they might be eager to 
jump into an alternative technological paradigm. However, if resources in the industry are 
under the total control of incumbents, then their decision about the use of such resources can </p>

<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

<p>
not be free from the influence of the previous investments, i.e. the presence of sunk costs 
heavily affects the direction of technological change if the decision making is centralised in the 
hands of the main players. Therefore, if regulation contributes to such centralised decision 
making and if the outcome of the decision making is affected by the presence of sunk costs, 
then this contribution shapes the entire way of technological change. Meanwhile, active 
participation of newcomers in innovation activity may facilitate the process of creative 
destruction and, thereby, result not only in positive economic effects, but also in alleviation 
of socio-economic problems (see., e.g., an analysis of the impact of this process on income 
inequalities in Antonelli and Agnieszka 2016). 
Nowadays the LTE camp analyses the possibility to use the technology in the unlicensed 
radio bands and considers that technology is able to be adopted by private entities as an 
analogy of Wi-Fi. The same was heard in 2004 -2010 from the disruptors of the mainstream 
market, but now the ideas of the disruptive innovation have been transformed into the 
sustaining innovation of the orthodox part of the industry. Furthermore, now the regulation 
moves towards such experiments, but, again, this movement supports the mainstream. It shows 
that regulation is able to support evolution of established technologies and adjust itself to 
sustaining innovations, but if leaders win in battles of sustaining innovations and entrants have 
opportunities to beat incumbents when disruptive innovations emerge (Christensen 2006), then 
this is the regulatory regime that does not leave chances to change the landscape of the core of 
the industry but not the superiority of the leaders. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments The author is grateful to Ronald Leenes for helpful suggestions and discussion. The author 
would also like to thank an anonymous referee for many valuable comments. </p>

<p>Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International 
License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and repro-
duction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a 
link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>



<p> 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>



<p>J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>



<p>
 
J Ind Compet Trade (2017) 17:399-420 </p>

</text></tei>