<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fobes.12195" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>We investigate the asymptotic and finite sample properties of the most widely used informa-
tion criteria for co-integration rank determination in 'partial' systems, i.e. in co-integrated 
vector autoregressive (VAR) models where a sub-set of variables of interest is modelled 
conditional on another sub-set of variables. The asymptotic properties of the Akaike infor-
mation criterion (AIC), the Bayesian information criterion (BIC) and the Hannan-Quinn 
information criterion (HQC) are established, and consistency of BIC and HQC is proved. 
Notably, the consistency of BIC and HQC is robust to violations of weak exogeneity of the 
conditioning variables with respect to the co-integration parameters. More precisely, BIC 
and HQC recover the true co-integration rank from the partial system analysis also when 
the conditional model does not convey all information about the co-integration parameters. 
This result opens up interesting possibilities for practitioners who can now determine the 
co-integration rank in partial systems without being concerned about the weak exogeneity 
of the conditioning variables. A Monte Carlo experiment based on a large dimensional data 
generating process shows that BIC and HQC applied in partial systems perform reasonably 
well in small samples and comparatively better than 'traditional'methods for co-integration 
rank determination. We further show the usefulness of our approach and the benefits of the 
conditional system analysis in two empirical illustrations, both based on the estimation of 
VAR systems on US quarterly data. Overall, our analysis shows the gains of combining 
information criteria with partial system analysis. </p>

<p>Co-integration rank determination in vector autoregressive (VAR) systems where some 
variables of interest, Y t , are modelled conditional on some other variables, Z t , has been 
addressed in Harbo et al. (1998) [HJNR hereafter], see also Johansen (1992a, b, 1996). 
The idea of the conditional analysis is that the dimensionality of the system is reduced, 
and, when conditioning is valid, co-integration tests may have better power properties. The 
'partial system' approach proves to be useful in situations where (i) the dimension of the 
whole VAR system p := dim(X t ), X t := (Y t , Z t ), is large relative to the sample size T ; (ii) 
the practitioner is essentially interested in modelling Y t and it is known that Z t contributes 
to the long-run equilibrium of the system but either the theory is silent about the short run 
properties of Z t , or the scope of the analysis does not require modelling Z t explicitly; (iii) 
the time series used for Z t are considered poor proxies of the corresponding theoretical 
variables they should measure, especially as concerns their transitory dynamics. 
In general, the parameters of the (conditional) model for Y t given Z t (Y t | Z t ) and of 
the marginal model for Z t are interrelated, which means that a full system analysis is 
needed to draw efficient inference about the parameters of the two models. The special 
case where the partial (conditional) model for Y t given Z t contains as much information 
about the parameters of interest as the full system is when Z t is weakly exogenous, see 
Engle, Hendry and Richard (1983). Under the weak exogeneity of Z t for the co-integrating 
parameters, HJNR derive the asymptotic distribution of the likelihood ratio test for co-
integrating rank in the partial model, and provide tables of critical values. When Z t is not 
weakly exogenous for the co-integrating parameters, the conditional model for Y t given Z t 
conveys only partial information about the long-run structure of the system. 
Actually, the requirement of weak exogeneity of Z t can nullify the benefits of the partial 
system analysis as suggested in HJNR and limit its usefulness in applied work. On the one 
hand, when weak exogeneity of Z t fails, the practitioner cannot apply the asymptotic critical 
values tabulated in HJNR and must resort to the full system analysis. On the other hand, 
it is difficult to check the hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t efficiently without a full 
system analysis or disregarding the model for Z t . Urbain (1992) shows that 'traditional' 
orthogonality tests (Pesaran and Smith, 1990) are not sufficient to address the issue of 
weak exogeneity in error-correction models, see also Boswijk and Urbain (1997). It is 
not surprising, therefore, that despite conditional (structural) error-correction models have 
been widely applied in applied work, only seldom the partial system approach has been 
used for inference on the co-integration rank, see Doornik, Hendry and Nielsen (1998), 
Bårdsen and Fisher (1999), Bruggeman, Donati and Warne (2003), and Johansen (1992b)  for an early example. In empirical studies where a (structural) conditional system for Y t 
given Z t is used, the co-integration rank is typically either assumed to be known, or is 
assumed to be inferred from a full system analysis in a previous stage, see e.g. Boswijk  (1995) and Ericsson (1995). 
Information-based methods are a well-established alternative to approaches based on 
(sequential) Neyman-Pearson type tests for co-integration rank determination. In partic-
ular, Aznar and Salvador (2002) and Cavaliere et al. (2015) [CDRT hereafter], among 
others, show that standard information criteria such as the familiar Bayesian information 
criterion (BIC) and Hannan-Quinn information criterion (HQC) provide powerful alterna-</p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>tives to the traditional Johansen's co-integration rank tests, as they are weakly consistent 
estimators of the co-integration rank. Conversely, the Akaike information criterion (AIC) 
does not deliver a consistent estimate of the co-integration rank as its penalty does not 
satisfy the required rate condition (formally defined in section III below). Therefore, it is 
an asymptotically upward biased estimator of the co-integration rank. 
In this paper, we put forth an information criteria-based approach for co-integration 
rank determination in the partial (conditional) model for Y t given Z t , which does not require 
the hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t with respect to the co-integration parameters. Our 
main result is that the use of either BIC or HQC in partial systems yields weakly consistent 
estimates of the true co-integration rank (the same result does not apply to the AIC). 
Compared to HJNR, the suggested approach does not require the use of tables of critical 
values: the selected co-integration rank is the one which minimizes BIC or HQC across rank 
r = 0, 1,…, p Y , where p Y := dim(Y t ). Notably, we prove the consistency of BIC and HQC 
irrespective of whether Z t is weakly exogeneous or not. The main implication of this result 
is that the practitioner can in fact disregard the marginal model for Z t without pretesting 
or being concerned with the weak exogeneity of Z t . BIC and HQC select asymptotically 
the 'true' co-integration rank from the conditional model of Y t given Z t , and perform 
reasonably well in finite samples. Thus, our approach to co-integration rank determination 
fully restores the main benefits of the partial system analysis. 
We document the advantages of our approach in finite samples by a set of Monte Carlo 
experiments. We investigate co-integration rank determination by information criteria in 
the partial system approach and compare results with those obtained with the full sys-
tem approach. We consider two scenarios: one where the conditioning variables Z t are 
weakly exogenous with respect to the co-integration parameters, and the other where the 
weak exogeneity constraint does not hold. We show that, under weak exogeneity, BIC 
tends to outperform 'traditional' co-integration rank tests in both full and conditional sys-
tems. The selection frequency of the null hypothesis of co-integration rank equal to the 
true co-integration rank delivered by HJRN's sequential test is remarkably inferior to the 
corresponding selection frequencies provided by BIC when Z t is weakly exogenous for 
the co-integration parameters. Conversely, when the hypothesis of weak exogeneity is not 
valid, BIC tends to underestimate the true co-integration rank in small sample sizes. In-
stead, HQC in partial systems outperforms its analogue in full systems, irrespective of Z t 
being weakly exogenous or not. That is, its selection frequencies are roughly the same in 
the two cases and the finite sample performance tends to be better than Johansen's (1996)  sequential procedure in the full (unconditional) VAR system. Quite surprisingly, the results 
from the Monte Carlo experiments also show that the violation of the hypothesis of weak 
exogeneity has only a limited impact on the finite sample performance of HJNR's sequential 
test, although the associated critical values are tabulated under the maintained hypothesis 
of exogeneity. In particular, when the conditioning variables are not weakly exogenous for 
the co-integration parameters, HQC and HJNR's sequential procedure perform in partial 
systems and in samples of lengths typically available to practitioners no worse than their 
full system analogues. Thus, despite ignoring the marginal model for Z t may imply a loss 
of information on the adjustment mechanisms at work in the whole system, the benefits 
of reduced dimensionality tends to compensate possible power losses when HQC is used. 
Interestingly, our Monte Carlo experiments also suggest that the finite sample performance </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>of HQC and BIC (as well as HJNR's sequential procedure) is still satisfactory when VAR 
disturbances are driven by GARCH-type components. This robustness finding lines up 
with what Cavaliere, Rahbek and Taylor (2010) and CDRT have shown to be the case in 
full system analyses. 
We also provide two empirical illustrations. In the first example, we emphasize the 
benefits of combining information criteria and the partial system approach by focusing on 
a relatively large system including seven (p = 7) US macroeconomic variables observed 
at quarterly frequency on the period 1984-2008. We show that co-integration rank deter-
mination from the conditional model for Y t given Z t delivers, for suitable choices of Z t , 
reliable results relative to the full system analysis. In the second example, we consider 
the co-integration/common-trend implications of a version of the small-scale dynamic 
stochastic general equilibrium (DSGE) monetary model of Benati and Surico (2009). We 
show that in this case, even if the dimension of X t is not large relative to the sample size, it 
may be convenient to marginalize Z t out of the analysis. Our empirical results confirm that 
co-integration rank determination by information criteria, especially by the HQC, delivers 
reasonable and reliable results. 
The paper is organized as follows. Section II describes the reference co-integrated 
VAR model. In section III, we outline the information criteria for co-integration rank 
determination in partial systems and we establish their asymptotic properties. The results 
from our Monte Carlo simulations are reported in section IV, while section V shows the 
usefulness of the suggested approach for the two empirical illustrations mentioned above. 
Section VI contains some concluding remarks. The proof of our main result, Theorem 1, 
is given in the accompanying online appendix. </p>

<p>II. A conditional co-integrated VAR model </p>

<p>Consider the p-dimensional process {X t } (the full system) which satisfies the k-th order 
reduced rank VAR model: </p>

<p>X t = X t−1 + </p>

<p>k−1 </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>i X t−i + D t + d t + " t , t = 1,…, T 
(1) </p>

<p>where X t := (X 1t ,…, X pt ) and the initial values, X 1−k ,…, X 0 , are fixed in the statistical anal-
ysis. In the context of equation (1), we assume that the standard 'I(1, r 0 ) conditions', where 
r 0 ∈ {0,…, p} denotes the co-integration rank of the system, defined in Cavaliere, Rahbek  and Taylor (2012) hold; that is, the characteristic polynomial associated with equation (1) 
has p − r 0 roots equal to 1 with all other roots lying outside the unit circle, and where 
and have full column rank r 0 . The innovation process " t := (" 1t ,…, " pt ) is assumed inde-
pendent and distributed as N p (0, ), where is a (p × p) positive definite and symmetric 
matrix. Conditional heteroscedasticity can be allowed as in Cavaliere et al. (2010). The 
deterministic variables in equation (1) are taken to satisfy one of the following cases (see 
e.g. Johansen, 1996): (i) D t = 0, d t = 0 (no deterministic components); (ii) D t = 1, d t = 0 
(restricted constant); or (iii) D t = t, d t = 1 (restricted linear trend). 
We decompose X t as X t = (Y t , Z t ), where Y t is of dimension p Y and Z t is of dimension 
p Z , with p Y + p Z =: p. Therefore, " t = (" </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>t , " </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>t ) in equation (1) are i.i.d. Gaussian with mean </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>zero and covariance matrix </p>

<p>:= </p>

<p>YY 
YZ </p>

<p>ZY 
ZZ </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>All other matrices of parameters in system (1) are partitioned conformably. As in HJNR, 
we define the partial and marginal models assuming, for simplicity and without loss of 
generality, that k = 2 (extension to the case k &gt; 2 is straightforward). 
The conditional (or partial) model is </p>

<p>Y t = 
Z t + c X t−1 + c X t−1 + c D t + c d t + " ct 
(2) </p>

<p>where := YZ </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>ZZ , c := Y − Z , c := Y 1 − </p>

<p>Z1 </p>

<p>1 := ( Y 1 , Z1 ), c := Y Y − 
Z Z , c := Y − Z and " ct := " </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>t − " </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>t , with covariance matrix c = YY .Z := YY − </p>

<p>YZ 
−1 </p>

<p>ZZ ZY . 
1 The marginal model is </p>

<p>Z t = Z X t−1 + Z1 X t−1 + Z Z D t + Z d t + " </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>t . 
(3) </p>

<p>In general, both the conditional model in equation (2) and the marginal model in equa-
tion (3) incorporate information about the co-integration relations. Only when Z = 0, the 
conditional model (2) solely incorporates information about the co-integration relations. 
The statistical analysis of the likelihood function of the partial model in equation (2) 
can be performed by reduced rank regression of the process Y t on X t , corrected for lagged 
differences and the conditioning (stationary) variable Z t (see chapter 8 in Johansen, 1996,  and HJNR). 
2 By concentrating the likelihood function of the partial model in equation 
(2) with respect to the parameters , Y , , c and c , the residuals R 0t , R 1t , and R "t 
corresponding to Y t , X t−1 , and " ct , respectively, are obtained, as well as the corresponding 
residual product moments </p>

<p>S ij := T </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>R it R jt , i, j = 0, 1, ". </p>

<p>Up to a constant term which does not depend on r, the maximized pseudo log-likelihood 
function associated with equation (1) is`T (r) := − </p>

<p>T 
2 </p>

<p>log |ˆ c,r |, whereˆ c,r is the residual 
covariance matrix estimated from the conventional reduced rank regression based on equa-
tion (2) with rank r (see Johansen, 1996). Moreover, |ˆ c,r | := |S 00 | </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>i=1 (1 −ˆ i ), and hencè 
T (r) := − </p>

<p>T 
2 </p>

<p>log |S 00 | − </p>

<p>T 
2 </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>i=1 log(1 −ˆ i ), whereˆ 1 &gt; · · · &gt;ˆ p Y are the p Y largest solutions 
of the eigenvalue problem </p>

<p>S 11 − S 10 S </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>00 S 01 = 0. 
(4) </p>

<p>Note that since S 11 is p × p and S 00 is p Y × p Y , the rank of S 10 S </p>

<p>−1 </p>

<p>00 S 01 is at most p Y . There-
fore, the eigenvalue problem in equation (4) has p Z = p − p Y zero solutions, thus reducing 
the possible choice of the (maximum) number of co-integration relations from p to p Y . </p>

<p>1 We implicitly assume that Y = Z , which implies c = 0.As stated in HJNR, the special case c = 0 is problematic </p>

<p>since conducting inference on from the conditional model (2) alone would be not only inefficient due to the violation 
of the hypothesis of weak exogeneity, but also inconsistent. 
2 For simplicity, here we consider the case of no deterministic components, i.e. case (i) below equation (1). </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>Henceforth we call the sequential testing procedure based on the conditional model (2) 
and the implied eigenvalue problem in equation (4) 'HJNR's testing procedure'. 
Johansen (1992a) shows that when r = r 0 p Y , if Z t is weakly exogenous for , the con-
ditional model in equation (2) conveys full information on the co-integration relations and 
the maximum likelihood estimator for ( , ) in the partial (conditional) model (2) has the 
same asymptotic efficiency of the full system (unconditional) maximum likelihood estima-
tor. In this case, the asymptotic distribution of HJNR's testing procedure for co-integration 
rank is free of nuisance parameters. Asymptotic critical values have been tabulated under 
such conditions in HJNR. This is no longer the case if the assumption of weak exogeneity, </p>

<p>Z = 0, does not hold. More precisely, when Z = 0, the conditional model does not convey 
all the information on the co-integration relations and maximum likelihood inference on 
based on system (2) is neither fully efficient nor of standard type. However, we will show 
below that when 0 r 0 p Y , it is possible to consistently recover the co-integration rank 
also with Z = 0 by using information criteria. 
Next, we discuss an information criteria-based approach to consistent co-integration 
rank determination that does not require the investigator to take any stand on the weak 
exogeneity condition of Z t with respect to . </p>

<p>III. Information criteria for co-integration rank determination in partial 
systems </p>

<p>We now focus on the conditional partial model (2) and the implied eigenvalue problem dis-
cussed in the previous section. Let IC(r) := −2`T (r) + p T denote an information criterion, 
where p T := c T (r) is a penalty function that depends upon the number of parameters (r) 
and on a term c T , to be specified below. We have that </p>

<p>IC(r) := T log |ˆ c,r | + c T (r) = T log |S 00 | + T </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>log(1 −ˆ i ) + c T (r) 
(5) </p>

<p>where the eigenvaluesˆ i , i = 1,…, r, are determined from equation (4) and (r) := 
r(p Y + p − r) when no deterministic components are involved, (r) := r(p Y + p − r + 1) 
in the case of a restricted constant and (r) := r(p Y + p − r + 1) + p Y in the restricted trend 
case. Different values of the coefficient c T yield different information criteria through the 
resulting penalty function, p T . In particular, as is well-known, c T = 2, log T , and 2 log log T 
yields the AIC, BIC, and HQC, respectively. 
The co-integration rank estimator is then given, in generic form, bŷ </p>

<p>r := arg min </p>

<p>r=0,1,…,p Y </p>

<p>IC(r). 
(6) </p>

<p>Importantly, the determination of the co-integration rank based on the estimator in equation 
(6) exempts practitioners from the use of tables of asymptotic critical values which are 
instead required when sequential testing procedures as in HJNR are applied. 
In the following theorem, we state our main result about the consistency of the infor-
mation criteria. The key requirement is that the penalty term c T diverges at a rate lower 
than T , as T → ∞. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>Theorem 1. Let {X t } be generated as in equation (1) with the true parameters satisfying 
the I(1,r 0 ) conditions. </p>

<p>(a) If r 0 p Y , it holds that, as T → ∞: 
(a.i) for r 0 &lt; r p Y , P(IC(r) &gt; IC(r 0 )) → 1, provided c T → + ∞; 
(a.ii) for 0 r &lt; r 0 , P(IC(r) &gt; IC(r 0 )) → 1, provided c T /T →0. 
(b) If r 0 &gt; p Y , for all r &lt; p Y , as T → ∞, it holds that P(IC(r) &gt; IC(p Y )) → 1, provided 
c T /T →0. </p>

<p>Remark 1. The results in case (a) of Theorem 1 imply that, when r 0 p Y , either BIC or 
HQC penalties in the partial system (2) will yield a weakly consistent estimate of r 0 . The 
AIC will not deliver a consistent estimate of the co-integration rank as its penalty does not 
satisfy condition (a.i) in Theorem 1. Therefore, this criterion will not be considered further. </p>

<p>Remark 2. When r 0 &gt; p Y (case (b) of Theorem 1), i.e. the dimension of the conditional 
system is lower than the true number of co-integration relations in the full system (1), 
only certain linear combinations of the co-integrating vectors can be estimated on the basis 
of the partial model in equation (2). In such cases, the co-integration rank estimator in 
equation (6) will tend to select the maximum possible rank,r = p Y . Therefore, the results 
in Theorem 1 imply that, in general,r will converge to min(r 0 , p Y ). Hence, in the limit 
r = p Y whenever r 0 p Y . </p>

<p>Remark 3. Importantly, inTheorem 1 the determination of the co-integration rank based 
on the estimator in equation (6) does not require Z to be zero in equation (3). That is, our 
approach can be also applied when the variables in Z t adjust to X t−1 , which is a concrete 
possibility in applied work. The practitioner can determine the co-integration rank without 
being concerned about the possible adjustment of Z t to X t−1 . The robustness of BIC and 
HQC to possible violations of weak exogeneity of the conditioning variables allows one to 
fully benefit from reductions of the dimensionality of the system. When r 0 p Y (case (a) of 
Theorem 1), the intuition at the basis of this result is that the asymptotic behaviour of the 
eigenvalues from the determinantal problem (4) is such that, for 0 r p Y , the condition 
IC(r) &gt; IC(r 0 ) holds, under the conditions (a.i) and (a.ii) of Theorem 1, irrespective of 
Z t being weakly exogenous for or not. More precisely, as formally shown in the proof 
of Theorem 1 (see the accompanying online appendix), when r &gt; r 0 , information criteria 
rely on a consistent estimator of the error variance matrix c,r 0 because the eigenvalueŝ </p>

<p>r 0 +1 ,…,ˆ r of the determinantal problem (4) are O p (T 
−1 ). This is valid regardless of the 
weak exogeneity condition. In this case, the difference IC(r) − IC(r 0 ) involves the term 
T </p>

<p>r </p>

<p>i=r 0 +1 log(1 −ˆ i ) which is O p (1), plus a term which diverges under the condition (a.i) 
of Theorem 1, leading to IC(r 0 ) &lt; IC(r). Instead, when r &lt; r 0 p Y , albeit when the weak 
exogeneity condition fails nuisance parameters are involved in the limit distribution of the 
eigenvalues of the determinantal problem (4), there are still r 0 − r positive solutions. In this 
case, the difference IC(r) − IC(r 0 ) involves the term −T </p>

<p>r 0 </p>

<p>i=r+1 log(1 −ˆ i ) which is O p (T ), 
plus a term which converges to zero under the condition (a.ii) of Theorem 1, leading again 
to IC(r 0 ) &lt; IC(r). When r 0 &gt; p Y (case (b) of Theorem 1), the argument is similar. Finally, 
notice that since we do not have any particular restriction on the conditioning variables, Z t 
could also contain co-integrated variables. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>Remark 4. Theorem 1 assumes that the system lag length k in equation (1) is known. 
This assumption, which is often unreasonable in practice, can be relaxed and information 
criteria can be used to determine both the autoregressive lag length and the co-integration 
rank following either a jointly or a sequential procedure (see Cavaliere et al., 2016). More-
over, Aznar and Salvador (2002) provide an approach based on information criteria to also 
determine the form of the deterministic component. While we do not consider the determi-
nation of the system lag order and the choice of the form of the deterministic component 
in this paper, the strategies outlined by Cavaliere et al. (2016) and Aznar and Salvador  (2002), respectively, can also be extended to the present framework. </p>

<p>Remark 5. Given the correct choice of the co-integration rank, the maximum likelihood 
estimator of in the conditional model (2) is still super-consistent (albeit inefficient), but 
the asymptotic distribution theory becomes very difficult, not to say impossible, without 
the assumption of weak exogeneity, see Johansen (1992a), Boswijk (1995), Phillips (1991,  1994) and Phillips and Hansen (1990). This complicates the problem of testing hypotheses 
concerning from the conditional model (2). Johansen (1992a, point (iii), section 4) sug-
gests simulating the distribution involved in the asymptotic tests of hypotheses concerning 
in these cases. </p>

<p>IV. Simulation results </p>

<p>In this section, we investigate the finite sample performance of BIC and HQC in partial sys-
tems through a Monte Carlo experiment which uses large scale systems of p = dim(X t ) = 7 
variables as data generating processes. 
3 In particular, we consider a DGP where the seven-
dimensional process {X t } satisfies the following VAR(2) model with 'true' co-integration 
rank r 0 = 1: </p>

<p>X t = X t−1 + 1 X t−1 + 
+ " t , " t ∼ iidN (0, ), t = 1,…, T 
(7) </p>

<p>where := (a, 0, 0, 0, c, c/ 2, c/ 3), := (1, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0, 0) and 1 := I 7 . 
4 For the sake of 
comparison and with the intention of gathering additional insights, the DGP is chosen by 
extending the Monte Carlo set-up already exploited by Cavaliere et al. (2012), CDRT and  Cavaliere et al. (2016) to the case of larger dimensional VARs. Moreover, in order to fully 
exploit the potential of the conditional analysis we specify a 'full' (and rather arbitrary) 
structure for the covariance matrix such that the resultant matrix in equation (2) is 
non-zero for all DGPs considered. 
5 The initial conditions X −1 and X 0 are fixed to zero. 
Data are generated by setting a = −0.4 and = 0.5. The settings for the parameter c are 
discussed below because in our Monte Carlo design the condition c = 0 is related to the </p>

<p>3 All calculations in this and in the next section have been performed in <rs type="software">OxMetrics</rs> and <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs>. Codes are </p>

<p>available from the authors upon request. 
4 Note that the assumption := (1, 0,…, 0) does not imply any loss of generality. Indeed, any process X t satisfying </p>

<p>equation (1) under the I(1,r 0 ) conditions with r 0 = 1 and = (1, 0,…, 0) can be suitably linearly transformed into the 
new process X </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>t such that 
* X </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>t ∼ I (0) with 
* := (1, 0,…, 0) . The likelihood ratio test is invariant to such rotation. 
5 The matrix has been obtained using the following spectral decomposition: = GDG , where the diagonal </p>

<p>elements of D are generated randomly from a truncated standard normal and the elements of G are generated randomly 
using the standard normal distribution and such that GG = I p . The specific matrix used in our simulations is available 
upon request to the authors. We also considered Monte Carlo experiments based on specifications of leading to 
= 0 in equation (2). Also in this case, results are available upon request to the authors. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>failure of the weak exogeneity of the conditional variables. Samples of length T = 100, 
200 and 1,000 are generated M = 5, 000 times from VARs of the form equation (7) with 
k = 2 lags. </p>

<p>6   For each generated sample, the partial (conditional) system (2) is estimated and the 
procedure for co-integration rank determination discussed in section III is applied. In 
particular, to evaluate the impact of the dimension of the conditioning variable vector Z t 
on the ability of the information criteria to determine the true co-integration rank, we 
consider the partition X t = (Y t , Z t ), where the dimension of Y t ranges from two to four, i.e. 
p Y = 2, 3 and 4, which implies a dimension for Z t of p Z = 5, 4 and 3, respectively. Thus, it 
is seen that the scalar parameter c in the matrix in equation (7) determines whether Z t is 
weakly exogenous (c = 0) or not (c = 0) for . 
We consider two scenarios. In the first scenario, 'A' in the following, the parameter c is 
set to zero hence Z t is weakly exogenous for . In the second scenario, 'B' in the following, 
the parameter c is fixed to </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>. 
7 Consequently, the asymptotic distribution of HJNR's test 
statistic will depend on nuisance parameters and tabulated critical values are no longer valid. 
Within Scenario B, we consider two additional situations which are of potential interest 
for applied work. One is the case where, in addition to the violation of the assumption of 
weak exogeneity, the conditioning set Z t contains co-integrated variables. The other is the 
situation where, in addition to the violation of the assumption of weak exogeneity of Z t , 
VAR disturbances are non-Gaussian and driven by GARCH-type components. </p>

<p>Scenario A: weak exogeneity </p>

<p>The results for the case of weak exogeneity (c = 0 in of equation (7)) are reported in 
Table 1, which summarizes the selection frequencies, i.e. the percentage of times BIC and 
HQC select co-integration rank r = 0,…, p Y in the partial systems out of the M = 5, 000 
Monte Carlo replications. 
8 The finite sample performance of these information criteria are 
compared with that of HJNR's sequential test at the 5% nominal significance level. The 
asymptotic critical values for this test are taken from table 3 of HJNR. Results are also 
compared with those obtained from the (unconditional) full VAR analysis. Specifically, for 
the full system, we consider the BIC and HQC as outlined in CDRT and Johansen's (1996)  sequential trace test for co-integration rank, again at the 5% nominal significance level. 
Results in Table 1 show that, as expected, both information criteria and the HJNR 
tests applied to the partial system overall outperform their 'standard' counterparts from 
the (unconditional) full system when the hypothesis of weak exogeneity is valid. Indeed, 
comparing the results in the three left-panels of Table 1 (partial systems, p Y = 2, 3 and 4) 
with the results in the right-panel of Table 1 (full system, p Y = p = 7 and p Z = 0) we observe </p>

<p>6 For each replication, a sample of T + 200 observations is generated and the first 200 observations are then </p>

<p>discarded. 
7 For given , a = −0.4 and = 0.5, the parameter c cannot be fixed arbitrarily but such that the characteristic </p>

<p>equation associated with the VAR in equation (7) does not generate explosive roots. The value c = 3/ 4 respects such 
a condition. 
8 We do not considerAIC in the Monte Carlo experiments since its poor performance in finite samples is documented </p>

<p>in many contributions in the literature (see e.g. CDRT; Kapetanios, 2004; Wang and Bessler, 2005; Cavaliere et al.,  2016). Additional simulations show that, also in the case of partial system analysis, this criterion tends to severely 
overestimate the true co-integration rank. These results are available upon request to the authors. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>TABLE 1 </p>

<p>Monte Carlo results for 'Scenario A': VAR(2) model with r 0 = 1 with weak exogeneity of Z t </p>

<p>Partial: p Y = 2 
Partial: p Y = 3 
Partial: p Y = 4 
Full: p Y = p = 7 
( p Z = 5) 
( p Z = 4) 
( p Z = 3) 
( p Z = 0) </p>

<p>BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC Johan </p>

<p>T = 100 
r = 0 
0.2 
0.0 
0.0 
0.8 
0.0 
0.0 
1.6 
0.0 
0.1 
12.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 1 
96.8 71.9 
79.1 
95.6 57.9 
70.7 
94.8 50.2 
62.1 
86.7 48.8 
44.4 
r = 2 
3.0 28.1 
20.9 
3.4 35.3 
26.2 
3.5 37.4 
31.1 
1.4 36.2 
36.6 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.1 
6.9 
3.1 
0.1 10.3 
5.8 
0.0 11.5 
13.8 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
2.1 
0.9 
0.0 
2.7 
3.4 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.4 
1.1 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.1 
T = 200 
r = 0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 
99.7 89.7 
88.9 
99.8 82.7 
84.2 
99.9 81.0 
82.4 
100.0 83.5 
75.3 
r = 2 
0.3 10.3 
11.1 
0.2 16.1 
14.6 
0.1 17.3 
15.9 
0.0 15.5 
20.3 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
1.3 
1.2 
0.0 
1.6 
1.5 
0.0 
1.0 
3.6 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.2 
0.2 
0.0 
0.1 
0.6 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
T = 1, 000 
r = 0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 100.0 98.2 
93.9 
100.0 96.8 
93.0 
100.0 97.1 
91.9 
100.0 98.6 
91.1 
r = 2 
0.0 
1.8 
6.1 
0.0 
3.1 
6.6 
0.0 
2.8 
7.5 
0.0 
1.4 
8.0 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.3 
0.0 
0.1 
0.5 
0.0 
0.0 
0.7 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>that the three methods perform better in partial models compared to the (unconditional) 
full system, especially so for HQC and HJNR's sequential test. In particular, when T = 100 
(T = 200), in the full system, HQC and Johansen's sequential test respectively select the 
'true'co-integration rank, r = r 0 = 1, only 48.8% and 44.4% (83.5% and 75.3%) of the time, 
while these percentages increase to 71.9% and 79.1% (89.7% and 88.9%) for HQC and 
HJNR's sequential test, respectively, in the case of a partial system with p Y = 2 and p Z = 5 
(left-panel of Table 1). These results highlight the benefits from analysing the partial system 
in place of the (unconditional) full VAR system in small samples under weak exogeneity. 
In line with the results in CDRT, BIC delivers the best overall performance and correctly 
estimates the 'true' co-integration rank more than 86% of the time in both partial and full 
systems, even when the sample size is relatively small (T = 100) and irrespectively of 
the dimension of the set of conditioning variables Z t . Specifically, when T = 100, BIC 
correctly estimates r = r 0 96.8%, 95.6% and 94.8% of the time for p Y = 2, 3 and 4 (p Z = 5, 
4 and 3), respectively, while the percentages for T = 200 and T = 1000 are substantially 
constant over the different dimensions of the conditioning set. Conversely, HQC appears to </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>be more affected than BIC by the dimension of the conditioning set when the sample size 
is relatively small, namely when T = 100 and T = 200: the larger the dimension of Z t , p Z , 
the better its finite sample performance. HJNR's sequential test performs similarly to HQC 
in partial systems. For instance, when T = 200, HJNR's sequential test correctly estimates 
the 'true' co-integration rank 88.9%, 84.2% and 82.4% of the time, against 89.7%, 82.7% 
and 81% of the time for HQC, when p Y = 2, 3 and 4, respectively. </p>

<p>Scenario B: no weak exogeneity </p>

<p>In this scenario, we evaluate the impact of the lack of weak exogeneity of the conditioning 
variables on the performance of the methods for co-integration rank determination in partial 
systems. Since such an hypothesis is difficult to test in practice, it is interesting to quan-
tify possible drawbacks associated with a partial system analysis, when the conditioning 
variables Z t are not weakly exogenous. Table 2 reports, for the case of no weak exogeneity 
(c = </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>in of equation (7)), the estimated selection probabilities, i.e. the percentage of 
times BIC and HQC select r = 0,…, p Y , respectively, for p Y = 2, 3 and 4. Also in this case, 
we sketch the estimated selection probabilities associated with HJNR's sequential test and, 
as in the previous scenario, we also consider co-integration rank determination using the 
(unconditional) full system (right-panel of Table 2). 
Although it clearly outperforms both HQC and Johansen's sequential procedure in the 
full system analysis (see the results in the right-panel of Table 2), the results in the left-
panels of Table 2 show that, when weak exogeneity does not hold, the performance of BIC 
deteriorates considerably when the sample size is relatively small, as it tends to underes-
timate the true co-integration rank. In particular, when T = 100 (T = 200) the selection 
frequency of the 'true' rank for BIC drops to 41.4%, 33.4% and 27.7% (80.1%, 71.1% 
and 63.2%) for p Y = 2, 3 and 4, respectively. As predicted by the results in Theorem 1, this 
effect tends to disappear as T increases: similarly to the case of weak exogeneity in Table 1, 
when T = 1, 000 BIC always selects r = r 0 = 1, even when the weak exogeneity hypothesis 
is not valid. Conversely, the HQC performs similarly to the case of weak exogeneity and 
still outperforms its counterpart in the (unconditional) full system (right-panel of Table 
2). In particular, HQC selects r = r 0 = 1 only 49.7% (82.8%) of the time in the full system 
when T = 100 (T = 200), while these frequencies are 69.5%, 57.2% and 52.5% (89.6%, 
84% and 83%) in partial systems for p Y = 2, 3 and 4, respectively. Moreover, these results 
are very close to (and, in some cases, even outperform) the corresponding results under 
weak exogeneity (cf. Table 1). These results highlight that the HQC is not severely affected 
by the violation of the weak exogeneity hypothesis of the conditioning set. Quite surpris-
ingly, also the performance of the HJNR's sequential test does not appear to be strongly 
affected by the lack of weak exogeneity of Z t as we would expect, given that the critical 
values reported in table 5 of HJNR are tabulated under the weak exogeneity assumption. 
Moreover, HJNR's sequential test displays a less marked tendency to overestimate the 'true' 
co-integration rank than Johansen's sequential procedure in the (unconditional) full sys-
tem, thus leading to a better overall performance also in the case of no weak exogeneity. In 
particular, Johansen's sequential test selects r = r 0 = 1 only 45.5% (74%) of the time when 
T = 100 (T = 200), while the corresponding selection frequencies in partial systems for 
HJNR's sequential test are 69.3%, 62.1% and 57.9% (88.4%, 85.4% and 81.8%) in the case </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>TABLE 2 </p>

<p>Monte Carlo results for 'Scenario B': VAR(2) model with r 0 = 1 without weak exogeneity of Z t </p>

<p>Partial: p Y = 2 
Partial: p Y = 3 
Partial: p Y = 4 
Full: p Y = p = 7 
( p Z = 5) 
( p Z = 4) 
( p Z = 3) 
( p Z = 0) </p>

<p>BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC Johan </p>

<p>T = 100 
r = 0 
57.7 
8.7 
15.2 
65.4 
9.7 
16.4 
71.4 
8.8 
14.9 
13.5 
0.1 
0.2 
r = 1 
41.4 69.5 
69.3 
33.4 57.2 
62.1 
27.7 52.5 
57.9 
85.2 49.7 
45.5 
r = 2 
1.0 21.7 
15.4 
1.2 28.0 
19.4 
1.0 30.4 
22.8 
1.2 36.3 
36.1 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
5.1 
2.2 
0.0 
6.9 
3.8 
0.0 11.2 
13.5 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
1.4 
0.6 
0.0 
2.0 
3.4 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.4 
0.9 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.3 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.2 
0.1 
T = 200 
r = 0 
19.7 
0.4 
0.8 
28.7 
1.0 
1.9 
36.7 
1.1 
3.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 
80.1 89.6 
88.4 
71.1 84.0 
85.4 
63.2 83.0 
81.8 
100.0 82.8 
74.0 
r = 2 
0.3 10.0 
10.7 
0.2 14.1 
11.7 
0.1 14.6 
13.7 
0.0 15.4 
21.5 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
0.9 
0.9 
0.0 
1.2 
1.2 
0.0 
1.6 
3.6 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.2 
0.0 
0.1 
0.7 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
T = 1, 000 
r = 0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 100.0 97.6 
93.6 
100.0 96.7 
92.9 
100.0 97.1 
91.9 
100.0 98.6 
91.3 
r = 2 
0.0 
2.4 
6.4 
0.0 
3.3 
6.6 
0.0 
2.8 
7.2 
0.0 
1.4 
7.6 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.5 
0.0 
0.1 
0.8 
0.0 
0.0 
0.9 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.2 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>of p Y = 2, 3 and 4, respectively. Furthermore, as in the case of weak exogeneity (Table 1), 
the empirical performance of HJNR's sequential test and HQC in partial systems are simi-
lar. As such, these two methods usefully complement each other in practice and are rather 
robust to violations of the hypothesis of weak exogeneity. </p>

<p>9   We consider a further case which, in addition to the violation of the weak exogeneity 
hypothesis, allows Z t to contain co-integrated variables. In particular, we add a further 
co-integration relation in model (7), ceteris paribus, by specifying </p>

<p>:= 
a 
0 0 0 
c 
c/2 
c/ 3 
−a/ 2 0 0 0 −0.5 −0.3 0.25 
and := 
1 0 0 0 0 0 0 
0 0 0 0 0 1 −1 
,   9 It is also interesting to stress that the finite sample behaviour of BIC is the one which is more sensitive to the </p>

<p>extent of the violation from weak exogeneity: The larger the value of c in in equation (7), the worse its performance 
for small T . However, as expected from a theoretical viewpoint and in line with the results in Table 2, the tendency 
for BIC to underestimate the true co-integration rank in partial systems with no weak exogeneity disappears as T 
increases. Conversely, HQC and HJNR's sequential test are robust in finite samples to departures from the weak 
exogeneity assumption. Results for different values of c are available from the authors upon request. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>where, as in the previous case of Scenario B, we set a = −0.4 and c = </p>

<p>3 
4 </p>

<p>. In this case, we have 
that the last two variables in X t (and in Z t ) co-integrate among themselves, so that the true 
co-integration rank is r 0 = 2. The selection frequencies of r = 0,…, p Y for BIC, HQC and 
HJNR's sequential procedure in partial systems of dimension p Y = 2, 3 and 4 are reported 
in the left-panels of Table 3, whereas the results obtained from the (unconditional) full 
VAR analysis are reported in the right-panel of Table 3. Results in Table 3 show that, also in 
the case when Z t contains co-integrated variables, HQC and HJNR's sequential procedure 
provide satisfactory results in partial systems, especially when p Z is large, outperforming 
their analogues in the (unconditional) full system, even when the sample size is small. 
Conversely, when T = 100 and 200, BIC tends to underestimate the true co-integration 
rank and its performance in partial systems is worse than that obtained from the full 
system analysis. 
Therefore, the story we learn from Table 2 and Table 3 is that when the conditioning 
variables are not weakly exogenous for the co-integration parameters and in samples of 
lengths typically available to practitioners, HQC and HJNR's sequential procedures (but 
not BIC) perform in partial systems no worse than their analogues perform in full systems. 
Thus, despite ignoring the marginal model for Z t may imply a loss of information on 
the adjustment mechanisms at work in the whole system, with HQC the reduction of 
dimensionality tends to fully compensate the possible loss of power in co-integration rank 
determination from the conditional system. 
As we noticed in section II, co-integration rank determination in partial systems can 
potentially be extended to the case of conditional heteroscedasticity along the lines of 
Cavaliere et al. (2010) and CDRT. 
10 When the actual unconditional probability distribution 
of " t in system (1) is non-Gaussian, it is still in principle possible to factorize the density of 
X t as the product of the conditional density for Y t given Z t and the marginal density for Z t . 
However, the dynamic structure of the conditional system might not necessarily conform 
to that in equation (2) and the parametric restrictions under which Z t is weakly exogenous 
for might become more involved. It turns out that checking the robustness of the HQC 
and BIC to conditional heteroscedasticity in partial systems is crucial for applied work. We 
perform such robustness check by considering the same DGP as in Table 2 but specifying 
the innovation process " t in equation (7) as a CCC-GARCH (Bollerslev, 1990) process, i.e., </p>

<p>" t =H </p>

<p>1/ 2 
t </p>

<p>t , 
t ∼ iidN (0, I p ) 
H t :=D t RD t = ( ij h it h jt ) </p>

<p>D t :=diag(h </p>

<p>1/ 2 </p>

<p>1t ,…, h </p>

<p>1/ 2 </p>

<p>pt ) 
h it =d 0,i + d 1 " </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>it−1 + d 2 h it−1 , i = 1,…, p 
R :=( ij ), ii = 1, i, j = 1,…, p </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>10 Cavaliere et al. (2010) show that the extension to conditional heteroscedasticity is allowed as long as that </p>

<p>the innovations {" t } in equation (1) (i) form a martingale difference sequence with respect to the filtration F t := 
(X t ,…, X t−1 ), where F t−1 ⊆ F t for t =…, − 1, 0, 1, 2,…, (ii) satisfy the condition E " t </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>K &lt; ∞, · being the 
Euclidean norm, and (iii) fulfil the global homoscedasticity condition: </p>

<p>1 
T </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>E " t " t |F t−1 </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>→ &gt; 0. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>TABLE 3 </p>

<p>Monte Carlo results for 'Scenario B': VAR(2) model with r 0 = 2 without weak exogeneity of 
Z t (and Z t contains co-integrated variables) </p>

<p>Partial: p Y = 2 
Partial: p Y = 3 
Partial: p Y = 4 
Full: p Y = p = 7 
( p Z = 5) 
( p Z = 4) 
( p Z = 3) 
( p Z = 0) </p>

<p>BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC Johan </p>

<p>T = 100 
r = 0 
22.1 
0.5 
0.7 
21.5 
0.2 
0.7 
27.8 
0.4 
0.8 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 
57.1 
25.8 
33.5 
53.6 14.5 
28.0 
54.8 16.3 
28.9 
52.2 
1.2 
3.7 
r = 2 
20.8 
73.7 
65.8 
24.1 67.9 
61.1 
16.8 57.4 
56.9 
46.9 56.2 
58.7 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.8 17.4 
10.2 
0.6 21.6 
11.9 
0.9 32.1 
28.6 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
4.2 
1.5 
0.0 
8.2 
7.0 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
1.7 
1.5 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.4 
0.3 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.2 
0.2 
T = 200 
r = 0 
0.8 
0.0 
0.0 
0.3 
0.0 
0.0 
0.7 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 
36.5 
2.9 
2.7 
25.4 
0.9 
2.2 
35.4 
1.3 
3.8 
1.1 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 2 
62.8 
97.1 
97.3 
74.1 89.2 
89.1 
63.8 84.6 
86.1 
98.9 84.4 
82.4 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.2 10.0 
8.7 
0.1 13.1 
9.3 
0.0 14.2 
15.1 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
1.0 
0.8 
0.0 
1.3 
2.1 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.2 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
T = 1, 000 
r = 0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 2 100.0 100.0 100.0 100.0 97.8 
94.5 
100.0 96.6 
94.1 
100.0 98.0 
92.8 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
2.2 
5.5 
0.0 
3.3 
5.5 
0.0 
2.0 
6.5 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.4 
0.0 
0.0 
0.6 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>where H t = E(" t " t |F t−1 ) is the conditional variance of " t , F t := (X t ,…, X t−1 ) is the filtration 
at time t and R is a symmetric positive definite matrix containing the constant conditional 
correlations ij . 
11 Results are reported in Table 4. By comparing selection frequencies in 
Table 4 with those in Table 2, we observe that the CCC-GARCH(1,1) disturbances have 
only a limited impact on the finite sample ability of information criteria (as well as HJNR's 
sequential procedure) to correctly select co-integration rank. This evidence confirms, as 
expected, the results already documented by Cavaliere et al. (2010) and CDRT in the full 
system framework. 
In summary, the results of our Monte Carlo simulations in scenarios A and B show 
that the benefits of combining information criteria with partial system analyses can be 
substantial and usefully complement HJNR's sequential test approach in practice. More-</p>

<p>11 Data are generated by using the same specification of , and 1 as in Table 2. As concerns the CCC-GARCH </p>

<p>part, we draw the coefficients ij (i = j) from independent uniform distributions with support (−1, 1) and set the 
GARCH parameters in equation (8) to d 1 = 0.05, d 2 = 0.94 and d 0, i = 1 − 0.1(i − 1), i = 1,…, p. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>TABLE 4 </p>

<p>Monte Carlo results for 'Scenario B': VAR(2) model with r 0 = 1, CCC-GARCH(1,1) innovations and 
without weak exogeneity of Z t </p>

<p>Partial: p Y = 2 
Partial: p Y = 3 
Partial: p Y = 4 
Full: p Y = p = 7 
( p Z = 5) 
( p Z = 4) 
( p Z = 3) 
( p Z = 0) </p>

<p>BIC HQC HJNR BIC HQC HJNR BIC HQC HJNR BIC 
HQC Johan </p>

<p>T = 100 
r = 0 59.2 22.9 
29.1 
51.4 14.1 
19.7 
45.6 
8.9 
12.6 
0.4 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 39.7 58.5 
57.5 
46.4 53.1 
58.1 
51.9 49.6 
55.4 
97.1 42.9 
38.7 
r = 2 
1.1 18.6 
13.3 
2.1 27.2 
19.5 
2.4 30.8 
26.7 
2.4 38.4 
38.2 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
5.6 
2.8 
0.0 
9.1 
4.7 
0.1 14.1 
16.6 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
1.6 
0.6 
0.0 
3.2 
4.3 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.9 
1.5 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.4 
0.6 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.2 
0.2 
T = 200 
r = 0 50.6 23.5 
24.8 
39.9 13.6 
15.0 
32.2 
8.5 
9.3 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 49.1 68.4 
66.5 
59.7 71.7 
71.6 
67.6 73.5 
73.2 
99.8 79.9 
70.5 
r = 2 
0.2 
8.0 
8.7 
0.4 13.7 
12.4 
0.2 15.9 
15.7 
0.2 17.8 
23.2 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
1.0 
1.0 
0.0 
2.0 
1.6 
0.0 
2.1 
5.0 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.1 
0.1 
0.0 
0.2 
0.9 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.2 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.1 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
T = 1, 000 
r = 0 23.1 10.2 
8.4 
11.8 
3.2 
2.7 
6.1 
1.3 
1.1 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 1 76.9 87.1 
84.2 
88.1 92.2 
87.7 
93.9 93.3 
87.3 
100.0 95.7 
84.1 
r = 2 
0.0 
2.6 
7.4 
0.1 
4.6 
9.2 
0.0 
5.1 
10.6 
0.0 
4.2 
13.8 
r = 3 
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.5 
0.0 
0.3 
1.0 
0.0 
0.1 
1.7 
r = 4 
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
0.3 
r = 5 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 6 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 
r = 7 
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
-
0.0 
0.0 
0.0 </p>

<p>over, the results in scenarios A and B also show that the HJNR's sequential test does not 
appear to be severely affected by violations of the weak exogeneity hypothesis, even though 
the asymptotic distribution of the involved test statistics depends on nuisance parameters 
and tabulated critical values are no longer valid. It is worth remarking that HQC and BIC 
in partial systems perform reasonably well in small samples also under deviations from 
normality induced by GARCH-type innovations. </p>

<p>V. Empirical illustrations </p>

<p>Despite conditional (possibly uni-equational) error-correction models have been used ex-
tensively in the literature (e.g. Urbain, 1992), only seldom the partial system approach 
to co-integration rank determination has been applied in empirical works. Doornik et al.  (1998), Bårdsen, Jansen and Nymoen (2003) and Bruggeman et al. (2003) are some of 
the few examples where HJNR's testing procedure is implemented. As already observed, </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>two main difficulties characterize the use of HJNR's sequential test in applied work. First, 
it is generally difficult to select a priori the vector Z t of weakly exogenous conditioning 
variables. Second, testing weak exogeneity of Z t efficiently requires either a full-system 
approach or the analysis of the marginal model for Z t , see e.g. Urbain (1992), Boswijk  (1995), Ericsson (1995) and Boswijk and Urbain (1997). In both cases the benefits of the 
partial system analysis are nullified. 
In the previous sections, we have shown that we can use BIC and/or HQC to determine 
co-integration rank in the conditional model Y t given Z t in equation (2), without being 
concerned about the weak exogeneity of Z t . Moreover, the Monte Carlo results show that 
the finite sample performance of BIC and HQC in the conditional model Y t given Z t 
is generally not worse than the empirical performance of the BIC and HQC in the full 
system for X t := (Y t , Z t ) regardless of whether VAR disturbances are Gaussian or driven 
by GARCH-type components. In this section, we illustrate the advantages of our approach 
by two empirical examples, both based on the estimation of VAR models on US quarterly 
data. 
In the first empirical example (section 'Large-dimensional VAR'), we consider a rela-
tively large-scale VAR system estimated on quarterly data relative to the 'Great Modera- tion' period, 1984Q1-2008Q2. The idea in this case is to show that, other than reducing 
the dimensionality of the system, the partial system approach combined with the use of 
information criteria can be useful for co-integration rank determination. In particular, it is 
argued that in the absence of clear theoretical guidances about the number of stochastic 
trends in X t := (Y t , Z t ), one useful empirical specification strategy is to start the analysis 
by including in Z t time series that are not supposed to co-integrate. Indeed, although Z t can 
be co-integrated in our approach (see Remark 3 and the Monte Carlo results in Table 3), 
in large systems it can be relatively easier to make conjectures on which time series should 
not co-integrate rather than on the variables which should be weakly exogenous. Given 
different choices of the candidate Z t vector, the empirical illustration shows that our em-
pirical specification strategy, combined with BIC and HQC, simplifies co-integration rank 
determination. 
In the second empirical example (section 'Small-scale DSGE model'), we investigate 
the co-integration/common-trend implications of a small-scale DSGE model for the US 
business cycle. We show that our approach can be advantageous compared to the full system 
analysis when the researcher does not want to take any explicit modelling stand on one 
of the time series that contributes to the system's long-run equilibrium. More specifically, 
the DSGE model we consider features the natural rate of output, which is a variable that 
captures a highly theoretical concept, difficult to characterize in applied work. We show 
that it is convenient to treat (proxy of the) natural rate of output as a conditioning variable, 
disregarding whether it is weakly exogeneous or not. </p>

<p>Large-dimensional VAR </p>

<p>We consider a vector X t containing seven US quarterly macroeconomic variables, which 
includes (the log of) non-durable personal real consumption, cnd t , (the log of) durable per-
sonal real consumption, cd t , (the log of) fixed-private real investments, i t , (the log of) the real 
gross domestic product (GDP), y t , the inflation rate, inf t , the federal funds rate, f t , and the </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 </p>

<p>-520 </p>

<p>-518 </p>

<p>-516 </p>

<p>-514 </p>

<p>-512 </p>

<p>-510 </p>

<p>-508 </p>

<p>cnd -y </p>

<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 </p>

<p>-715.0 </p>

<p>-712.5 </p>

<p>-710.0 </p>

<p>-707.5 </p>

<p>-705.0 </p>

<p>-702.5 </p>

<p>-700.0 </p>

<p>-697.5 </p>

<p>-695.0 </p>

<p>-692.5 </p>

<p>cd -y </p>

<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 
2010 </p>

<p>-660 </p>

<p>-655 </p>

<p>-650 </p>

<p>-645 </p>

<p>-640 </p>

<p>-635 </p>

<p>i -y </p>

<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>1.50 </p>

<p>1.75 </p>

<p>2.00 </p>

<p>2.25 </p>

<p>2.50 </p>

<p>R-inf </p>

<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>R -ff </p>

<p>1985 
1990 
1995 
2000 
2005 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>ff -inf </p>

<p>Figure 1. The 'great ratios' (cnd t − y t ), (cd t − y t ) and (i t − y t ), the (ex post) real interest rates (R t − inf t ), 
(ff t − inf t ) and the interest rate spread (R t − ff t ), US economy, period 1984Q1-2008Q2. </p>

<p>10 year-Treasury Bill rate, R t . The macroeconomic literature has recently documented a 
dramatic fall in the variances of the main macroeconomic time series, which has been 
termed 'Great Moderation'. Kim and Nelson (1999) and Stock and Watson (2002) offer 
support for a break in the macroeconomic volatilities around 1984. McConnell and Perez- Quiros (2000) identify 1984Q1 as the breakdate of the variance of the US real GDP. Boivin  and Giannoni (2006) also detect a break in the coefficients of a reduced-form VAR for 
the US economy in the early 1980s. In line with this literature, we identify the beginning 
and the end of the 'Great Moderation' sample with the dates 1984Q1 and 2008Q2, respec-
tively, for a total of T + k = 98 quarterly observations, where k is the VAR lag order for 
X t := (cnd t , cd t , i t , y t , inf t , f t , R t ) . The end of the sample, 2008Q2, is justified by our decision 
to avoid dealing with the acceleration of the financial crisis and, above all, with the binding 
zero-lower bound (ZLB) that has kicked in since the end of 2008. 
Figure 1 plots the 'great ratios' cnd t − y t , cd t − y t and i t − y t , the (ex post) real interest 
rate, R t − inf t , the interest rate differential, R t − f t , and the (ex post) real version of the 
policy rate, f t − inf t , on the period 1984Q1-2008Q2. According to neoclassical theory, 
under balanced growth there should be a common stochastic trend driving cnd t , cd t , i t and 
y t , and the 'great ratios'cnd t − y t , cd t − y t and i t − y t should be stationary (King et al., 1991). 
Also the interest rates R t , f t and the inflation rate inf t should be driven by a single (common) 
stochastic trend while the (ex post) real interest rates and the interest rate differential should 
be stationary. The simple graphical inspection of Figure 1 suggests, however, that aside </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>perhaps from cd t − y t , the 'great ratios' do not seem fully consistent with stationary (or 
trend-stationary) patterns on the period 1984Q1-2008Q2. In particular, the fluctuations of 
cnd t − y t around a possible linear trend and of i t − y t around a constant level do not line 
up with the typical persistence of stationary, mean-reverting processes. Moreover, only 
the interest rate differential, R t − f t , appears to be stationary (although highly persistent) 
around a constant level, while the (ex post) real interest rates R t − inf t and f t − inf t display 
some trending behaviour (which can partially be explained in terms of the 'aggressive' 
monetary policy undertaken by the Fed to fight inflation since the end of the seventies). 
All this evidence is consistent with the view that it was the change in conduct of monetary 
policy undertaken by the Fed at the end of the seventies/beginning of the eighties that 
'stabilized' the US economy through an aggressive behaviour against inflation. In line with 
the 'Great Moderation' explanation of the US business cycle (Clarida, Galì and Gertler, 
2000), one can hardly claim that there are only two common stochastic trends (i.e. five 
co-integrating relations) driving the variables in X t . Rather, it would seem reasonable to 
expect the presence of not more than three co-integrating relationships in the 1984Q1-
2008Q2 period, corresponding to the existence of at least four common stochastic trends 
in X t . Given our purposes, we prefer not to take any stand about the possible additional 
co-integration relation other than cd t − y t and R t − f t . 
We start our empirical analysis by estimating a VAR for X t := (cnd t , cd t , i t , y t , inf t , f t , R t ) 
(p = 7) with four lags (k = 4) and a restricted linear trend, which corresponds to the case 
(iii) D t = t, d t = 1 in system (1). The model with restricted linear trend allows for trend-
stationary co-integration relationships, which can be an interesting case given the time 
series patterns observed in Figure 1. Notice that the full system analysis is carried out 
for comparative purposes only, namely to check whether we obtain significant differences 
in the co-integration rank determination with respect to the partial system approach. The 
right-panel of Table 5 reports results from Johansen's (1996) sequential co-integration 
rank procedure at the 5% nominal (asymptotic) level and using BIC and HQC. We select 
co-integration ranks of 4 (Johansen's test), 2 (BIC) and 4 (HQC), respectively. 
Given the relatively large dimension of X t and the relatively small number of observa-
tions, we investigate whether a partial system analysis delivers a different co-integration 
rank. Consider, for instance, the following partition of X t : X t = (Y t , Z t ) , with Y t := 
(cnd t , cd t , R t , y t , f t ) (p Y = 5) and Z t := (i t , inf t ) (p Z = 2). In this case, we have included in Z t 
as initial step of the analysis a set of conditioning variables (the fixed-private investments 
and the inflation rate) which are expected to be I(1) but not co-integrated. Albeit Z t can 
potentially be co-integrated in our setup (see Remark 3 and Table 3), our suggestion is 
that it may be convenient to start the analysis with this choice because it is often easier 
to make conjectures on which variables are likely to be no co-integrated, rather than on 
which variables should not adjust to the long run equilibria. Modelling Y t conditional on 
Z t requires considering a five-dimensional system as in equation (2) and, notably, we can 
apply BIC and HQC ignoring the weak exogeneity condition of Z t . Results are reported in 
the middle panel of Table 5, which also reports, for completeness, the outcome of HJNR's 
sequential procedure. Although the asymptotic critical values associated with HJNR's test 
are computed under the assumption of weak exogeneity of Z t , the Monte Carlo evidence 
summarized in Tables 1-4 has shown that HJNR's test performs reasonably well in samples 
of length T = 100 irrespective of whether Z t is weakly exogenous or not (or co-integrated or </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>TABLE 5 </p>

<p>Empirical results for the large-scale VAR on US macroeconomic variables </p>

<p>Partial: Z 
t := (cnd </p>

<p>t , i 
t , inf 
t ) ( p 
Z = 3) </p>

<p>Partial: Z 
t := (i </p>

<p>t , inf 
t ) ( p 
Z = 2) </p>

<p>Full: p 
Y = p 
= 7 ( p 
Z = 0) </p>

<p>HJNR 
(5% c.v.) </p>

<p>BIC </p>

<p>HQC </p>

<p>HJNR 
(5% c.v.) </p>

<p>BIC </p>

<p>HQC </p>

<p>Johan 
(5% c.v.) </p>

<p>BIC </p>

<p>HQC </p>

<p>r 
= 0 </p>

<p>138.3 </p>

<p>(89.2) </p>

<p>−1, 150.4 </p>

<p>−1, 150.4 </p>

<p>173.8 </p>

<p>(108.0) 
−1, 365.5 </p>

<p>−1, 365.5 </p>

<p>247.1 </p>

<p>(146.7) 
−1, 678.4 </p>

<p>−1, 678.4 </p>

<p>r 
= 1 </p>

<p>70.5 </p>

<p>(62.9) </p>

<p>−1,168.2 
−1, 184.9 </p>

<p>105.0 </p>

<p>(80.9) </p>

<p>−1,379.7 
−1, 397.9 </p>

<p>168.7 </p>

<p>(114.9) 
−1, 693.2 </p>

<p>−1, 714.5 </p>

<p>r 
= 2 </p>

<p>37.9 </p>

<p>(39.9) </p>

<p>−1, 159.9 </p>

<p>−1, 190.2 </p>

<p>61.5 </p>

<p>(56.3) 
−1, 377.9 </p>

<p>−1, 411.2 </p>

<p>104.5 </p>

<p>(86.9) </p>

<p>−1,702.9 
−1, 742.3 </p>

<p>r 
= 3 </p>

<p>12.2 </p>

<p>(20.7) </p>

<p>−1, 153.9 </p>

<p>−1,194.8 </p>

<p>29.1 </p>

<p>(35.5) 
−1, 373.9 </p>

<p>−1,419.4 </p>

<p>64.9 </p>

<p>(62.6) 
−1, 697.0 </p>

<p>−1, 751.5 </p>

<p>r 
= 4 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>−1, 143.3 </p>

<p>−1, 191.8 </p>

<p>12.0 </p>

<p>(17.9) 
−1, 363.7 </p>

<p>−1, 418.2 </p>

<p>33.4 </p>

<p>(42.2) 
−1, 692.2 </p>

<p>−1,758.9 </p>

<p>r 
= 5 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>−1, 357.5 </p>

<p>−1, 418.2 </p>

<p>19.9 </p>

<p>(25.5) 
−1, 678.4 </p>

<p>−1, 754.2 </p>

<p>r 
= 6 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>7.8 </p>

<p>(12.4) 
−1, 672.3 </p>

<p>−1, 754.2 </p>

<p>r 
= 7 </p>

<p>= p </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>−1, 671.1 </p>

<p>−1, 756.0 </p>

<p>Notes: Results from the partial and full system analyses of X </p>

<p>t := (cnd </p>

<p>t , cd </p>

<p>t , i 
t , y 
t , inf </p>

<p>t , f 
t , R 
t ) (p 
= 7). VAR model with k 
= 4 lags and restricted trend. The 5% c.v. for </p>

<p>HJNR's test are taken from table 3 of Harbo et al. (1998) and the 5% c.v. for Johansen's test ('Johan') are taken from tables 15.3 and 15.4 of Johansen (1996). The selected 
co-integration rank according to the test/criterion used are denoted in bold. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>not). The results in the middle panel of Table 5 show that we select co-integration ranks of 3 
(HJNR), 1 (BIC) and 3 (HQC), respectively. Therefore, we observe a systematic reduction 
of the co-integration rank compared to the (unconditional) full system analysis. 
We repeat the co-integration rank determination analysis by changing the choice of Y t 
and Z t , in particular using Y t := (cd t , R t , y t , f t ) (p Y = 4) and Z t := (cnd t , i t , inf t ) (p Z = 3). In 
this case, the partial system for Y t given Z t in equation (2) is four-dimensional. Results are 
summarized in the left-panel of Table 4. We select co-integration rank 2 (HJNR), 1 (BIC) 
and 3 (HQC), respectively. 
Overall, the partial system approach combined with the use of BIC and HQC suggests 
that the selected co-integration rank does not exceed the rank a practitioner would select 
by using the full system. The inference we have obtained with the conditional model seems 
in line with the idea that there should be no more than three co-integration relationships 
in X t over the period 1984Q1-2008Q2. More precisely, the application of the HQC on the 
conditional models Y t given Z t provides clear and robust indications that, as expected, X t is 
driven by at least four common stochastic trends. It is worth stressing that this conclusion is 
obtained without any assumption about the weak exogeneity of the conditioning variables 
included in Z t . 
To complete our analysis, we test whether the hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t := 
(i t , inf t ) (p Z = 2) and then of Z t := (cnd t , i t , inf t ) (p Z = 3) is supported by the data when 
the co-integration rank is fixed at r = 3 as suggested by the partial system approach. To 
do so, we estimate the full VAR for X t := (cnd t , cd t , i t , y t , inf t , f t , R t ) , fix the co-integration 
rank to r = 3 and then test the corresponding zero restrictions on the matrix, given . 
The likelihood-ratio test for the null hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t := (i t , inf t ) is 37.4 
and implies the rejection of the null at the 5% nominal level. Likewise, the likelihood-ratio 
test for the null hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t := (cnd t , i t , inf t ) equals 55.9 and also 
leads to reject the null considering the 5% nominal level. 
Finally, we observe that the empirical evidence summarized in Table 5 is consistent 
with the Monte Carlo evidence discussed in section IV. For instance, the results for the full 
system analysis reported in Table 2 (Scenario B) suggest that for small values of r 0 relative 
to p and in samples of length T = 100, HQC and Johansen's test tend to select co-integration 
rank larger than the true one, while BIC tends to select the true co-integration rank more 
accurately. On the other hand, HQC and HJNR's procedure improve considerably their 
selection performance in the partial system approach and become more powerful than 
BIC, which in turn tends to underestimate the true co-integration rank. Based on these 
considerations, the conclusion from the partial system approach that the co-integration 
rank is 3 appears a sensible one. </p>

<p>Small-scale DSGE model </p>

<p>We consider the small-scale DSGE monetary model of Benati and Surico (2009), also 
estimated in Bårdsen and Fanelli (2015). The structural model features the following equa-
tions:x </p>

<p>t = E txt+1 + (1 − )x t−1 − (i t − E t t+1 ) + x,t 
(9) </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>t = 
1 + 
E t t+1 + 
1 + 
t−1 + x t + ,t 
(10) </p>

<p>i t = i t−1 + (1 − )( 
t + xxt ) + i,t 
(11) </p>

<p>a,t = a a,t−1 + u a,t , − 1 &lt; a &lt; 1, u a,t ∼ WN(0, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>a ), a =x, , i 
(12) </p>

<p>and expectations are conditional on the agents' information set F t , i.e. E t · := E(· | F t ). The 
first equation is a forward-looking IS curve, the second is the New Keynesian Phillips 
curve and the third is the policy rule through which the Central Bank fixes the short 
term interest rate.x t = (x t − x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) is the output gap, where x t is the log of output and x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t the 
natural rate of output; t is the inflation rate and i t is the nominal policy interest rate; a,t , 
a =x, , i, are stochastic disturbances autocorrelated of order one, while u a,t , a =x, , i, 
can be interpreted as demand, supply and monetary shocks, respectively. The structural 
parameters are collected in the vector = ( , , , , , , , x , x , , i , </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x , 
2 , </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i ) and 
their economic interpretation may be found in Benati and Surico (2009). Notice that system 
(9)-(12) does not specify how the natural rate of output is generated. To complete the model, 
we assume that x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t obeys the equation 
x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t = (i t−1 − t−1 ) + x n ,t , 
x n ,t ∼ WN(0, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x n ) 
(13) </p>

<p>where 
0 is an additional auxiliary parameter. When = 0, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t in equation (13) follows 
a driftless random walk which captures the effects of technology shocks and represents 
the I(1) stochastic trend driving system. With &lt; 0, instead, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t is still I(1) but the natural 
growth rate of output is negatively tied to the level of the (ex post) real interest rate. 
System (9)-(13) with = 0 is analysed in Bårdsen and Fanelli (2015) to investi-
gate the testable implications of small DSGE models, including their common trend/co-
integration properties. The appealing feature of system (9)-(13) is that, under particular 
conditions, the rational expectations solution of the DSGE model can be approximated by 
a four-dimensional (p = 4) co-integrated VAR system for X t := (x t , t , i t , x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) . More specif-
ically, the testable co-integration implications of this DSGE model are captured by the 
term˜ </p>

<p>X t−1 := </p>

<p>1 0 0 −1 
0 1 0 
0 
0 0 1 
0 </p>

<p>⎛ </p>

<p>⎜ 
⎝ </p>

<p>x t−1 </p>

<p>t−1 </p>

<p>i t−1 
x </p>

<p>n 
t−1 </p>

<p>⎞ </p>

<p>⎟ 
⎠ 
(14) </p>

<p>which implies (true) co-integration rank r 0 = 3, and requires the 'output gap' x t − x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t , the 
inflation rate t and the policy rate i t to be jointly stationary. Moreover, it can be shown 
that when = 0 in equation (13), the variable x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t does not adjust to the three co-integrating 
relations, i.e. it is weakly exogenous with respect to =˜ in equation (14). In contrast, 
when &lt; 0, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t adjusts to the inflation rate and the policy rate. Equation (14) suggests that if 
the solution of the DSGE model (9)-(13) is captured by a VAR model for X t = (x t , t , i t , x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) , 
the system should be driven by a single stochastic trend representing the cumulated effects 
of technology shocks. 
In this model, the natural rate of output x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t enters the co-integration relations in equation 
(14). However, a practitioner might not be interested in modelling x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t directly within the </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>VAR framework. Indeed (see also the previous example), the natural rate of output is a 
variable which captures a highly theoretical concept: it refers to the highest level of real 
output that can be sustained over the long term and there is some disagreement among 
economists about how to characterize such a concept in applied work. In many empirical 
business cycle models, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t is treated as an unobserved (latent) state variable, while in 
empirical applications, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t is often proxied with measures of economic activity provided 
by official institutions or national statistical institutes. Thus, albeit in this example the 
dimension of X t is not particularly large, x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t represents a 'natural' conditioning variable for 
the purpose of testing the co-integration implications of the DSGE model. In addition, the 
practitioner might not be interested in modelling x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t directly within the VAR framework due 
to poor confidence on the short run properties of the time series used to proxy x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t . Hence, it 
seems reasonable to investigate whether the data support the co-integration/common trend 
implications predicted by the DSGE model by considering the partition X t = (Y t , Z t ), with 
Y t = (x t , t , i t ) (p Y = 3) and Z t = x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t (p Z = 1), and then apply BIC and HQC to the conditional 
model for Y t given Z t . For comparative purposes, we also compute the sequential co-
integration rank testing procedure of HJNR which requires Z t to be weakly exogenous 
with respect to˜ matrix in equation (14), namely that = 0 in equation (13). As in the 
previous example, in order to show the usefulness of the partial system approach relative 
to the (unconditional) full system analysis, we also determine the co-integration rank of X t 
through the full VAR system approach. 
The variables in X t = (x t , t , i t , x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) are chosen as follows: x t is the (logged) real GDP, 
t is measured by the quarterly growth rate of the GDP deflator, i t is measured by the 
effective federal funds rate expressed in quarterly terms (averages of monthly values), x </p>

<p>n 
t </p>

<p>is approximated with the official measure provided by the Congressional Budget Office 
(CBO). The data source is the web site of the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. Also in 
this case the data cover the 'Great Moderation' period. To compare results with Bårdsen 
and Fanelli (2015), we focus on the sample 1985Q1-2008Q3 which comprises T = 95 
quarterly observations. The partial (conditional) system (2) is estimated with k = 2 lags 
and a restricted constant (corresponding to case (ii) D t = 1 and d t = 0 in the full system 
(1)). Results are reported in the left-panel of Table 6, which summarizes the co-integration 
rank selected by the BIC and HQC, as well as HJNR's sequential procedure. While BIC 
selects co-integration rank r = 1, HQC selects r = 3 as predicted by the DSGE model. 
Instead, HJNR's sequential procedure selects r = 2 at the 5% nominal significance level. 
Recall, however, that the asymptotic critical values reported in Table 6 have been tabulated 
under the maintained hypothesis of weak exogeneity of Z t = (x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) which might not hold 
(see below). The right panel of Table 6 summarizes the results obtained from the full 
VAR system analysis and reports the co-integration rank selected by BIC and HQC and 
Johansen's sequential procedure. We notice that in this case BIC selects r = 1, HQC selects 
r = 2 and Johansen's sequential procedure selects r = 1 at the 5% nominal significance 
level. Aside from BIC and compared to the full system analysis, the co-integration ranks 
selected by HQC and HJNR's sequential procedure in the conditional model are in line 
with the prediction of the DSGE model. 
It is interesting in this case to test whether for fixed co-integration rank r = 3, which is 
the value selected by the HQC in the partial system analysis, the variable Z t = (x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) is weakly 
exogenous with respect to in the full system. This amounts to testing whether the last row </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>



<p>TABLE 6 </p>

<p>Empirical results for the DSGE model </p>

<p>Partial system 
Full system </p>

<p>BIC 
HQC 
HJNR (5% c.v.) BIC 
HQC 
Johan (5% c.v.) </p>

<p>r = 0 
−1, 806.1 −1, 806.1 71.1 
(41.7) 
−3, 699.3 −3, 699.3 108.7 
(53.4) 
r = 1 
−1, 816.6 −1, 827.3 28.8 
(25.5) 
−3, 701.7 −3, 713.7 
33.0 
(34.8) 
r = 2 
−1, 811.5 −1, 829.7 11.2 
(12.3) 
−3, 692.9 −3, 714.1 
15.1 
(19.9) 
r = 3 = p Y 
−1, 809.0 −1, 831.8 
-
-
−3, 684.9 −3, 712.1 
2.4 
(9.13) 
r = 4 = p 
-
-
-
-
−3, 680.9 −3, 711.1 
-
-</p>

<p>Notes: Results from the full system analysis of X t := (x t , t , i t , x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) (p = 4) and from the partial system analysis of 
Y t := (x t , t , i t ) and Z t := (x </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>t ) (p Y = 3 and p Z = 1). The 5% c.v. for HJNR's test are taken from table 3 of Harbo et al.  (1998) and the 5% c.v. for Johansen's test ('Johan') are taken from table 15.2 of Johansen (1996) (restricted constant). 
The selected co-integration rank according to the test/criterion used are denoted in bold. The co-integration rank 
predicted by the theory under the null of the DSGE model is r = r 0 = 3. </p>

<p>of the p × 3 matrix is zero in the full system for a given (exactly) identified specification 
of the p × 3 matrix . The likelihood-ratio test for the three zero restrictions in the matrix 
is equal to 35.2 and when compared with asymptotic critical values taken from its null 
2 -distribution with 3 degree of freedom leads to a firm rejection of the null hypothesis of 
weak exogeneity. This evidence suggests that, although our Monte Carlo results show that 
HJNR's sequential procedure tends to perform reasonably well in small samples also when 
Z t is not weakly exogenous, it must be interpreted with caution in applied work. Conversely, 
our approach based on information criteria, allows us to disregard any consideration about 
the weak exogeneity of Z t and therefore is robust to whether the parameter is = 0 or 
&lt; 0 in the structural equations of our DSGE model. 
We complete our investigation of the small scale DSGE model by comparing results 
with Bårdsen and Fanelli (2015). The analysis in Bårdsen and Fanelli (2015), based on a 
full system approach, suggests that if the co-integration rank is fixed at r = 3, a likelihood-
ratio test for the restrictions that =˜ as in equation (14) leads to a p-value of 0.009 
when asymptotic critical values are used, and to a p-value of 0.04 when a non-parametric 
bootstrap version of the likelihood-ratio test is computed along the lines of Boswijk et al.  (2016). Overall, we can interpret these evidences as supportive of the small-DSGE model 
(9)-(13) on the period 1985Q1-2008Q3. </p>

<p>VI. Concluding remarks </p>

<p>Information criteria have been recently used as valid alternative to co-integration rank tests 
in co-integrated VAR systems. There are cases where it is convenient to devote attention to 
the model that characterizes the dynamics of the variables of interest, conditional on some 
other variables whose dynamic characterization is not of primary interest. This approach 
is useful either in large systems or when the practitioner benefits from marginalizing out 
variables which contribute to the long-run equilibrium but do not play a key role in the 
rest of the analysis. In this paper we have extended the use of information criteria for co-
integration rank determination to the case of partial systems. We have proved consistency 
of BIC and HQC in partial systems and shown the robustness of these criteria to violations </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>



<p>Bulletin </p>

<p>of the weak exogeneity of the conditioning variables for the co-integration parameters. 
A set of Monte Carlo experiments and two empirical illustrations have shown that these 
criteria represent valid alternatives to the 'traditional' approaches to co-integration rank 
determination. 
Since the focus of the paper is on co-integration rank determination in partial (con-
ditional) systems, it can be correctly argued that, once the co-integration rank has been 
determined from the conditional model by information criteria, the inference on the co-
integration parameters (e.g. testing hypotheses on the co-integration parameters) can be 
more involved relative to the full system analysis if Z t is not weakly exogenous; see 
Johansen (1992a) and Boswijk (1995). In particular, if the conditioning variables are not 
weakly exogenous for the long-run parameters, the maximum likelihood estimator of the 
co-integration parameters is still super-consistent (albeit not fully efficient) but its asymp-
totic distribution is not mixed-Gaussian, making the construction of tests cumbersome; see 
also Phillips (1991, 1994). In this paper we have shown that the benefits of marginalizing 
Z t out may compensate, in some specific problems and cases of interest, possible losses of 
efficiency of estimates and the problem of dealing with non-standard inference. As the ex-
amples in the empirical section of this paper show, our approach is particularly convenient 
when the primary concern of the investigator is co-integration rank determination. Obvi-
ously, the decision of whether it is preferable to rely on a full or partial system approach 
for the problem under investigation depends on the specific purposes of the analysis. </p>

<p>Final Manuscript Received: April 2017 </p>



<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>Co-integration in partial systems </p>





<p>Supporting Information </p>

<p>Additional supporting information may be found in the online version of this article: </p>

<p>Appendix S1. Proof of Theorem 1. </p>

<p>© 2017 The Department of Economics, University of Oxford and John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

</text></tei>