<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1530-9134.2009.00228.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Patents and entrepreneurship are intimately linked. For many new ven-
tures, intellectual property rights are an important asset that provides 
protection from imitation or a basis for contracting in the market for 
technology. At first blush, therefore, it may seem obvious that strength-
ening patent rights or expanding the scope of the patent system would 
stimulate entrepreneurship. Yet many economists and legal scholars 
have grown skeptical about whether the current U.S. patent system is 
promoting or hindering innovation. As one prominent researcher in the 
field, Adam Jaffe, has stated in testimony before Congress "the patent 
system-intended to foster and protect innovation-is generating waste 
and uncertainty that hinder and threaten the innovative process." </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>These concerns are most acute in industries such as software and 
semiconductors, where products are highly complex, each embodying 
thousands of innovations, and where technological progress tends to be 
incremental and cumulative. In such circumstances, critics argue, any 
"stimulating" effect of stronger patents on incentives to innovate will be 
offset, or even swamped, by the "stifling" effect of higher transactions 
costs, increased threat of litigation, and constraints imposed on the 
cumulative development of technologies by multiple blocking patents. 
New enterprises that have limited resources and lack experience 
and managerial expertise in "working the patent system" are likely 
to be among those most severely affected by these stifling effects. 
Thus, far from supporting entrepreneurship, the current patent system 
may be choking innovation and hindering new venture formation in 
some sectors. In such circumstances, the enterprises that were the 
first to perceive these institutional changes and respond to them most 
effectively are likely to have been most successful in bringing their 
innovations to market. "Environmental awareness" and the ability to 
exploit the evolution of legal and regulatory institutions may therefore 
be an important complement to the innovative capability of new 
ventures. </p>

<p>1.1 Patents and the Software Industry </p>

<p>In this paper, we examine the impact of the changing IP landscape 
the interaction of entrant firms into a sample of software with external 
investors. The software industry provides an unusual and interesting 
opportunity to evaluate the impact of changes in patent rights on 
innovation and entrepreneurship. Software has been an important locus </p>

<p>1. U.S. House of Representatives Oversight Hearing on the Patent System, February 
15, 2007. See Jaffe and Lerner (2004) and Bessen and Meurer (2008). </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>of innovation in the U.S. economy, and one where entrepreneurial ven-
tures have played a particularly important role in driving technological 
change. Yet much foundational innovation occurred in the absence of 
strong patent protection, and until relatively recently many leading 
innovators in the industry, including highly visible firms like Microsoft, 
filed relatively few patents. Only after changes in patent law and USPTO 
practice in the mid 1990s generated a surge in patenting in software 
(that continues unabated) did patents become an important aspect of 
competition. The industry thus presents a "quasi-experiment" in which 
these policy changes may allow the impact of patents on new ventures 
to be much more clearly distinguished than in contexts where high 
levels of patenting have always been present. 
The nature of software products and of the innovation process in 
this technology also means that industry participants face an increas-
ingly forbidding "thicket" of IP. Software products are highly complex, 
with even quite modest products containing millions of lines of code 
and thousands or tens of thousands of interrelated component modules, 
any of which could potentially infringe one or more patents. With 
several hundred thousand software patents issued in the United States 
since 1990, 
2 and ever-greater complexity and scale of software products, 
the cost of "clearing" new products for potential infringement can be 
very large. Even where an innovator can identify which patents it may 
need to license or invent around, if very large numbers of patents are 
potentially infringed the total "tax" on entry to the market may be 
prohibitively high. Where, as Shapiro suggests, these patents form "a 
dense web of overlapping intellectual property rights that a company 
must hack its way through in order to actually commercialize new 
technology" 
3 or where the entrant has to bargain with large numbers of 
licensors, additional transactions costs associated with clearing a path 
to market may be very substantial. 
These problems may have been exacerbated by poor patent "qual-
ity" in the sense that the validity, enforceability, and scope of claims 
of some software patents is unusually difficult to assess. Allegedly 
poor standards of patent examination in this area in the past may have 
generated large numbers of issued patents with inadequate disclosure, 
and excessively broad claims, raising the costs of determining the scope 
of existing IP, and increasing uncertainty about possible future litigation 
from competitors and noncompetitors alike. </p>

<p>2. Exactly how many software patents have been issued is a controversial issue, 
because many software inventions may be embedded in other technology. See Graham  and Mowery (2003), Bessen and Hunt (2007). 
3. Shapiro (2001), p.2. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50,000 </p>

<p>100,000 </p>

<p>150,000 </p>

<p>200,000 </p>

<p>1 9 8 0 
1 9 8 2 
1 9 8 4 
1 9 8 6 
1 9 8 8 
1 9 9 0 
1 9 9 2 
1 9 9 4 
1 9 9 6 
1 9 9 8 
2 0 0 0 
2 0 0 2 
2 0 0 4 
2 0 0 6 </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. TOTAL PATENTS IN FORCE IN 27 SOFTWARE MARKETS </p>

<p>Figure 1 shows how dramatic the increase in software patenting 
has been. The figure plots the total number of patents in force that are 
relevant to 27 distinct software product markets between 1980 and 2006. 
Over this period the CAGR (compound annual growth rate) of the total 
number of patents outstanding was 29.8%. Over the decade from 1994 to 
2004 alone, the number of patents in the average market in our sample 
grew by almost 600%, while the number of active firms grew by less 
than 300%. By 2006, the average market in this sample had 5,858 patents 
in force, collectively asserting more than 127,000 claims. 
Data such as these suggest that costs associated with patents-
searching prior art, building patent portfolios, and defending against 
the threat of patent litigation-have grown very substantially, and may 
now be having a significantly negative impact on the pace of innovation 
in the industry. To cite just two authoritative observers, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Donald Knuth</rs>, 
author of The Art of Computer Programming and inventor of <rs id="software-0" type="software">TeX</rs>, has 
stated that "I don't think I would have been able to create TeX if 
the present [patent] climate had existed in the 1970s," while erstwhile 
entrepreneur Bill Gates has opined that "If people had understood how 
patents would be granted when most of today's ideas were invented and 
had taken out patents, the industry would be at a complete standstill 
today." </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4. Pignalberi (2004), Lessig (2002). </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>1.2 Patent Thickets, Innovation, and Entrepreneurship </p>

<p>Ideally, we would want to evaluate the impact of patents and "thick-
eting" on innovation and entrepreneurship in software with reference 
to direct economic outcomes such as indicators of the pace of technical 
change or the prices prevailing in innovation markets. Unfortunately 
these data are generally poor, and measurement challenges are partic-
ular severe in software. Data on licensing transactions, for example, is 
very sparse and highly selective, 
5 though see Cockburn et al. (2008)  which examines the relationship between patent thickets and the extent 
to which small and medium enterprises in German manufacturing 
engage in licensing. Research on these issues has therefore tended to 
focus on indirect measures of the impact of patents, such as the stock 
market value of companies (see e.g., Hall and MacGarvie, 2006). In 
software, one useful indicator of technical change-recognizing the 
important role of new ventures in driving innovation in this industry-
is market entry and the founding and financing of new firms. Here we 
focus on the effect of thickets on the ability of new entrants to finance 
market entry by secure external funding from various sources, a critical 
economic mechanism in this and other sectors, and one through which 
patents play an important role in determining incentives to launch new 
products and new ventures. </p>

<p>6   We hypothesize that patent thickets affect the ability of software 
start-ups to raise money from outside investors in two main ways. 
First, the transaction costs of entering a market may be higher when 
that market has a patent thicket. Patents that block a would-be entrant 
from producing or selling its product mean that the entrant must either 
bear additional costs of "inventing around" such patents, pay licensing 
fees to the patent holder, or accept potentially severe ex post penalties 
from launching its product "at risk" of infringement litigation. 
7 One 
dimension of a patent thicket is thus the number of the patents that 
an entrant may potentially infringe, where more patents impose a 
proportionately higher "tax" on entrants. Suppose an entrant was to </p>

<p>5. See Robbins (2008). Public auctions of IP such as those conducted by Ocean Tomo 
in recent years are provocative, but cover only very small and highly selective samples of 
patents. 
6. In a related paper (Cockburn and MacGarvie, 2007), we looked at the impact of 
thickets on rates of entry of new firms, and find that there are fewer entrants into software 
markets in which there are more patents, after controlling for characteristics of the firm 
such as age or own patent holdings, and characteristics of the market such as the average 
importance of patents and the stage of the product lifecycle. 
7. Infringing valid patents can present the entrant with very substantial ex post 
penalties, such as damages judgments (tripled in the case of "willful infringement") 
or the loss in value of assets stranded in the wake of an injunction obtained by the patent 
holder. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>obtain licenses to all of the patents that it infringes. All else equal, we 
expect that the more patents that must be licensed, the higher the total 
cost of entry. However, particularly in complex technologies, patents 
are frequently bundled or pooled, or jointly licensed, thus total costs of 
entry may not have a simple linear relationship to the number of patents 
blocking the would-be entrant. In particular, costs imposed by a thicket 
may also reflect the structure of ownership of these patents (Ziedonis,  2004). For example, transactions costs associated with bargaining with 
licensors may be lower when ownership of patents is more concentrated. 
To the extent that there are fixed costs of conducting a negotiation, 
having to conduct fewer negotiations will lower costs. A licensee may 
be able to get better terms per patent when negotiating with a relatively 
small number of licensors who each control large bundles of patents. 
Conversely, where the entrant has to conduct a complex bargaining 
process with many licensors, each of whom has some holdup power, 
higher total costs may be incurred-that is., the height of the "royalty 
stack" may rise nonlinearly in the number of its components. Noel and  Schankerman (2006) provide evidence on the costs imposed by patent 
thickets from a sample of publicly traded software firms by showing that 
market value decreases when patent rights held by a firm's competitors 
are more fragmented, reflecting the higher costs of negotiating with 
more parties. 
Second, the uncertainty of the firm's future profit stream may 
be higher when it faces a patent thicket. Lemley and Shapiro (2005)  argue that there are two types of uncertainty associated with patents: 
uncertainty about the commercial value of the property right granted 
to the inventor, and uncertainty about the validity and scope of 
the property right. The latter form of uncertainty may be especially 
prevalent in software, a field in which patents were until recently not 
used to protect IP and which saw a dramatic growth of patenting 
following changes in the USPTO's patentability guidelines in the mid 
1990s. The lack of experience with software patents at the USPTO, 
combined with the ambiguity associated with what is covered by many 
patents in this sector, has meant that software developers face significant 
uncertainty about existing prior art and the possibility of being sued for 
infringement. Bessen and Meurer (2008) find that software patents are 
more than twice as likely as other patents to have claim construction 
appealed to the Federal Circuit, and, which they take as an indicator of 
elevated uncertainty about the boundaries of patents in software. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>8. Brian Kahin (2004) cites the hearings in 2002 on Competition and Intellectual Property 
Law and Policy in the Knowledge-Based Economy, held by the U.S. Federal Trade Commission 
and the Department of Justice at which Frederick J. Telecky of Texas Instruments stated </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>We look for evidence of the impact of increased transaction costs 
and greater uncertainty on new ventures in "thicketed" markets in 
the following ways. First, higher anticipated transaction costs should 
affect negatively affect investors' valuations of start-up companies, 
"raising the bar" for new entrants in terms of meeting minimum 
levels of profitability required by outside inventors, and thus reducing 
the number of entrants that receive funding from outside investors. 
Once a firm becomes an incumbent, the effect of thickets is less clear: 
thickets may offer protection from entrants, or result in future additional 
transaction costs, with an ambiguous effect on the value of the enterprise 
and the probability that a firm is able to create a "liquidity event" 
for early-stage investors by going public or being acquired. Second, 
higher uncertainty about future profits should affect the timing of 
investments. When investments are irreversible, the opportunity cost 
of current investment (versus investment at a later date) increases 
with uncertainty about future profits. Thus, all else equal, increases 
in uncertainty increase the value of delaying investment. </p>

<p>9   We hypothesize that higher levels of uncertainty over the threat 
of litigation or other future patent-related costs increases the value 
of delaying investments in anticipation of information such as court 
rulings that clarify the scope of relevant patents, or the results of "field 
testing" licensing and enforcement strategies. As a result, we expect 
that, after controlling for firm-and investor-level characteristics, firms 
operating in markets characterized by larger or more fragmented patent 
thickets, or markets in which the relevant prior art is less well defined, 
will see investments delayed. We look for evidence of delay in duration 
models for the timing of investment at two points in the lifecycle of 
new ventures: the time elapsed from the birth of a new venture until it 
obtains its first round of funding from outside investors (both venture 
capitalists and corporate investors), and the time elapsed between the 
first round of funding and "exit" from the entrepreneurial phase via 
IPO or acquisition. This transition often marks a significant change 
in entrepreneurial ventures' ability to generate significant profits, and 
in their business model, capital requirements, scale of operation, and 
management. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>that: "TI has something like 8000 patents in the United States that are active patents, and 
for us to know what's in that portfolio, we think, is just a mind-boggling, budget-busting 
exercise to try to figure that out with any degree of accuracy at all." Kahin notes that, "If 
a company with TI's resources cannot assess what they have in-house, it is difficult to 
expect a small company entering a market to evaluate what claims they may be facing." 
9. Arrow (1968), Bernanke (1983), Dixit and Pindyck (1994), among others. 
10. These "exits" are also important mechanism for industry consolidation and 
restructuring, which is a topic beyond this scope of this paper. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Third, we examine which strategies may help firms succeed when 
faced with patent thickets. Following Hall and Ziedonis (2003) and 
Ziedonis (2004), we hypothesize that start-up companies with patents 
will be able to use them in cross-licensing negotiations to defend 
themselves against litigation, or more generally to obtain better terms 
in any licensing negotiation. These patents may then act to reduce the 
transaction costs associated with operating in a "thicketed" market. 
These firms should also face less uncertainty, and thus we expect 
investment will take place earlier. 
We believe this paper makes several contributions to the literature. 
First, we provide novel empirical evidence on several aspects of the 
impact of patent thickets on early-stage firms. Using a differences-in-
differences methodology that uses shifts in the software patent regime 
to identify the effects of interest, we find that patent thickets make it 
more difficult for early-stage firms to obtain initial funding. The impact 
of patent thickets on the ability of firms to "exit" from the start-up phase 
via IPO or acquisition, is more ambiguous, however, there is evidence 
that the negative effect of thickets intensified following changes in 
patentability and that this effect was felt disproportionately by firms 
without patents of their own. We consistently find a positive correlation 
between the firm's own patent holdings and "success" in financing 
transactions. Interestingly, however, we observe that it is the number 
of patents pending, rather than the number of patents already granted, 
which matters in our regressions. This raises important questions about 
the value of patents as property rights relative to their value as signals 
of quality. 
Second, we also contribute to the literature on entrepreneurship 
by analyzing a dataset that contains both venture-or corporate-funded 
firms from the SDC universe as well as pre-funding start-ups drawn 
from the CorpTech database. This allows us to examine how funded 
firms differ from firms that do not obtain funding, and to analyze 
determinants of the timing of first investment. While other research 
has looked at differences between venture-backed and non venture-
backed firms in small samples, we are not aware of other papers that 
exploit as comprehensive a dataset as the one we use here. </p>

<p>1.3 Literature Review </p>

<p>A number of strands of literature are relevant to this paper. Studies of 
the impact of quasi-natural experiments associated with legal changes 
to patent regimes on innovation include Branstetter and Sakakibara  (2001), Lanjouw and Cockburn (2001), Moser (2005), Scherer and  Weisburst (1995), Branstetter et al. (2006), Lerner (2002), and Hall and </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Ziedonis (2001). On software patents in particular, negative effects of 
more-and-stronger patent rights have been found by Bessen and Maskin  (2007) and Bessen and Hunt (2007). See also Noel and Schankerman  (2006), Hall (2005) and Hall and MacGarvie (2006) for evidence on 
the impact of patents on market value of software firms, and Mann  (2006) who shows that software start-ups holding patents receive more 
investment from venture capitalists than those without patents. 
Arora et al. (2001), Gans and Stern (2000), Gans et al. (2002), and 
others have highlighted the role of patents and other formal IP rights 
in supporting a "market for technology," which provides an avenue 
for new entrants to realize value from innovation by licensing, or 
selling themselves to incumbents. Hsu and Ziedonis (2007) show that 
a doubling in a start-up firm's patent stock is associated with a 24% 
increase on average in investors' valuations. 
In contrast to the number of papers that use datasets comprising 
exclusively venture-backed firms, the literature that models the prob-
ability that start-up companies obtain external investment from other 
sources is relatively sparse. Hellmann and Puri (2002) provide evidence 
on the impact of VC funding on start-ups, using a sample of venture-
backed and non venture-backed firms. See also Kortum and Lerner  (2000) and Goldfarb et al. (2005). 
Analyses of the role of uncertainty in the duration and timing 
of investment in start-ups include Gompers (1995) and Guler (2007). 
Empirical analyses of exits via IPO include Lerner (1994), Gompers  (1995), Giot and Schwienbacher (2007), Ljungqvist et al. (2007), and 
Cockburn and Wagner (2007). </p>

<p>2. Data and Empirical Approach </p>

<p>Our approach here is to estimate reduced form regressions in which we 
look for evidence of an association between measures of patent thickets 
and indicators of entry and financing of new ventures, controlling for 
other market characteristics, such as demand, market structure, and 
the state of technology. We look at the impact of patent thickets at two 
levels. In the first set of regressions presented here we look at the market-
level association between patents and aggregate volumes of entry and 
financing activity. A second set of regressions looks at the effect of the 
patent landscape on the timing of investment using much more detailed 
firm-level data. 
One obvious potential problem is endogeneity: the nature of 
the patent thicket prevailing in these markets presumably reflects 
optimizing responses to the competitive environment. Motivations for </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>firms to file patents are, however, complex. Incumbents may well apply 
for patents strategically to deter entry, to raise the costs of rivals already 
in the market, or to protect themselves from litigation (Ziedonis, 2004), 
thus making the size of the thicket in a given market endogenous with 
respect to competition. But patenting behavior may also reflect other 
factors such as the use of patents as part of internal systems for providing 
incentives or monitoring employees, or the firm's participation in other 
patent-intensive industries (such as hardware). 
11 Other aspects of the 
institutional context of this study and of our estimation methods also 
suggest that any endogeneity bias is quite limited, and to the extent 
that it does affect our estimates it will bias coefficients toward zero, 
leading to underestimates rather than overestimates of any causal effect 
of patent thickets. In all of our regressions we use market fixed effects, so 
that our identification comes from within-market changes in the patent 
thicket and the outcomes of interest rather than from purely cross-
sectional correlations. It is also important to recognize that the timing of 
incumbents' patent grants (or their ability to obtain patent protection at 
all) is in large part affected by exogenous changes in resources and policy 
at the patent office. The average time between patent application and 
grant in our dataset is close to 3 years. 
12 Given the high speed of product 
cycles and turnover in the software industry, incumbents filing patents 
in response to threats from competitors will in most cases be unable to 
use the granted patents until well after entry has taken place, and the 
infringing product has been superseded. Because of this, a substantial 
portion of the thicket faced by entrants in any market is composed of 
patents obtained far in the past, and by noncompetitors. Thus, after 
controlling for time-invariant unobserved effects, and a variety of other 
potential sources of bias (such as confounding growth in the patent 
thicket with maturity of the technology in a market), endogeneity of 
our thicket measures created by incumbents' responses to time-varying 
shocks to the threat of entry appears not to be a major issue. </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>11. Allison et al. (2007) describes the patent filing behavior of several large players in 
the industry, showing that IBM was an early patenter while firms like Adobe, Autodesk, 
Computer Associates and Oracle came late to the software patent game (in terms of 
applications filed). While a detailed examination of the various motivations for patenting 
by the firms in our sample is indeed an interesting subject for future research, we focus 
here on the observed patterns of patenting and entry and investment rather than on 
documenting the organizational processes at work. 
12. According to the USPTO website, "The length of this delay is determined by 
many factors, including PTO workload, budget and manpower levels, and patent printing 
schedules. . .[for example,] The 1986 patent grant data are lower than would have normally 
been expected due to a lack of printing funds." 
13. In Cockburn and MacGarvie (2007) we used an instrumental variables approach to 
address the potential endogeneity of patenting by incumbents, and obtained coefficients 
essentially identical to those estimated by OLS. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Here we additionally exploit a series of changes in the legal regime 
that substantially expanded patentability of software inventions, and 
were accompanied by a dramatic increase in the number of software 
patents granted during the 1990s. These changes can be thought of as a 
quasi-experiment in which the strength of issued patents exogenously 
increased, raising barriers to entry in markets with more patents relative 
to markets with fewer patents. This allows us to examine patterns 
of entry and financing before and after changes in the legal regime 
using a differences-in-differences approach. In this model, for any 
there to any bias arising from a correlation between financing/entry 
and patents induced by omitted variables, the relationship between 
financing/entry and the omitted variable(s) in question would have to 
occur simultaneously with the changes in software patentability that 
took place during our sample. </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>2.1 Data 
2.1.1 Market and Firm Characteristics </p>

<p>The firms we study are drawn from the CorpTech directory of technol-
ogy companies, which covers 19,717 public and private firms active in 
software markets over the period 1990-2004. 
15 We know the founding 
date of the firm, revenues, and employment for most (but not all) of 
the firms in the dataset, the patents held by the firm, information on 
corporate parents, funding sources, and a number of other variables. To 
the CorpTech sample, we add data from SDC's VentureXpert database, 
matched by firm name using a name-matching algorithm augmented 
by manual inspection. 
16 VentureXpert lists over 60,000 companies. Our 
matching algorithm found a match for 4,531 of the software firms listed 
on CorpTech in the list of VentureXpert firms. While there is obvious 
potential for both Type I and Type II errors in this matching process, 
our considerable effort spent on manual inspection of matches and 
nonmatches between these sources suggests that these are small. </p>

<p>14. Of course, if these changes in the legal regime result in increased incentives 
to obtain patents, the thicket we evolve endogenously over time, leading to more 
complicated dynamics that are beyond the scope of this paper. Note though that the 
given the pendency period at the USTPO, these effects are manifested in granted patents 
only very slowly. The differences-in-differences approach used here thus identifies only 
the "prompt" impact of the regime shift. 
15. We define software companies as the firms listed in CorpTech as having at least 
one product classification beginning with "SOF," which is CorpTech's code for software. 
Note that the CorpTech data reports biennially rather than annually, so that we see 12 
sample years of data rather than 24 calendar years. 
16. We are grateful to Bronwyn Hall for code that comprises the core of our name-
matching program. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>For each matched firm we obtained information on the number of 
rounds of investment received, the amounts invested, the identities of 
investors, the stage of the investment, the founding date of the venture, </p>

<p>17   and whether the venture ultimately went public or was acquired, and 
the name of the acquirer when relevant. We also collect Compustat 
data on the sales, employment, and two-digit SIC codes of corporate 
investors. 
The CorpTech data contain fine-grained information on the prod-
uct classes in which the firm develops software (the "SOF category"). 
This self-reported variable can include products under development as 
well as products already launched. CorpTech reports more than 290 SOF 
categories; however, many of these are quite vaguely defined, or appear 
to be defined in terms of customer segments rather than in terms of a 
technology-for example, "secondary school software, dental practice 
management software, etc." Furthermore mapping patents to markets 
is a challenging and resource-intensive task. We therefore focus our 
analysis on 27 of these SOF-defined markets, listed in Table AI. These 
27 markets were chosen primarily to facilitate subsequent mapping to 
patent data, primarily on the basis of our assessment as to whether the 
technology/product is reasonably distinctive, and we could define a set 
of keywords that could be fruitfully searched in the abstract of patent 
documents. </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Table I gives summary statistics for the number of firms of various 
types averaged over successive years and across markets. On average, 
15.4 firms entered a market in the 2-year period between CorpTech 
sample years. The number of "de novo" entrants, as opposed to firms, 
which are new to the market in question, but already have an established 
presence in other markets, is quite small, averaging 3.05 per market per 
year. (This figure is likely to be an underestimate of the fraction of 
entrants into these markets that are "new," reflecting issues with the 
way that CorpTech collects data, and our screen for identifying new </p>

<p>17. The founding dates on CorpTech and SDC are within 3 years of each other 83% of 
the time. For firms with more than 3 years disagreement between founding dates in the 
two samples, we used web searches to obtain the correct founding year. 
18. Clearly there is some potential for selection bias to influence our results, however, 
we believe that the criteria used to choose these markets are independent of entry and 
exit dynamics and the sample of 27 SOFs does not appear to be markedly different from 
the other 262 in terms of firm characteristics and entry and exit rates (see the appendix 
of Cockburn and MacGarvie [2007]). One area in which our sample differs, however, 
is in terms of the average number of patents held by firms active in the market. The 
average firm active in one of the sample markets has 29 patents, while the average firm 
in a market omitted by the sample has only 18 patents, and this difference is statistically 
significant. Note though that this difference arises by construction: it is difficult, if not 
impossible to identify patents related to many of the more vaguely defined markets. In 
our judgment, therefore, this subset of markets is reasonably representative of software 
products in general. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Table I. 
Descriptive Statistics </p>

<p>243 Market-Level Observations </p>

<p>Variable 
Mean 
Min 
Max 
Std. Dev. </p>

<p>Market Characteristics 
Number of incumbents 
157.5 
0 
766 
179.5 
Number of entrants 
15.2 
0 
104 
18.4 
Number of "de novo" entrants 
3.06 
0 
45 
5.4 
Fraction of all entrants with VC 
funding (%) </p>

<p>24.9 
0 
100 
22.1 </p>

<p>Fraction of all entrants with 
corporate funding (%) </p>

<p>6.4 
0 
50 
10.0 </p>

<p>Number of firms receiving first 
round of financing </p>

<p>1.9 
0 
50 
5.6 </p>

<p>Number if firms experiencing 
IPO or acquisition </p>

<p>0.885 
0 
19 
2.329 </p>

<p>Proxy for total sales in market 
($MM) </p>

<p>2, 684 
0 
6, 517 
6, 319 </p>

<p>CR4 of sales proxy 
0.80 
0 
1 
0.17 
Growth rate of sales proxy (in 
logs) </p>

<p>0.576 
−2.9 
4.3 
0.97 </p>

<p>Modal citation lag to patents in 
the market (years) </p>

<p>5.6 
1 
14 
4.9 </p>

<p>Patent Thicket Measures 
Stock of patents in the market 
1947.19 
10 
9409 
2025 
Number of cited assignees 
505.65 
0 
2209 
434.16 
Herfindahl index for citations 
over assignees </p>

<p>0.04 
0.014 
0.266 
0.027 </p>

<p>Average claims per backward 
citation for patents in the 
market </p>

<p>2.14 
1.08 
3.56 
0.34 </p>

<p>Average share of nonpatent 
references in total backward 
cites (%) </p>

<p>17.4 
1.7 
43.6 
8.9 </p>

<p>versus continuing ventures.) 
19 Among these new entrants, 16% receive 
external funding from VCs prior to the year in which they enter the 
market, while 6% receive funding from a corporate investor at this 
point in their lifecycle. There is substantial variation in rates of entry in 
the cross-section and over time, with the number of entrants ranging 
from 0 to 104 per sample year. 
We do not have data on market-specific sales, but we construct 
a proxy for total sales based on the sales of firms that are active in a </p>

<p>19. Firms are treated as de novo entrants if the firms are younger than 10 years old 
and specialize in only one of CorpTech's main software product classes, e.g. AI: artificial 
intelligence. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>market. 
20 On average, markets in this sample have a total of $2.7bn in 
annual sales, with substantial growth over time. Markets vary widely 
in size, from less than $70MM per year in sales to over $6.5BN. </p>

<p>2.1.2 Patents </p>

<p>Identifying the set of patents relevant for firms operating in a particular 
market is not a trivial task. Cockburn and MacGarvie (2007) describe 
in detail the process used to match USPTO patent classifications to the 
CorpTech SOF categories using an adaptive/iterative algorithm that 
combines keyword searching of the abstracts and titles of patents with 
the technology class codes applied by the USPTO. 
21 Using the mapping 
between patent classes and CorpTech product markets described above, 
we obtained all the relevant patents in these classes from the NBER 
Patent Database. There is a striking increase in the volume of patenting 
over time: annual patent grants relevant to this set of 27 product markets 
increased more than 40-fold between 1980 and 2006, from 366 per year 
to 16,285 per year. We base our analysis on "patents in force" in any 
particular year, that is, net of patents that have reached the end of their 
term or were not renewed. These expirations represent a nontrivial 
fraction of the total number of patents in force: in the late 1990s, for 
example, new patents were being added to the sample at a rate of about 
7,000 per year, while about 1200 were being removed from the "patent 
stock." 
Table I gives descriptive statistics for the patent landscape in the 27 
product markets considered here. In total we identified 108,863 patents 
issued since 1977 that are relevant to the set of markets considered. 
(Some of these are relevant to more than one market.) There are very 
substantial changes over time in the observable characteristics of these 
patents. The average number of claims per patent doubled between 
1980 and 2006, from 12.6 to 22.4, while the average number of backward 
citations per patent almost tripled over this period, rising from 7.2 to 19.1 
and the average number of citations to nonpatent literature increased </p>

<p>20. For firm i active in in market j as well as n-1 other markets, we compute average 
sales per market in market j as SALES i /n (the total sales of the firm divided by the number 
of markets in which it is active). We then add up the average sales per market for all firms 
active in the market. CorpTech contains a numerical sales variable as well as a categorical 
variable that indicates the range in which the firm's revenues fall. A significant portion 
of observations on the former are missing, and we fill in these observations with the 
midpoint of the range indicated by the categorical sales variable. 
21. Arora et al. (2007) use a somewhat similar approach to create a comprehensive 
concordance between USPTO classes and software product categories. Silverman (1999)  is a notable example of the principle alternative to this approach, which is to link data 
on patent classes to industry classifications using on a concordance developed from 
"industries of use" assigned by Canadian patent examiners. We judged this approach to 
be unhelpful here, given the fine-grained industry definition that we use, and substantial 
differences over this period between the US and Canada in patentability of software. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1400 </p>

<p>1600 </p>

<p>1800 </p>

<p>1 9 8 5 
1 9 8 7 
1 9 8 9 
1 9 9 1 
1 9 9 3 
1 9 9 5 
1 9 9 7 
1 9 9 9 
2 0 0 1 
2 0 0 3 </p>

<p>704: language 
analysis </p>

<p>705: financial / 
business </p>

<p>706: artificial 
intelligence </p>

<p>709: 
multicomputer 
processing </p>

<p>711: memory </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. PATENTS GRANTED BY YEAR, SELECTED USPTO 
CLASSES </p>

<p>more than 10-fold from 0.5 per patent to 6.9. While some of the growth 
in citations reflects growth in the pool of references available to be cited, 
these figures also suggest significant changes in the nature of the patent 
rights being awarded and in the stringency of patent examination. 
As Figure 2 shows, there is substantial variation the numbers of 
patents issued in different technology classes as well as in trends in 
patenting in different technology classes. 
After mapping these classes to product markets, this variation 
is reflected in substantial cross-sectional and time series differences 
between these markets in the number of patents granted. In some 
markets only a few hundred patents met our search criteria, while in 
others there are more than 16,000 patents issued over the sample period. 
Less substantial differences are also apparent in the average number of 
claims and in the amount of patent and nonpatent prior art that is 
cited. (Note though that ANOVA F-tests strongly reject the hypothesis 
of equality of means across markets for all of these measures.) </p>

<p>2.1.3 Quantitative Measures of Patent Thickets </p>

<p>Patents that block a would-be entrant from producing or selling its 
product can clearly be a significant barrier to entry. The entrant must 
either bear additional costs of "inventing around" such patents, pay 
licensing fees to the patent holder, or accept potentially severe ex post 
penalties. 
22 As a first step toward characterizing the patent "landscape" </p>

<p>22. Infringement of valid patents can present the entrant with very substantial ex post 
penalties, such as damages judgments (tripled in the case of "willful infringement") or </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>in a market, we therefore compute the cumulative stock of patents in 
force in the markets in which each ventures operates as an indicator 
of the overall amount of intellectual property faced by the venture. </p>

<p>23   There was substantial growth over time in the size of the thicket, and 
substantial variation across markets, with the stock of patents ranging 
from 10 to over 11,000 patents. 
However, as argued above, it may not be just the absolute number 
of patents in an area that can deter entry, but also the extent to 
which those patents constitute a "thicket" in the sense of generating 
transactions costs above and beyond simple blocking power. Following 
Ziedonis (2004) and Noel and Schankerman (2006) we hypothesize that 
a key factor driving transactions costs may be the degree to which 
ownership of patent rights is fragmented, and capture this second effect 
by measuring the concentration of IP ownership in each market using 
patent citations. 
24 Patent citations are references to existing patented 
technologies, listed in the patent document. 
25 Because these citations 
delimit the property rights represented by a patent by describing related 
claims contained in other patents, citations made by a patent give an 
indication of the extent to which a technological area is already covered 
by intellectual property rights and is thus (in principle) foreclosed to 
entrants who do not obtain a license. Assuming that the share of citations 
received by an assignee proxies the importance of negotiating with that 
assignee, we postulate that, in a market that has many cited assignees 
but where citations go disproportionately to a small number of firms, 
entry costs may actually be lower than in a market with fewer assignees 
each of which receives a similar share of total citations. To capture this 
effect, we calculate the Herfindahl index of citations over assignees 
for each market in each year. 
26 The number of cited assignees is quite </p>

<p>the loss in value of assets stranded in the wake of an injunction obtained by the patent 
holder. 
23. Following the literature we also computed a patent stock from annual flows 
of patent grants, using the perpetual inventory method and the standard "Griliches 
constant" 15% depreciation rate. By depreciating the stock over and above expirations of 
patents, this would allow for some obsolescence of patents. During the sample period, 
while the average market had 2371 patents in force, the depreciated stock averaged 1238. 
Very similar results were obtained in the regressions below using the this measure as an 
alternative to the undepreciated accumulated stock of patents in force. 
24. In Cockburn and MacGarvie (2007) we use an alternative measure, a count of the 
number of cited assignees in each market. 
25. "Prior art" is not confined to patents, indeed most forms of printed publication 
describing the claimed invention can constitute prior art, as can public knowledge, use, 
or sale of the technology. 
26. We also experimented with using the four-firm concentration index of citations 
across assignees to measure the concentration of patent rights, and obtained similar 
results. These results are available from the authors upon request. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>large, averaging 505 per market per year, and the Herfindahl indexes 
correspondingly low. 
Some of these patent measures will be correlated with the maturity 
of the technology. Gort and Klepper (1982), for example, document an 
increase in patenting as technologies reach the late stages of the product 
life cycle. We want to separate the effects of increased patenting at any 
given stage of the technology life cycle from the natural accumulation of 
larger patent stocks as time passes. To control for the average maturity 
of technology in the product market, we use the modal citation lag. 
Because the number of citations to a patent is a function of the number 
of potential citations, we estimate the modal lag using a framework 
that adjusts for this effect. For each product class and citing-cited year 
pair, we compute the citation frequency, or ratio of actual to potential 
citations (see Jaffe and Trajtenberg, 1999), and then identify the citation 
lag (citing year-cited year) with the highest citation frequency for a 
given product class and citing year. 
27 If the modal lag in a product 
category is short, it implies that the most highly cited patents in that 
market were granted recently, which suggests that the market is at a 
relatively early stage of the product cycle. </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>2.1.4 Quantitative Measures of Uncertainty About 
Patent Rights </p>

<p>Capturing market participants' ex ante degree of uncertainty about the 
scope and validity of the patents that they face is clearly a substantial 
challenge. Based on discussions with practitioners and our reading of 
the ongoing debates about "patent quality" we identify two aspects of 
patents that may signal that their scope and validity may be difficult to 
assess. First, we look at the number of nonpatent references cited as prior 
art. Software patent applications (and their review by the patent office) 
have been widely criticized for failing to recognize or consider relevant 
prior art in the form of articles in professional journals, trade press, 
widely circulated product manuals and the like, which could potentially 
have sharply reduced the scope of claims allowed. According to this 
view, patents with very few citations to this type of prior art are more 
likely to be held invalid if subjected to legal challenge. (Of course, it 
may be that such patents reflect truly innovative inventions for which </p>

<p>27. We compute the citation frequency as the ratio of the number of observed citations 
to the number of potential citations. That is, if Ckgd is the number of citations made to 
patents in market k in citing year g to patents granted in market k in cited year d, Pkg 
is the number of patents granted in class k in year g, and Pkd is the number of patents 
granted in class k in year d, the citation frequency is Ckgd/(Pkg Pkd). 
28. The usefulness of this variable as an indicator of the stage of the product cycle 
obviously depends on the assumption that the key inventions are patented, and that the 
propensity to patent stays more or less constant over the lifecycle. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>no prior art existed.) Arguably, therefore, markets with many such 
patents are ones in which the degree to which the technology space 
is "covered" is particularly hard to assess. For patents in the average 
market, the mean share of nonpatent citations in the count of total 
backward citations per patent was 17.6%, with substantial variation 
across markets (1.7% to almost 50%) and over time. 
Second, we compute the average number of claims per patent in 
a market. Arguably, the difficulty of assessing the scope of a patent is 
increasing in the number of claims. One of the USPTO's recent initiatives 
to improve patent quality has been to limit the number of claims in a 
patent to no more than 25 (with no more than 5 independent claims.) 
Further, Allison et al. (2004) show that patents with larger numbers 
of claims are more likely to be litigated, and while the likelihood of 
litigation is undoubtedly related to the value of the patent, it is also more 
likely to occur when parties disagree over the validity or scope of the 
patent-that is, when there is greater uncertainty. 
29 As a measure of this 
type of uncertainty about the strength of a patent we calculate the ratio of 
the number of claims allowed on a patent to the number of patents (both 
U.S. and foreign) cited. Our reasoning is that patents with a very large 
number of claims and very few citations to prior art are whose validity 
and scope are likely to be particularly difficult to assess. (Such patents 
are sometimes referred to by practitioners as "problem patents.") One 
difficulty with this measure is that low numbers of backward cites may 
simply reflect the "newness" or novelty of the invention rather than 
poor examination (or strategic behavior by the applicant). However, it is 
uncorrelated with the model citation lag, which we believe more directly 
captures "newness," suggesting that it is capturing an independent 
dimension of the data. 
For patents in the average market, the mean number of claims per 
backward citation is 2.14, with industry averages ranging from 1.67 to 
2.72. Variation in this ratio across markets is statistically significant: an 
ANOVA F-test strongly rejects the hypothesis of equal industry means 
(p &lt; 0.0001). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1 Impact of Patent Thickets at the Market Level </p>

<p>Tables II and III give estimates of the impact of patent thickets on market-
level measures of activity by new software ventures. In Table II, the 
dependent variable in the regressions is the number of new entrants in </p>

<p>29. See also Bessen and Meurer (2006). </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Table II. </p>

<p>Market-Level Results on Entry </p>

<p>Poisson Regressions with Year and Market Fixed Effects and Standard Errors Clustered by Market </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>Entrants </p>

<p>De Novo </p>

<p>Diversifiers </p>

<p>Key Patent Variables 
Ln(Market's patents) </p>

<p>−0.628 </p>

<p>−0.774 </p>

<p>−0.657 </p>

<p>−0.097 </p>

<p>−0.139 </p>

<p>−0.671 </p>

<p>−0.702 </p>

<p>(0.276)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.268)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.272)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.651) </p>

<p>(0.646) </p>

<p>(0.263)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.265)  *  *  </p>

<p>Average claims per cite </p>

<p>−0.466 </p>

<p>in market </p>

<p>(0.182)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Nonpatent share of prior </p>

<p>−0.874 </p>

<p>art </p>

<p>(2.234) </p>

<p>D(Regime change) </p>

<p>0.735 </p>

<p>1.721 </p>

<p>0.470 </p>

<p>(0.287)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.882) </p>

<p>(0.236)  *  </p>

<p>D(Regime change) × </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>0.083 </p>

<p>−0.229 </p>

<p>−0.051 </p>

<p>ln(market's patents) </p>

<p>(0.038)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.109)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.032) </p>

<p>Control Variables 
Ln(Avg Quality of </p>

<p>−1.297 </p>

<p>−1.390 </p>

<p>−1.267 </p>

<p>0.585 </p>

<p>0.721 </p>

<p>−1.671 </p>

<p>1.685 </p>

<p>market's patents) </p>

<p>(0.639)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.619)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.647)  *  </p>

<p>(1.608) </p>

<p>(1.631) </p>

<p>(0.634)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.646)  *  </p>

<p>Incumbents (in hundreds) </p>

<p>0.788 </p>

<p>0.880 </p>

<p>0.840 </p>

<p>1.226 </p>

<p>1.265 </p>

<p>0.724 </p>

<p>0.761 </p>

<p>(0.106)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.110)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.100)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.197)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.180)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.077)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.079)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Incumbents (in hundreds) </p>

<p>−0.058 </p>

<p>−0.068 </p>

<p>−0.063 </p>

<p>−0.105 </p>

<p>−0.108 </p>

<p>−0.051 </p>

<p>−0.054 </p>

<p>squared </p>

<p>(0.012)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.014)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.012)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.020)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.018)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.010)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.010)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Growth of revenues </p>

<p>0.171 </p>

<p>0.165 </p>

<p>0.193 </p>

<p>0.159 </p>

<p>0.209 </p>

<p>0.149 </p>

<p>0.164 </p>

<p>(0.072)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.075)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.071)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.114) </p>

<p>(0.137) </p>

<p>(0.077)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.076)  *  *  </p>

<p>Continued </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table II. 
Continued </p>

<p>Poisson Regressions with Year and Market Fixed Effects and Standard Errors Clustered by Market </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>Entrants </p>

<p>De Novo </p>

<p>Diversifiers </p>

<p>Constant </p>

<p>8.317 </p>

<p>10.278 </p>

<p>8.167 </p>

<p>−4.427 </p>

<p>−5.167 </p>

<p>9.966 </p>

<p>10.046 </p>

<p>(3.403)  *  *  </p>

<p>(3.437)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(3.424)  *  *  </p>

<p>(8.337) </p>

<p>(8.350) </p>

<p>(3.374)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(3.420)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>162 </p>

<p>Year fixed effects </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Market fixed effects </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Dummies for deciles of modal citation lag </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Median Marginal Effects of Interaction Terms 
D(Regime change) × </p>

<p>ln(market's patents) </p>

<p>−2.135 </p>

<p>−0.435 </p>

<p>−1.45 </p>

<p>median standard error </p>

<p>1.316 </p>

<p>0.444 </p>

<p>1.06 </p>

<p>median p-value </p>

<p>0.090 </p>

<p>0.308 </p>

<p>0.147 </p>

<p>Average effect below 25 th </p>

<p>percentile of market size </p>

<p>−0.984 </p>

<p>−0.300 </p>

<p>−0.642 </p>

<p>Average effect above 75 th </p>

<p>percentile of market size </p>

<p>−8.317 </p>

<p>−1.70 </p>

<p>−5.93 </p>

<p>Robust standard errors clustered by market in parentheses. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Significant at 10%;  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 5%;  *  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 1%. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Table III. </p>

<p>Market-Level Results on Financing and IPOs </p>

<p>Estimation Method </p>

<p>Poisson </p>

<p>Tobit </p>

<p>Poisson </p>

<p>Number of Firms in Market j </p>

<p>Median Amount Invested in </p>

<p># of IPOs and Acquisitions in </p>

<p>Receiving Initial Funding in Year t </p>

<p>Market j 
in Year t </p>

<p>Market j 
in Year t </p>

<p>Dependent Variable </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>Patent Variables 
Ln(Market's patents) </p>

<p>−1.263 </p>

<p>−0.809 
−0.590 −11, 
608.122 −10, </p>

<p>981.753 −10, </p>

<p>084.730 </p>

<p>−1.362 </p>

<p>−1.122 </p>

<p>−1.048 </p>

<p>(0.710)  *  </p>

<p>(0.807) 
(0.743) (12, 091.284) </p>

<p>(11, 099.054) </p>

<p>(10, 695.009) </p>

<p>(0.663)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.720) </p>

<p>(0.721) </p>

<p>D(regime change) </p>

<p>1.358 </p>

<p>2.249 </p>

<p>10, 658.633 </p>

<p>14, 718.818 </p>

<p>1.272 </p>

<p>2.487 </p>

<p>(1.219) </p>

<p>(1.176)  *  </p>

<p>(8, 585.367) </p>

<p>(8, 974.368) </p>

<p>(1.355) </p>

<p>(1.909) </p>

<p>D(regime change) × </p>

<p>− </p>

<p>0.299 </p>

<p>−0.402 </p>

<p>−1, </p>

<p>590.659 </p>

<p>−2, </p>

<p>040.591 </p>

<p>−0.272 </p>

<p>−0.457 </p>

<p>ln(patents in market) </p>

<p>(0.169)  *  </p>

<p>(0.158)  *  *  </p>

<p>(1, 343.024) </p>

<p>(1, 319.938) </p>

<p>(0.206) </p>

<p>(0.269)  *  </p>

<p>Average claims per cite </p>

<p>−0.907 </p>

<p>−6, </p>

<p>765.088 </p>

<p>−0.246 </p>

<p>(0.616) </p>

<p>(4, 807.813) </p>

<p>(0.702) </p>

<p>Average Nonpatent </p>

<p>−10.618 </p>

<p>−14, </p>

<p>295.353 </p>

<p>−11.242 </p>

<p>share of citations to </p>

<p>(5.679)  *  </p>

<p>(53, 120.186) </p>

<p>(8.080) </p>

<p>prior art 
Control Variables 
No. of firms "at risk" </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>39.429 </p>

<p>32.472 </p>

<p>20.058 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>(0.004)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.004)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.005)  *  </p>

<p>(25.747) </p>

<p>(25.969) </p>

<p>(24.197) </p>

<p>(0.006)  *  </p>

<p>(0.006)  *  </p>

<p>(0.006)  *  </p>

<p>Ln(Avg Quality of </p>

<p>−1.798 </p>

<p>−0.743 
−0.513 −23, 
947.016 −21, </p>

<p>080.091 −20, </p>

<p>663.239 </p>

<p>−2.544 </p>

<p>−1.736 </p>

<p>−1.908 </p>

<p>market's patents) </p>

<p>(1.392)  *  *  </p>

<p>(1.655) 
(1.717) (26, 137.731) </p>

<p>(24, 249.336) </p>

<p>(23, 038.502) </p>

<p>(2.046) </p>

<p>(2.190) </p>

<p>(2.162) </p>

<p>Modal citation lag </p>

<p>0.076 </p>

<p>0.079 </p>

<p>0.070 </p>

<p>92.786 </p>

<p>227.868 </p>

<p>142.470 </p>

<p>0.110 </p>

<p>0.119 </p>

<p>0.114 </p>

<p>(0.065) </p>

<p>(0.062) </p>

<p>(0.061) </p>

<p>(504.331) </p>

<p>(546.373) </p>

<p>(503.970) </p>

<p>(0.094) </p>

<p>(0.092) </p>

<p>(0.092) </p>

<p>Continued </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table III. 
Continued </p>

<p>Estimation Method </p>

<p>Poisson </p>

<p>Tobit </p>

<p>Poisson </p>

<p>Number of Firms in Market j </p>

<p>Median Amount Invested in </p>

<p># of IPOs and Acquisitions in </p>

<p>Receiving Initial Funding in Year t </p>

<p>Market j 
in Year t </p>

<p>Market j 
in Year t </p>

<p>Dependent Variable </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>(9) </p>

<p>Number of Incum-
bents </p>

<p>−0.002 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>−34.112 </p>

<p>−14.305 </p>

<p>7.310 
−0.006 −0.005 </p>

<p>−0.005 </p>

<p>(0.002) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(0.003) </p>

<p>(30.004) </p>

<p>(37.962) </p>

<p>(42.373) 
(0.005) (0.005) </p>

<p>(0.006) </p>

<p>Incumbents squared </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>−0.000 </p>

<p>−0.000 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>−0.016 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>(0.034) </p>

<p>(0.041) </p>

<p>(0.047) 
(0.000) (0.000) </p>

<p>(0.000) </p>

<p>Growth of revenues </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>−0.078 </p>

<p>−0.073 </p>

<p>−130.503 </p>

<p>139.678 </p>

<p>144.367 </p>

<p>0.444 </p>

<p>0.343 </p>

<p>0.367 </p>

<p>(0.205) </p>

<p>(0.220) </p>

<p>(0.215) 
(1, 291.428) </p>

<p>(1, 633.240) </p>

<p>(1, 628.958) </p>

<p>(0.279) (0.279) </p>

<p>(0.278) </p>

<p>Average age of 
firms </p>

<p>−1.002 </p>

<p>−1.132 </p>

<p>−1.023 </p>

<p>−355.331 </p>

<p>−568.7817 </p>

<p>489.5794 
−0.138 −0.241 </p>

<p>−0.110 </p>

<p>"at risk" </p>

<p>(0.125)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.122)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.140)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(1436.831) </p>

<p>(1529.166) </p>

<p>(1624.668) 
(0.269) (0.252) </p>

<p>(0.261) </p>

<p>Constant </p>

<p>12.181 </p>

<p>5.470 </p>

<p>6.834 
143, 759.126 </p>

<p>124, 575.481 </p>

<p>131, 543.380 </p>

<p>13.986 </p>

<p>9.057 </p>

<p>11.278 </p>

<p>(7.723) </p>

<p>(9.490) 
(9.665) (141, 569.881) (129, 668.456) (123, 260.089) </p>

<p>(11.014) (11.764) (11.412 </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>297 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>243 </p>

<p>All regressions include market and year fixed effects. 
Robust standard errors clustered by market in parentheses. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Significant at 10%;  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 5%;  *  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 1%. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>each market in each sample year. In Table III we look at the impact of 
patent thickets on three measures of financing activity: the number of 
firms receiving an initial round of funding from external investors in 
that market-year, the median amount invested per firm in that market-
year, and the number of IPOs or acquisitions of sample firms in that 
market per year. 
In each of these regressions we focus on the total number of patents 
in force in each market at a given point in time as an explanatory 
variable. We control for market size, market structure and demand 
using market and year fixed effects, the number of incumbents (and its 
square), and the growth rate of sales. We further control for the quality 
of patents in the market using the average number of forward citations 
received per patent in force, and for the maturity of the technology in 
the market using the modal citation lag. 
As discussed above, we also present "differences-in-differences" 
estimates that make use of the fact that the expansion of software 
patentability took place at different times for different types of software. 
Though driven to some extent by pressure from patent applicants, 
arguably these changes are exogenous to the extent of the patent thicket 
in a particular market. Briefly, these regime changes were as follows. 
In 1972, the Supreme Court's ruling in Gottschalk v. Benson held that 
because software is essentially a collection of algorithms, it could not 
be patented. However, in 1981 in the Diamond v. Diehr ruling, the 
court allowed for patenting of software tied to physical or mechanical 
processes, such as the program implemented in the method for curing 
rubber at issue in the case. While patents were granted during the 
1980s for inventions with a substantial software component, and the 
distinction between patentable and nonpatentable subject matter in 
this area was progressively shifted and weakened by various court 
decisions and creative drafting of patent claims, the effectiveness of 
patent protection for software was far from clear, with many leading 
software companies filing only limited numbers of applications, or 
eschewing software patents altogether. This uncertainty was resolved 
in the mid 1990s, when the 1994 Federal Circuit decision In re Alappat 
drew a definitive distinction between unpatentable software in the form 
of "a disembodied mathematical concept. . .which in essence represents 
nothing more than a 'law of nature,' 'natural phenomenon,' or 'abstract 
idea'" and patentable software that is "rather a specific machine to 
produce a useful, concrete, and tangible result." 
30 A series of further 
court decisions in 1994 and 1995 following Alappat culminated in a new </p>

<p>30. In re Alappat, 33 F.3d 1526, 1544 (Fed. Cir. 1994), quoted in Sterne and Bugaisky, 
p. 222. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>set of guidelines, issued by the Commissioner of Patents in May of 1996, 
which allowed inventors to patent any software embodied in physical 
media. 
31 Further expansion of software patentability came in 1998 with 
the State Street Bank &amp; Trust vs. Signature Financial Corp. ("State Street") 
decision, which eliminated the requirement that the software algorithm 
be tied to a "physical transformation." 
This evolution of legal and administrative doctrine means that 
some categories of software patents became more clearly obtainable, 
and more easily enforceable before others. While software used in 
manufacturing or "embedded" in hardware devices was covered prior 
to the 1996 change in guidelines, software more generally was covered 
after 1996, and financial or business methods software became clearly 
patentable after State Street in 1998. The markets in our sample fall 
into three groups that were affected by these "regime changes" at 
different times: those for which software was patentable before 1996 
(manufacturing software), those for which it became patentable in 1996 
(other types of software not including those affected by State Street), 
and those for whom patentability increased in 1998 (financial software 
and business methods algorithms). Using the standard differences-in-
differences specification, we therefore include in the regression the 
log of the number of patents in a market, the regime-change dummy, 
and the interaction of the latter two variables. The coefficient on this 
interaction term gives the change in the effect of the market's patents 
on the dependent variable following the expansion of the strength of 
patents that are relevant to the market. 
Figure 3 shows the average number of patents granted in each 
market, grouped by the applicable regime change. As the figure shows, 
changes in the volume of patenting and the timing of these changes 
behave quite differently across the three groups, reflecting the differen-
tial impact of the regime changes in 1996 and 1998. Group 1, the set of 
software markets characterized by manufacturing applications, shows 
a stable increase over time. Group 2, the set we classify as primarily 
affected by the legal decisions following Alappat and the change in 
USPTO guidelines as of 1996, sees a dramatic jump after 1996 followed 
by a return to trend. 
32 Markets in the third group, which were affected 
by Alappat but also by State Street in 1998, see an increase after 1996 and 
continue to grow until 2000, when the USPTO began performing more 
rigorous examinations of business methods patents (the "second pair 
of eyes"). This change may account for the dip in the number of patents </p>

<p>31. Sterne and Bugaisky, p. 223. 
32. As a robustness check, we have also used 1994 (the year of the Alappat decision) 
as the date at which software became generally patentable. Results were little changed. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>1 9 7 7 
1 9 7 9 
1 9 8 1 
1 9 8 3 
1 9 8 5 
1 9 8 7 
1 9 8 9 
1 9 9 1 
1 9 9 3 
1 9 9 5 
1 9 9 7 
1 9 9 9 
2 0 0 1 
2 0 0 3 
2 0 0 5 </p>

<p>Unambiguously Patentable before 1996 </p>

<p>Unambiguously Patentable after 1996 </p>

<p>Unambiguously Patentable after 1998 </p>

<p>Unambiguously patentable before 1996: Automatic teller machine software, Robotic software, Quality control software, 
Peripheral device drivers 
Unambiguously patentable after 1996: Voice technology software, Natural language software, Neural network software, Fax 
software, Internet tools, Wide area network software, Local area network software, File management software, Hierarchical 
DBMS software, Relational DBMS software, Database query language software, 3D representation software, Electronic message 
systems software, Desktop publishing software, Artificial intelligence R&amp;D, Geographic information systems software, Disaster 
recovery software, Security/auditing software, Performance measuring software 
Unambiguously patentable after 1998: Invoicing/Billing Software, Tax preparation and reporting software, Inventory 
management software, Order entry/processing software </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. PATENTS GRANTED BY YEAR AND TYPE OF SOFT-
WARE </p>

<p>granted in Group 3 after 2000, though other factors such as backlogs 
and resource constraints at the USPTO may also be at work. </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>3.1.1 Patents and Entry </p>

<p>To provide some context, we begin by examining rates of entry into these 
markets. Table II reports coefficient estimates from Poisson regressions 
on the number of entrants in each market-year. Standard errors are 
clustered by market. Column (1) of Table II confirms the findings 
reported in Cockburn and MacGarvie (2007)-after controlling for 
market structure, demand, and so forth, 
34 the number of patents in force 
in the market has a substantial negative and significant effect on the 
number of entrants with an elasticity of −0.6. In column (2) we include 
measures of uncertainty about the scope of patent rights, with the 
negative and significant coefficient on the number of claims per patent </p>

<p>33. Similar patterns are visible when patents are counted by application year rather 
than grant year. 
34. We use dummies for the deciles of the modal citation lag to allow for a potentially 
nonlinear relationship between the stage of the product cycle and the rate of entry. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>citation suggesting that markets in which there are a preponderance of 
such "problem patents" see less entry. </p>

<p>35   Column (3) of Table II gives the "differences-in-differences" esti-
mates. The negative and significant coefficient on the interaction term 
indicates that markets with more patents saw larger reductions in 
entry following the regime change when compared with other post-
regime-change markets with fewer patents as well as preregime-change 
markets. (The positive and significant coefficient on the regime change 
dummy indicates that there was more entry into markets post-regime-
change, but this likely reflects confounding with other factors that are 
not picked up with by our controls rather than a causal effect of the 
regime shift.) In columns (4) through (7) we report results estimated 
separately for "de novo" entrants versus "diversifiers" that is, entry into 
new product markets by firms that are already established in other 
markets. The marked difference in the estimated coefficients on the 
number of patents in force and on the interaction term with the regime 
shift dummy suggest that the negative effect of patent thickets on entry 
is largely driven by the impact on the de novo entrants. 
This finding is provocative because it suggests that small, special-
ized firms were more affected by increases in the strength of IP rights 
than established firms. As argued above, one mechanism through which 
this effect may operate is the financing of early-stage firms. If increases 
in barriers to entry reduce the expected profitability of entrants, they 
will also reduce their attractiveness to investors and may make it more 
difficult for de novo entrants to raise capital. Note that coefficient on 
the interaction term with the regime shift dummy (the "treatment 
effect" from strengthening patent rights in the market) is the average 
treatment effect measured in terms of elasticities. Though it is negative 
and statistically significant at the 5% level, this coefficient conceals 
substantial differences across individual market-year observations the 
marginal "treatment effect" measured in numbers of entrants. Table II 
reports estimates of the marginal effect of the interaction term at </p>

<p>35. In regressions not reported here (but available upon request) we split the sample 
into "small" markets (with a number of incumbents below the median for that year) and 
"large" markets, to investigate the hypothesis that transaction costs matter more for entry 
into small markets while uncertainty is a more significant barrier to entry when the stakes 
are high. We found that the smaller markets had a larger patent elasticity (i.e. the effects 
of transaction costs are more substantial), and the effects of the average number of claims 
per citation were insignificant, while the share of non patent prior art was positive and 
significant. In larger markets, the number of patents in the market has a less negative but 
still statistically significant coefficient, while the effect of uncertainty as measured by the 
claims/cite ratio is stronger and more significant. The share of non patent prior art is not 
significantly related to entry in large markets. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>the 25th, 50th, and 75th percentiles of the market size distribution. </p>

<p>36   Individual estimated treatment effects are all negative, although some 
are quite small and not statistically distinguishable from zero. Larger 
marginal effects tend to be found in markets with more incumbent firms, 
suggesting a more complex relationship between the patent landscape 
and competition than is captured by this simple regression model. </p>

<p>3.1.2 Patents and Initial Funding </p>

<p>Turning to the impact of patent thickets on financing, the first three 
columns of Table III present results from Poisson regressions on the 
number of new ventures receiving their first round of financing from 
external investors. As before, standard errors are clustered by market, 
and all regressions have market and year fixed effects. The dependent 
variable is the number of firms in market j that have not previously 
received external financing and which obtain such investment for the 
first time in year t. (The following section describes in greater detail 
how this indicator is constructed, and performs a firm-level analysis 
of the probability that a firm receives initial investment by a given 
year. Here we present a preview of these findings by examining the 
broad market-level association between in initial financing episodes and 
patenting in the market.) The regressions are run on a balanced panel 
of observations on our 27 markets between 1994 and 2002, for a total of 
243 observations. 
The number of firms in a market receiving investment for the 
first time in year t will depend on the number of firms "at risk" 
(i.e., the number of early-stage firms that have not previously received 
investment). We therefore include in the regression a count of the total 
number of new ventures identified as being present in the previous 
sample year. Additional controls include the stage of development of 
firms in the market (the average age of the firms), and the same variables 
as in the entry regressions to control for demand and market structure, 
which affect the anticipated profitability of entrants. In column (1) the 
coefficient on the number of patents in force is large and negative, 
implying that software ventures that enter markets with larger patent 
thickets see are less likely to receive funding from outside investors. In 
this regression the estimated coefficient is negative and significant at 
the 10% level. </p>

<p>37 </p>

<p>36. These effects were obtained by calculating the pre-and post-regime change 
difference in the partial derivative with respect to the log of patents in the market, using 
<rs type="software">Stata</rs>'s predictnl command. This command computes standard errors via the delta method. 
See Ai and Norton (2003) for more on interaction effects in nonlinear models. 
37. With only 243 observations, a full set of market and year fixed effects, and limited 
independent variation in some of these control variables these estimates are somewhat 
sensitive to the set of controls that are included. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>In columns (2) and (3) we use the differences-in-differences 
specification, and here a significant negative coefficient is estimated on 
the interaction term with dummy for change in regime. This indicates 
that patent-intensive markets saw a significant reduction in initial 
investment by external parties in early-stage firms relative to low-
patent markets following the expansion of software patentability in the 
1990s. 
In column (3) we include measures of the uncertainty of patent 
rights. We find a negative effect on entry of the mean share of 
nonpatent references in the citations made by patents in the market. 
This result is consistent with idea that markets in which patents have 
relatively more references to the technical literature-that is, are more 
clearly distinguished from the prior art, and perhaps more likely to be 
held valid-appear to make new ventures less attractive to outside 
investors. In specifications where we include interaction terms of 
the regime shift dummy with the uncertainty variables they are not 
significant. </p>

<p>3.1.3 Patents and Funding Levels </p>

<p>Columns (4), (5) and (6) of Table III report regression results where 
the dependent variable is the median amount of financing received 
by firms active in each market in each year as reported by Ventur-
eXpert. 
38 We use tobit to estimate the model, because this variable 
is truncated at zero. These regressions perform rather poorly, with 
very few variables found to be significant. We believe this reflects 
the very high level of measurement error in the amount of financing 
received at the transaction level, which creates some very large and 
influential outliers, as well as difficulties in adequately capturing het-
erogeneity across different rounds and unobserved aspects of individual 
transactions. 
The estimated coefficient on patents in the market is negative, as 
is the coefficient on the interaction of patents with the regime change 
dummy. However, these estimates are not statistically significant. 
Similarly, the uncertainty variables have no significant effect on fund-
ing amounts, and controlling for these subtler aspects of the patent 
landscape in each market has little impact on the estimated effect of the 
number of patents in force. Note that the impact of increased uncertainty 
on funding has at least two potential effects: uncertainty may affect both </p>

<p>38. As in the previous two columns, in these regressions we again have a balanced 
sample of 27 markets, but the data end in 2002 because we construct the number of pre-
IPO firms active in the market using information from CorpTech on ownership status that 
does not go past 2002. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>the timing of investment and the amount invested and our measure 
conflates the two effects. </p>

<p>3.1.4 Patents and "Exit" </p>

<p>Finally, columns (7) and (8) and (9) in Table III present results from 
a Poisson regression on the number of sample firms "exiting" via 
either IPO or acquisition in each market per year. The coefficient 
estimates suggest that relative to markets with fewer patents, markets 
with a large number of patents in force are associated with a lower 
volume of "exits." Strengthening patents appears to make software 
enterprises less attractive to public markets or other outside investors, 
though the coefficient is only significant at the 10% level. (Adding or 
dropping control variables, or relying exclusively on market and year 
fixed effects, can make some of these estimates statistically significant.) 
We also recognize that there may be difficulties in identifying this 
effect separately from other factors affecting IPOs. For example, the 
"tech stock" bubble of the late 1990s is somewhat coincident with 
the changes in legal regime. We experimented with using the level of 
the NASDAQ index and the book-to-market ratio in the ICT industry 
as control variables but found that their inclusion did not substantially 
alter the main findings and we concluded that the influence of aggregate 
forces such as these were better captured by the year dummies included 
in these regressions. 
We find similar results for the association of the uncertainty 
measures with the volume of IPO and acquisition activity. While the 
estimated effects of some of the uncertainty measures are large, they are 
not statistically significant. </p>

<p>3.2 Impact of Patent Thickets at the Firm Level </p>

<p>The market-level results, though provocative, do not permit any inves-
tigation of our other hypotheses about the impact on uncertainty about 
patent-related costs on the timing of outside investment. By looking at 
firm-level data, we can measure the timing of investments at different 
stages in the growth of new ventures, and test for any impact of patent 
thickets and our other measures of uncertainty about the scope of 
patent rights. We can also control for the degree to which investors' 
concerns about patent thickets are mitigated by new ventures holding 
their own patents. Cockburn and MacGarvie (2007) find a substantial 
positive effect of own patent holdings on the probability of entry into a 
market, suggesting that this may also be an important factor in funding 
decisions. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>3.2.1 Receipt of Initial Funding from VCs and 
Corporate Investors </p>

<p>We hypothesize that, if patent thickets reduce a venture's expected 
profits, investors faced with two otherwise identical companies will 
choose the one operating in a less "thicketed" market. 
In order to test this, we would ideally have a dataset comprising 
firms that sought external funding and were either granted or denied 
such funding. While this type of data is very difficult to find, we have 
created what we believe to be a reasonable approximation of such a 
dataset using a subsample of firms extracted from the CorpTech direc-
tory. CorpTech lists more than 19,000 companies producing software 
that were active at some point between 1992 and 2004, but is unlikely to 
capture the entire population of software firms. To the extent that firms 
that appear on CorpTech have passed some threshold of success that 
warrants their inclusion in the directory, our sample may not be entirely 
representative of the universe of entrepreneurial companies. Inference 
based on firm-level census data would allow for unbiased estimates of 
the effects of patent thickets on investment in early-stage firms. Lacking 
such data, our estimates may therefore provide a lower bound for the 
effects of interest. 
From the CorpTech sample we select firms founded in 1990 or 
later that are active in no more than one of our 27 product classes. For 
firms that appear in CorpTech more than 1 year after being founded, 
we extrapolate the firm-level data on firm size backward. We eliminate 
firms that have already gone public or been acquired. 
CorpTech reports the initial source(s) of capital for the firm, for all 
smaller firms founded between 1992 and 2002. This variable allows us 
to construct a database comprising firms that obtain funding at an early 
stage from venture capitalists or corporate investors and firms that do 
not obtain such funding. We use CorpTech to identify the set of firms that 
did and did not receive funding, and we use VentureXpert to identify the 
timing of first investment. Kaplan et al. (2002) show that VentureXpert 
omits 15% of financing rounds and 20% of financing committed. To 
ensure that we do not mistakenly classify firms that receive external 
funding but are not listed on VentureXpert, we drop from the sample 290 
firms that are listed on CorpTech as having VC or corporate investment 
prior to 2002 but that do not appear on VentureXpert. We also drop firms 
for which no information is available from CorpTech on initial sources 
of capital. We are left with a sample of 951 firms, of which 475 receive 
external funding for the first time between 1992 and 2002. 
Using information on the first round of investment from Ventur-
eXpert, we create a dummy variable equal to 1 if firm i receives venture 
or corporate financing for the first time in year t, 0 before year t, and </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 </p>

<p>time since firm founding 
fraction of firrms not yet receiving funding </p>

<p>No. of patents in market below 25th percentile </p>

<p>No. of patents in market between 25th and 75th percentiles </p>

<p>No. of patents in market between 75th and 95th percentiles </p>

<p>No. of patents in market above 90th percentile </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. SURVIVAL FUNCTIONS FOR THE HAZARD OF OBTAIN-
ING OUTSIDE FUNDING </p>

<p>missing after year t. This variable takes on a value of zero in all years for 
firms that never receive funding before 2002. We then perform duration 
analysis using the Cox Proportional-Hazard model. </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Figure 4 gives the Kaplan-Meier survival curves estimated from 
these data for firms grouped by where their target market falls in the dis-
tribution of the numbers of patents in force per market. Here "survival" 
means failure to attract outside funding, and the survival functions plot 
the fraction of firms that have yet to receive funding as a function of 
time elapsed since they were founded. As can be seen from the figure, it 
takes about 5 years on average for 50% of firms to get their first round of 
funding. Separate survival functions are estimated for markets falling 
in various percentiles of the "thicketedness" distribution. 
There are no striking differences across these groups of markets. 
However, once the survival functions are adjusted for the size of the 
market (number of incumbents and number of incumbents squared), </p>

<p>39. Essentially similar results are obtained using logit Discrete-Time Hazard models. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 </p>

<p>time since firm founding 
fraction of firms not yet receiving outside funding </p>

<p>No. of patents in market below 25th percentile </p>

<p>No. of patents in market between 25th and 75th percentiles </p>

<p>No. of patents in market between 75th and 95th percentiles 
No. of patents in market above 90th percentile </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. SURVIVAL FUNCTIONS FOR THE HAZARD OF OB-
TAINING OUTSIDE FUNDING, ADJUSTED FOR THE NUMBER OF 
INCUMBENTS IN EACH MARKET </p>

<p>we see quite striking differences in the impact of patent thickets. 
40 As 
can be seen in Figure 5, the estimated survival functions for different 
groups of markets show that software ventures in the most thicketed 
markets have a very small probability of obtaining outside funding in 
any given year and thus on average receive outside funding much later 
than firms operating in less thicketed markets. Moving from the most 
thicketed groups to the least, each survival function falls below that for 
the previous quartile: for any given duration since firm founding, the 
fraction of firms not received outside funding is lower in less thicketed 
markets. 
These results show the importance of controlling for market 
characteristics, and in the hazard models, our explanatory variables 
include year and product market fixed effects and the modal citation 
lag for patents in the market. Other market-level controls relating 
to profitability in the firm's target market include the number of </p>

<p>40. These graphs were created using <rs type="software">Stata</rs>'s sts command, which estimates separate 
Cox regressions for each percentile group. Adjusting for the number of incumbents means 
that the number of incumbents and the number of incumbents squared were included as 
covariates in the Cox regression. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>incumbents in the market and the number of incumbents squared, and 
the growth of sales in the market. 
41 Variables relating to the patent 
landscape include the log of the patent stock in the market and the 
Herfindahl over assignees of citations made by patents in the market. </p>

<p>42   Firm-level explanatory variables include the aforementioned dummies 
for firm size range, implicitly the age of the firm (because the "duration" 
variable is years since the birth of the firm), and the number of each 
firm's patents granted and pending. </p>

<p>43 </p>

<p>Table IV gives results from these regressions, reported as hazard 
ratios. Estimates larger than one indicating a positive effect on the 
hazard of receiving funding, and estimates less than one indicating 
a negative effect. In general the hazard of funding is nonlinearly related 
to the number of competitors in the market, with an initial increase-
presumably reflecting an increase in expected profits due to a reduction 
in the market power of incumbents or a reduction of barriers to entry 
created by network effects-then falling as the number of incumbents 
increases, which could reflect the fact that large numbers of incumbents 
indicate more mature, more crowded, and less attractive markets. The 
dummies for the range of firm size (not reported, but available upon 
request) display a concave relationship between firm size and the hazard 
of initial funding. The standard errors in these regressions are somewhat 
sensitive to the selection of control variables, but adding or dropping 
control variables has little effect on the estimated coefficients on the 
patent variables. 
The "patent landscape" variables display a pattern consistent with 
several of our hypotheses. In all of the regressions, increases in the 
total number of patents in the market are associated with a substantial 
reduction in the hazard of receiving funding (or, equivalently, longer 
delays in receiving funding). Conversely, we find a positive and sig-
nificant effect on the hazard of receiving funding for software ventures 
that have their own patents. Consistent with the idea that investors 
are forward-looking (and with anecdotal evidence about interaction </p>

<p>41. The inclusion of a proxy for the CR4 of sales in the market was rejected by a 
likelihood ratio test. The same is true of the log of the number of forward citations per 
patent in the market. 
42. This is computed by taking patents associated with a given market (SOF) in 
application year t, and calculating the share of their backward citations received by each 
of a set of assignees. Assignee names were cleaned using a combination of an algorithm 
and manual inspection. Backward citations to patents granted no more than ten years 
previously are omitted. 
43. We also tried including controls for characteristics of the investors in each venture 
(total patents held by investors, the receipt of earlier rounds of funding corporate investors 
as opposed to VCs, and the cumulative number of IPOs by firms in which investors had 
previously invested) and of the venture itself (total amount invested to date, and number 
of patents held.). These variables were not significant. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table IV. </p>

<p>Hazard model of initial funding episode </p>

<p>Dummies for Year, Market and Employment Size Range Category Included. Standard Errors Clustered by Firm </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Patent Variables </p>

<p>Full Sample </p>

<p>Post-Regime Change </p>

<p>Discrete-Time </p>

<p>Ln (Patents in Market) </p>

<p>0.748 </p>

<p>0.767 </p>

<p>0.209 </p>

<p>0.155 </p>

<p>0.201 </p>

<p>0.935 </p>

<p>(0.274) </p>

<p>(0.268) </p>

<p>(0.160)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.120)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.161)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.350) </p>

<p>Firm's patents granted </p>

<p>0.963 
(0.050) </p>

<p>Firm's patents pending </p>

<p>1.161 </p>

<p>1.154 </p>

<p>1.149 </p>

<p>1.149 </p>

<p>1.148 </p>

<p>1.243 </p>

<p>(0.050)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.047)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.049)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.049)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.049)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.080)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>D(Regime Change) </p>

<p>3.024 </p>

<p>4.069 </p>

<p>(2.657) </p>

<p>(4.065) </p>

<p>D(Regime Change) × </p>

<p>ln </p>

<p>0.776 </p>

<p>0.749 </p>

<p>(Patents in Market) </p>

<p>(0.095)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.105)  *  *  </p>

<p>Herfindahl of citations </p>

<p>0.998 </p>

<p>in market </p>

<p>(0.001)  *  </p>

<p>Average claims per 
citation in market </p>

<p>3.479 
(4.484) </p>

<p>Share of non-patent 
prior art </p>

<p>0.051 
(0.576) </p>

<p>Control Variables </p>

<p># incumbents </p>

<p>1.004 </p>

<p>1.005 </p>

<p>1.009 </p>

<p>1.009 </p>

<p>1.009 </p>

<p>1.005 </p>

<p>(0.002)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.002)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.004)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.004)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.004)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.002)  *  *  </p>

<p># incumbents squared </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>0.999 </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.000)  *  *  *  </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>Table IV. 
Continued </p>

<p>Dummies for Year, Market and Employment Size Range Category Included. Standard Errors Clustered by Firm </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>Patent Variables </p>

<p>Full Sample </p>

<p>Post-Regime Change </p>

<p>Discrete-Time </p>

<p>Growth of revenues </p>

<p>0.831 </p>

<p>0.818 </p>

<p>0.930 </p>

<p>0.953 </p>

<p>0.878 </p>

<p>0.845 </p>

<p>(0.123) </p>

<p>(0.120) </p>

<p>(0.173) </p>

<p>(0.176) </p>

<p>(0.168) </p>

<p>(0.136) </p>

<p>F i r m s i z e r a n g e e f f e c t s </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y e a r e f f e c t s </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>M a r k e t e f f e c t s </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Log likelihood </p>

<p>−2819.306 </p>

<p>−2816.983 </p>

<p>−2180.497 </p>

<p>−2179.015 </p>

<p>−2179.775 </p>

<p>−1356.805 </p>

<p>Number of observations </p>

<p>5357 </p>

<p>5357 </p>

<p>3704 </p>

<p>3704 </p>

<p>3704 </p>

<p>5356 </p>

<p>Marginal Effects of Selected Patent Variables </p>

<p>ln Patents in market </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>(6) </p>

<p>marginal effect of one 
std. dev. increase </p>

<p>−0.012 </p>

<p>−0.011 </p>

<p>−0.038 </p>

<p>−0.041 </p>

<p>−0.039 </p>

<p>−0.003 </p>

<p>Firm's Patents pending 
marginal effect of one 
unit increase </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>D(Regime Change) × </p>

<p>ln </p>

<p>(Patents in Market) 
Average marginal effect </p>

<p>of one log-unit 
increase in patents </p>

<p>−0.009 </p>

<p>Average standard error </p>

<p>of marginal effect </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>Coefficients expressed as hazard ratios. </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>significant at 10%;  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 5%;  *  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 1%. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>of start-ups with venture capitalists) a much larger and statistically 
significant effect is found for the number of patents pending than for 
the number of patents granted. 
44 This finding is consistent with the 
results of Haussler, Harhoff, and Muller (2009), who also find that 
patent applications matter for the financing of start-up firms while 
patent grants do not. 
In column (2), the differences-in-differences specification shows 
that the negative effect of patent thickets is larger in markets where 
patent rights were strengthened relative to those where it was not. A 
one standard deviation increase in the number of patents in the market 
is associated with a reduction in the hazard of being funded of about one 
percentage point. This effect is much larger after the regime changes, 
with for a one standard deviation increase in the patent stock in the 
market associated with a 0.04 reduction in the hazard of funding. Given 
that the mean probability of obtaining funding in a given year is 0.086 
overall and 0.101 after the regime changes, this effect appears to be of 
considerable importance. The significance of these results is robust to 
clustering at the market level. The "average treatment effect" implied 
by the interaction term is of similar magnitude, estimated from a logit 
discrete-time version of the Cox continuous-time model. 
Comparing estimates using the full sample of data to those 
obtained for the subsample of observations after the regime change 
shows that the impact of patent thickets was much larger during this 
latter period. Consistent with the quite large negative interaction term 
effect in column (2), the hazard of receiving funding is substantially 
lower for this subsample than for the full sample. The marginal effect 
of the number of patents in force is almost four times larger after 1996 
than for the full sample. 
Column (4) of Table IV reports results from including the Herfind-
ahl index of citations across assignees, a measure of the concentration 
of ownership of patent rights which is our proxy for bargaining costs. 
(We report results only for the post-regime subsample. Coefficients were 
insignificant but of the same sign and similar magnitude when the same 
specification was used on the full sample.) In contrast to the hypotheses 
about bargaining costs and the concentration of patent ownership 
discussed above, we find a negative and borderline significant (with a p-
value of 0.051) effect on the hazard of receiving initial funding. In other 
words, an initial round of funding by external investors is less likely to be </p>

<p>44. To limit the influence of a small number of outliers in the number of patents 
granted and pending, we winsorize these variables at the 99.9 th percentile. Similar results 
were obtained using lower percentile cutoffs. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>obtained by software ventures operating in markets where IP ownership 
is more concentrated. Our alternative measure of bargaining costs, a 
quadratic in the number of cited assignees, was not significant. This 
finding contrasts with other papers in the literature, such as Ziedonis  (2004) and Noel and Schankerman (2007). It is more consistent with 
an alternative story laid out in Galasso and Schankerman (2008), in 
which increases in fragmentation of ownership of IP reduce the amount 
at stake in licensing negotiations and thus reduce the probability of 
litigation. </p>

<p>3.2.2 Exits </p>

<p>Table V presents results of a model of the probability that a new venture 
ultimately "exits" from the entrepreneurial phase by going public or 
being acquired by another firm, as opposed to continuing to operate as 
an independent privately held firm (or being liquidated.) Most of the 
information on the dates of IPO or M&amp;A comes from VentureXpert. For 
a subset of firms that are listed on CorpTech as having gone public or 
been acquired by 2002, we performed lexis-nexis and web searches to 
obtain the dates of these events. Firms that were founded after 1990 
and are listed as private on CorpTech as of 2002 for which there is no 
date of IPO on VentureXpert are assumed not to have gone public in 
the interim. 
45 Although not all of the firms contained in the time-to-
first funding sample analyzed in Table IV are included in the dataset 
analyzed in Table V, the number of observations in Table V is larger than 
in Table IV because firms exit the time-to-first funding sample once they 
receive their first round of funding. The market-level variables are as 
described above. </p>

<p>46   The unit of observation for this analysis is a calendar year, and in 
columns (1), (2), and (3) we use a Cox proportional hazard model. As in 
Table IV, coefficients presented in the table are hazard ratios. 
The last two columns of Table V give results from estimating 
a competing risks discrete time hazard model in which we use a 
multinomial logit for the probability in each period of "exit" versus 
IPO, "exit" via acquisition. The dependent variable is equal to 0 in each 
year prior to exit via IPO or acquisition, 1 in the year that the firm goes 
public, and 2 when the firm exits via acquisition. Firms that are censored </p>

<p>45. While it is conceivable that a firm could have gone public and then returned to 
privately held status by 2002 without showing up on VentureXpert, we feel the number 
of firms in our sample for which this could be true is very small. 
46. The coefficient on this variable is not reported but is available upon request. We 
also estimated models in which an observation was a firm-round, rather than a firm-year, 
and obtained comparable results. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>Table V. </p>

<p>Duration Model of IPO/Acquisition </p>

<p>Dummies for Year, Market, and Employment Size Range Included. Standard Errors Clustered by Firm. </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>(4) </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>Cox Proportional-Hazards Model </p>

<p>Competing Risks Model </p>

<p>All Firms </p>

<p>Firms Without Patents </p>

<p>All Firms </p>

<p>Patent Variables </p>

<p>IPO </p>

<p>M&amp;A </p>

<p>Ln (Patents in the market) </p>

<p>0.525 </p>

<p>0.529 </p>

<p>0.998 </p>

<p>0.194 </p>

<p>0.896 </p>

<p>(0.268) </p>

<p>(0.268) </p>

<p>(0.664) </p>

<p>(0.215) </p>

<p>(0.562) </p>

<p>Firm's patents pending </p>

<p>1.092 </p>

<p>1.094 </p>

<p>1.291 </p>

<p>0.832 </p>

<p>(0.046) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.046) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.074) </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p>(0.158) </p>

<p>Firm's patents granted </p>

<p>1.019 </p>

<p>1.111 </p>

<p>0.940 </p>

<p>1.148 </p>

<p>(0.033) </p>

<p>(0.124) </p>

<p>(0.072) </p>

<p>(0.059) </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p>D(Regime change) </p>

<p>5.201 </p>

<p>13.572 </p>

<p>(7.970) </p>

<p>(23.851) </p>

<p>D(Regime change) × </p>

<p>Ln(Market's </p>

<p>patents) </p>

<p>0.709 </p>

<p>0.596 </p>

<p>(0.156) </p>

<p>(0.154) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>D(Regime change) × </p>

<p>Firm's patent </p>

<p>grants) </p>

<p>0.915 </p>

<p>Control variables </p>

<p>(0.105) </p>

<p>Number of incumbents </p>

<p>0.864 </p>

<p>0.951 </p>

<p>1.235 </p>

<p>1.676 </p>

<p>0.528 </p>

<p>(0.250) </p>

<p>(0.298) </p>

<p>(0.487) </p>

<p>(0.851) </p>

<p>(0.238) </p>

<p>Incumbents squared </p>

<p>1.019 </p>

<p>1.013 </p>

<p>0.989 </p>

<p>0.958 </p>

<p>1.080 </p>

<p>(0.031) </p>

<p>(0.032) </p>

<p>(0.039) </p>

<p>(0.065) </p>

<p>(0.050) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>Growth of sales in market </p>

<p>1.204 </p>

<p>1.165 </p>

<p>1.100 </p>

<p>1.080 </p>

<p>1.424 </p>

<p>(0.292) </p>

<p>(0.286) </p>

<p>(0.335) </p>

<p>(0.499) </p>

<p>(0.431) </p>

<p>modal citation lag </p>

<p>1.169 </p>

<p>1.170 </p>

<p>1.211 </p>

<p>1.305 </p>

<p>1.033 </p>

<p>(0.082) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.082) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.110) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.276) </p>

<p>(0.094) </p>

<p>Corporate </p>

<p>1.651 </p>

<p>1.646 </p>

<p>1.838 </p>

<p>1.801 </p>

<p>1.597 </p>

<p>(0.362) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.360) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.467) </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>(0.725) </p>

<p>(0.490) </p>

<p>VC backing </p>

<p>1.177 </p>

<p>1.178 </p>

<p>1.360 </p>

<p>1.376 </p>

<p>1.045 </p>

<p>(0.180) </p>

<p>(0.180) </p>

<p>(0.238) </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>(0.382) </p>

<p>(0.200) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>9054 </p>

<p>9054 </p>

<p>7839 </p>

<p>9054 </p>

<p>9054 </p>

<p>Robust standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p> *  
significant at 10%;  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 5%;  *  *  *  </p>

<p>significant at 1%. </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>or liquidated take on a value of zero in all periods. (Competing risks 
can be estimated using this type of multinomial logit model provided 
the competing risks are independent, see Allison (1982). 
Consistent with the market-level results on IPOs, we find that 
the hazard of going public or being acquired is generally lower in 
markets with more patents, though the coefficient is not significant. 
We also find that the hazard of exiting from the sample in these ways 
is increasing in the number of pending patents owned by the venture 
(a strongly significant effect) and is substantially higher for VC-backed 
and corporate investor-backed firms. 
In the differences-in-differences specification in column (2) we 
find a negative and insignificant effect of the number of patents in 
the market on the probability of exiting via IPO or acquisition, an 
insignificant positive effect of the regime shift dummy, 
47 and a negative 
but insignificant interaction effect of the legal regime change with the 
number of patents in the market. As with the model for hazard of initial 
funding the firm's own patents pending have a strongly significant 
positive effect on the probability if getting outside investment, but not 
patents granted. Note also that the regime shift has an insignificant 
interaction with the firm's own patents. 
The impact of patent thickets is apparent when we estimate the 
model on the subset of firms that did not obtain any patents of their 
own (column (3).) Here the estimated "treatment effect" of the regime 
shift is substantially more negative, and statistically significant. This 
finding is striking in light of the fact that only a minority of the firms 
in our sample hold patents by the time of exit (approximately 20% 
have patents granted by the time of IPO/acquisition). An important 
question for future research is why, given the apparent differences in 
success rates between patent-holding and firms that do not hold patents, 
relatively few firms in these markets filed patents during this time 
period. 
The competing risks model results are presented in columns (5) 
and (6). We cannot reject the hypothesis that the effect of number 
of patents in the market is the same for IPO and acquisition. In-
terestingly, while granted patents do not matter for IPOs, they are 
positively and significantly associated with the probability of being 
acquired. </p>

<p>47. The main effect of the regime shift dummy is very difficult to estimate in this 
sample due to collinearity with market and year fixed effects, and some very small cell 
counts. The estimated hazard ratios of 14 or 15 reported in the table have very large 
standard errors and should not be taken literally. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>4. Summary and Conclusions </p>

<p>The impact of stronger intellectual property rights in the software 
industry is controversial. One often underemphasized means by which 
patents can affect technical change, industry dynamics, and ultimately 
welfare, is through their role in stimulating or stifling entry by new 
ventures. The mechanisms through which patents can impact this 
process are, as ever, complex. Patents can block entry, or raise entrants' 
costs in variety of ways, while at the same time they may stimulate entry 
by improving the bargaining position of entrants vis-à-vis incumbents, 
and supporting a "market for technology," which enables new ventures 
to license their way into the market, or realize value through other forms 
of trade in their intangible assets. Some of the impact of patent thickets 
may therefore be felt in the interaction of new ventures with the capital 
markets, and here we find evidence that the extraordinary growth in 
patenting of software has had a variety of effects on the financing of 
software companies. 
Our analysis of an unique dataset that contains information on 
software ventures that do not obtain outside funding as well as those 
that do attract VC and corporate investments provides evidence that 
patents significantly affect the likelihood of obtaining funding for early-
stage firms. Firms in "thicketed" markets with large numbers of patents 
are less likely to receive funding from outside investors at both early 
and late stages in the entrepreneurial process compared to those in 
markets with fewer patents. In aggregate, start-up software companies 
operating in markets characterized by larger patent thickets see their 
initial round of VC or corporate funding delayed relative to firms in 
markets less affected by patents. In firm-level analyses that control for 
additional characteristics of start-up firms, we find similar results. We 
also find that changes in the legal regime that strengthened patent rights 
made the association between patents in a market and the probability 
of receiving initial outside funding significantly more negative. Our 
results suggest that there is less entry into markets where patents on 
average have a higher ratio of claims made to the amount of prior 
cited, which we interpret as a proxy for uncertainty about the quality of 
patents in a market. However, these results were not found in the firm-
level models of timing of funding from outside investors or liquidity 
events. 
One of the most statistically robust (and provocative) findings 
of this paper is the importance of new ventures obtaining their own 
patents. Firms that have higher numbers of their own patents are 
more likely to receive funding from outside investors, and more likely 
to subsequently "exit" from the entrepreneurial phase through IPO </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>



<p>or acquisition. Interestingly, the number of a firm's patents pending 
is positively and significantly related to the probability of obtaining 
external funding, while the number of patents already granted is not-
holding constant the number of patents granted, outside investors 
appear to be more focused on these firms' "pipeline" of IP assets under 
development. The estimated effect is quite large: each additional patent 
pending increases the hazard of funding by around 15%. 
One interpretation of these results is simply that patents reflect the 
value of the firm's technology: firms with higher quality innovations 
obtain more patents and are also more attractive to outside investors. 
However, patents may also convey other information. For example 
these findings may in part reflect the value to outside investors of the 
ability to obtain patents as signal of the quality of a new venture's 
management. Hsu and Ziedonis (2007) show that larger numbers of 
patent applications are associated with higher valuations of early-stage 
semiconductor companies, and attribute this in part to factors other 
than the information about a firm's technology that is provided by 
patents. Beyond this "capabilities" argument, we suggest that when 
faced with a patent thicket, patents also confer significant competitive 
advantages on entrant firms in minimizing transactions costs associated 
with incumbents' patent holdings. 
Unfortunately, it is hard to disentangle these effects in these 
data without independent information about the value of nonpatented 
innovations. Nonetheless, we find it striking that only 20% of the firms in 
our funding regression sample (and only 33% of the firms that ultimately 
got funding) ever filed for a patent during our sample period. If the 
benefits from holding patents are as substantial as our results suggest, 
it is puzzling why more of the firms that were active in these markets 
during this period did not obtain them. One explanation may be that 
causality between funding and patent applications runs in the opposite 
direction: it may be that investors require early-stage firms to file patent 
applications as a condition of receiving funds, or that applications are 
observed disproportionately by firms that get funding and are more 
able to support the substantial costs of patent prosecution. In these 
data we only observe applications that are subsequently granted, so 
this may be a significant source of bias if large numbers of unobserved 
applications are abandoned by firms who are not funded. 
This paper documents a number of mechanisms through which 
patents confer private benefits to software companies. Patent thick-
ets appear to offer significant protection to incumbent firms, and 
their presence also appears to have given entrant firms a pow-
erful incentive to acquire their own patents. These effects are re-
flected in the extraordinary surge in patenting in this industry. </p>



<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>

<p>However, these incentives to obtain patents may ultimately become 
collectively self-destructive. Our differences-in-differences estimates 
of the relative impact of strengthening patent rights show a general 
intensification of the negative association with entry and financing 
in the most heavily thicketed markets. Continued accumulation of 
patents therefore could potentially result in the "stifling" effects 
identified here substantially offsetting the "stimulating" effect on 
innovation. </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>Table AI. 
Timing of Regime Changes in Software 
Patentability for Markets in the Sample </p>

<p>Pre-1996 
ba_a 
Automatic teller machine software 
ma_c 
Robotic software 
ma_q 
Quality control software 
ut_h 
Peripheral device drivers 
After 1996 
ai_a 
Voice technology software 
ai_l 
Natural language software 
ai_n 
Neural network software 
cs_f 
Fax software 
cs_i 
Internet tools 
cs_l 
Wide area network software 
cs_w 
Local area network software 
dm_f 
File management software 
dm_mh 
Hierarchical DBMS software 
dm_mr 
Relational DBMS software 
dm_q 
Database query language software 
oa_gd 
3D representation software 
oa_me 
Electronic message systems software 
oa_p 
Desktop publishing software 
sv_ar 
Artificial intelligence R&amp;D 
ts_er 
Geographic information systems software 
ts_er 
Geographic information systems software 
ut_r 
Disaster recovery software 
ut_x 
Security/auditing software 
ut_y 
Performance measuring software 
After 1998 
ac_b 
Invoicing/Billing Software 
ac_t 
Tax preparation and reporting software 
wd_i 
Inventory management software 
wd_o 
Order entry/processing software </p>

<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>







<p>Journal of Economics &amp; Management Strategy </p>



<p>Patents, Thickets and the Financing of Early-Stage Firms </p>





</text></tei>