<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Ftwec.12479" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>I </p>

<p>N the recent past -perhaps owing to perceptions of increased uncertainty in the wake of 
the Great Recession and the related slowdown in the growth of world trade -a number of 
long-term economic projections have been made, ranging from a time horizon of several 
decades to almost one hundred years ahead, with some of these studies also touching upon the 
prospects for international trade. These include qualitative, multidisciplinary analyses, such as 
European Commission (2012), multisector partial equilibrium models, such as IMF (2012) as 
well as computable general equilibrium (CGE) models, such as World Bank (2007). While the 
studies make assumptions about productivity advances, which then shape sectoral develop-
ments, they do not employ an explicit model of economic growth. Other studies, such as Duval  and de la Maisonneuve (2010), Four e et al. (2013), Asian Development Bank (2011) and  OECD (2012), provide economic growth projections over the long term. Only a few papers 
have combined the two approaches, linking models of economic growth to sectoral simula-
tions. Petri and Zhai (2013) use the growth projections by the ADB (2011) as a baseline for 
their CGE model. They focus on the economic prospects of the Association of Southeast Asian 
Nations (ASEAN), China and India by the year 2030. Anderson and Strutt (2012) make predic-
tions for Asia at the same time horizon (2030), supplementing the growth predictions from 
ADB (2011) with the ones from Four e et al. (2013) for countries not contained in the former 
study. Finally, Fontagn e et al. (2013) combine <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">CEPII</rs>'s macroeconomic model (<rs id="software-1" type="software">MaGE</rs>) with 
its multisectoral dynamic CGE model of the world economy (<rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>). This study considers 
economic prospects up to the year 2100, making some simplifying assumptions about key 
exogenous variables, and principally aims at providing a baseline for the evaluation of climate 
change policies, although some sectoral and trade issues are discussed as well. 
Our paper seeks to extend this relatively small, but rapidly expanding body of the literature 
in a number of ways: first, using the methodology described in detail in Fontagn e and Four e 
(2013), we combine an explicit economic growth model with a multisectoral model in order 
to construct scenarios for the world as a whole (around 150 countries) up to a maximum time 
horizon (year 2035), for which reasonable forecasts of a number of key variables (e.g. energy 
prices, demographics) can be obtained from specialised institutions (e.g. IEA, 2011; UNPD, </p>

<p>The opinions expressed in this paper are not meant to represent the positions or opinions of the WTO 
and its members and are without prejudice to members' rights and obligations under the WTO. The 
authors would like to thank Olivier Cadot, Lucian Cernat, Patrick Low, Marcelo Olarreaga, Fr ed eric 
Robert-Nicoud and Robert Teh as well as conference participants at the University of Geneva, Univer-
sity of Mauritius, European Commission and WTO for helpful comments on this paper. All errors and 
omissions remain our own. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>The World Economy (2017) 
doi: 10.1111/twec.12479 </p>

<p>The World Economy </p>

<p>2011). To the best of our knowledge, our study is the only exercise at this extensive geo-
graphic and timescale, while remaining grounded in realistic assumptions about key economic 
variables. Second, unlike other papers, we provide an entirely consistent modelling frame-
work, which makes the macroeconomic scenarios fully traceable throughout the sectoral simu-
lations. This is crucial to be able to identify the relative importance of key economic drivers 
of future developments. Third, we undertake to examine to what extent the main trends that 
have strongly altered the volume, composition, geography and nature of international trade in 
recent times (WTO, 2013) are likely to continue or reverse over the next decades. This is 
important in order to be able to identify challenges that may arise from possible changes to 
existing trade developments. Finally, given the wide scope of our simulations, we are able to 
determine the policy implications of different scenarios for different groups of countries, 
which may allow policymakers to focus on the issues of principal concern to their constituen-
cies and evaluate their options. 
The paper is organised as follows: Section 2 briefly describes the macroeconomic and trade 
scenarios we implement and highlights key methodological advantages as well as limitations 
of our approach. Section 3 examines the relative impact of the main fundamental economic 
driving forces. In Section 4, we analyse whether, under these scenarios, major trends in trade 
are likely to continue. In both of these sections, we discuss what the implications would be 
for different groups of countries. Section 5 concludes providing an overview of major policy 
challenges ahead and ideas for further work. </p>

<p>2. METHODOLOGY AND SCENARIOS </p>

<p>First, this section discusses the advantages and limitations of our dynamic CGE approach. 
Second, the scenarios in terms of shocks to various economic and trade variables are intro-
duced. </p>

<p>a. Methodology and Limitations </p>

<p>This paper combines CGE modelling (<rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>) with the macroeconometric model 
<rs type="software">MaGE 1</rs> to address the sectoral implications of the envisaged growth trajectory of national 
economies. 
2 The driving forces of the changes modelled with MIRAGE are the change in 
countries' GDP per capita, the (sectorally differentiated) gains in total factor productivity 
(TFP) by these countries, their changing comparative advantage and evolving country sizes. 
On the demand size, country size and GDP per capita determine the size of markets and 
demand composition. With the reshaping of the world economy, the patterns of international 
demand will be affected profoundly. Meanwhile, the capabilities of countries will change, as 
developing economies accumulate human capital, invest in infrastructure and new production 
capacities and progressively catch up in terms of efficiency. Finally, markets will change as 
well as exporters, leading to a profound revamping of world trade patterns. MIRAGE is pro-
viding a detailed description of these changes for a given classification of countries and 
regions and a given sectoral aggregation of traded goods and services. The transformations of </p>

<p>1 The versions used in this paper are, respectively, <rs id="software-5" type="software">MIRAGE-e</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">1.0</rs> (based on GTAP 7) and <rs id="software-6" type="software">MaGE</rs> <rs corresp="#software-6" type="version-number">2.1</rs>. 
2 A methodological companion paper to the policy-oriented analysis presented here discusses the two 
modelling frameworks used in great depth. See Fontagn e and Four e (2013). Both are also jointly referred 
to in WTO (2013). </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD 
37 </p>

<p>bilateral and sectoral trade flows are driving changes in the sectoral value added in each coun-
try, which leads to a reallocation of resources and ultimately changes in factor prices. Last 
but not least, these reference trajectories will be 'bent' by the shocks to trade costs or the 
migratory movements simulated in various scenarios. 
To track these repercussions, CGE modelling is essential. The even bigger advantage of 
CGE analysis is its internal consistency: markets are cleared; what is produced somewhere is 
bought elsewhere; available production factors bind the production capacities of countries; 
sectors must invest to produce; excess demand will be covered by net imports; the external 
account will be balanced by capital flows when needed or else the real exchange rate (country 
competitiveness) will have to adjust. Such intrinsic consistency is precious when it comes to 
addressing issues of an extremely high dimensionality, with many countries growing at differ-
ent speeds, trading with each other in various sectors ranging from agriculture to business ser-
vices. In our mind, this intrinsic consistency in the representation of the changing patterns of 
the world economy, when all factors of growth are combined at the country level, is an enor-
mous asset to conduct large-scale and medium-term foresight activities. Still, it has limits 
which have to be kept in mind when interpreting the results. These limits are either common 
to any CGE model of this type, or specific to the version of <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs> used here. 
Common to all CGE approaches are the simplicity of the functional forms describing agent 
behaviour and the rather aggregated representation of the world economy, both imposed by 
computational constraints. The downside of such aggregation is that models do not track what is 
happening within a given sector in a given region. Similarly, simple functional forms (e.g. the 
absence of intertemporal optimisation by individual agents) imply that the dynamics of the 
model are rather elementary -meaning sequential. The model is solved sequentially, on a yearly 
step, and transition from one period to the next relies on changes in capital depletion, the sec-
toral allocation of new capital as well as changes in the labour force, TFP and energy efficiency. 
Also, the parameterisation of key behavioural parameters is rather crude and hardly addresses 
individual countries' idiosyncrasies. As sectors are aggregated, models do not fully reflect what 
could happen within a sector affected by, for example, a tariff cut on one product. Changes in 
tariffs, as any obstacles to trade, are modelled at the sectoral level, even if shocked at the most 
detailed level before aggregation. This implies that the impact of changes in trade costs (which 
depends on the variance of the trade costs on the top of the mean) is not measured precisely and 
that the creation of new flows of exports, the so-called extensive margin of trade, is not 
accounted for. In a nutshell, a country that does not export a category of goods will not begin to 
export these goods, when trade costs in the sector come down, as the trade elasticity is applied 
to a zero flow. Last but not least, CGE models generally are not confronted with historical data 
for validation. Partial remedies were considered in the current exercise, notably by making sure 
that <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs> reproduces the observed past response of trade to changes in world income. More 
specifically, some of the literature addressing the recent slowdown in the growth of international 
trade have pointed to the slowing pace of international vertical specialisation (Constantinescu  et al., 2015; Crozet et al., 2015) besides slow GDP growth as a possible explanation. Therefore, 
at the global level in the reference case, <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs> is set to reproduce a conservative elasticity of 
world trade to income observed in the long run, with the exception of the 1990s, a transitory per-
iod characterised by the expansion of global value chains and the surge of new big traders. 
Not all limitations could be addressed in this framework: for instance, if decisions were to 
depend on the future state of the economy, and uncertainty to be taken into account, a differ-
ent class of models (dynamic stochastic general equilibrium models) would need to be used, 
which hardly allow for any sectoral or regional decomposition. Regarding the extensive </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>38 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>margin of trade, or the more detailed representation of trade responses to shocks in trade 
costs, the large-scale ambition of this exercise did not allow us to use modelling advances 
sometimes implemented in smaller scale models. </p>

<p>3   We also faced specific computational or data constraints in our present endeavour that might 
be circumvented in other simulations. The first issue concerns the representation of competition 
among firms. Many CGE models fit imperfect competition, and this can also be done in 
<rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>. However, given the long-term horizon of the exercise and the structural changes of 
the economies at stake, we were neither confident that the initial parameterisation of the model 
would fit well the development of these economies, nor were we convinced that the same 
parameterisation of market structures could apply in different economies. Combined with addi-
tional computing complexity, this led us to work with perfect competition. One important con-
sequence of this choice is that our estimation of the gains from trade (via consumer demand or 
via producers' purchases of intermediate goods) is rather conservative, as it does not reflect 
variety gains, scale economies or firm selection. For the present endeavour, this is of lesser 
importance, as we do not focus on the gains from trade and specialisation, but on trade patterns. 
The next limitation relates to trade in services. Not all modes of supply (as defined by the 
WTO's General Agreement on Trade in Services (GATS) Art. I:2) are modelled in our exer-
cise. We model services exported under mode 1 (cross-border trade) and mode 2 (consumption 
abroad), but modes 4 (presence of natural persons) and 3 (commercial presence) are absent. 
Quantitatively, this is not a major problem regarding mode 4, which is currently still small, 
although this might change substantially in the future. More importantly, the absence of ser-
vices supply via commercial presence abroad is due to our decision not to activate the foreign 
direct investment (FDI) module in <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>. We made this choice as a result of the lack of 
reliable information on future movements of FDI (although a snapshot of the current situation, 
which is usable for CGE modelling purposes, is provided by Guimbard et al., 2012). This limi-
tation is linked to the more general problem regarding foreign presence. We do not have reli-
able information on the activity of foreign affiliates, with some exceptions (United States and, 
quite recently, EU Member States). The reason for this lack of information is that FATS (For-
eign Affiliate Trade in Statistics) are not collected systematically and that FDI stocks (when 
available) are a poor proxy for the activity of foreign affiliates (Fukui and Lakatos, 2012). 
Besides these intrinsic limitations of CGE models and the specific choices made for this 
modelling exercise, CGE models are said not to take into account an important development 
of international trade patterns in recent times, namely the expansion of global value chains 
(GVCs), exemplified by 'Factory Asia' (WTO-IDE-JETRO, 2011). The development of GVCs 
changes many aspects of trade patterns, how to analyse them and the way in which technol-
ogy, services, investment and trade interplay (Elms and Low, 2013). For example, it can be 
shown that services are increasingly also traded indirectly through trade in goods (Stehrer,  2012). Baldwin (2011) provides a theoretical framework explaining why the fragmentation of 
production occurs. In order to understand the implications of global production networks for 
CGE modelling, it is important to recall that CGE modelling is in line with input-output stud-
ies a la Leontief, and, in addition, puts emphasis on prices, market clearing and substitution. 
Inter-industry relationships are instrumental for the construction of CGE models, and the ori-
gin (domestic or imported) of intermediate consumption is traced. As the results of changing </p>

<p>3 See Gouel et al. (2011) for development of <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs> at the product level and Balistreri et al. (2011) 
for an inclusion of firm heterogeneity. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
trade patterns can be expressed in terms of value added (and this is what we do here), it is 
possible to say that GVCs are intrinsically embodied in CGE models, even if trade is not 
reported in value-added terms in the simulations. 
4 This way of addressing the international 
fragmentation of production is still far from perfect. In <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>, the geographic composition 
of the basket of intermediates applies overall and is not differentiated by importing sector. 
We can, for instance, track the various origins of imported steel in a country, but we cannot 
know the origin of steel imported by the car industry. We simply assume that the geographic 
origins of steel imports in that sector are similar to the overall distribution in the economy. 
Hence, GVCs de facto are present in CGE models, such as <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs>, but are not modelled as 
such owing to this proportionality assumption. Also, the activity of foreign affiliates is present 
in the database, but not identified as such, and the composition by country of origin of each 
imported intermediate product is present, but not at the level of the importing industry. 
Although trade is expressed in gross terms, changes in the value added of the sector mirror 
the reaction of industries to trade shocks and take into account international input-output rela-
tions, albeit with less detail than in dedicated GVC studies. </p>

<p>b. Economic and Trade Scenarios </p>

<p>In order to simulate future trade patterns, assumptions about the principal drivers of econ-
omic activity and international trade need to be made. Given the time frame envisioned here, 
these are subject to considerable uncertainty. While expert forecasts exist for certain variables, 
such as demography or energy prices, assumptions for other exogenous variables are based on 
historical experience, for example concerning productivity improvements. For population, we 
take United Nations Population Division (UNPD) projections, in particular the two contrasting 
scenarios 'high fertility' and 'low fertility' which are meant to encompass a range of possible 
demographic outcomes. 
5 In a similar manner, we rely on energy price projections by the 
American Energy Information Administration (EIA), who also provide alternative 'high' and 
'low' oil price scenarios, as well as projections by the International Energy Agency (IEA) for </p>

<p>4 This view is challenged by Koopman et al. (2013), who compared the impact of a US tariff on Chinese 
imports using data that explicitly take account of GVCs (using a new USITC database) to the impact 
using conventional data (GTAP database on which our simulations are based as well). The authors use 
two CGE models, one by the USITC and GTAP. In the former model, export processing zones (EPZ), for 
example in Mexico, are treated as separated economies, that is two 'Mexicos' appear in the exercise, trad-
ing with their usual partners as well as with their twin. Another improvement in the USITC model relates 
to intermediate consumption, which differentiates intermediate goods according to the exporting country. 
The upshot of the model comparison is that a tariff faced by Mexico (but not by the Mexican EPZ) will 
hardly affect Mexican exports in the USITC model, while it does in the traditional model. The 'price to 
be paid' by GVC-oriented studies for providing more information is the absence of substitution and price 
effects included in traditional CGE modelling. Koopman et al. (2013) show how this limitation can be 
overcome, but for a model that is much narrower in scope than our approach. 
5 The two UNPD scenarios already embody migration assumptions ('normal migrations') that are cali-
brated by UN experts on a country by country basis. For these migrants, information on age, gender and 
education levels are not known, and, thus, we consider them as natives. However, we consider migration 
to also be a source of uncertainty, and focus on the two main migratory flows towards the EU and the 
United States, which would roughly double the flows presumed by UNPD. These 'additional' migrants 
(as opposed to the ones embedded in UNPD projections) are assumed to be characterised by the life 
expectancy of their destination, while keeping the age structure, gender repartition and educational level 
of their country of origin. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>40 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>the breakdown of energy prices between coal, oil and gas. The economic growth assumptions 
underlying these projections naturally are not identical to our growth model projections, but 
these differences are not very large for the default case. 
As far as the other variables are concerned, the 'reference case' is calibrated using econ-
ometric estimations over the period 1980-2010, therefore being in line with historical evi-
dence. The shocks we propose are quite simplistic, yet mimic orders of magnitude observed 
in the data, or theoretical eventualities. For instance, we calibrated our TFP shock based on 
the fall of the USSR or the technological performance of Japan during the 1990s. Sensitivity 
to capital mobility can either reproduce current but geographically circumscribed practices 
(low correlation between savings and investment in non-OECD countries), or encompass the 
theoretical eventuality that countries progressively close their capital flows with the rest of the 
world. Finally, the trade opening scenario, even if extreme, is not out of touch with reality, 
such as the full liberalisation scenarios used elsewhere (e.g. Anderson and Martin, 2006). For 
the lower bound as well, pre-Uruguay Round tariffs would simply imply making use of exist-
ing binding overhang between applied and bound ceiling rates for certain countries and prod-
ucts. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Hence, we take uncertainty into account by developing two 'extreme' trajectories: a 'high' 
scenario and a 'low' scenario (according to the expected impact on GDP) is designed for each 
main economic variable, which, when combined, result in an upper and lower projection. 
Combining positive and negative 'shocks' in this manner not only provides a range in which 
future outcomes are likely to fall, but is also reasonable in the sense that economic downturns 
tend to be associated with negative developments for a range of economic variables, including 
protectionist responses, and vice versa. Table 1 describes the scenarios chosen for each key 
economic variable. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>3. MAIN DRIVING FORCES OF FUTURE ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENTS </p>

<p>This section analyses the relative contribution of the fundamental economic factors simu-
lated each at a time under the two different scenarios in <rs type="software">MaGE</rs>. An overview showing the rel-
ative deviation from economic growth under the reference scenario attributable to each main 
economic driver is given in Figure 1. </p>

<p>6 Trade costs are, of course, affected by a wide range of factors of considerable interest to policymakers, 
including transportation costs and institutions. While the appropriate detail and disaggregation cannot be 
provided in a global model of this nature, there is still some indirect representation of such factors, for 
example through changes in productivity and the assumptions on broader transaction costs. Trade costs 
related to transportation are also specifically taken into consideration via energy price developments and 
sector-specific productivity developments. 
7 Although, for simplicity, these variables are grouped by supply side factors, namely endowments 
and technology, as well as trade costs, linkages exist, including on the demand side. For example, 
demographic developments are intimately linked to savings, the geographic distribution of which in 
turn is influenced by the assumptions about capital mobility. Again, scenarios have been developed 
based on forecasts and empirical evidence. Where alternative forecasts do not exist, the flipside of a 
chosen scenario may simply reflect its mirror image. For example, the lower bound scenario on tech-
nology is symmetric to the (empirically documented) higher bound scenario, which ensures that the 
interpretation of results is not unduly influenced by vastly differing assumptions on the up-and down-
side, respectively. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
For all countries/regions/groups, variations in TFP have the largest impact by far on aver-
age GDP growth up to 2035. Developed countries 
8 can expect around one half of a per cent 
more or less average growth per year, amounting to around 9 per cent higher/lower GDP </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Scenarios, by Exogenous Variable </p>

<p>Low 
High </p>

<p>Labour 
Demography 
Reference case in high-income 
countries, low fertility (UNPD) in 
others </p>

<p>Reference case in high-income 
countries, high fertility (UNPD) in 
others 
Education 
convergence </p>

<p>1.5 half-life time 
0.5 half-life time </p>

<p>Female participation No improvements 
Reference case 
Migration 
Reference case 
Additional migration from SSA and 
MENA to EU, and from SAM to the 
US 
Capital 
Capital mobility 
Convergence to I = S in 2050 
Low Feldstein-Horioka correlation 
coefficient (as in non-OECD) for all 
countries 
Natural resources 
Energy price 
High-price scenario (EIA) 
Low-price scenario (EIA) 
Energy productivity 
+50% in high-income countries, 
reference case in others </p>

<p>+50% for low-and mid-income 
countries, reference case in others 
Technology 
Total factor 
productivity </p>

<p>À50% TFP growth rate for low-and 
mid-income countries, À25% for 
high-income countries </p>

<p>+50% TFP growth rate for low-and 
mid-income countries, +25% for 
high-income countries 
Trade costs 
Tariffs 
'Trade war': return to pre-UR applied 
tariffs </p>

<p>'Trade opening': À50% in applied 
tariffs 
Other transaction 
costs on goods </p>

<p>+50% cost in low-and mid-income 
countries, +25% for others </p>

<p>À50% cost in low-and mid-income 
countries, À25% for others 
Services measures 
Reference case 
'Trade opening': À50% in services 
non-tariff measures. </p>

<p>Notes: 
(i) Trade costs only vary in the trade scenarios. 'Reference case' means that a variable is projected forward on the 
basis of its estimated behaviour in the past, taking into account also interlinkages with other relevant variables. This 
is done for all countries in the model individually and may imply an improvement or deterioration depending on the 
estimated behaviour for the country in question. 
(ii) Regarding educational convergence, half-life time is the time a country will take to reduce its difference with the 
initial position of the leader by half. Here, the leader is a virtual country composed of the leaders for each age group, 
level of education and time period. 
(iii) On capital, a lower Feldstein-Horioka correlation coefficient in OECD countries means that the correlation 
between domestic savings and domestic investment is assumed to be lower, as in non-OECD countries. This impacts 
the allocation of investment between countries, which is reduced in the former and increased in the latter. 
(iv) Notations: MENA for 'Middle East and North Africa', SSA for 'sub-Saharan Africa' and SAM for 'South America'. </p>

<p>8 Throughout the paper, 'developed countries' include countries of the European Union, of the European 
Free Trade Association, the US, Canada, Japan, Australia and New Zealand. All other countries/regions 
are referred to as 'developing/emerging'. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>42 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>-3 </p>

<p>-2.5 
-2 
-1.5 
-1 
-0.5 
0 
0.5 </p>

<p>USA 
Japan 
EU 
Brazil 
Russia 
India 
China 
Latin America 
MENA 
SSA 
Rest of Asia 
Rest of the World 
Developing 
Developed 
Total world </p>

<p>TFP 
Population 
Energy 
Capital mobility Total </p>

<p>-0.5 
0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 </p>

<p>USA 
Japan 
EU 
Brazil 
Russia 
India 
China 
Latin America 
MENA 
SSA 
Rest of Asia 
Rest of the World 
Developing 
Developed 
Total world </p>

<p>TFP 
Population 
Energy 
Capital mobility Total </p>

<p>GDP Growth Variation in 2035, High Scenario </p>

<p>GDP Growth Variation in 2035, Low Scenario </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 
Relative Contribution of Each Key Economic Factor to Deviations from GDP Growth Under the 
Reference Scenario Between 2012 and 2035 (Per Cent). </p>

<p>Notes: 
(i) The 'total' effect can be different from the sum of the components due to n-round effects. 
(ii) Notations: MENA for 'Middle East and North Africa', SSA for 'sub-Saharan Africa' and SAM for 'South America'. </p>

<p>Source: Author's calculations. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD 
43 </p>

<p>levels in 2035. For developing countries, and especially emerging economies, continued tech-
nological progress is crucial. Brazil can add/subtract about 1 per cent growth per year owing 
to TFP developments, which rises to roughly AE1.5 per cent for sub-Saharan Africa, 2 per cent 
for India and over 2 per cent for China. As a result, projected GDP levels in 2035 would vary 
by about AE20 per cent in Brazil, 30 per cent in sub-Saharan African, 40 per cent in India and 
more than 55 per cent in China compared to the reference GDP scenario. Developing coun-
tries as a group may face a more than 1.5 per cent difference in GDP growth per year 
depending on the path of technological progress, leading 30 to 40 per cent higher/lower levels 
in GDP by 2035 compared to the reference scenario. TFP growth could thus make a strong 
contribution to convergence under the 'optimistic' scenario, resulting in an about 6 per cent 
higher share in global GDP for developing countries and vice versa. 
For many countries, demography has the second largest impact if not only the pure impact 
in terms of population numbers is taken into account, but possible improvements in education, 
female labour participation and migration as well. Population is bound to grow significantly 
in India and sub-Saharan Africa. India's population is expected to overtake the current leader 
(China) by around 2035, with sub-Saharan Africa surpassing China in 2045 at the latest, and 
possibly several years earlier, and ultimately becoming the largest region in terms of popula-
tion numbers under the 'high' scenario. However, despite these additions to the labour pool, 
the demographic effect on GDP is relatively small, increasing/lowering the reference GDP in 
2035 by barely 1 per cent in India and even less in sub-Saharan Africa. For these regions, 
improvements in education matter significantly. If India and sub-Saharan Africa catch up fas-
ter in terms of educational attainment than under the reference scenario, GDP levels can be 
about 3 per cent higher in 2035. Similar results can be obtained for other developing countries 
in the Middle East and North Africa as well as Latin America. Increasing female participation 
in the labour force can make a similarly big impact, particularly in India and the Middle East 
and North Africa, where a lack of improvement would decrease GDP in 2035 by around 4 
per cent compared to the reference case. For several developed countries as well as China, 
population numbers are expected to decline having an unfavourable impact on labour force 
participation. Particularly for the European Union (EU), and to a lesser extent also for the 
United States, additional migration may have an important balancing impact. Additional 
migration not only affects the size and composition of the labour force, but can also play a 
positive role for savings/investment. Under such a scenario, per capita incomes in the EU and 
United States would be 2 per cent higher in 2035 compared to the reference case. </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>For a range of developing countries, improvements in capital mobility will make as much 
or more of a difference. In an optimistic scenario, which would reduce the observed bias 
towards domestic investment, annual GDP growth in the developing world could be up to 
one-third of a per cent higher than under the reference scenario. This would lead to 8 per cent 
higher levels in GDP in the Russian Federation in 2035, over 6 per cent in India and China 
and more than 4 per cent in Brazil, sub-Saharan Africa and the developing world overall, with 
GDP in the Middle East and North Africa and the Rest of Asia still increasing by around 2 
per cent. While if capital mobility is not increasing as much surplus developing countries 
(principally the Russian Federation, India and China) might still avert a negative deviation 
from reference growth rates, Brazil would be hardest hit with almost 4 per cent lower levels </p>

<p>9 Per capita GDP cannot be read from the data presented here, but is easily calculated on the basis of 
projected GDP and population levels. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>44 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>in GDP by 2035. Sub-Saharan Africa and Latin America would lose 1 per cent in GDP by 
2035, bringing the average impact on developing countries to just above zero. Under any sce-
nario of improved capital mobility, developed countries will obviously see lower investment 
for a given amount of savings. At most, high capital mobility could reduce GDP levels in 
2035 by about 4 per cent for the EU, United States and Japan. 
Finally, energy prices are of substantial importance to leading oil exporting nations on the 
one hand and to import-dependent countries, particularly those emerging and developing 
economies with high energy intensities (China, India, sub-Saharan Africa), on the other hand. 
Higher energy prices, as forecasted by the United States EIA, can reduce average annual 
GDP growth by up to a fifth of a per cent in China and India, reducing GDP in 2035 by 
almost 4 per cent in these countries. Exporters, such as the Russian Federation, parts of Latin 
America (Venezuela, Colombia and Mexico) and in particular the Middle East and North 
Africa, would benefit in such a scenario, with the latter adding up to one-third of a per cent 
to their annual GDP growth and seeing almost 7 per cent higher GDP levels in 2035 com-
pared to the reference case. These patterns would be reversed under a low-price scenario, with 
oil exporters in the Middle East and North Africa being particularly hurt. However, energy 
prices may ultimately have hardly any effect on GDP if improvements in energy productivity 
are taken into account. Higher energy productivity (together with substitution effects triggered 
by higher energy prices) would practically wipe out any negative economic effects in devel-
oped countries. Similarly, the impact of higher energy prices on economic growth in China, 
India and sub-Saharan Africa, for instance, would be reduced by at least 40 to 50 per cent in 
the former two countries and completely compensated for by energy productivity improve-
ments in the latter. </p>

<p>4. TRENDS IN TRADE </p>

<p>The direction, composition and nature of international trade have changed substantially 
over the past couple of decades, and many of these trends may be related to the proliferation 
of GVCs. Emerging economies have gained a larger share in global trade and increasingly 
trade with one another. At the sectoral level, developing countries have diversified their 
exports and obtained a higher overall share in manufacturing trade. The importance of ser-
vices trade has also risen. At the same time, much of 'global' trade is actually concentrated at 
the regional level. In analysing country, sector and factor outcomes of our integrated <rs type="software">MaGE</rs> 
and <rs type="software">MIRAGE</rs> simulations in more detail, we will now examine to what extent these trends in 
trade can be expected to continue in the future. 
Table 2 gives an overview of the combined macroeconomic and trade simulations in terms 
of projected average annual growth rates of GDP and exports up to 2035. Exports of goods 
are likely to vary more than GDP in the 'high' scenario despite the very conservative elastic-
ity used in our model, as noted in Section 2. In the 'low' scenario, by contrast, trade would 
grow much slower and even less than GDP. Whether a future scenario of key economic and 
policy variables is rather optimistic or pessimistic matters a lot more for developing than for 
developed countries, with the former being characterised by a much larger variation in out-
comes than the latter. While growth rates are generally lower in a gloomy economic and trade 
environment across both groups of countries, the difference is barely three-quarters of a per 
cent for developed countries' average GDP growth, but over 4 per cent for developing coun-
tries. Growth in GDP and services trade in developing countries is widely superior to growth 
rates in developed countries in the optimistic scenario, but much less so in a pessimistic </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
scenario, where growth in goods trade could advance even more slowly than in developed 
countries. Examining specifically the trade cost component, it turns out that growth in devel-
oping countries would be about half a per cent higher/lower in an open/restrictive trade policy 
environment, while growth in developed countries would hardly be affected. 
The simulated growth rates imply that, in terms of GDP, China would be larger than the 
United States and the European Union by 2030 at the latest under the 'high' scenario. India 
would reach China's current economic size by about 2025, but only under the 'high' scenario, 
in which case it would also attain China's 'low' scenario GDP level by 2035. Whether the 
future economic and policy outlook is rather optimistic or pessimistic is of considerable 
importance for sub-Saharan Africa, whose GDP levels would practically stagnate under a 
'low' scenario, falling further behind the economic size of Brazil in 2035, but which could 
outperform the latter under a 'high' scenario, and this already before the year 2030. The Rus-
sian Federation can stay ahead of these two regions only for an optimistic outlook, falling 
behind sub-Saharan Africa and Brazil in terms of GDP levels in the adverse case. In sum, 
whether future developments are closer to the upper than the lower growth path makes a par-
ticularly big difference for developing countries. The resulting variation of around 2 per cent 
on either side around baseline GDP growth results in about one-third lower or 50 per cent 
higher per capita incomes in this group of countries by 2035, with an even larger divergence 
for individual countries, notably China and India. </p>

<p>a. Trend 1: New Players in the World Economy </p>

<p>In Table 3, current and simulated shares in global GDP and exports are given for major 
countries and regions. Emerging economies, such as the BRICs group, have the possibility to 
further increase their share in both world GDP and exports under the 'high' scenario. But the 
BRICs would also be particularly affected by a gloomy economic and trade policy outlook, in 
which case their share in global exports would fall below its current level, while the share of 
other developing countries would remain about unchanged. The possible difference in trade out-
comes is particularly stunning for China, which could enlarge its share in world exports to 
almost one-quarter under the 'high' scenario, but would lose ground in the reverse case (in both 
relative and absolute terms). As far as China's GDP developments are concerned, it could more 
than double its share to reach one-fifth of world GDP under the 'high' scenario, but would only 
realise a modest increase compared to its present share (about 7 per cent) in the 'low' scenario. 
While for developed countries, both export and GDP shares would decline under the 'high' </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Projected Average Annual Growth Rate of GDP, Exports in Goods and Exports in Services, 2012-2035 
(Per Cent) </p>

<p>GDP (Volume) 
Trade in Goods 
(Volume) </p>

<p>Trade in Services 
(Volume) </p>

<p>High 
Low 
High 
Low 
High 
Low </p>

<p>Developed 
2.2 
1.5 
3.6 
1.5 
4.9 
1.6 
Developing 
7.1 
2.8 
8.4 
0.4 
9.1 
3.8 
World 
4.2 
1.9 
6.2 
1.1 
6.7 
2.5 </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>46 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>scenario, this does certainly not mean that they would lose out. To the contrary, the simulations 
show that developed countries would be better off realising a smaller share of a 'much larger 
pie' under the high scenario than vice versa in terms of both GDP and exports. 
The more prominent role of developing countries in international trade under an 'opti-
mistic' scenario would also entail a significantly higher share of 'South-South' relationships, 
that is trade among developing countries, at 43 per cent of the global trade (currently at 19 
per cent), which would then constitute the dominant direction of trade compared to 40 per 
cent of 'North-South' and 17 per cent of 'North-North' trade. By contrast, under the 'low' 
scenario, the situation would be practically inverted, with North-North and South-South 
trades in the year 2035 remaining approximately at their current shares of around 40 per cent 
and just below 20 per cent, respectively. In absolute terms, despite the lower share, North-
North trade would still be one-quarter bigger under the 'high' than under the 'low' scenario. </p>

<p>b. Trend 2: Export Diversification </p>

<p>As far as the product composition of trade is concerned, many studies have shown -often 
using the concept of revealed comparative advantage (RCA) -that countries have become 
less specialised over time and diversified their range of export products. The reason for this 
may be that while countries continue to specialise in sectors based on comparative advantage, 
both technological and policy factors, such as advances in telecommunications and informa-
tion technology and increased economic integration, have facilitated the diffusion of technol-
ogy and movement of production factors across borders. Depending on how such factors </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Country/Regional Shares in Global GDP and Exports (Per Cent) </p>

<p>GDP (Volume) 
Exports (Volume, Excluding 
Intra-EU Trade) </p>

<p>2012 
High 2035 Low 2035 2012 
High 2035 Low 2035 </p>

<p>World total (2004 US$ billion) 49,992 
129,618 
77,759 
10,165 
48,206 
13,827 
Developed 
70.1 
44.3 
63.9 
47.8 
28.6 
51.1 
EU 
28.2 
18.1 
24.6 
18.2 
11.6 
18.4 
USA 
26.5 
16.8 
24.4 
15.2 
9.3 
17.4 
Japan 
9.9 
5.7 
8.7 
6.5 
3.8 
6.5 
Other developed 
5.5 
3.7 
6.2 
7.9 
3.8 
8.8 
BRICs 
12.9 
31.1 
15.9 
19.3 
31.5 
15.9 
China 
7.3 
20.4 
9.2 
14.2 
22.5 
10.9 
India 
2.4 
6.4 
3.3 
2.0 
5.0 
2.4 
Brazil 
1.7 
1.7 
1.7 
1.0 
0.8 
0.8 
Russia 
1.6 
2.7 
1.7 
2.1 
3.1 
1.8 
Other 
17.0 
24.5 
20.2 
32.9 
39.9 
33.0 
ASEAN 
2.4 
3.7 
2.6 
8.1 
8.9 
8.4 
MENA 
4.3 
6.9 
5.4 
7.0 
10.0 
6.2 
SSA 
1.6 
3.3 
2.2 
2.3 
4.6 
2.5 
Other 
8.7 
10.6 
9.9 
15.5 
16.4 
15.9 </p>

<p>Note: 
Notations: MENA for 'Middle East and North Africa', SSA for 'sub-Saharan Africa' and SAM for 'South America', 
ASEAN stands for 'Association of Southeast Asian Nations'. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
evolve in the future, current patterns of specialisation may change. A growing literature analy-
ses the link between export diversification and economic growth and, hence, illustrates the 
particular importance of this trend for developing countries. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Figure 2 shows possible shifts in RCA for aggregate sectors under the different scenarios for 
a selection of countries/regions. The sectoral aggregation presented here illustrates the possibil-
ity that the current trend of increased specialisation into skill-intensive sectors, 
11 particularly in 
emerging economies, such as China, may be reversed under an unfavourable trade cost scenario. 
In such a situation, China's RCA in skilled manufacturing, which currently stands at just above 
unity, would fall to about 0.8 as opposed to a further strengthening to almost 1.5 under an opti-
mistic outlook on trade costs. At the more disaggregate sectoral level, this would imply a further 
RCA expansion for China in traditional unskilled-labour-intensive sectors, such as textiles, 
under the 'low' scenario, while RCA in skill-intensive sectors, such as electronics and machin-
ery, would significantly retreat, threatening to fall back below unity in the latter sector and, 
hence, frustrating efforts to further diversify the country's export base. The opposite would 
occur in the 'high' scenario, in which case China would also broaden its RCA into high skill-
intensive sectors, such as transport equipment, where this is not presently the case. Two main 
drivers are behind these developments: on the one hand, the continued 'upskilling' of production 
(implicit in the education scenarios) substantially reshapes comparative advantage towards more 
skill-intensive activities, both directly as the skill premium decreases, and indirectly as upskill-
ing leads to higher TFP, more revenues and ultimately a higher demand in services and skill-
intensive goods. On the other hand, a negative trade policy outlook can modify this link between 
skills and comparative advantage. As far as tariffs are concerned, these are presently lower for 
skill-intensive sectors, but were on the same order of magnitude as non-skill-intensive sectors 
before the Uruguay round. Therefore, skill-intensive sectors are comparatively more impacted 
by a confrontational trade policy scenario, moving China's specialisation (which is particularly 
dependent on foreign demand in the 'low' scenario) towards non-skill-intensive sectors. 
Similar drivers are at work for other regions, such as sub-Saharan Africa, where, under the 
'low' scenario, a lack of trade policy cooperation would leave its RCA for all manufacturing 
below unity. Conversely, in the 'high' case, sub-Saharan Africa would gain in manufacturing 
RCA, making also progress in skill-intensive sectors. At the same time, being the worst per-
forming region in terms of agricultural productivity in both crops and livestock, the 'high' 
scenario would help sub-Saharan Africa to significantly reduce its reliance on agriculture (and 
other primary commodities), which currently exhibits the by far largest RCA in the region. 
The situation and prospects in developed countries in this regard are quite different. In our 
estimations, the United States is and will continue to be the technological leader in the crops 
sector, being also very productive in the livestock sector. It can be expected to increase its 
RCA in the agricultural sector under any scenario, but much more so in the 'high' case, 
including through an additional boost from trade opening. A favourable trade policy outlook 
would also further propel the United States' RCA in the area of services, where, in the </p>

<p>10 Cadot et al. (2013) provide an excellent guide to the literature on diversification and productivity. 
See particularly Feenstra and Kee (2007, 2008) for an empirical analysis of the endogenous nature of 
this relationship and the importance of trade liberalisation in that regard. 
11 The categorisation into 'skilled' and 'unskilled' manufacturing sectors was made on the basis of pay-
roll data from the United States, taking the median of the skilled share as the dividing line. Unskilled 
sectors include for example textiles, food and metals, while skilled sectors comprise sectors such as cars 
and trucks, transport equipment, electronics and machinery. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>48 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>opposite case, its existing RCA may be lost. The two diverging scenarios make less of a dif-
ference for the United States in manufacturing, where the RCA risks remaining slightly sub-
par in a number of sectors. Predicted RCA patterns for the EU are quite similar, with the 
exception of agriculture, where it is nowhere near the unity threshold under any scenario. </p>

<p>c. Trend 3: Importance of Services Trade </p>

<p>Services account for an increasing share in global trade, in particular if measured in value-
added terms (WTO, 2013). The continued importance of services trade compared to goods 
applies to both scenarios. The increased share of services in global trade (about one-quarter) </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>A 
g r i c u l t u r e 
S k i l l e d 
M 
a n u f a c t u r e s </p>

<p>U 
n s k i l l e d </p>

<p>M 
a n u f a c t u r e s 
S e r v i c e s 
A 
g r i c u l t u r e 
S k i l l e d 
M 
a n u f a c t u r e s U 
n s k i l l e d </p>

<p>M 
a n u f a c t u r e s 
S e r v i c e s </p>

<p>A 
g r i c u l t u r e 
S k i l l e d 
M 
a n u f a c t u r e s </p>

<p>U 
n s k i l l e d </p>

<p>M 
a n u f a c t u r e s 
S e r v i c e s 
A 
g r i c u l t u r e 
S k i l l e d 
M 
a n u f a c t u r e s </p>

<p>U 
n s k i l l e d </p>

<p>M 
a n u f a c t u r e s 
S e r v i c e s </p>

<p>China </p>

<p>2012 
Low 2035 
High 2035 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 
European Union </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>5.0 
Sub-Saharan Africa (Excl. South Africa) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>4.0 
United States of America </p>

<p>2012 
Low 2035 
High 2035 </p>

<p>2012 
Low 2035 
High 2035 
2012 
Low 2035 
High 2035 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2 
Changes in Aggregate Revealed Comparative Advantage, Present (2012) and 2035 </p>

<p>Note: 
In this figure, the energy sector is not shown separately, as results would be unduly influenced by poor input-output 
accounting in certain regions and sectors, notably gas distribution and production. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations. </p>

<p>12 Goods trade here comprises manufacturing, energy and agriculture. In the following, we concentrate 
on a comparison of trade in services and manufactures, which is particularly relevant from a develop-
ment perspective. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
under a 'low' scenario is obviously influenced by possible negative trade policy developments in 
the area of goods. However, the share of services compared to goods also goes up in the 'high' 
scenario, where symmetric improvements in trade costs for both goods and services are simu-
lated, with the absolute value of services exports rising by a factor of between three and four in 
2035 compared to the current situation. Developing countries as a group would capture a larger 
share of services trade under the 'high' scenario, particularly owing to China, who would see its 
contribution to global services exports more than triple to account for 18 per cent in 2035. The 
higher involvement in services trade would not come at the expense of developing countries' 
exports of manufactures (see Table 4). Under the assumption of a bright economic and trade pol-
icy outlook, developing countries would continue to capture a larger market share in manufactur-
ing exports as well. Again, China would be dominant in this regard, accounting for almost 30 
per cent of global exports in manufactures under such a scenario. By contrast, if economic condi-
tions were to deteriorate and countries flout on their trade policy commitments, developing coun-
tries would see their share in manufacturing trade fall, with China suffering the largest 
percentage decline. Larger manufacturing export shares for the European Union and the United 
States in such a scenario cannot conceal the fact that they too would lose in absolute terms. </p>

<p>d. Trend 4: Regionalism </p>

<p>A major trend in trade policy has been towards the conclusion of preferential trade agree-
ments, particularly at the regional level (World Trade Organization, 2011). In certain regions, </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
World Exports of Manufactured Goods and Services, Country/Regional Shares in 2012 and 2035 
(Billion US$ and Per Cent) </p>

<p>Manufactures 
Services </p>

<p>2012 
High 2035 Low 2035 2012 
High 2035 Low 2035 </p>

<p>World total (2004 US$ billion) 7,245 
33,285 
9,078 
1,706 
8,678 
3,216 
Developed 
48.4 
25.3 
53.8 
58.8 
40.8 
47.7 
EU27 
18.1 
10.2 
18.6 
26.9 
20.5 
22.7 
US 
15.1 
8.0 
17.7 
20.1 
14.0 
14.5 
Japan 
8.1 
4.7 
8.5 
3.9 
2.4 
4.0 
Other developed 
7.1 
2.4 
9.0 
7.9 
3.9 
6.5 
BRICs 
22.5 
37.2 
17.6 
9.9 
24.3 
13.0 
China 
18.3 
27.7 
13.9 
5.7 
18.0 
7.2 
India 
2.0 
6.2 
2.0 
2.5 
3.2 
3.9 
Brazil 
0.9 
0.6 
0.5 
0.6 
0.3 
0.4 
Russia 
1.3 
2.8 
1.1 
1.1 
2.7 
1.6 
Other 
29.1 
37.5 
28.6 
31.3 
34.9 
39.3 
ASEAN 
9.0 
9.8 
9.8 
5.4 
5.3 
5.8 
MENA 
3.4 
6.9 
2.8 
7.4 
8.1 
9.9 
SSA 
1.3 
3.7 
1.5 
2.0 
4.6 
3.2 
Other 
15.4 
17.0 
14.4 
16.5 
17.0 
20.4 </p>

<p>Notes: 
(i) Again, intra-EU trade is excluded. 
(ii) Notations: MENA for 'Middle East and North Africa', SSA for 'sub-Saharan Africa' and SAM for 'South Amer-
ica', ASEAN stands for 'Association of Southeast Asian Nations'. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>50 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>particular Asia, intra-regional trade has persistently increased over the past two decades in 
both relative and absolute terms (WTO, 2013). Our model simulations until 2035, however, 
do not foresee this trend to continue unabated. Looking at some of the largest free trade 
arrangements, the relative share of trade taking place within these regions is expected to 
decline under the 'high' scenario (see Table 5, which also indicates that no major changes 
would occur under the 'low' scenario). The share of trade within the European Union would 
be particularly affected, falling more than a half, from 22 per cent to just 9 per cent of world 
trade, even though in absolute numbers intra-trade volumes would still increase. Similarly, the 
share of trade within the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) in global com-
merce would decline by more than half by 2035. By the same token, assuming no further 
preferential trade integration, extra-regional trade would vastly increase in importance, in both 
absolute and relative terms, accounting for 70 per cent at present and more than 85 per cent 
of world trade in 2035 under the 'high scenario'. While these predictions give strong support 
to further economic integration at the multilateral level, the possibility of intensified and 
enlarged preferential trade arrangements in the future cannot be discarded, especially in the 
light of certain 'mega-regional' deals already being under discussion today. 
In order to assess the effect of further preferential trade integration on multilateral trade 
relationships, we introduce an additional, 'extreme' policy shock in the 'low' scenario (now 
called 'low reg'), in which three purely hypothetical mega-regional trade deals are presumed 
to exist in the Americas, Asia and Europe-Africa. First, such mega-regional agreements could 
increase world trade by 16 per cent, partly compensating the downturns we observe in our 
'low' scenario. This set-up would obviously imply significant trade diversion from existing 
trade agreements, and the long-term trend towards the importance of multilateralism would 
still prevail. By 2035, extra-regional trade relations would still account for 37 per cent of glo-
bal trade even with the three hypothetical large free trade areas. These results also emphasise 
that the largest unexploited potential in regional integration remains in Asia, since it would be 
the only region to register a significant increase in its share of global trade due to a </p>

<p>TABLE 5 
Intra-regional and Extra-regional Trade as Shares of Global Trade (Including Intra-EU Trade), Constant 
2004 Prices, by Agreement and Potential 'Mega-regional' Free Trade Arrangement </p>

<p>2012 
High 2035 
Low 2035 
Low Reg 2035 </p>

<p>World total (2004 US$ billion) 
12,945 
52,714 
17,588 
20,446 
By current agreement 
EU 
21.5 
8.6 
21.4 
17.8 
NAFTA 
6.5 
3.3 
8.2 
7.0 
ASEAN 
1.3 
1.7 
2.1 
1.6 
MERCOSUR 
0.7 
0.7 
0.5 
0.6 
By potential mega-regional agreement 
EurAfrica 
34.5 
23.7 
35.8 
35.5 
Americas 
9.1 
5.3 
10.2 
10.1 
Asia 
10.9 
17.2 
8.8 
17.0 </p>

<p>Note: 
Notations: EU stands for 'European Union', NAFTA for 'North American Free Trade Agreement', ASEAN for 'Asso-
ciation of Southeast Asian Nations' and MERCOSUR for 'Southern Common Market'. </p>

<p>Source: Author's calculations. </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD 
51 </p>

<p>mega-regional agreement, and this despite trade volumes increasing also in the other two 
hypothetical mega-regions. This relative increase would mainly be due to the high initial tariff 
levels in this region compared to EU-Africa and the Americas, and this trade potential is 
likely to be exploited as negotiations within Asia have already made progress, for instance, 
between the ASEAN and its regional partners (ASEAN+6) (Kawai and Wignaraja, 2013). </p>

<p>5. CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This study has examined both major trends in trade, seeking to project these several dec-
ades into the future, and the forces that drive such developments. For that purpose, we have 
combined a macroeconomic growth model with a multisectoral CGE framework and con-
structed two extreme, internally consistent scenarios up until the year 2035 -one of further 
dynamic growth and trade integration and one of a worsening economic environment and slip-
page in trade cooperation. This has allowed us to chart out boundaries for possible future 
developments in international trade, based on existing forecasts and well-grounded assump-
tions about individual economic variables. Making the influence of each factor traceable 
throughout our model, we have also been able to assess the relative importance of individual 
policy areas for specific countries and regions. 
A notable trend over the last two decades was the emergence of new players in the world 
economy. Under the 'high' scenario, developing countries will continue to claim a growing 
share of global GDP and trade. In the reverse case, however, they might lose ground in trade 
and register only modest increases in their share of global GDP. Individual developing coun-
tries, notably China, appear to have particularly high stakes in the future economic and trade 
policy outlook, given the enormous difference in impact that the two scenarios can have. The 
emergence of developing countries in international trade in recent times has also been fuelled 
by South-South trade relations. While this could become the dominant direction of trade 
under a dynamic economic and open trade environment, the opposite is the case for a gloomy 
economic and confrontational trade policy scenario. Another trend in the direction of trade 
has been its increased regionalisation, with the phenomenal growth in intra-Asia trade stand-
ing out. This trend is unlikely to continue under a 'high' scenario, in which case trade rela-
tionships with countries around the globe would account for more than four-fifths of total 
trade. The 'low' scenario would leave the current state of regionalism practically unchanged, 
while 'mega-regional' deals, some of which are already under negotiation, would foster inter-
national trade, but not necessarily along with further regionalisation, with the exception of 
Asia, where intra-trade would continue its ascent. Even under such a scenario, trade outside 
the hypothetical regional blocs would still comprise nearly 40 per cent of world trade, thus 
giving new emphasis to the importance of further multilateral trade opening. 
As far as the product composition of trade and the related issue of factor intensity are 
concerned, an important trend has been the increased diversification of developing countries' 
export baskets into skill-intensive sectors. While this trend is likely to last for a continuing 
convergence in educational attainment and related TFP improvements, it can be undermined 
in part by an unfavourable scenario on trade costs. Using RCA as an indicator of specialisa-
tion into various sectors, we find that under a 'low' scenario, some of the emerging econ-
omies may be faced with a loss of RCA in skilled manufacturing sectors, such as electronics 
and machinery, and a fallback onto an expanding RCA in non-skill-intensive sectors, such as 
textiles. Conversely, favourable developments on trade costs may not only help to expand 
the former, but also build RCA in further skill-intensive manufacturing sectors, such as </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>52 
L. FONTAGN 
E, J. FOUR 
E AND A. KECK </p>

<p>transport equipment in the case of China. Sub-Saharan Africa would also benefit from a 
'high' scenario to diversify away from its heavy dependence on commodities towards manu-
factured exports. Services trade will continue to rise in importance, particularly for develop-
ing countries under a 'high' scenario. A degree of divergence exists in this group, with 
regions, such as sub-Saharan Africa, expanding their RCA in manufacturing rather than ser-
vices in such a case. 
The second objective of this study has been to assess the relative importance of key driv-
ing factors in different countries. Technology has the biggest impact on economic develop-
ment for practically everyone. This includes continued improvements in energy productivity, 
which would be of considerable importance to both developing and developed countries to 
counter possible effects of persistently higher energy prices. For many developing countries, 
such as India, countries in the Middle East and sub-Saharan Africa, population dynamics are 
an important consideration as well. These countries may benefit from a demographic dividend, 
but much will depend on education policy and the integration of women in the work force to 
take advantage of these developments. The reverse -a declining and ageing population -will 
be a challenge for China as well as most developed countries. Policies of openness to migra-
tion can provide some measure of relief to the EU and United States, depending also on the 
skill composition of additional labour resources as well as savings behaviour. For China, con-
tinuing the path of rapid accumulation of capital together with skill and technology-upgrading 
can more than compensate for these effects. Most developing countries could benefit to a sim-
ilar extent from improved capital mobility. In the adverse case, developing countries featuring 
a surplus (such as the Russian Federation, India and China) can cushion the consequences on 
economic growth, while others, notably Brazil, would be negatively affected. Finally, trade 
costs can have a significant impact on specialisation patterns in developing countries. Unfa-
vourable trade cost scenarios have the potential to disrupt the successful diversification pro-
cess by emerging economies. Resource-rich countries, for instance in sub-Saharan Africa and 
the MENA region, also need to reduce the 'distance' to world markets in order to diminish 
their commodity export dependency and exposure to presumed price volatility, for example in 
international energy markets. 
This paper has sought to fill a gap in the existing literature by combining an explicit econ-
omic growth model with a multisectoral model at the world level and for a time horizon 
(year 2035) that is long enough in order to allow for fundamental macroeconomic factors to 
have an impact and yet is not too distant in order for reasonable assumptions on their future 
trajectories to be made. We have also shown some limitations that can be addressed in our 
further work. One extension would be to explicitly address the role of multinational firms in 
shaping world trade patterns. To do so, we need a database of foreign presence at the 
investor-host-sector level (Fukui and Lakatos, 2012) and to implement foreign presence in 
the CGE framework by splitting production by ownership of firms. Goods and services could 
then be differentiated by ownership of the firm, instead of being differentiated by region of 
production (an i-phone produced in China would then be a United States product) -an 
approach initiated by Petri (1997). 
13 A second extension would be to improve upon the mea-
surement of non-tariff measures and their trade restrictiveness and provide for a more detailed 
modelling of agreements aimed at tackling 'behind the border protection'. Finally, more work </p>

<p>13 An example of this approach is provided by Lakatos and Fukui (2013) on a small scale (liberalisation 
of retail services in India). </p>

<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
is needed regarding the energy and carbon content of trade flows, to take into account how 
major environmental policy concerns potentially affect future economic developments. </p>



<p>© 2016 John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd </p>

<p>SIMULATING WORLD TRADE IN THE DECADES AHEAD </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>