<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1017%2Fs136510051300076x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>MACROECONOMIC DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Editor: William A. Barnett, University of Kansas, Department of Economics, 356 Snow Hall, 1460 Jayhawk 
Boulevard, Lawrence, KS 66045-7523, USA, and The Center for Financial Stability, 1120 Avenue of the 
Americas, 4th Floor, New York, NY 10036, USA. </p>

<p>Book Review Editors: Michele Boldrin, Department of Economics, Washington University, One Brookings 
Drive, St. Louis, MO63130, and Universidad Carlos III, Madrid; Gregory D. Hess, Department of Economics, 
500 East 9th Street, Claremont McKenna College, Claremont, CA 91711. </p>

<p>Special Issues Editors: Stephen Turnovsky, Department of Economics, Box 353330, University of Washington, 
Seattle, WA 98195; Lee Ohanian, Department of Economics, UCLA, 2261 Bunche Hall, 405 Hilgard Avenue, 
Los Angeles, CA 90024. </p>

<p>Editorial Information System Manager: Stephen E. Spear, Graduate School of Industrial Administration, 
Carnegie Mellon University, Pittsburgh, PA 15213. </p>

<p>Local Area Network Manager: Nathan Haley, Lawrence, Kansas. </p>

<p>Editorial Associate: Melinda Barnett, University of Kansas. </p>

<p>Advisory Editors: 
Jean-Pascal Bénassy (CEPREMAP, Paris), Willem Buiter (London School of Economics and Political Science, 
London), Francis X. Diebold (University of Pennsylvania), Steven Durlauf (University of Wisconsin), Douglas Gale 
(New York University), Giancarlo Gandolfo (University of Rome), Roger Guesnerie (DELTA, Paris), Takatoshi Ito 
(University of Tokyo), Timothy Kehoe (University of Minnesota), Finn Kydland (Carnegie Mellon University), 
Lung-Fei Lee (Ohio State University), Adrian Pagan (Australian National University), Robert Townsend 
(Massachusetts Institute of Technology), Mark Watson (Princeton University), Kenneth West (University of 
Wisconsin), Michael Woodford (Columbia University), Randall Wright (University of Pennsylvania) </p>

<p>Associate Editors: 
Stefania Albanesi (Federal Reserve Bank of New York), Robert Amano (Bank of Canada), Gaetano Antinolfi 
(Washington University), Jasmina Arifovic (Simon Fraser University), Pierpaolo Benigno (LUISS Guido Carli, 
Rome), Joydeep Bhattacharya (Iowa State University), Florin Bilbiie (Paris School of Economics), Volker Böhm 
(University of Bielefeld, Germany), Hafedh Bouakez (HEC Montreal, Canada), Raouf Boucekkine (Universite 
Catholique de Louvain, Belgium), Jeffrey Campbell (Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago), Shankha Chakraborty 
(University of Oregon), Marcelle Chauvet (University of California at Riverside), Rose-Anne Dana (Université 
Paris IX-Dauphine), Christophe Deissenberg (University d'Aix-Marseille II), Huberto Ennis (Federal Reserve 
Bank of Richmond), Alvaro Escribano (Universidad Carlos III de Madrid, Spain), Emilio Espino (Buenos Aires, 
Argentina), George Evans (University of Oregon), Ester Faia (Goethe University of Frankfurt), Roger Farmer 
(UCLA), Alessandra Fogli (Minneapolis Federal Reserve Bank), Luisa Fuster (Madrid Institute of Advanced 
Studies, Spain), Oded Galor (Brown University and Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Marc Giannoni (Federal 
Reserve Bank of New York), Liam Graham (University College, London), Antonio Guarino (University College, 
London), Thorvaldur Gylfason (University of Iceland), Niels Haldrup (Aarhus University, Denmark), John 
Hassler (Stockholm University), Moshe Hazan (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Cars Hommes (University 
of Amsterdam, The Netherlands), Kevin Huang (Vanderbilt University), Leo Kass (University of Konstanz, 
Germany), Todd Keister (Federal Reserve Bank of New York), Keith Kuester (University of Bonn, Germany), 
Blake LeBaron (Brandeis University), Helmut Lütkepohl (European University Institute, Florence), Iourii 
Manovskii (University of Pennsylvania), David Marshall (Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago), Alfredo Medio 
(University of Udine, Italy), Jianjun Miao (Boston University), Kaushik Mitra (University of St. Andrews, UK), 
Omer Moav (The Hebrew University of Jerusalem), Cyril Monnet (University of Bern, Switzerland), José V. 
Rodriguez Mora (University of Edinburgh, UK), Lee Ohanian (UCLA), Patrick Pintus (Université de la 
Méditerranée &amp; GREQAM, France), Bruce Preston (Columbia University), Neil Rankin (University of York, 
UK), Francisco Ruge-Murcia (University of Montreal), Gilles Saint-Paul (Université de Toulouse, France), 
Argia M. Sbordone (Federal Reserve Bank of New York), Klaus Martin Schneider (Stanford University), 
Apostolos Serletis (University of Calgary, Canada), Tony Smith (Yale University), Stephen Spear (Carnegie 
Mellon University), Stephen Turnovsky (University of Washington), Farshid Vahid (Monash University, Australia), 
Francois R. Velde (Federal Reserve Bank of Chicago), Nicolaas Vriend (Queen Mary, University of London), Neng 
Wang (Columbia University), Ronald Wendner (University of Graz, Austria), Sevin Yeltekin (Carnegie Mellon) </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S136510051300076X </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 17:02:46, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>MACROECONOMIC DYNAMICS </p>

<p>Volume 18, Number 1, January 2014 
Contents </p>

<p>ARTICLES </p>

<p>Patent Length and Price Regulation in an R&amp;D Growth Model 
with Monopolistic Competition 
Jinli Zeng, Jie Zhang, and Michael Ka-Yiu Fung 
1 </p>

<p>Interest Rate Rules and Equilibrium Stability under Deep Habits 
Sarah Zubairy 
23 </p>

<p>Estimated Thresholds in the Response of Output to Monetary Policy: 
Are Large Policy Changes Less Effective? 
Luiggi Donayre 
41 </p>

<p>Can Capacity Constraints Explain Asymmetries of the Business Cycle? 
Malte Knüppel 
65 </p>

<p>The Endogenous Determination of Retirement Age and Social 
Security Benefits 
Francisco Cabo and Ana García-González 
93 </p>

<p>How Child Costs and Survival Shaped the Industrial Revolution 
and the Demographic Transition 
Holger Strulik and Jacob Weisdorf 
114 </p>

<p>Which Inflation to Target? A Small Open Economy with Sticky Wages 
Alessia Campolmi 
145 </p>

<p>Loose Commitment in Medium-Scale Macroeconomic Models: 
Theory and Applications 
Davide Debortoli, Junior Maih, and Ricardo Nunes 
175 </p>

<p>Multiple Testing for Output Convergence 
Thomas Deckers and Christoph Hanck 
199 </p>

<p>MD SURVEY </p>

<p>Optimum Savings and Optimal Growth: The Cass-Malinvaud-Koopmans 
Nexus 
Stephen E. Spear and Warren Young 
215 </p>

<p>NOTES </p>

<p>A Note on Bubbles, Worthless Assets, and the Curious Case of 
General Motors 
Tom Ahn, Jeremy Sandford, and Paul Shea 
244 </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S136510051300076X </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 17:02:46, subject to the Cambridge </p>

<p>SUBSCRIPTION INFORMATION: Macroeconomic Dynamics (ISSN 1365-1005) is published 
eight times a year in January, March, April, June, July, September, October, and December. Annual 
subscription rates for Volume 18, 2014: Institutional rate is (print and electronic) $1018.00 in the 
USA, Canada, and Mexico, £614.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional rate (electronic only) $743.00 in 
the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £454.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional rate (print only) $944.00 in the 
USA, Canada, and Mexico, £560.00 + VAT elsewhere. Individual rate is (print and electronic) $236.00 
in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £134.00 + VAT elsewhere. Individual rate (print only) $229.00 in 
the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £131.00 + VAT elsewhere. Students (print only) $122.00 in the USA, 
Canada, and Mexico, £46.00 + VAT elsewhere. For members of the Econometric Society, the Society 
for the Advancement of Economic Theory, the Society for Nonlinear Dynamics and Econometrics, 
the Society for Computational Economics, and the Society for the Promotion of Economic Theory 
the rate is $100.00 in the USA, Canada, and Mexico, £62.00 + VAT elsewhere. Institutional access 
is via IP address range(s) or domain name(s); individual subscriber access is via a username and 
password. Prices include postage; airmail is extra. Write to Cambridge University Press, 32 Avenue 
of the Americas, New York, NY 10013-2473, or outside the USA, Canada, and Mexico to Cambridge 
University Press, The Edinburgh Building, Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge CB2 8RU, England. Claims 
for missing issues should be made immediately after receipt of the next issue. </p>

<p>Periodicals postage pending at NewYork, NY and additional mailing offices. Postmaster: send address 
changes in the USA, Canada, and Mexico to: Macroeconomic Dynamics, Cambridge University 
Press, 100 Brook Hill Drive, West Nyack, NY 10994-2133. Send address changes elsewhere to: 
Macroeconomic Dynamics, Journals Dept., Cambridge University Press, The Edinburgh Building, 
Shaftesbury Road, Cambridge, CB2 8RU, U.K. </p>

<p>c 2014 Cambridge University Press. Photocopying information for users in the USA: The Item-Fee Code for 
this publication indicates that copying for internal or personal use beyond that permitted by Section 107 or 108 
of the US Copyright Law is authorized for users duly registered with the Copyright Clearance Center (CCC) 
Transactional Reporting Service, provided that the appropriate remittance of $18.00 per article is paid directly to: 
CCC, 222 Rosewood Drive, Danvers, MA 01923. Specific written permission must be obtained from the publisher 
for all other copying. The Item-Fee Code for this journal is 1365-1005/14 $18.00. </p>

<p>ISI Tearsheet Service, 3501 Market Street, Philadelphia, PA 19104, USA is authorized to supply single copies 
of separate article for private use only. Article reprints are available from the authors. For orders of 50 or more 
reprints, contact Cambridge University Press. </p>

<p>Macroeconomic Dynamics is indexed in EconLit; The Journal of Economic Literature (e-JEL and JEL on CD); ISI: 
Current Contents/Social &amp; Behavioral Sciences; Social Sciences Citation Index; Research Alert; Mathematical 
Reviews; MathSciNet; Zentralblatt fur Mathematik. </p>

<p>EDITORIAL POLICY </p>

<p>Macroeconomic Dynamics publishes research of the highest theoretical, empirical or quan-
titative sophistication. Papers of high quality are welcomed from all areas of advanced 
macroeconomics and allied fields, so long as the research is founded in a rigorous scientific 
approach. Major advances in macroeconomics without immediate policy applications also 
are accepted, if they show potential for application in the future. Occasional book reviews, 
software reviews, announcements, conference proceedings and interviews are published. </p>

<p>An electronic version of the journal is published just prior to the paper version at 
journals.cambridge.org/mdy. Access to the full-text articles of the electronic version will 
be limited to institutional subscribers of the hard copy version of the journal, with access 
available to all online users at that institution's registered domain. Tables of Contents, 
abstracts, searching and alerting services will remain free of charge. To view the full text 
of Macroeconomic Dynamics, you will need to use the <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">Acrobat Reader</rs> software. 
If you do not have a copy already, you can get it free of charge. Just follow the link from 
our Cambridge Journals Online home page, download it, and install it as a plug-in helper 
application for your browser. </p>

<p>Core terms of use, available at https://www.cambridge.org/core/terms. https://doi.org/10.1017/S136510051300076X </p>

<p>Downloaded from https://www.cambridge.org/core. University of Texas Libraries, on 30 Mar 2018 at 17:02:46, subject to the Cambridge </p>

</text></tei>