<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.20120942" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T14:04+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We present evidence that cultural proximity (shared codes, beliefs, 
ethnicity) between lenders and borrowers increases the quantity 
of credit and reduces default. We identify in-group lending using 
dyadic data on religion and caste for officers and borrowers from an 
Indian bank, and a rotation policy that induces exogenous matching 
between them. Having an in-group officer increases credit access and 
loan size dispersion, reduces collateral requirements, and induces 
better repayment even after the in-group officer leaves. We consider 
a range of explanations and suggest that the findings are most easily 
explained by cultural proximity serving to mitigate information 
frictions in lending. (JEL D82, D83, G21, G28, O16, Z12, Z13) </p>

<p>Shared codes, language, religion-what we will call cultural proximity-between 
potential parties of a transaction can affect the likelihood that the transaction takes 
place, and also its outcome. Commonalities in religion and in ethnic origin, for 
example, are positively associated with trade flows between countries (Guiso, 
Sapienza, and Zingales 2009). The effect of cultural proximity on the quality and 
efficiency of transactions where parties are asymmetrically informed is ambiguous, 
however. There are two prominent explanations, both of which predict a higher level 
of transactions between culturally proximate parties, but with divergent predictions 
on the economic value of these transactions. On the one hand, if members of a group 
tend to do business with one another for preference-based reasons, this may lead to 
discrimination or favoritism and result in resource misallocation. Alternatively, if 
cultural proximity reduces asymmetric information by, for example, reducing the 
cost of communication or contract enforcement, in-group transactions may create 
more economic value for both parties. Given these opposing forces, the effect of </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>cultural proximity on outcomes in markets with asymmetrically informed partici-
pants is an empirical question, and the focus of our analysis in this paper. 
There are a number of challenges in empirically examining the various conse-
quences of preferential in-group treatment, and distinguishing among the various 
explanations underlying such behavior. First, it requires information on the group 
membership of both transacting parties. Most studies have been conducted at a high 
level of aggregation (as in Guiso, Sapienza, and Zingales 2009, for example); or 
they have relied exclusively on the religion or race of only one side of the market, 
and have thus been best set up to detect discrimination against minorities rather than 
dyadic preferences for one's own type. This confounds any improvement in out-
comes from in-group interactions with statistical or animus-based discrimination, 
especially when the in-group advantages are more prevalent within relatively small 
minority groups. Second, even when dyadic data are available, matching between 
parties is driven by the expected profitability of transactions, which is not observed 
by the econometrician. Unobservable differences in profitability-for example, in 
the case where minority agents are relatively "unprofitable"-may result in find-
ing no in-group preferences within minority groups even when one exists, or an 
in-group preference among majority groups even when none exists. Finally, it is dif-
ficult to assess the distortions introduced by information frictions in many economic 
transactions-the sale price of an automobile (as in Ayres and Siegelman 1995), for 
example, largely involves the distribution of a fixed pie. 
We use data from a large state-owned bank in India, a setting that is well-suited 
to studying the consequences of, and rationales for, preferential in-group treatment 
in individual interactions with private information. The setting makes it possible to 
better confront the three identification problems highlighted above. Detailed credit 
and personnel records allow us to match all borrowers and branch head officers to 
their religion and caste, providing a dyadic characterization of the cultural "dis-
tance" between transacting parties in the allocation of personal loans for almost 
three million borrowers over a five year period. An explicit officer rotation policy 
among branches provides variation in the matching between lenders and borrowers. 
We are thus able to control effectively for time-invariant attributes of borrowers 
and lenders, and for time varying credit conditions of each group within narrowly 
defined geographic markets. Further, using detailed records on loan characteristics 
and their ex post performance we can identify the degree to which cultural proxim-
ity may reduce the rationing of credit, the main distortion that arises in the face of 
severe information asymmetries (Stiglitz and Weiss 1981). In addition to the econo-
metric advantages of our data, understanding the link between culture and informa-
tion frictions is of first order importance in an environment characterized by credit 
rationing and a long history of religious and caste conflict. </p>

<p>1   We find strong evidence of preferential in-group treatment. In the baseline results 
we define two individuals as belonging to the same group when both are members of 
the same minority religion (Christian, Muslim, Sikh, Parsi, or Buddhist) or, condi-
tional on belonging to the majority religion (Hindu), when both belong to the same 
official caste (General Class, Scheduled Caste, Scheduled Tribe, or Other Backward </p>

<p>1 For evidence and discussions, see Banerjee, Cole, and Duflo (2004); Banerjee and Duflo (2014); and Field 
et al. (2008). </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>Classes). In our preferred (and most conservative) specifications, we find that on 
average, the total amount of new loans to borrowers in a group increases by 6.5 per-
cent when the officer assigned to the branch belongs to the same group. Having an 
in-group officer also increases the number of new loan recipients by 5.7 percent and 
the probability that a member of the group receives any credit by 2.5 percent. The 
inclusion of branch-quarter, district-group-quarter, and group-branch fixed effects in 
our analysis indicates that the estimated effects are not driven by unobserved varia-
tion in the demand for credit by any group or at any locality, by policies that direct 
credit differentially to different groups and regions over time, or by reverse causal-
ity, where officers are transferred to areas where her group is thriving. The results 
are also robust to an alternate and independent classification where we use individ-
uals' surnames to assign borrowers and officers based on the religious caste system 
that prevailed in ancient India. This rules out the possibility that our findings result 
from systematic errors in the classification of individuals in the bank's records, or 
by targeted lending policies based on this classification. 
We then go on to examine the effect of in-group lending on the quality of credit 
provision and the cost of credit to borrowers. Loans made to in-group borrowers 
have better repayment performance ex post. The economic magnitude of this effect 
is large: in-group borrowers are 0.6 percentage points less likely to be late in loan 
payments, a 7 percent decline relative to the average default probability in the sam-
ple (8.6 percent). The decline in default probability persists even after the in-group 
officer is replaced by an out-group one, implying that the effect on loan quality is 
not driven by officers rolling over loans to bad borrowers (evergreening). Since all 
loans have the same interest rate, we evaluate the effect of proximity on the cost of 
borrowing through its impact on the collateral required per rupee of credit. We find 
that cultural proximity lowers the cost of borrowing measured this way. Under mild 
assumptions, our credit quality and quantity results also imply that cultural proxim-
ity improves the profitability of lending. </p>

<p>2   Standard models of in-group favoritism predict resource misallocation, as trans-
acting agents trade off efficiency against higher payoffs from the utility gain of 
favoring their in-group counterparts. In our context this would imply loan officers 
bearing the cost of higher default rates in exchange for lending more to their own 
group. In contrast, standard models of credit markets with asymmetric information 
predict that, if cultural ties reduce information asymmetries (either ex ante because 
of better communication or ex post because of better enforcement), they should 
lead to less credit rationing, e.g., more and cheaper credit to lower risk borrowers. 
The prima facie evidence from our main results is consistent with the latter type of 
models. 
We emphasize that our data do not allow us to rule out all favoritism-based expla-
nations. In particular, the distinction we describe in the previous paragraph focuses 
on types of favoritism that generate lower performance for the loan officer, which 
captures the cost he bears for favoring his own type. We offer some additional results 
that help to further evaluate our rationing interpretation, in particular repeating our </p>

<p>2 Specifically, we require the further assumption that government banks in India lend too little relative to their 
marginal cost of capital. This view finds empirical support in Banerjee, Cole, and Duflo (2004) and Banerjee and 
Duflo (2014). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>estimation using only branches in districts where the bank we study is the only 
formal lender. We find that cultural proximity leads to an expansion of credit even 
in areas where the only alternative source of funds are expensive moneylenders. 
In these areas, borrowers cannot simply substitute across similarly priced funding 
sources. This reinforces the interpretation that cultural proximity may reduce credit 
rationing. </p>

<p>3   In a final set of analyses, we look at the specific predictions of existing models of 
information frictions in lending, and examine the extent to which these predictions 
are borne out in the data. Cornell and Welch (1996) suggest that cultural proximity 
may reduce information asymmetries in a credit transaction by improving the preci-
sion of the signal that the officer obtains of a borrower's creditworthiness. A direct 
prediction of their model is that cultural proximity should increase the variance of 
loan sizes, as the officer's distribution of prior beliefs of borrower quality widens 
with the more precise signal. Consistent with this prediction, we find that in-group 
loans have a substantially larger size dispersion than out-group ones. Rajan (1992)  argues that the repeated interaction between a lender and a borrower provides the 
lender with "soft" private information about a borrower's credit quality. We can 
examine the role of repeated interaction by looking at heterogeneity of the in-group 
effect across first-time and existing borrowers, and over time as the loan officer and 
the borrower interact. We find that officers expand lending to in-group borrowers 
that have a prior relationship with the bank as well as to new borrowers, and that the 
credit expansion occurs immediately on the officer's arrival at a branch and persists 
throughout his tenure. These results suggest that the benefits of cultural proximity 
are distinct from and additive to those that potentially derive from a borrower's 
observable track record with the lending institution or those that come from repeated 
interaction between officer and borrower. 
Our main conclusion, that cultural proximity improves the quantity, quality, and 
cost of lending, has a number of economic and policy implications that are indepen-
dent of the specific mechanism through which it operates. The first is that the net 
positive effect of cultural proximity on credit outcomes can be mistaken for discrim-
ination in the data, since minority borrowers are far less likely to be "matched" with 
an in-group lender than borrowers that belong to a large group. A naïve regression of 
loan access on borrower group identity that ignores the group identity of the lender 
would indicate discrimination against minorities rather than preferential in-group 
treatment among all groups. This calls for caution in the interpretation of, and policy 
prescriptions that can be derived from, empirical studies that identify differential 
treatment based solely on the identity of one of the parties of the transaction. This 
point is raised theoretically in Cornell and Welch (1996). </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3 Our estimates of the effect are also significant and of comparable magnitude in areas where there are many 
alternative sources of formal funding. In these areas, however, we do not have means of pinning down whether or 
not cultural proximity alleviates credit rationing. 
4 See, for example, Goldin and Rouse (2000), Bertrand and Mullainathan (2004), and Charles and Guryan  (2008) for evidence in labor markets, and List (2004) for evidence in sports card trading markets. There is also 
evidence of discrimination in different types of credit markets, such as mortgages (see Ross et al. 2008 for one 
recent example, and Ladd 1998 for a survey of the evidence), small business lending (Blanchflower, Levine, and  Zimmerman 2003), trade credit (Fafchamps 2000, Fisman 2003), and online person-to-person lending (Pope and 
Sydnor 2011). </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>A second, related implication is that a naïve data analysis may also lead to the 
formation of statistical discrimination against minority groups. Even if all groups in 
the population have the same ex ante average propensity to default, minority group 
borrowers will have a worse credit repayment history because they are more likely 
to be matched to an out-group officer. Since all consumer credit scoring models 
ignore the identity of the lender, minorities will face higher borrowing costs in the 
marketplace purely due to statistical discrimination. This insight relates to a body of 
theoretical work, following Arrow (1973), that rationalizes statistical discrimination 
as an equilibrium with self-confirming beliefs, but that is silent about the origin of 
these beliefs. If statistical discrimination is a consequence of in-group preferential 
treatment, a policy that increases the likelihood of a group match between lenders 
and borrowers would unambiguously improve the efficiency of credit allocation in 
consumer credit markets. </p>

<p>5   Prior work that examines the role of group identity using dyadic data finds mixed 
results. Ayres and Siegelman (1995) finds evidence of race and gender discrimi-
nation in an audit study of price bargaining in the US new car market, but finds no 
evidence of in-group preferential treatment. In contrast, Price and Wolfers (2010)  and Parsons et al. (2011) find evidence consistent with race-based discrimination 
among NBA referees and MLB umpires, and Schoar, Iyer, and Kumar (2008) find 
that sellers bargain for lower prices when the seller belongs to the same community 
in an audit study in India. The key contribution of our study is to provide evidence 
of the effect of cultural proximity in a context where the negative effects of ani-
mus-based discrimination may be countered by the positive effects of better infor-
mation exchange and enforcement. 
Our paper also relates to the literature on the economic consequences of social ties 
between transacting parties. 
6 Our results indicate that cultural proximity increases 
the likelihood of two individuals who have likely never met interacting in the mar-
ket and forming a tie. This suggests that social ties are endogenously formed as a 
consequence of common cultural endowments. The effects of cultural endowments 
and social ties are typically confounded in existing work that associates endogenous 
past social interactions with future market transactions. 
7 The distinction is import-
ant because cultural endowments, such as religion and caste, are assigned at birth 
and transmitted across generations of individuals of the same group, while social 
ties and connections are dynamic and often subject to individual choice (Becker  1996). This implies that the economic consequences of cultural endowment differ-
ences across groups that we document in our analyses can persist in the long run, 
and potentially perpetuate inequality. 
Finally, our study relates to the literature on the role of soft information in eco-
nomic transactions. Much of this research has focused on credit relationships, and 
indeed many of the outcomes that we examine-the extent and price of credit, as </p>

<p>5 See Kim and Loury (2009) for a discussion of the origin of statistical discrimination, and Coate and Loury  (1993), Norman (2003), and Fryer and Loury (2005), for discussions of optimal policy prescriptions in such mul-
tiple equilibrium settings. 
6 For evidence of the effect of social connections on economic interactions see, for example, Banerjee and  Munshi (2004) and Bandiera, Barankay, and Rasul (2009). 
7 For examples of this work see Cohen, Frazzini, and Malloy (2008, 2010); Hwang and Kim (2009); Engelberg, 
Gao, and Parsons (2012); Jackson and Schneider (2011); and Li (2012). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>well as loan quality-are also the focus of this literature (see, for example, Keys et  al. 2010; Petersen and Rajan 1994). We note, however, that owing to officer rota-
tion, we are better able to identify the effects of soft information relative to papers 
that have used time-invariant proxies for soft information between lenders and 
borrowers. 
In the next section, we provide a brief discussion of models of lending under 
conditions of asymmetric information, and discuss the implications for the analysis 
that follows. Then, Section II, we turn to providing an overview of the data and a 
description of the Indian bank that we study-its organization, the incentives of its 
officers, and so forth. In Section III we present the baseline empirical specification 
for the analysis. Section IV presents our results on lending quantity and quality; 
Section V presents an additional set of results on loan dispersion, and heterogeneity 
by borrower, officer, and branch characteristics, which we use to explore which 
prominent models of in-group lending are consistent with the data. In Section VI we 
conclude with some policy implications and directions for future work. </p>

<p>I. Theoretical Background and Motivation </p>

<p>In the discussion that follows, we will lay out the comparative statics provided by 
prominent models of information asymmetries in credit markets, describing how we 
expect loan quantity, repayment rates, and loan dispersion to be affected by reduced 
informational frictions. These frictions may be either ex ante, relating to the lender's 
ability to assess project quality, or ex post, affecting the lender's ability to ensure that 
funds are used as agreed and that the loan is repaid. We will take whether bank offi-
cer and borrower are of the same group-henceforth referred to as SameGroup-as 
a measure of cultural proximity, and consider the empirical predictions of a model 
where cultural ties reduce information asymmetries. It is beyond the scope of our 
analysis to decisively pin down the mechanism through which cultural proximity 
affects lending, but we can explore the extent to which our data are consistent with 
these existing models. 
In the canonical models of credit markets under asymmetric information, the 
effect of better information on credit access is ambiguous. For example, asymmet-
ric information may increase or decrease the level of credit depending on whether 
borrowers have private information on the level or the variance of project returns 
(De Meza and Webb 1987, Stiglitz and Weiss 1981). At the extreme, a lender that 
faces severe information asymmetry will pool all borrowers, which may lead to a 
larger amount of credit than in the high-information SameGroup case, or to no credit 
at all. Given this theoretical ambiguity, our empirical exercise can be viewed as an 
assessment of which type of effect dominates in an important real-world setting. 
There is greater agreement across these well-known models in their predic-
tions on the effect of information frictions on default. In both of the cases above, 
a better-informed lender can screen out low-quality (from the bank's perspective) 
projects ex ante thus reducing default. Improved information similarly reduces the 
cost of borrowing for those that receive credit. The emphasis in these models is on 
screening, but reduced informational frictions can also improve credit access and 
outcomes by allowing for improved ex post enforcement as documented, for exam-
ple, by Fafchamps (2000) in ethnic trading networks in sub-Saharan Africa. Thus, </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>a primary pair of predictions shared by these (and other) models of lending in the 
face of information frictions is that default rates and the cost of funds are lower 
for SameGroup borrowers. Since interest rates are fixed in our setting, we focus 
on collateral as a measure of borrowing cost (higher risk borrowers will post more 
collateral holding the interest rate constant), and examine whether collateral to loan 
ratios are lower for SameGroup loans. 
Cornell and Welch's (1996) screening model shows that lower information fric-
tions within a group will be reflected in larger loan size dispersion for the group. 
The reason for this is that better-informed lenders receive more precise signals of 
creditworthiness, which implies that the variance of the distribution of priors of 
SameGroup borrower quality across borrowers will be greater. Thus, a prediction 
that may help us to identify the presence of better in-group screening is that loans 
to SameGroup borrowers have higher dispersion. 
8 Note that this does not rule 
out enforcement-based explanations, which make no strong predictions about the 
ex ante loan size distribution, but will allow us to assess whether our data are con-
sistent with models where better screening plays a role. 
We conclude our background discussion with an overview of how models of 
reduced informational frictions through shared culture contrast with models of 
preference-based discrimination in the spirit of Becker (1957). Favoritism in this 
class of models is manifested in the cost that an individual incurs as a result of his 
in-group preferences. For example, a business owner sacrifices profits or, in our con-
text, a loan officer reduces his performance (and hence career progression) in order 
to indulge his discriminatory preferences. Such models of SameGroup favoritism 
predict a higher level of SameGroup interactions and on more favorable terms-
predictions potentially shared by models of information asymmetries-but predict 
lower-quality transactions. 
9 In our context, preference based discrimination implies 
a higher default rate for SameGroup borrowers-the cost to the loan officer of favor-
itism. This also highlights some limitations of our analysis-our data are less suited 
to picking up on the effects of SameGroup favoritism that do not entail a cost to the 
loan officer. </p>

<p>II. Data </p>

<p>The main variables in the analysis are obtained from the individual loan portfolio 
and personnel records of a large state-owned bank in India, which operates over 
2,000 geographically dispersed branches (see Appendix Figure A1). The sample 
starts in the second quarter of 1999 and ends in the first quarter of 2005. This section 
describes in detail the structure and construction of the dataset and relevant back-
ground information on the organization of the bank itself. </p>

<p>8 Rajan, Seru, and Vig (2015) use a similar test to show that an increase in "distance" brought about by securi-
tization leads to lower information production on loans. 
9 Parsons et al. (2011), for example, find evidence of racial bias in baseball umpires' strike calls, but only in 
stadiums where their calls are not monitored, and thus there is no possible sanction to their biased behavior. This 
represents evidence that agents trade off the benefits of acting according to biased preferences against the potential 
costs of doing so. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>A. Loans, Borrowers, and Branch Heads </p>

<p>The individual loan portfolio data include loan-level information for every bor-
rower with a loan outstanding during the sample period (2.92 million individuals). 
Loan contract characteristics and repayment status are reported on a quarterly basis 
(1.23 million borrowers per quarter on average). Since we are interested in compar-
ing the lending decisions of in-group and out-group officers around officer rotations, 
we focus our analysis on the flow of new debt from a branch b , to a group g , in 
quarter q . The bank issued just over 1.8 million new loans during the sample period. 
The mean (median) new loan amount is 59,681 (22,506) rupees. We focus on flows, 
given that the incoming officer played no part in the decision to issue a loan prior to 
their arrival at a branch. </p>

<p>10   We use the bank's quarterly personnel records to identify the head officer of each 
branch in each quarter (4,270 distinct officers in total). Loan officers are classified 
into six grades, with increasing seniority and ability to approve larger loan amounts. 
The highest-ranking officer in each branch is the branch head. For smaller branches, 
the head officer may himself have a relatively low grade. This implies that any larger 
loan request that comes through the branch will have to be approved by a higher 
grade officer elsewhere in the region. Still, in these cases the decision of whether 
to submit the loan for approval at a higher level of the bank hierarchy is at the head 
officer's discretion, and based on information collected at the branch level. Officers 
have control over loan and collateral amounts, but they have no discretion over inter-
est rates, which are determined by headquarters based on loan type. For example, 
all home improvement loans pay the same rate, as do all educational loans above 
Rs 400,000. 
Branch heads-the focus of our analysis here-are evaluated annually using a 
range of criteria. 
11 These include quantitative measures such as the amount and 
profitability of lending, as well as qualitative considerations such as employee skill 
development, effective customer communication, and other aspects of "leadership 
competency." Officers are held accountable for loan defaults after moving branches. 
Typically, officers are responsible for loans they approve for three years following 
their departure, at which point responsibility is transferred to an officer in the branch 
where the loan was made. 
While there is limited incentive pay, branch heads are motivated through promo-
tion to higher grades or better postings. As a result, branch heads face strong incen-
tives to issue profitable loans and perform well along other qualitative dimensions 
that serve as inputs into their evaluations. Since successful branch heads may be 
sent to locales with more or better perquisites, such as higher pay (overseas), larger 
houses, the use of a car, or control over a larger portfolio (large branches), in the 
analysis that follows we evaluate the extent to which such endogenous allocation of 
officers to branches affects our estimates. </p>

<p>10 The analysis in a previous version of the paper focused on the stock of debt: amount of debt outstanding for 
the borrowers in a group at any point in time. The results are qualitatively similar, but noisier. We thank the editor 
and an anonymous referee for suggesting this change. 
11 Information on evaluation and compensation of managers within the bank come primarily from interviews 
with bank staff; we do not have access to individual evaluations. </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>B. Religion, Official Caste, and Religious Caste </p>

<p>The bank records contain information on the religion and official caste classifica-
tions of each borrower and employee. Individuals are grouped into seven categories 
based on the prominent religions in India: Hindu, Muslim, Christian, Sikh, Parsi, 
Buddhist, and others. They are also classified into four castes based on the categories 
explicitly recognized by the Constitution of India: General Class (GC), Scheduled 
Castes (SC), Scheduled Tribes (ST), and Other Backward Classes (OBC). The SC 
category comprises all the castes historically treated as "untouchable" by the upper 
castes in India. The ST category includes indigenous, typically geographically iso-
lated, tribal groups. The OBC category is a collection of caste groups ranked above 
untouchables in the ritual hierarchy, but socially and educationally disadvantaged. 
Individuals belonging to the SC, ST, and OBC categories receive targeted govern-
ment aid and benefit from positive discrimination policies (subject to means testing) 
such as reservations in public sector employment and higher education. 
12 Although 
the SC, ST, and OBC categories include a wide variety of social groups across India, 
locally they are often relatively homogeneous. The GC category is essentially a col-
lection of all the individuals not belonging to the aforementioned "backward" classes. 
In order to obtain a group classification that is independent of the bank's records, 
we use the borrower and officer surnames to generate a classification based on 
religious castes. According to religious texts such as Manusmriti, Hindu society is 
broadly divided into four Varnas: the Brahmins (priests and scholars), Kshatriyas 
(warriors), Vaishyas (merchants and traders), and Shudras (laborers and artisans). 
Each Varna is a unification of several Jatis, or communities (see Bühler 1886), and a 
person's surname typically reflects the Jati they belong to. We exploit this link with 
surnames to classify each individual into their Varna (see Banerjee et al. 2009 for a 
further discussion of the link between surnames and castes in India). In the Appendix 
we provide a description of the matching procedure and some specific examples. 
Using surnames to classify borrowers and officers by religious caste results in 
several sources of additional noise and imprecision. First, many surnames can be 
classified into two or more Varnas. 
13 We create three special categories for individ-
uals where this ambiguity arises (Kshatriya-Brahmin, Kshatriya-Brahmin-Vaishya, 
and Kshatriyas-Vaishyas). We note, however, that within a region there is usu-
ally only a single Varna associated with each surname. So once we condition on 
region-as we do throughout our analysis-there is a clearer link between names 
and communities. Second, it is unclear how to categorize individuals into the Shudra 
Varna according to their community affiliations, which precludes using surnames for 
individuals outside of the General Classes. Finally, in less than 1 percent of cases, 
the surname-based classification conflicted with the bank classifications assigned 
to loan officers and borrowers. For example, many bank-classified Muslims had </p>

<p>12 The categories of Scheduled Caste (SC) and Scheduled Tribes (ST) which represented a majority of 
lower-status castes and tribes were first protected in anti-discrimination laws through the ninth schedule of the 
Constitution in 1950 (Article 15, 17, and 46). In 1990, the further caste-based categorization of OBC was added 
for identifying additional socially and economically deprived communities. A few years later the category of OBC 
was extended to include a significant segment of the non-Hindu population, notably Muslims, Christians, and Sikhs. 
13 For example Saxena is grouped under both Brahmins and Kshatriyas. Similarly Desai is grouped under both 
Brahmins and Vaishyas. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>"Hindu" surnames, and vice-versa. Still, exploring the effect of proximity along 
the Varna dimension is interesting in its own right, and will allow us to ascertain 
whether the results based on bank classifications are driven by systematic misclassi-
fication of officers and borrowers in the bank records. </p>

<p>C. Descriptive Statistics: Group Composition </p>

<p>The religion, official caste, and Varna compositions of the borrower and officer 
populations are shown in Table 1. By religion, Hindus represent the majority of 
borrowers (89.4 percent) and officers (93.8 percent). The largest group of minority 
borrowers is Muslim (6.33 percent), and the largest officer minority is Christian 
(2.1 percent). Hindus are over-represented and Muslims under-represented in the 
borrower and officer populations relative to the total population (80.5 percent Hindu 
and 13.4 percent Muslim according to the 2001 census). Most borrowers and offi-
cers are classified as General Class (66.7 percent and 74.3 percent, respectively). 
The largest borrower minority is the OBC category (16.6 percent), while the largest 
officer minority is ST (15.7 percent). SCs are under-represented in the borrower 
sample and STs under-represented in the officer sample, relative to the population 
(16.2 percent SC and 8.2 percent ST in the 2001 census). </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>14 The 2001 India Census does not keep track of OBCs. </p>

<p>Table 1-Borrower and Head Officer Composition, by Religion and Caste </p>

<p>Borrowers (percent) 
Head officers (percent) </p>

<p>Panel A. By religion 
Hindu 
89.36 
93.79 
Muslim 
6.33 
1.84 
Christian 
1.81 
2.06 
Sikh 
1.95 
1.76 
Parsi 
0.13 
0.05 
Buddhist 
0.19 
0.25 
Other 
0.23 
0.25 </p>

<p>Panel B. By official caste 
General 
66.66 
74.31 
SC 
10.67 
15.68 
ST 
6.02 
5.12 
OBC 
16.64 
4.89 </p>

<p>Panel C. By Varna 
Brahmin 
18.28 
23.01 
Kshatriya 
60.52 
43.43 
Vaishya 
6.59 
11.67 
Kshatriya/Brahmin 
1.72 
10.77 
Kshatriya/Brahmin/Vaishya 
6.76 
3.48 
Kshatriya/Vaishya 
0.41 
1.29 
Other 
5.72 
6.35 </p>

<p>Notes: Group refers to the religion and caste (conditional on Hindu religion) that the borrower 
belongs to. There are nine groups: five minority religions and, conditional on Hindu religion, 
four government sanctioned castes. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>We are able to match surnames to Varnas for a subsample of the population. 
A total of 502,723 borrowers (18.3 percent Brahmin, 60.5 percent Kshatriya, 6.6 
percent Vaishya, 1.7 percent mixed categories, and 5.72 percent in other catego-
ries) and 1,689 officers (23.0 percent Brahmin, 43.4 percent Kshatriya, 11.7 percent 
Vaishya, 15.5 percent mixed categories, and 6.4 percent in other categories) have 
Varna assignments. These represent approximately 17 percent of borrowers and 40 
percent of officers in our sample. All identifiable Varnas in our sample belong to 
the General Class according to official caste definitions. The average size of new 
loans issued to surname-matched borrowers is 4 percent larger than the average 
size of loans issued to unmatched borrowers classified as Hindu General Caste in 
the bank's records. The difference is statistically significant, indicating that the sur-
name-matched sample is comprised of borrowers with access to marginally higher 
loan amounts relative to the general population of Hindu General Caste borrowers. </p>

<p>D. Descriptive Statistics: Branches and Groups </p>

<p>In the average (median) branch quarter, the total flow of new loans is 2.36 (1.50) 
million rupees, issued to 39.6 (31) borrowers (Table 2, panel A). The borrower com-
position is generally heterogeneous: the median branch issues new loans to borrow-
ers of two different religions and two different official castes. The median branch is 
small, with two loan officers including the head officer, and the modal branch has a 
single officer. </p>

<p>Table 2-Summary Statistics </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
p1 
p50 
p99 </p>

<p>Panel A. Branch-quarter statistics, N = 46,753 
Total new credit (millions of rupees) 
2.36 
3.74 
0.00 
1.50 
14.22 
Number of borrowers 
39.6 
48.9 
0.0 
31.0 
200.0 
Number of different borrower religions 
1.85 
0.91 
0.00 
2.00 
4.00 
Number of different borrower castes 
2.35 
1.08 
0.00 
2.00 
4.00 
Number of different borrower groups 
3.18 
1.50 
0.00 
3.00 
6.00 
Number of loan officers (including head officer) 
3.53 
4.20 
0.00 
2.00 
16.00 
Number of clerks 
6.40 
7.12 
0.00 
4.00 
31.00 </p>

<p>Panel B. Group-branch-quarter statistics, N = 339,366 
Sum new credit (1,000s of rupees) 
245.8 
1227.9 
0.0 
0.0 
4,183.0 
Fraction of branch new credit 
0.116 
0.259 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 
Number of new credit recipients 
4.11 
15.13 
0.00 
0.00 
55.00 
Fraction of branch number of new credit recipients 
0.116 
0.249 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 
Standard deviation new credit (1,000s of rupees) 
29.9 
124.1 
0.0 
0.0 
337.6 
IQR new credit (1,000s of rupees) 
22.6 
96.3 
0.0 
0.0 
312.7 
Dummy = 1 if new credit &gt; 0 
0.338 
0.473 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 
Total collateral/outstanding debt 
10.50 
633.61 
0.33 
2.37 
14.92 
Maturity (years) 
2.83 
2.95 
0.00 
2.43 
15.00 
Interest rate (percent) 
10.98 
2.22 
3.62 
11.46 
15.50 
Fraction borrowers over 60 days late after 1 year 
0.086 
0.233 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 
Fraction new debt over 60 days late after 1 year 
0.036 
0.159 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 
SameGroup 
0.110 
0.312 
0.000 
0.000 
1.000 </p>

<p>Notes: Panel A: branch-quarter panel statistics. Panel B: branch-quarter-group panel statistics (group: borrower's 
religion and caste conditional on Hindu religion). There are nine groups: five minority religions and, conditional on 
Hindu religion, four government sanctioned castes. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>The unit of analysis is the branch-group-quarter level (indexed by b , g , and q , 
respectively) where group refers to the cultural group of the borrower. In our main 
specification we use the full set of religion and caste information to group borrowers 
into nine categories: five minority religions, and four official castes conditional on 
the religion being Hindu. In other specifications we consider group definitions based 
on Varna classifications. The panel employing our main group classifications has 
339,366 branch-group-quarter observations (descriptive statistics shown in Table 2, 
panel B). In the average group-branch-quarter cell the sum of new loans is 245,800 
rupees. Not all groups receive new loans in all periods from all branches: only 33.8 
percent of the cells have positive debt flow (as a consequence the median group-
branch-quarter debt flow is zero). 
In order to have a dependent variable that captures both changes in the amount of 
credit to a group (group-intensive margin) and the probability of a group receiving 
credit (group-extensive margin), our preferred specifications use the flow of credit 
to a group in a branch divided by the total flow of new credit allocated by the branch 
in the same quarter (in what follows we will use the terms new credit and new loans 
interchangeably to refer to the flow of new credit issued). The group-branch-quarter 
average (median) fraction of branch new credit is 0.116 (0.0). Similarly, we define 
fraction of new loan recipients as the ratio of the number of new loan recipients in 
a group-branch-quarter divided by the number of new loan recipients in the same 
branch quarter (the average is also 0.116). 
We use two measures of the cross-sectional dispersion of new loan sizes among 
the individuals in a group, the standard deviation (SD) and the interquartile range 
(IQR). The average branch-group-quarter SD and IQR of loans are 29.9 and 22.6 
thousand rupees, respectively. The bank records the sum of all the collateral pledged 
by a borrower at any given time (not the amount of collateral that secures a particu-
lar loan). Thus, we report and analyze collateralization based on the stock of credit 
outstanding to the set of borrowers receiving new loans in each quarter. The median 
branch-group-quarter ratio of total collateral to total outstanding debt for these bor-
rowers is 2.37. The average maturity is 2.8 years and the average interest rate is 11 
percent. New loan recipients must be current in repayments in order to receive a 
loan. We measure default as the probability of a new loan recipient being over 60 
days late (in any loan) 1 year after the loan is issued. The branch-group-quarter 
average fraction of borrowers that default according to this definition is 8.6 percent. 
We merge the branch-level personnel information to this panel to obtain our main 
explanatory variable, SameGrou p bgq , a dummy variable that is equal to one for the 
branch-group-quarter loan cells where the branch head officer belongs to group g , 
and zero otherwise. For example, if the head officer of branch b in quarter q is 
Muslim, then SameGrou p bgq = 1 for loans to group g if g = Muslim, and zero for 
all other groups in that branch quarter. Since this dummy is equal to 1 for one and 
only one group at any given branch quarter, its sample average is 1/9 = 0.11 by 
construction. </p>

<p>E. Officer Rotation </p>

<p>The bank follows an explicit policy of geographical officer rotation, with the 
stated objective of reducing opportunities for corruption, nepotism, and other </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>perverse incentives in the allocation of loans. As a result, branch turnover is high: 
we observe an average of 127 head officer reallocations per quarter, and the median 
branch has 1 officer change during our sample period. The mean (median) spell of 
a head officer in a branch is 8.3 (8) quarters, with standard deviation of 4.1. Head 
officers are always assigned to branches that are located away from their home town, 
and the average officer reallocation assigns the officer to a new branch that is 250 
kilometers from the previous assignment. This implies that although officers gener-
ally stay within the same region, it is unlikely that they have had any prior interac-
tion with any of the potential borrowers in their new location. 
In Table 3 we report the empirical distribution of branch transition rates by group, 
along with the theoretical distribution of transition rates that would result from ran-
dom matching across branches nationally. We observe a total of 3,316 officer tran-
sitions. To examine the extent to which the empirical distribution differs from that 
dictated by random assignment, we perform a permutation test as follows: we fill 
each of 3,316 positions in an array in proportion to the number of officer-quar-
ter observations of that group observed in our data. So, for example, given that 
70.2 percent of officer-quarter observations are General Caste Hindus, 2,327 (0.702 
× 3,316) of the initial positions are assigned to General Caste Hindu. We then 
randomly permute the ordering of the initial assignment, and use the observed </p>

<p>Table 3-Empirical and Theoretical Officer Group Transition Rates </p>

<p>Empirical transition rates (theoretical transition rates) </p>

<p>To group: 
Muslim Christian 
Sikh 
Parsi 
Buddhist Others Hindu/SC Hindu/ST </p>

<p>Hindu/ 
OBC </p>

<p>Hindu/ 
general </p>

<p>From group: 
Muslim 
0.0009 
0.0006 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0018 
0.0009 
0.0012 
0.0130 
(0.0004) (0.0004) (0.0003) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0001) (0.0027) (0.0008) (0.0009) (0.0133) </p>

<p>Christian 
0.0003 
0.0045 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0033 
0.0006 
0.0027 
0.0166 
(0.0004) (0.0006) (0.0004) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0001) (0.0034) (0.0010) (0.0011) (0.0166) </p>

<p>Sikh 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0024 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0024 
0.0003 
0.0003 
0.0109 
(0.0003) (0.0004) (0.0003) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0001) (0.0025) (0.0007) (0.0008) (0.0122) </p>

<p>Parsi 
0.0000 
0.0003 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0003 
(0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0001) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0004) </p>

<p>Buddhist 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0018 
(0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0003) (0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0015) </p>

<p>Others 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0003 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0003 
0.0009 
(0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0000) (0.0004) (0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0021) </p>

<p>Hindu/SC 
0.0030 
0.0033 
0.0024 
0.0000 
0.0006 
0.0006 
0.0344 
0.0063 
0.0066 
0.0781 
(0.0027) (0.0034) (0.0025) (0.0001) (0.0003) (0.0004) (0.0204) (0.0060) (0.0068) (0.1002) </p>

<p>Hindu/ST 
0.0009 
0.0009 
0.0003 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0054 
0.0069 
0.0027 
0.0178 
(0.0008) (0.0010) (0.0007) (0.0000) (0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0060) (0.0018) (0.0020) (0.0297) </p>

<p>Hindu/OBC 
0.0009 
0.0015 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0000 
0.0060 
0.0027 
0.0048 
0.0305 
(0.0009) (0.0011) (0.0008) 0.0000 (0.0001) (0.0001) (0.0068) (0.0020) (0.0023) (0.0334) </p>

<p>Hindu/general 
0.0130 
0.0145 
0.0139 
0.0006 
0.0012 
0.0018 
0.0856 
0.0232 
0.0299 
0.5314 
(0.0133) (0.0166) (0.0122) (0.0004) (0.0015) (0.0021) (0.1002) (0.0297) (0.0334) (0.4929) </p>

<p>Notes: In this table we report branch officer empirical transition rates by officer group, based on 3,316 officer transi-
tions. In parentheses are the theoretical transition rates that would result if the officers had been randomly assigned 
to branches. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>transitions to generate a transition matrix. We repeat this process 1,000 times, and 
test whether the empirical transition rates fall within the 90, 95, or 99 percent confi-
dence interval of the simulated distribution. A comparison of the empirical and sim-
ulated distributions indicates that, overall, there are significantly more within-group 
transitions than would be expected from random rotation. 
The relatively high proportion of within-group transitions is expected since some 
states in India have reservation policies that require a minimum representation of 
SC, ST, and OBC officials in any government position. The key assumption of our 
identification approach, which we discuss in detail in the next subsection, is that 
the rotation policy induces variation in the matching between officer and borrower 
group identity that is plausibly uncorrelated with the demand for credit. We will 
return to the issues raised by possible nonrandom assignment, and the validity of our 
empirical approach, in Section IV where we present "event study" patterns around 
officer transitions to show that assignment to an in-group officer is not preceded by 
abnormal increases or decreases in credit to a group. In addition, our main empirical 
specification uses saturated regressions that incorporate branch-quarter (which sub-
sume officer fixed-effects), group-quarter, and district-group-quarter dummies that 
address various selection-based alternative explanations. </p>

<p>III. Empirical Specification </p>

<p>Our baseline empirical specification identifies the effect of cultural proximity 
from the time series variation in loan outcomes for a particular group, in a particular 
location, when the group identity of the officer changes due to the rotation policy. 
The specification takes the following form: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>y gbq = β SameGrou p bgq + α gb + τ bq + ∑ </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>γ gq 
d + ϵ bgq . </p>

<p>The dependent variable in most specifications is a lending outcome of a group 
in a branch quarter, relative to the overall outcome in the same branch quarter. For 
example, when we analyze the impact on the flow of new credit, the dependent vari-
able is the ratio of new credit to all borrowers that belong to group g in branch b and 
quarter q to the new credit issued to all groups in branch b in quarter q. SameGroup 
is an indicator variable denoting whether the branch head in branch b belongs to 
group g in quarter q . 
For most of our results, we present specifications that include group-branch 
( α gb ), branch-quarter ( τ bq ), and district-group-quarter ( γ gq 
d ) dummies, where d 
indexes the district in which the branch is located. This full set of fixed effects helps 
to rule out a range of identification concerns. The group-branch dummies capture 
time-invariant attributes of each group within each branch, and ensure that the esti-
mation of β does indeed come from the time series variation induced by officer 
rotation. The branch-quarter fixed effects account for all changes in the demand for 
credit in a particular location, as well as changes in directed credit policies aimed at 
certain localities. Since there is only one branch head at a time in each branch, the 
branch-quarter fixed effects also account for changes in an officer's behavior over 
time, for example, due to experience or learning. Finally, the district-group-quarter </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>dummies capture shocks to and trends in the demand for credit of specific groups 
in narrowly defined geographical areas (conditional on having a branch, the median 
district has three bank branches in our sample). This helps us to rule out the possi-
bility that the estimated β is the result of, for example, reverse causality driven by 
the endogenous allocation of officers into areas where their own group is thriving. 
In the estimation we allow the error term ϵ bgq to be clustered at the branch level. 
This accounts for serial correlation in lending and for the mechanical correlation of 
SameGroup across groups in the same branch. </p>

<p>15   The coefficient on SameGroup is a difference-in-differences estimate of the effect 
of cultural proximity between a lender and a borrower on loan outcomes. Consider, 
for example, the regression with the fraction of new credit as the dependent vari-
able and, for simplicity, suppose there are only three groups: Hindus, Muslims, and 
Christians. Suppose that a branch has a Hindu officer during the first half of the 
sample, and a Muslim officer during the second half. The coefficient on SameGroup 
will be the weighted average of (i) the difference between the fraction of new credit 
obtained by Hindu borrowers in the branch when the officer is a Hindu (in-group) 
officer relative to when the officer is a Muslim, and (ii) the difference between the 
fraction of new credit obtained by Muslim borrowers with a Muslim officer relative 
to a Hindu one. While our main results show the average effect across all groups, we 
will also allow the effect of SameGroup to vary across religions and castes. </p>

<p>IV. Results: Loan Quantity and Quality </p>

<p>We begin with a graphical description of (unconditional) lending patterns around 
officer transitions. First we classify borrowers into two categories based on whether 
they have the same group identity as the outgoing officer: in-group borrowers are 
those belonging to the same group as the officer, and all others are categorized 
as out-group borrowers. For example, in a branch where the outgoing officer is 
Christian, the Christian borrowers are in-group before the officer change, and bor-
rowers from all other religions are classified as out-group. Each of these borrower 
groups may or may not experience a change in their in-group/out-group status 
after the officer change. For example, suppose the Christian officer is replaced by 
a Muslim one. Then, Christian borrowers transition from in-group to out-group, 
Muslim borrowers transition from out-group to in-group, and other religions remain 
as out-group throughout. Alternatively, if the replacement officer is also Christian, 
then Christian borrowers remain as in-group and all minority borrowers remain as 
out-group. 
We use these borrower classifications to construct "event study" plots around 
officer changes. The horizontal axis of the plots in Figure 1 measures time in quar-
ters since the officer change in a branch. Event time t = 0 represents the first quar-
ter when a new officer appears as the branch head in the personnel files. Given that 
our analysis is based on quarterly data, the new officer may arrive up to 11 weeks </p>

<p>15 By construction, every time SameGroup changes from zero to one for group g in branch b , it will change from 
one to zero for some other group in the same branch b . </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>before the observed entry time. 
16 The vertical axis measures the average fraction 
of new debt in a branch allocated to a group of borrowers and the 95 percent confi-
dence interval (with group-branch means removed, and normalized to zero at time 
t = −4 to facilitate visual inspection of the time series). Since officers remain at 
an assignment for a minimum of two years, we use an eight quarter window around 
their arrival. This ensures that we do not double-count observations in the figure. </p>

<p>16 This measurement error in the time of arrival of the new officer will tend to bias toward zero our estimates of 
the in-group effect in specification (1). </p>

<p>Panel A. From out-group to in-group officer 
Panel B. From out-group to out-group officer </p>

<p>Panel C. From in-group to out-group officer 
Panel D. From in-group to in-group officer </p>

<p>Fraction of branch debt </p>

<p>Fraction of branch debt </p>

<p>Fraction of branch debt </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>−0.06 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>Fraction of branch debt </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>−0.06 </p>

<p>−0.08 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−0.02 </p>

<p>−0.04 </p>

<p>−4 −3 −2 −1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 </p>

<p>−4 −3 −2 −1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 
−4 −3 −2 −1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 </p>

<p>−4 −3 −2 −1 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 </p>

<p>Event time (t = 0: quarter of 
new officer arrival) 
Event time (t = 0: quarter of 
new officer arrival) </p>

<p>Event time (t = 0: quarter of 
new officer arrival) 
Event time (t = 0: quarter of 
new officer arrival) </p>

<p>Figure 1. New Credit around Officer Transitions, Partitioned by Group Identity of Officer and 
Borrowers before and after the Transition </p>

<p>Notes: The horizontal axis measures time, in quarters, since the group experienced an officer change (0 represents 
the first quarter of the new officer). The vertical axis measures the average fraction of credit to a group, with group-
branch means removed, and normalized to zero at t = −4 . Group is defined based on a classification of borrowers 
and officers into five minority religions and four government sanctioned castes (conditional on the religion being 
Hindu). Borrowers are partitioned into four subsamples depending on whether they experience a transition from an 
out-group to an in-group officer (panel A), an out-group to an out-group officer (panel B), and so on. The dashed 
lines indicate the 95 percent confidence interval of the mean by quarter. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>There are, however, fewer observations at points further from t = 0 owing to trun-
cation of officer spells at the beginning and end of our sample period. 
To construct the plots we partition the borrower groups into four subsamples 
depending on the type of in-group/out-group status change they experience due to 
officer rotation. Panel A is constructed for the subsample of borrowers for which an 
in-group officer replacing an out-group one leads to increased cultural proximity 
for these borrowers. Panel C contains borrowers who have experienced the oppo-
site transition, from in-group to out-group officer. For these borrowers, the officer 
change thus led to a decrease in cultural proximity. Panel B (D ) is for borrowers who 
have experienced no change in their out-group (in-group) status, and thus no change 
in their cultural proximity to the officer. 
We highlight three patterns in these plots, as they are strongly suggestive of a 
causal relationship of cultural proximity on the flow of credit. First, officer changes 
that involve an increase (decrease) in cultural proximity between the officer and 
set of borrowers are immediately followed by a statistically significant 3 to 4 per-
cent increase (decrease) in the fraction of new credit allocated to those borrowers. 
Second, officer changes that do not affect officer-borrower cultural proximity are 
not followed by changes in the flow of credit (implying that our estimates are not 
confounded by a "new officer" effect). 
17 Third, there is no pre-officer-change trend 
in the fraction of credit allocated to a group in any of the four plots. This observation 
represents strong evidence that the group identity of the new officer is unrelated to 
either the group identity of the outgoing officer or the evolution of credit market 
conditions leading up to the officer change. Taken together, the patterns observed in 
Figure 1 validate the identification assumptions behind the difference-in-difference 
estimator of the in-group effect in specification (1). </p>

<p>A. In-Group Effect on Credit Quantity </p>

<p>In Table 4, we present the effect of having an in-group branch head on new credit, 
estimated using the specification (1) above. We emphasize that these analyses use 
a combination of branch-quarter, district-group-quarter, and group-branch fixed 
effects. 
18 Outcomes are measured at the level of group g in branch b in quarter q , 
starting in column 1 with total new debt obtained by group g as a fraction of total 
new debt in branch b , and in column 2 with the number of new credit recipients in 
group g as a fraction of the total number of new credit recipients in branch b . In both 
cases, we find a positive and significant effect of SameGroup on credit access. The 
estimated coefficients indicate that the fraction of credit obtained by group g bor-
rowers increases by nearly 6.5 percentage points, and the fraction of new borrowers 
from group g relative to total new borrowers increases by 5.65 percentage points 
following the transition to an in-group branch manager. </p>

<p>17 These plots do not mean that a "new officer" effect does not exist, merely that it is second order relative to 
the effect of cultural proximity and statistically indistinguishable from zero in the data. The patterns also indicate 
that an increase in the fraction of new lending to in-group borrowers does not mechanically decrease the fraction 
of lending to all other groups, as would occur, for example, if branches were subject to a binding capital constraint. 
The decline in lending occurs exclusively for those borrowers that lose in-group status with the officer change. 
18 There are 37,709 branch-quarter dummies, 19,155 group-branch dummies, and 43,723 district-group-quarter 
dummies. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>In the remaining columns of Table 4, we explore the group-extensive and 
group-intensive margins to examine how cultural proximity affects the probability 
that a group will receive credit, and conditional on receiving credit, how it affects 
the amount given. We report on the coefficients on SameGroup using our baseline 
specification with four dependent variables: a dummy equal to one if the group 
receives any new credit (column 3), the average (log) new credit (column 4), the 
(log) number of new credit recipients (column 5), and (log) average new loan size 
(column 6). Due to the log transformation the last three variables are defined only 
for group-branch-quarters where there is a positive debt flow. The point estimates 
indicate that all these measures of lending increase when an in-group officer is pres-
ent in a branch, and the effect is significant at the 1 percent level. </p>

<p>19   We present a pair of additional tables in the Appendix to probe the robustness of 
our results to different specifications and definitions of cultural proximity. First, in 
Appendix Table A1 we present analyses similar to those of Table 4, columns 1 and 2, 
with various combinations of fixed effects that are less stringent than those in our sat-
urated specification (1). Neither the magnitudes nor the significance of the estimated 
parameters change markedly. We take the stability of these estimates as strong evi-
dence that the relationship between our variable of interest, SameGroup, and credit 
market outcomes, is unlikely to result from problems such as omitted variable bias. 
Appendix Table A2 repeats the estimation (again using saturated specifications) 
using the group definitions based on the traditional religious caste system (Varna), 
obtained through surname matching. The dependent variable is now scaled by the </p>

<p>19 The estimates on total debt, number of borrowers, and loan size (columns 4, 5, and 6) are still significant after 
accounting for the fact that these are estimated conditional on the group receiving credit using Lee (2009) bounds 
(not reported). </p>

<p>Table 4-Effect of Cultural Proximity on New Credit to a Group </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>Group 
credit/branch 
credit </p>

<p>Number of 
borrowers/ 
number 
of branch 
borrowers 
Dummy = 1 if 
credit &gt; 0 
ln(credit) </p>

<p>ln(number 
of borrowers) </p>

<p>ln(average new 
loan size) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
0.0647 
0.0565 
0.0250 
0.1391 
0.0691 
0.0691 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
(0.005) 
(0.027) 
(0.018) 
(0.018) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
331,053 
331,053 
350,711 
105,610 
105,701 
105,610 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.852 
0.869 
0.745 
0.806 
0.856 
0.687 </p>

<p>Notes: In this table, we report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on the new debt to a group as a fraction of 
branch debt (column 1), on the number of new loan recipients from a group as a fraction of the number of new loan 
recipients in a branch (column 2), on the probability that a group receives credit (column 3), on the (log) total new 
debt received by a group (column 4), on the (log) number of borrowers that received new loans in a group (col-
umn 5), and on the (log) average new loan size (column 6). Group is defined by combining religion and caste-based 
measures of cultural proximity (five minority religions and four government designated castes conditional on Hindu 
religion). The variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the branch manager are of the same 
group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>total lending in the branch to all matched borrowers (and not all branch loans), so 
the estimate magnitudes of this specification are not directly comparable to those 
above. The estimated effect of cultural proximity on lending is again positive and 
significant for the fraction of credit, the number of borrowers, and the probability 
of receiving credit (the effect on loan size and other intensive margin measures 
is not statistically significant). The Varna grouping is constructed independently 
of the bank's classification of officers and borrowers, indicating that the observed 
in-group effects are not driven by systematic misclassification of borrowers by the 
bank. Also, since it is implausible (and illegal) for the bank to use Varnas to allocate 
credit or assign jobs, the Varna-based results provide an independent validation of 
the identification assumption that the group identity of the officer in a branch is 
uncorrelated with directed lending policies targeted to borrowers of the same group. </p>

<p>B. In-Group Effect on Loan Quality and Cost </p>

<p>As highlighted in Section I, prominent models of credit markets under asym-
metric information predict that, if cultural proximity reduces information frictions, 
then the expansion of in-group credit access that we document in the preceding 
section should be accompanied by improved repayment. By contrast, if favoritism is 
the dominant source of within-group preferences, standard models predict that the 
increase in lending will be the result of credit expansion to (lower-quality) marginal 
borrowers, leading to a deterioration in average lending quality. 
We first examine the impact of cultural proximity on future loan performance by 
estimating specification (1) using the fraction of borrowers who are more than 60 
days past due in a year. 
20 As before, the unit of analysis is the branch-group-quarter 
level, and our outcomes of interest are calculated over all the borrowers in branch b , 
group g , that received new loans in quarter q . The outcome of interest is the fraction 
of borrowers that received new loans in quarter q who are past 60 days overdue in 
quarter q + 4 ( FractionInDefaul t bgq+4 ). Since the bank keeps record of late repay-
ments as a borrower outcome (and not a loan outcome), our default measure reflects 
payments overdue on any loan, not just the loan received in quarter q . 
The estimated coefficient on SameGroup for loan performance is presented in 
Table 5, column 1. The point estimate of the effect of cultural proximity on the 
fraction of loans more than 60 days overdue 12 months forward is negative and sig-
nificant at the 5 percent level. The coefficient of −0.006 (−0.6 percentage points) 
implies an 7 percent reduction in the default probability for in-group loans relative 
to the mean of 8.6 percent. 
A taste-based model of higher in-group lending that would also lead to higher 
repayment rates is one where cultural proximity induces loan officers to extend 
additional loans to insolvent in-group borrowers to make payments on past loans. 
This "evergreening" explanation also implies that the impact on loan performance 
should be relatively short-lived, and in particular that it should disappear when 
an in-group officer is replaced by an out-group one. In column 2, we test whether </p>

<p>20 The results are almost identical when we use 30 and 90 days past due. We also employed specifications that 
used the log of one plus the number of days late as the outcome variable. These regressions generated results that are 
qualitatively very similar to those we report in the text, but do not have any clear economic interpretation. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>the positive effect of cultural proximity on performance disappears or is attenu-
ated when the in-group officer is replaced with an out-group one by using a pair of 
interactions to distinguish between the following two cases (i) SameGroup = 1 
12 months after the loan is issued by an in-group officer, versus (ii) there is no 
longer an in-group officer 12 months after an in-group loan is made. Specifically, 
we consider the separate effects of SameGrou p bgq on default four quarters ahead 
( FractionInDefaul t bgq+4 ) when the officer still belongs to the same group four quar-
ters ahead ( SameGrou p bgq × SameGrou p bgq+4 ) and when the officer does not belong 
to the same group four quarters ahead ( SameGrou p bgq × (1 − SameGrou p bgq+4 ) ). 
Intuitively, the latter of these terms captures the extent to which default declines 
even when the SameGroup officer is replaced by an out-group one. We find that both 
terms are negative and significant, implying that the improvement in performance 
observed at quarter q that is caused by having an in-group officer originate a loan 
in quarter q − 4 is present even if the loan officer at time q is no longer an in-group 
one. This result suggests that evergreening is unlikely to account for the higher 
quality of SameGroup loans. It also indicates that the increase in performance is 
unlikely driven by direct supervision, monitoring, or other actions that require the 
loan officer's presence. 
The view that in-group lending reduces information frictions further predicts that 
the lower default rates we observe should reduce the average cost of borrowing. 
Since loan interest rates are fixed in our setting, we focus instead on collateral as 
a proxy for the borrowing cost, and examine whether collateral to loan ratios are 
lower for in-group loans (holding the interest rate constant, higher risk borrowers 
will be required to post more collateral to borrow the same amount). To do so, we 
employ our baseline specification (1), using as a measure of collateral intensity the 
logarithm of the group's average ratio of total collateral to outstanding loan amount </p>

<p>Table 5-Effect of Cultural Proximity on Loan Repayment and Cost </p>

<p>Loan quality 
Loan characteristics </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>Fraction borrowers in 
default in t + 4 </p>

<p>ln(collateral/ 
debt) 
Interest rate 
Maturity 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
−0.0060 
−0.0398 
0.0162 
0.0614 
(0.003) 
(0.012) 
(0.039) 
(0.045) </p>

<p>SameGroup × SameGroup t+4 
−0.0082 
(0.005) </p>

<p>SameGroup × (1 − SameGroup t+4 ) 
−0.0137 
(0.005) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
98,229 
81,482 
205,811 
239,106 
239,106 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.814 
0.515 
0.782 
0.927 
0.650 </p>

<p>Notes: In this table we report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on the probability of default, the (log) aver-
age collateral to debt ratio, the interest rate (in percentage points) and the maturity (in months) of debt using spec-
ification (1). The unit of analysis is a branch-group-quarter, where group is defined by combining religion-and 
caste-based measures of cultural proximity. The variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and 
the branch manager are of the same group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>(note that, in contrast to ratio-based outcomes, our collateral measure is defined only 
for groups with positive credit outstanding). 
21 In Table 5, column 3, we show that 
the estimated in-group effect on collateral to loan ratios is −3.98 percentage points, 
significant at the 1 percent level. This indicates that in-group borrowers post on 
average 4 fewer rupees of collateral per every 100 rupees of credit outstanding, rel-
ative to out-group ones. This is consistent with cultural proximity reducing the cost 
of borrowing, and rules out preference based explanations in which the borrower 
becomes safer (e.g., because they do not want to default on someone from their own 
group) but the officer is unaware of it. 
Finally, in Table 5, columns 4 and 5, we repeat our baseline specification using 
two additional loan characteristics-loan maturity in years and interest rate-as 
the dependent variable. In both cases, the coefficient on SameGroup is statistically 
insignificant. The coefficients also indicate that if there is an effect on these con-
tract dimensions, it is of low economic significance. For term length, the coefficient 
implies that average maturity increases by 0.06 years (21 days), and for interest 
rates the coefficient implies that the annualized interest rate increases by 0.016 per-
centage points, both negligible magnitudes relative to the average loan. This is an 
indication that, as we note in Section II, loan officers exercise very little discre-
tion over interest rates or maturity. It further indicates that officers do not reclassify 
loans-e.g., investment versus consumption-to achieve the same end. </p>

<p>C. Heterogeneity by Caste and Religion </p>

<p>In our main results, we presented the average effect of cultural proximity over 
all castes and religions. It is natural to ask how our findings may differ by group. 
In Table 6 we allow for the impact of shared culture to vary by religion and caste 
by interacting SameGroup with dummies for each of the five major minority reli-
gions and, conditional on the religion being Hindu, the four government sanctioned 
castes. The effects are on average larger, sometimes by an order of magnitude, for 
minority religions than for castes within Hindus. Since Hindu castes represent larger 
groups, one interpretation of these results is that there is a strong negative correla-
tion between group size and the effect of cultural proximity. This across-group het-
erogeneity potentially indicates that the benefits of cultural proximity in access to 
credit may be limited by group size. 
The effect of cultural proximity also exhibits substantial heterogeneity across 
minority religions: the effects range from 0.66 (significant at the 1 percent level) for 
SameGroup × Muslim to 0.03 (not significant) for SameGroup × Parsi , and the 
difference of the effect across groups is always statistically significant. A plausible 
explanation for the very small effect for Parsis is that they are, as summarized by a 
2012 article in the popular press, widely known for "diligence and trustworthiness." 
The same article goes on to observe that Parsis tend not to be "clannish," which </p>

<p>21 Recall that the bank does not record the collateral pledged to secure a specific loan, but the total amount of 
collateral pledged by the borrower. For that reason we cannot measure the collateral associated with new loans only. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>might suggest that any role of favoritism in increasing loan quantities is also muted 
amongst Parsis. </p>

<p>22   Across castes the heterogeneity is much smaller: the effects range from 0.033 for 
SameGroup × General to 0.012 for SameGroup × SC , and the differences across 
groups are not always significant. This is a natural result of government-mandated 
castes serving as less potent sources of identity and differentiation relative to reli-
gion. (Given that the effect of caste is much smaller, combined with the fact that 
Hindus are a significant majority in India, our estimated effect of SameGroup in 
Table 4 may be seen as an overestimate of the average impact of cultural prox-
imity for the overall population. In unreported results, we find that the coefficient 
on SameGroup falls by about half in estimating the effect of cultural proximity on 
lending quantity (significant at the 1 percent level) when we weight observations by 
one plus the number of borrowers.) </p>

<p>22 Arti Sharma, "Straight, Honest Parsimoney," Outlook India, October 1, 2012, http://www.outlookindia.com/ 
magazine/story/straight-honest-parsimoney/282353. </p>

<p>Table 6-Heterogeneity by Religion and Caste </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Group credit/branch credit </p>

<p>Number of borrowers/ 
number of branch 
borrowers 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>SameGroup × Muslim 
0.6370 
0.6354 
(0.038) 
(0.039) </p>

<p>SameGroup × Christian 
0.3901 
0.3905 
(0.027) 
(0.027) </p>

<p>SameGroup × Sikh 
0.4039 
0.4137 
(0.043) 
(0.044) </p>

<p>SameGroup × Parsi 
0.0303 
0.0077 
(0.028) 
(0.015) </p>

<p>SameGroup × Buddhist 
0.3542 
0.3397 
(0.114) 
(0.105) </p>

<p>SameGroup × General caste 
0.0310 
0.0185 
(0.007) 
(0.007) </p>

<p>SameGroup × SC 
0.0115 
0.0057 
(0.004) 
(0.004) </p>

<p>SameGroup × ST 
0.0112 
0.0041 
(0.010) 
(0.009) </p>

<p>SameGroup × OBC 
0.0323 
0.0267 
(0.012) 
(0.011) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
331,053 
331,053 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.854 
0.872 </p>

<p>Notes: In this table we report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on the new debt and num-
ber of recipients (as a fraction of branch debt and number of recipients) by religion, and, con-
ditional on the religion being Hindu, by caste. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>Overall, these results highlight the nuanced relationship between the effect of cul-
tural proximity and group size. While there is a rough concordance between group 
size and strength of identity on the impact of in-group lending, the relationship is 
more complex: for example, the impact of SameGroup on borrowing is greatest for 
Muslims, the largest religious minority. Among Hindu borrowers, the biggest effect 
is also among the largest group (General). In the future, we may shed further light 
on these patterns by delving further into general attitudes toward particular groups, 
and into the extent of assimilation of individual religions or castes. </p>

<p>V. Further Results: Heterogeneity and Loan Dispersion </p>

<p>The preceding section documented robust patterns along the two main dimen-
sions of credit market outcomes: quantity and quality of lending. Among prominent 
models of credit markets under information asymmetries, our findings are more 
easily reconciled with those where cultural proximity reduces information frictions 
rather than those that emphasize favoritism. In our final section, we present findings 
on how credit provision differs across borrower, officer, and branch characteristics, 
as well as results on loan size dispersion, to explore a broader set of potential expla-
nations for our results. </p>

<p>A. Heterogeneity by Branch Density and Size </p>

<p>We have assumed, up to this point, that in-group favoritism is driven by lender 
rather than borrower preferences. If borrowers prefer same-group loan officers, they 
may choose to reward them with higher-quality lending opportunities. While our 
data cannot fully rule out this possibility-as we note in our introduction, they are 
best-suited to detecting favoritism which comes at a cost to the lender-we may 
probe the plausibility of this argument by examining how the SameGroup effect 
varies by branch attributes. 
In particular, we examine whether the impact of SameGroup is affected by the 
presence of other borrowing options as proxied by branch density in a district, given 
by number of branches from all financial institutions per 1,000 inhabitants. The 
number of branches per district is obtained from the website of the Reserve Bank 
of India and the number of inhabitants per district from the India Census, both from 
2001. The average number of branches per 1,000 inhabitants is 0.81 across the 357 
districts with a branch from the bank in our data. There is substantial heterogeneity 
in this measure across districts, with 0.18, 0.54, and 1.88 as the first, fiftieth, and 
ninety-ninth percentiles, respectively. The districts with the highest branch densities 
typically correspond to urban areas and the lowest densities to rural ones. 
In Table 7, panel A, we estimate specification (1) using only the 89 branches 
where the bank is the only one in its district (since there is only one branch per dis-
trict in this sample we have to amend the specification to include state-group-quarter 
dummies instead of district-group-quarter dummies). These are rural areas where 
there are essentially no other formal financing opportunities available. We observe 
that, if anything, the SameGroup effect is stronger in isolated areas, with the coef-
ficient in column 1 taking a value of 0.082 (significant at the 1 percent level) com-
pared to 0.065 for the full sample. We further observe that these isolated branches </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>tend to be small, with a median of just a single officer (i.e., the branch head) across 
all branch-quarter observations compared to a median of two for the full sample, 
so the absence of other branches more plausibly indicates an uncompetitive market 
rather than an entry deterrence strategy by the bank. 
In Table 7, panel B, we present results for the full sample that allow the effect of 
SameGroup to vary across branch density quartiles; the effect of cultural proximity 
is strongest in branches with few nearby banking options. (We also find a strong </p>

<p>Table 7-Heterogeneity by Branch Density in District and Branch Size </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>Group credit/branch 
credit </p>

<p>Number of borrowers/ 
number of branch borrowers 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>Panel A. Sole branch/bank in district subsample (88 branches) 
SameGroup 
0.0818 
0.1224 
(0.024) 
(0.030) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-state-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
13,358 
13,358 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.895 
0.920 </p>

<p>Panel B. Effect heterogeneity by branch density in the district 
SameGroup 
0.0758 
0.0687 
(0.013) 
(0.013) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
−0.0476 
−0.0416 
× branches/1,000 district inhabitants = quartile 2 
(0.020) 
(0.019) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
−0.0176 
−0.0213 
× branches/1,000 district inhabitants = quartile 3 
(0.017) 
(0.016) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
0.0003 
−0.0013 
× branches/1,000 district inhabitants = quartile 4 
(0.016) 
(0.016) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
329,325 
329,325 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.853 
0.870 </p>

<p>Panel C. Effect heterogeneity by number of officers in the branch 
SameGroup 
0.0462 
0.0363 
(0.010) 
(0.010) </p>

<p>SameGroup × number of officers in branch = 2 
0.0208 
0.0213 
(0.014) 
(0.015) </p>

<p>SameGroup × number of officers in branch &gt; 2 
0.0306 
0.0340 
(0.013) 
(0.013) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
322,654 
322,654 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.853 
0.870 </p>

<p>Notes: We report the heterogeneity of the estimated effect of cultural proximity on lending outcomes using specifi-
cation (1) across districts of different branch density and branch size. The unit of analysis is a branch-group-quarter, 
where group is defined by combining religion-and caste-based measures of cultural proximity. The variable 
SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the branch manager are of the same group. Panel A is esti-
mated using only the subsample of branches located in districts where there is no other branch (of the bank or any 
other) in the same district. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>positive correlation between branch density and branch size, again suggesting 
that the lack of nearby branches indicates lack of competition rather than entry 
deterrence.) 
These findings are difficult to reconcile with demand-side explanations for the 
in-group effect where, for example, there are readily observable low-risk borrow-
ers that generate relatively high profits for any bank attracting them as custom-
ers. If these sought-after borrowers choose to take their business to bank branches 
based on cultural affinity then the arrival of a same-group officer would trigger an 
increase in lending and also an improvement in loan performance with same-group. 
However, this type of "business-stealing" effect should be attenuated in regions 
where the bank holds significant monopoly power, counter to our finding of a strong 
SameGroup effect in districts with low bank density. This does not fully rule out the 
possibility that our results are driven by borrower preferences-for example, cul-
tural ties may be so strong that they lure low-risk borrowers across district boundar-
ies-but given that districts with a single bank branch are geographically isolated, 
our full set of findings is more easily reconciled with an interpretation based on 
same-group officers serving to reduce information frictions. (Additionally, the fact 
that the effect of cultural proximity remains strong even in small markets with few 
competitors suggests that the expansion of credit for in-group borrowers is unlikely 
to crowd out credit by other banking institutions.) </p>

<p>23   B. Heterogeneity by New versus Pre-Existing Borrowers </p>

<p>We now turn to evaluating how the effect of cultural proximity varies across bor-
rowers who have an existing credit record with the bank versus those who do not. 
This comparison is useful in understanding how cultural proximity interacts with 
hard sources of information used in the credit assessment process. Since there is no 
centralized credit registry that collects borrowers' credit histories during our sample 
period, the only source of hard information available to lenders is a customer's own 
borrowing and repayment record at the bank. We can therefore use heterogeneity in 
the effect of cultural proximity across first-time and preexisting borrowers to eval-
uate whether the information advantage from cultural proximity is a substitute or a 
complement for the hard information contained in credit histories. 
We partition the borrower sample into two groups: (i) borrowers that have estab-
lished a credit relationship with the bank prior to the arrival of the current officer, 
and (ii) borrowers that receive credit from the bank for the first time with the cur-
rent officer. We scale the dependent variable by the total new loans of the branch to 
each group of borrowers and estimate the group-branch level regressions on these </p>

<p>23 In Appendix Table A3 we show that the fraction of lower-level loan officers in a branch from a particular 
group increases lending to borrowers from their group, but the effect is about a tenth of that which we estimate for 
the impact of the group ties of branch heads. There are several factors that can account for the modest in-group 
effect of lower-level officers. First, it is consistent with branch heads playing a dominant role in loan decisions. 
This is particularly the case for higher loan amounts, which require approval from a higher-ranked officer. As we 
observe in Appendix Table A4, the in-group effect is increasing in loan size percentile (consistent with the increased 
loan dispersion associated with in-group lending that we document in subsection VD), which already comprise a 
disproportionately high fraction of total loan amounts. A further potential explanation for the muted in-group effect 
of lower-level officers is that, according to bank officials, these data are updated less frequently than branch head 
information, resulting in classical measurement error. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>subsamples, which provide the effect of cultural proximity on the flow of credit to 
preexisting versus new borrowers. 
Table 8, panel A, shows the estimates of a branch-group level specification that 
includes in every branch-group-quarter bgq those borrowers who had positive credit 
at any time before the officer in charge of branch b in quarter q arrived. The esti-
mates indicate that the arrival of an in-group branch head increases the amount of 
new loans (column 1) and the number of new loan recipients (column 2) amongst 
those borrowers with a pre-existing relationship with the bank. Table 8, panel B, 
shows a very similar impact of SameGroup for the subsample of borrowers obtain-
ing credit from the bank for the first time. 
The similarity of the point estimates suggests that the informational advantage 
conferred by cultural proximity is not a substitute for the hard information held by 
the lending institution in the form of a history of past borrowing and repayment 
behavior. In this were the case, we would expect to see a smaller effect of cultural 
proximity on loan outcomes for existing borrowers. By contrast, the evidence sug-
gests that cultural proximity and loan history have additive effects on loan outcomes. 
This in turn suggests that the documented effect of cultural proximity is unlikely to 
be mitigated by the introduction of a credit bureau or other changes in the informa-
tion environment that rely on past borrower behavior to evaluate creditworthiness. </p>

<p>C. Heterogeneity by Officer Tenure at Branch </p>

<p>We conclude our analysis of heterogeneity by examining the dynamics of the 
effect of cultural proximity over an officer's tenure in the branch. These dynamics </p>

<p>Table 8-Existing and First-Time Borrowers </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Group debt/branch debt </p>

<p>Number of borrowers/number 
of branch borrowers 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>Panel A. Subsample of borrowers who obtained credit from bank prior to officer's arrival 
SameGroup 
0.0512 
0.0446 
(0.007) 
(0.006) </p>

<p>Branch-group and quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Observations 
266,273 
266,539 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.737 
0.770 </p>

<p>Panel B. Subsample of borrowers obtaining credit for the first time 
SameGroup 
0.0510 
0.0473 
(0.006) 
(0.006) </p>

<p>Branch-group and quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Observations 
360,910 
360,910 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.809 
0.809 </p>

<p>Notes: In this table we report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on lending patterns 
(specification (1)) separately for existing borrowers (panel A) and first-time borrowers (panel 
B). Existing borrowers are those that have obtained credit at any time in our sample prior to 
the arrival of the current officer in charge of the branch. First time borrowers receive their first 
credit from the bank under the current officer. The unit of analysis is a branch-group-quarter, 
where group is defined by combining religion-and caste-based measures of cultural proximity. 
The variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the branch manager are 
of the same group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>may inform our understanding of whether the effect of cultural proximity requires 
time to develop (this would be the case, for example, if the officer collects informa-
tion through a network of acquaintances that takes time to build), or if its importance 
diminishes over time as a result of the loan officer's experience and interaction with 
out-group borrowers. 
Figure 2 plots the coefficients on the interaction between SameGroup and a set 
of indicator variables for the officer's quarter of arrival at the branch ( t = 0 ), his 
second quarter at the branch ( t = 1 ), and so on until t = 7 . The graphs for the 
effect of cultural proximity on both the fraction of new credit (panel A) and the frac-
tion of new credit amongst first-time borrowers (panel B) in a group show an imme-
diate impact of the new in-group officer: In the first quarter of the officer's recorded 
arrival ( t = 0 ), both measures increase by about 10 percentage points. This imme-
diate increase in the flow of credit is followed by slow decay, and although the point 
estimates are positive throughout, the estimates are no longer statistically different 
from zero after t = 1 . We also observe that, while the point estimates decline with 
officer tenure, the confidence intervals increase such that we also cannot reject an 
increase in the SameGroup effect over the officer's tenure. 
These dynamics suggest that cultural proximity confers an immediate advantage 
to the officer, and that the officer uses it to extend new credit to a "backlog" of 
in-group borrowers (both borrowers that already received credit from the bank and 
new ones). The integral below this plot represents the change in the stock of lending 
to in-group borrowers, and suggests that cultural proximity generates a permanent 
increase in access to credit while the in-group officer is in place. The effect of cul-
tural proximity on the flow of credit never becomes negative, as would occur if the 
in-group advantage disappeared as the loan officer became more acquainted with 
out-group borrowers. Overall, the observed patterns suggest that loan officers are </p>

<p>Figure 2. Effect Heterogeneity by Officer Tenure in the Branch </p>

<p>Notes: The horizontal axis measures time, in quarters, since the officer arrived in the branch (0 represents the first 
quarter with the new officer). The vertical axis plots the point estimates and 95 percent confidence interval of the 
estimated in-group effect by tenure of the officer in the branch (using specification (1) augmented with interactions 
between SameGroup and a set of indicator variables for the time of the officer in the branch). </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 </p>

<p>Quarters since officer arrived in branch </p>

<p>Panel A. Effect on total new credit to group </p>

<p>−0.20 </p>

<p>−0.15 </p>

<p>−0.10 </p>

<p>−0.05 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 </p>

<p>Group number of borrowers/total 
branch number of borrowers </p>

<p>Quarters since officer arrived in branch </p>

<p>Panel B. Effect on number of borrowers </p>

<p>Group debt/total branch debt </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>−0.10 </p>

<p>−0.20 </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>"endowed" with an information advantage in evaluating in-group borrowers, and 
that the advantage of lending to in-group borrowers is not attenuated with the offi-
cer's interaction with other groups. </p>

<p>D. In-Group Effect on Loan Size Dispersion </p>

<p>Cornell and Welch (1996) provide the novel prediction that improved ex ante 
screening should increase the dispersion in lending: officers receive higher precision 
signals of creditworthiness from in-group borrowers, increasing the variance of the 
distribution of priors across in-group borrowers. In our setting, a higher variance of 
priors will imply a higher variance of loan sizes to in-group borrowers. 
To assess the effect of cultural proximity on loan dispersion, we estimate the 
baseline specification (1) using two measures of within-group loan dispersion: the 
standard deviation and the interquartile range of the new loans issued in branch b , 
group g , quarter q . The estimated in-group effects, presented in Table 9, are positive 
and significant for both measures. The point estimates indicate that cultural prox-
imity increases the standard deviation (interquartile range) of loans outstanding by 
11.8 percent (11.1 percent). In Appendix Table A4 we show that an in-group officer 
has a positive and significant effect on all percentiles of the loan size distribution 
in a group (10 percent, 25 percent, 50 percent, 75 percent, and 90 percent), though 
the coefficient on SameGroup increases monotonically with percentile. The esti-
mated effect on the ninetieth percentile of the distribution of new loans (0.033) in 
Appendix Table A4 is smaller than the average effect in Table 4 (0.08). Thus, cul-
tural proximity shifts up the entire distribution of loan sizes, but the effect on loan 
amount is large for a small fraction of in-group borrowers. 
These results indicate that cultural proximity has heterogeneous effects on access 
to credit across borrowers. Combined with the observed effect on loan performance, 
the dispersion results suggest that cultural proximity improves the sorting and </p>

<p>Table 9-Effect of Cultural Proximity on Loan Dispersion </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>ln(loan size standard 
deviation) </p>

<p>ln(loan size interquartile 
range) 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
0.1182 
0.1110 
(0.027) 
(0.027) 
Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
72,329 
71,842 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.726 
0.703 </p>

<p>Notes: In this table we report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on (log) measures of 
the size dispersion of new loans to a group (interquartile range and standard deviation of the 
distribution of loan amounts to a group). The unit of analysis is a branch-group-quarter, where 
group is defined by combining religion-and caste-based measures of cultural proximity. The 
variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the branch manager are of the 
same group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>allocation of credit across in-group borrowers. These findings are consistent with 
better in-group ex ante screening as in Cornell and Welch (1996) or with heteroge-
neous monitoring effectiveness across in-group borrowers. </p>

<p>VI. Discussion and Conclusion </p>

<p>In this paper, we have measured the extent of differential treatment in the loan 
market for those with a shared cultural background. Our empirical context is well-
suited to assessing differential in-group treatment: since we have data on both lender 
and borrower group affiliations, we may distinguish between own-group preferences 
versus differential treatment of minorities. Furthermore, exogenous officer rotation 
allows us to distinguish in-group preferences from changes in officer branch assign-
ments. Finally, since we focus on credit markets, by analyzing loan outcomes we 
may explore whether the data are more easily reconciled with standard models of 
reduced information asymmetries versus standard models of favoritism. Overall, 
our findings are best explained by cultural proximity serving to reduce information 
frictions in the credit markets we study. 
Our study has a number of implications for theories of discrimination as well as 
economic policy. First, we note that the preferential treatment we uncover can itself 
perpetuate income inequality among minorities. In our context, 74.4 percent of the 
officers belong to the General Class category. This implies that the probability of a 
backward caste borrower (SC, ST, or OBC) facing unfavorable loan conditions is 
nearly 75 percent, purely for reasons of cultural affiliation. 
Moreover, our findings suggest one possible mechanism through which statistical 
discrimination against minorities can arise. Minorities will not often be "matched" 
with a loan officer of their own group and will hence have inferior loan outcomes on 
average. As a result lenders may form what are ultimately self-confirmatory beliefs 
about the creditworthiness of minorities if they rely on past average group perfor-
mance to generate lending rules (Kim and Loury 2009). 
Finally, our findings have several policy implications. In the Indian context, tar-
geted reservation policies that impose a larger proportion of backward caste officers 
in regions with a high concentration of backward caste borrowers may improve effi-
ciency and reduce inequality of loan allocation. The reason, however, is different 
from preference-based rationales for political reservations (Chattopadhyay and Duflo  2004). Our analysis suggests that reservations may improve contracting outcomes 
because they reduce information asymmetries between loan officers and borrowers. 
While it is impossible to fully evaluate the overall welfare implications of our 
findings, we may assess the conditions under which borrower welfare and the bank's 
profitability improve, which are useful metrics in evaluating the impact of in-group 
lending. As concerns borrower welfare, increased access to credit and a lower cost 
of borrowing unambiguously increase welfare. As we show in Appendix Table A4, 
an in-group officer has a positive and significant effect on all percentiles of the loan 
size distribution in a group. Thus, under the assumption of equal utility weighting 
across good and bad borrowers, cultural proximity leads also to an increase in bor-
rower welfare. 
From the lender's perspective, a welfare analysis requires first taking a stance 
on whether the bank's objective is to maximize loan profitability. If we take the </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>normative view that the goal of a government bank in India should be to improve 
borrower welfare, then the discussion in the previous paragraph already implies 
that, under plausible assumptions, cultural proximity furthers this objective. If 
one augments the bank's objectives to include profit maximization, the welfare 
analysis is complicated by the difficulty of measuring loan profitability in our 
context. Specifically, it requires that we make an assumption on whether the mar-
ginal cost of capital is lower than the cost of funding the marginal loan. Existing 
work evaluating lending practices of government banks in India suggests that 
banks lend too little relative to their cost of capital (Banerjee, Cole, and Duflo  2004; Banerjee and Duflo 2014). Under this assumption, the combined effect of 
an increase in lending and a reduction in default probability would necessarily 
increase bank profits, assuming that the loss-conditional-on-default does not sub-
stantially increase. We showed in Table 2 that the median loan in the sample is 
over-collateralized by a factor of 2-the total collateral posted by the borrower is 
more than double the total amount of credit outstanding. This means that the rel-
atively small decline in the collateral requirement observed with in-group officers 
is unlikely to affect the recovery rate on defaulted loans. We also obtained data on 
recovery rates for a small number (16,924) of loans in default; we find no differ-
ence in recovery rates for SameGroup loans (whether defined at time of write-off 
or initiation). It is thus likely that the expansion in lending caused by cultural 
proximity improves loan profitability. 
Our findings also provide valuable input for policy discussions on the group-
based assignment of loan officers or other bureaucrats. It is important to observe 
that there are many considerations involved in such decisions. As such, our findings 
should not be taken as a blanket endorsement of a policy of maximizing cultural 
proximity through officer rotation as it may, for example, reduce officers' incentives 
to learn about the cultural traits of out-group borrowers. That is, while the "local" 
effect of in-group matching could be positive, it may be outweighed by longer-term 
consequences. Further, a policy of maximizing cultural proximity could also impact 
the level of corruption within the bank, or even affect the average quality of loan 
officers selected to be branch managers. A more detailed analysis of such trade-offs 
may serve as fertile ground for future analysis. 
There are a number of additional areas for research that are needed to draw 
out the full policy consequences of our findings. First, it would be useful to 
assess whether policies directly aimed at reducing cultural differences across 
groups-for example, by teaching a common language-lead to improvements 
in cross-group contracting. Second, while our findings highlight improvements 
in transaction-level efficiency from cultural proximity, to make an overall assess-
ment of the efficiency consequences for the bank as a whole, it would be necessary 
to understand how the increase in overall lending that comes from matching bor-
rowers and lenders affects allocation within the bank more generally. As noted in 
Banerjee, Cole, and Duflo (2004), bank officer incentives may lead to under-lend-
ing in Indian state banks and as such a credit expansion of the sort we document 
in our paper may represent efficiency gains more broadly. Providing rigorous evi-
dence on this question of bank-level efficiency would require more detailed infor-
mation on the bank's fuller set of funding and lending opportunities; we leave this 
for future work. </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>Appendix </p>

<p>A1. Matching Surnames to Varnas </p>

<p>Since the association between individual names and their borrowing and employ-
ment records is proprietary and cannot be disclosed outside the bank, the process of 
assigning individuals to the Brahmin, Kshatriya, and Vaishya groups followed four 
steps: </p>

<p>(i) The bank provided us with a list of all surnames-both borrowers and offi-
cers-present in bank records. </p>

<p>(ii) We searched <rs type="software">Google</rs> and the Anthropological Survey of India (Singh et al. 
1998, Singh et al. 2003, Singh et al. 2004) to establish a community associa-
tion for each name. </p>

<p><rs type="software">Google</rs><rs type="software">Google</rs><rs type="software">Google</rs></p>

<p>24 "Deshastha Brahmin," Wikipedia, http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_Deshastha_Brahmin_surnames. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>A2. Auxiliary Figures and Tables </p>

<p>Table A1-Robustness of the Saturated Regression </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>Group credit/branch 
credit </p>

<p>Number of borrowers/ 
number of branch borrowers 
(1) 
(2) </p>

<p>Panel A. Baseline branch-group fixed effects 
SameGroup 
0.0814 
0.0765 
(0.006) 
(0.006) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
364,056 
364,056 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.823 
0.841 </p>

<p>Panel B. Branch-quarter dummies 
SameGroup 
0.0719 
0.0569 
(0.005) 
(0.005) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
364,056 
364,056 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.152 
0.169 </p>

<p>Panel C. Branch-quarter and group-quarter dummies 
SameGroup 
0.0721 
0.0575 
(0.005) 
(0.005) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
364,056 
364,056 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.159 
0.191 </p>

<p>Panel D. State-group-quarter dummies 
SameGroup 
0.0884 
0.0741 
(0.006) 
(0.006) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
State-group-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
364,056 
364,056 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.077 
0.085 </p>

<p>Panel E. District-group-quarter dummies 
SameGroup 
0.0889 
0.0748 
(0.006) 
(0.006) 
Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
District-group-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
364,056 
364,056 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.242 
0.251 </p>

<p>Notes: We report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on loan outcomes using specifica-
tion (1) with alternative sets of dummies as controls. Group is defined by combining religion 
and caste based measures of cultural proximity (five minority religions and four government 
designated castes conditional on Hindu religion). The variable SameGroup is an indicator 
denoting that borrowers and the branch manager are of the same group. Standard errors are 
clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>

<p>Table A2-Robustness: Alternate Group Definition Based on Surnames (Varnas) </p>

<p>Dependent variable </p>

<p>Group 
credit/ 
branch 
credit </p>

<p>Number of 
borrowers/ 
number 
of branch 
borrowers 
Dummy = 1 
if credit &gt; 0 ln(credit) </p>

<p>ln(number of 
borrowers) </p>

<p>ln(average 
loan size) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) </p>

<p>SameVarna 
0.0149 
0.0164 
0.0344 
−0.0667 
−0.0364 
−0.0303 
(0.009) 
(0.007) 
(0.009) 
(0.064) 
(0.029) 
(0.051) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
82,578 
82,578 
92,214 
21,196 
21,196 
21,196 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.731 
0.797 
0.735 
0.796 
0.880 
0.742 </p>

<p>Notes: We report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on loan outcomes using specification (1). The unit of 
analysis is a branch-group-quarter, where group is defined by Varna, the caste system that was prevalent in ancient 
India. Individuals are assigned to Varnas using a surname-matching algorithm (the algorithm cannot correctly iden-
tify individuals from the Shudra Varna). The variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the 
branch manager are of the same group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p>Table A3-Effect of Cultural Proximity on the Flow of Credit: Other Officers </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
Group credit/branch credit </p>

<p>Number of borrowers/number 
of branch borrowers 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Fraction of same group officers 
0.0087 
0.0076 
0.0090 
0.0080 
(Excluding head officer) 
(0.002) 
(0.001) 
(0.002) 
(0.001) 
SameGroup 
0.0957 
0.0873 
(Head officer) 
(0.008) 
(0.008) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
213,896 
213,896 
213,896 
213,896 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.859 
0.860 
0.876 
0.877 </p>

<p>Notes: We report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on the new debt to a group as a fraction of branch debt 
(columns 1 and 2), and on the number of new loan recipients from a group as a fraction of the number of new loan 
recipients in a branch (columns 3 and 4). The estimates are obtained using specification (1), but using as the right-
hand-side variable the fraction of loan officers in the branch, excluding the branch head, that belongs to the same 
group as the borrower (group defined as before). This variable is only defined for branches with more than one loan 
officer. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>

<p>Table A4-Effect of Cultural Proximity on the Distribution of New Loan Sizes </p>

<p>Percentile: loan amount/branch credit </p>

<p>Dependent variable 
10th 
25th 
50th 
75th 
90th 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) </p>

<p>SameGroup 
0.0175 
0.0180 
0.0212 
0.0266 
0.0331 
(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.002) 
(0.003) 
(0.003) </p>

<p>Branch-group fixed effects 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Branch-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Group-district-quarter dummies 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes 
Yes </p>

<p>Observations 
229,865 
229,865 
229,865 
229,865 
229,865 
R </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.580 
0.586 
0.625 
0.646 
0.664 </p>

<p>Notes: We report the estimated effect of cultural proximity on the ratio of the p-th percentile of the flow of new debt 
to a group in a branch quarter divided by total flow of branch debt. Group is defined by combining religion-and 
caste-based measures of cultural proximity (five minority religions and four government designated castes condi-
tional on Hindu religion). The variable SameGroup is an indicator denoting that borrowers and the branch manager 
are of the same group. Standard errors are clustered at the branch level. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p>Figure A1. Geographical Distribution of Branches, Weighted by Total Lending </p>

<p>Notes: The centers of the circles indicate the location of the branches. The area represents the total amount of lend-
ing in the branch in 2002. </p>

<p>Source: Authors' calculations </p>

<p> 
Fisman et al.: Cultural Proximity and loan outComes 
Vol. 107 no. 2 </p>





<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
fEbRuARy 2017 </p>



<p>This article has been cited by: </p>

<p>1. Danielle Li. 2017. Expertise versus Bias in Evaluation: Evidence from the NIH. American Economic 
Journal: Applied Economics 9:2, 60-92. [Abstract] [View PDF article] [PDF with links] </p>

</text></tei>