<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1002%2Fsoej.12249" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>In this article, we provide a framework for determining when it is optimal to move when labor 
market opportunities are declining. We model the decision to migrate as akin to owning a 
financial option in which the exercise price is the fixed cost of moving. We show that a higher 
fixed cost associated with moving and a higher standard deviation of the quality of the labor 
market reduce the incentive to migrate. We then empirically examine whether the standard 
deviation of indicators of labor market quality reduce the likelihood of migration. Our findings 
strongly support this hypothesis, and imply that for the relatively mobile population of high-
skilled workers the counterfactual outmigration rates that would obtain if future labor-market 
quality were known with certainty are more than twice observed rates. </p>

<p>JEL Classification: R23, J61 </p>

<p>The share of workers employed in manufacturing has been declining as the mid-20th century 
(ON. Fisher 2004). Amidst this transition, one often reads stories about small towns with econo-
mies that have been devastated by the loss of a local factory and the struggles of the workers who 
have been left behind to maintain a lower standard of living. For example, a recent article in the 
New York Times describes the town of Port Clinton, Ohio: </p>

<p>The manufacturing foundation of Port Clintons modest prosperity in the 1950s and 1960s 
began to tremble in the 1970s. The big Standard Products factory at the east end of town pro-
vided nearly 1000 steady, good-paying blue-collar jobs in the 1950s, but the payroll was more 
than halved in the 1970s. After two more decades of layoffs and "give backs," the plant gates 
on Maple Street finally closed in 1993, leaving a barbed-wire-encircled ruin now graced with 
Environmental Protection Agency warnings of toxicity. But that was merely the most visible 
symbol of the towns economic implosion. </p>

<p>Manufacturing employment in Ottawa County plummeted from 55% of all jobs in 1965 to 25% 
in 1995 and kept falling. By 2012, the average worker in Ottawa County had not had a real 
raise for four decades and, in fact, is now paid roughly 16% less in inflation-adjusted dollars 
than his or her grandfather in the early 1970s (Putnam 2013). </p>

<p>Another example can be found in a recent article in the Washington Post about Decatur, 
Tennessee: </p>

<p>* Department of Economics, University of Mississippi, 366 Holman Hall, University, MS 38677, USA; E-mail: 
jrgardne@olemiss.edu. 
 † Department of Economics, University of Mississippi, 229 North Hall, University, MS 38677, USA; E-mail: 
jrhendr1@olemiss.edu; corresponding author. 
Received November 2016; accepted September 2017. </p>

<p>786 
Ó 2017 by the Southern Economic Association </p>

<p>Southern Economic Journal 2018, 84(3), 786-814 
DOI: 10.1002/soej.12249 </p>

<p>Today, although, all traces of the Decaturville Sportswear plant, which once used some 1500 
locals, have vanished, and nothing comparable has replaced it. The unemployment rate is 
higher in Decatur County now than it was when Clinton took office. One out of every four resi-
dents use food stamps. . . </p>

<p>. . .Decatur County has just under 12,000 residents. About 800 of them live in Decaturville, the 
county seat. The countys unemployment rate has doubled, to 9%, from where it was at the end 
of the Clinton administration. Factory employment has been cut in half since 2000. Fewer peo-
ple had jobs in the county last year than in 2001 (Tankersley 2015). </p>

<p>In light of such stories, it is natural to ask when it becomes optimal to migrate away from 
labor markets experiencing declining quality in search of better opportunities elsewhere. Dating 
back to Sjaastad (1962), the traditional view is that migration is akin to an investment to be made 
if the value of the benefits of increased labor market opportunities available elsewhere outweigh 
the fixed costs associated with migrating. These costs, which reflect both direct moving expenses 
and the psychological costs of leaving friends and family behind, are often considerable. 
We agree with this perspective. Given the important nature of fixed costs, however, we believe 
that the investment literature can inform analysis of the migration decision even more deeply. The 
literature on real options associated with investment implies that when a firm faces a substantial 
fixed cost, the firms investment decision is to determine the optimal point in time to undertake 
the investment. 
1 In this article, we argue that the decision to move to a new location in search of </p>

<p>better job opportunities is akin to this investment decision by firms. For workers, the choice is to 
decide how long they should remain in a location in which the quality of economic opportunities 
is declining. 
In this type of economic environment, the decision to move is akin to owning a financial 
option-the worker has the option, but not the obligation, to move at any point in time. The prob-
lem for the worker is to determine the optimal point in time to exercise this option. The worker 
must choose this point in time to move with the understanding that one can only leave their cur-
rent location once and that exercising the option requires bearing the fixed costs associated with 
moving. 
We develop an investment theory of migration in which the greater the degree of uncertainty 
about the quality of future labor-market opportunities, the longer the individual will wait before 
moving. The intuition for this result is that, even when the economic opportunities available to the 
worker are declining over time, in a world with uncertainty there is some probability that these 
opportunities will be greater next period. Nonetheless, if economic opportunities are decreasing 
on average over time, there eventually comes a point at which it is no longer optimal for the worker 
to wait to observe next periods labor market shock. At that point, the worker would be better off 
moving than holding on to the option. 
We then examine this hypothesis empirically, estimating a series of models that relate outmi-
gration to measures of the level and volatility of local labor-market quality during the Great 
Recession. Regardless of how we measure quality, we find that volatility causes substantial 
declines in the rate of migration out of local labor markets. We take several steps, including con-
trolling for prerecession outmigration and instrumenting for quality using a widely accepted tech-
nique due to Bartik (1991), to address the possibility that endogeneity or simultaneity explain the 
relationship that we identify between volatility and outmigration; our findings are robust to these 
noncausal interpretations. Our estimates imply that average outmigration rates would be </p>

<p>1 For a textbook treatment of these types of problems, see Dixit and Pindyck (1994) and Stokey (2009). </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
substantially higher if people knew with certainty the quality that they would face if they remained 
in their current labor markets. For higher-skilled workers, whom previous research (Wozniak 
2010; Cadena and Kovak 2016) has shown relatively mobile, the counterfactual rates that would 
obtain if outmigration were not inhibited by volatility would be more than double observed rates, 
on average. 
This article extends the human-investment theory of migration originated by Sjaastad 
(1962), who argued that net in-migration is likely to occur in locations in which the present dis-
counted value of expected wages is high relative to other locations. Subsequent research used 
search-theoretic models to address imperfect information across locations (e.g., Rogerson [1982]; 
Gordon and Vickerman [1982]; Maier [1985]; Berninghaus and Seifort-Vogt [1991]). For example, 
individuals considering moving to a new location might lack information about the current oppor-
tunities available in other locations. The search-theoretic models imply that those considering 
moving should use searching as a way of discovering such opportunities. This implies that there is 
a speculative motive to migration. 
Later work, however, emphasizes the role of future uncertainty. For example, Burda 
(1993) appeals to the early literature on the option theory of investment to make predictions 
regarding migration. He notes that there is uncertainty about expected future outcomes in for-
eign locations. The greater the uncertainty about those expected future outcomes, the longer 
(on average) an individual will wait before deciding to migrate. OConnell (1997) extends this 
work to develop a formal model of migration and return migration. The benefit of his model is 
that it allows for the analysis of both the speculative motive for migration and the incentive to 
wait discussed in Burda (1993). </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Our model, although similar to this more recent strand of research, differs in that we assume 
that individuals take opportunities in other locations as given. This allows us to focus on the con-
ditions in the current, observable labor market and the uncertainty about the quality therein. We 
do this because the motivation for our article is to understand why migration is so infrequent even 
when local labor-market quality is in relative decline. This is in contrast to Burda (1993) and 
OConnell (1997), who focus on uncertainty about wages in foreign locations. 
3 In addition, we </p>

<p>consider the value associated with the overall quality of the labor market, rather than just expected 
wage differentials. Consistent with Burda (1993) and OConnell (1997), the model generates the 
prediction that greater uncertainty about the future implies that the individual should wait. How-
ever, as our focus is on uncertainty about the quality of local labor market conditions, the main 
contribution of our model is that it generates the specific, testable hypothesis that areas with 
greater variation in labor market quality should experience less out-migration. In this respect, our 
article takes up the challenge put forth by OConnell (1997) to empirically examine the role of 
uncertainty in migration decisions. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 A somewhat related article is Anam, Chiang, and Hua (2008), who examine the decision-making of a family rather </p>

<p>than an individual. Their model provides a motive for some family members to move to diversify the risk of the family. 
3 OConnell (1997) features return migration, but the uncertainty is always about the wage in what is initially the foreign </p>

<p>location. 
4 Note that OConnell (1997) solves for labor market equilibrium and finds that the option value of migration is zero. If </p>

<p>our model was only a model of wage differentials, we could assume that the decision to migrate has an incremental 
effect on the wage differential. This would imply that in the limit as we approach a perfectly competitive labor market, 
the option value of migration would go to zero. However, our emphasis on labor market quality precludes this sort of 
assumption because we would need to know how an individuals migration decision affects not only the wage differen-
tial, but other characteristics of the labor market as well such as relative unemployment rates. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>Our empirical findings suggest that our theoretical model has considerable power to explain 
why outmigration from areas experiencing relative declines is not more common. In addition, they 
shed new light on the longstanding, yet still somewhat puzzling, empirical regularity that internal 
migration is relatively uncommon, despite apparent arbitrage opportunities presented by spatial 
differences in labor-market conditions. Card (2001), for example, finds no evidence of outmigra-
tion among natives in response to inflows of immigrants. Similarly, Cadena and Kovak (2016) 
find that internal migration is substantially less sensitive to employment shocks for U.S. natives 
than for foreign immigrants, potentially suggesting that natives choose to forgo the gains to be 
had from moving. Furthermore, in their empirical model of the relationship between expected 
income and migration, Kennan and Walker (2011) find that high moving costs must be invoked to 
rationalize the dearth of observed migrations. Our model, and the empirical evidence that sup-
ports it, suggest that uncertainty about future labor-market quality may interact with moving 
costs, amplifying the effects of even modest disincentives to moving. 
Our results may also help explain long-run and cyclical trends in internal migration. For 
example, Saks and Wozniak (2011) document a secular decline in internal migration within the 
United States during the end of the 20th Century and examine several competing explanations for 
this trend; increases in local labor market volatility may help explain their findings. Investigating 
the sources of pro-cyclicality in internal migration, Molloy et al. (2011) show that national (that is, 
across-state) variation in employment measures does not explain aggregate rates of internal migra-
tion within the United States. Our results, in contrast, suggest that within-labor-market increases 
in such variation are related to outmigration, and therefore may help explain the relationship 
between internal migration and the business cycle. </p>

<p>2. The Model </p>

<p>Time is continuous and continues forever. There is a representative worker who is deciding 
whether to move or whether to stay. Let q(t), where qð0Þ5q 0 , denote the value associated with the 
quality of the labor market and assume that this measure follows a geometric Brownian motion: </p>

<p>dq 
q 
5ldt1rdz 
(1) </p>

<p>where l &lt; 0 is a parameter that measures the average change in labor market quality, r is the con-
ditional standard deviation per unit of time, and dz is an increment of a Wiener process. 
5 The </p>

<p>assumption that l &lt; 0 is designed to capture the idea that the economic opportunities available to 
the worker are decreasing, on average, over time. </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5 The assumption of geometric Brownian motion as the process for labor market quality is motivated as follows. First, </p>

<p>what we want to have is an assumption that labor market quality is declining on average over time. Second, we want 
there to be some degree of uncertainty about labor market quality over time. Third, we want labor market conditions 
to be persistent. Geometric Brownian motion allows for all three of these features because it is equivalent to a random 
walk with drift in discrete time (but is bounded from below at zero). Finally, this assumption has the additional benefit 
of allowing us to get a closed form solution for the threshold to motivate the numerical examples that follow. 
6 The traditional way to think about the migration decision is through expected wages. However, this ignores other char-</p>

<p>acteristics of the labor market. Fields (1976), for example, suggests valuing employment opportunities using the prod-
uct of the wage and 1 minus the unemployment rate. Our formulation can be thought of as similar to this idea. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
If the worker decides to leave, they receive a perpetual dividend w. We assume that the dividend is 
known and constant over time. The assumption of exogenous outside opportunities can be justi-
fied as follows. First, individuals might not have reliable information about outside opportunities. 
Second, as we are interested in testing our results empirically, we focus on the role of changes in 
labor market quality that we can observe. To be able to identify the characteristics of outside 
opportunities, we would need to know all of the possible places that the individual looked or was 
willing to look when they made the migration decision. Third, as the optimal threshold for migra-
tion will illustrate below, this is equivalent to assuming that individuals care about the relative 
quality of the labor market. 
Moving requires paying a fixed cost, M &gt; 0. This could be thought of narrowly as the pecuni-
ary cost of moving, but it might also include other costs such as the psychological cost of separa-
tion from family and friends (as alluded to above) and any net loss of amenities. 
The Bellman equation for a worker in a given location is given as </p>

<p>rV ðqÞ5q1 
1 
dt 
EdV </p>

<p>where E denotes the expectation and r denotes the real interest rate. Using Itos Lemma and Equa-
tion 1, this can be rewritten as </p>

<p>1 
2 
r 
2 q 
2 V 
00 ðqÞ1lqV 
0 ðqÞ2rV ðqÞ1q50 
(2) </p>

<p>This is a second-order differential equation in V(q). The differential equation has a solution </p>

<p>V ðqÞ5A 1 q 
a 1 1A 2 q 
a 2 1V p ðqÞ 
(3) </p>

<p>where A 1 q 
a 1 and A 2 q 
a 2 are homogeneous solutions, V p ðqÞ is a particular solution, A 1 and A 2 are </p>

<p>constants, and a 1 and a 2 are the roots of the equation </p>

<p>1 
2 
r 
2 a 
2 1 l2 
1 
2 
r </p>

<p>2 </p>



<p>
a2r50: 
(4) </p>

<p>Note that Equation 3 has the following economic interpretation. The particular solution is 
the value that the worker would receive if the option to move is never exercised. The homo-
geneous solutions represent the value of the option to move. Given this interpretation, we 
can simplify the solution by imposing boundary conditions consistent with economic 
reasoning. 
First, note that as the quality of the local labor market becomes sufficiently large, the value 
of the option to move becomes worthless. Thus, it should be true that </p>

<p>lim </p>

<p>q!1 </p>

<p>½V ðqÞ2V p ðqÞ50: </p>

<p>This condition implies that as the quality of the labor market increases, the value of the option to 
move goes to zero. From Equation 4, it is clear that there is one negative root and one positive 
root. Denote a 2 as the positive root. It follows that A 2 must be equal to zero to satisfy the condi-
tion above. 
Denote the quality of the labor market at which it is optimal to leave as q </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>. Note that it must 
be true that </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>V ðq 
Ã Þ5 
w 
r 
2M </p>

<p>where w/r is the present value of the dividend that the individual receives when they move and M is 
the cost of moving. This condition is the value-matching decision. It implies that, at the optimal 
moving time, the individual is indifferent between staying and moving. 
It follows from these two conditions that </p>

<p>A 1 5ðq 
Ã Þ </p>

<p>2a 1 </p>

<p>
w 
r 
2M2V p ðq 
Ã Þ </p>

<p>
: </p>

<p>Substituting this into Equation 3 yields </p>

<p>V ðqÞ5 
q 
q Ã </p>

<p>a 1 
w 
r 
2M2V p ðq 
Ã Þ </p>

<p>1V p ðqÞ: 
(5) </p>

<p>As q is stochastic and w, r, and M are taken as given, the objective of the individual is to choose q </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>to maximize this expression. This choice requires optimally balancing a particular trade-off. The 
lower the value of q 
Ã that the individual chooses, the greater net benefit the individual receives </p>

<p>when they move. However, the lower the value of q 
Ã the individual chooses, the longer (on average) </p>

<p>the individual will have to wait before they move. This reduces the present value of the net benefit 
to moving by reducing the stochastic discount factor ðq=q 
Ã Þ 
a 1 . Thus, the individuals decision is to </p>

<p>choose q 
Ã to maximize Equation 5. The first-order condition is given as </p>

<p>2a 1 </p>

<p>
w 
r 
2M2V p ðq 
Ã Þ </p>

<p>5q 
Ã V </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>p ðq 
Ã Þ: 
(6) </p>

<p>As noted above, the particular solution V p ðqÞ can be thought of as the present discounted value of 
never moving. In this case, </p>

<p>V p ðqÞ5 
q 
r2l 
: </p>

<p>It follows that q 
Ã is given as </p>

<p>q 
Ã 5 
a 1 
a 1 21 </p>



<p>ðr2lÞ </p>

<p>
w 
r 
2M </p>



<p>: 
(7) </p>

<p>There are two important implications that one can draw from this condition. First, the partial 
derivative of the optimal stopping threshold with respect to moving costs is negative. Thus, the 
greater the cost of moving, the lower the quality of the labor market that an individual is willing to 
endure before moving. 
The second implication concerns the role of economic uncertainty. From Equation 7, the 
optimal stopping decision depends on a 1 . Note that from Equation 4 that a 1 depends on r. Com-
parative statics are difficult to obtain analytically. In lieu of comparative statics, we plot the rela-
tionship between q 
Ã and r in Figure 1 using a numerical example. As shown, the threshold </p>

<p>exhibits monotonic decay as r rises. This implies that the greater degree of uncertainty about 
future labor market quality, the longer individuals are willing to stay in their present location. The 
intuition is as follows. Even though the quality of the labor market is declining on average, over 
any given time interval there is a chance that the quality of the labor market improves. The magni-
tude of such an improvement is proportional to r. Thus, a larger r implies a larger possible </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
improvement in the quality of the labor market over a given time interval. It is the possibility of a 
large improvement that gives the individual an incentive to wait. 
Consider the following example in which the quality of the labor market is measured by the 
unemployment rate. An individual worker observes the unemployment rate each period and deter-
mines whether or not to move. As the unemployment rate rises, the quality of labor market oppor-
tunities is declining. Eventually the unemployment rate will rise to a level at which the individual 
worker will realize that he or she is better off moving. 
Now consider this decision at the margin. As the worker observes the unemployment rate 
each period, the decision to move will be conditional on the workers expectations of the unem-
ployment rate in the next period. A positive shock to the unemployment rate makes the individual 
worker more likely to move. A negative shock to the unemployment rate makes the worker more 
likely to stay. It is only when even the expectation of a negative shock to the unemployment rate is 
insufficient to justify waiting to observe the shock that the worker will ultimately move. It follows 
that, all else equal, the larger the volatility of the unemployment rate, the larger will be the size of 
the shock and the longer an individual worker will be willing to stay. 
Thus, the predictions of the model with regard to how individuals should respond to both 
the level and volatility of labor market quality produce two testable hypotheses. The first is that 
declines in labor market quality make an individual worker more likely to move from the present 
location. The second is that increases in the volatility of labor market quality give workers the 
incentive to stay in their present location longer. This first hypothesis is straightforward. As the </p>

<p>Figure 1. The Effect of Changes in Volatility. 
Notes: Volatility affects the threshold for moving through the effect on a 1 . This figure plots the relationship 
between the threshold for labor market quality, q 
Ã , and r using a numerical example. For the numerical exam-
ple, we set l520:02, w 5 100, M 5 100, and r 5 0.05. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>quality of labor market opportunities declines, workers eventually reach a point at which it is not 
worth staying and they seek better opportunities elsewhere. The second hypothesis, although 
prima facie counterintuitive, is a straightforward implication of the option approach. As it is 
always possible that there could be a positive shock to labor market quality next period, it might 
be beneficial to wait until next periods shock is revealed rather than pay the cost associated with 
moving. The larger the volatility of these shocks, the longer an individual worker should be willing 
to stay in their present location. </p>

<p>3. Empirical Evidence </p>

<p>Identification Strategy, Data, and Variable Construction </p>

<p>The theoretical argument developed above suggests that migration out of local labor markets 
should respond to both the level and volatility of the quality of those markets. In particular, 
increasing volatility may slow the counterfactual rate of outmigration due to declining levels of 
labor market quality. To provide an empirical test of this theory, we estimate a series of models 
that relate outmigration behavior to measures of the level and volatility of local labor market 
quality. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Our measures of the quality and extent of migration out of local labor markets are based on 
Integrated Public Use Microdata Samples (IPUMS) of the American Community Survey (ACS) 
(Ruggles et al. 2015). 
8 Our theoretical model makes predictions about the impact of the volatility </p>

<p>of labor-market quality when the level of that quality is decreasing, on average. To focus on the 
motivating question with which we introduce our article-the relationship between outmigration 
and labor-market quality during times of economic upheaval-and to increase the relevance of 
our findings for public policy, our primary sample, drawn at the height of the Great Recession, is 
the 2010 ACS. In parts of our analysis, we also use a 2006 ACS sample to control for pre-recession 
trends. Each annual IPUMS ACS sample represents 1% of the U.S. population, from which we 
retain observations on all working-age men (ages 16-64) who were not enrolled in school at the 
time of enumeration. Partially to focus on longer-range moves and partially to increase the sizes of 
our market-specific samples, we define local labor markets as three-digit metropolitan areas. 
Within a given metropolitan area, members of different skill groups may face different local 
labor-market quality. Furthermore, previous studies have shown that higher-skilled workers are 
more mobile (Wozniak, 2010; Cadena and Kovak, 2016). Accordingly, we stratify our samples 
into those with a high-school education or less and those with at least some college. This approach 
enables us to allow for skill differences in the outmigration response to local labor market quality 
while still constructing reasonably precise measures of those variables. 
We proxy for the level and volatility of quality using the area 3 skill-group 3 year sample 
means and standard deviations of unemployment, weeks worked, and annual income from wages. 
In constructing these statistics, we use the ACS definition of unemployment (which excludes 
labor-force nonparticipants) and average weeks worked and income over all observations not </p>

<p>7 Although our theory relates outmigration to the volatility of changes in quality, when quality evolves according to a </p>

<p>Brownian motion, areas with more volatile changes in quality will also have more volatile levels of quality, justifying 
our approach of comparing outmigration to the contemporaneous volatility of labor-market quality. 
8 We obtain similar results when we construct quality measures using samples from the Current Population Survey, </p>

<p>although we focus on the ACS, for which the metropolitan-area samples are considerably larger, here. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
otherwise excluded from the sample. 
9 Our motivation for focusing primarily on employment out-</p>

<p>comes as quality measures is prior evidence that these outcomes are the main channel through 
which labor markets adjust to recessions (see, e.g., Bewley 1999). Respondents to each ACS report 
the metropolitan areas where they lived both at the time of enumeration and during the prior year. 
When these metropolitan areas differ, we code respondents as outmigrants from the initial area 
and measure annual outmigration as the area-and skill-group-specific one-year outmigration rate. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Table 1 summarizes the key variables that we use in our empirical analysis. As the table 
shows, the Great Recession induced substantial variation in the level and volatility of labor market 
quality, increasing the national average standard deviation of unemployment and income, and 
decreasing that average for weeks worked, for both skill groups. At the same time, outmigration 
rates decreased for both skill groups during this period. The table also shows that, across periods, 
there are large between-skill-group differences in the volatility of labor-market quality. Figure 2, 
which plots estimated densities of skill-group-specific local labor-market volatility for 2010, dem-
onstrates that there is significant dispersion in the volatility of each of our quality measures across 
local labor markets. </p>

<p>Labor-Market Volatility and Outmigration </p>

<p>In Table 2, we present coefficient estimates from models that relate outmigration to the level 
and volatility of each of the labor-market quality measures described above. We estimate the equa-
tions by least squares, weighting each observation by the size of its population (and reporting </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary Statistics </p>

<p>HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
N 
Mean 
SD 
N </p>

<p>2006 
Unemployment rate 
0.0782 
0.0297 
283 
0.0306 
0.0143 
283 
Mean weeks worked 
19.72 
2.389 
283 
24.22 
2.653 
283 
Mean income 
20,426 
2,976 
283 
43,060 
8,576 
283 
SD unemployment 
0.263 
0.0456 
283 
0.167 
0.0402 
283 
SD weeks worked 
15.17 
0.982 
283 
15.06 
1.098 
283 
SD income 
22,185 
5,032 
283 
46,440 
11,727 
283 
Outmigration rate 
0.0377 
0.0246 
283 
0.0473 
0.0291 
283 
2010 
Unemployment rate 
0.148 
0.0461 
283 
0.0619 
0.0250 
283 
Mean weeks worked 
16.70 
2.378 
283 
19.29 
2.872 
283 
Mean income 
17,472 
2,879 
283 
40,444 
8,375 
283 
SD unemployment 
0.349 
0.0463 
283 
0.235 
0.0463 
283 
SD weeks worked 
13.67 
1.073 
283 
13.84 
1.232 
283 
SD income 
20,843 
4,240 
283 
44,288 
10,352 
283 
Outmigration rate 
0.0322 
0.0206 
283 
0.0403 
0.0247 
283 </p>

<p>National averages of metropolitan-area statistics from IPUMS ACS samples. HS denotes a high-school education or 
less, Col. denotes at least some college. </p>

<p>9 We impute weeks worked as the midpoint of the reported range of weeks worked (only an intervalled version of this </p>

<p>variable is available for both years that we study). We use the IPUMS-supplied CPI weights to deflate income to 1999 
dollars. 
10 We apply IPUMS-supplied sampling weights when computing all aggregate variables. The average skill-group 3 met-</p>

<p>ropolitan area 3 year cell in our sample consists of about 1000 observations. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>robust standard errors). 
11 The first two columns of the table summarize skill-group-specific estimates </p>

<p>of our simplest specification, which includes only the mean and standard deviation of quality. 
12 Con-</p>

<p>sistent with our theory, the coefficient on the standard deviation is negative and statistically signifi-
cant for both skill groups when we proxy for quality using unemployment, and for the high-skilled 
when we measure volatility using the standard deviation of weeks worked or income. 
13 Although the </p>

<p>0 
5 10 15 
Density </p>

<p>.1 
.2 
.3 
.4 
.5 
SD unemployment </p>

<p>HS 
Col. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.5 </p>

<p>1 
Density </p>

<p>8 
10 
12 
14 
16 
18 
SD weeks worked </p>

<p>HS 
Col. </p>

<p>0 .00005 .0001 .00015 </p>

<p>Density </p>

<p>0 
50000 
100000 
150000 
SD income </p>

<p>HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Dispersion in the Volatility of Labor-Market Quality. 
Notes: Nonparametric densities of estimated metro-level standard deviations of labor market quality measures 
based on the IPUMS Sample of the 2010 ACS and weighted by population size. HS denotes a high-school 
education or less, col. Denotes at least some college. </p>

<p>11 In almost every case, unweighted estimates are similar but less precise. 
12 In these models, we include data from both 2006 and 2010 in the estimation sample, although we obtain similar results </p>

<p>when we limit the sample to 2010. 
13 For high-skilled workers, the coefficient on the level of unemployment is positive, also consistent with our theoretical </p>

<p>model. Although the coefficients on mean weeks worked and income are insignificant for the high skilled when we 
control for lagged outmigration, these measures may be related to outmigration through channels not included in our 
model (e.g., income may be also proxy for housing or amenity prices, which might be positively correlated with outmi-
gration). Similarly, since unemployment volatility may also impact outmigration through risk aversion, our unemploy-
ment models may understate the impact of volatility on outmigration through option-value channels. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
estimated outmigration response to local labor-market volatility is less robust among the low-skilled, 
the disparity between the high-and low-skill groups that we identify is highly consistent both with the 
above-cited prior evidence that higher-skilled workers are more mobile and the simple theoretical 
intuition that mobility should be less responsive among groups with low overall mobility. 
To put the implied magnitudes of the estimated outmigration response to volatility into 
perspective, recall from Table 1 that in 2010 the across-metropolitan-area standard deviation of the 
volatility of unemployment was about .05 for both skill groups. Hence, our estimates imply that a 
one-standard-deviation increase in volatility (i.e., an increase of .05 in the standard deviation of 
unemployment) decreases outmigration among members either group by about 2% (%.05 3.436 3 
100). The effects of volatility in weeks worked and income are similar, although smaller in magnitude. 
These partial effects are somewhat counterfactual, however, because the level and volatility 
of labor-market quality tend to be correlated. When we proxy for quality using unemployment, in 
fact, they are deterministically related, which implies that the level and volatility effects are jointly 
identified only through functional form, albeit the particular nonlinear form implied by our the-
ory (Figure Figure B1 in Appendix B shows that, for the remaining quality measures, the means 
and standard deviations are related, but not deterministically). 
14 A consequence is that the </p>

<p>Table 2. Outmigration and Labor Market Volatility </p>

<p>HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Mean unemployment 
0.261** 
0.728*** 
0.136 
0.781*** 
(0.120) 
(0.209) 
(0.126) 
(0.295) 
SD unemployment 
20.276*** 
20.436*** 
20.126 
20.439*** 
(0.103) 
(0.104) 
(0.129) 
(0.167) 
Lag outmig. 
0.416*** 
0.495*** 
(0.135) 
(0.127) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Weeks worked 
Mean weeks 
0.000713 
0.00160*** 
20.000886* 
0.000233 
(0.000462) 
(0.000379) 
(0.000502) 
(0.000391) 
SD weeks 
0.00257** 
20.00221* 
0.00140 
20.00268** 
(0.00105) 
(0.00117) 
(0.00111) 
(0.00119) 
Lag outmig. 
0.415*** 
0.500*** 
(0.135) 
(0.128) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Income 
Mean income 
5.92e-07 
1.71e-07 
2.26e-07 
3.04e-07 
(4.14e-07) 
(2.40e-07) 
(4.74e-07) 
(1.98e-07) 
SD income 
24.18e-07 
23.57e-07* 
25.86e-07 
23.95e-07*** 
(3.98e-07) 
(2.13e-07) 
(3.64e-07) 
(1.51e-07) 
Lag outmig. 
0.417*** 
0.488*** 
(0.136) 
(0.128) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is metro-level outmigration rate. Equations estimated by least squares, weighted by population size. 
HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. Robust standard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; 0.01. 
**p &lt; 0.05. 
*p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p>14 Also note that the relative magnitudes of the coefficients suggest that they do not primarily reflect nonlinearities in </p>

<p>the direct effect of the unemployment rate, a point to which we return below. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>estimated partial effects of volatility may not translate to manifestly lower rates of migration out of 
relatively volatile local labor markets. Rather, our estimates should be viewed as decomposing the equi-
librium relationship between outmigration and labor-market quality into coincident level and volatility 
effects. 
One threat to the causal interpretation of these estimates is the possibility that metro-level 
factors not included in the regressions affect both outmigration and labor-market volatility. Eco-
nomic decline, for example, may cause greater outmigration and unemployment volatility, attenu-
ating our estimates. Conversely, a relative boom may slow outmigration, increasing the size of the 
labor force, exacerbating volatility and, consequently, overstating the causal relationship between 
volatility and outmigration. Note however that in both of these examples the confounding vari-
able is the level of labor-market quality, for which we proxy using mean quality measures them-
selves. Thus, only factors that are correlated with volatility and outmigration but not our mean 
quality measures threaten the causal interpretation of the estimates. 
To the extent that such factors are correlated over time within local labor markets, we can 
proxy for them by including prerecession outmigration rates in our models. Note that a lagged 
dependent-variable structure is likely more appropriate to control for serially correlated unob-
served heterogeneity in outmigration rates than a fixed-effects model, which implies monotone 
increasing or decreasing population (other things equal). The remaining columns of Table 2 pre-
sent estimates of specifications that include lagged skill-specific local outmigration rates. For the 
high-skill group, the estimates do not suggest that our previous findings are a consequence of 
unobserved area-level confounders. For every quality measure, the coefficient on the standard 
deviation increases in absolute value when we include lagged outmigration in the model. 
15 For the </p>

<p>low-skilled, the evidence is somewhat mixed. The coefficients on the standard deviations of unem-
ployment and income remain negative, although insignificant, while the coefficient on the stan-
dard deviation of weeks worked is no longer significantly positive. One explanation for this 
pattern is that conditioning on lagged migration leaves little variation in current migration for 
members of this less mobile group, although the possibility remains that there is greater endogene-
ity between outmigration and labor-market volatility for less skilled workers. </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>Another potential threat to the causal interpretation of our estimates is that simultaneity 
may create a mechanical relationship between migration and labor-market volatility. Moreover, 
the direction of the resulting bias, which depends on whether the level and volatility faced by out-
migrants tends to be relatively high or low compared to those who remain, is not clear a priori. To 
test for whether such simultaneity can explain the apparent relationship between outmigration 
and volatility, we estimate models that replace current with prerecession measures of labor-market 
quality. The intuition for this test (which we formalize in Appendix A) is that if the observed rela-
tionship between migration and quality is entirely an artifact of simultaneity, the coefficient on 
lagged migration (which is determined before current volatility), will be zero. </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Table 3 presents the results of this test. For unemployment, both lagged volatility coefficients 
are significantly negative for each group. For nearly all of the remaining quality measures, the </p>

<p>15 When we estimate models relating changes in the outmigration rate between 2006 and 2010 to changes in volatility </p>

<p>over this period, the resulting confidence intervals are too wide to permit any meaningful inference (presumably 
because differencing exacerbates the error with which our migration and quality proxies are measured). 
16 It is also possible that including the lags over-attributes prerecession migration rates to local unobservables, attenuat-</p>

<p>ing the estimated effects. 
17 As we note in Appendix A, it is possible that both current and lagged volatility inform migration decisions, in which </p>

<p>case our estimates identify a weighted average of the effects of both. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
coefficients on volatility remain negative (with the exception of weeks worked among the low-
skilled), although they are smaller than the corresponding coefficients on contemporary volatility. 
Because correlation between current and lagged migration can transmit simultaneity to the coeffi-
cient on the lag, this test is uninformative about the extent of bias due to simultaneity or, conse-
quently, the magnitudes of the underlying causal effects. For most of our measures, however, it 
suggests that the previously observed relationship between volatility and outmigration cannot be 
explained away by simultaneity. </p>

<p>Instrumental Variables Estimates </p>

<p>The tests implemented above suggest that neither reverse nor simultaneous causality explain our 
findings. As further evidence of the causal interpretation of our estimates, we estimate a series of mod-
els that instrument for labor-market quality with predictions based on national industry-specific 
trends. In particular, we predict the level l it of labor-market quality in area i and period t aŝ </p>

<p>l it 5 
X </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>s i;j;t21 l jt ; </p>

<p>where s i;j;t21 is the industry j share of employment in area i in the prior period and l jt is the national 
average level of quality in industry j. Similarly, we appeal to the law of total variance to predict the 
standard deviation of quality in area i and period t as </p>

<p>Table 3. Lag Tests for Simultaneity </p>

<p>HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Lag mean unemp. 
0.990*** 
1.513*** 
0.671*** 
0.931** 
(0.336) 
(0.505) 
(0.245) 
(0.386) 
Lag SD unemp. 
20.704*** 
20.662*** 
20.477*** 
20.395*** 
(0.208) 
(0.187) 
(0.163) 
(0.150) 
Lag outmig. 
0.393*** 
0.483*** 
(0.130) 
(0.128) 
Observations 
283 
283 
283 
283 
Weeks worked 
Lag mean wks. 
0.000835 
0.00151*** 
0.000102 
0.000868* 
(0.000608) 
(0.000520) 
(0.000492) 
(0.000485) 
Lag SD wks. 
0.000744 
20.00213 
0.000485 
27.54e-05 
(0.00152) 
(0.00161) 
(0.00132) 
(0.00113) 
Lag outmig. 
0.416*** 
0.493*** 
(0.137) 
(0.128) 
Observations 
283 
283 
283 
283 
Income 
Lag mean inc. 
4.36e-07 
1.86e-08 
8.59e-07** 
1.13e-07 
(6.26e-07) 
(3.04e-07) 
(4.22e-07) 
(2.15e-07) 
Lag SD inc. 
25.05e-07 
23.03e-07 
25.74e-07* 
22.17e-07 
(4.57e-07) 
(2.33e-07) 
(3.07e-07) 
(1.61e-07) 
Lag outmig. 
0.423*** 
0.489*** 
(0.134) 
(0.130) 
Observations 
283 
283 
283 
283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is metro-level outmigration rate. Equations estimated by least squares, weighted by population size. 
HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. Robust standard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; 0.01. 
**p &lt; 0.05. 
*p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>r it 5 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>s i;j;t21 r </p>

<p>2 
jt </p>

<p>! 1=2 </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>where r </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>jt is the national variance of quality in industry j. The intuition behind this instrument, which 
is originally due to Bartik (1991), is that these predictions are derived from nationwide trends, and 
therefore cannot be correlated with factors that are idiosyncratic to any local labor market and period 
of time (including those factors that might affect the rate of outmigration). 
18 A secular decrease in the </p>

<p>demand for goods manufactured in the United States (say due to increased competition from abroad) 
might increase unemployment in a traditionally manufacturing-intense labor market, for example, 
although outmigration from that market is unlikely to have any effect on the national rate of 
manufacturing unemployment. Consequently, the instrument is neither simultaneously determined 
with local outmigration rates nor related to unobserved location 3 time-specific determinants of 
outmigration. 
We present our IV estimates in Table 4. For the high-skilled, the results suggest a significantly neg-
ative relationship between outmigration and each of our volatility measures (even among the </p>

<p>Table 4. Instrumental Variables Estimates </p>

<p>HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Mean unemployment 
0.771 
0.920 
2.617 
2.178** 
(1.117) 
(0.878) 
(2.916) 
(1.071) 
SD unemployment 
20.717 
20.551 
22.714 
21.280** 
(0.914) 
(0.432) 
(2.912) 
(0.617) 
Lag outmig. 
0.379*** 
0.477*** 
(0.132) 
(0.124) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Weeks worked 
Mean weeks 
0.00396 
0.00472*** 
20.00806 
0.0241 
(0.00747) 
(0.00174) 
(0.00539) 
(0.0336) 
SD weeks 
20.00273 
20.0149** 
0.0111 
20.00327 
(0.0143) 
(0.00737) 
(0.0138) 
(0.0127) 
Lag outmig. 
0.397*** 
0.617** 
(0.135) 
(0.241) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Income 
Mean income 
2.48e-06*** 
7.90e-07** 
4.46e-07 
4.76e-07 
(8.82e-07) 
(3.37e-07) 
(1.35e-06) 
(3.02e-07) 
SD income 
22.22e-06** 
28.56e-07*** 
22.63e-06*** 
26.58e-07*** 
(1.00e-06) 
(2.77e-07) 
(9.26e-07) 
(2.30e-07) 
Lag outmig. 
0.409*** 
0.477*** 
(0.139) 
(0.129) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is metro-level outmigration rate. Equations estimated by IV using Bartik predictions of indepen-
dent variables as instruments and weighted by population size. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. 
denotes at least some college. Robust standard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; 0.01. 
**p &lt; 0.05. 
*p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p>18 Other uses of the Bartik instrument include Blanchard and Katz (1992), Bound and Holzer (2000), Autor and Dug-</p>

<p>gan (2003), Wozniak (2010), Molloy et al. (2011), Charles et al. (2013), and Cadena and Kovak (2016). </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
statistically insignificant estimates, the coefficients are negative and their confidence intervals con-
tain the corresponding OLS point estimates). As in our previous findings, the evidence is weaker 
for the low-skilled, although even for this group most of the point estimates for the volatility coef-
ficients remain negative. These estimates provide strong evidence that neither simultaneity nor 
endogeneity drive our previous findings, especially for the high-skill group. In particular, when we 
control for lagged outmigration, the variation with which we identify the effect of volatility on 
migration is uncorrelated with factors that are idiosyncratic to labor markets at a given point in 
time (as a consequence of the instrument) as well as with factors that are common to a given labor 
market over time (as a consequence of the lag); the variation that remains is highly exogenous. 
The magnitudes of the IV point estimates and confidence intervals are larger than the corre-
sponding OLS estimates, illustrating the difficulty of instrumenting simultaneously for two collin-
ear variables. However, the confidence intervals for the IV estimates almost all contain the 
corresponding OLS point estimates. Furthermore, the first-stage regressions presented in Table 
B1 of Appendix B show that in most cases the instruments strongly predict both the means and 
standard deviations of our quality measures, particularly for the high-skilled; this is true even 
when we included measures of lagged outmigration, which have considerable power to explain 
contemporaneous outmigration. For the low-skilled, some of the first-stage F-statistics are rela-
tively small; this is potentially because local labor-market quality is more idiosyncratic, and hence 
the IV estimates less precise, for this group. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>Robustness Tests and Heterogeneity </p>

<p>For the high-skill group, outmigration responds negatively to every measure of labor-market 
quality in every specification that we estimate and for each estimation method that we use. Our 
estimates evince a strong relationship between labor-market volatility and outmigration, and one 
that cannot be explained by simultaneous or reverse causality. The results are weaker and more 
specification-sensitive for the low-skill group, although this is consistent with descriptive evidence 
and findings from previous studies that less-skilled workers are not as mobile as their more edu-
cated counterparts. 
In addition, we perform a series of robustness exercises to assess the sensitivity of our esti-
mates to different sample selections and noncausal interpretations. Although in the results pre-
sented above, we have weighted each area 3 skill group by its population size, we have also 
included all groups with nonmissing data in the estimation sample. To determine whether our 
results are sensitive to the presence of outliers derived from relatively small samples, we re-
estimate our richest lagged-dependent-variable specifications for each quality measure, restricting 
the estimation sample to include only area 3 skill groups with at least 50,000 members. 
20 As the </p>

<p>first set of columns in Table 5 shows, when we measure quality using unemployment or income, 
excluding these smaller cells actually increases the estimated relationships for the high skilled. For 
the low skilled, and for all of the weeks worked estimates, the volatility coefficients are all statisti-
cally insignificant, presumably because reducing the sample size by about two thirds increases the 
confidence intervals commensurately. It appears, therefore, that the inclusion of smaller local skill </p>

<p>19 Also note that the F-statistics are relatively small for both groups when we measure quality using weeks worked. This </p>

<p>is likely an unavoidable consequence of using an intervalled weeks worked measure, and may also explain why our IV 
results are relatively weak for this measure. 
20 We measure population size as the group-specific sum of sampling weights. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>Table 5. Robustness Exercises </p>

<p>Large MSAs </p>

<p>Excluding largest MSAs </p>

<p>Natives only </p>

<p>Random IV </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment </p>

<p>Mean unemployment </p>

<p>0.0928 </p>

<p>1.072** </p>

<p>0.116 </p>

<p>0.812*** </p>

<p>20.0271 </p>

<p>0.817*** </p>

<p>0.159 </p>

<p>21.111 </p>

<p>(0.228) </p>

<p>(0.527) </p>

<p>(0.132) </p>

<p>(0.300) </p>

<p>(0.130) </p>

<p>(0.300) </p>

<p>(1.281) </p>

<p>(2.959) </p>

<p>SD unemployment </p>

<p>20.0608 </p>

<p>20.594** </p>

<p>20.0976 </p>

<p>20.457*** </p>

<p>0.0277 </p>

<p>20.434*** </p>

<p>20.00822 </p>

<p>0.657 </p>

<p>(0.235) </p>

<p>(0.299) </p>

<p>(0.136) </p>

<p>(0.170) </p>

<p>(0.131) </p>

<p>(0.166) </p>

<p>(1.375) </p>

<p>(1.740) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.345** </p>

<p>0.408** </p>

<p>0.399*** </p>

<p>0.487*** </p>

<p>0.466*** </p>

<p>0.504*** </p>

<p>0.416*** </p>

<p>0.515*** </p>

<p>(0.147) </p>

<p>(0.157) </p>

<p>(0.132) </p>

<p>(0.127) </p>

<p>(0.153) </p>

<p>(0.126) </p>

<p>(0.142) </p>

<p>(0.126) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Weeks worked 
Mean weeks </p>

<p>20.00108 </p>

<p>0.000316 </p>

<p>20.000967* </p>

<p>0.000170 </p>

<p>20.000309 </p>

<p>0.000226 </p>

<p>20.00269 </p>

<p>0.0210 </p>

<p>(0.000804) </p>

<p>(0.000683) </p>

<p>(0.000524) </p>

<p>(0.000396) </p>

<p>(0.000541) </p>

<p>(0.000389) </p>

<p>(0.0192) </p>

<p>(0.0422) </p>

<p>SD weeks </p>

<p>0.00188 </p>

<p>0.000235 </p>

<p>0.00115 </p>

<p>20.00211* </p>

<p>0.00265** </p>

<p>20.00143 </p>

<p>0.0360 </p>

<p>20.000250 </p>

<p>(0.00194) </p>

<p>(0.00240) </p>

<p>(0.00102) </p>

<p>(0.00116) </p>

<p>(0.00124) </p>

<p>(0.00133) </p>

<p>(0.0716) </p>

<p>(0.0417) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.346** </p>

<p>0.419** </p>

<p>0.398*** </p>

<p>0.494*** </p>

<p>0.462*** </p>

<p>0.509*** </p>

<p>0.378*** </p>

<p>0.605** </p>

<p>(0.147) </p>

<p>(0.162) </p>

<p>(0.131) </p>

<p>(0.129) </p>

<p>(0.150) </p>

<p>(0.129) </p>

<p>(0.141) </p>

<p>(0.238) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Income 
Mean income </p>

<p>2.47e-07 </p>

<p>4.65e-07* </p>

<p>27.19e-08 </p>

<p>2.76e-07 </p>

<p>23.62e-07 </p>

<p>3.48e-07 </p>

<p>29.86e-06 </p>

<p>21.04e-06 </p>

<p>(5.84e-07) </p>

<p>(2.47e-07) </p>

<p>(4.27e-07) </p>

<p>(1.95e-07) </p>

<p>(5.39e-07) </p>

<p>(2.86e-07) </p>

<p>(1.39e-05) </p>

<p>(2.41e-06) </p>

<p>SD income </p>

<p>27.67e-07 </p>

<p>24.35e-07** </p>

<p>24.61e-07 </p>

<p>23.80e-07** </p>

<p>24.89e-08 </p>

<p>23.85e-07* </p>

<p>4.54e-06 </p>

<p>3.31e-07 </p>

<p>(5.13e-07) </p>

<p>(1.89e-07) </p>

<p>(3.43e-07) </p>

<p>(1.51e-07) </p>

<p>(3.65e-07) </p>

<p>(2.22e-07) </p>

<p>(1.20e-05) </p>

<p>(7.67e-07) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.347** </p>

<p>0.408** </p>

<p>0.397*** </p>

<p>0.481*** </p>

<p>0.463*** </p>

<p>0.500*** </p>

<p>0.369** </p>

<p>0.461*** </p>

<p>(0.149) </p>

<p>(0.158) </p>

<p>(0.132) </p>

<p>(0.129) </p>

<p>(0.152) </p>

<p>(0.129) </p>

<p>(0.156) </p>

<p>(0.175) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>133 </p>

<p>115 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>273 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is local skill-specific outmigration rate. Columns labeled "Large MSAs" are population-weighted least-squares estimates from a sample of local skill groups with </p>

<p>at least 50,000 members in 2010. Columns labeled "Excluding Largest MSAs" are estimated using a sample that excludes the ten most populous MSAs as of 2006. Columns labeled 
"Natives only" are population-weighted least-squares estimates from a sample of native U.S. citizens. Columns labeled "Random IV" instrument for quality using Bartik-predicted 
quality for members of the same skill group in a randomly assigned metropolitan area. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. Robust stan-
dard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; </p>

<p>0.01. </p>

<p>**p &lt; </p>

<p>0.05. </p>

<p>*p &lt; </p>

<p>0.1. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
groups in the sample serves primarily to increase the precision with which we measure the relation-
ship between volatility and outmigration. A related question is whether our results are driven pri-
marily by residents of the largest MSAs. To test for this, we re-estimate our main specification 
using a sample that excludes the ten most populous (as of 2006) MSAs. The results in the second 
set of columns of the table show that this exclusion has little effect on the estimated impact of vola-
tility on outmigration behavior. 
Cadena and Kovak (2016) show that foreign immigrants are significantly more likely than 
natives to make long-distance moves during a recession. If the observed relationship between vola-
tility and migration were driven primarily by foreign immigrants, the power of our theoretical 
argument to explain residential location choices would be limited. To test for immigrant-native 
heterogeneity in the effect of volatility on outmigration, we estimate models of outmigration using 
samples that exclude foreign immigrants. The results, presented in the third set of columns in Table 
5, are nearly identical to the full-sample estimates presented above, implying that our findings are 
not driven primarily by immigrants. </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Our instrumental variables estimates identify the impact of volatility on outmigration using 
national variation in labor-market quality that is plausibly exogenous to factors idiosyncratic to 
local labor markets, both within and across time. One challenge to this argument is that migration 
out of some metropolitan areas may respond to the national economic conditions that the instru-
ment uses to predict local labor-market quality. To provide evidence against this interpretation, we 
run a falsification exercise in which we randomly match local skill groups to the Bartik-predicted 
quality facing members of the same skill group living in a different area. If the IV estimates 
reflected sensitivity to national economic conditions for some area 3 skill groups, on average we 
would expect outmigration in these groups to respond negatively to the quality facing a randomly 
selected group. The fourth set of estimates in Table 5 shows that this is not the case, further sugges-
ting that our IV estimates identify the effects of volatility using variation that is otherwise exoge-
nous to outmigration. 
Our focus on the Great Recession period increases the policy relevance of our analysis and 
allows us to exploit increased geographic variation in the quality and volatility of local labor-
market quality. However, it also raises the question of whether the reduced outmigration that we 
observe in the data can be explained by recession-driven changes in housing prices. Of course, in 
order for changes in housing prices to explain away our findings, they would have to be correlated 
with the volatility of local labor-market quality. We have no prior reason to suspect a correlation 
between volatility and relative house prices and, at any rate, the instrumental variables estimate 
that we present above will have been purged of any such correlation. As further evidence that vari-
ation in housing prices does not explain our findings, we present OLS estimates of our primary 
specification with local housing price indices included as regressors. 
22 The results presented in the </p>

<p>21 An interesting possibility is that the inhibiting effect of labor-market volatility on outmigration helps explain </p>

<p>immigrant-native differences in mobility, for example, if immigrants are less attached to residential locations and 
hence more willing to move in the face of uncertainty (a fuller exploration of this hypothesis is beyond our present 
scope). 
22 We use the All-Transactions indices supplied by the Federal Housing Financing Agency and available from https:// </p>

<p>www.fhfa.gov/DataTools/Downloads/Pages/House-Price-Index-Datasets.aspx; the construction of the indices is dis-
cussed in Calhoun (1996). Because these indices are only available at the Core-Based Statistical Area (CBSA) level, we 
use the crosswalk available at http://www.nber.org/data/cbsa-msa-fips-ssa-county-crosswalk.html to map CBSAs to 
Census MSAs. This mapping is not one-to-one; when multiple CBSAs map to the same MSA, we use the average 
price. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>first set of columns in Table 6 show that, while housing prices appear to be positively associated 
with outmigration, the estimated effects of volatility are robust to their inclusion. 
While our findings for high-skilled workers are robust to how we measure quality and how 
we estimate the effect of the mean and volatility of quality on outmigration, we find only weak 
and specification-sensitive evidence of a volatility effect for low-skilled workers. Wozniak and 
Murray (2012) argue that foreign immigration "traps" low-skill workers in relatively isolated met-
ropolitan areas that are further from other areas, and hence more costly to move away from. To 
test whether a similar effect might help explain the skill disparity in the estimated effects of </p>

<p>Table 6. Robustness Exercises (Continued) </p>

<p>House price 
Excluding isolated MSAs 
IV 2i </p>

<p>HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Mean 
unemployment </p>

<p>0.128 
0.871*** 
0.273 
0.880** 
2.485 
1.836* </p>

<p>(0.129) 
(0.290) 
(0.179) 
(0.347) 
(1.770) 
(0.992) 
SD 
unemployment </p>

<p>20.126 20.483*** 
20.276 
20.502** 
22.582 
21.098* </p>

<p>(0.133) 
(0.161) 
(0.185) 
(0.198) 
(1.816) 
(0.574) 
Lag outmig. 
0.408*** 0.478*** 
0.395*** 
0.466*** 
0.381*** 
0.479*** 
(0.146) 
(0.132) 
(0.141) 
(0.136) 
(0.124) 
(0.126) 
House price 
1.13e-05 4.35e-05* 
(3.03e-05) (2.25e-05) 
Observations 
252 
252 
239 
239 
283 
283 
Weeks 
Mean weeks 
20.000605 0.000206 20.000654 
0.000217 
20.0122 
0.0110 
(0.000475) (0.000387) (0.000539) (0.000436) 
(0.0111) 
(0.00964) 
SD weeks 
0.00118 20.00286** 0.00150 
20.00300** 
0.0215 
0.000585 
(0.00111) (0.00124) 
(0.00131) 
(0.00136) 
(0.0204) 
(0.00880) 
Lag outmig. 
0.410*** 0.480*** 
0.398*** 
0.474*** 
0.382*** 
0.557*** 
(0.145) 
(0.133) 
(0.142) 
(0.137) 
(0.136) 
(0.150) 
House price 
2.77e-06 5.15e-05** 
(2.77e-05) (2.28e-05) 
Observations 
252 
252 
239 
239 
283 
283 
Income 
Mean income 
6.57e-08 
1.73e-07 
3.97e-07 
3.40e-07 
2.04e-08 
5.48e-07 
(5.39e-07) (1.97e-07) (5.12e-07) 
(2.08e-07) 
(1.98e-06) 
(3.42e-07) 
SD income 
24.00e-07 24.07e-07** 27.83e-07** 24.23e-07*** 22.91e-06** 27.34e-07*** 
(3.19e-07) (1.80e-07) (3.86e-07) 
(1.58e-07) 
(1.33e-06) 
(2.84e-07) 
Lag outmig. 
0.409*** 0.467*** 
0.396*** 
0.462*** 
0.405*** 
0.475*** 
(0.147) 
(0.135) 
(0.142) 
(0.138) 
(0.143) 
(0.129) 
House price 
1.42e-05 7.41e-05*** 
(3.27e-05) (2.31e-05) 
Observations 
252 
252 
239 
239 
283 
283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is local skill-specific outmigration rate. Columns labeled "House price" are population-weighted 
least-squared estimates from regressions that include Federal Housing Agency indices of housing prices as regressors. 
Columns labeled "Excluding isolated MSAs" are population-weighted least-squares estimates obtained from a sample 
that excludes MSAs that are more than 75 miles away from another MSA. Columns labeled "IV 2i "instrument for 
quality using Bartik predictions that exclude metropolitan area i when constructing national quality measures. HS 
denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. Robust standard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; 0.01. 
**p &lt; 0.05. 
*p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
volatility on outmigration behavior, we re-estimate our primary specification using least squares 
on a sample that excludes isolated metropolitan areas that are further than 75 miles away from 
another metropolitan area. 
23 The results do support the hypothesis that the degree to which an </p>

<p>area is isolated might mediate the relationship between volatility and outmigration among the low 
skilled. The point estimates on the standard deviation of unemployment and income are substan-
tially larger in absolute value for the low-skilled when isolated MSAs are excluded (although the 
estimate for unemployment remains insignificant). 
The Bartik instrumental variables strategy that we use in the previous section is premised on 
the notion that secular, nationwide shocks to the quality faced by workers in a given industry are 
exogenous to outmigration from any particular local labor market. A threat to this interpretation 
is that, since the national labor market is itself composed of many local labor markets, there will 
be a mechanical correlation between any local and national measures of labor market quality. To 
show that our IV estimates are not driven by such a correlation (which is likely to be small in any 
case), we follow Wozniak and Murray (2012) and Smith (2012) in instrumenting for quality in 
each metropolitan area using predictions obtained by excluding that area when computing 
national industry-specific quality measures. 
24 The estimates, shown in the rightmost columns of </p>

<p>Table 6, support the conclusion of the previously reported IV estimates (and the other estimates in 
this article) that volatility discourages outmigration. 
As we note above, the level and volatility of local labor market quality tend to be correlated, 
making it difficult to separately identify the effects of these aspects of quality. Although the magni-
tudes of our coefficient estimates, combined with the fact that for weeks worked and income there 
is variation in volatility among local skill groups with the same level of quality, suggest otherwise, 
the possibility remains that our estimates reflect migration responses to higher-order variation in 
the level, rather than the volatility, of labor market quality. As evidence that this is not the case, we 
estimate versions of the specifications summarized in Table 2 that add quadratics in the levels of 
our quality measures. The estimates, presented in Table 7, do not suggest that our volatility mea-
sures proxy for higher-order variation in mean quality. For the high-skill group, the coefficient on 
the standard deviation of unemployment in our preferred lagged-dependent-variable specification 
is nearly the same as that reported above in Table 2, and the coefficients on the standard deviations 
of weeks worked and income remain negative and statistically significant. Mirroring those 
reported above, the results for the low-skilled are weaker, although including the quadratic term in 
mean unemployment actually renders the coefficient on the standard deviation of unemployment 
significantly negative for this group. 
Finally, we test the robustness of our findings to the use of different samples and explore 
demographic heterogeneity in the effect of volatility on migration. As we note in the beginning of 
this section, there is a tradeoff between the specificity and the precision with which we can measure </p>

<p>23 To compute this indicator, we started with the geographical coordinates of each CBSA (provided by Matt Holian at </p>

<p>http://mattholian.blogspot.com/2013/05/central-business-district-geocodes.html and used in Holian and Kahn 
[2015bb]). We then used the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Bing Maps Application Programming Interface</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">https://www.microsoft.com/maps</rs>/) to 
determine the distance between each pair of CBSAs and hence the distance from each CBSA to its nearest neighbor. 
Finally, we used the crosswalk detailed above to match CBSAs to MSAs. When multiple CBSAs matched to an MSA, 
we used the average distance. Because the crosswalk uses more recent MSA definitions than IPUMS, we exclude met-
ropolitan areas that do not match uniquely to the MSAs in the crosswalk (indicating code changes between the cross-
walk and IPUMS definitions). 
24 That is, we replace the l jt and r jt in the formulae given above with the sample analogs of Eðq hjt jh 6 ¼ iÞ and </p>

<p>Ef½q hjt 2Eðq hjt jh 6 ¼ iÞ 
2 jh 6 ¼ ig 
1=2 . </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>labor-market quality. Accordingly, we explore heterogeneity with respect to a few coarse, but key, 
demographic measures. In the left panel of Table 8, we divide our sample into those employed in 
manufacturing and nonmanufacturing industries (using 1950 industrial classifications). The 
results show that the relationship between volatility and outmigration is more pronounced among 
those employed in nonmanufacturing sectors. This is perhaps unsurprising given that there may 
be fewer locations in which manufacturing employment can be pursued and that those working in 
relatively low-paying manufacturing jobs may face income constraints that make migration diffi-
cult. Even within the manufacturing sector, our results are more robust for those with at least 
some college. The right panel of the table divides the sample into those below and above the age of 
forty. Again unsurprisingly, the estimated relationship is stronger among younger workers, 
although it is evident for members of both age groups. </p>

<p>Table 7. Quadratic Specifications </p>

<p>HS 
Col. 
HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment 
Mean unemployment 
1.238* 
20.418 
2.013** 
0.536 
(0.663) 
(0.960) 
(0.931) 
(1.639) 
Mean unemployment </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>21.709 
4.282 
22.778** 
0.736 
(1.091) 
(3.398) 
(1.283) 
(4.610) 
SD unemployment 
20.733** 
20.112 
21.155** 
20.358 
(0.330) 
(0.283) 
(0.541) 
(0.574) 
Lag outmig. 
0.407*** 
0.494*** 
(0.135) 
(0.127) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Weeks 
Mean weeks 
20.0131*** 
20.00939*** 
20.0128*** 
20.00349 
(0.00434) 
(0.00277) 
(0.00460) 
(0.00384) 
Mean weeks </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0.000370*** 
0.000249*** 
0.000343*** 
9.59e-05 
(0.000115) 
(6.25e-05) 
(0.000127) 
(9.87e-05) 
SD weeks 
0.00313*** 
20.00136 
0.00162 
20.00235** 
(0.00106) 
(0.00122) 
(0.00110) 
(0.00117) 
Lag outmig. 
0.410*** 
0.496*** 
(0.132) 
(0.129) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 
Income 
Mean income 
26.42e-07 
21.24e-06*** 
21.32e-06 
25.01e-07 
(3.10e-06) 
(3.03e-07) 
(3.02e-06) 
(3.53e-07) 
Mean income </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 
0*** 
0 
0*** 
(7.95e-11) 
(0) 
(8.28e-11) 
(0) 
SD income 
24.26e-07 
24.41e-07** 
25.95e-07 
24.32e-07*** 
(3.99e-07) 
(2.01e-07) 
(3.66e-07) 
(1.47e-07) 
Lag outmig. 
0.417*** 
0.475*** 
(0.135) 
(0.130) 
Observations 
566 
566 
283 
283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is metro-level outmigration rate. Equations estimated by least squares, weighted by population 
size. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. Robust standard errors in 
parentheses. 
***p &lt; 0.01. 
**p &lt; 0.05. 
*p &lt; 0.1. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
Table 8. Heterogeneity in the Effects of Volatility </p>

<p>Non-mfg. </p>

<p>Mfg. </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>&gt;40 </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>Unemployment </p>

<p>Mean unemployment </p>

<p>0.344*** </p>

<p>0.712** </p>

<p>0.0350 </p>

<p>0.219** </p>

<p>0.191 </p>

<p>0.658** </p>

<p>0.0805 </p>

<p>0.302** </p>

<p>(0.205) </p>

<p>(0.307) </p>

<p>(0.0424) </p>

<p>(0.0885) </p>

<p>(0.149) </p>

<p>(0.280) </p>

<p>(0.0606) </p>

<p>(0.139) </p>

<p>SD unemployment </p>

<p>20.297 </p>

<p>20.371** </p>

<p>20.0173 </p>

<p>20.112** </p>

<p>20.220 </p>

<p>20.351** </p>

<p>20.0576 </p>

<p>20.152** </p>

<p>(0.194) </p>

<p>(0.166) </p>

<p>(0.0399) </p>

<p>(0.0509) </p>

<p>(0.183) </p>

<p>(0.164) </p>

<p>(0.0513) </p>

<p>(0.0685) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.364* </p>

<p>0.476* </p>

<p>0.222* </p>

<p>0.238* </p>

<p>0.399* </p>

<p>0.582* </p>

<p>0.262* </p>

<p>0.251* </p>

<p>(0.118) </p>

<p>(0.116) </p>

<p>(0.0666) </p>

<p>(0.0632) </p>

<p>(0.131) </p>

<p>(0.0787) </p>

<p>(0.0784) </p>

<p>(0.0831) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Weeks worked 
Mean weeks </p>

<p>20.000794 </p>

<p>0.000414 </p>

<p>6.20e-05 </p>

<p>1.10e-05 </p>

<p>20.000543 </p>

<p>0.000432 </p>

<p>20.000148 </p>

<p>0.000147 </p>

<p>(0.000606) </p>

<p>(0.000409) </p>

<p>(0.000270) </p>

<p>(0.000360) </p>

<p>(0.000630) </p>

<p>(0.000630) </p>

<p>(0.000296) </p>

<p>(0.000273) </p>

<p>SD weeks </p>

<p>0.00118 </p>

<p>20.00285** </p>

<p>20.000507 </p>

<p>20.00158* </p>

<p>25.76e-05 
20.00363** 20.000186 </p>

<p>20.000530 </p>

<p>(0.00127) </p>

<p>(0.00122) </p>

<p>(0.000489) </p>

<p>(0.000522) </p>

<p>(0.00129) </p>

<p>(0.00140) </p>

<p>(0.000658) </p>

<p>(0.000607) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.369* </p>

<p>0.479* </p>

<p>0.223* </p>

<p>0.245* </p>

<p>0.406* </p>

<p>0.584* </p>

<p>0.267* </p>

<p>0.257* </p>

<p>(0.119) </p>

<p>(0.116) </p>

<p>(0.0666) </p>

<p>(0.0652) </p>

<p>(0.131) </p>

<p>(0.0802) </p>

<p>(0.0801) </p>

<p>(0.0860) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>280 </p>

<p>275 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Income 
Mean income </p>

<p>3.57e-09 </p>

<p>2.82e-07 </p>

<p>25.40e-07*** </p>

<p>25.57e-08 </p>

<p>9.46e-07 </p>

<p>6.37e-07 </p>

<p>22.07e-07 </p>

<p>1.66e-07 </p>

<p>(5.72e-07) </p>

<p>(2.12e-07) </p>

<p>(2.95e-07) </p>

<p>(2.47e-07) </p>

<p>(8.91e-07) </p>

<p>(3.91e-07) </p>

<p>(2.61e-07) </p>

<p>(1.28e-07) </p>

<p>SD income </p>

<p>25.59e-07 </p>

<p>24.05e-07** </p>

<p>3.66e-07 </p>

<p>3.37e-08 </p>

<p>29.79e-07 </p>

<p>28.29e-07* </p>

<p>2.19e-09 </p>

<p>22.40e-07** </p>

<p>(3.59e-07) </p>

<p>(1.75e-07) </p>

<p>(2.58e-07) </p>

<p>(1.97e-07) </p>

<p>(6.34e-07) </p>

<p>(2.33e-07) </p>

<p>(2.10e-07) </p>

<p>(9.71e-08) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.365* </p>

<p>0.460* </p>

<p>0.218* </p>

<p>0.245* </p>

<p>0.399* </p>

<p>0.561* </p>

<p>0.262* </p>

<p>0.253* </p>

<p>(0.119) </p>

<p>(0.117) </p>

<p>(0.0667) </p>

<p>(0.0637) </p>

<p>(0.128) </p>

<p>(0.0791) </p>

<p>(0.0815) </p>

<p>(0.0864) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>Dependent variable is outmigration rate by skill group and either industry or age. Skill groups are denoted by "HS" for high school and "Col." for college. Industry groups are 
denoted by "Mfg." for manufacturing and "Non-mfg." for other industries. Age groups are denoted by " 40" for those 40 years of age or younger, and "&gt;40" otherwise. Equations 
estimated by least squares, weighted by group population size. Robust standard errors in parentheses. </p>

<p>***p &lt; </p>

<p>0.1. </p>

<p>**p &lt; </p>

<p>0.05. </p>

<p>*p &lt; </p>

<p>0.01. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>Counterfactual Migration Rates </p>

<p>The evidence that we have presented establishes that, other things equal, people are less likely 
to migrate away from more volatile local labor markets. Of course, other things are rarely equal-
geographic differences in factors such as the level of quality accompany such differences in volatil-
ity, and observed differences in outmigration rates reflect variation across labor markets in all of 
these factors. To provide a sense of the aggregate effect of volatility on internal migration, in Fig-
ure 3 we plot against observed rates the counterfactual outmigration rates that would arise if </p>

<p>0 .05 .1 .15 .2 .25 </p>

<p>Counterfactual </p>

<p>0 
.05 
.1 
.15 
Observed </p>

<p>Unemp. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.05 </p>

<p>.1 </p>

<p>.15 </p>

<p>Counterfactual </p>

<p>0 
.05 
.1 
.15 
Observed </p>

<p>Wks. </p>

<p>0 .05 .1 .15 
Counterfactual </p>

<p>0 
.05 
.1 
.15 
Observed </p>

<p>Col. 
HS </p>

<p>45 deg. line </p>

<p>Inc. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Observed and Counterfactual Outmigration. 
Notes: Counterfactual rates based on estimated lagged-dependent-variable models with coefficients on the 
standard deviation of quality set to zero. Average rates weighted by population size. HS denotes a high-school 
education or less, col. Denotes at least some college. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
outmigration were unaffected by volatility. 
25 This comparison highlights the role that volatility </p>

<p>effects play in determining aggregate internal mobility. For the high-skilled, nearly every counter-
factual rate lies above the 458 line, as do many for the low-skilled (except when quality is measured 
using weeks worked, where the volatility coefficient is negative, although insignificant). 
Table 10 presents national-average counterfactual and observed outmigration rates. For the 
low-skill group, our estimates imply that outmigration would increase from an observed average 
rate of 2.7% to as high as 7%, depending on the quality measure used. For the high skilled, among 
whom the observed rate is 3.2%, the predicted counterfactual rates range from 5% when quality is 
measured in terms of annual income to as high as 14% when it is measured in terms of unemploy-
ment. To provide a deeper look at how volatility affects internal migration, Table 9 lists the metro-
politan areas for which skill-specific observed and counterfactual outmigration rates differ the 
most (calculated using lagged-dependent-variable specifications that proxy for quality using 
unemployment). Although these areas experienced virtually no outmigration in 2010, our esti-
mates imply that they would have lost roughly 10% of their low-skilled and 20% of their high-
skilled residents absent volatility in unemployment rates. The implied effects, although large, may 
not be implausible: what this counterfactual exercise tells us is the fraction of people that would 
migrate if they knew with absolute certainty the quality that they would face if they chose to 
remain in their current location. It should be noted, however, that these are partial-equilibrium 
counterfactuals that do not account for the influence of increased internal mobility on the </p>

<p>Table 9. Areas with Greatest Unemployment Volatility Effects </p>

<p>Area 
Observed 
Counterfactual 
Difference </p>

<p>HS 
New Orleans, LA 
0.03 
0.14 
20.11 
Flint, MI 
0.00 
0.08 
20.08 
Medford, OR 
0.02 
0.09 
20.08 
Biloxi-Gulfport, MS 
0.03 
0.11 
20.07 
Jackson, TN 
0.01 
0.09 
20.07 
Lexington-Fayette, KY 
0.02 
0.09 
20.07 
Erie, PA 
0.01 
0.08 
20.07 
Lima, OH 
0.00 
0.07 
20.07 
Saginaw-Bay City-Midland, MI 
0.01 
0.08 
20.07 
State College, PA 
0.01 
0.08 
20.07 
Col. 
Flint, MI 
0.00 
0.18 
20.18 
New Orleans, LA 
0.03 
0.21 
20.18 
Goldsboro, NC 
0.06 
0.22 
20.17 
Salem, OR 
0.02 
0.19 
20.16 
New Bedford, MA 
0.03 
0.19 
20.16 
Eugene-Springfield, OR 
0.05 
0.20 
20.15 
Visalia-Tulare-Porterville, CA 
0.02 
0.17 
20.15 
Salinas-Sea Side-Monterey, CA 
0.00 
0.15 
20.15 
Daytona Beach, FL 
0.05 
0.20 
20.15 
Medford, OR 
0.02 
0.17 
20.15 </p>

<p>Counterfactual rates based on estimated lagged-dependent-variable models with coefficients on the standard deviation 
of unemployment set to zero. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some college. </p>

<p>25 Our counterfactual predictions are derived from OLS estimates of models that include lagged outmigration rates </p>

<p>(Table 2), setting the coefficients on the standard deviations to zero. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>geographic dispersion of labor-market quality. Even with this caveat in mind, these counterfac-
tuals suggest that our theoretical model has considerable power to explain why observed migration 
rates are not higher, especially in times of economic tumult. </p>

<p>4. Conclusion </p>

<p>When the quality of labor market opportunities is declining on average over time, workers 
face a decision about whether to move in search of new opportunities. Moving, however, requires 
a substantial fixed cost. This cost includes not only the pecuniary costs of moving, but also the 
costs associated with leaving family, various amenities, and familiarity behind. Given the substan-
tial fixed cost involved, we have developed a framework for thinking about this migration decision 
by drawing on work in the investment literature. Our framework treats migration as an optimal 
stopping problem in which workers must choose a threshold for labor market quality at which it is 
optimal to move. Our model implies that greater volatility in the quality of labor market opportu-
nities reduces the likelihood of migration. 
We test this hypothesis by relating outmigration rates to multiple proxies for the level and vol-
atility of labor market quality. Consistent with our theoretical model, we find that increases in the 
volatility of labor market quality reduce the likelihood of migration, regardless of how we measure 
quality or how we estimate its effects on migration. These results are robust to alternative, non-
causal interpretations, and imply that outmigration rates from local labor markets would be con-
siderably higher absent the inhibiting effects of volatility. Our findings lend credibility to the 
ability of our theoretical model to explain why relatively few people leave labor markets experienc-
ing relative declines. 
Our model and results also suggest topics for further work. For example, while our theoreti-
cal model assumes for the sake of simplicity that outside options are known with certainty, it is 
possible to amend the model to consider the role of uncertainty with regards to outside opportuni-
ties. In addition to being interesting in its own right, extending the model in this way would permit 
sharper predictions about the internal migration response to different kinds of local quality shocks 
(e.g., if migration responds differently to a national recession, in which quality shocks are likely to 
be positively correlated across labor markets than it does to idiosyncratic local shocks that might 
induce a negative correlation). Our theoretical results may also have implications for internal 
migration policy, particularly if volatility reduces welfare by discouraging would-be migrants from 
paying the fixed costs required to obtain a better location match. We leave these suggestions for 
future research. </p>

<p>Table 10. Average Counterfactual Outmigration Rates </p>

<p>HS 
Col. </p>

<p>Observed 
0.027 
0.032 
Counterfactual 
Unemployment 
0.072 
0.141 
Weeks worked 
0.001 
0.070 
Income 
0.040 
0.052 </p>

<p>Counterfactual rates based on estimated lagged-dependent-variable models with coefficients on the standard deviation 
of quality set to zero. Average rates weighted by population size. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. 
denotes at least some college. </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
Appendix A </p>

<p>Lag Identification </p>

<p>Suppose that after partialling out all covariates and expressing the remaining variables as deviations from 
means, the outmigration rate m and volatility r satisfy the causal relationship </p>

<p>m t 5b 1 r t 1b 2 r t21 1E t ; 
(A1) </p>

<p>while the effect of outmigration on the volatility of unemployment outcomes can be approximated as </p>

<p>r t 5a 1 m t 1a 2 r t21 1u t ; 
(A2) </p>

<p>where E t and u t are iid white noise. 
Solving Equations A1 and A2 for m t and r t gives </p>

<p>m t 5 
ðb 1 a 2 1b 2 Þr t21 1b 1 u t 1E t 
12b 1 a 1 
(A3) </p>

<p>and </p>

<p>r t 5 
ðb 2 a 1 1a 2 Þv t21 1a 1 E t 1u t 
12a 1 b 1 
: 
(A4) </p>

<p>As E t is white noise that is determined after r t21 , these variables are uncorrelated, implying with Equations A3 and 
A4 that </p>

<p>Covðm t ; E t Þ5 
VarðE t Þ 
12b 1 a 1 
and Covðr t ; E t Þ5 
a 1 VarðE t Þ 
12a 1 b 1 
: </p>

<p>(Note that the observation that r t21 is uncorrelated with E t is not inconsistent with the observation that r t is corre-
lated with both r t21 and E t .) </p>

<p>26 </p>

<p>The coefficient from a population regression of m t on r t is </p>

<p>b mtjrt 5 
Covðb 1 r t 1b 2 r t21 1E t ; r t Þ 
Varðr t Þ 
5b 1 1b 2 b rt21jrt 1 
CovðE t ; r t Þ 
Varðr t Þ 
; 
(A5) </p>

<p>where b rt21jrt is the coefficient from a population projection of r t21 onto r t (if r t21 were included in the model, this 
would be textbook simultaneity bias). Conversely, Equation A3 implies that the coefficient from a population regres-
sion of m t onto r t21 is </p>

<p>b mtjrt21 5 
b 1 a 2 1b 2 
12b 1 a 1 
: 
(A6) </p>

<p>Reed (2015) and Bellemare, Masaki, and Pepinsky (2017) obtain similar results. 
As Equation A5 shows, the coefficient from the regression of outmigration on current volatility may differ 
from zero even if neither current nor lagged unemployment exert a casual influence on outmigration (i.e., if 
b 1 5b 2 50). However, Equation A6 shows that the coefficient from the lagged model will be zero in this case. Finally, 
note that if the simultaneity bias is negligible (i.e., a 1 is small) and, as is the case in our data, the coefficients a 2 and 
b rt21jrt from regressions of current onto lagged and lagged onto current volatility are similar, then the coefficients 
b mtjrt and b mtjrt21 from the current and lagged regressions will be similar as well. </p>

<p>26 From Equation A2, r t21 5a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>2 ðr t 2a 1 m t 2u t Þ, so Covðr t21 ; E t Þ5a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>2 ½Covðr t ; E t Þ2a 1 Covðm t ; e t Þ5a </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>2 ½a 1 VarðE t Þ= 
ð12a 1 b 1 Þ2a 1 VarðE t Þ=ð12b 1 a 1 Þ50. In other words, r t21 is related to t through two mutually negating channels. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>Appendix B </p>

<p>.2 .3 .4 .5 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>0 
.1 
.2 
.3 
.4 
Mean </p>

<p>Unemp. (HS) </p>

<p>.1.15.2.25.3.35 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>0 
.05 
.1 
.15 
Mean </p>

<p>Unemp. (Col.) </p>

<p>8 1012141618 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>10 
15 
20 
25 
Mean </p>

<p>Wks. (HS) </p>

<p>10 12 14 16 18 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
Mean </p>

<p>Wks. (Col.) </p>

<p>10000 20000 30000 40000 50000 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>10000 
15000 
20000 
25000 
30000 
Mean </p>

<p>Inc. (HS) </p>

<p>0 50000 100000 150000 </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>20000 
40000 
60000 
80000 100000 120000 
Mean </p>

<p>Inc. (Col.) </p>

<p>Figure B1. Means and Standard Deviations of Labor Market Quality Measures. 
Notes: Statistics derived from IPUMS sample of 2010 ACS </p>

<p>Option View of Migration </p>

<p>
Table B1. First-Stage Regressions </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>HS </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>Col. </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Mean </p>

<p>SD </p>

<p>Unemployment </p>

<p>Pred. mean unemp. </p>

<p>2.892 </p>

<p>2.278 </p>

<p>8.469*** </p>

<p>12.18*** </p>

<p>223.46** </p>

<p>222.37** </p>

<p>4.122 </p>

<p>23.620 </p>

<p>(1.965) </p>

<p>(2.860) </p>

<p>(2.198) </p>

<p>(4.067) </p>

<p>(9.900) </p>

<p>(9.094) </p>

<p>(8.869) </p>

<p>(15.73) </p>

<p>Pred. SD unemp. </p>

<p>21.374 </p>

<p>20.706 </p>

<p>23.468*** </p>

<p>24.668** </p>

<p>22.36*** </p>

<p>21.47*** </p>

<p>20.628 </p>

<p>5.003 </p>

<p>(1.500) </p>

<p>(2.196) </p>

<p>(1.033) </p>

<p>(1.916) </p>

<p>(8.586) </p>

<p>(7.760) </p>

<p>(4.883) </p>

<p>(8.679) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>0.145 </p>

<p>0.129 </p>

<p>0.0269 </p>

<p>0.0528 </p>

<p>(0.0970) </p>

<p>(0.0923) </p>

<p>(0.0558) </p>

<p>(0.0969) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>162.8 </p>

<p>180.3 </p>

<p>157.4 </p>

<p>173.2 </p>

<p>9.058 </p>

<p>13.89 </p>

<p>22.11 </p>

<p>22.58 </p>

<p>Weeks worked 
Pred. mean wks. </p>

<p>0.891** </p>

<p>0.131 </p>

<p>0.578*** </p>

<p>20.252*** </p>

<p>1.497* </p>

<p>20.367 </p>

<p>20.496 </p>

<p>20.412** </p>

<p>(0.429) </p>

<p>(0.152) </p>

<p>(0.196) </p>

<p>(0.0666) </p>

<p>(0.847) </p>

<p>(0.335) </p>

<p>(0.613) </p>

<p>(0.171) </p>

<p>Pred. SD wks. </p>

<p>0.000478 </p>

<p>0.754** </p>

<p>1.719** </p>

<p>2.051*** </p>

<p>22.800* </p>

<p>20.993 </p>

<p>20.196 </p>

<p>2.911*** </p>

<p>(0.998) </p>

<p>(0.348) </p>

<p>(0.868) </p>

<p>(0.291) </p>

<p>(1.582) </p>

<p>(0.697) </p>

<p>(1.364) </p>

<p>(0.594) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>21.558 </p>

<p>0.172 </p>

<p>25.348 </p>

<p>1.926 </p>

<p>(3.354) </p>

<p>(1.693) </p>

<p>(4.470) </p>

<p>(1.944) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>187 </p>

<p>279.2 </p>

<p>474.4 </p>

<p>193.9 </p>

<p>2.958 </p>

<p>1.567 </p>

<p>0.333 </p>

<p>17.03 </p>

<p>Income 
Pred. mean inc. </p>

<p>0.374** </p>

<p>21.102*** </p>

<p>1.662*** </p>

<p>20.690 </p>

<p>0.545 </p>

<p>20.989** </p>

<p>2.769*** </p>

<p>0.529 </p>

<p>(0.175) </p>

<p>(0.228) </p>

<p>(0.440) </p>

<p>(0.576) </p>

<p>(0.353) </p>

<p>(0.449) </p>

<p>(0.647) </p>

<p>(0.581) </p>

<p>Pred. SD inc. </p>

<p>1.257*** </p>

<p>2.976*** </p>

<p>0.756** </p>

<p>3.097*** </p>

<p>1.006** </p>

<p>2.998*** </p>

<p>0.787 </p>

<p>3.331*** </p>

<p>(0.293) </p>

<p>(0.371) </p>

<p>(0.383) </p>

<p>(0.561) </p>

<p>(0.491) </p>

<p>(0.655) </p>

<p>(0.524) </p>

<p>(0.678) </p>

<p>Lag outmig. </p>

<p>23,123 </p>

<p>2,764 </p>

<p>20,259 </p>

<p>43,344** </p>

<p>(7,658) </p>

<p>(9,259) </p>

<p>(15,849) </p>

<p>(19,381) </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>566 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>283 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>55.42 </p>

<p>36.85 </p>

<p>126.7 </p>

<p>74.28 </p>

<p>18.21 </p>

<p>14.85 </p>

<p>100.7 </p>

<p>60.41 </p>

<p>Dependent variables are metro-level means and standard deviations of unemployment, weeks worked, and annual income, as indicated. Independent variables are Bartik-predictions </p>

<p>of these variables, as described in text. Equations estimated by least squares, weighted by population size. HS denotes a high-school education or less, Col. denotes at least some col-
lege. Robust standard errors in parentheses. 
***p &lt; </p>

<p>0.01. </p>

<p>**p &lt; </p>

<p>0.05. </p>

<p>*p &lt; </p>

<p>0.1. </p>

<p> 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>We thank Chris Brunt, the co-editor, and two anonymous referees for helpful comments 
and suggestions. </p>



<p>Option View of Migration </p>



<p>
 
John Gardner and Joshua R. Hendrickson </p>

</text></tei>