<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.15.2.25" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>case: the source and strength of Microsoft's market power, the competitive effects 
of Microsoft's practices, the degree of consumer harm, and proposed remedies. </p>

<p>Early Skirmishes </p>

<p>Microsoft's antitrust woes began in 1990 when the Federal Trade Commission 
(FTC) launched an investigation of the company. After three years, the FTC's legal 
staff-but not its economics staff-recommended that the Commission bring a 
case focusing on Microsoft's licensing practices with personal computer manufac-
turers. The FTC investigation ended in February 1993 when the Commission 
deadlocked in a 2-2 vote, with one commissioner recused (Lopatka and Page, 1995, 
p. 324). 
The U.S. Department of Justice continued the investigation of Microsoft's 
conduct and, on July 15, 1994, brought a complaint alleging that Microsoft used 
exclusionary and anticompetitive contracts with personal computer manufacturers 
to maintain an unlawful monopoly of personal computer operating systems. Simul-
taneous with the filing of the complaint, Microsoft and the Department of Justice 
entered into a consent decree in which Microsoft agreed to abide by certain 
restrictions on its licensing arrangements (United States v. Microsoft Corp., 1995-2 
Trade Cas. P 71,096 [D.D.C. 1995]). 1 After almost a year of legal wrangling, an 
appellate court approved the consent decree on June 16, 1995. 
Disputes over the scope and interpretation of the decree soon arose. Among 
other conduct restrictions, the consent decree (Section IV.E) stipulated: </p>

<p>Microsoft shall not enter into any License Agreement in which the terms of 
that agreement are expressly or impliedly conditioned upon: (i) the licensing 
of any other Covered Product, Operating System Software product or other 
product (provided, however, that this provision in and of itself shall not be 
construed to prohibit Microsoft from developing integrated products) . . . </p>

<p>The force of this restriction turns on the definitions of what constitute "other" 
and "integrated" products. Not long after Microsoft and the Department of Justice 
signed the consent decree, Microsoft began requiring computer manufacturers to 
license and install <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft</rs>'s <rs id="software-0" type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> browser as a condition for being 
able to obtain a license for the Windows 95 operating system. Microsoft argued that 
the <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> browser was part of the operating system, not a separate 
product. The Department of Justice disagreed and sought an injunction against 
Microsoft. 
On December 11, 1997, Judge Thomas Penfield Jackson ordered Microsoft to 
offer its <rs id="software-2" type="software">Windows</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">95</rs> operating system and Internet Explorer as separate products. 
Microsoft appealed his ruling. The appeals court reversed Judge Jackson's order, </p>

<p>1 See Gilbert (1998) for a discussion of the economic issues in the case. </p>



<p>ruling that <rs id="software-3" type="software">Windows</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">95</rs> and <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> provided computer users with 
functionality that did not exist with separate programs and thus passed the "inte-
grated product" provision of the consent decree (U.S. v. Microsoft, U.S. Court of 
Appeals for the District of Columbia Circuit, No. 97-5343, June 23, 1998, at footnote 
14). Whatever one thinks of the merits of the two sides' positions following the 1995 
consent decree, it is clear that the conduct remedy did not work as the Department 
of Justice had intended. </p>

<p>The Battle is Joined </p>

<p>On May 18, 1998, the government brought an antitrust case against Microsoft 
alleging that the company had monopolized the markets for personal computer 
operating systems and browsers (U.S. v. Microsoft, 1998). The government's case 
against Microsoft rested on allegations that Microsoft compelled computer manu-
facturers to license and install <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>, entered into contracts that tended 
to exclude rivals, and engaged in various forms of predatory conduct. 
Microsoft and the government both considered Internet browsers combined 
with the Java language and server-based applications to be particularly potent 
sources of potential competition for Windows. In theory, the Java programming 
language offered a standard to which creators of applications, such as spreadsheet 
and word processing programs, could write without regard for the underlying 
operating system. Java did this by providing a "middleware" layer of software 
between applications programs and the underlying operating system. <rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Netscape</rs> was 
a threat to Microsoft because its <rs id="software-6" type="software">Navigator</rs> browser was a distribution vehicle for 
Java that could further its acceptance as a language for application programs that 
was independent of the underlying operating system. In addition, there was a 
possibility that <rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-7" type="software">Navigator</rs> itself could grow into a substitute for <rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> 
<rs id="software-8" type="software">Windows</rs> or facilitate server-based applications that made minimal use of the 
desktop operating system. These are the outcomes the government sought to 
preserve and Bill Gates (1995) feared when he wrote that Netscape threatened to 
"commoditize the underlying operating system." 
The government alleged that Microsoft sought to eliminate the competitive 
threat posed by Java and Netscape in two ways. The first was to eliminate Netscape's 
browser as a commercially viable product through an offer of market division 
and-after that offer was rejected-a combination of predatory and exclusionary 
actions. The second was to undermine Java as an operating-system-independent 
platform by promoting a Windows-specific version of Java. </p>

<p>The Assessment of Market Power </p>

<p>A firm's conduct is unlikely to have significant adverse consequences for 
economic welfare if the firm lacks significant market power. Therefore, the assess-
ment of market power is the initial step in a typical economic antitrust analysis. The </p>

<p>Richard J. Gilbert and Michael L. Katz 27 </p>

<p>courts commonly assess market power by first defining the relevant market(s) 
affected by a firm's conduct. A relevant market is a set of products that consumers 
consider to be reasonably close substitutes for each other (see, for example, U.S. 
Department of Justice, 1992, sec. 1.11). Once a relevant market has been defined, 
the assessment of market power moves to the calculation of market share, exami-
nation of competitive interactions, determination of the conditions of entry, and 
analysis of other pertinent structural features of the market. Katz and Shapiro 
(1999) discuss the assessment of market power in software markets. 
The government alleged that Microsoft was a monopolist in the relevant 
market comprising Intel-compatible personal computer operating systems. The 
government reasoned that buyers of Intel-compatible personal computers have no 
substitutes for operating systems designed to work on those systems. Microsoft's 
share of shipments of Intel-based personal computer operating systems has been 
90 percent or more in recent years. 
The government also argued that another operating system would be hard-
pressed to displace Windows directly. IBM was reported to have spent more than 
$1 billion to develop, test, and market its <rs type="software">OS/2</rs> operating system as an alternative 
to Windows (Gilbert, 1998). The new operating system was a commercial failure, in 
part because IBM could not overcome the chicken-and-egg problem that arises 
from "network effects," whereby the demand for a product increases with the 
number of other users of the product or with the number of complementary goods 
and services for that product. Specifically, because of switching costs and consum-
ers' desires for a variety of applications programs, an operating system cannot gain 
widespread acceptance until it has a large set of available applications. But because 
of economies of scale and sunk costs in software development, applications pro-
grammers do not want to write to an operating system unless there is a large base 
of users. The government labeled this problem the "applications barrier to entry." 
Professor Richard Schmalensee, Microsoft's chief economics expert at trial, 
countered that competition in the personal computer software market was among 
"platforms," not operating systems. 2 A platform is a set of software interfaces to 
which programmers can write applications such as spreadsheets or schedulers. 
Platforms include operating systems such as the <rs type="software">Mac OS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-24" type="creator">Sun</rs> <rs id="software-24" type="software">Solaris</rs>, and <rs type="software">Linux</rs>, 
and various forms of middleware including web server/browser software, <rs type="software">Lotus 
Notes</rs>, and <rs corresp="#software-27" type="creator">Sun</rs>'s <rs id="software-27" type="software">Java</rs>, that are intermediate between operating systems and desk-
top applications. Schmalensee argued that Microsoft faced significant competition 
from existing and future software platforms, any one of which could emerge as the 
new standard for desktop computing. 
Schmalensee also asserted that in high-technology markets traditional mea-
sures of market share provide misleading assessments of the degree of competition. 
Markets with significant network effects, technological progress, and production 
economies of scale can exhibit catastrophic entry, whereby one product dominates 
the market until another product is sufficiently superior that it becomes the new </p>

<p>2 Schmalensee's testimony in U.S. v. Microsoft on January 13, 1999, available at ͗http://www.microsoft. 
com/presspass/trial/schmal/III.asp͘. </p>



<p>network bandwagon. Rivalry in such markets can take the form of competition 
to become a dominant firm-competition for the market, rather than competi-
tion within the market. Thus, computer software markets may be characterized 
by a succession of temporary monopolies (although multiple firms can prosper 
simultaneously if there is strong product differentiation or cross-supplier product 
compatibility). 
To a large extent the government and Microsoft agreed about the potential for 
technical change and catastrophic entry in the software industry. However, the 
government asserted that Microsoft preserved its monopoly by using exclusionary 
and predatory tactics to block catastrophic entry, while Microsoft claimed that it was 
just competing in the face of huge forces of change in the industry. 
Another argument raised by Schmalensee was that Microsoft did not behave 
like a firm with monopoly power. Working backward from an estimate of the 
elasticity of demand for personal computers, he calculated that the monopoly price 
of Windows should have been at least 16 times the price actually charged (see also 
Reddy et al., 1999). He attributed the difference to platform competition ignored 
by the government. 
Professor Franklin Fisher was one of the government's expert witnesses and 
Professor Daniel Rubinfeld was the U.S. Department of Justice's chief economist 
during most of the trial. They argued that Microsoft's prices were consistent with 
long-run monopoly pricing once one takes into account factors that encourage 
Microsoft to restrain its prices, such as the value of growing its installed base, raising 
demand for complementary products, and discouraging software pirating (Fisher 
and Rubinfeld, 2000, pp. 13-14). 3 Moreover, they argued that the relatively low 
price charged to personal computer manufacturers for Windows licenses could 
represent compensation for Microsoft's onerous contract restrictions. 
Fundamentally, the difference between the government's characterization of 
Microsoft's market power and Microsoft's position is that the government consid-
ered Microsoft a monopolist that faced limited potential competition from other 
platforms, whereas Microsoft saw the market as already invigorated with significant 
actual platform competition. It appears clear to us that, largely because of network 
effects and the applications barrier to entry, Microsoft did possess significant 
market power. Microsoft certainly had the ability to raise prices significantly above 
marginal costs. Indeed, Microsoft possessed the ability to raise prices significantly 
above long-run average costs, as suggested by the large multiple of Microsoft's 
market value to the cost of its asset base. 
This conclusion does not prove that Microsoft used its market power to 
disadvantage consumers. The possession of market power is in itself not objection-</p>

<p>3 Fisher and Rubinfeld (2000, p. 13-14) also reject Schmalensee's elasticity calculation as irrelevant to 
the determination of monopoly power: "Since Microsoft's marginal cost is essentially zero, the short-run 
profit-maximizing action for the firm is to price at the point where the elasticity of demand that it faces 
is unity. That is true whether or not Microsoft has market power." While correct, this observation does 
not refute Schmalensee's point. A profit-maximizing firm responds to its perceived, or firm-specific, 
demand elasticity. In the presence of competition, which Schmalensee asserts exists, inelastic market 
demand is consistent with elastic firm-specific demand, and it is the latter that constrains prices. </p>

<p>An Economist's Guide to U.S. v. Microsoft 29 </p>

<p>able under antitrust policy (for example, U.S. Department of Justice, 1995, 
sec. 2.2). Indeed, it would not make economic sense to punish a firm that possesses 
market power solely as a consequence of its having developed a superior product, 
because doing so would erode the incentives for innovation. We return to the issue 
of whether Microsoft abused its market power below. 
In addition to creating substantial market power for Microsoft, the applica-
tions barrier to entry was central to the government's theory of why Microsoft took 
the actions it did with respect to browsers and <rs type="software">Java</rs>. According to the government, 
Microsoft had incentives to work hard to protect that barrier by ensuring that other 
operating systems could not share a common set of applications through middle-
ware. The reason middleware, such as <rs type="software">Java</rs> or a web browser, is a threat to Microsoft 
in a way that full operating systems are not is the following. If a user were to adopt 
an operating system other than Windows, the user would have to forego the large base 
of Windows applications. Thus, an operating systems entrant either has to offer 
consumers much lower value or has to incur large sunk costs to develop (or subsidize) 
a wide range of applications programs before there is a large user base to purchase 
them. Middleware written on top of <rs type="software">Windows</rs> would not suffer from this problem. 
Users could adopt the middleware and still make use of the large number of programs 
that run on Windows. Hence, middleware that offered useful new features to a wide 
range of users would have the potential to become widely adopted, which would then 
make it attractive for applications programmers to write to it. As this happened, new 
applications would not be associated with a particular operating system, which would 
reduce the applications barrier to entry for operating systems. 
Evans and Schmalensee (2000a, pp. 62-63) argued that the government's claim 
that there were high barriers to entry but that middleware could overcome them was 
internally inconsistent. We do not see any inconsistency in the position that middle-
ware was a significant crack in the armor of what would otherwise be a strong 
applications barrier to entry and that Microsoft attempted to patch that crack. 
Hall and Hall (1999, p. 25) argued that if the threat of software piracy or other 
factors unrelated to the extent of competition drove Microsoft's operating system 
pricing decisions-as Fisher and Rubinfeld assert-then Microsoft's challenged 
conduct might have no influence on the equilibrium price. Consequently, Mi-
crosoft would not have anticompetitive incentives. This argument, however, ignores 
the possibility that, absent the challenged conduct, the strength of competition 
could have grown to limit Microsoft's market power. The existence of significant 
market power, even if in the short run constrained by factors other than competi-
tion, can provide stimulus for Microsoft to engage in conduct intended to protect 
that market power in the long run. </p>

<p>A Closer Look at Allegedly Harmful Conduct </p>

<p>The government alleged two sets of closely related mechanisms by which 
Microsoft's practices weakened competition and harmed consumers: exclusionary 
behavior and several types of predatory behavior. </p>



<p>Exclusionary Behavior 
Exclusionary behavior entails denying rivals access to some resource or set of 
consumers in order to raise the rivals' costs and weaken their ability to compete (for 
example, Salop and Scheffman, 1987). The government charged that Microsoft 
used several types of contractual arrangements that tended to exclude competitors 
(U.S. v. Microsoft, 1998, para. 75-102). One set of arrangements was with online and 
Internet service providers, such as America Online and AT&amp;T Worldnet, in which 
Microsoft agreed to include a feature in its operating system that made it easy for 
a user to establish an account with a service provider, but only if the service provider 
agreed to deny most or all of its subscribers a choice of Internet browser. 4 A second 
set of agreements was made with personal computer manufacturers, under which 
the manufacturers could neither remove the <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> icon nor feature a 
rival browser more prominently than <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>. Finally, in a third set of 
agreements, Microsoft offered Internet content providers preferential, no-cost 
placement on the <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> "channel bar" in return for their agreement to 
promote <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> as their browser of choice, not to accept compensation 
for featuring their content on Netscape's browser, or to customize their content so 
that it was more attractive when accessed using <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> (U.S. v. Microsoft, 
2000b). 
The traditional "Chicago" view of exclusionary contracts and exclusive dealing 
arrangements is that they must promote efficiency because the buyers in these 
transactions would not agree to contracts that made themselves worse off (Bork, 
1978, p. 309). There is, however, a fundamental flaw in this argument: a buyer may 
agree to an exclusive contract without taking into account harm to third parties. A 
buyer who accounts for only a small fraction of industry purchases has little reason 
to believe that its individual decisions affect the overall degree of competition in a 
market. But if a large number of buyers accept inducements to deal exclusively with 
a single supplier, the overall effect can be to reduce competition to the detriment 
of consumers (Rasmussen, Ramseyer and Wiley, 1991). This analysis applies with 
even greater force when a seller with market power can strategically price discrim-
inate and bargain sequentially with buyers (Segal and Whinston, 2000). A related 
argument holds even with a single buyer if the bargaining takes place before other 
competitors have arrived. By signing a long-term exclusive dealing agreement with 
penalty clauses, the buyer and incumbent seller can force an efficient entrant to 
compensate the buyer for breaking the agreement. In this way, the buyer and 
incumbent seller can appropriate some of the benefits from entry in the form of 
higher profits for themselves (Aghion and Bolton, 1987). 
In many cases, exclusionary practices that raise rivals' costs will lower economic </p>

<p>4 Some authors have argued that America Online wanted an exclusive arrangement to distribute a single 
browser to its customers and that Microsoft merely won the bidding to supply America Online (for 
example, Cass and Hylton, 1999). Moreover, Evans and Schmalensee (2000b) claim that America 
Online is so large that this outcome alone is enough to explain Internet Explorer's dominant market 
share. Even if these statements are accurate, they still do not explain Microsoft's conduct with respect 
to other Internet and online service providers. </p>

<p>Richard J. Gilbert and Michael L. Katz 31 </p>

<p>welfare. However, there are circumstances under which such practices can increase 
efficiency and consumer welfare. For example, raising an inefficient supplier's costs 
can increase total surplus by shifting share to more efficient producers (Katz and 
Shapiro, 1985). And, as discussed below, elimination of a rival may promote 
innovation in some circumstances. Moreover, exclusive dealing that raises distribu-
tion costs for other manufacturers may also support efficient relationship-specific 
investments by the parties entering into the exclusive contract. The net welfare 
effects can be positive or negative (Segal and Whinston, 1998; Gilbert, 2000). Given 
these mixed theoretical predictions about the welfare effects of exclusive dealing, 
antitrust analysis must focus on the institutional details of the specific practices at 
issue in a given case to determine their effects. 
Microsoft defended its contracts on the grounds that they were in force when 
Internet Explorer accounted for only a small share of browser usage and that the 
contracts enabled Microsoft to build share rapidly to become a more formidable 
competitor to Netscape. 5 By describing Microsoft as if it consisted only of a 
fledgling browser striving to compete against established Netscape, this defense 
sidesteps the fact that Microsoft possessed considerable market power in personal 
computer operating systems. The question is whether Microsoft used this market 
power, in combination with exclusionary practices, to hobble a potential compet-
itor to the detriment of consumers. 
Moreover, whatever the theoretical arguments about exclusive contracts in 
general, in this specific case there is little reason to believe that most of these 
contracts promoted efficiency. Microsoft presented no evidence, and we are un-
aware of any evidence, that contracts with online and Internet service providers 
promoted relationship-specific investments. 6 Instead, the main consequence was to 
disadvantage Netscape and other browser competitors. Microsoft asserted that its 
requirements that personal computer manufacturers not remove the <rs type="software">Internet 
Explorer</rs> icon and not feature a rival browser more prominently than <rs type="software">Internet 
Explorer</rs> were justified as promoting a standard <rs type="software">Windows</rs> "look and feel." However, 
the government responded that Microsoft's actions belied this claim, because 
Microsoft permitted personal computer manufacturers to modify the Windows 
desktop when doing so did not promote a competing browser (U.S. v. Microsoft, 
1999, Section V.C). 
In contrast, Microsoft's contracts with Internet content providers had plausible 
efficiency benefits. Microsoft offered favorable placement on the <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> 
channel bar to Internet content providers who designed their content to favor 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>. This arrangement might have generated incentives for these </p>

<p>5 Direct testimony of Cameron Myhrvold in U.S. v. Microsoft, ͗http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/ 
trial/mswitness/myhrvold/myhrvold.asp͘. Myhrvold was a vice-president at Microsoft responsible for 
business relationships with Internet service providers. 
6 Schmalensee (1999, p. 226) pointed to Microsoft's investment in the Windows feature that made it easy 
for a user to establish an account with an online or Internet service provider. However, this investment 
was not specific to any given service provider and thus exclusive arrangements appear unnecessary to 
support such investment. </p>



<p>firms to make complementary investments with Microsoft. Indeed, Judge Jackson 
concluded the contracts with Internet content providers were not anticompetitive. </p>

<p>Predatory Conduct 
Predatory behavior typically involves an initial stage during which a firm 
offers a product at an unprofitably low price as a means of driving rivals from 
the market and facilitating the later exercise of market power. The distinction 
between exclusionary and predatory practices, while useful for organizing dis-
cussion, can be blurred. To the extent that Microsoft sacrificed short-run profits 
to obtain exclusionary contracts and thus to reduce Netscape's long-run com-
petitive threat, an exclusionary contract can be viewed as a form of predation. 
Conversely, by denying a rival sales that are necessary to realize increasing 
returns, predatory behavior can raise the rival's costs and thus look like exclu-
sionary behavior. 
Judges, lawyers, and economists have struggled to distinguish conduct that is 
predatory from that which is vigorously competitive. For example, Areeda and 
Turner (1975) proposed a rule that predatory conduct occurs if a firm prices below 
its average variable cost of production. However, such a rule may afford too much 
latitude for pricing that has predatory effects in industries like software, where 
average variable costs of production are close to zero. At the same time, the rule 
may provide too little scope for firms to use low prices as promotional investments, 
particularly in markets with network effects (for a preliminary analysis, see Farrell 
and Katz, 1999). 
A more general definition of predation, proposed by Ordover and Willig 
(1981), is any business strategy that is profitable only because of the long-run 
benefits of eliminating one or more competitors. This definition sensibly captures 
anticompetitive conduct-including nonprice conduct-that would harm compe-
tition yet would not be deemed predatory under the cost-based Areeda-Turner test. 
However, the meaning of eliminating a competitor may not be a precise concept in 
a market with network effects (Farrell and Katz, 1999). Moreover, the Ordover-
Willig definition should be modified to account for the fact that consumers and 
efficiency can be harmed when the prey is weakened, even if it is not eliminated. 
In a typical predation case, the plaintiff claims that the defendant sacrificed 
short-run profits from sales of a product to eliminate competition and subsequently 
raise prices for that product in the long run. Here, however, the government asserted 
that Microsoft sacrificed browser profits in the short run primarily to preserve its 
operating system monopoly in the long run. 
At first glance, predation against a complementary product might appear 
puzzling. According to the "one monopoly rent" argument, a monopolist would 
never engage in predation against a competitively supplied complementary 
product. To see why, suppose that each customer is willing to pay $100 for a 
package consisting of products A and B; in the Microsoft case, think of these as 
an operating system and a web browser. Suppose that firm M is the monopoly 
supplier of product A. In the first case, the complementary product B is supplied 
competitively at a price equal to its marginal cost of, say, $10. As a result, the </p>

<p>An Economist's Guide to U.S. v. Microsoft 33 </p>

<p>monopolist can charge $90 (ϭ $100 -$10) for its product A. Now, suppose that 
the monopolist forces consumers to purchase a bundle consisting of A and B. 
Consumers still would pay at most $100 for the bundle, the marginal cost of 
product B would still be $10, and the monopolist would earn $90 from selling 
A. In other words, "extending" its monopoly from A to both A and B would not 
increase the firm's profits. 
There are two reasons why the "one monopoly rent" argument does not apply 
to Microsoft's situation. First, as we discuss below, <rs corresp="#software-42" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-42" type="software">Navigator</rs> initially was 
priced significantly above marginal cost and, consequently, Microsoft had incen-
tives to influence competition in the browser market. Second, the "one monopoly 
rent" argument does not address the fact that predation against complementary 
product B may affect the threat of entry faced by product A. Aron and Wildman 
(1999), Carlton and Waldman (2000), and Whinston (1990) offer models of 
bundling to deter entry. 
The government alleged that Microsoft tried to keep <rs corresp="#software-43" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-43" type="software">Navigator</rs> from 
becoming well established as a browser so that it could not evolve into an operating 
system competitor. The government also alleged that Microsoft wanted to block 
<rs type="software">Navigator</rs> as a distribution vehicle for <rs type="software">Java</rs>, as well as undermine <rs type="software">Java</rs> directly, 
because the widespread deployment of <rs type="software">Java</rs> as a programming language that was 
independent of the underlying operating system threatened to reduce the appli-
cations barrier to entry in operating systems. The government attacked several 
Microsoft practices as predatory. 
Pricing Internet Explorer Below Cost. <rs corresp="#software-48" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> gave <rs id="software-48" type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> away for 
free and paid Apple to use its browser. The government argued that Microsoft's 
actions were predatory because they could be profitable only after taking into 
account benefits to Microsoft from the elimination of competition (Fisher and 
Rubinfeld, 2000, p. 20). Microsoft responded that the profitability of its actions did 
not depend on excluding competition from Netscape. Microsoft claimed that wide 
distribution of Internet Explorer at a zero price made business sense because it 
made personal computers more attractive and thus increased the sales of its 
Windows operating system and other software. Microsoft also said that giving away 
its browser product for free was a valid business model, one followed by many 
software companies, because it would generate future revenues. For example, a free 
browser could help Microsoft establish an Internet portal on which it could sell 
advertising. 
On the surface, Microsoft's position fits the model of Farrell and Katz (2000). 
In that model, product A is monopolized by firm M and the market for comple-
mentary product B is imperfectly competitive. By integrating into the supply of 
product B, firm M can engage in a "squeeze," where it sets the quality-adjusted price 
of its variant of product B lower than would a stand-alone supplier. The squeeze can 
force independent suppliers to charge lower quality-adjusted prices for their variants of 
product B and thus allow firm M to earn greater profits from the sale of comple-
mentary product A. In this model, firm M neither extends its monopoly nor acts in 
a predatory fashion, although independent suppliers could be expected to accuse </p>



<p>it of doing so. Instead, firm M lets the most efficient supplier of component B make 
sales, and firm M takes its profits by charging higher prices for component A. 7 
If Microsoft was concerned with increasing the value of its personal computer 
platform, however, it should have supported any well-made browser product, 
without regard to whether the browser was supplied by Microsoft or by a rival. Trial 
evidence submitted by the government suggested that Microsoft did not want to 
support a rival browser, no matter how good the product might be, and was mainly 
concerned with reducing <rs corresp="#software-49" type="creator">Netscape</rs>'s <rs id="software-49" type="software">Navigator</rs> sales. The government hauled out 
a stack of Microsoft e-mails to argue that Microsoft intended to quash Netscape. 
The government also showed that Microsoft had carried out studies of the impact 
on Netscape's revenues of giving <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> away for free, 8 and a govern-
ment witness testified that Paul Maritz (a senior Microsoft executive) informed him 
that Microsoft's Internet strategy was "to cut off Netscape's air supply, . . . by giving 
away free browsers, Microsoft was going to keep Netscape from getting off the 
ground." 9 
The government also noted that, if Microsoft's strategy of giving away Internet 
Explorer for free was based on promoting sales of its software products, that 
rationale could not explain why Microsoft paid Apple to take its browser. To the 
extent that Microsoft was motivated by sales of software such as <rs type="software">Office</rs> for the 
Macintosh, these concerns would be best served by encouraging Apple to use the 
best browser. The government also did not accept Microsoft's claims that its 
browser distribution strategy was profitable because it promoted the sale of web 
services, such as a portal site. 
Tying and Bundling. To the government, the "integration" of <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> 
with <rs id="software-53" type="software">Windows</rs> <rs corresp="#software-53" type="version-number">95</rs> and later versions of the operating system was little different from 
the contractual bundling of separate products. The government alleged that Mi-
crosoft bundled the operating system and browser as a way to protect its existing 
operating system monopoly by blocking <rs corresp="#software-54" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-54" type="software">Navigator</rs> from growing into a 
platform competitor. The government's main concern was not that Microsoft 
offered an integrated product that combined <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> and <rs type="software">Windows</rs>, but 
rather that Microsoft refused to offer customers the option of taking Windows 
without the browser (Fisher and Rubinfeld, 2000, p. 23). Under the government's 
theory, the bundling was predatory rather than exclusionary. Consumers with 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> already loaded on their personal computers still could install and 
make use of <rs type="software">Navigator</rs>. However, the incremental cost to such customers of using 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> was zero. 
Microsoft responded to the government's bundling charge by contending that </p>

<p>7 Although not predatory, a squeeze may lower welfare. It can do so by allowing firm M to appropriate 
the benefits of innovation undertaken by independent suppliers of B, thus reducing their incentives to 
innovate. 
8 These included November 27, 1996, and November 16, 1998, e-mails from A. Nehru detailing 
Netscape's revenue sources, and a September 23, 1996, e-mail from B. Akerlind stating: "Netscape can 
no longer make any money on the browser in the OEM [original equipment manufacturer] market." 
9 Trial transcript, U.S. v. Microsoft, November 9, 1999 (p.m. session), available at ͗http://www.microsoft. 
com/presspass/trial/transcripts/nov98/11-09-pm.asp͘. </p>

<p>Richard J. Gilbert and Michael L. Katz 35 </p>

<p>the browser was an integral component of the operating system and that bundling 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> with the operating system was a product improvement no differ-
ent from including a file management program with the operating system. More-
over, Microsoft argued, even if the operating system and browser were distinct 
products, there are plausible efficiency advantages from bundling in the form of 
lower distribution and transactions costs. Microsoft also noted that other operating 
system vendors, such as BeOS, Linux, and Sun, bundled browsers with their 
operating systems. 
Polluting the Java Language. Microsoft developed a version of <rs type="software">Java</rs> that was 
optimized for <rs type="software">Windows</rs> and encouraged programmers to write applications for this 
version. The government alleged that Microsoft tried to "pollute" <rs type="software">Java</rs> so that it 
would not become a standardized language that would run equally well on all 
operating systems. Microsoft's response was that it was merely optimizing <rs type="software">Java</rs> to 
exploit the advanced features of <rs type="software">Windows</rs>, to the benefit of consumers. 10 
According to the government, Microsoft's <rs type="software">Java</rs> strategy was predatory because 
Microsoft was incurring unnecessary costs in the short run to undermine the 
middleware threat posed by a widely deployed programming language that was 
independent of the underlying operating system. Judge Jackson agreed with the 
government in finding that Microsoft acted in ways that did not support its 
efficiency arguments, but were instead intended to undermine the portability of 
<rs type="software">Java</rs>. Judge Jackson concluded that: Microsoft designed its <rs type="software">Java</rs> developer tools to 
encourage developers to write applications using certain abbreviations that could 
only be executed properly by Microsoft's version of the <rs type="software">Java</rs> environment for 
<rs type="software">Windows</rs>; Microsoft refused to incorporate as standard components certain Java 
developments that would enhance portability in the version of <rs type="software">Java</rs> that it shipped 
with <rs id="software-72" type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> <rs corresp="#software-72" type="version-number">4.0</rs>; and Gates pressured Intel not to share its work on a 
high-performance Java virtual machine with Sun or Netscape or to allow Netscape 
to include the Intel product with <rs type="software">Navigator</rs>. In addition, Judge Jackson found that 
Microsoft pressured software vendors, such as the developer of the <rs type="software">RealNetworks</rs> 
multimedia player, to rely on <rs type="software">Windows</rs>-specific <rs type="software">Java</rs> technology rather than more 
portable <rs type="software">Java</rs> implementations in their products (U.S. v. Microsoft, 2000b, Section 
VI.) Lemley and McGowan (1998) also point out Microsoft's opposition to certify-
ing Java as an international standard. </p>

<p>Did Microsoft Neutralize the Threat of Navigator/Java 
Competition? </p>

<p>The trial record offers ample evidence that Microsoft intended to eliminate 
the middleware threat to <rs type="software">Windows</rs> posed by the combination of <rs corresp="#software-79" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-79" type="software">Navigator</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Java</rs>. Has Microsoft succeeded in annihilating browser competition? Probably </p>

<p>10 For an example of this argument, see testimony of Richard Schmalensee at U.S. v. Microsoft, Section 
III, available at ͗http://www.microsoft.com/presspass/trial/schmal/III.asp͘, at para. 149. </p>



<p>not. During the Microsoft trial, America Online purchased Netscape for approxi-
mately $4 billion in stock, so that Netscape is now a subsidiary of, and has the 
backing of, the world's largest online service provider. 
Yet by tipping the market in favor of <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>, Microsoft's conduct 
undermined the ability of <rs corresp="#software-82" type="creator">Netscape</rs> <rs id="software-82" type="software">Navigator</rs> to attract software developers to write 
applications that will run in the Netscape/Java environment. According to Ad-
Knowledge, Inc., <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>'s share of monthly browser usage increased 
from 20 percent in January 1997 to more than 50 percent by August 1998, and 
other data suggest it has increased since 1998. 11 Judge Jackson concluded that 
Microsoft's anticompetitive conduct contributed to Netscape's decision not to do 
the engineering work necessary to continue bundling up-to-date "<rs type="software">Java</rs> Virtual 
Machines"-the programs that interpret <rs type="software">Java</rs> for a particular operating system-
that would be compliant with Sun's standards in future versions of Navigator (U.S. 
v. Microsoft, 2000b, at para. 397). </p>

<p>Did Microsoft Harm Consumers? </p>

<p>The courts have long recognized that antitrust policy is concerned with harm 
to competition, not harm to competitors, because competitors can be casualties of 
aggressive competition that benefits consumers and/or increases efficiency. Did 
Microsoft harm consumers in the sense that they would have faced lower prices-
adjusted for the quality and variety of the available products-in the absence of 
Microsoft's challenged conduct? 
Assessment of consumer harm from predation is difficult because predation 
can benefit consumers in the short run while harming them in the long run. For 
example, consumers were not clearly worse off in the short run as the result of 
Microsoft's <rs type="software">Java</rs> development, and some consumers may have been better off 
because Microsoft's implementation of the <rs type="software">Java</rs> virtual machine provided advan-
tages for <rs type="software">Windows</rs> users ("Performance Tests: Compatibility," 1998). 
However, what might appear to be an obvious short-term consumer benefit of 
Microsoft's allegedly predatory behavior-namely, receiving a free copy of <rs type="software">Internet 
Explorer</rs> bundled with <rs type="software">Windows</rs> rather than paying for a browser-might be 
illusory. The availability of free browsers may have allowed Microsoft to raise (or avoid 
lowering) the price of <rs type="software">Windows</rs>. To the extent that Microsoft internalized the benefits </p>

<p>11 For movement of browser market shares from 1997 to 1998, see ͗http://www.usdoj.gov/atr/cases/ 
exhibits/5.pdf͘. Statmarket claims that <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs>'s share of browser usage in June 2000 was 
more than 86 percent (Scott Clark, "Browser Statistics Look Good for IE," June 27, 2000, ͗http:// 
www.internetnews.com/wd-news/article/0,,10_403661,00.html͘. Positive Support Review estimated In-
ternet Explorer's market share at about 76 percent in July 2000, with Netscape at about 15 percent (see 
͗http://www.psrinc.com/MSExplorer.htm͘). BrowserWatch reported that 58.7 percent of the hits on its 
website in July 2000 were from Internet surfers using <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> and 26.1 percent of the hits were 
from surfers using Netscape Navigator, as reported at ͗http://browserwatch.internet.com/stats/stats. 
html͘. </p>

<p>An Economist's Guide to U.S. v. Microsoft 37 </p>

<p>from free browsers through the <rs type="software">Windows</rs> price, the short-run consumer benefits 
from giving away Internet Explorer and bundling it with <rs type="software">Windows</rs> were limited. 
The main thrust of the government's case was that, in the long run, consumers 
would suffer from reduced competition among both browsers and operating 
systems. The result could be higher prices in the long run, or a reduction of 
investment in R&amp;D and product development that reduced or degraded the set of 
available products. 
The need to consider long-run effects of Microsoft's actions raises a number of 
difficulties. First, there is the matter of predicting what will happen in a market 
subject to rapid technological change. One cannot be certain that the combination 
of alternative browsers and a <rs type="software">Java</rs> programming language that was independent of 
the underlying programming language would have emerged as a serious platform 
competitor absent Microsoft's challenged conduct. For example, one obstacle to 
the widespread acceptance of <rs type="software">Java</rs> is the additional execution time required to 
translate the <rs type="software">Java</rs> code. Clearly, however, Microsoft perceived that such competi-
tion was possible. 
Second, the link between the degree of competition and the degree of 
innovation is complex. Certain theoretical arguments support the conclusion that 
large firm size and high market share are conducive to R&amp;D investment, because a 
firm in such a market can amortize the fixed costs of the R&amp;D and appropriate most 
of the R&amp;D's benefits. Catastrophic entry, combined with large investment demands, 
can necessitate concentrated markets as a means to achieve the returns necessary to 
motivate large investments that must be recouped over relatively short periods of 
time before the dawning of the next technological revolution. On the other hand, 
as Sir John Hicks (1935, p. 8) wrote: "The best of all monopoly profits is a quiet 
life." There is considerable anecdotal evidence that competitive market structures 
are more innovative than are protected monopolies, although econometric evidence 
on the general linkage between concentration and innovation is inconclusive. 
While it is impossible to make definitive statements about the linkage between 
market structure and innovation in general, competition has stimulated innovation 
in browsers and operating systems. For example, Evans and Schmalensee (2000a, 
pp. 45-46) concluded that, by increasing competition in the browser market, 
"Microsoft's actions speeded innovation in Web-browsing software and left consum-
ers with the choice of two first-rate browsers instead of one." Moreover, Microsoft 
appears to have accelerated the introduction of <rs id="software-103" type="software">DOS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-103" type="version-number">5.0</rs> in response to competi-
tion from <rs type="software">DR-DOS</rs> and to have accelerated the development of <rs type="software">Windows</rs> in 
response to competition from Apple and OS/2. Further, the continuing develop-
ment of Apple's operating system suggests that significant innovation by firms with 
much smaller sales than Microsoft is feasible. 
A third difficulty in assessing the long-run consequences of Microsoft's con-
duct is that, even if one has found there would be greater competition and more 
innovation absent Microsoft's actions, as a matter of theory the linkage between 
innovation and welfare is ambiguous. For example, firms may enter rent-seeking 
races in which they invest more than the socially efficient amounts in R&amp;D (for a 
review of the theoretical literature on R&amp;D competition, see Reinganum, 1989). As </p>



<p>an empirical matter, however, private incentives for R&amp;D typically are much lower 
than the social benefits of the R&amp;D because private firms typically are unable to 
appropriate all of the benefits that their R&amp;D generates for the economy (Griliches, 
1992; Jones and Williams, 1998). Certainly, no evidence of socially excessive R&amp;D 
investment was presented at trial. 
It appears to us that if the record in the case had consisted solely of the fact that 
Microsoft took the actions the government alleged to be predatory-that is, giving 
<rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> away for free, bundling <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> with <rs type="software">Windows</rs>, and 
creating a non-standard implementation of <rs type="software">Java</rs>-Microsoft could have made a 
plausible case that it was engaged in a non-predatory squeeze of Netscape, was 
improving <rs type="software">Java</rs>, and its conduct did not harm consumers. 
There are, however, two significant problems with this interpretation of the 
record. First, there is significant evidence that Microsoft took actions for the 
explicit purpose of harming competition. Economists are often loath to endorse an 
intent-based approach to evaluating firm behavior because managers often use 
florid language to describe their actions in memoranda ("kill the competition") 
and even ill-intended actions may not harm consumers in some cases. We fully 
agree that caution is warranted in interpreting such evidence. However, when there 
is a clear economic rationale that certain types of conduct can harm competition 
and lead to higher prices, and there is evidence that managerial intent was to harm 
competitors, it can be appropriate to use this evidence to sort harmful from 
innocent behavior. Of course, one has to be sensitive to the possibility that exec-
utives will strategically write memoranda that put soothing spins on their descrip-
tions of firm conduct. 
Second, in addition to the allegedly predatory actions, Microsoft undertook a 
variety of exclusionary tactics that cannot be explained as procompetitive "squeezes" 
on Netscape. If Microsoft had been trying to maximize its returns on <rs type="software">Windows</rs> by 
ensuring that consumers enjoyed maximal benefits from complementary browsers, 
it would not have worked so hard to make it difficult for consumers to use 
non-Microsoft browsers. In particular, Microsoft would not have taken measures to 
discourage consumers from using Netscape's browser. 
Judge Jackson concluded that Microsoft's contracts with Internet and online 
service providers and with computer manufacturers were exclusionary and contrib-
uted to a verdict of monopolization. However, he also found that because the 
contracts did not completely foreclose competition from Netscape and other 
browsers, the contracts were not illegal in and of themselves. Judge Jackson's 
finding notwithstanding, imposing costs on competitors can harm consumers even 
if the competitors are not completely driven from the market. Netscape was forced 
to pursue other distribution alternatives to compensate for Microsoft's restrictive 
arrangements, thereby increasing Netscape's costs of distributing its browser to 
consumers. At least some consumers were harmed because they were unable to 
obtain their preferred product or they incurred greater costs to do so (for example, 
time spent downloading the product) as the result of Microsoft's practices. The 
contracts do not appear to have contributed to efficiencies that would offset these 
harms. Moreover, in the presence of network effects, a lower current market share </p>

<p>Richard J. Gilbert and Michael L. Katz 39 </p>

<p>can have negative feedback effects on future sales and thus weaken incentives for 
product improvements and future competition. 
Neither the government nor Microsoft offered numerical projections of wel-
fare effects. Our review of the case suggests the following overall effects. In the 
short run, Microsoft's allegedly predatory actions of developing a <rs type="software">Windows</rs>-
optimized version of <rs type="software">Java</rs>, giving <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> away for free, and bundling 
Internet Explorer with Windows probably benefited consumers directly. In addi-
tion, consumers benefited from the latter two actions because they forced Netscape 
to make its browser available for free. The short-run consumer gains from a free or 
bundled browser may have been limited, however, because a zero browser price 
may have enabled Microsoft to maintain the price of <rs type="software">Windows</rs> at a higher level than 
it otherwise would have. In the short run, Microsoft's contracts with personal 
computer manufacturers and online service providers imposed costs on consumers 
who preferred the Netscape browser. In the long run, consumers were likely 
harmed because much of Microsoft's challenged conduct reduced the probability 
that Netscape/Java would emerge as a platform competitor. The contracts with 
Internet content providers, however, had potential efficiency benefits. </p>

<p>Remedies </p>

<p>On April 3, 2000, Judge Jackson found Microsoft guilty of violating the 
Sherman Act (U.S. v. Microsoft, 2000c). The government and Microsoft then pro-
posed remedies. Both parties proposed conduct remedies that would constrain 
certain aspects of Microsoft's behavior, such as the use of exclusive contracts and 
prohibitions on removing the <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> icon. The government proposed 
more extensive conduct remedies than did Microsoft, as well as a structural dives-
titure of the company into two parts. One part would receive the <rs type="software">Windows</rs> oper-
ating system; the other would receive the applications programs and all other 
Microsoft lines of business. Both parts would get intellectual property rights to the 
Internet Explorer browser, but the operating systems company would be limited in 
its ability to develop, license, or distribute modified or derivative versions of the 
browser (U.S. v. Microsoft, 2000a, sec. 1.c). 
From an efficiency perspective, remedies should stop a firm that has engaged 
in anticompetitive conduct from continuing to do so and should deter that firm 
and others from engaging in similar anticompetitive conduct in the future. At the 
same time, remedies should not introduce large administrative costs, deter efficient 
conduct, or create opportunities for firms to engage in costly strategic behavior. 
Judge Jackson found that Microsoft illegally sustained the applications barrier 
to the entry of operating system competitors. Conduct remedies, such as mandatory 
unbundling of <rs type="software">Internet Explorer</rs> from <rs type="software">Windows</rs>, deal directly with Microsoft's 
challenged behavior. However, as experience with the earlier consent decree 
illustrates, conduct remedies can be difficult to enforce and may not be sufficient 
to deter Microsoft from engaging in other behavior that has similar effects. In 
addition, conduct remedies may provide a forum for competitors to challenge </p>



<p>Microsoft's business decisions-including those that might benefit consumers-
with a potentially chilling effect on innovation. 
Compared to conduct requirements, structural remedies typically require less 
regulatory oversight and can be less susceptible to strategic intervention by com-
petitors. But structural remedies may fail if the required structure does not reflect 
an efficient organization of the industry. 
The government's theory was that its proposed structural remedy would invig-
orate competition by encouraging the applications company to port its software to 
other operating systems or to develop its own operating system. In either case, 
Windows would face more vigorous competition. The breakup was also intended to 
encourage the operating system company to assure interoperability with applica-
tions programs from all vendors. More generally, each company would have 
incentives to encourage competition in the market for the complementary product. 
By relying on market forces, the proposed remedy sidesteps the prospect of 
continuing government oversight of Microsoft. It does not order the applications 
division to work with other operating systems vendors. It does not seek to define 
terms like "operating system" and then set up restrictions about what such a system 
can or cannot include. It does not contain permanent line-of-business restrictions 
on the Microsoft offspring. 12 
However, the proposed breakup of a huge company would certainly entail 
substantial direct costs of reorganization. Moreover, the divestiture might well 
impose indirect costs through its effects on the two companies' abilities and 
incentives to cooperate, including cooperation in pricing and product develop-
ment. The concern with respect to pricing is the "double marginalization problem" 
identified by Cournot (1838). Suppose that every consumer of a personal computer 
requires one operating system and one application program (for example, a word 
processor). If the monopoly supplier of the operating system is also the monopoly 
supplier of the application, it will take foregone application sales into account when 
analyzing the effects of an increase in the price of the operating system. But if a 
separate firm sells the application, the operating system monopolist will not count 
lost application sales as a cost and thus has less incentive to restrain price. A similar 
logic applies to pricing the application. Hence, this argument suggests that the sum 
of the operating system and application prices set by an integrated monopolist will 
be lower than the sum of those prices when set separately by two independent firms 
each with significant market power. 
The separation of suppliers of complementary products can have other nefar-
ious effects. The separate operating system and applications companies might not 
have incentives to push new products that require commitments from both the 
operating system and application sides of the business. The introduction of Win-
dows provides a suggestive case study. Microsoft had a strong incentive to design 
and market applications that took advantage of the <rs type="software">Windows</rs> graphical user inter-</p>

<p>12 Many commenters have drawn comparisons between the proposed breakup of Microsoft and the 1984 
breakup of AT&amp;T, but the proposals are actually quite different. The AT&amp;T breakup entailed line-of-
business restrictions that kept the courts heavily involved in the workings of the industry. </p>

<p>An Economist's Guide to U.S. v. Microsoft 41 </p>

<p>face, because Microsoft could internalize benefits from the complementarities 
between Windows and applications. Independent companies, such as Lotus, were 
slower to make the transition to <rs type="software">Windows</rs> for their applications than was Microsoft. 
It is impossible to predict with confidence how splitting Microsoft in two would 
actually work and how large any coordination losses would be. The two companies 
would have incentives to reach agreements to overcome the distortions induced by 
their separate structure, subject to being allowed to do so by the remedy and antitrust 
law generally. More broadly, the hope of the government is that divestiture would 
invigorate competition in both the operating systems and applications markets. If 
stronger competition occurred, it would reduce the double marginalization problem 
and could even reduce the total price of software bundles from current levels. 
Some have argued for a structural remedy that would create immediate 
additional competition in the market for personal computer operating systems by 
breaking Microsoft into an applications company and several competing operating 
systems companies, often referred to as the "Baby Bills." (The friend-of-the-court 
submission, U.S. v. Microsoft, 2000e, is an example.) Such a proposal offers the 
benefit of eliminating, or at least greatly reducing, the operating systems market 
power that was the driving force for anticompetitive conduct. However, this pro-
posal also raises substantial risks of imposing an inefficient market structure be-
cause the efficient number of personal computer operating systems companies is 
unknown. Moreover, the relationship between innovation and market structure is 
not a simple one. If market forces compelled three Baby Bills to remain compatible 
with each other, innovation might be limited by the rigidities inherent in a 
multi-firm effort to preserve standards. Alternatively, a failure among the Baby Bills 
to cooperate on standards could lead to fragmentation and the loss of network 
effects. Finally, there are no clear organizational lines along which to cut the 
operating system company into multiple pieces. 
Financial penalties are another potential remedy for unlawful conduct. Except 
to compensate for harm suffered in its role as a consumer, the government cannot 
pursue monetary damages in civil litigation. But private parties can do so and have 
the added incentive of possibly receiving treble damages. While monetary damages 
have the disadvantage that they do not directly address the conduct at issue, they 
can serve as a deterrent to future conduct that likely would be found to harm 
competition. Moreover, monetary damages create neither large administrative costs 
nor opportunities for strategic behavior (although litigation to obtain such dam-
ages can give rise to both). 
In any event, Judge Jackson accepted the government's proposed remedies-
including the breakup-although he immediately stayed their implementation 
pending appeals (U.S. v. Microsoft, 2000d). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>We find ourselves somewhat torn about remedies. Microsoft took actions that 
appear to have imposed short-run costs on consumers and reduced the long-run </p>



<p>likelihood of platform competition. Thus, we believe that some remedy by the 
antitrust authorities is appropriate. While the competitive dynamics of the software 
industry challenge the ability of economic analysis to make precise and certain 
predictions about competitive effects, the potential welfare effects of business 
practices in these markets are too important to keep antitrust on the sidelines. 
In the light of experience with the earlier consent degree, we are pessimistic 
that a limited conduct remedy would be effective in this case. Structural remedies, 
such as the divestiture remedy proposed by the government and accepted by Judge 
Jackson, may be less subject to gaming, but pose the risk of substantial costs. 
Ironically, in this case, the most effective remedy may be that the government's 
victory eases the way for plaintiffs in private antitrust suits to collect monetary 
damages, which could be sufficient to deter future anticompetitive conduct. Of 
course, at the time of this writing, the results of those suits-and Microsoft's appeal 
of Judge Jackson's decision-remain to be seen. </p>

<p>y We gratefully acknowledge comments and suggestions from Dennis Carlton, Charles Clarke, </p>

<p>Brad De Long, Neil Gandal, Timothy Taylor, Hal Varian, and Michael Waldman. Gilbert 
was Chief Economist at the Antitrust Division of the U.S. Department of Justice from 1993 to 
1995 and consulted for the U.S. Department of Justice in the case. This article is based on 
publicly available information and does not rely on any confidential information. </p>



<p>Richard J. Gilbert and Michael L. Katz 43 </p>







</text></tei>