<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.27.1.3" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">


<p>theories of innovation emphasizing competition and fi rst-mover advantage as the 
theories of innovation emphasizing competition and fi rst-mover advantage as the 
main drivers of innovation, and they directly contradict "Schumpeterian" theories 
main drivers of innovation, and they directly contradict "Schumpeterian" theories 
postulating that government-granted monopolies are crucial to provide incentives 
postulating that government-granted monopolies are crucial to provide incentives 
for innovation. A properly designed patent system might serve to increase innovation 
for innovation. A properly designed patent system might serve to increase innovation 
at a certain time and place -and some patent systems, such as the late-nineteenth 
at a certain time and place -and some patent systems, such as the late-nineteenth 
century German system allowing only process but not fi nal product patents, have 
century German system allowing only process but not fi nal product patents, have 
been associated with rapid innovation. Unfortunately, the political economy of 
been associated with rapid innovation. Unfortunately, the political economy of 
government-operated patent systems indicates that such systems are susceptible to 
government-operated patent systems indicates that such systems are susceptible to 
pressures that cause the ill effects of patents to grow over time. The political economy 
pressures that cause the ill effects of patents to grow over time. The political economy 
pressures tend to benefi t those who own patents and are in a good position to lobby 
pressures tend to benefi t those who own patents and are in a good position to lobby 
for stronger patent protection, but disadvantage current and future innovators as 
for stronger patent protection, but disadvantage current and future innovators as 
well as ultimate consumers. This explains why the political demand for stronger 
well as ultimate consumers. This explains why the political demand for stronger 
patent protection comes from old and stagnant industries and fi rms, not from new 
patent protection comes from old and stagnant industries and fi rms, not from new 
and innovative ones. Our preferred policy solution is to abolish patents entirely and 
and innovative ones. Our preferred policy solution is to abolish patents entirely and 
to fi nd other legislative instruments, less open to lobbying and rent seeking, to foster 
to fi nd other legislative instruments, less open to lobbying and rent seeking, to foster 
innovation when there is clear evidence that laissez-faire undersupplies it. However, 
innovation when there is clear evidence that laissez-faire undersupplies it. However, 
if that policy change seems too large to swallow, we discuss in the conclusion a set 
if that policy change seems too large to swallow, we discuss in the conclusion a set 
of partial reforms that could be implemented as part of an incremental strategy of 
of partial reforms that could be implemented as part of an incremental strategy of 
reducing the harm done by the patent system. 
reducing the harm done by the patent system. </p>

<p>Do Patents Encourage Productivity Growth? </p>

<p>If there is to be any rationale for patent systems, with all their ancillary costs, it 
If there is to be any rationale for patent systems, with all their ancillary costs, it 
must be that they increase innovation and productivity. What is the evidence? 
must be that they increase innovation and productivity. What is the evidence? 
Simply eyeballing the big trends shows that patenting has exploded over the 
Simply eyeballing the big trends shows that patenting has exploded over the 
last decades. In 1983 in the United States, 59,715 patents were issued; by 2003, 
last decades. In 1983 in the United States, 59,715 patents were issued; by 2003, 
189,597 patents were issued; and in 2010, 244,341 new patents were approved. In 
189,597 patents were issued; and in 2010, 244,341 new patents were approved. In 
less than 30 years, the fl ow of patents more than quadrupled. By contrast, neither 
less than 30 years, the fl ow of patents more than quadrupled. By contrast, neither 
innovation nor research and development expenditure nor factor productivity 
innovation nor research and development expenditure nor factor productivity 
have exhibited any particular upward trend. According to the Bureau of Labor 
have exhibited any particular upward trend. According to the Bureau of Labor 
Statistics, annual growth in total factor productivity in the decade 1970 -1979 was 
Statistics, annual growth in total factor productivity in the decade 1970 -1979 was 
about 1.2 percent, while in the decades 1990 -1999 and 2000 -2009 it has been a bit 
about 1.2 percent, while in the decades 1990 -1999 and 2000 -2009 it has been a bit 
below 1 percent. Meanwhile, US research and development expenditure has been 
below 1 percent. Meanwhile, US research and development expenditure has been 
oscillating for more than three decades in a narrow band around 2.5 percent of 
oscillating for more than three decades in a narrow band around 2.5 percent of 
GDP. The recent explosion of patents, in other words, has not brought about any 
GDP. The recent explosion of patents, in other words, has not brought about any 
additional surge in useful innovations and aggregate productivity. In new industries 
additional surge in useful innovations and aggregate productivity. In new industries 
such as biotechnology and software -where innovation was already thriving in their 
such as biotechnology and software -where innovation was already thriving in their 
absence -patents have been introduced without any positive impact on the rate 
absence -patents have been introduced without any positive impact on the rate 
of innovation. The software industry is an important case in point. In a dramatic 
of innovation. The software industry is an important case in point. In a dramatic 
example of judge-made law, software patents became possible for the fi rst time in 
example of judge-made law, software patents became possible for the fi rst time in 
the early 1990s. Bessen and Meurer, in a large body of empirical work culminating 
the early 1990s. Bessen and Meurer, in a large body of empirical work culminating 
in in Patent Failure (2008), have studied the consequences of this experiment and have 
(2008), have studied the consequences of this experiment and have 
concluded that it damaged social welfare. 
concluded that it damaged social welfare. </p>

<p>Miche le Boldrin and David K. Levine 5 </p>

<p>Academic studies have also typically failed to fi nd much of a connection 
Academic studies have also typically failed to fi nd much of a connection 
between patents and innovation. In Boldrin and Levine (2008b), we conducted 
between patents and innovation. In Boldrin and Levine (2008b), we conducted 
a metastudy gathering the 24 studies (including three surveys of earlier empirical 
a metastudy gathering the 24 studies (including three surveys of earlier empirical 
work) we could fi nd in 2006 that examined whether introducing or strengthening 
work) we could fi nd in 2006 that examined whether introducing or strengthening 
patent protection leads to greater innovation. The executive summary states: 
patent protection leads to greater innovation. The executive summary states: 
"[T]hese studies fi nd weak or no evidence that strengthening patent regimes 
"[T]hese studies fi nd weak or no evidence that strengthening patent regimes 
increases innovation; they fi nd evidence that strengthening the patent regime 
increases innovation; they fi nd evidence that strengthening the patent regime 
increases patenting! They also fi nd evidence that, in countries with initially weak 
increases patenting! They also fi nd evidence that, in countries with initially weak 
IP [intellectual property] regimes, strengthening IP increases the fl ow of foreign 
IP [intellectual property] regimes, strengthening IP increases the fl ow of foreign 
investment in sectors where patents are frequently used." Actually, the issue of 
investment in sectors where patents are frequently used." Actually, the issue of 
promoting foreign direct investment, while a well-established empirical conse-
promoting foreign direct investment, while a well-established empirical conse-
quence of strengthening patent regimes, is entirely beside the point of this essay. 
quence of strengthening patent regimes, is entirely beside the point of this essay. 
There are a number of ways to strengthen a country's institutions and infrastruc-
There are a number of ways to strengthen a country's institutions and infrastruc-
ture in a way that would encourage foreign direct investment-and, in any case, 
ture in a way that would encourage foreign direct investment-and, in any case, 
foreign direct investment is not equivalent to innovation. 
foreign direct investment is not equivalent to innovation. 
Our conclusion was in keeping with other studies that have addressed this ques-
Our conclusion was in keeping with other studies that have addressed this ques-
tion. Some studies have failed to fi nd any connection even between changes in 
tion. Some studies have failed to fi nd any connection even between changes in 
the strength of patent law and the amount of patenting, while others fail to fi nd a 
the strength of patent law and the amount of patenting, while others fail to fi nd a 
connection between patents and some measure of innovation or productivity. For 
connection between patents and some measure of innovation or productivity. For 
example, after failing to fi nd a single study claiming that innovation increased as 
example, after failing to fi nd a single study claiming that innovation increased as 
a consequence of the strengthening of US patent protection in the 1980s, Gallini 
a consequence of the strengthening of US patent protection in the 1980s, Gallini  (2002, p. 139) wrote in this journal: "Although it seems plausible that the strength-
(2002, p. 139) wrote in this journal: "Although it seems plausible that the strength-
ening of US patents may have contributed to the rise in patenting over the past 
ening of US patents may have contributed to the rise in patenting over the past 
decade and a half, the connection has proven diffi cult to verify." 
decade and a half, the connection has proven diffi cult to verify." Similarly, Jaffe 
Similarly, Jaffe 
(2000) also examines many studies and concludes: "[D]espite the signifi cance of 
(2000) also examines many studies and concludes: "[D]espite the signifi cance of 
the policy changes and the wide availability of detailed data relating to patenting, 
the policy changes and the wide availability of detailed data relating to patenting, 
robust conclusions regarding the empirical consequences for technological innova-
robust conclusions regarding the empirical consequences for technological innova-
tions of changes in patent policy are few. There is widespread unease that the costs 
tions of changes in patent policy are few. There is widespread unease that the costs 
of stronger patent protection may exceed the benefi ts. Both theoretical and, to a 
of stronger patent protection may exceed the benefi ts. Both theoretical and, to a 
lesser extent, empirical research suggest this possibility." 
lesser extent, empirical research suggest this possibility." </p>

<p>1 1   1 The study by Kanwar and Evanson (2001) illustrates some of the issues that arise in these kinds of studies. 
They have two fi ve-year averages on 31 countries for the period 1981-1990. They fi nd support for the idea 
that higher patent protection leads to higher research and development spending as a fraction of GDP. 
However, a different story seems equally plausible. Countries with a larger market can more easily pay the 
fi xed costs of innovation. Indeed, one perspective is that their data essentially compares countries with 
relatively small economies, little intellectual property protection, and low R&amp;D spending with countries 
with relatively larger economies, greater intellectual property protection, and higher R&amp;D spending. For 
example, R&amp;D spending as a fraction of GDP in their data ranges from a ten-year average of 0.2 percent in 
Jordan to 2.8 percent in Sweden. If we combine their data with GDP data from The 1990 CIA World Fact Book 
to take account of the size of the economy, increasing the strength of intellectual property protection from 
0 to 1 to 2 on their fi ve-point scale does increase R&amp;D expenditure. But as intellectual property protection 
is increased further, the gains to R&amp;D expenditure levels then falls. Even at the lower levels, we are probably 
observing primarily the effect of foreign direct investment: that is, among poor countries with near-zero 
intellectual property protection, increases bring in more foreign investment and in doing so directly raise 
R&amp;D spending. In higher-income countries with larger economies, foreign investment is not an issue, and 
increases in intellectual property have little or no effect on innovation. </p>



<p>The Lerner (2002) study is especially notable because he examined all signifi -
The Lerner (2002) study is especially notable because he examined all signifi -
cant changes in patent law in all countries over the last 150 years. His conclusion: 
cant changes in patent law in all countries over the last 150 years. His conclusion: 
"Consider, for instance, policy changes that strengthen patent protection. Once 
"Consider, for instance, policy changes that strengthen patent protection. Once 
overall trends in patenting are adjusted for, the changes in patents by residents of 
overall trends in patenting are adjusted for, the changes in patents by residents of 
the country undertaking the policy change are negative, both in Great Britain and 
the country undertaking the policy change are negative, both in Great Britain and 
in the country itself. Subject to the caveats noted in the conclusion this evidence 
in the country itself. Subject to the caveats noted in the conclusion this evidence 
suggests that these policy changes did not spur innovation." This, in summary, 
suggests that these policy changes did not spur innovation." This, in summary, 
is what is currently known as the "patent puzzle"-although as we will explain, it is 
is what is currently known as the "patent puzzle"-although as we will explain, it is 
substantially coherent with a theory of innovation that emphasizes the gains from 
substantially coherent with a theory of innovation that emphasizes the gains from 
competition and fi rst-mover incentives, rather than benefi ts from the monopoly 
competition and fi rst-mover incentives, rather than benefi ts from the monopoly 
power of patents. 
power of patents. 
Evidence at the sectoral level of the US economy shows the same disconnect 
Evidence at the sectoral level of the US economy shows the same disconnect 
between patenting and productivity. In Boldrin, Correa, Levine, and Ornaghi  between patenting and productivity. In Boldrin, Correa, Levine, and Ornaghi  (2011), we carried out a sequence of statistical tests and econometric estima-
(2011), we carried out a sequence of statistical tests and econometric estima-
tions on two datasets: an original microeconomic dataset obtained by combining 
tions on two datasets: an original microeconomic dataset obtained by combining 
fi rm-level information obtained through Compustat, the National Bureau of 
fi rm-level information obtained through Compustat, the National Bureau of 
Economic Research, and the Bureau of Labor Statistics and an enriched version 
Economic Research, and the Bureau of Labor Statistics and an enriched version 
of the dataset used by Aghion, Bloom, Blundell, Griffi th, and Howitt (2005) in 
of the dataset used by Aghion, Bloom, Blundell, Griffi th, and Howitt (2005) in 
their study of industry-level mark-ups. Conclusions must of course be drawn with 
their study of industry-level mark-ups. Conclusions must of course be drawn with 
care from this kind of data because, across industries, the strength of competi-
care from this kind of data because, across industries, the strength of competi-
tion, patenting, and productivity are simultaneously determined and intertwined 
tion, patenting, and productivity are simultaneously determined and intertwined 
with technological change. With that reservation appropriately noted, at the 
with technological change. With that reservation appropriately noted, at the 
industry level there is, in general, no statistically signifi cant correlation between 
industry level there is, in general, no statistically signifi cant correlation between 
measures of productivity (whether measured by labor or total factor productivity) 
measures of productivity (whether measured by labor or total factor productivity) 
and of patenting activity (whether measured by number of patents or citations 
and of patenting activity (whether measured by number of patents or citations 
of patents). 
of patents). 
We then investigated the relationships between patents, competition, and 
We then investigated the relationships between patents, competition, and 
productivity further. When we regressed measures of patents (or patent citations) 
productivity further. When we regressed measures of patents (or patent citations) 
on a measure of competition (as measured by the inverse of profi tability) used 
on a measure of competition (as measured by the inverse of profi tability) used 
by Aghion, Bloom, Blundell, Griffi th, and Howitt (2005), we found a positive 
by Aghion, Bloom, Blundell, Griffi th, and Howitt (2005), we found a positive 
relationship that is remarkably robust to changes in industry classifi cation, time 
relationship that is remarkably robust to changes in industry classifi cation, time 
period, and set of sampled industries. That is, patents were more common in 
period, and set of sampled industries. That is, patents were more common in 
competitive industries. We also studied the correlation between the same measure 
competitive industries. We also studied the correlation between the same measure 
of competitive pressure and objective measures of labor productivity growth. In 
of competitive pressure and objective measures of labor productivity growth. In 
our preferred specifi cation, we found that average annual growth of productivity 
our preferred specifi cation, we found that average annual growth of productivity 
in the sectors with the highest level of competition is up to 2 percent bigger than 
in the sectors with the highest level of competition is up to 2 percent bigger than 
in the sectors with the lowest level of competition. These are strikingly large 
in the sectors with the lowest level of competition. These are strikingly large 
differences when cumulated over various decades, as it is the case in our dataset. 
differences when cumulated over various decades, as it is the case in our dataset. 
This fi nding of a positive correlation between competition and productivity at 
This fi nding of a positive correlation between competition and productivity at 
the sectorial level replicated a pioneering, and unfortunately forgotten, pattern 
the sectorial level replicated a pioneering, and unfortunately forgotten, pattern 
reported in Stigler (1956). 
reported in Stigler (1956). 
The accumulated fi ndings of no positive relationship between patenting and 
The accumulated fi ndings of no positive relationship between patenting and 
productivity are not conclusive, and arguments have raged over the specifi c data 
productivity are not conclusive, and arguments have raged over the specifi c data 
used, whether to look for a structural break in the data, how the researcher seeks 
used, whether to look for a structural break in the data, how the researcher seeks </p>

<p>The Case Against Patents 7 </p>

<p>to correct for endogeneity, and so on. 
to correct for endogeneity, and so on. 
2 2 However, it is fair to say that the sector-level, 
However, it is fair to say that the sector-level, 
national, and cross-national evidence fail to provide any clear empirical link from 
national, and cross-national evidence fail to provide any clear empirical link from 
patents to innovation or to productivity. This lack of connection is consistent with 
patents to innovation or to productivity. This lack of connection is consistent with 
the view that the use of patents either as a defensive or as a rent-seeking tool is more 
the view that the use of patents either as a defensive or as a rent-seeking tool is more 
widespread than one might have predicted. In addition, the empirical evidence is 
widespread than one might have predicted. In addition, the empirical evidence is 
consistent with the proposition that greater competition, not patents, is the main 
consistent with the proposition that greater competition, not patents, is the main 
factor leading to innovation and greater productivity. 
factor leading to innovation and greater productivity. </p>

<p>Theory and Practice of Patents and Innovation </p>

<p>There is little doubt that providing a monopoly as a reward for innovation 
There is little doubt that providing a monopoly as a reward for innovation 
increases the incentive to innovate. There is equally little doubt that granting a 
increases the incentive to innovate. There is equally little doubt that granting a 
monopoly for any reason has the many ill consequences we associate with monopoly 
monopoly for any reason has the many ill consequences we associate with monopoly 
power-the most important and overlooked of which is the strong incentive of 
power-the most important and overlooked of which is the strong incentive of 
a government-granted monopolist to engage in further political rent seeking to 
a government-granted monopolist to engage in further political rent seeking to 
preserve and expand its monopoly or, for those who do not yet have a monopoly, 
preserve and expand its monopoly or, for those who do not yet have a monopoly, 
to try to obtain one. These effects are at least to some extent offsetting: while 
to try to obtain one. These effects are at least to some extent offsetting: while 
the positive impact of patents is the straightforward partial equilibrium effect of 
the positive impact of patents is the straightforward partial equilibrium effect of 
increasing the profi ts of the successful innovator to the monopolistic level, the 
increasing the profi ts of the successful innovator to the monopolistic level, the 
negative one is the subtler general equilibrium effect of reducing everybody else's 
negative one is the subtler general equilibrium effect of reducing everybody else's 
ability to compete while increasing for everyone the incentive to engage in socially 
ability to compete while increasing for everyone the incentive to engage in socially 
wasteful lobbying efforts. 
wasteful lobbying efforts. </p>

<p>Downstream Innovation, Defensive Patenting, and Patent Trolls 
In the long run, even the positive partial equilibrium effect of patents in 
In the long run, even the positive partial equilibrium effect of patents in 
providing an incentive for innovation may be more apparent than real: the exis-
providing an incentive for innovation may be more apparent than real: the exis-
tence of a large number of monopolies created by past patent grants reduces the 
tence of a large number of monopolies created by past patent grants reduces the 
incentives for current innovation because current innovators are subject to constant 
incentives for current innovation because current innovators are subject to constant 
legal action and licensing demands from earlier patent holders. The downstream 
legal action and licensing demands from earlier patent holders. The downstream 
blocking effect of existing monopoly grants on incentives for future innovation 
blocking effect of existing monopoly grants on incentives for future innovation </p>

<p>2 For a sense of these controversies, Aghion, Bloom, Blundell, Griffi th, and Howitt (2005) fi nd an 
"inverted-U" relationship between the extent of competition, as measured by the inverse of mark-ups, 
and a measure of patenting activity, based on a dataset of US patents of UK fi rms. In other words, they 
fi nd that the maximum innovative effort (as measured by patents) occurs at some "intermediate" posi-
tion between a high and low level of competition. However, Hashmi (2011) reexamines the inverted-U 
relationship using data from publicly traded US manufacturing fi rms and fi nds a robust positive relation-
ship between the inverse of markups and citation-weighted patents. Correa (2012) reexamines the same 
dataset of UK fi rms and shows that the prediction of an inverted-U is overturned when allowing for the 
possibility that innovations follow a "memory process," where the current probability of introducing 
a new innovation increases when a fi rm successfully innovated in the previous period. He also fi nds a 
structural break in the data in 1981, when the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit was established 
to hear appeals of patent cases. Overall, Correa fi nds a positive innovation-competition relationship for 
the memory industries before the 1982 reform, but no relationship between innovation and competition 
for those industries that he classifi es as memory-less. </p>



<p>has greatly increased in recent decades because modern products are made up 
has greatly increased in recent decades because modern products are made up 
of so many different components. The recent-and largely successful-efforts of 
of so many different components. The recent-and largely successful-efforts of 
Microsoft to impose a licensing fee on the large and expanding Android phone 
Microsoft to impose a licensing fee on the large and expanding Android phone 
market is but one case in point. With the exception of Motorola Mobility, all the 
market is but one case in point. With the exception of Motorola Mobility, all the 
handset manufacturers have agreed to the fee, and Motorola lost its fi rst battle 
handset manufacturers have agreed to the fee, and Motorola lost its fi rst battle 
against the fee in spring 2012-fought not in court but in the more receptive 
against the fee in spring 2012-fought not in court but in the more receptive 
domain of the US International Trade Commission (Investigation Number 337-TA-
domain of the US International Trade Commission (Investigation Number 337-TA-
744, May 18, 2012). Microsoft is attempting to charge a licensing fee solely over a 
744, May 18, 2012). Microsoft is attempting to charge a licensing fee solely over a 
patent involving the scheduling of meetings-a rarely used feature of modern smart-
patent involving the scheduling of meetings-a rarely used feature of modern smart-
phones. The meeting-schedule feature is but one of many thousands of patented 
phones. The meeting-schedule feature is but one of many thousands of patented 
"ideas" used in a modern smartphone, and each owner of each patent potentially 
"ideas" used in a modern smartphone, and each owner of each patent potentially 
can charge a licensing fee. Hence, the main dynamic general equilibrium effect of 
can charge a licensing fee. Hence, the main dynamic general equilibrium effect of 
a patent system is to subject future inventions to a gigantic hold-up problem: with 
a patent system is to subject future inventions to a gigantic hold-up problem: with 
many licenses to be purchased and uncertainty about the ultimate value of the new 
many licenses to be purchased and uncertainty about the ultimate value of the new 
innovation, each patent holder, in raising the price of his "component," imposes an 
innovation, each patent holder, in raising the price of his "component," imposes an 
externality on other patent holders and so charges a higher than effi cient licensing 
externality on other patent holders and so charges a higher than effi cient licensing 
fee. In Boldrin and Levine (2005) and Llanes and Trento (2009), we and others 
fee. In Boldrin and Levine (2005) and Llanes and Trento (2009), we and others 
have explored the theory; and many case studies involving patents (and other frac-
have explored the theory; and many case studies involving patents (and other frac-
tionated ownership problems) can be found in Heller (2008). 
tionated ownership problems) can be found in Heller (2008). 
To understand more about the actual effect of patents in the real world, 
To understand more about the actual effect of patents in the real world, 
consider the recent purchase by Google of Motorola Mobility, primarily for its 
consider the recent purchase by Google of Motorola Mobility, primarily for its 
patent portfolio-not for the ideas and innovations in that portfolio. Few if any 
patent portfolio-not for the ideas and innovations in that portfolio. Few if any 
changes or improvements to Google's <rs type="software">Android operating system</rs> will result from 
changes or improvements to Google's Android operating system will result from 
the ownership or study of these software patents. Google's purpose in obtaining 
the ownership or study of these software patents. Google's purpose in obtaining 
this patent portfolio is purely defensive: it can be used to countersue Apple and 
this patent portfolio is purely defensive: it can be used to countersue Apple and 
Microsoft and blunt their legal attack on Google. These remarks apply to the vast 
Microsoft and blunt their legal attack on Google. These remarks apply to the vast 
bulk of patents: they do not represent useful innovation at all and are just weapons 
bulk of patents: they do not represent useful innovation at all and are just weapons 
in an arms race. This is not news: the same message emerged decades ago from the 
in an arms race. This is not news: the same message emerged decades ago from the 
Levin, Klevorick, Nelson, and Winter (1987) and Cohen, Nelson, and Walsh (2000)  Levin, Klevorick, Nelson, and Winter (1987) and Cohen, Nelson, and Walsh (2000)  surveys of research and development managers. 
surveys of research and development managers. 
One could argue that the costs of building up a patent portfolio to engage 
One could argue that the costs of building up a patent portfolio to engage 
in this sort of defensive patenting are not too large: after all, it can cost as little as 
in this sort of defensive patenting are not too large: after all, it can cost as little as 
$15,000 to fi le a successful patent application, and fi ling applications on a larger 
$15,000 to fi le a successful patent application, and fi ling applications on a larger 
scale might be cheaper. However, the acquisition of large patent portfolios by 
scale might be cheaper. However, the acquisition of large patent portfolios by 
incumbents creates huge barriers to entry. In the smartphone market, for example, 
incumbents creates huge barriers to entry. In the smartphone market, for example, 
Apple is the market leader and Microsoft is unable to produce a product that 
Apple is the market leader and Microsoft is unable to produce a product that 
appeals to consumers. Each are incumbent fi rms with a large patent portfolio. In 
appeals to consumers. Each are incumbent fi rms with a large patent portfolio. In 
this market, Google is the new entrant and innovator and, while wealthy, Google 
this market, Google is the new entrant and innovator and, while wealthy, Google 
found itself lacking a large defensive patent portfolio. Hence we see both Apple 
found itself lacking a large defensive patent portfolio. Hence we see both Apple 
and Microsoft attacking Google with patent litigations, generating hundreds of 
and Microsoft attacking Google with patent litigations, generating hundreds of 
millions in wasteful legal costs and no social benefi t whatsoever. 
millions in wasteful legal costs and no social benefi t whatsoever. 
Despite the fact that patents are mostly used for arms races and that these, 
Despite the fact that patents are mostly used for arms races and that these, 
in turn, are driven by patent trolls, there does not yet exist convincing formal 
in turn, are driven by patent trolls, there does not yet exist convincing formal 
models of the ways in which this interaction can inhibit innovation. In a pure arms 
models of the ways in which this interaction can inhibit innovation. In a pure arms </p>

<p>Miche le Boldrin and David K. Levine 9 </p>

<p>race theory, if all fi rms get counterbalancing patent portfolios and all innovate, 
race theory, if all fi rms get counterbalancing patent portfolios and all innovate, 
then they would all have innovated in the absence of patents-hence, patents do 
then they would all have innovated in the absence of patents-hence, patents do 
not encourage innovation. This follows because with counterbalancing patent 
not encourage innovation. This follows because with counterbalancing patent 
portfolios, no fi rm can sue any other fi rm-exactly as would be the case in the 
portfolios, no fi rm can sue any other fi rm-exactly as would be the case in the 
absence of patents. Hence in this setting patents simply add a cost to innova-
absence of patents. Hence in this setting patents simply add a cost to innova-
tion: if you wish to innovate, you must acquire an expensive patent portfolio to 
tion: if you wish to innovate, you must acquire an expensive patent portfolio to 
avoid trolls. On the other hand if a patentholder does not produce a marketable 
avoid trolls. On the other hand if a patentholder does not produce a marketable 
product and hence cannot be countersued-like Microsoft in the phone market 
product and hence cannot be countersued-like Microsoft in the phone market 
or other patent trolls in other markets-then patents become a mechanism for 
or other patent trolls in other markets-then patents become a mechanism for 
sharing the profi ts without doing the work. In this scenario, not only do patents 
sharing the profi ts without doing the work. In this scenario, not only do patents 
discourage innovation, but they are also a pure waste from a social standpoint. 
discourage innovation, but they are also a pure waste from a social standpoint. </p>

<p>Patents and Information Disclosure 
Another widely cited benefi t of patent systems-although not so much in 
Another widely cited benefi t of patent systems-although not so much in 
the economics literature-is the notion that patents are a substitute for socially 
the economics literature-is the notion that patents are a substitute for socially 
costly trade secrecy and improve communication about ideas. From a theoretical 
costly trade secrecy and improve communication about ideas. From a theoretical 
point of view, the notion that patents are a substitute for trade secrecy fails in the 
point of view, the notion that patents are a substitute for trade secrecy fails in the 
simplest model. If a secret can be kept for 
simplest model. If a secret can be kept for N years and a patent lasts 
years and a patent lasts M years, then 
years, then 
an innovator will patent when 
an innovator will patent when N &lt; &lt; M. In other words, ideas will be patented when it 
. In other words, ideas will be patented when it 
seems likely that the secret would have emerged before the patent expired and not 
seems likely that the secret would have emerged before the patent expired and not 
patented if the secret can be kept. In practice, it is uncertain when the secret will 
patented if the secret can be kept. In practice, it is uncertain when the secret will 
leak out, but it can be shown that the basic intuition remains intact in the face of 
leak out, but it can be shown that the basic intuition remains intact in the face of 
uncertainty (Boldrin and Levine 2004; Ponce 2007). 
uncertainty (Boldrin and Levine 2004; Ponce 2007). </p>

<p>3 3 </p>

<p>It is also the case that the extent of practical "disclosure" in modern patents 
It is also the case that the extent of practical "disclosure" in modern patents 
is as negligible as the skills of patent attorneys can make it. It is usually impossible 
is as negligible as the skills of patent attorneys can make it. It is usually impossible 
to build a functioning device or software program from a modern patent applica-
to build a functioning device or software program from a modern patent applica-
tion; this is made especially clear by the fact that some patented ideas do not and 
tion; this is made especially clear by the fact that some patented ideas do not and 
cannot work. For example, US Patent 6,025,810 was granted for moving information 
work. For example, US Patent 6,025,810 was granted for moving information 
through the fi fth dimension. While detailed studies of the usefulness of disclosure 
through the fi fth dimension. While detailed studies of the usefulness of disclosure 
in patent applications are not available, companies typically instruct their engineers 
in patent applications are not available, companies typically instruct their engineers 
developing products to avoid studying existing patents so as to be spared subsequent 
developing products to avoid studying existing patents so as to be spared subsequent 
claims of willful infringement, which raises the possibility of having to pay triple 
claims of willful infringement, which raises the possibility of having to pay triple 
damages. According to sworn testimony by Google's chief of Android development 
damages. According to sworn testimony by Google's chief of Android development 
during the legal battles between Oracle and Google (for example, Niccolai 2012), 
during the legal battles between Oracle and Google (for example, Niccolai 2012), 
the engineers that developed Android were unaware of Apple (or other) patents, 
the engineers that developed Android were unaware of Apple (or other) patents, 
and so were unlikely to have been helped by them. The opinion of Brec (2008), a 
and so were unlikely to have been helped by them. The opinion of Brec (2008), a 
Microsoft developer, refl ects that of many practitioners: 
Microsoft developer, refl ects that of many practitioners: </p>

<p>[Microsoft policy is for developers to] never search, view, or speculate about 
patents. I was confused by this guidance till I wrote and reviewed one of my </p>

<p>3 A more subtle point is that secrecy may bias the type of inventive activity away from innovations that 
are not easily kept secret to those that can be. In this symposium, Moser offers some of the historical 
evidence on this point. </p>



<p>own patents. The legal claims section-the only section that counts -was 
indecipherable by anyone but a patent attorney. Ignorance is bliss and strongly 
recommended when it comes to patents. </p>

<p>The related idea that patents somehow improve communication about ideas, 
The related idea that patents somehow improve communication about ideas, 
thereby creating some positive externality-a notion key to the "public-private" 
thereby creating some positive externality-a notion key to the "public-private" 
partnership between governments and private research organizations in which the 
partnership between governments and private research organizations in which the 
government funds the research and then gives the private organization a monopoly 
government funds the research and then gives the private organization a monopoly 
over what is developed in the course of research-is backed by neither theory nor 
over what is developed in the course of research-is backed by neither theory nor 
evidence. It is impossible to study the history of innovation without recognizing 
evidence. It is impossible to study the history of innovation without recognizing 
that inventors and innovators exchange ideas as a matter of course and that secrecy 
that inventors and innovators exchange ideas as a matter of course and that secrecy 
occurs, when it occurs, typically in the fi nal stages of an innovation process when 
occurs, when it occurs, typically in the fi nal stages of an innovation process when 
some ambitious inventors hope to corner the market for a functioning device by 
some ambitious inventors hope to corner the market for a functioning device by 
patenting it. A good case in point is that of the Wright brothers, who made a modest 
patenting it. A good case in point is that of the Wright brothers, who made a modest 
improvement in existing fl ight technology that they kept secret until they could 
improvement in existing fl ight technology that they kept secret until they could 
lock it down on patents, then used their patents both to monopolize the US market 
lock it down on patents, then used their patents both to monopolize the US market 
and to prevent further innovation for nearly 20 years (Shulman, 2003). The role 
and to prevent further innovation for nearly 20 years (Shulman, 2003). The role 
that Marconi and his patent played in the development of the radio is altogether 
that Marconi and his patent played in the development of the radio is altogether 
similar (Hong 2001), as are innumerable other stories. At the opposite extreme 
similar (Hong 2001), as are innumerable other stories. At the opposite extreme 
we have, again among many, the example of the Cornish steam engine discussed 
we have, again among many, the example of the Cornish steam engine discussed 
in Nuvolari (2004, 2006). Here engineers exchanged nonpatented ideas for 
in Nuvolari (2004, 2006). Here engineers exchanged nonpatented ideas for 
decades in a collaborative effort to improve effi ciency. The contemporary FLOSS 
decades in a collaborative effort to improve effi ciency. The contemporary FLOSS 
(Free/Libre and Open Source Software) community is another successful example 
(Free/Libre and Open Source Software) community is another successful example 
of how collaboration and exchange of ideas can thrive without the monopoly power 
of how collaboration and exchange of ideas can thrive without the monopoly power 
granted by patents. 
granted by patents. </p>

<p>First-Mover Advantages and Incentives for Innovation 
In most industries, the fi rst-mover advantage and the competitive rents it 
In most industries, the fi rst-mover advantage and the competitive rents it 
induces are substantial without patents. The smartphone industry-laden as it is 
induces are substantial without patents. The smartphone industry-laden as it is 
with patent litigation-is a case in point. Apple derived enormous profi ts in this 
with patent litigation-is a case in point. Apple derived enormous profi ts in this 
market before it faced any substantial competition. The fi rst iPhone was released 
market before it faced any substantial competition. The fi rst iPhone was released 
on June 29, 2007. The fi rst serious competitor, the HTC Dream (using the Android 
on June 29, 2007. The fi rst serious competitor, the HTC Dream (using the <rs type="software">Android operating system</rs>) was released on October 22, 2008. By that time, over 5 million 
operating system) was released on October 22, 2008. By that time, over 5 million 
iPhones had been sold, and sales soared to over 25 million units during the subse-
iPhones had been sold, and sales soared to over 25 million units during the subse-
quent year, while total sales of all Android-based phones were less than 7 million. In 
quent year, while total sales of all Android-based phones were less than 7 million. In 
the tablet market, the iPad has no serious competitor as of late 2012 despite having 
the tablet market, the iPad has no serious competitor as of late 2012 despite having 
been introduced on April 10, 2010. While it is hard to prove this delayed imitation 
been introduced on April 10, 2010. While it is hard to prove this delayed imitation 
also would have occurred in the complete absence of patents, intuition suggests-
also would have occurred in the complete absence of patents, intuition suggests-
and our formal model in Boldrin and Levine (2004) predicts-that there is little 
and our formal model in Boldrin and Levine (2004) predicts-that there is little 
reason to assert patent rights while the fi rst-mover advantage is still active. Apple did 
reason to assert patent rights while the fi rst-mover advantage is still active. Apple did 
not initially try to use patents to prevent the Android phones from coming into its 
not initially try to use patents to prevent the Android phones from coming into its 
market and the subsequent "patents' fi ght" has been taking place largely after 2010; 
market and the subsequent "patents' fi ght" has been taking place largely after 2010; 
these facts are consistent with a substantial fi rst-mover advantage. How valuable for 
these facts are consistent with a substantial fi rst-mover advantage. How valuable for 
Apple was the delay in the Android phones entry? Largely because Apple kept its 
Apple was the delay in the Android phones entry? Largely because Apple kept its </p>

<p>The Case Against Patents 11 </p>

<p>fi rst-mover advantage in spite of a large imitative entry in this market, the value of 
fi rst-mover advantage in spite of a large imitative entry in this market, the value of 
Apple stock-during a severe market downturn-rose by a factor of approximately 
Apple stock-during a severe market downturn-rose by a factor of approximately 
fi ve. While there may have been some delay in entry from the competition due 
fi ve. While there may have been some delay in entry from the competition due 
to Apple's threat-since executed -of patent litigation, the fact is that similar but 
to Apple's threat-since executed -of patent litigation, the fact is that similar but 
less-successful devices had been available for a number of years before Apple fi nally 
less-successful devices had been available for a number of years before Apple fi nally 
cracked the market. 
cracked the market. 
Less anecdotal than the story of the iPhone is the survey of research and devel-
Less anecdotal than the story of the iPhone is the survey of research and devel-
opment managers in Cohen, Nelson, and Walsh (2000). Here, over 50 percent of 
opment managers in Cohen, Nelson, and Walsh (2000). Here, over 50 percent of 
managers indicate lead time (fi rst-mover advantage) is important to earning a return 
managers indicate lead time (fi rst-mover advantage) is important to earning a return 
on innovation; outside the pharmaceutical and medical instruments industry, less 
on innovation; outside the pharmaceutical and medical instruments industry, less 
than 35 percent of managers indicate that patents are important. 
than 35 percent of managers indicate that patents are important. 
To understand patents in practice, it is necessary to examine the lifecycle of 
To understand patents in practice, it is necessary to examine the lifecycle of 
industries (for example, Jovanovich and MacDonald 1994; Scherer 1990). Typically 
industries (for example, Jovanovich and MacDonald 1994; Scherer 1990). Typically 
a new, hence innovative, industry begins with a competitive burst of entries through 
a new, hence innovative, industry begins with a competitive burst of entries through 
which very many innovators try hard to get their products to market. In these early 
which very many innovators try hard to get their products to market. In these early 
stages, many fi rms bring different versions of the new product to the market (think 
stages, many fi rms bring different versions of the new product to the market (think 
of the American auto industry in the early twentieth century or the software industry 
of the American auto industry in the early twentieth century or the software industry 
in the 1980s and 1990s) while demand for the new product grows rapidly and the 
in the 1980s and 1990s) while demand for the new product grows rapidly and the 
quality of products is rapidly improved. At this stage of the industry lifecycle, the price 
quality of products is rapidly improved. At this stage of the industry lifecycle, the price 
elasticity of demand is typically high; what is important is not to dominate the market, 
elasticity of demand is typically high; what is important is not to dominate the market, 
but rather to get your own products quickly to market and to reduce costs. From the 
but rather to get your own products quickly to market and to reduce costs. From the 
perspective of competing fi rms, your cost-reducing innovation is good for me in 
perspective of competing fi rms, your cost-reducing innovation is good for me in 
the same way that my cost-reducing innovation is good for you-hence, let us all 
the same way that my cost-reducing innovation is good for you-hence, let us all 
imitate each other and compete in the market. 
imitate each other and compete in the market. 
As the industry matures, demand stabilizes and becomes much less price elastic; 
As the industry matures, demand stabilizes and becomes much less price elastic; 
the scope for cost-reducing innovations decreases; the benefi ts of monopoly power 
the scope for cost-reducing innovations decreases; the benefi ts of monopoly power 
grow; and the potential for additional product innovation shrinks. Typically there 
grow; and the potential for additional product innovation shrinks. Typically there 
is a shakeout in which many fi rms either leave the industry or are bought out. The 
is a shakeout in which many fi rms either leave the industry or are bought out. The 
automobile industry is a classical historical example, but many readers will have a 
automobile industry is a classical historical example, but many readers will have a 
more vivid memory of the bursting of the dot-com bubble, which makes this point 
more vivid memory of the bursting of the dot-com bubble, which makes this point 
even more forcefully. At this stage of the industry lifecycle, rent seeking becomes 
even more forcefully. At this stage of the industry lifecycle, rent seeking becomes 
important and patents are widely used to inhibit innovation, prevent entry, and 
important and patents are widely used to inhibit innovation, prevent entry, and 
encourage exit. If we look at patent litigation in practice-and as predicted by theo-
encourage exit. If we look at patent litigation in practice-and as predicted by theo-
ries of fi rst-mover competition (Boldrin and Levine 2004, among others)-it takes 
ries of fi rst-mover competition (Boldrin and Levine 2004, among others)-it takes 
place when innovation is low. When an industry matures, innovation is no longer 
place when innovation is low. When an industry matures, innovation is no longer 
encouraged; instead, it is blocked by the ever-increasing appeal to patent protection 
encouraged; instead, it is blocked by the ever-increasing appeal to patent protection 
on part of the insiders. 
on part of the insiders. 
While patent litigation has increased, few patents are actively used. Patent litiga-
While patent litigation has increased, few patents are actively used. Patent litiga-
tion often involves dying fi rms that have accumulated huge stockpile of patents but 
tion often involves dying fi rms that have accumulated huge stockpile of patents but 
are no longer able to produce marketable products and that are now suing new and 
are no longer able to produce marketable products and that are now suing new and 
innovative fi rms. For example, Texas Instruments was one of the fi rst producers of 
innovative fi rms. For example, Texas Instruments was one of the fi rst producers of 
microchips, and many in our generation remember the capabilities of their fi rst TI 
microchips, and many in our generation remember the capabilities of their fi rst TI 
calculator. But Texas Instruments was unable to make the transition to the personal 
calculator. But Texas Instruments was unable to make the transition to the personal 
computer revolution and became, for a while, the symbol of a dying company 
computer revolution and became, for a while, the symbol of a dying company </p>



<p>trying to stay alive by suing the newcomers. 
trying to stay alive by suing the newcomers. 
4 4 In more recent times, Microsoft-once 
In more recent times, Microsoft-once 
the giant bestriding the software industry-has been unable to make the leap to 
the giant bestriding the software industry-has been unable to make the leap to 
portable devices such as telephones and tablet personal computers. Thus, Microsoft 
portable devices such as telephones and tablet personal computers. Thus, Microsoft 
now uses patent litigation to try to claim a share of the profi ts Google generates in 
now uses patent litigation to try to claim a share of the profi ts Google generates in 
this market. Back in 1991, Bill Gates said: "If people had understood how patents 
this market. Back in 1991, Bill Gates said: "If people had understood how patents 
would be granted when most of today's ideas were invented and had taken out 
would be granted when most of today's ideas were invented and had taken out 
patents, the industry would be at a complete standstill today . . . A future start-up 
patents, the industry would be at a complete standstill today . . . A future start-up 
with no patents of its own will be forced to pay whatever price the giants choose to 
with no patents of its own will be forced to pay whatever price the giants choose to 
impose." Today, Microsoft lobbies across Europe and Asia for the introduction of 
impose." Today, Microsoft lobbies across Europe and Asia for the introduction of 
software patents, a prize it has already obtained in its home country. 
software patents, a prize it has already obtained in its home country. 
The cost of litigating patents is not insubstantial either. Bessen and Meurer 
The cost of litigating patents is not insubstantial either. Bessen and Meurer  (2008) used stock market event studies to estimate the cost of patent litigation: 
(2008) used stock market event studies to estimate the cost of patent litigation: 
they estimate that during the 1990s such costs rose substantially until, at the end of 
they estimate that during the 1990s such costs rose substantially until, at the end of 
the period, they constituted nearly 14 percent of total research and development 
the period, they constituted nearly 14 percent of total research and development 
costs. A related but more diffi cult-to-quantify phenomenon is the rise of uncertainty 
costs. A related but more diffi cult-to-quantify phenomenon is the rise of uncertainty 
caused by the legal system. A case in point is the NTP Inc. patents that were used 
caused by the legal system. A case in point is the NTP Inc. patents that were used 
to threaten the Blackberry network with a shutdown. In 2006, Research in Motion 
to threaten the Blackberry network with a shutdown. In 2006, Research in Motion 
(RIM), the producer of Blackberry, agreed to pay $612.5 million to license the 
(RIM), the producer of Blackberry, agreed to pay $612.5 million to license the 
patent in question from NTP (Svensson 2006). The patent was later invalidated by 
patent in question from NTP (Svensson 2006). The patent was later invalidated by 
the court-but RIM did not get its money back (Salmon 2012). Here, the behavior 
the court-but RIM did not get its money back (Salmon 2012). Here, the behavior 
of a single judge cost RIM more than half a billion dollars. In this setting, it is no 
of a single judge cost RIM more than half a billion dollars. In this setting, it is no 
surprise that patent trolls hope to get rich quickly. 
surprise that patent trolls hope to get rich quickly. 
It is easier to list the main social welfare implications of the tradeoff between 
It is easier to list the main social welfare implications of the tradeoff between 
costs of legal monopoly and incentives to patent holders than it is to calculate their 
costs of legal monopoly and incentives to patent holders than it is to calculate their 
magnitudes. Still, the provisional evidence we have suggests that the net welfare effects 
magnitudes. Still, the provisional evidence we have suggests that the net welfare effects 
of the current patent system could easily be negative. It is somewhat conventional to 
of the current patent system could easily be negative. It is somewhat conventional to 
think of welfare losses from distortions as small, with the idea that welfare triangles 
think of welfare losses from distortions as small, with the idea that welfare triangles 
due to monopoly power are small being the paradigmatic case in point. Unfortu-
due to monopoly power are small being the paradigmatic case in point. Unfortu-
nately, monopolies have no incentive to avoid large social losses even when the private 
nately, monopolies have no incentive to avoid large social losses even when the private 
gains are small. Witness, for example, the fact that patented pharmaceutical products 
gains are small. Witness, for example, the fact that patented pharmaceutical products 
often sell for hundreds of times the marginal cost of production, as some astonishing 
often sell for hundreds of times the marginal cost of production, as some astonishing 
pricing differences between the US and the European markets show. Most revealing 
pricing differences between the US and the European markets show. Most revealing 
is the empirical study of the Quinolones family of drugs (Chaudhuri, Goldberg, and 
is the empirical study of the Quinolones family of drugs (Chaudhuri, Goldberg, and 
Gia 2006). It measures the economic consequences of the introduction of pharma-
Gia 2006). It measures the economic consequences of the introduction of pharma-
ceutical patents for this family of drugs and concludes that the consequence of patent 
ceutical patents for this family of drugs and concludes that the consequence of patent 
protection to India will be nearly $300 million in welfare losses-while the gain to the 
protection to India will be nearly $300 million in welfare losses-while the gain to the 
pharmaceutical companies will be less than $20 million. 
pharmaceutical companies will be less than $20 million. </p>

<p>5 5 </p>

<p>4 Texas Instruments is such an important source of litigation that empirical work on patent litigation 
usually uses a dummy variable for TI. Empirical studies of the importance of fi rms no longer doing busi-
ness in an industry to litigation can be found in Bessen and Meurer (2005) and Hall and Ziedonis (2007). 
5 Although the focus of this paper is on patents rather than copyright, it is worth noting that most of 
the copyright wars revolve around measures to prevent piracy, empirically a relatively minor factor as far 
as profi ts of media corporations are concerned (see for example Sinha, Machado, and Sellman 2010; 
Danaher, Dhanasobhon, Smith, and Telang 2010; Sanchez 2012). </p>

<p>Miche le Boldrin and David K. Levine 13 </p>

<p>Pharmaceuticals Pharmaceuticals 
This brings us to the controversial issue of drug patents. The standard 
This brings us to the controversial issue of drug patents. The standard 
argument says: No patents, no drugs. The total cost of developing a new drug, 
argument says: No patents, no drugs. The total cost of developing a new drug, 
including failures, is quickly approaching the $1 billion mark (DiMasi, Hansen, 
including failures, is quickly approaching the $1 billion mark (DiMasi, Hansen,  and Grabowski 2003). So how can anyone, faced with such a gigantic fi xed cost and 
and Grabowski 2003). So how can anyone, faced with such a gigantic fi xed cost and 
a microscopic marginal cost of reproduction, innovate without the protection of 
a microscopic marginal cost of reproduction, innovate without the protection of 
patents? But consider the following facts: Under current law, the chemical formula 
patents? But consider the following facts: Under current law, the chemical formula 
and the effi cacy of the cure as established by clinical trials are made available to 
and the effi cacy of the cure as established by clinical trials are made available to 
competitors essentially for free. About 80 percent of the initial fi xed cost of drug 
competitors essentially for free. About 80 percent of the initial fi xed cost of drug 
development comes from Stage III clinical trials, a public good that legislation 
development comes from Stage III clinical trials, a public good that legislation 
requires be 
requires be privately produced. The downstream social cost of monopoly pricing of 
produced. The downstream social cost of monopoly pricing of 
pharmaceutical products is highest for life-saving drugs, and the cost of monopoly 
pharmaceutical products is highest for life-saving drugs, and the cost of monopoly 
pricing of other pharmaceutical products is also quite high. Given all this, various 
pricing of other pharmaceutical products is also quite high. Given all this, various 
economists, such as Kremer and Williams (2009), have argued that 
economists, such as Kremer and Williams (2009), have argued that if government government 
intervention is 
intervention is indeed needed in this market, a system of prizes might be superior 
indeed needed in this market, a system of prizes might be superior 
to the existing system of monopolies. 
to the existing system of monopolies. 
There are four things that should be born in mind in thinking about the role 
There are four things that should be born in mind in thinking about the role 
of patents in the pharmaceutical industry. First, patents are just one piece of a 
of patents in the pharmaceutical industry. First, patents are just one piece of a 
set of complicated regulations that include requirements for clinical testing and 
set of complicated regulations that include requirements for clinical testing and 
disclosure, along with grants of market exclusivity that function alongside patents. 
disclosure, along with grants of market exclusivity that function alongside patents. 
Second, it is widely believed that in the absence of legal protections, generics would 
Second, it is widely believed that in the absence of legal protections, generics would 
hit the market side by side with the originals. This assumption is presumably based 
hit the market side by side with the originals. This assumption is presumably based 
on the observation that when patents expire, generics enter immediately. However, 
on the observation that when patents expire, generics enter immediately. However, 
this overlooks the fact that the generic manufacturers have had more than a decade 
this overlooks the fact that the generic manufacturers have had more than a decade 
to reverse-engineer the product, study the market, and set up production lines. 
to reverse-engineer the product, study the market, and set up production lines. 
Lanjouw's (1998) study of India prior to the recent introduction of pharmaceutical 
Lanjouw's (1998) study of India prior to the recent introduction of pharmaceutical 
patents there indicates that it takes closer to four years to bring a product to market 
patents there indicates that it takes closer to four years to bring a product to market 
after the original is introduced-in other words, the fi rst-mover advantage in phar-
after the original is introduced-in other words, the fi rst-mover advantage in phar-
maceuticals is larger than is ordinarily imagined. Third, much development of 
maceuticals is larger than is ordinarily imagined. Third, much development of 
pharmaceutical products is done outside the private sector; in Boldrin and Levine 
pharmaceutical products is done outside the private sector; in Boldrin and Levine  (2008b), we provide some details. Finally, the current system is not working well: 
(2008b), we provide some details. Finally, the current system is not working well: 
as Grootendorst, Hollis, Levine, Pogge, and Edwards (2011) point out, the most 
as Grootendorst, Hollis, Levine, Pogge, and Edwards (2011) point out, the most 
notable current feature of pharmaceutical innovation is the huge "drought" in the 
notable current feature of pharmaceutical innovation is the huge "drought" in the 
development of new products. 
development of new products. 
With these four factors in mind, it is possible to make proposals for reforming 
With these four factors in mind, it is possible to make proposals for reforming 
the pharmaceutical industry along with the patent system. For example, we could 
the pharmaceutical industry along with the patent system. For example, we could 
either treat Stage II and III clinical trials as public goods (where the task would be 
either treat Stage II and III clinical trials as public goods (where the task would be 
fi nanced by National Institutes of Health, who would accept bids from fi rms to carry 
fi nanced by National Institutes of Health, who would accept bids from fi rms to carry 
out this work) or by allowing the commercialization of new drugs-at regulated 
out this work) or by allowing the commercialization of new drugs-at regulated 
prices equal to the economic costs of drugs-if they satisfy the Food and Drug 
prices equal to the economic costs of drugs-if they satisfy the Food and Drug 
Administration requirements for safety even if they do not yet satisfy the current 
Administration requirements for safety even if they do not yet satisfy the current 
(overly demanding) requisites for proving effi cacy. In other words, pharmaceutical 
(overly demanding) requisites for proving effi cacy. In other words, pharmaceutical 
companies would be requested to sell new drugs at "economic cost" until effi cacy 
companies would be requested to sell new drugs at "economic cost" until effi cacy 
is proved, but they could start selling at market prices after that. (It is ensuring 
is proved, but they could start selling at market prices after that. (It is ensuring </p>



<p>the effi cacy-not the safety-of drugs that is most expensive, time-consuming, and 
the effi cacy-not the safety-of drugs that is most expensive, time-consuming, and 
diffi cult.) In this way, companies would face strong incentives to conduct or fund 
diffi cult.) In this way, companies would face strong incentives to conduct or fund 
appropriate effi cacy studies where they deem the potential market for such drugs 
appropriate effi cacy studies where they deem the potential market for such drugs 
to be large enough to bear the additional costs. The new policy could begin with 
to be large enough to bear the additional costs. The new policy could begin with 
drugs aimed at rare diseases, which, because of their small potential market, are 
drugs aimed at rare diseases, which, because of their small potential market, are 
not currently worth the costs of effi cacy testing; without the new policy, they might 
not currently worth the costs of effi cacy testing; without the new policy, they might 
never make it to market at all. If this new progressive approval approach works for 
never make it to market at all. If this new progressive approval approach works for 
rare diseases, it could be adopted across the board. Our broader point is that, rather 
rare diseases, it could be adopted across the board. Our broader point is that, rather 
than just ratcheting up patent protection, there are a number of moves we could 
than just ratcheting up patent protection, there are a number of moves we could 
make to reduce the risks and cost of developing new drugs. 
make to reduce the risks and cost of developing new drugs. </p>

<p>The Political Economy of Patents </p>

<p>We do believe, along with many of our colleagues, that a patent system 
We do believe, along with many of our colleagues, that a patent system 
designed by impartial and disinterested economists and administered by wise and 
designed by impartial and disinterested economists and administered by wise and 
incorruptible civil servants could serve to encourage innovation. In such a system, 
incorruptible civil servants could serve to encourage innovation. In such a system, 
very few patents would ever be awarded: only those for which convincing evidence 
very few patents would ever be awarded: only those for which convincing evidence 
existed that the fi xed costs of innovation were truly very high, the costs of imita-
existed that the fi xed costs of innovation were truly very high, the costs of imita-
tion were truly very low, and demand for the product was really highly inelastic. 
tion were truly very low, and demand for the product was really highly inelastic. 
(The curious reader may check Boldrin and Levine, 2008a, for a more detailed 
(The curious reader may check Boldrin and Levine, 2008a, for a more detailed 
explanation as to why these three conditions need to be satisfi ed to make a patent 
explanation as to why these three conditions need to be satisfi ed to make a patent 
socially valuable). There is little dispute, among these same colleagues, that the 
socially valuable). There is little dispute, among these same colleagues, that the 
patent system as it exists is very far from satisfying such requirements and it is, 
patent system as it exists is very far from satisfying such requirements and it is, 
in fact, broken. To quote a proponent of patents, Shapiro (2007): "A growing 
in fact, broken. To quote a proponent of patents, Shapiro (2007): "A growing 
chorus of scholars and practitioners are expressing concerns about the operation 
chorus of scholars and practitioners are expressing concerns about the operation 
of the US patent system. While there is no doubt that the US economy remains 
of the US patent system. While there is no doubt that the US economy remains 
highly innovative, and there is no doubt that the patent system taken as a whole 
highly innovative, and there is no doubt that the patent system taken as a whole 
plays an important role in spurring innovation, the general consensus is that the 
plays an important role in spurring innovation, the general consensus is that the 
US patent system is out of balance and can be substantially improved." Actually, 
US patent system is out of balance and can be substantially improved." Actually, 
we believe the evidence is clear that the patent system taken as a whole does not 
we believe the evidence is clear that the patent system taken as a whole does not 
play an important role in spurring innovation. But if a well-designed and well-
play an important role in spurring innovation. But if a well-designed and well-
administered patent system 
administered patent system could serve the intended purpose, why not reform it 
serve the intended purpose, why not reform it 
instead of abolishing it? 
instead of abolishing it? 
To answer the question we need to investigate the political economy of patents: 
To answer the question we need to investigate the political economy of patents: 
why has the political system resulted in the patent system we have? Our argument 
why has the political system resulted in the patent system we have? Our argument 
is that it cannot be otherwise: the "optimal" patent system that a benevolent 
is that it cannot be otherwise: the "optimal" patent system that a benevolent 
economist-dictator would design and implement is not of this world. It is of course 
economist-dictator would design and implement is not of this world. It is of course 
fi ne to recommend patent reform. But if political economy pressures make it impos-
fi ne to recommend patent reform. But if political economy pressures make it impos-
sible to accomplish that reform, or if they make it inevitable that the patent system 
sible to accomplish that reform, or if they make it inevitable that the patent system 
will fail to meet its goals, then abolition-preferably by constitutional means as was 
will fail to meet its goals, then abolition-preferably by constitutional means as was 
the case in Switzerland and the Netherlands prior to the late nineteenth century-is 
the case in Switzerland and the Netherlands prior to the late nineteenth century-is 
the proper solution. This political economy logic brings us to advocate dismantle-
the proper solution. This political economy logic brings us to advocate dismantle-
ment of the patent system. 
ment of the patent system. </p>

<p>The Case Against Patents 15 </p>

<p>The political economy of patent protection is shaped by many players, but 
The political economy of patent protection is shaped by many players, but 
"consumers" are not prominent among them. On one side, the side of the potential 
"consumers" are not prominent among them. On one side, the side of the potential 
patentees, there are individual inventors, corporate inventors, and patent trolls. 
patentees, there are individual inventors, corporate inventors, and patent trolls. 
Other players include the patent offi ce, the patent lawyers who fi le and litigate 
Other players include the patent offi ce, the patent lawyers who fi le and litigate 
patents, and the courts where the litigation takes place. The rules of the game are 
patents, and the courts where the litigation takes place. The rules of the game are 
established by some combination of legislation, judicial action, and custom. But 
established by some combination of legislation, judicial action, and custom. But 
because patenting is a technical subject about which few voters know anything 
because patenting is a technical subject about which few voters know anything 
with clarity, interests of voters are not well represented. In many spheres of govern-
with clarity, interests of voters are not well represented. In many spheres of govern-
ment regulation, this lack of representation for voters has often led to "regulatory 
ment regulation, this lack of representation for voters has often led to "regulatory 
capture"-as Stigler (1971) and other public choice theorists have argued-where 
capture"-as Stigler (1971) and other public choice theorists have argued-where 
regulators act in the interests of the regulated, not the broader public. Nowadays, 
regulators act in the interests of the regulated, not the broader public. Nowadays, 
if there is one "regulator" who is captured, it is the one in charge of regulating 
if there is one "regulator" who is captured, it is the one in charge of regulating 
patents. To understand why, we need to understand the motivation and incentives 
patents. To understand why, we need to understand the motivation and incentives 
of the relevant players. 
of the relevant players. 
Let us start with the US Patent Offi ce and the infamous "one-click" patent 
Let us start with the US Patent Offi ce and the infamous "one-click" patent 
#5960411 issued to Amazon in September 1999. According to 35 U.S.C. 103, the 
#5960411 issued to Amazon in September 1999. According to 35 U.S.C. 103, the 
statute under which the Patent Offi ce operates, to obtain a patent "the differences 
statute under which the Patent Offi ce operates, to obtain a patent "the differences 
between the subject matter sought to be patented and the prior art are such that 
between the subject matter sought to be patented and the prior art are such that 
the subject matter as a whole would have been not obvious at the time the inven-
the subject matter as a whole would have been not obvious at the time the inven-
tion was made to a person having ordinary skill in the art to which said subject 
tion was made to a person having ordinary skill in the art to which said subject 
matter pertains . . ." Now consider the patent in question, which claims, among 
matter pertains . . ." Now consider the patent in question, which claims, among 
other things, a monopoly over: 
other things, a monopoly over: </p>

<p>11. A method for ordering an item using a client system, the method com-
prising: displaying information identifying the item and displaying an indica-
tion of a single action that is to be performed to order the identifi ed item; 
and in response to only the indicated single action being performed, sending 
to a server system a request to order the identifi ed item whereby the item is 
ordered independently of a shopping cart model and the order is fulfi lled to 
complete a purchase of the item. </p>

<p>The idea of taking a single action to accomplish a goal is hardly innovative, and 
applying the idea of taking a single action to making a purchase is obvious to anybody 
who has ever used a soft drink machine. Purchases were already being made over 
the Internet in 1999. It was thus clear that orders would be made by a credit card, 
and either the credit card information would be provided at the time of the transac-
tion, or stored in advance by the retailer. Either way, the user must identify itself 
when the purchase is made. Those obvious steps are exactly what Amazon describes 
in its patent, albeit with a few fl ow charts thrown into the eleven-page patent appli-
cation. But through the fog of those fl ow charts, it is relatively easy to see that the 
verbal description of the single-click procedure applies equally well to what happens 
on the Amazon site and to what happens in front of millions of vending machines 
every day. The Amazon patent was reexamined by the US Patent Offi ce starting in 
May 2006. After a preliminary fi nding that, indeed, "obvious" means "obvious" even </p>



<p>at the Patent Offi ce, the offi ce then reversed itself and in October 2007, reaffi rmed 
the Amazon patent, albeit limiting its scope slightly. So we cannot dismiss such an 
absurd patent as an aberration. 
What lead the US Patent Offi ce to interpret, essentially, the words "not obvious" 
What lead the US Patent Offi ce to interpret, essentially, the words "not obvious" 
as meaning "obvious"? The Patent Offi ce is constantly under pressure from appli-
as meaning "obvious"? The Patent Offi ce is constantly under pressure from appli-
cants and their lawyers to be more generous in issuing patents-that is, to adopt 
cants and their lawyers to be more generous in issuing patents-that is, to adopt 
lower standards of obviousness and steeper standards for what is considered "prior 
lower standards of obviousness and steeper standards for what is considered "prior 
art." The following statement by David Kappos (2010), director of the US Patent 
art." The following statement by David Kappos (2010), director of the US Patent 
Offi ce concerning the allowance rate-what fraction of patents are accepted-is 
Offi ce concerning the allowance rate-what fraction of patents are accepted-is 
revealing: "Overall in FY 2010, the allowance rate increased to 45.6%, compared to 
revealing: "Overall in FY 2010, the allowance rate increased to 45.6%, compared to 
an allowance rate of 41.3% in FY 2009 . . . So, while we still have a lot of work to do, 
an allowance rate of 41.3% in FY 2009 . . . So, while we still have a lot of work to do, 
I think we are on the right path." Apparently, accepting a higher fraction of patents 
I think we are on the right path." Apparently, accepting a higher fraction of patents 
applications is defi ned as "the right path." Talk about "regulatory capture"! 
applications is defi ned as "the right path." Talk about "regulatory capture"! 
Patent lawyers play a large role in the political economy of patents. According 
Patent lawyers play a large role in the political economy of patents. According 
to Quinn (2011), who is a patent attorney, legal fees for fi ling a patent run upwards 
to Quinn (2011), who is a patent attorney, legal fees for fi ling a patent run upwards 
of $7,000 and roughly half are rejected. In 2010, according to the US Patent Offi ce, 
of $7,000 and roughly half are rejected. In 2010, according to the US Patent Offi ce, 
244,341 patents were issued, which would imply roughly $3 billion in legal fees per 
244,341 patents were issued, which would imply roughly $3 billion in legal fees per 
year. Obviously, patent attorneys as a group have a tremendous incentive to see 
year. Obviously, patent attorneys as a group have a tremendous incentive to see 
that more patents are issued. This insight helps us understand better the role of 
that more patents are issued. This insight helps us understand better the role of 
the courts and their relatively recent reform. In 1982-lobbied by patent lawyers-
the courts and their relatively recent reform. In 1982-lobbied by patent lawyers-
Congress passed the Federal Courts Improvement Act, which moved federal patent 
Congress passed the Federal Courts Improvement Act, which moved federal patent 
appeals out of the regular court system to a special court system for dealing with 
appeals out of the regular court system to a special court system for dealing with 
patents. Naturally, many of the judges for this new court were chosen from the ranks 
patents. Naturally, many of the judges for this new court were chosen from the ranks 
of patent attorneys. For example, when a court voted, in a 1994 decision, to expand 
of patent attorneys. For example, when a court voted, in a 1994 decision, to expand 
the scope of patents to software (In 
the scope of patents to software (In re Kuriappan P. Alappat, Edward E. Averill and  James G. Larsen 33 F.3d 1526 [ July 29, 1994]), of the six judges who voted in favor, half 
[ July 29, 1994]), of the six judges who voted in favor, half 
had previously been patent attorneys, while of the two that voted against, neither 
had previously been patent attorneys, while of the two that voted against, neither 
had been. The referee of the patent game is biased both materially and ideologi-
had been. The referee of the patent game is biased both materially and ideologi-
cally. As Landes and Posner (2004, p. 26) write in their discussion of the political 
cally. As Landes and Posner (2004, p. 26) write in their discussion of the political 
economy of patents: "That has been the experience with the Federal Circuit; it has 
economy of patents: "That has been the experience with the Federal Circuit; it has 
defi ned its mission as promoting technological progress by enlarging patent rights." 
defi ned its mission as promoting technological progress by enlarging patent rights." 
Notice, too, that many patent lawsuits have a public goods aspect. Consider 
Notice, too, that many patent lawsuits have a public goods aspect. Consider 
a case in which the plaintiff is asserting that its patent has been infringed. If the 
a case in which the plaintiff is asserting that its patent has been infringed. If the 
plaintiff wins the lawsuit, by confi rming its monopoly position it appropriates all 
plaintiff wins the lawsuit, by confi rming its monopoly position it appropriates all 
the benefi ts of winning the lawsuit. A victory by the defendant, by contrast, benefi ts 
the benefi ts of winning the lawsuit. A victory by the defendant, by contrast, benefi ts 
partly itself, but also other fi rms that might be sued by the plaintiff for patent 
partly itself, but also other fi rms that might be sued by the plaintiff for patent 
infringement as well as consumers who would have a more competitive market. 
infringement as well as consumers who would have a more competitive market. 
Thus, the defendant receives only a slice of the overall benefi ts from winning the 
Thus, the defendant receives only a slice of the overall benefi ts from winning the 
lawsuit, and will be willing to spend less on such lawsuits than it would if it were to 
lawsuit, and will be willing to spend less on such lawsuits than it would if it were to 
receive all the benefi ts. This dynamic is nothing but the patent court version of the 
receive all the benefi ts. This dynamic is nothing but the patent court version of the 
(already noted) fundamental asymmetry in the distribution of economic incentives 
(already noted) fundamental asymmetry in the distribution of economic incentives 
that defi nes the foundations of the political economy of patent law. 
that defi nes the foundations of the political economy of patent law. 
Finally, political economy can be infl uenced by how standard terminology 
Finally, political economy can be infl uenced by how standard terminology 
frames a problem. Landes and Posner (2004) point out that there is an "ideological" 
frames a problem. Landes and Posner (2004) point out that there is an "ideological" </p>

<p>Miche le Boldrin and David K. Levine 17 </p>

<p>argument in support of stronger patent rights: supporters of free markets tend to 
argument in support of stronger patent rights: supporters of free markets tend to 
favor institutions of private property, and patents and copyright are intellectual 
favor institutions of private property, and patents and copyright are intellectual 
"property." Hence, strengthening them is ideologically and politically consistent 
"property." Hence, strengthening them is ideologically and politically consistent 
with the general principle that "private property is good for growth." But as we 
with the general principle that "private property is good for growth." But as we 
(Boldrin and Levine 2008b) and many others elsewhere have argued, patents are 
(Boldrin and Levine 2008b) and many others elsewhere have argued, patents are 
just a monopoly, not property. 
just a monopoly, not property. 
Given this set of players and their incentives, the patent game moves naturally 
Given this set of players and their incentives, the patent game moves naturally 
towards its equilibrium, as we have observed over time. Two centuries or so ago, 
towards its equilibrium, as we have observed over time. Two centuries or so ago, 
patents were restricted in their areas of applicability and limited in both depth and 
patents were restricted in their areas of applicability and limited in both depth and 
duration over time; they were somewhat "reasonable," to the extent social gains 
duration over time; they were somewhat "reasonable," to the extent social gains 
and costs seemed balanced. But we have witnessed a steady process of enlargement 
and costs seemed balanced. But we have witnessed a steady process of enlargement 
and strengthening of patent laws. At each stage, the main driving force was the 
and strengthening of patent laws. At each stage, the main driving force was the 
rent-seeking efforts of large, cash-rich companies unable to keep up with new and 
rent-seeking efforts of large, cash-rich companies unable to keep up with new and 
creative competitors. Patent lawyers, patent offi cials, and wannabe patent trolls 
creative competitors. Patent lawyers, patent offi cials, and wannabe patent trolls 
usually acted as foot soldiers. While this political economy process is pretty straight-
usually acted as foot soldiers. While this political economy process is pretty straight-
forward in broad terms, we are still missing an empirical, quantitative analysis of the 
forward in broad terms, we are still missing an empirical, quantitative analysis of the 
stakes involved and of the gains and losses accruing to both the active players and 
stakes involved and of the gains and losses accruing to both the active players and 
to the rest of society, from the general public to the innovators that never emerged 
to the rest of society, from the general public to the innovators that never emerged 
due to preexisting patent barriers. 
due to preexisting patent barriers. 
Perhaps surprisingly, despite the key importance of political economy in under-
Perhaps surprisingly, despite the key importance of political economy in under-
standing why we have the patent system we have, economists have had relatively 
standing why we have the patent system we have, economists have had relatively 
little to say on the subject. The few prominent papers that we know of on this subject 
little to say on the subject. The few prominent papers that we know of on this subject 
typically build from analyses very similar to what we have presented here-but then 
typically build from analyses very similar to what we have presented here-but then 
shy away from drawing the logical conclusions. 
shy away from drawing the logical conclusions. 
For example, Landes and Posner (2004) recognize that patent laws are mostly 
For example, Landes and Posner (2004) recognize that patent laws are mostly 
designed by interest groups keen to increase their monopoly rents, not aggregate 
designed by interest groups keen to increase their monopoly rents, not aggregate 
welfare, and that this drove the enormous growth in patent legislation and judi-
welfare, and that this drove the enormous growth in patent legislation and judi-
ciary activity during the last 30 years. The more elaborate writing by Scherer (2009)  ciary activity during the last 30 years. The more elaborate writing by Scherer (2009)  on "The Political Economy of Patent Policy Reform in the United States" follows 
on "The Political Economy of Patent Policy Reform in the United States" follows 
a similar approach. It focuses on the fact that "government emphasis on patent 
a similar approach. It focuses on the fact that "government emphasis on patent 
systems increased" while academic research was starting to become more and more 
systems increased" while academic research was starting to become more and more 
aware that patents are playing a minor positive role, if any at all, in creating incen-
aware that patents are playing a minor positive role, if any at all, in creating incen-
tives for high R&amp;D and in fostering productivity growth. After providing a concise 
tives for high R&amp;D and in fostering productivity growth. After providing a concise 
and very well-informed historical survey of all major changes in US patent policies 
and very well-informed historical survey of all major changes in US patent policies 
over the last century or so, Scherer (p. 195) wonders why the political system would 
over the last century or so, Scherer (p. 195) wonders why the political system would 
increase patent protection so much in light of the fact "that the record of debates 
increase patent protection so much in light of the fact "that the record of debates 
on the enabling bill contains no solid evidence that the change would in fact stimu-
on the enabling bill contains no solid evidence that the change would in fact stimu-
late R&amp;D, and that there is no evidence of an acceleration in company-fi nanced 
late R&amp;D, and that there is no evidence of an acceleration in company-fi nanced 
R&amp;D between the 27 years before the bill was enacted and the 18 years thereafter." 
R&amp;D between the 27 years before the bill was enacted and the 18 years thereafter." 
He then extends the same argument to the international arena, paying particular 
He then extends the same argument to the international arena, paying particular 
attention to the case of pharmaceutical patents. While Scherer's language and argu-
attention to the case of pharmaceutical patents. While Scherer's language and argu-
ments are strongly critical of current trends in patents, he does not seek to explain 
ments are strongly critical of current trends in patents, he does not seek to explain 
why an institution, such as the patent system, that was supposed to be theoretically 
why an institution, such as the patent system, that was supposed to be theoretically 
sound would degenerate into something so socially damaging over same 30-year 
sound would degenerate into something so socially damaging over same 30-year </p>



<p>period that academic researchers were realizing the institution's limitations and 
period that academic researchers were realizing the institution's limitations and 
potential dangerousness. 
potential dangerousness. 
In our view, even insightful writers such as Landes and Posner (2004) and 
In our view, even insightful writers such as Landes and Posner (2004) and 
Scherer (2009) seem unable to shake themselves free of the belief that patents are 
Scherer (2009) seem unable to shake themselves free of the belief that patents are 
essential in fostering innovation and that any problems can be fi xed with some 
essential in fostering innovation and that any problems can be fi xed with some 
tweaks to the patent system; they fail to seriously consider the possibility of intrinsic 
tweaks to the patent system; they fail to seriously consider the possibility of intrinsic 
problems with the design of the institution itself. This belief in patents fl ies in the 
problems with the design of the institution itself. This belief in patents fl ies in the 
face of the structural realities: Marginal extensions of patents result in substantially 
face of the structural realities: Marginal extensions of patents result in substantially 
higher per capita rents for the few holders of the right while marginally reducing 
higher per capita rents for the few holders of the right while marginally reducing 
the individual welfare of the much larger number of nonpatent holders. The rent 
the individual welfare of the much larger number of nonpatent holders. The rent 
of the monopolist is a lot higher than an individual consumer's deadweight loss, 
of the monopolist is a lot higher than an individual consumer's deadweight loss, 
so the monopolist has an incentive to perpetuate the system while the individual 
so the monopolist has an incentive to perpetuate the system while the individual 
consumer has no incentive to fi ght it. Those who possess a patent do not hold a 
consumer has no incentive to fi ght it. Those who possess a patent do not hold a 
"property right" in the conventional sense of that term, but they do hold a socially 
"property right" in the conventional sense of that term, but they do hold a socially 
granted "monopoly" right, and will tend to leverage whatever initial rents their 
granted "monopoly" right, and will tend to leverage whatever initial rents their 
monopoly provides in order to increase their monopoly power until all potential 
monopoly provides in order to increase their monopoly power until all potential 
rents are extracted (and, in all likelihood, also largely dissipated by the associated 
rents are extracted (and, in all likelihood, also largely dissipated by the associated 
lobbying and transaction costs). This scenario helps explain how patents interact 
lobbying and transaction costs). This scenario helps explain how patents interact 
with the industry lifecycle -why patents are either ignored or scarcely used in new 
with the industry lifecycle -why patents are either ignored or scarcely used in new 
and competitive industries, while being highly valued and overused in mature and 
and competitive industries, while being highly valued and overused in mature and 
highly concentrated ones. 
highly concentrated ones. </p>

<p>Conclusion Conclusion </p>

<p>In 1958, the distinguished economist Fritz Machlup in testimony before 
In 1958, the distinguished economist Fritz Machlup in testimony before 
Congress famously said: "If we did not have a patent system, it would be irrespon-
Congress famously said: "If we did not have a patent system, it would be irrespon-
sible, on the basis of our present knowledge of its economic consequences, to 
sible, on the basis of our present knowledge of its economic consequences, to 
recommend instituting one. But since we have had a patent system for a long time, it 
recommend instituting one. But since we have had a patent system for a long time, it 
would be irresponsible, on the basis of our present knowledge, to recommend abol-
would be irresponsible, on the basis of our present knowledge, to recommend abol-
ishing it." A proposal to abolish patents may seem "pie in the sky." Certainly, many 
ishing it." A proposal to abolish patents may seem "pie in the sky." Certainly, many 
interim measures could be taken to mitigate the damage caused by the current 
interim measures could be taken to mitigate the damage caused by the current 
system: for example, properly enforcing the standard that patents should only be 
system: for example, properly enforcing the standard that patents should only be 
granted for nonobvious insights; requiring genuine disclosure of working methods 
granted for nonobvious insights; requiring genuine disclosure of working methods 
in patents (the opposite of certain recent "protectionist" proposals to institute 
in patents (the opposite of certain recent "protectionist" proposals to institute 
secret patents); and allowing an "independent invention" defense against claims of 
secret patents); and allowing an "independent invention" defense against claims of 
patent infringement. But why use band-aids to staunch a major wound? Economists 
patent infringement. But why use band-aids to staunch a major wound? Economists 
fought for decades-ultimately with considerable success-to reduce restrictions on 
fought for decades-ultimately with considerable success-to reduce restrictions on 
international trade. A similar approach, albeit less slow, should be adopted to phase 
international trade. A similar approach, albeit less slow, should be adopted to phase 
out patents. Because policy proposals are often better digested and metabolized in 
out patents. Because policy proposals are often better digested and metabolized in 
small bites, here is our list of small reforms that could be easily implemented. 
small bites, here is our list of small reforms that could be easily implemented. </p>

<p>1) Patents are time limited, which makes it relatively easy to phase them out by 
phasing in ever shorter patent durations. This conservative approach also </p>

<p>The Case Against Patents 19 </p>

<p>has the advantage that if reducing patent terms indeed has a measurable 
effect on innovation, the process can be reversed. 
2) Stop the rising tide that, since the early 1980s, has extended the set of what 
can be patented and has shifted the legal and judicial balance substantially 
in favor of patent holders. 
3) Because competition fosters productivity growth, antitrust and competition 
policies should seek to limit patents when they are hindering innovation. 
This policy may be of particular relevance for high-tech sectors, from soft-
ware to bioengineering, to medical products and pharmaceuticals. 
4) Current international trade negotiations that affect patents often occur 
as part of either the Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual 
Property Rights (TRIPS), which was signed in 1995 as part of the World Trade 
Organization negotiations, or as part of the World Intellectual Property 
Organization, an agency of the United Nations. The nature of these agree-
ments and organizations is well indicated by the use of the propaganda term 
"intellectual property" in their titles. In both cases, these talks are often 
focused on how to prevent ideas from high-income countries from being used 
in low-income countries-what we would characterize as essentially a neo-
mercantilist approach toward free trade in goods and ideas. We should be 
highly cautious about this agenda. Within a couple of decades, the "balance 
of trade in ideas" between the US and European economies and emerging 
economies in Asia might easily equalize or reverse. Engaging in "mercantilism 
of ideas" may seem favorable to certain large US fi rms now, but such rules may 
become costly to the US economy if they are applied to protect patents held 
in the future by producers in the now-developing Asian economies. 
5) If the US economy is to have patents, we may want to start tailoring their 
length and breadth to different sectoral needs. Substantial empirical work 
needs to be done to implement this properly, although a vast legal literature 
is already pointing in this direction. 
6) Patents should not be granted based only on technological insights, but 
should also take economic evidence into account. For example, if an inven-
tion is easy to copy or has a high fi xed cost, then patent protection to pro-
vide an incentive for the inventor may be more suitable. Ultimately, patents 
should be awarded only when strictly needed on economic grounds, as 
spelled out earlier. 
7) We advocate returning to the rule prior to the Bayh-Dole Act of 1980 accord-
ing to which the results of federally subsidized research cannot lead to pat-
ents, but should be available to all market participants. This reform would 
be particularly useful for encouraging the dissemination of innovation and 
heightening competition in the pharmaceutical industry. 
8) In several industries, notably pharmaceuticals, it would be useful to rethink 
all of the government policies that bear on incentives for invention. The 
broad point is that there are a number of ways to reduce the risks and cost of 
developing new drugs, rather than just trying to ratchet up patent protection. </p>



<p>In general, public policy should aim to decrease patent monopolies gradu-
ally but surely, and the ultimate goal should be the abolition of patents. After 
six decades of further study since Machlup's testimony in 1958 has failed to fi nd 
evidence that patents promote the common good, it is surely time to reassess 
his conclusion that it would be irresponsible to abolish the patent system. The 
patent system arose as a way to limit the power of royalty to award monopolies to 
favored individuals; but now its primary effect is to encourage large but stagnant 
incumbent fi rms to block innovation and inhibit competition. </p>

<p> We are grateful to the editors, the referees, and to Richard Stallman for a careful reading 
and comments. </p>



<p>Miche le Boldrin and David K. Levine 21 </p>







<p>This article has been cited by: </p>



</text></tei>