<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Faer.20160542" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Online prices are increasingly used for measurement and research 
applications, yet little is known about their relation to prices col-
lected offline, where most retail transactions take place. I conduct the 
first large-scale comparison of prices simultaneously collected from 
the websites and physical stores of 56 large multi-channel retailers 
in 10 countries. I find that price levels are identical about 72 per-
cent of the time. Price changes are not synchronized but have similar 
frequencies and average sizes. These results have implications for 
national statistical offices, researchers using online data, and any-
one interested in the effect of the Internet on retail prices. </p>

<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>stores. The question is important because relatively few retail transactions take place 
online. In fact, according to Euromonitor (2014), online purchases are currently less 
than 10 percent of all retail transactions in the United States, and even lower in other 
countries. 
This paper provides the first large-scale comparison of online and offline prices 
in large multi-channel retailers designed to answer this question. Using a combina-
tion of crowdsourcing platforms, a mobile phone app, and web scraping methods, I 
simultaneously collected prices in both the online and offline stores of 56 of the larg-
est retailers in 10 countries: Argentina, Australia, Brazil, Canada, China, Germany, 
Japan, South Africa, United Kingdom, and the United States. These data are used to 
compare price levels, the behavior of price changes, and the selection of products 
available for sale in the offline and online stores. I document country, sector, and 
retailer heterogeneity, and test whether online prices vary with IP address locations 
or persistent browsing habits. The results have implications for NSOs and research-
ers using online data, as well as those interested in the effect of the Internet on retail 
prices. 
The data collection effort is unprecedented in scope and size, and was carried 
out as part of the BPP. I first selected the retailers to be sampled by focusing on 
the top 20 companies by market shares in each country that sell both online and 
offline (" multi-channel"), and have product barcodes that can be matched across 
samples. Next, I used crowdsourcing platforms such as <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Amazon</rs> <rs id="software-1" type="software">Mechanical Turk</rs>, 
<rs type="software">Elance</rs>, and <rs type="software">UpWork</rs> to hire 323 workers to collect the offline data. Each worker 
was assigned a simple task: to scan the barcodes and collect prices for a random set 
of 10 to 50 products in any physical store of a given retailer. In some cases they had 
to return to the same store multiple times to scan the same set of products. Using 
a special app for android phones developed to simplify and standardize the data 
collection process, these workers scanned each product's barcode, manually entered 
the price, took a photo of the price tag, and sent all the information via e-mail to the 
BPP servers, where it was automatically processed and cleaned. A scraping software 
then used the barcode numbers to look for the same product in the website of each 
retailer, and collected the online price within a period of seven days. The matched 
online-offline dataset contains prices for more than 24,000 products and 38,000 
observations sampled between December 2014 and March 2016. 
The main finding is that online and offline price levels are identical about 72 per-
cent of the time, with significant heterogeneity at the country, sector, and retailer 
level. These percentages range from 42 percent in Brazil to 91 percent in Canada 
and the United Kingdom. The United States is close to the average, with 69 percent. 
At the sector level, drugstores and office-product retailers have the lowest share of 
identical prices, with 38 percent and 25 percent, respectively, while in electronics 
and clothing these numbers rise to 83 percent and 92 percent, respectively. When 
there is a price difference, the online markup tends to be small, with a magnitude 
of −4 percent in the full sample. If I include observations with identical prices, the 
online price difference is only −1 percent on average. 
I also find that price changes have similar frequencies and sizes in the online and 
offline data. However, only 19 percent of weekly price changes occur at the same 
time. While this is higher than the unconditional probability of a simultaneous price 
change, the individual price series are not well synchronized. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>The reasons for the online-offline price differences seem to vary across retailers 
and countries. Sales tend to create some discrepancies, with only 36 percent of sale 
prices being identical across samples, but they have a small impact in the aggregate 
results because the number of sale observations is relatively small (11 percent of the 
total dataset). A similar thing happens with offline price dispersion across physical 
stores, which tends to be low. Using a small sample of offline prices collected for 
multiple zip codes on the same day, I find that about 78 percent of goods have a 
single price within stores of the same retailer. I also found no evidence of "dynamic 
pricing" strategies that could potentially cause online-offline differences. At least in 
the United States, online prices do not change with the location of the IP address 
of the computer connecting to the website or when the scraping robot repeatedly 
browses the same web page of a particular good for a prolonged period of time. 
There is also no evidence that online-offline price differences are being driven by 
attempts to match the prices of Amazon.com, which are identical to the online prices 
in multi-channel retailers about 38 percent of the time. 
In terms of product selection, 76 percent of the products sampled offline were 
also found online by either using the automated scraping matching or by manu-
ally searching for the product description on the website. The price comparison 
results for goods that can be automatically matched are similar to those that had to 
be manually matched. There is also no evidence that retailers try to obfuscate the 
online-offline price comparisons by changing the products' identification numbers. 
Despite the general similarity in online and offline prices, there is significant 
heterogeneity in pricing behaviors across retailers. Three main types of compa-
nies stand out: those with nearly identical online and offline prices, those with 
stable online markups (either positive or negative), and those with different prices 
that are not consistently higher or lower online. Some of these patterns seem to 
be sector-level behaviors, while others are common for most retailers within a 
country. 
For research economists using online data, these results provide evidence that 
most large multi-channel retailers price similarly online and offline. There are both 
advantages and disadvantages of using online data, as I discuss in Cavallo (forth-
coming), but the ability to collect a massive amount of prices so cheaply provides 
unprecedented opportunities for economic research. My results suggest that these 
prices are valid sources of information for retail transactions, even those that take 
place offline. Retailer heterogeneity, however, implies that researchers using rela-
tively few sources of data should be cautious to understand particular pricing pat-
terns and control for any sampling biases. 
For NSOs, these results imply that the web can be effectively used as an alter-
native data-collection technology to obtain the same prices found offline. Prices 
collected through the web are very similar to those that can be obtained at a much 
higher cost by physically walking into a store. While many challenges to the use 
of online data in CPIs remain, such as the more limited sectoral coverage or the 
lack of quantity data, my results should help alleviate concerns about the peculiar-
ities of prices collected online. The BPP app and methodology developed in this 
paper are also publicly available at bpp.mit.edu to be used for more country and 
retailer-specific validation tests, which are sensible given the high degree of hetero-
geneity in pricing behaviors. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>Lastly, my findings have implications for people interested in the effects of the 
Internet on retail prices. The fact that online prices are the same for all locations and 
also similar to offline prices collected from many different zip codes implies there 
is little within-retailer price dispersion. I also show this explicitly with some offline 
data in multiple zip codes in Section IVB. In practice, most retailers seem to have a 
single price for the majority of products, regardless of the location of the buyer and 
whether the product is sold online or at a particular offline store. This suggests that 
while the web has not reduced price dispersion across different retailers, as docu-
mented by a large literature surveyed by Baye, Morgan, and Scholten (2006), it may 
have created incentives for firms to price identically in their own stores. This type 
of within-retailer price dispersion has received little attention in the literature, even 
though it could have large welfare implications within countries. 
This paper is related to a literature that studies the behavior of online prices. 
Some papers written in the early 2000s compared manually-collected prices of 
online retailers and traditional brick-and-mortar stores in a few narrow catego-
ries of goods. For example, Brynjolfsson and Smith (2000) compared prices for 
CDs and books in both online-only and multi-channel retailers ("hybrids" in their 
notation). They report that online prices were 9-16 percent lower and had smaller 
price changes, but note that "findings would be strengthened if we excluded hybrid 
retailers from our comparisons of price levels," which implies that online and 
offline prices for multi-channel retailers were closer together (Brynjolfsson and  Smith 2000, p. 572). Clay et al. (2002) also found similar prices for 107 books in 
both the websites and some physical stores of Barnes &amp; Noble and Borders, which 
is consistent with my results. 
4 More recent comparisons of online and offline prices 
expanded on the categories covered but were limited to small ad-hoc samples in 
a few stores. Examples include Cavallo, Neiman, and Rigobon (2014, 2015); 
Borraz et al. (2015); and Cavallo (forthcoming). A separate branch of the litera-
ture uses online prices from "shopbots," or price comparison websites, which are 
easier to collect. Examples include Brynjolfsson and Smith (2001); Brynjolfsson,  Dick, and Smith (2009); Ellison and Ellison (2009a, b); Lunnemann and Wintr  (2011); Gorodnichenko, Sheremirov, and Talavera (2014); and Gorodnichenko  and Talavera (2017). Although these papers do not directly compare prices with 
offline data, their results suggest that online prices change more frequently and 
with smaller sizes than comparable findings in papers with offline CPI prices. The 
difference with my findings is likely caused by their focus on retailers that partic-
ipate in price-comparison websites. As Ellison and Ellison (2009a) discuss, such 
retailers face a uniquely competitive environment that can significantly affect their 
pricing behaviors. </p>

<p>4 For other papers in this literature, see OECD (1998); Tang and Xing (2001); Clemons, Hann, and Hitt (2002); 
and Xing, Yang, and Tang (2006). </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>I. Simultaneous Online-Offline Data Collection </p>

<p>A. Multi-Channel Retailers </p>

<p>There are many types of "online prices," from those in marketplaces such as 
eBay, online-only retailers such as Amazon, and those at stores with both an online 
and offline presence. In this paper, I focus on the prices of large " multi-channel" 
retailers that sell both online and offline. When considering all retail sales, this type 
of retailer still concentrates the vast majority of all retail transactions, making them 
the most important source of price data for applications that require "representative" 
data (such as inflation measurement). Despite its importance, this is also the type 
of online price that has received the least attention in the academic literature due to 
lack of data. Furthermore, as pointed out by Brynjolfsson, Hu, and Rahman (2013), 
technology is blurring the distinctions between physical and online retailing, mak-
ing both traditional brick-and-mortar and online-only companies behave increas-
ingly like multi-channel retailers. </p>

<p>B. Retailer Selection </p>

<p>The names of the retailers included in the data collection are shown in Table 1. 
They satisfy three conditions. First, they are in the list of top 20 retailers by mar-
ket share in their respective countries. The rank information was obtained from 
Euromonitor International's Passport Retailing Global Rankings. This condition 
helps to ensure a representative sample of the retail sector. Second, they sell both 
online through a country-specific website and offline through physical stores. Most 
large retailers satisfy this condition. Third, there is a way to perfectly match prod-
ucts online and offline. In practice, this means that the product id number collected 
offline can be used to find the product on the website. </p>

<p>C. Collecting Offline Prices in Physical Stores </p>

<p>Collecting prices offline is normally an expensive and complicated process. NSOs 
rely on a large number of trained data collectors to do it correctly. Unfortunately, the 
micro data collected by NSOs for CPI purposes cannot be used for my comparisons 
because the retailer and product details are confidential information. Lacking the 
budget for a traditional data collection effort, I looked for alternatives using new 
technologies. In particular, I relied on popular crowdsourcing platforms, such as 
<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Amazon</rs> <rs id="software-7" type="software">Mechanical Turk</rs>, <rs type="software">Elance</rs>, and <rs type="software">UpWork</rs>, to find people willing to do simple 
data collection tasks. To minimize the chance of data-entry errors, I developed a 
custom mobile phone app that simplified the data collection process. 
Crowdsourcing platforms have many advantages. First, they allowed me to hire 
a large number of workers and reach multiple locations and cities within each 
country. Second, there were enough workers to limit the number of individual 
prices that each had to collect. This reduced the burden on the worker and also 
minimized the " showrooming" concerns of the retailers. Showrooming is a term 
used to describe the practice of visiting a physical store to examine a product but 
later purchasing it online in another store. Many retailers worry about people who </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>use mobile apps to scan the product's barcode and buy products online at other 
retailers, so if the data collectors spent too much time at each store, they might be 
asked to leave. </p>

<p>5   Two main versions of the task were posted on the crowdsourcing websites. In the 
simplest case, the worker had to use a mobile app provided by the BPP team to scan 
10 to 50 random offline products in any physical store, with some basic instructions 
to spread out the data collection across categories of goods. This provided the bulk 
of the data that I use to compare price levels across samples. A more complex ver-
sion of the task required the worker to return to the same store every week for a full 
month and scan the same items. This gave me the panel of prices that I use to study 
price changes in Section III. 
The mobile app was custom-built to simplify and standardize the data collection 
process. It is an app for android phones called "<rs type="software">BPP @ MIT</rs>," available for down-
load at the Google Play Store. 
6 Every time a worker visits a store, she clicks on a 
button to open a new file. For the first product, she has to enter the store's name, zip 
code, and country. Then she scans the UPC barcode of the product (or the barcode 
on the price tag, depending on the particular retailer instructions provided), manu-
ally enters the price shown in the price tag next to the product (including all sales), 
marks the price as "regular" or "sale," and takes a photograph of the price tag (which 
is used to detect errors and validate the data). All products are scanned in a loop 
which makes the process quick and simple. When done, the worker taps an icon to 
e-mail the data to the BPP servers. A member of the BPP team verifies the submitted 
data and pays the worker. </p>

<p>5 I tried to conduct a similar large-scale offline data collection with MIT students in the Boston area in 2011, but 
most of them were asked to stop and leave the stores after some time. Collecting data this way appears to be easier 
now that more people use smartphones inside stores. Indeed, Fitzgerald (2013) reports that the fear of showroom-
ing has faded for many US retailers. See Balakrishnan, Sundaresan, and Zhang (2013) for an economic analysis of 
showrooming practices. 
6 See https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.mit.bpp. The app can be downloaded for free, but a 
"project code" must be requested from the BPP team. This code is used to separate the data from different projects. 
See http://bpp.mit.edu/ offline-data-collection/ for more details. </p>

<p>Table 1-Retailers Included </p>

<p>Argentina 
Carrefour, Coto, Easy, Sodimac, Walmart 
Australia 
Coles, Masters, Target, Woolworths </p>

<p>Brazil 
Droga Raia, Extra, Magazine Luiza, Pao de Azucar, Renner </p>

<p>Canada 
Canadian Tire, Home Depot, The Source, Toys R Us, Walmart 
China 
Auchan Drive, Sams Club </p>

<p>Germany 
Galeria Kaufhof, Obi, Real, Rewe, Saturn </p>

<p>Japan 
Bic Camera, K's Denki, Lawson, Yamada 
South Africa 
Clicks, Dis-Chem Pharmacy, Mr Price, Pick n Pay, Woolworths </p>

<p>United Kingdom 
Asda, Marks and Spencer, Sainsburys, Tesco </p>

<p>United States 
Walmart, Target, Safeway, Stop&amp;Shop, Best Buy, Home Depot, 
Lowe's, CVS, Macy's, Banana Republic, Forever 21, GAP, Nike, 
Urban Outfitters, Old Navy, Staples, OfficeMax/Depot. </p>

<p>Notes: These retailers satisfy three conditions. First, they are in the list of top 20 retailers by mar-
ket share in their respective countries according to Euromonitor International. Second, they sell 
both online through a country-specific website and offline through physical stores. Third, there 
is a way to perfectly match products online and offline for the price comparison. See the online 
Appendix for more detailed characteristics and results. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>Every few hours, the BPP servers automatically processed the incoming offline 
files to clean and consolidate the data for each retailer. The offline barcode informa-
tion was then used to collect the online price from the retailer's website, as described 
below. </p>

<p>D. Collecting Online Prices on Each Retailer's Website </p>

<p>To collect online prices, I built a custom scraping "robot" for each retailer. These 
robots are specialized software that are programmed to use the product barcode to 
query the retailer's website and collect the online price and other product informa-
tion. In most cases, the robot was designed to use the website's search box to enter 
the product id obtained offline. For more general details on the BPP's online scrap-
ing methods, see Cavallo and Rigobon (2016). 
The price collected online is the posted price for the product on the retailer's web-
site, including any sales or discounts that apply to all customers. Whether taxes are 
added or not depends on the display conventions for prices in each country, but the 
same condition applies both online and offline. For example, US prices include sales 
but are typically shown without taxes, both on the website and the price tags found 
in physical stores. In all other countries, sales or value-added tax rates are usually 
included in the price in both locations. Shipping costs are never included in these 
online prices, so my comparisons are for posted prices excluding shipping costs. 
Retailers have different ways to charge for shipping. The most common is a set of 
shipping fees that varies with the total amount of the sale or weight of the products. 
Some retailers offer free shipping, which could mean that they adjust their online 
prices to compensate. The results at the retailer level provide information that can 
be used to determine when this occurs. 
Nearly all of the online retailers in the sample have a single price online for each 
product, independent of the location of the buyer. In other words, someone purchas-
ing a laptop from Best Buy in San Francisco sees the same price as someone doing it 
from Boston. The only exceptions are supermarkets, which sometimes require buy-
ers to enter their zip code or location before displaying prices. There are only five 
retailers that do this in my sample. I always use the same zip code when collecting 
data online, independently of the one where the offline price was obtained, so this 
can cause some price-level differences between the online and offline data for those 
retailers. In the online Appendix, I use a scraping experiment with one of the largest 
US supermarkets to show that even retailers that ask for zip code information tend 
to price their goods identically in most locations. Furthermore, removing this type 
of retailer has little impact on my aggregate results. 
For all benchmark results, I allow online prices to be collected within seven days 
of the offline price and also exclude sale prices. Results are similar for prices col-
lected on the same day, or including sale prices, as shown in the online Appendix. </p>

<p>E. The Online-Offline Matched Data </p>

<p>Table 2 shows the main characteristics of the matched data. I collected prices in 
56 retailers for more than a year, between December 2014 and March 2016. There 
are more than 24,000 products and 38,000 observations in total. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>The data coverage varies across countries. The effort was concentrated in the 
United States, with 17 retailers and about 40 percent of all observations. On the 
other extreme is China, with only two retailers. I was unable to expand the offline 
data collection in China because large retailers explicitly prohibit taking photo-
graphs and recording prices at physical locations. Apparently, showrooming is more 
extended in China, so retailers try to prevent the use of mobile phones in their stores. 
A survey conducted by IBM in 2013 found that about 24 percent of people in China 
admitted to having visited a physical store to buy online, compared with only 4 per-
cent in the United States. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>II. Price Levels </p>

<p>Table 3 compares the price levels across the online and offline samples. Column 3 
shows the percentage of observations that have identical online and offline prices up 
to the second decimal. 
The percentage of identical prices is 72 percent for all pooled observations and 
for the average across countries. Some countries, such as Japan, have percentages 
close to 50 percent, while others such as Canada and the United Kingdom have over 
90 percent of all prices being identical online and offline. The United States is close 
to the average, with 69 percent of identical prices. 
Columns 4 and 5 show the share of prices that are either higher or lower online. 
Conditional on a price difference, most countries tend to have lower online prices, 
with the exception of Argentina and Australia. The three countries with the low-
est percentages of identical prices, where differences matter the most, tend to have 
heterogeneous behaviors. In Argentina, nonidentical prices tend to be higher online, </p>

<p>7 See Klena and Puleri (2013). </p>

<p>Table 2-Data by Country </p>

<p>Retailers 
Start 
End 
Workers 
Zip codes 
Products 
Observations 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>Argentina 
5 
02/15 
08/15 
18 
23 
2,324 
3,699 
Australia 
4 
03/15 
08/15 
13 
22 
3,073 
3,797 
Brazil 
5 
05/15 
03/16 
18 
26 
1,437 
1,915 
Canada 
5 
12/14 
07/15 
15 
45 
2,658 
4,031 
China 
2 
07/15 
03/16 
5 
6 
410 
513 
Germany 
5 
03/15 
03/16 
9 
20 
1,215 
1,604 
Japan 
4 
04/15 
03/16 
7 
23 
1,127 
2,186 
South Africa 
5 
03/15 
03/16 
21 
31 
2,336 
3,212 
United Kingdom 
4 
03/15 
05/15 
12 
32 
1,661 
2,094 
United States 
17 
12/14 
03/16 
206 
274 
7,898 
15,332 </p>

<p>All countries 
56 
12/14 
03/16 
323 
499 
24,132 
38,383 </p>

<p>Notes: Column 1 shows the number of retailers. Columns 2 and 3 show the start and end months of data collection. 
Columns 4 and 5 report the number of workers that collected the data and zip codes with offline prices. Columns 
6 and 7 provide the number of products and price observations that could be matched with both online and offline 
information. Details by retailer are provided in the online Appendix. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>with an average markup of 3 percent. In Brazil, they are lower, with a markup of 
−7 percent. Japan is an outlier, with prices that are lower online 45 percent of the 
time, with an average markup of −13 percent. 
The average size of the price differences is quite small. This can be seen in 
columns 6 and 7, where a positive number means that prices are higher online. 
Column 6 shows the online "markup," excluding cases where prices are identical, 
while column 7 shows the online "difference," which includes cases with no price 
difference. The online markup tends to be small, with a magnitude of −4 percent 
in the full sample. Adding prices that are identical makes the online-offline price 
difference only −1 percent on average. 
Overall, these results show little difference between online prices collected from 
the website of multi-channel retailers and the offline prices that can be obtained by 
visiting one of their physical stores. 
The aggregate results, however, hide important heterogeneity at the sector level. 
Table 4 shows similar results for retailers grouped by the type of good they sell. 
Drugstores and office-supply retailers have the lowest share of identical prices 
online and offline. For office products, prices are sometimes higher and sometimes 
lower online, without any clear patterns, as if the stores were managed independently. 
Drugstores, by contrast, tend to have lower prices online, possibly because they are 
"convenience" stores such as CVS and Walgreens in the United States that may 
charge higher prices to offline customers. 
Electronics and clothing have the highest share of identical prices. For clothing, 
prices are basically the same, with most of the observed differences possibly coming 
from offline data collection errors. For electronics, prices are lower online 13 per-
cent of the time, with an average markup of −9 percent (the highest in this sample). 
Figure 1 shows the histograms for nonzero price differences in each country. The 
cases of Argentina and Australia stand out because there are spikes around the 5 per-
cent magnitude of differences. This is caused by stable markups in online prices for </p>

<p>Table 3-Country: Price-Level Differences (Percent) </p>

<p>Retailers Observations Identical </p>

<p>Higher 
online </p>

<p>Lower 
online </p>

<p>Online 
markup </p>

<p>Online 
difference 
Country 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>Argentina 
5 
3,699 
60 
27 
13 
3 
1 
Australia 
4 
3,797 
74 
20 
5 
5 
1 
Brazil 
5 
1,915 
42 
18 
40 
−7 
−4 
Canada 
5 
4,031 
91 
3 
5 
−5 
0 
China 
2 
513 
87 
7 
6 
3 
0 
Germany 
5 
1,604 
74 
4 
23 
−8 
−2 
Japan 
4 
2,186 
48 
7 
45 
−13 
−7 
South Africa 
5 
3,212 
85 
6 
9 
−3 
−1 
United Kingdom 
4 
2,094 
91 
2 
7 
−8 
−1 
United States 
17 
15,332 
69 
8 
22 
−5 
−1 </p>

<p>All countries 
56 
38,383 
72 
11 
18 
−4 
−1 </p>

<p>Notes: Column 3 shows the percentage of observations that have identical online and offline prices. Column 4 
shows the percent of observation where prices are higher online and column 5 the percentage of prices that are lower 
online. Column 6 shows the online markup, defined as the average price difference excluding cases that are identi-
cal. Column 7 shows the average price difference including identical prices. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>some of the largest retailers. In all other countries, the price differences are more 
dispersed in the range of −50 percent to 50 percent. 
As pointed out by Nakamura and Steinsson (2008), sale events are frequent in 
some countries, and the magnitude of the price changes that they generate can be 
large. I do find that sale prices create more differences between online and offline 
samples, the share of identical online and offline prices for sale observations being 
only 36 percent. But this has little impact on the full-sample results because the </p>

<p>Table 4-Sector: Price-Level Differences (Percent) </p>

<p>Retailers Observations Identical </p>

<p>Higher 
online </p>

<p>Lower 
online </p>

<p>Online 
markup </p>

<p>Online 
difference 
Sector 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>Food 
10 
5,953 
52 
32 
15 
3 
1 
Clothing 
7 
2,534 
92 
5 
3 
3 
0 
Household 
9 
7,875 
79 
5 
16 
−8 
−2 
Drugstore 
4 
3,053 
38 
11 
52 
−5 
−3 
Electronics 
5 
3,712 
83 
4 
13 
−9 
−1 
Office 
2 
1,089 
25 
37 
38 
1 
1 
Multiple/Mix 
18 
14,149 
80 
5 
15 
−9 
−2 </p>

<p>Notes: Data classified into sectors at the retailer level. Column 3 shows the percentage of observations that have iden-
tical online and offline prices. Column 4 shows the percent of observation where prices are higher online and column 
5 the percentage of prices that are lower online. Column 6 shows the online markup, defined as the average price dif-
ference excluding cases that are identical. Column 7 shows the average price difference including identical prices. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Histograms of Nonzero Price-Level Differences (Percent) </p>

<p>Notes: Price differences excluding identical prices. A positive number means that the online price is higher than the 
offline price. Histogram scales are matched across countries. Bin width is 1 percent. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>−50 
0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 
0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 
0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 
0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 
0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>−50 </p>

<p>0 
50 </p>

<p>Difference </p>

<p>Argentina 
Australia 
Brazil 
Canada 
China </p>

<p>Germany 
Japan 
South Africa 
United Kingdom 
United States </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>number of sales is small: only 11 percent of all matched observations have either 
an online sale (4.12 percent), an offline sale (5.03 percent), or both (1.92 percent). </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Similarly, restricting the sample to include only prices collected on the same day 
(instead of a seven-day window) has little impact on the main results. The reason is 
that prices do not typically change more than once a week. Details are provided in 
the online Appendix. 
Another potential reason for some of the price-level differences is that goods have 
prices with similar time series that are not synchronized. I look for direct evidence 
of this in the next section, by comparing online and offline changes for a smaller 
sample of goods for which I have multiple weekly observations. </p>

<p>III. Price Changes </p>

<p>This section compares the behavior of price changes in the online and offline 
samples. A price change is computed here as a nonzero log difference in the price 
between weeks t and t + 1. I study the frequency, size, and timing of price changes. 
Table 5 shows that the frequency of online and offline price change is quite simi-
lar. The first two columns show the number of observations and price changes. There 
are fewer observations than in previous sections because I have a short time series 
for a limited subset of goods, and only about 10 percent of those observations have 
a price change. The frequency statistics reported in columns 3 and 4 are computed 
for each individual good first (as the share of observations with a price change), 
and then averaged across countries. Column 5 shows the p-value of a two-sided 
t-test with a null hypothesis of equal average frequencies in the online and offline 
samples. I can only reject the null of equality with some confidence in the cases of 
Australia and Japan. Although the full sample results appear to have slightly more 
frequent changes online, this is entirely driven by the data from Japan. 
In addition to similar frequencies, online and offline price changes tend to have 
similar sizes. This can be seen in columns 6 and 7, where I report the mean absolute 
size of price changes. Column 8 is again the p-value of a two-sided t-test of equality 
in the online and offline means. The null hypothesis can only be rejected in Canada, 
where online price changes seem to be larger. In all other countries, the difference 
is not statistically significant. 
Similar frequencies and sizes do not imply that price changes are perfectly syn-
chronized. This can be seen in Table 6, which focuses on the timing of changes. 
Price changes can occur online, offline, or in both locations. Column 3 reports the 
percentage of price changes for a given product that occur both online and offline 
at the same time, which I refer to as "synchronized." Only 19 percent of the 1,328 
price changes are synchronized across online and offline samples. While this is 
higher than the unconditional probability of a simultaneous price change shown in 
column 4 (using the unconditional frequencies and assuming independence), these 
price series are still far from being perfectly synchronized. </p>

<p>8 My ability to control for sales is somewhat limited because workers could not identify offline sales with the 
app until October 2015, and some of the scrape jobs were not able to include online sale indicators. It is therefore 
possible that the main results still contain a lot of sales that I cannot control for, and the share of identical prices 
would rise significantly if these observations were removed. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>Overall, these results suggest that the online and offline price series behave sim-
ilarly but are not perfectly synchronized. In a related paper, Cavallo and Rigobon  (2016), we find evidence that online price inflation tends to anticipate offline CPI 
inflation. A faster adjustment to shocks could be the reason why online price changes 
are not synchronized with offline changes. Unfortunately, the limited panel data 
available does not allow me to explicitly test this hypothesis. </p>

<p>IV. Other Reasons for Online-Offline Differences </p>

<p>In this section, I consider three other potential reasons for the differences between 
online and offline prices that required a special data-collection effort: different online </p>

<p>Table 5-Country: Price-Change Frequency and Size </p>

<p>Observations </p>

<p>Price 
changes </p>

<p>Mean 
frequency 
online </p>

<p>Mean 
frequency 
offline </p>

<p>Equality 
test 
p-value </p>

<p>Mean 
absolute 
size 
online 
(percent) </p>

<p>Mean 
absolute 
size 
offline 
(percent) </p>

<p>Equality 
test 
p-value 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) 
(8) </p>

<p>Argentina 
1,392 
245 
0.137 
0.146 
0.56 
13.61 
12.46 
0.57 
Australia 
759 
72 
0.056 
0.090 
0.07 
45.76 
42.62 
0.67 
Brazil 
483 
85 
0.167 
0.138 
0.36 
10.55 
9.36 
0.53 
Canada 
1,427 
120 
0.077 
0.068 
0.48 
31.11 
21.71 
0.06 
Germany 
419 
16 
0.035 
0.041 
0.74 
27.08 
15.86 
0.26 
Japan 
1,071 
98 
0.074 
0.014 
0.00 
12.10 
8.20 
0.34 
South Africa 
882 
109 
0.100 
0.077 
0.17 
23.33 
16.99 
0.11 
United Kingdom 
429 
25 
0.046 
0.070 
0.28 
47.68 
41.78 
0.67 
United States 
7,505 
563 
0.052 
0.046 
0.33 
23.78 
21.31 
0.20 </p>

<p>All countries 
14,367 
1,328 
0.076 
0.068 
0.07 
22.02 
19.94 
0.10 </p>

<p>Notes: China is excluded due to lack of price change data. The first two columns show the number of observations 
and price changes. The frequency statistics reported in columns 3 and 4 are computed for each individual good as 
the share of observations with a price change, and then averaged across countries. Column 5 shows the p-value of 
a two-sided t-test with a null hypothesis of equal average frequencies in the online and offline samples. Columns 6 
and 7 report the mean absolute size of price changes. Column 8 shows the p-value of a two-sided t-test of equality 
in the online and offline means. </p>

<p>Table 6-Synchronized Price Changes </p>

<p>Observations 
Price changes </p>

<p>Synchronized 
price changes 
(percent) </p>

<p>Unconditional 
probability 
(percent) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Argentina 
1,392 
245 
35 
2.0 
Australia 
759 
72 
22 
0.5 
Brazil 
483 
85 
18 
2.3 
Canada 
1,427 
120 
32 
0.5 
Germany 
419 
16 
31 
0.1 
Japan 
1,071 
98 
1 
0.1 
South Africa 
882 
109 
15 
0.8 
United Kingdom 
429 
25 
44 
0.3 
United States 
7,505 
563 
11 
0.2 </p>

<p>All countries 
14,367 
1,328 
19 
0.5 </p>

<p>Notes: China is excluded due to lack of price change data. Column 3 reports the percentage of price changes for a 
given product that occur both online and offline at the same time, which I refer to as "synchronized." The uncondi-
tional probability of a synchronized price change in column 4 is obtained by multiplying the frequencies of price 
change in Table 5. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>prices based on IP address or persistent browsing habits, multiple offline prices in 
different physical stores, and attempts to match prices at Amazon.com. </p>

<p>A. IP Address Location and Persistent Browsing </p>

<p>There have been reports suggesting that some retailers change online prices based 
on the browsing habits of the consumer or the location associated with the IP address 
of the computer being used to purchase online. See, for example, Valentino-DeVries, 
Singer-Vine, and Soltani (2012) and Mikians et al. (2012, 2013). If these pricing 
behaviors are common for the multi-channel retailers in my sample, they could help 
explain some of the price-level differences in the data. To test whether prices vary 
with browsing habits or IP address, I ran two experiments with special versions of 
the scraping robots for US retailers. 
The first experiment was designed to test whether prices change based on the zip 
code associated with the IP address of the computer collecting the data. IP addresses 
are unique numeric identifiers for computers that are connected to a network. They 
are assigned by Internet service providers and have an associated geographical loca-
tion that is public information. For example, MIT's campus IP addresses range from 
18.0.0.0 to 18.255.255.255 and are geographically linked to the 02139 zip code in 
Cambridge, Massachusetts. In principle, retailers could detect the IP address of the 
consumer visiting a site and automatically change the prices displayed based on its 
geolocation information. To test if this is happening, I randomly selected 5 products 
in each of the 10 US retailers and scraped their prices 12 times in a consecutive 
loop. In each loop, I changed the IP address of the robots by using 12 different proxy 
servers in 9 US cities (Atlanta, Burbank, Charlotte, Chicago, Cleveland, Miami, 
Nashville, New York, and two proxies in Phoenix) and 2 international locations 
(Canada and United Kingdom). 
9 I did not find any evidence of this type of price 
discrimination. In all cases, prices were the same for a given product, regardless of 
what IP address was used to connect to the retailer websites. 
The second experiment was designed to test if frequent visits to the web page of a 
particular product could lead the retailer to change the price displayed. In this case, 
I scraped a single product in each retailer every five minutes for a full day. Once 
again, there was no evidence of price discrimination based on persistent-browsing 
habits: prices were always the same. 
While these forms of online price discrimination may be important in other 
industries (for example airlines and hotels), my results suggest that they are not 
commonly used in large multi-channel retailers in the United States. A likely reason 
is that retailers may fear antagonizing their customers if reports of these tactics were 
to become publicized in the press, as it famously happened in 2000 with Amazon's 
pricing tests. </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>9 A proxy server is a computer that acts as an intermediary for the communications between two other com-
puters in a network-in this case, between the machine where the scraping software runs and the server hosting 
the website of the retailer. From the retailer's website perspective, the request was coming from the IP address 
associated with the proxy server. 
10 See CNN (2000) and Valentino-DeVries, Singer-Vine, and Soltani (2012) for a more recent example. A 
pricing strategy that appears to be more common than price discrimination is called "steering," in which the retailer 
changes the order or ranking of goods shown to customers based on their location or browsing characteristics. See, 
for example, Mattioli (2012). </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>B. Offline Price Dispersion </p>

<p>Most retailers have a single price online regardless of the location of the buyer, so 
a second potential reason for online-offline differences may be that there are some 
price difference across physical stores. 
To test for the effects of offline price dispersion, I use a small subset of products 
for which I have offline prices for multiple zip codes collected on the same day. 
These data include 406 observations in 9 retailers and 46 zip codes in the United 
States. Table 7 shows the results for the online-offline comparison restricted to this 
multi-zip code dataset. 
There are several things to note here. First, even though the sample is small, we 
get roughly the same share of identical online-offline prices that are reported in 
Table 3 of this paper, with 60 percent of the prices being identical online and offline. 
Second, as expected, goods that have different offline prices across zip codes tend 
to have much lower probability of identical online-offline prices, about 35 percent 
of the time. Third, if we focus exclusively on products with the same offline price 
everywhere, labeled "Identical Offline," the percentage of identical online-offline 
prices rises from 60 percent to 67 percent. 
While offline price dispersion can create online-offline price differences, the 
impact is limited because there is not much offline dispersion to begin with. Indeed, 
about 78 percent of products sampled have the same price in different physical stores 
within the same retailer, as seen in column 2. Sector results range from 66 percent 
in drugstores to 96 percent in electronics, consistent with the sectoral differences 
in the online-offline comparison in Section II. 
11 In the online Appendix, I further 
show that a large multi-channel supermarket that explicitly asks online buyers to 
enter their zip codes also tends to limit the amount of price dispersion across loca-
tions. Overall, these results reinforce the finding that price dispersion is low for both 
online and offline prices within multi-channel retailers. 
To some readers, the lack of offline price dispersion may appear to be at odds 
with a growing literature that uses scanner data and documents a significant price 
difference across physical stores. For a recent example, see Kaplan and Menzio  (2015). There are many reasons that can explain the apparent differences with my 
results. First, many papers in this literature compare data from different retailers, so 
that within retailer price dispersion is mixed with between retailer price dispersion. 
My results focus exclusively on price differences within retailers. Second, the price 
in scanner datasets is typically a weekly average. As I discuss in Cavallo (forth-
coming), this can cause significant measurement error for some applications. For 
example, consider a good with identical prices in two stores, a price change on a 
Wednesday, and a single transaction in each store. If one store sold the good on a 
Monday, and the other on Friday, the "weekly" price will appear to be different 
when in fact prices were identical on a daily basis. Similarly, some scanner datasets 
tend to have unit values instead of prices. These are calculated as the ratio of sales 
to quantities sold, and can therefore be affected by the number of coupons used 
or the share of transactions that take place at different prices. Of course, for some </p>

<p>11 See the online Appendix for more details as well as results from a larger dataset that includes offline observa-
tions for which no online price is available. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>purposes it makes sense to include coupons or transaction weights that affect the 
price actually paid by the consumer, but the fact that there is price dispersion caused 
by coupons should not lead us to believe that prices for the same goods are shown 
with different prices across stores of the same retailer. Third, price dispersion is 
often measured within a month or a quarter, so much of the difference in observed 
prices is caused by the same good being bought at different times. Finally, most 
scanner datasets contain prices for groceries and related goods. These are also the 
sectors for which I find more online-offline price dispersion, as well as offline price 
differences across physical stores. </p>

<p>C. Amazon Pricing </p>

<p>A third potential reason for differences in online and offline prices is that 
multi-channel retailers may be matching their online prices to those in online-only 
retailers such as Amazon.com, and by doing so, they create a wedge with the prices 
at their physical stores. 
To test this possibility, I created a special dataset that contains three prices for 
each product: the offline price at a multi-channel retailer, the online price in the same 
retailer, and the price at Amazon.com. The matched data contain 1,361 observations 
from 455 products and 8 multi-channel retailers: Best Buy, CVS, Walmart, Target, 
Lowe's, Macy's, OfficeMax, and Staples. The Amazon prices considered here cor-
respond to those products marked as "Sold by Amazon.com." To be consistent with 
the rest of the paper, I focus on prices collected within seven days and excluding 
sales. More details on how these data were collected, as well as results for products 
with sales or sold by third-party sellers are provided in the online Appendix. 
Figure 2 compares Amazon's prices separately to both the offline and online 
prices from multi-channel firms. A large share of prices are identical in both cases, 
which is surprising given that this is comparing prices across different retailers. As 
expected, Amazon's prices are closer to the online prices. They are identical to the 
online prices approximately 38 percent of the time, and the average price difference 
is −5 percent. The same estimates for the Amazon-offline comparison are 31 per-
cent and −6 percent respectively. 
This finding does not mean that multi-channel retailers are making their online 
and offline prices different to match the online price to Amazon's. In fact, as Table 8 
shows, the conditional probability of having an identical online price with Amazon </p>

<p>Table 7-Online-Offline Price-Level Differences for Multiple Zip Codes (Percent) </p>

<p>Retailers 
Observations 
Identical </p>

<p>Higher 
online </p>

<p>Lower 
online </p>

<p>Online 
markup </p>

<p>Online 
difference 
Country 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>United States 
9 
406 
60 
11 
29 
−4 
−2 
Different offline 
7 
85 
35 
16 
48 
−5 
−3 
Identical offline 
8 
316 
67 
9 
24 
−3 
−1 </p>

<p>Notes: Column 3 shows the percentage of observations that have identical online and offline prices. Column 4 has 
the percent of observations where prices are higher online and column 5 the percentage of prices that are lower 
online. Column 6, is the online markup, defined as the average price difference excluding cases that are identical. 
Column 7 is the average price difference including identical prices. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>is roughly the same for goods with identical online-offline prices than for those that 
have some online-offline price difference. The same conclusion can be obtained by 
running a simple probit regression of an identical online-offline price on an identical 
Amazon-online price. There is no statistically significant relation between these two 
variables. The only indication that Amazon's prices matter for the online-offline 
price differences is found in columns 6 and 7, which show that the difference with 
Amazon's prices is smaller for goods that are not identical within the multi-channel 
retailers. </p>

<p>V. Product Selection </p>

<p>The similarity between online and offline prices in previous sections would have 
different implications if most goods sold offline were not available online. I there-
fore now estimate the "overlap" in product selection across samples, defined as the 
share of offline goods that are also available online. </p>

<p>12   In principle, I could use the 63 percent of offline barcodes received through the app 
for which the scraping software found data online. The problem with this number, 
however, is that the automated matching procedure can fail for many reasons: the </p>

<p>12 Note that, given the data characteristics, I can estimate how many offline products are also sold online, but not 
the other way around. In some retailers, the online selection of goods can be larger than in a single physical store 
because online sales can be shipped from large centralized warehouses. See Quan and Williams (2015) for a recent 
discussion of the welfare effect of online and offline product variety. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Percent </p>

<p>−100 
−50 
0 
50 
100 </p>

<p>Price difference (percent) </p>

<p>Amazon versus offline </p>

<p>Amazon versus online </p>

<p>Figure 2. Price Differences with Amazon.com (US Only) </p>

<p>Notes: Price difference in Amazon.com prices relative to the offline and online prices from 
multi-channel retailers obtained from 1,361 observations from 455 products and 8 multi-channel 
retailers: Best Buy, CVS, Walmart, Target, Lowe's, Macy's, OfficeMax, and Staples. A negative 
number means Amazon is cheaper. Results for products marked as "Sold by Amazon.com" are 
shown here, with prices collected within seven days and excluding sales. More details and results 
for products with sales or sold by third-party sellers at Amazon's "Marketplace" are provided in 
the online Appendix. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>worker may scan the wrong barcode, the app may incorrectly read the barcode, or the 
scraping robot may fail while checking the website. To get a better estimate of the 
overlap degree, the BPP team manually checked how many of the offline products 
could also be found online for a sample of 100-200 observations per retailer using all 
the information submitted by the workers, including the product description readable 
in the photo of the price tag. The results, grouped by country, are reported in Table 9. 
As can be expected given the large product variety in these websites, a large frac-
tion of goods found offline can also be found online. On average, 76 percent of all 
products randomly collected at the physical stores could also be found on the retail-
er's website. There are important differences among countries, although they seem 
to be unrelated to the findings in previous sections. China and Germany have the 
lowest overlap, while Australia, Brazil, and the United Kingdom have the highest. In 
the United States, 81 percent of offline products were also found online. 
Furthermore, both the automatic and manually-matched goods produced simi-
lar results for online and offline price-level comparisons, as shown in the online 
Appendix. This finding rules out the possibility that goods that could not be auto-
matically matched were precisely those for which the online and offline prices are 
different. This would happen, for example, if retailers changed the online id number 
for those goods to obfuscate their price differences and prevent comparisons. The 
evidence suggests that this is not generally the case. </p>

<p>VI. Retailer Heterogeneity </p>

<p>The country-level results in the previous sections conceal a great deal of het-
erogeneity across retailers in each country. Details for each retailer can be seen in 
online Appendix Table A1, where I show price-level and price-changes results for 
all retailers with at least 100 observations. 
Three main types of retailers are typical. First, there are retailers where online 
and offline prices are identical most of the time. These are cases where the retailer 
explicitly chooses to have the same online and offline price. Second, there are also 
some retailers with a low share of identical prices, but no clear online markups. 
Many retailers in Brazil, for example, exhibit this pattern. These are likely cases 
where the online store is simply treated as another outlet, sometimes cheaper, some-
times more expensive. Third, there are retailers with a low share of identical prices </p>

<p>Table 8-Amazon: Online Price-Level Differences (Percent) </p>

<p>Country 
Retailers 
Observations 
Identical </p>

<p>Higher 
Amazon </p>

<p>Lower 
Amazon </p>

<p>Amazon 
markup </p>

<p>Amazon 
difference 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) 
(5) 
(6) 
(7) </p>

<p>All observations 
8 
1,049 
38 
14 
47 
−9 
−5 </p>

<p>Identical on-off 
8 
801 
38 
11 
51 
−10 
−6 
Different on-off 
8 
248 
38 
25 
37 
−3 
−2 </p>

<p>Notes: There are 312 observations with an Amazon price and either an online or offline price, but not both, so they 
are excluded from these results. Column 3 shows the percentage of observations that have identical Amazon and 
online prices at multi-channel retailers. Column 4 has the percentage of prices that are higher in Amazon and col-
umn 5 the percentage of prices that are lower in Amazon relative to the online prices. Column 6, is the Amazon 
markup, defined as the average price difference excluding cases that are identical. Column 7 is the average price 
difference including identical prices. </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>and a significant online markup (either positive or negative). There are some exam-
ples in Argentina, Brazil, Japan, and the United States. These patterns may reflect 
a desire to compensate for shipping costs or price-discriminate online consumers. 
Whether each kind of retailer is useful as a source of data depends on the pur-
pose of the paper or application. For example, using online prices for the retailer in 
Argentina where 79 percent of prices are higher online is not a problem for measur-
ing inflation if the online markup is relatively constant over time, but it would bias 
the results if we were interested in comparing price-level differences across coun-
tries. Unless a correction is applied, the online data would make prices in Argentina 
appear higher than what they are. Identifying these special patterns and correcting 
for any biases is particularly important in papers or applications that use online data 
from one (or a few) retailers. </p>

<p>VII. Conclusions </p>

<p>This paper shows that in large, multi-channel retailers there is little difference 
between the online price collected from a website and the offline price obtained 
by visiting the physical store. Prices are identical about 72 percent of the time, and 
while price changes are not synchronized, they have similar frequencies and sizes. 
At the same time, there is considerable heterogeneity across countries, sectors, and 
retailers. 
For research economists using online data for macro and international research 
questions, my results provide evidence that online prices are a representative source 
of retail prices, even if most transactions still take place offline. At a more micro 
level, the differences in behaviors can be used to better model the pricing dynamics </p>

<p>Table 9-Retailer: Product Selection Overlap </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>Found 
automatically </p>

<p>Found 
manually </p>

<p>Total 
overlap 
(percent) 
(1) 
(2) 
(3) 
(4) </p>

<p>Argentina 
500 
294 
52 
73 
Australia 
500 
435 
36 
95 
Brazil 
400 
331 
12 
86 
Canada 
500 
279 
132 
85 
China 
100 
50 
3 
53 
Germany 
400 
178 
23 
52 
Japan 
500 
329 
61 
74 
South Africa 
500 
332 
60 
76 
United Kingdom 
500 
373 
59 
86 
United States 
1,600 
1,003 
316 
81 </p>

<p>All countries 
5,500 
3,604 
754 
76 </p>

<p>Notes: The BPP team took a random sample of 100-200 offline prices per retailer and manually 
searched for the same products in the corresponding website. Column 2 shows the number of 
products that were found online by the automated process used to build the matched dataset in 
the paper. Column 3 shows the number of products that were missed by the automated process 
but were found online by manually checking the website. Column 4 shows the estimate for the 
total overlap in product selection. Only a subset of retailers in each country are included. These 
numbers are lower-bound estimates for the overlap because some of our manual checks took 
place several days after the original offline data was collected. Results by retailer are provided 
in the online Appendix. </p>

<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>

<p>and strategies of different types of retailers in various sectors and countries. This 
high degree of heterogeneity also implies that papers that use relatively few sources 
of data should be cautious to understand relevant pricing patterns and control for any 
potential sampling biases. 
For NSOs considering the use of online data for consumer price indexes, my 
results show that the web can be effectively used as an alternative data-collection 
technology for multi-channel retailers. Particularly for products such as electronics 
or clothing, the price collected on the web will tend to be identical to the one that 
can be obtained by walking into a physical store. Online prices are not only cheaper 
to collect, but they also provide information for all goods sold by each retailer, 
with many details per product, uncensored price spells, and can be collected on a 
high-frequency basis without any delays. Of course, there are also many potential 
disadvantages of using online data, including limited sector coverage and the lack of 
information on quantities, as we discuss in Cavallo and Rigobon (2016). But from 
a data-collection perspective, my results suggest that the online-offline price differ-
ences should not be a major source of concern. 
For those interested in the effect of the Internet on retail prices, my findings imply 
little within-retailer price dispersion, both online and offline. While the Internet may 
not have reduced dispersion across retailers, it seems to have created the incentives 
for companies to price identically across their own physical and online stores. More 
research is needed to understand the mechanisms that drive this effect. One possi-
bility is that retailers are worried about antagonizing customers who can now easily 
compare prices online through the web or their mobile phones. This might even 
be affecting cross-country pricing, as suggested by Cavallo, Neiman, and Rigobon  (2014), where we found evidence that global firms such as Apple and IKEA tend to 
price identically in countries that use the same currency, where it is trivial for con-
sumers to compare prices across borders. 
Future work should also try to understand why there are still some observed 
price-level differences. One explanation may be that online prices adjust faster to 
shocks. That would be consistent with the unsynchronized price change results in 
this paper and the anticipation in online price indices documented in Cavallo and  Rigobon (2016). Another potential reason is that location-specific sales or offline 
price dispersion may play a larger role than I can detect in these data. In particu-
lar, the offline price comparisons for multiple zip codes in Section IVB could be 
expanded to cover more sectors and countries. In addition, good-level characteris-
tics, such as the bargaining power of the manufacturer or the nature of its production 
and distribution costs, may help explain why some goods have identical prices while 
others do not. 
Another limitation of my analysis is the lack of quantity information at the prod-
uct and retailer levels. For some applications, such as the computations of price 
indices, we can use category weights in official CPI data. But other pricing statistics 
may change considerably when individual goods are weighted by transactions, as 
shown with online book sales by Chevalier and Goolsbee (2003). Future research 
should try to combine online prices with other micro data, such as scanner datasets, 
that can provide more detailed quantity information. 
Finally, except for the Amazon results in Section IVC, this paper does not study 
the prices of online-only retailers or small companies that participate in online </p>



<p>THE AMERICAN ECONOMIC REVIEW 
JANuARy 2017 </p>

<p>marketplaces. If their share of retail transactions continues to grow, a large-scale 
comparison with traditional multi-channel retailers will be needed to better under-
stand how pricing strategies and dynamics are likely to evolve in the future. </p>



<p> 
Cavallo: are online and offline PriCes similar? 
vol. 107 no. 1 </p>



</text></tei>