<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1057%2Fs11369-017-0056-y" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract High tax rates that distort incentives and create 
large deadweight losses have been reduced, but there is still 
much more to be done to improve the tax system. It is 
useful to distinguish between tax rules that represent tax 
expenditures relative to a pure income tax from rules that 
represent tax expenditures relative to a consumption tax. I 
think it is important to focus on tax expenditures relative to 
a consumption tax base. It is possible that if there were no 
estate tax, the present value of the taxes paid by future heirs 
would exceed the revenue lost by abolishing the estate tax. 
On the corporate side, a shift to a territorial system of 
taxation would have very substantial favorable effects, 
while pass-through entities have a very weak case for a 
significantly lower tax rate. The net effect of such tax 
changes would be an increase in the budget deficit, though 
that increase is likely to be only temporary due to leg-
islative rules. I am optimistic that there will be tax reforms 
enacted in the next twelve months holding great promise 
for improving our tax system and our economy. </p>

<p>1 The tax reform act of 1986 </p>

<p>Before I talk about the current agenda, let me provide a 
little historic background by focusing on the last major tax 
reform, the Tax Reform Act of 1986. 
TRA86 focused on the personal income tax. It combined 
base broadening with rate reduction to generate a reform 
that was revenue neutral on a static basis, i.e., even without 
taking into account the favorable effect of the lower tax 
rates on increasing taxable incomes. 
Here is the strategy that produced that important reform. 
For each income group-i.e., for each tax bracket-the 
Treasury calculated the revenue gain that would be 
achieved from eliminating a variety of ''tax benefits''-i.e., 
exclusions, deductions, and also the ''tax shelters'' like 
cattle feeding and oil drilling used by high-income tax-
payers. The Treasury then reduced the tax rate for each 
bracket to offset that revenue gain in a static calculation. 
Amazingly, because of the widespread use of tax shelters 
by high-income taxpayers, that strategy allowed reducing 
the top rate from 50 to 28%. 
Perhaps even more amazing, the legislation passed on a 
bipartisan basis with a Republican in the White House 
(Ronald Reagan) and a Democratic majority in the House 
of Representatives. Since the legislation reducing tax rates 
had come as a surprise to taxpayers, they had not been able 
to shift income from the high tax rate years before 1986 to 
the years after the rate reductions. It was a great natural 
experiment to see how taxpayers responded to a major 
change in marginal tax rates. 
Looking back after the fact, it was clear from the data 
that taxpayers responded to the reductions in marginal tax 
rates in ways that substantially increased taxable incomes. I 
studied that effect using a large panel of anonymous tax 
returns provided by the IRS (Feldstein 1995). The panel 
structure of the data meant I could compare the behavior of 
the same individuals in 1985 and 1988. The detailed data 
for each taxpayer meant I could exclude the effects on 
revenue of the tax shelter losses. 
Taxpayers who faced a marginal tax rate of 50% in 1985 
had a marginal tax rate of just 28% after 1986, implying 
that the marginal net-of-tax rate rose to 72% from 50%, an 
increase of 44%. For this group, the average taxable 
income rose between 1985 and 1988 by 45%. A more 
detailed difference-in-difference analysis also implied that 
the elasticity of taxable income to the net-of-tax rate was 
about one. 
This dramatic increase in taxable income reflected three 
favorable effects of the lower marginal tax rate: the greater 
net reward for extra effort and extra risk-taking leading to 
increases in earnings, in entrepreneurial activity, in the 
expansion of small businesses, etc. Lower marginal tax </p>

<p>rates also caused individuals to shift some of their com-
pensation from untaxed fringe benefits and other perks to 
taxable earnings. Taxpayers also reduced spending on tax-
deductible forms of compensation. 
Let me just note that this estimated response to lower 
marginal tax rates was not the full-scale dynamic scoring 
now used by the Congress, the Treasury, and the Con-
gressional Budget Office. The response that I described 
was just the short-term change in taxable income in 
response to the change in marginal tax rates. 
The tax rate reductions of TRA86 were too good to last. 
President George H. W. Bush agreed to raise the top rate 
from 28 to 31%. President Clinton then raised that rate to 
36%, adding what he called a ''temporary'' 10% increase to 
39.6% for high-income taxpayers, an increase that still 
remains. And President Obama added a 3.8% extra tax on 
investment income of high-income taxpayers. 
One final bit of tax history: The Congressional Budget 
Office (2016) did a very careful study of effective tax rates 
by income quintiles for the 35 years from 1979 to 2013. 
The CBO concluded that while the effective tax rate fell in 
every income quintile over those 35 years, it rose to well 
above the 35-year average for taxpayers in the top one 
percent of the income distribution. </p>

<p>2 The current proposals for changing individual 
taxes </p>

<p>That brings me to the proposals that are now on the table. I 
will start with the personal tax proposals and then turn to 
the corporate income tax. 
The Congressional tax writers are proposing to lower the 
top rate from 39.6 to 35% and to reduce the tax rates on 
lower brackets as well. The experience of TRA86 implies 
that this will change taxpayer behavior in ways that 
increase taxable incomes, partially offsetting the revenue 
losses of the rate reductions. Full dynamic scoring calcu-
lations will add longer-term growth effects that imply 
additional increases in taxable incomes. 
The plan is to pay for the remaining revenue losses by 
eliminating or limiting some of the deductions and other 
tax expenditures. The tax writers have not spelled out the 
details of what would be eliminated, although they have 
said that they will not eliminate the deductions for mort-
gage interest or charitable contributions. 
Preserving the deduction for mortgage interest is 
important because eliminating it would be capitalized in 
declines in the value of homes, potentially by enough to 
wipe out the equity of a home owner with a high loan-to-
value ratio. 
Preserving the charitable deduction is important for 
maintaining the decentralized private support for cultural, </p>

<p>The tax reform agenda </p>

<p>
educational, and religious organizations and for hospitals. 
Without that decentralized support, the United States could 
be forced to follow the European model in which those 
organizations are all financed and controlled by the 
government. 
The tax writers have indicated that their primary target 
is to eliminate the deduction for all state and local taxes, a 
tax expenditure that reduces federal revenue by about $100 
billion a year (Joint Committee 2017). The current 
deduction for state and local taxes can be viewed as a 
subsidy for the consumption of such government services 
and therefore as an incentive for voters to support increased 
spending and taxes for services provided by state and local 
governments. 
There is no doubt that eliminating the deductions for 
state and local taxes will be strongly resisted by the gov-
ernors of states with relatively high taxes and by their 
representatives in Congress. The Administration and others 
who want to pass this important revenue raiser might 
increase their chance of political success by postponing the 
effective starting date for several years to a time past the 
political horizon of most governors. 
More generally, it is useful to distinguish between tax 
rules that represent tax expenditures relative to a pure 
income tax from rules that represent tax expenditures rel-
ative to a consumption tax that does not tax saving or the 
income from savings. Except for the proposed limits on 
deductions for state and local taxes, virtually all of the 
other current deductions on the tax expenditure list pro-
duced by the Joint Committee would not be considered as 
tax expenditures under a consumption tax because they are 
designed to encourage saving and personal investment, 
including the deduction for contributions to pension plans 
and individual retirement accounts and the reduced tax 
rates on dividends and capital gains. 
While I have long been an advocate of limiting tax 
expenditures, I think it is important to focus on tax 
expenditures relative to a consumption tax base. Taxing 
saving or the return to saving weakens economic growth 
and creates an excess burden in addition to the deadweight 
loss created by taxing ordinary earnings. 
It would be useful to go beyond eliminating the 
deduction for state and local taxes to limit the exclusion 
from taxable income of the employer payments for health 
insurance. That is the largest of the tax expenditures with a 
revenue loss of $165 billion in 2017. Limiting the untaxed 
amount that can be provided to employees would not only 
produce substantial revenue but would reduce the demand 
for the kind of insurance policies with low copayments that 
contribute to the rapid increase in health care costs. Since 
only about half of employers provide these untaxed health 
insurance benefits, subjecting the benefits to taxation would 
increase the fairness of the tax system. </p>

<p>I have recently suggested a political compromise of 
subjecting employer payments for health insurance to the 
payroll tax (Feldstein 2017) rather than the income tax. 
Doing so would produce revenue of about $135 billion this 
year, reducing the overall deficit by that amount and adding 
it to the Social Security Trust Fund. The increase in the size 
of the Trust Fund would postpone the time when the Trust 
Fund would be depleted, requiring either a substantial cut 
in Social Security benefits or a significant increase in taxes 
to pay the benefits. 
More generally, subjecting health insurance benefits to 
either the income tax or the payroll tax would raise revenue 
without increasing marginal tax rates and would therefore 
not reduce incentives to work or to invest. 
An alternative to eliminating a few deductions and 
exclusions would be to put an overall limit on the amount 
that a taxpayer can benefit from such tax expenditures. 
That might be politically easier to enact since no group of 
taxpayers would feel that they were being singled out to 
lose their deductions. A few years ago, Dan Feenberg, 
Maya MacGuineas, and I (2011) proposed such a plan, 
allowing each individual to benefit from the full range of 
tax expenditures but limiting the resulting tax reduction to 
two percent of that taxpayer's adjusted gross income. 
Simulations using the <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">NBER</rs> <rs id="software-0" type="software">TAXSIM</rs> model projected 
that such a cap would have raised $278 billion in 2011. A 
two percent cap would also cause substantial simplification 
by inducing more than 35 million taxpayers to shift from 
itemizing their deductions to using the standard deduction. </p>

<p>3 Changing estate and gift taxes </p>

<p>The change in personal taxes may extend beyond the per-
sonal income tax to the estate and gift tax. Although only a 
tiny fraction of all individuals will ever pay any estate tax, 
surveys show that most Americans think that the estate tax 
is unfair because it levies a tax on wealth that was previ-
ously taxed when it was earned as wage and salary income 
and then taxed again as a tax on interest, dividends, and 
capital gains. The estate tax with a maximum federal rate 
of 40 percent also has a discouraging effect on saving 
among high-income older individuals. Since capital gains 
are not taxed on assets that pass when an individual dies, 
the current arrangement also creates a lock-in effect with 
older individuals induced to hold securities that they would 
otherwise want to sell. 
Defenders of the existing estate and gift tax assert that it 
produces revenue that is currently about $25 billion a year. 
Although this is less than one percent of total tax revenue, I 
think that even this relatively small amount overstates the 
revenue effect that would result from eliminating the estate 
tax. Individuals with substantial wealth now give a large </p>

<p> 
M. Feldstein </p>

<p>fraction of their wealth at the time of death to charita-
ble entities rather than lose more than half of those assets to 
federal and state taxes. But once those assets pass to non-
profit organizations, the return on those assets is no longer 
subject to the income tax. If there were no estate tax, those 
funds would pass to taxable heirs where the returns on the 
investments would be subject to the income tax. I have not 
done the calculation, but it is certainly possible that, if 
there were no estate tax, the present value of the taxes paid 
by future heirs would exceed the revenue lost by abolishing 
the estate tax itself. 
The Administration and the Congressional leadership 
have said that they will eliminate the estate tax but they 
have not provided any details of how the law would 
change. It is possible that they will follow the example of 
Canada where the estate tax was abolished, but capital 
gains on accumulated assets are subject to the capital gains 
tax at the time of death. That would be a change from the 
current US capital gains rule in which there is no tax on the 
accumulated capital gains at the time of death or in the 
hands of the heirs. Another possibility would be to treat 
capital gains at death the way the US now treats capital 
gains on assets that are given during life, requiring the 
recipient of the gift to carry over the basis of the assets and 
pay the capital gains tax when those assets are sold. 
Depending on the details of the treatment of accumulated 
gains, the elimination of the estate tax could have different 
tax consequences for estates of different size and with 
different amounts of accumulated gains. </p>

<p>4 Proposals for changing corporate taxes </p>

<p>I will turn now to the proposed changes in the taxation of 
corporations. </p>

<p>1   The Tax Reform Act of 1986 did not improve the tax-
ation of corporate income. The changes in depreciation 
rules in TRA86 actually reduced corporate incentives to 
invest, biasing the tax system more in favor of owner-
occupied housing in comparison to productivity-increasing 
investments in corporate plant and equipment. 
In contrast, the current tax reform proposals aim to 
change the corporate tax system in three ways: lowering 
the statutory rate on corporate profits; changing the tax 
treatment of the foreign subsidiaries of US corporations; 
and shifting from a traditional corporate tax to what its 
advocates call a destination-based cash flow corporate tax. 
I will discuss each of these although I believe that the plan 
for a cash flow corporate tax will not happen. </p>

<p>4.1 Reducing the corporate tax rate </p>

<p>The federal corporate tax rate is now 35%, the highest 
among all the major industrial countries. In addition, 
individual states levy corporate taxes with an average rate 
of 9%. Since those state taxes are deductible when calcu-
lating the federal taxable income, the overall tax rate is 
about 40%. The average rate among OECD countries is 
only about 25%. 
The effective corporate tax rate is reduced by acceler-
ated depreciation of investment in plant and equipment and 
by the deduction of nominal interest payments rather than 
the lower real interest payments. These are similar to the 
practices in other industrial countries. 
The House Republican tax plan developed when Paul 
Ryan was chairman of the Ways and Means Committee 
called for reducing the statutory rate from 35 to 20%. The 
Trump presidential campaign called for reducing it to 15%. 
Reducing the corporate tax rate would attract funds to 
the corporate sector from other uses like owner-occupied 
housing and agriculture. It would also attract foreign cap-
ital to the US corporate sector. These shifts would increase 
the efficiency with which capital is allocated across sectors 
and across international markets. The increased capital in 
the US business sector would raise the productivity and 
real wages of American workers. It would also increase 
real GDP growth as the corporate capital stock grows. 
There is substantial debate and confusion about who 
benefits if the corporate tax rate is reduced. Much of the 
discussion assigns a substantial share of the benefit to the 
shareholders or the owners of capital more generally with 
the rest going to labor. Basic theory makes it clear that the 
incidence of a reduction in the corporate tax rate depends 
on the effect of that rate reduction on the flow of capital to 
the corporate sector. Over time, the induced flow of capital 
to the corporate sector drives down the pretax rate of return 
to capital and raises the marginal product of labor. The 
division of the gain from the reduction of the corporate tax 
rate therefore evolves over time with a larger share going to 
the initial owners of capital in the short term and less as 
time goes by. 
The advocates of reducing the corporate tax rate often 
claim that doing so would also increase employment in the 
United States. This would obviously be true as a response 
to a corporate rate cut in an economy with substantial 
unemployment in which a reduction of the corporate tax 
would stimulate demand and aggregate employment. But in 
the current condition of the US economy with an unem-
ployment rate of just 4.4% there is no scope for a corporate 
tax cut to have such a traditional Keynesian effect on 
aggregate demand and employment. 
A cut of the corporate tax rate could nevertheless cause 
an increase in employment as the increased flow of capital </p>

<p>1 This section draws on remarks that I made at the September 2017 
meeting of the Brookings Panel on Economic Activity. </p>

<p>The tax reform agenda </p>

<p>
to the corporate sector raised the productivity of labor in 
that sector. Corporate firms would raise wages to attract 
labor, leading to an increase in the labor force participation 
rate and therefore in overall employment (See Feldstein  2016). 
Although lowering the corporate tax rate would have 
substantial economic benefits, it would also have a sig-
nificant budget cost. Since the corporate income tax now 
collects about 1.6% of GDP, cutting the rate from 35% to 
about half that level would reduce revenue directly by 
about 0.8% of GDP. Although this would be partly offset 
by the faster economic growth and by the rise in real wages 
and profits, there would still be an increase in the budget 
deficit. 
Unlike the personal income tax, there are very few tax 
expenditures in the corporate tax rules that could be 
eliminated to raise revenue. The analysis by the Joint Tax 
Committee identifies only relatively few corporate tax 
expenditures in comparison to the large number and sub-
stantial value for personal tax expenditures. The largest of 
these is the deferral of income of foreign subsidiaries, a 
subject to which I will turn in a minute. The only other 
large corporate tax expenditures are the deduction for 
domestic production activities (a tax expenditure of $15 
billion) and the effect of accelerated depreciation (a tax 
expenditure of $25 billion). In order to limit the revenue 
loss and achieve a long-run budget balance, the statutory 
rate might have to be reduced to no less than 25%. </p>

<p>4.2 Correcting the tax treatment of the foreign 
subsidiaries </p>

<p>I turn now to proposed changes in the tax treatment of the 
profits of foreign subsidiaries. The United States is virtu-
ally alone in the way that it taxes the profits earned by the 
foreign subsidiaries of its corporations. 
Consider a foreign subsidiary of a US corporation that 
earns profits in Ireland. It pays the Irish government a 
corporate profit tax equal to 12% of those profits and is 
then free to do what it wants with the after-tax profits 
without paying any extra Irish tax. It can invest them in 
Ireland, or hold them in financial assets, or invest them in 
any country of the world except the United States. But if it 
brings those after-tax profits back to the United States, it 
must pay the US tax of 35% minus the 12% paid in Ireland 
before it can either invest them in the United States or 
distribute them to shareholders. Not surprisingly, American 
corporations generally decide not to repatriate those after-
tax profits. The Treasury estimates that American corpo-
rations have decided to leave about $2.5 trillion of the 
after-tax profits of its subsidiaries outside the United States. 
In contrast, other countries follow what is called the 
''territorial'' method of taxing the profits of foreign </p>

<p>subsidiaries. Profits can be repatriated and invested in the 
home country or distributed to domestic shareholders after 
paying either no tax or a very small corporate tax (like 5 or 
10%). 
American multinational corporations that don't want to 
repatriate the profits of their foreign subsidiaries have two 
options if they don't want to earn only the low rate of 
return available on financial assets. They can invest those 
profits in offshore businesses or they can hold those profits 
in financial assets and borrow an equal amount at home to 
invest in the United States. The fact that about half of the 
$2.5 trillion of unrepatriated funds are invested in foreign 
operating businesses shows that US multinationals prefer to 
invest a substantial part of their foreign subsidiary profits in 
overseas businesses. Their reluctance to borrow in the 
United States in order to invest at home may reflect the 
equity market's negative view of increased debt on the 
company's balance sheet even if it is in principle balanced 
by the holding of bonds or bank deposits in the foreign 
subsidiary. This behavior implies that a shift to a territorial 
tax system will cause multinational corporations to repa-
triate more of the profits of their foreign subsidiaries rather 
than investing them abroad. 
A shift by the United States to a territorial system of 
taxation would therefore have very substantial favorable 
effects. Much of the $2.5 trillion of funds that have been 
accumulated abroad would eventually be repatriated and 
invested in the United States. In addition, the future profits 
of the foreign subsidiaries of US corporations would also 
be more likely to be repatriated instead of being invested in 
new companies outside the US. But even if paid out as 
dividends or used to buy back shares, most of those funds 
would find their way into new investments by other firms. 
In this way, the shift to a territorial system would have 
favorable effects similar to a reduction of the corporate rate 
cut: raising capital per worker, increasing productivity and 
real wages, and stimulating higher growth and higher 
taxable incomes. 
A US shift to a territorial system would also increase the 
incentive for foreign companies to invest in the United 
States and to establish the United States as their head-
quarters, knowing that they could repatriate foreign profits 
to the US for further investment in the US or elsewhere. 
A territorial system would thus raise corporate tax rev-
enue for the United States by shifting more profits to be 
invested in the United States. An initial ''deemed repatri-
ation tax'' on the $2.5 trillion of previously untaxed foreign 
subsidiary profits would provide a significant short-term 
boost to corporate tax revenue. 
But there are potential adverse effects of the shift to a 
territorial system. It could encourage the US firms to 
establish subsidiaries in ''tax shelter'' countries with 
extremely low tax rates in order to earn profits there and </p>

<p> 
M. Feldstein </p>

<p>then return them to the US with little or no further tax. It 
could encourage firms to shift profits to such tax shelter 
jurisdictions by transfer pricing or debt transactions. These 
would require careful monitoring or special rules for such 
tax shelter countries. Since every other industrial country 
with a territorial tax system has dealt with this challenge, I 
assume that the United States could do so as well. 
A permanent shift to a territorial system would be quite 
different from the one-time repatriation holiday that was 
tried in 2004. Companies were then allowed to repatriate 
foreign subsidiary profits with the understanding that those 
funds would be invested in the United States. Much of the 
repatriated funds were nevertheless used for share buy-
backs and dividends. It is not possible however to know 
how much of the funds that were paid out as dividends or 
share buybacks were then used to finance investments in 
other firms. Moreover, a permanent shift to a territorial 
system would have different incentives than the one-off 
repatriation holiday. </p>

<p>4.3 Adopting a cash flow corporate tax </p>

<p>I'll turn now to the idea of adopting a cash flow corporate 
tax. 
At an annual AEA meeting some years ago, I proposed 
replacing our corporate income tax with a cash flow tax. 
Each company's tax base would be increased by any inflow 
of cash-whether from product sales, borrowing, or the 
issuance of equity-and would be decreased by any out-
flow of cash-whether from the cost of inputs, from 
repaying debt, from paying interest or dividends, or buying 
back shares. I was not alone in proposing such a cash flow 
tax to replace the traditional corporate tax. Like many good 
ideas, it was not pursued at the time so I will not comment 
on its potential virtues. 
There is now discussion of a so-called ''destination-
based cash flow tax'' that has a very different structure. 
There are three components to this DBCFT: first compa-
nies would get an immediate write-off for all investments 
in plant and equipment; second, companies would not be 
allowed to deduct interest on new loans; and third there 
would be a deduction for export sales and an extra tax on 
imports. I think that in some long-run steady state this 
would be equivalent to the simpler cash flow tax that I 
proposed earlier although it would be very different during 
the transition years. 
Allowing an immediate write-off of all expenditures for 
plant and equipment would provide a strong incentive for 
productivity-increasing investments. It would also cause a 
very large loss of revenue. 
Eliminating interest deductions on new loans would 
raise significant revenue but would be difficult to imple-
ment. When is a loan ''new'' rather than a rollover of an </p>

<p>existing loan? How should leasing be distinguished from 
borrowing? How should loans of foreign subsidiaries be 
treated? 
The firms that gain from expensing would be different 
from those that lose from eliminating interest deductions, 
making it politically difficult to enact such a pair of 
proposals. 
To complete the similarity to a true cash flow tax, the 
DBCF plan adds a border adjustment piece: all imports 
would be subject to an additional tax at the corporate tax 
rate, while all exports would be granted an additional 
deduction at that rate in calculating table profits. Although 
this might look like a plan to increase exports and decrease 
imports, it need not be. As economists understand, an 
improvement in the trade balance requires a change in the 
difference between national saving and national invest-
ment. The fundamental economic relation is that ''exports 
minus imports equals national saving minus national 
investment.'' Since the border adjustment tax causes no net 
change in saving or investment (because the net revenue 
would be used to pay for the corporate rate cut), there 
would be no change in imports and exports despite the tax 
on imports and subsidy to exports. The textbook resolution 
of this apparent paradox is that the exchange rate of the 
dollar would rise enough to make the value of foreign 
goods when they reach the US lower by enough to just 
balance the effect of the tax on imports. The same 
exchange rate effect would apply to neutralize the subsidy 
on exports. 
The real purpose of the border adjustment tax was, as I 
just indicated, to raise revenue to pay for the reduction in 
the corporate tax rate. The BAT would raise substantial 
revenue because the tax on imports would raise more 
revenue than the subsidy on exports loses. The US imports 
about 15% of GDP and exports about 12%. With a 20% 
corporate rate applied to both, the net revenue effect would 
be to raise revenue by 20% of 3% of GDP, equivalent to 
0.6% of GDP or about $120 billion at today's level of 
GDP. That would probably be enough to offset the net 
revenue loss of the corporate rate reduction. Although the 
gap between imports and exports should in theory reverse 
in the long run, it has continued for many decades, pre-
sumably because foreign savers welcome the opportunity 
to invest in the United States. 
In principle, therefore, the border adjustment tax would 
have no net effect on the prices paid by US consumers or 
the prices received by US exporters. There are of course 
reasons why the full textbook adjustment of the exchange 
rate might not happen in practice. Importers and retailers 
therefore fear that they might lose from the tax on imports. 
Since there is no gain for them in the border adjustment and 
a risk of a serious loss, they have been opposing it </p>

<p>The tax reform agenda </p>

<p>
politically, arguing that it would raise prices to American 
consumers. 
The opponents of the border adjustment tax system 
appear to have won the political battle. A statement by the 
Republican leadership dealing with taxes has explicitly 
withdrawn support and my judgment is that Congress will 
not enact the border adjustment tax or any other part of the 
DBCF plan. </p>

<p>4.4 Dealing with pass-through businesses </p>

<p>There is a further tax issue about dealing with pass-through 
businesses. It is said that about half of business activity in 
the United States is conducted by organizations that are not 
traditional Subchapter C corporations. These include sub-
chapter S corporations (the income of which is added to 
other personal income for personal income tax purposes), 
partnerships, and sole proprietorships. 
If the top rate of the personal income tax is reduced from 
the current 39.6 to 35%, the pass-through entities would 
pay tax on their profits under current law at their personal 
tax rate or 35%. The owners of such businesses complain 
that would be much higher than the proposed 20% rate that 
would be paid by regular Subchapter C corporations. 
The representatives of small businesses and other pass-
through entities are therefore lobbying to have a special 
lower rate for these entities. Doing so would create an 
incentive for salaried individuals who are able to do so to 
incorporate their activities as Subchapter S corporations or 
other forms that qualify for the proposed lower tax rate in 
order to take advantage of that new lower rate. 
The gap between the proposed personal income tax rate 
of 35% and the proposed corporate rate of 20% exaggerates 
the true effective difference between owners of Subchap-
ter C corporations and owners of pass-through businesses. 
The full effective rate on corporate businesses includes not 
just the corporate tax rate but also the additional tax that 
must be paid by shareholders when the after corporate tax 
profits are distributed to the owners of the corporation. 
Here is the relevant arithmetic. A pass-through entity 
with $100 of profits would have a net-of-tax income of $65. 
A Subchapter C corporation with the same $100 of pretax 
profits would pay the new 20% corporate rate, producing 
an after-tax profit of $80. If that $80 were paid out as 
dividends, the net income to the owner would be less than 
$65 if the tax on dividends exceeds 18.75%. Even with a 
15% tax on dividends, the $80 paid out as dividends would 
yield a net income of just $68 and therefore only $3 more 
than the income of the pass-through owner. If instead the 
after-tax profits were retained until the corporation is dis-
solved, the accumulated profits would under current law be 
subject to tax at both the corporate and personal levels. In </p>

<p>short, the pass-through entities have a very weak case for a 
significantly lower tax rate. </p>

<p>4.5 Tax reform and the budget deficit </p>

<p>I will conclude with some brief comments about the impact 
of tax reform on future budget deficits. 
The direct effect of the lowering tax rates on personal 
and corporate income will be to reduce tax revenue and 
raise the budget deficit. This will be offset in part by the 
limits on personal deductions. Limiting the exclusion of 
employer payments for health insurance could raise sub-
stantially more revenue, at least as much as the amount that 
had been expected from the border adjustment tax. Lower 
marginal tax rates on personal income will induce indi-
viduals to increase taxable income by a combination of 
greater earnings, a shift of compensation from fringe 
benefits to taxable cash, and a reduced use of deductible 
consumption expenditures. The shift to a territorial system 
for taxing the income of foreign subsidiaries of US cor-
porations will raise taxable profits, especially in the short 
run as companies pay the deemed repatriation tax. The 
combination of lower tax rates on personal incomes and 
corporate profits will lead to increased growth of taxable 
incomes and profits. 
Nevertheless, the net effect of the tax changes would be 
an increase in the budget deficit. That deficit increase is 
likely however to be only temporary because of the pres-
sure created by legislative rules. Here is why. 
Unless there is a change in the attitudes of the Demo-
cratic members of the Senate, the Republicans will have to 
pass the tax legislation without any support from the Senate 
Democrats. Although it is generally difficult to pass leg-
islation without Democratic votes because the Republicans 
have a majority of only two in the Senate and it takes 60 
votes to stop a filibuster, there is an exception for budget 
legislation. The tax reform legislation can be passed with a 
simple majority using the so-called reconciliation process. 
But the reconciliation process can be used only if there is 
no projected increase to the fiscal deficit after the 10-year 
budget period. 
Even with dynamic scoring that recognizes the extra 
revenue from faster economic growth, achieving that 
necessary long-term budget balance may require limit-
ing the size of the corporate rate reduction and offset-
ting the reductions in the personal tax rates by 
eliminating or limiting a variety of personal deductions 
and exclusions. 
I am optimistic that the advocates of tax reform will 
adopt the changes needed to pass the legislation using 
reconciliation. If this happens, the deficit increase will be 
only temporary and the tax reforms enacted during the next </p>

<p> 
M. Feldstein </p>

<p>12 months will hold great promise for improving our tax 
system and our economy. 
Thank you. </p>



<p>The tax reform agenda </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>