<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1007%2Fs10888-015-9317-z" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>I presented an earlier version of this report to the Editorial Board meeting held in July 
2015 in conjunction with the ECINEQ conference at the University of Luxembourg. The 
statements about editorial policy below were endorsed by the Editorial Board. As the Board 
meets in person only every second year, my 2016 Editorial will be shorter, focusing on 
publication statistics and acknowledgements. </p>

<p><rs type="software">Springer's Editorial Manager</rs></p>

<p>S. P. Jenkins </p>

<p>The fraction of submissions that is desk-rejected has risen markedly from 47 % in 2013 
to 60 % in 2014. When papers are submitted, they are screened by the Editor-in-Chief who 
may either desk-reject the paper, handle the paper himself (sending the paper to referees), 
or assign the paper to an Associate Editor to handle. Associate Editors, who have fully 
devolved powers, may desk-reject papers assigned to them or decide to send them to ref-
erees. Papers estimated to have a low chance of eventual publication are now less likely to 
clog up the system, and we make fewer calls on the precious time of our referees. Desk-
rejected authors may be disappointed but I hope that they receive some consolation: we aim 
is to make desk-rejections within seven days of receipt of the submission and also to provide 
some explanatory comments. Some advice for submitting authors is provided below. 
The increase in desk-rejections has also changed the distribution of manuscript process-
ing times. According to Springer's "2014 Publisher's Report", the mean number of days 
from submission to first decision was 88 in 2013 and 53 in 2014. The mean numbers of 
days to final deposition Accept were 282 (2013) and 407 (2014), and to final deposition 
Reject were 85 (2013) and 60 (2014). The increase in mean time to final deposition Accept 
is related to the change-over in Editor-in-Chief that is described below, and we expect the 
mean for 2015 to be substantially lower than that for 2014. 
As regards the total number of articles published, there are around 20 Original Research 
Articles per year, on average. Submissions in 2014 came from 47 countries, including 30 
from the USA, 21 from Italy, 17 from Spain, and 10 from Germany and India. There are 
also papers in our Forum and Rediscovered Classics sections, and occasional Special Issues, 
each of which is discussed further below. 
The journal's Impact Factor has increased year on year since 2010. It was 1.352 for 2013 
and 1.362 for 2014. There are debates about what is an appropriate metric for summarizing 
journal performance, and Impact Factors are known to be imperfect. The comparability of 
Impact Factors across disciplines is particularly problematic too. However, Impact Factor 
data are readily available and we are pleased when our score is increasing! 
The 10 most downloaded papers from the Springer website in 2014 are shown in Table 1. 
It is striking that the majority of the papers appeared either in a themed Special Issue, 
or in the Rediscovered Classics section. The 15 most cited papers (according to Google 
Scholar, as at July 2015) are shown in Table 2, with papers ranked by number of citations 
per year. Original Article submissions feature more prominently in this table than Table 1 
but, nonetheless, a notable fraction appeared either in a themed Special Issue or in the 
Rediscovered Classics section </p>

<p>2 Special Issue and Forum papers </p>

<p>Special Issue (SI) and Forum papers are clearly popular with JEI readers, as the down-
load and citation statistics indicate. Forum topics are proposed by the Forum Editor (Nora 
Lustig), and final decisions about whether to proceed and, if so, how much journal space is 
available for them, are made after discussion with the Editor-in-Chief. The commissioning 
of the Forum papers themselves, and their subsequent handling, is done by the Forum Edi-
tor. Agreed and currently in planning is a Forum on 'Global poverty lines', handled by Nora 
Lustig together with Jacques Silber (founding Editor-in-Chief). 
Decisions about SIs are taken by the Editor-in-Chief in consultation with the Associate 
Editors and occasionally more widely. An SI on 'Appraising cross-national databases on </p>

<p>Editorial 2015 </p>



<p>Table 1 Top 10 most downloaded papers from Springer's JEI website, calendar year 2014 </p>

<p>Rank Number of downloads Paper 
Corresponding Author </p>

<p>1 
897 
Inequality and growth: evidence 
Vollmer </p>

<p>from panel cointegration </p>

<p>2 
833 
The measurement of multidimensional poverty 
Bourguignon </p>

<p>3 
714 
Decomposition procedures for distributional 
Shorrocks </p>

<p>analysis: a unified framework based on the </p>

<p>Shapley value </p>

<p>4 
543 
Understandings and misunderstandings of 
Alkire </p>

<p>multidimensional poverty measurement </p>

<p>5 
528 
The HDI 2010: new controversies, old critiques 
Klugman </p>

<p>6 
478 
Inequality and happiness: insights from 
Graham </p>

<p>Latin America </p>

<p>7 
433 
The origins of the Gini index: extracts from 
Ceriani </p>

<p>Variabilità e Mutabilità (1912) by Corrado Gini </p>

<p>8 
424 
A vulnerability approach to the definition of 
López-Calva </p>

<p>the middle class </p>

<p>9 
391 
The Foster-Greer-Thorbecke (FGT) poverty 
Thorbecke </p>

<p>measures: 25 years later </p>

<p>10 
380 
Polarization and the decline of the middle 
Foster </p>

<p>class: Canada and the U.S. </p>

<p>income inequality', with guest editors Chico Ferreira and Nora Lustig, is to be published 
in issue 4 of 2015. Since February 2014, I have received two SI proposals and turned both 
down after consultation. 
Given the popularity of SI and Forum papers, one might ask whether we might have 
more of them. Our views on this issue are influenced by factors in addition to popularity. 
First, the opportunity cost of SI and Forum papers is reduced publication space or increased 
publication delays for Ordinary Research Articles. (Springer owns the journal; they set the 
page budgets in advance; and there are four journal issues per year. Unlike some other jour-
nals which are owned by an association, we cannot run additional issues to accommodate 
special issues even if a proposer offers to fund them.) Second, and related, although SI and 
Forum papers usually receive comments from their handling editor, they are typically invited 
papers and not subject to quite the same anonymous refereeing process. The papers are often 
by senior authors already well-known in the profession. And yet a journal's reputation for 
research quality is strongly determined by its publication of peer-reviewed articles from a 
submission process open to all. Third, it is harder to monitor and administer the editorial 
process, and to maintain a consistent editorial policy across all of the articles published in 
the JEI, if SIs are guest-edited by people who are not Editors (or Editorial Board members). 
At its 2015 meeting, the Editorial Board agreed that we need to be careful about expand-
ing the proportion of SI and Forum papers. It recognised the popularity of SI and Forum 
papers but recommended that we continue to operate a relatively conservative attitude 
towards commissioning them. In particular, it was agreed that SIs only be approved if the </p>



<p>S. P. Jenkins </p>

<p>Table 2 Top 15 JEI papers ranked by number of citations per year (as at July 2015) </p>

<p>Rank Cites per year Cites Authors 
Title 
Year </p>

<p>1 
312.0 
624 
AF Shorrocks 
Decomposition procedures for distributional 2013 </p>

<p>analysis: a unified framework based on the </p>

<p>Shapley value </p>

<p>2 
89.0 
89 
LF López-Calva, 
A vulnerability approach to the definition 
2014 </p>

<p>E Ortiz-Juarez 
of the middle class </p>

<p>3 
78.2 
938 
F Bourguignon, 
The measurement of multidimensional 
2003 </p>

<p>SR Chakravarty 
poverty </p>

<p>4 
45.0 
180 
S Alkire, J Foster Understandings and misunderstandings 
2011 </p>

<p>of multidimensional poverty measurement </p>

<p>5 
41.8 
167 
M Ravallion 
On multidimensional indices of poverty 
2011 </p>

<p>6 
40.8 
326 
J Esteban, 
An extension of a measure of polarization, 
2007 </p>

<p>C Gradín, 
with an application to the income </p>

<p>D Ray 
distribution of five OECD countries </p>

<p>7 
37.3 
448 
AB Atkinson 
Multidimensional deprivation: contrasting 
2003 </p>

<p>social welfare and counting approaches </p>

<p>8 
35.6 
178 
D Checchi, 
Inequality of opportunity in Italy 
2010 </p>

<p>V Peragine </p>

<p>9 
35.5 
142 
J Klugman, 
The HDI 2010: new controversies, 
2011 </p>

<p>F Rodríguez, 
old critiques </p>

<p>HJ Choi </p>

<p>10 
34.9 
314 
F Bourguignon, 
Microsimulation as a tool for evaluating 
2006 </p>

<p>A Spadaro 
redistribution policies </p>

<p>11 
27.0 
27 
EN Wolff, 
Inheritances and the distribution of wealth 
2014 </p>

<p>M Gittleman 
or whatever happened to the great </p>

<p>inheritance boom? </p>

<p>12 
25.0 
125 
GS Fields 
Does income mobility equalize 
2010 </p>

<p>longer-term incomes? New measures </p>

<p>of an old concept </p>

<p>13 
22.6 
113 
JE Foster, 
Polarization and the decline of the middle 
2010 </p>

<p>MC Wolfson 
class: Canada and the US </p>

<p>14 
21.3 
192 
C Graham, 
Inequality and happiness: 
2006 </p>

<p>A Felton 
insights from Latin America </p>

<p>15 
20.7 
62 
W Bossert, 
Poverty and time 
2012 </p>

<p>SR Chakravarty, </p>

<p>C d'Ambrosio </p>

<p>Extracted on 2015-07-06 using <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Harzing</rs>'s <rs id="software-1" type="software">Publish or Perish</rs> TM software (statistics derived from Google 
Scholar) </p>

<p>guest editor(s) is an existing JEI editor, a former editor, or a member of the Editorial Board. 
In this connection, the Board noted that the Forum section is like a smaller version of a SI, 
but without the editorial policy issue cited above. Submit suggestions for Special Issues to 
the Editor-in-Chief and for Forums to the Forum Editor. </p>

<p>Editorial 2015 </p>



<p>3 Rediscovered Classics </p>

<p>Under the expert guidance of Peter Lambert, the JEI has published much research of interest 
to the readership. However, over the two years, proposals have almost dried up. Given the 
popularity of the section to date, the Editorial Board endorsed my proposal that the journal 
continue to publish Rediscovered Classics if we receive suitable proposals. In addition, 
because Peter is unable to continue in his post, the handling of new proposals will now be 
undertaken by the Editor-in-Chief. One proposal is currently under consideration. Readers 
are invited to email me with additional suggestions. </p>

<p>4 Assorted other changes </p>

<p>Referees are now automatically blind copied into emails containing decisions made by the 
editors. We believe it is useful to provide feedback to referees about the fate of papers that 
they have commented on, and there are benefits to referees from reading the comments of 
editors and other reviewers. 
The journal now uses the Harvard (author-date) style for citations and references rather 
than a numbering style. The change should improve the reader's experience (it is much more 
informative to see text referring to, say, "(Ferreira, 2013)" rather than "[7]"); it is easier for 
authors to prepare lists of References using an author-date style; and, with such a style, it is 
easier to correct proofs of accepted articles and impose the journal's house style consistently 
(the Editor-in-Chief sees all proofs). 
When authors submit a paper via Editorial Manager, they must explicitly declare that 
the paper contains original work and that it is not also under submission at another journal. 
Occasional instances of simultaneous submission have come to light. In such cases, the 
paper is withdrawn from the system and the author is banned from submitting to the journal 
for a period. </p>

<p>5 Replication policy for empirical papers </p>

<p>Economics journals are increasingly moving towards implementation of a replication policy 
of some kind for empirical papers. So too are other journals in quantitative social science 
and cognate disciplines. An early leader in Economics was the Journal of Human Resources. 
Other journals with related policies now include American Economic Association journals, 
the Economic Journal, the Journal of Applied Econometrics, and the journals of the Royal 
Statistical Society. The policies differ a lot in their interpretation and implementation. For a 
useful summary of the current state-of-play, see Duvendack et al. (2015). 
Other things being equal, the ability to check the replicability of empirical work is good 
for social science in general, and for this journal and its readership in particular. Also, 
replicability would put empirical research on a more equal footing with theoretical research: 
theorists are expected to provide proofs for their theorems. But instituting a replication 
policy for empirical papers raises non-trivial issues. They include the following. 
What materials would authors have to make available for replication purposes? We 
may distinguish several types of data: (a) original parent database(s); and (b) databases 
derived from these by authors for their analysis. In addition, data may be (i) freely down-
loadable, (ii) available through a data archive (requiring registration, but usually without 
cost), or (iii) proprietary or secure data, with access restricted to users satisfying e.g. </p>



<p>S. P. Jenkins </p>

<p>data security requirements, and/or paying requisite fees to the data owners. In addition to 
data, there are the all-important code scripts: (A) code used to extract data from parent 
databases, (re)organise the data, and create derived variables; and (B) code for the anal-
ysis. Code scripts are usually software dependent, and/or different software is used for 
data extraction, management, or analysis. Having data without code scripts is largely use-
less for replication. But having code scripts -of both types A and B -may be sufficient, 
because replication exercises can still be undertaken if the replicator has access to the data 
by other means. 
From an author's perspective, there are incentives against making replication materials 
available. It is costly in terms of time, and perhaps money, to prepare replication materials 
in a form that can be made publicly available, and (depending on the nature of the policy) to 
archive the materials. There are potential risk-to-reputation costs were replicators unable to 
replicate published research findings or to find errors that made findings non-robust. These 
problems are difficult to address except collectively, e.g. by journals making some form of 
replication provision a condition of publication. On the other hand, some researchers derive 
a 'warm glow' from making replication materials available and are willing to provide them 
themselves. But they are relatively rare. 
From a journal's perspective, there are the costs of maintaining webpage archives of 
replication materials (if journals rather than authors are responsible for the repository). More 
fundamentally, there are serious issues of monitoring and enforcement, with the costs of 
these dependent on the nature of materials (data and/or code scripts) required to be archived. 
Comprehensive monitoring and enforcement could not be done with this journal's editorial 
resources. Moreover, the nature of any journal-based replication archive and its maintenance 
would need to be agreed with Springer, the journal's owner. There is also a potential issue 
that, if the journal were to implement a comprehensive replication policy, it might deter 
authors of potentially good papers from submitting to the journal and we would lose them 
to our competitors. 
In sum, there are many difficult issues to address and resolve in the design of a replica-
tion policy for empirical papers. At its 2015 meeting, the Editorial Board supported moves 
towards more replication in principle but recognised the costs as well as the benefits. In the 
interim, it was agreed that authors of empirical papers should be encouraged to self-archive 
the materials associated with their papers -both data (if feasible) and code scripts -and to 
make them freely accessible. 
Potential archive locations could be the author's personal or institutional website, 
or free or cheap cloud-based storage such as provided by Dropbox TM and similar 
providers. There are also specialist hosts such as Harvard Dataverse (https://dataverse. 
harvard.edu/) with fee-free provision of opportunities to "Share, publish, and archive 
your data. Find and cite data across all research fields." Code scripts can also 
be deposited there. 
The journal will look favourably on empirical papers that provide access to replication 
materials, and prefers that this access be given at submission time as well as at publication. 
There are various ways of announcing access. One would be to include statements in the 
Acknowledgements section along the lines of: "Replication materials (code and data) are 
available from http://URL-of-website" or "Replication materials (code and data) are avail-
able from the corresponding author" who would then provide the materials to enquirers on 
a one to one basis or via a web link. </p>

<p>Editorial 2015 </p>



<p>The journal will consider the publication of replication studies of previously-published 
papers on their merits. They should be submitted as Original Research Articles in the usual 
way. Currently we have no plans to have a separate Replication Section. </p>

<p>6 Advice for authors submitting original research articles </p>

<p>Given the high rejection rate, authors might reasonably ask what factors make acceptance 
of their submission more likely. Here follows some advice. </p>

<p>(a) Ensure that your article's subject falls within the journal's scope. We continue to 
receive submissions that should clearly have been sent to a different journal and these 
are desk-rejected immediately. No particular subject or approach to the analysis of 
economic inequality is privileged or deprecated. However, issues regarding scope do 
more commonly arise for papers addressing topics that span other fields and their jour-
nals, whether theoretical or empirical in approach. For example, for us to consider a 
submission about trade and inequality, or inequality and growth, it needs to squarely 
address the economic inequality dimension in order to persuade us that this journal is 
the appropriate target. The same is true for papers considering the inter-relationships 
between the income distribution and the labour market, public policy, or demography. 
Recent issues provide a guide to our coverage. We seek high quality articles focus-
ing on "economic inequality", broadly defined, that are of interest to our international 
readership. For more details of our scope, see the journal's website at http://www. 
springer.com/economics/growth/journal/10888. 
(b) Ensure your article provides a clear "contribution" to the analysis of economic inequal-
ity. Communicate what it is and focus on it. For example, if the methods you use are 
well-known and so your innovation is in the particular application, do not waste space 
explaining the former in great detail. Single country studies are acceptable, but ensure 
that the issues addressed or methods employed are of wide interest and relevance. 
More generally, ask: what is the research question that you are addressing, why is it 
important, how do you answer it, and what answer do you provide? Communicate and 
justify the answers to these questions to our target readership. 
(c) Work hard on your Introduction and Conclusions sections and also your Abstract (as 
well as the rest of your analysis). These are the sections that the editors and referees 
look at first and are also of great importance to non-specialist readers. You need to 
write in a way that persuades these groups to read your paper further. There is an 
apocryphal story about the former editor of a top economics journal who said that if he 
did not understand what the paper was about by the end of the first page, it was desk-
rejected. We don't employ explicit rules of thumb like this but please note the message 
well. Abstracts should not be longer than around 150 words. "Conclusions" sections 
should focus on the genuine conclusions to be drawn from the article. They might also 
indicate promising lines for future research. Too often these sections simply contain a 
summary -this is redundant repetition. 
(d) Do not submit "review articles" or "survey articles". The journal does not pub-
lish them. Short "notes" or "comments" are not published either (with rare 
exceptions). </p>



<p>S. P. Jenkins </p>

<p>(e) Do not submit articles that are too long. Polish your prose to improve succinctness 
and focus and to remove repetition. The average length of a published article is around 
20 journal pages, so aim for that target at submission stage. To do this, make judi-
cious use of an appendix to contain proofs and sensitivity analyses (for example). 
Few appendices are published along with articles, but we can make them available as 
Online Supplementary Material hosted on Springer's webpages with a hyperlink from 
the main text. Currently there are no length restrictions on these online appendices. 
Clearly indicate at the time of submission which materials are intended to appear in an 
online appendix. 
(f) Use footnotes sparingly and avoid long footnotes. If there are more footnotes than 
pages of your main text, that is a strong signal that there is a problem. So too is 
a footnote of more than a few sentences. Do not include equations. Some journals 
ban footnotes altogether on the grounds that something worth saying is either worth 
saying in the main text or not at all. We allow footnotes but are sympathetic to the 
reasoning. 
(g) Prepare tables and figures with the same care and diligence as the rest of your arti-
cle: they are an essential component of the effective communication of your analysis. 
Readers should be able to understand most of what a table or figure shows without 
consulting the main text. Use explanatory notes if necessary. For examples of standard 
table formats used by the journal, consult recent issues. In tables, do not use colour or 
shading, and omit vertical lines. In figures, ensure that there are appropriate axis titles, 
axis labels, and legends. Give careful consideration to using black and white and grey 
shades rather than colour. Although the journal has the facility to publish graphs in 
colour in the online version, the hard copy version and what most readers see when 
they print articles out is black and white, and legibility is often lost if colour used. 
Appropriate choice of marker symbols and line patterns may help avoid this problem. 
If you do use colour, select shades that colour-blind readers can distinguish. Put figure 
titles and notes in the article text, not in the graph itself. 
(h) Authors of empirical papers are recommended to produce replication materials. See the 
discussion earlier. Authors of theoretical papers should continue to provide proofs or 
other relevant derivations (but see also the remarks about judicious use of appendices 
above). 
(i) Authors whose first language is not English are recommended to have their submission 
copy-edited by a native English speaker. 
(j) Submit a polished 'final' version, not a version which you think might be tidied up later 
in the process or a version for which you hope referees will help resolve unresolved 
issues. To this end, get feedback on your paper -and be prepared to revise it multiple 
times -prior to submission. Papers that are insufficiently well developed face a high 
desk-rejection risk. </p>

<p>Potential submitters might also reflect on the advice of Maureen Pirog, long-time edi-
tor of the Journal of Policy Analysis and Management. She discusses a "top 10 list of 
things that prospective authors should and should not do if they want to publish their work" 
(2014: 843). Most of her points are generic, and hence also relevant for submission to this 
journal. </p>

<p>Editorial 2015 </p>



<p>7 Acknowledgments </p>

<p>I took over as JEI Editor-in-Chief from Chico Ferreira from 1 February 2014. I thank Chico 
for his support and advice, and for continuing to handle the submissions under his care 
until Autumn 2014 (after which I took over the balance remaining). I am pleased that Chico 
continues on the Editorial Board. 
I couldn't do my job without the contributions of the Associate Editors: Andrea 
Brandolini, Valentino Dardanoni, Markus Jäntti, Cecilia Garcia-Peñalosa, and Buhong 
Zheng. I thank them all. Buhong resigned at the end of 2014 due to other commitments 
but saw out the remaining papers under his charge. We are grateful for his service and 
glad that he continues on the Editorial Board. I am pleased to welcome as new Asso-
ciate Editors Dirk Van de gaer (from August 2015) and Olivier Bargain (from October 
2015). 
Also making substantial contributions to the JEI are Nora Lustig (Forum Editor), Xavi 
Ramos (Book Review Editor), and Peter Lambert (Rediscovered Classics Editor). After long 
and distinguished service, Peter has resigned his post but we shall continue the section (see 
above). 
Our eminent Advisory Council continues to be: Tony Atkinson, François Bourguignon, 
Nanak Kakwani, Serge-Christophe Kolm, and Amartya Sen. 
I am also pleased to acknowledge the support and advice of the Editorial Board, the 
members of which are listed in the journal and on Springer's website. To be able to call on 
such an august body of individuals for advice and support is invaluable for developing the 
journal's editorial policy. The general responsibilities of a member, agreed at the 2013 and 
2015 Editorial Board meetings, are as follows: 
First and foremost, the Editorial Board provides overall editorial guidance and direc-
tion to the Journal's Editor in Chief and Associate Editors. . . . [E]ditorial board members 
are also expected to assist the Editors with timely referee reports, when requested, at 
least some two or three times per year. In addition, at our [2013] meeting, Board mem-
bers agreed to provide "emergency referee reports" on a short notice, in those (relatively 
rare) situations in which referees are excessively late with their reports, and the Editor 
in charge of the paper feels that he or she cannot make a well-informed decision on the 
basis of a single report. This new commitment was suggested as a means to reduce review 
delays in the Journal. Requests of this nature remain infrequent -but they are certainly a 
possibility. 
The Editorial Board also agreed in 2015 that the existing policy of gradual refreshment 
of its membership be continued. Springer devolves the choice of Editorial Board member-
ship (and Associate Editors), entirely to the Editor-in-Chief, but of course I take advice 
on these matters before making decisions. If you have suggestions, send them directly 
to me. 
I value the advice and assistance received from the Springer team, especially the 
following individuals: Lorraine Klimowich (Senior Editor), Allan Nebres and (from Octo-
ber 2014) Janelle Caculba (Editorial Assistants), plus Barney Boy Cutamora (Journals 
Production). 
Finally, we should pay tribute to those individuals who have given their time and 
expertise to refereeing papers for us. </p>



<p>S. P. Jenkins </p>

<p>Referees in 2014 </p>

<p>We would like to express our gratitude for the assistance of the following individuals 
who agreed to referee articles during Calendar Year 2014: </p>

<p>Rolf 
Aaberge 
Rafael 
Domenech 
Julie 
Litchfield 
Timothy Smeeding 
Antonio 
Abatemarco 
Markus Eberhardt 
Haiyong 
Liu 
Ricardo Sousa 
Adrian 
Adermon 
Tor 
Eriksson 
Joan 
Llull 
David 
Stifel 
Jim 
Alm 
John 
Ermisch 
Brice 
Magdalou 
Steve 
Stillman 
Yoram 
Amiel 
Fernanda Estevan 
Elisabetta 
Magnani 
Brennan Thompson 
Gordon 
Anderson 
Ivan 
Faiella 
Paul 
Makdissi 
Aurelio Tobias 
James 
Ang 
Hans 
Fehr 
Tuomas 
Malinen 
Pietro 
Tommasino 
Benedicte 
Apouey 
Martin 
Feldkircher 
Marco 
Manacorda 
Florencia Torche 
Joao Pedro Azevedo 
Priscila Ferreira 
Fabio 
Mariani 
Jenny 
Torssander 
Francisco 
Azpitarte 
Ada 
Ferrer-i-Carbonell Pekka 
Martikainen Matti 
Tuomala 
Elena 
Barcena-Martin Gary 
Fields 
James 
McDonald 
Renos 
Vakis 
Steve 
Beckman 
Carlo 
Fiorio 
Paul 
McNelis 
Justin 
Valasek 
Rui 
Benfica 
John 
Fitzgerald 
Luca 
Merlino 
Robert Valletta 
Christopher Bennett 
Liana 
Fox 
Branko 
Milanovic 
Philippe Van Kerm 
Simone 
Bertoli 
Tommaso Frattini 
Anirban 
Mitra 
Tom 
Van Ourti 
Martin 
Biewen 
Nobuhiko Fuwa 
Valentine 
Moghadam 
Arthur van Soest 
John 
Bishop 
Francisco Gallego 
Salvatore 
Morelli 
Gerlinde Verbist 
Rene 
Boeheim 
Robert 
Gary-Bobo 
Alexander Mosthaf 
Gregory Verdugo 
Kristof 
Bosmans 
Chiara 
Gigliarano 
Redzo 
Mujcic 
Sarah 
Voitchovsky 
Bruce 
Bradbury 
Jeremie Gignoux 
Stephane 
Mussard 
Oscar 
Volij 
Julia 
Bredtmann 
Paul 
Glewwe 
Renata 
Narita 
Daniel Waldenstrom 
Richard 
Breen 
Carlos 
Gradin 
Ronald 
Oaxaca 
Daniel Westbrook 
Ylenia 
Brilli 
Carol 
Graham 
Donal 
O'Neill 
Bradley Wimmer 
Richard 
Brown 
Paul 
Gregg 
Eduardo 
Ortiz-Juarez Gaston Yalonetzky 
Paolo 
Brunori 
John 
Haisken-DeNew Berkay 
Ozcan 
Kazuhiro Yamamoto 
Gustaf 
Bruze 
Susan 
Harkness 
Flaviana 
Palmisano 
Shlomo Yitzhaki 
Isabel 
Cairo 
Tarjei 
Havnes 
Fabrizio 
Panebianco 
Buhong Zheng 
Lisa 
Cameron 
Ruth 
Hill 
Eugenio 
Peluso 
Natalia Zinovyeva 
Raymundo Campos-Vazquez Emilio 
Huet-Vaughn 
Vito 
Peragine 
Claudio Zoli 
Lorenzo 
Cappellari 
Gordon Hughes 
Jukka 
Pirttilä 
Alessandra Casarico 
William Jack 
Nicolas 
Pistolesi 
Amparo 
Castello 
John 
Jerrim 
Maria Grazia Pittau 
Arpita 
Chatterjee 
Lamia 
Kandil 
Andre 
Portela de Souza 
Luc 
Christiaensen 
Loukas 
Karabarbounis 
Nick 
Powdthavee 
Federico 
Cingano 
Murat 
Kirdar 
Esteban 
Puentes 
Andrew 
Clark 
Gustav 
Kjellsson 
Paul 
Ramskogler 
Fabio 
Clementi 
Stephan Klasen 
Michael 
Ransom 
Fabrizio 
Colonna 
Christian Kleiber 
Sean 
Reardon 
Frank 
Cowell 
Stephen Knowles 
Philipp 
Rehm 
Alberto 
Dalmazzo 
Martyna Kobus 
Giacomo 
Rodano 
Conchita 
D'Ambrosio 
Martyna Kobus 
Jesper 
Roine 
Sara 
De La Rica 
Wolfgang Kuhle 
Laurence 
Roope 
Joyee 
Deb 
Audun 
Langorgen 
Mariacristina Rossi 
Koen 
Decancq 
Peter 
Lanjouw 
Anna 
rosso 
Andre 
Decoster 
Casilda 
Lasso de la Vega Francois 
Rycx 
Uwe 
Deichmann 
Junsoo 
Lee 
Ernesto 
Savaglio 
Coral 
Del Rio 
Marco 
Leonardi 
Christian 
Schluter 
Manthos 
Delis 
Peter 
Levell 
Suman 
Seth 
George 
Deltas 
Guay 
Lim 
Dina 
Shatnawi 
Walter 
Distaso 
Joanne 
Lindley 
Eva 
Sierminska </p>



</text></tei>