<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1257%2Fjep.4.1.99" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>S </p>

<p>imulation models, now widely used in the physical sciences, can also help 
economists in depicting the actions and interactions of individuals and firms 
through time. Such models can be built and run on any personal computer. 
They can illuminate a wide variety of issues that are difficult to analyze with an 
economist's conventional tool-kit and are especially useful in studying dynamic 
processes. Microsimulation models allow the analyst to produce simulated aggregate 
time series that are rigorously consistent with the assumptions made about behavior on 
the micro level. Thus, simulations provide a means of bridging the micro-macro split 
in economic analysis. 
This article provides an introduction to microsimulation: how it works, how to do 
it, its potential, and its drawbacks. It then allows readers, even those with no 
experience in computer programming, to work through the details of a simple 
microsimulation model. Readers can put this model on their PCs, watch it run 
through its paces, and experiment with their own modifications. With this model as an 
example, it should be fairly easy to create programs for new models on other subjects 
for use in theoretical exploration, empirical research, or classroom demonstrations. 
The demonstration model I present depicts the experience of individual workers 
during recession and recovery in the labor market. As the model runs, its internal 
"Census Bureau" performs surveys on the microlevel, and sums up to macrolevel 
variables. The model is simple, but it has some interesting applications. After 
explaining how to set it up, I use it to explore the effect of unemployment insurance 
on the level of unemployment, and to point up a common fallacy in current labor 
market literature. </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>A diskette containing the program for the model discussed in this article, plus programs for the 
microsimulation models of Pryor (1973), Nelson, Winter, and Schuette (1976), and some others is 
available free from Member Services, Inter-university Consortium for Political and Social Research, 
University of Michigan, P.O. Box 1248, Ann Arbor, MI 48106. However, you do not need the 
diskette to follow the discussion in this article, or to try out the program it presents on a PC. </p>

<p>Constructing a Computer-Simulated Scenario and 
Watching It Play Out </p>

<p>A microsimulation of an economic activity is constructed by assembling an 
appropriate cast of characters, and fitting out each individual person or firm with a 
set of behavioral rules. An actor in the simulation will "exist" in the computer's 
memory space as a collection of pieces of information, rather like the record of an 
actual person's account in the computer of a brokerage house, which is updated each 
time a transaction is made. The analyst may derive the behavioral rules for the actors 
from a theory depicting a utility-maximizing process of choice, from a regression study 
on Census data, from a laboratory experiment with human subjects, or may simply 
make up rules that seem reasonably realistic or that are merely serviceable to the 
analytic task at hand. Wherever the rules come from, all the functional forms and 
parameter values must be specified for each run of the simulation on the computer. 
The analyst must also set highly specific ground rules for the simulated interac-
tions of the individuals (or firms) with each other. Interactions are recorded as they 
occur. Numerical reports summarizing the action are issued at suitable intervals, as 
Dow Jones indexes are issued during the trading day, or unemployment rates are 
issued each month. The analyst uses the reports to try to make generalizations about 
how the specified micro situation, as well as any exogenous events, have affected the 
simulated macro outcomes. 
Microsimulation models have a number of advantages over conventional meth-
ods used by economists. One advantage is the explicitness with which the interactions 
on the micro level can be depicted. Conventional methods of economic analysis often 
provide cogent derivations of individuals' contingency plans, but tend to be weak in 
describing the process that allows all the contingency plans to mesh together. Highly 
mathematical accounts of the derivation of individuals' behavior rules are not 
infrequently followed by vague verbal descriptions of what goes on when the individu-
als come together and interact. This vagueness can lead to error, as has been the case 
in the labor market issues discussed below. 
Simulation can be especially helpful in dealing with problems of information and 
expectations. The model builder can specify in a precise way the information the 
actors come to have as the action proceeds, the expectations they form, and how they 
react to that knowledge and those expectations. The actors can be allowed to be led 
into mistakes by their decision rules, suffer from their mistakes, and even learn from 
them. </p>

<p>Barbara R. Bergmann 101 </p>

<p>Another advantage of simulation models is that they can be set up to be 
completely recursive, as real life is. The elimination of simultaneous equations allows 
us to get results from a simulation model without having to go through a process of 
solution. Instead one gets the computer to play out the scenario and analyzes the 
numerical outcome, which may or may not achieve an equilibrium. Models that don't 
have to be solved can be changed or added to freely and easily, as exemplified below. 
Nonlinearities, switches of regime, and other complexities are easily accommodated. 
A number of small-scale simulation models have been built to explore subjects 
that conventional methods handle only awkwardly, if at all. For example, Nelson, 
Winter, and Schuette (1976) modeled the spread and effects of technical change. 
Individual firms were depicted discovering and trying out new modes of production, 
or imitating successful competitors. The hiring, capital purchases, and profits of every 
firm at each moment in time were kept track of, and parameter values were found 
that allowed the model's simulated macrodata to track U.S. macrodata on income and 
productivity. 
In other examples, Bergmann (1973) simulated U.S. poverty rates by tracking 
the incomes of simulated individuals as unemployment rates and wage rates changed 
in accordance with historical patterns. Pryor (1973) looked at the effect of marriage 
and inheritance patterns on income distribution through many generations. He 
simulated individuals picking spouses, accumulating assets, having children, dying, 
and leaving an inheritance to one or more of the children. His model displays the 
resulting trends in the degree of inequality by computing simulated time series of Gini 
coefficients based on the simulated microdata. Pryor's model can be embodied in a 
program of 75 lines. Large-scale microsimulation models that sum to national income 
accounts have been built by Eliason for Sweden (1976), by Adelman and Robinson 
for Korea (1978), and by Bennett and Bergmann for the United States (1986). 
For studies of policy, simulation models offer an opportunity to embed into a 
formal model a realistic description of how a regulation, tax, or subsidy affects the 
economic actors. (See Orcutt, Caldwell and Wertheimer, 1976; Haveman and Hollen-
beck, 1980). Our delineation here of unemployment insurance shows how a govern-
ment program with nonlinear rules can easily be added to a simulation model with a 
very few additional computer instructions. Simulation models can also serve as a 
theoretical framework for empirical studies, just as conventional models can. Data can 
be used to estimate a model's parameters and to gauge its goodness of fit (Bergmann, 
1974; 1989). 
Of course, simulation models have their drawbacks. When using them, the 
analyst has to give up the formal or informal deduction used in conventional models 
and has to rely instead on inductive analysis of numerical results. This may be less 
certain and is certainly less entertaining. Drawing qualitative generalizations from the 
numerical results is fraught with the possibility of error. The very ease with which new 
detail can be added to simulation models poses a danger. When the models grow more 
complex, the job of checking their cogency, of rooting out bugs, and interpreting and 
generalizing from their results becomes more problematical. </p>

<p>102 Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>A simulation study can explore what happens when the actors follow optimizing 
behavioral rules, as in Fair (1974). But simulations can just as easily explore what 
happens when the actors follow rules of thumb which have not been proved out as 
optimal. Such simulations may seem sleazy to those economists for whom respectable 
microeconomics is synonymous with solving optimization problems. They fear that 
simulation opens the door to a loss of quality control in the profession, if the stringent 
paradigm of mathematical specification and solution for optima is relaxed. 
However, the way to make an optimum decision is not known in many important 
economic arenas that deserve economists' attention and analysis. Sometimes the actor 
does not have the information that economic theory assumes, like a reliable demand 
curve for one's product, or a good line on what one's competitor is likely to do. 
Sometimes there is too much information around, and it is difficult to process it all. 
Sometimes the actor cannot be presumed to know the optimization technique. In such 
cases, simulated experimentation with the effects of varying rules of thumb may be the 
nearest possible approach to optimization. Some empirical research (Tversky and 
Kahneman, 1988; Thaler's columns in this Journal) suggests that human beings are 
apt to follow rules that produce results that are inferior to those obtained with rules 
that economists might devise. Where this is the case, simulations of non-optimal but 
empirically true behavior patterns should yield more realistic predictions than norma-
tive theories that are empirically false. 
Obviously, simulation models that depict individuals who endlessly repeat obvi-
ous mistakes deserve condemnation, and all models can benefit from criticism. But 
treating the simulation methodology itself as entirely taboo cuts out a lot of valuable 
possibilities for exploration. Economists need more tools in our kits, not fewer. 
Let me now turn to an example that will display some of the advantages and 
disadvantages of the simulation methodology. The reader, after studying it, can draw 
his or her own conclusions. </p>

<p>An Example of Labor Market Simulation </p>

<p>The labor market makes a good subject for simulation, since the results of the 
search process of individuals are not easy to represent as functions, or to aggregate. 
The demand side of the market and the interactions of workers with potential 
employers, which have been left rather vague in much of the current literature, can be 
fleshed out. 
Much conventional analysis of the labor market concentrates on the individual 
unemployed worker who searches for a job and finds an ample array of vacancies for 
his or her consideration. In each period, the utility-maximizing worker weighs the 
benefits of taking one of these available jobs at the offered wage against the benefits of 
remaining unemployed. Unemployed people are then thought of, following Lucas and 
Rapping (1969), as a group of workers who could have taken jobs at some wage or </p>

<p>Micro-to-Macro Simulation 103 </p>

<p>other, but chose otherwise. Anything that increases the propensity of some workers to 
refuse employment is viewed as increasing the number of unemployed. 
The microsimulation approach presented here seeks to develop a dynamic 
portrayal of the action on the microeconomic level that characterizes the behavior of 
individual workers but also the behavior of employers, rejecting the usual implicit 
assumption of unlimited job availability. The model also sets a protocol for the 
interactions of employers and unemployed workers. After these steps have been taken, 
one can run the simulation program, and watch unemployed workers searching for 
jobs, interacting with employers who have empty job slots they want to fill. 
An unemployment insurance system is added to this simulated labor market, 
complete with eligibility requirements and limited-time benefits. Then, by running the 
model again, we can see what difference the unemployment insurance program makes 
to the unemployment rate. To preview the results, the simulation will show that, 
contrary to the claims of conventional analysts, refusals of job offers by stipend-receiv-
ing malingerers does not in all circumstances increase the number of unemployed 
people. The simulation avoids a narrow focus on the isolated choice of a single worker, 
thus bringing to visibility a point that conventional analysts tend to lose sight of as 
they verbally pass from the micro to the macro: that the refusal of one worker to take 
a particular job allows another worker a shot at that vacancy. </p>

<p>The Simulation Technique 
The core of the model is an extremely simple representation of worker move-
ments into and out of jobs. It is written in <rs type="software">BASIC</rs>, a close analogue to <rs type="software">FORTRAN</rs>. 
Most PC owners have access to the software necessary to build and run BASIC 
programs. 
In this simple model, workers will be homogeneous as to skills and other 
characteristics, and all will be equally acceptable to employers for all jobs. Considera-
tions relating to wage levels, either on the supply side or the demand side, will be 
pushed under the rug. (The significance of this formulation is discussed below.) The 
number of jobs that employers want to fill each week will be exogenously determined: 
fed into the computer as data. Workers, after a brief period of search, will take any 
job that is offered. The size of the labor force will be constant. If the analyst desires a 
more realistic model, all of these features can be changed quite easily. 
Each "week," the actors in the model carry out a round of simulated activities. 
The micro-level scenario for a week is as follows: First, employers decide on the stock 
of jobs they wish to have filled this week. Some workers will be laid off, others will 
quit. The workers to be separated from jobs are picked at random from the ranks of 
the employed to join the ranks of the unemployed. After the separations have 
occurred, the unemployed (including some separated in previous periods who have not 
yet taken jobs) search for job vacancies; some are chosen at random to come to an 
interview, and some of these agree to become employed. At the end of the weekly 
activity, the "Census Bureau" surveys the situations of all the simulated individuals. It 
notes whether they are in a state of unemployment, and how long that state has </p>

<p>104 Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>persisted. It "publishes" simulated macro-data based on its survey: the unemployment 
rate and the average of unemployment durations. 
The individual workers and their activities are "depicted" by the information in 
the computer's memory spaces. This model will use just two pieces of information 
about each of them. IEMPST(I) is the current employment status of the Ith worker, 
which takes the value 0 if the worker is unemployed and the value 1 if the worker is 
employed. IDATE(I) is the week the Ith worker last moved from employment to 
unemployment. For example, if the 4th worker makes such a move in the 3rd week of 
the simulation, IDATE(4) is at that point set equal to 3. In the course of the 
simulation, the worker's activities take the form of changes in those values. A worker 
can be "observed" by the analyst at any point in simulated time by asking the 
computer for a printout of the current value of these two variables for that worker. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>One device used in many simulation programs, including this one, is the 
introduction of an element of randomness to the action. For example, in depicting 
labor turnover, individual workers are picked at random to leave their jobs and 
become unemployed, rather than being chosen by some systematic rule, as might be 
the case in a more complex model. 
2 BASIC provides the computer with a routine for </p>

<p>the computation of random numbers with uniform distribution between 0 and 1. 
Whenever the variable RND appears in an instruction the computer is executing, a 
new random number is computed, and RND takes on the value of that number. 
The variable names used in the BASIC program that performs the simulation are 
listed in Table 1, and the program itself is listed in Table 2. Each line of the program 
is an instruction, or a set of instructions to the computer. 
3 The beginning of the </p>

<p>program is devoted to computer setup, so it is more interesting to skip down and 
examine first the lines of the program which arrange for some individuals to move 
from employment to unemployment. 
Lines 180-210 of the program pick out a particular employed worker and 
change that worker's status to unemployed: </p>

<p>180 ICHOSE = RND*LABFOR + .5 [A random integer between 1 and LABFOR is 
generated and stored in the memory location designated to hold the value for </p>

<p>1 Obviously, for a more detailed model it would be useful to depict additional characteristics of the 
individual actors. In a labor market model, each individual's race, sex, skill, experience, current reservation 
wage, and so on, might be kept track of. Initial values for some of these characteristics might be imported 
from a (real) census database, as pioneered by Orcutt (1960). 
2 Other assumptions might be implemented. For example, those more recently hired, or those marked as 
having low skills might be given a relatively high chance of leaving. In a model by Nichols (1980) in which 
jobs and workers are heterogeneous, quits are motivated when workers find out about higher-wage openings 
for which they consider themselves competent. 
3 Some lines have several instructions, separated by the symbol ":", as in line 70. The computer performs 
instructions one after the other in the order they appear, unless directed elsewhere by a GOTO, as in line 
190. Repetition may be called for, as in line 130, which calls for 69 repetitions of the instructions between 
130 and 410. Each variable has a memory space associated with it that stores its current value. Almost all 
instructions tell the computer to change the value recorded in a single memory space. </p>

<p>Barbara R. Bergmann 105 </p>

<p>Table 1 </p>

<p>Variables Used in Labor Market Simulation Programs </p>

<p>ICHOSE, which will serve as the ID number of the worker chosen to be moved from 
employment to unemployment.] </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>190 IF IEMPST(ICHOSE) = 0 THEN GOTO 180 [If the worker chosen in line 
180 is already unemployed, go back and chose another. Otherwise, go on to the next 
instruction.] 
200 IEMPST(ICHOSE) = 0 [Change the status of the employed worker chosen to 
"unemployed."] 
210 IDATE(ICHOSE) = IWEEK [Record the current week, IWEEK, as the date of 
this worker's most recent transition from employment to unemployment.] 
The number of workers who move from employment to unemployment in a 
given week depends on changes in the number of jobs and rates of turnover among 
workers in jobs. In each week the simulation runs, we want the appropriate number of 
people to make such a transition in status. That means determining how many times 
the program should run through lines 180-210, and then instructing the computer to </p>

<p>4 When a random number between 0 and 1, RND, is multiplied by LABFOR, the size of the labor force, 
and .5 is added, we get a real number X between .5 and LABFOR + .5. When that number is stored in the 
memory space for ICHOSE, which has been marked as an integer as a result of instruction 10, BASIC 
rounds it off to the nearest integer. This procedure produces an ICHOSE that is an integer between 1 and 
LABFOR. </p>

<p>Table 2 
BASIC program of labor market simulation </p>

<p>Micro-to-Macro Simulation 107 </p>

<p>do the required number of run-throughs. These tasks are accomplished in lines 
140-170: </p>

<p>140 LEAVS = RATLV*( LABFOR -UN) [The number of persons involved in turnover 
(other than turnover due to a net change in the number of jobs), LEAVS, is 
determined. The (exogenously supplied) turnover rate, RATLV, is multiplied by the 
number of currently occupied job slots, LABFOR-UN.] 
150 DIFEMP -NEMP(IWEEK) -NEMP(IWEEK -1) [The change since the previous 
week in the number of job slots employers wish to fill is computed.] 
160 IF DIFEMP&lt;0 THEN ISEP = LEAVS -DIFEMP ELSE ISEP = LEAVS 
[The number of persons going from employment to unemployment this week, ISEP, is 
calculated. ISEP is set at the number of jobs that have been vacated, LEAVS, unless 
there has been a net loss of jobs. If that has been the case, ISEP is increased (by 
subtracting a negative number) by the number of jobs lost.] 
170 FOR K = 1 TO ISEP [Perform the disemployment routine ISEP times.] 
Then come the four steps already explained above: </p>

<p>180 ICHOSE = RND*LABFOR + .5 
190 IF IEMPST(ICHOSE) = 0 THEN GOTO 180 
200 IEMPST(ICHOSE) = 0 
210 IDATE(ICHOSE) = IWEEK 
and the instruction that serves to mark the end of the disemployment routine: 
220 NEXT K </p>

<p>The movement of workers from unemployment into employment is achieved in 
an analogous way. The appropriate number of hires is calculated (line 230), and the 
computer instructed to perform that many (lines 240, 290). The people to be 
"interviewed" by employers are chosen at random from among the unemployed (lines 
250-260). Employers are programmed to accept any interviewed worker who wants a 
job. But workers who have become unemployed in the current week refuse any job 
offer (line 265), so as to have time to feel out the market. Workers unemployed at least 
a week who are chosen for an interview are programmed to accept any offered job, 
and if chosen their status is changed (line 270). 
This depiction of hiring can be thought of as a rudimentary, shorthand account 
of a search process. Searchers for job openings walk the streets of the business district 
at random, and the person who happens to be closest to the window in which a sign 
announcing a vacancy has appeared gets the next interview with the employer who 
controls the slot. 
The program starts with a group of lines which feed the computer the informa-
tion it needs to start the simulation off. The computer memory is set up (lines 10-30). 
An exogenous macroeconomic time series giving the number of jobs that employers 
want filled each week is entered (lines 40-60) into NEMP(IWEEK). In the first 19 
weeks, we assume employers wish to employ 950 workers, out of a constant labor force 
LABFOR of 1000. Thereafter, desired employment falls steadily for 10 weeks, </p>

<p>108 Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>remains steady at 895 for 11 weeks, and then rises again to its old value. Any 
alternative pattern of fluctuations in labor demand that the researcher wants to test, 
including actual time series data, can be entered instead. 
In lines 90-120, initial values of IEMPST and IDATE are assigned. 
5 In line 130, </p>

<p>the simulation is set running, with IWEEK taking on the values 2, 3, 4 . . . 70, in turn. 
The commands between lines 130 and 410 are performed each week. 
Following the changes in workers' status that constitute each week's activity, a 
"census" of the computer memory is taken, so that the information may be printed 
out on the simulated economy's macro-level variables. The counting of the unem-
ployed is done on lines 320-330, which tell the computer to add 1 to the current value 
of UN for each worker found whose value of IEMPST is 0. UTIMAV, the average 
duration of unemployment (lines 340, 380), is the macro-level analogue of the micro-
level expression IWEEK-IDATE(I). </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>On line 350, the computer is ordered to printed the ID number of each 
unemployed worker, and the length of time the current spell of unemployment has 
lasted for that worker. Printing out microdata provides a check that the program is 
working properly and provides some insight into the process being simulated. The 
macrodata generated are sent to the computer's screen on line 400 and sent to a file 
called "results" on line 405. </p>

<p>Results of Running the Simulation 
Given the program, the output of the simulation depends on the sequence of 
values given to NEMP(IWEEK), the number of employees that employers wish to 
have on board each week, the turnover rate RATLV, and the sequence of random 
numbers generated. The macroseries shown in Figure 1 were generated by a single run 
of the model in Table 2. 
The fall and subsequent recovery in job availability produces changes in the 
average length of unemployment spells that are more complex than one might have 
imagined. As unemployment starts to rise, average duration of uncompleted spells 
falls for a time. This results from the increase in the number of newly unemployed 
people, whose spells so far are short. However, unemployed workers experience 
increasing difficulty in re-entering employment, as more of them are vying for a 
slightly smaller number of openings. So average duration starts to increase. Durations 
start to fall only after the recovery in demand has been going on for some time, but 
then fall rapidly. </p>

<p>5 Better initial conditions on the microeconomic level can be generated by running the simulation for a 
considerable number of time periods at an appropriate setting of the exogenous variables, and printing the 
microeconomic information about the actors into a data file at the end of the last period. In subsequent 
runs, this file can be read in, and can replace lines 90-120. If this technique is used, care must be taken to 
insure that the macro and micro conditions that one starts off with are consistent. 
6 Of course, the simulation's Census Bureau can be programmed to print the average length of completed 
spells. This is a good exercise for the novice. </p>

<p>Barbara R. Bergmann 109 </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Unemployment Rates and Average Durations from the Simulation Model in 
Table 2 </p>

<p>In this first version of the model, all jobs employers wish to fill are filled, so the 
unemployment rate has no random element. However, there is a random element to 
the average duration. The unemployed group is small, and if those people picked at 
random out of that group to go into jobs have unusually long or short durations, the 
average duration of those remaining unemployed shifts down or up in response. The 
reported duration series could be smoothed out by running the simulation repeatedly 
with different sequences of random numbers and averaging out the duration series or 
by increasing the size of the population represented. 
The conventional analysis implicitly assumes that the number of open job slots 
could increase so as to take care of all unemployed workers, if only the unemployed 
(or the employers) would bid the wage down to a sufficiently low level. Of course, the 
simulation could be rewritten to allow for varying wage bids, and for elasticity in the 
supply of and demand for labor. But in that case, unemployment would occur solely 
on account of the job refusals induced by line 265, and would reflect only the number 
of recent separations. Durations would no longer reflect any difficulty in getting 
reemployed, because such difficulty would have been assumed away. 
The simulation presented here, by leaving wage offers out of the picture, 
implicitly casts the unemployed as passive "wage takers" and employers as "wage 
makers," who do not adjust wages downward when there is unemployment. This may 
well be more realistic than the conventional approach, and comport better with the 
"efficiency wage" ideas now current (for example, see the articles collected in Akerlof 
and Yellen, 1986). </p>

<p>110 Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>Putting Unemployment Insurance into the Model </p>

<p>When practitioners of the conventional approach tackle the effect of unemploy-
ment insurance on the rate of unemployment, they concentrate on the effect of 
unemployment insurance coverage on the duration of unemployment for current 
individual workers. A utility-maximizing unemployed worker will factor the availabil-
ity of unemployment benefits into the decision as to whether to take one of the open 
job slots or to prolong his or her spell of unemployment. Common sense suggests that 
these substantial stipends motivate some covered workers into prolonging their unem-
ployment, and regression analysis of microdata on unemployed workers supports this. 
The implication is then drawn that each person who stays out of work because of 
the availability of an unemployment insurance stipend thereby constitutes a net 
addition to the stock of unemployed persons. Those taking this approach and drawing 
this implication include Feldstein (1973), Hamermesh (1977), Baily (1977), Clark and 
Summers (1982), and Topel (1985). 
7 However, the simulation will demonstrate that </p>

<p>this one-for-one increase does not necessarily occur. 
Our labor market simulation program can be easily amended to add an unem-
ployment insurance regime, and to study its effects on the level of unemployment. 
Table 3 shows the new program, which is the old program of Table 2 with some new 
lines interpolated in bold-faced type. 
I have created for each worker a new piece of information, ELIG(I), the weeks of 
unemployment insurance that the Ith worker is currently eligible for. Each week the 
simulation runs, the value of ELIG is altered for each worker according to the 
assumed rules governing eligibility. I will assume that an employed worker gets a 
week of eligibility for each three weeks of employment, to a maximum of 6 weeks. The 
model can keep track of each worker's value of ELIG by adding four lines: </p>

<p>311 IF IEMPST(IPERS) = 1 THEN ELIG(IPERS) = ELIG(IPERS) + 1/3 </p>

<p>[Each week, an employed worker earns an additional eligibility credit of 1/3 of a 
week.] 
312 IF IEMPST(IPERS) = O THEN ELIG(IPERS) = ELIG(IPERS) -1 [Each 
week, an unemployed person uses up one week of eligibility.] 
313 IF ELIG(IPERS)&gt;6 THEN ELIG(IPERS) = 6 [Number of weeks of eligi-
bility cannot exceed 6.] 
314 IF ELIG(IPERS)&lt;0 THEN ELIG(IPERS) = 0 [Number of weeks of eligi-
bility cannot be negative.] 
The next step is to make workers with unemployment insurance coverage pickier 
about the jobs they will accept. To do so in a simple way, let us make an extreme </p>

<p>7 Many of these authors also discuss the probability that the existence of unemployment insurance raises the 
unemployment rate in a second way-it motivates employers to conduct temporary layoffs that would not 
occur without it. A simulation model that took account of that possibility might have to model employers' 
weighting of the likelihood of laid-off workers taking another job given the expected timing of callbacks, the 
firm's investment in these workers' training, and the benefits of having a large crew at times of peak load. </p>

<p>Micro-to-Macro Simulation 111 </p>

<p>assumption and suppose that out-of-work persons malinger by refusing any job offer 
whatever until their remaining eligibility for unemployment insurance is down to one 
week. An employer may fill a job slot with a non-malingerer, if one can be found. But 
if the employer cannot fill a job after a certain number of interviews (here set at 10), 
the job remains vacant until the next period. This can be expressed by adding the 
following lines: </p>

<p>241 NFAIL = 0 [NFAIL is a variable used to keep track of the number of times the 
employer tries unsuccessfully to fill the job. At the initiation of the effort to fill each 
job, NFAIL is set back to zero.] 
266 IF ELIG(ICHOSE) &lt;2 THEN GOTO 270 [If the chosen worker has less 
than 2 periods of eligibility left, the worker consents to take the job offer. In this case, 
control passes to line 270, an instruction to reemploy that worker. Otherwise, the 
instruction on line 267 is performed.] 
267 NFAIL = NFAIL + 1 [Control has passed to this instruction (rather than line 
270) because the worker chosen is malingering, and not yet ready to accept a job. The 
number of times the employer has tried to fill this job, NFAIL, is recorded as 
increased by 1.] 
268 IF NFAIL&lt;10 THEN GOTO 250 ELSE GOTO 290 [If there have been 
fewer than 10 unsuccessful tries to fill this job, the employer chooses another 
out-of-work candidate to interview by passing to line 250. If 10 tries have been made, 
the job will remain vacant until next week. In this case, control will pass to statement 
290, and efforts commence to fill the next job.] </p>

<p>We interpolate a line to compute the number of held-over vacancies: </p>

<p>372 VAC = NEMP(IWEEK) -(LABFOR -UN) [Vacancies, VAC, are calculated as 
the difference between the employment desired by employers, NEMP(IWEEK), and 
the number of workers actually in jobs.] 
In the next week, when the hiring routine is performed, the number of hires 
employers desire should be augmented by the number of vacancies. This is done by 
adding a line: </p>

<p>231 IHIR = IHIR + VAC [The hires that employers would like to make is 
increased by the number of jobs left vacant at the end of the previous week.] </p>

<p>Results of Running the Unemployment Insurance Simulation </p>

<p>Figure 2 compares simulated unemployment rates when malingering is absent 
and when it is present due to the availability of unemployment insurance. Malinger-
ing does have a positive effect on the unemployment rate under some circumstances, 
but the effect is shown by the simulation model to be dependent on the degree of slack 
in the labor market. In the tighter labor market periods, when employers want to fill 
jobs that would employ all but 5 percent of the labor force, the heavy malingering 
behavior we have assumed in the simulation raises the measured unemployment rate 
to 6.2 percent. In the slacker period, where employers would prefer to employ all but </p>



<p>Journal of Economic Perspectives </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>Simulation of Labor Market with Unemployment Insurance </p>

<p>Barbara R. Bergmann 113 </p>

<p>Table 3 </p>

<p>(Continued) </p>

<p>10.5 percent, malingering does not increase measured unemployment at all. This 
conclusion also holds for much of the recovery period. 
It must be emphasized that this simulation is "theoretical" in the sense that no 
effort has been made to produce a realistic account of job availability, or of 
separations, or of the unemployment insurance system itself. The simulation results 
thus allow only a qualitative conclusion. Nevertheless, they do present a proof that 
lengthened durations of unemployment for unemployment insurance beneficiaries 
need not necessarily translate into an increase in the number of unemployed persons, 
as conventional theoretical analysts of the labor market have claimed. 
The parameter NFAIL, the maximum number of interviews an employer can 
hold in a hiring period, is clearly influential in the numerical result. We could conduct 
a sensitivity analysis by running the model with differing values of NFAIL to gauge its 
effect. Obviously, the larger is the value given to NFAIL, the lower is the effect of 
malingering on the unemployment rate. If NFAIL were infinite-as it implicitly is in 
the program of Table 2-malingering would have no effect on measured unemploy-
ment in all but the tightest labor markets. If this model was fit to actual time series 
macrodata, NFAIL could be one of the parameters whose values were chosen to 
optimize goodness of fit of the unemployment and duration series. Then it might be 
said that we had "estimated" NFAIL empirically. 
The conventional analysis neglects the fact that a malingerer's refusal of a job 
offer makes that job available to a non-malingerer. So an act of malingering does not </p>



<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Unemployment Rates with and without an Unemployment Insurance System, from 
the Simulation Model in Table 3. </p>

<p>necessarily create unemployment beyond what is caused by a shortage of job open-
ings, provided there is a good supply of non-malingerers in the market. </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>The explanation of the different effect of malingering at different unemployment 
levels is readily apparent. 
9 The number of non-malingerers available to take jobs </p>

<p>differs, depending on the degree of slack in the labor market. The addition of a line in 
the program (not shown) allows a survey of the proportion of non-malingerers among 
the unemployed. In the tighter labor market periods, only about 22 percent of the 
unemployed were willing to take jobs. In the slack period, 60 percent of a much larger 
pool of unemployed are willing. 
The slacker the labor market, the larger will be the number of people who have 
been out of a job for long enough to have exhausted their unemployment insurance 
benefits (or be close to having done so), and who would welcome a job. In slack 
markets, malingering merely changes the order in which unemployed people reenter 
employment. It has the effect of reserving whatever job openings there are for those 
who have been out of work the longest. It promotes uniformity of experience among </p>

<p>8 Clark and Summers (1982) and Topel (1985) did run simulations of the Orcutt type, using the work 
history records of actual individuals derived from a survey. Estimates based on regressions were made of 
what the behavior of each individual would have been in the absence of unemployment insurance. 
However, their simulations look at individuals and their unemployment spells one at a time, and neglect the 
way one worker's actions affect another's opportunities. 
9 Hamermesh (1977) and Clark and Summers (1982) speculated that the state of the labor market would 
affect the extent to which unemployment insurance raised the level of unemployment, and suggested that 
high unemployment leads to a low impact of unemployment insurance. The simulation study presented 
here can be thought of as a systematic exploration of this hypothesis. </p>

<p>Micro-to-Macro Simulation 115 </p>

<p>the unemployed. Malingering reduces the right-hand tail of the distribution of 
durations of unfinished spells. 
Of course, a malingerer, a person not actively seeking work, should not be 
counted unemployed according to the official definition of that term, but should be 
labelled as out of the labor force. Since many of the out-of-work people counted as 
unemployed in the simulation are malingerers, the "true" unemployment rate is much 
lower than the measured rate throughout the period. However, if unemployment 
insurance were abolished, and malingering on this account ended, measured employ-
ment would change only by the amounts shown in Figure 2. </p>

<p>Final Comments </p>

<p>The focus of the simulation presented here is not, "How will utility maximizing 
individuals behave?" Rather, I have specified a particular behavioral pattern for the 
actors and asked, "What will the mechanical result of their interactions be?" Even 
though the actors are not depicted as fervid optimizers, the simulation does shed light 
on the pattern of spell durations over the cycle and on the effect of unemployment 
insurance on unemployment rates, which were goals of the analysis. 
Of course, one could construct a model in which the simulated actors behaved 
with greater rationality. For example, one might try to depict them optimizing the 
degree of their malingering. They might be shown calculating, as the expiration date 
of their unemployment insurance benefits grows nearer, the probability that the 
failure to accept an offer now will lead to a period of unemployment without benefits 
later. The analyst might assume that a mathematical derivation of the optimal 
malingering rule is within the workers' capabilities. Unfortunately, it is not within the 
present author's. 
But it is unlikely that a simulation model with actors more inclined toward 
finding and following optimal rules of behavior would give answers that differ 
qualitatively from those given by this model. The nonoptimizing actors of this model 
were servicable for the analysis we aimed at. The reader should remember, moreover, 
that the simulation model with nonoptimizing actors provided better insights about 
how unemployment is generated than the conventional models depicting allegedly 
optimizing actors. </p>

<p>• Much of the work underlying this paper was done while I was a member of the Department of 
Economics of the University of Maryland at College Park, where I was immeasurably helped by 
generous access to computers of all kinds. </p>





</text></tei>