<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fj.1467-8381.2009.02008.x" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>By assessing the sustainability of regional trade agreements (RTAs) for East 
Asia, we quantitatively evaluate the likely impact of proposed East Asian RTA 
strategies on the East Asian economies and the world economy with respect to 
consumption, production, volume of trade and terms of trade effects by applying 
a multi-country and multi-sector computable general equilibrium model. These 
strategies include: (i) the ASEAN Free Trade Area (AFTA: a being-left-alone 
strategy); (ii) an ASEAN Hub RTA (a hub-and-spoke type of overlapping RTA 
strategy); (iii) the AFTA versus a China-Japan-Korea RTA (a duplicating or 
competing RTA strategy); and (iv) an ASEAN+3 RTA (an expansionary RTA 
strategy). We find that an expansionary ASEAN+3 RTA could be a sustainable 
policy option because the members' gains would be significantly positive, with 
more equitably distributed gains between members than when using other 
strategies. The effect on world welfare would also be positive and the negative 
effect on nonmembers would not be very strong. More interestingly, if the East 
Asian countries cooperate with Pacific Basin countries to form an APEC-level 
RTA, such as a free trade area of the Asia-Pacific, the extension of the regional 
trade bloc might be considered a more desirable policy option than the proposed 
East Asian RTAs for East Asian economies, even though countries excluded from 
the free trade area of the Asia Pacific are worse off. </p>

<p>East Asia has been making very rapid progress in market-driven regionalization. </p>

<p>1,2   Since the financial crisis occurred in 1997, East Asia's effort to achieve regional 
economic cooperation has been very aggressive, resulting in a proliferation of </p>

<p>* Park: Division of International Studies, Korea University, Anam-Dong, Seongbuk-Gu, Seoul 
136-701, Korea. Email: iwpark@korea.ac.kr. The author is grateful to David Greenaway, Richard 
Pomfret, Suthiphand Chirathivat, Josef Yap, seminar participants at the University of Nottingham, 
Kuala Lumpur Campus and the 4th Conference of East Asian Institutes Forum organized by the 
Korea Institute for International Economic Policy, and an anonymous referee for helpful comments 
and suggestions. This research was supported by the research fund of the Center for International 
Commerce and Finance in Graduate School of International Studies at Seoul National University, 
Seoul, Korea. </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>

<p>170 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>regionalism in East Asia. In particular, negotiating regional trade agreements 
(RTAs), mostly the result of the formation of bilateral free trade areas (FTAs) 
like Singapore-Korea and Japan-Malaysia FTA, and some plurilateral or 
multilateral FTAs like ASEAN-China and ASEAN-Korea FTA, is now common-
place in the region. Accordingly, several studies have dealt with East Asian 
regionalism, focusing on why it is proliferating, what the likely impact of East 
Asian RTAs will be, and whether East Asian RTAs can lead the world economy 
to global free trade or not. 
3 However, they do not ask whether the existing or 
proposed East Asian RTAs will be viable in the long run. In other words, none 
of the existing studies quantitatively analyze whether the RTAs for East Asia 
are sustainable in a globalizing world. 
An effective RTA should create a significant enough positive welfare effect 
on all the participating member countries and should result in equitably distributed 
gains from free trade between members. 
4 Next, what is the sufficient condition 
for sustainability? An RTA should create enough static and dynamic effects 
on world welfare to ensure nondiscriminatory global free trade, as Bhagwati  (1993) indicates. Otherwise, the RTA will easily stall and be ineffective as time 
passes. Last but not least, an RTA will be more sustainable if it does not 
seriously damage nonmembers. </p>

<p>5   Even though most existing studies have not considered the sustainability of 
RTA, there are some exceptions. The global welfare gains from East Asian 
RTAs are tested by Lee and Shin (2006), using a gravity regression analysis, 
and by Park (2006), who applies a computable general equilibrium (CGE) 
model analysis for East Asian economies as a whole. However, these studies do 
not evaluate the welfare effects on individual economies in East Asia or the 
possible welfare improvements through equitable distribution of the gains 
between participants as a result of RTA. Our work, that is, evaluating whether 
particular East Asian RTAs are sustainable, is an attempt to fill this gap by 
quantitatively evaluating the likely impact of possible East Asian RTAs. 
Each of the East Asian countries may consider the following four different 
RTA strategies: (i) no further effort to liberalize the regional market and then </p>

<p>1. In this paper, we narrowly define East Asia by including ASEAN 10 countries in Southeast 
Asia and China, Japan and Korea in Northeast Asia. In addition, we treat the ASEAN 10 countries 
as a single economy. Therefore, there exist 4 individual East Asian economies in this paper; namely, 
the ASEAN+3, which includes ASEAN, China, Japan and Korea. 
2. For market-driven regionalization, see Urata (2006). For more recent overviews of East Asian 
regionalism, see ADB (2008) and Kawai and Wignaraja (2008). 
3. For proliferating RTAs in East Asia, see JETRO (2003), Lu (2003), Kawai (2004), Feridhanu- setyawan (2005) and Lee and Park (2005). 
4. Theoretically, Kemp and Wan (1976) prove the possibility of Pareto-improving customs unions 
if there is a system of internal transfer of gains from free trade only between members, along with 
a common external tariff scheme. 
5. As point out by the referee, the seriousness of the damage, that is, the significance of the negative effect 
on nonmembers, is a matter of subjective judgment. We clarify the significance (X) as follows: strongly (or 
significantly) negative if X &lt; − 1%, negative if − 1% ≤ X &lt; − 0.1% and insignificant if − 0.1% ≤ X &lt; 0%. </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>the existing ASEAN Free Trade Agreement (AFTA) will be activated in the 
region (being-left-alone strategy); (ii) the ASEAN+1 approach will likely build 
an ASEAN Hub RTA web, including an ASEAN+China, an ASEAN+Japan and 
an ASEAN+Korea FTA (hub-and-spoke type of overlapping RTA strategy); </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>(iii) the Northeast Asian three countries will form their own separate RTA 
competing against ASEAN, that is, the AFTA versus a China-Japan-Korea FTA 
(duplicating or competing RTA strategy); 
7 and (iv) ASEAN, as a whole, and the 
three Northeast Asian countries cooperate with each other to form an East 
Asian FTA, that is, ASEAN+3 RTA (expansionary RTA strategy). </p>

<p>8   In terms of our evaluation of the sustainability of East Asian RTAs, what is 
the most desirable RTA strategy among the four policy alternatives? To answer 
this, we should consider the interests of all the parties involved, individually 
and altogether. In this paper, we describe our quantitative examination of the 
sustainability of proposed East Asian RTAs with respect to the abovementioned 
three conditions: (i) country-specific gains; (ii) distribution of gains between 
members; and (iii) global welfare gains. More specifically, we quantitatively 
evaluate the likely effect of the proposed strategies on the East Asian economies 
with respect to the equivalent variation of welfare, real GDP, exports, imports 
and income terms of trade by applying a multi-country and a multi-sector CGE 
model. 
9 The CGE model analysis has the advantage of measuring the welfare 
effect directly and of comparing the possible outcomes of different scenarios 
while maintaining logical consistency even though the complicated ex-ante 
simulation methodology sometimes misspecifies the model economy. 
The present paper is organized as follows. Section II provides a brief discussion of 
the main characteristics of East Asian RTAs and of the debated issues regarding 
proliferating RTAs in East Asia. Section III introduces the CGE model adopted, 
the data used, and some ex-ante scenarios. Section IV quantitatively measures the 
effects of the proposed East Asian RTA strategies and evaluates the sustainability 
of the RTAs. Section V presents concluding remarks with policy implications. </p>

<p>II. Regional Trade Agreements in East Asia </p>

<p>II.1 Main characteristics of East Asian regional trade agreements </p>

<p>Both intra-regional and inter-regional trade agreements are proliferating in 
East Asia, as shown in Table 1. As briefly described in Park and Park (2008), </p>

<p>6. For the general concept of the hub-and-spoke RTA, see Lloyd (2002), Umemoto (2003) and 
Baldwin (2004). 
7. If there is a first mover advantage, as suggested in Freund (2000), forming a new RTA will be 
preferable to joining an existing RTA. 
8. See Baldwin (1993) for the domino effect of regionalism. 
9. For East Asian RTAs with CGE models, see McKibbin (1998), Scollay and Gilbert (2001), 
Urata and Kiyota (2003), McKibbin et al. (2004), Sulamaa and Widgrén (2005), Zhai (2006), Park  (2006), Kawai and Wignaraja (2007, 2008) and Lee and van der Mensbrugghe (2007). </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Table 1 Major regional trade agreements including countries in East Asia as of September 2008 </p>

<p>Implemented (year into force) 
Signed (year of signing) 
Under negotiation 
Under consideration </p>



<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Plurilateral and intra-regional 
AFTA (1992) 
ASEAN-Japan (2008) 
ASEAN-India 
ASEAN+3 (or +6) 
ASEAN-China (2005) 
China-GCC 
ASEAN-Taiwan 
ASEAN-Korea (2007) 
Japan-GCC 
China-Japan-Korea 
Singapore-GCC 
Plurilateral and inter-regional 
Korea-EFTA (2006) 
ASEAN-CER 
ASEAN-EFTA 
Singapore-EFTA (2003) 
Korea-EU 
ASEAN-EU 
ASEAN-US 
Korea-MERCOSUR 
Singapore-EU 
Thailand-EFTA </p>

<p>Notes: AFTA, ASEAN Free Trade Area; ASEAN+3 (or +6), ASEAN plus China, Japan and Korea (or India, Australia and New Zealand); CER, Closer 
Economic Relations between Australia and New Zealand; EFTA, European Free Trade Association; GCC, Gulf Cooperation Council; MERCUSOR, 
Southern Common Market. 
Source: Park and Park (2008). </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>

<p>174 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>the RTAs that include countries in East Asia have some distinguishing 
characteristics. 
First, the trend of reducing or eliminating trade barriers between members 
is relatively new in East Asia. Most of the East Asian countries, especially 
countries in Northeast Asia, have been well-known to prefer nondiscriminatory 
multilateral liberalization efforts rather than discriminatory regional liberalization 
policies. However, after realizing the importance of regional economic cooperation 
as a result of the East Asian financial crisis in 1997, East Asian countries have 
changed their policy stance from favoring a global approach to favoring a 
regional approach. As in Table 1, among the 34 RTAs implemented or signed 
that include East Asian countries, 33 RTAs were implemented after the crisis. 
Only the AFTA was established prior to the crisis. Second, most of RTAs in East 
Asia have taken a form of bilateral negotiation similar to the worldwide trend of 
seeking a lower and easier negotiation cost even though the gains from freer 
trade are limited. Third, there has been no distinction between intra-regional 
and inter-regional partnerships. Recent innovations in information and com-
munication technology have resulted in significantly reduced transaction costs 
and have made geographical distance relatively less important. Pre-RTA 
economic interdependence has been important in the consideration of the right 
partners to approach for the formation of RTA. Fourth, with respect to the 
partnership issue of RTA, most East Asian RTAs have taken the form of hub-
and-spoke overlapping RTA, which could cause a 'spaghetti bowl' phenomenon. </p>

<p>10   In particular, ASEAN, Singapore and Thailand have been very aggressive in 
pursuing leading roles in the formation of RTA. Fifth, there has been very slow 
progress in the expansionary path of RTA, which could trigger a domino effect 
of regionalism. </p>

<p>II.2 Why are regional trade agreements proliferating in East Asia? </p>

<p>Recognizing the necessity for regional economic cooperation for regional economic 
stability and revitalization of the regional economic dynamism post-East Asian 
financial crisis could be one of the most important market-driving forces in 
East Asia. The intra-regional trade share in ASEAN+3 has been steadily rising, 
increasing from 29. 4 percent in 1990, to 37.3 percent in 2000, 38.9 percent in  2005, and 38.3 percent in 2006.   11   Furthermore, the strong incentives for a country to be RTA leaders make 
both individual Southeast Asian countries and ASEAN as a whole aggressively 
seek to initiate multiple negotiations for RTA. At the same time, the fear of 
being left behind in the worldwide movement toward regionalism has made most 
Northeast Asian countries jump on the wagon. </p>

<p>10. See Bhagwati et al. (1998) and Panagariya (1999) for the spaghetti bowl phenomenon caused 
by overlapping RTA. 
11. See table 1 in Kawai (2007). </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Disappointing outcomes after multilateral institutions' efforts for global free 
trade, such as the stalled Doha Development Agenda negotiation under the 
WTO and the sluggish achievement of the Bogor Goals under APEC, have also 
pushed East Asia's pursuit of regional cooperation. Leadership competition 
between China and Japan is an important political factor behind the proliferation 
of East Asian regionalism. </p>

<p>II.3 Whither East Asian regional trade agreements? </p>

<p>Carefully analyzing the recent change in the regional trade pattern of East Asia, Urata  (2006) finds an increasing trend of intra-regional trade, trade in the manufacturing 
sector, vertical intra-industry trade, and trade in manufacturing parts and components 
between countries in East Asia. Considering the recent changes, we may expect that: (i) 
the rising pre-RTA intra-regional trade volume will cause a stronger trade creation effect; 
(ii) the increasing volume of trade in the manufacturing sector will improve economic 
efficiency through the formation of a more competitive regional market environment; 
(iii) the increasing vertical intra-industry trade will result in bigger short-term gains 
from economies of scale; and (iv) the resulting trade in manufacturing parts and 
components that is closely connected to the supply chain and higher productivity 
growth expected from an international division of labor will also enhance economic 
efficiency and bring about greater gains from regional free trade. 
In sum, the expected positive effects of the recent changes in the region will 
create more favorable conditions for the formation of RTAs in East Asia. 
Through estimation using a gravity regression analysis, Lee and Park (2005)  and Lee and Shin (2006) support the facts observed in East Asia. They argue 
that most East Asian RTAs will create more intra-bloc trade, will not divert 
extra-bloc trade, and will lead to global free trade. 
However, there are some important impediments to consider. The currently 
proliferating East Asian RTAs have been initiated mostly by the private sector, 
which is oriented toward profit-seeking, unlike in Europe, where RTAs have 
generally been formed based on political and ideological harmonization. This 
makes the formation of an institutional framework for regional integration difficult 
in East Asia. In addition, the hub-and-spoke type of many overlapping RTAs in 
East Asia could result in the spaghetti bowl phenomenon of discriminatory trade 
blocs, which have the potential to inhibit global free trade. 
Park (2006) and Lee and van der Mensbrugghe (2007) quantitatively evaluate 
the effects of some proposed East Asian RTAs by applying a static and a 
dynamic CGE model analysis, respectively. Their findings strongly support the 
ASEAN+3 RTA as the best policy strategy for East Asian countries to take. In 
particular, Park (2006) proposes that East Asian RTAs should take expansionary 
paths to establish global free trade rather than competing to achieve the first 
mover advantage. Baldwin (2004) and Zhai (2006) also highlight the negative 
welfare effect expected from overlapping RTAs in East Asia. Kawai (2007) and 
Kawai and Wignaraja (2007) suggest that either an ASEAN+3 (the East Asian </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Summit countries) or an ASEAN+6 (including Australia, New Zealand and 
India) FTA would be economically desirable in East Asia and would maximize 
the positive gains from trade liberalization and minimize the negative 'noodle 
bowl' effects of regionalism. </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>III. Computable General Equilibrium Model </p>

<p>III.1 Model and data </p>

<p>What will be the effect of the proposed East Asian RTAs on each of the East 
Asian countries considered in this paper: China, Japan, Korea and the ASEAN 
nations? Are there any sustainable RTAs? The answers to these questions can be 
found by assessing the macroeconomic aggregate effects of the proposed East 
Asian RTA strategies by applying a traditional static CGE model simulation 
technique. We have adopted a trade-linked multi-sector and multi-country CGE 
model to measure the impact of East Asian regional economic integration 
efforts on welfare, real GDP, exports and income terms of trade. We have 
carefully selected those four aggregate variables to measure the effectiveness of 
proposed strategies according to type of RTA for each economy considered. The 
equivalent variations in welfare have been selected mainly for the consumption 
effect. Real GDP is used for the production effect. Exports have been chosen 
for the volume of trade effect. Income terms of trade are another important 
measure of welfare change. 
13 In addition, to support our findings, we report the 
effect on imports and bilateral trade patterns. 
The CGE model we describe in this section is the <rs id="software-1" type="software">GTAP6inGAMS</rs> model 
developed by <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Rutherford</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">2005</rs>). 
14 The model has three economic agents: 
producers, representative consumers (private and public) and trading partners. 
The <rs type="software">GTAP6inGAMS</rs> model is a traditional static Arrow-Debreu general 
equilibrium model in which the zero profit condition and market clearance 
define the equilibrium. The <rs type="software">GTAP6inGAMS</rs> is a modified version of the GTAP 
model version 6 developed for GAMS users. Most of the model specifications 
are the same as the <rs type="software">GTAP</rs> model. The differences between the <rs type="software">GTAP</rs> model 
and <rs type="software">GAMS</rs> version of the model are as follows. First, the <rs type="software">GTAP</rs> model is based 
on a constant difference elasticity demand system, but the <rs type="software">GAMS</rs> model uses 
Cobb-Douglas preferences. Second, the <rs type="software">GTAP</rs> model assumes that global 
capital is endogenously allocated by regional rates of return. However, for </p>

<p>12. They, however, propose to achieve the bigger trade blocs by utilizing ASEAN as the hub for the 
integration (e.g. the three sets of ASEAN+1 FTA), which is not desirable based on the empirical analysis 
in the present paper. 
13. An income terms of a trade measure, the purchasing power of exports in terms of imports (the 
ratio of the value of exports to the price of imports), can be a better measure of income or welfare 
effect of price changes in international trade, especially for developing countries, relative to the net 
barter terms of trade. See Chacholiades (1990, pp. 136-7). 
14. The explanation of the CGE model used in this paper is derived from Park (2006). </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>simplicity, the GTAP6inGAMS model exogenously fixes the global capital 
flows. The model described in the present paper uses a classification consisting 
of 7 sectors and 25 economies, as in Park (2006). 
15 The model solution has 
been calibrated, with 2001 as the base year, using global trade, assistance and 
production data from the <rs id="software-19" type="software">GTAP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-19" type="version">6</rs> Database. 
16 The model has been implemented 
using the <rs type="software">GAMS MPSGE</rs>. 
17 The <rs type="software">GTAP6inGAMS</rs> model is adopted because the 
CGE model is in line with the commonly used GTAP model and the solver, 
<rs type="software">GAMS MPSGE</rs>, is simple and easy to handle. </p>

<p>III.2 Scenarios </p>

<p>As indicated by Lee et al. (2008) and Park (2006), the proliferating RTAs in 
East Asia will take any of the three paths: expansionary RTAs, where the 
membership of existing RTAs increase by attracting new members; duplicating 
(or competing) RTAs, where separate RTAs are created between nonmembers 
of existing RTAs and compete with existing RTAs; and overlapping RTAs, 
where some members are focusing on being RTA hubs, by forming multiple 
memberships with countries in the region. 
More specifically, the existing AFTA could be successfully expanded to a 
bigger trade bloc, such as an ASEAN+3 RTA. That is, ASEAN, as a whole, 
and the three Northeast Asian countries could cooperate with each other to 
form an East Asian FTA. In contrast to the optimistic cooperation scheme 
in East Asia, some RTAs looking for the first mover advantage, such as those 
between China, Japan and Korea, will be formed in the near future, and will 
compete with existing RTAs such as the AFTA. However, considering the recent 
regional economic environment in East Asia, the ASEAN+1 approach will 
build an ASEAN Hub RTA web in East Asia, including an ASEAN+China, 
an ASEAN+Japan, and an ASEAN+Korea RTA separately, which will have 
overlapped membership. 
To quantitatively measure the impacts of the proposed East Asian RTAs on 
welfare, output production and trade flows for each of the participating 
countries, members as a whole, nonmembers and the world economy, we 
empirically designed and tested four scenarios. For each of the scenarios, both 
import tariffs and export taxes between members were eliminated, but the trade </p>

<p>15. The seven sectors are: agricultural products, food products, extractive industry, light 
manufacturing, heavy manufacturing, technology-intensive manufacturing, and services. The 27 
economies are: Indonesia, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore, Thailand, Vietnam, the rest of Southeast 
Asia, China, Japan, Korea, Hong Kong, Taiwan, Australia, Brazil, Canada, Chile, India, Mexico, 
New Zealand, Peru, Russia, the USA, the European Free Trade Association, the Western European 
countries, and the rest of the world. 
16. The <rs id="software-20" type="software">GTAP</rs> <rs corresp="#software-20" type="version">6</rs> Database is a global database representing the world economy for a given reference 
year (2001). For more detailed information, see Dimaranan (2006). 
17. <rs id="software-17" type="software">MPSGE</rs> (Mathematical Programming System for General Equilibrium analysis) is a subsystem 
within <rs type="software">GAMS</rs>. See <rs corresp="#software-17" type="url">http://www.gams.com/solvers/mpsge/index.htm</rs>. </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>barriers between members and nonmembers were retained. 
18 The scenarios we 
have examined are: </p>

<p>• AFTA: An FTA among the ASEAN countries as a reference (the being-left-alone 
RTA strategy) 
• ASEAN Hub: Three separate FTAs, including an ASEAN-China, an 
ASEAN-Japan and an ASEAN-Korea FTA, assuming that the AFTA is effective 
(the hub-and-spoke type of overlapping RTA strategy) 
• AFTA versus [China-Japan-Korea]: Two separate FTAs including the AFTA and 
a China-Japan-Korea FTA (the duplicating or competing RTA strategy) 
• [ASEAN+3]: An FTA among ASEAN, China, Japan, and Korea (the expansionary 
RTA strategy). </p>

<p>For the base solution of the model economy, we ran the CGE model without 
changing its initial condition and derived general equilibrium values for each of 
the economies in the model. Next, we reestimated the model under different 
scenarios and recalculated the equilibrium values for each case. Then, we com-
pared the different equilibrium values with the initial base solution in terms of 
percentage deviation from the base to evaluate the experimental impacts of each 
scenario on each country. </p>

<p>19 </p>

<p>IV. Sustainable Regional Trade Agreements in East Asia: 
Scenario Analysis </p>

<p>IV. 1 Sustainable regional trade agreements in East Asia </p>

<p>Table 2 provides a comparative summary of regional economic effects of the 
proposed East Asian RTAs by type of RTA. The aggregate effect of the currently 
effective AFTA had no significant negative effects on the discriminatory 
liberalization of the Northeast Asian neighbors, but produced significant enough 
positive gains to ASEAN members. However, if ASEAN members decide to 
pursue the ASEAN Hub scenario, which includes three sets of ASEAN+1 FTA, 
it could raise ASEAN's gains from free trade. ASEAN's welfare and GDP gains 
could be raised to more than three times that of the AFTA. The negative effects 
on excluded neighbors could be problematic, although the neighboring countries </p>

<p>18. The trade barriers include both tariff and non-tariff barriers. For import tariffs, trade-weighted 
ad valorem tariffs include tariff rate quotas and the ad valorem equivalents of specific tariffs. The 
export taxes cover ordinary export subsidies, export tax equivalents of Agreement on Textiles and 
Clothing quotas, price undertakings and voluntary export restraints. The protection rates in service 
sectors are assumed to be zero in the <rs id="software-21" type="software">GTAP</rs> Database. For more detailed information, visit <rs corresp="#software-21" type="url">https:// www.gtap.agecon.purdue.edu/databases/v6/v6_doco.asp</rs>. 
19. As the referee indicated, the base year for existing RTA, such as the ASEAN-China FTA, should be 
2004 or 2005 (right before the year into force in Table 1). However, similar to other hypothetical 
scenarios in the present paper, the complete elimination of trade barriers between ASEAN and 
China are assumed and simulated. Of course, we acknowledge this data problem as a limitation. </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Table 2 Effects of the proposed East Asian RTAs on the participating economies (percentage deviation from the base) </p>

<p>Existing RTA 
Welfare 
(EV) </p>

<p>Real 
GDP </p>

<p>Exports 
Imports 
Income terms 
of trade </p>

<p>Bilateral trade </p>

<p>ASEAN 
China 
Japan 
Korea 
World </p>

<p>AFTA 
ASEAN 
1.06 
1.45 
2.22 
2.90 
4.30 
23.01 
− 4.34 
− 2.86 
− 3.66 
0.15 
China 
− 0.06 
− 0.07 
− 0.08 
− 0.19 
− 0.04 
− 4.34 
0.26 
0.28 
− 0.13 
Japan 
− 0.02 
− 0.05 
− 0.13 
− 0.21 
− 0.18 
− 2.86 
0.26 
0.30 
− 0.17 
Korea 
− 0.06 
− 0.08 
− 0.13 
− 0.18 
− 0.14 
− 3.66 
0.28 
0.30 
− 0.15 
World 
0.28 
0.02 
0.09 
0.09 
0.15 
− 0.13 
− 0.17 
− 0.15 
0.08 </p>

<p>Overlapping RTA 
(hub and spoke) </p>

<p>Welfare 
(EV) </p>

<p>Real 
GDP </p>

<p>Exports 
Imports 
Income terms 
of trade </p>

<p>Bilateral trade </p>

<p>ASEAN 
China 
Japan 
Korea 
World </p>

<p>ASEAN Hub 
ASEAN 
3.77 
4.78 
2.59 
5.22 
4.21 
16.32 
51.02 
2.13 
4.53 
2.33 
China 
− 0.58 
− 0.19 
3.23 
3.21 
5.16 
51.02 
− 2.49 
− 4.79 
3.22 
Japan 
− 0.09 
− 0.24 
0.49 
0.02 
1.48 
2.13 
− 2.49 
0.27 
0.27 
Korea 
−0.33 
−0.30 
0.23 
−0.12 
0.91 
4.53 
−4.79 
0.27 
0.07 
World 
0.98 
0.06 
0.29 
0.29 
2.33 
3.22 
0.27 
0.07 
0.24 </p>

<p>Duplicating 
(competing) RTA </p>

<p>Welfare 
(EV) </p>

<p>Real 
GDP </p>

<p>Exports 
Imports 
Income Terms 
of Trade </p>

<p>Bilateral Trade </p>

<p>ASEAN 
China 
Japan 
Korea 
World </p>

<p>AFTA versus 
China-Japan-Korea </p>

<p>ASEAN 
0.38 
0.89 
2.03 
2.34 
4.02 
25.02 
−14.35 
−6.13 
−11.05 
−0.48 
China 
−0.10 
2.29 
10.49 
14.24 
15.86 
−14.35 
58.03 
104.06 
12.04 
Japan 
0.31 
1.58 
4.40 
6.95 
6.63 
−6.13 
58.03 
32.53 
5.58 
Korea 
4.88 
3.24 
12.13 
12.12 
15.07 
−11.05 
104.06 
32.53 
12.13 
World 
0.21 
0.33 
1.16 
1.16 
−0.48 
12.04 
5.58 
12.13 
0.95 </p>

<p>Notes: AFTA, ASEAN Free Trade Area; EV, equivalent variation; RTA, regional trade agreements. </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Table 2 (continued) </p>

<p>Expansionary RTA 
Welfare (EV) 
Real GDP 
Exports 
Imports 
Income terms 
of trade </p>

<p>Bilateral trade </p>

<p>ASEAN 
China 
Japan 
Korea 
World </p>

<p>ASEAN+3 
ASEAN 
2.69 
3.77 
2.28 
4.25 
3.89 
19.02 
33.19 
−1.51 
−3.27 
1.33 
China 
-0.34 
2.17 
13.07 
16.86 
20.44 
33.19 
53.14 
96.68 
14.64 
Japan 
0.25 
1.32 
4.77 
6.87 
8.08 
−1.51 
53.14 
31.29 
5.74 
Korea 
4.57 
2.86 
12.13 
11.87 
15.73 
−3.27 
96.68 
31.29 
12.01 
World 
0.82 
0.36 
1.30 
1.30 
1.33 
14.64 
5.74 
12.01 
1.07 </p>

<p>Global RTA 
Welfare (EV) 
Real GDP 
Exports 
Imports 
Income terms 
of trade </p>

<p>Bilateral trade </p>

<p>ASEAN 
China 
Japan 
Korea 
World </p>

<p>FTAAP 
ASEAN 
2.28 
4.59 
5.19 
6.67 
10.26 
5.24 
41.19 
9.87 
9.68 
5.93 
China 
0.69 
5.49 
21.01 
28.65 
32.23 
41.19 
36.48 
77.21 
24.16 
Japan 
0.54 
2.29 
8.04 
11.08 
13.86 
9.87 
36.48 
19.90 
9.44 
Korea 
5.10 
4.50 
13.45 
14.39 
18.11 
9.68 
77.21 
19.90 
13.89 
World 
1.06 
0.78 
3.01 
3.01 
5.93 
24.16 
9.44 
13.89 
2.53 </p>

<p>Notes: The income terms of trade measures the purchasing power of exports in terms of imports. See footnote 13. AFTA, ASEAN Free Trade Area; EV, 
equivalent variation; RTA, regional trade agreements; FTAAP, free trade area of Asia Pacific. </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>could increase their exports because of the income effect from the additional 
GDP gains of ASEAN, with the increase in bilateral trade volume between 
ASEAN and each of the three Northeast Asian countries. 
In terms of the negative effects that could be expected from AFTA or the 
ASEAN Hub scenario, the Northeast Asian neighbors might decide to form 
their own regional protection strategy against ASEAN by developing a China-
Japan-Korea FTA. The trade warfare between the two regions could be harmful 
to the less-developed ASEAN economy and would enormously benefit the 
Northeast Asian countries, especially the smallest country, like Korea. However, 
this duplicating RTA competition might not be beneficial to the world economy. 
It will cause much lower welfare gains to the world economy than those with 
the existing AFTA and ASEAN Hub scenario. 
However, if the neighboring countries in both Southeast and Northeast Asia 
cooperate with each other to form an East Asian trade bloc, the ASEAN+3 
FTA, all the participating countries would benefit, although there would be a 
negative welfare effect on China. The negative welfare effect of all the four 
proposed East Asian RTAs on China is a very interesting result which is also 
highlighted by Zhai (2006). It can be explained by the heavy and increasing 
intra-regional dependence of imported parts and components to China as a world 
factory. In addition, East Asian RTAs reallocate resources from the manufacturing 
industry to the agricultural industry within China and it may deteriorate 
economic efficiency of the Chinese manufacturing sector resulting in the 
deterioration of welfare as Zhai (2006) mentioned. 
In terms of the trade effect including volumes measured by the growth of 
exports and imports, the income terms of trade, and bilateral trade relations, all 
the proposed East Asian RTAs have a positive effect on participating countries 
and the world economy as a whole. 
Figures 1, 2 and 3 compare the relative size (percentage deviation from the 
base) of the ex-ante simulation analysis figured in Table 2 by type of RTA 
(AFTA, ASEAN Hub, AFTA versus China, Japan and Korea, and ASEAN+3), 
by economy (ASEAN, China, Japan, Korea), and by measure (equivalent variation 
of welfare, real GDP, exports, and income terms of trade), respectively. More 
specifically, Figure 1 compares the aggregate effects of the four proposed East 
Asian RTAs on the four regional economies in terms of the four measures. The 
Figure 1 illustrates which economy is the biggest gainer from each different 
type of RTA. The ASEAN gains the most from the existing AFTA and an 
ASEAN Hub scenario. This finding explains why most of the nonmembers of 
RTAs fear being left alone. This fear motivates nonmembers to jump on the 
RTA band wagon. This finding explains why countries are competing to be a 
hub and making a very complicated overlapping RTA map. There is no distin-
guishing difference in the effects of an AFTA between nonmembers of the RTA 
but the effects of an ASEAN Hub RTA will cause a relatively better effect on 
China. The competing Northeast Asian RTA and the expansionary East Asian 
RTA will distribute relatively more favorable gains to Korea and China when </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 1 Aggregate effects of East Asian regional trade agreements by type of regional 
trade agreement (% deviation from the base) </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>

<p>183 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 1 (continued) </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>

<p>184 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 2 Aggregate effects of East Asian regional trade agreements by economy 
(% deviation from the base) </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>

<p>185 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 2 (continued) </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>

<p>186 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Aggregate effects of East Asian regional trade agreements by measure 
(% deviation from the base) </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>

<p>187 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Figure 3 (continued) </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>

<p>188 </p>

<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>we measure the size of the rectangles. The ASEAN will benefit least of the 
competing and expansionary RTA strategies. 
Figure 2 illustrates Table 2 by highlighting which scenario is the best for each 
of the economies in East Asia in terms of the four measures. For the sake of the 
ASEAN, the ASEAN Hub RTA is the best and competing with the Northeast 
Asian neighbors is the worst scenario. For the three Northeast Asian countries, 
the ASEAN+3 RTA will be the most desirable RTA but it is not much better 
than the Northeast Asian RTA between the three countries competing against 
the AFTA. Both the AFTA and ASEAN Hub RTA will be the worst scenarios 
for the countries in Northeast Asia. 
Figure 3 illustrates the effect of the East Asian RTAs on the four measures 
representing each country's gains from free trade. In terms of the welfare effect, 
there is no Pareto-improving RTA among the four different scenarios possible 
in East Asia. Reallocating resources from an existing AFTA to any alternative 
trade bloc may hurt at least one economy in the region. It is mainly because of 
the strong substitution effect cased by the change in relative prices, especially 
large country like China. The case of income terms of trade shows the same 
pattern. However, in terms of the real GDP reflecting the strong income or 
growth effect relative to the substitution effect, the expansionary ASEAN+3 
RTA can be a sustainable scenario where the shift from the AFTA to the bigger 
trade bloc can make all the participating economies better off. For export 
promotion raising trade volume, both the ASEAN Hub and the ASEAN+3 RTA 
can be counted as sustainable RTA strategies. 
More interestingly, if we expand the regional liberalization effort toward a 
global level including the Pacific Basin partners, that is, a Free Trade Area of the 
Asia-Pacific (FTAAP), the APEC RTA can be a more desirable policy to proposed 
East Asian RTAs for East Asian economies, especially considering the positive 
welfare gains to China. 
20 However, the desirable APEC FTA for the East Asian 
economies has proven to be less attractive for the global economy than the ASEAN+3 
FTA when we consider countries excluded from the FTA as shown in Table 3. 
Even though the positive effects on the world economy including both members 
and nonmembers are estimated to be higher than those of the proposed East 
Asian RTA strategies, the negative effects on nonmembers are much stronger. </p>

<p>IV.2 East Asian regional trade agreements in a globalizing world </p>

<p>Will the proposed East Asian RTAs be beneficial to the members as a whole and 
the world economy? If not, the proposed East Asian RTAs may not be effective 
and sustainable. As presented in Table 3, all the proposed East Asian RTAs raise </p>

<p>20. Our findings fit very well with some of the rules of thumb in Harrison et al. (2003). They 
argue that: (i) countries excluded from Preferential Trade Arrangement almost always lose; and (ii) 
that multilateral trade liberalization results in significantly larger gains to the world than exist with 
the current network of regional arrangements. </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. 
Table 3 Effects of the proposed East Asian regional trade agreements on regional and global economies (percentage deviation from the base) </p>

<p>Existing RTA 
Welfare (EV) 
Real GDP 
Exports 
Imports 
Bilateral trade </p>

<p>Members (ASEAN) 
Nonmembers 
World </p>

<p>AFTA 
Members (ASEAN) 
1.06 
1.45 
2.22 
2.90 
23.01 
−2.84 
0.15 
Nonmembers 
−0.03 
−0.01 
−0.05 
−0.06 
−2.84 
0.07 
−0.15 
World 
0.28 
0.02 
0.09 
0.09 
0.15 
−0.15 
0.08 </p>

<p>Overlapping RTA 
(hub and spoke) </p>

<p>Welfare (EV) 
Real GDP 
Exports 
Imports 
Bilateral trade </p>

<p>Members 
ASEAN 
CJK 
Nonmembers 
World </p>

<p>ASEAN Hub 
Members 
2.54 
0.30 
1.81 
2.33 
10.31 
15.55 
6.56 
−1.50 
1.90 
ASEAN 
3.77 
4.78 
2.59 
5.22 
15.55 
16.32 
15.24 
−6.39 
2.33 
CJK 
−0.33 
−0.23 
1.47 
1.05 
6.56 
15.24 
−2.36 
0.18 
1.72 
Nonmembers 
−0.06 
−0.00 
−0.12 
−0.13 
−1.50 
−6.39 
0.18 
0.09 
−0.24 
World 
0.98 
0.06 
0.29 
0.29 
1.90 
2.33 
1.72 
−0.24 
0.24 </p>

<p>Duplicating 
(competing) RTA </p>

<p>Welfare (EV) 
Real GDP 
Exports 
Imports 
Bilateral trade </p>

<p>Members 
ASEAN 
CJK 
Nonmembers 
World </p>

<p>AFTA versus 
China-Japan-Korea </p>

<p>Members 
0.78 
1.76 
6.23 
7.89 
15.54 
0.86 
26.04 
−3.80 
1.77 
ASEAN 
0.38 
0.89 
2.03 
2.34 
0.86 
25.02 
−9.08 
−1.35 
−0.48 
CJK 
1.70 
1.87 
8.02 
10.33 
26.04 
−9.08 
62.15 
−4.64 
2.75 
Nonmembers 
−0.16 
−0.02 
−0.22 
−0.24 
−3.80 
−1.35 
−4.64 
0.34 
−0.52 
World 
0.21 
0.33 
1.16 
1.16 
1.77 
−0.48 
2.75 
−0.52 
0.95 </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>Expansionary RTA 
Welfare (EV) 
Real 
GDP </p>

<p>Exports 
Imports 
Bilateral trade </p>

<p>Members 
ASEAN 
CJK 
Nonmembers 
World </p>

<p>ASEAN+3 
Members 
2.33 
1.86 
7.10 
9.01 
23.12 
10.66 
32.04 
−4.50 
3.46 
ASEAN 
2.69 
3.77 
2.28 
4.25 
10.66 
19.02 
7.22 
−4.81 
1.33 
CJK 
1.50 
1.63 
9.16 
11.11 
32.04 
7.22 
57.56 
−4.39 
4.38 
Nonmembers 
−0.18 
−0.01 
−0.28 
−0.31 
−4.50 
−4.81 
−4.39 
0.38 
−0.64 
World 
0.82 
0.36 
1.30 
1.30 
3.46 
1.33 
4.38 
−0.64 
1.07 </p>

<p>Global RTA 
Welfare (EV) 
Real 
GDP </p>

<p>Exports 
Imports 
Bilateral Trade </p>

<p>Members 
Nonmembers 
World </p>

<p>FTAAP 
Members 
1.47 
1.32 
7.16 
7.14 
14.25 
−3.94 
4.59 
Nonmembers 
−0.24 
−0.14 
−0.65 
−0.65 
−3.94 
0.79 
−0.64 
World 
1.11 
0.78 
3.05 
3.06 
4.59 
−0.64 
2.53 </p>

<p>Notes: In order to calculate the percentage deviations of members, nonmembers, and world as a group, each individual country's (see footnote 15 in page 9) 
deviations are measured and added for the corresponding group. AFTA, ASEAN Free Trade Area; CJK, China, Japan and Korea; RTA, regional trade 
agreements; FTAAP, free trade area of Asia-Pacific. </p>

<p>Table 3 (continued) </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>world welfare between a minimum of 0.21 percent in the case of the competing 
RTAs, including the AFTA and the China-Japan-Korea RTA, and a maximum of 
0.98 percent in the case of the ASEAN Hub RTA. The GDP gains range from 
0.02 percent for the AFTA to 0.36 percent for the ASEAN+3 RTA. The world 
trade volume also rises. The expansionary ASEAN+3 RTA can be evaluated 
as the best strategy for maximizing world output and trade. For the members' 
welfare, real GDP, and trade as in Table 3, the expansionary ASEAN+3 RTA is 
also the best strategy for East Asian participants in terms of creating bigger 
gains in many aspects and more evenly distributed gains between the Southeast 
and Northeast Asian members. 
In summary, considering the effects of the ASEAN+3 RTA on members, 
nonmembers, and the world economy relative to other alternative strategies, the 
expansionary East Asian RTA-ASEAN+3 FTA-can be effective and sustainable 
because the effect on members is significantly positive enough and more equitably 
distributed, the effects on the world welfare is positive enough, and the negative 
effect on nonmembers is not very strong. In particular, the ASEAN+3 FTA 
improves members' real GDP by 1.86 percent and hurts nonmembers' real GDP 
by -0.01 (-0.01358) percent compared to 1.45 percent and -0.01 (-0.01389) 
percent, respectively, in the case of AFTA. </p>

<p>V. Concluding Remarks </p>

<p>In our analysis of effective and sustainable RTAs in East Asia, we quantitatively 
evaluated the likely effect of the proposed RTA strategies on East Asian economies 
with respect to the equivalent variation of welfare, real GDP, exports, imports 
and income terms of trade by applying a multi-country and multi-sector CGE 
model: (i) the AFTA (the being-left-alone strategy); (ii) an ASEAN Hub RTA 
(the hub-and-spoke type of overlapping RTA strategy); (iii) the AFTA versus a 
China-Japan-Korea RTA (the duplicating or competing RTA strategy); and (iv) an 
ASEAN+3 RTA (the expansionary RTA strategy). 
From the ex-ante simulation analysis testing for the sustainability of the 
proposed East Asian RTAs, and as reflected in Table 4, we found that both the 
duplicating and expansionary RTA strategies of forming the Northeast Asian 
RTA separately from the existing AFTA and the ASEAN+3 RTA, respectively, 
were desirable for both the East Asian economies and the world economy. Even 
though the ASEAN Hub strategy appears to be a better policy option for ASEAN 
and the world economy, it is not necessarily a desirable strategy for the neighboring 
countries in Northeast Asia. 
We also found that there was no Pareto-improving RTA among the four different 
scenarios possible in East Asia because reallocating resources from an existing 
AFTA to any alternative trade bloc would hurt at least one member economy in 
the region. This is mainly because of the strong substitution effect caused by the 
change in relative prices, particularly in a large country like China. However, in terms 
of the production effect and trade volume effect, the expansionary ASEAN+3 </p>

<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. 
Table 4 The sustainability test for regional trade agreements in East Asia </p>

<p>Conditions for the sustainability test 
AFTA 
ASEAN Hub 
AFTA versus China-Japan-Korea 
ASEAN+3 </p>

<p>Individual 
member 
economy </p>

<p>ASEAN 
Consumption (EV of welfare) 
+ 
++ 
+ 
++ 
Production (real GDP) 
+ 
+++ 
+ 
++ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
++ 
+++ 
++ 
++ 
Terms of trade (income TOT) 
+++ 
+++ 
+++ 
++ 
China 
Consumption (EV of welfare) 
-
-
-
Production (real GDP) 
-
++ 
++ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
++ 
+++ 
+++ 
Terms of trade (income TOT) 
+++ 
+++ 
+++ 
Japan 
Consumption (EV of welfare) 
* 
+ 
+ 
Production (real GDP) 
-
+ 
+ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
+ 
+++ 
+++ 
Terms of trade (income TOT) 
+ 
+++ 
+++ 
Korea 
Consumption (EV of welfare) 
-
+++ 
+++ 
Production (real GDP) 
-
++ 
++ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
* 
+++ 
+++ 
Terms of trade (income TOT) 
+ 
+++ 
+++ 
Members on 
average </p>

<p>Consumption (EV of welfare) 
+ 
++ 
+ 
++ 
Production (real GDP) 
+ 
+ 
++ 
++ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
++ 
++ 
+++ 
+++ 
Nonmembers 
on average </p>

<p>Consumption (EV of welfare) 
* 
* 
-
-
Production (real GDP) 
* 
* 
-
-
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
* 
-
-
-
World economy 
on average </p>

<p>Consumption (EV of welfare) 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Production (real GDP) 
* 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Volume of trade (exports and imports) 
* 
+ 
+ 
+ 
Distribution of gains 
Overall evaluation between members 
NE 
NE 
E </p>

<p>Notes: + (positive), ++ (significantly positive), +++ (strongly positive), * (insignificant), -(negative) where 0.1% ≤ + &lt; 2%; 2% ≤ ++ &lt; 4%; 4% ≤ +++; 
-0.1% &lt; * &lt; 0.1%; −1% ≤ − ≤ −0.1%. E, equitably distributed; NE, not equitably distributed. </p>

<p>SUSTAINABILITY OF REGIONAL TRADE AGREEMENTS </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>

<p>RTA could be a sustainable scenario: the evolution from AFTA to the bigger trade 
bloc could make all the participants better off. Furthermore, when we evaluated 
the effects of the ASEAN+3 RTA on members, nonmembers, and the world economy 
relative to other alternative strategies, we found that the expansionary East Asian 
RTA would be more desirable than other strategies because the members gains 
would be significantly positive and more equitably distributed between members. 
The effects on world welfare are also positive, and the effect on nonmembers is not 
strongly negative. Moreover, we found that moving from a regional RTA to a global 
level RTA such as an FTAAP could be a desirable policy for the East Asian 
countries, even though countries excluded from the RTA are worse off. </p>



<p>ASIAN ECONOMIC JOURNAL </p>



<p>© 2009 The Author 
Journal compilation © 2009 East Asian Economic Association and Blackwell Publishing Ltd. </p>



</text></tei>