<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.1111%2Fjors.12246" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>180 </p>

<p>Review by Tomaz Dentinho. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
Immigration, Poverty, and Socioeconomic Inequality, edited by David Card and 
Steven Raphael. Review by Jamie Goodwin-White . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>182 </p>

<p>New Developments in Spatial Economics and Economic Geography, edited by 
Philip McCann. Review by Julie Le Gallo . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . </p>

<p>184 </p>

<p>Geocomputation: A Practical Primer, edited by Chris Brunson and Alex Singleton. 2015. 
London: Sage Publication Ltd. 369+xx. ISBN: 9781446272930. $52.00. </p>

<p>Geocomputation: A Practical Primer is a timely book whose content will appear obvious in 
a few years time but would have probably seemed unusual, to say the least, just a few years 
ago. Its publication coincides with many substantial changes and shifts occurring in the world of 
computation, science, and geographic data. Although those are subjects for a different discussion, 
a few examples will help contextualize the moment in which this book has come about. Computing 
has been moving away from the desktop for a few years now: lighter, everyday tasks are pushed into 
ever smaller devices (tablets, smartphones, wearables, etc.), while more heavy-duty jobs are reserved 
for servers, data-warehouses, or somewhere else, all of it blurred through the convenience of the 
cloud. At the same time, the scientific endeavor is experiencing a crisis of public trust and reliability 
and more open and reproducible approaches are being proposed as the best way to keep science 
credible and useful for society (Peng, 2011). The data deluge produced by the digital era we live in is 
shifting the interest from classical statistical methods designed for "reliable little data" to machine 
learning and pattern recognition techniques created for "messy big data." Closer to the discipline 
of geography, there is a strong push to take cartography from static publication-ready formats onto 
the web, opening the door for engaging interactive features and much richer presentations. How 
these and other changes will affect geocomputation is unclear. Some will probably pass and soon be 
forgotten, while some others will foreseeably remain with us and, in the process, redefine the way 
we understand the discipline. With such uncertainty ahead, the temptation to write a "classical" 
book, one that relies on the topics, methods, and approaches we have "known and loved" for decades, 
is very strong. Fortunately, that was not the route chosen by Brunsdon and Singleton. 
Instead, the editors took a braver approach by reconciling some of the classical themes in 
the field that will arguably remain relevant in the future (as they represent the core upon which 
much of the new approaches build), and blending them with more recent approaches that only 
few would have seen coming just a few years ago. The book is structured around four blocks of 
three to four chapters each, revolving around common broad topics but mixing more theoretical 
approaches with eminently practical articles. The first part, "Describing how the world looks," 
considers geocomputational approaches to representing the world, from the very microlevel, such as 
the one on 3D geosimulation (Torrens, chapter 2), to very macrolevel views on rank size and power 
laws (Batty, chapter 3). "Exploring movements in space," part 2, considers several approaches to 
the blending of space and time, as well as dynamic modeling. Topics like the combination of agent-
based modeling and Geographic Information Science (GIS) (Crooks, chapter 4), or microsimulation </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. 
DOI: 10.1111/jors.12244 </p>



<p>BOOK REVIEWS </p>



<p>(Harland and Birkin, chapter 5), find their place in this part of the book, but so do more general 
overviews about circular statistics (Rohde and Corcoran, chapter 7) or storage, management, and 
analysis of large space-time datasets (Miller, chapter 6). In part 3, "Making geographical decisions," 
the editors have compiled a set of geocomputational techniques used in real-world applications 
to solve specific problems. This comprises geodemographics (Alexiou and Singleton, chapter 8), 
self-organizing maps (Spielman and Folch, chapter 9), kernel densities (Lewis, chapter 10), and 
location-allocation models (Tomintz, Clarke, Alfadhi, chapter 11). These are usually illustrated with 
a practical application, rather than merely described in abstract terms, which makes the reading 
much more intuitive and serves as a good starter for the nonexperienced reader interested in 
discovering the "big picture" of the techniques. 
The fourth block of the volume, "Explaining how the world works," delves into confirmatory ap-
proaches that seek to provide insight into underlying social or natural processes. Two good examples 
are chapter 12 on Geographically Weighted GLMs (Nakaya) and chapter 13 on spatial interaction 
models (Morrisey). The final section, "Enabling interactions," covers several examples of new av-
enues for geocomputation that would have not normally been part of a more traditional book. Topics 
such as the use of crowd-sourced datasets (Brunsdon and Comber, chapter 16) or public participation 
through GIS (Kingston, chapter 18) can be found here. 
In addition to these thematic blocks, a most welcome feature of the book is the series of 
chapters intelligently inserted in each block that cover aspects of geocomputation referring to tools 
and software. In particular, it is refreshing to see how all of these relate to open-source projects freely 
available to use. The landscape where the only choices to perform geocomputational analyses were 
proprietary, desktop, point-and-click, GIS programs, or custom routines in low-level languages such 
as C or <rs type="software">FORTRAN</rs> is no longer the norm. Instead, an entire ecosystem of open-source software, more 
flexible than traditional desktop GIS and more accessible than low-level computer programming 
has emerged. Just a few years ago, it was not very clear that one day it would be possible to carry 
out serious research in geocomputation using only free and/or open-source software. That the field 
has evolved in this direction to a point where there is a full stock of tools (Rey, 2009) that realize 
such a vision is greatly inspiring and it is something that the larger community of researchers who 
have made it possible should feel proud of. The book contains an overview of open-source software 
for GIS (O'Brien, chapter 17), and two other chapters are devoted to the most common programming 
languages used in geocomputation, R (Cheshire and Lovelace, chapter 1) and <rs type="software">Python</rs> (Rey, chapter 
14). An additional chapter (15) by Brunsdon and Singleton elaborates on the idea of reproducibility, 
describing the concept, why it should be adopted, and how it can be realistically implemented. 
This bit echoes a larger debate that relates to the very core of what Science is about and how to 
keep it serving society in the 21st century, and its inclusion in the book is a reassuring sign of the 
forward-looking attitude of the editors. 
There is much to like in this book. For a domain so wide, diverse, and eclectic as geocomputation, 
the selection of topics does a remarkable job of capturing some key themes, applications, and domains 
where geocomputational approaches are used and useful. This is further enhanced by the fact that 
the text lives up to the "practical" in its title: instead of delving into the thorough math underlying 
many of these techniques, each chapter presents the intuition and application, making it a very 
suitable companion for a graduate seminar in social sciences (e.g., economics or sociology), or for 
researchers from different disciplines with an interest in what geocomputation has to offer to them. 
Part of this success in meeting its own goals is undoubtedly related to the fact that the authors are 
among the key leaders in the field they are writing about, and thus are particularly well placed 
to write introductory texts that get to the essence without much of the underlying math. However, 
this is nicely complemented by a short section at the end of each chapter with a few key references 
for the interested reader to continue learning about the topic. Most of these do include some of the 
equation-heavy books and articles required to master these techniques, making the book a perfect 
introduction-a primer after all-with a clear path forward for the interested minds. 
At a more global level, the book recognizes and embraces many of the "big picture" shifts 
occurring in the field and accommodates them throughout the book. In addition to the already 
mentioned new approaches to geocomputational software and tools, there is an explicit recognition 
that the data landscape is changing and that this will require adaptation to be able to extract 
the most value and knowledge. This is very clear in parts of the book, such as chapter 9 (Miller), </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 56, NO. 1, 2016 </p>

<p>which recognize the need to accommodate and properly represent these new forms of data. But 
it is also more subtly present in the choice of methods reviewed. For example, the inclusion of a 
chapter on self-organizing maps, a machine learning technique to reduce data dimensionality and 
visualize large complex datasets, is very much in that same spirit. Very welcome is also the role 
given by the editors to visualization. One could argue that graphics have always been an essential 
part of GIS and, by extension, geocomputation. However, it is easy to get lost in the complexity and 
computational aspects of some of the methodologies and assume that because the results come from 
very complicated techniques, the presentation of such results is of secondary importance. The book 
takes a clear stance on this and recognizes not only its importance, but its nontriviality, including 
chapters that walk the reader through some of the cutting-edge tools such as R, <rs type="software">Python</rs>, or <rs type="software">JavaScript</rs> 
libraries for the web. 
As much as there is to praise about this edited volume, one can always wish for more. Arguably, 
the following are a reflection of my own interests and preferences, but I do think they would have 
made the book a slightly more complete and consistent one. I have two main remarks: one relating to 
the structure and the other one to the content. I think there could have been a bit more consistency 
in the structure of each chapter. While some chapters are practical applications of a particular 
method, others are a more conceptual overview. To some extent, this is unavoidable in an edited 
volume with so many and varied authors, and some would argue even desirable as it exposes the 
reader to a larger range of approaches and ways of understanding the field, and I agree. However, 
I think a more consistent presentation of different methods provides a better way to introduce the 
unfamiliar reader to a family of new techniques. I would have also enjoyed some discussion of how 
geocomputation does or should engage with the nascent discipline of data science. Data science is in 
some ways a buzz term around which there is much hype and in that sense, it is correct not to give 
it much attention as the risk of the fashion fading soon is too high. However, the strong emphasis 
it places on practical applications and the use of data and quantitative techniques in industry and 
policy warrant some respect. A chapter on how geocomputation fits into the field of data science and 
how this can help make the discipline even more useful and valuable would have been very welcome. 
Geocomputation is a vibrant field that is constantly reimagining and reinventing itself, in-
fluenced by several technological and scientific advances, but also feeding back into those arenas. 
Because of that, the discipline should be of interest not only for experts on these computational 
techniques, but also to a wide variety of students and researchers in the natural and social sciences. 
Particularly for those, the book is an excellent introduction that will provide a good overview of what 
is on offer, and how to make the most of it. </p>

<p>Daniel Arribas-Bel 
Geography and Planning 
University of Liverpool </p>



<p>Accessibility and Spatial Interaction, edited by Ana Condeço-Melhorado, Aura Reggiani, and 
Javier Gutiérrez. 2014. NECTAR Series on Transportation and Communications Networks 
Research. Cheltenham, U.K. and Northampton, Massachusetts: Edward Elgar. 256. ISBN: 
9781782540724. $120.00. </p>

<p>Accessibility and spatial interaction are two core concepts in multiple social science fields, 
including regional science, spatial economics, transportation, geography, and city and regional plan-
ning. Although it is well accepted that these two concepts are interconnected, open questions persist 
on how to use their connections to provide an accurate measurement of one family of indicators (e.g., </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>BOOK REVIEWS </p>



<p>accessibility) through the other one (e.g., spatial interaction) and to better understand the economic 
and social benefits of accessibility improvement. The book edited by Condeço-Melhorado, Reggiani, 
and Gutiérrez attempts to concentrate on these questions by assembling chapters written by leading 
researchers mainly from Europe. 
This book includes three sections. The first section focuses on advanced data and analytical 
methodologies to enhance the measurement of accessibility and spatial interaction.Östh, Reggiani, 
and Galiazzo (chapter 2) articulate the importance of distance-decay functions in computing potential 
accessibility and spatial interaction measured by the magnitude of flows between locations. When ac-
cessibility is not measurable, it can be estimated by spatial interaction models using flow data. They 
further examine which specification of the distance-decay function is least sensitive to the modifiable 
areal unit problem (MAUP) using Swedish data. These aggregate, social-physics-oriented estima-
tions of accessibility are straightforward but somewhat arbitrary. McArthur, Thorsen, and Ubøe's 
research (chapter 3) is economics-oriented, developing a spatial general equilibrium model (SGEM) 
to endogenize the relationship between transportation network, accessibility, and relocations of res-
idents and jobs. This study is particularly useful to understand how a change in transportation 
network (e.g., removing topographical barriers) affects accessibility, how a change in accessibility 
leads to relocations of population and employment, and, in turn, how these relocations alter acces-
sibility. Other advantages of SGEM studies are that they can track the change of accessibility and 
calculate an economically efficient or socially optimal level of accessibility. 
Nicolai and Nagel (chapter 4) present a logsum indicator to compare the spatial distribution 
of accessibility under different spatial resolutions of locations on the flow origin side in Zurich. It 
is somewhat disappointing that the authors coarsely treat the spatial resolution of opportunities 
and overlook an examination of whether the resolutions of opportunities affects the accessibility 
computation. Given the location of an origin, the measure of accessibility could largely depend 
on the resolutions of travel opportunities, rather than the origin. Schintler, Kulkarni, Haynes, 
and Stough (chapter 5) offer an insightful introduction to how to use geosocial data to calculate 
accessibility and develop several social network analysis (SNA) metrics (i.e., degree, betweenness 
centrality, and entropy) to identify the positions (or importance) of locations within the U.S. network 
of counties. They also apply a community detection algorithm to find the "mobility sheds" (p. 107) and 
identify territories with close spatial interaction. While the SNA approach generates an innovative 
understanding of accessibility and spatial interaction, the authors mistakenly regard betweenness 
centrality as accessibility (p. 97). There are particular indicators in SNA that measure accessibility 
or reachability, e.g., closeness centrality. Also, we would expect a more thorough comparison of the 
accessibility computation based on the SNA and traditional approach (e.g., potential accessibility 
indicators). 
The chapters in the second section, "The Social and Spatial Dimension of Accessibility," inves-
tigate the spatial and social factors of the accessibility of locations or population groups. De Montis, 
Caschili, and Trogu (chapter 6) offer a spatial autocorrelation analysis to explore the influence of the 
accessibility attributes of adjacent counties and regional demographics on the accessibility of U.S. 
counties. This spatial analysis demonstrates the importance of spatial dependence in accessibility 
measures but cannot clarify the causality between accessibility and demographics (e.g., whether 
high population densities attract more infrastructure investment, leading to a high level of acces-
sibility, or high accessibility facilitates population clustering). Salas-Olmedo, Condeço-Melhorado, 
and Gutiérrez (chapter 7) measure the border effects on intranational and international interaction 
through manufacturing trade among European nations. They also evaluate how these border ef-
fects vary with the distance metrics employed and affect the computation of accessibility (or market 
potential). Ribeiro, Remoaldo, and Gutiérrez (chapter 8) connect accessibility indexes with transport-
related social exclusion and look at the roles of street slope and walking speed in the accessibility 
computation of elderly people to public transit in the municipality of Braga, Portugal. 
By its title, the third section of the book appears set to proclaim "accessibility as a driver of 
spatial interaction," while all three chapters tackle the influence of accessibility on economic activ-
ities on the production side only. Arbués, Mayor, and Baños (chapter 9) examine the output effects 
of the accessibility of road transportation infrastructure, simply measured by the distance-decay 
sum of the population in all other provinces in Spain. Holl (chapter 10) uses a similar measure of 
accessibility at the municipality level in Spain also and tests its impact on firm-level total factor </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 56, NO. 1, 2016 </p>

<p>productivity. Both chapters rely on panel data models and control for the effects of production exter-
nalities, measured by spillovers to neighboring regions (chapter 9) or agglomeration benefits from 
the denser population (chapter 10). They are solid empirical studies. However, both fail to discuss 
the endogeneity between accessibility and production externalities: that is, how accessibility could 
affect spillovers and agglomeration and indirectly affect productivity. As later noted by Gråsjö and 
Karlsson in the last chapter, the measure of accessibility "incorporates 'global' spillovers and does 
not only account for the impact from neighbors or locations within a certain distance band" (p. 229). 
The latter is often done by spatial dependence models (e.g., the spatial Durbin model in chapter 
9). Thus, accessibility could play a more important role in spatial economics than spatial depen-
dence. By reviewing various empirical studies in Sweden, Gråsjö and Karlsson further encourage a 
more extensive application of the accessibility approach in spatial economics studies, including the 
analysis of knowledge spillovers, spatial variations of productivity and economic growth, new firm 
formation and locational dynamics, exports, and labor mobility. This is a valuable reminder at the 
end of the book that there is a complex interplay between accessibility and spatial economics and 
that the accessibility approach remains overlooked or undervalued in related empirical studies. 
Although the editors believe that what sets this volume apart from other contributions to 
the scholarship of accessibility is its focus on "the link between spatial interaction and accessibility" 
(p. 3), only four chapters directly address this important link in theory or empirics (chapters 1-3 and 
11). These chapters represent the state of the art but meanwhile highlight the complexity of situating 
accessibility within the framework of spatial interaction theory. Much more work is needed to inves-
tigate how accessibility affects the spatial distribution of opportunities and spatial interaction and, 
in turn, how they change accessibility. For empirical studies, a reduced-form estimation probably 
cannot accurately reflect the connection between spatial interaction and accessibility and structural 
models are needed. Many chapters in this book are useful contributions to help develop accurate 
accessibility computations, for example, through the articulation of the influence of the functional 
specification of distance decay, spatial resolutions, topographical and border constraints, and spatial 
dependence. Is it rather disappointing, however, that the measures of accessibility devised in the 
spatial economics contributions presented in Section III are oversimplified. The coarseness of these 
measures of accessibility could lower the credibility of the estimated relationship between accessi-
bility and space economy. Also, this volume would have benefitted from a review (or synthesis) of 
the state of the art in accessibility measurement across different empirical applications either at 
the beginning or at the end of the volume. 
Overall, the book is a welcome addition to the study of accessibility and spatial interaction. It 
will appeal to regional scientists, spatial economists, and transportation engineers who are inter-
ested in the measurement and properties of spatial accessibility and the complex connection between 
accessibility and spatial economics. The book would be a useful text to support graduate courses in 
spatial and transport analysis. </p>

<p>Wenjia Zhang 
Department of Geography and Earth 
Sciences 
University of North Carolina at Charlotte </p>

<p>Jean-Claude Thill 
Department of Geography and Earth 
Sciences 
University of North Carolina at Charlotte </p>

<p>Global Amenity Migration: Transforming Rural Culture Economy and Landscape, edited 
by Laurence A.G. Moss and Romella S. Glorioso. 2014. Kaslo, British Columbia: The New Ecology 
Press. 435. ISBN: 9780993635106. $76.00 </p>

<p>Lawrence Moss and Romella Gloriosa assemble 24 chapters and 42 authors from all the conti-
nents and from a large variety of disciplines to make available utopian emotions, shared intuitions, </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>BOOK REVIEWS </p>



<p>careful witnesses, and prospective reflections on the "colonization of areas by a middle class thirst 
for authenticity"-as amenity migration is named in a quote of Lawrence Moss (p. 83). 
The divide is either "living in the countryside," as the amenity migrants want to do, or "living 
from the countryside" as historical settlers always did, to serve themselves and outsiders, with their 
resources, tools, deeds, and beliefs, and also to migrate when the competitiveness of their services to 
outsiders changed due to outside causes. This idea of competing and schizophrenic uses of "mother 
land" is also in the book where the difference is highlighted between regions of consumption of 
amenities and regions of production that, jointly with the environment, created and sustained those 
amenities (p. 190). What drives this new colonization movement? Does it create sustainable places? 
What can be done to guarantee such sustainability? Those are the questions addressed by the 
authors in a long, well-structured, and pleasant to read piece of work. 
Utopian emotions are implicit in all the text and that is probably what makes the reading so 
interesting. The dedication to the son of the editors, Cézanne, and his generation, is revealing, partly 
because the painter Cézanne showed how the beauty of the landscape is in the eyes of the painter, 
and in those who love paintings. Actually, amenity is often taken as beauty (p. 86), but beauty is 
not necessarily related to good or even to just. Does the landscape and those who created it have 
a say? Are these locals the creators and the artists? Or are the outsiders that worship and desire 
the amenities? Is there space for both through Catholic Sunday masses as it is described in the 
book (p. 92)? Emotive utopians do not seem to care: they reject what was created in the urban fast 
food culture of workaholic consumers and assume that by slowing down the complex relationships 
between nature and the self, and between the self and the society, it is possible to create a better 
world (p. 94). 
Shared Intuitions based on particular cases rather than on sound-generalized evidence from 
reality is mostly what we can get on amenity migration from this nice book. It is said that amenity 
migration refers to movements of people from urban areas to rural areas in search of environmental 
and cultural amenities (p. 67). Nevertheless, the instinct also suggests that it is a process associated 
with rural gentrification, stimulating the creation of nonshared visions of the same world (p. 75) and 
distinct ontological universes in the same territory (p. 88). In some cases, peripheral regions can be 
seen just as specialized residential areas (p. 102) designing inequalities with former settlers while, 
typically, aiming at a democracy of people living in real places (p. 119). 
Careful Witnesses provide some proof that goes further than the shared intuitions. What makes 
the argument resistant is the ability of the opinions to fit with common sense related with sources 
of income, land ownership, and political participation. Regarding the source of income, it is said 
that the lack of employment in amenity areas has been a problem for those who do not bring other 
sources of income with them (p. 53); actually, amenity migrants, besides including wealthy and often 
seasonal migrants (p. 260), also comprise poor people living on minimal income schemes attracted 
by lower costs of housing in the countryside and with marginal small activities in agriculture and 
tourism (p. 209). Concerning land ownership, the argument is that rich people from outside buy land 
as consumption and make land unproductive for traditional uses while changing the local multiplier 
effects of the land value. All this can be done without any restriction to avoid that process (p. 59) 
and this is strongly associated with the gradual disappearance of small ethnic communities, long 
protected or disguised in regions close to remote national borders (p. 241). Finally, vis-à-vis political 
participation, there is some evidence that although collaborative management is becoming easier 
through the use of digital technologies (p. 173), seasonal amenity migrants usually do not attend 
public meetings and do not volunteer for collective works (p. 151) while generating high hidden costs 
because developing land as properties fragments the ecosystems and creates pressure to protect 
those fragments from wild fires at the expense of others (p. 177). 
What about prospective thinking? There is not much on that. Mainly worries and divided 
hearts. Where is rationality when most of the exposition is related to emotions, intuitions, and 
partial evidence believable though common sense? Even without reason could we make a divide 
between, on the one hand, the good guys of nomadic, emotional, intuitive and smart authors, and, 
on the other hand, the folkloric settlers? And vice-versa when the supposed good guys are the bad 
ones? Labeling places or people as either rural or urban is not particularly useful (p. 273). In fact, 
there seems to be a flexible cycle of amenity migration-from visitors, to seasonal migrants and 
to long-term outsiders that then can sell their houses or hand them over to relatives (pp. 288 and </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 56, NO. 1, 2016 </p>

<p>373), eventually generating long-term equilibriums between tradition and globalization (p. 306). As 
happens in any migration movement, there are the ones that are engaged with the place and the 
ones that become frustrated and move away (p. 323). In all, amenity migration is both an opportunity 
and a threat to sustain the integrity of natural ecologies and their symbiotic human communities 
(p. 11; p. 361). 
The issue is whether some planning is possible to manage spatially defined environments with 
time-referenced unrooted impacts. Can places be restricted (p. 59)? Do we need to constrain flows 
of amenity migrants with the intervention of the government (p. 339 and p. 354)? Or we just need 
constraints on the resource use that sustains the existing settlers (p. 368) and, at the same time, 
qualify land use planning (p. 403)? The danger, I would say, is to take an ideological and utopian 
attitude that has guided some public interventions in the countryside. 
This book on global amenity migration provides a very useful and nice to read set of texts that 
look at the recurring and reinforcing phenomenon of amenity migration from different disciplinary 
and, sometimes, ideological perspectives and looking at quite a variety of regions around the world. 
Amenity migration is a cysergic event, good and bad at the same time. On the one hand, it inter-
connects people and territories raising the value of both. On the other hand, it can degrade those 
territories with their people because it is based on unrooted and alien cultures that try to "marry" an 
embedded and often fragile ethos. Like any marriage, it can be paradise or hell. And like marriage, 
it only works with respect, trust, humbleness, and proximity-or love, using a less politically correct 
wording. 
In fact, the main problem of the book is that it does not tackle appropriately the two main issues 
that are at stake when nomadic and sedentary attitudes interact with each other. On the one hand, 
the spatial dimensions of families and, on the other hand, the interconnected spatial distribution of 
property rights over localized resources. 
Where are the children that require school services, the elderly that request company and 
health care, and the unemployed that demand space and opportunity? How are land and property 
transmitted from generation to generation and what about the sense of belonging is fructified? It 
seems that the book only talks about new nomadic tribes without family shifting from workaholic 
nightmares to amenity "pastures" around the world while forgetting the ones that sustain those 
intrinsically cultural amenities to produce and host relatives and, why not, all the others that like 
and respect those symbiotic cultural, familiar, creative, environmental, and cysergic landscapes? </p>

<p>Tomaz Dentinho 
Department of Agrarian Sciences 
University of the Azores </p>

<p>Immigration, Poverty, and Socioeconomic Inequality, edited by David Card and Steven 
Raphael. 2013. Series: National Poverty Center Series on Poverty and Public Policy. New York: 
Russell Sage Foundation. 469 + xiv. ISBN: 978-0-87154-498-8, $55. </p>

<p>The contributors to Immigration, Poverty, and Socioeconomic Inequality could hardly be pleased 
with the current tone accorded these topics in the looming presidential election. Editors David Card 
and Steven Raphael (as well as many of their contributors) have long produced critically informed 
research on how and why immigrants impact U.S.-born workers, the significance of demographic and 
economic shifts, and the socioeconomic trajectories of immigrants over time and across generations. 
Much of this compilation is more of the same, modeling a rigorously objective, question-led approach 
to a contentious field, while demonstrating the abundance of ways issues are framed and debated. In 
addition, the volume provides a timely focus on varying and changing state policies on immigration 
and welfare, and relatedly on the lives of young immigrants and members of the second generation. 
Attention to these authors' concerted efforts to answer urgent questions with innovative thoughtful 
approaches would significantly improve public discourse. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>BOOK REVIEWS </p>



<p>Card and Raphael's substantial introduction has numerous detailed summary tables illuminat-
ing questions from policy and academic circles as well as the data and measurements used to answer 
them. It is useful on its own merits to any reader seeking a comprehensive introduction to these 
issues. The book is then divided into four parts, with chapters coming from a well-assembled team 
of economists, sociologists, geographers, and education and public policy researchers. The authors' 
understanding of each other's contributions both within and outside of this volume yields analytical 
dividends beyond disciplinary divides. 
The first part focuses on immigrants in the labor force and the geography of immigrant poverty. 
Giovanni Peri and Ethan Lewis employ counterfactual simulations to formalize and test arguments 
of immigrant-native worker substitutability. Peri finds that new low-skilled immigrants diminish 
the wages of older less-skilled immigrants and Lewis finds similar effects operating through English 
language skills-but crucially neither finds negative effects for native-born workers. In a volume 
where geography provides analytical grounding in terms of comparing and disaggregating composi-
tion and policy effects across scales, the next two chapters are the most explicit about places. After 
finding that places with high levels of racial (black/white) segregation are also places of high immi-
grant segregation with native-born whites, Michael Stoll's intervening variable approach suggests a 
causal relationship between segregation and English language ability. Mark Ellis, Richard Wright, 
and Matthew Townley's chapter enquires about the changing relationships between immigrant 
poverty and changing locations. Their decomposition analysis shows immigrant poverty increased 
as the most disadvantaged immigrants sorted into lower waged cities pressed into higher poverty 
by the Great Recession. These authors are all able to test causal hypotheses through experimental 
models that formally specify relationships and disaggregate groups, places, and time periods. 
The second part of the book concentrates on the socioeconomic progress of immigrants and their 
children, both across generations and over time. These three studies all focus on Los Angeles, with 
the first two utilizing the very relevant Immigration and Intergenerational Mobility in Metropolitan 
Los Angeles (IIMMLA) data. Renee Reichl Luthra and Roger Waldinger analyze group-variant inter-
cepts and slopes of parent-child education and occupation as the interplay of origin country selection 
of parents and second-generation outcomes. In contrast to conventional upward or downward as-
similation accounts, they emphasize significant intergenerational mobility of the second-generation 
overall, but also posit alternatives such as the "working class incorporation" (p. 201) of children of 
less educated Mexicans. The other chapters provide in-depth ethnographic investigation of different 
second-generation outcomes. Lee and Zhou explore the "frames of achievement" (p. 215) that condi-
tion 1.5/second-generation Asian success but are largely absent for 1.5/second-generation Mexicans. 
In a frame that affects some of Lee and Zhou's participants, Gonzales' study of young Mexican-origin 
adults illuminates the obstacles of undocumented status and how they unfold over a critical period 
for intergenerational mobility and adult outcomes. These authors stress the significance of parental 
resources and social and educational context for the large cohort of young adult and nearly adult 
children of immigrants. 
The third part of the volume focuses on how public policy-from immigration enforcement to 
employment and welfare restrictions-affects immigrant poverty. Douglas Massey's comprehensive 
historical analysis catalogues modern immigration policy and its racialized stigmatizing practice 
toward Mexicans and Mexican Americans. This provides an excellent set text for those unfamiliar 
with how Mexicans became so different from other immigrant groups but also sets the stage for anal-
ysis of contemporary policy shifts. Marianne Bitler and Hilary Hoynes similarly conduct a thorough 
analysis of how the status quo of relatively poorer immigrant households and children emerged from 
two decades' worth of increasing limitations on immigrants' access to social welfare. Sara Bohn and 
Magnus Lofstrum's synthetic comparison examines the probable effects of Arizona's recent Legal 
Arizona Workers Act (LAWA), finding that it drove undocumented workers toward informal employ-
ment or out of Arizona, but failed to benefit legal immigrants or native-born workers. Cybelle Fox, 
Irene Bloemraad, and Christel Kesler test immigrant explanations (disenfranchisement, perceived 
group threat, and diversity) for reduced state welfare provision, but find only that states with larger 
black (and to a lesser extent, larger Asian and Hispanic) populations have less redistribution. With 
rapidly shifting state and federal policies, the context within which immigrants and others experi-
ence poverty or social mobility, these authors investigate the origins of the current system and its 
ongoing emergence. </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 56, NO. 1, 2016 </p>

<p>The final section is a single chapter in which Christian Dustmann and Tommaso Frattini crit-
ically detail the European experience with immigration and its differences from the U.S. experience 
in terms of history, source countries, migrant stocks, and education and labor market outcomes. It 
is useful in that much theory in this field has been framed from North America with overwhelming 
reference to its post-1965 shift in source countries. In standing alone this chapter begs for another 
European chapter or two on immigration and inequality, and is a reminder of the rarity of compar-
ative work in this field (despite increasingly ever-present political contestation of immigration and 
austerity on both sides of the Atlantic). 
Some of the chapters could be better edited so that intensive data analysis does not threaten to 
subsume key findings. But this is a minor quibble for, overall, the tables excellently demonstrate the 
numerous relationships that condition hypotheses and their testing in this enormous and seismic 
field. The second-generation accounts could come from somewhere else as well as Los Angeles 
(even Europe), but they serve to illustrate theoretical differences in expectations, as well as the 
very different experiences by origin group. This 469-page volume is already a massive contribution. 
Challenging model approaches and findings are detailed in footnotes for specialists or skeptics, but 
explained in more comprehensible language for a wider public in the text. The multidisciplinary 
array of researchers is carefully modest, often asserting the limitations of their own approach 
while detailing it so carefully as to encourage scrutiny, critical attention to questions, concepts, and 
data, and further research. The writing is often exceptional, and the significance of the issues both 
theoretical and political made clear. Immigration, Poverty, and Socioeconomic Inequality should be of 
interest to any researcher working in the area. It deserves careful reading from any of us evaluating 
these issues, whether at work or at the ballot box. </p>

<p>Jamie Goodwin-White 
Department of Geography and California 
Center for Population Research 
University of California, Los Angeles </p>

<p>New Developments in Spatial Economics and Economic Geography, edited by Philip Mc-
Cann. 2013. Series: The International Library of Critical Writings in Economics. Cheltenham, 
U.K. and Northampton, Massachusetts: Edward Elgar. 514 + xiii. ISBN: 978-1-84844-432-4, 
$252 </p>

<p>Edited by Philip McCann, this book is part of the collection "International Library of Critical 
Writings in Economics" published by Edward Elgar. It contains a selection of research articles with 
the aim of highlighting the major features and breakthroughs of spatial economics and economic 
geography for the last two decades. Twenty-four papers, ranging from 1997 to 2011, are organized 
within four sections of six papers each. The sections are entitled: "Knowledge, Innovation and 
Geography," "Cities and Clustering," "Labour and Markets," and "Empirics." A short introduction 
by McCann sets the tone of the volume: its purpose is to provide a sense of all the developments of 
the field, with its "foundations and framework for understanding where the field is currently going, 
what the key questions and challenges being addressed are, and what the current consensus and 
disagreements are" (p. xii). However, with a field as broad as this, some choices had to be made as 
to the topics chosen for the sections of the volume with a focus on innovation (part 1), cities (part 2) 
and land markets (part 3), and methods (part 4). 
The fundamental role played by geographical proximity in knowledge flows and innovation 
activities is investigated in the first part of the volume. Anselin, Varga, and Acs (chapter 1) provide 
evidence of the local geographical extent of spillovers between university research and high tech-
nology innovations, while Carlino, Chatterjee, and Hunt (chapter 3) show that patent intensity is 
positively related to the density of employment. However, as stated by Boschma in chapter 2, geo-
graphical proximity is neither a necessary nor a sufficient condition for learning but can strengthen 
the other dimensions of proximity. The factors behind innovative capacity are investigated in the </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

<p>BOOK REVIEWS </p>



<p>following two chapters, with a comparative analysis between Europe and the United States under-
taken by Crescenzi, Rodríguez-Pose, and Storper (chapter 4) and an assessment of the impact of 
variety by Frenken, Van Oort, and Verburg (chapter 5). Finally, in a somewhat disconnected paper, 
Shearmur and Polèse (chapter 6) focus on the factors explaining local employment growth. Because 
its focus is on agglomeration economies, this chapter would have been more appropriate in part 2. 
The second part of the book deals with cities, systems of cities, and linkages between economic 
activities. In an important contribution, Duranton (chapter 7) proposes a general model that ac-
counts for the rapid location changes of industries across cities and the stability and skewed nature 
of the city size distribution. Specific aspects are then considered. On the one hand, the nature of the 
worldwide urban hierarchy is investigated in Henderson and Wang (chapter 11) with an attention to 
the role of institutions. On the other hand, the determinants of the location of industries and firms 
can be envisaged through the lens of Marshallian externalities. By constructing pairwise agglomera-
tion indices for United States manufacturing industries, Ellison, Glaeser, and Kerr (chapter 8) show 
that all three of Marshall's theories of agglomeration are supported but that input-output linkages 
are particularly important. Industrial clusters stemming as a consequence from agglomeration ex-
ternalities have attracted much attention as they have been seen as the basis for public intervention. 
The concept in itself is, however, ambiguous, as demonstrated by Gordon and McCann (chapter 9) 
and can be related to different models of processes (pure agglomeration, industrial complex, and 
social networks). Moreover, because of their specific properties, Storper and Venables (chapter 12) 
argue that face-to-face contacts should be considered as the most fundamental aspect of proximity. 
Hence, social interactions are facilitated in dense urban areas so that the resurgence of big cities 
is seen by Glaeser and Gootlieb (chapter 10) as resulting from an increased demand from these 
interactions. 
Labor and land markets and their interactions are considered in the third part of the volume. 
This part is relatively heterogeneous with several topics. The issue of migration is investigated 
in three chapters. Faggian and McCann (chapter 13) focus on interregional migration behavior 
of British university graduates and the role played by the labor market characteristics in these 
migrations. Other factors of migration are examined: community satisfaction in Mellander, Florida, 
and Stolarick (chapter 15) and the weather in Rappaport (chapter 17). In these two cases, the link 
with the title of the third part is not obvious. Two other papers focus on housing prices. A theoretical 
model of the growth of housing prices, including the effects of zoning and amenities, is proposed 
by Glaeser, Gyourko, and Saks (chapter 14). The role played by regulation is considered by Quigley 
and Raphael (chapter 16), who compare housing prices between more or less regulated cities and 
estimate the price elasticity of housing supply in regulated and unregulated cities. Finally, Shapiro 
(chapter 18) looks at the relationship between human capital and employment growth. 
The last part, "Empirics," consists of a disparate set of papers. It starts with a methodological 
literature review of applied spatial econometrics by Elhorst (chapter 19). Bel and Fageda (chapter 
20) examine the determinants of the location of large firms' headquarters across European urban 
areas. Because of its topic, it could have been placed in the second part. Fingleton and Fisher (chapter 
21) provide a range of estimations to test the comparative relevance of neoclassical theory and new 
economic geography to explain cross-regional variation in economic regional European development. 
The marginal benefits of public capital are estimated in Haughwout (chapter 22). A meta-analysis 
of urban agglomeration estimates is provided by Melo, Graham, and Noland (chapter 23). Finally, 
Rodrik, Subramanian, and Trebbi (chapter 24) estimate the respective contributions of institutions, 
geography, and trade. Unfortunately, there is no apparent logic in the organization of this part. 
With the explosion of theoretical, analytical, and empirical papers dealing with the spatial 
organization of economic activities, the determinants of location choices and the role played by 
geography in economic development, any volume providing a state of the art of spatial economics 
and economic geography should be a welcome addition. However, precisely because the field is 
large and encompasses many different traditions, it cannot be exhaustive, as acknowledged by 
the editor. The choices of the topics (innovation, cities, land market, and methods) are relevant in 
their own right but not justified with respect to other issues that could have been tackled, such 
as the structure of cities, sociospatial segregation, agglomeration, and regional growth or local 
public economics. Moreover, while it provides a good mix between theoretical and empirical papers, 
the normative dimension of economic geography is relatively absent. Each part is more or less </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>



<p>JOURNAL OF REGIONAL SCIENCE, VOL. 56, NO. 1, 2016 </p>

<p>homogenous but the last part on methods comprises articles without a clear link between them. 
Rather than grouping disparate empirical contributions, it could have been interesting to provide 
here more methodological literature reviews in the spirit of Elhorst. Probably, a less ambitious title 
combined with some thematic narrowing would have been preferable. Despite these limitations, the 
book will be of interest for people wanting to have available a selection of quality research on various 
aspects of spatial economics and economic geography. </p>

<p>Julie Le Gallo 
Université Bourgogne Franche-Comté, 
CESAER 
Agrosup Dijon 
Dijon, France </p>

<p>C 2016 Wiley Periodicals, Inc. </p>

</text></tei>