<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.2307%2F3585311" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>While stock returns in the United States this past century have exceeded 
Treasury returns by an average of about 6% annually, in the last few years 
they have done so by more than 12% annually. Commentators have sug-
gested a variety of explanations for the dramatic stock-market run-up that 
accompanied these high returns. The baby boom is entering peak savings 
years, productivity has escalated worldwide due to technological im-
provements and political change, and stock-market participation rates are 
on the rise. The growth of mutual funds has lowered transaction costs and 
made diversification feasible. Public awareness of the benefits of stock-
market investing is high. On the other hand, irrational exuberance could 
be fueling the price rise, with inexperienced investors expecting double-
digit returns to continue indefinitely or at least long enough to reap a 
substantial gain. 
Whether the price rise is due primarily to fundamentals or whether it 
is the result of a bubble is important to policymakers concerned with 
avoiding the real disruption a sharp stock-market decline could precipi-
tate. It is also important to the academic debate over the determinants of 
stock valuations. Because this paper is about the relations between stock 
prices and fundamentals, we emphasize three broad categories of expla-
nations for the recent price rise: changes in corporate earnings growth, 
changes in consumer preferences, and changes in stock-market participa-
tion patterns. The goal in qualifying the importance of fundamental 
effects is to better understand whether a combination of fundamentals 
and statistical fluctuation can plausibly explain the observed magni-
tudes, or whether a bubble is the likely cause of the price rise. </p>

<p>The paper has benefited from the comments of John Campbell, Annette Vissing-
Jorgensen, and participants of the 1999 NBER Macroeconomics Annual Conference. We 
thank the National Science Foundation for financial support. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Although the paper touches on a variety of issues, its main contribution 
is to look more closely at how participation patterns have changed, and at 
how they are expected to affect required returns in a stochastic equilib-
rium model. We interpret participation broadly to include both the frac-
tion of the population that holds any stocks, and the degree of diversifica-
tion of a typical stockholder. To review the evidence, we use data from the 
Survey of Consumer Finances (SCF) to document changes in stock-
holding patterns and reported attitudes toward risk from 1989 to 1995. 
Consistent with previous studies (e.g., Poterba, 1993; Vissing-Jorgensen, 
1997), we see an increasing rate of stock-market participation over time. 
Participation rates among the wealthy, who own the majority of stock, 
however, have increased only slightly. Foreign participation changes may 
also influence required returns. Using data from the U.S. Treasury, we 
find that net purchases of stocks by foreigners have been relatively high in 
recent years, but small in comparison with total trading volume. Finally, 
flow-of-funds data show that diversification has increased markedly, with 
large outflows of individual stocks from household portfolios moving into 
mutual funds and other institutional accounts. 
To quantify the potential impact of these changes, we calibrate an 
overlapping-generations model that allows for considerable heterogene-
ity in the cross section of nonmarketable income risk, preferences, diversi-
fication, and participation. This extends the analyses of Basak and Cuoco 
(1998), Saito (1995), and Vissing-Jorgensen (1997), all of whom consider 
the effect of participation when traded securities span income realiza-
tions. We use this framework to experiment with changes in stock-market 
participation rates, changes in background risk, changes in preferences, 
and changes in the expected dividend process reflecting changes in diver-
sification. We find that for realistic changes in raw participation rates, 
expected stock returns change very little. Within the range of risk-
aversion parameters normally considered, preference changes also have 
little effect on expected return differentials. Changing the rate of time 
preference has a significant effect on the level of all returns, but not on 
the differential between stock and bond returns. One factor that appears 
to have a significant effect on required returns is the degree of assumed 
diversification. This suggests that one fundamental reason for the stock 
price run-up may be the rapid growth of mutual funds and the accompany-
ing large increase in diversification. 
The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. In Section 2 we 
review the statistical evidence on whether the current stock price level 
is anomalous. In Section 3, we discuss some possible explanations for 
the stock price increase in the context of a simple discounted-cash-flow 
model, and present some evidence from the SCF and other sources on </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
215 </p>

<p>changes in stock-market participation patterns. The influence of partici-
pation rates, extent of diversification, background income risk, and 
preferences on stock prices is examined in Section 4 in an overlapping-
generations model. By considering a variety of scenarios reflecting si-
multaneous changes in several of these factors, we show that changes 
in fundamentals can account for perhaps half of the observed increase 
in price-dividend ratios in the model. Section 5 concludes. </p>

<p>2. Empirical Facts </p>

<p>Historically stocks have returned a substantial premium over bonds. Over 
the period 1871 to 1998, the average annual (log) real return on a broad-
based index of U.S. stocks was 7.3%, compared to an average (log) real 
return on bonds of about 3%.1 The return on stocks over the last few years 
has exceeded this historical average. For example, since 1991, the average 
real return on stocks was 17% per year. This has led many observers to 
question whether expected returns looking forward are lower than they 
have been in the past. 
A related issue is the composition of recent returns, which have been 
mostly the result of capital gains rather than increased dividend pay-
ments. To illustrate this, Figure 1 plots the ratios of prices to dividends 
and prices to earnings for aggregate U.S. stocks. (For the years since 
1926 this is based on the S&amp;P 500 index.) Notice that the price-dividend 
ratio for this index has increased to an unprecedented level since about 
1995. The increase in this ratio is significant because in a discounted-
cash-flow model of stock valuation, it indicates a reduction in the ex-
pected rate of return or an increase in the dividend growth rate (see 
Section 3). Because dividends are discretionary and only one of the ways 
in which corporations distribute cash to shareholders, it may be more 
informative to look at price-earnings ratios. Figure 1 also shows the ratio 
of prices to earnings. This ratio is also at a relatively high level, but the 
change has not been as dramatic as for dividends. 
A notable aspect of the rise in the price-dividend ratio is that there is 
substantial evidence that a large value of the price-dividend ratio pre-
dicts lower stock returns in the future. For example, Table 1 reports the 
results of regressing annual (log) stock returns on a constant and the log 
of the price-dividend ratio lagged one year for the period 1887 to 1998. 
Notice that the coefficient on the dividend-price ratio is negative. This is 
consistent with a large body of evidence (e.g., Campbell and Shiller, 
1988; Hodrick, 1992; Lamont, 1998). At the current high level of the </p>

<p>1. Source: Robert Shiller's data, available at http://www.econ.yale.edu/shiller/chapt26.html. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Figure 1 PRICE-DIVIDEND RATIO AND PRICE-EARNINGS RATIO, 
1871-1998 </p>

<p>Price-Dividend Ratio, _.... Price-Earnings Ratio </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>40 
i </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20". </p>

<p>1 
12 </p>

<p>1860 
1880 
1900 
1920 
1940 
1960 
1980 
2000 </p>

<p>price-dividend ratio, this regression predicts a substantial decline in the 
stock market over the next year. In fact, since 1995 this regression has 
consistently predicted a decline in the stock market. 
On the other hand, due to the substantial variability in stock returns, it 
is possible that the recent returns are within the bounds of normal statis-</p>

<p>Table 1 REGRESSION OF ONE-
YEAR STOCK RETURNS 
ON LAGGED P/D OVER 
THE PERIOD 1871 TO 1998 </p>

<p>Coefficient Estimate Standard Errora </p>

<p>a 
0.28 
0.02 </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>-0.07 
0.05 </p>

<p>logR,+ = a + 
plog(Pt/Dt) 
+ Et. </p>

<p>aCorrected for conditional heteroskedasticity 
and autocorrelation using the procedure of 
Newey and West (1987) and two years of lags. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
217 </p>

<p>tical fluctuations, without any change in the underlying driving pro-
cesses. For example, the standard deviation of the annual premium of 
stock returns over bond returns over the period 1871 to 1998 was 18%. 
Therefore, it is not improbable that one would observe several years of 
premiums in excess of 20% per year, even with no change in the underly-
ing statistical process. Since there is not a statistically definitive answer 
to the question of whether returns have been abnormally high, we focus 
below on whether recent changes in various aspects of the economy are 
large enough to suggest a fundamental change in expected returns. </p>

<p>3. Possible Explanations </p>

<p>In this section, we discuss some of the potential explanations that have 
been offered for the stock price run-up, and begin to evaluate their likely 
quantitative importance in the context of a simple discounted-cash-flow 
model. We also present some evidence on changes in market participa-
tion patterns that may be influencing required returns. </p>

<p>3.1. GORDON GROWTH MODEL </p>

<p>The Gordon growth model is perhaps the simplest fundamentals-based 
approach to predicting stock prices.2 In this model, stock prices are 
based on the discounted present value of future expected dividend pay-
ments. It is assumed that dividends grow, on average, at a constant rate, 
g, and investors discount dividends at a constant rate, r. Dividends, </p>

<p>earnings, and growth are connected by two equations: DIV = (1 -p)E </p>

<p>and g = p(ROE), where DIV is dividends, E is earnings, p is the propor-
tion of earnings reinvested, and ROE is the marginal physical product of 
capital. If the marginal physical product of capital is constant, and if the 
fraction of reinvested earnings is constant, then, all else equal, dividend 
growth is constant. Then the price-dividend ratio equals 1/(r -g). 
The model highlights two of the fundamental reasons that the price-
dividend ratio can change. The first is due to changes in dividend 
growth, reflected in the choice of g. The second is due to changes in 
preferences that affect the subjective rate of time preference or the pre-
mium demanded for risk, reflected in the choice of r. 
Expectations of g may be higher than in the past for several reasons. A 
major determinant of dividend growth is the availability of profitable 
investment projects. The potential for sustained economic growth in 
excess of historical precedent has been attributed to the opening and </p>

<p>2. This valuation model, a staple of market analysts, is described, for instance, in Brealey 
and Myers (1996). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>218 -HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>integration of world markets, continuing technological advances, and an 
increasingly educated labor force. In fact, U.S. per capita GDP growth 
has been slightly higher than average in recent years, averaging 2.3% 
from 1995 to 1998, compared with 2.0% from 1947 to 1998. 
Other considerations suggest that r may be lower than in the past. 
One possibility is that aggregate preferences have changed. Either a 
decrease in risk aversion or an increase in patience could contribute to 
the run-up in stock prices. Risk aversion could vary across generations 
due to their varying experiences and circumstances. For example, baby 
boomers do not share their parents' first-hand experience with the Great 
Depression. Some have argued that the economy is more stable, reduc-
ing the exposure to background risk, and possibly reducing the risk to </p>

<p>dividends. Davis and Willen (1998) show, for example, that the income 
risk for households with various educational attainments has changed </p>

<p>over time. Reduced transaction costs in financial markets make diversifi-
cation easier, which, as discussed below, can reduce effective aversion to 
the risk of holding stocks as people hold more diversified portfolios. 
It should be noted that these types of changes affect the risk-free rate 
as well as the expected return on stocks. Since the risk-free rate has been 
relatively stable over the period of the recent stock price run-up, in much 
of what follows we focus on factors that affect the equity premium, 
rather than the absolute level of rates.3 
The Survey of Consumer Finances (SCF) is one of the few data sources 
that provides some direct survey evidence on peoples' attitude towards 
financial risk and how it has changed over time. Respondents to the SCF 
answer detailed questions, both quantitative and qualitative, about their 
financial situation. The survey is conducted by the Federal Reserve 
Board every three years, with different households in each survey year. 
Here we focus on the question: </p>

<p>Which of the statements on this page comes closest to the amount offinancial risk 
that you (and your husband/wife) are willing to take when you save or make 
investments? If more than one box checked, code smallest category #. </p>

<p>1. take substantial financial risks expected to earn substantial returns 
2. take above average financial risks expecting to earn above average returns 
3. take average financial risks expecting to earn average returns 
4. not willing to take any financial risks </p>

<p>3. See Blanchard (1993) for an analysis of historical trends in the equity premium and risk-
free rate. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? </p>

<p>
Table 2 AVERAGE RESPONSE BY AGE AND SURVEY YEAR TO 
QUESTIONS ABOUT RISK AVERSION FROM THE SCF. </p>

<p>Responsea 
Year 
Age &lt; 35 
35-65 
&gt;65 </p>

<p>1989 
3.14 (0.88) 
3.32 (0.77) 
3.63 (0.61) 
1992 
3.19 (0.84) 
3.26 (0.81) 
3.64 (0.60) 
1995 
3.07 (0.87) 
3.18 (0.82) 
3.58 (0.68) </p>

<p>aImplied population standard deviations in parentheses. </p>

<p>Table 2 reports the average response by age and survey year. The implied 
population standard deviation across responses is reported in parenthe-
ses. Since the population represented by the survey totals approximately 
90 million households, the standard errors of the estimates of the means 
are quite small. Consistent with the idea that risk tolerance has in-
creased, the average reported aversion to risk has decreased slightly for 
each age category over time. Older households own significantly more 
stock than younger households, and reported risk aversion increases 
with age in each survey year. When a similar tabulation (not reported 
here) is done conditional on households that own at least $500 in stocks, 
the same patterns emerge with respect to age and time. The average 
reported level of risk tolerance, however, is higher when we condition on 
stockholders. For instance, in 1995 the average risk attitude for stockhold-
ers over age 65 was 3.17, as compared to 3.58 for all households over 65. 
This suggests that those who already own stocks are more risk-tolerant 
as a group than nonparticipants. Hence, the entry of new stockholders 
may slightly decrease the average level of risk tolerance. One would 
expect this to mitigate the effect of wider participation in reducing the 
equity premium. 
There are objective reasons why the underlying subjective rate of time 
preference also may be changing. Increases in life expectancy beyond 
retirement would likely increase the incentive to save and thereby re-
duce required returns. Mortality, for example, has declined at an average 
annual rate of 3.3% over the period 1900 to 1988 (Social Security Adminis-
tration). Past improvements in health and life expectancy might under-
state expected improvements in these factors that are premised on con-
tinued medical progress.4 As with the other explanations considered for 
the stock price run-up, however, it is hard to point to events that would </p>

<p>4. In fact, there is a lively debate in the demographic literature on these questions, with 
some authors claiming that a life expectancy at birth of 100 years will be realized early in 
the next century. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>trigger a large change in aggregate preferences over the course of only a 
few years. 
Calibrating the Gordon growth model gives a rough sense of how far 
earnings growth rates or stock returns would have to deviate from their 
historical averages to justify current price levels. This approach has the 
advantage that it allows one to avoid taking a definitive stand on the 
magnitude of technology or preference parameter changes. In the tabula-
tions presented here, we focus on earnings-adjusted price-dividend ra-
tios rather than actual price-dividend ratios because earnings are likely to 
be a more stable proxy for long-run payments to shareholders. Consistent 
with the average ratio of dividends to earnings over the period 1947 to 
1997, we assume an average reinvestment rate of 50%. Hence, the ad-</p>

<p>justed price-dividend ratio is defined as twice the price-earnings ratio.5 
Over the past century, real earnings growth has averaged about 1.4% 
annually, with a standard deviation of about 25%. Table 3 shows the 
required growth rate in the future to match current and historical ad-
justed price-dividend ratios, for various levels of required returns. For r 
ranging from 5% to 15%, column 2 reports the growth rate g that is 
consistent with the adjusted price-dividend ratio of 28 for the period 
1872 to 1998. Column 3 reports the growth rate necessary to match the 
adjusted price-dividend ratio of 48 in January 1998 (the ratio in January 
1999 is even higher at 58). For instance, to realize a real stock return of </p>

<p>7% (consistent with a 6% equity premium and a 1% real risk-free rate) 
and to match the average historical adjusted price-dividend ratio of 28 </p>

<p>requires growth of 3.4%. To match the 1998 adjusted price-dividend </p>

<p>ratio of 48, assuming a real risk-free rate of 3% and an equity premium of 
6%, requires perpetual growth of 6.9%. This is a large number by histori-
cal standards, suggesting that, at least in this simple model, a plausible 
increase in the expected long-run growth rate is unlikely to be the sole 
explanation for the increase in stock prices. 
The growth rate and required return enter symmetrically in these 
calculations. Therefore, another interpretation of the results in Table 3 is 
that if growth rates are expected to be similar to historical averages, the 
expected real return on the stock market is now less than 5%. Again 
assuming a risk-free return of 3%, this implies an equity premium below 
2%. This large a change in expected returns also seems unlikely to have 
taken place over the period of only a few years. 
One shortcoming of this model is the restriction that the expected </p>

<p>5. While stock prices depend on the long-run behavior of dividends, properly measured, 
in the short run dividends can vary due to temporary changes in payout policy (for 
instance, in response to changes in the tax law). Therefore, it is common to focus on the 
price-earnings ratio, adjusted for reinvestment rates, to approximate long-run price-
dividend ratios. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals -221 </p>

<p>Table 3 GROWTH RATES IMPLIED BY THE GORDON GROWTH MODEL </p>

<p>Ten-Year g to 
Long-Run g to 
Long-Run g to 
Match 1998 P/E </p>

<p>rs </p>

<p>Match Historical P/E 
Match 1998 P/E 
with 2% Tail </p>

<p>0.05 
0.014 
0.029 
0.064 
0.07 
0.034 
0.049 
0.134 
0.09 
0.054 
0.069 
0.189 
0.11 
0.074 
0.089 
0.236 
0.13 
0.094 
0.109 
0.280 
0.15 
0.114 
0.129 
0.320 </p>

<p>growth rate is constant. This assumption, however, can be relaxed quite 
easily. A minor variation on the model is to assume a higher growth rate 
for some number of years, followed by a return to a lower long-run 
growth rate. Column 4 of Table 3 reports, for each value of r in column 1, 
the growth rate over 10 years necessary to explain the adjusted price-
dividend ratio in January 1998. The calculation assumes that the growth 
rate returns to the long-run average of 2% from year 10 onward. In this 
case achieving a 9% average rate of return requires a growth rate of 
18.9% for ten years! 
Although these calculations are admittedly primitive, more detailed 
analyses along similar lines produce qualitatively similar conclusions. 
For instance, Lee and Swaminathan (1999) estimate the value of individ-
ual stocks in the Dow Jones Industrial Average, projecting cash flows 
using accounting data and analysts' forecasts, and discounting using the 
CAPM. They conclude that the index is about 1.6 times the fundamental 
value predicted by their analysis. 
Despite the apparently large changes in parameters necessary to ex-
plain current price levels, these results do not preclude a fundamentals-
based explanation. It is possible that there have been a simultaneous 
increase in expected growth rates and a reduction in required returns. 
For instance, if the long-run growth rate is realistically expected to be 
about 2.4% and if expected returns fall to about 6.6%, current prices are 
in line with fundamentals. Our focus in the rest of the paper is on 
whether such a change in expected returns can be attributed to measur-
able changes in the economy, in the context of an equilibrium model. 
One factor of particular interest is the change in stock-market participa-
tion patterns, which is the topic of the next subsection. </p>

<p>3.2 STOCK-MARKET PARTICIPATION PATTERNS </p>

<p>It is well documented that a large fraction of the U.S. population holds 
little or no stocks (Bertaut and Haliassos, 1995; Blume and Zeldes, 1993) </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>and that participation varies systematically with factors such as wealth 
and age (Gentry and Hubbard, 1998; King and Leape, 1987). As noted 
in several recent studies (e.g., Basak and Cuoco, 1998; Constantinides, 
Donaldson, and Mehra, 1998; Saito, 1995; Polkovnichencko, 1998; Vis-
sing-Jorgensen, 1997), an increase in the stock-market participation rate 
has, in theory, the potential to decrease the required risk premium on 
stocks because it spreads market risk over a broader population.6 Not 
only has the number of participants been rising, but the nature of 
participation has changed. A typical stockholder today has a more di-
versified portfolio than in the past, presumably due to the lower cost of 
diversification. Thus, the effective risk of the typical portfolio may have 
declined. In this subsection, we review some of the evidence on these 
changes. 
The best source of data on market participation rates in the United 
States is perhaps the SCF, which reports detailed information about 
household wealth composition every three years. Using these data, 
Poterba (1998) reports that in 1995 there were approximately 69.3 million 
shareholders in the United States, compared to 61.4 million in 1992 and 
52.3 million in 1989. There is also evidence that people are entering the 
market at a younger age. Poterba and Samwick (1997) show that baby 
boomers are participating more heavily in the market than previous 
generations at a similar age. Baby boomers are entering peak savings 
years and directing some of their savings into stocks. More generally, the 
aging of the population should result in a greater demand for stocks, 
since older people hold proportionally more of their wealth in the mar-
ket than do younger people (see, e.g., Heaton and Lucas, 1998). Finally, 
foreign participation in the U.S. markets has increased, further spread-
ing the risk across a broader population. 
Market participants are also holding more diversified portfolios, which 
reduces their exposure to risk from their stockholdings. This is potentially 
important, since holders of diversified portfolios may demand a lower 
average return. Historical evidence on this phenomenon of improving 
diversification is summarized in Allen and Gale (1994). Friend and Blume 
(1975) found that a large proportion of investors had only one or two 
stocks in their portfolios and very few had more than ten. At the time, this 
lack of diversification in individual stockholdings could not be justified by 
the claim that these investors achieved diversification through unre-
ported mutual-fund holdings. In fact, King and Leape (1984) found that </p>

<p>6. Bakshi and Chen (1994) note that to the extent that demographic changes have an effect 
on the demand for stocks, they will have a predictable effect on asset prices. Bodie, 
Merton, and Samuelson (1992) provide a theoretical justification for the demand for 
stocks to vary with age. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
223 </p>

<p>only 1% of investors' wealth was in mutual funds at around that time. In 
contrast, Poterba (1998) reports a sharp increase in the proportion of stock 
held in mutual funds over time and a reduction in directly held stocks. For 
instance, while the total number of individuals holding stock increased 
from 61.4 million to 69.3 million from 1992 to 1995, the number of individu-
als holding stock directly fell from 29.2 million to 27.4 million over the 
same period. In the calibrations presented below, we will look at whether 
this diversification effect is significant by comparing stock prices with 
different underlying assumptions about dividend volatility, where high 
assumed dividend volatility proxies for less diversification. 
Although these statistics point to an increase in participation and a 
reduction in risk exposure, it is questionable how significant these ef-
fects are quantitatively. The change from 52 million to 69 million partici-
pants is a 33% increase, but when the numbers are wealth-weighted, the 
increase is much smaller. Now as in the past, the vast majority of stocks 
are held by wealthy individuals. For instance, Poterba (1998) finds that in 
the 1995 SCF, 82% of stock was held by households with a stock portfolio 
exceeding $100,000, and 54% of stock was held by households with 
annual income over $100,000. This suggests that stockholdings remain 
extremely concentrated. Figures 2 and 3 present a more complete picture 
of how the distribution of stockholdings vs. wealth and income has 
changed over the period 1989 to 1995 (see also Table 4). Using data from 
the SCF, we plot the share of stocks held against the share of income or 
wealth. Stockholding looks more democratic when measured relative to 
income than relative to wealth, since as noted in Vissing-Jorgensen 
(1997), lower-labor-income households own a larger share of the market 
than in the past. When the metric is wealth, however, there has been 
very little change-holdings were and are extremely concentrated. </p>

<p>Table 4 PROPORTION OF POPULATION THAT HOLDS STOCK BY 
WEALTH COHORT </p>

<p>Percentile 
Range 
Proportion 
Range 
Proportion 
Range (%) 
($) 
(%) 
($) 
(%) </p>

<p>&lt;25 
&lt;801 
2.3 
&lt;1101 
4.7 
26-50 
801-40,051 
13.0 
1102-40,500 
17.8 
51-75 
40,052-121,500 
21.6 
40,501-126,251 
28.7 
76-90 
121,501-279,001 
36.7 
126,252-309,501 
47.8 
91-95 
279,001-456,000 
55.4 
309,502-574,000 
62.8 
96-99 
456,001-1,767,730 
65.8 
574,001-1,814,330 
78.3 
&gt;99 
&gt;1,767,730 
84.3 
&gt;1,814,331 
82.0 </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Figure 2 PERCENTAGE OF STOCK HELD BY INCOME PERCENTILE </p>

<p>0: 1995, X: 1989 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>c', </p>

<p>o0Z </p>

<p>0 50-</p>

<p>u 40 </p>

<p>U-</p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
Income Percentile </p>

<p>Figure 3 PERCENTAGE OF STOCK HELD BY WEALTH PERCENTILE </p>

<p>0: 1995, X: 1989 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>0 60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>o 50 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>i 40 </p>

<p>LL </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 
100 
Wealth Percentile </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
225 </p>

<p>Table 5 NET PURCHASES OF STOCKS BY INDIVIDUALS </p>

<p>Purchases (billions of dollars) </p>

<p>Year 
Net 
Through Mutual Funds 
Outside Mutual Funds </p>

<p>1995 
-116.1 
91.3 
-207.4 </p>

<p>1996 
-101.9 
218.4 
-320.3 </p>

<p>1997 
-179.0 
190.2 
-369.2 </p>

<p>Ideally, one would like to measure the net investment in the stock 
market in recent years on behalf of households. If net inflows were large, 
one could perhaps conclude that the demand for stocks had significantly 
increased. The fact that aggregate savings rates are low is indirect evi-
dence that these net inflows cannot be large. Still, there could be substitu-
tion out of money and bonds into stocks, increasing the net flow into 
stocks. According to the flow-of-funds accounts, U.S. Treasury securities 
are the only category of fixed-income investment that had a large net 
outflow from the household sector in recent years. Calculating flows into 
stocks directly is tricky because there have been large changes in the 
institutional structure of the investment industry. Table 5, using data 
from the Investment Company Institute, shows net purchases of stocks, 
purchases made through mutual funds, and purchases made outside 
mutual funds, by households, from 1995 to 1997. While purchases made 
through mutual funds increased significantly over the period, net pur-
chases of equities by households were actually negative in each year. 
This is because households were net sellers of equities to institutions. 
Changes in foreign participation in the U.S. market may also affect 
expected returns. Assuming that foreign participants are similar to U.S. 
stockholders in their attitude towards risk and their ex ante risk expo-
sure, an increase in foreign participation should lower expected returns 
by increasing opportunities for diversification. Net foreign purchases of 
stock have spiked sharply in recent years (see Figure 4), and these in-
flows, over the period January 1988 to February 1999, have a correlation 
of 0.13 with monthly returns on the S&amp;P 500. The average monthly net 
inflow between January 1996 and February 1999 is $3.8 billion, compared 
to only $349 million from the period January 1988 to December 1995. 
Although the inflows have increased significantly, they still represent a 
small fraction of total market transactions, which totaled approximately 
$479 billion per month in 1997 on the New York Stock Exchange alone.7 </p>

<p>7. Data on foreign purchases and sales of U.S. stocks are from the U.S. Department of the 
Treasury's table "TIC Capital Movements, U.S. Transactions with Foreigners in Long 
Term Securities." S&amp;P 500 monthly returns data are from Robert Shiller. Total trading </p>

<p>volume is from the NYSE 1997 Fact Book. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>Figure 4 FOREIGN NET INVESTMENT AND RETURNS </p>

<p>Foreign Net Stock Investment </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>_S&amp;P </p>

<p>500 Return </p>

<p>15000 
0.3 </p>

<p>10000 
-0.2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>I 
I0 </p>

<p>-5000 
-0.1 </p>

<p>1988 
1990 
1992 
1994 
199 
1998 
2000 </p>

<p>Date </p>

<p>E' 
lr 
w ~ </p>

<p>II 
I </p>

<p>Date </p>

<p>4. An Overlapping-Generations Model </p>

<p>In this section, we ask whether changing stock-market participation pat-
terns and increased diversification can have a quantitatively important 
effect on stock prices in an equilibrium model. We calibrate an overlap-
ping-generations (OLG) model in which agents face both aggregate and 
idiosyncratic income risk, and a variable subset of agents has limited 
access to financial markets. 
The effects of limited participation in financial markets has been con-
sidered by a number of authors, including Basak and Cuoco (1998), 
Saito (1995), and Vissing-Jorgensen (1997). In these papers, aggregate 
consumption is completely traded in financial markets in the form of 
dividends. Only a limited number of agents can trade claims on this 
dividend flow directly. The other agents participate in financial markets 
only by trading claims to risk-free bonds. The result is incomplete 
sharing of aggregate risk, with stockholders often taking leveraged posi-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
227 </p>

<p>tions to accommodate the demand for bonds by nonparticipants. Be-
cause of this, a larger risk premium is necessary to induce those in the 
stock market to hold all of the aggregate risk. It is difficult to justify the 
magnitude of the observed equity premium in these models, however, 
unless one assumes very high risk aversion or very low participation 
rates. 
One way to increase the effects of limited participation is to include 
other sources of uninsurable income risk. For instance, income from 
wages and/or privately held businesses constitutes the majority of in-
come for most households (Heaton and Lucas, 1998). These income 
flows are difficult to contract upon, and a large component of this 
income risk is specific to each individual of household. We refer to the 
sum of labor income and privately held business income as non-
marketed income. Potential differences in the properties of this income 
for participants versus nonparticipants are likely to influence the ef-
fects of limited participation on asset returns. This is consistent with 
the empirical observation that the consumption of stockholders is 
more volatile than that of nonstockholders (Mankiw and Zeldes, 1991). 
Polkovnichenko (1998) demonstrates how differential income risk and 
risk aversion can affect asset prices in a model with infinite-lived 
heterogeneous agents. He shows that a small fixed transaction cost 
that endogenously limits stock-market participation can interact with 
idiosyncratic risk to result in a bigger equity premium than in a repre-
sentative agent model, although matching the observed premium is 
still elusive. 
The model presented here allows us to examine the effect of participa-
tion and diversification while considering a greater degree of cross-
sectional heterogeneity than in the previous literature, due to the simpli-
fying assumption of two-period lives. Unlike the papers discussed 
above, which focus on whether limited participation can explain the 
historical equity premium, we focus on the question of to what extent 
observed changes in participation rates can explain the recent run-up in 
stock prices. We also emphasize the effect of changes in the degree of 
portfolio diversification. </p>

<p>4.1 STRUCTURE OF THE MODEL </p>

<p>At each time period, t, a generation of J "young" agents are born and live 
for two periods.8 Let C(j,t) be the consumption of agent j when young, </p>

<p>8. Storesletten, Telmer, and Yaron (1998) consider an OLG model in which the agents face 
nontradable idiosyncratic risk and live for a large number of periods. We limit ourselves 
to a smaller number of periods to make numerical solution of the model easier. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>and C'(j,t + 1) be the consumption of agent j when old (j = 1,2, . . . , J). </p>

<p>The utility specification for agent j distinguishes between risk aversion 
and the elasticity of intertemporal substitution. We use the parametric 
form proposed by Epstein and Zin (1989) and Weil (1990): </p>

<p>U(j,t) logC(j,t) + 
logE[C'(j,t + </p>

<p>1)1_ </p>

<p>I (t)], 
(1) </p>

<p>where 3j &gt; 0 and aj &gt; 0. Here 5(t) is the information available at time t and 
is assumed to be common across agents. As discussed by Epstein and Zin 
(1989), the parameter aj is the coefficient of relative risk aversion. The 
elasticity of intertemporal substitution equals one. In the experiments 
considered below, changes in participation affect the equilibrium volatil-
ity of individual consumption in the second period. In general, this affects 
both the level of interest rates and the equity premium. By distinguishing 
between risk aversion and the elasticity of intertemporal substitution, the 
effect of the income process on the equity premium is to some extent 
separated from its effect on the risk-free rate. </p>

<p>Each agent j(j = 1,2, . . ., J) is endowed with random nonmarketed </p>

<p>income Y(j,t) at time t and random nonmarketed income Yo(j,t + 1) 
when old at time t + 1. The details of the individual income processes 
are described below. The agents trade in financial markets in an attempt 
to smooth consumption over time. There are two securities that can be 
traded: a stock and a risk-free bond. At time t the stock represents a </p>

<p>claim to future dividends {D(t + 7) : T = 1,2, . . . }. The total supply of </p>

<p>stock is normalized to one. The bond is assumed to be in zero net supply. 
Each agent is exposed to nonmarketed income risk that has both an 
aggregate component and an idiosyncratic component. Aggregate non-
marketed income at time t is denoted by Ya(t), where </p>

<p>J 
J </p>

<p>ya(t) = Y(jt) + EY(jt). 
(2) </p>

<p>j= 1 
j= 1 </p>

<p>In equilibrium, this endowment plus dividends equals aggregate con-
sumption at time t. The properties of individual nonmarketed income 
Y(j,t) and Yo(j,t) will be potentially important in assessing the effects of 
changing participation and background income risk on equilibrium 
returns. 
At time t each young agent maximizes utility (1) subject to a constraint </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
229 </p>

<p>that depends on the agent's access to financial markets. Let Ps(t) be the 
price of the stock at time t, and pb(t) be the price of a bond that pays one 
unit of consumption at time t + 1 for sure. If agent j has access to both 
financial markets, then the agent's flow wealth constraints are </p>

<p>C(j,t) = Y(j,t) -S(j,t)ps(t) -B(j,t)pb(t), 
(3a) 
Co(j,t + 1) = Yo(j,t + 1) + S(j,t)[Ps(t + 1) + D(t + 1)] + B(j,t), 
(3b) </p>

<p>where S(j,t) gives the stockholdings of agent j, and B(j,t) gives the 
bondholdings of agent j. A subset of the agents is assumed to have only 
limited access to financial markets and can trade only in bonds. In this 
case the constraints (3) are replaced by </p>

<p>C(j,t) = Y(j,t) -B(j,t)pb(t), </p>

<p>(4a) </p>

<p>Co(j,t + 1) = Yo(j,t + 1) + B(j,t). 
(4b) </p>

<p>An equilibrium is given by processes for stock and bond prices {Ps(t) : t = </p>

<p>0,1, ... } and {Pb(t) : t = 0,1, . . } such that </p>

<p>SS*(j,t) = 1, 
(5a) </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>B*(j,t) = 0, 
(5b) </p>

<p>j=1 </p>

<p>where {S*(j,t),B*(j,t)} maximizes (1) subject to (3) if the agent can trade in 
both markets, or subject to (4) if the agent can trade only in the bond 
market. </p>

<p>We assume that nonmarketed income {Ya(t) : t = 0,1, . . . } and divi-</p>

<p>dend income grow over time in such a way that the growth rate of 
aggregate income is a stationary process. Consistent with this, we as-</p>

<p>sume that at time t we have Y(j,t) = y(j,t)Ya(t) and D(t) = d(t)Ya(t), where </p>

<p>y(j,t) denotes the share of individual j's income in aggregate income, 
and d(t) the dividend relative to aggregate nonmarketed income. Simi-</p>

<p>larly we assume that Yo(j,t) = ya(j,t)Ya(t). This implies that one can look </p>

<p>for an equilibrium in which the stock price also scales with aggregate </p>

<p>income, so that PS(t) = ps(t)Ya(t). Finally, we assume that the face value of 
a bond purchased at time t is given by Ya(t), so that B(j,t) = b(j,t)Y'(t), </p>

<p>where b(j,t) gives the quantity of these "rescaled" bonds purchased by 
agent j. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>4.2 CALIBRATION </p>

<p>In this subsection, we calibrate the model in order to revisit quantita-
tively some of the questions discussed in Section 3. How much do as-
sumed changes in participation rates affect the predicted equity pre-
mium and expected returns (and hence prices)? How does the degree of 
portfolio diversification affect required returns? Can small changes in 
preference parameters, reflecting changes in patience or risk aversion, 
result in large changes in required returns? How important is hetero-
geneity in income risk? To answer these questions, the model is solved 
numerically using standard techniques. Although we assume consider-
able heterogeneity in the cross section, the fact that agents only live for 
two periods makes the problem numerically tractable.9 
We begin by describing the parameterization of the income processes 
and preferences. Parameters are chosen to reflect limited stock-market 
participation, and to try to match gross features of the data with respect 
to stock returns, the risk-free rate, and the driving processes for non-
marketed income and dividends. 
As in most exercises of this type, the equity-premium puzzle remains 
a serious problem. For income and dividend processes and participation 
rates based on historical data, the model predicts an unrealistically small 
equity premium. We have increased the assumed volatility of aggregate 
income to increase the predicted premium, but want to emphasize that 
this may not be a neutral adjustment with respect to the other quantities 
of interest.10 </p>

<p>4.2.1 Income and Preferences Let y(t) -log[Ya(t)/Ya(t -1)] be the growth </p>

<p>rate of aggregate nonmarketed income at time t. Then the aggregate state </p>

<p>of the economy is given by z(t) = [y(t) d(t)]', which is assumed to be </p>

<p>generated by a Markov chain. To calibrate a process for z(t) we assume that 
a period corresponds to 25 years. The first period roughly corresponds to 
the working years between age 40 and retirement, and the second period 
is the time in retirement. Over the period 1889 to 1985, the average annual 
(log) growth rate in real aggregate consumption was 1.7% with a standard 
deviation of 3.5%. So that the model will produce a nonnegligible equity 
premium, we assume that the standard deviation of the aggregate growth 
rate in the model is 1.5 times the historical standard deviation of aggregate </p>

<p>9. The <rs type="software">Matlab</rs> code is available upon request. 
10. Recently Campbell and Cochrane (1998) suggested that time-varying habit provides a 
higher estimate of the equity premium in a model based on aggregate consumption. 
However, Cochrane (1997) claims that this preference specification cannot account for 
the recent run-up in stock prices. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
231 </p>

<p>consumption. For the same reason, we assume that annual income 
growth is independently and identically distributed over time, although 
in fact it is slightly negatively autocorrelated. This implies a 25-year aver-
age (log) growth rate of 42.5% with a standard deviation of 17.5%. This 
distribution is discretized by assuming that y takes on the values 0.16 and 
0.69 with equal conditional probability. 
The capital share in total income averages approximately 30%. Consis-
tent with the aggregate statistics reported in Heaton and Lucas (1998), 
we assume that only half of this capital income is actually tradable. The 
nontradable portion, generated by private business holdings, is ac-
counted for in nonmarketed income. Since dividends in the model are 
scaled relative to nonmarketed income, this means that we require d(t) to 
average 18%. In most of the calculations d(t) is fixed at 18%. In other 
experiments described below, we assume a more volatile dividend pro-
cess to proxy for a lack of diversification.11 
The relative nonmarketed income of young agent j and of old agent k 
at time t are given by </p>

<p>y(j,t) = E (j,t)[1 -ij(t)], 
(6) 
yo(k,t) = E(k,t)Tq(t), 
(7) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>I 
I </p>

<p>E(j,t) = 1 and ~ ~(k,t)=1. 
(8) </p>

<p>j=1 
k=1 </p>

<p>Under this normalization, q(t) gives the share of old individuals' non-
marketed income in total nonmarketed income. The analysis is sensitive 
to this parameter because the amount of nonmarketed income influ-
ences agents' attitude towards the risk of investment income. For the 
basic analyis we assume that qj = 0.2 for all t, reflecting the observation 
that noninvestment wealth is relatively small for retirees. In the sensitiv-
ity analysis, this parameter is varied to a maximum of 0.3. </p>

<p>The process for E(j,t) and e'(k,t) captures idiosyncratic income risk </p>

<p>across agents. We know from earlier work (e.g., Constantinides and 
Duffie, 1996) that asset returns are potentially sensitive to the persis-
tence of idiosyncratic income shocks and to the correlation and condi-
tional covariance of idiosyncratic and aggregate shocks. We assume a 
process for individual income risk based in part on the estimations re-</p>

<p>11. In constructing the total dividend series, we always normalize the level of dividends so 
that they average 15% of GDP. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
" 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>ported in Deaton (1992) and adjusted for the assumed 25-year period 
length. Deaton reports a standard deviation of shocks for an MA(1) 
specification of individual income growth of 15%, and an MA coefficient 
of -0.4. Based on this, the idiosyncratic income shocks for both the 
young and the old are assumed to have a standard deviation of 45% over 
each 25-year period. The shock when young is assumed to be completely 
persistent, so that </p>

<p>E?(j,t + 1) = e(j,t)Wo(j,t + 1), 
(9) </p>

<p>where w(j,t + 1) is the further 45%-standard-deviation shock to relative 
nonmarketed income that agent j faces when old. In experiments below, 
we also consider the situation in which the idiosyncratic shocks of a 
subset of the population are correlated with dividends. This captures the 
possibility that certain classes of agents, such as business owners or 
executives who own large shares of stock in their own corporation, face 
risks that are more correlated with the market than a typical individual. 
Because preferences are homothetic, when agents are assumed to be 
homogeneous only the w-shock affects prices and portfolio choice. When 
the wealth and income of participants and nonparticipants differ, how-
ever, the income distribution of the young can affect predicted returns. 
For most of the analysis, preferences are parametrized with P3, = 0.9525 
and a, = 5 for all j. These parameters are also varied in the sensitivity 
analysis. </p>

<p>4.2.2 Varying Participation Rates Table 6 shows what happens when the 
assumed participation rate in the stock market is varied between 30% 
and 100% of the population, assuming the preference specification and 
processes for individual and aggregate income described above. As one 
would expect, increased participation lowers the equity premium. No-
tice, however, that the effect is small in the region of participation rates 
that correspond to the data. For example, when participation increases 
from 50% to 80% of the population, the equity premium and the absolute 
level of equity returns are reduced by less than a tenth of a percent. 
Changing participation also has a small effect on the level of the risk-free 
rate, with an increase in participation increasing the average rate of 
return. This can be attributed to a precautionary effect that decreases 
when risk is spread more evenly over the population. Although small, 
this effect is in keeping with the observation that the risk-free rate has 
risen in recent years. 
Consistent with the literature on the equity-premium puzzle, aggre-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
233 </p>

<p>Table 6 AVERAGE ANNUAL RETURNS AS A FUNCTION 
OF PARTICIPATION </p>

<p>Percentage ofReturns 
(%) </p>

<p>Stockholders 
E (rb) 
E(rs) 
E (rs -rb) </p>

<p>100 
4.42 
5.47 
1.05 
90 
4.40 
5.48 
1.08 
80 
4.38 
5.49 
1.11 
70 
4.37 
5.50 
1.13 
60 
4.35 
5.51 
1.16 
50 
4.33 
5.52 
1.19 
40 
4.32 
5.53 
1.21 
30 
4.32 
5.55 
1.23 </p>

<p>gate income and dividend risk alone are not sufficient to generate a 
sizable equity premium. This is true even under the assumption of ex-
tremely limited participation, inflated aggregate risk, and nonmarketed 
income risk. Still, the premium predicted here is higher than in Mehra 
and Prescott (1985) by about 1%. Experiments not reported here indicate 
that this difference is due primarily to the assumption that aggregate risk 
is higher than that observed in the data, rather than to limited participa-
tion or exposure to idiosyncratic income risk. 
In the experiments that follow, we examine other stochastic steady 
states based on different degrees of diversification, risk aversion, etc. 
Although looking across steady states does not allow one to watch re-
turns gradually changing over time as parameters gradually change, it 
does provide an upper bound on the size of these effects. Thus, one can 
give a temporal interpretation to some of the experiments. For instance, 
we will compare the stylized historical past, with low diversification and 
low participation rates, to the stylized present, with greater diversifica-
tion, more complete participation, and greater patience. </p>

<p>4.2.3 Increasing Diversification As a proxy for the increased diversifica-</p>

<p>tion of a typical market participant over time, we vary the assumed 
volatility of the dividend process. It is an empirical fact that the variabil-
ity of returns falls dramatically as diversification increases. Based on 
CRSP monthly data from 1962 to 1997, Table 7 shows the effect of diversi-
fication on a typical portfolio's annual standard deviation. In monthly 
data, we find an average individual stock standard deviation of 16% and 
an average pairwise covariance of 0.01. The portfolio standard devia-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Table 7 THE EFFECT OF DIVERSIFICATION ON 
PORTFOLIO VOLATILITY </p>

<p>No. of 
Standard Deviation (%) 
Stocks 
Monthly 
Annual </p>

<p>1 
16.0 
55.4 
2 
11.7 
40.4 </p>

<p>3 
9.8 
33.9 </p>

<p>4 
8.7 
30.2 
5 
8.0 
27.7 
10 
6.3 
21.9 
20 
5.3 
18.3 
100 
4.3 
14.9 
500 
4.1 
14.1 </p>

<p>tions reported in the table assume equal value weights on each stock. 
Monthly returns are annualized under the assumption that they are 
independent. These calculations show that holding a one-stock portfolio 
results in an annual standard deviation of 55%, while increasing hold-
ings to five stocks decreases the standard deviation to 28%, and holding 
500 stocks brings it down to 14%. 
The above statistics on portfolio returns do not translate directly into 
parameter values, since the inputs into the model are income and divi-
dend processes, whereas returns are endogenous. One assumption 
about dividends that produces returns consistent with those observed in 
CRSP data is that d(t) is variable over time, taking on the values 0.11 and 
0.25 with equal probability. This level of variation essentially brackets the 
variation in dividends' share in total income, based on the S&amp;P 500 
dividend flow and U.S. gross domestic product since 1947. We call this 
the case of high dividend volatility. It implies variation that is approxi-
mately consistent with a three-stock portfolio under the parametriza-
tions we focus on. 
Second, we consider a situation referred to as correlated high dividend 
volatility. Here the aggregate dividend is assumed to be correlated with 
nonmarketed income, taking on the value 0.11 in the low-nonmarketed-
income state and 0.25 in the high-nonmarketed-income state. These first 
two cases bracket two views of the relation between dividend growth 
and income growth. The first is that there is very little correlation be-
tween income growth and dividend growth on an annual basis. The 
second is that over longet time periods, such as the 25-year periods </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
235 </p>

<p>considered here, there is a positive correlation between dividends and </p>

<p>income.12 </p>

<p>Finally, we represent the increased volatility in a poorly diversified 
portfolio by assuming a skewed distribution of dividends. The dividend 
share, 8, is fixed at 0.1865 for 95% of the time, but falls to 0.06 for 5% of the 
time, independent of the aggregate state. This skewed dividend case repre-
sents bankruptcy of a poorly diversified portfolio. It is further assumed 
that zero is an absorbing state for the value of a bankrupt portfolio after 
this small dividend is paid. To maintain stationarity, bankrupt shares are 
replaced by new shares in the new generation. These new shares are held 
in the portfolios of the young, but cannot be sold until the following 
period. The reason to consider a more skewed distribution of payoffs is 
twofold. First, although catastrophic outcomes are rare for the U.S. stock 
market as a whole, individual firms fail quite frequently. Secondly, the 
properties of the utility function suggest that skewed outcomes will have 
a much different effect on asset prices than a symmetric distribution with 
the same variance. In fact, the implied volatility of returns in this case is 
set to be similar to that in the case of high dividend volatility. 
Table 8 is similar to Table 6, but reports results under the assumptions 
of high dividend volatility, correlated high dividend volatility, and 
skewed dividends. Panel A reproduces the predicted returns under the 
base-case set of assumptions for participation rates of 50% and 100%. 
Relative to panel A, assuming high dividend volatility (panel B) has the 
effect of decreasing the risk-free rate by 0.61% and 0.82% for participa-
tion levels of 100% and 50% respectively. It increases the equity premium 
by 0.71% and 0.97%, respectively, for the same participation rates. These 
results are consistent with the view that increased diversification has 
significantly reduced the required equity premium, although for these 
parameters it suggests only a slight decrease in the level of the required 
return on equities. For the case of correlated high dividend volatility 
(panel C), the effect on the equity premium of an increase in dividend 
volatility is even larger. 
Notice that for high dividend volatility an increase in participation re-
sults in a larger decline in the equity premium than for low dividend 
volatility. This occurs in part because with high dividend volatility case 
there is more risk to be shared, and hence a greater benefit from spreading </p>

<p>12. As one would expect, predicted returns are sensitive to the assumed degree of correla-
tion between dividends and nonmarketed income. It is not obvious, however, whether 
the dividends from a poorly diversified portfolio are likely to be more or' less highly 
correlated with nonmarketed income than for a well-diversified portfolio. If, for in-
stance, households own stock primarily in the companies for which they work (a 
common phenomenon), the correlation may be relatively high. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p> 
HEATON &amp; LUCAS </p>

<p>Table 8 AVERAGE RETURNS AS A FUNCTION OF PARTICIPATION AND 
THE DIVIDEND PROCESS </p>

<p>Percentage ofReturns 
(%) </p>

<p>Stockholders 
E(rb) 
E(rs) 
E(rs -rb) </p>

<p>A. Low Dividend Volatility </p>

<p>100 
4.42 
5.47 
1.05 </p>

<p>50 
4.33 
5.52 
1.19 </p>

<p>B. High Dividend Volatility </p>

<p>100 
3.81 
5.57 
1.76 
50 
3.51 
5.67 
2.16 </p>

<p>C. Correlated High Dividend Volatility </p>

<p>100 
3.38 
5.87 
2.49 </p>

<p>50 
3.36 
5.95 
2.59 </p>

<p>D. Skewed Dividends 
100 
1.54 
6.17 
4.63 </p>

<p>50 
0.47 
6.93 
6.46 </p>

<p>this risk to new participants with no initial exposure to market risk. For 
correlated high dividend volatility, however, changes in participation 
have a smaller effect on the equity premium than for uncorrelated high 
dividend volatility. This is because the new entrants are less willing to 
bear stock-market risk when it is correlated with their nonmarketed risk. 
Finally, the much more dramatic results in the skewed-dividend case 
are shown in panel D. The small risk of a catastrophic outcome reduces 
the risk-free rate to 0.47% and increases the equity premium to 6.46% 
with 50% participation. With 100% participation, the risk-free rate equals 
1.54% and the equity premium is 4.63%. This assumption therefore 
allows one to match the historical equity premium. It also suggests that 
in this region of parameter space the premium is more sensitive to 
changes in participation rates. This points to changes in diversification 
as a potentially large factor in explaining changes in expected returns. </p>

<p>4.2.4 Preference-Parameter Changes The potential effects of changing risk 
attitudes are explored by changing the coefficient of relative risk aver-
sion, aj. Recall that in all the results reported above a1 is set to 5. If ac is 
increased to 10, with all else as in the high-dividend-volatility case and at 
a 50% participation rate, the equity premium rises by only 0.16%. The 
risk-free rate falls by 0.3%. It is clear that over the range of risk-aversion 
coefficients usually considered, a change in risk aversion does not ac-
count for large changes in stock prices in this model. </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
237 </p>

<p>As discussed in Section 3, increases in life expectancy may affect the 
subjective rate of discount. Varying 13, is a proxy for these changes. </p>

<p>Unlike in an infinite-horizon model, where P3 generally does not have a </p>

<p>first-order effect on the equity premium, varying P here influences the </p>

<p>equity premium as well as the general level of returns. The reason is that 
when 83 increases, the value of future dividends and nonmarketable 
income increases relative to the value of first-period income. This 
changes the share of capital in wealth and increases the importance of 
second-period income risk. For the parameters we consider, this results 
in a lower equity premium in levels, but a higher premium relative to the </p>

<p>risk-free rate. For instance, increasing P from 0.9525 to 0.9625, with 50% </p>

<p>participation, high dividend volatility, a equal to 5, and q7 equal to 0.2, 
moves the equity premium from 2.16% to 2.02%, and the risk-free rate 
from 3.51% to 3.05%. We interpret the increase in the relative premium 
as a response to the increased exposure to market risk. The reduction in 
the absolute premium reflects the increased precautionary demand for 
savings with the increase in risk, which lowers all required rates of 
return. 
Varying qj, the share of nonmarketed income accruing to the elderly, 
similarly affects risk and hence returns. For instance, increasing 77 from 
0.2 to 0.3, with 03 equal to 0.9525 and all else as in the case above, moves 
the equity premium from 2.16% to 2.49% and the risk-free rate from 
3.51% to 4.14%. </p>

<p>4.2.5 Heterogeneity in Idiosyncratic Income Shocks An interesting question 
is whether background income risk (i.e., nonmarketable risk) is different 
for stockholders and nonstockholders, and whether this difference inter-
acts with the effect of participation changes on asset returns. In Heaton 
and Lucas (1998) we present evidence that many large stockholders de-
pend more heavily on income from privately held businesses than on 
labor income. Business income is more volatile and more highly corre-
lated with stock returns than is labor income. Hence, the equity pre-
mium is likely to fall more sharply if new entrants who are otherwise 
similar to stockholders depend predominantly on labor income. As dis-
cussed in Section 3.2, in recent years there has been an increase in 
participation by middle-income households, which are likely to contain 
wage earners. We investigate the potential quantitative effect of this 
change by assuming a different idiosyncratic income process for a subset 
of the stockholders and for nonstockholders.13 </p>

<p>13. Ideally we would make participation endogenous and hence a function of the assumed 
income process, as in Polkovnichenko (1998). This tends reduce the risk-sharing capac-
ity of new entrants, since the most risk-tolerant agents already hold stocks when entry </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>Table 9 AVERAGE RETURNS AS A FUNCTION OF PARTICIPATION AND 
THE DIVIDEND PROCESS (HETEROGENEOUS INCOME RISK) </p>

<p>Returns (%) </p>

<p>Percentage of 
Stockholders 
E(rb) 
E(rs) 
E(rs -rb) </p>

<p>A. High Dividend Volatility </p>

<p>100 
3.74 
5.49 
1.75 
50 
3.42 
5.58 
2.16 </p>

<p>B. Correlated High Dividend Volatility </p>

<p>100 
3.32 
5.79 
2.47 
50 
3.28 
5.85 
2.57 </p>

<p>C. Skewed Dividends </p>

<p>100 
1.18 
6.12 
4.94 </p>

<p>50 
0.17 
6.82 
6.65 </p>

<p>To implement this, we assume that a fixed number of participants 
have nonmarketed income that is correlated with the dividend flow from 
stocks. New entrants to the stock market and nonparticipants have a less 
correlated income process. More precisely, we assume that 25% of the 
population receive idiosyncratic income when old, with a standard devia-
tion of 67.5% and a correlation with dividends' share in aggregate in-
come of 0.2. this group is always assumed to hold stocks.14 The rest of 
the population receives idiosyncratic shocks that have a standard devia-
tion of 45% as before, and a correlation with dividends of -0.1. This 
negative correlation is necessary to produce an average correlation that 
is consistent with data. In annual data, one does in fact see a slight 
negative correlation between labor income and stock returns. 
Table 9 reports results under these assumptions for high dividend 
volatility (panel A), correlated high dividend volatility (panel B), and 
skewed dividends (panel C). In each case, the experiment is to move 
from a situation in which 50% of the stockholding population is exposed 
to high background risk to one in which 25% has this exposure. Changes 
in participation now have only slightly more effect than in Table 8 for 
high dividend volatility. The effect of a change in participation is slightly 
smaller for skewed dividends. The effect of an increase in participation 
on the premium relative to the risk-free rate is higher in each case, </p>

<p>is endogenous. For simplicity, and to put an upper bound on this effect, we assume 
that participation is completely exogenous. 
14. These parameter assumptions are consistent with the estimates reported by Heaton 
and Lucas (1998). </p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

<p>Stock Prices and Fundamentals 
? 
239 </p>

<p>however, because of the greater volatility of the nonmarketed income of 
stockholders. As in Table 8, the greatest effect of participation is in the 
case of skewed dividends, where the equity premium falls by 1.71% 
when participation increases from 50% to 100%. </p>

<p>4.2.6 Simultaneous Changes As discussed in the introduction, each of 
the factors that we have looked at individually has been suggested as a 
fundamental reason for the stock price run-up. We have seen that none 
of these factors alone is sufficient to produce a large change in required 
equity returns, and hence the large run-up in stock prices. Here we 
examine the best case for the model, simultaneously changing a number </p>

<p>of parameters. The stylized historical past is characterized by a P of </p>

<p>0.9525, dividends as described in the skewed-dividend case, and a partici-
pation rate of 50%. Income processes are heterogeneous as described in 
the previous subsection, so that 50% of stockholders have highly volatile 
income that is correlated with dividends. The risk aversion a is fixed at </p>

<p>5, and 77 is fixed at 0.2. The stylized present is described by a P of 0.9625, </p>

<p>reflecting an upward revision of expected life expectancy, low-volatility 
dividends as in Table 6 reflecting a considerable increase in diversifica-
tion, and a participation rate of 80%. All else is as in the past. This results 
in a risk-free rate that rises from 0.17% to 3.73%, and an expected return 
on stocks that decreases from 6.82% to 4.84%. The equity premium is 
substantially reduced, from 6.65% to 1.11%. We conclude, then, that 
assuming reasonable changes in a number of variables simultaneously 
can account for changes in expected returns in keeping with what ap-
pears to be the case in the U.S. economy. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>In this paper, we have looked at a number of potential fundamentals-
based explanations for the recent stock price run-up. In particular, we 
focused on whether changes in market participation patterns or changes 
in portfolio diversification are likely to account for a substantial fraction 
of the rise in stock prices. We conclude that the changes in participation 
that have occurred over this decade are unlikely to be a major part of the 
explanation. This conclusion is based both on the data, which suggest 
only small changes in participation for wealthy households, and the 
model, which implies that participation changes have to be quite ex-
treme to substantially affect expected returns. Increased portfolio diversi-
fication, however, is likely to have had a larger effect. There is empirical 
evidence that households have significantly diversified their portfolios, 
selling individual stocks and buying mutual funds. An important differ-</p>

<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>ence between poorly diversified portfolios and a market index is the 
likelihood of catastrophic outcomes. When this difference is reflected in 
model parameters, the expected equity premium falls by more than 4%. 
More generally, we can construct scenarios that are loosely consistent 
with the data in which the required return on stocks falls by 2%. As shown 
in Section 3.1 using a calibrated Gordon growth model, this amount of 
change in expected returns goes at least halfway towards justifying the 
current high level of the price-dividend ratio in the U.S. market. We 
interpret this as quite a positive result, especially because it is difficult to 
produce much variation in the predicted equity premium in this class of 
models. The model also predicts an increase in the real risk-free rate, 
which also appears to be consistent with the data. 
These results depend in an important way on changes in diversifica-
tion and, to a lesser extent, on income heterogeneity. There is evidence 
that entrepreneurs and managers tend to be large stockholders who bear 
a sizable amount of undiversifiable risk in the form of their own busi-
nesses. Still, we do not have a complete picture of the income and 
wealth characteristics of large stockholders, and we are uncertain about 
the extent of their diversification. We also do not have a satisfactory 
understanding of how older stockholders, who own a substantial frac-
tion of the market, view the risk of stock ownership. Looking even more 
closely at the characteristics of large stockholders remains a useful direc-
tion for future research. </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM </p>

<p>All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>





<p>1. Introduction </p>

<p>During the period 1995-1998 the U.S. stock market experienced four 
consecutive years with real stock returns above 20%. Suppose as a rough 
approximation that annual real log gross stock returns are normally dis-
tributed and independent over time. With a mean and variance of this 
distribution equal to the historical values for the period 1871-1994, the 
probability of observing four years of above 20% returns is 0.4%.1 The 
high returns have come primarily from capital gains driving price-
dividend and price-earnings ratios to historical highs (the latest num-
bers from August 9 for the S&amp;P 500 are P/D = 78.5 and P/E = 31.9). Thus, 
even taking into account statistical fluctuation, it is becoming increas-
ingly unlikely that nothing has changed. The only period since 1871 with 
as impressive returns was 1924-1928, with five years of above 20% real 
stock returns. Over the three-year period following that event, real stock 
returns averaged -15.4% annually. 
In the present paper Heaton and Lucas ask whether the recent stock-
market boom can be explained by changes in economic fundamentals. 
Three candidates are considered: changes in corporate earnings growth, 
changes in consumer preferences, and changes in stock-market participa-
tion patterns. Participation is defined broadly as concerning both the 
level of stock-market participation and the amount of diversification 
among participants. Poor diversification is found to have large effects on 
equilibrium returns in an overlapping generations exchange economy. 
The main conclusion of the paper is that increased diversification by 
itself can explain at least half of the increase in the adjusted P/D ratio. 
This is an interesting finding, not only for interpreting the recent past 
but also seen in the context of the literature on the equity premium </p>



<p>This content downloaded from 146.006.168.120 on March 30, 2018 09:47:54 AM 
All use subject to University of Chicago Press Terms and Conditions (http://www.journals.uchicago.edu/t-and-c). </p>

</text></tei>