<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.20955%2Fr.2018.1-16" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Bitcoin originated with the white paper that was published in 2008 under the pseudonym 
"Satoshi Nakamoto." It was published via a mailing list for cryptography and has a similar 
appearance to an academic paper. The creators' original motivation behind Bitcoin was to 
develop a cash-like payment system that permitted electronic transactions but that also 
included many of the advantageous characteristics of physical cash. To understand the spe-
cific features of physical monetary units and the desire to develop digital cash, we will begin 
our analysis by considering a simple cash transaction. </p>

<p>1.1 Cash </p>

<p>Cash is represented by a physical object, usually a coin or a note. When this object is 
handed to another individual, its unit of value is also transferred, without the need for a third 
party to be involved (Figure 1). No credit relationship arises between the buyer and the seller. 
This is why it is possible for the parties involved to remain anonymous. 
The great advantage of physical cash is that whoever is in possession of the physical object 
is by default the owner of the unit of value. This ensures that the property rights to the units </p>

<p>In this article, we give a short introduction to cryptocurrencies and blockchain technology. The focus 
of the introduction is on Bitcoin, but many elements are shared by other blockchain implementations 
and alternative cryptoassets. The article covers the original idea and motivation, the mode of operation 
and possible applications of cryptocurrencies, and blockchain technology. We conclude that Bitcoin 
has a wide range of interesting applications and that cryptoassets are well suited to become an 
important asset class. (JEL G23, E50, E59) </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis Review, First Quarter 2018, 100(1), pp. 1-16. 
https://doi.org/10.20955/r.2018.1-16 </p>

<p>Aleksander Berentsen is a research fellow at the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis and a professor of economic theory at the University of Basel. 
Fabian Schär is managing director of the Center for Innovative Finance at the Faculty of Business and Economics, University of Basel. </p>

<p>© 2018, Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. The views expressed in this article are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of 
the Federal Reserve System, the Board of Governors, or the regional Federal Reserve Banks. Articles may be reprinted, reproduced, published, 
distributed, displayed, and transmitted in their entirety if copyright notice, author name(s), and full citation are included. Abstracts, synopses, 
and other derivative works may be made only with prior written permission of the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis. </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 1 </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>2 First Quarter 2018 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>of value circulating in the economy are always clearly established, without a central authority 
needing to keep accounts. Furthermore, any agent can participate in a cash payment system; 
nobody can be excluded. There is a permissionless access to it. Cash, however, also has disad-
vantages. Buyers and sellers have to be physically present at the same location in order to 
trade, which in many situations makes its use impracticable. </p>

<p>1.2 Digital Cash </p>

<p>An ideal payment system would be one in which monetary value could be transferred 
electronically via cash data files (Figure 2). Such cash data files retain the advantages of physical 
cash but would be able to circulate freely on electronic networks. 1 A data file of this type could 
be sent via email or social media channels. 
A specific feature of electronic data is that it can be copied any number of times at negli-
gible cost. This feature is highly undesirable for money. If cash data files can be copied and 
the duplicates used as currency, they cannot serve as a payment instrument. This problem is 
termed the "double spending problem." </p>

<p>1.3 Electronic Payment Systems </p>

<p>To counteract the problem of double spending, classical electronic payment systems are 
based on a central authority that verifies the legitimacy of the payments and keeps track of 
the current state of ownership. In such systems, a central authority (usually a bank) manages 
the accounts of buyers and sellers. The buyer initiates a payment by submitting an order. The </p>

<p>Goods </p>

<p>Cash transaction </p>

<p>Buyer 
Seller </p>

<p>Figure 1 </p>

<p>Cash Transaction </p>

<p>Goods </p>

<p>Electronic payment </p>

<p>Buyer 
Seller </p>

<p>Ctrl 
C </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Figure 2 </p>

<p>Electronic Payment </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 3 </p>

<p>central authority then ensures that the buyer has the necessary funds and adjusts the accounts 
accordingly (Figure 3). 
Centralized payment systems solve the double spending problem, but they require trust. 
Agents must trust that the central authority does not misuse the delegated power and that it 
maintains the books correctly in any state of the world-that is, that the banker is not running 
away with the money. Furthermore, centralized systems are vulnerable to hacker attacks, 
technical failures, and malicious governments that can easily interfere and confiscate funds. </p>

<p>1.4 Stone Money of Yap </p>

<p>The key feature of the Bitcoin system is the absence of a centrally managed ledger. There 
is no central authority with an exclusive right to keep accounts. In order to understand how 
this is possible, we will first discuss a historical payment system that has certain similarities 
with the Bitcoin system. 
On Yap Island, large millstone-like stones were used as a medium of exchange. 2 The 
stones were quarried almost 280 miles away on the island of Palau and brought to Yap by 
small boats. Every inhabitant could bring new stone money units into the system. The money 
creation costs, in the form of labor effort and equipment such as boats, protected the economy 
from inflation. 
Instead of having to laboriously move the stones, which are up to 13 feet in diameter, 
with every transaction from a buyer's front yard to a seller's front yard, the ownership rights 
were transferred virtually. A stone remained at its original location, and the unit of value could 
be detached from it and circulated irrespective of the stone's whereabouts. It was sufficient 
that all the inhabitants knew who the owner of every stone was. The separation between the 
unit of value and the stone went so far that even the unit of value for stones that were lost at 
sea remained in circulation. The stone money of Yap can therefore be described as a quasi-
virtual currency, as each unit of value was only loosely linked to a physical object. </p>

<p>Goods </p>

<p>Payment </p>

<p>Buyer 
Seller </p>

<p>Bookkeeper </p>

<p>Payment 
Payment 
Balance </p>

<p>Figure 3 </p>

<p>Payment System with a Central Authority </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>4 First Quarter 2018 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>The Yap system was based on a distributed ledger, in which every inhabitant would keep 
track of a stone's ownership. When a buyer made a purchase, this person told his or her neigh-
bors that the stone now belonged to the seller. The neighbors then spread the news until finally 
all of the island's inhabitants had been informed about the change in ownership (Figure 4). 
Through this communication, every islander had a precise idea of which unit of value belonged 
to which person at any point in time. 
In its essential features, the Yap payment system is very similar to the Bitcoin system. A 
major difference is that in the Yap system false reports could not be immediately identified, 
so conflicts regarding the current state of the implicit ledger would have to be argued and 
settled by the group. The Yap system therefore was restricted to a group of manageable size 
with close relationships, in which misconduct could be punished by the group. In contrast, 
the Bitcoin system is designed to function in a network where no participant can trust any 
other participant. This feature is necessary because it is a permissionless payment system in 
which participants can remain anonymous through the use of pseudonyms. </p>

<p>1.5 Bitcoin and the Bitcoin Blockchain </p>

<p>Bitcoin is a virtual monetary unit and therefore has no physical representation. A Bitcoin 
unit is divisible and can be divided into 100 million "Satoshis," the smallest fraction of a Bitcoin. 
The Bitcoin Blockchain is a data file that carries the records of all past Bitcoin transactions, 
including the creation of new Bitcoin units. It is often referred to as the ledger of the Bitcoin </p>

<p>Goods </p>

<p>Stone ownership </p>

<p>Buyer 
Seller </p>

<p>Communication </p>

<p>Figure 4 </p>

<p>Payment System with a Distributed Ledger </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 5 </p>

<p>system. The Bitcoin Blockchain consists of a sequence of blocks where each block builds on 
its predecessors and contains information about new Bitcoin transactions. The average time 
between Bitcoin blocks is 10 minutes. The first block, block #0, was created in 2009; and, at 
the time of this writing, block #494600 was appended as the most recent block to the chain. 
Because everyone can download and read the Bitcoin Blockchain, it is a public record, a ledger 
that contains Bitcoin ownership information for any point in time. 
The word "ledger" has to be qualified here. There is no single instance of the Bitcoin 
Blockchain. Instead, every participant is free to manage his or her own copy of the ledger. 
As it was with the stone money, there is no central authority with an exclusive right to keep 
accounts. Instead, there is a predefined set of rules and the opportunity for individuals to 
monitor that other participants adhere to the rules. The notion of "public record of ownership" 
also has to be qualified because the owners of Bitcoin units usually remain anonymous through 
the use of pseudonyms. 
To use the Bitcoin system, an agent downloads a Bitcoin wallet. A <rs type="software">Bitcoin wallet</rs> is soft-
ware that allows the receiving, storing, and sending of (fractions of) Bitcoin units. 3 The next 
step is to exchange fiat currencies, such as the U.S. dollar, for Bitcoin units. The most common 
way is to open an account at one of the many Bitcoin exchanges and to transfer fiat currency 
to it. The account holder can then use these funds to buy Bitcoin units or one of the many 
other cryptoassets on the exchange. Due to the widespread adoption of Bitcoin, the pricing 
on large exchanges is very competitive with relatively small bid-ask spreads. Most exchanges 
provide order books and many other financial tools that make the trading process transparent. 
A Bitcoin transaction works in a way that is similar to a transaction in the Yap payment 
system. A buyer broadcasts to the network that a seller's Bitcoin address is the new owner of 
a specific Bitcoin unit. This information is distributed on the network until all nodes are 
informed about the ownership transfer. We will examine some technical details of this step 
in Section 2. 
For a virtual currency to function, it is crucial to establish at every point in time how 
many monetary units exist, as well as how many new units have been created. There must 
also be a consensus mechanism that ensures that all participants agree about the ownership 
rights to the virtual currency units. In small communities, as with the Yap islanders, everyone 
knows everyone else. The participants care about their reputation, and conflicts can be dis-
puted directly. In contrast, within the Bitcoin system the number of participants is substan-
tially larger, and network participants can remain anonymous. Consequently, reputation 
effects cannot be expected to have a significant positive impact, and coordination becomes 
very difficult. Instead, there is a consensus mechanism that allows the Bitcoin system to reach 
an agreement. This consensus mechanism is the core innovation of the Bitcoin system and 
allows consensus to be reached on a larger scale and in the absence of any personal relations. </p>

<p>1.6 Bitcoin Mining </p>

<p>To understand the consensus mechanism of the Bitcoin system, we first have to discuss 
the role of a miner. A miner collects pending Bitcoin transactions, verifies their legitimacy, 
and assembles them into what is known as a "block candidate." The goal is to earn newly cre-</p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>ated Bitcoin units through this activity. The miner can succeed in doing this if he or she can 
convince all other network participants to add his or her block candidate to their copies of 
the Bitcoin Blockchain. 
Bitcoin mining is permissionless. Anyone can become a miner by downloading the respec-
tive software and the most recent copy of the Bitcoin Blockchain. In practice, however, there 
are a few large miners that produce most of the new generally accepted blocks. The reason is 
that competition has become fierce and only large mining farms with highly specialized hard-
ware and access to cheap electricity can still make a profit from mining. 
For a block candidate to be generally accepted, it must fulfill a specific set of predefined 
criteria. For instance, all included transactions must be legitimate. Another important crite-
rion is the so-called "fingerprint" of the block candidate. A miner obtains this fingerprint by 
computing the block candidate's hash value using the hash function dSHA256. 
For example, we will look at the hash value for the text, "Federal Reserve Bank of Saint 
Louis." The fingerprint of this text, which was calculated using the hash function dSHA256, is </p>

<p>72641707ba7c9be334f111ef5238f4a0b355481796fdddfdaac4c5f2320eea68. </p>

<p>Now notice the small change in the original text to "federal Reserve Bank of Saint Louis." It 
will cause an unpredictable change of the fingerprint, which can be seen from the correspond-
ing new hash value: </p>

<p>423f5dd7246de6faf8b839c41bf46d303014cffa65724ab008431514e36c4dba. </p>

<p>As suggested by this example, a data file's hash value cannot be prognosticated. 
This characteristic is employed in the mining process as follows. For a block candidate to 
be accepted by all miners, its fingerprint must possess an extremely rare feature: The hash 
value must be below a certain threshold value-that is, it must display several zeroes at the 
beginning of the fingerprint. An example of a fingerprint of a block that was added to the 
Bitcoin Blockchain in 2010 is given in the following example: </p>

<p>Block #69785 (July 23rd, 2010, 12:09:36 CET) </p>

<p>0000000000 </p>

<p>Need to be zero </p>

<p>1 2 
4 
3 
4 293b78a2833b45d78e97625 f 6484ddd1accbe0067c2b8 f 98b57995 </p>

<p>Miners are continuously trying to find block candidates that have a hash value satisfying the 
above mentioned criterion. For this purpose, a block includes a data field (called the nonce) 
that contains arbitrary data. Miners modify this arbitrary data in order to gain a new finger-
print. These modifications do not affect the set of included transactions. Just as with our 
example, every modification results in a new hash value. Most of the time, the hash value lies 
above the threshold value, and the miner discards the block candidate. If, however, a miner 
succeeds in creating a block candidate with a hash value below the current threshold value, 
he or she broadcasts the block candidate as quickly as possible to the network. All the other 
network participants can then easily verify that the fingerprint satisfies the threshold criterion 
by computing it themselves. </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 7 </p>

<p>1.7 Consensus Mechanism </p>

<p>The consensus among miners is that every miner who receives a block candidate with a 
valid fingerprint adds it to his or her own copy of the Bitcoin Blockchain. From a game theo-
retical perspective, a strategy profile where all miners add valid blocks to their own copies of 
the Bitcoin Blockchain is a Nash equilibrium. If a miner believes that all other miners are act-
ing accordingly, then it is a best response for that miner to add a valid block candidate to his 
or her own copy of the Bitcoin Blockchain. A deviation is not worthwhile, because it is not 
profitable to work on a version of the Bitcoin Blockchain that is not generally accepted. Any 
reward for finding blocks on a version of the chain that is not accepted by anyone else is worth-
less. Thus, although there is no authority enforcing this rule and miners are free to modify 
their copy of the Blockchain as they wish, there is a strong incentive to follow this rule. This 
self-enforcing rule allows the network to maintain consensus about the ownership of all 
Bitcoin units. 4  Mining is expensive, as the computations use large amounts of electricity and are increas-
ingly dependent on highly specialized hardware. Moreover, valid block candidates can be 
found only through a trial-and-error procedure. The consensus mechanism is therefore called 
"proof of work." If a miner finds a valid fingerprint for a block candidate, then this is proof 
that he or she has, on average, performed a large number of costly computations. Adding 
false information (e.g., illegitimate transactions) to a block candidate would render the block 
candidate invalid and essentially waste all the computations. Finding a valid fingerprint is 
therefore proof that the miner helped to maintain the Bitcoin system. </p>

<p>1.8 Monetary Policy </p>

<p>Every payment system needs rules that regulate how new monetary units are produced 
(or destroyed). The Bitcoin network is calibrated in such a way that, on average, a block can-
didate with a valid hash value is found every 10 minutes. The winner of the mining contest 
receives a predefined number of newly created Bitcoin units. The number currently is 12.5. 
In the Bitcoin system, money creation is scheduled so that the number of Bitcoin units 
will converge to 21 million units (Figure 5). This limit exists because the reward for the miners 
is halved every 210,000 blocks (approximately every four years). Correspondingly, miners 
will be increasingly rewarded through transaction fees. But even today, the quick processing 
of a transaction can be guaranteed only if an adequate fee is paid to incentivize the miners to 
include the transaction in their block candidates. 
Most Bitcoin users believe that Bitcoin's limited supply will result in deflation. That is, 
they are convinced that its value will forever increase. Indeed, up to this point we have wit-
nessed a spectacular price increase from essentially a value of $0 for one Bitcoin unit in 2009 
to a value of $7,000 at the time of this writing (Figure 6). 
Nonetheless, these beliefs need to be challenged. Bitcoin units have no intrinsic value. 
Because of this, the present price of the currency is determined solely by expectations about 
its future price. A buyer is willing to buy a Bitcoin unit only if he or she assumes that the unit 
will sell for at least the same price later on. The price of Bitcoin, therefore, reacts highly elas-</p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>2010 
2015 
2020 
2025 
2030 
2035 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Bitcoins In Circulation (millions) </p>

<p>Figure 5 </p>

<p>Bitcoins in Circulation: Scheduled to Converge to 21 Million Units </p>

<p>Price (USD) </p>

<p>2010 
2012 
2014 
2016 
2018 </p>

<p>6,000 </p>

<p>4,000 </p>

<p>2,000 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 6 </p>

<p>Market Price in U.S. Dollars (USD) for One Bitcoin Unit </p>

<p>SOURCE: Blockchain.info. </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 9 </p>

<p>tically to changes in the expectations of market participants and is reflected in extreme price 
volatility. From monetary theory, we know that currencies with no intrinsic value have many 
equilibrium prices. 5 One of them is always zero. If all market participants expect that Bitcoin 
will have no value in the future, then no one is willing to pay anything for it today. 
However, Bitcoin is not the only currency that has no intrinsic value. State monopoly 
currencies, such as the U.S. dollar, the euro, and the Swiss franc, have no intrinsic value either. 
They are fiat currencies created by government decree. The history of state monopoly curren-
cies is a history of wild price swings and failures. This is why decentralized cryptocurrencies 
are a welcome addition to the existing currency system. 
In the Bitcoin system, the path for the money supply is predetermined by the Bitcoin 
protocol written in 2008 and early 2009. Since then, many changes have been applied to the 
Bitcoin protocol. Most of these changes are not controversial and have improved the function-
ing of the Bitcoin system. However, in principle all aspects of the Bitcoin protocol can be 
amended, including the money supply. Many Bitcoin critics see this as a major shortcoming. 
Theoretically speaking, this is correct. Any network participant can decide to follow a new set 
of rules and, for example, double the amount of newly created "Bitcoin" units in his or her 
version of the ledger. Such a modification, however, is of no value because convincing all the 
other network participants to follow this new set of rules will be almost impossible. If the 
change of the protocol is not supported unanimously, there will be a so-called fork, a split in 
the network, which results in two co-existing blockchains and essentially creates a new crypto-
asset. In this case, there would be Bitcoin (the original) and Bitcoin42 (a possible name for an 
alternative implementation with an upper bound of 42 million Bitcoin42 units). The market 
would price the original and the newly created Bitcoin42 assets according to the community's 
expectations and support. Therefore, even though in theory it is possible to increase the Bitcoin 
supply, in practice, such a change is very unlikely because a large part of the Bitcoin commu-
nity would strongly oppose such an attempt. 
Moreover, the same critique can be raised against any current government-operated fiat 
currency system. For example, since the Second World War, many central banks have become 
independent in order to shield them from political interference that yielded some undesirable 
outcomes. This independence has been given to them by the respective parliaments or related 
institutions and can be taken away if politicians decide accordingly. Political interference in 
the fiat currency system can be interpreted as a change in the "fiat currency protocol." Undesir-
able changes in fiat currency protocols are very common and many times have led to the com-
plete destruction of the value of the fiat currency at hand. It could be argued that, in some 
ways, the Bitcoin protocol is more robust than many of the existing fiat currency protocols. 
Only time will tell. </p>

<p>2 BITCOIN TRANSACTIONS </p>

<p>The complexity of the present material is due to interdisciplinarity. To understand the 
Bitcoin system, it is necessary to combine elements from the three disciplines of economics, 
cryptography, and computer science (Figure 7). </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>Having presented a broad overview of 
the Bitcoin system, we will explain a few 
technical elements of the system in greater 
detail. Blockchain uses proven technologies 
and links these in an innovative way. This 
combination has made the decentralized 
management of a ledger possible for the 
first time. 
Berentsen and Schär (2017) argue that 
transaction processing demands that three 
requirements are satisfied: (1) transaction 
capability, (2) transaction legitimacy, and 
(3) transaction consensus. These three 
requirements will now be considered. In 
particular, we will explain how these con-
ditions can be satisfied in the absence of a 
central authority. </p>

<p>2.1 Transaction Capability </p>

<p>What has to be resolved is how transactions can be initiated if there is no central authority. 
In a classical banking system, a client talks to his or her advisor or submits his or her payment 
instructions via the bank's online banking service. The infrastructure provided by the com-
mercial bank and other central service providers ensures that the transaction will be commu-
nicated for execution. In the absence of a central authority, communicating a payment order 
in this traditional sense is not possible. 
In the Bitcoin system, a payment order can be communicated to any number of network 
nodes. The network nodes are linked together in a loose network and forward the message 
until all nodes have been informed about the transaction (Figure 8). 
The decentralization of the system has many advantages. In particular, it makes the system 
extremely robust. There is neither a central point of failure that can be attacked nor any system-
relevant nodes that could cause the system to collapse. Therefore, the system functions even 
when some network nodes are unreachable, and it can always establish new connections and 
communication channels. </p>

<p>2.2 Transaction Legitimacy </p>

<p>Every participant can generate new payment orders and spread them across the network. 
This feature carries the risk of fraudulent messages. In this respect, there are two important 
questions that arise: 
1. How do the nodes know that the initiator of the transaction is the rightful owner and 
that he or she is thereby entitled to transfer the Bitcoin units? 
2. How can one ensure that the transaction message will not be tampered with before it 
is passed from one node to the next? </p>

<p>Cryptography </p>

<p>Economics 
Computer 
Science </p>

<p>Figure 7 </p>

<p>Interdisciplinarity </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 11 </p>

<p>Edith </p>

<p>Edith: "I transfer 1 Bitcoin 
unit to Daniel. " </p>

<p>Edith's message is repeated. </p>

<p>Marcia 
Brian </p>

<p>Jake </p>

<p>Claudia 
Michèle </p>

<p>Tony </p>

<p>Figure 8 </p>

<p>Bitcoin Transaction Communicated to Network Nodes </p>

<p>Edith </p>

<p>Edith: "I transfer 1 Bitcoin 
unit to Daniel. " </p>

<p>Manipulation attempt </p>

<p>Marcia </p>

<p>Michèle </p>

<p>Tony </p>

<p>Edith: "I transfer 1 Bitcoin 
unit to Tony. " 
Refused! </p>

<p>Figure 9 </p>

<p>Bitcoin Transaction Manipulation Attempt </p>

<p>Edith </p>

<p>Edith: "I transfer Bitcoin 
unit X to Daniel. " </p>

<p>Transaction A </p>

<p>Marcia 
Brian </p>

<p>Jake </p>

<p>Claudia 
Michèle </p>

<p>Tony </p>

<p>Edith: "I transfer Bitcoin 
unit X to Lucas. " </p>

<p>Transaction B </p>

<p>Figure 10 </p>

<p>First Bitcoin Transaction Added to a Valid Block Candidate Is Confirmed </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>In the Bitcoin system, transaction legitimacy is guaranteed using asymmetric cryptography. 6  The idea is based on using pairs of keys consisting of a private and a public key. A private key 
should not be shared. It corresponds to a random value from an incredibly large set of num-
bers. A public key, on the other hand, is derived from that number and can be shared freely. 
It serves as a pseudonym in the Bitcoin network. 7  A private key is used to encrypt a message that can be decrypted only by using its corre-
sponding public key. This type of encryption is also known as a "signature." The signature 
clarifies that this approach is not used to hide any of the information in the encrypted message. 
Anyone can simply decrypt a message using its public key, but the signature serves as proof 
that the message has been previously encrypted using its corresponding private key; it's like a 
handwritten signature but much more secure. 
For example, consider Edith, who wants to send a Bitcoin payment to Daniel over the 
Bitcoin network. She uses her private key to encrypt the message. The other network partici-
pants can only decrypt this message using Edith's public key. If an attempt is successful, it 
ensures that the message was encrypted using the corresponding private key. Because no one 
else has access to Edith's private key, this approach can be used to validate the transaction's 
origin (Figure 9). 
When the transaction circulates in the network, any network participant can decrypt this 
message and is in the position to subsequently change the payment instructions. However, 
because the participant does not possess Edith's private key, he or she cannot re-encrypt the 
manipulated message. The tampered transaction will therefore be identified and rejected by 
the rest of the network. </p>

<p>2.3 Transaction Consensus </p>

<p>We have now discussed how a transaction message is communicated and how its legitimacy 
and origin can be verified. We have also explained how consensus regarding ownership of 
the Bitcoin units is achieved in the Bitcoin network by using the proof-of-work consensus 
protocol. 
However, Edith would be able to generate two transactions that both reference the same 
Bitcoin units. Both transactions could be propagated simultaneously over the network (trans-
action capability), and both would display a valid origin (transaction legitimacy). Because of 
differences in the propagation of these two messages in the Bitcoin network, some of the nodes 
would first receive a message for transaction A while others would first receive a message for 
transaction B (Figure 10). In order to avoid double spending, it is important that only one of 
the two transactions finds its way into the Bitcoin Blockchain. A mechanism that decides 
which of the two transactions gets included in the Blockchain is therefore necessary. 
The Bitcoin system solves this double spending problem in a clever way. The transaction 
that is first added to a valid block candidate, and therefore added to the Blockchain, is con-
sidered confirmed. The system ceases to process the other one-that is, miners will stop add-
ing the conflicting transaction to their block candidates. Moreover, it is not possible for a 
miner to add conflicting transactions to the same block candidate. Such a block would be 
illegitimate and thus be rejected by all the other network participants. </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 13 </p>

<p>3 OUTLOOK </p>

<p>As with any fundamental innovation, the true potential of blockchain technology will 
become apparent only many years, or possibly decades, after it becomes generally adopted. 
Forecasting the areas in which blockchain technology will be used to the greatest effect is there-
fore not possible. We nevertheless would like to mention a few areas where blockchain tech-
nology serves as an infrastructure platform that facilitates a variety of promising applications. </p>

<p>3.1 Cryptoassets </p>

<p>The most apparent application is Bitcoin as an asset. It is likely that cryptoassets such as 
Bitcoin will emerge as their own asset class and thus have the potential to develop into an 
interesting investment and diversification instrument. Bitcoin itself could over time assume 
a similar role as gold. Moreover, the potential for trading securities on a public blockchain is 
large. So-called colored coins can be traded on the Bitcoin (or similar) Blockchain and used 
in smart contracts, as described below. </p>

<p>3.2 Colored Coins </p>

<p>A colored coin is a promise of payment that is linked to a Bitcoin transaction. This promise 
is possible because the communication protocol of the Bitcoin network allows additional 
information to be tied to a transaction. For example, promises for the delivery of an ounce 
of gold or a dividend payment can be added to a Bitcoin transaction and represented on the 
Bitcoin Blockchain. Any of these promises are of course subject to issuer risks and require 
some extent of trust. This is in sharp contrast to native cryptoassets such as Bitcoin units. </p>

<p>3.3 Smart Contracts </p>

<p>Smart contracts are self-executing contracts. 8 They can be used to stipulate that a Bitcoin 
payment will be executed only when a certain condition is met. The Ethereum network is cur-
rently the leader in the field of smart contracts. Similar to Bitcoin, it is based on blockchain 
technology and provides a native cryptoasset, called Ether. In contrast to Bitcoin, Ethereum 
provides a more flexible scripting language and is able to track contractual states. Potential 
applications include but are not limited to e-voting systems, identity management and decen-
tralized organization, and various forms of fundraising (e.g., initial coin offerings). </p>

<p>3.4 Data Integrity </p>

<p>Another application for public blockchains is the potential to monitor data files. We have 
already shown how fingerprints of block candidates play an important role in the Bitcoin 
network. The same technology can be used to produce fingerprints for all kinds of data files 
and then store them in a blockchain. The entry of a fingerprint into a blockchain ensures that 
any manipulation attempt will become apparent because any change to the data file will lead 
to a completely different hash value. Because it is very difficult to change a blockchain retro-
actively, a fingerprint can serve as proof that a specific data file existed at a specific point in 
time and ensures the integrity of the data. </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>

<p>4 RISKS </p>

<p>Much like any other key innovation, blockchain technology introduces some risks. The 
following sections will consider some of these risks. As we mentioned in Section 3, we would 
like to note that this list is non-exhaustive. </p>

<p>4.1 Forks </p>

<p>As discussed in Section 1.8, the Bitcoin protocol can be altered if the network participants, 
or at least a sufficient number of them, agree on the suggested modification. It can happen 
(and in fact has happened) that a blockchain splits because various groups cannot agree about 
a modification. A split that persists is referred to as a "fork." The two best-known examples 
of persistent splits are the Bitcoin Cash fork and Ethereum's ideological dissent, which resulted 
in the split to Ethereum and Ethereum Classic. </p>

<p>4.2 Energy Wastage </p>

<p>Proof-of-work mining is expensive, as it uses a great deal of energy. There are those that 
criticize Bitcoin and assert that a centralized accounting system is more efficient because con-
sensus can be attained without the allocation of massive amounts of computational power. 
From our perspective, however, the situation is not so clear-cut. Centralized payment systems 
are also expensive. Besides infrastructure and operating costs, one would have to calculate 
the explicit and implicit costs of a central bank. Salary costs should be counted among the 
explicit costs and the possibility of fraud in the currency monopoly among the implicit costs. 
Moreover, many cryptoassets use alternative consensus protocols, which do not (solely) rely 
on computational resources. </p>

<p>4.3 Bitcoin Price Volatility </p>

<p>The price of Bitcoin is highly volatile. This leads us to the question of whether the rigid 
predetermined supply of Bitcoin is a desirable monetary policy in the sense that it leads to a 
stable currency. The answer is no because the price of Bitcoin also depends on aggregate demand. 
If a constant supply of money meets a fluctuating aggregate demand, the result is fluctuating 
prices. In government-run fiat currency systems, the central bank aims to adjust the money 
supply in response to changes in aggregate demand for money in order to stabilize the price 
level. In particular, the Federal Reserve System has been explicitly founded "to provide an 
elastic currency" to mitigate the price fluctuations that arise from changes in the aggregate 
demand for the U.S. dollar. Since such a mechanism is absent in the current Bitcoin protocol, it 
is very likely that the Bitcoin unit will display much higher short-term price fluctuations than 
many government-run fiat currency units. </p>

<p>5 CONCLUSION </p>

<p>The Bitcoin creators' intention was to develop a decentralized cash-like electronic payment 
system. In this process, they faced the fundamental challenge of how to establish and transfer </p>

<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p>Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW 
First Quarter 2018 15 </p>

<p>digital property rights of a monetary unit without a central authority. They solved this challenge 
by inventing the Bitcoin Blockchain. This novel technology allows us to store and transfer a 
monetary unit without the need for a central authority, similar to cash. 
Price volatility and scaling issues frequently raise concerns about the suitability of Bitcoin 
as a payment instrument. As an asset, however, Bitcoin and alternative blockchain-based 
tokens should not be neglected. The innovation makes it possible to represent digital property 
without the need for a central authority. This can lead to the creation of a new asset class that 
can mature into a valuable portfolio diversification instrument. Moreover, blockchain tech-
nology provides an infrastructure that enables numerous applications. Promising applications 
include using colored coins, smart contracts, and the possibility of using fingerprints to secure 
the integrity of data files in a blockchain, which may bring change to the world of finance 
and to many other sectors. n </p>

<p>NOTES </p>

<p>1 An initial attempt was DigiCash in the 1990s; however, it was not able to establish itself. </p>

<p>2 See Furness (1910) who describes the Island of Stone Money. </p>

<p>3 Strictly speaking, Bitcoins are not "traveling" on the Bitcoin network. A Bitcoin payment is simply a message that 
is broadcasted to the network to communicate a change in ownership of the respective Bitcoin units. </p>

<p>4 In practice, a split in the Blockchain may occur if the network participants do not agree about changes in the 
Bitcoin protocol (i.e., the rule set). This issue is discussed further in this article. </p>

<p>5 See Kiyotaki and Wright (1993) for a search theoretic approach to money, Berentsen (1998) for a study of the 
acceptability of digital money, and Nosal and Rocheteau (2011) for a comprehensive introduction into the search 
theoretic approach to monetary economics. </p>

<p>6 Similar technologies are also used in traditional electronic payment systems and in many other fields, such as 
with online banking and shopping. </p>

<p>7 In fact, a public key is usually used to derive a so-called Bitcoin address. This address is then used as a pseudonym. 
We ignored this additional step to keep things as simple as possible. Both operations-that is, private key to public 
key and public key to Bitcoin address-are one-way functions. There is no known way to reverse these operations, 
so it is not feasible to obtain a private key from a corresponding pseudonym. </p>

<p>8 For an introduction to smart contracts and potential business applications, see Schär and Langer (2017). </p>



<p>Berentsen and Schär </p>

<p> 
Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis REVIEW </p>



</text></tei>