<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fjbem.2010.28" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:22+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. In this paper we consider the idea of negotiations conducted by means of the 
software support tools. We present the advantages of the negotiation support systems 
discussing their different functions and typologies focusing later on the possibilities of 
decision support they can give to the negotiating parties in all negotiation phases. After 
presenting the most popular solutions we introduce also two of our own procedures that 
can be applied in the pre-negotiation phase for eliciting negotiators' preferences and build-
ing the offers' scoring systems for the parties. The first one is based on the Hammond, 
Keeney and Raiffa's procedure of even swaps, while the second derives from the Roy's 
ELECTRE-TRI. Both of them can be easily applied as the analytic engines in electronic 
negotiation systems replacing the classical additive scoring systems. We discuss also the 
issue of using different scoring systems in the successive negotiation phases. </p>

<p>Negotiation is an everyday task. Except for simple and typical situations like discussing 
the task shared in a family (i.e. walking the dog, cleaning the apartment, etc.) influenc-
ing someone to change their mind or dividing the scarce resources, it includes also 
the complex deliberations between the companies, political parties or nations. We can 
describe negotiation situation as the problem of making decision about parties' interde-
pendent goals and objectives (Lewicki et al. 1999). Moreover, the parties are committed 
to peaceful means of solving the problem and there is no clear or established method of 
making the decision. Usually, while thinking of the negotiation we consider a regular 
face-to-face meeting where the parties are sitting at the negotiation table and solving 
the problem using some advisors, analysts, facilitators or mediators. But we live in the 
time of technological explosion, and nowadays it influences nearly all the activities </p>



<p>undertaken by humans, including negotiation. Negotiations are consequently being con-
ducted by means of the electronic media, starting with simple phone calls, through the 
videoconferences, online chatting, with the use of software negotiation support system 
(NSS), ending with the electronic negotiation system (ENS) -a software that employs 
Internet technologies and is deployed on the web for the purpose of facilitating, organ-
izing, supporting and/or automating activities undertaken by the negotiators and/or the 
third party (Kersten and Lai 2007). More and more people and organizations are decid-
ing to negotiate electronically, since it saves time and money and allows to develop and 
maintain the business contacts regardless of the distance of time and space between the 
counterparts. Therefore, the negotiation support tools are still being developed to make 
the negotiation process more fluent and bring negotiators closer to the most satisfying 
agreement. Usually, these systems implement the formal models deriving from opera-
tional research and decision science that are used to help negotiators define negotiation 
space, evaluate offers and determine efficient solutions. There are a lot of NSSs and 
ENSs that have been used for simulating, training and teaching negotiations or for 
research purposes like <rs id="software-12" type="software">INSPIRE</rs> (Kersten and Noronha <rs corresp="#software-12" type="version-date">1999</rs>), <rs id="software-13" type="software">Negoisst</rs> (Schoop et al. 
<rs corresp="#software-13" type="version-date">2003</rs>), NeGoGo (Lai et al. 2007) or <rs id="software-14" type="software">NegoCalc</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-14" type="creator">Wachowicz</rs> <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-date">2008</rs>). Lots of theoretical 
and practical solutions for electronic negotiation support are also proposed in the lit-
erature, that focuse on both the methodological and applicational aspects of electronic 
negotiations (see Stroebel and Weinhardt 2003; Urbanavičienė et al. 2009a, b). Unfor-
tunately, there are only a few examples of using the formal models and systems in the 
large and complex real-world negotiations of business or political nature. One of them 
was introducing the Deep Ocean Mining Model into the United Nations' UNCLOS III 
negotiations (Sebenius 1984) concerning the rights to exploit the deep sea. It allowed 
to make a consensus between the developed and developing countries according to the 
profits sharing. Another system, developed by International Institute for Applied System 
Analysis, is RAINS (Hordijk 1991), which was used in the international negotiations 
between the European countries on the air pollution limits. Some other systems are still 
being developed to support real-world problems like <rs id="software-16" type="software">Familly_Winner</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-16" type="creator">Bellucci and Zeleznikow</rs> <rs corresp="#software-16" type="version-date">2005</rs>) designed on Victoria University, Australia, for supporting divorcing 
disputes or <rs id="software-17" type="software">Smartsettle</rs> (Thiessen and Soberg <rs corresp="#software-17" type="version-date">2003</rs>), which is now being adapted to 
support negotiations between First Nations and the Government of Alberta Province in 
Canada (Thiessen and Shakun 2009). </p>

<p>In this paper we describe the negotiation process supported by NSS and ENS with 
considering all the subsequent negotiation phases and activities required within each 
phase and the support that can be given by the software systems. In the first section 
we discuss the fundamental elements of negotiation process and analyze the different 
types of NSSs that can be used for supporting different aspects of negotiation process. 
In the successive sections we consider the subsequent negotiation phases. Considering 
the pre-negotiation phase we focus on negotiators' preference elicitation and process of 
building offers' scoring systems that require formal modeling and usually implement 
an additive scoring system. We also propose two alternative solutions that can be intro-
duced instead of classical additive scoring system. Next we describe the support that </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>can be given within the actual negotiation phase for exchanging the messages and offers 
and analyzing the negotiation progress. Afterwards, we analyze the post-negotiation 
mechanisms that can be introduced by NSS to help negotiators evaluate the compromise 
and find better solutions. </p>

<p>2. Negotiations and negotiation software support </p>

<p>2.1. Negotiation process </p>

<p>In vast majority of situations the basis of negotiation is some form of conflict. But 
negotiation and conflict are not the same thing. As far as conflict is the perception 
of differences of interest among people, negotiation is a decision making process in 
which two or many people make joint decision about the allocation of scarce resources 
(Thompson 1998). Since we perceive negotiation as a decision making process we need 
to be aware of multitude tasks the parties must accomplish to obtain the satisfying so-
lution. Negotiators need to understand the essence of the conflict (i.e. to diagnose the 
negotiation problem), gather all information required (e.g. about the problem, parties, 
possible solutions) and process it to manage the negotiation process well (e.g. analyze 
the counterpart's personality, select negotiation strategies, etc.). Negotiation thus is a 
very complex activity, which requires from the parties many skills of the behavioral and 
analytical nature to cope with different problems that can appear during the negotiation 
process. This process in not uniform, and depending on the stage of the conflict it may 
require different tasks to perform or problems to solve. There are many proposals of 
dividing the negotiation process into separate phases (Douglas 1962; Morley and Ste-
phenson 1977). Some of them are quite general, like a six-phase model of Greenhalgh 
(2001) including preparing, relation building, information gathering, information using, 
submitting offers, closing and implementing agreement; others are specific to nego-
tiation problems or context, like Four-Phase Model of Hostage Negotiation (Madrigal 
et al. 2009) that consists of establishing initial dialogue, building rapport, influencing, 
and Surrender; or a five phases model for negotiating transactions (Tafreschi et al. 2008) 
distinguishing the information, intention, agreement, execution and service phases. Here 
we will focus on a very general and straightforward categorization that allows to dis-
tinguish three main negotiation phases (Gulliver 1979): pre-negotiation phase, actual 
negotiation phase and post-negotiation phase. </p>

<p>2.1.1. Pre-negotiation phase </p>

<p>Pre-negotiation phase is in fact the preparation for negotiation. Preparing itself consists 
of some subsequent steps that should lead to a plan of action. The first step of pre-
negotiation phase is called the ideas stage (Scott 1999), which aim is to review the 
area of negotiation and the other party. Negotiators should gather all the data and facts 
describing the present situation between the parties and the essence of conflict. Within 
the second stage -analysis stage -the data is processed. Parties should identify the 
strengths and weaknesses of both their own and their counterparts. The goals, intentions, 
positions, expectations, aspiration and reservation levels and BATNAs of the parties 
should also be identified. It will lead to the construction of negotiation space, identifica-
tion of possible alternatives and determination of the zone of possible agreement (Raiffa </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>1982). Then in the last stage -organizing the meeting -the negotiators, facilitators and 
analysts are chosen, the negotiation place and agenda are also prepared. These three 
stages lead to formulating a direct plan, linking the overall goals with operational tactics 
which we call a negotiation strategy (Kuhn 1999). </p>

<p>2.1.2. Actual negotiation phase </p>

<p>This negotiation phase includes the main talks, offers exchange, making concessions 
and all the verbal and non-verbal endeavors that parties use to achieve a compromise 
(see Thompson 1998). This is a sequential process within which we can distinguish five 
different stages (elements). The first stage is the partner inquiry, which is necessary 
to find out the true intentions, emotions and position of a counterpart. The next, called 
mutual influencing, consists in revealing negotiators' views and emotions and is strongly 
connected with the third element -negotiation maneuvers -which includes all the 
specific tactics and techniques, both constructive and destructive ones, that are to move 
negotiators towards the aspired agreement (see Aaronson 1989). These three stages can 
be repeated iteratively but then stabilizing is required, which will lead the negotiators to 
the stage of reaching agreement that consists in exchanging the proposals for the final 
compromise. This entire process starting from the first offer and ending with the mutual 
agreement is also known as a negotiation dance (Raiffa 1982). </p>

<p>2.1.3. Post-negotiation phase </p>

<p>The last negotiation phase begins with the agreement concluding, which effects in writ-
ing an official contract and its execution (Lewicki et al. 2004). But this phase extends 
also to some other tasks, usually realized by the third party -facilitators or mediators, 
like analyzing the final compromise and looking for the gains that are left on the ne-
gotiation table. It is often conducted by means of formal models that help negotiators 
to evaluate the compromise and, using some elements of mathematical programming, 
find the effective solutions that dominate the current compromise. It is also the time for 
conclusions and summarizing the lessons learned that negotiators make use of during 
the future negotiations. </p>

<p>2.2. Negotiation support in the software negotiation system </p>

<p>The software systems may support different tasks at different stages of negotiation 
process. They can also act as a supportive tool for one negotiator only or have imple-
mented the procedures to support all of them, including the third party (i.e. facilitator 
or mediator). What is more, they can be either passive tools gathering and visualizing 
data or can act actively by processing the data, doing calculations, making simulations 
or suggesting some solutions. We will now focus on the ways of support that negotiation 
support systems may offer and present some categorization of such systems. </p>

<p>2.2.1. Support for negotiation phases and parties </p>

<p>Deriving form the three-phase negotiation model presented in the previous section and 
taking into account the parties involved in the negotiation process we can categorize 
negotiation support systems into four types (Kersten and Lai 2007): </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>1. Planning and preparation systems used mainly in the pre-negotiation phase. They 
are designed to support a single negotiator in analyzing private and public informa-
tion about the negotiation problem and context. They allow to build and evaluate 
the alternatives applying some scoring methods (e.g. utility based ones). They also 
support negotiator in formulating their negotiation strategies and tactics that they 
can apply later in the actual negotiation phase. 
2. Assessment systems used within all negotiation phases and support single party. 
They help in constructing offers, analyzing counter-offers and propose some alter-
native solutions. They allow to track negotiation progress by analyzing the conces-
sion paths. 
3. Intervention systems designed to support mediators or arbitrators in all the tasks 
they are supposed to undertake during the whole negotiation process. 
4. Process systems designed for supporting simultaneously all the negotiators. They 
act according to selected negotiation protocol and impose on negotiators specific 
organization of the negotiation process, including communication procedures, 
mechanisms for exchanging offers, etc. Usually they support all negotiation phases. </p>

<p>As we see NSSs can support different phases and actors of negotiation process but, 
simultaneously, it is also very important how they give this support. The negotiator's 
satisfaction from using the supporting system is significantly different if the system 
helps only to present or organize the data or if it offers advanced analytic mechanisms 
that allow him to act as an advisor or facilitator. Therefore we can consider NSSs taking 
into account the type of activity they offer. </p>

<p>The general scheme of support the NSS may offer to all the parties involved in the 
negotiation process is presented in a form of high level use case diagram in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. NSSs and their functions </p>

<p>Mediator/Facilitator </p>

<p>Arbitrating </p>

<p>Solving impasses </p>

<p>As se ss m en t sy st em s </p>

<p>P a la n in g 
p r e p a r a t io n </p>

<p>s y s t e m </p>

<p>&amp; </p>

<p>NSS 
Process 
systems </p>

<p>« 
» 
uses 
« 
» 
uses </p>

<p>Intervention 
systems 
Analyzing 
concessions </p>

<p>Constructing 
ff 
&amp; evaluating o ers </p>

<p>Suggesting 
solutions </p>

<p>De ning negotiation 
fi 
protocol 
Scoring o ers 
ff </p>

<p>Analyzing private &amp; 
public information </p>

<p>Formulating 
negotiation strategy </p>

<p>Negotiator </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>2.2.2. Activity of NSSs </p>

<p>Taking into account the scale of participation of supporting systems in the negotiation 
process, the three following types of system can be distinguished (Kersten 2005): 
1. Passive systems require users to control over their actions. If used for communica-
tion purposes they are simple messengers providing users with mechanisms for 
conducting the talks. If used for calculation they support negotiators in solving 
mathematical formulas required to compare the negotiation offers. They also help 
to display data on graphs or maps. These systems do not verify requirements and 
assumptions defined by users and expect all the data required to be provided by 
negotiators. 
2. Active facilitation-mediation systems support the whole decision making process 
in negotiations, starting with problem definition and structuring, and ending with 
producing the final results in the form of offers that can be suggested as the agree-
ment proposals. They support also concession-making process, and the final as-
sessment of the agreement. The models implemented in these systems take into 
consideration simultaneously the problem, the negotiators and the process. 
3. Pro-active intervention-mediation systems except for playing the role of active 
facilitation-mediation systems they also intervene in the process by suggesting to 
the parties some alternative solutions and coordinating their activities. They can 
monitor the concession path and stimulate the parties to act in the way that will 
bring them closer to the agreement. </p>

<p>2.2.3. Roles of NSSs </p>

<p>We know the different scale of support NSSs give in the successive negotiation phases 
and the degree of their participation in the negotiation process. The mix of these ele-
ments determines in fact the role NSS plays in the negotiations as a third party. We 
usually distinguish three major roles the third party can play in negotiation, which is 
a mediator, facilitator and analyst (expert). Therefore analyzing the role NSS plays in 
the negotiation process we can distinguish three types of negotiations (Kersten and 
Lai 2007): 
1. Computer-facilitated negotiations use software with communication and coordina-
tion components implemented only. The technology used do not affect the content 
of communications therefore the decision and concession making process depends 
only on the skills of the negotiators. In terms of decision support the system acts 
passively, however it can inform negotiators of the current stage of talks (e.g. 
send emails informing of new compromise proposals prepared by counterpart in 
the system). 
2. Computer-supported negotiations use software that can provide negotiators with 
the information they would not be able to obtain otherwise. This software affects 
the negotiation process and parties by organizing the negotiation activities and 
proposing individual mechanisms for analyzing the data and understanding the 
problem better, like simulation tool or preference elicitation engines. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>3. Computer-mediated negotiations use software that helps parties to achieve an 
agreement. This software not only supports individual tasks of negotiators but 
also their cognitive efforts. It tries to identify the potential conflicts by analyzing 
the moves of counterparts and redirects them by proposing them the concession 
and suggests the alternative compromises. </p>

<p>3. Pre-negotiation phase support </p>

<p>Having discussed the negotiation process and the general way of its support that can 
be given by software systems we will focus now on the details of decision support in 
successive negotiation phases. The decision support given by NSSs within the pre-
negotiation phase focuses mainly on the negotiators' preference elicitation and building 
the scoring system for offers evaluation. All the formal models required for such a sup-
port derive from the negotiation analysis (Young 1991; Raiffa 1982; Raiffa et al. 2002) 
which is a huge and modern trend within the decision science. The common idea of 
these models is to define the negotiation outcome quantitatively and use some methods 
from game theory and multiple attribute decision making to evaluate the implication 
of the potential solutions and find the efficient, fair or compromising agreement (Luce 
and Raiffa 1957; Keeney and Raiffa 1976; Brams 1990; Zeckhauser et al. 1996; Ham-
mond et al. 2002). We will discuss below a very popular MCDM model -the additive 
scoring model -that is usually applied in computer-supported negotiation to develop 
an assessment capabilities of NSSs. </p>

<p>3.1. Additive scoring systems </p>

<p>Additive scoring system is commonly used to evaluate negotiation offers in multi-issue 
negotiations. The fundamentals of this scoring method can be found in works of Keeney 
and Raiffa (Keeney and Raiffa 1976; Raiffa 1982; Keeney and Raiffa 1991). Usually 
this scoring is applied to discrete decision making problems, however it can be easily 
adapted to the continuous problems by introducing linear or nonlinear interpolation 
between the scores. We will assume then, that there is a negotiation problem and ne-
gotiation space defined in the form of the set of issues I and finite sets of options X i 
(realization levels of each issue i = 1, …, |I |). Each negotiation offer, perceived as the 
complete package, can be thus denoted as </p>

<p>1 2 </p>

<p>[ , ,..., ] </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>a x x 
x 
= 
, 
(1) </p>

<p>where x i is a realization level chosen from the set of feasible options X i for issue i. 
The main idea of the additive scoring system is to score each option that can comprise 
the negotiation offer by using an artificial criterion like utility or desirability. The pro-
cess of scoring offers and building the final ranking of them requires four stage analysis: 
1. Assigning weights to the negotiation issues by distributing a certain number of scor-
ing points among all of them. 
In the first step negotiator declares the importance of issues. He assigns the weights 
w i for each issue i = 1, …, |I|, such as: </p>

<p>i 
i </p>

<p>w P 
= </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>, 
(2) </p>

<p>where P is the total pool of scoring points established by the negotiator. </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>To make the interpretation of scores easier it is recommended to use a pool of 100 
scoring points, which allows then to explain the global score of offers as percentage 
of satisfaction (Kersten and Noronha 1999). 
2. Assigning scores to each option within each issue, using the pool of scores assigned 
to the issue. 
Negotiator distributes the scoring points according to his subjective perception of the 
quality of each option and following the rule that the most preferred the option is, the 
higher score it receives. He assigns a certain number of scoring points to each option </p>

<p>k 
i 
i </p>

<p>x 
X 
∈ 
up to the limit defined by the weight of this option: </p>

<p>( ) [0, ] </p>

<p>k 
i 
i </p>

<p>u x 
w 
∈ 
, 
(3) </p>

<p>for 
1,..., i 
k 
X 
= 
i 
1,..., 
i 
I 
= 
, 
where the least preferred option least </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x 
receives the score of 0 points and the most 
preferred one most </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x 
-the score of w i . </p>

<p>3. Determining the global scores of offers by adding up the scores of options that com-
prise them. 
Each offer m 
a 
A 
∈ (A -set of feasible offers, built with the combination of all pos-
sible options defined for all negotiation issues) receives the score: </p>

<p>( ) 
( 
) </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>m 
a 
i 
i </p>

<p>u a 
u x </p>

<p>= ∑ </p>

<p>, 
(4) </p>

<p>for 
1,..., 
m 
A 
= 
i 
1,..., 
i 
I 
= 
, where </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>a 
i </p>

<p>x is the option value for the issue i that builds 
the offer a m . 
4. Building the ranking of offers according to descending global scores. </p>

<p>Having completed all four steps of the above procedure we obtain a full scoring system 
of the feasible offers. Negotiators can use this system to compare proposals submitted 
by their counterparts and analyze the differences between quality (satisfaction rate) of 
the subsequent offers (that have the interval scale interpretation). Negotiators can also 
observe how the score is determined while the options are added or changed within the 
offer they prepare. The system allows also to follow the negotiation progress by analyz-
ing the concession paths -the shape of the graph built with scores of successive offers 
submitted both by the negotiator himself and his counterpart. Such a solution is com-
monly applied in the NSS, for example in <rs id="software-18" type="software">Inspire</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-18" type="creator">Kersten and Noronha</rs> <rs corresp="#software-18" type="version-date">1999</rs>), Smartset-
tle (Thiessen and Soberg <rs corresp="#software-20" type="version-date">2003</rs>) or <rs id="software-20" type="software">Negoisst</rs> (Schoop et al. 2003). An example of scoring 
negotiation offers with additive scoring system in <rs type="software">Inspire</rs> ENS is shown in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>But there are some disadvantages of additive scoring system. The first is that the scores 
negotiators use need to be simply assigned to the issues and options instead of determin-
ing them -deriving from their preferences defined verbally (Saaty 2001). What is more, 
operating with utility or desirability scores requires from negotiators some mathemati-
cal skills and at least a basic knowledge of decision theory, otherwise the global scores 
may be misinterpreted or, which is worse, the whole scoring system may not reflect the 
true preferences of negotiator. The second problem is that negotiators do not have to 
assume full compensation between the issues. Negotiation experiments conducted by </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>Wachowicz and Kersten (2009) show that negotiators very often reject some alterna-
tive solutions proposed by ENS despite they result in the higher score than the current 
negotiation agreement. It happens because these alternative solutions do not meet the 
minimal accepted levels for one or more issues. Therefore some alternative solutions 
are proposed based, for instance, on AHP (Mustajoki and Hamalainen 2000), outranking 
methods (Wachowicz and Wieszała 2009; Ulubeyli and Kazaz 2009) or verbal analysis 
(Ustinovichius et al. 2009). </p>

<p>We also decided to develop alternative methods for scoring negotiation offers that will 
try to overcome some of the problems mentioned above. </p>

<p>3.2. Even swaps based scoring system </p>

<p>The first method is based on the straightforward decision making model called even 
swaps (Hammond et al. 1998). This method has the same mathematical foundations 
as the additive scoring system, but differs in the philosophy of assigning the scores. It 
derives from the concept of vector domination assuming that each dominated alterna-
tive can be eliminated from the decision process, since it cannot be recommended to 
the decision maker as the most satisfying one. Furthermore it emphasizes that if all the 
alternatives result in equal consequences for any criterion, this criterion can be ignored 
in the decision making process as well (eliminated). Then, the even-swap method tries 
to adjust the consequences of all considered alternatives to make them equivalent in 
terms of a given objective, which requires increasing the value of one alternative in 
terms of one objective while decreasing its value by the equivalent amount in terms </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Additive scoring system in ENS Inspire </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>of another objective. The equivalent amounts are defined subjectively by the decision 
maker and reflect the structure of his preferences. After such an adjustment the consid-
ered objective can be eliminated and domination analysis can be conducted once again 
with respect to the rest of the objectives. </p>

<p>The process of the objectives elimination is repeated until the decision maker is able 
to find the best decision (the one that dominates over all the others) or the decision 
making problem is reduced (by eliminating the criteria) to the single criterion decision 
making problem. </p>

<p>Let us consider a simple problem of choosing between two alternatives (dwelling houses 
under construction) that differ in consequences for two criteria: price and building time 
(Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1. Alternatives under consideration </p>

<p>Criteria 
Alternatives </p>

<p>House 1 
House 2 </p>

<p>Price (in thousands of $) 
400 
370 </p>

<p>Building time (in months) 
18 
20 </p>

<p>Comparing these two houses we see that House 2 is cheaper but with longer building 
time than House 1 (investor wants to minimize both the criteria). No vector domination 
occurs. Investor needs to conduct then the even-swap analysis between two criteria. Ac-
cording to the procedure he will try to adjust the consequences of these two alternatives 
to become equal in terms of building time -say, both to be realized within 18 months. 
House 1 is going to be built within this time, but House 2 not. Investor needs to declare 
thus an equivalent amount (in terms of thousands of dollars) that will describe what 
the costs of shortening the building time form 20 to 18 months are. Let us assume that 
he evaluates the difference as $15,000 price equivalent. This amount may reflect some 
objective costs that decision maker needs to pay for waiting two moths longer for a 
new house, but also all the subjective and "non-measurable" costs (e.g. the costs of two 
months longer irritation for an annoying neighbor that lives next door and plays piano 
until midnight everyday) may (and should) be taken into consideration as well. Now, 
the equivalent amount can be added to the actual price of House 2 and Table 1 can be 
rewritten to Table 2. </p>

<p>Table 2. Alternatives after even-swap analysis </p>

<p>Criteria 
Alternatives </p>

<p>House 1 
House 2 </p>

<p>Price (in thousands of $) 
400 
370 385 </p>

<p>Building time (in months) 
18 
20 18 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>Since both alternatives result in the same value for criterion "building time", it can be 
eliminated from the decision making problem. After this elimination investor considers 
between these two alternatives analyzing only the criterion of price, therefore House 2 
will be selected as the most preferable solution, since it is cheaper than House 1. </p>

<p>The even-swap method can be easily applied for building the negotiation offers' scoring 
system. All the modifications required were previously described in details by Wacho-
wicz (2007). The modified procedure requires four step analysis: 
1. Defining of the base issue. Base issue is used as a global score for the offers evalu-
ation (like utility payoff in additive scoring system). It is chosen from the set of 
all negotiation issues that parties agreed to negotiate. It is recommended to choose 
the quantitative issue as the base, which will make the interpretation of the global 
scores much easier (it is easier to understand the difference between two prices: 
$200 and $250, than to understand the difference between two verbal descriptions: 
interesting and very interesting). 
2. Defining the base options for all issues. Making all the offers equal for one par-
ticular issue requires selecting the base option as a common result for all the 
offers. It is recommended to use the best option (i.e. the one that satisfied each 
issue the most) as a base. The equivalent amount defined then for other options 
may be interpreted as the cost of upgrading the offer's consequence to the best 
possible resolution. 
3. Assigning the equivalent amounts for options within issues. For each issue sepa-
rately the negotiator needs to compare all the options with the base option and 
define the equivalent amount for the differences between them (the base option 
receives the equivalent amount of 0). These equivalent amounts for the quantita-
tive base issue are calculated automatically as the differences between the actual 
values of the options. 
4. It is allowed to conduct such a within-issue analysis because the even-swap meth-
od employs an additive aggregation of the scores, which means it assumes that the 
score associated with each option of one issue does not depend on the options of 
other issues (Keeney and Raiffa 1991). 
5. Calculating the overall scores of offers by adding the equivalent amounts of op-
tions that comprise the offers. Similarly to the additive scoring system the global 
score of offer is determined by adding up the equivalent amounts defined for op-
tions that comprise this offer. The overall scores of the offers are interpreted as 
the costs of their upgrading to the ideal (best) level. </p>

<p>Even-swap based scoring system was applied in a simple spreadsheet based negotia-
tion support tool called <rs id="software-22" type="software">NegoCalc</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-22" type="creator">Wachowicz</rs> <rs corresp="#software-22" type="version-date">2008</rs>). The key stages of building the 
negotiation offers' scoring system in NegoCalc are shown in Fig. 3. First the base issue 
has been selected as the price, and then, after identification of the best options for all 
remaining issues (building time and warranty time), the equivalent amounts for even 
swaps in terms of price have been declared. </p>

<p>The even-swap based scoring system overcomes one disadvantage of additive scoring 
system. It allows negotiators to operate with the global score that they choose them-</p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>selves and the values of which they can interpret and compare easily. For instance, they 
can select the base issue like price or time and use their units to score offers. However, 
similarly to additive scoring system, even swaps require assigning swaps instead of 
determining them and, what is more important, assumes the full compensation for all 
negotiation issues. </p>

<p>3.3. Application of calibrated ELECTRE-TRI for scoring negotiation offers </p>

<p>The recent work of Wachowicz and Wieszała (2009) on alternative pre-negotiation pro-
tocols shows that outranking methods (like PROMETHEE) may be applied in nego-
tiation process to evaluate offers. What is interesting, these outranking methods that 
employ veto thresholds, reject the assumption of compensation, which is concordant 
with the true negotiation behavior recognized in the research of Wachowicz and Ker-
sten (2009). But on the other hand PROMETHEE or ELECTRE base on pair-wise 
comparisons and produce the offers scoring systems very sensitive to any change of 
the negotiation space. The ranking of offers may change diametrically if new options 
are added, which is a result of the ranking reversal problem (see De Keyser and Peeters 
1996). Therefore we decided to employ one of the sorting method from the ELECTRE 
family -ELECTRE TRI (Roy and Bouyssou 1993). </p>

<p>ELECTRE TRI allows to classify multi-criteria alternatives into the predefined catego-
ries, described by the lower and upper-limit profiles. Let F denote the set of indices of 
the criteria g 1 , g 2 , …, g m (F = {1, 2, …, m}), and B -the set of indices of the profiles 
defining p + 1 categories (B = {1, 2, …, p}), where b h is an upper limit of category C h 
and a lower limit of category C h+1 , h = 1, 2, …, p (Fig. 4). We assume here that decision 
maker's preferences increase with the value on each criterion. </p>

<p>ELECTRE-TRI classifies alternatives into the category C h+1 described by the lower 
limit b h and the higher limit b h+1 by verifying the assertion aSb h , interpreted as "a 
is at least as good as b h ". To verify this assertion a notion of pseudo-criteria is ap-
plied, introducing the preference, indifference and veto thresholds (Roy and Vincke 
1984) required for determining the credibility indices s(aSb h ) ∈ [0.1] of assertion aSb h . </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Building a scoring system of negotiation offers in NegoCalc </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>Then the assignment procedure is started, which (in the pessimistic approach) compares 
a successively to b i for i = p, p -1, …,1 and identifies first profile b h , for which aSb h . 
Alternative a is assigned then to the category C h+1 . </p>

<p>ELECTRE-TRI requires from decision maker the declaration of lots of parameters like 
profiles, weights, preference, indifference and veto thresholds. It can be troublesome, 
taking into consideration that these parameters are not so intuitive. Therefore, a few pro-
cedures were proposed to estimate the parameters of the ELECTRE-TRI model. One of 
them, by Mousseau and Slowinski (1998) -let us call it MS model -tries to determine 
the parameters by analyzing the assignment examples performed by the decision maker. 
The decision maker is asked to formulate examples of alternatives that he can easily 
classify to the categories. Basing on these assignments a simple quadratic programming 
model is constructed, solution of which allows to determine all the parameters except 
the veto thresholds. </p>

<p>ELECTRE-TRI together with the MS model can be easily applied to build the nego-
tiation offers' scoring system. The only problem that occurs is the precision of offers 
evaluation. Negotiators can consider the offers from the lower category to be worse 
than the ones from higher category, but cannot distinguish the differences between the 
offers classified to the same category. To obtain higher precision of a scoring system a 
huge number of categories should be defined, but it automatically increases the number 
of examples negotiator needs to assign in the preliminary stage. We propose an alterna-
tive approach that allows for increasing a scoring system's precision, which bases on 
calibration of the outcomes obtained by solving MS model. The procedure of calibration 
imposes on negotiator the declaration of satisfaction level that comes from reaching 
each profile, which we denote u(b h ). Consequently each offer a assigned to category 
C h+1 will result in satisfaction level from the range </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>( ), ( 
) </p>

<p>h 
h </p>

<p>u b u b + . If the range is too 
big to make an effective offers comparison, we propose to divide it into n sub-ranges 
of equal dimensions, which is equivalent to definition of new sub-categories within the 
considered category C h+1 , i.e.: </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Definition of categories using limit profiles (Mousseau and Slowinski 1998) </p>

<p>Category 1 </p>

<p>g 2 </p>

<p>g 3 </p>

<p>g m-</p>

<p>g m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>b 1 
b 1 </p>

<p>p-</p>

<p>b p </p>

<p>Category 2 
Category -1 
p 
Category p 
Category p 
g 1 </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p> 
 </p>

<p> 
− 
+ </p>

<p>− 
− 
+ 
∈ </p>

<p>⇒ 
→ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>b 
u 
b 
u 
s 
b 
u </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>b 
u 
b 
u 
s 
b 
u 
a 
u </p>

<p>C 
a </p>

<p>h 
h 
h </p>

<p>h 
h 
h </p>

<p>s 
h </p>

<p>) 
( 
) 
( 
) 
( </p>

<p>, 
) 
( 
) 
( 
) 
1 
( 
) 
( 
) 
( </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>where s = 1, …, n. </p>

<p>Each sub-category is defined by new profiles and the issues' values need to be identified 
for each of these profiles. They can be determined by linear interpolation between the 
issues' values of neighboring profiles defining this category. The upper-limit profile of 
each sub-category but the last (most preferred) one can be determined as: </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>( 
) 
( ) 
( ) 
( ) 
1 </p>

<p>k h 
k h 
k h 
k h </p>

<p>g b 
g b 
g b 
g b 
s 
n </p>

<p>+ − 
= 
+ ⋅ 
− 
, 
(6) </p>

<p>for k = 1, …, m and s = 1, …, n -1. The upper limit profile for the sub-category n is b h . 
The whole idea of dividing the ELECTRE-TRI scoring system into sub-categories and 
calibrating the outcomes in terms of satisfaction levels is presented in Fig. 5. </p>

<p>Having prepared the offers' scoring system as described above, negotiator can evaluate 
each negotiation offer by assigning it first to the general category, and then to the sub-
category within this category. Such an algorithm reduces the number of comparisons 
that would be far more bigger if the alternative was compared with sub-categories 
directly. </p>

<p>Let us assume that the negotiator wants to evaluate an offer 1 [320;10;8] 
a = 
within the 
scoring system shown in Fig. 4, where weights of issues estimated from MS model 
are 
[0,35;0,15;0,5] 
w = 
. He declares also the veto thresholds </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>( ) 
( ) [10;5;5] 
p b 
p b 
= = 
. </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Sub-categories and satisfaction scores </p>

<p>b 0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>b 0 
u( ) = 0% 
b 0 </p>

<p>C 1 
C 2 
C 3 </p>

<p>b 1 
u( ) = 40% 
b 1 </p>

<p>b 2 
u( ) = 70% 
b 2 </p>

<p>b 3 
u( ) = 100% 
b 3 </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>b 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>b 0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>b 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>30% 
50% </p>

<p>b 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>60% </p>

<p>b 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>77,5% </p>

<p>b 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>85% </p>

<p>b 2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>92,5% </p>

<p>-420 </p>

<p>-20 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>6.25 
13.25 
25 </p>

<p>-6 </p>

<p>-300 
-372.7 
-338.8 </p>

<p>-12.2 
-9 </p>

<p>g 1 </p>

<p>g 2 </p>

<p>g 3 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>According to the pessimistic assigning procedure this offer is compared first with pro-
file b 2 and later with b 1 , by examining the relation a 1 Sb 2 , i.e. s(a 1 Sb 2 ) ≥ λ (we assume 
λ = 0.746 estimated also from MS model). We obtain s(a 1 Sb 2 ) &lt; λ and s(a 1 Sb 1 ) = 
1 &gt; λ, which means a 1 may be classified to the category C 2 assuring the satisfaction at 
level no less than 40% and no higher than 70%. To make the evaluation more precise 
we compare now the offer a 1 with upper-limit profiles 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>[350,1;10, 08;10,91] 
b = 
and </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1 [361, 4;11,14;8,58] 
b = 
and obtain the values of credibility indices: </p>

<p>2 
1 1 </p>

<p>( 
) 0,5 
a Sb 
σ 
= and </p>

<p>1 
1 1 </p>

<p>( 
) 0,503 
a Sb 
σ 
= . With the assumed λ = 0.746 we cannot assign a 1 to any higher cat-
egory. Therefore a 1 will be assigned to sub-category 1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>C that assures the satisfaction at 
the levels from 40% to 50% (Fig. 6). </p>

<p>The significant advantage of the calibrated ELECTRE-TRI based scoring system is 
that it does not need a specification on all feasible options in the pre-negotiation phase, 
which was required for additive scoring system and even-swap based scoring system. 
Negotiators need only to agree over negotiation issues, and then define individually their 
reservation and aspiration levels that determine their negotiation space. And therefore 
in, the actual negotiation phase they can freely propose as an agreement proposals any 
offer (even those out of their negotiation space), not only the one based on the pre-
defined options. What is more, negotiators do not need to assign explicitly the scores 
to issues and options using their decision making skills. All the parameters required for 
building the scoring system are estimated basing on the assignment examples negotia-
tors declared in the pre-negotiation phase. The idea of scoring negotiation offers with 
calibrated ELECTRE-TRI scoring system is being tested in the experimental electronic 
negotiations system. </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Assigning the offer to sub-categories </p>

<p>C 2 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>C 2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>C 2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>b 1 
40% </p>

<p>b 2 
70% </p>

<p>a 1 </p>

<p>g 1 </p>

<p>g 2 </p>

<p>g 3 </p>

<p>-12.2 
-9 </p>

<p>6.25 
13.25 </p>

<p>-372.7 </p>

<p>70% 
60% 
77,5% </p>

<p>-338.8 </p>

<p>85% </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>4. Software support for further negotiation phases </p>

<p>Having the offers' scoring system built, negotiators may take advantage of it in the 
actual negotiation phase, for following the negotiation progress and analyzing the scale 
of concessions and also in post-negotiation phase (after achieving agreement), for ana-
lyzing the gains left on the table. </p>

<p>4.1. Actual negotiation phase support </p>

<p>Both an additive scoring system and even-swap based scoring system can be used in 
the offer's formulation process for analyzing in details the trade-offs between issues and 
options. While building the offer (i.e. adding the propositions for reservation levels of 
successive issues) negotiator can observe how the overall score changes. He can im-
mediately react if the score is lower than his aspiration level by balancing with different 
combination of options (increasing value of one issue, while decreasing it for another). 
The process of building negotiation offer in <rs type="software">NegoCalc</rs> system is presented in Fig. 7. </p>

<p>These two scoring systems may be also helpful in graphical illustration of the negotia-
tion progress. A graph depicting the history of offers in the evaluation (utility) space 
can be used to analyze the dynamics of negotiation -how frequently the offers and 
counteroffers are submitted and what outcome they produce. It is also very useful in 
recognizing the scale of successive concessions, basing on which negotiators can con-
clude on their counterparts negotiation strategy. An example of a history graph displayed 
in ENS <rs id="software-24" type="software">Inspire</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-24" type="creator">Kersten and Noronha</rs> <rs corresp="#software-24" type="version-date">1999</rs>) is presented in Fig. 8. </p>

<p>The ELECTRE-TRI based offers' scoring system cannot be used the same way, since 
it does not operate on the options rating. It does not allow to score any offer until the 
full package is not created, therefore, negotiators cannot observe in details the direct 
trade-offs between the different resolution levels of issues. The graph of history cannot 
be depicted for the offers scored by ELECTRE-TRI either, since the scores are in fact 
the ranges that correspond to the actual sub-category but not the scalar values. Instead 
of the classic history graph a simple general map can be drawn showing the pace of 
concession in terms of moving from one sub-category to another. </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Analyzing an offer under construction in NegoCalc system </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>Negotiation support system may also have implemented the optimization engines that 
allow them to act pro-actively in the actual negotiation phase, like some heuristics or 
game theory models. These engines may determine the fair solutions and suggest ne-
gotiators the alternative offers as the agreement proposals, like in Smartsettle (Thiessen 
and Soberg 2003). </p>

<p>4.2. Post-negotiation phase support </p>

<p>In post-negotiation phase a final contract is signed by the negotiating parties, but be-
fore it happens there is time for analyzing the agreement and consider its effectiveness. 
NSSs can help in analyzing the negotiation space of both the negotiators and finding 
the better solutions. It is quite a simple task for discrete negotiation problems that are 
supported by additive scoring systems or even-swap scoring systems. NSSs simply 
search a finite negotiation space and try to identify the offers that result in scores at 
least as good as the current compromise simultaneously for both the negotiators. The 
results of the electronic negotiation experiments show that NSSs find the solutions better 
than the negotiated agreement for 65% of all cases (Wachowicz and Kersten 2009). The 
post-negotiation optimization capabilities of NSSs seem to be very important because 
they are giving the opportunity to improve the agreement and consume the gains left 
on negotiation table. The results of post-negotiation optimization conducted by eNS 
Inspire are shown in Fig. 9. </p>

<p>Fig. 8. History graph in eNS Inspire </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>



<p>Knowing the scale of possible improvements negotiators can renegotiate the current 
agreement trying to move themselves to one of the solutions proposed by the system. 
But what is interesting, only 22% of negotiators that NSS suggested the improvements 
to, took an advantage of the renegotiation and improved their final score (Wachow-
icz and Kersten 2009). The rest of them decided to stay in the negotiated agreement 
claiming that the system proposals cannot be accepted (despite they resulted in higher 
score than an agreement) because these offers do not satisfy their reservation levels on 
some options. This explanation shows that negotiators reject sometimes the notion of 
compensation and the alternative scoring mechanisms, like the one based on calibrated 
ELECTRE-TRI, that should be implemented. However, there are yet no research works 
showing the post-negotiation capabilities of scoring systems based on ELECTRE-TRI 
or other outranking or sorting methods. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>In this paper we discussed the problem of decision support that can be given in negotia-
tions supported by negotiation support systems. This is a very interesting problem, since 
more and more negotiations are conducted in the electronic way and sooner or later 
negotiators will require professional tools that could efficiently help them in the conduct 
of negotiation. We described thus the structure of negotiation process and showed dif-
ferent possibilities of its support considering the role and activity NSSs can play. Then 
we tried to focus on the decision process that takes place in the pre-negotiation phase 
discussing the classical approach to eliciting preferences and building the offers' scor-
ing system that was based on the additive scoring system with the utility payoffs. We 
tried to emphasize its simplicity showing also some disadvantages of it and proposing 
two alternative approaches. </p>

<p>Fig. 9. Improvement of current agreement found by eNS Inspire </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>



<p>The first approach derived from Hammond, Keeney and Raiffa even-swap method also 
assumes full compensation on issues. The main difference in comparison with the utility 
based additive scoring system is the philosophy of defining the trade-offs. Here negotia-
tors decide themselves what kind of units to use to express the overall score of offer. 
They select the base issue and try to evaluate all other options of all issues in terms 
of base one, using its units to define the equivalent amounts for swaps between issues. </p>

<p>The second approach rejects compensation and tries to build the scoring system using 
pseudo-criteria. This ELECTRE-TRI based model in conjunction with the MS model for 
estimation of key parameters can become a very helpful and simple to use supporting 
tool. Instead of asking negotiators to assign the scores it tries to derive the preferences 
basing on the assignment examples. This indirect approach does not force negotiators 
to score each negotiation option separately and declare the abstract values (i.e. utili-
ties, desirabilities) to what they can sometimes perceive as immeasurable. It only asks 
to formulate the alternatives that negotiators can judge intuitively to be good, medium 
or bad and then, using some assumptions, tries to identify the profiles that limit these 
categories. To increase the precision of such an evaluation we decided to calibrate the 
scoring system using satisfaction scores assigned to the initial profiles of the categories. 
What is more, we decided to divide the categories into the sub-categories by simple 
interpolation between the values of the successive profiles, which allowed to distinguish 
the differences between two offers that were previously classified to the same category. </p>

<p>We also tried to show that the choice of scoring system has the consequences for the 
subsequent negotiation phases. The methods that can easily build the scoring system 
in the pre-negotiation phase deriving from the negotiators' decision or choices may not 
allow later for making any sophisticated analysis of the negotiation progress or the scale 
of concessions (i.e. the ELECTRE-TRI based scoring system). </p>

<p>The future work will focus on the implementation of the calibrated ELECTRE-TRI 
model to the electronic negotiation system and making the comparison study with the 
utility based scoring system that will show how the negotiators perceive a use and use-
fulness of these two different tools. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This work has been supported by Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education, as 
a part of scientific project number N N111 234936. </p>



<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>





<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>





<p>T. Wachowicz. Decision support in software supported negotiations </p>





<p>DERYBŲ SPRENDIMŲ PARAMOS PROGRAMA </p>

<p>T. Wachowicz </p>

<p>Santrauka </p>

<p>Straipsnyje pateikiama idėja apie derybų vykdymą naudojantis sprendimų paramos programa. Pristato-
mi derybų sistemos privalumai aptariant skirtingas funkcijas ir tipologijas, vėliau akcentuojant sprendi-
mų paramos sistemos galimybes, kurias gali duoti ši sistema kiekvienai iš derybų šalių bet kuriuo dery-
bų etapu. Pristačius populiariausius sprendimus pateikiamos dvi procedūros, kurios gali būti taikomos 
norint išsiaiškinti derybininko prioritetus ir sudaryti siūlančio asmens šalių vertinimo sistemą. Pirmoji 
paremta Hammond, Keeney and Raiffa lygių mainų procedūra, o antroji -Roy sukurta ELECTRE-TRI. 
Šios procedūros gali būti lengvai pritaikytos kaip analitinė sistema elektroninėje derybų sistemoje, 
pakeičiant klasikines adityviąsias vertinimo sistemas. Nagrinėjama, kaip skirtingos vertinimo sistemos 
naudojamos tolesniuose derybų etapuose. </p>

<p>Reikšminiai žodžiai: derybos, sprendimų paramos sistemos, sprendimo analizė, daugiakriterinis 
vertinimas, lygūs mainai, ELECTRE-TRI. </p>

<p>Tomasz WACHOWICZ. Graduated in 1999 from the Karol Adamiecki University of Economics 
in Katowice (Poland) with a degree in management science. He was employed as an analyst in the 
Advertising Agency of Polish National Radio in Katowice. In 2000 he joined a PhD program at the 
Karol Adamiecki University of Economics and obtained his PhD in 2004 with the thesis entitled: 
"Quantitative Methods In Modeling The Business-to-Business Negotiation". Since 2005 he has been 
employed in the Department of Operations Research at the Karol Adamiecki University of Economics 
in Katowice. 
The main focus of his research is the negotiation analysis. He is the author of scientific papers on 
negotiation support, negotiation support systems, multiple criteria decision making, game theory and 
project management. He participated in international scientific projects, such as "Electronic Negotia-
tion, Media And Transactions For Socio-Economic Interactions" (2003) organized by University of Ot-
tawa, or "Global Research In INSPIRE Negotiations" (2009) organized by InterNeg Research Centre 
and also took part in a few scientific projects founded by the Polish Ministry of Science and Higher 
Education (PMSHE) and nowadays he leads a three-year research project "Preference Analysis and 
Support of the Negotiators" supported by PMSHE. He cooperates with international research cent-
ers and universities such as InterNeg research Centre (Montreal), Vienna University of Technology 
(Austria), University of Economics in Prague (Czech Republic) and University of Malaga (Spain). 
He has been the head of organizing committee of the cyclical national conference "Preference Mod-
eling Versus Risk" and "International Workshop on Multiple Criteria Decision Making" (www.iwom-
cdm.ae.katowice.pl). He is also a member of the International Society on Multiple Criteria Decision 
Making and EURO Working Group on Multi-Criteria Decision Aiding. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 576-597 </p>

</text></tei>