<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2013.27" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The present paper provides practical implications for the Central and Eastern European equity investors, who seek 
dividend income in addition to the capital appreciation. The insight into the dividend puzzle in the CEE companies, provided 
in the research, gives an overview of the dividend yields and payment stability as well as the relationship between the dividend 
payments and the type of ownership. Main findings of the study prove that the highest yield and the highest payout ratio are 
obtained in the case of strategic investor acting as a major shareholder (&gt;10% of ownership capital). Binary logistic regression 
results provide the possibility to forecast whether the company will pay dividends. The typical dividend payer should not have 
family/management as a major investor, the ownership still should be concentrated and the investor preferably should be of 
local origin. </p>

<p>The famous Black's (1976) quote "The harder we look at 
the dividend picture, the more it seems like a puzzle, with 
pieces that just do not fit together" precisely addresses the 
comprehensive issue of the dividend policies. The problems 
of the dividend payouts, its determinants, its stability are 
widely discussed in the financial management resulting in 
the numerous empirical and theoretical papers. Signaling 
theory, which gains importance within the modern capital 
markets, can provide certain hints for the dividend puzzle: 
the dividend announcements almost always are followed by 
the firm's price increase, while the announcements about 
the dividend reduction have a significant negative reaction 
on the stock price (Koch, Shenoy 1999; Lee, Xiao 2003;  Guttman et al. 2007; Hussainey, AalEisa 2009; Fairchild  2010). When the dividends are being initiated or raised the 
management signals about the quality of earnings, about 
earnings stability and sustainability, which is the main 
concern of the firm's shareholders. Financial managers 
deciding on the dividend increase focus on maintaining 
stable or increasing earnings aiming to sustain smooth </p>

<p>dividend stream (Lintner 1956; Skinner 2004; Brav et al.  2005; DeAngelo et al. 2006). 
However, the research is mainly done on the sample of 
the listed companies in the developed markets and the topic 
of dividend seems to be underresearched in the developing 
countries. While the emerging markets dividend paying 
companies are becoming good choice for the investment 
portfolio due to their ability to provide higher capital growth 
on top of the attractive dividend yields. They also provi 
de certain hedging during the crisis time as the emerging 
market stock companies to a great extent are exposed to the 
downturn as indicated by Bareikienė and Sūdžius (2011)  in Lithuania. 
Besides, according to Manu Vandenbulck (2012), at the 
moment the dividend yield of the emerging market stocks 
is 3%, which is higher than in some major developed mar 
kets such as the US at 2% dividend yield and Japan at 2.6%. 
Moreover, emerging market companies become more wil 
ling to attract more investors by increasing share of profits 
paid out -35% currently vs. 10% in 2000. Therefore, the pre 
sent research focuses on the emerging CEE countries also </p>

<p>because their offered products are becoming accessible and 
integrated in the global context (Gudonytė, Tvaronavičienė  2012). 
The decision to pay dividends is a part of company's cor 
porate policy and according to the authors' previous study, 
it was found out that the balance sheet strength, operating 
profitability, industry factor as well as the firm's size impose 
a significant influence on the payout ratios (Bistrova, Lace  2012). However, these factors were not able to fully explain 
the changes in the dividend payments. 
Stein and Ginevičius (2010)analyzed the profit sharing 
problem depending on the business collaboration form and 
found out that the factors that mostly influence the profit 
sharing are the input balance of every member, which is 
expressed as the aggregate of profit (financial benefit) and 
the technology (intangible benefit). 
The authors of the present article believe that a signifi 
cant impact on the payout ratios might be also exerted by 
the ownership type and origin, which can be especially vital 
in the underdeveloped emerging markets. 
The aim of the present research is to find out what type 
and origin of the largest shareholder are associated with the 
highest dividend payouts. 
When speculating about the hypotheses of the study, the 
authors came to the conclusion that in the emerging markets 
the highest dividend payments might be stimulated in case 
of financial investors, which tend to be reluctant to invest in 
future developments and are eager to receive high dividends 
now. Moreover, foreign shareholders most probably would 
consider investments in the emerging market companies 
more willingly in case of high dividend opportunity as an 
additional risk hedging option. Therefore, the hypotheses 
of the research are the following: 
H1: CEE listed companies having financial investor 
as a main shareholder exhibit highest dividend payout 
ratios. 
H2: CEE listed companies having foreign investor as a 
main shareholder exhibit highest dividend payout ratios. 
The authors employ various statistical methods such 
as graphical analysis, multifactor regressions, correlation 
analysis, binary logistic regression analysis, to determine 
the most beneficial ownership structure, meaning the one 
which provides highest payout, for the minority sharehol 
ders. </p>

<p>1. Ownership Influence on the Dividend Policy </p>

<p>According to the agency theory, large shareholder may 
either minimize or exacerbate the conflicts between the 
stockholders and the management. Agency costs are be 
lieved to be minimized in case of managerial ownership as 
the management bears the same risks and rewards as other 
stockholders, thus, they have to consume also losses arising </p>

<p>from their dividend behavior. On the other hand large sha 
reholder might be interested solely in lifting company's 
valuation and, therefore, neglect the interests of minority 
shareholder. </p>

<p>1.1. Managerial ownership </p>

<p>These circumstances lead to the belief that the dividends 
play a major role as a controlling mechanism to mitiga 
te the potential corporate governance conflicts. Jensen  (1986) concluded that dividend payment reduce free cash 
flow available to managers and, therefore, restrain them 
from investing in the unprofitable and too risky projects. 
Several studies stated the evidence of the negative asso 
ciation between the large managerial ownership and the 
dividend payments (Rozeff 1982; Mahmud, perry, Rimbey  1995; Short, Zhang, Keasey 2002). The other side of the 
coin, when dealing with managerial ownership, is positive 
association between the dividend payouts and the managers 
acting as a major shareholder (White 1996; Fenn, Liang  2001), which is explained by the researchers as a way to 
eliminate free cash flow problem. </p>

<p>1.2. Institutional ownership </p>

<p>Substantial number of studies was conducted to discover 
the association between the institutional ownership and 
the dividend payments. Institutional investors have better 
ability to control the management and have greater influ 
ence on the dividend policy determination compared to the 
individual investors due to their size of investments and 
professional approach to their investments (meaning dee 
per analysis, constant contact with the management etc.). 
Eckbo and Verma (1994) showed that institutional inves 
tors prefer free cash flow distribution in form of dividends. 
Short et al. (2002) showed the same positive relationship, 
while he observed the negative relationship between the 
managerial ownership and the dividend policy. 
Studies on the emerging markets confirm the findings 
from the developed markets. Iranian companies provide an 
evidence of positive relationship between the institutional 
ownership and the dividend payments (Mehrani et al. 2011). 
Study on 70 pakistani companies confirmed the positive re 
lationship between institutional holdings and the dividend 
payments, while there was a negative association between 
the management shareholding and dividend payments 
(Ullah et al. 2012). </p>

<p>1.3. Foreign ownership </p>

<p>Foreign ownership is an important issue for the emer 
ging markets companies. The association of foreign ow 
nership and dividend payment is found to be positive as </p>

<p> 
N. Lace et al. Ownership type influence on dividend payments in CEE countries </p>

<p>foreign investors tend to overweight large and profitable 
firms, which pay high dividends as observed in Korean 
stock market (Chai 2010). The confirming findings were 
also demonstrated by Warrad et al. (2012), who research 
Jordanian companies. However, Ullah et al. (2012) and 
Abdullah et al. (2012), researching pakistani and Malaysian 
firms, respectively, were not able to find a significant prove 
of foreign ownership influence on dividend policy. </p>

<p>2. Research Methodology </p>

<p>2.1. Research Design </p>

<p>To determine the influence of the ownership structure 
on the dividend policy, the authors divided all researched 
companies into five groups according to their ownership 
structure pattern. In order to be classified as a certain group 
the company should have an investor, which holds not less 
than 10% of the total share capital, and it should be the 
major holding. The groups were the following: </p>

<p>-Financial: major investor holds the company prima 
rily for financial interest, which is share price appre 
ciation and dividend payments. Usually these are 
banks, trust accounts, insurance companies, pension 
funds or investment holdings. </p>

<p>-Strategic: major stake in company's capital is held by 
the company, which operates in the same industry, 
usually headquartered in Western Europe or US. 
This is very common situation in telecommunication, 
pharmaceuticals, and financial industry groups. </p>

<p>-Government: state owns significant part of the com 
pany. In this case the shares as a rule do not change 
the hands and the state kept its controlling stake 
(common in industries of strategic importance). </p>

<p>-Family/management: large stake of the company be 
longs to the private person, which usually takes acti 
ve part in the company management, being member 
of the board or the management team. Sometimes 
large stakes belong to several members of the fami 
ly, who exert significant influence on the corporate 
management. </p>

<p>-Free float: companies with the dispersed ownership. 
Stake of the largest shareholder does not exceed 10%. 
Besides, the majority investors were classified according 
to their origin into the local and foreign investors. 
The authors of the research consider two dependent va 
riables: the dividend payout ratio, which provides with the 
view on the capital management policy, and the dividend 
yield ratio, which demonstrates shareholders' dividend 
preferences. Historical data quality of the CEE companies 
ownership structure is relatively weak. So, it lead to using 
every ownership variable in the regression as the dummy 
variable. There were two multifactor regressions studied: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>(2) </p>

<p>where: 
DP -dividend payout ratio; 
DY -dividend yield; 
b -regression coefficient, i = 0,1…6; 
Size -company size taken a natural logarithm of market 
capitalization; a control variable in the regression; 
Fin -1 in case of financial ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
Strat -1 in case of strategic ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
Gov -1 in case of government ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
Fam -1 in case of family ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
FF -1 in case of free float ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
Local -1 in case of local ownership, 0 -otherwise; 
ε -error term. 
The authors considered also nonlinear regression 
approach; however it was not possible to obtain the plau 
sible results. Therefore, the authors provide the results of 
linear regression only. </p>

<p>2.2. Research Sample </p>

<p>The authors studied the sample of 117 largest compa 
nies, listed on the stock exchanges of 10 Central and 
Eastern European countries: Czech Republic, Croatia, 
Slovakia, Slovenia, Hungary, poland, Romania, Baltic 
States (Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania). The companies were 
selected based on the principle of their inclusion in the 
exchanges' main lists. The period examined in the course 
of the study spanned from January 2005 to June 2012. 
In total there were 725 firmobservations as number of 
the companies were excluded from the study due to the 
unavailability of annual report, ownership information, 
market capitalization data etc. 
The sources for obtaining the ownership and dividend 
data were the following: corporate annual reports, corpo 
rate websites, local stock exchange provided information, 
newspaper articles available from the Internet. </p>

<p>3. Results of the Research </p>

<p>3.1. General Overview </p>

<p>Average dividend yield in the CEE countries ranges from 
2% to 5% (Fig. 1), which appears to be relatively high. It 
is rather surprising, taking into account the nature of the 
developing markets, which often means that companies are 
in the developing phase and, therefore, require large capex. 
partly this can be explained by the favourable dividend tax 
policy. To compare, in 2012 the dividend yield in US was 
2.1%, in Japan -2.5%, while in CEE region it was almost 6% </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(3): 259-266 </p>

<p>
according Societe Generale's estimates (ChavezDreyfuss  2012). 
The dividends in the CEE equity market are paid by 
almost half of the companies in the analyzed sample. The 
share declined due to the financial crisis, but later managed 
to recover to the precrisis level, the same as the dividend 
yields. 
Current dividend payout ratio in Central and Eastern 
Europe is around 30%, which is rather modest but is reco 
vering after the dividend cuts due to the financial crisis. 
Besides, the low level of the ratio is explained by the deve 
loping stage of many companies listed in CEE countries. To 
compare, payout ratio in USA is 27%, while in Europe it is 
around 40% (Blackrock 2012). Low payout ratio in USA is 
compensated by the share repurchases, which are common 
among the US companies. </p>

<p>3.2. Ownership Structure and Dividend Policy </p>

<p>In Central and Eastern Europe strategic ownership is the 
most important as it is represented by a third of the studied 
companies. This is a common situation in the financial 
and energy industries. Other type of ownership structures 
are less represented on the CEE market: 22% -financial 
investors, 18% -governmental, 22% -family/management/ 
CEO. Besides, the ownership structures of 75% CEE com 
panies are concentrated when one shareholder owns more 
than 25% of the company, which is contrasting with the US 
share market, where the vast majority of the companies has 
dispersed ownership. 
The chart on Fig. 2 provides an overview on the average 
dividend payouts, according to the ownership type: strategic 
ownership succeeds highest dividend payments in almost 
all periods studied. Government in the role of major sha 
reholder obviously also presses for higher payouts. Family 
ownership does not ensure high dividend payouts, which 
might be explained by the fact that family/management is 
determined to invest in longterm project to gain higher 
return later and is able to give up shortterm profit now. 
The results reflected in Table 1 confirm the abovemen 
tioned results that the companies with the strategic and 
governmental ownership share their profit more frequently 
and more generously than the companies of other types of 
shareholding. With familyowned companies there is the 
opposite case -less than half of the companies studied pay 
dividends, which is the lowest proportion among all ow 
nership structures. 
It is evident from Fig. 3 that the dividend yield (average 
yield of paying companies) in all ownership type groups is 
on a rather high level, especially if compared to the current 
very low bond yields rates. The highest return is seen in the 
strategic ownership group, which in 2012 gave up its leader 
positions to the governmental ownership. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Dividend Yield and Share of Dividend paying Com 
panies in CEE </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Dividend payout Ratio According to the Type of 
Ownership </p>

<p>Table 1. proportionate number of paying companies accor 
ding to the type of ownership </p>

<p>Type of 
Ownership 
2012 
2011 
2010 
2009 2008 </p>

<p>Fin </p>

<p>0.58 
0.60 
0.41 
0.38 
0.75 </p>

<p>Strat </p>

<p>0.62 
0.64 
0.61 
0.68 
0.76 </p>

<p>Gov </p>

<p>0.65 
0.78 
0.88 
0.75 
0.84 </p>

<p>Fam </p>

<p>0.32 
0.41 
0.43 
0.42 
0.59 </p>

<p>FF 
0.33 
0.43 </p>

<p>0.57 
0.57 
0.60 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Dividend Yield Ratio According to the Type of 
Ownership </p>

<p> 
N. Lace et al. Ownership type influence on dividend payments in CEE countries </p>

<p>Governmentheld companies obviously feel pressure 
from the main shareholder for the dividend payments 
as both the payout ratio and the dividend yield post an 
uptrend started in 2005 with a minor setback due to 
the recent financial crisis. Family/management's owned 
companies exhibit rather high average yields as well, 
which, however, posted a significant decline during the 
crisis years. 
With the help of statistical software <rs id="software-0" type="software">SpSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20.0</rs> the authors 
run of the regressions and test the possible violations of the 
regression assumptions. Table 2 shows the correlation matrix 
of the independent variables used in the regressions. High 
correlation (r = -0.771) between the strategic and local ow 
nership is observed as indicated in the table 2, which could </p>

<p>Table 2. Correlation Matrix of the independent variables </p>

<p>Correlations </p>

<p>Size 
Fin 
Strat 
Gov 
Fam 
FF </p>

<p>Fin 
pearson Correlation 
-.275 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.000 </p>

<p>Strat 
pearson Correlation 
.181 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.310 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.000 
.000 </p>

<p>Gov 
pearson Correlation 
.383 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.215 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.329 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.000 
.000 
.000 </p>

<p>Fam 
pearson Correlation 
-.266 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.255 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.390 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.271 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.000 
.000 
.000 
.000 </p>

<p>FF 
pearson Correlation 
-.039 
-.114 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.175 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.122 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.144 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.291 
.002 
.000 
.001 
.000 </p>

<p>Local 
pearson Correlation 
-.206 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>.152 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>-.771 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>.336 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>.371 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>.179 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Sig. (2tailed) 
.000 
.000 
.000 
.000 
.000 
.000 </p>

<p>** Correlation is significant at the 0.01 level (2-tailed), * Correlation is significant at the 0.05 level (2-tailed) </p>

<p>have been supposed by the authors as the majority of strategic 
investors in CEE companies are foreign institutions. This high 
correlation might lead to the multicollinearity problem in 
the regression, thus, it would be worth to omit one of these 
variables in the final regression model. 
Running the regression models shows that the owners 
hip structure has higher impact on the dividend payout 
ratio than on the dividend yield: F test (Dp -dependent 
variable) is 38.19 vs. F test (DY -dependent variable) is 
18.54. It should be noted that both of the regressions ap 
pear to be significant due to the high F test values, despite 
the fact that adjusted R in the case with the dividend yield 
regression model is 2.5% and in the case with the dividend 
payout regression model it is 9.6% (Tables 3, 4). </p>

<p>Table 3. The Results of Multiple Regression Analysis of Dividend payout Ratio (Dp -Dependent variable); variables Fin, Gov, 
Fam, FF and Local were automatically (stepwise method) excluded from the regression by SpSS due to their insignificance </p>

<p>Regression equation </p>

<p>Independent variables 
t-statistic 
VIF 
Model Parameters 
Statistics </p>

<p>(Constant) 
-2.157 
F test 
38.189 </p>

<p>Size 
6.891 
1.034 
pvalue 
0.000 </p>

<p>Strat 
4.036 
1.034 
R 
0.309 </p>

<p>Fin 
-.383 
1.170 
R Square 
0.096 </p>

<p>Gov 
.534 
1.452 
R Square Adjusted 
0.093 </p>

<p>Fam 
-.267 
1.237 
DurbinWatson 
1.868 </p>

<p>FF 
-1.491 
1.032 
Std. Error of the 
Estimate </p>

<p>0.3528595 </p>

<p>Local 
-.731 
2.495 </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(3): 259-266 </p>

<p>
Dividend payout Ratio (Table 3): The regression results 
provide evidence that there is a significant positive relations 
hip between the dividend payout ratio and the strategic 
investors. Other variables do not seem to exert a significance 
influence on the amount of dividend payout. 
Dividend Yield (Table 4): The same as in the regression 
with the dividend payout, there is a significant positive as 
sociation between the dividend yield and the case, when the 
strategic investor has the majority ownership. The compa 
ny's size does not have a significant influence on the yield 
ratio. 
The authors decided to run also the binary logistic re 
gression to discover how high the probability to forecast the 
dividend payments (if the company does or does not pay the 
dividends at all) depending on the ownership type variables 
can be. The dependent variable is DY_1, which in case of 
dividend payments is 1 and in case of dividend absence is 0. 
The equation to explain the binary logistic regression was 
the following: </p>

<p>(3), </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>The results of the logistic regression, which are reflected 
in the Table 5, demonstrate that the dividend payments can 
be forecasted with the probability of 68.1%. The variables 
significant to the regression equation were the following: 
Size, Fam, FF, Local. 
Therefore, there is a high probability of dividend pay 
ments if the company: </p>

<p>-is relatively large; </p>

<p>-does not have family as a major investor; </p>

<p>-does not have a dispersed ownership; </p>

<p>-has local investor as major owner. </p>

<p>Conclusions and Recommendations </p>

<p>The main objective of the present paper was to study the 
relationship between the dividend policy and the type of 
ownership in the CEE listed companies. All largest inves 
tors in the CEE companies were classified according to 
their type (financial, strategic, government, family/mana 
gement, free float) and according to their origin (local and 
foreign). These ownership structures were used as dummy 
variables in the regression equation to find out the signifi 
cance of their relation to the firm's dividend policy, which 
is primarily reflected in the dividend payout ratio. Besides, 
the authors considered also the dividend yield as a depen 
dent variable to find out if a retail investor can base his </p>

<p>Table 4. The Results of Multiple Regression Analysis of Dividend Yield (DY -Dependent variable) </p>

<p>Regression equation </p>

<p>Independent variables 
t-statistic 
VIF 
Model Parameters 
Statistics </p>

<p>(Constant) 
9.424 
F test 
18.536 </p>

<p>Strat 
4.305 
1.000 
pvalue 
0.000 </p>

<p>Size 
1.751 
1.034 
R 
0.158 </p>

<p>Fin 
-1.942 
1.106 
R Square 
0.025 </p>

<p>Gov 
1.532 
1.122 
R Square Adjusted 
0.024 </p>

<p>Fam 
.364 
1.179 
DurbinWatson 
1.890 </p>

<p>FF 
-1.948 
1.032 
Std. Error of the 
Estimate 
0.074 </p>

<p>Local 
-.762 
2.467 </p>

<p>Table 5. Binary logistic regression results obtained 
with the forward method in SpSS (0.00 -dividends 
are not paid, 1.00 -dividends are paid) </p>

<p>Panel a. Overall regression results </p>

<p>Dividend 
payment cases 
0.00 
1.00 
Percentage 
correct </p>

<p>0.00 
129 
152 
45.9 </p>

<p>1.00 
79 
365 
82.2 </p>

<p>Overall 
percentage 
68.1 </p>

<p>Panel b. Independent variables statistics </p>

<p>Independent 
variable 
Coefficients 
Std. error 
p-value </p>

<p>Size 
.314 
.043 
.000 </p>

<p>Fam 
.824 
.209 
.000 </p>

<p>FF 
.852 
.344 
.013 </p>

<p>Local 
.550 
.199 
.006 </p>

<p>Constant 
1.505 
.314 
.000 </p>

<p> 
N. Lace et al. Ownership type influence on dividend payments in CEE countries </p>

<p>investment decision also on the ownership type to receive 
the highest return in the form of dividends, which might 
become very crucial in the current low yield environment. 
The research on 117 CEE listed companies shows that 
the most generous companies in terms of dividend payouts 
are those, which have strategic investors or government as 
major owners. Highest dividend yields are also seen in the 
investment case of the strategic owners, however, govern 
mentowned companies are catching up. Evidently for these 
investors today's cash flows are not sacrificed to get higher 
cash flows in the future. One of the explanations might be 
that these companies are in their life cycle 4, when they have 
very good cash flows, they are leaders in their niches and 
have limited investment opportunities. It is worth noticing 
that the companies, where the major owners are the finan 
cial investors, whose primary investment goal is financial 
benefit, exhibit rather low dividend yields and payout ratios. 
Graphical analysis results were proved by the both re 
gressions (to forecast dividend payout and the dividend 
yield), which demonstrated that the only significant variable 
is strategic ownership. Therefore, the hypotheses about the 
foreign and financial ownership, having highest influence 
on the dividend amounts, were refuted. 
Binary logistic regression, which the authors used to 
forecast if the company will or will not pay the dividends, 
demonstrated 68% chance to correctly predict the payments 
at the several preconditions. First, the company has to be 
of the tangible size, which is usually the common case not 
only for the emerging markets, but also for the developed 
markets. Second, the company should not have family/ma 
nagement investor in the ownership structure, which can be 
explained by the family's willingness to invest for the future 
rather than to distribute the profits now. Third, it should not 
have a dispersed ownership -there still has to be one major 
owner (above 10% of ownership capital structure), who will 
exert certain influence on the profit distribution decisions. 
Fourth, the major investor should be of local origin. 
The results of this study provide an insight into the re 
lationship between the dividend payments and the type of 
ownership, which have practical implications for the inves 
tors in CEE companies, who would like to have an exposure 
to the emerging markets dividend payers. </p>



<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(3): 259-266 </p>



<p>
 
N. Lace et al. Ownership type influence on dividend payments in CEE countries </p>

</text></tei>