<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fjbem.2010.13" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. This study investigates the determinants of firm size. Data was collected in 
face-to-face structured-questionnaire interviews of 1314 firm founders from 14 counties 
in Argentina. Quantile regression was used as a more suitable methodology to measure 
the determinants of firm size. Our results show that the main sets of explanatory variables 
related to founder characteristics (age, experience, education, and vocation) provide a full 
explanation of firm size. We have also found evidence that a high degree strategic plan-
ning and a better competitive position are positively related to firm size as well. Finally, 
environmental factors were less representative. </p>

<p>There is systematic empirical evidence that entrepreneurship is important for economic 
growth (e.g. Audretsch and Thurik 2000; Carree et al. 2002; Wennekers and Thurik 
1999). Over the last several decades, new firm growth has become a popular research 
topic, especially since Birch (1979) found that new firms had created the majority of 
new employment in the U.S. In this respect, the SME sector's contribution to the econ-
omy has attracted the attention of academics and policy makers in both developed 
economies and those in transition (Krasniqi 2007). </p>

<p>The fact that entrepreneurs perform specialized functions that directly or indirectly con-
tribute to output and growth is not a novel concept in the literature (Baumol 1968, 2004). 
As Salas and Sanchez (2006) mentioned, the list of entrepreneurial activities reported 
includes: innovation and creative destruction (Schumpeter, 1934; Acs and Audretsch 
1990); the creation of new firms and the resulting increased competition (Nickell et al. 
1997; Callejon and Segarra 1999); matching supply and demand (Kirzner 1979); input </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management </p>

<p>www.jbem.vgtu.lt 
2010, 11 2 : 259 282 </p>



<p>co-ordination (Coase 1937); monitoring input quality in team production (Alchian and 
Demsetz 1972); and risk taking (Knight 1921; Kihlstrom and Laffont 1979). </p>

<p>The vast majority of studies have focused on the causes of firm growth in the U.S. and 
in the most developed countries in Europe. Evidence regarding the influence firms have 
on employment growth in developing countries, especially in Latin America, is still very 
scarce. In light of this shortcoming, the purpose of this study is to explore the factors 
influencing firm size of new and established firms in Argentina. </p>

<p>Why was Argentina special and what can we learn from it? According Perry and Serven 
(2003) Argentina outperformed most other economies in the region until 1997 in terms 
of growth per capita (see Table 1) in a relatively benign external environment, in spite 
of a short-lived interruption in 1995 1 . But after the major slowdown in growth in 1999 
that affected the whole region, mainly due to capital flow retrenchment after the Russian 
crisis, other countries in the region began a modest recovery, while Argentina plunged 
into a protracted recession, reversing most of her previous gains at poverty reduction. </p>

<p>Table 1. Real GDP Growth Rate (Percentages) </p>

<p>Country 
1991-97 
1998 </p>

<p>1999 
2000-2001 
Argentina 
6.7 
3.9 
-3.4 
-2.1 
Bolivia 
4.3 
5.5 
0.6 
1.5 
Brazil 
3.1 
0.2 
0.8 
3.1 
Chile 
8.3 
3.9 
-1.1 
4.3 
Colombia 
4.0 
0.5 
-4.3 
2.2 
Costa Rica 
4.9 
8.4 
8.2 
1.3 
Ecuador 
3.2 
0.4 
-7.3 
3.9 
Mexico 
2.9 
4.9 
3.8 
3.3 
Peru 
5.3 
-0.4 
1.4 
1.9 
Venezuela 
3.4 
0.2 
-6.1 
3.3 
Average 
3.6 
3.2 
1.6 
2.1 </p>

<p>Source: World Development Indicators Database. World Bank (2010). </p>

<p>In this context, the bulk of papers are devoted to examine to which extent and why was 
the Argentine economy more vulnerable to adverse external shocks than other Latin 
American economies, and to what extent were policy mistakes the main culprit. In Rou-
bini (2001), it examines the vulnerabilities associated with deflationary adjustments to 
shocks under a hard peg. In Sachs (2002) the focus is the public debt, the fragile fiscal 
position and the strength in the banking sector. </p>

<p>Although there were important vulnerabilities in each of these areas, the impact was 
very different in the Argentina's firms. Especially important was the size of the firm 
to overcome this crisis. In this situation is very important try to understand the link 
between entrepreneur's characteristics and firm size. </p>

<p>1 When it suffered severe contagion from the so-called Tequila crisis. </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>The primary information upon which this research is based was collected during the 
period from April to September 2002, i.e. six months after the beginning of the most 
serious political and social crisis in Argentina's modern history (December 2001). In just 
one month (December 2001 -January 2002), President De La Rua resigned, three new 
transition presidents came and went in quick succession, and the Argentine currency 
was formally devalued by 40%. This resulted in economic chaos and a real devaluation 
of the peso of over 200%, with the currency dropping from 1 peso = $1 to almost 4 
pesos per dollar. </p>

<p>This crisis worsened entrepreneurs' general distrust of Argentina's public institutions, 
which was already poor the previous year (2001) when, according to the Latinobaro-
metro opinion survey, only 17% of the Argentine population had confidence in the 
Parliament or National Congress. Combined with the recession that had been worsening 
since 1998 (convertibility plan 1 peso = $1), the result was an unstable business envi-
ronment with a high level of uncertainty and hopelessness among small and medium-
sized entrepreneurs. Figure 1 shows the evolution of GDP per worker in Argentina over 
more than 50 years. </p>

<p>As can be appreciated in Figure 1, the crisis is related to this paper's period of analysis 
(2001-2002). </p>

<p>The contribution of our study to the existing literature is twofold. First, quantile regres-
sion based on work by Mata (1996) is used as a more suitable methodology to measure 
the determinants of firm size. Second, the previous objective is carried out in a context 
of economic and social of crisis where the lessons learned are even more important. </p>

<p>Our results show that the main sets of explanatory variables related to entrepreneurial 
characteristics (age, experience, education, and vocation) provide a full explanation of 
firm size. However, the group of variables related to the strategy continued by entre-
preneurs or the environment was less representative. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>4,1 </p>

<p>4,2 </p>

<p>4,3 </p>

<p>4,4 </p>

<p>4,5 </p>

<p>4,6 </p>

<p>4,7 </p>

<p>1950 
1952 
1954 
1956 
1958 
1960 
1962 
1964 
1966 
1968 
1970 
1972 
1974 
1976 
1978 
1980 
1982 
1984 
1986 
1988 
1990 
1992 
1994 
1996 
1998 
2000 
2002 
2004 
Log (GDP) and Log (Pop) </p>

<p>GDP_w </p>

<p>Population </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Real GDP per worker in Argentina from 1950 to 2004 </p>



<p>The study is structured as follows. Section 2 examines previous empirical research and 
hypotheses. Section 3 discusses data, variables, and methodology. In Section 4, we dis-
cuss our empirical findings; and Section 5 draws conclusions and implications. </p>

<p>2. Literature review and hypothesis </p>

<p>We can say that our work, on the characteristics of the entrepreneur in Argentina, joins 
other empirical studies conducted -in the last years -in other countries such as Mexico 
(Hernandez-Trillo et al. 2005; Heino 2006), USA (Kim et al. 2006; Goetz and Rupas-
ingha 2009), Germany (Wagner 2007; Fossen 2009), Japan (Masuda 2006), Sweden 
(Nykvist 2008), Republic of Korea (Kang and Heshmati 2008), Irish (Bhaird and Lucey 
2009), Italy (Bonaccorsi and Giannangeli 2008; Gagliardi 2009), Lithuania (Milius 
2008), and The Netherlands (Koster 2009). </p>

<p>Recent works (Mesnard and Ravallion 2006; Buera 2009; Quadrini 2009; Jaimovich 
2010) stress the need to include the entrepreneur's characteristics and others structural 
factors in the traditional models of economic development. In relation with entrepre-
neur's characteristics the literature considers different factors like: Age (Mondragón-
Vélez 2009), Gender (Minniti and Nardone 2007; Startiene and Remeikiene 2008, 
Kobeissi 2010), Race (Fairlie and Robb 2007), Education (Backes-Gellner and Werner 
2007; Van der Sluis et al. 2008), Risk Taking (Vereshchagina and Hopenhayn, 2009), 
etc. Relative to structural factors the literature has focused in: Liquidity Constraints 
(Oliveira and Fortunato 2006; Chapelle 2010), Credit Rationing (Blumberg and Let-
terie 2008; Gagliardi 2009), Regulations (Capelleras et al. 2008), Institutional context 
(Henrekson and Johansson 1999; Bowen and De Clercq 2008; Nyström 2008), Local 
Knowledge and Innovation (Bae and Koo 2009; Braunerhjelm et al. 2010), etc. </p>

<p>In order to explain the firm growth and its determinants, this paper uses Storey's (1994) 
analytical framework as its main guide. This framework proposes three main factors 
that can be seen as a variety of different elements: resources and characteristics of the 
entrepreneur (individual), the firm (organizational), strategy and environment. </p>

<p>At the individual level, the entrepreneur's human capital is often seen as a good indica-
tor of their likely success. Becker's (1964) theory of human capital extended micro-
economic analysis to a wide range of human behaviors and suggested that knowledge 
can increase cognitive ability and lead to more effective activity. Many scholars have 
examined the influence of human capital within the process of entrepreneurship (Cooper 
et al. 1994; Honig 2001; Peña 2004) and the positive effect human capital has on firm 
growth (McPherson 1996; Roper 1999; Walsilczuk 2000; Almus 2002). </p>

<p>For instance, the positive effect of formal education on firm survival and growth has 
been extensively reported (e.g. Cooper et al. 1994; Gimeno et al. 1997; Peña 2004). 
Prior experience has also been shown to influence firm growth, and entrepreneurs with 
some managerial experience, normally in their previous job, are likely to form firms 
which grow faster than firms started by individuals without such experience (Stuart and 
Abetti 1990; Storey 1994). </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>However, there is no consensus about the influence of gender on growth (Fischer et al. 
1993; Du Rietz and Henrekson 2000; Liedholm 2002). Several psychological traits and 
motivations have been found to influence firm growth (Roper 1999; Walsilczuk 2000; 
Baum et al. 2001; Sadler-Smith et al. 2001). </p>

<p>In order to examine how human capital and motivations affect the growth of SMEs, the 
following hypotheses will be tested: </p>

<p>H1: There will be a positive relationship between an individual's level of general hu-
man capital and firm size. </p>

<p>H2: There will be a positive relationship between entrepreneurial vocation and firm size. </p>

<p>Besides the characteristics related to entrepreneurs and firms, size also depends on the 
strategies employed by entrepreneurs themselves. In this respect, entrepreneurs con-
sciously select strategies and their choices, at least in part, reflect their views on what 
the optimal strategy should be in a given environment. Porter (1980) identifies three 
broad business-level choices: cost leadership, differentiation, and focus. Focus refers 
to competitive strategies that target a particular set of customers for a product line, or 
geographical market. The low-cost strategy involves the construction of efficient-scale 
facilities, the aggressive pursuit of cost reduction in all functions of organizations. Dif-
ferentiation strategies are designed to create and market innovative, high-quality prod-
ucts and/or services. The three competitive strategies are alternative, viable options to 
deal with the environmental forces, and to outperform firms that implement combined 
strategies. However, various authors suggest that strategy should be adapted to the en-
vironment (Tushman and Romanelli 1985; Sandberg and Hofer 1987). In this respect, 
McDougall et al. (1992) found that, with regard to small firm growth, broad strategies 
were more successful, thus questioning the otherwise common niche argument (Davids-
son et al. 2005). </p>

<p>As Capelleras and Rabetino (2008) mentioned, and according to Storey (1994), there 
are other strategic variables, considered actions taken by the entrepreneur after start-up, 
which are likely to have an impact on growth. For example, the use of a formal business 
plan or strategic planning. Delmar and Shane (2003, 2004) argue that business planning 
is central to the organizational activities of new ventures and firm growth. </p>

<p>Finally, many external factors may influence firm growth, such as location-specific 
advantages, industry-specific factors, macroeconomic conditions, and public policies. 
Authors like Shane and Kolvereid (1995) found strategy to have little influence on firm 
growth, whereas variations in national environments accounts for almost all perform-
ance variation. In this context, the industry sector has been shown to be a significant 
variable when analyzing firm growth (Davidsson et al. 2002). Several scholars conclude 
that the more dynamic industries are, the more firm growth there is (Jovanovic 1982; 
Audretsch 1995; Carroll and Hannan 1989, 2000). The location of the firm was also 
considered to have a potential influence on firm growth. </p>

<p>However, evidence is not conclusive with respect to the effect firm location has on 
growth (Birley and Westhead 1990; Storey 1994; Davidsson et al. 2002). </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>



<p>In order to examine how strategy and environment affect the growth of SMEs, the fol-
lowing hypotheses will be tested: </p>

<p>H3: The specific definition levels of entrepreneurial strategy (in terms of competitive 
price and the knowledge of competitors' prices) have a significant influence on firm 
growth. </p>

<p>H4: Location and industry activity will be significant variables in explaining firm 
size. </p>

<p>3. Data, variables, and methodology </p>

<p>3.1. Data, variables, and descriptive statistics </p>

<p>The determinants mentioned in earlier studies have led us to use two types of informa-
tion sources together in this paper. One is of a primary nature, using the entrepreneur 2 
as a unit of analysis, and the other is secondary, at the province level 3 . With respect to 
the sample selection for the primary analysis, as was mentioned above, we have con-
sidered firms located in 14 provinces in Argentina 4 , where the total number of firms is 
360,709 (data referring to July 2002), the target population being firms with between 
1 and 250 employees, representing 99.63% of all firms in Argentina. A total of 1,690 
firms (0.36%) employ more than 250 workers. </p>

<p>2 In this case, we have designed a specific survey to collect information about the characteristics of the 
environment in which the entrepreneurs operate, as well as their attitudes and behavior with respect 
to the economy and the management of the company. The method employed was a personal survey 
using a questionnaire that was specially designed for our research and self-administered by the firms. 
The firms were located within the borders of Argentina and came from all economic sectors, with a 
workforce of between 1 and 250 employees (total population 448.497 firms). The sample unit was 
the entrepreneur or person designated by this figure, and from a planned sample of 2.300 firms of 1 
to 249 employees, a real sample of 1.314 firms of under 250 employees was obtained. 
The surveys were done by means of personal interviews to entrepreneurship realized by auxiliary 
teachers and university students advanced and coordinated by teachers in the following universities: 
Universidad Nacional de Salta, Universidad Nacional de Jujuy, Universidad Nacional de Tucumán, 
Universidad Nacional de Catamarca, Universidad Nacional de Santiago del Estero, Universidad 
Nacional de Buenos Aires, Universidad Nacional de Misiones, Universidad Nacional del Nordeste, 
Universidad Nacional de San Juan, Universidad Nacional de Córdoba, Universidad Nacional de Río 
Cuarto, Universidad Nacional de la Patagonia y Universidad Nacional del Comahue. The Association 
of National Teachers of General Administration (ADENAG) was the institution that helped in this 
project. </p>

<p>3 Given the absence of official databases, we requested that the Center for Statistical Services -Special 
Works Division of the Argentine National Institute of Statistics and Census -generate a database 
that was specially designed for our research on the total population of companies in the formal sec-
tor of the Argentine economy. The content of the Report on Companies in Europe (Eurostat) was 
taken as its reference. </p>

<p>4 The choice of this scope of analysis was motivated by our interest in studying one of what is con-
sidered an emerging region (in a particularly complex time period due to its substantial political and 
economic instability), in contrast to those other studies referred to above that center on regions. </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>The representativeness of the sample were determined by province (see Table 2). Rep-
resentativeness by sector was 0.29% taking into consideration the total number of firms 
in the country (primary: 0.12; industrial: 0.4; construction: 0.25; and services: 0.31). </p>

<p>Table 2. Sample representativeness by province </p>

<p>Firms 
% of 
Total 
% of Total </p>

<p>No. </p>

<p>Province </p>

<p>Surveyed 
Sample 
Population Population </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>San Juan 
102 
7.76 
5204 
1.96 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Catamarca 
110 
8.37 
1835 
5.99 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Tucuman 
105 
7.99 
7565 
1.39 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Jujuy 
110 
8.37 
3008 
3.66 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Salta 
97 
7.38 
6303 
1.54 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>Santiago del Estero 
99 
7.53 
3204 
3.09 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>Chaco 
97 
7.38 
8312 
1.16 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Corrientes 
95 
7.23 
5221 
1.82 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>Chubut 
92 
7.00 
6434 
1.43 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Cordoba 
149 
11.34 
39315 
0.38 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Neuquen 
40 
3.04 
4748 
0.84 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>Rio Negro 
53 
4.03 
6814 
0.77 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>Misiones 
96 
7.31 
6501 
1.47 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Buenos Aires </p>

<p>69 
5.25 
256245 
0.02 </p>

<p>Totals 
1314 
100 
360709 </p>

<p>0.364 </p>

<p>We understand firm employment growth to be a multidimensional and complex phe-
nomenon. According to the literature review in the previous section, three sets of factors 
can be used to explain firm growth. Each of these components can be broken down 
into more detailed subset variables, which will be used in our empirical analysis. In 
this respect, firm growth (G) can be explained by the human capital of the entrepreneur 
(HC); the entrepreneur's strategy behavior (ST); as well as external factors or environ-
mental influences (E Regions +E Sector ), where is a firm-specific stochastic variable that is 
independent across firms: </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>As was previously mentioned (Delmar 1997; Weinzimmer et al. 1998; Wiklund 1998), a 
wide variety of different variable growth (G) measures have been used in the literature, 
such sales and employment, or other more subjective measures of growth. We favor 
measuring employment for different reasons: i) In the Argentine context, it minimizes 
inflation, currency, and accounting problems; ii) We are interested in researching organic </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>



<p>employment growth because this represents genuine job creation and not simply growth 
through acquisition. </p>

<p>The size distribution of the sample is briefly described in Figure 2 and Table 3. The 
typical Latin-American firm is quite small. </p>

<p>It is clear that the size distribution of firms is highly skewed and that 50% of them em-
ploy no more than five people, though average firm size is about 12 people. The present 
distribution does not conform to the statistical distributions that have been suggested in 
the literature which underlie the firm size distribution. However, our data do not have a 
normal distribution and thus dependent variables were transformed into a logarithm. </p>

<p>The Shapiro-Wilk normality test computed for the log of the firm size distribution gives 
a Z statistic of 7.39 significant at 1%. The mean values of firm sample are: firm age = 
16.5, entrepreneur age = 46.2, experience = 15.3 years, respectively. Males account 
for 75.27% of the total and 24.73% are female. With respect to their educational level, 
35.02% of the entrepreneurs had university studies and 64.92% had others. </p>

<p>As was mentioned before, one of the relevant factors to understand managerial growth 
is knowing the type of actions carried out by entrepreneurship. To determine this, three 
questions associated to the strategic aspects were formulated. First, How often is the 
planning process carried out? (annually, quarterly, monthly, or none). Second, which 
competitive position does their company occupy with respect to their most direct com-
petitors? (1 = very weak to 5 = very strong). Third, what is their cost strategy level with </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 
100 150 200 250 </p>

<p>Quantiles of Employment </p>

<p>0 
25 
5 
75 
1 </p>

<p>Fraction of the data </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Firm size </p>

<p>Mean 
Standard 
deviation 
Skewness Kurtosis Minimum 
Lower 
quartile 
Median Upper 
Maximum </p>

<p>12.567 
24.979 
4.930 
32.793 
1 
2 
5 
142 
245 </p>

<p>Table 3. Firm size: Descriptive statistics </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>respect to their most direct competitors? (1 = smaller, 2 = equal, 3 = larger, 4 = not 
known). Likewise, market expectations play an important role mainly on the manager's 
decisions which have a direct impact on company growth, given the conditions during 
the Argentinean crisis to which this paper refers. In this respect, besides controlling with 
dummy variables for county and sector, the manager was asked about his/her market 
estimate (1 = expansive, 2 = recessive, 3 = stable, 4 = not known). Finally, this section 
ends by presenting the descriptive statistics of the variables used which can be found 
below in Table 4. </p>

<p>Table 4. Quartile averages for key variables </p>

<p>10th 
25th 
50th 
75th 
90th </p>

<p>Variables </p>

<p>Age 
43.21 (11.69) 
44.63 
(11.71) </p>

<p>44.86 
(11.67) </p>

<p>48.20 
(12.04) </p>

<p>48.84 
(11.87) </p>

<p>Experience </p>

<p>12.07 (11.07) 
13.58 
(11.54) </p>

<p>13.91 
(10.47) </p>

<p>16.36 
(11.65) </p>

<p>18.66 
(11.11) </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Male 
33.33% 
26.18% 
28.53% 
23.90% 
16.36% </p>

<p>Female </p>

<p>66.67% 
73.82% 
71.47% 
76.10% 
83.84% </p>

<p>Vocation </p>

<p>No 
19.57% 
21.46% 
11.96% 
13.55% 
8.33% </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>80.43% 
78.54% 
88.04% 
86.45% 
91.67% </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>University studies 
31.16% 
25.75% 
28.53% 
38.65% 
48.15% </p>

<p>Others </p>

<p>68.84% 
74.25% 
71.47% 
61.35% 
51.85% </p>

<p>Family firm </p>

<p>No 
62.32% 
44.64% 
44.23% 
46.22% 
46.91% </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>37.68% 
55.36% 
55.77% 
53.78% 
53.09% </p>

<p>Business Plan </p>

<p>No 
26.09% 
26.19% 
30.43% 
26.30% 
45.06% </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>73.91% 
73.82% 
69.57% 
73.7% 
54.94% </p>

<p>Competitive position </p>

<p>Strong or very strong 
26.08% 
24.47% 
28.81% 
30.28% 
40.44% </p>

<p>Critical, weak, average </p>

<p>73.92% 
75.53% 
71.19% 
69.72% 
59.56% </p>

<p>Market estimate </p>

<p>Expansive or stable 
42.03% 
38.2% 
46.47% 
47.41% 
55.56% </p>

<p>Recessive or not known 57.97% 
61.8% 
53.53% 
52.59% 
44.44% </p>

<p>3.2. Model </p>

<p>In this section, the model that will be used in this paper is presented. The model is 
developed along the lines of small business economic theory (see, for example, Evans </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>



<p>1987; Jovanovic 1982). According to Basu and Goswami (1999), for the purposes of 
statistical analysis, Equation (1) can be transformed into a double log linear specifica-
tion as follows: </p>

<p>Log y i = 
(2) </p>

<p>and i </p>

<p>y = </p>

<p>t 
t </p>

<p>y </p>

<p>/ </p>

<p>1 , where i </p>

<p>y refers to the ith firm's sales for period t and x is is a pre-</p>

<p>viously mentioned vector of variables [the human capital of the entrepreneur (HC); 
the entrepreneur's strategy behavior (ST); external factors or environmental influences 
(E Regions +E Sector )]. </p>

<p>The empirical model specified in Equation (2) is estimated using the Regression Quan-
tiles (RQ) estimator as was introduced by Koenker and Bassett (1978, 1982). Quantile 
regression allows the effects of independent variables x is to be quantified at different 
points along the conditional distribution of the dependent variable y i . Assuming that the 
distribution function F of y is continuous, this is the θth quantile (0 ≤ θ ≤ 1), and Ψ θ is 
the value at which P(y &lt;Ψ θ ) = F(Ψ θ ) = θ. While OLS measures the effect of explana-
tory variables on the conditional mean of y, quantile regression measures the effect at 
any point along the conditional distribution, for example at the 50 th percentile (i.e., 
median), 75 th percentile, etc. </p>

<p>Mata and Machado (1996) point out a number of advantages of using the RQ estimator 
instead of standard lest square regression models. According to Görg and Strobl (2002), 
one of the advantages is that RQ enables different slope parameters to be estimated at 
different quantiles along the conditional distribution of the dependent variable. This 
may prove particularly valuable when estimating the effect of industry covariates on 
the start-up size of firms, where one may expect, for example, small firms (or entrants) 
to be affected differently by, say, minimum efficient scale (MES) than large firms. This 
should then be reflected in differences in the coefficients on the MES for the low and 
high quantiles of the conditional distribution for start-up size. </p>

<p>There are also disadvantages associated with the RQ estimator. Probably the main prob-
lem is that only asymptotic of the estimators are known, which raises the issue of how 
parameters behave in finite samples. This may not be too problematic in our case since 
we have a large sample. Though estimating quantile regressions is computationally </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>demanding, this problem was less so because of the availability of powerful comput-
ers and software programs such as <rs id="software-0" type="software">Stata</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.0</rs> which allow estimates to be performed 
relatively easily. </p>

<p>4. Empirical findings </p>

<p>The results of estimating Equation (2) for two models in which region variables are 
included where the company is located in Model 1 and GDP in Model 2 are reported in 
Table 5. For both models, the results for five different quantiles of the size distribution 
are reported, namely for the 0.1, 0.25, 0.5 (i.e. median), 0.75, and the 0.9 quantiles. 
Our choice of the lowest and highest quantiles, i.e., 0.10 and 0.90, was dictated by the 
nature of our data set. </p>

<p>Generally, an investigation of Table 4 reveals that there are statically significant differ-
ences in the coefficients between and among the various quantile regression estimates 
for most independent variables 5 . Specifically, it can be seen that the coefficients of the 
variables are linked to the founder of the company. The coefficients of age, experience, 
and the age*experience interaction varies significantly from 0.034 to -0.281, 0.042 to 
-0.779, and -0.010 to 0.132, respectively among quantiles. In this respect, in the 0.1 and 
0.25 quantiles, as the manager's experience and age increases, firm growth increases, 
although the effects that a combination of age and experience have are negative. That 
is to say that the effects of these two variables help the firm grow until the limits of age 
and experience are reached, with a subsequent decline in growth. </p>

<p>However, in the 0.5 to 0.9 quantiles, the initial effects of age and experience maintain 
an inverse relationship with growth, though the combined effect of age and experience 
produces a positive relationship. That is to say that starting at a limit, age and experi-
ence play a relevant role affecting firm size. The gender variable is significant in the 
0.75 and 0.9 quantiles, indicating that firms created/managed by women are smaller. 
As was expected, managers with university studies and a larger vocation experience 
more growth than those who do not possess these characteristics. Family firms have 
lower levels of growth linked to the inferior quantile. These results allow us to accept 
hypotheses H1 and H2, therefore affirming that a positive relationship exists between 
company size, human capital, and entrepreneur vocation. </p>

<p>However, the strategic factors that seek to capture entrepreneurial behavior indicate that 
entrepreneurs who plan their decisions are connected with companies of a larger size than 
those who do not plan. This result is shown as statistically significant for all quantiles. 
Likewise, there are no statistically significant differences for the planning periods. </p>

<p>5 To further evaluate the importance of the differences in the quantile parameter estimates presented in 
Table 4, we tested the equality of coefficients for any two quantiles as well as jointly for all quantiles. 
The tests were performed using the F-statistic. The results confirm the importance of the variables 
related to human capital, showing a major significance for most of the contrasts among quantiles 
(seven contrasts), with the exception of the comparison between the 0.1-0.25 and 0.75-0.9 quantiles 
(two contrasts). (The results were not included to save space.) </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>



<p>Model 1 </p>

<p>Model 2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.75 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>Variables 
Constant 
-0.114*** -0.278*** 0.807*** </p>

<p>1.733 </p>

<p>2.642*** 
-0.146*** -0.281*** </p>

<p>0.778*** </p>

<p>1.427*** </p>

<p>3.070*** </p>

<p>0.056 </p>

<p>0.102 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>0.233 </p>

<p>0.465 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>0.103 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>0.214 </p>

<p>0.326 </p>

<p>Entrepreneurial characteristics </p>

<p>Lnage </p>

<p>0.034** </p>

<p>0.103*** </p>

<p>-0.123*** 
-0.281*** -0.259** </p>

<p>0.036*** </p>

<p>0.109*** 
-0.110*** -0.151*** -0.321** </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.069 </p>

<p>0.127 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.057 </p>

<p>0.088 </p>

<p>Lnexperience </p>

<p>0.042* </p>

<p>0.094** </p>

<p>-0.322*** 
-0.676*** -0.779*** </p>

<p>0.057** </p>

<p>0.100*** 
-0.298*** -0.494*** -0.855*** </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.090 </p>

<p>0.188 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.084 </p>

<p>0.138 </p>

<p>Lnage*Lnexperience </p>

<p>-0.010* 
-0.031*** 0.059*** </p>

<p>0.131*** </p>

<p>0.132*** </p>

<p>-0.014** </p>

<p>-0.033*** </p>

<p>0.054*** </p>

<p>0.082*** </p>

<p>0.154*** </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>Gender (male=1) </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>-0.011 </p>

<p>-0.034** </p>

<p>-0.065** </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>-0.013* </p>

<p>-0.041** </p>

<p>-0.068** </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>Vocation (with vocation = 1) </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.019*** </p>

<p>0.034* </p>

<p>0.067* </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.021*** </p>

<p>0.037*** </p>

<p>0.071*** </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.037 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>Education (university studies </p>

<p>= 1) </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.014** </p>

<p>0.015*** </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.014** </p>

<p>0.014** </p>

<p>0.021* </p>

<p>0.042*** </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>Table 5. Estimation results of firm size </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>Family firm (family = 1) </p>

<p>-0.012*** -0.008 </p>

<p>-0.006 </p>

<p>-0.005 </p>

<p>-0.006 
-0.014*** -0.013** </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.016 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.026 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>Strategy 
Business plan (four categories) 
Quarterly </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>-0.005 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>-0.056** </p>

<p>-0.075 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>-0.055** </p>

<p>-0.084*** </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.055 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.038 </p>

<p>Monthly </p>

<p>-0.0005 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>-0.005 </p>

<p>-0.039 </p>

<p>-0.043 
-0.018*** -0.015 </p>

<p>0.005 
-0.054*** -0.062* </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.051 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>Improvised </p>

<p>-0.015*** -0.015* </p>

<p>-0.028*** 
-0.076*** -0.122*** </p>

<p>-0.026*** -0.025*** 
-0.024*** -0.089*** -0.108*** </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>Competitive position (five 
categories) </p>

<p>Weak </p>

<p>0.012* </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.015*** </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>Average </p>

<p>0.013** </p>

<p>0.016* </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.019*** </p>

<p>0.016* </p>

<p>0.021** </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>Strong </p>

<p>0.014** </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>-0.005 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.017*** </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>Very strong </p>

<p>0.034*** </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>-0.084 </p>

<p>0.049*** </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>-0.064 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.052 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>

<p>Continued Table 5 </p>



<p>Low-cost strategy (four 
categories) </p>

<p>Equal </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.040 </p>

<p>-0.529*** </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>-0.060 </p>

<p>-0.614*** </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.061 </p>

<p>0.119 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.056 </p>

<p>0.083 </p>

<p>Larger </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>-0.526*** </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.034 </p>

<p>-0.057 </p>

<p>-0.614*** </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.117 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.055 </p>

<p>0.081 </p>

<p>Not known </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>0.050 </p>

<p>-0.496*** </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>-0.049 </p>

<p>-0.549*** </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.064 </p>

<p>0.129 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.058 </p>

<p>0.084 </p>

<p>Environment </p>

<p>Market estimate (four 
categories) </p>

<p>Stable </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>-0.006 </p>

<p>-0.022 </p>

<p>-0.015 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>-0.005 </p>

<p>-0.014 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>Recessive market </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>-0.011 </p>

<p>-0.017 </p>

<p>-0.043** </p>

<p>-0.011 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>-0.008 </p>

<p>-0.028 </p>

<p>-0.006 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.045 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.020 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>Not known </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>-0.012 </p>

<p>-0.051** </p>

<p>-0.010 </p>

<p>-2.4 E04 </p>

<p>-0.006 </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>-0.029 </p>

<p>-0.026 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.052 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.029 </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.035 </p>

<p>LnGDP </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>0.013** </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.018 </p>

<p>-0.075** </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>Provinces (14 categories) 
Catamarca </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>Continued Table 5 </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.048 </p>

<p>Tucuman </p>

<p>-0.003 </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.054 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.041 </p>

<p>Jujuy </p>

<p>-0.012 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>-0.001 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>Salta </p>

<p>0.038*** </p>

<p>0.055*** </p>

<p>0.092*** </p>

<p>0.156*** </p>

<p>-0.084 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.106 </p>

<p>Santiago del Estero </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.027* </p>

<p>0.040*** </p>

<p>0.070** </p>

<p>-0.014 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.070 </p>

<p>Chaco </p>

<p>-0.014 </p>

<p>-0.009 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.064 </p>

<p>Corrientes </p>

<p>-0.0008 </p>

<p>-0.011 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>-0.074 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.063 </p>

<p>Chubut </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.024 </p>

<p>0.099 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.032 </p>

<p>0.067 </p>

<p>Cordoba </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.003 </p>

<p>0.026* </p>

<p>0.059** </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.079 </p>

<p>Neuquen </p>

<p>0.026** </p>

<p>0.036* </p>

<p>0.025 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.02 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.065 </p>

<p>Rio Negro </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.01 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>

<p>Continued Table 5 </p>



<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.019 </p>

<p>0.039 </p>

<p>0.070 </p>

<p>Misiones </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>-0.0005 </p>

<p>0.065** </p>

<p>-0.065 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.016 </p>

<p>0.033 </p>

<p>0.067 </p>

<p>Buenos Aires </p>

<p>0.006 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>0.174** </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.017 </p>

<p>0.036 </p>

<p>0.075 </p>

<p>Sectors (four categories) 
D_Industrial </p>

<p>0.012 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>-0.027 </p>

<p>0.016*** </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>-0.002 </p>

<p>-0.006 </p>

<p>0.009 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.031 </p>

<p>0.060 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.015 </p>

<p>0.030 </p>

<p>0.047 </p>

<p>D_Construction </p>

<p>0.031** </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.018 </p>

<p>-0.050 </p>

<p>0.035*** </p>

<p>0.023 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>-0.017 </p>

<p>-0.010 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.046 </p>

<p>0.090 </p>

<p>0.011 </p>

<p>0.021 </p>

<p>0.022 </p>

<p>0.042 </p>

<p>0.066 </p>

<p>D_Services </p>

<p>-0.007 </p>

<p>-0.0009 </p>

<p>-0.003 </p>

<p>0.004 </p>

<p>0.052 </p>

<p>-0.003 </p>

<p>-0.0009 </p>

<p>-0.023* </p>

<p>-0.012 </p>

<p>0.066 </p>

<p>0.008 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.028 </p>

<p>0.055 </p>

<p>0.007 </p>

<p>0.013 </p>

<p>0.014 </p>

<p>0.027 </p>

<p>0.043 </p>

<p>F(β 
i = 0) </p>

<p>2.91** </p>

<p>16.79*** </p>

<p>259.56*** 
183.50*** 88.16*** </p>

<p>9.17*** </p>

<p>16.79*** </p>

<p>14.67*** </p>

<p>17.15*** </p>

<p>10.52*** </p>

<p>F(equality) </p>

<p>4.59*** </p>

<p>21.74*** </p>

<p>12.63*** </p>

<p>5.20*** </p>

<p>4.59*** </p>

<p>24.18*** </p>

<p>13.24*** </p>

<p>5.67*** </p>

<p>No. observations </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>1302 </p>

<p>Note: Standard errors in the second line of each value of the estimated coefficient. ***,**,* represent significance at 1%, 5%, and 10%, 
respectively. Omitted group: males, no vocation, without university studies, non-family firm, annual planning, very weak competitive position, </p>

<p>smaller levels of costs, expansive market, county of San Juan, agriculture sector. </p>

<p>Continued Table 5 </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>



<p>Similarly, managers who manifest to be in an unfavorable competitive position run 
companies of a smaller size. However, when they respond to the question regarding 
their cost strategy with respect to the competition, the managers that indicated having 
smaller cost levels are connected with larger companies compared to the rest. This fact 
is reflected in the superior quantile (0.9). These results allow us to accept hypothesis 
H3 although statistical significance is not shown in all quantiles. The results reported in 
Table 4 are not as conclusive as those with reference to human capital. </p>

<p>The explanatory factors of the environment do not have the same importance as those 
relative to the human capital of entrepreneurs. As is shown in the results for Model 1 
(Table 5), only in the .75 quantile is it reflected that entrepreneurs who perceive market 
expectations in an expansionary way run larger firms compared to those with recessive 
market expectations or who do not know how it will evolve. The companies located in 
the counties of Salta, Cordoba, Neuquen, Misiones, and Buenos Aires are larger than 
companies in San Juan. There are no statistically significant differences with the rest 
of the counties. Finally, it should be said that there are no significant differences at the 
sectoral level. </p>

<p>With respect to Model 2, we observe the same behavior with regard to the variables 
that measure entrepreneurial characteristics and strategic behavior. The connection with 
LnGDP, the negative coefficients, which is statistically significant at the 95% level, 
could suggest that the economic situation in Argentinean firms as perceived by entrepre-
neurs improves as GDP declines in the 0.9 quantile, and vice versa in the 0.1 quantile. 
These results make it necessary to reject hypothesis H4. </p>

<p>In sum, the determinant of firm size depends on entrepreneurs' general and specific 
human capital and vocation as Becker (1964), Cressy and Storey (1995), and Cooper 
(1981) have suggested. However, although strategic factors and environment have had 
relative importance, they were not as significant as those relative to entrepreneurship. 
In this respect, authors like Mata and Machado (1996) and Görg et al. (2000) indicate 
the importance of industry characteristics in the determination of size. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>Four primary hypotheses are tested in this paper: a) Is the general and specific human 
capital of the entrepreneur positively related to firm size? b) Is the vocation of the 
entrepreneur positively related to firm size? c) Does the specific definition level of the 
entrepreneur's strategy (in terms of competitive price, knowledge of competitors' price) 
have an important influence on firm size? and d) Can location and type of industry be 
used as significant variables to explain firm size? </p>

<p>A sample of 1314 firms in the manufacturing, agriculture, construction, and service sec-
tors operating in Argentina in 2002 was used. The empirical answers provided by our 
analysis support the theoretical proposition that the higher the degree of general and 
specific Human this strongly related with the size of the firm. This result is related to 
those reached by Mata (1996) and Almus (2002). A positive effect of education on firm 
size has been extensively reported (Cooper et al. 1994; Burke et al. 2002). Personality </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>



<p>theories point to the importance of personal predispositions for venture success. In this 
context, a number of traits and motives of successful entrepreneurs have been identified, 
but these concepts have typically produced weak relationships with venture performance 
(Baum et al. 2001). However, our results were able to confirm the positive influence of 
motivation on firm size. </p>

<p>From a strategic point of view, we have been able to see the importance that planning 
has on the resources of a company as well as on its strategic behavior, concluding that 
larger firms are connected with entrepreneurs who carry out an annual planning process 
compared to those who do not plan. We have also found evidence that a better competi-
tive situation and knowledge of the competition is connected with larger. This result 
is interesting because competitive strategies reflect the choices of managers. Thus, the 
determinants of individual decision making and behavior are among the determinants 
of strategy because people choose plans in part on the basis of: a) what they are pre-
disposed to do, b) what they are motivated to do, and c) what they think they can do 
(Bandura 1986; Hollenbeck and Whitener 1988). </p>

<p>As was mentioned earlier, the explanatory factors of the environment have not had the 
same importance as those concerning the human capital of entrepreneurs. The relatively 
low impact of the environmental domain on firm size (market estimate, location, sectors) 
is perhaps surprising. Although other studies have found similar results in this direction, 
such as Baum et al. (2001). In our case, a possible explanation could be derived from 
the widespread crisis that existed during the period of analysis. However, De Jorge et al. 
(2007) indicated differences in regional dynamism as well as the relevant heterogeneity 
of the typology of different entrepreneurs in Argentina. In this respect, future research 
should explore the role played by environment on firm size and subsequent growth. It 
is also necessary to use longitudinal data for firms in order to monitor their employment 
change. Efforts should be made to further study the growth of new firms using data sets 
that are as comparable as possible across different countries in Latin America. </p>

<p>In terms of policy implications, these findings show that generic public programs may 
not be the best way to increase the firm's competitiveness. It would be better to design 
intervention strategies targeted toward specific characteristics of firms. In the context 
of the Latin American countries this is much more important since usually there is a 
tendency to generate general incentive policies -at the sector or regional level -that 
do not take into account the specific characteristics of the firms 6 . </p>



<p>6 The OECD (2001) provides a framework allowing policy-makers to identify strong and weak points 
in their country's business environment. This report concludes that four micro-drivers (human capi-
tal, information and communications technology, innovation and entrepreneurship) are key drivers 
of performace and economic growth. </p>

<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>





<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>





<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>





<p>Koenker, R.; Bassett, G. 1978. Regression quantiles, Econometrica 46(1): 287-312. 
doi:10.2307/1913643 </p>

<p>Koster, S. 2009. Individual foundings and organizational foundings: their effect on employment growth </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>





<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>





<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(2): 259-282 </p>





<p>J. de Jorge Moreno et al. Firm size and entrepreneurial characteristics... </p>

</text></tei>