<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2F1611-1699.2009.10.279-289" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Although any fi rm operates in a local environment, which includes specifi c economic, social and cultural con-
texts, there is still a lack of studies connecting culture and values with operations strategies and practices. This paper at-
tempts to explore a look at how cultural dimensions are connected with manufacturing strategies and choices. The current 
article is based on data from the International Manufacturing Strategy Survey (IMSS) project and the GLOBE study. Ad-
vanced mass production is more common to countries with high assertiveness, power distance and uncertainty avoidance. 
The model of manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural context is developed based on empirical results of the study. </p>

<p>Majority of manufacturing management literature has 
been content-related (Dangayach, Deshmukh 2001). At 
the same time in the framework developed for evalu-
ation of manufacturing strategy process Mills et al. 
(1995) suggest to consider also the fact that external 
context and research in multinational corporations has 
indicated, that organizational processes in manufac-
turing are infl uenced by national institutional features 
(Geppert, Matten 2006). The need to consider cul-
tural factors in strategic issues has been emphasized 
(Wilkinson et al. 2008). Galan and Sanchez-Bueno 
(2009) point out the importance of context factors as 
highly important in fi rm's choice of strategy. </p>

<p>Although any fi rm operates in a local environment 
which includes specifi c economic, social and cultural 
contexts (Moattar-Husseini, O'Brien 2004) and there 
has been signifi cant body of operations management 
research (Frohlich 2002; Rungtusanatham et al. 2003) 
there is still a lack of studies connecting culture and </p>

<p>values with operations strategies and practices. The 
paper tries to explore how cultural dimensions are 
connected with manufacturing choices and patterns of 
responses. </p>

<p>The use of fi eld-based empirical methodologies in the 
production and operations management (POM) area 
has been steadily increasing over the past decade. 
One of the most prominent among these is the survey 
research methodology which has often been used to 
capture data from business organizations (Malhotra, 
Grover 1998). </p>

<p>The article is based on data from the fourth Internation-
al Manufacturing Strategy Survey (IMSS) project and 
GLOBE study. Paper starts with theoretical framework 
for these studies. Which is followed by the results of 
an empirical analysis and the model of manufacturing 
strategies and choices in cultural context. </p>

<p>2. The research framework </p>

<p>According to comprehensive assessment of 285 sur-
vey research articles in operations management since 
the second half of the 1990s, two topics stood out as </p>

<p>________ </p>

<p>1 Research was supported by ETF grant 7537 </p>



<p>showing fastest ascendancy to prominence -opera-
tions strategy and supply chain management (Rungtu-
sanatham et al. 2003). Swamidass and Newell (1987) 
were among the first researchers who focused on 
connections between environment and manufactur-
ing strategy. Prochno and Correa (1995) connected 
manufacturing strategy with political and economic 
situation. </p>

<p>One of the most contributing surveys for studying 
manufacturing strategies on a global scale and at the 
national level is the International Manufacturing Strat-
egy Survey (IMSS) (Cagliano et al. 2008; Moattar-
Husseini, O'Brien 2004). First round of this survey was 
in 1993 (Lindberg et al. 1998). The research method is 
a questionnaire survey, performed by an international 
network of researchers in various countries. After data 
collection, a database from the entire worldwide study 
will be distributed to all contributing researchers and 
participating companies. </p>

<p>The framework of the study is based on a manufactur-
ing strategy perspective (Alas et al. 2009). This means 
that emphasis is placed on understanding the strategies 
and market priorities of the business units, the strat-
egy's translation into manufacturing objectives, the 
manufacturing practices, and the areas of current and 
future manufacturing improvement activities (Cagliano 
et al. 2008; Caniato et al. 2009). The questionnaire is 
divided into the following sections: 
A. Description, strategy and performance of the 
business unit. This section explores strategies, 
markets, primary modes of competition and cost 
structure data of the business unit. 
B. Description, strategy and performance of the 
dominant activities of the plant. This section ex-
plores the manufacturing strategy, process design 
and manufacturing performance of the dominant 
activity. 
C. Current manufacturing and supply chain prac-
tices, and past and planned improvement pro-
grammes. This section explores the structure 
(facilities, technology, and degree of integration) 
and infrastructure (organization, planning and 
control systems, quality, and product develop-
ment) and focuses on use and results from broad 
areas of activity, action programs, and improve-
ments, such as IT, automation, quality, empower-
ment, etc. </p>

<p>The goal of the questionnaire development was to 
provide the tool for fi nding connection of different 
manufacturing choices with macro-economic and so-
cio-cultural contexts. Current paper is focusing only 
on manufacturing strategies and choices in different 
cultural contexts. </p>

<p>Cultural context </p>

<p>Culture represents the culmination of a range of his-
torical experiences that have shaped an existing pattern 
(Forbes, Wield 2002). The deepest level of culture is 
values (McEwan 2001). Values are active standards 
that defi ne social and professional behavior (Rassin 
2008). Today most organizations are focused on eco-
nomic values, ethical and emotional values are under-
estimated (Raich, Dolan 2008). </p>

<p>There is no universally agreed-upon defi nition among 
social scientists for the term culture. For the GLOBE 
Project, which has been considered as one of the most 
comprehensive studies on national cultures, culture is 
defi ned as the shared motives, values, beliefs, iden-
tities, and interpretations or meanings of signifi cant 
events that result from common experiences of mem-
bers of collectives that are transmitted across genera-
tions (House, Javidan 2004). The most parsimonious 
operationalizations of societal culture consist of com-
monly experienced language, ideological belief sys-
tems (including religion and political belief systems), 
ethnic heritage and history. </p>

<p>Culture matters because it is a powerful, latent, and 
often uncon scious set of forces that determine both 
our individual and collec tive behaviour, perception, 
thought patterns and values. Globalization opens up 
many opportunities for business, but it also creates 
many challenges. One of the most important challeng-
es is acknowledging and appreciating cultural values, 
practices, and subtleties in different parts of the world. 
All experts in international business agree that to suc-
ceed in global business, managers need the fl exibility 
to respond positively and effectively to practices and 
values that may be drastically different from what they 
are accustomed to (House et al. 2004). </p>

<p>The GLOBE Project has studied diverse dimensions 
of societal and organizational cultures. To address this 
issue, 735 ques tionnaire items have been developed 
on the basis of prior literature and the theories of the 
GLOBE Project. Responses to these ques tions by mid-
dle managers in two pilot studies were analyzed by 
conventional psychometric procedures. These analyses 
resulted in the identifi cation of nine major attributes of 
culture (House, Javidan 2004): 
• Uncertainty Avoidance is the extent to which mem-
bers of an organization or society strive to avoid 
uncertainty by relying on established social norms, 
rituals, and bureaucratic practices. People in high 
uncertainty avoidance cultures actively seek to 
decrease the probability of unpredictable future 
events that could adversely affect the operation of </p>

<p>R. Alas et al. Manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural contexts </p>



<p>an organization or society and remedy the success 
of such adverse effects. 
• Power Distance is the degree to which members 
of an organization or society expect and agree that 
power should be stratifi ed and concentrated at high-
er levels of an organization or government. 
• Institutional Collectivism, or Collectivism I, is the 
degree to which organizational and societal insti-
tutional practices encourage and reward col lective 
distribution of resources and collective action. 
• In-Group Collectivism, or Collectivism II, is the 
degree to which individuals express pride, loyalty 
and cohesiveness in their organizations or families. 
• Gender Egalitarianism is the degree to which an 
organization or a society minimizes gender role dif-
ferences while promoting gender equality. 
• Assertiveness is the degree to which individuals 
in organizations or societies are assertive, con-
frontational and aggressive in social relationships. 
• Future Orientation is the degree to which individu-
als in organizations or societies engage in future-
oriented behaviours such as planning, investing 
in the future and delaying individual or collective 
gratifi cation. 
• Performance Orientation is the degree to which 
an organization or society encourages and rewards 
group members for performance improvement and 
excellence. 
• Humane Orientation is the degree to which an or-
ganization or society encour ages and rewards in-
dividuals for being fair, altruis tic, generous, caring 
and kind to others. </p>

<p>In order to examine manufacturing choices and re-
sponses in different cultural contexts, data from two 
international surveys -International Manufacturing 
Strategy Survey (IMSS) and Globe study -were com-
bined. </p>

<p>3. Empirical studies </p>

<p>3.1. Methodology </p>

<p>Fourth International Manufacturing Strategy Survey 
(IMSS) was designed to explore and identify strate-
gies, practices and performance of manufacturing fi rms 
around the world during 2005. The survey included 
711 companies in 23 countries: Argentina, Brazil and 
Venezuela from South America; Canada and USA from 
North America; Belgium, Denmark, Estonia, Germa-
ny, Greece, Hungary, Ireland, Italy, Norway, Portugal, 
Sweden, The Netherlands and United Kingdom from 
Europe; China, Israel and Turkey from Asia; also Aus-
tralia and New Zealand. </p>

<p>Independent country-based research teams performed 
surveys in each country. The overall coordinator of the 
project is Politecnico di Milano. </p>

<p>The primary method for data gathering was a question-
naire, which was distributed to the major business units 
in the ISIC 28-35 industrial sector within each country. 
The questionnaire was translated from English into lo-
cal languages and retranslated to English in order to 
be sure, that translation is accurate. The questionnaire 
was fi lled in by operations, manufacturing or technical 
managers of the companies. </p>

<p>The data about cultural dimensions listed in Appendix 
1 is taken from the Globe study (House et al. 2004; 
Alas 2006, Papalexandris 2006). Cultural practices 
were measured using the responses of middle manag-
ers to questionnaire items concerning "What Is", or 
"What Are", common behaviours, institutional prac-
tices, pro scriptions, and prescriptions. A 7-point scale 
was used, where '1' indicated 'strongly disagree' and 
'7' 'strongly agree'. </p>

<p>The authors of the current paper conducted both stud-
ies in one country: Estonia. </p>

<p>In order to group variables, principal component analy-
sis and exploratory factor analysis with varimax rota-
tion was completed. For grouping countries hierarchi-
cal as well as k-means cluster analysis was undertaken. </p>

<p>3.2. Subscales for manufacturing strategies </p>

<p>In order to reduce number of variables and get more 
reliable indicators, principal component analysis fol-
lowed by the exploratory factor analysis with varimax 
rotation was completed for the variables describing 
different aspects of manufacturing strategies and op-
erations. Some of the original variables were excluded 
from the analysis due to the bad fi t with the result-
ing factor model. In the fi nal model 3 factors explain 
66.6% of the total variance of 31 initial variables (see 
Appendix 2). The subscales for each factor were com-
puted by the aid of the regression algorithm built into 
the factor analysis tool in the <rs type="software">SPSS</rs> software. The in-
ternal reliability of our three subscales was confi rmed 
by theoretical fi t and also by the fact that the factor 
loadings of every initial variable were very high for 
one factor and relatively high proportion of the initial 
variance is described by the model. </p>

<p>The fi rst factor, where the following item has the high-
est factor loading: coordinating planning decisions 
and fl ow of goods takes place by collaborative plan-
ning, forecasting and replenishment with key/strategic 
customers, can be called Advanced Mass Production 
(F1-AMP). Companies ranking highly in this factor </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(4): 279-289 </p>



<p>manage or hold inventories of materials at customers' 
site(s) and may even have physical integration with the 
partner. Such methods as Management Product Life-
Cycle and Project Management by using of Enterprise 
Resource Planning (ERP) systems are also important. 
Job rotation between design and manufacturing takes 
place. Improvement goals for manufacturing function 
for the next 3 years are planned to improve companies' 
environmental performance and employee satisfaction. 
Also, over the past three years programs for quality 
improvement and control (e.g. TQM programs, 6σ 
projects, quality circles, etc.) have been undertaken. 
Mass production is dominating. </p>

<p>The second factor could be called Enterprise Resource 
Planning (F2-ERP). The companies ranking highly in 
this factor are becoming more contemporary through 
the use of Enterprise Resource Planning systems for 
supporting the most of core management areas: Pur-
chasing and supply management, Material manage-
ment, Production planning and control, Material man-
agement, Production planning and control, Account-
ing and fi nance, Distribution management and Sales 
management. Action program undertaken over the 
past three years is Rethinking and restructuring supply 
strategy and the organization and management of sup-
pliers portfolio through e.g. tiered networks, bundled 
outsourcing, and supply base reduction. Implementing 
Continuous Improvement Programs through system-
atic initiatives (e.g. kaizen, improvement teams, etc.) 
had been planned for the coming three years. </p>

<p>The third factor can be called the Most Fluctuating 
Demand (F3-MFD). The companies ranking highly 
in this factor value trustful relationship with custom-
ers achieved by delivering in time although demand 
is fl uctuating. In order to be able to do this, they share 
inventory level knowledge with key/strategic custom-
ers. In the cost structure the proportion of direct mate-
rials/parts/components is relatively high. Improvement 
goals for manufacturing function for the next 3 years 
are connected with increasing volume of fl exibility 
and labour productivity, and with reducing procure-
ment costs. </p>

<p>Values of factor variables for each country are given 
in Table 1. Also number of companies participating in 
survey from each country could be found in Table 1. 
For the fi rst factor China and Brazil have the highest 
values. Next are Israel and Turkey. Lowest are Ger-
many and Sweden. In the second factor Sweden and 
Brazil are the highest, lowest are New Zealand and 
Canada. In the third factor highest values are for Ven-
ezuela and Turkey, lowest for Australia and Israel. </p>

<p>Table 1. Values of 3 manufacturing factors in 
different countries </p>

<p>Country 
N 
F1 
F2 
F3 </p>

<p>Argentina 
44 
0.202 
-0.311 
0.304 </p>

<p>Australia 
14 
-0.094 
-1.187 
-2.376 </p>

<p>Belgium 
32 
-0.401 
0.601 
-0.551 </p>

<p>Brazil 
16 
2.027 
0.986 
0.327 </p>

<p>Canada 
25 
-0.065 
-1.727 
-1.088 </p>

<p>China 
38 
2.356 
0.152 
-0.736 </p>

<p>Denmark 
36 
-0.432 
0.793 
-0.692 </p>

<p>Estonia 
21 
0,.638 
-0.892 
0.427 </p>

<p>Germany 
18 
-1.334 
0.954 
0.945 </p>

<p>Greece 
13 
0.257 
0.117 
-0.703 </p>

<p>Hungary 
54 
-0.477 
-1.508 
1.479 </p>

<p>Ireland 
15 
-0.943 
-0.059 
0.217 </p>

<p>Israel 
20 
1.638 
0.156 
-1.892 </p>

<p>Italy 
45 
-0.471 
0.065 
0.033 </p>

<p>New Zealand 
30 
-0.768 
-2.247 
-0.280 </p>

<p>Norway 
17 
-0.728 
-0.803 
0.773 </p>

<p>Portugal 
10 
0.514 
-0.604 
0.306 </p>

<p>Sweden 
82 
-1.056 
1.417 
0.527 </p>

<p>The Netherlands 
63 
-0.672 
0.647 
-1.343 </p>

<p>Turkey 
35 
1.620 
0.940 
1.172 </p>

<p>United Kingdom 17 
-0.587 
-0.923 
-1.626 </p>

<p>USA 
36 
0.458 
0.003 
0.591 </p>

<p>Venezuela 
30 
1.070 
-0.223 
1.589 </p>

<p>Notes: Bold marks highest values, italic -lowest values. 
F1 -Advanced Mass Production ( F1-AMP) 
F2 -Enterprise Resource Planning systems users (F2-ERP) 
F3 -Most Fluctuating Demand (F3-MFD) </p>

<p>3.3. Connections between Manufacturing 
and Culture </p>

<p>The results of the correlation analysis in Tables 2 and 
3 indicate how cultural practices and values are con-
nected with three factors of manufacturing. These con-
nections are taken as the bases for developing model 
of manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural 
context. </p>

<p>3.4. Clusters of countries </p>

<p>Hierarchical cluster analysis using Average Linkage 
Between Groups indicated 5 clusters of countries. 
First cluster consists of Belgium, Denmark, The Neth-
erlands, Greece, Ireland, Italy, Germany and Sweden. 
Second is formed by Hungary, Norway, Estonia, Portu-
gal, Argentina, USA and Venezuela. Australia, United </p>

<p>R. Alas et al. Manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural contexts </p>



<p>Kingdom, Canada and New Zealand form the third 
cluster. The fourth cluster includes Brazil and Turkey, 
and the fi fth -China and Israel. </p>

<p>Table 4 lists the cluster centers which are the mean 
values of every cluster for underlying three factor 
variables. The fi rst cluster could be called traditional 
Europe. This cluster has the lowest value for the fi rst 
factor and average values for the second and third fac-
tors. This cluster compared to other clusters has the 
highest values for Future orientation and Uncertainty 
avoidance. </p>

<p>Table 4. Final Cluster Centers and means for 
Cultural variables </p>

<p>Clusters </p>

<p>1 
N = 8 </p>

<p>2 
N = 7 </p>

<p>3 
N = 4 </p>

<p>4 
N = 2 </p>

<p>5 
N = 2 </p>

<p>F1-AMP 
-0.63 0.24 -0.38 1.82 
2.00 </p>

<p>F2-ERP 
0.57 -0.62 -1.52 0.96 
0.15 </p>

<p>F3-MFD 
-0.20 0.78 -1.34 0.75 -1.31 </p>

<p>Cultural 
practices </p>

<p>Assertiveness 
4.17 
4.24 
4.04 
4.34 
3.98 </p>

<p>Institutional 
collectivism </p>

<p>4.36 
3.87 
4.49 
3.98 
4.54 </p>

<p>Group 
Collectivism </p>

<p>4.35 
5.15 
4.01 
5.48 
5.25 </p>

<p>Future 
Orientation </p>

<p>4.13 
3.66 
4.07 
3.82 
3.75 </p>

<p>Gender 
egalitarianism </p>

<p>3.52 
3.62 
3.48 
3.23 
3.12 </p>

<p>Humane 
Orientation </p>

<p>4.02 
3.84 
4.25 
3.84 
4.18 </p>

<p>Performance 
Orientation </p>

<p>4.04 
3.75 
4.46 
3.97 
4.20 </p>

<p>Power 
Distance </p>

<p>4.97 
5.32 
5.01 
5.34 
4.87 </p>

<p>Uncertainty 
Avoidance </p>

<p>4.64 
3.76 
4.63 
3.71 
4.39 </p>

<p>Note: Bold marks highest values, italic -lowest values. </p>

<p>The second cluster is a mixed cluster from peripheral 
European countries including also USA and two south 
American countries: Argentina and Venezuela. This 
cluster has the highest value on the third factor, middle 
value for the fi rst factor and relatively low value for the 
second factor. This cluster has the lowest Institutional 
collectivism, Uncertainty avoidance, Future orienta-
tion, Humane orientation and Performance orientation 
compared to other clusters. At the same time Gender 
egalitarianism is highest. </p>

<p>Table 2. Correlations between Manufacturing and 
cultural practices </p>

<p>F1 
F2 
F3 </p>

<p>Assertiveness 
.138(**) 
-.227(**) 
.095(*) </p>

<p>Institutional 
collectivism </p>

<p>-.297(**) 
.410(**) 
-.324(**) </p>

<p>Group 
Collectivism </p>

<p>.694(**) 
-.228(**) 
.356(**) </p>

<p>Future 
Orientation </p>

<p>-.332(**) 
.473(**) 
-.442(**) </p>

<p>Gender 
egalitarianism </p>

<p>-.518(**) 
-.057 
.127(**) </p>

<p>Humane 
Orientation </p>

<p>.048 
.077(*) 
-.374(**) </p>

<p>Performance 
Orientation </p>

<p>-.026 
-.131(**) 
-.594(**) </p>

<p>Power Distance 
.156(**) 
-.339(**) 
.629(**) </p>

<p>Uncertainty 
Avoidance </p>

<p>-.412(**) 
.448(**) 
-.401(**) </p>

<p>Notes: ** Correlation is signifi cant at the 0.01 level (2-tailed). 
* Correlation is signifi cant at the 0.05 level (2-tailed). 
F1 -Advanced Mass Production ( F1-AMP) 
F2 -Enterprise Resource Planning systems users (F2-ERP). 
F3 -Most Fluctuating Demand (F3-MFD) </p>

<p>Table 3. Connections between Manufacturing and 
cultural practices </p>

<p>Advanced 
Mass 
Production </p>

<p>Enterprise 
Resource 
Planning 
systems 
users </p>

<p>Most 
Fluctuating 
Demand </p>

<p>Assertiveness 
+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Group 
Collectivism </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Power 
Distance </p>

<p>+ 
-
+ </p>

<p>Institutional 
Collectivism </p>

<p>-
+ 
-</p>

<p>Future 
Orientation </p>

<p>-
+ 
-</p>

<p>Uncertainty 
Avoidance </p>

<p>-
+ 
-</p>

<p>Gender 
Egalitarianism </p>

<p>-
+ </p>

<p>Humane 
Orientation </p>

<p>+ 
-</p>

<p>Performance 
Orientation </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(4): 279-289 </p>



<p>The third cluster consists of Australia and New Zea-
land, UK and Canada. This cluster has the lowest val-
ues in the second and third factors and second lowest 
in the fi rst factor. Humane orientation and Performance 
orientation are the highest in this cluster. Group col-
lectivism is lower than in all other clusters. </p>

<p>The fourth cluster includes Brazil and Turkey and has 
very high values compared to the other clusters by all 
three factors. Also Assertiveness, Group collectivism 
and Power distance are highest in this cluster and Hu-
mane orientation and Uncertainty avoidance is lowest 
in this cluster. </p>

<p>The fi fth cluster consisting of China and Israel has 
the highest value for the fi rst factor, but the lowest 
for the third one. Institutional collectivism is the high-
est in this cluster. Assertiveness, Power distance and 
Gender egalitarianism are the lowest compared to other 
clusters. </p>

<p>4. Conclusions and discussion </p>

<p>Although any fi rm operates in a local environment 
which includes specifi c economic, social and cultural 
contexts (Moattar-Husseini, O'Brien 2004), there have 
been only few articles exploring manufacturing with 
soft issues (Fang, Wang 2006). This paper attempts 
to fi ll this gap. Based on data from the fourth Interna-
tional Manufacturing Strategy Survey (IMSS) project 
and GLOBE study, authors explored how cultural di-
mensions are connected with manufacturing choices 
and patterns of responses. </p>

<p>Data from International Manufacturing Strategy Sur-
vey (IMSS) enabled authors to fi lter out three dominant 
manufacturing strategies and choices: 
-Advanced Mass Production (F1-AMP), 
-Enterprise Resource Planning systems usage 
(F2-ERP), 
-Most Fluctuating Demand (F3-MFD). </p>

<p>Advanced Mass Production means coordinating plan-
ning decisions and fl ow of goods by collaborative 
planning, forecasting and replenishment with key/ 
strategic customers. Companies ranking highly in this 
factor also manage or hold inventories of materials at 
customers' site(s) and may even have physical integra-
tion with the partner. They use most advanced meth-
ods of Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems 
for managing product life-cycle. Job rotation between 
design and manufacturing gives possibility to develop 
both functions better by sharing knowledge between 
employees responsible for these two functions. Im-
provement goals for manufacturing function for the </p>

<p>next 3 years are to improve companies' environmental 
performance and employee satisfaction. Over the last 
three years programs for quality improvement and con-
trol (e.g. TQM programs, 6σ projects, quality circles, 
etc.) were undertaken. </p>

<p>Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP) systems users 
are becoming more contemporary through the use of 
Enterprise Resource Planning systems for supporting 
the most of core management areas: purchasing and 
supply management, material management, production 
planning and control, material management, produc-
tion planning and control, accounting and fi nance, dis-
tribution management and sales management. Action 
programs have been undertaken for rethinking and re-
structuring of supply strategy. Implementing Continu-
ous Improvement Programs through systematic initia-
tives (e.g. kaizen, improvement teams, etc.) has been 
planned for the coming three years. </p>

<p>The Most Fluctuating Demand requires trustful rela-
tionship with customers achieved by delivering in time 
although demand is fl uctuating. In order to be able to 
do this, inventory level knowledge is shared with key/ 
strategic customers. Improvement goals for manufac-
turing function for the next 3 years are connected with 
increasing volume fl exibility and labour productivity. 
At the same time procurement costs should be reduced. 
Cluster analysis grouped countries into 5 clusters ac-
cording to manufacturing strategies. </p>

<p>Based on IMSS survey in 1993 Moattar-Husseini and 
O'Brien (2004) compared 4 largest economies in Latin 
America with such industrially leading countries as 
USA and Japan and with industrially advanced Euro-
pean countries such as UK, Germany and Italy. They 
found that as a result of considerable environmental 
changes during last decades, fi rms in Latin American 
countries have had to adopt new strategies and these 
fi rms are catching up their competitors in well-estab-
lished industrial countries. According to current survey 
this trend has continued as Latin American countries 
belong to the same group with USA. The results of 
the survey indicate most advanced production taking 
place in Brazil. </p>

<p>Current paper indicates connections between manu-
facturing strategies and cultural orientations from the 
Globe study. </p>

<p>For example, countries with high fi rst factor values -
advanced mass production -have low uncertainty 
avoidance while at the same time there are less estab-
lished social norms, rituals, and bureaucratic practices 
in these countries. These countries have also high in-
group collectivism. Members of these societies express </p>

<p>R. Alas et al. Manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural contexts </p>



<p>pride, loyalty, and cohesiveness in their organizations 
or families. </p>

<p>In countries, where the value for the second factor 
is high -companies are becoming more contempo-
rary through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems for supporting the most of core management 
areas -Institutional collectivism, Uncertainty avoid-
ance and Future orientation are higher than in other 
countries. </p>

<p>Countries with high third factor values -the most 
fl uctuating demand -have higher power distance and 
lower performance orientation. Members of these so-
cieties expect and agree that power should be stratifi ed 
and concentrated at higher levels of an organization or 
government. Individual group members are not encour-
aged and rewarded for performance improvement and 
excellence. </p>

<p>Based on empirical data authors developed the Model 
of manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural 
context (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Based on connections between manufacturing strate-
gies and cultural practices three groups of cultural di-
mensions could be differentiated. </p>

<p>First group is formed from Assertiveness, Group Col-
lectivism and Power Distance. In the countries with 
higher Assertiveness, Group Collectivism, Power Dis-
tance the manufacturing strategy based on the use of 
Enterprise Resource Planning systems is more common 
than in other countries. The advanced mass production 
is more common in countries with lower Assertiveness, 
Group Collectivism and Power Distance practices. At 
the same time fl uctuation of demand can also be high. </p>

<p>The second group consists of Institutional collectiv-
ism, Future Orientation and Uncertainty Avoidance. 
Enterprise Resource Planning systems are more often 
used in the countries with lower Institutional Collec-
tivism, Future Orientation and Uncertainty Avoidance 
practices. Demand is more fl uctuating and there are 
more plants orientated to advanced mass production in 
countries with lower Institutional Collectivism, Future 
Orientation and Uncertainty Avoidance. </p>

<p>There are statistically less signifi cant connections and 
no regularity in the third group of cultural dimensions: 
Gender Egalitarianism, Humane Orientation and Per-
formance Orientation. </p>

<p>Societal cultural practices are divided into desired and 
undesired practices (Alas 2006). Practices, which form 
the fi rst group in the current study -high Assertive-
ness, Power distance and Uncertainty avoidance -are 
undesired practices. People in these countries want 
to change these. Second group in the current study is 
formed from the desired practices like Institutional col-
lectivism, Future orientation, and Uncertainty avoid-
ance. Humane orientation from the third group is also 
desired practice. In connections with development of 
human resource management function in organizations 
these groups of practices have been called enabling 
and disabling practices (Alas et al. 2008). But accord-
ing to results of current study authors found the terms 
'desired and undesired practices' more suitable. </p>

<p>To summarize the model, advanced mass production 
and more fl uctuating demand are more common to the 
countries with such undesired cultural practices as high 
Assertiveness, Power distance and Uncertainty avoid-
ance. Countries with desired cultural practices use En-
terprise Resource Planning systems in most of func-
tional areas, although previous research has indicated, 
that implementing ERP systems has proven unexpect-
edly diffi cult (Yen, Sheu 2004). Advanced mass pro-
duction moves out from countries with desired cultural 
practices to countries with undesired cultural practices. </p>

<p>To conclude, although there are several factors infl u-
encing manufacturing strategy and choices, cultural 
practices also have the connection with manufacturing. 
Advanced mass production moves out from countries 
with desired cultural practices to countries with unde-
sired cultural practices. Therefore, obtaining knowl-
edge about traditions and customs in a concrete coun-
try is useful before starting production in this country. </p>

<p>Alas, R. 2006. Ethics in countries with different cultural 
dimensions, Journal of Business Ethics 69(3): 237-247. </p>

<p>Alas, R.; Kaarelson, T.; Niglas, K. 2008. Human resource 
management in cultural context: empirical study of 11 coun-
tries, EBS Review 24(1): 50-62. </p>

<p>Alas, R.; Eklund, T.; Collan, M.; Kraus, A. 2009. Interna-
tional patterns in manufacturing strategies, in Pablos, P. O. 
and Lytras, M. D. (Eds.). The China Information Technology 
Handbook. Springer. Forthcoming. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Model of manufacturing strategies and choices in 
cultural context </p>

<p>Undesired cultural 
practices: 
Assertiveness 
Power distance 
Group Collectivism </p>

<p>-
-
-</p>

<p>Advanced 
Mass Production </p>

<p>Enterprise Resource 
Planning systems users </p>

<p>Most Fluctuating 
Demand </p>

<p>Desired cultural 
practices: 
Institutional 
Collectivism 
Future orientation 
Uncertainty 
avoidance </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(4): 279-289 </p>

<p>doi:10.1007/s10551-006-9088-3 </p>

<p>References </p>







<p>APPENDIX 1 </p>

<p>Cultural practices </p>

<p>Country 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 </p>

<p>United Kingdom 
4.23 
4.31 
4.08 
4.31 
3.67 
3.74 
4.16 
5.26 
4.70 </p>

<p>Germany 
4.66 
3.97 
4.16 
4.41 
3.25 
3.30 
4.42 
5.48 
5.35 </p>

<p>Sweden 
3.41 
5.26 
3.46 
4.37 
3.72 
4.09 
3.67 
4.94 
5.36 </p>

<p>Denmark 
4.04 
4.93 
3.63 
4.59 
4.02 
4.67 
4.40 
4.14 
5.32 </p>

<p>The Netherlands 
4.46 
4.62 
3.79 
4.72 
3.62 
4.02 
4.46 
4.32 
4.81 </p>

<p>Italy 
4.12 
3.75 
4.99 
3.34 
3.30 
3.66 
3.66 
5.45 
3.85 </p>

<p>Norway </p>

<p>Turkey 
4.42 
4.02 
5.79 
3.74 
3.02 
3.92 
3.82 
5.43 
3.67 </p>

<p>Ireland 
3.93 
4.57 
5.12 
3.93 
3.19 
4.96 
4.30 
5.13 
4.25 </p>

<p>Greece 
4.55 
3.41 
5.28 
3.53 
3.53 
3.44 
3.34 
5.35 
3.52 </p>

<p>Belgium </p>

<p>Hungary 
4.71 
3.63 
5.31 
3.31 
4.02 
3.39 
3.50 
5.57 
3.26 </p>

<p>Australia 
4.29 
4.31 
4.14 
4.09 
3.41 
4.32 
4.37 
4.81 
4.40 </p>

<p>New Zealand 
3.53 
4.96 
3.58 
3.46 
3.18 
4.43 
4.86 
5.12 
4.86 </p>

<p>Israel 
4.19 
4.40 
4.63 
3.82 
3.21 
4.07 
4.03 
4.71 
3.97 </p>

<p>USA 
4.50 
4.21 
4.22 
4.13 
3.36 
4.18 
4.45 
4.92 
4.15 </p>

<p>Canada 
4.09 
4.36 
4.22 
4.40 
3.66 
4.51 
4.46 
4.85 
4.54 </p>

<p>Estonia 
4.04 
3.71 
4.79 
4.20 
3.60 
3.39 
3.87 
5.16 
4.01 </p>

<p>Argentina 
4.18 
3.66 
5.51 
3.10 
3.44 
3.94 
3.63 
5.56 
3.63 </p>

<p>Brazil 
4.25 
3.94 
5.16 
3.90 
3.44 
3.76 
4.11 
5.24 
3.74 </p>

<p>China 
3.77 
4.67 
5.86 
3.68 
3.03 
4.29 
4.37 
5.02 
4.81 </p>

<p>Portugal 
3.75 
4.02 
5.64 
3.77 
3.69 
3.96 
3.65 
5.50 
3.96 </p>

<p>Venezuela 
4.26 
3.96 
5.41 
3.43 
3.60 
4.19 
3.41 
5.22 
3.55 </p>

<p>Notes: 
1 -Assertiveness 
2 -Institutional collectivism 
3 -Group Collectivism 
4 -Future Orientation 
5 -Gender egalitarianism 
6 -Humane Orientation 
7 -Performance Orientation 
8 -Power Distance 
9 -Uncertainty Avoidance </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(4): 279-289 </p>



<p>APPENDIX 2 </p>

<p>Factors of manufacturing strategies </p>

<p>Factor </p>

<p>1 
variance 
explained: 
27% </p>

<p>2 
variance 
explained: 
25% </p>

<p>3 
variance 
explained: 
14% </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Coordinate planning decisions and fl ow of goods with key/strategic customers: 
Collaborative Planning, Forecasting and Replenishment </p>

<p>.889 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
(ERP) systems : Product Life-Cycle Management </p>

<p>.852 
.264 </p>

<p>Coordinate design and manufacturing: Job rotation between design and 
manufacturing </p>

<p>.849 </p>

<p>Operational activity in plant performed using the following technologies: 
Automated guided vehicles (AGVs) </p>

<p>.845 
.204 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Project Management </p>

<p>.817 </p>

<p>Action programmes planned efforts for the coming three years: Increasing the 
technological integration between product development and manufacturing 
through e.g. CAD-CAM </p>

<p>.807 </p>

<p>Improvement goals for your manufacturing function for the next 3 years: 
Improving your environmental performance </p>

<p>.779 
.398 </p>

<p>Coordinate planning decisions and fl ow of goods with your key/strategic 
customers : You manage or hold inventories of materials at your customers' 
site(s) (e.g. Vendor Managed Inventory, Consignment Stock) </p>

<p>.769 </p>

<p>Process types (percentage of total volume): Mass production 
.742 
.419 </p>

<p>Coordinate planning decisions and fl ow of goods with key/strategic customers: 
Share production planning decisions and demand forecast knowledge </p>

<p>.699 
-.220 
.494 </p>

<p>Coordinate planning decisions and fl ow of goods with your key/strategic 
customers : Physical integration with the partner (e.g. cross-docking, co-location) </p>

<p>.683 
-.286 
.403 </p>

<p>Improvement goals for your manufacturing function for the next 3 years: 
Improving employee satisfaction </p>

<p>.679 
.418 </p>

<p>Degree of the action programs undertaken over the last three years: Undertaking 
programs for quality improvement and control (e.g. TQM programs, 6σ projects, 
quality circles, etc.) </p>

<p>.636 
.256 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Purchasing and supply management </p>

<p>.949 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Material management </p>

<p>.929 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Production planning and control </p>

<p>.853 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Accounting and fi nance </p>

<p>.847 
.262 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Distribution management </p>

<p>.791 
.211 </p>

<p>Operational activity in your plant performed using the following technologies : 
Automated parts loading/unloading </p>

<p>.223 
.780 
.215 </p>

<p>R. Alas et al. Manufacturing strategies and choices in cultural contexts </p>



<p>1 
2 
3 </p>

<p>Degree of the action programs planned efforts for the coming three years: 
Implementing Continuous Improvement Programs through systematic initiatives 
(e.g. kaizen, improvement teams, etc.) </p>

<p>.759 </p>

<p>Management areas supported through the use of Enterprise Resource Planning 
systems: Sales management </p>

<p>.271 
.725 </p>

<p>Action programs undertaken over the last three years: Rethinking and 
restructuring supply strategy and the organization and management of suppliers 
portfolio through e.g. tiered networks, bundled outsourcing, and supply base 
reduction. </p>

<p>.709 </p>

<p>Coordinate design and manufacturing: Formal meetings 
.606 
.244 </p>

<p>Action programs undertaken over the last three years: 
Restructuring manufacturing processes and layout to obtain process focus and 
streamlining (e.g. reorganize plant-within -a-plant; cellular layout, etc.) </p>

<p>.215 
.496 
-.249 </p>

<p>To win orders from your major customers: more dependable deliveries 
.853 </p>

<p>Improvement goals for your manufacturing function for the next 3 years: 
Increasing labor productivity </p>

<p>.326 
.792 </p>

<p>Improvement goals for your manufacturing function for the next 3 years: 
Reducing procurement costs </p>

<p>.220 
.787 </p>

<p>Coordinate planning decisions and fl ow of goods with your key/strategic 
customers: Share inventory level knowledge </p>

<p>.386 
.305 
.619 </p>

<p>Cost structure: Direct materials/parts/components 
.324 
.562 </p>

<p>Improvement goals for your manufacturing function for the next 3 years: 
Increasing volume fl exibility </p>

<p>.494 
.535 </p>

<p>Variation of market demand over a year: demand for lowest month 
-.302 
.240 
.517 </p>

<p>Extraction Method: Principal Component Analysis. 
Rotation Method: Varimax with Kaiser Normalization. 
a Rotation converged in 5 iterations. 
Factor loadings below 0.2 are not shown. </p>

<p>End of Appendix 2 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(4): 279-289 </p>

</text></tei>