<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2013.11" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The article presents issues of performance measurement. Currently, the performance plays an important role in man-
agement of companies. Usually, it could be defined as a system that uses the information to produce the appropriate changes in 
organizational culture, systems and processes to achieve optimal performance agreement targets, allocation of resources, informa-
tion management on possible modifications of business strategy or sharing the results continued individual goals. In many cases, 
the performance is very crucial competitive advantage in the market. Due the performance monitoring the companies can find 
the Key Performance Indicators, also known as KPIs that help to organization define and measure progress toward organizational 
goals. The main aim of the paper is to find which factors of corporate performance system are in Czech companies important. 
To find these factors was used theoretical information from the area of KPIs and data from primary research (questionnaire 
survey). This data are applied by statistical evaluation of selected indicators which can help determine the significance of the 
indicators in the monitored area. </p>

<p>The theme of this paper is the performance measurement, 
which can help to companies organize to achieve strategic 
goals in day-to-day activities. Indicators, that are used, are 
taken as the performance indicators. This is a group of in-
dicators that focus on the most critical areas for current and 
future development of the company. As we mentioned in 
the abstract of this paper, the performance is very crucial 
competitive advantage in the market and it should be in the 
interest of the enterprises monitor key indicators and factors. 
The company can improve performance by creating 
and implementing such a system performance measure-
ment and management, which will be used in accordan-
ce with the vision and strategy of the company and will 
integrate the different views of the performance -a view 
of the customer, the business owner, manufacturing and </p>

<p>financial manager. Historical perspective on performance 
measurement and management shows the evolution from 
traditional approaches based on the measurement of finan-
cial standards -profit, profitability, cash flow approaches to 
modern measurement value for the owners and sharehol-
ders (Aschenbrennerová 2010). 
Businesses operating in industrial markets are much 
more sensitive to sales volume in comparisons with com-
panies in the consumer market. Important problem in 
companies is that they do not measure own performance 
at the customer level, especially on a misunderstanding of 
the results obtained from previous successful marketing 
programs (Zahay, Griffin 2010). 
The main aim of the paper is to present theoretical infor-
mation from the area of Key Performance Indicators connec-
ted with data from primary research. This data are applied by </p>

<p>statistical evaluation, especially by factor analysis. A statisti-
cal evaluation of selected indicators can help determine the 
significance of the indicators in the monitored area. </p>

<p>1. Theoretical background </p>

<p>Performance measurement is an important tool for sustai-
nable management. Well-defined indicators can potentially 
support the identification of current and desired perfor-
mance and provide us with information on the progress 
of individual performances (Muchiri et al. 2010; West 
2011). In addition, it can be a link between strategy and 
management, thereby promoting the establishment and 
implementation of initiatives related to the improvement 
company (Maria 2009). 
Measurements can be divided according to the type 
of key indicators and results. The measureable indicators 
should be divided according their essence to several groups 
(Smith 2008; Zaherawati et al. 2011; Samsonova, Buxman, 
Gerteis 2009; Kocmanová, Karpíšek, Klímková 2012): </p>

<p>-Result indicators are focused on achieving the objecti-
ves of indicators (Key Goal Indicators -KGI). They 
represent a measure of success and verification success. 
Indicate whether the goal has been achieved. </p>

<p>-Critical success factors (CSF) includes the elements, 
which are essential for businesses to achieve their go-
als. They are used to manage, control and trace of the 
actions, which are necessary to achieve results. Once 
aware of these critical success factors is to determine 
key performance indicators easier. </p>

<p>-Performance indicators (efficiency) are focused on 
performance measurement and its support (Key Per-
formance Indicators -KPIs). They are used to quan-
tify objectives to reflect the performance of a process 
or service. They are usually used for measuring the 
value, efficiency, quality, and customer satisfaction. 
Indicators, contained in KPIs, must reflect business 
objectives, must be measurable and should become a 
key to success. </p>

<p>-Key Result Indicators (KRIs) includes information 
about many activities which have done and if company 
goes to right direction. KRIs provide such information 
which are prepared mainly for top management. 
KPIs could help to companies manage own priorities 
in various fields -environmental, governmental or social. 
These fields are linked with corporate strategy and usually 
include many non-financial indicators, for which exist rele-
vant information (Kocmanová, Dočekalová 2011). 
As the author Marinič (2008) and Parmenter (2010) 
mentioned, once defined the correct key indicators that ref-
lect goals of the company (those that can be measured), it 
is possible to use these performance indicators as a tool for 
performance measurement. It depends on the perspective </p>

<p>how entities inside and outside the company approach to per-
formance process, and why they monitor own performance. 
Measuring performance is quite difficult process. 
According Turban and Volonino (2010) measuring process 
needs to ensure four conditions: 
1. Identify the most useful indicators; 
2. Use them through correct measuring; 
3. Chose set of measures which provides indicator of 
total corporate performance; 
4. Define to whom is set intended. 
Performance system can rise by using selected tools, 
mainly by creating and implementing system of performan-
ce measurement and management, which will be used in 
accordance with the vision, mission and strategy of the com-
pany and will integrate different perspectives on corporate 
performance (De Lima, da Costa, Angelis 2009). 
Typical examples of KPIs should be market share, 
economic value added per employees, Return on capital 
employed, Return on equity or number of employees. These 
indicators are possible to involve into financial indicators 
(O'Sullivan, Abela, Hutchinson 2009). The KPIs includes 
huge amount of individual indicators of different fields 
(Hřebíček, Soukopová, Štencl, Trenz 2011; Kocmanová, 
Hornungová, Klímková 2010). </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>The first part of the paper presents main secondary infor-
mation, which was processed by many scientific articles and 
literature. Authors of the paper are interested in the area of 
performance measurement. The next, and the main part 
of the paper, is to introduce research data that was obtai-
ned from the primary research. Whole primary research 
was focused on the performance evaluation of enterprises 
(in the area of economic, social and environmental per-
formance) in the Czech Republic. The primary research 
was designed by questionnaire survey, focused on IT and 
agriculture companies in Czech Republic in 2011. The qu-
estionnaire was sent to 32 companies, from which answer 
only 23 companies. The conditions for choice were: 
1. size of company (number of employees over 250); 
2. geographical location (Czech Republic); 
3. classification of economic activities according to 
CZ-NACE, reduced to information and commu-
nication area; </p>

<p>-60 -Programming and broadcasting activities, </p>

<p>-61 -Telecommunications, </p>

<p>-62 -Computer programming, consultancy and 
related activities, </p>

<p>-63 -Information service activities). 
Basic sample was made by 32 companies to which were the 
questionnaire sent. From this amount of 32 companies we recei-
ved answers from 23 companies (effectiveness was almost 72%). </p>

<p> 
F. Milichovský, J. Hornungová. Methodology for the selection of financial indicators in the area of information... </p>

<p>In the paper there is utilized only one part of economics 
area. This count has been designed in different industry 
fields. From point of view of factor analysis this sample is 
adequate. 
Results and discussion of the paper are based on the ana-
lysis of secondary sources and selected data of questionnaire 
survey, which are involved on measuring the performance 
of Czech companies. To process the results of the question-
naire survey were used both of basic types of descriptive 
statistics and factor analyze on the selected data set. The 
data were processed by using the statistical program <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">IBM</rs> 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS Statistics</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">20</rs>. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>It is clear from analysis of results that companies usually 
use for measuring performance and corporate effective-
ness different indicators. Based on the analysis of statistical 
characteristics of the examined group we will present our 
conclusions as approximate result, which is limited by the re-
sulting reliability. In the results of the paper there are charac-
teristics of research barriers and next research possibilities. 
Table 1 includes rudimentary data where are clear that 
companies use in performance measurement system mainly 
return indicators, cash-flow indicators and profit indicators. 
The conclusions are given by the characteristics of the limits 
of research and its possible future direction. 
Based on the analysis of descriptive statistical charac-
teristics of the sample, our conclusions will be presented as 
an explorative result limited by the resultant reliability. The 
conclusions provide characteristics of the limitations of our 
research and its potential further direction. If the value of 
the Coefficient of variation is under 0.10, it indicates low 
variability, and arithmetic mean can be considered as typical 
value of the data file. Other way round, if the value is near 
to 1.00, it denotes high variability; arithmetic mean cannot 
be typical value. For this reason, it is appropriate to focus on </p>

<p>lower values. The maximum of results of the Coefficient of 
variation from questionnaire survey is 0.202. That means 
in all components could be mean accepted as typical value 
(see Table 1). 
Factor analysis gives up reduction of surveyed corpo-
rate performance indicators which, companies use in own 
measurement process. Main input into factor analysis was 
correlation matrix where showed individual correlation 
values of the chosen indicators are (see Table 2). 
From the values, listed in the Table 2, is possible to say 
that correlations exist only on five relations they are high-
lighted. These relations are: </p>

<p>-Free cash flow and EBIT (0.529); </p>

<p>-Market share and Free cash flow (0.529); </p>

<p>-Value added per personal costs and Value added 
(0.520); </p>

<p>-Value added per employee and Value added per per-
sonal costs (0.662); </p>

<p>-Market share and Value added per personal costs 
(0.580). 
To the KPIs is possible to insert only Market share and 
Value added per employee. Free cash flow, EBIT and Value 
added per personal costs could be involved in KRIs. 
Explained total variance of inputs in factor analyze des-
cribe process of extraction. Beginning of extraction (Initial 
Eigenvalues) comprehends whole components which 
were put into extraction. Second step (Extraction Sums of 
Squared Loadings) according the key (Eigenvalue &gt; 1) are 
reduced to the four strongest components which are used 
in next processing. Last step (Rotation Sums of Squared 
Loadings) show differences in individual components. 
From this point of view there is important Extraction 
Sums of Squared Loadings with cumulative percentage. 
Factor analysis extracted only two factors, which explain 
almost 70% of variance (exact amount was 69.773%). This 
result confirms good factor result of interpreted variance. </p>

<p>Table 1. Basic statistics indicators </p>

<p>EBT 
EBIT 
EAT 
Operating cash </p>

<p>flow 
Total free cash 
flow 
Free cash flow 
Profit margin 
Size turnover 
Value added 
Value added per 
personal costs 
Value added per 
employee 
Market share </p>

<p>Mean 
3.61 
3.13 
3.83 
3.43 
3.48 
2.87 
3.52 
3.74 
3.09 
1.91 
2.65 
2.30 </p>

<p>Standard deviation 
0.891 1.290 0.491 0.843 0.898 1.359 0.665 0.541 1.311 1.345 1.496 1.259 </p>

<p>Variance 
0.794 1.664 0.241 0.711 0.806 1.846 0.443 0.292 1.719 1.810 2.237 1.585 </p>

<p>Coefficient of variation 
0.049 0.094 0.121 0.024 0.155 0.160 0.201 0.137 0.066 0.156 0.202 0.175 </p>

<p>Source: own research </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(2): 97-102 </p>

<p>
Table 2. Correlation Matrix </p>

<p>EBT 
EBIT 
EAT 
Operating cash </p>

<p>flow 
Total free cash 
flow 
Free cash flow 
Profit margin 
Size turnover 
Value added 
Value added per 
personal costs 
Value addend 
per employee 
Market share </p>

<p>EBT 
1 
0.125 
0.045 0.418* -0.096 0.219 
0.207 -0.033 0.225 
0.311 
0.200 
0.232 </p>

<p>EBIT 
0.125 
1 
-0.178 -0.138 0.415 0.529 
0.129 
0.181 
0.020 
0.295 -0.187 0.478 </p>

<p>EAT 
0.045 -0.178 1 
0.410 
0.094 0.033 
0.151 
-0.007 0.307 
0.114 
0.285 
-0.278 </p>

<p>Operating cash 
flow 
0.418* -0.138 0.410 
1 
0.133* -0.107 0.144 
0.360* 0.499* 0.275 0.341* 
0.041 </p>

<p>Total free cash 
flow 
-0.096 0.415* 0.094 0.133 
1 
0.314* 0.324 0.456 0.272* 0.149 
0.062 
0.308* </p>

<p>Free cash flow 
0.219 
0.529** 0.033 -0.107 0.314 
1** 
0.481 0.075 0.236** 0.516 
0.245 
0.529** </p>

<p>Profit margin 
0.207 0.129 
0.151 
0.144 
0.324 0.481 
1 
0.395 -0.106 0.205 0.282 
0.236 </p>

<p>Size turnover 
-0.033 0.181 
-0.007 0.360 0.456 0.075 
0.395 1 
0.226 
0.155 
-0.005 0.255 </p>

<p>Value added 
0.225 0.020 
0.307 0.499* 0.272 0.236 -0.106 0.226 1 
0.520 0.503 
0.314 </p>

<p>Value added per 
personal costs 
0.311 
0.295 
0.114 
0.275 
0.149 
0.516 
0.205 0.155 
0.520 
1 
0.662 
0.580 </p>

<p>Value added per 
employee 
0.200 -0.187 0.285 0.341 0.062 0.245 0.282 -0.005 0.503 
0.662 1 
0.131 </p>

<p>Market share 
0.232 
0.478* -0.278 0.041 
0.308 0.529* 0.236 0.255 0.314* 0.580 0.131 
1* </p>

<p>* Correlation is significant at the 0.05 level 
** Correlation is significant at the 0.01 level </p>

<p>Source: own research </p>

<p>Table 3. Rotated Component Matrix </p>

<p>Profit 
Value added </p>

<p>Free cash flow 
0.779 
0.266 </p>

<p>EBIT 
0.870 
-0.203 </p>

<p>Market share 
0.779 
0.275 </p>

<p>Value added 
0.129 
0.770 </p>

<p>Value added per personal costs 
0.503 
0.761 </p>

<p>Value added per employee 
-0.063 
0.907 </p>

<p>Cronbach´s alpha 
0.759 
0.793 </p>

<p>Extraction Method: Principal Component Analysis. 
Rotation Method: Varimax with Kaiser Normalization. Rotation converged in 3 iterations. </p>

<p>Source: own research </p>

<p> 
F. Milichovský, J. Hornungová. Methodology for the selection of financial indicators in the area of information... </p>

<p>Total variance of the performance indicators is explai-
ned due eigenvalues, which represents the total variance 
explained by each factor. The eigenvalues found own figures 
and only two components have figures more over or is very 
close to 1. That means the two components make almost 
70 % of total variance of all four components. 
In extraction were divided all components into new 
two strongest component groups. These new component 
groups have diverse depth with previous four components 
(see Table 3). </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Cronbach's alpha is a measure of internal consistency, that 
is closely related to a set of items are as a group. A "high" 
value of alpha is often used (along with substantive argu-
ments and possibly other statistical measures) as evidence 
that the items measure an underlying (or latent) construct. 
However, a high alpha does not imply that the measure 
is unidimensional. If, in addition to measuring internal 
consistency, you wish to provide evidence that the scale 
in question is unidimensional, additional analyses can be 
performed. Exploratory factor analysis is one method of 
checking dimensionality. Cronbach's alpha is not a statis-
tical test; it is a coefficient of reliability (or consistency). It 
could be written as a function of the number of test items 
and the average inter-correlation among the items. Below, 
for conceptual purposes, we show the formula for the stan-
dardized Cronbach's alpha: </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>× 
α = 
+ 
− × </p>

<p>N c 
v N 
c 
, 
(1) </p>

<p>where N is equal to the number of items, 
c-bar is the average inter-item covariance among the 
items, 
v-bar equals the average variance. 
If would increase the number of items (N), is it possible 
to increase Cronbach's alpha. Moreover, if the average inter-
item correlation is low, alpha will be low. As the average 
inter-item correlation increases, Cronbach's alpha increases 
as well. 
Values of Cronbach's alpha could be reached from 0 to 
1. If the values would be close to 0.5, it signifies bad quality 
of internal consistency. Over 0.7 the value is acceptable and 
values close to 1 mean excellent. 
According our results, values of Cronbach's alpha were 
for Profit group in acceptable level, and for group of Value 
added almost in good level. 
First group depths especially "Free cash-flow" and "Market 
share". Second group impregnates primarily "Value added per 
employee" and "Value added per personal costs". That means 
the informative value of the indicator is very credible. These 
two groups define two synthetic dimension of view on mea-
suring performance with impact on managerial decision. </p>

<p>In order to assess, whether it is possible to use factor 
analysis, was used Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin method (KMO) and 
Bartlett's test of sphericity. KMO method is based on selective 
correlation and partial correlation coefficients. Value range 
of KMO is between 0 and 1. Each variable correlates perfectly 
with itself (approximate to 1), but has no correlation with 
the other variables (approximate to 0). In our case KMO 
reached value of 0.655, what means that the performed level 
of usefulness of factor analysis is at average level. 
Bartlett's test of sphericity is statistic test that is used to exa-
mine the hypothesis that the variables are correlated or uncor-
related. There was found no correlation with other variables 
(Sig = 0.000). Nevertheless, Bartlett's Test of Sphericity is 
significant because of the value which is lower than 0.05. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The correct choice of performance indicators is important 
part of the corporate strategic process. The definition of 
performance indicators is quite difficult because of com-
plexity of measureable areas. 
Limitation of this paper is focusing on domestic compa-
nies. Therefore it is necessary to do next researches where 
is possible to use knowledge not only in domestic envi-
ronment, but especially in international environment to 
ascertain the influence of corporate performance measu-
rement system. 
Despite a great progress in the understanding and utili-
zation of findings and experience with marketing manage-
ment by companies in the Czech environment. Our research 
showed that there is large space for improvement and can 
offer new and new ways for companies to be competitive. 
Company is able to create a comprehensive performance 
evaluation system that measures the economic indicators 
and thus can assess how strong the company is on the ove-
rall. Complex assessment of company is much better and 
more effective than individual performance measurement. 
The reason for this is mainly the fact that only some of the 
indicators are directly measurable and comprehensive eva-
luation is necessary to take into account both indicators long 
and short term performance. 
The article is focused on the area of economic perfor-
mance in relation to KPIs. Currently more and more com-
panies use in their management performance measurement 
that is important not only for the actual management, but 
also for other interested parties involved in the entity with 
each other stakeholders. Performance measurement is an 
important tool for sustainable management. And sustaina-
bility is a term that can be more and more often heard from 
various areas of the Czech environment. 
The aim of the article is to present application of theoreti-
cal information from the area of Key Performance Indicators 
(KPIs) connected with the data from primary research. This data 
were applied by statistical evaluation by factor analysis. Data for </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(2): 97-102 </p>

<p>
this article were obtained from the project funded by the Grant 
Agency (Czech Science Foundation), named "Construction of 
Methods for Complex Multifactor Assessment of Company 
Performance in Selected Sector", No. P403/11/2085. 
Empirical research deals with factor analysis that gives 
up reduction of surveyed corporate performance indicators 
which companies use in own measurement process. Main 
input into factor analysis was correlation matrix. From this 
matrix were obtained data that tell us, that in our case cor-
relations exist only on four economic indicators (Free cash 
flow, Value added per personal costs, Value added per emplo-
yee, Market share). Then we found two strongest component 
groups. In connection with the KPIs it is possible to insert only 
Market share and Value added per employee. Free cash flow 
and Value added per personal costs could be involved in KRIs. 
If company declares that is efficient and effective, it should 
be able to demonstrate with indicators, standard or other pro-
cedures it used. Companies would not miss comparison with 
direct competitors in industry area as is shown by current level 
of knowledge. That is possible with suitably selected indica-
tors, according to using tools, whether financial or non-finan-
cial (Milichovský, Solčanský, Sychrová 2011). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This paper is supported by the Czech Science Foundation. 
Name of the Project: 'Construction of Methods for 
Multifactor Assessment of Company Complex Performance 
in Selected Sectors' . Registration No. P403/11/2085. </p>



<p> 
F. Milichovský, J. Hornungová. Methodology for the selection of financial indicators in the area of information... </p>

</text></tei>