<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2016.534" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>(Peltier 2005), RIPRAN method (Lacko 2004; Doležal et al. 
2012) and more. 
Risks evaluations are essential activities of management 
of project risk. It is directly determines the success or failure 
of a project. It is often based on vague, inconsistent, parti-
ally subjective data (knowledge) items of interdisciplinary 
nature. 
For this reason, in risk management used different 
approaches, techniques and tools, both traditional and 
advanced. For example expert method, brainstorming, si-
mulation, fuzzy sets, e.g. methods of fuzzy numbers and 
fuzzy logic. 
The authors Banaitiene et al. present a research in area of 
construction projects. The aim of the research is to discover 
how construction companies perceive the significance of the 
construction projects risks they face and the extent to which 
they employ potential risk responses (Banaitiene et al. 
2011). Abstract. The article deals with the use of fuzzy logic as a support of evaluation of total project risk. A brief description of actual 
project risk management, fuzzy set theory, fuzzy logic and the process of calculation is given. 
The major goal of this paper is to present am new expert decision-making fuzzy model for evaluating total project risk. This fuzzy 
model based on RIPRAN method. RIPRAN (RIsk PRoject ANalysis) method is an empirical method for the analysis of project 
risks. The Fuzzy Logic Toolbox in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> software was used to create the decision-making fuzzy model. The advantage of the 
fuzzy model is the ability to transform the input variables The Number of Sub-Risks (NSR) and The Total Value of Sub-Risks 
(TVSR) to linguistic variables, as well as linguistic evaluation of the Total Value of Project Risk (TVPR) -output variable. With this 
approach it is possible to simulate the risk value and uncertainty that are always associated with real projects. The scheme of the 
model, rule block, attributes and their membership functions are mentioned in a case study. The use of fuzzy logic is a particular 
advantage in decision-making processes where description by algorithms is extremely difficult and criteria are multiplied. </p>

<p>Project management is nowadays a widely discussed 
theme. This fact is substantiated by numerous scien-
tific articles, books and publications dealing with these 
problems (Bergantiños, Vidal-Puga 2009; Pérez et al.  2005; Rosenau 2007; Schwable 2011). This discipline 
is also included in the courses of numerous faculties 
focusing on economy both in the Czech Republic and 
abroad. Experts are also associated in various profession-
al organizations or associations (International Project  Management Association 2014; Project Management  Institute 2014; AXELOS 2015). 
Project risk management is the responsibility of the 
entire life cycle of project. Risk management of the pro-
ject consists of process of risk analysis and process of risk 
monitoring. Project manager or other members of project 
team can for risk project analysis use some methods (Rais,  Smejkal 2013): scoring method (Podmolík 2006), FRAAP 
method -Facilitated Risk Analysis and Assessment Process </p>

<p>mathematical theory and gray relational analysis method in 
the risk evaluation of construction project (Zhang, Li 2011). 
The authors Park et al. present a systematic framework 
for risk management is proposed for handling risk factors, 
risk degrees, integrated risk degree, and responding activi-
ties with corresponding data flow diagrams in their article 
"A Risk Management System Framework for New Product 
Development (NPD)" (Park et al. 2011). 
The research by the authors Liu and Ye presented mo-
dels for comprehensive evaluating modelling of investment 
project risk with trapezoid fuzzy linguistic information. A 
practical example for evaluating the investment project risk 
is used to verify the developed approach (Liu, Ye 2015). 
The method of fuzzy logic applied to the risk mana-
gement process is described in (Nasirzadeh et al. 2014). 
The authors present an integrated fuzzy system dynamic 
modelling for quantitative risk assessment. The values of 
the various factors, which are characterized by the nature 
of uncertainty, are defined by fuzzy numbers. The proposed 
model was simulated at different levels of risk; the optimum 
level of risk is determined by the point at which the mini-
mum cost of the project. See e.g. (Nasirzadeh et al. 2014). 
The same risk issues of construction projects are pre-
sented by authors Yao-Chen Kuo and Shih-Tong Lu. This 
study deals with a fuzzy multiple criteria decision-making 
(FMCDM) approach to systematically assess risk for a me-
tropolitan construction project where twenty risk factors 
were identified. Triangular fuzzy sets are used for describing 
of identified factors. The overall risk level of the project 
depends on the individual impact of individual risk factors; 
the scheme was evaluated based on the relative impact and 
likelihood. They note that the suggested model for risk as-
sessment is more reliable, more convenient than traditional 
statistical methods, and that this model can be used to ef-
ficiently identify risks metropolitan construction projects. 
See Kuo and Lu (2013). 
An article by Nieto Morote-and-Ruz Vila is a methodo-
logy for risk assessment based on fuzzy set theory, which 
is an effective tool for dealing with subjective assessments. 
The proposed methodology is based on the knowledge 
and experience gained from many experts. Risk factors are 
evaluated by qualitative criteria in the form of trapezoidal 
fuzzy numbers. Fuzzy numbers describe the uncertainty 
variables at the language level. See e.g. (Nieto-Morote, Ruz-
Vila 2011). 
In the study 'The moderating effect of risk on the 
Relationship between planning and success' authors 
Zwikael, Pathak, Singh, Ahmed deal with examination the 
relationship between the project planning process and its 
success. They show the level of success (measured in the 
form of risk) associated with the project plan. They conclude 
the high risk projects must be carefully planned. See e.g. 
(Zwikael et al. 2014). </p>

<p>The science aim of the paper is to present a new expert 
decision-making fuzzy model for evaluation of the total 
project risk. This fuzzy model is based on RIPRAN method, 
specifically on the phase: risk assessment. See below. This 
phase evaluates the total project risk based on two parame-
ters: the number of sub-risks and the total value of sub risk. 
For creating of model is used fuzzy set theory and fuzzy 
logic. See below. 
The advantage of fuzzy sets in comparison with the clas-
sical set theory is its ability to record inaccurate (vague) 
concepts that project managers use natural language in the 
design and implementation of projects. Individual charac-
teristics associated with the process of project management, 
although the project practice countable relatively well, but 
usually only with large variance. This means that they are 
more or less well estimated. 
The current approach in the area of risk engineering 
applied either numerical values of probability and impact, 
or worked with classical sharp jurisdiction of these values 
into certain sets, which for many applications not appro-
priate and did not correspond to the actual perception of 
risk. Fuzzy approach to modeling these processes minimizes 
this shortcoming. 
Research in the field of evaluation of total project risk is 
based on an empirical research. This research was realised in 
region Vysočina in Czech Republic in the first half of 2014. 
A secondary analysis was used to obtain and process rele-
vant secondary data. General theoretical methods, based 
on principles of logic and logical thinking (analysis -synt-
hesis, induction -deduction, abstraction -concretization), 
were used to own processing, especially for pronouncing of 
conclusions. Fuzzy modelling (fuzzy set theory and fuzzy 
logic) was used to create the decision-making fuzzy mode. 
For identification of rules of the fuzzy model was used met-
hod guided interview with experts in project management. 
The advantage of the fuzzy model is the ability to trans-
form the input variables The Number of Sub-Risks (NSR) 
and The Total Value of Sub-Risks (TVSR) to linguistic va-
riables, as well as linguistic evaluation of the Total Value of 
Project Risk (TVPR) -output variable. 
Application of fuzzy logic (Dostál 2011) is based on 
the fuzzy set theory (Zadeh 1965; Zimmermann 2001;  Klir, Yuan 1995). The theory of fuzzy sets and applica-
tions of fuzzy logic in project management also focused 
a lot of authors (Relich, Muszyński 2014; Khazaeni et al.  2012; Nassif et al. 2013; Relich 2013; Relich 2012). Authors 
Kuchta, Chanas and Zielinski, Oliveros and Fayek, Bushan 
Rao and Shankar presented fuzzy sets using fuzzy numbers 
to obtaining critical paths of project (Kuchta 2001; Chanas,  Zielinski 2001; Oliveros, Fayek 2005; Bushan Rao, Shankar  2012). The technique EVM is also scientific goal for some 
authors (Naeni et al. 2011; Lipke et al. 2009; Khamooshi,  Golafshani 2014). </p>

<p> 
R. Doskočil. An evaluation of total project risk based on fuzzy logic </p>

<p>1. Theoretical background </p>

<p>RIPRAN (RIsk PRoject ANalysis) method is an empiri-
cal method for the analysis of project risks. Author of the 
RIPRAN method is Associate Professor Branislav Lacko. 
RIPRAN method can be used in all phases of the project. 
The method was originally created for risk analysis automa-
tion projects in the framework of the research project at the 
Technical University in Brno. Experience has shown that 
after certain adjustments, it is possible to apply the method 
for risk analysis of a wide range of different projects and 
in some cases also for the analysis of other types of risks 
than are project risks. RIPRAN method is a trademark, 
registered author of the Industrial Property Office in Prague 
under reg.no. 283536 (Lacko 2014). 
The risk analysis process by RIPRAN method comprises 
the following phases: 
-Risk preparing -agreement on the process, identifi-
cation of materials, team building, identification of 
relationships. 
-Risk identification -identification of threats and sce-
narios. Can be used risk trees. 
-Risk quantification -identification of probabilities 
of threats and impact of scenarios. 
-Risk response -identification of steps to reduce the 
risk. 
-Risk assessment -total project risk evaluation based 
on the number of sub-risks and the total value of 
sub-risks (Lacko 2014; 2004). </p>

<p>2. Materials and methods </p>

<p>A fuzzy set is a set whose elements have degrees of mem-
bership. Fuzzy set was introduced by Lotfi A. Zadeh in 
1965 as an extension of the classical notion of set and can 
be applied in many fields of human activity. Fuzzy set de-
termines "how much" the element belongs to the set. This 
is the basic principle of fuzzy set. 
A fuzzy set is defined following: Let X is a non-empty set 
and µ </p>

<p> 
A </p>

<p>: 
  
→   
0; 1 
X 
. Then fuzzy set  
A is a set of all ordered 
pairs µ ) 
( , 
) 
( 
A x 
x 
therefore </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>= 
µ 
∈ µ 
∈  
  </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p> 
, 
: 
, 
0;1 . </p>

<p>A 
A </p>

<p>A 
x 
x x X 
x 
(1) </p>

<p>Where X is a universe, µ </p>

<p> 
A </p>

<p>is a membership func-
tion of fuzzy set  
A , see Fig. 1. Triangular and trapezoidal 
type of the membership function, and µ 
 ( ) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>x is a grade 
of membership of x. µ </p>

<p> 
A </p>

<p>is defined for all ∈ 
x X and 
( 
0 
) 
µ 
= </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>x </p>

<p> </p>

<p>for ∉  
x A . 
A support of a fuzzy set  
A is the classical set </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>= ∈ µ 
&gt; </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
supp 
: 
) 0 . 
( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A x X 
x 
(2) </p>

<p>A kernel or core of a fuzzy set  
A is the classical set </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>= ∈ µ 
= </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
ker 
: 
. 
) 1 
( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A x X 
x 
(3) </p>

<p>A height of a fuzzy set  
A is the number </p>

<p>= 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
hgt 
sup 
( ). </p>

<p>x A </p>

<p>A 
x 
(4) </p>

<p>For example when fuzzy set  
A is "about 2", see 
triangular membership function in Figure 1, then 
= 
 
supp 
(1; 3), 
A </p>

<p>{ } </p>

<p>= 
 
ker 
2 
A 
and 
= 
 
hgt 
1 
A 
. 
Let α be a number form   
  
0; 1 then α level cut of fuzzy 
set  
A is a classical set </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>α = 
∈ 
µ 
≥ α </p>

<p> </p>

<p>: 
) 
. 
( </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>A 
x X 
x 
(5) </p>

<p>A fuzzy set </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>= 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
R, A 
A 
is called real fuzzy number on 
set of real number R when fulfils following conditions: 
-Fuzzy set  
A is convex ( µ </p>

<p> 
A </p>

<p>is a convex function). 
-Fuzzy set  
A is normal ( 
= 
 
hgt 
1 
A 
). 
-µ </p>

<p> 
A </p>

<p>is a piecewise continuous function. 
With fuzzy numbers basic binary operations are used, 
e.g. + − ×  
, , , . Let * is a binary operation on R then an 
extended binary operation on  , where  is a set of all </p>

<p>fuzzy numbers, means a operation  , e.g. ⊕ ,  , ⊗ ,  . </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>µ = 
µ 
µ </p>

<p> 
 
 
 
 
sup 
, 
* </p>

<p>min 
( 
, 
. 
) 
( ) ( ) </p>

<p>B 
A B 
A 
x y 
x y z </p>

<p>z 
x 
y 
(6) </p>

<p>Practical computing of the extended binary operations 
is often realised by α level cut (5). For increasing binary 
operation the extended binary operations is </p>

<p>α 
α 
α∈  
  </p>

<p>= 
α 
  </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p>0;1 </p>

<p>. 
A B 
A 
B 
(7) </p>

<p>If we denote α </p>

<p>α 
α </p>

<p> 
 
=  
 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>; 
A 
a a 
and α </p>

<p>α 
α </p>

<p> 
 
=  
 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>; 
B 
b b 
then 
the extended binary operation for increasing binary opera-
tion * is </p>

<p>α 
α 
α 
α 
α 
α </p>

<p> 
  
 
=  
  
 
 
 </p>

<p>1 
2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>; 
; 
. 
A 
B 
a a 
b b 
(8) </p>

<p>Each α level cut of fuzzy number can be regarded as 
the interval number. The interval number means interval 
  
  
; , 
a b where ≤ 
a b , a and b are real numbers. The interval 
numbers are a special case of fuzzy number, so arithmetic </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Triangular and trapezoidal type of the membership 
function </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2016, 17(1): 23-31 </p>

<p>
operations with interval number have properties of opera-
tions with fuzzy numbers (Karpíšek 2009). 
Arithmetic operations on interval numbers are defined 
following relationships (Dostál 2008): </p>

<p>     
 
+ 
= + 
+ 
     
 
; 
; 
; 
a b 
c d 
a c b d ; 
(9) </p>

<p>     
 
− 
= − 
− 
     
 
; 
; 
; 
a b 
c d 
a d b c ; 
(10) </p>

<p>{ 
} 
{ 
} </p>

<p>; · ; </p>

<p>min , , , 
; max , , , 
; </p>

<p>a b c d </p>

<p>ac ad bc bd 
ac ad bc bd </p>

<p>    = 
    
 
 
 
 
(11) </p>

<p> 
 
      
  
= 
∉ 
      
  
 
 
1 
1 
; / ; 
; · 
; 
for 0 
; 
a b 
c d 
a b 
c d 
d 
c 
. (12) </p>

<p>Fuzzy logic measures the certainty or uncertainty of how 
much the element belongs to the set. By means of fuzzy logic 
it is possible to find the solution of given task from rules, 
which were defined for analogous tasks. The calculation of 
fuzzy logics consists of three basic steps: fuzzification, fuzzy 
inference and defuzzification (Fig. 2). 
1. Fuzzification -transforms real variables to linguis-
tic variables using their attributes. The variable has 
usually from three to seven attributes. The attribute 
and membership functions are defined for input 
and output variables. The degree of membership of 
attributes is expressed by mathematical function -
membership function (Π, Z, S, etc.) (Dostál 2011). 
2. Fuzzy inference -defines the behavior of system by 
using of rules of type &lt;When&gt;, &lt;Then&gt; on linguistic </p>

<p>level. Conditional clauses typically have the follow-
ing form: 
&lt;When&gt; [Input_a1 &lt;And&gt; Input_a2 &lt;And&gt; ... 
&lt;And&gt; Input_an] &lt; And &gt; [Input_b1 &lt;And&gt; Input_ 
b2 &lt;And&gt; ... &lt;And&gt; Input_bm] &lt;Then&gt; Output_1. 
Each combination of attributes of input and output 
variables, occurring in condition &lt;When&gt;, &lt;Then&gt;, 
presents one rule. The rules are created by the user 
or expert himself (Dostál 2011). 
3. Defuzzification -transfers the results of fuzzy infer-
ence (numerical values) on output variables by linguis-
tic values. It describes results verbally (Dostál 2011). 
The system with fuzzy logic works as an automatic sys-
tem. The user must enter input data only. These can be re-
presented by many variables and their attributs. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>The case study presents the use of fuzzy logic at evaluation 
of total project risk base on RIPRAN method. The Fuzzy 
logic Toolbox of the <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> software was used for the 
creating of the decision making model. At first is it ne-
cessary to design the variables, their attributes and their 
membership functions. 
The developed expert decision-making fuzzy model 
system (ERS_TVPR) consists of two input ariables with 
five attributes, one rule block and one output variable also 
with five attributes. The inputs are represented by two varia-
bles: The Number of Sub-Risk (NSR) and The Total Value of 
Sub-Risks (TVSR). Both input variables are very important 
indicators based on RIPRAN method. The output from the 
rule block and the output variable is The Total Value of 
Project Risk (TVPR) (Fig. 3). 
It was used membership function of the shape Π in 
the model. This membership fuction names trapmf (tra-
pezoidal-shaped). Syntax of the function is following: y = 
trapmf(x,[a b c d]). Description of the trapezoidal curve is 
a function of a vector, x, and depends on four scalar para-
meters a, b, c, d, as given by </p>

<p>≤ 
 
 
 
 
− 
 
 
≤ ≤ 
 
 
− 
 
 
≤ ≤ 
=  
 
 
 
− 
 
 
≤ ≤ 
− 
 
 
 
 
≤ 
 
 </p>

<p>0; </p>

<p>; </p>

<p>1; 
( ; , , , ) </p>

<p>0; </p>

<p>x a 
x a a x b 
b a 
b x c 
f x a b c d 
d x c x d 
d c 
d x </p>

<p>. 
(13) </p>

<p>The parameters a and d locate the "feet" of the trapezoid 
and the parameters b and c locate the "shoulders". Figure 4 
denotes trapmf trapezoidal-shaped membership functions. 
As can be seen from the chart, the function has a value 
between 0 and 1, which also characterises how much it be-
longs to a certain fuzzy set. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Decision-making -solved by fuzzy processing 
(Dostál 2011) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Build up model </p>

<p> 
R. Doskočil. An evaluation of total project risk based on fuzzy logic </p>

<p>The following Figures 5 and 6 show the attributes and 
membership functions of the variables. 
Figure 5 shows the input variable NSR with five attribu-
tes (membership functions): VH -very high, H -high, M -
middle, L -low and VL -very low. It was used membership 
function of type Π (trapmf) and range [0;100] to creation 
of fuzzy model. The parameters of membership functions 
are adjusted balanced for each of the variables. The mem-
bership function VH -very high has the parameters: [-22.5 
-2.5 2.5 22.5]. The membership function H -high has the 
parameters: [2.5 22.5 27.5 47.5]. The membership function 
M -middle has the parameters: [27.5 47.5 52.5 72.5]. The 
membership function L -low has the parameters: [52.5 72.5 
77.5 97.5]. The membership function VL -very low has the 
parameters: [77.5 97.5 102.5 122.5]. 
The input variable TVSR has got also with five attributes 
(membership functions): VH -very high, H -high, M -
middle, L -low and VL -very low. It was used membership 
function of type Π (trapmf) and range [0;100] to creation 
of fuzzy model. The parameters of membership functions 
are adjusted balanced for each of the variables. The mem-
bership function VH -very high has the parameters: [-22.5 
-2.5 2.5 22.5]. The membership function H -high has the 
parameters: [2.5 22.5 27.5 47.5]. The membership function 
M -middle has the parameters: [27.5 47.5 52.5 72.5]. The 
membership function L -low has the parameters: [52.5 72.5 
77.5 97.5]. The membership function VL -very low has the 
parameters: [77.5 97.5 102.5 122.5]. 
Figure 6 shows the output variable TVPR with five attri-
butes (membership functions): VH -very high, H -high, 
M -middle, L -low and VL -very low. It was used mem-
bership function of type Π (trapmf) and range [0;100] to 
creation of fuzzy model. The parameters of membership 
functions are adjusted balanced for each of the variables. 
The membership function VH -very high has the parame-
ters: [-22.5 -2.5 2.5 22.5]. The membership function H -
high has the parameters: [2.5 22.5 27.5 47.5]. The members-
hip function M -middle has the parameters: [27.5 47.5 52.5 
72.5]. The membership function L -low has the parameters: 
[52.5 72.5 77.5 97.5]. The membership function VL -very 
low has the parameters: [77.5 97.5 102.5 122.5]. 
Figure 7 shows the rule box with 25 rules and degree of 
support that set up the relationship between the input and 
output variables. 
The module allows you to set rules and work with them. 
Rule number one is a situation where: </p>

<p>&lt;If&gt; = NSR = VH &lt;And&gt; TVSR = 
VH &lt;Then&gt;TVPR = VH. </p>

<p>Interpretation of the rules is as follows: If the Number 
of Sub-Risk (NSR) is very high (VH) and the Total Value of 
Sub-Risks (TVSR) is very high (VH), then the Total Value 
of Project Risk (TVPR) is evaluated to be very high (VH). </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Membership function -Trapmf </p>

<p>Fig. 5. The attributes and membership functions of input 
variable NSR </p>

<p>Fig. 6. The attributes and membership functions of output 
variable TVPR </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2016, 17(1): 23-31 </p>

<p>
Similarly can be interpreted other fuzzy rules in the model. 
The listing of a combination of all 25 of the rules of the 
system based on the following linear distribution (Table 1). 
Explanatory combination rules of the system. 
Input variable NSR and TVSR: 
1 -VH (very high) 
2 -H (high) 
3 -M (middle) 
4 -L (low) 
5 -VL (very low) 
Output variable TVPR: TVPR = VH (very high) 
TVPR = H (high) 
TVPR = M (middle) 
TVPR = L (low) 
TVPR = VL (very low) 
The list and combination of fuzzy rules for the total pro-
ject risk evaluation system is based on an empirical research 
into the given subject carried out by the guided interview 
method. These rules can be change or defined for specific 
project. 
Figure 8 shows correlation between inputs and output 
variables. Concretely this picture shows graphically corre-
lation between two input variable NSR, TVSR and output 
variable TVPR. It is a functional dependence TVPR = f 
(NSR, TVSR). 
Point with coordinates [0; 0] represents the situation 
where the input variable NSR is very high and the input 
variable TVSR is very high, then the output variable TVPR 
is evaluated as very high. 
Point with coordinates [100; 100] represents the si-
tuation where the input variable NSR is very low and the 
input variable TVSR is very low, then the output variable 
TVPR is evaluated as very low. 
Graphical display of dependencies of input and output 
variables allows you to check the set parameters of fuzzy 
model. Generally speaking, the displayed area of the model </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Rule block and rules </p>

<p>Table 1. The listing of a combination of rules </p>

<p>NSR 
TVSR 
NSR 
TVSR 
NSR 
TVSR 
NSR 
TVSR 
NSR 
TVSR </p>

<p>1 
1 
2 
1 
3 
1 
4 
1 
5 
1 </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH 
TVPR = H TVPR = M </p>

<p>1 
2 
2 
2 
3 
2 
4 
2 
5 
2 </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH 
TVPR = H TVPR = M TVPR = L </p>

<p>1 
3 
2 
3 
3 
3 
4 
3 
5 
3 </p>

<p>TVPR = 
VH 
TVPR = H TVPR = M TVPR = M TVPR = VL </p>

<p>1 
4 
2 
4 
3 
4 
4 
4 
5 
4 </p>

<p>TVPR = H TVPR = M TVPR = M TVPR = VL TVPR = VL </p>

<p>1 
5 
2 
5 
3 
5 
4 
5 
5 
5 </p>

<p>TVPR = M TVPR = M TVPR = VL TVPR = VL TVPR = VL </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Correlation between variables </p>

<p> 
R. Doskočil. An evaluation of total project risk based on fuzzy logic </p>

<p>is satisfactory because the specified rules and members-
hip functions selected model adequately generalize. User 
(expert) can change this variables how for presentation in 
graphs. In this graphs you can see very important informa-
tion about fuzzy model. </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Figure 9 shows the evaluation of total project risk of concre-
te project. The input variables are set up NSR = 0, TVSR = 
0. It leads to the result (output) TVPR = 7.29 which means 
that the total risk of the project is very high. 
Using the first rule is expressed by the output variable 
TVPR coloration ( Fig. 9). 
Figure 9 shows the result, where the total value of risk of 
concrete project is evaluated as very high. The model was 
verified in this manner. The results match the requirement, 
so fuzzy model can be regarded generally as functional. 
After the model is created, it must be tuned (to set up the 
inputs on known values, evaluate the results and change the 
rules or weights, if necessary). The tuning and validation of 
the fuzzy model must be realised on real data of the project. 
The parameters of the model must be adjusted on the basis 
of the real data for each of the variables. If the validation 
shows, that the model provides relatively accurate results, 
can be used in practice. 
For implementation of fuzzy model in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> 
software was created executable file called "M-file". This file 
contains the following sequence of commands (Fig. 10). 
This file is used to enter the input values (NSR, TVSR) 
and automatically evaluate the total value of project risk 
(TVPR). 
The first line (see Fig. 10) loads a variable BCHRP from 
the file ERS_TVPR.fis. There are the parameters of fuzzy 
model in this file. The second line (see Fig. 10) loads the 
input variables: The Number of Sub-Risk (NSR); The Total 
Value of Sub-Risks (TVSR). The third line (see Fig. 10) im-
plements an evaluation with command evalfis. Inputs are va-
riable DataBTVPR and parametres of fuzzy model BTVPR. 
The value of the output is the variable EvaluationBTVPR. 
The fourth to ninth line (see Fig. 10) implements own eva-
luation. When the value of the output variable is evaluated 
less than 20, then the output linguistic value is Very high 
value of the total project risk. When the value of the output 
variable is evaluated in the interval from 20 to 40, then the 
output linguistic value is High value of the total project risk. 
When the value of the output variable is evaluated in the 
interval from 40 to 60, then the output linguistic value is 
Middle value of the total project risk. When the value of the 
output variable is evaluated in the interval from 60 to 80, 
then the output linguistic value is Low value of the total 
project risk. When the value of the output variable is eva-
luated more than 80, then the output linguistic value is Very </p>

<p>low value of the total project risk. Command fuzzy(BTVPR) 
displays and allows set-up work fuzzy model (see Fig. 10, 
line 10). Command mfedit(BTVPR) displays and allows 
edit membership functions of input and output variables 
(see Fig. 10, line 11). Command ruleedit(BTVPR) displays 
and allows edit fuzzy rules (see Fig. 10, line 12). Command 
surfview(BTVPR) displays graphical viewing dependency 
input and output variables (see Fig. 10, line 13). Command 
ruleview(BTVPR) displays and allows testing and simu-
lation output variable to input variables (see Fig. 10, line 14). 
If the M-file called TVPR.m is used to simulate (in 
<rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> software) a request to enter inputs [The Number 
of Sub-Risk and The Total Value of Sub-Risks] is displayed. 
After enter inputs e.g.: The Number of Sub-Risk = 0 and 
The Total Value of Sub-Risks = 0 in forme [0;0], is receive 
the result TVPR = Very high value of the total project risk 
(Fig. 11). 
After enter inputs e.g.: The Number of Sub-Risk = 100 
and The Total Value of Sub-Risks = 100 in forme [100;100], is </p>

<p>Fig. 9. The evaluation of total project risk of concrete project </p>

<p>Fig. 10. M-file -TVPR.m </p>

<p>Fig. 11. Evaluation of calculation -Very high value of the 
total project risk </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2016, 17(1): 23-31 </p>

<p>
receive the result TVPR = Very low value of the total project 
risk (see Fig. 12). 
The advantage of fuzzy sets in comparison with the 
classical set theory is its ability to record inaccurate (va-
gue) concepts that project managers use natural language 
in the design and implementation of projects. Individual 
characteristics associated with the process of project mana-
gement, although the project practice countable relatively 
well, but usually only with large variance. This means that 
they are more or less well estimated. The current approach 
eg. In the field of risk engineering applied either numerical 
values of probability and impact, or worked with classical 
sharp jurisdiction of these values into certain sets, which for 
many applications not appropriate and did not correspond 
to the actual perception of risk. Fuzzy approach to modeling 
these processes minimizes this shortcoming. Application 
of fuzzy modeling approach controversial (in relation to 
the possibilities and practical usability exact calculation) 
selected project processes is one of the major contributions 
of this paper. 
Suggested model is recommended to apply repeatedly 
throughout the project life cycle. Applications reentrancy 
proposed model is otherwise a static model added an ele-
ment of dynamism, but they are mainly obtained data on the 
future development of the project. This will not only project 
managers with valuable information and hence knowledge 
to support further decisions. Another advantage of the pro-
posed model is the possibility of a subsequent experiment 
with it eg. through simulation. This is more information 
available about a possible variant development projects and 
to get warning signals to support future decisions. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The expert fuzzy decision-making model of evaluation of 
total project risk is only one of possible options how to 
use fuzzy logic for support of decision-making. This paper 
presented a new expert fuzzy model, based on the RIPRAN 
method, specifically on the phase: risk assessment. This 
phase evaluates the total project risk based on two parame-
ters: the number of sub-risks and the total value of sub risk. 
For creating of model is used fuzzy set theory and fuzzy 
logic. The advantage of fuzzy sets in comparison with the 
classical set theory is its ability to record inaccurate (vague) 
concepts that project managers use natural language in the 
design and implementation of projects. </p>

<p>The advantage of this fuzzy model is the ability to trans-
form the input variables The Number od SUb-Risks (NSR) 
and The Total Value of Sub-Risk (TVSR) to linguistic va-
riables, as well linguistic evaluated The Total Value Project 
RIsk (TVPR) -output variable. With this approach it is 
possible to simulate an uncertainty that is always associated 
with projects. After the fuzzy model is constructed, it is 
necessary to tune it (to set up the inputs on known values, 
evaluate the results and to change the rules or weights, if 
necessary) when the model was built. If the fuzzy model is 
tuned, it is possible to use it in practice. For implement the 
fuzzy model in <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> can also created an executable file 
called M-File. M-file is used to enter the input values and 
automatically evaluate the total risk of the project. 
The fuzzy model has a lot of benefits for users (pro-
ject managers and others). Some of them are: speed up the 
decision-making in risk management, automatization and 
standardization of risk analysis process, effective project 
management etc. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This paper was supported by grant FP-S-15-2787 'Effective 
Use of ICT and Quantitative Methods for Business Processes 
Optimization'' from the Internal Grant Agency at Brno 
University of Technology. </p>



<p> 
R. Doskočil. An evaluation of total project risk based on fuzzy logic </p>



<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2016, 17(1): 23-31 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>