<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2015.433" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Motivation can be changed significantly in dependence on meeting human needs, life situations, internal and external 
environment, etc. It is caused by different factors which affect motivation in different ways. These factors do not act separately 
but they are a part of mutually connected network of specific relations. In the paper we show the possibility of the impact of age, 
education and seniority on the motivation of employees. The level of employee motivation and employee performance can be 
influenced by means of their detailed knowledge. </p>

<p>Human resource management is one of the newest ap 
proaches of personnel management which, as well as 
changed approach to personnel, results from social changes 
at the end of the 20 
th century that affects all private and 
public spheres of life. The basis of this management consists 
in an effort of senior managers to change personality traits 
of supervised employees following the objectives of an en 
terprise (Bolfíková et al. 2010), to create positive approach 
to their work, work team and at last also to identify with 
the corporate culture, its strategy and with the objectives 
of an enterprise (Blašková, Grazulis 2009). The issue of 
human resource management is connected to the issue 
of its utilisation in the context of outsourcing principles 
(Potkány 2011; Vetráková et al. 2011) and process audit 
(Závadská et al. 2013). Personnel controlling tries to find its 
position in the area of motivation too. In a narrow sense, its 
character is quantitative and operative and it evaluates effi 
ciency of personnel processes. In a broad sense, it monitors </p>

<p>the quality of human resource management, its tools and 
practices (Kucharčíková 2014). Different parameters and 
indicators are required by personnel controlling to manage 
different personnel processes (Potkány et al. 2012). 
A man became the most important and the most ex 
pensive factor of production in an enterprise, its main asset 
which, if an enterprise wants to exist, run and develop, must 
be used to achieve goals very carefully. In order to meet 
these requirements, employees must be motivated by the 
enterprise (Bivainis, Morkvėnas 2008). If we want to achieve 
successful results when managing people, negotiating or 
their reaction predicting we must respect differences among 
people (Stacho et al. 2013; Teplická 2004). It means their 
intrinsic motivation must be influenced by motivational 
tools, methods and techniques (Skačkauskienė, Kiselevskaja 
2014). The aim of the paper is to define terms like age, educa 
tion and seniority and their impact on the level of employee 
motivation and in case of some significant differences to 
propose the way of employee motivation. Some changes </p>

<p>in the area of motivation could be observed in the research 
conducted in Slovenia and Croatia (Kropivšek et al. 2011). 
The research was carried out in the year 2012. We also tried 
to prove or to disprove the statement that considering the 
age, completed education and seniority the motivation re 
quirements of employees change. Following the Maslow's 
hierarchy of needs we suppose that requirements of employ 
ees that are fulfilled will become unnecessary. Hereby, we 
suppose that employees with better education and greater 
seniority will prefer different motivation factors than em 
ployees with lower education and less seniority. Main hy 
pothesis is the presumption that mentioned factors affect 
the level of employee motivation and employers can affect 
employee performance actively through their knowledge. 
Mentioned facts are described also by Blašková (2010) and 
by Jelačić, Moro, Drábek, Sujová (2012). </p>

<p>1. Issue </p>

<p>Motivation is one of the essential elements of human re 
source management. Without appropriate level of motivated 
behaviour and activity we cannot determine goals and re 
quire their meeting. Motivation is an important term com 
monly used to encourage people to carry out the assigned 
work with sincerity, dedication, and enthusiasm. Motivation 
is the tonic to provide additional energy to overcome the 
fatigue, disinterest and feelings to drop the job (Srivastava, 
Kakkar 2008). Considering the employee motivation their 
working results can be expected. Statement that the perfor 
mance depends mainly on human motivation is simplified 
especially because motivation is not the only factor affect 
ing the performance. Other factors affecting the employee 
performance are abilities, knowledge and skills of a man de 
termining their career growth potential (Korsakienė 2011). 
Motivation can deviate depending upon meeting human 
needs, life situations, internal and external environment, etc. 
It can be caused by effect of different factors which influence 
motivation in different ways. In addition, these factors do 
not act separately but they create a system of specific rela 
tions that are mutually interconnected. At the present time 
the financial crisis in enterprises and countries' economies 
makes the process of motivation more difficult. Recession 
is a difficult period not only for employees but for employ 
ers as well. Employees with the key competences, respon 
sibilities should be able to motivate their team also during 
recession. When the first signs of the financial crisis appear 
in the organisation, most of traditional methods applied by 
the enterprise in the area of employee motivation before 
this period are not suitable for new situation or cannot be 
carried out at all. Incentives, extra holidays, corporate en 
tertaining and rewards as the most commonly used tools 
of motivation seem to be less important in the atmosphere 
of insecurity. During the recession employees lose mainly </p>

<p>the sense of security. All employees are afraid of losing their 
jobs because mass layoff became one of the basic actions of 
the organisation to eliminate unfavourable impact of the 
crisis on the enterprise. If the organisation wants to keep 
employee productivity of its employees, their willingness 
to work, it is appropriate to offer them incentives and extra 
pay. However, we can say, in general, monetary incentives, 
as a motivation factor, have an important role only from a 
shortterm point of view. 
As the recession influences the workplace atmosphere, 
it is particularly difficult for each senior manager to in 
crease employee motivation. But if employees also during 
the time of recession work with enthusiasm, it can also 
point out that the enterprise recovers from the recession 
faster and without any serious damage. No senior manager 
should forget the fact that his employees are motivated 
also by the way he communicates with them or by his 
body language. Other motivation factors can be employee 
understanding, communication with employees, employee 
engagement, building loyalty and professional trainings 
(Stachová, Stacho 2010). 
According to the authors also other methods and types 
of motivation applied during the crisis can be distinguished: 
creating teams, highlighting accomplishments, interaction 
with senior management, key suppliers and customers, de 
veloping communication skills within a team, cooperation 
between teams, acceptance of new ideas, harmonisation, new 
strategies and new trends. </p>

<p>2. Methodology </p>

<p>Determination of the motivation level and the analysis of 
motivation factors in the enterprises in a perticular time 
were carried out through a questionnaire which consists of 
30 closed questions (Hitka 2009: 149). The questionnaire 
was divided into two parts. Sociodemographic and quali 
fication characteristics of employees were searched in the 
first part. Basic data about respondents relating to their age, 
sex, seniority, completed education and job position were 
obtained in this part. The second part consisted of individual 
motivation factors through which information about work 
environment, working conditions, applied appraisal and 
reward system, about personnel management, health and 
social care system and system of employee benefits as well 
as information about employee satisfaction or dissatisfac 
tion, value orientation, relation to work and enterprise or 
coworkers' relationship in the enterprise can be found out. 
Motivation factors are in alphabetical order not to affect 
respondents's decision. In the questionnaire respondents 
evaluated individual motivation factors by one of the five 
levels of importance from a predefined 5point rating scale, 
5 -the most important and 1 -unimportant (Table 1) from 
a predefined evaluation scale (Table 1). </p>

<p> 
M. Hitka, Ž. Balážová. The impact of age, education and seniority on motivation of employees </p>

<p>Table 1. Scale of the order of motivation factors according to 
their importance (source: Hitka 2009: 149) </p>

<p>5 
4 
3 
2 
1 </p>

<p>the most 
important </p>

<p>very 
important </p>

<p>medium 
impor tant </p>

<p>slightly 
important </p>

<p>un impor 
tant </p>

<p>Each motivation factor was marked by employees with 
one of five types of importance for required as well as for cur 
rent conditions. The required condition can be defined as an 
idea of employees how the motivation should look like, i.e. 
what would motivate them to increase their performance. The 
current conditions represents the employees' opinion how 
they are satisfied with current motivation in the enterprise. 
The questionnaires were evaluated using the programme 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">STATISTICA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">7</rs> (Statsoft <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-date">2004</rs>). Descriptive statistics was used 
to describe the primary sampling unit. Statistical character 
istics, which compressed information about studied primary 
sampling units into smaller number of numerical character 
istics and made mutual comparison of sampling units easier, 
were computed for each motivation factor. Each motivation 
factor was described in summary by basic characteristics of 
size and variability of quantitative features -average x 
 , stand 
ard deviations s x and coefficients of variation. Subsequently 
the results of the enterprises were compared. 
Besides simple comparison of descriptive characteristic 
values, considering the selected type of obtained data, testing 
the equality of averages and standard deviations of primary 
sampling units was carried out. The purpose of testing was 
to verify statistical significance of differences in averages 
and standard deviations of individual motivation factors in 
studied enterprises so that the fact, that detected differences 
of descriptive characteristics at the selected level of signi 
ficance α were not caused only by the mistake made by 
representative sampling, was eliminated. Twosample ttest 
was used to test the equality of averages of motivation factors 
of two primary sampling units (Scheer 2007). When calcula 
ting ttest three cases depending upon the fact whether the 
variances of compared primary sampling units are equal or 
not </p>

<p>2 
2 
2 
2 
1 
2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>( 
, 
) </p>

<p>σ = σ σ ≠ σ or whether the studied attributes X 1 , 
X 2 are dependent or not can occur so the test of equality of 
variances, i.e. Ftest had to be carried out at first. Following 
the results of Ftest, the twosample Ttest for independent 
selection at the same or different variances was used. The 
null hypothesis vs. the alternative hypothesis was tested, they 
were as follows: </p>

<p>2 
2 
0 
1 
2 </p>

<p>: 
H σ = σ vs. </p>

<p>2 
2 
1 
1 
2 </p>

<p>: 
H σ ≠ σ . </p>

<p>H 0 : we suppose that averages of studied motivation fac 
tors (required, current) in terms of maximum of 10 years of 
seniority are equal to averages of studied motivation factors 
in terms of more than 10 years of seniority and at the same 
time we suppose that the difference between them, if any, 
is caused only owing to the random variation of results. </p>

<p>H 1 : we suppose that averages of studied motivation fac 
tors (required, current) in terms of the age of maximum 50 
are not equal to averages of studied motivation factors in 
terms of the age over 50 and at the same time we suppose 
that the difference between them, if any, is not caused only 
owing to the random variation of results. 
H 2 : we suppose that averages of studied motivation fac 
tors (required, current) in terms of completed education 
(primary education and lower secondary education) are 
not equal to averages of studied motivation factors in terms 
of completed education (upper secondary education and 
higher education) and at the same time we suppose that the 
difference between them, if any, is caused only owing to the 
random variation of results. 
The random variable t was used as a test criterion. The 
Student's t distribution was as follows: 
if 2 </p>

<p>2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>σ = σ ; X 1 and X 2 are independent: </p>

<p>1 
2 
2 
2 
1 1 
2 2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1 
2 
1 2 </p>

<p>· 
· 
· 
2 
· </p>

<p>x x 
t 
n s n s n n </p>

<p>n n 
n n </p>

<p>− 
= 
+ 
+ 
+ − </p>

<p>, 
(1) </p>

<p>if 2 </p>

<p>2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>σ ≠ σ ; X 1 and X 2 are independent: </p>

<p>1 
2 
2 
2 
1 
2 </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>1 
1 </p>

<p>x x 
t 
s 
s 
n 
n </p>

<p>− 
= </p>

<p>+ 
− 
− </p>

<p>. 
(2) </p>

<p>In the end of the test we compared t to /2; f 
t α 
, in a case </p>

<p>/2; f </p>

<p>t t α 
≤ 
, H 0 was accepted and the difference was not con 
sidered significant but in a case </p>

<p>/2; f </p>

<p>t t α 
&gt; 
, H 0 was rejected at 
the level of significance α % and the alternative hypothesis 
H 1 was accepted. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>The analysed enterprise is a limited company dealing with 
processing of wood and wood products processing situated 
in the centre of Slovakia. It is an enterprise with long history 
and experience in line of business. Fluctuation of skeleton 
staff is at the minimum level (approx. 1.5%) that is a sign of 
employee stability. At the present time employees are mo 
tivated through basic salary, further financial reward and 
different forms of trainings, job security and social policy. 
Mentioned motivation factors are in terms of increasing 
employee performance inadequate. 
Motivation questionnaire was submitted to 60 respon 
dents (3 females). Questionnaire response rate was 100%. In 
terms of age 36 employees (60.00%) belonged to the group 
of maximum 50 years old and 24 employees (40.00%) over 
50 years old. In terms of education the large group was a 
group of 33 employees with primary and lower secondary 
education (55.00 %). The second group with 27 employees 
was a group with upper secondary education (45.00%). In </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2015, 16(1): 113-120 </p>

<p>
terms of seniority 13 employees were employed for less than 
10 years (21.67%). Remaining 47 employees (78.33%) were 
employed in the enterprise for more than 10 years. It is a sign 
of reliable approach to work on the part of employers but also 
on the part of employees who are identified with the corporate 
culture and philosophy and are loyal to the employer. </p>

<p>3.1. Impact of seniority on motivation </p>

<p>Motivation factors basic salary and further financial reward 
were preferred by staff employed for less than 10 years on 
average. These factors were significantly followed by the third 
motivation factor in the order -fair appraisal system. The 
fourth motivation factor with the highest preference was 
job security; the fifth one was good work team. Basic salary 
was the most important motivation factor also for the staff 
employed for more than 10 years. The second highest ran 
ked motivation factor was job security and the third one in 
ranking was fair appraisal system. The fourth most important 
motivation factor good work team. The second group of the 
staff shows higher interest in all motivation factors. The fifth 
motivation factor that affects the employee performance 
markedly was further financial reward (Table 2). </p>

<p>Table 2. The most important motivation factors in terms of 
seniority (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>Employed less than 10 years Employed more than 10 years </p>

<p>SN 
Motivation 
factor 
∅ 
SN 
Motivation 
factor 
∅ </p>

<p>1 Basic salary 
4.68 
1 Basic salary 
4.85 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Further 
financial 
reward </p>

<p>4.67 
2 Job security 
4.72 </p>

<p>3 
Fair appraisal 
system 
4.58 
3 
Fair appraisal 
system 
4.70 </p>

<p>4 Job security 
4.50 
4 
Good work 
team 
4.59 </p>

<p>5 
Good work 
team 
4.42 
5 
Further finan 
cial reward 
4.52 </p>

<p>3.2. Impact of the age on motivation </p>

<p>When comparing the age of employees we divided them 
into two main groups -employees under the age of 50 and 
over 50. For the group of employees under 50 the most 
important motivation factor was basic salary. Next higher 
ranked motivation factors were further financial reward and 
fair appraisal system. The fourth motivation factor with the 
highest preference was, for the former group of employees, 
job security and the fifth one good work team. For the latter 
group of employees, with the age over 50, the most im 
portant motivation factor was basic salary followed by job 
security. Next higher ranked motivation factors were good 
work team, social benefits and fair appraisal system (Table 3). </p>

<p>Table 3. The most important motivation factors in terms of 
age (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>under 50 
over 50 </p>

<p>SN 
Motivation 
factor 
Ø 
SN 
Motivation 
factor 
Ø </p>

<p>1 Basic salary 
4.83 
1 Basic salary 
4.78 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Further 
financial 
reward </p>

<p>4.71 
2 Job security 
4.65 </p>

<p>3 
Fair appraisal 
system 
4.71 
3 
Good work 
team 
4.61 </p>

<p>4 Job security 
4.69 
4 Social benefits 
4.61 </p>

<p>5 
Good work 
team 
4.51 
5 
Fair appraisal 
system 
4.61 </p>

<p>3.3. Impact of the completed education on motivation </p>

<p>Analysis of motivation factors in terms of the completed 
education was carried out in two groups of employees -
group of employees with primary and lower secondary 
education and group of employees with upper secondary 
and higher education. Results of the analysis show that basic 
salary was the most important motivation factor for the 
former group of people in 2012. The second highest ranked 
motivation factor was job security and the third one was 
social benefits. Next higher ranked motivation factors were 
work performance and further financial reward. The latter 
group of employees, i.e. employees with upper secondary 
and higher education, preferred same motivation factors as 
the former group, besides work performance. The highest 
ranked motivation factor was basic salary followed by social 
benefits. The third higher ranked motivation facto was, for 
the latter group of employees, job security and the fourth 
one was good work team. The last mentioned motivation 
factor shows the importance of good relationship and po 
sitive atmosphere in the workplace that can affect com 
munication and fulfilling prescribed work task in positive 
way. The fifth most important motivation factor was further 
financial reward (Table 4). </p>

<p>Table 4. The most important motivation factors in terms of 
completed education (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>Primary + Lower secondary 
Upper secondary + Higher </p>

<p>SN 
Motivation 
factor 
∅ 
SN 
Motivation 
factor 
∅ </p>

<p>1 Basic salary 
4.69 
1 Basic salary 
4.96 </p>

<p>2 Job security 
4.59 
2 Social benefits 
4.81 </p>

<p>3 Social benefits 
4.56 
3 Job security 
4.77 </p>

<p>4 
Work 
performance 
4.47 
4 
Good work 
team 
4.73 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Further 
financial 
reward </p>

<p>4.46 
5 </p>

<p>Further 
financial 
reward </p>

<p>4.65 </p>

<p> 
M. Hitka, Ž. Balážová. The impact of age, education and seniority on motivation of employees </p>

<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>Considering the independence of selected sampling units 
and their big sizes a twosample Ttest for independent 
selection at the same or different variances was used to 
review the significance. 
The null hypotheses about the equality of two averages 
of compared sampling units were tested. Null hypothesis 
testing about the equality of averages of motivation factors 
in the time was carried out at the level of significance α = 
0.5. Results are shown in Tables 4, 5, 6. Criteria for compa 
rison were the level of employee motivation regarding the </p>

<p>age, seniority and completed education. Following achieved 
results we can state that significant differences at the level 
of significance α = 0.5 did not occur. 
Twosample Ttest was used to determine significant 
dependence. Following the results (Table 5) we can state that 
in spite of different order of motivation factor importance 
there are no differences in the level of employee motivation 
employed for less or more than 10 years. Twosample Ttest 
was used to determine significant dependence. Following 
the results (Table 6) we can state that only in case of the 
motivation factor further financial reward there is signifi 
cant difference. </p>

<p>Table 5. Reviewing of significant dependence in terms of work practice (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>Motivation factor </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x 
tvalue 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S 
F 
p </p>

<p>Atmosphere in the workplace 
4.23 
4.36 
-0.6 
0.544 
0.44 
0.74 
2.81 
0.056 </p>

<p>Good work team 
4.38 
4.6 
-1.2 
0.236 
0.51 
0.58 
1.3 
0.646 </p>

<p>Further financial reward 
4.69 
4.53 
0.7 
0.483 
0.85 
0.69 
1.55 
0.283 </p>

<p>Physical effort at work 
3.77 
3.68 
0.3 
0.754 
1.09 
0.84 
1.7 
0.195 </p>

<p>Job security 
4.38 
4.72 
-1.7 
0.101 
0.96 
0.54 
3.17 
0.005 </p>

<p>Communication in the workplace 
4.23 
4.4 
-0.8 
0.426 
0.83 
0.65 
1.65 
0.223 </p>

<p>Name of the company 
3.77 
4.26 
-1.8 
0.071 
0.73 
0.87 
1.44 
0.499 </p>

<p>Opportunity to apply one's own ability 
4.15 
4.19 
-0.2 
0.855 
0.55 
0.68 
1.5 
0.451 </p>

<p>Workload and type of work 
3.77 
4.21 
-2 
0.055 
0.73 
0.72 
1.01 
0.906 </p>

<p>Information about performance results 
4.08 
4.21 
-0.5 
0.616 
0.86 
0.86 
1.01 
0.911 </p>

<p>Working time 
4 
4.21 
-0.9 
0.364 
0.82 
0.72 
1.28 
0.520 </p>

<p>Work environment 
4.08 
4.53 
-1.7 
0.088 
1.26 
0.69 
3.34 
0.003 </p>

<p>Work performance 
4.15 
4.4 
-1.3 
0.210 
0.69 
0.61 
1.26 
0.549 </p>

<p>Moving up corporate ladder 
4.31 
4.47 
-0.7 
0.468 
0.85 
0.65 
1.71 
0.193 </p>

<p>Competences 
3.69 
3.77 
-0.3 
0.791 
0.75 
0.91 
1.48 
0.469 </p>

<p>Prestige 
3.77 
3.81 
-0.1 
0.888 
0.73 
0.92 
1.62 
0.364 </p>

<p>Supervisor's approach 
4.15 
4.45 
-1.3 
0.194 
0.9 
0.65 
1.89 
0.121 </p>

<p>Individual decision making 
3.92 
4.19 
-1.4 
0.172 
0.64 
0.61 
1.09 
0.778 </p>

<p>Selfactualization 
3.77 
4.02 
-1.1 
0.293 
0.83 
0.74 
1.27 
0.531 </p>

<p>Social benefits 
4.15 
4.49 
-1.4 
0.176 
0.9 
0.75 
1.44 
0.363 </p>

<p>Fair appraisal system 
4.54 
4.7 
-0.7 
0.504 
0.88 
0.75 
1.37 
0.430 </p>

<p>Stress /limitation of stress in the 
workplace/ 
4.23 
4.43 
-0.8 
0.456 
0.93 
0.8 
1.34 
0.460 </p>

<p>Mental effort 
4 
4.4 
-1.6 
0.113 
0.82 
0.8 
1.05 
0.851 </p>

<p>Mission of the company 
4.15 
4.3 
-0.5 
0.628 
1.07 
0.91 
1.39 
0.413 </p>

<p>Region's development 
3.92 
4.32 
-1.5 
0.139 
0.76 
0.86 
1.29 
0.657 </p>

<p>Education and personal growth 
3.92 
4.34 
-1.9 
0.067 
0.49 
0.76 
2.37 
0.106 </p>

<p>Company relation to the environment 
4.08 
4.4 
-1.3 
0.192 
0.64 
0.83 
1.66 
0.343 </p>

<p>Free time 
4.15 
4.19 
-0.1 
0.892 
0.8 
0.9 
1.26 
0.686 </p>

<p>Recognition 
4.08 
4.34 
-1.2 
0.243 
0.86 
0.67 
1.66 
0.214 </p>

<p>Basic salary 
4.69 
4.85 
-0.7 
0.458 
0.85 
0.62 
1.87 
0.128 </p>

<p>Note: Data marked number 1 characterise respondents with work practice up to 10 years, data marked number 2 characterise res 
pondents with work practice over 10 years; differences in arithmetic means of examined motivation factors significant at the level of 
significance 5% are written in cursive. </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2015, 16(1): 113-120 </p>

<p>
Twosample Ttest was used to determine significant 
dependence. Following the results (Table 7) we can state 
that that in spite of different order of motivation factor im 
portance there are no differences in the level of employee 
motivation in dependence on their education. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>Creating motivational programmes is a difficult and ex 
pensive activity for each enterprise. Its effectiveness is in 
fluenced by exact employee analysis. Based on our analy 
ses (Vetráková et al. 2007; Hitka et al. 2005) we can say </p>

<p>following findings: in spite of employee heterogeneity in 
terms of age, seniority and level of completed education it is 
possible to create a unified motivational programme for the 
analysed enterprise that will suit all employees regardless of 
their age, seniority or education. Its main items are follow 
ing factors: basic salary, job security, good work team, further 
financial reward and fair appraisal system in different order 
according to preferences of specific group of employees. 
Regarding the seniority we can state that in spite of dif 
ferent order of importance of motivation factors there are no 
differences in the level of motivation of employees hired for 
less than 10 years and more than 10 years. Regarding the age </p>

<p>Table 6. Reviewing of significant dependence in terms of age (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>Motivation factor </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x 
tvalue 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S 
F 
p </p>

<p>Atmosphere in the workplace 
4.361 
4.292 
0.38 
0.702 
0.683 
0.690 
1.02 
0.932 </p>

<p>God work team 
4.500 
4.625 
-0.84 
0.406 
0.561 
0.576 
1.05 
0.868 </p>

<p>Further financial reward 
4.722 
4.333 
2.10 
0.040 
0.615 
0.816 
1.76 
0.126 </p>

<p>Physical effort at work 
3.667 
3.750 
-0.35 
0.725 
0.926 
0.847 
1.19 
0.663 </p>

<p>Job security 
4.639 
4.667 
-0.16 
0.875 
0.723 
0.565 
1.64 
0.215 </p>

<p>Communication in the workplace 
4.306 
4.458 
-0.84 
0.404 
0.710 
0.658 
1.16 
0.713 </p>

<p>Name of the company 
4.167 
4.125 
0.18 
0.856 
0.737 
1.035 
1.97 
0.068 </p>

<p>Opportunity to apply one's own ability 
4.167 
4.208 
-0.24 
0.810 
0.655 
0.658 
1.01 
0.958 </p>

<p>Workload and type of work 
4.167 
4.042 
0.64 
0.525 
0.697 
0.806 
1.34 
0.427 </p>

<p>Information about performance results 
4.139 
4.250 
-0.49 
0.625 
0.833 
0.897 
1.16 
0.681 </p>

<p>Working time 
4.111 
4.250 
-0.71 
0.481 
0.820 
0.608 
1.82 
0.134 </p>

<p>Work environment 
4.417 
4.458 
-0.18 
0.854 
0.874 
0.833 
1.10 
0.822 </p>

<p>Work performance 
4.361 
4.333 
0.17 
0.869 
0.543 
0.761 
1.97 
0.069 </p>

<p>Moving up corporate ladder 
4.417 
4.458 
-0.22 
0.823 
0.732 
0.658 
1.24 
0.599 </p>

<p>Competences 
3.806 
3.667 
0.60 
0.552 
0.786 
1.007 
1.64 
0.182 </p>

<p>Prestige 
3.861 
3.708 
0.66 
0.514 
0.798 
0.999 
1.57 
0.226 </p>

<p>Supervisor's approach 
4.361 
4.417 
-0.29 
0.771 
0.683 
0.776 
1.29 
0.485 </p>

<p>Individual decision making 
4.111 
4.167 
-0.34 
0.738 
0.622 
0.637 
1.05 
0.882 </p>

<p>Selfactualization 
3.889 
4.083 
-0.97 
0.335 
0.820 
0.654 
1.57 
0.256 </p>

<p>Social benefits 
4.278 
4.625 
-1.70 
0.095 
0.882 
0.576 
2.35 
0.035 </p>

<p>Fair appraisal system 
4.694 
4.625 
0.34 
0.737 
0.786 
0.770 
1.04 
0.932 </p>

<p>Stress /limitation of stress in the workplace/ 
4.472 
4.250 
1.02 
0.311 
0.810 
0.847 
1.09 
0.795 </p>

<p>Mental effort 
4.361 
4.250 
0.52 
0.608 
0.833 
0.794 
1.10 
0.822 </p>

<p>Mission of the company 
4.306 
4.208 
0.39 
0.697 
0.980 
0.884 
1.23 
0.609 </p>

<p>Region's development 
4.250 
4.208 
0.18 
0.854 
0.732 
1.021 
1.94 
0.074 </p>

<p>Education and personal growth 
4.222 
4.292 
-0.36 
0.721 
0.681 
0.806 
1.40 
0.358 </p>

<p>Relation of the company to the environment 
4.278 
4.417 
-0.66 
0.512 
0.849 
0.717 
1.40 
0.400 </p>

<p>Free time 
4.194 
4.167 
0.12 
0.905 
0.822 
0.963 
1.37 
0.389 </p>

<p>Recognition 
4.306 
4.250 
0.29 
0.771 
0.749 
0.676 
1.23 
0.611 </p>

<p>Basic salary 
4.833 
4.792 
0.23 
0.817 
0.697 
0.658 
1.12 
0.785 </p>

<p>Note: Data marked number 1 characterise respondents of maximum 50 years old, data marked number 2 characterise respondents 
over 50 years old; differences in arithmetic means of examined motivation factors significant at the level of significance 5% are written 
in cursive. </p>

<p> 
M. Hitka, Ž. Balážová. The impact of age, education and seniority on motivation of employees </p>

<p>we can state that only in a case of the motivation factor fur 
ther financial reward there was seen a significant difference 
among employees. Regarding the completed education we 
can state that despite different order of importance of mo 
tivation factors there were not seen differences in the level 
of employee motivation, too. Finally we can state that at the 
present time the motivational programme can be proposed 
on the basis of the average importance of individual motiva 
tion factors unifiedly. However, differences are more likely 
to exist also among employees themselves. The differences 
can be analysed by cluster analysis to define groups of em 
ployees motivated in a similar way. Moreover, in the future </p>

<p>motivation requirements of employees can also change after 
meeting their needs. Therefore we suggest the enterprise to 
update motivational programme from time to time. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This research has been supported by the project VEGA 
No. [1/0067/11] Dynamics and content of decisiontaking 
processes in motivating of human potential and VEGA 
No. [1/0268/13] Perspectives of facility management ap 
plication for the increasing of competitiveness within the 
woodprocessing and forestry companies in the context of 
outsourcing principles. </p>

<p>Table 7. Reviewing of significant dependence in terms of completed education (source: own data processing) </p>

<p>Motivation factor </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x 
tvalue 
p </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>S 
F 
p </p>

<p>Atmosphere in the workplace 
4.303 
4.370 
-0.38 
0.706 
0.81 
0.49 
2.71 
0.011 </p>

<p>God work team 
4.455 
4.667 
-1.46 
0.150 
0.62 
0.48 
1.65 
0.194 </p>

<p>Further financial reward 
4.424 
4.741 
-1.72 
0.091 
0.87 
0.45 
3.77 
0.001 </p>

<p>Physical effort at work 
3.576 
3.852 
-1.20 
0.234 
1.00 
0.72 
1.94 
0.086 </p>

<p>Job security 
4.545 
4.778 
-1.37 
0.177 
0.75 
0.51 
2.22 
0.041 </p>

<p>Communication in the workplace 
4.364 
4.370 
-0.04 
0.970 
0.70 
0.69 
1.03 
0.941 </p>

<p>Name of the company 
4.242 
4.037 
0.92 
0.362 
0.75 
0.98 
1.70 
0.153 </p>

<p>Opportunity to apply one's own ability 
4.152 
4.222 
-0.42 
0.679 
0.62 
0.70 
1.27 
0.511 </p>

<p>Workload and type of work 
4.000 
4.259 
-1.36 
0.178 
0.90 
0.45 
4.07 
0.000 </p>

<p>Information about performance results 
4.182 
4.185 
-0.02 
0.988 
0.98 
0.68 
2.08 
0.059 </p>

<p>Working time 
4.091 
4.259 
-0.87 
0.385 
0.80 
0.66 
1.51 
0.288 </p>

<p>Work environment 
4.333 
4.556 
-1.01 
0.318 
1.02 
0.58 
3.13 
0.004 </p>

<p>Work performance 
4.394 
4.296 
0.59 
0.557 
0.70 
0.54 
1.69 
0.173 </p>

<p>Moving up corporate ladder 
4.485 
4.370 
0.63 
0.532 
0.71 
0.69 
1.07 
0.861 </p>

<p>Competences 
3.788 
3.704 
0.37 
0.714 
0.89 
0.87 
1.06 
0.895 </p>

<p>Prestige 
3.697 
3.926 
-1.00 
0.320 
0.95 
0.78 
1.48 
0.305 </p>

<p>Supervisor's approach 
4.242 
4.556 
-1.71 
0.092 
0.79 
0.58 
1.88 
0.102 </p>

<p>Individual decision making 
4.091 
4.185 
-0.58 
0.565 
0.63 
0.62 
1.03 
0.955 </p>

<p>Selfactualization 
3.939 
4.000 
-0.31 
0.761 
0.70 
0.83 
1.40 
0.368 </p>

<p>Social benefits 
4.303 
4.556 
-1.24 
0.219 
0.92 
0.58 
2.53 
0.018 </p>

<p>Fair appraisal system 
4.545 
4.815 
-1.35 
0.182 
0.97 
0.40 
6.02 
0.000 </p>

<p>Stress /limitation of stress in the workplace/ 
4.364 
4.407 
-0.20 
0.840 
0.96 
0.64 
2.29 
0.033 </p>

<p>Mental effort 
4.212 
4.444 
-1.10 
0.274 
0.93 
0.64 
2.10 
0.057 </p>

<p>Mission of the company 
4.182 
4.370 
-0.77 
0.442 
1.07 
0.74 
2.10 
0.056 </p>

<p>Region's development 
4.303 
4.148 
0.70 
0.488 
0.77 
0.95 
1.52 
0.260 </p>

<p>Education and personal growth 
4.242 
4.259 
-0.09 
0.930 
0.71 
0.76 
1.16 
0.677 </p>

<p>Relation of the company to the environment 
4.455 
4.185 
1.31 
0.194 
0.71 
0.88 
1.53 
0.254 </p>

<p>Free time 
4.152 
4.222 
-0.31 
0.758 
0.87 
0.89 
1.05 
0.888 </p>

<p>Recognition 
4.364 
4.185 
0.96 
0.341 
0.74 
0.68 
1.19 
0.660 </p>

<p>Basic salary 
4.697 
4.963 
-1.53 
0.131 
0.88 
0.19 
21.07 
0.000000 </p>

<p>Note: Data marked number 1 characterise respondents with lower secondary education, data marked number 2 characterise res 
pondents with upper secondary education; differences in arithmetic means of examined motivation factors significant at the level of 
significance 5% are written in cursive. </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2015, 16(1): 113-120 </p>



<p>
Miloš HITKA is Associate Professor at the Department of Enterprise Management, Faculty of Wood Sciences and 
Technology,Technical University in Zvolen. He is an author of many peerreviewed scientific papers. His research studies have 
been presented and published at national and international level. His research interests include human resource management, 
management, ergonomics, logistics, etc. </p>

<p>Žaneta BALÁŽOVÁ is Assistant at the Institute of Foreign Languages, Technical University in Zvolen. Her research studies have 
been presented and published at national and international levels. Her research interests include human resource management, 
management, logistics, etc. </p>

<p> 
M. Hitka, Ž. Balážová. The impact of age, education and seniority on motivation of employees </p>

</text></tei>