<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2F1611-1699.2009.10.169-180" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The aim of the study is to show innovative possibilities for improvement of safety culture at enterprises through 
complex approach to occupational health and safety (OH&amp;S). The knowledge of the leadership and workers in OH&amp;S is 
not suffi cient at present in Estonia, particularly in small and medium-sized enterprises (the number is 60 000). The small 
(up to 50 workers) or medium-sized enterprises (up to 150 workers) have no possibility to hire the working environment 
specialist who would deal only with OH&amp;S problems. Usually obligations in the fi eld of OH&amp;S in small and medium-sized 
enterprises are delegated to one employee in addition to other responsibilities related to personnel, security, fi re protection 
and environmental problems. Therefore, the complex approach to management of OH&amp;S issues is needed in order to cre-
ate a good safety culture and to achieve positive results in company safety performance. The complex method consists of 
risk assessment and determination of safety level. The authors offer possible tools -simple computer applications which 
are available for managers, interviews with employers, employees and occupational health specialists for development and 
dissemination of safety culture. The opinion of workers and occupational health specialists has been taken into considera-
tion in the planning of improvements of working conditions by the employers. The economic issues of safety and health 
improvement measures are presented. </p>

<p>Safety culture is a key element in the development of 
complex models to explain or predict safety relevant 
outcomes, such as safety behaviour, safety compliance 
or accidents, and may help explain the "human factor" 
in relation to organisational safety issues and perform-
ance. These processes may be studied at different lev-
els of analyses and even at different levels of analyses 
simultaneously (Cheyne et al. 2008). Safety culture 
contains three interacting elements: risk controls, at-
titudes and behaviour, and its effective development 
depends on good cooperation and communications be-
tween employers, employees and Occupational Health 
Services (OHS). In Estonia, the services provided by 
an occupational health physician, an occupational 
health nurse, an occupational hygienist, a psycholo-
gist or a specialist of ergonomics are considered to 
be OHS. These service providers are all called 'oc-
cupational health specialists' (OHsp). According to 
the Estonian Act on Occupational Health and Safety, 
only entrepreneurs or private medical companies may 
provide the OHS. </p>

<p>The benefi ts of OHS are obvious and objectively de-
monstrable. Economic evaluation (cost-benefi t analy-
sis, cost-effectiveness analysis, and cost utility anal-
ysis) of such service is thus important as a guide to 
rational choices, the dependency on the validity of as-
sumptions made being the main limitation, along with 
the non-consideration of social and ethical objectives 
if decisions are based on costs and benefi t alone. Ul-
timately, the formulation of policies on OHS must be 
both economically and ethically sound (Meng 2005; 
Grozdanovic 2001). </p>

<p>Work-related injuries and illnesses kill an estimated 
1.2 million people around the world every year. 250 
million work-related accidents and 160 million work-
related illnesses occur annually (Somavia 2005) and 
these numbers translate into an annual economic loss 
of approximately 4% of the world gross national prod-
uct (International … 2001). Only an estimated 5-10% 
of the workers in developing countries and 20-50% of 
the workers in industrialized countries (85% in Fin-
land, (Walters 1996) have access to adequate OHS. 
Relatively little information is available on the process 
and customers of OHS. The only indications of the </p>



<p>coverage and contents of OHS are obtained indirectly 
form the information labour inspectors gather annually 
from employers. In addition, only a minority (22%) 
of workers is covered by the OHS and has access to 
the occupational health physician in Estonia (Järvis 
and Tint 2007). Even in a developed country like the 
United States, approximately 70% of the 100 million 
workforce are not covered by OHS (Somavia 2005). 
The OHS have been endorsed by both the WHO and 
the ILO as a prescription for a healthier, happier, and 
more productive workforce. </p>

<p>Although a healthier workforce will almost certainly 
mean decreased absenteeism and increased workers' 
compensation claims, one must still weigh the ben-
efi ts against the costs and seek the most cost-effective 
way of achieving the same results. In the estimation 
of the benefi ts, a monetary value is apportioned to the 
avoided consequences (for example costs of health 
care, rehabilitation, or workers' compensation). The 
analysis should also take into consideration the fact 
that costs and benefi ts may be generated over a pe-
riod of time, the costs and benefi ts often occurring 
in different time periods. Because costs or benefi ts 
10 years later are not directly comparable with their 
value today. The effects on productivity and reduced 
sickness absence can also be quantifi ed and refl ected 
as savings. More sophisticated forms of cost-benefi t 
analyses would factor other intangible benefi ts into the 
equation. Providing employees with on-site primary 
health care may give them a sense of loyalty to the 
company because the company is demonstrating that it 
cares for its employees. The full economic losses due 
to accidents are not demonstrated clearly in Estonia. 
Data from the Health Insurance Fund (responsible for 
public health care in Estonia) have been publicly ac-</p>

<p>cessible only in two recent years. However, these data 
(Table 1) do not contain the indirect costs of accidents 
and diseases (the costs for hiring the substitute labour, 
training for the job, the lost or degraded production 
quality, etc.). At present, the coverage for occupational 
accidents and occupational diseases are integrated into 
the Estonian health insurance (temporary loss of work 
ability) and pension insurance (permanent loss of work 
ability) schemes. The system of occupational disability 
and occupational accidents insurance is voluntary in 
Estonia and not effective (Järvis and Tint 2007). </p>

<p>Many companies have embarked on the road to estab-
lish safe working cultures in order to improve their 
safety performance. The so-called behaviour-based 
safety programs are the vehicles to achieve this desired 
outcome (Gadomski 2008). Indeed, some companies 
have experienced huge improvements in their safety 
performance while others, however, utterly failed 
(Pheiffer 2008). The behaviour-based safety program 
accepts that risk-taking is essential and fundamental to 
doing work and that no work at the workplace can ever 
be made risk-free. Therefore, the focus should be that 
employees become competent to identify and assess 
risks and act appropriately. This approach specifi cally 
targets the complacency factor, which is a natural re-
sult if people perceive their work environments and 
procedures to be safe. One of the tools in achieving 
safety is to focus on employees' behaviour and atti-
tudes. In order to encourage the employees to achieve 
high safety standards the managers must lead by the 
models of the behaviour that include risk awareness 
tools, motivational tools and behaviour observations. 
Over the years companies have installed many pro-
grams and processes to prevent incidents and to con-
trol losses. According to Germain et al. (1998) some </p>

<p>Table 1. Number of workdays lost and expenses incurred due to occupational accidents (Ministry … 2006) </p>

<p>1995 
2000 
2002 
2003 
2004 
2006 </p>

<p>Number of workdays lost due to the 
occupational accidents </p>

<p>83 643 
157 051 
171 850 
146 411 
118 941 
125 314 </p>

<p>Percentage of workdays lost due to 
occupational accidents in the total number 
of sick-leave days </p>

<p>….. 
3.1 
3.7 
3.1 
3.7 
2.3 </p>

<p>Occupational accident benefi t, million EEK/ 
million EURO </p>

<p>6.3/0.4 
19.5/1.23 25.2/1.6 23.1/1.47 20.4/1.3 22.9/1.46 </p>

<p>Number of certifi cates of incapacity for work 
2783 
6921 
7572 
6871 
5863 
5996 </p>

<p>Compensation for damages related to 
occupational accidents and diseases, million 
EEK/million EURO </p>

<p>…. 
21.6/1.38 34.6/2.2 36.9/2.35 38.3/2.44 36.0/2.20 </p>

<p>Number of people receiving compensation 
for damages </p>

<p>…. 
1111 
1553 
1646 
1745 
2216 </p>

<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>



<p>companies believe that the best way to achieve incident 
control is through additional regulations, focusing on 
prescriptive and technological approach, there is also 
a merging willingness by people in industry and busi-
ness to try a new and complementary approach. This 
approach is then effective safety management through 
good management systems. It is clear that there is a 
direct link between good safety management systems 
and good business management (Wallace 1995). Or-
ganisations with high safety standards are those with 
high operational standards because the management 
actions necessary to achieve safety are the same which 
are required to achieve business effi ciency. Over time 
various safety approaches were indeed developed and 
implemented by companies to assist them in the man-
aging of safety and include engineering design, legal 
approach, safety systems, risk management and more 
recently behaviour-based safety. The aim is to change 
employees' perception and attitudes (at all levels) to-
ward s safety behaviour, so that they understand the 
role and impact of their own behaviours on safety. 
The way, in which employees understand risks, their 
attitudes towards safety and taking the responsibility 
of safety of the person himself and the others are im-
portant factors in good safety culture. There are three 
major factors which infl uence employee behaviour: 
the company safety culture, which should promote 
involvement and commitment to the company goals 
and standards; the job itself; the strengths and weak-
nesses of the employee, which include habits, attitudes, 
personality and current stresses (Wallace 1995). New 
demands from the companies' environment entail that 
work safety becomes strategically more important for 
management (Järvis and Tint 2007; Reinhold and Tint 
2007). The safety management system consists of the </p>

<p>following elements (thematic areas): management and 
leadership, training of management and personnel, 
operations, maintenance, risk assessment, emergency 
planning, monitoring of performance and audit (Mach-
aira et al. 2008). </p>

<p>2. Material and methods </p>

<p>1) Management of hazards at workplace-following 
Fig. 1; 2) A simple risk assessment method (Reinhold 
et al. 2006), described on p. 4; 3) For the determina-
tion of safety level at the six enterprises, the modi-
fi ed Diekemper &amp; Spartz method (Kuusisto 2000) was 
used, also described on p. 5; 4) The questioning of 
managers about their activities and willingness to carry 
out improvements in the fi eld of OH&amp;S (p. 7); 5) The 
questioning of workers for taking into consideration 
their opinion in working out plans for positive changes 
in the working environment (p. 6); 6) The questioning 
of occupational health specialists (doctors and nurses) 
for clearing-up the possibilities to increase their role 
in improvement of safety culture at enterprises (p. 9). </p>

<p>The investigated enterprises were from manufacturing: 
printing, mechanical, plastics, wood processing, textile 
industry and the water purifi cation plant (Cases I-VI). </p>

<p>3. Risk assessment at the workplace based 
on a simple risk assessment method </p>

<p>A computerized version of the simple/fl exible risk as-
sessment method (Reinhold et al. 2006) is shown in 
Fig. 2. The method gives four risk levels (negligible, 
justifi ed, inadmissible, intolerable risk) and enables 
to show graphically the level of risk according to the 
measurements in the work environment (Table 2). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. The management of hazards at workplace </p>

<p>mechanical factors </p>

<p>chemicals </p>

<p>noise </p>

<p>vibration </p>

<p>microclimate </p>

<p>lighting </p>

<p>psychological risk factors </p>

<p>physiological risk factors </p>

<p>organizational factors </p>

<p>The selection of the 
work area to study </p>

<p>Gathering the information 
for evaluating the risks </p>

<p>Identification of risks </p>

<p>Risk evaluation </p>

<p>Planning of reductions </p>

<p>Risk reduction </p>

<p>Periodic checks 
of occupational risks </p>

<p>People at risk </p>

<p>Medical health examinations </p>

<p>Slight 
disturbances 
to health </p>

<p>Recoverable 
damages 
Occupational 
disease </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(2): 169-180 </p>



<p>Fig. 2. The computerized method for risk assessment at workplace </p>

<p>Table 2. Overall results of measurements of working conditions in manufacturing (Reinhold and Tint 2009) </p>

<p>Industry </p>

<p>Indoor air temperature, 
°C, U = 0.6 °C </p>

<p>Indoor air humidity, 
%, U = 2.0% 
Dust, mg/m 3 
U = 0.3 mg/m 3 </p>

<p>Lighting, lx, 
U = 10.4% 
Noise level, 
dB(A), 
U = 2.0 dB 
Cold 
season </p>

<p>Warm 
season </p>

<p>Cold 
season </p>

<p>Warm 
season </p>

<p>General 
lighting </p>

<p>Case I 
(printing) 
21.7..22.4 22.5...24.3 38.2…52.2 44.2…62.4 
0.7…2.5 
264…1625 
66.4…90.3 </p>

<p>Case II 
(mechanical) 
10.8..21.4 17.6...23.2 31.3…39.9 41.4…48.7 
2.0…10.0 
88…1256 
73.0…97.5 </p>

<p>Case III 
(plastic) 
14.0..22.4 18.6...25.5 26.1…40.7 36.5…45.7 
0.4... 1.0 
138…742 
61.1…83.8 </p>

<p>Case IV 
(wood) 
21.2..24.0 24.3...26.5 34.2…42.6 35.1…47.6 
2.05…6.0 
320…1050 
84.2…94.4 </p>

<p>Case V 
(textile) 
20.3..23.5 22.7...25.6 44.4…53.0 48.2…53.0 
1.2.... .4.4 
525…2040 
62.1…89.5 </p>

<p>Case VI 
(water 
purifi cation) </p>

<p>14.0..23.0 17.0...26.7 32.6…47.9 39.5…54.6 </p>

<p>not 
measured 
200....500 
67.6....82.4 </p>

<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>



<p>For example, lighting 200 lx in wood processing indus-
try is inadmissible risk for work with saws and other 
tools and equipment for cutting wooden raw mate-
rial and also in furniture industry (400-500 needed). 
Noise level 84 dB(A) is acceptable risk if earmuffs are 
used (85 dB(A) -the exposure limit for 8-hours work-
day). Dust 4 mg/m 3 is acceptable risk as the limit is 
5 mg/m 3 for inhalable dust and 10 mg/m 3 for overall 
dust (2 mg/m 3 for pure wood dust). </p>

<p>4. Safety management at the enterprise </p>

<p>Safety audits are a vital way of verifying that com-
pany's safety management is working properly. Several 
methods have been developed for supporting safety 
auditing: questionnaires, interviews, observations and 
document reviews. Safety management systems in 6 
Estonian enterprises were assessed using Diekemper 
&amp; Spartz (D&amp;S) method, which was modifi ed by Kuu-
sisto considering the demands of the OH&amp;S standard 
OHSAS 18001 (Diekemper and Spartz 1970). The in-
vestigated enterprises were selected from the manufac-
turing industries (Cases 1-VI). </p>

<p>The assessment in this method is carried out on four 
level systems: level 1(poor); level 2 (fair); level 3 
(good); level 4 (excellent) (example Table 3A). </p>

<p>The modifi ed D&amp;S method addresses 30 activities. 
These are categorized into the following activity areas: 
A* -organization and administration (statement of 
policy, responsibilities assigned; direct management 
involvement; safety instructions to hazardous tasks; 
workplace design; health care). 
B* -industrial hazard control (housekeeping-storage 
of materials; machine guarding; maintenance of equip-
ment, guards, hand tools; material handling-manual 
and automated; and personal protective equipment). 
C* -fi re control and industrial hygiene (chemical 
hazard control references; storage of fl ammable and 
explosive materials; ventilation-fumes, smoke and </p>

<p>dust control; skin contamination control; fi re control 
measures). </p>

<p>D* -supervisory participation, motivation and train-
ing, line supervisor safety training; training of new 
employees; job hazard analysis; training for special-
ized operations (fork trucks, grinding, punch presses, 
solvent handling, etc.); worker/manager safety contact 
and communication. </p>

<p>E* -accident investigation, statistics and reporting 
procedures, accident investigation by line personnel; 
accident cause analysis and statistics; near-accident 
investigation. </p>

<p>Case I (printing industry) was carried out at the enter-
prise with 162 employees. The factory has invested in a 
great deal to improve the status of premises. The manu-
facturing process operated in three shifts. The premises 
were new. The company had no safety manager; the 
duties were delegated to the personnel manager, who 
had the responsibility to deal not only with OH&amp;S 
issues but also environmental and security manage-
ment systems. The main types of accidents occurred 
in the company were slips, pinching of fi ngers and 
back injuries. The company's employees were rather 
experienced (half of them worked in the factory for 
10-20 years). </p>

<p>The highest scores were given to part B -industrial 
hazard control (15: workers were equipped with per-
sonal protective equipment, good storage of materials, 
material handling -manual and automated, etc.), the 
lowest one (10) was given to part E (accident inves-
tigation). The E part was assessed low for all investi-
gated companies (except Case VI) as the near-accident 
investigation was not performed in any of the compa-
nies (except Case VI). Part D obtained the score 11: 
safety training was carried out on a regular basis, but 
no written guidelines or programme for internal audits 
were presented. In most cases, new employees were 
trained by senior workers. </p>

<p>Table 3A. Modifi ed Diekemper &amp; Spartz method for assessment of safety system. 
Determination activities' safety level (area A) 
A. Organization and administration </p>

<p>Activity 
LEVEL I (Poor) 
LEVEL 2 (Fair) 
LEVEL 3 (Good) 
LEVEL 4 (Excellent) </p>

<p>1. Statement 
of policy, 
responsibilities 
assigned </p>

<p>No statement of 
safety policy. 
Responsibility and 
accountability not 
assigned </p>

<p>A general understanding 
of safety, responsibilities 
and accountability, but 
not in written form </p>

<p>Safety policy 
responsibilities 
written and 
distributed to 
supervisors </p>

<p>In addition to previous items, 
safety policy is reviewed annually. 
Responsibility and accountability 
is emphasized in supervisory 
performance evaluations </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(2): 169-180 </p>



<p>Case II (mechanical industry) was carried out in a 
mechanical factory producing two-wheeled trailers for 
passenger cars. The number of workers is 136. The 
company is located in 3 different places: the sale de-
partment is situated in Tallinn and the manufacturing 
buildings about 25 km from the capital. The welding 
process (6 workplaces) was carried out in unsafe work-
ing conditions (in the building made of silica brick, 
without any ventilation). However, the number of oc-
cupational accidents showed a decreasing trend. The 
workers were complaining on back injuries caused by 
lifting tasks. These injuries were typically caused by 
sharp pieces of sheet metal. The interest from the side 
of management was obvious. The highest scores (10) 
were given to the parts A to C. The lowest score (8.3) 
was obtained for part E: neither accident statistics nor 
near-accident investigation took place in the company. 
Vast attempts were taken by the management to im-
prove the ventilation in welding activities, but some 
rearrangements are still possible for cleaning the air 
in the breathing zone of workers. The respirators were 
used during the welding work. </p>

<p>Case III (plastic industry) was carried out in the fi rm 
on Saaremaa island (located in the west of Estonia), 
which is producing rubber products for car industry 
situated outside of Estonia (Germany). The number of 
employees is 160. The quality control of these products 
(package rings included) needs very good eye-sight 
from workers. Therefore, only the girls at the age of 
18-25 years old not wearing glasses were hired to per-
form this work. The plastic fi rm only planned to send 
the workers to the medical health examination after the 
reviewing of the risk assessments results. The high-
est score (12) in safety performance was obtained in 
part B (housekeeping, machine guarding, etc.) because 
almost all machines were new, premises good as the 
factory itself was only 2 years old. The lowest score 
(9) was obtained in part A, because there was absence </p>

<p>of safety policy and instructions as well as a lack of 
worker's health examinations. </p>

<p>Cases IV (wood processing industry) was performed 
in the enterprise with approximately 300 workers, 
which is located in a small town in the west of Esto-
nia. This company produced furniture and used dif-
ferent volatile chemicals in lacquering process. The 
main occupational hazard was dust (5-10 mg/m 3 in the 
air of the working environment). The safety training 
seemed to be performed and good, because earmuffs 
and plugs were used properly and most of the workers 
were aware of health risks. The safety manager has 
long-working experience. </p>

<p>Case V (textile industry, 400 employees, situated in 
Tallinn). The accidents were investigated in depth and 
relative corrective measures were effectively imple-
mented. In textile industry, the workers were not keen 
on wearing the earplugs (all other personal protective 
equipment was used correctly). The safety manager has 
good safety training and therefore was able to carry out 
risk assessments at workplaces herself. </p>

<p>Case VI was performed in water purifi cation plant in 
Tallinn (320 workers) which has an international occu-
pational health and safety management system speci-
fi cation (OHSAS 18000). Nearly all of the parts of the 
audit (from A to E) were assessed as level "4" -excel-
lent; only in part D there were some shortcomings (ab-
sence of written program outlining internal inspection 
guidelines, responsibilities, frequency and follow up). 
The results of the implementation of the D&amp;S method 
for external safety audit are given in Table 3B and a 
computerized method for determination of safety level 
is presented in Fig. 3. </p>

<p>The investigation of safety level had the positive re-
sults in every company. The workers and the manage-
ment of the companies had the possibility to perceive 
the problems that were essential parts of the working </p>

<p>Table 3B. Results of auditing of safety system in Estonian enterprises </p>

<p>Industry 
A* 
B* 
C* 
D* 
E* 
Total score </p>

<p>Case I (printing industry) 
13 
15 
11 
11 
10 
60 </p>

<p>Case II (mechanical industry) 
10 
10 
10 
9 
8.3 
47.3 </p>

<p>Case III (plastics industry) 
9 
12 
10 
11 
11.6 
53.6 </p>

<p>Case IV (wood processing industry) 
8 
10 
10 
11 
11.6 
50.6 </p>

<p>Case V (textile industry) 
13 
15 
10 
9 
10 
57 </p>

<p>Case VI (water purifi cation plant), 
OHSAS 18001 implemented </p>

<p>18 
18 
19 
15 
15 
85 </p>

<p>* Maximum score in each area (A, B, C, D, E) is 20. Maximum total score is 100. </p>

<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>



<p>environment before (noise, draught, etc.). The man-
agers were satisfi ed with the database on legislation, 
proposed new methods for advanced learning in the 
fi eld of OH&amp;S and computerized method for risk as-
sessment. The greatest problems in the implementation 
of the model came up in the communication between 
the worker and co-worker, and the worker and the fi rst 
level foremen. Therefore a guide was elaborated for 
co-workers safety behaviour. The interviews with em-
ployers were carried out in the same enterprises where 
the safety level was assessed. </p>

<p>The original D&amp;S method is a rough method, and it 
does not help the auditor to assess the individual safety 
activities very thoroughly and demands the high ex-
pertise of the auditor. The D&amp;S method also suggests 
certain activities which may not always be the most 
suitable and relevant solutions for every company. </p>

<p>5. The worker's opinion about 
working conditions </p>

<p>The data were collected during 2002-2004. The ob-
jective of the questionnaire was to gather information 
about the workers' knowledge of the occupational risks 
connected with their occupation, possible work-related 
occupational hazards, and attitudes towards using per-
sonal protective equipment and safety routines. Ques-</p>

<p>tions about the workers' opinions and their perceptions 
about the exposure to occupational risks (noise, chemi-
cals, vibration, bad microclimate, insuffi cient lighting, 
and ergonomics), experienced health symptoms and 
their awareness of the Occupational Health and Safety 
Act were also asked. The workers were randomly se-
lected from textile, printing, mechanical, plastic, food 
processing industries and offi ces. A questionnaire was 
distributed to 412 workers in investigated industries. 
The average age was 43.6 years. Confi dentiality of 
information was always maintained and only coded 
information was used in the analysis. Data collected 
on the questionnaire study was coded and then en-
tered into the statistical software programme (<rs type="software">Excel</rs>) 
for analyses. The investigation gave results as follows: 
1. 65% of workers considered excessive exposure 
to noise, 60% bad microclimate (too cold work-
rooms), 54% bad lighting at workplaces; not-ef-
fective ventilation was the main occupational risk 
factor (75% of workplaces). 
2. Only some of the workers (10%) answered that 
they know which information about the danger-
ousness of chemicals may be obtained from the 
chemical labels. Nobody of respondents pointed 
at the chemical safety data sheets as one of the 
important source of information. 
3. Most of the workers (80%) reported that personal 
protective equipment (PPE) was accessible; how-
ever, the questionnaire did not show the attitudes 
towards using PPE. Some of the respondents 
(36%) pointed that the PPE disturbs the work; 
others mentioned (46%) that the quality of PPE is 
not very good. 
4. In the present study, 63% of the workers reported 
that they were aware of the person who was the 
working environment specialist in their company. 
At the same time, only 20% of workers knew who 
was elected to be their working environment rep-
resentative. 
5. Different opinions were given on safety instruc-
tions and guidelines. In the present study, 25% of 
the workers reported that they had not received 
safety instructions and guidelines. The assessment 
of the safety instructions was made on a 6-point 
scale (from 0 to 5, where 0 was bad and 5 -very 
good). According to workers' opinion, the quality 
of accessed safety instruction was satisfactory (2.8 
points). 
6. The questionnaire revealed that only 25% were 
generally aware of the safety legislation. </p>

<p>The investigation of the workers' knowledge on the 
legislation in the fi eld of OH&amp;S was carried out by 
the authors also in September 2008 in four enterprises. 
The 422 questionnaires were received from different </p>

<p>Fig. 3. A simple computerized method for determination 
of safety level at enterprise </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(2): 169-180 </p>



<p>branches of industry: 162 from the textile industry; 
25 from the wood processing industry; 200 from the 
mechanical industry and 35 from the printing indus-
try. The average age of the workers (N = 422) was 45 
years. The results show that the workers are aware of 
their rights and responsibilities decreed by the OH&amp;S 
regulations. Even, if workers know who their working 
environment representative is, in the case of shortages 
in the working environment, they prefer to turn to the 
direct foreman at their workplace, not to their work-
ing environment representative. The workers consid-
ered the insuffi cient lighting (82%), dust (34%), noise 
(75%) and vibration (45%) to be the main occupational 
risk factors in their workplaces. </p>

<p>In addition, half of the correspondents (50%) stated 
that they have to work in a stationary position. </p>

<p>On the basis of the investigation it could be concluded 
that the questionnaire for workers has to be rather short 
(10 questions, including list of hazards in the working 
environment and the scale has to be not more that 4 
(from 1 as bad to 4 as very good working conditions). 
The questionnaire for workers has to include the fol-
lowing questions: 
1. Do you know your working environment repre-
sentative? 
2. What kind of the following hazards disturbs you in 
the working environment: noise, vibration, insuf-
fi cient or too strong lighting, cold or hot micro-
climate, too dry air, smell of chemicals, dust and 
how strongly? Do you lift heavy loads or work in 
the compulsory position? 
3. What do you do with your co-workers and fore-
man? To whom do you approach with non-com-
pliance in the working environment? 
4. Are you supplied with the Chemical Data Sheets 
(CDS)? What information do you get from CDS? 
What are R-and S-phrases? 
5. Have you the instructions for safe work methods 
in written form at your workplace? 
6. Are you supplied with personal protective equip-
ment (PPE)? Are these comfortable or does the 
PPE disturb your work? Do you wear PPE always 
when it is needed by the instructions? </p>

<p>6. The awareness of employers on OH&amp;S 
matters in investigated companies </p>

<p>Semi-structured interviews with top management were 
carried out in 6 enterprises in order to gather informa-
tion about their awareness in the fi eld of OH&amp;S. The 
management of 80% of the investigated companies 
(Cases I-VI) considered the role of working environ-</p>

<p>ment as an important. 30% of the interviewed compa-
nies had a certain plan of activities to improve work-
ing conditions, 15% of companies were composing 
the plan how to reduce the occupational risks. Psycho-
logical risk factors (also forced position, monotonous 
work) received the most negative assessment from dif-
ferent sides of working environment. It is understand-
able as the factor appears in the case of all fi elds of 
activities and different size of companies, when at the 
same time, for example, physical load of the job or its 
dangerousness appears only in the case of some fi eld 
of activities or occupations (printing, wood process-
ing). Attitudes to working conditions, design/furniture 
of the workplace and work related daily living con-
ditions received less negative assessments. Respond-
ents were asked also to evaluate on a 10-point scale 
their employees' risk to impair their health at work. 
Two thirds of respondents consider the risk to their 
employees' health suffi ciently low (1-4 points). 15% 
of interviewed companies did not see any risk factors 
that would endanger employees' health. Industry man-
agers mentioned as the main risk factors to the employ-
ees' health are noise (80%), vibration (70%), physical 
overload (50%), fl uctuation of temperature (50%) and 
work monotonousness (50%). Despite the fact that 
companies from different fi eld of activities evaluate 
risk factors to employees' health differently, there are 
no signifi cant differences in assessment of employees' 
sickness problems. Occupational diseases and the other 
health problems were bothering factors only for some 
(30%) of the companies. In order to assess the persons, 
who follow the situation of the working environment, 
companies' management was asked about the exist-
ence of different specialists like working environment 
representative or council in their companies. Only in 
a half of the companies the working environment rep-
resentative was elected and working environment spe-
cialists were working in 30% of companies. Looking 
at the evaluations of different persons' effi ciency to 
the improvement of working environment, we can see 
that only some companies, where separately relevant 
persons exist, estimate their work as very effi cient and 
half up to 2/3 of interviewed companies as suffi cient. 
Therefore, the relevant specialists have not found suf-
fi cient employment in their positions. In addition to 
specialists who work inside the company, there is a 
possibility to include the agreement for carrying out 
the working environment investigations externally. 
100% of investigated companies (Cases I-VI) used 
the last possibility. The external specialist's help has 
been mainly used for conducting workplace risk as-
sessment (including hazards' measurements) and con-
sulting companies in the fi eld of OH&amp;S. </p>

<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>



<p>7. The assessment of economic losses 
connected with lack of safety performance </p>

<p>The most deep working environment survey includ-
ing economic side of OHS in Estonian enterprises and 
fi rms was carried out by TNS Emor in March 2000 
(Working ... 2000). TNS Emor is the largest full service 
marketing research and consulting company in Estonia. 
One of the parts of the survey also concluded the em-
ployers' survey (402 successful interviews). </p>

<p>Only 8% of companies had tried to evaluate the eco-
nomic loss that had been caused by the employees' 
sicknesses. Bigger companies, with more than 150 em-
ployees, have done it more frequently than the average 
(19%), but 67% of all those who have tried to evalu-
ate that, were not able to give the concrete amount of 
money spent in 2000. That is why it was also impos-
sible to estimate companies' economic loss, caused by 
employees' sicknesses. Nine companies estimated the 
economic losses caused by employees sicknesses of 
approximately 39 000 EEK (1 EUR = 15.6 EEK) per 
one year. In addition to the abovementioned sicknesses, 
also work-related accidents during the last three years 
were observed in the survey. In total, in 12% of com-
panies, that operate in Estonia work-related accidents 
had taken place. More frequently than the average the 
accidents had appeared in industrial, construction and 
transportation companies. </p>

<p>The overview of different types of expenditures made 
by companies on their employees and the working en-
vironment: on average, each company had made dif-
ferent types of expenditures during 2000: 4.2 times. 
The majority of companies had made expenditures on 
improvement of working and work-related daily living 
conditions and purchase of working clothes and PPE. 
The expenditures, made during 2000 by companies 
that operate in Estonia, on improvement of working 
environment in total amount estimation together with 
probability limits. The highest expenditures were re-
lated to improvement of working conditions: between 
1.13-3.06 billion EEK (p &lt; 0.05), it was followed by 
the expenditures on improvement of work-related dai-
ly living conditions -between 0.49-0.72 billion EEK 
and on working clothes and personal protection equip-
ment -0.22-0.4 billion EEK. The expenditures made 
by companies in connection with employees' health: 
the biggest amounts had been spent on employees' 
sporting possibilities: 113-215 million EEK (p &lt; 0.05), 
it was followed by almost the same level expenditures 
on health control, occupational health and safety train-
ing and making of health insurance contracts. In total, 
the expenditures made by the companies on improve-</p>

<p>ment of working environment per one year were be-
tween 3.45-4.47 billion EEK (p &lt; 0.05). Depending 
on the type of expenditures, they apply to 15-81% of 
companies. Of those companies, who had not made 
any certain type of expenditures on working environ-
ment or employees' health-related factors during 2000, 
were asked how necessary would they evaluate that 
the employer makes such kind of expenditures. Three-
quarters of companies, who did not make expenditures 
on improvement of working and work-related daily liv-
ing conditions during the previous year, considered the 
expenditures necessary. Also, explanation of occupa-
tional safety questions to employees was evaluated as 
very necessary. </p>

<p>The respondents were also asked to name concrete 
factors that need to be improved in their company's 
working environment. 44% of respondents brought 
out different factors. The abovementioned improve-
ments presume relatively big investments. Respond-
ents gave sums between 2000 EEK and up to 20-30 
million EEK. The last one means practically construct-
ing a new building. Considering partially very approxi-
mately given assessments by respondents and also the 
fact that 67% of all interviewed companies were not 
able to name a certain number that they would spend 
on making changes in the working environment, it is 
not correct to extend the results in order to fi nd out 
the investment needs of all companies that operate in 
Estonia. </p>

<p>As a result of the investigation the proposal for self-
assessment questionnaire for employers is presented: 
1. How much do your company's working conditions 
correspond to the requirements set by the law of 
occupational health and safety? 
2. Have you composed the plan of activities to im-
prove the working conditions in your company/ 
institution? 
3. How much do you take into consideration the 
proposals that employees make for improving the 
working conditions? 
4. Has the National Labour Inspectorate inspected 
your company/institution? What were the results 
of the inspecting? 
5. Please give your assessments on a 10-point scale, 
how big is your employees' risk to impair their 
health at work? 
6. Which of the following hazards in the working 
environment (dust, noise, vibration, bad lighting, 
lack of ventilation, temperature, dangerous chemi-
cals, forced position, monotonous work, physical 
load, mental stress) do you estimate as risk factors 
to your employees' health? </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(2): 169-180 </p>



<p>7. How much do the employees' illnesses bother 
your company's/institution's activities? 
8. Have you evaluated economic loss caused by 
employees' sicknesses -lost working time, un-
done work? 
9. Have you spent money during the previous year 
on employees' vaccination, employees' health 
control, offering sporting opportunities to em-
ployees, making insurance contracts to employ-
ees on company's/institution's initiative, work-
ing environment specialist and representative 
training and advance training, fi rst-aid training, 
measuring the working environment risk factors, 
improving working conditions, improving work-
related daily living conditions, working clothes 
and personal protection equipment? 
10. Does a working environment specialist work in 
your company/institution, has the working envi-
ronment representative been chosen among the 
employees, does the working environment coun-
cil operate? 
11. Have you included Occupational Health Service 
or an occupational health specialist (medical doc-
tor, nurse) into the working condition analyses? </p>

<p>8. Survey of occupational health and safety 
professionals in Estonia </p>

<p>As part of the Estonian-Finnish Twinning Project on 
Occupational Health it was decided to carry out a sur-
vey of occupational health and safety practices and 
development needs in Estonia. The aim of the survey 
was to get knowledge of the current practices, main 
priorities and major problems, attitudes, professional 
skills and perceived needs for further education among 
OH&amp;S professionals. The study was carried out using a 
questionnaire designed for the occupational health and 
safety professionals. The target group for the survey 
were all the 103 OH&amp;S professionals (occupational 
health physicians (OH physicians), OH nurses, hygien-
ists, ergonomists, psychologists) who were practising 
as occupational health and safety professionals at the 
time of the data collection in Estonia (Kempinen and 
Sarap 2002). Although the response rate was low, 40%, 
the size of the study group was large enough to assess 
the major problems in the fi eld of occupational health 
and safety and to describe the occupational health and 
safety professionals' attitudes, level of education and 
knowledge. However, statistical analysis for the dif-
ferences between the groups could not be done. The 
work experience in the fi eld of OH&amp;S of the partici-
pants in the survey varied between the professional </p>

<p>groups. OH physicians had longer work experience 
(the average 21.4 years) than other specialists. 60% 
of OH physicians and 80% of nurses worked in health 
care centres where they performed OHS besides other 
medical services. The main tasks of OH&amp;S profes-
sionals consisted of risk assessments, workplace sur-
veys, health examinations, advice related to work, but 
also health promotion activities. Most of the respond-
ents were experienced professionals, with high level 
of training. The professionals stated that occupational 
diseases and work-related diseases (diagnostic and pre-
vention), rehabilitation and/or promotion of work abil-
ity were the main subjects for need in further training. 
Also, a need for clarifying guidelines of Occupational 
Health and Safety, legislation and regulations in Esto-
nia was identifi ed. 90% of OH physicians stated that 
they can understand Estonian, 42% of OH physicians 
can speak Russian; 27% can speak English and most of 
the physicians reported that they understand the Finn-
ish language. Access to Internet was available for 82% 
of the respondents, and most of them used it for infor-
mation search, on average 5 hours/week. All of the oc-
cupational health physicians and nurses answered that 
workers told them about work-related health problems 
at least weekly. Two thirds of the respondents consid-
ered, that the workers were not afraid of telling about 
these problems to them (Kempinen and Sarap 2002). 
According to OH&amp;S professionals' responses, there are 
the following main priorities and major problems in the 
OH&amp;S practice in Estonia: 
1. The absence of Insurance Act of Occupational Ac-
cidents and Diseases. 
2. The absence of the Governmental participation in 
the fi eld of occupational health and safety (Gov-
ernmental fi nancial support). 
3. It is impossible to analyse sensitive personal data. 
4. The absence of an agreement between OH physi-
cians and Health Insurance Fund in order to pro-
vide fi nancial support for the rehabilitation serv-
ices. 
5. There is a lack of OHS in Estonia (low coverage 
of the OHS services offered to employees). 
6. There is insuffi cient work collaboration between 
Occupational Health and Safety Institutions in Es-
tonia. 
7. Lack of knowledge among employers and work-
ers concerning the Estonian National Policy on 
the working environment and their awareness of 
OH&amp;S is insuffi cient. 
8. Lack of the OH&amp;S professionals and of the re-
search activities in Estonia (Kempinen and Sarap 
2002). </p>

<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>



<p>9. Discussion and conclusions </p>

<p>As the conclusion of the investigation, the following 
scheme can been drawn for the improvement of safety 
culture at the enterprise (Fig. 4). The most important 
issue at companies is the collective awareness of safety 
learning necessity (Kumpikaitė 2008; Kumpikaitė and 
Čiarnienė 2008). Instructions and rules are the key 
ways of achieving a healthy working environment and 
risk control. There is a concentration on observable 
action, both human and social. The machinery or the 
rules may not be fl exible when changes in production 
are required. It is likely that production would come 
out victorious in any such confl ict. The occupational 
disease develops by stages (Fig. 1): some complaints, 
recoverable disease, non-recoverable disease. The co-
operation between the employer, worker and occupa-
tional health physicians is urgent in order to achieve 
the positive safety culture and high safety performance 
at the enterprise. At present, most of the occupational 
diseases are diagnosed at the very last stage in Esto-
nia. The diagnoses of occupational diseases as well as 
maintenance of work ability are still in the need for 
development in Estonian OH&amp;S system. </p>

<p>The knowledge about safety and health is very differ-
ent in different companies. Some of the managers are 
competent, but the workers' knowledge of OH&amp;S is 
low because they do not receive proper safety train-
ing and there is a lack of guidelines. Only workers 
involved in very dangerous operations are instructed 
and trained regularly. </p>

<p>Further research is needed in order to understand the 
factors involved in safety culture and safety manage-</p>

<p>ment system at the enterprise, how OH&amp;S knowledge 
is disseminated and translated into practice, especially 
focusing on knowledge management for young work-
ers, non-Estonian speaking, for employers and em-
ployees in small business. There is also a need for 
strengthening of national OH&amp;S system in Estonia as 
well as awareness of the public through tripartite col-
laboration, and this includes legal provisions, enforce-
ment, compliance and labour inspection capacity and 
capability, knowledge management strategy, informa-
tion exchange, research and support services. </p>



<p>Fig. 4. The infl uence of different parties on OH&amp;S at workplaces </p>

<p>Training of managers </p>

<p>Managers' 
commitment </p>

<p>Training of 
occupational health 
&amp; safety specialists </p>

<p>Risk management </p>

<p>Safety management </p>

<p>Communication, training 
&amp; monitoring </p>

<p>Safety culture </p>

<p>Cooperation between managers 
and occupational health 
physicians (OHS) </p>

<p>Training of workers </p>

<p>Workers' 
opinion </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2009, 10(2): 169-180 </p>





<p>M. Järvis, P. Tint. The formation of a good safety culture at enterprise </p>

</text></tei>