<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2F1648-0627.2009.10.107-117" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The paper aims to analyse sustainable development indicators taken from the Eurostat database and to determine a 
rational relationship between the sustainable development indicators and the economic growth of the country. The suggested 
hypothesis implies that the process of the country's development differs depending on the stage of the development. in order 
to establish the relationship between the sustainable development and the economic growth, the correlation analysis was used. 
Lithuania, Latvia and Estonia were taken as the research objects and the results obtained were compared with those describing 
the developed countries (). The results obtained outline the main 
economic trends as well as determining their variation depending on the development stage of the country. </p>

<p>Sustainable development is a leading concept of nowa-
days. it started to be considered as urgent issue since 1972 
Stockholm Conference on the Human Environment, where 
the conflicts between environment and development had 
been acknowledged the first time (Kates et al. 2005). A 
lot of studies have been devoted to the new philosophy. 
However, there are various definitions of this phenom-
enon. The widely known definition states that it is the 
"ability of humanity to ensure that it meets the needs of 
the present generation without compromising the ability 
of future generation to meet their own needs" (Brundtland  1987). Germination of the concept of sustainable develop-
ment at institutional level has been analysed by Grybaitė  and Tvaronavičienė (2008). The concept of sustainable 
development contains three dimensions of welfare, com-
prising economic, environmental, social aspects and their 
interrelations. 
The aim of the paper is to analyse the relationship 
between the economic growth and sustainable development 
in different countries, juxtaposing the Baltic states with 
developed European countries. The assumption is made that 
economic processes of a particular country differ depending 
on the stage of its development. it might be the case that, at 
the lower level of economic development, there is a stronger 
relationship between the economic growth of the country 
and social-economic variables, while at the higher level, the 
environmental indicators are very important. 
The modern study of economic growth was started by 
Adam Smith and David Ricardo. Since then, many theories 
have been defining the major factors of economic growth, 
but three basic factors, such as capital formation, popula-
tion growth, technological changes and their interactions 
were mainly emphasized. The role of capital formation, 
reflected in saving and investment has been a crucial fac-
tor in many works of economics thinkers for centuries, and 
it remains important even today (Tvaronavičienė 2006;  Tvaronavičienė, Tvaronavičius 2008). During the past fifty 
years the term "economic growth" was being transformed 
to a new notion -economic development, emphasizing not 
only the growth of the quantity of material goods and serv-
ices, but also a higher level of welfare of the country. it was 
suggested (Theobald 1961) to divide the process of economic 
development into five stages, which every nation can pass 
regardless of its social and political structure. Notably, this 
approach is often presented as one of the leading theories 
of economic development (Parr 2001). in the middle of the 
20th century social capital was made a focus in the analysis 
of factors, influencing the economic growth. T. W. Schultz 
was one of the first researchers who began to treat entrepre-
neurship as human capital, i.e. skills obtained by investing 
in a particular type of human resources (Huffman 2006). 
The social positions of development became even more </p>

<p>prominent with the adoption of Human Development index 
(Ghosh 2008). Social factor has been widely explored and 
now social development is considered to be a prerequisite 
for economic growth, while economic and social systems 
are often presented as one. 
Since the 1970s, when the Club of Rome put forth the 
theory of "limits to growth", environment has been con-
sidered as a new prerequisite for economic growth. The 
world has recognized new challenges and responsibilities 
for changing climate and diminishing natural resources. 
The most effective theory based on the relationship between 
pollution and income level was developed (Bradford et al.  2005). Since then the economists have been analysing the 
question: "Do poor people care less about their health than 
rich people? if not, what makes the populations in poor 
countries, generally speaking, less healthy?" (Torras 2006). 
The later notion emphasizes that economic development and 
ecological services cannot be observed as one system, where 
the causality flows from both directions. 
Hence, the concept of sustainable development is a vision 
of progress that links economic development, protection 
of the environment and social justice, and its values are 
recognised by democratic governments and political move-
ments the world over (Grybaitė, Tvaronavičienė 2008). The 
evaluation of sustainable development is the basic approach 
to the assessment of the development level. This is the only 
way to find reasons and solutions to our position in many 
fields of sustainable development (Kovačič 2007). 
Not going into the discussion about the need for new 
theories of inclusive development, the research is framed as 
follows. if sustainable development leads to higher and more 
stable economic growth, then the goal of the analysis is to 
find the most important sustainable development indicators 
for the Baltic region and compare them with those char-
acteristic of developed countries in the European Union's 
context. </p>

<p>2. The relationship between economic growth 
and sustainable development </p>

<p>in order to define the relevant variables, Eurostat sus-
tainable development indicators, which are grouped in 
ten areas, were analysed. The groups were described in 
detail by Grybaitė and Tvaronavičienė (2008). All indica-
tors from the Eurostat sustainable development database 
were reviewed and only those satisfying the conditions 
given below were chosen for analysis: </p>

<p>Lithuanian data is available; 
-</p>

<p>The same data sets cover more than one country; 
-</p>

<p>The data gathered in the period from 1997 to 2006 
-
without intervals; </p>

<p>The variables are statistically measured. 
-</p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2009, 10(2): 107-117 </p>



<p>A correlation analysis is used as a statistical method to 
define the relationship. Calculations were made using <rs type="software">MS Excel</rs> and are presented in Appendix 1. 
Based on the countries' classification provided by the 
World Economic Forum (Sala-i-Martin et al. 2008), several 
countries were chosen for comparison: the Baltic states 
as having the most similar economic situation. Austria, 
Denmark, Belgium, Netherlands were chosen as small but 
highly developed countries, while France and Germany 
were included as similarly developed big countries. As GDP 
growth is used as a basic indicator for this analysis it should 
be emphasized that it is different in the groups of the Baltic 
states and the developed countries. The growth of all three 
Baltic states is about four times that (except Russian crisis 
in 1999) of other countries analysed. This is graphically 
shown in Fig. 1. 
only the indicators with the statistically significant cor-
relation are chosen and presented in Table 1. Correlation 
coefficients were calculated using the log change of sustain-
able development indicator and the log change of GDP (in 
constant prices) for the respective country. in many sources 
(Čekanavičius, Murauskas 2002) the correlation coefficient 
of 0.30 is described as a minimal level for the relationship 
to be valid, but this is only true for large data samples, 
more than 50 data points. For a small data sample (as in 
this work) the significance of the correlation coefficient can 
be determined by using standard distribution calculated by 
Student t test. Alternatively, a simple formula to determine 
the approximate critical value of the correlation coefficient 
at 0.05 level of significance was introduced (Walsh 2008):   where n is the number of data items. </p>

<p>Accordingly, the calculated threshold for the correlation 
coefficient in the presented data sample is 0.63. 
Hence, the indicators for further analysis were chosen 
based on the following criterion: at least one country in 
the group (the Baltic region -a transition stage versus the 
(developed countries) should have a coefficient of more than 
0.63, while others should demonstrate similar trends. 
Based on the use of the mentioned criteria, only social-
economic and environmental variables presented in Table 1 
were chosen. other (social inclusion, demographic, health) 
indicators were excluded from the analysis as their correla-
tion coefficients were insignificant. 
Social-economic indicators make the largest subgroup, 
covering the topics such as investment, labour, exchange 
rate, energy intensity, sustainable consumption and produc-
tion and good governance. 
Total investment is divided into the areas of public and 
business investments. Public investment was eliminated 
from the analysis because the correlation coefficients were 
insignificant. Hence, the correlation coefficients established 
between investment and GDP are being higher than 0.50 
(Lithuania -0.67; Estonia -0.79; Latvia -0.75; Germany -
0.71; Belgium -0.55). it confirms the statement of the classi-
cal theories of economic growth that investments, particu-
larly those made in business, contribute to the growth. The 
investment as the most important driving force influencing 
the economic development of a country in transition was 
analysed by many scholars (Tvaronavičienė, Tvaronavičius 
2008; Tvaronavičienė 2006). 
The established significant relationship between labour 
market indicators and GDP confirms the importance of this 
variable in Europe. The total employment is the classical </p>

<p>-4% </p>

<p>-2% </p>

<p>0% </p>

<p>2% </p>

<p>4% </p>

<p>6% </p>

<p>8% </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>12% </p>

<p>14% </p>

<p>1997 1998 1999 2000 2001 2002 2003 2004 2005 2006 2007 </p>

<p>Lithuania </p>

<p>Latvia </p>

<p>Estonia </p>

<p>Belgium </p>

<p>Denmark </p>

<p>Germany </p>

<p>France </p>

<p>Netherlands </p>

<p>Austria </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Changes in GDP in the considered countries </p>



<p>G. Lapinskienė, K. Peleckis. Impact of sustainable development indicators on economic growth… </p>

<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Social-Economic indicators </p>

<p>Economic 
Total 
investment -
% of GDP </p>

<p>0.67 
0.79 
0.75 
0.20 
0.55 
0.56 
0.60 
0.57 
0.71 </p>

<p>Business 
investment -
% of GDP </p>

<p>0.70 
0.79 
-0.09 
0.12 
0.59 
0.58 
0.69 
0.69 
0.71 </p>

<p>Total 
employment 
rate -% </p>

<p>0.43 
0.70 
0.65 
0.25 
0.72 
0.83 
0.79 
0.31 
0.55 </p>

<p>Employment 
rate, by 
highest level 
of education 
attained -
% of age group 
25-64 years </p>

<p>0.17 
0.40 
0.62 
0.13 
0.82 
0.79 
0.46 
0.00 
0.37 </p>

<p>Unemployment 
rate </p>

<p>-0.41 
-0.58 
-0.70 
-0.41 
-0.61 
-0.73 
-0.72 
-0.74 
-0.92 </p>

<p>Growth rate 
of labour 
productivity 
per hour 
worked -% 
change over 
previous year </p>

<p>0.40 
0.29 
0.38 
0.91 
0.75 
0.24 
0.45 
0.35 
0.61 </p>

<p>Real effective 
exchange rate -
index 1999 = 
100 </p>

<p>0.07 
-0.05 
0.52 
-0.55 
-0.73 
-0.80 
-0.71 
-0.88 
-0.75 </p>

<p>Energy 
intensity of 
the economy -
kgoe per 1 000 
euro </p>

<p>0.36 
-0.31 
-0.55 
-0.88 
-0.12 
-0.64 
-0.86 
-0.26 
-0.49 </p>

<p>Sustainable 
consum-
ption and 
production </p>

<p>Municipal 
waste 
generated -
kg per capita </p>

<p>0.70 
0.06 
0.52 
0.41 
0.47 
0.43 
0.33 
0.43 
0.55 </p>

<p>Final energy 
consumption -
1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.80 
0.62 
0.62 
-0.68 
-0.24 
-0.33 
-0.20 
0.17 
0.14 </p>

<p>Household 
expenditure 
per inhabitant -
Volume index 
(1995=100) </p>

<p>0.69 
0.91 
0.85 
0.77 
0.66 
0.12 
0.83 
0.79 
0.79 </p>

<p>Table 1. Relationships between the GDP growth and sustainable development </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2009, 10(2): 107-117 </p>



<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Social-Economic indicators </p>

<p>Good 
governance </p>

<p>Shares of 
labour taxes 
in total tax 
revenues -% </p>

<p>-0.71 
-0.82 
-0.55 
0.11 
-0.41 
-0.02 
-0.07 
-0.27 
0.01 </p>

<p>General 
government 
debt -General 
government 
consolidated 
gross debt as a 
percentage of 
GDP </p>

<p>-0.83 
-0.50 
-0.56 
0.10 
-0.48 
-0.57 
-0.77 
-0.61 
-0.78 </p>

<p>Environmental indicators </p>

<p>Climate 
change </p>

<p>Greenhouse 
gas emissions -
index base 
year = 100 </p>

<p>0.82 
0.35 
0.69 
-0.84 
-0.53 
-0.38 
-0.53 
0.01 
-0.12 </p>

<p>Gross inland 
energy 
consumption -
1 000 tonnes of 
oil equivalent </p>

<p>0.64 
0.26 
0.57 
-0.81 
0.06 
-0.39 
-0.49 
0.17 
0.10 </p>

<p>Sustainable 
transport </p>

<p>Energy 
consumption 
of transport -
1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.77 
0.44 
0.54 
-0.26 
-0.08 
-0.08 
-0.03 
0.71 
0.52 </p>

<p>Greenhouse gas 
emissions from 
transport -1 
000 tonnes of 
Co 2 equivalent </p>

<p>0.77 
0.62 
0.50 
-0.21 
-0.06 
-0.25 
0.20 
0.20 
0.30 </p>

<p>Emissions of 
particulate 
matter from 
transport -
1 000 tonnes </p>

<p>0.65 
0.60 
0.41 
-0.09 
0.58 
-0.31 
0.24 
0.10 
0.56 </p>

<p>End of Table 1 </p>

<p>index of macroeconomy. it might lead to the growth of 
GDP at all development stages. Positive significant corre-
lation has been found for the Baltic states (Lithuania -0.43; 
Estonia -0.70; Latvia -0.65) and for the developed countries 
as well (Belgium -0.72; Denmark -0.83; Netherlands -
0.79; Germany -0.55). A high correlation coefficient of the 
employment rate of people with the highest level of educa-
tion is found in Latvia -0.62; Belgium -0.82; Denmark -
0.79. A relatively low correlation coefficient can be observed 
in Lithuania -0.17. Lithuania is lagging behind in this 
respect. Unemployment rate negatively affects the GDP 
growth. Most values are less than -0.50, which confirms 
that unemployment reduces the economic growth, acting in 
the opposite direction to employment. it is evident that the </p>

<p>higher rate of labour productivity per hour worked should 
result in GDP. The strong relationship between them can 
be observed in Austria -0.91; Belgium -0.75. Strong cor-
relation between these indicators has not been found in the 
Baltic countries. in general, the relation between all labour 
indicators and GDP is lower in the Baltic states compared to 
that in the developed counties. This leads to the conclusion 
that the economic processes in this market of transitional 
countries are more volatile. 
Real effective exchange rate can be used to assess the 
competitiveness of the state's currency. it should be noted 
that national currency in all Baltic states is historically 
pegged to base currency (USD, SDR, EUR), while all ana-
lysed developed countries have introduced Euro since 1999. </p>



<p>G. Lapinskienė, K. Peleckis. Impact of sustainable development indicators on economic growth… </p>

<p>These historical differences in foreign exchange mode can 
be seen from the correlation results. There is a strong eco-
nomically logic negative correlation, indicating that the 
increase in competitiveness causes the growth of GDP in 
the Euro zone countries. However in the Baltic region, the 
exchange rates have been fixed and the relationship is not 
so straightforward. 
Energy intensity shows the amount of energy needed 
to produce one unit of economic output. A lower coeffi-
cient number indicates energy efficiency. The correlation 
obtained in the developed countries confirms that energy 
efficiency contributes to the GDP growth (negative corre-
lation Austria -0.88; Denmark -0.64; Netherlands -0.86; 
italy -0.85). in Lithuania, the coefficient (0.36) is statistically 
insignificant but surprisingly positive. it can be attributed 
to a lower technological level. 
in economic terms, the sustainable consumption and 
production subgroup is based on life cycle approach to the 
use of resources, every day consumption and waste. in this 
chain, all levels embracing governments, citizens/consum-
ers and business should be included. The importance of 
the indicator showing the waste generated by the industry 
has increased in recent years and this process is related to 
the increasing irresponsible production and consumption. 
Hence, it is evident that it is closely connected with GDP. 
The significant positive correlation coefficient was found 
only for Lithuania (0.70). in the developed countries, the 
relationship is weaker; it can be attributed to better man-
agement of waste in highly developed countries. 
There are significant statistical correlation coefficients 
of household expenditure per inhabitant and GDP in all 
the countries analysed (except Denmark -0.12). Therefore, 
it can be concluded that stimulation of this rate leads to 
a higher GDP. on the other hand, it is very important to 
have sustainable consumption. 
Total energy consumption shows the use of energy in 
all areas, including industry, transport, household, agri-
culture, services and others. Energy is an important eco-
nomic resource in all regions. High significant correlation 
is found for Lithuania (0.80), Estonia (0.62), Latvia (0.62). 
These results indicate that the economy of the Baltic re-
gion is highly dependent on energy. on the other hand, 
there is no significant relation in this area in the developed 
countries. 
The concept of sustainable consumption and produc-
tion is more widely known in the developed countries. 
The Baltic states have to use and sustain resources effec-
tively. Good governance is a subgroup related to institu-
tional work and some scholars suggest adding institutional 
work as the fourth dimension to a concept of sustainable 
development concept since it is very important for smooth 
development. 
Shares of labour taxes in the total tax revenue are gen-</p>

<p>erally defined as all personal income taxes, payroll taxes 
and social contributions of employees and employers that 
are levied on labour income (both employed and non-
employed).The higher rate of labour taxes in the total tax 
revenues leads to a lower GDP as taxes make a kind of busi-
ness costs. Significant and negative correlation is found in 
the Baltic states (Lithuania -0.71; Estonia -0.82; Latvia -
0.55). The statistically significant relation is not found in 
the developed countries. The results might indicate that in 
the Baltic states, changes in labour taxes greatly affect GDP, 
and therefore, they should be implemented with care. 
General government debt is the financial indica-
tor showing the ability of the government to meet its 
future liabilities. The results show that in many countries 
a lower debt relates to a higher GDP (Lithuania -0.83; 
Netherlands -0.77; Germany -0.78). This rate is one of the 
most important values at all stages of development. 
The conclusion can be made that there are indica-
tors, such as investment, government debt, household 
expenditure, employment rate and exchange rate, which 
influence GDP at all stages of development. There are areas 
which have to be monitored at particular stages in order 
to improve the welfare of the country. Sustainability is a 
popular philosophy in the developed world. The lower rates 
of waste and effective energy consumption in the developed 
countries encourage others to use resources in such a way 
to preserve the environment for future generations. 
Many scientists and the growing number of Greenpeace 
activists warn us that every day of rough development is 
damaging our environment irreversibly. There is a paradox 
question associated with the nature of sustainable develop-
ment: "is it possible to reconcile sustainability with devel-
opment?" Trying to ensure the welfare of human beings, at 
the same time, they are destroying the main surroundings 
of every creature. Therefore, not going into a painful theo-
retical discussion, let us define the group of environmental 
indicators. 
Environmental indicators chosen as having a statisti-
cally significant correlation are climate change and sus-
tainable transport. Climate change is linked with many 
areas of human activities. it requires taking some measures 
in many sectors from energy and transport to land use 
and urban development. All these measures, if success-
fully managed, result in sustainable development. Climate 
change is mostly caused by greenhouse gas emission. This 
indicator is strictly controlled by Kyoto protocol, however, 
despite this fact, it is increasing every year in most of the 
countries. The high rate of positive correlation between 
the total greenhouse gas emissions and GDP is found 
in the Baltic region (Lithuania -0.82, Estonia -0.35, 
Latvia -0.69). The relation with GDP is negative or insig-
nificant in the developed countries. The results show that 
the Baltic states produce GDP using energy associated </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2009, 10(2): 107-117 </p>



<p>with high greenhouse gas emission. in the developed West 
European context the weak points of the Baltic states' sus-
tainable development may be clearly seen. Climate change is 
closely related to energy consumption. Gross inland energy 
consumption shows the usage of various energy sources 
(fuel, gas, renewable energy sources, etc.). Positive signifi-
cant correlation is found for Lithuania (0.64) and Latvia 
(0.57) with not so strong correlation observed in Estonia 
(0.26). Negative and significant correlation is found in 
Austria (-0.81), and negative but not strong correlation can 
be observed in Denmark (-0.39) and Netherlands (-0.49). 
Hence, higher consumption of fuel is closely related to the 
GDP growth in the Baltic states. in general, it can be seen 
that the Baltic region does not demonstrate the effective 
policy against the climate change. The results are different 
in the developed European countries. only Estonia show 
positive trends to sustainability. 
Vehicles make a large contribution to overall pollution 
and climate change. The chosen indices prove the impor-
tance of this factor. The indicator "Energy consumption in 
transport" has a significant high correlation with GDP in 
the Baltic region (Lithuania -0.77; Latvia -0.54; Estonia -
0.44), while in the developed countries similar results can 
be observed in France (0.71) and Germany (0.52). in other 
countries, this relationship is insignificant. 
A significant and positive relation was found between 
the GDP growth and greenhouse gas emission by transport 
facilities as well as the emission of particulate matter by ve-
hicles, exclusively in the Baltic region (among the developed 
countries only Belgium and Germany show the relation-
ship between GDP and emission of particulate matter by 
transport facilities). Hence, the data obtained in the pre sent 
work allow us to conclude that the Baltic region is lagging 
behind in creating a sustainable transport system. 
Based on the results of the correlation analysis performed 
using the environmental indicators, the differences in their 
relationships in the Baltic states and those characterizing 
developed countries can be observed. This can be used as 
a proof that sustainable development policy is being imple-
mented more effectively in the developed countries. </p>

<p>3. Conclusions </p>

<p>The philosophy of sustainable development has been built 
evolutionally, as the economic growth was supplemented 
with new social values and environmental protection chal-
lenges. Despite many attempts to frame this concept, it is 
still alive and changes in time. Recently, the scholars have 
been challenged to create a unified theory of many di-
mensions, including economic, social and environmental 
and other (institutional, religion, etc.) aspects in order to 
ensure prosperity in the world for the present and future 
generations. </p>

<p>After the collapse of the centrally planned and control-
led systems in the Baltic states these countries demonstrate 
a rapid economic growth (despite some economic down-
turns). it should be noted that during the last decade the 
rate of GDP growth in the Baltic region has been much 
higher than in the developed European countries. Still, a 
large gap in the level of per capita income remains between 
the Baltic states and the developed European countries. 
The results of the analysis performed confirm the widely 
accepted notion that positive macroeconomic indicators 
impact on the prosperity of a country at every stage of 
its development. investment, total employment, exchan-
ge rate, household expenditure, government debt have a 
statistically significant relationship with GDP. 
To ensure the long-term economic growth, using the 
policy of sustainable development, environmental pro-
tection programs have to be implemented. Based on the 
results of the correlation analysis performed using the 
environmental indicators, the difference in the priorities 
in the Baltic states and those characterizing developed 
countries can be defined. The Baltic region has a highly 
significant correlation between environmental indicators 
and GDP and, unfortunately, the relationship is the stron-
gest in Lithuania. it confirms the statements of the theories 
that at the lower stage of development, pollution is asso-
ciated with a higher GDP. in the developed countries, the 
relationship is often negative: the lower level of pollution 
is related to a higher GDP. This is a proof that the policy 
of sustainable development is being implemented more 
effectively in the developed countries, and this does not 
contradict to the prospect of higher economic growth in 
the longer perspective. </p>





<p>G. Lapinskienė, K. Peleckis. Impact of sustainable development indicators on economic growth… </p>

<p>Kates, R.; Parris, T.; Leiserowitz, A. 2005. What is sustainable 
development? Environment: Science and Policy for Sustain-
able Development 47(3): 8-21. 
Kovačič, A. 2007. Sustainable Development and the Problems of 
Measuring, International Journal of Humanities and Social 
Sciences 1(2): 83-91. 
Mason, R. D.; Lind, D. A.; Marchal, W. G. 1999. Statistical 
Techniques in Business and Economics. Tenth edition. irwin 
McGraw-Hill. 
Parr, J. 2001. on the regional dimensions of Rostow's theory of 
growth, Review of Urban and Regional Development Stu dies 
13(1): 2-19. 
Sala-i-Martin, X.; Blanke, J.; Hanouz, M. D.; Geiger, T.; Mia, i.; 
Paua, F. 2008. The Global competitiveness index: prioritizing 
the economic policy agenda. World Economic Forum 2008. 
The global competitiveness Report 2008-2009. Available 
from internet: &lt; http://www.weforum.org/documents/ 
GCR0809/index.html&gt;. </p>

<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Labour productivity per 
person employed -GDP 
in Purchasing Power 
Standards (PPS) per 
person employed relative 
to EU-27 
(EU-27 = 100) </p>

<p>0.44 
-0.06 
0.15 
0.45 
0.42 
0.47 
0.41 
0.16 
-0.68 </p>

<p>Total investment -% of 
GDP </p>

<p>0.67 
0.79 
0.75 
0.20 
0.55 
0.56 
0.60 
0.57 
0.71 </p>

<p>Public investment -% of 
GDP </p>

<p>0.13 
0.29 
0.36 
0.28 
0.25 
0.16 
-0.36 
0.12 
0.07 </p>

<p>Business investment -% 
of GDP </p>

<p>0.70 
0.79 
-0.09 
0.12 
0.59 
0.58 
0.69 
0.69 
0.71 </p>

<p>Dispersion of regional 
GDP per inhabitant -in % 
of the national GDP per 
inhabitant </p>

<p>-0.28 
0.32 
-0.52 
-0.36 
0.08 
na* 
-0.08 
0.34 
0.09 </p>

<p>Net national income -% 
of GDP </p>

<p>0.26 
-0.25 
0.33 
-0.06 
0.66 
-0.20 
0.27 
0.47 
-0.12 </p>

<p>Gross household 
saving -% of gross 
household disposable 
income </p>

<p>-0.26 
0.05 
-0.09 
0.21 
-0.22 
-0.20 
-0.23 
-0.20 
-0.69 </p>

<p>Labour productivity per 
hour worked -% change 
over previous year </p>

<p>0.25 
na 
na 
0.58 
0.44 
-0.29 
na 
0.05 
0.32 </p>

<p>Total R&amp;D 
expenditure -% of GDP </p>

<p>0.36 
-0.36 
0.59 
-0.26 
0.30 
-0.31 
-0.05 
-0.05 
0.39 </p>

<p>Energy intensity of the 
economy -kgoe per 
1 000 euro </p>

<p>0.36 
-0.31 
-0.55 
-0.88 
-0.12 
-0.64 
-0.86 
-0.26 
-0.49 </p>

<p>Total employment rate -% 
0.43 
0.70 
0.65 
0.25 
0.72 
0.83 
0.79 
0.31 
0.55 </p>

<p>Appendix 1. Correlation between changes in sustainable development indices and GDP change </p>

<p>Theobald, R. 1961. Toward a practical theory of economic 
growth, American Journal of Economics &amp; Sociology 20(3): 
327-331. 
Torras, M. 2006. The impact of power equality, income, and 
the environment on human health: Some inter-Country, 
International Review of Applied Economics 20(1): 1-20. 
Tvaronavičienė, M. 2006. investment driving forces affecting 
Lithuanian economic growth, Journal of Business Economics 
and Management 7(2): 69-76. 
Tvaronavičienė, M.; Tvaronavičius, V. 2008. Role of fixed 
investments in economic growth of country: Lithuania 
in European context, Journal of Business Economics and 
Management 9(1): 57-64. 
Walsh, D. A. 2008. Simple rule of thumb for statistically signifi-
cant correlation. Middle Tennessee State University. Avail-
able from internet: &lt;http://frank.mtsu.edu/~dwalsh/436/ 
CoRRSiG.pdf&gt;. </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2009, 10(2): 107-117 </p>



<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Employment rate, by 
highest level of education 
attained -% of age group 
25-64 years </p>

<p>0.17 
0.40 
0.62 
0.13 
0.82 
0.79 
0.46 
0.00 
0.37 </p>

<p>Electricity consumption 
by households -1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.05 
-0.08 
0.49 
0.25 
-0.34 
-0.21 
-0.15 
0.01 
-0.56 </p>

<p>Electricity consumption 
by households -1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.05 
-0.08 
0.49 
0.25 
-0.34 
-0.21 
-0.15 
0.01 
-0.56 </p>

<p>Household expenditure 
per inhabitant, by 
category -Volume index 
(1995 = 100) </p>

<p>0.69 
0.91 
0.85 
0.77 
0.66 
0.12 
0.83 
0.79 
0.79 </p>

<p>Total long-term 
unemployment rate -% </p>

<p>0.01 
-0.48 
-0.50 
-0.21 
-0.40 
-0.80 
-0.71 
-0.55 
-0.65 </p>

<p>Lifelong learning -% 
0.26 
-0.23 
na 
-0.12 
0.00 
-0.25 
0.34 
-0.46 
-0.55 </p>

<p>Public expenditure on 
education -Percent of 
GDP </p>

<p>-0.16 
-0.54 
-0.16 
0.07 
na 
-0.02 
-0.61 
-0.03 
-0.39 </p>

<p>Early school-leavers -% 
-0.24 
-0.42 
na 
0.25 
-0.54 
0.19 
0.04 
-0.18 
-0.09 </p>

<p>Employment rate of older 
workers </p>

<p>0.12 
0.56 
0.32 
0.14 
0.33 
0.03 
0.17 
-0.56 
-0.24 </p>

<p>Net migration, including 
corrections -persons </p>

<p>0.41 
0.02 
0.28 
-0.34 
-0.40 
0.12 
0.29 
-0.36 
-0.30 </p>

<p>incidence of 
salmonellosis -new cases 
per 100 000 persons </p>

<p>0.37 
0.22 
-0.19 
-0.31 
0.15 
0.27 
-0.03 
-0.20 
0.43 </p>

<p>Death rate due to chronic 
diseases -per 100 000 
persons </p>

<p>0.00 
0.48 
0.55 
-0.12 
na 
na 
-0.02 
-0.03 
-0.44 </p>

<p>Total greenhouse gas 
emissions -index base 
year = 100 </p>

<p>0.82 
0.35 
0.69 
-0.84 
-0.53 
-0.38 
-0.53 
0.01 
-0.12 </p>

<p>Renewables in 
gross inland energy 
consumption -% </p>

<p>-0.69 
-0.05 
-0.11 
0.62 
-0.52 
0.12 
0.07 
0.55 
-0.40 </p>

<p>Energy dependency -% 
-0.10 
-0.21 
-0.06 
-0.10 
-0.43 
na 
0.40 
0.27 
0.00 </p>

<p>implicit tax rate on 
energy -Ratio of energy 
tax revenues to final 
energy consumption, 
deflated </p>

<p>-0.33 
0.10 
-0.21 
-0.23 
-0.22 
-0.07 
0.67 
-0.04 
0.02 </p>

<p>Electricity generated from 
renewable sources -% of 
gross energy consumption </p>

<p>-0.06 
0.09 
0.07 
0.62 
0.12 
0.08 
-0.09 
0.28 
0.08 </p>

<p>Energy consumption of 
transport, by mode -
1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.77 
0.44 
0.54 
-0.26 
-0.08 
-0.08 
-0.03 
0.71 
0.52 </p>

<p>Shares of environmental 
taxes in total tax 
revenues -% </p>

<p>-0.31 
0.14 
-0.28 
-0.45 
-0.29 
0.17 
-0.07 
-0.40 
-0.16 </p>

<p>Shares of labour taxes in 
total tax revenues -% </p>

<p>-0.71 
-0.82 
-0.55 
0.11 
-0.41 
-0.02 
-0.07 
-0.27 
0.01 </p>

<p>Continued next page </p>



<p>G. Lapinskienė, K. Peleckis. Impact of sustainable development indicators on economic growth… </p>

<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Growth rate of labour 
productivity per hour 
worked -% change over 
previous year </p>

<p>0.40 
0.29 
0.38 
0.91 
0.75 
0.24 
0.45 
0.35 
0.61 </p>

<p>Real effective exchange 
rate -index 1999 = 100 </p>

<p>0.07 
-0.05 
0.52 
-0.55 
0.00 
-0.80 
-0.71 
-0.88 
-0.75 </p>

<p>Employment rate, by 
gender -% </p>

<p>0.43 
0.70 
0.65 
0.25 
0.61 
0.71 
0.61 
0.31 
0.60 </p>

<p>Unemployment rate, by 
gender -% </p>

<p>-0.41 
-0.58 
-0.70 
-0.41 
-0.61 
-0.73 
-0.72 
-0.74 
-0.92 </p>

<p>Municipal waste 
generated -kg per capita </p>

<p>0.70 
0.06 
0.52 
0.41 
0.47 
0.43 
0.33 
0.43 
0.55 </p>

<p>Municipal waste 
treatment, by type of 
treatment method -kg per 
capita </p>

<p>0.90 
-0.01 
0.41 
-0.07 
0.08 
0.66 
0.42 
0.11 
-0.35 </p>

<p>Emissions of acidifying 
substances, by source 
sector -1 000 tonnes acid 
equivalents </p>

<p>0.45 
0.23 
0.48 
-0.58 
-0.28 
-0.42 
-0.01 
0.04 
-0.38 </p>

<p>Emissions of ozone 
precursors, by source 
sector -1 000 tonnes 
ozone-forming potential </p>

<p>0.62 
0.35 
0.59 
-0.71 
0.44 
-0.33 
0.33 
0.18 
-0.02 </p>

<p>Emissions of particulate 
matter by source sector -
1 000 tonnes particulate-
forming potential </p>

<p>0.58 
0.04 
0.51 
-0.47 
0.33 
-0.44 
0.09 
0.01 
-0.23 </p>

<p>Final energy consumption, 
by sector -1 000 toe </p>

<p>0.80 
0.62 
0.62 
-0.68 
-0.24 
-0.33 
-0.20 
0.17 
0.14 </p>

<p>Persons with low 
educational attainment, 
by age group -% </p>

<p>-0.06 
0.31 
0.20 
0.28 
-0.11 
0.18 
0.38 
0.27 
-0.18 </p>

<p>Employment rate of older 
workers -% </p>

<p>0.12 
0.56 
0.32 
0.14 
0.33 
0.03 
0.17 
-0.56 
-0.24 </p>

<p>Life expectancy at age 65, 
by gender -years </p>

<p>-0.25 
-0.10 
na 
0.31 
0.29 
0.15 
na 
0.16 
0.42 </p>

<p>Total fertility rate -
number -of children per 
woman </p>

<p>0.17 
-0.06 
-0.07 
0.03 
na 
0.44 
0.40 
0.58 
0.19 </p>

<p>General government 
debtGeneral government 
consolidated gross debt as 
a percentage of GDP </p>

<p>-0.83 
-0.50 
-0.56 
0.10 
-0.48 
-0.57 
-0.77 
-0.61 
-0.78 </p>

<p>Suicide death rate, by age 
group -Total -crude 
death rate per 100 000 
persons </p>

<p>-0.60 
-0.69 
0.19 
-0.02 
na 
na 
0.26 
0.33 
0.06 </p>

<p>Continued next page </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2009, 10(2): 107-117 </p>



<p>Lithuania Estonia Latvia Austria Belgium Denmark Nether. France Germany </p>

<p>Greenhouse gas 
emissions -index base 
year = 100 </p>

<p>0.82 
0.35 
0.69 
-0.84 
-0.53 
-0.38 
-0.53 
0.01 
-0.12 </p>

<p>Greenhouse gas emissions 
by sector -million tonnes 
Co² equivalent </p>

<p>0.84 
0.35 
0.68 
-0.84 
-0.54 
-0.38 
-0.54 
0.01 
-0.12 </p>

<p>Greenhouse gas emissions 
intensity of energy 
consumption -index 
2000 = 100 </p>

<p>0.19 
-0.03 
0.12 
-0.74 
-0.58 
-0.36 
-0.29 
-0.04 
-0.34 </p>

<p>Gross inland energy 
consumption, by fuel -
1 000 tonnes of oil 
equivalent </p>

<p>0.64 
0.26 
0.57 
-0.81 
0.06 
-0.39 
-0.49 
0.17 
0.10 </p>

<p>implicit tax rate on 
energy -Euros per tonne 
of oil equivalent </p>

<p>-0.33 
0.10 
-0.21 
-0.23 
-0.22 
-0.07 
0.67 
-0.04 
0.02 </p>

<p>Modal split of freight 
transport -% in total 
inland freight tonne-km </p>

<p>0.51 
-0.09 
-0.45 
0.21 
-0.17 
0.15 
0.16 
0.14 
0.10 </p>

<p>Volume of freight 
transport -index 
2000 = 100 </p>

<p>-0.36 
-0.53 
-0.13 
-0.07 
0.28 
-0.16 
0.03 
0.36 
0.28 </p>

<p>Greenhouse gas emissions 
from transport -1 000 
tonnes of Co 2 equivalent </p>

<p>0.77 
0.62 
0.50 
-0.21 
-0.06 
-0.25 
0.20 
0.20 
0.30 </p>

<p>People killed in road 
accidents -Number of 
killed people </p>

<p>0.61 
0.47 
-0.57 
-0.27 
0.18 
0.01 
0.03 
0.49 
0.05 </p>

<p>Emissions of ozone 
precursors from 
transport -1 000 tonnes 
of ozone-forming 
potential </p>

<p>0.60 
0.29 
-0.51 
-0.05 
-0.27 
-0.13 
0.32 
0.10 
0.60 </p>

<p>Emissions of particulate 
matter from transport -
1 000 tonnes </p>

<p>0.65 
0.60 
0.41 
-0.09 
0.58 
-0.31 
0.24 
0.10 
0.56 </p>

<p>Forest trees damaged by 
defoliation -% </p>

<p>0.76 
-0.04 
0.10 
-0.26 
-0.23 
-0.15 
-0.34 
-0.67 
-0.05 </p>

<p>Shares of environmental 
and labour taxes in total 
tax revenues -% </p>

<p>-0.31 
0.14 
-0.28 
-0.45 
-0.29 
0.17 
-0.07 
-0.40 
-0.16 </p>

<p>*na -data not available </p>

<p>Giedrė LAPINSKIENĖ. Master of Management and Business administration, Vilnius Gediminas Technical University. Research 
interests: sustainable development, indicators of sustainable development, economic growth. </p>

<p>Kęstutis PELECKIS. Associate Professor, Doctor of Social Sciences (Economics), Dept of Enterprise Economics and Management, 
Vilnius Gediminas Technical University. Author of more than 70 publications. Research interests: increase of efficiency of functioning 
and development of higher school potential. </p>

<p>End of Appendix </p>

</text></tei>