<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fjbem.2010.30" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. This paper proposes a fuzzy multi-period newsvendor model with pre-season 
extension for innovative products. The demand of the product is represented by fuzzy 
numbers with triangular membership function. The holding and shortage cost parameters 
are considered as imprecise and also represented by triangular fuzzy numbers. As the sell-
ing season draws closer, suppliers lead times shortens and thus production costs increase. 
In contrast, caused by the oncoming selling season, demand fuzziness decreases and more 
accurate demand forecasts can be maintained that lead to lower overage/underage costs. 
The objective of the model is to find the best order period and the best order quantity that 
will minimize the fuzzy expected total cost. The model is experimented with an illustra-
tive example and supported by sensitivity analyses. </p>

<p>In today's competitive market conditions, development of innovative products is ex-
tremely important for an enterprise to achieve and sustain the superiority. Innovative 
products are products that have shorter life cycles with higher innovation and fashion 
contents (Lee 2002). Fashion goods, electronic products and mass customized goods 
are examples of innovative products. Although innovative products tend to have higher 
product profit margins, the cost of obsolescence is high for them. These kinds of prod-
ucts have much product variety and short product life cycles. Caused by the innovative 
nature of the product, usually no historical data are available for forecasting demand 
of such products. In addition to the short life cycle and high demand unpredictability 
of these products, another important feature is the long supply lead times. Because of 
having such long supply lead times and short sales seasons, procurement problem of 
these products corresponds to the single-period inventory (also known as newsvendor 
or newsboy) problem. </p>



<p>The single-period inventory problem (SPP) deals with finding product's order quantity 
that minimizes the expected total cost or maximizes the expected total profit under linear 
purchasing, holding, and shortage costs and probabilistic demand. In SPP, product or-
ders are given before the selling period begins. There is no option for an additional order 
during the selling period or there will be a penalty cost for this re-order. The assumption 
of the SPP is that if any inventory remains at the end of the period, either a discount is 
used to sell it or it is disposed of (Nahmias 1996). If the order quantity is smaller than 
the realized demand, the seller misses some profit. An extensive literature review on 
a variety of extensions of the single-period inventory problem and related multi-stage, 
inventory control models can be found Khouja (1999) and Silver et al. (1998). Most 
of the extensions have been made in the probabilistic framework, in which the uncer-
tainty of demand is described by probability distributions. However, the methods based 
on the probability theory allow only quantitative uncertainties. For instance, Kopytov 
et al. (2006) developed a stochastic single-product inventory control model for the 
chain "producer -wholesaler -customer" for transport and industrial companies. The 
optimization criterion is the minimum of average expenses for goods holding, ordering 
and losses from deficit per a time unit. </p>

<p>In reality, most of the evaluations are imprecise, fuzzy and cannot be quantified. The 
fuzzy set theory, introduced by Zadeh (1965), is the best form that adapts all the un-
certainty set to the model. When subjective evaluations are considered, the possibility 
theory takes the place of the probability theory (Zadeh 1978). The fuzzy set theory can 
represent linguistic data which cannot be easily modeled by other methods (Dubois and 
Prade 1980). </p>

<p>In the literature, fuzzy modeling is used for single-period inventory problems by sev-
eral researchers. Ishii and Konno (1998) introduced a fuzzy newsboy model restricted 
to shortage cost that is given by an L-shape fuzzy number while the demand is still 
stochastic. Thus the total expected profit function also becomes a fuzzy number and an 
optimum order quantity is obtained in the sense of fuzzy max (min) order of the profit 
function. Petrovic et al. (1996) developed two fuzzy models to handle uncertainty in 
the SPP. In the first model, uncertain demand is represented by a discrete fuzzy set but 
the inventory costs thought as precise and in the second model inventory costs also 
described as triangular fuzzy numbers. In the paper the concept of level-2 fuzzy set 
and the method of arithmetic defuzzification are employed to access an optimum order 
quantity. Li et al. (2002) studied the single-period inventory problem in two differ-
ent cases to maximize the profit through ordering fuzzy numbers with respect to their 
total integral values. In order to minimize the fuzzy total cost, Kao and Hsu (2002) 
constructed a single-period inventory model. They adopted a method for ranking fuzzy 
numbers to find the optimum order quantity in terms of the cost. In their first study, 
Dutta et al. (2005) presented a SPP in an imprecise and uncertain mixed environment. 
They introduced demand as a fuzzy random variable and developed a new methodology 
to determine the optimum order quantity where the optimum is achieved using a graded </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>mean integration representation. In their second study, Dutta et al. (2007) proposed 
a single-period inventory model of profit maximization with a reordering strategy in 
an imprecise environment. They divided the entire ordering period into two slots and 
considered the customer demand as a fuzzy number in both slots. They represented a 
solution procedure using ordering of fuzzy numbers with respect to their possibilistic 
mean values. Ji and Shao (2006) extended SPP in bi-level context, where the decision 
of retailer (lower level) was considered separate from this of the "manufacturer" (upper 
level). In another study Shao and Ji (2006) extended SPP in multi-product case with 
fuzzy demands under budget constraint. In both studies they adopt credibility theory 
and used chance-constrained programming. They solved their models by a hybrid in-
telligent algorithm based on genetic algorithm and developed a fuzzy simulation. Lu 
(2008) studied a fuzzy newsvendor problem to analyze optimum order policy based on 
probabilistic fuzzy sets with hybrid data. They verified that the fuzzy newsvendor model 
is one extension of the crisp models. Xu and Zhai (2008) proposed a fuzzy model to 
find an optimal technique for dealing with the fuzziness aspect of demand uncertainties. 
They used a triangular fuzzy number to model the external demand, and they developer 
optimal decision models for both an independent retailer and an integrated supply chain. 
In their more recent study, Xu and Zhai (2010) considered a two-stage supply chain 
coordination problem and focused on the fuzziness aspect of demand uncertainty. They 
used fuzzy numbers to depict customer demand, and investigated the optimization of 
the vertically integrated two-stage supply chain under perfect coordination and contrast 
with the non-coordination case. </p>

<p>Most of the papers mentioned above proposed single-period inventory models with only 
fuzzy environment extensions. Through this paper, we combine two extensions to SPP 
which are; an extension to fuzzy environment and an extension to models with more 
than one period to prepare for the selling season. The idea behind the second extension 
is that there may be many periods to produce or purchase the items which will be sold 
in a single season. The question becomes when and what orders should be placed from 
the suppliers as the selling season draws closer. Related references about this extension 
can be found in Silver et al. (1998). However, these papers consider only the probabil-
istic demand cases. In this study, a multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season 
extension under fuzzy demand is analyzed. As the selling season draws closer, suppliers 
lead times shortens and the production cost increases. In contrast, demand fuzziness 
decreases and more accurate demand forecasts can be maintained that lead to lower 
overage/underage costs. The purpose of this study is to find the best order period and 
best order quantity for the single-period inventory problem with multi-period pre-season 
extension under fuzzy demand. </p>

<p>The remainder of the paper is organized as follows. The single-period inventory prob-
lem is subjected in Section 2. In Section 3, a fuzzy model with multi-period pre-season 
extension is described. A numerical illustration of the presented model is issued and 
sensitivity analyses over cost parameters are presented. Lastly the paper is concluded 
in Section 4. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>2. Single-period inventory problem </p>

<p>The objective of the stochastic single-period inventory problem is to determine the order 
quantity Q* for a fixed time period that will minimize the expected total cost. The total 
cost is the linear sum of purchase, overage, and underage costs. It is assumed that there 
is no initial inventory on hand. Demand is a random variable and represented by prob-
ability distributions. Items are purchased (or produced) for a single-period at the cost 
of c p . The holding cost which is the cost of storing excess products minus their salvage 
value is c h and the shortage cost which is the cost of lost sales due to the inability to 
supply the demand is c s . The total cost function will be as follows: </p>

<p>( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>, 
max 
, 0 
max 
, 0 , </p>

<p>p 
h 
s </p>

<p>TC Q X 
c Q c 
Q X 
c 
X Q 
= + 
− 
+ 
− 
(1) </p>

<p>where Q represents order quantity and X stands for the demand given by the domain </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>0 1 2 </p>

<p>, , ,..., n 
X 
x x x 
x 
= 
. If demand has a probability distribution function </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>X 
i </p>

<p>p x , than 
the total expected cost function will be: </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>( ) ( ) 
( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} ( ) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>, 
, 
= </p>

<p>max 
, 0 
max 
, 0 
, </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>= 
 
 
 
 
 
 
+ 
− 
+ 
− 
 
 </p>

<p>∑ 
∑ </p>

<p>n 
i 
i 
i 
n 
p 
h 
i 
s 
i 
i 
i </p>

<p>E TC Q X 
TC Q x p x </p>

<p>c Q 
c 
Q x 
c 
x Q 
p x 
(2) </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>0,1, 2,..., 
= 
i 
n </p>

<p>which is equal to: </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>( 
) ( ) 
( 
) ( ) </p>

<p>1 
0 </p>

<p>, 
. </p>

<p>Q 
n 
p 
h 
i 
i 
s i 
i 
i 
i Q </p>

<p>E TC Q X 
c Q 
c Q x p x 
c x Q p x </p>

<p>− 
= = </p>

<p> 
 
 
 
= + 
− 
+ 
− 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 </p>

<p>∑ 
∑ </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>Let </p>

<p>( 
) 
( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>, 
1, 
, 
. 
E TC Q X 
E TC Q 
X 
E TC Q X 
∆ 
= 
+ 
− 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
(4) </p>

<p>Then, </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>, 
E TC Q X 
∆  
 
 
 is the change in expected total cost when we switch from Q 
to Q + 1. For a convex cost function, the optimum Q will be the lowest Q where </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>, 
E TC Q X 
∆  
 
 
 is greater than zero. Therefore, we select the smallest Q for which, </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>, 
0. 
E TC Q X 
∆ 
≥ 
 
 
 
 
(5) </p>

<p>The equation above holds if </p>

<p>( 
) 
( 
) </p>

<p>1, 
, 
0. 
E TC Q 
X 
E TC Q X 
+ 
− 
≥ 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
(6) </p>

<p>Substituting Equation 3 into Equation 6 leads to: </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>( 
) ( ) 
( 
) ( ) </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>( 
) ( ) 
( 
) ( ) 
( ) 
( ) </p>

<p>0 
1 
1 
0 </p>

<p>0 
1 </p>

<p>1 
1 
1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0. </p>

<p>Q 
n 
p 
h 
i 
i 
s i 
i 
i 
i Q 
Q 
n 
p 
h 
i 
i 
s i 
i 
i 
i Q 
Q 
n 
p 
h 
i 
s 
i 
i 
i Q </p>

<p>c Q 
c Q 
x p x 
c x Q 
p x </p>

<p>c Q 
c Q x p x 
c x Q p x </p>

<p>c 
c p x 
c p x </p>

<p>= 
= + 
− 
= = </p>

<p>= 
= + </p>

<p> 
 
 
 
+ + 
+ − 
+ 
− − 
− 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
+ 
− 
+ 
− 
≥ 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
 
+ 
− 
≥ 
 
 
 
 </p>

<p>∑ 
∑ 
∑ 
∑ 
∑ 
∑ </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>While </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1, </p>

<p>n 
X 
i 
i </p>

<p>p x </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>∑ </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>( ) </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>s 
p 
X 
h 
s </p>

<p>c c 
p 
Q 
c c </p>

<p>≤ </p>

<p>− 
≥ 
+ 
(8) </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>p 
Q </p>

<p>≤ </p>

<p>is the probability that the demand X is smaller or equal to the order 
quantity Q. The expected total cost, </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>, 
E TC Q X 
 
 
 </p>

<p> will be minimized by the smallest 
value of Q(call it Q*) satisfying the equation above (Equation 8). </p>

<p>3. Fuzzy model with multi-period pre-season extension </p>

<p>The fuzzy set theory provides a proper framework for description of uncertainty related 
to vagueness of natural language expressions and judgments. Fuzzy sets have been 
introduced by Zadeh (1965) as an extension of the classical notion of set. In classical 
set theory, the membership of elements in a set is assessed in binary terms according 
to a bivalent condition where an element either belongs or does not belong to the set. 
By contrast, fuzzy set theory permits the gradual assessment of the membership of ele-
ments in a set; this is described with the aid of a membership function valued in the 
real unit interval [0, 1]. </p>

<p>Let U be a classical set of objects, called the universe, whose generic elements are de-
noted by x. Membership in a classical subset X of U is often viewed as a characteristic 
function, μ X from U to such that: </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>1 iff 
( ) 
. 
0 iff </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x X 
x 
x X </p>

<p>∈ 
µ 
= 
∉ 
(9) </p>

<p>If the valuation set ({0,1}) is allowed to be the real interval [0,1],  X is called a fuzzy 
set (Zadeh 1965), 
 ( ) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
is the grade of membership of x in  X . The closer the value 
of 
 ( ) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
is to, the more x belongs to  X .  X is completely characterized by the set of 
pairs: </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
{( , ( )), 
}. </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X 
x 
x x X 
= µ 
∈ 
(10) </p>

<p>Fuzzy numbers are a particular kind of fuzzy sets. A fuzzy number is a fuzzy set R 
of real numbers set with a continuous, compactly supported, and convex membership 
function. </p>

<p>Let U be a universal set; a fuzzy subset  X of U is defined by a function </p>

<p> </p>

<p>[ ] </p>

<p>( ) : 
0,1 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x U 
µ 
→ 
is called membership function. Here, U is assumed to be the set of real numbers R and 
Fis the space of fuzzy sets. </p>

<p>The fuzzy set  X F 
∈ is a fuzzy number iff: </p>

<p>I. For </p>

<p>[ ] </p>

<p>0,1 
∀α ∈ 
, the set </p>

<p> </p>

<p>{ 
: 
( ) 
} </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X 
x R 
x 
α = 
∈ µ 
≥ α , which is called α cut of  X is a 
convex set. 
II. 
 ( ) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
is a continuous function. </p>

<p>III. 
 </p>

<p> </p>

<p>sup( ) { 
: 
( ) 0} </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X 
x R 
x 
= ∈ µ 
≥ 
is a bounded set in R. </p>

<p>IV. 
 </p>

<p> </p>

<p>( ) max 
( ) 
0 </p>

<p>x U X </p>

<p>height X 
x h </p>

<p>∈ </p>

<p>= 
µ 
= ≥ . </p>

<p>By conditions (I) and (II), each α-cut is a compact and convex subset of R hence it is a closed 
interval in R, 
( ), 
( ) </p>

<p>L 
R </p>

<p>X 
X 
X 
α = 
α 
α 
 
 
 
 . If h = 1 we say that the fuzzy number is normal. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>Let us show a fuzzy number  ( , , , ) </p>

<p>l m n u </p>

<p>X 
x x x x 
= 
where l </p>

<p>m 
n 
u </p>

<p>x x 
x 
x 
&lt; 
&lt; &lt; 
in this form. 
The fuzzy number  X is a so-called triangular fuzzy number  ( , 
, ) </p>

<p>l m 
n u </p>

<p>X 
x x 
x x 
= = 
, </p>

<p>l 
m 
n 
u </p>

<p>x x 
x 
x 
&lt; 
= &lt; 
if its membership function </p>

<p> </p>

<p>[ ] </p>

<p>( ) : 
0,1 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x R 
µ 
→ 
is equal to (Fig. 1): </p>

<p> </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>( ) 
. </p>

<p>0 
x&gt;x </p>

<p>l </p>

<p>l 
l 
m 
m 
l 
X 
u 
m 
u 
u 
m </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>x x </p>

<p>x x 
x x x 
x 
x 
x 
x x 
x x x 
x x </p>

<p>&lt; 
 
 
− 
 
 
 
&lt; &lt; 
 
 
 
− 
  
 
µ 
=  
− 
 
 
 
&lt; &lt; 
 
 
 
− 
 
 
 
  </p>

<p>(11) </p>

<p>The fuzzy function  X is a function of parameters , 
and </p>

<p>l m 
u </p>

<p>x x 
x , known as the lower 
value, middle value and upper value respectively. The figure (Fig. 1) shows the member-
ship function for a fuzzy number "approximately x m ". </p>

<p>In this study, a multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy 
demand is analyzed. As the selling season draws closer, suppliers lead times shortens 
and the production cost increases. In contrast, demand fuzziness decreases and more 
accurate demand forecasts can be maintained that lead to lower overage/underage costs. </p>

<p>The purpose of the model is to find the best order period (M*) and best order quantity 
(Q*)for the multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under discrete 
fuzzy demand  X with membership function 
 ( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
, precise production cost c p , fuzzy 
unit holding cost  </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c with </p>

<p> </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>µ and fuzzy unit shortage  </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c cost with </p>

<p> </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>µ . </p>

<p>3.1. Fuzzy demand and fuzzy inventory costs with precise purchasing cost </p>

<p>Let the membership function 
 ( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
of fuzzy demand  X given by domain </p>

<p> </p>

<p>0 1 2 </p>

<p>{ , , ,..., } </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>X 
x x x 
x 
= 
have the triangular membership function (Fig. 1). Unit produc-
tion cost, (c p ) is precise while unit holding cost  
( ) </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c and unit shortage cost  
( ) </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c , are 
represented by triangular fuzzy numbers. The uncertain demand and uncertain cost </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Triangular membership function </p>

<p>x l 
x m 
x u 
x </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>0°m </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>parameters cause uncertain overage and underage costs. For a given Q and 
 </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x X 
∈ , the 
fuzzy overage  
( ) 
OC and underage costs  
( ) 
UC , are as follows; </p>

<p>  
 </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>  
 </p>

<p>( 
) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>max 
, 0 </p>

<p>max 
, 0 . </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>OC c 
Q X </p>

<p>UC c 
X Q </p>

<p>= 
− </p>

<p>= 
− </p>

<p>(12) </p>

<p>The unit penalty cost  
( ) 
PC is the sum of unit overage cost and unit underage cost with 
the membership function </p>

<p> 
PC </p>

<p>µ . </p>

<p>   . 
PC OC UC 
= 
+ 
(13) </p>

<p>The unit penalty cost  
( ) 
PC ) is a level-2 fuzzy set which means that it includes two 
fuzzy values and there are corresponding membership degrees of these fuzzy values. </p>

<p>A level-2 fuzzy set can be reduced to an ordinary fuzzy set by s-fuzzification process 
(Zadeh 1971). The membership function of an ordinary fuzzy set is maintained via s-
fuzzification ("s" stands for support) as follows: </p>

<p> 
 </p>

<p> </p>

<p>0,1,2,..., 
( ) </p>

<p>( ) sup 
[ 
( ) 
( )], 
, </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i 
n 
c 
s fuzz PC 
PC </p>

<p>x 
i 
x x X </p>

<p>= 
− </p>

<p>µ = 
µ 
× µ 
∈ 
(14) </p>

<p>where c i (x) is the i th possible fuzzy cost of  
PC and 
 ( ) </p>

<p>PC </p>

<p>i 
µ 
is the possibility of that 
cost.According to the properties of possibility measure (Zadeh 1978), 
 ( ) </p>

<p>PC </p>

<p>i 
µ 
is ob-
tained as follows: </p>

<p> 
  </p>

<p>( ) max 
( ), 
0,1, 2,..., . </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i 
x X X 
PC </p>

<p>i 
x 
i 
n </p>

<p>∈ </p>

<p>µ = 
µ 
= 
(15) </p>

<p>The fuzzy total cost is minimized by the best order quantity (Q*): </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>( , ) min 
( 
( )) . </p>

<p>Q 
p </p>

<p>TC Q X 
c Q defuzz s fuzz PC 
 
 
= 
+ 
− 
 
 
(16) </p>

<p>Here, the operator "defuzz" denotes the defuzzification process. Defuzzification is the 
conversion of a fuzzy quantity to a precise quantity; in contrast fuzzification is the 
conversion of a precise quantity to a fuzzy quantity. Usually, a fuzzy system will have 
a number of rules that transform a number of variables into a "fuzzy" result. Defuzzifi-
cation would transform this result into a single number (Ross 1995). There are several 
methods for defuzzification. In this study centroid defuzzification method is applied. 
Centroid defuzzification method (also called center of area, center of gravity) is the 
most common of all the defuzzification methods. It is given by the algebraic expression 
as follows. 
For continuous functions: </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>( ) 
* </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>C z </p>

<p>C z </p>

<p>zdz 
z 
dz </p>

<p>µ 
= 
µ </p>

<p>∫ 
∫ </p>

<p>(17) </p>

<p>For discrete functions: </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>( ) 
* </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>, </p>

<p>C z </p>

<p>C z </p>

<p>z 
z </p>

<p>µ 
= 
µ </p>

<p>∑ 
∑ </p>

<p>(18) </p>

<p>where  </p>

<p> </p>

<p>( ) 
1 
z 
z 
i 
i </p>

<p>C 
C </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>= 
 
and  i 
C is one of the membership functions those figure the fuzzy 
output. This method is represented in Fig. 2. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>Best order quantity (Q*) which minimiz-
es the fuzzy total cost is found by brute-
force search algorithm which is a very 
general problem-solving technique that 
consists of systematically enumerating all 
possible candidates for the solution and 
checking whether each candidate satisfies 
the problem's statement. </p>

<p>The procedure explained above is exam-
ined for every pre-season ordering period. 
Through these periods as the selling sea-
son draws closer the production cost increases and demand fuzziness decreases and 
more accurate demand forecasts can be maintained that lead to lower overage/underage 
costs. </p>

<p>In the multi-period model, </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>c denotes unit production cost for period j. Demand fuzzi-
ness decreases as the ordering period closes to the selling season. This decrease of 
fuzziness is maintained by fuzzy concentration of the membership function of demand 
according to the periods. The membership function 
 ( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
of fuzzy demand  X is 
given by domain  </p>

<p>0 1 2 </p>

<p>{ , , ,..., } </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>X 
x x x 
x 
= 
concentrates as the selling season draws closer. </p>

<p>Concentrations tend to concentrate the element of a fuzzy set by reducing the degree of 
membership of all elements that have lower membership degrees in the set. The less an 
element is in a set, the more it is reduced in membership through concentration (Ross 
1995). </p>

<p>The membership function of fuzzy demand for period j is denoted by 
 ( ) </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
. Fuzzy 
total cost for pre-season ordering periods is as follows: </p>

<p> 
 
 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>( , ) min [ 
( 
( 
))]. </p>

<p>j 
j </p>

<p>j 
j 
j 
Q 
p 
j </p>

<p>TC Q X 
c Q defuzz s fuzz PC 
= 
+ 
− 
(19) </p>

<p>Here  j 
PC represents the penalty cost for period j where j=1,2,...,m. The best order 
period </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>( ) 
M is the period which has the minimum fuzzy total cost. </p>

<p>3.2. Numerical illustration </p>

<p>Suppose that a retailer wants to introduce an innovative product to the market at the 
beginning of July and have six possible periods (January, February, March, April, May, 
June) to give the manufacturing order to the manufacturer. As the selling season draws 
closer, suppliers lead times shorten and the production cost increases. On the other hand 
demand fuzziness decreases and more accurate demand forecasts can be maintained that 
lead to lower overage/underage costs. </p>

<p>Let unit holding cost  
( ) </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c and unit shortage cost  
( ) </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c be imprecise and represented 
with triangular fuzzy numbers as,  </p>

<p>[ 
] </p>

<p>$ 1, 2,3 </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c = 
and  </p>

<p>[ 
] </p>

<p>$ 4,5, 6 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c = 
, respectively. Unit 
purchasing cost is precise and increases 5% according to the previous months' cost 
Table 1. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Centroid defuzzification method </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>z* 
z </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>Table 1. Unit purchasing cost per month ($) </p>

<p>Jan 
Feb 
March 
April 
May </p>

<p>June </p>

<p>3.50 
3.68 
3.86 
4.05 
4.25 </p>

<p>4.47 </p>

<p>Let the membership function 
 ( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
of fuzzy demand  X for January be </p>

<p> {1000,1500, 2000, 2500,3000,3500, 4000, 4500,5000,5500, 6000} 
X = 
with the triangu-
lar membership function as follows: </p>

<p> </p>

<p>0 
1000 </p>

<p>1000 
1000 
3500 
2500 
( ) 
. 
6000 
3500 
6000 
2500 </p>

<p>0 
x &gt;6000 </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>i 
i </p>

<p>i 
X 
i 
i </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>x 
x 
x 
x 
x </p>

<p>&lt; 
 
 
− 
 
 
 
&lt; &lt; 
 
 
 
  
 
µ 
=  
− 
 
 
 
&lt; &lt; 
 
 
  
 
 
  </p>

<p>(20) </p>

<p>For example let x 1 = 1000. The membership value of x 1 will be </p>

<p> 1 </p>

<p>( ) 0 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
= or if x 7 = 
1000 then the membership value of x 7 will be </p>

<p> 7 </p>

<p>( ) 0.80 </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>x 
µ 
= and so on. The member-
ship functions for other months are maintained through the membership function of the 
demand for January using fuzzy concentration (Table 2 and Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Table 2. Membership values of demand per month </p>

<p>Jan 
Feb 
March 
April 
May 
June </p>

<p>Demand 
 ( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>1.25 </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p> </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x 
µ </p>

<p>1000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>1500 
0.200 
0.134 
0.089 
0.040 
0.008 
0.002 </p>

<p>2000 
0.400 
0.318 
0.253 
0.160 
0.064 
0.026 </p>

<p>2500 
0.600 
0.528 
0.465 
0.360 
0.216 
0.130 </p>

<p>3000 
0.800 
0.757 
0.716 
0.640 
0.512 
0.410 </p>

<p>3500 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 
1.000 </p>

<p>4000 
0.800 
0.757 
0.716 
0.640 
0.512 
0.410 </p>

<p>4500 
0.600 
0.528 
0.465 
0.360 
0.216 
0.130 </p>

<p>5000 
0.400 
0.318 
0.253 
0.160 
0.064 
0.026 </p>

<p>5500 
0.200 
0.134 
0.089 
0.040 
0.008 
0.002 </p>

<p>6000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 
0.000 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>For example, let us order a quantity of 2000 units at the beginning of January. The unit pen-
alty cost  
( ) 
PC is a level-2 fuzzy set including imprecise demand and costs. For x 1 = 1000, 
the fuzzy penalty cost will be  (1, 2,3) 1000 (1000, 2000,3000) 
PC = 
× 
= 
with possibility of 
0. For x 5 = 3000, the fuzzy penalty cost will be  (4,5, 6) 1000 (4000,5000, 6000) 
PC = 
× 
= 
with the possibility 0.80 and so on. For the ordering period January fuzzy unit penalty 
cost values for Q = 2000 is given in Table 3. </p>

<p>The graphical representations of level-2 fuzzy sets of  
( ) 
PC for January when Q = 
2000 and the corresponding s-fuzzified set 
 
( ) 
s fuzz PC 
− 
are shown in Figs. 4a and 
4b, respectively. </p>

<p>Table 3. Unit penalty cost values for January, Q = 2000 </p>

<p> X 
 ( ) 
x i 
X 
µ 
 
( ) 
OC 
 
( ) 
UC 
 
( ) 
PC </p>

<p>x 1 
1000 
0 
(1000,2000,3000) (0,0,0) 
(1000,2000,3000) </p>

<p>x 2 
1500 
0.20 
(500,1000,1500) 
(0,0,0) 
(500,1000,1500) </p>

<p>x 3 
2000 
0.40 
(0,0,0) 
(0,0,0) 
(0,0,0) </p>

<p>x 4 
2500 
0.60 
(0,0,0) 
(2000,2500,3000) 
(2000,2500,3000) </p>

<p>x 5 
3000 
0.80 
(0,0,0) 
(4000,5000,6000) 
(4000,5000,6000) </p>

<p>x 6 
3500 
1 
(0,0,0) 
(6000,7500,9000) 
(6000,7500,9000) </p>

<p>x 7 
4000 
0.80 
(0,0,0) 
(8000,10000,12000) (8000,10000,12000) </p>

<p>x 8 
4500 
0.60 
(0,0,0) 
(10000,12500,15000) (10000,12500,15000) </p>

<p>x 9 
5000 
0.40 
(0,0,0) 
(12000,15000,18000) (12000,15000,18000) </p>

<p>x 10 
5500 
0.20 
(0,0,0) 
(14000,17500,21000) (14000,17500,21000) </p>

<p>x 11 
6000 
0 
(0,0,0) 
(16000,20000,24000) (16000,20000,24000) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Fuzzy concentration of  X°m </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>i 
X </p>

<p>x </p>

<p>1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 </p>

<p>January </p>

<p>February </p>

<p>March </p>

<p>April </p>

<p>May </p>

<p>June </p>

<p>1.000 </p>

<p>0.900 </p>

<p>0.800 </p>

<p>0.700 </p>

<p>0.600 </p>

<p>0.500 </p>

<p>0.400 </p>

<p>0.300 </p>

<p>0.200 </p>

<p>0.100 </p>

<p>0.000 </p>

<p>Fuzzy Concentration of°X </p>

<p>x i </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>According to the s-fuzzified value of the penalty cost, total cost for the given values 
when Q = 2000 is calculated as below: </p>

<p> 
 
 
(2000, ) [3.50 2000 
( 
( ))]. 
TC 
X 
defuzz s fuzz PC 
= 
× 
+ 
− 
(21) </p>

<p>Here, the operator "defuzz" denotes the centroid method for defuzzification. Centroid 
defuzzification values have been obtained by using <rs type="software">MATLAB R2008a Fuzzy Logic 
Toolbox</rs> as in Fig. 5. </p>

<p> 
 
(2000, ) [3.5 2000 10, 022] $17, 022 
TC 
X = × 
+ 
= 
. 
(22) </p>

<p>Fuzzy total cost values for all other order quantities of the ordering period January are 
given in Table 4. For the ordering period January, best order quantity which gives the 
min fuzzy total cost is found 3000 units with the fuzzy total cost value $16,820. </p>

<p>The procedure continues with calculation of other periods best order quantities. Using 
Equation 19, the fuzzy total costs for pre-season ordering periods are calculated and 
given as in Table 5 and Fig. 6. </p>

<p>As stated by Table 5, best order period (M*) is found January with fuzzy total cost 
$16,820 with 3000 units. Here the decrease of demand fuzziness causes a decline on 
the fuzzy total cost values among ordering periods. However, the change of production 
cost also affects the cost function. The proposed model offers best order period and 
corresponding order quantity for the given fuzzy variables. </p>

<p>Fig. 4a. Level-2 fuzzy set  
( ) 
PC </p>

<p>Fig. 4b. 
 
( ) 
s fuzz PC 
− </p>

<p>± </p>

<p>m ( ) </p>

<p>PC </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 
± * 
( $1000) 
PC </p>

<p>i = 1 2 4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
1 </p>

<p>0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 21 22 23 24 
± * 
( $1000) 
PC </p>

<p>0,2 </p>

<p>0,4 </p>

<p>0,6 </p>

<p>0,8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>Fig. 5. Centroid defuzzification of 
 
( ) 
s fuzz PC 
− </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
x10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Centroid </p>

<p>Table 4. Fuzzy total costs 
for January, ($) </p>

<p>Order quantity Fuzzy total cost </p>

<p>1000 
17,356 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>17,159 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>17,022 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>16,930 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>16,820* </p>

<p>3500 </p>

<p>16,828 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>17,258 
4500 
19,079 </p>

<p>5000 </p>

<p>21,514 </p>

<p>5500 </p>

<p>24,045 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>26,681 </p>

<p>Table 5. Fuzzy total cost for pre-season ordering periods,  </p>

<p>[ 
]  [ 
] </p>

<p>$ 
, 
$ 
1,2,3 
4,5,6 </p>

<p>h 
s </p>

<p>c 
c 
= = </p>

<p>Q 
 ( 
) 
TC Jan 
 ( 
) 
TC Feb 
 ( 
) 
TC March  ( 
) 
TC April 
 ( 
) 
TC May 
 ( 
) 
TC June </p>

<p>c p 
3,50 
3,68 
3,86 
4,05 
4,25 
4,47 </p>

<p>1000 
17,356 
17,335 
17,360 
17,327 
17,262 
17,332 </p>

<p>1500 
17,159 
17,161 
17,219 
17,184* 
17,098 
17,202 </p>

<p>2000 
17,022 
17,089 
17,210* 
17,202 
17,087* 
17,202* </p>

<p>2500 
16,930 
17,082 
17,282 
17,333 
17,223 
17,350 </p>

<p>3000 
16,820* 
17,075* 
17,375 
17,515 
17,448 
17,617 </p>

<p>3500 
16,828 
17,168 
17,553 
17,787 
17,815 
18,087 </p>

<p>4000 
17,258 
17,718 
18,237 
18,659 
19,003 
19,589 </p>

<p>4500 
19,079 
19,709 
20,401 
21,063 
21,708 
22,508 </p>

<p>5000 
21,514 
22,252 
23,059 
23,861 
24,678 
25,636 </p>

<p>5500 
24,045 
24,902 
25,831 
26,775 
27,756 
28,843 </p>

<p>6000 
26,681 
27,658 
28,703 
29,778 
30,880 
32,058 </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>3.3. Sensitivity analysis </p>

<p>In this section, various experiments have been performed to analyze the effect of mem-
bership function shapes to the fuzzy models. Through these experiments fuzzy unit 
holding cost and fuzzy unit shortage cost values have been changed (Table 6). </p>

<p>Table 6. Performed experiments and values of the cost parameters </p>

<p>Experiments 
 ($) </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c 
 ($) </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1 
(1,2,3) 
(4,5,6) </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(1,2,3) 
(4,5,8) </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>(1,2,3) 
(4,5,10) </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>(1,2,3) 
(4,5,12) </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>(1,2,5) 
(4,5,6) </p>

<p>6 
(1,2,5) 
(4,5,8) </p>

<p>7 
(1,2,5) 
(4,5,10) </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>(1,2,5) 
(4,5,12) </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>(1,2,7) 
(4,5,6) </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>(1,2,7) 
(4,5,8) </p>

<p>11 
(1,2,7) 
(4,5,10) </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>(1,2,7) 
(4,5,12) </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>(1,2,9) 
(4,5,6) </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>(1,2,9) 
(4,5,8) </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>(1,2,9) 
(4,5,10) </p>

<p>16 
(1,2,9) </p>

<p>(4,5,12) </p>

<p>Q </p>

<p>30 000 </p>

<p>25 000 </p>

<p>20 000 </p>

<p>15 000 </p>

<p>± 
TC </p>

<p>1000 1500 2000 2500 3000 3500 4000 4500 5000 5500 6000 </p>

<p>January </p>

<p>February </p>

<p>March </p>

<p>April </p>

<p>May </p>

<p>June </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Fuzzy total cost for pre-season ordering periods </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>



<p>In these experiments, production cost values and demand membership functions are 
considered the same as the previous illustration while the membership of holding cost 
and the membership of shortage cost have been changed. According to the provided 
membership values, the fuzzy model generates the results represented in Table 7. </p>

<p>Table 7. 
* 
M , * 
Q and  
TC for different  </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>c and  </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Experiments 
* 
M 
* 
Q 
 ($) 
TC </p>

<p>1 
Jan 
3000 
16,820 </p>

<p>2 
Jan 
2500 
17,716 </p>

<p>3 
May 
2500 
18,484 </p>

<p>4 
June 
3000 
19,152 </p>

<p>5 
Jan 
3000 
16,626 </p>

<p>6 
Jan 
3000 
17,619 </p>

<p>7 
May 
2500 
18,457 </p>

<p>8 
May 
3000 
19,093 </p>

<p>9 
Jan 
3000 
16,509 </p>

<p>10 
Jan 
3000 
17,545 </p>

<p>11 
May 
3000 
18,431 </p>

<p>12 
May 
3000 
19,062 </p>

<p>13 
Jan 
3000 
16,449 </p>

<p>14 
Jan 
3000 
17,498 </p>

<p>15 
May 
3000 
18,417 </p>

<p>16 
May 
3000 
19,048 </p>

<p>The results provided in Table 7 represents that, the increase of the fuzziness of cost 
parameters causes an increase of fuzzy total cost values. For example, in experiment 
2, we increased the fuzziness of shortage cost by changing the membership function 
shape to  </p>

<p>[ 
] </p>

<p>$ 4,5,8 </p>

<p>s </p>

<p>c = 
. This change increased the fuzzy total cost value from $16,820 
to $17,716. Shortage cost values as they have higher fuzziness affect the order period 
in that way. In experiments 3 and 4 membership values of shortage costs are wider than 
the values in experiments 1 and 2. For the experiments 1 and 2 best order period is 
found as January which has the maximum demand fuzziness and minimum production 
cost. However, for experiments 3 and 4 best order period changes to May and June, 
respectively, which have minimum demand fuzziness and maximum production costs. </p>

<p>Best order quantities for the experiments do not change much according to different sce-
narios. The reason of this situation is the symmetrical shape of demands' membership 
function. Only in three experiments best order quantity decreases from 3000 to 2500. 
If nonsymmetrical membership functions are used for demand data, more changes on 
offered order quantities can be observed. </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>4. Conclusion </p>

<p>The classical single-period inventory problem has been considered extensively in the 
relevant literature. Through these studies, most of the extensions have been made in the 
probabilistic and possibilistic framework. Most of the papers under possibilistic frame-
work proposed single-period inventory models with only fuzzy environment extensions. 
Through this paper, we combine two extensions to single-period inventory problem 
which are; an extension to fuzzy environment and an extension to models with more 
than one period to prepare for the selling season. The model is developed for innovative 
products. The demand, holding and shortage cost parameters are represented by fuzzy 
numbers. The model has been experimented with an illustrative example and supported 
by sensitivity analyses. </p>

<p>Contrary to the crisp model, fuzzy model proposes highly flexible solutions for all pos-
sible states. When the solutions of the model are analyzed, it is seen that the decrease of 
demand fuzziness causes a decline on the fuzzy total cost values among ordering peri-
ods. The fuzzy model offers the best order period and corresponding order quantity for 
the given fuzzy variables. Furthermore, the increase of the fuzziness of cost parameters 
causes an increase in fuzzy total cost values. Shortage cost values as they have higher 
fuzziness affect the order period in that way. Best order quantities for the experiments 
do not change much according to different scenarios. The reason of this situation is the 
symmetrical shape of demands' membership function. </p>

<p>For further research, we suggest the examination of the influence of nonsymmetrical and 
different type of membership functions for demand data on order quantities. Further-
more, the use of an imprecise continuous demand function instead of the discrete case 
of this paper can be examined. This will require optimization techniques for solution 
procedure. Lastly, dependent demand structure among ordering periods is suggested to 
be applied. </p>



<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>





<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman. A multi-period newsvendor problem with pre-season extension under fuzzy demand </p>



<p>KELIŲ LAIKOTARPIŲ PARDAVIMŲ MODELIS, PAPILDYTAS PARUOŠIAMUOJU 
LAIKOTARPIU, ESANT NERAIŠKIAJAI PAKLAUSAI </p>

<p>H. Behret, C. Kahraman </p>

<p>Santrauka </p>

<p>Straipsnyje pasiūlytas neraiškusis kelių laikotarpių pardavimo modelis, papildytas paruošiamuoju lai-
kotarpiu inovatyviems produktams. Produkto paklausa apibūdinama neraiškiaisiais skaičiais, aprašytais 
trikampe priklausomumo funkcija. Turto ir sąnaudų parametrai laikomi netiksliais ir taip pat apibūdi-
nami trikampe priklausomumo funkcija aprašytais neraiškiaisiais skaičiais. Kai pardavimo laikotarpis 
priartėja, tiekimo laikas trumpėja, o gaminio kaina išauga. Priešingai, dėl praeinančio pardavimo laiko-
tarpio paklausos neapibrėžtumas sumažėja ir galima tiksliau prognozuoti paklausą, o tai padeda suma-
žinti išlaidas dėl gaminių pertekliaus ar trūkumo. Šio modelio tikslas -rasti geriausią užsakymo laiką ir 
geriausią užsakymo kiekį, kurie padėtų sumažinti visų numatomų sąnaudų neapibrėžtumą. Pateikiamas 
modelio taikymo pavyzdys ir modelio jautrumo analizė. </p>

<p>Reikšminiai žodžiai: atsargų problema, neraiškusis modeliavimas, pardavimas, inovatyvus produktas, 
neraiškioji paklausa, neraiškioji atsargų savikaina, paruošiamasis laikotarpis. </p>

<p>Hülya BEHRET. M. Sc., a research assistant at Istanbul Technical University, Industrial Engineering 
Department and working on her PhD dissertation on "Fuzzy Single-Period Inventory Models in Pro-
duction Systems" under the supervision of Prof. Cengiz Kahraman. Her research areas are Production 
and Inventory Systems, Fuzzy Modeling, and Simulation. </p>

<p>Cengiz KAHRAMAN. A professor of industrial engineering at Istanbul Technical University, Indus-
trial Engineering Department. He has published about 100 international journal papers and 50 interna-
tional book chapters on fuzzy applications of industrial engineering. His research areas are engineering 
economics, quality control and management, statistical decision making, and production engineering. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(4): 613-629 </p>

</text></tei>