<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2007.31" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Construction contract is one of the steps of the construction process. In order to conclude acceptable and thought-
out construction contracts, effective methodologies for their evaluation and comparison must be developed. In order to solve 
various legal problems, electronic legal decision support systems have been developed in the world. Application of the 
electronic legal decision support systems can help to navigate in the legal system easier, makes additional reading of legal 
acts redundant, creates opportunities to analyse decision variants and to select the most favourable one, provides users with 
the newest and most extensive information, enables quick search and can use classification and information transfer features. 
In order to conclude acceptable and well-thought construction contraction agreements, effective methodologies for their 
evaluation and comparison must be developed. In order to prepare such methodologies, it is necessary to analyse not only 
technical, organisational and economic aspects in construction but also legal aspects of a construction contraction agree-
ment. Management of construction works includes conclusion of contracts between the client and the contractor. Contract 
making has great influence on economic success of both parties, on their behaviour in order to increase their profit and it can 
protect against possible loss. 
This article analyses construction contraction agreements by providing a model of construction contraction agreement provi-
sions based on their functions. Construction contraction agreements should be concluded, evaluated and compared on the 
basis of this model. Values of indicators are determined and a multiple criteria decision support system is developed on the 
basis of this model. </p>

<p>Construction is a complex multi-stage process, and the 
stages must be appropriately aligned and managed. The 
client that commissioned construction works must make 
various multi-purpose decisions at various stages of con-
struction. 
Most problems encountered during construction depend 
upon the selected contractor. Therefore, selection of a con-
tractor is a very important stage while implementing an 
investment project. Patrick Sik-Wah Fong and Sonia Kit-
Yung Choi [1] have analysed methods of contractors' se-
lection and noted that some methods are non-exhaustive 
and tend to be biased: there is a lack of opportunities to 
evaluate abilities of a contractor and meet time, price, qual-
ity and security requirements at the same time. These au-
thors have analysed possibilities to apply the Analytical Hi-</p>

<p>erarchy Process (AHP) Method for contractor's selection 
according to different criteria. 
Management of construction works includes conclusion 
of contracts between the client and the contractor. Contract 
making has great influence on economic success of both 
parties, on their behavior in order to increase their profit 
and protect against possible loss. 
Lord Diplock [2] has defined a construction contrac-
tion agreement (CCA) as: an agreement of sale of goods 
and work for a certain price, according to which payment 
is executed in parts after goods are delivered and works 
performed. Periodically, important decisions must be made 
related to matters such as correction of orders, size of inter-
mediate expenditures, time inputs for the work related to 
the project. CCA conclusion and implementation differs 
from other manufacturing processes. An important fact, </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>

<p>
which must be thought over before concluding a CCA, is 
that construction of a building differs from industrial prod-
ucts made in a factory. The project scope, the conditions of 
the place, use of many construction materials and work 
variety are the reasons why it is impossible to achieve the 
same level of perfection as in a factory. It must be a new 
unique building, in which each bolt and brush stroke must 
be exact and in place. No special rules are applicable to 
such contracts, whether they are construction contraction 
or designing agreements. Lord Reid [2] has noted that when 
parties want to make detailed CCAs, it is impossible to ap-
ply any main rules or principles embracing contractual re-
lationships between such parties, except for those which 
are used in general cases. 
Scientific literature increasingly pays attention to analy-
sis of construction contraction agreements. Bushait and 
Almohawis [3] have distinguished 11 good-quality features 
(such as clarity, composition, quality, etc.), which help to 
achieve quality in wording of an agreement but do not de-
termine which most important aspects must be discussed 
in the agreement.. Hinze and Tada [4] have analysed gen-
eral provisions of agreements used in 52 US facility com-
panies by paying attention to legal aspects. They determined 
that owners should thoroughly evaluate the aim of each 
province by general agreement provisions. Marsh, Kerzner 
and Hedley [5, 6] have been trying to determine what as-
pects an agreement should include. Kerzner offers a list 
starting at "the type of services" and ending with "the 
completion time", Marsh describes standard agreement pro-
visions (including bad work quality, inspections, insurance, 
safety, taxes, payment schedule, arbitration and non-
fulfilment). 
Construction contracts by various aspects were analysed 
by R. M. Skitmore. His research work is described in dif-
ferent publications. R.M. Skitmore and Z. Hatush [7] 
analysed contractor selection using multicriteria utility 
theory, S. T. Ng and R. M. Skitmore [8] described client and 
consultant perspectives by prequalification criteria, 
D. Drew, R. M. Skitmore and Hing Po Lo [9] offered a bid-
ding strategy model for use by contractors as part of a more 
informed approach in selecting which contracts to bid for, 
S. T. Ng, Kam Pong Cheng and R. M. Skitmore [10] exam-
ined the importance of Safety Performance Evaluation 
through a questionnaire survey conducted in Hong Kong 
and developed a Safety Performance Evaluation framework, 
suitable for use in the construction industry, and protocols 
for evaluating the safety performance at the organizational 
and project level. 
The construction industry is among the most important 
in each country's economy. The fact is witnessed by exten-
sive attention of various authors paid to an increase in ef-
fectiveness of construction contraction agreement making. 
However, such an important issue as integrated evaluation 
of construction contraction agreements remains untouched </p>

<p>or almost untouched. Even when the construction contrac-
tor is selected and the price and work terms are negotiated, 
the client still can choose at least several variants of agree-
ments. Selection of the most favourable variant is a mul-
tiple criteria task, and a new methodology must be created 
for its solution. 
In order to develop the methodology for multiple crite-
ria evaluation of CCAs, a systematic analysis of provisions 
for a CCA and of the model of CCA provisions is a must. 
This article aims to develop a hierarchical model of CCA 
provisions and to analyse provisions and subsystems in-
cluded in this model. Construction contracts can be con-
cluded, evaluated and compared on the basis of this model. </p>

<p>2. Model of the System of CCA Provisions </p>

<p>Decision-making is a very important stage in the con-
struction process as in life of every person; it determines 
the future of the person or of construction works. For ex-
ample, when preparing a construction contraction agree-
ment, hundreds of decisions must be made: the larger the 
project, the bigger the number of various level decisions. 
Those who prepare a construction contraction agreement 
must be knowledgeable about provisions of laws, the re-
quirements of parties, possible variants of risk transfer, etc. 
Conclusion of a CCA is one of the components of the 
construction process. In order to conclude a proper CCA, it 
is necessary to analyse agreement provisions properly and 
to consider their characteristics. It is very important to prop-
erly evaluate CCA provisions, such as contractor's liabili-
ties, provided guarantees, client's liabilities, provisions for 
contract termination and suspension, etc. This stage is re-
lated to certain decision-making. 
One of the most important contract elements is the con-
tents of the agreement, which consists of the entire system 
of agreement provisions. Contract provisions are determined 
on the basis of one of the main principles of the civil law: 
the principle of contract freedom. Contract provisions de-
termine rights and duties of the parties, i.e. their certain 
behaviour. In practice, it is important to formulate exact 
agreement provisions, because they determine peculiarities 
of rights and duties related to liabilities and their proper 
implementation. 
The system of CCA provisions may be also modelled 
considering the functions of agreement provisions. All CCA 
provisions have a certain function. For example, agreement 
provisions regulating guarantees, surety or forfeit have the 
function of liability guarantee. All provisions regulating the 
aforementioned function may be joined to a separate sub-
system. Similarly, other agreement provisions may also be 
joined to subsystems. Following the aforementioned prin-
ciple, a hierarchical model of CCA provisions based on their 
functions has been made and provided in Fig. 1. While con-
sidering functions of agreement provisions they are joined 
to groups or, in other words, to subsystems. In their turn </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>



<p>subsystems according to their functions are grouped into 
systems of higher level. At the end of the process, the high-
est point of the system of agreement provisions is reached, 
which coincides with the aim of the decision-making pro-
cess. Thus the aim is specified at the first level of the hier-
archy, i.e. the construction contraction agreement. The sec-
ond level of hierarchy consists of criteria which make 
immediate influence on the final goal. At the same time 
each criterion is at the top of the created hierarchy, con-
necting to its top. The third level consists of criteria deter-
mined by the second level. Hierarchical structures are de-
veloped on the basis of transfer of authorisation, i.e. on the 
basis of subordination. Therefore, they cannot include hori-
zontal relationships. Such relationships reflect not subordi-
nation but coordination [11]. 
Using an expert method, provisions have been deter-
mined which influence construction contract contents: 
• performance of construction works according to the 
contract and following the requirements specified 
in normative documents of construction; 
• performance of construction works keeping to the 
environment protection and work safety require-
ments; 
• permits for construction works; 
• supply of the construction site with construction 
materials, equipment, spare parts and other construc-
tions; 
• contractor 's duty to do all works independently, if 
not specified otherwise in the contract; 
• the right to require recalculation of the contract price, 
if the factual price of the construction works in-
creased by over 15 % due to circumstances not in-
fluenced by the contractor; 
• client's duty to provide a land plot for construction 
in time; 
• to obtain required construction permits; 
• client's duty to pass to contractor buildings and 
equipment for use and to install temporary energy 
or water supply networks in cases specified in the 
contract; 
• to allow to use buildings and temporary energy or 
water supply networks; 
• client's duty to pay for all works performed before 
conservation; 
• implementation of client's rights related to construc-
tion supervision and control; 
• acceptance of constructions works; 
• cooperation of parties; 
• recognition of the building as suitable for use; 
• quality guarantee terms; 
• payment for construction works; 
• contract guarantee; 
• contract termination; 
• contract suspension. </p>

<p>When CCA contents are divided into separate provi-
sions, which influence smooth construction process, we get 
a model (Fig. 1), which is broadly applicable in CCA prepa-
ration. It is possible to distinguish the following advantages 
of a hierarchical structure: 
• hierarchical structure may be used to describe how 
lower level priorities influence the change of higher 
level priorities; 
• hierarchy provides considerably more detailed in-
formation about lower level structures, functions and 
their influence on higher levels; 
• when systems reflecting real situation are developed 
by means of hierarchy, i.e. by developing and later 
uniting models, their development is more effective 
than in cases when the system is made at once; 
• a hierarchical system is both stable and flexible. Sta-
bility means that slight modifications in the hierar-
chy cause very small changes. Flexibility means that 
introduction of several new criteria does not change 
the essence of a well-developed hierarchy. 
The used hierarchy has its own specific features, there-
fore, the following presumptions are offered for use [10]: 
a) all partial indicators of the same level are equal in 
the initial calculations; 
b) compared to previous level, partial indicators of a 
higher level have bigger influence on the highest 
level of the structure; 
c) the sum of weights of all partial indicators of each 
level is equal to one; 
d) the total value of all indicators of any level is equal 
to the value of one indicator of a higher level, i.e. to 
one; 
e) any indicator is related only to one indicator of a 
higher level; 
f) the "depth" of structuring of separate indicators is 
different, and the structuring "chain" is inconsecu-
tive. 
In order to evaluate CCAs and compare their different 
variants, it is not enough only to develop a model of agree-
ment provisions. Striving to the aforementioned aims, it is 
necessary to determine the significance of structural ele-
ments of the developed model, i.e. of agreement provisions 
and groups of agreement provisions (model subsystems). 
Thus during evaluation or interpretation of evaluation re-
sults, different provisions of a CAA may be treated differ-
ently. In turn, it may cause certain misunderstandings, cre-
ate erroneous results or cause erroneous interpretation of 
the results. Therefore, it is very important to describe each 
CCA provision in detail. </p>

<p>3. Determination of indicator significance using expert 
surveys </p>

<p>In order to determine indicator significance in calcula-
tions more objectively, an opinion of a group of experts </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>

<p>
should be evaluated. For this purpose an expert group of 26 
persons was formed during pilot calculations. A fragment 
of calculation results is shown in Fig. 2. The expert group 
consisted of lawyers, civil engineers and other specialists 
(Fig. 2). 
The experts were surveyed by questionnaires. The ques-
tionnaire was prepared on the basis of the method of paired 
evaluation of indicator significance. The generalised cal-
culations of survey results showed that the compatibility of 
expert opinions meets the requirements; therefore, it is pos-
sible to claim that indicator significances derived during 
the expert survey are reliable and can be used for typical 
evaluation of contracts. However, these indicator 
significances would change with changing economic situ-</p>

<p>ation and upon evaluation of specific requirements of a 
construction project; anyway, they serve as a basis for ini-
tial calculations. 
During the pilot calculations, three contracts were evalu-
ated using the indicator significances derived from the sur-
vey of the expert group (Fig. 3). It was determined that the 
first contract meets the requirements in the best way, and 
the remaining contracts need to be improved. Therefore, 
the conclusion is drawn that calculations using the selected 
methodology provide yet another advantage, i.e. an oppor-
tunity to form an expert group for determination of criteria 
significance. 
Having summarised the results of evaluation of all three 
agreements according to each evaluation criteria, it is pos-</p>

<p>Fig. 1. The model of CCA provisions based on functions </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>



<p>Fig. 2. A fragment of the window with aggregated criteria significance and the priority list of contracts </p>

<p>Fig. 3. List of members of the expert group </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>

<p>
sible to review the priorities of alternatives determined af-
ter the evaluation (Fig. 4). According to the results obtained 
in this case, the first contract has the highest priority, the 
second has medium priority and the third has the lowest. 
The model of CCA provisions based on their functions 
has been used for evaluation. No problems related to for-
mation of the evaluation criteria hierarchy have been en-
countered during the evaluation; therefore, it can be claimed 
that the developed model of CCA provisions based on their 
functions meets the requirements applicable to a hierarchy 
and may be used for evaluation of CCAs. 
Analysis of the sensitivity of evaluation helps to deter-
mine the factors which made the greatest influence on the 
evaluation results and whether the provided evaluation of 
criteria significance is correct, to review results of the evalu-
ation of conformity of alternatives with the selected crite-
ria again and to determine opportunities for improvement 
of agreements. On the basis of the results of sensitivity 
analysis, it is possible to claim that evaluation of criteria 
significance meets evaluator's expectations on distribution 
of evaluation results. After the evaluation, evaluation of 
alternatives according to some criteria was slightly modi-
fied. The following possibilities of agreement improvement 
can be specified: 
1) Payment provisions should be improved in the sec-
ond contract. 
2) Payment provisions should be improved in the third 
contract; agreement guarantee and termination pro-
visions should be reviewed. 
Assuming that agreements are final and not subject to 
editing, the first variant must be selected on the basis of the 
evaluation results. However, if an agreement is subject to 
change, the evaluation needs to be repeated after making 
the amendments. Evaluation results may be used not only 
to determine weak points in agreements but also to deter-
mine their advantages, and thus to try improving agreement 
provisions. 
The <rs type="software">Expert Choice</rs> software was used to make pilot 
calculations. This software opens wide opportunities for its 
users. However, it has drawbacks as well. The main draw-
back of this software is that it is adjusted for use in station-
ary work places. The model of indicator hierarchy for con-
struction contract evaluation developed this way is just an 
extra feature of this software. Meanwhile, users without </p>

<p>special software cannot use the developed system of indi-
cators. True, that this system provides a possibility to pub-
lish the hierarchical model in Internet; however, only Ex-
pert Choice users can make full use of such a model. Besides, 
this software has other drawbacks characteristic of other 
stationary software: limited number of workstations, attach-
ment to a specific workstation, little opportunities to share 
experience with other users, etc. </p>

<p>4. Possibilities to implement the hierarchical model in 
decision support systems </p>

<p>One of the main aims of future decision support sys-
tems is the use of IT to increase productivity of people work-
ing in the sphere of information processing in "the age of 
information" and to solve various problems of different 
complexity and structure. Otherwise, people will simply 
fail to evaluate the available information properly and to 
make proper choice with the increasing flood of informa-
tion. This opinion is based on statistical data, which shows 
that the amount of information in a company increases twice 
annually. An employee can analyse only about 5 % of the 
received information effectively in such a situation and as-
sistance becomes vital [12]. Such situation shapes a num-
ber of tasks for a decision support system. 
One of the most important opportunities to develop de-
cision support systems is an increase of their integration. 
First, a system must be developed inside the organisation, 
and such system with a simple user interface would pro-
vide access to and exchange of information among 
company's employees. A clear link between the decision 
support system and various data must be provided and it 
must facilitate installation of various means for resource 
allocation. In this case, accessibility of the system can be 
achieved by using standard graphic user interface. Such 
standardisation is the main reason why <rs corresp="#software-11" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-11" type="software">Windows</rs> 
and related products have become widely distributed so fast. 
The main problem of decision support systems is an inter-
face with additional means that is difficult to implement. 
From the perspective of a user of a decision support sys-
tem, the main criterion when a system for work is being 
selected is the simplicity of its user interface. 
Therefore, the ideas related to information presentation 
must be improved both by the developers and users. A proper 
evaluation of the form (charts, plans, diagrams), in which </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Priorities of alternatives according to the results of ten-point evaluations </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>



<p>the information will be presented in the future, is impor-
tant. There is a chance that new forms of information pre-
sentation may be available in the future, like dynamic charts 
or multi-dimensional reports. 
Use of expert systems and other available AI forms in 
decision support systems determines the main direction. 
Knowledge bases determine the shape of a database or a 
model base, models of conclusion presentation determine 
the knowledge-based management system, and there are 
attempts to develop a user interface in all EU languages. 
One of the issues that is important as well is a closer inte-
gration of decision support systems and software applica-
tions used in a company, thus increasing the level of use-
fulness of decision support and effectiveness of the work 
of a decision-maker as well. 
The consolidating function of a decision support sys-
tem is an important component of the future decision sup-
port systems. It is especially relevant in the sphere of com-
munication. Currently it is possible to connect clients using 
local networks, external networks and other methods, and 
it is the path for further development. Further opportunities 
are standardisation of communication protocols, commu-
nication channels and data presentation allowing to ex-
change large amounts of data, graphic databases, digital 
images and videos. A possibility to connect to other net-
works is important to organisations, because it creates an 
opportunity for emergence of new and more global sources 
of information. The main problem here is security. 
Another opportunity to improve decision support sys-
tems is improvement of accessibility to documents and their 
management both inside and outside of an organisation. 
New search and structuring technologies such as underlin-
ing of an idea, hypertext and multimedia have been rapidly 
developed both for scientific research and commercial pur-
poses. One of the most successful examples thereof is 
groupware, such as <rs corresp="#software-16" type="creator">Lotus</rs> <rs id="software-16" type="software">Notes</rs>, which emerged recently 
and is growing fast. The world becomes a uniform con-
nected whole, which is the basis for further development of 
decision support systems. 
Proper presentation of knowledge creates conditions for 
a system to better reflect expert opinion. These possibili-
ties enable knowledge acquisition; and it is essential in sys-
tems which are used in vital areas where especially valu-
able decisions are made. A possibility to reach documents 
available in different locations and provided by different 
sources using fast search algorithms increases competitive-
ness of companies as well. With increasing importance of 
communication, a decision support system must operate in 
Internet and allow companies to keep up with the newest 
technologies and innovations in decision-making and to 
operate successfully in the expanding cyberspace. 
Cyberspace technologies allow single persons to be in-
volved and participate actively in electronic environment. 
Such computer graphics is based on development of in-</p>

<p>creasingly complex hardware and software able to create a 
more real environment. The cyberspace environment in-
cludes both a theatrical image shown on a big screen and 
computer displays or helmets with built-in stereo displays 
ands special headphones. The perceived experience is multi-
sensory: visible, audible and touchable, and is more accept-
able. Technology helps a viewer to understand relationships 
between different elements and provides ways to learn to 
react to the available data effectively and efficiently. 
A common principle dominating in Europe is that con-
tracts are valid despite their execution; however, laws some-
times provide for formal requirements, for example, con-
tracts must be made in writing. First, this legal requirement 
attempts to reduce the number of disputes, because con-
tracts allow explicit determination of rights and liabilities 
of parties. Second, it is an attempt to guarantee movement 
of goods and services, because they make clear who must 
perform what actions, under what conditions and what limi-
tations are applicable. Third, such formalities allow parties 
to know their rights and liabilities explicitly months and 
years after conclusion of a contract, because it is possible 
to store the contents of the document. However, laws pro-
viding for formalities may have other aims as well: they 
may make an attempt at a psychological effect. In this case 
it is attempted to make a person think about the risk and 
dangers before signing a contract, at least a little. A rel-
evant example of such contracts are loan contracts; they 
are considered dangerous, because consumers are often al-
lured by advertisements, etc. and thus fail to realise the ac-
cepted financial liabilities fully and fail to evaluate their 
economic potential. For this reason, the EU Directive 
No. 87/102/EEC On Consumer Loans determines that a 
consumer loan must be executed in the written form. 
E-commerce understands that e-contracts lack expres-
siveness and that the button "I agree/accept" contract pro-
visions do not have the same psychological effect as writ-
ten documents. Therefore, the European Union doubled the 
steps of contract conclusion (offer and acceptance) and es-
tablished a four-stage process (offer, acceptance, 
acknowledgement that the offer is received and 
acknowledgement that the acceptance is received), which 
was reduced to three stages in the later edition of the EU 
Directive No. 2000/31/EC; so now the recipient must give 
its consent by technological means in order to express its 
consent to conclude a contract, and the contract is consid-
ered as concluded from the moment the service recipient 
receives an electronic acknowledgement of the provider, 
that received the consent of the recipient (acceptance). Mem-
ber states supplement their laws by the provision that dif-
ferent steps of the process of e-contract conclusion shall be 
provided explicitly and defined so that parties shall be fa-
miliarized with their contents and procedure and that any 
steps shall be made only upon expressing consent of the 
parties. In such case, these requirements of explicitness shall </p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>

<p>
serve for equalisation of the conventional and electronic 
consent and shall not provide for the reinforced consent 
required by the nature of some contracts (e.g. consumer 
loan). 
Considering a possibility to conclude electronic con-
struction contracts, e-signature can be used, which has an 
effect similar to signing a written document. The author 
thinks that e-signatures are as authentic as handwritten sig-
natures. EU Directive No. 1999/93/EC on E-signature speci-
fies that member states shall grant secure e-signatures based 
on qualified certificates and created by secure e-signature 
development means. Such e-signatures meet legal require-
ments of relationship between a signature and data stored 
or kept in electronic form, the same as handwritten signa-
tures meet these requirements in respect of data stored or 
kept on paper. Classic civil law considers a contract as a 
result of expression of two wills. If the will is not present 
or is faulty, the main element of a contract is missing. No-
body can be bound by a contract against his/her will. Should 
the modern law know only these features of contract mak-
ing, it would become a serious barrier to validate contracts 
concluded by e-agents, which may be controlled by a third 
party (e.g. e-shop). 
However, both general law and civil law are rather rap-
idly developing legal systems, thus issues related to liabil-
ity outcomes of contractual will expression, errors and con-
sent provided by a more obvious agent are evaluated broadly 
by underlining the reliability of the other party and not the 
identification of an independent will expression. Sometimes 
negligent actions of a party are used as a basis, for example, 
a party was negligent in selection of contract phrases and 
was not attentive enough to remove the circumstances be-
cause of which somebody was considered its representa-
tive. Sometimes it is made objective by an opinion that par-
ties accept responsibility for the selected means of contract 
conclusion. 
The general validity of contracts concluded by e-agents 
is a fictitious problem initiated by suspicions caused by 
outdated civil and commercial law, often resultant from non-
lawyers and stereotypic understanding of the will of con-
tract parties. There is a considerably strong basis to claim 
that nobody can be exempt from an obligation to fulfil a 
contract only because an e-agent was an intermediary in its 
conclusion. The problem is related to settlement of errors 
made by e-agents. Another problem is related to a question 
whether it is allowed to exempt a party from liabilities un-
der a contract if it proves that the error occurred due to 
technical problems of an e-agent. 
On the basis of the aforementioned provisions, a model 
of the Web-based Decision Support System for Construc-
tion Contract Preparation was developed. This model can 
help to implement the functional model of the system of 
construction contract provisions developed by the authors 
and other principle elements. </p>

<p>5. Conclusions </p>

<p>1. Currently, multiple criteria methods and models are 
offered for efficiency improvement when solving various 
issues related to construction; however, preparation, evalu-
ation and comparison of CCAs is still rather disregarded. 
In order that the construction process is effective and 
smooth, the CCA must be properly prepared. In order to 
solve this task successfully, a model of the system of CCA 
provisions has been created. The model is based on func-
tions of provisions. 
2. The model of CCA provisions based on their func-
tions is convenient to determine significance of agreement 
provisions. Then it is possible to develop an Internet-based 
legal CCA decision support system. Such conclusion can 
be made for the following reasons: first, experts can easier 
evaluate significance of agreement provisions grouped ac-
cording to their functions and, second, legal power of all 
CCA provisions is equal, irrespective of the group they are 
attributed to according to any of the analysed classifica-
tions. However, the latter classification illustrates real op-
eration of a CCA and its functions best. 
3. Three CCAs have been selected for calculations and 
evaluation provided as an example. The evaluation has 
shown that the first variant is the most favourable to a cli-
ent, and having analysed graphic information, it is possible 
to determine possibilities for improvement of agreements. 
Software Expert Choice, which has been used in this pro-
cess, is well adjusted to development of a good hierarchy, 
to determination of criteria significance, to evaluation and 
analysis of the evaluation results. 
4. The calculations provided as an example enable the 
following conclusion: although the aforementioned soft-
ware has a number of advantages, several main disadvan-
tages can also be distinguished. The software is designed 
for stationary workstations. Thus the developed hierarchi-
cal model of CCA evaluation criteria can be only an extra-
module of the aforementioned software. Whereas users who 
do not have specialised software cannot use the developed 
system of criteria. Although the system foresees a possibil-
ity to place hierarchy models in the Internet, only Expert 
Choice software users can use them to full extent. Consid-
ering the results of the analysis, a specialised decision sup-
port system should be developed for CCA evaluation; the 
system would implement advantages of an Internet-based 
system. 
5. Since computer and information technologies are 
developing constantly, it is very important to foresee the 
possibilities to improve a decision support system. The vi-
tal task is to increase system's integration considering the 
trends of development of the aforementioned technologies 
and the purpose of a decision support system. This way a 
user can use the developed system without special training 
or with the minimum training, the need for additional soft-</p>

<p>S. Mitkus, E. Trinkûnienë / VERSLAS: TEORIJA IR PRAKTIKA -2007, VIII t., Nr. 4, 221-229 </p>



<p>ware is lower, requirements to hardware are reduced, new 
and better conditions for electronic exchange of data are 
created and more functions (video conferencing, video and 
audio records, contract signing by electronic means, etc.) 
related to preparation of construction contracts become in-
tegrated. </p>



</text></tei>