<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2013.31" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The goal of this research is to determine the dimensions of beliefs about internet advertising affecting Syrian consumers' 
attitudes and behaviors towards internet advertising. The results indicate that Attitudes are influenced positively by information, 
and entertainment; and negatively by irritation and values' corruption. Irritation positively influences consumers' behaviors of 
leaving websites showing the ads. Entertainment positively influences consumers' behaviors of clicking on internet ads for further 
information concerning advertised products. Attitude is found to fully mediate the relationships between beliefs of information, 
irritation, and values' corruption and the behaviors clicking on internet ads, and partially mediate the relationship between enter 
tainment and the behaviors of clicking on internet ads. Attitudes fully mediate the relationships between beliefs of information, 
entertainment, and values' corruption and the behaviors of leaving websites showing the ads, and partially mediate the relation 
ship between irritation and the behaviors of leaving websites showing the ads. This research comes to be one of the first studies 
to investigate Syrian consumers' beliefs about, attitudes, and behavioral responses towards internet advertising. As well as, this 
study provides evidence of the direct relationship between some of the beliefs about internet advertising (i.e. entertainment and 
irritation) and the behavioral responses towards it. </p>

<p>Advertising is a standard promotional tactic that is desi 
gned to reach a target audience and to either affect beha 
vior or to introduce, persuade, and/or remind consumers 
of an offer (Nihel 2013). Advertising messages could be 
delivered through various mediums (e.g. TV, radio, and 
magazines). Some scholars characterize advertising as 
ubiquitous and an important part of the fabric of modern 
life (Shavitt et al. 1998). Advertising has advanced with 
technological innovation, now common throughout the 
world. Several new advertising mediums are emerging and 
these have paved the way for advertisers to increase their 
interactivity with target consumers. Berthon et al. (1996)   were the first researchers to investigate how advertising 
might operate on the internet and they characterized it 
as a new medium in the marketing communication mix. 
Other researchers differentiated between offline and on 
line advertising, suggesting that traditional media (print, 
TV, and radio) is based on messages that are connected 
to entertainment, whereas the internet is better viewed as 
an informationbased medium Lei (2000). Further deba 
te over how to characterize the internet followed. Wolin  et al. (2002: 88) reason that the internet also possesses an 
entertaining component. They see internet advertising as 
a broad format that consists of "commercial content paid 
for by sponsors, designed for audiences, delivered by video, 
print, audio, graphics or animation". Recently, the internet </p>

<p>has been regarded as the most powerful advertising media 
(Radbâță, Kubenka 2012). 
With an estimated amount of $2,660,000 as an expen 
diture on internet advertising in the Middle East by the 
year 2013 (Dubai press Club 2010), Advertisers targe 
ting Syrian consumers are well aware of the promise of 
the internet as an advertising. The escalation of internet 
advertising has grown rapidly in Syria, and is exhibited 
in a wide variety of forms (e.g. websites, banner ads, 
rich media ads, web logs, electronic mail ads, and onli 
ne social network advertising). While some researchers 
have addressed the internet as a very effective adverti 
sing medium pabedinskaite, RojutėGaukštienė (2004), 
Wolin et al. (2002) refered to the internet as a source of 
challenges and opportunities for advertisers, and that in 
cludes the need for investigating internet users' beliefs, 
attitudes, and even their behavioral responses towards this 
type of advertising espcially when it comes to the results 
of previous research which considered consumer attitu 
des towards advertising as an indication of advertising 
effectiveness (e.g. Russell et al. 1994; Ducoffe 1996; Mehta  2000; Wolin et al. 2002; Wolin, Korgaonkar 2005; Karson  et al. 2006; Wang, Sun 2010a, 2010b; Sun, Wang 2010;  Mahmoud 2012a, 2012b). Effective internet advertising 
could promote for purchase intentions towards advertised 
products (Sathish et al. 2011). Therefore, modelling the 
relationships among beliefs about, attitudes and behaviors 
towards internet advertising, through the results of the 
current study, could help advertisers produce conveniently 
advertising messages that reach audience more effective 
ly in the Syrian context. Yet while research and practice 
have identified the promise of internet advertising, little 
is known about the impact of internet advertising in the 
Syrian context as the literature has largely focused on deve 
loped nations (Sun, Wang 2010; Wang, Sun 2010a, 2010b;  Kamal, Chu 2012). See Mahmoud (2012a, 2012b) for pre 
liminary research into research focusing on developing 
countries such as Syria. Therefore, the aim of the present 
study is to validate scales measuring beliefs and attitudes 
towards internet advertising with respect to the Syrian cul 
tural context and test a model (see Fig. 1) linking beliefs, 
attitudes, and behaviors related to internet advertising. 
This model is proposed on the basis of previous research 
and will utilize structural equation modeling. </p>

<p>Literature review and research hypotheses </p>

<p>Beliefs </p>

<p>Beliefs have been conceptualized as predictions held by 
people in regard to the possibilities that their knowledge 
about a referent is true (Wyer, Albarracin 2005) or, alter 
natively, that an event or state of affairs has or will occur 
(Fishbein, Ajzen 1975; Eagly, Chaiken 1998). Mahmoud </p>

<p>(2012a: 92) defined beliefs about internet advertising as 
all knowledge that one could perceive as correct for in 
ternet advertising. So consumers could perceive internet 
advertising as good source of product information (Ju 
pak 1999). Likewise, consumers may be entertained by 
internet advertising as it may involve tactics such as inte 
ractivity and multimedia (Watson et al. 1998). Conversely, 
internet offers may be a source of irritation as advertising 
may cause feelings of confusion if information is perceived 
as intense (Ducoffe 1996). Some users of the internet 
may install ad blockers, which are software that prevent 
internet ads from downloading on the browsed website 
(McCormally 2000). As well as, internet advertising could 
be perceived as promoting lifestyles embodied by types 
of products and brands advertised online (pollay, Mittal  1993; Mahmoud 2012b). Internet advertising could be a 
symbol of materialism as it encourages people to achieve 
satisfaction through consumption (pollay, Mittal 1993). 
Falsity refers to the belief about advertising as a source 
of false information and deceptive claims (Nadilo 1998). 
Wolin et al. (2002) argue that internet advertising has the 
ability to shape internet users' values; therefore, it could 
be a cause of values corruption. </p>

<p>Attitudes </p>

<p>In general, attitudes refer to the positive or the negative 
cognitive dispositions that one person holds towards a 
referent. In this regard, some attitude theorists (e.g. Fazio  1989) propose that attitudes be thought of as objecteva 
luation associations. That is, an attitude can be viewed 
as a simple twonode semantic network, with one node 
representing the object, the second node the global eva 
luation of the object, and the link between the two nodes 
the strength of the association (Fabrigar et al. 2005: 80). 
Lutz (1985: 53) defines attitudes towards advertising, in 
general, as a learned predisposition to respond in a con 
sistently favorable or unfavorable manner to advertising. 
In the context of the internet, Mahmoud (2012a: 92) re 
fers to attitudes towards internet advertising as a general 
predisposition to like or dislike advertising messages de 
livered online. </p>

<p>Behavioral responses </p>

<p>Overall, behavioral responses towards advertising are 
prompted actions that consumers take after exposure to 
an ad. Such behaviors could be actioned through seeking 
of further information after watching the ad (Nedungadi  et al. 1993). In the case of internet advertising, behavioral 
responses are mostly defined as "clicking on ad" and "le 
aving the website showing the ad" (e.g. Wolin et al. 2002;  Wang, Sun 2010a, 2010b). </p>

<p> 
A. B. Mahmoud. Syrian consumers: beliefs, attitudes, and behavioral responses to internet advertising </p>

<p>Beliefs about and attitudes towards internet 
advertising </p>

<p>The investigation of the relationship between beliefs 
about and attitudes towards advertising goes back to the 
early 1990s when Alwitt, prabhaker (1992) found that 
negative affection towards advertising was related to the 
perception of advertising as a source of irritation. Later 
studies have confirmed the significant role that beliefs 
about advertising could play in predicting consumers' 
attitudes towards advertising (Wolin et al. 2002; Yang  2003; Wang, Sun 2010a, 2010b; Kamal, Chu 2012b; Li  Ming et al. 2013). Some dimensions of beliefs about in 
ternet advertising like information (Shavitt et al. 1998;  Zhou, Bao 2002; Usman et al. 2010; Eze, Lee 2012; Zabadi  et al. 2012; Mahmoud 2012b; Mir 2012; Saxena, Khanna  2013), entertainment (Shavitt et al. 1998; Zhou, Bao 2002;  Eze, Lee 2012; Mahmoud 2012b; Saxena, Khanna 2013), 
and irritation (Zabadi et al. 2012; Mahmoud 2012b;  Saxena, Khanna 2013) are found to be more predictive 
for attitudes towards internet advertising than other di 
mensions of beliefs. 
Based on the above review we can state hypothesis one 
(H1) as follows: 
(H1): Beliefs about internet advertising will significantly 
influence attitudes towards it. </p>

<p>Attitudes and behavioral responses towards 
internet advertising </p>

<p>previous research results exhibit a robust relationship 
between attitudes and behavioral responses towards in 
ternet advertising (Mehta 2000; Wolin et al. 2002; Sohail,  Saeed 2004; Wang, Sun 2010a; Mir 2012; Kamal, Chu  2012b). In other words, positive attitudes towards inter 
net advertising will probably be accompanied with favo 
rable behavioral responses towards internet advertising 
(e.g. clicking on banners for more details about products 
advertised). Likewise, negative attitudes will lead to unfa 
vorable responses towards internet advertising (e.g. leaving 
websites showing ads). For an instant, Mehta (2000) found 
that consumers with favorable affection towards adverti 
sing are more likely to recall brand advertised. Wolin et al.  (2002) concluded that the more positive attitudes towards 
advertising were, the greater the likelihood would be to 
produce favorable behavioral responses to internet ads. 
Wang, Sun (2010a; 2010b) proved, through a crosscultural 
investigation, that positive behaviors regarding clicking 
on internet ads are significantly associated with favorable 
attitudes towards advertising. Inspecting people attitudes 
and behaviors towards social media advertising in a Middle 
Eastern country, Kamal, Chu (2012b) found that behaviors 
towards social media advertising are significantly predicted 
by attitudes. </p>

<p>With regard to the previous review, consideration to 
(H1), and Baron, Kenny (1986) approach to hypothesizing 
mediations, we propose the following hypothesis (H2): 
(H2): Attitudes will fully mediate the relationship 
between beliefs and behavioral responses towards inter-
net advertising. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>We adopt a quantitative procedure in analyzing the data 
for the present study. We collect our data through a cross 
sectional correlational field study design (Tharenou et al.  2007). </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>We select randomly 384 electronic mail addresses of active 
internet users from one internet service provider operating 
in Syria. An online survey was sent in an email to the ran 
domly selected users and this yielded 288 valid responses 
for our statistical analyses. </p>

<p>Measures </p>

<p>Measures of the present study are validated concerning the 
Syrian Arab culture (see Table 1). 
First, scale items to measure variables are translated 
from English to Arabic and then backtranslated from 
Arabic to English in purpose of eliminating items that give 
different meanings upon this procedure. Aiming to improve 
the translation accuracy, bilingual third parties are asked 
to conduct the backtranslation (Sun, Wang 2010a). Then 
we ask academicians from the department of Marketing 
&amp; International Trade in the Higher Institute of Business 
Administration (HIBA), and the department of Business 
Administration in Damascus University in Damascus </p>

<p>fig. 1. The proposed Model </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(4): 297-307 </p>

<p>
Table 1. Measures used in the present study </p>

<p>Scale 
Source 
Recoded 
Item 
Dimension </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>Ducoffe 1996 </p>

<p>N/A 
is a good source of product information </p>

<p>Information </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
provides timely information </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
provides meaningful information about the product use of 
other consumers </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
provides useful information about new products </p>

<p>Likert 
Wolin et al. 2002; 
Ducoffe 1996; Wang, 
Sun 2010a, 2010b </p>

<p>N/A 
is entertaining </p>

<p>Entertainment 
Likert 
N/A 
is pleasing </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
is fun to use </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
is exciting </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>pollay, Mittal 1993; 
Wolin et al. 2002 </p>

<p>N/A 
It lets me know what is in fashion and what I should buy 
for keeping a good social image </p>

<p>Social Role 
Likert 
N/A 
tells me what people like myself are buying and using </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
helps me know which products will or will not reflect the 
sort of person I am </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>Wolin et al. 2002 </p>

<p>N/A 
make you buy things you don't really need </p>

<p>materialism </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Increases dissatisfaction among consumers by showing 
products which some consumers can't afford </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Is making us a materialistic society -interested in buying 
and owning things </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Makes people buy unaffordable products just to show off </p>

<p>Likert 
Wang, Sun 2010a, 
b; Wolin et al. 2002; 
Burnett 2000) </p>

<p>R 
Helps the consumer buy the best brand for the price </p>

<p>falsity 
Likert 
N/A 
I don't believe online ads </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Is not objective </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>Ducoffe 1996 </p>

<p>N/A 
Is irritating </p>

<p>Irritation 
Likert 
N/A 
Is confusing </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Is annoying </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
insults people's intelligence </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>Wang, Sun 2010a, b; 
Wolin et al. 2002) </p>

<p>N/A 
Makes people live in a world of fantasy </p>

<p>Values 
Corruption </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
takes undue advantage of children </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Leads children to make unreasonable purchase demands 
on their parents </p>

<p>Likert </p>

<p>Wolin et al. 2002; 
Wang, Sun 2010a, b </p>

<p>N/A 
Overall, I consider online advertising as a good thing </p>

<p>Attitude </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Overall, I like online advertising </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Overall, I regard online advertising as an essential thing </p>

<p>Likert 
N/A 
Overall, watching online advertising is important to me </p>

<p>Likert 
R 
Overall, online advertising is not interesting to me </p>

<p>Likert 
Wolin et al. 2002 
N/A 
When I see online advertisement, I click on it for further 
information 
Behavioral 
Response 
Likert 
N/A 
When I see online advertisement, I leave the website </p>

<p>to evaluate the Arabic wording for our scales' items 
to guarantee that our measures are facevalidated. As 
recommended by many researchers (e.g. Tharenou et al.  2007), our questionnaire is piloted before distributed. 
The pilot study involves 57 internet users. The purpose 
of this procedure is to guarantee a good understanding 
and acceptance by respondents, so some questions may </p>

<p>need deleting or modifying. Second, measures are fac 
toranalyzed using the approach of principal Component 
Analysis and Varimax rotation (see Table 2) to check for 
the dimensionality of the scales measuring beliefs and 
attitudes. Third, measures are assessed for reliability using 
Cronbach alpha to check for their internal consistency 
(see Table 3). </p>

<p> 
A. B. Mahmoud. Syrian consumers: beliefs, attitudes, and behavioral responses to internet advertising </p>

<p>Table 2. Factor analysis </p>

<p>Attitude 
Values 
Corruption 
Irritation 
falsity 
materia 
lism 
Social Role 
Enter tainment 
Infor 
mation 
Item </p>

<p>0.777 
inf01 
0.887 
inf02 
0.44 
inf03 
0.589 
inf04 
0.577 
ent01 
0.878 
ent02 
0.85 
ent03 
0.446 
ent04 
0.691 
soc01 
0.728 
soc02 
0.608 
soc03 
0.763 
mater01 
0.527 
mater02 
0.74 
mater03 
0.76 
mater04 
0.434 
fals01 
0.83 
fals02 </p>

<p>0.779 
fals03 </p>

<p>0.816 
irr01 
0.631 
irr02 
0.795 
irr03 
0.66 
irr04 
0.788 
vc01 
0.86 
vc02 
0.511 
vc03 
0.355 
att01 
0.756 
att02 
0.762 
att03 
0.808 
att04 
0.786 
att05 </p>

<p>2.55 
2.287 
2.892 
2.051 
2.421 
1.845 
2.519 
2.582 
Eigenvalue </p>

<p>50.996 
9.148 
11.567 
8.206 
9.685 
7.379 
10.074 
10.326 
%Variance </p>

<p>Table 3. Reliability test </p>

<p>Alpha 
Items # 
factor </p>

<p>0.712 
4 
Information </p>

<p>0.757 
4 
Entertainment </p>

<p>0.639 
3 
Social Role </p>

<p>0.750 
4 
materialism </p>

<p>0.681 
3 
falsity </p>

<p>0.807 
4 
Irritation </p>

<p>0.727 
3 
Values Corruption </p>

<p>0.743 
5 
Attitude </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Demographic data description </p>

<p>As table 4 exhibits, our respondents consist of (56.94%) 
men and (43.06%) women. The majority of the respon 
dents hold a bachelors degree (43.06%), with age ranging 
between 20 to less than 30 years (65.97%), and a monthly 
income of less than 10,000 SYp or unemployed. </p>

<p>Hypotheses testing </p>

<p>The model testing hypotheses of the present study (Fig. 1) is 
evaluated through the statistical method of structural equa 
tion modeling (SEM) using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SpSSAMOS</rs> (v. <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">18</rs>) software. </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(4): 297-307 </p>

<p>
Bootstrapping is used as well to confirm the significance of 
mediations exhibited in the model regardless of normality 
of our data (Byrne 2010). We use the following statistics in 
testing the goodness of fit: Chi square (c²) (Bollen 1989); 
normed fit index (NFI) (Bentler, Bonett 1980); comparative 
fit index (CFI) (Bentler 1990); root mean square residual 
(RMR) (Hu, Bentler 1995); and root mean square error of 
approximation (RMSEA) (Browne, Cudeck 1993). Those 
statistics will help to test for how good the model is in fit 
ting the collected data. 
Table 5 shows the results of the proposed model test 
ing. The values of RMR (0.036 &lt; 0.05) (Hu, Bentler 1995), 
CFI (0.958 &gt; 0.9) (Bentler 1990), and NFI (0.942 &gt; 0.9) 
(Bentler, Bonett 1980) indicate a good fit for the proposed 
model. However, RMSEA (0.88 &gt; 0.08) demonstrates a poor 
fit of the proposed model for our data (Jöreskog, Sörbom  1989) -besides there are three insignificant paths: Social 
Role → Attitude (pvalue = 0.281 &gt; 0.05), Materialism → 
Attitude (pvalue = 0.218 &gt; 0.05), and Falsity → Attitude 
(pvalue = 0.176 &gt; 0.05). Therefore, our model needs to be 
revised, and then retested. <rs type="software">AMOS</rs> suggests adding two new 
paths (Entertainment → Click on ad; Irritation → Leave 
website) as modification indices to improve the model fit 
ting for the data. Therefore, we eliminate the insignificant 
paths, draw the new suggested two paths, and retest the 
alternative mo del. Table 6 shows the results of testing the 
alternative model. All paths are significant. The goodness of 
fit statistics show that the alternative model is presenting a </p>

<p>Table 4. Demographic description </p>

<p>maximum 
minimum </p>

<p>% frequency 
frequency 
Values 
Variable </p>

<p>56.94 
164 
Males </p>

<p>gender 
43.06 
124 
Females </p>

<p>100 
288 
Total </p>

<p>9.03 
26 
High School or less </p>

<p>Education </p>

<p>30.56 
88 
Intermediate Diploma or Some years 
of College </p>

<p>43.06 
124 
Bachelor </p>

<p>17.36 
50 
postgrads </p>

<p>100 
288 
Total </p>

<p>50 Years 
18 Years </p>

<p>22.22 
64 
Less than 20 years </p>

<p>Age 
65.97 
190 
From 20 to less than 30 years </p>

<p>11.81 
34 
30 years and above </p>

<p>100 
288 
Total </p>

<p>350,000 SYp 
0 (Unemployed) </p>

<p>53.82 
155 
Unemployed or of less than 10,000 
SYp </p>

<p>Income </p>

<p>20.14 
58 
10,000 to less than 20,000 SYp </p>

<p>12.85 
37 
20,000 to less than 30,000 SYp </p>

<p>13.19 
38 
30,000 SYp and above </p>

<p>100 
288 
Total </p>

<p>Table 5. proposed Model Results </p>

<p>The Proposed model </p>

<p>Pva lue 
C.R. 
S.E. 
Esti 
mate 
The Relationship </p>

<p>0.001 
3.211 
0.058 
0.185 
Attitude 
→ 
Informa 
tion </p>

<p>0.000 
7.995 
0.044 
0.35 
Attitude 
→ 
Enter tain 
ment </p>

<p>0.281 
-1.077 
0.039 
-0.042 
Attitude 
→ 
Social 
Role </p>

<p>0.218 
1.233 
0.036 
0.044 
Attitude 
→ 
Materia 
lism </p>

<p>0.176 
1.352 
0.041 
0.055 
Attitude 
→ 
Falsity </p>

<p>0.000 
-5.75 
0.05 
-0.286 
Attitude 
→ 
Irritation </p>

<p>0.000 
-4.619 
0.035 
-0.16 
Attitude 
→ </p>

<p>Values 
Corrup 
tion </p>

<p>0.000 
13.533 
0.075 
1.011 
Click on 
ad 
→ 
Attitude </p>

<p>0.000 
-5.476 
0.103 
-0.562 
Leave 
website 
→ 
Attitude </p>

<p>pvalue = 0.000 
c² / df = 3.232 
Chi 
square </p>

<p>0.942 
NfI </p>

<p>0.958 
CfI </p>

<p>0.036 
RmR </p>

<p>0.880 
RmSEA </p>

<p> 
A. B. Mahmoud. Syrian consumers: beliefs, attitudes, and behavioral responses to internet advertising </p>

<p>good fit for our data. In this regard, we notice that c² value 
is insignificant (c²/ df = 1.076, pvalue &gt; 5%), the normed 
fit index is higher than 0.9 (NFI = 0.982), the comparative 
fit index is higher than 90% (CFI = 0.999), the root mean 
square residual is less than 0.05 (RMR = 0.032), and the 
root mean square error of approximation is less than 0.08 
(RMSEA = 0.020) (Jöreskog, Sörbom 1989; Hu, Bentler  1995; Bentler 1992; MacCallum et al. 1996). Consequently, 
we conclude that the alternative model expresses a good fit 
ting for our data. As well as, Table 8 shows that all indirect 
effects are significant. That is, we come to a decision that H1 
and H2 are partially supported in the light of the following 
results (see Fig. 2). </p>

<p>Beliefs as predictors of attitudes towards 
internet advertising </p>

<p>Attitudes towards internet advertising are directly inf 
luenced positively by information (Estimate = 0.155, 
pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = 0.382), and entertainment (Estimate = 
0.35, pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = 0.382); and negatively by irritation 
(Estimate = -0.258, pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = -0.437) and values' 
corruption (Estimate = -0.141, pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = -0.375). </p>

<p>Beliefs as predictors of behaviors towards 
internet advertising </p>

<p>Irritation positively influences consumers' behaviors of 
bouncing away from websites that show the ads (Estimate = 
0.368, pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = 0.282). Entertainment positively 
influences consumers' behaviors of clicking on internet ads 
for further information concerning advertised products 
(Estimate = 0.245, pvalue &lt; 0.01, r = 0.494). </p>

<p>Attitude as a mediator between internet advertising 
beliefs and behaviors </p>

<p>Attitudes fully mediate the relationships between beliefs of 
information (pvalue &lt; 0.01), irritation (p value &lt; 0.01), and 
values' corruption (pvalue &lt; 0.01) and the behaviors click 
ing on online ads, and partially mediate the relationship 
between entertainment (pvalue &lt; 0.01) and the behaviors 
of clicking on internet ads. 
Attitudes fully mediate the relationships between beliefs 
of information (pvalue &lt; 0.05), entertainment (pvalue &lt; 
0.05), and values' corruption (pvalue &lt; 0.05) and the be 
haviors of leaving websites showing the ads, and partially 
mediate the relationship between irritation (pvalue &lt; 0.05) 
and the behaviors of leaving websites showing the ads. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The present study finds that Syrian consumers perceive 
beliefs about internet advertising as a multidimensional </p>

<p>Table 6. Alternative Model Results </p>

<p>Alternative model Results </p>

<p>Pva lue 
C.R. 
S.E. 
Esti 
mate 
The Relationship </p>

<p>0.005 
2.79 
0.056 
0.155 
Attitude 
→ 
Infor 
mation </p>

<p>0.000 
9.072 
0.039 
0.35 
Attitude 
→ 
Enter 
tainment </p>

<p>0.000 
-5.493 
0.047 
-0.258 
Attitude 
→ 
Irri tation </p>

<p>0.000 
-4.263 
0.033 
-0.141 
Attitude 
→ </p>

<p>Values 
Corrup 
tion </p>

<p>0.000 
10.252 
0.084 
0.866 
Click 
on ad 
→ 
Attitude </p>

<p>0.042 
-2.034 
0.119 
-0.243 
Leave 
website 
→ 
Attitude </p>

<p>0.000 
3.373 
0.109 
0.368 
Leave 
website 
→ 
Irritation </p>

<p>0.000 
3.423 
0.072 
0.245 
Click 
on ad 
→ 
Enter 
tainment </p>

<p>pvalue = 0.375 
c² / df = 1.076 
Click 
on ad </p>

<p>0.982 
NfI </p>

<p>0.999 
CfI </p>

<p>0.032 
RmR </p>

<p>0.020 
RmSEA </p>

<p>fig. 2. The Alternative path Model </p>

<p>construct (i.e. information, entertainment, the social role, 
materialism, falsity, values corruption, and irritation), and 
attitude as a unidimensional construct. This result con 
curs with previous findings of the literature (e.g. Alwitt,  prabhaker 1992; Wolin et al. 2002; Wang, Sun 2010b;  Mahmoud 2012a, 2012b). </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(4): 297-307 </p>

<p>
Irritation is found to exert a direct effect on Syrian con 
sumer's behavioral responses of leaving the website that 
presents the ads. For example, if consumers get encountered 
with a website bearing many ads, those consumers will pro 
bably feel confused and consequently leave the adsbearing 
site. That is, consumers who perceive of internet ads as being 
irritating or confusing will probably drive Syrian consumers 
to leave the website showing the ads, regardless of whether 
he or she holds favorable or unfavorable affects towards 
internet advertising in general. This result is considered a 
significant contribution to the current literature as beliefs 
could directly influence consumer behavioral responses 
towards internet advertising. 
Our results also show that entertainment directly inf 
luences Syrian consumers' responses towards clicking on 
internet ads to get additional information related to the 
advertised product. So, perceiving internet advertising as a 
source of entertainment (e.g. containing flash games) may 
predict consumers to click on internet ads, even if Syrian 
consumers hold negative attitudes to internet advertising 
in general. proving a direct relationship between entertain 
ment and clicking on internet ads, a contribution has been 
made to current literature demonstrating that beliefs could 
be directly linked to behavior. 
Attitudes towards internet advertising is found to 
mediate fully the relationship between some beliefs (i.e. </p>

<p>information, irritation, and values corruption) and the be 
havioral response of clicking on internet ads (Shavitt et al.  1998; Wolin et al. 2002; Zhou, Bao 2002; Yang 2003; Wang,  Sun 2010a, 2010b; Usman et al. 2010; Eze, Lee 2012; Zabadi  et al. 2012; Kamal, Chu 2012b). Additionally, attitudes are 
found to partially mediate the relationship between enter 
tainment and clicking on internet ads. This finding implies 
that Syrian consumers with positive beliefs about internet 
advertising will probably form favorable attitudes towards 
it and consequently enhance the possibility of clicking on 
internet ads. Moreover, Syrian consumers who like internet 
advertising in general, will likely click on internet ads, even 
if they describe those ads as entertaining or not. 
The present study finds that attitudes toward inter 
net advertising in general mediates fully the relationship 
between some beliefs (i.e. information, entertainment, and 
values corruption) and the behavioral response of leaving 
the website showing the ads (Shavitt et al. 1998; Wolin et al.  2002; Zhou, Bao 2002; Yang 2003; Wang, Sun 2010a, 2010b;  Usman et al. 2010; Eze, Lee 2012; Zabadi et al. 2012; Kamal,  Chu 2012b). In addition, attitude towards advertising will 
mediate partially the relationship between irritation and 
leaving the website showing ads. That is, when Syrian con 
sumers hold positive beliefs about internet advertising, they 
probably develop favorable affection and consequently are 
less possible to leave a website with an advertising content. </p>

<p>Table 7. Descriptive statistics and intercorrelations </p>

<p>Variables 
mean 
S.D. </p>

<p>Information 
4.24 
0.50 </p>

<p>Entertainment 
3.31 
0.68 
0.27** </p>

<p>Social Role 
3.37 
0.79 
0.25** 
0.47** </p>

<p>materialism 
2.91 
0.85 
-0.04 
0.31** 
0.35** </p>

<p>falsity 
2.51 
0.70 
-0.38** -0.09 -0.23** 
0.02 </p>

<p>Irritation 
2.03 
0.59 
-0.31** -0.13* 
-0.08 
0.28** 
0.35** </p>

<p>Values Corruption 
3.12 
0.83 
-0.27** -0.09 -0.16** 0.29** 
0.24** 
0.37** </p>

<p>Attitude 
3.59 
0.57 
0.38** 
0.50** 
0.25** 
0.02 
-0.18** -0.44** -0.38** </p>

<p>Click on ad 
2.92 
0.93 
0.27** 
0.45** 
0.25** 
0.03 
-0.15* -0.34** -0.21** 0.62** </p>

<p>Leave website 
2.01 
1.05 
-0.14* -0.33** -0.25** 
0.01 
0.17** 
0.28** 
0.17** -0.31** -0.36** </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01; * P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Table 8. Mediation effect confirmation -Indirect effects significance </p>

<p>Dimension 
Values Corruption 
Irritation 
Entertainment 
Information 
Attitude </p>

<p>Attitude 
... 
... 
... 
... 
... </p>

<p>Click on ad 
0.022* 
0.031* 
0.03* 
0.031* 
... </p>

<p>Leave website 
0.001** 
0.001** 
0.001** 
0.002** 
... </p>

<p>** P &lt; 0.01; * P &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p> 
A. B. Mahmoud. Syrian consumers: beliefs, attitudes, and behavioral responses to internet advertising </p>

<p>As well as, Syrian consumer with positive attitudes towards 
internet advertising will probably keep navigating the web 
site, even if they find internet ads irritating or not. </p>

<p>Implications </p>

<p>Researchers are advised to consider using the validated 
scales used in the present study, when they measure public 
beliefs about and attitudes towards advertising in the Syrian 
or even in the Arab country contexts. 
Advertisers promoting in Syria are encouraged to influ 
ence Syrian consumers' beliefs about internet advertising to 
be more positive and less negative. That could be through 
working towards having internet advertising more infor 
mative (e.g. providing timely productrelated information), 
more entertaining (e.g. including flash games within in 
ternet ads, or enclosing amusing pictures), less irritating 
and confusing (e.g. avoiding high volumes of ads within a 
website), and less values corruptive or provalues through 
enhancing targeting tools in a way preventing kids from 
being exposed to inappropriate ads (e.g. Most social networ 
ks ads are accurately communicated to targeted segments of 
consumers). So consumers will mostly have more favorable 
affection and that leads to more favorable behavioral res 
ponses towards internet ads in respect to click on them or 
the period of time that consumers spend exposing to them. </p>

<p>Limitations and suggestions for future research </p>

<p>The results of this research in regard to the relationships 
between beliefs, attitudes, and behaviors towards internet 
advertising may need further investigation in cases of ot 
her electronic advertising media (e.g. SMS ads) or other 
traditional advertising media (e.g. newspapers, magazines, 
or radio ads) to test the validity of our results across diffe 
rent advertising medium types (e.g. Mittal 1994; Mahmoud  2010). 
A crosssectional method is used in the present study, 
That is, some researchers make criticism of using cross 
sectional design in testing causal relationships (e.g. Reisel  et al. 2010). So, it is recommended to conduct further in 
vestigations for our results using a longitudinal design, as 
having longitudinal data will help check consistency across 
waves. Besides, this research lacks the use of qualitative data, 
which could contribute in giving more meaningful results 
when used in accompany with quantitative data (Tharenou  et al. 2007). </p>



<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(4): 297-307 </p>



<p>
 
A. B. Mahmoud. Syrian consumers: beliefs, attitudes, and behavioral responses to internet advertising </p>



<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2013, 14(4): 297-307 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>