<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2017.018" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:28+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The aim of this research is to examine the effect of the role and level of in-sector trust (involving clients, subcontrac-
tors, and other logistics providers) and trust within firms in creating competitiveness in logistics service providers. The data 
were collected from 51 logistics service providers in Hungary. During our research we established that trust related to staff is 
decisive in the direction of the firm's profitability, and the trust communicated by the top manager (trust in partners) is essential 
in ensuring smooth operations and long term, stable flexible cooperation. The results of this paper effectively support logistics 
service providers in finding economic success factors, thanks to which they can completely satisfy the expectations of customers 
in the supply chain. </p>

<p>The logistics services industry has demonstrated tremen-
dous growth over several decades, and there has been an 
increasing academic interest in logistics service providers 
(LSPs), especially since the 1990s (Maloni and Carter 2006). 
According to Lukassen and Wallenburg (2010), the work 
of LSPs has been increasingly recognised over the last 
few years, as has the significance of functioning supply 
relationships (Huemer 2012). Third-party logistics (3PL) 
plays a main role in supply chain management and, as a 
result, has experienced remarkable growth. The demand 
for 3PL providers has become a main approach (Govindan  et al. 2016). Companies generally outsource their logistics </p>

<p>By enhancing operational performance, integration imp-
roves outsourcing performance in terms of both financial 
performance and overall satisfaction. Lastly, operational 
performance also contributes to financial performance 
(Yang and Zhao 2016). 
Building relationships of trust seems to be a continu-
ously attractive feature for business partners in contempo-
rary society. However, achieving the close level of trust in 
relationships which business partners hope for is not easy 
during the business cooperation period. Basically, in real-
life business environments the building of trust relation-
ships appears to be impacted by the implementation of every 
detailed element of business cooperation decision-making 
during the business development processes (Wang 2012). 
The fundamental meaning of building trust can be under-
stood in the sense that in-depth business collaboration with 
business partners is affected by the speed of trust-building, 
i.e. the time taken to create trust during the processes of 
developing the business. Therefore, trust is an important 
element in building long-term relationships (Ganesan 1994)  and is considered a critical factor in the success of logistics 
outsourcing relationships (Tian et al. 2008, Schoenherr et al.  2015). Trust is an essential factor for successful resource 
sharing in logistics. Trust building is long-term multi-dis-
ciplinary agenda in collaborative networked organizations 
including those in supply chain and logistics (Daudi et al.  2017). They continue that trust is important for the informa-
tion sharing and collaboration between supply chain part-
ners and it enables development of log-term collaborative 
strategy (Stonkutė and Vveinhardt 2016). For supply chains, 
collective optimization, with sharing and cooperation is key 
to success. Therefore, trust between Inter-organizational 
Information System partners is essential. However, firms 
are wary of sharing information across organizational 
boundaries (Sing and Teng 2016). For supply chains, col-
lective optimization, with sharing and cooperation is key 
to success. Therefore, trust between inter-organizational 
information system partners is essential (Singh and Teng  2016). Our research aim was to examine the role of trust 
and the effect of the level of trust in the competitiveness of 
logistics services providers and within this, to examine the 
in-sector level of trust (involving clients, sub-contractors 
and other logistics service providers), as well as the essential 
factors in the development of trust within the firm. The 
study of trust is important from the perspective of logistics 
service providers because, given its cost-reducing effect, 
it represents an important factor in competitiveness and 
growth. This research contributes to the sparse literature 
that has examined the relationship between key success 
factors (inter-organisational and inter-firm firm relation-
ships) and the performance of logistics service providers in 
a Hungarian context. </p>

<p>1. Literature Review </p>

<p>1.1. Factors of trust levels in inter-organisational 
relationships </p>

<p>Organizational trust can be divided into intra-and inter-
organizational trust. Inter-organizational trust refers to the 
extent to which organizational members have a collectively 
held trust orientation towards the partner firm (Zaheer  et al. 1998, Ring and Van de Ven 1994, Jeffries and Reed  2000). 
There are real problems in separating the two concepts; 
however, most studies have opted to use individuals' reports 
to assess inter-organisational trust levels. A few studies have 
looked at both interpersonal and inter-organisational trust 
in buyer-supplier relationships (Zaheer et al. 1998). Trust 
shapes inter-firm relational embeddedness, which is char-
acterised as a range of integration activities reflecting close 
working practices between buyers and suppliers (Lawson  et al. 2008). Based upon a widespread belief on the part of 
those involved in business, having positive trust relation-
ships potentially supports and promotes further business 
collaboration between business partners (Blomqvist 1997,  Gambetta 2000, Schumacher 2006). Trust refers to the ex-
tent to which partners in a relationship perceive each other 
as credible and benevolent. Credibility reflects the extent to 
which a firm in a relationship believes that the other party 
has the required expertise to perform the expected task ef-
fectively, while benevolence occurs when one relationship 
partner believes that the other party has intentions and mo-
tives that will benefit the relationship (Nyaga et al. 2010). 
Sahay (2003) described the trust factors related to col-
laborating enterprises as follows: the cost and/or profit side 
of the relationship, the foreseeable good performance and 
procedure, the role of common values and standards, the 
fact that the other party is able to meet its commitments, the 
development of trust, the long-term strategy, the transfer 
of trust as well as the commitments and competence-based 
trust can be achieved also if one of the partners are able 
to meet its commitments. Three aspects of a supply chain 
network influence network-level trust in supply chains: the 
number of uninfluenced partners, the number of uninflu-
ential partners and the degree of interdependence (Capaldo  and Giannoccaro 2015). 
Morgan and Hunt (1994) emphasise the importance of 
meeting commitments, since this is the pre-requisite of trust 
for partners in the supply chain. In addition, Hurley (2006)  confirms that the personality, culture and previous experience 
of the leading manager of the enterprise has a significant im-
pact, both on the establishment of the work environment and 
on the development of enterprise relationships and partner 
behaviours. The existing literature shows extensive support for 
the overall beneficial effect of trust on business transactions, 
operational effectiveness and product quality (Shin et al. 2000), </p>

<p> 
J. Oláh et al. An examination of trust as a strategical factor of success in logistical firms </p>

<p>and inter-organisational relationships (Szulanski et al. 2004). 
Wang (2012) pointed out that business partners today no 
longer only emphasize the importance of trust building, 
because there is no doubt that the prerequisite of building 
trust is becoming an inevitable common understanding in 
business. Hence, business partners prefer to seek a way to 
build trust relationships, or organizations are even more 
eager to stimulate trust relationships with their business 
partners. </p>

<p>1.2. Factors of trust levels in interfirm 
relationships </p>

<p>Trust is an important coordinating mechanism in inter-
firm relations, reducing transaction costs and fostering 
successful collaborations among organizations (Aoyama,  Ratick 2007). The importance of trust in organizations is 
increasingly recognized (Lapointe et al. 2014). Bradach  and Eccles (1989) defined trust as "a type of expectation 
that alleviates the fear that one's exchange partner will act 
opportunistically. " Dore (1983) and Sako (1992) studied the 
case of interfirm relations in Japan, leading them to identify 
goodwill as a factor in interfirm relations. Conventionally, 
research on interfirm relations has largely been conducted 
on the intra-industry level, typically in manufacturing sec-
tors such as automobiles, textiles, and electronics (Womack  et al. 1990, McKendrick et al. 2000, Wong 2002). In contrast, 
the logistics industry involves both intra-and inter-industry 
relational dynamics; intra-industry relations are represen-
ted by inter-firm relations between logistics providers, and 
inter-industry relations are represented by those existing 
between logistics providers and logistics users. Anderson  et al. (2017) find that higher initial trust is associated with 
reduced expenditures for management controls and increa-
sed investments in the collaboration. Minnaar et al. (2017)  find that trust is interactively related to control in complex 
and often unpredictable ways rather than in linear ways that 
result from managerial decision-making. In the network 
of associations that constitutes the interfirm relationship, 
trust is not a stable solution that generates predictability, 
but a quasi-actor that is made to act by the contract and 
the incorporated control structures. Lusher et al. 's (2012)  results confirm that trust induces awareness and produces 
expectations of reciprocity -features that are consistent 
with the view of trust as a general organizing principle. 
Trust in interfirm exchange has traditionally been treated 
as mutually held and jointly determined by the two parties 
in a relationship. Yet, the expectations of exchange part-
ners can, and routinely do, differ with respect to the goals, 
preferences, and vulnerabilities in their shared relationship 
(McEvily et al. 2017). 
Results also show that networks of perceived trust rela-
tions are characterized by tendencies toward reciprocity 
and a generalized giving of trust. </p>

<p>2. Research methodology </p>

<p>Of the 284 logistics service providers, 56 responded, of 
which 51 were evaluated. This shows a response rate of 
almost 20%, which can be regarded as representative when 
viewed in terms of general beliefs and academic acceptance. 
Representativeness is further strengthened by the market 
share of the respondents (50%), and the test results of the 
general and sample population in terms of their geographi-
cal location and distribution. From this list the target group 
was selected, including enterprises with a revenue (net sa-
les) of at least 100 000 EUR, but not higher than EUR 100 
million per year. Our sample represents the opinions of 
big companies of the sector, because of their relatively low 
response rate and large share of revenue in the industrial 
sector. At the same time, as shown above, the geographical 
distribution of the sample corresponded to the distribution 
of the population. 13% of the interviewed LSPs were esta-
blished in 1990, when a number of entrepreneurs decided 
to set up their own companies due to the political and 
economic restructuring occurring in the region. More than 
50% of the examined LSPs were engaged in the domestic 
and international road transport of goods or road forwar-
ding services directly after their establishment. 32% of the 
newly-established LSPs were primarily involved in ware-
housing activities. The following activities ranged between 
10%-20%: railway transport and/or forwarding, air freight 
and/or forwarding, water freight and/or forwarding, trans-
port and/or forwarding of containers, custom-house agent 
activities, transport and/or forwarding of oversized goods, 
logistics activities outsourced by clients inside or outside 
the factory yard, freight insurance and logistics consultan-
cy. Seventy-five per cent of the enterprises involved in the 
research were primarily Hungarian-owned. 
GfK Hungary Market Research Institute contributed 
significantly to the structure of the questionnaire, we created 
the professional content, and the possible response forms 
and types were greatly influenced by the data quality and 
type that can be managed and expected by the evaluation 
software (<rs type="software">SPSS</rs>). Questionnaires were completed using the 
Computer Assisted Web Interviewing (CAWI) method. The 
internet-based questionnaire technique provided an effec-
tive research background for this target group by allowing 
respondents to answer questions on delicate corporate is-
sues (financial issues, role of suppliers, etc.) more honestly, 
as the interviewee's response was not affected by the pres-
ence of the interviewer. </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Levels of trust within industrial sectors </p>

<p>Based on a deeper analysis of the data on which Fig. 1 
is based, and highlighting certain critical levels, we 
can state that -on a scale ranging from 1 to 10-21% of </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2017, 18: 171-177 </p>

<p>
respondents rated the level of trust within the industry 
(clients, subcontractors, other logistics service providers) as 
5, which was not a very positive result, with 50% rating con-
fidence levels between 6 and 9. In total 4% of respondents 
rated it as 9, i.e. they almost completely trust their partner; 
this is a very low level. At the same time, 4% rated the level 
of trust at 2, reflecting mistrust within the industry. If we 
break down the data relating to trust levels according to the 
various actors, we do not find a single client company with a 
value of between 0 and 2, so clients trust the logistic service 
companies rather than the other operators around them 
in the market. In addition, 77% (48 + 29) of the logistics 
service providers involved in the research evaluated their 
clients between 7 and 10, reflecting a strong level of trust. 
They have least trust in other logistics service companies, 
with 14% rating the level of trust at zero, which is a sign 
of total distrust. In summary, this means that although in 
many cases they consider each other as competitors rather 
than partners, in contrast to this, when Hungarian logistic 
companies were asked how they see other logistics com-
panies, 66% replied that they are both competitors and 
co-operative partners. This duality, however, explains the 
level of confidence shown in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Following this, companies had to answer the same ques-
tion, but this time as regards how they feel they are evaluated 
by their partners. They evaluated themselves as most trusted 
by their clients (48%), while they feel that subcontractors 
(16%) and other logistics companies (18%) do not trust 
them at all (Fig. 2). 
From Fig. 1 and 2 it is clear that logistics providers tend 
to have close relationships of trust with their clients. The 
relationship, however, can be manifold: strategic, cooper-
ative-partnership, or client and provider. Fig. 3 shows the 
relationship between Hungarian logistics providers and 
their clients. 
Firms consider 30% of their clients to be strategic part-
ners, while the simple client-provider relationship is more 
typical (36%). In relation to signing a contract, 60% of re-
spondents consider that proportional rights are established 
between the contracting parties, while 40% believe these 
contracts give rise to unwarranted advantages for the cli-
ent (termination, conditions of payment etc.). Presumably 
those who report this latter type of contract are also those 
who are in a client-provider relationship. Contracts drawn 
up with clients are considered the result of a comprehensive, 
but justified and manageable, process by 50% of logistics 
service providers, while 25% of these firms consider them 
the result of a quick, routine process. 
If clients demand an unplanned, unexpected service 
from the service provider, 95% of logistics firms will react 
to their clients' request within 1 to 24 hours of receiving 
it. Within this group, 29% of firms react within 1 hour to 
the request received. Among the leading managers of the 
logistics firms asked, about 18% consider their own role to 
be important, i.e. on a scale of 10 they rate the trust estab-
lished with their partners as 10. No-one assessed their own 
role between 0 and 2, i.e. the majority are clear about the 
importance of their own role. 88% of the leading managers 
asked were aware of which professional organisation their 
firm was a member of. 63% of logistic service providers were 
members of one or two professional organisations, and as 
an extreme example, we can point out that of the 56 firms 
questioned, one was simultaneously a permanent member 
of 8 organisations during the period of the research. 
As regards clusters, the situation was reversed: 82% of 
logistics firms did not belong to any cluster. The reasons for 
this may include: the low level of trust in the environment 
around logistics firms, the unfavourable choice of region 
and headquarters, and the lack of readiness towards coop-
eration and initiative taking. If a firm from the sample did 
choose to be a member of a cluster (18%), then it only joined 
one cluster, and not more. </p>

<p>3.2. Trust within firms </p>

<p>Trust within the firm is an important foundation stone for 
the firm to achieve a profitable operation and success. The </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Trust in partners (authors' own research 2015) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Trust in logistic service provider firms (authors' own 
research 2015) </p>

<p>Fig. 3. The relationship between the logistic service providers 
and their clients (authors' own research 2015) </p>

<p> 
J. Oláh et al. An examination of trust as a strategical factor of success in logistical firms </p>

<p>atmosphere of trust within the firm was, all things consi-
dered, evaluated positively by the respondents. Of the firm 
leaders, 82% (30 + 52) rated the level of trust within their 
own firms as between 7 and 10. The level of trust within 
the firm can be seen (Fig. 4). 
14% of the respondents do not trust their direct subor-
dinates at all, which can have a negative effect on everyday 
operations. Respondents' answers were more varied regard-
ing direct subordinates than regarding other employees. 
According to 88% of leading managers at logistics firms, 
there is a significant relationship between the firm culture 
and the level of trust within the organisation. Leading man-
agers at logistics firms are aware of the importance of this 
relationship, as well as of the fact that it is important to 
work continuously towards achieving a higher level of trust 
with subordinates. Creating a trusting atmosphere depends 
largely on leadership behaviour, so in the following we pres-
ent the results related to leadership style. 
The development of the atmosphere of trust is primarily 
dependent on the behaviour of the manager, and so in what 
follows we will show the results relating to leadership style. 
Fig. 5 shows the answers of the managers, highlighting the 
four categories which received the most responses. 
According to the greatest number of leaders, the task 
of the leader is to present the problem, search for solutions 
and make decisions (39%), while according to others the 
leader decides and announces the decision (38%). These two 
significantly diverging categories are both present in sig-
nificant proportions in the answers of those in the sample. 
The task of a leader moves along a wide "scale", ranging 
from generating ideas, through reaching decisions, to su-
pervision. Consequently, this makes it difficult to categorise 
leadership style, because it is often dependent on firm size 
and age, as well as tasks and colleagues; it is also related to 
the extent to which the leading manager needs to take an 
active role in individual work processes. 
The other essential factor in the development of trust 
within the firm is job security. 55% of the logistics firms 
asked considered that job turnover is significantly below the 
average for the logistics sector, with 30% being at the sector 
average. Job security is the key to long term success, since 
human nature means that employees work harder and more 
carefully if they see the results of their work, and if they are 
aware of the effect they have on the firm. 
The level of trust related to staff and the commitment of 
employees can be significantly increased by the use of fringe 
benefits. In this sense almost 90% of logistics firms make 
use of a fringe benefit package for their employees. Accident 
insurance and study grants were less popular (present in 
hardly 40% of cases), despite the fact that study grants, for 
example, can support lifelong learning and personal devel-
opment, which can directly increase the competitiveness of 
logistics firms. </p>

<p>In 57% of cases firms have drawn up an organisational 
chart or diagram. A diagram of the firm makes its operations 
more transparent, makes the tasks and responsibilities of 
the staff clearer, reduces conflict situations and reveals the 
weak points within the firm. Of the firms, 54% operate with 
a functional organisational structure, 13% with a linear one, 
9% a divisional one, 2% have a matrix structure, while 23% 
have some other form. 
From a financial perspective, 73% of logistics firms are 
confident that their income will grow in the next 3 years. 
Regarding profits before tax, they are less sure, with 66% 
confident it will grow. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>For firms, trust has a decisive importance. According to 
88% of leading managers at logistics firms, there is a si-
gnificant relationship between the firm culture and the 
level of trust within the organisation. Leading managers 
at logistics firms are aware of the importance of this re-
lationship, as well as of the fact that it is important to work 
continuously towards achieving a higher level of trust with 
subordinates. When Hungarian logistics companies were 
asked how they see other logistics companies, 66% replied 
that they are both competitors and co-operative partners. 
The level of trust in staff determines the direction of the 
firm's profitability, with the trust expressed by the leading 
manager (trust in partners) being indispensable for smooth 
operation and long term existence. We established that in 
relation to client-logistic service provider relationships, the </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Levels of trust within the firm (authors' own research 
2015) </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Leadership style (authors' own research 2015) </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2017, 18: 171-177 </p>

<p>
attempt to work as partners and think together is accom-
panied by more communication and closer cooperation, 
which results in more win-win situations. The quantity of 
communication, good performance, the capacity to meet 
expectations and be at the customer's disposal, and fulfil-
ment of payment obligations all increase the level of trust 
in a partner. When creating a high level of trust partners 
acquire a comprehensive level of knowledge about each 
other's activities and processes. This "specific knowledge" 
(deep knowledge of each other) and the timely provision 
of information results in a high level of flexibility in the 
relationship. As a suggestion, in relation to the search for 
the appropriate size of the firm, by measuring the level of 
trust within the firm (related to staff) and maintaining its 
level (or increasing it further), the leading management of 
the firm can, by ensuring effective, continuous development 
and growth, increase the economic size of service firms. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Supported by the ÚNKP-17-4-III New National Excellence 
Program of the Ministry of Human Capacities. </p>



<p> 
J. Oláh et al. An examination of trust as a strategical factor of success in logistical firms </p>



<p>György KARMAZIN, PhD. In 1991, György Karmazin achieved a degree in Transportation Engineering at the Budapest University 
of Technology, Faculty of Transportation Engineering and in 2001 also at the Budapest University of Technology has successfully 
completed the transport manager -marketing engineer postgraduate training. In 2014 he became the PhD of the Management and 
Business Administration after he successful finished his studies at the St. Stephen's University of Economics and Business Admi-
nistration PhD School. Since 2003 he has been educating at the Pallasz Athéné University different logistics subjects. He is constantly 
publishing and revising in professional journals and yearbooks. He is invited lecturer and organizer of professional conferences. </p>

<p>Mária FARKASNÉ FEKETE PhD, Habil, Professor. She is head of Department of Microeconomics at Szent István University, 
Faculty of Economic and Social Sciences, Gödöllő, Hungary. Her research in applied microeconomics has made important cont-
ributions to understanding problems of sustainable development, competitiveness and efficiency, valuation and management of 
production factors, economic aspects of climate change, land use and renewable energy. She is member of editorial board of several 
international journals and of organizing committee of international conferences. She is also acting as a reviewer. </p>

<p>József POPP, DSc. He is Professor at the University of Debrecen, Faculty of Economics and Business, Institute of Sectoral Economics 
and Methodology, Hungary. He is the head of Károly Ihrig Doctoral School of Management and Business. He has acted as a reviewer 
for several international journals and his research interests includes international agricultural policy analysis, competitiveness, 
rural development, supply chain management and bioenergy. He is also an active member and chairman of several academic and 
professional organisations and regularly conducts professional training seminars for various organisations. </p>

<p>Business: Theory and Practice, 2017, 18: 171-177 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>