<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fjbem.2010.20" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. The investigation carried out by the authors of this paper under "Intelligent 
Cities" (Framework 6 programme) and e-City (Phare PPF) projects helped to identify and 
describe major trends of e-cities development in industrialized countries as well as provid-
ing recommendations for e-Vilnius development. Research included the following four 
stages: comparative description of the e-cities development in developed countries and 
in Vilnius, comparison and contrast of e-cities development in developed countries and 
in Vilnius, development of some of the general recommendations as how to improve the 
efficiency levels for e-Vilnius, submission of particular recommendations for e-Vilnius. 
In order to throw more light on the Model, a more detailed description of some above 
stages follows in the paper. </p>

<p>A fundamental reference in e-cities field are the actions (Europe's Information Society... 
2005a, b etc.) put into effect by the European Union from the year 2000. On that date 
the European Council of Lisbon decided that the EU should aim at turning by the year 
2010 into the most dynamic knowledge-based economy in the world. The aim of eEu-
rope 2005 (Europe's Information … 2005a) is to provide a favourable environment for 
private investment and for the creation of new jobs, to boost productivity, to modernise 
public services, and to give everyone the opportunity to participate in the global infor-
mation society. European Information society in 2010 ("i2010") (Europe's Information 
… 2005b) is an initiative which will provide an integrated approach to information 
society and audio-visual policies in the EU, covering regulation, research, and deploy-
ment and promoting cultural diversity. i2010 objective will be to ensure that Europe's 
citizens, businesses and governments make the best use of ICTs in order to improve </p>



<p>industrial competitiveness, support growth and the creation of jobs and to help address 
key societal challenges. </p>

<p>The world's best scientists are working in these components: intelligent cities (Ko- makech 2005), e-city Europe: status, propositions and opportunities (Paskaleva-Shapira  2007), geographic information e-training (Beconytė et al. 2008), geographic informa-
tion management (Stankevičius et al. 2010), e-Government strategies (Kahraman et  al. 2007; Jakaitis et al. 2009; Kažemikaitienė and Bilevičienė 2008; Limba 2007), e-
Procurement (Vitkauskaitė and Gatautis 2008; Gatautis and Vitkauskaite 2008), e-man-
agement (Davidavičienė 2008), e-commerce (Kaklauskas et al. 2007), e-interoperability 
(Gøtze et al. 2009; Gatautis et al. 2009), local readiness for city e-governance in Europe 
(Paskaleva 2008), citizens' expectations: implications for urban planning and design 
(Curwell et al. 2005), advanced transport management (McQueen et al. 2005), virtual 
trips and transport infrastructure planning (Jauneikaitė and Carreno 2009), virtual spaces 
and collaborative innovation (Komninos et al. 2007), street lamp monitoring and control 
system (Chen and Lin 2009); intelligent systems for real estate (Urbanavičienė et al.  2009a, b), negotiation (Kaklauskas and Urbanavičienė 2005; Kaklauskas et al. 2007), 
pollution and health effect analysis (Zavadskas et al. 2007a, b), international trade (Za- vadskas et al. 2005), regional policy (Damaskopoulos et al. 2008), management of 
water resources (Dzemydiene 2008). </p>

<p>Several examples are described below. The Institute for Prospective Technological 
Studies (IPTS) defines five important thematic trends in ICT research: macroeco-
nomic and social conditions for ICT-based innovations; ICT, organizational changes 
and transformation of work processes; the social dimension of ICT; political instru-
ments related to ICT development. One of the main impacts of ICT is the capacity 
"to move people to the centre". </p>

<p>In this context the European Union declares a possibility "to move every citizen, 
home and school to the digital century; create literate Europe in digital systems 
supported by business culture ready to finance and develop new ideas; ensure that 
the process is socially comprehensive, creating consumer reliance and enforcing 
social cohesion". </p>

<p>This includes efforts like the development of e-learning, e-government, e-health, 
etc. E.g. digital technologies (remote network systems, Internet and mobile tech-
nologies) are used to facilitate the process of decision-making for public institutions, 
improve public policy in local communities and transform relations with citizens, 
business and other public institutions (Gatautis 2008). </p>

<p>The key drivers for enabling eBusiness development are commitment and support of 
industry associations, in particular in sectoral initiatives, synergies by having access 
to resources from other initiatives or organizations, competitive pressure and ease of 
participation. The key barriers slowing ICT adoption are competition among compa-
nies in the target group, Lack of awareness, often combined with mistrust regarding 
ICT and ICT service providers, costs, lack of internal ICT and management knowl-
edge, Network infrastructure issues: access and interoperability, Legal uncertainties. </p>

<p>E. K. Zavadskas et al. Application of e-technologies for regional development: the case of Vilnius city </p>



<p>The European Commission has identified 3 factors that make it difficult for SMEs, in 
particular, to engage more fully with ICT and develop sustainable business practices: 
1) the relatively high costs associated with investments in ICT; 2) the lack of technical 
and managerial skills and; 3) reluctance on the part of SMEs to network with other en-
terprises. The proposed framework summarizes the main policy directions derived from 
the analysis and the key areas of eBusiness support -Business environment, Skills up-
grading, Network infrastructure, Trust infrastructure, Digital products and information 
services, Intangible investments and assets, Information, Government online (Gatautis  and Vitkauskaitė 2009). </p>

<p>Vilnius is the capital of Lithuania and one of the country's oldest cities. The honour of 
founding Vilnius is justly given to Gediminas (a Lithuanian Duke) in the year 1323. 
The capital is listed in the World Heritage Register of UNESCO. The population of 
Vilnius is 700,000. </p>

<p>Vilnius city mayor stated the goals in the area of information society (Vilnius city 
municipality 2005): knowledge society development (to improve education quality ac-
cording to knowledge society requirements; to improve education infrastructure and 
develop and support all-life education and qualification improvement system), economic 
development area (economic environment that supports business and investments; de-
velopment of supportive environment for knowledge economy and formation of knowl-
edge society clusters), innovation development area (environment for innovations and 
cooperation of science, education and business organisations; improvement of commu-
nication and information infrastructure), city council effectiveness area (improvement 
of current and development of new electronic public services to citizens and businesses; 
improvement of Vilnius city council management and operations efficiency). </p>

<p>2. Model for e-cities development </p>

<p>The research's aim was to produce an analytical model for the development of e-Vilnius by 
undertaking a complex analysis of micro, meso and macro environment factors affecting it 
and to present recommendations on increasing its competitive ability (Kaklauskas 2006). </p>

<p>The research was performed by studying the expertise on advanced industrial economies 
and by adapting it to Vilnius by taking into consideration its specific history, develop-
ment level, needs and traditions. </p>

<p>A simulation was undertaken to provide insight into creating an effective environment 
for the e-Vilnius development by choosing rational micro, meso and macro factors. The 
word 'model' implies 'a system of game rules', which the sustainable e-Vilnius develop-
ment could use to its best advantage. This research included the following four stages. </p>

<p>Stage I. Comparative description of the e-cities development in developed countries 
and in Vilnius: a system of criteria characterizing the efficiency of e-cities develop-
ment was determined; based on a system of criteria, a description of the present state 
of e-cities of developed and transitional countries and Vilnius is given in conceptual 
and quantitative forms. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>



<p>Stage II. A comparison and contrast of e-cities development in developed countries and 
in Vilnius includes: identifying the global development trends (general regularities) of 
the e-cities; identifying e-cities differences between developed countries and Vilnius; 
determining pluses and minuses of these differences for Vilnius; determining the best 
practice of e-cities for Vilnius as based on the actual conditions. </p>

<p>Stage III. A development of some of the general recommendations as how to improve 
the efficiency levels for e-Vilnius. </p>

<p>Stage IV. Submission of particular recommendations for e-Vilnius was presented at this 
stage. Each of the general recommendations proposed in the third stage carries several 
particular alternatives. </p>

<p>In order to throw more light on the Model, a more detailed description of some above 
mentioned stages of analysis follows: description of a system of criteria characterizing 
the efficiency of e-cities development, identifying e-Vilnius developmental advantages 
and disadvantages, determining the best practice and some lessons to be learned from 
advanced e-cities. </p>

<p>3. A System of criteria characterizing the efficiency of e-cities development </p>

<p>Micro, meso and macro environments have a direct impact on e-cities development 
opportunities. This may facilitate e-cities development or, on the contrary, may cre-
ate constraints. When drawing up the system of criteria (indicators, indexes) that fully 
describes the e-cities development, it is worthwhile taking into account the suggestions 
of other researchers. </p>

<p>The e-City Index (e-City Network 2005) is a set of tools and processes for measuring 
the e-readiness of a city region, and assisting in the strategic planning of how and where 
Information &amp; Communication Technologies (ICT) could be deployed. In measuring the 
e-readiness of a city region, cities will use the index assessment tools to derive indica-
tors for the various theme dimensions. This process requires data and evidence to be 
accessed which will allow the city to determine its indicator levels. When completed, 
this results in an e-City Index for the city comprising the range of indicators in each 
theme (e-City Network 2005): 
Democracy (use of ICT and digital media tools by citizens to shape city vision, ICT 
• 
based collaboration to influence policy making, one-to-one electronic interaction 
with city government over policy and decision-making, electronic submission of 
opinion to city government, business of the city government available online). 
Services (use of intelligent technologies to improve service delivery, electronic in-
• 
teroperability between city government services, conduct and conclude transactions 
electronically with city government services, downloadable forms/documentation 
on city government services, information on city government services available 
online). 
Procurement (automated and intelligent procurement systems, integrated electronic 
• 
purchasing across multiple city government services, and multiple suppliers, pur-</p>

<p>E. K. Zavadskas et al. Application of e-technologies for regional development: the case of Vilnius city </p>



<p>chasing transactions managed electronically, electronic access to suppliers' data, 
electronic publication of city government purchasing requirements). 
Promotion (use of digital media to virtually experience city characteristics, ICT 
• 
environments to allow sharing of city information and experience, customisable 
electronic interaction with city information and data, electronic promotion of city 
is segmented by target market, city is represented on the WorldWideWeb). </p>

<p>e-City Working Group (Dublin as a... 2001) produced quantitative, qualitative and rating 
assessment for each of the e-Cities (Copenhagen, Dubai, Dublin, London, Singapore, 
Tel Aviv and Washington) studied, on a range of criteria (central and local government 
leadership, infrastructure, labour supply, business building skills and entrepreneurial 
culture, legal and regulatory environment, availability of development and VC capital, 
financial incentives encouraging corporate investment, integration of technology and 
the digital divide). </p>

<p>The purpose of the Framework 5 project INTELCITY (INTELCITY 2002) was the de-
velopment of a research "roadmap". This implies that identifying possible future visions 
and scenarios for the intelligent application of information communication technologies 
will enable cities to become more sustainable and able to map out research paths that 
offer the most potential in assisting society to implement them. Visions of the intel-
ligent city see the potential for ICTs in helping to solve many of the current problems 
in cities, both in terms of the design and redevelopment processes and in terms of their 
operation and use. </p>

<p>The main outcome was 5 alternative visions and scenarios for the city of the future in 
the knowledge society: e-democracy city (social inclusiveness), virtual city (resource 
efficiency), cultural city (preservation of culture and diversity), environmental city (eco-
logical protection) and post-catastrophe-city (resilience). On the basis of these possible 
future perspectives of urban development a large number of other alternative scenarios 
may be framed and forecasted. </p>

<p>These scenarios were analysed on the basis of the following criteria groups (INTEL- CITY 2002): equity, participation, accessibility, decentralized decision-making, safety, 
education, non-complexity, cultural heritage, population density, age distribution, mi-
gration, employment, globalization, distribution equity, allocative efficiency, optimiza-
tion of use of resources, environment aesthetics, health situation, compact city design, 
multifunctionality, integration of technologies, degree of innovation, security of data, 
decision support systems, real time simulation, nD modelling and simulation, ICT domi-
nation, accessibility of technologies and information, information richness, technology 
awareness and societal integration of technologies. </p>

<p>In Framework Project 6 "Intelligent Cities" (Intelligent Cities project 2005) these and 
other scenarios were further analysed. For example, the modern city aims at being a 
"knowledge capital" and depends on education. The educated city should be accessible 
to all its citizens. The criteria describing strengths of the educated city are: Infrastructure 
(pre-school provision, quality schools for all, diversity of educational opportunity (e.g. 
faith schools, specialist colleges), availability of higher education facilities, high pen-</p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>



<p>etration of new technologies enabling learning opportunities), People (culture of learn-
ing, lifelong learning opportunities, the "creative class", a skilled workforce), Business 
(links between education and businesses, good job opportunities), Culture (good public 
libraries and archives, high number of cultural assets, close proximity of educational 
facilities to each other and to cultural assets). </p>

<p>Following the above-mentioned and other criteria systems, the generalized criteria sys-
tem for a thorough description of sustainable development of e-Vilnius was framed. </p>

<p>4. Identifying e-cities developmental advantages and disadvantages </p>

<p>Vilnius varies from the compared cities according to ICT infrastructure, institutional 
arrangements and government policy in ICT field, economic structure and functions, 
social, planning and legislative systems, institutions, traditions and cultures, economic 
performance, immigrant communities and other indicators. </p>

<p>After the analysis of Vilnius and compared cities it was established that Vilnius falls 
behind them according to a number of quantitative and qualitative indicators. Some of 
the indicators are provided below: ICT facilities are not that well developed; low level 
of ICT penetration in such sectors as education, health services, lower-tier municipal 
institutions; a fairly large informal economy; older generation is a much less active user 
of IS services and participant in IS in general; increased "brain drain" of ICT specialists; 
further deepening of IST as a separated, but not integrated into general socio-economic 
discourse field of activity and learning; lack of knowledge of teachers to use ICT in 
education; IST is treated as a separate subject only and not integrated into the learning 
process in general (especially in secondary education); widespread belief in ability to 
solve all problems by administrative measures, disregard to market laws; insufficient 
pace of growth of ICT penetration in to public sector and households; inefficient use of 
EU funds for IST projects; narrow scope of eGovernment services, a lack of detailed 
and sound public policy on the matter; an unstable and fragmented institutional frame-
work for IS policy; a low rank of IS policy in comparison with traditional policies on 
the governmental agenda. </p>

<p>However, Vilnius has several advantages: dynamic development of IST and public inter-
est in IST; new laws to leave behind administrative and intrusive regulation systems and 
to implement rules that support innovations, a variety of services and investments in tel-
ecommunications, data distribution, Internet services, eSignature services; liberalised tel-
ecommunication market; strong competition in mobile telecommunication market and in 
ICT services diminishes costs for end-users and offers new services; comparatively cheap 
education of ICT specialists; diminishing costs for Internet and hardware speed up the 
Internet penetration into households, business and public sector; growing ICT market size 
and value reflects the orientation of industry towards more knowledge-based activities; 
expanding ICT-related sectors (telecommunications, IT industry and services) and increas-
ing level of ICT usage in service sectors; recognized need for expanding eGovernment 
services; private initiatives to support ICT infrastructure; participation in international ICT 
programmes; more efficient methods of e-learning; relatively low profit tax. </p>

<p>E. K. Zavadskas et al. Application of e-technologies for regional development: the case of Vilnius city </p>



<p>5. Determining the best practice and some lessons to be learned from 
advanced e-cities </p>

<p>While implementing projects "Intelligent Cities" (INTELCITY 2002, Intelligent Cities  project 2005), e-City (e-City 2003) and other projects the experience of different cities 
was analysed by the authors of this paper and it helped to determine the best practice 
of e-cities development for Vilnius. In order to throw more light on the best practices, 
a more detailed description of some examples (virtual communities, greater community 
involvement in decision-making of societal decisions, etc.) is as follows. </p>

<p>Virtual communities portals-have proliferated and these are broadly of 2 types: creating 
a virtual space for 'communities of interest'; online access to information and services 
for residents of specific geographical areas. Whilst the former can exist devoid of any 
shared physical space and bring together users who are separated by large distances and 
are never likely to meet, the latter is built on the potential for 'real space and real-time' 
interaction of users. </p>

<p>Its aim is to support users as they live in their cities and communities, enabling deci-
sion-making, providing another access route to services, and a forum for discussion 
(Saragossa towards … 2003). New information technologies must not serve as another 
instrument of social or personal segregation. </p>

<p>On the contrary, its possibilites must be exploited in all its potential to put into practice 
new ways of relationship, virtual communities, spontaneous groups of shared interests, 
forums of debate and participation. </p>

<p>It is necessary to build a virtual city totally interrelated with the physical city and with 
a big density of contents and interactions. And it must be constructed from the acknowl-
edgement that this will be only possible by spreading technological culture to the whole 
of society and creating spaces for the own society to build its own means of expression 
(Saragossa towards … 2003). </p>

<p>In many cities residents living in social housing are able to access a range of services 
electronically, including: information about their tenancy such as rent, reporting repairs 
or booking appointments online, online benefit calculators, paying rates or local taxes, 
rubbish removal, streetlight, pavement or road repairs. Even people without direct ac-
cess to computers can use one-stop-shop call centers that are in turn using technology 
to deliver a range of local services (Saragossa towards … 2003). </p>

<p>The project <rs type="software">E-VOICE</rs> (E-Voice … 2005) intends to concentrate on e-democracy/e-
government in order to try and renew the political information, communication and 
interaction processes between elected politicians, the administration and the citizens -
including young people -on a local and/or regional level at various locations in the 
North Sea Region with the support of the 'new' media (Internet, e-mail, sms, i-mode,  etc.) in combination with the 'old' media (television, radio, (mobile) telephone, news-
papers, etc). Some possible examples are: the organisational development of digital 
office hours -citizens get the opportunity to pose questions to mayor, aldermen and/ 
or council members by e-mail or by direct communication via the Internet and web-</p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>



<p>TV; online townhall (e.g. experimental broadcasts of the yearly local-council budgetary 
meeting); digital debates and online panel discussions for citizens; electronic neighbour-
hood groups (E-Voice … 2005). </p>

<p>As a result of the delegation of various functions to the local districts and the resulting 
increased focus on a flatter, less bureaucratic structure in relation to decision-making 
processes it became necessary to develop new methods for use in local government 
(INTELCITY 2002). </p>

<p>Xie (2003) describes a complex online decision support system, <rs type="software">WebPolis</rs>, in the context 
of eGovernment and eDemocracy. <rs type="software">WebPolis</rs> is designed to facilitate greater community 
involvement in decision-making and offers a series of public communication and commu-
nity application modules useful to local governments through a common online interface 
for users (both citizens and officials). <rs type="software">WebPolis</rs> communication modules include e-mail, 
community newsletters, discussion conferences, online resources metadata harvesting 
and searching engine, and online surveys. <rs type="software">WebPolis</rs> application toolsets contain Decision 
Action Process, Geographic Information Systems databases, landuse suitability analyst, 
infrastructure cost analyst, economic development analyst, and GASB34. </p>

<p>In recent years, there have been growing demands for a more participative approach 
to societal decision-making and a higher level of accountability on the part of politi-
cians and decision-makers. Concurrently, the development of the Internet has provided 
an infrastructure to achieve these ends through substantive e-democracy. e-Democracy 
systems have the potential to draw on developments in decision support systems (DSS), 
involving stakeholders and the public in societal decisions (Niculae and French 2005). </p>

<p>Ballas et al. (2003) demonstrates the potential for linking GIS-based spatial micro-
simulation decision support systems (SDSS) to Virtual Decision-Making Environments 
(VDMEs) to allow local policy makers as well as the general public to explore local 
policy problems and become more involved in the public participation processes. </p>

<p>It will therefore be of interest to local government policy makers and practitioners as 
well as to researchers interested in the prospects of policy simulation models for the 
enhancement of local democracy. </p>

<p>Also some other examples of the best practices were defined: 
Different advanced cities are using new technologies in order to render more ef-
• 
ficient public services and to establish an integral Open Digital Administration 
oriented to the users participation and transparency. 
Estonia's cabinet meetings have only computers on their tables. All ministers and 
• 
their assistants have access to a ministerial chat room for this purpose. This makes 
things work faster (Guardian Unlimited 2005). 
Modern service industries such as ICT are highly concentrated in the central areas 
• 
of regional capitals (Competitive European Cities... 2004). 
The diversification of the local economy of Saragossa through the biggest presence 
• 
of the advanced services and new technologies sector is essential to create skilled 
jobs and to increase productivity in an environment which is more and more com-</p>

<p>E. K. Zavadskas et al. Application of e-technologies for regional development: the case of Vilnius city </p>



<p>petitive and global. To get this, it is necessary to create the objective conditions to 
attract investments and companies of knowledge economy (Saragossa towards … 
2003). 
The free/open source software is reaching in the last years the indisputable rel-
• 
evance in the world of computing (Saragossa towards … 2003). 
Jörgen S. Svensson (The Use of Legal ... 2005) investigates the use of expert sys-
• 
tems as support to street-level bureaucrats in Dutch local social services. The back-
ground is a very high percentage of decisions made by the street-level bureaucrats 
that did not comply with existing laws. 
Also the other experiences of different cities have been analysed (Dublin as a... 
• 
2001): 
Copenhagen e-development revolves around a number of issues: close links have 
• 
been fostered between the technology educational and research institutions and 
the commercial sector, Technology parks, university and enterprise; partnerships, 
incubation centres, training initiatives and incentives are all interacting with the 
other elements of the economy in stimulating innovation and adoption; perhaps, 
to be expected, Copenhagen has been particularly successful in overcoming the 
digital divide. 
Some factors contributing to Singapore's successful development as an e-City are: 
• 
strong government leadership and vision coupled with the ability to drive change 
and deliver on the vision; a legislative framework that facilitates and supports e-com-
merce; financial incentives to encourage inward investment and ICT development 
and training; heavy government and corporate investment in technology and R&amp;D. 
Some factors contributing to Washington DC's successful development as an e-city 
• 
include: strong Government leadership and its commitment to putting all govern-
ment services Online; a legislative framework to facilitate and support e-commerce; 
commitment to training the US workforce for high-tech jobs; availability of R&amp;D 
tax credit for investment in ICT by business and tax breaks for ICT training; wide-
spread public Internet access. </p>

<p>6. Conclusions </p>

<p>The following aspects were analysed in this paper and the conclusions are as follows: 
e-Cities should be well informed of the micro, meso and macro environment levels in 
which they operate; e-Cities analyse the micro, meso and macro environment levels and 
distribute their resources to take advantage of the opportunities and to minimize threats 
to their activities; micro, meso and macro level factors can be optimized; model for 
e-Vilnius development was proposed; some global development trends (general regu-
larities) of the e-cities development were identified; some general and particular recom-
mendations how to improve the efficiency levels for e-Vilnius were developed. </p>

<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>





<p>E. K. Zavadskas et al. Application of e-technologies for regional development: the case of Vilnius city </p>





<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>









<p>Journal of Business Economics and Management, 2010, 11(3): 415-427 </p>

</text></tei>