<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3846%2Fbtp.2011.05" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract. Mystery shopping is a tool often used for evaluation of providing services quality. It is also a tool, which enables to 
examine and evaluate communication skills of employees in order to identify their weakness and define the way of improve-
ment. The reason is that their applied abilities are connected with customer´s total perception of providing services. National 
post operators must learn to listen to their customers through their employees. This process is crucial for the market environ-
ment -it enables to gain customer´s loyalty and trust. In order to ensure higher level of customer oriented behaviour between 
the employees, Slovak Post starts a pilot project called "Mystery Customer". Main goal of the project is to analyze behaviour 
of selected post office personnel towards the mystery customer. The paper also deals with the practical use of mystery shop-
ping in conditions of Slovak Post. </p>

<p>Santrauka. Slaptojo pirkėjo metodas yra priemonė, dažnai naudojama vertinti paslaugų teikimo kokybę. Be to, tai priemo-
nė, kuri leidžia išanalizuoti ir įvertinti darbuotojų bendravimo įgūdžius, nustatyti jų bendravimo silpnąsias vietas ir kartu 
numatyti tobulinimo būdus, siekiant pagerinti vartotojų požiūrį į teikiamas paslaugas. Aplinkos veiksniai lemia šalies pašto 
operatorių pastangas atsižvelgti į vartotojų poreikius, siekiant didinti jų lojalumą. Šia paskirtimi, t. y. siekiant sudaryti sąlygas 
kuo geriau pažinti vartotoją, be to, pagrįsti darbuotojų mokymą, Slovakijos paštas nuo 2000 m. pradėjo įgyvendinti bandomąjį 
projektą "Slaptasis pirkėjas". Projekto tikslas išnagrinėti pašto darbuotojo elgseną slaptojo pirkėjo atžvilgiu. Taigi straipsnyje 
nagrinėjamas slaptojo pirkėjo metodo pritaikymas Slovakijos pašte. </p>

<p>Reikšminiai žodžiai: slaptasis pirkėjas, bendravimo įgūdžiai, vertinimas, kokybė, kriterijai, marketingo tyrimas. </p>

<p>http://www.btp.vgtu.lt/en </p>



<p>R. Jankal, M. Jankalová. Mystery shopping − the tool of employee communication skills evaluation </p>

<p>The problematics of customers and relationship with them, 
their retention, impact on business profitability, factors 
of success on the market, etc. is very large and analysed 
in various ways and also for various sectors (Ginevičius, 
Krivka 2008; Korsakienė, Tvaronavičius, Mačiulis 2008; 
Jasilionienė, Tamošiūnienė 2008; Tamošiūnienė, Jasilionienė 
2007; Žvirelienė, Bučiūnienė 2008). 
One of the determining factors of success on the market 
is high satisfaction and loyalty (retention) of customers 
which is possible to achieve and maintain through the 
loyalty and motivation of employees. This includes their 
identification with company, relationships with sellers, 
suppliers and trading partners. 
Assumption of high satisfaction and loyalty of custo-
mers is the satisfaction with providing services. Factor, 
which affects their satisfaction in great measure mostly by 
services, is the process of service providing linked with the 
proximate contact with service staff. The final impression 
depends on their communication skills which customer 
gets. Possible way how to examine and evaluate commu-
nication skills of employees is to identify their weakness 
and define the way of improvement through the mystery 
shopping. 
Misunderstandings and bad human relations are eviden-
ce of malfunctions in communication. It is always necessary 
to learn the way of appropriate communication. On the 
world markets the contest for customer is performed in all 
spheres of business. One of the basic pillars of management 
work is to know how to communicate (Dicova 2007). 
Through the evaluation of employee communication 
skills we can obtain feedback, i.e. information about the 
work results. Based on this information the employees 
can improve their future work performance and prevent 
the past mistakes, wrong procedures, or duplicity in work 
(Blaškova 2003: 139). 
A fight for a customer is won by the companies that 
realize the task of a serious approach to business suffici-
ently. They are the companies that know their customers, 
they listen to their comments and they try offering them 
the best possible product for their needs. It is extremely 
demanding to achieve this status because success is in an 
unsure element -human behaviour here. The task of ef-
ficient management is -inter alia -to lead this behaviour 
in a correct way within specified ethic principles (Soviar, 
Strišš 2010: 92). </p>

<p>2. What is Mystery Shopping? </p>

<p>Mystery shopping is not marketing research (see Table 1); 
it is the practice of using trained shoppers to anonymously 
evaluate customer service, operations, employee integrity, 
merchandising, and product quality (Michelson 2004: 2; 
Potužak 2007). </p>

<p>Table 1. How mystery shopping is different from marketing 
research (Michelson 2004: 28-29) </p>

<p>Mystery shopping is a "cousin" 
to marketing research (related, 
but not the same) </p>

<p>Mystery shoppers are not real 
customers -they know what 
to evaluate before entering the 
store 
-they may not typically visit 
the store they are evaluating </p>

<p>Marketing research involves 
determining real customer and 
prospect opinions, perceptions, 
needs, and wants 
Mystery shopping should not 
be used alone to determine 
customer satisfaction 
-it can compliment, but not 
replace, satisfaction research </p>

<p>Mystery shopping is typically 
more operational in nature 
than marketing research and 
is most often used for training 
and incentive purposes 
Mystery shopping is not 
predictive of every customer's 
experience 
-unless sufficient samples are 
taken and data analyzed in 
aggregate </p>

<p>Mystery shopping fills in a 
gap of information between 
operations and marketing </p>

<p>The verification is performed using a simulated pur-
chase by trained inspectors who verify the general quality 
of customers´ service at the fictitious order of the goods or 
services (selling processes, technical and social standards of 
a seller, their expert knowledge and professional behaviour) 
as well as general appearance and shopping area layout 
(exterior, interior). 
A trained inspector poses as a client, and following the 
prearranged evaluation criteria, reviews the behaviour of 
workers including the ambience and atmosphere. The data 
and knowledge from mystery shopping can be used for 
enhancing and preventive measures to improve the quality 
of services to retain existing customers and gain the new 
ones (Clark 2008; Toptest 2008). 
The intention of mystery shopping is not to prove the 
workers that they do their work wrongly. The goal is a per-
manent improvement of their attitude to customers and 
professional growth (Toptest 2008). 
Mystery shopping provides companies with a means 
of monitoring service from the consumers' perspective. 
It gives management the ability to be the proverbial "fly 
on the wall". Mystery shopping is used in a wide variety of 
industries such as retail, manufacturing, hospitality (hotels, 
restaurants, resorts), property management, multi-family 
housing, banking/financial, petroleum and c-store, enter-
tainment, travel, utilities, business-to-business, automoti-
ve service, medical care (Michelson 1997; Canning 2008; 
Mallett 2008; Agency of the week 2008; Mystery Shopper 
from … 2008; Putting an end to … 2008; The only mystery 
shopper … 2008). 
For companies in competitive industries where pro-
duct pricing and assortment are no longer unique selling 
propositions, customer service is often the key to success 
or failure. Consider the following well known marketing 
mantras (Michelson 1997, 2004: 3): </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2011, 12(1): 45-49 </p>



<p>-It costs 10x more to get a new customer than to keep 
an existing one; 
-One unhappy customer will tell 10 other people of 
their bad experience with service. These people may then 
tell 10 others, and so on; 
-Why customers leave: 
-69% for poor customer service, 
-13% for poor product quality, 
-9% for competitive reasons, 
-5% for other, 
-3% move away, 
-1% die; 
-"What gets measured, gets done" (Tom Peters). 
The benefits of a mystery shopping program are nume-
rous (Table 2). A well designed program can help train and 
motivate front-line employees. It effectively communicates 
to employees what is most important in serving customers. 
It can be used to measure customer satisfaction along with 
other methods. It is an important competitive tool in mo-
nitoring pricing, promotions and product quality. It can 
be used to identify potential problems before they develop 
into major problems (Michelson 1997). </p>

<p>Table 2. The benefits of a mystery shopping program (Michel-
son 2004: 4-5) </p>

<p>Monitors and measures service 
performance </p>

<p>Supports promotional pro-
grams </p>

<p>Improves customer retention 
Audits pricing &amp; merchandis-
ing compliance </p>

<p>Makes employees aware of 
what is important in serving 
customers </p>

<p>Allows for competitive analyses </p>

<p>Compliments marketing re-
search data </p>

<p>Reinforces positive employee/ 
management actions with 
incentive-based reward systems </p>

<p>Identifies training needs and 
sales opportunities </p>

<p>Provides feedback from front 
line operations </p>

<p>Educational tool for training &amp; 
development </p>

<p>Monitors facility conditions -
asset protection </p>

<p>Ensures positive customer rela-
tionships on the front line </p>

<p>Ensures product/service deliv-
ery quality </p>

<p>Enforces employee integrity </p>

<p>3. The History of Mystery Shopping </p>

<p>Mystery shopping started back in the 1940s with finan-
cial institutions. A shopper would enter the banking es-
tablishment, make a cash deposit, and state that a receipt 
was not needed. Observations of how the transaction was 
processed or not processed were made. This type of assi-
gnment is called an integrity assignment and mainly deals 
with the potential act of theft. From this type of assignment, 
mystery shopping has developed into a rather large and </p>

<p>unique industry covering areas from auto repair to fast 
food. In fact, some fast-food restaurants are mystery-shop-
ped three times a day and shoppers are rotated (Newhouse 
2004: 2). 
Mystery shopping got its start as a way to check on em-
ployee integrity and minimize theft primarily in the finan-
cial services industry. In the 1990's, fuelled by the internet, 
the mystery shopping industry experienced rapid growth 
and acceptance. Into the 2000's, the creation of software 
packages such as <rs type="software">SASSIE</rs> and <rs type="software">Prophet</rs> have revolutionized 
the industry (Michelson 1997, 2004: 6). </p>

<p>4. Mystery shopping in conditions of Slovak Post </p>

<p>Endeavour of Slovak Post is customer orientation. All steps 
in the human resources management, organization work 
and also portfolio improvement should be realized for the 
purpose of attracting customers. It is necessary to pay at-
tention to the post offices, which as the contact point of the 
intercourse with the customers, form the concrete image 
of the whole company. The point is that the user of postal 
services should have good feeling by the entry to the post 
office and also by the exit. By providing of services the 
influence on the customer has a lot of effects. One of them 
is compliance of employees to show the interest about the 
customer´s needs and requirements. Important are also 
additional factors which affect the quality of providing ser-
vices: employee behaviour, proficiency, service rate, work 
organization quality at the post office, arrangement and 
cleanness of interior, etc. Slovak Post continually educates 
employees not only in the proficiency, but also about the 
communication with the customers. 
Therefore Slovak Post, for the support of higher level 
of customer awareness between employees with the aim to 
verify the validity of employee training, began from the year 
2000 to apply a pilot project called "Mystery Customer".The 
aim of the project is to find out the behaviour of counter 
employee of selected post office towards the mystery cus-
tomer. From 2002 this project is realized through trained 
employees of University of Žilina. 
Intent of realized evaluation is to perform homogeneous 
methodical procedure of reactions review and behaviour 
of counter employees by the application of experimental 
situations in selected post offices. 
The subject of evaluation is an experimental situation, 
which is realized in the post office between counter em-
ployee and mystery customer. The experimental situation 
is designed and approved by the operations division of 
Slovak Post. 
By performance of measurement particular reviewers 
have an important role. They act as mystery customers 
with intention to determine and evaluate behaviour, ap-
proach and proficiency of counter employees of selected 
post offices. </p>



<p>R. Jankal, M. Jankalová. Mystery shopping − the tool of employee communication skills evaluation </p>

<p>Scenario of experimental situation consists of proficien-
cy requirement addressed from reviewer to counter emplo-
yee, consequently of correct answer, as well as alternative 
of incorrect answer of counter employee. In connection 
with the answer correctness, it also includes the reaction 
of mystery customer oriented to reviewed criteria evalu-
ation -tolerance. 
The evaluation is oriented to verification of four areas 
of postal operations -letters, parcels, financial items and 
third-party activities. Eight scenarios of experimental si-
tuations are realized within each area. 
The main goal is to evaluate the following criteria: 
-verbal communication: 
-greeting (greeting at the beginning and at the end 
of communication -from 2007), 
-proficiency by solving the requirements of mystery 
shopper, 
-tolerance to the customer (till 2007); 
-nonverbal communication: 
-eye contact, 
-facial gestures and voice ton. 
For the evaluation a two-level scale is applied -in the 
case that the counter employee achieves the required stage 
of evaluated criterion, he will receive 1 point, in the reverse 
case he will not receive any point. The results are inscribed 
in reports according to various experimental situations 
and evaluated criteria for the entire Slovak Post and also 
separately for each Regional Postal Centre (RPC). (Internal 
materials of Slovak Post) </p>

<p>4.1. Mystery shopping in conditions of Slovak Post 
in 2005 </p>

<p>The number of realized appraisals was 648. The evaluation 
was realized in 4 stages, from August till November in 204 
selected post offices all over the Slovak Republic. 
Maximal sum of points, which was possible to achieve 
for the whole Slovak Post was 3240 (number of realized 
appraisals (648) x number of evaluated criteria (5)). The 
results of appraisals are presented in the Table 3. </p>

<p>Table 3. Total results of mystery shopping project (Internal 
materials of Slovak Post 2005) </p>

<p>Results 
Sum of points 
% </p>

<p>Maximal sum of points 
3 240 
100.00 </p>

<p>Sum of attained points 
2 604 
80.37 </p>

<p>Sum of zero points 
636 
19.63 </p>

<p>Results of the project realized in 2005 (Table 4) showed 
that the most problematic area by the appraisal of employees 
of Slovak Post was proficiency, analogous to the year 2004. </p>

<p>Substantial inter-annual difference is evident by the 
criterion -greeting. Reason for decrease in this criterion 
was the change in the evaluation methodology. In 2005 it 
was approved by the methodology that the assigning of the 
point to the counter employee will occur in the case, that he 
greeted (spoke to) customer first. Mentioned change resul-
ted from the need to synchronize the system of employees' 
evaluation with the Behaviour standards of employees -
published on the intranet of Slovak Post. 
In the year 2007 this criterion was split into two -gre-
eting at the beginning and greeting at the end of commu-
nication. The tolerance criterion was eliminated from the 
evaluation, as it was very difficult to evaluate it objectively. 
The total results of the appraisal in 2007 are presented in 
Table 5. </p>

<p>Table 4. Results of evaluated criteria by mystery shopping 
project (Internal materials of Slovak Post 2004, 2005, 2007) </p>

<p>Evaluated criteria 
2004 (%) 2005 (%) 2007 (%) </p>

<p>Eye contact 
96.30 
93.06 
97.60 </p>

<p>Facial gestures and voice ton 
95.06 
93.52 
96.53 </p>

<p>Greeting 
76.85 
67.75 
-</p>

<p>Greeting at the beginning 
-
-
73.47 </p>

<p>Greeting at the end 
-
-
55.47 </p>

<p>Proficiency 
50.46 
51.85 
69.33 </p>

<p>Tolerance 
95.52 
95.68 
-</p>

<p>Table 5. Total results of mystery shopping project (Internal 
materials of Slovak Post 2007) </p>

<p>Results 
% </p>

<p>Sum of attained points 
78.48 </p>

<p>Sum of zero points 
21.52 </p>

<p>Defects determined by reviewers in verbal and also in 
nonverbal communication are presented and discussed 
with responsible employees of Slovak Post in order to take 
consequent actions and eliminate potential appearance of 
repeated defects in the future. 
In order to evaluate the quality of services provided by 
employees of the post office with consecutive determina-
tion of deviation from the level of provided services in the 
former year, Slovak Post will continue with the realization 
of this project also in the next years (Internal materials of 
Slovak Post 2007). </p>

<p>5. Conclusion </p>

<p>In market environment it is crucial that national post ope-
rators are sensitive to customers' requirements through 
their emploees in order to retain their loyalty. </p>

<p>Verslas: teorija ir praktika, 2011, 12(1): 45-49 </p>



<p>This art of thinking is also typical of Slovak Post. They 
take high costs for the project realization and also reali-
ze Mystery Shopping several times in the year by trained 
external personnel. 
Slovak Post is trying to improve communication skills 
of their employees in order to improve general impression 
of organisation in the customers' eyes. </p>

<p>Acknowledgement 
This paper has been supported by the grant VEGA 
1/0709/08. </p>



</text></tei>