<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.3138%2Fh400-0370-l1p4-k804" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Cette recherche avait pour objets : 1. de décrire les facteurs qui influencent la collaboration entre les 
intervenants venant de différentes disciplines en santé mentale ; 2. d'expliquer l'association de différents 
intervenants dans des modèles existants d'offre de soins en partenariat ; et 3. de concevoir un cadre théorique 
pour mieux comprendre les facteurs qui facilitent et ceux qui entravent l'offre de soins en partenariat par 
des intervenants de diverses disciplines, et ce, en utilisant le cas de l'Ontario comme exemple. Pour établir 
les facteurs importants pour le développement, en santé mentale, des soins offerts en partenariat par des 
intervenants de diverses disciplines, nous avons puisé dans la littérature existante sur le sujet (travaux 
universitaires et rapports traitant de politiques publiques), et nous avons réalisé des entrevues en profondeur 
avec des personnes clés travaillant en médecine familiale, en psychiatrie, en psychologie, en travail social et 
en soins infirmiers. </p>

<p>The purpose of this research was (i) to describe the factors that affect collaboration among mental health 
service providers of different disciplines, (ii) to understand the mix of providers in existing collaborative 
care models, and (iii) to develop a framework to better understand the barriers and facilitators to 
interdisciplinary collaborative mental health delivery using Ontario as a case example. We draw upon the 
academic and policy literature and in-depth interviews with key informants from the disciplines of family 
medicine, psychiatry, psychology, social work, and nursing to identify factors that are important to the 
successful development of interdisciplinary collaborative mental health care. </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>amily physicians have always provided a sub-
stantial proportion of mental health services in 
Canada and this proportion has grown in recent years 
(Arboleda-Flórez and Saraceno 2001). Long waits 
to see specialists and shortages of psychiatrists and 
family physicians (Goel et al. 1996; Pitblado and 
Pong 1999; Pare and Gilbert 2004) have placed pres-
sure on practising family physicians, especially 
when treating more complex cases. Increasingly, 
family physicians have indicated their need for sup-
port from mental health professionals in mental 
health service delivery (Craven et al. 1997). In 1997, 
the Canadian Psychiatric Association and the Col-
lege of Family Physicians of Canada issued a joint 
paper stressing the need for improved communica-
tion between family physicians and psychiatrists 
entitled, "Shared Mental Health Care in Canada." 
They challenged physicians and policymakers to fa-
cilitate the expansion of shared mental health care 
(Kates and Ackerman 2002). </p>

<p>A number of models of "shared" or "collabora-
tive" mental health delivery have emerged in recent 
years. What sets collaborative care apart from tra-
ditional approaches is that the family physician and 
psychiatrist or other mental health professional are 
concurrently involved in the patient's treatment, 
often using a team approach, with the family physi-
cian remaining the ongoing health-care provider 
(Kates and Ackerman 2002; Craven and Bland 
2002). According to the Canadian Collaborative 
Mental Health Initiative (CCMHI): </p>

<p>Collaborative mental health care is a concept that 
emphasizes opportunities to strengthen the acces-
sibility and delivery of mental health services in 
primary care settings through interdisciplinary 
collaboration. It is not a fixed model or specific 
approach (Gagné 2005, 5). </p>

<p>Increasingly, there are calls to widen the array of 
disciplines in the collaborative care team (Craven </p>

<p>and Bland 2002; Canadian Mental Health Associa-
tion 2003). The best-practice literature indicates 
psychotropic medications and psychotherapy should 
be used alone or in combination according to pa-
tient needs (Dewa et al. 2000; Ontario Medical 
Association 2001). Only physicians have prescrib-
ing rights in Canada, but other mental health 
providers (e.g., nurses, social workers, and psy-
chologists) can offer psychotherapy and counselling 
support. 1 The Canadian Mental Health Association 
in its brief to the Standing Senate Committee on 
Social Affairs, Science and Technology, which stud-
ied mental illness and mental health care in Canada 
(Kirby 2005), called for a national mental health 
human resources plan and recommended "interdis-
ciplinary linkages between physicians and 
psychologists, nurses, social workers, occupational 
therapists and addiction counselors" (Canadian 
Mental Health Association 2003, 22). </p>

<p>Models that promise improved access and qual-
ity of care using existing health human resources 
are particularly appealing to policymakers who face 
budget constraints and long lead times to develop 
additional health human resources. From a political 
perspective, there are encouraging prospects for 
expanding interdisciplinary collaborative care mod-
els at both the federal and provincial levels in 
Canada. The First Minister's Accord on Health Care 
Renewal (Health Canada 2003) provided transitional 
funding for primary care renewal that led to a number 
of interdisciplinary collaborative mental health-care 
pilot projects. 2 More recently, the Kirby Commission 
recommended the creation of a Canadian Mental 
Health Commission to advance mental health reforms 
in Canada, including expansion of collaborative care 
(Kirby 2005). In Ontario, the government's ongoing 
Transformation Agenda (Ontario. Ministry of Health 
and Long-Term Care 2006) includes the development 
of interdisciplinary primary health-care delivery teams, 
which present an opportunity to integrate interdisci-
plinary mental health-care providers into developing 
Family Health Teams (FHTs) (Ontario. Ministry of 
Health and Long-Term Care 2004). </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S51 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>It must be recognized, however, that traditional 
solo physician-based practice has a long tradition 
in Canada and that changing health-service deliv-
ery models and altering the mix of providers is not 
simply a matter of rearranging headcounts of pro-
fessionals and the settings in which they practise. If 
these models are to succeed, careful attention must 
be given to understanding (i) traditional barriers to 
their advancement, (ii) the prospects for develop-
ing interdisciplinary models within the context of 
existing barriers, and (iii) necessary policy reform 
over the longer term to remove those barriers. </p>

<p>The purpose of this research was (i) to describe 
the factors that affect collaboration among mental 
health service providers of different disciplines, 
(ii) to understand the mix of providers in existing 
collaborative care models, and (iii) to develop a 
framework to better understand the barriers and 
facilitators to interdisciplinary collaborative men-
tal health delivery. Ontario was selected as a case 
study because many of the early collaborative men-
tal health-care models were developed in the 
province, in part due to impetus from the Hamilton 
HSO Mental Health and Nutrition Program (Kates 
and Ackerman 2002), one of the first such programs. </p>

<p>PRIMARY MENTAL HEALTH-CARE DELIVERY 
IN ONTARIO </p>

<p>There has been rapid growth in primary mental 
health-care delivery in Ontario in recent years. The 
percentage of patients requiring mental health serv-
ices rose by 13 percent between 1992 and 1998, 
while overall growth in health-care users was 4 per-
cent (Arboleda-Flórez and Saraceno 2001). Family 
physicians are the main point of access and major 
providers of mental health-care services. Based on 
OHIP billing data, in 1997/98, most mental health-
care users (63 percent) received care from a general 
practitioner or family physician only; 22 percent saw 
a psychiatrist only; and 12 percent saw both (Lin 
and Goering 2000). </p>

<p>Family physicians need backup from mental health 
professionals for more challenging cases and "are of-
ten concerned about the patient's access to appropriate 
care once they require care outside the physician's level 
of expertise" (Ontario. Ministry of Health and Long-
Term Care 2001). They are concerned about having 
adequate time to deal with patients requiring psycho-
therapy and detailed assessments in a busy practice. 
Shortages of psychiatrists magnify these concerns in 
rural areas. While 15 percent of the population lives 
outside urban areas (Statistics Canada 2002), only 
about 2 percent of psychiatrists reside in these areas 
(Canadian Psychological Association 1999; Craven 
and Bland 2002). Northern regions also face longer 
wait times, greater distance for referral, and provider 
isolation (Commission on the Future of Health Care 
in Canada 2002; Pong and Russell 2003). </p>

<p>From the perspective of health human resources, 
there may be other providers available who could 
provide services or support family physicians in 
supplying mental health care. It has long been rec-
ognized that there are many potential providers of 
counselling and psychotherapy services, such as 
family doctors, psychologists, nurses, social work-
ers, and occupational therapists (Dewa et al. 2000). 
In its review of Ontario's health system in 1970, the 
Committee on the Healing Arts stated that: "Psy-
chodiagnosis and psychotherapy are two major 
functions of psychiatrists that can, in principle be 
shared with other senior mental health profession-
als, such as clinical psychologists and psychiatric 
social workers" (Hanly 1970, 98). </p>

<p>Even though there are only a modest number of 
collaborative care programs in the province, there 
is widespread interest in further development of pro-
grams. Existing models typically include 
psychiatrists, family physicians, social workers, and 
nurses. Very few include psychologists. Our study 
helps to illuminate the various contextual factors that 
have affected the numbers of programs in existence 
in the province and their human resources compo-
sition from different disciplines. </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S52 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>A multi-method, though largely qualitative, policy 
analysis approach was used in this study. Data 
sources included primary and secondary source lit-
erature pertaining to primary care renewal and 
collaborative mental health care in Ontario and a 
series of key informant interviews. </p>

<p>The published academic literature (i.e., second-
ary source) on collaborative (or shared) mental 
health care and the gray literature (i.e., primary 
source policy documents, reports by various 
stakeholder groups) from 1980 to 2005 were re-
viewed. Various databases, including Pubmed and 
Ingenta were searched to locate key secondary 
sources. Keywords included: mental health services, 
collaboration, collaborative care, integrated serv-
ices, interprofessional relations, multidisciplinary, 
shared care, organized delivery services, teams, fam-
ily medicine, primary care, professional barriers, and 
professional roles. Stakeholder groups targeted for 
primary source documents included the Canadian 
Psychological Association, Canadian Psychiatric 
Association, Ontario Medical Association, Canadian 
Collaborative Mental Health Initiative, Canadian 
Mental Health Association, Ontario Psychological 
Association, Centre for Addiction and Mental 
Health, Ontario College of Family Physicians, On-
tario Federation of Community Mental Health and 
Addiction Programs, General Practice Psycho-
therapy Association, and College of Physicians and 
Surgeons of Ontario. Submissions to the Romanow 
and Kirby Commissions were reviewed, as were 
mental health policy documents of the Ministry of 
Health and Long-Term Care, and reports of the On-
tario Mental Health Implementation Task Forces. 3 </p>

<p>The document review served as a basis for un-
derstanding the policy context, identifying existing 
programs for initial sampling of interview partici-
pants, and developing the initial interview guides. 
The literature was revisited following the analysis 
of key themes in the interviews to confirm and ex-</p>

<p>pand more fully on some of the factors raised by 
the key informants. </p>

<p>Interviews were conducted with 12 key inform-
ants (KI) to explore their views on factors that affect 
multidisciplinary collaboration in mental health 
service delivery. 4 Participants were selected through 
purposive sampling, with a maximum variation sam-
pling strategy in terms of provider discipline 
(psychiatry, family medicine, nursing, psychology, 
and social work), setting of service delivery (which 
affects funding and remuneration and public versus 
private payment), professional role, service-delivery 
model (degree of multidisciplinary collaboration), 
and geographic location. Wherever possible, partici-
pants who had experience working in a variety of 
settings and who could comment from a number of 
perspectives were selected. Through snowball sam-
pling, additional informants were added to complete 
the sampling matrix. 5 </p>

<p>All interviews followed a semi-structured guide, 
were conducted by the first author by telephone, and 
took between 45 minutes and an hour and a half. 
The initial interview guide focused on how geogra-
phy and economic issues identified in the literature 
(e.g., differences in insurance coverage, remunera-
tion, and funding streams across disciplines) could 
act as barriers to collaboration. With each progres-
sive interview, the guide was used more flexibly, 
because its open-ended nature enabled the respond-
ents to identify numerous other factors that were also 
critical for interdisciplinary collaboration. The in-
terviews were recorded on audiotape and transcribed 
by a professional transcriber who signed a confi-
dentiality agreement. Ethics approval was obtained 
from the McMaster Research Ethics Board. Partici-
pants had an opportunity to review relevant portions 
of the analysis to ensure their accuracy. </p>

<p>Analysis of the findings was ongoing throughout 
the data-collection period. This allowed emergent 
issues to be probed during subsequent interviews 
and to inform the sampling of additional informants. </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S53 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>Sampling continued until saturation with regard to 
the contextual factors was reached. Each transcript 
was then thoroughly reviewed by the first author to 
reveal common themes. These themes were coded 
using <rs type="software">NVivo</rs> qualitative analysis software. Some of 
the themes were directly related to the interview 
questions and others emerged from the interviews. 
The richness of the diversity of factors raised by 
respondents and their concurrence about the impor-
tance of these factors prompted a return to the 
literature to further assess the salience of these is-
sues. It also led directly to thinking about how to 
place the diversity of factors into a coherent frame-
work that would be helpful to policymakers and 
health-care providers interested in developing suc-
cessful interdisciplinary collaborative mental health-
care programs. The conceptual framework presented </p>

<p>here should be considered a starting point for fur-
ther development. </p>

<p>CONCEPTUAL FRAMEWORK </p>

<p>Figure 1 presents the conceptual framework that 
emerged from this analysis. The meaning of each 
factor within the framework is detailed in Table 1. </p>

<p>The framework is portrayed as a series of con-
centric rings that operate at three levels to determine: 
first, the broadest or global level, which affects all 
programs; second, the local level that affects team 
characteristics within a particular local context; and 
third, individual characteristics within a particular 
team. As we move from the outer to the inner ring, </p>

<p>FIGURE 1 </p>

<p>Factors that Affect the Mix of Health Human Resources and Quality of Collaboration in Interdisciplinary Primary Mental 
Health-Care Delivery </p>

<p>Degree of hierarchy 
-Communication 
-Team vision 
-Professional cultures 
-Practice styles </p>

<p>-Population health needs 
-Geography 
-Provider supply 
-Technology 
-Local health system </p>

<p>-Funding 
-Financing 
-Remuneration </p>

<p>-Scopes of practice 
-Registration requirements 
-Provider accountability 
-Prescription privileges </p>

<p>-Interdisciplinary training 
opportunities </p>

<p>Central Ministry 
Economic </p>

<p>Collaborative 
Mental Health 
Teams 
Mix and Quality </p>

<p>Global Factors </p>

<p>Local Factors </p>

<p>Within Team </p>

<p>Regulatory and Legal </p>

<p>LHIN/Regional Authority </p>

<p>FHT </p>

<p>Education and Training </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S54 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>TABLE 1 </p>

<p>Meaning of the Various Contextual Factors </p>

<p>Global Factors 
Factors that Operate Across all Programs </p>

<p>Economic Factors 
Funding 
• stability and level of funding for interdisciplinary collaborative 
mental health-care delivery 
Remuneration 
• variation in how providers are paid within and across disciplines 
• lack of remuneration for non-patient contact activities that 
promote collaboration within traditional fee-for-service payment 
Limits on public payment 
• lack of insurance coverage for non-physician providers in the 
private practice primary care setting </p>

<p>Regulatory and Legal Factors 
Education requirements 
• differences in education levels required for professional registra-
tion by discipline 
Overlapping scopes of practice 
• overlapping scopes of practice can cause friction across providers 
within the team 
• overlapping scopes of practice can allow substitution of profes-
sionals with different training within a team to meet local needs 
Prescription privileges 
• legal restriction of prescribing rights to physicians can alienate 
some providers from collaborative care arrangements (e.g., 
psychologists) 
Issues in provider accountability 
• compatibility of provider insurance across disciplines 
• comfort with delegating most responsible provider authority </p>

<p>Education and Training 
Interdisciplinary learning 
• opportunities though collaborative care residency placements 
• teaching within an interdisciplinary environment 
• team-based learning approaches </p>

<p>Local Factors 
Factors that Apply when Setting up a Program in the Local Context </p>

<p>Population health needs 
• demographic, cultural, and health needs of the local population 
Provider supply 
• availability of mental health providers of different disciplines who 
can address population health needs within a collaborative mental 
health team 
Existing local health system 
• recognition that the team must fit within the existing mix of 
services to meet gaps in service delivery, and provide an effective 
continuum of care across settings 
Geography 
• recognition of the role of geography (i.e., distance to travel, 
provider shortages) in developing in-house interdisciplinary 
collaborative teams 
Technology 
• opportunities to overcome distance barriers through use of 
technological infrastructure. For example, through 
teleconferencing to deliver tele-mental health by remote special-
ists who are part of the multidisciplinary team </p>

<p>... continued </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S55 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>the scope of influence of factors narrows from the 
whole province, to a local area, to a particular team. 
Together the factors determine the mix of mental 
health human resources and quality of collaboration 
in a program, as shown in the circle at the centre. </p>

<p>Each level corresponds to a particular level of 
decision-making authority in the proposed reorgan-
ized health-care system in Ontario. The global level 
corresponds to the central ministry, which is to be 
the steward of the overall health-care system, the 
local level corresponds to decision-making at the 
Local Health Integration Network (LHIN) level, and 
the within team corresponds to the FHT level. Simi-
lar divisions of responsibility between the central 
ministry, regional authority, and individual service 
delivery teams exist in other provinces. </p>

<p>The global factors include economic factors such 
as funding, remuneration, and public payment; le-</p>

<p>gal and regulatory factors, such as standards for pro-
fessional registration, overlapping scopes of 
professional practice, and prescribing rights; and op-
portunities to learn collaborative practice and 
team-based approaches through education and train-
ing. These global factors set the "rules" in terms of 
how interdisciplinary teams can be established, and 
also affect the practice style and culture of different 
health disciplines and their willingness and ability 
to work together collaboratively. As such they can 
be expected to operate across all interdisciplinary 
collaborative programs. They are potentially ame-
nable to change, with leadership at the central 
ministry level. </p>

<p>The local factors affect a particular program or 
population being served. From an analytical perspec-
tive they can be considered fixed in the short term 
and so must be taken into account when trying to 
set up a collaborative care program at the local level. </p>

<p>Within Team Factors 
Factors that Affect Quality of Collaboration Within Teams </p>

<p>Degree of hierarchy 
• the degree to which a traditional hierarchical approach across 
disciplines is adopted versus a team-based approach where all 
disciplines are equally valued for their different contributions 
Professional cultures and practice styles 
• degree to which differences in professional cultures and practice 
styles are recognized within the team and adjustments made to 
respect differing needs and expectations 
Team vision 
• the extent to which there is a team vision, typically with the needs 
of the patient at the centre of this vision 
Communication 
• formal and informal methods of communication among team 
members ranging from: 
• informal team meetings 
• case conferencing 
• joint education sessions 
• hallway consultations and interactions 
• regularly scheduled meetings of all team members 
• use of technology to support communication (e.g., electronic 
patient management and health records, correspondence by 
e-mail, etc.) </p>

<p>TABLE 1 </p>

<p>(continued) </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S56 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>For example, it is important to consider: the char-
acteristics (demographic, cultural, health status) of 
the population to be served by the program; how 
the program will fit within the structure of the ex-
isting local health-care system; the local supply and 
availability of providers with the necessary competen-
cies; and geographic distance to care as well as 
available useful technologies (e.g., telementalhealth). 
Ontario's proposed Local Health Integration Networks 
(LHINs) and regional authorities in other provinces 
will be important to policy development at this level. </p>

<p>The within-team factors include the degree of 
hierarchy among team members, the extent to which 
a team vision exists, communication among team 
members, and interdisciplinary tensions due to dif-
ferences in professional culture and practice style. 
These affect the quality of collaboration in a team. </p>

<p>The large arrow indicates that there are also 
important interactions among the factors. Remunera-
tion, scope of practice and education, and training 
at the global level can indirectly affect the within-
team factors, such as degree of hierarchy and 
communication. Interactions can also occur between 
factors within a level (e.g., effective provider sup-
ply at the local level can depend on geographic 
factors and the technology used to overcome them) 
or across levels (e.g., even when there is a supply of 
all the needed providers, programs may be restricted 
to physicians, because of lack of funding for non-
physician providers). </p>

<p>Each factor is discussed more fully in the fol-
lowing sections. </p>

<p>GLOBAL FACTORS </p>

<p>Economic, regulatory and legal, and education and 
training factors are expected to directly influence 
the mix of health human resources in delivery teams 
and to indirectly affect the quality of collaboration 
within a team in all collaborative care programs in 
the province. </p>

<p>Economic Factors </p>

<p>Funding. Funding was the most frequently men-
tioned barrier. Here, funding refers to the ability to 
pay for non-physician providers, such as nurses, 
psychologists, and social workers within a primary 
care setting where physicians are typically paid fee-
for-service (FFS) and funded through the Ontario 
Health Insurance Program (OHIP). </p>

<p>You can always bill fee-for-service, but you can't 
find the same funding to support a counselor. 
(KI 10) </p>

<p>Creative approaches were often adopted to include 
these providers in collaborative care programs. For 
example, funding could be diverted from another 
program in the hospital and justified as a way to 
ease long waiting lists for outpatient care. </p>

<p>We'll divert funding from the outpatient depart-
ment to fund this particular program. I would say 
almost universally that's what happens. (KI 1) </p>

<p>Alternatively, a collaborative care program could be 
established as a demonstration research project, 
which would secure funds for non-physician care 
providers. The challenge with diverting funds from 
existing programs or with research-based funding 
is the stability over the long term. This was an issue 
for collaborative mental health demonstration 
projects funded through the primary care transition 
fund, which officially ended in September 2006. </p>

<p>Remuneration. Provider remuneration affects pros-
pects for collaborative practice in a number of ways. 
Lack of physician remuneration through OHIP for 
collaborative activities such as case-conferencing 
and team meetings that did not involve direct pa-
tient contact (Dewa, Hoch and Goering 2001; Craven 
and Bland 2002) was frequently raised. </p>

<p>They [physicians] can't bill OHIP for case con-
sultation … They can only bill OHIP when 
they're eyeball to eyeball with the client…. So if 
all you're buying is direct service and you're not </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S57 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>willing to pay for consultation or anything else…. 
They're not going to feel like they're part of the 
team. (KI 7) </p>

<p>Differences in remuneration of team members can 
also create different incentives that can be an obsta-
cle to setting up collaborative teams and lead to 
different practice styles that affect the quality of 
collaboration. </p>

<p>In [city name] I worked with docs who were only 
fee-for-service. And their two concerns were (i) 
who is going to pay for the … time? … i.e., when 
I'm talking with you who is going to be paying 
me?… So that was particularly challenging when 
you have a mismatch between a psychiatrist who 
takes salary and a family doc who is fee-for-
service … and (ii) who is going to pay for the 
space? … if the family doc is running essentially 
a business … then part of what he needs to be 
remunerated for … is the space itself. (KI 1) </p>

<p>The fast pace of FFS primary health-care delivery 
can also represent a cultural challenge for psychia-
trists and counselors, who may be accustomed to 
working in an environment where patient contacts 
are routinely scheduled well in advance (e.g., 
weekly, monthly, etc.) (Hall 2005). It can also dis-
courage providers from spending time with patients 
to discuss time-consuming psychosocial issues. </p>

<p>Because the way the OHIP system is set up is 
you bill per unit … So what that does is really 
encourages folks to push them through and not 
spend that extra 15 minutes doing the stuff like 
elaboration of psychosocial issues or something 
like that. (KI 1) </p>

<p>Moving away from FFS toward roster-based or 
blended capitation is seen as more supportive of 
team-based care (Dewa, Hoch and Goering 2001) 
and can combine the best features of each method 
of reimbursement. For example, capitation can cre-
ate incentives to take a team approach to care and 
improve communication between providers, which </p>

<p>are absent in FFS payment, but targeted FFS can 
avoid the incentive to roster only healthier patients 
in a capitated system. By blending features of both 
payment systems, consultative activities can be re-
warded and special incentives can be designed to 
encourage physicians to include more challenging 
patients. </p>

<p>Limits on Public Payment. Non-physician provid-
ers (e.g., psychologists, social workers, and nurses) 
cannot bill OHIP for services provided in private 
practice, which means patients must pay out-of-
pocket for their services. As one of our informants 
noted, </p>

<p>Psychologists are not in the equation because 
they're not in OHIP. (KI 4) </p>

<p>This can effectively exclude non-physician provid-
ers from collaborative care models (in the absence 
of creative funding arrangements) and even discour-
age referrals to these providers by physicians, unless 
the patient has adequate private coverage for their 
services. </p>

<p>Regulatory and Legal Factors </p>

<p>Regulatory and legal (accountability) factors were 
a second set of global factors. In Ontario, the Regu-
lated Health Professions Act (RHPA) regulates the 
activities of 23 health professions, including physi-
cians, nurses, nurse practitioners, and psychologists 
(Health Professions Regulatory Advisory Council 
2006). Social workers are subject to different legis-
lation as a self-regulating profession. Similar 
regulatory packages exist in other provinces, most 
notably British Columbia and Alberta. Regulatory is-
sues raised for collaborative practice included 
differences in requirement for professional registra-
tion across provider groups, overlapping scopes of 
professional practice, prescription privileges and ac-
countability within teams of multiple care providers. </p>

<p>Prescription Privileges. Restrictions on prescribing 
privileges for psychologists and nurse practitioners 
limit the scope of activities these providers can bring </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S58 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>to the collaborative care team. Psychologists could 
support family physicians with more complex cases 
where there is a need for ongoing psychological 
therapy in addition to treatment with medication. 
Nurse practitioners could provide support to a busy 
primary care practice by monitoring medication; 
however, there are virtually no medications for men-
tal illness that they are legally allowed to prescribe. 
This can create tensions and limit the ability to al-
locate activities like medication-monitoring among 
team members. </p>

<p>Nurse practitioners have a lot more autonomy in 
medical terms than social workers have in social 
work terms … the problem with being non-medi-
cal is that you're moving further away from the 
psychiatrist being able to provide advice to some-
one who can do things like administer 
medication.… there's a restrictive number of 
medications they [nurse practitioners] can pre-
scribe. And there's only one medication of all the 
medications for nurse practitioners that resem-
bles a psychiatric drug, and that's lorazepam…. 
No antidepressants. No anti-psychotic. There's 
no medication for the side effects of some of these 
medications. (KI 1) </p>

<p>Scopes of Practice. Overlapping scopes of practice 
enabled through the RHPA can be seen as (i) en-
hancing the ability to establish collaborative care 
teams by allowing substitution of available local 
providers to perform certain activities, and (ii) po-
tentially detracting from the quality of collaboration 
in the team by creating friction among team mem-
bers over boundary issues (Hall 2005). Some may 
feel underutilized, others overutilized; either situa-
tion can lead to a tendency for providers to withdraw 
from full participation in the team (ibid.). </p>

<p>Part of the problem too is that there is some over-
lap between what we [psychologists] provide and 
other professions … Mental health counselling 
is potentially in everybody's scope of practice.… 
But there's a distinction between counselling and 
therapy. Counselling … is more educational ... </p>

<p>more the provision of support. It is not treatment. 
It's psychotherapy, which is a form of treatment 
and requires a different knowledge base; a dif-
ferent set of skills … Psychotherapy is not a 
restricted activity. It is … in essence an unregu-
lated activity except when it is provided by a 
practitioner who happens to be regulated. (KI 3). </p>

<p>In practice, these issues have been worked out in 
existing programs. This may be driven more by ne-
cessity than by an ideal solution. For example, where 
providers are in short supply, there is a kind of creep-
ing increase in scope of practice for available 
providers. </p>

<p>…in northern Ontario for instance … they 
[nurses] tend to take on more … their threshold 
for involving a physician is probably higher just 
because the physicians aren't around than it 
would be in southern Ontario. (KI 1) </p>

<p>Education Requirements for Registration. The 
RHPA requires that a psychologist complete doc-
toral training in order to be registered. For social 
workers a master's degree is the requirement for 
registration. With higher educational requirements 
and a different set of skills, such as psychological 
testing and research skills, psychologists are often 
paid more than social workers and nurses. Many 
informants suggested that the fact that psychologists 
are more expensive than social workers or nurses is 
the most important reason that they are generally 
not included in collaborative care models. </p>

<p>… psychologists … among those who will pro-
vide mental health care … are probably the 
highest paid except for the physicians. (KI 3) </p>

<p>…they get a regulated professional in a nurse or 
a social worker at a cheaper rate than a regulated 
psychologist.… psychologists are generally more 
expensive. (KI 11) </p>

<p>Provider Accountability. Under the RHPA there are 
13 "controlled acts" which can only be performed </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S59 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>by certain regulated health professionals; 12 of these 
can be performed by a physician or may be delegated 
when appropriate to others. When a controlled act 
is delegated, the responsibility remains with the 
physician who authorized it (College of Physicians 
and Surgeons of Ontario 2004): </p>

<p>… the constant concern of physicians is who is 
the most responsible physician … So in the 
shared care context, the reason why you see it's 
physician to physician is because the psychiatrist 
[and family doctor] can negotiate between the two 
of them who is kind of the most responsible at 
any one time … although that's blurry at the best 
of times. But when you bring in a social 
worker…[the psychiatrist] end[s] up carrying the 
responsibility for that, not only for that patient 
but for what that social worker does in certain re-
gards …You're making an even more complex 
relationship in terms of the accountabilities. (KI 1) </p>

<p>Having to work out legal responsibility between 
physician and non-physician providers can be a chal-
lenge to interdisciplinary collaboration. Informants 
suggested that policymakers looking to advance 
interdisciplinary collaborative care need to work out 
the legal framework for responsibility for patient 
care and liability issues when providers are covered 
under different malpractice insurance schemes. </p>

<p>if the remuneration thing and the medical-legal 
concerns are there … physicians being as busy 
as they are, it's just not worth the bother to go 
ahead and try and work through those issues. Now 
it's not to say that they're not "work-throughable." 
But again, who is going to take care of the pa-
tients as they're [physicians] taking the time to 
work through these things. And who is going to 
pay them for the time it's going to take to run 
around doing these more structural, organiza-
tional, administrative type things? (KI 1) </p>

<p>Education and Training </p>

<p>There is an extensive literature on the importance 
of professional education and exposure to collabo-</p>

<p>rative models during training (See Oandasan and 
Barker 2005; Hall and Weaver 2001; Banks and 
Janke 1998; Craven and Bland 2002, ch. 7; McVicar 
et al. 2005). Our informants viewed interdiscipli-
nary education as critical if new graduates are to 
participate in collaborative care models. Continu-
ing education can similarly expose existing 
providers to collaborative modes of health-care 
delivery. </p>

<p>the barriers are principally education…. how we 
pay for things…. and the enculturation process 
that takes place on the way to becoming a pro-
fession. (KI 2) </p>

<p>A respondent described the indirect effect of edu-
cation on quality of collaboration within a team: </p>

<p>… from my own experience, it's been the fact 
that we've had the influx of … some quite pro-
gressive psychiatrists come to this area … that 
has helped a lot…. and these psychiatrists have 
been trained in a different style, a style of col-
laboration…. In other ways of interacting with 
people and interacting with other practitioners 
and also in … just the way they have been taught 
… in collaborative care models … it's more of a 
collegial relationship that is emerging versus a 
sort of top-down relationship. (KI 5) </p>

<p>LOCAL CONTEXTUAL FACTORS </p>

<p>At the local level, population health needs, charac-
teristics of the local health system, the supply of 
providers, and the role of geography and technol-
ogy determine the mix of providers in a collaborative 
mental health-care program. </p>

<p>Population Health Needs </p>

<p>The optimal mix of mental health human resources 
depends on the health needs of the population served 
by the program and on existing services in the area. 
Demographic factors, such as age, gender, culture, and 
health needs of the population must be considered. </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S60 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>Local Health System </p>

<p>Existing services in the local area may present gaps 
in service use and potential opportunities to use ex-
isting resources more effectively. It is important that 
collaborative care programs not be viewed as draw-
ing resources away from existing services. </p>

<p>The idea of having psychiatric backup is great, 
but what has made me very angry about that … 
is that as soon as the collaborative mental health 
thing was instituted … guess what they did? They 
pulled the social workers; they pulled the best of 
them out and put them into selected family doc-
tors' offices thereby making them unavailable to 
me and the fee-for-service docs to utilize. (KI 9) </p>

<p>Provider Supply </p>

<p>The local supply of available providers is critical in 
determining the mix of professionals in a collabora-
tive care model. Although it is difficult to obtain 
comparable estimates of health human resource sup-
ply by region in Ontario (Pitblado and Pong 1999; 
Canadian Institute for Health Information 2004), ear-
lier work suggests that in areas where there are severe 
shortages of psychiatrists, there may be non-physician 
mental health specialists, such as psychologists and 
social workers who could provide backup to family 
physicians (Mulvale and Bourgeault 2005). </p>

<p>Geography </p>

<p>The effective provider supply can also depend to a 
great extent on geography and available technology 
to overcome geographic obstacles to accessing 
specialty care. In an urban setting, for example: </p>

<p>…we have all the secondary and tertiary re-
sources fairly close to hand…. and distances are 
not nearly as great for an individual to come to 
an appointment or to do a home visit or an 
outreach visit. And I think again if we were in a 
rural practice, we'd be doing a lot more treatment 
by phone. (KI 10) </p>

<p>A particular issue for rural collaborative care programs 
is the vulnerability of a specialist leaving the area: </p>

<p>… it was an excellent program which had to re-
ally be put on hold when [the psychiatrist] left … 
there was nobody either with the qualifications 
or interest to take over the program … [as a result] 
we saw an upswing in pressure on those beds and 
even pressure on our outpatient service. (KI 16). </p>

<p>Technology </p>

<p>In many cases, shortages of psychiatrists in rural 
areas and the distance needed to travel to care in 
remote regions have been overcome through "at-a-
distance programs." These include telepsychiatry 
programs which combine teleconferencing with pe-
riodic fly-in/drive-in services of psychiatrists 
(Ontario Psychiatric Outreach Programs 2005; Monier-
Williams 2006), and the Ontario Collaborative Care 
Mentoring Program, which enables family physicians 
to consult with psychiatrists and physician psycho-
therapists in other parts of the province (Rockman et 
al. 2004). These at-a-distance programs require appro-
priate technological infrastructure and alternate 
funding to support their operation. </p>

<p>WITHIN-TEAM FACTORS AFFECTING QUALITY 
OF COLLABORATION </p>

<p>The quality of collaboration within a team depends 
directly on the degree of hierarchy, differences in 
professional cultures and practice styles, effective 
communication, and a vision for teamwork centred 
on patient needs. </p>

<p>Degree of Hierarchy </p>

<p>The traditional hierarchical structure within medi-
cine was seen as an important barrier to effective 
collaboration. Physicians are often trained to take a 
leadership role and may perceive a loss of autonomy 
when working in a team environment (Craven and 
Bland 2002; Hall 2005). This is reinforced by legal 
accountabilities, which may make physicians wary 
of delegating authority to other team members. </p>

<p>I think for most doctors, they would not, well 
some doctors won't give it [decision-making </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S61 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>authority] to anybody. I think they would certainly 
want to make sure it was somebody that they knew 
and knew well, and really trusted. (KI 7) </p>

<p>Moving away from this hierarchy to more peer-to-
peer collaboration was seen as critical: </p>

<p>one of the issues in collaboration is [whether] it 
[is] peer to peer or is it some kind of a hierarchi-
cal thing? Well it's only going to work if it's peer 
to peer. (KI 2) </p>

<p>Two respondents pointed to changes that are begin-
ning to move toward a less hierarchical structure 
when working in interdisciplinary teams. </p>

<p>If you have a psychiatrist come in and she or he 
is a collegial person who values the disciplines 
and you have strong nurses, then you have a re-
ally good collegial give and take. If you have 
somebody who comes in with a slightly more 
patriarchal view, then you shift back to the older, 
more traditional kinds of models. (KI 8) </p>

<p>… there have been some breakthroughs in the last 
couple of years in people being able to actually 
work in teams, number one … I've seen a lot more 
autonomy in how I practice in the community…. 
Some of the decision-making now is coming from 
a different discipline…. It's now happening with 
the other disciplines we work with. (KI 5) </p>

<p>Professional Cultures and Practice Styles </p>

<p>Respondents indicated that professionals must un-
derstand each others' roles and practice styles in 
order to develop a culture of collaboration within 
the team. Disciplines must be recognized for their 
different strengths and approaches. </p>

<p>If you have psychology you tend to have much 
more of an individual look. Your social worker 
tends to have much more of a systemic family, 
broader-based community look. [The] psychiatrist 
brings the medical piece both as a doctor and with 
a specific talented psychiatric level. (KI 7) </p>

<p>Regulatory issues can affect understanding of these 
cultural differences. For example, overlapping 
scopes-of-practice can create tensions across pro-
vider groups and regulations may reinforce cultural 
differences with respect to treatment approaches. </p>

<p>Psychologists are very anti-medication … [it's] 
a reflection of their inability to prescribe. Unless 
you have good working relationship, where 
they're coming from is not the same. (KI 4) </p>

<p>Communication </p>

<p>Without an effective strategy for communication 
among team members, there may be interdiscipli-
nary providers on the team, but not much 
collaboration between them. </p>

<p>… what we discovered was that in some places 
it's [collaboration] not being practised at all. 
People are kind of … lone professionals and 
there's kind of a loose connection with the team. 
And in other areas you've got whole issues of 
power dynamics that need to be addressed … the 
whole issue of people feeling that they had a voice 
and a say in these discussions. (KI 11) </p>

<p>Communication needs to be tailored to what works 
best in each team and may encompass formal and 
informal team meetings, education sessions, and 
electronic health records among other strategies. </p>

<p>Team Vision </p>

<p>What is seen by one respondent as a critical way to 
overcome these differences is to have a strong vi-
sion of what the team is trying to accomplish, which 
is the placement of the patient's needs at the centre 
of that vision. </p>

<p>I think if you have a respectful focus and if you 
have a vision in terms of what you're trying to 
do, people either organize around enemies or they 
organize around a vision. Vision is much more 
difficult. (KI 7) </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>S62 Gillian Mulvale and Ivy Lynn Bourgeault </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>CONCLUDING COMMENTS </p>

<p>A large number of interrelated factors, which oper-
ate at the global, local, and within-team levels, 
influence the development of collaborative mental 
health-care programs. These factors explain the lim-
ited number of programs to date in Ontario and the 
mix of particular disciplines (e.g., the limited role 
of psychology), within existing programs. We 
present a conceptual framework that helps to organ-
ize this wide array of factors that will be useful not 
only in helping direct future research, but also im-
portant in framing policy. </p>

<p>Future research should test the applicability of 
the framework to other jurisdictions and to other 
health conditions. Examples include investigating 
the framework's relevance to collaborative mental 
health initiatives in other provinces, to interdisci-
plinary primary care models more generally, such 
as Ontario's developing FHTs (see Bourgeault and 
Mulvale 2006), and to collaborative maternity-care 
initiatives emanating from the recently completed 
Multidisciplinary Collaborative Primary Maternity 
Care Project. Such applications will also help to 
refine the framework and provide a better under-
standing of the linkages between the factors we have 
identified. Understanding these linkages is neces-
sary if we are to successfully analyze health human 
resource use in collaborative care models and de-
sign programs that foster effective collaboration. </p>

<p>The framework also helps to identify the appro-
priate level of decision-making at which barriers 
need to be addressed. Global factors will be best 
addressed at the level of the central ministry. Local 
level and within-team factors will be best addressed 
at the LHIN and FHT levels respectively in Ontario, 
or regional authority and delivery team levels in 
other provinces. It may require strong political lead-
ership to address cross-jurisdictional level factors 
such as education, training, and regulatory and le-
gal factors. Federal-provincial accords have proven 
to be fruitful opportunities to address cross-</p>

<p>jurisdictional issues and with the leadership of a Ca-
nadian Mental Health Commission (Health Canada 
2005; Kirby 2005), there may be an important op-
portunity to shift national attention to these issues. </p>

<p>This research has been presented to a number of 
conferences and think-tanks, and informally to 
policymakers at the provincial level in Ontario. In-
formal feedback confirms the importance of the 
identified factors to providers and to policymakers 
working to develop interdisciplinary models of men-
tal health delivery in the primary health-care setting. 
For example, in trying to prioritize specific factors 
for study in the next stages of research, a 
decisionmaker responded "We want all of it!" </p>

<p>Future research as suggested above, will enhance 
the usefulness of the framework for policymakers 
interested in setting up a policy context that pro-
motes adoption of interdisiciplinary, collaborative 
models of mental health service delivery. </p>

<p>NOTES </p>

<p>Funding for this research was provided in part through a 
CIHR New Investigator Award to Ivy Lynn Bourgeault 
and in part through an Ontario Training Centre in Health 
Services and Policy Research stipend to Gillian Mulvale. 
Helpful feedback on previous versions of this paper were 
also provided by Jerry Hurley, Paula Goering, Julia 
Abelson, and various attendees at two Canadian collabo-
rative mental health-care conferences. </p>

<p>1 Note that nurse practitioners have only limited pre-
scribing authority in this area. They are able to prescribe 
anti-anxiety medications, but not antidepressants nor anti-
psychotics. </p>

<p>2 Such funding was used to establish the Canadian 
Collaborative Mental Health Initiative (CCMHI) in March 
2004, with the goal of enhancing mental health services 
in primary health care through furthering research, de-
veloping implementation toolkits for patients, providers 
and policymakers, and developing a national charter for 
collaborative mental health care. </p>

<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

<p>Finding the Right Mix S63 </p>

<p>CANADIAN PUBLIC POLICY -ANALYSE DE POLITIQUES, VOL. XXXIII, SUPPLEMENT/NUMÉRO SPÉCIAL 2007 </p>

<p>3 For a listing of policy documents reviewed see Ap-
pendix B of Mulvale (2006). </p>

<p>4 Note that these interviews were carried out as part of 
a larger case study that looked at the role of gender and 
location in determining professional roles in primary, 
maternity, and mental health care. The sampling strategy 
for the mental health component of the larger study was 
modified to include providers with experience in collabo-
rative mental health care in various settings to inform this 
analysis. </p>

<p>5 A coding scheme was used to preserve anonymity of 
the key informants. They are identified as (KI n), where 
n refers to the number of the key informant. For a list of 
the characteristics of the key informants in terms of their 
professional disciplines or occupations, their work set-
tings, work roles and experience with collaborative mental 
health care, see Appendix C of Mulvale (2006). </p>



<p>http://utpjournals.press/doi/pdf/10.3138/H400-0370-L1P4-K804 -Friday, March 30, 2018 10:07:01 AM -University of Texas at Austin IP Address:146.6.168.120 </p>

</text></tei>