<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="10.5935%2F0034-7140.20150005" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>We develop a theoretical model for parental behavior regarding land inheri-
tance, accounting for consumption and savings strategies. We identify two 
types of modeling: one with, and another without, strategic behavior. In the 
first model, we assume that children do not act strategically towards their 
parent. We find that the child with the highest return to human capital is more 
likely to receive a larger share of the land if the difference in offspring's returns 
is large. In the second model, we allow for each child to influence parent's 
optimal choice of bequest by providing services to the latter. We illustrate 
that the child's strategy for service provision is sufficient to assure that the 
one providing more assistance will receive a larger share of the bequest in a 
Nash equilibrium. We conclude by illustrating our theoretical model with some 
empirical analysis using longitudinal data for the rural Brazilian Amazon. </p>

<p>Este trabalho apresenta um modelo teórico para o comportamento dos pais em rela-
ção à transferência de seu patrimônio rural para os filhos, levando em conta estraté-
gias de consumo e investimento. Identificamos dois tipos de modelagem, incluindo 
ou não um comportamento estratégico na família. No primeiro modelo, assumimos 
que os filhos não se comportam estrategicamente em relação aos pais. Neste caso, 
mostramos que o filho com o maior retorno em capital humano é mais propenso a re-
ceber uma parcela maior da herança se a diferença nos retornos em capital humano 
entre os irmãos é grande. No segundo modelo, permitimos que cada filho influencie 
a escolha ótima de transferência de herança através do provimento de serviços aos 
pais. Ilustramos, através de uma simulação numérica, que é possível que o filho 
com maior comprometimento com relação à assistência aos pais receberá a maior 
parte da herança em um equilíbrio de Nash, mesmo que tenha um capital humano 
inferior. Concluímos, ilustrando o nosso modelo teórico através de uma análise 
empírica baseada em dados longitudinais coletados na Amazônia rural brasileira. </p>

<p>The study of income transfers within a family is of great interest to the literature on economic demo-
graphy. Private transfers act as a way to improve the well-being of individuals, either by smoothing 
or increasing inequality among family members (Becker &amp; Tomes, 1979; Tomes, 1981). Thus, both the 
amount and the rule of parental investment have intergenerational consequences on wealth accumula-
tion (Keister, 2003). It can also influence the effectiveness of government redistribution depending on 
an agent's motives (Altonji, Hayashi, &amp; Kotlikoff, 1997; Barro, 1974; Cox &amp; Jakubson, 1995; Lee &amp; Ma-
son, 2010). Finally, because family members can enter into a contractual arrangement for mutual risk 
smoothing, private transfers may reduce aggregate market insurance and interest rates (VanWey, 2004). 
In this paper, we focus on how parents transfer wealth to their children, mainly in the form of 
bequests. We assume that children have varying relative skills, yielding different returns to their invest-
ment in land-specific human capital. Parents then value this random return in their decision on how 
much to bequeath. We develop a theoretical model in which agents live for two periods in an environ-
ment where wealth transfers between two consecutive periods are available. In the first period, children 
save to invest in land-specific human capital 1 characterized by specific skills, such as training on how to 
grow perennials or how to raise cattle. In the second period, income from job specialization generates 
returns to the previous investment in land-specific human capital as in Baker and Micelli (2005). 
Our theoretical model also contemplates the situation where children provide services to their pa-
rents. Uncertainty in the first period is a consequence of differences among children's relative abili-
ties. To model this uncertainty, we use the concept of subjective probability as in Savage (1964), which 
consists of assigning a subjective probability distribution for the returns in the second period. These 
probability distributions can differ among children and are of common knowledge within the family. A 
risk-free asset with known return is available at the initial period, which allows parents to save wealth 
for the next period. For the sake of simplicity, we assume that all family members live for two periods 
and that parents transfer a part of the total wealth. Therefore, we assume that parents consume the 
remaining goods by their death, in contrast to Bernheim and Severinov (2003). Without loss of gene-
rality, we suppose that all bequeatable wealth is represented by intended bequests. Finally, we assume 
that children do not invest in the second period, with all surviving to be eligible as heirs. 
In particular, we consider two different approaches. In the first approach, the parent makes transfers 
in the second period and no strategic behavior from the children arises. The lack of strategic behavior 
holds because children do not provide any good or service valued by the parent. As an important result, 
we provide conditions on the primitives of the model to show that the child with the highest subjective 
return to land-specific human capital receives the largest share of total bequest. In the second approach, 
each child may provide a good or service as a way to alter their parents' optimal choice for bequests. 
As in Baker and Micelli (2005), all family members are in a sequential move game in which each child 
strategically chooses to invest in land-specific human capital. Furthermore, the parent strategy consists 
in establishing a sharing rule for the bequest. In contrast to Baker and Micelli (2005), we consider 
that children's consumption 2 directly affects the parent's preference. In addition, the sharing rule for 
the bequeatable wealth is endogenously defined, contrary to Baker and Micelli (2005). We exhibit a 
numerical example showing that the lowest return child can supply additional levels of services to 
compensate for a parent's predisposition to transfer a higher share to the most productive child. 
The literature on transfers usually contemplates two major types of motives: altruistic (Altonji et al., 
1997; Becker, 1974; Becker &amp; Tomes, 1979; McGarry, 1999; Stark &amp; Zhang, 2002) and exchange (Bernheim, 
Shleifer, &amp; Summers, 1985; Chang, 2007). The first approach focuses on how parents use transfers to 
smooth the consumption of needed family members. The second approach considers the transfer as a 
way to induce the behavior of beneficiaries who provide services of interest. Altonji et al. (1997) define </p>

<p>1 Measured in units of the consumption good and represented by the opportunity cost of alternative paid activities. </p>

<p>2 And not only children's land-specific production. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>the economic perfect altruism whether an increase by one dollar in the income of parents actively ma-
king transfers to a child coupled with a one-dollar reduction in that child's income results in the parents' 
increasing their transfer to the child by one dollar. We use a parsimonious definition of altruism by consi-
dering that the parent is altruist when he seeks to smooth offsprings' wealth. The theoretical literature 
on private transfers is majorly in tandem with non-altruistic behavior (Altonji et al., 1997; Baker &amp; Mi-
celli, 2005; Bernheim et al., 1985), although some alternative arguments in favor of indirect altruism 3 
exist (McGarry, 1999; Stark &amp; Zhang, 2002). Empirical literature on transfer motives has provided mi-
xed evidence on both altruistic and strategic behavior (VanWey, 2004). The non-consensual empirical 
support is mainly explained by data quality, sample size in highly demanding asymptotic estimation 
procedures, and the difference in how transfers are measured. 
Baker and Micelli (2005) propose a model of land inheritance based on strategic behavior. Their 
model considers a production function including children's random relative skills and stocks of land-
specific human capital. Differing from typical altruistic models of transfers, parents do not take into 
account the well-being of children. The model considers a simultaneous move game yielding results 
under a Nash equilibrium and does not include wealth transfers over consecutive periods. The authors 
find that children overinvest in land-specific human capital when compared to equal sharing. </p>

<p>2. MOTIVES FOR PRIVATE TRANSFER </p>

<p>The effects of private transfers on the well-being of individuals and their relations to public transfers are 
directly linked to the reasons for why individuals engage in passing on wealth to others within the family. 
In general, there are two major motives for familial transfers: altruism (Altonji et al., 1997; Becker, 1974; 
McGarry, 1999) and exchange motive (Bernheim et al., 1985; Cox, 1987). We describe briefly each one of 
these models and discuss their strengths and limitations. 
The original altruism model (Becker, 1974) assumes that an unselfish individual's utility function 
is directly affected by his/her own consumption level and by the well-being of others cared about by 
this individual. The altruistic individual can adjust his/her behavior if close relatives suffer any change 
in their well-being. The model predicts that altruistic parents try to equalize utility levels across their 
offspring, making the largest transfer to the least well-off child. Moreover, if altruism is operative, it 
should lead to the Ricardian equivalence, crowding out the effect of public transfers (Barro, 1974). 
Under the traditional altruistic models, an increase in a child's pre-transfer income reduces the 
parents' marginal utility of making a transfer to that child. Thus, we expect a negative relationship 
between the incidence of transfers and the recipient's pre-transfer income under the altruism hypothe-
sis. However, Altonji et al. (1997) and McGarry (1999) argue that this relation depends on the kind of 
transfer. Inter vivos transfers should be negatively associated to a child's current income because low-
income children are considered to be liquidity constrained. Bequests, on the other hand, hold weak 
(positive in families who make inter vivos transfers) or no (families making no inter vivos transfers) rela-
tionship with a child's current income. Stark and Zhang (2002) emphasize that the available empirical 
evidence is not in agreement with theoretical predictions. They present a model for parents who are 
equally altruistic towards their children. Their model, however, predicts that parents would actually 
make the largest transfers to the child whose current income or potential earnings is higher. The key 
point is that altruistic parents believe that their children are equally altruistic, and as family members 
are interlinked, indirect transfers between siblings would smooth out direct transfers from parents to 
children. An optimal choice would be to transfer more to the child with the largest earning potential, 
because this child would transfer part of the augmented wealth to the less talented sibling. This result 
holds only if the beneficiary child has a marginal propensity to save sufficiently higher than his/her 
siblings. The authors, however, do not take this fact into account in their theoretical model of transfers. </p>

<p>3 For instance, Stark and Zhang (2002) assume that larger transfers to children with highest earning capability would be compen-
sated by inter-siblings altruistic transfers. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>The exchange motive (Bernheim et al., 1985; Cox, 1987) assumes that parents bequeath as re-payments 
for services provided by their children at some point. They do so by assigning an ex-ante sharing rule 
for bequests, directly caring about some actions taken by their children. This direct care establishes 
the motive for strategic as opposed to nonstrategic influence, as in Becker's rotten kid theorem (Becker, 
1974). The model predicts, for instance, that the child who helped the parents more often (with hou-
sehold chores, companionship, or agricultural tasks) would receive the largest transfer or bequest. The 
transfers profile will be the result of a second best Nash equilibrium among credible beneficiaries in 
situations where there are at least two recipients. Bernheim, Shleifer, and Summers (1986) generalized 
this game problem for more than one period. Chang (2007) presents a similar approach using the Nash 
equilibrium to describe intrahousehold transfers when children provide services for parents. However, 
the author does not consider the case when children's return to human capital is uncertain. Moreover, 
the credible threat of parents in transferring unequal bequests is derived exclusively from altruism and 
not from differences in children's returns to human capital. 
Baker and Micelli (2005) develop a theoretical model of land inheritance showing that the knowledge 
about parents' sharing rules for a bequest affects children's investment in land-specific human capital 
under some assumptions. The authors argue that in the absence of an uncertainty in future wealth and 
of a formal land market, fixed inheritance rules prevent wasteful competition among potential heirs for 
they maximize their investment in land-specific human capital. For example, if the parent decides to 
leave the largest amount of land to the eldest son (primogeniture), he can invest in agricultural training, 
thus boosting his productivity. 
The existence of a formal land market undermines the fixed inheritance rule because the potential 
heir could sell the land if this would yield a greater return than its retention (Baker &amp; Micelli, 2005). This 
behavior is also affected by ecological conditions. More productive land can induce agents to behave in 
a way as when a land market is absent; in this situation, land selling is not an optimal choice (Hrdy &amp; 
Judge, 1993). 
In our study area, there is evidence of a formal land market. VanWey, Guedes, and Dantona (2012) 
suggest a level of change in land ownership due to selling and buying practices, which can affect parent's 
preferences. Furthermore, land quality varies significantly across the region focused on in our analysis. 
Older farmers own land of better quality and closer to a main road, whereas new farmers are pushed to 
worse quality land. This implies differences in land accessibility and soil quality. Empirical evidence by 
Carneiro (2001) corroborates the importance of land quality on parents' behavior towards land division. 
According to the author, farmers in less productive areas practice an equal division of land, whereas 
those in more productive areas follow a fixed unequal division rule. In the next section, we present our 
theoretical model of land inheritance based on the framework of choice under uncertainty. </p>

<p>3. THE MODEL </p>

<p>We propose a theoretical model for bequests based on the notion of uncertainty as in Savage (Savage, 
1964). We assume that parents assign subjective probabilities for the children's returns, anticipating an 
exogenous prior. We develop two different models. In the first (unilateral transfers), the child derives 
utility by his/her own consumption and the transfer received. In the second (bilateral transfers), a service 
is provided by the child to the parent; this service enters both the parent's and the child's objective 
function. </p>

<p>3.1. Unilateral transfers </p>

<p>Suppose that a parent has two children and lives for two periods. In the first period the parent chooses 
optimal consumption and investment. In the second period the parent makes a decision about the </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>amount of wealth to bequeath, consuming the remaining wealth by his/her death 4 . A subjective prior 
established by the parent characterizes the return to each child's land-specific human capital. These 
priors are of common knowledge. This is a sufficient condition to define the expected returns of an 
offspring's investment in land-specific human capital. 5 Consider y = (y p , y j , y k ) and a = (a p , a j , a k ) 
representing the income and optimal investment profile of parent p and the two children, j and k, 
respectively. All agents have the same strictly concave utility function u: R + → R, representing the 
benefit for each consumption level. This implies that agents are risk averse, in contrast to Chang (2007) 
which assumes that siblings are risk neutral. For the sake of simplicity, we assume that there is a single 
numeraire good, that is, the amount of consumption and savings are given in units of this good. 
Write t i as the optimal bequest from the parent to the child i = j, k. The value function of child i 's 
problem is given by </p>

<p>v i (t i ) = max </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>u(c i ) + β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u ((1 + r)a i + t i ) f i (r) dr c i + a i ≤ y i </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>and the corresponding choices given by </p>

<p>(ĉ i (t i ),â i (t i )) = arg max </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>u(c i ) + β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u ((1 + r)a i + t i ) f i (r) dr c i + a i ≤ y i </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>, 
(2) </p>

<p>where f i is the density function inducing the subjective probability of returns and β the intertemporal 
discount rate characterizing the agent's impatience. The parameter β is also related to the marginal 
saving rate 6 . Lemma A.1 in the Appendix shows that v i is strictly concave for i = j, k. 
Consider µ the parameter representing a parent's utility discount relative to the child's utility. A 
risk-free asset with returns r p is available for the parent. The problem of the parent p is given by </p>

<p>v p = max </p>

<p>{ 
u(c p ) + βu </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r p )a p − t j − t k </p>

<p>) 
+ µv j (t j ) + µv k (t k ) </p>

<p>} 
, 
(3) </p>

<p>where the max is evaluated over all (c p , a p , t j , t k ) ∈ R 4 
+ such that c p + a p ≤ y p and t j + t k ≤ (1 + r p )a p . 
In (3), t j and t k represent the transfers for child j and k, respectively. 
This model predicts larger bequests to the child with the highest subjective expected return to land-
specific human capital. This prediction contradicts the altruistic behavior. In order to show this, we 
provide certain conditions on the child's optimal investment strategies and on the densities f j , f k such 
that the child with the highest return must receive the largest transfer. 
To assure this result we establish two assumptions. Assumption 3.1 below assumes that the child 
with the lowest return always invests a strictly positive amount on land-specific human capital under 
the optimal choice. 7 </p>

<p>Assumption 3.1. Letâ j ,â k be given by (2). There exits a constant a k &gt; 0 such thatâ k (t) ≥ a k for all 
t ∈ R + . </p>

<p>4 For the sake of simplicity we use a two-period instead of a three-period model. Ideally, parents should pass on the land after their 
death. In our model, however, they bequeath their goods in the second period. This assumption does not alter our predictions 
and numerical solutions. 
5 The model described in Altonji et al. (1997) contemplates uncertainty on income only, not on the children's return, as is assumed 
in our model. Our assumption allows us to isolate the direct effect of land-specific human capital's return on bequests. This was 
not done by any of the models revised in the literature. 
6 This concept is not considered in the theoretical literature on private transfers. </p>

<p>7 Under this assumption, the more productive child also invest a positive amount because he/she has a higher return than his/her 
sibling. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>Assumption 3.2 states that the expected value of the marginal benefit for the more productive child 
at his/her maximum second period consumption level is still higher than the less productive child's at 
his/her minimum second period consumption level. Thus, even when consumption is at its maximum 
for the more productive child he/she still has a propensity to save, rendering an expected marginal 
benefit higher than the one for his/her sibling. </p>

<p>Assumption 3.2. Consider a k the constant given in Assumption 3.1 and write y = max </p>

<p>{ 
y j , y k </p>

<p>} 
. The 
subjective densities f j , f k satisfy 
∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u 
′ ((1 + r)y + t) f j (r) dr &gt; </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u 
′ ((1 + r)a k + t) f k (r) dr for all t ∈ R + . 
(4) </p>

<p>The following result exhibits certain conditions that favor a non-altruistic behavior. Intuitively, As-
sumption 3.2 assures that child j has higher expected returns. </p>

<p>Theorem 3.3. Suppose Assumptions 3.1 and 3.2. Then, the optimal transfers t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k must satisfy t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j &gt; t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k . </p>

<p>Proof: See appendix. 
□ </p>

<p>3.2. Bilateral transfers </p>

<p>Suppose now that the children provide services to the parent as in Bernheim et al. (1985) and Chang 
(2007). In this case, the environment of friction between family members can be described as a game. 
Children keep private information on some of their own characteristics due to two credible threats of 
the parent. One of those relates to the largest transfer that would be made to the most productive child; 
the other relates to the smoothing of wealth among siblings. We assume that the parent knows his/her 
children's indirect utility, but not their investment strategies in human capital. In this sequential game, 
the parent announces a transfer rule conditional on the level of services provided by each child. Thus, 
each child provides the assistance that maximizes his/her own benefit. This approach is, in essence, 
similar to that adopted by Faith (2001). Faith assumes that parents partition their inheritable wealth 
into inter-vivos gifts and bequests. Siblings may compete to engage in rent-seeking to move wealth 
from the "inter-vivos gifts pool" to the "bequest pool," or vice versa, depending on their relative shares 
in the two pools. 
Consider y = (y p , y j , y k ) and a = (a p , a j , a k ) as the income and optimal investment profile of parent 
p and the two children, j and k, respectively. The amount of consumption and saving is given in units 
of the single good. Write t i as the bequest from the parent to the child i = j, k. This variable may 
depend on the amount of services provided by the child. The variable s i represents the amount of 
service supplied by the child i to the parent measured as an opportunity cost. Children have the same 
concave utility function u i : R 2 
+ → R, with u i (c i , s i ) representing the benefit of a consumption level 
c i and supplied services s i . A representative parent has a concave utility function u p : R 3 
+ → R, with 
u p (c p , s j , s k ) yielding the benefit of a consumption level c p and a profile (s k , s j ) of services received 
from the children. We assume that services generate disutility for the children and utility for the parent, 
that is, ∂ s i u i (c i , s i ) &lt; 0 and ∂ s i u p (c p , s j , s k ) &gt; 0 for i = j, k. As in the previous section, the utility 
defined only for consumption is given by a concave differentiable u: R + → R + . We consider utility 
functions separable on consumption and services, that is, u i (c i , s i ) = u(c i ) + u i (s i ) for i = j, k and 
u p (c p , s j , s k ) = u(c p ) + u p (s j , s k ), u i : R + → R + for i = j, k and u p : R 2 
+ → R + satisfying the Inada 
conditions. A risk-free asset with return r p is available for the parent. 
The value function of child i 's problem is then given by </p>

<p>v i (t i ) = max </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>u i (c i , s i ) + β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u ((1 + r)a i + s i t i ) f i (r) dr c i + a i + s i ≤ y i </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>and the corresponding choices given by </p>

<p>(ĉ i (t i ),â i (t i ),ŝ i (t i )) = arg max </p>

<p>{ </p>

<p>u i (c i , s i ) + β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u ((1 + r)a i + s i t i ) f i (r) dr </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>, 
(6) </p>

<p>where the max operator is chosen over all (c i , a i , s i ) such that c i + a i + s i ≤ y i . 
Consider µ the parameter representing a parent's utility discount relative to the child's utility. Writẽ </p>

<p>u p (c p , a p , s j , s k , t j , t k ) = u p (c p , s j , s k ) + βu </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r p )a p − s j t j − s k t k </p>

<p>) 
+ µv j (t j ) + µv k (t k ) </p>

<p>as the parents' utility function. The parent's problem is given by </p>

<p>v p (s j , s k ) = max </p>

<p>{ũ </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>( 
c p , a p , s j , s k , t j , t k </p>

<p>) ( 
c p , a p , t j , t k </p>

<p>) 
∈ R </p>

<p>4 
+ </p>

<p>} 
(7) </p>

<p>and such that c p + a p ≤ y p and s j t j + s k t k ≤ (1 + r p )a p . The corresponding optimal choice, 
(ĉ 
p (s j , s k ),â p (s j , s k ),t j (s j , s k ),t k (s j , s k ) </p>

<p>) 
, </p>

<p>written asx p (s j , s k ) is given bŷ </p>

<p>x p (s j , s k ) = arg max </p>

<p>{ũ </p>

<p>p </p>

<p>( 
c p , a p , s j , s k , t j , t k </p>

<p>) ( 
c p , a p , t j , t k </p>

<p>) 
∈ R </p>

<p>4 
+ </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>such that c p + a p ≤ y p and s j t j + s k t k ≤ (1 + r p )a p . 
The next theorem characterizes the solution for this case. It will be given as a Nash Equilibrium. Its 
proof is similar to that found in Nash (1951). </p>

<p>Theorem 3.4. There exists a profile of bilateral transfers (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k , s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) such that: </p>

<p>s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j =ŝ j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j ), s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k =ŝ k (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ), t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j =t j (s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ), t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k =t k (s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , s </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ). </p>

<p>3.3. Examples </p>

<p>To illustrate our theoretical model of unequal transfers under uncertainty, we show three numerical 
examples. Examples 3.5 and 3.6 illustrate the model in section 3.1, while Example 3.7 elucidates the 
model in section 3.2. In the first example, children's returns are quite close implying that the parent 
transfers more to the child with the lowest return. In the second example, the difference in children's 
returns to land-specific human capital is very large. In this case, the numerical solution shows that 
the parent transfers a larger share to the more productive child, increasing the aggregate benefit of the 
family. We conclude that parents' altruistic behavior depends on the variability of capital returns among 
their offspring. 
In the next example, we show that when the variability of the children's human capital returns is 
low, the parent behaves altruistically. Intuitively, when children have a low contrast in returns, the 
smoothing effect prevails since the additional benefit obtained with the consumption smoothing is 
greater than the gain obtained by the additional investment in the more productive child. </p>

<p>Example 3.5. Suppose that β = 1/2, y p = y j = y k := y , and µ = 1/2. The probability distributions of 
returns are induced by the densities f j ∼ U [0, 0.6] and f k ∼ U [0, 0.5]. Under these distributions the 
expected values of returns are given by 0.3 and 0.25, respectively. In the case of identical preferences 
with the utility function given by u(c) = y </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>2 − c 2 , the optimal choices and bequests, conditional to some 
specific income level y , are 8 </p>

<p>c j (t j ) = 0.3495t j + 0.5094y 
c k (t k ) = 0.3488t k + 0.4942y </p>

<p>8 All of the following examples were calculated using the software <rs type="software">Mathematica</rs>. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>a j (t j ) = −0.3495t j + 0.4906y 
a k (t k ) = −0.3488t k + 0.5058y </p>

<p>t j = 0.2364y 
t k = 0.2385y </p>

<p>Observe that child k has the lowest expected return on his/her investment and receives the largest 
bequest. In the next example, the variability on returns to human capital is larger enough so that the 
transfers do not favor altruistic parental behavior. </p>

<p>Example 3.6. Suppose that β = 1/2, y p = y j = y k := y , and µ = 1/2. The probability distributions of 
returns are induced by the densities f j ∼ U [0, 1] and f k ∼ U [0, 1/2]. Under these distributions, the 
expected values of returns are given by 0.5 and 0.25, respectively. In the case of identical preferences 
with utility function given by u(c) = y </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>2 − c 2 , the optimal choices and bequests, conditional to some 
specific income level y , are </p>

<p>c j (t j ) = 0.3461t j + 0.5673y 
c k (t k ) = 0.3488t k + 0.4941y </p>

<p>a j (t j ) = −0.3461t j + 0.4326y 
a k (t k ) = −0.3488t k + 0.5058y </p>

<p>t j = 0.2415y 
t k = 0.2356y </p>

<p>Observe that child j has a greater expected return on his/her investment and receives the largest bequest. 
In the last example, children behave strategically by providing services to the parent. </p>

<p>Example 3.7. Suppose that β = 1/2, y p = y j = y k := 5, and µ = 9/10. The utility function of the 
children is identical and given by u(c i ) = 20c i − c </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>i and their utility for services is given by u i (s i ) = −s i 
for i = j, k. The utility function of the parent is given by u(c p ) = 20c p − c 2 
p and his utility for services 
given by u(s j , s k ) = s j + s k . A risk-free asset with return r p = 9/10 is available for the parent. The 
probability distributions of returns are induced by the densities f j ∼ U [0, 1] and f k ∼ U [0, 0.75]. 
Under these distributions, the expected values of returns are given by E[r j ] = 0.5 and E[r k ] = 0.325, 
respectively. In this case, the optimal choices and bequests are </p>

<p>c j (t j ) = 3.909 
c k (t k ) = 4.389 
a j (t j ) = 1.092 
a k (t k ) = 0.611 </p>

<p>s j = 1.474 
s k = 7.994 
t j = 0.122 
t k = 0.122 </p>

<p>Observe that child k has the lowest expected return on his/her land-specific human capital investment 
and receives the largest bequest since t j s j &lt; t k s k . </p>

<p>Note that t j = t k reinforces the result given in Chang (2007). Chang (2007) states that parents 
choose to split their bequests equally between their children, regardless of earnings differentials across 
the children. This behavior can be explained by the fact that rent seeking among children generates 
disutility for the parent. In this case, the loss is not compensated by the return provided by the most 
productive child since the less productive child has incentive to provide services to offset the potential 
reduction of his/her inheritance. </p>

<p>4. EMPIRICAL ANALYSIS </p>

<p>In this section, we employ novel longitudinal data in the rural Brazilian Amazon to explore the relati-
onship between our theoretical model and patterns in land inheritance among smallholders. Because 
of the longitudinal aspect of our data, we are able to compare actual and intended behavioral patterns, 
validating the use of intended bequests in a model where agents live for only two periods. 
The Brazilian civil law regarding inheritance posits that wealth must be divided equally after a pa-
rent's death in case the disposition option is not evoked in the will. At most 25% of the total wealth 
can be used for unequal sharing, which relaxes the legal restriction to equal division of wealth (Pereira, </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>2004). This is important because the intention to bequeath or the actual bequest are not fully enforced 
or determined by law. Furthermore, the study area from where the data was collected is a frontier area 
in the Brazilian Amazon. This location has less direct government and market intervention, which likely 
yields non-standard choices as induced by the general inheritance principle of the law. 
Our approach differs from previous literature on private transfers as in Stiglitz (1969), Becker (1974), 
Bernheim et al. (1985), Altonji et al. (1997), McGarry (1999), Stark and Zhang (2002), and Baker and Micelli 
(2005) in the following aspects. First, we assume that uncertainty will be given on a latent variable 
representing the returns to land-specific human capital, such as agricultural skills; Altonji et al. (1997) 
and McGarry (1999) instead assume uncertainty on the future permanent income. Second, we suppose 
that unequal transfers 9 can be explained by many factors, including endogenous sharing rules for the 
bequeatable wealth, contrasting to the exogenous rules assumed by Altonji et al. (1997) and Baker and 
Micelli (2005). These sharing rules are given as the result of strategic interactions between parents and 
children, with the latter providing services to maximize their share in the bequeatable wealth. There 
are few empirical papers testing behavioral models of private transfers because of a lack of quality data 
(Bernheim et al., 1985; Cox &amp; Rank, 1992; Schoeni, 1997). The few studies that have been performed 
are mostly concentrated in developed countries (Arrondel &amp; Masson, 2006; VanWey &amp; Nelson, 2007). 
Despite its important role on consumption smoothing in developing countries where a social welfare 
system is not fully developed, little is known about patterns of transfers in Latin America (De Vos, 1987) 
and, specially, in Brazil (Carneiro, 2001; Saad, 1988; VanWey &amp; Cebulko, 2007). 
Our empirical results do not support altruistic behavior for bequests in two ways. First, the ma-
jority of intended bequest follows an equal division. Second, most of the significant variables for the 
probability of unequal sharing suggests that parents favor their children with the highest level of land-
specific human capital. The striking prevalence of equal division of land among offspring must be a 
result of strong constraints that arise from the Brazilian legal system of equal inheritance. The lack of 
evidence supporting altruistic behavior for bequests is associated with a developed frontier settlement 
area, where smallholders have strategically consolidated the use of land. In the case of a property speci-
alized in cocoa production, where investment requirements are high and paid back after approximately 
25 years, the child with the best ability to continue the land use strategy should receive the largest share 
of the land. Risk averse landowners would then use the possibility that is opened with the disposition 
criterion in the Brazilian legislation to model their intention. For instance, if a parent has five children 
with one of them best suited for continuing cocoa production, he could transfer 15% for each children 
and additionally 25% to the best suited child. </p>

<p>4.1. Description of the data </p>

<p>We test our model on a government sponsored settlement project in the rural area of Altamira, in the 
state of Pará, Brazil. Our study site comprises a total area of 404.700 hectares, located 740km away 
from Belém, the state capital, crossed by the Xingu River from North to South and by the Transamazon 
Highway from East to West (see Figure 1). 
The rural area under study has some important characteristics that need to be stressed. Altamira 
is a relatively recent settlement frontier area. The Brazilian Government, through its National Institute 
of Colonization and Agrarian Reform, established a grid of small farm units (about 100 hectares) along 
the Transamazon Highway. All of the properties have their front to a road (called Travessão), or to the 
Transamazon Highway, in spite of considerable variation in soil fertility and accessibility during the 
rainy season along the site. The small size units were designed to incentivize family agriculture and 
small scale cattle ranching, although land use specialization has been observed in some farms (Guedes 
et al., 2012; VanWey, D'Antona, &amp; Brondízio, 2007). Land quality and land use specialization may affect </p>

<p>9 The actual transfer is not directly observed. We estimate it by means of the probability of transferring the land unequally as in 
McGarry (1999) and Baker and Micelli (2005). </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>the way the parent evaluates their children's return to land-specific human capital, altering the sharing 
rule for the land. 
The Altamira dataset is part of a larger NIH-funded project, entitled Amazonian Deforestation and the 
Structure of Households (NIH #R01-HD35811-09). The project was led by the Department of Anthropology 
at the University of Indiana in collaboration with the Department of Demography at the State University 
of Campinas, Brazil. Data was first collected in 1997/1998, with a follow-up survey being conducted in 
2005. During the first wave, 402 households on different pieces of land were sampled, being stratified 
by cohorts of settlement 10 . The researchers interviewed the head of the household, the spouse, and any 
other women at the property aged 15 and over. The 2005 follow-up was aimed at three groups present 
in the first wave: a) same couples interviewed in 1997/1998; b) other households located on the same 
piece of land sampled in the first wave, and c) children of the couples interviewed in 1997/1998 who 
were living in their own households in 2005. </p>

<p>4.2. Analytical Samples </p>

<p>In order to understand the behavior of farmers related to land transmission, we analyze the group of 
land owners in 1997/1998 who still held the property title in 2005. We were able to identify what the 
property owners intended to do with the land in the future for both waves of data. 
We divided the observations into two groups: effective bequest (for the former owners who died 
between 1997/1998 and 2005 and for the ones who passed on the land during the period of analysis) 
and intended bequests (the future plan for the land reported in 2005 by those holding the title during the 
period). For the group of deceased farmers, we compare what happened to their land after death with 
their intentions in 1997/1998. We also conducted the same analysis for the children who effectively 
inherited the land sometime between 1997 and 2005. This comparison between effective and intended 
bequest was used to justify behavioral consistency between what is said and what has been done about 
land inheritance in our study area. 
From the 402 farms interviewed in 1997/1998, 399 recorded the farm's owner as the person respon-
sible for the land. In the other three cases, a child was considered the owner. In 2005, 22 out of 399 
former owners had died. From the 377 surviving former owners, 315 still held the property ownership, 
but only 301 of them where interviewed in 2005. 
We developed two models to analyze the land inheritance behavior in the region. The first model 
corresponds to all former owners who held the property title and were interviewed in 2005. This model 
corresponds to the determinants of the intention to pass on the land to the offspring. Approximately 280 
out of 301 owners had valid information about the future plan for the land in the 2005 survey. We had 
to drop one case because of a missing observation on the area of the lot in 1997/1998 and six additional 
cases of households with no children. The final sample used in the study had 273 valid cases. 
The second model analyzes the determinants of intended unequal land division. From the 280 ow-
ners with valid information about the future plans for their land, 180 wanted to pass on the property 
to their offspring. We dropped one unit because of a missing observation on the land size in 1997/1998. 
Eleven more cases were excluded because they consisted of families with less than two children. Ad-
ditional seven cases were eliminated because of an absence of information about children's age and 
education used to create intra-siblings age and schooling variance. We focus on families with at least 
two children, since this is the most interesting setting to study transfers choices. Thus, the final sample 
was restricted to 161 observations. </p>

<p>10 For more details on sampling strategies see VanWey et al. (2007) </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>Figura 1. Altamira Study Site, Legally defined Brazilian Amazon Region. </p>

<p>4.3. Measurement of Dependent Variables </p>

<p>Because we focus on the circumstances under which the land is divided unequally among the offspring, 
our primary dependent variable is the intended sharing rule for the land. In both waves of data, land 
owners where asked about their future plans for the lands they possessed. In the 2005 questionnaire, 
the following options where listed: a) divide equally among children, b) divide among sons, c) divide 
among daughters, d) give to a specific child, e) give somehow to children, and f) other plans. These 
categories were combined to create two different variables: one representing the intention to pass on 
the land in the future, 11 the other representing the unequal sharing rule. To create the first dummy 
variable, categories a) to e) were combined to represent the intention to pass on the land to the children. 
The second dummy variable, representing the intention to divide the land unequally, was created by 
combining categories b) to e) against category a). 12 
An important validation step for our primary dependent variable (intended unequal division) was the 
comparison between reported intentions in 1997/1998 with the actual division observed from 1997/1998 </p>

<p>11 This variable was used to estimate the selection equation, as will be explained later in this section. </p>

<p>12 Category f) was considered incidental truncation. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>and 2005. During this period, some land owners died or decided to pass on the land while still alive. 
As shown in Table 1, in about one-third of the cases for which the owner planned to pass the land to 
their children, the widow was the beneficiary of the transfer. Another one-third of the properties were 
divided equally among offspring. In-depth interviews with the deceased former owners back in 1997 
were used to qualify their future plans before death. Content analysis indicates that the 19 cases (11 
kept by the widow and eight with formal equal division to children) reflected a reported intention of the 
deceased to follow the equal sharing rule. For the three cases where informal equal division prevailed, 
the still living parent continued to reside on the farm. Lastly, for the two cases where informal unequal 
division prevailed, the still living parent moved to an urban area and passed on the land to the male 
children who already dwelt on the farm and had a long history of connection with the land. These 
results support our decision to use the future plan reported by the land owners in 2005 as a consistent 
proxy for actual behavioral decision regarding land inheritance patterns. 
In our analytical sample for the first model (intention to pass on the land), 59% (161) of the owners in 
2005 planned to give the land to their children in the future. Among these 161 cases, 26% (42) declared 
their intention to divide the property unequally. This is a remarkably high share of unequal bequests 
for a setting under a legal system that induces equal sharing. Similar levels of an equal bequest were 
also found in the US in the past (Tomes, 1981). </p>

<p>4.4. Methods and Estimation </p>

<p>We focus on the influence of upward transfers, children's liquidity constraints, and land-specific human 
capital return, as well as the potential of inter-siblings variance on unequal division. Since this model 
is biased because of sample selection, we performed a two-stage estimation model (Greene, 2003). The 
first stage corresponds to the selection equation (intention to pass on the land). Then, we generate the 
Inverse of Mills Ratio and apply it to the model of unequal intended bequest. 
In order to estimate the models, we selected a series of variables derived from the survey. We use 
a woman's reproductive history to generate the children's demographic characteristics. The number of 
offspring was applied in the models to capture how family size affects the motive to transfer. We also 
use the number of sons and daughters separately as well as children's age. The gender division allows 
us to understand gender preferences in land inheritance. Children's age is used as a proxy for the young 
household life-cycle, which represents a liquidity constraint. We also consider occupation and educatio-
nal attainment of the offspring as proxies for land-specific human capital investment. The occupation </p>

<p>Tabela 1. Comparison between effective bequest outcomes in 2005 and original future plan of the old 
owner in 1997/1998 -Altamira Study Area, Pará State, Brazil. </p>

<p>Bequest outcome </p>

<p>Future plan for the land 
reported in 1997/1998 </p>

<p>Widow 
kept 
Equal Division Unequal Division Total </p>

<p>Formal Informal Formal 
Informal </p>

<p>Pass on to children 
11 
8 
3 
3 
2 
27 
Increase the number of properties 
2 
0 
1 
1 
0 
4 
Other 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
Missing 
1 
0 
0 
0 
0 
1 
Total 
15 
8 
4 
4 
2 
33 </p>

<p>Note: the difference between formal and informal is the legal transfer of ownership. 
Source: Altamira dataset (1997/1998 and 2005). </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>characteristic is especially relevant because it can reveal land-specific human capital investments. For 
age and schooling, we included the inter-siblings variance in order to test if parents consider the relative 
distribution of their offspring's return to land-specific human capital when deciding to adopt fixed or 
unequal rule for an intended bequest. 
We also controlled for some of the parent's characteristics. We controlled for parents' health sta-
tus and educational level. The owner's place of birth was also used to account for the cultural-spatial 
differences in land transmission, as is argued by Carneiro (2001). </p>

<p>5. RESULTS </p>

<p>5.1. Empirical Exercise </p>

<p>Table 2 presents summary measures of the data, broken down by endogenous and exogenous variables. 
The descriptive results show that, on average, 64% of smallholders intend to pass on the land to their 
children in the future. Among those, 26% intend to share it unequally. Children are approximately 20 ye-
ars old, with five years of schooling, although educational variance is high. About 64% of male children 
have a land related occupation, similarly to 65% for female children. The type of agricultural activity 
by children's gender, however, differs. While female children are predominantly involved in household 
chores on the property, such as helping with milking and cheese production, male children are more 
frequently involved in harvesting, land clearing or more technical tasks. Upward transfers are not un-
common, with 25% of children helping their parents, mostly with on-the-lot work. Household annual 
income is about US$2,309, with an additional US$1,530 of equivalent production for self-consumption. 
This result shows the importance (56%) of production for self-consumption for household well-being in 
rural areas. Although most of smallholders have a single property, 30% have other types of properties, 
such as another rural lot or urban residence. The average lot allocates 45.6% of the area for commer-
cial use (pasture and cocoa), with approximately 23% of those having high-fertility soil. Most of the 
properties have good accessibility during the rainy season, although road conditions vary considerably 
throughout the year due to precarious maintenance. 
When variables are compared by intention and division rules, interesting differences arise as was 
predicted by our theoretical model. One interesting finding is the striking difference in land size and soil 
fertility by sharing rule. As shown in Table 2, the mean area in commercial land use for farmers adopting 
unequal sharing is 40% higher than this area for those favoring an equal division of land. Regarding soil 
fertility, this difference is 52% higher. These differences are important for our theoretical model, since 
larger farms and more fertile soils favor unequal sharing by maximizing the parent's utility function. 
When the property is small, equal division would prevail in two situations. First, a minimum land 
size is required to allow small and different agricultural units to be productive if we assume that a 
threshold for the motivation to divide the land exists. This is exactly what we see from results in Table 2. 
Furthermore, for very small farms the impact of the variability in land-specific human capital among 
children is not enough to trigger unequal sharing. In this situation, the parent prefers to sell the land and 
equally divide the amount among the offspring. Second, the smaller the land size the smaller the amount 
t that is transferred to the child, implying that a large contrast between expected children's return is 
required to satisfy equation (4). Intuitively, the family welfare would be reduced if the parent transferred 
a marginal unit of wealth from one child to another when both farm size and children's capital return 
are small. The wealth transferred, in this case, would be represented by an investment in the child's 
land-specific human capital. This is due to the fact that the marginal utility is decreasing in the total 
child's wealth. Therefore, a marginal reduction of his/her wealth considerably impacts his/her benefit. 
In short, even if the land remains productive when fractionated, the effect of smoothing consumption 
among children in the parent's utility function overlaps the other effects, favoring equal division. 
Some children's characteristics also support our theoretical models. For instance, farmers who intend 
to share the land equally have a 37% higher probability of being helped by their children than those </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>Tabela 2. Descriptive Statistics: mean of explanatory variables-Altamira Study Area, Pará State, Brazil. </p>

<p>Selected Explanatory Variables </p>

<p>Analytical 
sample 
Intention to 
pass on </p>

<p>Other 
intentions </p>

<p>Equal 
bequest </p>

<p>Unequal 
bequest </p>

<p>Children's Characteristics </p>

<p>Mean age 
20.01 
21.00 
18.19 
21.35 
19.97 </p>

<p>Age variance among siblings 
4.66 
4.76 
4.48 
4.72 
4.87 </p>

<p>Mean schooling 
4.57 
4.71 
4.32 
4.67 
4.81 </p>

<p>Schooling variance among sibling 
4.66 
2.04 
1.64 
2.09 
1.91 </p>

<p>Schooling missing (count) 
0.43 
0.37 
0.56 
0.36 
0.40 </p>

<p>Not currently married (count) 
3.20 
3.31 
3.00 
3.33 
3.24 </p>

<p>Married (count) 
2.08 
2.28 
1.70 
2.29 
2.27 </p>

<p>Son with non-agricultural occupation (0/1) 
0.36 
0.36 
0.36 
0.36 
0.37 </p>

<p>Daughter with non-agricultural 
occupation (0/1) 
0.35 
0.39 
0.27 
0.38 
0.43 </p>

<p>Upward transfer (0/1) 
0.25 
0.28 
0.21 
0.30 
0.22 </p>

<p>Living in the same household (count) 
2.51 
2.51 
2.52 
2.63 
2.18 </p>

<p>Living on the same lot (count) 
0.29 
0.34 
0.20 
0.32 
0.42 </p>

<p>Living off the lot (count) 
2.70 
2.90 
2.35 
2.79 
3.22 </p>

<p>Parents' Characteristics 
Form of land acquisition 
(1-won/0-bought) 
1.4 
1.4 
1.3 
1.4 
1.5 </p>

<p>Household annual income (Brazilian R$) 
5,104.8 
5,710.4 
3,964.0 
4,046.7 10,620.4 </p>

<p>Monetized annual prod. for self-cons. 
(Braz. R$) 
3,381.3 
3,128.7 
3,857.1 
3,017.1 
3,457.9 </p>

<p>Has another property(ies) in the region? 
(0/1) 
0.3 
0.3 
0.3 
0.4 
0.2 </p>

<p>Is father sick? (0/1) 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.3 </p>

<p>Is mother sick? (0/1) 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.1 
0.3 </p>

<p>Father's age (years) 
51.2 
53.3 
47.5 
53.5 
52.7 </p>

<p>Father is illiterate (0/1) 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 </p>

<p>Father has primary education (0/1) 
0.6 
0.7 
0.6 
0.7 
0.7 </p>

<p>Father has secondary education (0/1) 
0.1 
0.1 
0.2 
0.1 
0.2 </p>

<p>Mother has secondary education (0/1) 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.2 
0.3 </p>

<p>Area in pasture (ha) 
40.1 
44.7 
31.9 
41.9 
53.0 </p>

<p>Area in cacao (ha) 
5.5 
6.5 
3.6 
4.7 
11.8 </p>

<p>Rest of lot area (ha) 
63.5 
65.3 
60.1 
68.8 
55.3 </p>

<p>Year of acquisition (year) 
1,982.7 
1,981.4 
1,985.0 
1,981.6 
1,980.8 </p>

<p>Area with high-fertility soil (%) 
22.6 
24.3 
19.5 
21.4 
32.7 </p>

<p>Land accessible during rainy season (0/1) 
0.8 
0.8 
0.8 
0.8 
0.8 </p>

<p>Distance to Medicilândia urban center 
(km) 
35,064.6 
34,031.3 
36,477.9 34,568.1 32,467.6 </p>

<p>Source: Altarmira dataset (1997/1998; 2005) </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>intending to share unequally. The same pattern emerges when we look at the association between 
children's place of residence and the sharing rule. While 51% of the children live in the same household 
among those parents intending to divide the land equally, this proportion is 12% lower among parents 
who plan to distribute their property unequally. The opposite holds for the proportion of children living 
on the lot, which signals a child's investment in land-specific human capital. While these results are in 
accordance with our theoretical model, they are bivariate associations. Thus, we turn now to multiple 
regression associations. 
All independent variables are measured in 1997, while the dependent variable is measured in 2005, 
thus reducing potential bias caused by simultaneity. Because of the potential sample selection in our 
regression model for unequal sharing, we used a Heckman Selection Probit model. The Likelihood Ratio 
test of independent equations was not significant (p-value = 0.8745). Thus, we interpret results based 
on a traditional Probit model with correction for heteroskedasticity (Huber-White variance sandwich 
estimator). In addition, we use one-tail hypotheses testing because we derive the effect signs from our 
theoretical models. Table 3 renders statistical support for the main variables from our theoretical model. 
As shown in Figure 2, the increase in the number of children up to five reduces the probability of unequal 
sharing by increasing the marginal utility of children's wealth. This effect favors parent's intentions to 
smooth their children's consumption. For families with more than five children, further increase in fa-
mily size favors unequal sharing. This is due to the fact that larger family size favors high contrast on 
returns in land-specific human capital. Properties with larger proportions dedicated to commercial agri-
culture are more likely to be divided unequally because of the reduction in the child's marginal utility 
of the amount bequeathed. Smallholders with other properties in the region are more likely to divide 
the land equally among offspring. This may be explained by the ability to use other properties to im-
plement unequal division. Although our proxy for children's service provision is marginally statistically 
significant using a two-tail test, the one-tail result would be significant (p-value=0.044). Thus, parents 
who receive some help from their children are less likely to favor a specific child, suggesting the ability 
of these children to compensate for the contrast in an offspring's land-specific human capital return. 
Coefficients in Table 3 can be readily compared across independent variables because all the measures 
were standardized to have a zero mean and unit variance. </p>

<p>Tabela 3. Probit and Heckman Probit Regression for Unequal Sharing of Land-Altamira Study Area, 
Pará State, Brazil. </p>

<p>Variables 
Heckman Probit 
Probit </p>

<p>Number of surviving children 
−1.164* [0.574] 
−1.197* [0.564] 
Squared number of surviving children 
1.368** [0.549] 
1.368** [0.547] 
% of lot on commercial land use 
0.202 [0.175] 
0.175 [0.176] 
Distance to Altamira urban center 
−0.230* [0.133] 
−0.230* [0.133] 
Has another rural lot 
−0.636** [0.266] 
−0.631** [0.268] 
Total household annual income 
0.216* [0.128] 
0.203* [0.123] 
Upward transfers (0/1) 
−0.500* [0.293] 
−0.495* [0.290] 
Inverse of Mills ratio 
1.075 [2.464] 
Constant 
−0.862 [1.055] 
−0.406** [0.168] 
Observations 
161 
161 </p>

<p>Note: Robust standard errors in brackets. One-tail test ** p&lt;0.01, * p&lt;0.05. 
Source: Altamira dataset (1997, 1998, 2005). </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>Figura 2. Predicted probability of unequal sharing-Altamira Study Area, Pará State, Brazil. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>.2 </p>

<p>.4 </p>

<p>.6 </p>

<p>.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 
4 
6 
8 
10 
12 
14 
16 
Surviving Children </p>

<p>Number of Surviving Children 
Squared Number of Surviving Children </p>

<p>Altamira Study Area -1997 and 2005 </p>

<p>By Number and Squared Number of Surving Children </p>

<p>Predicted Probability of Unequal Sharing </p>

<p>5.2. Theoretical model </p>

<p>In the standard altruism model with uncertainty, an increase by one dollar in the income of parents 
actively making transfers to a child coupled with a one-dollar reduction in that child's income, results in 
the parents' increasing the transfer to the child by one dollar. The findings of Altonji et al. (1997) strongly 
reject the altruism hypothesis. Redistributing one dollar from a recipient child to donor parents leads 
to less than a 13-cent increase in the parents' transfer to the child. This is far less than the one-dollar 
increase implied by perfect altruism. Our result strengthens this evidence for the case of low levels of 
marginal utility and large contrasts in land-specific human capital returns. We conclude that an increase 
by one dollar unit in parents' wealth may not alter the current amount bequeathed to a less productive 
child. Indeed, an increase in parents' utility due to a transfer of one-dollar to a more productive child 
can compensate for the reduction of one-dollar in wealth from the less productive child. 13 
Baker and Micelli (2005) discuss two important results on unequal sharing rules, considering the 
amount of land-specific human capital and abilities for managing the land as distinct parameters. In the 
first case, they assume scale economies and show that heirs overinvest in land-specific human capital to 
induce unequal or non-altruistic bequest choices. Consequently, the bequest is entirely awarded to the 
heir with the higher relative ability to manage the land. The assumption of scale economies, however, 
does not embody wealth smoothing effects among children. In the second case, the authors assume 
scale diseconomies and the production function is concave only on the amount of land transferred by the 
parent. Therefore, the smoothing effects do not incorporate the total wealth from children investment 
in land-specific human capital. 
In our model, we assume that there is a return to the human capital parameter that simultaneously 
incorporates the ability for managing the land and the land-specific human capital. Parents' utility em-
bodies wealth smoothing effects which are quite robust in the case of high marginal utilities and low 
contrast in human capital returns among children. Therefore, parents can choose equal or altruistic sha-
ring rules even when assumptions given in Baker and Micelli (2005) are assured, contrasting with their </p>

<p>13 Obviously, the less productive child has the lower income. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Private Transfer Choices under Uncertainty in Human Capital </p>

<p>results. We establish a condition on the parents' priors over land-specific human capital under which 
the child with the higher expected return receives the largest amount bequeathed. Furthermore, in our 
model including upward transfers, the equal sharing is a dominant rule regardless of any assumption 
of heterogeneity in children's land-specific human capital. This also contrasts with the results given in 
Baker and Micelli (2005). </p>

<p>6. CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Building on previous models of private transfers, we developed a theoretical model for intergenerational 
land transmission in rural settings. We propose an environment where agents live for two periods, con-
sidering consumption and investment strategies. Two different approaches were considered. In the first 
approach, parents make unilateral transfers to their children. In the second approach, children act stra-
tegically by providing services to their parents, thus influencing their transferring behavior. Different 
from Altonji et al. (1997), where uncertainty holds for income only, our model contemplates uncertainty 
on children's returns to land-specific human capital. The advantage of including uncertainty on returns 
is to strengthen Altonji et al. (1997)'s result of imperfect altruism and allow for strategic behavior of 
agents. Indeed, in our first model parents can transfer a larger share of inheritance to the child with the 
highest relative return among offspring. Our model of unilateral transfers assures that under a certain 
level of contrasts among children's returns, the child with the largest return will always receive a larger 
share of the total transfer. This result probes the economic altruism concept, and reinforces the finding 
of imperfect altruism provided by Altonji et al. (1997). 
In the second model, we allow children to behave strategically, as is suggested in Bernheim et al. 
(1985). Based on a sequential move game, we provided a numerical example in which a parent can 
potentially choose different transferring amounts. As a result, rent seeking occurs as heirs compete for 
a larger share of the land. In a Nash equilibrium solution, however, the parent announces equal sharing 
and waits for his/her children to provide services. This minimizes rent seeking. Under this equilibrium, 
the less productive child can provide a sufficient amount of services to receive a larger inheritance share, 
inducing the parent to smooth consumption. 
Neither Baker and Micelli (2005) nor Altonji et al. (1997) treated the human capital return as an 
endogenous variable in the model. This prevented them from establishing conditions on the primitives 
in order to prove theoretical results, assuring a larger share to the most productive child. Our model, 
therefore, provides a link between these two models by showing, through the game theory, as in Baker 
and Micelli (2005) and Bernheim et al. (1985), evidence of non-altruistic behavior as in Altonji et al. (1997). 
Our numerical and empirical results support the theoretical predictions established by our model. By 
using primary data on smallholders in an Amazonian frontier, we provide descriptive evidence of equal 
sharing as a predominant rule, indicating non-altruistic private behavior. Even among those intending 
to pass on the land unequally, our econometric results suggest that larger shares are more likely to be 
transferred to more productive children. </p>



<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>





<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>





<p>A. APPENDIX </p>

<p>Lemma A.1. The value function v i : R + → R + defined by (1) is strictly concave. </p>

<p>Proof: Fix α &gt; 0. First note thatĉ i (t) +â i (t) ≤ y i for t ∈ </p>

<p>{ 
t i , t </p>

<p>′ 
i </p>

<p>} 
implies </p>

<p>αĉ i (t i ) + (1 − α)ĉ i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) + αâ i (t i ) + (1 − α)â i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) ≤ y i . 
(A-1) </p>

<p>Furthermore 
v i (t) = u(ĉ i (t)) + β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u ((1 + r)â i (t) + t) f i (r) dr for t ∈ </p>

<p>{ 
t i , t </p>

<p>′ 
i </p>

<p>} </p>

<p>and the concavity of u imply </p>

<p>αv i (t i ) + (1 − α)v i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) = αu(ĉ i (t i )) + (1 − α)u </p>

<p>(ĉ 
i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>+ β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>αu ((1 + r)â i (t i ) + t i ) + (1 − α)u((1 + r)â i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) + t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i )f i (r) dr </p>

<p>≤ u </p>

<p>( 
αĉ i (t i ) + (1 − α)ĉ i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>+ β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>[ 
α ((1 + r)â i (t i ) + t i ) + (1 − α) </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r)â i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) + t </p>

<p>′ 
i </p>

<p>)] 
f i (r) dr </p>

<p>≤ u </p>

<p>( 
αĉ i (t i ) + (1 − α)ĉ i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>+ β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>[ 
(1 + r) </p>

<p>( 
αâ i (t i ) + (1 − α)â i (t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i ) </p>

<p>) 
+ αt i + (1 − α)t </p>

<p>′ 
i </p>

<p>] 
f i (r) dr </p>

<p>≤ v i </p>

<p>( 
αt i + (1 − α)t </p>

<p>′ 
i </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>by Equation (A-1) and (1). Clearly, when t i t </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i , the inequations can be chosen strictly because u is 
strictly concave. 
□ </p>

<p>Theorem A.2. Suppose Assumptions 3.1 and 3.2. Then, the optimal transfers t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k must satisfy t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j &gt; t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k . </p>

<p>Proof: Assuming an interior solution, 14 differentiating with respect to t i and applying the Envelop 
theorem to equation (1) we get for each t i ∈ R + </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i (t i ) = β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u 
′ ((1 + r)â i (t i ) + t i ) f i (r) dr for i = j, k. 
(A-2) </p>

<p>14 The condition lim c→0 + u ′ (c) = ∞ assures the interior optimum. </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>



<p>Rodrigo J. Raad and Gilvan R. Guedes </p>

<p>Moreover, the F.O.C. of equation (3) with respect to t j , t k evaluated on the optimum (a  *  
p , t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j , t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) for a 
interior solution yields </p>

<p>βu </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r p )a </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>p − t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j − t </p>

<p> *  
k </p>

<p>) 
= µv </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>i (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>i ) for i = j, k. </p>

<p>Assumptions 3.1, 3.2 and equation (A-2) evaluated on t i = t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k imply that 15 </p>

<p>v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) = β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r)â j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) + t </p>

<p> *  
k </p>

<p>) 
f j (r) dr </p>

<p>≥ β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r)y + t </p>

<p> *  
k </p>

<p>) 
f j (r) dr </p>

<p>&gt; β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r)a k + t </p>

<p> *  
k </p>

<p>) 
f k (r) dr </p>

<p>≥ β </p>

<p>∫ </p>

<p>R + </p>

<p>u </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>( 
(1 + r)â k (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) + t </p>

<p> *  
k </p>

<p>) 
f k (r) dr </p>

<p>= v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>k (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) = v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j ). </p>

<p>Therefore we conclude that v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k ) &gt; v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>j (t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j ). This implies that t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>j &gt; t </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p>k since Lemma A.1 assures that v j is 
concave and hence v </p>

<p>′ </p>

<p>j is decreasing. 
□ </p>

<p>15 Observe that in the second and fourth inequality we use that u ′ is decreasing,â j (t  *  </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>) ≤ y andâ k (t  *  </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>) ≥ a k . </p>

<p>RBE Rio de Janeiro v. 69 n. 1 / p. 105-124 Jan-Mar 2015 </p>

</text></tei>