<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2000-04-MOL_ECOL" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T01:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>To make inferences about the glacial refugia that harboured the limber pine, Pinus flexilis 
James, we examined the range-wide population structure of mitochondrial DNA 
(mtDNA) with eight size variants in the second intron of nad1 . The data consisted of haplo-
types from 704 trees collected from 40 localities. The value of F ST for these populations 
was 0.80, which is a much larger value than has been reported for allozymes and chloroplast 
DNA (cpDNA) in limber pine, and it suggests that the number of seeds moving among 
localities per generation is ≈ ≈ ≈ 
≈ 0.12. Gene flow of this magnitude would allow mutation and </p>

<p>subsequent genetic drift to have a substantial impact on the population structure of 
mtDNA. The majority of the mtDNA haplotypes are restricted to minor portions of the 
geographical range. The data are consistent with mtDNA differentiation in seven glacial 
refugia, followed by dispersal out of those refugia. </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to survey mitochondrial 
DNA (mtDNA) variation across the range of limber pine, 
Pinus flexilis , to test whether the pattern of geographical 
variation of mtDNA is consistent with the hypothesis of 
differentiation in isolated glacial refugia and subsequent 
dispersal. This hypothesis was suggested by results of our 
previous survey of mtDNA, chloroplast DNA (cpDNA), 
randomly amplified polymorphic DNA (RAPD) and allozymes 
among seven populations along an elevational transect 
in the Front Range of Colorado (Latta &amp; Mitton 1997). 
Among-population variation was low for 10 allozyme loci 
(mean F ST = 0.016) and for one cpDNA marker ( F ST = 0.013), 
and all of these estimates were homogeneous. However, 
both the mtDNA ( F ST = 0.679) and the RAPD markers 
(predominantly, if not exclusively, nuclear) had much 
higher levels of population differentiation, and the RAPD 
markers gave heterogeneous estimates of F ST . The major-
ity of the population differentiation was produced by a 
single population, which was strikingly different for mtDNA </p>

<p>and RAPD markers, consistent with a zone of secondary 
contact. That study (Latta &amp; Mitton 1997 ) tested and rejected 
the hypothesis that genetic variation was associated with 
an environmental gradient, but the data suggested the 
hypothesis that mtDNA and, to a lesser extent, RAPD 
markers became differentiated in refugia east of the Rocky 
Mountains and in the Great Basin. 
Evidence from two sources reveal that limber pine 
resided in several, and perhaps in many, refugia when 
glaciers displaced the trees from the high mountains. A 
glimpse of the ancient distribution of limber pine can be 
gained by examining the macrofossils in packrat middens 
-materials preserved in middens can be identified and 
carbon dated to reconstruct plant communities of the past 
(Betancourt et al . 1990, 1991). Studies of packrat middens 
led Wells (Wells 1983a; Wells &amp; Stewart 1987) to propose 
that the limber pines in eastern Colorado (Pawnee Buttes) 
and eastern Wyoming (Pine Bluffs) are relicts of the last 
glacial maximum, when conifers, including limber pine 
and Engelmann spruce, moved off the mountains and 
spread into present-day Kansas, Oklahoma and Texas. 
Similar studies revealed that limber pine was found at 
numerous sites between 4000 and 8000 feet in elevation 
in the Great Basin and on the Colorado Plateau (Wells 1983b; 
Betancourt 1990; Thompson 1990). In addition, macrofossils </p>

<p>Correspondence: J. Mitton, Campus Box 334, University of 
Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309, USA. Fax: +303-4928699; E-mail: 
Mitton@Colorado.edu </p>

<p>MEC840.fm Page 91 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>

<p>92 J . B . M I T T O N , B . R . K RE I S E R and R . G . L A T T A </p>

<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>

<p>document the presence of limber pine 22 720 years before 
present ( bp ) in the mountains of Colorado (Fremont Co.) 
and between 40 000 and 27 000 years bp in Bighorn Co., 
Wyoming, less than 300 km south of the southernmost 
margin of the glacier (Wells &amp; Stewart 1987 ). Thus, it 
appears that limber pine may have had at least four glacial 
refugia, but it is probable that there were other refugia 
that we have not yet identified. 
Genetic markers in the mtDNA of pines are ideal for 
detecting ancient events of differentiation and dispersal 
(Sinclair et al . 1999). The nuclear, chloroplast and mito-
chondrial components of the genomes of most conifers </p>

<p>have different modes of inheritance, disparate potentials 
for gene flow and heterogeneous degrees of population 
structure (Mitton 1997 ). For most species in the family 
Pinaceae, mtDNA is inherited maternally (Neale et al . 1991; 
Marshall &amp; Neale 1992; Dong &amp; Wagner 1994; but see 
Wagner et al . 1991; Neale et al . 1989, 1991), and is dispersed 
only by the movement of seeds, whereas cpDNA is inher-
ited paternally, and is dispersed first by wind-borne pollen 
and then by the movement of fertilized seeds (Neale et al . 
1986; Strauss et al . 1989; Dong &amp; Wagner 1994). Nuclear 
genes, like cpDNA, are dispersed by both pollen and seeds. 
In the absence of selection, gene flow is inversely related </p>

<p>Table 1 Mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) haplotype frequencies in limber pine </p>

<p>Region 
Locality 
1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>Southern Rockies 
1 Sandia Crest, NM 
15 
8 
2 Red River, NM 
16 
3 Magdalena Mts, NM 
15 
4 Manzanos Mts, NM 
6 
5 Gallinas Mts, NM 
2 
6 Mt. Withington, NM 
4 
4 
7 Sierra Blanca, NM 
6 
8 Sacramento Mts, NM 
1 
9 Sangre de Cristo, NM 
2 
10 Black Mt, CO 
10 
5 
11 Independence Pass, CO 
10 
12 Monarch Pass, CO 
12 
13 Trout Creek Pass, CO 
2 
14 Sheep Mt, CO 
4 
38 
15 Weston Pass, CO 
20 
16 La Veta Pass, CO 
14 
20 
17 Berthoud Pass, CO 
1 
6 
18 Golden Canyon, CO 
5 
19 Red Hill Pass, CO 
23 
20 Rollins Pass, CO 
1 
3 
21 Niwot Ridge, CO 
2 
37 
22 Hallet Peak, CO 
4 
36 
23 Sugarloaf Mt, CO 
2 
35 
24 Green Mt, CO 
3 
38 
25 Ouray, CO 
16 
26 Durango, CO 
2 
27 Wolf Creek Pass, CO 
2 
6 
28 Pawnee Buttes, CO 
41 
29 Pine Bluff, WY 
37 
30 Tie Siding, WY 
8 
Great Basin 
31 San Francisco Peak, AZ 
10 
32 East Humboldt Mts, NV 
18 
33 Wheeler Peak, NV 
15 
1 
34 Sheep Creek, UT 
11 
3 
35 Ferron Canyon, UT 
1 
16 
3 
36 Avintaquin, UT 
18 
2 
Canada 
37 Whirlpool Pt. AB 
28 
38 Porcupine Hills, AB 
20 
California 
39 Mt. Pinos, CA 
20 
40 Horseshoe Meadows, CA 
13 
3 </p>

<p>AB, Alberta; AZ, Arizona; CA, California; CO, Colorado; NM, New Mexico; NV, Nevada; UT, Utah; WY, Wyoming. </p>

<p>MEC840.fm Page 92 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>

<p>G L A C I A L R E F U G I A O F L I M B E R P I N E 93 </p>

<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>

<p>to the degree of population differentiation as measured 
using F ST , a standardized measure of the variance of allelic 
frequencies. Because wind-borne pine pollen typically 
moves much further than pine seeds, the potential for gene 
flow is high for cpDNA and nuclear genes, but low for 
mtDNA. Empirical studies of conifers are consistent with 
these expectations in that the F ST values of maternally 
inherited markers are greater than the F ST values for 
nuclear or cpDNA markers in lodgepole pine, P. contorta 
(Wheeler &amp; Guries 1982; Dong &amp; Wagner 1993, 1994), 
Monterey pine, P. radiata , Bishop pine, P. muricata , and 
knobcone pine, P. attenuata (Hong et al . 1993; Strauss et al . 
1993; Wu et al . 1998), and limber pine, P. flexilis (Latta &amp; 
Mitton 1997 ). For example, in Bishop pine, P. muricata , the 
value of F ST for allozymes is 0.22 (Millar et al . 1988) but the 
value of F ST for mtDNA is 0.96 (Strauss et al . 1993). </p>

<p>Here we present a study of the population structure of 
mtDNA in limber pine, which was based on 704 trees 
sampled from 40 populations. The data suggest that the 
mtDNA of limber pine became differentiated in a minimum 
of seven glacial refugia. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Sample sites are listed in Table 1 and illustrated in Fig. 1. 
The sites include those sampled previously by Latta &amp; 
Mitton (1997 ) and additional sites for this study. A total of 
704 trees were sampled from 40 sample sites. More detailed 
information on the sites is available from the correspond-
ing author (J. B. M.). 
Samples consisted of a single twig and a few needles 
taken from a mature tree in the field. The twigs were kept </p>

<p>Fig. 1 The distribution of limber pine, Pinus 
flexilis, showing sample sites and the fre-
quencies of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) 
haplotypes in selected sample sites. The 
site numbers correspond to those in Table 1 
and Fig. 2. The full data set for mtDNA is 
presented in Table 1. </p>

<p>MEC840.fm Page 93 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>



<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>

<p>cool until DNA was extracted from them at the genetics 
facility at the University of Colorado. 
Total genomic DNA was extracted from needle tissue 
using the hexadecyltrimethyl ammonium bromide (CTAB) 
extraction procedure of Doyle &amp; Doyle (1987 ). The primers 
of Demesure et al . (1995) were used to amplify the second 
intron of nad1 from the mitochondrial genome. The poly-
merase chain reaction (PCR) contained, in a 15-µ L reac-
tion volume, 50 m m KCl, 10 m m Tris-HCl, 0.01% gelatin, 
3 m m MgCl 2 , 200 µ m of each dNTP, 0.5 U of Taq poly-
merase, 200 n m of each primer and 20 ng of template 
DNA. The amplification cycle consisted of an initial 3-
min denaturation at 94 ° C followed by 45 cycles of: 1 min 
denaturation at 94 ° C, 1 min annealing and 2.5 min exten-
sion at 72 ° C, with a final 10-min extension at 72 ° C. The 
annealing temperatures employed a touchdown temper-
ature profile, with four cycles at each of a descending 
series of temperatures (63 ° C, 61 ° C, 59 ° C and 57 ° C); the 
following 39 cycles used an annealing temperature of 
55 ° C. The 2.2-kb fragment was digested with Rsa I, and 
visualized by silver staining (Klinkicht &amp; Tautz 1992) 
after electrophoresis on a 5% denaturing acrylamide gel. 
The cleaved fragments of the amplified DNA were 
assigned numbers: 1 was assigned to the smallest frag-
ment and other fragments were labelled sequentially with 
increasing size. 
Frequencies of mtDNA haplotypes were treated as allelic 
frequencies at a single locus for statistical purposes. F ST was 
used to describe the variation among populations and 
was calculated using <rs id="software-15" type="software">biosys</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-15" type="creator">(Swofford &amp; Selander 1981)</rs>). 
The homogeneity of haplotype frequencies was tested 
using a row-by-columns test of independence, which 
employs χ 2 . Because some of the sample sites had 
small sample sizes, we grouped the samples into the 
geographical regions listed in Table 1 for the calculation 
of χ 2 . </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Eight size variants of the cleaved fragment of the second 
intron of nad1 were detected (Table 1) and we refer to 
these as haplotypes 1 to 8. The sizes of the fragments 
from haplotypes 1, 3, 6, 7 and 8 formed a regular series; 
the sizes of these fragments were 1080, 1120, 1160, 1200 
and 1240, respectively. However, the fragments from 
haplotypes 2, 4 and 5, which were ≈ 1100, 1130 and 1150, 
respectively, are interspersed in this series, disrupting the 
pattern of even spacing. 
A row-by-columns test of independence revealed that 
the allelic frequencies were heterogeneous among the geo-
graphical areas ( χ 2 = 181.1, P &lt; 0.001). The value of F ST 
for the haplotypes was 0.80, indicating that relatively little 
of the variation resided within populations, and that most 
of the variation was among populations. </p>

<p>Most of the haplotypes were restricted to a small area 
of the range of limber pine (Table 1, Fig. 1). Haplotype 1 
reached its highest frequencies in the mountains of New 
Mexico, where it was the most common haplotype on 
Sandia Crest, and was fixed in the Magdalena Mountains. 
Haplotype 1 was found only as a rare variant in a few of 
the collection sites in the Rocky Mountains in Colorado 
and in the Wasatch Mountains of Utah. Haplotype 2 
was found only in the two sites in California; it appeared 
to be fixed on Mt. Pinos, and was the most common 
haplotype at Horseshoe Meadows. Haplotype 3 was the 
most widespread; it was distributed from the Sacramento 
Mountains of southern New Mexico to the Porcupine 
Hills of Alberta, and from Pawnee Buttes in eastern 
Colorado to the Wasatch Mountains of Utah. Haplotype 
4 was only found at Horseshoe Meadows, California, 
where it was less common than haplotype 2. Haplotype 
5 was restricted to the southwest. It was fixed at Ouray, 
Colorado, and in the San Francisco Peaks, Arizona, and 
it was nearly fixed at Wheeler Peak, Nevada. Haplotype 
6 was limited to the Wasatch and Uintah Mountains of 
Utah, and in those areas it was less common than 
haplotype 3. Haplotype 7 was most common at high 
elevation sites along the Continental Divide in Colorado, 
and it was also found on Black Mountain and La Veta 
Pass, which are also relatively high sites. This haplotype 
was not detected in Utah, but it appeared again in the 
East Humboldt Mountains and as a rare variant on 
Wheeler Peak. In general, this haplotype was only 
detected at collection sites with elevations exceeding 
3000 m. Haplotype 8 was found in just one collection site, 
our most northern site, at Whirlpool Point, Alberta, 
where it appeared to be fixed. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>It is probable that the mtDNA variation among extant 
populations (Table 1) evolved when glaciers displaced 
limber pines, restricting them to refugia that were repro-
ductively isolated by the distances among them. Macro-
fossils from packrat middens and palynological data 
provide evidence that limber pine resided in a minimum 
of four glacial refugia: east of the Rocky Mountains in 
Colorado and Kansas (Wells 1983a; Wells &amp; Stewart 1987 ) 
and at numerous sites in the Great Basin (Wells 1983b; 
Betancourt 1990; Thompson 1990), Fremont Co., Colorado 
(Wells &amp; Stewart 1987 ) and Bighorn Co., Wyoming (Wells 
&amp; Stewart 1987 ). Furthermore, it is probable that addi-
tional refugia existed that have not yet been discovered. 
The distributions of the haplotypes are informative and 
suggest areas that may have served as glacial refugia and 
the subsequent routes of dispersal out of them (Fig. 2). 
For example, haplotype 1 is common in the Magdalena 
Mountains and on Sandia Crest in New Mexico, but rare </p>

<p>MEC840.fm Page 94 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>

<p>G L A C I A L R E F U G I A O F L I M B E R P I N E 95 </p>

<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>

<p>in Colorado and Utah, suggesting that it emigrated from 
a refugium in southern New Mexico and moved with 
limited success to the north. Haplotypes 2 and 4, cur-
rently restricted to sites in California, might have become 
fixed in a refugium in the southern Sierra Nevada without 
ever invading the remainder of the range of limber pine. The 
distribution of haplotype 3 suggests that it predominated 
either on the eastern foothills of the Rocky Mountains or 
in refugia further east (Wells 1983a), where it is currently 
fixed. Haplotype 5 may have become fixed in a refugium 
near the San Francisco Peaks of Arizona, then migrated 
north to reach Wheeler Peak in Nevada and the San Juan 
of Colorado. Haplotype 6 probably became fixed in refugia 
in the Great Basin (Betancourt 1990), for it is restricted to 
that area. Haplotype 7 may have become fixed in Fremont 
County, Colorado, close to its present distribution, which </p>

<p>meanders from La Veta Pass to the western fringe of South 
Park and the Continental Divide in central Colorado. Hap-
lotype 8 is fixed in and restricted to our most northern site 
in Canada; perhaps this haplotype became fixed in the 
refugium in Bighorn County, Wyoming (Wells &amp; Stewart 
1987 ), less than 300 km south of the glacier's margin when it 
reached its maximum. Trees from this refugium probably 
spread to the north as the Wisconsin glacier receded. 
Dispersal out of the glacial refugia would have been 
assisted by Clark's nutcracker, Nucifraga columbiana , 
which harvest and cache the seeds of limber pine (Tomback 
&amp; Linhart 1990). Although the birds would have helped 
to carry the seeds for expanding populations, their flight 
distances are insufficient to maintain gene flow of mtDNA 
across today's fragmented distribution. Flight distances 
of a few hundred metres are probably typical, although </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Possible glacial refugia for limber 
pine, Pinus flexilis, and routes of dispersal 
from the refugia as the glaciers receded. 
The numbers of the sites correspond to 
those in Table 1 and Fig. 1. The numbers 
in bold are the haplotypes listed in Table 1. </p>

<p>MEC840.fm Page 95 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>



<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>

<p>flights up to 22 km have been reported (VanderWall &amp; 
Balda 1977; Tomback &amp; Linhart 1990). While 22 km is a 
substantial distance, this range of dispersal is insufficient 
to connect all the extant portions of the range of limber 
pine (Fig. 1). For example, we estimate the minimal distance 
between populations of limber pine in the Rocky Mountains 
of Colorado and the Uintah Mountains of Utah to be 
150 km. This gap could be crossed by wind-borne pollen, 
but not by Clark's nutcrackers carrying seeds. Similarly, 
limber pine on Mt. Pinos in California and in the 
Magdalena Mountains may be exchanging pollen (and 
therefore nuclear genes and cpDNA) with pines in other 
populations, but the mtDNA in these populations may be 
perfectly isolated. Gene flow of nuclear and chloroplast 
genes is substantial in limber pine (Latta &amp; Mitton 1997; 
Schuster et al . 1989), as it is in most conifers. For example, 
when 10 polymorphic allozyme loci were used to survey 
population structure for limber pine populations in the 
Front Range of Colorado, the mean F ST was 0.02, and 
inferences of the number of migrants among populations 
ranged from five to 250 (Latta &amp; Mitton 1997). Similarly, 
when 23 polymorphic allozyme loci were used to survey 
limber pine populations in the Great Basin and Colorado 
Plateau, the mean F ST was 0.101 (Hamrick et al . 1994), 
yielding an estimate of 2.2 for the number of migrants 
among populations per generation. In contrast, the F ST for 
mtDNA for the limber pine populations in the Front 
Range was 0.67 (Latta &amp; Mitton 1997 ), yielding an estimate 
of migrants per generation of 0.24. The value of F ST for 
the data in Table 1 is 0.80, from which we infer that the 
average number of migrants per generation is 0.12. Thus, 
in comparison to the genes moved by pollen (nuclear 
genes and cpDNA), the genes moved only by seeds 
(mtDNA) have much lower rates of gene flow. 
Not only does the limited gene flow of mtDNA prob-
ably account for the substantial geographical structuring, 
but it also provides an explanation for the sharp discontinu-
ity in mtDNA haplotypes found in Colorado. The popu-
lations on the fringe of South Park (Black Mountain, Red 
Hill Pass) and the populations to the east have predom-
inantly haplotype 3, while all populations to the west of 
South Park (Sheep Mountain, Monarch Pass, Independence 
Pass, Weston Pass) are fixed or nearly fixed for haplotype 
7. For example, most of the limber pine on Sheep Mountain 
have haplotype 7, but Red Hill Pass, less than 16 km east 
of Sheep Mountain, is fixed for haplotype 3. Thus, the 
mtDNA data indicate that there is little or no exchange of 
seed between these localities. This abrupt discontinuity 
might be an area of secondary contact of limber pines 
from genetically differentiated refugia. The limited dis-
persal of seeds would allow mtDNA to record secondary 
zones of contact long after gene flow had erased similar 
differentiation for nuclear and chloroplast genes. 
We cannot determine whether the haplotype diagnostic </p>

<p>for a geographical area is a unique mutation that became 
fixed, or is the sole haplotype remaining after lineage 
sorting. At one extreme is the hypothesis that the pre-
glaciation limber pines had little or no mtDNA variation, 
and that all of the haplotypes detected here arose by new 
mutations and became fixed in refugia isolated by 
distance. At the other extreme is the hypothesis that the 
preglaciation limber pines had abundant mtDNA vari-
ation, and that lineage sorting fixed different haplotypes 
in the various refugia. Understanding the phylogenetic 
relationships among the haplotypes might allow us to 
reject one of the hypotheses, and to refine the hypotheses 
concerning the number of refugia, their locations and 
routes of emigration from them. For example, if the haplo-
types present within a region were sister lineages, then 
they probably represent de novo mutation, whereas if they 
were more distantly related, lineage sorting is the more appro-
priate explanation. Currently, however, owing to the 
extreme conservation of plant mtDNA sequences, we lack 
the variable sites needed to estimate phylogenetic 
relationships. 
Because the haplotypes are identified solely by size, it 
is possible that some of our haplotype designations con-
tain homoplasies; haplotypes identical in size may not be 
identical by descent. For example, we found haplotype 7 
along the Continental Divide in Colorado and also in the 
East Humboldt Mountains of Nevada. Are these haplo-
types identical by descent or are they the product of separate 
mutational events? This a problem common to studies of 
organellar genomes, for even haplotypes homogeneous 
for a particular sequence may be heterogeneous for other 
genes in the organellar genome. However, despite the 
potential for additional variation within the haplotypes 
we have identified, the strong geographical structuring of 
size variants clearly indicates that seed exchange between 
glacial refugia has been very limited. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Friends helped in this study by sending needle tissue from limber 
pines in New Mexico (R. Reiss), California (R. Graton, T. J. Brady) 
and Alberta (G. E. Rehfeldt, N. Dhir). B. Kreiser, S. Kelley and 
M. Grant commented on drafts of the manuscript. </p>



<p>MEC840.fm Page 96 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>

<p>G L A C I A L R E F U G I A O F L I M B E R P I N E 97 </p>

<p>© 2000 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 9, 91-97 </p>



<p>MEC840.fm Page 97 Thursday, December 16, 1999 11:04 AM </p>

</text></tei>