<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2001-40-MOL_ECOL" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>In an effort to link quantitative morphometric information with molecular data on the popu-
lation level, we have analysed 19 populations of the conchologically variable land snail 
Candidula unifasciata from across the species range for variation in quantitative shell traits 
and at the mitochondrial 16S ribosomal (r)DNA locus. In genetic analysis, including 21 
additional populations, we observed two fundamental haplotype clades with an average 
pairwise sequence divergence of 0.209 ± 0.009 between clades compared to 0.017 ± 0.012 
within clades, suggesting the presence of two different evolutionary lineages. Integrating 
additional shell material from the Senckenberg Malacological Collection, a highly signific-
ant discriminant analysis on the morphological shell traits with fundamental haplotype 
clades as grouping variable suggested that the less frequent haplotype corresponds to the 
described subspecies C. u. rugosiuscula , which we propose to regard as a distinct species. 
Both taxa were highly subdivided genetically ( F ST = 0.648 and 0.777 P &lt; 0.001). This was 
contrasted by the partition of morphological variance, where only 29.6% and 21.9% of the 
variance were distributed among populations, respectively. In C. unifasciata , no significant 
association between population pairwise F ST estimates and corresponding morphological 
fixation indices could be detected, indicating independent evolution of the two character 
sets. Partial least square analysis of environmental factors against shell trait variables in 
C. u. unifasciata revealed significant correlations between environmental factors and certain 
quantitative shell traits, whose potential adaptational values are discussed. </p>

<p>The evolutionary processes shaping the phenotypic 
variation among and within subdivided natural populations 
have only recently started to become a focus of research 
interest (e.g. Bonnin et al . 1996; Yang et al . 1996; Lynch et al . 
1999). This is probably due to the multitude of factors 
shaping phenotypic traits in natural populations. The 
phenotypic appearance is influenced in a complex fashion 
by phylogenetic history, genetic drift, gene-flow, selection, 
environment and developmental processes. The relevant </p>

<p>evolutionary processes are supposed to take place in 
natural populations and consequently should be studied 
there (Ritland 2000). To gain information about phylo-
genetic relations and population processes on the 
species level and beyond, effective neutral genetic markers 
such as microsatellites, restriction fragment length 
polymorphisms (RFLPs) or mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) 
sequences have been widely used (reviewed in Avise 
2000). This information can be used as a background 
against which the phenotypic variation can be compared 
in order to gain insight into the processes shaping the 
phenotypic appearance. 
A necessary prerequisite for such a study is a detect-
able amount of genetic and phenotypic variation among </p>

<p>Correspondence: Dr Markus Pfenninger. Fax: +49 69 798 24910; 
E-mail: Pfenninger@zoology.uni-frankfurt.de </p>



<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>populations. A strong population structure is most likely 
found in species with poor dispersal capacity. Land snails 
with their restricted vagility, therefore, appear very suited 
organisms for the study on the issue of phenotypic evolu-
tion. Phenotypic variability of shell traits within and 
among populations of geographically subdivided taxa is 
often observed in land snails. While qualitative differences 
in shell colour and banding within Helicid snail species is 
well studied in conjunction with molecular markers (e.g. 
Arter 1990; Davison &amp; Clarke 2000), quantitative variation 
has not yet been explored and causes much uncertainty 
about the evolutionary and taxonomical relevance (Kerney 
&amp; Cameron 1979). Substantial variation in shell morpho-
logy can be observed in the small land snail Candidula 
unifasciata ssp. (Poiret 1801) throughout the species range 
(Gittenberger 1993). This has led to the description of at 
least four subspecies, based on differences in shell traits: 
C. u. unifasciata (Poiret 1801), C. u. rugosiuscula (Michaud 
1831), C. u. soosiana (Wagner 1933) and C. u. acosmia 
(Bourguignat 1882). Studying the original descriptions of 
the subspecies (Michaud 1831; Bourguignat 1882; Wagner 
1933), it becomes clear that the authors refer to quantitative 
rather than to qualitative differences to distinguish the 
taxa. Because this makes unequivocal identification diffi-
cult, there is much confusion about the distribution of 
each subspecies, though most authors agree that there is 
a 'geographical component' in the range of each type 
(Gittenberger 1993). 
In this study, we use the genetic information from mito-
chondrial 16S haplotype analysis as a background to study 
quantitative morphologic differences at the population 
level throughout the core species range of all described 
C. unifasciata taxa. In particular, we focus on three questions: 
(i) does the observed phenotypic variation correspond to 
different evolutionary lineages? (ii) How is the phenotypic 
variation distributed within and among populations in 
relation to the 16S variation? And (iii) Can we identify 
environmental variables that co-vary with population dif-
ferences in morphology? </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Samples and DNA extraction </p>

<p>Samples for this study were collected from 40 locations, 
comprising the core species range of Candidula unifasciata 
(Kerney &amp; Cameron 1979). Morphologic analyses were 
performed on individuals from a subset of 19 populations 
(Fig. 1 and Table 1). Within these populations, we tried to 
analyse all available samples both morphologically and 
genetically. However, for some individuals the 16S 
analysis failed at some point [DNA extraction, polymerase 
chain reaction (PCR) or sequencing] and some indi-
viduals were subadults and not suitable for morphologic </p>

<p>analysis. The overlap of both data sets was therefore not 
complete. 
Individuals destined for morphological analyses were 
photographed (see below) prior to DNA extraction. In 
total, 220 individuals were crushed with their shells in 10% 
w/v laundry detergent solution for storage at room tem-
perature and tissue digestion following the protocol of 
Bahl &amp; Pfenninger (1996). Additionally, we tried to extract 
DNA from museum specimens that were apparently 
sampled alive and contained dried remains of tissue. To 
preserve the shells, they were soaked in laundry detergent 
solution overnight and treated for 5 min with supersonic 
to detach the tissue from the shell. All samples were 
shaken for 24 h at 37 ° C in the laboratory prior to phenol/ 
chloroform extraction of total DNA following a standard 
protocol (Sambrook et al . 1989). </p>

<p>Amplification of 16S ribosomal DNA, 
sequencing and alignment </p>

<p>The 16S target-DNA was amplified for all samples by PCR 
with universal primers of the sequence 16S1 5 ′ &gt; CGCAGT-
ACTCTGACTGTGC &lt; 3 ′ and 16S2 5 ′ &gt; GTCCGGTTTGAA-
CTCAGATC &lt; 3 ′ . Amplification was performed with </p>

<p>Fig. 1 Geographical location of sampled populations. The framed 
part of the upper map corresponds to the lower map. Populations 
where both morphological and genetic analysis was performed 
are bold and underlined. </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2543 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology , 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>Table 1 (a ) Locations, regions and countries sampled for Candidula unifasciata ssp., ordered from South to North, their abbreviations used, 
geographical position, number of individuals sampled for 16S rDNA ( N gen ) and morphologic analysis ( N morph ), respectively. (b ) C. 
unifasciata ssp. Samples from the Malacological collection of the Senckenberg Museum/Frankfurt am Main, their origin as far as indicated 
on the collection label, the reference number of the collection, number of specimen used in morphologic and 16S rDNA analysis </p>

<p>(a) 
Location 
Region 
Abbr. 
Position 
N gen 
N morph </p>

<p>1 Sainte Baume 
Bouches du Rhône 
STB 
43 ° 20 ′ 37 ′′ N 
4 
1 3 
05 ° 38 ′ 87 ′′ E 
2 Sainte Victoire 
Bouches du Rhône 
STV 
43 ° 32 ′ 18 ′′ N 
3 
8 
05 ° 34 ′ 66 ′′ E 
3 Vauvenargue 
Bouches du Rhône 
VAU 
43 ° 33 ′ 14 ′′ N 
5 
9 
05 ° 35 ′ 06 ′′ E 
4 Coudoux 
Bouches du Rhône 
COU 
43 ° 33 ′ 89 ′′ N 
4 
1 3 
05 ° 14 ′ 58 ′′ E 
5 Regasse 
Var 
REG 
43 ° 39 ′ 30 ′′ N 
2 
-
06 ° 08 ′ 00 ′′ E 
6 Saint Paul 
Var 
SPA 
43 ° 40 ′ 30 ′′ N 
5 
-
05 ° 41 ′ 15 ′′ E 
7 Grotte de Saint Cezaire 
Alpes Maritimes 
GSC 
43 ° 40 ′ 82 ′′ N 
1 0 
1 8 
06 ° 48 ′ 57 ′′ E 
8 Rognes 
Bouches du Rhône 
ROG 
43 ° 41 ′ 18 ′′ N 
5 
1 4 
05 ° 18 ′ 78 ′′ E 
9 Maussane 
Bouches du Rhône 
MAU 
43 ° 41 ′ 71 ′′ N 
4 
4 
04 ° 50 ′ 55 ′′ E 
10 Escragnolles 
Alpes Maritimes 
ESC 
43 ° 43 ′ 78 ′′ N 
1 1 
1 9 
06 ° 47 ′ 58 ′′ E 
11 Lauris 
Vaucluse 
LAU 
43 ° 45 ′ 35 ′′ N 
5 
1 2 
05 ° 15 ′ 31 ′′ E 
12 Grand Luberon 
Vaucluse 
LUB 
43 ° 47 ′ 55 ′′ N 
6 
-
05 ° 26 ′ 10 ′′ E 
13 Petit Luberon 
Vaucluse 
PLU 
43 ° 48 ′ 18 ′′ N 
5 
2 1 
05 ° 17 ′ 02 ′′ E 
14 Valensole 
Alpes de H te Provence 
VAL 
43 ° 49 ′ 40 ′′ N 
4 
-
05 ° 58 ′ 50 ′′ E 
15 Naverre 
Alpes de H te Provence 
NAV 
43 ° 52 ′ 55 ′′ N 
5 
-
06 ° 13 ′ 50 ′′ E 
16 Saint Jurs 
Alpes de H te Provence 
SJU 
43 ° 53 ′ 55 ′′ N 
8 
-
06 ° 12 ′ 40 ′′ E 
17 Col d'Orme 
Alpes de H te Provence 
CDO 
43 ° 54 ′ 40 ′′ N 
2 
5 
06 ° 12 ′ 36 ′′ E 
18 Col de Murs 
Vaucluse 
CMU 
43 ° 58 ′ 50 ′′ N 
5 
-
05 ° 13 ′ 45 ′′ E 
19 Plateau de Vaucluse 1 
Vaucluse 
PTV 
44 ° 00 ′ 10 ′′ N 
5 
-
05 ° 32 ′ 05 ′′ E 
20 Les Eicharettes 
Vaucluse 
EIC 
44 ° 04 ′ 50′′ N 
6 
-
05°26′45′′ E 
21 Plateau de Vaucluse 7 
Vaucluse 
ADR 
44°04′50′′ N 
5 
-
05°26′45′′ E 
22 Le Ventouret 
Vaucluse 
VEN 
44°07′45′′ N 
5 
-
05°22′20′′ E 
23 Alès 
Gard 
ALE 
44°07′45′′ N 
4 
-
04°12′40′′ E 
24 Sisteron 
Drôme 
SIS 
44°12′15′′ N 
4 
1 2 
05°54′39′′ E 
25 Saint Martin d'Ardèche 
Ardèche 
ARD 
44°18′30′′ N 
5 
-
04°33′22′′ E 
26 Aubenas 
Ardèche 
AUB 
44°35′30′′ N 
1 
-
04°25′10′′ E 
27 La Mure 
Isère 
MUR 
44°52′55′′ N 
1 5 
1 9 </p>

<p>2544 M . P F E N N I N G E R and F . M A G N I N </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>05°50′62′′ E 
28 Montalieu 
Isère 
MON 
45°08′30′′ N 
5 
-
05°23′25′′ E 
29 Mons Salève 
Haute Savoie 
SAL 
46°04′40′′ N 
6 
6 
06°07′30′′ E 
30 Fort d'Ecluse 
Ain 
FDE 
46°07′25′′ N 
5 
-
05°53′15′′ E 
31 Gex 
Ain 
GEX 
46°21′05′′ N 
5 
-
06°03′00′′ E 
32 Col de Marchaidruz 
Fribourg 
CMA 
46°32′62′′ N 
6 
9 
06°15′15′′ E 
33 Herticourt 
Doubs 
HER 
47°15′30′′ N 
5 
-
06°45′10′′ E 
34 Münsingen 
Baden-Württemberg 
MÜN 
48°25′00′′ N 
1 0 
4 
09°30′00′′ E 
35 Jakobsberg 
Rheinland-Pfalz 
JAK 
49°75′71′′ N 
3 
1 4 
07°59′08′′ E 
36 Flörsheim 
Hessen 
FLÖ 
50°00′01′′ N 
7 
9 
08°23′10′′ E 
37 Schlüchtern/Elm 
Hessen 
SLE 
50°21′40′′ N 
8 
-
09°33′20′′ E 
38 Winterscheid 
Hessen 
WIN 
50°55′85′′ N 
4 
7 
09°01′91′′ E 
39 Dierdorf 
Thüringen 
DID 
51°10′66′′ N 
5 
1 1 
10°17′34′′ E 
40 Halle 
Sachsen-Anhalt 
HAL 
51°42′35′′ N 
5 
-
11°53′15′′ E </p>

<p>(a) 
Location 
Region 
Abbr. 
Position 
N gen 
N morph </p>

<p>(b) 
Taxon 
Location 
Region / Country 
SNG reference no. 
N gen 
N morph </p>

<p>C. u. unifasciata 
Grasse 
Alpes Maritimes/F 
60827 
-
6 
C. u. unifasciata 
? 
Bayern / D 
60737 
-
6 
C. u. acosmia 
Carpentras 
Vaucluse / F 
97053 
1 
6 
C. u. soosiana 
Budapest 
Hungary 
217549 
1 
7 
C. u. soosiana 
Budapest 
Hungary 
278316 
-
6 
C. u. rugosiuscula 
Cariès 
Var/F 
97130 
-
5 
C. u. rugosiuscula 
Castres 
Provence/F 
60212 
-
5 
C. u. rugosiuscula 
Bois de Pires 
Provence/F 
97134 
-
7 </p>

<p>Table 1 Continued </p>

<p>Boehringer Taq-polymerase in 12.5 µL total reaction volume 
with standard reaction conditions. Samples were amplified 
for 10 cycles (92 °C for 50 s, 44 °C for 50 s and 72 °C for 40 s) 
and 36 cycles (92 °C for 30 s, 48 °C for 40 s and 72 °C for 40 s) 
after initial incubation of 90 °C for 2 min 30 s. Both strands 
of the purified amplification products were cycle -sequenced 
with the Perkin Elmer Taq DyeDeoxy™ Terminator Cycle 
Sequencing Kit following the supplier's protocol and read 
automatically on the <rs type="software">ABI Prism 377®</rs> sequencing device from 
the same manufacturer. Sequences were deposited in <rs type="software">GenBank</rs> 
(Accession nos AF407841-AF408058) and were aligned 
manually after an initial alignment with the <rs id="software-81" type="software">clustal</rs> 
option (<rs corresp="#software-81" type="creator">Thompson et al.</rs>. 1994) in the computer program 
<rs id="software-50" type="software">sequencenavigator</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-50" type="creator">Perkin Elmer, Applied Biosystems</rs>). </p>

<p>16S Pairwise distance statistics and maximum 
likelihood analysis </p>

<p>The 16S sequences were collapsed to haplotypes with the 
<rs id="software-74" type="software">collapse 1.0</rs> tool provided by <rs corresp="#software-74" type="creator">David Posada</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-74" type="url">http://bioag.byu.edu /zoology/crandall_lab</rs>). For the maximum 
likelihood (ML) analyses, the best-fit model of nucleotide 
substitution (TrNef + G) was selected using the hierarchy of 
likelihood ratio tests implemented in <rs id="software-48" type="software">modeltest</rs> <rs corresp="#software-48" type="version-number">3.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-48" type="creator">Posada &amp; Crandall</rs> <rs corresp="#software-48" type="version-date">1998</rs>). ML heuristic search was conducted with 
100 random sequence addition replicates. Nodal support 
was estimated using the bootstrap approach (Felsenstein 
1985) with 1000 replicates. ML analyses were performed 
with <rs id="software-49" type="software">paup</rs> <rs corresp="#software-49" type="version-number">4.03b</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-49" type="creator">Swofford</rs> 1998). A pairwise sequence </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2545 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>divergence frequency distribution, including 16S rDNA 
sequences from the Helicellinae species Trochoidea geyeri 
(Soós 1926) (79 sequences, Accession nos AF407751-
AF407829) and C. gigaxii (L. Pfeiffer 1850) (10 sequences 
Accession nos AF407830 -AF407840), was calculated. 
Analysis of Molecular Variance (amova) was performed 
on a matrix of pairwise Euclidean differences between haplo-
types, grouped after population of origin. The calculations 
were performed using <rs id="software-55" type="software">amova</rs> <rs corresp="#software-55" type="version-number">1.55</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-55" type="creator">Excoffier et al</rs>. 1992). </p>

<p>Morphological analysis </p>

<p>Morphological analysis was performed on adult indi-
viduals of a subset from 19 locations (226 individuals) and 
eight samples (38 individuals), from the Malacological 
Collection of the Senckenberg-Museum Frankfurt am 
Main, of the four presumed subspecies (Table 1). The data 
set for morphological and genetic analysis overlapped 
in 105 individuals for sampled populations and two 
individuals for the museum samples. The locations of first 
descriptions for the subspecies C. u. unifasciata and C. u. 
rugosiuscula are not very well described in literature, but 
the approximate areas were included in our sampling 
scheme (see Table 1). A lectotype locality exists for C. u. 
acosmia (Gittenberger 1993) that was not sampled. However, 
in the original description (Bourguignat 1882), neither type 
locality nor distribution range were given. C. u. soosiana 
was first described from Budapest/Hungary ( Wagner 1933) 
and is represented by two Museum samples. Individuals 
were photographed through a Zeiss ZV8 binocular with 
10× enlargement from the front and 30× from above, 
always including a ruler on the image. The paper prints 
were digitalized with a resolution of 300 pixel / inch. 
Variables for the morphological analysis were chosen 
based on the original descriptions of the presumed sub-
species of C. unifasciata (Michaud 1831; Bourguignat 1882; 
Wagner 1933; Gittenberger 1993). Eight variables repres-
enting three character sets were measured by digital 
image analysis from the individuals. Shell sculpture traits as 
the first character set were measured through rib-spacing 
as an average distance between ribs, coarseness as an 
average distance between a base line and perimeter of ribs, 
and regularity of ribs as the coefficient of variation of inter-
rib distances. Size independent shell shape (shape 1, 2 and 
3) was assessed through the use of the first three relative warp 
scores of a Thin Plate Spline (TPS) analysis (Rohlf 1995). 
This geometrical analysis of shape was based on 55 land-
marks applied to an electronic image of the individual. The 
height and breadth measurements of the shell were taken. 
These standardized shell morphology variables were 
used to perform a principal component analysis (PCA) 
and discriminant analysis (DA), with <rs id="software-51" type="software">statistica</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-51" type="creator">StatSoft,Inc.</rs>. <rs corresp="#software-51" type="version-date">1995</rs>). The mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) type (A or B) 
of the respective individual resulting from 16S analysis </p>

<p>was applied as grouping variable in DA. Museum speci-
mens and not genetically typed individuals were then 
classified a posteriori with equal a priori probability to 
belong to one of the respective groups. 
Euclidean squared distance matrices between all indi-
viduals were calculated for all standardized shell varia-
bles together and for each of the 10 variables separately. 
These matrices were used to perform an analysis of mor-
phological variance in the same way as described above 
for the distance matrix derived from haplotypes. Standard 
deviations and confidence intervals of the M-statistics 
were obtained by bootstrapping 100 times over popula-
tions. Note, however, that these derived F-statistics 
(named here M ST for distinction) cannot directly be com-
pared to Spitze's (1993) Q ST and similar coefficients (e.g. 
Yang et al. 1996), because we have no information about 
the heritability of the measured traits. Estimates of herit-
ability of quantitative traits were obtained in these studies 
from elaborated breeding designs or a priori information 
about relatedness. Such information was not available for 
C. unifasciata. Hence, the presented population fixation 
indices comprise not only their genetic component, but are 
also indications of the total morphologic variance. 
Associations between genetic, morphological and geo-
graphical distance between populations were explored 
through Mantel-tests on the pairwise population fixation 
indices derived from amova analysis to test for parallel 
evolution between genetic and morphological data and 
isolation by distance, respectively. 
Partial least square (PLS) analysis was performed using 
the PLS option of the package <rs id="software-57" type="software">ntsys-pc</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-57" type="version-number">2.2f</rs> to 
assess the correlations between the average population 
values of quantitative shell traits on the one hand and environ-
mental variables for each population on the other. </p>

<p>Environmental variables </p>

<p>Information about long-term climatical conditions at the 
sites sampled for morphological analysis was obtained 
from the web sites of MeteoFrance, Deutscher Wetterdienst, 
and Bessemoulin (1989). We used annual mean temperature, 
annual mean precipitation, and mean precipitation during 
the months of June, July and August (summer precipit-
ation), and altitude, latitude and longitude as variables for 
each sampling site. The precipitation during the summer 
months was considered to be important, because most of 
the shell growth is achieved during this time. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Haplotype analyses </p>

<p>The 220 sequences were collapsed to 60 haplotypes (see 
Table 2), of which 53 (88%) were present in individuals used </p>



<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>Table 2 Distribution of C. unifasciata haplotypes (columns) at each sampled location or museum sample (rows) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 
11 
12 
13 
14 
15 
16 
17 
18 
19 
20 
21 
22 
23 
24 
25 
26 
27 
28 
29 
30 
31 
32 
33 
34 
35 
36 
37 
38 
39 
40 
41 
42 
43 
44 
45 
46 
47 
48 
49 
50 
51 
52 
53 
54 
55 
56 
57 
58 
59 
60 </p>

<p>STB 
1 1 1 
1 
STV 
2 
1 
VAU 
2 
2 
1 
MAU 
3 
1 
COU 
1 1 1 1 
SPA 
3 1 1 
REG 
1 1 
VAL 
1 
3 
SJU 
3 
5 
NAV 
4 1 
CDO 
2 
GSC 
8 
1 
1 
ROG 
1 1 1 
1 1 
ESC 
1 
7 
1 
1 1 
SIS 
2 2 
VEN 
4 
1 
EIC 
3 
3 
PTV 
2 
3 
ADR 
3 
1 1 
LUB 
2 
1 
1 1 1 
CMU 
1 1 1 1 1 
PLU 
1 
2 1 1 
LAU 
1 1 
1 1 1 
ALE 
4 
ARD 
5 
AUB 
1 
MUR 
8 
3 
2 
1 1 
MON 
3 
2 
GEX 
5 
FDE 
4 
1 
SAL 
2 
2 
1 1 
HER 
5 
CMA 
6 
MÜN 
8 
2 
FLÖ 
7 
SLE 
4 
3 
1 
WIN 
1 3 
HAL 
1 4 
JAK 
3 
DID 
1 4 
aco 
1 
soos 
1 </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2547 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>for the morphologic analysis. Therefore, our morpho-
logical analyses comprised a large part of the genetic 
variation present in Candidula unifasciata ssp. Base changes 
and indels were observed exclusively in regions known to 
be variable in molluscs (Lydeard et al. 2000). Accidental 
amplification of nuclear copies of 16S target fragments 
is therefore unlikely. The average pairwise sequence 
divergence between haplotypes was 0.038 (0.065) (mean ± 
SD) changes per site. The topology of the ML tree strongly 
suggested the presence of two fundamental haplotype 
clades named A and B (see Fig. 2). Analysing each clade 
separately, the sequence divergence between haplotype 
clades A and B was 0.209 (0.009) changes per site compared 
to 0.014 (0.010) and 0.022 (0.016) changes within clade 
A and clade B, respectively. The 16S sequences 
derived from the museum shells assigned to the subspecies 
C. u. acosmia and C. u. soosiana clustered both in haplotype 
clade A. Clade B haplotypes occurred only in populations 
COU, STB and ROG, where no clade A haplotype was 
found. </p>

<p>The frequency distribution of pairwise sequence diver-
gence estimates including sequences from the Helicellinae 
species C. gigaxii and Trochoidea geyeri, showed that the 
level of divergence between sequences belonging to clades 
A and B correspond to between rather than within species 
(Fig. 3). </p>

<p>Morphological analyses </p>

<p>The coarseness of the ribs was 0.036 (0.032) mm (mean 
± SD), their average spacing 0.147 (0.057) mm and the </p>

<p>regularity 0.274 (0.105). The first relative warp score of TPS 
analysis turned out to be a descriptor of a depressed vs. 
globular shell shape (24.95% of total shape variability), the 
second opposed roundish vs. elliptical apertures (17.87%) 
and the third score represented large apertures and a 
round periphery vs. a small aperture with an angular 
periphery of the last whorl (13.93%). The values for the 
shell size parameters were 3.828 (0.554) mm for the height, 
and 6.333 (0.854) mm for breadth. </p>

<p>0.1 changes per site </p>

<p>27 
28 
10 
26 
25 
24 
23 
22 
21 
8 
7 
6 
5 
4 
3 
2 
1 
11 
20 
18 
17 
16 
15 
14 
13 
12 
19 
29 
35 
34 
33 
32 
31 
30 
36 
37 
9 
40 
39 
38 
44 
45 
46 
47 
43 
41 
42 
51 
52 
53 
58 
57 
56 
55 
54 
48 
60 
59 
50 
49 </p>

<p>C andidula gigaxii 
H elicella conspurcata 
Trochoidea geyeri </p>

<p>clade A </p>

<p>clade B </p>

<p>96 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>94 </p>

<p>87 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>99 </p>

<p>89 </p>

<p>aco </p>

<p>soos </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Maximum likelihood tree of 16S 
haplotypes. Branch tips are labelled with 
the haplotype number. Italicised numbers 
indicate percentage bootstrap support of 
nodes from 1000 replicates; only bootstrap 
values in excess of 80% are given. The 
position of the sequence obtained from the 
museum specimen classified as Candidula 
unifasciata acosmia was labelled with 'aco', 
from C. u. soosiana with 'soos'. The two 
fundamental haplotype clades have been 
designated as clade A and clade B, 
respectively. Clade B consists exclusively of 
haplotypes from locations COU, ROG and 
STB. Haplotypes from these locations are 
not found in the clade A and vice versa. </p>



<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>The first two axes of the PCA on all eight standardized 
variables accounted for 26.5% and 24.1% of total concho-
logical variation. The plot of the factor scores on the first 
two PCA axes shows that the morph-spaces of the museum 
specimens assigned to C. u. unifasciata, C. u. acosmia and 
C. u. soosiana overlap, whereas C. u. rugosiuscula forms a 
distinct cluster (Fig. 4). However, the morph-spaces of all 
museum taxa are interconnected or enclosed by sampled 
individuals, thus forming a more or less continuous range 
of conchological variation. </p>

<p>DA </p>

<p>Using the observed fundamental haplotypes A or B as 
grouping variables in DA yielded a highly significant 
discrimination model (Wilks' λ = 0.168, appr. F [8,107] = 65.58, 
P &lt; 0.0000). All eight variables were retained in the model, 
but the single root extracted discriminated the groups mainly 
in correlation to the coarseness of the shell. The posterior 
classifications of all individuals to clades in the analysis all 
had a probability greater than 95%. The result of the DA is 
in concordance with the results from haplotype analysis 
insofar as no morphotype associated with haplotype clade 
A was found in a population with phenotypes associated 
with haplotype clade B and vice versa. The haplotype clade 
B morphs are found only in the populations COU, ROG and 
STB in the south of the investigated area. Representative 
individuals of each clade are depicted in Fig. 4. 
The museum specimens classified as C. u. unifasciata, 
C. u. acosmia and C. u. soosiana were all predicted to belong 
to the phenotype associated with haplotype clade A; the </p>

<p>specimen named C. u. rugosiuscula corresponded to the 
phenotype exhibited by individuals of clade B. </p>

<p>Partition of molecular and morphological variance </p>

<p>Most of the 16S variation (89.47%) is partitioned between 
clade A and clade B. There is moderate variation (6.92%) 
between locations within the types, but the populations 
tend to be rather uniform (3.61%). In contrast, the morpho-
logical variance component between the clades accounts for 
only 18.04% of the total variance. Most of the morphological 
variation (70.63%) is due to differences between individuals 
within populations, leaving 11.33% of conchological variation 
for differences between locations within type A and B. All vari-
ance components were significantly different from zero. 
In clade A alone, the F ST between populations is as high 
as 0.648 (0.038), indicating high phylogenetic relatedness of 
haplotypes within and very little gene flow among popu-
lations. This is not matched by overall phenotypic simil-
arity of the shells within populations, where M ST was 
estimated to be 0.292 (0.042). This difference is similar in 
type B, where the F ST was 0.777 and the corresponding 
morphological fixation index 0.219. All the above-
mentioned variance components were highly significantly 
different from zero; standard deviations for clade B are 
not given because bootstrapping populations makes no 
sense with only three populations. 
When looking at the measured traits separately, the 
picture becomes more differentiated in haplotype clade A. 
Except for the regularity of rib spacing, all fixation indices 
were significantly different from zero, indicating population </p>

<p>0,1 </p>

<p>0,2 </p>

<p>0 
0.08 
0.16 
0.24 
0.32 
0.40 
0.48 
0.56 
0.64 </p>

<p>Relative frequency </p>

<p>type A &lt;&gt; type B </p>

<p>w ithin species </p>

<p>C . unifasciata 
C . gigaxii 
&lt;&gt; </p>

<p>C andidula spec 
T. geyeri 
. &lt;&gt; </p>

<p>Pairwise sequence divergence 
[changes per site] </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Frequency distributions of pairwise 
sequence divergence between 16S rDNA 
sequences of Candidula unifasciata, C. gigaxii 
and Trochoidea geyeri. </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2549 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>differentiation. The range of M ST estimates lied between 
0.150 (0.062) for shape2 and 0.691 (0.078) for the coarse-
ness of the shell (Table 3). Because regularity of rib spacing 
was not significantly different between populations, this 
variate was omitted from subsequent analyses. </p>

<p>Mantel tests </p>

<p>The Mantel test for association between the population 
pairwise F ST and M ST was nonsignificant in all cases. There </p>

<p>was no correlation between geographical distance separating 
populations and pairwise F ST either. By contrast, geographical 
distance proved to co-vary significantly (P &lt; 0.05) with the 
overall phenotypic similarity, as well as with the variable 
height (Table 3). </p>

<p>PLS analysis </p>

<p>PLS analysis detected a significant correlation between the 
average population values of shell traits and environmental </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Scatterplot factor scores on the first two axes of Principal component analysis on shell morphological variables. Axis 1 accounts for 
26.5%, axis 2 for 24.1% of total variance. Museum specimen are labelled according to the Senckenberg Malacological Collection, where 
uni = Candidula unifasciata unifasciata, aco = C. u. acosmia, rug = C. u. rugosiuscula and soos = C. u. soosiana. Sampled individuals not typed 
genetically are represented by a cross, individuals that were genetically typed with their haplotype number (see Fig. 2). Haplotypes from 
clade A are encircled and from clade B in a square, respectively. Two individuals of each haplotype clade are shown exemplarily, 
representing the gradient of variation in shell coarseness along axis 2. The scale on each photograph represents 1 mm. </p>

<p>2550 M . P F E N N I N G E R and F . M A G N I N </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>variables for the respective sampling site (approximately 
χ 2 
[40] = 60.8, P = 0.028). The first two canonical variates 
accounted for 79.8% and 16.8% of the total squared covari-
ance between the character sets. The first canonical axis 
showed that populations with a high annual mean 
temperature lying in the south of the species range tend to 
be composed of individuals showing a coarse shell 
surface with largely spaced ribs and a depressed shell 
shape with a small aperture. The second axis revealed a 
negative correlation between the annual amount of 
precipitation and shell trait variables measuring the size 
of the specimen (see Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Two genetically and morphologically distinct 
evolutionary lineages in Candidula unifasciata ssp </p>

<p>Substantial morphologic and genetic variation within and 
among populations was detected in the present survey 
over the greatest part of the range of the taxon that was 
described as C. unifasciata ssp. The PCA on the 
morphometric data showed that the field samples used in 
the present study comprised most of the phenotypic 
variance described in this taxon, as evidenced by the </p>

<p>Table 3 Fixation indices from analysis of molecular and morphologic variance and correlation coefficients from Mantel tests between 
population pairwise M ST , F ST and geographical distance between populations for haplotype clade A (Candidula unifasciata) </p>

<p>Variable 
F ST ; M ST ± (s.d.) 
P 
r (F ST ) 
r (geo. dist.) </p>

<p>16S haplotypes 
0.648 (0.038) 
&lt; 0.001 
-
0.131 
Overall phenotypic similarity 
0.296 (0.039) 
&lt; 0.001 
0.034 
0.281* 
Shell shape 
Shape1 (depressed &lt;&gt; globular shell) 
0.195 (0.095) 
&lt; 0.001 
-0.059 
0.164 
Shape2 (round &lt;&gt; elliptical aperture) 
0.150 (0.062) 
&lt; 0.001 
-0.214 
-0.009 
Shape3 (large &lt;&gt; small aperture) 
0.381 (0.112) 
&lt; 0.001 
0.134 
0.225 
Shell size 
Breadth 
0.399 (0.088) 
&lt; 0.001 
-0.030 
0.116 
Height 
0.446 (0.071) 
&lt; 0.001 
0.024 
0.244* 
Shell sculpture 
Spacing of ribs 
0.338 (0.048) 
&lt; 0.001 
0.083 
0.029 
Coarseness of shell 
0.691 (0.078) 
&lt; 0.001 
-0.067 
0.021 
Regularity of rib spacing 
0.053 (-) 
0.057 
-0.038 
-0.032 </p>

<p>s.d. = standard deviation obtained from 100 bootstraps, P = probability of obtaining a random F ST equal or greater than the observed 
estimated from 9999 randomizations, r = Pearson's moment product correlation coefficient between pairwise among population M ST for 
all variables and F ST , and geographical distance between populations. *Indicates a significant correlation at the 5% level. </p>

<p>A X IS 2 (16.8% of total covariance) </p>

<p>-0.8 </p>

<p>-0.6 </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>-0.2 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>A X IS 1 (79.8% of total covariance) </p>

<p>-0.6 
-0.4 
-0.2 
0.0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Partial least square analysis of mean 
shell variables against environmental 
variables for all populations belonging to 
haplotype clade A (Candidula unifasciata). </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2551 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>inclusion of samples from the Malacological Collection of 
the Senckenberg Museum (see Fig. 4). Even though the 
PCA revealed a more or less continuous distribution of 
individuals in morph-space, the two highly divergent 
haplotype clades in 16S analysis indicated the presence 
of two independently evolving lineages. The sequence 
divergence between the clades was almost as high as 
between other Helicellinae species and was in the 
magnitude of those reported between genera of other 
gastropod species (Koufopanou et al. 1999; Medina &amp; 
Walsh 2000; but see Thomaz et al. 1996). 
Despite of an almost continuous morph-space when 
looking at the overall phenotypic similarity, DA yielded a 
highly significant discrimination model with the haplo-
type clade as classification variable (Table 3). This shows 
that the haplotype clade of an individual is a good predic-
tor of its morphology. Moreover, DA predicted a posteriori 
the clade membership of all individuals not screened for 
16S variation with probabilities greater than 95%. This is in 
concordance with results from the analysis of variance that 
detected a significant variance component among the 
clades that accounted for approximately 20% of the total 
morphological variance. 
The presence of two highly divergent haplotype clades 
or evolutionary lineages is therefore in concordance with 
morphological differences (Table 3, Fig. 4). This led us to 
the conclusion that there are two separately evolving line-
ages in C. unifasciata ssp. This view is strengthened by the 
observation that clade B, found only in populations ROG, 
COU and STB from the southeast of France, occurs in para-
patry to populations of clade A (Fig. 1), but was not found 
together in the same population (Table 2). This obvious 
absence of gene-flow between neighbouring populations 
of clade A and clade B suggested reproductive isolation of 
the clades. Additionally, initial surveys with allozymes 
and random amplified polymorphic DNAs indeed showed 
divergence in the nuclear genome as well (data not shown). 
The average sequence divergence among clade A and B 
equalled 0.209 changes per site. Even if we consider a very 
high mutation rate of 10% per million years, we have to 
assume that the clades diverged at least 2 million years ago. 
Most species concepts (reviewed in Hull 1997) would recog-
nize clade B as separate species in the light of the presented 
evidence. However, additional evidence, like crossbreed-
ing experiments and analyses of habitat differences, are 
needed to confirm the species status of the inferred clades. </p>

<p>Taxonomic considerations </p>

<p>Having established the presence of two genetically and 
morphologically distinct evolutionary lineages, we 
wanted to know if there were arguments that allowed 
assigning an existing taxonomic name to them. DA 
predicted that the rarer haplotype clade B corresponded </p>

<p>to museum specimen named by the collectors C. u. 
rugosiuscula as described by Michaud (1831). More 
evidence for the association of the identified evolutionary 
lineage (clade B) with this taxon arises from the 
correspondence of the morphotype with the original 
description and the fact that populations of clade B were 
found exclusively in the type area ('around Aix-en-
Provence', Michaud 1831). We will therefore refer to clade 
B individuals as C. rugosiuscula hereafter. Specimen of each 
population have been deposited in the Senckenberg-Museum, 
Frankfurt/Germany (Collection nos 322884-322886). 
The museum specimens assigned to C. u. unifasciata, 
acosmia and soosiana have overlapping morph spaces in 
PCA, which proposes that either the traits chosen by the 
original describers did not define statistically distinguish-
able entities in the first place or that they were not precise 
enough to allow successive collectors to distinguish them 
unequivocally. Corroboration of this view arises from a 
DA that failed to yield a significant morphologic discrimi-
nation model while using the taxonomic designation of the 
museum specimens as classification variable (data not 
shown). In addition, neither PCA nor 16S analysis sug-
gested that there were more than two objectively distin-
guishable groups of individuals present in our sample. The 
16S sequences obtained from museum shell material 
assigned to C. u. soosiana and C. u. acosmia belonged both to 
clade A and were, in case of the latter individual, identical 
to the widespread haplotype 4 (see Table 2). However, the 
collectors of the museum material might have misinter-
preted their findings and because the holotype locality 
for C. acosmia is unknown and the lectotype locality was 
not sampled, we cannot exclude that more than the two 
identified evolutionary lineages exist in the southeast of 
France. 
We will refer to all individuals with haplotypes of clade 
A as C. unifasciata. All sequences from the 20 populations 
that were not screened for quantitative shell variation, 
because no shell material was available, belonged to 
haplotype clade A. Since the haplotype clade has proven to 
be a good predictor for the two morphological types, it 
was likely that these populations corresponded equally to 
C. unifasciata. This confirmed our subjective impression 
of the spatial distribution of this morphotype during 
the sampling. 
The assignment of existing taxonomic names to genetic-
ally identified evolutionary lineages is difficult and arbit-
rary to a certain degree, especially when holotype material 
for morphological comparison is not available. However, 
additional support for our taxonomical interpretation of 
the presented results arises from Kerney &amp; Cameron 
(1999), where C. u. rugosiuscula is described on the basis of 
shell characteristics as only a subspecies to C. unifasciata. 
The description closely matches the morphotype associ-
ated with clade B. </p>



<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>Associations between 16S haplotypes and morphological 
variability within C. unifasciata </p>

<p>Portions of the molecular and phenotypic variation could 
be shown to be due to an obviously long lasting separa-
tion of different evolutionary lineages that we can 
regard as separate evolutionary entities C. unifasciata and 
C. rugosiuscula. As this was a rather unexpected result, we 
could not adjust the sampling scheme towards the 
inclusion of more populations of C. rugosiuscula into this 
study. This lack of data prevented us from exploring 
further the spatial distribution of phenotypic variation in 
this taxon and to compare it to the organization in C. 
unifasciata. An initial survey of the geographical distri-
bution of C. rugosiuscula suggests however, that there are 
differences in habitat preference between the two lineages. 
In the area of parapatric occurrence, C. rugosiuscula can be 
found in more Mediterranean lowland habitats, whereas 
C. unifasciata is more frequently found on mountainous 
grasslands. We are working on a study to quantify these 
differences. 
The sequence variation exhibited by mitochondrial 
markers like the 16S rRNA gene is presumably evolving in 
a selectively neutral fashion. The spatial distribution of this 
variation is therefore shaped mainly by recurrent popula-
tion processes like neutral genetic drift and gene flow as 
well as singular historic events like fragmentation of 
populations or range expansions (Avise 1994). These issues 
have been addressed in a phylogeographic framework 
elsewhere; here we wanted to study how the phenotypic 
population structure relates to the background pattern of 
selectively neutral evolution at the 16S locus. 
The results in Table 3 show that the M ST estimates for 
quantitative shell traits were significantly smaller than the 
corresponding F ST , except for the coarseness of the shell, 
which was indistinguishable from the latter. This shows 
that the populations did not diverge phenotypically to a 
level that should be expected from the estimation of neu-
tral drift among populations. If this variation is heritable, 
the large proportion of phenotypic variation within popu-
lations of C. unifasciata could be maintained by a fine-
scaled spatial population structure within land snail 
populations (e.g. Bahl et al. 1996; Pfenninger et al. 1996; 
Arnaud et al. 1999) that tends to maintain genetic diversity 
compared to an equal sized panmictic population 
(Lacy 1987). Phenotypic plasticity, common in land snails 
(Goodfriend 1986), could be another explication for the 
observed level of intrapopulation phenotypic variation. 
As mentioned above, the presented phenotypic fixation 
indices termed M ST cannot be used to infer directly the 
action or direction of natural selection, because they are 
obtained from the total morphologic variance of the quant-
itative traits and not only their genetic component (see 
Podolsky &amp; Holtsford 1995). This has the consequence that </p>

<p>we cannot distinguish between the action of natural selec-
tion, direct influences of the environment and individual 
random effects on the exhibited phenotype. The presented 
estimates, nevertheless, put an upper limit to the possible 
genetic contribution to the phenotypic among-population 
variances. There are several approaches to estimate the rel-
ative contribution in natural populations. But they are only 
feasible with elaborated breeding designs (Spitze 1993; 
Lynch et al. 1999) or independent estimates of within 
population relatedness, using nuclear markers (Yang et al. 
1996) to estimate the heritability of the investigated traits. 
Both approaches were, however, not practicable here 
because C. unifasciata does not breed in the laboratory and 
information about the relatedness of individuals in popu-
lations is not available. Recently, Ritland (2000) reviewed 
approaches to jointly estimate both heritability and among 
population genetic variances of quantitative traits with 
nuclear markers that promise much potential for future 
studies. 
The results from the Mantel-tests indicated that the null 
hypothesis of no association between population pairwise 
F ST and among population differences in shell traits could 
not be rejected within C. unifasciata (Table 3). This sug-
gested that the observed phenotypic differences have not 
evolved in concordance with the mitochondrial genome 
and resulting phenotypic population structure does not 
reflect the phylogenetic history of the populations. The 
significant phenotypic divergence among populations 
must therefore have other explanations. </p>

<p>Associations between the environment and morphological 
variability within C. unifasciata (haplotype clade A) </p>

<p>The results from PLS analysis showed that differences 
between populations in some traits co-varied significantly 
with long-term climatic conditions and information about 
the geographical position of the sampling site. Axis 1 in 
Fig. 5 shows that shells found in climatically warmer 
sampling sites in the south tend to have a coarser shell, 
larger spaced ribs, smaller apertures and more depressed 
shells. This association allows formulating hypotheses 
about the causes for these characteristics: in areas with a 
more Mediterranean climate, there are, despite of 
considerable mean annual precipitation, prolonged phases 
of drought that prevents activity of the snails in order to 
avoid desiccation. Like most other Helicidae (McQuaid 
et al. 1979), C. unifasciata manages to survive such periods 
aestivating at the roots of bushes, under stones or attached 
to the vegetation. A small aperture, minimizing the area of 
exposed surface, and a flat shell, allowing to penetrate 
deeper into the vegetation or under stones, could thus 
constitute a selective advantage by minimizing the loss of 
humidity under water stress conditions, as discussed in 
Goodfriend (1986). Association of shell shape with </p>

<p>P H E N O T Y P I C E V O L U T I O N I N C A N D I D U L A U N I F A S C I A T A 2553 </p>

<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>

<p>physical habitat conditions was found as well by Johnson 
&amp; Black (2000) in the littorine snail Bembicium vittatum. 
Because of the independence of gene flow patterns and the 
high heritability of shell shape in this species, they 
conclude that this association is due to local adaptation. 
An adaptive explanation for shell sculpture character-
istics is less readily found. Welter-Schultes (2000) found an 
altitude dependence of rib density in Albinaria idaea, that 
he attributed to the temperature gradient co-varying with 
altitude. Kemperman &amp; Gittenberger (1988) proposed 
humidity and temperature related effects like surface 
water adhesion and shell permeability as factors influencing 
shell surface adaptation in these species. However, the 
formation of coarse, large spaced ribs on the shell surface 
could be influenced, at least in part, by the irregular 
feeding opportunities forced by aestivation periods (Cameron 
1970) and thus probably be shaped mainly by environmen-
tal forces. This view was corroborated by our observation 
that the shell of C. unifasciata, after transferring them in a 
subadult stage to constant high humidity in the laboratory, 
grows much smoother. 
The second axis revealed that sampling sites with more 
annual precipitation were associated with small snails (see 
Fig. 5). This was astonishing at first sight because a humid 
climate allows more feeding activity and snails should 
therefore attain a larger size. A similar tendency of increas-
ing size with lower rainfall in small snail species was noted 
in Goodfriend (1986), and explained as a potential adapta-
tion of the area/volume ratio to reduce the loss of water in 
drier areas. Johnson &amp; Black (2000) on the other hand 
found that the growth rate was highly plastic in B. vittatum. 
Life history differences related to reproductive traits may 
as well be responsible for differences in shell size, as shown 
by Madec et al. (2000) for Helix aspersa populations. It is 
possible that C. unifasciata reaches sexual maturity, after 
which there is no further shell growth, earlier in wetter 
places in order to reproduce earlier. This would offer the 
next generation the possibility to reach a bigger size before 
winter. Early reproduction could thus constitute a selective 
advantage because winter mortality in juveniles has been 
shown to be size dependent in H. aspersa (Madec et al. 
2000). Further experiments are needed to determine 
whether the size/precipitation correlation in C. unifasciata 
is due to phenotypic plasticity in response to the prevailing 
conditions or whether it has an adaptational significance. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>We consider the phenotypic and phylogenetic divergence 
between the two identified lineages as sufficiently large to 
propose the presence of two distinct evolutionary entities 
described as Candidula unifasciata and C. rugosiuscula, 
though additional studies are necessary to confirm a 
species status for the latter. In the absence of obvious </p>

<p>qualitative characters to distinguish the two lineages, only 
the joint statistical analysis of molecular genetic variation 
and quantitative shell traits was able to reveal this hidden 
divergence. 
On the intraspecific level, the correlation of among popu-
lation divergence to environmental variables in C. unifas-
ciata allowed formulating hypotheses about their adaptive 
value. These hypotheses can now be tested in future stud-
ies. Integrating environmental, phenotypic and genetic 
data was thus a major step from observing and describing 
patterns to the understanding of the underlying evolution-
ary processes. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>Part of this study was performed during the postdoctorate of M.P. 
at IMEP in Marseille, financed by a grant of the DAAD (No). We 
thank Dr R. Janssen for providing the shell material from Malaco-
logical Collection of the Senckenberg museum/Frankfurt am 
Main. Discussions with Anne Pfenninger, Klaus Schwenk and 
Tom Wilke improved the manuscript. Comments of three referees 
improved the manuscript further. We thank John Majstrick for his 
patience during his trials to amplify 16S from museum material. </p>





<p>© 2001 Blackwell Science Ltd, Molecular Ecology, 10, 2541-2554 </p>



</text></tei>