<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2008-02-WATERBIRDS" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:13+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>brown eye color, dark versus light hair and fair skin 16-18 . Expanding 
on a discovery initially made in zebrafish, a coding SNP in 
the SLC24A5 gene (encoding solute carrier family 24, member 5) 
was recently found to be associated with skin pigmentation in 
admixed African-American and African-Caribbean populations 19 . 
Similar gene-association approaches have been used to relate variants 
in MATP (encoding membrane-associated transporter protein, also 
known as SLC45A2) 20 , ASIP (encoding agouti signaling protein, non-
agouti homolog (mouse)) 21 and TYR (encoding tyrosinase) 22 to 
differences in skin pigmentation among populations of mixed African 
and European ancestry. 
Several recent evolutionary analyses have yielded signals of positive 
selection in different sets of pigmentation candidate genes in popula-
tions of European and East Asian ancestry, but there is little evidence 
for selection in populations of African ancestry 23-26 . This supports 
the idea that dark pigmentation represents the ancestral state in 
humans and that the lighter pigmentation of European and East 
Asian groups can be traced to convergent selective sweeps of muta-
tions in different genes. 
With the aim of identifying variants that affect the variability of 
normal pigmentation in humans, we carried out a genome-wide 
association scan for sequence variants that influence hair color, eye 
color, freckles and skin sensitivity to sun using a set of 317,511 SNPs 
genotyped in 2,986 Icelanders. Promising SNPs were tested in replica-
tion samples of 2,718 Icelanders and 1,214 Dutch. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The frequencies of variants associated with natural hair and eye color, 
skin sensitivity and the presence of freckles in the two Icelandic 
samples and the Dutch sample are shown according to sex in 
Table 1. The samples are broadly similar, although the Icelanders 
have red hair, freckles and green eyes more often and brown eyes less </p>

<p>often. The most notable difference between the sexes is the higher 
frequency of green eyes and freckles in females. The higher frequency 
of green eyes in females is consistent with a previous report in which 
eye color was assessed by a single expert 18 . 
We examined the association of sequence variants with pigmenta-
tion traits in six genome-wide association scans of the Icelandic 
discovery sample. We carried out two scans for eye color (blue versus 
green and blue versus brown), two for hair color (red versus non-red 
and blond versus brown) and two for skin pigment traits (skin 
sensitivity to sun and the presence of freckles). Overall, these genome 
scans revealed 104 associations that reached genome-wide significance 
(P o 1.5 Â 10 -7 ), accounted for by 60 distinct SNPs (Supplementary 
Table 1 online), of which 32 showed genome-wide association with 
only one pigmentation trait, 12 with two traits and 16 with three traits. 
The 60 SNPs were clustered in different genomic regions along five 
different chromosomes (6, 12, 14, 15 and 16; Supplementary Figs. 1-5 
online), with the largest covering 1 Mb on chromosome 16 and the 
smallest covering a single SNP on chromosome 12. Notably, two of the 
regions overlap with or are near well-known pigmentation genes 
(MC1R on chromosome 16 and OCA2 on chromosome 15), and 
one of the regions is near a strong candidate pigmentation gene 
(KITLG on chromosome 12, which encodes the KIT ligand). One of 
the remaining two regions overlaps with SLC24A4 on chromosome 14, 
which belongs to the same family as SLC24A5, a recently discovered 
pigmentation gene 19 . The other is located between IRF4 (encoding 
interferon regulatory factor 4) and EXOC2 (also known as SEC5L1, 
and encoding exocyst complex component 2) on chromosome 6, 
neither of which has previously been reported to affect pigmentation. 
We defined a subset of seven SNPs that capture the strongest 
association signals within these five regions from the Icelandic dis-
covery sample. In addition, we chose two SNPs located in TYR, a key 
pigmentation gene on chromosome 11, that showed associations that </p>

<p>Table 1 Frequencies of eye, hair and skin pigmentation types among Icelandic and Dutch individuals a </p>

<p>Iceland discovery group (N ¼ 2,986) 
Iceland replication group (N ¼ 2,718) 
Dutch group (N ¼ 1,214) </p>

<p>Pigmentation type 
Male (N ¼ 911) 
Female (N ¼ 2,075) 
Male (N ¼ 1,153) 
Female (N ¼ 1,565) 
Male (N ¼ 696) 
Female (N ¼ 518) </p>

<p>Eye 
Blue or gray 
80.0 
70.3 
79.6 
68.2 
69.5 
52.3 </p>

<p>Green 
8.0 
17.9 
9.7 
21.0 
5.6 
17.2 
Brown or black 
9.9 
10.3 
8.1 
8.6 
19.1 
24.3 </p>

<p>Other or unknown 
2.1 
1.5 
2.6 
2.2 
5.7 
7.4 </p>

<p>Hair 
Red or reddish 
6.1 
8.1 
5.9 
7.6 
1.9 
3.3 </p>

<p>Blond 
15.3 
15.2 
14.7 
17.4 
22.1 
19.7 
Dark blond or light brown 
50.8 
48.1 
53.2 
45.8 
50.9 
50.2 </p>

<p>Dark brown or black 
26.1 
26.3 
23.9 
28.1 
25.0 
26.8 
Unknown 
1.6 
2.3 
2.3 
1.1 
0.1 
0.0 </p>

<p>Skin sensitivity to sun b </p>

<p>Positive 
29.3 
35.5 
29.0 
34.2 
36.5 
46.5 </p>

<p>Negative 
66.0 
58.6 
66.3 
59.6 
63.3 
53.5 
Unknown 
4.7 
5.9 
4.7 
6.1 
0.2 
0.0 </p>

<p>Freckles </p>

<p>Present 
38.4 
50.8 
42.8 
60.3 
29.3 
45.2 
Absent 
57.3 
45.4 
55.5 
38.3 
70.1 
54.1 </p>

<p>Unknown 
4.3 
3.7 
1.6 
1.3 
0.6 
0.8 </p>

<p>a Frequencies are given in percentages. b Based on the Fitzpatrick score in the Icelandic samples. Estimated from related questions in the Dutch sample (see Methods). </p>

<p>1 4 4 4 </p>

<p>VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>were near genome-wide significance in two of the scans (P o 6 Â 10 -6 ; 
Supplementary Fig. 6 online). No SNPs in the other candidate genes 
remained significant after correcting for the number of SNPs in these 
candidate genes, possibly owing to the lack of power. All nine SNPs 
showed similar strength of association with the same pigmentation 
traits in the Icelandic and Dutch replication samples (Tables 2-4 
and Supplementary Table 2 online). They were also all significant in </p>

<p>the combined discovery and replication samples, after correction for 
the 317,511 SNPs tested and the six genome-wide scans carried out 
(P o 2.6 Â 10 -8 ). We summarize the primary and secondary 
pigmentation traits that are associated with the SNPs in these six 
genomic regions (Fig. 1) in separate sections below and discuss 
whether they have been subject to positive selection (Supplementary 
Table 3 online). </p>

<p>Table 2 Association of genetic variants with eye color in the two Icelandic and one Dutch sample a </p>

<p>Iceland </p>

<p>Locus 
Variant 
Discovery OR (95% CI) 
Replication OR (95% CI) 
Netherlands OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Blue versus brown eyes </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
1.15 (0.95, 1.38) 
1.29 (1.05, 1.59) 
1.12 (0.91, 1.36) 
0.032 
KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
1.13 (0.89, 1.42) 
1.20 (0.92, 1.56) 
0.96 (0.71, 1.30) 
0.31 </p>

<p>6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
1.11 (0.93, 1.34) 
1.18 (0.95, 1.46) 
1.07 (0.87, 1.30) 
0.10 
TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.20 (0.98, 1.47) 
1.27 (1.01, 1.60) 
1.18 (0.94, 1.48) 
0.0044 </p>

<p>rs1042602 C 
1.01 (0.83, 1.24) 
0.99 (0.78, 1.25) 
0.97 (0.79, 1.19) 
1.00 
OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
29.43 (21.47, 40.35) 
18.46 (12.93, 26.35) 
15.34 (10.75, 21.88) 
1.3 Â 10 -241 </p>

<p>rs7495174 A 
6.90 (3.85, 12.39) 
5.56 (3.02, 10.23) 
4.87 (2.43, 9.74) 
3.0 Â 10 -24 </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
1.15 (0.87, 1.52) 
1.02 (0.77, 1.35) 
1.29 (0.88, 1.89) 
0.20 
rs1805007 T 
1.37 (0.98, 1.93) 
0.95 (0.70, 1.28) 
0.90 (0.60, 1.36) 
0.044 </p>

<p>Blue versus green eyes </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
2.06 (1.76, 2.42) 
1.49 (1.27, 1.73) 
2.08 (1.58, 2.74) 
4.1 Â 10 -38 </p>

<p>KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
0.92 (0.76, 1.11) 
1.09 (0.90, 1.33) 
1.18 (0.78, 1.80) 
0.34 
6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
0.99 (0.85, 1.16) 
1.14 (0.98, 1.33) 
0.88 (0.68, 1.15) 
0.59 </p>

<p>TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.52 (1.28, 1.81) 
1.43 (1.21, 1.71) 
1.38 (1.01, 1.89) 
3.3 Â 10 -12 
rs1042602 C 
1.08 (0.91, 1.27) 
0.88 (0.74, 1.05) 
1.16 (0.88, 1.52) 
0.11 </p>

<p>OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
6.74 (4.61, 9.83) 
5.83 (4.07, 8.36) 
5.96 (3.48, 10.21) 
1.5 Â 10 -53 
rs7495174 A 
1.41 (0.75, 2.62) 
2.02 (1.12, 3.65) 
1.45 (0.52, 4.01) 
0.11 </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
1.04 (0.83, 1.31) 
0.85 (0.69, 1.04) 
0.87 (0.55, 1.37) 
0.92 
rs1805007 T 
0.94 (0.73, 1.22) 
0.74 (0.59, 0.92) 
1.12 (0.63, 1.98) 
0.73 </p>

<p>a The three samples consisted of 2,986 Icelandic discovery individuals, 2,718 Icelandic replication individuals and 1,214 Dutch replication individuals. </p>

<p>Proteins encoded by each gene: KITLG, KIT ligand; MC1R, melanocortin 1 receptor; OCA2, oculocutaneous albinism II; SLC24A4, solute carrier family 24, member 4; TYR, tyrosine. </p>

<p>Table 3 Association of genetic variants with hair color in the two Icelandic and one Dutch sample a </p>

<p>Iceland </p>

<p>Locus 
Variant 
Discovery OR (95% CI) 
Replication OR (95% CI) 
Netherlands OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Red versus non-red hair </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
1.06 (0.85, 1.31) 
1.07 (0.85, 1.34) 
0.88 (0.52, 1.49) 
0.56 </p>

<p>KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
1.01 (0.78, 1.31) 
0.88 (0.67, 1.17) 
0.65 (0.27, 1.55) 
0.84 
6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
1.01 (0.82, 1.24) 
1.18 (0.94, 1.48) 
1.05 (0.63, 1.76) 
0.88 </p>

<p>TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.04 (0.83, 1.30) 
1.05 (0.82, 1.34) 
0.79 (0.43, 1.45) 
0.81 
rs1042602 C 
0.86 (0.69, 1.07) 
0.98 (0.77, 1.27) 
1.21 (0.71, 2.07) 
0.14 </p>

<p>OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
0.91 (0.58, 1.44) 
0.81 (0.49, 1.33) 
1.44 (0.53, 3.96) 
0.83 
rs7495174 A 
1.49 (0.70, 3.18) 
1.26 (0.58, 2.73) 
1.15 (0.23, 5.73) 
0.16 </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
7.86 (5.96, 10.36) 
4.53 (3.55, 5.77) 
3.71 (1.85, 7.43) 
4.2 Â 10 -95 
rs1805007 T 
12.47 (9.37, 16.60) 
6.12 (4.78, 7.82) 
13.02 (7.02, 24.16) 
2.0 Â 10 -142 </p>

<p>Blond versus brown hair </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
2.56 (2.12, 3.09) 
2.34 (1.94, 2.82) 
1.86 (1.47, 2.36) 
1.4 Â 10 -48 </p>

<p>KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
2.32 (1.86, 2.89) 
1.90 (1.52, 2.38) 
2.43 (1.67, 3.54) 
3.8 Â 10 -30 
6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
0.69 (0.58, 0.82) 
0.85 (0.71, 1.03) 
0.92 (0.73, 1.17) 
1.1 Â 10 -7 </p>

<p>TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.29 (1.06, 1.56) 
1.36 (1.12, 1.66) 
1.22 (0.94, 1.59) 
0.00011 </p>

<p>rs1042602 C 
0.85 (0.70, 1.03) 
0.81 (0.66, 1.00) 
0.94 (0.74, 1.20) 
0.021 
OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
4.94 (3.16, 7.71) 
5.96 (3.73, 9.52) 
5.51 (3.49, 8.69) 
5.5 Â 10 -35 </p>

<p>rs7495174 A 
1.92 (0.95, 3.90) 
1.84 (0.86, 3.95) 
0.82 (0.40, 1.68) 
0.070 
MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
1.88 (1.40, 2.51) 
1.74 (1.33, 2.28) 
1.93 (1.25, 2.96) 
2.2 Â 10 -11 </p>

<p>rs1805007 T 
2.34 (1.69, 3.24) 
2.00 (1.52, 2.64) 
1.59 (0.95, 2.66) 
1.9 Â 10 -13 </p>

<p>a The three samples consisted of 2,986 Icelandic discovery individuals, 2,718 Icelandic replication individuals and 1,214 Dutch replication individuals. </p>

<p>Proteins encoded by each gene: KITLG, KIT ligand; MC1R, melanocortin 1 receptor; OCA2, oculocutaneous albinism II; SLC24A4, solute carrier family 24, member 4; TYR, tyrosine. </p>

<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>MC1R 
A total of 38 SNPs spanning a 1-Mb region of strong linkage 
disequilibrium (LD) on chromosome 16 showed an association with 
red hair, skin sensitivity to sun and freckles that reached genome-wide 
significance, and they also showed a trend towards association with 
blond hair. The SNP rs4785763 most effectively captured the associa-
tion (odds ratio (OR) ¼ 5.62, P ¼ 3.2 Â 10 -56 for red hair, OR ¼ 2.03, 
P ¼ 1.2 Â 10 -33 for freckles). This region contains the well-
documented MC1R gene. More than 30 non-synonymous mutations 
have been described in populations of European ancestry that impair 
the normal function of the MC1R gene product 13,14 , leading to the 
generation of melanosomes that contain red-yellow pheomelanin 
rather than brown-black eumelanin 4,27 and resulting in pigmentation 
traits such as red and blond hair, freckles, fair skin and sensitivity to 
UVR 12,13 . Two non-synonymous MC1R mutations are common 
enough in European populations to have a major effect on normal 
differences in pigmentation: R151C (rs1805007) and R160W 
(rs1805008) 14 , neither of which is assayed on the Illumina 317K 
SNP chip. After genotyping these SNPs in the Icelandic and Dutch 
samples, we found that their T alleles (that is, the mutated alleles) were 
correlated with the A allele of rs4785763 and that the strong associa-
tion with rs4785763 disappeared in both samples when adjusted for 
rs1805007 and rs1805008. We therefore concluded that the association 
signal detected in the genome scan is due to the previously docu-
mented non-synonymous mutations in MC1R. 
The T alleles of rs1805007 and rs1805008 are found at a frequency 
of 0.142 and 0.108, respectively, in the CEPH Utah (CEU) HapMap 
sample, but are not present in the East Asian (ASN) and Nigerian 
Yoruban (YRI) HapMap samples 28 . Although this represents only a 
moderate level of population divergence and is not consistent with 
strong selective sweep on these variants in European populations, we 
note that only 5.13% of HapMap SNPs that have the same overall 
frequency in the CEU and ASN samples show a greater difference 
between these populations. Moreover, only 6.6% and 6.2% of the </p>

<p>alleles with equal frequencies in the CEU sample have greater extended 
haplotype homozygosity (based on the irEHH (integrated relative 
extended haplotype homozygosity) statistic; see Methods) than the 
rs1805007 and rs1805008 T alleles, respectively. These findings suggest 
that both mutated alleles may have been at least weakly affected by 
recent positive selection. </p>

<p>6p25.3 
Two SNPs that lie only 8 kb apart in region 6p25.3, rs4959270 and 
rs1540771, showed association with the presence of freckles in the 
Icelandic sample that reached genome-wide significance (Supplemen-
tary Table 1). This small segment lies between two genes, SEC5L1 and 
IRF4, neither of which is an obvious pigmentation candidate gene; no 
such genes are found within the LD range of the two SNPs. Although 
strongly correlated (r 2 ¼ 0.77), the A allele of rs1540771 had the 
stronger association (OR ¼ 1.40, P ¼ 1.9 Â 10 -9 ) and remained 
significant after adjusting for rs4959270 (P ¼ 0.043), whereas the 
association of rs495270, adjusted for rs1540771, did not remain 
significant (P ¼ 0.34). The association of rs1540771 with freckles 
was confirmed in the Icelandic and Dutch replication samples 
(Table 4). Notably, the A allele of rs1540771 shows secondary 
associations with brown (rather than blond) hair and with skin that 
is sensitive to UVR (Fig. 1 and Tables 3 and 4). Thus, like MC1R, the 
variant on 6p25.3 that is associated with freckles is also associated with 
sun sensitivity, but unlike MC1R, it shows no association with red hair. 
The frequency of the rs1540771 A allele is approximately 50% in 
European populations, but 30% and 5% in the East Asian and YRI 
HapMap samples, respectively (6.3% of HapMap SNPs of a similar 
frequency in the CEU and YRI HapMap samples differ more in 
frequency), and only 4.1% of alleles at the same frequency in the 
CEU HapMap data set have greater irEHH values. This suggests that 
the rs1540771 A allele has been subject to positive selection in 
European populations, perhaps owing to its effect on reduced skin 
pigmentation. In addition, SNPs that are near rs1540771 were recently </p>

<p>Table 4 Association of genetic variants with skin sensitivity to sun and freckles in the two Icelandic and one Dutch sample a </p>

<p>Iceland </p>

<p>Locus 
Variant 
Discovery OR (95% CI) 
Replication OR (95% CI) 
Netherlands OR (95% CI) 
P </p>

<p>Skin sensitivity to sun </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
1.21 (1.07, 1.36) 
1.04 (0.92, 1.18) 
0.98 (0.84, 1.16) 
0.00035 
KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
1.07 (0.93, 1.24) 
1.22 (1.05, 1.42) 
0.84 (0.66, 1.08) 
0.71 </p>

<p>6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
1.21 (1.08, 1.36) 
1.12 (0.99, 1.26) 
1.12 (0.95, 1.32) 
4.0 Â 10 -6 
TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.26 (1.11, 1.43) 
1.49 (1.31, 1.70) 
1.11 (0.92, 1.34) 
1.6 Â 10 -6 </p>

<p>rs1042602 C 
0.96 (0.85, 1.09) 
1.05 (0.91, 1.20) 
0.87 (0.73, 1.02) 
0.12 
OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
1.24 (0.95, 1.62) 
1.24 (0.93, 1.65) 
1.34 (1.00, 1.81) 
0.0034 </p>

<p>rs7495174 A 
1.30 (0.87, 1.96) 
0.99 (0.64, 1.53) 
1.65 (1.03, 2.63) 
0.17 </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
2.30 (1.94, 2.73) 
2.07 (1.77, 2.43) 
1.65 (1.23, 2.20) 
1.8 Â 10 -43 
rs1805007 T 
2.94 (2.42, 3.58) 
2.51 (2.11, 2.98) 
2.01 (1.44, 2.81) 
1.8 Â 10 -55 </p>

<p>Freckles </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T 
0.99 (0.88, 1.11) 
1.04 (0.92, 1.16) 
1.03 (0.87, 1.22) 
1.00 </p>

<p>KITLG 
rs12821256 C 
0.89 (0.78, 1.02) 
1.01 (0.88, 1.17) 
0.96 (0.75, 1.24) 
0.074 
6p25.3 
rs1540771 A 
1.40 (1.26, 1.57) 
1.25 (1.11, 1.40) 
1.26 (1.06, 1.49) 
3.7 Â 10 -18 </p>

<p>TYR 
rs1393350 A 
1.13 (1.00, 1.28) 
1.13 (1.00, 1.28) 
1.10 (0.91, 1.32) 
0.0029 
rs1042602 C 
1.32 (1.17, 1.49) 
1.39 (1.22, 1.58) 
1.23 (1.04, 1.46) 
1.5 Â 10 -11 </p>

<p>OCA2 
rs1667394 A 
1.16 (0.90, 1.48) 
1.09 (0.83, 1.41) 
1.39 (1.02, 1.88) 
0.026 
rs7495174 A 
0.84 (0.58, 1.21) 
0.82 (0.55, 1.23) 
1.04 (0.65, 1.66) 
0.29 </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T 
2.63 (2.21, 3.11) 
2.49 (2.11, 2.93) 
2.06 (1.54, 2.76) 
2.8 Â 10 -60 
rs1805007 T 
4.37 (3.56, 5.37) 
2.54 (2.13, 3.04) 
3.96 (2.81, 5.58) 
1.2 Â 10 -96 </p>

<p>a The three samples consisted of 2,986 Icelandic discovery individuals, 2,718 Icelandic replication individuals and 1,214 Dutch replication individuals. </p>

<p>Proteins encoded by each gene: KITLG, KIT ligand; MC1R, melanocortin 1 receptor; OCA2, oculocutaneous albinism II; SLC24A4, solute carrier family 24, member 4; TYR, tyrosine. </p>

<p>1 4 4 6 </p>

<p>VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>shown to be among the SNPs most strongly 
associated with geographic location in a 
British population 29 . </p>

<p>Tyrosinase 
The two SNPs in TYR chosen for replication, 
rs1042602 and rs1393350, are found in the 
same block of LD (r 2 ¼ 0.16 in the Icelandic 
sample), but their pigmentation association 
effects are essentially independent. The asso-
ciation of rs1042602 (a non-synonymous 
S192Y mutation) with freckles in the 
Icelandic discovery sample was close to 
reaching genome-wide significance (OR ¼ 
1.32, P ¼ 5.3 Â 10 -6 ), which was con-
firmed in the replication samples (combined 
P ¼ 1.5 Â 10 -11 ; Table 4). Although previous 
studies have reported that this SNP may be 
associated with skin 22 and eye color 17 , we did 
not detect an association with any of the 
pigmentation traits studied other than 
freckles. This sets rs1042602 apart from the 
variants in MC1R and 6p25.3, where the 
association with freckles is accompanied by 
an association with sun sensitivity and hair 
color (Fig. 1). The ancestral C allele of 
rs1042602 is fixed in the East Asian and 
YRI HapMap samples, whereas the A allele 
is found at a frequency of approximately 35% 
in European populations. There is strong 
evidence that the rs1042602 A allele (which is associated with the 
absence of freckles) has been subject to positive selection in European 
populations (Supplementary Table 3). Thus, only 1.7% of compar-
able HapMap SNPs show greater frequency differences between the 
CEU and YRI samples and only 0.37% show greater frequency 
differences between the CEU and East Asian samples. Moreover, 
only 0.55% of alleles of the same frequency in the HapMap CEU 
samples have greater or equal irEHH values. 
The second SNP in TYR chosen for replication, rs1393350, is 
strongly correlated with the rs1126809 SNP, which codes for a 
non-synonymous R402Q mutation (D¢ ¼ 1 and r 2 ¼ 0.86). The 
association of the A allele of rs1393350 with blue versus green eye 
color was close to reaching genome-wide significance (OR ¼ 1.52, 
P ¼ 2.0 Â 10 -6 ), which was confirmed in the replication samples 
(combined P ¼ 3.3 Â 10 -12 ; Table 2). For this SNP, the greatest 
difference in allele frequency was between blue-and green-eyed 
individuals, with brown-eyed individuals having an intermediate 
frequency (Fig. 1). In addition to the primary association with eye 
color, possible secondary associations with blond versus brown hair 
and with skin sensitivity to sun were also detected (Tables 3 and 4). 
However, despite the pleiotropic effect of rs1393350 on pigmentation 
traits, we found no evidence for the action of positive selection based 
on population divergence or extended haplotype homozygosity. </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
Three SNPs (rs4904864, rs4904868 and rs2402130) in a 37-kb region 
on chromosome 14 showed association with blond versus brown hair 
and blue versus green eyes in the Icelandic discovery sample that 
reached genome-wide significance (all P o 1.9 Â 10 -8 , Supplementary 
Table 1). This region is located within a single block of LD that 
contains the first exons of SLC24A4. This is the first report of any link </p>

<p>between pigmentation and variants in SLC24A4, but the gene belongs 
to the same family as SLC24A5, which is a recently discovered 
pigmentation gene 19 . No common SNPs at SLC24A5 are available in 
our data set; all SNPs in the region have a frequency of less than 1%. 
Analysis of two SNP haplotypes from the Illumina 317K chip within 
the block of LD revealed that the haplotypic combination of the 
rs4904868 C allele and the rs2402130 A allele had a stronger and 
more significant association with pigmentation traits than any of the 
three individual SNPs in the Icelandic discovery sample (OR ¼ 2.56, 
P ¼ 8.5 Â 10 -24 for blond versus brown hair and OR ¼ 2.06, 
P ¼ 2.0 Â 10 -18 for blue versus green eyes). This haplotype almost 
completely accounted for the association signal provided by the three 
SNPs individually, with adjusted association P values that were greater 
than 0.25, except for the association of rs4904868 with blond versus 
brown hair (P ¼ 0.032). An analysis of the HapMap data revealed that 
the haplotype tags (r 2 ¼ 1) a group of equivalent SNP alleles 
(rs12896399 T allele, rs4904866 T allele, rs1885194 C allele and 
rs17184180 A allele) that have a frequency of 60% in the CEU sample 
but less than 1% in the YRI sample. The T allele of rs12896399 showed 
a similarly strong association with blond versus brown hair and blue 
versus green eyes in the Icelandic and Dutch replication samples as in 
the Icelandic discovery sample (Tables 2 and 3). 
The high frequency of the rs12896399 T allele in the CEU HapMap 
sample relative to the frequency in the YRI HapMap sample (2.1% of 
autosomal SNPs in HapMap show a greater difference in frequency) 
and the low diversity of CEU haplotypes that carry this allele (6.4% of 
alleles found at 60% frequency in the CEU sample have greater irEHH 
values) suggest that it may have been influenced by positive selection 
in European populations. 
Note that in the Icelandic and Dutch samples, the greatest 
difference in allele frequency for rs12896399 was between blue-and </p>

<p>KITLG 
rs12821256 C </p>

<p>OCA2 
rs1667394 A </p>

<p>SLC24A4 
rs12896399 T </p>

<p>TYR R402Q 
rs1393350 A </p>

<p>TYR S192Y 
rs1042602 C </p>

<p>CHR 6 
rs1540771 A </p>

<p>MC1R 
rs1805008 T </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>66 </p>

<p>46 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>Frequency 
Blue Green Brown 
Red Blond 
Dark 
blond 
Brown 
Sensitive 
to sun 
Freckles </p>

<p>Eye color 
Hair color 
Skin </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>Frequency: 
Low 
High </p>

<p>Figure 1 A schematic representation of how different genetic variants are associated with pigmentation. 
For eye and hair color, each cell shows how frequent the genetic variant is for each phenotype relative 
to the population frequency of the variant. For sun sensitivity and freckles, each cell shows how 
frequent the variant is in this group compared with people who are not sensitive to sun or have not had 
freckles, respectively. The OR scale is used to compare frequencies. For simplicity, only cells that 
correspond to characteristics with significant association (P o 0.001) are colored. Cells that 
correspond to highly significant results from the six genome-wide scans are marked with an asterisk 
(P o 1 Â 10 -8 ). For simplicity, only one variant is shown for each of the MC1R and OCA2 genes, as 
the other variants have different association profiles for both genes. CHR, chromosome. Proteins 
encoded by each gene: KITLG, KIT ligand; SLC24A4, solute carrier family 24, member 4; TYR, tyrosine. </p>

<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>green-eyed individuals, which is similar to what was observed 
for the second TYR variant (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>OCA2 
A total of 16 SNPs, spanning 1 Mb on chromosome 15, showed 
association with blue versus brown eyes, blue versus green eyes, blond 
versus brown hair or some combination of these traits in the Icelandic 
sample that reached genome-wide significance (Supplementary 
Table 1). This region overlaps with the well-known gene OCA2, rare 
mutations of which have long been known to be a major cause of 
albinism 16,17 . A recent study reported three common variants in 
intron 1 of OCA2 (rs7495174, rs6497268 and rs11855019), which 
are strongly associated with eye, hair and skin pigmentation in 
populations of European ancestry 18 . Although all three SNPs were 
among the 16 detected in our genome scan, rs1667394 showed the 
strongest association (OR ¼ 35.42, P ¼ 1.4 Â 10 -124 for blue versus 
brown eyes, OR ¼ 7.02, P ¼ 5.1 Â 10 -25 for blue versus green eyes, 
and OR ¼ 5.62, P ¼ 4.4 Â 10 -16 for blond versus brown hair); this 
SNP is located 200 kb downstream of OCA2, within intron 4 of 
HERC2 (encoding the protein hect domain and RLD 2). For each of 
the three pigmentation traits, the rs1667394 association was stronger 
in the Icelandic discovery sample than the individual association of the 
three previously reported SNPs. Furthermore, the rs1667394 associa-
tion remained significant after adjustment for all haplotypes over the 
other three SNPs. However, as the link between OCA2 and pigmenta-
tion is well established, it seems unlikely that the association signal 
provided by rs1667394 was due to a functional effect on HERC2. 
Rather, it may be that sequence variation in the introns of HERC2 
affects the expression of OCA2 or possibly that as yet unidentified 
functional variants exist within OCA2 that correlate with rs1667394. 
The pattern of association of the rs1667394 A allele with hair and 
eye color was one of a gradient of reduced pigmentation, with the 
lowest allele frequency in brown-haired and brown-eyed individuals 
and the highest frequency in blond-haired and blue-eyed individuals. 
We note that the same kind of gradient was observed for the 
association of the rs1393350 A allele in TYR and the rs12896399 
T allele in SLC24A4 with hair color, but not with eye color (Fig. 1). It 
is also notable that the nominal association with skin sensitivity to sun 
observed in both the TYR and SLC24A4 variants was not present for 
the OCA2 variants, even though OCA2 showed stronger association 
with both eye and hair color (Fig. 1 and Table 4). 
The A allele of rs1667394 is found at a frequency of 80-90% in 
northern European populations. Several studies have reported that 
there is extremely strong positive selection acting on pigmentation, 
reducing the number of OCA2 variants in populations of European 
ancestry 23-25 . Similarly, we found that only 0.54% of HapMap SNPs 
show greater divergence than rs1667394 between the CEU and YRI 
samples, and 0.66% of HapMap SNPs show greater divergence 
between the CEU and East Asian samples. Furthermore, only 0.32% 
of HapMap SNPs in the CEU sample have an irEHH value that is 
greater than or equal to that observed for the rs1667394 A allele. </p>

<p>KITLG 
A single SNP on 12q21.33, rs12821256, showed genome-wide sig-
nificance in the initial scan for association with blond versus brown 
hair (OR ¼ 2.32, P ¼ 1.9 Â 10 -14 ). This association was confirmed in 
both replication samples (Table 3). The gene nearest to rs12821256 is 
KITLG (encoding the ligand for KIT receptor tyrosine kinase), a 
pigmentation candidate gene that has a role in controlling the 
migration, survival and proliferation of melanocytes 30 . Rare mutations 
in the mouse homolog of KITLG are known to affect coat color 31 , but </p>

<p>no association with pigmentation has so far been reported for the 
human gene 30 . This SNP lies 350 kb upstream of KITLG and may 
affect the expression of the gene, or may be in LD with a SNP that 
affects its expression. This idea is supported by the fact that the mouse 
homolog of KITLG is regulated by a region that is 100-300 kb 
upstream of the gene 30 . 
Four recent studies uncovered a strong signal suggestive of positive 
selection in both European and East Asian populations at 
KITLG 23,24,26,32 . This signal stems from an extended haplotype span-
ning a 400-kb region that is centered on the gene and is found at 
frequencies of 80%, 63% and 3% in the CEU, East Asian and YRI 
HapMap samples, respectively. We did not find that the alleles tagging 
this haplotype were consistently associated with any of the six 
pigmentation traits. Notably, the blond hair-associated rs12821256 
C allele was found almost exclusively on the background of this 
extended haplotype in populations of European ancestry (at a fre-
quency of approximately 15%), but is not present in the YRI or East 
Asian HapMap samples. Only 1.65% of alleles at the same frequency 
in the CEU HapMap sample have greater or equal irEHH values. 
However, the irEHH value of the rs12821256 C allele was substantially 
reduced when examined only on the background of the extended 
haplotype. Thus, the rs12821256 C allele is not itself under positive 
selection, but rather is a hitch-hiker whose frequency is driven up by 
some selective advantage that is conferred by the extended haplotype. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Although numerous genes have been identified as candidates for 
pigmentation through animal models or linkage to diseases with 
mendelian patterns of inheritance, most of the genetic variants that 
contribute to the variability of normal human pigmentation remain 
unknown. Based on genome-wide association scans, we have identi-
fied several new variants that account for differences in the pigmenta-
tion of eyes, hair and skin among individuals of European ancestry. 
Except for the variant in 6p25.3, these variants are located within or 
near genes that have either been proposed by others as pigmentation 
candidate genes (KITLG and TYR) or have homology to known 
candidates (SLC24A4). 
Each of these variants can be viewed as having a high minor allele 
frequency and a moderate effect on pigmentation in Europeans, with 
allelic ORs in the range of 1.2-2.5. This contrasts with the large effect 
but lower minor allele frequency of variants from the remaining two 
genes detected in our genome scan, MC1R and OCA2, which were 
described in previous reports 12,15 . It is also fascinating to note the 
apparent differences in the observed association of the different 
variants with the pigmentation characteristics, with some variants 
associated with many characteristics and others with only one. 
Examples are the striking difference in the pattern of association 
with eye color for the TYR and SLC24A4 variants when compared 
with those of OCA2 and the difference in the sign of the correlation 
with blond hair color between the MC1R and 6p25.3 variants, both of 
which are associated with sensitive skin and freckles (Fig. 1). These 
patterns of association have an important role in creating the 
differences in hair, eye and skin pigmentation that are observed 
between individuals from European populations. Our data on the 
characteristics of pigmentation are based on self assessment, and it is 
likely that more complete and objective measurement techniques 
would strengthen the observed associations and potentially lead to 
further discoveries. In addition, the homogeneity of skin pigmentation 
in our discovery population reduces the power to detect new variants 
and to replicate previously reported variants that affect skin pigmen-
tation (in particular those that are fixed in Icelanders). </p>

<p>1 4 4 8 </p>

<p>VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>In spite of the observed frequency difference in some of the 
pigmentation characteristics, we did not find evidence for a difference 
between the sexes in the strength of association with any of the 
variants (Supplementary Table 4 online). 
Given this new set of genetic determinants of pigmentation, we have 
attempted to predict eye and hair pigmentation based on genotype 
(Fig. 2 and Supplementary Table 5 online). For eye color, the 
prediction of blue versus brown eye color is dominated by variants 
in OCA2, and the discoveries described in this report add resolution to 
the discrimination between blue and green eye color. For hair color, 
the contribution of the new variants is much more substantial. 
Although the prediction of red hair color is based solely on MC1R 
variants, the new variants add predictive power in distinguishing the 
shades of non-red hair. Red and either blond or brown hair color can 
be excluded with a high degree of certainty for a substantial propor-
tion of individuals. </p>

<p>It has long been thought that before the 
migrations that first brought our species out 
of Africa some 60,000 years ago, ancestral 
human populations had characteristically 
dark skin, eyes and hair 24 . This idea is con-
sistent with the positive correlation in 
humans between the degree of skin pigmen-
tation and proximity to the equator 1,2 and 
with the findings that some genes that are 
involved in the synthesis of eumelanin are 
under strong purifying selection in popula-
tions who are exposed to high levels of 
UVR 33 . More recently, several studies have 
provided evidence in support of the idea that 
positive selection drove lighter skin pigmen-
tation to near fixation in populations at 
northerly latitudes, such as those of European 
and East Asian ancestry 19,23-25 . Our results 
support this conclusion, in that most of the 
pigmentation variants discovered in this 
study show signals of positive selection in 
European populations. In each case the var-
iant that is likely to contribute to lighter 
pigmentation of the skin has been swept to 
high frequency, which is consistent with posi-
tive selection on the sequence variants that 
undermine the formation of pigments. The 
most obvious functional advantage of lighter 
skin pigmentation in northerly latitudes is 
that it facilitates the synthesis of vitamin D3 
in spite of low levels of UVR exposure 3 . 
However, other functional advantages or con-
straints cannot be ruled out. 
The growing number of known sequence variants that underlie the 
differences in normal human pigmentation within and between 
populations may provide new inroads into the molecular physiology 
of these traits, which in turn could enhance our understanding of how 
they evolved. At the very least, the newly discovered genetic determi-
nants of human pigmentation provide promising candidates for 
forensic geneticists and for studies of diseases of the skin and eyes 
that are known to be correlated with such traits. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>The Icelandic samples. A total of 2,986 Icelandic adults, recruited through 
cardiovascular, neoplastic, neurological and metabolic studies, were genotyped 
for 317,511 SNPs using the <rs id="software-8" type="software">HumanHap300 BeadChip</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-8" type="creator">Illumina</rs>). These studies 
were approved by the Data Protection Commission of Iceland and the National 
Bioethics Committee of Iceland. Written informed consent was obtained from 
all participants. Personal identifiers associated with phenotypic information </p>

<p>Observed eye color </p>

<p>Blue eyes 
Green eyes 
Brown eyes </p>

<p>Population 
distribution </p>

<p>Brown &lt; 20% 
Green &lt; 10% 
Green 10-30% </p>

<p>Brown &lt; 20% 
Brown &lt; 20% 
Brown 20-50% </p>

<p>Blond 30-40% 
Brown 30-50% </p>

<p>Green &gt; 30% 
Brown &gt; 50% </p>

<p>Eye color prediction </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Icelandic discovery sample </p>

<p>N = 2,928 
N = 955 
N = 1,430 
N = 122 
N = 162 
N = 259 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 
Frequency </p>

<p>Icelandic replication sample </p>

<p>N = 2,603 
N = 1,080 
N = 1,021 
N = 118 
N = 107 
N = 277 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 
Frequency </p>

<p>Dutch replication sample </p>

<p>N = 1,140 
N = 445 
N = 375 
N = 53 
N = 57 
N = 210 </p>

<p>Observed hair color 
Red hair </p>

<p>Blond hair </p>

<p>Dark-blond or light-brown hair </p>

<p>Brown or black hair </p>

<p>Population 
distribution 
Red &gt; 50% 
Blond &gt; 40% </p>

<p>Blond &lt; 30% 
Brown &lt; 30% 
Brown &gt; 50% </p>

<p>Hair color prediction </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Icelandic discovery sample </p>

<p>N = 2,903 
N = 154 
N = 61 
N = 217 
N = 1,559 
N = 627 
N = 285 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Icelandic replication sample </p>

<p>N = 2,622 
N = 140 
N = 81 
N = 215 
N = 1,387 
N = 571 
N = 228 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>Dutch replication sample </p>

<p>N = 1,211 
N = 19 
N = 6 
N = 46 
N = 547 
N = 377 
N = 216 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Figure 2 Overview of the accuracy of 
pigmentation prediction based on genotype 
status. (a) Eye pigmentation. (b) Hair 
pigmentation. The prediction rules were created 
from the Icelandic discovery sample and then 
applied to the Icelandic and Dutch replication 
samples. Only those individuals who were 
genotyped for all necessary markers, or good 
surrogates of these markers, were used. 
Histograms show the distribution of pigmentation 
within each sample and within groups of 
individuals with similar predicted pigmentation. </p>

<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>and blood samples were encrypted using a third-party encryption system as 
previously described 34 . Only individuals with a genotype yield over 98% were 
included in the study. A second sample of 2,714 Icelandic individuals was 
recruited in a similar fashion and genotyped to replicate the SNPs identified in 
the genome-wide scan. 
Each participant completed a questionnaire that included questions 
about natural eye color categories (blue/gray, green or black/brown), natural 
hair color categories (red/reddish, blond, dark blond/light brown or brown/ 
black) and the presence of freckles at any time (Table 1). Skin sensitivity to 
sun was self-assessed using the Fitzpatrick skin-type score 35 , where the lowest 
score (I) represents very fair skin that is very sensitive to UVR and the 
highest score (IV) represents dark skin that tans rather than burns in reaction 
to UVR exposure. Individuals scoring I and II were classified as being sensitive 
to sun and individuals scoring III and IV were classified as not being sensitive 
to sun. 
No objective measurements of pigmentation (for example, spectrophoto-
metry) were carried out. The benefits of the self-reported measurements are 
that they are cheap and easy to collect, but their subjective nature is likely to 
introduce misclassifications, leading to a loss of power in the discovery phase 
and a decrease in prediction accuracy. </p>

<p>The Dutch sample. The SNPs with the most significant associations that were 
identified in the genome-wide scans carried out on the Icelandic discovery 
sample were genotyped and tested for association in a sample of 1,214 Dutch 
individuals. The Dutch sample was composed of 696 males recruited for a 
prostate cancer study 36 and 518 females recruited for a breast cancer study by 
the Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre (RUNMC) and through a 
population-based cancer registry held by the Comprehensive Cancer Centre 
IKO in Nijmegen. All individuals were of self-reported European ancestry. 
The study protocol was approved by the Institutional Review Board of 
Radboud University and all study subjects gave written informed consent 
for the collection of questionnaire data on lifestyle, medical history and 
family history. 
As in the case of the Icelandic samples, information about pigmentation 
traits for the Dutch sample was obtained through a questionnaire. The 
questions about natural eye and hair color were the same as those in the 
Icelandic questionnaire, with the addition of a category for an 'other' eye color. 
A total of 5.9% of the Dutch participants selected this category and were 
excluded from our analysis. Skin sensitivity to sun was assessed by two 
questions about the tendency of individuals to burn or tan when exposed to 
sun without sun block protection. The answers to these two questions were 
used to create a dichotomized grouping of individuals according to sensitivity 
to sun, corresponding to the grouping used for the Icelandic sample. Two 
questions from the Dutch questionnaire assessed the density of freckles on the 
face and arms, respectively. For the sake of comparison with the Icelandic data, 
participants reporting freckles at either location were considered as having 
freckles present, whereas those reporting absence of freckles at both locations 
were considered to have no freckles. In addition, the Dutch questionnaire 
included questions about skin color category (white, white with brownish tint 
and light-brown), the number of naevi on the left forearm and the number of 
serious sunburns in their lifetime. </p>

<p>Statistical methods. In the genome-wide association stage, Icelandic case and 
control samples were assayed with the Infinium HumanHap300 SNP chips 
(Illumina), containing 317,511 SNPs, of which 316,515 were polymorphic and 
satisfied our quality criteria. 
A likelihood procedure described in a previous publication 37 was used for 
the association analyses. Allele-specific ORs were calculated assuming a multi-
plicative model 38 . Results from multiple case-control groups were combined 
using a Mantel-Haenszel model 39 . In Tables 2-4, P values for variants at MC1R, 
TYR and OCA2 were calculated adjusting for the effect of the other variant at 
that locus. </p>

<p>Pigmentation prediction. A model to predict eye and hair pigmentation was 
created based on the Icelandic discovery sample (Fig. 2). A generalized linear 
model, in which eye color was treated as a categorical response with three 
categories and genotypes at all associated sequence variants were used as </p>

<p>covariates, was used to model eye color. A two-step model was used to 
predict hair color. The first step involved predicting red hair and was based 
solely on the MC1R coding variants. The second step involved modeling non-
red hair color as an ordinal variable, with dark-blond or light-brown hair lying 
between the extremes of blond and brown or black hair. Eye and hair 
pigmentation in the Icelandic and Dutch replication samples were then 
predicted on the basis of the model parameters estimated in the Icelandic 
discovery sample. </p>

<p>Correction for relatedness and genomic control. Some of the individuals in 
the Icelandic case-control groups were related to each other, causing the w 2 test 
statistic to have a mean 41 and median 40.675 2 . We estimated the inflation 
factor by using a previously described procedure in which we simulated 
genotypes through the genealogy of 731,175 Icelanders 40 . For the initial 
discovery samples, for which the genotypes for the 316,515 genome-wide SNPs 
were available, we also estimated the inflation factor by using genomic controls 
and calculating the average of the 316,515 w 2 statistics and by computing the 
median of the 316,515 w 2 statistics and dividing it by 0.675 2 as previously 
described 41,42 . The inflation factors for the Icelandic discovery samples are 
given in Supplementary Table 6 online. </p>

<p>Single SNP and microsatellite genotyping. SNP genotyping was carried out 
using the <rs id="software-10" type="software">Centaurus</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Nanogen</rs>) platform 43 in (Supplementary Table 7 online). 
The quality of each Centaurus SNP assay was evaluated by genotyping each 
assay in the CEU and/or YRI HapMap samples and comparing the results with 
the HapMap data. Assays with mismatch rates of 41.5% were not used, and an 
LD test was used for markers known to be in LD. </p>

<p>Controlling for population stratification. Most of the variants that show 
significant association with pigmentation are also present in frequencies that 
differ among European populations and between European, Asian and African 
populations. These frequency differences are to be expected given the differ-
ences in pigmentation between the populations. However, if our method of 
discovery were applied to a stratified sample of Europeans, without taking this 
stratification into account, then variants with population frequencies that 
correlate with pigmentation could show spurious association with pigmenta-
tion. We therefore carried out a series of tests to search for signs of stratifica-
tion, even though the Icelandic population has been relatively isolated 
throughout its history. 
First, we applied the method of genomic control to the analysis, which takes 
into account the genome-wide inflation of the w 2 statistics. The inflation factors 
we observed were similar to inflation factors estimated from known relation-
ships between individuals, which suggests that the overall inflation due to 
stratification is small (Supplementary Table 6). 
Second, from a published set of 400 SNPs known to have differing 
frequencies between European poulations 44 , we selected a subset of 97 SNPs 
that are also present on the Illumina 317K Human Hap chip. We then tested for 
LD between 4,417 pairs of markers on different chromosomes among 1,984 
Icelanders who are unrelated to a meiotic distance of 3. Of the 4,417 pairs 
tested, 225 had P o 0.05, compared with 220.8 expected, and 6 had P o 0.001, 
compared with 4.4 expected. We also tested for LD between the 97 SNPs and 
the 9 SNPs, resulting in 834 tests in which the two markers were not on the 
same chromosome. Again we observed no significant excess of low P values (39 
observed compared with 41 expected at P o 0.05 and 2 observed compared 
with 0.8 expected at P o 0.001). 
Third, the gene encoding lactase is well described and has a large degree of 
variation between populations 45 , but no known association with pigmentation. 
We chose the intragenic marker rs2322659 and tested its LD with the nine 
SNPs that are associated with pigmentation (P 4 0.01 in all instances). We also 
carried out six tests for association of rs2322659 with pigmentation without 
detecting any significant association. 
Finally, we applied the <rs type="software">EIGENSTRAT</rs> method 46 , which relies on patterns of 
correlation between individuals to detect stratification, to our Icelandic 
discovery sample. No evidence of substantial stratification was detected, 
with the largest principal component estimated to explain 0.2% of the 
overall variation of the data. The correction factors based on correcting for 
the ten largest principal components are close to 1 (Supplementary Table 8 </p>



<p>VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>online) and do not have any effect on our conclusions. Inspection of the first 
few principal components suggests that they correspond to small sets of close 
relatives, whose relationship had not been properly accounted for. </p>

<p>Assessing signals of positive selection. Evidence for the effect of positive 
selection on the SNPs that are associated with pigmentation traits was 
examined by applying two methods to the data from the HapMap project 
(release 21; Supplementary Table 9 online) 28 . First, we examined whether the 
degree of population divergence in allele frequencies among the HapMap 
groups exceeded the expectations from neutral evolution. Under neutrality, the 
frequencies of any particular allele in a population set are shaped by the 
counteracting forces of genetic drift, gene flow and mutation, which constrain 
the expected range of allele frequency differences between populations. When 
the observed divergence between populations is in the upper extreme of the 
expected range, or outside it, the neutral model may be rejected in favor of one 
in which allele frequencies have been shaped by population differences in the 
intensity of selective forces 47 . 
The Wahlund F ST statistic </p>

<p>F ST ¼ 
varðpÞ </p>

<p>pð1 À 
pÞ </p>

<p>was used to measure allele frequency differences between populations, where 
var(p) represents the variance of the frequencies of an allele from a biallelic 
SNP, and 
p represents the average frequency of the allele among the populations 
under consideration. This statistic was calculated for all HapMap SNPs 
genotyped in at least two HapMap samples, with 3,020,798 SNPs yielding 
F ST values based on all three HapMap samples (CEU, YRI and ASN), and 
3,064,337, 3,118,875 and 3,094,443 for the population pairs CEU-YRI, CEU-
ASN and YRI-ASN, respectively. For each combination of HapMap samples, 
the SNPs were grouped into 50 bins according to the overall frequency of the 
more common allele and using an interval of 0.01. To assess whether a 
particular SNP showed an unusual degree of population divergence, the 
percentile rank of each SNP's F ST value was determined within each bin for 
each combination of HapMap samples. 
The second method used to detect signals of positive selection is based on an 
examination of the pattern of diversity within populations. Under neutrality, 
there is an expected positive relationship between the frequency of an allele, its 
age, its variability at linked sites and the extent to which LD with other loci 
decays at increasing physical distance. Common alleles with unusually low 
diversity at linked sites and/or slow decay of LD with increasing physical 
distance represent probable targets of recent positive selection. We used the 
relative extended haplotype homozygosity (rEHH) statistic to assess the 
fragmentation of haplotypes around putative selected variants 48 . To simplify 
the comparisons between different genomic regions, we calculated a single 
irEHH value for each allele, representing the area beneath the line defined 
by the rEHH point estimates that are obtained as haplotypes, extended in 
both directions from the allele being tested (until the EHH value in both 
directions has fallen below 0.05) 49,50 . Calculations were carried out for all 
HapMap SNPs in the CEU HapMap sample with a minor allele frequency 
41%, yielding irEHH values for a total number of 4,906,866 alleles. To make 
comparisons of irEHH values meaningful between regions with different rates 
of recombination, the positions of SNPs were defined in centimorgans for these 
calculations (using recombination rate maps for phase II of the HapMap, which 
are available at the International HapMap website). To determine whether a 
particular irEHH value could be considered unusually great, thereby indicating 
the action of positive selection, we grouped all HapMap SNPs of the same 
frequency in the CEU HapMap group into separate bins and calculated the 
percentile rank for each irEHH value within each of the bins. </p>



<p>Note: Supplementary information is available on the Nature Genetics website. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
We thank the study participants from Iceland and Holland whose contributions 
made this work possible. We also thank the nurses at Noatun (deCODE's sample 
recruitment center) and the personnel at the deCODE core facilities for their hard 
work and enthusiasm. This work was funded in part by contract number 018827 
(Polygene) from the 6th Framework Program of the European Union. </p>

<p>AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION 
P.S., D.F.G., A.H. and K.S. wrote the first draft of the paper. S.N.S., T.R., K.P.M., 
A.K., F.J., B.S., K.T., R.R., K.R.B. and J.H.O. collected the Icelandic samples and 
phenotypes. K.K.A. and L.A.K. collected the Dutch samples and phenotypes. 
S.N.S., T.R., M.J. and U.T. carried out the genotyping. P.S., D.F.G., A.H., A.M., 
A.P., G.T., S.S., S.P. and A.K. analyzed the data. P.S., D.F.G., S.N.S., A.H., F.J., 
L.A.K., J.H.O., J.G., U.T. and K.S. planned, supervised and coordinated the work. 
All authors contributed to the final version of the paper. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS STATEMENT 
The authors declare competing financial interests: details accompany the full-text 
HTML version of the paper at http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics/. </p>

<p>Published online at http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics 
Reprints and permissions information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions </p>



<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>





<p>VOLUME 39 [ NUMBER 12 [ DECEMBER 2007 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2007 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

</text></tei>