<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2008-39-NAT_BIOTECHNOL" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:57+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>More effective therapies are urgently needed against hepatitis C virus (HCV), a major cause of viral hepatitis. We used in vitro 
protein expression and microfluidic affinity analysis to study RNA binding by the HCV transmembrane protein NS4B, which 
plays an essential role in HCV RNA replication. We show that HCV NS4B binds RNA and that this binding is specific for the 
3¢ terminus of the negative strand of the viral genome with a dissociation constant (K d ) of B3.4 nM. A high-throughput 
microfluidic screen of a compound library identified 18 compounds that substantially inhibited binding of RNA by NS4B. One of 
these compounds, clemizole hydrochloride, was found to inhibit HCV RNA replication in cell culture that was mediated by its 
suppression of NS4B's RNA binding, with little toxicity for the host cell. These results yield new insight into the HCV life cycle 
and provide a candidate compound for pharmaceutical development. </p>

<p>Over 150 million people are infected with HCV worldwide. Unfortu-
nately, many of these individuals are unable to clear their infection 
with the current standard of care, which consists of a combination of 
interferon and ribavirin 1 (Copegus, Rebetol, Rebetron, Virazole). 
Moreover, this treatment is associated with substantial side effects, 
precluding its use by many individuals. Thus, current therapies are 
inadequate for the majority of patients 1 , and there is a pressing need 
for new HCV drugs 1 . 
The 9.6-kb, positive, single-stranded RNA HCV genome encodes a 
3,000-amino-acid polyprotein that is proteolytically processed into 
structural proteins, which are components of the mature virus, and 
nonstructural proteins (NS), which are involved in replicating the viral 
genome 2 . Like other positive-strand RNA viruses 3 , HCV appears to 
replicate in association with intracellular membrane structures. In the 
case of HCV, the structures are termed the membranous web 4 and are 
believed to be induced by the NS4B protein. NS4B is also required to 
assemble the other viral NS proteins within the apparent sites of RNA 
replication 5 . It is not known how viral RNA, especially the negative-
strand template required for production of progeny genomes, might 
be incorporated or maintained at these replication sites. 
NS4B and HCV RNA have been shown to colocalize to the 
membranous web 6,7 , suggesting that NS4B is in intimate contact 
with viral RNA in the context of authentic viral RNA replication. 
The hepatitis A and polio picornaviruses have proteins termed 2C, 
which are required for replication, bind RNA 8,9 and have an 
N-terminal amphipathic helix and a nucleotide binding motif 8-10 . 
NS4B contains the same structural features, and both of them are 
required for HCV replication 5,11 . We thus hypothesized that NS4B </p>

<p>may similarly bind RNA, that this interaction might be critical for the 
HCV life cycle, and that RNA binding by NS4B could be amenable to 
pharmacologic disruption. To test these hypotheses, we established an 
in vitro RNA binding assay in a format enabling simultaneous 
analysis of multiple conditions, mutants, replicates, quantitative 
K d measurements and high-throughput screening for potential 
pharmacologic inhibitors. 
Like the majority of drug targets 12 , NS4B is a membrane protein. 
Membrane proteins are notoriously difficult to express and character-
ize biochemically, especially in the quantities required for pharma-
ceutical screening. Moreover, solubilization by detergents can alter 
their natural membrane-associated topology. To ameliorate these 
problems, we used microfluidic tools to perform binding assays 
with nanoliter protein consumption. This enabled use of an in vitro 
cell lysate expression system, which was supplemented with micro-
somal membranes to create more natural folding conditions, under 
which the best NS4B topology data available to date have been 
obtained 13 . The reduced yield relative to conventional expression 
methods is offset by low sample consumption. 
Previous microfluidic tools to measure drug interactions have been 
limited to enzymatic targets that can catalyze formation of a fluor-
escent substrate 14 . In this case we directly measured binding constants 
by using mechanical trapping of molecular interactions (MITOMI), a 
microfluidic affinity assay that has previously been used to measure 
interactions between transcription factors and DNA 15 . We have 
extended the previous work by showing that MITOMI can be used 
to measure both binding constants of membrane protein-RNA inter-
actions and inhibition of such interactions by small molecules in a </p>

<p>high-throughput screen. The latter point was particularly surprising in 
that the elastomer used to fabricate the device is known to have 
limitations in chemical compatibility 16,17 ; here we show that this does 
not prevent its use in a drug screen or the discovery of a small 
molecule with the desired pharmacological properties. Taken together, 
the results of this paper reveal a novel HCV target and show that 
microfluidic technology can be used to discover a new pharmaceutical, 
thereby validating the use of microfluidic tools in drug discovery 18,19 . </p>

<p>RESULTS 
We validated the use of the microfluidic platform for RNA binding by 
studying two human proteins from the embryonic lethal abnormal 
visual system (ELAV) family, the RNA binding activity of which is 
well characterized 20-22 . We then applied this methodology to study 
RNA interactions with the transmembrane HCV NS4B protein. We 
(i) tested the hypothesis that HCV NS4B binds RNA, (ii) determined 
the K d for this interaction, (iii) studied the substrate specificity of this 
binding, (iv) determined the amino acids within NS4B required for 
RNA binding and (v) screened a compound library for pharmacologic 
inhibitors of NS4B RNA binding and HCV replication. </p>

<p>Microfluidic assay validation: HuD binding to RNA 
HuD is a host cell protein from the ELAV-like family with well-
characterized RNA binding activity 20-22 . It is a cytoplasmic protein 
that contains three conserved RNA recognition motifs through which 
it binds AU-rich elements in the 3¢ untranslated region (UTR) of genes 
such as those encoding cytokines and proto-oncogenes. Binding was 
tested against two Cy3-labeled RNA probes: AU3 and a known AU3 
mutant to which HuD binding is impaired 21,22 (Fig. 1). RNA binding 
experiments with MITOMI were performed essentially as described 15 , 
except that in this case RNA was used instead of DNA (Supplemen-
tary Fig. 1 online). Briefly, we spotted a microarray of target RNA 
sequences labeled with Cy3 onto an epoxy-coated slide. These arrays 
were used to program the microfluidic devices by aligning each spot in 
the array to a unit cell in the device. After bonding the microfluidic 
device to a microarray it was subjected to surface patterning that </p>

<p>resulted in a circular area coated with biotinylated antihistidine 
antibodies within each unit cell. The device was then loaded with 
an in vitro transcription-translation mixture containing DNA 
templates coding for HuD fused in-frame with a C-terminal V5-6 
histidine tag (HuD-V5-his) or Gus protein fused in-frame with a 
C-terminal 6 histidine tag (Gus-his). Bodipy-labeled tRNA Lys was 
added for protein labeling. Each unit cell was then isolated using 
micromechanical valves followed by an incubation to allow protein 
synthesis, binding of the synthesized protein to the surface biotiny-
lated anti-his antibodies, solvation of target RNA and equilibration of 
proteins and target RNA. MITOMI was then performed by actuation 
of a 'button' membrane to trap surface-bound complexes while 
expelling any solution-phase molecules. After a brief wash to remove 
untrapped, unbound material, the trapped molecules and expressed 
protein were subsequently detected with an array scanner. The ratio of 
bound RNA to expressed protein was calculated for each data point by 
measuring the median signal of Cy3 to the median signal of bodipy. 
The assay detected strong binding of HuD to the AU3 RNA probe; 
background binding by Gus-his was 7-to 16-fold lower than the HuD 
signal (Fig. 1a). This background level did not increase with RNA 
probe concentration and was subtracted from all chambers (Supple-
mentary Fig. 2 online). The binding affinity of HuD to the AU3 probe 
was much greater than that of the AU3 mutant probe: the K d for AU3 
binding was 23 ± 5 nM and that for AU3 mutant binding was 268 ± 
95 nM (Fig. 1a). These values agree with previous measurements in a 
gel shift assay 21,22 and validate the MITOMI microfluidic affinity assay 
for RNA-protein interactions. RNA binding analysis of another 
protein from the ELAV-like family, HuR, is shown in Supplementary 
Fig. 3 online. </p>

<p>NS4B binds HCV RNA and Kd is determined by microfluidics 
We then tested whether HCV NS4B binds RNA. Because NS4B is 
important in viral RNA replication, and initiation of positive-strand 
RNA synthesis is likely to start at the 3¢ terminus of the negative-
strand RNA, we first tested binding of NS4B to this region, using a 
probe designated 3¢ negative terminus. A fusion of the amphipathic </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>d 
b </p>

<p>Expressed 
protein 
(GFP signal) </p>

<p>Bound RNA/ 
protein ratio 
(Cy5/GFP) </p>

<p>Bound RNA 
(Cy5 signal) </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>NS4B-GFP </p>

<p>NS5A(AH)-GFP </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.001 
0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 </p>

<p>RNA probe concentration (µM) 
Relative bound RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.01 
0.1 
1 
10 
100 
1,000 </p>

<p>RNA probe concentration (nM) 
Relative bound RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>K d = 3.4 ± 1nM 
P = 0.01 </p>

<p>Bmax = 1 ± 0.1 
P = 8.74E-0.6 </p>

<p>UUAUCUAUC 
UAUCUAUU </p>

<p>UUAUUUAUU 
UAUUUAUU </p>

<p>RNA probe 
sequence </p>

<p>ND (&gt;220) 
AU3 
mutant </p>

<p>19 ± 3 
AU3 </p>

<p>K d (nM) by 
MITOMI </p>

<p>UUAUCUAUC 
UAUCUAUU </p>

<p>UUAUUUAUU 
UAUUUAUU </p>

<p>268 ± 95 </p>

<p>23 ± 5 </p>

<p>K d (nM) by gel 
shift assay </p>

<p>Figure 1 Protein-RNA interactions measured on 
microfluidic platform. (a) Target RNA sequences 
used to study binding of HuD to RNA and 
comparison of K d values measured using 
microfluidic affinity analysis to values previously 
measured by gel shift assay 21,22 . ND, not 
determined. (b) Binding curve of HuD to 
increasing concentration of AU3 () and AU3 
mutant (n) RNA, as determined in the 
microfluidic affinity assay. Normalized mean 
values for 10-20 replicates measured in two 
independent experiments are shown for each 
graph. Error bars represent s.d. (c) Fluorescent 
images from microfluidic chip. Left: NS4B-GFP 
and NS5A(AH)-GFP were anchored to the 
microfluidic device surface via its interaction with 
anti-GFP. Middle: an RNA probe corresponding to 
the 3¢ terminal region of the negative viral strand 
was labeled with Cy5 and incubated with the 
proteins on the device. Cy5 signal representing 
bound RNA is shown following a brief wash. 
Right: an overlay of the Cy5 signal and GFP 
signal representing bound RNA to protein ratio. 
(d) In vitro binding curve of NS4B to serial 
dilutions of the RNA probe. Each data point 
represents the mean of 10-20 replicates, and the 
bars represent the standard error. </p>

<p>1 0 2 0 
VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>helix of NS5A to the N terminus of GFP 5 was used as a negative 
control. This protein also binds to membranes and can thus anchor 
the microsomal membranes to the device surface through the inter-
action of GFP with anti-GFP (Fig. 1c). The K d of NS4B binding to the 
3¢ terminus of the HCV negative-strand RNA was measured at 3.4 ± 
1.0 nM (Fig. 1d). To the best of our knowledge this is the first report 
that HCV NS4B binds RNA. Conventional glutathione-S-transferase 
(GST) pull-down assays and RNA filter binding assays using recom-
binant forms of purified NS4B expressed in Escherichia coli confirmed 
this finding (Supplementary Fig. 4 online), although these were 
less convenient and amenable to the types of analyses and high-
throughput format that we sought. </p>

<p>NS4B specifically binds the 3¢ terminus of the (-) viral strand 
We measured the substrate specificity of the observed NS4B-HCV 
RNA interaction with three additional HCV probes (Fig. 2a). The 
probes designated 5¢ UTR pos and 3¢ UTR pos correspond to the 
5¢ UTR and 3¢ UTR sequences of the positive viral strand, respectively, </p>

<p>and 5¢ negative terminus corresponds to the 5¢ terminus of the 
negative strand. The RNA binding experiment was repeated and 
binding of NS4B to equimolar concentrations (3 nM) of the various 
probes was compared. Whereas NS4B binds all four HCV probes, its 
apparent affinity to the 3¢ negative terminus probe is 5-to 12-fold 
greater than to the other three HCV RNA regions tested or to an 
unrelated delta virus RNA genome sequence 23,24 (see Fig. 2b). These 
findings suggest that it is the RNA sequence, and likely the secondary 
RNA structure, that determines the specificity of NS4B binding to the 
3¢ terminus of the negative strand. </p>

<p>An ARM in NS4B is essential for RNA binding and HCV 
replication 
Various structural motifs responsible for the interaction between 
proteins and RNA have been reported 25 . One of these is the arginine 
rich motif (ARM). ARMs were originally defined as short (10 to 20 
amino acids) arginine-rich sequences found in viral, bacteriophage 
and ribosomal proteins (Fig. 3a) 9,25,26 . There is little identity between 
ARM sequences, other than the preponderance of arginine residues. 
Subsequently, ARM-like motifs, consisting of longer sequences con-
taining fewer arginines, were identified 9,26 . Inspection of the primary 
sequence of NS4B reveals the presence of multiple positively charged 
amino acids (Fig. 3b). The majority of these arginine residues are 
within the last 71 amino acids, in the C-terminal region of NS4B 
(Fig. 3b,c). This region is predicted to form a cytoplasmic 
segment based on empirical topology studies using glycosylation 
markers 13 . Elements of this region conform with previously described 
ARM-like motifs. </p>

<p>N S 5 B </p>

<p>Negative strand: </p>

<p>Positive strand: 
3' UTR 
HCV ORF 
C o r e </p>

<p>1 
530 
9599 
9000 </p>

<p>HCV ORF </p>

<p>5' terminus 
3' terminus </p>

<p>5' UTR </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>5 ′ U T R </p>

<p>p o s </p>

<p>3 ′ U T R </p>

<p>p o s </p>

<p>3 ′ t e r m </p>

<p>in 
u s </p>

<p>n e g 
5 ′ t e r m </p>

<p>in 
u s </p>

<p>n e g 
D e lt a 
Relative bound RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Cytoplasm </p>

<p>ER lumen </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>R R </p>

<p>R 
R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R R 
R R </p>

<p>R R 
R R </p>

<p>R R 
R R </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>N 
S 4 B -G </p>

<p>F P </p>

<p>N 
S 4 B -R </p>

<p>r a -G </p>

<p>F P </p>

<p>N 
S 4 B -R </p>

<p>R 
b -G </p>

<p>F P </p>

<p>N 
S 5 A </p>

<p>( A H </p>

<p>) -G </p>

<p>F P </p>

<p>Normalized bound 
RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>ASHLPYIEQGMMLAEQF KQKALGLLQTASRHAEVITPA 
VQTNWQKLEVFWAKHMWNFISGIQYLAGLSTLPGNPAIA 
SLMAFTAAVTSPLTTGQTLLFNILGGWVAAQLAAPGAATA 
FVGAGLAGAAIGSVGLGKVLVDILAGYGAGVAGALVAFKI </p>

<p>MSGEVPSTEDLVNLLPAILSPGALVVGVVSAAILRR HVG </p>

<p>PGEGAVQWMNRLIAFASRGNHVSPTHYVPESDAAARV </p>

<p>TAILSSLTVTQLLRR LHQWISSECTTPC </p>

<p>Poliovirus 2C </p>

<p>HCV NS4B </p>

<p>BaMV TGBp1 </p>

<p>P22 N </p>

<p>HIV Tat </p>

<p>HIV Rev </p>

<p>Protein </p>

<p>NERNRRSN </p>

<p>RRHVGPGEGAVQWMNRLIAFASR 
GNHVSPTHYVPESDAAARVTAILSSLTVTQLLRR </p>

<p>MDNRITDLLTRSGYLRTSEPRGAGQQLVVHAVAGAGKT </p>

<p>GNAKTRRHERRRKLAIER </p>

<p>ALGISYGRKKRRQRRRP </p>

<p>MDAQTRRRERRAEKQAQW </p>

<p>λ N </p>

<p>GTAKSRYKARRAELIAER </p>

<p>TRQARRNRRRRWRERQ </p>

<p>RNA binding domain </p>

<p>Φ21 N </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>Figure 2 NS4B binds specifically to the 3¢ terminus of the HCV negative-
strand RNA. (a) Four HCV probes were designed. 5¢ UTR pos and 3¢ UTR 
pos corresponded to the 5¢ UTR and 3¢ UTR sequences of the positive viral 
strand, respectively, and 5¢ negative terminus and 3¢ negative terminus 
corresponded to the 5¢ and 3¢ terminal regions of the negative strand, 
respectively. The position of these sequences with respect to the HCV open 
reading frame (ORF) is shown. (b) Fractional binding of NS4B to equimolar 
concentrations of the four HCV probes and to a non-HCV RNA (delta virus 
RNA) probe. The 3¢ terminus of the negative genome strand is favored 
by 4 5Â. Each data point represents the mean of 10-20 replicates, and 
the bars represent the standard error. </p>

<p>Figure 3 Identification of RNA binding domains 
within NS4B. (a) Arginine-rich sequences known 
to confer RNA binding found in viral and bacterio-
phage proteins 9,25,26 . Elements in the terminal 
loop of NS4B that conform with arginine rich-like 
motifs are shown at the bottom. Proteins listed are 
HIV Rev and Tat 25 ; l, F21 and P22 bacterio-
phage antiterminator N proteins 25 ; triple gene 
block protein 1 (TGBp1) of the bamboo mosaic 
virus (BaMV) 26 and poliovirus 2C 9 . (b) Positively 
charged amino acids (highlighted) within the 
primary sequence of NS4B (genotype 1a). 
(c) Schematic diagram indicating predicted 
transmembrane and intracellular domains of 
NS4B. Conserved positively charged amino acids 
in the C-terminal segment of NS4B are shown in 
red. (d) Arginine residues mediate RNA binding by 
NS4B. Binding of wild-type NS4B-GFP, RRa and 
RRb NS4B-GFP mutants and NS5A(AH)-GFP to 
the 3¢ terminus of the negative viral RNA strand 
(1.5 nM) was determined by microfluidic affinity 
analysis. Bars represent s.d. </p>

<p>NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 
1 0 2 1 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>Using a series of point mutations, we tested if RNA binding by 
NS4B is mediated by some of its positively charged residues. A 
substitution of Arg-Arg in positions 192-193 with Ala-Ala was termed 
'RRa mutant' and a similar substitution in positions 247-248 was 
designated 'RRb mutant' . Whereas the RRb mutant decreased binding 
by NS4B to the 3¢ negative terminus probe by fivefold, RNA binding 
activity to the RRa mutant was completely eliminated at the same 
probe concentration (1.5 nM; Fig. 3d). These results suggest that the 
tested arginine residues mediate RNA binding by NS4B in vitro. To test 
the hypothesis that these positively charged residues are also impor-
tant for HCV replication, we introduced these mutations into high-
efficiency subgenomic HCV replicons and assayed them in standard 
replicon colony formation assays (data not shown). The various 
mutations substantially impaired HCV RNA replication and the 
degree of replication inhibition correlated with the degree of NS4B 
RNA binding impairment (unpublished data). These results suggest 
that efficient binding of HCV RNA is required for viral replication 
in vitro. Alignment of the sequences of natural HCV isolates currently 
available in databases reveals that these positively charged residues are 
highly conserved across all HCV genotypes. This conservation suggests 
that there is a requirement for the RNA binding residues for 
productive viral infection in vivo. </p>

<p>High-throughput screening for inhibitory compounds 
We screened a compound library for small molecules that could inhibit 
the RNA-NS4B interaction. We spotted 1,280 compounds from a 
small-molecule library on epoxy-coated slides in a microarray format 
(Fig. 4a). The array was allowed to dry and was then aligned and 
bonded to a microfluidic device. The rest of the assay was performed as 
before, except that the device was loaded with NS4B-GFP followed by 
Cy5-labeled 3¢ terminus negative RNA probe. In the primary screen, 
the compounds were spotted at a concentration of B1 mM. The entire 
library was screened in duplicate using only two microfluidic devices. 
Out of 1,280 compounds, 104 were found to have an inhibitory effect </p>

<p>(490% inhibition) on RNA binding by NS4B. In addition, there were 
110 compounds for which there was a substantial discrepancy between 
the two tested replicates or for which one or two of the measurements 
had been disrupted due to technical errors. 
The 214 compounds (104 + 110) identified in the primary screen 
were subjected to a secondary screen (Fig. 4a). This was done in a 
similar manner except that a smaller device was used, the spotted 
compound concentration was tenfold lower than in the primary 
screen and five replicates were spotted for each compound. Eighteen 
compounds were confirmed to substantially inhibit RNA binding by 
NS4B out of the 214 compounds tested (Fig. 4b). Six of these 
compounds were tested for specificity; five of them did not inhibit 
binding of HuR protein to its own 4A target RNA sequence (Supple-
mentary Fig. 3) nor did they inhibit HuR binding to its previously 
described HCV RNA target, that is the 3¢ terminus of the negative viral 
strand 27 , suggesting that these hits are specific. This data and addi-
tional data supporting the validity of the screen are presented in 
Supplementary Data and Supplementary Fig. 5 online. </p>

<p>Inhibitors of HCV RNA replication 
We measured the inhibitory effect on HCV RNA replication of the 
compounds identified in the above screen in cell culture. After 
electroporation with a full-length HCV RNA genome harboring a 
luciferase reporter gene 28 , Huh7.5 cells were grown in the presence of 
increasing concentrations of these compounds. Luciferase assays were 
performed at 72 h. In parallel, the viability of cells in the presence of 
the compounds was assessed by an Alamar Blue-based assay. Six of 
the compounds showed some antiviral effect above that solely 
attributable to cellular toxicity. One of these, clemizole hydrochloride 
(1-p-chlorobenzyl-2-(1-pyrrolidinyl) methylbenzimidazole hydro-
chloride), an H1 histamine receptor antagonist, was found to sub-
stantially inhibit HCV replication. A tenfold decrease in viral 
replication was measured at 20 mM concentration of the drug, with 
an half-maximal effective concentration (EC 50 ) of B8 mM (Fig. 4c). 
At these concentrations there was no measurable cellular toxicity 
(Fig. 4c). Similar results were obtained by real-time PCR assays 
performed in clemizole-treated Huh7.5 cells infected with the infec-
tious HCV clone (J6/JFH) 29 (Supplementary Fig. 6 online). The 
in vitro half-maximal inhibitory concentration (IC 50 ) of clemizole for 
RNA binding by NS4B is B24 ± 1 nM (Fig. 4d). </p>

<p>Clemizole-resistant mutants 
The mechanism of action of clemizole's antiviral activity was further 
substantiated by selecting for clemizole-resistant HCV mutants. 
Established HCV replicon-harboring cells and Huh7 cells electropo-
rated de novo with a genotype 1b subgenomic HCV replicon 
(Bart 79I) 30 were passaged in the presence of the drug, yielding </p>

<p>214 
18 </p>

<p>No inhibition </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 101112131415161718 
Compound number 
Relative fold inhibition </p>

<p>Cell screen </p>

<p>&gt;50% inhibition </p>

<p>No inhibition </p>

<p>Ambiguous </p>

<p>&gt;90% inhibition </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c 
d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0 
0.01 0.05 
0.1 
1 
Clemizole concentration (µM) 
Relative bound RNA/protein </p>

<p>ratio </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
Clemizole concentration (µM) 
Relative viral replication </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>Relative viability </p>

<p>Figure 4 Small-molecule screen reveals that clemizole hydrochloride inhibits 
RNA binding by NS4B and HCV RNA replication in cell culture. (a) The first 
screen represented a low-stringency measurement of inhibition of 1,280 
compounds where the latter were categorized as having high (green), 
ambiguous (blue) or no (red) inhibition. Based on the initial screen, 214 
compounds were then measured again with higher stringency and with a 
greater number of replicates and the best 18 inhibitors were tested for their 
ability to inhibit HCV replication via a cellular assay. (b) In vitro inhibition of 
NS4B-RNA binding by the top 18 small molecules. (c) HCV luciferase 
reporter-linked cellular assay showing that clemizole inhibits HCV 
replication (left axis, blue E) with no measurable toxicity to the cell as 
measured by Alamar Blue (right axis, red &amp;). (d) In vitro NS4B-RNA 
binding: inhibition curve of clemizole. Each data point represents the mean 
of 10-20 replicates and the bars represent the standard error. </p>

<p>1 0 2 2 
VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>B60 colonies that were able to grow in the presence of the compound. 
Eleven individual colonies were successfully expanded, passaged 5-10 
times and the HCV RNA replicating in the cells was subjected to 
sequence analysis. In addition, RNA from a pool of clemizole-resistant 
colonies was isolated and subjected to a similar analysis. Three 
colonies were found to harbor replicons with mutations that mapped 
to the NS4B region, and six colonies were found to harbor replicons 
with mutations that mapped to the negative strand 3¢ terminus RNA 
region. In addition there was one colony with mutations that mapped 
to both NS4B and the negative strand 3¢ terminus, and one where we 
have yet to find the location of the mutation conferring resistance to 
clemizole. No such mutations were identified in ten replicon colonies 
that were passaged in parallel in the absence of the drug. 
Two of the clemizole-resistant NS4B mutants were characterized in 
detail. The first, W55R is depicted in Figure 5a. It involves the 
substitution of an arginine for the tryptophan at amino acid 55 
within a predicted cytoplasmically oriented segment of NS4B. This 
mutation is sufficient to confer a clemizole-resistant phenotype in 
cells: Huh7.5 cells transfected with either whole-cell RNA extracted 
from the W55R mutant cells (Fig. 5b) or with in vitro-transcribed J6/ 
JFH RNA encoding this point mutation and a linked luciferase 
reporter gene (Fig. 5c) were unaffected by 10 mM clemizole. The 
EC 50 of clemizole on the W55R mutant J6/JFH RNA was B18 mM 
(2.25 times the EC 50 of the wild-type RNA). Similar to other HCV 
mutants resistant to an NS3 protease inhibitor 31 , the absolute level of 
replication of the W55R mutant was lower than that of the wild-type 
genome, suggesting that the drug-resistant mutation comes at the cost 
of impaired replication fitness. 
We also introduced this mutation into the NS4B-GFP vector and 
tested it for its RNA binding activity using the in vitro micro-
fluidic assay. Although both mutant and wild-type NS4B proteins </p>

<p>experienced an approximately twofold reduction of RNA binding in 
the presence of 10 nM clemizole, because the baseline RNA binding of 
the mutant is higher, the residual amount of RNA bound by the 
mutant in the presence of clemizole was comparable to that bound by 
the wild type in the absence of clemizole (Fig. 5d). Furthermore, this 
mutant demonstrates greater apparent affinity to the viral RNA with a 
K d of 0.75 nM (versus 3.4 nM for wild-type NS4B) (Fig. 5e). 
The second clemizole-resistant mutation, termed R214Q, was 
identified in a resistant colony as well as in pooled resistant cells. It 
involves the substitution of a glutamine for the arginine at amino acid 
214 within the cytoplasmic C-terminal segment of NS4B. Similar 
results to the first mutation were obtained in cellular and in vitro 
analyses done on this mutation, with an EC 50 of 40.3 mM (B5 times 
higher than the EC 50 on the wild-type RNA) in the luciferase 
reporter-linked replication assay and a K d of 0.6 nM in the 
in vitro binding assay (data not shown). Presumably both of these 
mutations alter the conformation of NS4B so as to increase its 
affinity for the viral RNA. Indeed the K d s measured by the in vitro 
RNA binding assay reflect this. Taken together, the above data 
provide genetic and biochemical evidence for clemizole's mechanism 
of action. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
The above results demonstrate that HCV NS4B binds RNA and that 
this binding is specific for the 3¢ terminus of the negative strand of the 
viral genome. Because the in vivo specificity of this interaction has not 
yet been determined quantitatively, one should use the usual caution 
in extrapolating the numerical value of our in vitro results. We also 
showed that an arginine rich-like motif in NS4B is essential for RNA 
binding and for HCV replication. Clemizole hydrochloride was found 
to have a substantial inhibitory effect on HCV RNA replication 
mediated by its suppression of NS4B's RNA binding. 
Because NS4B is associated with membranes 5 and is known to 
induce membrane replication sites 4 , its RNA binding activity offers a 
mechanism to incorporate the viral genome into the HCV replication 
compartment. This may facilitate the initiation of synthesis of the 
nascent positive strand from the membrane-anchored negative strand. 
NS4B may also act by recruiting the polymerase complex to the HCV 
RNA, through its interaction with the NS5B polymerase or other 
components of the replication complex 32 . </p>

<p>Cytoplasm </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>R R </p>

<p>ER lumen </p>

<p>R R </p>

<p>R R </p>

<p>R 
R </p>

<p>R 
R R </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>W 
R </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>NS4B-GFP 
NS4B 
(W55R)-GFP 
Bound RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>Wild-type 
RNA </p>

<p>W55R mutant 
RNA 
HCV replication relative 
to untreated control </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>Wild-type 
replicon cells </p>

<p>W55R mutant 
replicon cells 
Number of colonies relative to 
untreated control </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0.01 0.1 
1 
10 100 1,000 </p>

<p>RNA probe concentration (nM) </p>

<p>Normalized bound 
RNA/protein ratio </p>

<p>Figure 5 Clemizol-resistant mutant. Replicon cells were passaged in the 
presence of clemizole and individual colonies were isolated, propagated and 
the HCV genomes harbored within were subjected to sequence analysis. 
(a) Schematic diagram indicating predicted transmembrane and intracellular 
segments of NS4B. Conserved positively charged amino acids are shown in 
red. The clemizole-resistant mutation, W55R, is shown in green. (b) HCV 
replication in Huh7.5 cells electroporated with 50 mg of whole-cell RNA 
extracted from cells harboring either wild type or the W55R mutant clone, 
followed by growth in the absence (white bars) or presence (gray bars) of 
10 mM clemizole. Results represent relative numbers of colonies obtained 
compared to each corresponding untreated control. (c) HCV replication 
assays initiated by electroporation of in vitro transcribed luciferase reporter-
linked wild-type or W55R mutant HCV RNA genomes performed in the 
absence (white bars) or presence (gray bars) of 10 mM clemizole. Results 
represent replication level of each genome relative to its untreated level. 
(d) HCV RNA binding of wild-type NS4B and the W55R NS4B mutant as 
measured in vitro by microfluidics in the presence of 10 nM clemizole 
(gray bars) and its absence (white bars). (e) In vitro binding curves of W55R 
NS4B mutant (solid line, J) and wild-type NS4B (broken line, m) to serial 
dilutions of the RNA probe. Each data point represents the mean of 10-20 
replicates, and the bars represent the standard error. </p>

<p>NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 
1 0 2 3 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>The in vitro IC 50 of clemizole for RNA binding by NS4B is B24 ± 
1 nM, whereas its EC 50 for viral replication is B8 mM. It is possible 
that poor cellular permeability accounts for the B400-fold difference 
between the IC 50 measured for in vitro RNA binding by NS4B and the 
EC 50 measured for the antiviral effect in cells. We hypothesize that 
improved drug delivery and optimization of the compound after 
structure-activity relationship analysis will improve its potency as an 
antiviral agent and that the microfluidic platform can facilitate 
this process. 
This study also demonstrates the utility of a microfluidic approach. 
The microfluidic affinity assay has several important advantages over 
currently used methods, which make it a promising and general tool 
for drug discovery, especially against membrane-bound targets. First, 
protein synthesis by mammalian reticulocyte lysates in the presence 
of microsomal membranes provides the natural conditions required 
for protein folding. Second, the microfluidic assay eliminates the 
need for a high level of protein expression and purification, a 
problem common to currently used methods. Third, this assay is 
capable of detecting transient and low-affinity interactions 15 . Fourth, 
the microfluidic device is capable of making many parallel measure-
ments, and therefore can be used for high-throughput screening. 
Finally, we have shown, in spite of known chemical compatibility 
issues with the elastomer used to fabricate the device, that one can 
successfully screen and discover small molecules with desired phar-
macological properties. 
As with HIV and tuberculosis, effective pharmacologic control of 
HCV will likely best be achieved by a cocktail of several drugs against 
independent virus-specific targets. Combination of even a moderate 
NS4B inhibitor with other emerging anti-HCV agents represents an 
attractive paradigm for increasing current virologic response rates. 
Although we hypothesize that more potent inhibitors than clemizole 
can be obtained, because clemizole has already been extensively used 
in humans (albeit for a different indication based on its antipruritic 
properties) it may find immediate use as a critical component of next 
generation anti-HCV strategies. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Plasmids. Standard recombinant DNA technology was used to construct and 
purify all plasmids. All regions that were amplified by PCR were analyzed by 
automated DNA sequencing. Plasmid DNAs were prepared from large-scale 
bacterial cultures and purified by aMaxiprep kit (Marligen Biosciences). 
Restriction enzymes were purchased from New England Biolabs. 
The open reading frames (ORF) of HuR and HuD were obtained from the 
ORFeome library of cDNA clones (Open Biosystems). These ORFs were 
inserted into the expression vectorpcDNA-Dest 40 vector (Invitrogen) by the 
use of gateway technology (Invitrogen) allowing addition of a C-terminal 
V5-his tag. 
The plasmid pcDNA-NS4B-GFP encoding NS4B of genotype 1a fused in 
frame with a C-terminal GFP was previously described 5 . The mutations RRa, 
RRb and W55R were introduced into this plasmid by site-directed mutagenesis 
(using the QuikChange kit (Stratagene)). The plasmid NS5A(AH)GFP was 
constructed as previously reported. Gus-his vector was obtained from Roche. 
The plasmids pcDNA3.1-5¢ UTR pos, which encodes the 5¢ UTR of the 
positive viral strand, was generated by amplification of the 5¢ UTR positive 
sequence from the Bart79I plasmid 33 with primers containing EcoRV restriction 
sites, digestion with EcoRV and ligation into the corresponding site in 
pcDNA3.1 (Invitrogen). The plasmid pcDNA3.1-3¢ negative terminus, which 
encodes the 3¢ terminal region of the negative RNA strand, was generated 
the same way except that the EcoRV-flanked insert was ligated in an 
inverse orientation. 
The plasmids pcDNA3.1 -3¢ UTR pos and 5¢ negative terminus were 
similarly generated except that the inserted gene was flanked by HindIII and 
Xho1 restriction sites. </p>

<p>The vector encoding the delta virus genomic RNA sequence was cloned by 
inserting NheI-flanked HDV sequence into a pSPT19 vector (Roche Diagnos-
tics) cut with XbaI 23,24 . 
The plasmid FL-J6/JFH-5¢C19Rluc2AUbi that consists of the full-length 
HCV genome and expresses Renilla luciferase was a gift from Charles M. Rice 28 . 
The W55R mutation was introduced into this plasmid by site-directed 
mutagenesis (using the QuikChange kit). </p>

<p>In vitro RNA transcription and fluorescent and radioactive labeling. Plasmid 
DNA of the 5¢ and 3¢ terminal regions of the negative and positive viral strands 
were linearized with XbaI. The plasmid DNA of the delta genomic sequence 
was linearized with XbaI. Linearized plasmids were then treated with proteinase 
K, followed by phenol-chloroform extraction and precipitation with ethanol. 
The DNA was resuspended in RNase-free water to a final concentration of 
1 mg/ml. We used 4 mg of DNA as a template for transcription with the T7 
MEGAscript (Ambion) according to the manufacturer's protocol. The template 
DNA was digested by the addition of 5 U of RQ1 DNase (Ambion) and a 
15-min incubation at 37 1C. The unincorporated ribonucleotides were removed 
by size exclusion with a Micro Bio-Spin P-30 column (Bio-Rad), and the 
transcribed RNA was extracted with phenol-chloroform, followed by precipita-
tion in ethanol. The RNA pellet was washed with 70% ethanol and resuspended 
in H 2 O. Determination of the RNA concentration was performed by measure-
ment of the optical density at 260 nm. The integrity of the RNA and its 
concentration were confirmed by 1% agarose gel electrophoresis and ethidium 
bromide staining. 
The RNA sequences were labeled with Cy5 by using Label IT kit (Mirus) 
according to the manufacturer's protocol followed by purification on a 
microspin column (Mirus) and ethanol precipitation. The number of fluor-
escent labels per RNA molecule was determined by measuring the spectro-
photometric absorbance of the nucleic-dye conjugate at 260 nm and the l MAX 
for Cy5 (650 nm). This was proportional to the probe's length and was used to 
adjust our binding experiments results. 
Cy3-labeled RNA probes used to study RNA binding by HuR and HuD were 
purchased from IDT. 
Radioactive labeling of RNA probes with 32 P was done as previously 
described 34 . </p>

<p>Device design. Device fabrication and design was done essentially as 
described 15 . In brief, a 'control' layer, which harbors all channels required to 
actuate the valves, is situated on top of a 'flow' layer, which contains the 
network of channels being controlled. All biological assays and fluid manipula-
tions are performed on the flow layer. A valve is created where a control channel 
crosses a flow channel. The resulting thin membrane in the junction between 
the two channels can be deflected by hydraulic actuation. Using multiplexed 
valve systems allows a large number of elastomeric microvalves to perform 
complex fluidic manipulations within these devices. Introduction of fluid into 
these devices is accomplished through stainless steel pins inserted into holes 
punched through the silicone. Computer-controlled external solenoid valves 
allow actuation of multiplexors, which in turn allow complex addressing of a 
large number of microvalves. Each unit cell is controlled by three micro-
mechanical valves as well as a 'button' membrane (Supplementary Fig. 1). The 
'button membrane' of each unit cell masks a circular area within the flow 
channel between two 'sandwich' valves. Aligning and bonding a microarray to 
the device allows positioning of the spotted material (RNA probes or inhibitory 
compounds) within the 'RNA chamber' of each unit cell. This chamber can 
then be opened to the flow channel by the control of a 'neck valve' . Devices had 
either 640 or 2,400 unit cells. </p>

<p>RNA binding assay. The approach used was a modification of the 
previously described method for protein-DNA interactions 15 (Supplementary 
Fig. 1). 
For soluble proteins: RNA arraying and device alignment. A dilution series of 
Cy3-labeled target RNA sequences were spotted as a microarray onto epoxy-
coated glass substrates slide (CEL Associates) by OmniGrid Micro (GeneMa-
chines) microarrayer using a CMP3B pin (TeleChem International) with 
column and row pitches of 680 mm and 320 mm, respectively. Each sample 
solution contained 1% BSA in dH 2 O to prevent covalent linkage of the target 
RNA to the epoxy functional groups as well as for visualization during </p>

<p>1 0 2 4 
VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>alignment. After spotting the arrays were quality controlled on a GenePix4000b 
(Molecular Devices). The arrays were then aligned to a microfluidic device by 
hand on a SMZ1500 (Nikon) stereoscope and bonded overnight in the dark on 
a heated plate at 40 1C. 
Surface chemistry (Supplementary Fig. 1c online). All devices were driven 
between 10 and 15 p.s.i. in the control line and between 4 and 6 p.s.i. for the 
flow line. For the initial surface-derivatization steps the chamber valves 
remained closed to prevent liquid from entering the chambers containing the 
spotted RNA targets. First, all accessible surface area was derivatized by flowing 
a solution of biotinylated BSA (Pierce) resuspended to 2 mg/ml in dH 2 O for 
30 min through all channels, followed by a 10 min PBS wash. Next a 500 mg/ml 
neutravidin (Pierce) solution in PBS was flowed for 20 min, followed by a 
10 min PBS wash. Next, the button membrane was closed and the PBS wash 
continued for an additional 5 min. Then all remaining accessible surface area 
except for the circular area of 60 mm masked by the button was passivated with 
the same biotinylated solution as above for 30 min, followed by a 10 min PBS 
wash. Finally a 1:1 solution ofbiotinylated-5-histidine antibody (Qiagen) in 2% 
BSA in PBS was loaded for 2-5 min, after which the button membrane was 
opened and flow continued for 20 min allowing specific functionalization of 
the previously masked circular area. This was again followed by a 10 min PBS 
wash completing the surface derivatization procedure. 
Protein synthesis and MITOMI. Next a standard 25 ml TNT T7-coupled 
wheat germ extract mixture (Promega) was prepared and spiked with 1 ml 
tRNALys-bodipy-fl (Promega) and 2 ml of plasmid DNA template coding for 
the appropriate protein (HuR, HuD or Gus). The mixture was immediately 
loaded into the device and flushed for 5 min, after which the chamber valves 
were opened allowing for dead-end filling of the chambers with wheat germ 
extract. The chamber valves were again closed and flushing continued for an 
additional 5 min. Next the segregation valves separating each unit cell were 
closed followed by opening of the chamber valves allowing for equilibration of 
the unit cell by diffusion. The entire device was heated to 30 1C on a 
temperature-controlled microscope stage and incubated for up to 90 min to 
complete protein synthesis, binding of protein to the surface-bound biotiny-
lated-5-histidine antibody, solvation of target RNA, and equilibration of 
proteins and target RNA. MITOMI was then performed by closing the button 
membrane as well as the chamber valves allowing trapping surface-bound 
complexes while expelling any solution phase molecules. Radial closure pre-
vents solvent pockets from forming between the two interfaces and effectively 
creates zero dead volume while preserving the equilibrium concentrations of 
the molecular interactions. This was followed by a 5 min PBS wash to remove 
untrapped unbound material. The device was then imaged on a modified 
arrayWoRxe (AppliedPrecision) microarray scanner to detect protein synthesis 
and the trapped molecules. 
Image and data analysis. All images were analyzed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">GenePix3.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>). For each experiment an image was taken after MITOMI 
and the final PBS wash. This was used to determine the concentration of 
surface-bound protein (FITC channel) as well as surface-bound target RNA 
(Cy3 channel). Each unit cell generated a single data point that consisted of the 
ratio of median signal of Cy3 to median signal of bodipy; thus, representing the 
ratio of surface-bound RNA to surface-bound expressed protein. Data from 
multiple data points were averaged and their s.d. calculated. Results were then 
normalized to 1. Between 10 and 20 replicates were included for each probe 
tested. A control protein, Gus-his (Roche) was included in each experiment and 
subjected to the same analysis. When present, detected signal with Gus-his was 
used for background subtraction. 
For membrane-associated proteins. Detection of RNA binding by NS4B 
was done as described except for the following modifications. NS4B was 
expressed off the microfluidic device by using a coupled transcription/ 
translation rabbit reticulocyte system (Promega). We added 2 ml canine 
microsomal membranes (Promega) to the reaction mixture to allow appro-
priate protein folding. An NS4B-GFP construct was used thus eliminating 
the need for tRNALysÀbodipyÀfl in the reaction mixture. A biotinylated 
anti-GFP antibody (Abcam) was used to specifically functionalize the 
protected circular area defined by the button. The protein was anchored to 
the chip via its interaction with the surface-bound anti-GFP antibodies. 
The surface-bound protein and the Cy5-labeled HCV RNA probes were loaded 
into the chip and allowed to incubate for 5-20 min in a 50-mM HEPES KOH </p>

<p>(pH 6.8) buffer. Next, MITOMI was performed followed by a brief wash in 
HEPES KOH (pH 6.8) buffer. The device was then scanned and results 
quantified as described above. NS4B-GFP mutants and NS5A(AH)-GFP were 
assayed the same way. Signal detected with NS5A(AH)-GFP was used for 
background subtraction. </p>

<p>Screening of inhibitory compound library. The 1,280 compounds of the 
Lopac library (Sigma) solubilized in DMSO were spotted onto epoxy-coated 
glass substrates slide by OmniGrid Micro microarrayer using a CMP3B pin as a 
microarray. For the primary screen compounds were spotted at a high 
concentration (B1 mM) in duplicates. The array was allowed to dry and 
was then aligned and bonded to a microfluidic device. Two large devices 
(2,400 unit cells per device) were used for the primary screen. The rest of the 
procedure was done similarly to the described above (RNA binding assay). In 
brief, the device was subjected to surface patterning that resulted in a circular 
area coated with biotinylated anti-GFP antibodies within each unit cell. Next, 
NS4B-GFP expressed off chip using coupled transcription/translation rabbit 
reticulocyte system in the presence of microsomal membranes was loaded 
into the chip and bound to the surface biotinylated anti-GFP antibodies. 
Cy5-labeled 3¢ neg terminus RNA probe was then loaded at a concentration of 
1.5 nM. Each unit cell was then isolated followed by a 30 min incubation to 
allow binding of the protein to surface-biotinylated anti-GFP antibodies, 
solvation of library compounds, and equilibration of proteins and target 
RNA. Next, MITOMI was performed trapping surface-bound complexes while 
expelling any solution phase molecules. After a brief wash to remove untrapped 
unbound material the device was scanned and results analyzed. The ratio of 
bound RNA to expressed protein was calculated for each data point by 
measuring the median signal of Cy3 to median signal of bodipy. Results were 
normalized to signal measured in unit cells containing no inhibitory com-
pound. Greater than 90% inhibition was defined as the cutoff for inhibition in 
the primary screen; 104 compounds which were above this cutoff and an 
additional 110 yielding ambiguous results were subjected to a secondary screen. 
This was performed similarly, except that two smaller devices (640 unit cells per 
each) were used; the spotted compound concentration was 10-fold lower 
than in the primary screen, and five replicates were spotted for each compound. 
Inhibition 42.5 fold was considered significant. 18 compounds identified 
in this screen were further analyzed for their inhibitory effect on HCV 
RNA replication. </p>

<p>Determination of IC 50 for in vitro RNA binding. For an accurate measure-
ment of IC 50 s, serial dilutions of the inhibitory compound were loaded onto 
the microfluidic device by continuous flow while maintaining a steady con-
centration of the compound in the flow channel. This helped to avoid losses of 
the spotted compounds from incomplete solubilization and/or binding of the 
compound to PDMS. The experiment was performed essentially as described in 
the RNA binding assay for transmembrane proteins except that the expressed 
protein and the Cy5-labeled HCV RNA probes were incubated in the device in 
the presence of the inhibitory compounds or their absence. IC 50 s were 
measured as described in the statistical analysis section below. </p>

<p>Expression and purification of recombinant NS4B. GST-NS4B and GST were 
expressed in E. coli BL21 and purified as described elsewhere 11 . NS4B was fused 
in frame with an N-terminal 6his-MISTIC protein (membrane-integrating 
sequence for translation of IM protein constructs) 35 . Overnight cultures of 
E. coli transformed with mistic-NS4B plasmid were diluted 1:100 in 400 ml of 
fresh medium and grown at 37 1C to an OD of 0.8. IPTG (Invitrogen) was then 
added to a final concentration of 0.1 mM. After 3 h growth at 37 1C cells were 
pelleted and resuspended in 30cml lysis buffer (50 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris HCL 
(pH8), 100 mM imidazole, 10 mM decylmaltoside, Complete EDTA-free 
protease inhibitors (Roche Applied Science)). Cells were lysed by one cycle in 
a French Press at a pressure of 10,000 p.s.i. for 1 min, followed by centrifugation 
at 12,000g for 5 min at 4 1C. The supernatant was loaded on a nickel column 
(Amersham). After washes, protein was eluted in a buffer containing 400 mM 
imidazole. Glycerol was added at a final concentration of 20% and samples 
were stored at -20 1C. Purification was monitored by SDS-PAGE. Total protein 
concentration was measured using the RC-DC assay (Bio-Rad). NS4B-mistic 
was identified by western blot analyses using monoclonal antibodies against </p>

<p>NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 
1 0 2 5 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

<p>6-his (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) and NS4B (Virostat). 6his-mistic was 
expressed and purified in a similar manner. </p>

<p>GST pull-down assay. Similar to a previously described strategy 36 , 1 mg of 
purified GST-NS4B or GST was incubated for 1 h at 37 1C in a 50 ml reaction 
mixture containing 32 P-labeled in vitro-transcribed HCV RNA (corresponding 
to the 3¢ terminus of the negative viral strand) and binding buffer (10 mM 
DTT, 10 mM Na HEPES (pH 7.4), 33 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM EDTA, 10 mM 
MgCl2). We then added 50 ml oftRNA precoated glutathione-agarose beads 
(Sigma), followed by 1 h incubation at 4 1C to allow binding of GST to the 
beads. The beads were then washed three times in binding buffer and bound 
RNA was measured by liquid scintillation counting of sample aliquots. Control 
incubations with an RNA probe prepared in the absence of T7 RNA polymerase 
were used for background subtraction. </p>

<p>RNA filter binding assay. Assays were performed essentially as described 34 . 
Briefly, various concentrations of mistic-NS4B protein or mistic control were 
incubated for 1 h at 30 1C with 3.3 nM 32 P-labeled in vitro-transcribed HCV 
RNA probe in binding buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.0, 50 mM NaCl, 1 mM 
MgCl2, 10 ng/ml tRNA and 0.2 mM decylmaltoside) in a final volume of 40 ml. 
Membranes were presoaked in the binding buffer and assembled in a dot-blot 
apparatus (Schleicher &amp; Schull) from top to bottom as follows: nitrocellulose 
(Biorad), Hybond N+ (Amersham Biosciences), Whatman 3-mm filter paper. 
The binding reactions were loaded onto the dot-blot apparatus and filtered 
through the membranes. After washing, the membranes were air-dried and 
visualized by phospho-imaging. Results represent percentage of bound RNA 
calculated by dividing the signal detected in the nitrocellulose membrane by the 
sum of the signals detected in the nitrocellulose and the Hybond membranes. </p>

<p>Cell culture and electroporation. Huh7.5 cells were maintained in DMEM 
(Gibco) supplemented with 1% L-glutamine (Gibco), 1% penicillin, 1% 
streptomycin (Gibco), 1Â nonessential amino acids (Gibco) and 10% FBS 
(Omega Scientific). Cell lines were passaged twice weekly after treatment with 
0.05% trypsin-0.02% EDTA and seeding at a dilution of 1:5. Subconfluent 
Huh7.5 cells were trypsinized and collected by centrifugation at 700g for 5 min. 
The cells were then washed three times in ice-cold RNase-free PBS (BioWhit-
taker) and resuspended at 1.5 Â 10 7 cells/ml in PBS. Wild-type or mutant 
FL-J6/JFH-5¢C19Rluc2AUbi RNA for electroporation was generated by in vitro 
transcription of XbaI-linearized DNA templates using the T7 MEGAscript kit 
(Ambion), followed by purification, essentially as described above (in vitro 
RNA transcription and fluorescent labeling). We mixed 5 mg of RNA with 
400 ml of washed Huh7.5 cells in a 2-mm-gap cuvette (BTX) and immediately 
pulsed (0.82 kV, five 99 ms pulses) with a BTX-830 electroporator. After a 
10 min recovery at 25 1C, pulsed cells were diluted into 10 ml of prewarmed 
growth medium. Cells from several electroporations were pooled to a common 
stock and seeded in 6-well plates (5 Â 10 5 cells per well). After 24 h, medium 
was replaced and cells were grown in the presence of serial dilutions of the 
various inhibitory compounds (Sigma) identified in the screen. Seventeen 
commercially available compounds, out of the 18 identified, were analyzed. 
Untreated cells were used as a negative control for water-soluble compounds. 
For compounds solubilized in DMSO, untreated cells were grown in the 
presence of corresponding concentrations of the solvent as a negative control. 
Medium was changed daily. After 72 h of treatment cells were subjected to an 
Alamar Blue-based viability assay and luciferase assay. </p>

<p>Viability assay. After 72 h of treatment cells were incubated for 3 h at 37 1C in 
the presence of 10% Alamar Blue reagent (TREK Diagnostic Systems). Plates 
were then scanned and fluorescence was detected by using FLEXstation II 384 
(Molecular Devices). Depending on the inhibitory compound's solvent, water 
or DMSO, signal was normalized relatively to untreated samples or samples 
grown in the presence of DMSO, respectively. </p>

<p>Luciferase assay. Viral RNA replication was determined using Renilla luciferase 
assay (Promega). The same samples subjected to the viability assay described 
above were analyzed in this assay. Cells were washed with ice-cold PBS and 
scraped off the plate into 250 ml of ice-cold Renilla lysis buffer according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. We then loaded 20 ml of the cell lysates onto 96-well 
plates. We injected 100 ml of the Renilla luciferase assay buffer containing the </p>

<p>assay substrate and measured luciferase activity using a Berthold LB 96 V 
luminometer. As above, signal was normalized relative to untreated samples or 
samples grown in the presence of the corresponding concentration of DMSO. 
Luciferase activity detected in samples treated with 100 u/ml interferon a B2 
(PBL Biomedical Labs) was used as a positive control, demonstrating three log 
reduction at 72 h treatment. The experiment was repeated four times, each time 
with triplicates. IC 50 s were measured by fitting data to a three-parameter 
logistic curve using the formula Y ¼ a+(b -a)/(1 + 10^(X -c)) (<rs id="software-19" type="software">BioDataFit</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-19" type="creator">Chang Bioscience</rs>). </p>

<p>Real-time PCR. 5 Â 10 4 Huh7.5 ells were infected with cell culture-grown HCV 
titered at 1.4 Â 10 4 TCID 50 /ml, as described 29 . Two hours after infection, cells 
were washed three times in culture medium. Cells were then treated daily with 
various concentrations of clemizole. After 72 h samples were subjected to the 
viability assay described above, following which TRIzol Reagent (Invitrogen) 
was added and total cell RNA was extracted in triplicates according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Reverse transcription was then performed using 
random hexamers and Superscript II reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen). Real-
time PCR was performed on the resulting cDNA to quantify the amounts of 
HCV and actin RNA (in separate reactions) in each sample. Standards were 
made using an in vitro-transcribed HCV RNA and human actin standard 
(Applied Biosystems). HCV was quantified using primers AGAGCCATAG 
TGGTCT and CCAAATCTCCAGGCATTGAGC and probe 6-carboxyfluores-
cein-CACCGGAATTGCCAGGACGACCGG-6-carboxytetramethylrhodamine. 
Actin was quantified using beta-actin control reagents (Applied Biosystems) 
according to the manufacturer's instructions. HCV RNA level was adjusted to 
actin level and normalized relative to untreated samples. </p>

<p>Selection of resistant mutants. Established HCV replicon-harboring cells and 
Huh7 cells electroporated de novo with a genotype 1b subgenomic HCV 
replicon (Bart 79I) 30 were passaged in the presence of neomycin and increasing 
concentration of clemizole (1-16 mM). Colonies that were able to grow in the 
presence of the compound were isolated and propagated for 5-10 passages. 
Eleven colonies (out of B60) survived the passages and were subjected to 
sequence analysis, as previously described 11 . </p>

<p>Whole-cell RNA electroporation. Whole-cell RNA was extracted from clem-
izole-resistant replicon clones and from untreated replicon cells using TRIzol 
reagent. Equal amounts of whole cell RNA (50 mg) were electroporated into 
Huh7.5 cells, as described above. Cells were grown under G418 selection 
in the presence or absence of clemizole for 3 weeks. The number of colonies 
was determined using <rs id="software-4" type="software">Image J</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">National Institutes of Health</rs>) following fixation 
and staining with crystal violet. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis. Dissociation equilibrium constants were determined by 
fitting data to the equation describing equilibrium binding; Y ¼ a Â X/(b + X) 
(a and b represent maximum binding and K d , respectively) by nonlinear least-
squares regression fitting (<rs id="software-1" type="software">BioDataFit</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Chang Bioscience</rs>). IC 50 s were measured 
by fitting data to a three-parameter logistic curve using the formula Y ¼ a + 
(b -a)/(1 + 10^(X -c)) (a, b and c represent minimum binding, maximum 
binding and logEC 50 , respectively)(<rs id="software-3" type="software">BioDataFit</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Chang Bioscience</rs>). </p>

<p>Note: Supplementary information is available on the Nature Biotechnology website. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
This work was supported by a Burroughs Wellcome Fund Clinical Scientist 
Award in Translational Research (to J.S.G.) and National Institutes of Health 
(NIH) RO1 DK066793, an NIH Director's Pioneer Award (to S.R.Q.) and NIH 
1RO1 HG002644-01A1. D.G. was supported in part by the Fulbright 
Foundation. S.E. is a recipient of an American Liver Foundation Postdoctoral 
Fellowship Award. We also wish to thank the Stanford University SPARK 
Program, High-Throughput Bioscience Center and the Microfluidic Foundry. 
The plasmid FL-J6/JFH-5¢C19Rluc2AUbi that consists of the full-length HCV 
genome and expresses Renilla luciferase was a gift from Charles M. Rice, 
Rockefeller University. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS STATEMENT 
The authors declare competing financial interests: details accompany the full-text 
HTML version of the paper at http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology/ </p>

<p> 
VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>



<p>NATURE BIOTECHNOLOGY VOLUME 26 NUMBER 9 SEPTEMBER 2008 
1 0 2 7 </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2008 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturebiotechnology </p>

</text></tei>