<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2007-48-UNDERSEA_HYPERBAR_M" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Krauza ML, Lundgren CEG. The effect of body position on inspiratory airflow in divers. Undersea Hyperb 
Med 2007; 34(6):425-430. The purpose of this study was to examine the possibility that body position 
influences inspiratory airflow of submerged subjects. Our previous studies have suggested that for a given 
(negative) inspired gas pressure, exercising divers experience more dyspnea in the prone than in the upright 
position. Methods: Six subjects performed maximal inspiratory efforts recorded as esophageal pressure 
(balloon catheter); simultaneously inspiratory flow and lung volumes were recorded. To standardize static 
lung load, the subjects' chest pressure centroids (representing the average water pressure on the chest) were 
held at a constant depth (0.33m) throughout the experiments. Results: Recordings of peak inspiratory flow 
(PIF) showed a decrease of 25.56 ± 4.14% (mean ± SD, P =0.01) from the submerged upright position mean 
flow of 6.19 ± 1.48 (l/s) to the submerged prone mean flow of 4.37 ± 0.69 (l/s). Nadiral esophageal pressure 
exhibited no significant differences: 5.40 ± 4.32% (mean ± SD, P = 0.512), from the upright mean pressure 
of (-) 51.70 ± 24.09 (cm H 2 O) to the prone mean pressure of (-) 48.53 ± 25.86 (cm H 2 O). Conclusions: The 
significant decrease in PIF when changing from the upright to the prone position, suggests a difference 
in the patency of the extra-thoracic airways. The higher water pressure exerted on the neck in the prone 
position may explain this difference. The similarity of pleural pressures in the two positions indicates that 
the differences in PIF were not due to differences in inspiratory effort. </p>

<p>Previous experiments performed in our 
laboratory by Thalmann et al(1) and Hickey et 
al (2) have investigated respiratory function 
during submersion. The former study involved 
exercise in the prone position. In those 
experiments, both depth and static lung load 
were varied. It was observed that, at maximal 
exertion levels, severe work limiting dyspnea 
became a significant problem. At submaximal 
exertion levels, dyspnea would be greatly 
aggravated by increasing the negative static 
lung load (equivalent to negative pressure 
breathing). This dyspnea was also observed to be 
experienced almost exclusively on inspiration. 
Considerably lower dyspnea scores during 
exercise in the upright position were noted by 
Hickey and colleagues (2) Upon comparison </p>

<p>to the earlier study (1), they hypothesized that 
the difference depended primarily on body 
position leading to differences in hydrostatic 
pressure exerted on the extra-thoracic airways, 
the airways being exposed to a greater external 
pressure in the prone than in the upright body 
position. 
During inspiration, at any point in 
the airways downstream from the mouth, the 
pressure is negative. This negative pressure 
will be most pronounced during a maximal 
inspiratory effort. Since the airways are not 
uniformly rigid, it is possible that during 
submersion, when the hydrostatic pressure 
outside the subject's extrathoracic airways is 
greater than the pressure inside the airways 
(negative transmural pressure), compression 
of the airway is highly likely to occur. As the 
cross-sectional area of an airway decreases, </p>

<p>http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org </p>

<p>UHM 2007, Vol. 34, No. 6 -Body position and inspiratory gas flow in divers </p>



<p>flow resistance increases and the flow of air 
is reduced, if the pressure driving the flow 
remains unchanged. Increased resistance to 
airflow increases the work of breathing. This 
increased work of breathing loads the muscles 
of inspiration, which may cause respiratory 
muscle fatigue and possibly dyspnea (1, 2). </p>

<p>HYPOTHESIS </p>

<p>At a constant inspiratory effort against a 
negative static lung load, as commonly imposed 
by an underwater breathing apparatus, airflow 
is likely to be reduced in the prone compared to 
the upright body position. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Six volunteer subjects (4 male, 2 female; 
age 19-26 years) were recruited from the student 
population of the University at Buffalo, State 
University of New York. Informed consent 
was obtained in accordance with procedures 
of the Institutional Review Board, which also 
approved the study protocol. The subjects 
were randomized with a coin toss into two 
groups at the time of enrollment. All subjects 
completed the experimental protocol. Group 
1 was tested in the prone position first, while 
group 2 was tested in the upright position first. 
The subjects breathed room air at atmospheric 
pressure through a non-rebreathing bag-in-box 
system. Thus, there were no changes in gas 
density between the experimental conditions. 
The location of the chest pressure 
centroid of each subject was determined from 
guidelines in the literature (2-4). A reference 
point was marked on the skin of the chest wall 
in the frontal and sagittal planes. This mark 
was placed on the skin at a point 14 cm below 
the sternal notch and 7 cm behind a frontal 
plane crossing through the sternal notch. The 
subject was then placed in a harness used for 
the submerged portion of the experiment. The </p>

<p>harness consisted of a rigid back-plate, rigid 
padded shoulder bars and an adjustable belt. The 
belt was adjusted to lie across the pelvis and not 
infringe upon chest or abdominal movements 
during respiratory maneuvers. After fitting the 
harness, the waist belt was tightened so that 
the pelvis was comfortably held against the 
back-plate. Measurements from the externally 
marked representation of the subject's chest 
pressure centroid to fixed hard-points on the 
harness were made. The harness was connected 
to scaffolding which could be adjusted so that 
the subject was submerged with the pressure 
centroid at a constant depth (0.33 m ± 0.005 m) 
in both body positions. 
An esophageal, balloon-tipped catheter 
(Nolato Inc., Torekov, Sweden) was used 
to measure esophageal pressure, which is a 
widely-used representation of pleural pressure. 
Before the subject was placed in the harness, 
the esophageal balloon was passed through 
a nostril and swallowed to a depth of 40 cm 
(measured from the nostril.) The balloon 
was inflated with 1.0 ml of air, and the upper 
end of the narrow plastic catheter tube was 
connected to a pressure transducer. Thereafter, 
the subject performed sub-maximal inspiratory 
expiratory and Valsalva maneuvers to confirm 
that the balloon was placed above the level 
of the diaphragm. The subject was then fitted 
with a full face diving mask containing valves 
separating inspiratory and expiratory flow as 
well as a port for the esophageal balloon tube. 
The respiratory circuit was then connected to 
the bag-in-box system, and the subject was 
strapped into the diving harness. The subject 
(still unsubmerged) performed maximal-effort 
inspiratory maneuvers with volume, esophageal 
pressure and time being simultaneously 
recorded. 
The subject was subsequently 
submerged and allowed 15 min to recover 
from the previous respiratory maneuvers 
and acclimate to the experimental situation. 
Water was held at thermoneutral temperature 
(35 ± 0.05° C.) During the recovery period, 
the harness was attached to the scaffolding. </p>

<p>http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org </p>

<p>UHM 2007, Vol. 34, No. 6 -Body position and inspiratory gas flow in divers </p>



<p>After recovery, the subject was strapped 
into the diving harness. Once the subject 
was securely fastened to the diving harness/ 
scaffolding and depth measurements had been 
confirmed, maximal inspiratory maneuvers 
were performed. The subject was allowed 
another recovery period between experimental 
conditions while the harness was recalibrated 
for the other body position. 
The volume and pressure instruments 
were calibrated prior to subject immersion. 
Pressure measurements were made with a 
Validyne model # 1059 pressure transducer 
(Validyne Engineering Corp, Northridge CA 
91324.) Volume measurements were obtained 
at the level of the mouth from the mask using a 
Hans Rudolph model # 3700 pneumotachograph 
(Hans Rudolph Inc, Kansas City, MO 
64114.) Inspiratory flow was determined 
by differentiating the volume signal after the 
experiment had been performed. All data were 
sampled at 100 Hz. For the analyses, results 
from three repetitive maneuvers were averaged 
for each subject and condition. Average flow 
and pressure measurements were compared, 
upright and prone position data being expressed 
as percentages of the results obtained in the 
unsubmerged condition. </p>

<p>STATISTICAL ANALYSIS </p>

<p>Data were analyzed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Microsoft 
Excel</rs> Version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-date">2003</rs>, (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Microsoft Corp.</rs>., 
Redmond, WA.). Mean percent differences in 
flow and pressure from control condition were 
compared using paired two tailed Student's t-
tests. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The unsubmerged peak inspiratory 
flow (PIF) was 8.44 ± 3.54 l/s (mean ± SD.) 
A non-significant decrease in PIF to 6.19 ± 
1.48 l/s was observed with submersion in the 
upright position. A further decrease in PIF to </p>

<p>4.37 ± 0.69 l/s (P = 0.003) was observed with 
submersion in the prone position. A direct 
comparison of the upright versus prone mean 
differences in flow showed a 24.52 ± 19.41 % 
reduction (P = 0.006,) (Fig. 1) </p>

<p>During inspiration, pleural pressure is 
negative. The pressure measurement of interest 
is actually the nadir esophageal pressure 
measured during the inspiratory effort. For 
conceptual ease, this will be referred to as the 
maximal inspiratory pressure, understanding 
that this is a negative value. 
Maximal 
inspiratory esophageal pressures actually 
become more negative with submersion. This 
change indicates that the subjects generated 
an increased inspiratory pressure during 
submersion. Despite the increased inspiratory 
effort, PIF was reduced. A direct comparison 
of the upright versus prone mean differences 
in pressure exhibited a non-significant decrease 
from 51.70 ± 24.09 cm H 2 O in the upright to 
48.53 ± 25.86 cm H 2 O in the prone position 
(Fig 1). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>This randomized crossover experiment 
clearly demonstrates that, as the extra-thoracic </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Relative relationships of inspiratory (esophageal) 
pressure and gas flow. The values for the unsubmerged 
inspiratory pressure (USIP), submerged upright 
inspiratory pressure (SUIP), and submerged prone 
inspiratory pressure (SPIP) are shown in white while 
the unsubmerged inspiratory flow (USIF,) submerged 
upright inspiratory flow (SUIF) and the submerged 
prone inspiratory flow (SPIF) are shown in black. Values 
are percentages of the control condition. </p>

<p>http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org </p>

<p>UHM 2007, Vol. 34, No. 6 -Body position and inspiratory gas flow in divers </p>



<p>airways are exposed to increased hydrostatic 
pressure, peak inspiratory flow is reduced. 
The significance of these experiments lies in 
emphasizing the physiological role of extra-
thoracic airway resistance in the inspiratory 
flow limitations experienced by divers during 
submersion. The results of the present study 
may have implications for divers using different 
types of breathing gear, especially when 
engaging in strenuous work such as swimming 
for extended periods. These results are 
consistent with the observation that respiratory 
muscle fatigue limits swimming endurance in 
divers swimming in the prone position at 70% 
of maximal O 2 consumption and that their 
endurance is enhanced by respiratory muscle 
training (5). 
Previous experiments have shown an 
increase in the dyspnea experienced by divers 
in the prone versus the upright body position. 
Hickey et al. hypothesized there were three 
major factors explaining this phenomenon (2). 
The present study was designed to isolate the 
role of body position on the inspiratory flow 
limitations experienced by divers. Since the 
lung pressure centroid was held at a constant 
depth throughout the experiment, changing 
the body position of the submerged subjects 
altered the hydrostatic forces exerted on their 
extra-thoracic airways alone. The prone body 
position showed a lower maximal inspiratory 
flow rate than the upright body position, with 
the same pleural pressures, static lung load 
and breathing gas density. In the prone body 
position, a greater hydrostatic force was put 
on the extra-thoracic airways. This increase in 
external hydrostatic pressure is likely to have 
resulted in greater compression of the airway 
(Fig. 2). 
A consequent decrease in extra-
thoracic airway cross-sectional area is likely 
to have led to increased resistance to airflow. 
The resulting limitation in PIF may explain 
the more pronounced dyspnea during exercise 
experienced by prone versus upright divers (1, 
2). </p>

<p>The subjects were able to generate 
greater (more negative) inspiratory pressures 
during the submerged phases of the 
experiments. This may have been due to the 
hydrostatic pressure on the chest, lowering 
its end-expiratory volume and stretching the 
inspiratory muscles so as to place them in a 
more favorable position on the length-tension 
curve. 
A unique phenomenon of paradoxical 
inspiratory 
effort-independent 
flow 
is 
theoretically possible. Because there is a 
negative static lung load while breathing with a 
positive hydrostatic pressure load on the extra-
thoracic airway, increases in inspiratory effort 
may raise the airway trans-mural pressure 
gradient. As this pressure gradient increases, 
the airway cross-sectional area can be expected 
to fall. This would result in an effort-dependent 
reduction in airway patency. As limitations in 
inspiratory flow are experienced, the natural </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Schematic of the hydrostatic and gas pressures 
acting on a diver's respiratory system when a generic 
rebreather apparatus is used in the prone or upright 
position. These two situations correspond to the 
experimental conditions of the present study. The size 
of the arrows symbolize the magnitude of the water 
pressure acting on the diver and breathing apparatus and 
the resulting gas pressure in the lungs and extrathoracic 
airway. The gas pressure is set by the water pressure on 
the breathing bag and is the same (same depth) in the two 
positions. By contrast, a higher water pressure (greater 
depth: greater ∆P relative to bag) is acting on the diver's 
neck and thus on the extra-thoracic airways (compressing 
them more) in the prone than in the upright position. </p>

<p>http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org </p>

<p>UHM 2007, Vol. 34, No. 6 -Body position and inspiratory gas flow in divers </p>



<p>compensation is to increase effort. This 
could conceivably result in further reductions 
in flow, which can augment the sensation of 
dyspnea. The physiology of this phenomenon 
is very similar to the expiratory flow limitations 
observed with dynamic airway compression 
due to loss of pulmonary elastic recoil in 
emphysema. 
Due to resource limitations, we were 
unable to measure each individual subjects' 
chest pressure centroid. The pressure centroid 
locations were therefore based on historical 
data. As a result, some very small changes in 
chest volume were noted between submerged 
conditions. The volume differences represent 
a systematic error, which is not likely to have 
impacted the results. 
This study highlights the importance 
of the design and use of underwater breathing 
devices. When so-called rebreathers are used, 
the position of the breathing bag relative to the 
diver's chest and the diver's body orientation 
in the water are important. While the present 
experimental design reproduced the effects of 
a common rebreather-type diving apparatus, 
in which the breathing bag is positioned on 
the divers back, similar relationships between 
breathing gas and airway pressures apply to other 
designs which, for instance, use a bag placed 
on the back but extending over the shoulders. In 
equipment with a chest-mounted bag, the most 
disadvantageous position of the diver is supine, 
for example when working under the bottom of 
a boat. It is of practical interest that a design has 
been published in which a back-mounted bag is 
acted upon by a weight so as to appropriately 
add or reduce breathing gas pressure depending 
on body position (6, 7). Conventional open-
circuit scuba gear (popular among sport divers) 
delivers air equilibrated to the water pressure 
acting on the breathing regulator at the mouth. 
It follows that the maximal negative inspiratory 
pressure is experienced in the upright position. 
By contrast, practically no negative pressure 
will act on the divers' extrathoracic airways in 
the prone position. </p>

<p>While this study addresses a 
phenomenon relevant to diving, it has parallels 
in medicine. Obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) is 
a disorder of the upper airway which results in 
its collapse during nocturnal breathing. Neck 
circumference and obesity are well established 
risk factors for this condition (8-11). Some of 
the airway resistance change observed in OSA 
occurs through mechanisms similar to the one 
proposed to account for the presently-observed 
flow limitations. The main difference is that, 
in OSA, the mass of the soft tissue in the neck 
region is a causative factor, while in our study it 
is an externally imposed hydrostatic pressure. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>The significant decrease in peak 
inspiratory flow observed when changing 
from the submerged upright to the submerged 
prone position is interpreted as a difference in 
the patency of the extrathoracic airways. The 
higher water pressure exerted on the neck in 
the prone position may explain why a lower 
inspiratory flow was achieved than in the 
upright position. The absence of differences in 
pleural pressure between the upright and prone 
positions indicates that the aforementioned 
differences in inspiratory flows were not effort-
dependent. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Professor Brydon Grant, MD for 
valuable discussions of this manuscript and Messrs. 
Dean Marky, Andrew Barth and Bradley Panoff for 
skillful technical assistance. </p>



<p>UHM 2007, Vol. 34, No. 6 -Body position and inspiratory gas flow in divers </p>





<p>http://archive.rubicon-foundation.org </p>

</text></tei>