<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2004-40-NAT_GENET" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A new class of dominant dark skin (Dsk) mutations discovered in a screen of B30,000 mice is caused by increased dermal 
melanin. We identified three of four such mutations as hypermorphic alleles of Gnaq and Gna11, which encode widely expressed 
Gaq subunits, act in an additive and quantitative manner, and require Ednrb. Interactions between Gq and Kit receptor tyrosine 
kinase signaling can mediate coordinate or independent control of skin and hair color. Our results provide a mechanism that can 
explain several aspects of human pigmentary variation and show how polymorphism of essential proteins and signaling pathways 
can affect a single physiologic system. </p>

<p>Understanding the genetic basis of quantitative phenotypes has 
challenged biologists for more than 80 years, with theories outpacing 
specific examples of the underlying molecular architecture. We are 
investigating variation in mouse skin color as a model for other 
quantitative traits and as an entry point for studying basic aspects of 
cell and developmental biology. Genetic studies of skin color examine 
developmental mechanisms at the time when melanoblasts, pigment 
cell precursors migrating from the neural crest, are sorted into three 
alternative locations: the dermis, the epidermis and the hair follicles 1 . 
Until recently, there were few opportunities to study skin color with 
a phenotype-driven approach. Large-scale chemical mutagenesis 
screens have now identified a large and previously unnoticed class 
of pigmentation mutants with dark skin 2-4 . In our initial character-
ization, ten dominant dark skin (Dsk) mutants were placed into two 
distinct groups depending on whether pigment accumulated in the 
dermis or the epidermis 5 . This indicated that epidermal and dermal 
melanocyte populations could be regulated independently by distinct 
sets of genetic pathways. 
Among the dermal class of dark skin mutations, Dsk1, Dsk7 and 
Dsk10 are phenotypically indistinguishable. Here we report that these 
three mutations represent gain-of-function alterations in two genes 
encoding G-protein aÀsubunits: Gnaq (Dsk1 and Dsk10) and Gna11 
(Dsk7). These findings provide new insight into G-protein signaling 
during mammalian development and help to explain how hair and 
skin color can be controlled both coordinately and independently. </p>

<p><rs type="software">Ensembl v5.3.1</rs>only approximately one to three nucleotide substitutions in the 
intervals to which Dsk1 and Dsk7 were mapped. We measured 
expression of Gnaq and Gna11 by RT-PCR and detected mRNA for 
both genes in cultured primary and immortalized melanocytes and in 
dermal and epidermal preparations of neonatal skin (Fig. 2d). Taken 
together with the observation that three independent mutations with </p>

<p>identical phenotypes have nucleotide alterations in the same gene 
or gene family, and the genetic interaction data described below, 
we conclude that Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 are point mutations in 
Gaq class subunits. 
We used the crystal structure for Gas to predict the location of the 
Dsk mutations 12 . Dsk1 in Gnaq (V179M) lies in the all-helical domain </p>

<p>c 
d 
e </p>

<p>f 
g 
h </p>

<p>i 
j </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>D 
HF </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>D 
HF </p>

<p>+/+ 
Dsk1/+ 
Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Dsk10/+ 
+/+ 
Dsk1/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ 
Dsk10/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/Dsk7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Dsk1/+ 
Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Dsk1/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ Dsk10/+ </p>

<p>Figure 1 Morphologic and histologic characteristics of mice heterozygous with respect to Dsk1, Dsk7 or Dsk10. (a) Adult mice can be recognized by dark 
skin on the ears, tails or footpads, and the pattern of footpad pigmentation is identical for the three mutations (Dsk10 not shown). The footpad images were 
published previously 5 . (b) Tail and foot pigmentation 5 d after birth. (c-j) Tail (c-f) and dorsal trunk (g-j) skin from 5-d-old mice of the indicated genotypes. 
Melanin in the sections appears black. Arrows indicate extrafollicular dermal melanin. Scale bars: c-j, 50 mm. E, epidermis; D, dermis; HF, hair follicle. </p>

<p>D19Mit95 </p>

<p>Gnaq Gna14 </p>

<p>Gna15 Gna11 </p>

<p>73719-2 </p>

<p>Gnaq </p>

<p>Gna11 </p>

<p>Ras-like domain 
All helical domain 
PLC-binding domain </p>

<p>Dsk7 </p>

<p>Nonmutant ATC </p>

<p>(I63V) </p>

<p>Dsk1 </p>

<p>Nonmutant GTG </p>

<p>(V179M) 
(F335L) </p>

<p>Nonmutant 
Dsk10 </p>

<p>a 
d </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>All-helical 
domain </p>

<p>Ras-like 
domain </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>I63V 
(Dsk7) </p>

<p>GTP </p>

<p>V179M 
(Dsk1) </p>

<p>F335L 
(Dsk10) </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Gnaq </p>

<p>Gna11 </p>

<p>Tyrp1 </p>

<p>Mitf </p>

<p>Krt5 </p>

<p>Col1a1 </p>

<p>Gapd </p>

<p>0.1 0.5 0.1 0.5 0.1 0.5 0.1 0.5 </p>

<p>M 
e l a n -a 
1° </p>

<p>m 
e l a n . 
E p i d e r m </p>

<p>i s </p>

<p>D 
e r m </p>

<p>i s 
M 
C </p>

<p>µg RNA </p>

<p>13.9 </p>

<p>80.4 </p>

<p>1/1,089 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Dsk1 
Dsk7 
Dsk10 
Mus Dsk 
Mus GnaQ 
Mus Gna11 
Homo GnaQ 
Homo Gna11 
Xenopus GnaQ 
Xenopus Gna11 
Hydra G 3 
Sponge G 3 
Drosophila G 49B 
Caenorhabditis Egl30 
Saccharomyces Gpa2 
Saccharomyces Gpa1 D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>D M </p>

<p>I 
I 
I 
I L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>L R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R 
R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>R </p>

<p>K K </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
I 
L L </p>

<p>L 
L </p>

<p>V H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H 
H F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>F V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V L </p>

<p>L A 
A 
A 
A 
A 
A 
A 
A </p>

<p>A 
A 
A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V 
V </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>I 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F 
F </p>

<p>1/142 
0/142 
1/142 </p>

<p>15.2 15.4 15.7 
16.5 </p>

<p>5/1,089 
0/1,089 
0/1,089 </p>

<p>D10Mit42 
79498-6 
8143-1 </p>

<p>82.2 
81.7 
81.4 
81.3 
80.8 </p>

<p>TTA 
ATG </p>

<p>TTT </p>

<p>GTC </p>

<p>D19Mit128 
D19Mit28 </p>

<p>Figure 2 Positional cloning of Dsk mutations. 
(a) Genetic and physical maps of the Dsk1 
(chromosome 19; top) and Dsk7 (chromosome 
10; bottom) intervals. For each SSLP marker, 
the number of recombinants and number of 
mapping progeny are recorded. Below this, the 
position on the current <rs type="software">Ensembl</rs> mouse genomic 
assembly is shown (in Mb). (b) The positions and 
sequences of the point mutations Dsk1, Dsk7 and 
Dsk10 are shown on a graphic representation of 
the Gnaq and Gna11 transcripts. The locations of 
the main protein domains are marked. (c) The 
amino acid substitutions for the mutations Dsk1, 
Dsk7 and Dsk10 are shown, along with the 
nonmutant sequences of mouse Gnaq and 
Gna11 and the sequences from homologs in 
other species, including Homo sapiens, 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae and Caenorhabditis 
elegans. (d) Expression of Gnaq and Gna11 
mRNA relative to that of genes specific for 
different components of the skin was determined 
by RT-PCR of mRNA purified from melan-a cells, 
primary melanocytes cultured from neonatal skin 
and neonatal dermis and epidermis separated by 
treatment with trypsin. M, molecular weight 
markers (1-kb ladder); C, control (no cDNA). 
(e) The positions of the mutations are projected 
onto the structure of Gas described in ref. 12. 
Dsk7 (I63V) lies in a1 of the ras domain, Dsk1 
(V179M) lies in aF of the all-helical domain, and 
Dsk10 (P335L) lies towards the end of the 
protein in a5. </p>

<p>9 6 2 </p>

<p>VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>(aF) adjacent to switch region I and, therefore, might affect GTPase 
activity or GTP binding (Fig. 2e). The locations of the other 
Dsk mutations are spatially distinct and do not suggest obvious 
mechanisms of action. </p>

<p>Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 are hypermorphic 
To investigate whether the Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 mutations increased 
activity, decreased activity or generated new activity in the resultant 
protein, we crossed mice carrying these mutations with mice carrying 
previously constructed knockout (Gnaq KO or Gna11 KO ) alleles 13,14 . 
Using a quantitative assay for the extent of dermal pigmentation, we 
determined that a single Gnaq KO allele reduced dermal pigmentation 
caused by a single Dsk1, Dsk7 or Dsk10 allele (P ¼ 0.00064; 
Fig. 3a-c,f). A single Gna11 KO allele had no effect on skin darkening 
(Fig. 3d-f), but two Gna11 KO alleles reduced dermal pigmentation 
caused by Dsk1 (P ¼ 0.033; Fig. 3d,f). 
We also noticed that heterozygous Gnaq KO mice had a lighter 
dermis than their normal littermates, a phenotype that was obscured 
in the whole mouse by a normally pigmented epidermis (P ¼ 0.0025; 
Fig. 3a,b,f). In contrast, heterozygous Gna11 KO mice did not have an 
obvious change in dermis pigmentation (data not shown). These 
results indicate that the three Dsk mutations are hypermorphic, with 
effects exactly opposite to that caused by reduced gene dosage. Normal </p>

<p>skin color is more sensitive to reduced dosage of Gnaq than to reduced 
dosage of Gna11, but the two genes must function cooperatively, as 
knock-out of one can ameliorate a hypermorphic mutation in the 
other gene. 
These results also speak to the relative strength of the mutations in 
terms of gene dosage. Mice hemizygous with respect to any of the 
three Dsk alleles were intermediate in phenotype between wild-type 
mice and single heterozygotes (Gnaq Dsk10/+ 4 Gnaq Dsk10/KO 4 
Gnaq +/+ ), which suggests that the activity of a single Dsk allele is 
greater than that of two copies of the normal allele. </p>

<p>Dsk1 and Dsk7 act additively and quantitatively 
To determine the effect of progressively increasing total Gaq signaling, 
we generated mice carrying both Dsk1 and Dsk7 mutations (Fig. 4). 
Dermal pigmentation increased progressively and in a step-wise 
manner in mice carrying zero, one, two, three and four Dsk alleles 
in any combination (Fig. 4a). 
In examining mutant mice for additional phenotypes, we found 
that double homozygotes appeared grossly normal but small. Increas-
ing the number of mutated alleles caused a progressive and linear 
decrease in body mass at 6 weeks of age (Fig. 4b; linear regression 
analysis, P o 0.0001). In a cohort of mice aged to 36 weeks, 
the linear relationship between body weight and number of Dsk </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 
Males 
Females </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Weight (g) </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>170 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>190 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
Body length (mm) </p>

<p>b 
c </p>

<p>Epidermis </p>

<p>Dermis </p>

<p>Number of hypermorphic Gnaq and/or Gna11 alleles </p>

<p>Number of hypermorphic Gnaq and/or Gna11 alleles </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Gnaq 
Gna11 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>+/+ 
+/+ 
+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ 
+/+ 
Gof/+ 
Gof/+ Gof/+ </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
Gof/+ </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
Gof/Gof </p>

<p>Gof/Gof 
Gof/Gof Gof/Gof </p>

<p>Gof/Gof </p>

<p>Figure 4 Additive effects of Gaq activity on pigmentation and body size. (a) Tail epidermis (top) and dermis (bottom) from 3-week-old Dsk1 and Dsk7 mice 
on an isogenic background. The number of gain-of-function (Gof) Dsk1 and Dsk7 alleles is indicated for each sample, which is representative of at least 
three mice. (b) The linear relationship between average body weight and the number of Dsk1 and Dsk7alleles on a mixed genetic background is shown for 
6-week-old males and females. (c) The relationship between body length and the number of Dsk1 and Dsk7 alleles is shown for 36-week-old females. </p>

<p>+/+ 
Gof/+ 
1 </p>

<p>+/+ 
Gof/Lof 
2 </p>

<p>+/+ 
Gof/+ 
5 </p>

<p>+/+ 
Gof/Lof 
6 </p>

<p>+/+ 
+/+ 
7 (3, 13) </p>

<p>+/+ 
Lof/+ 
8 (4) </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
+/+ 
9 </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
Lof/+ 
10 </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
Lof/Lof 
12 </p>

<p>+/+ 
Gof/+ 
14 </p>

<p>Lof/+ 
Gof/+ 
15 </p>

<p>Lof/Lof 
Gof/+ 
16 </p>

<p>Gof/+ 
+/+ 
17 (18) </p>

<p>Gof/Lof 
+/+ 
19 (20) </p>

<p>Dermis pigmentation (relative units) </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 
100 </p>

<p>Gna11 Gnaq </p>

<p>Dsk1 </p>

<p>Dsk7 </p>

<p>Dsk10 </p>

<p>Dsk1 </p>

<p>Dsk7 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>9 
10 
11 
12 
13 </p>

<p>14 
15 
16 </p>

<p>17 
18 
19 
20 </p>

<p>Figure 3 Interaction of Gnaq and Gna11 
knockout mutations with Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10. 
(a-e) Representative samples of tail dermis from 
3-week-old mice. (f) The average pixel intensity of 
each genotype was normalized to the average of 
the Dsk heterozygotes in each cross, which was 
set at 100. Genotypes, shown below tails in a-e 
and to the right of the histogram in f, are as 
follows: 1, Gnaq Dsk1/+ ; 2, Gnaq Dsk1/KO ; 3, +/+; 
4, Gnaq KO/+ ; 5, Gnaq Dsk10/+ ; 6, Gnaq Dsk10/KO ; 
7, +/+; 8, Gnaq KO/+ ; 9, Gna11 Dsk7/+ ; 10, 
Gna11 Dsk7/+ Gnaq KO/+ ; 11, Gna11 Dsk7/KO 
Gnaq KO/+ ; 12, Gna11 Dsk7/+ Gnaq KO/KO ; 13, +/+; 
14, Gnaq Dsk1/+ ; 15, Gnaq Dsk1/+ Gna11 KO/+ ; 16, 
Gnaq Dsk1/+ Gna11 KO/KO ; 17,18, Gna11 Dsk7/+ ; 
19,20, Gna11 Dsk7/KO . Lof, loss-of-function 
(knockout alleles); Gof, gain-of-function 
(Dsk alleles). </p>

<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>alleles persisted (data not shown); these mice also had a progressive 
decrease in body length (Fig. 4c). Increasing numbers of Dsk1 or Dsk7 
mutations had no effect on the relative amount of lean body mass 
(zero mutations, 61.4 7 5.5%; one mutation, 62.1 7 3.1%; two 
mutations, 63.6 7 2.6%; three mutations, 62.8 7 5.2%; four muta-
tions, 60.7 + 3.0%), suggestive of a general effect on cell number or 
size rather than a perturbation of intermediary metabolism or energy 
homeostasis. These observations indicate that Gnaq and Gna11 act 
additively and quantitatively, with the extent of Gaq activity read with 
unexpected precision by downstream signaling components. </p>

<p>Developmental mechanism of Dsk1 and Dsk7 action 
To determine whether increased pigmentation in Dsk1 and Dsk7 
mutants represents a difference in pigment cell number or pigment 
production, we made use of a lacZ reporter gene controlled by 
regulatory sequences from the gene Dct (also called Tyrp2). Between 
embryonic day (E) 10 and E16.5, melanoblasts migrate from the 
neural crest to the dermis, and then to the epidermis 15-17 . The 
Dct-lacZ transgene is expressed in melanoblasts as soon as they 
leave the neural crest and persists through most developmental stages 
and in epidermal melanocytes 17,18 . 
We observed more lacZ-positive cells in Gnaq Dsk1/+ and Gna11 Dsk7/+ 
embryos beginning at the earliest stage at which melanoblasts can 
be detected (E10.5; Fig. 5a-j). At E12.5, lacZ-positive cells were 
more numerous in both the dermis and the epidermis of mutant 
embryos, but by E16.5, the nonmutant cell number caught up to the 
number of the mutants in the epidermis (Fig. 5e-j). This time 
period corresponds to a main period of epidermal development, 
the appearance of a stratified epithelium 19,20 ; thus, events inherent 
to this process may actively regulate the density of melanocytes 
'permitted' in the epidermis. 
To look for the underlying cause of the increased number of lacZ-
positive cells, we measured the mitotic index and extent of apoptosis 
in lacZ-positive cells of Gnaq Dsk1/+ , Gna11 Dsk7/+ and wild-type 
embryos carrying the Dct-lacZ transgene (Fig. 5k-l). At E11.5, we 
found no difference in mitotic index (Table 1) or TUNEL staining 
(data not shown). We also observed no effect of Dsk1 or Dsk7 on 
dorsoventral migration, as judged by the position of the migrating 
ventral edge of lacZ-positive cells (data not shown). These observa-
tions suggest that increased Gq signaling may act by increasing the 
number of neural crest cells that differentiate into melanoblasts. </p>

<p>Adult Gnaq Dsk1/+ (data not shown) and Gna11 Dsk7/+ mutants 
had the same number of lacZ-positive cells in the tail epidermis 
as did wild-type mice (Fig. 5m,n), even though increased dermal 
pigmentation persisted (Figs. 3 and 4). Taken together, these 
observations indicate that the fundamental defect of Dsk1 or Dsk7 
that causes dark skin is a doubling of the melanoblast population 
(Table 1) before E10.5. The expanded melanoblast population is 
otherwise normal, and the dermal specificity of the dark skin 
phenotype is a secondary effect of mechanisms intrinsic to the 
developing epidermis. </p>

<p>Requirement for Ednrb but not Kit 
In principle, hypermorphic mutations of Gnaq and Gna11 could result 
in constitutive activation independent of a seven-transmembrane 
receptor or hyperactivation when signaling is initiated normally. To 
test this possibility in vivo, the receptor(s) that normally couple to Gq 
during pigmentary development must be identified. One of the best 
candidates is the endothelin receptor B (Ednrb), which is required for 
normal pigmentation between E10 and E12.5 (ref. 21). We generated 
Ednrb s-l/s-l Gnaq Dsk1/+ and Ednrb s-l/s-l Gna11 Dsk7/+ double mutants 
and found that they were indistinguishable from Ednrb s-l/s-l single 
mutant littermates (Fig. 6a-c). 
The requirement of Dsk1 or Dsk7 for Ednrb is not caused by a block 
in melanocyte development, because additional crosses to mice 
carrying a loss-of-function mutation in the Kit receptor tyrosine 
kinase gene showed that Dsk1 or Dsk7 could partially rescue the 
more severe deficit of melanocytes observed in Kit w-v/w-v mice 22 . 
Double-mutant Kit w-v/w-v Gnaq Dsk1/+ or Kit w-v/w-v Gna11 Dsk7/+ mice 
lack all hair pigmentation but have conspicuous dark ear skin </p>

<p>h </p>

<p>i </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>a 
b 
c 
d </p>

<p>m </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>E12.5 Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>E12.5 
+/+ </p>

<p>E10.5 </p>

<p>E16.5 
+/+ </p>

<p>E16.5 Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Adult 
+/+ </p>

<p>Adult Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>E 
D </p>

<p>l 
k </p>

<p>NT </p>

<p>E16.5 
+/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>j </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>E12.5 </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ 
Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Dermis 
Epidermis </p>

<p>+/+ 
+/+ 
Dsk1/+ 
Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Figure 5 Developmental mechanism by which dark skin is caused by 
increased Gaq activity. (a-f,h-i) X-gal-stained Dct-lacZ transgenic embryos 
and skin samples from mice of the indicated ages and genotypes. Each 
image is representative of at least three mice or embryos. E, epidermis; 
D, dermis. (g) The number of lacZ-positive cells per cm of section in the 
dermis and epidermis of E12.5 wild-type (+/+) and Gna11 Dsk7/+ embryos, as 
measured in the anterior-most flank skin. The lacZ-positive cells directly 
adjacent to the exterior were considered to be located in the single cell-
layered epidermis. (j) The number of lacZ-positive cells per cm of section in 
the dermis and epidermis of E16.5 wild-type (+/+) and Gna11 Dsk7/+ 
embryos, as measured in the mid-back dorsal skin. At this stage, the 
epidermis has differentiated into a thickened layer, as indicated. 
(k,l) An E11.5 Dct-lacZ transgenic embryo sectioned and incubated with 
fluorescently labeled antibodies: antibody to phosphorylated histone H3 
(red) and antibody to b-galactosidase (green). A doubly labeled cell (yellow) 
is visible in l. NT, neural tube. (m,n) Tail epidermal sheets from 3-week-old 
mice. There was no significant difference in the number of epidermal 
lacZ-positive cells per scale (79 7 3 and 72 7 4 for wild-type and 
Gna11 Dsk7/+ mice, respectively). Scale bars: a-d, 500 mm; e,f,h,i,m,n, 
200 mm; k,l, 50 mm. </p>

<p>9 6 4 </p>

<p>VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>(Fig. 6d,e), which was never observed in Kit w-v/w-v littermates. Thus, 
the mechanism by which Dsk1 and Dsk7 act depends on a functional 
receptor. This indicates that endothelin signaling is the main mediator 
of the Dsk1 and Dsk7 mutant phenotype. </p>

<p>Signaling pathway interactions 
Because Dsk1 and Dsk7 increase Gq activity, they provide a unique 
opportunity to investigate how different signaling pathways interact to 
modulate hair and skin pigmentation. Many white-spotting mutations 
are thought to act by compromising the proliferation or survival of 
melanoblasts, such that progenitor pools are exhausted before migra-
tion is complete 23-26 . If this is the case, the increased number of early 
melanoblasts caused by Dsk1 and Dsk7 mutations might rescue white 
spotting, regardless of the underlying cause. 
We found that Dsk1 or Dsk7 decreased the proportion of white-
spotted mice among mice heterozygous with respect to Kit w-v , Ednrb s-l 
or Pax3 Splotch (Fig. 6f,g). Pax3 Splotch/+ and Ednrb s-l/+ mice were 
rescued more effectively than Kit w-v/+ mice, and in each case, Dsk7 
was more effective at rescuing white spotting than Dsk1 (Fig. 6g). 
These results confirm that Dsk1 and Dsk7 promote expansion of the 
early melanoblast population, and indicate that in conditions where 
melanoblast number is limiting, increased Gq signaling can promote 
hair and skin pigmentation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
Gnaq and Gna11 encode two of the four members of the Gaq subunit 
class, the 'classical' pathway for coupling seven transmembrane </p>

<p>receptors to phospholipase Cb 7 . Gain-of-function mutations of 
GNAS have been described as genetic mosaics in the human condition 
McCune-Albright syndrome and in neuroendocrine tumors 27,28 . In 
C. elegans, three hypermorphic alleles of the Gaq homolog, egl-30, 
have been isolated in suppressor screens 29,30 . Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 are 
the first examples of hypermorphic Gq mutations in vertebrates and 
the first hypermorphic mutations of any Ga subunit recognized in the 
vertebrate germ line. 
Theoretically, increased Gaq activity could be caused by specific 
alterations that increase affinity for GTP, the receptor, the effector or 
accessory proteins, or by nonspecific alterations that disrupt Gaq 
structure and impair intrinsic GTPase activity. Because the six 
hypermorphic mutations (three from mouse and three from worm) 
lie in different regions, a nonspecific mechanism (reduced GTPase 
activity) seems more likely. 
Gnaq and Gna11 are widely expressed, but expression of Ednrb 
during pigment cell development occurs mainly in melanoblasts 
rather than their surrounding cells 31,32 . Because Dsk1 and Dsk7 
depend on a functional Ednrb gene, and because Ednrb couples to 
Gaq proteins, we believe that Dsk-induced dermal melanocytosis 
occurs through a cell-autonomous mechanism in which amplification 
of normal endothelin signaling through mutant Gq subunits causes an 
excess number of early melanoblasts. Recent organ culture studies, 
however, suggest that a non-cell autonomous mechanism is possible, 
as Ednrb-deficient pigment cells can be partially rescued by coculture 
with nonmutant neural tubes or exogenous Kit ligand 33 . 
Increased Gq signaling in pigment cells may also underlie dermal 
hyperpigmentation and melanocytic tumors that develop in transgenic 
mice in which a metabotropic glutamate receptor, Grm1, is driven 
by the Dct promoter 34 . Finally, dermal melanocytosis has been 
described 35 in transgenic mice in which hepatocyte growth factor 
(Hgf) is controlled by the keratin 14 promoter. The Hgf receptor is a 
tyrosine kinase that does not couple directly to Gq subunits, but its 
activation could intersect with that of Ednrb or Grm1 signaling in 
pigment cells. 
We expected to find additional phenotypes in Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 
mutants, as our quantitative analysis suggested that each Dsk mutation 
more than doubles the effective gene dosage 9,14 . By contrast, even 
moderate gain-and loss-of-function alleles of egl-30 have more </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>g 
f </p>

<p>b 
c 
d 
e </p>

<p>Percentage of mice with white spotting </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Gnaq 
Gna11 
Spotting mutation 
Number </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Gof 
Gof </p>

<p>Gof 
Gof 
Gof </p>

<p>Gof </p>

<p>Kit Kit Kit 
14 11 
8 </p>

<p>Sp Sp Sp 
17 
9 
7 
20 16 23 </p>

<p>Ed Ed Ed </p>

<p>Kit </p>

<p>w-v </p>

<p>Kit </p>

<p>w-v </p>

<p>Kit </p>

<p>w-v </p>

<p>Kit </p>

<p>w-v </p>

<p>Kit </p>

<p>w-v </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ 
Dsk1/+ 
Ednrb </p>

<p>s-l </p>

<p>Ednrb </p>

<p>s-l </p>

<p>Ednrb </p>

<p>s-l </p>

<p>Dsk1/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ 
Dsk7/+ 
+/+ 
+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>+/+ </p>

<p>Dsk7/+ </p>

<p>Figure 6 Rescue of white-spotting mutations by 
Dsk1 or Dsk7. (a-c) Ednrb sÀl/sÀl , Ednrb sÀl/sÀl 
Gnaq Dsk1/+ and Ednrb sÀl/sÀl Gna11 Dsk7/+ mice. 
(d,e) Kit wÀv/wÀv , Kit wÀv/wÀv Gna11 Dsk7/+ and 
Kit wÀv/wÀv Gnaq Dsk1/+ mice. Mice shown are 
representative of more than five of each genotype. 
(f) Representative 5-week-old progeny from a 
cross between Gna11 Dsk7/+ and Kit wÀv/+ mice. 
(g) The percentage of mice with white belly hair 
is indicated for each genotype. Gof, gain-of-
function (Dsk1 and Dsk7 alleles); Kit, Kit wÀv ; 
Sp, Pax3 Splotch ; Ed, Ednrb sÀl . </p>

<p>Table 1 Pigment cell number and proliferation at E11.5 </p>

<p>Characteristic 
Genotype </p>

<p>Wild-type 
Gnaq Dsk1/+ 
Gna11 Dsk7/+ 
Number of pigment cells per section 
7.9 7 1.3 18.0 7 7.2 14.8 7 6.7 
Percentage of pigment cells in mitosis 2.9 7 0.3 
3.0 7 0.5 
2.8 7 0.5 </p>

<p>Number of embryos examined 
7 
4 
5 </p>

<p>Embryos carrying the Dct-lacZ transgene were doubly labeled with fluorescent antibodies: an 
antibody to b-galactosidase, which labels melanocytes, and an antibody to phosphorylated 
histone H3, which labels cells in mitosis. Results are given as mean 7 s.e.m. </p>

<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>substantial effects 30,36 . This apparent difference-in which a mammal 
is better able than an invertebrate to buffer changes in Gaq activity-
might be explained by more complex regulation of G-protein signal-
ing. As a corollary, the sensitivity of skin color to Gaq gene dosage 
may indicate that pigment cells rely more on the intrinsic GTPase 
activity of Ga subunits than do other cells. If so, we expect Dsk 
mutants to have pleiotropic phenotypes if one or more GAP 
genes are deleted, as Gq signaling is increased past the buffering 
capabilities of the pathway. For example, an increase of Gnaq 
expression in the mouse heart by a factor of more than 4 causes 
cardiac hypertrophy 37 . 
In species with a broad range of pigmentary variation, such as 
humans and domestic mice, there is a strong correlation between 
dark skin and dark hair. Together with earlier work on Kit and 
Ednrb signaling 21,38,39 , our studies of Gnaq and Gna11 mutations 
show how these traits can be controlled both coordinately and 
independently (Fig. 7). 
The earliest steps in melanoblast differentiation occur before E10 
and depend on Kit, but not Ednrb, signaling 21,38-41 . The situation is 
reversed between E10 and E12.5, when Ednrb, but not Kit, is required 
as melanoblasts migrate within the embryonic dermis. In a penulti-
mate step, melanoblasts enter the epidermis between E12.5 and E16.5 
and undergo additional rounds of proliferation, during which time Kit 
is again required, but Ednrb is not. 
Our results show that increased Gq signaling acts before E10.5 to 
produce more early melanoblasts (Fig. 7). The effects appear in both 
the embryonic dermis and epidermis, but the dermis permits a 
permanent increase in melanoblast number whereas the epidermis 
does not (Fig. 7a,b). An independent effect on hair and skin color is 
most readily apparent under conditions where survival of epidermal 
melanoblasts is compromised, leading to dark skin in the absence of 
hair pigmentation (Fig. 7f; see also Fig. 6d,e). </p>

<p>An important goal of large-scale mutagenesis studies currently 
underway is to increase the repertoire of genes implicated in specific 
physiologic processes, with the underlying assumption that genotype-
phenotype correlations for most morphogenetic pathways are far from 
saturation. Given that Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 are three of the four 
dermal dark skin mutations recovered from a screen of B30,000 mice, 
it is notable that all three act by increasing the activity of Gaq 
subunits. This fact suggests that dermal melanocytosis is a phenotypic 
signature for increased signaling through receptors that activate 
phospholipase Cb. 
Gnaq and Gna11 arose early in vertebrate evolution and are 
coexpressed in most tissues 9,10 . In crosses with knockout alleles, 
reduction of gene dosage from four to two copies has little effect in 
tissues where both genes are expressed, but further reduction is 
lethal 14 . This threshold effect has been interpreted as genetic overlap, 
in which more copies of Gnaq and Gna11 exist than are necessary. 
But the observation that Dsk mutations act additively on pigment-
ation and body size indicates that, at least for these two 
characteristics, the exact amount of Gq signaling is critical and acts 
directly and quantitatively. The ability of downstream effectors to 
interpret the amount of Gaq activity and precisely transmit this 
information probably provided selective pressure against variation in 
gene dosage, and could represent a general theme in evolution of 
signal transduction proteins that couple transmembrane receptors to 
intracellular machinery. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Mouse strains. We generated Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 mutants on an isogenic 
C3HeB/FeJ background as previously described 3,5 . We crossed Gnaq and Gna11 
knockout mice (provided by T. Wilkie, UT Southwestern, Dallas, Texas, 
USA) 13,14 for two generations to C3HeB/FeJ mice. We obtained C57BL/6J 
mice, CAST/Ei mice and mice carrying Ednrb s-l , Kit w-v or Pax3 Splotch from The 
Jackson Laboratory. We maintained Kit w-v and Pax3 Splotch mice on a C57 
background and Ednrb s-l mice on a SSL/Le background. We crossed mice 
carrying the Dct-lacZ reporter transgene (provided by M. Shin (Fox Chase 
Cancer Center, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, USA) with the permission of 
I. Jackson (MRC Human Genetics Unit, Western General Hospital, Edinburgh, 
Scotland)) 24 for at least three generations to C3HeB/FeJ mice. All experiments 
were carried out under a protocol approved by the Stanford Administrative 
Panel on Laboratory Animal Care. </p>

<p>Genotyping. We genotyped Dsk1, Dsk7, Dsk10 or Pax3 Splotch mice by digesting 
PCR-amplified fragments from tail or extraembryonic membrane DNA with a 
restriction enzyme (NspI, FokI DdeI or BsrI, respectively) that distinguished 
between the mutant and nonmutant fragments; primer sequences are available 
on request. We genotyped Gnaq and Gna11 knockout mice 42 and Kit w-v mice 24 
as previously described. To detect the Ednrb s-l allele, which is a complete </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Adult skin </p>

<p>Embryonic skin </p>

<p>d 
e 
f </p>

<p>E10.5 
E12.5 
E16.5 </p>

<p>Ednrb/Gq-dependent </p>

<p>Kit-dependent </p>

<p>Melanoblast 
movement 
into epidermis </p>

<p>Dorsoventral 
migration 
through dermis </p>

<p>Melanoblast 
proliferation 
in epidermis </p>

<p>Hairy 
Hairy 
Hairy 
Hairy </p>

<p>Nonmutant </p>

<p>Decreased 
melanoblasts 
from neural crest </p>

<p>Increased Gq 
+ 
decreased 
melanoblasts 
from neural crest </p>

<p>Increased Gq 
+ 
late decrease 
of epidermal 
melanoblasts </p>

<p>E10.5 
E12.5 
E16.5 </p>

<p>Gnaq Dsk1 
or 
Gna11 Dsk7 </p>

<p>Non-
mutant </p>

<p>Nonhairy 
Nonhairy 
Nonhairy 
Nonhairy </p>

<p>Figure 7 Coordinate and independent control of hair and skin color. 
(a) Neural crest-derived melanoblasts migrate ventrally through the 
embryonic dermis between E10 and E12.5; this process is dependent on 
Ednrb 21 and on Gq activity. Starting at E12.5, melanoblasts move from 
the embryonic dermis to the epidermis and then proliferate extensively in 
the epidermis. (b) Hypermorphic mutations of Gnaq or Gna11 result in 
more early melanoblasts by E10.5 in the dermis and more epidermal 
melanoblasts at E12.5. By E16.5, the number of epidermal melanoblasts 
in nonmutant mice has caught up to the number in Dsk1 or Dsk7 
mutants. (c,d) Fewer early melanoblasts, as would result from loss-
of-function mutations in Ednrb or Gnaq, gives rise to white spotting 
or decreased dermal pigmentation, respectively. (e) Hypermorphic 
mutations of Gnaq or Gna11 can rescue white spotting caused by a 
reduced number of neural crest-derived melanoblasts, but have no 
effect (f) if white spotting is caused by a late decrease in the number of 
epidermal melanoblasts. </p>

<p>9 6 6 </p>

<p>VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

<p>deletion of the Ednrb locus, we used a simple sequence length polymorphism 
(SSLP) marker located 1 cM from the Ednrb locus, D14Mit42, that distin-
guishes between the SSL/Le and C3HeB/FeJ alleles 43 . </p>

<p>Positional cloning of Dsk1 and Dsk7. Linkage of Dsk1, Dsk7 and Dsk10 to 
chromosome 10 or chromosome 19 was described previously 5 . For Dsk1 and 
Dsk7, we used recombinants to narrow the genetic interval with additional 
SSLP markers with an outcross-backcross mapping strategy to either C57/BL6 
mice (Dsk1) or CAST/Ei mice (Dsk7). In areas with no polymorphic Mit 
markers, we generated new SSLP markers that distinguished between C3HeB/ 
FeJ and CAST/Ei sequences in the Gna11 interval with the following genome 
sequence coordinates (mm4, October 2003, National Center for Biotechnology 
Information build 32): marker 73719-2, chr 10: 82937910-82938055; marker 
8143-1, chr 10: 83325512-83325696; 79498-6, chr 10: 84426706-84426815. We 
directly sequenced DNA from mutant and nonmutant tail tissue biopsies after 
PCR amplification. All mutations were confirmed using sequencing, PCR and 
restriction digestion of genomic DNA from three or more mutant mice and 
nonmutant littermates. </p>

<p>RT-PCR. We isolated total RNA from melan-a cells, primary melanocytes, 
neonatal epidermis and neonatal dermis using Trizol (Invitrogen) and purified 
it using RNeasy (Qiagen). We then treated 100-500 ng of RNA with DNAseI 
before reverse transcription using Superscript II (Invitrogen). We diluted the 
cDNA products 40-fold before carrying out PCR. All primer sequences were 
designed to span introns and are available on request. </p>

<p>Histology and immunofluorescence. We fixed dorsal trunk and tail skin from 
5-d-old mice overnight in 4% paraformaldehyde, embedded tissues in paraffin, 
cut 8-mm sections and stained them with eosin and hematoxylin. For lacZ 
staining of embryos, we crossed C3HeB/FeJ Gnaq Dsk1/+ or Gna11 Dsk7/+ mice 
with transgenic heterozygous Dct-lacZ mice in timed matings (with the day of 
the copulation plug designated E0.5). We fixed embryos between E10.5 and 
E16.5 for 1 h in 4% paraformaldehyde and then incubated them in X-gal 
staining solution overnight at room temperature with rocking. We embedded 
tissues in paraffin, cut 12-mm sections and counterstained them with eosin. For 
lacZ staining of adult tail epidermis, we removed a 1-cm length of tail, removed 
the skin and allowed it to adhere, epidermis side down, to a grease-coated glass 
slide and then incubated it overnight in X-gal staining solution. We then 
incubated the samples at 37 1C for 75 min in 2 M NaBr and peeled away the 
dermis using forceps. 
For measurement of mitotic index, we recovered E11.5 embryos as described 
above, fixed them overnight in 4% paraformaldehyde, washed them in 30% 
sucrose and then embedded them in OCT. We cut 50 transverse serial sections 
(12 mm) from each embryo, beginning with the first section containing 
forelimb, and stained them overnight at 4 1C with a monoclonal antibody 
against b-galactosidase (Promega, 1:500) and a rabbit polyclonal antibody 
against phosphorylated histone H3 (Upstate, 1:200). We then incubated them 
with secondary antibodies, antibody to mouse conjugated to fluorescein 
isothiocyanate and antibody to rabbit conjugated to rhodamine (Jackson 
Immunoresearch, 1:63), for 1 h at room temperature. Using fluorescence 
microscopy, we counted at least 196 lacZ-positive cells for each embryo. For 
all experiments, we examined at least three embryos or mice and 50 sections of 
each genotype at each stage. </p>

<p>Weight and body composition assays. We intercrossed Gnaq Dsk1/+ Gna11 Dsk7/+ 
mice on a mixed (C3HeB/FeJ and C57BL/6J) background and weighed F 1 or F 2 
progeny from 23 litters at 6 weeks of age. We allowed a cohort of females from 
ten litters to age to 36 weeks, at which time we determined weight, body length 
and lean body mass (measured using Piximus dual energy X-ray absorptio-
metry, GE Medical Systems). </p>

<p>Genetic interactions. The following five crosses were made to study the effect 
of null alleles of Gnaq and Gna11 on the Dsk phenotype: 1, Gnaq Dsk1/+ Â 
Gnaq KO/+ ; 2, Gnaq Dsk10/+ Â Gnaq KO/+ ; 3, Gna11 Dsk7/+ Gnaq KO/+ Â Gna11 KO/+ 
Gnaq KO/+ ; 4, Gnaq Dsk1/+ Gna11 KO/+ Â Gna11 KO/+ ; and 5, Gna11 Dsk7/+ Â 
Gna11 KO/+ . To study signaling pathway interactions, we crossed inbred 
Gnaq Dsk1/+ and Gna11 Dsk7/+ mice to inbred Kit wÀv/+ , Pax3 Splotch/+ and </p>

<p>Ednrb s-l/+ mice, genotyped progeny as described above and counted the 
number of mice with any white belly hair. </p>

<p>Accession numbers. GenBank: Saccharomyces cerevisiae Gpa2, J03609; Hydra 
magnipapillata Ga3, AB006541; Ephydatia fluviatilis sponge Ga3, AB006545; 
Drosophila melanogaster Ga49B, NM_165920; Xenopus laevis GnaQ and Gna11, 
L05540 and U10502, respectively; Mus musculus Gna11, BC011169; Homo 
sapiens GnaQ and Gna11, NM_002072 and NM_002067, respectively. GenBank 
Protein: Saccharomyces cerevisiae Gpa1, AAB68432; C. elegans Egl-30, 
AAG32092; Mus musculus GnaQ, P21279. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS 
We thank T. Wilkie for Gnaq and Gna11 knockout mice, I. Jackson and M. Shin 
for Dct-lacZ transgenic mice and C. April for RNA samples. This investigation 
was supported by a grant from the National Institutes of Health. C.V.R was 
supported by a training grant from the National Cancer Institute and by a 
Johnson &amp; Johnson Skin Research Grant. G.S.B. is an Associate Investigator of 
the Howard Hughes Medical Institute. </p>

<p>COMPETING INTERESTS STATEMENT 
The authors declare that they have no competing financial interests. </p>

<p>Received 9 April; accepted 13 July 2004 
Published online at http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics/ </p>



<p>NATURE GENETICS VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 </p>



<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>





<p>VOLUME 36 [ NUMBER 9 [ SEPTEMBER 2004 NATURE GENETICS </p>

<p>A R T I C L E S </p>

<p>© 2004 Nature Publishing Group http://www.nature.com/naturegenetics </p>

</text></tei>