<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="a2010-05-BMC_MOL_BIOL" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Background: Gene expression analysis has many applications in cancer diagnosis, prognosis and therapeutic care. 
Relative quantification is the most widely adopted approach whereby quantification of gene expression is 
normalised relative to an endogenously expressed control (EC) gene. Central to the reliable determination of gene 
expression is the choice of control gene. The purpose of this study was to evaluate a panel of candidate EC genes 
from which to identify the most stably expressed gene(s) to normalise RQ-PCR data derived from primary 
colorectal cancer tissue. 
Results: The expression of thirteen candidate EC genes: B2M, HPRT, GAPDH, ACTB, PPIA, HCRT, SLC25A23, DTX3, 
APOC4, RTDR1, KRTAP12-3, CHRNB4 and MRPL19 were analysed in a cohort of 64 colorectal tumours and tumour 
associated normal specimens. CXCL12, FABP1, MUC2 and PDCD4 genes were chosen as target genes against which 
a comparison of the effect of each EC gene on gene expression could be determined. Data analysis using 
descriptive statistics, geNorm, <rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> and <rs type="software">qBasePlus</rs> indicated significant difference in variances between 
candidate EC genes. We determined that two genes were required for optimal normalisation and identified B2M 
and PPIA as the most stably expressed and reliable EC genes. </p>

<p>Conclusion: This study identified that the combination of two EC genes (B2M and PPIA) more accurately 
normalised RQ-PCR data in colorectal tissue. Although these control genes might not be optimal for use in other 
cancer studies, the approach described herein could serve as a template for the identification of valid ECs in other 
cancer types. </p>

<p>Background </p>

<p>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is one of the most common 
causes of cancer worldwide affecting almost a million 
people annually and resulting in approximately 500,000 
deaths [1]. Approximately 5% of individuals born today 
will be diagnosed with colorectal cancer during their 
lives, representing a lifetime risk of 1 in 19. CRC 
remains a serious threat to life with approximately 20% 
of patients presenting with late stage metastatic disease. 
Although 5 year survival rates are favourable at 80-90% 
for early stage disease, this drops significantly to less 
than 10% with the presence of distal metastasis. 
The majority of colorectal tumours originate from 
adenomatous precursor lesions and develop along a </p>

<p>well-defined adenoma-carcinoma sequence. According 
to this model the culmination of mutational events 
including activation of oncogenes and loss of function 
of tumour suppressor genes results in the emergence of 
carcinomas [2]. Molecular profiling across the spectrum 
of normal-adenoma-tumour tissue types has yielded 
many candidate genes in the search for novel molecular 
diagnostic and prognostic markers and treatment strate-
gies [3-5]. In latter years real-time quantitative (RQ-) 
PCR has become established as the gold standard for 
accurate, sensitive and rapid quantification of gene 
expression [6,7]. In comparison to alternative methods 
such as Northern blotting and Ribonuclease Protection 
Assays (RPA), RQ-PCR has been universally adopted as 
the transcriptomic method of choice due to its superior-
ity with regard to speed, sensitivity, reproducibility and </p>

<p>* Correspondence: nicola.miller@nuigalway.ie </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Surgery, National University of Ireland, Galway, Ireland </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>

<p>© 2010 Kheirelseid et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative 
Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and 
reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>the wide range of instrumentation and reagents com-
mercially available. 
To accurately quantify an mRNA target by RQ-PCR, 
samples are assayed during the exponential phase of the 
PCR reaction during which the amount of target is 
assumed to double with each cycle of PCR without bias 
due to limiting reagents. Analysis of cycle threshold 
(C t ), the cycle number at which signals are detected 
above background, can be used to estimate gene expres-
sion levels by relating C t values either to a standard 
curve (absolute quantification) or to a control gene 
(relative quantification). The latter method requires the 
generation of standard curves of known copy number 
for each target and so is limited due to logistical issues 
associated with the generation of standards in studies of 
multiple gene targets. Relative quantification is the most 
widely adopted approach and as the name suggests, 
quantification of gene expression is based on the analy-
sis of a target gene whose expression is normalised rela-
tive to the expression of a control gene. Central to the 
reliable determination of gene expression is the choice 
of control gene with which to normalise real-time data 
from target genes. Normalisation can be achieved using 
endogenous or exogenous controls; however the use of 
endogenous control (EC) genes is the most widely 
adopted approach as it excludes variation associated 
with differences in amounts of template RNA. Vandes-
tompele et al 2002 described a normalisation method 
whereby geometrical averaging of multiple EC genes 
improved accuracy [8]. This approach has been adopted 
to reliably measure levels of gene expression in many 
studies in different tissue types including breast [9-11], 
lung [12], kidney [13], brain [14] and liver [15]. 
An ideal EC gene (or genes) should be stably 
expressed and unaffected by parameters such as disease 
status and in the case of CRC, should remain unaffected 
by whether a tissue was derived from normal, adenoma 
or carcinoma lesions. Traditionally GAPDH (glyceralde-
hyde phosphate dehydrogenase) has been widely used to 
normalise RQ-PCR data. A common feature of earlier 
studies was that the stability of reference gene expres-
sion between different sample types was assumed with 
little consideration paid to validation of these EC genes 
as suitable normalisers. More recent studies have 
brought into question the stability of commonly used 
EC genes such as GAPDH on the basis that gene expres-
sion levels have been found to vary in response to treat-
ment or as a result of physiological, pathological or 
experimental changes. For example, alteration in oxygen 
tension and hypoxia were found to be associated with 
wide variation in GAPDH, B-ACTIN and CYCLOPHILIN 
expression [16]. In addition, GAPDH expression was 
found to be strongly unregulated in diabetic patients 
and down-regulated in response to the administration of </p>

<p>bisphosphonate compounds in the treatment of meta-
static breast cancer [17]. Other evidence indicates that 
neoplastic growth can affect EC expression levels [18]. 
Goidin et al [19] found differences in the expression of 
GAPDH and B-ACTIN in two sub-populations of mela-
noma cells derived from a tumour in a single patient. 
Treatment agents such as dexamethasone, deprenyl and 
isatin also affect EC gene expression [20,21]. Schmittgen 
et al [22] reported increased expression of GAPDH, 
B2M, 18S rRNA and b-ACTIN in fibroblasts after the 
addition of serum: evidence of the effect of experimental 
conditions on EC expression. These findings were 
further supported by Wu et al [23] in their investigation 
of the effect of different skin irritants on GAPDH and 
PolyA+ RNA expression. GAPDH was found to be 
involved in age-induced apoptosis in mature cerebellar 
cells [24] and also as a tRNA binding protein present in 
the nuclei of HeLa cells [25]. 
As the use of unreliable ECs can result in inaccurate 
results, the identification of the most reliable gene or set 
of genes at the outset of an investigation is critical. 
Thus far, a pervasive stably expressed gene (or genes) 
has yet to be identified across all tissue types [26,27]. 
This would indicate that the identification of robust ECs 
at the outset of transcriptomic analysis would yield 
more reliable and meaningful RQ-PCR data. 
The aim of this study was to evaluate a panel of thir-
teen candidate EC genes from which to identify the 
most stably expressed gene (or genes) to normalise RQ-
PCR data derived from primary colorectal tumour and 
tumour associated normal (TAN) tissue. Six of the can-
didate EC genes were selected from the literature and 
represent the most frequently studied reference genes in 
cancer including, but not limited to, colorectal cancer. 
Each gene was previously reported as being constitu-
tively expressed in various tissues. These EC genes 
included B2M (beta-2-microglogulin) [5], HPRT (hypox-
anthine guanine phosphoribosyl transferase 1) [3,28], 
GAPDH [29], ACTB (beta-actin) [30], PPIA (peptidyl-
prolyl isomerise A) [9] and MRPL19 (mitochondrial ribo-
somal protein L19) [9]. The remaining seven genes 
included HCRT, SLC25A23, DTX3, APOC4, RTDR1, 
KRTAP12-3, and CHRNB4. The latter candidates were 
selected from an unpublished whole genome microarray 
dataset of 20 human tumour specimens and represented 
the most stably expressed probes with a fold-change of 
1.0-1.2, (p &lt; 0.05). Expression of CXCL12 [31], FABP1 
[32], MUC2 [33] and PDCD4 genes were chosen as tar-
gets against which to measure the effects of candidate 
EC expression on the basis of their previously identified 
roles in tumourigenesis. In addition to its tumour sup-
pressor properties, PDCD4 [34] also has diagnostic and 
prognostic utility and represents a promising target for 
anti-cancer therapy. </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>Results </p>

<p>Range of Expression of Candidate EC Genes </p>

<p>A range of C t values was observed across the candidate 
EC genes in tumour and TAN tissue from CRC patients 
as indicated in table 1. Only samples with a standard 
deviation &lt; 0.3 from the mean C t of the triplicates were 
included for further analysis. The expression of RTDR1, 
HCRT, APOC4 and KRTAP12-3 could not be deter-
mined in all 64 tissue samples, resultantly these candi-
dates were excluded from further analysis. 
Mean C t values for the remaining genes ranged from 
19.48 (± 0.14 s.e.m) for B2M to 32.30 (± 0.19 s.e.m) for 
CHRNB4. B2M displayed the narrowest range of C t </p>

<p>values between 17.5 and 21.5 (mean 19.5 ± 0.14 s.e.m, 
range of 4.04) followed by PPIA and MRPL19, while 
ACTB had the widest range of C t values between 33.8 
and 21.1. The genes broadly fell into three categories, 
those least abundant genes with mean C t values of 27-
32 (SLC25A23, MRPL19, DTX3 and CHRNB4), moder-
ately abundant genes with mean C t values of 22-26 
(HPRT and ACTB) and the most abundant highly 
expressed genes with mean C t values of 19-21 (B2M, 
PPIA and GAPDH) Table 2. </p>

<p>Identification of Optimal EC genes </p>

<p>Scaled expression levels across the remaining nine can-
didate ECs analysed (figure 1) indicated within-gene dif-
ferences in expression between tumour and normal 
tissue groups in both SLC25A23 (p = 0.040) and 
CHRNB4 (P = 0.002) but not in the remaining genes (p 
&gt; 0.05), (figure 2A). Therefore, SLC25A23 and CHRNB4 
genes were excluded from further analysis. Significant 
differences in variance of EC expression were identified 
using Levene's test (p &lt; 0.001, figure 2B). These findings 
necessitated further evaluation of each candidate EC 
gene prior to their possible use to accurately quantitate 
gene expression levels of the target genes CXCL12, 
FABP1, MUC2 and PDCD4. 
The stability of candidate EC genes was analysed using 
geNorm [8] and <rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> [35] programmes. Stability 
was further evaluated using <rs id="software-5" type="software">qBasePlus</rs> [<rs corresp="#software-5" type="version">8,36</rs>], a commer-
cially available RQ-PCR data mining package. These 
programmes were used to calculate amplification effi-
ciency-corrected relative quantities from raw fluores-
cence data. The ranking of candidate EC genes as 
determined by each of these programmes is illustrated 
in Table 3. In the case of GeNorm the variable V indi-
cating the pairwise variation (Vn/Vn+1) between two 
sequential normalisation factors (NFn/NFn+1) indicated 
that three EC genes was the optimal number of genes 
for accurate normalisation (figure 2), however, target 
genes expression did not differ significantly if two rather 
than three EC genes were used (figure 3). Use of all 
three programmes confirmed that B2M and PPIA was 
the best combination of genes for normalising RQ-PCR 
data in CRC tissues (table 3). The Equivalence test [37]  was used to examine the expression of candidate ECs. 
All genes were equivalently expressed between the nor-
mal and tumour colorectal tissues using a fold cut-off of 
2 (figure 4). </p>

<p>Association between EC genes and target genes </p>

<p>There was a significant effect of the expression of the 
candidate EC genes on relative expression of CXCL12 (p 
&lt; 0.001), FABP1 (p &lt; 0.001), MUC2 (p &lt; 0.001) and 
PDCD4 (p &lt; 0.001) (figure 5A and 5B). Moreover, a sig-
nificant effect of the choice of EC with regard to the 
estimation of error (figure 5C) was also detected. These 
findings were further confirmed for each EC gene </p>

<p>Table 1 Clinico-pathological patient data for tumour and 
tumour associated normal colorectal tissues </p>

<p>Clinicopathological Variable 
Number of Patients N = 42 </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Males 
29 </p>

<p>Females 
13 </p>

<p>Mean Age (SD) 
66.5 (12.84) </p>

<p>Tumour Location </p>

<p>Colon 
12 </p>

<p>Rectum 
30 </p>

<p>Tumour Diameter (mm) </p>

<p>&lt;10 
11 </p>

<p>10-15 
15 </p>

<p>&gt;15 
17 </p>

<p>Tumour Thickness (mm) </p>

<p>&lt;30 
15 </p>

<p>30-40 
12 </p>

<p>&gt;40 
15 
Distant Metastasis </p>

<p>M0 
36 </p>

<p>M1 
6 </p>

<p>Nodal Status </p>

<p>N0 
22 </p>

<p>N1 
11 </p>

<p>N2 
9 </p>

<p>UICC Stage </p>

<p>Stage 0 
6 </p>

<p>Stage I 
10 </p>

<p>Stage II 
10 </p>

<p>Stage III 
11 
Stage IV 
5 </p>

<p>Tumour Differentiation </p>

<p>Well 
12 </p>

<p>Moderate 
24 </p>

<p>Poor 
6 </p>

<p>Mucin Secretion </p>

<p>Mucinous 
8 </p>

<p>Non-mucinous 
34 </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>compared to each other by ANOVA Tukey post hoc 
tests (Additional files 1). The combined use of B2M and 
PPIA significantly reduced the magnitude of error in 
comparison to the use of either gene individually for 
both CXCL12 and PDCD4 expression. The addition of a 
third EC gene (MRPL19) to the B2M/PPIA combination 
did not result in any further improvement of the estima-
tion of error (figure 3C). </p>

<p>Non-normalised expression levels of target genes </p>

<p>To assess whether normalisation was necessary in a 
large cohort such as this in which the biological effect 
of the target genes is already established, we compared 
the expression of the four target genes in tumour vs. 
normal tissues using non-normalised cycle threshold 
(C t ) values in the entire sample set (n = 64) and in a 
sub-set of randomly selected 10 normal and 10 tumour 
tissues (n = 20). This analysis showed down-regulated 
target gene (CXCL12, FABP1, MUC2 and PDCD4) 
expression in tumour compared to normal tissues (fig-
ure 6), in keeping with their documented tumour sup-
pressor functions, when using the larger set of samples. 
The unchanged target gene expression levels in the 
large cohort could be explained by the fact that in larger 
sample sizes the biological milieu may diminish subtle 
variations in individual samples. In contrast, when the 
smaller sample size was used, no significant differences 
in target gene expression were observed. Furthermore 
the expression levels of PDCD4 appeared slightly higher 
in tumours than in normal tissues. When the same sub-
set of 20 samples were normalised with PPIA/B2M, </p>

<p>significant differences in target gene expression were 
observed. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Since its introduction in 1996 [38] many methods have 
been developed for the analysis real-time quantitative 
PCR data. Relative quantification has come to the fore 
as the method of choice due to its superior flexibility 
and reduction in inherent variation associated with sam-
ple preparation. Prior to the availability of high-through-
put realtime PCR instrumentation, a handful of genes 
were commonly used to normalise real-time data. Major 
technological advances enabling high throughput analy-
sis of both samples and target genes have enabled inves-
tigation and validation of putative EC genes prior to 
their use to normalise target gene expression. It is now 
accepted that the use of more than one gene to normal-
ise RQ data improves experimental accuracy compared 
to the use of a single EC gene [8,35,38]  In their study of EC gene expression in breast and 
colon cancer tissues Tricarico et al [39] illustrated sig-
nificant variation in the expression levels of 10 com-
monly used housekeeping genes including 18S rRNA, 
both between individuals and between biopsies taken 
from the same patient. They concluded that normalisa-
tion to a single EC gene was inappropriate for human 
tissue samples. Moreover, Vandesompele et al identified 
errors of up to 6.5 fold when a single EC gene was used 
in comparison to the use of multiple genes for data nor-
malisation [8] thereby clearly indicating the potential for </p>

<p>Table 2 Cycle threshold (Ct) values of candidate EC genes and PCDC4 in colorectal tissues </p>

<p>EC Gene 
C t Range 
C t Min 
C t Max 
Mean C t ± s.e.m 
Standard deviation (SD) </p>

<p>B2M 
4.03 
17.47 
21.51 
19.48 ± 0.14 
1.04 </p>

<p>PPIA 
4.13 
17.78 
21.91 
19.90 ± 0.14 
1.06 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
5.80 
18.51 
24.32 
21.00 ± 0.17 
1.29 </p>

<p>ACTB 
12.74 
21.08 
33.32 
25.14 ± 0.34 
2.61 </p>

<p>HPRT 
8.54 
22.74 
31.28 
26.68 ± 0.25 
1.89 </p>

<p>DTX3 
6.6 
24.95 
31.56 
28.62 ±0.17 
1.37 </p>

<p>SLC25A23 
7.26 
24.48 
31.74 
27.36 ±0.19 
1.54 </p>

<p>CHRNB4 
9.40 
27.99 
37.38 
32.30 ±0.19 
2.15 </p>

<p>RTDR1 
-
30.59 
UD 
35.82 ±0.36 
2.15 </p>

<p>HCRT 
-
33.96 
UD 
38.46 ±0.29 
1.67 </p>

<p>APOC4 
-
UD 
UD 
-
-</p>

<p>KRTAP12-3 
-
33.16 
UD 
36.95 ±0.19 
1.46 </p>

<p>MRPL19 
4.10 
26.70 
30.80 
28.62 ± 0.13 
0.98 </p>

<p>CXCL12 
13.54 
21.85 
35.39 
25.77 ± 0.32 
2.61 </p>

<p>FABP1 
15.57 
16.61 
32.19 
20.83 ± 0.40 
3.24 </p>

<p>MUC2 
17.71 
17.62 
35.33 
22.43 ± 0.53 
4.16 </p>

<p>PDCD4 
11.92 
21.35 
33.27 
24.56 ± 0.32 
2.59 </p>

<p>B2M and PPIA were the most abundantly expressed genes, having the lowest mean Ct values while MRPL19 was the least abundantly expressed gene with 
average Ct values &gt; 26. Both B2M and PPIA had the lowest range in their Ct values. </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>superior accuracy when due consideration is paid to the 
choice of EC genes. 
Many analytical programmes for relative quantification 
have been developed, certain of which enable the identi-
fication of EC genes from a study population [37,40,41]. 
In the present study the stability of expression of candi-
date EC genes was determined using a pair-wise com-
parison model: geNorm [8] and an <rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">MS</rs> <rs id="software-6" type="software">Excel</rs> ANOVA 
based model, <rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> [35]. No effect of disease sta-
tus EC gene expression was identified in colorectal tis-
sue. Since both geNorm and <rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> are based on 
the assumption that candidate genes are not differen-
tially expressed between samples, this was an important 
first step prior to their continued use [9,10]. 
In this study GeNorm was used to identify the most 
stably expressed EC genes from our panel of candidates </p>

<p>and also provided a measure of the optimal number of 
EC genes. B2M and PPIA were identified as the most 
stable pairing. In order to achieve a pair-wise variation 
value (V) below the cut-off of 0.15 additional genes 
should theoretically be used; however this cut-off point 
is not absolute [14] and may not always be achievable 
[42]. No significant difference in target gene expression 
was observed when the top three most stable EC genes 
identified by geNorm were used confirming that using 
of a pair of genes may be more practicable given cost, 
work load and sample availability considerations. 
<rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> was designed to identify EC genes with 
the lowest stability values; these values are calculated 
based on intra-and inter-group variation. In this study 
<rs type="software">NormFinder</rs> was used to define the best combination of 
genes using tumour and normal as group identifiers in </p>

<p>Figure 1 Scaled expression levels and variation of each candidate EC gene. (A) Log 10 of cycle threshold of candidate EC genes ACTB, 
B2M, GAPDH, HPRT, MRPL19, SLC25A23, DTX3, CHRNB4 and PPIA in tumour and normal colorectal tissues. Boxplot shows interquartile range box, 
median, range whiskers and outliers (*). Within gene, differences were found in expression between tissue groups in both SLC25A23 (p = 0.040) 
and CHRNB4 (p = 0.002) but not the other genes (p &gt; 0.05) (ANOVA). (B) Variation associated with EC gene expression. There was a significant 
difference in variation associated with gene expression (p &lt; 0.001) with ACTB, GAPDH and HPRT showing greater variation than B2M, MRPL19 or 
PPIA. DTX3, CHRNB4 and SLC25A23 showed the least variations (Levene's test). </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>the calculations. MRPL19 was selected as the most 
stable gene using these criteria; however B2M and PPIA 
were highlighted as the best combination of genes with 
even lower stability value compared to MRPL19 alone. 
<rs type="software">QBasePlus</rs> real-time PCR data manager programme was 
developed based on geNorm and qBase [36] algorithms. 
<rs type="software">QBasePlus</rs> was used to confirm our selection of the 
B2M and PPIA pairing as the best combination of ECs 
in colorectal tissue. </p>

<p>Equivalence testing was developed in biostatistics to 
address the situation where the aim is not to show the 
difference between groups, but rather to establish that 
two methods are equal to one another. In equivalence 
testing, the null hypothesis is that the two groups are 
not equivalent to one another, and hence rejection of 
the null indicates that the two groups are equivalent. 
Therefore, as stated by Haller et al, there is a risk of 
accepting non-differentially expressed genes as suitable </p>

<p>Figure 2 Analysis of candidate EC genes using geNorm. (A): Average expression stability values of eligible EC genes. Expression stability 
of the control genes as calculated by geNorm. Stability value M is based on the average pair-wise variation between all genes. The least stable 
gene with highest M value was excluded and M value recalculated till end up with the most stable pair. (B): Determination of optimal 
number of control genes for normalisation. The GeNorm programme calculates a normalisation factor (NF) which is used to determine the 
optimal number of EC genes required for accurate normalisation. This factor is calculated using the variable V as the pairwise variation (Vn/Vn + 
1) between two sequential NFs (NFn and NFn + 1). To meet the recommended cut off V-value which is the point at which it is unnecessary to 
include additional genes in a normalisation strategy. The recommended limit for V value is 0.15 but it is not always achievable. In this instance, 
the GeNorm output file indicated that the optimal number of genes required for normalisation was three. </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>Figure 3 Relative quantity of CXCL12, FABP1, MUC2 and PDCD4 in colorectal tissue. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. No 
significant differences in the relative quantities of target genes were found using a combination of PPIA and B2M (PB) genes in comparison to 
the use of combination of PPIA, B2M and MRPL19 (PBM) EC genes (ANOVA). </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>controls although they are not equivalently expressed 
[43]. Equivalence of expression between tumour and 
normal colorectal tissue was confirmed for all candidate 
EC genes using the equivalence test and a fold cut-off of 
2. DTX3, B2M, MRPL19 and PPIA showed the mini-
mum of variability in the confidence interval hence can 
be used for normalisation. 
In their study to identify EC genes to monitor entero-
cyte differentiation and to compare normal and adeno-
carcinoma of the colon from microarray data, 
Dydensborg et al [5] recommended RPLP0 for </p>

<p>normalising gene quantification in human intestinal 
epithelial cells and B2M for studying gene expression in 
human colon cancer. In addition, Blanquicett et al [44]  analysed the extent of variability in gene expression 
between tumour and normal colorectal and liver tissues 
using two-tailed T tests. They showed that 18S, S9 and 
GUS were the least variable genes in normal and meta-
static liver specimens and were also appropriate for nor-
mal and tumour colorectal tissues. In the present study, 
we confirmed that more than one EC gene is required 
for optimal normalisation in colorectal tissue. We used </p>

<p>Figure 4 Equivalence test for candidate control genes in colorectal tissue. Differences in logarithmic expression levels between tumour and 
normal tissues (•) are indicated. The upper and lower bars of each line indicate the upper and lower limits of the symmetrical confidence 
intervals, respectively. The deviation area (-1, 1) for a fold change of 2 or less is plotted as a continuous line while the deviation area of (-1.58, 
1.58) for a fold change of 3 is plotted as a dotted line. </p>

<p>Table 3 Ranking and best combination of EC genes as determined by geNorm, NormFinder and qBasePlus. </p>

<p>Rank 
GeNorm 
NormFinder 
qBaseplus </p>

<p>Gene 
Stability (M) 
Gene 
Stability (M) 
Gene 
CV value </p>

<p>1 
GAPDH 
1.477 
MRPL19 
0.008 
GAPDH 
0.555 </p>

<p>2 
MRPL19 
1.467 
B2M 
0.015 
PPIA 
0.659 </p>

<p>3 
PPIA 
1.535 
HPRT 
0.016 
HPRT 
0.775 </p>

<p>4 
B2M 
1.636 
PPIA 
0.017 
MRPL19 
0.914 </p>

<p>5 
HPRT 
1.813 
GAPDH 
0.018 
B2M 
0.923 </p>

<p>6 
DTX3 
2.251 
DTX3 
0.020 
ACTB 
0.957 </p>

<p>7 
ACTB 
2.454 
ACTB 
0.026 
DTX3 
5.829 </p>

<p>Best Combination 
B2M/PPIA 
1.005 
B2M/PPIA 
0.007 
B2M/PPIA 
0.460 </p>

<p>For GeNorm, lower stability values (M) indicate greater stability. In the case of <rs type="software">NormFinder</rs>, stability is calculated from inter-and intra-group variation. By 
grouping the tissues into tumour and normal the best combination of genes was identified. For geNorm stability was based on the estimation of pair-wise 
variation. <rs type="software">QBasePlus</rs> through its components, geNorm and qBase, identified coefficient of variation (CV) and stability (M) values and thereby the best 
combination of genes for normalisation only when more than one gene is used. </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>Figure 5 Relative quantity of target gene expression in colorectal tissues relative to each EC gene and to the geometric mean of the 
combined use of PPIA and B2M (PB). (A) Target gene expression in tumour versus normal using either individual candidate EC genes or the 
PB combination. (B) Significant differences in relative gene expression values as determined using ANOVA to compare mean expression levels 
across all tissues using either individual EC genes or PB in combination. (C) One way ANOVA indicating a reduction in the magnitude of error 
when the PB combination was used to normalise expression of CXCL12 (p &lt; 0.001) and PDCD4 (p &lt; 0.001) in comparison to the use of 
individual EC genes. See Table 1 Additional files for Post Hoc tests. Error bars indicate 95% confidence intervals. </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>clinico-pathologically diverse tissues to systematically 
evaluate normalisation of gene expression data in color-
ectal tissues. We also conducted equivalence testing to 
confirm the equality of expression of each EC gene. 
Thereby, the risks of incorrect rejection (type 1 error) 
and of false negativity (type 2 error) were minimised. 
As stated above significant differences in target gene 
expression were noticed when using each of the EC 
genes and the combination of PPIA and B2M. More-
over, significant effect of EC on the magnitude of error 
associated with estimation of target gene expression was 
also determined in this study (figure 6). Our results 
were further confirmed by post hoc testing of individual 
levels of EC gene expression (Additional files 1). Reduc-
tion in the magnitude of error achieved using the com-
bination of PPIA and B2M in comparison to using 
individual EC genes alone, further indicates that using 
two EC genes to normalise real-time data achieves 
greater accuracy in the determination of gene expression 
levels. </p>

<p>Conclusions </p>

<p>The findings reported in this study confirm that use of 
two EC genes to normalise RQ-PCR data resulted in 
superior accuracy in the quantification of gene expres-
sion in colorectal tissue. The combined use of B2M and 
PPIA was validated as the optimal pair of EC genes with 
which to estimate the expression of all four target genes 
in colorectal cancer tissue. Although these ECs may not 
be ideal in other tissue types, the approach described </p>

<p>herein could serve as a template to identify valid ECs in 
other tissue types. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Tissue Samples </p>

<p>A study group of 64 biopsies of human colon tissue 
samples was gathered from consenting patients at the 
time of primary curative surgical resection at Galway 
University Hospital, Ireland. The cohort comprised of 
30 colorectal tumour specimens and 34 and tumour-
associated normal (TAN) tissues. Following excision, all 
samples were subject to histopathological review prior 
immediate snap-freezing in liquid nitrogen and archival 
at -80°C until further use. Concomitant clinicopathologi-
cal data on patients and specimens was obtained from 
the Department of Surgery Biobank, NUI Galway as 
detailed in Table 4. Ethical approval for this study was 
granted by the Clinical Research Ethics Committee, Gal-
way University Hospitals. </p>

<p>RNA Extraction and Analysis </p>

<p>Tissue samples (50-100 mg) were homogenised using a 
hand-held homogenizer (Polytron® PT1600E, Kinematica 
AG, Littau-Luzem, Switzerland) in 1-2 ml of QIAzol 
reagent (Qiagen, Crawley, UK). To minimise variation in 
sample processing, tumour and TAN samples were 
homogenised separately, but on the same day. RNA was 
extracted as previously described (Davoren et al) using 
the RNeasy® Plus Mini Kit and RNeasy MinElute® 
cleanup kit (Qiagen, Crawley, UK) according to the 
manufacturer's instructions. Briefly, large (&gt; 200 nt) and </p>

<p>Figure 6 Non-normalised cycle threshold (C t ) of CXCL12, FABP1, MUC2 and PDCD4 in colorectal tissue. Using this approach, the 
expression of each gene appears to be down-regulated in tumours compared to normal tissues in the large cohort of patients (30 tumour and 
34 normal tissue specimens), similar to previous published reports of reduced expression in colorectal tumours. No significant differences were 
noted in expression levels of target genes when using the small cohort of patients (10 tumour and 10 normal tissue specimens) (2-sample t-
test). This confirms the effect of sample size on findings when using non-normalised C t values and therefore the importance of normalisation 
especially in such type of studies </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



<p>small RNA (&lt; 200 nt) fractions were isolated separately. 
For this study, only large RNA was utilised for further 
analysis. RNA was eluted in 60 μl volumes and stored at 
-80°C. 
RNA concentration and purity was assessed in dupli-
cate samples using a using a NanoDrop™ ND-1000 Spec-
trophotometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA). RNA 
integrity was evaluated using the RNA 6000 Nano Chip 
Kit (Series II) and the Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer System 
(Agilent technologies, Palo Alto, CA, USA). An RNA 
integrity number (RIN) was generated for each sample 
using the <rs id="software-7" type="software">Agilent 2100 Expert Software</rs> (Version 
<rs corresp="#software-7" type="version">B.02.03</rs>) based on the ratio of ribosomal bands and also 
the presence or absence of degradation products on the 
electrophoretic and gel-like images. A threshold value of 
RIN ≥ 7 was applied and RNA purity was verified by an 
average A260/A280 ratio of 1.98 (range 1.97-2.01) and 
A260/A230 ration of 1.7 (range 1.5-1.83). </p>

<p>Candidate Endogenous Control Genes </p>

<p>Based on literature search six commonly used candidate 
endogenous control genes were selected for analysis: 
ACTB, GAPDH, HPRT, B2M, PPIA and MRPL19. An 
additional panel of seven genes: HCRT, SLC25A23, 
DTX3, APOC4, RTDR1, KRTAP12-3 and CHRNB4, was 
also selected for analysis (Table 2). To our knowledge 
all genes have independent cellular functions and were 
assumed not to be co-regulated. </p>

<p>cDNA Synthesis and RQ-PCR </p>

<p>First strand cDNA was synthesised using Superscript™ 
III reverse transcriptase (Invitrogen Life technologies, 
Paisley, UK) and random primers (N9; 1 μg, MWG Bio-
tech, AG, Ebersberg, Germany). Negative control sam-
ples were included in each set of reactions. Reactions 
were incubated at 25°C for 5 minutes followed by 50°C 
for 1 hour and final denaturation at 72°C for 15 </p>

<p>minutes. Samples were subsequently diluted to 50 μL in 
nuclease-free water and stored at -20°C. The expression 
of each EC gene was analysed by RQ-PCR using Taq-
Man® gene expression assays using a 7900HT instru-
ment (Applied Biosystems, Foster city, USA). All 
reactions were performed in 20 μL reactions, in tripli-
cate within the same PCR run. Negative controls were 
included for each gene target under assay. On each 
plate, an interassay control was included to account for 
any variations between runs. For each well 2 μl of 
cDNA from each sample was added to 18 μl of PCR 
reaction mix which consisted of 10× TaqMan® universal 
master mix, No AmpErase UNG, 7× nuclease free water 
and 1× gene expression assay primer-probe mix 
(Applied Biosystems, Foster city, USA). The PCR reac-
tions were initiated with a 10 minute incubation at 95°C 
followed by 40 cycles of 95°C for 15 seconds and 60°C 
for 60 seconds, in accordance with the manufacturer's 
recommendations. </p>

<p>PCR Amplification Efficiency </p>

<p>Amplification efficiencies for each EC gene assay were 
calculated applying the formula E = (10-1/slope -1) × 
100, using the slope of the plot of Ct versus log input of 
cDNA (10-fold dilution series). A threshold of 10% 
above and below 100% efficiency was applied. PCR 
amplification efficiency for each candidate EC gene is 
shown in table 2. </p>

<p>Data Analysis </p>

<p>Cycle threshold (C t ) is defined as the PCR cycle number 
at which the fluorescence generated from amplification 
of the target gene within a sample increases to a thresh-
old value of 10 times the standard deviation of the base 
line emission and is inversely proportionate to the start-
ing amount of the target cDNA. <rs type="software">QBasePlus</rs> was used for 
calculation of PDCD4 expression relative to each of the </p>

<p>Table 4 Candidate endogenous control (EC) genes and their PCR amplification efficiencies (E) </p>

<p>EC 
Function 
Chromosomal Location 
Amplicon Size (bp) 
Assay Identifier* 
E (%) </p>

<p>B2M 
Defence/immunity 
15q21-22.2 
64 
Hs00187842_m1 
101.8 </p>

<p>GAPDH 
Oxidoreductase, dehydrogenase 
12p13 
122 
Hs99999905_m1 
99.8 </p>

<p>PPIA 
Isomerase 
7p13 
98 
Hs99999904_m1 
96.6 </p>

<p>HPRT 
Glycosyl transferase 
Xq26.1 
100 
Hs99999909_m1 
97.9 </p>

<p>MRPL19 
Protein biosynthesis 
2q11.1-11.2 
72 
Hs00608519_m1 
102.2 </p>

<p>ACTB 
Cytoskeletal structure 
7p15-12 
171 
Hs99999903_m1 
95.2 </p>

<p>DTX3 
Signals transduction 
12q13.3 
64 
Hs00400987_m1 
99.1 </p>

<p>SLC25A23 
Mitochondrial carrier 
19p13.3 
86 
Hs00225469_m1 
97.8 </p>

<p>CHRNB4 
Nicotinic receptor 
15q24 
75 
Hs00609523_m1 
103.6 </p>

<p>RTDR1 
Aminopeptidase transport 
22q11.2 
112 
Hs00205353_m1 
UD </p>

<p>HCRT 
Homeostatic regulator 
12q21 
101 
Hs00533664_m1 
UD </p>

<p>APOC4 
Apo-lipoprotein 
19q.2 
144 
Hs00155791_m1 
UD </p>

<p>KRTAP12-3 
Acetylgalactoa-minyltransferase 
3q25 
83 
Hs01651247_s1 
UD </p>

<p>* Applied Biosystems TaqMan® gene expression assay ID 
UD: undetermined </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>

<p>Page 11 of 13 </p>

<p>EC genes. It applies ΔΔC t method was used where ΔΔCt 
= (C t target gene, test sample -C t endogenous control, 
test sample) -(C t target gene, calibrator sample -C t 
endogenous control, calibrator sample). Relative quanti-
ties were corrected for efficiency of amplification and 
fold change in gene expression between groups was cal-
culated as E-ΔΔCt ± s.e.m. Where more than one endo-
genous control are used, fold change estimates were 
calculated using the geometric mean of EC quantities 
relative to the calibrator sample which could be the 
minimum, maximum or a named sample or an average. 
Stability of the EC genes expression was evaluated 
with two freely available statistical models, geNorm and 
<rs type="software">NormFinder</rs>. It is further validated with <rs type="software">qBasePlus</rs>. Sta-
tistical analysis was carried out with <rs id="software-10" type="software">Minitab</rs>® <rs corresp="#software-10" type="version">15</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="creator">Mini- tab Ltd</rs>, Coventry, UK). Anderson-Darling normality test 
was applied and parametric tests were used where 
appropriate. The equivalence test was used to assess the 
equivalently of expression of the candidate genes 
between tumour and normal tissues. One-way ANOVA, 
two-sample t-test, Levene's test and Spearman and Pear-
son correlations were used to determine association and 
comparisons between groups. P values &lt; 0.05 were con-
sidered statistically significant. </p>

<p>Additional file 1: Table 1 Supplementary data. Post hoc testing of 
individual levels of EC gene expression. 
Click here for file 
[ http://www.biomedcentral.com/content/supplementary/1471-2199-11-
12-S1.PPT ] </p>

<p>Acknowledgements 
The authors would like to acknowledge the National Breast Cancer Research 
Institute (NBCRI) for their continued financial support. We gratefully 
acknowledge Ms. Emer Hennessy and Ms. Catherine Curran for continued 
technical assistance. </p>

<p>Author details </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Department of Surgery, National University of Ireland, Galway, Ireland. </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Biostatistics Unit, Clinical Research Facility, National University of Ireland, 
Galway, Ireland. </p>

<p>Authors' contributions 
EAHK performed the experiments, was responsible for data analyses and 
drafted the manuscript. KHC contributed to sample preparation from clinical 
samples and collation of clinicopathological data. NM conceived, designed 
and supervised experimental work and manuscript editing. JN contributed 
to statistical analysis of clinical data and drafting of the manuscript. MJK 
contributed throughout the experiment, critically reviewed the manuscript 
and participated clinically. All authors read and approved the final 
manuscript. </p>

<p>Received: 6 April 2009 
Accepted: 1 February 2010 Published: 1 February 2010 </p>







<p>Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central 
and take full advantage of: </p>

<p>• Convenient online submission </p>

<p>• Thorough peer review </p>

<p>• No space constraints or color figure charges </p>

<p>• Immediate publication on acceptance </p>

<p>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar </p>

<p>• Research which is freely available for redistribution </p>

<p>Submit your manuscript at 
www.biomedcentral.com/submit </p>

<p>Kheirelseid et al. BMC Molecular Biology 2010, 11:12 
http://www.biomedcentral.com/1471-2199/11/12 </p>



</text></tei>