<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1636350" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:45+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We have developed <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, a program to con-
struct multiple protein sequence alignment using 
probabilistic consistency. <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> improves 
alignment quality by using pairwise alignment 
hidden Markov models (HMMs) with multiple match 
states that describe local structural information 
without exploiting explicit structure predictions. 
Parameters for such models have been estimated 
from a large library of structure-based alignments. 
We show that (i) on remote homologs, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> 
achieves statistically best accuracy among several 
leading aligners, such as <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> and 
<rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs>, albeit the average improvement is small, 
in the order of several percent; (ii) a large collection 
(.10 000) of automatically computed pairwise struc-
ture alignments of divergent protein domains is 
superior to smaller but carefully curated datasets 
for estimation of alignment parameters and perfor-
mance tests; (iii) reference-independent evaluation 
of alignment quality using sequence alignment-
dependent structure superpositions correlates well 
with reference-dependent evaluation that compares 
sequence-based alignments to structure-based 
reference alignments. </p>

<p>Genome sequencing events have resulted in a rapid 
accumulation of protein sequences in public databases. 
As an essential tool in computational sequence analysis, 
sequence alignment is widely used in similarity searches, 
structure modeling, functional prediction and phylogenetic 
analysis (1-5). Construction of a multiple sequence alignment 
aims at arranging residues with inferred common evolution-
ary origin in the same position for a set of sequences (6). </p>

<p>Valuable information regarding position-specific residue 
usage and conservation can be extracted numerically from a 
multiple sequence alignment for various applications. 
A classical method for constructing a multiple alignment 
aligns sequences progressively, as exemplified by the program 
<rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> (7). Guided by a tree or a dendrogram that reflects 
the similarities among sequences, a progressive method 
makes a series of pairwise alignments for neighboring seq-
uences or pre-aligned sequence groups. In this way, similar 
sequences are aligned prior to divergent sequences. However, 
progressive methods do not correct errors made in each pair-
wise alignment step. While similar sequences can be aligned 
with acceptable quality, progressive methods using general 
amino acid substitution matrices have limited success in obtain-
ing high-quality alignments for divergent sequences (8). 
Two main techniques are utilized to correct or minimize 
mistakes made in the progressive alignment process. One is 
iterative refinement of the alignment after the progressive 
steps (9-11), e.g. by repeatedly dividing the aligned sequences 
into two groups and realigning the groups. The other tech-
nique, pioneered by the program <rs type="software">T-COFFEE</rs> (12), makes 
a consistency measure among a set of pairwise sequence 
alignments before the progressive alignment steps. Such 
consistency-based scoring functions are superior to scoring 
functions based on general amino acid substitution 
matrices (12). 
Improving pairwise sequence alignments is a key to 
provide high-quality starting materials for a consistency 
measure. The most common technique of constructing a 
protein pairwise alignment utilizes a substitution matrix of 
amino acids and a dynamic programming algorithm with 
gap penalties (13,14). Commonly used substitution matrices, 
such as the BLOSUM or PAM series matrices (15,16)  are derived from large-scale analysis of relatively similar 
sequences. Other matrices have been derived from distant 
homologs based on structural alignments (17,18), and they 
are more suitable for aligning divergent sequences. Several 
studies have also shown that real or predicted local structural 
information can be used to improve pairwise alignment 
quality (19,20). </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 214 645 5951; Fax: +1 214 645 5948; Email: jpei@chop.swmed.edu </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>4364-4374 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 
Published online 26 August 2006 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl514 </p>

<p>Another approach to constructing a pairwise alignment 
relies on a hidden Markov model (HMM) (21,22). In a simple 
HMM for global pairwise alignment, aligned residue pairs 
are modeled by a hidden match state, while insertions and 
deletions are modeled by two hidden states that generate 
unmatched residues in either of the two sequences (22). In 
addition to being able to find an optimal alignment, a pairwise 
alignment HMM can be used to estimate the posterior pro-
bability of any residue in the first sequence being aligned 
to any residue in the second sequence (22). These residue 
match probabilities have been used in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> (23), a 
multiple sequence alignment program based on probabilistic 
consistency. 
In this study, we aim to improve alignment quality 
by using: (i) more complex pairwise alignment HMMs that 
incorporate local structural information and (ii) better 
estimation of HMM parameters from a large set of structural 
alignments of divergent domain pairs from SCOP database 
(24). We show that these two techniques improve both 
pairwise alignments and probabilistic consistency-based 
multiple sequence alignments in reference-dependent and 
reference-independent tests. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Training and testing datasets of SCOP domain pairs </p>

<p>Protein domain sequences and structures were obtained from 
the ASTRAL database (25) based on SCOP (24) version 1.69. 
We used the dataset consisting of representatives at the 40% 
sequence identity threshold (SCOP40). Domains from SCOP 
classes 1 to 4 [all alpha, all beta, alpha and beta (a/b), alpha 
and beta (a + b)] were selected. For each domain pair from 
the same superfamily of SCOP40, we computed a structural </p>

<p>alignment using the program <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> (26). Alignments with 
coverage (fraction of aligned region to the length of the 
shorter sequence) less than 0.6 were removed. The remaining 
alignments were divided into four datasets corresponding 
to four sequence identity bins: &lt;10, 10-15, 15-20 and 
20-40%. The method for calculating sequence identity that 
takes into account unaligned regions is described in 
Supplementary Data. To apply cross validation training and 
testing, we divided the domain pairs in each identity bin 
into four subsets at the SCOP fold level, so that no domains 
belonging to the same SCOP fold were shared by any two 
subsets. We estimated HMM parameters using alignments 
in three subsets and tested the programs on representative 
domain pairs of the remaining fourth subset. This procedure 
was performed four times corresponding to four ways of 
partitioning into training and testing datasets. To obtain 
representative alignments from a subset for testing, we 
randomly selected one domain pair from each SCOP fold 
in that subset. The number of domain pairs in each training 
dataset is larger than 10 000 (Supplementary Table S1). </p>

<p>HMMs of pairwise sequence alignment </p>

<p>Description of HMM structures. The standard pairwise 
alignment HMM has three hidden states emitting residues: 
a single match state 'M' emitting residue pairs, an 'X' state 
emitting residues in the first sequence and a 'Y' state emitting 
residues in the second sequence (Figure 1b) (22). This model 
structure is named HMM_1_1_0 (the format of HMM names 
is described below and in Table 1 and Supplementary Table S2). 
The novelty of our complex HMMs is the introduction of 
more match states based on <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> structural alignments, 
which have aligned core blocks (structurally superimposable, 
shown in uppercase letters) and unaligned regions (struc-
turally not superimposable, shown in lowercase letters) </p>

<p>(a) Structure-based alignment and hidden state paths </p>

<p>(b) HMM_1_1_0 
(d) HMM_1_3_1 
(c) HMM_1_1_1 </p>

<p>Figure 1. (a) An illustration of structure-based sequence alignment and hidden state paths. In Sequences 1 and 2, uppercase letters and lowercase letters represent 
aligned core blocks and unaligned regions, respectively. If two corresponding unaligned regions bounded by the same two core blocks are of different length, we 
split the shorter one into two pieces and introduce contiguous gaps in the middle. For both N-and C-terminal ends, the shorter unaligned region is pushed toward 
the core blocks. Secondary structure (ss) types (helix, 'h'; strand, 'e'; coil, 'c') are shown for Sequence 1. The hidden state paths for three models are shown 
below the amino acid sequences. (b) Model structure of HMM_1_1_0. Residue pairs in unaligned regions are modeled using the same match state ('M') as those 
in the aligned blocks. Insertions in the first sequence and second sequence are modeled using states 'X' and 'Y', respectively. (c) Model structure of 
HMM_1_1_1. Residue pairs in the unaligned regions are modeled using a different match state ('U') than the match state in the core blocks ('M'). (d) Model 
structure of HMM_1_3_1. Residue pairs in aligned core blocks are modeled using three match states ('H', 'S', 'C') according to three secondary structure types 
of the first sequence. In (b), (c) and (d), match states are shown as squares and insertion states are shown as diamonds. Begin state, end state, and transitions from 
or to them are present in these models, but are not shown. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 4365 </p>

<p>(Figure 1a). Residue pairs in aligned core blocks can be 
modeled by a match state ('M'). If the two unaligned regions 
in between two core blocks have different and non-zero 
lengths, they can be modeled using a different 'match' state 
('U', for unaligned) (Figure 1c) and 'X' or 'Y' state. This 
is done by evenly splitting the unaligned residues in the 
sequence with the shorter unaligned region into two 
segments, placing them beside the two adjacent core blocks 
and separating them by a single stretch of gap symbols. In 
this way, transitions between 'X' and 'Y' do not occur. 
The residue pair emission probabilities of these artificially 
forced matches in unaligned regions ('U') are expected 
to be different from those in the core blocks ('M'). This 
model (HMM_1_1_1) has two distinct match states: 'M' 
and 'U' (Figure 1a and c). 
Furthermore, the residue matches in aligned core blocks 
can be modeled by several distinct match states based on 
the local structure information of the first sequence, for 
instance, secondary structure types (Figure 1d). Since residue 
usage and substitution patterns can vary for different local 
structural environments, the three match states according to 
secondary structure types have different sets of emission 
probabilities of 400 residue pairs. Secondary structure types 
were assigned using program <rs type="software">DSSP</rs> (27) for SCOP domains. 
The model that incorporates three secondary structure types 
('H': helix, 'S': strand and 'C': coil) of the first sequence 
and unaligned match state ('U') is named HMM_1_3_1 
(Figure 1d). Similarly, multiple match states can be intro-
duced based on several solvent accessibility categories, or a 
combination of solvent accessibility categories and secondary 
structure types. Solvent accessibilities of residue sidechains 
were calculated by program <rs type="software">NACCESS</rs> (28). Three solvent 
accessibility categories were used based on our previous 
studies (29). The model that incorporates three solvent 
accessibility categories and unaligned match state is named 
HMM_3_1_1. Combination of three solvent accessibility 
categories and three secondary structure types results in 
nine classes of match states for the core blocks (model 
HMM_3_3_1). 
Each HMM model is named in the format 
'HMM_solv_ss_u', where 'solv' is the number of solvent 
accessibility categories, 'ss' is the number of secondary 
structure types, and 'u' is 1 if unaligned regions are modeled 
with an additional match state. Some statistics about the five 
HMMs, such as the number of hidden states, the number of 
parameters and time complexity, are listed in Supplementary 
Table S2. </p>

<p>Estimation of HMM parameters. We used a supervised 
learning method to estimate HMM parameters from DaliLite 
structural alignments, since hidden state paths are known for 
them (Figure 1a) (22). These parameters are: transition pro-
babilities among hidden states [match state(s), 'X' state, 
'Y' state, begin state and end state], emission probabilities 
of residue pairs for each match state, and residue emission 
probabilities for 'X' state and 'Y' state (22). Given a training 
dataset, we assign a weight to each sequence. If a sequence 
occurs N times in the dataset, its weight is 1/N 
1/2 . For large 
SCOP superfamilies, one sequence is involved in a large 
number of pairwise alignments. Sequence weighting aims 
to reduce the bias introduced by large superfamilies and </p>

<p>folds. The parameters were estimated from weighted 
counts of observed transitions and emissions in <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> 
alignments (22). 
The supervised learning method was also used to estimate 
model parameters from pairwise alignments in BAliBASE2.0 
(30), from which <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> derived its HMM parameters 
with a different approach (23). These alignments also have 
core blocks assigned (uppercase letters). However, local 
structural information is not available for every sequence. 
Therefore, from BAliBASE2.0 pairwise alignments, we 
derived parameters only for models HMM_1_1_0 and 
HMM_1_1_1 that do not have local structure-dependent 
match states. </p>

<p>Pairwise alignment with optimal match probabilities. 
We apply standard forward and backward algorithms (22)  to align two sequences x ¼ (x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x m ) and y ¼ 
(y 1 , y 2 , . . . , y n ) (m and n are the lengths of x and y). Given 
a pairwise HMM, the forward algorithm applies a dynamic 
programming technique to calculate the probability of 
observing two subsequences (x 1 , . . . , x i ) and (y 1 , . . . , y j ) gen-
erated by an HMM, with the last position of the two sub-
sequences being in a certain hidden state. The formula of 
forward probability is: </p>

<p>F K ði‚jÞ ¼ P½x 1 ‚. . .‚ x i ‚y 1 ‚ . . .‚ y j ‚pði‚jÞ ¼ K 
1 </p>

<p>Here, p(i, j) is the hidden state of the last position. K is one 
of the hidden states. For example, for model HMM_1_3_1, 
K is from the set {'H', 'S', 'C', 'U', 'X', 'Y'} (Figure 1d). 
The backward algorithm calculates the probability of 
generating two subsequences (x i+1 , . . . , x m ) and (y j+1 , . . . , y n ), 
given the condition that the previous position of the two 
subsequences is of a certain type of hidden state. The formula 
of the backward probability is: </p>

<p>B K ði‚jÞ ¼ P½x iþ1 ‚. . .‚ x m ‚y jþ1 ‚. . .‚ y n j pði‚ jÞ ¼ K 
2 </p>

<p>The following formula can be derived (22): </p>

<p>P½pði‚jÞ ¼ K j x‚y ¼ F K ði‚ jÞ * B K ði‚ jÞ/Pðx‚ yÞ‚ 
3 </p>

<p>where P[p(i, j) ¼ K j x, y] is the probability of aligned residue 
pair (x i , y j ) being generated by a certain hidden match state K 
given the two full-length sequences x and y, and P(x, y) is the 
full probability of observing sequences x and y given the 
model. P(x, y) can be calculated by forward algorithm or 
backward algorithm (22). 
The posterior probability (22,31) of residue i in sequence x 
being aligned to residue j in sequence y (match probability) 
can be calculated as: </p>

<p>Pðx i aligned to y j Þ ¼ 
X </p>

<p>K m </p>

<p>P½pði‚jÞ ¼ K m j x‚y 
4 </p>

<p>Here, K m belongs to a set of match states. For model 
HMM_1_3_1, K m is from the set {'H', 'S', 'C', 'U'}. 
We then find the alignment path that maximizes the sum of 
match probabilities of residue pairs in the alignment path 
using dynamic programming with zero gap penalties. It has 
been shown that this technique can give better alignment 
quality than Viterbi algorithm (23). </p>



<p>Multiple sequence alignment procedure </p>

<p>We have developed a progressive multiple sequence align-
ment program implementing our HMMs (<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, 
standing for MUltiple alignment with Multiple MAtch state 
models of Local Structure). It applies a probabilistic consis-
tency scoring function similar to the one in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> (23). 
First, a tree is built-in a fast way based on a k-mer count 
method (10). An initial alignment is built progressively 
guided by the tree with a simple sum-of-pairs scoring func-
tion. A second tree is then built with a UPGMA method 
based on sequence identities calculated from the initial 
alignment. We then apply the probabilistic consistency stra-
tegy as described by Do et al. (23). For each sequence pair, 
we calculate the match probabilities of residue pairs using 
one of the HMMs. These probability matrices are subject to 
consistency measure, which involves multiplications of the 
matrices (23). Finally, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> progressively aligns the 
sequences guided by the second tree using the consistency-
based scoring function. 
To properly balance alignment speed and accuracy, we 
have also applied a two-stage alignment strategy similar to 
the one used in our program <rs type="software">PCMA</rs> (32). In the first stage, 
highly similar sequences are progressively aligned in a fast 
way without consistency scoring. The scoring function in 
this stage is a weighted sum-of-pairs measure of BLOSUM62 
scores (16). If two neighboring groups on a tree have an 
average sequence identity higher than a certain threshold, 
they are aligned in this fast way. The result of the first 
stage is a set of pre-aligned groups that are relatively diver-
gent from each other. In the second alignment stage, one 
representative sequence is selected from each pre-aligned 
group, and these representative sequences are subject to the 
more time-consuming probabilistic consistency measure. 
Then the representatives are aligned progressively according 
to the consistency-based scoring function. Finally, the pre-
aligned groups obtained in the first stage are merged accord-
ing to the alignment of the representatives to obtain the final 
alignment of all sequences. </p>

<p>Performance assessment of multiple sequence 
alignment programs </p>

<p>To test multiple sequence alignment programs, we used the 
same representative SCOP pairs selected for pairwise align-
ment tests (Supplementary Table S1). For each domain, we 
added up to 24 homologs, which were obtained from PSI-
BLAST searches (1) with five iterations and an E-value 
cut-off of 0.0001. We removed highly similar sequences 
(&gt;97% identity) and sequence fragments (coverage less 
than half of the query) before randomly selecting up to 24 
homologs. This procedure is similar to the one used to 
build the PREFAB database (10). Similar to pairwise align-
ment tests, the 4-fold cross validation approach is applied 
to the tests of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>. 
Two large testing datasets compiled by other researchers 
were used as well. One is the SABmark database (version 
1.65) (33), which is based on homologous SCOP domains, 
and the other is PREFAB database (version 4) (10), which 
is based on structural alignments and homologous sequences 
from database searches. Alignment quality scores (Q-scores) 
were calculated using the built-in programs in SABmark and </p>

<p>PREFAB packages. The Q-score is the fraction of the number 
of correctly aligned residue pairs in the test alignment to the 
total number of aligned residue pairs in the reference align-
ment. Additional series of smaller datasets constructed by 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> authors (11) were 55 HOMSTRAD (34) structural 
alignments with various numbers of close homologs added 
('HOM + X', 'X' is the number of close homologs added 
and is 0, 20, 50 or 100). To obtain more balanced datasets 
from 'HOM + 100', we used <rs type="software">BLASTCLUST</rs> to cluster 
sequences in any 'HOM + 100' alignment at 50 or 60% iden-
tity level, and selected up to two homologs in each sequence 
cluster. The resulting datasets are called 'HOM + 100_bcl50' 
and 'HOM + 100_bcl60'. We also tested programs on 218 
BAliBASE3.0 (35) alignments with full-length sequences. 
The column scores (the fraction of entirely correct columns) 
were reported in addition to Q-scores for BAliBASE3.0. 
Wilcoxon signed-ranks tests were performed to calculate 
statistical significance of comparisons between alignment 
programs, which include <rs id="software-124" type="software">ProbCons</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-124" type="version-number">1.10</rs>) (23), 
<rs id="software-125" type="software">MAFFT</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-125" type="version-number">5.667</rs>) (11) with several options, <rs id="software-126" type="software">MUSCLE</rs> 
(version <rs corresp="#software-126" type="version-number">3.52</rs>) (10) and <rs id="software-127" type="software">ClustalW</rs> (version <rs corresp="#software-127" type="version-number">1.83</rs>) (7). 
In addition to Q-score, we utilized a reference-independent 
assessment of alignment quality from a structural modeling 
perspective. Given a test sequence alignment of two SCOP 
domains with known structures, corresponding Ca atoms in 
aligned residue pairs were used as equivalent points for struc-
tural superposition to minimize the root mean square distance 
(RMSD). The structural similarity scores were calculated 
based on this forced superposition of the aligned residue 
pairs. The following scores were used: DALI Z-score (36), 
GDT score (37), TM-score (38), 3D-score (39) and two 
LiveBench contact scores (39) (see Supplementary Data for 
the equations of 3D-score and LiveBench contact scores). 
An alignment with better quality should have a higher 
similarity of the two structures superimposed in a sequence-
dependent way described above, and thus have a larger struc-
tural score. Two reference-independent sequence similarity 
scores were also calculated for aligned residue pairs in a 
test alignment: sequence identity and average BLOSUM62 
scores (16). Additionally, each of the scores was rescaled to 
take into account a random model (the reversed alignment), 
self-comparisons and alignment coverage (see Supplementary 
Data for details). Such rescaling places each score between 0 
(random match) and 1 (self-match) and makes different 
scoring schemes more comparable to each other. </p>

<p>Availability </p>

<p>The <rs id="software-128" type="software">MUMMALS</rs> multiple alignment web server is at: 
<rs corresp="#software-128" type="url">http://prodata.swmed.edu/mummals</rs>/, with the source code 
of MUMMALS available for download. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Complex HMMs with local structural information 
improve pairwise alignments </p>

<p>Applying a cross validation approach, we tested our pairwise 
alignment HMMs on representative domain pairs from the 
ASTRAL SCOP40 dataset (Table 1 and Supplementary 
Table S3). Model HMM_1_1_0 represents the simplest </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 4367 </p>

<p>model with a single match state (Figure 1a). It can serve as a 
control for more complex models, including HMM_1_1_1 
that assigns residue pairs in unaligned regions to a different 
match state, HMM_1_3_1 that captures secondary structure 
information, HMM_3_1_1 that captures solvent accessibility 
information, and HMM_3_3_1 that has both types of local 
structural information (see Materials and Methods). 
Several conclusions can be drawn from Table 1 and 
Supplementary Table S3. (i) For each testing dataset, the 
best performance is usually achieved with parameters esti-
mated on the training dataset with the same identity range 
(Supplementary Table S3). For example, models trained on 
alignments with the highest identity range (20-40%) exhibit 
best performance on testing alignments in that range. 
Thus residue substitution and insertion/deletion statistics are 
different for sequence pairs with different degrees of similar-
ity, in agreement with other reports (16,17). Although models 
trained on pairs with the lowest identity range can perform 
slightly better (2%) on representatives in that range, 
they perform much worse on alignments with the highest 
identity range (nearly 10% decrease as compared to models 
trained on pairs with the highest identity range). (ii) More 
complex HMMs improve alignment quality. For example, 
HMM_1_3_1 performs better than HMM_1_1_1 in almost 
every case. HMM_1_3_1 performs almost equally well to 
HMM_3_3_1. (iii) Our models trained on pairs with 
20-40% identity range perform better than several other 
aligners, such as <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> (23), <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> (11) with several 
option, <rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs> (10) and <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> (7) on any testing data-
set. Although the simplest model HMM_1_1_0 has the same 
model structure as the one used in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, it gives 3-4% 
increase over ProbCons for every testing dataset. The best 
models HMM_1_3_1 and HMM_3_3_1 give 4-5% increase 
over <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>. (iv) When trained on BAliBASE2.0, 
HMM_1_1_0 and HMM_1_1_1 exhibit inferior performance </p>

<p>compared to the same models trained on SCOP domain pairs 
with identity above 20%, suggesting that SCOP domain pairs 
with above 20% identity is a better training dataset than 
BAliBASE2.0. The two models (especially HMM_1_1_1) 
trained on BAliBASE2.0 nevertheless give slightly better 
performance than <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, which was also trained on 
BAliBASE2.0 but with a different training method (unsuper-
vised learning) (23). 
To further compare the performance of our HMMs and 
the one used in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, we tested sequence pairs from 
BAliBASE2.0, on which the HMM in ProbCons was trained 
(Supplementary Table S4). BAliBASE2.0 is a manually 
curated database for testing multiple alignment programs. It 
contains core blocks (uppercase letters) with good quality 
and a large fraction of lowercase letter regions where high 
alignment quality is not guaranteed. HMM_1_1_0 and 
HMM_1_1_1 trained on <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> alignments of SCOP 
domain pairs with above 20% identity show better results 
than these two models trained on BAliBASE2.0 as well as 
<rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, suggesting that the structural alignments of rela-
tively divergent SCOP domains form a better training set 
than BAliBASE2.0. HMM_1_3_1 trained on the same 
SCOP domain pairs gives the best BAliBASE2.0 results 
(Supplementary Table S4), confirming that a more complex 
model with multiple match states of secondary structures 
improves alignment quality. </p>

<p>MUMMALS and multiple sequence alignment tests </p>

<p>We implemented our HMM models in a multiple sequence 
alignment program based on probabilistic consistency. 
Our program is named <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, standing for MUltiple 
alignment with Multiple MAtch state models of Local 
Structure. <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> was compared to several other pro-
grams, such as <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> (23), <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> (11), MUSCLE (10) </p>

<p>Table 1. Average Q-scores in pairwise alignment tests on representative SCOP40 domain pairs </p>

<p>Method/Model 
Testing datasets 
SCOP 0-10% 
SCOP 10-15% 
SCOP 15-20% 
SCOP 2-40% 
SCOP All 
(355) 
(432) 
(420) 
(578) 
(1785) </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.146 
0.322 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.568 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.851 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.516 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.146 
0.328 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.573 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.855 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.520 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HMM_3_1_1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.150 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.327 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.574 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.858 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.521 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HMM_1_3_1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.152 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.334 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.585 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.858 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.526 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HMM_3_3_1 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.151 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.335 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.586 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.860 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>0.527 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.123 
0.295 
0.551 
0.843 
0.498 
HMM_1_1_1 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>0.132 
0.31 
0.572 
0.851 
0.511 
ProbCons 
0.116 
0.294 
0.536 
0.833 
0.490 
MAFFT-fftnsi 
0.087 
0.256 
0.496 
0.809 
0.457 
MAFFT-einsi 
0.081 
0.248 
0.491 
0.809 
0.453 
MAFFT-linsi 
0.116 
0.262 
0.495 
0.794 
0.460 
MAFFT-ginsi 
0.116 
0.265 
0.496 
0.794 
0.461 
MUSCLE 
0.139 
0.293 
0.507 
0.817 
0.482 
ClustalW 
0.136 
0.27 
0.482 
0.809 
0.467 </p>

<p>Each HMM is named in the format 'HMM_solv_ss_u', where 'solv' is the number of solvent accessibility categories, 'ss' is the number of secondary structure types, 
and 'u' is 1 if unaligned regions are modeled with an additional match state. Average Q-scores of four testing datasets with different identity ranges are shown. 
Q-score is the number of correctly aligned residue pairs in the test alignment divided by the total number of aligned residue pairs in the reference alignment. The 
number of alignments in each testing dataset is shown in parentheses and the identity range in % is specified above the number of alignments. The best results of our 
models and the best results of other programs are in bold numbers. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Trained on <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> alignments of SCOP40 domain pairs with 20-40% identity. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Trained on BAliBASE2.0 pairwise alignments. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Our model is statistically better than the best of other programs according to Wilcoxon signed-rank test (P &lt; 0.015). </p>



<p>and ClustalW (7). We assembled testing datasets of multiple 
sequences by adding homologs to pairwise alignments 
of SCOP domain pairs (see Materials and Methods). For 
three testing datasets with identity ranges below 20%, 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> shows 3-4% increase of average Q-score 
over <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> when the best-performing HMMs are selected 
(HMM_1_3_1 and HMM_3_3_1) (Table 2). For the dataset 
with identity range above 20%, the improvement is less 
prominent (1%), although still statistically significant (P &lt; 
0.005). Among the other programs tested (<rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, several 
options of <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>, <rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs> and <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs>), MAFFT with 
options [lg]insi usually gives the best performance. Our pro-
gram still outperforms any <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> option by 2% for the 
three datasets with identity ranges below 20%. 
The other two large datasets we have used for testing are 
PREFAB version 4 (PREFAB4) (10) and SABmark version 
1.65 (33). PREFAB4 consists of 1682 alignments based on 
the consensus of two structural alignment programs <rs type="software">SOFI</rs> 
(40) and <rs type="software">CE</rs> (41), with up to 24 homologous sequences 
added from database searches. SABmark database has two 
alignment sets. The 'twilight zone' set contains SCOP 
(version 1.65) domain pairs with very low-to-low similarity 
and the 'superfamily' set contains SCOP domains with 
low to intermediate similarity. The reference alignments in 
SABmark were also derived from the consensus of <rs type="software">SOFI</rs> 
and CE. The comparison of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with the other 
programs on PREFAB4 and SABmark shows similar trends 
as seen in datasets assembled by us. <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with the 
best-performing models (HMM_1_3_1 and HMM_3_3_1) 
gives the highest average Q-scores, with 2-4% increase 
over <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> and 1% increase over the best of the 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> series (Table 2). 
We also tested these programs on datasets of 55 
HOMSTRAD structural alignments (11,34) with various 
numbers of homologs added (Supplementary Table S5). </p>

<p><rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> performs better than other programs for testing 
datasets 'HOM + 0', 'HOM + 20' and 'HOM + 50'. The 
results of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> on 'HOM + 100' are inferior to 
those on 'HOM + 50', which is in contrast to <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> that 
shows consistent increase of accuracy when more homologs 
are added. We reason that such a problem of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> 
is due to excessive number of close homologs in some 
sequence subgroups in 'HOM + 100' test cases, since our 
consistency measure does not take into account similarities 
among the testing sequences. To test this hypothesis, we 
removed closely related sequences in 'HOM + 100' align-
ment at 50 or 60% identity level (datasets 'HOM + 
100_bcl50' and 'HOM + 100_bcl60'). The remaining 
sequences are more balanced in terms of similarities among 
them. We indeed obtained the best <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> performance 
after removing closely related sequences (Supplementary 
Table S5). A similar degrading effect of closely related 
sequences is observed for <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, which is also based on 
probabilistic consistency. 
Recently, BAliBASE3.0 multiple alignment benchmark 
has been released (35). We tested the programs on 218 
BAliBASE3.0 alignments with full-length sequences. These 
alignments represent difficult cases since N-or C-terminal 
non-homologous regions are included for some sequences. 
The average Q-scores and column scores (the fraction of 
entirely correctly columns) in manually defined core blocks 
are reported in Table 2. For Q-score measurement of align-
ment quality, the Wilcoxon signed rank tests show that 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with best-performing models (HMM_3_3_1 or 
HMM_1_3_1) is statistically better than other programs, 
albeit MUMMALS does not have the highest average 
Q-score. For column score measurement of alignment 
quality, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with HMM_3_3_1 or HMM_1_3_1 
has a lower average column score than <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>-[le]insi and 
<rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, but the difference between them is not statistically </p>

<p>Table 2. Average alignment scores in tests of multiple sequence alignment programs </p>

<p>Methods/Models Testing datasets 
SCOP 0-10% SCOP 10-15% SCOP 15-20% SCOP 20-40% SCOP 
PREFAB SABmark SABmark BAliBASE3.0 
(355) 
(432) 
(420) 
(578) 
All (1785) (1682) 
Sup (425) Twi (209) Q/col (218) </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 
0.313 
0.514 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.727 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.885 
0.644 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.723 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.516 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.193 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.862/0.551 
HMM_1_1_1 
0.313 
0.512 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.728 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.886 
0.644 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.724 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.512 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.186 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.861/0.550 
HMM_3_1_1 
0.321 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.514 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.730 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.888 
0.647 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.726 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.516 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.186 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.862/0.554 
HMM_1_3_1 
0.327 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.518 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.732 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.889 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.650 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.729 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.519 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.194 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.863/0.554 
HMM_3_3_1 
0.329 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.520 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.733 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.889 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.651 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.731 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.522 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.196 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.863/0.557 
ProbCons 
0.291 
0.486 
0.702 
0.879 
0.625 
0.716 
0.485 
0.166 
0.862 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.556 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>MAFFT-fftnsi 
0.283 
0.472 
0.673 
0.865 
0.608 
0.7 
0.45 
0.147 
0.829 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.515 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>MAFFT-einsi 
0.293 
0.498 
0.71 
0.882 
0.631 
0.72 
0.502 
0.175 
0.866 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.585 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>MAFFT-linsi 
0.301 
0.5 
0.707 
0.883 
0.633 
0.722 
0.51 
0.184 
0.868 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.586 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>MAFFT-ginsi 
0.308 
0.497 
0.714 
0.888 
0.637 
0.715 
0.495 
0.176 
0.840 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.526 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>MUSCLE 
0.262 
0.453 
0.662 
0.866 
0.597 
0.68 
0.433 
0.136 
0.816 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.472 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>ClustalW 
0.21 
0.357 
0.566 
0.798 
0.519 
0.617 
0.39 
0.127 
0.749 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>/0.373 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>The format of the HMM names ('HMM_solv_ss_u') is explained in Table1. Average Q-scores are shown for all the testing datasets. For the BAliBASE3.0 dataset, 
both the Q-score ('Q', first number) and column score ('col', second number, fraction of entirely correct columns) are shown. The first four testing datasets are 
representative SCOP40 domain pairs with added homologs. SABmark has 'superfamily' dataset (sup) and 'twilight zone' dataset (twi). The number of alignments in 
each testing dataset is shown in parentheses and the identity range in % is specified above the number of alignments for SCOP datasets. <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> implementing 
different HMMs are the first five methods. All sequences pairs are subject to consistency measure in <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>. The best scores of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> and the best 
scores of other programs are in bold. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p><rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with this model is statistically better than the best of other programs according to Wilcoxon signed-rank test (P &lt; 0.015). 
b For BAliBASE3.0 test, the difference between <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with model HMM_1_3_1 or HMM_3_3_1 and this program is not statistically significant (P &gt; 0.05) 
according to Wilcoxon signed-ranks test. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>For BAliBASE3.0 test, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with model HMM_1_3_1 or HMM_3_3_1 is statistically better than this program (P-value less than 0.01, except for Q-scores 
of <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, for which P ¼ 0.017). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 4369 </p>

<p>significant. In fact <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with HMM_3_3_1 out-
performs <rs type="software">MAFFT-linsi</rs> (having the best average scores) in 
106 cases while MAFFT-linsi performs better in 67 cases, 
measured by column score. 
We found that the major cause of lower average column 
score of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> is due to a few alignments that 
MUMMALS gives considerably lower scores as compared 
to <rs type="software">MAFFT-linsi</rs> (10 alignments with a score difference larger 
than 0.5). Manual inspections of these alignments revealed 
some interesting scenarios. In some cases, the low scores of 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> are due to wrong alignment of a few divergent 
sequences, some of which have long extensions at the ends. 
Column score is very sensitive in such situations, since a 
low score is produced even if only one sequence is incorrectly 
aligned in many places. <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> alignments with local 
options ([le]insi) indeed show advantage in these situations 
(11). In several other cases, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> produces struc-
turally meaningful alignments that are scored very low 
since they are not consistent with the reference alignments 
(Supplementary Figure S1). One example is testing case 
BB40037, for which the reference alignment aligns the 
'fer2' domain [2Fe-2S iron sulfur cluster binding domain, 
named by Conserved Domain Database (42)] that is present 
in every sequence. Inspection of the sequences revealed 
two groups of sequences with different domain architectures 
in BB40037 (Supplementary Figure S1a). One group contains 
three domains in the order of 'fer2', 'FAD_binding_6' (oxi-
doreductase FAD-binding domain) and 'NAD_binding_1' 
(oxidoreductase NAD-binding domain). The other group 
contains the same three domains, but in the order of 
'FAD_binding_6', 'NAD_binding_1' and 'fer2'. <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> 
aligns 'FAD_binding_6' and 'NAD_binding_1' for the two 
groups and thus misaligned the 'fer2' domain. Since the 
reference-dependent evaluation is based on 'fer2' domain, 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> alignment gets a column score of zero. Another 
evaluation problem is caused by domain duplication or 
repeats, as exemplified by test case BB40040. Most of 
BB40040 sequences have a single domain of carbonic anhy-
drase. However, the sequence 'CAH_DUNSA' has two such 
domains (Supplementary Figure S1b). The reference align-
ment aligns the first domain of 'CAH_DUNSA' to other 
sequences while <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> aligns most of the second 
domain to other sequences, resulting in a low column score. </p>

<p>Secondary structure prediction and alignment quality </p>

<p>Model HMM_1_3_1 has hidden secondary structure-
dependent match states that are used in alignment construc-
tion. However, secondary structure predictions are not 
explicitly generated and remain 'hidden' in the alignment 
process. A posterior decoding technique can be applied to 
this model to output explicit secondary structure predictions 
(see Supplementary Data for details). The prediction accuracy 
is 60% on representative SCOP domains (Supplementary 
Table S6). This prediction accuracy is lower than many 
advanced methods, such as <rs type="software">PSI-PRED</rs> (43), which use 
homologs from database searches to enhance the secondary 
structure signal of a single sequence. Our HMM-based pre-
diction of secondary structure corresponds to a single 
sequence predictor, since position-specific information from 
multiple homologs is not used. The prediction accuracy of </p>

<p>model HMM_1_3_1 is comparable to other methods that 
generate predictions based on a single sequence (44). 
If secondary structure information is known for one of the 
aligned sequences, model HMM_1_3_1 can be modified to 
restrict the hidden state path to follow the experimental 
secondary structure (see Supplementary Data). Using real 
secondary structural information in <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with 
model HMM_1_3_1, we were able to obtain an average 
Q-score increase of 3% on SABmark datasets (Supplemen-
tary Table S8). Such a result suggests that one limitation of 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> is the low accuracy of the implicit secondary 
structure prediction. Further improvement of alignment 
quality should be possible with more accurate secondary 
structure predictions that explore database homologs. </p>

<p>Evaluation of programs with reference-independent 
scores </p>

<p>All previously described tests are based on comparison with 
reference alignments that are treated as 'gold standards'. It is 
unclear how the quality of reference 'gold' alignments influ-
ences the ranking of alignment programs (45). Several exam-
ples from BAliBASE3.0 show some problems with reference-
dependent evaluation. Since the structures of all domains in 
our testing datasets are known, we can evaluate the quality 
of a test alignment using reference-independent scores that 
reflect the similarity between two structures after they are 
superimposed according to aligned residues in the test align-
ment. The structural scores we have used are: DALI Z-score, 
TM-score, GDT-TS score, 3D-score and two LiveBench 
contact scores. From Table 3, it is clear that <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> 
with the best-performing models (HMM_1_3_1 and 
HMM_3_3_1) produces higher average reference-
independent structural scores than other programs for diver-
gent domain pairs (identity below 20%), suggesting that our 
HMM models produce potentially more useful alignments in 
terms of structure modeling. Interestingly, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> does 
not produce the highest reference-independent sequence-
based similarity scores (sequence identity and BLOSUM62 
scores of aligned residue pairs). This result suggests that 
minimization of these sequence similarity measures alone 
does not lead to better alignment quality for divergent 
sequences. Our experiments with reference-independent 
evaluation shows good correlation with reference-dependent 
results described above, thus rendering a 'gold standard' 
reference unnecessary for alignment evaluation. </p>

<p>Pairwise comparisons of multiple sequence aligners </p>

<p><rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> shows improvement over <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> and <rs type="software">Prob- Cons</rs> by only a few percent in terms of average alignment 
quality scores on various testing datasets. Although this 
improvement is statistically significant and does not depend 
on the testing dataset (assembled by us, or by other 
researchers) or alignment quality measure (reference-
dependent Q-score, or reference-independent DALI Z-score, 
TM-score, GDT-TS, etc), it is not clear what these average 
scores actually represent. To gain more understanding, we 
directly compared alignment scores of different programs 
for individual domain pairs. Table 4 shows the number of 
alignments where one program performs better than another 
program by 10% or more (measured by Q-score or </p>



<p>normalized TM-score) for 1207 divergent SCOP40 pairs with 
added homologs (sequence identity &lt;20%). The numbers for 
such differences among <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> family of programs 
with five different HMMs are relatively small, suggesting 
that MUMMALS with different HMMs generates alignments 
not that different from each other. The differences between 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> and other programs are significantly larger. 
For example, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with HMM_3_3_1 has a large 
Q-score increase (&gt;10%) over <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> on 201 alignments, 
while ProbCons is better by 10% or more on 62 alignments. 
For <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with HMM_3_3_1 and <rs type="software">MAFFT-ginsi</rs>, these 
numbers are 199 and 117, respectively. Our comparisons thus 
suggest that different programs can explore somewhat differ-
ent regions in alignment space, and the program giving lower 
average performance may be capable of generating better 
alignments in many cases. However, selection of a better 
alignment in the absence of structural comparison is still a 
difficult task (46). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Comparison of multiple sequence alignment programs </p>

<p><rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> (23) and <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> (11) are two of the most accurate 
multiple sequence alignment programs that explore only 
sequence information. They use different strategies to 
improve the accuracy of progressive alignment. <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> 
mainly relies on the consistency-based scoring function and 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> utilizes iterative refinement. <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>'s scoring func-
tion is a weighted sum-of-pairs score of BLOSUM62, a gen-
eral amino acid substitution matrix. Recent versions of 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> enhance performance by exploring aligned core 
regions with a simple consistency measure (11). However, 
the time-consuming <rs type="software">ProbCons-type</rs> consistency operations 
on sequence triplets are not implemented in <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>. Our 
results show that <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> based on probabilistic consis-
tency can perform better than <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>, implying that 
consistency-based scoring function is superior to weighted 
sum-of-pairs measures of general substitution matrices. 
Among existing multiple aligners, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> is meth-
odologically closest to <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>. However, we implement </p>

<p>HMMs that are different from the one used in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> 
in three aspects. First, we introduce more complex model 
structures by increasing the number of match state types. 
While HMM_1_1_0, used mainly as a control, has the 
same model structure as the one in <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, the other 
four models (HMM_1_1_1, HMM_1_3_1, HMM_3_1_1 
and HMM_3_3_1) incorporate more match states, which 
take into account residue substitution differences in unaligned 
regions and aligned core blocks, as well as local structural 
differences in aligned core blocks. Second, we have estimated 
model parameters from <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> structural alignments of 
divergent SCOP domains (&lt;40% identity), while the training 
data of <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> are from BAliBASE2.0. Third, we applied a 
supervised learning approach to estimating model parameters 
from structural alignments that have known hidden state 
paths. <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> applied an unsupervised learning approach 
(expectation maximization) to derive parameters without 
using reference alignments. Trained and tested on <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> 
structural alignments of SCOP40 domain pairs and on 
BAliBASE2.0 alignments, our models give better alignment 
quality than <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs> and a number of other programs. We 
show that more complex models improve alignment quality 
and SCOP40 superfamily pairs with identity range of 20-
40% provide a better training dataset than BAliBASE2.0 
alignments. 
Although we do not explicitly perform structure prediction 
in the course of alignment construction, our HMMs with 
multiple match states have built-in information of residue 
substitution characteristics in distinct local structure 
environments. Such information is learned from structural 
alignments in the training process and is encoded in the mod-
els. Since these match states are hidden states, our HMMs 
construct alignments using only sequence information. In 
this aspect, our method is different from some other methods 
that require direct use of real or predicted local structural 
information (19,47). </p>

<p>Time complexity of HMMs and MUMMALS </p>

<p>The trade-off for improvement of alignment quality with 
more complex model structures is more time for computation </p>

<p>Table 3. Assessment of multiple sequence alignment programs using reference-independent sequence and structural similarity scores on 1207 representative 
SCOP40 domain pairs with identity &lt;20% </p>

<p>Method 
Structural similarity 
Sequence similarity 
DALI Z-score 
GDT-TS 
TM-score 
3D-score 
LBcona 
LBconb 
Sequence identity 
Blosum62 score </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 
0.1178 
0.2510 
0.3005 
0.2499 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2181 
0.2828 
0.0953 
0.1687 
HMM_1_1_1 
0.1200 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2519 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3010 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2514 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2190 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2838 
0.0955 
0.1688 
HMM_3_1_1 
0.1217 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2540 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3034 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2532 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2215 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2872 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0938 
0.1665 
HMM_1_3_1 
0.1226 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2564 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3061 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2557 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2230 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2892 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0944 
0.1662 
HMM_3_3_1 
0.1231 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2570 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.3070 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2563 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2240 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.2909 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0.0932 
0.1651 
ProbCons 
0.1003 
0.2324 
0.2767 
0.2307 
0.2060 
0.2670 
0.0983 
0.1719 
MAFFT-fftnsi 
0.0982 
0.2333 
0.2814 
0.2297 
0.2004 
0.2632 
0.0917 
0.1621 
MAFFT-einsi 
0.1136 
0.2425 
0.2886 
0.2410 
0.2105 
0.2763 
0.0940 
0.1666 
MAFFT-linsi 
0.1135 
0.2485 
0.2982 
0.2467 
0.2143 
0.2820 
0.0923 
0.1632 
MAFFT-ginsi 
0.1126 
0.2454 
0.2960 
0.2429 
0.2152 
0.2803 
0.0972 
0.1725 
MUSCLE 
0.0980 
0.2297 
0.2777 
0.2266 
0.1941 
0.2535 
0.0939 
0.1686 
ClustalW 
0.0723 
0.1916 
0.2318 
0.1876 
0.1551 
0.2030 
0.0733 
0.1344 </p>

<p>The first five methods are <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> implementing different HMMs. The format of the HMM names ('HMM_solv_ss_u') is explained in Table 1. The best scores 
of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> and the best scores of other programs (<rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>, <rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> with different options, <rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs>, <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs>) are in bold. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p><rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with this model is statistically better than the best of other programs according to Wilcoxon signed-rank test (P &lt; 0.01). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 4371 </p>

<p>(Supplementary Table S2). HMM_3_3_1 (modeling both 
secondary structure and solvent accessibility) has the 
largest number of hidden states and is the most time-
consuming model, running about three times slower than 
HMM_1_3_1 (modeling only secondary structure). However, 
the performance of these two models is fairly similar in pair-
wise or multiple sequence alignment tests (Tables 1-3). 
HMM_3_1_1 (modeling only solvent accessibility) has the 
same time complexity as HMM_1_3_1, but usually shows 
slightly inferior performance to HMM_1_3_1. These obser-
vations suggest that HMM_1_3_1 (modeling only secondary 
structure) is most efficient in balancing alignment accuracy 
and speed. 
For <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, the rate-limiting steps are the computa-
tion of match probabilities using forward and backward algo-
rithms (time order is N 
2 *L 
2 *K </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>, N: number of sequences, 
L: average length, K: number of hidden states), and the com-
putation of the consistency-based scoring function, which 
requires operations on all sequence triplets (time order is 
N 
3 *L 
2 ). If probabilistic consistency measure is applied to 
every sequence pair, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> is much slower than 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs>, <rs type="software">MUSCLE</rs> and <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> (Supplementary Table S9). 
For example, the median CPU time of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with 
model HMM_1_3_1 on 1785 SCOP40 pairs with added 
homologs is 174s per alignment, as compared to 2.5s for 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> with 'ginsi' option (on Redhat Enterprise Linux 3, 
AMD Opteron 2.0 GHz). Applying a two-stage alignment 
strategy similar to the one used in the program <rs type="software">PCMA</rs> (32), 
we were able to make <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> almost an order of mag-
nitude faster while still maintaining the same level of align-
ment accuracy on SCOP testing datasets (Supplementary 
Table S9). Since highly similar sequences can be aligned 
accurately with a general scoring function (8), there is no 
need for all of them to be subject to the time-consuming con-
sistency measure. Although adding homologous sequences 
can in general improve alignment quality, our results on 
HOMSTRAD datasets suggest that proper balance of the 
similarity among the added homologs is also critical for 
<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> as well as <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>. </p>

<p>Methods for alignment quality evaluation </p>

<p>Reference-dependent alignment evaluation relies on compari-
son of a test alignment to a reference alignment that is 
assumed to be correct. A commonly used alignment quality 
score is the fraction of correctly aligned residue pairs 
(Q-score). More complex scores have been designed to take 
into account the relative shifts of residues (48,49). Even 
though structure-based alignments can serve as high-quality 
references, there are several well-known drawbacks. First, 
structural alignments generated by automatic programs 
could still contain errors, especially for pairs with relatively 
low structural similarity, i.e. careful expert-driven multila-
teral research may generate alignments more meaningful 
than those obtained by programs. Second, defining the opti-
mal structural alignment in certain regions is difficult for 
structurally divergent pairs, i.e. it is simply not possible to 
identify a single 'correct' alignment, which may not even 
exist. Third, for multi-domain proteins, especially those 
with repeats or duplications, multiple ways of aligning struc-
turally similar parts exist, resulting in a variety of reference </p>

<p>Table 4. Number of large 
Q-score or TM-score differences (no less than 0.1) among the multiple sequence alignment programs on 1207 representative SCOP40 domain pairs with identity </p>

<p>&lt;20% </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 HMM_1_1_1 HMM_3_1_1 HMM_1_3_1 HMM_3_3_1 ProbCons MAFFT-fftnsi MAFFT-einsi MAFFT-linsi MAFFT-ginsi MUSCLE ClustalW </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_0 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>13/8 </p>

<p>41/18 </p>

<p>29/15 </p>

<p>45/24 </p>

<p>50/157 </p>

<p>105/191 </p>

<p>108/163 </p>

<p>119/127 </p>

<p>85/102 </p>

<p>92/208 </p>

<p>73/399 </p>

<p>HMM_1_1_1 </p>

<p>14/14 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>35/16 </p>

<p>18/6 </p>

<p>38/24 </p>

<p>53/156 </p>

<p>100/189 </p>

<p>103/171 </p>

<p>109/124 </p>

<p>90/110 </p>

<p>91/209 </p>

<p>76/397 </p>

<p>HMM_3_1_1 </p>

<p>28/45 </p>

<p>22/40 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>16/24 </p>

<p>4/5 </p>

<p>39/164 </p>

<p>86/211 </p>

<p>101/183 </p>

<p>109/135 </p>

<p>81/124 </p>

<p>82/225 </p>

<p>63/418 </p>

<p>HMM_1_3_1 </p>

<p>19/29 </p>

<p>9/22 </p>

<p>26/20 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>25/19 </p>

<p>46/155 </p>

<p>90/202 </p>

<p>107/169 </p>

<p>110/124 </p>

<p>89/116 </p>

<p>92/214 </p>

<p>70/408 </p>

<p>HMM_3_3_1 </p>

<p>29/57 </p>

<p>22/54 </p>

<p>6/17 </p>

<p>20/36 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>38/169 </p>

<p>85/207 </p>

<p>97/185 </p>

<p>111/138 </p>

<p>82/128 </p>

<p>82/227 </p>

<p>59/431 </p>

<p>ProbCons </p>

<p>187/76 </p>

<p>186/80 </p>

<p>203/67 </p>

<p>189/73 </p>

<p>201/62 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>149/133 </p>

<p>152/98 </p>

<p>172/80 </p>

<p>162/76 </p>

<p>162/169 </p>

<p>110/336 </p>

<p>MAFFT-fftnsi 334/123 </p>

<p>334/118 </p>

<p>354/113 </p>

<p>344/115 </p>

<p>352/115 </p>

<p>242/154 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>123/98 </p>

<p>137/71 </p>

<p>153/76 </p>

<p>115/143 </p>

<p>88/342 </p>

<p>MAFFT-einsi </p>

<p>234/156 </p>

<p>232/152 </p>

<p>260/147 </p>

<p>247/152 </p>

<p>258/138 </p>

<p>152/186 </p>

<p>116/225 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>80/37 </p>

<p>133/96 </p>

<p>134/193 </p>

<p>93/369 </p>

<p>MAFFT-linsi </p>

<p>206/138 </p>

<p>204/140 </p>

<p>237/131 </p>

<p>219/143 </p>

<p>239/128 </p>

<p>133/188 </p>

<p>87/207 </p>

<p>62/82 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>85/98 </p>

<p>93/196 </p>

<p>60/387 </p>

<p>MAFFT-ginsi </p>

<p>160/124 </p>

<p>162/124 </p>

<p>192/119 </p>

<p>176/126 </p>

<p>199/117 </p>

<p>113/184 </p>

<p>109/253 </p>

<p>129/158 </p>

<p>111/132 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>90/185 </p>

<p>67/395 </p>

<p>MUSCLE </p>

<p>370/94 </p>

<p>374/94 </p>

<p>390/83 </p>

<p>384/90 </p>

<p>401/83 </p>

<p>302/138 </p>

<p>218/136 </p>

<p>309/134 </p>

<p>295/110 </p>

<p>327/106 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>75/288 </p>

<p>ClustalW </p>

<p>627/67 </p>

<p>628/66 </p>

<p>645/60 </p>

<p>645/65 </p>

<p>649/55 </p>

<p>559/103 </p>

<p>498/96 </p>

<p>582/91 </p>

<p>585/70 </p>

<p>600/76 </p>

<p>449/100 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>The first five methods are <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> implementing different HMMs. The format of the HMM names ('HMM_solv_ss_u') is explained in Table 1. Each none-diagonal cell has two numbers separated by a slash. 
The first number is the number of cases where the alignment quality score of the program listed to the left (in a row) is inferior to that of the program listed above (in a column) by 0.1 or more. The second number is 
the number of cases where the score of the 'row' program is better than that of the 'column' program by 0.1 or more. The alignment quality scores in the lower triangle and upper triangle are </p>

<p>Q-scores and weighted </p>

<p>and normalized TM-scores, respectively. Comparisons of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> with the best model (HMM_3_3_1) with other programs are highlighted in bold. </p>



<p>alignments that are correct from structure modeling pers-
pective. However, structure superposition programs usually 
provide a single best alignment. Some problems of reference-
dependent evaluations are illustrated by examples from 
BAliBASE3.0. For SCOP40 testing datasets, we found 
about 20 domain pairs for which all sequence-based programs 
failed to align a single position correctly according to 
<rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> reference alignment. Manual inspection of these 
instances suggests that most of these domains involve struc-
tural repeats. Many alignments produced by the tested pro-
grams did produce structurally meaningful results, but they 
had zero scores because they matched different repeats than 
those aligned by <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs>. 
Reference-independent evaluation can avoid these 
drawbacks. Although reference-independent evaluation is 
routinely used for assessing structure prediction models 
(50,51), it has not been frequently used in assessment of 
multiple sequence alignment programs (10,45). Our results 
show that reference-independent evaluation using various 
structural similarity scores produces similar, if not identical, 
rankings of the programs compared to reference-dependent 
evaluations using <rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> alignments (Table 3). On the one 
hand, this result suggests that a large collection of reference 
alignments generated by structure alignment program 
<rs type="software">DaliLite</rs> are on average well-suited for assessment of align-
ment quality. On the other hand, it is probably unnecessary 
to have a set of 'gold standard' reference alignments. 
Reference-independent evaluation through scoring super-
positions generated according sequence-based alignments 
is an easier and maybe more fair method to assess align-
ment quality and to compare different aligners. Therefore, 
particularly when the size of a testing dataset is large, 
improving reference alignment quality either by manual 
inspection and adjustment (30), or by using the consensus 
of structural aligners (10,33) is probably not necessary. 
With reference-independent evaluation techniques, we 
even suggest bypassing the step of generating reference 
alignments. </p>

<p>Multiple sequence alignment: still an unsolved problem </p>

<p>Despite several percentage points' improvement in align-
ments provided by <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, alignment quality for 
divergent sequences (sequence identity &lt;15%) is still not 
high, since only 50% or even less residue pairs on average 
are aligned correctly according to reference alignments 
(Table 2). Although the best programs (<rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs>, 
<rs type="software">MAFFT</rs> and <rs type="software">ProbCons</rs>) have limited differences in terms of 
average alignment quality score, they can produce quite 
different alignments for some sequence pairs (Table 4). It 
can be a good practice to use several aligners to generate 
alignments for divergent sequences. Manual examination of 
these alignments can be helpful in making expert judgments. 
Exploration of the consensus among programs is fruitful as 
well and is frequently used in meta-servers for structure 
prediction (52-54). Results of the meta-aligner <rs type="software">M-COFFEE</rs> 
(46) as well as ours (data not shown, <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> package 
contains a meta-program similar to M-COFFEE) suggest 
that combining different multiple sequence aligners can 
give significant but limited improvement of alignment 
quality. </p>

<p>One advantage of <rs type="software">MUMMALS</rs> is the use of HMMs with 
local structure information learned from structural align-
ments. Our model HMM_1_3_1 gives low secondary struc-
ture prediction accuracy. Providing real secondary structure 
information to this model can further improve alignment 
quality by a few percent. These results suggest that applica-
tion of more accurate secondary structure predictions can 
lead to better alignment quality. Exploration of database 
sequence homologs and available 3D structures was also 
shown to be helpful (11,55,56). Further enhancement of 
multiple alignment quality could be achieved by effective 
integration of existing alignment techniques and various 
evolutionary and structural information resources. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Bong-Hyun Kim for the 
program to calculate reference-independent sequence and 
structural scores and Dr Kazutaka Katoh for providing the 
HOMSTRAD datasets. The authors would also like to thank 
Lisa Kinch, James Wrabl and anonymous referees for helpful 
comments. Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by Howard Hughes 
Medical Institute. This work was supported in part by NIH 
grant GM67165 to NVG. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 16 4373 </p>





</text></tei>