<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1849898" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T01:00+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>This study developed a method to boost the 
expression of recombinant proteins in a cell-free 
protein synthesis system without leaving additional 
amino acid residues. It was found that the nucleot-
ide sequences of the signal peptides serve as 
an efficient downstream box to stimulate protein 
synthesis when they were fused upstream of the 
target genes. The extent of stimulation was critically 
affected by the identity of the second codons of 
the signal sequences. Moreover, the yield of the 
synthesized protein was enhanced by as much as 
10 times in the presence of an optimal second 
codon. The signal peptides were in situ cleaved and 
the target proteins were produced in their native 
sizes by carrying out the cell-free synthesis reac-
tions in the presence of Triton X-100, most likely 
through the activation of signal peptidase in the S30 
extract. The amplification of the template DNA and 
the addition of the signal sequences were accomp-
lished by PCR. Hence, elevated levels of recombi-
nant proteins were generated within several hours. </p>

<p>The cultivation of transformed cells has long been used as a 
standard route for preparing recombinant proteins. However, 
the recent explosion in the number of the newly identified 
open reading frames (ORFs) is now demanding a high 
throughput of protein expression that cannot be readily 
covered by the present in vivo expression technology. 
Cell-free protein synthesis is attracting renewed attention 
as an alternative technique for overcoming the limited 
throughput of in vivo expression (1-4). While the conven-
tional protocols of cell-free protein synthesis have been 
unable to provide sufficient quantities of proteins, recent </p>

<p>improvements in the understanding of the key factors 
involved in cell-free synthesis have allowed the development 
of more efficient and robust protocols. Among the many 
attempts to enhance the accumulation of protein products in 
cell-free synthesis reactions, major improvements have been 
made through the stable supply of energy and substrates; ATP 
and amino acids (5-8). Kim et al. reported that the stable 
maintenance of the magnesium concentration against accu-
mulating phosphate is also essential for prolonging the 
reaction period of cell-free protein synthesis (9). 
However, the efficiency of gene expression is affected by 
the nature of the sequence elements as well as by environ-
mental factors. Therefore, providing the optimal biochemical 
conditions is not sufficient for obtaining a high protein 
yield when the identity and arrangement of the nucleotide 
sequences have not been optimized for translation. In addi-
tion to the initiation codon and the Shine-Dalgarno (SD) 
sequence, several other sequence elements surrounding the 
start codon affect the efficiency of translation initiation 
significantly (10-14). In particular, the sequence of the first 
few nucleotides in close proximity to the start codon (down-
stream box) has a profound effect on the translation efficiency 
of many transcripts. 
In this study, it was found that many of the naturally occur-
ring signal peptide sequences stimulate protein synthesis in 
a cell-free protein synthesis system derived from Escherichia 
coli. For example, when the nucleotide sequence of the 
OmpA signal peptide (ompAss) was fused with the target 
genes, the amounts of the cell-free synthesized proteins 
were enhanced 10 times. The effectiveness of the different 
signal sequences were compared in a rapid and parallel man-
ner through the PCR-based generation of the DNA templates 
for cell-free protein synthesis. As a result, it was found that 
the stimulatory effect of a signal peptide sequence was depen-
dent on the identity of its second codon, and that most of 
the effective nucleotide sequences have an AAA triplet at 
the +2 position. 
Finally, the 'open' nature of the cell-free protein synthesis 
enabled the in situ removal of the signal peptide from the </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +82 42 821 5899; Fax: +82 42 823 7692; Email: dmkim@cnu.ac.kr </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Published online 20 December 2006 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 e21 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl917 </p>

<p>expressed proteins. All the expression products were found 
at the native size of the target protein using the cell-free 
protein synthesis reactions in the presence of Triton X-100, 
most likely through the activation of the endogenous signal 
peptidase. 
The method presented in this report enables the parallel 
expression of authentic proteins at elevated levels, and will 
provide a valuable platform for the large-scale translation 
of genomic information into protein molecules. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>ATP, GTP, UTP, CTP, creatine phosphate, creatine kinase 
and the E.coli total tRNA mixture were purchased from 
Roche Applied Science (Indianapolis, IN). The L-[U-
14 C]-
leucine (11.9 GBq/mmol) was obtained from Amersham 
Biosciences (Uppsala, Sweden). The detergents were 
obtained from Pierce Biotechnology (Rockford, IL). All the 
other reagents were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis, MO). 
The E.coli strain BL21-StarÔ(DE3) was purchased from 
Invitrogen (Carlsbad, CA). The S30 extract was prepared 
from the strain BL21-StarÔ(DE3) according to the method 
reported elsewhere (15,16). </p>

<p>Statistical analysis of nucleotide sequences </p>

<p>The full-length genome sequences of E.coli (strain K-12) 
were downloaded from the GeneBank database (NC_000913). 
000913). The nucleotide sequences encoding the E.coli signal 
peptides were obtained from a signal peptide database 
(release 3.2) (17). </p>

<p>Construction of plasmid expression templates </p>

<p>Seven signal peptide sequences were fused to the structural 
gene of human erythropoietin (hEPO) using conventional 
PCR methods. The sequences were subcloned into the 
pK7 vector (18) between the nucleotide sequences of the 
T7 promoter and T7 terminator. The plasmid constructs 
were sequenced and purified using the Maxiprep kit (Qiagen, 
Valencia, CA) before being used as templates for cell-free 
protein synthesis reactions (Table 1 and Figure 1). </p>

<p>Construction of linear expression templates </p>

<p>For the parallel expression of different ORFs, the PCR-
amplified DNAs were used directly as templates for the 
cell-free synthesis reactions. The ompA fused-gene constructs 
were prepared using overlap extension PCR techniques. In 
the first-round PCR, three of the primary PCRs were carried 
out in separate reactions as follows: the T7 regulatory ele-
ments and ompA sequence were amplified from pK7ompAss-
EPO using the primers, P1 (5 
0 -TGGCACGACAGGTTT-
CCCGA-3 
0 ) and P2 (5 
0 -GGCCTGCGCTACGGTAGCGA-3 
0 ). 
The target ORFs were amplified using the primers, P3 [5 
0 -
TCGCTACCGTAGCGCAGGCC-(20 nt sequence for target 
gene)-3 
0 ] and P4 [5 
0 -TGATGATGAGAACCCCCCCC-
(complementary 20 nt sequence for target gene)-3 
0 ] from 
the cloned plasmid or genomic DNA. The 3 
0 -UTR region 
including the T7 terminator was amplified from the 
pIVEX2.3d plasmid (Roche Applied Science) using the 
primer P5 (5 
0 -GGGGGGGGTTCTCATCATCA-3 
0 ) and P6 
(5 
0 -CCCAGTCCTGCTCGCTTCGC-3 
0 ). The 1st PCR prod-
ucts were purified by gel extraction and used for the second-
round PCR, in which the full-length expression templates 
were synthesized using the primers P1 and P6. After ampli-
fication, the PCR products were purified using a PCR 
clean-up kit (Promega) before being used in the cell-free 
protein synthesis reactions. </p>

<p>Cell-free protein synthesis and analysis of 
the expressed proteins </p>

<p>The standard reaction mixture for cell-free protein synthesis 
consisted of the following components at a final volume 
of 15 ml: 57 mM Hepes-KOH (pH 8.2), 1.2 mM ATP, 
0.85 mM each of CTP, GTP and UTP, 2 mM DTT, 
0.17 mg/ml E.coli total tRNA mixture (from strain MRE600), 
0.64 mM cAMP, 90 mM potassium glutamate, 80 mM 
ammonium acetate, 12 mM magnesium acetate, 34 mg/ml 
L-5-formyl-5,6,7,8-tetrahydrofolic acid (folinic acid), 1.0 mM 
each of 20 amino acids, 2% polyethylene glycol (PEG) 8000, 
67 mM creatine phosphate (CP), 3.2 mg/ml creatine kinase 
(CK), 0.01 mM L-[U-
14 C]leucine (11.9 GBq/mmol, 
Amersham Biosciences), 6.7 mg/ml DNA, 4 ml of S30 
extract. The cell-free synthesized protein was quantified by 
measuring the TCA-precipitated radioactivity using a liquid 
scintillation counter (WALLAC 1410), as described else-</p>

<p>Table 1. Strains and plasmids used in this study </p>

<p>Bacterial strains 
JM109 
e14 </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>(McrA </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>) recA1 endA1 gyrA96 thi-1 hsdR17 (r K 
-m K 
+ ) 
supE44 relA1 D(lac-proAB) [F' traD36 proAB lacI 
q ZDM15] </p>

<p>Laboratory stock </p>

<p>BL21 starÔ(DE3) 
F 
-ompT hsdS B (r B 
-m B 
-) gal dcm rne131 
Invitrogen 
Plasmids </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>pIVEX2.3d 
Ampicillin resistant, C-terminal His-tag 
Roche Applied Sciences 
pK7hEPO 
EPO (501 bp) cloned into NdeI/SalI sites 
(18) 
pK7pelBss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of pelB (66 bp) 
This study 
pK7ompAss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of ompA (63 bp) 
This study 
pK7phoAss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of phoA (63 bp) 
This study 
pK7malEss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of malE (78 bp) 
This study 
pK7ompCss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of ompC (63 bp) 
This study 
pK7ompTss-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of ompT (60 bp) 
This study 
pK7heposs-EPO 
pK7EPO derivative containing the signal peptide sequence of human EPO (81 bp) 
This study </p>

<p>a All the pK7 plasmids have kanamycin resistance and the same 5 
0 -UTR sequences including T7 promoter and RBS. </p>

<p>e21 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 </p>

<p>
where (15). The size of the cell-free synthesized protein was 
analyzed by western blotting after running the reac-
tion samples on a 13% Tricine-SDS-polyacrylamide gel, as 
described by Schagger and von Jagow (19). </p>

<p>Removal of the signal peptide from the expressed 
fusion proteins </p>

<p>The signal peptides were removed in situ by carrying out 
cell-free protein synthesis in the presence of different concen-
trations of Triton X-100 (0.01%-0.5%, w/v) from the start of 
incubation in order for the N-terminal signal peptide to be 
cleaved-off immediately after its translation in the reaction 
mixture. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Optimized biochemical conditions are not sufficient 
for the efficient cell-free expression of many ORFs </p>

<p>It was previously reported that the efficiency of cell-free 
protein synthesis is improved remarkably when the reaction 
mixture is supplied with sufficient amounts of energy and 
substrates (9). For example, in reactions utilizing creatine 
phosphate for the continuous regeneration of ATP, the use 
of an excess amount of creatine phosphate enabled prolonged 
protein synthesis provided that the reaction mixture was sup-
plied periodically with fresh magnesium ions to compensate 
for their loss through the formation of insoluble magnesium 
phosphates. Using this approach, as much as 1.2 mg/ml of 
chloramphenicol acetyltransferase (CAT) could be produced 
from a single batch reaction of cell-free protein synthesis. 
An increase in the productivity of many other proteins was </p>

<p>also shown after improving the supply of ATP and amino 
acids (9). 
However, the provision of optimal biochemical conditions 
does not always enhance the productivity of cell-free protein 
synthesis. For example, the expression level of hEPO was not 
affected significantly in the presence of the elevated levels of 
ATP and amino acids, and remained at &lt;100 mg/ml. Since 
all of our ORFs were routinely cloned in the same expression 
vectors (pK7 and pIVEX2.3d) (9,18), such a discrepancy 
would be due to the nature of the nucleotide sequences of 
the structural genes. </p>

<p>Signal peptide sequences-mediated stimulation of 
protein expression </p>

<p>With respect to the effect of the sequence elements on the 
efficiency of gene expression, many recent reports strongly 
suggest that the translational efficiency of a gene is deter-
mined primarily by the nature of the initial nucleotide 
sequences. For example, Stenström and Isaksson recently 
demonstrated that the translational efficiency of the lacZ 
reporter gene was critically affected by the identity of the 
first +2 to +5 codons (13). In particular, the expression 
level was dramatically changed according to which codon 
was placed at the +2 position. While the expression level of 
the reporter gene was strongly stimulated when the AAA 
codon was located at +2 position (11), the placement of the 
NGG codons (CGG, AGG, GGG and UGG) at the same 
position was associated with remarkably lower expression 
efficiency (12,20). 
Based on their results, it was assumed that the yields of 
otherwise poorly expressed genes might be stimulated by </p>

<p>Figure 1. Nucleotide and amino acid sequences of the N-terminal regions of the hEPO fused with the signal peptides. </p>

<p> 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 e21 </p>

<p>placing the optimal nucleotide sequences beforehand. It 
was also expected that such a stimulatory sequence could 
be used as a universal translation enhancer to increase the 
productivity of recombinant proteins. In search of the nucle-
otide sequences that possibly enhance the expression of 
their fusion partners, the <rs type="software">python</rs> script was used to analyze 
the codon usage in the entire E.coli genome. Interestingly, 
it was found that the nucleotide sequences of many signal 
peptides had strong bias for AAA as the second codon. 
Approximately 40% of signal peptides had the AAA triplet 
as the second codon (Table 2). 
According to the analysis reported by Sato et al. (21), 
&gt;10% of the E.coli genes use AAA as their second codon 
whereas the frequency of AAA triplet in the entire E.coli 
genome is 3.3%. It was also suggested that the higher fre-
quency of the AAA triplet at the +2 position is related to 
the translation efficiency of a gene. Therefore, from the 
exceptionally high frequency of the AAA triplet as the second 
codon, it was assumed that the signal sequences might work 
as a translation-enhancing element. 
Therefore, the genes of hEPO with different signal 
sequences were fused and experiments were carried out to 
determine if their presence affects the efficiency of protein 
synthesis in our cell-free synthesis system. The nucleotide 
sequences of the seven different signal peptides (pelBss, 
ompAss, phoAss, malEss, ompCss, ompTss, heposs) were 
fused to the upstream of hEPO sequence in the plasmid 
pK7hEPO, and the resulting constructs were expressed in 
the reaction mixture for cell-free protein synthesis. As 
summarized in Table 3, the five signal sequences except for 
ompTss and heposs dramatically enhanced the expression 
level, yielding 9-10 times higher amounts of the target 
proteins (Figure 2). For example, the expression level of </p>

<p>hEPO was increased from 55 to 588 mg/ml through its fusion 
with the ompA sequence. </p>

<p>Effect of the identity of the second codon on 
the translation efficiency </p>

<p>However, not all the signal sequences were effective in 
enhancing the expression of the downstream ORF. For exam-
ple, the nucleotide sequence of the OmpT signal sequence 
(ompTss) failed to stimulate the synthesis of hEPO with the 
amount of the accumulated protein being similar to the 
wild-type sequence. Similarly, the addition of the natural sig-
nal sequence of hEPO (heposs) did not affect the expression 
level of hEPO. 
Interestingly, when the second codons of ompTss and 
heposs were switched to AAA (from CGG and GGG, respec-
tively), there was an 4-fold increase in protein synthesis 
(Figure 3A). In contrast, switching the second codons of 
ompAss and ompCss from AAA to NGG (AGG, TGG, 
GGG and CGG) almost completely abolished its stimulatory 
effect (Figure 3B). This suggests that the identity of the 
second codon critically affects the stimulatory effect of the 
signal sequences. </p>

<p>PCR-based addition of the stimulatory signal sequence 
and the direct expression of the amplified DNAs </p>

<p>Encouraged by the dramatic increase in hEPO expression in 
the presence of the signal sequences, this study examined 
whether or not the signal sequence-assisted stimulation of 
protein synthesis is generally applicable to the expression 
of other proteins. Sixteen different ORFs that normally 
show a very low expression level in our cell-free protein syn-
thesis system were selected. Instead of cloning each of the 
fusion constructs in the expression vector, the PCR-amplified 
DNA with or without the ompAss were used directly as the 
templates for cell-free protein synthesis, thereby eliminating 
the time-and labor-intensive cloning steps (Figure 4). As 
summarized in Table 4, the presence of ompAss remarkably 
enhanced the expression of the target proteins in all the 
cases examined, which suggests that the proposed strategy </p>

<p>Table 2. Codon biases of the nucleotide sequence of the E.coli signal peptides </p>

<p>Sequence data 
Frequency of AAA 
codon at position +2 </p>

<p>Whole E.coli K12 genome 
440/4241 (10.3%) 
Unverified E.coli signal sequences 
22/45 (48.9%) 
Verified E.coli signal sequences 
16/54 (29.6%) </p>

<p>E.coli signal sequence data set were obtained from a signal peptide 
database (http://proline.bic.nus.edu.sg/spdb/). This database currently contains 
99 entries of E.coli signal sequences: 54 of the entries are experimentally 
verified signal sequences (the N-terminal amino acid residues were 
sequenced), and 45 are computationally predicted sequences (17). </p>

<p>Table 3. Expression level of the signal peptide-EPO fusion constructs </p>

<p>Plasmid 
Signal 
peptide </p>

<p>Second 
codon </p>

<p>Expression 
level </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>(mg/ml) </p>

<p>Relative level 
of expression </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>pK7pelBss-EPO 
pelB 
AAA 
569 ± 34 
10.3 
pK7ompAss-EPO 
ompA 
AAA 
588 ± 28 
10.7 
pK7phoAss-EPO 
phoA 
AAA 
515 ± 31 
9.4 
pK7malEss-EPO 
malE 
AAA 
524 ± 13 
9.5 
pK7ompCss-EPO 
ompC 
AAA 
522 ± 24 
9.5 
pK7ompTss-EPO 
ompT 
CGG 
107 ± 17 
1.9 
pK7heposs-EPO 
heposs 
GGG 
101 ± 13 
1.8 </p>

<p>a Data from three independent experiments. 
b Expression level as compared with the expression of the wild-type EPO 
(EPO expression level ¼ 1; EPO expression level ¼ 55 mg/ml) </p>

<p>Figure 2. SDS-PAGE analysis of the cell-free synthesized hEPOs fused with 
different signal peptides. The reaction mixture was incubated at 37 
C for 2 h. 
The reaction mixture (2 ml) was loaded on a 13% Tricine-SDS-PAGE gel 
and stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue. </p>

<p>e21 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 </p>

<p>
can be employed as a general method for boosting the expres-
sion of the recombinant proteins in a cell-free protein synthe-
sis system. However, the extent of stimulation showed 
significant variations among different proteins implying that 
the expression of protein can also be substantially affected 
by the nucleotide sequences of the target ORFs. </p>

<p>In situ cleavage of signal peptide in an E.coli 
cell-free protein synthesis system </p>

<p>Although it was shown that the presence of ompAss dramati-
cally enhances the expression of the recombinant proteins, 
it also adds 21 non-native amino acid residues to the target 
proteins that might interfere with the biological functions </p>

<p>and proper folding of the expressed proteins. Therefore, it 
would be desirable if the signal peptides are removed during 
protein synthesis so that the resulting polypeptide of the 
target protein follows its natural folding pathway. Since the 
reactions of cell-free protein synthesis are carried out in a 
crude lysate of E.coli (S30 extract), it was presumed that 
most of the soluble E.coli proteins are present in the reaction 
mixture. In addition, the signal peptidase of E.coli retains its 
activity even when it is detached from the cellular membrane 
(22,23). Therefore, the added signal peptide should be 
removed in situ by the endogenous signal peptidase activity. 
As shown in Figure 5A, SDS-PAGE and western blot anal-
yses confirmed that a significant proportion of the cell-free </p>

<p>Figure 3. Effect of the expression level of the fused proteins according to the 
identity of the second codon. The efficiency of cell-free protein synthesis was 
enhanced by switching the second codon of ompTss and heposs into AAA 
(A). In contrast, protein synthesis was repressed when the second codons 
(AAA) of ompAss and ompCss were mutated into NGG codons (AGG, TGG, 
GGG and CGG) (B). After 2 h incubation, 15 ml of the reaction samples 
were withdrawn from the reaction mixture, and the [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]leucine-labeled 
radioactivity was measured as described in Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Construction and expression of the linear expression templates 
by PCR. (A) Schematic diagram of the PCR-based generation of the ompA 
fusion constructs. Three primary PCR products with defined overlapping ends 
were synthesized by the first PCR. These three fragments were joined in the 
second PCR, overlap extension PCR, which also simultaneously introduced 
the regulatory elements and the OmpA signal peptide sequence to the target 
genes. The red bar indicates the overlapping region. The blue and black bar 
indicate UTR and ORF, respectively. (B) Agarose gel electrophoresis of the 
PCR products. Second PCR products have an additional 600 bp as a result of 
the fusion with 5 
0 -UTR and 3 
0 -UTR. (C) Cell-free expression of ompA-fused 
PCR products. The reaction mixture for cell-free protein synthesis was 
prepared as described in Materials and Methods. After 2 h of incubation, 2 ml 
of the reaction mixture was loaded on a 13% Tricine-SDS-PAGE gel and 
stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue. Cell-free expressed proteins are 
indicated by arrows. </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 8 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 e21 </p>

<p>expressed protein had the native size without the signal 
peptide. This indicates that the S30 extract retains the signal 
peptidase activity under the reaction conditions for cell-free 
protein synthesis. 
Tschantz et al. reported that the catalytic activity of truncated 
E.coli signal peptidase, which lacks the membrane-anchoring </p>

<p>domain, was stimulated in the presence of the detergent 
Triton X-100 (22,24). By taking advantage of the 'open' 
nature of cell-free protein synthesis, an attempt was made 
to express the ompAss-hEPO construct in the presence of 
Triton X-100 with the anticipation that the enhanced signal 
peptidase activity would increase the fraction of the correctly 
sized product. Indeed, the efficiency of the cleavage of 
signal peptide was improved remarkably upon the addition 
of Triton X-100, and virtually all the products were found 
at the correct molecular weight (Figure 5A). When tested 
at different concentrations, the presence of Triton X-100 
&gt;0.1% (w/v) effectively facilitated the removal of the 
OmpA sequence, and virtually all of the cell-free expressed 
products were found at the native size of EPO. At least up 
to the concentration of 0.5% (w/v), the presence of Triton 
X-100 did not affect the efficiency of protein synthesis 
(Figure 5B). Therefore, enhanced efficiency of the cleavage 
of the signal sequence was not due to a reduced yield of 
protein synthesis. In addition, solubility of the cell-free 
expressed products was substantially enhanced in the pres-
ence of Triton X-100. While the EPO molecules (regardless 
of the presence of signal sequences) were almost completely 
insoluble in the reaction mixture without any detergents, 
70% of the expressed protein was found in the soluble 
fraction. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, it was found that the nucleotide sequences of 
signal peptides could serve as efficient downstream boxes 
to stimulate protein synthesis. When analyzed in a cell-free 
protein synthesis system derived from E.coli, different target 
genes showed increases in protein expression of 2.3-to 32-
fold through their fusion with the nucleotide sequences of 
the signal peptides. The stimulatory effect of the signal 
sequences appeared to be closely related to the presence of 
the AAA triplet at the +2 position. 
Based on this discovery, a method was developed to 
rapidly generate authentic protein molecules at elevated </p>

<p>Table 4. Cell-free expression of the ompAss fused genes </p>

<p>Protein 
Wild-type 
(mg/ml) </p>

<p>ompA fusion 
(mg/ml) </p>

<p>Relative level 
of expression </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>GenBank ID/references 
Molecular weight 
of protein (kDa) </p>

<p>Origin </p>

<p>IL-2 
91 
545 
6.0 
S77834 
15.5 
Homo sapiens 
TNF-a 
226 
513 
2.3 
X01394 
17.5 
Homo sapiens 
DsRed2 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>98 
665 
6.8 
-
25.9 
Synthetic gene 
BMP2 
128 
431 
3.4 
M22489 
13.0 
Homo sapiens 
UK 
83 
387 
4.7 
NM_008873 
30.5 
Mus musculus 
VEGF 
n.d. 
489 
-
X62568 
22.3 
Homo sapiens 
IFN-g 
45 
460 
10.2 
K00083 
16.0 
Mus musculus 
v-TACc 
125 
487 
3.9 
AAK25105 
47.8 
Caulobacter crescentus 
v-TAMl 
206 
537 
2.6 
BAB48961 
48.2 
Mesorhozobium loti 
v-TATr 
173 
436 
2.5 
AAL44116 
49.0 
Agrobacterium tumefaciens 
v-TAVf 
237 
539 
2.3 
(32) 
50.3 
Vibrio fluvialis 
v-TAXc 
198 
529 
2.7 
AAM41635 
48.4 
Xanthomonas axonopodis 
smTG 
11 
358 
32.5 
AAS68222 
45.7 
Streptomyces mobaraensis 
oleV 
35 
645 
18.4 
AAD55451 
53.1 
Streptomyces antibioticus 
oleW 
26 
689 
26.5 
AAD55450 
35.8 
Streptomyces antibioticus 
urdR 
n.d. 
702 
-
AAF72551 
26.8 
Streptomyces fradiae </p>

<p>a The relative expression level was determined by dividing the amount of the ompA fused protein by the expressed wild-type protein. 
b Plasmid pDsRed2 is obtained from Clontech. 
n.d., not determined. </p>

<p>Figure 5. In situ cleavage of the signal peptides during cell-free protein 
synthesis. (A) The indicated concentration of Triton X-100 was added to the 
reaction mixture from the start of the synthesis reaction, and examined to 
determine it could increase the level of signal peptide cleavage. After 
incubation, the reaction mixture was centrifuged at 10 000 g for 10 min, and 
the soluble and pellet fractions were analyzed by 13% Tricine-SDS-PAGE 
stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue (upper panel) and western blot 
using the anti-EPO antibody (lower panel). P and S represent the insoluble 
and soluble fractions of the cell-free synthesized EPO, respectively. 
(B) [ </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>C]leucine-labeled radioactivity of the expressed protein was measured 
as described under Materials and Methods. </p>

<p>e21 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 </p>

<p>
levels. First, overlap extension PCR techniques were used to 
amplify the target genes in the fused form with the nucleotide 
sequence of signal peptide. The amplified DNA was then 
used to direct protein synthesis, and protein molecules were 
generated within several hours. In addition, by mimicking 
the in vivo process of the signal peptide cleavage, the target 
proteins were produced in their native amino acid sequences 
without additional signal peptides. 
Although the detailed mechanism of the signal sequence-
mediated stimulation of protein synthesis is not completely 
understood, it appears that the effect of the initial nucleotide 
sequences is not related to the relative abundance or stability 
of the mRNA species. Computational analyses of the mRNA 
structure did not indicate any notable difference caused by 
the presence of these signal sequences. In addition, among 
the gene constructs examined in this study, the relative 
level of mRNA with or without the signal sequence was simi-
lar (data not shown). Therefore, it appears that the initial nuc-
leotide sequence affects the process of translation initiation 
and/or the early phase of elongation (12,20,25). In particular, 
Gonzalez de Valdivia and Isaksson demonstrated that the 
presence of NGG triplets in the early coding region causes 
inefficient translation through an accelerated drop-off of 
peptidyl-tRNA (12,20). 
Although extensive evidence has been presented that entire 
codon context in the early coding region (from positions +2 
to +5) influence gene expression, the presence of additional 
AAA triplet at the positions +3 to +5 of ompTss did not fur-
ther increase the yield of protein synthesis in our experiments 
(data not shown). However, still, it might be of worth to note 
that some of the effective signal sequences have additional 
AAA triplet in the early coding region (e.g. malEss and 
ompCss have an additional AAA triplet at +4 position). It 
might be possible to further improve the effectiveness of 
the signal sequences by engineering the nucleotide sequences 
in this region. Apart from the precise mechanism of action, 
the use of signal sequences as a translation-enhancing down-
stream box offers distinctive advantages in cell-free protein 
synthesis. In addition to the remarkably enhanced expression 
level of the target proteins, the in situ cleavage of the signal 
peptides provides a simple way for removing the N-terminal 
methionine. The issue of removing the translation initiator, 
N-formyl-methionine or methionine, from a recombinant pro-
tein is often critical for obtaining active and stable recombi-
nant proteins (26-30). 
It is believed that these results can be further extended to 
controlling the expression level of genes. Using the signal 
sequences that have been engineered to stimulate protein 
synthesis at different efficiencies, a mixture of template DNA 
can be co-expressed to generate the proteins in the desired 
abundances. Such a system will provide an ideal platform 
for constructing an in vitro metabolic network. As demon-
strated by Ku et al. (31), the in vitro reproduction of a meta-
bolic pathway can be ideally used to further understand and 
optimize the production of metabolites. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Authors gratefully acknowledge the financial support from 
the Ministry of Commerce, Industry and Energy, Korea (grant </p>

<p>No. 10021962). We wish to thank Mr. Joo-Hyun Seo for his 
kind help and advice in the computational analysis of the bias 
of codon usage in E.coli genome. We also thank Professor 
Byung-Gee Kim for providing the transaminase genes. 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for 
this article was provided by Ministry of Commerce, Industry 
and Energy, Korea (grant No. 10021962). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>PAGE 7 OF 8 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 e21 </p>



<p>e21 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>