<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1802622" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>To determine the sequence specificity of dimeric 
Ss-LrpB, a high resolution contact map was con-
structed and a saturation mutagenesis conducted 
on one half of the palindromic consensus box. 
Premodification binding interference indicates that 
Ss-LrpB establishes most of its tightest contacts 
with a single strand of two major groove segments 
and interacts with the minor groove at the center of 
the box. The requirement for bending is reflected in 
the preference for an A+T rich center and confirmed 
with C·G and C·I substitutions. The saturation muta-
genesis indicates that major groove contacts with 
C·G at position 5 and its symmetrical counterpart 
are most critical for the specificity and strength of 
the interaction. Conservation at the remaining 
positions improved the binding. Hydrogen bonding 
to the O 
6 and N 
7 acceptor atoms of the G 5 
0 residue 
play a major role in complex formation. Unlike many 
other DNA-binding proteins Ss-LrpB does not 
establish hydrophobic interactions with the methyls 
of thymine residues. The binding energies deter-
mined from the saturation mutagenesis were used 
to construct a sequence logo, which pin-points the 
overwhelming importance of C·G at position 5. The 
knowledge of the DNA-binding specificity will con-
stitute a precious tool for the search of new 
physiologically relevant binding sites for Ss-LrpB 
in the genome. </p>

<p>Understanding the sequence-specific binding of a transcrip-
tion regulator is of central importance in order to unravel </p>

<p>the functioning of this protein in the establishment of the 
regulatory process. In vivo any sequence-specific DNA-
binding protein will also bind to pseudo-sites with a reduced 
affinity. These pseudo-sites nevertheless play an important 
role both thermodynamically, by setting the concentration 
of freely available regulatory protein and kinetically, by regu-
lating the rate of location of the specific targets. Furthermore, 
low affinity sites may have a considerable impact on the 
outcome of the regulatory response if they occur in proper 
juxtaposition with a high affinity site and are bound in a 
cooperative fashion. A detailed knowledge of the sequence 
specificity is therefore required to search for new binding 
sites and to distinguish between physiologically relevant 
regulatory sites and pseudo-sites. 
At the present time, archaeal regulation is still poorly 
documented. The lack of efficient tools in genetics and 
molecular biology, especially for hyperthermophilic archaea, 
constitutes a severe limitation for the analysis of regulator 
function and the identification of regulons, modulons and 
stimulons. Nevertheless, the (potential) binding sites of a 
handful archaeal regulators have been identified in upstream 
promotor/operator regions of their respective target genes 
through in silico or experimental approaches (in vitro or 
more rarely in vivo) [for a review on archaeal transcription 
regulation, see Ref. (1)]. Most of these sites are semi-palin-
dromic. 
Several characterized archaeal regulators belong to the 
archaeal/bacterial Lrp/AsnC family (2). Lrp-like regulators 
are widely distributed among archaea, but with the exception 
of LysM from Sulfolobus solfataricus, the physiological role 
of these potential regulators in archaea remains mainly 
elusive (3). Lrp-like proteins show a variable degree of 
amino acid sequence identity, but share the same fundamental 
architecture. Crystal structure determination has been done 
for the archaeal members LrpA (4) and FL11 (5), both 
from Pyrococcus species and for the bacterial members 
LrpC from Bacillus subtilis and AsnC from Escherichia 
coli (6). The N-terminal helix-turn-helix DNA-binding </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +32 2 629 13 42; Fax: +32 2 629 13 45; Email: dcharlie@vub.ac.be </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Published online 18 December 2006 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 623-633 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl1095 </p>

<p>domain is connected with a flexible linker to the C-terminal 
domain that shows a typical ab sandwich fold, also called 
RAM domain (regulation of amino acid metabolism) (7). 
The latter is involved in effector binding and oligomerization. 
In solution, Lrp proteins exist as dimers or oligomers of 
dimers. They usually bind cooperatively to operators carrying 
an array of degenerate semi-palindromic targets (2). 
Ss-LrpB is an Lrp-like protein from S.solfataricus. This 
regulator binds its own operator region at three similar, regu-
larly spaced 15-bp binding sites (8). The deduced palindromic 
consensus sequence, 5 
0 -TTGCAAAATTTGCAA-3 
0 , has four 
highly conserved base pairs (in bold) in each half-site and a 
5-bp long central region exclusively composed of weak base 
pair. A recent AFM (atomic force microscopy) study of Ss-
LrpB:operator complexes indicates that each binding site is 
contacted by an Ss-LrpB dimer (9). Furthermore, 
occupation of the three binding sites results in the formation 
of a globular complex in which $100 bp of the operator DNA 
are wrapped around the interacting regulator molecules. 
The DNA-binding sequence specificity of a regulator can 
be determined by using the SELEX strategy (systematic 
evolution of ligands by exponential enrichment) (10). This 
technique will select a set of high affinity DNA sites that 
define a consensus-binding sequence for the protein. It has 
been applied for the Lrp-like regulators E.coli Lrp and Ptr1 
and Ptr2 from Methanocaldococcus jannaschii (11,12). In 
the present study we have followed another strategy. We 
determined the DNA-binding sequence specificity of 
Ss-LrpB by measuring the in vitro binding to a set of mutated 
variants of the idealized symmetrical consensus box. This 
was done systematically for all possible single base pair 
substitutions of one half of the binding site (saturation muta-
genesis) and also for targets containing an abasic position or a 
non-canonical base: inosine, uracil, 5-methyl cytosine or 
2-aminopurine. The importance of the spacing between the 
two consensus-half-sites was assessed by including single 
and double base pair deletions and insertions. Binding 
profiles were constructed based on electrophoretic mobility 
shift assay (EMSA) experiments, allowing an estimation of 
the apparent binding equilibrium dissociation constants 
(K D ). The quantitative binding data from the saturation 
mutants were represented in an energy normalized sequence 
logo (13,14). Combined with the results of a high resolution 
contact probing analysis of the Ss-LrpB:consensus box inter-
action, this provides a detailed view of how each base pair 
energetically contributes to the specific binding. Such an 
extended and detailed experimental analysis had not yet 
been performed for an archaeal regulator or a bacterial/ 
archaeal Lrp-like regulator. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Protein purification </p>

<p>Recombinant Ss-LrpB protein was produced in E.coli and 
purified by a combination of heat treatment and ion exchange 
chromatography as described previously (9). The protein 
concentration was determined by a MicroBCA assay (Pierce). 
The purified protein was divided into small aliquots, which 
were frozen and thawed individually before each EMSA 
experiment. </p>

<p>Footprinting and binding interference analysis </p>

<p>Footprinting and binding interference analysis were 
performed with a 150-bp DNA fragment with the consensus 
box near the center. This fragment was generated by PCR 
using the plasmid pBendCon as template and the oligonu-
cleotides EP9 and EP10 as primers (8). PCRs were performed 
by using ReadyMix Taq PCR Mix (Sigma-Aldrich). One of 
the oligonucleotides was 5 
0 end labeled with [g-
32 P]ATP 
(GE Healthcare Bio-Sciences) and T4 polynucleotide kinase 
(Roche). The resulting DNA fragments (either top strand or 
bottom strand labeled) were purified by PAGE prior to 
analysis. 
DNase I footprinting (15), in-gel Cu-OP footprinting (8) 
and premethylation, deoxyuridine substitution, depurination 
and depyrimidation binding interference experiments (16) 
were all performed as described previously. All binding reac-
tions were done in LrpB binding buffer [20 mM Tris-HCl 
(pH 8.0), 1 mM MgCl 2 , 0.1 mM dithiothreitol, 12.5% 
glycerol, 50 mM NaCl and 0.4 mM EDTA]. Using chemical 
sequencing reference ladders were generated (17). </p>

<p>EMSA </p>

<p>EMSA experiments were performed either with the labeled 
150-bp fragment, as described above, or with 45-bp oligonu-
cleotide duplexes (annealing of complementary oligonu-
cleotides) of which one oligonucleotide was 5 
0 end labeled 
with [g-
32 P]-ATP and T4 polynucleotide kinase (Roche). 
The latter applies for all mutated variants of the consensus 
box. These 45-bp oligonucleotides contain the wild-type 
(TAAAAAGGCATTATCTTGCAAAATTTGCAATAATC-
CTTTTATGTT) or mutated consensus sequence starting at 
position 16, preceded and followed respectively by 15-bp 
of the sequences upstream and downstream of the naturally 
occuring strong Box1 in the Ss-lrpB promotor/operator region. 
All oligonucleotides have been purchased from Sigma-Aldrich, 
except the abasic variants (Eurogentec) and the 2-aminopurine 
variant (VBC Biotech Services GmbH). 
EMSAs were performed as described previously (15). 
All binding reactions proceeded at 37 
C in LrpB binding buffer 
(see above) and in the presence of a large excess of non-specific 
competitor DNA (25 mg/ml sonicated herring sperm DNA). </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>All EMSA autoradiographs were scanned and the integrated 
band intensities were quantified using the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Intelligent 
Quantifier</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Bio Image</rs>). For each lane, the back-
ground intensity was also measured and subtracted from the 
band intensities. Only the integrated intensities (I.I.) from 
the unbound DNA bands were considered for further analysis 
because of the 'smearing' effect. All I.I. values where divided 
by the average of two I.I. measurements of free DNA (with-
out addition of Ss-LrpB). This corresponds to the fraction of 
unbound DNA. The fraction of bound DNA in each lane was 
then calculated to be: fraction bound DNA ¼ 1 À fraction 
unbound DNA. These quantitated data were plotted versus 
Ss-LrpB concentration (binding profile) and fitted using the 
Hill equation (Origin, non-linear least squares method): </p>

<p>Fraction bound DNA ¼ v max · ½Ss-LrpB 
n /ðk 
n ½Ss-LrpB 
n Þ 1 </p>



<p>In this equation, n corresponds to the Hill coefficient, which 
is a measure of binding cooperativity. In several cases, v max 
was &lt;1 and therefore k did not equal the apparent K D . The 
apparent K D was instead determined to be the protein concen-
tration at which the fraction of bound DNA equals 
0.5. EMSAs were repeated several times (at least twice, 
mostly four times) for each oligonucleotide duplex variant. 
Visible outliers, due to experimental errors such as pipetting 
errors, were omitted prior to plotting. Typically, K D values 
determined from EMSA experiments can vary by as much 
as 2-fold (18). The largest source of errors in determining 
apparent K D values from EMSAs is the size of increments 
in the used protein concentrations. We have been particularly 
careful to keep these increments low, generally 1.5-fold, with 
a maximum of 2-fold. This led to variations comprised 
between 20 and 50% for good binding sites and to higher 
values for very low affinity binding sites. 
Sequence logos were constructed with the web-based tool 
enoLOGOS, using relative entropy [(14); available at http:// 
biodev.hgen.pitt.edu/enologos]. This tool was used to create 
a logo from the aligned forward and reverse sequences 
from the naturally occuring Ss-LrpB binding sites. A logo 
was also created based on the binding affinity data. A position 
weight matrix was constructed with binding energy data from 
the saturation mutagenesis analysis. Binding energies 
(expressed in kT units) were calculated to be: </p>

<p>E ¼ ln K D : 
2 </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>High resolution contact probing </p>

<p>Previously it has been shown that Ss-LrpB binds a 150-bp 
fragment bearing the consensus-binding site with an apparent 
K D of $20 nM (8). Here, the study of this interaction is 
extended by enzymatic and chemical footprinting and by pre-
modification binding interference assays (Figure 1). Ss-LrpB 
protected on both strands a 22 nt long stretch against DNase I 
cleavage. This stretch covers the 15-bp consensus box and 
extends 5 nt towards the 3 
0 end and 2 nt towards the 5 
0 end 
(Figure 1a and f). Protection on both strands is therefore off-
set by 3 nt towards the 3 
0 end; this reflects how DNase I is 
positioned in the minor groove and cleaves phosphodiester 
bonds on opposing strands across the minor groove. The pres-
ence of hyperreactive sites at the 3 
0 -boundaries of the consen-
sus box are indicative of Ss-LrpB-induced DNA deformations 
resulting in local minor groove widening. The limits of pro-
tection areas and the sites of reactivity and hyperreactivity are 
fully symmetrical (Figure 1f). This indicates that specific 
binding results in the alignment of the 2-fold symmetry of 
the Ss-LrpB dimer to the dyad axis of symmetry of the 
palindromic binding site. 
In order to obtain a higher resolution footprint, the nucle-
ase activity of the smaller 1, 10-phenanthroline-copper ion 
[(OP) 2 -Cu 
+ ] (19) was used for in-gel footprinting of Ss-LrpB: 
consensus box DNA complexes separated from bare DNA by 
gel electrophoresis (Figure 1b). This resulted in a protection 
area that is on both strands limited to the 15-bp consensus 
sequence (Figure 1b and f). Remarkably, in the DNase I 
and in-gel footprinting experiments the bare DNA showed </p>

<p>Figure 1. (a)-(e) Autoradiographs of various footprinting and binding 
interference experiments with the top strand labeled. The position of the 
consensus box is indicated on the right of each autoradiograph. The Ss-LrpB 
concentrations used in the DNase I footprinting experiment are indicated on 
top of the DNase I footprint (in nM, monomer equivalents). DNase I 
hypersensitivity is represented by an open circle (weak effect) or filled circle 
(strong effect) on the left side of the DNase I autoradiograph. The bar on the 
left side of both footprints corresponds to the protected area. For the in-gel 
Cu-OP footprinting and all binding interference experiments, the lanes with 
input DNA (I), bound DNA (B) and free DNA (F) are indicated. (f) Linear 
sequence of the consensus box (bold) and flanking sequences (grey) with a 
summary of all observations made in the high-resolution contact probing 
analysis. Position numbering is also indicated. The DNase I protected regions 
are boxed, the Cu-OP protection is indicated in gray. Circles represent effects 
observed in the depurination (black) and depyrimidation (gray) binding 
interference experiments. Triangles represent effects observed in the 
premethylation binding interference experiments. Strong and weak effects 
are depicted by filled and open symbols, respectively. DNase I hyper-
sensitivity is indicated by a vertical bar with a circle, DNase I reactivity by a 
vertical bar. (g) Helical representation of the observed effects, with indication 
of the major and minor groove segments that are contacted by Ss-LrpB. The 
same symbols have been used as in (f). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 625 </p>

<p>little cleavage activity in the consensus box whereas the 
flanking sequences were cleaved more efficiently. This het-
erogeneity in the sensitivity to both the enzymatic and the 
chemical nuclease reflects local conformational variations 
of the DNA and suggests a narrowing of the minor groove 
in the A+T rich (73.3%) consensus-binding site (20,21). 
Critical base-specific contacts were identified by premodi-
fication binding interference experiments. These techniques 
are based on the creation of a pool of DNA molecules with 
on average one base-specific modification per molecule. 
Low and high affinity molecules are subsequently separated 
in an EMSA designed to result in $50% binding. Free and 
bound DNA are recovered from the gel, cleaved at the site 
of modification and analyzed by gel electrophoresis in dena-
turing conditions to distinguish positions that are crucial for 
binding from sites that are irrelevant (see Materials and 
Methods). Experimental results are shown for the top strand 
only (Figure 1c-e); a summary of all the effects is given in 
Figure 1f and in a helical presentation in Figure 1g. Methyla-
tion of the N 
7 atom (major groove) of any of four guanine 
residues (at the adjacent positions 4, 5 
0 and the symmetrical 
counterparts À4 
0 , À5) strongly inhibited complex formation 
(Figure 1c and f) indicating that Ss-LrpB makes strong 
major groove contacts with these parts of the binding site 
(Figure 1g). The methylation of the N 
3 atom (minor groove) 
of 12 adenine residues (positions 0, 1 
0 , 2 
0 , 3 
0 , 6, 7 and the 
symmetrical counterparts) resulted in a weaker but significant 
interference (Figure 1c and f). A similar effect was observed 
at two symmetrically related adenine residues juxtaposing the 
15-bp target. These results suggest local minor groove 
contacts, mainly in the central part of the binding site and 
near its extremities (Figure 1g), though it can not be excluded 
that some effects might be indirect and result from subtle 
local alterations of the helix induced by the methyl group. 
Base removal binding interference effects (missing con-
tact) are usually considered to represent direct effects, 
which imply that they reflect interactions established between 
these bases and the interacting protein molecule (22). Alter-
natively, indirect effects might occur owing to structural 
alterations or changes in the DNA conformability generated 
by the absence of a base (8,23). Based on the observed effects 
(Figure 1d-g) it can be concluded that the vast majority of 
the purine and pyrimidine residues of the consensus box 
contribute to Ss-LrpB binding. On the top strand the strongest </p>

<p>effects were observed upon removal of G À5 and any adenine 
of the stretch A À3 -A 0 and of T À7 , T À6 , T 1 , T 2 and T 3 . 
Removal of the adenine 5 
0 to the consensus box also inter-
fered with Ss-LrpB binding. Weaker effects were observed 
upon removal of G 4 , C 5 and A 6 . In contrast, the removal of 
C À4 and A 7 hardly affected complex formation. Therefore 
the inhibitory effect of premethylation of residue A 7 is likely 
indirect since it occurs in the minor groove, on the backside 
of the DNA molecule. The effects observed upon removal of 
residues of the lower strand provided essentially the symmet-
rical image of the results on the top strand (Figure 1f and g). 
It appears that Ss-LrpB establishes the vast majority of its 
tightest major groove contacts with one single strand segment 
in each half-site (Figure 1f and g). Generally, the results 
of the footprinting and missing contact probing assays 
performed with the consensus box are in good agreement 
with the results obtained previously with the array of three 
degenerate binding sites in the Ss-lrpB control region (8). 
Finally, random deoxyuridine substitution binding interfer-
ence experiments (24) were performed. Substitution of 
thymine by uracil, which corresponds to the removal of the 
C 
5 -methyl group in the major groove, did not impair complex 
formation (data not shown). This indicates that the methyl 
groups of thymine residues potentially contacted through 
the major groove (positions 3, 6 
0 , 7 
0 and the symmetrical 
counterparts at À3 
0 , À6 and À7) do not significantly 
contribute to Ss-LrpB binding. This is unlike what has been 
observed in many other protein-DNA complexes and is even 
more surprising in view of the elevated A+T content of the 
consensus box. </p>

<p>Binding affinity of Ss-LrpB to the consensus box 
depends on the length of the flanking sequences </p>

<p>The sequence preference of Ss-LrpB at all positions of one 
half-site of the binding site was studied with derivatives of 
a 45-bp duplex DNA (see Materials and Methods). The 
annealing of complementary oligonucleotides allowed to 
study in identical conditions all the substitution mutants, 
the abasic molecules and molecules carrying a non-canonical 
base. The apparent equilibrium dissociation constant (K D ) 
of the interaction was determined by applying the EMSA 
technique (Figure 2). This was done by quantitating the 
free DNA population by densitometry and plotting the </p>

<p>Figure 2. (a) Autoradiograph of an EMSA with a 150-bp fragment containing the consensus box. Ss-LrpB concentrations are indicated on top of the 
autoradiograph (in nM, monomer equivalents). (b) Autoradiograph of an EMSA with a 45-bp oligonucleotide duplex containing the consensus box. (c) Binding 
profiles of the two EMSAs shown in (a) and (b). </p>



<p>fraction of bound DNA versus the concentration of Ss-LrpB. 
As demonstrated previously, the EMSA can provide esti-
mates of the macroscopic binding constants of protein-
DNA interactions (25). The construction of a binding profile 
by fitting the Hill equation allowed us to determine the appar-
ent K D as the protein concentration required to shift a DNA 
fraction of 0.5. This also allowed us to determine the 
Hill coefficient, which is a measure of binding cooperativity. 
The affinity of binding to the 45-bp consensus duplex (K D of 
91 nM) was $3-fold lower than binding to a 150-bp DNA 
fragment bearing the same consensus-binding site (K D of 
33 nM) (Figure 2 and Table 1). Similar differences in binding 
affinity depending on the length of the flanking sequence 
have been observed in other studies (26). Footprinting experi-
ments (DNase I and in-gel Cu-OP) clearly indicate that the 
150-bp fragment does not assemble &gt;1 Ss-LrpB dimer. 
Therefore, the most plausible explanation of the size effect 
is that the flanking sequences provide 105 non-specific sites 
that contribute the equivalent of two specific sites. Further-
more, accelerated targeting by 1D diffusion along the DNA 
molecule and the possibility of having different dissociation 
rates from internal sites and the ends of the fragments may 
add to the observed differences in binding affinity to the 
105-and 45-bp fragments (27). 
The Hill coefficient was similar for binding to the 150-bp 
fragment and the 45-bp duplex, on average 2.4. This indicates 
positive cooperativity. Since Ss-LrpB binds to a single palin-
dromic site, this cooperativity might indicate the existence 
of an equilibrium between monomeric and dimeric forms 
of Ss-LrpB at low protein concentration. Indeed, although 
gel filtration and crosslinking experiments indicate that the 
predominant oligomeric form of Ss-LrpB in solution is a 
dimer (9), this does not exclude that dissociation might 
occur in the nM range. </p>

<p>Analysis of the binding specificity of Ss-LrpB </p>

<p>Complex formation was studied with a complete set of 
24 single base pair substitution mutants of one half of the 
symmetrical consensus box (saturation mutagenesis of 
positions 0-7) as described above. This allowed a detailed 
analysis of the sequence-specific contribution of each base 
pair to the interaction. An example of such analysis is pre-
sented for position 5 (Figures 3a-e). Average apparent K D 
values for all mutants are summarized in Table 2. In the pres-
ence of excess non-specific competitor DNA, binding to these 
annealed oligonucleotides rarely resulted in a complete deple-
tion of the free DNA population, even at the highest protein 
concentrations used and showed a more intense smearing, 
indicative of the formation of less stable complexes. As a 
consequence, the maximal fraction of bound DNA (corre-
sponding to v max ) in the Hill fittings is slightly &lt;1 in most 
cases and significantly &lt;1 in a few instances (very low 
affinity binders). 
None of the 24 single base pair substitution mutations 
resulted in a better binding of Ss-LrpB. Therefore, the 
consensus box appears to be optimized. In contrast, all 
possible changes except the A·T!T·A substitution at position 
0 resulted in a nearly 2-to &gt;100-fold reduction of the binding 
affinity (Table 2). A survey of the relative binding affinities 
(Figure 4) indicates that all base pairs of the consensus </p>

<p>contribute in a sequence-specific manner and to a variable 
degree to complex formation, but that position 5 is crucial. </p>

<p>Major groove contacts: hydrogen bonding at C 5 ·G 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>is crucial for Ss-LrpB binding </p>

<p>The saturation mutagenesis study (Table 2, Figure 4) clearly 
indicates that the C·G at position 5 is the most discriminat-
ing base pair of the Ss-LrpB binding site. Representative 
autoradiograms of binding to mutants of position 5 are 
shown in Figure 3a-d. Remarkably, substituting A·T for 
C·G almost completely destroyed binding. Even at the 
highest Ss-LrpB concentration used (16 220 nM), only </p>

<p>Table 1. Apparent K D -values of Ss-LrpB binding to the consensus box and 
derivatives thereoff as determined by EMSA; WT consensus </p>

<p>K D (nM) 
K Drel </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>45-bp duplex 
91 
1 
150-bp fragment 
33 
0.36 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>K Drel is the relative K D value compared with the K D of binding to the WT 
oligonuclotide duplex, which is 91 nM. </p>

<p>Table 2. Single base pair substitution mutants </p>

<p>Position 
WT bp 
Substitution 
K D (nM) 
K Drel </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>0 
A T 
C G 
348 
3.82 
G C 
260 
2.86 
T A 
109 
1.20 
ab T 
477 
5.24 
1 
T A 
A T 
168 
1.85 
C G 
218 
2.40 
G C 
217 
2.39 
2 
T A 
A T 
271 
2.98 
C G 
284 
3.12 
G C 
360 
3.96 
3 
T A 
A T 
801 
8.80 
C G 
664 
7.30 
G C 
488 
5.36 
4 
G C 
A T 
386 
4.24 
C G 
467 
5.13 
T A 
356 
3.91 
5 
C G 
A T 
&gt;16 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;176 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>G C 
7830 
86.0 
T A 
811 
8.91 
ab G 
399 
4.38 
C ab 
1447 
15.9 
ab ab 
&gt;11 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;121 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>C I 
115 
1.26 
A U 
645 
7.09 
C 
Me G 
184 
2.02 
C 2AP 
&gt;11 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;121 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>6 
A T 
C G 
465 
5.11 
G C 
450 
4.95 
T A 
281 
3.09 
7 
A T 
C G 
633 
6.96 
G C 
172 
1.89 
T A 
369 
4.05 
ab T 
214 
2.35 
A ab 
278 
3.05 
ab ab 
416 
4.57 
I C 
155 
1.70 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>K Drel is the relative K D value compared with the K D of binding to the WT 
oligonuclotide duplex, which is 91 nM. 
b Represents the minimal value. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 627 </p>

<p>some unstable binding was observed. The C·G!G·C 
mutant showed detectable specific binding, although with 
a strongly reduced affinity (86-fold increase in K D ). The 
smallest effect was observed with the T·A substitution 
(8.9-fold increase in K D ). </p>

<p>Hydrogen bonds are by far the most important sequence-
specific contributors to complex formation. Given the 
more extensive reorganization of potential hydrogen bonding 
groups when substituting T·A as compared with A·T for 
C·G (Figure 3a-d) one might have expected the latter to be </p>

<p>Figure 3. Examples of some EMSA analyses that have been used for the determination of the apparent K D 's. All the variants shown here are mutated at position 
5. Ss-LrpB concentrations are indicated in nM (monomer equivalents). If appropriate, the molecular structure of the base pair is also shown. (a) Autoradiograph 
of an EMSA with the WT fragment (45-bp oligonucleotide duplex). (b)-(d) Autoradiographs of EMSAs with saturation mutagenesis variants. (e) Binding 
profiles of the EMSAs shown in (a)-(d). </p>



<p>the less detrimental change. The opposite was observed: this 
appears to be due to a position-dependent inhibitory effect of 
the hydrophobic methyl group of thymine, as demonstrated 
with the use of uracil and 5-methyl cytosine substitutions 
(Figure 5a and b; Table 2). Uracil is equivalent to thymine 
but lacks the C 
5 methyl group on the major groove side of 
the base. Binding to the A·U mutant [7.1-fold increase in 
K D as compared with wild type (WT)] was much better 
than to the A·T mutant (&gt;170-fold increase in K D ) and com-
parable with the T·A mutant (8.9-fold increase). The substitu-
tion of C 5 by 5-methyl cytosine (C 
Me ), keeping the 
complementary G 5 
0 residue intact, resulted only in a 2-fold 
increase in the K D . Combined, these results clearly indicate 
the strong negative position-dependent effect of a methyl 
group at position 5 
0 of the bottom strand. 
The importance of the C·G base pair is also reflected in 
the results of the high resolution contact probing analysis. 
Both depyrimidation of C 5 and depurination of G 5 
0 strongly 
interfered with complex formation (see above). The respec-
tive contribution of each base to complex formation was 
further quantified with target molecules abasic for either 
one of these complementary bases or both (Figure 5e-g; 
Table 2). The removal of G 5 
0 resulted in a 3-to 4-fold higher 
K D than the removal of its partner C 5 . Binding to the double 
abasic consensus site was hardly detectable. This result 
emphasizes the overwhelming importance of G 5 
0 for the 
strength and specificity of complex formation. 
The strong inhibitory effects of depurination and of 
premethylation of the N 
7 atom of G 5 
0 suggest direct hydrogen 
bonding of Ss-LrpB to the N 
7 and/or O 
6 hydrogen bond 
acceptors on the major groove side of the guanine ring. To 
evaluate the importance of hydrogen bonding with the C </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>carbonyl of G 5 
0 we compared complex formation with targets 
carrying either 2-aminopurine (2-AP) or inosine instead 
of guanine (Figure 5c and d; Table 2). 2-AP lacks the 
carbonyl group on the major groove side of the base, whereas 
inosine lacks the exocyclic amino group on the minor groove 
side. 2-AP was highly detrimental for complex formation 
(&gt;120-fold increase in K D as compared with the WT) 
whereas, as expected, inosine had nearly no effect (1.3-fold 
increase in K D ). Combined, our results pin-point the capital 
importance of hydrogen bonding with the C 
6 carbonyl of </p>

<p>guanine at position 5 (and its symmetrical counterpart G À5 
0 ) 
in the site selectivity of Ss-LrpB. 
Arginine:guanine is the most common specific contact 
found in crystal structures of protein-DNA complexes, 
followed by arginine:cytosine (28). Furthermore, in 87% of 
the arginine:guanine pairs, hydrogen bonds are formed with 
the amide group of arginine and the N 
7 and O 
6 acceptor 
atoms of the guanine. Therefore, the C·G base pair at position 
5 and its symmetrical counterpart might very well be 
contacted by the side chain of one or more arginine residues 
of the recognition helix of Ss-LrpB. Ss-LrpB bears three 
arginine residues in its recognition helix, at positions 42, 44 
and 47. Of these, R 44 is highly conserved among Lrp-like 
regulators. Alanine substitution of these residues might pro-
vide further molecular details on the interaction of Ss-LrpB 
with position 5 of the binding site. It is worth noting that 
HTH motives generally do not interact in a one-to-one 
mode with their DNA target but rather establish complex 
patterns of interactions in which one base is contacted by 
different amino acids and one amino acid contacts several 
bases. </p>

<p>Major groove contacts: positions 3, 4, 6 and 7 </p>

<p>At position 3, contacted through the major groove, the 
T·A!G·C mutant showed the smallest reduction in binding 
affinity (5.4-fold increase in K D ), followed by the C·G 
(7.3-fold) and A·T (8.8-fold increase) mutants. This particu-
lar order in the base pair preference might in part be 
explained by the fact that the hydrogen bond acceptor 
groups of T and G are only slightly shifted in a G·C base 
pair as compared with a T·A pair, whereas they are com-
pletely rearranged in an A·T pair (see Figure 3a-d). Here, 
unlike what we observed at position 5, the hierarchy of 
relative binding affinities correlates with the degree of reor-
ganization of major groove constituents in the different 
substitution mutants. Otherwise, steric hindrance on neigh-
boring contacts and differences in the local groove geometry 
might also contribute to the observed differences in binding 
affinity. 
Replacing the G·C base pair at position 4 of the consensus 
box by any of the three other possible combinations resul-
ted in a similar modest effect (4-to 5-fold increases in 
K D ; Table 2). This observation is compatible with the higher 
variability observed at position 4 in the three Ss-LrpB binding 
sites in the control region of its own gene. 
Together with position 4, position 6 appears to contribute 
the least to the specific binding of all major groove-contacted 
positions. The A·T!T·A mutant showed the highest binding 
affinity (3.1-fold increase in K D ). Both the G·C and C·G sub-
stitutions resulted in a similar, $5-fold increase in K D . The 
A·T base pair at position 7 is also contacted through the 
major groove, as indicated by the similar relative binding 
affinities of G·C and I·C substitution mutants (K D of 
172 and 155 nM, respectively; Table 2). Nevertheless, the 
nature and the specificity of these interactions appear to be 
completely different from position 6 as indicated by the 
hierarchy in the binding specificities. At position 7, the G·C 
transition mutant had the smallest effect (1.9-fold increase 
in K D ), followed by the T·A mutant ($4-fold increase) and 
the C·G mutant ($7-fold increase). The surprisingly small </p>

<p>Figure 4. Histogram of ln(K Drel ) values based on the results of the saturation 
mutagenesis analysis (Table 1). The value of the A 5 mutant corresponds to a 
minimal value. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 629 </p>

<p>effect of the G·C substitution suggests that alternative 
contacts may be established upon the profound reorganization 
of the bottom of the major groove accompanying this 
substitution. 
The mild effect (2.4-fold) of a double substitution mutant 
with uracil instead of T 6 
0 and T 7 
0 indicates that the methyl 
group of these residues does not contribute much to the 
binding energy and sequence specificity of the interaction 
(Table 3). This result is in full agreement with the random 
deoxyuridine substitution binding interference experiments </p>

<p>(see above). The comparable mild (2-to 3-fold) reduction in 
relative binding affinity to the single and double (4.6-fold) 
abasic mutants (Table 2) indicates that the A and T residues 
of position 7 contribute significantly less to the binding energy 
and specificity than the G residue at position 5 
0 . </p>

<p>Minor groove contacts: positions 0, 1 and 2 </p>

<p>The positions that are supposed to be contacted through the 
minor groove generally had a higher tolerance to base pair </p>

<p>Figure 5. Examples of some EMSA analyses that have been used for the determination of the apparent K D 's. (a)-(d) Autoradiographs of EMSAs with an A·U bp, 
a C </p>

<p>Me </p>

<p>·G bp, a C·2AP base pair or a C·I bp, respectively, at position 5 of the consensus box. (e)-(g) Autoradiographs of EMSAs with abasic molecules. </p>



<p>substitution than the half-site positions contacted through 
the major groove (Table 2, Figure 4). At these positions, 
the highest tolerance we observed is to mutation in the 
opposite weak base pair (T·A to A·T or the inverse). This 
reflects the fact that a protein can hardly distinguish a T·A 
base pair from an A·T base pair on the minor groove side 
since their hydrogen bond acceptor groups (C 
2 carbonyl 
from T and N 
3 of A) will roughly switch positions. The effect 
of the A·T to T·A transversion was smallest at the central 
position 0 (1.2-fold increase in K D ). In fact, this base pair 
substitution leaves the 15-bp consensus box unchanged; it 
simply corresponds to reading the opposite strand. Therefore, 
the observed 1.2-fold difference in binding affinities reflects 
the experimental error and is within the error range observed 
in the EMSAs (see Materials and Methods). Both bases of 
this complementary pair contribute significantly to complex 
formation as indicated by the missing contact probing assays 
(see above). This was confirmed and better quantified for A 0 ; 
binding to the abasic 45-bp duplex occured with an $5.2-fold 
reduced affinity (Table 2). 
None of the three Ss-LrpB binding sites in the own control 
region has a strong base pair in the central part of the box. 
The apparent prohibition of strong base pair might be related 
to the exocyclic C </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>-amino group of guanine, which plays 
a dual role in DNA structure and recognition. The introduc-
tion of an NH 2 group in the minor groove results in groove 
widening and consequently in a decrease of the electrone-
gative potential as compared with weak base pairs. It also 
constitutes a steric hindrance for the compression of the 
minor groove upon bending of the operator DNA towards 
the interacting Ss-LrpB molecule (8,9). The need for bending 
of an operator site is generally reflected in the fact that there 
is a preference for A+T rich sequences at the midpoint of the 
target, where the minor groove has to be narrow. To evaluate 
the influence of the C 
2 -amino group of guanine upon substi-
tution of strong base pairs for A·T and T·A in the minor 
groove we measured complex formation with a pair of double 
base pair substitutions carrying G·C and C·G (positions À1 
and 1, respectively) and the equivalent construct carrying ino-
sine instead of guanine (Table 3). Inosine lacks the C 
2 -amino 
group of guanine on the minor groove side of the base and is 
also equivalent to C 
6 -deaminated adenine. Therefore an I·C 
pair resembles an A·T pair in the minor groove and a G·C 
pair in the major groove. The double guanine-bearing mutant 
exhibited an $7-fold reduction in the relative binding affinity 
compared with the WT; a similar effect was observed in a 
double G·C for A·T substitution at positions 0 and 1 
(Table 3). In contrast, the inosine bearing double mutant 
showed a 1.6-fold increase in K D , only. Therefore, inosine 
interferes significantly less with complex formation than gua-
nine. This result emphasizes the importance of minor groove 
geometry in the central part of the Ss-LrpB binding site. </p>

<p>Binding to insertion and deletion mutants </p>

<p>To examine the importance of the alignment of the two 
half-sites of the consensus box contacted through the major 
groove we studied the binding to insertion and deletion 
mutants (Table 4). These mutants had an insertion or deletion 
of either 1 or 2 bp in the A+T rich central segment contacted 
through the minor groove. The insertion of one extra T·A </p>

<p>base pair (ins1: in the stretch T 1 -T 3 ) still allowed the for-
mation of the specific complex, though with a 3.3-fold 
increase of the K D as compared with the WT. In contrast, 
deleting a single A·T base pair (del1: in the stretch of 
A À3 -A 0 ) completely abolished Ss-LrpB binding (K D &gt; 
11 000 nM; Table 4). A similar result was observed with a 
double base pair deletion mutant (A·T and T·A). A double 
base pair insertion mutant (consecutive A·T and T·A base 
pairs in the center of the box) resulted in a specific binding 
with a 11.8-fold increased K D . These results indicate a limited 
conformational flexibility of the Ss-LrpB dimer. Increasing 
the separation between the two half-sites contacted through 
the major groove, thereby disturbing the helical alignment, 
is tolerated to a certain extent. In contrast, reducing their 
separation (thereby inducing a similar rotation of $34 
per 
base pair but in the opposite direction) is highly detrimental. 
These results suggest that steric hindrance between the two 
subunits of the Ss-LrpB dimer might exclude the simultane-
ous binding of their HTH motives to the unproperly aligned 
major groove segments of the deletion mutants. </p>

<p>Energy normalized sequence logo-modeling </p>

<p>DNA-binding sequence motifs can be graphically represented 
by sequence logos, based on the information theory (13). The 
height of the stack of letters corresponds to the sequence 
conservation, expressed in bits of information. The relative 
heights of the bases correspond to their relative frequencies. 
Therefore, a sequence logo provides more information than 
a consensus sequence. Here, we generated two kinds of 
logos with a web interface called enoLOGOS: (i) based on 
sequence comparisons, (ii) based on binding energies 
(Figure 6a and b; 14). A sequence logo was constructed 
based on the three binding sites for Ss-LrpB in the control 
region of its own gene (Figure 6a; 8). An alignment of both 
forward and reverse sequences was used since Ss-LrpB binds 
as a dimer. Two corrections were applied in the creation of 
this logo: (i) A small-sample correction, since the information 
content tends to be overestimated in the case of a small </p>

<p>Table 3. Double base pair substitution mutants </p>

<p>Position 
Substitution 
Position 
Substitution 
K D (nM) 
K Drel </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>À1 
A T ! G C 
1 
T A ! C G 
638 
7.01 
À1 
A T ! I C 
1 
T A ! C I 
145 
1.59 
0 
A T ! G C 
À1 
A T ! G C 
580 
6.37 
6 
A T ! A U 
7 
A T ! A U 
221 
2.43 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>K Drel is the relative K D value compared with the K D of binding to the WT 
oligonuclotide duplex, which is 91 nM. </p>

<p>Table 4. Insertion and deletion mutants </p>

<p>Mutant 
K D (nM) 
K Drel </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>ins1 
299 
3.29 
ins2 
1073 
11.79 
del1 
&gt;11 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;121 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>del2 
&gt;11 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>&gt;121 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>K Drel is the relative K D value compared with the K D of binding to the WT 
oligonuclotide duplex, which is 91 nM. 
b Represents the minimal value. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 631 </p>

<p>dataset. (ii) A correction for background base frequencies 
in the case of genomes with a biased GC content such as 
S.solfataricus (GC content of 37%). The Ss-LrpB sequence 
logo confirms our previously deduced consensus sequence. 
Conservation is higher in the major groove contacted half-
sites than in the A+T rich center. However, since only 
three binding sites have been used to create the logo, its 
significance is rather low. 
In contrast, the saturation mutagenesis dataset used to 
create an energy normalized sequence logo is much larger 
and therefore more significant (Figure 6b). Full symmetry 
was assumed to construct the logo for the complete 15-bp 
binding site. The correction for the biased GC content was 
not applied since it is irrelevant in this case. Compared 
with the logo based on the natural targets, this 'enologo' 
has a higher resolution. The relative importance of a C at 
position 5 (and G at position À5) is highly emphasized. 
A cosine wave represents the twist of the DNA helix. 
Positions recognized in the minor groove have a maximal 
information content of 1 bit as opposed to 2 bits in the major 
groove (29). This is explained by the fact that in the minor 
groove a protein cannot discriminate weak base pairs from 
each other or strong base pairs from each other. Binding of 
the C 5 ·G 5 
0 base pair in the major groove is confirmed since 
the information content exceeds 1. On the contrary, based 
on our binding affinity data, the sequence in the minor groove 
is relatively less important. This is certainly the case for posi-
tions À1, 0 and 1, where little sequence preference is 
indicated in the logo. The total information content of this 
enologo is 7.2 bits as compared with 10.4 for the sequence 
logo based on the natural binding sites. 
The logo constructed with the binding energy data from the 
saturation mutagenesis analysis can be used to search for new 
high affinity binding sites in the S.solfataricus P2 genome. 
Assuming additivity, which is usually a good approximation 
in order to find new sites (30), the binding affinity of each 
sequence can be predicted. Nevertheless, setting the threshold </p>

<p>such that relevant high affinity sites are retrieved and 
the amount of false positives is minimalized, is a delicate 
and not so straightforward process. The algorithm will be 
designed to allow an extra 1 or 2 bp in the center of the 
box. The joint occurence of high and low affinity sites 
should also be considered. When correctly aligned the latter 
will be bound in a cooperative manner and consequently 
acquire a physiological role, as already demonstrated by the 
concentration-dependent formation of structurally very 
different complexes of Ss-LrpB with the control region of 
its own gene (9). 
Although our binding assays indicate that the consensus 
box bears the optimal base at each position, this does not 
necessarily imply that the consensus box is the best possible 
binding site. Some positions might be functionally interde-
pendent and therefore give rise to context-dependent effects. 
The tightest binding site could have been found by SELEX, 
but on the other hand this technique does not provide 
the energy landscape that was determined here. It is also 
worth noting that the consensus box does not occur in the 
S.solfataricus genome. This is frequently observed with 
regulatory sites. Tight binding and long half-lives of such 
complexes might be incompatible with the flexibility required 
to adapt to rapidly changing environmental conditions and 
microbial generation times. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by a grant from the Research-
Foundation-Flanders (FWO-Vlaanderen, G.0015.04), the 
Research Council of the Brussels University (OZR1184-
VUB) and the Vlaamse Gemeenschapscommissie. E.P. is 
holder of a PhD grant of the Institute for the promotion of 
Innovation through Science and Technology in Flanders 
(IWT-Vlaanderen). We also thank the reviewers for their 
helpful remarks and constructive comments. Funding to pay 
the Open Access publication charges for this article was 
provided by grant G.0015.04 of the Research Foundation-
Flanders (FWO-Vlaanderen). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 2 633 </p>

</text></tei>