<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1874646" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Efficient transcription in eukaryotes requires interplay 
between the RNA polymerase II (pol II) transcription 
machinery and factors regulating modification of the 
chromatin (reviewed in: 1). Tri-methylation of lysine 4 on 
histone H3 (H3K4) occurs co-transcriptionally (2) and 
is strongly correlated with transcriptional activity (3). 
H3K4 methylation is mediated by the Set1p histone 
methyltransferase (HMT) complex in yeast (4-7). In 
recent years, several factors required for this modifica-
tion have been identified. It is now apparent that 
ubiquitylation of histone H2B is necessary for methyla-
tion of H3K4 by Set1p (8,9) and of H3K79 by Dot1p (10). </p>

<p>H2B ubiquitylation is mediated by the Bre1p-Rad6p 
E3-E2 pair (11,12). 
The Bur1/2 kinase complex is involved in transcription 
elongation. This CDK-cyclin pair can phosphorylate the 
C-terminal domain (CTD) of the largest subunit of pol II 
in vitro (13), but it does not seem to contribute to CTD 
phosphorylation in vivo (14). This kinase complex is 
required for H2B ubiquitylation and H3K4 tri-methyla-
tion (15), which may involve direct phosphorylation of 
Rad6p (16). Interestingly, mono-and di-methylation of 
H3K4 are not affected by BUR1/2 mutations (15). Like 
the Bur1/2 complex, the PAF complex is implicated 
in transcription elongation and is essential for efficient 
H2B ubiquitylation and H3K4 methylation, but not for 
recruitment of Rad6p (17,18). The PAF complex 
consists of five subunits (Paf1p, Rtf1p, Ctr9p, Leo1p 
and Cdc73p) and interacts with pol II (19,20). BUR2 is 
required for efficient PAF complex recruitment to 
chromatin, but the mechanism by which this occurs 
remains unclear (15,16). 
The evolutionarily conserved Ccr4-Not complex is 
composed of nine core subunits and is implicated in 
various steps of mRNA production and processing 
(reviewed in: 21,22). The genes encoding the Not-proteins 
(NOT1-5) were initially identified as negative regulators of 
transcription initiation. Support for such a role was 
provided by the observation that several mutations in 
NOT genes suppress a temperature-sensitive allele of 
SRB4 (23), which encodes an essential subunit of the 
mediator co-activator complex (24). However, various 
reports also indicate a positive role for the Ccr4-Not 
complex (25-27). For example, this complex is required 
for transcription of RNR genes following DNA damage 
or replication stress (27). Genetic and physical interac-
tions of Ccr4-Not complex components with transcription 
initiation and elongation factors have been described 
(reviewed in: 21,22). Besides this, Ccr4p and Caf1p 
represent the major mRNA deadenylases in yeast (28). 
To further investigate the role of the Ccr4-Not complex, 
we performed a genome-wide screen to find non-essential 
gene deletion mutants that display synthetic genetic </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ31-30-2538981; Fax: þ31-30-2539035; Email: h.t.m.timmers@med.uu.nl </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>interactions with a deletion of NOT4. Here, we describe 
genetic interactions of components of the Ccr4-Not 
complex with BUR2 and BUR1. We found that the 
NOT genes are required to specifically facilitate tri-
methylation, but not mono-or di-methylation, of H3K4. 
Deletion of NOT4 reduced both histone H2B ubiquityla-
tion and PAF complex recruitment, but did not affect 
Bur1/2 activation or recruitment. Taken together, our 
results show a novel role for the Ccr4-Not complex in 
chromatin modification and suggest a mechanism by 
which it contributes to positive regulation of transcription. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Yeast genetics, media and plasmids </p>

<p>The yeast strains used in this study and their relevant 
genotypes are indicated in Table 1. Knock-out, TAP-and 
mycAVI-tagged strains were constructed by homologous 
recombination of a PCR product and verified by PCR, 
phenotypic and/or western blot analysis. Cells were 
routinely cultured in YPD or SC medium lacking the 
appropriate amino acids. The GAL1-LacZ fusion and </p>

<p>pGR422 plasmids have previously been described (29,30). 
The pRS306-based NOT4 integrative vector was 
previously published (27). </p>

<p>Phenotypic assays </p>

<p>Here, 10-or 5-fold serial dilutions of the indicated strains 
were spotted on SC-U À/þ 6-azauracil (6-AU) (100 mg/ml) 
or SC À/þ 5FOA (0.1%). For the 6-AU sensitivity assay, 
cells were transformed with pRS316. Growth at 308C was 
assessed after 3-4 days. </p>

<p>In vivo elongation assay </p>

<p>Cells transformed with the GAL1-LacZ plasmid were 
grown in SC-U medium containing 2% raffinose over-
night, collected and subsequently shifted to a medium 
containing 2% galactose. Samples were taken at the 
indicated time points. RNA extraction and northern blot 
analysis were performed as described previously (27). PCR 
product probes spanning the ORFs were radiolabeled 
using the Redi-prime II kit (Invitrogen). </p>

<p>Table 1. Saccharomyces cerevisiae strains used in this study </p>

<p>Strain 
Genotype 
Source </p>

<p>BY4741 
MATa his3D1 leu2D0 met15D0 ura3D0 
EUROSCARF 
KMY57 
Isogenic to BY4741 except not3:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY58 
Isogenic to BY4741 except not4:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY59 
Isogenic to BY4741 except not5:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY60 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf1:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY61 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf40:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY62 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf130:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY107 
Isogenic to BY4741 except ccr4:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY108 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf4:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY109 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf16:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY110 
Isogenic to BY4741 except caf120:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
MY1 
MATa ura3-52, trp1-D1, leu2::PET56 gal2 gcn4-D1 
(48) 
KMY102 
Isogenic to MY1 except not1-1 
Gift from M. Collart 
KMY114 
Isogenic to MY1 except not1-2 
Gift from M. Collart 
KMY103 
Isogenic to MY1 except not2:KanMX 
Gift from M. Collart 
KMY104 
Isogenic to MY1 except not3:KanMX 
Gift from M. Collart 
KMY97 
Isogenic to MY1 except not4:KanMX 
Gift from M. Collart 
KMY105 
Isogenic to MY1 except not5:KanMX 
Gift from M. Collart 
W303-1B 
MATa leu2-3,112 his3-11 trp1-1 can1-100 ade2-1 ura3-1 
(52) 
KMY2 
Isogenic to W303-1B except not4:KanMX 
(53) 
UCC7164 
MATa ade2D::hisG his3D200 leu2D0 lys2D0 met15D0 trp1D63 
ura3D0 ADE2-TEL-VR adh4::URA3-TEL-VIIL </p>

<p>Gift from F. van Leeuwen </p>

<p>UCC7183 
Isogenic to UCC7164 except dot1:KanMX 
Gift from F. van Leeuwen 
KMY81 
Isogenic to UCC7164 except not4:KanMX 
This work 
KMY161 
Isogenic to BY4741 except bur2:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
KMY162 
Isogenic to BY4741 except spp1:KanMX 
EUROSCARF 
YSB787 
MATa bur1:HIS3 ura3-52 leu2D1 trp1D63 his3D200 lys2D202 (pRS316-BUR1) 
(14) 
KMY140 
Isogenic to YSB787 except not4:KanMX 
This work 
KMY40 
MATa mfa1D::MFA1pr-HIS3 his3D1 ura3D0 lys2D0 can1D not4:URA3 
This work 
KMY133 
not4:LEU2 CTR9-HA6:TRP1, seggregant of YJJ1753 X not4:LEU2 (KMY73) 
This work 
KMY136 
Isogenic to KMY133 except not4:LEU2::NOT4:URA3 
This work 
YZS276 
hta1-htb1D::LEU2 hta2-htb2D HTA-Flag-HTB1:HIS3 
(9) 
YZS277 
Isogenic to YZS276 except HTA-Flag-htb1-K123R 
(9) 
YNL019 
Isogenic to YZS276 except not4D:KanMX 
Gift from B. Strahl 
YSB770 
MATa BUR1-HA3:TRP1 ura3-52 leu2D1 trp1D63 his3D200 lys2D202 
(14) 
YSB813 
MATa BUR2-HA3:TRP1 ura3-52 leu2D1 trp1D63 his3D200 lys2D202 
(14) 
KMY199 
Isogenic to YSB770 except not4D:KanMX 
This work 
KMY41 
Isogenic to KMY2 except not4L35A:URA3 
(29) 
KMY200 
Isogenic to YSB813 except not4D:KanMX 
This work 
KMY201 
MATa mfa1D::MFA1pr-HIS3 bur2D:URA3 his3D1 ura3D0 lys2D0 can1D 
This work </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2429 </p>

<p>Western blotting and antibodies </p>

<p>Samples were taken from cells grown in YPD, and extracts 
were prepared as described previously (31). Proteins were 
separated by SDS-PAGE and analyzed by western blot. 
Antibodies against H3K4me1 (Ab8895), H3K4me2 
(Ab7766), H3K4me3 (Ab8580), H3K79me3 (Ab2621) 
and the C-terminus of H3 (Ab1791) were obtained from 
Abcam. H3K36me2 (#07-369) and H3K79me2 (#07-366) 
antibodies were from Upstate Biotechnology. TBP anti-
serum was a kind gift from P.A. Weil. Antibodies H5 and 
H14 were used to detect the serine 2, serine 5 phosphory-
lated forms of the CTD of RNA pol II. The CTD-specific 
antibody 8WG16 was used to detect RNA pol II. TAP-
tagged proteins were detected using IgG-peroxidase 
conjugates. Antibodies against the HA-tag (12CA5 and 
3F10) or the FLAG-tag (M2, sigma) were used to detect 
Ctr9-HA, Bur1-HA, Bur2-HA and FLAG-H2B, respec-
tively. Immunoblots in Figure 2B were quantified using 
<rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> software and represented as fraction of WT 
after normalization on total H3 levels. </p>

<p>Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) </p>

<p>Cell cultures and extract preparation were essentially 
performed as described previously with minor modifica-
tions (27). Briefly, protein A-coupled agarose beads were 
incubated with the antibodies indicated above for 30 min 
at 48C, washed and subsequently incubated with extracts 
of cross-linked cells for 2-3 h at 48C. Beads were washed, 
DNA eluted and cross-links reversed at 658C overnight. 
DNA was isolated using a PCR purification kit (Qiagen) 
and analyzed by SYBR-green-based quantitative PCR 
analysis. Not4-mycAVI was purified using streptavidin-
coated Dyna-beads (Dynal) and subjected to stringent 
washing conditions (3% SDS in TE) before reverse cross-
linking. Further analysis was performed as above. Data is 
represented as percentage of input with a region from the 
HMR locus as a control. </p>

<p>Northern blot analysis and reverse transcriptase qPCR </p>

<p>RNA extraction and Northern blots were performed as 
described previously (27). Equal amounts of total RNA 
were used to prepare cDNA using random hexamers and 
the SuperScript II kit (InVitrogen) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. A dilution series of genomic 
DNA was used to determine the cDNA levels by SYBR-
green-based quantitative PCR analysis. </p>

<p>Tandem affinity purification </p>

<p>TAP-tag-mediated protein purifications were performed 
essentially as described (32). Briefly, 20 l of YPD culture 
was grown to OD600 $ 2-3, washed and lysed in E-buffer 
(20 mM HEPES-KOH pH 8, 350 mM NaCl, 10% 
glycerol, 0.1% Tween-20). Lysates were cleared by 
centrifugation in a Beckman 50.2Ti rotor (45 000 r.p.m., 
45 min, 48C). An aliquot of lysate was used for purifica-
tion over a 200 ml IgG sepharose column (IgG-sepharose 
fast flow, Pharmacia). Proteins were bound by rotating at 
48C for 2 h and subsequently washed with 35 ml E-buffer 
and 10 ml TEV protease cleavage-buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl </p>

<p>pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1% Tween-20, 0.5 mM EDTA and 
1 mM DTT). TEV protease (100 U) cleavage was per-
formed in 1 ml at 188C for 2 h. The TEV eluate was bound 
to 100 ml calmodulin affinity resin (Stratagene) in binding 
buffer (10 mM Tris pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgAc, 
1 mM imidazole, 2 mM CaCl 2 , 0.1% Tween-20, 10% 
glycerol and 10 mM b-mercaptoethanol) rotating at 48C 
for 1 h. The column was washed with 25-ml binding buffer 
and bound proteins were recovered in elution buffer 
(10 mM Tris-HCl pH 8, 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM MgAc, 
1 mM imidazole, 2 mM EGTA, 0.1% Tween-20, 10% 
glycerol and 10 mM b-mercaptoethanol). A fraction of 
the purified proteins was precipitated as described (33), 
separated on a 4-12% SDS-PAGE gradient gel (NuPage, 
Invitrogen), stained with Biosafe (BioRad) and processed 
for mass spectrometric analysis. </p>

<p>Tandem mass spectrometry </p>

<p>In-gel proteolytic digestion of Coomassie-stained bands 
was performed essentially as described (34), using trypsin 
(Roche). Samples were subjected to nanoflow liquid (LC) 
chromatography (Agilent 1100 series) and concentrated 
on a C18 precolumn (100 mm ID, 2 cm). Peptides were 
separated on an analytical column (75 mM ID, 20 cm) at a 
flow rate of 200 nl/min with a 60 min linear acetonitrile 
gradient from 0 to 80%. The LC system was directly 
coupled to a QTOF Micro tandem mass spectrometer 
(Micromass Waters, UK). A survey scan was performed 
from 400 to 1200 a.m.u./s and precursor ions were 
sequenced in MS/MS mode at a threshold of 150 counts. 
Data were processed and subjected to database searches 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Proteinlynx Global Server</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">version 2.1</rs> (Micromass, 
UK) or <rs id="software-2" type="software">MASCOT</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Matrixscience</rs>) against 
SWISSPROT and the NCBI non-redundant database, 
with a 0.25-Da mass tolerance for both precursor ion and 
fragment ion. The identified peptides were confirmed by 
manual interpretation of the spectra. </p>

<p>In vitro methylation assay </p>

<p>Set1p complexes (10-20 ml TEV eluate) from WT or not4D 
cells were incubated with 10 mg purified histones (Sigma) 
or 2.5 mg H3K4 (methylated) tail peptides (Abcam, 
Ab7228, Ab1340, Ab7768 and Ab1342, respectively), 
1.5 mCi 
3 H-S-adenosyl methionine in buffer (50 mM Tris-
HCl pH 8, 10 mM MgCl 2 and 10 mM b-mercaptoethanol) 
at 308C for 30 min. After separation by SDS-PAGE, the 
gels were dried and exposed to X-ray films. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The Ccr4-Not and Bur1/2 complexes interact genetically </p>

<p>To obtain more insight into the function of the Ccr4-Not 
complex, we performed a genome-wide survey to find 
synthetic genetic interactions with a null allele of NOT4. 
We identified several interactions with genes implicated in 
transcription elongation by RNA polymerase II (K.W.M., 
A.I. and H.T.M.T., submitted for publication). Most 
striking was the interaction between NOT4 and BUR2. 
Subsequent tetrad analysis of double deletions of BUR2 </p>



<p>and Ccr4-Not components showed additional synthetic 
lethal interactions with NOT2 and CCR4, but not with 
NOT3, CAF40 and CAF130 (Figure 1A). Notably, 
deletion of the gene encoding Bur1p, the cyclin-dependent 
kinase partner of Bur2p, results in a strong growth defect 
and this strain was not represented in the library used for 
the genetic screen. To test a genetic interaction between 
NOT4 and BUR1 in a direct manner, we introduced a 
plasmid-based WT or temperature-sensitive mutant of 
BUR1 (bur1-23) into either NOT4 or not4D strains in 
which the sole copy of BUR1 was expressed from a URA3 
plasmid (pRS316). Plasmid-shuffle analysis demonstrated 
synthetic lethality between a deletion of NOT4 and 
bur1-23 (Figure 1B). 
Considering that the Bur1/2 complex was found to play 
a role in transcription elongation (13,14), not4D and bur2D 
strains were first tested for sensitivity to 6-AU. In 
agreement with observations linking the Ccr4-Not com-
plex to transcription elongation (25), cells lacking NOT4 
or BUR2 were 6-AU sensitive (Figure 1C). Strikingly, </p>

<p>a strict correlation was observed between the 6-AU 
sensitivity of Ccr4-Not gene deletions and synthetic 
lethality with BUR2 (25). This suggests that this synthetic 
lethality may be due to defects in transcription elongation. 
To extend these observations, we investigated requirement 
of NOT4 for transcription of a long and GC-rich reporter 
gene. This experimental setup has previously been used to 
study transcription elongation defects (29,35). Figure 1D 
shows that in cells lacking NOT4, the GAL1-promoter-
driven LacZ reporter gene was inefficiently transcribed, 
whereas the endogenous GAL1 gene was expressed to WT 
levels. Taken together, these experiments show that Ccr4-
Not complex components genetically interact with both 
BUR2 and BUR1 and confirm a role for this complex in 
transcription elongation (25). </p>

<p>Efficient H3K4 tri-methylation is dependent on the 
Ccr4-Not complex </p>

<p>The Bur1/2 complex is implicated in the regulation of 
tri-methylation of H3K4 (15,16). The genetic interactions 
between NOT4, BUR2 and BUR1 prompted us to 
investigate the involvement of the Ccr4-Not complex 
in this process by analyzing global levels of H3K4me1, 
H3K4me2 and H3K4me3 using specific antibodies. 
Strains deleted for NOT4 or NOT5 displayed a strong 
reduction of H3K4 tri-methylation, but not of mono-or 
di-methylation (Figure 2A). However, deletion of NOT3, 
CCR4 or any of the Ccr4-associated factors (CAFs) did 
not give rise to this effect (Figure 2A). It is worth noting 
that several CCR4-NOT gene deletion phenotypes are not 
evident in not3D cells (26,27; Figure 1A and data not 
shown). 
To extend these observations, two mutant alleles of the 
essential NOT1 gene and deletions of the other NOT genes 
were analyzed in a different genetic background. Under 
permissive conditions, both not1 alleles displayed a clear 
decrease in overall H3K4me3 levels (50-70% reduction as 
shown by quantification of the results), whereas growth of 
these cells was not affected. Moreover, deletion of NOT2, 
NOT4 or NOT5 reduced H3K4me3 levels (86-94% 
reduction; Figure 2B). In contrast, only a slight decrease 
in H3K4me2 levels was observed in these strains (Figure 
2B). It has been reported that Set1p complexes lacking 
Spp1p are unable to tri-methylate H3K4 (36,37). We 
found that deletion of NOT4 or NOT5 resulted in 
H3K4me3 levels comparable to deletion of SPP1 
(Figure 2C). In addition, H3K79me2 and H3K79me3 
levels in extracts of CCR4-NOT deletion strains were 
essentially not affected (Figure 2D), although a minor 
decrease in H3K79me2 in cells lacking NOT5 was 
observed. As expected, deletion of RAD6 led to a severe 
decrease in H3K79me2 and H3K79me3 levels (10). 
These results suggest a specific requirement for the NOT 
genes for efficient H3K4 tri-methylation. Similarly, BUR1 
and BUR2 are required for tri-methylation, but not for 
mono-or di-methylation of H3K4 (15). Dot1p, the HMT 
specific for methylation of H3K79 plays an important role 
in silencing of genes near telomeres (38). Deletion of SET1 
results in a similar defect in this process (4,39). Notably, 
integrity of telomeric silencing was not affected by deletion </p>

<p>Figure 1. Ccr4-Not complex components genetically interact with 
BUR1 and BUR2 and play a role in transcription elongation. (A) 
Tetrad analysis of bur2D (KMY201) and BY4741 Ccr4-Not deletion or 
not4D (KMY40) BY4741bur2D diploids. Circles indicate double knock-
out strains. Relevant genotypes of the haploid strains obtained are 
indicated (B) Plasmid-shuffle analysis of bur1-23 and not4D double-
mutant strains containing pRS316-BUR1. Here, 10-fold serial dilutions 
of the indicated strains were spotted on SC and SC containing 0.1% 
5FOA. (C) 6-Azauracil sensitivity assay. Here, 10-fold serial dilutions 
of the indicated strains were spotted on SC-U and SC-U containing 6-
AU (100 mg/ml). (D) In vivo transcription elongation analysis of a long 
GC-rich reporter. BY4741 and not4D (KMY58) strains transformed 
with a GAL1pr-LacZ plasmid (pGR422) were grown in a medium 
containing raffinose and shifted to a medium containing galactose for 0, 
45 and 90 min. Northern blot analysis on LacZ and endogenous GAL1 
mRNA was performed using 18S rRNA as a control. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2431 </p>

<p>of NOT4 (Figure 2E). This is consistent with the notion 
that H3K4me3 is not required for telomeric silencing (37) 
and our observation that NOT4 is specifically required for 
tri-methylation of H3K4. 
Taken together, these results show that the NOT-
module of the Ccr4-Not complex is essential for efficient 
H3K4 tri-methylation but not for H3K79 methylation or 
telomeric silencing. </p>

<p>H3K4 tri-methylation on the PYK1 locus is affected by 
deletion of NOT4 </p>

<p>To investigate the role of NOT4 in the regulation of 
histone H3 methylation on active genes, ChIP experiments </p>

<p>on the constitutively active and highly expressed PYK1 
gene were performed using extracts of WT and not4D 
cells. Using specific antibodies H3K4me3, H3K4me2, 
H3K36me2 and H3K79me2 levels at the 5 
0 and the 
middle region of the PYK1 ORF were examined (Figure 
3A-E). Not4D cells displayed a clear decrease in the level 
of H3K4me3 at the 5 
0 end of the PYK1 ORF compared to 
WT (Figure 3B), whereas H3K4me2 levels were much less 
affected by deletion of NOT4 (Figure 3C). Further 
analysis showed that H3K36me2 and H3K79me2 levels 
were not decreased in not4D cells (Figure 3D and E). In 
addition, pol II occupancy was determined using anti-
bodies against the CTD of Rpb1p as a measure for 
transcriptional activity. In parallel, PYK1 and TUB1 
mRNA levels were measured by quantitative RT-PCR in 
WT and not4D cells. Both pol II association to the PYK1 
ORF and PYK1 transcript levels were diminished in the 
absence of NOT4 (Figure 3F and G). Extending on these 
results, we determined the H3K4 methylation status of 
cells deleted for NOT2. Indeed, examination of not2D cells 
confirmed a requirement for NOT2 in the regulation of 
H3K4me3 specifically (Figure 3H and I). Notably, 
essentially identical results were obtained when analyzing 
the PGK1 locus (data not shown), in line with a broader 
role for NOT4 in regulating H3K4me3 levels. 
To assess the direct involvement of Not4p in the 
regulation of PYK1 expression, ChIP analysis using a 
chromosomally expressed tagged form of NOT4 was 
performed. The encoded protein (Not4p-mycAVI) was 
biotinylated in vivo by co-expression of the E. coli-derived 
BirA biotin ligase (40). Phenotypic analysis indicated that 
the Not4p-mycAVI fusion protein was fully functional 
(data not shown). Streptavidin-coated beads were used to 
capture the biotinylated Not4 proteins from chromatin 
extracts of cells containing either a plasmid expressing 
BirA or an empty vector. Interestingly, Not4p was 
detected on the 5 
0 end of the PYK1 ORF and the region 
spanning the TATA box (Figure 3J), coinciding with the 
region targeted for tri-methylation by the Set1p complex 
(see Figure 3B and H). Taken together, these ChIP 
experiments confirm the specificity of the H3K4me3 defect 
and indicate that Not4p is physically present on the 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>region of the PYK1 ORF. In addition, deletion of NOT4 
resulted in decreased pol II occupancy and transcript 
levels, suggesting direct regulation of PYK1 expression by 
Not4p through tri-methylation of H3K4. </p>

<p>Decreased H3K4me3 levels in cells deleted for NOT4 
does not strictly correlate with a decrease in RNA 
polymerase II association </p>

<p>The exact mechanism of recruitment of the Set1 complex 
to transcribing polymerase is not fully understood. 
However, it has been suggested that phosphorylation of 
serine 2 and 5 of the hepta-peptide repeat of the CTD of 
RNA pol II is important for this (2,7). In this light, the 
global decrease of H3K4me3 in cells lacking NOT4 could 
be a consequence of a global loss of RNA pol II CTD 
phosphorylation. Immunoblot analysis using antibodies 
against phosphorylated serine 2, serine 5 or total RNA pol 
II (H5, H14 and 8WG16, respectively) did not reveal a </p>

<p>Figure 2. Specific requirement for the NOT genes for global H3K4 tri-
methylation. (A) Histone H3K4 mono-, di-and tri-methylation levels 
were determined in lysates from logarithmically growing BY4741-based 
CCR4-NOT gene deletion strains. Protein extracts of the indicated 
strains were separated by SDS-PAGE (15%) and subjected to western 
blotting using H3K4me1-, H3K4me2-and H3K4me3-specific anti-
bodies. TBP levels were determined as a loading control. (B) MY1-
based NOT mutant strains were used to determine H3K4me2, 
H3K4me3 and total H3 levels as in (A). H3K4me3 and H3K4me2 
levels were quantified using ImageQuant software and represented as 
relative to WT after normalization to total H3 levels. (C) Direct 
comparison of H3K4me2 and H3K4me3 levels in BY4741, not4D, 
not5D and spp1D strains. Analysis was performed as in (A). (D) 
H3K79me2 and H3K79me3 levels in the indicated BY4741 deletion 
strains. Analysis was performed as in (A). (E) Silencing assay using 
strains, containing URA3 in the telomeric region of the left arm of 
chromosome 7, lacking NOT4 or DOT1. Cells were spotted in 5-fold 
serial dilutions on SC plates or on SC plates containing 5FOA. </p>



<p>decrease of phosphorylation of these residues in extracts 
from WT and not4D cells (data not shown). This indicates 
that the role of NOT4 in regulating H3K4me3 levels is 
independent of RNA pol II phosphorylation. Arguably, 
the loss of H3K4 tri-methylation could be a consequence, 
rather than a cause, of decreased RNA pol II recruitment. 
To address this issue we investigated the HSP104 gene, 
which allowed determination of the level of H3K4me3 on 
a gene that is not decreased in transcription in not4D 
cells (data not shown). We observed a decrease of H3K4 
tri-methylation of the promoter region of HSP104, albeit 
less pronounced than what was observed for PYK1 
(Figure 4A). In addition, we found a small increase in 
RNA pol II occupancy, which is in line with a slightly 
increased transcription rate (Figure 4A and data not 
shown). Indeed, previous observations suggest that H3K4 
methylation is not a critical determinant of HSP gene 
expression (41). In conclusion, this result shows that a 
decrease in H3K4me3 in not4D cells is not a consequence 
of decreased RNA pol II association per se. </p>

<p>To further investigate the role of H3K4me3 in 
transcription, we compared the levels of H3K4me3 on 
the PYK1 locus in WT, not4D and spp1D cells. As shown 
in Figure 4B, this modification is decreased by deletion of 
NOT4 or SPP1 to comparable levels. In addition, deletion 
of SPP1 gave rise to a decrease in mRNA levels 
reminiscent of deletion of NOT4 (Figure 4B). Similar 
reductions of mRNA levels were observed for the PGK1 
gene (data not shown). This suggests that the diminished 
PYK1 and PGK1 mRNA levels are a consequence of 
decreased H3K4 tri-methylation. Taken together, these 
experiments show that the reduction of H3K4me3 levels in 
not4D cells is not a direct result of reduced RNA pol II 
association. </p>

<p>NOT4 is not required for HMT activity of the Set1p complex </p>

<p>The observed effect on H3K4me3 levels in not4D cells 
could be the result of NOT4 being required for transcrip-
tion of genes encoding factors essential for Set1p complex 
integrity or activity. For instance, deletion of SPP1 results </p>

<p>Figure 3. NOT4 is required for H3K4 tri-methylation but not di-methylation of the PYK1 ORF. (A) Schematic representation of the PYK1 locus and 
the amplicons used in (B-H). (B) ChIP analysis of the PYK1 ORF in BY4741 and not4D strains. Exponentially growing cells were subjected to ChIP 
analysis using H3K4me3 antibodies. (C) As in (A), using H3K4me2 antibodies. (D) As in (A), using H3K36me2 antibodies. (E) As in (A), using 
H3K79me2 antibodies. (F) As in (A), using CTD antibodies (8WG16). (G) Quantitative reverse-transcriptase PCR analysis of PYK1 and TUB1 
mRNA levels in BY4741 WT and not4D strains. (H) ChIP analysis of H3K4me3 levels in MY1 WT and not2D cells. (I) ChIP analysis of H3K4me2 
levels in MY1 WT and not2D cells. (J) Not4p is recruited to the 5 
0 region of the PYK1 ORF. Strains expressing mycAVI-tagged Not4p were 
transformed with a BirA expression plasmid and subjected to ChIP analysis. Signals were normalized to an empty plasmid control. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2433 </p>

<p>in the formation of a Set1p complex that is unable to tri-
methylate H3K4 (16). We investigated this by purifying 
the Set1p complex from WT and not4D strains via a TAP-
tagged version of the Bre2p subunit. In addition, we tested 
mRNA expression levels of Set1p complex subunits by 
northern blot analysis in strains containing or lacking 
NOT4. This indicated that neither transcript levels of its 
subunits nor composition of the Set1p complex are 
significantly affected by deletion of NOT4 (Figure 5A 
and B). Notably, the additional bands present in the 
purification from not4D cells were found to be non-specific 
lysosomal proteins (data not shown), which probably 
relates to differences in protein concentration between the 
extracts from WT or not4D cells. Using soluble histones as 
substrate in an in vitro HMT assay, no intrinsic defect in 
the methylation activity of Set1p complexes purified from 
not4D cells could be detected (Figure 5C). In addition, 
(pre-methylated) synthetic peptides were used to deter-
mine whether Set1 complexes purified from not4D cells 
were active in tri-methylation of a di-methylated substrate. 
Notably, Set1 complexes from WT and not4D cells were 
equally efficient in modifying this synthetic peptide 
(Figure 5D). 
Taken together, these experiments show that the 
mechanism underlying the H3K4me3 defect in not4D 
cells is distinct from deregulation of the Set1p complex at 
the level of transcription, composition or intrinsic activity 
and specificity. </p>

<p>Deletion of NOT4 reduces ubiquitylation of histone H2B 
and recruitment of the PAF complex </p>

<p>H2B ubiquitylation is required for efficient H3K4 
methylation (16). To investigate the role of Not4p in 
ubiquitylation of H2B, plasmid-based FLAG-tagged H2B 
was expressed in not4D cells. Ubiquitylated H2B could 
be detected in logarithmically growing WT cells, but 
H2B-ubiquitin levels were significantly decreased in cells 
lacking NOT4. As expected, ubiquitylated H2B could 
not be detected in cells expressing FLAG-tagged H2B-
K123R (Figure 6A, 39). Interestingly, Not4p contains a </p>

<p>RING-finger motif and displays ubiquitylation activity in 
vitro (K.W.M., A.I. and H.T.M.T., submitted for pub-
lication). Therefore, the H3K4me3 status was determined 
in cells expressing an inactive (L35A) mutant of Not4p as 
a measure for H2B ubiquitylation. The H3K4me3 defect 
of not4D cells was fully complemented by the L35A mutant 
of Not4p, suggesting that its RING-finger is not required 
for ubiquitylation of H2B (Figure 6B). In addition, in vitro 
ubiquitylation assays indicated that H2B does not serve 
as a substrate for Not4p (data not shown). 
In vivo, H2B ubiquitylation is dependent on recruitment 
of the PAF complex to chromatin (18). To assess the role 
of Not4p in the recruitment of the PAF complex, strains 
expressing HA-tagged Ctr9p and containing or lacking 
NOT4 were constructed. Ctr9-HA was expressed to equal 
levels in the two strains, whereas H3K4me3 levels were 
reduced in the not4D cells as expected (Figure 6C). 
Extracts were prepared from exponentially growing cells 
and subjected to ChIP analysis. Whereas Ctr9-HA was 
readily detected in the ORFs of PYK1 and PGK1 in WT 
cells, binding was severely reduced in cells lacking NOT4 
(Figure 6D and E). Taken together, these results show a 
requirement for NOT4 in H2B ubiquitylation and a role in 
the regulation of PAF complex recruitment to the PYK1 
and PGK1 genes to facilitate tri-methylation of H3K4. </p>

<p>The Ccr4-Not complex functions parallel to or downstream 
of the Bur1/2 kinase </p>

<p>Chromatin association of the PAF complex depends on 
the Bur1/2 complex (15,16). The requirement for NOT4 
for efficient PAF complex recruitment places the Ccr4-Not 
complex in the pathway containing the Bur1/2 kinase. 
To investigate this further, strains expressing HA-tagged 
Bur1p or Bur2p, containing or lacking NOT4, were con-
structed to determine occupancy of Bur1p and Bur2p. 
Expression of the HA-tagged versions of Bur1p and Bur2p 
was equal between WT and not4D cells (Figure 7A). ChIP 
analysis with these strains showed that both Bur1p 
and Bur2p were found to associate with the PYK1 and 
PGK1 loci with similar efficiencies (Figure 7B and C). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Decreased H3K4me3 in not4D cells is not necessarily due to decreased RNA polymerase II loading (A) ChIP analysis of H3K4me3 and 
RNA pol II levels on the HSP104 locus. Data are represented as relative to WT. ChIP efficiencies were 2-3% and 0.15-0.2% for H3K4me3 and 
8WG16 antibodies, respectively. (B) Deletion of NOT4 or SPP1 lead to a similar decrease in H3K4me3 and transcript levels on the PYK1 gene. 
Chromatin extracts of BY4741, not4D and spp1D strains were subjected to ChIP analysis using H3K4me3-specific antibodies. PYK1 mRNA 
transcript levels are affected by deletion of NOT4 or SPP1. PYK1 mRNA in total RNA of BY4147, not4D and spp1D strains was analyzed by 
quantitative reverse-transcriptase PCR. </p>



<p>In addition, NOT4 is not required for the activation of 
the Bur1p kinase since the active phosphorylated 
form of Bur1p is readily detected in cells lacking NOT4 
(Figure 7A). These results place the Ccr4-Not complex 
parallel to, or downstream of the Bur1/2 kinase and 
upstream of the PAF complex in a pathway leading to 
H3K4 tri-methylation. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The Ccr4-Not complex is involved in mRNA biogenesis at 
different levels (reviewed in 21,22). Here, we show that the 
NOT genes, in contrast to CCR4 and the CAF genes, are 
required for global and gene-specific tri-methylation of 
H3K4 (Figures 2, 3 and 4). In addition, we found that the 
Ccr4-Not complex is functionally linked to the Bur1/2 
kinase complex (Figure 1), which is also specifically 
required for H3K4 tri-methylation (20). The mechanism 
by which the Ccr4-Not complex is involved in this histone 
modification is independent of direct regulation of the 
Set1p histone methyltransferase complex (Figure 5). 
Instead, the Ccr4-Not complex functions parallel to or </p>

<p>Figure 5. The H3K4me3 defect in not4D cells is independent of direct 
regulation of the Set1p complex. (A) mRNA levels of Set1p complex 
components. RNA was extracted from exponentially growing BY4741 
and not4D and subjected to northern blot analysis using the indicated 
probes. (B) Subunit composition of purified Set1p complexes. Strains 
containing or lacking NOT4 and expressing a TAP-tagged Bre2p were 
used to purify Set1p complexes (upper panel). Equal expression of 
Bre2-TAP proteins was checked by western blot analysis (lower panel). 
The indicated proteins were identified using LC-MS/MS. Several 
additional proteins were present in the not4D purification when com-
pared to the WT. Mass spectrometry showed that these bands 
contained non-related lysosomal proteins. We consider this an artifact 
of the purification, likely caused by differences in the concentration of 
the lysates of the WT and not4D cells. (C) Histone methyl transferase 
assay using purified Set1p complexes. Increasing amounts of Set1p 
complex or a mock-purification control were use to methylate soluble 
histones (from calf thymus) in vitro. Samples were separated on a 15% 
SDS-PAA gel, stained with Coomassie, dried and exposed to an X-ray 
film. (D) In vitro methylation of synthetic pre-methylated histone H3-
tail peptides. Pre-methylated peptides were used as substrates for in 
vitro methylation using Set1p complexes purified from WT or not4D 
cells. Samples were separated on a 20% SDS-PAA gel, dried and 
exposed to an X-ray film. Signals were quantified using <rs type="software">ImageQuant</rs> 
software and represented as arbitrary units after background correction. </p>

<p>Figure 6. Deletion of NOT4 diminishes H2B ubiquitylation and PAF 
complex recruitment. (A) NOT4 is required for efficient H2B 
ubiquitylation. Extracts of the indicated strains carrying a FLAG-
HTB1 plasmid were separated on a 12.5% SDS-PAGE gel and 
subjected to western blot analysis using FLAG antibodies. The lower 
panel shows a shorter exposure of the same blot, indicating equal 
loading. (B) The ubiquitin-ligase activity of Not4p is not involved in 
the regulation of H3K4me3 levels. The H3K4 methylation status in 
extracts from cells expressing NOT4 or not4L35A alleles from the 
endogenous NOT4 locus and cells lacking NOT4 were subjected to 
western blot analysis. (C) Ctr9-HA is equally expressed in NOT4 and 
not4D cells. Strains expressing HA-tagged Ctr9p, containing or lacking 
NOT4, were used to determine Ctr9-HA levels by western blotting. 
H3K4me3 and TBP levels were used as controls. (D and E) NOT4 is 
required for PAF complex recruitment to the PYK1 and PGK1 ORFs. 
Strains from (C) were subjected to ChIP analysis of the PYK1 locus 
(amplicons are schematically depicted in upper panel). Exponentially 
growing cells were cross-linked and ChIPs were performed using 
anti-HA (12CA5) antibodies. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2435 </p>

<p>downstream of Bur1/2p at the level of PAF complex 
recruitment, resulting in decreased ubiquitylation of H2B, 
in cells lacking NOT4 (Figure 8). Taken together, our 
results provide a detailed study of the role of the Ccr4-Not 
complex in the regulation of global H3K4 tri-methylation. 
Further, they confirm a functional distinction between the 
cytoplasmic deadenylase activity of the Ccr4p-Caf1p 
module and the nuclear function of the Not-proteins of 
the Ccr4-Not complex (42). </p>

<p>Cooperation between the Bur1/2 and Ccr4-Not complexes 
in establishing H3K4 tri-methylation </p>

<p>The Bur1/2 complex was shown to be required for H3K4 
tri-methylation (15) and this involves phosphorylation </p>

<p>of Rad6p (16). The genetic interactions between genes 
encoding Ccr4-Not complex subunits (NOT2, NOT4 
and CCR4) and BUR1 and BUR2, suggest a role for 
this complex in transcription elongation (Figure 1). 
Interestingly, deletions of several Ccr4-Not components 
were shown to exhibit 6-AU sensitivity, suggesting such a 
role (25). Notably, a strict correlation between the 
published 6-AU sensitivity for Ccr4-Not components 
and synthetic lethality with BUR2 was observed. Since 
the Bur1/2 complex was shown to be involved in the 
regulation of H3K4me3 levels (15), we determined the 
levels of various histone H3 lysine methylation marks 
in cells lacking genes encoding Ccr4-Not components. 
In contrast to the NOT-gene deletion strains, decreased 
H3K4me3 levels were not observed in ccr4D cells 
(Figure 2), suggesting that Ccr4p and the Not-module 
contribute to transcription elongation by distinct mecha-
nisms. An alternative explanation could be that deletion 
of Ccr4-Not components and BUR2 results in partial loss 
of subsequent activities within the same pathway, 
ultimately resulting in the observed synthetic lethality. 
Insight into the mechanism by which the Not-proteins 
function in the pathway leading to H3K4 tri-methylation 
comes from the observations that PAF complex recruit-
ment and subsequent efficient ubiquitylation of H2B, but 
not Bur1/2 complex recruitment, are dependent on the 
presence of NOT4. However, other modifications such as 
H3K4 mono-and di-methylation or H3K79 di-and tri-
methylation were not affected by deletion of NOT4. These 
results suggest a model in which the pathways leading to 
H3K4 and H3K79 methylation bifurcate upstream of the 
Ccr4-Not complex and are in agreement with a recent 
report showing that BUR2 is only required for H3K4 tri-
methylation (15,16). Alternatively, the residual degree of 
ubiquitylated H2B that is observed in cells lacking NOT4 
may be sufficient to sustain H3K79me2/3 and H3K4me2, 
but not H3K4me3 levels. Support for this hypothesis 
comes from the observation that cells deleted for PAF1 
show significant levels of H3K4 di-methylation but not 
tri-methylation (43, data not shown). </p>

<p>Regulation of H3K4 tri-methylation by the Ccr4-Not complex 
and involvement of the PAF complex </p>

<p>The Set1p complex (or COMPASS) represents the sole 
HMT for H3K4 in yeast (4-6). The observation that 
transcription, subunit composition, activity and specificity 
of the Set1p complex are not affected by Not4p suggests 
that the Ccr4-Not complex functions further upstream in 
a pathway regulating H3K4 tri-methylation. The finding 
that Not4p is physically present at the 5 
0 region of the 
PYK1 ORF, coinciding with the H3K4 tri-methylation 
mark and the PAF complex, suggests a direct role for the 
Ccr4-Not complex in the regulation of this modification. 
Possibly, recruitment of the Ccr4-Not complex to this 
region aids localization of the H3K4me3 mark. Another 
important insight into the mechanism by which the Ccr4-
Not complex controls H3K4me3 levels comes from the 
observation that PAF complex recruitment is severely 
decreased in the absence of NOT4, whereas Bur1p 
and Bur2p recruitment and activation are not affected </p>

<p>Figure 7. The Ccr4-Not complex functions downstream of or parallel 
to the Bur1/2 kinase. (A) Bur1-HA and Bur2-HA are equally expressed 
in WT and not4D cells. Extracts of cells expressing HA-tagged Bur1p or 
Bur2p containing or lacking NOT4, or a non-tagged control, were 
subjected to western blot analysis using antibodies against the HA-tag, 
H3K4me3 and TBP. (B) Recruitment of the Bur1/2 complex to the 
PYK1 locus does not depend on NOT4. WT and not4D cells expressing 
HA-tagged Bur1p or Bur2p, and a no-tag control, were subjected to 
ChIP analysis using anti-HA (12CA5) antibodies (amplicons are 
schematically depicted in the upper panel). (C) As in (B), except that 
the analysis was performed for the PGK1 locus. </p>



<p>(Figures 6 and 7). The Bur1/2 kinase is known to act 
upstream of PAF complex recruitment (15). Thus, the 
Ccr4-Not complex could either act downstream of the 
Bur1/2 kinase, or in a parallel pathway to regulate PAF 
complex recruitment (Figure 8). It is interesting to note 
that both Not3p and Not5p are phospho-proteins (44), 
but the connection with Bur1/2 complex remains un-
explored. In the parallel pathway, the Bur1/2 and Ccr4-
Not complexes would act independently of each other in 
the recruitment of the PAF complex to chromatin. 
Strikingly, deletion of BUR2 or NOT4 results in only a 
partial loss of H2B ubiquitylation, PAF complex 
recruitment and subsequent H3K4 tri-methylation (15, 
Figures 2 and 6). 
Previous experiments have physically linked the PAF 
complex and Ccr4p (45). However, we and others have 
failed to detect PAF complex members or Bur1p/2p in 
Ccr4-Not purifications (46, data not shown). In addition, 
deletion of PAF1 gives rise to an HU-sensitive phenotype 
and deregulation of RNR gene transcription (47). 
Intriguingly, this was also observed for deletions of 
CCR4-NOT genes (27) and deletion of BUR2 (data not 
shown), suggesting a functional interplay between these 
complexes. Alternatively, alteration of other components 
of the histone code might also contribute to the regula-
tion of H3K4me3 levels by the Ccr4-Not complex. 
Irrespective of this, it is clear that further experiments 
are required to elucidate the connections between the 
Ccr4-Not and PAF complexes. </p>

<p>Positive and negative regulation of transcription by the 
Ccr4-Not complex </p>

<p>Our results support a global role for the Ccr4-Not 
complex in the positive regulation of transcription. </p>

<p>In addition, mutation of components of this complex 
results in derepression of a variety of genes (26,48). These 
seemingly contradicting observations may be reconciled 
by recent findings of recognition of H3K4-methylated 
histones by PHD finger containing proteins (49-51). These 
domains are believed to recruit chromatin-modifying 
complexes, like NURF and the mSin3a-HDAC1 complex 
to H3K4-methylated chromatin (49,51). Yeast contains 15 
PHD fingers residing in a variety of chromatin-modifying 
complexes and these motifs display different relative 
affinities for H3K4me2 and H3K4me3 (50). Specific loss 
of H3K4 tri-methylation could therefore shift the balance 
of chromatin regulatory complexes at particular genes. It 
is unlikely that the sole function of the Ccr4-Not complex 
is regulation of H3K4 tri-methylation via recruitment of 
the PAF complex. Besides the well-documented role of the 
Ccr4p and Caf1p subunits in mRNA deadenylation, 
multiple observations indicate that the Not-proteins can 
directly affect TFIID function (reviewed in 21,22). This 
suggests that the Ccr4-Not complex integrates several 
steps of mRNA expression. The functional consequences 
of Ccr4-Not gene deletions are likely to be gene specific as 
suggested, for example, by our results on the PYK1 and 
HSP104 genes. Taken together, these findings provide an 
explanation for the observation that the Ccr4-Not 
complex can have both negative and positive effects on 
gene transcription. 
In summary, we have identified a role for the Ccr4-Not 
complex in the regulation of H3K4 tri-methylation 
levels by acting parallel to or downstream of the Bur1/2 
kinase to facilitate PAF complex recruitment and sub-
sequent H2B ubiquitylation. These results provide a 
connection between the role of the Ccr4-Not complex in 
the regulation of transcription and histone methylation 
marks. </p>

<p>Figure 8. A model indicating how the Ccr4-Not complex may function in establishing H3K4 tri-methylation through regulation of PAF complex 
recruitment. The Ccr4-Not complex could be controlled by the Bur1/2 kinase to facilitate PAF complex recruitment (downstream). Alternatively, the 
Bur1/2 and Ccr4-Not complexes function in distinct pathways sharing several components and independently regulate PAF complex recruitment 
(parallel). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2437 </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Drs M. Collart, F. van Leeuwen, J. Jaehning, 
W.W. Pijnappel, S. Buratowski, P.A. Weil, G.P. Prelich, 
A. Aguilera and B. Strahl for generously sharing reagents, 
Drs G.S. Winkler and F.C. Holstege for critical reading of 
the manuscript and members of the Timmers laboratory 
for helpful discussions, technical advice and assistance. 
Drs N.J. Krogan and B. Strahl are gratefully acknowledged 
for sharing results prior to publication. This work was 
supported by grants from The Netherlands Organization 
for Scientific Research (NWO-MW Pionier #900-98-142 
and NWO-CW #700-50-034), European Union (Improving 
Human Potential RTN2-2001-00026 and STREP 
LSHG-CT-2004-502950) and EMBO (ASTF 184.00-02). 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charge was 
provided by the University Medical Center Utrecht. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 7 2439 </p>

</text></tei>