<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1933159" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:08+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We present <rs type="software">taveRNA</rs>, a web server package that 
hosts three RNA web services: alteRNA, inteRNA 
and pRuNA. <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> is a new alternative for RNA 
secondary structure prediction. It is based on 
a dynamic programming solution that minimizes 
the sum of energy density and free energy of an 
RNA structure. <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> is the first RNA-RNA 
interaction structure prediction web service. It also 
employs a dynamic programming algorithm to 
minimize the free energy of the resulting joint 
structure of the two interacting RNAs. Lastly, 
<rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> is an efficient database pruning service; 
which given a query RNA, eliminates a significant 
portion of an ncRNA database and returns only 
a few ncRNAs as potential regulators. <rs id="software-4" type="software">taveRNA</rs> is 
available at <rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http://compbio.cs.sfu.ca/taverna</rs>Until recently RNA was thought to have only two 
functions: (i) primarily as an information transmitter 
between DNA and proteins in the form of a messenger 
RNA (mRNA) and (ii) as a catalyser or an information 
decoder in protein synthesis in the form of a ribosomal 
RNA (rRNA) or a transfer RNA (tRNA). The discovery 
that RNA molecules can regulate gene expression 
completely altered this simplistic picture (1). This impor-
tant discovery, in particular the discovery of RNA 
interference (RNAi), the post-transcriptional silencing of 
gene expression via interactions between mRNAs and 
their antisense RNAs (by A. Fire and C. Mello) was 
awarded with the 2006 Nobel Prize for Physiology or 
Medicine. 
Recent studies have revealed that antisense RNAs are 
only a very small subset of non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs). 
A large fraction of the genome sequence (up to 10% in the 
human genome) appears to give rise to RNA transcripts 
that do not code for proteins (2). The functionality of 
many such ncRNAs are only scarcely known. </p>

<p>Regulatory ncRNAs that are generally responsible for 
regulating gene expression exhibit an exact or partial 
complementarity to their target mRNAs. Their interac-
tion forms a complex that consists of several non-
contiguous helical segments which prevent ribosomal 
access to the target mRNA. Generally, regulatory 
ncRNAs contain one or more stem loop structures that 
are (almost) complementary to specific sequences in the 
target mRNAs. Interaction with a target RNA is either 
initiated at such a loop structure of the antisense RNA 
and a loop structure from the target (forming kissing loop 
pairs) or between a loop structure and a single-stranded 
segment of the complementary RNA. 
As the number of ncRNAs and in particular regulatory 
RNAs increase it has become of crucial importance to 
establish software tools that can help identify their 
functionality. For this purpose we introduce <rs type="software">taveRNA</rs>, 
a web-based computational tool set that can help identify 
structure and functionality of ncRNA molecules. 
<rs type="software">taveRNA</rs> involves tools whose algorithmic foundations 
were developed by Simon Fraser University's Lab for 
Computational Biology over the past few years. The tools 
aim to solve the following key problems: </p>

<p>1. RNA secondary structure prediction problem, which 
asks to compute all basepairs established by a given 
(nc)RNA sequence. 
2. RNA-RNA interaction prediction problem, which 
asks to predict the joint secondary structure between 
two given RNA sequences; a joint secondary 
structure between two RNAs can be represented 
via the set of internal and external base pairs 
established between the interacting RNAs. 
3. ncRNA search problem which asks to compute all 
ncRNAs that can establish stable secondary struc-
tures (and in principle play a role in the regulation 
of) with a given query mRNA. </p>

<p><rs type="software">taveRNA</rs> involves web interfaces to the algorithmic 
tools we have developed for each one of the above 
problems: (1) <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs>, an alternative thermodynamic 
model-based RNA secondary structure prediction </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first three authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ1-604-268-7040; Fax: þ1-604-291-3045; Email: cenk@cs.sfu.ca </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>program, (2) inteRNA, a program for predicting the joint 
secondary structure of two interacting RNAs and 
(3) pRuNA, a tool for quickly identifying all potential 
regulatory ncRNAs for a query mRNA. 
RNA secondary structure prediction is one of the earliest 
problems considered in computational biology. Despite 
a 30-year-effort towards its solution, the best algorithms 
and software for RNA structure prediction are still far 
from perfect. The most common approach to the RNA 
secondary structure prediction problem is the standard 
thermodynamic approach. This general methodology 
suggests to compute the secondary structure of an RNA 
molecule by minimizing the total free energy of its 
substructures such as stems, loops and bulges. <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> is 
an alternative thermodynamic approach to the RNA 
secondary structure prediction problem, which aims 
to minimize a linear combination of total free energy and 
total energy density using the dynamic programming 
formulation proposed in (3), in contrast to the available 
alternatives such as <rs type="software">Mfold</rs> (4), <rs type="software">RNAscf</rs> (5) and alifold 
(6), which all employ the standard thermodynamic 
approach. 
As mentioned earlier, there are a number of algorithms 
for predicting the secondary structure of a single RNA 
molecule. However, until recently no such algorithm 
existed for reliably predicting the joint secondary structure 
of two interacting RNA molecules, or measuring the 
stability of such a joint structure. At SFU Lab for 
Computational Biology, <rs corresp="#software-14" type="creator">we</rs> developed <rs id="software-14" type="software">inteRNA</rs> the first 
program that aims to compute the joint structure 
prediction of two given RNA sequences through 
minimizing their total free energy, which is a function of 
the topology of the joint structure. The algorithmic 
foundations of <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> were introduced in (7). 
<rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> aims to minimize the joint free energy under 
a number of energy models with growing complexity. Our 
default energy model is based mostly on stacked pair 
energies given by Mathews et al. (8)-the free energy 
model employed by <rs type="software">Mfold</rs>. Because there is very little 
thermodynamic information on kissing loop sequences in 
the literature, <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> employs the approach used by 
Rivas and Eddy (9) to differentiate the thermodynamic 
parameters of 'external' bonds from the 'internal' bonds, 
i.e. we simply multiply the external parameters with 
a weight slightly smaller than 1. Note that the default 
algorithmic engine used by <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> requires substantial 
resources in terms of running time and memory which 
could be prohibitive for predicting joint structure of 
sufficiently long RNAs. Thus we made available an 
alternative heuristic engine that aims to capture 
the joint secondary structure of interacting RNAs. This 
heuristic approach is based on the observation that the 
substructures that are available independently in each 
RNA are mostly preserved in their joint secondary 
structure. 
Regulatory ncRNAs play important roles in controlling 
gene expression via establishing stable joint structures 
with target mRNAs and prohibiting ribosomal access. 
As many novel regulatory RNA classes are being 
discovered, the determination of the exact functionality 
of all regulatory ncRNAs is one of the most significant </p>

<p>scientific challenges to be tackled in the coming years. 
Our software tool <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> is developed for helping to 
address this challenge: it aims to identify all potential 
regulatory ncRNAs that can establish stable joint 
structures with a query mRNA (10). An important 
component of <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> is a sequence filter which eliminates 
a significant fraction of the available ncRNA collection 
and retains only the most likely ncRNA candidates for 
forming a stable joint structure with the query mRNA. 
We note that the majority of regulatory ncRNAs are only 
partially complementary to their target mRNA sequences. 
Typically these RNAs contain at least two short (5-7 nt) 
motifs on their loop structures that are complementary to 
the specific single-stranded locations in the target RNAs 
(11). Thus <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> first identifies all pairs of 5-mer motifs 
from the ncRNA loop sequences that are complementary 
to a pair of 5-mer motifs in the loop sequences of the 
query mRNA. The ncRNAs that include such 5-mer motif 
pairs are then tested against the query mRNA via the use 
of <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> and those which can establish stable joint 
structures are returned by the program. </p>

<p><rs type="software">alteRNA</rs>: AN RNA SECONDARY STRUCTURE 
PREDICTION TOOL BASED ON AN ALTERNATIVE 
THERMODYNAMIC APPROACH </p>

<p>Input and output </p>

<p><rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> requires a sequence in FASTA format, where the 
sequence is represented as a string of characters from 
the alphabet AE ¼ {A,C,G,U,T} (the characters are case 
insensitive). The length of the input RNA sequence is 
limited by 500 nt. There are two user-specified parameters, 
s and b, which will be explained in detail later. 
alteRNA outputs the results in three different forms: </p>

<p>1. The predicted RNA structure in dot-parenthesis 
format. The sequence is given from 5 
0 to 3 
0 end, 
and the structure is given with matching parenthesis 
denoting a base pair and a dot denoting an 
unbounded base. 
2. The predicted RNA structure in Connect(.ct) file 
format, which is the standard <rs type="software">Mfold</rs> output format. 
The sequence length is given in the first line. 
For each nucleotide i, there is a line which consists 
of: the line number (i), the letter denotion of the 
nucleotide, the predecessor base index (i À 1), the 
successor base index (i þ 1), the paired base index 
(0 if unpaired) and the original base index (i). 
3. The graphics files for the predicted secondary 
structure in Postscript(.ps) and GIF format. These 
graphs are created using <rs type="software">NAVIEW</rs> (12) and <rs type="software">Mfold</rs>/ 
plt2. </p>

<p>The secondary structure predicted by <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> for 
5sRNA is shown in Figure 1a. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>It has been shown in (3) that delocalizing the thermo-
dynamic cost of forming an RNA substructure can be 
achieved by consideration of the energy density of the </p>



<p>substructure, which, in return, can improve the secondary 
structure prediction of several ncRNA families. 
This alternative thermodynamic approach which we call 
Densityfold (3) aims to minimize the linear combination 
of the total free energy and total energy density of all 
substructures in the RNA molecule. Given an RNA 
secondary structure, the energy density of a basepair is 
defined as the free energy of the substructure that starts 
with the basepair, normalized by the length of the 
underlying sequence. The energy density of an unpaired 
base is then defined to be the energy density of the closest 
basepair that encloses it. Densityfold thus aims to 
minimize ED(n) þ sÁE(n), where ED(n) is the total energy 
density of paired and unpaired bases, E(n) is the total free 
energy and n is the length of the RNA sequence. Here s 
determines the weight of the contribution of the total free 
energy in the optimization function. As s approaches to 
1, the predicted secondary structure gets closer to that 
implied by the standard thermodynamic approach 
(employed by <rs type="software">Mfold</rs>). We have observed that s ¼ 5 
generally gives the most accurate prediction, in terms of 
structure edit distance (13), however in some RNA 
sequences, different s values can outperform s ¼ 5. 
We note that the free energy of a multi-branch loop 
as implied by the standard thermodynamic model is not 
a linear function and as a result cannot be used in 
a dynamic programming formulation. Thus we use the 
same approximate formulation as per Mfold, which, for 
a given multi-branch loop, L sets: </p>

<p>GðLÞ ¼ a þ b Á l s ðLÞ þ c Á l d ðLÞ þ G stack </p>

<p>Here a, b, c are constants in thermodynamic model, l s is 
the number of unpaired bases, l d is the number of base </p>

<p>pairs and ddG stack is the free energy of each branch in the 
loop. The default setting for b, the coefficient for the 
number unpaired bases, is 0 in Mfold; this implies 
that there will be no penalty for the unpaired bases. 
However, when used with Densityfold, this setting seems 
to produce large stretches of unpaired bases in multi-
branch loops. In order to counter this effect we suggest the 
user to set b to a small positive value less than 1. <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs>, 
our web-based tool for RNA secondary structure predic-
tion via the Densityfold approach allows the user to 
specify any positive value for s and b. The default values 
of s and b are 5 and 0, respectively and the folding 
temperature is fixed at 378C. </p>

<p><rs type="software">inteRNA</rs>: A Web-Based Tool For RNA-RNA 
Interaction Prediction </p>

<p>Input and output </p>

<p><rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> requires as an input two RNA sequences in 
FASTA format. The sequences are represented as strings 
of characters from the alphabet AE ¼ {A,C,G,U,T} 
(the strings are case insensitive). The length of each 
input RNA sequence is limited by 150 nt for Stacked Pair 
Model and by 500 nt for Loop Models. There are three 
user-specified parameters; gap penalty, maximum 
subsequence length and energy model; each of these 
parameters are explained in detail later. 
<rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> reports the results in three different output 
forms: </p>

<p>1. A text file that contains the base-pair information of 
the joint secondary structure. Here, each line denotes 
either a base pair with nucleotide indices or a gap. </p>

<p>Figure 1. The output pages of <rs type="software">taveRNA</rs>. (a) <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> secondary structure prediction for 5sRNA. (b) <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> joint structure prediction for 
CopA and CopT. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue W327 </p>

<p>A base pair is represented by a quadruple (Sequence, 
Position, Sequence, Position), where Sequence can be 
either S or R (representing the first and the second 
sequences, respectively) and Position is the base 
index. Gaps are represented with (S,''Gap'',R,i) in 
sequence R and represented with (S,i,R,''Gap'') in 
sequence S, where i is the index of the free 
nucleotide. 
2. A JPEG image file that can help visualize the joint 
secondary structure prediction of the input RNAs. 
The input RNAs are represented by their sequences 
only. Internal bonds are represented by blue arcs and 
external bonds are represented by red lines. 
3. A text file reporting the calculated free energy of the 
predicted joint secondary structure. </p>

<p>A sample interaction between CopA and CopT, 
predicted by <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> is shown in Figure 1b. </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p><rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> uses a dynamic programming algorithm, which 
aims to predict the joint secondary structure of two 
interacting RNA molecules through minimizing their total 
free energy. In other words, it predicts the secondary 
structure of both RNA strands and the interaction 
simultaneously. Since the general joint structure predic-
tion problem is NP-Complete, it is necessary to set some 
limitations on the structures predicted: inteRNA does not 
allow any (internal or external) pseudoknots; it does not 
allow any zig-zag structures either (7). 
<rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> can employ the following two models for 
approximating the total free energy of the joint structure. 
Stacked pair model: This model uses stacking pair 
energy functions both externally and internally. A gap 
penalty parameter is used to penalize opening a gap. Due 
to high computational complexity and memory require-
ments of this model, inteRNA cannot accept inputs with 
large (4200 nt) sequence lengths with this setting. 
Loop model: It has been observed that RNA molecules 
mostly preserve their independent secondary structure 
when they interact with other RNA. Interactions thus 
typically occur between kissing hairpin loops. The loop 
model first predicts the secondary structure of each RNA 
sequence independently using three different approaches: 
(i) through the standard thermodynamic model (<rs type="software">Mfold</rs> 
Loop Model), (ii) through Stacked Pair Model using 
a single RNA sequence (Default Loop Model) and 
(iii) through <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> (alteRNA Loop Model). It then 
identifies all independent subsequences of each RNA 
structure: these are substructures (each implied by 
a basepair) whose sequence length is less than a specified 
value. It then computes the joint secondary structure that 
can be established between each pair of independent 
subsequences (one subsequence from each RNA) and the 
free energy of this joint structure. Finally, it finds the set of 
independent subsequence pairs which can co-exist and 
minimize the total free energy of the overall secondary 
structure. </p>

<p><rs type="software">pRuNA</rs>: A REGULATORY RNA SEARCH ENGINE </p>

<p>Input and output </p>

<p><rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> asks for a query mRNA sequence as well as its 
corresponding secondary structure in parenthesis format. 
It returns a list of possible regulating ncRNAs available 
through the Rfam database (14). </p>

<p>Method </p>

<p>At the heart of <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> we have a lookup table of size 
1024 Â 1024, which represents every possible pair of 5-mer 
motifs from the 4-letter RNA alphabet. Each entry in the 
lookup table maintains a pointer to every occurrence of 
the respective 5-mer motif pair in the loop sequences of the 
ncRNA structures in the Rfam database. For querying the 
index, <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> first identifies the loop sequences from 
the mRNA, based on the given secondary structure 
information. It then extracts each pair of non-overlapping 
5-mer motifs from the mRNA loop sequences and checks 
the lookup table for its reverse complement. The union of 
the set of ncRNAs that include each motif pair are 
retained by <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs>, whereas the remainder of the 
ncRNAs in the database are eliminated. We have observed 
that many of the motif pairs in the lookup table occur very 
frequently in ncRNA sequences and thus have limited 
information content. We omitted the 5-mer pairs which 
occur in more than the number (14) of ncRNAs that 
include a 'typical' motif pair. This increased our pruning 
efficiency substantially yet had no effect on the quality of 
the results: we have tested <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> mRNAs that are 
known to be regulated by an ncRNA available through 
the NPInter database (15). For all 24 of these mRNAs, 
<rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> was able to return the known regulatory 
ncRNA among the set of potential regulators, while 
achieving a pruning efficiency of 86% on the average. 
If the search is restricted to E. coli ncRNAs, the pruning 
efficiency for the 22 mRNAs regulated by these ncRNAs 
go up to 91% on the average. Further details on <rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> 
(including the method and experimental results) can be 
found in (10). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p><rs type="software">taveRNA</rs> is a web application implemented in html/php; 
the underlying algorithms are all implemented in C/Cþþ. 
Our server is hosted on a Linux machine with 16 GB 
RAM and 4 AMD Opteron 2200 processors. On an RNA 
sequence with length n, the running time of <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs> is 
O(n 
4 ) and the memory requirement is O(n 
4 ). On two input 
RNA sequences S and R, where |S| ¼ n and |R| ¼ m, the 
running time of <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> is O(n 
3 m 
3 ) and the memory 
requirement is O(n 
2 m 
2 ). It is possible to improve the 
running time using the loop model to where k is the 
maximum independent structure size. The running time of 
<rs type="software">pRuNA</rs> is linear with the input sequence length and the 
result set. Because of the large running-time requirements 
of <rs type="software">inteRNA</rs> and <rs type="software">alteRNA</rs>, <rs type="software">taveRNA</rs> has an e-mail 
notification option. 
<rs id="software-58" type="software">taveRNA</rs> has been developed by <rs corresp="#software-58" type="creator">the Lab for Computational Biology at Simon Fraser University</rs> and </p>



<p>it is accessible from http://compbio.cs.sfu.ca/taverna. 
We acknowledge our funding sources, in particular 
NSERC, Canada Research Chairs Program, Canada 
Foundation for Innovation and Michael Smith Founda-
tion for Health Research. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges 
for this article was provided by NSERC, CIRC Program, 
CFI, MITACS and MSFHR. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statment. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue W329 </p>

</text></tei>