<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1933234" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic 
repeats (CRISPRs) constitute a particular family of 
tandem repeats found in a wide range of prokaryotic 
genomes (half of eubacteria and almost all archaea). 
They consist of a succession of highly conserved 
regions (DR) varying in size from 23 to 47 bp, 
separated by similarly sized unique sequences 
(spacer) of usually viral origin. A CRISPR cluster is 
flanked on one side by an AT-rich sequence called 
the leader and assumed to be a transcriptional 
promoter. Recent studies suggest that this struc-
ture represents a putative RNA-interference-based 
immune system. Here we describe CRISPRFinder, a 
web service offering tools to (i) detect CRISPRs 
including the shortest ones (one or two motifs); 
(ii) define DRs and extract spacers; (iii) get the 
flanking sequences to determine the leader; 
(iv) blast spacers against Genbank database and 
(v) check if the DR is found elsewhere in 
prokaryotic sequenced genomes. CRISPRFinder is 
freely accessible at http://crispr.u-psud.fr/Server/ 
CRISPRfinder.php. </p>

<p>Genomic structures corresponding to CRISPRs were 
observed first in 1987 in Escherichia coli (1) and were 
subsequently reported in other organisms under different 
names [TREP (2), SRSR (3,4), DRVs (5), LCTR (6), 
SPIDR (7)] until the CRISPR acronym was proposed by 
Jansen et al. (8). The direct repeat sequences carry in 
general a low level of palindromic symmetry; they are 
remarkably well conserved within a species (up to 248 
exact copies in Verminephrobacter eiseniae EF01-2). 
However, one of the flanking DRs is frequently truncated 
or diverged (see Supplementary Data). The DR size varies 
from 24 to 47 bp whereas the spacer sequence is generally 
within the range of 0.6-2.5Â the DR size. The originality 
of spacers is that they apparently derive from conjugative </p>

<p>plasmids or bacteriophages (2,9-11). A prokaryotic 
genome may harbour up to 16 CRISPR clusters with the 
same or a different DR. In a genome, a single CRISPR is 
generally associated with a family of genes called cas for 
CRISPR-associated (8,12), encoding proteins showing 
functional similarity with components of the eukaryotic 
RNA interference (RNAi) systems (13). In addition, it was 
demonstrated in two archaea, Archaeoglobus fulgidus (14) 
and Sulfolobus solfataricus (15), that the CRISPR locus 
is transcribed into small RNAs (smRNA) probably 
from one of the flanking regions, the leader, acting as a 
promoter. These observations and the viral origin 
of spacers have led to the hypothesis that the CRISPR-
associated system (CASS) is a prokaryotic defence 
mechanism against genetic aggressions (10,13,16). Within 
species, CRISPRs may be present in a subset of strains, 
where they sometimes show polymorphism. The DR and 
the order of the spacers are well conserved, but the 
number of motifs (DR þ spacer) differs from strain to 
strain. To better understand the mechanisms underlying 
the CRISPRs' evolutionary scenario, three evolution rules 
were proposed by Pourcel et al. (10) and confirmed by 
Lillestol et al. (15): (i) polarized acquisition of spacers 
near the leader sequence; (ii) random loss of motifs and 
(iii) shared ancestry when spacers are identical. 
CRISPRs' in silico analyses started in 1995 (2) but no 
specific stand-alone CRISPR software tool was created. 
Several software were used by different authors to identify 
these particular repeats but usually a manual discard 
of background was necessary, and generally some 
<rs type="software">CRISPR</rs> clusters were missed or neglected, especially the 
shortest one (less than three motifs). This is the case, for 
example, of Tandem Repeat Finder (17) when considering 
a motif (DR þ spacer) as a degenerate repeat (10,18), or 
Locating Uniform poly-Nucleotide Areas (LUNA), 
a program for finding degenerate repeats in microbial 
genomes on a desktop computer. The repeats can be 
filtered using several parameters including length, distance 
and level of conservation. LUNA was used especially for 
finding CRISPRs in archaea (4,15). Another program, 
Patscan (19) a pattern-matching tool that searches 
sequences fitting the introduced pattern, was applied to </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 33 1 69 15 30 01; Fax: 33 1 69 15 66 78; Email: Ibtissem.Grissa@igmors.u-psud.fr </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>identify CRISPRs containing at least three (20) or four 
exact direct repeats (8). PYGRAM (21) is a visualization 
program browsing all the repeats in the submitted 
genomic sequence and showing perfectly conserved 
palindromic repeats as pyramids. The PYGRAM pro-
gram is mostly efficient in visually displaying large 
CRISPRs (CRISPRs with as many as seven motifs are 
considered as being very short in this work) since they will 
be recognized as a concentration of horizontal bars 
referring to a group of co-occurring repeats that differ 
by only a few nucleotides. Finally, Haft et al. (12) used 
REPfind (http://bibiserv.techfak.uni-bielefeld.de/reputer/), 
a part of the REPuter package (22-24) and BLASTN to 
identify smaller repeat clusters. 
These programs are the most used tools in CRISPR 
detection, although none of them is especially conceived 
for this purpose. They require further manual manipula-
tions to eliminate background data (tandem repeats for 
example) and importantly, do not define accurately the 
DR consensus (due to errors on the boundaries). Recently, 
two CRISPR-dedicated software tools were proposed, 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">CRT</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">http://www.room220.com/crt</rs>) and <rs type="software">PILER-CR</rs> (25). 
Both of them run fast and perform well in finding 
CRISPRs. However, CRT results in a considerable 
background since tandem repeats are considered as 
putative CRISPRs and in addition, the same CRISPR is 
sometimes detected more than once with different 
consensus DRs. PILER-CR has also some drawbacks 
since it often misidentifies the DR boundaries and omits 
the truncated DR. 
In addition, there is no user-friendly dedicated web site. 
A specialized program to automatically identify CRISPRs 
seems to be mandatory for their optimum, rapid explora-
tion and in-depth analysis, in order to increase the 
efficiency of CRISPRs investigations. CRISPRFinder is 
a web service offering fundamental tools for CRISPR 
detection, including the shortest ones, allowing an 
accurate definition of the DR consensus boundaries and 
extraction of the related spacers. It offers also additional 
tools to analyze the CRISPR loci: (i) obtain the CRISPR 
and the flanking sequences according to flexible size; 
(ii) make a blast of selected spacers or flanking sequences 
against the Genbank database and (iii) check if the DR is 
found elsewhere in prokaryotic sequenced genomes. The 
CRISPRFinder web interface is accessible through http:// 
crispr.u-psud.fr/Server/CRISPRfinder.php </p>

<p>METHODS AND IMPLEMENTATION </p>

<p>CRISPRFinder core routines were developed in Perl 
under Debian Linux. The input of the web tool is a 
genomic query sequence of length up to 67 Mb in 
'FASTA' format. Possible locations of CRISPRs (con-
sisting of at least one motif) are detected by finding 
maximal repeats. A maximal repeat (26) is a repeat that 
cannot be extended in either direction without incurring a 
mismatch. The total number of maximal repeats in a 
sequence of size n is linear (less than n) which is interesting 
since the computation may be done in linear time using a 
suffix-tree-based algorithm. A CRISPR pattern of two </p>

<p>DRs and a spacer may be considered as a maximal repeat 
where the repeated sequences are separated by a sequence 
of approximately the same length. 
The operation of the program can be divided into four 
main steps summarized in Figure 1: (Step 1) browsing the 
maximal repeats of length 23-55 bp interspaced by 
sequences of 25-60 bp, (Step 2) selecting the DR consensus 
according to a defined score taking into account the 
number of occurrences of the candidate DR in the whole 
genome and privileging internal mismatches between the 
DRs rather than mismatches in the first or the last 
nucleotides, (Step 3) defining candidate CRISPRs after 
checking if they fit CRISPR definition, (Step 4) eliminat-
ing residual tandem repeats. 
In the first step, maximal repeats are found by the 
software <rs id="software-1" type="software">Vmatch</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.vmatch.de/</rs>/), the upgrade of 
REPuter (22-24). Vmatch is based on a comprehensive 
implementation of enhanced suffix arrays (27) which 
provides the power of suffix trees with lower space 
requirements. A one nucleotide mismatch is allowed 
permitting minimal CRISPRs with a single nucleotide 
mutation between DRs to be found. Hereafter, the 
obtained maximal repeats are grouped to define regions 
of possible CRISPRs with a display of consensus DR 
candidates related to each cluster. 
The second step is aimed at retrieving the DR consensus 
of each cluster. The difficulty resides especially in the 
identification of boundaries, which is very important to 
extract the correct spacers and compare DRs. In fact, 
the consensus DR is selected as the maximal repeat which 
occurs the most in the whole underlying genome sequence 
with respect to the forward and the reverse complement 
directions (since two CRISPRs having the same 
DR consensus may be in opposite directions). Thus, 
ambiguity in the choice of a DR will be eliminated in the 
case of presence of similar DRs in other CRISPRs of the 
related genomic sequence. However, if occurrence num-
bers are equal, more than a single DR consensus candidate 
are kept and later compared. Given a candidate consensus 
DR, the pattern search program fuzznuc of the EMBOSS 
package (28) is applied to get DRs' positions in the 
related cluster. As the first or the last DR in a CRISPR 
may be diverged/truncated, a mismatch of one-third of the 
DR length is allowed between the flanking DRs and the 
candidate consensus DR, whereas smaller nucleotide 
differences are allowed between the other DRs to take 
into account possible single mutations. In case of multiple 
DR candidates, a score is computed and the best one 
(minimum) is picked. This score favours candidates which 
are encountered more frequently, rather than consensus 
DR showing less internal mismatches. 
Once the DR consensus is determined, the correspond-
ing spacers (Step 3) are extracted according to the DR 
boundaries determined previously. The spacer length is 
not allowed to be shorter than 0.6 or longer than 2.5 times 
the DR length. These sizes are in the range of CRISPRs 
described in the literature. 
The last step consists in discarding false CRISPRs. 
Therefore, tandem repeats are eliminated by comparing 
the consensus DR with the spacer if there is only 
one spacer, or by comparing spacers between each other. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue W53 </p>

<p>The comparison is done with the CLUSTALW program 
(29) and the percentage of identity between spacers is 
not allowed to exceed 60%. Finally, candidates having 
at least three motifs and at least two exactly identical 
DRs are considered as confirmed CRISPRs. The remain-
ing candidates are considered as questionable. These 
should be critically investigated by, for example, checking 
for intraspecies size variation of the locus. </p>

<p>INPUT AND OPTIONS </p>

<p>The query sequence must be in 'FASTA' format. Ns 
characters are accepted, IUB/GCG letters (MRWSY-
KVHDBX) will be converted to Ns and considered as 
mismatches but any other characters will be deleted. 
One can either paste the genomic sequence into the input 
field or upload it from a file on the local machine. 
Multisequence files are also allowed by the program and </p>

<p>will be treated independently. Users may use the default 
version or click on the 'advanced version' link to set and 
modify all the program parameters, which may be 
especially useful for fixing the DR size. </p>

<p>OUTPUT </p>

<p>After querying a genomic sequence by CRISPRFinder, 
results are summarized in a table with the number 
of confirmed and questionable CRISPRs (Figure 2A). 
A CRISPR locus is presented according to a colour code 
showing DRs in yellow and spacers in different colours. 
The respective positions are displayed, in addition to links 
to two files: a summary of the displayed properties 
(number of motifs, DR consensus, positions, etc.) and 
a fasta file containing the list of spacers. In addition, 
a PNG (Portable Network Graphics) figure displays the 
different candidates' location in the analysed sequence. </p>

<p>Figure 1. CRISPR Finder flow chart. (Step 1) Browsing the maximal repeats to get possible CRISPR localizations using the Vmatch program. 
(Step 2) Consensus DR selection according to candidate occurrences and a score computation: the score privileges internal mismatches between direct 
repeats of a cluster rather than boundary mismatches. (Step 3) DR and spacers size check. (Step 4) Tandem repeats elimination using ClustalW for 
aligning spacers. </p>

<p>W54 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue </p>

<p>Figure 2. An example of CRISPRFinder output using the Aquifex aeolicus VF5 genomic sequence (Refseq: NC_000918). (Panel A) (1) Home page 
where the genomic sequence is submitted. (2) Table listing the detected CRISPRs candidates (questionable and confirmed) providing links to each 
one. (3) CRISPRs details, the DR is showed in yellow and the spacers in different colours. (4) A fasta file displaying the first CRISPR spacers. 
(5) Figure showing the Aquifex circular chromosome with CRISPRs positions. (Panel B) One or several spacers may be blasted against NCBI 
databases by clicking on the blast_spacers button. (Panel C) The flanking and the CRISPR sequences may be viewed by clicking on the Get 
sequences button. The sequences boundaries may be modified by the user. (Panel D) The list of consensus DRs for all CRISPRs is shown with a 
link to identical DRs in the CRISPR database. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue W55 </p>

<p>In the case of presence of CRISPR clusters, further 
analysis may be done through three hyperlinks in the left 
menu: (i) blast spacers against the Genbank databases 
with a cutoff of 0.1 for the E-value and a matching 
length of at least 70% the queried spacer size (Figure 2B); 
(ii) obtain CRISPR and flanking sequences which are 
especially useful to define the leader sequence. As the size 
of the leader sequence depends on the species (it varies 
from 100 to 500 bp), the retrieved sequence may be 
manually modified by the user (Figure 2C) and (iii) display 
identical DRs in other known CRISPR loci (Figure 2D). 
This utility corresponds to a link to CRISPR database 
(Grissa et al. submitted for publication). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>CRISPRFinder is a program that allows the identification 
of structures with the principal characteristics of 
CRISPRs, the smaller being composed of a truncated or 
diverged DR, a spacer and a complete DR. In their 
analysis, Godde et al. (20) using Patscan had chosen to 
retain only CRISPRs with at least three exact repeats 
(eliminating CRISPRs constituted of a first truncated 
repeat plus two exact repeats) thus ignoring most 
CRISPRs containing less than three spacers. Similarly in 
the work by Durand et al.(21), the PYGRAM program is 
mostly efficient in visually displaying large CRISPRs. 
Such stringent criteria were appropriate in order to avoid 
ambiguities in early investigations which were essentially 
describing these new structures. However, it is now 
important, in order to better understand the evolution 
and spreading of CRISPRs, to provide tools which will 
not eliminate the smallest CRISPRs. This is what we chose 
to achieve with CRISPFinder. The major drawback is that 
when looking for the shortest structures, such as those 
with a unique spacer, it is clear that the background of 
spurious candidates can be very high. The output of 
Patscan and CRT also contains a large quantity of noised 
data that needs a manual treatment. 
CRISPRFinder is accessible on the web and submission 
is very simple. We provide several samples on the website 
as demonstrators. Upon submission of the complete 
genome of Aquifex aeolicus VF5 (sample1), five confirmed 
and five possible CRISPRs are displayed in the following 
pages. On the contrary, while using the webservice for 
Patscan (http://www-unix.mcs.anl.gov/compbio/PatScan/), 
it is necessary to first define a pattern (which is not 
straightforward) and it is not possible to seek for 
CRISPRs in a single genomic sequence but rather in an 
entire predefined database. In addition, Patscan requires a 
Sun machine for local implementation. Similarly, 
PYGRAM only runs on linux systems and its installation 
requires advanced skills. CRT requires either to install 
JRE (Java Runtime Environment) or compile the source 
files, and PILER-CR needs to be compiled before use. 
A comparison between layouts of available online 
programs 
(REPuter, 
Patscan, 
TRF) 
and 
of 
CRISPRFinder is provided in the Supplementary Data. 
To check that CRISPRFinder was efficient in recover-
ing all the CRISPRs from a genome, we compared the </p>

<p>results to other available studies on CRISPRs (15,20). The 
data were generally in good agreement, the differences 
being always in the DR boundaries' identification 
(more accurate with CRISPRFinder) or in the number 
of motifs found, as the truncated DR is sometimes 
neglected or short clusters are not detected with other 
programs. Interestingly, some strains were claimed to 
be devoid of CRISPRs by Godde and colleagues but 
proved to have short CRISPRs with CRISPRFinder, such 
as in different Shigella sp. (S. sonnei Ss046, S. flexneri 
2a str. 301, S. flexneri 2a str), or even long CRISPRs such 
as in Pseudomonas aeruginosa UCBPP-PA14. The latter 
example is shown on the CRISPRfinder website 
(sample2), and as can be seen by using the BLAST 
spacer function, six spacers out of thirty six at two 
different CRISPR loci, correspond to a bacteriophage 
sequence (bacteriophages F116, B3, D3112, DMS3 
and phi CTX). 
The tools developed here will assist in future CRISPRs' 
analysis. Furthermore, the possibility to identify 
CRISPRs containing one or two motifs may help under-
stand how new CRISPRs are created. The very small 
candidates will need to be typed across different isolates 
within the same species or very closely related species to 
search for variations. For instance, as shown with the 
sample file provided on the website (YP1 Yersinia), 
five Yersinia pestis strains possess at the same CRISPR 
locus two to eight spacers, some being unique and others 
shared by two or more strains (10). This strain-dependent 
polymorphism is especially interesting for epidemiological 
and phylogenetic studies (30,31). A tool to easily create a 
dictionary of spacers from different strains is proposed 
in a CRISPR-dedicated web database (http://crispr. 
u-psud.fr/crispr/). 
The CRISPRFinder web server is an interface to extract 
with precision and to further analyse CRISPRs from 
genomic sequences. Four main advantages may be cited: 
(i) short CRISPR-like structures are detected, they are 
labelled questionable but may be of great interest if later 
confirmed; (ii) DRs are accurately defined to single 
base pair resolution; (iii) summary files may be uploaded 
(CRISPR properties summary and spacers file in Fasta 
format) and (iv) flanking sequences or spacers can be 
easily extracted and blasted against different databases. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The CNRS and Universite´Paris Sud 11 have funded this 
project. Work on the development of genotyping tools for 
bacterial pathogens is supported by the  
Ge´ne´rale pour l'Armement (DGA). Funding to pay the 
Open Access publication charges for this article was 
provided by ADGE. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>W56 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Web Server issue W57 </p>

</text></tei>