<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1538888" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The large number of experimentally determined 
protein 3D structures is a rich resource for studying 
protein function and evolution, and protein struc-
ture comparison (PSC) is a key method for such 
studies. When comparing two protein structures, 
almost all currently available PSC servers report 
a single and sequential (i.e. topological) alignment, 
whereas the existence of good alternative align-
ments, including those involving permutations 
(i.e. non-sequential or non-topological alignments), 
is well known. We have recently developed a novel 
PSC method that can detect alternative alignments 
of statistical significance (alignment similarity 
P-value ,10 
À5 Protein structure comparison (PSC) has been a staple method 
for obtaining information about a protein when its 3D struc-
ture is determined experimentally or predicted computation-
ally. It is therefore not surprising that the development of 
new PSC algorithms has been continuing for more than two 
decades with no sign of ceasing (1-6). These efforts are 
needed not only to meet new scientific challenges but also 
to benefit maximally from the large number of new structures 
now pouring in from structural genomics projects (7,8). </p>

<p>To these ends, a number of laboratories have created 
PSC servers in recent years to provide information beyond 
the basic PSC operations, including, e.g. those that do flexible 
alignment (9,10), those that discover recurring substructures 
or motifs (11,12), those that perform multiple structure align-
ment (13) and those that focus on fast structure feature 
extraction (14-16). 
Here we offer a new PSC server with the functionality to 
report statistically significant alternative alignments (17,18)  and structural permutations (19,20) at all levels of complex-
ity. Our method, named OPAAS, which has been detailed 
elsewhere (21,22), deduces the probabilities of aligning 
every possible pair of secondary structure elements (SSEs) 
between two protein structures prior to the search for a 
solution of their alignment. This deduction allows the ready 
identification of most, though not all, statistically significant 
alignment solutions, many of which being distinct alterna-
tives to the 'optimal' solution, the target of conventional 
PSC operations. As we reported previously from a study of 
all-against-all database comparisons (22), about half of the 
alternative alignments were detectable only when permuta-
tion, i.e. non-topological alignment, was allowed. Moreover, 
many of the permuted alignments exhibited a permutation 
complexity higher than that of circular permutation, meaning 
that more than two separable regions of the protein structure 
could be aligned non-sequentially. To quantitatively measure 
the level of permutation complexity for all the alignments, we 
devised a permutation index (PI) as follows: </p>

<p>PI ¼ 
ð 
P n 
i¼1 S i Þ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>P n 
i¼1 S </p>

<p>2 
i </p>

<p>‚ </p>

<p>where S i is the size (number of aligned amino acid residues) 
of the aligned region i and n is the total number of aligned 
regions. A region is an independently, and, within the region 
itself, topologically aligned part of an alignment. That is, 
within a region, all the aligned residues are ordered sequen-
tially, which may or may not be interrupted by gaps, but 
these regions, if there are more than one, are aligned non-
sequentially. It follows that an alignment without any permu-
tation will have just one region, and will have, by definition, a 
PI value of 1.0. Also by definition, a circular permutation, </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +886 2 2789 9033; Fax: +886 2 2788 7641; Email: mjhwang@ibms.sinica.edu.tw </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commerical use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, Web Server issue W95-W98 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl264 </p>

<p>which involves swapping two regions in a non-topological 
alignment (19,20), will receive a PI value &gt;1.0 but not 
&gt;2.0. PI hence furthermore let us know how much the sizes 
of the separately aligned regions differ. For example, given 
two permuted protein pairs having PI 3.0 and 2.5, respec-
tively, we will know that they both have three aligned 
regions, but the sizes of the three regions are equal for the 
former and vary significantly for the latter. 
Both permuted and non-permuted alternative alignments 
are reported by the OPAAS server in a fashion that is easy 
for a non-specialist user to grasp the main significance of 
the comparison as one would with the 'optimal' alignment 
featured by other PSC servers. This is aided by the server's 
user-friendly interfaces described below, which use intuitive 
viewing directions, informative tables that can be sorted by 
different parameters, cascading information windows, and a 
structured user guide with examples. </p>

<p>OPAAS WEB SERVER LAYOUT </p>

<p>At the portal of the OPAAS web server (Figure 1a) lay two 
main structure comparison functions, '1 against SCOP90 
dataset' and '2 chains alignment', and a Help webpage for 
a structured OPAAS user guide, which can be viewed 
on-line (http://opaas.ibms.sinica.edu.tw/help/opaas.html) as 
well as interactively in different contexts (see below). </p>

<p>One-against-all search on SCOP90 </p>

<p>The one-against-all on SCOP90 function is designed to find 
structural neighbors of a protein of interest in the structure 
classification of proteins (<rs type="software">SCOP</rs>) (23) database. One of the 
following three input options (left panel in Figure 1b and </p>

<p>user guide 3.1.1) is available for the search: a structure 
domain already in <rs id="software-1" type="software">SCOP</rs>90 (SCOP version <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">1.55</rs>, &lt;90% 
sequence identity non-redundant set), a structure in the cur-
rent Protein Data Bank (PDB; the server updates its local 
PDB weekly) (24) with a specified chain (PDB ID option), 
or a structure in PDB format uploaded by user (User's struc-
ture option). All of the three inputs can be accompanied with 
optional parameter settings for customized output. The 
parameters that could be changed from default include mini-
mum rough Z-score [for the alignment prior to refinement 
(21)], minimum refined Z-score, maximum root mean square 
deviation (RMSD) of Ca superposition between two aligned 
protein chains, minimum aligned sequence identity, maxi-
mum number of shown matches, and sorting options (right 
panel in Figure 1b and user guide 3.1.2). Unlike the first 
input option, for which pre-computed results will be 
retrieved, the last two input options require entry of user's 
e-mail address (user guide 3.1.3) because the OPAAS server 
needs time for computation and will return the result via 
email in, typically, minutes to hours, depending mainly on 
the stringency of the selected parameters. 
For the first input option, a table of matched results 
retrieved from a pre-computed database will be displayed 
directly on the web page (Figure 1c and user guide 3.2). In 
this table, Z-score, #a.a. aligned (number of aligned amino 
acids), and RMSD reported are those for the optimal align-
ment solution only, #alt. sol. is the number of alternative 
alignment solutions that satisfy the parameters specified by 
the user, and PI indicates the level of permutation complexity 
as described above. User can sort the table by the field 
selected (user guide 3.2.2) and download this table either as 
a plain text file or a comma separated values format file (user 
guide 3.2.3). User also can click on the matched entry to view </p>

<p>Figure 1. Snapshots of the OPAAS web server. (a) The portal page of the server. Two main applications can be chosen here. (b) The input page for the function 
of one-against-all search in the SCOP90 dataset. Three different input preferences and optional parameter settings are allowed in the left and right panel, 
respectively. (c) This table of matched results is retrieved from a database containing pre-computed all-against-all comparison results, which is available only 
with the one-against-all function. (d) The input page for the function of two chain alignment. (e) Output of a two chain alignment. The information of all 
alignment solutions ('optimal' and alternatives) is hierarchically laid out in three frames. </p>



<p>details of each alignment solution, which will have exactly 
the same output as that from using the function of '2 chains 
alignment' (user guide 3.2.4; see below). For the output of the 
last two input options, an e-mail of search result with the 
subject title 'OPAAS result' will be sent back to the e-mail 
address supplied (user guide 3.3). The e-mail contains a 
table of search result like that of the first input option 
described above, but to interactively view details of individ-
ual alignment solution, the second function, described below, 
needs to be separately invoked. </p>

<p>Alignment of two protein chains </p>

<p>For the function of '2 chains alignment' (Figure 1d and user 
guide 4.1), the structures of the two protein chains could 
either be selected from PDB (i.e. entering PDB ID) or 
uploaded by user in PDB format. Display of the comparison 
results, which can be expected to follow immediately upon 
submission of the request, is split into three frames to show 
'basic information of the comparison', 'information of each 
solution', and 'detail alignment of selected region' 
(Figure 1e and user guide 4.2). 
In the frame of 'basic information of the comparison', one 
of two tables gives some basic information about the two 
chains compared: size (number of amino acid residues), and 
number of SSE (user guide 4.2.1). User can click a hyperlink 
on the name of the two chains placed above the table to learn 
more about the compared proteins from the PDB website 
(user guide 4.2.2). The other table shows information of all 
the solutions (both the 'optimal' and alternative alignments, 
if any) of this comparison including #a.a. aligned (number 
of aligned residues), RMSD, refined Z-score, PI and region 
(number of permutedly aligned regions). Clicking on the 
solution number shows details of that solution in another 
two frames (user guide 4.2.3). The frame of 'information of 
each solution' shows the alignment of the selected solution 
graphically (user guide 4.2.4), both in a schematic representa-
tion and in a 3D superposition supported by chime plug-in 
(user guide 4.2.5). A file containing Cartesian coordinates 
of this alignment solution in standard PDB format can be 
exported. Different colors of the boxes in the diagram of 
the schematic representation, as well as of the traces in the 
3D superposition, refer to different aligned regions. Clicking 
on the region box will show 'detail alignment of the selected 
region' in the third frame. The sequence alignment of this 
region can also be downloaded in MFA (Multi-FASTA 
Alignment) format by clicking 'export alignment' at the top 
of this frame. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The best way to compare two protein structures often depends 
on the question being asked (6), so having a server like 
OPAAS that can simultaneously analyze solutions beyond 
the 'optimal' alignment is useful. Although most of the pub-
lished PSC algorithms can be modified to offer similar capa-
bility, to our knowledge, only two PSC servers give user the 
option to see alternative alignments: Prosup (25) and SARF2 
(26), but Prosup is limited to topological alignments and 
neither offers one-against-all database searching service. 
Moreover, with an intuitive hierarchical layout of the com-</p>

<p>parison results and optional parameter settings to view most 
significant alignments (e.g. with similarity P-value set at 
10 
À5 , a typical comparison usually resulted in &lt;5 such solu-
tions), an informative summary that could lead to unexpected 
insight from unexpected alternative alignments is effectively 
produced. The main limitation of OPAAS, at its current ver-
sion, arose from a compromise to trade for computational 
efficiency, which dictates that a structure must possess at 
least three SSEs to be compared (21,22); elimination of this 
limitation is in progress. Significantly, our server allows data-
base search with an efficiency comparable that of the popular 
CE server (27), despite ours being run on a personal computer 
(Pentium IV) and being asked to find alternative alignments. 
The source code of OPAAS is also available at the server for 
free download for standalone computations and for incorpora-
tion of structure database other than SCOP. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this 
article was provided by the Academia Sinica and National 
Science Council of Taiwan. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>









</text></tei>