<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1950546" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:19+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>PrrC, the optional Escherichia coli anticodon nuclease 
(ACNase) (1,2) represents potential antiviral devices 
widespread among bacteria (3). PrrC's activity is silenced 
by the genetically linked type Ic DNA restriction 
endonuclease EcoprrI (4-7) and is unleashed by Stp, the 
phage T4-encoded peptide inhibitor of EcoprrI (8). The 
activation of PrrC causes specific cleavage of tRNA Lys </p>

<p>5 0 to the wobble base (2) and, consequently, could block 
T4-late translation and contain the infection (9). However, 
the T4-coded RNA healing and sealing enzymes 
3 0 -phosphatase/5 0 -polynucleotide kinase (Pnk) and RNA 
ligase 1 (Rnl1) (10) normally restore the intact form of 
tRNA Lys (1,2), exercising perhaps their intended functions 
(11,12). Known PrrC homologs are invariably linked to 
EcoprrI homologs and, hence, could also act as secondary 
defenses mobilized when an associated DNA restriction 
endonuclease is compromised (3,8,13). 
When PrrC is expressed by itself it exhibits overt (core) 
ACNase activity (14) that purifies with a homo-oligomeric 
PrrC form, possibly a dimer of dimers (3). PrrC's 
N-proximal $265 amino acids are thought to constitute 
an NTPase domain that mediates the activation of the 
latent ACNase (3,13) (Figure 10A). This region contains 
ABC ATPase-like motifs (15), albeit, sufficiently different 
from the typical to justify classifying PrrC's N-domain 
as a distinct subtype. The divergent sequence of PrrC's 
N-domain could account for the unusual nucleotide 
requirements of the ACNase activation reaction and 
PrrC's idiosyncratic nucleotide binding attributes. 
Namely, the activation depends on the cooperation of 
GTP and dTTP and is inhibited by ATP. Moreover, dTTP 
exhibits higher affinity for PrrC than GTP or ATP 
(mM versus mM-range); and dTTP but not GTP or ATP 
stabilizes PrrC's core ACNase activity. PrrC differs from 
the typically dimeric ABC ATPases (16) also in its 
apparent dimer of dimers structure (3). The remaining 
$130 amino acid region of PrrC harbors residues 
implicated in tRNA Lys recognition (17-19) and cleavage 
(3) and does not resemble a known protein structure. 
The main cues PrrC recognizes in tRNA Lys map to 
the anticodon stem-loop (ASL). They comprise the 
anticodon sequence, base modifications and base-pairing 
interactions (17-20). 
Peptide mimicry and Cys-mediated intersubunit 
cross-linking data reported here suggest that the 
tRNA Lys -binding motif of PrrC is shared by C-domain 
portions interfacing in parallel. The proposed parallel 
dimerization of the C-domains can be reconciled with the </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 972 3 642 6213; Fax: +1 972 3 640 6834; Email: gabika@tauex.tau.ac.il </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>expected head-to-tail dimerization of the N-domains (15) 
by further suggesting that the regulatory and functional 
sites of PrrC arise at distinct assembly stages of its dimer 
of dimers form. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Purified E. coli tRNA Lys labeled with 32 P at the 33p34 
junction (13,21) and synthetic tRNA Lys ASL analogs 
(22,23) were prepared as previously described. The 
analogs included ASL-3 that matches mammalian 
tRNA Lys3 in RNA sequence and base modifications but 
contains an extra 3 0 -dT that facilitated its synthesis; and 
ASL-C that has the same RNA sequence but base 
modifications of E. coli tRNA Lys (Figure 1); both were 
[5 0 -32 P] labeled as described (19). The synthetic end-
protected peptides used (Figure 2) were purchased from 
Genscript Corporation and were over 80% pure. 
Diazenedicarboxylic acid (diamide) was purchased from 
Sigma. </p>

<p>PrrC mutagenesis </p>

<p>The PrrC forms used contained a C-terminal His 6 tag and, 
except where indicated, also the leaky D222E mutation </p>

<p>that allows high level expression of the protein (3). The 
triple mutant D222E/C268A/C385A termed PrrC Ã , its Cys 
replacement derivatives and the H356A/F292S double 
mutant were generated by Quick Change (24). Other PrrC 
mutants have been described (3,17). </p>

<p>PrrC-expression plasmids and bacterial hosts </p>

<p>The PrrC proteins were expressed under the control of the 
T7-Lac promoter and Shine-Dalgarno sequence of 
plasmid pRRC11 (17) in E. coli Rosetta (DE3)pLysS 
(Novagen, UK) encoding T7 RNA polymerase, T7 
lyzozyme (25) and rare tRNAs from plasmid pRARE. 
The cells were grown in LB medium at 378C to a density of 
$6.10 8 cells/ml. They were shifted then to 308C and PrrC's 
expression induced by adding 1 mM IPTG. After further 
incubation for 2 h, the cells were harvested and the 
PrrC proteins purified by immobilized metal affinity 
chromatography as described (3). </p>

<p>Diamide treatment of cells expressing PrrC to-Cys mutants </p>

<p>Escherichia coli cells induced to express the indicated 
PrrC forms were harvested by high-speed centrifugation, 
re-suspended in 0.01 vol of 10 mM diamide in water and 
incubated at 108C for the indicated time. The cells 
were then lyzed by heating them for 1 min at 1008C in 
SDS-PAGE sample buffer, their proteins were separated 
by SDS-PAGE and PrrC monitored by immunoblotting 
using purified polyclonal anti-PrrC antibodies (17). </p>

<p>ACNase isolation and assays </p>

<p>The standard core ACNase form used in the in vitro assays 
was a His 6 -tagged derivative of the leaky PrrC mutant 
D222E. It was purified by TALON Õ (Clontech) affinity 
chromatography followed by Superdex-200 gel filtration 
(3). The standard ACNase reaction mixture (10 ml) 
contained 1 fmol of the 32 P-labeled E. coli tRNA Lys or 
the indicated [5 0 -32 P] labeled ASL, both at 3000 Ci/mmol; 
2 mM dTTP, 4 mM Na-HEPES buffer, pH 7.5; 0.5 mM 
MgCl 2 , 15 mM NaCl, 5% glycerol and 0.5 M 
trimethylamine-N-oxide (TMAO). The reaction was </p>

<p>Figure 1. ASL analogs of tRNA Lys and their modified bases. (A and B) Secondary structure presentations and indicated tRNA positions of 
ASL-3 and ASL-C, respectively. (C) Notations and structures of modified ASL bases. U9 (mcm 5 s 2 U), A9 (ms 2 t 6 A) appear in human tRNA Lys3 , 
U8 (mnm 5 s 2 U) and A7 (t 6 A) in corresponding positions of E. coli tRNA Lys and É appears in both. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Sequences of LARP and LARP derivatives used in this work. 
All the peptides used were protected at their N-and C-ends by 
respective acetyl and amide groups. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 4705 </p>

<p>performed at 108C. It was initiated by adding the enzyme 
and terminated at the indicated time by adding 1.5 vol of 
10 M urea, 0.01% bromphenol blue and 0.01% xylene 
cyanol. The products were separated by polyacrylamide-
urea gel electrophoresis and quantified by densitometry or 
counting. </p>

<p>Peptide-RNA UV-cross-linking </p>

<p>Peptide-RNA UV-cross-linking was performed in 
mixtures (10 ml) containing $0.1 pmol of [5 0 -32 P] labeled 
ASL-3, 0.1-2.0 nmol of Lys-anticodon recognizing peptide 
(LARP) or indicated LARP derivative, 5 mM Na-HEPES 
buffer, pH 7.5; 1 mM MgCl 2 , 30 mM NaCl, 0.5-1.0 M 
TMAO and 10% glycerol. The mixture was placed in a 
35-mm polystyrene culture dish and irradiated for 5 min at 
48C over a TFX-20 M transilluminator providing radia-
tion spectrum with a peak at 312 nm. Aliquots were mixed 
with 1.5 vol of 10 M urea containing 0.01% each of xylene 
cyanol and bromphenol blue and separated by denaturing 
gel electrophoresis. </p>

<p>PrrC-RNA UV-cross-linking </p>

<p>ThePrrC mutant proteins H356A and H356A/F292S were 
cross-linked to ASL-3 in 12 ml ACNase reaction mixtures 
essentially as described above but containing 0.3 pmol of 
ASL-3 and $1 mg of the indicated PrrC allele purified by 
TALON cobalt affinity chromatography. The mixture was 
irradiated for 5 min at 48C as described for the LARP-
ASL-3 cross-linking. An equal volume of 2Â SDS-PAGE 
gel sample buffer devoid of reducing agent was added and 
the products separated by 10% SDS-PAGE. The proteins 
were transferred then to a nitrocellulose membrane, PrrC </p>

<p>monitored by immunoblotting using anti-PrrC antibodies 
(17) and the PrrC/ASL-3 cross-linking product detected 
by autoradiography. </p>

<p>Glutaraldehyde (GA)-mediated protein-protein cross-linking </p>

<p>The indicated PrrC forms were subjected to GA-mediated 
protein-protein cross-linking as previously described and 
the products monitored by immunoblotting (3). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The synthetic 11-mer LARP matching PrrC residues 
284-294 inhibits ACNase activity </p>

<p>Mutations that alter ACNase cleavage specificity have 
implicated PrrC's Asp 287 in tRNA Lys recognition (17-19). 
Asp 287 maps to a consensus sequence shared by a subset of 
the known PrrC homologs. This sequence comprises a 
predicted coil region (284-92) and the essential aromatic 
residues Phe 292 and Tyr 294 (Figure 3) (3,17). Its possible 
role in tRNA Lys recognition was investigated using an 
end-protected 
mimic 
(Ac-KYGDSNKSFSY-NH 2 ). 
This mimic was termed LARP to indicate its anticipated 
function. LARP inhibited PrrC's ACNase activity in a 
dose-dependent manner when assayed with E. coli 
tRNA Lys (Figure 4A and B) or ASL analogs 
(Figure 4C-E). An IC 50 value of $10 -4 M was obtained 
in all cases. The inhibition decreased with increasing 
substrate level within the range examined (Figure 4F 
and G). These results hinted that LARP acted by 
occluding the RNA substrate and/or competing with the 
substrate over the protein. </p>

<p>279 
287 
330aa(Eco) 
| 
| 
| 
SSpro 
EEEECCCCCCCCCHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHCCHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHC 
Jpred 
EEECCCCCCCCCCHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHCCHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHHCC </p>

<p>Eco 
ALTEKYGDSNKSFSYHLHLKQTIEQAIADNNVERYHFTLLRNLYEKTASFL 
Yfr 
EIEDKKGDSNKSFSYHLYIKRLIEQAIEKNEVQRYHFTLLRNLYEKSANFL 
Nme 
DILEKQGDSNKSFSYHLHLKGVIEKAIENQQVERFHFMLLRNLYEKTANFL 
Hin 
DLEEKQGGSNKSFSYHLFLRNLLE-EVESKDIQKYHFMLLRNLYEKTANFL 
Apl 
ELHTKKGDSNTSFNYHIYLKHTLENAISNNAIEKYHFTLLRNLYEKTASFL 
Lin 
SYELANQSTDSPFSYHLHLKAELEKAIETGQLHKYHFNFLRNILEKTSTFV 
Plu 
TYQLAIQPNDSPFSYHLYLKSELEKAIENGQLSKYHFNFLRNILEKTSTFL 
Rhp 
TFSLSPQPNDSPFSYHLYLLRELQAASENGEIKKYHFNFIRNILEKSSTFL 
Smu 
KYLLNSQDNDAPFAYHLMLVDELKKAIAEDRVEKYHFNLLRNLLEKTATFL 
Bli 
GWTLARQSKDSPFSYHLGIIKDIQEAISANAIERSHFNQFRALLEKTANFL 
: :*: 
: 
: 
** 
* : *::: * </p>

<p>Figure 3. Multiple sequence alignment of a region containing a residue implicated in tRNA Lys recognition. Escherichia coli PrrC (indicated by Eco) 
residues 279-330 were aligned using <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> (31) with corresponding portions of representative homologs detected by BLAST (32). Secondary 
structure predictions according to SSpro (33) and <rs type="software">Jpred</rs> (34) are indicated above the alignment. The region corresponding to LARP in a subset of the 
homologs is shaded. The arrows indicate residues whose replacement by Cys triggered intersubunit cross-links (Figure 9). The PrrC homologs 
indicated by the three-letter abbreviations are encoded by the following bacteria and indicated by the respective accession numbers: Yfr-Yersinia 
frederiksenii ATCC 33641, ZP_00829622.1; Nme-Neisseria meningitidis MC58, Hin-Haemophilus influenzae R2846, ZP_00154666.1; 
Lin-Leptospira interrogans serovar Copenhageni str. (Lin.), NC_005823.1; YP_000904.1; Photorhabdus luminescens subsp. laumondii TTO1 (Plu), 
NP_931496.1; RhpRhodopseudomonas palustris HaA2, NZ_AALQ01000003.1; Smu-Streptococcus mutans, NC_004350.1; Bli-Brevibacterium linens 
BL2 H, NZ_AAGP01000001.1. Identical residues shared by all homologs are marked in red, conserved residues in green. </p>



<p>LARP UV-cross-links ASL-3 </p>

<p>The possible interaction of LARP with the ACNase 
substrate was tested by attempting to UV-cross-link the 
peptide to ASL-3. The cross-linking was performed at 
312 nm where the tRNA Lys wobble base is highly 
photoreactive (26). Several cross-linking products were 
obtained in amounts proportional to the dose of LARP 
(Figure 5A and B). The most abundant (designated a) was 
retarded in gel electrophoresis relative to ASL-3 by the 
equivalent of $4 nt, possibly due to a single LARP </p>

<p>adduct. Slower migrating products designated b-d could 
contain additional LARP moieties, judged from their 
incremental retardations and dependence on LARP. 
Presumably, they arose through peptide-peptide cross-
links since data shown below suggested that LARP could 
also self-interact (Figures 8 and 9). The non-irradiated 
mixture yielded weaker bands over a continuous distri-
bution trailing behind ASL-3 (lane 2), probably non-
covalent complexes that partially dissociated during the 
fractionation. </p>

<p>Figure 4. LARP inhibits ACNase activity. (A) Effect of LARP on the PrrC-catalyzed cleavage of E. coli tRNA Lys . The ACNase assay was performed 
in the presence of the indicated LARP levels and aliquots analyzed at the indicated time points. (B) Time course of the reactions of panel A. 
(C and D) Effect of LARP on the respective PrrC-catalyzed cleavages of ASL-3 or ASL-C. Only 15-min time points are shown. (E) ASL-3 or ASL-C 
cleavage by PrrC versus LARP's level. (F and G) Effect of LARP on ACNase activity at different ASL-3 levels. tRNA Lys fr. 1-33, ASL-3 fr. 1-7 and 
ASL-C fr. 1-7, respective labeled ACNase cleavage products of tRNA Lys , ASL-3 and ASL-C. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 4707 </p>

<p>Mutating LARP impairs the ASL-cross-linking and 
ACNase-inhibiting activities </p>

<p>LARP was mutated to evaluate the importance of its 
sequence to the ASL-cross-linking and ACNase-inhibiting 
activities. Trimmed derivatives lacking Lys 1 (Á1) or Tyr 11 
(Á11) formed UV-cross-links to ASL-3 $ 7-or 3-fold less 
efficiently than LARP, respectively (Figure 6A). The 
conjugates obtained with the trimmed mutants (desig-
nated a 0 , a Ã , b 0 and b Ã ) were less retarded than those of 
LARP, possibly due to their lower mass. Á1 and Á11 also 
hardly inhibited ACNase (Figure 6B). 
LARP's sequence was also changed by PrrC missense 
mutations that confer an ACNase null phenotype. These 
mutations: F292S (17), Y294S or Y294F (3) were 
respectively termed F9S, Y11S and Y11F in the peptide 
context. They were introduced in a LARP derivative 
containing an extra N-terminal Cys (CLARP, described in 
more detail later). CLARP was far more efficient than 
LARP both in cross-linking ASL-3 and inhibiting 
ACNase (Figure 8) and using it as the reference peptide 
facilitated the detection of residual mutant activities. </p>

<p>F9S and Y11S impaired the two activities in a 
correlated manner. The milder Y11S mutation reduced 
the yield of the primary UV-cross-linking conjugate with 
ASL-3 nearly 2-fold (Figure 7A, lane 3 versus 4) and 
partially impaired the inhibition of ACNase (Figure 7B, 
lane 3 versus 4). It is noteworthy that this mutation also 
prevented the formation of a stable secondary conjugate, 
as inferred from the absence of the expected band b and 
appearance instead of a smear trailing behind band a. The 
more drastic mutation F9S reduced the cross-linking to 
ASL-3 8-fold (Figure 7A, compare lanes 8 and 9) 
and severely impaired ACNase inhibition (Figure 7B, 
compare lanes 8 and 9). The corresponding PrrC mutation 
F292S could also abrogate the UV-cross-linking of PrrC 
to ASL-3. This was inferred from the observation that the 
active site PrrC mutant H356A, which lacks ACNase 
activity (3) but efficiently binds tRNA Lys (data not 
shown), formed UV-cross-links to ASL-3 $ 30-fold more 
efficiently than F292S/H356A (Figure 7C). 
The Y11F mutation conferred a different phenotype. 
It nearly abolished the ACNase-inhibiting potential of 
CLARP (Figure 7B, compare lanes 2, 3 and 5) yet doubled 
the yield of the primary UV-cross-linking conjugate 
obtained with ASL-3 (Figure 7A, compare lanes 3 and 
5). In part this increase could be ascribed to the failure of 
Y11F to form stable higher conjugates, as with Y11S. 
Nonetheless, the overall cross-linking yield obtained 
with Y11F suggested that this mutant bound ASL-3 at 
least as efficiently as CLARP. The discrepant behavior </p>

<p>Figure 6. Effect of trimming LARP on its ASL-3 cross-linking and 
ACNase-inhibiting activities. (A) The UV-cross-linking of the indicated 
peptides (employed each at 200 mM) to ASL-3 was performed 
essentially as in Figure 3A. (B) Effect of the indicated peptides on 
the PrrC-catalyzed cleavage of ASL-3. The ACNase assay was 
performed essentially as in Figure 2C. a and b indicate respective 
cross-linking products assumed to contain one or two LARP moieties 
per ASL-3; a 0 and b 0 indicate corresponding cross-linking conjugates of 
Á1, a Ã and b Ã indicate cross-linking conjugates of Á11. </p>

<p>Figure 5. LARP UV-cross-links ASL-3. (A) LARP was cross-linked to 
ASL-3 by irradiating their mixture at 312 nm (UV) as detailed in the 
Methods section. Lanes: 1, ASL-3 irradiated alone; 2, Non-irradiated 
mixture of ASL-3 and LARP (330 mM); 3-8, Irradiated mixtures of 
ASL-3 with the respective levels of LARP: 8.25, 16.5, 33, 82.5, 165 or 
330 mM. XC, dye marker corresponding in position to a 22 nt 
oligoribonucleotide; a-d indicate cross-linking products assumed to 
contain one, two, three or four LARP moieties per ASL-3, respectively. 
(B) Relative levels of the primary (a), secondary (b) and tertiary 
(c) conjugates versus that of LARP. The amount of primary conjugate 
formed at the highest LARP level is assigned a value of 1.0. </p>



<p>of Y11F hinted that the ACNase-inhibiting forms of 
LARP exerted their effect not only by occluding the 
RNA substrate but also by forming a binary complex 
with PrrC. Since LARP was employed in excess over 
PrrC and ASL-3, it could exert these two ACNase-
inhibiting modes independently. The possibility that 
LARP interacted with PrrC directly was reinforced by 
data shown below suggesting that both LARP and its 
matching PrrC sequence can self-interact (Figures 8 
and 9). The failure of the Y11S and Y11F mutants to 
form 
stable 
conjugates 
containing 
additional 
peptide moieties could not be ascribed to a critical 
role of Tyr 11 in peptide-peptide UV-cross-linking since 
deleting this residue did not elicit such an effect 
(Figure 6A, lane 5). </p>

<p>Extending LARP with Cys augments its activities under 
suitable redox conditions </p>

<p>LARP derivatives extended at the N-or C-end with Cys 
(CLARP and LARPC, respectively) were intended for 
further modification with Fe-EDTA that rendered them 
artificial nucleases (M. Amitsur, D. Klaiman and 
G. Kaufmann; unpublished data). Unexpectedly, 
CLARP and, to a lesser extent, LARPC were far more 
potent than LARP in UV-cross-linking ASL-3 and 
inhibiting ACNase. Thus, when CLARP, LARPC or 
LARP were UV-cross-linked to ASL-3 at 1 mM DTT and 
identical peptide levels, similar product patterns were 
obtained. However, the product yields with CLARP or 
LARPC were about an order of magnitude higher than </p>

<p>with LARP (Figure 8A). Employing the Cys-containing 
peptides at a level 10-fold lower than that of LARP 
resulted in comparable yields (Figure 8B). CLARP and 
LARPC UV-cross-linked ASL-3 more efficiently than 
LARP also without DTT, LARPC yielding under these 
conditions a relatively high proportion of the secondary 
conjugate (Figure 8C). However, the cross-linking effi-
ciency of CLARP and LARPC to ASL-3 was relatively 
weak at 10 mM DTT (Figure 8D). CLARP and LARPC 
inhibited ACNase more strongly than LARP at 1 mM 
DTT (Figure 8E) but were less effective than LARP at 
10 mM DTT (Figure 8F). 
Thus, tethering Cys to one or the other end of LARP 
enhanced the ACNase-inhibiting and ASL-3 cross-linking 
activities of the peptide although not under highly 
reducing conditions. Moreover, LARPC yielded under 
oxidizing conditions higher proportions of conjugates 
likely to contain two peptide moieties per ASL-3. These 
facts may be accounted for by the stabilization of a 
common functional form of LARP both by a C-terminal 
or N-terminal S-S bond, a requirement satisfied by a 
parallel but not a head-to-tail LARP dimer. An alternative 
explanation is that mere dimerization of LARP by a 
disulfide bond at either end increased the probability of 
non-specific electrostatic, hydrogen bonding and stacking 
interactions between the peptide and the RNA. 
The tethered Cys residue enhanced the UV-cross-
linking efficiency of LARP to ASL-3 optimally at 
intermediate redox conditions (1 mM) rather than oxidiz-
ing conditions. This outcome suggested that 
reversible formation of the disulfide link facilitated the </p>

<p>Figure 7. ASL-3 cross-linking and ACNase-inhibiting activities of missense mutants of CLARP. (A) The UV-cross-linking of CLARP and its 
indicated missense mutants to ASL-3 was performed essentially as in Figure 3A except that the peptide level was only 20 mM. (B) The effect of 
CLARP and its indicated missense mutants on PrrC-catalyzed cleavage of ASL-3 was determined essentially as in Figure 2C except that the peptide 
level was 20 mM. (C) The F292S mutation of PrrC inhibits the UV-cross-linking of the protein to ASL-3. ASL-3 was UV-cross-linked to the indicated 
alleles of PrrC. The products were separated by SDS-PAGE, transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane and detected by immunoblotting and 
autoradiography as detailed in the Methods section. a and b indicate respective cross-linking products assumed to contain one or two LARP moieties 
per ASL-3. ASL-3 fr. 1-7; labeled ACNase cleavage product of ASL-3; PrrC/ASL-3 and PrrC 2 /ASL-3, respective UV-cross-linking products of 
ASL-3 with a PrrC monomer or PrrC dimer. X-linking, cross-linking. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 4709 </p>

<p>fixation of original LARP-LARP and LARP-RNA 
contacts by UV-cross-linking. In other words, a stable 
S-S bond could impede the UV-cross-linking by 
constraining the dimer. </p>

<p>Placing Cys at or near the PrrC region matching LARP 
triggers intersubunit cross-links </p>

<p>The suspicion that LARP exerted its ASL-3 cross-linking 
and ACNase inhibiting activities as a parallel dimer </p>

<p>prompted us to examine if the matching PrrC sequence 
dimerizes similarly. To this end, a Cys residue was 
introduced in this sequence instead of Ser 288 , Ser 291 or 
Ser 293 . We expected that the mutant Cys residues will 
self-interact and form intersubunit disulfide cross-links 
if the region containing them dimerizes in parallel. 
Each of the three mutations was placed over the D222E/ 
C268A/C385A background termed PrrC Ã . This facilitated 
the isolation of the mutant proteins (3,17) and precluded </p>

<p>Figure 8. Cys extensions enhance LARP activities under suitable redox conditions. (A) Terminal Cys extensions enhance the UV-cross-linking of 
LARP to ASL-3. The indicated peptides employed each at 0.2 mM were UV-cross-linked to ASL-3 in the presence of 1mM DTT. (B-D) Effect of the 
DTT level on the cross-linking efficiencies of LARP, CLARP and LARPC on their ability to form UV-cross-links to ASL-3. LARP, CLARP and 
LARPC employed at the indicated concentrations were UV-cross-linked to ASL-3 at 1 mM DTT (panel B), without DTT (panel C) or at 10 mM 
DTT (panel D). (E) Effect of LARP, CLARP and LARPC on ACNase activity at 1 mM DTT. The incubation times were 2 (lanes 2, 5, 8, 11, 14 
and 17), 5 (lanes 3, 6, 9, 12, 15 and 18) and 10 min (lanes 4, 7, 10, 13, 16 and 19). (F) Effect of 10 mM DTT on the ACNase-inhibiting potential of 
LARP, CLARP or LARPC. The incubation times were 2 (lanes 2, 5, 8, 11, 14, 17 and 20), 5 (lanes 3, 6, 9, 12, 15, 18 and 21) and 10 min (lanes 4, 7, 
10, 13, 16, 19 and 22). a-c indicate respective cross-linking products assumed to contain one, two or three LARP moieties per ASL-3; a 0 -c 0 , 
corresponding products of CLARP and LARPC. ASL-3 fr. 1-7, labeled ACNase cleavage product of ASL-3. </p>

<p>4710 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 </p>

<p>the formation of non-specific S-S cross-links due to 
the wild-type Cys residues. The PrrC Ã control 
and to-Cys derivatives exhibited comparable in vivo 
ACNase activities and protein levels (data not shown). </p>

<p>However, only PrrC Ã and S288C/PrrC Ã retained ACNase 
activity in vitro (Figure 9A). 
To induce the formation of S-S cross-links the cells 
expressing the to-Cys mutants or the PrrC Ã control were </p>

<p>Figure 9. Cys substitutions within or near the PrrC region corresponding to LARP trigger inter-subunit cross-links. (A) In vitro ACNase activity of 
PrrC* and the indicated to-Cys derivatives of PrrC*. These PrrC forms were isolated by affinity chromatography and assayed for ACNase activity as 
detailed in the Methods section. (B) Escherichia coli cells expressing the indicated PrrC forms were suspended in 10 mM diamide and incubated at 
108C for the indicated time. The cells were lyzed, their proteins separated in SDS-PAGE without a reducing agent and PrrC visualized by 
immunoblotting. (C) The indicated PrrC forms were purified by TALON Õ immobilized-metal affinity-chromatography and further fractionated by 
SDS-PAGE, as such (lanes 1, 4, 7 and 10), after treatment with 1 mM DTT (lanes 2, 5, 8 and 11) or further treatment with 2 mM diamide (lanes 3, 6, 
9 and 12) and then monitored by immunoblotting. (D) The indicated PrrC forms were treated as in panel C and monitored by protein staining. 
(E) The indicated PrrC forms were subjected to GA-mediated protein-protein cross-linking. (F) The indicated PrrC mutant forms were analyzed as in 
panel B: L298C (lanes 1-3), Q300C (lanes 4-6), I302C (lanes 7-9), I306C (lanes 10-12), PrrC Ã (lanes 13-15), PrrC-D222E (lanes 16-18). The bands 
indicated as Xa and Xb are in respective order the common form of band X generated by the majority of the to-Cys mutants and the faster migrating 
form generated only by Q300. ASL-3 fr. 1-7, labeled ACNase cleavage product of ASL-3 containing residues 1-7; kDa, protein size markers; 2 mers, 
3 mers and 4 mers, indicate cross-linking forms thought to contain 2, 3 or 4 PrrC subunits, respectively; M, PrrC monomer; X, the major S-S cross-
linking product. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 4711 </p>

<p>exposed to diamide (27). The cellular proteins were 
separated then by SDS-PAGE under non-reducing con-
ditions and PrrC visualized by immunoblotting. 
As shown, the three mutants, but not PrrC Ã yielded 
products that migrated in SDS-PAGE slower than the 
$47.5-kDa PrrC monomer (Figure 9B). These products 
included a major form designated X that migrated below 
the 175-kDa size marker as well as several less pronounced 
and faster migrating forms. These various products 
appeared also without diamide, perhaps due to partial 
in vitro oxidation. However, their amounts increased 
considerably with diamide, consistent with their formation 
by disulfide cross-linking. 
To determine if any of the diamide-dependent products 
arose by intra-PrrC cross-links, the four PrrC forms were 
isolated by immobilized metal affinity chromatography in 
the absence of a reducing agent. Subsequently they were 
fractionated by SDS-PAGE as such, after prior treatment 
with 1 mM DTT or also with 2 mM diamide. Western 
analysis revealed that the purified Ser ! Cys mutants, 
but not PrrC Ã , yielded a single product with mobility 
similar to that of band X of the diamide treated cells 
(compare Figure 9C, lanes 1, 4, 7 and 10 to Figure 9B 
lanes 4, 8, 12 and 16). Moreover, this band was abolished 
by DTT (Figure 9C. lanes 2, 5, 8 and 11) and restored by 
excess diamide (lanes 3, 6, 9 and 12), indicating 
it depended on disulfide cross-linking. Corresponding 
protein staining (Figure 9D) ascertained that the various 
PrrC forms were not contaminated by significant amounts 
of other proteins and, consequently, that band X was 
unlikely to contain proteins other than PrrC. The failure 
of a considerable fraction of the to-Cys mutant proteins to 
generate band X could be attributed to its misfolding since 
PrrC is thermally unstable. Alternatively, this fraction 
could represent a functionally relevant conformation 
incompatible with the S-S cross-linking; e.g. due to a 
substrate or inhibitor bound to the tRNA Lys site. 
Band X migrated in SDS-PAGE less than expected of a 
cross-linked PrrC dimer of $95 kDa. This fact could 
be attributed to its particular shape or irreversible </p>

<p>entanglement of two such dimers within the PrrC 
tetramer. To distinguish between these possibilities, we 
subjected PrrC Ã and S293C/PrrC Ã to GA-mediated 
protein-protein cross-linking. PrrC Ã yielded the familiar 
pattern (3) where the monomer is gradually converted into 
apparent GA-cross-linked tetramer forms via dimeric 
and less pronounced trimeric intermediates (Figure 9E, 
lanes 1-4). The monomeric fraction of the mutant 
behaved similarly (lanes 5-8). Band X, which coincided 
with the most retarded GA-cross-linked dimers, was also 
gradually converted into higher forms superimposed over 
those generated by the fraction that failed to form the S-S 
cross-links. These data suggested that band X was a dimer 
that was retarded due to its particular shape. 
We analyzed in a similar fashion PrrC Ã derivatives 
containing Cys in the predicted a-helix found immediately 
downstream to the LARP-like region (Figure 3). 
It replaced L298, I302 or I306 of the a-helix hydrophobic 
face or the hydrophilic Q300. These mutants also 
yielded the S-S cross-linked form designated X, L298C 
yielding the highest proportion (Figure 9F, lanes 1-3), 
possibly due to closer contact of the dimerizing a-helices 
at position 298. Q300C yielded a variant (designated Xb) 
that migrated slightly faster than the form X 
generated by the other mutants designated here Xa 
(Figure 9F, compare lanes 3 and 4, 6 and 7). The slight 
mobility difference may be attributed to the presence of 
Cys 300 at the hydrophilic and, hence, outward-pointing 
face of the dimerizing a-helix. Consequently, an S-S cross-
link mediated by it could constrain the dimer into a 
more compact, faster migrating form. The PrrC mutant 
D222E containing the wild-type residues Cys 268 
and Cys 385 failed to generate band X (Figure 9F, lanes 
16-18). This result underscored the specificity of the 
intersubunit cross-links triggered by the mutant Cys 
residues placed in the 288-306 range. </p>

<p>Peptide mimicry of tRNA Lys recognition by PrrC </p>

<p>LARP formed UV-cross-links to ASL analogs of 
tRNA Lys and inhibited their PrrC-catalyzed cleavage </p>

<p>Figure 10. PrrC's functional organization and possible quaternary topology. (A) Functional organization of PrrC. The crimson bar represents the 
N-proximal NTPase domain, the green bar the C-proximal ACNase domain. The ABC ATPase-like motifs indicated below the bar are, from left to 
right, the Walker A (P-loop), ABC signature, Walker B/D loop and switch region motifs (15). The PrrC-box motif indicated above the bar is unique 
to the PrrC proteins. The D222E mutation in this domain attenuates ACNase activity and facilitates the overproduction and isolation of PrrC (3). 
In the C-proximal ACNase domain are indicated the sequence matching LARP thought to partake in tRNA Lys recognition, the conserved putative 
catalytic residues Arg 320 , Glu 324 and His 356 (3), the seven to-Cys mutations in the 288-306 range and the wild-type Cys residues at the edges of the 
domain that were replaced by Ala in PrrC Ã . (B) Proposed quaternary topology of PrrC. According to this model, the nucleotide binding pockets arise 
by head-to-tail interaction of the regulatory N-domains (crimson rectangles), as in ABC/ATPases (15). The tRNA Lys -sites are formed at parallel 
dimer-dimer interfaces between the ACNase C-domains (green squares). The upper dimer (darker forms) obscures part of the lower dimer 
(paler forms). P-loop, Walker A motif, ABC, ABC signature motif. </p>



<p>(Figures 4 and 5). Moreover, the two activities were 
impaired by trimming LARP (Figure 6) or placing in it 
missense mutations that confer a null ACNase phenotype 
in the PrrC context (Figure 7). Importantly, the CLARP 
mutation F9S and the corresponding inactivating PrrC 
mutation F292S severely inhibited the respective UV-
cross-linking of ASL-3 to the peptide (Figure 7A) or 
protein (Figure 7C). These results could be taken to 
indicate that LARP mimics its matching PrrC sequence 
in tRNA Lys recognition. However, even in that case 
LARP would probably represent only part of PrrC's 
tRNA Lys -binding motif since the level at which it 
effectively inhibited ACNase (Figure 4) far exceeds the 
Km of efficient ACNase substrates (19). Moreover, known 
RNA-binding motifs including that of colicin E5-ACNase 
are several fold longer than LARP (28,29). </p>

<p>The tRNA Lys site of PrrC may arise between C-domains 
interfacing in parallel </p>

<p>The functional relevance of LARP to its matching PrrC 
region was suggested also by the apparent ability of both 
to dimerize in parallel. We deduced that LARP acted as a 
parallel dimer in forming UV-cross-links to ASL-3 and 
inhibiting ACNase from the ability of a single Cys residue 
tethered to either the N-or C-end of LARP to 
dramatically enhance these activities and abolition of 
these enhancements under highly reducing conditions 
(Figure 6). These coincidences could be accounted for by 
the stabilization of a common functional dimeric structure 
of LARP by a disulfide bond formed at one or the other 
end of its protomers, a requirement met by a parallel but 
not anti-parallel dimer. Alternatively, the similar effects of 
the N-and C-proximal Cys extensions reflected the 
increased probability of non-specific peptide-RNA inter-
actions caused by mere dimerization of the peptide, 
whether caused by the N-or C-terminal S-S bond. 
However, we favor the first explanation in view of the 
intersubunit S-S cross-links triggered by all seven 
Cys substitutions placed along the C-proximal PrrC 
288-306aa region overlapping the sequence matching 
LARP (Figure 9). Such an outcome is consistent with 
parallel dimerization of the mutated region and lends 
support to the assumption that LARP could also dimerize 
in this orientation. The PrrC region that dimerizes in 
parallel could be confined to a portion of the ACNase 
domain since the regulatory N-domain is expected 
to dimerize in a head-to-tail fashion, like typical 
ABC/ATPases where the nucleotide binding pocket 
arises by the interaction of the Walker A motif of one 
subunit with the ABC signature motif of the second (15). 
Moreover, the wild-type Cys 268 and 385 at the edges of the 
C-domain (Figure 10A) did not trigger intersubunit cross-
links (Figure 9F). The relation of the PrrC region that 
dimerizes in parallel to the tRNA Lys -binding motif may be 
revealed by accurately mapping and functionally char-
acterizing it. 
Finally, as illustrated in Figure 10B, the opposite 
orientations in which PrrC's N-and C-domains dimerize 
dictate a phosphofructokinase-like topology (30) where </p>

<p>the NTPase and tRNA Lys sites arise at distinct assembly 
stages of the PrrC dimer of dimers (3). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Ezra Yagil for comments and Elena Davidov 
for PrrC mutant proteins. This work was supported by 
grants from the Israel Science Foundation, and the 
German-Israeli Foundation for Scientific Research and 
Development to G.K. and the United-States-Israel 
Binational Science Foundation to G.K. and D.R.D. 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for 
this article was provided by the Israel Science Foundation. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>4714 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 14 </p>

</text></tei>