<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1635254" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:24+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We describe an optimized microarray method for 
identifying genome-wide CpG island methylation 
called microarray-based methylation assessment 
of single samples (MMASS) which directly compares 
methylated to unmethylated sequences within a 
single sample. To improve previous methods we 
used bioinformatic analysis to predict an optimized 
combination of methylation-sensitive enzymes that 
had the highest utility for CpG-island probes and 
different methods to produce unmethylated repres-
entations of test DNA for more sensitive detection of 
differential methylation by hybridization. Subtraction 
or methylation-dependent digestion with McrBC 
was used with optimized (MMASS-v2) or previously 
described (MMASS-v1, MMASS-sub) methylation-
sensitive enzyme combinations and compared with 
a published McrBC method. Comparison was per-
formed using DNA from the cell line HCT116. We 
show that the distribution of methylation microarray 
data is inherently skewed and requires exogenous 
spiked controls for normalization and that analysis 
of digestion of methylated and unmethylated control 
sequences together with linear fit models of 
replicate data showed superior statistical power 
for the MMASS-v2 method. Comparison with pre-
vious methylation data for HCT116 and validation 
of CpG islands from PXMP4, SFRP2, DCC, RARB 
and TSEN2 confirmed the accuracy of MMASS-v2 
results. The MMASS-v2 method offers improved 
sensitivity and statistical power for high-throughput 
microarray identification of differential methylation. </p>

<p>Epigenetic changes are heritable changes that include 
reversible covalent modifications of histone proteins and 
methylation of DNA. The vast majority of mammalian DNA 
methylation is located at the cytosine of CpG dinucleotides 
which are particularly frequent within CpG islands. The 
definition of a CpG island continues to evolve but the follow-
ing criteria are currently accepted (1): a length &gt;500 bp, 
G + C content &gt;50% and CpG dinucleotides at an observed-
to-expected ratio &gt;0.60. Approximately 70% of mammalian 
genomic CpG dinucleotides are methylated and commonly 
occur within repetitive elements (2). In contrast, most 
unmethylated CpG islands span the promoter regions 
of house-keeping genes and tumour suppressor genes 
and are critical in gene expression regulation and cell 
differentiation (3). 
The number of cancer-related genes inactivated by epigen-
etic modifications may equal or exceed the number inactiv-
ated by genetic mutations or allele loss (4-10). Therefore, 
the development of high-throughput methods to characterize 
methylated and unmethylated CpG islands in normal and 
neoplastic tissues is vital to enable discovery of methylation 
markers for cancer predisposition as well as understanding 
the role of DNA methylation in neoplastic progression and 
drug resistance (9-11). 
Differential methylation hybridization (DMH) is an array-
based method for comparing the methylation status of CpG 
islands between test samples and a common reference (12- 17). The two DNAs are first digested with MseI to reduce 
the size of genomic fragments followed by a combination 
of methylation-sensitive enzymes that only restrict unmethyl-
ated recognition sequences. The MseI recognition sequence 
(TTAA) is found frequently within bulk DNA, but is rarely 
found within CpG islands which remain intact after digestion 
(18). Subsequent linker-mediated PCR results in amplicons </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +44 1223 256295; Fax: +44 1223 586670; Email: aeki2@cam.ac.uk </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Published online 13 October 2006 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl551 </p>

<p>that are enriched for methylated sequences. The labelled 
amplicons are competitively hybridized and the ratio of test 
to reference signal intensities at each probe on the array 
reflects methylation differences between the two samples. 
Nouzova et al. (19) modified this method by using digestion 
with a methylation-dependent enzyme, the homing endo-
nuclease McrBC. This enzyme has a degenerate methylation 
recognition sequence that only cleaves methylated DNA and 
is very frequent in CpG islands. Amplicons from digested 
DNA therefore represent unmethylated sequences, and com-
petitive hybridization of amplicons from McrBC digested 
and undigested DNA from the same sample was used to 
identify methylated sequences by within-sample comparison. 
This avoided the need for a common reference design 
which is advantageous for profiling clinical samples where 
no appropriate reference tissue may be available or where 
the available reference sample may not have a 'normal' 
methylation pattern. However, a potential disadvantage of 
the Nouzova et al. (19) method is that there is unequal repres-
entation of methylated and unmethylated sequences in a sin-
gle hybridization and this may reduce sensitivity to detect 
differential methylation. 
Previous DMH profiling studies used microarrays for 
which the full sequences of the probes, and consequently 
their restriction map sites, were unknown (12-17). This pre-
vented rational design of the digestion steps and rigorous ana-
lysis of probe performance to exclude artefactual errors (16). 
For example, if a probe sequence lacks the restriction site for 
a methylation-sensitive enzyme that digests unmethylated 
target, the signal from this probe will be falsely assigned as 
methylated. In this work, we used bioinformatic tools to 
provide detailed annotation of all probes on a publicly avail-
able CpG island array and used this information to develop 
and validate a high-throughput method called microarray 
methylation assessment of a single sample (MMASS). We 
show that MMASS offers improved sensitivity to profile 
methylated as well as unmethylated CpG islands from single 
samples. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Cell line </p>

<p>HCT116 colon cancer cells were cultured in McCoy's 5A 
modified medium supplemented with 10% foetal bovine 
serum and 1% penicillin/streptomycin. High-molecular 
weight DNA was isolated using standard proteinase K and 
phenol extraction methods. </p>

<p>Derivation of probe sequences and preparation 
of spike control DNA </p>

<p>Human CpG island arrays containing 13 056 features 
(HCGI12K) were obtained from the Microarray Centre, 
University Health Network, Toronto, Canada (http:// 
www.microarrays.ca/products/types.html#HCGI12K). End 
sequences for the CpG island probes were obtained from 
the Sanger Centre (available from http://www.sanger.ac.uk/ 
HGP/cgi.shtml) and aligned by BLAST (20) against the 
NCBI v.35 human genome assembly. Each probe sequence 
was predicted from contiguous sequence tag alignments </p>

<p>containing two MseI recognition sites as MseI digestion 
was used to create the CpG island library (18). Sequences 
were further annotated with <rs type="software">PERL</rs> scripts using <rs type="software">BioPerl</rs> 
libraries (21) together with data and libraries from 
<rs type="software">Ensemble</rs> (22) (Supplementary Table 1 and Supplementary 
Perl scripts 1-3). Repetitive sequences were identified using 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">repeatmasker</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="url">http://www.repeatmasker.org</rs>). 
Spike control amplicons were prepared by PCR from DNA 
extracted from normal blood. Methylated spikes were methyl-
ated in vitro using SssI (New England Biolabs) following the 
manufacturer's instructions and methylation was confirmed 
by digestion with appropriate methylation-sensitive enzymes 
and gel electrophoresis. Methylated and unmethylated spikes 
were added to the samples before MseI digestion at concen-
trations corresponding to 1-1000 copies (Supplementary 
Table 2). </p>

<p>Preparation of genomic DNA </p>

<p>Genomic representation of methylated and unmethylated 
sequences by enzyme digestion. The MMASS-v1 and 
MMASS-v2 methods used methylation-sensitive and 
methylation-dependent enzyme digestion for within-sample 
comparison (Figure 1). Genomic DNA (2 mg for MMASS-
v1 and 1.2 mg for MMASS-v2 methods) was digested over-
night in a 30 ml volume using 20 U MseI at 37 
C. Digested 
DNA was then ligated to the linkers H-14 5 
0 -tactccctcggata-
3 
0 and H-24 5 
0 -aggcaactgtgctatccgagggag-3 
0 which prevented 
reconstitution of the MseI site. Ligation was carried out in a 
mixture comprising 30 ml MseI digested DNA, 16 mM 
annealed linkers, 10· ligase buffer, 1.5 ml of 10 mM ATP, 
6 ml PEG 6000, 400 U T4 DNA ligase and 10 U MseI in a 
total volume of 60 ml at 20 
C for 4 h. The ligated DNA frag-
ments were purified using the Qiaquick PCR purification kit 
(Qiagen), eluted in 100 ml water and vacuum dried. For rep-
resentation of unmethylated sequences, half the sample was 
restricted with McrBC, after resuspension in 40 ml water 
with 10· NEB buffer 2, 10· GTP, 10· BSA and 20 U 
McrBC at 37 
C for 4 h. For representation of methylated 
sequences, the other half of the sample was restricted by 
either the combination of BstUI, HhaI and HpaII (MMASS-
v1) in a volume of 30 ml (17) or the combination of AciI, 
HinP1I, HpyCH4IV and HpaII (MMASS-v2) in a volume 
of 70 ml with 10· NEB buffer 1, 10· BSA and 20 U of 
each of the enzymes. A further 10 U of each enzyme was 
added after 4 h for the MMASS-v2 method and the reaction 
was allowed to continue for a further 2 h. </p>

<p>Genomic representation of unmethylated sequences by 
subtraction. The MMASS-sub method used subtractive 
hybridization to obtain the unmethylated representation 
from the starting DNA (Figure 1). Amplicons representing 
methylated CpG islands were prepared using the MMASS-
v1 method as above by digesting 2 mg of DNA and using 
both halves for methylation-sensitive enzyme digestion. 
One amplicon was then used as the subtractor DNA from 
an additional 1 mg of the test DNA digested with MseI. 
Subtraction was performed using biotin-labelling (BioNick 
Labeling System; Invitrogen) of the subtracter DNA and 
recovery with streptavidin-coated magnetic particles (Strep-
tavidin Magnetic Particles; Roche Diagnostics) following 
the manufacturer's recommendations and as described </p>

<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>

<p>
previously (23). The resulting subtracted DNA (unmethylated 
representation) was then amplified as below before being 
hybridized against the remaining methylated amplicon. </p>

<p>Representation using Nouzova method </p>

<p>The Nouzova et al. (19) method was carried using both indir-
ect labelling (see below) and as described previously using 
direct incorporation of Cy3-or Cy5-labelled dCTP and co-
hybridization with Cot-1 DNA. </p>

<p>PCR amplification </p>

<p>Each restricted DNA sample was purified using a Qiaquick 
PCR purification column (Qiagen) and eluted in 100 ml 
water. PCR amplification was performed in a 300 ml volume 
comprising 100 ml digested DNA, 10· thermo-start buffer 
(Applied Biosystems), 100 mM MgCl, 25% DMSO, 
200 mM Betaine (Sigma), 0.5 mM H-24 primer, 0.1 mM 
dNTP mixture and 6 U Deep Vent R (exo 
À ) DNA polymerase 
(New England Biolabs). The thermocycling conditions were 
5 min at 72 
C to fill in the overhanging ends of the ligated 
DNA fragments, followed by 21 cycles (25 cycles for the 
MMASS-v2 method) of 1 min at 94 
C, 1 min at 65 
C and 
3 min at 72 
C, with a final extension for 10 min at 72 
C. 
Five microlitres of the PCR product was electrophoresed on </p>

<p>a 1.5% agarose gel and a diffuse smear pattern between 
0.2 and 2kb was taken to indicate successful PCR amplifica-
tion as described previously (17). </p>

<p>Labelling and hybridization </p>

<p>For each methylated and unmethylated amplicon 300 ng of 
PCR product was vacuum dried and resuspended in 33 ml 
of water with 2.5· random primer buffer (BioPrime Labeling 
Kit; Invitrogen) together with 0.5 ng of control Arabidopsis 
thaliana cDNA (synthesized from pARAB obtained from 
the Microarray Centre, University Health Network, Toronto, 
Canada) and denatured at 95 
C for 5 min. Each denatured 
sample was placed on ice with 7.5 ml of 10· dNTP mixture 
(2 mM each of dATP, dCTP and dGTP, and 0.35 mM 
dTTP), 1.8 ml of 10 mM aminoallyl-dUTP together with 
80 U Klenow Fragment and incubated at 37 
C for 2 h then 
stopped with 5 ml of stop buffer (BioPrime Kit). The total vol-
ume was increased to 425 ml with water and unincorporated 
aminoallyl-dUTP was removed by two centrifugations at 
10 000 r.p.m. using a Microcon YM30 concentrator (Milli-
pore). Purified sample was collected by centrifuging the 
inverted column at 4500 r.p.m. for 5 min and then vacuum 
dried. Each sample was reconstituted in 4.5 ml of water 
together with 4.5 ml Cy dye (Amersham-Pharmacia Biotech) </p>

<p>TTAA 
TTAA 
TTAA </p>

<p>Linker PCR </p>

<p>Label 
Label </p>

<p>Mix and hybridise </p>

<p>Linker PCR </p>

<p>Digest 
unmethylated CpG </p>

<p>Digest 
methylated CpG </p>

<p>MseI digestion and adaptor ligation 
± control spikes </p>

<p>Mix and hybridise </p>

<p>Linker PCR </p>

<p>Digest 
unmethylated CpG </p>

<p>Digest 
unmethylated CpG </p>

<p>Linker PCR </p>

<p>Digest with MseI </p>

<p>Linker PCR </p>

<p>Label </p>

<p>Label </p>

<p>TTAA 
TTAA 
TTAA </p>

<p>MseI digestion and adaptor ligation 
± control spikes </p>

<p>Figure 1. MMASS method. (a) DNA from HCT116 was digested with MseI (restriction sequence TTAA) followed by adaptor ligation and addition of control 
spikes as appropriate. (b) One-half of the sample was digested with McrBC (to cut methylated sequences) and the other by a combination of methylation-
sensitive enzymes (to cut unmethylated sequences). (c) Linker-mediated PCR resulted in two amplicons representing methylated and unmethylated sequences 
which were (d) labeled then (e) mixed and hybridised to the CpG island array. For the MMASS-sub method, an amplicon representing methylated sequences 
prepared as described above was subtracted from a MseI digested sample (f) resulting in DNA enriched for unmethylated sequences (g). The subtracted 
preparation was subsequently amplified and competitively hybridized against a reciprocal amplicon (h). </p>

<p>PAGE 3 OF 12 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 </p>

<p>in 0.1M sodium bicarbonate titrated with sodium hydroxide 
to pH 9.0. The mixture was held at room temperature in 
the dark for 1.5 h and the coupling reaction was stopped by 
adding 4.5 ml of 4M hydroxylamine and 35 ml of 100 mM 
sodium acetate (pH 5.2). Labelled DNA was purified using 
a Qiaquick PCR purification column and then vacuum 
dried. Both dye-coupled DNAs were then resuspended 
together in 85 ml of DIG Easy Hyb solution (Roche Diagnost-
ics) together with 5 ml of salmon sperm DNA (10 mg/ml) and 
denatured at 95 
C for 5 min. The hybridization mixture was 
allowed to cool briefly and 5 ml of yeast tRNA (10 mg/ml) was 
added and the mixture was held at 65 
C for 2 min and 
allowed to cool to room temperature. Hybridization to the 
microarray was carried out under a cover slip in a humidified 
chamber at 37 
C for 8 h. The cover slip was floated off in 1· 
SSC and each slide was washed three times in 1· SSC and 
0.1% SDS at 50 
C for 15 min followed by removal of SDS 
at room temperature in 1· SSC and 0.1· SSC for 5 min 
each. The slides were dried by centrifugation at 500 r.p.m. 
for 5 min and scanned immediately using the GenePix 
4000A scanner (Axon). The settings for PMT gain were 
adjusted during the initial rapid scan to achieve a balance 
between the two channels and these settings were used for 
the high resolution scan. <rs id="software-7" type="software">GenePix</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-7" type="version-number">4.1</rs> was used to 
perform image analysis and feature segmentation. </p>

<p>COBRA </p>

<p>Sodium bisulphite conversion of HCT116 DNA was per-
formed as described previously (24,25). PCR was then per-
formed on bisulphite-modified DNA samples using primers 
designed to amplify both methylated and unmethylated 
DNA (Supplementary Table 3). This was followed by restric-
tion digestion using appropriate enzymes that contain CpG 
within their recognition sequence as these will change in 
the DNA samples if the original cytosine bases were 
unmethylated and followed by quantification using electro-
phoresis on a 2.5% agarose gel. </p>

<p>Microarray analysis </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">limma</rs> (26) package within the <rs type="software">R</rs> environment (27) was 
used to background-correct, normalize and analyse the data. 
Where the background exceeded the foreground intensity, 
the minimum background value for the array was subtracted 
rather than the local background measurement of the spot. 
We combined replicate dye-swap arrays for each method 
using the linear model and empirical Bayes smoothing 
procedures available in the <rs type="software">limma</rs> package. A full transcript 
of all statistical code and the results of computations are pro-
vided in the Supplementary Sweave document which allows 
the analysis to be examined and repeated exactly (28-30). 
The raw data from the array experiments is available from 
the Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO; www.ncbi.nlm.nih. 
gov/geo) under the series accession number GSE5326. </p>

<p>Calculation of spike statistics </p>

<p>For each spiked probe we obtained the spike, digestion and 
non-digestion effect statistics which represented the spike 
amount (compared to background level) and the amount 
of the spike that was digested and undigested, respectively. 
The spike effect was estimated from the difference in </p>

<p>log-intensities between the spiked and unspiked experiments. 
For the comparisons between labelling methods, intensities 
were obtained from the channel in which the spike was 
not expected to be digested and averaged between arrays. 
The digestion effect was defined as the difference in 
log-ratios between the spiked (M 
0 ) and non-spiked (M) 
arrays for methylated (D m i ¼ 
M M </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>i À 
M M i ) and unmethylated 
(D u i ¼ 
M M i À 
M M </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>i ) spiked probes (i), respectively. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Analysis of probe sequences </p>

<p>We first used bioinformatic methods to predict the complete 
sequence for all probes on the CpG island arrays, as at the 
start of the project only end-sequence tags were available 
(18). The majority of the library was subsequently fully 
sequenced by the University Health Network Microarray 
Centre, Toronto (sequences available at http://derlab.med. 
utoronto.ca/CpGIslands/). After BLAST comparison to the 
human genome 5435 out of 13 056 (41.6%) probes were 
selected that had a percentage identity of &gt;97% and &lt;30% 
masked repeat elements and these were annotated as single 
copy sequences. A further 1190 probes (9.1%) contained 
100% repeat sequences and the remainder was either not 
identifiable or had an intermediate percentage of repetitive 
sequences. The restriction sites for all commercially available 
methylation-sensitive enzymes were identified for unique 
probes together with the distance to the nearest neighbouring 
genes and the percentage and type of included repetitive 
sequences (Supplementary Table 1). 
From these analyses, we found that 4160 out of 5435 
(76.5%) of the probes on the CpG array would be informative 
when using the previously described combination of BstUI, 
HpaII and HhaI enzymes to generated representations 
of methylated target DNA (17). We predicted that using a 
novel combination of four enzymes (AciI, HpaII, HinP1I 
and HpyCH4IV) would utilize 4403 out of 5435 (81%) of 
the array probes and therefore improve utility. In addition 
this combination of enzymes was more convenient as all 
four enzymes could digest efficiently in the same buffer. In 
contrast, digestion with BstUI, HpaII and HhaI required a 
two-step digestion protocol with an additional purification 
step. 
We hypothesized that the sensitivity of array-based 
methylation detection could be improved if greater contrast 
could be achieved between methylated and unmethylated 
signal. We therefore evaluated two different methods for gen-
erating representations of unmethylated sequences. First, we 
used McrBC to digest methylated DNA in one-half of the 
sample for comparison against digestion with the combina-
tions of methylation-sensitive enzymes above (MMASS-v1 
and MMASS-v2; Figure 1). Second, we used subtractive 
hybridization using a subtractor DNA digested with BstUI, 
HpaII and HhaI (MMASS-sub; Figure 1). </p>

<p>Exploratory data analysis </p>

<p>For each of the methods we obtained four microarray hybrid-
izations, using replicate biological preparations in a balanced 
dye-swap design and compared the results to the method of </p>

<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>

<p>
Nouzova et al. (19). DNA from the colorectal cancer cell line 
HCT116 was used for all experiments as methylation patterns 
have been well characterized in this cell line (31,32). 
The overall quality of individual hybridizations was 
assessed by inspection of MA and spatial plots (33) for 
each of the arrays (Figure 2 and Supplementary Sweave 
document). Unsatisfactory array experiments were repeated 
and 16 high-quality hybridizations were obtained from a 
total of 19 experiments. 
Log ratios (M) for control A.thaliana probes showed little 
variation around M ¼ 0 indicating high reproducibility 
(Figure 2). Inspection of blank spots showed uniform low 
intensities as expected (Figure 2). In contrast to MA plots 
from expression array and array CGH experiments, the distri-
bution of log-ratios from MMASS and Nouzova experiments 
was not symmetrical. It is important to note that for the 
Nouzova et al. (19) method the log-ratios should theoretically 
all be positive, as a mixture of methylated and unmethylated 
sequences was directly compared to unmethylated sequences. 
Comparison between arrays showed that each method had 
a characteristic distribution of data points on the MA plot 
that was highly consistent between replicate experiments. 
For the MMASS-v2 and the MMASS-sub methods there </p>

<p>was a bimodal distribution of log-ratios at higher probe 
intensities (Figures 2 and 3) indicating increased separation 
between methylated and unmethylated sequences. 
We evaluated different strategies for optimum normali-
zation of each method and these are discussed in detail in 
the Supplementary Sweave document. The A.thaliana probes 
proved unreliable for location normalization except for the 
MMASS-v2 method where pipetting error was well con-
trolled, allowing the use of median correction (Supplement-
ary Figure S1). Replicate arrays for the MMASS-v1 and 
Nouzova methods were sufficiently comparable after global 
loess normalization. For the MMASS-sub method, normaliza-
tion was performed using a subset of high-intensity methyl-
ated clones that demonstrated consistent log-ratios between 
replicate arrays (Supplementary Figure S2). </p>

<p>Identification of differentially methylated probes </p>

<p>For each of the methods we fitted a linear model followed 
by empirical Bayes smoothing to obtain B statistics (26,34)  so that probes could be ranked by the likelihood of differen-
tial methylation. Volcano plots summarizing the results 
showed striking differences in the B statistics obtained from </p>

<p>Figure 2. MA plots of methylation profiling experiments. Columns show replicate arrays for the MMASS-v1, MMASS-v2, MMASS-sub and Nouzova et al. (19) 
methods. Positive M values represent increased ratio of methylated sequences and negative M values increased ratio of unmethylated sequences (except for the 
Nouzova et al. method where the negative M values are artefactual as no differential signal should be obtained from unmethylated sequences). A values represent 
average fluorescence intensity. Coloured points are A.thaliana, green; mitochondrial DNA, purple; empty points, orange. Linear lines at low A values are 
artefacts from background subtraction. </p>

<p> 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 </p>

<p>each method (Figure 3). Most notably, the Nouzova method 
gave a very low and limited range of B statistics demonstrat-
ing a lack of power to assess methylation. In contrast, the 
MMASS-v2 and MMASS-sub methods resulted in much 
higher B values indicating better assessment of methyla-
tion. However, compared to the MMASS-v2 method, the 
MMASS-sub method was more variable as shown by the 
wide spread of points with low B values in the MMASS-
sub method volcano plot (Figure 3). The MMASS-v2 method 
resulted in markedly higher B values than the MMASS-v1 
method. The poor discrimination of the Nouzova data was 
surprising. To exclude artefact caused by our use of indirect 
labelling or different hybridization conditions, we repeated 
the original protocol exactly as described for four additional 
arrays. No significant increase in performance was obtained 
by using the unmodified protocol (Supplementary Sweave 
document). 
We next examined results for mitochondrial DNA and 
repetitive element probes as these are known to be substan-
tially unmethylated and methylated, respectively (35-37). 
The MA plots showed the mitochondrial DNA to be con-
sistently unmethylated in data from the MMASS methods 
(Figure 2). However the Nouzova et al. (19) method had 
poor sensitivity for distinguishing unmethylated mitochon-
drial genes. Ranking by B statistics showed that the top 
unmethylated probes were mitochondrial DNA sequences 
and that the most methylated probes were repeat elements 
(Figure 4). It is important to note that as mitochondrial and 
repetitive sequences are present in high copy number in the 
genome (36) and over-represented on the HCG12K arrays 
(see earlier), more consistent probe measurements would be </p>

<p>expected, making it easier to detect differential methylation 
for these probes as compared to single copy genes. 
We then assessed the effect of spiking in vitro methylated 
and unmethylated target DNAs into the hybridization samples 
as positive and negative controls for the detection of methyl-
ated and unmethylated sequences. We first labelled 32 can-
didate spikes and hybridized them to two HCGI12K arrays 
to test the stringency of hybridization (Supplementary Figure 
S3). Eight spikes which showed correct hybridization and had 
the largest spike effects (Supplementary Figure S4) were 
selected for further analysis. Adequacy of in vitro methyla-
tion was confirmed with BstUI digestion (Supplementary 
Figure S5) and spikes that were poorly methylated or that 
had inconsistencies between predicted and actual DNA 
sequence were excluded from analysis. The spikes were 
added to two hybridizations for each method leaving the 
remaining two unspiked so that background measurements 
for spiked probes could be established. 
To quantify the amount by which the spikes were digested, 
we calculated the spike effect at each of the four methylated 
and unmethylated spiked probes and compared this to the 
spike remaining after digestion (Figure 5 and Supplementary 
Figure S4). For unmethylated spikes, the largest spike effect 
was seen for probes shown in Figure 5g and h where almost 
complete digestion by the MMASS-v1 and MMASS-v2 
methods was observed. As expected there was minimal diges-
tion by the Nouzova et al. (19) method as McrBC does not 
restrict unmethylated sequences. The spike effect at probes 
shown in Figure 5 e and f was too small to allow meaningful 
interpretation. For methylated spikes (Figure 5a-d) the 
largest digestion effect was observed for the MMASS-sub </p>

<p>Figure 3. Correlation between COBRA and array methylation results. Plots show data from the linear model fitted to replicate arrays for each of the MMASS-v1, 
MMASS-v2, MMASS-sub and Nouzova et al. (19) methods. MA plots (upper panel) and volcano plots (lower panel) are shown. Coloured probes 
indicate validation results from COBRA analysis. Orange indicates confirmed as methylated and blue indicates unmethylated. Legend shows probe id. See also 
Supplementary Table 3. </p>

<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>

<p>
and MMASS-v2 method. However the subtraction process 
could also have attenuated the spiked sequences, increasing 
the apparent effect. There was little digestion effect seen 
for the Nouzova (19) and MMASS-v1 methods. 
To validate the results for single copy genes, we selected 
14 probes randomly within low, medium and high average 
probe intensity (A) ranges and compared results from array 
hybridizations from each MMASS method with independent 
assessment by COBRA (Figure 3, Supplementary Figure S6 
and Supplementary Table 3). Although COBRA only surveys 
two to four CpGs in an amplicon, our experience in cancer 
samples is that this gives a good indication of the methylation 
status of the locus. Results from probes with A values higher 
than the median intensity of the A.thaliana control spots 
were more consistent with the COBRA results and these </p>

<p>higher intensity probes were also more consistent 
across all MMASS methods (Figure 3 and Supplementary 
Table 3). 
The MMASS-sub method resulted in greatest separation 
between the methylated and unmethylated COBRA validated 
clones (Figure 3). The ranking of the MMASS probes by 
degree of methylation was consistent with full and partial 
methylation results detected by COBRA (Figure 3 and 
Supplementary Table 3). </p>

<p>Validation of methylation of cancer-related genes </p>

<p>We then examined 325 single copy probes identified by 
the MMASS-v2 method with values of B &gt; À3 as this cut-
off was consistent with the COBRA validation experiments </p>

<p>gene 
LINE1(GC=58%) 
LINE1(GC=59%) 
LINE1(GC=58%) 
LINE1(GC=53%) 
LINE1(GC=55%) 
LINE1(GC=55%) 
ALUs and LINE1(46%) 
ALUs(GC=47%) 
ALUs(GC=58%) 
ALUs(GC=56%) 
ALUs(GC=63%) 
ALUs(GC=55%) 
ALUs and LINE2(GC=48%) 
LINE1(GC=55%) 
LINE1(GC=56%) 
ALUs(GC=52%) 
ALUs(GC=47%) 
ALUs and ERVL(GC=46%) 
ALUs and ERV_1(GC=46%) 
ALUs(GC=48%) 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
NADHubiquinone oxireduc. 
NADHubiquinone oxireduc. 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II 
Cytochrome b. 
Cytochrome c oxidase polypeptide II </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>-6 
-4 
-2 
0 
2 </p>

<p>Figure 4. Mitochondrial and repetitive sequence probes show highest differential methylation. Volcano plot of linear fit model combining four experiments 
using the MMASS-v2 method. The top 20 methylated and unmethylated sequences are plotted as vermilion and blue points respectively. Legend shows 
probe type. </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 12 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 </p>

<p>(Supplementary Table 4). From these, 22 were selected that 
were proximal to genes reported previously as having cancer-
related functions (Figure 6), including DNA replication and 
repair (PMS2L4, MCM7 and BRCA1) and tumour suppressor 
function in colorectal cancer (SFRP2) (38). Validation of the 
methylation status of five CpG islands (PXMP4, SFRP2, 
DCC, RARB and the unmethylated housekeeping gene 
TSEN2) confirmed correct array results using COBRA or 
MSP (Supplementary Figure S7). Our array result for 
HNRPA2B1 (Figure 6) was not in agreement with previous 
data that has shown it to be unmethylated in HCT116 (39) 
but we were unable to obtain a satisfactory MSP result to 
confirm this (data not shown). The reproducibility of the 
MMASS-v2 method was also demonstrated by the finding 
of very similar B values for several duplicate probes from sin-
gle copy genes, including MCM7 (Figure 6 and Supplement-
ary Figure S8). 
We also examined array data from 23 probes representing 
9 genes (SYK, ZFP37, DIRAS3, RARB, LMX1A, DAPK1, 
SFRP2, FAT and RASSF1) that have been reported previously 
to be methylated in HCT116 (32,40). Inspection of MA and 
volcano plots for each of the four methods (Figure 7) showed 
that the MMASS-v2 results were most consistent with previ-
ous data. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Genomic profiling of methylated and unmethylated sequences 
using methylation-sensitive restriction enzyme digestion and 
hybridization to microarrays is a potentially powerful and 
convenient technique. However, in contrast to work carried </p>

<p>out on expression microarray data, no detailed assessment 
of the effects of different protocols or analysis methods has 
been performed (17,19,31,41,42). We have developed and 
optimized new restriction enzyme methods to profile both 
methylated and unmethylated sequences within a single 
sample. 
The three MMASS methods resulted in very consistent 
data representation between replicate experiments but there 
were marked differences in sensitivity. The MMASS-sub 
method increased the power to resolve methylation dif-
ferences as compared to the previously published Nouzova 
et al. (19) method, but also increased noise (Figure 3). The 
subtraction steps were time consuming, and there remains a 
theoretical disadvantage that the subtraction may compound 
errors caused by partial digestion. For example, an excess 
of the partially digested sequences in the subtracter DNA 
amplicon could result in disproportionate removal of target 
DNA and a skewed representation of methylation. The 
MMASS-v2 method resulted in better representation of the 
methylation status of the target DNA (Figure 7) and had 
less noise, and therefore increased power, as compared to 
other methods (Figures 3 and 7). This may be in part because 
of better digestion of unmethylated sequences (Figure 5). As 
additional fresh enzymes were added in the MMASS-v2 
method and digestion was carried out in a single step using 
one buffer-enzyme combination, minimizing potential loss 
of sample. 
The poor performance of the Nouzova et al. (19) method 
was surprising and cannot be explained simply by technical 
reasons, such as failure of McrBC digestion, as all exp-
eriments were carried out using the same conditions, batch </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>a 
b 
c 
d </p>

<p>methylated spikes </p>

<p>Combined 
MMASS-v1 
MMASS-v2 
MMASS-sub </p>

<p>Nouzova et al 
Combined 
MMASS-v1 
MMASS-v2 
MMASS-sub </p>

<p>Nouzova et al 
Combined 
MMASS-v1 
MMASS-v2 
MMASS-sub </p>

<p>Nouzova et al 
Combined 
MMASS-v1 
MMASS-v2 
MMASS-sub </p>

<p>Nouzova et al </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>e 
f 
g 
h </p>

<p>unmethylated spikes </p>

<p>Figure 5. Digestion of methylated and unmethylated spikes. Bar plot shows the spike effect averaged over all the methods (open bars) of methylated (upper 
panel) and unmethylated (lower panel) spiked probes. Non-digestion effects (grey bars) for each probe are shown by method and should be compared to open 
bars. Vertical lines over bars indicate 2 SEs around the mean. </p>

<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>

<p>
of enzyme and in vitro methylated spikes. In addition, the 
dynamic range for probe data was very similar between our 
Nouzova experiments and the original publication. It is pos-
sible that other effects such as array quality or the higher 
genomic complexity of the amplicon from the undigested 
DNA (containing unmethylated and methylated sequences) 
may have altered spike-probe hybridization results. However 
in contrast to MMASS, the Nouzova method has very poor 
sensitivity for detecting hypomethylation (Figure 2) such as 
mitochondrial spots. 
The mixtures being compared by hybridization may 
have had strong effects on sensitivity. The direct comparison 
of methylated to unmethylated representations appears more 
sensitive (larger M values) than comparisons to a mixture 
of methylated and unmethylated sequences as in the Nouzova 
et al. (19) method. The MMASS methods resolved with high 
precision the methylation status for repetitive and mitochon-
drial target DNAs as these are represented in high copy num-
ber in the genome (Figure 4). They also were able to resolve 
single copy CpG methylation and identify correctly the 
methylation status of a number of CpG islands which have 
been described previously to be methylated or unmethylated 
in HCT116 (Figures 6 and 7). 
The bioinformatic analysis of methylation array data is 
very different to that of expression data in which symmetrical 
distribution of log-ratios is assumed and the main aim of 
normalization is to remove dye bias. We show here that 
data distributions from different methods are inherently 
skewed and may be bi-modal at high intensities. It is not 
possible to estimate how much asymmetry to expect since 
this will depend upon the method used and global levels of </p>

<p>methylation in the samples. We have carefully investigated 
and applied appropriate methods for these analyses. From 
these data it is clear that proper normalization is funda-
mentally reliant on exogenous controls including the spiked 
A.thaliana cDNA used here, but better reagents are needed. 
Significant collaborative efforts are now underway for 
designing reproducible control spikes for expression studies 
(43). It is important to note that use of simplistic location-
based normalization in other datasets is likely to have preven-
ted detection of real effects and combining probe-level data 
between different datasets that have used different methods 
and comparator DNAs may be impossible to achieve. 
We were able to optimize our methods by using bioinform-
atic tools to identify and annotate the predicted probe 
sequences on the HCGI12K array and to identify the 
optimum set of restriction enzyme sites to maximize probe 
utilization. Optimization of this enzyme set was based on 
analysis of 5435 CpG island sequences and therefore likely 
to be of high utility to other CpG island platforms. This 
may also have contributed to the improved effects seen 
with the MMASS-v2 method. However, our analysis was lim-
ited by the low number of informative probes caused by 
inclusion of repeat and nonsense sequences from the original 
library. Improved array platforms with better representation 
of all CpG islands across the genome, as well as fine mapping 
within individual CpG islands, are now needed for detailed 
studies. 
MMASS has several advantages over current high-
throughput methods; e.g. MMASS in common with DMH 
employs a universal primer complementary to the ligated 
adaptor rather than a complex sequence-specific primer </p>

<p>TSEN2 
FOXD4L1 
PCDH11X 
PMS2L4 
MCM7 
MCM7 
HECA 
BRIP1 
HSPA2 
PXMP4 
IKIP 
HNRPA2B1 
BRCA1 
CACYBP 
SFRP2 
TUSC4 
TES 
PGD 
DCC 
RARB 
GATA4 
MMP2 
CTMP 
ING4 
ABCD3 </p>

<p>-4 
-2 
0 
4 </p>

<p>-4 </p>

<p>-2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>Figure 6. Methylation results for 22 cancer-related probes in HCT116 using the MMASS-v2 method. Figure shows detail from volcano plot of linear fit model. 
Legend shows gene symbols. </p>

<p>PAGE 9 OF 12 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 </p>

<p>design such as in methylation-specific oligonucleotide micro-
array (44) and MALDI mass spectrometry (45). Methylation 
analysis using BAC microarrays requires the use of rare cut-
ting methylation-sensitive enzymes which limits resolution to 
a single BAC probe, or only provides an average estimate of 
methylation across a large genomic region (46,47). Other 
methods that have used within-sample comparison methyla-
tion analysis have either used non-optimized enzyme com-
binations (48) or complex specific linker/enzyme pairings 
that have not been shown to improve sensitivity (49). 
MMASS is able to resolve the overall methylation status of 
a single copy CpG island probe on a spectrum from mostly 
unmethylated to mostly methylated. Our results also show 
that in contrast to DMH and the Nouzova et al. (19) method, 
we were able to detect unmethylated sequences such as 
housekeeping genes (Figure 6). This will be particularly 
important in the context of the human epigenome project 
and for cancer studies where comparison is needed for both 
methylated and unmethylated sequences (50). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>A.E.K.I. conceived the study, conducted the microarray 
experiments and drafted the manuscript. N.P.T. participated 
in the study design as well as manuscript preparation and 
conducted the analysis. K.B. helped in conducting the 
microarray and COBRA experiments. N.L.B.M. annotated </p>

<p>the array platform sequences and wrote the <rs type="software">Perl</rs> scripts used 
for bioinformatic analysis. S.T. participated in data analysis 
and manuscript preparation. V.P.C. participated in the 
coordination of the study. A.H.W. participated in the 
coordination of the study. M.J.A. participated in designing 
and coordinating the study and manuscript preparation. J.D.B. 
participated in designing the experiments, coordinating the 
study, data analysis and manuscript preparation. All authors 
read and approved the final manuscript. We thank Dr Koichi 
Ichimura for technical advice on genomic hybridization 
protocols. This work was funded by grants from Cancer 
Research UK (CR-UK) and the Department of Pathology, 
University of Cambridge. A.E.K.I. is a CR-UK Bobby Moore 
Fellow and J.D.B. is a CR-UK Senior Clinical Research 
Fellow. N.L.B.-M. is supported by a PhD Fellowship 
(PRAXIS XXI SFRH/BD/2914/2000) from Fundação para a 
Ciência e a Tecnologia, Portugal. Funding to pay the Open 
Access publication charges for this article was provided by 
grants from Cancer Research-UK. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Figure 7. Methylation results for 9 genes (23 independent probes) reported previously to be methylated in HCT116. MA plots (upper panel) and volcano plots 
(lower panel) of linear fit models for each method are shown. Probes representing the same gene are plotted with the same colour. Legend shows gene symbol 
and probe id. </p>

<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>



<p>
PAGE 11 OF 12 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 e136 </p>



<p>e136 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 20 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>