<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1540729" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We demonstrate the specific identification of single 
nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) responsible for 
rifampicin resistance of Mycobacterium tuberculo-
sis applying fluorescently labeled DNA-hairpin 
structures (smart probes) in combination with 
single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy. Smart 
probes are singly labeled hairpin-shaped oligonu-
cleotides bearing a fluorescent dye at the 5 
0 end that 
is quenched by guanosine residues in the comple-
mentary stem. Upon hybridization to target sequen-
ces, a conformational change occurs, reflected in a 
strong increase in fluorescence intensity. An excess 
of unlabeled ('cold') oligonucleotides was used to 
prevent the formation of secondary structures in the 
target sequence and thus facilitates hybridization of 
smart probes. Applying standard ensemble fluores-
cence spectroscopy we demonstrate the identifica-
tion of SNPs in PCR amplicons of mycobacterial 
rpoB gene fragments with a detection sensitivity 
of 10 
À8 M. To increase the detection sensitivity, 
confocal fluorescence microscopy was used to 
observe fluorescence bursts of individual smart 
probes freely diffusing through the detection vol-
ume. By measuring burst size, burst duration and 
fluorescence lifetime for each fluorescence burst 
the discrimination accuracy between closed and 
open (hybridized) smart probes could be substan-
tially increased. The developed technique enables 
the identification of SNPs in 10 
À11 On a global scale, infectious diseases are the most frequent 
cause of death. A growing spectrum of so called opportunistic 
microorganisms and the notorious tendency of microbes to 
develop resistance patterns against anti-infective drugs (i.e. 
antibiotics) cause a rapidly growing challenge for routine 
diagnostic services. A number of methods are available in 
order to test for antimicrobial susceptibility. The most widely 
used techniques are culture-based while novel techniques 
take advantage of specific molecular detection of resistance 
determinants. Determination of antimicrobial resistance 
using culture-based methods may be sufficiently fast for 
rapidly growing microorganisms. However, the discrimi-
nation between resistant and wild type slow growers, such 
as Mycobacterium tuberculosis, will benefit remarkably 
from molecular methods. Rapid, reliable, economic and 
highly sensitive DNA detection methods have thus become 
increasingly important in many fields, including health care, 
environmental studies, physical and biochemical research. 
Today, molecular methods already play an important role 
in early-stage diagnosis of cancer diseases, diagnostic of 
viral diseases (e.g. HIV infections), laboratory test for the 
confirmation of tuberculosis and fast detection of antimicro-
bial resistance mechanisms (1-5). The molecular methods 
currently available are, however, poorly standardized (many 
of them being in house methods). Furthermore, sensitivity 
is still an important issue as these available methods need 
amplification of the specific target in combination with down-
stream methods. Consequently, there is a growing interest in 
diagnostic methods that enable the detection of very small 
amounts of target DNA. 
Current state of the art routine diagnostics constitutes 
amplification of the target sequence by PCR or related tech-
niques that increase the concentrations of target sequence </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 622 154 5044; Fax: +49 622 154 5050; Email: knemeyer@single-molecule-spectroscopy.de </p>

<p>The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 e90 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl495 </p>

<p>prior to analysis. The amplified DNA is hybridized to immo-
bilized complementary oligonucleotides and hybridization 
between target sequence and probe is visualized by use of 
chromogenic techniques (e.g. GenoType Mycobacterium 
direct kit or the GenoType MTBDR kit, Hain Lifescience, 
Nehren, Germany). In contrast to heterogeneous assay for-
mats, homogeneous assays enable the detection of specific 
DNA sequences without washing or separation steps. One 
approach uses a probe consisting of a short fluorescently 
labeled oligonucleotide complementary to the target sequence 
and fluorescence correlation spectroscopy (FCS) to monitor 
hybridization to the target sequence by an increase in diffu-
sion time or a change in fluorescence polarization (6,7). 
Other assays are based on two dye-labeled oligonucleotides 
that form a fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET)-
pair which disappears upon hybridization of a probe oligo-
nucleotide to the target sequence (8). Generally, single 
nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analysis is performed using 
commercially available template directed dye terminator 
incorporation (TDI) (9) or the TaqMan assay (10). Alter-
natively, the ligase detection reaction (LDR) assay can be 
used for identification of SNPs (11). Here two oligonu-
cleotides that hybridize in direct neighborhood are ligated if 
they perfectly match the target DNA. Applying ensemble 
fluorescence spectroscopy these standard methods exhibit 
detection limits in the micro-to nanomolar range. 
Recent methods like the molecular beacons developed by 
Tyagi and Kramer (12,13) use probes that report the presence 
of a specific DNA sequence by an increase in fluorescence 
intensity. These probes are based on hairpin-shaped oligo-
nucleotides labeled with a fluorescent dye and a quenching 
moiety. The loop sequence of the hairpin probe is comple-
mentary to the target DNA. Upon hybridization to the target, 
fluorescence quenching is reduced owing to the formation of 
the thermodynamically favored double helix. Molecular 
beacons can be used for SNP analysis in the nanomolar 
range under optimized conditions (14). Instead of using 
organic quencher molecules like DABCYL or the more effec-
tive black hole quencher (BHQ) (15), also gold nanoparticles 
have been successfully applied (16). The major advantage of 
these types of self-quenched probes is their application in 
homogeneous DNA assays because they do not require any 
washing or separation step and they enable online monitoring 
of hybridization kinetics (17-19). 
Recently, an alternative technique for specific detection of 
target sequences was introduced that takes advantage of the 
fact that several oxazine and rhodamine derivatives are selec-
tively quenched by the DNA base guanine (20-26). The 
method uses the low oxidation potential of the DNA base 
guanine to efficiently quench the fluorescence of suited 
fluorophores via photoinduced electron transfer upon contact 
formation (26). These so-called smart probes (22) are rela-
tively easy to design because only a single labeling step is 
required and they exhibit a free terminus for further modifica-
tion of the hairpin, e.g. for immobilization on a solid support 
without further chemical modifications in the loop (Figure 1) 
(24). With careful design of these conformational flexible 
DNA probes and the selection of appropriate fluorophores, 
efficient and highly sensitive DNA-hairpins can be synthe-
sized that increase fluorescence intensity up to 20-fold upon 
specific hybridization to target sequences (23). Applying </p>

<p>smart probes in time-resolved single molecule fluorescence 
spectroscopy measurements, we demonstrated a detection 
limit for synthetic target sequences well below the nanomolar 
range (22). 
In the present work, we demonstrate the identification of 
SNPs in PCR amplified subgenic fragments of the rpoB 
gene (which codes for the DNA dependent RNA polymerase) 
of M.tuberculosis using smart probes in homogeneous assays. 
As proof of principle we investigated a mutation that causes 
rifampicin resistance in Mycobacteria. Here, displacement of 
an adenine by a thymine residue (GAC ! GTC) at position 
nt 1322 of the rpoB gene causes an amino acid substitution in 
the protein sequence and induces rifampicin resistance. The 
particular mutation chosen is one of the most common ones 
and serves as model to optimize the described detection tech-
nique. Rifampicin resistance may, however, as well be caused 
by other mutations. The current literature lists $90 different 
mutations, mainly within a short 81 bp fragment of the gene 
(27-30). 
In contrast to the detection of synthetic target sequences 
using DNA-hairpin probes, the detection of mutations in 
amplified target samples, i.e. PCR amplicons, is more compli-
cated because of the formation of secondary structures (25). 
In order to reduce the effect of secondary structures in the 
target sequence we used an excess of flanking 'cold' oligonu-
cleotides to guarantee the accessibility of the target sequence 
for hybridization of the smart probe. Applying confocal 
single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy in combination 
with multiparameter analysis we demonstrate the identifi-
cation of SNP in 10 
À11 M solutions of PCR amplicons 
from M.tuberculosis in only 100 s. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Synthesis and spectroscopic characteristics of 
smart probes </p>

<p>All oligonucleotides were purchased from IBA (Göttingen, 
Germany). For the smart probe-WT (wild type) and for the 
smart probe-M (mutant) the oligonucleotides CCC TCT 
GGT CCA TGA ATT GAG GG and CCC TCT GGA CCA 
TGA ATT GAG GG were modified at their 5 
0 end using </p>

<p>Figure 1. Principle of operation of smart probes. The fluorophore is attached 
to the 5 
0 end of the oligonucleotide and quenched by guanosine residues in the 
complementary stem. Hybridization to the target sequence forces the stem 
apart and completely restores the fluorescence because efficient quenching of 
the fluorophore by guanosine residues requires contact formation. </p>

<p>e90 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 </p>

<p>
C 6 -amino-linker. For fluorescence labeling the oligo-
nucleotides were mixed in carbonate buffer (0.1 M, pH 8.5) 
with a 10-fold excess of the N-hydroxysuccinimidyl ester 
of ATTO655 (Atto-Tec GmbH, Siegen, Germany). The reac-
tion solution was incubated for 12 h at room temperature 
before the product was finally purified by HPLC (Hewlett-
Packard, Böblingen, Germany) using a reversed-phase 
column (Knauer, Berlin, Germany) with octadecylsilanehy-
persil C18. A linear gradient (20 min) from 0 to 75% acetoni-
trile containing 0.1 M triethylammoniumacetat was used for 
separation. All fluorescence spectra and temperature profiles 
were obtained from a Cary Eclipse fluorescence spectrometer 
(Varian, Darmstadt, Germany) and 50 ml-cuvettes. Absorp-
tion spectra were measured on a Cary 500 UV-Vis-NIR 
spectrometer (Varian, Darmstadt, Germany) using standard 
quartz cuvettes with an optical pathway of 10 mm. Ensemble 
fluorescence lifetime measurements were carried out with an 
IBH spectrometer (model 5000MC, Glasgow, Scotland) using 
the technique of time-correlated single-photon counting 
(TCSPC). All measurements were performed at pH 7.0 in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing 140 mM NaCl. 
To exclude polarization effects, fluorescence was observed 
under magic angle (54.7 
) conditions. Typically, 5000 photon 
counts were collected in the maximum channel using 2056 
channels. The decay parameters were determined by least-
square deconvolution, and their quality was judged by the 
reduced c 
2 values and the randomness of the weighted resi-
duals. In case that a monoexponential model was inadequate 
to describe the measured decay, a multiexponential model 
was used to fit the decay (Equation 1), </p>

<p>IðtÞ ¼ Ið0Þ 
X 
a i t i ‚ 
1 </p>

<p>where a i are the pre-exponential factors that describe the ratio 
of the excited species and t i denote their lifetimes. </p>

<p>Preparation of the PCR-products </p>

<p>PCR was carried out applying standard protocols. Briefly, 
primers Tr8 (TGCACGTCGCGGACCTCCA) and Tr9 
(TCGCCGCGATCAAGGAGT) were used in a concentration 
of 5 pmol/ml in final reaction volumes of 100 ml. DNA poyl-
merase and PCR reagents were obtained from MBI Fermen-
tas (St Leon Rot, Germany). The thermal cycling profile 
consisted of 95 
C (denaturation for 60 s), 57 
C (primer 
annealing for 60 s) and 72 
C (extension for 60 s). PCR 
products were checked for the expected length in 2% agarose 
gels. Purified amplicons were used for cycle sequencing 
applying standard protocols where reagents were obtained 
from Applied Biotech, Mörfelden, Germany. Sequence anal-
ysis was done on an ABI Prism 310 analyzer. Only amplicons 
with verified sequence (i.e. absence or presence of the resis-
tance conferring mutation) were used for hybridization 
experiments. Secondary structures of the PCR amplicons 
were calculated using mfold (31). The program uses nearest-
neighbor energy rules to estimate the free energies of possible 
secondary structures of a given DNA sequence. </p>

<p>Hybridization of smart probes to target DNA amplicons </p>

<p>For ensemble measurements the respective smart probe was 
mixed in PBS (pH 7.0) containing 140 mM NaCl with a 
10-fold excess of target DNA (artificial oligonucleotides or </p>

<p>PCR amplicons) resulting in a final concentration of the 
smart probe of 1 · 10 
À8 M whereas the concentration of 
the target DNA was 1 · 10 
À7 M. Before addition of the 
PCR amplicons it was denaturated for 10 min at 97 
C and 
chilled on ice. The mixed solutions were heated to 65 
C 
and slowly cooled down to 25 
C with a gradient of 0.4 
C 
per minute. Samples were prepared in the same way for 
single-molecule experiments, but the concentration of the 
smart probes was 5 · 10 
À10 M. The samples were transferred 
onto a microscope slide with a small depression and covered 
by a cover slide. </p>

<p>Single molecule spectroscopy data analysis </p>

<p>The experimental setup for single-molecule measurements is 
based on a standard inverse fluorescence microscope 
(Axiovert 100TV, Zeiss, Germany) and is described in 
more detail elsewhere (22,32). Briefly, a pulsed diode laser 
emitting light at 635 nm with a repetition rate of 80 MHz 
and a pulse duration of &lt;100 ps full width at half-maximum 
(PDL800B, Picoquant, Berlin, Germany) served as an excita-
tion source. Passing an excitation filter (639DF9, Omega 
Optics, Brattleboro, VT) the collimated laser beam was cou-
pled into an oil-immersion objective (100·, NA ¼ 1.4, 
Nikon, Japan) by a dichroic beam splitter (645DMLP; 
Omega Optics, Brattleboro, VT). The average laser power 
was adjusted to 600 mW at the sample. Fluorescence light 
was collected with the same objective and focused through 
the TV outlet of the microscope onto a 100 mm pinhole. 
Fluorescence light passing through the pinhole was filtered 
by a longpass filter (650 nm) and focused onto the active 
area of an avalanche photodiode (AQR-14, EG&amp;G, Canada). 
The detector signal was registered by a PC plug-in card for 
time-correlated single-photon counting (TCSPC) (SPC-630, 
Becker&amp;Hickl, Berlin, Germany). The photons recorded on 
the TCSPC card were summed into 1 ms time bins to gene-
rate multi-channel-scalar (MCS) traces (Figure 2). To analyze 
the MCS-traces, a peak recognition filter (Burst scout, 
Atto-Tec, Siegen, Germany) extracting bursts that have a 
maximum intensity above a certain threshold was applied. 
We used a burst recognition threshold of 30 kHz (Figure 2, 
black line). For each burst &gt;30 MHz, the burst duration 
(in milliseconds), maximum intensity, overall intensity 
(total number of photons) and the fluorescence lifetime 
were calculated and stored. To determine the fluorescence 
lifetime (decay time) of each burst, the arrival times of all 
photons of the respective burst were histogrammed with 
respect to the laser pulse (Figure 2, inset). Fluorescence life-
times were calculated using a maximum likelihood estimator 
(MLE) algorithm (33,34). 
For FCS measurements the APD output was connected to a 
correlator card (model 5000/E, ALV, Langen, Germany). Six 
runs of 30 s were averaged to get a correlation curve. All fluo-
rescence signals were measured at room temperature (25 
C). 
Fluorescence intensity autocorrelation functions were calcu-
lated by the correlator board and saved as ASCII files. The 
autocorrelation functions were analyzed with <rs type="software">Origin</rs> (Micro-
cal Software, Northhampton, MA). FCS measures the fluores-
cence fluctuations arising from fluorescent molecules as they 
pass the detection volume to obtain information about 
dynamic processes at the molecular level (35). Using FCS, </p>

<p> 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 e90 </p>

<p>the time dependent fluorescence signal F ¼ dF + hFi is 
described by the fluorescence fluctuations dF(t) about an 
average value hFi. These fluctuations are analyzed in the 
form of a normalized autocorrelation function G(t), where 
t denotes the correlation time (Equation 2). </p>

<p>GðtÞ ¼ 
hFðtÞFðt þ tÞi </p>

<p>hFðtÞi </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>¼ 1 þ 
hdFðtÞdFðt þ tÞi </p>

<p>hFðtÞi </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>FCS can be used to gain information about all processes 
influencing the fluorescence intensity in the detection volume, 
e.g. translational diffusion, triplet states or equilibrium 
constants (35-37). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Spectroscopic characteristics of smart probes </p>

<p>Owing to the small number of compounds with intrinsic fluo-
rescence &gt;600 nm, near-infrared (NIR) fluorescence detection 
in bioanalytical samples is a desirable alternative to visible 
fluorescence detection (38-40). This fact, as well as the avail-
ability of diode laser for this spectral region, has prompted 
our efforts to develop so-called smart probes (Figure 1) 
based on NIR dyes (20-22). For our experiments, we syn-
thesized two smart probes using the red-absorbing dye 
ATTO655. In aqueous solvents, ATTO655 exhibits an 
absorption maximum at 661 nm, and emits at an emission 
maximum of 673 nm with a fluorescence lifetime t of 
1.85 ns. The smart probe ATTO655-WT contains a DNA </p>

<p>sequence complementary to the wild-type PCR product 
whereas the smart probe ATTO655-M fits the mutant PCR 
product. Both probes, ATTO655-WT and ATTO655-M, 
show bathochromic shifts of a few nanometers in the absorp-
tion and emission spectra in aqueous solvents compared to 
spectra of the free fluorophore, indicating the formation of 
non-or only weakly fluorescent complexes. Upon addition 
of an excess synthetic target sequence (short complementary 
oligonucleotides) to smart probes, spontaneous hybridization 
occurs, reflected in an $7-fold increase in fluorescence inten-
sity. The fluorescence decays of the closed smart probes 
ATTO655-WT and ATTO655-M could be best described 
using a biexponential model with t 1 ¼ 2.71 ± 0.34 ns 
(a 1 ¼ 0.76 ± 0.06), t 2 ¼ 0.42 ± 0.18 ns (a 2 ¼ 0.24 ± 
0.08). Accordingly, we measured an increase in fluorescence 
lifetime upon addition of an excess of target sequence. The 
fluorescence decays measured after hybridization show an 
almost monoexponential decay with t 1 ¼ 2.93 ± 0.25 ns 
(a 1 ¼ 0.98 ± 0.04), t 2 ¼ 0.32 ± 0.16 ns (a 2 ¼ 0.02 ± 
0.02). Comparison of the changes in fluorescence intensity 
and lifetime before and after hybridization to artificial target 
sequences shows that quenching electron transfer reactions 
between guanosine residues and ATTO655 are mainly 
manifested by static quenching. This indicates that the 
quenching reaction is faster than the time resolution of our 
TCSPC apparatus of $40 ps. (27) </p>

<p>Influence of the secondary structure of the PCR 
amplicon on hybridization efficiency </p>

<p>Although the double-stranded PCR product was denatured for 
10 min at 97 
C and immediately chilled on ice, addition of a 
10-fold excess of single-stranded PCR product did not result 
in a significant increase in fluorescence intensity in contrast to 
the addition of short artificial target DNA oligonucleotides. 
This can be attributed to the formation of suboptimal secon-
dary structures of the PCR product (25). As depicted in 
Figure 3. the calculated secondary structure for the 157 bp 
PCR amplicon of M.tuberculosis is not accessible for hybridi-
zation of a smart probe under the used standard conditions 
(aqueous buffer containing 140 mM NaCl, 25 
C). In particu-
lar, 8 of the 15 DNA bases responsible for hybridization of 
the smart probe (marked dark gray in Figure 3) are involved 
in base pairing and thus are not accessible for hybridization. 
Modification of the conditions for secondary structure 
calculation, e.g. by increasing temperature and varying salt 
concentration, demonstrates that below a temperature of 
$50-60 
C several target DNA bases are always involved in 
double helix formation. To realize hybridization of the smart 
probes to the PCR product so-called 'cold' or 'breaking' 
oligonucleotides were used. Such artificial oligonucleotides 
can rip the secondary structure of the PCR product and there-
fore facilitate hybridization of the smart probe. In Figure 3 
the binding sites for the 'cold' oligonuleotides 1-6 are 
marked light gray (58-73: cold oligonucleotide 1; 74-98: 
cold oligonucleotide 2; 99-133: cold oligonucleotide 3; 
134-157: cold oligonucleotide 4; 1-19: cold oligonucleotide 
5; 20-40; cold oligonucleotide 6). To investigate the influ-
ence of cold oligonucleotides on hybridization efficiency, 
the denaturated PCR product (10 
À7 M) was mixed with the 
smart probe-WT (10 
À8 M) in the presence of different cold </p>

<p>Figure 2. Fluorescence intensity with time (MCS-trace) recorded from a 5 · 
10 
À10 M solution of a smart probe (1 ms/bin). Fluorescence bursts are defined 
by a recognition threshold, i.e. a count rate of 30 kHz (black line). Origin and 
end of a burst were defined by a count rate of 20 kHz (dashed line). The 
fluorescence lifetimes of recognized bursts were calculated applying a MLE-
algorithm. Using the described burst recognition definition, we identify two 
fluorescence bursts at $25 ms (223 photon counts, 3 ms burst duration, 
fluorescence lifetime, t ¼ 2.9 ns) and at $58 ms (138 photon counts, 4 ms 
burst duration, fluorescence lifetime, t ¼ 2.2 ns). </p>

<p>e90 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 </p>

<p>
oligonucleotides. Afterwards, the mixture was heated to 65 
C 
and cooled down to 25 
C during 100 min. Addition of cold 
oligonucleotide 1 results in a 1.4-fold increase in fluorescence 
intensity whereas all other cold oligonucleotides (1-5) gener-
ate a smaller increase in the range of 1.1-1.2 fold. Upon 
simultaneous addition of all cold oligonucleotides 1-6, a 
2.0-fold increase in fluorescence intensity was measured. In 
addition, the influence of various combinations of cold 
oligonucleotides was studied (data not shown). In conclusion 
the results demonstrate that addition of cold oligonucleotide 1 
is most effective in breaking the secondary structure of the 
PCR product. However, in order to achieve the best results 
addition of all six cold oligonucleotides is advantageous. 
Applying this technique and the two smart probes (smart 
probe-WT and smart probe-M), discrimination between the 
wild-type amplicon and the mutant amplicon containing the 
SNP was easily possible. In these experiments, the mixture 
containing the matching or non-matching smart probe 
together with the denaturated PCR products and all cold 
oligonucleotides was heated to 65 
C and subsequently cooled 
down very slowly (0.05 
C per minute) before ensemble fluo-
rescence measurements. Using conventional fluorescence 
spectroscopy, we achieved an increase in fluorescence inten-
sity of up to 2-fold in the presence of relative large amounts 
of complementary target PCR-products ($10 
À6 M) with a 
detection limit in the 10 
À8 M range. Even though limited in 
sensitivity, the introduced assay technique exhibits great 
potential when applied in combination with time-resolved 
single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy. </p>

<p>Time-resolved single-molecule fluorescence 
spectroscopy </p>

<p>Single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy (SMFS) enables 
the investigation of characteristics of individual molecules, 
i.e. identification of subpopulations in a heterogeneous </p>

<p>mixture, while ensemble measurements yield only infor-
mation on average properties (41). Figure 4 shows the 
fluorescence intensities recorded over time (MCS-traces) of 
a 5 · 10 
À10 M solution of smart probe-M in the absence 
and presence of a perfectly matching artificial target DNA. 
The average count rate measured for smart probe-M of 
$12.5 kHz increases to $45 kHz after addition of an excess 
of artificial target sequence. Considering a background signal 
of $7.5 kHz measured for pure buffer, we estimate, in accor-
dance with ensemble measurements, a 7-8-fold increase in 
overall fluorescence intensity upon hybridization to the 
perfectly matching artificial target sequence. However, as 
compared to ensemble spectroscopy, SMFS might be advan-
tageously used in diagnostic applications because it enables 
an improved discrimination between closed (quenched 
smart probes), and probes that are hybridized to target 
DNA. The reason for the improved discrimination stems 
from the fact that fluorescence signals of fluorophores can 
be easily separated from background signal that also contains 
Raman and Rayleigh scattering, as well as autofluorescence </p>

<p>Figure 3. mfold structures (modeling parameters: 140 mM Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, 0 mM Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, 
25 
C) of the 157 bp PCR amplicon of M.tuberculosis. The binding sites for 
the loop sequence of the smart probe marked dark gray. The binding sites for 
the 'cold' oligonuleotides 1-6 are marked light gray (58-73: cold 
oligonucleotides 1; 74-98: cold oligonucleotides 2; 99-133: cold oligonu-
cleotides 3; 134-157: cold oligonucleotides 4; 1-19: cold oligonucleotides 5; 
20-40: cold oligonucleotides 6). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Fluorescence intensity (MCS)-traces observed from a 5 · 10 
À10 M 
solution of smart probe-M before and after addition of a 100-fold excess of 
an artificial target DNA. Measurements were carried out at room temperature 
in PBS (pH 7.0) containing 140 mM NaCl at an average excitation power of 
0.6 mW at the sample. </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 e90 </p>

<p>of impurities. Therefore, signals with higher count rates 
(&gt;30 kHz) corresponding to smart probes diffusing through 
the detection volume can be easily extracted from the moni-
tored MCS-trace. The closed smart probes show almost only 
signals &lt;100 kHz in the absence of target DNA. Only very 
few signals, i.e. &lt;1%, show higher count rates that could be 
somehow caused by opened probes, probes in which the 
fluorophores do not interact with a guanosine residue in the 
complementary stem, or by free fluorescent dyes that might 
still be present even after HPLC purification. 
On the other hand, after adding an excess of artificial target 
DNA, fluorescence bursts with maximum count rates between 
100 and 600 kHz are evident (Figure 4b). During a measure-
ment time of 100 s, we found 7616 fluorescence bursts for 
the hybridized and 63 fluorescence bursts for the closed 
(unbound) smart probe, respectively, with a count rate 
&gt;100 kHz. Thus, the number of fluorescence signals above 
the selected threshold of 100 kHz increases by a factor of 
$121, i.e. much stronger than determined in ensemble fluo-
rescence experiments. In standard cuvette experiments we 
found an $7-fold increase in fluorescence intensity upon 
addition of an excess of complementary target sequence. To 
further increase the discrimination efficiency between open 
and closed smart probes, we determined simultaneously the 
fluorescence decay time for each burst recognized above 
the 100 kHz threshold. As expected from ensemble measure-
ments the fluorescence decay time of smart probes increases </p>

<p>considerably upon addition of target sequence. Applying a 
monoexponential MLE-algorithm results in a typical fluores-
cence decay time of $1.2 and $3 ns for the closed and open 
smart probe, respectively (22). 
The major aim of this work was the highly sensitive and 
specific identification of a SNP responsible for rifampin resis-
tance in M.tuberculosis. Therefore, different concentrations 
of the PCR-products of the wild type and the mutant form 
were mixed in PBS with smart probe-WT and smart probe-
M (containing a single mismatch in the loop sequence), 
respectively. Furthermore, all six cold oligonucleotides 
were added in order to avoid secondary structures. Finally, 
the solutions were heated and slowly cooled down from 65 
to 25 
C during 14 h before experiments were performed 
with a typical measurement time of 100 s. Figure 5 shows 
20 s sections of the raw data recorded from four different 
samples of the mutant smart probe-M in the presence of 
different concentrations of the corresponding PCR-product. 
The MCS-trace of the pure smart probe-M shows mainly 
fluorescence bursts with a maximum count rate well below 
100 kHz (Figure 5a). Only few signals with higher count 
rates can be observed. Upon addition of a 40-fold excess 
(2 · 10 
À8 M) of the matching PCR product the fluorescence 
signal increases as can be seen by the increasing number of 
fluorescence bursts with count rates &gt;100 kHz (Figure 5b). 
In agreement with ensemble measurements the increase in 
fluorescence intensity upon hybridization of smart probes to </p>

<p>Figure 5. Fluorescence intensity traces observed from 5 · 10 
À10 M solution of the smart probe-M in absence (a) and presence of (b) 2 · 10 
À8 M, (c) 1 · 10 
À9 M 
and (d) 5 · 10 
À11 M of the matching PCR-product. To all samples the cold oligonucleotides 1-6 were added. Before measuring all samples were heated to 65 
C 
and cooled down to 25 
C over night. Measurements were carried out at room temperature in PBS (pH 7.0) containing 140 mM NaCl using an average excitation 
power of 0.6 mW. </p>

<p>e90 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 </p>

<p>
real samples, i.e. to PCR products, is less pronounced. Using 
background corrected average count rates we calculate only a 
2-fold increase in fluorescence intensity upon addition of a 
40-fold excess of matching PCR product in the presence of 
all cold oligonucleotides. In the presence of lower concentra-
tions of matching PCR product the average increase in count 
rate is even less pronounced. However, the fluorescence 
intensity traces shown in Figure 5c and d clearly demonstrate 
the potential of SMFS. Even in the presence of only 5 · 10 </p>

<p>À11 </p>

<p>M of matching PCR product the MCS-trace reveals slightly 
higher fluorescence bursts than without addition of any 
PCR product (compare Figure 5a and d). In contrast, the 
addition of a 40-fold excess of the respective non-matching 
PCR product to smart probe-WT or smart probe-M neither 
results in an increased average count rate nor in an increase 
in the number of fluorescence bursts with count rates 
&gt;100 kHz (data not shown). In order to quantify the concen-
tration of target sequence present in the sample we compared 
the spectroscopic properties of the fluorescence bursts of the 
closed smart probes and probes that are hybridized to the 
PCR product (Figure 6). The signals were obtained from 
MCS-traces as shown in Figure 5a and b. 
First, we investigated the intensity of the fluorescence sig-
nals, which is the sum of all photons detected per fluores-
cence burst (Figure 6a). The burst size, i.e. the number of 
photon counts detected per burst, increases significantly 
after hybridization to the target PCR-product. Less than 1% 
of the closed smart probes show intensities &gt;220 photons/ 
burst. In contrast, for the probes hybridized to the matching 
PCR-product over 12% of the signals exhibit a burst size of 
&gt;220 photons/burst. Above 150 photons/burst, the hybridized 
probe shows significantly more signals (22.2%) than the pure 
smart probe (4.0%). Furthermore, the fluorescence lifetime 
changes owing to hybridization (Figure 6b). For the closed 
hairpin probe the fluorescence signals show fluorescence 
lifetimes centered around 1 ns, corresponding to ensemble 
lifetime data measured for closed smart probes. For &lt;6% of 
the signals detected for closed probes, fluorescence lifetimes 
longer than 2.25 ns were measured. After adding an excess of 
artificial target DNA we found a Gaussian-shaped lifetime 
distribution centered at 2.8 ns and &lt;10% of the signals 
below 2.25 ns (data not shown). On the other hand, addition 
of a 40-fold excess of matching PCR-product does not induce 
the hybridization, i.e. opening, of all hairpin probes. Here, we 
found a bimodal lifetime distribution with two maxima at 
$1.3 ns and $2.5 ns. Nevertheless, fluorescence decay time 
information (Figure 6b) is suited as additional parameter to 
increase the identification accuracy of opened (unquenched) 
smart probes. More than 34% of the signals show a fluores-
cence life longer than 2.25 ns. Upon hybridization to the 
PCR-product not only an enhancement of the fluorescence 
intensity and lifetime is observed, but also the burst duration 
time enhances, i.e. the diffusion constant increases because of 
the increase in molecular weight (Figure 6c). In the experi-
ments presented, a 23 nt containing smart probe hybridizes 
to a 157 nt containing PCR product including several cold 
oligonucleotides. Thus, the molecular weight increases con-
siderably. While 99.5% of all unhybridized probes show 
diffusion times shorter than 5 ms, 10% of the hybridi-
zed hairpins exhibit diffusion times longer than 5 ms 
(Figure 6c). Already at a burst duration of 4 ms we found </p>

<p>significantly more signals for the hybridized probe (19.3%) 
than for the unhybridized probe (6.1%). 
Figure 6a and c clearly demonstrate that the combi-
nation of all three parameters can substantially increase the </p>

<p>Figure 6. (a) Burst size, (b) fluorescence decay time and (c) burst duration 
distribution of 3500 photon bursts detected from a 5 · 10 
À10 M solution of 
smart probe-M in the absence (gray) and presence (open) of 2 · 10 
À8 M 
matching PCR product. </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 e90 </p>

<p>identification accuracy of hybridized smart probes. Therefore, 
we plotted the burst size versus the fluorescence lifetime for 
each signal measured in the absence and presence of match-
ing PCR-product (Figure 7). Furthermore, all signals with 
burst durations of four or more milliseconds were color 
encoded in red. Comparison of the two scatter plots clearly 
uncovers an area defined by the rectangle in Figure 7 where 
mainly signals from hybridized smart probes are located. 
During a measurement time of 100 s smart probe-M shows 
only 10 fluorescence signals (i.e. 0.2% of all signals recorded) 
with a lifetime &gt;2.25 ns, a burst size &gt;150 photon counts and 
a burst duration of longer than 4 ms in the absence of match-
ing PCR-product (red circles in Figure 7a). In contrast, in the 
presence of 2 · 10 
À8 M matching PCR-product $500 fluores-
cence signals (i.e. $10% of all signal) are located within the 
same area (Figure 7b). 
Figure 8 shows the number of fluorescence signals located 
within the area defined in Figure 7 at different PCR-product 
concentrations of the wild type and mutant form. In the 
nanomolar range, 5-10 times more signals were found for 
the smart probe hybridized to the fully matching PCR-
product compared to the respective PCR-product containing </p>

<p>one mismatch. Also for lower concentrations a significant 
increase in the number of signals located within the area is 
apparent, e.g. for a concentration of 5 · 10 
À11 M $20 signals 
were found, i.e. a 2-fold increase. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this article we present for the first time the detection of 
SNP in PCR-products using smart probes. Our study 
demonstrates that PCR-products show significantly different 
properties than artificial target-DNA sequences. After 
addition of a 40-fold excess of a short (20mer) artificial 
target-DNA to smart probes (5 · 10 
À9 M) the hairpin-
structured probe hybridizes immediately reflected in a 
7-fold increase in fluorescence intensity. On the other hand, 
addition of the same amount of PCR-product has no effect 
owing to the presence of stronger secondary structures. As 
shown, the formation of stable secondary structures can be 
at least partly avoided by adding an excess of unlabeled 
('cold') oligonucleotides. Applying this method we observed 
a 2-fold increase in fluorescence intensity upon addition of 
an excess of PCR-product. 
However, the discrepancy in fluorescence signals between 
closed and opened smart probes can be further increased by 
applying single-molecule fluorescence spectroscopy. Owing 
to the relatively high mass of the DNA-strand including the 
hybridized 'cold' oligonucleotides, the diffusion time of the 
fluorescence labeled smart probe decreases significantly 
upon binding to its target. This effect can be investigated 
by FCS that analyses the fluctuations of the fluorescence sig-
nal. Figure 9a shows FCS measurements of a 5 · 10 
À9 M 
solution of smart probe-WT in the absence of any target 
(dotted line), in presence of a 20-fold excess of artificial 
target DNA (dashed line) and of an excess of matching 
PCR-product (solid line). The calculated diffusion time for 
the unhybridized smart probe is $100 ms and increases to </p>

<p>Figure 7. Fluorescence lifetime of each signal measured from a 5 · 10 
À10 M 
solution of the smart probe-M (a) in the absence and (b) presence of 
2 · 10 
À8 M of the matching PCR-product is plotted versus the respective 
burst size (photon counts/burst). Signals with a burst duration &gt;4 ms are 
marked red. </p>

<p>Figure 8. Detected signals of the smart probe-M (triangles) and the smart 
probe-WT (squares) with a burst size of &gt;150 photons, a fluorescence lifetime 
of &gt;2.25 ns and a burst duration of &gt;4 ms during a measurement time of 100 s 
plotted versus the concentration of PCR-product of the wild type and the 
mutant of M.tuberculosis, respectively. The data points obtained from the 
matching PCR-product are black and the respective reference sample 
containing the other PCR-product containing one mismatch is marked gray. </p>

<p>e90 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 </p>

<p>
$180 ms upon addition of artificial target-DNA. Hybridi-
zation to the PCR-product results in a diffusion time of 
$380 ms which is almost four times longer than the diffusion 
time of the unhybridized smart probe. Consequently, the anal-
ysis of burst durations can help to discriminate between 
hybridized and unhybridized smart probes. Furthermore, 
longer diffusion times result in higher burst sizes. 
Using standard ensemble fluorescence spectroscopy, smart 
probe concentrations down to about 10 
À8 M can be measured. 
However, in the presence of an equimolar amount of PCR-
product no significant increase in fluorescence intensity 
occurs. Even a 40-fold excess of PCR-product is able to 
open $15% of the hairpin probes and thus the fluorescence 
intensity is doubled. A 100% opening of the smart probe 
generates a 7-fold increase and can be achieved by adding 
artificial target-DNA. To improve the hybridization of the 
probe to the target-DNA the hairpin probe could be designed 
less stable, e.g. by using shorter stems that contain only four 
base pairs, or one could choose a longer loop sequence that is 
complementary to the target-DNA. Actually, both ways 
would result in more efficient hybridization, but on the 
other hand, this also reduces the specificity of the probes 
and the quenching efficiency in the closed state. However, 
the presented smart probes are appropriate to identify a single 
point mutation in a 157 bp PCR-product of M.tuberculosis. </p>

<p>We demonstrated that the sensitivity can be enhanced drama-
tically using single-molecule detection techniques. Measuring 
the diffusion of individual molecules through the open 
volume element of a confocal fluorescence microscope 
presents an easy and fast detection and identification scheme 
for PCR target sequences in the nanomolar range simply by 
counting fluorescence signals above a threshold count rate 
of 150 kHz. At lower concentrations the use of additional 
information like burst duration, fluorescence lifetime and 
burst size further improve the discrimination accuracy. To 
summarize, the proof of principle that smart probes can be 
utilized for the identification of PCR-targets with single-
nucleotide accuracy has been demonstrated. A single point 
mutation in a PCR-product at very low concentrations 
down to 10 
À11 M can be detected by time-resolved single-
molecule spectroscopy. It has to be investigated in future 
experiments whether this novel method can be applied for 
analyzing a broad range of clinical relevant PCR products. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This 
work was 
financially 
supported by 
the 
Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung (Grants 
13N8349 and 13N8348) and the Landesstiftung Baden-
Württemberg and the European Commission as part of the 
MoITools project. Funding to pay the Open Access publica-
tion charges for this article was provided by the German 
Cancer Research Center. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>PAGE 9 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 e90 </p>



<p>e90 Nucleic Acids Research, 2006, Vol. 34, No. 13 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>