<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1934993" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The specific aminoacylation of tRNA by tyrosyl-
tRNA synthetases (TyrRSs) relies on the identity 
determinants in the cognate tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>Aminoacyl-tRNA synthetases (aaRSs) play a central role 
in the assembly of amino acids into polypeptide chains. 
They catalyze the specific esterification of a given amino 
acid to its corresponding tRNA through a two-step 
reaction (1). In the first step, the specific amino acid and 
ATP substrates are recognized and then are converted into 
a reactive aminoacyl-adenylate (aa-AMP) intermediate in 
the presence of magnesium ions. In the next step, the 
amino acid moiety from the aa-AMP is transferred to the 
3 
0 -CCA terminus of the cognate tRNA. This enzymatic 
function is crucial for the fidelity of protein synthesis, in 
which the genetic code is translated to the amino acid 
sequence. The primary sequence analyses as well as the 
tertiary structure determinations allowed the partition of 
the 20 aaRSs into two exclusive classes, I and II, each 
consisting of 10 enzymes (2). Each class I enzyme has a 
Rossmann-fold domain as the catalytic domain. 
In addition, two consensus motifs, HIGH and KMSKS, 
are conserved among the class I enzymes. The class I 
enzymes are further divided into three sub-classes: Ia, Ib 
and Ic (3,4). The class Ic enzymes are aaRSs for tyrosine 
and tryptophan and are unusual in that they act as dimers, 
while the other class I (Ia and Ib) enzymes act as 
monomers. 
Tyrosyl-tRNA synthetase (TyrRS) is the first aaRS to 
have its crystal structure solved (5). The specific amino-
acylation of tRNA by TysRS relies on the identity 
determinants (the anticodon bases, the C1-G72 base 
pair, and the discriminator base A73) in the cognate 
tRNA 
Tyr (6-8). To date, a number of crystal structures of </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +81-3-3784-8200; Fax: +81-3-3782-5635; Email: ntanaka@pharm.showa-u.ac.jp </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>the TyrRSs have been solved: they are from four bacteria, 
Bacillus 
stearothermophilus 
[BstTyrRS, 
(9)], 
Staphylococcus aureus [SauTyrRS, (10)], Thermus thermo-
philus [TthTyrRS, (11)] and Escherichia coli [EcoTyrRS, 
(12)]; from eukarya Homo sapiens [HsaTyrRS, (13)]; and 
from four archaea, Methanococcus jannaschii [MjaTyrRS, 
(14,15)], Archaeglobus fulgidus, Pyrococcus horikoshi 
and Aeropyrum pernix [AfuTyrRS, PhoTyrRS, and 
ApeTyrRS, respectively, (16)]. Because the archaeal/ 
eukaryotic TyrRSs-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s pairs do not cross-react 
with their bacterial counterparts (8), the recognition 
modes of the identity determinants by the archaeal and 
eukaryotic TyrRSs were expected to be similar to each 
other but different from that by the bacterial TyrRSs. 
Such orthogonality is used for the incorporation of 
unnatural amino acids into proteins with engineered 
pairs of TyrRSs and tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s (17). In such situations, 
structural information on archaeal, eukaryotic and 
bacterial TyrRSs complexed with their cognate 
tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s has long been awaited. In a half-decade, crystal 
structure analyses of bacterial (Thermus thermophilus) (11) 
and archaeal (Methanococcus jannaschii) (14) TyrRSs 
complexed with their cognate tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s have been 
reported. Although previous experiments showed that 
TyrRS could bind only one tRNA per dimer (18) in 
solution, the crystal structure analyses (11,14) have shown 
that two tRNA 
Tyr s are bound to each dimer in a 
symmetrical fashion in the crystal. A plausible explanation 
for this discrepancy (asymmetry in solution vs symmetry 
in crystal) has been described by Yaremchuk et al. (11). 
A structural comparison revealed the structural basis for 
orthogonal specificities of archaeal and bacterial TyrRSs 
(14). On the other hand, no structures are available for 
eukaryotic TyrRSs complexed with their cognate 
tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s. To understand the molecular basis for the 
recognition of their cognate tRNA 
Tyr s by eukaryotic 
TyrRSs, we initiated the structure analysis of TyrRS from 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae (SceTyrRS), the model organism 
for lower eukaryotes. 
Here we present the crystal structure at 2.4-Å resolution 
of the ternary complex of SceTyrRS complexed with a 
Tyr-AMP analog and the native tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>(GÉA). The 
present structure of SceTyrRS complexed with the cognate 
tRNA 
Tyr and the previously reported structures of 
bacterial and archaeal TyrRSs (TthTyrRS and 
MjaTyrRS, respectively) complexed with their cognate 
tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s provide a full set of the recognition modes of 
the identity determinants of tRNA 
Tyr s by TyrRSs from 
three kingdoms. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Crystallization </p>

<p>Chemicals were purchased from Wako Pure Chemical Co. 
(Tokyo, Japan). The purification of native modified 
tRNA 
Tyr was performed in a way similar to the 
method as described (44). A Tyr-AMP analog 
(O-(adenosine-5 
0 -O-yl) 
N-(L-tyrosyl)phosphoramidate 
(Tyr-AMPN), (Figure 1A) was prepared as described 
(45). We expressed and purified a C-terminally truncated </p>

<p>SceTyrRS (hereafter simply SceTyrRS, residues 1-364), 
which has full TyrRS activity, for the present crystal 
structure analysis. SceTyrRS was expressed and purified in 
a way similar to the method described previously for 
the full-length SceTyrRS (residues 1-394) (34). Crystals of 
the ternary complex of SceTyrRS were obtained by the 
hanging-drop vapor diffusion method, as described else-
where (46). Briefly, a droplet was prepared by mixing an 
equal volume of a protein solution containing ca. 0.2 mM 
SceTyrRS, 5 mM Tyr-AMPN (Figure 1A), ca. 0.2 mM 
tRNA 
Tyr , 40 mM KCl in 20 mM Tris buffer at pH 7.5 and 
a reservoir solution containing 25% (v/v) polyethylene-
glycol 400 (PEG400) and 100 mM CaCl 2 in 100 mM Tris 
buffer at pH 7.5. The crystals belong to tetragonal space 
group P4 1 2 1 2 with cell dimensions of a = b = 63.85 Å and 
c = 330.3 Å (under the cryogenic conditions described 
below). Assuming one SceTyrRS subunit and one 
tRNA 
Tyr molecule per asymmetric unit, we obtained a 
V M value of 2.55 Å 
3 /Da, corresponding to a solvent 
content of 52%. Since the crystallization conditions of 
SceTyrRS contained 25% (v/v) PEG400 in reservoir 
solutions, X-ray data collections could be performed 
under cryogenic conditions without further addition of a 
cryo-protectant. Crystals were mounted in nylon loops 
and flash-cooled in a cold nitrogen gas stream at 100 K 
just before data collection. Crystals of the ternary complex 
of full-length TyrRS were obtained in a similar condition 
as described above and had similar morphology and cell 
dimensions to those of the truncated TyrRS. However, 
they diffracted quite poor (ca. 10-Å resolution). </p>

<p>Data collection </p>

<p>Initially, a native dataset was collected and several 
attempts were made to solve the structure of SceTyrRS 
by the molecular replacement techniques. The structures 
of several TyrRSs complexed with or without cognate 
tRNA 
Tyr and deposited in the Protein Data Bank, having 
ca. 10-20% sequence identity with SceTyrRS, were used 
as search models. Secondly, attempts were made to find 
good heavy-atom derivatives for phasing by the isomor-
phous replacement techniques. Since both of these 
attempts failed, we prepared a Se-Met substituted 
SceTyrRS using LeMaster medium (47) and E. coli 
B834(DE3) cells for phasing by the multiwavelength 
anomalous diffraction (MAD) method. The MAD data 
collection was performed at beamline 38B1, SPring-8. 
XAFS measurements were carried out around the 
selenium K absorption edge using an Se-Met SceTyrRS 
crystal in a cold nitrogen gas stream at 100 K. 
Subsequently, four datasets were collected from a new 
single crystal of Se-Met SceTyrRS on and around the 
selenium K absorption edge at 100 K using an ADSC 
Quantum-4R CCD detector. All datasets were integrated 
using the program package DPS (48). Scaling and 
processing were performed using the <rs type="software">CCP4</rs> program 
suite (49). Thereafter, a high-resolution dataset was 
collected from a single crystal of native SceTyrRS at 
beamline 40B2, SPring-8 ( = 1.00 Å ) in a similar way. 
The data collection statistics are summarized in Table 1. </p>



<p>Structure determination </p>

<p>Initial phase calculation was carried out at 3.0-Å 
resolution using the program <rs type="software">SHARP/autoSHARP</rs> (50). 
Of the nine selenium sites, seven were found. 
Interpretation of the electron density maps and model-
building procedures were carried out on a Linux PC with 
the aid of the program X-fit as implemented in the 
program <rs id="software-2" type="software">XtalView</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 4.0</rs> (51). The obtained model 
was refined at 2.4-Å resolution with the programs <rs type="software">CNS</rs> 
(52) and <rs type="software">REFMAC</rs> (53). After each refinement calcula-
tion, the obtained model was corrected with difference 
Fourier maps using XtalView. Water molecules were 
picked by the water-add routine in XtralView. The 
stereochemistry of the model was verified using the 
program PROCHECK in the <rs type="software">CCP4</rs> program suite. 
The present model includes residues 8 to 356 of 
SceTyrRS, one tRNA 
Tyr molecule, one Tyr-AMPN 
molecule, one magnesium ion and 57 water molecules 
per asymmetric unit. Residues 224-233 of SceTyrRS, the 
base moieties 16, 20, 31, 40, 41 and 46 of tRNA 
Tyr , and 
the whole nucleotides 17, 20a, 20b, 32 and 33 of tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>, 
were disordered. The current R-factor is 0.245 
(R free = 0.289) for the resolution range of 40.0-2.4 Å . 
The root-mean-square-distances (RMSDs) from ideal 
values are 0.006 Å for bond lengths and 1.124 for bond 
angles. The refinement statistics are summarized in 
Table 1. The atomic coordinates have been deposited in 
the Protein Data Bank with the entry code 2DLC. </p>

<p>Graphics programs </p>

<p>Figures were produced using both the <rs id="software-9" type="software">DINO</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-9" type="url">http:// www.dino3d.org</rs>) and <rs id="software-10" type="software">POV-Ray</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-10" type="url">http://www.povray.org</rs>) 
programs (Figure 1B and D) or both the <rs type="software">Ribbons</rs> (54) and 
POV-Ray programs (Figures 1C, 2, 4, 5, 6 and 7). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Structure determination </p>

<p>The crystallization trials conducted to date have not 
successfully obtained crystals of ligand-free SceTyrRS. 
Fortunately, however, crystals of the ternary (SceTyrRS/ 
Tyr-AMP analog/tRNA 
Tyr ) complex of SceTyrRS were 
successfully obtained. For this study, a Tyr-AMP analog 
having an N-acyl phosphoramidate linkage where the 
oxygen atom of the mixed anhydride bond (-C-O-P-) of 
Tyr-AMP was replaced by an amino group (-C-NH-P-) 
(O-(adenosine-5 
0 -O-yl) 
N-(L-tyrosyl)phosphoramidate 
[(hereafter Tyr-AMPN), Figure 1A], was used for crystal-
lization. Initial phase calculation was performed by the 
MAD method using the Se-Met-substituted SceTyrRS at 
3.0-Å resolution (Figure 1B). Further model building and 
structure refinement were performed using the native 
SceTyrRS, and we refined resulting model to an R-factor 
of 0.245 (R free of 0.289) at 2.4-Å resolution. The data 
collection and refinement statistics are summarized 
in Table 1. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 1. Structure determination of the ternary complex of SceTyrRS. 
(A) Structure of the Tyr-AMP analog (Tyr-AMPN), having an N-acyl 
phosphoramidate linkage where the oxygen atom of the mixed 
anhydride bond (-C-O-P-) of Tyr-AMP was replaced by an amino 
group (-C-NH-P-), used for the present crystal structure analysis. 
(B) Stereo diagram of the experimentally phased MAD map at 3.0-Å 
resolution of the Tyr-AMPN binding site of the ternary complex of 
SceTyrRS. The contour level is 1.2s. (C) <rs type="software">Ribbon</rs> drawing of the dimer 
of the ternary complex of SceTyrRS. The SceTyrRS (yellow and green) 
and tRNA 
Tyr (blue and orange) molecules are shown as ribbon models. 
The catalytic and anticodon-binding domains of TyrRS are shown as 
light and dark colors, respectively. The bound Tyr-AMPN molecules 
are shown as CPK models. The molecular two-fold axis [coinciding 
with the (1 1 0) crystallographic two-fold axis] is perpendicular to the 
plane of the paper. The structural discontinuity in the anticodon-loop 
of tRNA 
Tyr is due to the disordered nucleotides C32-U33. (D) Stereo 
diagram of the experimentally phased MAD map at 3.0-Å resolution 
showing the well-ordered anticodon bases (G34-É35-A36) of 
Sce-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>. The contour level is 1.0s. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 13 4291 </p>

<p>Overall structure </p>

<p>The overall structure of the ternary complex of SecTyrRS 
is shown in Figure 1C. As observed in the cases of 
TthTyrRS (11) and MjaTyrRS (14), SecTyrRS forms 
a homo dimer and two tRNA 
Tyr s are bound to each 
dimer in a symmetrical fashion. The asymmetric 
unit contains one SceTyrRS subunit and one tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>molecule (one-half of a 2:2 complex). The molecular two-
fold axis coincides with a [1 1 0] crystallographic two-fold 
axis. In addition, a Tyr-AMP analog, Tyr-AMPN, is 
bound at the active site of SceTyrRS (Figure 1B). 
A perfectly symmetrical SceTyrRS/tRNA 
Tyr /Tyr-AMPN 
complex in crystal presented here is contrary to the 
functional asymmetry of TyrRSs in solution (18) that the 
enzyme exhibit half-of-the-sites' reactivity with respect to 
the binding of tyrosine or Tyr-AMP and one tRNA 
molecule is bound per dimer of TyrRS. As for the 
explanations for this discrepancy, we completely agree 
with the notion pointed out by Yaremchuk et al. (11) 
that perfectly (or nearly) symmetrical structure observed 
in the crystal structures of TyrRSs is due to the fact 
that (i) there is ample time for substrate binding to both 
active sites in a crystallization experiment and there is 
quite likely preferential crystallization of a symmetrical 
form and (ii) in the case of tRNA binding, the same 
arguments hold. In addition, we postulate that consider-
ably higher concentrations (as compared with the previous 
functional studies for TyrRSs in solution) of SceTyrRS </p>

<p>(ca. 0.2 mM), tRNA 
Tyr (ca. 0.2 mM) and Tyr-AMPN 
(5 mM) and a large excess of Tyr-AMPN in the crystal-
lization solution favor the formation of symmetrical dimer 
in the crystal. 
The subunit of SceTyrRS consists of two domains. One 
of these, the catalytic domain, provides the groups 
necessary for converting the substrates Tyr and ATP 
into reactive intermediate Tyr-AMP (the first step of the 
aaRS reaction) and for transferring the amino acid moiety 
from the Tyr-AMP to the 3 
0 -CCA terminus of the cognate 
tRNA 
Tyr (the second step of the aaRS reaction). The other 
domain is responsible for the recognition of the anticodon 
bases of the cognate tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>. The two domains are 
unequal in size; the catalytic domain is somewhat larger 
and comprises 232 residues, whereas the anticodon-
binding domain comprises 117 residues. The catalytic 
domain comprises residues 8 to 239. The structural core of 
this domain is an a/b structure (or Rossmann fold) 
comprised of a six-stranded parallel b-sheet and 10 
surrounding a-helices (Figure 1C, light colors). The Tyr-
AMPN molecule is bound in the central region of the 
carboxyl end of the parallel b-sheet in the center of the 
domain. The anticodon-binding domain comprises resi-
dues 240 to 356. The basic element of the secondary 
structure in this domain consists of six a-helices and a 
two-stranded anti-parallel b-hairpin (Figure 1C, dark 
colors). A loop region between the two domains (residues 
224-233), including the KMSKS signature motif, which is </p>

<p>Table 1. Data collection and refinement statistics for the ternary complex of SceTyrRS </p>

<p>Data collection statistics 
Data set 
Native 
Se-MAD (4 wavelengths) </p>

<p>Peak 
Edge 
Low-Remote 
High-Remote </p>

<p>X-ray source 
SPring-8 BL40B1 
SPring-8 BL38B2 
Temperature 
100K 
100 K 
Detector 
ADSC Q4R 
ADSC Q4R 
Resolution (outer shell) (Å ) 
2.4 (2.53-2.4) 
3.0 (3.16-3.0) 
Wavelength (Å ) 
1.0000 
0.9798 
0.9801 
0.9819 
0.9727 
Unique reflections 
27 897 
14 733 
14 738 
14 737 
14 741 
Multiplicity 
4.1 (4.2) 
19.8 (19.4) 
13.4 (13.1) 
13.4 (13.0) 
13.5 (13.6) 
Completeness (%) 
99.4 (99.6) 
99.9 (100) 
99.9 (100) 
99.9 (100) 
99.9 (100) 
I/s(I) 
11.7 (2.0) 
9.1 (2.5) 
8.9 (2.2) 
8.7 (2.0) 
8.6 (1.9) 
R sym (%) 
4.8 (39.6) 
6.8 (29.9) 
7.1 (34.4) 
7.2 (36.4) 
7.3 (38.4) </p>

<p>Refinement statistics 
Resolution range (outer shell) (Å ) 
40 -2.4 (2.46-2.4) 
No. of reflections: 
working set 
test set </p>

<p>26 411 
1403 
R-factor 
0.245 (0.347) 
Free R-factor 
0.289 (0.405) 
No. of protein atoms [average B-factors (Å </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>)] 
2699 (33.4) 
No. of Mg atoms [average B-factors (Å </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>)] 
1 (42.5) 
No. of Tyr-AMPN atoms [average B-factors (Å 
2 )] 
35 (48.3) 
No. of tRNA atoms [average B-factors (Å </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>)] 
1472 (33.6) 
No. of water molecules [average B-factors (Å 
2 )] 
57 (55.7) 
RMSDs: 
bond lengths (Å ) 
bond angles (deg.) </p>

<p>0.006 
1.124 
Ramachandran plot: 
most favored (%) 
90.2 
additional allowed (%) 
9.2 
generously allowed (%) 
0.6 </p>



<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 2. Overall structures of TyrRSs complexed with their cognate tRNA 
Tyr s. The TyrRS and tRNA 
Tyr molecules are colored as in Figure 1C. 
Cloverleaf models of tRNA 
Tyr s are shown in the right panel. The disordered nucleotides in the crystal structure analyses are shown in blue for the 
disordered bases (phosphate backbone is visible) and red for the entirely disordered nucleotides. (A) Eukaryotic TyrRS (SceTyrRS). (B) Archaeal 
TyrRS (MjaTyrRS). (C) Bacterial TyrRS (TthTyrRS). A variable arm of tRNA and an additional C-terminal domain of TyrRS that specifically exist 
in bacterial systems are indicated by an ellipsoid. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 13 4293 </p>

<p>one of the two consensus motifs conserved among the 
class I aaRSs, is disordered. 
The tRNA 
Tyr molecule forms an L-shaped structure. 
The acceptor stem and anticodon loop of the tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>interact with different subunits of the dimeric TyrRS 
molecule (Figure 1C). The structural discontinuity in the 
anticodon-loop of tRNA 
Tyr is due to the disordered 
nucleotides C32-U33. However, the anticodon triplet of 
tRNA 
Tyr (GÉA) was well ordered (Figure 1D). The 
catalytic domain of one subunit (yellow) recognizes the 
acceptor stem of a tRNA (blue), while the anticodon-
binding domain of the other subunit (green) recognizes the 
anticodon bases of the same tRNA (blue). The overall 
structure of the ternary complex of SceTyrRS is similar to 
that of MjaTyrRS (Figure 2A and B), which is expected 
from the amino acid sequence similarity (Figure 3). 
In the TthTyrRS structure, on the other hand, a 
characteristic long variable arm of bacterial tRNA 
Tyr is 
recognized by an additional C-terminal domain of </p>

<p>TthTyrRS (Figure 2C). Amino-acid sequence alignment 
of the C-terminal domain of bacterial TyrRSs suggested 
that the conserved sequences of the C-terminal domains 
determined a conserved secondary structure (19). The 
structure of the C-terminal domain of BstTyrRS was 
determined using NMR (20), and was found to have a 
very similar structure to that of TthTyrRS (11). Recent 
advances in genome sequencing revealed that bacterial 
tyrosyl-tRNA synthetases occur in two large subfamilies; 
TyrRS and TyrRZ that possess about 25% amino-acid 
sequence identity (21 and references therein). More 
detailed functional and structural analyses of the 
TyrRZ-tRNA 
Tyr complex are necessary to shed more 
light on the evolutionary divergence of the enzyme-tRNA 
interactions of the TyrRS and TyrRZ subfamilies in the 
bacterial domain. 
As observed in the structures of the ternary complexes 
of TthTyrRS and MjaTyrRS, SceTyrRS has a class II 
mode of tRNA recognition, i.e. it interacts with tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>YEAST LGYKKRAHLMNPMVPG-LAQGGKMSASDPNSKIDLL---EEPKQVKKKINSAFCSPGNVEENGLLSFVQYVIAPIQELKF 281 
HUMAN LGYSKRVHLMNPMVPGLTGS--KMSSSEEESKIDLL---DRKEDVKKKLKKAFCEPGNVENNGVLSFIKHVLFPL---KS 273 
METJA ---KKVVCIHNPVLTG-LDGEGKMSSSKG-NFIAVD---DSPEEIRAKIKKAYCPAGVVEGNPIMEIAKYFL---E----250 
BACST EA-R-AFGLTIPLVTK-ADGT-KFGKTES-GTIWLDKEKTSPYEFYQFWINTDD-------RDVIRYLKYFT---F----272 </p>

<p>THETH ---SPQVCFLMPLLVG-LDGREKMSKSLD-NYIGLT---EPPEAMFKKLMRVPD-------PLLPSYFRLLT---D----271 </p>

<p>ECOLI ---Q-VFGLTVPLITK-ADGT-KFGKTEG-GAVWLDPKKTSPYKFYQFWINTAD-------ADVYRFLKFFT---F----276 </p>

<p>YEAST ..DPN---EAFGLITKN--LQEVLNPQIIKDVLEVQKRH-LKLYWGTAP-TGRPHCGYFVPMTKLADFLKAGCEVTVLLA 77 
HUMAN APSPE---EKLHLITRN--LQEVLGEEKLKEILK--ERE-LKIYWGTAT-TGKPHVAYFVPMSKIADFLKAGCEVTILFA 74 
METJA 
M---DEFEMIKRN--TSEIISEEELREVLK-K-DE-KSAYIGFEP-SGKIHLGHYLQIKKMIDLQNAGFDIIILLA 67 
BACST 
M-DLLAELQWRGLVNQTTDEDGLRKLLN-E--ERVTLYCGFDPTADSLHIGHLASILTMRRFQQAGHRPIALVG 70 </p>

<p>THETH ....HTPEEALALLKRG--AEEIVPEEELLAKLK-E-GRPLTVKLGADPTRPDLHLGHAVVLRKMRQFQELGHKVVLIIG 77 </p>

<p>ECOLI 
MASSNLIKQLQERGLVAQVTDEEALAERLA-Q--GPIALYCGFDPTADSLHLGHLVPLLCLKRFQQAGHKPVALVG 72 </p>

<p>YEAST DLHAFLD-------NM--K--AP-LEVVNYRAKYYELTIKAILRSINVPI-----EK-LKFVVGSSYQLTPDYTM-DIF-138 
HUMAN DLHAYL--------DNMK----APWELLELRVSYYENVIKAMLESIGVPL-----EK-LKFIKGTDYQLSKEYTL-DVY-134 
METJA DLHAYLN-------Q---K--GE-LDEIRKIGDYNKKVFEAMG----L-K--------AKYVYGSEFQLDKDYTL-NVY-119 
BACST GATGLIGDPSGKKSE---RTLNA-KETVEAWSARIKEQLGRFL----D-FEADGN--PAKIKNNYDWIGP--LDVITFLR 137 </p>

<p>THETH DFTGMIGDPSGRSKT---RPPLT-LEETRENAKTYVAQAGKIL----R-Q-EPHL---FELRYNSEWLEG--LTFKEVV-141 </p>

<p>ECOLI GATGLIGDPSFKAAE---RKLNT-EETVQEWVDKIRKQVAPFL----D-FDCGEN--SAIAANNYDWFGN--MNVLTFLR 139 </p>

<p>YEAST RLSNIVSQNDAKRAGADVVKQV-----ANPLLSGLIYPLMQALDEQFLD----VDCQFGGVDQRKIFVLAEENLP----S 205 
HUMAN RLSSVVTQHDSKKAGAEVVKQV-----EHPLLSGLLYPGLQALDEEYLK----VDAQFGGIDQRKIFTFAEKYLP----A 201 
METJA RLALKTTLKRARRSMELIARED-----ENPKVAEVIYPIMQVNDIHYLG----VDVAVGGMEQRKIHMLARELLP-----185 
BACST DVGKHFSVNYMMAKES--VQSRIE---TGISFTEFSYMMLQAYDFLRLYETEGCRLQIGGSDQWGNITAGLELIRKTKG-211 </p>

<p>THETH RLTSLMTVAQMLERED--FKKRYEAG-IPISLHELLYPFAQAYDSVAIR----ADVEMGGTDQRFNLLVGREVQRAY-GQ 213 </p>

<p>ECOLI DIGKHFSVNQMINKEA--VKQRLNREDQGISFTEFSYNLLQGYDFACLNKQYGVVLQIGGSDQWGNITSGIDLTRRLHQN 217 </p>

<p>YEAST GTNHFEFFIDRPEKFGGPITYKSFEEMKLAFKEEKL----S-PPDLKIGVADAINELLEPIRQEFANNKEFQEASEKGYP 356 
HUMAN -----EFVILRDEKWGGNKTYTAYVDLEKDFAAEVV----H-PGDLKNSVEVALNKLLDPIREKFNT-PALKKLASAAYP 342 
METJA ----YPLTIKRPEKFGGDLTVNSYEELESLFKNKEL----H-PMDLKNAVAEELIKILEPIRKRL 
306 
BACST ----L-----------------S-KEEIEALE--QELREAPEKRAAQKTLAEEVTKLVHG-( 11 residues) 
319 </p>

<p>THETH ----L-----------------E-EEEIEALL--KA----G-PVPAHRVLARLLTAAYAL-(130 residues) 
432 </p>

<p>ECOLI ----M-----------------S-IEEINALE--EEDKNSGKAPRAQYVLAEQVTRLVHG-( 9 residues) 
322 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Structure-based sequence alignment of TyrRSs. The sequences are derived from eukaryotes, yeast (PDB code: 2DLC) and human (1N3L); 
in an archaea, M. jannaschii (1J1U); and in bacteria, B. stearothermophilus (1TYD), E. coli (1X8X) and T. thermophilus (1H3E). The secondary 
structure elements of yeast and T. thermophilus TyrRSs are shown above and below the alignment, respectively. The residues mentioned in the text 
are shown in red (Tyr-AMP recognition), green (acceptor stem recognition) and blue (anticodon recognition). The residues that are disordered in the 
crystal structures are represented in italics. Class I signature motifs, HIGH and KMSKS, are highlighted in yellow. </p>



<p>from the variable loop and acceptor stem major groove 
side. This is in strong contrast to canonical class I 
enzymes, which approach cognate tRNA from the 
acceptor stem minor groove side. </p>

<p>Anticodon recognition mode </p>

<p>In the present structure analysis, the anticodon triplet 
of tRNA 
Tyr (GÉA) was well ordered (Figure 1D). The 
first anticodon, G34, is flipped out and base-specifically 
recognized by SceTyrRS (Figure 4A). The guanine ring 
moiety of G34 shows a stacking interaction with Phe296. 
The opposite face of the base has hydrophobic contact 
with Pro320. The N1 and O6 atoms of G34 have base-
specific interactions with Asp321 through bifurcated </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Figure 5. Acceptor arm recognition by TyrRSs. Protein and tRNA 
backbones are shown as in Figure1C. Possible hydrogen bonds 
are indicated by dashed lines. (A) Eukaryotic TyrRS (SceTyrRS). 
(B) Archaeal TyrRS (MjaTyrRS). (C) Bacterial TyrRS (TthTyrRS). 
(D) Possible recognition model of the 3 
0 -CCA terminus of tRNA 
Tyr by 
SceTyrRS. The C74-C75-A76 of tRNA 
Tyr is modeled (orange) into the 
active site of SceTyrRS by manually rotating the experimentally 
determined 3 
0 -CCA terminus of tRNA 
Tyr (light gray), which was 
ordered but flipped out from the active site in the present crystal 
structure analysis. The backbone conformation of the 3 
0 -CCA terminus 
and the positions of the bases are by no means necessarily correct. 
The aim is to show that the observed mode of tRNA 
Tyr binding 
to SceTyrRS allows the positioning of 2 
0 -OH of the ribose 
of A76 adjacent to the carboxyl group of the Tyr-AMP without 
steric clashes. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 4. Anticodon recognition by TyrRSs. Protein and tRNA 
backbones are shown as in Figure 1C. Possible hydrogen bonds are 
indicated by dashed lines. (A) Eukaryotic TyrRS (SceTyrRS). The 
structural discontinuity in the anticodon-loop of tRNA 
Tyr is due to 
the disordered nucleotides C32-U33. (B) Archaeal TyrRS (MjaTyrRS). 
(C) Bacterial TyrRS (TthTyrRS). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 13 4295 </p>

<p>hydrogen bonds. It is reported that mutation of G34 in 
yeast tRNA 
Tyr impairs aminoacylation by SceTyrRS (7). 
The second and third anticodon bases, É35 and A36, have 
fewer base-specific interactions with the enzyme; only N3 
of É35 hydrogen bonds with the main chain carbonyl 
group of Cys255 (Figure 4A). They are accommodated in 
a hydrophobic patch composed of Phe254, Pro257, 
Pro319 and Pro320 (Figure 1D). This observation is also 
consistent with the results of the functional analysis of </p>

<p>SceTyrRS by Fechter et al. (7). It is of note here that 
the tyrosylation activity is compatible with an 'a+1 
shift' [Figure 6 (7)] of the anticodon in the 3 
0 -direction 
(G35-U36-A37) but is strongly inhibited in the opposite 
5 
0 -direction (G33-U34-A35) (7). This result is explained by 
the present structure analysis, which shows that the 
electron density of the anticodon stem region was rather 
poor: the base moieties 31, 40 and 41 and the whole 
nucleotides 32 and 33 of tRNA 
Tyr were disordered. 
In addition, our recent biochemical analysis (22) also 
suggests the flexibility of the anticodon stem region of 
Sce-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>. This is consistent with the low G-C content 
at the anticodon stem region of Sce-tRNA 
Tyr as compared 
with that of Mja-tRNA 
Tyr . The flexibility in the 5 
0 -portion 
of the anticodon loop enables the shift of the anticodon in 
the 3 
0 -direction, which can be regarded as an insertion of 
one nucleotide before G34. 
The anticodon recognition mode of archaeal MjaTyrRS 
(Figure 4B) is quite similar to that of eukaryotic SceTyrRS 
(Figure 4A), except that the hydrophobic interaction 
between Pro320 and G34 in SceTyrRS is replaced by the 
stacking interaction between His283 and G34 in 
MjaTyrRS. 
The anticodon recognition mode of prokaryotic 
TthTyrRS (Figure 4C) is markedly different from those 
of eukaryotic and archaeal enzymes. In the TthTyrRS 
complex, the guanine base of G34, base-specifically 
recognized by Asp259, is stacked with the third </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Figure 6. Amino acid and ATP recognition by TyrRSs. The bound 
substrate analogs are shown as stick models (cyan). Possible hydrogen 
bonds are indicated by dashed lines. Two consensus motifs, HIGH and 
KMSKS, conserved among the class I aaRSs are shown in blue and 
red, respectively. (A) Eukaryotic TyrRS (SceTyrRS). (B) Archaeal 
TyrRS (MjaTyrRS). (C) Bacterial TyrRS (TthTyrRS). </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 7. Triplet motifs crucial for the cytokine activity of eukaryotic 
TyrRSs. (A) The ELR motif of human TyrRS. (B) The NYR motif of 
yeast TyrRS. </p>



<p>anticodon base, A36. The second anticodon base, É35, is 
oppositely flipped out and base-specifically recognized 
by Asp423. </p>

<p>Acceptor arm recognition mode </p>

<p>The specific aminoacylation of tRNA by TysRS relies 
on the identity determinants (the anticodon bases, the 
C1-G72 base pair, and the discriminator base A73) in the 
cognate tRNA 
Tyr (6-8). A previous observation showed 
that the strongest determinants are base pair C1-G72 and 
discriminator base A73 for SceTyrRS, while the three 
anticodon bases (G34, É35 and A36) contribute to lesser 
extents (7). A similar observation was reported for 
MjaTyrRS (8). Before the present crystal structure 
analysis, the recognition modes of the identity determi-
nants by the archaeal and eukaryotic TyrRSs were 
expected to be similar to each other but different from 
that by the bacterial TyrRSs. Interestingly, however, 
the tRNA 
Tyr recognition modes of SceTyrRS have both 
similarities and differences compared with those in 
MjaTyrRS: the recognition of the C1-G72 base pair by 
SceTyrRS is similar to that by MjaTyrRS, whereas the 
recognition of the A73 by SceTyrRS is different from that 
by MjaTyrRS but similar to that by TthTyrRS (Figure 5). 
The expected feature is that the recognition mode of the 
identity base pair C1-G72 by SceTyrRS (Figure 5A) is 
similar to that by MjaTyrRS (Figure 5B). The recognition 
mode of the C1 base by the side chain of Arg193 in 
SceTyrRS is equivalent to that by the side chain of Arg174 
in MjaTyrRS. The G72 base is recognized by a slightly 
different manner between SceTyrRS and MjaTyrRS. The 
3 
0 -terminal strand of the acceptor stem of SceTyrRS 
shows a helical conformation. The G72 base in SceTyrRS 
is recognized by a base-specific hydrogen bond with the 
side chain of Arg151 and a stacking interaction with 
the discriminator base A73, which is fixed by a hydrogen 
bond with Arg193. On the other hand, the 3 
0 -terminal 
strand of the acceptor stem of MjaTyrRS shows a rather 
extended conformation. The G72 base is far from the side 
chain of Arg132, corresponding to Arg151 in SceTyrRS, 
and is recognized by the side chain of Lys175. The side 
chain of Arg132 is involved in the recognition of the C1 
base, rather than the G72 base, via a water-mediated 
hydrogen bond (Figure 5B). Although the G72 base 
recognition mode of SceTyrRS and that of MjaTyrRS 
have some differences, the archaeal/eukaryotic TyrRSs 
recognize the identity base pair C1-G72 by conserved 
residues (Figure 3) and we assume that the recognition 
mode of the C1-G72 base pair by the archaeal/eukaryotic 
TyrRSs are essentially conserved. 
The unexpected feature is that the recognition mode of 
A73 by SceTyrRS (Figure 5A) is similar to that by 
TthTyrRS (Figure 5C) but is different from that by 
MjaTyrRS (Figure 5B). In the case of SceTyrRS 
(Figure 5A), the N3 of A73 is recognized by Arg193 via 
a single hydrogen bond, and the discriminator base A73 is 
stacked with the G72 base. An equivalent recognition 
mode is observed for the TthTyrRS complex (Figure 5C): 
the N3 of A73 is recognized by Arg198 via a single 
hydrogen bond, and the discriminator base A73 is stacked </p>

<p>with the C72 base. In the case of MjaTyrRS (Figure 5B), 
the discriminator base A73 is unstacked with the G72 base 
and out of the helical continuity of the acceptor stem. The 
N1 and N6 atoms of A73 are base-specifically recognized 
by the main-chain amino and carbonyl groups, respec-
tively, of Val195. Since Arg193 in SceTyrRS (Arg198 in 
TthTyrRS) is also conserved in MjaTyrRS (Arg174), the 
observation that A73 is bound in a different manner in 
SceTyrRS and MjaTyrRS may reflect different modes of 
binding, rather than species-specific difference. However, 
it should be noted here that the Arg residues are not 
conserved in BstTyrRS (Trp196) and EcoTyrRS (Trp201) 
(Figure 3). The different recognition pattern of A73 would 
be observed in BstTyrRS and EcoTyrRS. 
In the present crystal structure of SceTyrRS, the 
3 
0 -CCA terminus of tRNA 
Tyr is well ordered by a triplex 
stacking interactions of the C74, C75 and A76 bases, but 
was flipped-out from the active center. Manual model 
adjustment of the 3 
0 -CCA terminus allows the 2 
0 -OH of 
the terminal ribose to be correctly positioned for 
aminoacylation (Figure 5D). This model is consistent 
with the fact that TyrRSs preferentially aminoacylate the 
2 
0 -OH of A76 in accordance with other class I enzymes, 
although it can also aminoacylate the 3 
0 -OH (23). Thus we 
assume that the present structure of the acceptor region of 
Sce-tRNA 
Tyr is not an artifact at least up to the 
discriminator base A73. 
As for the binding mode of the 3 
0 -CCA terminus of 
tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>, the CCA terminus of MjaTyrRS (14) and that 
of TthTyrRS (11) were disordered, while that of SceTyrRS 
was flipped out from the active site. Because neither of the 
available complex structures (SceTyrRS-tRNA 
Tyr -Tyr-
AMPN, MjaTyrRS-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>-tyrosine and TthTyrRS-
tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>-tyrosinol-ATP) contains true reactive intermedi-
ate, Tyr-AMP, the non-productive binding of the 3 
0 -CCA 
terminus may occur. </p>

<p>Aminoacyl-AMP recognition mode </p>

<p>The present study successfully revealed the recognition 
modes of Tyrosyl-AMP, the reactive aminoacyl-adenylate 
(aa-AMP) intermediate, by SceTyrRS, as a result of our 
use of a Tyr-AMP analog, Tyr-AMPN (Figure 1A). The 
Tyr-AMP recognition mode is well conserved among the 
archaeal, bacterial and eukaryotic TyrRSs as described 
below. The tyrosine moiety is accommodated in a deep 
pocket of the enzyme (Figure 6A). The hydroxyl group of 
the tyrosine moiety makes hydrogen bonds with the side 
chains of Tyr43 and Asp177. The main-chain amino group 
of the tyrosine moiety is specifically recognized by three 
hydrogen bonds: they are from the side chains of Tyr170, 
Gln174 and Gln192. The carbonyl group of the tyrosine 
moiety is recognized by the side chain of Gln192. 
In archaeal and bacterial TyrRSs (Figure 6B and C), the 
recognition mode of the tyrosine moiety of Tyr-AMP is 
apparently similar to that of SceTyrRS. Tyr170, Gln174, 
Asp177 and Gln192 in SceTyrRS are well conserved 
(Figure 3) and play the same roles in the binding of the 
tyrosine moiety of Tyr-AMP (or its analog) among 
TyrRSs. In the case of BstTyrRS/TyrAMP complex (9), 
however, the side chain of Gln195 (Gln192 in SceTyrRS) </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 13 4297 </p>

<p>does not form a hydrogen bond with the amino group of 
Tyr-AMP. Instead, the side chain of Asp78 is involved in 
the hydrogen bond with the amino group of Tyr-AMP 
together with the side chains of Tyr169 and Gln173 
(Tyr170 and Gln174 in SceTyrRS). As for the recognition 
mode of the AMP moiety of Tyr-AMPN, the adenine ring 
is base-specifically recognized by the main-chain atoms of 
Val219 in SceTyrRS [N6(Ade)-O(Val229) and 
N1(Ade)-N(Val229), Figure 6A]. A similar recognition 
mode is also found for the main chain atoms of Leu224 in 
TthTyrRS (Figure 6C). The oxygen atom of the phosphate 
group of Tyr-AMPN is fixed to the protein surface 
[Ala47(O), Tyr56(OH), and Tyr101(OH)], via a magne-
sium ion (Figure 6A). </p>

<p>The conserved HIGH and KMSKS signature motifs </p>

<p>The conserved signature motifs of class I aaRSs, HIGH 
and KMSKS (blue and red, respectively, in Figure 6), are 
involved in the catalysis of tyrosine activation with ATP. 
It is reported that the HIGH motif is involved in binding 
with the g-phosphate group of ATP in EcoTyrRS (12). 
In the present structure analysis, the HIGH motif's 
important role in tyrosine activation is not observed 
because of the absence of b-and g-phosphate groups in 
Tyr-AMPN (Figure 6A). 
The KMSKS motif shows conformational changes in 
tyrosine activation (12): initially, the KMSKS motif 
adopts the open form and then, upon binding of the 
adenosyl moiety of ATP, shifts to the semi-open form 
before finally assuming the ATP-bound closed form. 
In that study, Kobayashi et al.(12) assumed that after 
the amino acid activation, the KMSKS motif adopts the 
semi-open form to accept the 3 
0 -CCA terminus of tRNA 
for the aminoacyl transfer reaction. In the present 
structure of SceTyrRS, residues 224-233, including the 
KMSAS sequence (Figure 3), are disordered. This 
flexibility of the loop containing the KMSKS motif 
would allow the Tyr-AMP to be fully exposed and the 
3 
0 -CCA terminus of tRNA to access the aminoacyl 
transfer center. Unfortunately, however, the 3 
0 -CCA 
terminus of tRNA 
Tyr is ordered but flipped out from the 
active center in the present crystal structure (Figure 5D). 
In the case of TthTyrRS (Figure 6C), the loop containing 
the KMSKS motif interacts with ATP and is structurally 
well ordered. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The structural origin of tyrosine identity and species 
difference </p>

<p>In the aminoacylation of tRNAs, each amino acid is 
matched with a tRNA that contains the anticodon that 
corresponds to that amino acid. Although the anticodons 
within tRNAs are conserved for a given amino acid 
throughout evolution, the aaRS from one species does not 
aminoacylate its cognate tRNA from another species in 
some cases. Typical example is TyrRSs that exhibit 
species-specific tRNA 
Tyr recognition (8,24-30). The 
origin of species-specific tRNA 
Tyr recognition is the 
presence of a G1-C72 base pair in bacterial tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>and a C1-G72 pair in archaeal/eukaryotic tRNA 
Tyr (29). 
Because the archaeal/eukaryotic TyrRSs-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s pairs 
do not cross-react with their bacterial counterparts, 
the recognition modes of the identity determinants by 
the archaeal and eukaryotic TyrRSs were expected to be 
similar to each other but different from that by the 
bacterial TyrRSs. Interestingly, however, a structural 
comparison between the present crystal structure of the 
ternary complex of SceTyrRS with the available crystal 
structures of the ternary complexes of TthTyrRS (11) and 
MjaTyrRS (14) revealed (i) an unexpected similarity in the 
recognition mode of the discriminator base A73 between 
SceTyrRS and TthTyrRS (Figure 5A and C) and (ii) some 
differences in the recognition mode of the G72-A73 bases 
between SceTyrRS and MjaTyrRS (Figure 5A and B). 
These features indicate that the interaction mode between 
TyrRS and the cognate tRNA 
Tyr appears to have evolved 
separately for the three kingdoms of life, i.e. TyrRSs/ 
tRNA 
Tyr s pairs have diverged after the kingdoms sepa-
rated (31). 
The present crystal structure analysis of the eukaryotic 
SceTyrRS and structural comparisons strongly support 
the notion pointed out by Wakasugi et al. (29) that the 
lack of cross-reactivity between archaeal/eukaryotic and 
bacterial TyrRS-tRNA 
Tyr pairs most probably lies in the 
different sequence of the last base pair of the acceptor 
stem (C1-G72 vs G1-C72) of tRNA 
Tyr . 
On the other hand, the recognition modes of Tyr-AMP 
are conserved among the TyrRSs from all three kingdoms 
(Figure 6). In the class I aaRSs, the amino acid binding 
pocket lies at the bottom of an active site cleft in the 
Rossmann-fold domain. In general, the class I aaRSs use a 
lock-and-key mechanism to recognize the side chains of 
their amino acid substrates, although some exceptions 
exist. Detailed sequence alignment of TyrRSs and TrpRSs 
as well as the crystal structure analyses of human TyrRS 
(HsaTyrRS) and human TrpRS (HsaTrpRS) by Yang 
et al. (32) provided a unique example for amino acid 
discrimination by TyrRS and TrpRS. An environment for 
recognition of the hydroxyl group of Tyr side chain is 
provided by the universal presence of aspartate (Asp173 in 
HsaTyrRS) and the presence of either tyrosine (Tyr39 in 
HsaTyrRS) or lysine (Lys41 in TthTyrRS) (Figures 3 and 
6). Interestingly, TrpRS uses the structurally equivalent 
residues (either Pro287 or Tyr159, respectively, in 
HsaTrpRS, but not both) to hydrogen bond to the 
indole nitrogen of tryptophan. In the case of yeast 
system [Asp177 and Tyr43 in SceTyrRS (Figure 6A) and 
Thr233 and Tyr106 in SceTrpRS(GI:51013347)], the 
same arguments appear to hold, although crystal 
structure analysis of SceTrpRS has not yet reported. The 
present crystal structure analysis of SceTyrRS and 
structural comparisons of the amino acid binding site 
of TyrRSs (Figure 6) are consistent with the structural 
and phylogenetic studies of TyrRS and TrpRS by 
Yang et al. (32). </p>

<p>Expanding the genetic code </p>

<p>The archaeal/eukaryotic TyrRSs-tRNA </p>

<p>Tyr </p>

<p>s pairs do 
not cross-react with their bacterial counterparts (8). </p>



<p>Such orthogonality is used for the incorporation of 
unnatural amino acids into proteins with engineered 
pairs of TyrRSs and tRNA 
Tyr s (15,17,33-38). We have 
been trying to utilize the yeast TyrRS/tRNA 
Tyr pair as a 
candidate for the carrier of unnatural amino acid in the E. 
coli translation system in vivo (39) or in vitro (40). 
We previously showed that the substitution of tyrosine 
at position 43 to glycine (Y43G mutation) in SceTyrRS 
led to a drastic change in amino acid specificity. 
The Y43G mutant was found to be able to utilize several 
3-substituted L-tyrosine analogs, rather than L-tyrosine, 
as substrates for aminoacylation (34). Used together with 
yeast amber suppressor tRNA 
Tyr , the Y43G mutant 
should serve as an effective tool for site-specific incorpora-
tion of 3-substituted tyrosine analogs into proteins in an 
appropriate E. coli translation system (41). The present 
crystal structure analysis can explain the structural 
basis for recognition of 3-substituted tyrosine analogs 
by the Y43G mutant SceTyrRS. Since the side chain of 
Tyr43 is directly involved in binding with the tyrosine 
moiety of Tyr-AMPN (Figure 6A), substitution of the 
tyrosine residue to a smaller residue creates a space 
to accommodate an extra functional group at position 
3 of the substrate. Similar replacements are also reported 
for EcoTyrRS (17,38). The proteins containing unnatural 
amino acids will be used as molecular switches for 
signaling pathways, as photocrosslinkers, fluorescently 
labeled probes, or heavy-atom derivatives for phasing in 
X-ray structure determination. </p>

<p>The cytokine activity of TyrRS </p>

<p>It is reported that human TyrRS is secreted during 
apoptosis in cell culture and is cleaved with an extra-
cellular elastase, and the two released fragments (the 
N-terminal 'mini-TyrRS' and the EMAP II-like 
C-terminal domain) are active cytokines (42). The mini-
TyrRS has an ELR motif in the Rossmann-fold domain. 
This motif is responsible for IL-8-like cytokine activity 
and is conserved among segmented animals, whereas it is 
absent in yeast and lower eukaryote. In the case of yeast, 
SceTyrRS is inactive as a cytokine and has a NYR motif 
instead of an ELR motif. Interestingly, Liu et al. (43) 
reported that substitution of the tripeptide NYR to ELR 
in SceTyrRS resulted in mutant TyrRS with cytokine 
activity. This result suggests that it is the E and L that are 
strong candidates for a direct involvement in cytokine 
receptor binding. However, the Arg side chain appears to 
be also important for the cytokine activity of TyrRS, 
because an Arg93-to-Gln mutation in human mini-TyrRS 
abolished cytokine activity (42). A structural comparison 
between the ELR motif of human mini-TyrRS and the 
NYR motif of SceTyrRS (Figure 7) reveals that the 
overall structures around the motifs are similar to each 
other. Since the side chains of the ELR motif of human 
mini-TyrRS and the NYR motif of SceTyrRS are exposed, 
it is quite reasonable that substitution of the tripeptide 
NYR to ELR in SceTyrRS resulted in mutant TyrRS with 
cytokine activity. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Drs N. Matsugaki, N. Igarashi and M. Suzuki 
of Photon Factory, and Drs H. Sakai, M. Kawamoto and 
K. Miura of SPring-8 for their help with the data 
collection at synchrotron facilities. This work was 
supported in part by Grants-in Aid for Scientific 
Research No. 14704067 (to T.Y.) and a grant for the 
Protein 3000 Project (to N.T.) from the MEXT of Japan. 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for 
this article was provided by Showa University. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 13 4299 </p>





</text></tei>