<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1851647" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T06:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Over the past few years, small ubiquitin-like 
modifier (SUMO) modification has emerged as an 
important regulator of diverse pathways and 
activities including protein localization and tran-
scriptional regulation. We identified a consensus 
sumoylation motif (IKEE), located within the 
N-terminal activation domain of the ATF7 transcrip-
tion factor and thus investigated the role of this 
modification. ATF7 is a ubiquitously expressed 
transcription factor, homologous to ATF2, that 
binds to CRE elements within specific promoters. 
This protein is able to heterodimerize with Jun or 
Fos proteins and its transcriptional activity is 
mediated by interaction with TAF12, a subunit of 
the general transcription factor TFIID. In the present 
article, we demonstrate that ATF7 is sumoylated 
in vitro (using RanBP2 as a E3-specific ligase) and 
in vivo. Moreover, we show that ATF7 sumoylation 
affects its intranuclear localization by delaying 
its entry into the nucleus. Furthermore, SUMO 
conjugation inhibits ATF7 transactivation activity 
by (i) impairing its association with TAF12 and 
(ii) blocking its binding-to-specific sequences 
within target promoters. </p>

<p>In eukaryotic cells, post-translational protein modifica-
tions are crucial mechanisms to regulate protein function. 
Polypeptide conjugation to substrate proteins is one of 
these known mechanisms. Ubiquitin and ubiquitin-like 
proteins are small polypeptides of about 8-11 kDa that </p>

<p>covalently modify various intracellular proteins. Among 
these, the small ubiquitin-related modifiers (SUMO-1-4)  are covalently linked as a 93-97 amino-acid polypeptides 
to specific target lysine residues (1-4). Sumoylation is 
catalyzed by an enzymatic machinery analogous to that of 
ubiquitin-modification (2) and usually takes place at sites 
matching the sequence fKXE (where f stands for I, L or 
V and X for any amino acid residue). In addition to this 
core consensus motif, an extended sequence encompassing 
several acidic residues clustered within the 10-amino-acid 
region located immediately downstream has been recently 
described to play an important role in determining 
the efficiency of substrate sumoylation (5). Sumoylation 
depends on an activating SAE1/SAE2 E1-enzyme hetero-
dimer, the SUMO conjugating enzyme Ubc9 and recently 
identified E3 SUMO ligases. In contrast to ubiquitination 
that targets the conjugated proteins to 26S proteasome-
mediated degradation, the biological consequences 
of SUMO modification include nuclear targeting, the 
formation of subnuclear structures, the regulation of 
transcriptional activities and the control of protein 
stability (1,4,6). 
The family of ATF7 (formerly ATFa) transcription 
factors, structurally and functionally related to ATF2, is 
composed of at least three members (ATF7-1, 2, 3) (7,8)  translated from alternatively spliced messengers issued 
from a single gene (9). Although the three ATF7 isoforms 
differ by the presence of small motifs within their 
N-terminal region, they exhibit indistinguishable activ-
ities. Their transcriptional activation domain has been 
delineated within the N-terminal part of the protein and 
shown to include a critical zinc-binding element and two 
conserved threonine residues (T51 and T53, correspond-
ing to the T69 and T71 homologs in ATF2) (10,11). 
This region, together with sequences located in the </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ(33) 390 244 787; Faxþ(33) 390 244 770; Email: bchatton@esbs.u-strasbg.fr 
The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the second and third authors contributed equally to this work. </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>C-terminal portion of the ATF7 proteins, contributes to 
their interaction with the adenovirus E1a oncoprotein (8). 
ATF7, like ATF2, can also associate with c-Jun or c-Fos 
proteins through their C-terminal leucine-zipper (b-ZIP) 
region. While ATF proteins usually bind as homodimers 
to ATF/CRE promoter elements, they also can bind TRE 
sequences if heterodimerized with members of the Jun 
family (10,12). ATF7 proteins also strongly interact with 
the JNK2 protein kinase (13), although they do not 
constitute substrates for this kinase but rather serve as a 
JNK2-docking site for ATF7-associated partners like 
JunD, (11). Collectively, these data suggest that ATF7 
proteins play important functions early in cell signaling. 
The transcriptional activity of ATF7 is potentiated by 
the expression of TAF12, a subunit of TFIID, through 
direct interactions implicating the N-terminal domains of 
the two proteins, as well as the TAF12 histone fold 
domain (14). TAF4, the HFD-containing protein partner 
of TAF12 within TFIID also interacts with ATF7 and 
thereby competes for the coactivator effect of TAF12. 
Interestingly its paralog TAF4b, that plays a role in 
fertility does not (14,15). In fact, TAF4 has been shown to 
play a central role in multiple signaling pathways by 
competing with TAF4b (16) for the presence of various 
transcription factors, among these CREB, SP1, RAR and 
ATF7 (17). 
In the present study, we investigate the modification of 
ATF7 protein by SUMO-1. We demonstrate that ATF7 is 
sumoylated in human cells and that this modification 
delays its nuclear localization and therefore inhibits ATF7 
transcriptional activity by impairing its interaction with 
TAF12 in TFIID. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Expression vectors </p>

<p>The recombinant human ATF7 isoform used in the 
present study is ATF7-1 and will be referred as ATF7, 
with coordinates corresponding to the amino acid 
numbering of the largest protein (ATF7-3, 494 
residues) (14). 
The vectors pG4-ATF7-1 recombinant and correspond-
ing derivatives encode the DNA-binding domain of the 
yeast Gal4 protein fused to the wild type (wt) or mutated 
human ATF7-1 polypeptide, as described (10). The 
cDNAs of ATF7-1 and derivatives, and human ATF2, 
RanBP2iFG have also been inserted into the pXJ or 
pXJ-HA vectors, under the control of the CMV promoter 
(18), generating the px-ATF7 series and px-hsATF2, 
px-RanBP2iFG, respectively. 
The (17m5)-TK-Luc reporter (19) contains the lucifer-
ase gene, driven by the thymidine kinase promoter and five 
Gal4 binding sites (see Figure 5A). 
The pATF-GFP was constructed by cloning the 
sequence encoding the N-terminal portion of ATF7 
(amino acids 1-250) into an engineered XhoI site immedi-
ately 3 
0 to the start codon of GFP in pXRGG (20), 
a derivative of pGreenLantern (Life Technologies). This 
plasmid encodes a fusion protein containing the ATF7 
activation domain, followed by the hormone-response </p>

<p>element of the rat glucocorticoid receptor and by the 
GFP. pGST-RanBP2ÁFG was a gift of Anne Dejean. 
Point-mutations and deletions were created in the 
ATF7-1 moiety by oligonucleotide-directed mutagenesis 
using the Pfu-DNA polymerase (21), PCR-amplification 
of appropriate DNA fragments, or restriction fragment 
deletion. All constructions were verified by DNA 
sequencing. </p>

<p>Cells, transfection and extract preparation </p>

<p>HeLa-SUMO cells, a gift from P. O'Hare (22), were grown 
as monolayers in Dulbecco medium supplemented with 
glucose (1 g/l) and 10% fetal calf serum. Huvec-c cells 
were grown in Ham's F12K medium supplemented with 
2 mM L-glutamine, 0.1 mg/ml heparin, 0.05 mg/ml 
endothelial cell growth supplement (ECGS), and 10% 
FBS. Cells were transfected with recombinant plasmids, 
8 h after plating, using Transfectin reagent (Bio-Rad, 
USA), with the amounts of recombinant DNA indicated 
in the figure legends. After 36 h, cells were harvested in 
phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and resuspended in RIPA 
buffer (150 mM NaCl, 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.2, 0.1% 
SDS, 1% Triton X-100, 1% deoxycholate, 5 mM EDTA, 
0.4 mM PMSF, 2.5 ng/ml each of leupeptin, pepstatin, 
aprotinin, antipain and chymostatin). After 30 min on ice, 
the resulting crude suspension was cleared by centrifuga-
tion for 20 min at 10 000 g. 
Raji cells were grown in RPMI 1640 medium containing 
10% calf serum. Cos-1 cells, grown as monolayers in 
Dulbecco medium supplemented with glucose (1 g/l) and 
5% fetal calf serum, were transfected with recombinant 
plasmids, 8 h after plating, using ExGen 500 reagent 
(Euromedex, France) (23), with the amounts of recombi-
nant DNA indicated in the figure legends. After 48 h, cells 
were harvested in PBS and resuspended in lysis buffer 
(0.4 M KCl, 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 20% glycerol, 
5 mM dithiothreitol, 0.4 mM PMSF, 2.5 ng/ml each of 
leupeptin, pepstatin, aprotinin, antipain and chymosta-
tin). After one freeze-thawing cycle in liquid nitrogen, the 
resulting crude suspension was cleared by centrifugation 
for 20 min at 10 000 g (24). </p>

<p>Antibodies </p>

<p>Rabbit antisera against ATF7, and monoclonal antibodies 
specifically recognizing the ATF7 isoforms (2F10, 1A7, 
3C12), GFP (2A5) GST (1D10), FLAG (M2) and HA 
epitopes (12CA5) have been described (13,14). Rabbit 
antisera against RanBP2 (PA1-082) was purchased from 
Affinity BioReagen. Rabbit antisera against SUMO-1 was 
a gift from Dr Jacob Seeler (Institut Pasteur, Paris). 
The monoclonal antibody against Nuclear Pore Complex 
proteins (mAb414) was a kind gift from V. Doye (Institut 
Curie, Paris). </p>

<p>In vitro SUMO-1 conjugation </p>

<p>The SUMO-1 conjugation assay was previously 
described (25). Briefly, this assay was performed in a 
system containing an ATP-regenerating system 
(50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.6, 5 mM MgCl2, 10 mM </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 1135 </p>

<p>creatine phosphate, 3.5 units/ml creatine kinase, 0.6 units/ 
ml inorganic pyrophosphatase, 2 mM ATP). Twenty-
microliter reactions contained 100 ng of purified recombi-
nant hsSAE1/2 (E1), 400 ng of purified recombinant 
hsUbc9 (E2), 1 mg of purified recombinant human 
6His:Myc:SUMO-1(1-97) and either 100 ng purified 
recombinant protein substrate (ATF7) or 5 ml of in vitro 
transcription/translation-coupled reactions (ATF2) (10). 
Reactions were incubated at 378C for 1-2 h. </p>

<p>NiNTA-agarose affinity chromatography and 
immunoblotting </p>

<p>Aliquots of cell extracts were incubated (1 h at 48C) with 
50 ml of a NiNTA-agarose bead suspension (Qiagen) in 
PBS. The beads were washed three times with 1 ml of PBS, 
0.5% Nonidet P-40 and NaCl adjusted to 250 mM. The 
proteins were then dissociated by boiling for 5 min in 20 ml 
sample buffer, before SDS-10% polyacrylamide gel 
electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE). Protein analysis by western 
blotting was carried out as described (13). Briefly, proteins 
were electrotransferred onto nitrocellulose, reacted with 
specific primary antibodies (see above) and revealed with 
peroxidase-linked goat anti-mouse Kappa-light chain 
or goat anti-rabbit immunoglobulins (SantaCruz) 
as indicated, using the ECL system (Amersham). </p>

<p>Luciferase assay </p>

<p>Transfected cells were harvested in ice-cold PBS, pelleted, 
washed once in PBS and resuspended in lysis buffer 
(100 mM potassium phosphate, pH 7.8). After three 
freeze-thawing steps in liquid nitrogen, the resulting cell 
lysate was cleared by centrifugation. Aliquots of the 
extracts (normalized by protein concentration) were 
assayed for luciferase activity using a Berthold Centro 
LB 960 luminometer, as previously described (26,27). 
In all cases, at least five independent transfections 
were carried out and the results always agreed within 
10%. The results of typical experiments are shown in the 
figures. </p>

<p>Electrophoretic DNA-binding assay </p>

<p>Gel-retardation experiments were performed as previously 
described (28). Briefly, about 0.3 ng (5000 cpm) of a </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-5 
0 -end-labeled double-stranded oligonucleotide probe 
was incubated with the cell extract in the presence of poly 
(dI-dC), poly (dI-dC) as non-specific competitor and 1 mg 
of anti ATF7(3C12) monoclonal antibody when indicated. 
For competition experiments, the protein fractions were 
preincubated with 50 ng of unlabeled oligonucleotides 
before addition of the labeled probe. After 10 min at 258C, 
the complexes were separated by electrophoresis on a 
non-denaturing 4.5% polyacrylamide gel. </p>

<p>RNA expression analysis (RT-PCR) </p>

<p>Total RNA was extracted using TRIzol reagent. One 
microgram of purified total RNA was used for RT-PCR 
analysis using the Transcriptor First Strand CDNA 
Synthesis Kit (Roche Diagnostics GmbH). For PCR 
reaction, 25 cycles were performed (denaturation: 958C, </p>

<p>1 min; annealing: 608C, 2 min; polymerization: 688C, 
2 min). PCR products were separated onto agarose gels 
and DNA was visualized by ethidium bromide staining. 
Primers for E-selectin RNA amplification were designed 
according to the E-selectin mRNA sequence published 
[NCBI Nucleotide GenBank (accession number: NM-
000450) 5 
0 -primer: 5 
0 -TCTCTCAGCTCTCACTTTG-3 
0 , 
3 
0 -primer: 
5 
0 -TTCTTCTTGCTGCACCTCT-3 
0 ]. 
E-selectin PCR product is 383 bp in length. Primers for 
b-actin amplification (367 bp PCR product) were as 
follows: 5 
0 -primer: 5 
0 -CTCACCATGGATGATGATAT-
3 
0 and 3 
0 -primer: 5 
0 -TGGGTCATCTTCTCGCGGTT-3 
0 . </p>

<p>ChIP and quantitative real-time PCR </p>

<p>HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with either 
px-ATF7WT px-ATF7K118R or px-SUMO-GA-
ATF7K118R vectors. Forty-eight hours after transfection, 
ChIP assays were performed using a ChIP Assay Kit 
(Upstate Biotechnology, USA), following the manufac-
turer recommendations. 
Quantitative real-time PCR was performed on 
LightCycler (Roche Diagnostics, Switzerland), as specified 
by the manufacturer, using LightCycler FastStart DNA 
Master SYBR Green I reagents with 45 cycles of three-
step amplification. The 5 
0 to 3 
0 sequences of the primers 
used in the PCR were: Fwd: GTCATATTAATAAAATT 
GCATATACGATAT; Rev:TCTCAGGTGGGTATCAC 
TGCTGCCTCTGTC. After PCR, amplified DNA was 
collected and migrated on 1% agarose gels. </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence </p>

<p>Immunofluorescence staining experiments were carried 
out as previously described (29). Briefly, 48 h after 
transfection, HeLa-SUMO cells, grown on coverslips, 
were fixed with formaldehyde (4% [vol/vol] in PBS) and 
permeabilized with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS. The 
primary antibodies were diluted in PBS containing 0.1% 
Triton X-100. Antibodies were used at the following 
dilutions in PBS containing 0.1% Triton X-100: the anti-
ATF7 monoclonal (2F10 or 1A7) and polyclonal anti-
bodies were used both at 1/2000 dilution; the anti-RanBP2 
and NCP4 antibody were used at 1/1000 dilution. After 
incubation at 208C for 1 h, the coverslips were washed 
several times in PBS, 0.1% Triton X-100 and then 
incubated 1 h at 208C with donkey CY3-conjugated anti-
rabbit or anti-mouse IgG and/or donkey Alexa588-labeled 
anti-rabbit IgG (Sigma), at concentrations recommended 
by the suppliers. Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 
33258. After the staining, the coverslips were mounted and 
analyzed using a confocal laser-scanning microscope 
(Leica). Image-enhancement software was used to balance 
signal strength, and 8-fold scanning was used to separate 
signal from noise. </p>

<p>Time laps experiments </p>

<p>For monitoring the nuclear import of the ATF constructs, 
HeLa-SUMO cells were seeded on coverslips, grown for 
24 h, before mounting in a Life Imaging Services Ludin 
Chamber kept at 378C, 5% CO 2 , placed in a Leica 
DMIRE2 microscope equipped with a Life Imaging </p>



<p>Services temperature control system. The induction of 
nuclear importation was triggered by addition of 
dexamethasone (100 mM) to the cell-culture medium. 
Images were acquired every 25 s during 15 min, using a 
Leica DC350FX CCD camera piloted by the <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Leica</rs> 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">FW4000</rs> software. Eight fields (corresponding to a 
minimum of 60 cells) were recorded during each experi-
ment by the use of a Marzhauser automated stage piloted 
by the <rs type="software">FW4000</rs> software. To compare the intensity of 
the fluorescent signals in the cytoplasm and the nucleus, 
the sequences were loaded in the <rs type="software">Universal Imaging Metamorph</rs> software, and average signal intensity were 
recorded in regions selected in the perinuclear cytoplasm 
and inside the nucleus. Signal intensity values were 
transferred in <rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Microsoft</rs> <rs id="software-4" type="software">Excel</rs> where the cytoplasmic 
and nuclear signals were compared. The equilibration 
point refers to the time needed for each construct to reach 
a signal intensity superior in the nucleus than in the 
cytoplasmic perinuclear region. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>ATF7 Sumoylation </p>

<p>To identify polypeptides that are able to interact with 
the activation domain of ATF7 transcription factor, 
a two-hybrid screen in yeast was performed to a mouse 
cDNA fusion library, using the 60% N-terminal portion 
of ATF7 as a bait. In this screening only the N-terminal 
portion of ATF7 lacking the leucine-zipper (b-ZIP) was 
chosen to avoid potential interactions with other b-ZIP-
containing molecules. Among the selected clones, one 
corresponded to mBLM, a DNA helicase implied in the 
Bloom Syndrome disease (30), another one to mAM (29) 
a recently described protein shown to facilitate conversion 
from dimethyl to trimethyl lysine 9 of histone H3 by ESET 
and cause transcriptional repression (31). Interestingly, 
a third one corresponded to Ubc9, the SUMO 
E2-conjugating enzyme (32,33). In addition, protein 
sequence analysis revealed that ATF7 contains a potential 
sumoylation target site (I-K-X-E) matching the consensus 
sequence (Figure 1A) (1,34,35). To investigate whether 
ATF7 could be sumoylated, we first used an in vitro assay 
(Figure 1B). Purified bacterially expressed ATF7 proteins 
were incubated with a minimal SUMO-1 conjugation 
system composed of purified recombinant human E1 
(SAE1/2), E2 (Ubc9) enzymes and purified mature 
SUMO-1 (aa 1-97) (36,37). Immunoblot analysis revealed 
an additional band of slower mobility when the ATF7 
protein was the substrate (ATF7WT) but not when its 
sumoylation site was mutated (ATF7K118R). As a 
negative control, ATF2, a protein closely related to 
ATF7 that lacks the consensus sumoylation site 
(Figure 1A), was shown not to be sumoylated in this 
assay (Figure 1B). 
Detection of SUMO-1 conjugates in living cells is often 
difficult because only a small proportion of cellular 
SUMO-1 target proteins is modified at any given time. 
For this reason, SUMO conjugation is generally investi-
gated using cells overexpressing SUMO proteins. 
To verify SUMO-1 modification of ATF7 in a cellular </p>

<p>context, we thus transfected a human cell line 
(HeLa-SUMO) that constitutively expresses elevated 
levels of 6His:Myc:epitope-tagged human SUMO-1 
protein (22) with plasmids expressing either the 
ATF7WT or the K118R derivative (Figure 1C). 
Transfected cells were lysed in the presence of SDS and 
N-ethylmaleimide (NEM) to inhibit SUMO-specific 
proteases activity. Cellular extracts were passed over 
nickel-charged agarose resin (Ni-NTA agarose, Qiagen) 
to purify 6His:Myc:SUMO-1 conjugated proteins. 
Analysis of Ni-NTA bound fractions was first performed 
by immunoblotting using SUMO-1 specific antibodies 
(Figure 1C, left panel). Ladders of many SUMO 
conjugated proteins retained on the Ni-NTA beads 
could be observed, but interestingly a major band with 
an apparent molecular weight compatible with that of a 
mono-sumoylated form of ATF7 was detected only into 
the cells transfected with ATF7WT. The same blot was </p>

<p>ATF7-SUMO1 </p>

<p>ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>ATF7 WT </p>

<p>ATF7 
ATF2 </p>

<p>71 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>System </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>WB 
(anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>WB 
(anti-SUMO1) </p>

<p>WB 
(anti-ATF7) 
(anti-SUMO1) </p>

<p>WB </p>

<p>ATF7-SUMO1 
ATF7 </p>

<p>ATF7-SUMO1 </p>

<p>WT 
K118R </p>

<p>Consensus 
ATF2 </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>I E 
E E </p>

<p>A 
F K </p>

<p>S K 104 
I K 118 </p>

<p>X E </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>C 
WT 
K118R 
D 
IP-antiATF7 </p>

<p>Ni-NTA </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>− 
− 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ 
− 
− 
− 
+ </p>

<p>ATF2 WT 
System </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
− 
+ 
+ 
− </p>

<p>1 
2 3 
4 
5 
6 </p>

<p>Figure 1. SUMO-1 modification of recombinant ATF proteins. Peptide 
sequence alignments between ATF7 and ATF2. (A) Amino acid 
sequences (one-letter code) of relevant portions of the proteins are 
given, below the consensus sumoylation target site (È, hydrophobic 
residues; X, any residue). Bold-faced characters represent potential 
sumoylation sites, with respective coordinates. (B) Purified bacterially 
expressed ATF7 WT (lanes 3 and 4), ATF7 K118R (lanes 1 and 2) 
and in vitro synthesized 
35 S-labeled ATF2 (lanes 5 and 6) were 
subjected to in vitro SUMO-1 conjugation, as indicated (System 
refers to the complete assay reaction as described in Materials and 
Methods-AU refers to arbitrary unit). Reaction products were 
analyzed by SDS-PAGE, followed by immunoblotting using ATF7 
(2F10) monoclonal-antibodies (lanes 1-4) or autoradiography (lanes 5 
and 6). (C) HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with 0.5 mg px-
ATF7WT or pXATFK118R. Extracts (500 mg) from transfected cells 
were passed through Ni-NTA agarose (affinity-purification). Proteins 
were separated by SDS-PAGE and the presence of sumoylated ATF7, 
and then ATF7 was revealed by western blotting (WB) using specific 
antibodies, as indicated. (D) Extracts (500 mg) from Raji cells were 
immunoprecipitated with the anti-ATF7 (2F10) antibodies. Proteins 
were separated by SDS-PAGE and the presence of ATF7, and then 
sumoylated ATF7 was revealed by western blotting (WB) using specific 
antibodies, as indicated. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 1137 </p>

<p>then probed with ATF7-specific antibodies to confirm in 
both cell-extracts the presence of similar amounts of 
non-modified ATF proteins that also bind to the resin 
through their zinc-binding domain (Figure 1C, right 
panel). Together these results clearly demonstrate that 
the mutation K118R impairs the symoylation of ATF7. 
To demonstrate that the endogenous ATF7 proteins are 
covalently modified by SUMO in vivo, we used Raji cells, 
a human lymphoid cell line in which ATF7 is naturally 
more abundant than in other cell lines (14). Cells were 
lysed in the presence of SDS and N-ethylmaleimide 
(NEM) to inhibit SUMO-specific proteases activity. 
The cellular extracts were immunoprecipitated using 
monoclonal anti-ATF7 antibodies and analyzed by 
western blotting using first ATF7 antibodies (Figure 1D, 
left panel). A major band corresponding to ATF7 was 
observed. Interestingly, a minor band with an apparent 
molecular weight compatible with that of a mono-
sumoylated form of ATF7 was also detected. To assess 
the specificity of this band, the same blot was then probed 
with anti SUMO-1 polyclonal antibodies. As shown 
in Figure 1D (right panel), the SUMO-1 antibodies 
specifically recognized the upper band. Thus the endo-
genous ATF7 proteins are subjected to modification by 
SUMO-1 in vivo. </p>

<p>SUMO-1 modification affects ATF7 intracellular 
localization </p>

<p>Previous studies had correlated SUMO modification 
with the recruitment of target proteins to specialized 
subnuclear domains, (1-3,34,35,38). To address this issue, 
we transiently expressed ATF7WT and ATF7K118R 
mutant into HeLa-SUMO cells and followed their 
intracellular localization by fluorescence microscopy. 
Immunostaining of transfected cells with anti-ATF7 
antibody revealed two patterns of localizations: 90% of 
the transfected cells mainly showed a nuclear localization 
for ATF7WT, with a diffuse distribution excluding the 
nucleoli (Figure 2A) while 10% of the transfected cells 
showed a distinct pattern restricted to the periphery of the 
nucleus (Figure 2B). On the other hand, expression of 
ATF7K118R proteins that cannot be sumoylated showed 
exclusively the nucleoplasmic localization pattern 
(Figure 2C). These results suggest that sumoylation may 
trap the protein at the vinicity of the nuclear envelope. 
In order to check this hypothesis, we engineered a 
constitutively sumoylated form of ATF7 by covalently 
attaching SUMO-1 to ATF7 by gene fusion as previously 
described for Sp3 or TAF5 (25,39). We therefore 
generated a ATFK118R derivative composed of the 
protein SUMO-1 (amino acids 1-96) directly fused 
N-terminus of ATF7. The C-terminal Gly of full-length 
SUMO-1 was replaced by an Ala in order to prevent 
cleavage of the fusion proteins by C-terminal SUMO 
hydrolases (39). As shown in Figure 2D and E, 20% of 
the cells transfected with this construct displayed an 
immunofluorescence staining localized at the periphery of 
the nucleus. This represents a 2-fold increase compared 
to the number observed with wild-type ATF7. 
The observation that not all the cells showed such a </p>

<p>perinuclear localization pattern suggests that sumoylation 
may only transiently block the protein at this level. </p>

<p>RanBP2 functions as a SUMO E3 ligase for ATF7 </p>

<p>The observed perinuclear localization of the sumoylated 
form of ATF7 proteins strongly suggests that the 
corresponding modification process may occur during 
their entry into the nucleus. Since it has been shown 
that the nuclear pore complex (NPC) RanBP2 protein 
strongly enhances SUMO-1 modification of the nuclear 
body-associated SP100 protein (40) and HDAC4 deace-
tylase (41), we tested whether this protein could function 
as a SUMO E3 ligase for ATF7. To verify this hypothesis, 
our reconstituted in vitro modification assay (see Figure 1) 
was performed with recombinant ATF7 in the presence 
or absence of a bacterially produced RanBP2 fusion 
protein (GST-RanBP2iFG). This truncated protein was 
previously described to exhibit an E3 ligase activity (40). 
As shown in Figure 3A, although the sumoylation of 
ATF7 occurred to some extent in the absence of SUMO 
ligase (lane 3), the reaction was strongly stimulated by 
addition of the RanBP2 derivative (lane 5). To confirm the </p>

<p>ATF7WT </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Anti-ATF7 
DNA 
Merge </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-
ATF7K118R </p>

<p>ATF7K118R 
100% </p>

<p>80% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>Figure 2. Localization of ATF7 is regulated by SUMO-1. 
HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with plasmids encoding wild-type 
ATF7 (WT, rows A and B) or mutated ATF7 (K118R, row C; SUMO-
GA-ATF7 K118R, rows D and E), as indicated. At 36 h post-
transfection, cells were processed for immunostaining with monoclonal 
anti-ATF7 antibodies (2F10) and donkey Cy3-labeled anti-mouse IgG. 
Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33258. Bar, 10 nm. </p>



<p>specificity of the assay, we used GST-PIAS1 instead of 
RanBP2 in a similar in vitro modification experiment. 
PIAS1 also exhibits E3 ligase activity but directed towards 
different transcription factors, like c-jun or p53 (42,43). </p>

<p>Whereas sumoylation of ATF7 was greatly enhanced by 
RanBP2, PIAS1 failed to catalyze SUMO modification of 
ATF7 in a parallel reaction (data not shown). These 
observations support the conclusion that RanBP2 func-
tions as a specific SUMO E3 ligase towards ATF7. 
We next analyzed the ability of the fusion SUMO-GA-
ATF7 and RanBP2 proteins to interact within a 
cellular context. To that end, HeLa-SUMO cells were 
transfected with plasmids expressing either px-ATF7WT, 
px-ATF7K118R, px-SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R and px-
HA-RanBP2ÁFG (Figure 3B). Whole cell extracts were 
then submitted to immunoprecipitation (IP) with anti-
bodies against ATF7 and the precipitated proteins were 
analyzed by western blotting using anti-HA antibodies. 
As shown in Figure 3B, RanBP2 was detected in the 
immunoprecipitates only when coexpressed with the 
constitutively sumoylated ATF7 construct, but not in 
the presence of ATF7WT or ATF7K118R. Therefore, 
these results strongly suggest that sumoylation promotes 
the interaction between ATF7 and RanBP2, supporting 
the idea that RanBP2 is the ATF7 specific E3 ligase. 
The fact that no interaction could be detected between 
ATF7WT and RanBP2 can be explained by a very 
low amount of the sumoylated ATF7WT protein in 
HeLa-SUMO-transfected cells. 
In order to refine the location of sumoylated ATF7 
within the nucleus of transfected cells, we performed 
co-localization experiments using antibodies against 
nuclear pore complex proteins (anti-NPC) and ATF7 
(Figure 3C). 
As expected, the anti-NPC antibodies primarily stained 
the nuclear membrane. While the non-sumoylatable ATF7 
derivative (ATF7K118R) was clearly nucleoplasmic 
(row b), the ATF7 WT (row a) and its constitutively 
sumoylated derivative (SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R; row c) 
were confined to the nuclear periphery, within up to 20% 
of the transfected cells, in agreement with the results 
shown in Figure 2. Furthermore, as revealed by the double 
immunostaining, these ATF7 proteins clearly accumulate 
in close proximity to the nuclear membrane, in a region 
documented to be transcriptionally inactive (4). </p>

<p>Sumoylation delays the entry into the nucleus </p>

<p>The results of our immunofluorescence experiments 
suggest that the entry of ATF7 into the nuclei is a 
dynamic phenomenon which may be modulated by 
sumoylation. In order to visualize ATF7 diffusion into 
the nucleoplasm more precisely, time laps microscopy 
experiments using GFP-tagged constructs were per-
formed. We used hormone-inducible GFP-tagged 
chimeric ATF7 protein (ATF7-GR-GFP) (Figure 4A) 
to study the ATF7 nuclear import in living cells. The first 
250 amino acid residues of ATF7 (to delete the ATF7 
endogenous NLS sequence) were fused to the hormone-
responsive element from the glucocorticoid receptor-GFP 
(GFP-GR) chimera. 
To assess the effect of sumoylation, the import of 
ATF7WT, ATFK118R and SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R 
GR-GFP derivatives was examined in HeLa-SUMO cells 
(Figure 4B). In the absence of steroid, the chimeric </p>

<p>System (AU) 
ATF7 (50 ng) </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>ATF7 -SUMO1 </p>

<p>20 
20 
1 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>1 
+ 
-
-</p>

<p>0 
-
+ 
GST-RanBP2FG (50 ng) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Anti -NPC 
Anti -ATF7 
DNA 
Merge </p>

<p>ATF7 WT </p>

<p>ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R 
WB 
(anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>IP (anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>Extracts </p>

<p>WB 
(anti-HA) 
HARanBP2 </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>HARanBP2 </p>

<p>px-ATF7 WT 
px-ATF7 K118R 
px-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>px-HARanBP2 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 </p>

<p>1 2 
3 4 5 6 </p>

<p>Figure 3. Nuclear-membrane markers co-localize with ATF7. 
(A) Purified bacterially expressed ATF7WT was subjected to in vitro 
SUMO-1 conjugation, in the presence or in the absence of purified 
bacterially expressed GST-RanBP2. Reactions in lanes 4-5 were 
performed with 20-fold less in vitro sumoylation reaction mix 
(System) than in lanes 1-3. Reaction products were analyzed by 
SDS-PAGE and by immunoblotting using ATF7 antibodies. (B) HeLa-
SUMO cells were transfected with 0.5 mg px-ATF7 derivatives and 
px-HA-RanBP2iFG as indicated. Extracts from transfected cells were 
immunoprecipitated (IP) with the anti-ATF7 (2F10) monoclonal 
antibodies as described in Materials and Methods. The purified 
complexes were separated by SDS-PAGE. The presence of 
HA-RanBP2iFG proteins in both IP and extracts, and ATF7 
derivatives in the extracts was revealed by western blotting (WB) 
using specific antibodies. (C) HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected 
with plasmids encoding mutated ATF7WT (a), ATF7 K118R (b) 
or SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R (c), as indicated. At 36 h post-
transfection, cells were processed for immunostaining with monoclonal 
anti-ATF7 antibodies (2F10) and donkey Alexa488-labeled anti-
mouse IgG or rabbit polyclonal anti-NPC and donkey Cy3-labeled 
anti-rabbit IgG. Nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33258. 
Bar: 10 nm. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 1139 </p>

<p>proteins were all localized in the cytoplasm and transloca-
tion of the three variants into the nucleus was observed 
only after the addition of dexamethasone (Figure 4B). 
For each construct, we measured the mean time required 
to reach a nuclear signal of same intensity as the one 
observed in the cytoplasmic perinuclear region. Clearly, 
constitutively sumoylated ATF requires twice as much 
time as the other proteins to equilibrate the nuclear signal 
to the level of the cytoplasm. This indicates that 
sumoylation specifically delays the import of the ATF7 
protein into the nucleus. </p>

<p>Sumoylation of ATF7 interferes with its transcriptional 
activity </p>

<p>To get an insight of the effect of sumoylation on the 
transcriptional activation mediated by ATF7, we analyzed 
the effect of K118R mutation specifically impairing 
the sumoylation of ATF7 on its transcriptional activity. 
We investigated the interplay of this modification using 
the Gal4 protein fusion system (44), in which the ATF7 
protein is linked to the yeast Gal4 DNA binding domain 
(1-147). The activity of the chimeric products was 
assayed in cotransfection experiments with a luciferase 
reporter gene whose promoter contained five Gal4 binding 
sites (44). Cos-1 cells were transfected with the pG4-ATF7 
vector or derivatives and the luciferase reporter. 
The results of a typical experiment are shown in 
Figure 5A. The K118R mutant stimulated transcription 
of the reporter gene 2-fold more than the WT protein. </p>

<p>In contrast, the Gal4-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R construc-
tion was about 4-fold less active than the WT protein 
while equal levels of Gal-ATF7 fusions were expressed 
and showed identical cellular distribution as the non-fused 
proteins. These results indicate that a large part of the WT 
protein activity is due to its non-sumoylated form. 
Identical results were obtained with the three ATF7 
isomers (9), namely ATF7-1, ATF7-2 and ATF7-3 (not 
shown). Thus sumoylation plays a negative role in the 
ATF7-induced transactivation process under these experi-
mental conditions, possibly by sequestering the proteins in 
the periphery of the nucleus. 
We previously showed that the transcriptional activity 
of ATF7 is potentiated by expression of TAF12 and 
that the two proteins are interacting in vivo (14). We 
investigated the ability of the fusion SUMO-GA-ATF7 
and TAF12 proteins to interact within a cellular 
context. To that end, HeLa-SUMO cells were trans-
fected with plasmids expressing p-hsTAF12 together 
with px-ATF7, px-ATF7K118R and px-SUMO-GA-
ATF7K118R (Figure 5B). Whole cell extracts were then 
submitted to immunoprecipitation (IP) with antibodies 
against ATF7, and the precipitated proteins were analyzed 
by western blotting using anti-TAF12 antibodies. As 
shown in Figure 5B (lanes 1-4), TAF12 was detected in 
the immunoprecipitates only when coexpressed with 
ATF7WT or ATF7K118R, but not when coexpressed 
with the constitutively sumoylated ATF7 construct. 
In HeLa-SUMO transfected cells, the majority of the 
overexpressed ATF7WT protein is not sumoylated. 
Therefore, these results strongly suggest that sumoylation 
may prevent the interaction between ATF7 and TAF12, 
and this loss of interaction would thus account for the 
transcriptional inhibitory effect of ATF7 sumoylation. To 
gain some insight into the molecular mechanism of this 
differential action on transcription, we first performed a 
chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP) experiment on the 
E-selectin gene. ATF7 has previously been shown to 
specifically bind to the NF-ELAM1 promoter element of 
the E-selectin gene and to interact with TAF12 (14). 
HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with vectors expres-
sing either ATF7WT, K118R ATF7, or SUMO-GA-
ATF7K118R under conditions where equal levels of 
proteins were expressed, as verified by immunoblotting 
with specific antibodies (Figure 6A). We also checked by 
gel-shift assays that the three proteins were able to bind 
the NF-ELAM1 promoter element with very similar 
efficiencies (Figure 6B). As shown in Figure 6A, the 
E-selectin promoter was immunoprecipitated more effi-
cently in ATF7K118R expressing cells than in ATF7WT 
or SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R transfected cells. These 
results clearly indicate that, in the context of a natural 
promoter (and in a steady-state level), non-sumoylated 
ATF7 form is more strongly associated with the chroma-
tin. Therefore sumoylation prevents the association of 
ATF7 with the target promoter or facilitates its removal 
in vivo. In addition, a direct measurement of transcription 
was performed to analyze the changes in an ATF7 
target gene expression upon the changes in ATF7 
sumoylation. RT-PCR analysis clearly shows that 
transcription of the E-selectin gene is enhanced in the </p>

<p>GR 
GFP </p>

<p>GR 
GFP </p>

<p>GR 
GFP 
ATF7-1 
ATF7-GFP </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R-GFP </p>

<p>1 
250 </p>

<p>SUMO-1 </p>

<p>95 
1 
1 </p>

<p>K118R </p>

<p>-G-A-</p>

<p>ATF7 K118R-GFP </p>

<p>600 
400 
200 
0 
500 s 
200 s 
0 s </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Mean cytoplasm /nucleus equilibration 
time (s) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R-GFP </p>

<p>WB (anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>Extracts </p>

<p>ATF7-GFP/ATF7K118R-GFP </p>

<p>Figure 4. Sumoylation delays protein entry into the nucleus. 
(A) The structures of the different ATF7 constructs are schematized. 
(B) Time laps microscopy monitoring of cells expressing GFP 
fused constructs ATF7WT, ATF7K118R or SUMO-GA-ATF7. 
HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with 0.25 mg of the different 
plasmids as indicated. Twenty-four hours later 10 nM Dexamethasone 
was added to the culture medium (t ¼ 0). The level of fluorescence in 
the nucleus was monitored using time laps microscopy. Bar: 20 nm. 
Quantification of the mean time required to reach a nuclear signal of 
same intensity as the one measured in the cytoplasm perinuclear region 
(cytoplasm/nuclear equilibration). Constitutively sumoylated ATF 
requires twice as much time as the other constructs to equilibrate the 
nuclear signal to the level of the cytoplasm. </p>



<p>presence of ATF7K118R (Figure 6C) whereas the expres-
sion level of the control gene (b-actin) is unaffected. 
Altogether, these observations clearly confirm the inhibi-
tory effect of sumoylation of ATF7 on the transactivation 
process: sumoylation not only impairs the interaction 
between ATF7 and TAF12 but blocks the access of ATF7 
to promoters. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Small ubiquitin-like modifier (SUMO) modification has 
emerged as an important regulator of diverse pathways 
and activities including protein targeting, transcriptional 
regulation, modulation of enzyme activity and protein </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R 
WB 
(anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>IP (anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>Extracts </p>

<p>WB 
(anti-TAF12) 
hsTAF12 </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>hsTAF12 </p>

<p>px-hsTAF12 </p>

<p>px-ATF7 WT </p>

<p>px </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>px-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>px-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Gal4-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>WB (anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>Extracts </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7WT </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7 WT </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Gal4-SUMO-GA-
ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>ATF7-1 </p>

<p>Activators </p>

<p>pG4-ATF7 </p>

<p>pG4-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Reporter 
2 
494 </p>

<p>SUMO-1 </p>

<p>Gal4(1-147) </p>

<p>95 
1 
2 
494 </p>

<p>Relative Luciferase activity </p>

<p>-G-A-</p>

<p>Gal4(1-147) </p>

<p>pG4-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Luciferase </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>+TBPspm3 
+TAF12 </p>

<p>0 
100 
200 </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7 WT </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Gal4-SUMO-GA-
ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Gal4-ATF7118R </p>

<p>90% </p>

<p>10% </p>

<p>100% </p>

<p>20% </p>

<p>Gal4(1-147) 
17m5TGTA </p>

<p>Figure 5. Sumoylation affects ATF7 transcriptional activity. (A) HeLa-SUMO cells were co-transfected with 0.25 mg of the pG4-ATF7 expression 
vectors, 2 mg of the luciferase reporter, 0.25 mg of the TBP-spm3 and 0.25 mg of p-hsTAF12 expression vectors. The structures of the pG4-ATF7 
activator and the luciferase reporter plasmids are schematized. The results of luciferase assays are presented (arbitrary units). (B) HeLa-SUMO cells 
were transfected with 0.5 mg px-ATF7 derivatives and hsTAF12. Extracts from transfected cells were immunoprecipitated (IP) with the anti-ATF7 
(2F10) monoclonal antibody as described in Materials and Methods. The purified complexes were separated by SDS-PAGE. The presence of 
hsTAF12 proteins in both IP and extracts, and ATF7 derivatives in the extracts was revealed by western blotting (WB) using specific antibodies. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 1141 </p>

<p>turnover (for reviews, see References (1,3,35)). In the 
present article, we demonstrate that the ATF7 transcrip-
tion factor is sumoylated in vitro and in vivo, and that 
sumoylation affects its intranuclear localization and its 
transcriptional activity by impairing the interaction 
between ATF7 and TAF12, thereby blocking the access 
of ATF7 to its specific promoters. </p>

<p>ATF7, but not ATF2, is sumoylated </p>

<p>Since their discovery, ATF7 and ATF2 although encoded 
by distinct genes (9,45) have always been described as two 
closely related proteins, with very similar properties (7,46). 
For example, the two proteins mediate transactivation by 
the adenovirus oncoprotein E1a (8,47) and heterodimerize 
with Jun or Fos proteins (10). They are also phoshorylated 
by p38 and JNK MAP-kinases (11,48,49) and their </p>

<p>transcriptional activity is mediated by TAF12 (14). 
By contrast, a survey of the protein sequences derived 
from all sequenced eukaryotic genomes clearly reveals a 
consensus sumoylation site (fKXE) within all known 
ATF7 protein sequences, whereas it is absent in all ATF2 
proteins. We clearly show here that ATF7, but not ATF2, 
is sumoylated in vivo at the lysine residue (K118) 
belonging to this element. Though this sequence is located 
in the previously described transactivating domain, it is 
the first time that such a striking difference is observed 
between the activity of the two proteins. This indicates 
that, notwithstanding their high functional and structural 
homologies, these two ATF proteins likely play distinct 
roles in the cell. 
It has been suggested that SUMO modification could 
affect the subcellular localization of proteins (3). As shown 
for many nuclear proteins, sumoylation can direct some 
transcription factors to the so-called PML nuclear 
bodies (50), thus sequestering them away from the DNA 
and taking them out of action (50-52). Furthermore, 
sumoylation can also be coupled with the transport of 
proteins between the cytoplasm and the nucleus (53,54). 
As revealed by our localization studies, the wild-type 
ATF7 (ATF7WT) is dispersed throughout the nucleo-
plasm in the majority of the cells (about 90%), while it is 
restricted to a perinuclear distribution in approximately 
10% of the cells. The fact that a non-sumoylatable mutant 
protein (ATF7K118R) never accumulates at the nuclear 
periphery, strongly suggests that the nucleoplasmic ATF7 
corresponds to the non-sumoylated fraction of the 
protein. On the other hand, the in vivo perinuclear 
localization is in good agreement with the fact that the 
ATF7 sumoylation process requires (i) Ubc9, a conjugat-
ing enzyme which is associated to both cytoplasmic and 
nucleoplasmic fibrils of the nuclear pore complex (NPC) 
in vivo (55), and (ii) the E3 ligase RanBP2, a protein 
also belonging to the NPC (40). Thus, it appears that 
the ATF7 localization is affected by sumoylation, as 
previously reported for other transcription factors, 
like Sp3 (39), CtBP (56), Elk-1 (57) or SATB2 (58). 
In the latter case, a very similar correlation between 
sumoylation and subnuclear localization has also 
been observed: sumoylated SATB2 was predominantly 
localized at the nuclear periphery, whereas a sumoylation-
deficient SATB2 protein had a more diffuse nuclear 
localization (58). 
Our results clearly indicate that sumoylation does not 
block the nuclear entry of ATF7 since a constitutively 
sumoylated ATF7 derivative (SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R) 
exhibits a distribution pattern similar to the WT protein, 
as revealed by classical immunofluorescence microscopy 
experiments based on snapshot pictures of fixed cells. 
Time laps microscopy further extended our views. Indeed, 
the stably sumoylated protein takes twice as long as the 
non-sumoylated form (ATF7K118R) to enter the nucleus 
and evenly to redistribute over the nucleoplasm. These 
kinetic experiments strongly suggest that ATF7 sumoyla-
tion is a dynamic process that affects its in vivo localization 
behavior. Thus an equilibrium between the relative 
amounts of sumoylated and non-sumoylated forms of 
the protein might exist in the cell. </p>

<p>px-ATF7 WT </p>

<p>IP </p>

<p>px </p>

<p>Input </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 </p>

<p>209 bp </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>px-ATF7 K118R 
px-SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>Anti-ATF7 </p>

<p>ATF7 WT/K118R </p>

<p>IP + WB 
(anti-ATF7) </p>

<p>Anti-GFP </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 12 </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>Anti-ATF7 
Competitor wt 
mt 
+ </p>

<p>− 
Extract </p>

<p>Probe 
E-selectin 
B </p>

<p>ATF7 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R ATF7 K118R </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>C 
p X 
px-ATF7WT 
px-ATF7K118R 
px-SMO-GA-ATFK118R 
E-selectin 
β-actin </p>

<p>Figure 6. Sumoylation affects ATF7 activity. (A) ChIP analysis of 
genomic E-selectin promoter: HeLa-SUMO cells were transfected with 
px-ATF7WT(lanes 1,3) or px-ATF7K118R (lanes 2,4). Two days later, 
cells were subjected to ChIP assay with antibodies against ATF7 
(lanes 1 and 2) or Flag (lanes 3 and 4). Endogenous E-selectin 
promoter DNA, coprecipitated with the indicated antibodies, was 
detected by PCR. (B) Recombinant pSG5-based vectors (0.5 mg) 
directing the expression of the various chimeras were transfected into 
HeLa-SUMO cells, and cell lysates were analyzed by EMSA: 20 mg of 
extracts were preincubated with either 50 ng of non-specific (mt) or 
specific (wt) competitor before addition of E-selectin CRE probe. 
Where indicated, reactions were further incubated (30 min, 08C) with 
the anti-ATF7 antibody before loading on the gel. The black 
arrowhead points to the specific complex and the white one to the 
supershifted one. (C) Recombinant pX-based vectors (0.5 mg) directing 
the expression of the various chimeras were transfected into HUVEC-
C-cells. Two days later, RNA was isolated and E-selectin mRNA 
expression was analyzed by semi-quantitative RT-PCR method using 
b-actin as internal control. Ethidium bromide-stained gel is shown in 
the figure. </p>



<p>Sumoylation affects ATF7 transcriptional activity </p>

<p>Besides its contribution to the subcellular localization of 
ATF7, a functional role for the sumoylation was inferred 
from the analysis of the SUMO-deficient mutant protein 
(ATF7K118R). First, chromatin immunoprecipitation 
experiments revealed that the SUMO-deficient mutant 
ATF7 derivative associates more efficiently than 
ATF7WT with the CRE promoter element of the 
endogenous E-selectin gene. Second, SUMO-deficient 
ATF7 stimulated expression from a cotransfected reporter 
plasmid more efficiently than ATF7WT. By contrast, 
fusion of SUMO to the K118R mutant of ATF7 (as in 
SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R) resulted in a decrease of its 
transcriptional activation potential, an observation most 
likely related to the negative effect of SUMO on the ability 
of ATF7 to interact with its TAF12 partner. As previously 
shown, TAF12 potentiates ATF7-induced transcriptional 
activation through direct interaction with the N-terminal 
ATF7 transactivation domain (14). It appears therefore 
that the SUMO modification clearly contributes to the 
regulation of the ATF7 transcriptional activity by 
impairing the interaction between ATF7 and TAF12. 
Interestingly, both TAF5 and TAF12-TFIID subunits-
have been shown to be sumoylated (25). However, only 
SUMO conjugation of TAF5 interferes with binding of 
TFIID to promoter DNA, whereas modification of 
TAF12 has no detectable effect in this respect. 
Furthermore, SUMO conjugation has also no detectable 
effect on nuclear import or intranuclear distribution of 
these two TAFs. Clearly sumoylation may differentially 
affect proteins involved in a same function, i.e. transacti-
vation of target genes. It is difficult to directly correlate the 
functional differences observed between native ATF7WT 
and its non-sumoylatable counterpart (ATF7K118R), 
in terms of transcriptional activity or occupation of its 
target promoters, with their actual respective sumoylation 
levels. Indeed, the action of endogenous SUMO proteases 
(Senp1 and/or 2), released into the cell extracts, likely 
alters the apparent proportion of sumoylated proteins. 
This is best illustrated in Figure 5, where ATF7WT and 
ATF7K118R exhibit significantly different transcriptional 
and promoter binding activities (panels A and D), while 
showing equally low levels of sumoylation, compared to 
the Senp-resistant SUMO-GA-ATF7K118R derivative 
(panel B). A model has recently been proposed (4), 
in which the pool of sumoylated transcription factors 
constitutes a built-in portion of more general transcrip-
tional repression complexes. Within these structures, 
factors could be desumoylated while remaining associated 
with the complex of repression, independent of SUMO. 
Thus, SUMO would be required to initiate but not to 
maintain repression (4). However, upon sustained 
desumoylation, the overall number of repression com-
plexes might ultimately decrease. Such a scenario has 
been described in the case of the Elk-1 transcription 
factor whose phosphorylation by MAP-kinases is con-
comitant with its desumoylation and the activation of 
transcription (59). The fact that transcriptional activity of 
ATF7 is enhanced when the p38 MAP-kinase pathway is 
stimulated supports this model. Consequently, it would be </p>

<p>advisable to check the relationships between phosphoryla-
tion and sumo/desumoylation of ATF7. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank P. O'Hare, D. Bailey, V. Doye, J.L. Bocco, 
B. Wasylyk, A. Werner, J. Seeler, M.Donzeau and J. De 
Mey for gifts and helpful discussions. 
This work was supported by funds and/or fellowships 
from the Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique, the 
Universite´Louis Pasteur de Strasbourg, the French 
Ministry of Research, the Institut National de la Santeé 
t de la Recherche Me´dicale, the Association pour la 
Recherche sur le Cancer (contract 3712) and the Ligue 
Nationale contre le Cancer-Comite´s Alsace (Haut-Rhin 
et Bas-Rhin) et Vosges. Funding to pay the Open Access 
publication charge was provided by the Association pour 
la Recherche sur le Cancer. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 4 1143 </p>





</text></tei>