<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC1747177" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:17+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>RNA interference (RNAi) has opened new avenues for the 
systematic analysis of phenotypes. With the completion of 
many whole genome sequences, RNAi allows the depletion 
of gene products in a wide range of organisms, thus enabling 
reverse genetic approaches where genetic tools are lacking. 
The molecular mechanism of RNAi-mediated gene silencing 
is conserved from plants to higher animals and studies in 
many organisms have benefited tremendously from the </p>

<p>availability of RNAi libraries. Compared to classical genetic 
screens, RNAi has the advantage to provide a link from 
phenotype to gene without the need for positional cloning 
of mutant alleles, but it lacks the possibility to make stable 
mutations and may display non-specific off-target effects. 
Depending on the experimental system, RNAi approaches 
are amenable for high-throughput screening, thereby allowing 
complete genomes to be queried for specific phenotypes. 
Screens can be performed for whole organism phenotypes, 
which has been done in Caenorhabditis elegans (1,2). Cell-
based RNAi experiments have become widely used in par-
ticular in Drosophila and to a smaller extent in vertebrates, 
organisms for which many cell lines are available (3-6). 
Cell-based phenotypes can be measured using simple fluores-
cent or luminescence reporters or more complex phenotypes 
as can be detected by immunofluorescence and microscopy 
(7). However each phenotypic readout method has its specific 
analysis method and a generally accepted ontology for 
phenotypes is still missing. 
In the past few years different RNAi libraries have been 
constructed that cover large parts of many genomes. For 
invertebrates, such as C.elegans and Drosophila, libraries 
can be produced relatively cheaply, since long double-
stranded RNAs (dsRNAs) can be generated by in vitro trans-
cription. In addition, use of dsRNA in these organisms does 
not elicit an interferon response (8,9). Expression of 
dsRNA in bacteria that are fed to C.elegans is sufficient to 
produce an efficient knock-down of target transcripts (9). In 
Drosophila cells, simple addition of long dsRNA to the cell 
culture medium is sufficient for cells to take up the dsRNAs 
and intracellularly dice them in many different 21-23 bp 
siRNAs (8). The efficiency of RNAi in invertebrates is likely 
due to the diversity of siRNA species that are intracellularly 
produced. 
Drosophila cell-based assays are widely used since the 
genome is well-annotated and many cellular pathways are 
conserved from flies to man (10,11). Moreover, Drosophila 
lacks a redundancy of factors often found in mammalian 
genomes. For example, depleting Dsh by RNAi is sufficient 
to fully recapitulate a Wg loss-of-function phenotype, 
whereas it is necessary to deplete all three homologs 
(Dvl1-3) in human cells to observe a Wnt phenotype 
(D. Ingelfinger and M. Boutros, unpublished data). Such </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be adddressed. Tel: +49 6221 421951; Fax: +49 6221 421959; Email: m.boutros@dkfz.de </p>

<p>Ó 2006 The Author(s). 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>D492-D497 Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Database issue 
Published online 28 November 2006 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkl906 </p>

<p>examples occur in many cellular pathways and it might be 
necessary in mammalian cells to pool RNAi reagents for mul-
tiple candidates to generate a loss-of-function phenotype. 
While this is technically possible, it will significantly increase 
the complexity of screens. 
More than 20 genome-wide (or genome-scale) screens in 
Drosophila cells have been published since 2003 and a key 
challenge remains to integrate and compare different datasets. 
Since many screens have been performed using different 
RNAi libraries and readouts, a proper annotation using 
minimal information for RNAi experiments would be req-
uired. The equivalent of a MIAME convention is currently 
lacking and the breadth and quality of data provided for 
screens varies. Data structures and databases will be needed 
to cross-correlate phenotypic information. 
As large-scale studies remain largely untested in follow-up 
experiments for a certain period of time, it is crucial to 
systematically integrate phenotypes and annotation informa-
tion to estimate false positive and false negative rates. A com-
parison across multiple screens can also be used to evaluate 
the reliability of a phenotype or a particular RNAi reagent 
used in these studies. Ultimately, phenotypic profiles of 
many screens can serve to cluster unknown genes and provide 
guideposts for follow-up analysis (12). Since most cell-based 
RNAi screens have been published using Drosophila RNAi 
libraries, these screens can serve as a model for the organi-
zation of data produced in large-scale RNAi experiments. 
Here we describe a publicly accessible database to inte-
grate annotation of RNAi reagents and functional information 
obtained from large-scale RNAi experiments. The database 
allows the user to access phenotype data from published 
screens and the sequences of their underlying perturbation 
reagents. Specificity and other sequence features are display-
ed in the context of the genomic location of the targeted 
gene model. <rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> also facilitates the design of 
new experiments, using previously designed RNAi reagents 
from independent libraries and links to a design program of 
RNAi constructs for independent retests (13). The database 
structure is flexible and allows adding large-scale cell-based 
phenotypic datasets from other organisms once they become 
available. </p>

<p>DATABASE CONTENT </p>

<p>The database integrates the sequence information of the 
RNAi reagents with phenotypic information based on 
genome-scale and genome-wide published RNAi screens. It 
contains 90 998 RNAi probes that have been designed by 
various groups. These include libraries used in Heidelberg 
and Boston (4,14), by groups in San Francisco and others 
(15). Using the sequence information, all RNAi constructs 
were computationally mapped onto the latest genomic 
sequence using <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> and <rs type="software">MUMmer</rs> (16,17) and gene 
and isoform annotations were derived through the mapping 
process. All probe information is visualized using an imple-
mentation of the <rs type="software">Generic Genome Browser</rs> (<rs type="software">GBrowse</rs>) 
(18). Additional information was added to describe the 
specificity of dsRNAs. To this end, we have generated all 
possible 19mer sequences of annotated gene models (in 
total &gt;40 Mio.) and identified homologous sequences in the </p>

<p>complete genome. These are annotated as 'tracks' in 
<rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> and allow evaluation of the specificity of RNAi 
probe sequences. In addition, <rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> tracks are included 
that show other types of non-specific regions, such as low 
complexity and repetitive elements in the gene model 
which should be avoided in the design of RNAi probes. Phe-
notypes mapping to such elements should also be treated with 
caution until further confirmatory data is available. Further-
more, for every single 19mer sequence we have calculated 
an RNAi efficiency score (19) which is shown as a 'RNAi 
efficiency' column in the database. The average predicted 
efficiency is shown for individual RNAi probes from various 
libraries as well as a 'track' for complete gene models in the 
<rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> interface. Specificity and efficiency information can 
also be used to guide the design of new RNAi probes for 
follow-up experiments. 
RNAi phenotypes of large-scale screens from our own lab 
and all to-date published screens were curated from the 
author's websites or the Supplementary Data. To date, the 
database contains 24 genome-scale screens which were 
performed with different genome-wide and subset RNAi 
libraries. A total of 5436 phenotypes are currently stored in 
<rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs>, which will be expanded as more data becomes 
available. Phenotype frequency varies among the screens 
from 23 to &gt;1000 hits per screen. A list of all currently avail-
able screens can be accessed at http://www.dkfz.de/signaling/ 
screens/. </p>

<p>DATA QUERY </p>

<p>The database can be accessed through various routes. Indivi-
dual gene entries can be directly accessed via a linkout 
('Heidelberg RNAi') from <rs type="software">Flybase</rs> (20). From the entry web-
page of the database, user can search by gene identifier, by 
RNAi probe ID (if known) or by phenotype (Figure 1). For 
all these search options more detailed web pages are available 
which offer advanced input options (e.g. sequence homology 
search). Through the 'phenotype' entry page a complete list 
of all phenotypes can be requested by clicking the 'Display 
list of all phenotypes' link. This can then be used to access 
an individual gene or probe list. A second way to search 
for phenotypes and RNAi probe information is by sequence 
similarity. In the 'Gene' or 'Probe' menu page, the user can 
enter a Drosophila (or heterologous) nucleotide or protein 
sequence which is mapped by using <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> against the 
BDGP transcript file or probe files. This allows for example 
to search for phenotypes of a homolog of human cdc2 or can 
be used to find all RNAi probes from various libraries that 
overlap with a query sequence. </p>

<p>DATA OUTPUT </p>

<p>Information with respect to genes or RNAi probes is subse-
quently retrieved from the database. In case of gene query, 
the database retrieves all mapped RNAi probes and displays 
them as a table (Figure 2A), including information of pheno-
types that were reported, the calculated target transcripts and 
whether all isoforms are targeted (columns 'Transcripts' and 
'Specificity'). This view shows also how many in silico 
diced siRNAs map to gene model and whether additional </p>



<p>transcripts are targeted (column 'Other Targets') by the 
dsRNA. The database allows then to drill down and retrieve 
more detailed information, including primer and amplicon 
sequences (Figure 2B) by following the 'RNAi probe' link 
as well as more detailed information on other targets by fol-
lowing the corresponding link. The completeness of available 
RNAi constructs in their genomic context is summarized in 
an interactive <rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> implementation, which shows the 
gene model, the RNAi probes of all available libraries and 
tracks that allow evaluating the efficiency and specificity of 
probe sequences (Figure 2C). Other <rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> functions can 
then be used to extract for example non-targeted regions, com-
mon exons, regions with high specificity or regions of low-
complexity. Information can be extracted as text or XML files. 
An example of a database session is shown in Figure 2. In 
this case, the user searched for RNAi probes that target 
CG6210 (FBgn0036141), a factor required for the secretion 
of Wg/Wnt ligands (3). Figure 2A shows that multiple 
RNAi probes are available in different libraries and also 
links to <rs type="software">FlyBase</rs>, if more information on CG6210 is reques-
ted. When the user selects the HFA10605 RNAi probe, the 
database shows more detailed information, such as primer 
sequences used to amplify a template for in vitro transcrip-
tion, the length and sequence of the amplicon. This page 
also shows all other phenotypes that were observed with 
this RNAi probe, allowing evaluation of the specificity of </p>

<p>the RNAi experiment. When selecting the <rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> image, 
the user can locate other RNAi probes in relation to the 
gene model; for example, whereas for CG6210 six dsRNAs 
from different libraries have a similar location, a single 
dsRNA ('AMC-Amplicon') targets only one splice variant 
(CG6210-RA) and might give only a partial phenotype. 
These assignments are even more complex for gene models 
that have a larger number of splice variants and/or overlap-
ping transcripts. 
The database can also be accessed through searching for 
phenotypes or selecting from an all phenotypes list which 
can be retrieved from phenotype search menu. 
Through these pages, the database provides gene annota-
tion by comparing phenotypes in the light of the sequence 
content of probes targeting the gene of interest. Furthermore, 
individual gene models are linked to external databases such 
as <rs type="software">FlyBase</rs> and <rs type="software">FLIGHT</rs> for other functional information. A 
link to <rs type="software">E-RNAi</rs> (13) is provided to allow a direct redesign of 
independent RNAi probes. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS AND OUTLOOK </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> database presents phenotype information 
of large-scale screens in the context of associated sequence 
information. We believe that this is an important issue </p>

<p>Figure 1. Entry page of the <rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> database. This page allows direct access to search function by gene, RNAi ID or phenotype. More detailed search 
pages which allow for example to search by sequence homology can be accessed via the main menu. </p>



<p>since in contrast to genetic mutants, RNAi phenotypes 
depend on the specificity of the used siRNAs or dsRNAs 
(21-23). Furthermore, with changes in gene models, RNAi 
phenotypes attributed to a specific gene may be linked to a 
different gene in the future. Similar limitations apply to </p>

<p>RNAi reagents targeting specific splice variants of genes. 
RNAi libraries evolve, as we learn more about the RNAi 
mechanism and potential pitfalls such as off-target effects 
second generation libraries will incorporate these findings 
into design rules and attempt to generate more specific </p>

<p>Figure 2. Example of a database search using the Web interface. (A) The table shows the search results from a user query for all probes targeting the CG6210 
transcripts. The 'Specificity' column summarizes how many of the theoretical possible diced 21mer sequences hit the transcript. (B) Drill down to access 
sequence information associated with a particular RNAi probe. This information can also be used to redesign RNAi reagents. (C) <rs type="software">GBrowse</rs> image of all RNAi 
probes that target a particular gene model. Different libraries are shown in tracks. Specificity and other information are shown below the RNAi probes. If RNAi 
probes target other genes in addition to the intended one, this information is displayed below the RNAi probes [e.g. FBgn0036141 (CG6210) + 24 other targets]. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Database issue D495 </p>

<p>reagents and make them publicly available (T. Horn, 
A. Kiger, M. Boutros, unpublished data). 
The <rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> database is linked to other databases, 
such as <rs type="software">FLIGHT</rs> and <rs type="software">FlyRNAi</rs> (24,25). While all these data-
bases contain RNAi phenotype information, the focus of 
<rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> is to present phenotypes in the context of 
genomic information, which should facilitate the analysis 
of RNAi phenotypes with respect to gene models and speci-
ficity information. <rs type="software">GenomeRNAi</rs> has an integrated pipeline 
for mapping of RNAi probes and phenotypes and integrating 
the information of different RNAi libraries, but the focus is 
less on the integration of different genomic datasets as 
provided by <rs type="software">FLIGHT</rs>. 
A major issue in representing RNAi phenotypes remains a 
lack of standards on minimal information which need to be 
provided for small and large-scale screening approaches, as 
well as an ontology to properly describe cellular phenotypes. 
With time we expect that the community will develop such 
standards which will become a prerequisite for publication. 
The same holds true for the analysis of numerical data asso-
ciated with phenotypic information, which can be analyzed in 
different ways and which may lead to different 'phenotype 
lists' depending on the arbitrary threshold that is being used 
as a cut-off. Compendia that include both primary data and 
the analysis route could alleviate analysis diversity and 
enable the re-analysis of datasets when new algorithms will 
be available or datasets will be cross-correlated (26,27). 
In the future, we plan to add cell-based phenotypes from 
other species, such as human, including sequence information 
which is currently largely not available due to proprietary restric-
tions. Cross-specific comparisons should provide a useful means 
to extract functional and highly confirmed phenotypes. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary data are available at NAR online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We would like to thank Anan Ragab, David Kuttenkeuler, 
Dorothee Nickles, Florian Fuchs and Sandra Steinbrink for 
helpful comments on the manuscript and members of the 
Boutros lab for critical suggestions and discussions through-
out the project. We are grateful to Tobias Reber for support 
with server infrastructure. T.H. was supported by a fellowship 
of the Studienstiftung des deutschen Volkes. The research 
was funded by the Emmy Noether Program of the Deutsche 
Forschungsgemeinschaft and a Research Grant of the Human 
Frontier Science Program to M.B. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, Database issue D497 </p>

</text></tei>