<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2447781" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> (protein flexibility analyzer) web server 
detects and displays conformational changes in 
remotely related proteins, without relying on 
sequence homology. To do so, it first applies a 
reliable statistical test to align core protein frag-
ments that are structurally similar and then clusters 
these aligned fragment pairs into 'super-alignments', 
according to the similarity of geometric transforma-
tions that align them. The result is that the dominant 
conformational changes occur between the clusters, 
while the smaller conformational changes occur 
within a cluster. <rs id="software-4" type="software">pFlexAna</rs> is available at <rs corresp="#software-4" type="url">http:// bigbird.comp.nus.edu.sg/pfa2</rs>/. </p>

<p>Conformational change plays a critical role in the func-
tioning and regulation of many proteins, and comparing 
protein structures with different backbone conformations 
is a common task in structural biology (1). This task is 
particularly challenging when we compare two evolution-
arily divergent proteins. The main goal of our work is to 
provide an automated tool for detecting conformational 
changes in remotely related proteins. 
For proteins undergoing conformational change, we 
can often find in them backbone fragments that remain 
rigid and are well aligned. However, these rigid local 
fragments reorient themselves with respect to one another 
during the conformational change, resulting in poor 
global alignment. A good example is large-scale domain 
movement. Consider the HECT domain of the human 
ubiquitin ligase WWP1, which is homologous to the 
human ubiquitin ligase E6AP. Comparing their crystal 
structures [PDB codes 1D5F:C (2) and 1ND7 (3)] reveals 
a dramatic conformational change (Figure 1) crucial 
for their biological function, which is to move the ubiqui-
tin molecule from one substrate protein to another. </p>

<p>The crystallographers who determined the WWP1 struc-
ture described in detail its comparison with E6AP (3), and 
they produced several figures depicting superpositions 
carried out manually, similar to what <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> produces 
automatically. To our knowledge, there are currently no 
other computational tools that aim to automate such 
analyses. 
Our <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> (protein flexibility analyzer) web server 
aims at automatically detecting conformational changes 
between a pair of protein structures, without relying on 
sequence homology. Specifically, it detects regions exhibit-
ing structural change, contrasted with regions exhibiting 
structural similarity. The <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> results can be viewed 
as indications of the endpoints of hypothesized molecular 
motions or mutation-induced conformational changes. 
To detect conformational changes in dissimilar proteins, 
we must first find structurally similar fragments (domains, 
sub-domains, etc.) in the proteins. <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> employs a 
statistical test to match core protein fragments that are 
structurally similar and determine the geometric transfor-
mations that align them. This statistical test of structural 
similarity has been shown to be effective in detecting many 
different types of conformational changes (4). <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> 
displays the protein structures superimposed according to 
each aligned fragment pair. The superimposed display 
highlights the discontinuity from the similar to the dis-
similar regions of the proteins and aids visualization of 
the conformational changes that occur relative to the 
aligned fragment pair used as the basis for superposition. 
See Figure 3 for a sample result. Furthermore, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> 
clusters the aligned fragment pairs into 'super-alignments', 
according to the similarity of geometric transformations 
that align them. The result is that the dominant conforma-
tional changes occur between the clusters, while the smaller 
conformational changes occur within a cluster. 
There are many approaches for studying conforma-
tional changes. One possibility is to perform molecular 
dynamics (MD) simulation to generate alternative con-
formations from a single known protein structure (5). 
However, MD simulation is computationally intensive, </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +65 6516 2978; Fax: +65 6779 4580; Email: dyhsu@comp.nus.edu.sg </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>and usually it can only explore conformational changes 
that are small in magnitude. An alternative approach is to 
compare directly the structures of a protein in different 
conformations. There are several good methods for this 
(4,6-8), but they can be applied only if the structures of 
the same protein in different conformations are available. 
It is thus sometimes necessary to compare conforma-
tions of related, but different proteins in order to infer 
conformational changes. One possibility is to perform 
sequence alignment as a preprocessing step to match the 
proteins and then detect conformational changes between 
them (9). This method, however, is restricted to proteins 
with 90% sequence identity (9). 
As a complementary approach, for cases with low 
sequence homology, one may attempt structural align-
ment i.e. matching the proteins based on structural simil-
arity instead of sequence similarity. However, both rigid 
and flexible structural alignment methods focus on finding 
a single best fit between the protein structures, and may 
ignore small yet significant conformational changes. 
Consider, for example, the relatively simple case of a 
same protein in two conformations. Given the bound and 
unbound structures [PDB codes 3MBP (10) and 1LLS:A 
(11)] of the maltose-binding protein, two popular struc-
tural alignment methods, CE (12) and FATCAT (13), </p>

<p>align the entire structures together without recognizing the 
hinge-like conformational change occurring between the 
two domains of the protein. FlexProt (14), on the other 
hand, requires the user to know the number of hinges in 
order to interpret its results. What we need in this case is 
a method that automatically detects the 'discontinuity' in 
structural similarity at the hinge due to the conforma-
tional change and matches the two domains on each side 
of the hinge separately. See Figure 2 for a comparison 
between the results from FATCAT and <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs>. In 
general, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> aims to detect such conformational 
changes for two related, but different proteins. Further-
more, it tries to identify and group together those protein 
fragments that move in tandem. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Input </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> server takes as input two protein structures 
in PDB format, which may be uploaded or specified using 
PDB codes. The user may also specify chain identifiers or 
a restricted range of residues for each file. Finally, there 
are two optional parameters that the user may adjust. The 
parameter k is the desired number of clusters for grouping </p>

<p>Figure 1. Superposition of the structures of ubiquitin ligases WWWP1 and E6AP. The two different superpositions, produced automatically by 
<rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs>, are obtained by aligning a pair of fragments (marked in red and green) with high structural similarity. Dotted ovals annotate the parts of 
the proteins that are well aligned in the superpositions. To see the magnitude of the conformational change, note that the pose of E6AP (blue) 
remains the same in both (a) and (b). Only the pose of WWWP1 (orange) changes. </p>

<p>Figure 2. Superposition of the bound (red) and unbound (blue) structures of the maltose-binding protein. (a) FATCAT aligns the entire protein 
structures. (b) <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> correctly identifies two rigid domains that undergo hinge bending. The proteins are shown aligned on one domain. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W247 </p>

<p>the aligned fragments together, and is the noise param-
eter, which determines how strictly structural similarity is 
applied. For low -values, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> matches only frag-
ments that are highly similar. For high -values, it also 
matches fragments with weak similarity and ignores small 
differences. Based on our experiences, -values between 
0.2 and 0.4 work well for proteins with reasonably high-
sequence homology (40% or higher). For proteins that are 
even more distantly related, we find -values up to 0.8 to 
be useful as well, though this may lead to false positive 
matches in some cases. </p>

<p>Output </p>

<p><rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> identifies pairs of fragments-one fragment 
from each protein-that show significant conformational 
similarity. They are listed in a table and grouped into 
clusters, according to the similarity of the geometric 
transformation that aligns the fragment pair. See Figure 3 
for an example. Two or more fragment pairs may move 
together and form a semi-rigid domain. By categorizing 
fragment pairs that are moving together versus moving 
independently, clustering helps to characterize conforma-
tional changes caused by domain movements or correlated 
motions. 
For each aligned fragment pair, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> provides a 
static cartoon of the proteins superimposed according to 
the aligned pair. This highlights the movement of the 
proteins with respect to the aligned regions. Jmol links are </p>

<p>also provided so that the user may view the proteins from 
different angles. Finally, the transformed PDB coordinate 
files that align the second protein to the first are available 
for download and the transformation matrices used for 
alignment are provided. The same information is also 
provided for each cluster of aligned fragment pairs. </p>

<p>Processing </p>

<p>To analyze the conformational changes between two 
protein structures, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> proceeds in two main steps. 
In the first step, it identifies pairs of fragments that are 
structurally similar. These fragment pairs serve as rigid 
cores for superimposing the two proteins and detecting 
conformational changes with respect to the cores. In the 
second step, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> clusters the aligned fragment pairs 
into 'super-alignments', according to the similarity of 
geometric transformations that align two fragments in a 
pair. The result is that the dominant conformational 
changes occur between the clusters, while the smaller 
conformational changes occur within a cluster. We now 
describe the two steps in greater detail below. 
To identify structurally similar fragment pairs, 
<rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> uses an all-against-all approach that effectively 
compares every contiguous fragment from one protein 
with that from the other. First, we match the residues of 
the two proteins by 'sliding' one protein against the other 
(Figure 4). For each sliding position, let P and P 
0 represent 
the matched residues from the two proteins, respectively. 
We generate all contiguous fragments of P and P 
0 and 
check their structural similarity by applying a reliable 
statistical test (4). Briefly, this test uses a Gaussian noise 
model to represent acceptable deviations in atomic 
coordinates between two putatively similar protein frag-
ments. Two fragments are considered statistically different 
if their coordinates deviate too much according to the 
Gaussian model. We then assign to each residue a 
flexibility score that incorporates information from all 
fragment comparisons that involve this residue. A high 
score indicates greater rigidity. Finally, each pair of 
aligned fragments must pass the following filter: the 
fragments must consist entirely of residues whose flex-
ibility scores are above a threshold, and they must be 
longer than a given minimum length. Intuitively, this filter 
ensures that such a pair of fragments and all sub-
fragments contained in them are structurally identical up 
to statistical variations. The minimum length requirement 
is imposed to avoid accidental structural matches. One 
advantage of our method is that it highlights the genuine 
conformational changes by suppressing the spurious ones 
due to noise. More details on this method and its 
advantages are available in ref. (4). Since we perform an </p>

<p>Figure 3. A screenshot showing the pFlexAna result for the mal-
tose-binding protein. The pose of the protein is different from that in 
Figure 2. 
Figure 4. Sliding one protein against the other. </p>



<p>exhaustive comparison of all contiguous fragments in the 
two protein structures, our method can detect structurally 
similar fragments that are in opposite order along the 
protein sequences. 
After obtaining an exhaustive list of structurally similar 
fragment pairs, we need to resolve the conflicts among 
them. A conflict occurs if in the list of matched fragment 
pairs, a residue from one protein is matched with multiple 
residues from the other protein. In practice, we have found 
that biologically significant matches have much longer 
fragment length than the spurious ones due to accidental 
structural similarity. So we remove the conflicts in the list 
by preferring fragment pairs with longer length. 
Finally, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> hierarchically clusters the fragment 
pairs. The idea is to treat each structurally similar fragment 
pair as a point and divide these points into k clusters so 
that the dominant structural differences occur across 
clusters. To do this, we build a similarity graph. The ver-
tices of this graph correspond to the fragment pairs 
obtained after conflict resolution. There is an edge between 
every two vertices, and the associated edge weight rep-
resents the similarity between the fragment pairs corre-
sponding to the two vertices. Here, similarity is defined as 
the root mean square deviation (RMSD) for the best 
superposition when the two fragment pairs are combined. 
After constructing the similarity graph, we recursively 
remove from the graph the edge with the greatest weight 
and thus separate the most dissimilar fragment pairs, 
which represent the largest structural difference. We con-
tinue this edge removal process until the graph breaks into 
k connected components. 
The web server implementation of our method uses 
PHP for its front-end interface, C++ for back-end pro-
cessing, and a Ruby daemon to interface the front and 
back ends. The output images are generated using <rs type="software">PyMol</rs> 
(15) and interactive displays of each alignment are pro-
vided using <rs type="software">Jmol</rs> (16). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>We illustrate the results of <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> on several repre-
sentative cases. </p>

<p>Ubiquitin ligase </p>

<p>The crystal structures of the E6AP and WWP1 ubiquitin 
ligases [PDB codes 1D5F:C (2) and 1ND7 (3)] display a 
striking example of domain movement (Figure 1). 
<rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> finds six core regions of significant structural 
similarity between the proteins and successfully clusters 
them into two domains which move independently (see 
Figure 1). These images are obtained directly from the web 
server, but annotated with an arrow and dotted ovals to 
draw attention to the domains that are aligned. The 
relative movement between the domains has been char-
acterized as a 100 degree sweep with a 30 degree tilt (3). 
Superpositions, such as those shown in Figure 1, help to 
highlight the context of each protein region undergoing 
conformation change. 
Superpositions of similar regions, as shown in Figure 1, 
are ideal for visualization because they show the difference 
as a divergence from a fixed reference point. Beyond 
simply showing the context of each 'flexible' region, each 
superposition indicates a transition from similar (rigid) to 
different (flexible). </p>

<p>Glutamine amidotransferase and 
arabinose-binding protein </p>

<p>The ubiquitin ligases have moderate sequence identity 
(&lt; 40%), but we have tested <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> on a range of pro-
tein pairs with low sequence identity such as the isomerase 
domain of glucosamine 6P synthase [1MOQ (17)] and 
arabinose binding protein [8ABP (18)], which have 10% 
sequence identity. Figure 5 shows the alignments of 
1MOQ and 8ABP. <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> finds two independent 
domains. Each aligned domain centers around a parallel 
b-sheet buried by a-helices. In this figure, each align-
ment is rotated for viewing down the plane of an aligned 
sheet. To see the magnitude of the domain movement, 
note that the N-terminal domain of 8ABP (magenta) 
appears in the upper-right of both views, and 1MOQ 
(orange) is dramatically shifted between the two 
alignments. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Proteins 1MOQ (orange) and 8ABP (purple) are aligned by pFlexAna according to their N-terminal domains in (a) and according to their 
C-terminal domains in (b). The N-terminal residues of each protein are shaded lighter than the C-terminal residues. Each alignment includes a 
parallel b-sheet (circled). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W249 </p>

<p>PX domain </p>

<p><rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> is particularly useful for proteins exhibiting 
domain moments, but applying it to proteins with more 
subtle conformational changes and without major domain 
movements can also be informative. In particular, we set 
parameter k = 1 when we expect only a single cluster 
corresponding to the aligned protein core. For example, 
Figure 6 compares two PX domain proteins [1KMD (19)  and 1GD5 (20)]. The N-and C-termini of the two proteins 
are conserved, but the loop region in between contains 
several insertions/deletions. Most structural alignment 
methods attempt to align these two proteins by super-
imposing their entire backbones globally. While this may 
be useful for some purposes, single global alignments may 
be skewed as they include the loop region. A more 
informative view of the evolutionary impact on conforma-
tional structure is shown by aligning only the conserved 
segments. On the PX domains, <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> automatically 
finds the fragments of tightest similarity, distinct from the 
loop region, and it presents the clustered alignment result 
without skew from the inserted amino acids. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p><rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> is a new tool for protein structure comparison. 
It detects and displays conformational changes in 
remotely related proteins, without relying on sequence 
homology. Our tests show that <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> helps in anal-
yzing a wide variety of conformational changes. It can 
detect conformational changes in proteins with identical 
sequences or those with very low sequence similarity. It 
can detect dramatic domain movements as well as smaller, 
more subtle conformational changes. 
The output of <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> helps the analysis of conforma-
tional changes in several ways. <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> uses a reliable 
statistical test of structural similarity to demarcate the 
protein regions that undergo conformational changes. It 
also clusters the protein fragments that move in tandem. 
The clustering helps in finding domains comprised of frag-
ments that are discontiguous and out of order along the 
sequences, e.g. in the case of the maltose-binding protein 
(Figure 3). Visualization of such information, provided 
in <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs>'s output, helps the user to scan for hinge 
locations, active binding sites, domain movements, etc. For </p>

<p>more detailed analysis, the user may use the quantitative 
information provided in <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs>'s output, e.g. use the 
provided transformation matrix for alignment to compute 
the angle of bending at a particular hinge. pFlexAna's 
output may also help users interested in predicting 
conformational motion. They may use the information 
that <rs type="software">pFlexAna</rs> provides as a starting point and combine it 
with other methods such as targeted molecular dynamics 
(21), where an MD simulation trajectory is 'directed' from 
an inital conformation towards an alternative target 
conformation. 
pFlexAna uses purely structural information to match 
two proteins. While this is often advantageous as it does 
not rely on sequence homology, it can potentially cause 
false positive matching. For example, for proteins with 
many secondary structure elements (SSEs), it is possible 
for unrelated long alpha helices or other common motifs 
comprised of multiple SSEs to be identified as aligned 
fragment pairs. Comparing glutamine amidotransferase 
(1MOQ) with a ubiquitin ligase (1ND7) matches two pairs 
of highly similar a-helices, with RMSD values of 
0.22 Å and 1.64 Å , respectively. While such aligned pairs 
are justified based on purely structural similarity, they 
may not be biologically significant to form a basis for 
inferring conformational changes. In the future, we 
intend to filter out such false positives by incorporating 
secondary structure or sequence information during the 
matching. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>I.M. and C.V. gratefully acknowledge support by 
Biomedical Research Council of A*STAR, Singapore. 
L.T.K. was supported by a Lee Kuan Yew Postdoctoral 
Fellowship. Funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by the NUS AcRF 
grant R-252-000-342-112. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W251 </p>

</text></tei>