<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2936008" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:41+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: </p>

<p>Objectives: To assess depression, anxiety, and alcohol abuse in a Gastroenterology ICU, and the level of its detection by 
the staff. </p>

<p>Method: All patients consecutively admitted to the ICU during a six-month period, 18 or above, and staying 24 hours, 
were assessed with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale (HADS) and the CAGE. Doctors and nurses assessed the 
type and severity of patients' morbidity. Data were analyzed with Student's t-test, Pearson's and Spearman's correlations 
for ordinal variables, chi-square for nominal variables, and multiple logistic regression. </p>

<p>Results: The 65 patients assessed had a mean age of 57, and were predominantly male (58.5%), married (72.3%), and re-
tired (53.8%); 27.7% had a psychiatric history, 24.6% were on psychotropic drugs, and 32.3% had an alcohol intake 
above standards. Anxiety and depression HADS scores 8 were present in 29.2% and 35.4% of the patients, respectively; 
20%, mainly men, scored positive on the CAGE. Women had significantly higher anxiety scores (=.012) than men but did 
not differ in depression. A psychiatric history was significantly associated with higher anxiety (p&lt;.001) and depression 
(p=.007) scores, as well as being on psychotropic drugs regularly (p&lt;.001; p=.03, respectively). </p>

<p>Doctors diagnosed somatic illness in 48.8%, and somatic illness with psychiatric co-morbidity in 51%; for nurses the rates 
were, respectively, 41.5% and 58.6%. Doctors' and nurses' detection of psychiatric disorders were significantly associated 
with the HADS anxiety scores (p=.013; p=.001, respectively), and doctor's detection with depression (p=.046) scores. 
There were no significant associations between nurses' detection of psychiatric disorders and depression, and between 
both professional groups detection and alcohol abuse. </p>

<p>Conclusion: High prevalence of depression, anxiety, and alcohol abuse in Gastroenterology ICU was confirmed. How-
ever, the level of detection by the staff was low and mainly when anxiety symptoms were present. </p>

<p>The prevalence of psychiatric morbidity in general hospi-
tal inpatients has been described as very high [1] varying 
between 21 and 40% [2, 3]. A large percentage of these pa-
tients suffer from diagnosable psychiatric disorders, fre-
quently triggered by hospital admission, which can be re-
lated or not to the somatic condition. Patients admitted to an 
Intensive Care Unit (ICU) are more at risk for psychiatric co-
morbidity, due to the severity of somatic illness, as well as to 
pharmacological and environmental factors, and will proba-
bly present higher rates of psychiatric symptoms. Rincon et 
al. [4] found that 29.2% of the adult patients in ICU screened 
positive in at least one of the following scales: anxiety, de-
pression, delirium, and drinking problems. </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Serviço de Psiquiatria, Hospi-
tal Fernando Fonseca, 2720-276 Amadora, Portugal; Tel: +351 21 434 
8272; Fax: +351 21 434 5566; E-mails: gracacardoso@gmail.com, 
joanaalexandre@gmail.com, alda_rosa@hotmail.com </p>

<p>Delirium is a frequent complication in ICU, and the 
prevalence reported in medical and surgical ICU cohort stud-
ies varies from 40 to 80%, depending upon the severity of 
illness and methods of diagnosis [5,6]. </p>

<p>Depression and anxiety disorders and symptoms are fre-
quent in ICU, and not uncommonly associated with cogni-
tive dysfunction. They may precede or be part of delirium. In 
the Rincon et al. study [4], the prevalence rates were 13.7% 
for depression and 24% for anxiety. </p>

<p>Depressive and anxiety symptoms can persist several 
months after discharge. The prevalence of clinically signifi-
cant depressive symptoms in patients 2 months after dis-
charge from ICU was 33% [7], and depression and anxiety 
symptom rates, measured with the Hospital Anxiety and De-
pression Scale (HADS), were as high as 47% and 24% re-
spectively, 9 months after discharge from ICU [8]. </p>

<p>Substance abuse or dependence, being a risk factor for 
severe somatic illness, is frequently present in ICU patients. </p>



<p>Cardoso et al. </p>

<p>Alcohol consumption increases the risk of intensive care 
admission and of hospital death in men [9], and is directly 
related to the admission in 21 to 28% of ICU patients 
[10,11,12]. Drinking problems have been reported in 37.9% 
of ICU patients [4], and alcohol-related conditions described 
in 44 to 51% of gastroenterology inpatients [13,14]. This 
could point to a higher prevalence rate of alcohol abuse in 
gastroenterology ICUs compared to general ICUs, that has 
not been addressed in previous studies. On the other hand, in 
general ICUs there is great variety of severe somatic ill-
nesses, with respiratory, cardiovascular, traumatic condi-
tions, and suicide attempts, while in a gastroenterology ICU 
there is a more homogeneous somatically ill population. </p>

<p>Despite the high rates of psychiatric co-morbidity, less 
than 5% of general hospital inpatients are referred to psy-
chiatry [3]. Since the presence of psychiatric morbidity is 
associated with worse prognosis and increased mortality in 
patients with somatic illness, [15, 16] there is a great need to 
promote and improve the level of detection by general hospi-
tal staff. </p>

<p>To our knowledge, there are no published studies on as-
sessment of depression, anxiety and alcohol abuse preva-
lence rates and detection in gastroenterology intensive care 
units. The current study had two main hypotheses: 1) the 
rates of psychiatric morbidity in a gastroenterology ICU dif-
fer from those in general ICUs; 2) the levels of detection by 
doctors and nurses in this setting are low to moderate. </p>

<p>AIMS </p>

<p>The objectives of this study were to assess the level of 
depressive and anxiety symptoms, and of alcohol abuse in 
patients admitted to a gastroenterology intensive care unit, 
and to establish the level of detection of psychiatric morbid-
ity by ICU doctors and nurses. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Sample </p>

<p>All the patients consecutively admitted to the Gastroen-
terology Intensive Care Unit (GE ICU) of Hospital Santa 
Maria, a university general hospital in Lisbon, between Feb-
ruary and July 1995, and with no cognitive impairment of 
sufficient severity to preclude a standardized assessment, 
were included in the study. Length of ICU stay shorter than 
24 hours and being under 18 years of age were considered 
exclusion criteria. </p>

<p>Description of the Unit </p>

<p>The unit is part of the Gastroenterology Department, and 
only admits patients with severe gastroenterological condi-
tions. It consists of a large room with ten beds, separated by 
curtains, and of a smaller room with 2 beds for patients with 
more severe conditions. </p>

<p>Procedures </p>

<p>The patients were interviewed during the first 72 hours of 
admission to the unit by one of the authors (A.R.), and as-
sessed with the HADS [17], a self-report Likert scale that 
includes two subscales, for depressive and anxiety symp-
toms, with 7 questions each, rating from 0 to 3, and a total 
score range between 0 and 21, a higher score being more </p>

<p>symptomatic. A cut off of 8 in any of the subscales was used 
in the study. </p>

<p>The patients were also assessed with the CAGE [18], a 
self-report 4 question yes/no scale aimed at assessing alcohol 
dependence, and positive when at least one question is an-
swered yes. </p>

<p>The following variables were collected during hospital 
stay: age, gender, marital and professional status, level of 
education, living situation, somatic diagnoses, psychiatric 
history, being on psychotropic drugs, level of alcohol intake, 
number of days in the unit, and type of discharge. The pa-
tients were considered to have an alcohol intake above stan-
dard levels if it was at least 80g per day for males, and 40g 
per day for females. Psychological distress was operational-
ised as a total score of the HADS equal or above 16 (the sum 
of the subscales cut-off). </p>

<p>Doctors and nurses of the GE ICU were asked to fill a 
questionnaire aimed at assessing their patients as being so-
matic only, somatic with psychiatric morbidity, or psychiat-
ric with somatic comorbity and the condition severity in a 
linear scale from 1 to 5, in which 1 represented minimum 
and 5 highest possible severity. They were also asked to 
formulate a diagnosis of the psychiatric morbidity, when 
present. </p>

<p>The study was submitted to the Hospital Santa Maria 
Ethics and Research Committee, and was approved without 
restrictions. All the patients gave their oral informed consent 
after reading the study description, and having their ques-
tions answered. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using the program 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 14</rs>. The sample's characteristics were de-
scribed with descriptive measures such as mean, standard 
deviation, percentages and range. Student's t-test and, when 
appropriate, Mann-Whitney test were used for quantitative 
variables, and Spearman and Pearson's correlations for ordi-
nal variables. Chi-square and Fisher's exact test (whenever 
chi-square assumptions were not met) were calculated for 
nominal variables. To assess the effect of past variables on 
current psychological distress and its detection by physicians 
and nurses, multiple logistic regression was carried out. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>During the inclusion period, 168 consecutive patients 
were admitted to the GE ICU, of which 68 were excluded on 
the grounds of staying in the unit less than 24 hours (n=67), 
and being under 18 (n=1). Seventeen patients could not be 
interviewed during the first 72 hours, and further 17 patients 
could not be assessed due to severe cognitive impairment 
during the first 72 hours of admission. </p>

<p>The group of 65 patients that met the inclusion criteria 
and were assessed with the HADS and the CAGE (as shown 
on Table 1) had a mean age of 57 years, and the majority 
were men (59%), married (72%), retired (54%), living with 
their family (89%), and with less than 4 years of education 
(51%). Most of the patients (72%) had never been treated for 
emotional problems, and were not currently taking psycho-
tropic drugs (75%). The main reason for admission was 
gastrointestinal bleeding in 39 patients (60%) -38.5% of the 
total sample due to peptic ulcer and 21.5% to esophageal </p>

<p>Depression, Anxiety and Alcohol Abuse in a Gastroenterology Intensive </p>

<p>Clinical Practice &amp; Epidemiology in Mental Health, 2010, Volume 6 49 </p>

<p>varices -followed by pancreatitis (21.5%). The mean length 
of stay in the unit was 7 days, and more than half of the pa-
tients were transferred to a medical ward (54%), while 3% 
died while in Intensive Care. </p>

<p>The CAGE and HADS scores are shown on Table 2. 
Thirteen patients (20%) were considered positive with the 
CAGE. The HADS mean anxiety score was 6.2±4.0, and the </p>

<p>mean depression score was 6.2±4.8. Nineteen patients 
(29.2%) had a score above the cut off ( 8) in the HADS 
anxiety subscale, and 23 (35.4%) in the depression subscale. </p>

<p>Table 2. Assessment with the Hospital Anxiety and Depression 
Scale and the CAGE (n=65) </p>

<p>CAGE -n (%) </p>

<p>Negative (scoring 0) </p>

<p>Positive (scoring at least 1) </p>

<p>52 (80) </p>

<p>13 (20) </p>

<p>HADS -Depression, mean (sd) </p>

<p>HADS -Depression 8, n (%) </p>

<p>6.2 (4.8) </p>

<p>23 (35.4) </p>

<p>HADS -Anxiety, mean (sd) </p>

<p>HADS -Anxiety 8, n (%) </p>

<p>6.2 (4.0) </p>

<p>19 (29.2) </p>

<p>Tables 3 to 5 show the relationship between demographic 
and clinical variables and the scales' scores, as well as be-
tween the HADS and the CAGE scores, using Student´s t-
test, chi-square, Fisher's exact test and Pearson's correlation. </p>

<p>Women had significantly higher mean anxiety scores on 
the HADS than men (7.7 vs. 5.2, p= .012), but the two gen-
ders did not differ on the HADS mean depression scores. 
Higher anxiety and depression scores on the HADS were 
significantly associated with past psychiatric history (10.0 
vs. 4.7, p&lt; .001 for anxiety; 9.6 vs. 5.1, p&lt; .001 for depres-
sion), and use of psychotropic drugs (8.7 vs. 5.2, p= .007 for 
anxiety; 8.4 vs. 5.5, p= .030 for depression). Alcohol intake 
above standard was significantly associated with higher de-
pression scores (8.6 vs. 5.1, p= .005), but not with anxiety 
scores. A significant positive correlation between anxiety 
and depression scores on the HADS (Pearson's= .582; p&lt; 
.001) was found. Depression or anxiety HADS scores were 
not significantly correlated with being CAGE positive. </p>

<p>Multiple logistic regression, considering psychological 
distress (HADS total score at least 16) as dependent variable 
and having as main independent variables the use of psycho-
tropic drugs and psychiatric history, showed that the main 
variable, current use of psychotropic medication, had an 
Odds Ratio (OR) of 2.3 (95% Confidence Interval (CI): 0.33 
-16.43; p=.398) but no statistical effect on psychological 
distress, while psychiatric history obtained an OR of 7.4 
(95% CI: 1.14 -47.55; p=.036) and a significant effect on 
psychological distress. </p>

<p>There was a statistically significant correlation between 
the CAGE scores and gender, with 31.6% of men rating 
positive vs. 3.7% of women, p= .01. On the other hand, 
52.4% of the inpatients scoring positive on the CAGE had an 
alcohol intake above standard vs. 4.5% of those with con-
sumption below standard (p&lt; .001). The sensitivity and 
specificity of the CAGE test for the detection of alcohol in-
take above 80g for men and 40 g for women in this sample 
were 52% and 95%, respectively. </p>

<p>Detection of Psychiatric Co-Morbidity by ICU Staff </p>

<p>Results of ICU doctors' and nurses' detection of somatic 
and psychiatric disorders in their patients are shown on 
Table 6. Twenty patients were not evaluated by the doctors 
and 24 by the nurses. </p>

<p>Table 1. Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of the Sam-
ple (n=65) </p>

<p>Age yrs, x±sd [range] 
57.2±15.8 (20-92) </p>

<p>38 (58.5) </p>

<p>Gender (%) </p>

<p>Male </p>

<p>Female 
27 (41.5) </p>

<p>Marital status (%) </p>

<p>Married </p>

<p>Single </p>

<p>Widower </p>

<p>Divorced/separated </p>

<p>47 (72.3) </p>

<p>8 (12.3) </p>

<p>7 (10.8) </p>

<p>3 (4.6) </p>

<p>Professional status (%) </p>

<p>Retired </p>

<p>Active </p>

<p>Unemployed </p>

<p>On sick leave </p>

<p>35 (24.5) </p>

<p>35 (53.9) </p>

<p>26 (40.0) </p>

<p>3 (4.6) </p>

<p>1 (1.5) </p>

<p>Education (%) </p>

<p>Illiterate </p>

<p>No formal education </p>

<p>Basic education </p>

<p>High school </p>

<p>College </p>

<p>17 (26.2) </p>

<p>16 (24.5) </p>

<p>25 (38.5) </p>

<p>4 (6.2) </p>

<p>3 (4.6) </p>

<p>Living conditions (%) </p>

<p>With family </p>

<p>Alone </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>58 (89.2) </p>

<p>6 (9.3) </p>

<p>1 (1.5) </p>

<p>Main reason for admission (%) </p>

<p>Gastrointestinal bleeding </p>

<p>Pancreatitis </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>39 (60.0) </p>

<p>14 (21.5) </p>

<p>12 (18.5) </p>

<p>Alcohol intake above standards (%) 
21 (32.3) </p>

<p>Psychiatric history (%) 
18 (27.7) </p>

<p>On psychotropic drugs (%) 
16 (24.6) </p>

<p>Length of ICU stay (days), x±sd [range] 
7.2±4.0 [3-24] </p>

<p>Outcome (%) </p>

<p>Transferred to medical ward </p>

<p>Death </p>

<p>Other </p>

<p>35 (53.8) </p>

<p>2 (3.1) </p>

<p>28 (43.1) </p>



<p>Cardoso et al. </p>

<p>Doctors assessed the presence or absence of somatic and 
psychiatric disorders in 45 of their patients (69.2%), and 
considered that the majority (48.8%) had just a somatic dis-
ease, followed by 42.2% having a somatic disease with psy-
chiatric co-morbidity, and 8.8% having a psychiatric disor-
der with somatic co-morbidity. In those diagnosed with a 
psychiatric condition 17.8% were considered to have depres-
sive disorders, followed by anxiety disorders, delirium and 
psychosis. Diagnosis was not clear in 6.7% of the patients 
assessed. The mean severity of the somatic and psychiatric 
diagnosis in a 1 to 5 scale was 3.3 and 3.0, respectively. </p>

<p>ICU nurses assessed the presence or absence of somatic 
and psychiatric disorders in 41 of the patients (63.1%), and 
considered that the majority (53.7%) presented a somatic 
disease with psychiatric co-morbidity, followed by 41.5% 
having just a somatic disease, and 4.9% having a psychiatric 
disorder with somatic co-morbidity. In those diagnosed with 
a psychiatric problem, 24.4% were considered to have a de-
pressive disorder, 24% an anxiety disorder, and the remain-
ing delirium. The mean severity of the somatic and psychiat-
ric diagnosis was 3.4 and 2.8, respectively. </p>

<p>ICU doctors' and nurses' detection of psychiatric disor-
ders (all the patients considered to have a psychiatric disor-
der either primary or secondary) were compared with the 
CAGE results and the HADS scores (Table 6), and statisti-
cally significant relationships were found with the HADS </p>

<p>anxiety scores for both professional groups (p= .013 for doc-
tors, and p=.001 for nurses), and with HADS depression 
scores for doctors (p=.046). </p>

<p>Severity of psychiatric disorder assessed by ICU doctors 
and nurses and the HADS scores were analyzed using 
Spearman's correlation (Table 7). There were significantly 
positive correlations between both doctors' and nurses' as-
sessment of psychiatric disorder severity and anxiety scores 
on the HADS, and between doctors' assessment of the sever-
ity of psychiatric disorder and the HADS depression scores. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our results confirm those of previous studies in the fact 
that depressive and anxiety symptoms are highly prevalent in 
patients admitted to intensive care units. In this sample of 
Gastroenterology ICU patients, 29% had a positive score in 
the HADS anxiety subscale and 35% in the depression sub-
scale. These figures are higher than those obtained in previ-
ous studies: 24% for anxiety and 13.7% for depression in the 
study by Rincon et al. [4]. This difference can be explained 
by their inclusion of patients from different types of ICU, 
thus confirming our hypothesis of psychiatric morbidity 
higher rates in a GE ICU. It can also be related with their 
earlier assessment (first 24 hours). </p>

<p>As in other studies [4,7], the high rates of ICU depression 
and anxiety symptoms found in our study (27% and 25% </p>

<p>Table 3. Demographic and Clinical Characteristics of the CAGE Positive and Negative Cases (n=65) </p>

<p>CAGE 
Positive 
Negative 
Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>Gender (% males / females) 
31.6 / 3.7 
68.4 / 96.3 
Fisher's; p=.010* </p>

<p>Age, yrs, mean (sd) 
49.4 (15.2) 
59.2 (16.4) 
t=2.039; p=.046** </p>

<p>Marital status (% married / other) 
19.1 / 22.2 
80.9 / 77.8 
Fisher's; p=.743* </p>

<p>Employment (% active / other) 
15.4 / 23.1 
84.6 / 76.9 
Fisher's; p=.538* </p>

<p>Psychiatric history (%Y / N) 
22.2/19.1 
77.8 / 80.9 
Fisher's; p=.743* </p>

<p>Psychotropic drugs (%Y / N) 
12.5 / 22.4 
87.5 / 77.6 
Fisher's; p=.492* </p>

<p>Alcohol intake (%Y / N) 
52.4/4.5 
47.6 / 95.5 
Fisher's; p&lt;.001* </p>

<p>* Fisher's exact test; ** Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Table 4. Relationship Between Demographic and Clinical Variables and the HADS Subscales Scores, n=65, Student's t-test </p>

<p>Variable 
Anxiety, mean (sd) 
Depression, mean (sd) </p>

<p>Gender (M/F) 
5.2 (4.0) / 7.7 (3.6) (p=.012) 
5.7 (4.8) / 6.9 (4.8) (p= NS)* </p>

<p>Age 
Pearson's=-.200 (p= NS) 
Pearson's=.216 (p= NS) </p>

<p>Marital status (married/other) 
5.7(3.6) / .4 (4.8) (p= NS) 
5.7 (4.6) / 7.4 (5.2) (p= NS)* </p>

<p>Employment (active/other) 
7.1 (4.4) / 5.6 (3.7) (p= NS) 
5.0 (4.3) / 7.0 (5.0) (p= NS)* </p>

<p>Psychiatric history (Y/N) 
10.0 (4.1) / 4.7 (2.9) (p&lt;.001) 
8.7 (5.0) / 5.2 (4.4) (p=.007)* </p>

<p>Psychotropic drugs (Y/N) 
9.6 (3.5) / 5.1 (3.5) (p&lt;.001) 
8.4 (5.3) / 5.5 (4.4) (p=.030)* </p>

<p>Alcohol intake (Y/N) 
6.9 (3.6) / 5.9 (4.2) (p= NS) 
8.6 (4.8) / 5.1 (4.4) (p=.005)* </p>

<p>*Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Depression, Anxiety and Alcohol Abuse in a Gastroenterology Intensive </p>

<p>Clinical Practice &amp; Epidemiology in Mental Health, 2010, Volume 6 51 </p>

<p>respectively) were associated with a past psychiatric history 
and previous medication with psychotropic drugs. Patients 
with a psychiatric history had a 7.4 times greater risk of de-
veloping higher psychological distress (HADS total score) 
when admitted to ICU, while being on psychotropic drugs 
resulted in an increased risk of only 2.4 times. </p>

<p>Alcohol intake was expected to be high in this gastroen-
terology ICU sample, and the obtained rate of 32% of pa-
tients with intake above standard, and of 20% positive 
CAGE tests are in accordance with figures from mentioned 
studies [12,13,14,17] -24-28% in ICUs, and 44-51% in gas-
troenterology departments. CAGE scores were significantly 
higher in men, as expected. The sensitivity of the CAGE test 
(52%) was lower in this sample than the expected value of 
71%; however, the specificity (95%) was higher than the 
expected value of 90% [19]. The high cut-offs used for stan-</p>

<p>dard intake levels (40g for females and 80g for males) may 
explain these differences. </p>

<p>Compared to men, women presented significantly higher 
anxiety scores on the HADS but they did not differ in the 
HADS depression scores, contrary to the fact that women are 
usually more depressed than men in most studies. This result 
may be explained by higher levels of depression being asso-
ciated with alcohol intake above standard in our sample, and 
by men's higher alcohol intake. The significant association 
of high alcohol intake and depression (but not anxiety) 
scores found in this study confirms the well-established rela-
tionship between alcohol abuse and dependence, and depres-
sion [20]. </p>

<p>Detection of psychiatric disorders by the ICU staff was 
significantly associated with anxiety scores, as depression or </p>

<p>Table 5. Doctors' and Nurses' Assessment of Somatic and Psychiatric Disorders </p>

<p>Doctors (n=45) 
Nurses (n=41) </p>

<p>Cause of disorder (%) </p>

<p>Somatic only </p>

<p>Somatic with psychiatric co-morbidity </p>

<p>Psychiatric with somatic co-morbidity </p>

<p>22 (48.8) </p>

<p>19 (42.2) </p>

<p>4 (8.8) </p>

<p>17 (41.5) </p>

<p>22 (53.7) </p>

<p>2 (4.9) </p>

<p>Psychiatric diagnosis (%) </p>

<p>Absent </p>

<p>Depression </p>

<p>Anxiety </p>

<p>Delirium </p>

<p>Not clear </p>

<p>Psychosis </p>

<p>22 (48.8) </p>

<p>8 (17.8) </p>

<p>7 (15.6) </p>

<p>4 (8.9) </p>

<p>3 (6.7) </p>

<p>1 (2.2) </p>

<p>17 (41.5) </p>

<p>10 (24.4) </p>

<p>10 (24.4) </p>

<p>4 (9.7) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Severity of somatic illness, mean (sd) 
3.3 (0.8) 
3.4 (0.7) </p>

<p>Severity of psychiatric illness, mean (sd) 
3.0 (0.9) 
2.8 (1.0) </p>

<p>Table 6. Comparison between ICU Doctors' and Nurses' Diagnosis and the CAGE and HADS Scores </p>

<p>ICU Doctors Diagnosis (n=45) 
ICU Nurses Diagnosis (n=41) </p>

<p>Psychiatric 
Somatic 
Significance 
Psychiatric 
Somatic 
Significance </p>

<p>CAGE (% P / N)* 
76.9/63.5 
23.1/36.5 
p= NS ** 
92.3/69.2 
7.7/30.8 
p= NS** </p>

<p>HADS-A, mean (sd) 
8.6 (4.2) 
4.5 (3.2) 
p=.013*** 
8.0±4.2 
4.1±2.2 
p=.001*** </p>

<p>HADS-D, mean (sd) 
8.1 (5.4) 
5.2 (4.1) 
p= .046*** 
8.4±5.0 
5.5±4.2 
p= .057*** </p>

<p>* CAGE (case percentages Positive / Negative); **Fisher's exact test; *** Student's t-test. </p>

<p>Table 7. Correlation Between ICU Doctors' and Nurses' Assessment of the Severity of Psychiatric Disorder and HADS Scores, 
Spearman's Correlation </p>

<p>Doctors' Severity Assessment (n=45) 
Nurses' Severity Assessment 
(n=41) </p>

<p>HADS Anxiety 
rho=.495 
p=.001 
rho=.541 
p&lt;.001 </p>

<p>HADS Depression 
rho=.314 
p=.036 
rho=.201 
p=.208 </p>



<p>Cardoso et al. </p>

<p>alcohol abuse were not diagnosed. Although surprising, this 
result is not unexpected: anxiety symptoms can be more ap-
parent in daily contacts with the patients, and are more fre-
quently communicated, being more socially accepted and 
less stigmatizing than other symptoms. However, the number 
of patients not assessed by the staff, and related with rotation 
and shift work, can limit the reliability of these results. </p>

<p>The significant positive correlation found between ICU 
professionals' detection of severity of psychiatric disorders 
and anxiety and depression scores is a good indicator of the 
ability of these professionals to detect the most severe situa-
tions and refer them for psychiatric evaluation. These results 
are more favorable than those referred by Rincon et al. [4] in 
a coronary ICU, where there was no association between 
ICU doctors' detection and the HADS scores. </p>

<p>The current study has several main limitations. The fact 
that no formal psychiatric diagnosis was established and the 
use of a rating scale may have led to an overestimation in the 
results. Although severe cognitive impairment was an exclu-
sion criterion, non-systematic ruling out of milder forms 
could have the same effect. Finally, the small size of the 
sample, due to the exclusion of many patients, led to over-
fitting problems shown by the large confidence intervals. </p>

<p>Future research of psychiatric morbidity in ICU should 
address these limitations. The probability that large numbers 
of ICU inpatients are unable to collaborate in a psychiatric 
assessment can recommend the use of information provided 
by family members. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>We want to thank José Caldas de Almeida, Miguel Xa-
vier and Miguel Almedia for their review of the manuscript, 
and Ana Papoila for her valuable help with the statistical 
analysis. </p>



<p>Received: December 30, 2009 
Revised: March 25, 2010 
Accepted: May 13, 2010 </p>

<p>© Cardoso et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. </p>

<p>This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>