<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2386104" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Posttranscriptional regulation is a key aspect of gene expression 
and includes RNA surveillance, RNA splicing, mRNA stability, 
and mRNA translation ( Moore, 2005 ). In particular, transla-
tional regulation contributes to the spatio-temporal pattern of 
gene expression in animal development. For example, the ex-
pression of Oskar, which is required for pole plasm formation 
( Lehmann and Nusslein-Volhard, 1986 ), is regulated by transla-
tional repression via an RNA-binding protein, Bruno ( Nakamura 
et al., 2004 ). RNA-binding proteins are important in translational 
regulation, with critical roles in stem cell maintenance in pla-
narians (e.g., bruno-like protein [ Guo et al., 2006 ]) and mamma-
lian neural stem cells (NSCs) (e.g., Musashi1 protein [ Imai et al., 
2001 ; Sakakibara et al., 2002 ]). </p>

<p>The Musashi family is an evolutionarily conserved group 
of neural RNA-binding proteins that contain two RNA rec-
ognition motifs (RRMs) and has representatives in verte-
brates and invertebrates (for review see Okano et al., 2002 ). 
We previously identifi ed Musashi-binding sequences in mam-
mals ( Imai et al., 2001 ) and Drosophila ( Okabe et al., 2001 ). 
In the mammalian nervous system, Musashi1 (Msi1) is ex-
pressed in neural precursor cells, including NSCs ( Sakakibara 
et al., 1996 ). Our previous studies revealed that Msi1 con-
tributes to NSC maintenance by binding to the 3 Ј -untranslated 
region (UTR) of one of its target mRNAs, m-Numb , and re-
pressing its translation ( Imai et al., 2001 ). m-Numb encodes 
a membrane-associated protein that inhibits Notch signaling 
( Spana and Doe, 1996 ). Thus, Msi1 probably contributes to 
maintenance of the stem cell state by repressing the transla-
tion of its downstream target genes. In addition, Msi1 acts 
cooperatively with Musashi2 (a second mammalian Msi pro-
tein) in the proliferation and maintenance of NSCs ( Sakakibara 
et al., 2002 ). However, the detailed molecular mechanism 
underlying the Msi1-mediated translational repression has not 
been clarifi ed. </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>usashi1 (Msi1) is an RNA-binding protein that 
is highly expressed in neural stem cells. We pre-
viously reported that Msi1 contributes to the 
maintenance of the immature state and self-renewal activ-
ity of neural stem cells through translational repression of 
m-Numb . However, its translation repression mechanism 
has remained unclear. Here, we identify poly(A) binding 
protein (PABP) as an Msi1-binding protein, and fi nd Msi1 
competes with eIF4G for PABP binding. This competition 
inhibits translation initiation of Msi1 ' s target mRNA. Indeed, 
deletion of the PABP-interacting domain in Msi1 abolishes </p>

<p>its function. We demonstrate that Msi1 inhibits the assem-
bly of the 80S, but not the 48S, ribosome complex. Con-
sistent with these conclusions, Msi1 colocalizes with PABP 
and is recruited into stress granules, which contain the 
stalled preinitiation complex. However, Msi1 with muta-
tions in two RNA recognition motifs fails to accumulate 
into stress granules. These results provide insight into the 
mechanism by which sequence-specifi c translational re-
pression occurs in stem cells through the control of transla-
tion initiation. </p>

<p>Neural RNA-binding protein Musashi1 inhibits 
translation initiation by competing with eIF4G 
for PABP </p>

<p>Hironori Kawahara , 
1 Takao Imai , 
1 Hiroaki Imataka , 
2 Masafumi Tsujimoto , 
3 Ken Matsumoto , 
3 and Hideyuki Okano </p>

<p>1,4 </p>

<p>1 Department of Physiology, Keio University School of Medicine, Shinjuku, Tokyo 160-8582, Japan 
2 Genomic Sciences Center, RIKEN, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045, Japan 
3 Laboratory of Cellular Biochemistry, RIKEN, 2-1 Hirosawa, Wako, Saitama 351-0198, Japan 
4 Solution-Oriented Research for Science and Technology, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Kawaguchi, Saitama 332-0012, Japan </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
Two of these, migrating at 63 and 70 kD, were identifi ed as 
insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA binding protein (IMP) and 
poly(A) binding protein (PABP), respectively, by MALDI-TOF 
mass spectrometry. By immunostaining, we showed that Msi1 
was expressed diffusely in the cytoplasm, where it colocalized 
with PABP and IMP3 in P19 cells ( Fig. 1 B ). 
To verify whether Msi1 binds to PABP and IMP3, we per-
formed immunoprecipitation experiments with an anti-Msi1 
antibody and GST pull-down assays using tissue extracts prepared 
from mouse brain at embryonic day (E) 14 and 16, respectively. 
As shown in Fig. 1 C , the interaction between PABP and Msi1 
was less sensitive to RNase A than that between IMP3 and Msi1 
(lanes 3 to 4). These results suggest that Msi1 interacts directly 
with PABP, but indirectly with IMP3. This idea was supported 
by in vivo and in vitro GST pull-down assays using GST-PABP 
(Fig. S1, available at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb 
.200708004/DC1). In addition, the interaction between eIF4E 
and Msi1 was only weakly detectable in this assay, and that be-
tween eIF4G and Msi1 was even less clear. We therefore fo-
cused on PABP, as a protein that directly binds Msi1. 
We next used GST pull-down assays to examine the inter-
action between endogenous Msi1 and GST-PABP. Both Msi1 
and the PABP-binding protein eIF4G bound to PABP similarly 
in the presence and absence of RNase A. However, the co-
precipitation of PABP and eIF4E was sensitive to RNase A 
( Fig. 1 D ). Collectively, these immunostaining and binding experi-
ments show that PABP is included in a complex in which it 
interacts directly with Msi1 and eIF4G, and indirectly with eIF4E. 
To examine the colocalization of Msi1 and PABP in neural 
stem/precursor cells (NSPCs) of the developing embryonic neu-
ral tube, we conducted immunohistochemical analyses with an 
anti-Msi1 antibody and anti-PABP, eIF4G, or Sox1/(2)/3 anti-
bodies, using E14 mouse brain sections. Msi1 colocalized with 
PABP and eIF4G in the cytoplasm of putative NSPCs in the ven-
tricular zone (VZ) ( Fig. 1 E ). These results indicate that Msi1 
colocalizes with both PABP and eIF4G in NSPCs. </p>

<p>The C-terminal domain of Msi1 is necessary </p>

<p>for its interaction with PABP and </p>

<p>translation repression activity </p>

<p>To identify the PABP-binding site in Msi1, a series of C-terminal 
deletion mutants of T7-Msi1 ( Kaneko et al., 2000 ) was co-
expressed with Myc-PABP in 293T cells, followed by coimmuno-
precipitation. Immunoblot analysis revealed that two truncated 
Msi1 proteins lacking almost half the C terminus, 1 -216 ( Fig. 2, 
A and B , lane 10) and 1 -189 (lane 11), failed to interact with 
Myc-PABP. A GST pull-down assay ( Fig. 2, C and D ) showed 
that GST-Msi1-D2 and -D5, in which the region proximal to 
RRM was deleted, corresponding to amino acids 190 -234 (Msi1-
D2, lane 3) and 195 -234 (Msi1-D5, lane 6), respectively, showed 
almost no interaction with Myc-PABP, defi ning the PABP-
binding region. 
The N-terminal half of Msi1 protein contains two RRMs, 
which are essential for RNA binding, but the function of the 
C-terminal region has not been elucidated. To examine whether 
the C-terminal PABP-binding region is required for Msi1 ' s 
function as a translational repressor, we performed assays using </p>

<p>Translational regulation usually occurs at the translation 
initiation step, in which recruitment of the 40S ribosome to the 
mRNA is rate limiting ( Muckenthaler et al., 1998 ; Chekulaeva 
et al., 2006 ). Numerous eukaryotic initiation factors (eIFs) con-
tribute to translation initiation. One of these, eIF4G, is an es-
sential and multifunctional scaffold protein ( Gingras et al., 1999 ). 
It is a subunit of the heterotrimeric eIF4F complex, which asso-
ciates with the mRNA m 
7 G cap and facilitates ribosome joining 
to the mRNA ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). Two other components 
are the cap-binding protein eIF4E and the ATP-dependent RNA 
helicase eIF4A. eIF4G interacts with eIF4E, eIF4A, and the 
poly(A) binding protein (PABP), which stimulates initiation 
factor recruitment to mRNA and leads to mRNA circularization 
( Imataka et al., 1998 ; Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). The PABP -eIF4G 
interaction seems to be vital for effi cient translation, and it stim-
ulates the formation on mRNA of both the 48S and 80S ribo-
some complexes ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). 
Recent studies show that, in response to stress conditions, 
aggregates of stalled translation initiation complex localize to 
cytoplasmic foci called stress granules (SGs) ( Kedersha et al., 
2002 ; Anderson and Kedersha, 2006 ). SGs contain most com-
ponents of the 48S preinitiation complex, which contains proteins 
involved in translational regulation and mRNA. SGs containing 
microRNA are thought to be involved in mRNA recycling, and 
its shift to polysomes for translation or to docked processing 
bodies (PBs) for degradation in the cytoplasm ( Anderson and 
Kedersha, 2006 ; Tanaka et al., 2006 ; Parker and Sheth, 2007 ). 
PBs contain RNA (untranslated mRNA and noncoding RNA) 
and proteins involved in mRNA decapping, nonsense-mediated 
decay, and translational repression. Thus, although SGs and 
PBs are distinct RNA-containing granules, they share some 
components and seem to physically and functionally interact 
with each other. 
Here, we found that PABP is a direct binding partner of 
Msi1. A time-course reporter assay with the Msi1-D2 mutant, 
which lacks the PABP-interacting domain, failed to bind PABP, 
and revealed a correlation between failure to bind PABP and 
failure to repress translation. We also found that Msi1 localizes 
to the cytoplasm and accumulates in SGs under stress, where it 
colocalizes with PABP. Our results indicate that Msi1 inhibits 
the cap-dependent translation of its target mRNAs by compet-
ing with eIF4G to bind PABP, and inhibiting formation of the 
80S ribosome complex. Thus, we present a mechanism for se-
lective posttranslational regulation by the neural RNA-binding 
protein Msi1. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Identifi cation of PABP as an Msi1-specifi c </p>

<p>binding protein </p>

<p>To clarify the role of Msi1 in translational repression, we sought 
to identify Msi1-binding partners using the TAP (tandem affi nity 
puifi cation) method ( Rigaut et al., 1999 ). An Msi1-TAP fusion 
protein was expressed in 293T cells, and its associated molecules 
were recovered from purifi ed fi nal extracts. Several bands, repre-
senting proteins in Msi1-containing protein complexes, were de-
tected by Coomassie brilliant blue (CBB) staining ( Fig. 1 A , lane 4). </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identifi cation of PABP as an Msi1-specifi c binding protein by the TAP method. (A) Msi1-bound proteins that were extracted from 293T cells 
expressing Flag-Msi1-TAP were resolved by SDS -PAGE, visualized by CBB staining (lanes 2 and 4), and compared with those of control Flag-TAP-expressing 
cells (lanes 1 and 3). The bound proteins in the TEV-digested extracts are shown in lanes 1 and 2; similarly, those of in the fi nal extracts are shown in lanes 3 
and 4. CBB-stained PABP, IMP, and Msi1 are indicated with arrowheads. (B) Msi1 colocalized with PABP and IMP3 in the cytoplasm. P19 cells were stained 
with anti-Msi1 (green) antibody, and anti-PABP (red, top) or anti-IMP3 (red, bottom) antibodies. Nuclei were stained with Hoechst (blue in P19 cells) in the 
merged image. (C) Immunoblottings after immunoprecipitation with ant-Msi1 antibody using E14 mouse brain extracts were performed with each antibody, 
respectively. (D) Protein extracts prepared from mouse brain at E16 were mixed with bacterially expressed and purifi ed GST or GST-PABP fusion proteins. 
The GST fusion proteins were stained with CBB (lanes 1 and 2). Elutes were analyzed by immunoblotting using anti-eIF4G, anti-Msi1 14H1, or anti-eIF4E 
antibodies (lanes 3 -6). (E) Double-immunohistochemistry of Msi1 (red) and PABP (green), eIF4G (green), or Sox1/(2)/3 (green) in coronal sections of the 
E14 forebrain. Sox1/(2)/3 is a marker for neural precursor cells. Inset in E shows a low magnifi cation view of the main Msi1-expressing regions. CP, corti-
cal plate; IZ, intermediate zone; VZ, ventricular zone. Bars: 5 μ m (B), 50 μ m (E). </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
Figure 2. The C-terminal region of Msi1 that bound PABP is necessary for its function. (A) Illustration of proteins containing the T7-Msi1 variants: Msi1Amut 
(mutation in RRM1, and fails to bind mRNA: lane 2), Msi1Bmut (mutation in RRM2: lane 3), and a series of Msi1C-terminal deletions (lanes 4 -11). 
(B) Immunoprecipitation using the T7-Msi1 variants was performed and various T7-Msi1 mutants bound to Myc-PABP (middle). The intensities of binding with 
PABP are illustrated to the right of panel A. (C) Illustration of the GST-Msi1 variants. (D) GST-Msi1 variants or GST as a control were coimmunoprecipitated 
with Myc-PABP in 293T cells using glutathione-Sepharose 4B (middle). PABP bound to Msi1 variants was immunoblotted using an anti-Myc antibody and 
is indicated (middle). (E) The in vitro -transcribed reporter mRNAs are illustrated at top (left, mRNA containing MCS; right, mRNA containing MCSmut), 
were translated in RRL with equimolar amounts of purifi ed various GST proteins, and the luciferase activity was measured at each time point (0 -90 min). 
The values represent mean ± SD; n = 5. </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>quartz crystal microbalance (QCM) resonator, the Affi nixQ 
(Initium), whose oscillatory resonance frequency decreases 
linearly with the mass on the QCM electrode ( Okahata et al., 
1998 ). In this system, the action of an object binding to its 
ligand is detected as a decrease in resonance frequency (mass 
increase). Purifi ed Msi1 or eIF4G was immobilized on the 
Au-surface-coated QCM plate by binding the His-tag of His-Msi1 
or His-eIF4G to orient the molecules, and purifi ed GST-PABP 
in an aqueous solution was injected as the binding counter-
part ( Fig. 3 D ). The addition of GST-PABP (100 nM) to the 
reaction solution with immobilized Msi1, eIF4G, or eIF4G 
41 -244 resulted in typical frequency decreases, representing 
the frequency of immobilized PABP ( Fig. 3 E ). However, the 
change in individual resonance frequency when PABP was 
added to immobilized molecules that were not expected to 
bind it (eIF4G 41-244mut and Msi1-D2) was barely detect-
able ( Fig. 3 E ), indicating that the specifi c interactions of 
Msi1 -PABP and eIF4G -PABP were detectable by the resonance 
frequency curve. 
To calculate the association rate constant ( k on ) and disso-
ciation rate constant ( k off ), four concentrations of GST-PABP 
(25 to 100 nM) were individually injected into the reaction solu-
tion with immobilized Msi1 or eIF4G, and the time dependence 
of the frequency decrease was observed ( Fig. 3 E ). We analyzed 
these data by curve fi tting, according to the manufacturer ' s in-
structions (see Materials and methods for details). The K d value 
was estimated from the ratio of k off to k on . The results are sum-
marized in Fig. 3 F . The k on and k off were almost the same for the 
eIF4G (45 -1560)/PABP and eIF4G (41 -244)/PABP interactions. 
Although the constants for the Msi1-PABP interaction were not 
very different from those for eIF4G/PABP, the K d value calcu-
lated for Msi1 -PABP was approximately half that for eIF4G/ 
PABP ( Fig. 3 F ). Collectively, our data support the view that 
Msi1 can compete with eIF4G to associate with PABP in vitro. 
To investigate the in vivo signifi cance of Msi1 -PABP 
interaction, in vivo competition assays were performed as de-
scribed previously ( Khaleghpour et al., 2001 ). In this assay, 
the N-terminal portion of eIF4G (Flag-eIF4GN) was used for 
immunoprecipitation bait because its PABP-binding activity 
was stronger than that of full-length eIF4G in the QCM assay. 
Flag-eIF4GN expressed in 293T cells coimmunoprecipi-
tated with endogenous PABP ( Fig. 3 G , lanes 6 -10, top panel). 
The amount of coprecipitating PABP decreased dose-dependently 
when Myc-Msi1 was coexpressed (compare lane 6 to lanes 
8 -10, top panel), indicating that Msi1 and eIF4G directly com-
pete for binding to PABP in vivo. Together these data indi-
cate that Msi1 competitively inhibits the interaction between 
PABP and eIF4G through its PABP-binding domain. </p>

<p>Msi1 localizes to the cytoplasm and </p>

<p>accumulates in SGs, where it colocalizes </p>

<p>with PABP </p>

<p>To examine whether Msi1 and PABP colocalize subcellu-
larly, P19 cells were immunostained with anti-Msi1 ( Kaneko 
et al., 2000 ) and anti-PABP antibodies. Both Msi1 and PABP 
predominantly showed diffuse cytoplasmic staining; Msi1 also 
accumulated in discrete cytoplasmic foci ( Fig. 1 B ). We then </p>

<p>a chimeric reporter mRNA consisting of a 5 Ј -cap, the luciferase 
gene, 10 repeats of Msi1-binding consensus sequence (MCS; 
(G/AUUUAGU) derived from SELEX [ Imai et al., 2001 ]) or 
of a mutated Msi1-binding sequence (MCSmut; (G/AaaaAGU)), 
and a poly(A)-tail. The cap-fLuc-MCS-poly(A) reporter mRNA 
( Fig. 2 E , left) was translated in rabbit reticulocyte lysate (RRL) in 
the presence of buffered saline, GST, GST-Msi1, or GST-Msi1-D2. 
GST-Msi1 decreased the luciferase activity by ‫ف‬ 50.7% ( n = 5) 
after 15 min ( Fig. 2 E , left). The recombinant GST-Msi1-D2, 
which lacked the PABP-binding region, did not inhibit transla-
tion ( Fig. 2 E , left). In contrast, the cap-fLuc-MCSmut-poly(A) 
mRNA was translated in RRL equally well with GST proteins 
( Fig. 2 E , right). Thus, intact Msi1, but not Msi1-D2, caused 
sequence-specifi c translational repression ( Fig. 2 E ). These results 
indicate that Msi1 ' s interaction with PABP is essential for Msi1 ' s 
function as a translational repressor. </p>

<p>Msi1 can compete with eIF4G for </p>

<p>PABP binding </p>

<p>PABP includes four RRMs and a C-terminal domain (PABC), 
which contains a 60-amino acid sequence that is highly con-
served among species ( Deo et al., 2001 ). Each domain recruits 
several binding proteins and elicits diverse cellular functions: 
eIF4G binds to RRM1 and RRM2; Paip1 interacts with RRM1, 
RRM2, and the PABC domain; Paip2 interacts with RRM2, 
RRM3, and PABC; and GSPT/eRF3 binds to PABC ( Preiss 
and Hentze, 2003 ). To locate the Msi1-binding domain within 
PABP, a Myc-tagged series of deletion mutants in which the PABP 
functional domain was deleted (Myc-PABP and Myc-PABP 
variants) was coexpressed in 293T cells with Flag-Msi1, co-
immunoprecipitated with Flag-Msi1 ( Fig. 3 A ), and detected by 
immunoblotting with an anti-Myc tag antibody. Msi1 interacted 
strongly with the RRM1 and RRM2 of PABP, although the 
presence of PABC diminished the Msi1-binding activity of 
RRM1 or RRM2 ( Fig. 3 B , middle, lanes 1, 5, and 7). Notably, 
these results were similar to the binding pattern of the Flag-tagged 
N-terminally truncated protein (1 -585 aa) of mouse eIF4G1 
(Flag-eIF4GN) ( Fig. 3 B , bottom, lanes 1, 5, and 7), suggesting 
that Msi1 shares the binding region within PABP with eIF4G. 
Thus, Msi1 may compete with eIF4G for binding to the same 
domain of PABP. 
To examine this possibility, the interaction between PABP 
and eIF4G was tested in the presence of Msi1 by an in vitro 
pull-down assay, modifi ed as described previously ( Khaleghpour 
et al., 2001 ). Mixtures of GST-PABP and various proteins (GST, 
GST-Msi1, or GST-Msi1-D2) were added to Flag-eIF4G (41 -1560) 
immobilized on FLAG resin. After stringent washing, the bound 
proteins were subjected to immunoblotting with an anti-PABP 
antibody. Almost no PABP coprecipitated with FLAG resin 
alone ( Fig. 3 C , right, lane 7). Preincubation with 5.4 pmol 
GST or GST-Msi1-D2 did not interfere with PABP ' s association 
with Flag-eIF4G (compare lane 9 with 10), whereas GST-Msi1 
(1.8, 3.6, or 5.4 pmol) decreased the amount of GST-PABP 
precipitated. These data suggest that Msi1 and eIF4G directly 
compete for binding to PABP in vitro. 
To quantify the strength and kinetics of the Msi1 -PABP 
interaction, we measured kinetics parameters using a 27-MHz </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
Figure 3. Msi1 competed with binding of eIF4G to PABP. (A) Illustration of the PABP variants. (B) Flag-Msi1 or Flag-eIF4GN-(1 -582) was co-
immunoprecipitated with Myc-PABP variants in 293T cells using anti-FLAG resin. Notably, Msi1 and eIF4G bound to a common domain within PABP 
(middle, bottom). (C) In vitro competition assay between purifi ed GST-Msi1 and purifi ed Flag-eIF4G (45 -1560)-His immobilized FLAG resin. The 
CBB-stained, purifi ed fusion proteins Flag-eIF4G (41 -1560)-His, GST-PABP, GST, GST-Msi1-D2, and GST-Msi1 are shown (left panel, lanes 1 -5). 
(D -F) Analysis of the kinetics of PABP ' s interaction with Msi1 or eIF4G by the QCM. (D) Illustration of the His-tagged proteins immobilized on the 
QCM plate and GST-PABP. The His-tag proteins were anchored to the QCM plate by an anti-His antibody. (E) Curves showing the time course of the 
changes in frequency for the proteins coated on the QCM plate, His-eIF4G 41-244mut, His-Msi1-D2, His-eIF4G 41 -244, His-Msi1, and Flag-eIF4G 
(41 -1560)-His, in response to the addition of 100 nM GST-PABP. (F) Summary of the kinetics parameters for the binding of PABP to Msi1 or eIF4G 
on the QCM; for a more detailed description see Materials and methods. (G) In vivo competition assay using 293T cells expressing Flag-eIF4GN 
and Myc-Msi1. The quantitative analysis was performed with <rs id="software-1" type="software">Multigauge</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Fujifi lm</rs>) in C and G ( n = 5, mean ± SEM; *, P &lt; 0.01 vs. con-
trol;  † , P &lt; 0.05 vs. control). </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>the SGs ( Fig. 4 A ). We observed the colocalization of Msi1 and 
PABP at a frequency of ‫ف‬ 97% under stress, but Msi1 did not 
always colocalize with PB markers under normal conditions 
( Fig. 4 B ). These results indicate that Msi1 is recruited into 
SGs and is probably involved in SG function, in association 
with PABP. 
To verify the presence of Msi1 and PAPB in the mRNPs 
(i.e., RNA granules), we examined whether Msi1 and PABP were 
associated with heavy-sedimenting particles, using P19 cells. </p>

<p>investigated the colocalization of endogenous Msi1 with mark-
ers for PBs, Dcp1a and hRAP55 ( Tanaka et al., 2006 ; Parker 
and Sheth, 2007 ), and found that Msi1 colocalized with these 
markers in cytoplasmic foci in P19 cells at 37 ° C ( Fig. 4 A ), sug-
gesting that Msi1 also localized to PBs. Because PABP is a 
component of SGs ( Kedersha et al., 1999, 2002 ), we tested 
whether Msi1 and PABP colocalized in SGs under stress condi-
tions. After P19 cells were heat stressed at 44 ° C, we found that 
Msi1 colocalized with PABP (see Fig. 5 C) and with hRAP55 in </p>

<p>Figure 4. Cellular localization of Msi1. (A) Msi1 
localizes to cytoplasmic foci. P19 cells treated with 
(right columns; 44 ° C for 30 min) or without (left 
columns) heat stress were stained with anti-Msi1 
(green), and anti-hRAP55 (red, top) or anti-Dcp1a 
(red, bottom) antibodies, respectively. Nuclei were 
stained with TO-PRO-3 (blue) in the merged images. 
The white arrowheads and white arrow indicate 
PBs and SGs, respectively. Bars, 5 μ m. (B) Msi1-
positive granules were analyzed by two methods 
assessing the percent colocalization (1) or weighted 
colocalization coeffi cient (2) of their ratio to Dcp1a-, 
hRAP55-, PABP-, and eIF4G-containing granules. 
Msi1 mostly localized to SGs, but some was local-
ized to PBs. (C) Association of Msi1 with heavy-
sedimenting particles in an RNA-dependent manner. 
Each subcellular fraction with (lanes 4 -6) or without 
(lanes 1 -3) RNase A treatment after ultracentrifuga-
tion (top panels). S100, supernatants after ultracen-
trifugation; P100, pellets after ultracentrifugation. 
Total RNAs purifi ed from S100 (lanes 2 and 5) and 
P100 (lanes 3 and 6) are shown (bottom panel). 
(D) P19 cells treated with (left) or without (right) 
heat stress were separated by 15 -40% sucrose 
density gradients. Immunoblots of the gradient frac-
tions were probed using antibodies against the in-
dicated proteins (bottom panels). </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
Next, to ascertain whether Msi1 was included in a trans-
lational initiation complex, we further examined the intracellular 
localization of translation initiation factors, by immunostain-
ing. Msi1 and translation initiation factors PABP, eIF4G, and 
eIF4E predominantly showed diffuse cytoplasmic staining, 
and Msi1 and eIF4E were also detected in the PBs, and in SGs 
under heat stress in P19 cells ( Fig. 5 C ). Msi1 also colocal-
ized with eIF4E in cultured hippocampal neurons at 37 and 
44 ° C ( Fig. 5 D ). 
Several RNA-binding proteins involved in the regula-
tion of translational repression are known to inhibit ribosome 
complex formation ( Muckenthaler et al., 1998 ; Stebbins-Boaz 
et al., 1999 ; Ostareck et al., 2001 ; Chekulaeva et al., 2006 ). In ad-
dition, the 48S preinitiation complex is selectively recruited 
to SGs ( Kedersha et al., 2002 ). To examine whether Msi1 is 
involved in ribosome complex formation, 80S ribosome bind-
ing assays were performed with cap-fLuc-MCS-poly(A) reporter 
mRNA as described previously ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). The 
3 Ј -end 
32 P-labeled reporter mRNA and various GST proteins 
were incubated with RRL in the presence of cycloheximide, 
and the mixtures were applied to a 15 -30% sucrose density 
gradient ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ), subjected to ultracentrifu-
gation, fractioned, and the radioactivity of each fraction was 
counted. The addition of GST-Msi1 strikingly decreased the 
80S ribosome complex formation, to 52.7% ( n = 4) of the con-
trol level, represented as a peak in the 19th or 20th fraction, 
whereas the addition of equimolar amounts of GST-Msi1-D2 
had no effect on the 80S ribosome complex formation ( Fig. 5 E ), 
suggesting the Msi1 -PABP interaction is required for this in-
hibitory mechanism. Therefore, Msi1 inhibits the recruitment 
of the large ribosomal subunit onto mRNA, and the Msi1 -PABP 
interaction is probably required to inhibit the assembly of the 
80S ribosome initiation complex. 
To examine whether Msi1 also infl uences the 48S preini-
tiation complex formation on reporter mRNA, we performed a 
40S ribosome binding assay by adding GMP-PNP, an unhydro-
lyzable analogue of GTP, which blocks 60S ribosomal subunit 
recruitment, followed by sucrose density gradient analysis as 
described previously ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). We found that the 
48S complex formation, which was represented as a peak in the 
20th or 21st fraction, was unaffected by equimolar amounts of 
GST-Msi1 compared with controls ( Fig. 5 F ). Therefore, the 
Msi1 -PABP interaction did not inhibit the 48S preinitiation 
complex formation. Nevertheless, Msi1 is involved, through its 
inhibition of 80S formation, in repressing the formation of a 
functional translational initiation complex. </p>

<p>The intracellular localization of Msi1 </p>

<p>depends on two RRMs </p>

<p>Msi1 ' s function as an RNA sequence-dependent translation in-
hibitor and its requirement for PABP to carry out this function 
may correlate with Msi1 ' s accumulation in SGs under stress. 
To examine this possibility, HeLa cells under stress were tran-
siently transfected with the deletion and point mutants of Msi1 
described in Fig. 2 A and p3xFlag-Msi1-D2. All the deletion 
mutants -CdelG, CdelI, and Msi1-D2 (which lack the PABP-
interacting domain) -colocalized to eIF4G as clear marker of </p>

<p>Lysates were subjected to subcellular fractionation as described 
previously ( Aoki et al., 2002 ). Msi1 and PABP were detected 
mainly in the heavy-sedimenting particles in P100 fraction 
( Fig. 4 C , lane 3), with most of the ribosomes ( Fig. 4 C , bottom, 
lane 3). After RNase treatment, both Msi1 and PABP were also 
detected in the soluble S100 fraction ( Fig. 4 C , lane 5), suggest-
ing that Msi1 coexists with PABP in heavy-sedimenting RNP 
particles, which are likely to represent mRNPs. Furthermore, 
we investigated the polysome profi les in 15 -40% sucrose gradients 
using lysates of stressed or unstressed P19 cells. After heat stress, 
although some of the PABP was partly detected in the heavy 
(polysome) fractions, most of it was in the light fractions ( Fig. 4 D ). 
Msi1 and eIFs remained mostly in the light fractions after both 
conditions, and the fractionation pattern of eIFs coincided with 
that of a previous study ( Kedersha et al., 2002 ). These data indi-
cate that Msi1 comigrates with eIFs and PABP, and is likely to 
be involved in the regulation of translation initiation. </p>

<p>Msi1 is involved in translation </p>

<p>initiation regulation </p>

<p>Because SGs contain the stalled translation initiation com-
plex ( Kedersha et al., 2002 ), Msi1 ' s localization to SGs, its 
comigration with eIFs ( Fig. 4 ), and its binding to PABP in 
competition with eIF4G ( Fig. 3 ), suggested that Msi1 could 
be involved in the regulation of translation initiation. To ex-
amine whether the translational repression by Msi1 is cap de-
pendent, we added GST-Msi1 to RRL, using either cap, EMCV 
IRES, or HCV IRES to drive the translation of fLuc reporter 
mRNA containing MCS or MCSmut in its 3 Ј UTR before poly(A) 
( Fig. 5 A ), and measured the amount of reporter produced. 
HCV IRES-, but not EMCV IRES-directed translation initiation 
is also independent of eIF4G ( Pestova et al., 1998 ). In RRL, 
endogenous Msi1 is not detectable (unpublished data), but 
eukaryotic translation initiation factors and PABP are present 
( Imataka et al., 1998 ; Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). We found ‫ف‬ 50.6 ± 
3.0% ( n = 4) inhibition of the cap-dependent translation by 
GST-Msi1, compared with ‫ف‬ 27.0 ± 6.2% and ‫ف‬ 35.9 ± 1.2% 
decreases in the EMCV IRES-and HCV IRES-directed trans-
lation of the MCS-containing reporter mRNA, respectively, 
whereas GST-Msi1-D2 had little effect on reporter mRNA 
containing MCS or MCSmut ( Fig. 5 A ). We also conducted 
Northern blot analyses to evaluate the amount of reporter RNA 
(cap-rfLuc-MCS-poly(A) RNA) in each assay, and found that 
it was barely altered by the addition of the tested proteins 
(Fig. S3, available at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb 
.200708004/DC1). These observations suggest that Msi1 represses 
cap-dependent translation and exerts selective translational re-
pression through Msi1-binding sequences in the 3 Ј UTR of its 
target mRNAs. 
To investigate whether Msi1 is contained in the cap-binding 
complex, we performed a cap pull-down assay ( Stebbins-Boaz 
et al., 1999 ). Several Flag-tagged proteins, Msi1, eIF4G MD 
(middle domain) including the eIF4E-binding domain, and GST 
as a control, were expressed in HeLa cells, and tested for their 
ability to bind a cap analogue column. Immunoblotting with an 
anti-Flag tag antibody showed that Msi1 was included in the 
cap-binding complex ( Fig. 5 B , lane 6). </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>Figure 5. Msi1 inhibited the 80S ribosome initiation complex formation on mRNA. (A) Illustration of the in vitro -transcribed reporter mRNAs (top). The reporter 
mRNA and purifi ed GST-tagged proteins were incubated with RRL at 30 ° C for 90 min. Msi1 repressed the cap-dependent and IRES-dependent translation. 
The relative luciferase activity value represents the mean ± SD: ( n = 4; *, P &lt; 0.01 vs. buffer). (B) Cap column assay was performed in HeLa cells expressing 
Flag-GST, Flag-Msi1, or Flag-eIF4G-MD, which contains the eIF4E-binding domain. (C and D) Msi1 colocalized with translation initiation factors in P19 cells 
(C) and in cultured hippocampal neurons (D). Treatment with heat stress (44 ° C for 30 min) is indicated at the right (C) and bottom (D) of columns. Cells were 
stained with anti-Msi1 (green), anti-eIF4E, anti-eIF4G, and anti-PABP antibodies (red). Nuclei were stained with Hoechst (blue) in the merged images. Msi1 
accumulates in SGs under heat stress. Bars, 5 μ m. (E and F) 80S or 40S ribosome binding assay using in vitro -transcribed reporter mRNAs containing MCS-
poly(A). Curves show the relative radioactivity of each fraction from reaction mixtures supplemented with equimolar amounts of GST (purple line), GST-Msi1 
(green line), or GST-Msi1-D2 (red line), or buffer as a control (blue line). The percentage of the total recovered count was plotted against the fraction number 
(top panels). The RNAs purifi ed from each fraction are shown (bottom panels). These results were reproduced in three independent experiments. (E) Peaks 
(fraction 19 or 20) corresponding labeled reporter mRNA in a complex with 80S ribosomes are indicated with arrows (top). The peak of 28S and 18S rRNA 
was found in fraction 19 or 20 (bottom). With GST-Msi1 addition, the 80S ribosome complex formation decreased to 52.7 ± 3.0% ( n = 4; mean ± SD; P &lt; 
0.001) of the buffer control level. (F) Peaks (fraction 20 or 21) corresponding to labeled reporter mRNA in a complex with 48S ribosomes are indicated with 
arrows (top). The peak of 18S rRNA was found in fraction 20 or 21 (bottom). </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
PBs are sensitive to the natures of the mutant proteins them-
selves, and data from all the deletion mutants (CdelG, CdelI, 
and Msi1-D2) indicate that the C-terminal region of Msi1 plays 
an important role in its recruitment to PBs, probably via mol-
ecules that interact with this region. Also, all the mutants 
appeared to have little direct effect on the distribution of Dcp1-
positive PBs in an expression dose-dependent manner (unpub-
lished data). Collectively, these data suggest that an interaction 
with RNA is required for the appropriate cellular localization 
of Msi1. </p>

<p>SGs ( Fig. 6 B ). In contrast, the point mutants of each single 
RRM -Msi1Amut and Msi1Bmu -colocalized with eIF4G, 
while that of double RRM -Msi1ABmut (which cannot bind 
RNA) -instead accumulated predominantly in discrete aggre-
gates in the nucleus ( Fig. 6 B ). Meanwhile, under unstressed 
conditions, none of the Msi1 mutants in the PBs, except for 
Msi1ABmut, yielded intense staining patterns, compared with 
the wild type ( Fig. 6 B ). The intracellular distribution pattern 
of Msi1ABmut was similar to that under stressed conditions. 
These data suggest that the localizations of Msi1 mutants in </p>

<p>Figure 6. Two RRMs of Msi1 as a regulated 
modifi er domain of its cytoplasmic localization. 
Illustration of Msi1 variants that were modifi ca-
tions of the constructs described in Fig. 2 A . 
(B) HeLa cells were transfected with constructs ex-
pressing Flag-Msi1, Flag-Msi1ABmut, 3xFlag-
Msi1-D2 (1 -189 and 235 -362), T7-Msi1, 
T7-Msi1Amut, T7-Msi1Bmut, T7-Msi1CdelG 
(1 -234), and T7-Msi1CdelI (1 -189). HeLa 
cells treated with (44 ° C for 30 min; left pan-
els) or without (right panels) heat stress were 
stained with anti-Flag (green), anti-T7 (green), 
anti-eIF4G (red), and anti-Dcp1a (red, C) 
antibodies, respectively. Nuclei were stained 
with Hoechst (blue) in the merged images. The 
white arrowheads and white arrow indicate 
PBs and SGs, respectively. Bars, 5 μ m. </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>hibition of ribosome recruitment caused by perturbing the eIF4F 
(eIF4A and eIF4G) function induces SG formation without the 
phosphorylation of eIF2 ␣ ( Mazroui et al., 2006 ). In addition, al-
though SGs contain most of the components of the translational 
48S preinitiation complex, such as eIF4E, eIF4G, PABP, and the 
small ribosomal subunit, they do not include the large ribosomal 
subunit ( Kedersha et al., 2002 ; Anderson and Kedersha, 2006 ). 
Our present fi ndings suggest that Msi1 represses translation 
initiation, possibly by perturbing the function of eIF4G, and 
these events may take place in SGs under stress. That SGs lack 
the large ribosomal subunit is consistent with our model that 
Msi1 inhibits the formation of the 80S ribosomal complex ( Fig. 7 ). 
In addition, because two RRMs are required for the accurate 
intracellular distribution of Msi1, the localization of Msi1 may 
occur via capture of its target mRNA. 
PBs participate not only in mRNA decay but also in 
microRNA-mediated translational repression in response to stress. 
For example, this repression is reversed by HuR, which inter-
acts with the 3 Ј UTR of its target mRNA and depresses the re-
pression ( Bhattacharyya et al., 2006 ). As shown in Figs. 4 -6 , 
Msi1 also localizes to PBs, and it does not participate in its tar-
get mRNA decay (Fig. S3; Imai et al., 2001 ). It is possible that 
Msi1 is involved, via microRNA, in translational repression in 
PBs as well as in SGs. </p>

<p>Msi1 inhibits translation initiation in a </p>

<p>sequence-specifi c manner </p>

<p>The results of Fig. 5 (A and B) suggest that Msi1 repressed cap-
dependent translation but also modestly inhibited EMCV-IRES-
and HCV-IRES-dependent translation. Notably, Hentze ' s group 
showed that hnRNP K, which inhibits cap-dependent and IRES-
dependent translation, is involved in the inhibition of the re-
cruitment of the 60S ribosomal subunit but not of the 40S 
subunit ( Ostareck et al., 1997, 2001 ). Thus, these functions of </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Molecular mechanism of translational </p>

<p>repression and intracellular localization </p>

<p>by Msi1 </p>

<p>Here, we identifi ed PABP as an Msi1-binding protein, and found 
that Msi1 competes with another PABP binding partner, eIF4G, 
to bind PABP; the eIF4G -PABP interaction is required for the 
formation of the translational initiation complex in mammalian 
cells ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ) and for promoting the circularization 
of mRNA ( Wells et al., 1998 ). Therefore, we show here that Msi1 ' s 
function as a translational repressor of downstream target 
mRNAs is exerted by its competition with eIF4G for PABP. 
Recently, Paip2 was reported to act as a translational re-
pressor via competition with eIF4G for PABP binding ( Karim 
et al., 2006 ). However, the mechanisms used by Paip2 and Msi1 
to repress translation are different. Msi1 recognizes a specifi c 
RNA sequence (G/A)UnAGU ( n = 1 ‫ف‬ 3) with a relatively high 
affi nity ( K d value 4 nM) ( Imai et al., 2001 ) and represses the 
translation of mRNA in a sequence-dependent manner, as shown 
in Figs. 2 E and 5 A . Paip2, however, inhibits the translation of 
mRNA in a sequence-independent manner. Thus, we propose 
that the Msi1-mediated inhibition of the eIF4G -PABP inter-
action is a novel mechanism for the translational repression 
of mRNAs that are specifi cally bound by Msi1. 
Given that Msi1 physically and functionally interacts with 
PABP and that it colocalizes with PABP and eIF4G in SGs 
under stress, we propose that the PABP-mediated translational 
repression by Msi1 is, at least in part, the mechanism of transla-
tional repression that occurs in SGs. SGs contain aggregates 
of stalled initiation complex, and are thought to be involved in 
" the mRNA cycle, " which maintains an appropriate ratio of trans-
lation machinery to the amount of mRNAs being translated 
( Parker and Sheth, 2007 ). Recent fi ndings revealed that the in-</p>

<p>Figure 7. A working model for targeted translational repression by Msi1. Msi1 interacts with the 3 Ј UTR of its target mRNA and PABP, and subsequently 
inhibits translation initiation by competing with eIF4G for PABP. These sequential events inhibit formation of the 80S ribosome complex. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>

<p>
2006 ). The opposite effects of Msi1 on translational regulation 
in Xenopus may depend on whether xMsi is involved in cyto-
plasmic polyadenylation or not. The poly(A) tails of mRNAs 
expressed in the oocyte are often relatively short. Our model 
postulates that Msi1 participates in translational regulation by 
binding to PABP that is coupled with an elongated poly(A) tail. 
Msi1 may promote PABP stability by binding to PABP, and the 
stabilized PABP may maintain an extended poly(A) tail in the 
oocyte. Collectively, Msi could act as a bi-directional regulator 
of translation in a context-dependent fashion. </p>

<p>Translational control of stem cell </p>

<p>characteristics </p>

<p>The biological activity of stem cells in many tissues is regulated 
by translational and transcriptional controls. In particular, Msi1 
helps establish stem cell identity and/or the maintenance of 
stem cell status, given that Msi1 is strongly expressed in various 
types of stem cells, including NSCs ( Okano et al., 2005 ) and 
intestinal stem cells ( Potten et al., 2003 ), and its target mRNAs 
are involved in stem cell regulation. A recent report indicates 
that translational repression by Musashi is required intrinsically 
to maintain Drosophila germline stem cell identity ( Siddall et al., 
2006 ). Another group reported that the Msi1-mediated transla-
tional repression of p21 
waf1 mRNA is needed for cell cycle pro-
gression ( Battelli et al., 2006 ). These Msi1 functions depend on 
the translational repression mechanism revealed in this paper. 
For example, in response to environmental stress (e.g., hypoxia), 
cells, probably including neural stem/precursor cells (NSPCs), 
reprogram their translational machinery and sort mRNAs that 
are released from polysomes to SGs ( Kedersha et al., 1999 ; 
Stohr et al., 2006 ). Hypoxia promotes the survival and prolifer-
ation of several NSPCs ( Studer et al., 2000 ), indicating that 
NSPCs may elicit SGs and respond to stress via translational 
repression. In the present study, we show that Msi1 represses 
translation initiation under ordinary conditions, and sometimes 
repression events also take place in SGs under stress. Our previ-
ous studies revealed that Msi1 functions in neural stem cell 
maintenance by binding to its target gene, m-Numb , and repress-
ing its translation ( Imai et al., 2001 ), and that it is involved in 
the self-renewal of neural stem cells ( Sakakibara et al., 2002 ). 
Collectively, these results indicate that Msi1 is likely to play an 
important role in translation in the cytoplasm under ordinary 
conditions and in SGs under stress conditions, via its inhibition of 
translational initiation. In addition, the colocalization of Msi1 and 
eIF4G was high in the VZ (where neural precursor cells are 
dominant) but not in the cortical plate (where differentiated neu-
ronal cells dominate), in good agreement with our model, and 
these fi ndings lead to further research focused on the translational 
control of NSCs. However, the mechanism for the indirect and 
partial inhibition of eIF4G functions remains to be elucidated. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Vectors, buffers, and antibodies 
Details regarding the plasmid constructs expressing recombinant Msi1, 
PABP, and eIF4G in this study are available in the supplemental tables 
(http://www.jcb.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200708004/DC1). Buffers and 
antibodies used in this study are also described in the supplemental tables. </p>

<p>hnRNP K are likely to be similar to those of Msi1. Furthermore, 
a recent study demonstrated that domain II of HCV IRES is re-
quired for the 80S ribosome assembly process after 48S com-
plex formation ( Locker et al., 2007 ), which could be relevant to 
the repressive actions of Msi1 upon the recruitment of the 60S 
ribosomal subunit and HCV-IRES-dependent translation. 
Our ribosome-binding assays ( Fig. 5, E and F ) suggest 
that Msi1 inhibits the translation of the targets at steps between 
the formation of the 48S preinitiation complex and the forma-
tion of the 80S complex, which requires the PAPB-binding do-
main (D2). Relevantly, Sonenberg ' s group suggested that both 
the 40S and the 60S ribosomal subunit recruitment steps are 
separate targets of PABP, although their underlying molecular 
mechanisms remain to be elucidated ( Kahvejian et al., 2005 ). 
Thus, Msi1 could exert its regulatory function at some distinct 
steps among the multiple stages of translational initiation by 
binding to PABP. According to these previous reports and based 
on our present results ( Fig. 5, F and G ), we consider that Msi1 
is involved in inhibiting the formation of the 80S ribosomal 
complex through an interaction with PABP, without affecting 
the formation of the 48S complex. 
Thus, these actions of Msi1 on translational initiation dif-
fer from those of Bruno-Cup ' s and CPEB-Maskin, which in-
hibit the eIF4E -eIF4G interaction and the recruitment of the 
40S ribosomal subunit in a sequence-specifi c manner ( Stebbins-
Boaz et al., 1999 ; Nakamura et al., 2004 ; Chekulaeva et al., 
2006 ), but can be explained by one of the following four possi-
bilities. First, Msi1 might be post-translationally modifi ed and 
inactivated by factors in the RRL, rendering it incapable of 
binding PABP; an example of this is the Maskin -CPEB inter-
action, which is regulated by phosphorylation ( Groisman et al., 
2002 ). Second, Msi1 binding may be hindered by a unilateral 
PABP-binding protein like Paip1 ( Roy et al., 2002 ) or an un-
known factor. Third, to compete with the eIF4G-PABP, Msi1 
may need to recognize an accessible conformation of the 3 Ј UTR 
in its target mRNA. Most 3 Ј UTRs containing poly(A) tails, 
which bind to multiple PABPs, are probably too fl exible. Such 
structural flexibility leads to a situation in which Msi1 in-
completely inhibits the interaction between PABP and eIF4G, 
even if the number of Msi1 molecules on the 3 Ј UTR is greater 
than that of PABP. Indeed, Msi1 incompletely represses the 
translation of its target mRNA ( Figs. 2 E and 5 A ; Imai et al., 
2001 ). Thus, because the competition with the eIF4G -PABP in-
teraction by Msi1 may be necessary for the fl exibility and 
energy-requiring dynamic conformational changes of the 3 Ј UTR, 
no inhibition of 48S formation and incomplete inhibition of 80S 
formation may occur. Fourth, Msi1 may indirectly regulate 
molecules that are infl uenced by PABP and promote the 80S ri-
bosomal complex. For example, in yeast, the poly(A)/PABP in-
teraction inhibits Slh1p and Ski2p, which in turn inhibits eIF5 
and eIF5B, which promote 80S ribosomal formation ( Searfoss 
et al., 2001 ). To elucidate these events, further work is needed to 
clarify the relationship between Msi1 ' s function and the de-
tailed molecular mechanisms of ribosome formation. 
A recent study showed that Xenopus -Msi regulates the 
polyadenylation of multiple mRNAs during early Xenopus oo-
cyte maturation and activates translation ( Charlesworth et al., </p>

<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>

<p>and spun at 20,400 g. The supernatants, treated with RNase A or un-
treated, were precleared with protein G -Sepharose (GE Healthcare) for 
1 h at 4 ° C, followed by incubation with either an anti-Msi1 antibody 
(28 μ g/ml) or equimolar amounts of control purifi ed IgG (R &amp; D Systems) 
and protein G -Sepharose, and the beads were then washed extensively. 
The precipitated proteins were detected by immunoblotting. In vitro compe-
tition assays were performed in TC buffer without 1 mM DTT as described 
previously ( Khaleghpour et al., 2001 ). First, GST-PABP (5.4 pmol) was 
mixed with 1.8, 3.6, or 5.4 pmol of GST-Msi1 in 10 μ l of reaction mixture, 
and incubated for 1 h at 4 ° C. Second, the mixture was incubated again 
with 10 μ l of anti-FLAG M2 resin (Sigma-Aldrich) conjugated with Flag-
eIF4G (41 -1560)-His for 1 h at 4 ° C. Third, to remove unbound GST-PABP, 
the resin was washed three times with 1 ml of TC buffer. In vivo competition 
assays were also performed in TC buffer without 1 mM DTT, as described 
previously ( Khaleghpour et al., 2001 ). 293T cells expressing both Flag-
eIF4GN and Myc-Msi1 were homogenized and spun at 20,400 g . The su-
pernatants, with RNase A treatment, were then incubated with anti-FLAG 
M2 resin for 1 h at 4 ° C. The resin was washed extensively in 1 ml of TC 
buffer. Proteins were eluted with 2 × Laemmli sample buffer, and processed 
for immunoblotting. </p>

<p>Kinetics measurements by Affi nixQ 
Each of the His-tag proteins was immobilized onto the QCM Au electrode, 
as described in the manufacturer ' s protocol (Affi nixQ; Initium Inc.) and the 
previous studies ( Okahata et al., 1998 ; Sato et al., 2004 ). Measurements 
were performed under the following conditions: QCM Assay buffer-8, 750 
rpm, at 25 ° C. The binding between PABP and QCM-immobilized Msi1 (or 
eIF4G) was determined by Equation 1. </p>

<p>Msi1 PABP 
Msi1/PABP 
+ </p>

<p>⎯ → 
⎯⎯ 
← 
⎯ 
⎯⎯ </p>

<p>k on </p>

<p>koff </p>

<p>(1) </p>

<p>The concentration of Msi1/PABP complex formed at time t after injection is 
given by Equations 2 -4. The time dependence of the increase in mass is 
indicated by ⌬ m t . </p>

<p>Msi1/PABP 
Msi1/PABP </p>

<p>[ 
]= [ 
] ∞ − − 
( ) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>t 
t 
1 exp /τ 
(2) </p>

<p>Δ 
Δ 
m 
m 
t 
t = 
− 
− </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>{ 
} </p>

<p>∞ 1 exp /τ 
(3) </p>

<p>τ </p>

<p>− = [ 
]+ </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>k 
k </p>

<p>on 
off </p>

<p>PABP 
(4) </p>

<p>To obtain kinetics constants from the linear reciprocal plots of the relax-
ation time against the concentration of GST-PABP according to Equation 4, 
the relaxation time was used in the time range from 0 to 45 min. 
Dissociation constants ( K d ) were obtained with the equation [ K d = 
k off / k on ]. We analyzed these data by curve fi tting following the manufac-
turer ' s procedures. </p>

<p>Quantitation of colocalization in granules 
The ratio of Msi1-containing granules to total marker-containing granules 
was determined in Fig. 4 B . The percent colocalization (Fig. 4 B; 1) was 
estimated as described previously ( Barbee et al., 2006 ). The weighted 
colocalization coeffi cients (Fig. 4 B; 2) were calculated using <rs id="software-3" type="software">LSM Image 
Examiner</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Carl Zeiss, Inc.</rs>.). </p>

<p>Cap column assay 
Cap chromatography was performed as described previously ( Stebbins-
Boaz et al., 1999 ). Transfected HeLa cell lysate (supplemented with 0.2 mM 
GTP) was incubated at 4 ° C for 1 h with 15 μ l of m 
7 GTP resin (GE Health-
care) in TC buffer, and the resin was then washed extensively in TC buffer. 
The cap-binding complex was eluted with m 
7 GpppG (0.2 mM; Ambion), 
and proteins were resolved by SDS-PAGE. </p>

<p>Ribosome binding assay 
The 80S ribosome binding assays were performed with the following 
steps: (1) RRL was preincubated at 30 ° C for 20 min; (2) the RRL was then 
incubated with radio-labeled (3 Ј -end) reporter mRNA (0.36 pmol), equi-
molar amounts of Msi1 (3.6 pmol) or GST, cycloheximide (0.6 mM) (EMD), 
complete amino acid mix (0.05 mM) (Promega), RNasin (40 U) (Promega), 
and high salt buffer, in a total volume of 37.5 μ l, at 30 ° C for 20 min. </p>

<p>Screening for Msi1-binding proteins 
293T cells were transfected with a plasmid to express the Flag-Msi1-TAP 
tag or the Flag-TAP tag alone. After 2 d of culture, the cells were lysed in 
IPP150 buffer with Complete Protease Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche), and the 
TAP-fusion proteins in the lysate were purifi ed using the S é raphin Labora-
tory TAP protocol (http://www.cgm.cnrs-gif.fr/epissage/). The Msi1-binding 
proteins, the specifi c bands of which are shown in Fig. 1 A , were identifi ed 
by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry (Apro-Science). </p>

<p>Cell culture and transfection 
All cell lines (293T, P19, HeLa) were cultured as described previously ( Imai 
et al., 2001 ), and transfections of Msi1 variants, PABP variants, and eIF4G 
variants in 293T or HeLa cells were performed using the Fugene 6 transfec-
tion reagent (Roche) or Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen). Cultures of disso-
ciated rat primary hippocampal neurons were prepared as described 
previously ( Iijima et al., 2005 ), and then staining was examined in stage-5. </p>

<p>Protein purifi cation and immunoblotting 
GST-and His-tagged proteins were expressed in Escherichia coli strain 
BL21 and purifi ed by glutathione-Sepharose 4B and ProBond resin as de-
scribed by the manufacturer (GE Healthcare and Invitrogen) and the previ-
ous study ( Imai et al., 2001 ). Immunoblotting was performed using methods 
described previously ( Kaneko et al., 2000 ). To detect and quantify the 
probed proteins, ECL reagent (GE Healthcare) and the LAS 3000 mini 
PhosphorImager (Fujifi lm) and its software were used. </p>

<p>In vitro translation assay 
For the in vitro translation assays, luciferase reporter mRNAs containing 
the cap and poly(A)-tail were synthesized following the standard proce-
dure for mMESSAGE mMACHINE T7 Ultra (Ambion) after pT7-rLuc-MCS 
and pT7-fLuc-MCSmut were linearized with XhoI digestion, respectively. 
In this kit (Ambion), these capped mRNAs were synthesized by using ARCA 
(anti-reverse cap analogue; Ambion). Similarly, luciferase reporter mRNAs 
containing the IRES and poly(A)-tail were synthesized without the cap ana-
logue, according to standard procedures (Ambion), after pT7-HCV IRES 
rLuc-MCS, pT7-HCV IRES rLuc-MCSmut, pT7-EMCV IRES-fLuc-MCS, or pT7-
EMCV IRES-fLuc-MCSmut was linearized with XhoI digestion, respectively. 
The in vitro translation reactions were performed as described below, ac-
cording to the manufacturer ' s protocol (Promega). Each reaction mixture 
(total volume 12 μ l) contained: 8.0 μ l of nuclease-treated rabbit reticulo-
cyte lysate (RRL), 0.50 μ l of complete amino acid mix (1 mM stock; Pro-
mega), 0.25 μ l of RNasin (40 U/ μ l l stock; Promega), 0.28 μ l of 2 M KCl, 
0.075 pmol of luciferase reporter mRNA, and 7.5 pmol of recombinant 
proteins (GST, GST-Msi1, GST-Msi1-D2). The reaction mixtures were incu-
bated at 30 ° C for 0 -90 min, and the luciferase activity was measured 
at time points throughout the incubation period. To assay luciferase activity, 
1 μ l of the translation reaction was added to 25 μ l luciferase assay reagent 
(Picka-Gene Dual; Toyo B-net Co., ltd) and immediately measured in a 0.1-s 
reading using a Luminometer (Lumat LB 960). </p>

<p>Immunohistochemistry and immunofl uorescence 
The immunohistochemical staining of E14 mouse brain coronal sections 
with anti-Msi1 (Mab 14H1), PABP, eIF4G, or Sox1/(2)/3 antibodies were 
performed as described previously ( Okada et al., 2004 ; Tokunaga et al., 
2004 ). Immunocytochemistry was performed as described previously 
( Tanaka et al., 2006 ), and CSK buffer was used to wash before cells were 
fi xed. The stainings were visualized by AlexaFluor 488-, 555-, or 568-
conjugated secondary antibodies (Invitrogen). The digital images of cells 
were captured by a laser confocal microscope (LSM510; Carl Zeiss, Inc.), 
using in immunohistochemistry either a 20x/0.5 NA or 63x/1.2 NA 
water objective lens and in immunocytochemistry a 100x/1.45 NA oil or 
63x/1.4 NA oil objective lens. Image acquisition was performed with LSM 
Image Browser software (Carl Zeiss, Inc.). </p>

<p>Subcellular fractionation and sucrose gradient analysis 
Subcellular fractionation and sucrose gradient analysis were performed as 
described previously ( Matsumoto et al., 2000 ; Aoki et al., 2002 ), using 
P19 cells treated with heat shock at 44 ° C or untreated. Ultracentrifugation was 
performed using either the MLS 50 rotor (Beckman Coulter) at 100,000 g 
for 1 h at 4 ° C ( Fig. 4 C ) or a Hitachi P50S2 rotor at 48,000 rpm for 0.8 h at 
4 ° C ( Fig. 4 D ). The gradients in Fig. 4 D were then sequentially fractionated 
into 230-μ l fractions by a piston gradient fractionator (Biocomp). </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitation and in vitro and in vitro competition assays 
Immunoprecipitations were performed in TC buffer with Complete Protease 
Inhibitor Cocktail (Roche). E14 mouse brain was homogenized in TC buffer </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 181 • NUMBER 4 • 2008 </p>



<p>
Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows the specifi c interaction between Msi1 and PABP by coimmuno-
precipitation assay and GST pull-down assay using purifi ed proteins. 
Fig. S2 shows the biophysical analysis using a QCM-resonator, the Affi -
nixQ (Initium Inc.). Fig. S3 shows Northern blot analysis of the reporter 
mRNAs isolated from the RRL after in vitro translation in Fig. 5 A . The sup-
plemental tables include lists of plasmids, buffers, and antibodies used in 
this study. Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb 
.org/cgi/content/full/jcb.200708004/DC1. </p>

<p>We greatly appreciate our fruitful discussions with Drs. K.J. Tanaka and 
S. Yamasaki. We are grateful to Drs. M. Yano and Y. Okada for technical 
advice; Drs. T. Iijima, K. Sawai, H. Tada, S. Shibata, T. Yoshizaki, and T. 
Nishikata for help and encouragement; Drs. S. Hoshino and T. Katada for the 
pUC18-T7-R-luc-HCV IRES-F-luc plasmid; Dr. B. S é raphin and Cellzome for the 
pBS1539 plasmid; Dr. N. Standart for the pGEX2T-PABP plasmid; Dr. Y. 
Okada for the plasmid containing EMCV-IRES; Drs. H.J. Okano and M. Yano 
for several plasmids containing PABP mutants and pGEX6P-hnRNPK; Dr. H. 
Kondoh for the anti-Sox1/(2)/3 antibody; and Dr. T. Shimogori and Mr. T. 
Sunabori for information on the anti-eIFs antibodies. 
This work was supported by grants from the Japanese Ministry of Educa-
tion, Sports and Culture of Japan (MEXT) to H. Okano and T. Imai, the 21st 
Century COE Program at Keio University, and Keio University Grant-in-Aid for 
Encouragement of Young Medical Scientists. </p>

<p>Submitted: 1 August 2007 
Accepted: 18 April 2008 </p>



<p> 
A MECHANISM FOR TRANSLATIONAL REPRESSION BY MUSASHI1 • Kawahara et al. </p>



</text></tei>