<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2773253" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">Mobyle</rs>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Motivation: For the biologist, running bioinformatics analyses 
involves a time-consuming management of data and tools. <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs><rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs><rs type="software">Mobyle</rs><rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs>Over the last 10 years, an increasing number of bioinformatics tools, 
covering a growing spectrum of applications, including aspects of 
genomics, systems and structural biology have been made available 
to the community. The complexity of analyses undertaken in these 
domains makes the publication, integration and interconnection of 
these tools particularly challenging. 
Several systems propose a solution to automate the access to 
bioinformatics resources. Web-based user interfaces, such as the 
<rs id="software-35" type="software">Biology Workbench</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-35" type="creator">Subramaniam</rs>, 1998), <rs id="software-62" type="software">PISE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-62" type="creator">Letondal</rs>, 2001), 
<rs id="software-52" type="software">wEMBOSS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-52" type="creator">Sarachu and Colet</rs>, 2005), <rs id="software-114" type="software">Galaxy</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-114" type="creator">Giardine et al.,</rs>., 
2005), <rs id="software-130" type="software">GenePattern</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-130" type="creator">Reich et al.</rs>., 2006), MOWServ (Navas-Delgado 
et al., 2006), the <rs id="software-111" type="software">New Generation Biology Workbench</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-111" type="creator">Rifaieh et al.</rs>., 2007), <rs id="software-123" type="software">BioManager</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-123" type="creator">Cattley and Arthur</rs>, 2007) and <rs id="software-40" type="software">BioExtract</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-40" type="creator">Lushbough et al.</rs>., 2008), simplify the access to powerful computer 
resources by providing a familiar graphical-based environment for 
inexperienced users and by saving them from installing software on 
their own computer. In contrast with these tools which focus on the 
execution of programs, and where the users can often interactively 
chain analyses, <rs id="software-57" type="software">GBrowse MOBY</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-57" type="creator">Wilkinson</rs>, 2006) and <rs id="software-61" type="software">Seahawk</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-61" type="creator">Gordon and Sensen</rs>, 2007b) propose data-centric solutions where 
the user can explore a set of BioMOBY (Wilkinson, 2004) services to 
analyse a set of given data, with edition, navigation and visualization 
components which fully exploit the composite nature of BioMOBY 
objects. 
Standalone workflow systems such as Taverna (Oinn et al., 2004), 
Kepler (Altintas et al., 2004) or BioSide (Hallard et al., 2004) enable 
to combine tools within desktop applications, using graphically 
specified workflows. It is hence possible, for bioinformaticians, to 
organize and automate complex data processing. Such possibilities 
have also been offered on web interfaces, either in dedicated systems 
such as <rs id="software-27" type="software">Remora</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-27" type="creator">Carrere and Gouzy</rs>, 2006), or within some of the 
web-based systems cited above. <rs type="software">PISE</rs>, <rs type="software">Galaxy</rs> and <rs type="software">BioExtract</rs> also 
offer the possibility to save interactively designed protocols. 
Many of these systems now offer the possibility of accessing 
distributed resources, often using dedicated web-service solutions 
such as BioMOBY and SoapLab (Senger et al., 2003). While 
SoapLab offers a system to automate the distribution of 
asynchronous analytical services, the BioMOBY protocol provides 
in addition more detailed descriptions, including semantic metadata 
and a registration system to facilitate the discovery of relevant 
resources. A number of tools facilitates the publication and </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2009. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3006 3005-3011 </p>

<p>B.Néron et al. </p>

<p>management of BioMOBY services, such as <rs id="software-97" type="software">MoSeS</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-97" type="url">http:// biomoby.open-bio.org/CVS_CONTENT/moby-live/Java/docs/ Moses-generators.html</rs>) and the BioMOBY dashboard (http:// 
biomoby.open-bio.org/CVS_CONTENT/moby-live/Java/docs/ 
Dashboard.html). Many of the existing user interfaces rely on the 
descriptions provided by these systems to generate user interfaces: 
Ajax Command Definition from EMBOSS (Rice et al., 2000), 
BioMOBY or even pure WSDL definitions. 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> is a generic web-based framework. While including 
advanced technologies such as web services, remote execution and 
dataflow mechanisms, it addresses major end-user concerns arising 
from the use of sophisticated bioinformatics systems. A recent study 
(Gordon and Sensen, 2007a) shows how simple issues in the user 
interface can impede the use of a system by scientists, causing them 
to waste time and even preventing them from using it further. To 
address this issue, the design of <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs>'s interface is user-centered, 
to provide a usable yet customizable access to a large panel of 
services, from genome analysis to structural bioinformatics. The 
description language it uses to generate user interfaces is sufficiently 
extensive and flexible for rich user interfaces to be generated. Its 
core partly relies on concepts previously embedded in PISE and 
the RPBS portal (Alland et al., 2005). Moreover, different Mobyle 
servers can be federated to integrate services distributed over various 
sites. This functionality enables the federation of a network of 
curated portals, combining the skills of each of them. The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> 
program description language also enables to define web services, as 
shown by the <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> Mobyle companion tool, which automates 
the publication of BioMOBY web services, and has monitoring 
capabilities that provide the bases for service quality monitoring. </p>

<p>2 SYSTEM DESIGN </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> design process was based on a user-centered design 
process (Javahery et al., 2004; Letondal and Amanatian, 2004; 
Shachak et al., 2007), involving numerous interviews and a number 
of users workshops (see Section 4.1). We identified the major 
end-user concerns that needed to be addressed: </p>

<p>(1) An integrated bioinformatics framework needs to provide 
end users with several important capabilities: (i) reuse 
of data and results without the burden of unsafe copy-
and-paste operations; (ii) management of scientific studies 
(e.g. retrieving parameters of a job, comparing results or 
relaunching an analysis using different data); and (iii) access 
to a wide range of local or remote services within a unique 
user interface. </p>

<p>(2) A bioinformatics framework should enable scientists to share 
knowledge: (i) on setting up analyses, through tutorials based 
on curated examples; (ii) by accessing protocols designed 
and validated by experts in the domain; and (iii) through the 
use of a confidence network, allowing the interconnection 
of distributed resources, taking advantages of local skills 
to improve service quality, instead of favouring centralized 
platforms. </p>

<p>Technical requirements for such criteria to be satisfied include: 
(i) a well-designed web user interface, enabling easy navigation 
and data management within a user workspace; (ii) a distributed 
architecture, enabling access to and combined use of local and </p>

<p>remote services; (iii) workflow authoring and enacting tools to 
support protocols; (iv) sound software architecture and APIs, to 
simplify system maintenance, configuration and extension; (v) a 
flexible description language to enable domain-specific adaptation 
needs, including visualization of results using special-purpose 
graphics components. </p>

<p>3 SYSTEM OVERVIEW </p>

<p>In this section, we provide an overview of <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs>. We describe 
the underlying concepts of the system, the design of the web user 
interface, the server components and the distributed architecture. </p>

<p>3.1 Concepts </p>

<p>3.1.1 Homogeneous user interfaces to heterogeneous programs 
The steep learning curve involved in the use of command-line tools 
invocation is problematic for inexperienced users (Shneiderman, 
1983). A classical solution involves wrapping each application in 
a custom CGI script and providing a web interface to reduce the 
burden of remembering the syntax of the command line and the 
name of the parameters. Given the sheer number of bioinformatics 
software programs available, we chose to automate the generation 
of web interfaces using an abstract definition of a program's 
parameters. This solution provides a homogeneous interface to all 
the programs, minimizing the syntactic complexity. It is also helpful 
in file management issues and program chaining. </p>

<p>3.1.2 Persistent user workspaces One of the shortcomings of 
the <rs type="software">PISE</rs> environment is its lack of support for a persistent user 
workspace (Gilbert, 2002). The new system, while still allowing a 
fast and temporary 'guest' access to the programs, also gives to the 
users the possibility to create registered accounts, which allows user 
data and jobs to be maintained and managed across multiple work 
sessions. </p>

<p>3.1.3 XML description of interfaces Based on feedback from 
<rs type="software">PISE</rs> server administrators, as well as the need to extend the 
capacity of functionalities such as web service wrapping or workflow 
management, we modified the schema that describes the system. 
All <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> data, including program descriptions, job definitions 
and user workspaces are stored in XML documents. The main 
element of the system, the program description, is inherited from 
the PISE system. It describes various aspects, in a language that 
targets simplicity as much as possible (experience shows that the 
authoring and maintenance of program descriptions is a complex 
and tedious task). Aspects covered include: </p>

<p>• Program/service documentation: describes the accomplished 
task and guides users through the process. It also provides 
authoring and version informations. </p>

<p>• Data typing: characterizes the parameters and results of the 
different programs. Further details are provided in Section 3.3. </p>

<p>• Wrapping instructions: translates a user request into a valid 
execution of the program (e.g. in the case of a unix program 
call, the construction of the command line will be defined by 
rules included in the XML file). </p>

<p>• User interface layout: the layout of the program invocation form 
and job result pages are by default automatically generated from 
the XML definition, but can be customized. </p>

<p>3006 </p>

<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3007 3005-3011 </p>

<p>Mobyle </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Web user interface: portal overview, displaying the multiple alignment CLUSTALW submission form. The form in the main part displays a control, 
the databox, where the user can either paste data, enter a database ID or upload a file. The user can also select a previously uploaded file from the 'File 
bookmarks' menu. When available, results from previous jobs are also provided through a 'Results' menu. </p>

<p>• BioMoby integration: the XML files can be enriched with 
metadata such as BioMoby parameter types, which permits 
the publication of a program as a BioMoby service using 
<rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> (see Section 3.6). </p>

<p>A formal description of the XML grammar used to describe 
<rs id="software-63" type="software">Mobyle</rs> programs is available on the project webpage (see <rs corresp="#software-63" type="url">http://bioweb2.pasteur.fr/projects/mobyle/downloads.html</rs>), using Relax 
NG (Clark et al., 2001). </p>

<p>3.1.4 Network-enabled bioinformatics tools The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> system 
aims at acting as a 'hub' for a set of programs of interest. A program 
integrated in Mobyle can not only be local but also remote, using 
the Mobyle Net functionality (further described in Section 3.5). 
Additionally, current and future developments aim at providing 
gateways to web-service-based systems such as BioMOBY (see 
Section 3.6). The interest is to provide a unified framework for 
bioinformatics platforms maintainers, who have to publish and 
integrate various local or remote programs for both biologists and 
bioinformaticians. </p>

<p>3.2 User interface design </p>

<p><rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> provides the scientist with a global and integrated view of 
all the elements needed to perform his or her analyses. At one glance, 
the user can see which programs are available and which analyses 
have already been run. The portal is organized in three main parts 
(Fig. 1): a left navigation panel, a central panel displaying a selection 
of elements of the current work, such as forms and results, and 
horizontal tabs enabling the user to navigate between these elements. </p>

<p>3.2.1 Program search Available programs are classified so that 
they can be searched, using program and parameter names, prompts 
and documentation, or bibliographic references. The page that 
displays the results of a given analysis also provides the user with the 
list of programs that can be run for further analysis. This list guides </p>

<p>users, restricting them to a view of programs that are compatible 
with a given result file. </p>

<p>3.2.2 User workspace At any time, the user can navigate between 
previously used forms and details of individual analyses, for instance 
to compare results. This view persists over separate uses of the portal 
during a given amount of time. This navigation model gives a 'flat' 
multi-directional access to several forms, which was not previously 
possible with the classical browser history mechanism. A list of 
bookmarked data is available: this provides the user with reuse-based 
access and information on previously submitted data. </p>

<p>3.2.3 Forms and reusability Program forms are classical HTML 
forms. They contain a specific control element-the databox-
designed to facilitate data reuse by biologists. This control allows 
users to set parameter values for biological data (e.g. DNA sequence 
or 3D protein structure) using various methods (pasting, file upload, 
databank entry retrieval, bookmark reuse). </p>

<p>3.2.4 Results and interactive chaining The job status and results 
page provides a preview of the job data and metadata. It also 
includes an advanced control element-the resultbox-which lets 
users access results in plain browser windows, download them to 
their workstation, bookmark them or 'pipe' them to a new form, i.e. 
display a new form that is preloaded with the user data. This ability 
to pipe data into a new form, together with databox bookmark reuse, 
permits interactive program chainings within the portal. </p>

<p>3.2.5 Flexible layout design The portal, given a program 
definition, can automatically generate a form and a result page 
without any need for layout information. However, this process 
can be overridden to generate program-specific forms and job result 
pages with particular layouts. This possibility can prove extremely 
useful, for instance to fulfil custom program requirements, or to 
define a particular layout required for optimal use of a given program </p>



<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3008 3005-3011 </p>

<p>B.Néron et al. </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Web user interface: example of customised interface, showing the 
simultaneous display of a program output in both a text box and in a Jmol 
applet. </p>

<p>(see Fig. 2). This functionality relies on via specific layout tags or 
even HTML snippets embedded in the XML file, which can include 
inline javascript or Java applets. </p>

<p>3.3 Data typing and helpers </p>

<p>A major aspect of <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> is its capacity to facilitates automated 
data conversion and formatting for service integration, thus saving 
the user from tedious and non-scientific data manipulation tasks. The 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> typing system describes program parameters using a typing 
mechanism that aims to help users in such tasks. It modifies the 
interface display, the controls for user values (the input parameters), 
the possibility of chaining between programs and data reusability. 
Similarly to <rs id="software-101" type="software">SWAMI</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-101" type="creator">Rifaieh</rs> et al., 2007), data and parameter 
characterization is multidimensional: </p>

<p>• the biotype describes the biological object (e.g. nucleic acid, 
protein or drug); </p>

<p>• the datatype describes the data 'structure' (e.g. sequence, 
alignment and matrix, but also more basic types for 'non-bio' 
parameters such as string or integer); </p>

<p>• the format (blast html report, fasta sequence, phylip distance 
matrix). </p>

<p>The type of a data item or a parameter is used to: </p>

<p>• detect, check and convert the format of the data provided by 
the user, based on external ancillary tools; </p>

<p>• filter the available data sources (banks) that can be used to load 
data directly into a given tool; </p>

<p>• filter the data bookmarks that can be reused in a new analysis; </p>

<p>• filter the programs that a given result can be piped to; </p>

<p>• offer specific visualization options in the interface (such as Java 
applets) (currently in development). </p>

<p>In contrast with other typing systems, such as the one offered by 
BioMOBY, the parameter compatibility between two tasks is based 
on a more abstract description. Since the <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> system can convert 
the data to the format which is accepted by the next task, there is 
no need to have service interoperability rely on a bioinformatics 
format description. For instance, in the <rs type="software">Mobyle Pasteur</rs> server, </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Mobyle components overview. </p>

<p>the user can align a set of protein sequences using the clustalw-
multialign interface, then pipe the clustalw-formatted result to 
<rs type="software">Phylip</rs> protdist: although this program only accepts <rs type="software">Phylip</rs>-formatted 
multiple alignments, the <rs type="software">squizz</rs> program, which handles sequence 
and alignment conversions, will automatically detect and convert 
the multiple alignment into the accepted format. This approach 
simplifies the construction of the protocol: the user does not have to 
specify data transformation tasks, allowing optimal handling of the 
data (the format conversion information is directly accessible in the 
job result page). This typing system is configurable and relies on a 
'best-effort' approach. Tasks such as format detection or conversion 
are handled by the system only if they are compatible with the local 
configuration. 
This feature underlies the difference in what is considered to 
be a 'service' between <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> and BioMOBY: in Mobyle, data 
format conversions should be, as far as possible, considered as mere 
connectors in the analysis dataflow, whereas in BioMOBY they 
are considered to be on the same level as other analysis programs. 
Furthermore, since some programs accept multiple data formats as 
inputs, publishing them in BioMOBY involves registering multiple 
services on the registry (one per accepted format), whereas they are 
published as a single 'interface' in <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs>. </p>

<p>3.4 Components </p>

<p>The Web portal provides a unified access to the services available 
on the server which is briefly described on Figure 3. We use Ajax 
(Garrett, 2005) to coordinate required information and to enable the 
user to explore various functionalities on a single page. For instance, 
a user action such as a job submission triggers an update of the user's 
job list and the data bookmarks list. This event triggers an update 
of the history data available in the program forms, without the page 
having to be completely reloaded. 
The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> server, based on a set of python modules, handles 
the various aspects of job, data and session managements. The most 
important of these, job submission, includes: </p>

<p>• security validation of parameters and semantic validation (data 
types, range of value, compatibility between options); </p>

<p>• command-line construction; </p>

<p>• submission to an execution system, which could be local or on 
a cluster managed by SGE or torque; </p>

<p>• job cancelling or status querying; </p>

<p>• data management: all data needed to replay a job are stored 
(inputs, outputs, secondary parameters, etc.), ensuring the 
traceability of each job. </p>

<p>3008 </p>

<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3009 3005-3011 </p>

<p>Mobyle </p>

<p>Fig. 4. <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> network architecture. The Mobyle server can invoke either 
local or remote programs, integrating them in a single work environment. </p>

<p>The server also has a substantial capacity for configuration, such 
as setting program access permissions based on request address, 
user limit for space size and handling user account types (registered 
and/or guest accounts). All of these features are based on server 
administrator needs. </p>

<p>3.5 The Mobyle network </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> network allows the execution of programs that are 
available on different Mobyle servers from a single portal. This 
feature facilitates user access to services physically distributed over 
different <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> servers, within an integrated environment enabling 
data reuse and program chaining. As opposed to BioMOBY, <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> 
does not provide any central repository to register new services, 
relying instead on a distributed registration: each Mobyle server 
administrator chooses to publish a number of services, which can 
be upon his choice exported to or imported from remote Mobyle 
servers. Remote program invocation relies on the import of the 
remote program XML descriptions. Upon submission, this allows 
to generate a call to the remote server instead of generating and 
submitting a local batch call. In such a configuration, the user 
workspace, as well as the local jobs, remain stored on the initial 
server, but remotely invoked jobs are directly linked from their 
execution servers (Fig. 4). 
We demonstrate the use of this facility for the easy comparative 
modelling of the structure of a protein identified from analysis 
of the sunflower genome. A step by step tutorial is available on 
the MobyleNet help pages (http://mobyle.rpbs.univ-paris-diderot.fr/ 
help/MobyleTutorials_network.html). This task can be broken down 
into several successive steps: inferring protein sequence from the 
genomic information, performing a search for a template structure, 
fitting the query sequence to the template and then generating a 
3D model. Protein sequence inference can currently be performed 
through the <rs type="software">LIPM Mobyle</rs> server, using the heliagene resource 
dedicated to sunflower genomic information. The next steps can 
be achieved through the <rs type="software">RPBS Mobyle</rs> server using a two pass blast 
(PDBblast service) to identify candidate template structures from 
the query sequence. Sequence alignment can be performed through 
the <rs type="software">Institut Pasteur Mobyle</rs> server using the clustalw service. Finally, 
the 3D modelling and model visualization/analysis can be performed 
through the <rs type="software">RPBS</rs> site (Fig. 2). The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> network allows efficient 
organization of the complete sequence of tasks as a pipeline, without 
having to leave the <rs type="software">RPBS Mobyle</rs> portal, but making use of the 
resources and services at the three sites. </p>

<p>3.6 Deploying BioMOBY services from <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> 
program descriptions, using <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> </p>

<p><rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> is an external <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> companion tool allows 
the publication of BioMOBY-compliant web services, using 
Mobyle program descriptions. From the same XML description, 
bioinformatics programs can thus be both published on the 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> network and used by the code generator of PlayMOBY 
in order to implement, register and validate BioMOBY web 
services automatically. <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> also integrates a perl library 
to generate the corresponding <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> XML description file from 
program parameters. Thus, <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> reduces the overheads 
of publishing BioMOBY web services. To date, <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> 
handles more than 100 BioMOBY web services for providing 
generic sequence analysis tools and ensuring the interoperability of 
specialized databases (http://www.legoo.org, http://www.heliagene 
.org and http://narcisse.toulouse.inra.fr). 
In addition to web service deployment, <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> provides 
daily monitoring tools for the deployed web services. During the 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> to <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> format conversion step, a service developer 
can provide a test dataset for each service input. These data are used 
to test web services availability and consistency by the provider 
himself. We made the choice to not allow web services users 
to launch these tests, which are instead automatically launched. 
The tests consist in verifying accessibility to the web service and 
consistency and stability of the results on test data. Their results 
are published as XML reports and RSS feeds. The <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> 
description for the QoS presently follows the specifications stated 
by the <rs id="software-118" type="software">BioWorkflow</rs> group (<rs corresp="#software-118" type="creator">Wessner et al.</rs>., 2008). However, it could 
easily be extended to other frameworks such as the <rs id="software-25" type="software">BioCatalogue</rs> 
project (<rs corresp="#software-25" type="creator">Belhajjame et al.</rs>., 2008). In the case of failures or 
unexpected results, alerts are sent by e-mail to the developers. Thus, 
<rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> also provides the framework to evaluate <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> service 
reliability and curation. This problem is particularly important in 
bioinformatics, given the volatility of tools (especially web-based), 
impairing the reliability of biological data processing. </p>

<p>4 DISCUSSION AND PERSPECTIVES </p>

<p>4.1 System design: a user-centered approach </p>

<p>Over a period of 4 years leading up to Mobyle's first release, 
a series of about 30 user interviews and participatory design 
workshops involving brainstorming sessions and video prototyping 
were conducted. These were used to gain a deeper understanding 
of how a web portal could facilitate the use of bioinformatics 
tools by biologists. These studies are described in detail elsewhere 
(Letondal and Amanatian, 2004). The results showed the principal 
needs of biologists to be: (1) a stable and predictable set of known 
tools integrated in a portal designed for inexperienced users; (2) 
an overview of the analyses and careful organization of results; (3) 
reusability features to re-execute previous commands; and (4) user-
defined and ready-to-use analysis pipelines, similar to benchmarked 
protocols. We also concluded that caution should be taken regarding 
advanced features. Indeed, (5) biologists are often sceptical about 
sophisticated tools that are difficult to understand: they have to be 
able to anticipate the benefits that such tools may provide. 
Before opening the portal, we invited users to participate in test 
sessions. We selected 16 users among the users of the previous 
portal, ranging from beginners to frequent users, to participate in test </p>



<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3010 3005-3011 </p>

<p>B.Néron et al. </p>

<p>sessions. We used the think-aloud method (Nielsen, 1994), involving 
users working in pair. Participants were told they could bring their 
own data. Most of them tried 2D structure analysis, alignment and 
phylogenetic programs. Several users perceived the new system 
as more complex, but more complete than the current one. They 
appreciated being able to retrieve jobs results, particularly from the 
databox menus. Most of the concerns, which were consequently 
solved, were related to (i) having to navigate back and forth between 
forms and results; (ii) user accounting; (iii) not fully understanding 
some English terms (such as 'pairwise' alignment) used in program 
classification; and (iv) ambiguities concerning data storage. 
The <rs type="software">Institut Pasteur</rs>, <rs type="software">RPBS</rs> and <rs type="software">LIPM</rs> Mobyle servers have been 
publicly available since January 2008, October 2008 and January 
2009, respectively. The Pasteur server provides access to a wide 
range of bioinformatics tools mainly focused on sequence analysis 
and phylogeny; the <rs type="software">LIPM</rs> server offers access to tools related to 
plant genomics; and the <rs type="software">RPBS</rs> server publishes programs that mainly 
concern structural bioinformatics. Over 400 000 jobs have already 
been submitted by over 40 000 different users throughout the world 
on these servers. </p>

<p>4.2 Original contributions </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> project arose from the natural evolution of software 
such as <rs type="software">PISE</rs>, offering a simple way to publish and to share 
bioinformatics software on the Web. Program chaining is limited 
to the most common usage patterns that we identified, and does 
not provide any of the advanced workflow patterns included in 
previously described systems (<rs type="software">Taverna</rs>, <rs type="software">Kepler</rs>). It is not either 
intended to handle analyses of very large quantities of data, 
data transfer over the network being too costly for web-based 
applications. 
Several aspects make this approach novel: </p>

<p>• the simplicity of the interface, aiming to provide advanced 
functionalities without imposing the steep learning curve 
generally associated with complex systems. For instance, data 
can be directly uploaded onto the program form (without 
having to navigate to a separate upload interface) and the data 
format is automatically detected and validated. This simplicity 
is in the continuity of the PISE approach, with the addition 
of new features such as a persistent workspace and multiple 
functionalities to facilitate data reuse. </p>

<p>• flexibility in the design of the program user interfaces 
(submission forms and job results pages, as described in Section 
3.2.5) and in the configuration of the system. </p>

<p>• the <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> network enables the integration of local software 
with remote services, reducing the costs associated with 
the local maintenance of an exhaustive list of programs. 
Application of this strategy over several <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> sites should 
help to connect providers, generating a framework that 
emcompasses a wide spectrum of applications and covers 
complementary aspects of bioinformatics. This strategy needs 
to be tested for a large number of sites; however, we anticipate 
the generation of a confidence network combining specific 
tools offered by each platform and thus promoting quality 
management of the services. </p>

<p>• deployment of BioMOBY web services from bioinformatics 
programs is made available through <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs>. It thus benefits </p>

<p>from the conceptual strength of the BioMOBY architecture, 
while avoiding the duplication of wrapper authoring effort, 
using a common format for both Mobyle and BioMOBY 
publications. Additionally, it encourages good practices such 
as services monitoring by integrating the design of tests into 
the publication process. </p>

<p>4.3 Current developments </p>

<p>Workflows and protocols: <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> already embeds a prototype 
dataflow-oriented workflow engine, enabling the chaining of 
successive or parallel tasks to be automated. It runs on top of the 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> core library, exploiting the Mobyle network to execute tasks 
distributed between local and remote servers, and orchestrates the 
tasks to synchronize their execution with the availability of all their 
input data. 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> workflows modelize a set of tasks, but in contrast with 
existing workflow languages such as SCUFL in <rs id="software-72" type="software">Taverna</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-72" type="creator">Oinn et al.</rs>., 2004) or MoML in <rs id="software-85" type="software">Kepler</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-85" type="creator">Altintas et al.</rs>., 2004), do 
not specify explicitly some low-level data format detection and 
transformation tasks. Authors are, whenever possible according 
to local configuration, not asked to specify these steps. Hence, 
the storage of workflow definitions is planned to be based on 
an extension of the current <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> XML language, as they are 
based on a higher level perspective on the analyses they describe. 
An interesting outcome is the possibility to save an interactively 
designed program chaining as a reusable composite service. This 
perspective provides a gateway towards the publication of user-
acknowledged protocols on a community-based platform such as 
myexperiment.org (De Roure et al., 2007). Future end-user access 
to the workflow definitions and workflow engine will be integrated 
to the current web interface. 
Web services: the <rs type="software">PlayMOBY</rs> system already allows the 
automated publication of BioMOBY web services using <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> 
program definitions. Future work also includes enabling the use 
of other approaches such as custom SOAP or REST interfaces, 
and <rs type="software">SoapLab</rs>. Enabling the integration of such services as remote 
programs, for which the Mobyle Web Portal acts as a client will also 
be considered. 
Didactic tutorials: further developments will encompass the 
design of tutorials. As explained by Cattley and Arthur (2007), 
integrated web portals are a very efficient learning and teaching tool. 
<rs type="software">Mobyle</rs> additionally provides technical support for implementing 
interactive tutorials. A major issue to be incorporated in its design is 
to make more interactive components available: as shown by user 
studies, workflows should be available as semi-automatic protocols, 
with interactive components enabling the biologist to customize the 
visualization of the result from an analysis (e.g. a 3D molecule or 
an alignment). </p>

<p>5 CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The design of <rs type="software">Mobyle</rs>, which provides an effective way to 
make a large panel of curated bioinformatics tools available in 
a homogeneous environment, has been driven with the concern 
to meet the requirements of different audiences-biologists and 
bioinformaticians, mostly. Our objective was thus to facilitate the 
access to complex features and advanced technologies by a design </p>



<p>[09:28 4/11/2009 Bioinformatics-btp493.tex] </p>

<p>Page: 3011 3005-3011 </p>

<p>Mobyle </p>

<p>that suits the work of biologists, which we were able to observe and 
understand during a number of interviews and workshops. </p>

<p>Funding: the Agence Nationale de la Recherche (GPLA06026G 
ANR Genoplante, to PlayMOBY project ). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: none declared. </p>





</text></tei>