<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2447807" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:27+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>In plants, short RNAs including » 21-nt microRNA 
(miRNA) and 21-nt trans-acting siRNA (ta-siRNA) 
compose a 'miRNA ! ta-siRNA ! target gene' 
cascade pathway that regulates gene expression at 
the posttranscriptional level. In this cascade, bio-
genesis of ta-siRNA clusters requires 21-nt intervals 
(i.e. phasing) and miRNA (phase-initiator) cleavage 
sites on its TAS transcript. Here, we report a novel 
web server, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs>, which is developed to 
identify both the clusters of phased small RNAs as 
well as the potential phase-initiator. To detect 
phased small RNA clusters, the <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> maps 
input small RNAs against user-specified transcript/ 
genomic sequences, and then identifies phased 
small RNA clusters by evaluating P-values of hyper-
geometric distribution. To identify potential phase-
initiators, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> aligns input phase-initiators 
with transcripts of TAS candidates using the Smith-
Waterman algorithm. Potential cleavage sites on TAS 
candidates are further identified from complemen-
tary regions by weighting the alignment expectation 
and its distance to detected phased small RNA 
clusters. The <rs id="software-7" type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> web server is freely 
available at <rs corresp="#software-7" type="url">http://bioinfo3.noble.org/pssRNAMiner/</rs>/. </p>

<p>In plants, small regulatory RNAs including miRNAs, 
heterochromatic siRNAs (hc-siRNAs), repeat-associated 
siRNAs (ra-siRNAs), natural sense-antisense transcript 
siRNAs and trans-acting siRNAs (ta-siRNAs) are 
involved in regulating gene expression through various 
mechanisms (1). Recent studies have demonstrated that 
these various small RNA molecules, in combination with 
cellular transcription factors, form the basis of network 
responsible for regulating the cellular gene expression. 
The ta-siRNA, a newly identified class of 21-nt short 
siRNAs, play an essential role in bridging the miRNA and 
siRNA pathways, which were previously believed to be </p>

<p>two independent processes (2-5). Phase-initiators direct 
the cleavage of ta-siRNA gene (TAS) primary transcripts 
(precursors) and subsequently initiate the production 
of ta-siRNA clusters (4). To date, only a few known 
phase-initiators are ta-siRNAs as most of reported phase-
initiators are miRNAs. Following cleavage of the pre-
cursor, the 3 0 (or 5 0 )-cleavage products are converted into 
double-stranded RNA (dsRNA) by RDR6 and SGS3. The 
dsRNA is then processed into 21-nt increments, relative to 
the original cleavage site on both strands, by DCL4 in 
order to produce ta-siRNA clusters (3,4). The ta-siRNAs 
form an essential component of the RISC complex 
responsible for guiding AGO-dependent cleavage of the 
target transcript. Based on these data, several researchers 
have proposed a 'miRNA ! ta-siRNA ! target gene' 
cleavage cascade as an element of gene regulatory network 
in the model plant Arabidopsis (4-7). In this paper, we 
describe the development of the <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs>, a plant 
short small RNA regulatory cascade analysis server that is 
able to identify potential ta-siRNAs clusters and their 
phase-initiators. 
While miRNA biogenesis is dependent on the hairpin 
structure of the precursor, the formation of siRNA 
molecules occurs as a result of the processing of dsRNA 
by RNA-dependent RNA polymerases (RDRs). There-
fore, as compared to miRNA, there is no effective 
computational approach to identify siRNAs from either 
genomic or transcript sequence. Since 21-nt phased 
ta-siRNAs are generated from TAS precursors, it is 
possible to map known small RNA molecules to candidate 
TAS precursors and then cluster these small RNAs based 
on their 21-nt phase properties (8,9). By evaluating the 
P-value of phase features, Chen et al. (6) identified and 
validated a number of known, and several previously 
unknown, ta-siRNA clusters as well as the associated TAS 
gene loci in Arabidopsis. 
TAS precursors require at least one valid cleavage site, 
which is targeted by a phase-initiator to generate ta-
siRNAs. While some TAS genes possess multiple regions 
that are complementary with the phase-initiator, only 
one region effectively guides cleavage in vivo. A 'two-hit 
trigger' mechanism was recently proposed to correlate the 
number of complementary regions with the activity of </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 580 224 6725; Fax: +1 580 224 6692; Email: pzhao@noble.org </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>phased-initiators based on evidences from studies per-
formed in moss and Arabidopsis (7). Therefore, it is 
anticipated that analysis of both complementary regions 
as well as valid cleavage sites in TAS candidate precursors 
would facilitate screening of phased small RNA clusters. 
In this study, we describe the development of 
<rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs>, a web-based server which identifies 
ta-siRNA clusters as well as their potential phase-
initiators. This program requires that the user submit a 
set of small RNAs and specify one of listed transcript/ 
genomic libraries for mapping. To identify phase-
initiators, the user must submit at least one small RNA 
as candidate phase initiator. The <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> is able to 
identify phased small RNA clusters as ta-siRNA candi-
dates by evaluating the P-values of hypergeometric 
distribution. Furthermore, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> has the ability 
to identify potential phase-initiators based on the user 
input. To date, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> hosts 29 transcript/ 
genomic sequence libraries from 20 species. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Detection of phased small RNA clusters </p>

<p>The pssRNAMiner improves a previously described 
method of evaluating the P-value of random hypergeo-
metric distribution to detect phased small RNA clusters 
(6). First, pssRNAMiner maps the input small RNAs on 
transcript sequences and records each position. Then, as 
described by Chen et al. (6), the algorithm slides on both 
strands of the transcript sequence to search each mapped 
small RNA and count the number of phased/nonphased 
positions with small RNA hits in a 231 bp region 
downstream of the 5 0 start site of the small RNA. 
Equations (1) and (2), revised from Chen et al. (6), are 
used to calculate the P-value of phased small RNA 
clusters on the basis of a random hypergeometric 
distribution. Since the cleavage of phased small RNAs 
often occurs within 1-2 nt of the phased positions (8), we 
introduced a variable, s, in Equation (1) to reflect this 
shift. The addition of this variable will have the added 
effect of reducing the total number of nonphased position 
within the 231 bp region. </p>

<p>PrðX ¼ kÞ ¼ </p>

<p>400 À 21 Â 2 Â s 
n À k </p>



<p>21 
k </p>



<p>461 À 21 Â 2 Â s 
n </p>



<p>1 </p>

<p>n: Number of total positions having small RNA hits in 
231-bp region; 
k: Number of phase positions having small RNA hits in 
231-bp region; 
s: Maximum allowed offset from phase position </p>

<p>P-value : pðkÞ ¼ 
X minðn, 21Þ </p>

<p>X¼k </p>

<p>PrðXÞ 
2 </p>

<p>Analysis of cleavage sites guided by phase-initiator </p>

<p>In addition to detecting phased small RNA clusters, 
pssRNAMiner has the ability to predict whether the input </p>

<p>candidate phase-initiators have the potential to guide 
the cleavage of TAS candidate precursors and trigger the 
biogenesis of phased small RNA clusters identified in the 
first step. 
To perform this analysis, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> first searches 
the complementary regions between the phase-initiator 
and TAS candidate precursor using the Smith-Waterman 
algorithm (10). It then ranks the alignment of comple-
mentary regions based on a scoring scheme described by 
Zhang (11,12). Since the Smith-Waterman algorithm is 
only able to identify the optimal alignment for each pair of 
query/target sequences, an iterative algorithm has been 
developed to obtain as many complementary regions as 
possible. During each iteration, the identified complemen-
tary region of the precursor sequences are masked by 
'N' letters for the next iterative search until no further 
complementary region(s) can be identified in a given 
query/target sequence. 
Next, the server identifies whether these complementary 
regions have valid cleavage sites, which can result in the 
production of phased small RNA clusters. We applied two 
conditions in this analysis. First, the user-defined cleavage 
site in the complementary region must be located within a 
region calculated by ½B 1 À D,B 2 þ D, where B 1 , start 
position of phased small RNA cluster on the TAS 
precursor; B 2 , end position of phased small RNA cluster; 
D, a user-specific maximum distance between cleavage site 
and start site of small RNA cluster. Second, the distance 
between the cleavage site and start site of the small RNA 
cluster must meet the 21-nt phase property (i.e. multiples 
of 21 nt). </p>

<p>Architecture and implementation of <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> </p>

<p>The <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> consists of two independent compo-
nents, a backend pipeline that is responsible for directing 
the core functions and a web server. The core functions, 
which include the calculation of the P-value and analysis 
of cleavage sites directed by the phase-initiator, are 
performed by the backend pipeline written in <rs type="software">Java</rs> and 
<rs type="software">PERL</rs>. To perform a search for complementary regions, 
a third party software <rs type="software">ssearch</rs> has been used for Smith-
Waterman alignment. The web server was developed on 
top of a SQLite database. Scripts used to generate web 
interfaces and search results were written in <rs type="software">PHP</rs>. </p>

<p>USER INTERFACES </p>

<p>To identify 21-nt phased small RNA clusters as ta-siRNA 
candidates from the existing small RNA dataset, the user 
is required to submit small RNA sequences in either a 
simple sequence format or multi-FASTA format. The 
pssRNAMiner is able to recognize small RNA sequences 
between 17 and 28 nt in length but more readily identifies 
sequences of 21 nt in length. In addition, the user needs 
to specify a transcript/genomic library for mapping 
(Figure 1a). Following submission, pssRNAMiner maps 
each of the small RNAs onto the transcript/genomic 
sequence and then, calculates a P-value, in order to 
evaluate the potential phased small RNA cluster. The 
pssRNAMiner lists the candidate clusters having P-values </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W115 </p>

<p>lower than a user specified cutoff threshold (Figure 2a). 
The list view page enables the use of a filtering/searching 
function, in order to remove false positive clusters, such as 
transposon or ribosomal RNAs. In addition, this function 
enables the user to list only those clusters of interest by 
filtering based on specific annotation keywords or IDs. 
The users can further inspect the details of each cluster, 
including phased/nonphased small RNA sequences, the 
location of small RNAs on TAS candidate precursors, 
functional annotation of TAS candidate and valid 
cleavage site, etc. by clicking on the individual cluster 
ID for a detailed view (Figure 2b and c). The users are able 
to further check potential target sequences of these 
detected ta-siRNA candidates by clicking 'search' at the 
end of detailed view. 
Based on user preferences, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> can also 
identify potential cleavage site guided by phase-initiator 
on TAS candidate precursor. For <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> to per-
form this function, it is necessary for the user to submit 
potential phase-initiators in multi-FASTA format and 
specify the maximum expectation for screening the 
complementary region between the phase-initiators and 
TAS candidate precursors. In addition, it is necessary for </p>

<p>the user to specify the expected cleavage range in the 
complementary region (generally between 9 and 11 nt on 
miRNA sequence) (Figure 1b). After submission, the 
server aligns input phase-initiators with TAS candidate 
precursors to locate complementary regions. Next, the 
server searches valid cleavage sites from the complemen-
tary regions based on the distance between the cleavage 
site and the phased small RNA clusters and output a web 
page that lists clusters with cleavage site information 
(Figure 2a-c). 
To demonstrate the effectiveness of <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> and 
to facilitate its use, we have integrated a number of 
published small RNA datasets into pssRNAMiner. These 
data can be found under the 'dataset' sub-menu. Each 
dataset has been pre-run against their corresponding 
transcript/genomic sequences, and therefore users may 
click links on the right-hand column of dataset table to 
view these precalculated results. </p>

<p>PERFORMANCE </p>

<p>Finally, to evaluate the performance of <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs>, 
we downloaded RDR small RNA MPSS libraries from the </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>Figure 1. (a) Input interface for searching phased small RNA clusters. (b) Input interface for optional identification of phase-initiator for detected 
small RNA clusters. </p>

<p>W116 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue </p>

<p>(a) </p>

<p>(b) </p>

<p>(c) </p>

<p>Figure 2. (a) Output: list view of phased small RNA clusters with phase-initiator cleavage sites on TAS candidate. (b) Output: detailed view of a 
specific phased small RNA clusters with phase-initiator cleavage sites on a TAS candidate. (c) Output: detailed view of the alignment of specific 
phased small RNA clusters with phase-initiator cleavage sites on a TAS candidate. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W117 </p>

<p>Arabidopsis MPSS Plus database (http://mpss.udel.edu/ 
at/) (13,14). A total of 11 767 distinct small RNA signa-
tures were analyzed based on the Arabidopsis TAIR7 
cDNA release (ftp://ftp.arabidopsis.org/home/tair/Genes/ 
TAIR7_genome_release/). When these data were investi-
gated, <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> detected 124 significantly phased 
small RNA clusters (P &lt; 0.005) at 19 gene loci. Moreover, 
pssRNAMiner detected all the reported ta-siRNA gene loci 
with significant P-value, including TAS1a (AT2G27400), 
TAS1b (AT1G50055), TAS1c (AT2G39675), TAS2 
(AT2G39681), TAS3a (AT3G17185) and PPR proteins 
(AT1G63080 and AT1G63130) (see Supplementary 
Material for the list of detected phased RNA clusters and 
gene loci). To investigate the ability of <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> to 
identify valid cleavage site of phase-initiators, a reported 
phase-initiator, miRNA 'ath-miR390', was submitted for 
cleavage site analysis on TAS candidate precursors. The 
pssRNAMiner reported two complementary regions 
(expectation 5) with one region having a valid cleavage 
site on TAS3a. These results are consistent with previously 
published studies that demonstrated that the ath-miR390 
initiates production of phased small RNA clusters on 
TAS3a by guiding precursor cleavage (2,4) (see detailed 
alignment in the Supplementary Material). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are grateful to the members of our group, colleagues 
and our external beta testers, especially Vikram Agarwal, 
who have rigorously tested the <rs type="software">pssRNAMiner</rs> and 
provided valuable feedback. Financial support for this 
project and funding to pay the Open Access publication 
charges for this article was provided by The Samuel 
Roberts Noble Foundation. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>W118 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue </p>

</text></tei>