<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2921509" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:43+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Aims </p>

<p>Westernized countries face a growing burden of cardiovascular calcification and osteoporosis. Despite its vast clinical 
significance, the precise nature of this reciprocal relationship remains obscure. We hypothesize that cardiovascular 
calcification progresses with inflammation and inversely correlates with bone tissue mineral density (TMD). </p>

<p>Methods 
and results </p>

<p>Arterial, valvular, and bone metabolism were visualized using near-infrared fluorescence (NIRF) molecular imaging 
agents, targeting macrophages and osteogenesis. We detected significant arterial and aortic valve calcification in 
apoE 
2/2 mice with or without chronic renal disease (CRD, 30 weeks old; n ¼ 28), correlating with the severity </p>

<p>of atherosclerosis. We demonstrated decreases in osteogenic activity in the femurs of apoE 
2/2 mice when compared </p>

<p>with WT mice, which was further reduced with CRD. Three-dimensional micro-computed tomography imaging of 
the cortical and cancellous regions of femurs quantified structural remodelling and reductions in TMD in apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice. We established significant correlations between arterial and valvular calcification and </p>

<p>loss of TMD (R 
2 ¼ 0.67 and 0.71, respectively). Finally, we performed macrophage-targeted molecular imaging to </p>

<p>explore a link between inflammation and osteoporosis in vivo. Although macrophage burden, visualized as uptake 
of NIRF-conjugated iron nanoparticles, was directly related to the degree of arterial and valvular inflammation and 
calcification, the same method inversely correlated inflammation with TMD (R 
2 ¼ 0.73; 0.83; 0.75, respectively). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This study provides direct in vivo evidence that in arteries and aortic valves, macrophage burden and calcification 
associate with each other, whereas inflammation inversely correlates with bone mineralization. Thus, understanding 
inflammatory signalling mechanisms may offer insight into selective abrogation of divergent calcific phenomena. </p>

<p>---Clinical studies suggest that cardiovascular calcification, athero-
sclerosis, and chronic renal disease (CRD) are associated with 
osteoporosis. </p>

<p>1,2   Emerging epidemiological evidence shows 
age-independent correlation between bone mineral density and </p>

<p>cardiovascular events. 
3 -5 In limited mouse studies, atherosclerosis </p>

<p>susceptibility corresponds to a reduction in bone mineralization. </p>

<p>6,7   Although these observations suggest common underlying mechan-
isms, the precise nature of the relationship between arterial 
calcification, calcific aortic valve disease, and bone osteogenesis, 
as well as reciprocal regulation of these processes, remains </p>

<p> † The first two authors contributed equally to the study. </p>

<p>* Corresponding author. Tel: +1 617 730 7755, fax: +1 617 730 7791, Email: eaikawa@partners.org; eaikawa@rics.bwh.harvard.edu 
Published on behalf of the European Society of Cardiology. All rights reserved. &amp; The Author 2010. For permissions please email: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org </p>

<p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article 
for non-commercial purposes provided that the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal, Learned Society and Oxford University Press are attributed as the 
original place of publication with correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this 
must be clearly indicated. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org. </p>

<p>European Heart Journal (2010) 31, 1975-1984 
doi:10.1093/eurheartj/ehq237 </p>

<p>unknown. The National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute Working 
Group on Calcific Aortic Stenosis has recently underscored the 
importance of identifying the relationship between calcification of 
the aortic valve and bone and the reciprocal regulation of these 
processes. </p>

<p>8   Arterial and aortic valve calcification is a significant cause of 
morbidity and mortality. 
9,10 Arterial calcification not only </p>

<p>weakens vasomotor responses, but also affects atherosclerotic 
plaque stability. Emerging evidence suggests that atherosclerotic 
plaques are prone to rupture, particularly in regions of high back-
ground stress with microcalcifications located in the thin fibrous 
cap. 
11 -13 In addition, calcification impairs the movement of </p>

<p>aortic valve leaflets, causing life-threatening aortic stenosis and 
heart failure. 
14 Recent studies suggest that underlying mechanisms </p>

<p>of aortic valve calcification resemble those of atherosclerotic 
arterial calcification, triggered by haemodynamic stress, reactive 
oxygen species, and inflammatory cues. </p>

<p>14 -17   Cardiovascular calcification was conventionally viewed as an inevi-
table consequence of ageing, but recent landmark studies have 
demonstrated that it is a highly regulated process of mineralization, 
akin to embryonic bone formation. 
14,18 Indeed, calcified vascular </p>

<p>material is often indistinguishable from bone, and its formation 
involves cellular and molecular signalling processes found in 
normal osteogenesis. 
19,20 We have reported that valvular </p>

<p>myofibroblast-like cells, due to their plasticity, respond to various 
stimuli by undergoing activation and sequential phenotypic differen-
tiation. During cardiovascular calcification, macrophage-derived 
proteinases such as elastolytic cathepsins or metalloproteinases 
induce the release of biologically active, soluble elastin-derived pep-
tides that may promote the osteogenic differentiation of myofibro-
blasts or smooth muscle cells (SMC). 
21 This finding concurs with </p>

<p>studies of phenotypic conversion of vascular SMC and valvular myo-
fibroblasts into osteoblastic cells, characterized by the expression of 
bone-regulating proteins and osteogenic factors (e.g. alkaline phos-
phatase, osteopontin, osteocalcin, Runx2/Cbfa1, Osterix). </p>

<p>16,22,23   Imaging approaches that can spatially resolve and quantify the 
temporal pro-osteogenic molecular processes in arteries, valves, 
and bones are limited. Conventional imaging modalities can identify 
advanced late-stage calcification, but optical molecular imaging can 
detect tissue mineralization at the earliest stages. The present 
study tested the hypothesis that arterial and aortic valve calcifica-
tion is inversely correlated with low bone tissue mineral density 
(TMD). The specific objective was to quantify the relationship 
between cardiovascular calcification (arterial and valvular) and 
long bone remodelling (cortical and trabecular) in established 
models of atherosclerosis and CRD, 
14 -16 using optical molecular </p>

<p>imaging and high-resolution 3D micro-computed tomography 
(CT). In addition, to demonstrate the association between inflam-
mation, ectopic calcification, and osteoporosis, we directly com-
pared macrophage burden and progression of osteogenic 
changes in each region of the same animals in vivo and ex vivo. 
Our results on opposing effects of inflammation in soft tissues (car-
diovascular organs) and in bone agree with the previous reports on 
accelerated osteolysis in inflamed bones. 
24 Our study provides </p>

<p>new insight into the relationship between osteoporosis and cardi-
ovascular calcification and suggests shared inflammatory mechan-
isms of ectopic calcification and bone osteolysis. It also offers a </p>

<p>unique model for exploration of in vivo mechanisms regulating 
early cardiovascular calcification and bone mineral loss. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>An expanded Methods section is provided in the Supplementary 
material online. </p>

<p>Animal protocol </p>

<p>We studied osteogenic changes in carotid arteries, aortic valves, and 
femur bones obtained from 30-week-old apoE 
2/2 mice (n ¼ 10) </p>

<p>and mice with CRD (n ¼ 10), induced by 5/6 nephrectomy. Age-
matched wild-type C57/BL6 mice (WT, n ¼ 8) served as controls. 
At 30 weeks of age, mice underwent intravital microscopy and were 
euthanized for ex vivo imaging, followed by histology and statistical ana-
lyses. In addition to molecular imaging, the femurs of the mice under-
went quantitative micro-CT imaging analyses. The Subcommittee on 
Research Animal Care at Massachusetts General Hospital approved 
all procedures. </p>

<p>Molecular imaging agents </p>

<p>To image osteogenesis, we used imaging agent (Osteosense680/ 
OS680, VisEn Medical, Inc., Woburn, MA, USA) binding to hydroxy-
apatite in actively mineralized regions containing osteoblast-like cells 
in arteries, valves 
14 -16 (Supplementary material online, Figure S1A), </p>

<p>and bones. 
25 Macrophage-targeted near-infrared (NIR)-conjugated </p>

<p>iron nanoparticle (Supplementary material online, Figure S1B) was 
used to detect inflammation. </p>

<p>14 -16 </p>

<p>Statistical analyses </p>

<p>Data are presented as mean + standard deviation. Statistical analyses 
for comparison groups employed one-way ANOVA, followed by the 
Tukey-Kramer post hoc test performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">GraphPad prism</rs> software 
(version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">4.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software</rs>, San Diego, CA, USA). Tests were 
two-sided and adjusted for variance inequality where appropriate. 
Linear regression with Pearson's correlation test was used to deter-
mine the covariant relationships between data. Normal distribution 
of the data was confirmed by comparing against expected normal dis-
tributions with given means and standard deviation. In all cases, test 
probability values less than 0.05 were considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Serum phosphate, creatinine, cystatin 
C, and cholesterol levels in apoE 
2/2 and 
chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice </p>

<p>Total cholesterol was significantly increased in apoE 
2/2 and CRD </p>

<p>apoE 
2/2 mice, when compared with WT mice (467.2 + 51.1 and </p>

<p>397.1 + 24.8 mg/dL vs. 56.3 + 9.8 mg/dL; P , 0.05). In addition, 
CRD apoE 
2/2 mice had significantly increased serum phosphate, </p>

<p>creatinine, and cystatin C levels when compared with apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>and WT mice (phosphate: 11.4 + 0.9 vs. 6.3 + 0.4 and 4.7 + 
0.4 mg/dL; P , 0.05; creatinine: 0.6 + 0.04 vs. 0.4 + 0.01 and 
0.3 + 0.01 mg/dL; P , 0.05; cystatin C: 0.9 + 0.01 vs. 0.6 + 0.2 
and 0.3 + 0.02 mg/mL; P , 0.001). Greater serum phosphate, crea-
tinine, and cystatin C levels suggest that 5/6 nephrectomy induced 
kidney failure, which in turn promotes inflammation. </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>J. Hjortnaes et al. </p>



<p>Osteogenic activity in mouse arteries and 
aortic valves associate with each other 
and increase with atherosclerosis severity </p>

<p>Fluorescence reflectance imaging was used to map mineralization 
in aortas of WT, apoE 
2/2 , and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice. Strong </p>

<p>signals were detected at the levels of aortic valve, aortic root, 
aortic arch, and abdominal aorta, in apoE 
2/2 and especially CRD </p>

<p>apoE 
2/2 mice when compared with WT mice (Supplementary </p>

<p>material online, Figure S2). Intravital imaging of carotid arteries 
in vivo showed more than 47-and 78-fold increases of calcified 
tissue area (ROI) in apoE 
2/2 and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, respectively, </p>

<p>compared with WT cohort (Figure 1A and B). In addition, up to 
100-and 400-fold increases in osteogenic signal intensity (SI) </p>

<p>occurred in apoE 
2/2 and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, respectively, </p>

<p>when compared with the WT cohort (Figure 1A and C ). Imaging 
analyses of the aortic valves in WT, apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>, and CRD apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice revealed that ROI increased 4-and 20-fold in size in 
apoE2/2 and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, respectively, compared with </p>

<p>ROI in WT mice (Figure 1D and E). Osteogenic SI was further sig-
nificantly increased in aortic valves of apoE 
2/2 and CRD apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>mice (13-and 50-fold, respectively) when compared with WT 
mice (Figure 1D and F). We performed a correlative analysis, in 
addition to Pearson's correlation test, to evaluate an association 
between vascular and valvular calcification. Figure 1G shows a sig-
nificant correlation of arterial and aortic valve calcific ROI 
(r ¼ 0.75; P , 0.05). In addition, arterial osteogenic SI significantly 
correlated with valvular SI (r ¼ 0.67; P , 0.05; Figure 1H). </p>

<p>Figure 1 Induction of osteogenesis in carotid arteries and aortic valves of apoE </p>

<p>2/2 and chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice, detected by </p>

<p>intravital fluorescence microscopy. (A) Calcified regions (region of interest) and mineralization (signal intensities) in the carotid arteries of 
WT, apoE 
2/2 , and chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice injected with Osteosense680 (maximum signal intensity shown in red). (B) Quantitative </p>

<p>assessment of region of interest showed a significant increase in calcification in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 vs. WT and apoE 
2/2 mice. </p>

<p>(C ) Arterial osteogenic signal intensity is greater in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice, compared with other groups. (D) Pseudo-colour </p>

<p>mapping of mineralization region of interest and signal intensity in the aortic valves. Aortic valve calcified region of interest (E) and osteogenic 
signal intensity (F) are significantly higher in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice, compared with other groups. (A -F) WT, n ¼ 8; apoE 
2/2 , </p>

<p>n ¼ 10; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10. (G) Correlation of arterial and valve calcified tissue area (region of interest; pixels). (H ) Cor-</p>

<p>relation of arterial and valve osteogenic activity (signal intensity; AU). (G and H ) WT, n ¼ 3; apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 4; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , </p>

<p>n ¼ 4. </p>

<p>Ectopic calcification vs. osteoporosis </p>



<p>Figure 2 Loss of bone mineral density and alterations in microarchitecture in mouse femurs, detected by 3D micro-computed tomography </p>

<p>and molecular imaging. (A) Fluorescence microscopy of mid-shaft region of femurs of mice injected with Osteosense680. (B) Quantification 
analysis of bone mineralization signal intensity showed a significant reduction in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice, compared with </p>

<p>other groups. (A and B) WT, n ¼ 8; apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10. (C and D) Micro-computed tomography </p>

<p>imaging of femur mid-shaft region (normal bone ¼ red; loss of bone mineralization ¼ green -blue). (E) Quantification assessment of bone 
tissue mineral density shows significant bone loss in the apoE 
2/2 and chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice. (F) Cortical/marrow area shows </p>

<p>a tendency towards a decrease in the cortical/marrow ratio in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice. (G and H ) Micro-computed tomography </p>

<p>imaging of femur head. Quantification assessment of microarchitecture demonstrates (I) the decrease in trabecular number and (J ) the increase 
in trabecular spacing in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice. (K ) No changes in trabecular thickness were detected. (C-K) WT, n ¼ 3; </p>

<p>apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 4; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 4. </p>

<p>J. Hjortnaes et al. </p>



<p>Furthermore, correlative histopathology corroborated our imaging 
data (Supplementary material online, Figure S3A and B). These 
imaging and histological results support the association between 
arterial and aortic valve calcification. </p>

<p>Bone mineralization decreases in femurs 
of atherosclerotic mice and inversely 
correlates to arterial and aortic valve 
calcification </p>

<p>Figure 2 shows mineralization in the mid-shaft region of femurs in 
WT, apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>, and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, detected by molecular </p>

<p>imaging ex vivo. We observed significantly decreased osteogenic 
SI in apoE 
2/2 mice and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice when compared </p>

<p>with WT mice and in apoE 
2/2 mice when compared with CRD </p>

<p>apoE 
2/2 mice (Figure 2A and B). Micro-CT imaging further </p>

<p>showed a decrease in bone TMD in the mid-shaft region of 
femurs from apoE 
2/2 mice when compared with WT mice </p>

<p>(Figure 2C -F ), which supports our molecular imaging results. 
Quantitative analyses demonstrated a significant difference in 
TMD between apoE 
2/2 mice and WT mice and between CRD </p>

<p>apoE 
2/2 mice and WT mice (Figure 2E). Albeit not significant </p>

<p>(P ¼ 0.057), the difference between CRD apoE 
2/2 mice and </p>

<p>WT mice showed a tendency towards decreased cortical/ 
marrow area ratio in CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, suggesting more </p>

<p>severe loss of bone structure in the CRD cohort (Figure 2F). Peri-
osteal perimeters were not different between conditions, 
suggesting that the endosteal dimensions expanded through osteo-
clast activity. Micro-CT showed a decrease in TMD in the femur 
heads of apoE 
2/2 mice when compared with WT mice </p>

<p>(Figure 2G and H), though bone volume fraction was not signifi-
cantly changed (Supplementary material online, Figure S4). 
Further statistical analyses of trabecular microarchitecture 
showed a significant decrease in trabecular number (Figure 2I) 
and a significant increase in trabecular spacing (Figure 2J) 
between CRD apoE 
2/2 mice and WT mice, but there was no sig-</p>

<p>nificant difference in trabecular thickness between groups 
(Figure 2K). These results suggest that osteoporotic remodelling 
may occur as a consequence of calcific cardiovascular disease. 
To test this, we applied a linear regression analysis comparing 
arterial and valvular calcification with bone TMD (Figure 3). 
Tissue mineral density inversely correlates with the arterial and 
aortic valve regions of calcification (ROI: R 
2 ¼ 0.86 and 0.34; </p>

<p>respectively; Figure 3A and B). Furthermore, TMD is inversely cor-
related to osteogenic SI in carotid arteries and aortic valves (SI: 
R 
2 ¼ 0.67 and 0.72, respectively; Figure 3C and D). These data </p>

<p>Figure 3 Inverse correlation of bone tissue mineral density with arterial and aortic valve calcification. Relationship of bone tissue mineral </p>

<p>density to arterial (A) and valve (B) calcified area (region of interest). Relationship of tissue mineral density to arterial (C) and valve (D) osteo-
genic activity (signal intensity). n ¼ 11. </p>

<p>Ectopic calcification vs. osteoporosis </p>



<p>suggest a strong inverse correlation between cardiovascular calci-
fication and bone mineralization. </p>

<p>Enhanced inflammation correlates with 
calcification in arteries and aortic valves </p>

<p>Macrophage-targeted molecular imaging agent (CLIO750) showed 
negligible inflammatory signal in WT arteries, which was substan-
tially increased in apoE 
2/2 and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice (Figure 4A). </p>

<p>Quantitative assessment of arterial inflammatory ROI determined 
a 44-and 95-fold increases in inflammation tissue area in 
apoE 
2/2 mice and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice when compared with </p>

<p>WT mice, which was further confirmed with significant 326-and 
718-fold increases in SI (Figure 4B and C ). Likewise, the enhanced 
expression of inflammation was found in the aortic valves of 
apoE 
2/2 and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice (Figure 4D). Quantitative ana-</p>

<p>lyses demonstrated statistically significant increases in inflammatory 
valvular ROI and SI between WT, apoE 
2/2 , and CRD apoE </p>

<p>2/2 </p>

<p>Figure 4 Induction of inflammatory signal in carotid arteries and aortic valves of apoE </p>

<p>2/2 and chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice, detected </p>

<p>by intravital fluorescence microscopy. (A) Intravital microscopy detected CLIO750-derived inflammatory signals in the carotid arteries of mice. 
(B) Significant increase in arterial inflammation area (region of interest) and (C) inflammatory signal intensity in the chronic renal disease 
apoE 
2/2 mice vs. WT and apoE 
2/2 mice. (D) Fluorescence microscopy detected CLIO750-derived inflammatory signals in the aortic </p>

<p>valves. (E) Significant increase in the aortic valve inflammation area (region of interest) and (F ) signal (signal intensity) in the chronic renal 
disease apoE 
2/2 mice, compared with WT and apoE 
2/2 mice. (A-F ) WT, n ¼ 8; apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10. </p>

<p>(G) Relationship between arterial inflammation area (CLIO750; region of interest) and arterial calcified tissue area (Osteosense680; region 
of interest). (H ) Association of arterial inflammatory activity (CLIO750; signal intensity) with arterial osteogenic activity (Osteosense680; 
signal intensity). (I ) Relationship between valvular inflammation (CLIO750; region of interest) and aortic valve calcification (Osteosense680; 
region of interest). (J ) Association of valvular inflammatory signal (CLIO750; signal intensity) with valvular osteogenic activity (Osteosense680; 
signal intensity). (G-J ) n ¼ 14. </p>

<p>J. Hjortnaes et al. </p>



<p>groups (ROI: 1.5-and 5.7-fold increases, Figure 4E; SI: 2.6-and 
11.6-fold increases, Figure 4F). Further, we found a statistically sig-
nificant correlation between cardiovascular calcification and 
inflammation in both arteries (ROI: R 
2 ¼ 0.73; SI: R 
2 ¼ 0.54; </p>

<p>Figure 4G and H ) and valves (ROI: R 
2 ¼ 0.84; SI: R 
2 ¼ 0.81; </p>

<p>Figure 4I and J ). Macrophage staining confirmed our molecular 
imaging findings (Supplementary material online, Figure S5A and 
B). Overall, these results suggest that the extent of cardiovascular 
inflammation correlates with the severity of calcification. </p>

<p>Long bone inflammation correlates 
inversely with decreased bone mineral 
signal and associates positively with 
cardiovascular calcification </p>

<p>Evidence suggests that inflamed or infected bones shift towards an 
osteolytic environment. To address further the mechanisms for 
osteoporotic changes, we attempted to link inflammation and 
TMD in the same mice used for imaging of cardiovascular calcifica-
tion. Molecular imaging demonstrated robust inflammation signal in 
the long bones of both apoE 
2/2 mice and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, </p>

<p>whereas WT mice demonstrated virtually no inflammation 
(Figure 5A). Using the same approach as before, we found 
7.6-and 22-fold increases in long bone inflammation (CLIO SI) 
for apoE 
2/2 mice and CRD apoE 
2/2 mice, when compared </p>

<p>with WT mice (Figure 5B). In contrast to the cardiovascular con-
dition, this increased inflammation correlated with decreased 
bone mineral signal (R 
2 ¼ 0.75; Figure 6A). These results strongly </p>

<p>suggest that the inflammatory responses in long bones contribute 
to loss of bone mineralization. Finally, we found strong positive 
correlations in SI between the degree of arterial or valvular inflam-
mation and bone inflammation (R 
2 ¼ 0.97; Figure 6B and C ). These </p>

<p>results support our hypothesis that systemic inflammatory signal </p>

<p>simultaneously acts to decrease bone mass and increase cardiovas-
cular calcification. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>This study establishes direct in vivo evidence that the calcification of 
arteries and aortic valves in atherosclerosis and CRD correlates 
inversely with bone tissue mineralization. We demonstrate an 
association between aortic valve calcification and arterial calcifica-
tion and that the degree of cardiovascular calcification correlates 
directly with the loss of bone mineral. The increased inflammatory 
activity in arteries, aortic valves, and long bones in atherosclerosis 
and renal failure demonstrate that inflammation at these three 
locations is related probably via systemic or circulating inflamma-
tory cues. Furthermore, our study reveals that whereas macro-
phage burden positively correlates with the extent of early 
cardiovascular calcification, inflammation inversely associates with 
bone mineralization. These results build on previous studies of 
the pathogenesis of cardiovascular calcification, in which advanced 
molecular imaging approaches demonstrated that atherosclerotic 
and aortic valve calcification share similar risk factors and are 
induced by similar pro-inflammatory molecular and cellular pro-
cesses. 
14 -16 Our seemingly paradoxical in vivo evidence on inflam-</p>

<p>mation and bone mineralization concur well with previous reports 
on osteolytic environment in inflamed bones. </p>

<p>24   Arterial calcification occurs in two different forms: intimal calci-
fication, typically associated with atherosclerosis, and medial calci-
fication, an ossification process associated with renal failure and 
diabetes. 
9 In dysmetabolic patient populations, both types of arter-</p>

<p>ial calcification often develop simultaneously. Intimal calcification 
increases the risk of plaque rupture, whereas medial calcification 
increases arterial stiffness and impairs cardiovascular haemody-
namics. </p>

<p>9   Although the mechanism remains incompletely </p>

<p>Figure 5 Correlation of long bone inflammation with osteogenic activity. (A) Molecular imaging of inflammation in the long bones of mice </p>

<p>injected with CLIO750. (B) Significant increase in bone inflammation in the chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 mice vs. WT and apoE 
2/2 mice. </p>

<p>(A and B) WT, n ¼ 8; apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10. </p>

<p>Ectopic calcification vs. osteoporosis </p>



<p>understood, it is generally agreed that cardiovascular calcification is 
a more active biological process than previously considered. </p>

<p>26   Clinicopathological studies have shown similarity between calcified 
vascular material and bone material, 
20 have observed osteoblasts </p>

<p>and osteoclast-like cells in the arterial wall, 
19 and have </p>

<p>demonstrated the presence of various bone-regulating proteins 
in calcified arteries. 
27 Osteogenic differentiation of vascular SMC </p>

<p>or valvular myofibroblasts is likely caused by various mechanisms, 
including pro-inflammatory cytokines (e.g. IL-6, TNF-a), 
10 oxidized </p>

<p>lipids, 
17 and microenvironmental and mechanical cues. 
28 Biochemi-</p>

<p>cal imbalances also accelerate calcification. Studies show that 
excess phosphate levels in CRD accelerate calcification of vascular 
SMC or valvular myofibroblasts through the phosphate-induced 
release of matrix vesicles and apoptosis. </p>

<p>15,29   Systemic factors associated with CRD, including reduced circu-
lating levels of erythropoietin, have been shown to reduce osteo-
blast quantity and bone mineral density via Jak-Stat signalling in 
haematopoietic stem cells. 
30 Furthermore, the kidneys represent </p>

<p>the site of vitamin D activation, and therefore CRD-associated 
reductions in activated vitamin D may also induce parallel 
reductions in bone mass. Whether CRD-induced anaemia or acti-
vated vitamin D deficiency plays a role in the reduced bone mass 
or increased cardiovascular calcification remains uncertain. 
Our results directly quantified a paradox of simultaneous osteo-
lysis and ectopic calcification in vivo in the same animals. Although 
both correlate with age in humans, some clinical studies have 
shown the association of cardiovascular calcification and osteo-
porosis to be independent of age. 
3,31 Research has demonstrated </p>

<p>that patients with lower bone density and osteoporosis have 
more severe atherosclerosis. 
32,33 Dyslipidaemia also may link </p>

<p>bone loss with cardiovascular calcification. Pre-clinical studies 
suggest that hyperlipidaemia reduces bone mineral density 
34 and </p>

<p>promotes arterial and valvular calcification in mice 
14,16 and that </p>

<p>Figure 6 Relationship between bone osteogenic activity and </p>

<p>inflammation. (A) Inverse association of bone osteogenic activity 
(Osteosense680; signal intensity) with bone inflammation 
(CLIO750; signal intensity). (B) Positive relationship between 
arterial inflammation (CLIO750; signal intensity) and bone inflam-
mation (CLIO750; signal intensity). (C) Positive correlation of 
aortic valve inflammation (CLIO750; signal intensity) and bone 
inflammation (CLIO750; signal intensity). (A -C) WT, n ¼ 8; 
apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10; chronic renal disease apoE 
2/2 , n ¼ 10. </p>

<p>Figure 7 Schematic presentation of a hypothetical model on </p>

<p>the paradoxical relationship between cardiovascular calcification 
and bone mineral loss, associated with local and systemic inflam-
mation. Atherosclerosis and chronic renal disease-associated sys-
temic inflammatory stimuli enhance local inflammation in the 
cardiovascular system. Local pro-inflammatory microenviron-
mental cues in atherosclerotic plaques and diseased valves may 
shift vascular and valvular cells towards an osteogenic phenotype, 
resulting in increased mineral deposition. In the bone, the inflam-
matory milieu may increase the number/activity of bone-
resorbing osteoclasts, leading to decreased mineral. Additional 
factors arising from bone could further influence cardiovascular 
calcification. </p>

<p>J. Hjortnaes et al. </p>



<p>statins reduce calcification. 
14,35 Moreover, loss of bone mass leads </p>

<p>to increased circulating phosphate and calcium and decreased 
parathyroid hormone, which stimulate the Cbfa1-dependent min-
eralization of cardiovascular tissue. 
36 This evidence suggests that </p>

<p>osteoporosis may contribute to cardiovascular calcification by 
adding to a pathological microenvironment that promotes osteo-
genesis of the arterial wall and aortic valve. During bone resorp-
tion, biochemical factors are released into the circulation, 
contributing to vascular calcification; this observation agrees with 
studies showing that agents that block bone resorption in animal 
models also block vascular calcification. </p>

<p>37   Our findings strongly suggest in vivo that systemic and local 
inflammation drives both cardiovascular calcification and bone 
loss. In general, inflammation causes 'hardening' of soft tissue and 
'softening' of hard tissue, 
34 but it is unclear whether the pathways </p>

<p>are similar. Connections between inflammation and osteolysis 
were recently established in arthritic and periodontal diseases. </p>

<p>24   Pro-inflammatory cytokines such as IL-6 and TNF-a have been 
shown to increase the osteoclast activity through the NF-kB 
pathway. 
38 Osteoprotegerin, normally produced by vascular SMC </p>

<p>and osteoblasts, functions as a decoy receptor for the receptor 
activator of NF-kB ligand RANKL. 
26 RANKL, a cytokine that </p>

<p>induces osteoclast differentiation and activation, stimulates bone 
resorption, whereas osteoprotegerin neutralizes the binding of 
RANKL to RANK and prevents bone loss. Osteoprotegerin-
deficient mice demonstrated severe bone loss in addition to 
medial calcifications. 
39 Taken together, these studies suggest that </p>

<p>inflammation in cardiovascular and bone regions acts through the 
NF-kB -RANKL pathway, but whether this pathway is utilized sim-
ultaneously for ectopic calcification and bone loss is unknown. 
Figure 7 shows a schematic illustration of our working hypothesis. 
The presence of atherosclerosis or CRD likely associates with sys-
temic inflammatory signals, as described above. Local inflammation, 
as detected by macrophage-targeted NIR fluorescence nanoparti-
cles, associates with increased mineral in cardiovascular tissues and 
decreased mineral in bone, as detected by Osteosense. Potential 
mediators associated with systemic and local inflammatory pro-
cesses are shown, as are possible factors arising from bone, which 
could further influence cardiovascular calcification. Studies are 
needed to further establish the relationship between cardiovascular 
calcification and osteoporosis and to dissect the complex mechan-
isms for reciprocal regulation of these processes. 
Unravelling the mechanisms underlying cardiovascular calcifica-
tion is an important step towards future strategies. Therapeutic 
agents that selectively increase or inhibit osteogenesis will be 
much preferred over current systemic approaches such as statin 
therapy. The identification of high-risk patients at subclinical 
stages is an equally important task, requiring new imaging modal-
ities or biomarkers targeting calcification. 
8 Molecular imaging pro-</p>

<p>vides appealing new means to identify early-stage calcifying 
atherosclerotic plaques and aortic valve lesions and offers a 
powerful tool in personalized preventive cardiovascular medicine. </p>

<p>Supplementary material </p>

<p>Supplementary material is available at European Heart Journal 
online. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>The authors would like to thank Dr Masanori Aikawa for critical 
reading of the manuscript and Sara Karwacki for excellent editorial 
assistance. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This study was supported in part by Wijck-Casper-Stam Foun-
dation (J.H.), American Heart Association Scientist Development 
Grants (0835460N, E.A.; 0830384N, J.B.), NYSTAR CAT Award 
(J.B., M.R.), Donald W. Reynolds Foundation (R.W., E.A.), Leducq 
Foundation (07CVD04; E.A., J.B.) and Translational Program of 
Excellence in Nanotechnology (5-UO1-HL080731; R.W.). 
Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this 
article was provided by research grants to Dr Aikawa. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest: R.W. reports serving as a consultant for 
Visen Medical. Other authors report no disclosures. </p>



<p>Ectopic calcification vs. osteoporosis </p>





<p>J. Hjortnaes et al. </p>



</text></tei>