<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2768165" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:39+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Transgenic expression of diacylglycerol acyltrans-
ferase-1 (DGAT1) in skeletal muscle leads to protection against 
fat-induced insulin resistance despite accumulation of intramuscu-
lar triglyceride, a phenomenon similar to what is known as the 
"athlete paradox." The primary objective of this study is to deter-
mine how DGAT1 affects muscle fatty acid oxidation in relation to 
whole-body energy metabolism and insulin sensitivity. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-We first quantified 
insulin sensitivity and the relative tissue contributions to the 
improved whole-body insulin sensitivity in muscle creatine 
kisase (MCK)-DGAT1 transgenic mice by hyperinsulinemic-eu-
glycemic clamps. Metabolic consequences of DGAT1 overexpres-
sion in skeletal muscles were determined by quantifying 
triglyceride synthesis/storage (anabolic) and fatty acid oxidation 
(catabolic), in conjunction with gene expression levels of repre-
sentative marker genes in fatty acid metabolism. Whole-body 
energy metabolism including food consumption, body weights, 
oxygen consumption, locomotor activity, and respiration ex-
change ratios were determined at steady states. </p>

<p>RESULTS-MCK-DGAT1 mice were protected against muscle 
lipoptoxicity, although they remain susceptible to hepatic lipotox-
icity. While augmenting triglyceride synthesis, DGAT1 overexpres-
sion also led to increased muscle mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation 
efficiency, as compared with wild-type muscles. On a high-fat diet, 
MCK-DGAT1 mice displayed higher basal metabolic rates and 
5-10% lower body weights compared with wild-type littermates, 
whereas food consumption was not different. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscle led 
to parallel increases in triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxida-
tion. Seemingly paradoxical, this phenomenon is characteristic of 
insulin-sensitive myofibers and suggests that DGAT1 plays an active 
role in metabolic "remodeling" of skeletal muscle coupled with 
insulin sensitization. Diabetes Given the parallel increases in both muscle triglyceride 
stores and fatty acid oxidation activity as exemplified by 
oxidative type I myofibers or the exercise-trained muscle 
model, we hypothesized that triglyceride synthesis and 
fatty acid oxidation capacities are intrinsically intercon-
nected and both are upregulated in insulin-sensitive mus-
cles. The present study demonstrates upregulation of both 
triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid oxidation capacities in 
the insulin-sensitive, DGAT1 overexpressing muscle model. 
This study also suggests that DGAT1 overexpression is a 
cause of such a "paradoxical" change in fat metabolism. 
We postulate that this coordinated change enables the 
myocytes to keep the intracellular levels of fatty acid 
metabolites below a potentially lipotoxic level. By chan-
neling lipotoxic fatty acid metabolites into storage (as 
triglyceride) and into a pathway for terminal oxidation, 
such a change may lessen fatty acid-induced insulin 
resistance that is often associated with acquired obesity 
(3,12,13,19). </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice, diets, and exercise. MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice and wild-type 
littermates were fed standard rodent diet or high-fat diet (HFD) as previously 
described (3). The swimming exercise regimen was the same as described (3). 
Male mice were used in this study. Animal protocols were approved by the 
Columbia University Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee. 
Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps. Three-month-old mice were fed 
HFD or standard rodent diet for 8 weeks before the clamp study. The clamp 
was conducted in awake mice as previously described (19). All procedures 
were approved by the Yale University Institutional Animal Care and Use 
Committee. Briefly, after an overnight fast, [3-3 H]-glucose (high-performance 
liquid chromatography purified; Perkinelmer) was infused at 0.05 Ci/min for 
2 h to assess the basal glucose turnover. Hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp 
was conducted for 120 min with primed/continuous infusion of human insulin 
(Novo Nordisk; 105 pmol/kg prime, 15 pmol kg 1 min 1 infusion), keeping 
plasma glucose at 6.7 mmol/l (basal level). [3-3 H]-glucose was infused at 0.1 
Ci/min throughout the clamp to estimate insulin-stimulated whole-body 
glucose fluxes. Calculations of hepatic glucose output (HGO), whole-body 
glycolysis, and whole-body glycogen synthesis were also as described (20). To 
assess muscle glucose uptake, separate groups of mice were clamped and 
2-deoxy-D-[1-14 C]glucose (2-[ 14 C]DG; Perkinelmer) was injected as a bolus at 
the 75th min of the clamp as described (20). 
Mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation. Four-month-old mice pretreated with 
HFD for 8 weeks were used for these experiments. Mitochondria were 
isolated from muscle tissues using Mitochondria Isolation Kits (Sigma-
Aldrich, St. Louis, MO) according to the manufacturer's instructions. Mito-
chondrial fatty acid oxidation was performed by measuring the rate of 3 H 2 O 
production from the substrate [ 3 H]palmitate present in excess (final concen-
trations: 0.2 mmol/l palmitate with 10 Ci/ml of 9,10(n)-[ 3 H]palmitate and 
1.25% BSA) in a mitochondria incubation medium (containing 20 g mito-
chondria protein) as described (21). 
Mitochondrial DNA copy number, ATP production rate, citrate syn-
thase, -hydroxyacyl-CoA dehydrogenase, and carnitine palmitoyl 
transferase I activities. Four-month-old mice pretreated with HFD for 8 
weeks were used for these experiments. Mitochondrial DNA copy number was 
measured using quantitative real-time PCR as previously described (22). 
Mitochondrial DNA for NADH dehydrogenases 1 and 4 (ND1 and ND4) and 
nuclear DNA for -actin were coamplified within the same reaction wells (for 
primer sequences, see supplemental Table 1, available in an online appendix 
at http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org/cgi/content/full/db08-1096/DC1). Mito-
chondrial ATP production rates were measured in isolated mitochondria 
through time-course monitoring of bioluminescence in response to a luciferin-
luciferase ATP-monitoring reagent (Biotherma, Haninge, Sweden) as de-
scribed (23). Maximal activity of citrate synthase was measured in muscle 
homogenates by photospectrometry as described (24). -hydroxyacyl CoA 
dehydrogenase (HAD) activity was also measured in muscle homogenates by 
following spectrophotometrically the conversion of acetoacetyl-CoA to -hy-
droxybutyryl-CoA by -HAD as described (25). Total carnitine palmitoyl 
transferase (CPT) activity was assayed radiochemically in isolated mitochon-
dria by following the conversion of palmitoyl-L-carnitine from palmitoyl-CoA 
and radiolabeled L-carnitine as described (25,26). CPT-I activity was calcu-
lated from the total CPT activity after subtraction of CPT-II activity, which 
was measured in the presence of 0.2 mmol/l malonyl-CoA that inhibits CPT-I. </p>

<p>Transmission electron microscopy. Four-month-old mice pretreated with 
HFD for 8 weeks were used. Muscles were isolated, fixed with 2.5% glutaral-
dehyde in 0.1M Sorenson's buffer (PH 7.2), and treated with 1% OsO4 also in 
Sorenson's buffer for 1 h. After dehydration and embedment in Lx-112 (Ladd 
Research Industries), thin sections (60 nm) were cut using a MT-7000 
ultramicrotome, stained with uranyl acetate and lead citrate, and examined 
under a JEOL JEM-1200 EXII electron microscope. Pictures were captured by 
an ORCA-HR digital camera (Hamamatsu) and recorded with an AMT Image 
Capture Engine. 
Indirect calorimetry. Twenty-week-old weight-matched male MCK-DGAT1 
mice and wild-type littermates that had been on a HFD for 8 weeks were singly 
housed in metabolic chambers. After 2-4 days of adaptation, oxygen con-
sumption, locomotor activity, and respiration exchange ratio were measured 
continuously over at least 5 days during 12:12 light-dark cycles, using a CLAMS 
(Columbus Instruments, Columbus, OH) open-circuit indirect calorimetry 
system as previously described (27). 
RT-PCR, Western blot, DGAT activity, and triglyceride contents. Four-
month-old mice with 8-week HFD pretreatment were used for these experi-
ments. RT-PCR (3,28) and Western blot (3,29) were as described. Gene-
specific primer sets are listed in supplemental Table 1. Primary antibodies to 
pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase (PDK)4, uncoupling protein (UCP)-3, CD36, 
and GAPDH (glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase) were obtained 
from Abcam (Cambridge, MA). DGAT activity was measured in vitro using 
[ 14 C]-labeled palmitoyl-CoA as previously described (29,30). The method to 
quantify muscle triglyceride content was as described (3,29). 
Statistical analysis. Statistical differences were first analyzed by ANOVA to 
determine overall treatment effects (genotype or exercise), followed by post 
hoc comparisons between concerned study groups (Statistica V6.0, StatSoft, 
OK). A two-tailed P value of 0.05 was used to indicate statistical significance. 
For indirect calorimetry measurements, ANOVA repeated measures (<rs type="software">Prism, 
GraphPad</rs> Software, San Diego, CA) were used. Post hoc analyses were 
conducted using Tukey post hoc or Bonferroni comparisons. Data are 
expressed as means SE. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice demonstrate improved 
resistance to diet-induced lipotoxicity, but they re-
main susceptible to hepatic insulin resistance on 
HFD. Using glucose tolerance and insulin tolerance tests, 
we showed previously that MCK-DGAT1 mice were pro-
tected against HFD-induced insulin resistance (3). Ex vivo 
2-deoxyglucose uptake in skeletal muscles isolated from 
HFD-fed animals demonstrated that insulin sensitivity 
was greater in DGAT1-overexpressing muscles than in 
the wild-type muscles (3). In this study, whole-body and 
tissue insulin sensitivities were assessed in vivo by 
hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamps in combination 
with radioisotope-labeled glucose infusions. Three-
month-old male MCK-DGAT1 and wild-type mice were fed 
HFD for 8 weeks (WT-HF and DGAT1-HF, respectively) 
before the clamp study. Age-and sex-matched wild-type 
mice on standard rodent diet (WT-NC) were used as 
baseline control. The major findings are depicted in Fig. 1, 
and other energetic and clamp parameters are summarized 
in supplemental Table 2. As expected, WT-HF mice 
showed marked insulin resistance with the mean whole-
body glucose infusion rate at only 16 mg kg 1 min 1 
(Fig. 1A). DGAT1-HF mice were more insulin sensitive 
than WT-HF mice, achieving a mean whole-body glucose 
infusion rate of 29 mg kg 1 min 1 (Fig. 1A). However, 
the baseline whole-body glucose infusion rate in the 
control WT-NC mice was 45 mg kg 1 min 1 (Fig. 1A), 
indicating that DGAT1 overexpression provided 45% 
protection against HFD-induced insulin resistance. Trans-
genic mice were not protected from HFD-induced hepatic 
insulin resistance. Compared with a 50% suppression 
of HGO in WT-NC mice during the clamping, insulin-
mediated suppression of HGO was completely absent in 
both WT-HF and DGAT1-HF mice (Fig. 1B). To directly 
assess muscle insulin sensitivity under the same clamping </p>

<p>L. LIU AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 </p>

<p>
conditions, a bolus infusion of 2-deoxy-D-[1-14 C]glucose 
was given. Uptake of 2-deoxy-D-[1-14 C]glucose in skeletal 
muscle was 30% greater in DGAT1-HF mice than in 
WT-HF mice (Fig. 1C), confirming that increased lipotox-
icity tolerance in skeletal muscle was the physiological 
basis for the protection of MCK-DGAT1 mice, albeit in-
complete, against HFD-induced whole-body insulin 
resistance. 
DGAT1 overexpression in skeletal muscle leads to 
improved mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation effi-
ciency as well as increased triglyceride synthesis and 
storage. As expected, muscle DGAT activity was three-
fold increased in MCK-DGAT1 (Fig. 2A), which was asso-
ciated with a 70% increase in muscle triglyceride content 
(Fig. 2B). To characterize skeletal muscle fatty acid oxi-
dation capacity, we first determined mitochondrial DNA 
(mtDNA) copy number by assessing the ratio of mtDNA 
ND1 and ND4 to the nuclear DNA -actin gene in soleus 
and anterior tibial muscles. There were 30 -45% fewer 
mitochondria per copy genome DNA in DGAT1-overex-
pressing tibial and soleus muscles than those of the 
wild-type controls (Fig. 2C). However, analyses of mito-
chondrial ATP production rates (MAPR) per unit muscle 
protein revealed no reduction in transgenic mice as com-
pared with wild-type mice (Fig. 2D). Maximal tissue citrate 
synthase activity was significantly greater in the DGAT1-
overexpressing soleus muscle than the wild-type counter-</p>

<p>part was, although no significant difference was detected 
in tibialis anterior (Fig. 2D). Maximal tissue -HAD activity 
per unit muscle protein was significantly greater in the 
transgenic muscle than the wild-type muscle (Fig. 2E). 
Similarly, mitochondrial CPT-I activity per unit mitochon-
drial protein was significantly greater in the DGAT1-
overexpressing muscle than the wild-type muscle (Fig. 
2E). The unchanged or potentially enhanced mitochon-
drial oxidative capacity in the presence of fewer mitochon-
dria suggested a higher mitochondrial efficiency in 
DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. Direct examination of so-
leus muscles by electron microscopy confirmed that fewer, 
but bigger, mitochondria were present in the DGAT1-
overexpressing muscle (Fig. 2F) than in the wild-type 
muscle (Fig. 2G). Additionally, in vitro measurement of 
maximal fatty acid oxidation rates demonstrated a 20% 
increase in fatty acid oxidation capacity in the MCK-
DGAT1 muscle compared with the wild-type muscle (1,217 
vs. 1,019 nmol min 1 g 1 mitochondrial protein, P 
0.01; Fig. 2H). 
Upregulation of PDK4 and UCP3 in skeletal muscle of 
MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice. mRNA levels of marker 
genes in fat metabolism were examined by real-time PCR 
in soleus muscle from 4-month-old male wild-type and 
MCK-DGAT1 transgenic mice after 8-week HFD feeding 
(Fig. 3A). DGAT1 mRNA levels were approximately three-
fold as high in MCK-DGAT1 mice as in wild-type mice (P </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>WT-NC 
WT-HF Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>glucose infusion rate 
(mg/kg/min) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(n=7) 
(n=8) 
(n=10) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>WT-NC 
WT-HF Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>Basal HGO 
Clamp HGO </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Hepatic glucose 
output (mg/kg/min) 
2-DG uptake 
(nmol/g/m) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>260 </p>

<p>390 </p>

<p>520 </p>

<p>WT-HF 
Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(n=7) 
(n=8) 
(n=10) 
(n=9) 
(n=9) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Muscle 
Liver </p>

<p>Whole Body </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>WT-NC 
WT-HF Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>glucose infusion rate 
(mg/kg/min) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(n=7) 
(n=8) 
(n=10) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>WT-NC 
WT-HF Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>Basal HGO 
Clamp HGO </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Hepatic glucose 
output (mg/kg/min) 
2-DG uptake 
(nmol/g/m) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>130 </p>

<p>260 </p>

<p>390 </p>

<p>520 </p>

<p>WT-HF 
Dgat1-HF </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>(n=7) 
(n=8) 
(n=10) 
(n=9) 
(n=9) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Muscle 
Liver </p>

<p>Whole Body </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Whole-body, hepatic, and muscle insulin sensitivity assessed by hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp. A: Steady-state whole-body glucose 
infusion rates in age-, sex-, genetic background-, and breeding environment-matched wild-type mice on standard rat diet (WT-NC), wild-type mice 
pretreated with ad lib HFD feeding for 8 weeks (WT-HF), and MCK-DGAT1 mice pretreated with ad lib HFD feeding for 8 weeks (DGAT1-HF). 
B: Steady-state HGO before (basal HGO) and after (clamp HGO) insulin infusion at the rate of 3 mU kg 1 min 1 in WT-NC, WT-HF, and 
DGAT1-HF mice under the same clamp conditions as in A. C: 2-Deoxyglucose uptake in skeletal muscle after bolus injection of the [ 14 C]-labeled 
2-deoxyglucose under the same clamp conditions as in A and B. Data are presented as means SE; P and n are as indicated; *P &lt; 0.05. 2-DG, 
2-deoxyglucose. </p>

<p>FAT AND GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MCK-DGAT1 MICE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>0.05) as expected, and mRNA levels for PDK4 and UCP3 
were doubled in MCK-DGAT1 compared with wild-type 
mice (P 0.05). There was also a trend of approximate 
doubling of mRNA levels for CD36 (P 0.051), CPT1 (P 
0.120), ACC2 (P 0.072), and GLUT4 (P 0.117) in 
MCK-DGAT1 mice. No significant changes were detected 
in mRNA levels for DGAT2, fatty acids, ACS1, ADRP, 
sterol regulatory element-binding protein-1c, peroxisome </p>

<p>proliferator-activated receptor (PPAR)-, PPAR, PPAR, 
peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor coactiva-
tor-, CRAT, ECHS1, UCP1, UCP2, and PEPCK. 
PDK4 is believed to play a critical role in regulating the 
fuel partitioning between fat and glucose oxidation 
(31,32). To further understand the changes in PDK4 ex-
pression in MCK-DGAT1 muscles, we compared a group of 
DGAT1-overexpressing mice with a group of wild-type </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>ND1 
ND4 
ATP 
CS </p>

<p>mtDNA/actin DNA 
CS (mmol/min/g) </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>MAPR (µmol/min/g) </p>

<p>β-HAD (mmol/min/g) </p>

<p>Tibial </p>

<p>Soleus </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>β-HAD CPT-1 </p>

<p>CPT-1 (nmol/min/g) 
20 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>TG (nmol/mg) </p>

<p>[ 3 
H]TG (cpm x 1000) </p>

<p>DGAT activity (soleus) 
TG content (soleus) </p>

<p>B 
A </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>Soleus 
MAPR (µmol/min/g) 
CS (mmol/min/g) </p>

<p>mtDNA copy number </p>

<p>EM-mitochondria 
EM-mitochondria </p>

<p>MAPR and CS </p>

<p>β-HAD and CPT-1 </p>

<p>mtDNA/actin DNA </p>

<p>Maximum FA oxidation 
(mmol H 
2 O/mg/min) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Maximum FA oxidation 
(mmol H 
2 O/mg/min) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>H 
G 
F </p>

<p>Soleus </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>* 
* 
* 
* </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>Mt FA oxidatio n </p>

<p>WT-soleus 
Dgat1-soleus </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Assessment of anabolic and catabolic fatty acid metabolism in skeletal muscle of MCK-DGAT1 and control wild-type mice. Male mice 
pretreated with 8-week HFD as described in Fig. 1. A: DGAT activity in soleus muscles isolated from the 4-month-old wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 
mice (n 4, each group). B: Triglyceride content in soleus muscle from the wild-type (n 5) and MCK-DGAT1 (n 6) mice. C: Mitochondrial 
copy numbers as determined by PCR quantification of ND1 or ND4 as mitochondrial DNA (using -actin as reference for nuclear DNA) in anterior 
tibial and soleus muscles of the wild-type (n 7) and MCK-DGAT1 (n 6) mice. D: MAPR (determined in isolated mitochondria) and citrate 
synthase activity (measured in muscle homogenates) of the anterior tibial and soleus muscles from the wild-type (n 7) and MCK-DGAT1 (n 
6) mice. E: -HAD activity (measured in muscle homogenates) and CPT-I activity (measured in isolated mitochondria) of the soleus muscles from 
the wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (n 6, each group). F and G: Representative low-and high-power (inserts) views of the electron microscopic 
fields of the soleus muscle from the wild-type (F) and MCK-DGAT1 (G) mice. Quantification of 6000 EM micrographs using an image analysis 
system (<rs id="software-1" type="software">Imagine-Pro Plus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.0</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>) showed that wild-type and DGAT1 mice have 149 3.6 and 98 7.7 mitochondria per 10 10 
micron muscle area, respectively (P &lt; 0.001). The average mitochondrial size is 34,432 4,246 pixels for wild-type and 62,418 938 pixels for 
DGAT1 mice (P 0.014). H: Maximal mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation rates measured in isolated mitochondria of the soleus muscles from the 
wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (n 6, each group). Values are expressed as means SE; NS, no statistical significance (P &gt; 0.05); *P &lt; 0.05, 
**P &lt; 0.01 (n as indicated). CS, citrate synthase; FA, fatty acid; 28S, 28S rRNA; TG, triglyceride; WT, wild type. </p>

<p>L. LIU AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 </p>

<p>
mice after 1-week swimming exercise (3). Using sedentary 
wild-type mice as a baseline control, both DGAT1 overex-
pression and exercise led to 1.5-fold increases (P 0.05) 
in PDK4 mRNA levels in skeletal muscle (Fig. 3B and C), 
providing two independent cases in which upregulation 
of PDK4 mRNA expression was dissociated from glu-
cose intolerance. Western blot of CD36, UCP3, and 
PDK4 showed 1.4-to 1.8-fold increases of these proteins 
in DGAT1-overexpressing muscle relative to wild-type 
muscle (Fig. 3D). 
MCK-DGAT1 mice display increased energy expendi-
ture without changes in food intake. To determine the 
physiological significance of the above in vitro findings 
and to help interpret the physiological consequences of 
the increased triglyceride synthesis and increased mito-
chondrial fatty acid oxidation capacity (and higher expres-
sion levels of the uncoupling protein UCP3) in DGAT1-
overexpressing skeletal muscle, we measured whole-body 
energy metabolism in vivo. Four-month-old weight-and 
adiposity-matched (Fig. 4A) male MCK-DGAT1 and wild-
type mice were analyzed in metabolic chambers after </p>

<p>8-week HFD feeding. MCK-DGAT1 mice appeared less 
physically active than wild-type mice (Fig. 4B), although 
the changes seemed to be unrelated to food-seeking behav-
ior, as food intake was the same between MCK-DGAT1 and 
wild-type mice (Fig. 4G). In contrast to the changes in 
physical activity, oxygen consumption rates were signifi-
cantly higher in the transgenic mice than in wild-type mice 
(Fig. 4C, wild-type vs. MCK-DGAT1, P 0.05, repeated-
measures ANOVA). No significant difference was detected 
in respiration exchange rates (RER) under these condi-
tions (Fig. 4D). Further experimental maneuver with two 
consecutive 24-h measurements of VO 2 during fasting 
followed by refeeding revealed that the difference in 
energy expenditure was accentuated during refeeding. As 
expected, energy expenditure reduced and increased in 
response to prolonged fast and refeeding, respectively, in 
both wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice (Fig. 4E). However, 
the increase during refeeding was markedly greater in the 
transgenic mice than in wild-type mice (P 0.05, repeated-
measures ANOVA) (Fig. 4F). As was during regular ad lib 
feeding, no difference in food intake was observed during </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Relative mRNA expression levels in soleus muscle </p>

<p>mRNA expression 
levels relative to WT </p>

<p>DGAT1 
DGAT2 
ACC2 
FAS 
ACS1 
CD36 
ADRP 
SREBP1c 
PPAR-α 
PPAR-δ 
PPAR-γ 
PGC-β 
CRAT 
ECHS1 
CPT1 
UCP1 
UCP2 
UCP3 
PDK4 
PEPCK 
GLUT4 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>mRNA levels 
relative to WT </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>WT (n=14) 
Dgat1 (n=12) </p>

<p>p=0.022 </p>

<p>Dgat1 overexpression on 
Muscle PDK4 expression </p>

<p>mRNA levels 
relative to Sed </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Sed (n=15) 
Exe (n=14) </p>

<p>p=0.034 </p>

<p>Exercise on 
Muscle PDK4 expression </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>UCP3 </p>

<p>PDK4 </p>

<p>CD36 </p>

<p>Western blot -soleus muscle </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>1:1.4 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>Densitometry 
relative to GAPDH </p>

<p>1:1.8 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>1:1.6 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>WT/HFD </p>

<p>Dgat1/HFD </p>

<p>Relative mRNA expression levels in soleus muscle </p>

<p>mRNA expression 
levels relative to WT </p>

<p>DGAT1 
DGAT2 
ACC2 
FAS 
ACS1 
CD36 
ADRP 
SREBP1c 
PPAR-α 
PPAR-δ 
PPAR-γ 
PGC-β 
CRAT 
ECHS1 
CPT1 
UCP1 
UCP2 
UCP3 
PDK4 
PEPCK 
GLUT4 </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>* 
* * </p>

<p>mRNA levels 
relative to WT </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>WT (n=14) 
Dgat1 (n=12) </p>

<p>p=0.022 </p>

<p>Dgat1 overexpression on 
Muscle PDK4 expression </p>

<p>mRNA levels 
relative to Sed </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Sed (n=15) 
Exe (n=14) </p>

<p>p=0.034 </p>

<p>Exercise on 
Muscle PDK4 expression </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>GAPDH </p>

<p>UCP3 </p>

<p>PDK4 </p>

<p>CD36 </p>

<p>Western blot -soleus muscle </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>1:1.4 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>Densitometry 
relative to GAPDH </p>

<p>1:1.8 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>1:1.6 (WT:Dgat1) </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Effects of DGAT1 overexpression and exercise on relative levels of gene expression in soleus muscle. A: Gene expression levels were 
measured by RT-PCR in soleus muscles isolated from wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice pretreated with 8-week HFD as described in Fig. 1, using 
primer sets listed in suppl. Table 1. Gene abbreviations are the same as listed in suppl. Table 1. *P &lt; 0.05 (n 5-7 in each group). B: Relative 
gene expression levels of PDK4 in soleus muscles from HFD-pretreated wild-type versus MCK-DGAT1 mice. C: Relative gene expression levels 
of PDK4 in soleus muscles from sedentary (Sed) versus exercised (Exe) wild-type mice. The swimming exercise regimen is as previously described 
(3); P values and n are as indicated. D: Western blot analysis of CD36, UCP3, and PDK4 in soleus muscle from the 8-week HFD-pretreated 
wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice. WT, wild type. </p>

<p>FAT AND GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MCK-DGAT1 MICE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>the 24-h refeeding period between MCK-DGAT1 and wild-
type mice (Fig. 4G). 
Long-term food intake was followed in mice fed a standard 
rodent diet (total 11 weeks) or a HFD (total 8 weeks), 
starting at 2 months of age. Periodic fluctuations in food 
intake were observed in both transgenic and wild-type 
mice, more so in standard rodent diet-fed mice (Fig. 5A). 
However, no difference was found between the two geno-</p>

<p>types either on standard rodent diet or on HFD (Fig. 5A 
and B). A small but significant body weight difference 
(5-10%) was found between wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 
mice on HFD, which became evident after 5 weeks of HFD 
feeding and persisted throughout the remaining study 
period (Fig. 5C). In the absence of reduced food intake or 
increased physical activities, this finding indicates that 
metabolic energy expenditure in DGAT1-HF mice was </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Fat 
Lean </p>

<p>Body composition 
by MRI (g) </p>

<p>HFD Food intake 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>3500 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>4500 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>4500 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>Fasting 
Re-feeding </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>ad lib feeding </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Day Night </p>

<p>Ad lib Re-feeding </p>

<p>To tal </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Day Night Total </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Beam breaks 
(x1000) 
RER </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Body composition 
by MRI (g) </p>

<p>HFD Food intake 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 
WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT </p>

<p>WT 
DGAT 
NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>3500 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>4500 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>2500 </p>

<p>3000 </p>

<p>3500 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>WT 
Dgat1 </p>

<p>VO2 (ml/kg/hr) </p>

<p>Fasting 
Re-feeding </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>G 
F </p>

<p>D 
A </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>9 
1 5 9 
13 17 21 </p>

<p>9 
1 5 9 
13 17 21 
9 
1 58 
13 17 21 </p>

<p>Time (hr) </p>

<p>ad lib feeding </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>** ** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Beam breaks 
(x1000) 
RER </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Physical activity and whole-body oxygen consumption. Two-month-old male wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice were treated with 8-week 
HFD as in Fig. 1 before indirect calorimetry study. Weight-matched mice were used in this study to avoid the need to correct for differences in 
weight and body composition across the groups (wild-type vs. MCK-DGAT1 mice). A: Body composition by magnetic resonance imaging (MRI). B. 
locomotor activity. C: Twenty-four hour oxygen consumption (VO 2 ). D: RER, the above were measured during the study period while the mice had 
ad lib access to HFD. In a separate experiment, VO 2 was measured in the same wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice during a 24-h fasting period (E), 
followed by a 24-h period of ad lib refeeding (F). Food intake during the 24-h period of ad lib feeding and during the 24-h refeeding period were 
also measured (G). Data are expressed as means SE; P values are as indicated or denoted by "NS" for no statistical significance or **P &lt; 0.01. 
WT, wild type. </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 </p>

<p>WT (n=5) 
Dgat1(n=6) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>WT (n=4) 
Dgat1 (n=5) </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>FI (g/day) </p>

<p>Average FI 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>Average FI 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>Chow </p>

<p>HFD </p>

<p>Time (day) 
FI (g/day) 
Body weight (g) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 </p>

<p>WT (n=16) 
Dgat1 (n=20) </p>

<p>Time (week) </p>

<p>* * ** ** ** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 10 11 </p>

<p>WT (n=5) 
Dgat1(n=6) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 </p>

<p>WT (n=4) 
Dgat1 (n=5) </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>GROWTH CURVE 
FOOD INTAKE </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>4.5 </p>

<p>WT Dgat1 </p>

<p>FI (g/day) </p>

<p>Average FI 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>Average FI 
(g/d/mouse) </p>

<p>Chow </p>

<p>HFD </p>

<p>FI (g/day) </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Body weight (g) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>8 9 10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 </p>

<p>WT (n=16) 
Dgat1 (n=20) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Time (day) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Food consumption and growth curves. Food intake per day was averaged weekly and plotted over time in separate groups of age-matched 
male wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice either on standard rat diet (A) or on HFD (B) starting at age of 2 months. The growth curve is plotted using 
weekly measured body weights in wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 mice on HFD for 10 weeks starting at age of 2 months (C). P values are denoted by 
"NS" for no statistical significance, *P &lt; 0.05, and **P &lt; 0.01 (n as indicated). WT, wild type. </p>

<p>L. LIU AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 </p>

<p>
higher than that of the WT-HF mice. No differences in 
weight were observed between wild-type and MCK-DGAT1 
mice on standard rodent diet (data not shown). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this study, we first demonstrated in vivo that although 
skeletal muscle of MCK-DGAT1 mice was more resistant 
to developing HFD-induced lipotoxicity, their liver was 
as susceptible for lipotoxic insulin resistance as that of 
wild-type mice. Under hyperinsulinemic-euglycemic clamp 
conditions, MCK-DGAT1 mice were 45% protected 
against HFD-induced insulin resistance at the whole-body 
level compared with wild-type mice. The greater whole-
body insulin sensitivity in HFD-fed MCK-DGAT1 mice 
(compared to HFD-fed wild-type mice) was associated 
with 30% higher uptake of bolus-injected 2-deoxyglucose 
in skeletal muscle under the same feeding and clamp 
conditions, whereas insulin suppression of HGO was sim-
ilarly impaired in these mice, indicating that liver did not 
contribute to the improved whole-body insulin sensitivity. 
We showed that although triglyceride synthesis and 
storage capacities were increased in DGAT1-overexpress-
ing muscle, mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation efficiency 
was also improved. The latter was initially recognized by 
decreased mitochondrial copy number in combination 
with the uncompromised muscle citrate synthase activity 
and increased maximal -HAD and CPT-I activities in 
DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. This was then confirmed 
by increased maximal mitochondrial fatty acid oxidation 
capacity per unit mitochondrial protein in DGAT1-overex-
pressing muscles. Interestingly, MAPR per unit mitochon-
drial proteins was similar in the two genotypes, suggesting 
that the increased fatty acid oxidation efficiency does not 
lead to increased energy efficiency. Gene expression levels 
of muscle PDK4 and UCP3, normalized to -actin expres-
sion levels, were 100% greater in HFD-fed MCK-DGAT1 
mice than in age-, sex-, and diet-matched wild-type mice. 
Although increased PDK4 has been associated with greater 
fuel partition into fatty acid oxidation (31,32), higher levels 
of UCP3 may also signify increased use of fat as fuel 
substrate and/or conversion of fat to thermal energy 
(33,34). It is plausible that the lack of increase in MAPR in 
DGAT1-overexpressing muscle, in the presence of in-
creased fatty acid oxidation rates, is because of increased 
uncoupling of oxidative phosphorylation leading to in-
creased heat production. Although heat production was 
not directly measured, whole-body 24-h VO 2 production 
rates were greater in DGAT1-HF than in WT-HF mice in 
the absence of increased physical activity in the former. 
The increased energy expenditure in MCK-DGAT1 mice 
was further substantiated by the modest but significant 
lower body weight in the transgenic mice relative to 
wild-type mice without any difference in energy intake; 
long-term follow-up of the growth curve showed that 
MCK-DGAT1 mice weighed 5-10% less than wild-type mice 
on an at lib HFD feeding regimen, whereas food consump-
tion was the same in both groups. The reduced body 
weight may contribute to the improved insulin sensitivity 
shown in this study. However, the small weight difference 
appears to result from changed fuel metabolism and is 
unlikely a primary cause of the observed protection 
against lipotoxicity. Marked differences in insulin sensitiv-
ity were seen between "weight-matched" wild-type and 
MCK-DGAT1 mice and between isolated DGAT1 muscle </p>

<p>and wild-type muscle in ex vivo experiments, where 
weight was not a factor (3). 
Insulin resistance is associated with mitochondrial dys-
function in type 2 diabetes (23,35,36) and in the offspring 
of parents with type 2 diabetes (37). Reduced mitochon-
drial function and insulin resistance occur in aging in 
association with reduced mitochondrial DNA copy num-
ber (23). However, the issue regarding mitochondrial 
deficiency and insulin resistance is unresolved (38). The 
present study does not support the hypothesis that reduc-
tion in mitochondrial DNA copy number per se results in 
insulin resistance. In our model, despite a reduction in 
mitochondrial number, mitochondrial ATP production is 
maintained (and heat production probably increased) be-
cause of increased fatty acid oxidation efficiency. These 
findings suggest that mitochondrial quality is more critical. 
In this regard, a recent study by Koves et al. demonstrated 
that stressed mitochondria with greater but incomplete 
fatty acid oxidation are only detrimental to insulin sensi-
tivity (39). The present study further suggests that greater 
fatty acid oxidation capacity associated with increased 
uncoupling activity may also be important in maintaining 
insulin sensitivity. Of course, maintaining adequate oxida-
tive phosphorylation is necessary for muscle contractility, 
particularly during exercise. 
We have previously shown that skeletal muscle overex-
pressing DGAT1 behaved similarly to exercise-trained 
muscle in that it had higher triglyceride content but was 
more insulin sensitive, a phenomenon referred to as the 
"athlete paradox" or "exercise paradox." The decreased 
myocytic DAG and ceramide levels with increased myo-
cytic triglyceride content are the expected effects of 
DGAT1 actions (3). By converting fatty acyl-CoA and DAG 
to triglyceride, DGAT1 is believed to be directly responsi-
ble for lowering the levels of the lipotoxic fatty acid 
derivatives. The key finding of the present study is that 
DGAT1-overexpressing muscle, like exercised muscle, had 
increased fatty acid oxidation capacity, which was associ-
ated with increased steady-state metabolic rates at the 
whole body level and a smaller HFD-induced weight gain 
compared with wild-type mice. Importantly, because these 
findings are made in the muscle-specific DGAT1 transgenic 
mice, DGAT1 overexpression must be primarily responsi-
ble for these paradoxical changes. Because increased 
DGAT1 expression is also observed with exercise, we 
further postulate that DGAT1 may play a key mediatory 
role in exercise-induced augmentation of both triglyceride 
synthesis and, indirectly, mitochondrial fatty acid oxida-
tion. Together, the increased anabolic (triglyceride synthe-
sis/storage) and catabolic (fatty acid oxidation/degradation) 
capacities may both help remove fatty acid intermediates 
that can be overproduced during fatty acid overload. 
Reducing intramyocellular DAG levels to below the 
"threshold of lipotoxicity" is believed necessary to prevent 
the induction of a cascade of signaling events including 
activation of PKC isoforms and Jun NH 2 -terminal kinase-1 
and inhibition of IRS-1, Akt, and GLUT4 in HFD-fed mice 
(3). 
Parallel upregulated triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid 
oxidation seemed perplexing at the first glance because 
anabolic and catabolic pathways usually undergo changes 
in the opposite directions, determined by cellular sub-
strate levels and energy status. However, examination of 
typical myofibers does show interdependency between the 
two aspects of fatty acid metabolism: myofibers that have 
a high triglyceride content are typically the "oxidative" </p>

<p>FAT AND GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MCK-DGAT1 MICE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>type characterized by a high mitochondrial capacity, whereas 
those with low triglyceride content (and high glycogen 
content) are typically "glycolytic." Importantly, compared 
with glycolytic myofibers, oxidative myofibers with 
greater capacities for triglyceride synthesis and fatty acid 
oxidation appear to be intrinsically more insulin sensitive 
(4). The present study provided an example of the "para-
doxical" coupling of lipid synthesis and oxidation in the 
DGAT1-overexpressing muscles. 
Clearly, these are not the usual reciprocal regulations of 
the two aspects of the fatty acid metabolism driven by the 
fatty acid substrate availability. DGAT1 overexpression in 
skeletal muscle increased the capacities of both triglycer-
ide synthesis and fatty acid oxidation and enabled the 
myocytes to endure fat overload without developing sig-
nificant lipotoxicity or insulin resistance. However, instead 
of increasing mitochondrial densities, DGAT1-overex-
pressing muscle appeared to have greater mitochondrial 
fatty acid oxidation efficiency. Whether the improved fatty 
acid oxidation is coupled with increased fatty acid trans-
port (as suggested by upregulation of CD36 and CPT-I) 
and/or potentially increased de novo fatty acid synthesis 
will require further investigation. A "futile cycle" of fatty 
acid metabolism that consists of increased fatty acid 
oxidation coupled with increased de novo fatty acid 
synthesis has been proposed as a thermogenic mechanism 
in muscle (40). 
PDK is a key regulator of fuel partitioning between fatty 
acid and glucose oxidation, and PDK4 is the major isoform 
in muscle (41,42). PDK is acutely regulated, in general, by 
small molecular effectors generated from fatty acid 
oxidation. Gene expression of PDK4 also responds to fuel 
substrate availability and insulin levels (43-46). Addition-
ally, PDK4 gene expression appears to be modulated by 
several more complex biological processes, such as insu-
lin resistance or exercise. Insulin resistance is generally 
associated with upregulation of PDK4 (43,45), which may 
be because of elevated fatty acid overload (47,48) or 
deficient/impaired insulin action (45,46,48). While promot-
ing muscle insulin sensitivity, exercise also "paradoxi-
cally" upregulates PDK4 gene expression in skeletal 
muscle (49,50). Therefore, it appears that a different 
mechanism for upregulating PDK4 is involved in exercise-
trained skeletal muscle and that this mechanism is not 
substrate driven (49). Exercise upregulates PDK4 and fatty 
acid oxidation but does not inhibit insulin-stimulated 
glucose oxidation. In the present study, we showed that 
DGAT1 overexpression produced a result similar to exer-
cise with regard to PDK4 upregulation, increased fatty 
acid oxidation, and insulin sensitivity, suggesting that the 
change in PDK4 expression in this model is also not a 
secondary response to reduced insulin actions. It is cur-
rently unclear, in either the exercise model or the DGAT1-
overexpression model, what mediates upregulation of 
PDK4 gene expression and whether increased mitochon-
drial fatty acid oxidation is directly caused by upregulated 
PDK4. 
In summary, transgenic expression of DGAT1 in skeletal 
muscle results in a series of "paradoxical" metabolic 
changes often seen in the exercise-trained muscle, includ-
ing increased triglyceride synthesis, increased fatty acid 
oxidation, and preserved insulin sensitivity during the 
challenging of fat overload. Although a high triglyceride 
content and PDK4 expression level may serve as markers 
of insulin resistance in sedentary and obese individuals, 
the same parameters may reflect a greater capacity for </p>

<p>fat metabolism. In the latter situation, insulin sensitivity 
is preserved because of reduced levels of intracellular 
fatty acid derivatives. Because DGAT1 is induced in exer-
cise, and because the MCK-DGAT1 model presents a set of 
metabolic features similar to the exercise model, we 
hypothesize that DGAT1 mediates a significant part of 
exercise-induced metabolic remodeling in skeletal muscle. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by National Institutes of Health 
(NIH) Grants DK-60530, DK-071866, DK-063034, HL-73029, 
and HL45095. Contributions also came from New York 
Obesity Research Center Grant DK-026687 and Albert 
Einstein College of Medicine Diabetes Research and Train-
ing Center Grant NIH DK-020541. 
No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article 
were reported. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
FAT AND GLUCOSE METABOLISM IN MCK-DGAT1 MICE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, NOVEMBER 2009 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

</text></tei>