<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2789947" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:48+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To evaluate the clinical course of visual acuity and foveal thickness in the idiopathic epiretinal membrane 
(ERM) after a vitrectomy with the use of triamcinolone. 
Methods: We retrospectively reviewed the records of 30 patients (30 eyes) with ERM that were treated by vitrectomy 
from 2004 to 2008. Visual acuity and foveal thickness from optical coherence tomography imaging was obtained 
preoperatively and at every postoperative follow-up visit. 
Results: Visual acuity improved by two or more lines of vision in 30%, 50%, 60%, and 70%, and stayed the same 
within ±1 line in 47%, 50%, 40%, and 30% at one month, three months, five months, and seven months after surgery. 
Twenty-three percents of the subjects deteriorated by two or more lines of vision within one month after surgery. 
None of the subjects had reduced vision three months after surgery. Foveal thickness decreased significantly after 
surgery. The mean thickness was 409.7±107.9 μm before surgery and 288.6±66.1 μm seven months after surgery. 
Parameters which were significantly correlated with the final visual acuity included preoperative visual acuity (0.683), 
preoperative foveal thickness (0.544), and final foveal thickness (0.643) (p&lt;0.005). 
Conclusions: Foveal thickness and visual acuity improved until seven months after the vitrectomy in patients with 
idiopathic ERM. Preoperative visual acuity, foveal thickness, and final foveal thickness had a significant correlation 
with the final visual acuity. 
Korean J Ophthalmol 2009;23:249-252 ⓒ 2009 by the Korean Ophthalmological Society. </p>

<p>The epiretinal membrane (ERM) is a cellular avascular 
membrane that can cause visual disturbances due to retinal 
wrinkling. Although the natural history of ERM is variable 
and the condition may only have a mild effect on vision, many 
patients report significant symptoms of distortion and blurring 
of vision. ERM can be associated with posterior vitreous 
detachment, retinal breaks, vascular retinopathy, ocular infl-
ammation, some congenital conditions, and intraocular 
surgeries such as post-retinal detachment repair, retinal laser, 
and cryotherapy. However, idiopathic ERM is the most com-
mon. In 1978 Machemer was successful in removing the 
ERM by vitrectomy. Since then, surgery for the treatment of 
idiopathic ERM has had a 70-90% success rate. 
1-3 Today it 
is possible to remove the ERM more precisely with the use 
of triamcinolone during the vitrectomy. 
Several prognostic factors for the success of these surgeries 
have been suggested. These factors include preoperative visual 
acuity, the duration of symptoms, the presence of traction, 
the thickness of the ERM, and the presence of preoperative </p>

<p>macular edema. These factors are still controversial. 
3-5 Optical 
coherence tomography (OCT) offers a method for obtaining 
a quantitative measurement of the macular structure. In eyes 
with ERM, OCT can show increased thickness of the macula, 
loss of the foveal contour, or intraretinal cysts. Recent reports 
indicate that OCT has been used to investigate the preop-
erative or postoperative thickness and morphologic patterns 
of ERM. 
6-8 Massin et al. 
6 used OCT to examine the preo-
perative and postoperative anatomical features of the macula 
in patients who underwent surgery for ERM. However, they 
followed up three months after surgery to avoid the effects 
of nuclear cataracts. This period was too short to evaluate the 
clinical course and assess the prognostic factors. In another 
report, the authors analyzed the correlations between the pre-
operative characteristics of the OCT images and the visual 
improvements in ERM. However, postoperative OCT images 
were not included. </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>The purpose of this study was to evaluate the clinical 
courses of visual acuity and foveal thickness using OCT in 
patients with idiopathic ERM after a vitrectomy. We inves-
tigated the factors that correlated with visual acuity. </p>

<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.23, No.4, 2009 </p>



<p>Table 1. Demographics and clinical characteristics of the epiretinal membrane patients who underwent a vitrectomy </p>

<p>Demographic 
30 patients (30 eyes) 
Gender (Male : Female) 
7 : 23 
Spherical equivalent (diopter) 
0.15±2.50 
Age at the initial visit (yr) 
65.33±6.96 
Follow-up period (mon) 
8.6 (7-17) 
Vitrectomy+cataract surgery </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>18 
Vitrectomy only (phakic eye : pseudophakic eye) </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>12 (7 : 5) 
* Number of patients who underwent a vitrectomy with concomitant cataract surgery; 
 † Number of patients who underwent only a vitrectomy. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods </p>

<p>We reviewed the records of the patients who underwent 
a pars plana vitrectomy for idiopathic ERM between January 
2004 and February 2008. All of the subjects had a complete 
ocular examination to exclude possible peripheral retinal 
breaks or other anomalies which could result in ERM for-
mation. Exclusion criteria included a history of ocular or 
systemic conditions known to be associated with macular 
ERM formation, potentially irreversible significant loss of 
vision, less than seven months of follow-up, and clinical or 
angiographic evidence of a vascular occlusion or other ano-
maly involving the macula. Thirty eyes from 30 subjects were 
included in this study. The patients underwent a standard 
three port pars plana vitrectomy assisted with triamcinolone 
and membrane peeling. The procedures were performed by 
a single surgeon and used high-magnification viewing and 
intraocular forceps. Because the ERM was peeled without 
identification of the internal limiting membrane (ILM), the 
ILM was unintentionally peeled off together with the ERM 
in some patients. Concomitant cataract surgery was performed 
if necessary. Preoperative and postoperative examinations, 
performed at every follow-up visit, included the best-corrected 
visual acuity using a standard Korean visual acuity chart 
(Han's chart). The examinations also included a slit-lamp 
examination, fundus examination, fundus photography, and 
OCT. Patients followed-up every one or two months until 
they showed no further changes in visual acuity. After they 
were stable, they were followed every three to six months 
according to their postoperative status. 
Optical coherence tomography was performed using com-
mercially available equipment (software 3.0; Carl Zeiss Me-
ditec, Dublin, CA, USA). After papillary dilation, measure-
ments of the average thickness of the central 1 mm of the 
retina before and after surgery were compared. All of the 
subjects were divided into two groups according to the con-
comitant cataract surgery. Eighteen eyes underwent a vitrec-
tomy with concomitant cataract surgery; 12 eyes underwent 
a vitrectomy alone. The visual acuity and foveal thickness 
was measured for each group, and statistical analyses were 
carried out. 
The statistical analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 12.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA</rs>). All of the comparisons 
were two-tailed. Means of the two groups were compared us-</p>

<p>ing a t-test. Appropriate prognostic parameters were analyzed 
by Pearson's correlation against the final postoperative visu-
al acuity. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>The 30 subjects in this series consisted of seven men and 
23 women. They ranged in age from 52 to 78 years (mean, 
65.33 years). The follow-up period ranged from seven to 17 
months (mean, 8.7 months) (Table 1). The preoperative 
best-corrected visual acuity in logMAR units was 0.43 
±0.30 (Table 2). Eighteen eyes underwent concomitant cataract 
surgery. Twelve eyes had only a vitrectomy without con-
comitant cataract surgery. Five out of 12 eyes had a previous 
history of cataract surgery before the diagnosis of ERM. 
Visual acuity expressed on a logMAR scale at one month, 
three months, five months, and seven months after 
surgery were 0.45±0.40, 0.27±0.36, 0.22±0.35, 0.21±0.35, 
and 0.20 ±0.34, respectively. Visual acuity on the Han's 
chart at one month, three months, five months, and seven 
months improved by two or more lines of vision, in 30%, 
50%, 60%, and 70% of the patients and remained within ±1 
line in 47%, 50%, 40%, and 30% of the patients, respect-
ively. The proportion of the subjects who had worsened 
by two or more lines of vision decreased to 23% after one 
month and to 0.0% three months after surgery (Table 2). 
Visual acuity changes were greatest one month and three 
months after surgery. None of the eyes in either group 
showed changes in visual acuity seven months after surgery, 
with one exception. This exception was an eye which had ca-
taract surgery after six months due to a secondary cataract. 
Visual acuity improved greatly from one to three months 
after the vitrectomy in patients with idiopathic ERM. 
Seventy percent of the eyes showed visual improvements 
up to approximately seven months after the vitrectomy, 
but not thereafter. 
Optical coherence tomography showed that foveal thickness 
decreased significantly after surgery. The mean foveal thick-
ness was 409.7±107.9 μm before surgery and gradually de-
creased to 288.6±66.1 μm in the seven months after surgery 
(Table 2). 
Visual improvement was greater in the concomitant cataract 
surgery group compared to the group who underwent a vi-
trectomy alone. Visual acuities expressed on a logMAR scale </p>

<p>SI Kwon, et al. IDIOPATHIC EPIRETINAL MEMBRANE AFTER SURGERY </p>



<p>Table 2. LogMAR visual acuity, distribution of eyes according to visual improvement, and foveal thickness before 
and after surgery in all of the eyes (N=30) </p>

<p>Preop </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>3 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>7 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>BCVA 
0.43±0.30 
0.45±0.40 
0.27±0.36 
0.22±0.35 
0.21±0.35 
0.20±0.34 
VA&gt;2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
9 (30) 
15 (50) 
18 (60) 
21 (70) 
21 (70) 
VA&lt;±1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
14 (47) 
15 (50) 
12 (40) 
9 (30) 
9 (30) 
VA&lt;-2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
7 ( 2 3 ) 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Foveal (μm) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>409.7±107.9 
320.9±88.2 
311.9±73.4 
295.9±71.5 
288.6±66.1 
287.9±66.8 
Values are presented as mean±SD or number (%). 
BCVA=best corrected visual acuity expressed on a logMAR scale. 
* Preoperative, 1, 3, 5, 7 mon, and final follow-up after surgery; 
 † Visual acuity in Han's chart improved by two or more ines, stayed the same 
within ±1 line, worsened by two or more lines of vision; 
 ‡ Foveal thickness measured by optical coherence tomography. </p>

<p>Table 3. LogMAR visual acuity, distribution of eyes according to visual improvement, and foveal thickness before 
and after surgery in the eyes that underwent vitrectomy with concomitant cataract surgery and vitrectomy alone </p>

<p>Preop </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>1 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>3 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>5 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>7 mon </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Final </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Vitrectomy with concomitant cataract surgery (N=18) 
BCVA 
0.38±0.27 
0.30±0.33 
0.12±0.21 
0.09±0.18 
0.11±0.20 
0.09±0.17 
VA&gt;2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
7 (39) 
12 (67) 
14 (78) 
15 (83) 
15 (83) 
VA&lt;±1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
7 (39) 
6 (33) 
4 (22) 
3 (17) 
3 (17) 
VA&lt;-2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
4 ( 2 2 ) 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Foveal (μm) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>392.2±87.9 
314.9±44.2 
296.7±58.9 
281.7±58.1 
276.2±51.3 
274.8±52.6 
Vitrectomy alone (N=12) 
BCVA 
0.52±0.34 
0.65±0.39 
0.47±0.44 
0.42±0.45 
0.37±0.46 
0.36±0.47 
VA&gt;2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
2 (17) 
3 (25) 
4 (33) 
6 (50) 
6 (50) 
VA&lt;±1 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
7 (58) 
9 (75) 
8 (67) 
6 (50) 
6 (50) 
VA&lt;-2 </p>

<p> † </p>

<p>-
3 ( 2 5 ) 
0 
0 
0 
0 
Foveal (μm) </p>

<p> ‡ </p>

<p>436.1±132.3 
328.3±125.6 
333.6±88.2 
317.2±86.2 
307.2±82.5 
307.6±82.4 
Values are presented as mean±SD or number (%). 
BCVA=best corrected visual acuity expressed on a logMAR scale. 
* Preoperative, 1, 3, 5, 7 mon, and final follow-up after surgery; 
 † Visual acuity on the Han's chart improved by two or more lines, stayed the 
same within ±1 line, or worsened by two or more lines of vision; 
 ‡ Foveal thickness measured by optical coherence tomography. </p>

<p>preoperatively and one month, three months, five months, and 
seven months after surgery were 0.38±0.27, 0.30±0.33, 0.12 
±0.21, 0.09±0.18, and 0.11±0.20, respectively, in the con-
comitant cataract surgery group. The values in the vitrect-
omy only group were 0.52±0.34, 0.65±0.39, 0.47±0.44, 
0.42±0.45, 0.37±0.46, and 0.36±0.47, respectively (Table 3). 
Visual improvement was statistically significant in the 
concomitant cataract surgery group at three months and five 
months after surgery (p&lt;0.05). The proportion of subjects 
who improved by two or more lines of vision after surgery 
was significantly greater in the concomitant cataract surgery 
group compared to those in the vitrectomy only group (Table 
3). The foveal thickness before and after surgery showed no 
significant differences between the two groups (p&gt;0.05). 
The parameters which were statistically significantly cor-
related with the final visual acuity included the preoperative 
visual acuity (0.683), the preoperative foveal thickness (0.544), 
and the final foveal thickness (0.643) (p&lt;0.005). Therefore, 
it may be possible to predict the postoperative visual outcome 
based on preoperative visual acuity and foveal thickness. </p>

<p>D iscussion </p>

<p>Vitrectomy and membrane peeling for the idiopathic epi-
retinal membrane has been reported to result in visual im-
provement in 70-90% of eyes. 
8,9 In this study, visual im-
provement by two or more lines of vision was 30% after 
one month and 70% at the final follow-up. These results are 
similar to previous results that have been reported in the 
literature. 
2-7,10 Combined cataract and ERM surgery is 
another option for selected patients who have a concurrent 
cataract. Visual improvement by two or more lines of vision 
in combined cataract and ERM surgery was 39% after one 
month and 83% at the final follow up. The visual 
improvement in the vitrectomy only group was 17% after 
one month and 50% at the final follow-up. Compared to the 
vitrectomy only group, visual acuity was statistically better 
at three months and five months after surgery in the 
concomitant cataract surgery group. However, there was a 
borderline statistically significant difference at seven 
months. Removal of lens opacity could explain the three 
and five month results. Several patients who had undergone </p>

<p>Korean J Ophthalmol Vol.23, No.4, 2009 </p>



<p>a vitrectomy alone had a cataract surgery several months 
after the vitrectomy. This could be the reason why the 
borderline difference was seen after seven months. Because 
there were no differences in the foveal thicknesses between 
the concomitant cataract surgery group and the vitrectomy 
only group, concomitant cataract surgery may have little in-
fluence on the foveal thickness. Concomitant cataract surg0 
ery could enhance the visual improvement during the early 
postoperative period by removing lens opacity. However, a 
vitrectomy and delayed cataract surgery could show similar 
long-term visual outcomes. 
Massin et al. 
6 reported that foveal thickness decreased 
significantly after surgery in 55 of 62 cases. Foveal thickness 
did not return to a normal macular profile. The mean foveal 
thickness was 326±59 μm after surgery in 42 cases. Postope-
rative visual acuity did not correlate with preoperative and 
postoperative central macular thickness. However, there have 
been several reports that visual acuity does correlate with 
preoperative and postoperative foveal thickness. </p>

<p>10,11 </p>

<p>In our study foveal thickness decreased significantly from 
409.7±107.9 μm before surgery to 287.9±66.8 μm at the final 
follow-up after surgery. This is still greater than the normative 
data. The final visual acuity correlated with preoperative visual 
acuity (0.683), preoperative foveal thickness (0.544), and final 
foveal thickness (0.643, p&lt;0.005). Visual acuity improved 
in proportion to foveal thickness after surgery. We were able 
to predict the final visual outcome based on the preoperative 
visual acuity and foveal thickness. 
Intra-operative complications could include vitreous he-
morrhage, retinal petechiae, retinal surface damage, and pe-
ripheral iatrogenjuiic retinal breaks. Postoperative compli-
cations could include the recurrence of ERM, accelerated 
nuclear sclerosis of a crystalline lens, retinal detachment, and 
visual field disturbances. The most common complication, 
occurring in 12% to 68% of cases, is accelerated nuclear 
sclerosis of a crystalline lens. 
2,12,13 Recurrence occurs in 3% 
to 12% of cases, and retinal detachment occurs in 3% to 
14%. 
2,12-14 No intraoperative complications were noted in 
our study. Secondary cataracts developed in four of the seven 
phakic eyes (57%) that underwent only a vitrectomy. Two 
of these patients had cataract surgery at six months and 12 
months after the vitrectomy, respectively. Two patients did 
not have cataract surgery. One patient refused to have cataract 
surgery because of her general condition. An optic neuropathy 
was identified during follow-up in the other patient. Conse-
quently, we did not recommend cataract surgery. One eye out 
of the 30 subjects (3%) had a partially persistent ERM, and </p>

<p>a recurrence of ERM was seen in one eye out of 30 
subjects (3%) six months after surgery. A retinal hole was 
found in one eye, and it was immediately treated with a 
barrier laser. 
Foveal thickness and visual acuity showed improvements 
in patients with idiopathic ERM until seven months after 
the vitrectomy. Preoperative visual acuity, foveal thickness, 
and final foveal thickness showed a significant correlation 
with the final visual acuity. Because of this, surgeons may 
be able to predict the final visual outcome based on the 
preoperative visual acuity and foveal thickness. </p>



</text></tei>