<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2686489" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The MAPU 2.0 database contains proteomes of 
organelles, tissues and cell types measured by 
mass spectrometry (MS)-based proteomics. In con-
trast to other databases it is meant to contain a 
limited number of experiments and only those with 
very high-resolution and -accuracy data. MAPU 2.0 
displays the proteomes of organelles, tissues and 
body fluids or conversely displays the occurrence 
of proteins of interest in all these proteomes. 
Mass spectrometry (MS)-based proteomics has progressed 
dramatically in throughput, accuracy and sensitivity and 
this trend shows no sign of abating (1,2). In order to make 
the data useful to the larger biomedical community, they 
have to be easily accessible via the web. Existing proteome 
databases have focused on different aspects of proteomic 
data capture and data mining. The PRIDE database, for 
example, was primarily developed as a vehicle to share 
proteomic experiments (3). The PeptideAtlas project, on 
the other hand, is mainly interested in collecting data on 
peptide fragmentation patterns as a tool for improving 
future proteomics experiments (4,5). In a similar vein, </p>

<p>the Global Proteome Machine Database (GPMDB), col-
lects tandem mass spectra with a view to improve peptide 
identification (6,7). These and other proteome databases 
are beginning to be connected in the ProteomExchange 
Consortium (8). 
In contrast to the above efforts, our group has focused 
on the development of a proteome database specifically 
for very high-resolution and high-accuracy data. Such 
data could previously only be generated by a few specia-
lized laboratories but the required instrumentation has 
now spread to hundreds of sites. By only admitting 
high-resolution data, we avoid a problem endemic to data-
bases that aggregate a wide variety of heterogeneous data, 
namely the control of overall false positive rates for pro-
tein identification. 
The Max-Planck Unified (MAPU) proteome database 
contains data from large-scale projects on the mapping of 
body fluids, tissues and cell lines (9). Its new version, 
MAPU 2.0, provides a comprehensive proteome informa-
tion system consisting of the data integration of combined 
large-scale proteomic projects and the inclusion of protein 
annotations from standard protein databases, such as 
UniProt (10). To allow the peptide-based retrieval of 
high-accuracy proteomic data across projects in a scalable 
way, we changed the basic concept of the MAPU database 
completely. The main modifications are the combination 
of various proteomic sub-databases, of a modern pro-
gramming environment (C# and .NET) allowing a rich 
graphical user experience, solving MS specific problems 
such as peptide-to-protein assignments, the inclusion of 
additional large-scale proteomic datasets, the detailed 
cross-reference to SwissProt annotations and two-way 
connection to EnsEMBL using Distributed Annotation 
Service (DAS) technology. 
The last point is specifically pertinent, because as the 
number of sequenced genomes increases rapidly (11), the 
annotation of these sequences with biological information 
becomes increasingly important. Mapping large-scale 
data derived from MS-based proteomics to the genome 
sequence is one valuable annotation because it verifies </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +49 89 8578 2557; Fax: +49 89 8578 2219; Email: mmann@biochem.mpg.de </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>genes and gene models for part of the genome. The 
EnsEMBL project provides an excellent system to inte-
grate any kind of data that contributes to the annotation 
of the genome (12,13). In MAPU 2.0, we map high-accu-
racy proteomic data to the genome in a two way fashion 
and used the DAS source system to illustrate certain fea-
tures including the presence of the protein in specific cell 
types for each identified gene transcript. </p>

<p>METHODS AND MATERIALS </p>

<p>General concept of MAPU 2.0 </p>

<p>The initial content and format of MAPU have been 
described in Zhang et al. (9). The basic schema of the 
database has changed dramatically, and the new database 
version unifies all sub-databases by reassigning the mea-
sured peptides along with their corresponding data from 
each experiment to protein entries of an updated database 
version. The new architecture is based in part on concepts 
developed for the Phosphorylation Site Database 
[PHOSIDA; www.phosida.com (14,15)]. It allows the 
organism-specific retrieval of various cell-type and organ-
elle associated proteomic data. The user can query the 
database organism-specifically by protein name, protein 
description, gene symbol, accession of the database used 
for identification [such as the International Protein Index 
(IPI) (16)], SwissProt accession identifier, protein sequence 
or peptide sequence (Figure 1, left panel). If more than 
one protein entry matches with the submitted query string, 
MAPU 2.0 will list all relevant proteins and mark the ones 
identified in at least one proteomic experiment, in red 
(Figure 1, middle panel). Clicking on one of the red high-
lighted entries leads to the result page (Figure 1, right 
panel). If there is just a single match to the query, the 
web user will be guided directly to the result page describ-
ing the inquired protein. The left panel of the resulting </p>

<p>web page displays investigated cell types and tissues. If 
the protein was detected in a certain sub-proteome, 
the corresponding button is highlighted (Figure 1, right 
panel). Otherwise, the image of the tissue or cell type is 
illustrated in light colors indicating the absence of the 
specified protein of interest. Clicking on one of the buttons 
on the left panel results in the complete listing of all pep-
tides that have been measured in the selected cell type 
along with associated data such as peptide identification 
scores or identification scores for post-translational mod-
ifications (PTMs) (Figure 2). 
The peptide-to-protein assignment presents one of the 
main problems in 'shotgun' MS, where proteins are first 
digested to peptides, since a given peptide might occur in 
several proteins (17). Multiple incidences of a certain pep-
tide sequence can cause ambiguous protein assignments. In 
accordance with Occam's razor, we assign a given peptide 
sequence to the candidate protein with the highest number 
of peptides within one project. The user is alerted to this 
problem by color highlighting the listed peptides: green 
indicates that the selected protein of interest has the max-
imum number of peptides in comparison to all other pro-
teins that contain the same peptide, whereas blue indicates 
that there is another protein entry that contains the peptide 
and shows the same number of identified peptides in total. 
Red points to the occurrence of another protein, which 
shows a higher number of detected peptides in total and 
thus presents the more likely associated protein. When 
pointing the mouse to one of the corresponding 'occur-
rences' buttons, a blue colored pop-up box lists all protein 
entries that contain the given peptide along with the total 
number of containing peptides that have been identified 
(Figure 2). If the experimental design included the organel-
lar localizations of proteins, all organelles in which the 
protein of interest was detected are listed. 
In addition to the illustration of associated cell types 
and organelles along with the measured peptides, general </p>

<p>Figure 1. To retrieve proteomic data for a protein of interest, one can search organism specifically via accession number, gene symbol, protein 
description, protein name or peptide sequence (left panel). If there are several hits for a query, all potential proteins of interest are listed (middle 
panel). Proteins that have been identified in any of the projects in MAPU 2.0 are shown in red. The final result page provides a total overview of cell 
types and tissues that contain the protein of interest (right panel). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D903 </p>

<p>information about the protein is provided: Besides protein 
descriptions and full protein sequences, the corresponding 
<rs type="software">Gene Ontology</rs> identifiers (18) are listed linking to the 
<rs type="software">Gene Ontology</rs> web site reporting full descriptions of 
the selected annotation. Furthermore, the annotations to 
each instance include PubMed references and general fea-
tures such as active sites, motifs, domains or signaling sites 
derived from SwissProt (Figure 3). Since there may be 
several isoform entries corresponding to one SwissProt 
entry, we BLASTP-aligned the protein sequence of each 
SwissProt instance with that of the corresponding entry of 
the database used for matching the spectra to peptide 
sequence (usually the IPI). The main purpose of this exten-
sive alignment approach is to derive the exact sequence 
positions of relevant protein features that are annotated 
in SwissProt within the protein sequences of the entry of 
the database used for MS identification. 
Proteomics datasets containing quantitative informa-
tion in the form of isotope ratios are becoming the norm 
rather than the exception (19). In this case, the median 
quantitative data of all measured and assigned peptides 
is taken to quantify the protein. 
Additionally, each displayed web page includes a ques-
tion mark button that directs to the help section of MAPU 
2.0 describing the format of the current page or exempli-
fying the web application guideline. These help sections 
are also available via the 'background' section of 
MAPU 2.0, which also contains general descriptions of 
the experimental designs of various projects. </p>

<p>To allow the retrieval of legacy sub-databases that 
could not be included in the new concept, a link to the 
old database version is provided. This is the case for the 
organellar database (20) as well as the red blood cell data-
base (21), as both datasets are exclusively protein-based 
and therefore cannot be mapped to MAPU 2.0 due to the 
lack of peptide information. 
MAPU 2.0 is based on a modern and scalable software 
architecture, namely C# and the <rs type="software">ASP.NET</rs> technology. 
This allows MAPU 2.0 to share class libraries, with 
PHOSIDA (15). The concepts and web applications of 
MAPU 2.0 and PHOSIDA are very similar and show 
that very distinct proteomic databases can be built using 
shared components. </p>

<p>Genome Annotation </p>

<p>We spent particular efforts on precisely mapping our high-
resolution proteomic data to the genome. For this pur-
pose, we extracted measured peptides of each proteomic 
dataset and reassigned the peptide sequences to genes 
annotated in the EnsEMBL database (11). If a specified 
peptide matches with sequences of more than one trans-
lated gene, we assigned the peptide to the gene transcript 
that shows the highest number of matching peptides 
in total within the associated project. Therefore, the 
peptide-to-gene transcript assignment results one-to-one 
relationships reducing potential redundancy. </p>

<p>Figure 3. For each protein that has a SwissProt accession number, 
general features such as active sites, domains and motifs are displayed 
and mapped to the entry of the database that was used for 
identification. </p>

<p>Figure 2. For each project, all measured peptides are listed along with 
validation scores such as the <rs type="software">Mascot</rs> protein identification score. </p>

<p>D904 Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue </p>

<p>The genome annotation section is accessible via the 
'notepad' button located next to the main 'web book' of 
MAPU 2.0 (Figure 4). The user first selects a species of 
interest. The karyotype of the selected species is illustrated 
along with a link that connects to the EnsEMBL genome 
annotation webpage. Clicking of the displayed chromo-
somes generates a more detailed image of the chosen 
chromosome along with general information including 
chromosome length, number of known and predicted 
genes, quantity of occurring single nucleotide polymorph-
isms (SNPs) and number of gene transcripts. Besides these 
annotations, which are derived from the EnsEMBL data-
base, the number of gene transcripts that have been iden-
tified in MAPU 2.0 is indicated. 
Furthermore, each chromosome is divided into 93 bins: 
on the left hand side the number of transcripts annotated 
in <rs type="software">EnsEMBL</rs> is displayed. Selecting one of the bin boxes 
pops up the EnsEMBL web page, showing a detailed view 
of the selected chromosome region. On the right hand 
side, the number of transcripts that have been detected 
in any of the uploaded projects is illustrated for each 
bin. Clicking on one of these bin buttons results in the 
listing of all identified gene transcripts along with the 
descriptions of the corresponding genes and exact locali-
zations on the chromosome. Moreover, a link is provided 
for each gene transcript that connects to the EnsEMBL 
homepage displaying the full annotation of that tran-
script. In addition to the general annotation of the given 
gene transcript, the pop-up <rs type="software">EnsEMBL</rs> page will show all </p>

<p>peptides that have been identified via the MAPU 2.0 DAS 
source (12). Thus, whenever a web user requests the infor-
mation provided by MAPU 2.0 on EnsEMBL, the data 
included in the MAPU 2.0 database are illustrated via the 
DAS/Proserver system (13). Clicking on one of the illu-
strated peptides yields a report of all the cell types that 
contain the peptides for this gene transcript. In addition to 
the MAPU 2.0 DAS source, we have also established a 
PHOSIDA DAS source providing all phosphorylation 
sites that have been unambiguously identified (Class 1 
sites) (14), but also phosphosites that lack precise identi-
fication within the phosphorylated peptide sequence due 
to insufficient fragment information in MS/MS (ambig-
uous sites). </p>

<p>SUMMARY AND PERSPECTIVES </p>

<p>MAPU 2.0 is a database specifically created for high-
resolution, high-accuracy proteomic data. It provides a 
user-friendly environment and several of its concepts are 
innovative and could be transferred to proteomic data-
bases of a more general nature. We addressed MS-specific 
problems including ambiguous peptide-to-protein assign-
ments by straightforward approaches such as color high-
lighting of given peptide sequences. In addition, we used 
the proteomic data that are integrated in MAPU 2.0 to 
annotate the genome via the DAS technology provided by 
the EnsEMBL project. MAPU 2.0 is becoming a member </p>

<p>Figure 4. The genome annotation section of MAPU 2.0 provides insight into the number of identified gene transcripts. It links each detected 
transcript to the EnsEMBL database, which illustrates gene features derived from proteomic approaches via the MAPU 2.0 and PHOSIDA DAS 
sources. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D905 </p>

<p>of the ProteomExchange Consortium, allowing its data to 
be exchanged with other databases. 
Mass spectrometric data is becoming much more accu-
rate and faster to produce, paralleling in some ways the 
advent of next generation sequencing technology. This will 
also bring particular opportunities and challenges. For 
instance, we believe that proteomic data is now sufficiently 
readily produced in high quality, that it does not make 
sense to store all proteomics results accompanying publi-
cations in central databases, particularly if the data was 
generated in 'one-off ' projects and with low resolution 
technology. Instead, reference proteomes should be mea-
sured with extremely high-accuracy and in dedicated state 
of the art facilities. We intend to further develop MAPU 
with a view to serve as a model database for such high-
accuracy reference proteomes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>We thank Andrew Jenkinson and Eugene Kulesha for 
helping to establish the DAS system for MAPU 2.0, 
Phani Garapati and Markus Fritz for testing the web 
application and Michael Schuster for suggestions. We 
also thank all of the users of our website and especially 
those who have provided feedback. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Marie Curie Fellowship (to F.G.). Part of this work was 
supported by 'Interaction Proteome' as 6th Framework 
program by the EU directorate, which also funded for 
open access charge. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



</text></tei>