<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2808884" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:12+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>REBASE is a comprehensive database of informa-
tion about restriction enzymes, DNA methyl-
transferases and related proteins involved in the 
biological process of restriction-modification 
(R-M). It contains fully referenced information 
about recognition and cleavage sites, isoschi-
zomers, neoschizomers, commercial availability, 
methylation sensitivity, crystal and sequence data. 
Experimentally characterized homing endonucle-
ases are also included. The fastest growing 
segment of REBASE contains the putative R-M 
systems found in the sequence databases. 
<rs type="software">LinkOut</rs>Special thanks are due to the many individuals who have 
so kindly contributed their unpublished results for </p>

<p>Figure 1. The graph shows the numbers of R-M systems entering REBASE since its inception in 1975. The open bars show systems that have been 
characterized either biochemically or genetically. The black bars show the increasing accumulation of potential R-M systems that have been found 
by bioinformatic analysis of sequences in GenBank. The surge in 2004 represents the addition of metagenomic sequences from the Sargasso Sea 
collecting expedition (9). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, Database issue D235 </p>

<p>inclusion in this compilation and to the REBASE users 
who continue to guide our efforts with their helpful 
comments. We are especially grateful to Karen Otto for 
administrative help. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Library of Medicine (LM04971); New England 
Biolabs, Inc. Funding for open access charge: New 
England Biolabs; National Institutes of Health grant. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>





</text></tei>