<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2808580" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-11T20:21+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The aim of this study was to identify the main factor affecting compliance and intima-
media thickness of the elastic common carotid artery in continuous ambulatory peri-
toneal dialysis patients. Increased intima-media thickness and decreased arterial 
compliance are associated with elevated risk of cardiovascular disease. This study 
included 20 patients and 20 age-and sex-matched healthy control subjects. The 
compliance and intima-media thickness of the right common carotid artery within 1 cm 
to the bifurcation were measured three times using high-resolution B-mode echocar-
diography. Blood samples were obtained to measure levels of hemoglobin, phospho-
rus, total calcium, total CO2, serum albumin, C-reactive protein, serum total choles-
terol, LDL-and HDL-cholesterol and triglycerides. We found that the compliance of 
common carotid artery was lower in the patient group than in the control group. In 
the patient group, the compliance of common carotid artery was positively correlated 
with serum albumin concentration, and intima-media thickness of common carotid 
artery was negatively correlated with serum albumin levels. Stepwise regression 
analysis showed that serum albumin concentration was independently related to 
the compliance of common carotid artery, suggesting hypoalbuminemia can inde-
pendently give deleterious effects on the arterial wall in continuous ambulatory peri-
toneal dialysis patients. </p>

<p>Arterial Compliance in CAPD Patients </p>



<p>age of 53.9±12.4 yr and a mean time undergoing continu-
ous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis of 16 months (range: 4-120 
months). 
Individuals with the following medical conditions were ex-
cluded; cardiac failure (New York Heart Association [NYHA] 
class II and higher), unstable angina pectoris (NYHA class 
II and higher), peripheral vascular disease, peripheral pitting 
edema and pulmonary edema, above stage 3 hypertension 
(systolic blood pressure &gt;180 mmHg or diastolic blood pres-
sure &gt;110 mmHg), severe malnutrition (serum albumin &lt;2.5 
gm/dL), established infection and high-sensitivity C-reactive 
protein levels &gt;5 mg/L, intact parathyroid hormone levels 
&gt;200 pg/mL, serum total calcium levels &gt;11 mg/dL, and 
serum phosphate levels &gt;7 mg/dL. In 11 patients the primary 
kidney disease was associated with diabetes mellitus, while 
in 9 patients it was not diabetes-related. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>We compared arterial wall properties of controls and pati-
ents. After 15 min of supine rest, the compliance and intima-
media thickness of the right common carotid artery within 
1 cm to the bifurcation were measured three times using a 
high-resolution B-mode 7.5-MHz transducer. Patients were 
asked not to smoke, eat or drink for 4 hr before measurements 
were performed, but were allowed to take their regular med-
ication. 11 of 20 patients were administered antihypertensive 
drugs (calcium channel blocker, ACE inhibitor, beta-blocker, 
alpha-blocker). None of the antihypertensives nor other vasoac-
tive drugs (calcium containing phosphorus binder, etc.) of the 
patients were changed over 1 month. Blood pressure was mea-
sured 5 times consecutively in a sitting position using a con-</p>

<p>ventional sphygmomanometer by the same nurse on each 
occasion. Mean arterial pressure was calculated using the fol-
lowing formula: (systolic blood pressure+2×diastolic blood 
pressure)/3. Pulse pressure was calculated using the following 
formula: systolic blood pressure-diastolic blood pressure. 
Intima-media thickness was defined as the distance from 
the leading edge of the lumen-intima interface of the far wall 
to the leading edge of the media-adventitia interface of the 
far wall as validated by Pignoli et al. (13). 
Arterial compliance was defined by the arterial volume 
change per unit of pressure. Systolic and end-diastolic arterial 
diameter were measured three times and the compliance of 
the common carotid artery was calculated using the Hayoz 
formula (14): 
Arterial compliance (mm 2 /kPa)=( D× D)/2 P; where 
D=arterial diameter (mm), D=changes in systolic and dias-
tolic arterial diameter, and P=pulse pressure. 
Stroke volume was measured using 2-dimensional echocar-
diography. Stroke volume=left ventricular outflow tract area 
×the systolic velocity integral; where left ventricular outflow 
tract area= (D/2) 2 (D=LV diameter). 
Baseline echocardiography was performed using a Hewlett-
Packard Sonos 100 device equipped with a 2.25-MHz probe, 
allowing M-mode, 2-dimensional and pulsed Doppler mea-
surements. Measurements were made according to the recom-
mendations of the American Society of Echocardiography (15). 
Left ventricular mass was calculated according to the Penn 
convection (16). Left ventricular hypertrophy was defined as 
a left ventricular mass index &gt;136 g/m 2 in men and &gt;110 
g/m 2 in women. 
In the patient group, blood hemoglobin levels were deter-
mined using a Coulter-Genis (Coulter, CA, U.S.A.) machine. 
Blood phosphorus, total calcium and total CO2 levels were 
measured using a Hitachi 747 automatic analyzer, with nor-
mal values considered 1.9-4.4 mg/dL, 8.2-10.4 mg/dL and 
22-28 mol/ L, respectively. Intact parathyroid hormone was 
measured using a commercial immunoradiometric assay (Di-
agnostic products corporation, Los Angeles, CA, U.S.A.), with 
the normal range considered 12-72 pg/mL. Serum albumin 
was measured using a Hitachi 736-740 autoanalyzer (Hitachi 
Ltd, Tokyo, Japan), and high-sensitivity C-reactive protein 
was measured using the N High Sensitivity CRP kit (Dade 
Behring, Marburg, Germany) which has a lower limit of 0.15 
mg/L. Serum total cholesterol, LDL-cholesterol, HDL-choles-
terol and triglyceride levels were measured enzymatically using 
a Hitachi 736-740 autoanalyzer. Analysis of the mean of the 
previous three samples over the preceding 3-month period 
was included. 
To evaluate the total Kt/V urea index (Kt/V) in the patient 
group, the sum of the 24 hr residual and dialytic urea clear-
ances were divided by the urea distribution volume which 
was calculated using Watson's normogram. Residual renal 
function was estimated using the mean values of residual urea 
and creatinine clearances. </p>

<p>Variables 
Control group 
Patient group </p>

<p>Age (yr) 
59.1±10.1 
53.9±12.4 
Men/Women (n) 
10/10 
10/10 
DM/non-DM (n) 
0/20 
11/9 
CAPD duration (mo) 
0 
16 (4-45) 
Total Kt/V urea 
2.03±0.51 
Residual renal function (mL/min) 
2.3 (1-5.6) 
Serum albumin level (g/dL) 
4.4±0.2 
3.6±0.6* 
h-s CRP (mg/L) 
0.50 (0.15-1.50) 2.40 (0.20-5.00)* 
Serum calcium level (mg/dL) 
9.0±1.1 
8.6±0.8* 
Serum phosphorus level (mg/dL) 
3.7±1.3 
5.0±1.9* 
Ca×P product (mg/dL) 
32.15±1.53 
42.45±15.67* 
Total cholesterol level (mg/dL) 
211±60 
191±39 
LDL-cholesterol level (mg/dL) 
115±28 
111±31 
HDL-cholesterol level (mg/dL) 
53±15 
44±9 
PTH level (pg/mL) 
90.71±27.03 </p>

<p>Table 1. Subject characteristics </p>

<p>Figures represent mean±S.D or median (range), *p&lt;0.05 versus control 
group. 
h-s CRP, high sensitivity C-reactive protein; Ca×P product, calcium× 
phosphorus product; LDL, low density lipoprotein; HDL, high density 
lipoprotein; PTH, parathyroid hormone. </p>



<p>D.-J. Oh, K.-J. Lee </p>

<p>Statistical analysis was performed using Student's unpaired 
t-tests and Mann-Whitney U tests (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> Windows <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 9.0</rs>). Relationships between different parameters were assessed 
using Spearman's correlation coefficient. Where appropriate, 
stepwise regression analysis was performed to assess the con-
tribution of various variables to arterial wall properties. Results 
are expressed as mean±SD or median (range). Differences 
were considered significant if the p value was less than 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>We found that for the control group, the common carotid 
artery compliance was 0.268±0.127 mm 
2 /kPa, which was 
higher than that observed in the patient group, 0.163±0.082 
mm 
2 /kPa (p=0.018) (Table 2). The intima-media thickness 
of the common carotid artery was lower in the control group 
(0.06±0.03 cm) than in the patient group (0.08±0.02 cm; 
p=0.025). The control group left ventricular mass index (111.0 </p>

<p>±24.7 gm/m 
2 ) was lower than that of the patient group 
(174.0±54.8 gm/m 
2 ; p=0.01) (Table 2). In the control group, 
systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, mean arterial 
pressure and pulse pressure were 126±16 mmHg, 78±9 
mmHg, 94±11 mmHg and 48±9 mmHg respectively, 
with each being lower than the corresponding pressure in the 
patient group; 152±18 mmHg, 88±10 mmHg, 109±12 
mmHg and 63±13 mmHg, respectively (p=0.008, p=0.028, 
p=0.031, p=0.015, respectively) (Table 2). Stroke volumes 
were similar in each group; 66.32±26.85 mL/m 
2 in the con-
trol group and 66.10±25.75 mL/m 
2 in the patient group (p= 
0.45). Similarly, ejection fractions were similar for each group; 
60.32±6.35% in the control group and 61.10±20.75% 
in the patient group (p=0.65) (Table 2). 
In the patient group, common carotid artery compliance 
was positively correlated with serum albumin concentration 
(r=0.443; p=0.018) (Fig. 1), and common carotid artery inti-
ma-media thickness was negatively correlated with serum 
albumin concentration (r=-0.418; p=0.025) (Fig. 2). 
Stepwise regression analysis showed that the serum albu-
min concentration ( =0.467, p=0.044) was independently 
associated with common carotid artery compliance (Table 3). </p>

<p>Control group 
Patient group </p>

<p>CCA-AC (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/kPa) 
0.268±0.127 
0.163±0.082* 
CCA-IMT (cm) 
0.06±0.03 
0.08±0.02* 
LVM/BSA (g/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
111.0±24.7 
174.0±54.8* 
SBP (mmHg) 
126±16 
152±18* 
DBP (mmHg) 
78±9 
8 8 ±10* 
MAP (mmHg) 
94±11 
109±12* 
PP (mmHg) 
48±9 
6 3 ±13* 
SV (mL/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>) 
66.32±26.85 
66.10±25.75 
EF (%) 
60.32±6.35 
61.10±20.75 </p>

<p>Table 2. Comparison of hemodynamic parameters in control and 
patient groups </p>

<p>Figures represent mean±S.D. *p&lt;0.05 versus control group. 
CCA-AC, common carotid artery-arterial compliance; CCA-IMT, common 
carotid artery-intima media thickness; LVM/BSA, left ventricular mass/body 
surface area; SBP, systolic blood pressure; DBP, diastolic blood pressure; 
MAP, mean arterial pressure; PP, pulse pressure; SV, stroke volume; EF, 
ejection fraction. </p>

<p>Common carotid artery compliance </p>

<p>Std. Error 
p </p>

<p>Albumin 
0.467 
0.031 
0.044* </p>

<p>Table 3. Stepwise regression analysis with common carotid artery 
compliance as a dependent variable </p>

<p>R2=0.218, F=4.734. 
Selected variables: age, sex, presence of diabetes mellitus, serum albu-
min concentration, high-sensitivity C-reactive protein level, serum total cal-
cium and phosphorus concentrations, calcium×phosphorus product, 
Total/HDL cholesterol, LDL/HDL cholesterol, parathyroid hormone level, 
common carotid artery intima-media thickness, left ventricular mass index, 
systolic blood pressure, diastolic blood pressure, mean arterial pressure, 
pulse pressure and body mass index. </p>

<p>CCA-AC (mm </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>/kPa) </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.5 
3.0 
3.5 
4.0 
4.5 
5.0 </p>

<p>Serum albumin concentration (g/dL) </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Correlation between common carotid artery compliance and 
serum albumin concentration. 
CCA-AC, common carotid artery compliance. </p>

<p>r=0.443 
p=0.018 </p>

<p>CCA-IMT (cm) </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.0 
2.5 
3.0 
3.5 
4.0 
4.5 
5.0 </p>

<p>Serum albumin concentration (g/dL) </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Correlation between common carotid artery intima-media 
thickness and serum albumin concentration. 
CCA-IMT, common carotid artery intima-media thickness. </p>

<p>r=-0.418 
p=0.025 </p>

<p>Arterial Compliance in CAPD Patients </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The present study showed that common carotid artery com-
pliance and intima-media thickness differed between normal 
individuals and continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis 
patients. In addition, the study revealed that in the patient 
group, the compliance and the intima-media thickness were 
related to the serum albumin level. 
Our finding that arterial wall compliance was lower in the 
patient group compared to controls is in agreement with the 
findings of others (8, 12, 17), and there are probably multi-
ple factors which contribute to this reduced compliance in 
renal patients (12). In the present study, we found that serum 
albumin concentration was an independent factor in reduced 
compliance of the common carotid artery. This finding is con-
sistent with recent data suggesting hypoalbuminemia may 
represent a state of accelerated atherosclerosis in dialysis pati-
ents (18). It appears longitudinal studies are needed to con-
firm the nature of the association between albumin levels and 
atherosclerosis, and to elucidate the role of inflammation in 
that association (18). 
Traditionally, low albumin levels were believed to be the 
result of inflammation, and there is evidence that atheroscle-
rosis is an inflammatory process (19, 20). In the dialysis pop-
ulation, there is increasing evidence of a link between inflam-
mation, signified by elevated C-reactive protein or interleu-
kin-6 levels, and cardiovascular mortality (21, 22). Therefore, 
it is possible that poor nutrition, serum albumin levels and 
atherosclerosis could be interlinked by inflammation. How-
ever, in contrast, a recent study (23) showed that protein mal-
nutrition (diagnosed based upon total body nitrogen levels) 
and hypoalbuminemia were independently predictive of mor-
tality, whereas only hypoalbuminemia was predictive of vas-
cular morbidity. That study suggested hypoalbuminemia 
itself was pathogenically associated with vascular disease, but 
dissociated this effect from protein malnutrition (23). In the 
present study, we excluded patients with severe malnutrition 
and those with a level of established infection above the upper 
level of that observed in normal controls. Our data revealed 
no relationship between serum high sensitivity C-reactive 
protein levels and common carotid artery compliance in the 
patient group. This finding suggests that the serum albumin 
level itself is related to changes in compliance and intima-
media thickness in the elastic common carotid artery. 
Hypoalbuminemia may result in a hypercoagulable state 
(24) and may deplete L-arginine stores with a subsequent 
reduction in nitric oxide synthesis (24). Nitric oxide causes 
equipotent relaxation of arterial smooth muscle (25) and in-
hibits platelet aggregation (26). In our stepwise regression 
analysis, serum albumin levels were correlated with common 
carotid artery compliance independent of age, blood pressure, 
common carotid artery intima-media thickness, calcium and 
phosphorus levels, lipid profile and high-sensitivity C-reac-
tive protein levels. Furthermore, the common carotid artery </p>

<p>intima-media thickness was found to be inversely proportional 
to serum albumin levels. These results suggest that in the 
patient group, the wall properties of the common carotid artery 
are linked to serum albumin concentration. 
In the present study, although blood pressure in the patient 
group was higher than in controls, there was no relationship 
between blood pressure and compliance or intima-media thick-
ness of the common carotid artery. This finding that factors 
other than blood pressure per se affect arterial wall compliance 
is consistent with findings of the Tassin population study 
showing that arterial compliance was lower in long-term nor-
motensive hemodialysis patients (27). 
The design of the present study (cross-sectional) meant that 
it was unable to address whether hypoalbuminemia itself 
reflects vascular events and mortality in the patient group. 
Therefore, to determine the relationship between serum albu-
min level and vascular events in the patient group, longitu-
dinal follow-up studies with addition of nutritional markers 
are needed. In addition, future studies will ideally have larger 
and more homogenous subject groups compared to the pre-
sent study. While the present study did not examine patient 
volume status using reliable and objective methods, contin-
uous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis patients have relatively 
stable volume status compared to hemodialysis patients, and 
we excluded patients with peripheral pitting edema and pul-
monary edema. Therefore, we believe the results obtained in 
this study were not influenced by patient volume status. 
In conclusion, the present study showed that common ca-
rotid artery wall properties were independently associated with 
serum albumin levels, suggesting that independent of other 
factors, hypoalbuminemia can cause deleterious effects on arte-
rial wall properties in continuous ambulatory peritoneal dial-
ysis patients. </p>





<p>D.-J. Oh, K.-J. Lee </p>



</text></tei>