<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2238715" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The transgenomic metabolic effects of exposure to either Lactobacillus paracasei or Lactobacillus 
rhamnosus probiotics have been measured and mapped in humanized extended genome mice 
(germ-free mice colonized with human baby flora). Statistical analysis of the compartmental 
fluctuations in diverse metabolic compartments, including biofluids, tissue and cecal short-chain 
fatty acids (SCFAs) in relation to microbial population modulation generated a novel top-down 
systems biology view of the host response to probiotic intervention. Probiotic exposure exerted 
microbiome modification and resulted in altered hepatic lipid metabolism coupled with lowered 
plasma lipoprotein levels and apparent stimulated glycolysis. Probiotic treatments also altered a 
diverse range of pathways outcomes, including amino-acid metabolism, methylamines and SCFAs. 
The novel application of hierarchical-principal component analysis allowed visualization of 
multicompartmental transgenomic metabolic interactions that could also be resolved at the 
compartment and pathway level. These integrated system investigations demonstrate the potential 
of metabolic profiling as a top-down systems biology driver for investigating the mechanistic basis of 
probiotic action and the therapeutic surveillance of the gut microbial activity related to dietary 
supplementation of probiotics. 
The gut microbiome-mammalian 'Superorganism' (Leder-
berg, 2000) represents a level of biological evolutionary 
development in which there is extensive 'transgenomic' 
modulation of metabolism and physiology that is a character-
istic of true symbiosis. By definition, superorganisms contain 
multiple cell types, and the coevolved interacting genomes can 
only be effectively studied as an in vivo unit in situ using top-
down systems biology approaches (Nicholson, 2006; Martin 
et al, 2007a). Interest in the impact of gut microbial activity on 
human health is expanding rapidly and many mammalian-
microbial associations, both positive and negative, have been 
reported (Dunne, 2001; Verdu et al, 2004; Nicholson et al, </p>

<p>2005; Gill et al, 2006; Ley et al, 2006). Mammalian-microbial 
symbiosis can play a strong role in the metabolism of 
endogenous and exogenous compounds and can also be 
influential in the etiology and development of several diseases, 
for example insulin resistance (Dumas et al, 2006), Crohn's 
disease (Gupta et al, 2000; Marchesi et al, 2007), irritable 
bowel syndrome (Sartor, 2004; Martin et al, 2006), food 
allergies (Bjorksten et al, 2001), gastritis and peptic ulcers 
(Warren, 2000; Marshall, 2003), obesity (Ley et al, 2006; 
Turnbaugh et al, 2006), cardiovascular disease (Pereira and 
Gibson, 2002) and gastrointestinal cancers (Dunne, 2001). 
Activities of the diverse gut microbiota can be highly specific 
and it has been reported that the establishment of Bifidobacteria 
is important for the development of the immune system and </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 1 </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 4; Article number 157; doi:10.1038/msb4100190 
Citation: Molecular Systems Biology 4:157 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group All rights reserved 1744-4292/08 </p>

<p>www.molecularsystemsbiology.com </p>

<p>for maintaining gut function (Blum and Schiffrin, 2003; 
Salminen et al, 2005; Ouwehand, 2007). In particular, elevated 
counts in Bifidobacterium with reduced Escherichia coli, 
streptococci, Bacteroides and clostridia counts in breast-fed 
babies compared to formula-fed neonates may result in the 
lower incidence of infections, morbidity and mortality in 
breast-fed infants (Dai et al, 2000; Kunz et al, 2000). As the 
microbiome interacts strongly with the host to determine the 
metabolic phenotype (Holmes and Nicholson, 2005; Gavaghan 
McKee et al, 2006) and metabolic phenotype influences 
outcomes of drug interventions (Nicholson et al, 2004; Clayton 
et al, 2006), there is clearly an important role of understanding 
these interactions as part of personalized healthcare solutions 
(Nicholson, 2006). 
One of the current approaches used to modulate the balance 
of intestinal microflora is based on oral administration of 
probiotics. A probiotic is generally defined as a 'live microbial 
feed supplement which beneficially affects the host animal by 
improving its intestinal microbial balance' (Fuller, 2004). The 
gastrointestinal system is populated by potentially pathogenic 
bacteria that are capable of degrading proteins (putrefaction), 
releasing ammonia, amines and indoles, which in high 
concentrations can be toxic to humans (Cummings and 
Bingham, 1987). Probiotic supplementation aims at replacing 
or reducing the number of potentially harmful E. coli and 
Clostridia in the intestine by enriching the populations of gut 
microbiota that ferment carbohydrates and that have little 
proteolytic activity. Probiotics, most commonly Lactobacillus 
and Bifidobacteria, can be used to modulate the balance of the 
intestinal microflora in a beneficial way (Collins and Gibson, 
1999). Although Lactobacilli do not predominate among the 
intestinal microflora, their resistance to acid conditions and 
bile salts toxicity results in their ubiquitous presence through-
out the gut (Corcoran et al, 2005), hence they can exert 
metabolic effects at many levels. Fermented dairy products 
containing Lactobacillus have traditionally been used to 
modulate the microbial ecology (Dunne, 2001). In particular, 
L. paracasei was shown to modulate the intestinal physiology, 
to prevent infection of pathogenic bacteria (Sarker et al, 2005), 
to stimulate the immune system (Ibnou-Zekri et al, 2003), and 
to normalize gastrointestinal disorders (Martin et al, 2006). 
L. rhamnosus is also a significant probiotic strain with proven 
health benefits and therapeutic applications in the treatment of 
diarrhea (Szynanski et al, 2006), irritable bowel syndrome 
(Kajander et al, 2005), atopic eczema (Corcoran et al, 2005) 
and the prevention of urinary tract infections (Reid and Bruce, 
2006). However, the functional effects of probiotic interven-
tions cannot be fully assessed without probing the biochem-
istry of the host at multiple compartmental levels, and we 
propose that top-down systems biology provides an ideal 
approach to further understanding in this field. The microbiota 
observed in human baby flora (HBF) mice have a number of 
similarities with that found in formula-fed neonates (Mackie 
et al, 1999), which makes it to be a well-adapted and simplified 
model to assess probiotics impact on gut microbial functional 
ecosystems (in particular on metabolism of Bifidobacteria 
and potential pathogens) and subsequent effects on host 
metabolism. 
Metabolic profiling using high-density data generating 
spectroscopic techniques, in combination with multivariate </p>

<p>mathematical modelling is a tool which is well suited to 
generate metabolic profiles that encapsulate the top-down 
system response of an organism to a stressor or intervention 
(Nicholson and Wilson, 2003). Multivariate metabolic profil-
ing offers a practical approach to measuring the metabolic 
endpoints that link directly to whole system activity and which 
are determined by both host genetic and environmental factors 
(Nicholson et al, 2005). Recently, metabolic profiling strategies 
have been successfully applied to characterizing the metabolic 
consequences of nutritional intervention (Rezzi et al, 2007; 
Wang et al, 2007) the effects of the gut microflora on 
mammalian metabolism (Martin et al, 2006, 2007a, b) and 
mechanisms of insulin-resistance (Dumas et al, 2006). In the 
current study, 1 H nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectro-
scopy and targeted ultra performance liquid chromatography-
mass spectrometry (UPLC-MS) analysis have been applied to 
characterize the global metabolic responses of humanized 
microbiome mice subsequently exposed to placebo, Lactoba-
cillus paracasei or Lactobacillus rhamnosus supplementation. 
Correlation of the response across multiple biofluids and 
tissue, using plasma, urine, fecal extracts, liver tissues and 
ileal flushes as the biological matrices for the detection of 
dietary intervention, generates a top-down systems biology 
view of the response to probiotics intervention. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Gut bacterial composition </p>

<p>Microbiological analyses were performed on fecal samples to 
assess the growth of the HBF in germ-free mice and to ascertain 
the effects of probiotics on the development of gut bacteria. 
The measured terminal composition of the fecal microbiota is 
detailed in Table I, where the statistically significant differences 
between the various groups were calculated using a two-
tailed Mann-Whitney test. The bacterial populations of 
Bifidobacteria longum and Staphylococcus aureus were reduced 
after introduction of both probiotics. Additionally, unique 
effects of L. rhamnosus supplementation caused decreased 
populations of Bifidobacterium breve, Staphylococcus epidermi-
dis and Clostridium perfringens but an increase of E. coli. </p>

<p>Gut levels of short-chain fatty acids </p>

<p>Short-chain fatty acids (SCFAs), namely acetate, propionate, 
isobutyrate, n-butyrate and isovalerate, were identified and 
quantified from the cecal content using GC-FID. The results, 
presented in Table II, are given in mmol per gram of dry fecal 
material and as mean ± s.d. for each group of mice. The 
production of some of the SCFAs, that is, acetate and butyrate, 
by the HBF mice supplemented with both of the probiotics 
was reduced. In addition, increases of the concentrations in 
isobutyrate and isovalerate were observed in the mice fed with 
L. paracasei. </p>

<p>Analysis of 1 H NMR spectroscopic data on plasma, 
urine, liver and fecal extracts </p>

<p>A series of pairwise O-PLS-DA models of 1 H NMR spectra were 
performed to extract information on the metabolic effects of </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>2 Molecular Systems Biology 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>probiotic modulation. A statistically significant metabolic 
phenotype separation between untreated mice and probiotic 
supplemented animals was observed as reflected by the 
high value of Q Y 
2 for each model (Cloarec et al, 2005b; Table 
III). The corresponding coefficients describing the most 
important metabolites in plasma, liver, urine and fecal extracts 
that contributed to group separation are also listed in 
Supplementary Table 1. The area normalized intensities 
(10 1 a.u.) of representative metabolite signals are given as 
means ± s.d. in Table III. The O-PLS-DA coefficients plots are 
presented in Figure 1 using a back-scaling transformation and 
projection to aid biomarker visualization (Cloarec et al, 
2005b). The direction of the signals in the plots relative to 
zero indicates positive or negative covariance with the 
probiotic-treated class. Each variable is plotted with a color 
code that indicates its discriminating power as calculated from 
the correlation matrix thus highlighting biomarker-rich 
spectral regions. </p>

<p>Liver metabolic profiles </p>

<p>Livers of mice fed with L. paracasei showed relative decreases 
in dimethylamine (DMA), trimethylamine (TMA), leucine, 
isoleucine, glutamine, and glycogen and increased levels of 
succinate and lactate (Figure 1A). Mice supplemented with 
L. rhamnosus showed relative decreases in leucine and 
isoleucine and relative increases in succinate, TMA and 
trimethylamine-N-oxide (TMAO) in the liver compared to 
controls (Figure 1D). </p>

<p>Plasma metabolic profiles </p>

<p>Plasma samples showed relative decreases in the levels of 
lipoproteins and increases in the concentrations of glycero-</p>

<p>phosphorylcholine (GPC) and triglycerides in mice fed with 
both probiotics compared to controls (Figure 1B and E). 
Elevated choline levels were observed in plasma of mice fed 
with L. rhamnosus and reduced plasma citrate levels were 
observed in mice fed with L. paracasei compared to controls. </p>

<p>Fecal extract metabolic profiles </p>

<p>Marked changes were observed in the metabolic profiles of 
fecal extracts from all supplemented mice, for example relative 
decreased concentrations of choline, acetate, ethanol, a range 
of putative N-acetylated metabolites (NAMs), unconjugated 
bile acids (BAs) and tauro-conjugated bile acids (Figure 1C and 
F). Furthermore, relative higher levels of glucose, lysine and 
polysaccharides were detected in the feces from mice fed with 
probiotics. A relative increased level of n-caproate (chemical 
shifts d at 0.89(t), 1.27(m), 1.63(q), 2.34(t)) appeared to be 
associated with mice supplemented with L. paracasei. </p>

<p>Urine metabolic profiles </p>

<p>Urine samples of mice supplemented with both probiotics 
showed relative increased concentrations of indoleacetylgly-
cine (IAG), phenylacetylglycine (PAG), tryptamine and a 
relative decrease in the levels of a-keto-isocaproate and citrate 
(Figure 1G and H). Relative increased concentrations of a 
mixture of putative glycolipids (UGLp, chemical shifts of 
multiplets at d 0.89, 1.27, 1.56, 1.68, 2.15, 2.25, 3.10, 3.55, 
3.60), N-acetyl-glycoproteins (NAGs) and a reduction in 
3-hydroxy-isovalerate were also observed in mice supplemen-
ted with L. paracasei compared to controls. Urine of mice fed 
with L. rhamnosus showed a reduction in levels of creatine and 
citrulline. </p>

<p>Table II Short-chain fatty acid content in the cecum from the different groups </p>

<p>Amounts of SCFAs given in mmol per gram of dry 
feces for each group </p>

<p>Acetate 
Propionate 
Isobutyrate 
Butyrate 
Isovalerate </p>

<p>HBF (n=10) 
77.6±17.6 
22.3±4.3 
0.9±0.2 
3±0.6 
2.1±0.6 
HBF+L. paracasei (n=9) 
52.3 ± 23.6*** 
22.2 ± 10.8 
1.2 ± 0.5*** 
1.5 ± 0.8*** 
2.7 ± 1.2** 
HBF+L. rhamnosus (n=9) 
40.6 ± 8*** 
20.3 ± 2.8 
0.8 ± 0.2 
2.1 ± 0.4*** 
2.1 ± 0.5 </p>

<p>Data are presented in mmol per gram of dry feces and are presented as means±s.d. The amounts of SCFAs for the HBF mice supplemented with probiotics were 
compared to HBF control mice, ** and *** indicate a significant difference at 99 and 99.9% confidence levels, respectively. </p>

<p>Table I Microbial species counts in mouse feces at the end of the experiment </p>

<p>Groups/log 10 CFU 
HBF (n=10) 
HBF+L. paracasei (n=9) 
HBF+L. rhamnosus (n=9) </p>

<p>L. paracasei 
-
8.5±0.2 
-
L. rhamnosus 
-
-
7.8 ± 0.2 
E. coli 
9.2 ± 0.3 
9.4 ± 0.3 
9.8 ± 0.5** 
B. breve 
9.1±0.2 
7.78±2.13 
8.7±0.3* 
B. longum 
8.2 ± 0.6 
5.6 ± 1.9*** 
6.3 ± 0.5*** 
S. aureus 
7.4±0.3 
6.3±0.3*** 
6.6±0.5*** 
S. epidermidis 
4.8 ± 0.4 
4.9 ± 1.2 
4.0 ± 0.5** 
C. perfringens 
7.2 ± 0.3 
7.0 ± 0.5 
5.7 ± 1.0*** 
Bacteroides 
10.3±0.2 
10.4±0.2 
10.1±0.4 </p>

<p>log 10 CFU (colony-forming unit) given per gram of wet weight of feces. Data are presented as mean ± s.d. Absence of specific bacterial strains in the gut microflora is 
indicated by ''-''. The values for the HBF mice supplemented with probiotics were compared to HBF control mice, * , ** and *** indicate a significant difference at 95, 
99 and 99.9% confidence levels, respectively. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 3 </p>

<p>UPLC-MS analysis of bile acids in ileal flushes </p>

<p>The proportion of bile acids in ileal flushes from the different 
groups are given in Table IV and are shown as mean ± s.d. of 
the percentage of the total bile acid content. O-PLS-DA of the 
data set revealed that the relative concentrations of bile acids 
obtained from unsupplemented HBF mice are separated from 
those treated with probiotics, the correlation observed with 
L. paracasei being more significant than with L. rhamnosus as 
noted by the values of the cross-validated model parameter Q Y </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>(Figure 2). For example, HBF mice supplemented with 
L. paracasei showed strong correlations with higher amounts 
of GCA, CDCA and UDCA and lower levels of a-MCA in the 
ileal flushes when compared to controls. HBF mice fed with 
L. rhamnosus also showed higher levels of GCA associated 
with lower levels of TUDCA and TCDCA in the ileal flushes 
when compared to untreated HBF mice. </p>

<p>Integration of multicompartment metabolic data 
using hierarchical-principal component analysis </p>

<p>A principal component analysis (PCA) model was initially 
constructed separately for the metabolic data from each 
individual biological matrix (plasma, urine, liver, fecal extracts 
and bile acid composition in ileal flush; Figures 3 and 4). Three 
principal components were calculated for each cross-validated 
PCA model, except for the plasma where four principal 
components were retained to maximize the explained variance 
R 2 X and the cross-validation parameter Q 2 following the 
standard sevenfold cross-validation method (Cloarec et al, 
2005b). These PCA models descriptors (R 2 X/Q 2 ) were 0.70/ 
0.36 (plasma), 0.41/0.11 (urine), 0.80/0.71 (liver), 0.94/0.67 
(bile acid) and 0.61/0.42 (feces). The score vectors t b from 
each model were then assigned as new X-variables (Figure 3). 
Thus, the top level X-matrix contained 16 descriptors, denoted </p>

<p>Table III Summary of influential metabolites for discriminating NMR spectra of liver, plasma, fecal extracts and urine </p>

<p>Metabolites 
Chemical shift and multiplicity 
HBF controls 
HBF+L. paracsei 
HBF+L. rhamnosus </p>

<p>Liver 
Q Y 
2 =21%, R X 
2 =44% 
Q Y 
2 =41%, R X 
2 =37% 
Leu 
0.92(t) 
2.4 ± 0.6 
1.7 ± 0.3*** 
1.9 ± 0.5* 
Ileu 
0.94 (t) 
0.8 ± 0.1 
0.6 ± 0.05*** 
0.7 ± 0.2 
Lactate 
1.32(d) 
38.4±5.8 
46.2±8.2 a 
39.2±9.7 
Succinate 
2.41(s) 
0.2 ± 0.1 
1.0 ± 0.6** 
0.7 ± 0.3* 
MA 
2.61(s) 
0.1±0.06 
0.04±0.002** 
0.08±0.05 
TMA 
2.91 (s) 
0.2 ± 0.04 
0.07 ± 0.03*** 
0.2 ± 0.09 
TMAO 
3.27(s) 
10.3 ± 2.2 
13.1 ± 3.7 
18.5 ± 8.0** 
Gln 
2.44(m) 
0.4±0.1 
0.3±0.1* 
0.3±0.1 
Glycogen 
5.38-5.45 
3.4 ± 1.9 
1.5 ± 0.6* 
3.2 ± 1.9 </p>

<p>Plasma 
Q Y 
2 =44%, R X 
2 =50% 
Q Y 
2 =51%, R X 
2 =32% 
Lipoproteins 
0.84 (m) 
13.7 ± 1.8 
10.1 ± 0.9*** 
9.8 ± 4.2** 
Citrate 
2.65(d) 
1.4±0.3 
0.9±0.4** 
1.1±0.2** 
Choline 
3.2(s) 
11.6±2.6 
16.2±5.7* 
20.5±3.8*** 
GPC 
3.22(s) 
44.1 ± 4.6 
57.3 ± 12.5** 
68.1 ± 11.2*** 
Glyceryls 
3.91(m) 
2.0±0.3 
2.5±0.4** 
2.7±0.4** </p>

<p>Feces 
Q Y 
2 =90%, R X 
2 =48% 
Q Y 
2 =89%, R X 
2 =49% 
Caprylate 
1.27(m) 
2.5±0.1 
3.5±0.2*** 
2.4±0.1 
Lys 
3.00(m) 
3.2 ± 0.8 
5.0 ± 0.3*** 
4.9 ± 1.2** 
Osides 
5.42(m) 
0.9±0.09 
1.2±0.1*** 
1.4±0.1*** 
Bile acids 
0.72(s) 
3.1±0.9 
1.8±0.7** 
2.0±0.6* 
Ethanol 
1.18(t) 
2.5 ± 0.1 
2.0 ± 0.08*** 
1.9 ± 0.09*** 
Choline 
3.20(s) 
48.0±19.5 
11.3±4.1*** 
20.3±10.9*** 
NAM 
2.06(m) 
7.1 ± 1.0 
5.4 ± 0.3*** 
5.5 ± 0.3*** 
Acetate 
1.91(s) 
58.7 ± 34.2 
27.0 ± 9.2** 
32.9 ± 12.9* 
U1 
3.71(s) 
9.2±0.5 
7.3±0.3*** 
8.2±0.5*** </p>

<p>Urine 
Q Y 
2 =91%, R X 
2 =47% 
Q Y 
2 =59%, R X 
2 =46% 
IAG 
7.55(d) 
0.1±0.03 
0.6±0.2*** 
0.4±0.2** 
PAG 
7.37(m) 
0.8 ± 0.1 
1.5 ± 0.3*** 
1.2 ± 0.4* 
Tryptamine 
7.70(d) 
0.1±0.04 
0.4±0.1*** 
0.2±0.1** 
UGLp 
1.27(m) 
1.7 ± 0.1 
2.7 ± 0.4*** 
1.7 ± 0.2 
Glycero-metabolites 
4.04 (m) 
1.7 ± 0.1 
2.2 ± 0.2*** 
1.9 ± 0.2* 
NAG 
2.04(s) 
3.5±0.2 
4.3±0.2*** 
3.8±0.5 
Butyrate 
0.90(t) 
6.9 ± 0.8 
5.2 ± 0.7** 
5.2 ± 0.9** 
a-keto-isocaproate 
0.94(d) 
13.8 ± 4.6 
6.1 ± 2.3** 
7.9 ± 2.1** 
Propionate 
1.05(t) 
0.9±0.2 
0.8±0.04* 
0.8±0.1 
3-hydroxy-isovalerate 
1.24(s) 
3.0 ± 0.4 
2.1 ± 0.4** 
2.6 ± 0.2 
Citrate 
2.55(d) 
10.8±7.6 
1.6±0.6** 
2.2±0.9* 
Creatine 
3.92(s) 
5.7±2.1 
4.5±1.5 
3.5±0.3** 
Citrulline 
1.88(m) 
3.8 ± 0.5 
3.3 ± 0.4 
3.0 ± 0.4** </p>

<p>O-PLS models were generated for comparing probiotics treated to HBF control mice using one predictive and two orthogonal components, R X 
2 value shows how 
much of the variation is explained, Q Y 
2 value represents the predictability of the models, and relates to its statistical validity. Data are presented as area normalized 
intensities (10 1 a.u.) of representative metabolite signals as means±s.d. The values for the HBF mice supplemented with probiotics were compared to HBF control 
mice, a, * , ** and *** indicate a significant difference at 90, 95, 99 and 99.9% confidence levels, respectively. 
s, singlet; d, doublet; t, triplet; q, quartet; m, multiplet; dd, doublet of doublets. For metabolite abbreviations, refer to the key in Figure 1, MA: methylamine. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>4 Molecular Systems Biology 2008 </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>P i (plasma PCs 1-4), L i (liver PCs 1-3), U i (urine PCs 1-3), B i 
(bile acid PCs 1-3) and F i (fecal PCs 1-3), which comprise only 
the systematic variation from each of the blocks/compart-
ments. The two first principal components (p1 and p2) 
calculated for the hierarchical-principal component analysis </p>

<p>(H-PCA; Westerhuis et al, 1998) model (R 2 X¼0.60) accounted 
for 37 and 23% of the total variance in the combined multi 
compartment data respectively. The cross validation for the 
H-PCA model failed due to the high degree of orthogonality 
within the X-matrix, that is, within each of the blocks all variables </p>

<p>Figure 1 O-PLS-DA coefficient plots derived from 1 H MAS NMR CPMG spectra of liver (A, D), 1 H NMR CPMG spectra of plasma (B, E), 1 H NMR standard spectra of 
fecal extracts (C, F) and urine (G, H), indicating discrimination between HBF mice fed with probiotics (positive) and HBF control mice (negative). The color code 
corresponds to the correlation coefficients of the variables with the classes. BAs, Bile acids; DMA, dimethylamine; Glc, glucose; Gln, glutamine; GPC, 
glycerophosphorylcholine; IAG, indoleacetylglycine; Ileu, isoleucine; Leu, leucine; Lys, lysine; NAG, N-acetylated glycoproteins; NAM, N-acetylated metabolites; 
Osides, glycosides; PAG, phenylacetylglycine; TBAs, taurine conjugated to bile acids; TMA, trimethylamine; TMAO, trimethylamine-N-oxide; UGLp, unidentified 
glycolipids. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 5 </p>

<p>are orthogonal to each other, while each of the biological matrices 
could be cross-validated at the individual level. 
The H-PCA scores plot illustrated a degree of clustering with 
respect to the groups of HBF mice (Figure 4A). The 
corresponding H-PCA loadings plot indicated the contribution 
of the 16 descriptors to the differences observed between the 
samples in the H-PCA scores plot. Probiotic-supplemented 
HBF animals are separated from the controls along the first 
principal component, and this arises from the main variations 
modelled at the base level PCA of the individual plasma (P1, 
P2), liver (L2, L3), ileal flush (B2) and urine (U1, U2) data sets 
(Figure 4B). HBF mice fed with L. paracasei were separated 
from those fed with L. rhamnosus along the second principal 
component, which was mainly due to the variations modelled 
at the base level PCA of plasma (P2, P3), liver (L1) and urine 
(U1, U3). Interestingly, the metabolic variations in the fecal </p>

<p>samples have no weight in discriminating the bacterial 
supplementation from the corresponding controls in the global 
model. 
To uncover variables contributing to the H-PCA super 
scores, the loadings at the base level PCA model were 
interrogated (Figure 4C-F). HBF mice supplemented with 
probiotics showed higher concentrations of glucose, choline, 
GPC, glutamine, glutamate and lysine in the plasma profiles 
associated with elevated concentrations of glucose in the liver 
and higher levels of TUDCA and TCDCA in the ileal flushes. 
Controls showed higher levels of lipoproteins in the plasma, 
elevated concentrations of lipids, glycogen, glutamine, gluta-
mate, alanine, TMAO and lactate in the liver, associated with 
higher levels of TCA and TbMCA in the ileal content. 
Unsupplemented HBF mice also showed elevated urinary 
excretions of creatine, citrate, citrulline, lysine, UGLp, NAG 
and a-keto-isocaproate compared to animals fed with probio-
tics. Moreover, H-PCA also revealed that HBF mice treated 
with L. rhamnosus had higher levels of hepatic lipids and 
plasma lipoproteins but lower concentrations of lactate and 
amino acids in plasma and lower urinary excretion of PAG, 
IAG, tryptamine and taurine than HBF mice treated with 
L. paracasei. </p>

<p>Integration of correlations between bile acids and 
fecal flora </p>

<p>We further investigated the connections between fecal flora 
and intestinal bile acids using a correlation analysis based 
bipartite graphical modelling approach (see Materials and 
methods; Figure 5) used previously to investigate the effects of 
gut microbiome humanization in germfree mice (Martin et al, 
2007a). In the current study, we are working with a superior </p>

<p>Table IV Bile acids composition in gut flushes for the different microbiota </p>

<p>Microbiota/ 
Bile acids </p>

<p>HBF 
HBF+L. paracasei HBF+L. rhamnosus </p>

<p>CDCA 
ND 
0.04 ± 0.07 
0.01 ± 0.02 
UDCA 
ND 
0.1±0.1 
ND 
CA 
0.4 ± 0.5 
0.3 ± 0.7 
0.3 ± 0.2 
oMCA 
ND 
0.02 ± 0.07 
ND 
aMCA 
0.3±0.2 
0.3±0.6 
0.2±0.2 
bMCA 
0.9 ± 0.7 
1.3 ± 2.7 
0.8 ± 0.7 
GCA 
ND 
0.1±0.1 
0.1±.08 
TCDCA 
3.3±1 
4 ±2.1 
2.5±1.3 
TUDC A 
6.6 ± 1.4 
6.6 ± 5.2 
5.1 ± 1.02 
TbMCA 
50±4.8 
49.2±7.5 
50.5±5.2 
TCA 
38 ± 3.5 
38 ± 6.2 
40.4 ± 5 </p>

<p>Relative composition in bile acids given in percentage of total bile acid content. 
Species not detected with UPLC-MS experiment are shown as ND. The key is 
given in UPLC-MS material and methods. </p>

<p>Covariance </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.7 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>-2 
0 
2 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Class members hip </p>

<p>r 2 </p>

<p>r 2 </p>

<p>HBF </p>

<p>Class members hip </p>

<p>C 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>U 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>C 
A </p>

<p>α 
-
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>β 
-
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>G 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
C 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
U 
D 
C 
A T </p>

<p>β 
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
C 
A </p>

<p>C 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>U 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>C 
A </p>

<p>α 
-
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>β 
-
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>G 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
C 
D 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
U 
D 
C 
A T </p>

<p>β 
M 
C 
A </p>

<p>T 
C 
A </p>

<p>Tcv 1 </p>

<p>HBF+L. rhamnosus </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>Tcv 1 </p>

<p>5 
-3 </p>

<p>HBF </p>

<p>HBF+L. paracasei </p>

<p>-0.4 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>Covariance </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>-0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>Figure 2 O-PLS-DA coefficient plots derived from the bile acid composition obtained by UPLC-MS analysis of ileal flushes, which indicate discrimination between HBF 
control mice (negative) and HBF mice treated with probiotics (positive), (A) L. paracasei and (B) L. rhamnosus. The color code corresponds to the correlation 
coefficients of the variables. One predictive and one orthogonal component were calculated; the respective Q Y 
2 and R X 
2 are (76.4, 52.2%) and (50.3, 51.2%). </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>model where all the major bacteria strains are identified, 
which was not possible when considering conventional 
microflora. Positive and negative correlations show the multi-
colinearity between bile acids and gut bacteria, whose </p>

<p>concentrations are interdependent such as in the case of 
substrate-product biochemical reactions. Additional pixel 
maps of the correlation matrices are given to help interpreta-
tion in Supplementary Figure 1. </p>

<p>Original raw data </p>

<p>Logical Blocks </p>

<p>Urine Plasma 
Liver </p>

<p>Breaking down data </p>

<p>Urine </p>

<p>SUB-LEVEL </p>

<p>HIGH-LEVEL </p>

<p>Collecting the scores </p>

<p>Plasma </p>

<p>t T </p>

<p>p T </p>

<p>Feces </p>

<p>t 4 
t 3 
t 2 
t 1 </p>

<p>X1 
X5 
X4 
X3 
X2 </p>

<p>Bile 
acids </p>

<p>p 5 
p 4 
p 3 
p 2 
p 1 </p>

<p>t 5 
Bile 
acids </p>

<p>Feces </p>

<p>Separate PCA models for each block </p>

<p>Sub level for investigating t and p </p>

<p>Easy interpretation </p>

<p>PCA model score variables </p>

<p>High level for investigating t and p </p>

<p>Integration of the data </p>

<p>Liver </p>

<p>Figure 3 Schematic overview of H-PCA modelling: (Gunnarsson et al, 2003). In the sublevel, each block of data XB is modelled locally by a PCA model. Each block is 
summarized by one or more loading vectors p b and score vectors t p ('super variables'), which can be combined to form a new data matrix than can then be modelled 
using PCA, which generates the 'super scores' t T and the 'super loadings' p T . All conventional PCA statistics and diagnostics are retained. </p>

<p>HBF 
HBF + L. rhamnosus 
HBF-+L. paracasei </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>-5 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
5 
t 1 </p>

<p>t 2 </p>

<p>-0.3 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>-0.1 -0.0 
0.6 </p>

<p>H-PCA scores </p>

<p>p 1 </p>

<p>p 2 </p>

<p>H-PCA loadings </p>

<p>P1 </p>

<p>P2 </p>

<p>P3 </p>

<p>P4 </p>

<p>L1 </p>

<p>L2 
L3 </p>

<p>U1 </p>

<p>U2 </p>

<p>U3 </p>

<p>B1 B2 
B3 F1 F2 
F3 </p>

<p>B 2 </p>

<p>B 1 </p>

<p>-0.3 </p>

<p>-0.0 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>-0.4 
0.0 
0.4 </p>

<p>CDCA 
UDCA </p>

<p>CA </p>

<p>βMCA 
αMCA </p>

<p>GCA </p>

<p>TCDCA </p>

<p>TUDCA </p>

<p>TβMCA 
TCA </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
6.2 
6.7 
7.2 
7.7 
8.2 </p>

<p>U 2 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
6.2 
6.7 
7.2 
7.7 
8.2 </p>

<p>0 
U 3 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.04 </p>

<p>U 1 
L 1 </p>

<p>L 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
5.2 
5.7 
6.2 
6.7 
7.2 
7.7 
8.2 
8.7 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
5.2 
5.7 </p>

<p>L 3 </p>

<p>-0.03 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.03 </p>

<p>0.07 </p>

<p>0.06 </p>

<p>0.04 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>L 2 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
5.2 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.4 
1.9 
2.4 
2.9 
3.4 
3.9 
5.2 
5.7 
6.2 
6.7 
7.2 
7.7 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.05 </p>

<p>-0.04 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>0.03 </p>

<p>P 1 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.2 
1.4 
1.7 
1.9 
2.2 
2.4 
2.7 
2.9 
3.2 
3.4 
3.7 
3.9 
4.2 
5.2 </p>

<p>P 3 </p>

<p>0 0 </p>

<p>P 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.12 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0.9 
1.2 
1.4 
1.7 
1.9 
2.2 
2.4 
2.7 
2.9 
3.2 
3.4 
3.7 
3.9 
4.2 
5.2 </p>

<p>Lipids </p>

<p>Glc </p>

<p>Lipoproteins </p>

<p>Glc </p>

<p>Lactate </p>

<p>Choline, GPC </p>

<p>Choline, GPC </p>

<p>Glu, Gln, Lys </p>

<p>Glc </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H 
δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>δ 1 H </p>

<p>Lipoproteins </p>

<p>Glu , Gln Ala </p>

<p>Val , Leu , Ileu </p>

<p>Glu , Gln </p>

<p>Glycogen </p>

<p>Glu , Gln 
Ala </p>

<p>Lactate 
TMAO </p>

<p>Creatine 
Citrate </p>

<p>UGLp </p>

<p>Citrulline </p>

<p>δ-keto-isocaproate </p>

<p>PAG, IAG, Trypt </p>

<p>Citrulline, Lys </p>

<p>Taurine 
Pyruvate </p>

<p>NAG </p>

<p>Citrate 
Taurine </p>

<p>Figure 4 H-PCA scores (A) and loadings (B) plots for the two first components derived from scores of separate PCA constructed separately for the metabolic data 
from each individual biological matrix from HBF mice ('), HBF-L. paracasei mice (E) and HBF-L. rhamnosus mice (J). These PCA models explained 94% (bile 
acid, C), 70% (plasma, D), 80% (liver, E), 41% (urine, F) and 61% (feces, data not shown) of the total variation in the data, respectively. The systematic variation from 
each of the block/compartment is summarized by its score vectors denoted P i (plasma PCs 1-4), L i (liver PCs 1-3), U i (urine PCs 1-3), B i (bile acid PCs 1-3) and F i (fecal 
PCs 1-3), which can be combined to form a new data matrix than can then be modelled using PCA. The individual PCA loadings were color coded according to their 
contribution to the H-PCA model in red (principal component 1) and in blue (principal component 2). The model has been calculated from Pareto scaled data using two 
cross-validated PCs, R 2 X¼60%. Ala, alanine; see Figure 1. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 7 </p>

<p>Control HBF mice and HBF mice supplemented with 
probiotics show remarkably different bile acid/fecal flora 
correlation networks (Figure 5A-C), indicating that small 
modulations in the species composition of the microbiome can 
result in major functional ecological consequences. Network 
statistics reveal that microbiome/metabolome bipartite graphs 
from HBF mice supplemented with Lactobacilli show a totally 
different nodal structure (given for the cut-off value of 0.5). In 
particular, we observed that in the network obtained from 
control HBF mice, the most connected bacteria are Bifidobac-
teria, Staphylococci, and Clostridia, for which the variations 
are intrinsically correlated with the balance in tauro-conju-
gated bile acids (TCDCA, TbMCA, TCA, TUDCA) and uncon-
jugated bile acids (CA, aMCA, bMCA). In particular, the 
potentially harmful opportunist C. perfringens shows func-
tional correlation of opposite sign for TbMCA, TCDCA, aMCA 
and bMCA when compared to Bifidobacteria and S. aureus. </p>

<p>Network analysis for HBF mice supplemented with 
L. paracasei reveals that Lactobacilli supplementation resulted 
in decreasing the functional links between Bifidobacteria and 
bile acids, while new significant correlations were observed 
between bile acids, and Bacteroides, S. aureus, S. epidermidis 
and L. paracasei. Moreover, E. coli has several connections 
with UDCA, aMCA and TCDCA. Interestingly, Bacteroides 
shows functional correlations of opposite signs for TbMCA, 
TUDCA and TCA when compared to Lactobacilli and 
Staphylococci. 
When HBF mice received L. rhamnosus probiotic, the 
microbiome/metabolome network shows a significant lower 
level of complexity (given for the cut-off value of 0.5). The 
balance within B. breve, S. aureus and S. epidermidis appears 
highly correlated to the composition in tauro-conjugated 
bile acids (TbMCA, TCA) and unconjugated bile acids 
(bMCA, CA). </p>

<p>HBF </p>

<p>HBF-L. paracasei 
HBF-L. rhamnosus </p>

<p>CA </p>

<p>aMA </p>

<p>bMA </p>

<p>TCDCA </p>

<p>TUDCA </p>

<p>TMCA </p>

<p>TCA </p>

<p>E.c </p>

<p>S.a 
B.b </p>

<p>B.l 
C.p </p>

<p>Ba </p>

<p>S.e </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 
0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 
0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  
0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.7  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.7  *  *  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.7  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.6  *  </p>

<p>CA </p>

<p>aMA </p>

<p>bMA </p>

<p>TCDCA </p>

<p>TUDCA </p>

<p>TMCA </p>

<p>TCA </p>

<p>E.c </p>

<p>S.a 
B.b </p>

<p>B.l 
C.p </p>

<p>Ba </p>

<p>S.e </p>

<p>UDCA </p>

<p>La </p>

<p>CDCA </p>

<p>GCA </p>

<p>-0.6  *  </p>

<p>-0.6  *  </p>

<p>-0.7  *  </p>

<p>-0.6  *  </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 
0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>CA </p>

<p>aMA </p>

<p>bMA </p>

<p>TCDCA </p>

<p>TUDCA </p>

<p>TMCA </p>

<p>TCA </p>

<p>E.c </p>

<p>S.a 
B.b </p>

<p>B.l 
C.p </p>

<p>Ba </p>

<p>S.e </p>

<p>La </p>

<p>GCA 
0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>-0.5 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 5 Integration of bile acid and fecal flora correlations. The bipartite graphs were derived from correlations between fecal flora and bile acids in each group: HBF 
mice (A), HBF mice supplemented with L. paracasei (B) or L. rhamnosus (C). The cut-off value of 0.5 was applied to the absolute value of the coefficient |r| for 
displaying the correlations between fecal flora and bile acids. Bile acids and fecal bacteria correspond to blue ellipse nodes and green rectangle nodes, respectively. 
Edges are coded according to correlation value: positive and negative correlations are respectively displayed in blue and in red. aMA, a-muricholic acid; Ba, 
Bacteroides; Bb, B. breve; Bl, B. longum; bMA, b-muricholic acid; CA, cholic acid; CDCA, chenodeoxycholic acid; Cp, C. perfringens; Ec, E. coli; GCA, 
glycocholic acid; La, Lactobacillus probiotics; Sa, S. aureus; Se, S. epidermidis; TCA, taurocholic acid; TCDCA, taurochenodeoxycholic acid; TMCA, tauro-b-
muricholic acid; TUDCA, tauroursocholic acid; UDCA, ursocholic acid. * and *** indicate a statistically significant correlation at 95 and 99.9% confidence levels, 
respectively. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The cometabolic processes regulating mammalian systems 
and their coexisting gut microbiota are an essential evolu-
tionary driver towards providing more refined control me-
chanisms on the host physiology (Pereira and Gibson, 2002; 
Pereira et al, 2003; Backhed et al, 2004; Holmes and Nicholson, 
2005; Nicholson et al, 2005; Dumas et al, 2006; Martin et al, 
2006, 2007a). In the present study, we demonstrate a 
significant association between the probiotic modulation of 
the gut microbiome and the metabolism of SCFAs, amino acids 
and methylamines, bile acids and plasma lipoproteins, and 
also an association with stimulated glycolysis, showing the 
remarkable diversity of symbiotic cometabolic connections. </p>

<p>Gut microbiotal links to host energy metabolism </p>

<p>We have recently described that HBF mice supplemented with 
L. paracasei were characterized by a high gut content of tauro-
conjugated bile acids due to the inability of gut flora to 
deconjugate the bile acids, which resulted in high intestinal 
absorption of dietary lipids, accumulation of lipids in the liver 
and reduction of lipoprotein levels in plasma when compared 
to conventional animals (Martin et al, 2007a). Here, we show 
that probiotics supplementation of HBF mice resulted in a 
decrease in the plasma concentrations of VLDL and low-
density lipoproteins (LDL) and increased triglyceride and GPC 
concentrations in plasma when compared to HBF controls 
(Figure 1B). In addition, the Lactobacillus supplementation 
resulted in decreased fecal excretion of bile acids (Figure 1C), 
that may be caused by accumulation of bile acids in 
Lactobacillus probiotics (Kurdi et al, 2000). These observation 
indicated probiotic-induced changes in the enterohepatic 
recirculation of bile acids, which were shown to lower 
cholesterol and systemic levels of blood lipids (Pereira and 
Gibson, 2002). Moreover, probiotic-specific modulation of the 
ileal concentrations of UDCA and CDCA (Figure 2; Table IV) 
may also contribute to modulation of the synthesis and 
secretion of VLDL into the blood (Lin et al, 1996; Watanabe 
et al, 2004). 
Moreover, the main source of dietary lipids in animal chow 
is soybean oil, which is composed at 65% of long-chain 
polyunsaturated fatty acids. It is well known that Lactobacillus 
hydrolyzes soy oil to conjugated linoleic acid efficiently (Xu 
et al, 2005), which results in a reduction of plasma lipoprotein 
concentrations and hepatic cholesterol (Fukushima et al, 1996, 
1997; Al-Othman, 2000) and in the inhibition of S. aureus 
growth (Das, 2002), as observed in the current study. 
Furthermore, probiotics supplementation was associated with 
significant reduction of acetate in the cecal content (Table II) 
and in a reduced hepatic acetate:propionate ratio, for which a 
serum lipids lowering effect has previously been described 
(Wong et al, 2006). Our results illustrate the fine relationship 
between a specific gut microbial population modulation and 
the host's lipid metabolism and that a probiotic intervention 
can provide refined control mechanisms on the host's 
physiology. 
Furthermore, the molecular foundations of beneficial 
symbiotic host-bacteria relationships lie in the critical 
involvement of the microbiome in calorie recovery through </p>

<p>further processing of dietary nutrients and indigestible fibers. 
Levels of leucine and isoleucine were reduced together with 
their keto-acid derivative (a-keto-isocaproate) in L. paracasei-
supplemented mice. These observations suggest higher 
catabolism of branched-chain amino acids to produce acetyl-
CoA and glucose via gluconeogenesis. Decreased levels of 
citrate in urine and plasma, but increased liver succinate levels 
may also indicate the shunt of the tricarboxylic acid cycle 
towards production of phosphoenolpyruvate for gluconeogen-
esis in L. paracasei-supplemented mice. Moreover, reduction 
of liver glycogen observed with L. paracasei supplementation 
is consistent with our other observations of generalized host 
mobilization of other metabolic fuels. </p>

<p>Probiotics induce specific microbiome-host 
transgenomic metabolic interactions </p>

<p>We investigated the relationship between probiotic-induced 
changes in gut microbes and bile acid cometabolism using 
bipartite graphs to display correlation patterns between fecal 
flora and bile acids (Figure 5). Correlation analysis derived 
from bile acid and fecal flora profiles offers a unique approach 
to capture subtle variations in bile acid composition that may 
be directly related to changes in gut microbial levels, and that 
may be induced by accumulation of bile acids in Lactobacillus 
probiotics for instance. Control HBF mice and HBF mice 
supplemented with probiotics show remarkably different bile 
acid/fecal flora correlation networks. The different bacterial 
strains of Bacteroides, Clostridia, Streptococci and Lactobacilli 
share similar abilities to deconjugate the hepatic tauro-
conjugated bile acids (Midtvedt and Norman, 1967; Floch, 
2002). In that regard, the overwhelming contrast between the 
balance of these bacteria on one hand, and conjugated bile 
acids (TCDCA, TbMCA, TCA, TUDCA) and unconjugated bile 
acids (CA, aMCA, bMCA) on the other hand, highlights the 
metabolic flexibility of the gut microbiota in response to 
probiotics supplementation. These different correlative pat-
terns further characterize the microbial-mammalian transge-
nomic metabolic interactions, whereby probiotics-induced 
modulation of the gut microbial functional ecosystem results 
in different bile acid composition (Figure 2) and enterohepatic 
recirculation. 
The relationship between specific gut microbial strains and 
bile acid cometabolism is well illustrated with the contrast 
between Lactobacillus, which shows resistance to bile salt 
toxicity (Corcoran et al, 2005), and C. perfringens, which is 
sensitive to the strong growth inhibitory effects of unconju-
gated bile acids and TCDCA (Kishinaka et al, 1994; Floch, 
2002). In the absence of Lactobacillus supplementation, 
C. perfringens has anticorrelated connections with TCDCA, 
aMCA and bMCA, which highlights the strong inhibitory 
effects of these bile acids on C. perfringens growth. Interest-
ingly, the probiotic supplementation was either associated 
with maintenance or decrease of the Clostridial population 
(Table I), while no functional correlations between 
C. perfringens and bile acids were observed. In that regard, 
these observations may indicate different nutritional competi-
tion leading to modulation of C. perfringens population and 
maintainance of the intestinal ecology. Consequently, inter-
bacterial cooperation to transform bile acids is an important </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 9 </p>

<p>factor that needs to be considered not only for the fine tuning 
of microbial balance but also to modulate dietary fat 
emulsification and absorption. </p>

<p>Gut-bacterial production of methylamines via 
choline metabolism </p>

<p>The elevation of methylamines (TMA, TMAO) in liver, choline 
and GPC in the plasma and decreased choline in feces from 
HBF mice supplemented with L. rhamnosus (Figure 1) are 
additional illustrations of the complex 'microbial-mammalian 
metabolic axis,' as the microbiota are involved in the synthesis 
and metabolism of these methylamines (al-Waiz et al, 1992). 
The first reaction of the methylamine pathway involves 
conversion of dietary choline into TMA by gut microbiota 
(Zeisel et al, 1983), which is then detoxified to TMAO in the 
liver via the flavine monooxygenase system (Smith et al, 1994; 
(Figure 6). L. rhamnosus supplementation contributes to 
higher absorption of free choline and may induce elevated 
production of methylamines by Bacteroides and C. perfringens 
(Allison and Macfarlane, 1989) through nutritional com-
petition. </p>

<p>Interestingly, L. paracasei consumption may favor a 
different metabolic fate for choline through different bacterial 
reprocessing. Decreased fecal choline was associated with 
reduced concentrations of TMA and DMA in the liver, an 
increase in plasma GPC, but with no changes in liver TMAO 
and plasma choline after L. paracasei supplementation. These 
animals also showed a greater reduction in plasma lipopro-
teins when compared to other groups. Here, these observa-
tions may result from elevated bacterial consumption for 
cholesterol assimilation (Rasic, 1992) and phospholipid 
metabolism (Jenkins and Courtney, 2003; Taranto et al, 
2003; Kankaanpaa et al, 2004). Thus, the reduced availability 
of choline to other bacterial strains may have led to lower 
production of methylamines and absorption of free choline 
into host metabolism. </p>

<p>Probiotic modulation of amino-acid metabolism </p>

<p>Investigation of the urine metabolic profiles showed signifi-
cant increases in the concentrations of microbial cometabo-
lites PAG, IAG and tryptamine in probiotic supplemented mice 
(Goodwin et al, 1994; Smith and Macfarlane, 1996). These 
metabolites are produced from amino acids, which after </p>

<p>Choline </p>

<p>Diet </p>

<p>DMA </p>

<p>TMA </p>

<p>TMAO </p>

<p>Small 
intestine </p>

<p>Large 
intestine </p>

<p>TMA </p>

<p>DMA </p>

<p>MA </p>

<p>TMA </p>

<p>TMAO </p>

<p>DMA </p>

<p>Betaine </p>

<p>DMG </p>

<p>Sarcosine </p>

<p>Glycine </p>

<p>Urine </p>

<p>Body </p>

<p>Flavine 
Mono-oxygenase </p>

<p>Creatine </p>

<p>Phospho creatine </p>

<p>Creatinine </p>

<p>Gut 
microbiota </p>

<p>Phospho choline </p>

<p>Phosphatidyl-
choline 
Gut 
microbiota 
Bacterial 
proteolysis </p>

<p>Bacterial metabolism 
of amino acids </p>

<p>Casein </p>

<p>IAA </p>

<p>IAG </p>

<p>Octanoate 
Thiokinase </p>

<p>Peptides </p>

<p>IAA </p>

<p>Tyrosine 
Phenylalanine 
Tryptophan </p>

<p>Indole 
pyruvate </p>

<p>Tryptamine 
Phenyl 
pyruvate </p>

<p>OH-Phenyl 
pyruvate </p>

<p>PA 
p-cresol </p>

<p>PA </p>

<p>PAG </p>

<p>Figure 6 Gut-microbiota-mammalian cometabolism of methylamines and aromatic amino acids. DMG, dimethylglycine; IA, indoleacetate; MA, methylamine; 
PA, phenylacetate (see Figure 1). </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>depolymerization of dietary proteins (casein) by pancreatic 
endopeptidases and bacterial proteases and peptidases, 
become available for fermentation by the gut microflora 
(Smith and Macfarlane, 1996), as outlined in Figure 6. 
Metabolism of the aromatic amino acids phenylalanine, 
tyrosine and tryptophan generates phenylacetate (PA), 
p-cresol, indoleacetate (IA) and tryptamine, respectively 
(Donaldson, 1962; Smith and Macfarlane, 1996). PA and IA 
may be detoxified in the gut mucosa and the liver by glycine 
conjugation forming PAG and IAG prior to excretion via the 
urine (Donaldson, 1962; Smith and Macfarlane, 1996). The 
production of PA and IA has been restricted to a certain 
taxonomic group of gut bacteria, including Bacteroides, 
Clostridia and E. coli, which count among the dominant 
species in HBF colonized mice (Smith and Macfarlane, 1996; 
Xu et al, 2002). The increased urinary excretion of phenolic 
and indolic compounds reflects variations in gut microflora 
composition in relation to nutritional competition (Smith and 
Macfarlane, 1996; Nowak and Libudzisz, 2006). For instance, 
IA has been reported to inhibit the growth and survival of 
Lactobacilli, and specifically L. paracasei (Nowak and 
Libudzisz, 2006). 
In addition, increased levels of lysine in feces from mice 
supplemented with probiotics is another example of bacterial 
contribution to the mammalian amino-acid homeostasis 
(Metges, 2000) and hepatic protein synthesis (Metges et al, 
2006; Figure 1). Higher production of bacterial isobutyrate and 
isovalerate (Table II) suggests increased bacterial fermentation 
of leucine and valine that can also influence host energy 
metabolism (Macfarlane et al, 1992). Moreover, L. paracasei 
supplementation specifically induced higher urinary excretion 
of NAG and decreased N-acetylated metabolites in fecal 
extracts. A relationship between high casein diet and 
urinary excretion of NAG has been described previously 
(Hallson et al, 1997), which also suggested elevated bacterial 
proteolysis. 
Altogether, our data suggest that the probiotic-induced 
increased proteolytic activities may reflect the basal metabo-
lism of these Lactobacillus strains, in particular L. paracasei for 
which the proteolytic activities on casein medium are known 
to be elevated (Sasaki et al, 1995; Ikram and Mukhtar, 2006). 
Moreover, increased urinary NAG levels have been reported as 
a biomarker of increased tubular activity and tubular cell 
toxicity. Changes in bacterial fermentation of carbohydrates 
can lead to different ion absorption from the gut (Scholz-
Ahrens et al, 2001), which may contribute to altered kidney 
metabolism and tubular activity. Therefore, the gut microbial 
contribution to the modulation of the NAG biomarker is 
certainly of potential toxicological assessment significance. </p>

<p>H-PCA modelled multicompartmental matrices 
related to lipid metabolism </p>

<p>H-PCA has been explored for the first time as a top-down 
systems approach to model and integrate metabolic profiles 
from diverse biological compartments. H-PCA modelling 
summarized clearly the intercorrelated changes induced by 
probiotic-treatment in plasma, urine and liver matrices and 
composition in bile acids (Figure 4). One benefit of the </p>

<p>hierarchical approach lies in the much simplified simulta-
neous visualization of global system biochemical changes in 
multibiological matrices and improves interpretability. For 
instance, H-PCA resulted in a separation between the treated 
groups, which was not observed in separate PCA models. In 
addition, the H-PCA loadings plot gives the relative impor-
tance of the different blocks (biological matrices) in carrying 
diet-induced discriminant information. Moreover, the relation-
ships between the descriptors in the simplified H-PCA space 
(H-PCA loadings plot) indicate correlations and anticorrela-
tions between block variables, which may give insight into 
correlations between the metabolic variations in different 
biological matrices as exemplified here by metabolic changes 
in liver, plasma and urine and related to lipid metabolism. The 
H-PCA model also efficiently summarized the intercorrelated 
changes related to higher systemic glycolysis in plasma, urine 
and liver matrices, that is, reduced ketone body formation, 
anaerobic glycolysis, tricarboxylic cycle perturbation and 
amino-acid catabolism (Figure 4). Such observations might 
lead to better description of multiorgan metabolic perturba-
tions (Figure 4B). This multicompartmental top-down 
approach offers a way forward to study the systemic 
biochemical profiles and regulation of function in whole 
organisms by analyzing simultaneously several metabolite 
pools from different biofluids and tissues. This approach also 
provides a new strategy for the quantitative and qualitative 
evaluation of different probiotic (or indeed any functional 
food or nutriceutical) interventions in relation to host 
biochemistry. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>Significant associations between host metabolic phenotypes 
and a nutritionally modified gut-microbiota strongly supports 
the idea that changes across a whole range of metabolic 
pathways are the product of extended genome perturbations 
that can be oriented using probiotic supplementation, and 
which may play a role in host metabolic health. Bipartite 
network analysis highlights the metabolic flexibility of the gut 
microbiota, whereby bacterial strains communicate with each 
other to metabolize differently bile acids in a gut microbial 
ecosystem modulated with probiotics. In this case, probiotic 
consumption exerted a modification over the microbiome 
resulting in different hepatic influx and efflux of fatty acids in 
the liver, as observed with increased enterohepatic recycling of 
bile acids and dietary fats, lowered plasma lipoprotein levels 
and stimulated glycolysis. Probiotics also induced a different 
microbial proteolytic activity as well as modulation of 
bacterial metabolism of amino acids, methylamines and 
SCFAs. We showed the novel application of H-PCA as a means 
to study perturbation of metabolic profiles triggered by 
symbiotic microbiota at a 'global system' level by analyzing 
several metabolite pools simultaneously from different bio-
fluids and tissues. These integrated system investigations 
demonstrate the potential of metabolic profiling as a top-down 
systems biology driver for investigating the mechanistic basis 
of probiotic action and the therapeutic surveillance of the gut 
microbial activity related to dietary supplementation of 
probiotics and their health consequences. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 11 </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Animal handling procedure </p>

<p>All animal studies were carried out under appropriate national 
guidelines at the  Research Center (Lausanne, Switzerland). 
The HBF is constituted of a total of seven bacterial strains, isolated 
from stool of a 20-day-old female baby that was naturally delivered and 
breast-fed, namely E. coli, B. breve and B. longum, S. epidermidis and 
S. aureus, C. perfringens and Bacteroides distasonis. Bacterial cell 
mixtures contain approximately 10 10 cells/ml for each strain and were 
kept in frozen aliquots until use. Lactobacillus paracasei NCC2461 and 
L. rhamnosus NCC4007 probiotics were obtained from the  
Culture Collection (Lausanne, Switzerland). 
A total of 28 female germ-free mice (C3H strain), aged 6 weeks, 
received a single dose of HBF bacteria mixture and will be called HBF 
mice in the current manuscript. The experimental design is detailed in 
Supplementary Figure 2. The animals were fed with a standard 
pathogen-free rodent diet constituted of 50% cornstarch, 20% casein, 
10% sucrose, 7% soybean oil, 5% cellulose, 0.25% choline bitartrate, 
0.3% cystine and vitamin and mineral mixtures (Reeves et al, 1993) for 
2 weeks. A control group of HBF mice (n¼10) received a saline drink 
ad libitum containing Man, Rogosa and Sharpe (MRS) culture medium 
and was fed with a basal mix diet containing in composition 2.5% of a 
glucose-lactose mixture (1.25% each) for 2 additional weeks. Two 
groups of HBF mice were given a daily probiotic supplement, either 
L. paracasei (group A, n¼9) or L. rhamnosus (group D, n¼9), 
containing around 10 8 probiotic bacteria in MRS per day mixed with 
the saline solution ad libitum and were also fed with the basal mix diet. 
Fecal pellets were first collected in the morning for microbiological 
analysis and frozen at À801C for NMR spectroscopic analysis. Urine 
was then collected from animals prior to euthanasia and frozen at 
À801C. Urine samples were not obtained for every animal, as some 
mice had an empty bladder at the time of killing (group A, n¼8; group 
B, n¼6; group C, n¼8). Blood (400 ml) was collected into Li-heparin 
tubes and plasma was obtained after centrifugation and frozen at 
À801C. The ileum and liver were dissected and snap-frozen. Ileal flush 
samples were obtained by rinsing the ileal lumen using a 1 ml sterile 
syringe containing a phosphate buffer solution (0.2 M Na 2 HPO 4 / 
0.04 M NaH 2 PO 4 , pH 7.4) for UPLC-MS analysis. Cecal content was 
collected upon animal autopsy, snap-frozen immediately and main-
tained at À801C prior to analysis. </p>

<p>Microbial profiling of fecal contents </p>

<p>Immediately after collection, fecal pellets were homogenized in 0.5 ml 
Ringer solution (Oxoid, UK) supplemented with 0.05% (w/v) 
L-Cystein (HCl). The enumeration of specific microorganisms was 
performed after plating and incubation of different dilutions of the 
bacterial solution on selective and semiselective media, for example, 
Bifidobacteria on Eugom Tomato medium, Lactobacillus on 
MRS þ antibiotic (phosphomycine, sulfamethoxazole, trimethoprim) 
medium, C. perfringens on NN-agar medium, Enterobacteriaceae on 
Drigalski medium and Bacteroides on Shaedler Neo Vanco medium. 
Enterobacteriaceae cultures were incubated at 371C under aerobic 
conditions for 24 h, and other cultures were incubated under anaerobic 
conditions over a 48 h period. </p>

<p>Gas-chromatography on cecal content </p>

<p>An aliquot of cecal content was extracted with 4 ml buffer (0.1% (w/v) 
HgCl 2 and 1% (v/v) H 3 PO 4 supplemented with 0.045 mg/ml 2,2-
dimethylbutyric acid (as internal standard) per gram fresh weight. The 
resulting slurry was centrifuged for 30 min at 5000 g at 41C. Fecal 
SCFAs were analyzed using a gas-chromatograph (HP 6890) equipped 
with a flame ionization detector and a DB-FFAP column (J&amp;W 
Scientific, MSP Friedli &amp; Co, Switzerland) of 30 m length, 530 mm 
diameter and 1 mm film thickness. The system was run with helium gas 
at an inlet constant pressure of 10 psi at 1801C. Each sample run was 
preceded with a cleaning injection of 1.2% formic acid. Samples were 
run at an initial temperature of 801C for 1.2 min followed by heating to 
1451C in 6.5 min, heating to 2001C in 0.55 min and an additional </p>

<p>0.5 min at 2001C. SCFAs were identified using external standards 
(acetate, propionate, iso-butyrate, n-butyrate, iso-valerate, n-valerate) 
and the concentration was calculated using the internal standard. </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H NMR spectroscopic analysis </p>

<p>A volume of 100 ml of blood plasma was added to 450 ml of saline 
solution containing 10% D 2 O, which was used as a spectrometer field 
frequency lock, into 5 mm NMR tubes. Urine samples were prepared 
by mixing 20 ml of samples with 30 ml of a phosphate buffer solution 
containing 90% D 2 O and 0.25 mM 3-trimethylsilyl-1-[2,2,3,3-2 H 4 ] 
propionate (TSP), which was used as chemical shift reference (d 0.0), 
into 1.7 mm NMR tubes. Fecal pellets were homogenized in 650 ml of a 
phosphate buffer solution containing 90% D 2 O and 0.25 mM TSP. The 
fecal samples were sonicated for 30 min at 251C and then centrifuged at 
13 000 r.p.m. for 20 min to remove particulates. The supernatants were 
removed and centrifuged at 13 000 r.p.m. for 10 min. A 580 ml aliquot of 
the fecal supernatant was then pipetted into a 5 mm NMR tube for 
spectroscopic analysis. Portions of intact liver samples (B15 mg) were 
bathed in ice-cold 0.9% saline D 2 O solution and packed into a 
zirconium oxide 4 mm outer diameter rotor. 
1 H NMR spectra were acquired for each sample using a Bruker DRX 
600 NMR spectrometer (Rheinstetten, Germany) operating at 
600.11 MHz for 1 H. The instrument was equipped with a Bruker 
5 mm TXI triple resonance probe maintained at 298 K for liquid 
samples and a standard Bruker high-resolution MAS probe under 
magic-angle-spinning conditions at a spin rate of 5000 Hz for intact 
tissues (Waters et al, 2000). Tissue samples were regulated at 283 K to 
minimize biochemical degradation. 
One-dimensional (1D) 1 H NMR spectra were obtained from each 
sample using a standard solvent suppression pulse sequence (RD-901-
t1-901-tm-901-acquire FID) with t m fixed at 100 ms and t 1 at 3 ms (Wang 
et al, 2005). Additional spin echo Carr-Purcell-Meiboom-Gill (CPMG) 
spectra were acquired for plasma and liver samples using the pulse 
sequence (RD-901-(t-1801-t) n -acquire FID), with a spin-spin relaxation 
delay, 2nt, of 160 ms for plasma and 200 ms for tissue (Meiboom and 
Gill, 1958). The 901 pulse length was 9.0-12 ms. A total of 128 
transients were collected into 32K data points with a recycle delay (RD) 
of 2 s. The assignment of the 1 H NMR spectral peaks to specific 
metabolites was achieved based on the literature (Nicholson et al, 
1995; Fan, 1996), and confirmed by 2D COrrelation SpectroscopY 
(COSY) (Hurd, 1990) and TOtal Correlation SpectroscopY (TOCSY) 
(Bax and Davis, 1985). 2D NMR spectra were acquired on selected 
samples. Further assignment of the metabolites was also accomplished 
with the use of Statistical TOtal Correlation SpectroscopY (STOCSY) on 
1D spectra (Cloarec et al, 2005a). </p>

<p>UPLC-MS methods </p>

<p>The Ultra Performancet liquid chromatography of ileal flushes was 
performed on a ACQUITY UPLC system (Waters, Milford, MA, USA) 
equipped with a Toft LCT-Premier (Waters MS Technologies, 
Manchester, UK) for mass detection using the method we described 
previously (Martin et al, 2007a). The same conditions were applied for 
analysis of the following bile acid standards: cholic (CA), taurocholic 
(TCA), glycocholic (GCA), deoxycholic (DCA), taurodeoxycholic 
(TDCA), glycodeoxycholic (GDCA), chenodeoxycholic (CDCA), taur-
ochenodeoxycholic (TCDCA), glycochenodeoxycholic (GCDCA), 
lithocholic (LCA), taurolithocholic (TLCA), glycolithocholic (GLCA), 
ursodeoxycholic (UDCA), tauroursodeoxycholic (TUDCA), glycourso-
deoxycholic (GUDCA), hyocholic (HCA), a-muricholic (aMCA), 
b-muricholic (bMCA), o-muricholic (oMCA), tauro-b-muricholic 
(TbMCA) and tauro-a-muricholic (TaMCA) acids. We have previously 
given the molecular structure, the retention time and the mass to 
charge ratio (and not the molecular weight as published previously) of 
the observed ions. Unconjugated bile acids formed a formate adduct. </p>

<p>Data analysis </p>

<p>Microbial counts and SCFAs composition in the cecum were analyzed 
using a two-tailed Mann-Whitney test. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>H NMR spectra were corrected manually for phase and baseline 
distortion and referenced to the chemical shift of the CH 3 resonance of 
alanine at d 1.466 for plasma and liver samples, to the TSP resonance 
of alanine at d 0.0 for urine and fecal samples using <rs id="software-2" type="software">XwinNMR</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">3.5</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Bruker Biospin</rs>, Rheinstetten, Germany). The spectra were converted 
into 22K data points over the range of d 0.2-10.0 using an in-house 
developed <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> routine. The regions containing the water 
resonance (d 4.5-5.19), and for urine urea resonance (d 4.5-6.2), 
were removed. Chemical shift intensities were normalized to the sum 
of all intensities within the specified range before chemometric 
analysis. 
UPLC-MS data were processed using the Micromass MarkerLynxt 
applications manager Version 4.0 (Waters Corp, Milford, USA). The 
peaks of bile acids were identified by comparing the m/z ratio and 
retention time to the set of standard bile acids measured under the 
same conditions. Data were noise-reduced in both of the UPLC and MS 
domains using <rs type="software">MarkerLynx</rs> standard routines. Integration of the 
UPLC-MS bile acid peaks was performed using ApexTrack2t. Each 
peak integral was expressed as a ratio to the sum of integrals of the 21 
measured bile acids. 
The multivariate pattern recognition techniques used in this study 
were based on PCA (Wold et al, 1987), H-PCA (Westerhuis et al, 1998) 
and the orthogonal-projection to latent structure (O-PLS) (Trygg and 
Wold, 2003). PCA was carried out using the <rs id="software-4" type="software">SIMCA-P</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">11</rs> software 
(<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Umetrics</rs>, , Sweden) in order to detect the presence of inherent 
similarities between metabolic profiles. Both NMR and LC-MS 
variables were subjected to Pareto scaling, by dividing each variable 
by the square root of its standard deviation. Data were visualized by 
means of principal component scores and loadings plots. Each point in 
the scores plot represents an individual biochemical profile of a 
sample, whereas on the loadings plot each coordinate represents a 
single NMR spectral region or LC-MS retention time and mass to 
charge ratio (m/z). Because the scores and loadings plots are 
complementary, biochemical components responsible for the differ-
ences between samples detected in the scores plot can be extracted 
from the corresponding loadings plot. 
O-PLS-DA was also carried out using the method developed by Trygg 
et al (Trygg and Wold, 2003) and implemented for NMR spectral data 
by Cloarec et al (2005b) to exclusively focus on the effects of probiotic 
supplementation. All O-PLS-DA models were constructed using one 
predictive and two orthogonal components using data scaled to unit 
variance (i.e. by dividing each variable by its standard deviation). 
Here, the test for the significance of the Pearson product-moment 
correlation coefficient was used to calculate the cut-off value of the 
correlation coefficients at the level of Po0.05. To test the validity of 
the model against over-fitting, the cross-validation parameter Q 2 
was computed and the standard seven-fold cross validation method 
was used (Cloarec et al, 2005b). The interpretation of the model was 
achieved from correlation coefficient plots that incorporated a back-
transformation method such that the coefficients resembled the 
original structure of the NMR spectral data (Cloarec et al, 2005b). 
H-PCA methods have been proposed in the recent literature to 
improve the interpretability of multiple models (Westerhuis et al, 
1998) generated from several blocks of descriptor variables measured 
on the same objects (Bergman et al, 1998; Lundstedt et al, 1998; Janne 
et al, 2001). The data are divided into well-defined logical blocks X1, 
y, XB (where the index B refers to each biosample type), according to 
an event, instrumentation or biological compartment. A consensus 
direction among all the blocks is sought. Here, logical blocks were 
defined according to the biological nature of the samples obtained 
from the same animals (Figure 3). Hence, five independent blocks of 
variables were comprised of NMR data from plasma, liver, urine and 
fecal extracts as well as bile acids composition obtained by UPLC-MS. 
PCA was performed on each data matrix individually, and block 
loadings p b and scores t b were generated for each block (Figure 3). All 
block scores t b were then combined into a super block T. The PCA (H-
PCA) was then applied to the super block T to generate the super scores 
t T and the super loadings p T . The super scores t T gives the relationships 
between the observations and all the sources of variations. The 
super loadings p T gives the relative importance of the different blocks 
XB for each principal component as well as information on the 
relationship/covariance between the different variables in the different 
compartments. </p>

<p>Bipartite graph representation of bile acid and 
fecal flora profiles </p>

<p>The bipartite graph (Rgraphsviz) package from R was used to display 
the correlation matrix derived from bile acid and fecal flora profiles to 
assess the probiotic-induced changes to the microbial-mammalian 
transgenomic interactions (Figure 5). Pearson's correlation coeffi-
cients were computed between bile acid variables and fecal flora 
variables from the same mice and a cut-off value of 0.5 was applied to 
the absolute value of the coefficient |r| so that the bipartite graph only 
represents the correlations between the two types of nodes (fecal flora 
and bile acids) above the cut-off (Martin et al, 2007a). The sign of the 
initial correlation was then color coded (red: negative, blue: positive), 
and the correlation value displayed on the bipartite graph. In that 
context, presence of edges between two specific nodes (one of each 
type) reveals a functional correlation (above the cut-off) between these 
entities. </p>

<p>Supplementary information </p>

<p>Supplementary information is available at the Molecular Systems 
Biology website (www.nature.com/msb). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Dr J Trygg for use of O-PLS code and Dr O Cloarec for 
providing the MATLAB tool for data analysis. We acknowledge Isabelle 
Rochat, Catherine Murset and Gloria Reuteler for microbiota analysis; 
Christine Cherbut, Marc-Emmanuel Dumas and Florence Rochat for 
their input and help; John Newell, Monique Julita, Massimo 
Marchesini, Catherine Schwartz and Christophe Maubert for their 
help in animal husbandry. This work received financial support from 
Nestle to FPM, YW and from INTERMAP (grant 5-R01-HL 71950-2) to 
IKSY. </p>

<p>References </p>

<p>Al-Othman AA (2000) Growth and lipid metabolism responses in rats 
fed different dietary fat sources. Int J Food Sci Nutr 51: 159-167 
al-Waiz M, Mikov M, Mitchell SC, Smith RL (1992) The exogenous 
origin of trimethylamine in the mouse. Metabolism 41: 135-136 
Allison C, Macfarlane GT (1989) Influence of pH, nutrient availability, 
and growth rate on amine production by Bacteroides fragilis and 
Clostridium perfringens. Appl Environ Microbiol 55: 2894-2898 
Backhed F, Ding H, Wang T, Hooper LV, Koh GY, Nagy A, Semenkovich 
CF, Gordon JI (2004) The gut microbiota as an environmental factor 
that regulates fat storage. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 101: 15718-15723 
Bax A, Davis D (1985) MLEV-17-based two-dimensional homonuclear 
magnetization transfer spectroscopy. J Magn Reson 65: 355-360 
Bergman R, Johansson M, Lundstedt T, Seifert E, Aberg J (1998) 
Optimization of a tabletting process by sequential design and 
multivariate analysis. Chemom Intell Lab Syst 44: 271-286 
Bjorksten B, Sepp E, Julge K, Voor T, Mikelsaar M (2001) Allergy 
development and the intestinal microflora during the first year of 
life. J Allergy Clin Immunol 108: 516-520 
Blum S, Schiffrin EJ (2003) Intestinal microflora and homeostasis of 
the mucosal immune response: implications for probiotic bacteria? 
Curr Issues Intest Microbiol 4: 53-60 
Clayton TA, Lindon JC, Cloarec O, Antti H, Charuel C, Hanton G, 
Provost JP, Le Net JL, Baker D, Walley RJ, Everett JR, Nicholson JK 
(2006) Pharmaco-metabonomic phenotyping and personalized 
drug treatment. Nature 440: 1073-1077 
Cloarec O, Dumas ME, Craig A, Barton RH, Trygg J, Hudson J, Blancher 
C, Gauguier D, Lindon JC, Holmes E, Nicholson JK (2005a) 
Statistical total correlation spectroscopy: an exploratory approach 
for latent biomarker identification from metabolic 1 H NMR data 
sets. Anal Chem 77: 1282-1289 </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 13 </p>



<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>



<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>



<p>Molecular Systems Biology is an open-access journal 
published by European Molecular Biology Organiza-
tion and Nature Publishing Group. 
This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Licence. </p>

<p>Probiotics modulation of mammalian metabolism 
F-PJ Martin et al </p>

<p>&amp; 2008 EMBO and Nature Publishing Group </p>

<p>Molecular Systems Biology 2008 15 </p>

</text></tei>