<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2626671" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:58+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Activation of naive CD8 + T cells with antigen induces their differentiation into effector 
cytolytic T lymphocytes (CTLs). CTLs lyse infected or aberrant target cells by exocytosis of 
lytic granules containing the pore-forming protein perforin and a family of proteases 
termed granzymes. We show that effector CTL differentiation occurs in two sequential 
phases in vitro, characterized by early induction of T-bet and late induction of Eomesoder-
min (Eomes), T-box transcription factors that regulate the early and late phases of inter-
feron (IFN) expression, respectively. In addition, we demonstrate a critical role for the 
transcription factor Runx3 in CTL differentiation. Runx3 regulates Eomes expression as well 
as expression of three cardinal markers of the effector CTL program: IFN-, perforin, and 
granzyme B. Our data point to the existence of an elaborate transcriptional network in 
which Runx3 initially induces and then cooperates with T-box transcription factors to 
regulate gene transcription in differentiating CTLs. </p>



<p>RUNX3 AND EOMES COOPERATE IN EFFECTOR CD8 + T CELL DIFFERENTIATION | Cruz-Guilloty et al. </p>

<p>In contrast, granzyme B ( Gzmb ) mRNA was low or unde-
tectable in naive T cells but was strongly up-regulated by day 
2 after stimulation and increased progressively until day 6 
( Fig. 1, A and B ); similarly, granzyme B protein was expressed 
by day 4 and remained high until day 6 ( Fig. 1 E ). As ex-
pected, a small fraction of naive T cells expressed the cyto-
kines IFN-and TNF in response to stimulation, and this 
capacity increased signifi cantly in diff erentiated cells ( Fig. 1 E ; 
see also Fig. 2 A ). 
We evaluated antigen-dependent cytolytic function in a 
short-term assay in which target cell death was measured 
within 2 h ( Fig. 1 F ). By limiting the duration of TCR stimu-
lation, this strategy minimizes cytolysis secondary to new gene 
expression during the period of the assay. Naive T cells did 
not display signifi cant cytolytic function in this short-term as-
say (unpublished data), most likely because they express im-
mature (unprocessed) forms of perforin and lack the capacity 
to degranulate ( 18, 19 ). Even after activation for 2 or 4 d, the 
cells showed poor cytolytic activity ( Fig. 1 F ), in striking con-
trast to their capacity for effi cient cytokine production ( Fig. 1 E ). 
Only cells cultured until day 6 displayed robust cytotoxicity, 
as judged by their ability to induce apoptosis in a large num-
ber of target cells ( Fig. 1 F ). 
These results show that after a strong priming stimulus 
through TCRs and co-stimulatory receptors in vitro, gran-
zyme B expression and the ability to produce eff ector cyto-
kines are programmed early, whereas perforin expression 
and cytolytic function are induced later, during the phase of 
clonal expansion in IL-2. Therefore, the two major eff ector 
functions of CTL, cytokine production and cytolytic activity, 
are not intrinsically coregulated. </p>

<p>Distinct kinetics of T-bet and Eomes expression 
during CTL differentiation 
The T-box transcription factors T-bet and Eomes have been 
linked to the regulation of genes encoding eff ector cytokines 
(e.g., Ifn g) and genes important for cytolytic function (e.g., Prf1 
and GzmB ) ( 20 ). We investigated the kinetics of expression of 
these transcription factors in our in vitro cultures ( Fig. 1, A -D ). 
T-bet mRNA and protein were not detectable in naive CD8 + 
T cells, but were strongly induced upon TCR priming (day 2) 
and remained expressed through day 6 of diff erentiation ( Fig. 1, 
A and C ; quantifi ed in Fig. 1, B and D ). In contrast, Eomes ex-
pression was low or undetectable at both the mRNA and pro-
tein levels in naive CD8 + T cells, and TCR priming in culture 
had only a modest eff ect on its expression at day 2 ( Fig. 1, 
A and C ). Strong induction of Eomes mRNA and protein 
was only observed at day 4 and later ( Fig. 1, A and C ). T-bet 
mRNA expression slightly preceded the expression of GzmB 
mRNA; similarly, Eomes mRNA and protein were expressed 
1 d ahead of the reexpression of perforin mRNA and pro-
tein, respectively ( Fig. 1, B and D ). 
This detailed kinetic analysis suggested that, under our 
culture conditions, T-bet and Eomes contribute to distinct 
aspects of gene transcription during CTL diff erentiation. T-bet 
is required early for IFN-production, and our data suggested </p>

<p>diff erentiation, and Runx3 infl uences Th1 cell diff erentiation 
and function through direct regulation of the Il4 and Ifng cy-
tokine genes ( 15, 16 ). In contrast, all three Runx proteins are 
expressed in mature CD8 + T cells ( 10, 12 ), and Runx3-defi -
cient CD8 + T cells show reduced cytolytic activity ( 12, 13 ). 
We therefore tested whether Runx3 infl uenced cytolytic 
T cell diff erentiation. 
In this report, we show that Runx3 and T-box factors syn-
ergistically regulate CTL diff erentiation and function. T-bet is 
induced quickly upon TCR stimulation and is required for 
early programming of cytokine production ( 17 ), whereas Eomes 
is induced later during diff erentiation and sustains IFN-ex-
pression. Runx3 is required for Eomes and perforin expres-
sion, and both Eomes and Runx3 bind at the Prf1 locus; in 
contrast, perforin expression is unaff ected in T-bet -defi cient 
cells. T cells lacking Runx3 show decreased expression of 
IFN-and granzyme B, and Runx3 also binds the promoter 
regions of the Ifng and Gzmb genes. Collectively, these results 
provide evidence for a complex transcriptional network in 
which Runx3 is a primary regulator of Gzmb expression but 
synergizes with T-bet and Eomes, respectively, to promote 
transcription of the Ifng and Prf1 genes. </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION 
A cell culture system to monitor effector CTL differentiation 
We used a simple cell culture system to examine the kinetics 
of eff ector gene expression during CD8 + T cell diff erentia-
tion. Naive CD8 + T cells from P14 TCR transgenic mice 
were activated for 2 d with anti-CD3 and anti-CD28 or with 
splenic APCs in the presence of Gp33 peptide, and were cul-
tured in media containing 100 U/ml of recombinant human 
IL-2 (rhIL-2). We used TCR transgenic mice for these ex-
periments because they provide a reliable source of CD8 + 
T cells that are truly naive; however, we chose not to stimu-
late cells with antigen in most experiments so as to avoid con-
tamination with proteins and nucleic acids derived from APCs. 
There were only minor diff erences in gene expression during 
diff erentiation induced by antigen/APC versus anti-CD3/ 
anti-CD28, and the major conclusions presented in this re-
port are the same for both activating conditions. 
Under our culture conditions, activated CD8 + T cells ex-
panded exponentially and accumulated for &gt; 8 d. We limited 
our analysis to the fi rst 6 -8 d after activation, a period that 
coincides with clonal expansion of CD8 + T cells after activa-
tion in vivo. </p>

<p>Distinct expression kinetics of perforin and granzyme B 
during CTL development in culture 
Our experiments revealed clear diff erences in the kinetics of 
perforin, granzyme B, and cytokine expression during CD8 + 
T cell activation ( Fig. 1 ). Naive T cells showed detectable 
expression of perforin mRNA as well as perforin protein 
( Fig. 1, A -D ). Relative to its expression in naive T cells, per-
forin ( Prf1 ) mRNA expression did not increase appreciably at 
day 2 but showed a reproducible decrease at day 4, followed 
by robust reexpression between days 4 and 8 ( Fig. 1, A -D ). </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>



<p>BRIEF DEFINITIVE REPORT </p>

<p>Figure 1. Kinetics of gene expression during CD8 + T cell differentiation. (A) Kinetics of Prf1 , Gzmb , Tbx21 (T-bet), and Eomes mRNA expression in 
differentiating P14 CD8 + T cells analyzed by Northern blotting. RNA from day 7 Th1 cells was used as a control. Sizes of mRNA transcripts are indicated. 
(B) Quantifi cation of relative mRNA amounts by phosphorimager analysis. (C) Kinetics of protein expression in differentiating P14 CD8 + T cells analyzed 
by immunoblotting. Sizes of protein bands are indicated. (D) Relative protein amounts quantifi ed from the Western blots. (E) Intracellular staining for 
granzyme B, IFN-, and TNF. Granzyme B staining was specifi c relative to an isotype control (not depicted). Cells were restimulated with PMA and iono-
mycin for 4 h. (F) FACS-based assay to measure cytolytic activity of P14 CD8 + T cells against EL4 targets loaded with 0 ( ) or 1 (+) μ M Gp33 peptide 
(effector-to-target ratio = 5:1). Percentage of Annexin V + (apoptotic) target cells in the CD8-negative EL4 target population (dot plots) was determined 
(histograms). Cytolytic activity was blocked by incubation with 2 mM EGTA (not depicted), confi rming involvement of the granule exocytosis (perforin -
granzyme B) pathway. Data are representative of at least fi ve (A -E) or three (F) independent experiments. </p>



<p>RUNX3 AND EOMES COOPERATE IN EFFECTOR CD8 + T CELL DIFFERENTIATION | Cruz-Guilloty et al. </p>

<p>that Eomes might not function during this early period but 
rather might contribute later to the control of perforin expres-
sion. Our data seemed most consistent with a model in which 
TCR signals induce T-bet, which in turn induces IFN-( 17 ) 
and possibly granzyme B; subsequently, Eomes is induced 
during the period of clonal expansion in IL-2 and activates 
perforin expression. </p>

<p>Perforin and granzyme B expression are not appreciably 
regulated by T-bet 
To test the model outlined in the previous paragraph directly, 
we compared the expression of IFN-, perforin, and gran-
zyme B in CD8 + T cells from WT and Tbx21 (T-bet)-defi -
cient mice. As expected ( 17, 21 ), naive Tbx21 / CD8 + T 
cells produced IFN-poorly upon activation ( Fig. 2 A ). No-
tably, this deleterious eff ect of T-bet defi ciency was only ob-
served in diff erentiating CD8 + T cells until day 4 of culture 
but was almost completely mitigated by day 6 ( Fig. 2 A ). This 
most likely refl ected compensation by Eomes, which was 
strongly induced between days 4 and 6 ( Fig. 1 ). In contrast, 
T-bet -defi cient T cells cultured for 6 d showed no defect in 
perforin mRNA expression ( Fig. 2 B , compare lanes 1 and 4). 
We consistently observed a modest reduction in GzmB 
mRNA in T-bet -defi cient T cells ( Fig. 2 B , compare lanes 1 
and 4), which did not translate into a decrease in expression 
of granzyme B protein ( Fig. 2 C ). 
To examine the role of Eomes, we transduced naive CD8 + 
T cells from WT and Tbx21 / mice with retroviruses con-
taining internal ribosome entry site (IRES) -GFP that were 
either empty or encoded a strongly transactivating version of 
Eomes (Eo-VP16) ( 8 ), and expanded them for 6 d under our 
culture conditions. Eo-VP16, but not the empty GFP retro-
virus, increased perforin expression in both WT and T-bet -
defi cient CD8 + T cells ( Fig. 2 B , lanes 2, 3, 5, and 6). As 
expected, Eo-VP16 also rescued the early defect in IFN-
production observed in T-bet -defi cient CD8 + T cells ( Fig. 2 
D ). However, Eo-VP16 did not induce GzmB mRNA ex-
pression in either WT or T-bet -defi cient cells; thus, the par-
tial T-bet dependence of GzmB mRNA expression cannot be 
compensated for by Eo-VP16. </p>

<p>Runx3 controls multiple aspects of the CTL differentiation 
program, in part through induction of Eomes 
Because Runx3 is highly expressed in peripheral CD8 + 
T cells, and because of the T-bet-Runx3 cooperation we 
observed earlier in CD4 + T cells ( 15 ), we examined the 
role of Runx3 in eff ector CTL diff erentiation. We isolated 
CD8 + T cells from Runx3 / (KO) mice of the outbred 
ICR background and their WT Runx3 +/+ littermates by 
positive selection with anti-CD8 magnetic beads (Figs. S1 
and S2, available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/ </p>

<p>Figure 2. Regulation of perforin, granzyme B, and IFN-expres-
sion by T-bet and Eomes in differentiating CTLs. (A) IFN-expression 
by WT ( Tbx21 +/+ ) and T-bet -defi cient ( Tbx21 / ) T cells. Naive CD8 + T cells, 
or cells activated and cultured for 4 or 6 d, were restimulated with PMA 
and ionomycin for 6 h, and IFN-expression was assessed by intracellular 
staining. Numbers show the percentage of IFN-+ cells. (B) Northern blot 
analysis of Prf1 and GzmB mRNA expression in WT or T-bet -defi cient 
CD8 + T cells activated and either left uninfected (uninf) or transduced 
with retroviruses expressing Eomes-VP16 (Eo-VP16) or an empty IRES-
GFP cassette (GFP). Total cellular RNA was analyzed on day 6 of culture. 
The frequency of transduced cells in the cultures was equivalent for both 
constructs ( 65 -70% GFP + cells; not depicted). (C) Granzyme B and IFN-
expression by Tbx21 +/+ and Tbx21 / T cells analyzed in restimulated 
cells that had been cultured for 5 d. (D) IFN-production by cells trans-
duced with Eo-VP16 or control (GFP) retroviruses (RV) measured on day </p>

<p>4 after 6 h of restimulation with PMA and ionomycin. Numbers show 
the percentage of GFP + IFN-+ cells. Results are representative of three 
(A and C) or two (B and D) independent experiments. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>



<p>BRIEF DEFINITIVE REPORT </p>

<p>To test this hypothesis, we used chromatin immunoprecip-
itation (ChIP) assays to ask whether Eomes and Runx3 bound 
regulatory regions of the Prf1 , Ifng , and Gzmb genes ( Fig. 3 D ). 
Both proteins associated with gene regulatory regions in diff er-
entiated CTLs. Runx3 bound to the Prf1 and Gzmb transcrip-
tion start sites (TSS); to a known IL-2 responsive enhancer 
located near 1 kb of the Prf1 gene ( 23 ); to the distal CTL-
specifi c DNase I hypersensitive site 9 in the Prf1 locus ( 24 ); to 
the Ifng promoter near the TSS, as previously reported for Th1 
cells ( 10 ); and to several DNase I hypersensitive sites in the Ifng 
locus ( Fig. 3 D and not depicted) ( 25 ). Eomes bound primarily 
to the Prf1 TSS and the 1 kb enhancer; this binding was sub-
stantially greater than that observed at the promoter of the Il2rb 
gene, a known direct target of Eomes ( 8 ), and comparable to 
that observed at the Ifng TSS, a known target of T-box proteins 
in both Th1 and CD8 + T cells ( Fig. 3 D ) ( 17 ). 
To determine whether Runx3 controlled the expression of 
CTL eff ector genes through its induction of Eomes, we retrovi-
rally expressed Runx3 and Eo-VP16 in CD8 + T cells from 
Runx3 / mice. Because of the limited number of CD8 + T cells 
in these mice, and because we saw no diff erence between 
Runx3 / CD8 + CD4 SP and CD8 + CD4 + DP cells in our pre-
vious experiments, we used total Runx3 / CD8 + T cells with-
out further fractionation as recipients for retroviral transduction. 
Reconstitution of Runx3 / CD8 + T cells with Runx3 restored 
expression of Eomes as well as perforin, granzyme B, and IFN-
( Fig. 4, A and B ). In addition, Runx3 / T cells showed a </p>

<p>jem.20081242/DC1). Strikingly, Runx3 / CD8 + T cells 
were strongly impaired in their ability to diff erentiate into 
eff ector CTLs, as judged by expression of perforin, gran-
zyme B, and IFN-( Fig. 3 ). Compared with WT T cells, 
perforin mRNA and protein expression were essentially un-
detectable in Runx3 / T cells at day 6 of culture ( Fig. 3, 
A and B ). Runx3 / T cells also had no detectable Eomes 
expression; in contrast, T-bet expression was unimpaired 
( Fig. 3 A ). Furthermore, Runx3 was required for maximal 
production of IFN-, but not TNF or IL-2, by CD8 + T 
cells restimulated at day 6 ( Fig. 3 C ). 
We previously reported that Th1 cell diff erentiation was 
regulated through a feed-forward loop in which T-bet is up-
regulated early and induces Runx3, after which T-bet and 
Runx3 cooperate to induce IFN-and silence IL-4, thus pro-
moting stable diff erentiation toward the Th1 lineage ( 15, 22 ). 
Because (a) Runx3 appeared necessary for Eomes induction 
( Fig. 3 A ), (b) the kinetics of Eomes expression paralleled those 
of perforin expression ( Fig. 2 ), and (c) overexpression of Eo-
VP16 in either WT or T-bet -defi cient T cells led to an increase 
in both perforin and IFN-expression ( Fig. 2, B and D ), we 
asked whether CTL diff erentiation was also potentially regu-
lated by a feed-forward loop involving these same two classes of 
Runx and T-box transcription factors. Specifi cally, we asked 
whether Runx3, which was necessary for Eomes induction, 
then cooperated with Eomes to regulate transcription of the ef-
fector CTL markers perforin, IFN-, and granzyme B. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Key role for Runx3 in effector CTL differentiation. (A) Western analysis of Runx3, Eomes, T-bet, and perforin expression in Runx3 +/+ versus 
Runx3 / CD8 + SP T cells differentiated for 6 d. -Actin was used as a loading control. (B) Northern blot analysis of Prf1 mRNA expression in Runx3 +/+ ver-
sus Runx3 / CD8 + T cells differentiated for 6 d. -Actin was used as a loading control. (C) Expression of granzyme B, IFN-, TNF, and IL-2 by resting or 
restimulated (6 h) Runx3 +/+ versus Runx3 / CD8 + SP T cells differentiated for 6 d. The vertical gray line indicates the granzyme B MFI for WT GFP + cells. 
Results in A -C are representative of two independent experiments. (D) ChIP analysis of binding of endogenous Runx3 and Eomes to the Prf1 locus. Enrich-
ment of the indicated genomic regions was evaluated by real-time PCR of DNA from immunoprecipitated and input chromatin. The data are the means of 
duplicate measurements from two chromatin preparations from two independent CD8 + T cell differentiations. The effi ciency of recovery of input for the 
1-kb region of Prf1 was 0.97% for the Runx3 ChIP and 0.5% for the Eomes ChIP. </p>



<p>RUNX3 AND EOMES COOPERATE IN EFFECTOR CD8 + T CELL DIFFERENTIATION | Cruz-Guilloty et al. </p>

<p>cells are not entirely devoid of cytolytic activity and could still 
eff ectively kill targets, possibly by alternative mechanisms such 
as the Fas -Fas ligand pathway. </p>

<p>Runx3 and T-box factors control a complex program of 
transcriptional regulation during CTL differentiation 
Collectively, these data provide evidence that Runx3, together 
with T-box factors, orchestrates a complex program of tran-
scriptional regulation in diff erentiating CTL ( Fig. 4 C ). Runx3 
is present in naive CD8 + T cells before activation ( 12 ). It re-
presses Runx1 and has a positive role in the induction of 
Eomes, granzyme B, perforin, and IFN-. Runx3 binds to 
promoters and putative regulatory regions of the latter three 
genes, suggesting a direct eff ect on gene expression. Additional 
experiments are needed to determine whether Eomes and 
Runx1 are also direct target genes of Runx3. </p>

<p>compensatory up-regulation of Runx1, which was suppressed 
upon reconstitution with Runx3, indicating that Runx1 is a tar-
get of repression by Runx3. Notably, Eo-VP16 did not up-reg-
ulate perforin expression when expressed in Runx3 / cells, 
even though it restored the capacity to induce IFN-expression 
upon TCR restimulation ( Fig. 4, A and B ). This result suggests 
strongly that perforin expression requires Runx3 and Eomes. 
As expected from their defect in perforin and granzyme B 
expression, Runx3 / CD8 + T cells showed defective cytolytic 
activity in a mixed lymphocyte reaction ( 12 ). However, TCR-
stimulated Runx3 / CD8 + cells were as eff ective as WT cells 
in killing tumor cells in a redirected CTL assay ( 12 ). Further-
more, CD8 + cells from the peritoneal cavity of Runx3 / mice 
immunized with certain tumor cells eff ectively killed these tar-
gets ( 13 ). Therefore, although activation of the perforin/gran-
zyme B machinery is defective in Runx3 / CD8 + cells, these </p>

<p>Figure 4. Runx3 controls Eomes, perforin, granzyme B, and IFN-expression in effector CTLs. Runx3 +/+ or Runx3 / CD8 + T cells were activated 
and transduced with retroviruses bearing an empty IRES-GFP cassette (GFP) or also encoding Eomes-VP16 (Eo-VP16) or Myc-Runx3 (Runx3). The frequency 
of transduced cells in the cultures was equivalent for all constructs ( 75 -90% GFP + cells; not depicted). (A) Protein expression in whole-cell extracts (day 6) 
was analyzed by immunoblotting. Overexpression of Eomes-VP16 cannot be detected with the Eomes antibody, as the C-terminal epitope is within the region 
that has been replaced with the VP16 transactivation domain. (B) Expression of granzyme B and IFN-after culture for 6 d and restimulation for 4 h with 
PMA and ionomycin was determined by intracellular staining. The percentage of positively stained cells is shown above the gate; the mean fl uorescence 
intensity (MFI) of granzyme B staining for the total population is shown below the gate. The vertical gray lines indicate the MFI for WT GFP + cells. Results are 
representative of at least two independent experiments. (C) Schematic diagram of the transcriptional network involving Runx3 and T-box factors. T-bet is 
induced by TCR signals and is essential for early IFN-expression. Runx3 is present in naive CD8 + T cells and represses Runx1 and induces Eomes, perforin, 
granzyme B, and IFN-expression. Eomes may participate in sustaining late IFN-expression, whereas Runx3 and Eomes (but not T-bet) may cooperate to 
activate perforin expression. The dotted line indicates the partial effect of T-bet defi ciency on Gzmb mRNA but not granzyme B protein expression. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>



<p>BRIEF DEFINITIVE REPORT </p>

<p>produced by the Groner laboratory. The following antibodies were used 
for immunoblotting: antiperforin (Abcam), anti-Eomes (Abcam), and anti -
Pol-II (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.). The T-bet antibody was provided 
by L. Glimcher (Harvard School of Public Health, Boston, MA). 
The following reagents were used for the experiments presented in this 
report: Annexin V -FITC Apoptosis Detection Kit (BD), CD8 Negative Iso-
lation Kit (Invitrogen), CD8 MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotec), and SYBR 
Green PCR Core Reagents (Applied Biosystems). The Gp33 peptide 
(KAVYNFATC) was synthesized by the Tufts University Core Facility, and 
10 mM of stock solutions was prepared in DMSO. </p>

<p>Isolation and culture of primary CD8 + T cells. CD8 + T cells from 4 -8-
wk-old Tcra / × P14 TCR transgenic (Taconic), C57BL/6J WT, or 
Tbx21 / (The Jackson Laboratory) mice were purifi ed ( &gt; 95% purity) by neg-
ative selection (Invitrogen) from pooled spleen and lymph node cells. CD8 + 
T cells from Runx3 / mice on the ICR background were purifi ed by positive 
selection (Miltenyi Biotec). All mice were maintained in specifi c pathogen-free 
barrier facilities and used according to protocols approved by the Immune Dis-
ease Institute and the Harvard Medical School Animal Care and Use Commit-
tees. For stimulation, purifi ed CD8 + T cells were cultured at 10 6 cells/ml 
(10 ml) in T25 fl asks coated with 1 μ g/ml each of anti-CD3 (clone 2C11) and 
anti-CD28 (clone 37.51) by pretreatment with 300 μ g/ml goat anti -hamster 
IgG. After 48 h, cells were removed from the TCR stimulation and recultured 
at a concentration of 5 × 10 5 cells/ml in media supplemented with 100 U/ml 
rhIL-2. Every 24 h, viable cells were counted and readjusted to 5 × 10 5 cells/ml 
with fresh media containing the corresponding amount of rhIL-2. </p>

<p>Isolation of CD8 + T cells from Runx3 / mice. Runx3-defi cient T cells 
fail to silence CD4 expression normally (Fig. S1) ( 12, 13 ). We therefore fur-
ther fractionated the positively selected CD8 + T cells from Runx3 KO mice 
into CD8 + CD4 SP or CD8 + CD4 + DP cells by separation using anti-CD4 
magnetic beads. This yielded a Runx3 KO SP " enriched " population that 
contained 75% CD8 + CD4 cells and a KO DP enriched population that con-
tained 85% CD8 + CD4 + cells (Fig. S1). The cells were stimulated with anti-
CD3 + anti-CD28 for 2 d before removing them from the TCR stimulus and 
culturing them in media containing 100 U/ml IL-2. As previously reported, 
TCR-induced proliferation of Runx3 / CD8 + T cells was severely impaired, 
irrespective of CD4 expression (Fig. S1) ( 12, 13 ). However, the Runx3 / 
cells showed cell-surface expression patterns indicative of activated cells, in-
cluding up-regulation of CD25 and CD69 (Fig. S1). As expected from their 
ability to up-regulate CD25, Runx3 / CD8 + T cells responded to IL-2 sup-
plementation after day 2 and effi ciently expanded until day 6 of the culture 
period, albeit at slower rates compared with WT cells (Fig. S1). Although a 
fraction of the KO DP cells silenced CD4 expression after activation, the ratio 
of SP/DP cells in each enriched population remained constant thereafter, and 
we did not observe any major diff erences between these two populations 
throughout the culture period, indicating that in terms of eff ector CTL diff er-
entiation and under our culture conditions, Runx3 / CD8 + T cells that also 
coexpress CD4 are indistinguishable from those that do not. The data pre-
sented in Fig. S2 are from Runx3 KO SP cells, whereas those shown in Figs. 
3 and 4 are from total Runx3 KO CD8 cells. </p>

<p>FACS-based cytotoxicity assay. To measure cytotoxicity, EL4 thymoma 
target cells were loaded with 0 or 1 μ M Gp33 peptide for 2 h before a 2-h 
coincubation with P14 CD8 + T cells at the eff ector-to-target ratios indi-
cated in the fi gures in 96-well round-bottom plates. After the coincubation 
period, cells were stained with Annexin V -FITC and anti-CD8 -allophyco-
cyanin. Data analysis was performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">FlowJo</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Tree Star, Inc.</rs>.); 
EL4 target cells (CD8-negative events) were gated, and the percentage of 
Annexin V + target cells was determined. </p>

<p>Cytokine and surface marker staining. To assess cytokine production, 
cells were restimulated with 10 nM PMA + 1 μ M ionomycin for 6 h (unless 
indicated otherwise in the fi gures), and intracellular cytokine stains were per-
formed as previously described ( 28 ). To detect expression of surface molecules, </p>

<p>Surprisingly, Runx3 contributed to the optimal expression 
of TNF, IL-2, and IFN-at day 4 (Fig. S2). For TNF and IL-2, 
the requirement for Runx3 subsides by day 6 ( Fig. 3 C ), possi-
bly because of compensation by Runx1, which is derepressed 
in Runx3 / cells ( Fig. 4 A ). Runx3 continues to be required 
for IFN-expression even at day 6, perhaps because of its role 
in the induction of Eomes expression ( Fig. 4 A ). 
An unexpected fi nding was that the two T-box transcrip-
tion factors, T-bet and Eomes, are up-regulated with very dif-
ferent kinetics in CD8 + T cells under our culture conditions 
and have nonredundant roles in the subsequent expression of 
key eff ector proteins ( Fig. 4 C ). T-bet is needed early to confer 
on activated CD8 + T cells the competence to produce IFN-
upon restimulation, but its function is less important at later 
times. Eomes, which is induced late and functions downstream 
of Runx3, may substitute for T-bet in promoting the acute 
expression of IFN-in restimulated CTLs ( 8 ). Indeed, T-bet 
and Eomes both contribute to perforin expression in NK cells 
( 8, 26 ), and Eomes induces granzyme B as eff ectively as T-bet 
in developing Th2 cells ( 7 ); thus, the relative roles of these T-
box transcription factors vary depending on cell type. 
Surprisingly, however, Eomes and T-bet appeared nonre-
dundant in their ability to induce two other markers of CTL 
function, Prf1 and Gzmb ( Fig. 4 C ). Rather, T-bet and Eomes 
were involved in regulating granzyme B and perforin expression, 
respectively: up-regulation of T-bet and Eomes mRNA and 
protein closely preceded up-regulation of Gzmb and Prf1 mRNA 
and protein, respectively. T-bet had no role in perforin expres-
sion under our culture conditions, and Eo-VP16 did not aff ect 
granzyme B expression when expressed in T-bet / or Runx3 / 
cells. Because conventional Eomes-defi cient mice die before 
precursor cells can be isolated for bone marrow transfers ( 27 ) and 
because T cells conditionally defi cient in Eomes have only re-
cently been described ( 9 ), we were unable to introduce Runx3 
into Eomes-defi cient CD8 + T cells to test formally whether 
Eomes cooperated with Runx3 to induce perforin expression. 
Collectively, our data are consistent with a transcriptional 
network in which preexisting Runx3 cooperates with the in-
duced T-box factors T-bet and Eomes and IL-2R signals 
(unpublished data) to orchestrate CTL diff erentiation ( Fig. 4 C ). 
Our data recall the " feed-forward " interaction between T-bet 
and Runx3 that we previously described in CD4 + (Th1) 
T cells ( 15 ) but are distinct in two respects: in diff erentiating 
Th1 cells, T-bet is induced by TCR signals and IFN-, and in 
turn induces Runx3 ( 15 ), whereas in diff erentiating CD8 + 
T cells, preexisting Runx3 is required to induce the T-box 
transcription factor Eomes. Whole-genome experiments in 
these and other systems will be required to establish whether 
cooperation between T-box and Runx family transcription 
factors is a general feature of cellular diff erentiation programs. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Antibodies and reagents. The following antibodies used for intracellular 
or surface stains were obtained from eBioscience: anti -IL-2, anti -IFN-, 
anti-TNF, anti -granzyme B, anti-CD8, anti-CD25, and anti-CD44. Anti-
CD69 was purchased from BD. For ChIP experiments, the anti-Eomes an-
tibody was obtained from Abcam and the anti-Runx3 antibody was </p>



<p>RUNX3 AND EOMES COOPERATE IN EFFECTOR CD8 + T CELL DIFFERENTIATION | Cruz-Guilloty et al. </p>

<p>sion in 100 U/ml IL-2 with lysis buff er (50 mM Tris [pH 7.5], 150 mM NaCl, 
10% glycerol, 5 mM EDTA, 1% NP-40) by resuspending samples in 10 μ l per 
10 6 cells and incubating on ice for 30 min in the presence of protease inhibi-
tors. Immunoblot analysis was performed with the antibodies indicated in the 
fi gures after SDS-PAGE (10 -30 μ g of total protein was loaded per well). 
Quantifi cation of detected protein was performed with an Intelligent Dark 
Box unit (LAS-3000; Fujifi lm) and normalized for loading with the amount 
of RNA Pol-II detected in each lane. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material. Fig. S1 shows the characterization of periph-
eral CD8 + T cells from Runx3 / mice. Fig. S2 shows eff ector protein expres-
sion by Runx3 WT and KO cells at day 4 of in vitro culture. Primer sequences 
used for ChIP experiments are shown in Table S1. Online supplemental material 
is available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20081242/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank S. Reiner for providing the Eomes-VP16 expression plasmid and members 
of the Rao laboratory for helpful discussions. 
This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grants CA42471 and 
AI44432 to A. Rao, and Israel Science Foundation grants to Y. Groner. M.E. Pipkin is 
supported by National Cancer Institute postdoctoral fellowship F32 CA126247-01. 
F. Cruz-Guilloty was supported by a Ford Foundation Predoctoral Fellowship. I.M. 
Djuretic and F. Cruz-Guilloty are both predoctoral fellows of the Ryan Foundation. 
The authors have no confl icting fi nancial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 6 June 2008 
Accepted: 8 December 2008 </p>



<p>Retroviral transduction of primary CD8 + T cells. For transduction ex-
periments, viral supernatants were generated by calcium phosphate transfec-
tion of Phoenix cells and concentration by overnight centrifugation at 6,000 g . 
At 42 h after the initial TCR activation of 10 6 CD8 + T cells per well in 
12-well plates, the culture media was removed and replaced with complete 
media supplemented with 8 μ g/ml polybrene containing fresh plus concen-
trated virus. The plates were centrifuged at 700 g for 1 h at RT before return-
ing to 37 ° C for an additional 5 h. Retroviral constructs for Eomes-VP16 and 
the MIG control empty vector were a gift from S.L. Reiner (University of 
Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, PA) ( 8 ). </p>

<p>ChIP and real-time PCR analysis. 20 × 10 6 CD8 + T cells per immuno-
precipitation were fi xed by adding a 1/10th volume of fi xation solution 
(11.1% formaldehyde, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM EGTA, 50 
mM Hepes) to 1 volume of culture media and were incubated for 10 or 30 
min at RT. Fixation was stopped with 120 mM glycine on ice for 5 min. 
Fixed cells were washed 2 × with cold PBS, 1 × with cold solution I (10 mM 
Tris [pH 7.5], 10 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM EGTA, 1% Triton X-100), and 1 × 
with cold solution II (10 mM Tris [pH 7.5], 1 mM EDTA, 0.5 mM EGTA, 
200 mM NaCl). After washes, cell pellets were resuspended at 40 × 10 6 
cells/ml in ChIP lysis buff er (150 mM NaCl, 25 mM Tris [pH 7.5], 1% Tri-
ton X-100, 0.1% SDS, 0.5% deoxycholate plus protease and phosphatase in-
hibitors), and chromatin was sheared with a sonicator to yield 0.5 -1-kb 
DNA fragments. After preclearing the sheared chromatin with protein A -
sepharose beads and removing 5% as input chromatin, immunoprecipitation 
was performed by adding optimized antibody amounts (per 20 × 10 6 cell 
equivalents: 2.5 μ g anti-Eomes, 1:100 dilution anti-Runx3), followed by 
overnight incubation at 4 ° C; protein A -sepharose beads were added for the 
last 3 h of the incubation period. Beads were washed 2 × with RIPA buff er 
(50 mM Tris [pH 8], 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% NP-40, 0.1% SDS, 
0.5% deoxycholate), 1 × with high salt buff er (50 mM Tris [pH 8], 500 mM 
NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1% NP-40, 0.1% SDS), and 1 × with TE buff er. After 
the last wash, DNA was eluted by resuspending the beads in elution buff er 
(1% SDS, 100 mM NaHCO 3 ). Both input and ChIP chromatin were then 
treated with RNase A (5 μ g total) for 1 h at 37 ° C, followed by the addition 
of proteinase K (100 μ g total) and overnight incubation at 65 ° C to reverse 
cross-linking. DNA was then purifi ed with QIAquick columns (Gel Extrac-
tion Kit; QIAGEN) according to the manufacturer ' s instructions and resus-
pended in a 50-μ l volume. For real-time PCR detection of immunoprecipitated 
targets using the SYBR Green PCR Kit, a standard curve was obtained with 
serial dilutions of input DNA for each sample, and 1 μ l ChIP DNA was used per 
PCR reaction (performed in duplicates). Melt curves and agarose gels were 
analyzed to ensure amplifi cation of specifi c target sequences. Refer to Table 
S1 (available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20081242/DC1) 
for a list of primer sets. The data are presented as the number of immunopre-
cipitated target sequences relative to input chromatin, assuming two copies 
of target sequence per cell equivalent used for the ChIP. </p>

<p>Northern and Western blot analyses. RNA isolation and Northern blot 
analysis was performed as previously described ( 29 ). In brief, 10 μ g of total 
RNA was loaded per lane and transferred to positively charged nylon mem-
branes (Hybond-N + ; GE Healthcare), which was confi rmed by ethidium 
bromide staining of ribosomal RNA species on the membrane. Membranes 
were hybridized with 1 ng/ml -[ 32 P]dCTP -labeled trichloroacetic acid 
precipitable probe in ExpressHyb hybridization buff er (Clontech Laborato-
ries, Inc.). All cDNA probes were confi rmed to have the appropriate single-
copy specifi city under these conditions using genomic Southern blot analysis. 
Band intensities were acquired by phosphorimaging analysis. 
For Western analysis, whole-cell protein lysates were obtained from 
CD8 + T cells at the time points indicated in the fi gures during clonal expan-</p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>





</text></tei>