<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2241875" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Malignant transformation of normal, healthy cells is 
strongly dependent on changes in the expression of </p>

<p>oncogenes and tumor suppressor genes. DNA copy 
number alteration (CNA) is an important mechanism 
through which tumor cells can modulate expression of 
cancer genes. CNAs are a result of genomic instability, 
which has been described as an enabling mechanism 
of tumorigenesis (1). Aberrations range in size from 
relatively small regions (&lt;0.5 Mb) to entire chromosomes 
and the various mechanisms by which they arise are 
unclear (2). Comparative genomic hybridization (CGH) is 
a technique that is capable of measuring CNAs. The term 
CGH was first used for competitive hybridization of 
differentially labeled DNA on metaphase chromosomes 
(3) to measure CNAs. 
Various microarray platforms have enabled high-
resolution genome-wide analysis of CNAs by array-
based CGH (aCGH) (4). Many different platforms are 
currently available for aCGH analysis, such as bacterial 
artificial chromosome (BAC) clone (4), cDNA clone (5), 
single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) (6) and oligonu-
cleotide based platforms (7,8). Most of the platforms 
sample the genome at specific positions with a certain 
distance between the measurement points (probes). This 
distance is referred to as the resolution of the platform. 
Array CGH data generally consist of the log-ratios of 
normalized hybridization intensities of fluorescently 
labeled DNA from disease versus 2n control samples 
measured by the probes spotted on these microarrays. 
Array-CGH has been used extensively in cancer 
research (9) and careful analysis of CNAs can facilitate 
cancer gene discovery (10,11). Various automated 
methods have been described to analyze the results 
obtained from aCGH measurements. They typically 
either smooth the data and/or try to estimate the location 
of the aberration by defining 'break-points' at which the 
CNA is defined to start or end (12,13). This is always done 
at the single tumor level and procedures which define 
aberrations often rely on several parameter choices to find </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +31-205122000; Fax: +31-206691383; Email: j.jonkers@nki.nl 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Lodewyk Wessels. Tel: +31-205127987; Fax: +31-206691383; Email: l.wessels@nki.nl </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>putative CNAs. It is not always clear how these 
parameters relate to biological reality. Recently, methods 
to discretize aCGH data have been extended to include 
states other than 1, 0 and À1 (13-15). However, these 
methods do not provide a solid statistical framework to 
identify CNAs that occur in a significant fraction of the 
tumors. Especially these recurrent regions may harbor 
genes relevant for tumor development. 
Three methods have been developed to perform 
multiexperiment analysis to identify recurrent CNAs 
within a group of tumor samples: CMAR (16), STAC 
(17) and H-HMM (18), a hidden Markov Model (HMM)-
based algorithm. Of these, STAC and H-HMM provide 
probabilistic outputs. Both STAC and CMAR suffer from 
the fact that aCGH data have to be discretized into three 
states (1, 0 and À1) before the method can be applied. 
H-HMM uses continuous data as input, but still employs 
three discrete states in its hidden model. CNAs are discrete 
in nature on a single cell level, as gains and losses of 
a region of DNA can occur only on a per-copy basis. 
Although a method for single cell aCGH has recently been 
published (18), most aCGH analyses are not performed on 
single cells, but rather on a population of tumor cells 
mixed with stromal components. This stromal compart-
ment will influence the signal measured by quenching the 
true CNA level. Moreover, as solid tumors are known to 
be heterogenic in nature and contain sub-populations of 
clonally diverse cells (19), it is also safe to assume that not 
all tumors cells will carry the same CNAs. This implies 
that an aCGH measurement will measure a population of 
CNAs present in the tumor sample. Apart from the fact 
that there is no consensus regarding the best discretization 
method to use, reducing a signal from such a hetero-
geneous population of CNAs to values of 1, 0 and À1 
leads to loss of potentially valuable biological 
information. 
We have developed a statistical method for multi-
experiment aCGH analysis of nondiscretized aCGH data 
capable of detecting statistically significant aberrations of 
varying size. To this end, we developed KC-SMART, 
Kernel Convolution: a Statistical Method for Aberrant 
Region deTection. This method employs kernel convolu-
tion (20) to perform locally weighted regression (21), 
which produces a smoothed estimate of the CNAs. 
This approach takes into account (i) the nondiscretized 
strength of a clone; (ii) the strength of neighboring clones 
in the same tumor, as well as (iii) the occurrence frequency 
of this clone across all tumors in the dataset. Kernel 
regression automatically corrects for the unequal distances 
between the probes. KC-SMART allows analysis of both 
small and large aberrations using different values for the 
width of the kernel function. This is important, as DNA 
copy number aberrations have a large variation in size (2). 
Using a published dataset of 89 sporadic breast tumors 
(22) we find that KC-SMART identifies several aberra-
tions that correlate with breast cancer subtype and clinical 
parameters. We also identify regions that are enriched 
for known cancer genes. 
Furthermore, KC-SMART performs better than STAC 
(17), the only other statistically-based method currently 
available. Using aCGH and expression data from a novel </p>

<p>dataset of 19 mammary tumors from a conditional mouse 
model of sporadic breast cancer, we identify several cancer 
genes, and we show that complex aberrations can be 
analyzed by varying the width of the kernel function. 
Finally, we propose several new cancer gene candidates 
based on KC-SMART results. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Human breast cancer dataset </p>

<p>aCGH data were used as acquired from the 
Supplementary Data of Chin et al. (22). Preprocessing 
and normalization was performed and described by Chin 
et al. (22). Because no exact mapping information was 
available for all clones in the Chin dataset, we gave the 
clones a 3-bp length centered on the mapping position as 
supplied by Chin et al. We removed all clones with more 
than 50% missing values. We imputated the remaining 
missing values using the averaged values of their two 
positional neighbors. Probes mapped to the same area 
were averaged and represented as a single clone. 
This resulted in 2149 unique clones. Gene expression 
data were also acquired from Chin et al. (Arrayexpress 
accession number: E-TABM-158). Probes not mapping to 
a single ENSEMBL ID were removed; probes mapping 
to Y chromosome genes were removed. This resulted in 
21 339 unique Affymetrix probe measurements. </p>

<p>Mouse p53 dataset </p>

<p>All BAC information was based on NCBI assembly 36 
of the mouse genome. The platform used to analyze 
the mouse DNA was a 3k mouse BAC platform (23). 
Extraction of DNA, labeling and hybridization to the 
array was performed as described by Chung et al. (23). 
Dye-swaps were performed for all samples. The data were 
normalized using median normalization. BAC clones 
containing more than 10% missing values were deleted 
from the dataset. The remaining missing values were 
imputed using the values of their two positional neighbors. 
Should the imputed BAC clone be the first or the last on a 
chromosome, it is imputed using the value of its remaining 
neighbor. The preprocessing left 2895 BACs for analysis. 
Gene expression analysis was performed on in-house 32k 
mouse oligo arrays. Detailed methods can be found in the 
Supplementary Data. The data were normalized using the 
Rosetta error model. The oligos were BLASTed against 
the mouse transcriptome as of May 2006. All oligos 
targeting multiple genes were discarded. All positional 
information of the target genes was acquired from the 
NCBI assembly 36 of mouse. Genes for which no 
positional information was available were discarded. 
Genes containing more than 10% missing values were 
discarded. Remaining missing values were imputed using 
the gene average over the nonmissing values. 
Preprocessing left 25 809 oligos targeting 19 104 unique 
genes. p53 conditional knockout mouse aCGH data are 
under submission at the GEO database, accession number 
GSE7794. Gene expression data are deposited at the 
Arrayexpress database accession number E-NCMF-6, 
details are in the Supplementary Data. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 
PAGE 2 OF 16 </p>

<p>KC-SMART analysis </p>

<p>Both datasets were analyzed equally by permutation 
analysis. The KC-SMART permutation analysis was 
performed to create a null distribution, and peaks were 
detected at P &lt; 0.05 (Bonferroni corrected for multiple 
testing), for kernel widths: 6 = 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 16, 20, 
24, 30 and 40 Mb. One thousand permutations were used. 
The interpolation, as discussed below, was performed for 
an interval [2, 40] Mb, with steps of 0.2 Mb and was 
only applied to the mouse dataset. <rs type="software">MATLAB</rs> scripts used 
for implementation of the method are available from 
the authors upon request. </p>

<p>Scale space interpolation </p>

<p>To be able to lower the computational load which 
is required if the significance threshold needs to be 
determined for a large number of kernel widths, an 
interpolation step was introduced for more detailed 
analysis of the mouse dataset. The significance level at 
a certain P-value is determined for several different kernel 
widths employing the permutation approach outlined 
earlier. Then, a model is fitted to these data which 
describe the significance threshold as a function of the 
kernel width. The function found to fit the relationship 
best was a modified power function: </p>

<p>¼ a Á b w kernel þ c 
1 </p>

<p>where is the significance threshold for the given w kernel . 
The coefficients a, b and c are estimated using an iterative 
procedure that minimizes the sum of squared errors using 
randomized starting values. This function is then used to 
determine the significance threshold for all kernel widths 
within the range of the original widths tested. This allows 
a detailed examination of the 'scale space', which is 
defined as the significant areas in the genome given 
different kernel widths. </p>

<p>Integration of gene expression data </p>

<p>We correlated gene expression profiles of the genes 
in these significant regions with the CNA data. First 
we tested the pair-wise correlation of BAC clones in a 
significant region. If the average pair-wise correlation 
coefficient exceeded 0.5, we averaged the BAC-signals 
across all clones, resulting in a region BAC profile, 
capturing the average behavior of a BAC clone in the 
aberration. This profile was correlated with the gene 
expression profile of each of the genes in the same region. 
We calculated a P-value of the correlation of each gene's 
expression profile with the region BAC profile using the 
Students t-test. All genes that correlated at P &lt; 0.05 
(Bonferroni corrected) were called significantly correlated. </p>

<p>Cancer gene enrichment </p>

<p>The cancer gene census (CGC) list was retrieved from the 
Internet 
(www.sanger.ac.uk/genetics/CGP/Census/). 
Mapping information was retrieved from the Ensembl 
database (www.ensembl.org) using the <rs type="software">Biomart</rs> data 
mining tool. Only genes with valid mapping information 
were used. The genes described in the CGC were divided </p>

<p>according to their label 'recessive' or 'dominant'. This 
resulted in 275 unique dominant genes and 65 recessive 
genes. Enrichment for genes labeled as dominant was 
tested in gains and enrichment for genes labeled as 
recessive genes was tested in losses. For enrichment 
analysis of the genes in the Chin dataset, only those 
genes with measured gene expression profiles were used 
and only those genes with an ENSEMBL-gene identifier. 
This left 11 409 unique genes measured. </p>

<p>DAVID analysis </p>

<p>Genes found significant by correlation were compiled into 
gene lists according to method (KC-SMART, STAC) and 
according to gain/loss status. Only genes with valid Entrez 
and Ensembl IDs that were present on the gene expression 
microarray platform were considered. As background, 
gene list of all genes with Entrez and Ensembl Ids on the 
array platform was used. Association with cancer was 
calculated using the <rs id="software-1" type="software">DAVID</rs> web interface (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">david.abcc.ncifcrf.gov</rs>) and as described in ref. 24. </p>

<p>Discrete data </p>

<p>The raw data used for frequency analysis are described in 
Chin et al. (22) and were segmented using the parameter-
free segmentation algorithm CBS (25) and assigned 
copy number change using MergeLevels (13), courtesy of 
J. Fridlyand. All positive copy number changes were 
counted as gains (1); all negative copy number changes 
were counted as losses (À1) and no copy-number change 
was set to 0. </p>

<p>Frequency analysis. For each BAC clone, the overall 
frequencies of 1 (gains) and À1 (losses) were counted 
and plotted as a percentage on its genomic location. For 
comparison, frequencies of 30% and higher were chosen 
to be significant. </p>

<p>STAC analysis. STAC inputs data discretized to three 
levels: 1, 0 and À1. The raw data used for frequency 
analysis are described in Chin et al. (22) and were 
segmented using the parameter-free segmentation algo-
rithm CBS (25) and assigned copy number change using 
MergeLevels (13), courtesy of J. Fridlyand. All positive 
copy number changes were counted as gains (1); all 
negative copy number changes were counted as losses (À1) 
and no copy-number change was set to 0. We followed the 
advice on the <rs id="software-3" type="software">STAC</rs> website (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="url">cbil.upenn.edu/STAC/</rs>/) and 
divided each chromosome arm into stretches of 1 Mb. 
A stretch was called aberrant whenever a BAC clone 
present in that stretch was called aberrant. Stretches 
containing no BACs were set to 1/À1 when both 
neighbors were 1/À1, 0 when one of them was 0. The 
preprocessed data were loaded into the STAC 1.2 java 
applet and analyzed using 1000 permutations and a 1-Mb 
span constant. The OR regions were defined by either the 
frequency statistic or the footprint statistic being P &lt; 0.05. 
The 'AND' regions were defined by both the frequency 
statistic and the footprint statistic being P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>PAGE 3 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Array CGH data consist of the log-transformed ratios 
of normalized intensities from case versus control 
samples measured on certain positions on the genome. 
In heterogeneous tumors, gains or losses do not assume 
discrete amplitude values along the genome. To model the 
fact that CNAs are manifested in a continuous manner in 
an aCGH profile of a tumor, we start off by producing 
a smoothed estimate of the cross-tumor averaged genome-
wide CNAs profile using kernel convolution (20). 
Array CGH probes are not distributed equally across 
the genome. This unequal probe spacing influences the 
smoothed estimate and needs to be corrected for. To this </p>

<p>end, we employed a kernel convolution-based method 
to perform locally weighted regression (21). 
A schematic overview of the KC-SMART method 
is depicted in Figure 1. The general principle of 
KC-SMART is to place a kernel function at the position 
of each probe. At an arbitrary position x on the genome, 
the kernel smoothed estimate (KSE) of the log2 ratio 
is given by </p>

<p>KSEðxÞ ¼ </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>M i </p>

<p>a i Á g i ðxÞ 
P </p>

<p>M i </p>

<p>g i ðxÞ 
2 </p>

<p>Where a i is the sum of all positive or negative log2 values 
across all tumors for probe i, g i (x) is the kernel function </p>

<p>Figure 1. A schematic overview of KC-SMART. T1, T2 and T3 represent three arbitrary tumor samples. (a) Illustration of the nature of the data 
measured and how it is represented on the genome. The BAC clones are spaced along the genome where the sizes of the gaps depend on the platform 
used. Per BAC clone a log2 value is measured that is a representation of the CNA at that point on the genome. (b) The positive and negative log2 
values in the data are separated and summed across tumors and per BAC clone. After summation the kernel convolution is applied and the Kernel 
Smoothed Estimate (KSE: blue line) is determined. (c) An overview for the method of determining statistical significance is shown here. First, the 
original log2 values are shuffled randomly within each tumor. After summation across tumors the KSE is computed. For both the gains and the 
losses a cumulative density function (CDF) of the detected peaks is calculated. By testing the significance level against this CDF a value is obtained, 
above which peaks are found to be significant. (d) Here the result of a genome-wide analysis is shown. The blue line is the KSE obtained from 
the data and the red line is the significance threshold at P = 0.05, which was determined in (c). (e) The scale space is constructed by arranging 
the significantly aberrant areas (visualized as blocks) in order of scale on the genomic position. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 </p>

<p>
[Equation (3)] and M i the set of probes contributing 
to the KSE. The denominator implements the locally 
weighted regression to account for unequally distributed 
clones. 
Gains and losses are analyzed separately since gains and 
losses are fundamentally different (only a few copies of 
a region can be lost, depending on the ploidy of the cell, 
but many copies can be gained). The separation of gains 
and losses also prevents positive and negative values from 
summing to zero. Several kernel functions were considered 
for constructing the KSE. A flattop Gaussian kernel was 
chosen since it remains constant across the length of the 
BAC clone, and then drops off in a smooth, monotonically 
decreasing fashion. This choice is based on the assumption 
that probe signals of immediate neighbors are more 
predictive than more distant probes. A graphical repre-
sentation of the flattop Gaussian function is shown in 
Figure 2. The function g i (x) is defined as: </p>

<p>g i ðxÞ ¼ I fx i1 g Á e </p>

<p>ÀðxÀ i1 Þ 2 </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>þ I fx! i2 g Á e </p>

<p>ÀðxÀ i2 Þ 2 </p>

<p>2 2 </p>

<p>þ I fx2½ i1 , i2 g 
3 </p>

<p>The variables i1 and i2 represent the mapped genomic 
start and end position of the probes and determines the 
width of the kernel function. I is the indicator function 
defined as: </p>

<p>I fbg ¼ 
1 if b is true 
0 otherwise </p>

<p>
4 </p>

<p>Set M i theoretically contains all probes on the same 
chromosome as x, as they all contribute to sample point x. 
To reduce computational load we only consider probes </p>

<p>that lie 4 upstream and downstream from sample point 
x. In this range, 99.8% of the kernel surface is contained 
and the error for not including kernels further up-or 
downstream is negligible. To correct for boundary 
problems at the chromosome ends and the centromeres, 
the probes up to half the kernel width from the boundary 
are mirrored. 
It should be noted that the KSE of the aCGH ratio at 
a clone position is the result of information gathered 
along two dimensions: (i) information from all tumors 
is incorporated through cross-tumor averaging and 
(ii) information from neighboring clones is incorporated 
through local regression. 
The statistical significance of the peaks found in the 
KSE was determined by testing against a null distribution 
of peak heights acquired from the KSEs obtained from 
several random within-tumor permutations of the original 
data (Figure 1c). The P-value is corrected for multiple 
testing using a Bonferroni approach by multiplying the 
resulting P-value by the number of peaks tested, thus 
controlling the family-wise error (26). Combining the 
threshold found by permutation with the KSE produces 
the result visualized in Figure 1d. All regions where 
the KSE exceeds the significance threshold (red line) are 
significantly aberrant across the tumors, for a specific 
kernel width. 
Biologically, CNAs are found in a large variety 
of shapes and sizes, from small amplifications to whole 
chromosome loss due to uneven mitotic chromatid 
separation. It is desirable to detect both large and small 
aberrations. Furthermore, the strength of gain or loss is an 
important factor, as high-level gains may reflect strong 
oncogene activation and high-level losses may reflect 
homozygous deletion of tumor suppressor genes. Different 
kernel widths must be used to find both very localized, 
high-level and low-level CNAs that span a large region. 
The width of the kernel function will determine how broad 
the region will be across which a probe amplitude will 
influence the KSE, i.e. how much the kernels will overlap. 
A narrow kernel can be expected to detect small local 
aberrations, which will be smoothed away by a wide 
kernel. Conversely, a wide kernel will identify long 
aberrations of low to medium strength such as a single 
copy loss or gain of a chromosome in a fraction of 
the tumor cells, while missing localized aberrations. By 
applying KC-SMART to a dataset using different kernel 
widths, we can construct a scale space of the dataset which 
gives a comprehensive view of the aberrations in the 
dataset. Another advantage of the scale-space analysis is 
that within a single aberration multiple levels of CNA may 
be present. Analyzing these aberrations using multiple 
scales can identify the region within an aberration that is 
significant across scales, and therefore more interesting. 
A visualization of how the scale space is constructed is 
depicted in Figure 1e. 
A typical recurrent aberrant region is several megabases 
long and may contain many genes. To filter the genes in 
a recurrent region identified by KC-SMART we use gene 
expression measurements of the genes in those regions. 
When the gene expression of a gene within a recurrent 
CNA correlates well (P &lt; 0.05, Bonferroni corrected) with </p>

<p>2 
2.5 
3 
3.5 
4 
4.5 
5 
5.5 
6 
× 10 6 
Genomic position (bp) 
Amplitude of kernel (log2 values) </p>

<p>Flat-top gaussian kernel </p>

<p>µ i1 µ i2 </p>

<p>w BAC </p>

<p>+ w BAC 
gaussian: </p>

<p>Figure 2. Main properties of the flat top Gaussian function The BAC 
clone is depicted as a red rectangle. The amplitude of the kernel is 
determined by the summed log2 value of that BAC clone across all 
tumors. The red line is a representation of g i . </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>the average aCGH profile of all probes within the region, 
we consider it as an interesting candidate gene. </p>

<p>Validation of KC-SMART </p>

<p>We applied KC-SMART to a publicly available dataset 
of 89 human breast cancer samples for which both 
aCGH data and gene expression data were available 
(22). The results of the KC-SMART analysis are shown 
in Figure 3. As is immediately apparent, these tumors are 
characterized by a larger number of recurrent losses as 
opposed to recurrent gains. Whole chromosome arm 
aberrations, such as the well-known 1q and 8q gains and 
17p loss are found to be significantly recurrent (27,28). 
Also smaller, local aberrations are identified such as the 
17q amplification of the ERBB2 gene and the gain of the 
11q region containing cyclin D1. 
To test the biological relevance of the results, we 
assessed the enrichment for known cancer genes among 
the significantly correlating genes located in the signifi-
cantly recurrent regions. (See the Methods section for the 
determination of significantly correlating genes.) We used 
the hypergeometric test to assess significant enrichment. </p>

<p>As 'known' cancer genes, we used the Cancer Gene Census 
(CGC) (29). More specifically, we tested genes in gains 
against the CGC dominant genes and the genes in losses 
against the CGC recessive genes. We used the dominant/ 
recessive terminology from the Futreal et al. (29) paper 
which is not synonymous with the classical genetic 
definition of dominant and recessive alleles, but rather is 
a crude separation between oncogenes and tumor sup-
pressor genes. As shown in Table 1, both KC-SMART 
analyses show significant enrichment for CGC genes 
(P &lt; 0.05). 
As an alternate test we explored the association of the 
genes in the various lists to cancer using the Genetic 
Association Database (geneticassociationdb.nih.gov/). 
Their association with the 'cancer' category was deter-
mined using the DAVID Bioinformatics Resources (24). 
As shown in Table 1, the KC-SMART results also show 
a significant association with cancer (P &lt; 0.05) for this 
database. 
In order to extend our biological validation of the 
data, we determined whether regions found significant by 
KC-SMART were associated with molecular breast 
cancer subtypes (30). For each tumor in the 89 tumor </p>

<p>Figure 3. Results of KC-SMART analysis of 89 human breast tumor samples. The human tumor set was acquired from Chin et al. (22). Significant 
recurrent regions found by KC-SMART are shown in green. Significantly correlating genes from the Cancer Gene Census (CGC) list are shown 
below for each result. The cancer gene census list was split in CGC dominant genes (for gains) and CGC recessive genes (for losses). Black dotted 
lines represent the end of chromosomes; magenta dotted lines represent the centromere location. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 </p>

<p>
dataset Chin et al. (22) determined the molecular subtype 
based on gene expression profiles. To determine which 
tumors contribute to a certain significant aberration, 
we ranked the tumors based on their average log2 value 
across all BAC clones in the aberrant region. Next, we 
calculated the cumulative contribution of the top n tumors 
to the total average log2 value in the aberrant region. 
The top n tumors, for which the cumulative contribution 
reached 75%, were marked as significantly contributing to 
that aberration. The threshold of 75% is chosen to be 
a conservative estimate, to ensure that all tumors truly 
contain this aberration. Among the tumors that contribute 
to a certain aberration we calculated the enrichment 
for each molecular subtype using the hypergeometric 
distribution. As can be seen in Tables 2 and 3, this analysis 
reveals significant association of several well-known 
aberrant regions with distinct molecular subtypes (22,31) 
and clinicopathological features. 
Three regions with interesting associations were selected 
and summarized in Table 4. One of these regions is the 5q 
loss, which is associated with the basal-like breast cancer 
subtype and ER, PR and ERBB2 negative status. </p>

<p>Basal-like breast tumors are known to have a low 
frequency of ER and PR expression, and rarely over-
express ERBB2 (32). Similarly, a gain on chromosome 16p 
can be considered a marker for ER and PR positive 
tumors and the Luminal A subtype (28). The loss on 9p is 
most common in normal-like tumors, which are associated 
with a genomically stable diploid genotype (33). This 
region contains the well-known tumor suppressor 
CDKN2A (p14 ARF ). CDKN2A gene expression was also 
found to significantly correlate with the 9p CNA profile, 
and can therefore be considered a putative driver gene for 
this location. These results show that association studies 
with regions detected by KC-SMART not only recapitu-
late known associations (5q, 16p) but also identifies 
potential new associations (9p). 
The classical way of analyzing aCGH data is to produce 
frequency plots. This approach counts the frequency of 
occurrence of probes called as gained, lost or unchanged. 
The method of calling varies from setting a rough 
threshold on the raw data to applying dedicated segmen-
tation and calling algorithms. To compare KC-SMART 
results to frequency-based analyses we employed a </p>

<p>Table 1. Enrichment of correlating genes found by KC-SMART for known cancer genes </p>

<p>Cancer Gene Census Enrichment 
Number of genes in gene set a 
Number of CGC b genes in gene set 
P-value enrichment for CGC b genes c </p>

<p>KC-SMART gains Ã 
521 
17 
0.0213 
KC-SMART losses Ã 
590 
9 
0.0006 
DAVID analysis 
Number of correlating genes d 
Number of cancer genes 
P-value association with cancer 
category (EASE score) </p>

<p>KC-SMART gains Ã 
529 
13 
0.021 
KC-SMART losses Ã 
609 
11 
0.046 </p>

<p>Ã Gene sets marked with an asterisk showed significant enrichment for cancer genes at P &lt; 0.05. 
a Numbers of genes were based on genes that had an Ensembl ID. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Cancer Gene Census. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Calculated using the cumulative density function of the hypergeometric test. Total number of genes in the genome used for this analysis: 11409, 
total number of dominant CGC genes: 275, total number of recessive CGC genes: 65. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Numbers of genes were based on genes that had an Entrez ID. </p>

<p>Table 2. Association of KC-SMART significant regions to the five breast cancer subtypes (30) </p>

<p>For each subtype the significantly enriched aberrations are listed. Significance was determined using the hypergeometric distribution and corrected 
using Benjamini-Hochberg multiple testing correction. Locations mentioned in the start and end column are accurate up to maximally 1 Mb, as this 
is the resolution of the array. </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>discretized version of the Chin et al. dataset, kindly 
provided by J. Fridyland. These data have been discretized 
with discretization algorithms, such as CBS (25) and 
MergeLevel (13). The results of our comparison are shown 
in Figure 4. 
Figure 4a shows a genome-wide view of the frequency 
of alterations compared to the KC-SMART results for a 
single kernel width. Since most researchers use a frequency 
cutoff between 25 and 35% to define interesting regions 
(31,34-36), we chose a cutoff of 30% to define significant 
regions in the frequency analysis. The right panel shows 
the result for chromosome 17. It can be seen that by 
employing a smaller kernel width, KC-SMART detects 
the ERBB2 amplification, which is not picked up by the 
frequency analysis. The overlap between the number of 
probes in the significant regions for KC-SMART 
(P &lt; 0.05) and the number of probes in regions aberrated 
in !30% of the tumors is shown in Figure 4b. The Venn 
diagrams show that there is a large overlap in the copy 
number losses identified by both methods, but that the 
frequency method flags a larger number of probes as 
gained. To determine whether KC-SMART underesti-
mates the number of significant regions or whether the 
frequency method overestimates the number of aberrated 
regions, we used the aCGH data to assess the 'quality' </p>

<p>of the identified regions. More specifically, we computed, 
for each identified consecutive region, all the pair-wise 
correlation coefficients of clones within that region. 
Our hypothesis is that a higher degree of correlation will 
be indicative of a better delineation of the aberration. 
The smoothed histograms for both KC-SMART and the 
frequency approach are depicted in Figure 4c, As can be 
seen, the within-region correlation coefficients are, on 
average, much higher in the gained regions detected by 
KC-SMART than in the regions detected by the frequency 
approach. The frequency approach performs similar to 
KC-SMART when looking at the lost regions. 
To our best knowledge, the only other readily available 
method that incorporates a statistical framework 
for multiexperiment aCGH analysis is STAC (17). This 
method employs two statistics, the frequency statistic and 
the footprint statistic, to identify aberrant regions. STAC 
requires aCGH data to be discretized to contain only 
1 (gain), À1 (loss) and 0 (no change). We analyzed the 
same 89-sample breast cancer dataset using STAC. 
Results are shown in the Supplementary Data. When 
comparing the regions found significant by both methods 
it is striking that STAC does not identify the 1q arm gain 
or the 17q ERBB2 amplification as significant. Significant 
regions found by STAC seem to aggregate at boundaries </p>

<p>Table 3. Association of KC-SMART significant regions to the five breast cancer subtypes (30) </p>

<p>For each clinical parameter the significantly associated aberrations are listed. Significance was determined using the hypergeometric distribution and 
corrected using Benjamini-Hochberg multiple testing correction8. Locations mentioned in the start and end column are accurate up to maximally 
1 Mb, as this is the resolution of the array. 
Ã The 5q loss associated with PR-negative staining was included as it was the most significant association with PR-negativity and only borderline 
not-significant. </p>

<p>Table 4. Summary of association for three recurrent regions identified from 89 human breast tumors </p>

<p>Aberration 
Subtype 
ER 
PR 
ERBB2 
P53 mutated b </p>

<p>5q loss (53 Mb-138 Mb) 
Basal 
neg 
neg a 
neg 
pos 
16p gain (0 Mb-10 Mb) 
Luminal A 
pos 
pos 
neg 
neg 
9p loss (0 Mb-25 Mb) 
Normal-like 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A 
N/A </p>

<p>pos: significant association with positive immunohistochemistry (IHC), neg: significant association with negative IHC, N/A is used when no 
significant association was used. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>This association was identified as borderline significant, but was the most significant association found for PR-negative status. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>As determined by immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 
PAGE 8 OF 16 </p>

<p>of chromosome arms. This could point to a bias in the 
algorithm for boundary regions. To investigate the nature 
of the significant regions detected by STAC but not by 
KC-SMART, we analyzed the raw log2 values and 
compared them to the discretized values produced by 
Chin et al. (22). Two examples of this analysis are shown 
in the Supplementary Data. Generally, the areas exclu-
sively detected by STAC are scored as single copy 
alterations by the MergeLevels analysis done by Chin 
et al. (22). On a log2 scale these gains and losses were very 
small indeed ($0.1), but nevertheless large enough to be 
assigned a value of 1 or À1, and are therefore treated 
equally to large gains and losses. This discrete approach, 
which neglects the amplitude of an aberration can 
therefore be considered to be less conservative than 
KC-SMART and can/may therefore yield more false-
positives. </p>

<p>Cancer gene discovery using KC-SMART </p>

<p>To identify genes that are associated with CNA and 
potentially implicated in tumor formation we applied </p>

<p>KC-SMART to a dataset containing aCGH measure-
ments of 19 mammary carcinomas acquired from condi-
tional p53 knockout mice. Sporadic mammary tumor 
development in these mice is induced by cell type-specific 
stochastic inactivation of the tumor suppressor gene p53 
(37). Mouse mammary tumors present with relatively 
few passenger mutations as compared to human sporadic 
tumors. This is because tumors from genetically 
engineered mouse models have a more uniform cell type 
of origin and they develop relatively rapid giving less time 
for passenger CNA development. This will aid in 
identification of causal aberrations and will reduce the 
number of tumors required for cancer gene discovery. 
Mouse aCGH data were preprocessed as described in the 
Methods section. The result of the analysis is shown in 
Figure 5. In total, seven amplified and 11 deleted regions 
were identified by KC-SMART. 
The significant CNAs identified by KC-SMART are 
large and contain many genes. Oncogenic aberrations 
typically occur because it is the mechanism through 
which an oncogene is amplified or a tumor suppressor </p>

<p>0 
0. 5 
1 
1. 5 
2 
2. 5 
3 
9 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 22 
X </p>

<p>) </p>

<p>Frequency (% ) </p>

<p>0 
0. 5 
1 
1. 5 
2 
2. 5 
3 
x 10 9 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 
8 
9 
10 11 12 13 14 15 16 17 18 19 20 22 
X </p>

<p>Genomic Position </p>

<p>Frequency (% ) 
2.49 2. 5 2.51 2.52 2.53 2.54 2.55 2.56 2.57 
× 10 9 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Genomic Position </p>

<p>Frequency (%) 
) </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>KC-SMART -4 Mb Kernelwidth </p>

<p>KC-SMART -20 Mb Kernelwidth </p>

<p>p &lt; .05 KC-SMART </p>

<p>30% (freq.) </p>

<p>ERBB2/HER2 </p>

<p>−0.8 −0.6 −0.4 −0.2 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
Within aberration correlation coefficient </p>

<p>Losses </p>

<p>−0.6 
−0.4 
−0.2 
0 
0.2 
0.4 
0.6 
0.8 
1 </p>

<p>Gains </p>

<p>Frequency </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
C </p>

<p>Figure 4. Comparison of KC-SMART to frequency-based analysis. (a) A genome-wide frequency analysis of copy-number changes is show 
(gray bars). On top of the frequency analysis the KC-SMART result for 20-Mb kernelwidth is plotted (orange line). The dataset used for analysis is 
the 89 breast tumor data published by Chin et al. The significance threshold for KC-SMART is shown as an orange dotted line. The 30% frequency 
level has been shown as a gray dotted line. The zoom-panel shows a magnification of chromosome 17. Here the result for KC-SMART at 4 Mb is 
shown in green. The green dotted line shows the significant threshold for 4-Mb kernelwidth. (b) Proportional Venn diagrams showing the overlap 
between results from both KC-SMART and the frequency analysis. Overlap is determined on the basis of probes in significant regions (KC-SMART) 
or in regions over 30% frequency. (c) Smoothed histograms of within-region BAC pair correlation coefficients. </p>

<p>PAGE 9 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>is inactivated. We examined the gene expression profiles 
of all tumors to find the genes which are driving the 
aberrations. We used an in-house 32-k oligonucleotide 
microarray platform with 31 769 longmer probes targeting 
19 104 unique genes, which is 68% of the known mouse 
protein-coding genes. By analyzing only the genes that are 
measured on the array, we accept the possibility of missing 
the driver gene because there is no corresponding probe on 
the array. Furthermore, the gene expression data were 
obtained using a pool of 12 mouse mammary tumor 
samples as a common reference. While these measure-
ments will reveal the within-group variability of the tumor 
dataset, genes that are over-expressed or downregulated in 
all tumors will not be picked up, because their RNA levels 
in the reference pool are the same. The complete results of 
these analyses can be found in the Supplementary Data. 
As can be seen in Table 5 and Figure 6 the correlation 
analysis resulted in association of several known and 
novel cancer genes with significant recurrent CNAs. Our 
correlation analysis resulted in the association of three 
known cancer genes with gained regions (Ptpn11-Chr. 5, 
c-Met-Chr. 6 and Birc2-Chr. 9) and one known cancer 
gene within a deleted region (Cyld-Chr. 8). The mouse 
homologs from the CGC were used as 'known' cancer 
genes. The identification of known cancer genes validates 
this approach for cancer gene discovery. </p>

<p>Novel candidate cancer gene discovery </p>

<p>Correlation analysis can also be used for the identification 
of new cancer gene candidates. In addition to the purely 
data-driven approach, the candidate genes were further 
analyzed based on known functionality and possible links 
to carcinogenesis. The possibility exists that a gene with 
an unknown function could be a driver gene, and it will be 
missed by this approach. Keeping this in mind, one should </p>

<p>reconsider these genes when no obvious candidate is 
found, or when validation experiments do not show any 
causal role for the identified candidate genes. </p>

<p>Chromosome 8 gain. None of the 22 genes identified 
by correlation analysis are listed in the CGC. Based on 
previous studies we identified four possible candidates: 
Cdc16, Tfdp1, Cul4a and Fboxo25 (38). The human 
homolog of Cdc16, a subunit of the anaphase promoting 
complex which governs degradation of G1 checkpoint 
proteins, has also been linked to cancer (39). Tfdp1 is 
a transcription factor that operates in concert with the 
E2F family to upregulate genes associated with cell cycle 
progression (40). Cul4a is a ubiquitin ligase that targets 
the cyclin-dependent kinase inhibitor p27 for degradation 
and thereby Cul4a activity promotes proliferation and cell 
cycle progression (41). Fboxo25 is a member of the F-box 
only protein family (42), which is well known for their 
ubiquitin-ligase function. </p>

<p>Chromosome 18 gain. None of the seven genes identified 
by correlation analysis are listed in the CGC. Only one 
gene was found to have interesting functional annotation: 
Rfn138. The human homolog of Rnf138, dubbed NARF, 
has recently been identified as a ubiquitin ligase targeting </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 8 9 1 0 1 1 1 2 1 3 1 41 51 61 71 8 1 9 X </p>

<p>Mouse p53 deficient mammary tumors -losses </p>

<p>0 
0.5 
1 
1.5 
2 
2.5 
3 
× 10 9 </p>

<p>× 10 9 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
5 
6 
7 8 9 1 0 1 1 1 2 1 3 1 4 1 5 1 6 1 7 1 81 9 
X </p>

<p>Genomic Position (bp) </p>

<p>Genomic Position (bp) </p>

<p>Mouse p53 deficient mammary tumors -gains </p>

<p>Scale </p>

<p>Scale </p>

<p>Figure 5. KC-SMART results on the p53-deficient mouse model 
mammary tumors. The y-axis represents the interpolated scale space 
running from 2 to 40 Mb. Black dotted lines represent the end of 
chromosomes. </p>

<p>Table 5. Overview of the regions found by KC-SMART analysis of 
the mouse conditional p53 knockout dataset </p>

<p>Chromosome Position 
(Mb) </p>

<p>Number 
of 
correlating 
genes </p>

<p>Correlating 
cancer 
genes 1 </p>

<p>Candidate 
cancer genes </p>

<p>Gains 
5 
100-151 48 
PTPN11 
-
6 
3-26 
9 
C-MET 
-
8 
3-15 
22 
-
CDC16, TPDF1, 
CUL4A, FBOXO25 
9 
6-15 
7 
BIRC2 
-
11 
114-118 
9 
-
BIRC5 
15 
52-102 
0 
-
-
18 
10-26 
7 
-
RNF138 </p>

<p>Losses 
1 
37-40 
2 
-
GNT-IVA 
4 
91-103 
0 
-
-
4 
122-133 
0 
-
-
7 
72-85 
4 
-
-
7 
131-134 
3 
-
BUB3, BCCIP 
8 
23-131 37 
CYLD 
-
10 
112-129 10 
-
USP15 
11 
37-75 
29 
-
HINT1, RAD50, 
IRF-1 
12 
4-117 10 
-
NUMB 
14 
54-83 
1 
-
-
18 
55-83 
1 
-
-</p>

<p>The positions mentioned are based on the maximal width of the 
aberration found across all scales. Genes that either have a start or end 
position in the region were taken into account. Only genes against 
which an oligonucleotide probe was present on the gene expression 
micro-array platform were considered. The last column shows new 
likely cancer gene candidates, based on the result of the correlation 
analysis (Pearson correlation, P &lt; 0.05, Bonferroni-corrected) and 
based on functional analysis. When no likely candidates were found 
in the correlating genes based on functional analysis, none were listed. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 
PAGE 10 OF 16 </p>

<p>the TCF/LEF complex, thereby downregulating the 
Wnt-signaling target genes (43). Derepression of Wnt 
target genes due to loss of TCF/LEF might promote 
tumorigenesis. </p>

<p>Chromosome 7 loss. Of the three genes found by 
correlation analysis, two were interesting candidate 
cancer genes. Bub3 is a mitotic spindle checkpoint gene 
that can act as a repressor of cell cycle progression (44). 
Deletion of this gene could enhance cell cycle progression 
and thus proliferation. Bccip is a BRCA2 interacting 
protein and has been found to be important in double-
strand break repair (45). Loss of Bccip might lead to 
genomic instability and thus enable tumorigenic 
aberrations. </p>

<p>Chromosome 10 loss. Of the 10 genes found by correlation 
analysis, only one gene, Usp15, had functional annotation 
that could be related to tumor suppressor activity. Usp15 
has recently been found to be present in the COP9 
signalosome, which is an important regulator of ubiquitin 
ligase activity and has been implicated in cancer (46,47). 
It should be noted that the chromosome 10 region includes 
several cancer genes, including the known tumor suppres-
sor Ddit3, also known as CHOP. CHOP expression 
correlated just below the significance threshold set for 
correlation analysis. </p>

<p>Scale space aided aberration analysis </p>

<p>Our correlation analysis did not yield promising cancer 
genes for each region. For example, the chromosome 
15 copy number gain is a large aberration found by 
KC-SMART and spans around 50 Mb over all scales 
analyzed. Yet, no cancer gene candidates were identified </p>

<p>using the correlation approach. Since the chromosome 
15 gain is analogous to the human chromosome 8q, 
we expect the oncogene Myc to be the target of the 
amplification. The Myc oncogene is a well-known target 
of DNA amplification in human cancer (48,49). 
We therefore set out to analyze the chromosome 15 gain 
with the aid of the scale space. The scale space of mouse 
chromosome 15 identifies a large region as significant in 
the large scales, yet only a small region remains significant 
in the smaller scales (Figure 7a). If this region is analyzed 
in more detail (Figure 7b) one can see several genes 
situated next to the narrow significant region. The two 
genes that directly map onto the significant region 
are both predicted transcripts with unknown function. 
The Myc oncogene is situated slightly upstream from the 
significant region. If the heatmaps of the BAC clones are 
examined (Figure 7d) it is apparent that BAC Clone 
7 shows a gain in multiple tumors. This could indicate that 
amplification of the region downstream of Myc has 
a tumorigenic effect, either by affecting Myc in some 
way or acting on a previously unknown gene. It could also 
mean that the chromosome 15 gain is not directed at the 
Myc oncogene, but rather at the Ddef1 gene. Ddef1 has 
been identified as a pathologically relevant target of 
amplification in human uveal melanoma (50). This result 
shows that scale-space analysis can be effectively used to 
gain more insight in complex aberrations and to identify 
potential target genes. 
Besides giving more insight in the nature of aberra-
tions, the scale space is also used to identify both small 
focal aberrations and large low level CNAs such 
as chromosomal gains or losses. The smaller scales allow 
for identification of high-level amplifications, such as 
the ERBB2/HER2 amplification in human breast </p>

<p>Chromosome 7b loss: </p>

<p>Candidate cancer genes </p>

<p>Tumors </p>

<p>Average BAC </p>

<p>Bub3 
Bccip </p>

<p>Average BAC </p>

<p>Usp15 </p>

<p>Chromosome 10 loss: </p>

<p>BAC clone avg. </p>

<p>cdc16 </p>

<p>Tfdp1 
Fboxo25 
Cul4a </p>

<p>Chromosome 8 gain: </p>

<p>BAC clone avg. </p>

<p>Rnf138 </p>

<p>Chromosome 18 gain: </p>

<p>BAC clone avg. </p>

<p>Birc2 </p>

<p>Birc3 </p>

<p>Chromosome 9 gain: </p>

<p>BAC clone avg. </p>

<p>Chromosome 6 gain: </p>

<p>c-Met </p>

<p>Known cancer genes </p>

<p>Tumors </p>

<p>Figure 6. Expression and genomic profiles of the known cancer genes and the cancer gene candidates discovered in p53-deficient mouse mammary 
tumors. For each aberration the chromosome number is given as well as the average aberration BAC profile of the BAC clones in the aberrant 
region. The gene expression profiles of the genes that were selected based on their correlation with the BAC profile are depicted below each BAC 
profile. Green indicates downregulation/loss, red indicates overexpression/gain. </p>

<p>PAGE 11 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>cancer (Figure 7f). This small, but strong amplification 
is found to be significant in the smaller scales, but it is 
smoothed away in the larger scales. Conversely, a large 
systemic loss of chromosome 9p containing the INK4a/ 
ARF tumor suppressor locus is only detected as significant 
in the highest two scales analyzed (Figure 7g). By 
traversing the scale space we can find biologically relevant 
aberrations of all sizes. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Genomic instability is a powerful, yet chaotic way of 
acquiring aberrations that confer proliferative or survival 
advantages to a tumor cell. Correctly separating driver 
mutations from passenger mutations in aneuploid tumors 
is very difficult. The classical tumor model assumes clonal 
expansion of a tumor from a single progenitor cell; 
however, recent views on tumor development preferen-
tially model the tumor as an ecological model, with 
different populations of tumor cell clones competing for 
survival (19). In such a diverse population of tumor cells, 
CNA should also be diverse. As an aCGH measurement is 
an averaged view of all CNAs within a large heterogenic 
population of tumor cells, discretization of these values to </p>

<p>integer levels of copy number change may result in loss of 
information, which is exemplified by the fact that the level 
of ERBB2 amplification is a determinant of breast cancer 
progression (51). KC-SMART is the first method to 
use nondiscretized data to find statistically significant 
recurrent CNAs. KC-SMART uses the log2 values 
straight from the aCGH platform and is therefore 
not dependent on preprocessing steps, except for data-
normalization. We show that relevant biological data are 
contained in the continuous log2 aCGH measurements. 
So, instead of noise reduction, discretization may well 
cause information loss. We think that approaches that 
discretize the aCGH data prior to detecting CNAs are 
likely to perform very well in clonal systems, such as cell 
lines and hematological tumors. KC-SMART is preferable 
for analysis of aCGH data from more heterogeneous 
solid tumor samples. 
Tumor tissues are challenging biological samples and 
their copy number analysis is confounded by several 
factors. Stromal contamination will quench the signal by 
introducing normal 2n DNA in the sample. Very pure 
(clonal) tumors will have a larger effect on the analysis as 
their overall measured copy number levels are higher. 
Both discretization approaches and KC-SMART will be </p>

<p>Figure 7. Scale-space analysis of the chromosome 15 aberration. (a) Scale-space analysis of the complete chromosome. The outer black dotted lines 
denote the end of the chromosome. The inner black dotted lines denote the area shown in (b). (b) Zoom-in view of the scale-space analysis of 
chromosome 15. The BAC clones that are mapped to this region are shown as blue blocks. The genes that are situated in this region are depicted 
as red blocks. (c) Genes close to the region that is significant across all scales are shown in more detail. (d) This figure shows the heatmap of the 
BAC-clones shown in (b). Numbers along the horizontal axis correspond to the BAC clone numbers in (c). Positive log2 values as shown as red, 
negative log2 values as green. (e) Heatmap of the gene expression of genes Myc, Ddef1 and Adcy8. Note: The tumors are now depicted along the 
horizontal direction, as opposed to (d), where the tumors are depicted in the vertical direction. Positive log2 values as shown as red, negative log2 
values as green. No probe against Pvt1 was present on the gene expression array. The two unknown-function transcripts overlapping with BAC clone 
7 show equally uncorrelated expression profiles, and are denoted by I and II. (f) This figure shows a scale-space analysis of significant gains on 
chromosome 17. The analysis is from a set of 89 human breast tumors. (g) A scale-space analysis of chromosome 9 losses. The analysis is from a set 
of 89 human breast tumors. </p>

<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 
PAGE 12 OF 16 </p>

<p>affected by sample inhomogeneity. While KC-SMART 
will employ the measured aberration level in the analysis, 
discretization approaches will, depending on the chosen 
discretization threshold, either fully count an aberration 
(regardless of the degree to which it exceeds the threshold) 
or completely discard a probe when the CNA signal 
does not exceed the threshold defining an aberration. 
Very large focal amplifications will be maintained in the 
KC-SMART analysis, but if a sufficiently large set of 
tumors is analyzed, these aberrations will not be flagged as 
significant, unless they appear with sufficient frequency. 
Random signal noise is always a confounding factor in 
aCGH data analysis. Especially formalin fixed paraffin 
embedded (FFPE) samples are known to produce noisy 
measurements, making aCGH data from these samples 
hard to analyze. Since KC-SMART analyzes gains and 
losses separately, the possibility exists that noise which 
randomly fluctuates around zero will be detected as 
aberrations due to the separation of data in positive and 
negative values. However, this is countered in the random 
permutation scheme where all values including random 
fluctuations are incorporated in the construction of 
the background distribution. By determining a null-
distribution for each dataset analyzed, noise specific to 
that dataset is modeled and therefore also controlled. 
To gain the most power from an analysis we encourage 
researchers to keep comparable noise levels across the 
entire dataset. 
We showed association of recurrent aberrations found 
by KC-SMART with molecular subtype (30) or clinico-
pathological features such as p53, ERBB2, estrogen 
receptor (ER) and progesterone receptor (PR) expression 
status. Identification of the previously reported 16p and 
5q regions show that known relations are recapitulated by 
KC-SMART, and that these regions might be markers for 
the Luminal A and basal-like breast cancer subtypes, 
respectively. The 5q loss is an important feature employed 
in a classifier to separate BRCA1-mutated breast cancers 
from control tumors (52). BRCA1-mutated breast tumors 
are known to be generally basal-like (53), and the fact 
that aberrations on chromosome 5q can distinguish the 
BRCA1 tumors from control tumors is possibly due to 
their basal-like character. A BRCA1-modifier locus for 
hereditary breast cancer has been mapped to 5q (54) and 
multiple DNA-damage repair and cell cycle associated 
genes are present in the 5q region (e.g. RAD50, RAD17, 
APC). This finding might point to a more general DNA 
damage-related phenotype in basal breast tumors. 
Other relations with regions identified by KC-SMART 
are new, such as the association of 9p loss with normal-
like tumors, which could target the well-known INK4a/ 
ARF tumor suppressor locus located on 9p21. In a large 
clinical study, normal-like tumors were found to be mainly 
diploid, genomically stable tumors (33). In line with this, 
mouse mesotheliomas induced by Nf2 and Ink4a/Arf 
loss show significantly less genomic instability than 
mouse mesotheliomas induced by Nf2 and p53 loss 
(van Montfort,E. and Berns,A., unpublished data). 
Normal-like tumors may thus be driven by INK4a-ARF 
loss-of-function. </p>

<p>Array CGH data analysis can result in detection of 
large regions containing many genes. The application of 
KC-SMART in combination with gene expression micro-
array data facilitates prioritization of genes for biological 
validation. While there are many (epi)genetic mechanisms 
through which a tumor can upregulate oncogenes or 
downregulate tumor suppressor genes, it has been shown 
that CNAs can predict gene expression (55). Nevertheless, 
one should be aware of the risk of missing important genes 
that do not seem to correlate very well with the copy 
number data. 
Our results obtained from the KC-SMART analysis 
combined with gene expression data of the p53 conditional 
knockout mice did reveal some well-known cancer genes 
that have been associated with CNAs before. Two of the 
seven genes that are identified by the correlation analysis 
on chromosome 9 were previously implicated in tumor-
igenesis: Birc2 and Birc3 (56). Birc2 is also listed in 
the CGC list. Both are members of the cIAP family of 
antiapoptotic caspase-binding proteins. Zender et al. (56) 
demonstrated the tumorigenic effect of Birc2 in Myc 
overexpressing cells. Their comparative oncogenomics 
approach uses CNA information to find potential 
oncogenes and tumor suppressors. As human data are 
inherently complex, cross-species analysis can provide 
additional power to identify truly causal genes. CNA 
detection is an increasingly valued tool in cross-species 
oncogenomics (57). KC-SMART would be ideally suited 
to provide the first analysis of CNAs in a comparative 
oncogenomics study. 
The examples of Birc2/3 and other known cancer genes 
identified by correlation analysis show that biologically 
relevant results can be obtained using this approach. 
However, not every region delivered a promising cancer 
gene candidate after correlation analysis. Especially, the 
lost regions did not produce many obvious candidates, 
because the correlation analysis either delivered very many 
or very few genes. This could point to the fact that 
a tumor cell might be more inclined to use epigenetic 
factors to downregulate tumor suppressor genes so that 
the correlation between expression and copy number 
values would be disturbed. It could also mean that 
a deletion is more suited to incur haploinsuffiency of 
large numbers of genes, which may collectively contribute 
to tumor development (58). In contrast, amplification is 
more likely to result in overexpression of one or a few 
genes which are therefore more likely to be detected by 
correlation analysis. 
The scale space provided by KC-SMART facilitates 
analysis of complex aberrations. As our scale-space 
analysis of the chromosome 15 aberration in the mouse 
p53-deficient mammary carcinoma dataset shows, true 
targets of gains and losses can be determined. Of course, 
this analysis is spatially restricted to the resolution of the 
aCGH platform and quantitatively restricted to the degree 
with which individual probes on the microarray report 
CNAs. We foresee that the scale-space analysis will allow 
a very insightful and accurate determination of aberrant 
regions across multiple tumors. 
We sought to compare our results to those obtained 
by existing methods. First we compared our approach to </p>

<p>PAGE 13 OF 16 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 e13 </p>

<p>a frequency-based analysis, which is still often used to 
analyze aCGH data. We used the discretized version of the 
Chin et al. data, as discretized by the authors, using two 
different algorithms to obtain segmented and called data. 
Our method compares favorably to this more complicated 
approach. One intrinsic problem associated with fre-
quency analysis is that it is mainly descriptive. There is no 
statistical basis for calling a region significantly recurrent 
aberrated. KC-SMART provides the researcher with 
a solid statistical analysis, while frequency-based thresh-
olds will be arbitrarily chosen. Furthermore, KC-SMART 
has the added advantage of incorporating a scale-space 
analysis. The advantages of this feature have already been 
clearly demonstrated in the example where KC-SMART 
can readily identify high-level amplicons, while frequency-
based methods need additional adaptations to detect 
these amplifications. 
To the best of our knowledge, the only method 
that encompasses a statistical framework and has readily 
available software to perform multiexperiment aCGH 
data analysis is STAC (17). Several remarks can be made 
on the comparison between STAC and KC-SMART. 
STAC results are dependent on the manner in which the 
two STAC statistics are combined. Results for both the 
statistics (footprint and frequency) can be very different. 
This disparity complicated the interpretation and might 
lead to results-oriented use of statistics. Furthermore, 
STAC bases the background-distribution of their statis-
tical tests on local chromosome-arm permutation. This 
means that recurrent loss or gain of whole-chromosome 
arms cannot be detected. A prime example of this is the 
well-known gain of human 1q which was not identified 
as statistically significant by STAC. Also, basing the 
background distribution just on the chromosome arm is 
not a correct representation of the biological reality, 
where the exact position of a gain or amplification is not 
known and could be located on a completely different 
chromosome arm. To get a better average background 
distribution, permutation over the entire genome is 
preferable. 
In summary, we have developed the first parameter-free 
statistical method to find significantly recurrent CNAs 
from continuous aCGH measurements. In contrast to 
other approaches, KC-SMART inputs nondiscretized 
data, which minimizes loss of information and enables 
better modeling of the continuous-valued amplitude of 
CNAs. KC-SMART employs a permutation approach to 
detect statistically significant CNAs while keeping control 
of the error rate. A scale space is constructed which 
facilitates detailed inspection of CNAs at a range of 
genomic resolutions. KC-SMART compares favorably to 
existing aCGH analysis methods and produces biologi-
cally relevant results. Furthermore, using KC-SMART we 
identify several new candidate cancer genes. DNA is the 
static foundation of the dynamic cellular environment. 
Tumor cells often resort to modification of the DNA 
content of the cell to further their proliferative and 
survival strength. The ability to detect these changes will 
help us understand the genetic basis of cancer, and it 
allows us to prioritize our subsequent research into causal 
components of tumor cells. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank the following persons 
for critically reading the manuscript: E. van Beers, 
P. Derksen, B. Evers and K. de Visser. We would like to 
thank J. Fridlyand for kindly providing us with the CBS 
and MergelLevel data of the 89 human breast tumor 
samples. This work was supported by grants from the 
Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research 
(ZonMw 917.036.347), the Dutch Cancer Society (NKI 
2002-2635) and the Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer 
Foundation (BCTR 0403230). Funding to pay the Open 
Access publication charges for this article were provided 
by the Dutch Cancer Society (NKI 2002-2635). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>e13 Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 2 
PAGE 16 OF 16 </p>

</text></tei>