<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2518487" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:33+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>diabetes pathogenesis and prevention and may provide 
a novel cell-based approach to restore self-tolerance 
and regulation in treatment of type 1 diabetes. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice. Four-to six-week-old NOD mice (male and female; Taconic Laborato-
ries, Germantown, NY), female nonobese resistant (NOR) mice, male C57BL/6 
mice, and female C57BL/10SnJ mice (Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME) 
were used. Animals were housed in the barrier facility at the Institute for 
Cellular Therapeutics (Louisville, KY) and were cared for according to 
National Institutes of Health animal care guidelines. 
Antibodies. All monoclonal antibodies (mAbs) used in this study were 
purchased from BD Biosciences (San Diego, CA). c-Kit 
ϩ Sca-1 
ϩ Lin 
Ϫ (HSC) 
sorting experiments used the following mAbs: stem cell antigen-1 (Sca-1) 
phycoerythrin (PE), c-Kit allophycocyanin (APC), and the lineage panel 
consisting of the following: CD8␣ fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC), Mac-1 
FITC, B220 FITC, Gr-1 FITC, ␥␦-TCR FITC, and ␤-TCR FITC. CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FC 
sorting experiments used ␤-TCR FITC, ␥␦-TCR FITC, and CD8␣ PE. CD8 
ϩ / 
TCR 
Ϫ /CD19 
Ϫ sorting experiments used CD8␣ PE, ␤-TCR FITC, ␥␦-TCR FITC, 
and CD19 APC. CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ /NK1.1 
Ϫ DX5 
Ϫ cells were sorted by using CD8␣ 
APC, ␤-TCR FITC, ␥␦-TCR FITC, NK1.1 PE, and DX5 PE. 
Sorting of HSCs and FCs. HSCs and FCs were isolated from bone marrow 
by multiparameter, live sterile cell sorting (FACSVantage SE; Becton Dickin-
son, Mountainview, CA), as previously described (4). Briefly, bone marrow 
was isolated and collected in a single cell suspension at a concentration of 
100 ϫ 10 
6 cells/ml in sterile cell sort media, containing sterile 1ϫ Hank's 
balanced salt solution without phenol red, 2% heat-inactivated fetal bovine 
serum, 10 mmol ⅐ l 
Ϫ1 ⅐ ml 
Ϫ1 HEPES buffer, and 30 l/ml gentamicin (Gibco, 
Grand Island, NY). Directly labeled mAbs were added at saturating concen-
trations, and the cells were incubated for 30 min and washed with cell sort 
media. 
Phenotypic analysis of sorted CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs. Sorted FCs (purity was 
Ն95%) were incubated with Fc receptor block (anti-CD16/CD32) before 
staining with lineage-specific markers: anti-CD11 FITC, CD11b APC, CD14 
FITC, NK1.1 FITC, DX5 FITC, B220 PerCP, Gr-1 APC, and CD19 APC, as 
previously described (4). Sorted FCs were analyzed for p-preDC FCs as 
B220 
ϩ /CD11c 
ϩ /CD11b 
Ϫ using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Cell Quest</rs> Software (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Becton Dickinson</rs>). 
DC maturation and cytokine production. FCs were cultured alone or with 
1 mol/l TLR-9 ligand CpG-ODN 1668 (TCCATGACGTTCCGATGCT) (Gibco 
BRL Custom Primers) (13) for 18 h. Supernatants were assayed for cytokines 
by Linco Diagnostic (St Charles, MO) using LINCOplex Multiplex immunoas-
say, and cells were stained with anti-CD80, anti-CD86, or anti-MHC class II 
I-A 
d (39-10-8) FITC mAbs, with appropriately matched isotype controls. 
HSC and/or FC transplantation. In the syngeneic model, recipients were 
conditioned with 950 cGy total body irradiation (TBI) from a Cesium source 
(Nordion, ON, Canada) and transplanted with 500 HSCs Ϯ 30,000 FC 
populations by tail vein injection Ն6 h after irradiation (14). In the allogeneic 
model, recipients conditioned with 950 cGy TBI were transplanted with 5,000 
HSCs Ϯ 30,000 FL-PB FCs (4). 
Colony-forming cell assay. HSCs were cultured at a 1:2 ratio with or without 
FCs in methylcellulose containing mouse growth factors (MethoCult GF 
M3434; StemCell Technologies, Vancouver, BC, Canada) in duplicate at 37°C 
in 5% CO 2 and a humidified atmosphere (13). After 14 days, colonies 
containing more than 50 cells were scored. 
Chimerism testing. Engraftment of donor cells was evaluated by PBL typing 
using three-color flow cytometry, as previously described (15). 
FC morphology. Wright-Giemsa staining was performed on cytospins of 
100,000 FCs after being fixed in methanol. Slides were examined for dendritic 
morphology under optical microscopy. 
Statistical analysis. Experimental data were evaluated for significant differ-
ences using Student's t test; P Ͻ 0.05 was considered significant. Graft survival 
was calculated according to the Kaplan-Meier method (4). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>NOD FCs exhibit specific and significant differences 
in subpopulations compared with normal controls. In 
normal mice, the CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FC (FC total) population is 
heterogeneous, with the dominant subpopulation pheno-
typically resembling p-preDC (B220 
ϩ /CD11c 
ϩ /CD11b 
Ϫ ) 
(4). Smaller percentages of B-cell (CD19 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>), NK cell 
(NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>), granulocyte (Gr-1 
ϩ ), and monocyte 
(CD14 
ϩ ) subpopulations are also present in FC total from 
normal mice (4). We found that NOD and NOR FCs are 
comprised of similar distinct heterogeneous subpopula-
tions (Fig. 1A and C) and show a heterogeneous mor-</p>

<p>phology with Wright-Giemsa staining under light 
microscopy (Fig. 1B and D). p-preDC FCs represent the 
major CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FC subpopulation in all strains (female 
and male NOD mice, female NOR mice, and male B6 mice) 
examined (Fig. 1E). The B220 
ϩ /CD11c 
ϩ FC population in 
female and male NOD mice is significantly increased 
compared with control NOR or B6 mice (Fig. 1H; P Ͻ 
0.05). The B220 
Ϫ /CD11c </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/CD11b 
ϩ subset is significantly 
decreased compared with NOR mice (Fig. 1F; P Ͻ 0.007). 
As previously shown, the dominant cell population in 
CD19 
ϩ FC is pre-B-cells (B220 
ϩ /CD11c </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>/intracytoplasmic 
IgM 
ϩ ) (4). Of the female NOD FCs, 14% were CD19 
ϩ , 
which is significantly decreased compared with NOR and 
B6 mice (Fig. 1I, P Ͻ 0.05). Approximately 0.27% of NOD 
FCs are CD19 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/CD11c 
ϩ /B220 
ϩ cells (Fig. 1G), which is not 
significantly different than the control strain. DCs with a 
similar phenotype from normal LN and spleen have been 
shown to function as p-preDC (16). Of the female NOD FC 
total, B220 
ϩ /NK1.1 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>DX5 
ϩ and B220 
ϩ /Gr-1 
ϩ populations 
were significantly decreased compared with B6 FCs 
(Fig. 1K and J). The B220 
ϩ /CD14 
ϩ population was not 
significantly different in all strains examined (Fig. 1L). 
FCs produce cytokines and upregulate activation 
markers after stimulation. We evaluated whether NOD 
FCs resemble NOR FCs in response to CpG-ODN stimula-
tion. CD86 was upregulated on NOR FCs, whereas CD80 
and class II expression was similar in the absence of CPG 
stimulation (Fig. 2A and B). However, whereas CD86 was 
upregulated on NOD FCs, CD80 expression was markedly 
decreased with stimulation (Fig. 2A and B). After CpG-
ODN stimulation, the majority of NOR FCs were in a more 
activated state compared with NOD FCs, as evidenced by 
their dendritic morphology (Fig. 2C, right panel). In 
contrast, NOD FCs did not exhibit a mature morphology 
after CpG treatment (Fig. 2C, left panel). 
We also examined chemokine and cytokine production 
by NOD and NOR p-preDC FCs after CpG-ODN stimula-
tion. In the presence of CpG-ODN, p-preDC FCs produced 
more MIP-1␣/CCL3, RANTES/CCL5, interferon-␥-induced 
protein (IP)-10, IL-6, and TNF-␣ compared with the level of 
those in absence of stimulation (Fig. 2D). Notably, p-
preDC FCs from NOR mice produced higher amounts of 
IL-6 (5ϫ), RANTES/CCL5 (3.5ϫ), MIP-1␣/CCL3 (2.1ϫ), 
and TNF-␣ (1.9ϫ) compared with NOD p-preDC FCs (Fig. 
2D). In addition, we found that NOR p-preDC FCs produce 
GM-CSF more efficiently in response to CpG-ODN stimu-
lation, whereas NOD p-preDC FCs do not (Fig. 2D). Taken 
together, these data demonstrate that NOD p-preDC FCs 
are impaired in their ability to produce chemokines and 
cytokines after CpG-ODN stimulation. 
NOD CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FC function is significantly im-
paired in vivo. We next examined the ability of NOD FCs 
to facilitate HSC engraftment using a syngeneic model 
(13,14). NOD recipients were ablatively conditioned with 
950 cGy TBI and reconstituted with 500 HSCs Ϯ 30,000 
FCs sorted from NOD donors. Only 4 of 13 (31%) recipients 
of HSCs plus FCs and 4 of 17 (24%) recipients of HSCs 
engrafted survived up to 130 days (Fig. 3B). In striking 
contrast with normal controls (4), NOD FCs did not 
improve HSC engraftment in NOD recipients, as evidenced 
by the similar engraftment of HSCs with FCs compared 
with the HSCs alone (P ϭ 0.579). 
We then examined the function of NOR FCs. NOR mice 
are MHC-congenic to NOD mice, but do not develop 
diabetes (Fig. 3A) (5). Five (31%) of 16 recipients of HSCs 
alone engrafted and survived up to 130 days. In contrast, </p>

<p>Y. HUANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
70% (7 of 10) of recipients of HSCs plus FCs engrafted long 
term with survival over 130 days (Fig. 3C). Therefore, NOR 
FCs significantly enhance engraftment of HSCs in limiting 
numbers of HSCs (P ϭ 0.029). </p>

<p>To assess whether NOR FCs facilitate engraftment of 
NOD HSCs, 500 NOD HSCs plus 30,000 NOR FCs (n ϭ 15) 
were transplanted into NOD recipients conditioned with 
950 cGy. All recipients of HSCs alone expired before 130 </p>

<p>A NOD FC </p>

<p>C NOR FC </p>

<p>CD8α 
α </p>

<p>R3 </p>

<p>0 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>B220 
B220 </p>

<p>0 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>0 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>CD19 
β + γδ TCR </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>CD11c </p>

<p>220 
220 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>0 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Gr-1 </p>

<p>B22 </p>

<p>α 
0 </p>

<p>B2 </p>

<p>NK1.1/DX5 </p>

<p>B2 </p>

<p>CD14 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>CD19 </p>

<p>CD8α </p>

<p>CD11c </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>CD11b </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>CD8α 
B220 
B220 </p>

<p>0 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>0 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>0 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>β + γδ TCR 
CD11c 
CD19 </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 
10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 
10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>0 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>1 
10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>0 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>R4 </p>

<p>8α 
0 
20 </p>

<p>NK1.1/DX5 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>CD14 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>Gr-1 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>CD </p>

<p>CD11c 
CD11b </p>

<p>B22 </p>

<p>CD19 </p>

<p>B22 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>B NOD FC </p>

<p>10 µM </p>

<p>D NOR FC </p>

<p>10 µM </p>

<p>FIG. 1. NOD FC total is a heterogeneous population. A and C: CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs were sorted from NOD bone marrow, blocked using the anti-Fc 
receptor Abs and stained with anti-B220, anti-CD19, anti-CD11b, anti-NK1.1, anti-DX5, anti-Gr-1, and anti-CD14 mAbs. Flow cytometric profiles 
are representative of at least three experiments in NOD or NOR mice. B and D: Morphology of sorted NOD or NOR CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs were examined 
after Wright-Giemsa staining with optical microscopy. E-L: Comparison of phenotype of FCs from NOD, NOR, and B6 bone marrow. Represented 
are the means ؎ SD of three independent experiments. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.007. </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FCs EXHIBIT IMPAIRED FUNCTION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>days after transplantation (Fig. 3D). In striking contrast, 
the majority of (11 of 21) animals transplanted with NOD 
HSCs and NOR FCs survived over 130 days, demonstrating 
that NOR FCs also facilitate engraftment of NOD HSCs 
(Fig. 3D). As expected, NOD FCs did not enhance engraft-
ment of NOR HSCs (n ϭ 16; Fig. 3E). 
NOD CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs failed to promote generation 
of colonies from HSCs. To evaluate the function of NOD 
FCs in vitro, we tested them using the CFC assay, which 
enumerates the number of mono-lineage and multi-lineage 
colonies generated by HSCs (13). NOR HSCs cocultured 
with NOR FCs for 18 h, then cultured in methylcellulose 
for 14 days, generated significantly more colonies com-
pared with NOR HSCs alone (n ϭ 3; P ϭ 0.011; Fig. 4B). In 
contrast, NOD FCs failed to enhance colony formation 
when cultured with NOD HSCs (n ϭ 3; P ϭ 0.422; Fig. 4C). 
Figure 4A shows representative appearance of CFC-GM 
and CFC-granulocyte-erythroid-macrophage-megakaryo-
cyte (GEMM) for NOD HSC. FCs alone did not generate 
colonies (Fig. 4B and C). 
Removal of CD19 
؉ or NK1.1 
؉ DX5 
؉ cells from FCs 
does not significantly impair facilitation. To define the 
function of CD19 
ϩ or NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 
ϩ FC subpopulations, 
HSCs, CD8 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/TCR 
Ϫ , or CD8 
ϩ /TCR </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>/CD19 
Ϫ cells were 
sorted from NOR mice and tested in the syngeneic assay 
for in vivo facilitation (Fig. 5A). Four of nine (44%) 
recipients of HSCs plus CD8 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/TCR 
Ϫ /CD19 
Ϫ FCs exhibited 
long-term engraftment and survived at least 110 days (Fig. 
5B). Five of eight (63%) animals given HSC ϩ CD8 
ϩ /TCR </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>FCs survived up to 110 days (Fig. 5B). There was no 
significant difference in survival between the HSC plus FC 
total group compared with the HSC plus FC, from which 
CD19 
ϩ FCs had been depleted (P ϭ 0.49). Four of 17 (23%) 
of recipients transplanted with HSC alone survived up to 
110 days (Fig. 5B). These data suggest that the CD19 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>subpopulation may not play an important role in facilita-
tion and therefore that the low numbers of these cells was 
not the cause of ineffective facilitation by NOD FCs. </p>

<p>We next evaluated the contribution of the NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>FC subpopulation to total FC function. Donor NK cells 
have the potential to promote HSC engraftment and sup-
press GVHD in allogeneic transplantation (17). Our previ-
ous data showed that ϳ4 -6% of FCs are NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>cells (4). In NOD mice, 1-1.5% of FCs express 
NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 
ϩ . To test the contribution of the NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>FC subpopulation to FC function, HSCs, CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FCs, 
and CD8 
ϩ /TCR </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>/NK1.1 </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>DX5 
Ϫ cells were sorted from the 
marrow of B6 donors; 58% (7/12) of recipients of HSC plus 
CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FCs survived up to 110 days, and 42% (5/12) of 
HSC plus CD8 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/TCR 
Ϫ /NK1.1 
Ϫ DX5 
Ϫ recipients survived 
over 110 days (Fig. 5C). Survival of both groups was 
significantly enhanced compared with the group that re-
ceived HSCs alone (P ϭ 0.009). 
FL-mobilized NOD FCs facilitate HSC engraftment in 
allogeneic recipients. We previously reported that FL 
treatment of NOD mice restored production of defective 
mature myeloid DCs and plasmacytoid DCs in spleen and 
pancreatic lymph nodes and significantly increased T reg in 
pancreatic lymph nodes (18). This was associated with a 
significant delay in diabetes progression. To test whether 
FL treatment can restore the function of NOD FCs, we 
evaluated the phenotype and function of FL-PB FCs. NOD 
mice were treated with FL for 10 days. FCs were sorted 
from peripheral blood, and sorted FCs were stained with 
B220, CD11c, CD19, NK1.1DX5, and CD11b mAbs. There 
was a significant increase in B220 
Ϫ /CD11c 
ϩ /CD11b 
ϩ DC 
and NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 
ϩ subpopulations in FL-PB FCs (Fig. 6A). 
The percentage of CD19  ϩ FCs and p-preDC FCs remained 
at the same levels as untreated NOD bone marrow FCs 
(Fig. 6A). 
We next evaluated whether FL treatment can restore 
the facilitating function of NOD FCs. FL mobilized NOD 
PB FCs were in a more activated state than untreated 
NOD bone marrow FCs, as evidenced by their dendritic 
morphology (Figs. 6B and 1B). To test function of FL-PB 
FCs, HSCs were sorted from bone marrow of untreated </p>

<p>NOD (F) </p>

<p>NOD (M) 
NOR (F) 
B6 (M) </p>

<p>B220 + CD11b -</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>CD8 + </p>

<p>TCR -
CD11c + </p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>B220 -CD11b + </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>4.0 </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>* = p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>**= p &lt; 0.007 </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>B220 + CD19 + </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>B220 + CD14 + </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>L </p>

<p>B220 + CD19 + </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>I </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B220 + CD11c + </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>CD8 + </p>

<p>TCR -</p>

<p>(%) </p>

<p>H </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B220 + NK1.1 + DX5 + </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>K </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B220 + Gr-1 + </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>J </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Continued. </p>

<p>Y. HUANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
NOD mice and FCs from the PB of FL-treated NOD mice. 
Conditioned B10 recipients received 5,000 HSCs plus 
30,000 FL-PB FCs. Control mice were transplanted with 
5,000 HSCs Ϯ 30,000 FCs from bone marrow of un-</p>

<p>treated NOD mice. FL-PB FCs significantly enhanced 
engraftment of HSCs, as evidenced by 63% of recipients 
(n ϭ 8) that received HSC plus FL-PB FCs surviving 120 
days (Fig. 6C). A total of 13% and 20% of recipients of </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NOD FC + CpG ODN 
NOR FC + CpG ODN </p>

<p>10 µM 
10 µM </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 
6 
8 </p>

<p>RANTES/CCL5 </p>

<p>0 1 2 3 4 5 </p>

<p>GM-CSF </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 10 12 14 16 </p>

<p>TNFα </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FC+Medium </p>

<p>NOR p-preDC FC+Medium </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FC+CpG </p>

<p>NOR p-preDC FC+CpG </p>

<p>0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 </p>

<p>IP-10 </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 10 12 </p>

<p>MIP-1α/CCL3 </p>

<p>0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.01.2 </p>

<p>IL-6 </p>

<p>x 1,000 (pg/ml) </p>

<p>x 10 (pg/ml) </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FC+Medium </p>

<p>NOR p-preDC FC+Medium </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FC+CpG </p>

<p>NOR p-preDC FC+CpG </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Class II 
CD86 
CD80 </p>

<p>Medium CpG ODN </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>NOR FC 
NOD FC </p>

<p>Expression (%) </p>

<p>* 
* *p &lt; 0.05 </p>

<p>Medium CpG ODN </p>

<p>NOD FC </p>

<p>MHC Class II I-A d </p>

<p>Count </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>CD86 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>CD80 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 10 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 
10 0 
0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>10 1 
10 2 
10 3 
10 4 </p>

<p>Count 
NOR FC </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Medium 
Isotype 
CPG-ODN </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Expression of activation markers on FC. A: Sorted CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs (100,000) from NOD or NOR bone marrow were cultured with medium 
or CpG-ODN for 18 h and stained with anti-MHC class II I-A 
d , CD86, or CD80 FITC-labeled mAbs or isotype controls. The data shown are 
representative of three experiments. B: Level of expression of activation markers on FCs with or without CpG-ODN stimulation. The results are 
the percent of CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FC total from three separate experiments. C: The morphology of FCs was examined using Wright-Giemsa staining 
under optical microscopy after CpG-ODN stimulation. D: p-preDC FCs were cultured with CpG-ODN or medium only. Culture cell-free 
supernatants were collected after 18 h and MIP-1␣/CCL3, RANTES/CCL5, IP-10, IL-6, GM-CSF, and TNF-␣ were measured by LINCO plex 
multiplex immunoassay. Data showed an average of two separate experiments. </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FCs EXHIBIT IMPAIRED FUNCTION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>HSCs alone (n ϭ 9) or HSCs plus FCs (n ϭ 8) from 
untreated NOD mice survived over 120 days, respec-
tively (Fig. 6C). 
To confirm that recipients of HSCs plus FL-PB FCs 
exhibited durable engraftment and multi-lineage reconsti-
tution, animals were followed for Ͼ4 months. Three-color 
flow cytometric analysis was performed. Recipients of 
HSCs alone showed the presence of cells of donor origin 
including DCs (CD11c), macrophage (Mac-1) and granulo-
cytes (Gr-1), and NK cells (NK1.1DX5) and the presence of 
low levels of T-cells (CD8, CD4, ␣␤-TCR ϩ ␥␦-TCR) and </p>

<p>B-cells (B220) (Fig. 6D). In contrast, recipients of HSCs 
plus FL-PB FCs showed donor chimerism for multi-lin-
eages, including T-cells, B-cells, NK cells, macrophages, 
and granulocytes (Fig. 6E). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FCs play an important role in facilitating 
engraftment of syngeneic and allogeneic HSCs (1,14,19). 
CD8 
ϩ /TCR 
Ϫ FCs (FC total) are heterogeneous, including 
the following phenotypic subpopulations: p-preDC, B-</p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>0 
20 40 60 80 100 120 </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>P = 0.579 </p>

<p>NOD 
NOD 
NOD 
13 </p>

<p>Irradiation controls NOD 
7 </p>

<p>HSC 
FC 
Recipient n </p>

<p>NOD 
none 
NOD 
17 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>0 
20 40 60 80 100 120 </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>P = 0.029 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>0 
20 40 60 80 100 120 </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p>P = 0.145 </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>0 
20 40 60 80 100 120 </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>P = 0.000007 </p>

<p>K 
I-Aβ I-Aα I-Eβ I-Eα 
D </p>

<p>*MHC class II I-Eα is not expressed. Source: Jackson Laboratory, Bar Harbor, ME </p>

<p>NOR </p>

<p>NOD </p>

<p>Mouse strain </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>g7 </p>

<p>g7 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>d 
d </p>

<p>d </p>

<p> *  
 *  </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NOR 
NOR 
NOR 
10 </p>

<p>Irradiation controls NOR 
4 </p>

<p>HSC 
FC 
Recipient n </p>

<p>NOR 
none 
NOR 
16 </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>NOD 
NOR 
NOD 
15 </p>

<p>Irradiation controls NOD 
6 </p>

<p>HSC 
FC 
Recipient n </p>

<p>NOD 
none 
NOD 
21 
NOR 
NOD 
NOR 
16 </p>

<p>Irradiation controls NOR 
4 </p>

<p>HSC 
FC 
Recipient n </p>

<p>NOR 
none 
NOR 
20 </p>

<p>FIG. 3. NOD FCs are functionally impaired in vivo. HSCs (500) and FCs (30,000) were sorted from donor marrow and transplanted into syngeneic 
recipients. HSCs and FCs were mixed before injection. A: Haplotype pedigree of NOD and NOR mice. B: Survival of NOD recipients of NOD HSCs 
with or without NOD FCs. C: Survival of NOR recipients of HSCs and FCs or HSCs alone from NOR donors. D: Survival of NOD recipients of HSCs 
from NOD mice with or without additional FCs from NOR mice. E: Survival of NOR recipients of HSCs and FCs or HSCs alone, HSCs from NOR 
mice, and FCs from NOD mice. Results are from three to five separate transplant experiments for each experimental group. </p>

<p>Y. HUANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
cells, NK cells, and monocytes (4). The p-preDC FC 
subpopulation represents the majority of FCs and plays a 
critical role in this complex network (4). Removal of the 
p-preDC component from the FCs results in complete loss 
of facilitation, confirming that p-preDCs are the primary 
component in facilitation (4). However, p-preDC FCs 
facilitate HSC engraftment significantly less efficiently 
than total FCs (4), suggesting that other FC subpopula-
tions expressing the B-cell and NK cell phenotypes may 
play a collaborative role in facilitation. FCs induce gener-
ation of T reg in vitro and in vivo (20,21). More recently, T reg 
have been shown to enhance engraftment of HSCs in 
syngeneic recipients (22). The fact that the FC maintains 
its tolerogenic function in vivo addresses one of the major 
concerns regarding DC-based therapies: how to avoid 
immune activation and maintain tolerogenicity after infu-
sion in vivo (23). As such, FCs may offer a novel cell-based 
therapeutic approach to induce tolerance in the clinic for 
treatment of autoimmune disorders. 
In the present study, we evaluated the function of FCs in 
the context of a mouse model for type 1 diabetes, a 
systemic autoimmune disease (5). We found that NOD 
FCs, as a heterogeneous population, share phenotypic 
characteristics similar to those previously described for 
wild-type FCs (4). However, the percentages of both 
CD19 
ϩ and NK1.1 
ϩ DX5 
ϩ cells in NOD FCs were signifi-
cantly decreased compared with NOR or B6 FCs. NOD 
FCs were functionally impaired and failed to facilitate 
engraftment of HSCs in both syngeneic and allogeneic 
recipients, as well as in an in vitro assay for FCs. Notably, 
FL treatment expanded PB FCs in NOD mice and restored 
the ability of NOD FCs from the PB to facilitate engraft-
ment of allogeneic HSCs. We propose that the defective 
function of NOD FCs may be due to an abnormal activa-
tion status of the p-preDC FC subpopulation or the pres-
ence of impaired function of a collaborative subpopulation 
in FCs such as B-cells or NK cells. This hypothesis offers 
an attractive explanation for the mechanism by which FCs 
enhance HSC engraftment in vivo and induce tolerance. 
The majority of FCs are B220 
ϩ /CD11c 
ϩ /CD11b 
Ϫ and 
share characteristic features of p-preDC, including mor-
phology and phenotype, secretion of similar cytokines and 
chemokines, and maturation after stimulation with CpG-
ODN (4). However, their distinct differences, including the 
fact that FCs produce IL-10 whereas p-preDC do not, may 
offer an understanding as to how p-preDC FCs remain </p>

<p>tolerogenic in vivo. p-preDCs play an important role in 
regulating innate and adaptive immune responses. They 
selectively express toll-like receptors (TLR)-7 and TLR-9 
and are specialized in rapid secretion of type 1 IFN after 
viral stimulation (24). p-preDC can promote the function 
of NK cells, B-cells, T-cells, and myeloid DCs through type 
1 IFN during an antiviral immune response and differenti-
ate into unique types of mature DCs, which directly 
regulate the function of T-cells and thus link innate and 
adaptive immune responses. We were the first to show that 
p-preDC have the potential to facilitate engraftment of 
HSCs (4). p-preDCs also induce tolerance to heart allo-
grafts (25). Several studies have demonstrated an associ-
ation between the pathogenesis of autoimmune diseases 
(systemic lupus erythematosus, Sjogren's Syndrome, and 
dermatomyositis) and defective function of IFN-␣ produc-
ing p-preDC (26 -28). NOD mice exhibit an abnormal DC 
phenotype and function (10,11). We show here for the first 
time that FCs from NOD mice exhibit a functional defect 
in facilitating HSC engraftment in vivo and impaired 
function in vitro as well. However, the fact that FL 
treatment of NOD donors results in production of func-
tional FCs implies that the defect is probably not cell 
intrinsic, but rather due to a lacking signal or activated 
state. 
FL plays a critical role in the development of p-preDC in 
humans and mice (29,30). The ability of FL to promote 
p-preDC development in vivo was confirmed by experi-
ments showing that administration of FL into human 
volunteers led to an increase in the number of PB p-
preDCs in humans and that FL transgenic mice have 
increased numbers of p-preDCs, where FL-deficient mice 
have fewer p-preDCs (31). Our own work showed that 
treatment of prediabetic NOD mice with FL significantly 
decreased insulitis and progression to diabetes and was 
associated with a significant increase in myeloid DCs, 
plasmacytoid DCs, and T reg (18). When DCs from NOD 
mice bone marrow are treated with nuclear factor B-
specific ODN in vitro, administration of DCs into NOD 
mice can effectively prevent the onset of diabetes (32). FL 
is also a key cytokine for FC generation and expansion, as 
evidenced by FL-bone marrow culture and the mobiliza-
tion of FC in peripheral blood (4). FL-mobilized PB FCs 
promote the establishment of donor chimerism and toler-
ance induction. In the present study, we showed that FL 
treatment can restore the function of NOD FCs, demon-</p>

<p>CFC colonies (40x) </p>

<p>GM 
GEMM </p>

<p>NOR CFC at day 14 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>140 </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>180 </p>

<p>HSC HSC + FC FC </p>

<p>CFC/1000 HSC </p>

<p>P =0.011 </p>

<p>NOD CFC at day 14 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>HSC HSC + FC FC </p>

<p>CFC/1000 HSC </p>

<p>P = 0.422 </p>

<p>A 
B 
C </p>

<p>FIG. 4. NOD FCs fail to promote HSC colony formation in vitro. CFC assays were performed on sorted HSCs plus FCs from NOD or NOR mice. 
A: Representative appearance of colonies at 14 days. B: HSCs (2,000) and FCs (4,000) were sorted from bone marrow of NOR mice; results are 
expressed as CFC frequency per 1,000 HSCs from three different experiments. C: HSCs and FCs from NOD mice; data represent three different 
experiments. Each rectangle (f) represents one individual sample. The dotted lines link samples from the same experiments. Averaged data from 
three experiments are presented as means ؎ SE. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-0356 for a high-quality digital representation of this 
figure.) </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FCs EXHIBIT IMPAIRED FUNCTION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>strating that FL can promote that development and func-
tion of FCs in NOD mice. 
The importance of myeloid DCs on their ability to 
trigger B-cell growth and differentiation has been ad-
dressed (33). A recent study showed that the p-preDCs 
regulate B-cell function by producing IFN-␣ and IL-6, 
which thereby induces B-cell differentiation (34). Deple-
tion of p-preDC from human blood mononuclear cells 
abrogates the secretion of immunoglobulins in response to 
influenza virus and affects the differentiation of activated </p>

<p>B-cells into plasma cells through the secretion of IFN-␣␤ 
and IL-6 (34). Several experimental models in animals 
have shown that B-cells are involved in inducing T-cell 
tolerance in vivo (35,36). The role of B-cells in autoim-
mune diseases may occur through several mechanistic 
pathways that include self-reactive antibodies, secretion 
of inflammatory cytokines, participation in antigen presen-
tation, and augmentation of T-cell activation (37). In NOD 
mice, the B-cell subpopulation (CD19 
ϩ ) within the total 
FC population is present at a much lower frequency </p>

<p>NOR none 
none 
NOR 
17 
NOR NOR 
none 
NOR 
8 
NOR none 
NOR 
NOR 
9 
Irradiation 
NOR 
5 </p>

<p>HSC CD8 + /TCR -CD8 + /TCR -/CD19 -Recipient n </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>70 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>90 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 110 </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p> *  *  *  </p>

<p> *  *  * P = 0.044 </p>

<p> *  * P = 0.159 </p>

<p> * P = 0.49 </p>

<p> * P = 0.54 
 *  * P = 0.009 </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90100110 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p> *  </p>

<p> *  *  </p>

<p>B6 
none 
none 
C3H 
12 </p>

<p>B6 
B6 
none 
C3H 
12 
B6 
none 
B6 
C3H 
12 
Irradiation 
C3H 
3 </p>

<p>HSC CD8 + /TCR -CD8 + /TCR -/NK1.1 -DX5 -Recipient n </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 200 400 600 800 1000 </p>

<p>FSC-Height </p>

<p>R1 </p>

<p>SSC-Height </p>

<p>0 
200 400 </p>

<p>600 
800 1000 </p>

<p>10 4 
10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 </p>

<p>CD19 </p>

<p>CD19 + FC 
CD19 -FC </p>

<p>Counts </p>

<p>0 2 4 6 8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>NK 1.1DX5 </p>

<p>Counts </p>

<p>10 0 
10 1 
10 2 
10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>0 
2 4 6 8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>NK + FC </p>

<p>NK -FC </p>

<p>TCR FITC </p>

<p>CD8 PE </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>R2 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Removal of CD19 
؉ or NK1.1 
؉ DX5 
؉ FC 
subpopulations did not significantly affect fa-
cilitation. A: BM cells were stained with anti-
CD8 PE or APC, anti-TCR-␤ FITC, anti-
TCR-␥␦ FITC, and anti-CD19 APC, or anti-
NK1.1DX5 PE, and gated R2 for CD8 
؉ /TCR </p>

<p>؊ </p>

<p>FCs (middle panel), and CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ CD19 
؊ or 
CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ NK1.1 
؊ DX5 
؊ subpopulation was 
sorted (left panel). B: Survival of syngeneic 
recipients transplanted with HSCs and CD8 
؉ / 
TCR 
؊ FCs or CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ CD19 
؊ NOR recipi-
ents were conditioned with 950 cGy TBI and 
transplanted with 500 HSCs alone or in com-
bination with 30,000 CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs (HSC ؉ 
FC group), CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ CD19 
؊ (HSC ؉ CD8 
؉ / 
TCR 
؊ CD19 
؊ group). C: Survival of recipients 
transplanted with HSC plus CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ FCs 
or CD8 
؉ /TCR 
؊ NK1.1 
؊ DX5 
؊ in an allogeneic 
model (B6 3 C3H). Results are from three to 
four separate transplant experiments. </p>

<p>Y. HUANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
compared with NOR and B6 controls. The function of the 
CD19  ϩ FC subpopulation remains elusive. Removal of this 
subpopulation from normal donors did not impair facilita-
tion. It is formally possible that the CD19 
ϩ FC subpopula-
tion does not contribute to FC function or that there is 
redundancy in the system that is contributed from another 
FC collaborative subpopulation. 
NOD FCs also contain significantly lower numbers of 
NK1.1 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>DX5 
ϩ cells compared with B6 or NOR mice. It was 
unclear whether the failure of FC function was due to 
decreased numbers of the NK FC subpopulation. NK cells 
have been shown to play a major role in regulating early 
engraftment of allogeneic bone marrow cells, both by 
activation as well as inhibition of immune responses (38). 
Adoptive transfer of activated NK cells early after trans-
plantation inhibits GVHD and promotes graft-versus-tumor 
(GVT) in the mouse model (39). Recently, various studies 
have investigated the interaction between NK cells and 
plasmacytoid DCs, suggesting that the cross-talk between 
NK cells and DCs leads to NK cell activation and DC 
maturation (40). NOD mice exhibit an abnormally low 
level of NK cell activity (7,41) and a defect in NK/T-cells 
(42). To evaluate whether NK FCs were involved in 
facilitation of HSC engraftment, we performed allogeneic 
HSC transplantation (B6 3 C3H) using FCs depleted of </p>

<p>the NK FC subpopulation. There was no difference in 
engraftment in mice that receive HSC plus FC total vs. FCs 
depleted of NK FCs, suggesting that NK FCs did not 
contribute to facilitation. 
The interaction of DCs and T reg in the regulation of 
innate and adaptive immune responses has been reported 
(43). The consequences of DC interactions with T reg 
depend on the phenotype and maturation status of DCs. 
Mature DCs have the unique ability to promote natural T reg 
expansion, which limits immune responses to self-antigen 
(43,44), whereas immature DCs induce the generation of 
adaptive T reg , which control the immune response to 
non-self-antigen (45). Mice lacking CD28 or its ligands 
have decreased numbers of CD4 
ϩ /CD25 
ϩ cells (46). These 
data suggest that both CD86 and CD80 are capable of 
delivering the signals that promote T reg generation. It has 
been shown that on the NOD mouse background, genetic 
ablation of CD86 results in only a subtle decrease in T reg 
numbers (20 -30% reduction). The remaining T reg were 
largely dependent on CD80, as the additional injection of 
anti-CD80 blocking mAbs substantially decreased the 
number of CD4 </p>

<p>ϩ </p>

<p>/CD25 
ϩ cells (ϳ70% reduction). These 
data support a more important role for CD80 than CD86 in 
generation of T reg (47). Notably, we found that NOD FCs 
exhibit significantly impaired upregulation of CD86 after </p>

<p>NOD FL-PB FC </p>

<p>10 µM </p>

<p>B220 + CD11c + CD11b -</p>

<p>B220 -CD11c + CD11b + </p>

<p>B220 + NK1.1 + DX5 + </p>

<p>B220 + CD19 + </p>

<p>NOD BM FC </p>

<p>NOD FL-PB FC </p>

<p>% FC total </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90100 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NOD 
None 
B10 
9 
NOD 
BM NOD 
B10 
8 </p>

<p>NOD 
FL-PB NOD B10 
8 </p>

<p>HSC 
FC 
Recipient 
n </p>

<p>Days after transplantation </p>

<p>% survival </p>

<p>0 
20 40 60 80 100 120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>P = 0.02 </p>

<p>FIG. 6. FL-mobilized PB FCs facilitate HSC engraftment in allogeneic recipients. Recombinant human FL (expressed from CHO cells) (provided 
by Amgen, Thousand Oaks, CA) was diluted in 0.1% mouse serum albumin (MSA; Sigma, St. Louis, MO) at a concentration of 100 g/ml. Donor 
NOD female mice were injected with 10 g FL once daily subcutaneously from day 0 to day 9. Control mice received saline injections. A: Flow 
cytometric analysis of subpopulations in sorted FL-mobilized PB FCs. B: Sorted FL-PB FCs were examined after Wright-Giemsa staining by 
optical microscopy. C: Survival of recipients of HSC plus FL-mobilized PB FCs in allogeneic model (NOD 3 B10). B10 recipients were conditioned 
with 950 cGy TBI and transplanted with 10,000 HSCs from untreated NOD donors either alone or mixed with 30,000 purified FCs from untreated 
NOD bone marrow, or from FL-mobilized PB FCs from NOD mice. D and E: Multilineage typing of representative B10 recipients of NOD HSCs 
alone or recipients of NOD HSCs plus FL-PB FCs. Multilineage data are from PB 3 months after transplantation and analyzed based on the 
lymphoid and myeloid gate. Data shown are from one representative recipient. A total of three to five recipients were analyzed per group. </p>

<p>NOD p-preDC FCs EXHIBIT IMPAIRED FUNCTION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>stimulation with CpG. Similarly, and in contrast with FCs 
from diabetes-resistant donors, they failed to produce 
GM-CSF and produced significantly lower levels of IL-6 
after CpG stimulation. Several groups have reported that 
NOD mice exhibited reduced T reg frequency (48,49), and 
their impaired suppressive function has been linked to 
diabetes pathogenesis (50). The fact that wild-type FCs 
can induce the generation of T reg , but only in the presence 
of CpG-ODN (21), and that they are impaired in function in 
diabetes-prone NOD mice suggests that FCs may also play 
a distinct role in diabetes pathogenesis. 
In conclusion, our data reveal a novel defect in NOD FC 
function that is restored by treatment with FL. Our data 
suggest the critical role of FL in developing and maintain-
ing the function of FCs. These findings may have clinical </p>

<p>implications for the treatment of type 1 diabetes and 
possibly other autoimmune disease states. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported in part by National Institutes of 
Health grants R01 DK069766 and 5R01 HL063442; Juvenile 
Diabetes Research Foundation grants 1-2005-1037 and 
1-2006-1466; the Department of the Navy, Office of Naval 
Research; the Department of the Army, Office of Army 
Research; the Commonwealth of Kentucky Research Chal-
lenge Trust Fund; the W.M. Keck Foundation; and the 
Jewish Hospital Foundation. 
The authors thank Dr. Thomas C. Mitchell for review of 
the manuscript and helpful comments; Michael Tanner, 
Lala-Rukh Hussain, and Barry Udis for technical assis-</p>

<p>H-2K d </p>

<p>D HSC alone (NOD→ →B10) </p>

<p>CD8α </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>0.6% </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>CD4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>1.8% </p>

<p>TCRβ + </p>

<p>γδ </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 
2.2% </p>

<p>NK1.1/DX5 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 
0.4% </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 
10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>2.2% </p>

<p>CD11c </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>49.2% </p>

<p>Gr-1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>54.5% </p>

<p>Mac-1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>95% </p>

<p>E HSC+ FL-PB FC (NOD→B10) </p>

<p>H-2K d </p>

<p>CD4 
CD8α </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>4.5 % ± 0.5% </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>29 % ± 6% </p>

<p>TCRβ + </p>

<p>γδ </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>34 % ± 6% </p>

<p>NK1.1/DX5 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>0.3 % ± 0.0% </p>

<p>B220 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>44 % ± 12% </p>

<p>CD11c </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>14 % ± 13% </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>59 % ± 16% </p>

<p>Mac-1 </p>

<p>10 0 </p>

<p>10 1 </p>

<p>10 2 </p>

<p>10 3 </p>

<p>10 4 </p>

<p>10 0 10 1 10 2 10 3 10 4 </p>

<p>83% ± 9% </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Continued. </p>

<p>Y. HUANG AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
tance; Carolyn DeLautre for manuscript preparation; and 
the staff of the University of Louisville animal facility for 
outstanding animal care. </p>



<p>NOD p-preDC FCs EXHIBIT IMPAIRED FUNCTION </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, SEPTEMBER 2008 </p>

</text></tei>