<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2475704" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:42+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Despite the importance of airspace integrity in vertebrate gas 
exchange, the molecular pathways that instruct distal lung for-
mation are poorly understood. Recently, we found that fibril-
lin-1 deficiency in mice impairs alveolar formation and recapit-
ulates the pulmonary features of human Marfan syndrome. To 
further elucidate effectors involved in distal lung formation, we 
performed expression profiling analysis comparing the fibrillin-
1-deficient and wild-type developing lung. NeuroD, a basic 
helix-loop-helix transcription factor, fulfilled the expression 
criteria for a candidate mediator of distal lung development. We 
investigated its role in murine lung development using geneti-
cally targeted NeuroD-deficient mice. We found that NeuroD 
deficiency results in both impaired alveolar septation and 
altered morphology of the pulmonary neuroendocrine cells. 
NeuroD-deficient mice had enlarged alveoli associated with 
reduced epithelial proliferation in the airway and airspace com-
partments during development. Additionally, the neuroendo-
crine compartment in these mice manifested an increased num-
ber of neuroepithelial bodies but a reduced number of solitary 
pulmonary neuroendocrine cells in the neonatal lung. Over-
expression of NeuroD in a murine lung epithelial cell line 
conferred a neuroendocrine phenotype characterized by the 
induction of neuroendocrine markers as well as increased 
proliferation. These results support an unanticipated role for 
NeuroD in the regulation of pulmonary neuroendocrine and 
alveolar morphogenesis and suggest an intimate connection </p>

<p>between the neuroendocrine compartment and distal lung 
development. </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>3 The abbreviations used are: MFS, Marfan syndrome; bHLH, basic helix-loop-
helix; PNEC, pulmonary neuroendocrine cell; NEB, neuroepithelial body; 
PD1 and PD5, postnatal day 1 and 5, respectively; NCAM, neural cell adhe-
sion molecule; ACTH, adrenocorticotropic hormone; CGRP, calcitonin 
gene-related peptide; DAPI, 4Ј,6-diamidinio-2-phenylindole; CgA, chro-
mogranin A. </p>

<p>bellar, retinal, and inner ear development (5-7), islet cell mat-
uration in the pancreas, and enteroendocrine cell differentia-
tion in the small intestine (8, 9). Although targeted mice survive 
the neonatal period, a detailed examination of their lung phe-
notype has not been performed. Similarly, the role of other 
proneural bHLH factors (e.g. neurogenins and maths) in lung 
development is unknown. 
In this study, we show that NeuroD deficiency results in 
impaired distal airspace formation and altered neuroendocrine 
cell organization. One mechanism of impaired alveolar septa-
tion in NeuroD-deficient mice is reduced airspace epithelial cell 
proliferation. The reduction in solitary neuroendocrine cells 
and increase in neuroepithelial bodies (NEBs) observed in 
NeuroD-deficient lung further implicate an important role for 
NeuroD in pulmonary neuroendocrine morphogenesis. Over-
expression of NeuroD in lung epithelial cells imparts both a 
proliferative and neuroendocrine phenotype, suggesting a 
molecular link between neuroendocrine function and airspace 
morphogenesis. These data demonstrate cell-autonomous and 
cell-nonautonomous effects of NeuroD in the developing lung 
and illustrate the power of expression profiling analysis in the 
identification of determinants of complex tissue morphogenic 
programs. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Mice-Fibrillin-1-deficient mice and NeuroD-deficient mice 
were bred and maintained as described (1, 10). We used the 
NeuroD-deficient mice maintained in 129/SvJ background (11,  12). Progeny from heterozygote matings were used for the 
described studies. These mice were housed in a facility accred-
ited by the American Association of Laboratory Animal Care, 
and the animal studies were reviewed and approved by the 
institutional animal care and use committee of The Johns Hop-
kins School of Medicine. 
Expression Profiling Analysis-Lungs from fibrillin-1-defi-
cient mice and littermate controls at postnatal day 1 (PD1) and 
postnatal day 5 (PD5) were harvested and quickly frozen. Lungs 
from two groups of mice (wild-type and fibrillin-1-deficient) at 
each time point were pooled in groups of two or three. Total 
RNA was extracted using TRIZOL reagent (Invitrogen). 
Expression profiling was done with Affymetrix A734 Gene-
Chips (48 chips for this study), containing ϳ7000 full-length 
genes and ϳ1000 expressed sequence tags. Biotinylated cRNAs 
prepared from total RNAs were hybridized to U34A GeneChips 
in duplicate. Fluorescent signals were measured with a Hewlett 
Packard G2500A Gene Array Scanner. Data were analyzed with 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Affymetrix suite</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version">5.0</rs>, corrected for saturation, and evaluated 
with <rs id="software-1" type="software">GeneSpring</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version">5.0</rs> software. The primary gene expression 
data can be found on the World Wide Web at the NCBI GEO 
data base (GDS242). 
Morphology and Histology-Three to five mice of each geno-
type were studied at the noted ages. For histologic and morpho-
metric analyses, mouse lungs were inflated at 25 cm of H 2 O and 
fixed with 4% paraformaldehyde in low melt agarose. The lungs 
were equilibrated in cold 4% paraformaldehyde overnight, sec-
tioned, and then embedded in paraffin wax. Sections were cut at 
5 m and either stained with hematoxylin and eosin or pro-
cessed for immunohistochemistry. </p>

<p>Morphometry-Measurements were performed on hema-
toxylin and eosin-stained sections taken at intervals through-
out both lungs. Slides were coded, captured by an observer, and 
masked for identity. Ten to fifteen images per slide were 
acquired at ϫ20 magnification. Mean chord lengths and mean 
linear intercepts were assessed by automated morphometry 
with a macro operation performed by Metamorph Imaging 
Software (Universal Imaging, Molecular Devices, Downing-
town, PA). 
Semiquantitative PCR-Total RNAs were isolated from 
mouse lung by homogenization in TRIZOL reagent (Invitro-
gen). First-strand cDNA was prepared from 1 g of each RNA 
sample using the Invitrogen Superscript II RT kit and random 
hexamer primers. The primers for NeuroD amplification were 5Ј-
ATCGTCACTATTCAGAACCTT-3Ј (forward) and 5Ј-TTCCT-
CGTCCTGAGAACTGAG-3Ј (reverse). The primers for ␤-actin 
amplification were 5Ј-TTGCTGACAGGATGCAGAAG-3Ј (for-
ward) and 5Ј-ACATCTGCTGGAAGGTGGAC-3Ј (reverse). All 
samples were tested in the absence of reverse transcriptase to con-
trol for DNA contamination. PCR products were analyzed on aga-
rose gels. All results were confirmed with at least three different 
RNA samples. 
Western Blot Analysis-Total cell lysates were extracted in 
M-Per buffer from Pierce. Protein concentrations were deter-
mined using the Bio-Rad Protein Assay. Aliquots of 30 -50 g 
of protein were boiled and then loaded onto Tris-HCl gels and 
transferred electrophoretically to nitrocellulose membranes. 
Membranes were incubated with the primary antibody for 1 h 
at room temperature. Detection was by the Pierce West Dura 
ECL detection system. Primary antibodies and dilutions 
were as follows: ␤-actin (1:1000; Abcam), c-Myc (1:1000; 
Abcam), NCAM (1:500; Chemicon), NCAM (DHSB (13); 
1:500), ACTH (1:100; Abcam), Hes-1 (1:200; Chemicon), 
Mash1 (1:250; Abcam), Gfi-1 (1:250; Santa Cruz Biotechnol-
ogy, Inc., Santa Cruz, CA) and chromogranin A (1:250; Santa 
Cruz Biotechnology). 
Immunohistochemistry-Tissue sections were deparaf-
finized and rehydrated in an ethanol series. Sections were 
blocked for nonspecific binding with 3% normal serum from 
chicken and incubated with the primary antibodies for 1 h at 
room temperature. For immunofluorescence, sections were 
then incubated with secondary antibodies at 1:200 for 30 min at 
room temperature (Molecular Probes). Sections were counter-
stained with 4Ј,6-diamidinio-2-phenylindole (DAPI) and 
mounted with Vectashield hard set mounting medium (Vector 
Laboratories). For immunohistochemistry, following incuba-
tion with the primary antibody overnight at 4°C, slides were 
washed with PBST, incubated with an appropriate biotinylated 
secondary antibody (Jackson ImmunoResearch), and devel-
oped by using ABC protocol. 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl 
phosphate, and 3,3Ј-diaminobenzidine detection reagents 
(Vector Laboratories). Antibodies were used at the following 
concentrations: NeuroD (1:100; Santa Cruz Biotechnology), 
PGP9.5 (1:500; Dako), synaptophysin (1:100; Zymed Laborato-
ries Inc.), calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP; Sigma; 
1:3000), proliferating cell nuclear antigen (1:50; Santa Cruz Bio-
technology), Ki67 (1:50; Santa Cruz Biotechnology), NCAM </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>

<p>JULY 25, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 21161 </p>

<p>(1:250; Chemicon), CC10 (1:1500; gift from G. Singh), TTF-1 
(1:500; Dako), and active caspase-3 (1:25; Abcam). 
Neuroendocrine Cell Quantitation-For details of the proto-
col, refer to Ref. 14. To characterize NE differentiation in fibril-
lin-deficient mice and wild-type littermates, we counted the 
total number of synaptophysin, CGRP, and PGP9.5 immunore-
active solitary PNECs and NEBs (neuroendocrine foci) in form-
aldehyde-fixed, paraffin-embedded lung sections. This was cor-
related to the number of airways in the same sections (foci/ 
airway). To determine the size of NEBs in these same mice, 
pictures of each NEB were acquired using <rs id="software-2" type="software">MetaMorph</rs> soft-
ware (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Universal Imaging/Molecular Devices</rs>, Downingtown, 
PA). The immunoreactive area was manually outlined and 
measured using the same software, and the size in m 
2 for each 
individual NEB was tabulated. Statistical analysis was per-
formed using the Mann-Whitney test (<rs type="software">SigmaStat</rs>). 
For differential measurement of solitary PNECs versus NEBs, 
lung tissue sections were co-stained with PGP9.5 (Dako) and 
DAPI (Molecular Probes) as described under "Immunohisto-
chemistry." The total number of airway cells was determined by 
counting cells per 20ϫ field staining positive for DAPI in the 
airway. Neuroendocrine cells were quantified based on the total 
number of cells staining positive for PGP9.5. Those cells posi-
tive for PGP9.5 were characterized as either components of 
NEBs (cluster of Ն3 neuroendocrine cells) or solitary neuroen-
docrine cells based on morphology. These two neuroendocrine 
cell types were then quantified and normalized to airway base-
ment membrane length in m ϫ 10 
4 . 
Cell Culture and Transfection-The MLE12 cell line, an 
immortalized mouse lung epithelial cell line that maintains </p>

<p>characteristics of type II alveolar 
epithelial cells (15), was a kind gift 
from Dr. Jeffrey Whitsett (Univer-
sity of Cincinnati) and was main-
tained in Dulbecco's minimal essen-
tial medium/F-12 medium (1:1) 
supplemented with 2% fetal calf 
serum. Subconfluent cells were 
transfected with Lipofectamine Plus 
(Invitrogen) according to the manu-
facturer's protocol and harvested 
after 24 or 48 h. All transfections 
were performed in triplicate. The 
Myc-tagged murine NeuroD cDNA 
construct was a gift from Drs. David 
Turner (University of Michigan) 
and Jacqueline Lee (University of 
Colorado). 
For conditioned media experi-
ments, medium was removed from 
transiently transfected cells after 24 h 
and replaced with serum-free 
medium. Supernatants were har-
vested after 24 and 48 h, and cells 
were removed by low speed centrifu-
gation. After washing with phos-
phate-buffered saline, serum-starved 
MLE12 cells were treated with super-
natants from transfected cells. For proliferation assays, cells were 
incubated for the designated time periods after treatment or trans-
fection and then assayed per protocol with the Promega CellTitre 
96 nonradioactive proliferation assay. 
Data Analysis-Absolute analysis of <rs type="software">Affymetrix</rs> image data 
were done using <rs id="software-5" type="software">Affymetrix Microarray Suite</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version">4.0</rs>. Values of 
intensity differences as well as ratios of each probe pair are used 
for determination of whether a transcript is called "present" or 
"absent." The differentially expressed gene lists for each time 
point were generated using <rs id="software-6" type="software">GeneSpring</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">Silicon Genetics</rs>, CA). In <rs type="software">GeneSpring</rs>, those genes showing at least four 
<rs type="software">Affymetrix</rs> present calls were selected prior to further data 
processing. Welch's t test was performed to calculate the prob-
abilities of significant gene expression changes. Since the probe 
sets were tested multiple times, we used a highly stringent p 
value cut-off (p Ͻ 0.001) to reduce the number of false positives 
to less than 1 in 1000. 
Statistical Analysis-Analysis of variance and Student's 
t-tests were used to determine differences between groups. In 
the morphometric study, statistical differences were deter-
mined by the unpaired Student's t test for comparison of septal 
measurements. Values for all measurements were expressed as 
means Ϯ S.E., and p values for significance were designated at 
Ͻ0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Fibrillin-1 Deficiency Is Associated with Airspace Defects and 
Reduced Expression of NeuroD-Neonatal mice deficient in 
fibrillin-1 display increased airspace caliber at PD5, a time point 
that coincides with the initiation of alveolar septation in the </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Use of neonatal fibrillin-1-deficient mice to identify NeuroD as a candidate septation media-
tor. A, neonatal fibrillin-1-deficient mice demonstrate enlarged airspaces (as). Shown are representative his-
tologic sections of PD5 lungs stained with hematoxylin and eosin from fibrillin-1-deficient mice (MUT) and 
wild-type littermates (WT). B, morphometric assessment of airspace caliber by mean linear intercept confirms 
the increase in airspace caliber in the mutant mice. The figure shows significant increase in MLI in the fibrillin-
1-deficient mice compared with wild-type littermates. C, diagram of strategy to identify candidate septation 
mediators by expression profile analysis. A candidate mediator was judged to have both increased expression 
in the PD5 wild-type lung compared with PD1 and increased expression in the wild-type PD5 lung compared 
with the fibrillin-1-deficient PD5 lungs. D, reduced NeuroD expression in fibrillin-1-deficient lung by semiquan-
titative PCR. E, real time PCR analysis of NeuroD expression in lungs from PD5 wild-type mice treated with 
transforming growth factor-␤-neutralizing antibody demonstrated a 10-fold increase in NeuroD expression 
with antibody treatment. All data reflect 4 -6 mice/genotype. Ϫ/Ϫ, fibrillin-1-deficient mouse. </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 • JULY 25, 2008 </p>

<p>murine lung (Fig. 1, A and B). In order to identify candidate 
mediators of distal lung development, whole organ gene 
expression profiling was performed on wild-type and fibrillin-
1-deficient mice at PD1 and PD5. Upon pairwise comparison, 
we reasoned that candidate genes would be (a) down-regulated 
in the mutant lung compared with wild-type lung on PD5 and 
(b) increased in the wild-type PD5 lung compared with the 
wild-type PD1 lung (Fig. 1C). Interestingly, NeuroD, a basic 
helix-loop-helix protein, demonstrated a 25-fold induction in 
the wild-type PD5 lung compared with the wild-type PD1 lung 
and a 5-fold reduction in the fibrillin-1 PD5 lung compared 
with wild-type littermates. These results were confirmed by 
semiquantitative RT-PCR (Fig. 1D). Since transforming growth 
factor-␤-neutralizing antibody restores normal septation in 
fibrillin-deficient mice, we determined whether NeuroD levels 
responded to this maneuver. We found a 10-fold induction of 
NeuroD expression in the wild-type lung upon treatment with 
antibody treatment but only a 1.5-fold induction in the mutant 
lung. This finding suggests that although NeuroD deficiency 
may contribute in a minor way to the lung phenotype in the 
fibrillin-1-deficient mouse, it is not a predominant mechanism. 
Since fibrillin-1 deficiency is associated with complex distur-
bances involving tissue structure, cytokine dysregulation, and 
recently angiotensin signaling, the lack of an intimate mecha-
nistic association between NeuroD signaling and the fibrillin-1 
phenotype is not unexpected (1, 16 -19). Nonetheless, we sur-
mised, NeuroD might play a role in lung maturation distinct 
from the context of fibrillin-1 deficiency. 
NeuroD-deficient Mice Have Impaired Alveolar Formation 
Secondary to Reduced Airspace Epithelial Proliferation-Our 
expression profiling strategy was designed to identify determi-
nants of distal lung formation. In order to establish whether 
NeuroD is critically involved in distal lung morphogenesis, we 
examined the lung phenotype of mice deficient in NeuroD. 
These mice had known defects in pancreatic, enteroendocrine, 
cerebellar, and hippocampal morphogenesis, but their lung 
phenotype has not been examined. The homozygous mutant 
mice had a marked increase in distal airspace caliber at PD5 
and PD10 compared with littermate controls, similar to our 
findings in fibrillin-1-deficient mice (Fig. 2, A and B). By adult-
hood, the airspace caliber remained significantly larger than the 
wild type controls but showed no progression compared with 
the PD10 mutant lung. Using markers of alveolar epithelial cells 
(TTF-1) and airway epithelial cells (CC10), we found preserved 
epithelial differentiation in the neonatal mutant lung (Fig. 2, C 
and D). Since airspace simplification can result from reduced 
proliferation or increased cell death in the lung parenchyma, we 
examined distal lung proliferation and apoptosis in the devel-
oping and adult lungs. We found a dramatic reduction (27%) in 
proliferation of airway and alveolar epithelial cells in the devel-
oping airspace and airway of the mutant lung (Fig. 3, A and B) 
but no difference in apoptosis by terminal dUTP nick-end 
labeling and active caspase 3 staining (data not shown). This 
profile contrasts with our finding of increased apoptosis but 
normal proliferation in fibrillin-1-deficient murine lungs. 
Importantly, the mitotic index falls to trivial levels in the 
mutant and wild-type lung by adulthood (Fig. 3B) and is prob-
ably responsible for the inability to correct the airspace enlarge-</p>

<p>ment after lung maturation. Taken together, these data suggest 
that the early airspace phenotype of these mice is not attribut-
able to an altered epithelial differentiation program but rather 
to reduced epithelial proliferation. 
NeuroD-deficient mice in the Sv/129 background have 
ϳ30 -40% perinatal mortality, strictly observed within the first 
week of life (12). Between the time points of PD5 and adult-
hood, we observed no mutant pup loss. Since PD10 is beyond 
the point of expected pup loss but still within the terminal phase 
of lung alveolar development, our demonstration of persistent 
airspace enlargement suggests that the PD5 phenotype did not 
merely reflect mice that would ultimately die before adulthood 
(Fig. 2, A and B). However, in order to further establish that the 
PD5 and PD10 mice were comparable, we evaluated Mendelian 
ratios of respective genotypes. Assessment of 40ϩ mice at each 
time point revealed 26, 52, and 22% versus 23, 57, and 20% 
(NeuroD </p>

<p>ϩ/ϩ </p>

<p>, NeuroD </p>

<p>ϩ/Ϫ </p>

<p>, and NeuroD 
Ϫ/Ϫ genotypes), respec-
tively, at PD5 and PD10. We also found no reduction in weight 
in the mutant mice at either PD5 or PD10, suggesting that mice 
assessed at these two time points were comparable (see supple-
mental materials). 
NeuroD Is Expressed in Pulmonary Neuroendocrine Cells, 
and Fibrillin-1-deficient Mice Have Altered Neuroendocrine 
Cell Morphology-Mice with a targeted deletion in Mash1, 
another proneural bHLH factor, do not develop pulmonary 
neuroendocrine cells and die in the neonatal period (20). 
Because neuroendocrine cells probably perform an endocrine 
function for the developing lung by secreting growth factors 
that are instructive for distal lung morphogenesis (10, 11), we 
considered whether NeuroD might be involved in neuroendo-
crine cell differentiation and function (21, 22). We used the 
panneuroendocrine marker PGP9.5 to assess the morphology 
and abundance of neuroendocrine cells. Immunohistochemical 
studies employing antibodies against NeuroD and PGP9.5 
revealed that NeuroD is expressed in pulmonary neuroendo-
crine cells within the distal airway (Fig. 4A). To explore the 
possibility that the reduction in NeuroD expression in the 
fibrillin-1-deficient lung was secondary to an abnormality in 
the neuroendocrine compartment, we examined the quotient 
of neuroendocrine cells in fibrillin-1-deficient lungs. We have 
previously reported that reduced neuroendocrine cell number 
and/or mass area correlate with altered neuroendocrine matu-
ration (14). The total number of neuroendocrine foci (com-
posed of NEBs and PNECs) was significantly higher in PD5 
fibrillin-deficient mice compared with wild-type littermates 
(Fig. 4B). However, the average size of NEBs in fibrillin-defi-
cient animals was about 30% smaller than that in control mice 
(p ϭ 0.056) (Fig. 4C). Thus, although there was a modest 
increase in neuroendocrine foci in the fibrillin-1-deficient lung 
(Fig. 4B), we found a trend toward reduction in the size of NEBs 
in the NeuroD mutant lung (Fig. 4C), consistent with impaired 
neuroendocrine maturation. 
NeuroD-deficient Mice Have an Alteration in Pulmonary 
Neuroendocrine Morphology-Given that inactivation of the 
proneural bHLH factor Mash1 prevents pulmonary neuroen-
docrine differentiation (20), we hypothesized that a similar 
impairment might exist in NeuroD-deficient mice. Surpris-
ingly, we found that neuroendocrine cells were present </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>

<p>JULY 25, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 21163 </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. NeuroD-deficient mice have increased airspace caliber reminiscent of fibrillin-1-deficient mice and preserved lung epithelial differ-
entiation. A, representative histology of lungs from PD5, PD10, and 6-week-old wild type and NeuroD-deficient mice demonstrates a marked increase 
in airspace caliber in the neonatal mutant lung. Lungs were inflated at constant pressure, fixed, sectioned, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin. 
B, morphometric analysis confirms the significant increase in airspace size in the NeuroD-deficient lung using parameters of mean linear intercept (MLI) 
in m. *, p Ͻ 0.01. C, immunostaining of PD5 WT and NeuroD-deficient lungs for TTF-1, a marker of distal bronchiolar and type II alveolar epithelial cells, 
shows preserved differentiation in the mutant lung. D, immunostaining of PD5 WT and NeuroD-deficient lungs for CC10, a marker of nonciliated airway 
epithelial cells shows preserved differentiation in the mutant lung. All data reflect 4 -6 mice/genotype. ND ϩ/ϩ, control wild-type littermate; ND Ϫ/Ϫ, 
NeuroD-deficient mouse. </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 • JULY 25, 2008 </p>

<p>throughout airway and airspace development in the mutant 
lung (Fig. 5A). Pulmonary neuroendocrine cells exist in two 
distinct morphologies: solitary PNECs and NEBs. The former 
subserves a primary secretory function, liberating mitogenic 
and vasoactive amines, and the latter is thought to act as a 
hypoxia and/or chemoreceptor (23, 24). When we quantified 
the number of solitary PNECs versus NEBs in NeuroD-deficient 
mice, we found (a) a significant increase in the number of NEBs 
in the mutant lung, similar to the fibrillin-1 deficient lung, but 
(b) a striking reduction in solitary PNECs in the mutant lung 
(Fig. 5, B-D). Neuroendocrine hyperplasia attends several 
inflammatory and fibrotic lung disorders, such as bronchopul-
monary dysplasia and cystic fibrosis, and is thought to contrib-
ute to these conditions via the liberation of profibrotic cyto-
kines. Because solitary PNECs are thought to function 
primarily as endocrine cells without neural innervation, we 
considered whether the marked reduction in the number of 
these cells correlated with impaired liberation of mitogenic 
amines and reduced distal airspace cell proliferation. 
To determine whether the time course of the altered neu-
roendocrine morphology correlated with the evolution of air-
space lesion, we quantified neuroendocrine cells during murine </p>

<p>lung development (PD5 and PD10) 
and early adulthood (6 weeks). We 
found a persistent increase in NEBs 
and reduction in solitary PNECs 
during the first 2 weeks of postnatal 
life but a full normalization by 
adulthood (Fig. 5, E and F). Thus, by 
temporal criteria, the altered neu-
roendocrine morphology may par-
tially contribute to the airspace 
lesion, plausibly via suboptimal lib-
eration of mitogenic amines by sol-
itary PNECs. 
Since NeuroD-deficient mice 
were maintained in the Sv/129 
strain but the fibrillin-1-deficient 
mice were maintained in a mixed 
Sv/129:C57Bl/6 background, we 
wanted to establish that the base-
line relative neuroendocrine profile 
was comparable in these two 
strains. We quantified solitary 
PNECs, NEBs, and total neuroendo-
crine cells in PD5 mice of each back-
ground strain and found a reduced 
proportion of NEBs in both strains 
(18 Ϯ 5% NEB/PNEC ratio in 
Sv/129 strain and 30 Ϯ 2% in 
Sv/129/C57Bl/6 background). Acc-
ordingly, the reversal of this ratio in 
the NeuroD-deficient mice has 
broad relevance to both background 
strains. 
NeuroD Overexpression Confers a 
Neuroendocrine Phenotype-NeuroD 
family members promote progeni-
tor cell differentiation in neural and endocrine tissues. 
Although neuroendocrine cells are present in the primitive 
vertebrate lung, their resident precursor has not been iden-
tified. Notably, lineage tracing of surfactant protein C-ex-
pressing (SPC 
ϩ ) progenitors in the developing murine lung 
did not demonstrate CGRP 
ϩ neuroendocrine progeny in the 
perinatal period (25). By contrast, Wuenschell et al. (26) char-
acterized a pluripotent cell type in the developing lung that 
expressed neuroendocrine, airway, and alveolar epithelial 
markers, suggesting that a common precursor might exist. In 
order to determine whether the overexpression of NeuroD in a 
nonneuroendocrine-derived cell line was sufficient to induce 
the neuroendocrine phenotype, we overexpressed a Myc-
tagged NeuroD in a nonneuroendocrine mouse lung alveolar 
epithelial cell line (MLE12). Remarkably, NeuroD expression 
induced robust expression of chromogranin A and ACTH, both 
neuroendocrine markers and p21 expression (Fig. 6A). We did 
not find repression of surfactant protein B or TTF-1, markers of 
lung epithelial cells (data not shown). Furthermore, using two 
different antibodies for NCAM detection, we found that Neu-
roD expression induced high molecular weight NCAM140 
expression (Fig. 6B). Since Ito described opposing effects of </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. NeuroD-deficient lungs have reduced proliferation in airspace and airway compartments. 
A, the proliferative status of the wild-type and mutant PD5 lung was assessed by immunohistochemistry for 
Ki67, a proliferation marker. Top, lung parenchyma of representative wild-type and mutant mice. Bottom, 
airway compartment of representative wild-type and mutant mice. Red, Ki67; blue, DAPI. B, mitotic index of 
parenchymal cells in NeuroD-deficient and wild-type lungs at three different time points shows a significant 
reduction in proliferation in the mutant lung during the neonatal period. Lungs were stained for PCNA, another 
marker of proliferation. Positive cellular staining in the airspace and airway were normalized for total cell count 
as measured by DAPI immunofluorescence to generate a mitotic index. *, p Ͻ 0.001. ND ϩ/ϩ, control wild-type 
littermate; ND Ϫ/Ϫ, NeuroD-deficient mouse. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. NeuroD is expressed in NEBs in the developing lung, and fibrillin-1-deficient mice have abnor-
mal neuroendocrine system morphology. A, dual immunohistochemistry of PD5 wild type lung demon-
strates colocalization of NeuroD and PGP9.5, a neuroendocrine marker. The arrow denotes a nerve fiber accom-
panying the NEB. Red, NeuroD; black, PGP9.5. B, fibrillin-1-deficient mice have slightly increased 
neuroendocrine cell number compared with littermate controls. PD5 lungs from wild-type and fibrillin-1-
deficient mice were stained with PGP9.5. Positively stained foci were counted and normalized to airway num-
ber in a given specimen. C, fibrillin-1-deficient mice have a trend toward reduced neuroendocrine cell mass 
compared with littermate controls. Total area of NEBs (identified by the aforementioned marker) was meas-
ured in each lung specimen to generate a mean area per NEB. This parameter reflects NEB maturation. All data 
reflect 4 -6 mice/genotype. *, p ϭ 0.013; **, p ϭ 0.056, WT, wild type; MUT, fibrillin-1-deficient. </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>

<p>JULY 25, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 21165 </p>

<p>Mash1 and Hes-1 in neuroendocrine maturation, we sur-
veyed both of these candidate mediators after NeuroD over-
expression (27). Although we observed no change in the lev-
els of Hes-1, we did see an induction of Mash1 at 24 h, 
consistent with its critical early role in neuroendocrine dif-
ferentiation (Fig. S2). We also observed an induction of 
Gfi-1, a recently identified neuroendocrine determinant, in 
NeuroD-overexpressing cells (28). In summary, the whole 
cell studies suggest that NeuroD overexpression is sufficient 
to confer a neuroendocrine phenotype to lung epithelial 
cells. 
NeuroD Overexpression Induces Autocrine and Paracrine 
Proliferation in Lung Epithelial Cells-Although they represent 
a relatively sparse cell population in the lung, neuroendocrine 
cells can alter geographic proliferative and morphogenic pro-
grams via autocrine and paracine effects on local epithelial cells. </p>

<p>Notably, we have recently shown 
that mice that are deficient in Gfi1, a 
determinant of neuroendocrine cell 
morphogenesis, display reduced 
airway cell proliferation after naph-
thalene injury (29). In order to con-
nect the altered neuroendocrine 
developmental 
phenotype 
we 
observed in NeuroD deficient lungs 
with reduced epithelial prolifera-
tion, we examined whether overex-
pression of NeuroD in lung epithe-
lial cells increased proliferation. We 
found a significant increase in pro-
liferation in cells transfected with 
NeuroD compared with cells trans-
fected with a control vector (Fig. 
7A). Since we observed reduced 
proliferation in cells that did not 
express NeuroD in the airway and 
epithelium of the distal lung, we 
examined whether NeuroD-trans-
fected cells secreted mitogenic fac-
tors (a known property of neuroen-
docrine cells) that induced 
proliferation in cells not expressing 
NeuroD. Conditioned medium 
from cells transfected with NeuroD 
promoted a Ͼ55% increase in pro-
liferation compared with medium 
from vector-transfected cells (Fig. 
7B). These data suggest that Neu-
roD expression supports autocrine 
and paracrine proliferative signaling 
in lung epithelial cells. This mecha-
nism may account for the wide-
spread reduction in proliferation in 
the NeuroD-deficient lung. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Although neuroendocrine cells 
represent less than 1% of epithelial 
cells in the vertebrate lung, they are active participants in lung 
repair and malignant transformation (reviewed in Ref. 30). Con-
sistent with previous reports of NeuroD expression in neuroen-
docrine tumors (31), we show here that NeuroD is expressed in 
the neuroendocrine cells of the developing lung. We also 
describe for the first time a temporal association between the 
maturation of the pulmonary neuroendocrine compartment 
and distal lung morphogenesis. Reminiscent of its role in the 
gastrointestinal tract and the pancreas, one of the pulmonary 
effects of NeuroD deficiency is an alteration in the morphology 
of the pulmonary neuroendocrine compartment. However, it 
follows that for these relatively sparse PNECs to participate in 
global morphogenic functions, paracrine effects mediated by 
secreted factors must be operative. We show here that a dis-
turbance in PNEC morphology conferred by a deficiency in 
NeuroD may contribute to a more global morphogenic pertur-</p>

<p>FIGURE 5. NeuroD-deficient mice demonstrate abnormal neuroendocrine cell compartment morphol-
ogy. A, NeuroD-deficient murine lungs at embryonic day 16.5 and PD5 demonstrate NEBs within the airways. 
The arrowheads denote sites of PGP9.5 staining within the distal airway. B, wild-type PD5 lungs have both NEBs 
(arrow, left) and solitary pulmonary neuroendocrine cells (PNECs) (arrow, right). Representative sections from 
wild type (WT) and NeuroD-deficient lungs stained for PGP9.5 (red), a marker of neuroendocrine cells. Total cell 
nuclei are represented by DAPI staining (blue). NEBs are defined as a cluster of Ն3 PNECs. C, PD5 NeuroD-
deficient lungs have neuroepithelial cell bodies but rare solitary PNECs. Neuroendocrine cells in NeuroD-
deficient lungs stained for PGP9.5 are primarily in an NEB conformation. The arrowhead denotes representative 
NEB present in a NeuroD-deficient lung. D, quantitation of NEBs and solitary PNECs in airways of NeuroD-
deficient mice and wild-type littermates shows a significant increase in NEBs associated with a marked reduc-
tion in solitary PNECs per airway length in the mutant lung. Lungs from respective mice were stained for PGP9.5 
as described above. NEBs and PNECs were counted in 15 low power fields and normalized to total airway 
perimeter in fields. E, quantification of NEBs normalized to airway basement membrane (AWBM) length at three 
different time points demonstrates a persistent increase in these structures in the mutant lung during the first 
2 weeks of life compared with wild-type littermates but normalization by adulthood. *, p Ͻ 0.001. F, quantifi-
cation of solitary PNECs per airway basement membrane length at three different time points demonstrates a 
marked reduction in these cells in the mutant lung during the first 2 weeks of life compared with wild-type 
littermates but normalization by adulthood. *, p Ͻ 0.001. Arrowheads, NEBs and neuroendocrine cells. Arrows, 
proliferating epithelia. All data reflect 4 -6 mice/genotype. Lu, lumen; AW, airway. </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 • JULY 25, 2008 </p>

<p>bation. Several investigators have shown that mitogens (bomb-
esin-like peptides, gastrin-releasing peptide, CGRP, etc.) syn-
thesized and secreted by PNECs induce airway and alveolar 
epithelial cell proliferation in explant and whole cell systems 
(32-34). Sunday et al. (35) have also demonstrated adverse 
effects of exaggerated pulmonary neuropeptide secretion in 
the neonatal setting, possibly contributing to bronchopul-
monary dysplasia and other lung diseases of prematurity. 
Cutz and co-workers (36) have shown that the lung paren-
chymal phenotype of cystic fibrosis transmembrane con-
ductance regulator-deficient mice includes disturbances in 
PNEC and NEB morphogenesis. Taken together, the mitogenic 
and morphogenic consequences of PNEC dysregulation prob-
ably contribute to parenchymal lung disease. However, because 
of the paucity of reagents that alter local neuropeptide secretion 
and function in the lung, a direct confirmation of the in vivo </p>

<p>consequences of altered neuroendocrine system morphology 
has yet to be provided. 
The pulmonary phenotype of NeuroD-targeted mice reca-
pitulates selective aspects of the nonneuronal phenotypes 
observed in other organs. In the small intestine and pancreas, 
NeuroD deficiency promotes cell autonomous apoptotic cell 
loss and reduced proliferation. In this report, although we show 
compromised proliferation, we do not detect enhanced apopto-
sis in the lung parenchyma of mutant mice. However, we can-
not rule out the possibility that apoptotic loss of PNECs pre-
cedes the observed antiproliferative phenotype. 
Despite the fact that NEBs and solitary PNECs are highly 
conserved phylogenetically, the physiological significance and 
the developmental ontogeny of these two morphologies 
remain unclear (37). Additionally, the genetic and biochem-
ical pathways that instruct neuroendocrine differentiation 
are unknown. Apart from the complete absence of pulmonary 
neuroendocrine cells in Mash1-deficient mice, no published 
genetically targeted model has shown alterations of neuroen-
docrine morphology using the most PNEC-inclusive marker, 
PGP9.5. Mice deficient for Gfi-1 have reduced CGRP-express-
ing solitary PNECs and NEBs but preserved abundance of 
PGP9.5-expressing cells (28). The combination of a marked 
reduction in solitary PNECs and expansion in NEBs that we 
show in the NeuroD-deficient lung supports integrative devel-
opmental regulation of these two structures. Two models rec-
oncile this dual compartment mechanism. First, solitary 
PNECs may originate in the NEB niche, but at an early devel-
opmental time point, separate from the cluster. Accordingly, it 
remains possible that the lack of solitary PNECs in the NeuroD-
deficient lung reflects an as yet undefined defect in the NEB 
niche. A second model is that solitary PNECs and NEBs may 
have a common resident precursor but develop as distinct, non-
overlapping entities, with only the former requiring NeuroD 
expression for terminal differentiation. The development of 
methods to reliably isolate these low abundance cells from rodent 
lungs would greatly facilitate our dissection of their differentiation 
programs. 
The finding of impaired alveolar septation in the NeuroD-
deficient lung seems discordant, given that NeuroD is not 
expressed in the airspace. The 
markedly reduced airway and air-
space proliferation implicate a glo-
bal perturbation in mitogenesis. 
Two mechanisms are plausible. 
First, since neuroendocrine cells lib-
erate mitogenic amines that act in a 
local paracrine manner and which 
are known to be involved in lung 
morphogenesis, the reduced soli-
tary neuroendocrine cell compart-
ment might compromise the libera-
tion of requisite promorphogenic 
factors during alveolar develop-
ment. Our finding of NeuroD-in-
duced proliferation in transfected 
MLE12 cells supports this mecha-
nism. Second, the known diabetic </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. NeuroD overexpression in lung epithelial cells induces a neu-
roendocrine phenotype. A, NeuroD expression in a lung epithelial cell line 
induces ACTH, chromogranin A, and p21. Lysates from MLE12 cells transiently 
overexpressing NeuroD-Myc or plasmid control were subjected to immuno-
blotting for ACTH, chromogranin A, and p21. The same membrane was 
probed with an anti-␤-actin antibody to assess equal loading of the gel and an 
anti-c-Myc antibody to document the overexpression of NeuroD. B, NeuroD 
overexpression induces expression of NCAM1, a marker of mature neuroen-
docrine cells. Membranes of lysates from MLE12 cells transfected with 
NeuroD-Myc were immunoblotted for NCAM1 using both polyclonal anti-
body AB5032 (Chemicon) (top) and polyclonal antibody AG1 (DSHB) (bottom). 
The arrowheads denote position of low molecular mass (ϳ75 kDa) and high 
molecular mass (Ͼ150 kDa) NCAM. The blots are representative of Ͼ3 exper-
iments. 24h, 24 h after transfection; 48h, 48 h after transfection. LMW-NCAM, 
low molecular weight, nonmodified NCAM. </p>

<p>FIGURE 7. NeuroD overexpression enhances proliferation in an autocrine and paracrine manner. 
A, MLE12 cells transfected with NeuroD display increased proliferation. Cells transfected with either NeuroD-
Myc or pci-Neo (Vector) were evaluated after 24 and 48 h for proliferation, as measured by the CellTitre96 
nonradioactive proliferation assay (Promega). B, conditioned medium from NeuroD-Myc or transfected cells 
promote increased proliferation of MLE12 cells. Supernatants from cells transfected with NeuroD-Myc or pci-Neo 
were filtered and then added to subconfluent MLE12 as a 1:1 dilution with serum-free medium. Proliferation was 
measured after 24 and 48 h as described above. All experiments were performed in triplicate. *, p Ͻ 0.05. </p>

<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>

<p>JULY 25, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 21167 </p>

<p>phenotype of these mice could exert antimorphogenic effects 
on the lung, an interaction that has been observed in human 
and animal models (38, 39). Although the precise basis for the 
airspace phenotype is unclear, the finding supports an intimate 
interaction between lung morphogenesis and overall neuroendo-
crine function. 
Our induction of neuroendocrine marker expression in 
murine lung epithelial cells suggests that NeuroD expression is 
sufficient to confer a neuroendocrine phenotype. Leiter and 
co-workers (8) showed that NeuroD expression in HeLa cells 
promoted the expression of p21 and secretin. NeuroD overex-
pression in non-islet-derived pancreatic cell lines triggered a 
beta cell differentiation program exemplified by NKX2.2, pax4, 
and insulin induction (40, 41). Our results demonstrate that 
nonneuroendocrine lung epithelial cells harbor the requisite 
machinery to drive differentiation into neuroendocrine cells 
upon overexpression of NeuroD. We observed that NeuroD 
induced a restricted repertoire of neuroendocrine markers. 
Therefore, multiple transcription factors may be required for 
the expression of the full repertoire of panneuroendocrine 
markers in a given lung epithelial cell. Alternatively, a given 
bHLH protein may activate the differentiation of a restricted 
subset of pulmonary neuroendocrine cells that express a 
defined repertoire of markers, a pattern observed in the 
enteroendocrine compartment (42, 43). Ito et al. (27) demon-
strated that NeuroD expression in the postnatal lung tempo-
rally coincided with Mash1 mediated neuroendocrine cell dif-
ferentiation, suggesting some measure of cooperativity among 
these proneural factors. 
Lung alveolarization is a dynamic and highly regulated proc-
ess that integrates proliferative, apoptotic, and morphogenic 
cues. Both fibrillin-1 deficiency and NeuroD deficiency show 
impaired alveolar septation in the immediate postnatal period. 
However, meaningful differences in these phenotypes are evi-
dent. In fibrillin-1-deficient mice, the airspace lesion is progres-
sive throughout postnatal life, whereas in the NeuroD-deficient 
lung, the airspace lesion improves but does not fully correct 
over time. These findings suggest that NeuroD may participate 
in the onset of alveolar septation but not the maintenance of the 
airspace architecture. By contrast, fibrillin-1 deficiency, in 
affecting the structural integrity of the airspace as well as the 
cytokine milieu, affects both the establishment and the mainte-
nance of airspace architecture (1, 17, 19, 44). We reported that 
not only does fibrillin-1 deficiency compromise airspace forma-
tion and maintenance, but it also contributes to late onset 
inflammatory emphysema that recapitulates acquired airspace 
enlargement. Simply stated, isolated NeuroD deficiency versus 
relative NeuroD deficiency in the context of fibrillin-1 defi-
ciency leads to distinct airspace sequelae. In this view, our data 
suggest that NeuroD deficiency is not the sole or predominant 
determinant of the airspace enlargement observed in fibrillin-
1-deficient mice; rather, primary structural distortions and sec-
ondary alterations in cytokines are the critical determinants of 
the more severe and sustained lesion evident in these mice. 
There are significant differences between the lung pheno-
types of the fibrillin-1-deficient and the NeuroD-deficient 
mice. First, the airspace defect in the fibrillin-1-deficient mice is 
attributable to enhanced apoptosis conferred by increased </p>

<p>transforming growth factor-␤ signaling. By contrast, the air-
space defect in the NeuroD-deficient mice is a result of reduced 
proliferation. Second, the airspace lesion in fibrillin-1-deficient 
mice is progressive, whereas the airspace phenotype in the 
NeuroD-deficient mice remains stable throughout early adult-
hood, suggesting that the critical insult occurs during a discrete 
phase of development without ongoing perturbations. Thus, 
the down-regulation of NeuroD in fibrillin-1-deficient mice 
might well be a secondary effect of altered lung maturation and 
not specifically referable to fibrillin-1 biology. 
We conclude that NeuroD, a proneural bHLH factor, con-
tributes to early airway and airspace homeostasis. In the air-
space, NeuroD must utilize cell nonautonomous pathways to 
maintain the proliferative milieu required for normal alveolar 
morphogenesis. Similarly, dysregulated expression of NeuroD 
may contribute to pathologic proliferation, as is observed in 
lung malignancies that overexpress NeuroD (31). In keeping 
with this previously unrecognized capacity, we report increased 
proliferation in alveolar epithelial cells overexpressing NeuroD 
and in epithelial cells exposed to supernatants from NeuroD 
expressing cells. In the airway, NeuroD is a primary determi-
nant of NE morphology, facilitating the generation of solitary 
PNECs plausibly from preexistent NEBs. Since one or both of 
these morphologies may be the cellular substrate for the devel-
opment of neuroendocrine-type lung malignancies, a better 
understanding of the specific contextual functions of these cells 
is needed. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank Keri Pearson and Eric Hoffman (Chil-
dren's National Medical Center, Washington D. C.) for help with the 
microarray assays. We thank Dr. Xu Naizhen for immunohistochem-
ical staining and morphometric analyses. We thank Sylvia McCay 
and Kimberly Gordy for technical assistance. We thank Douglas Ball, 
Ari Zaiman, Mark Awad, Neda Sharifi, and other members of the 
Dietz and Tuder laboratories for critical reading of the manuscript 
and helpful advice. </p>



<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 • JULY 25, 2008 </p>



<p>Role of NeuroD in Lung Morphogenesis </p>

<p>JULY 25, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 30 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 21169 </p>

</text></tei>