<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2626662" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Human leukocyte antigen (HLA) gene polymorphism plays a critical role in protective 
immunity, disease susceptibility, autoimmunity, and drug hypersensitivity, yet the basis of 
how HLA polymorphism infl uences T cell receptor (TCR) recognition is unclear. We exam-
ined how a natural micropolymorphism in HLA-B44, an important and large HLA allelic 
family, affected antigen recognition. T cell -mediated immunity to an Epstein-Barr virus 
determinant (EENLLDFVRF) is enhanced when HLA-B*4405 was the presenting allotype 
compared with HLA-B*4402 or HLA-B*4403, each of which differ by just one amino acid. 
The micropolymorphism in these HLA-B44 allotypes altered the mode of binding and dy-
namics of the bound viral epitope. The structure of the TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENLLDFVRF complex 
revealed that peptide fl exibility was a critical parameter in enabling preferential engage-
ment with HLA-B*4405 in comparison to HLA-B*4402/03. Accordingly, major histocompat-
ibility complex (MHC) polymorphism can alter the dynamics of the peptide-MHC landscape, 
resulting in fi ne-tuning of T cell responses between closely related allotypes. </p>



<p>MHC POLYMORPHISM AND TCR RECOGNITION | Archbold et al. </p>

<p>such CTL clonotypes are important factors in controlling 
such persistent viral infections ( 15 ). 
In this paper, we have examined how this DM1 TCR 
interacts with the EENL determinant when bound to the 
three HLA-B44 allotypes. These fi ndings provide insight 
into the complex interactions controlling HLA-B44 restric-
tion and reveal how micropolymorphisms can aff ect epitope 
conformation that subsequently fi ne tunes the responding 
CTL repertoire. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
The DM1 TCR exhibits differential affi nity 
for the HLA-B44 allotypes 
Given that CTL clones isolated from HLA-B44 + individuals 
lyse target cells presenting HLA-B*4405 EENL better than the 
HLA-B*4402 and HLA-B*4403 counterparts, we sought to 
gain an understanding of whether this refl ected a diff erence in 
the affi nity of the interaction between the TCR and the HLA-
B44 allotypes. A previous analysis of HLA-B*4405 EENL tetra-
mer -sorted cells from the HLA-B*4405 + donor DM revealed 
that a single clonotype (termed DM1) dominated the EENL-
specifi c repertoire in this donor ( 15 ). Furthermore, this clono-
type remained dominant in this donor for an extended period, 
with " nucleotide-identical " TCRs dominating the EENL-spe-
cifi c repertoire in blood samples taken in 1994 and 2005. Ac-
cordingly, we chose the DM1 TCR for our analysis, which is 
encoded by the TRAV26-1*02 TRAJ13*02 , TRBV7-9*01 
TRBJ2-1*01 , and TRBD1*01 genes. 
First, we expressed, refolded, and purifi ed the DM1 TCR 
(see Materials and methods) ( 16 ) and showed that it interacted 
with anti-TCR mAbs (unpublished data). Next, we conducted 
surface plasmon resonance (SPR) studies between the DM1 
TCR and the refolded and purifi ed HLA-B*4405 EENL , HLA-
B*4403 EENL , and HLA-B*4402 EENL allotypes in which the 
pMHC was coupled to the sensor chip. The DM1 TCR bound 
to HLA-B*4405 EENL with a relatively high affi nity of 0.3 ± 0.1 
μ M ( Fig. 1 and Table I ), whereas the DM1 TCR bound to 
HLA-B*4402 EENL and HLA-B*4403 EENL with an affi nity of 
6.3 ± 0.3 μ M and 9.4 ± 0.2 μ M, respectively ( Fig. 1 and Table I ). 
Interestingly, the binding kinetics of the interaction also diff ered 
between the HLA-B44 allotypes. The disassociation rate (K off ) 
of the DM1 TCR for the HLA-B*4405 EENL was 10-fold slower 
than from the HLA-B*4402/3 EENL allotypes ( Fig. 1 and Table I ). 
Thus, the DM1 TCR interacted with the HLA-B*4405 EENL 
complex with &gt; 10-fold higher affi nity in comparison to HLA-
B*4402 EENL and HLA-B*4403 EENL . These SPR studies refl ect 
the intrinsic ability of DM1 to more readily recognize the cog-
nate HLA-B*4405 EENL complex despite the hidden nature of 
the polymorphic HLA-B44 residues. </p>

<p>Central mobility of the peptide in the binary 
HLA-B44 EENL complexes 
To begin to address whether the affi nity diff erences between 
the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL and the DM1 TCR -
HLA-B*4402/03 EENL complexes were caused by diff erences 
in the pMHC structures, we determined the structures of </p>

<p>interactions between MHC molecules and V ␤ 8.2-TCRs has 
been observed ( 6, 7 ). More globally, it is apparent that three 
positions (65, 69, and 155 in MHC-I) are invariably con-
tacted by the TCR and, thus, may represent a minimal MHC 
restriction element ( 8 ). However, in the mouse-based sys-
tems, the structures of TCRs ligated to H2-K b and H2-L d 
MHC molecules have only been reported, and in human-
based MHC-I systems, TCR co-complex structures have 
been limited to HLA-A2, HLA-B8, and HLA-B35 ( 3, 5 ). 
Accordingly, the potential diversity as well as the possible 
generalities of the TCR -pMHC interaction may be under-
or overestimated, respectively, by the limited number of dis-
tinct HLA allotypes that have been studied. Although the 
H2-K b mutant system has to an extent unraveled the impact 
of micropolymorphism on MHC structure and function ( 9, 10 ), 
it is nevertheless important to study the impact of naturally 
selected microvariation in HLA allotypes found in outbred 
human populations. 
The HLA-B44 family, which comprises 60 alleles, partic-
ipates in important antiviral, antitumor, and minor antigen-
specifi c responses. Within this large HLA supertype, HLA-
B*4402 is the predominant HLA-B44 allele in most Caucasian 
populations, HLA-B*4403 is the more common allele in Af-
rican and Asian populations, and HLA-B*4405 is a relatively 
rare allotype. Although these three HLA-B44 allotypes diff er 
only at two positions, 116 and 156 (HLA-B*4405: 116-Tyr, 
156-Asp; HLA-B*4402: 116-Asp, 156-Asp; HLA-B*4403: 
116-Asp, 156-Leu), both of which are buried within the an-
tigen-binding cleft, the impact of these micropolymorphisms 
on antigen presentation and TCR recognition is marked 
( 11, 12 ). For example, mismatching of HLA-B*4402 and 
HLA-B*4403 is associated with transplant rejection and acute 
graft-versus-host disease, indicating that they represent sig-
nifi cant barriers to clinical transplantation ( 13 ). In addition, 
although HLA-B*4402 and HLA-B*4403 are dependent on 
tapasin for the loading of their peptide cargo, HLA-B*4405 
is tapasin independent, and this feature engenders this allo-
type with a reduced susceptibility to viral evasion of immune 
responses ( 12 ). 
HLA-B44 + individuals recognize an immunodominant 
determinant (EENLLDFVRF, abbreviated to EENL) from 
the EBV nuclear antigen 6 (EBNA6, also called EBNA3C) 
( 14 ). This viral epitope is presented by HLA-B*4402, 
HLA-B*4403, and HLA-B*4405, but there is a distinct hi-
erarchy in the CTL responses to these pMHC complexes. 
Namely, HLA-B*4405 + individuals respond most strongly 
to this determinant, and CTLs preferentially lyse target 
cells presenting HLA-B*4405 EENL in comparison to HLA-
B*4402 EENL and HLA-B*4403 EENL targets ( 14 ). Moreover, 
this preferential recognition of HLA-B*4405 EENL target 
cells is observed irrespective of the HLA-B44 subtype of 
the CTLs, or whether the EENL epitope is exogenously 
added or endogenously processed ( 14 ). Interestingly, one 
such prototypical HLA-B*4405 EENL -restricted CTL, termed 
DM1 ( TRAV26-1/TRBV7-9 ), was observed to persist in an 
EBV-infected individual for at least 11 yr, suggesting that </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>P10-Phe represented the main anchor residues for the B-
pocket and F-pocket of HLA-B44, respectively ( 2 ), whereas 
the surface exposed residues P4-Leu, P6-Asp, P7-Phe, and 
P9-Arg represented potential TCR contact points. 
Previous crystal structures of HLA-B*4402 and HLA-
B*4403 in complex with a self-peptide revealed that the 156 
polymorphism aff ected both the heavy chain and peptide 
conformation ( 11, 17 ). However, superposition of the anti-
gen-binding clefts of the three HLA-B44 EENL allotypes 
showed virtually no movement of the ␣ 1 and ␣ 2 helices 
(root mean square distance [r.m.s.d.] of &lt; 0.1 and 0.2 Å , re-
spectively), indicating that the impact of the 156 polymor-
phism on the pMHC landscape is peptide dependent ( Fig. 2 d ). 
However, the positioning of the peptide within the antigen-
binding cleft diff ered markedly between the three allotypes, 
and these diff erences were attributable to the interactions 
between the polymorphic residues at the bound peptide 
( Fig. 2 d ). The r.m.s.d. of the superposed peptides ranged 
from 0.4 to 0.9 Å , with the greatest movement around the 
mobile, centrally bulged residues of P5-Leu to P7-Phe (with 
an r.m.s.d. of up to 1.9 Å ). As a consequence, the peptide is 
positioned more closely to the ␣ 2 helix in the HLA-B* 
4405 EENL structure, whereas in the HLA-B*4402 EENL structure 
it is positioned more closely to the ␣ 1 helix, and in HLA-
B*4403 EENL it is more centrally located within the antigen-
binding cleft ( Fig. 2 d ). 
In HLA-B*4403, Leu 156 formed favorable van der Waals 
(vdw) interactions with P5-Leu, whereas in HLA-B*4402 
and HLA-B*4405, Asp 156 was observed to " push away " the 
P5-Leu and instead formed an H bond to the P3-Asn, and 
was also able to form a network of water-mediated interac-
tions. In HLA-B*4402, the unfavorable P5-Leu -Asp 156 in-
teraction is exacerbated by Asp 114 and the polymorphic 
Asp 116 , thereby creating a marked electronegative pocket at 
the C-terminal end of the antigen-binding cleft that is miti-
gated to an extent by Arg 97 ( Fig. 2 e ). In HLA-B*4405, how-
ever, position 116 is replaced by a Tyr, which will not only 
form more favorable interactions with the aromatic P10-Phe, 
namely pi -pi interactions, but will also serve to reduce the 
electronegative potential around the C-terminal region of 
the cleft ( Fig. 2 e ). Accordingly, the diff ering hydrophobic 
and electrostatic properties of the antigen-binding clefts of 
the HLA-B44 allotypes impart diff ering conformations of the 
centrally bulged portion of the bound epitope (P5 -P9) that 
displays a more marked degree of mobility in HLA-B*4405. </p>

<p>HLA-B*4402 EENL , HLA-B*4403 EENL , and HLA-B*4405 EENL 
to 1.7, 1.6, and 2.1 Å resolution, respectively (Table S1, available 
at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20082136/DC1). 
The three pMHC complexes crystallized in the same space 
group with isomorphous unit cells, and the bound peptide did 
not participate in crystal contacts. Accordingly, any confor-
mational diff erences observed can be solely attributed to the 
buried polymorphic residues (positions 116 and 156) between 
the three allotypes. Position 116 is located at the F-pocket on 
the fl oor of the antigen-binding cleft, whereas position 156 
is located on the ␣ 2 helix forming part of the D/E pocket 
on HLA-B44. 
In all three HLA-B44 EENL complexes, the peptide bound 
in an extended conformation bulged centrally around the P6-
Asp and P7-Phe. A degree of mobility in the peptide around 
the P6 -P7 position was evident, especially in the HLA-
B*4405 EENL complex ( Fig. 2, a -c ). As expected, P2-Glu and </p>

<p>Figure 1. Differential affi nity and binding kinetics of the DM1 
TCR for the HLA-B44 allotypes. (a) Steady-state (or R equilibrium) 
binding of the three immobilized allotypes (HLA-B*4402 EENL , HLA-
B*4403 EENL , and HLA-B*4405 EENL ) to the DM1 TCR. (b -d) Binding of in-
creasing concentrations of the DM1 TCR (1.57 -50 μ M) to HLA-B*4402 EENL 
(b), HLA-B*4403 EENL (c), and HLA-B*4405 EENL (d). Data are representative of 
at least four experiments. Kinetic association and dissociation rate con-
stants were evaluated using the <rs type="software">BIAevalution</rs> software. The DM1 TCR 
displayed a 10-fold higher affi nity and a 10-fold slower dissociation rate 
constant for HLA-B*4405 EENL over the other allotypes. </p>

<p>Table I. Binding constants for the interaction of the DM1 TCR with HLA-B*4402/3/5 (determined by SPR) </p>

<p>Immobilized ligand 
Analyte 
K d ( μ M) 
K on ( × 10 4 /Ms) 
K off (1/s) 
K d calc ( μ M) </p>

<p>HLA-B*4402 EENL 
DM1 TCR 
6.3 ± 0.3 
1.4 
0.2 
14 
HLA-B*4403 EENL 
DM1 TCR 
9.4 ± 0.2 
1.3 
0.25 
16 
HLA-B*4405 EENL 
DM1 TCR 
0.3 ± 0.1 
6.8 
0.02 
0.23 
a DM1 TCR 
HLA-B*4405 EENL 
1 ± 0.5 
ND 
ND 
ND </p>

<p>ND, not determined. 
a For cross-validation, the affi nity for the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL interaction was determined. This was similar irrespective of whether the DM1 TCR or the pMHC was 
coupled to the chip (note that the levels for the HLA-B*4402 EENL and HLA-B*4403 EENL refolds were too low to permit these MHCs to be the analytes). </p>



<p>MHC POLYMORPHISM AND TCR RECOGNITION | Archbold et al. </p>

<p>nonliganded state and ligated to HLA-B*4405 EENL to a 2.75 
and 3.5 Å resolution, respectively ( Fig. 4 a and Table S1). The 
data collection and structure determination of the ternary 
complex was challenging, as the crystal form exhibited a cell 
edge close to 700 Å with three complexes in the asymmetric 
unit. Given that we had solved the structures of the nonligan-
ded counterparts of the ternary complex, the structure never-
theless refi ned readily at this resolution, and moreover, the 
electron density at the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL inter-
face was unambiguous ( Fig. 4 b ). The three complexes in the 
asymmetric unit were structurally identical. An overlay of the 
three complexes showed an overall r.m.s.d. of &lt; 1.4 Å , where 
major diff erences were in the diff ering juxtapositioning of the 
␤ 2 -microglobulin ( ␤ 2 m) domain (the r.m.s.d. without the ␤ 2 m 
domain is 0.7 Å ). Thus, unless explicitly stated, structural anal-
ysis is restricted to one complex in the asymmetric unit. 
The DM1 TCR docked at an angle of 80 ° across the long 
axis of the HLA-B*4405 EENL binding cleft, and accordingly, 
the DM1 TCR docked within the range of previously deter-
mined TCR -pMHC structures ( Fig. 4 c ) ( 5 ). The DM1 TCR 
was essentially centrally located above HLA-B*4405 EENL and 
formed fi ve H bonds, eight salt bridges, and a large number 
of vdw interactions ( Table II ). The total buried surface area 
(BSA) was ‫ف‬ 2,200 Å 2 , which lies within the range of previ-
ously determined TCR -pMHC-I structures ( 3 ). 
The V ␣ and V ␤ domains contributed roughly equally 
(54.6 and 45.4%, respectively) to the BSA at the HLA-B* 
4405 EENL interface. Moreover, all six complementarity deter-
mining region (CDR) loops of the DM1 TCR contributed to </p>

<p>The DM1 TCR recognizes the C-terminal end of the peptide 
To begin to gain an understanding of how the DM1 TCR 
engaged the HLA-B*4405 EENL complex, we undertook an 
alanine replacement scan of the epitope and assayed for CTL 
killing by the DM1 clone and for peptide -HLA-B*4405 
binding effi ciency. As expected, mutation of the P2-Glu and 
P10-Phe anchor residues markedly reduced binding to HLA-
B*4405 ( Fig. 3 ). Of the surface-exposed residues, substitu-
tions at position 8 reduced T cell recognition by ‫ف‬ 10-fold, 
whereas substitutions at positions 6 and 9 abrogated recogni-
tion by the T cells ( Fig. 3 ). Accordingly, it appeared that the 
DM1 TCR focused on the P6 -P9 region of the peptide, the 
region that displayed the greatest variation among the three 
HLA-B44 EENL allotypes. </p>

<p>Overview of the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex 
To gain a further understanding of why the DM1 TCR recog-
nizes HLA-B*4405 EENL more eff ectively than HLA-B*4402/ 
3 EENL , we determined the structure of the DM1 TCR in its </p>

<p>Figure 2. Structures of HLA-B*4402, HLA-B*4403, and HLA-
B*4405 presenting EENLLDFVRF show marked differences in the 
centrally bulged region of the epitope. (a -c) Structure of the EENL 
peptide bound to (with associated 2Fo-Fc electron density contoured at 
1 ) HLA-B*4402 (a), HLA-B*4403 (b), and HLA-B*4405 (c). The ␣ 2 helix has 
been removed for clarity. Potential TCR contact points are at P4, P6, P7, 
and P9. The central region (P5 -P9) of the epitope showed mobility in all 
three allotypes. (d) An overlay of the three HLA-B44 allotypes (HLA-
B*4402, orange; HLA-B*4403, green; HLA-B*4405, blue) revealing the mini-
mal movement of the ␣ helices and the movement of the central region 
(P5 -P7) of the C ␣ backbones of the peptides. (e) The hydrophobic (orange) 
Leu at P5 of the epitope in HLA-B*4402 is pushed away from the unfavor-
able hydrophilic (green) patch composed of R97, D114, D116, and D156, 
resulting in movement of the peptide backbone toward the ␣ 1 helix. In 
HLA-B*4403 and HLA-B*4405, this patch is less hydrophilic because of 
either the hydrophobic Leu at position 156 or the partially hydrophobic Tyr 
at position 116 (white), and can accommodate the hydrophobic P5 residue. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Alanine scanning mutagenesis of the peptide reveals a 
C-terminal focus. The impact of single amino-acid substitutions within 
the EENLLDFVRF peptide upon CTL recognition and HLA-B*4405 binding 
revealed P6 and P9 to be critical for TCR recognition. (a) EENL-specifi c CTL 
clones were tested for recognition of a panel of altered peptide ligands in 
which a single alanine substitution was introduced at each peptide posi-
tion. A range of peptide concentrations was used in the chromium release 
assays, and the concentration required for half-maximum lysis was deter-
mined from the dose -response data. (b) MHC peptide-binding assays 
were also conducted at a range of concentrations for their ability to sta-
bilize HLA-B*4405 expression. The concentration of peptide required for 
half-maximum HLA-B*4405 stabilization was calculated. Experiments 
were conducted once, with each sample tested in duplicate. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>the ␣ 2 helix. Accordingly, the structure of the nonliganded 
and ligated DM1 TCR provided insight into the large degree 
of plasticity that was required to enable HLA-B44 restriction. </p>

<p>Similar TCR usage against different HLA alleles 
The DM1 TCR ( TRAV26-1*02;TRAJ13*02;TRBV7-9*01; 
TRBJ2-1*01;TRBD1*01 ) uses V ␣ and V ␤ gene segments simi-
lar to those of the LC13 TCR ( TRAV26-2*01;TRAJ52*01/ 
TRBV7-8*03;TRBJ2-7*01;TRBD1/2 ), which interacts with 
HLA-B*0801 bound to the FLRGRAYGL antigen ( 21 ), as 
well as HLA-B44 when bound to an alloantigen. The DM1 
and LC13 TCRs share similarities in the CDR1 ␣ , CDR2 ␣ , 
CDR1 ␤ , and CDR2 ␤ loops (for sequence conservation see 
Table S2, available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/ 
jem.20082136/DC1) ( 22, 23 ). In comparison to the LC13 
footprint on HLA-B8 FLRGRAYGL , the CDR1 ␣ and CDR2 ␣ 
loops are in roughly equivalent locations, although the posi-
tioning of the corresponding loops in the V ␤ domain is more 
divergent ( Fig. 6, a and b ). From examination of all known 
TCR -pMHC co-crystal structures, it has been noted that 
TCRs often use a Tyr/Phe in the CDR1 ␣ to interact with </p>

<p>the HLA-B*4405 EENL interaction, albeit to varying degrees, 
which is consistent with the variable usage of CDR loops ob-
served in TCR -pMHC-I interactions ( 3, 18 -20 ). The CDR1 ␣ 
and CDR2 ␣ loops of DM1 TCR contributed 18 and 7.8%, 
respectively, and the CDR1 ␤ and CDR2 ␤ loops contributed 
7 and 11.8%, respectively, to the BSA. In contrast, the CDR3 
loops played a more prominent role, with the CDR3 ␣ and 
CDR3 ␤ loops contributing 19.6 and 17%, respectively, of the 
BSA at the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL interface. </p>

<p>Plasticity and the recognition of HLA-B44 
Our fi ndings represent the fi rst report of a TCR ligated to 
HLA-B44 and thereby provided us with an opportunity to 
gain an insight into the structural requirements underscoring 
HLA-B44 restriction. As we determined the structure of the 
DM1 TCR and HLA-B*4405 EENL in the nonliganded state, 
we were able to address the extent of plasticity that facilitates 
HLA-B44 restriction. Indeed, upon ligation, the V ␣ domain 
of the DM1 TCR changed orientation by 6 ° relative to the 
V ␤ domain ( Fig. 4 d ), in a manner analogous to that observed 
recently ( 20 ), and the CDR3 ␤ loop of the DM1 TCR changed 
conformation appreciably upon pMHC ligation. 
The DM1 TCR contacted HLA-B*4405 at positions 65, 
69, and 155, three positions that have been invariably contacted 
in all TCR -pMHC-I structures determined to date ( 5, 8 ), 
despite positions 65 and 69 representing polymorphic sites 
among the HLA alleles. To enable recognition, HLA-B*4405 
moved minimally upon ligation (the overall r.m.s.d. was 0.45 Å ), 
although rearrangement of four MHC residues (Glu 65 , Glu 76 , 
Arg 151 , and Gln 155 ) was observed. 
The CDR1 ␣ and CDR2 ␣ loops exclusively contacted res-
idues spanning 155 -163 from the ␣ 2 helix ( Table II and Fig. 5 a ). 
Asn 31 ␣ nestled in a shallow pocket that was fl anked by Leu 163 
and Gln 155 , the latter of which also interacted with Tyr 33 ␣ 
( Fig. 5 a ). Interestingly, Gln 155 , previously described as a 
gatekeeper residue, shifted conformation upon TCR ligation 
to form interactions with CDR1 ␣ as well as the peptide. The 
CDR2 ␣ played a limited role in interacting with HLA-B44 
( Table II and Fig. 5 a ), with Leu 57 ␣ forming vdw interactions 
with Glu 154 and Arg 151 , the latter of which also moved to salt 
bridge with framework residue Glu 67 ␣ ( Table II and Fig. 5 a ). 
The CDR1 ␤ and CDR2 ␤ contacted residues spanning 69 -76 
of the ␣ 1 helix ( Table II ), with the role of CDR1 ␤ being re-
stricted to interacting with Thr 73 and Glu 76 ( Fig. 5 b ), a residue 
that moved ‫ف‬ 2.5 Å to contact the CDR1 ␤ and CDR2 ␤ loops. 
The CDR2 ␤ loop comprised several polar residues (Gln 57 ␤ , 
Asn 58 ␤ , and Glu 59 ␤ ) and, accordingly, was observed to form 
several H bonds to the ␣ 1 helix of HLA-B*4405 ( Fig. 5 b ). 
In addition to participating in peptide-mediated interac-
tions, the CDR3 loops also contacted the HLA-B44 heavy 
chain. CDR3 ␣ made several vdw contacts with the ␣ 1 helix 
(residues 62 -66) that were centered on the aromatic residue 
Tyr 110 ␣ . Upon engagement, the CDR3 ␤ loop swung ‫ف‬ 90 ° 
and moved up to 5.8 Å to interact with the C terminus of the 
peptide (discussed in Epitope recognition by the DM1 TCR), 
and also formed a salt bridge between Asp 110 ␤ and Lys 146 of </p>

<p>Figure 4. Overview of the DM1 TCR in complex with HLA-
B*4405 EENL . (a) The DM1 -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex (DM1 TCR V ␣ , orange; 
DM1 TCR V ␤ , green; HLA-B*4405, gray; EENL peptide, blue; ␤ 2 m, pink). 
(b) A closer view of the DM1 TCR binding to the HLA-B*4405 EENL , showing 
the clear electron density for the peptide (2Fo-Fc map contoured at 1 ). 
(c) Relative docking angle of the DM1 TCR on the pMHC (80 ° ). For docking 
orientation, an axis was drawn through the points at the center of mass of 
the V ␣ and V ␤ domains. The positioning of the CDR loops of the DM1 TCR 
on HLA-B*4405 is also shown (CDR1 ␣ , orange; CDR2 ␣ , yellow; CDR3 ␣ , 
red; CDR1 ␤ , slate; CDR2 ␤ green; CDR3 ␤ , teal). (d) Scissoring action of the 
V ␣ domain compared with the V ␤ domain upon ligation. Superposition of 
the V ␤ domains of the nonliganded and liganded DM1 TCR revealed move-
ment of the V ␣ domain by 6 ° . The nonliganded V ␣ domain of the TCR is 
shown in blue, and the liganded V ␣ domain of the TCR is shown in orange. </p>



<p>MHC POLYMORPHISM AND TCR RECOGNITION | Archbold et al. </p>

<p>quite diff erent, the sandwiching of Gln 50 ␤ between Gln 72 
and Glu 76 is maintained ( Fig. 6 d ). Accordingly, there are 
some similarities, as well as notable diff erences, in the manner 
in which very similar V ␣ and V ␤ gene segments interact with 
diff ering pMHC landscapes. </p>

<p>Epitope recognition by the DM1 TCR 
Although the HLA-B*4405 heavy chain did not change con-
formation upon DM1 TCR ligation, we observed an altera-
tion in the conformation of the peptide (P4 -P7) upon ligation </p>

<p>position 155 ( 24 ). Indeed, both DM1 and LC13 use an aro-
matic residue to contact Gln 155 , as well as a Gly 30 ␣ to contact 
Ala 158 ( Fig. 6 c ). Moreover, although CDR2 ␣ played a minor 
role in interacting with HLA-B44, both the DM1 TCR and 
the LC13 TCR use a Leu at the same position in CDR2 ␣ to 
conserve the interaction with Glu 154 ( Fig. 6 c ). Although it 
has been suggested that a Ser in the CDR2 ␣ loop will con-
tact the MHC at position 154 -155 ( 24 ), this has not been 
observed in the DM1 TCR complex or other TCR -pMHC 
complexes. Although the positioning of the CDR2 ␤ loops is </p>

<p>Table II. DM1 -HLA-B*4405 EENL interactions </p>

<p>TCR residue 
MHC or peptide residues 
Bond type 
Gene segment </p>

<p>CDR1 ␣ 
Gly 30 
Ala 158 
vdw 
V ␣ 
CDR1 ␣ 
Asn 31 
Gln 155, Tyr 159, Leu 163 
vdw 
V ␣ 
CDR1 ␣ 
Tyr 33 
Arg 151, Gln 155 
vdw 
V ␣ 
CDR2 ␣ 
Leu 57 
Arg 151, Glu 154 
vdw 
V ␣ 
FW 
Glu 67 Oe1, Oe2 
Arg 151 NH1, NH2 
salt bridge 
V ␣ 
FW 
Glu 67 
Arg 151 
vdw 
V ␣ 
FW 
Glu 84 
Thr 41 
vdw 
V ␣ 
CDR3 ␣ 
Tyr 110 
Arg 62, Gln 65, Ile 66, 
vdw 
J ␣ 
CDR3 ␣ 
Gln 111 
Gln 65 
vdw 
J ␣ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Asn 30 N ␦ 2 
Glu 76 O 1 
H bond 
V ␤ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Asn 30 
Glu 76 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR2 ␤ 
Gln 57 N 2 
Glu 76 O 2 
H bond 
V ␤ 
CDR2 ␤ 
Gln 57 
Gln 72, Thr 73, Glu 76 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR2 ␤ 
Asn 58 O ␦ 1 
Gln 72 N 2 
H bond 
V ␤ 
CDR2 ␤ 
Asn 58 
Gln 72, Glu 76 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR2 ␤ 
Glu 59 
Gln 72 
vdw 
V ␤ 
FW 
Leu 66 
Thr 69 
vdw 
V ␤ 
FW 
Glu 67 
Glu 65 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR3 ␤ 
Asp 110 O ␦ 1 
Lys 146 NZ 
salt bridge 
D ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Asp 110 
Lys 146 
vdw 
D ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Ser 112 
Ala 150 
vdw 
J ␤ 
CDR3 ␣ 
Tyr 110 
Leu 4, Asp 6 
vdw 
J ␣ 
CDR3 ␣ 
Trp 107 
Asp 6, Phe 7 
vdw 
N region </p>

<p>CDR3 ␣ 
Gly 109 
Leu 5 
vdw 
J ␣ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Asn 30 
Arg 9 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Asn 30 N ␦ 2 
Arg 9 NH2 
H bond 
V ␤ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Arg 31 NH1, NH2 
Asp 6 O ␦ 1, O ␦ 2 
salt bridge 
V ␤ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Arg 31 N 
Arg 9 NH1 
H bond 
V ␤ 
CDR1 ␤ 
Arg 31 
Asp 6, Phe 7, Arg 9 
vdw 
V ␤ 
CDR3 ␤ 
Arg 107 NH1, NH2 
Asp 6 O ␦ 1, O ␦ 2 
salt bridge 
V ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Arg 107 
Asp 6 
vdw 
V ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Arg 109 
Arg 9 
vdw 
D ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Asp 110 ° 
Arg 9 N 
salt bridge 
D ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Asp 110 
Phe 7, Arg 9 
vdw 
D ␤ -N 
CDR3 ␤ 
Asp 111 
Arg 9 
vdw 
N-J ␤ 
CDR3 ␤ 
Ser 112 
Phe 7 
vdw 
J ␤ 
CDR3 ␤ 
Tyr 113 
Phe 7 
vdw 
J ␤ </p>

<p>Superscripted designations indicate the atom involved in hydrogen bonding. The vdw cutoff distance was ≤ 4 Å . D, diversity; FW, framework residue; J, joining; N, 
nongermline encoded; V, variable. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>was reminiscent of the highly specifi c interaction between the 
KK50.4 -HLA-E LIL interaction ( 27 ), and is likely to be a key 
driver in determining the specifi city of the DM1 TCR -HLA-
B*4405 EENL interaction, which is consistent with the peptide 
substitution data. Accordingly, the DM1 TCR made a num-
ber of critical interactions with the centrally bulged region of 
the epitope, which is the region that displayed the greatest de-
gree of variability between the HLA-B*4405 EENL , HLA-B* 
4402 EENL , and HLA-B*4403 EENL binary complexes. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION 
There are ‫ف‬ 3,000 diff erent HLA alleles ( 28 ) clustered into 
nine HLA supertypes ( 29 ), the maintenance of which within 
the human population is critical for protective immunity, 
disease susceptibility, autoimmunity, and drug hypersensitiv-
ity. Despite the importance of micropolymorphism in pro-
tective immunity, data are limited on how this directly relates 
to TCR recognition. This study provides simultaneous insight 
into HLA-B44 restriction, and how micropolymorphism be-
tween the HLA-B*4405, HLA-B*4403, and HLA-B*4402 </p>

<p>( Fig. 7 a ) analogous to the peptide " bulldozing " observed in 
the ELS4 TCR -HLA-B*3501 EPLP structure ( 25 ). Upon liga-
tion, the CDR3 ␣ loop reorientated the P4-Leu side chain, 
which consequently appeared to push the peptide toward the 
␣ 1 helix, resulting in the complete shift of the backbone con-
formation of P5-Leu and P6-Asp ( Fig. 7 a ). In addition, the 
side chain of P7-Phe, which was mobile in the nonliganded 
form ( Fig. 4 c ), became completely ordered via interactions 
with the CDR3 ␤ loop. 
The repositioning of the peptide enabled the CDR1 ␤ , 
CDR3 ␣ , and CDR3 ␤ loops to interact with positions 3 -7 
and 9 of the determinant. CDR1 ␤ played a major role in in-
teracting with the peptide courtesy of some large side chains 
bridging the gap between the C ␣ backbones of the CDR1 ␤ 
loop and peptide (specifi cally, P6-Asp salt bridges to Arg 31 ␤ 
and the P9-Arg H bonds to Asn 30 ␤ and Arg 31 ␤ ; Fig. 7 b ). 
The CDR3 ␣ loop interacted with the middle region of the 
peptide ( Fig. 7 b ) in which Tyr 110 ␣ and Trp 107 ␣ played 
a prominent role in this interaction. Tyr 110 ␣ packed against 
P4-Leu and Trp 107 ␣ interacted with P6-Asp and P7-Phe. 
Notably an analysis of the ␣ chain repertoire of HLA-
B*4405 EENL -specifi c TCRs from other HLA-B*4405 + , EBV-
exposed individuals (Table S3, available at http://www.jem 
.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20082136/DC1) revealed that this 
Trp is highly conserved despite this residue being encoded 
entirely from the N region. Furthermore, Trp is encoded by 
a single codon (TGG), and there is therefore a theoretically 
low (1 out of 64) probability of this codon appearing by co-
incidence ( 26 ). This bulky Trp residue also helped to orien-
tate the CDR3 ␤ loop, which abutted the C-terminal end of 
the peptide in an antiparallel manner. The main chain of Ser 
112 ␤ and Tyr 113 ␤ " sat " on the P7-Phe, whereas the P9-
Arg protruded into a niche formed between the CDR1 ␤ and 
CDR3 ␤ loops, forming an H bond to Asp 110 ␤ O ( Fig. 7 b ). 
The interactions include a salt bridge between P6-Asp and 
Arg 107 ␤ as well as P9-Arg and Asp 110 ␤ ( Fig. 7 b ). The 
cluster of charged interactions between the DM1 TCR (Arg 
31 ␤ and Arg 107 ␤ ) and the peptide (P6-Asp and P9-Arg) </p>

<p>Figure 5. DM1 interactions with HLA-B*4405 EENL . (a) Interactions 
with the HLA-B*4405 heavy chain mediated by the V ␣ domain of the DM1 
TCR (CDR1 ␣ , orange; CDR2 ␣ , yellow; CDR3 ␣ , red; HLA-B*4405 heavy chain, 
gray; EENL epitope, blue). (b) Interactions with the HLA-B*4405 heavy chain 
mediated by the V ␤ domain of the DM1 TCR (CDR1 ␤ , slate; CDR2 ␤ , green; 
CDR3 ␤ , teal; HLA-B*4405 heavy chain, gray; EENL epitope, blue). </p>

<p>Figure 6. DM1 -pMHC interactions compared with the LC13 -
pMHC structure, revealing similar positioning of the CDR ␣ loops. 
(a) DM1 TCR " footprint " on HLA-B*4405 EENL . HLA-B*4405 EENL (gray) is shown 
in surface representation. The pMHC residues are colored according to the 
relevant contacting CDR loop. The positions of the CDR loops are also 
shown (CDR1 ␣ , orange; CDR2 ␣ , yellow; CDR3 ␣ , red; CDR1 ␤ , slate; CDR2 ␤ , 
green; CDR3 ␤ , teal). (b) LC13 footprint on HLA-B*0801 FLR . HLA-B*0801 FLR 
(gray) is shown in surface representation. The pMHC residues are colored 
according to the relevant contacting CDR loop (CDR1 ␣ , orange; CDR2 ␣ , 
yellow; CDR3 ␣ , red; CDR1 ␤ , slate; CDR2 ␤ , green; CDR3 ␤ , teal). The LC13 
CDR loops are shown in gray. (c) Similar positioning of the CDR1 ␣ loops 
(CDR1 ␣ , orange; CDR2 ␣ , yellow; CDR3 ␣ , red) of DM1 compared with LC13 
(gray) allowed conservation of interactions with residues E154, Q155, and 
A158 on the ␣ 2 helix. (d) Although the positioning of the V ␤ loops of the 
two TCRs was divergent, the packing of Q50 ␤ of the CDR2 ␤ loop of DM1 
(green) and LC13 (gray) between Q72 and E76 was maintained. </p>



<p>MHC POLYMORPHISM AND TCR RECOGNITION | Archbold et al. </p>

<p>with HLA-B35, and one each is with H2-L d and HLA-B8 
( 3 ). Accordingly, any generalities proposed could potentially 
be skewed toward a particular MHC allele. For example, al-
though common pairwise interactions are observed in de-
fi ned V ␤ 8.2 -MHC interactions ( 6, 7 ), this generality does 
not extend to V ␤ 8.2 -CD1d interactions ( 31, 32 ). The HLA-
B*4405 -restricted DM1 TCR exhibits similar V ␣ and V ␤ 
usage to the LC13 TCR, whose cognate antigen is HLA-B8, 
but also alloreacts on HLA-B44 ( 33 ). Although the respec-
tive V ␤ domains showed a large degree of variation in dock-
ing, there was some similarity in the interaction mode within 
the CDR1 and CDR2 loops. However, mutational map-
ping has shown that for the LC13 -HLA B8 FLR interaction, 
the energetic driving force for the interaction rested not in 
the CDR1 and CDR2 loops but in the CDR3 loops ( 18 ). 
Perhaps the diff erent docking modes of the LC13 and DM1 
TCRs may relate to a given V gene " selecting " an orienta-
tion that is specifi c for a given MHC allotype. The distinct 
docking modes observed may represent two examples of 
several potential germline-encoded modes of interaction, 
with each being " selected " to optimize interactions with the 
distinct peptides presented by the specifi c MHC allotype. 
Studies on the experimental H2-K b /K bm3 system have 
indicated how a buried polymorphism can aff ect peptide 
presentation that leads to an increase in V ␤ -mediated inter-
actions ( 10 ). Similarly, studies in the H2-K b /K bm8 system pro-
vided some evidence to suggest that very subtle diff erences 
between the alleles, which may include diff ering pMHC dy-
namics, can aff ect TCR recognition ( 9 ). The eff ect of bur-
ied HLA polymorphism on peptide conformation/dynamics 
has implications in graft-versus-host disease. Namely, donor 
T cells that have escaped thymic deletion caused by being 
weakly autoreactive toward a given pMHC may recognize 
very similar recipient pMHC complexes with much greater 
affi nity because of the changes in the peptide conformation/ 
dynamics. For example, the eff ect of MHC micropolymor-
phism on TCR recognition has been observed in compara-
tive studies between HLA-B*3501 and HLA-B*3508. ( 34, 
35 ). Similarly, mismatching of HLA-B*4402 and HLA-
B*4403, two allomorphs that diff er by just one amino acid, 
is a known barrier in transplantation and has been termed a 
" taboo mismatch " ( 13 ). In this case, the polymorphism was 
shown to subtly aff ect the peptide repertoire, the conforma-
tion of the peptide, and the MHC itself ( 11 ). Moreover, 
within the HLA-B*3501/B*3508 setting, it has also been 
established that the immunogenicity of a viral epitope is 
controlled by the conformation of the peptide within the 
antigen-binding cleft ( 36 ), and our data resonate with these 
fi ndings. Such eff ects on TCR recognition of viral determi-
nants may be an important consideration for future vaccina-
tion strategies against viruses, as markedly diff erent CTL 
responses to the same viral epitope may be elicited in indi-
viduals expressing closely related HLA types. 
TCR degeneracy is considered to be an important factor 
enabling TCRs to bind a wide range of potential pMHC 
combinations with the limited number of T cells present in </p>

<p>allotypes fi nely tunes the CTL response toward an EBV de-
terminant. The micropolymorphisms between these allo-
types are not accessible to the TCR, and they did not 
appreciably aff ect the conformation of the MHC. Neverthe-
less, the DM1 TCR recognized the HLA-B*4405 allotype, 
presenting an EBV epitope, with a 10-fold increase in affi n-
ity when compared with HLA-B*4403 and HLA-B*4402. 
This is attributable to the altered conformation and dynamics 
of the peptide within the respective antigen-binding clefts. 
Specifi cally, residues 4 -7 of the EBV epitope varied between 
the allotypes, with the epitope displaying a greater degree 
of mobility in HLA-B*4405. The signifi cance of this vari-
ability and the dynamics of the epitope was apparent in the 
DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex, whereby the DM1 
TCR not only contacted this mobile region but also caused 
a radical reshaping of the peptide upon ligation. In addition, 
the slow association rates (K on ) for the DM1 TCR interac-
tion with all three pMHC complexes are consistent with 
marked conformational rearrangement occurring at the 
TCR -pMHC interface, which further refl ects the underly-
ing fl exibility of the TCR -pMHC interface ( 30 ). Interest-
ingly, the on rate for the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL 
interaction was approximately sixfold higher when com-
pared with the interactions with HLA-B*4403 EENL and 
HLA-B*4402 EENL . This is consistent with the increased fl ex-
ibility of the EENL epitope in HLA-B*4405 facilitating 
the DM1 TCR docking, whereas the more " rigid " HLA-
B*4403 EENL and HLA-B*4402 EENL complexes would be less 
favorable for DM1 TCR engagement. 
Although structural studies have been enormously infor-
mative in addressing how the TCR can engage the pMHC, 
they are somewhat limited in their scope, as the subset of 
diff erent MHC alleles that have been solved in complex with 
the TCR is relatively small. For example, of the 16 unique 
TCR -pMHC-Ia structures that have been determined to 
date, seven are with H2-K b , fi ve are with HLA-A2, two are </p>

<p>Figure 7. DM1-mediated peptide interactions. (a) Conformational 
movement of the EENL peptide upon ligation by the DM1 TCR revealing 
plasticity of the pMHC surface. The nonligand-bound conformation is 
shown in orange, and the ligand-bound conformation of the EENL epit-
ope is shown in blue. (b) DM1 interactions with the EENL peptide. A clus-
ter of charged interactions between the DM1 TCR and the peptide 
provides specifi city. This specifi city is driven by CDR3 ␣ (red), CDR1 ␤ 
(slate), and CDR3 ␤ (teal). Salt bridges are shown as red dashed lines, and 
H bonds are shown as black dashed lines. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>and ␤ loops start at residue number 27, the CDR2 ␣ and ␤ loops start at residue 
number 56, and the CDR3 ␣ and ␤ loops start at residue number 105. 
The HLA-B4402/3/5 EENL crystals belonged to the space group P2 1 2 1 2 1 
with unit cell dimensions (Table S1), each consistent with one molecule in the 
asymmetrical unit. The structure was determined by molecular replacement 
using the <rs type="software">MOLREP</rs> program with the HLA-B*4405 as the search model 
(available from the Protein Data Bank under accession no. 1SYV0 ) ( 11 ). Sub-
sequent model building was conducted using the <rs type="software">COOT</rs> software ( 42 ), fol-
lowed by maximum-likelihood refi nement with the <rs id="software-34" type="software">REFMAC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-34" type="version-number">5</rs> program 
( 40, 43 ). Refi nement was monitored by R free , and water molecules were in-
cluded in the model if they were within hydrogen-bonding distance to chem-
ically reasonable groups, and appeared in the Fo-Fc maps contoured at 3 sigma 
and had a B factor &lt; 80 Å 2 . 
For the DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex, the data were pro-
cessed and scaled using the <rs type="software">HKL2000</rs> software ( 38 ). The crystals belonged to 
the hexagonal space group P6 5 22 with unit cell dimensions (Table S1), each 
consistent with three complexes in the asymmetrical unit. The structure was 
determined by molecular replacement using the PHASER program using the 
fully refi ned unliganded DM1 TCR and the HLA-B*4405 EENL structures 
(minus peptide) as search models. Subsequent minimal model building was 
conducted using the <rs type="software">COOT</rs> software ( 42 ), followed by maximum-likelihood 
refi nement with the <rs id="software-37" type="software">REFMAC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-37" type="version-number">5</rs> program ( 40, 43 ). TLS displacement refi ne-
ment was used to model anisotropic displacements of defi ned domains. Again, 
the optimal TLS domains were determined using the TLS motion determina-
tion server ( 44, 45 ) and were read into the <rs id="software-31" type="software">REFMAC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-31" type="version-number">5</rs> program. Tight NCS 
restraints were also used during the refi nement process. 
All structures were validated using the <rs type="software">PROCHECK</rs> ( 47 ) and <rs type="software">MOL-
BROBITY</rs> ( 48 ) programs. Ramachandran plots were obtained from the 
<rs type="software">MOLPROBITY</rs> program ( 48 ). The fi nal Ramachandran statistics were as 
follows: DM1 TCR, 92.5% (most favored region) and 98.6% (allowed re-
gion); HLA-B*4402 EENL , 97.6% (most favored region) and 100% (allowed re-
gion); HLA-B*4403 EENL , 97.9% (most favored region) and 99.5% (allowed 
region); HLA-B*4405 EENL , 97.1% (most favored region) and 99.2% (allowed 
region); and DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL , 86.3% (most favored region) and 
97.5% (allowed region). All molecular graphics representations were created 
using the <rs type="software">PyMOL</rs> system ( 49 ). </p>

<p>SPR measurement and analysis. All SPR experiments were conducted at 
25 ° C on the BIAcore 3000 instrument (GE Healthcare) with HBS buff er (10 
mM Hepes [pH 7.4], 150 mM NaCl, and 0.005% surfactant P20). The HBS 
buff er was supplemented with 1% bovine serum albumin to prevent nonspe-
cifi c binding. The human HLA-specifi c mAb, W6/32 ( 50 ) was coupled to re-
search grade CM5 chips with standard amine coupling. For each experiment, 
HLA-B*4402/3/5 was passed over two fl ow cells and ‫ف‬ 200 -500 response 
units (RU) was captured by the antibody. The other two fl ow cells were used 
as control cells for each experiment. The DM1 TCR was injected over all four 
fl ow cells at a rate of 20 μ l/min with a concentration range of 0.39 -400 μ M. 
The fi nal response was calculated by subtraction of the response of the antibody 
alone from that of the antibody HLA-B44 complex. The antibody surface was 
regenerated between each analyte injection with Actisep (Sterogene). All ex-
periments were conducted in duplicate. 
For cross-validation of results, the reverse experiment was performed. The 
DM1 TCR was coupled to the CM5 chip using the 12H8 antibody ( 18 ), 
which is conformation specifi c for a region bridging the ␣ and ␤ constant do-
mains of the TCR. For this experiment, 400 -600 RU of the DM1 TCR was 
captured on the antibody, and HLA-B*4405 EENL (0.6 -150 μ M) was injected 
over the fl ow cells at 20 μ l/min. The total protein levels for the HLA-B* 
4402 EENL and HLA-B*4403 EENL refolds were too low to permit these pMHCs 
to be the analytes. 
<rs id="software-43" type="software">BIAevaluation</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-43" type="version-number">version 3.1</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-43" type="creator">GE Healthcare</rs>) was used for data 
analysis; the 1:1 Langmuir binding model was used to calculate the kinetic 
constants. To allow for the capture system, the model was modifi ed to include 
an additional parameter for the drifting baseline for the TCR capture by 12H8. 
The quality of the fi t between experimental data and the binding models was 
evaluated by monitoring the 2 values (i.e., &lt; 10), as well as the residual plots. </p>

<p>the periphery. Conversely, we illustrate how a single HLA 
polymorphism alters the dynamics of the pMHC landscape 
and aff ects TCR recognition, thereby providing direct in-
sight into the heightened specifi city of a TCR and the subtle-
ties of TCR recognition. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Protein expression, purifi cation, and crystallization. The DM1 TCR 
was expressed and purifi ed essentially as previously described ( 27 ) using an 
engineered disulfi de linkage in the constant domains between TRAC48 and 
TRBC57. In brief, the ␣ and ␤ chains of the DM1 TCR were expressed sep-
arately in Escherichia coli and purifi ed from inclusion bodies before being re-
folded before purifi cation. HLA-B*4402 1-276 , HLA-B*4403 1-276 , HLA-B* 
4405 1-276 , and ␤ 2 m were also expressed separately in E. coli and purifi ed from 
inclusion bodies before being refolded before purifi cation, as previously de-
scribed ( 17 ). An excess of peptide was required to drive refolding (e.g., 45 mg 
of HLA-B44 heavy chain, 15 mg of ␤ 2 m, and 50 mg of peptide were mixed, 
resulting in ‫ف‬ 2 -3mg of pure refolded protein). Purifi ed HLA-B*4405 EENL 
was mixed with an excess of purifi ed DM1 TCR, and the DM1 TCR -HLA-
B*4405 EENL complex was purifi ed using a gel fi ltration column (Sephadex-
200; GE Healthcare). Crystals were grown by the hanging-drop, vapor-diff usion 
method at 20 ° C with a protein/reservoir drop ratio of 1:1. 
Crystals of the DM1 TCR, the HLA-B44 peptide complexes, and the 
DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex were all grown by the hanging-drop, 
vapor-diff usion method at 20 ° C with a protein/reservoir drop ratio of 1:1. 
The DM1 TCR was at a concentration of 10 mg/ml in TBS (10 mM Tris, 
150 mM NaCl [pH 8]). Crystals appeared in 2 -5 d in 0.1 M Hepes (pH 7), 
0.1 M magnesium formate, 18% (weight/volume) PEG 3350. The HLA-B44 
peptide complexes were at a concentration of 3 mg/ml in TBS. Crystals ap-
peared in 1 -3 d in 0.1 M citrate (pH 5.6), 0.2 M ammonium acetate, 20 -30% 
(weight/volume) PEG 4K. The DM1 TCR -HLA-B*4405 EENL complex was 
at a concentration of 5 mg/ml in TBS. Crystals appeared after 7 d in 0.1 M 
bicine (pH 9), 0.2 M lithium sulfate, 16 -18% PEG 3350. </p>

<p>Data collection, structure determination, and refi nement. The DM1 
TCR crystals were frozen in liquid nitrogen using 5% glycerol as a cryopro-
tectant. The HLA-B*4402/03/05 EENL complexes were all frozen using 10% 
glycerol as the cryoprotectant. The DM1 TCR -HLA-B4405 EENL crystals 
were dehydrated in 25% PEG 3350 for 2 -5 min and fl ash frozen in liquid ni-
trogen. All data were collected on the Industrial Macromolecular Crystallog-
raphy Association Collaborative Access Team beamline at the Argonne 
Photon Source Synchrotron using the Quantum 210 CCD detector at 100 K 
(ADSC). Data for the unliganded DM1 TCR and the HLA-B4402/3/5 EENL 
binary structures were processed using either <rs type="software">MOSFLM</rs> ( 37 ) or <rs type="software">HKL2000</rs> 
( 38 ) software and were scaled using <rs type="software">SCALA</rs> software ( 39 ) from the <rs type="software">CCP4 
suite</rs> ( 40 ) or scalepack ( 38 ). 
The DM1 crystal belonged to the space group P2 1 with unit cell dimen-
sions (Table S1) consistent with two molecules in the asymmetrical unit. The 
structure was determined by molecular replacement using the <rs type="software">MOLREP</rs> pro-
gram with the 1G4 TCR as the search model (available from the Protein Data 
Bank under accession no. 2BNU ) ( 41 ). Subsequent model building was con-
ducted using the <rs type="software">COOT</rs> software ( 42 ), followed by maximum-likelihood re-
fi nement with the <rs id="software-29" type="software">REFMAC</rs> <rs corresp="#software-29" type="version-number">5</rs> program (CCP4 suite) ( 40, 43 ). Translation, 
liberation, and screw-rotation (TLS) displacement refi nement was used to 
model anisotropic displacements of defi ned domains. The optimal TLS do-
mains were determined using the TLS motion determination server ( 44, 45 ) 
and were read into the REFMAC 5 program. Refi nement was monitored by 
R free , and water molecules were included in the model if they were within hy-
drogen-bonding distance to chemically " reasonable " groups, and appeared in 
the Fo-Fc maps (where Fo and Fc are the observed and calculated structure 
factors, respectively) contoured at 3 sigma and had a B factor &lt; 80 Å 2 . Tight 
noncrystallographic symmetry (NCS) restraints were also used during the re-
fi nement process. The TCR was numbered according to the international 
ImMunoGeneTic (IMGT) unique numbering system ( 46 ), whereby the CDR1 ␣ </p>



<p>MHC POLYMORPHISM AND TCR RECOGNITION | Archbold et al. </p>

<p>Submitted: 24 September 2008 
Accepted: 11 December 2008 </p>



<p>Cytotoxicity assays: alanine substitution analysis. The DM1 CTL 
clone was tested in duplicate for cytotoxicity in a standard 5-h chromium re-
lease assay. In brief, CTLs were assayed against 51 Cr-labeled autologous PHA 
blast targets that were pretreated with synthetic peptide or left untreated. The 
percentage of specifi c lysis was calculated, and the peptide concentration re-
quired for half-maximum lysis was determined from dose -response curves. 
Peptides were synthesized by Mimotopes Ltd. Toxicity testing of all peptides 
was performed before use by adding peptide to 51 Cr-labeled PHA blasts in 
the absence of CTL eff ectors. A ␤ scintillation counter (Topcount Micro-
plate; PerkinElmer) was used to measure 51 Cr levels in assay supernatant 
samples. The mean spontaneous lysis for target cells in the culture medium 
was always &lt; 20%, and the variation from the mean specifi c lysis was &lt; 10%. </p>

<p>HLA peptide-binding assays. To assess peptide binding to HLA-B*4405, 
HLA stabilization studies were conducted using the mutant HLA-A/B null 
lymphoblastoid cell line C1R ( 51 ) that had been transfected to expressed 
HLA-B*4405 and the herpes virus -derived protein ICP47, which inhibits 
the transporter associated with antigen processing. These cells were incu-
bated in serum-free medium (AIM V; Invitrogen) with various concentra-
tions (0.1, 1, 10, or 100 μ M) of peptides at 26 ° C for 14 -16 h, followed by 
incubation at 37 ° C for 2 -3 h. HLA-B*4405 surface expression was measured 
by fl ow cytometry on a FACSCanto (BD) using an mAb to HLA-Bw4. 
Mean fl uorescence intensity was determined, and the peptide concentration 
required for half-maximum mean fl uorescence intensity was calculated. </p>

<p>EENL-specifi c T cell repertoire analysis. T cells specifi c for the EENL 
peptide were fi rst isolated from bulk EENL-specifi c CTL cultures raised from 
two HLA-B*4405 + family members of donor DM (from whom the DM1 CTL 
clone was raised) by stimulation of PBMCs with the EENL peptide, followed by 
expansion in rIL-2 -containing medium for 10 d. Using fl ow cytometric cell 
sorting, CTLs that bound an HLA-B*4405 EENL tetramer and costained with 
anti-CD3 and anti-CD8 mAbs (BD) were isolated. The sorting was performed 
on a MoFlo sorter (Dako), and purities of &gt; 96% were consistently achieved. 
Total RNA was extracted from the sorted CTLs using TRI zol reagent (Invit-
rogen). RT-PCR and PCR was performed using a One-Step PCR (Invitrogen) 
according to the manufacturer ' s guidelines. The forward primer was 1 out of 34 
previously published TCR TRAV family-specifi c primers ( 52 ); the reverse 
TRAJ13-specifi c primer was designed in house (5 Ј -GGATGACTTGGAG-
CTTTGTT-3 Ј ). PCR products were purifi ed and cloned into the pGEM-T 
vector system (Promega) and sequenced using the ABI PRISM Big Dye termi-
nation reaction kit (Applied Biosystems). The IMGT database TCR gene no-
menclature was used throughout ( 46 ). </p>

<p>Protein data bank accession codes. The atomic coordinates and struc-
ture factors are available from the Protein Data Bank under the following 
accession nos: DM1 TCR -HLA-B4405 EENL complex, 3DXA ; DM1 TCR, 
3DX9 ; HLA-B*4402 EENL , 3DX6 ; HLA-B*4403 EENL , 3DX7 ; and HLA-
B*4405 EENL , 3DX8 . </p>

<p>Online supplemental material. Table S1 summarizes data collection and 
refi nement statistics. Table S2 represents a sequence comparison between 
LC13 and DM1 TCR CDR loops. Table S3 shows a V ␣ sequence compari-
son between B44 EENL -restricted TCRs. Online supplemental material is 
available at http://www.jem.org/cgi/content/full/jem.20082136/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank the staff at the Industrial Macromolecular Crystallography Association, 
Advanced Photon Source, Chicago for assistance with data collection. 
This work was supported by the National Health and Medical Research Council 
(NHMRC) of Australia and the Australian Research Council (ARC). S.R. Burrows, A.W. 
Purcell, and M.C.J. Wilce are supported by NHMRC Senior Research Fellowships; 
W.A. Macdonald is supported by an NHMRC Peter Doherty Fellowship; T. Beddoe is 
supported by an NHMRC Career Development Award Fellowship; and J.K. Archbold 
is supported by a Dora Lush NHMRC Scholarship. J. Rossjohn is supported by an 
ARC Federation Fellowship. 
The authors have no confl icting fi nancial interests. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, January 19, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>





</text></tei>