<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2551674" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:10+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-The precise molecular mechanisms contributing 
to the development of insulin resistance, impaired glucose toler-
ance (IGT), and type 2 diabetes are largely unknown. Altered 
endogenous glucocorticoid metabolism, including 11␤-hydroxy-
steroid dehydrogenase type 1 (11␤-HSD1), which generates ac-
tive cortisol from cortisone, and 5␣-reductase (5␣R), which 
inactivates cortisol, has been implicated. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-A total of 101 obese 
patients (mean age 48 Ϯ 7 years, BMI 34.4 Ϯ 4.3 kg/m 
2 , 66 
women, 35 men) underwent 75-g oral glucose tolerance testing 
(OGTT), body composition analysis (dual-energy X-ray absorpti-
ometry), assessment of glucocorticoid metabolism (24-h urine 
steroid metabolite analysis by gas chromatography/mass spec-
trometry), and subcutaneous abdominal adipose tissue biopsies. </p>

<p>RESULTS-A total of 22.7% of women had IGT compared with 
34.2% of men. Two women and five men were diagnosed with 
type 2 diabetes. In women, adipose 11␤-HSD1 expression was 
increased in patients with IGT and correlated with glucose levels 
across the OGTT (R ϭ 0.44, P Ͻ 0.001) but was independent of 
fat mass. Total glucocorticoid secretion was higher in men with 
and without IGT (normal 13,743 Ϯ 863 vs. 7,453 Ϯ 469 g/24 h, 
P Ͻ 0.001; IGT 16,871 Ϯ 2,113 vs. 10,133 Ϯ 1,488 g/24 h, P Ͻ 
0.05), and in women, it was higher in those with IGT (7,453 Ϯ 469 
vs. 10,133 Ϯ 1,488 g/24 h, P Ͻ 0.001). In both sexes, 5␣R activity 
correlated with fasting insulin (men R ϭ 0.53, P ϭ 0.003; women 
R ϭ 0.33, P ϭ 0.02), insulin secretion across an OGTT (men R ϭ 
0.46, P ϭ 0.01; women R ϭ 0.40, P ϭ 0.004), and homeostasis 
model assessment of insulin resistance (men R ϭ 0.52, P ϭ 0.004; 
women R ϭ 0.33, P ϭ 0.02). </p>

<p>capable of inactivating cortisol to cortisone. Critically, the 
directionality of 11␤-HSD1 activity is cofactor (NADPH) 
dependent, which is supplied by a tightly associated 
endolumenal enzyme, hexose-6-phopshate dehydrogenase 
(H6PDH). Decreases in H6PDH expression and activity 
decrease oxoreductase and increase dehydrogenase activ-
ity (12,13). Recently, much attention has focused on 
pharmacological manipulation of cortisol metabolism as a 
therapeutic strategy. Selective 11␤-HSD1 inhibitors admin-
istered to rodents and primates decrease local glucocorti-
coid generation, improve glucose tolerance, increase 
insulin sensitivity, and may promote weight loss (14 -17). 
In contrast to the action of 11␤-HSD1, the A-ring reducta-
ses (5␣-reductase type 1 [5␣R1] and type 2 [5␣R2] and 
5␤-reductase) inactivate cortisol, decreasing local glu-
cocorticoid availability to bind and activate the glucocor-
ticoid receptor (GR). 5␣R1 is expressed in skin and 
adipose tissue (18,19) and 5␣R2 in prostate, epididymis, 
and seminal vesicles; both isozymes are expressed in the 
liver (18). 
Studies published to date have focused principally on 
the role of cortisol metabolism in the pathogenesis of 
obesity rather than that of insulin resistance. We have 
performed a detailed clinical study in a large cohort of 
obese patients exploring the concept that cortisol metab-
olism is an important regulator of insulin sensitivity and 
that this may be independent of fat mass. We have 
hypothesized that decreased local glucocorticoid availabil-
ity (through decreased 11␤-HSD1 and/or increased A-ring 
reductase activity) will represent a novel physiological </p>

<p>adaptive response to preserve insulin sensitivity in a 
cohort of patients predisposed to the development of 
insulin resistance, IGT, and type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>The study was approved by the South Birmingham Local Research Ethics 
Committee, and all subjects gave informed, written consent. A total of 101 
obese volunteers (35 male, 66 female, mean age Ϯ SD 48 Ϯ 7 years, mean BMI 
34.4 Ϯ 4.3 kg/m 
2 ) were recruited following local advertisement and underwent 
the clinical protocol described below. Patients had no significant past medical 
history, and none had received glucocorticoid therapy (oral, topical, or 
inhaled) within the last 12 months. All patients had normal blood counts and 
renal function. 
Subjects were investigated in the fasting state. Blood samples were drawn 
at 9 A.M. for measurement of total cholesterol, triglycerides, cortisol, corti-
sone, glucose, insulin, and A1C. Measurements of BMI, waist circumference 
(measured supine, at the level of the umbilicus), hip circumference (at the 
level of the greater trochanter), and blood pressure (average of three readings, 
measured supine after 10 min rest using Dynamap [Critikon, Tampa, FL]) were 
also taken. Patients underwent a standard 75-g oral glucose tolerance test, 
with samples taken at 30-min intervals for 120 min for measurement of insulin 
and glucose. 
In the fasting state, all patients had an abdominal subcutaneous adipose 
tissue biopsy (10 -15 cm lateral to the umbilicus) performed under local 
anesthetic (1-2 ml of 1% lidocaine) in order to obtain ϳ250 -500 mg of adipose 
tissue. The sample was immediately placed in RNALater (Ambion, Austin, TX) 
and, after initial storage for 24 h at room temperature, was stored at Ϫ20°C for 
subsequent total RNA extraction, reverse transcription, and real-time PCR 
analysis. 
In addition, all patients performed a 24-h urine collection for corticosteroid 
metabolite analysis (20). Body composition analysis was performed using 
dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry (DEXA) with a total body scanner (QDR 
45OO; Hologic, Bedford, MA). Coefficients of variation (CVs) for multiple </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Clinical and serum biochemical characteristics of obese men and women with normal or IGT </p>

<p>Women 
Men 
Normal 
IGT 
P 
Normal 
IGT 
P </p>

<p>n 
48 
15 
17 
12 
Age (years) 
48 Ϯ 7 
4 6Ϯ 8 
0.39 
48 Ϯ 8 
5 3 Ϯ 8 
0.11 
Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
124 Ϯ 17 
127 Ϯ 12 
0.52 
135 Ϯ 16* 
139 Ϯ 22 
0.60 
Diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 
72 Ϯ 11 
76 Ϯ 12 
0.28 
80 Ϯ 14* 
79 Ϯ 10 
0.88 
Anthropometry 
BMI (kg/m 
2 ) 
34.3 Ϯ 4.4 
36.4 Ϯ 3.8 
0.09 
33.4 Ϯ 5.1 
34.7 Ϯ 3.9 
0.47 
Waist circumference (cm) 
103 Ϯ 9.0 
111 Ϯ 9 
0.002 
114 Ϯ 13 
116 Ϯ 10 
0.57 
WHR 
0.87 Ϯ 0.05 
0.90 Ϯ 0.05 
0.05 
0.98 Ϯ 0.07 † 
0.99 Ϯ 0.04 † 
0.46 
Serum biochemistry 
Fasting glucose (mmol/l) 
4.6 Ϯ 0.6 
5.0 Ϯ 0.4 
0.02 
4.8 Ϯ 0.5 
5.4 Ϯ 0.6* 
0.009 
2-h glucose (mmol/l) 
6.0 Ϯ 1.0 
8.8 Ϯ 0.9 
Ͻ0.001 
5.4 Ϯ 1.4* 
9.2 Ϯ 1.5 
Ͻ0.001 
Fasting insulin (IU/l) 
10.0 Ϯ 7.2 
12.3 Ϯ 6.3 
0.27 
8.7 Ϯ 3.9 
12.1 Ϯ 7.2 
0.12 
2-h insulin (IU/l) 
97.8 Ϯ 66.0 
128 Ϯ 58.0 
0.12 
52.0 Ϯ 40.9* 
97.6 Ϯ 56.7 
0.02 
AUC insulin (IU ⅐ l 
Ϫ1 ⅐ h 
Ϫ1 ) 
167.6 Ϯ 91.8 
173.7 Ϯ 67.6 
0.81 
162.6 Ϯ 75.5 
158.9 Ϯ 107.6 
0.92 
A1C (%) 
5.4 Ϯ 0.5 
5.7 Ϯ 0.4 
0.08 
5.3 Ϯ 0.3 
5.9 Ϯ 0.9 
0.03 
HOMA-%B 
141.6 Ϯ 52.2 
143.5 Ϯ 52.6 
0.90 
119.2 Ϯ 32.6 
118.9 Ϯ 44.9 
0.98 
HOMA-%S 
104.6 Ϯ 71.5 
78.2 Ϯ 61.8 
0.20 
101.5 Ϯ 60.1 
75.7 Ϯ 42.1 
0.20 
HOMA-R 
1.5 Ϯ 1.0 
1.8 Ϯ 0.9 
0.25 
1.3 Ϯ 0.6 
1.3 Ϯ 1.1 
0.10 
Total cholesterol (mmol/l) 
5.0 Ϯ 1.0 
5.3 Ϯ 1.0 
0.29 
5.3 Ϯ 0.9 
5.0 Ϯ 0.7 
0.48 
Triglycerides (mmol/l) 
1.3 Ϯ 0.6 
1.6 Ϯ 0.6 
0.11 
2.0 Ϯ 1.8* 
1.7 Ϯ 0.8 
0.57 
Cortisol (nmol/l) 
216 Ϯ 103 
204 Ϯ 102 
0.70 
320 Ϯ 163 ‡ 
239 Ϯ 80 
0.12 
Cortisone (nmol/l) 
64 Ϯ 26 
55 Ϯ 22 
0.30 
66 Ϯ 20 
73 Ϯ 19* 
0.42 
Body composition (DEXA) 
Trunk fat mass (kg) 
19.5 Ϯ 5.0 
21.7 Ϯ 4.3 
0.14 
16.8 Ϯ 4.7 
19.2 Ϯ 4.8 
0.22 
Trunk fat-free mass (kg) 
25.2 Ϯ 3.2 
26.1 Ϯ 4.3 
0.39 
34.6 Ϯ 4.4 † 
35.7 Ϯ 3.9 † 
0.50 
Total fat mass (kg) 
38.8 Ϯ 9.2 
41.7 Ϯ 9.3 
0.30 
29.9 Ϯ 7.7 † 
34.4 Ϯ 8.9 ‡ 
0.17 
Total fat-free mass (kg) 
48.6 Ϯ 5.7 
50.2 Ϯ 8.4 
0.39 
66.9 Ϯ 8.1 † 
68.7 Ϯ 7.3 † 
0.54 
Total % fat 
43.0 Ϯ 4.3 
44.1 Ϯ 5.0 
0.41 
29.7 Ϯ 4.2 † 
32.2 Ϯ 5.6 † 
0.21 
Trunk fat-to-limb fat ratio 
1.1 Ϯ 0.2 
1.2 Ϯ 0.3 
0.09 
1.4 Ϯ 0.14 † 
1.4 Ϯ 0.23 
0.71 </p>

<p>Data are means Ϯ SD unless otherwise indicated. *P Ͻ 0.05;  †P Ͻ 0.0001;  ‡P Ͻ 0.01 vs. women. </p>

<p>J.W. TOMLINSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
scans were Ͻ3%. Regional fat mass (trunk and leg) was analyzed as previously 
described (21). 
Biochemical assays. Blood counts, urea, creatinine and electrolytes, choles-
terol, triglycerides, liver chemistry, glucose, and A1C were measured using 
standard laboratory methods (Roche Modular system; Roche, Lewes, U.K.). 
Insulin was measured using a commercially available colorimetric ELISA 
(Mercodia, Uppsala, Sweden) with an in-house CV of Ͻ5%. Cortisol was 
measured using a coat-a-count radioimmunoassay (Diagnostic Products, Los 
Angeles, CA) as per the manufacturer's guidelines. Cortisone was assayed 
after extraction from serum followed by radioimmunoassay of the extract 
with 
125 I-cortisone and Sac-Cel (IDS, Tyne and Weir, U.K.) second antibody 
separation (22). The CV for 10 consecutive assays was Ͻ15% for values 
between 50 and 100 nmol/l and Ͻ10% for values over 100 nmol/l. 
Calculated measures of pancreatic ␤-cell function and insulin resistance 
were made using the homeostasis model assessment (HOMA) 2 model (23). 
The HOMA of ␤-cell function (HOMA %B) values provide an index of 
pancreatic islet ␤-cell function relative to a normal individual with a value set 
at 100%. Similarly, HOMA of insulin sensitivity (HOMA %S) values represent a 
measure of insulin sensitivity relative to a normal individual, again with a 
value of 100%. The HOMA of insulin resistance is a reciprocal measure of the 
%S values. 
Urinary corticosteroid metabolites. Urinary corticosteroid metabolite 
analysis was performed by gas chromatography/mass spectrometry (GC/MS) 
as described previously (20). The sum of total cortisol metabolites (tetrahy-
drocortisol [THF ], tetrahydrocortisone [THE], 5␣-THF, ␣-cortolone, cortisone 
[E], cortisol [F], ␤-cortolone, ␤-cortol, and ␣-cortol) provides a reflection of 
cortisol secretion rate. The ratio of tetrahydrometabolites of cortisol (THF ϩ 
5␣THF) to those of cortisone (THE) provides a reflection of 11␤-HSD1 activity 
when considered with the ratio of urinary free cortisol to cortisone, which 
more accurately reflects renal 11␤-HSD2 activity (20). The ratios of cortols to 
cortolones and of 11␤-hydroxy-etiocholanolone and 11␤-hydroxy-andros-
terone combined to 11oxo-etiocholanolone also reflect 11␤-HSD1 activity 
(24). The activities of 5␣-and 5␤-reductases can be inferred from measuring 
the ratio of 5␣ THF to THF and androsterone to etiocholanolone. 
RNA extraction and reverse transcription. Following subcutaneous adi-
pose tissue biopsy, total RNA was extracted using a single-step extraction 
method (Magmax 96; Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA) as per the </p>

<p>manufacturer's guidelines. RNA integrity and quantity were assessed using a 
Nanodrop spectrophotometer (Wilmington, DE). 
One microgram of total RNA was initially denatured by heating to 70°C for 
5 min. Thirty units of avian myeloblastososis virus, 200 ng of random primers, 
20 units of ribonuclease inhibitor, and 40 nmol of deoxy-nucleoside triphos-
phates with 5ϫ reaction buffer were added to the RNA, and the reverse 
transcriptase reaction was carried out at 37°C for 1 h. The reaction was 
terminated by heating the cDNA to 95°C for 5 min. 
Real-time PCR. mRNA levels of genes of interest were determined using an 
ABI 7500 sequence detection system (Perkin-Elmer and Applied Biosystems, 
Warrington, U.K.). Reactions were performed in 25-l volumes on 96-well 
plates in reaction buffer containing 2ϫ TaqMan Universal PCR Master mix 
(Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA). Probes and primers for all genes were 
supplied by assay on demand (Applied Biosystems). All reactions were 
normalized against the housekeeping gene 18S rRNA, provided as a preopti-
mized control probe. 
Data were measured as the cycle number at which logarithmic PCR plots 
cross a calculated threshold line (CT) and used to determine ⌬CT values 
[(⌬CT of the target gene) Ϫ (⌬CT of the housekeeping gene). Data were 
expressed as arbitrary units (AU) using the following transformation: expres-
sion ϭ 10 
5 ϫ (2 
Ϫ⌬CT ) AU. 
Statistical analysis. Data are presented as means Ϯ SE unless otherwise 
stated. Area under the curve (AUC) analysis was performed using the 
trapezoidal method. For comparison of single variables, t tests have been used 
(or nonparametric equivalents where data were not normally distributed). 
Regression analyses were performed using Pearson correlations; where more 
than one variable was considered, multiple linear regression analysis was 
used. All analysis was performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">SigmaStat</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">3.1</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Systat Software</rs>, Point 
Richmond, CA). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>A total of 101 (66 women and 35 men) volunteers were 
recruited into the study; 48 women (72.7%) and 17 men 
(48.6%) had normal fasting glucose levels and normal 
glucose tolerance. Two women (3.0%) and three men </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Urinary corticosteroid metabolite analysis performed by GC/MS on 24-h urine samples from 73 obese volunteers divided by sex and 
glucose tolerance </p>

<p>Women 
Men 
Normal 
IGT 
P 
Normal 
IGT 
P </p>

<p>n 
35 
11 
14 
12 
Corticosteroid metabolite production (g/24h) 
Total glucocorticoid metabolites 
7,453 Ϯ 2,693 9,964 Ϯ 4,741 0.03 13,743 Ϯ 3,229* 16,871 Ϯ 7,619 † 0.17 
Total cortisol metabolites (Fm) 
3,088 Ϯ 1,230 3,933 Ϯ 2,103 0.10 
5,481 Ϯ 1,484* 
6,679 Ϯ 2,911 † 0.19 
Total cortisone metabolites (Em) 
4,364 Ϯ 1,697 6,031 Ϯ 2,702 0.02 
8,263 Ϯ 1,971* 10,192 Ϯ 4,833 † 0.18 
THF 
1,440 Ϯ 958 
1,756 Ϯ 910 
0.32 
2,387 Ϯ 481 ‡ 
2,757 Ϯ 1,346 † 0.34 
5␣THF 
1,087 Ϯ 597 
1,382 Ϯ 929 
0.21 
1,997 Ϯ 1,176 ‡ 
2,553 Ϯ 1,395 † 0.27 
THE 
2,777 Ϯ 1,670 3,677 Ϯ 1,720 0.12 
5,183 Ϯ 1,562* 
6,274 Ϯ 3,421 † 0.29 
UFF 
56 Ϯ 76 
48 Ϯ 22 
0.74 
80 Ϯ 29 
98 Ϯ 40 ‡ 
0.20 
UFE 
79 Ϯ 37 
83 Ϯ 35 
0.72 
127 Ϯ 43* 
152 Ϯ 71 ‡ 
0.27 
␣-cortol 
303 Ϯ 155 
351 Ϯ 179 
0.37 
415 Ϯ 112 † 
535 Ϯ 185 † 
0.05 
␤-Cortol 
379 Ϯ 183 
395 Ϯ 157 
0.79 
603 Ϯ 232 ‡ 
737 Ϯ 366 ‡ 
0.26 
␣-Cortolone 
1,243 Ϯ 516 
1,612 Ϯ 729 
0.06 
1,908 Ϯ 534* 
2,499 Ϯ 830 ‡ 
0.04 
␤-Cortolone 
524 Ϯ 278 
659 Ϯ 328 
0.17 
1,046 Ϯ 280* 
1,267 Ϯ 697 † 
0.28 
Androsterone 
1,054 Ϯ 746 
1,371 Ϯ 1,009 0.25 
2,246 Ϯ 900* 
2,602 Ϯ 2,169 
0.58 
Etiocholanolone 
1,020 Ϯ 742 
1,192 Ϯ 737 
0.49 
2,075 Ϯ 1,081* 
2,296 Ϯ 1,999 
0.72 
Corticosteroid metabolite ratios 
UFF-to-UFE 
0.64 Ϯ 0.53 
0.63 Ϯ 0.25 
0.93 
0.63 Ϯ 0.11 
0.66 Ϯ 0.13 
0.48 
(THF ϩ 5␣THF)-to-THF 
0.98 Ϯ 0.39 
0.84 Ϯ 0.18 
0.24 
0.86 Ϯ 0.0.16 
0.87 Ϯ 0.19 
0.88 
Cortols-to-cortolones 
0.39 Ϯ 0.1 
0.33 Ϯ 0.05 
0.06 
0.35 Ϯ 0.07 
0.34 Ϯ 0.09 
0.94 
(11OH-and ϩ 11OH-etio)-to-11oxo-etio 
3.17 Ϯ 2.0 
3.38 Ϯ 1.87 
0.76 
3.23 Ϯ 1.18 
2.83 Ϯ 1.29 
0.41 
Fm-to-Em 
0.73 Ϯ 0.23 
0.64 Ϯ 0.12 
0.21 
0.67 Ϯ 0.12 
0.66 Ϯ 0.12 
0.92 
Androsterone-to-etiocholanolone 
1.15 Ϯ 0.55 
1.14 Ϯ 0.43 
0.99 
1.27 Ϯ 0.58 
1.24 Ϯ 0.47 
0.89 
5␣THF-to-THF 
0.84 Ϯ 0.41 
0.76 Ϯ 0.26 
0.53 
0.84 Ϯ 0.45 
0.97 Ϯ 0.41 
0.47 </p>

<p>Data are means Ϯ SD. UFF, urinary free cortisol; UFE, urinary free cortisone; 11OH-and, 11hydroxyandrosterone; 11OH-etio, 11hydroxye-
tiocholanolone; 11oxo-etio, 11oxo-etiocholanolone; Fm, cortisol ϩ THF ϩ 5␣THF ϩ ␣-cortol ϩ ␤-cortol; Em, cortisone ϩ THE ϩ 
␣-cortolone ϩ ␤-cortolone. *P Ͻ 0.0001;  †P Ͻ 0.05;  ‡P Ͻ 0.01 vs. women. </p>

<p>INSULIN RESISTANCE AND STEROID METABOLISM </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>(8.6%) had impaired fasting glucose (IFG) (Ͼ5.6 mmol/l), 
and within this group, two men and no women had IGT. 
IGT with normal fasting glucose concentrations was ob-
served in 15 women (22.7%) and 10 men (28.6%). Type 2 
diabetes was diagnosed in two women (3.0%) and five men 
(14.3%), and all subjects with type 2 diabetes had IFG. 
Taking into account the sexual dimorphism described in 
body composition and glucocorticoid metabolite produc-
tion rates, subsequent analysis was performed separately 
in men and women. 
Normal glucose tolerance versus IGT and IFG. IGT 
was associated with increased waist circumference (103 Ϯ 
1.3 vs. 111 Ϯ 2 cm, P Ͻ 0.002) and waist-to-hip ratio (WHR) 
(0.87 Ϯ 0.01 vs. 0.90 Ϯ 0.01, P Ͻ 0.05) in women but not in 
men (waist circumference 114 Ϯ 3 vs. 116 Ϯ 3 cm, P ϭ 
0.57; WHR 0.98 Ϯ 0.02 vs. 0.99 Ϯ 0.01, P ϭ 0.46). 
A1C was increased in both men and women with IGT, 
although this only reached statistical significance in men 
(men 5.3 Ϯ 0.1 vs. 5.9 Ϯ 0.3%, P Ͻ 0.05; women 5.4 Ϯ 0.1 
vs. 5.7 Ϯ 0.1%, P ϭ 0.08). Surprisingly, measures of insulin 
resistance (HOMA-R, fasting and 2-h insulin concentra-
tions) were not different between groups (Table 1). Fur-
thermore, body composition analysis by DEXA failed to 
show differences in fat-free mass or total or regional fat 
mass between those patients with normal glucose toler-
ance or IGT (Table 1). Although men and women were not 
different in terms of insulin resistance (as measured by 
HOMA, fasting insulin, 2-h insulin or insulin AUC across 
the 75-g OGTT, percent trunk fat and absolute total and 
trunk fat mass were higher in women with correspond-
ingly lower fat-free masses (Table 1). </p>

<p>Urinary steroid metabolite analysis by GC/MS demon-
strated clear sexual dimorphism with increased total and 
individual glucocorticoid metabolite production rates in 
men compared with women for subjects with and without 
IGT (Table 2). When analyzed according to glucose toler-
ance, total glucocorticoid production rates were higher in 
women with IGT compared with women with normal 
glucose tolerance (10,133 Ϯ 1,488 vs. 7,453 Ϯ 469, respec-
tively, P Ͻ 0.05), but this relationship was not observed in 
men (16,871 Ϯ 2,113 vs. 13,743 Ϯ 863, respectively, P ϭ 
0.17). Furthermore, there were no differences in absolute 
production rates for individual metabolites or activities of 
metabolizing enzymes (in particular 11␤-HSD1 or 5␣R) 
when comparing normal and IGT subjects (Table 2). 
Adipose tissue biopsy gene expression. Successful 
isolation of total RNA and generation of cDNA from 
subcutaneous adipose tissue biopsies was achieved in 90 
volunteers. All samples expressed 11␤-HSD1, H6PDH, GR, 
and 5␣R1. In contrast, 5␣R2 was only expressed in 5 of 90 
samples and only at very low levels (data not shown). 
Whereas 11␤-HSD1, GR, and 5␣R1 mRNA expression 
levels were similar in men and women, H6PDH expression 
was higher in biopsies from male volunteers (2.3 Ϯ 0.4 vs. 
1.6 Ϯ 0.5 AU, P Ͻ 0.05). 
In women only, adipose tissue 11␤-HSD1 expression 
was higher in those with IGT than in those with normal 
glucose tolerance (0.5 Ϯ 0.06 vs. 0.29 Ϯ 0.03 AU, P Ͻ 
0.005), despite fat mass (total and regional) being similar 
between the two groups (Fig. 1A). Moreover, expression 
correlated with glucose AUC across the OGTT (R ϭ 0.44, 
P Ͻ 0.005) (Fig. 1B) but not with fat mass (total fat mass </p>

<p>5 
0 
1 
0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 
1.2 
0 
1 
0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 
1.2 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Adipose 11?-HSD1 mRNA 
expression (AU) </p>

<p>Glucose AUC (mmol/L.h) </p>

<p>R=0.44 
p&lt;0.001 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>Adipose mRNA 
expression (AU) </p>

<p>p=0.002 </p>

<p>p=0.02 </p>

<p>11?-HSD1 
GR 
5?R1 
H6PDH </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>3.5 </p>

<p>11?-HSD1 
GR 
5?R1 
H6PDH </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 
R=0.19 
p=ns </p>

<p>Glucose AUC (mmol/L.h) </p>

<p>Adipose 11?-HSD1 mRNA 
expression (AU) </p>

<p>Adipose mRNA 
expression (AU) </p>

<p>FIG. 1. In women only, IGT is associated with increased adipose tissue 11␤-HSD1 but decreased H6PDH mRNA expression (A) without alteration 
in fat mass; 11␤-HSD1 mRNA levels correlate with glucose AUC across an OGTT (B). However, in men with IGT, adipose 11␤-HSD1, H6PDH, GR, 
and 5␣R1 mRNA expression is not dysregulated (C and D). Ⅺ, normal glucose tolerance; f, IGT. </p>

<p>J.W. TOMLINSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
R ϭ 0.12, P ϭ NS; trunk fat mass R ϭ 0.15, P ϭ NS). 
H6PDH expression was lower in female volunteers with 
IGT (0.79 Ϯ 0.1 vs. 1.38 Ϯ 0.14 AU, P Ͻ 0.05), but GR and 
5␣R1 expression did not differ (Fig. 1A). In contrast to our 
findings in women, expression of 11␤-HSD1, H6PDH, GR, 
and 5␣R1 in adipose tissue biopsies from men did not 
differ between those with and those without IGT and did 
not relate to glucose levels across an OGTT (Fig. 1C 
and D). 
Regression analyses. Univariate regression analysis re-
vealed positive relationships between 5␣R activity (as 
measured by both the urinary androsterone-to-etiochol-
anolone and 5␣THF-to-THF ratios) and markers of insulin 
resistance. In women, significant correlations were ob-
served with fasting insulin, 2-h insulin levels after 75 g oral 
glucose, AUC insulin across the OGTT, and HOMA-R 
(Table 3 and Fig. 2A-D). In men, a similar pattern was 
observed (Table 3; Fig. 2A-D), but in addition, increased 
5␣R activity was associated with decreased pancreatic 
␤-cell function as calculated from the HOMA-%B (Table 3). 
Activity of 5␣R increased with increasing total and 
regional fat and fat-free mass in men but not in women 
(Table 3). While these relationships remained significant, 
they were weaker than those observed with markers of 
insulin resistance. There was no relationship in either sex 
with fat distribution as measured by waist circumference, 
WHR, or the trunk fat-to-limb fat ratio via DEXA. 
Total glucocorticoid secretion rate increased with total 
and regional fat and fat-free mass in women but not in men 
and was weakly associated with 2-h insulin concentration 
after 75 g oral glucose (Table 4). Global 11␤-HSD1 activity 
as measured by the 5␣ THF ϩ THF-to-THE ratio was 
unrelated to metabolic or anthropometric variables in 
women and only weakly related to HOMA-R in men (R ϭ </p>

<p>0.38, P ϭ 0.04). 11␤-HSD2 inactivates cortisol to cortisone 
in mineralocorticoid target tissues, notably the kidney. 
Activity is reflected in the ratio of urinary free cortisol to 
cortisone. This was unrelated to metabolic parameters 
with the exception of 2-h insulin levels in men only (R ϭ 
0.389, P ϭ 0.03) and inversely related to WHR in women 
only (R ϭ Ϫ0.30, P ϭ 0.04). 
Using multivariate modeling to correct for total and 
regional fat mass, 5␣R activity remained an independent 
predictor of insulin secretion across the OGTT (2-h insulin 
P Ͻ 0.005; insulin AUC P Ͻ 0.005) in women. In men, 5␣R 
activity and not fat mass independently predicted fasting 
insulin levels (P Ͻ 0.05), HOMA-%B (P Ͻ 0.05), HOMA-%S 
(P Ͻ 0.05), and HOMA-R (P Ͻ 0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In this unselected cohort of obese patients, we have 
identified the prevalence of IGT to be 22.7% in women and 
34.2% in men and the prevalence of type 2 diabetes to be 
3.0% in women and 14.3% in men. This was associated with 
central fat distribution (but not absolute fat mass) in 
women and unrelated to fat mass or distribution in men. 
In this cohort, subcutaneous adipose tissue 11␤-HSD1 
mRNA expression was higher in women with IGT and 
correlated with glucose secretion across the OGTT but 
was unrelated to fat mass, consistent with our previous 
observations (25). Previous studies have examined 11␤-
HSD1 mRNA expression and activity in adipose tissue in 
the context of fat mass with variable results. Within the 
subcutaneous depot, most studies, although not all, have 
suggested increased expression with indexes of obesity 
(25-29), but relative expression within the intra-abdominal 
depot remains controversial. Importantly, the expression 
of 11␤-HSD1 in adipose tissue and its relationship with </p>

<p>TABLE 3  Correlation of metabolic parameters with 5␣-reductase activity as assessed by the urinary 5␣THF-to-THF and androsterone-to-
etiocholanolone ratios analyzed by GC/MS </p>

<p>Women (n ϭ 49) 
Men (n ϭ 30) 
Androsterone-to-
etiocholanolone ratio 
5␣THF-to-THF ratio </p>

<p>Androsterone-to-
etiocholanolone ratio 
5␣THF-to-THF ratio 
Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Insulin sensitivity and glucose 
tolerance 
Fasting glucose 
0.082 
0.58 
0.065 
0.66 
0.26 
0.17 
0.22 
0.26 
2-h glucose 
0.14 
0.35 
0.13 
0.37 
0.13 
0.51 
0.81 
0.67 
Fasting insulin 
0.33 
0.022 
0.27 
0.07 
0.53 
0.003 
0.50 
0.006 
2-h insulin 
0.51 
0.0002 
0.51 
0.0002 
0.14 
0.48 
0.35 
0.06 
AUC insulin 
0.38 
0.007 
0.40 
0.004 
0.31 
0.10 
0.46 
0.01 
A1C 
Ϫ0.11 
0.47 
Ϫ0.09 
0.58 
0.39 
0.04 
0.14 
0.47 
HOMA-%B 
0.26 
0.07 
0.22 
0.13 
0.47 
0.01 
0.55 
0.003 
HOMA-%S 
Ϫ0.27 
0.06 
Ϫ0.23 
0.11 
Ϫ0.43 
0.02 
Ϫ0.53 
0.003 
HOMA-R 
0.33 
0.02 
0.26 
0.07 
0.52 
0.004 
0.49 
0.008 
Anthropometry 
BMI 
0.14 
0.35 
Ϫ0.02 
0.87 
0.28 
0.13 
0.32 
0.08 
Waist circumference 
0.15 
0.33 
0.02 
0.90 
0.03 
0.89 
0.14 
0.46 
WHR 
0.09 
0.56 
0.16 
0.27 
0.09 
0.62 
0.05 
0.81 
Body composition (DEXA) 
Trunk fat mass 
0.06 
0.67 
Ϫ0.04 
0.78 
0.44 
0.02 
0.46 
0.01 
Trunk fat-free mass 
0.11 
0.45 
Ϫ0.006 
0.97 
0.41 
0.03 
0.41 
0.03 
Total fat mass 
0.02 
0.90 
Ϫ0.10 
0.51 
0.36 
0.06 
0.38 
0.04 
Total fat-free mass 
0.09 
0.56 
Ϫ0.02 
0.87 
0.493 
0.008 
0.43 
0.02 
Total % fat 
Ϫ0.02 
0.89 
Ϫ0.07 
0.62 
0.18 
0.37 
0.24 
0.23 
Trunk fat-to-limb fat ratio 
0.10 
0.51 
0.10 
0.52 
0.27 
0.17 
0.26 
0.18 </p>

<p>INSULIN RESISTANCE AND STEROID METABOLISM </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>insulin resistance and glucose tolerance has not been 
examined before. While expression studies were only 
performed in subcutaneous adipose tissue, enhanced cor-
tisol generation through increased 11␤-HSD1 mRNA ex-
pression may contribute to glucose intolerance through 
increased lipolysis (30,31) and generation of free fatty 
acids, which impair peripheral glucose uptake (32). How-
ever, due to the small volumes of tissue obtained, activity 
studies were not performed and it is possible that de-
creased H6PDH expression that we also observed in the 
IGT group may decrease 11␤-HSD1 oxo-reductase activity 
by limiting cofactor supply. 
Sexually dimorphic activity and expression of 11␤-HSD1 
has been described in some studies (33) but not all (34). In 
our cohort, urinary GC/MS analysis was similar in men and 
women. Studies examining sex-specific regulation of ex-
pression within adipose tissue are lacking. In nonadipose 
tissue, estradiol has been shown to regulate expression 
levels, and it is possible that this may contribute to our 
observations; however, the published data are often con-
tradictory with studies showing both increased and de-
creased expression (35-38). With the exception of 
dehydroepiandrosterone (39), there is little evidence to 
support a role for regulation by androgens (35,38). Sexu-
ally dimorphic expression of H6PDH has not been de-
scribed previously, and the observed increase in 
expression in men will need to be endorsed with dedicated 
activity studies to see if changes in H6PDH expression 
translate into alterations in glucocorticoid availability. 
However, it is possible that this could contribute to 
differences in fat distribution between men and women, 
with the consequent increase in cardiovascular risk (40). </p>

<p>In our study, in both sexes, 5␣R activity as measured by 
urinary glucocorticoid metabolite ratios increased with 
indexes of insulin resistance, an observation that was 
independent of fat mass. The role of 5␣R in the control of 
body composition and insulin sensitivity has not been 
explored in detail in the published literature. The global 
measures of activity that we have used in this study do not 
allow us to distinguish between 5␣R1 and 5␣R2, and 
whereas patients with 5␣R2 mutations have clear evidence 
of abnormal hepatic cortisol metabolism (41), the contri-
bution of 5␣R1 is yet to be clarified. Sexual dimorphism of 
5␣R activity has been described with increased activity in 
male subjects (10,34). In our study, absolute levels of 5␣-
and 5␤-reduced metabolites were higher in men (as was 
total glucocorticoid production rate), but the relative 
balance of 5␣R and 5␤R activity was not different. Fur-
thermore, 5␣R1 mRNA expression in subcutaneous adi-
pose tissue was similar in men and women. Studies in 
small cohorts of patients have shown enhanced 5␣R 
activity with obesity (42) and type 2 diabetes (43) and 
regulation of 5␣R and 5␤R activity by dietary macro-
nutrient composition; high-fat, low-carbohydrate and 
moderate-fat, moderate-carbohydrate diets decrease 
5␣R and 5␤R activity in the context of weight loss (44). 
Thiazolidinedione treatment of obese Zü cker rats de-
creases 5␣R1 expression in the liver (45), but similar 
experiments in humans have not been performed. How-
ever, we have recently shown that following weight loss 
with consequent insulin sensitization, 5␣R activity de-
creased (46). 5␣R has been implicated in the pathogen-
esis of the insulin resistance associated with PCOS, in 
that patients with PCOS are more insulin resistant </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>0 
0 . 5 
1 
1 . 5 
2 
0 
0 . 5 
1 
1.5 
2 </p>

<p>0 
0 . 5 
1 
1.5 
2 
0 
0 . 5 
1 
1.5 
2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 
Fasting insulin (mU/L) 
2h insulin (mU/L) </p>

<p>Insulin AUC (mU/.h) </p>

<p>5αTHF / THF ratio </p>

<p>HOMA IR </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>C 
D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>5αTHF / THF ratio </p>

<p>5αTHF / THF ratio 
5αTHF / THF ratio </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>Women 
Men </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Increasing 5␣-reductase activity is associated with increased insulin secretion across an OGTT in men (F) and women (Ⅺ)-fasting insulin 
(A), 2-h insulin (B), area under curve insulin (C), and increased insulin resistance as measured by HOMA-IR (D). </p>

<p>J.W. TOMLINSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
compared with body composition-matched control sub-
jects (4) and have increased 5␣R activity (47). More-
over, within a cohort of patients with PCOS, 5␣R 
activity correlates with insulin resistance (48). Our 
findings are consistent with these data and extend this 
observation to healthy obese women and men, as well as 
demonstrate that the relationship (in both sexes) is 
independent of fat mass. In the context of insulin 
resistance, we postulate that increased 5␣R activity 
represents a compensatory mechanism to decrease lo-
cal glucocorticoid availability and occurs in conjunction 
with the decrease in 11␤-HSD1 activity (as evidenced by 
reduced cortisol generation following oral cortisone 
administration and decreased urinary 5␣-ϩ THF-to-
THE ratios) that we and others have previously de-
scribed in obesity (22,26). These processes act together 
(decreased generation of cortisol through a reduction in 
11␤-HSD1 and increased inactivation of cortisol through 
enhanced 5␣R activity) to decrease local glucocorticoid 
availability and decrease GR activation specifically 
within the liver, with the aim of maintenance of hepatic 
insulin sensitivity. A further impact of these changes 
will be to drive the hypothalamo-pituitary-adrenal axis 
in order to maintain circulating cortisol levels. While we 
believe that the changes that we have observed largely 
reflect hepatic glucocorticoid metabolism, a direct ef-
fect upon insulin secretion cannot be excluded. How-
ever, this remains highly speculative, bearing in mind 
that evidence of A-ring reductase expression in human 
pancreatic islets is lacking. 
Pharmacological manipulation of glucocorticoid avail-
ability through prereceptor metabolism adds credence to 
our observations. Selective 11␤-HSD1 inhibitors that de-
crease local glucocorticoid availability remain an exciting </p>

<p>therapeutic prospect. Significant improvements in insulin 
sensitivity, glucose tolerance, and lipid profiles following 
short-term administration in rodents and primates have 
been observed. Human clinical studies are still eagerly 
awaited. Conversely, Finasteride (5␣R2 inhibitor) and 
Dutasteride (combined 5␣R1 and 5␣R2 inhibitor) are 
widely used in the treatment of prostatic hypertrophy (49)  based upon their action upon androgen metabolism. How-
ever, by decreasing glucocorticoid inactivation, they may 
have a detrimental impact upon insulin sensitivity, but the 
studies to address this question have not been performed. 
In conclusion, this study adds to the growing body of 
evidence that supports a role for 5␣R in the control of 
insulin sensitivity in simple obesity. While little is cur-
rently known about the regulation of 5␣R activity, limiting 
local glucocorticoid availability through enhanced 5␣R 
and/or inhibition of 11␤-HSD1 activity may have significant 
clinical benefits. Finally, prospective studies examining 
the changes in activity and expression of these enzymes 
over time may begin to shed light on their potential role in 
the development of IGT and type 2 diabetes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was funded by the Wellcome Trust (program 
grant to P.M.S., ref. 066357/Z/01/Z, and clinician scientist 
fellowship to J.W.T., ref. 075322/Z/04/Z) and the Medical 
Research Council (experimental medicine initiative, ref. 
G0502165). 
We thank all the nursing staff on the Wellcome Trust 
Clinical Research facility, Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Bir-
mingham where this study took place. </p>



<p>TABLE 4 
Correlation of metabolic parameters with glucocorticoid secretion rate and 11␤-HSD1 activity (as measured by the urinary 5␣THF ϩ 
THF-to-THE ratio) analyzed by GC/MS </p>

<p>Women (n ϭ 49) 
Men (n ϭ 30) 
Total glucocorticoid 
secretion rate </p>

<p>(5␣THF ϩ 
THF)-to-THF ratio </p>

<p>Total glucocorticoid 
secretion rate </p>

<p>(5␣THF ϩ 
THF)-to-THF ratio 
Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Correlation 
coefficient (R) 
P </p>

<p>Insulin sensitivity and 
glucose tolerance 
Fasting glucose 
0.06 
0.70 
Ϫ0.05 
0.74 
0.07 
0.73 
0.28 
0.14 
2-h glucose 
0.22 
0.15 
Ϫ0.01 
0.97 
Ϫ0.10 
0.59 
0.34 
0.07 
Fasting insulin 
0.25 
0.09 
Ϫ0.01 
0.95 
0.04 
0.83 
0.37 
0.05 
2-h insulin 
0.34 
0.02 
0.07 
0.64 
0.12 
0.53 
0.03 
0.88 
AUC insulin 
0.17 
0.25 
Ϫ0.08 
0.61 
0.07 
0.70 
0.01 
0.96 
A1C 
Ϫ0.00 
1.0 
Ϫ0.12 
0.47 
Ϫ0.16 
0.43 
0.45 
0.17 
HOMA-%B 
0.19 
0.20 
Ϫ0.04 
0.78 
0.08 
0.67 
0.22 
0.26 
HOMA-%S 
Ϫ0.18 
0.24 
0.10 
0.49 
Ϫ0.16 
0.42 
Ϫ0.35 
0.06 
HOMA-R 
0.25 
0.09 
Ϫ0.00 
0.98 
0.04 
0.85 
0.38 
0.04 
Anthropometry 
BMI 
0.32 
0.03 
0.13 
0.38 
0.21 
0.28 
0.14 
0.46 
Waist circumference 
0.32 
0.03 
Ϫ0.03 
0.87 
0.07 
0.73 
0.28 
0.14 
WHR 
Ϫ0.04 
0.70 
Ϫ0.18 
0.23 
Ϫ0.05 
0.78 
Ϫ0.02 
0.92 
Body composition (DEXA) 
Trunk fat mass 
0.44 
0.002 
0.05 
0.76 
0.22 
0.27 
0.35 
0.07 
Trunk fat-free mass 
0.44 
0.002 
Ϫ0.06 
0.68 
0.28 
0.15 
0.33 
0.09 
Total fat mass 
0.41 
0.006 
0.14 
0.37 
0.25 
0.20 
0.25 
0.20 
Total fat-free mass 
0.38 
0.01 
Ϫ0.06 
0.67 
0.12 
0.56 
031 
0.11 
Total % fat 
0.19 
0.20 
0.21 
0.16 
0.23 
0.23 
0.14 
0.49 
Trunk fat-to-limb fat ratio 
0.19 
0.22 
Ϫ0.23 
0.13 
Ϫ0.005 
0.98 
0.31 
0.11 </p>

<p>INSULIN RESISTANCE AND STEROID METABOLISM </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>



<p>J.W. TOMLINSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>



<p>
INSULIN RESISTANCE AND STEROID METABOLISM </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

</text></tei>