<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2532740" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:27+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Primary transcripts of certain microRNA (miRNA) 
genes (pri-miRNAs) are subject to RNA editing that 
converts adenosine to inosine (A!I RNA editing). 
However, the frequency of the pri-miRNA editing 
and the fate of edited pri-miRNAs remain largely to 
be determined. Examination of already known 
pri-miRNA editing sites indicated that adenosine 
residues of the UAG triplet sequence might be 
edited more frequently. In the present study, there-
fore, we conducted a large-scale survey of human 
pri-miRNAs containing the UAG triplet sequence. By 
direct sequencing of RT-PCR products correspond-
ing to pri-miRNAs, we examined 209 pri-miRNAs 
and identified 43 UAG and also 43 non-UAG editing 
sites in 47 pri-miRNAs, which were highly edited in 
human brain. In vitro miRNA processing assay using 
recombinant Drosha-DGCR8 and Dicer-TRBP (the 
human immuno deficiency virus transactivating 
response RNA-binding protein) complexes revealed 
that a majority of pri-miRNA editing is likely to inter-
fere with the miRNA processing steps. In addition, 
four new edited miRNAs with altered seed 
sequences were identified by targeted cloning and 
sequencing of the miRNAs that would be processed 
from edited pri-miRNAs. Our studies predict that 
16% of human pri-miRNAs are subject to A!I edit-
ing and, thus, miRNA editing could have a large 
impact on the miRNA-mediated gene silencing. </p>

<p>One type of RNA editing involves the conversion of aden-
osine residues into inosine (A!I RNA editing) specifically 
in double-stranded RNAs (dsRNAs) through the action of </p>

<p>ADAR (adensosine deaminase acting on RNA) (1-3). The 
inosine residue converted from adenosine in RNA is 
detected as an A!G change of the cDNA sequence. 
The translation machinery reads inosine as guanosine, 
leading to alterations of codons. Three separate ADAR 
gene family members (ADAR1-3) are known in mammals. 
Both ADAR1 and ADAR2 are detected in many tissues, 
whereas ADAR3 is expressed only in brain (4-10). 
Involvement of both ADAR1 and ADAR2 in site-selective 
RNA editing has been demonstrated by in vitro editing 
experiments as well as by analysis of editing site selection 
changes in ADAR1 null and ADAR2 null mutant mice 
(7,11-15). When it occurs within the protein-coding 
sequence, A!I RNA editing results in the synthesis of 
proteins not directly encoded by the genome, as demon-
strated with the glutamate receptors (GluR), the serotonin 
receptor 2C (5-HT 2C R), the Kv1.1 potassium channel, and 
the a3 GABA A receptor, leading to diversification of these 
gene functions (11,14,16-18). Misregulated RNA editing 
may underlie certain human diseases and pathological pro-
cesses. Underediting of GluR-B mRNAs at the Q/R site has 
been implicated in human amyotrophic lateral sclerosis 
(19), whereas inappropriate editing of 5-HT 2C R mRNAs 
may have causative relevance to suicide, schizophrenia and 
depression (20-23). In addition, ADAR1 heterozygous 
mutations have been identified in dyschromatosis symmet-
rica hereditaria (DSH), a human disease of aberrant skin 
pigmentation with an autosomal dominant inheritance 
(24). However, the most common targets for A!I editing 
are non-coding RNAs that contain inversely oriented 
repeats of repetitive elements such as Alu and LINE 
(25-28). The biological significance of non-coding, repeti-
tive RNA editing is largely unknown (29). 
More recently, it has been reported that primary 
transcripts of certain microRNA (miRNA) genes 
(pri-miRNAs) are subject to A!I RNA editing (30-35). 
Pri-miRNAs are processed sequentially by two members of 
the RNase III superfamily, Drosha and Dicer (36). Nuclear 
Drosha, together with its essential partner, DGCR8, </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 215 898 3828; Fax: +1 215 898 3911; Email: kazuko@wistar.org </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>cleaves pri-miRNAs, releasing 60-70 nt precursor 
miRNAs (pre-miRNAs) (37-40). Recognition of correctly 
processed pre-miRNAs and their nuclear export is carried 
out by Exportin-5 and RanGTP (41). Cytoplasmic Dicer 
together with the dsRNA binding protein TRBP then pro-
cesses the pre-miRNAs into 20-22 nt imperfect dsRNAs 
(42,43). One or both strands of the duplex may serve as 
the mature miRNA. Following integration into RISC 
(RNA-induced silencing complex), miRNAs block the 
translation of partially complementary targets located in 
the 3 
0 UTR of specific mRNAs or guide the degradation 
of target mRNAs as do siRNAs (3,36,44-46). 
The presence of the post-transcriptional mechanisms 
that regulate processing of miRNAs at the Drosha or 
Dicer cleavage step has been reported (47-50). Editing of 
pri-miRNAs could alter their processing (31,35). For 
instance, editing of pri-miR151 suppresses the Dicer cleav-
age step (31), whereas editing of pri-miR142 inhibits the 
Drosha cleavage step and consequently suppresses the 
expression of the mature miRNA levels (35). 
Furthermore, editing of pri-miRNAs could also lead to 
the expression of edited mature miRNAs (32). For 
instance, editing of pri-miR-376 cluster RNAs resulted in 
expression of sequence altered miRNAs (edited miRNAs) 
and selection of a set of target genes different from those 
targeted by the unedited miRNAs (32). 
Although several examples of pri-miRNA editing have 
been investigated (30-33,35), the frequency of the miRNA 
editing and its biological significance remains to be estab-
lished. In this study, we conducted a large-scale survey and 
identified 86 A!I editing sites in 47 pri-miRNAs. We 
tested the significance of editing of select pri-miRNAs by 
performing an in vitro miRNA processing assay. Our stu-
dies revealed that a majority of pri-miRNA editing events 
appear to affect miRNA processing steps. In addition, we 
detected abundant expression of four new edited mature 
miRNAs with altered 'seed' sequences. These edited 
mature miRNAs are likely to repress a set of genes differ-
ent from those targeted by the unedited miRNAs. Having 
established that $16% of human pri-miRNAs are edited, 
it is anticipated that the expression of a large number of 
genes is affected globally by A!I editing of miRNAs. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Extraction of the potential UAG triplet from human 
pri-miRNAs </p>

<p>The 474 human miRNA hairpin structures available in 
miRBase 9.1 were retrieved and annotated with respect 
to mature sequence location using a <rs type="software">Perl program</rs>. A 
second program parsed these annotated structures to 
extract each class of potentially edited sites. We divided 
494 UAG triplet sites in dsRNA regions of 291 pri-
miRNAs into four groups: W-C group; U and G in UAG 
triplet form Watson-Crick base pairing (201 sites in 157 
pri-miRNAs). G-U group; Either U or G, or both in UAG 
triplet forms G-U wobble base pairing (122 sites in 105 pri-
miRNAs). Mismatch group; Either U or G in UAG triplet 
forms mismatch base pairing (90 sites in 79 pri-miRNAs). 
Others group; Both U and G in UAG triplet form </p>

<p>mismatch base pairing (81 sites in 76 pri-miRNAs). We 
excluded the Others group from further analysis, because 
it is very unlikely that RNA editing happens under this 
condition. Similarly, we also counted and divided all 
non-UAG triplet sites present in 474 pri-miRNAs into 
three categories: W-C group, G-U group and Mismatch 
group in order to estimate their editing frequency (Table 9). </p>

<p>Mice </p>

<p>All procedures involving mice were approved by the 
Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of The 
Wistar Institute and performed in accordance to the US 
National Institutes of Health Guidelines. </p>

<p>RNA preparation </p>

<p>Human total brain RNA was obtained from Clontech 
(Palo Alto, CA, USA) and Ambion (Austin, TX, USA). 
Mouse total RNA was extracted from dissected total 
brains using TRIZOL reagent according to the manufac-
turer's instructions (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Determination of pri-miRNA editing </p>

<p>The method was previously described (31,32). Briefly, first-
strand cDNA was synthesized using 1 mg of total RNA and 
each miRNA-specific RT primer (Tables S1, S2 and S3). 
The resultant cDNA was then amplified by PCR using 
each miRNA-specific PCR primer pairs (Table S1, S2 
and S3). RT-PCR products were directly sequenced 
using the inward primer. If the editing frequency was 
&lt;20%, RT-PCR products were sequenced from both 
directions to exclude the possibility of background noise. 
The editing frequency was determined as the % ratio of the 
'G' peak over the sum of 'G' and 'A' peaks of the sequen-
cing chromatogram. The editing frequency was given as 
round numbers of AE5%. When editing was found in cer-
tain human pri-miRNA, the corresponding mouse pri-
miRNA was also amplified from wildtype and ADAR2 
null brains as well as wildtype and ADAR1 null embryos 
to determine the conservation and the responsible editing 
enzyme in vivo. </p>

<p>Characterization of mature miRNAs </p>

<p>Small RNA (&lt;200 nt) was extracted from 50 mg of total 
brain RNA using mirVana 
TM miRNA Isolation Kit 
(Ambion). Preparation of the cDNA library enriched in 
small RNA was described previously (31,32). Briefly, 
1.5 mg of small RNA was polyadenylated using Poly(A) 
Tailing Kit (Ambion). A 5 
0 adaptor (5 
0 -CGACUGGAG 
CACGAGGACACUGACAUGGACUGAAGGAGUA 
GAAA-3 
0 ) synthesized at Dharmacon (Lafayette, CO, 
USA) was ligated to poly(A)-tailed RNA using T4 RNA 
ligase followed by RT using an RT primer: 5 
0 -ATTCT 
AGAGGCCGAGGCGGCCGACATG-d(T)30 (A, G, or 
C) (A, G, C, or, T)-3 
0 . The resultant cDNA was then ampli-
fied by PCR using cFW primer (5 
0 -CTGACATGGA 
CTGAAGGA-3 
0 ) and each miRNA-specific DW primer 
(Table S5), or each miRNA-specific FW primer 
(Table S5) and cDW primer (5 
0 -ATTCTAGAGGCCGA 
GGCGGCCGACATGT-3 
0 ). After gel purification, </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 16 5271 </p>

<p>RT-PCR products were subcloned using the TOPO TA 
cloning kit (Invitrogen) followed by sequencing more 
than 50 cDNA isolates. </p>

<p>Analysis of in vitro edited and processed pri-, pre-and mature 
miRNAs </p>

<p>In vitro pri-miRNA processing assay was described pre-
viously (31,35). The DNA fragment encompassing each 
pri-miRNA region was amplified by PCR, and then it 
was cloned into TOPO vector (Invitrogen). Unedited 
and edited (containing 'G') versions were screened by 
sequencing. 
In vitro transcription was performed with Riboprobe 
in vitro Transcription Systems (Promega, Madison, WI, 
USA) using 1 mg of linearized TOPO vector containing 
the fragment corresponding to each pri-miRNA in the 
presence of 50 mCi [a-32P] CTP according to the manufac-
turer's instructions. The labeled pri-miRNAs were purified 
using 6% (w/v) polyacrylamide, 8 M urea gel. 
The labeled pri-miRNAs (2Â 10 
5 c.p.m.) were digested 
using 20 ng of the Drosha-DGCR8 complex at 378C for 
60 min and, in some experiments, then to the Dicer cleavage 
reaction using 20 ng of the Dicer-TRBP complex at 378C 
for 90 min. The mixture was then incubated with Proteinase 
K at 378C for 60 min and was recovered by phenol/chloro-
form extraction and ethanol precipitation. The precipitated 
RNA was loaded on 15% (w/v) polyacrylamide, 8 M urea 
gel. The radioactivity in the dried gels was quantified with 
a PhosphorImaging System (Molecular Dynamics, 
Sunnyvale, CA, USA). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Survey for A!I RNA editing of UAG triplets of pri-miRNA 
sequences </p>

<p>A!I editing of select pri-miRNAs was reported by several 
groups (30-32,34,35). By examining the editing frequency 
of the miRNA editing sites previously investigated by us 
(31,32), we noted that high-frequency editing often 
occurred at the adenosine residue within the UAG triplets 
(Table 1). The preference of the UAG triplet sequences for 
editing was reported previously in a small-scale survey of 
pri-miRNA editing sites (30) as well as statistical analysis 
of editing sites present in non-coding repetitive element 
sequences such as Alu and SINE (25-27,51). We reasoned 
that the adenosine in the UAG triplet of pri-miRNA 
sequences may be preferentially edited in vivo. The pri-
miRNA sequences containing the UAG triplet were iden-
tified in 474 human pri-miRNAs registered at the Sanger 
Center miRBase site (miRBase 9.1). Since the UAG triplets 
in single-stranded regions are unlikely to be edited by 
ADARs, we selected 494 triplets in dsRNA regions of 
291 pri-miRNAs. Among these candidates, UAG triplets 
that are mismatched at both U and G are also unlikely to 
be edited; therefore, 257 pri-miRNAs that contain 341 
UAG triplet sequences in the dsRNA region were investi-
gated. We attempted to amplify all of the 257 pri-miRNAs 
by RT-PCR, and 209 pri-miRNAs ($80%) were success-
fully amplified from the total RNAs derived from human 
brain where pri-miRNAs are edited frequently (30-32,34). </p>

<p>Direct cDNA sequencing of RT-PCR products identified 
43 UAG triplets in 38 pri-miRNAs which were edited 
with frequency higher than 10% (Tables 2, 3 and 
Table S1, S2, S3). The 38 pri-miRNAs identified to contain 
one or more UAG editing sites accounted for 18.2% of 209 
pri-miRNAs examined (Table 3). In addition, 43 non-
UAG triplet editing sites were also identified while exam-
ining editing of UAG triplets (Table 8 and Table S4). 
Among those sites, 28 sites were detected in 11 pri-
miRNAs which also contained at least a separate UAG 
triplet editing site, whereas 15 non-UAG triplet sites were 
found in 9 pri-miRNAs that did not contain the UAG 
triplet editing site (Table 3 and Table S4). </p>

<p>Expression of edited mature miRNAs </p>

<p>Many pri-miRNA editing sites were located within the 
mature miRNA sequence or corresponding partner 
miRNA sequence in the opposite strand (Table S5), 
which could be processed to edited mature miRNAs as 
we previously reported for miR-376 cluster RNAs (32). 
We applied the targeted cloning strategy as described pre-
viously (31,32), attempting to isolate cDNA clones corre-
sponding to all of these potential edited mature miRNAs. 
Only four mature miRNAs containing UAG and/or non-
UAG editing sites not previously reported were identified; 
miR-379-5p, miR-411-5p, miR-607-3p and miR-99b-3p 
(Figure 1). Interestingly, both miR-379 and miR-411 are 
members of the miR-379 cluster. Simultaneous expression 
of several edited mature miRNAs of the miR-376 cluster </p>

<p>Table 1. Known pri-miRNAs subject to A!I RNA editing </p>

<p>hsmiR-376a2 
55 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-376b 
67 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-368 
48 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-376a2 
15 
5′GGUAGAG3′ 
3′gcaccua5′ 
mmmiR-376c 
58 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-376a2 
11 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′gcaccua5′ 
mmmiR-151 
45 
5′ACUAGAC3′ 
3′ugaucug5′ 
mmmiR-376a 
9 
5′GGUAGAU3′ 
3′gcaccua5′ 
hsmiR-376a1 
9 
5′GGUAGAU3′ 
3′gcaccua5′ 
mmmiR-376b 
56 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-376a1 
49 
5′CAUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-151 
49 
5′ACUAGAC3′ 
3′ugaucug5′ 
mmmiR-376a 
5 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′uuuugca5′ 
hsmiR-368 
4 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′uuuugca5′ 
mmmiR-376b 
12 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′uuuuuca5′ 
mmmiR-376c 
14 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′uuuugca5′ 
hsmiR-376a1 
5 
5′AAAAGGU3′ 
3′uuuugca5′ 
mmmiR-151 
42 
5′CCUAGUA3′ 
3′guaugau5′ 
hsmiR-151 
46 
5′CCUAGUA3′ 
3′guaugau5′ 
hsmiR-142 
24 
5′AGUAGAA3′ 
3′ucauccu5′ 
mmmiR-376a 
49 
5′CGUAGAG3′ 
3′guaucuu5′ 
hsmiR-151 
29 
5′UCUAGUA3′ 
3′agaucau5′ 
mmmiR-151 
26 
5′UCUAGUA3′ 
3′agaucau5′ 
hsmiR-376b 
24 
5′AAAACGU3′ 
3′uuuugua5′ </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Editing 
frequency 
in brain (%) </p>

<p>Complementary 
Editing site 
Site a 
pri-miRNA </p>

<p>95 
90 
90 
70 
55 
50 
50 
50 
50 
40 
40 
25 
25 
20 
20 
15 
10 
5 
0 
0 
0 
0 
0 </p>

<p>a The 5 
0 end of the pri-miRNA sequence, registered at the Sanger Center 
miRBase site, is counted as 1. </p>



<p>has been also reported (32), indicating the possibility of 
simultaneous editing of clustered miRNAs. The A!I edit-
ing sites identified in these mature miRNAs were located 
in the seed sequence known to play a major role in the 
hybridization of a miRNA with the target site, thus affect-
ing selection of the target genes. As we have demonstrated 
for edited miR-376 RNAs (32), application of target pre-
diction programs is likely to reveal that these newly iden-
tified edited mature miRNAs target genes that are 
different from those targeted by the unedited miRNAs. 
A recent global survey for miRNAs from various 
human and mouse tissues identified a large number of 
miRNAs that had nucleotide changes within the mature 
miRNA sequence, including those already reported pre-
viously as edited miRNAs such as miR-368, miR-376a1, 
miR-376a2 (32). However, four edited miRNAs identified 
in the present study as well as those identified previously 
(hs-miR-376b, mu-miR-376a, mu-miR-376b and mu-miR-
376c) by the targeted cloning strategy were not included in 
the list of the miRNAs with A!G changes determined by 
the unbiased cloning strategy (33), indicating a limitation 
of the unbiased cloning strategy for detection of certain 
miRNA editing sites. Nevertheless, this deep sequencing 
study for unbiased expression profiling identified a 
few new miRNAs that had A!G nucleotide changes 
(potential A!I editing) at a frequency higher than 5%, 
i.e. hs-19b-2, hs-miR-512-1 and hs-miR-512-2, mu-miR-
17, mu-miR-450b and mu-miR-483 (33). We tested some 
of these miRNAs containing the A!G sequence changes 
independently to see whether they are A!I edited 
miRNAs. Through analysis of the pri-miRNA sequence 
corresponding to the mature miRNAs with A!G 
changes, we found that at least the reported sequence </p>

<p>heterogeneity of hs-miR-19b-2 and mu-miR-17 is not 
due to A!I editing (data not shown), indicating that 
they are most likely sequencing errors. Together, expres-
sion of edited mature miRNAs appears to be relatively 
rare, although a large fraction of human pri-miRNAs 
undergoes editing at the sequence corresponding to 
mature miRNAs. Thus, processing of a majority of 
edited pri-miRNAs must be suppressed as we previously 
reported for miR-142 (35) and miR-151 (31). </p>

<p>Processing of edited pri-miRNAs </p>

<p>We then investigated the effects of miRNA editing on pro-
cessing of pri-to pre-or pre-to mature miRNAs by sub-
jecting unedited and edited pri-miRNAs to an in vitro 
processing assay using purified Drosha-DGCR8 or 
Dicer-TRBP complexes as described previously (31,35). 
We randomly selected six pri-miRNAs, i.e. pri-let-7g, pri-
miR-33, pri-miR-133a2, pri-miR-197, pri-miR-203 and 
pri-miR-379, among 43 pri-miRNAs that have at least 
one UAG triplet editing site (Figure 2). None of the 
edited mature miRNAs expected to be processed from 
pri-let-7g and pri-miR-33 were detected, although editing 
sites were located within the mature miRNA sequences of 
these pri-miRNAs. Although the edited miR-379 RNAs 
were detected (Figure 1B), the frequency of detection of 
edited mature miR-379 (15%) versus unedited miR-379 
was much lower than that expected from the editing </p>

<p>Table 2. Editing of UAG sites present in human pri-miRNAs </p>

<p>W-C 
group 
(a) </p>

<p>G-U 
group 
(b) </p>

<p>Mismatch 
group 
(c) </p>

<p>Total of 
three groups 
(a+b+c) </p>

<p>UAG sites examined 
172 
96 
73 
341 
Edited at UAG sites 
34 
4 
5 
43 
Editing frequency (%) 
19.8 
4.1 
6.8 
12.6 </p>

<p>Table 3. Editing of pri-miRNAs containing UAG triplets </p>

<p>W-C 
group 
(a) </p>

<p>G-U 
group 
(b) </p>

<p>Mismatch 
group 
(c) </p>

<p>Total of 
three groups 
(a+b+c) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>miRNAs examined 
131 
82 
65 
209 
Edited at UAG sites 
31 
4 
5 
38 
Edited at non-UAG sites 
4 
3 
4 
9 
All edited pri-miRNAs 
35 
7 
9 
47 
Frequency (%) 
23.7 
(26.7) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>4.9 
(8.5) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>7.7 
(13.8) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>18.2 
(22.5) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a Many pri-miRNAs contained multiple UAG triplets of different types, 
leading to the total pri-miRNA number that is less than the summation 
of three types. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Frequency for all pri-miRNAs edited at both UAG and non-UAG 
sites. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Identification of edited mature miRNAs. Four pri-miRNA 
structures and edited mature miRNAs are presented (A-D). Editing effi-
ciency of pri-miRNA and mature miRNAs is indicated in parentheses in 
black and red, respectively. The 5 
0 end of the mature miRNA is counted 
as +1, and the editing site is indicated by the number highlighted in red. 
The position of the pri-miRNA editing site is also indicated in parenthe-
sis. The 5 
0 end of the pri-miRNA structure registered at the Sanger Center 
miRBase site is counted as 1. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 16 5273 </p>

<p>frequency of pri-miR-379 (60%), indicating that proces-
sing of edited pri-miR-379 RNAs may not be as efficient 
as that of unedited pri-miR-379 RNAs. We also noted this 
proportionally less frequent detection of edited mature 
miR-411 RNAs (Figure 1C). Furthermore, neither une-
dited nor edited miR-203 was detected in human brain 
(Table S5), perhaps due to their low expression levels. 
We tested a set of unedited and 'pre-edited' pri-miRNAs 
for in vitro processing assays. In the 'pre-edited' pri-
miRNA used for the assay, the adenosine residue of the 
editing site was replaced with guanosine. We previously 
demonstrated that the A!G alteration of pri-miRNA is 
treated the same as A!I editing by Drosha-DGCR8 com-
plexes and also by the Dicer-TRBP complexes (31,35). 
Both +11 and +14 sites of pri-let-7g were edited at 10 
and 30% in vivo in human brain (Table S1). The effects of 
editing at the major +14 site were tested for in vitro pro-
cessing (Figure 2A). Although the editing at the +14 site 
did not affect the Drosha cleavage step, it suppressed the </p>

<p>Dicer cleavage step, leading to 2-fold reduction in the 
mature miRNA levels. In contrast, editing of pri-miR-33 
at the +15 site, pri-miR-133a2 at the +20 site and 
pri-miR-379 at the +10 site inhibited the Drosha cleavage 
step and reduced the generation of their precursor forms 
(pre-miRNAs) down to a 50% level as compared to their 
unedited controls (Figure 2B, C and F). This is likely the 
reason for less frequent detection of edited mature miR-
379 RNAs (Figure 1B). Editing of these three pri-miRNAs 
had no effect on the Dicer cleavage step (Figure 2B, 
C and F). Interestingly, editing of pri-miR-203 at the 
+85 site enhanced its processing by the Drosha-DGCR8 
complex, leading to 2-fold increase in generation of pre-
miR-203 RNAs (Figure 2E). This is the first example of 
pri-miRNA editing that results in promotion of processing. 
Similarly, a slight increase in processing of pri-miR-197 
edited at the +14 site by the Drosha-DGCR8 complex 
was detected (Figure 2D). Editing of both pri-miR-203 
and pri-miR-197 did not affect the Dicer cleavage step </p>

<p>Figure 2. In vitro processing of edited pri-miRNAs. In vitro cleavage of pri-miRNAs by Drosha/DGCR8 complexes and pre-miRNAs by Dicer/ 
TRBP were determined separately (A-F). Editing efficiency of pri-miRNA is indicated in parentheses. The editing site is indicated by the number 
highlighted in red. The 5 
0 end of the pri-miRNA structure registered at the Sanger Center miRBase site is counted as 1. Three independent assays 
were done (n = 3). Mann-Whitney U-test, 
Ã P &lt; 0.05. </p>



<p>(Figure 2D and E). The editing site of pri-miR-203 is 
located within the mature miRNA sequence (Figure 2E). 
Thus, although not detected in human brain investigated in 
this study, it is possible that edited miR-203 RNAs may 
be detected in the tissues where they are highly expressed. 
Interestingly, it has been recently reported that blockage of 
pri-let-7g processing by Lin28 RNA binding protein plays 
an important role in the miRNA-mediated differentia-
tion in stem cells (50). Furthermore, a critical role played 
by miR-203 and miR-133a2 in differentiation 
and proliferation of skin progenitor cells and cardiomyo-
cytes, respectively, has been reported (52-55). It remains to 
be investigated whether A!I editing of let-7g, miR-133a2 
and miR-203 affects the cellular process proposed to be 
regulated by these miRNAs. Although only a limited 
number of pri-miRNA editing sites were tested, all six 
examples investigated were found to affect the processing 
of miRNAs, indicating that the major function of pri-
miRNA editing is modulation of miRNA biogenesis 
and expression levels rather than generation of edited 
mature miRNAs and redirection of target gene selection. 
Finally, editing of pri-mRNAs may affect the processing 
steps not tested in this study such as nuclear export 
(36,41) as well as degradation of edited pri-miRNAs by 
the ribonuclease specific to inosine-containing RNAs 
(35,56). </p>

<p>Most preferred UAG triplet editing sites </p>

<p>While analyzing the sequence and dsRNA structure of the 
UAG triplets, we noted that the editing frequency varies 
dependent on the complementary strand sequence that 
form the duplex structure with the UAG triplet 
(Figure 3 and Table 1). Therefore, we subgrouped 341 
UAG triplets of 209 pri-miRNAs into three groups 
based on the nucleotide sequence complementary to U 
and G residues of the UAG triplet. (a) Both U and G 
are Watson-Crick base paired. (b) Either one of U and 
G, or both, are wobble base paired. (c) Either one of U 
and G is mismatched (Figure 1, Tables 2, 3 and Tables S1, 
S2, S3). We detected editing of 34 sites (19.8%) of 31 
pri-miRNAs (23.7%) with both U and G residues base 
paired with A and C, respectively, in the Watson-Crick 
base pairing, i.e. group (a) (Tables 2, 3 and Table S1), 
four sites (4.1%) of four pri-miRNAs (4.9%) with either 
U and G residues or both base paired in the wobble pair-
ing, i.e. group (b) (Tables 2, 3 and Table S2) and five sites 
(6.8%) in five pri-miRNAs (7.7%) with either U or G 
residues in a mismatched base pairing, i.e. group (c) 
(Tables 2, 3 and Table S3). The results revealed that 
the two neighboring nucleotides of the UAG triplet need 
to be stably base paired preferentially in the Watson-
Crick base pairing in order to be edited efficiently 
(Figure 3). Finally, the editing frequency was plotted 
against the effect of the nucleotide complementary to the 
adenosine residue of the UAG triplet. The presence of 
cytosine in the opposite strand resulted in the most fre-
quent (15/27 or 55.6%) and highest mean of the editing 
efficiency (57.3%) followed by uridine (27/275 or 9.8%) 
and absence of the complementary nucleotide (1/15 or 
6.7%) (Table 4). The preference of AÁC mismatched </p>

<p>pairs for editing was noted through mutagenesis of 
known protein coding pre-mRNA (57). Furthermore, ana-
lysis of non-coding Alu and SINE sequences once again 
revealed much higher frequency for AÁC mismatched edit-
ing sites, revealing its common preference for editing 
of pre-mRNAs, non-coding RNAs containing inversely 
oriented 
repeat 
elements 
and 
also 
miRNAs 
(25-27,30,51,58). </p>

<p>The effects of the À2 and +2 positions </p>

<p>We then examined the effects of base pairings at the À2 
and +2 positions on editing efficiency at UAG triplets 
that already had Watson-Crick base pairings at the À1 
and +1 sites (Table 5). When both the À2 and the +2 
positions were stabilized by Watson-Crick base pairings, 
editing efficiency was 29.0%. In contrast, the replacement 
of even a single Watson-Crick base pairing with a U-G 
wobble base pairing or a mismatched base pairing reduced 
the overall editing efficiency to 10.3 and 8.0%, respec-
tively, indicating the importance of the stable dsRNA 
structure locked by Watson-Crick base pairings not only 
at the À1 and +1 positions but also at the À2 and +2 
sites (Tables 2, 3 and 5). We also examined the influence of 
the À3 and +3 positions, which had no significant effects 
on the editing efficiency (data not shown). 
Effects of a specific nucleotide at the À2 and +2 posi-
tions on the editing efficiency were also investigated. No 
significant effects were detected for the editing frequency 
of UAG triplets with regard to the nucleotide at the À2 
position, although the average editing efficiency was 
slightly higher for the triplets with A or G compared to 
those U or C at the À2 position (Table 6). In contrast, the 
presence of the adenosine residue at the +2 position 
resulted in the highest rate of the UAG triplet editing 
(59.3%), followed by guanosine (20.0%) or cytidine 
(21.4%), and uridine (11.1%) (Table 7). The +2 nucleo-
tide appeared to influence also the mean editing frequency; 
adenosine the highest (69.1%) followed by uridine 
(50.0%), guanosine (24.0%) and cytidine (10.0%) 
(Table 7). </p>

<p>Figure 3. The most preferred sequence and dsRNA structure for A!I 
editing of UAG triplets. The most frequently edited UAG triplet of pri-
miRNA is indicated. The consensus pri-miRNA sequence with a 'pre-
ferred' editing site is derived by sequence comparison of 43 UAG triplet 
editing sites in 47 pri-miRNAs which we experimentally examined for 
in vivo editing. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 16 5275 </p>

<p>Together, our statistical analysis revealed the most pre-
ferred sequence and structure of the UAG triplet editing 
site (Figure 3). The adenosine residue of the UAG triplet 
with a partner nucleotide of cytidine stably locked with 
four Watson-Crick base pairings and the presence of ade-
nosine at the +2 position appears to be the most </p>

<p>frequently and highly edited site of pri-miRNAs in 
human brain. </p>

<p>Non-UAG editing sites </p>

<p>In this study, 43 non-UAG triplet editing sites were also 
identified in 209 pri-miRNAs examined (Table 8 and 
Table S4). Among 43 non-UAG triplets, 32 sites had 
Watson-Crick base pairings at both the À1 and the +1 
sites, indicating once again the importance of the stable 
structure surrounding the adenosine residue to be edited 
(Table S4). The presence of cytidine in the opposite strand 
resulted in most frequent editing (10/137 sites, 7.3%) in 
comparison to the presence of other partner nucleotides, 
e.g. uridine (32/2273 sites, 1.4%), indicating that 
mismatched AÁC pairs are also the most favored editing 
sites even among non-UAG triplets (Table 9). AAG, 
AAA, UAU, UAC and UAA were frequently edited. In 
contrast, editing of triplets having guanosine as the 5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>neighbor, e.g. GAU, was extremely rare. The preference 
of 5 
0 -A and U neighbors and disfavor of 5 
0 -G for A!I 
editing by ADAR1 and ADAR2 was first reported 
through studies on in vitro editing of a synthetic long </p>

<p>Table 4. Effects of the nucleotide complementary to the UAG editing site </p>

<p>The complementary nucleotide </p>

<p>C 
U 
G 
A 
None 
Total </p>

<p>Edited/total (%) 
15/27 (55.6) 
27/275 (9.8) 
0/11 (0.0) 
0/13 (0.0) 
1/15 (6.7) 
43/341 (12.6) 
Mean editing efficiency (%) 
57.3 
50.3 
-
-
20.0 
52.0 </p>

<p>Table 5. The effects of the basepairing at the À2 and +2 positions </p>

<p>W-C group 
G-U group 
Mismatch group 
Total </p>

<p>UAG sites examined 
93 
29 
50 
172 
Edited at UAG sites 
27 
3 
4 
34 
Mean editing efficiency (%) 
29.0 
10.3 
8.0 
19.8 </p>

<p>Table 6. The effect of the nucleotide À2 position </p>

<p>The nucleotide at À2 position </p>

<p>A 
G 
U 
C 
Total </p>

<p>Editing frequency, edited/total (%) 
10/27 (37.0) 
7/21 (33.3) 
4/16 (25.0) 
6/29 (20.7) 
27/93 (29.0) 
Mean editing efficiency (%) 
69.5 
58.6 
30.0 
30.0 
52.0 </p>

<p>Table 7. The effect of the nucleotide +2 position </p>

<p>The nucleotide at +2 position </p>

<p>A 
G 
U 
C 
Total </p>

<p>Editing frequency, edited/total (%) 
16/27 (59.3) 
5/25 (20.0) 
3/27 (11.1) 
3/14 (21.4) 
27/93 (29.0) 
Mean editing efficiency (%) 
69.1 
24.0 
50.0 
10.0 
52.0 </p>

<p>Table 8. Non-UAG editing sites </p>

<p>The number 
The mean editing efficiency (%) </p>

<p>AAG 
10 
49.5 
AAA 
8 
50.0 
UAU 
6 
23.3 
UAC 
5 
20.0 
UAA 
4 
43.8 
CAG 
2 
75.0 
CAC 
2 
20.0 
CAU 
2 
22.5 
CAA 
1 
40.0 
AAC 
1 
20.0 
AAU 
1 
10.0 
GAG 
1 
30.0 
Total 
43 
38.3 </p>



<p>dsRNA substrate (59). Although these non-UAG triplet 
editing sites identified were in some cases highly edited, 10 
AAG editing sites out of a total of 231 AAG triplets pres-
ent in 209 pri-miRNAs, among the most frequently edited 
non-UAG triplets, form a marked contrast to 43 UAG 
triplet sites (Tables 4 and 9). The 209 pri-miRNAs were 
selected unbiased for non-UAG triplet sites. According to 
non-UAG triplets located within the dsRNA region of 209 
pri-miRNAs (examined), we anticipate proportionally 
that an additional 11 AAG triplet editing sites might be 
identified among 253 AAG sites (data not shown) present 
in 217 pri-miRNAs not examined in this study, or a total 
of 21 AAG editing sites, far less than the 43 UAG triplets. 
Thus, the results of our survey indicate that the UAG 
triplet is likely the most favored triplet of pri-miRNAs 
for A!I editing. A statistical analysis of a large number 
of editing sites identified in Alu and mouse SINE repeat 
sequences also revealed the preference of U and C as the 
5 
0 -nearest neighbor and G preference for the 3 
0 -nearest 
neighbor and favored UAG triplet sequences (25-27,51). 
In vitro and in vivo editing analysis of 16 sites located 
within intron 4 of ADAR2 pre-mRNAs had previously 
revealed the 5 
0 -nearest neighbor preference (U = A&gt;G) 
(58), again consistent with our analysis of pri-miRNA 
editing sites. </p>

<p>Editing site location and ADAR enzymes responsible 
for editing of UAG triplets </p>

<p>We investigated whether the editing frequency of each site 
correlates with the distance from the end loop structure. 
The size and the structure of the loop varied significantly, 
relative to the position of the editing site. Therefore, the 
distance from the Dicer cleavage site and editing frequency 
of 86 editing sites (UAG and non-UAG triplets) were 
plotted, revealing that the pri-miRNA editing sites were 
more often found on the sense strand (5p strand) than 
the antisense strand (3p strand) and more distal to the 
Dicer cleavage site. The region near the end loop appeared 
to be devoid of editing (Figure 4). This trend of preference 
of 5p strand and more distal to the Dicer cleavage site was </p>

<p>noted also for analysis of UAG triplet editing sites 
(Figure 3) (data not shown). 
In order to determine the ADAR enzyme responsible for 
editing of a specific site, we examined mouse homologues 
of human pri-miRNAs in wild-type and mutant mice with 
inactivated ADAR1 or ADAR2 genes (Table 10). The edit-
ing frequency of these conserved pri-miRNAs was deter-
mined with the total RNAs extracted from ADAR1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>embryos or ADAR2 
À/À mouse brains (Table 10). 
ADAR2 
À/À mice are viable (14), whereas ADAR1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mouse embryos die at the embryonic day 12 (E12) 
(13,15). We used ADAR1 
À/À and wild-type embryos col-
lected at E11, whereas adult brains of wild-type and 
ADAR2 
À/À mice were utilized. We confirmed that pri-
miR-99b, -411 and -423 are edited by ADAR1, as we 
reported previously for miR-376b and miR-151 (31,32), 
since editing efficiency of these two pri-miRNAs remained 
the same in the wild-type and ADAR2 
À/À mouse brains as 
well as wild-type embryos but lost in the ADAR1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>embryos. ADAR2 appeared to be responsible for editing 
of pri-let-7g, pri-miR-27a, -99a, -203 and -379 RNAs, as 
we previously reported for miR-376a (32), because editing 
of these sites is present in wild-type and ADAR1 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>embryos as well as wild-type mouse brains, but lost in 
ADAR2 
À/À mouse brains (Table 10). No specific relation-
ship for the responsible ADAR enzyme and the position of </p>

<p>Table 9. Effects of the nucleotide complementary to the non-UAG site </p>

<p>The complementary nucleotide </p>

<p>C 
U 
G 
A 
None 
Total </p>

<p>AAG 
0/13 
10/185 
0/11 
0/16 
0/6 
10/231 
AAA 
3/15 
5/205 
0/31 
0/33 
0/12 
8/296 
UAU 
1/13 
4/240 
0/8 
1/20 
0/5 
6/286 
UAC 
0/10 
5/157 
0/8 
0/17 
0/9 
5/201 
UAA 
0/6 
4/164 
0/10 
0/27 
0/11 
4/218 
CAG 
1/19 
1/238 
0/16 
0/15 
0/7 
2/295 
CAC 
2/10 
0/170 
0/6 
0/9 
0/9 
2/204 
CAU 
1/5 
1/221 
0/4 
0/15 
0/13 
2/258 
CAA 
1/7 
0/166 
0/10 
0/18 
0/7 
1/208 
AAC 
0/9 
1/135 
0/13 
0/10 
0/7 
1/174 
AAU 
0/16 
1/190 
0/21 
0/17 
0/10 
1/254 
GAG 
1/14 
0/202 
0/11 
0/17 
0/9 
1/253 
Total </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>10/137 (7.3%) 
32/2273 (1.4%) 
0/149 (0.0%) 
1/214 (0.5%) 
0/105 (0.0%) 
43/2878 (1.5%) </p>

<p>a Edited and potential non-UAG sites identified in the 209 pri-miRNAs were counted (edited/potential). </p>

<p>Figure 4. Summary of UAG and non-UAG triplet editing sites identi-
fied in pri-miRNA hairpin structures. The mean editing efficiency of 86 
UAG and non-UAG triplets is plotted against the distance relative to 
the Dicer cleavage site (position 0). The number of pri-miRNAs edited 
at the specific site is also indicated for each bar. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 16 5277 </p>

<p>the editing site relative to the end loop or Drosha and Dicer 
cleavage sites was detected (data not shown). 
During comparison of conserved sets of human and 
mouse pri-miRNAs, we noted that the editing frequency 
of mouse pri-miRNAs is often lower than that of the cor-
responding human pri-miRNA (Table 10). It has been 
reported that A!I editing of non-coding RNAs consisting 
of inverted repeats of human Alu repetitive sequences is at 
least an order of magnitude higher compared with SINE 
repeats (mouse equivalent of Alu) (27,60). Furthermore, a 
4-fold lower frequency of A!I editing of mature miRNAs 
in mouse compared to human was recently reported (33). 
In contrast, certain editing sites of protein coding genes, 
e.g. GluR-B Q/R site, are highly edited in both human and 
mouse (61). Together, the overall A!I RNA editing fre-
quency of non-coding RNAs, i.e. repetitive RNAs and pri-
miRNAs, is set higher in human compared to mouse by a 
currently unknown mechanism. </p>

<p>Frequency of pri-miRNA editing </p>

<p>A small-scale survey for A!I editing of pri-miRNAs in 
human brain was conducted before, revealing 6 out of 99 
pri-miRNAs examined and thus the estimate of 6% of pri-
miRNAs to be subject to editing (30). In this study, we 
noted that many pri-miRNAs reported previously not 
subject to A!I RNA editing (30) were determined to be 
in fact highly edited, e.g. pri-miR-368, pri-miR-376a-2 and 
pri-miR-411. This is likely due to the relatively low fre-
quency of successful amplification of pri-miRNA 
sequences (99 pri-miRNAs amplified from 231 investi-
gated) in the previous study (30). For analysis of UAG 
triplet editing sites, we preselected 257 out of 474 human 
pri-miRNAs (miRBase 9.1) that contained 341 UAG tri-
plets in the dsRNA region. In this study, 209 pri-miRNAs 
out of the 257 pri-miRNAs were successfully RT-PCR 
amplified from human brain RNAs, revealing 47 </p>

<p>pri-miRNAs that indeed contained UAG and/or non-
UAG editing sites. Among the 47 pri-miRNAs, 20 pri-
miRNAs contained non-UAG editing sites regardless of 
the presence or absence of UAG editing sites (Table S4). 
Although 209 pri-miRNAs were selected for those con-
taining UAG triplets, they were unbiased for non-UAG 
triplets. Therefore, we proportionally anticipate an addi-
tional 21 pri-miRNAs to contain the non-UAG triplet site 
in 217 pri-miRNAs excluded in this study. Together, 
we expect 68 (47 + 21) out of 426 (209 + 217) pri-
miRNAs, or $16% of all human pri-miRNAs to contain 
UAG and/or non-UAG editing sites. Our updated esti-
mate of $16% certainly changes the global impact of 
A!I editing on the miRNA-based silencing of mamma-
lian genes. </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>In this study, we examined 209 pri-miRNAs out of 474 pri-
miRNAs registered at the Sanger Center miRBase site (9.1) 
and identified 43 UAG triplet and 43 non-UAG triplet 
editing sites in 47 pri-miRNAs that are highly edited 
in human brain. We expect that $16% of human 
pri-miRNAs contain UAG and/or non-UAG triplets that 
undergo A!I RNA editing. We show that editing and 
consequent alterations of the dsRNA structure most fre-
quently affects the processing of pri-miRNAs to functional 
mature miRNAs. However, four edited pri-miRNAs were 
processed to generate edited mature miRNAs with altered 
sequence at high levels. Their predicted target genes are 
likely to be different from those targeted by unedited 
mature miRNAs. Our study suggests that A!I editing 
of mammalian pri-miRNAs has a large impact on proces-
sing and function of miRNAs and thus affects expression 
(silencing) of many genes on a global scale. </p>

<p>Table 10. Conservation of miRNA editing between human and mouse </p>

<p>Location in human </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Human (%) 
Mouse (%) 
Responsible ADARs </p>

<p>let-7g 
11, UAG 
10 
0 
-
let-7g 
14, UAG 
30 
20 
ADAR2 
miR-7-2 
41, UAG 
10 
0 
-
miR-27a 
4, GAG 
30 
0 
-
miR-27a 
10, CAG 
50 
20 
ADAR2 
miR-27a 
17, UAG 
10 
0 
-
miR-33 
15, UAG 
30 
0 
-
miR-99a 
13, AAA 
20 
20 
ADAR2 
miR-99b 
44, CAC 
10 
10 
ADAR1 
miR-99b 
47, AAG 
50 
10 
ADAR1 
miR-151 
49, UAG 
40 
30 
ADAR1 
miR-153 
60, UAG; 59, UAG 
30, 10 
0 
-hsa-miR-153-1, -153-2 
miR-203 
85, UAG 
60 
30 
ADAR2 
miR-376a 
9, UAG; 15, UAG 
50, 90 
50 
ADAR2 hsa-miR-376a1, -376a2 
miR-376a 
49, UAG; 55, UAG 
40, 100 
0 
-hsa-miR-376a1, -376a2 
miR-376b 
67, UAG 
95 
50 
ADAR1 
miR-379 
10, UAG 
60 
20 
ADAR2 
miR-411 
20, UAG 
80 
60 
ADAR1 
miR-423 
13, UAG 
40 
20 
ADAR1 
miR-532 
34, UAG 
10 
0 
-
miR-652 
11, UAU 
40 
0 
-</p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The 5 
0 end of the pri-miRNA sequence, registered at the Sanger Center miRbase, is counted as 1. </p>



<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank M. Higuchi and P.H. Seeburg for ADAR2 </p>

<p>À/À </p>

<p>mice and J.M. Murray and Boris Zinshteyn for reading 
and comments. We also thank the Wistar Animal, Protein 
Expression and Mouse Genetics Core facilities for their 
services. This work was supported by grants from the 
National Institutes of Health (CA72764, GM-40536, 
GM079091 and P30 CA10815), the Juvenile Diabetes 
Research 
Foundation 
(1-2006-210) 
and 
the 
Commonwealth Universal Research Enhancement 
Program, Pennsylvania Department of Health. Funds 
received to L.V. are the National Institutes of Health 
Postdoctoral Supplemental Award (L070045) and the 
NCI National Institutes of Health Postdoctoral Training 
Grant (CA09171). Funding to pay the Open Access pub-
lication charges for this article was provided by National 
Institutes of Health. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, No. 16 5279 </p>





</text></tei>