<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2836542" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-12T00:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>The E2F family of transcription factors play a critical role in the control of cell prolifera-
tion. E2F-1 is the major cellular target of pRB and is regulated by pRB during cell pro-
liferation. E2F-1-mediated activation and repression of target genes occurs in different 
settings. The role of E2F-1 and E2F-1/pRB complexes in regulation of different target 
genes, and in cycling versus quiescent cells, is unclear. In this study, effects of free E2F-1 
(doesn't complex with pRb) and E2F-1/pRb complex, on E2F-1 target gene expression 
were compared in different cell growth conditions. Findings suggest that E2F-1 acts in 
different ways, not only depending on the target gene but also depending on different 
stages of the cell cycle. For example, E2F-1 acts as part of the repression complex with 
pRB in the expression of DHFR, b-myb, TK and cdc2 in asynchronously growing cells; 
on the other hand, E2F-1 acts as an activator in the expression of the same genes in cells 
that are re-entering the cycle. </p>

<p>The loss of pRB function either by mutation or 
by association with viral oncoproteins is linked to 
uncontrolled cell proliferation and is accompanied by 
the release of transcription factors such as E2F-1 [1-5]. 
Over the past decade, the E2F family of transcription 
factors has emerged as central components of the 
regulatory machinery of cell growth and proliferation 
[6]. E2F DNA binding sites in the adenovirus E2 
promoter were the first E2F binding sites to be identi-
fied [7]. 
Thereafter, E2F DNA binding sites have been 
identified in promoters of many genes intimately in-
volved in the regulation of cell cycle progression. It 
was shown that around 1,000 genes are regulated by 
E2F-1 [8-10]. E2F proteins are encoded by at least </p>

<p>eight genes, E2F-1 through E2F-8. While specific roles 
for individual E2Fs in mediating the effects of RB loss 
are emerging, it is also becoming clear that there are 
no simple divisions of labor among the E2F family. 
Instead, an individual E2F can function to activate or 
repress transcription, promote or impede cell cycle 
progression and enhance or inhibit cell death, de-
pendent on the cellular context [6]. 
In the initial model of E2F-1 action, activation of 
E2F-1 dependent transcription was proposed to be 
caused by the unmasking of an activation domain 
after release of pRB in the E2F complex [2, 3]. Re-
garding the mechanism of E2F-mediated transactiva-
tion, it is believed that "free" E2F binds to its binding 
sites in the promoters of the target gene. So-called </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>"free" E2F is the heterodimer formed between E2F 
family members and DP family members without 
making a complex with pRB or related proteins [11]. 
This view was supplemented by the discovery that 
E2F-1/pRB complexes can actively repress transcrip-
tion [12] [13]. Therefore, there appears to be three ge-
neric types of E2F complexes: activator E2F complexes 
("free" E2F), in which the E2F activation domain 
promotes transcription, inhibited E2F complexes, in 
which the activation domain is masked by 
pRB-family proteins to give a complex that is essen-
tially inert, and repressor E2F complexes, in which RB 
family proteins that are recruited to the DNA by E2F 
assemble a repressor activity [5]. 
The discovery of the E2F-1/pRB repressor has 
raised a debate that is still not completely settled. 
Should E2F binding sites be thought of as activators 
of gene expression in S phase or as elements that 
confer cell-cycle regulated repression in G 0 /G 1 ? Mu-
tational analysis of putative E2F-binding sites in rela-
tively small fragments of genomic DNA suggests that 
E2F-binding sites regulate gene expression in differ-
ent ways in different promoter contexts [11] [14, 15]. 
For example, promoter mutation experiments have 
shown that alteration in the E2F-1 binding sites of the 
c-myc, cdc2 and human DHFR promoters resulted in 
50-90% loss of transcription activity [16] [17, 18]. Here 
the E2F-1-binding sites appear to act as activator ele-
ments during the S phase of the cell cycle. Release of 
E2F-1 from pRB results in activation of gene expres-
sion during the S phase of the cell cycle. In contrast to 
the experiments described above, similar mutations 
of these sites in the promoters of other genes, such as 
b-myb [19] and mouse DHFR [20] caused increased 
transcriptional activity. Here the E2F-1-binding sites 
appear to act as repressor elements during G 0 /G 1 and 
gene expression results from the release of repression. 
It is still unclear how active repression by the 
E2F-1/pRB complex contributes to control of tran-
scription, compared to pRB-mediated inhibition of 
transcriptional activation by free E2F-1 on individual 
target gene expression. 
In this study, cell lines overexpressing E2F-1/wt 
and E2F-1/411, which doesn't complex with pRB [21, 
22], were used to better understand the role of 
E2F-1/pRB interaction on cell phenotype and gene 
expression. This paper presents a novel finding that 
the E2F-1/pRB complex acts in different ways not 
only dependent on the individual target genes, but 
also on the same target genes in cycling cells as com-
pared to cells re-entering the cell cycle. The findings 
show that E2F-1 acts as a part of the repression com-
plex with pRB on the expression of DHFR, b-myb, TK 
and cdc2 in cycling cells; on the other hand, E2F-1 </p>

<p>acts as an activator on the expression of the same 
genes of cells that are re-entering the cycle. DHFR, 
b-myb, TK and cdc2 are also actively growth regu-
lated by E2F-1, and free E2F increased the expression 
of these target genes in all stages of the cells 
re-entering the cycle. However, c-myc and cyclin D1 
are not significantly growth regulated by E2F-1 in 
any stage of the cell cycle. Rb is also growth regulated 
by E2F-1. Interestingly, free E2F-1 acts as a repressor 
of Rb expression at G 1 and as an activator at S phase 
of the cell cycle. </p>

<p>2. MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>2.1. Cells and viruses </p>

<p>ψ-CRE, a murine fibroblast cell line was used in 
these experiments. The cells were grown in DMEM 
supplemented with 5% (vol/vol) fetal bovine serum 
and 5% calf serum in a 5% CO 2 atmosphere at 37 0 C 
[23]. Retroviral vector, Linker Neo CMV E2F-1 was 
used to express E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/mutant genes as 
described below. Linker Neo CMV E2F-1 is identical 
to Linker CMV T [24]. except that the large T antigen 
gene from simian virus 40 was replaced by a cDNA, 
approximately 1326 bps long, encoding E2F-1/wt [25] 
or E2F-1/Y411A [2] (obtained from Dr. K. Helin). 
pX17 is a retroviral vector [24, 26] that encodes the 
neomycin resistance gene but does not encode E2F-1 
gene. pX17 was used as negative control in the ex-
periments. To produce infectious virus, the recombi-
nant plasmids encoding Linker Neo CMV E2F-1s 
were transfected together with helper virus contain-
ing vector (SV-A-MLV-env) which encoded genes 
needed to complement the linker virus, but did not 
encode whole virus, [27] into Cos-7 packaging cells 
using the calcium-phosphate transfection method 
[24]. Two to three days later, virus containing me-
dium was collected from these cells and used to infect 
established ψ-CRE murine cell lines [23]. </p>

<p>2.2. Antibodies </p>

<p>The antibodies used in immunoblotting for de-
tection of E2F-1, were E2F-1 (C-20), cdcp34 (cdc2; 
B-6), cyclin D1 (HD 11), c-myc (9E10) Santa Cruz Bio-
technology, respectively. The antibodies used for 
immunoprecipitation of E2F-1 and pRb were KH95 
(Santa Cruz Biotechnology) and G3-245 (Pharmingen; 
San Diego, CA) monoclonal antibodies, respectively </p>

<p>2.3. Immunoblotting </p>

<p>For Western blotting, cells were lysed by addi-
tion of 1 ml of lysis buffer (50 mM Tris [pH 8.0], 5 
mM EDTA, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% NP-40, 1 mM PMSF 
and 0.01 mg of aprotinin per ml to the cell monolayer. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Cell free extracts prepared from 4x10 4 cells were elec-
trophoresed 
on 
sodium 
dodecyl 
sul-
fate-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) 
gels and transferred to Hybond ECL membranes 
(Amersham; Arlington Heights, IL). Antibodies de-
scribed above were used for immunoblotting. </p>

<p>2.4. Immunoprecipitation </p>

<p>Immunoprecipitations were performed using 
cell-free extract prepared as described in the im-
munoblotting procedure. The extracts were pre-
cleared by incubation with Protein G Plus-/Protein 
A-Agarose beads (Oncogene Science; Uniondale, NY) 
that had been treated with BSA. E2F-1 or pRB was 
immunoprecipitated from precleared extracts by 
adding 2 µg of specific antibodies and 20 µl of BSA 
treated Protein G Plus-/Protein A-Agarose beads. 
This mixture was incubated for 15 hours and centri-
fuged as described above. The immune complexes 
were washed 4 times with lysis buffer and then ana-
lyzed by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotted as described 
above. </p>

<p>2.5. Soft agar assays </p>

<p>Five or ten thousand cells were plated in 1 ml of 
top agar composed of DMEM supplemented with 5% 
fetal bovine serum and 5% calf serum and containing 
0.38% Noble agar. Dishes were maintained at 37°C in 
a humidified 5% CO 2 atmosphere. After 3 weeks, 
colonies were either photographed or counted. For 
photomicrographs, dishes were stained with 
p-iodonitrotetrazolium violet and photographed. For 
counting, colonies were visualized with a microscope 
using low power magnification and those greater 
than 50 µm in diameter were counted. Six microscope 
fields per dish were counted and used to calculate the 
total number of colonies on the entire dish (based on 
dish surface area). Colony counts were obtained from 
four dishes each cell line for per experiment. The data 
are expressed as the means of counts from five inde-
pendent experiments. </p>

<p>2.6. Cell cycle synchronization </p>

<p>To synchronize cells by serum starvation, 5 x 10 5 
cells were seeded into 10-cm dishes. Forty-eight 
hours later, cells were washed with PBS and DMEM 
supplemented with 0.5% fetal bovine serum was then 
added. After 60 h, cells were stimulated into the cell 
cycle by addition of complete medium (DMEM sup-
plemented with 5% (vol/vol) fetal bovine serum and 
5% calf serum). Samples for total RNA preparation 
and flow cytometry were collected at time 0 and ap-
propriate intervals thereafter as indicated. </p>

<p>2.7. Total RNA isolation </p>

<p>RNA STAT-60 Total RNA (TEL-TEST, INC.; 
Friendswood, TX) isolation reagent kit was used and 
its protocol followed for total RNA isolation. Cells in 
culture dishes were homogenized with RNA 
STAT-60, followed by RNA extraction using chloro-
form. RNA was precipitated with 0.5 vol. of isopro-
panol followed by washing with 75% ethanol. The 
quality of the samples was checked electrophoreti-
cally, and quantification was done spectrophotomet-
rically. Two independent RNA preparations were 
used in the experiment. </p>

<p>2.8. Primers used in the MRT-PCR </p>

<p>All primers for E2F-1 target genes were 
designed with the <rs id="software-1" type="software">Primer3: WWW primer tool 
program</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://biotools.umassmed.edu/bioapps/ primer3_www.cgi</rs>) and are shown in the table 1. 
Primers were made by IDT, Inc. (Coralville, IA). </p>

<p>Table 1. Oligonucleotides used in this study </p>

<p>Primer 
n-mer sequence 
PCR fragment 
size (bp) 
FBmyb (for-
ward) 
21 
5'-GCC AGT CAC CCT TTT 
AAC CGC-3' 
713 </p>

<p>RBmyb (re-
verse) 
23 
5'-CAA ATT TAC TCA GGT 
CGC ACC AA-3' 
FDHFR (for-
ward) 
21 
5'-GAC CAT TGA ACT GCA 
TCG TCG-3' 
452 </p>

<p>RDHFR (re-
verse) 
25 
5'-AAT CAA TTT CTG GGA 
AAA ACG TGT C-3' 
FcycD1 (for-
ward) 
23 
5'-CTG ACA CCA ATC TCC 
TCA ACG AC-3' 
647 </p>

<p>RcycD1 (re-
verse) 
22 
5'-AAA GAA AGT GCG TTG 
TGC GGT A-3' 
Fcdc2 (for-
ward) 
23 
5'-AGA GCG TTT GGA ATA 
CCG ATA CG-3' 
423 </p>

<p>Rcdc2 (re-
verse) 
24 
5'-TGT CCA AGT CAT CAA 
AGT ACG GGT-3' 
Fc-myc (for-
ward) 
23 
5'-ATA AAA GAA GCT TTT 
CGG GCG TT-3' 
508 </p>

<p>Rc-myc (re-
verse) 
22 
5'-GGC TGT ACG GAG TCG 
TAG TCG A-3' 
FTK (for-
ward) 
21 
5'-GTA TGC CAA AGA CAC 
GCG CTA-3' 
395 </p>

<p>RTK (reverse) 22 
5'-ACA CGG AGT GAT ACT 
TGT CGG C-3' 
FRb (forward) 25 
5'-GCG ATA TAA ACT TGG 
AGT CCG ATT G-3' 
569 </p>

<p>RRb (reverse) 24 
5'-GCG TGC ACA GAG TGT 
ATT TAG TCG-3' </p>

<p>2.9. Semiquantitative Multiplex RT-PCR </p>

<p>Multiplex RT-PCR was performed using 
Promega's Access RT-PCR system. RT-PCR was used 
first to determine the linear range of target genes. 
Second, the linear range of the internal standard was 
determined using β-actin and β-actin competimer 
(QuantumRNA β-actin internal standards, Ambion). 
Conditions for MRT-PCR were optimized after de-</p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>termining the β-actin and β-actin competimer ratio. 
PCR cycles were optimized so that the target gene 
would be in the linear range. Reactions contained 
AMV-RT and Tfl DNA polymerase, AMV/Tfl Reac-
tion Buffer, dNTP mix, specific upstream and down-
stream primers, β-actin and β-actin competimer 
primers, MgSO4, and RNA template. The PCR ma-
chine was programmed as follows: 48 0 C for 45 min-
utes to synthesize first strand cDNA; 94 0 C for 2 min-
utes to denature template; 94 0 C 45 seconds for dena-
turation; at 60 0 C for 45 seconds for annealing; and 
68 0 C for 1 minute for extension. The PCR products 
were run in a 1.5% agarose gel and the gel was 
stained with EtBr. EtBr signals were analyzed by 
computer assisted densitometry. </p>

<p>2.10. Fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACS) 
analysis </p>

<p>To analyze cellular DNA content, cells were 
fixed and stained [28]. Briefly, 10 6 trypsinized cells 
were washed three times with PBS and then fixed by 
incubation with 50 μl of 0.125% paraformaldehyde at 
37 0 C for 5 minutes. Then 450 μl of ice-cold methanol 
was added to the sample. The fixed cells were 
washed three times with 0.1% Triton X-100 in PBS 
and treated with RNase A (0.04 Kunitz units) for 30 
minutes. The cells were then stained with 50 μg of 
propidium iodide per ml. Cell analysis was per-
formed using a Coulter EPICS Elite EPS flow cy-
tometer (Coulter Electronics; Miami, FL). The fraction 
of the total cell population present in each of the G 1 , S 
and G 2 /M cell cycle phases was obtained from DNA 
histograms by mathematical modeling using <rs type="software">MPLUS</rs> 
software (Phoenix Flow Systems; San Diego, CA [28]). </p>

<p>3. Results </p>

<p>3.1. Overexpression of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 
genes in ψ-CRE cell lines changes the cell growth 
phenotype differentially depending on interac-
tion with pRB </p>

<p>For overexpression of E2Fs, the mouse fibroblast 
ψ-CRE cell line was used since it had the highest 
amount of pRB protein among the cell lines 
C3H10T1/2, BALB/c-3T3 and NIH 3T3 (data not 
shown) and we wanted to examine interaction be-
tween pRB and E2F-1. Using retroviral vectors, three 
cell lines were established that overexpress E2F-1/wt, 
E2F-1/411 or the control, pX17 (the retroviral vector 
with no insert, negative control). Cell clones were 
pooled from cells growing in the presence of G418. 
Figure 1A shows immunoblots of the cells expressing </p>

<p>E2F-1. Multiple closely-migrating protein bands were 
seen. These are differentially-phosphorylated forms 
of E2F-1 protein [29]. In addition, cells infected with 
pX17 were used as negative controls. These cell lines 
were used for the remaining experiments of this 
study. The E2F-1/411 pRB interactions were de-
scribed previously in vitro and in the yeast 
two-hybrid system and a single mutation of E2F-1 411 
site decreased binding of E2F-1 to pRb without af-
fecting E2F-1 transcription activity [21]. Therefore it 
would be important to show E2F-1/411 pRB binding 
acts the same way in the cell. To test the in vivo affin-
ity of the E2F-1/411 for pRB, E2F-1 was immunopre-
cipitated from extracts made from asynchronously 
growing E2F-1/wt or E2F-1/411 cell lines using an 
anti-E2F-1-specific antibody as explained in detail in 
Material and Methods. It was found that E2F-1/411 
pRB binding is five fold less than E2F-1/wt pRB 
binding (Fig. 1B). </p>

<p>3.2. Overexpression of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 
changes the cell cycle of asynchronously growing 
cells and increased cell transformation </p>

<p>Overexpression of E2F-1 is sufficient to induce 
S-phase in most quiescent cells, as reported previ-
ously [30, 31]. However, cycling E2F-1 null mutant 
cells showed no difference in the cell cycle compared 
to cycling normal cells [32]. Therefore, we first deter-
mined the effects of E2F-1/wt and free E2F-1 in cy-
cling cells using flow cytometry. It was found that the 
overexpression of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 signifi-
cantly decreased the cell number in G 1 phase com-
pared to the control (pX17) cells. Furthermore, 
E2F-1/Y411A showed fewer cells in G 1 as compared 
to E2F-1/wt-expressing cells (Fig. 1C and D). 
As shown in this and some other laboratories 
previously [33, 34], overexpression of E2F-1 increases 
the transformation of cells. Therefore we aimed to 
assess how free E2F-1 (E2F-1/411) would change the 
transformation efficiency compared to E2F-1/wt. 
Anchorage-independent 
growth 
of 
E2F-1-overexpressing cells was tested by plating the 
cells in soft agar medium and assaying the ability of 
the cells to form colonies. E2F-1/wt-and E2F-1/411-
overexpressing cell lines showed significant increases 
in transformation, compared to the control (pX17) cell 
line. The mutant E2F-1/Y411A showed a significant 
increase compared to E2F-1/wt overexpressing cell 
line (Fig. 1E). Therefore, free E2F-1, unbound to pRB, 
decreased the G 1 phase and increased the transforma-
tion of ψ-CRE cell more than E2F-1 bound to pRB. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 1. A. Overexpression of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411. Cell free extracts from an equivalent number of cells (5 X 10 4 ) of 
E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 were analyzed by immunoblotting using anti-E2F-1 specific polyclonal antibody after separation on 
10% SDS-PAGE. The position of the E2F-1 bands are indicated on the right. B. Co-immunoprecipitation of pRb and E2F-1. 
Cell free extracts from the ψ-CRE cell lines overexpressing E2F-1/wt, E2F-1/411, or control (pX17) were co-precipitated 
with a monoclonal antibody specific for E2F-1 and followed by western blotting with E2F-1 polyclonal antibody or pRB 
polyclonal antibody as described in Materials and Methods. C. Histograms of cell cycle analysis of pX17, E2F-1/wt and </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>E2F-1/411 overexpressing asynchronously growing cells are shown with the mean of cell numbers in G 1 , S and G 2 /M phases. 
D. Number of pX17, E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 overexpressing asynchronously growing cells in G 1 . G 1 values are mean ± 
S.E.M., n=4, * P&lt; 0.05 compared to control (pX17) ψ-CRE cell line, P&lt; 0.05 compared to ψ-CRE E2F-1/wt cell lines. E. 
Cells were plated in soft agar medium and stained as described in Materials and Methods. Colonies greater than 50 μm in 
diameter were scored after three weeks of growth. Transformation frequency was expressed as the percentage of total 
plated cells that formed colonies. Values are mean ± S.E.M., n=5, * P&lt; 0.05 compared to control (pX17) ψ-CRE cell line, 
P&lt; 0.05 compared to ψ-CRE E2F-1/wt cell lines. </p>

<p>3.3. Overexpression of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 
changed the target gene expression in asyn-
chronously growing cells </p>

<p>It is likely that the different phenotypic changes 
that 
occurred 
in 
the 
E2F-1/wt 
and 
E2F-1/411-overexpressing cells are a result of 
changes produced by alterations in the expression of 
E2F-1 target genes. E2F-1 target genes, such as RB, 
c-myc, b-myb, DHFR, TK, cdc2, cyclin D and others, </p>

<p>are important cell cycle regulators. Therefore, the ef-
fects of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 on target gene ex-
pression using semiquantitative multiplex RT-PCR 
(MRT-PCR) were compared. 
Results obtained from asynchronized prolifer-
ating cells showed that overexpression of E2F-1/wt 
repressed the expression of DHFR, b-myb, cyclin D1, 
cdc2, c-myc and TK (Fig. 2). This finding correlates 
well with most of the previous studies [35, 36]. In ad-
dition, DHFR, b-myb, cyclin D1, cdc2, c-myc and TK 
gene expression were less repressed in cell lines 
overexpressing E2F-1/Y411A compared to cell lines 
overexpressing E2F-1/wt. However, none of these 
genes in E2F-1/411-overexpressing cells had expres-
sion levels exceeding those of the control (pX17). 
Therefore these data imply that in the asynchro-
nously growing cells for DHFR, b-myb, cdc2, TK and 
cyclin D1 expression, the functional consequence of 
the pRB-E2F-1 interaction is not that E2F-1 acts as 
activator and is repressed by pRB binding. Instead, 
E2F-1 might have a role as a protein helping the 
E2F-1/pRB complex possibly bind to the promoter 
and actively repress transcription. </p>

<p>Figure 2. E2F-1 target gene expression levels in asyn-
chronously growing ψ-CRE cells overexpressing E2F-1/wt, 
E2F-1/411 and control (pX17). A. (Left Column) 
MRT-PCR of the total RNA of the ψ-CRE cells overex-
pressing E2F-1/wt , 411 and control was carried out as 
described in Materials and Methods and products were 
analyzed on a 1.5% agarose gel. The gels were stained with 
EtBr, and EtBr signals were analyzed by computer assisted 
densitometry. B. (Right Column) Results are presented 
as fold increases in expression of target gene for each cell 
line compared to control (pX17), which was given the value 
of 100. Values are mean ± S.E.M., n&gt;3, * P&lt; 0.05 compared 
to control (pX17) ψ-CRE cells. In both columns, from top 
to bottom, the genes analyzed were DHFR, B-myb, Cyclin 
D1, Cdc2, c-myc, TK and RB. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>From this follows that, first, if E2F-1 acts as acti-
vator, target gene expression would be higher in 
E2F-1/wt-overexpressing cells compared to that of 
controls (pX17). Secondly and more importantly, tar-
get gene promoters will have only free E2F-1 (un-
bound to pRB) in E2F-1/411-overexpressing cells. 
Therefore, if E2F-1 acts as activator, target gene ex-
pression levels would be higher than the controls, 
pX17. However, the data shows that free E2F-1 did 
not increase target gene expression more than the 
control levels, and it only decreased the repression of 
the E2F-1/pRB complex by replacing E2F-1/pRB 
complex on the promoter. Therefore, E2F-1 does not 
act as activator, but it helps pRB repress the promoter 
of target genes including DHFR, b-myb, cyclin D1, 
cdc2, and TK in the asynchronously growing cells. 
Very different results were observed with RB 
expression (Fig. 2) from those described for the other 
target genes. The data show that E2F-1 acts as activa-
tor for the expression of RB. First, overexpression of 
E2F-1, even bound to pRB, increased the expression 
of RB; second, E2F-1/411 (unbound to pRB) increased 
RB expression more than did E2F-1/wt. These data, 
therefore, show that E2F-1 has different roles for the 
expression of different target genes and pRB has a 
role in controlling the E2F-1 effects on all target genes 
that were examined in asynchronously growing cells. </p>

<p>Figure 3. E2F-1 target protein expression levels in asyn-
chronously growing ψ-CRE cells overexpressing E2F-1/wt 
or E2F-1/411. Cell free extracts from an equivalent number 
of cells (5 X 10 4 ) of E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 were analyzed 
by immunoblotting using specific antibody for the indicated 
individual protein after separation on 10% SDS-PAGE. </p>

<p>3.4. The E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 overexpression 
changes the protein expression of E2F-1 target 
genes in asynchronously growing cells </p>

<p>Next, to see the effects of E2F-1/wt and 411 on 
target genes at the level of protein, the protein levels 
of some of the E2F target genes used in previous ex-
periments were checked. Western Blot analysis (Fig. 
3) showed similar results to RNA levels from 
RT-PCR. E2F-1/wt decreased the protein levels of 
cyclin D1, cdc2, c-myc and increased the pRB level. 
E2F-1/411 overexpression showed less repression 
compared to E2F-1/wt on the level of cdc2, c-myc 
and cyclin D1, and increased the pRB level more than 
E2F-1/wt. Difference in protein expression in differ-
ent cells is more remarkable compared to the RNA 
expression analysis. This difference might be related 
with the sensitivity of the techniques. </p>

<p>3.5. E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 change G 0 /G 1 
checkpoint controls and S-phase entry </p>

<p>The previous experiment showed that overex-
pression of E2F-1 in cells decreased the percentage of 
cells in the G 1 phase in cycling cells (Fig. 1). In this 
experiment the effect of overexpression of E2F-1/wt 
and free E2F-1 on cells re-entering the cell cycle was 
examined. E2F-1/wt and 411 showed significantly 
less accumulation in G 0 /G 1 , compared to the control 
(pX17) cells after serum starvation (Fig. 4A and B). 
Furthermore, E2F-1/411 showed less accumulation in 
G 0 /G 1 as compared to E2F-1/wt-expressing cells, 
similar to the result with cycling cells. Fig. 4C shows 
the time course of S phase entrance of E2F-1/wt-and 
mutant E2F-1/411-after resupplying cells with se-
rum. The E2F-1/411 mutant overexpressing cells 
showed the fastest S-phase entry compared to the 
other cell lines. </p>

<p>3.6. E2F-1 and pRB have different roles for the 
growth regulation of the different target genes </p>

<p>To better understand the function of free E2F-1 
and the E2F-1/pRB complex on individual target 
gene expression in different stages of the cell cycle, 
growth regulation of chosen target genes was inves-
tigated in control, E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 overex-
pressing cell lines. Growth regulation of these genes 
was expressed as the ratio of the expression levels of 
the target gene in S phase to that in G 0 /G 1 phase [20]. 
RNA was extracted from cell lines arrested in 
G 0 /G 1 . After serum stimulation, RNA was extracted 
at various times. Expression of E2F-1 target genes 
was measured by MRT-PCR. Subsequently, the 
growth regulation of target genes in E2F-1/wt and 
E2F-1/411 overexpressing cell lines was compared in 
Fig. 5. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 4. Cell cycle analysis of pX17, E2F-1/wt and E2F-1/411 overexpressing cells. A. Cells were starved in 0.5% FBS for 
60 hours, at which time samples were taken and analyzed by flow cytometry. The histograms from pX17, E2F-1/wt and 
E2F-1/411 overexpressing cells are shown with the mean of cell numbers in G 0 /G 1 , S and G 2 /M phases. B. Number of pX17, 
E2F-1/wt or E2F-1/411 overexpressing cells in G 0 /G 1 . G 0 /G 1 values are mean ± S.E.M., n=4, * P&lt; 0.05 compared to control 
(pX17) ψ-CRE cell line, P&lt; 0.05 compared to ψ-CRE E2F-1/wt cell lines. C. Cells were collected at various times after 
serum stimulation and the percentage of cells in S phase of the cell cycle was determined. Values are mean ± S.E.M., n=3. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Target genes, including b-myb, DHFR, cdc2, and TK, showed similar results for growth regulation (Fig. 5). 
For these genes, expression in control (pX17) cells was similar to that in cells expressing E2F-1/wt in both 
G 0 /G 1 and S phase. In contrast, to that, expression of these genes in the E2F-1/411 overexpressing cells in 
G 0 /G 1 was generally 3-4-fold higher than that of controls (pX17) and E2F-1/wt cells. In S phase, expression of 
DHFR and TK was increased as compared to pX17 and E2F-1/wt cells. Expression of c-myc was decreased in 
cells expressing E2F-1/wt 
in G 0 /G 1 as compared to 
cells expressing E2F-1/411. 
For RB, expression in 
E2F-1/411 expressing cells 
was increased in S phase as 
compared to cells express-
ing E2F-1/wt (Fig. 5). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Roles of E2F-1 and 
pRb on target gene expression 
levels in synchronously grow-
ing ψ-CRE cells. A. (Left 
Column) MRT-PCR of the 
total RNA of control ψ-CRE 
cells (pX17) and ψ-CRE cells 
overexpressing E2F-1/wt and 
E2F-1/-411. The cells were 
starved and then stimulated 
back into the cell cycle at time 
0 as described in Materials and 
Methods. Time points ana-
lyzed were time 0, 6 hours, 12 
hours and 18 hours. Products 
were analyzed on 1.5% aga-
rose gels. The gels were 
stained with EtBr, and EtBr 
signals were analyzed by 
computer assisted densi-
tometry. B. (Right Column) 
Results from A are presented 
as fold increases in expression 
(y-axis) of each bar graph of 
target genes for each cell line 
compared to control (pX17), 
which was given the value of 
100 at time 0. Values are mean 
± S.E.M., n&gt;3, * P&lt; 0.05 
compared to control (pX17) 
ψ-CRE cells at the same time 
point. In both columns, from 
top to bottom, the genes 
analyzed were DHFR, B-myb, 
Cdc2, Cyclin D1, c-myc, TK 
and RB. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>4. Discussion </p>

<p>It has been known that E2F-1 can be a transacti-
vator and a transrepressor depending on the target 
genes and cell lines. Here, it is shown that E2F-1 
could be both transactivator and transrepressor on 
the same target gene expression in the same cell de-
pending on the cell cycle. Although cell cycle pheno-
typic effects of E2F-1 are the same on both cycling 
cells and cells re-entering the cell cycle (Fig. 1C and 
4A and B), the target genes we examined are regu-
lated differently in re-entering cells compared to cy-
cling cells. It was found that on DHFR, b-myb, cdc2 
and TK expression, the functional consequence of the 
pRB-E2F-1 interaction is that E2F acts as activator and 
is repressed by pRB binding in cells re-entering the 
cycle. During the re-entry into the cell cycle, free 
E2F-1 increases the transcription levels of the same 
genes more than 3-4 fold compared to cells in which 
the E2F-1/pRB complex was present. However, free 
E2F-1 (E2F-1/411-overexpressing cells) only 
de-repressed the expression of DHFR, b-myb, cdc-2, 
Cyclin D1, C-myc and TK up to the control (pX17) 
level in asynchronously growing cells. In addition, 
while there was no significant effect of E2F-1/wt over 
control (pX17) on the expression of DHFR, B-myb, 
cdc-2, TK, cyclin D1 and RB in cells re entering the 
cell cycle, overexpression of E2F-1/wt significantly 
repressed the expression of the DHFR, B-myb, cdc-2, 
Cyclin D1, C-myc and TK in cycling cells. Therefore, 
E2F-1 acts as part of the repression complex for the 
the expression of the DHFR, B-myb, cdc-2, Cyclin D1, 
C-myc and TK in cycling cells and as transactivator in 
cells re-entering the cycle on the expression of DHFR, 
b-myb, cdc-2, and TK. This study shows that free 
E2F-1 increased the expression of B-myb, DHFR, cdc2 
and TK in cells re-entering the cell cycle and E2F-1 
overexpression de-repressed the expression of the 
same genes in cycling cells. 
It may be assumed in this study that E2F-1 
overexpression may replace other E2F proteins which 
have a role for repression of cell cycle at G 0 /G 1 . In 
contrast to the activator E2Fs, E2F4 and E2F5 lack 
NLS nuclear localization signals (NLS) [37]. So, 
without the association with pRb2/p130 and 
pRb/p107, E2F4 and E2F5 can no longer access the 
cell nucleus [38]. In addition to this mechanism, there 
is a second mechanism that completely eliminates the 
possibility of forming pRb2/p130-E2F4/5 complexes. 
This second mechanism contributed by Skp2, which 
is the ubiquitin ligase of pRb2/p130 and belongs to </p>

<p>the SCF (Skp1, Cullin, F-box protein) family. Skp2 
recognizes hyperphosphorylated pRb2/p130, ubiq-
uitin-ligases it and, therefore, causes the quick re-
moval of pRb2/p130 by proteosomes [39, 40]. At this 
point, the promoter regions become vacant for the 
activator E2Fs, which, in turn, express the set of gene 
to initiate the S phase entry [41]. 
It is obvious that E2Fs and related proteins are 
not the only factors related with gene expression re-
lated with the cell proliferation. Some other factors or 
changes are different in synchronously growing and 
asynchronously growing cells that give the differ-
ences for the target gene expression in cycling cells 
versus cells re-entering the cycle. As previous reports 
indicate, some other elements besides pRB might be 
involved in regulation of the target genes. For exam-
ple, in the c-myc promoter, transcription factors Sp1, 
ATF1, ATF2 and a novel factor distinct from E2F me-
diates C-MYC promoter activation through its E2F 
element during exit from quiescence, [42-44] for the 
b-myb promoter, CHR (cell cycle gene homology re-
gions), which is also found in some other target 
genes, and CDE (cell cycle-dependent elements) have 
been shown to be regulatory factors [45] effecting E2F 
regulation. 
Fig. 6 is proposed to explain the data obtained in 
these studies. For the target genes DHFR, b-myb, 
cdc-2, Cyclin D1, C-myc and TK, in cycling cells, the 
model shows pRB brought to the DNA by E2F-1, and 
repressing transcription. In this model, E2F-1 without 
pRB (free E2F) has no effect on expression of these 
targets. For DHFR, b-myb, cdc-2, and TK, in G 0 /G 1 , 
the functional consequence of the pRB-E2F-1 interac-
tion is that E2F acts as activator and is repressed by 
pRB binding in cells re-entering the cycle. In here, 
repression is due to the effect of pRB in repressing the 
transactivation function of E2F (because transcription 
is increased in cells expressing E2F-1/411). Therefore, 
the inhibited E2F complexes model most accurately de-
scribes the results from this group, showing that 
E2F-1 bound to pRB does not stimulate expression of 
these target genes. But, when pRB cannot bind E2F-1 
(in the E2F-1/411 cells) it does stimulate target gene 
expression. 
Interestingly, this study showed that B-myb, 
DHFR, cdc2 and TK expression was higher in cells 
overexpressing E2F-1/411 than in cells overexpress-
ing E2F-1/wt not only in the G 0 /G 1 but also in the S 
phases. Therefore, the E2F-1/pRB complex also regu-
lated these genes during S phase. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Figure 6. Models for the E2F-1 and pRb roles for target gene expression. Models were designed from the data presented 
in this paper. While repressor E2F complex generic types is the most appropriate for the target genes including, DHFR, b-myb, 
cdc-2, Cyclin D1, C-myc and TK in cycling cells, the inhibited E2F complex is the most appropriate generic types of E2F 
complexes for the RB. Possible models were designed for individual genes in cells re-entering the cycle according to the 
results. </p>

<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>



<p>Previously it was known that pRB is phos-
phorylated during S phase in the cells overexpressing 
E2F-1/wt, and therefore E2F-1 would not be com-
plexed with pRB. This implies that pRB would not 
have a function in the regulation of target genes in S 
phase. Our results contradict most of the previous 
studies in which it was shown that during S phase, 
the E2F-1 target gene promoter was not protected by 
a protein complex [46, 47]. However, results of this 
study showing that DHFR, cdc-2, and TK are regu-
lated during S phase, albeit to a lesser extent than in 
G 0 /G 1 are mostly consistent with the finding of Wells 
et al. [48, 49]. They showed with chromosomal im-
munoprecipitation that some of the genes have pro-
tein complexes on the E2F-1 sites not only at G 0 /G 1 
but also at S phase. 
The E2F-1/pRB complex regulates c-myc only 
during G 0 /G 1 phase, and no significant effect of the 
E2F-1/pRB complex on c-myc is seen during S phase. 
Since c-myc expression is lower in E2F-1/wt and 
E2F-1/411-overexpressing cells compared to control, 
active repressor complex model is the most appropriate 
for regulation of c-myc by the E2F-1/pRB complex 
and E2F-1 (Fig. 5 and 6). 
Although cyclin D1 showed growth regulation 
in both cell lines overexpressing E2F-1/wt and 
E2F-1/Y411A, the E2F-1/pRB complex does not play 
any role in this regulation. 
Regulation of RB gene expression was more 
complex. Contrary to previous reports, our study 
showed that E2F-1 activates RB expression in asyn-
chronously 
growing 
cells. 
The 
E2F-1/411-mutant-overexpressing cells showed that 
in G 0 /G 1 , free E2F-1 decreased RB expression, but the 
opposite happened in S phase. This result may indi-
cate that the RB expression was controlled by 
E2F-1/pRB and E2F-1 was inhibited by pRB during S 
phase but not in G 0 /G 1 . This fits well with the role of 
pRB in the cell cycle. During G 0 /G 1 , a cell needs pRB 
to repress genes involved in cell proliferation. How-
ever, in S phase, pRB effect should be reduced on the 
target gene promoter so that gene expression may 
occur. This might be another way of regulating tran-
scription-related proteins by pRB in S phase, distinct 
from pRB phosphorylation. 
It is possible that some additional factors may be 
involved with the E2F-1/pRB complex. For example, 
Udvadia et al. showed that pRB and Sp1 increased 
the activation of cyclin D1 [50]. It was presented pre-
viously [50] that RB promoter also has Sp1 site on 
promoter close to one of the E2F-1 site and deletion of 
Sp1 site decreased the activity of the promoter. Al-
though, not significantly, our data also shows that 
cyclin D1 expression in the E2F-1/wt-expressing cell </p>

<p>is higher than that of E2F-1/411 similar to the pRB 
expression in the cells re-entering the cycle. These 
may suggest that pRB may be an activator of certain 
promoters that contain Sp1 sites. Similar finding was 
also reported previously by Wells et all [48]. 
These novel findings about interaction of E2F-1 
-pRb complex at different cell cycle provide new in-
sight into the understanding of the molecular mecha-
nism of pRB-E2F-1 interaction. In addition, this find-
ing may represents a new characteristic of the tran-
scription factors, which may act differently at differ-
ent part of the cell cycle. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest </p>

<p>There are no conflicts of interest and financial 
disclosure in the subject matter of this paper. </p>



<p>Int. J. Biol. Sci. 2010, 6 </p>

<p>http://www.biolsci.org </p>





</text></tei>