<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2850939" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:55+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The addition of glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) an-
chors to proteins is an important posttranslational 
modification in eukaryotic cells. The complete structural 
elucidation of GPI anchors is a complex process that re-
quires relatively large amounts of starting material. In 
this paper, we assess the degree of structural information 
that can be obtained by applying electrospray mass spec-
trometry and tandem mass spectrometry to permethylated 
GPI glycans prepared from a well-characterized GPI-
anchored glycoprotein, the variant surface glycoprotein 
from Trypanosoma brucei. All GPI glycans contain a 
non-N-acetylated glucosamine residue, and permethyla-
tion leads to the formation of a fixed positive charge on 
the glycans, in the form of a quaternary amine. The per-
methylated glycans were detected as [M + Na] 2+ ions, and 
tandem mass spectrometry of these ions produced sub-
stantial, albeit incomplete, structural information on the 
branching patterns and linkage types for various GPI gly-
coforms of the variant surface glycoprotein. </p>

<p>Glycosylphosphatidylinositol (GPI) anchored proteins (GPI-
APs) are ubiquitous among the eukaryotes and are of consid-
erable biological interest, with functions in cell protection, cell 
signaling, cell-cell adhesion and host cell-pathogen interac-
tions (Ferguson et al. 2008; Paulick and Bertozzi 2008). GPI 
anchors are preassembled in the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) </p>

<p>and added to the C-termini of certain proteins in the ER in ex-
change for the C-terminal signal peptide via a transamidation 
reaction (Ferguson et al. 2008; Fujita and Kinoshita 2010). The 
GPI anchor may then be further processed via lipid remodeling 
and carbohydrate side-chain modifications, in a protein and 
cell type specific manner, as the GPI-AP transits the secretory 
pathway (Ferguson et al. 2008; Fujita and Kinoshita 2010). 
The final destination for most GPI-APs is the outer leaflet of 
the plasma membrane or the topologically equivalent luminal 
surface of secretory granule membranes. 
To elucidate the complete structure of a GPI anchor is a 
lengthy undertaking that requires relatively large amounts of na-
tive protein and techniques including 2D nuclear magnetic 
resonance spectroscopy, mass spectrometry and gas chromatog-
raphy-mass spectrometry (GC-MS)-based composition and 
methylation linkage analyses, for example (Fankhauser et al. 
1993; Ferguson et al. 1988; Homans et al. 1988; Schneider et 
al. 1990). However, with one exception (from the highly diver-
gent protist Entamoeba; Moody-Haupt et al. 2000), all GPI 
anchors determined thus far share the common core structure 
of: NH 2 CH 2 CH 2 PO 4 H-6Manα1-2Manα1-6Manα1-4GlcNα1-
6D-myo-inositol-1-HPO 4 -lipid (EtN-P-Man 3 GlcN-PI), where 
the amine of the ethanolamine phosphate (EtN-P) group is the 
attachment point to the α-carboxyl group of the C-terminus of 
the protein (Ferguson et al. 2008). In this paper, we exploit the 
chemistry of GPI anchors by using (a) aqueous hydrogen fluo-
ride (HF) dephosphorylation to liberate the GPI anchor glycan 
from the parent GPI-AP and (b) permethylation to convert 
the free amine of the single non-N-acetylated glucosamine 
residue to a quaternary amine carrying a fixed positive 
charge. The permethylated GPI glycans ionize well in pos-
itive ion electrospray mass spectrometry (ES-MS), thanks in 
part to this quaternary amine feature (Baldwyn 2005). We 
assess the scope and limitations of structural interpretation 
that can be obtained from collision-induced dissociation 
(CID) tandem mass spectrometry (ES-MS/MS) of permethy-
lated GPI glycans, using a series of well-characterized 
structures derived from a variant surface glycoprotein 
(VSG) from the protozoan parasite Trypanosoma brucei. </p>

<p>Results 
Preparation and profiling of sVSG121 GPI glycans 
In order to test the usefulness of electrospray tandem mass 
spectrometry for comprehensive GPI glycan characterization, </p>

<p>© The Author (2010). Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of British Society for the Philosophy of Science. All rights reserved. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>576 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>To whom correspondence should be addressed: Tel: +44-(0)1382-344219; 
e-mail: m.a.j.ferguson@dundee.ac.uk 
2 Current address: Wellcome Trust Centre for Stem Cell Research and 
Cambridge Systems Biology Centre, University of Cambridge, Tennis Court 
Road, Cambridge, CB2 1QR, UK </p>

<p>the carbohydrate component of the sVSG121 GPI anchor was 
released from the GPI protein by aqueous HF treatment, per-
methylated and purified by solvent extraction (see Figure 1). 
The permethylated glycans were redissolved in 80% acetoni-
trile and 0.5 mM sodium acetate and analyzed by electrospray 
mass spectrometry, revealing three major isobaric forms of GPI 
glycan. The permethylated glycans contained a fixed positive 
charge due to the quaternary amine formed during methylation 
of the glucosamine residue and ionized as sodium adducts, pro-
ducing doubly charged [M + Na] 2+ ions at m/z 871.9, 973.9 and </p>

<p>1075.9 (see Figure 2). These m/z values were consistent with 
fully permethylated glycan ions of composition [Hex 6 -HexN 
(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ , [Hex 7 -HexN(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ and 
[Hex 8 -HexN(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ . Based on the known structure 
of the sVSG121 GPI anchor (Strang et al. 1993) and of the 
closely related sVSG117 and sVSG221 anchors (Ferguson et 
al. 1988; Mehlert et al. 1997), these ions can be further as-
signed to the compositions [Gal 3 Man 3 GlcN(Me 3 ) + + Na] 2 , 
[Gal 4 Man 3 GlcN(Me 3 ) + + Na] 2+ and [Gal 5 Man 3 GlcN(Me 3 ) + + 
Na] 2+ . The glycoform distribution shown in Figure 2 provides </p>

<p>577 </p>

<p>EtN </p>

<p>P 
HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>NH 2 </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>NH 2 </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>HO </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>Glycan </p>

<p>Protein </p>

<p>sVSG121 </p>

<p>Dephosphorylation </p>

<p>Glycan </p>

<p>Glycan </p>

<p>aqueous HF </p>

<p>Permethylation </p>

<p>1. DMSO 
2. NaOH/CH 3 I </p>

<p>ES-MS </p>

<p>ES-MS/MS </p>

<p>3. CHCl extraction </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. General scheme for GPI structure determination using permethylation. The glycan fraction released by aqueous HF dephosphorylation was permethylated, 
recovered by solvent extraction and analyzed by ES-MS and ES-MS/MS. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry of GPI anchors </p>

<p>a rough estimate of the relative amounts of the different species 
in the sample. Thus, according to the spectrum, the Gal 3 -and 
Gal 4 -glycoforms of sVSG121 were much more abundant than 
the Gal 5 -glycoform, in agreement with the relative abundances 
observed by gel filtration of fluorescently labeled GPI glycans 
from the same glycoprotein (Zitzmann et al. 2000). 
The doubly charged permethylated GPI glycoforms were se-
lected for CID to provide structural information, in particular 
to define sequence, branching and linkage details. The precur-
sor [M + Na] 2+ ions produced singly charged product ions 
arising predominantly from cleavage across the glycosidic 
bonds together with a number of additional product ions de-
rived from cross-ring cleavages, as will be discussed later. 
The nomenclature used to define fragmentation is based on that </p>

<p>introduced by Domon and Costello (1988). In this instance, an 
α suffix is used to designate cleavages in the GPI anchor man-
nosyl core and a β suffix for cleavages in the 3-linked alpha-
galactose branch attached to the GPI core. Fragments derived 
from cross-ring cleavages are A-type ions, where the superscript 
defines the position of the cleavage after the corresponding car-
bon atom of the sugar ring. </p>

<p>Sequence, branching and linkage assignments for the Gal 3 
GPI glycan glycoforms 
Fragmentation of the doubly charged precursor ion at m/z 
871.9 produced singly charged product ions, which were ob-
served as an [M + Na] + ion series. The most abundant </p>

<p>578 </p>

<p>Mannose </p>

<p>Galactose </p>

<p>Glucosamine </p>

<p>Inositol </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>760 780 800 820 840 860 880 900 920 940 960 980 1000 1020 1040 1060 1080 </p>

<p>m/z 
0 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>973.95 </p>

<p>871.91 </p>

<p>767.28 </p>

<p>768.28 </p>

<p>872.41 </p>

<p>872.91 </p>

<p>873.41 </p>

<p>974.45 </p>

<p>974.95 </p>

<p>975.46 </p>

<p>1076.49 </p>

<p>1075.95 </p>

<p>[M + Na] 2+ </p>

<p>[M + Na] 2+ </p>

<p>[M + Na] 2+ </p>

<p>Fig. 2. ES-MS of permethylated GPI glycans of sVSG121. Ions at m/z 871.9, 973.9 and 1076.9 were consistent with [M + Na] 2+ ions of composition [Hex 6 -HexN 
(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ , [Hex 7 -HexN(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ and [Hex 8 -HexN(Me 3 ) + Ino + Na] 2+ , respectively. </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>OMe 
OMe </p>

<p>MeO 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>Na 
Na 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>HNMe 3 
OMe 
R </p>

<p>NMe 
+ </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>2+ 
+ </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>OMe 
OMe </p>

<p>MeO 
OMe 
OMe 
R </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>[M + Na] 2+ 
[(M -292) + Na] + </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Proposed fragmentation of permethylated GPI glycans that results in the simultaneous non-neutral loss of the permethylated D-myo-inositol moiety and 
quaternary ammonium group of the glucosamine. </p>

<p>I R E Nett et al. </p>

<p>579 </p>

<p>872.95 </p>

<p>1280.54 </p>

<p>1452.53 </p>

<p>1453.53 </p>

<p>400 450 500 550 600 650 700 750 800 850 900 950 1000 1050 1100 1150 1200 1250 1300 1350 1400 1450 </p>

<p>m/z 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>x5 </p>

<p>1451.53 </p>

<p>839.37 </p>

<p>635.27 </p>

<p>445.19 </p>

<p>533.24 
505.21 </p>

<p>667.32 
825.35 </p>

<p>1279.53 </p>

<p>872.46 </p>

<p>1261.54 </p>

<p>1233.52 
1029.46 </p>

<p>872.95 </p>

<p>1061.50 </p>

<p>1131.53 </p>

<p>1280.54 </p>

<p>1349.55 </p>

<p>1452.53 </p>

<p>1453.53 </p>

<p>1465.54 </p>

<p>649.29 723.30 </p>

<p>1043.49 </p>

<p>[M + Na] + </p>

<p>Hex 6 </p>

<p>Hex 5 </p>

<p>Hex 4 </p>

<p>Hex 3 </p>

<p>Hex 2 </p>

<p>621.32 </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>1061.4 </p>

<p>1043.5 </p>

<p>839.4 </p>

<p>445.5 </p>

<p>1261.5 </p>

<p>1279.5 </p>

<p>1451.5 </p>

<p>667.3 
649.3 </p>

<p>1043.5 
1061.4 
431.2 </p>

<p>635.3 </p>

<p>463.5 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>1061.4 </p>

<p>1043.5 
839.4 </p>

<p>445.5 </p>

<p>1261.5 </p>

<p>1279.5 </p>

<p>1451.5 </p>

<p>667.3 </p>

<p>649.3 </p>

<p>431.2 
635.3 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>621.35 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Product ion spectrum of the permethylated Gal 3 glycoform of the [M + Na] 2+ precursor ion (m/z 871.9). For further discussion, see text. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry of GPI anchors </p>

<p>product ion was m/z 1451.5, which corresponded to the per-
methylated glycan lacking the D-myo-inositol and quaternary 
ammonium group of the glucosamine. This non-neutral loss 
(see Figure 3) dominates the MS/MS spectrum since almost 
all of the other ions are the products of m/z 1451.5 (Figure 4). 
A pair of the product ions was observed at m/z 1279.5 and 
1261.5 resulting from C-and B-type cleavage at the Manα1-
4GlcN glycosidic bond, and further glycosidic bond cleavages 
within these metastable ions produced a number of double-
cleavage ions, as indicated in Figure 4. </p>

<p>The presence of double glycosidic cleavage fragments, 
termed D-ions, could be used to define the branching topology 
(a detailed overview of how to analyze interresidue linkages 
and branching patterns of permethylated glycans by CID is 
given in Reinhold et al. 1995). Two dominant double-cleavage 
ions observed at m/z 839.4 and 635.3 represented the structures 
[(Me-Hex) 2 (Hex) 2 -28 + Na] + and [(Me-Hex) 2 (Hex)-28 + Na] + , 
respectively, indicating two branching points within a sequence 
of hexoses. The double glycosidic cleavage ions suggested two 
topologies. One glycan structure carried a branched hexose 
side chain containing three hexoses (see Figure 4a); the other 
species contained two hexose residues in the side chain and a 
third hexose attached to the middle mannose of the GPI anchor 
glycan core (see Figure 4b). A minor disaccharide fragment ion 
at m/z 431.2 [Me(Hex) 2 -14 + Na] + further supported these to-
pologies. In contrast, an internal fragment ion at m/z 621.35 
[(Hex) 3 -14 + Na] + defined only one branching point in a se-
quence of four hexoses, suggesting a linear side chain of 
three alpha-galactose residues attached to the third mannose 
of the GPI anchor core (see Figure 4c). 
Fragments that help define 1→6, 1→4 and 1→2 linkages 
are derived from double-cleavage across the pyranose ring 
(Reinhold et al. 1995). Cross-ring cleavage ions at m/z 
505.2, 533.2, 723.3 and 1349.5 could be identified, though 
they were relatively weak (see Figure 4, indicated with black 
arrows). The m/z 533.2 and m/z 505.2 ions, which were 88 and 
60 amu above the glycosidic fragment ion at m/z 445.2, [Me 
(Hex) 2 + Na] + , indicated the Hex 2 moiety to be 6-linked (see 
Figure 5a). Thus, this ion is consistent with a 1→6 linkage in 
the trimannosyl GPI core (i.e., Man-Man1-6Man) and in the 
linear trigalactosyl side chain (i.e., Gal-Gal1-6Gal). The 
cross-ring fragment ion observed at m/z 1349.5 defined the tri-
mannosyl core to be linked to the 4-position of the glucosamine, 
as it resided 88 amu above the B-type ion at m/z 1261.5, and a 
60-amu increment could not be detected (see Figures 4 and 5b). 
This arrangement was further supported by an ambiguous 
A-type ion at m/z 723.3, which was 74 amu above the ion 
at m/z 635.3, [Me(Hex) 3 -14 + Na] + (see Figure 5c). Together, 
these results were consistent with the presence of the 
conserved sequence Manα1-2Manα1-6Manα1-4GlcN, pre-
sent in almost all GPI anchor structures characterized so far 
(Ferguson et al. 2008). </p>

<p>Sequence, branching and linkage assignments for the Gal 4 
GPI glycan glycoforms 
The tandem mass spectrum for the m/z 973.9 ion provided an 
analogous series of monosodium adducts to those recorded in 
the spectrum of the Gal 3 -glycoform (Figure 6, see spectrum). 
The branching was revealed by double-cleavage ions at m/z 
635.3, 825.3 and 839.4. The D-type ion observed at m/z 
635.3 represents the structure [Me(Hex) 3 -14 + Na] + , indicating 
one branching point in a linear sequence of three hexoses, as 
described in Ferguson et al. (1988) (Figure 6a). In addition, the 
ion at m/z 825.3 [Me(Hex) 4 -28 + Na] + supports the topology of 
two branching points within a sequence of four hexoses (Fig-
ure 6b). Evidence for an additional hexose attached to the 
middle mannose of the GPI anchor was provided by the ion 
at m/z 839.4 [(Me-Hex) 2 (Hex) 2 -28 + Na] + (Figure 6c). This 
ambiguous double-cleavage ion could also indicate the pres-
ence of a branched three-hexose side chain (Figure 6c). An </p>

<p>580 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>445.5 </p>

<p>1261.5 </p>

<p>635.3 </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>533.2 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>505.5 </p>

<p>0,4 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>NMe 3 + </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>1261.5 </p>

<p>1349.5 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>NMe 3 + </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>635.3 </p>

<p>723.3 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>NMe 3 + </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Cross-ring fragmentation of the permethylated GPI Gal 3 -glycoform of 
the doubly charged precursor ion at m/z 871.9. The A-type ions observed are 
shown in Fig. 3. For further discussion, see text. </p>

<p>I R E Nett et al. </p>



<p>973.52 </p>

<p>974.97 </p>

<p>975.46 </p>

<p>1044.45 </p>

<p>1045.47 </p>

<p>1484.53 </p>

<p>1623.48 </p>

<p>1485.55 </p>

<p>1656.49 </p>

<p>1657.48 </p>

<p>1669.48 </p>

<p>1671.47 </p>

<p>400 
500 
600 
700 
800 
900 
1000 
1100 
1200 
1300 
1400 
1500 
1600 </p>

<p>m/z 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>973.52 </p>

<p>974.97 </p>

<p>975.46 </p>

<p>x3 </p>

<p>973.96 </p>

<p>635.27 </p>

<p>445.18 </p>

<p>533.16 </p>

<p>973.52 </p>

<p>839.36 </p>

<p>825.34 
737.30 </p>

<p>871.38 </p>

<p>974.47 </p>

<p>1655.48 </p>

<p>1043.45 </p>

<p>974.97 </p>

<p>975.46 </p>

<p>1044.45 </p>

<p>1483.53 
1465.54 </p>

<p>1045.47 </p>

<p>1247.53 
1061.46 
1265.52 </p>

<p>1484.53 </p>

<p>1623.48 </p>

<p>1485.55 </p>

<p>1656.49 </p>

<p>1657.48 </p>

<p>1669.48 </p>

<p>1671.47 </p>

<p>431.18 
649.19 
667.30 
1335.50 
1321.55 
1553.51 </p>

<p>[M + Na] + </p>

<p>Hex 6 </p>

<p>Hex 7 </p>

<p>Hex 5 </p>

<p>Hex 4 </p>

<p>Hex 3 </p>

<p>Hex 2 </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>1265.5 </p>

<p>1043.5 </p>

<p>445.5 </p>

<p>1465.5 </p>

<p>1483.5 </p>

<p>1655.5 </p>

<p>871.4 </p>

<p>1247.5 
1265.5 
431.2 </p>

<p>635.3 
NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>839.4 </p>

<p>667.3 </p>

<p>649.3 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>825.3 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>1061.5 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>839.4 </p>

<p>505.18 </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Product ion spectrum of the permethylated Gal 4 -glycoform of the [M + Na] 2+ precursor ion (m/z 973.9). For further discussion, see text. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry of GPI anchors </p>

<p>arrangement of three linear hexose residues in the side chain 
was supported by the occurrence of a single glycosidic cleav-
age ion at m/z 649.2 [Me(Hex) 3 + Na] + (not drawn). A linear 
side chain consisting of four hexose residues was indicated 
by the ambiguous ion at m/z 635.3 [Hex 4 + Na] + (internal 
cleavage fragment, not drawn). 
Cross-ring fragment ions were also present in the spectrum 
of the sVSG121 GPI anchor Gal 4 -isoform (Figure 6). The ions 
at m/z 533.2 and 505.2 are consistent with the 1→6 linkage 
between the middle mannose and the mannose next to the glu-
cosamine of the GPI anchor core, as shown for the Gal 3 -
isoform (see Figure 4a). However, the same ions could also 
originate from within the branched Gal side chain (see Figure 
7a). The A-type ion identified at m/z 1553.5, which derived 
from the double-cleavage ion at m/z 1465.5 [Me(Hex) 7 , 
Na] + , permitted the assignment of a 1→4 linkage between 
the third mannose and the glucosamine (Figure 7b). </p>

<p>Sequence, branching and linkage assignments for the Gal 5 
GPI glycan glycoforms 
The CID spectrum of the Gal 5 -isoform showed similar features 
to the corresponding Gal 3 -and Gal 4 -glycoforms (see Figure 8). </p>

<p>Glycosidic cleavages resulting in the successive loss of hexose 
residues dominated the spectrum. Due to the ambiguity of many 
glycosidic fragment ions derived from this glycan, many differ-
ent branching topologies are possible. Figure 8 also shows a 
structure of the Gal 5 -glycoform, which corresponds to the 
known sequence of the sVSG117 Gal 5 -glycoform (Mehlert et 
al. 1998). This structure was supported by the double-cleavage 
ion observed at m/z 839.4 [(Me-Hex) 2 (Hex) 2 -28 + Na] + , indi-
cating an additional hexose attached to the middle mannose 
of the GPI anchor core. The presence of glycosidic cleavage 
ions at m/z 871.4 (C-type ion) and 853.5 (B-type ion) confirmed 
the structural feature of a side chain consisting of four hexose 
residues. However, no ion was detected that could describe a 
branching point within the side chain unambiguously. Cross-
ring fragments were less abundant and had lower intensities 
when compared to the CID spectra of the Gal 3 -and Gal 4 -glyco-
forms. Due to their very weak signals, they were not analyzed 
further. </p>

<p>GC-MS methylation linkage analysis of sVSG121 GPI 
glycoforms 
In order to confirm the types of linkages assigned for the Gal 3 -
and Gal 4 -glycoforms, a GC-MS methylation linkage analysis 
was performed using the sVSG121 glycan mixture. The per-
methylated glycans were hydrolysed, reduced and acetylated 
to form partially methylated alditol acetates (PMAAs), as de-
scribed in Ferguson (1994). The PMAAs were resolved by 
GC-MS (Agilent). The chromatogram (not shown) revealed 
the presence of a minimum of one terminal mannose, one 
terminal galactose, one 2-O-substituted mannose, one 2-O-sub-
stituted galactose, one 6-substituted galactose, one 2,3-
disubstituted mannose, one 3,6-disubstituted mannose and 
one 2,6-disubstituted galactose. Figure 9 shows the largest of 
the structures of the sVSG121 neutral glycans consistent with 
their GC-MS analysis and previous analyses of GPI anchors 
from other VSG variants (Ferguson et al. 1988; Mehlert et 
al. 1998). Sequence, branching and linkage types were consis-
tent with the proposed structures of ions found by CID-MS. 
Since cross-ring rupture ions of permethylated glycans cannot 
provide structural information of 1→3 linkages (Reinhold et al. 
1995), 3-substituted hexoses could not be detected by CID-
MS. Cross-ring cleavage fragments of terminal hexoses were 
also absent in the CID-MS spectra, possibly due to the very 
weak signal of the [Me-Hex + Na] + -precursor ions. The 
anomeric configurations of the sugar residue that are given 
in Figure 9 are taken from the fully characterized sVSG221 
GPI anchor (Mehlert et al. 1998) and cannot be determined 
by either GC-MS or CID-MS. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>Here, we describe the use of soft ionization electrospray mass 
spectrometry as a powerful technique for structural character-
ization of glycosylphosphatidylinositol membrane anchors 
from low picomole amounts of material. We show that se-
quence, branching and some linkage details of GPI glycans 
can be deduced from ES-MS/MS data and that these assign-
ments are consistent with previous research on structural 
characterization of GPI anchors from T. brucei (Ferguson et 
al. 1988; Mehlert et al. 1998). Our method involved the per-</p>

<p>582 </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>NMe 3 + </p>

<p>OMe </p>

<p>1465.5 </p>

<p>1553.5 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>MeO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>Me </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>NMe 3 + </p>

<p>505.5 </p>

<p>0,4 </p>

<p>533.2 </p>

<p>3,5 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>445.2 </p>

<p>Fig. 7. Cross-ring fragmentation of the permethylated GPI Gal 4 -glycoform of 
the doubly charged precursor ion at m/z 973.9. For further discussion, see text. </p>

<p>I R E Nett et al. </p>

<p>methylation of GPI membrane anchor glycans, which is the 
most important type of derivatization used in oligosaccharide 
MS (North et al. 2009) followed by positive ion ES-MS and 
CID-MS. The ES-MS data alone revealed the composition of 
three different galactose glycoforms of the sVSG121 variant 
GPI glycan structure (Gal 3 -Gal 5 ), which ionized as doubly 
charged sodium adducts [M + Na] 2+ . Collision-induced disso-
ciation provided sequences information by producing 
characteristic glycosidic cleavage ions. Taking into account 
the conserved Manα1-2Manα1-6Manα1-4GlcN motif found </p>

<p>583 </p>

<p>686.43 
1075.65 </p>

<p>1077.02 </p>

<p>1077.56 
1248.63 
1828.15 </p>

<p>1861.24 </p>

<p>1862.21 </p>

<p>400 
500 
600 
700 
800 
900 
1000 
1100 
1200 
1300 
1400 
1500 
1600 
1700 
1800 </p>

<p>m/z 
0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>% </p>

<p>x8 685.43 </p>

<p>431.16 </p>

<p>635.28 
445.14 </p>

<p>1860.24 </p>

<p>1076.57 </p>

<p>686.43 
1075.65 </p>

<p>1043.50 </p>

<p>839.37 </p>

<p>871.44 </p>

<p>1077.02 </p>

<p>1247.60 </p>

<p>1077.56 </p>

<p>1688.04 </p>

<p>1248.63 </p>

<p>1451.77 </p>

<p>1828.15 </p>

<p>1861.24 </p>

<p>1862.21 </p>

<p>649.24 667.25 </p>

<p>853.47 
1670.00 </p>

<p>[M + Na] + </p>

<p>Hex 6 </p>

<p>Hex 7 </p>

<p>Hex 5 </p>

<p>Hex 4 
Hex 3 
Hex 2 
Hex 8 </p>

<p>O 
O 
O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>1451.7 </p>

<p>1043.5 </p>

<p>1670 </p>

<p>1688.1 </p>

<p>1860.2 </p>

<p>871.4 </p>

<p>1451.7 
431.2 </p>

<p>NMe 3 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>O 649.2 </p>

<p>445.5 </p>

<p>839.4 </p>

<p>853.5 </p>

<p>1247.6 </p>

<p>Fig. 8. Product ion spectrum of the permethylated GPI Gal 5 -glycoform of the [M + Na] 2+ precursor ion (m/z 1076). For further discussion, see text. </p>

<p>O 
O </p>

<p>O 
NH 2 </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>OH </p>

<p>HO 
HO </p>

<p>O 
P O 
HO </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>Man )1 </p>

<p>6 
3 </p>

<p>Man )1-2Man )1 </p>

<p>Gal )1 </p>

<p>6 
2 </p>

<p>Gal )1 </p>

<p>+ -</p>

<p>Gal )1-2Gal )1 </p>

<p>Gal )1-3 </p>

<p>+ -</p>

<p>Fig. 9. Proposed structure of sVSG121 neutral glycan as analyzed by GC-MS. 
The highly conserved core of GPI anchors shows a variety of linear and 
branched galactosyl substituents specific to T. brucei. </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry of GPI anchors </p>

<p>in almost all GPI structures (Fankhauser et al. 1993), the se-
quence information could be refined and fitted to a model of 
a core sequence of Man-Man-Man-GlcN-Ino substituted 
with Gal residues. Sequence information regarding the branch-
ing pattern of the GPI anchor galactose residues around the 
mannose core of the different glycoforms could also be ob-
tained by ES-MS/MS. Double glycosidic cleavage ions 
revealed the presence of branched and linear galactose side 
chains from one up to five residues. However, due to the am-
biguity of some glycosidic fragment ions, especially when 
analyzing more complex glycan structures (e.g. Gal 5 -glyco-
form of sVSG121), complementary analytical methods have 
to be taken into consideration. The data also provided an indi-
cation of hexose linkage composition by observing cross-ring 
fragment ions of the permethylated GPI glycans, which was 
consistent with results obtained by GC-MS analysis from the 
same material. Cross-ring cleavage ions defined the linkage 
types within the conserved Manα1-2Manα1-6Manα1-4GlcN 
core, except for terminal hexoses, which is possibly due to 
the very weak signals of the [Me-Hex + Na] + -product ions 
by ES-MS/MS. 
Modern ultra-high sensitive mass spectrometry is commonly 
used for screening samples for specific classes of analytes. In 
recent years, MS strategies for screening different types of oli-
gosaccharides present in a diverse range of biological materials 
have been developed to investigate the glycome (North et al. 
2009). Often, these methods are based on the analysis of per-
methylated oligosaccharides and detection of characteristic 
product ions upon fragmentation. A triple quadrupole mass 
spectrometer is well suited to screen for the presence of ana-
lytes via the use of constant neutral loss and precursor ion scan 
modes. Unfortunately, sensitive screening for permethylated 
GPI glycans in complex biological samples using neutral loss 
scanning is ruled out by the fact that the most abundant report-
er ions generated by collision-induced dissociation result from 
a non-neutral loss of the D-myo-inositol residue together with 
the quaternary ammonium ion of the derivatized glucosamine. 
The principal mass transition for each permethylated GPI gly-
can is, therefore, from the doubly charged [M + Na] 2+ 
precursor ion to singly charged [(M − 292) + Na] + ion, making 
the transition different for each value of M. On the other hand, 
calculated [M + Na] 2+ to [(M − 292) + Na] + transitions can 
be used to build multiple reaction monitoring methods to 
sensitively search for permethylated GPI glycans of predeter-
mined composition. The scope for precursor ion scanning for 
permethylated GPIs is also limited by the aforementioned 
dominant non-neutral loss. Thus, the intensities of all of 
the other product ions are relatively low (note that in the 
spectra shown in Figures 4, 6 and 8 the y-axis is magnified 
five, three and eight times, respectively, relative to the 
1451.5, 1655.5 and 1859.7 [(M -292) + Na] + product ions). 
Furthermore, product ions that are common to all or most 
permethylated GPI glycans also tend to be rather nonspecif-
ic; for example, the [Me-Hex 2 + Na] + , [Hex 3 + Na] + and 
[Hex 4 + Na] + product ions at m/z 445, 635 and 839, respec-
tively, could also belong to permethylated oligomannose N-
linked glycans. 
While this study has focused on Q-Tof MS 2 experiments, we 
are aware that many laboratories now have access to ion trap 
instruments capable of MS 3 and higher-order experiments. We </p>

<p>have only begun to explore the potential of this type of meth-
odology to resolve some of the ambiguities referred to in the 
MS 2 interpretations herein, but it should, in many cases, re-
solve alternative branching structures. One such example 
was recently published by us (Izquierdo et al. 2009), where 
isolation of [(M − 292) + 2 Na] 2+ ions, derived from two 
isobaric [M + 2 Na] 3+ permethylated GPI glycan precursor 
ions, generated unique and highly informative MS 3 product 
ion spectra that discriminated two alternative side-chain 
branching patterns. </p>

<p>Materials and methods 
Materials 
Sephacryl S200 and QAE-Sephadex A-25 were supplied by 
Pharmacia, DEAE-cellulose (DE52) by Whatman, Bio-Gel 
P4 and AG 50W-X12 resin by Bio-Rad, HiTrap SP HP ion ex-
change column by Amershan Bioscience, 2 ml glass vials, 
dimethyl sulfoxide and methyl iodide by Sigma-Aldrich and 
HPTLC plates and Pronase protease from Merck. All other sol-
vents (HPLC grade) were from VWR. </p>

<p>Purification of sVSG121 
sVSG MIT at .1.6 (also known as variant 121) was purified from 
bloodstream form T. brucei strain 427 variant MIT at .1.6 cells 
using hypotonic lysis and DE52 chromatography, as described 
by Cross (1984). The VSG was further purified by gel filtration 
using Sephacryl S200 column (4 × 90 cm) equilibrated with 
0.1 M NH 4 HCO 3 . Typically, 10 mg freeze-dried sVSG was ob-
tained from 10 10 cells. </p>

<p>Preparation of the sVSG MIT at .1.6 GPI neutral glycans 
Approximately 1 mg of sVSG121 was treated with 50 µl 50% 
aqueous HF (48 h at 0°C), freeze-dried (Micro Modulyo), re-
suspended in 50 µl water and sonicated for 15 min 
(Ultrasonics Ltd.). The insoluble material was removed by 
centrifugation (15,000 rpm, 5 min) and washed twice with 
20 µl water. The combined supernatants were transferred into 
a 2-ml glass vial and dried in a Speedvac concentrator (Stra-
tech Scientific). After addition of 50 µl methanol and drying, 
the GPI glycans were used for permethylation. </p>

<p>GPI glycan permethylation 
The GPI glycans were resuspended in 50 µl dimethyl sulfox-
ide, left for 20 min at room temperature and deprotonated by 
adding a solution of 120 mg/ml sodium hydroxide in dimethyl 
sulfoxide (20 min). Methyl iodide was added in three intervals 
over a total of 30 min (10 µl, 10 min incubation; another 10 µl, 
10 min incubation, then 20 µl, 10 min incubation), and the per-
methylation reaction was continued for another 30 min. The 
permethylated glycans were partitioned between 250 µl chlo-
roform and 1 ml of 100 mg/ml sodium thiosulphate in water. 
The upper aqueous phase was removed and the chloroform 
phase re-extracted six times with 1 ml of water each. The per-
methylated glycans recovered in the lower chloroform phase 
were transferred into a new glass vial, dried under N 2 and re-
dissolved in 200 µl of 80% acetonitrile, 0.5 mM sodium 
acetate for ES-MS analysis. </p>



<p>I R E Nett et al. </p>

<p>Electrospray mass spectrometry 
Mass spectrometric data was acquired on a Q-Tof2 TM 
(Micromass) hybrid quadrupole time-of-flight instrument. 
Mass spectra were recorded by linear scanning over a range 
of m/z 500-2500. Several scans were summed from a 4 µl 
introduction of sample solution (100 pmol µl −1 of sVSG121 
glycan) in 80% acetonitrile containing 0.5 mM sodium acte-
tate using type-F nanotips (Micromass). The data acquired 
were averaged and processed using the <rs type="software">Mass-Lynx</rs> software 
supplied with the instrument. Positive ion spectra were re-
corded with a tip voltage of 1 kV and a cone voltage of 
35-50 V. Fragment ion spectra from the doubly charged 
pseudomolecular ions were obtained by collision-induced 
fragmentation in the collision cell using argon as the collision 
gas at a pressure of 1 bar. The CID mass spectra were re-
corded by linear scanning over the m/z range 200-2200. 
Glu-fibrinopeptide B (Glu-fib) was used as an internal stan-
dard for mass calibration at 1 pmol µl −1 in 90% acetonitrile 
containing 0.1% formic acid. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>This work was supported by a Wellcome Trust prize student-
ship to I.R.E.N., a Medical Research Council program grant to 
M.A.J.F. and A.M., and a Wellcome Trust Strategic Award 
[083481] to the Division of Biological Chemistry and Drug 
Discovery. </p>

<p>Abbreviations </p>

<p>CID, collision-induced dissociation; ER, endoplasmic reticu-
lum; ES, electrospray; GC-MS gas chromatography-mass 
spectrometry; GPI, glycosylphosphatidylinositol; GPI-AP, gly-
cosylphosphatidylinositol anchored protein; HF hydrogen 
fluoride; MS, mass spectrometry; MS/MS, tandem mass spec-
trometry; PMAAs, partially methylated alditol acetates; sVSG, 
soluble variant surface glycoprotein; T. brucei, Trypanosoma 
brucei. </p>





<p>Mass spectrometry of GPI anchors </p>

</text></tei>