<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2606938" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T16:59+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Paracellular ion transport in epithelia is mediated by pores formed by members of the claudin family. The degree 
of selectivity and the molecular mechanism of ion permeation through claudin pores are poorly understood. By 
expressing a high-conductance claudin isoform, claudin-2, in high-resistance Madin-Darby canine kidney cells un-
der the control of an inducible promoter, we were able to quantitate claudin pore permeability. Claudin-2 pores 
were found to be narrow, fl uid fi lled, and cation selective. Charge selectivity was mediated by the electrostatic in-
teraction of partially dehydrated permeating cations with a negatively charged site within the pore that is formed 
by the side chain carboxyl group of aspartate-65. Thus, paracellular pores use intrapore electrostatic binding sites 
to achieve a high conductance with a high degree of charge selectivity. </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>In previous studies, we subtracted from the voltage measure-
ments performed on cell monolayer voltages measured under 
identical conditions using blank fi lters, in an attempt to correct 
for liquid junction potentials at the pipette tips. This is a widely 
used technique ( Van Itallie et al., 2001 ; Yu et al., 2003 ; Hou et al., 
2008 ). However, we now realize that this is inaccurate because 
there is also a liquid junction potential across the fi lter itself when 
it is blank, but not when cells are cultured on it. Therefore, to de-
duce the pipette potentials, we had to correct for this blank fi lter 
junction potential. Fig. 2 A shows the Ussing chamber setup with 
a blank fi lter. The diffusion potential measured experimentally in 
this way is V EF , where, </p>

<p>V = (V 
V ) + V . </p>

<p>EF 
L </p>

<p>b 
L </p>

<p>a 
F </p>

<p>-
(1) </p>

<p>The blank fi lter behaves like a liquid junction, so V F was calcu-
lated using the generalized Henderson-Planck equation ( Barry and 
Diamond, 1970 ). Using this value and Eq. 1, we calculated the dif-
ference in pipette potentials, (V L </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Ϫ V L </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>). Fig. 2 B shows the Ussing 
chamber setup with a cell monolayer inserted. The true transmono-
layer diffusion potential, V M , was deduced from the experimentally 
measured potential, V EM , by subtracting the pipette potential: </p>

<p>V = V 
(V 
V ). </p>

<p>M 
E M 
L </p>

<p>b 
L </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>-
-
(2) </p>

<p>The complete rationale for this, detailed studies to support the 
use of this method, and the numerical values used for correction 
are described in Online Supplemental Material II, which is available 
at http://www.jgp.org/cgi/content/full/jgp.200810154/DC1. 
NaCl dilution potentials were measured by switching one hemi-
chamber (usually basolateral) to solution containing different 
concentrations of NaCl (typically 75 mM) with the other compo-
nents identical to the standard Ringer. The osmolality was bal-
anced using mannitol. For alkali metal biionic potentials, one 
hemichamber was switched to a solution containing 150 mM of 
the alkali metal cation chloride salt. For organic cation diffusion 
potentials, we used a solution containing 75 mM of the organic 
cation chloride salt and 75 mM NaCl. Ion permeability ratios were 
deduced from the Goldman-Hodgkin-Katz voltage equation. For 
dilution potentials, </p>

<p>V 
RT 
F 
= -
+ 
+ </p>

<p>ê </p>

<p>ë 
ê </p>

<p>ú </p>

<p>û 
ú 
1 
1 
n 
( 
) , 
a b 
ab </p>

<p>(3) </p>

<p>where V is the apical voltage with respect to the basolateral side, 
␤ = P Cl /P Na , ␣ is the activity ratio of NaCl in apical compared with 
basolateral compartments, and the individual ion activity coeffi -
cients of Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ are assumed to be the same (Guggenheim as-
sumption). This can be rearranged to: </p>

<p>b 
a 
a 
= 
-
-</p>

<p>x 
x 1 
, 
(4) </p>

<p>where x e </p>

<p>VF RT </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>-/ </p>

<p>. The activity coeffi cients used for NaCl at 150 
and 75 mM were 0.752 and 0.797, respectively. The additional Cl </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>arising from the presence of CaCl 2 and MgCl 2 in the solutions was 
ignored, an approximation that should introduce &lt; 2% error. Ab-
solute permeabilities were estimated by the method of Kimizuka 
and Koketsu (1964) , as we have described ( Yu et al., 2003 ; Angelow 
et al., 2006 ). </p>

<p>P 
RT 
F </p>

<p>G 
a </p>

<p>Na </p>

<p>M </p>

<p>= 
+ </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 
i 
( 
) 
, 
b </p>

<p>(5) </p>

<p>where a , the Na 
+ activity at 150 mM concentration, is 112.8 mM. </p>

<p>(WT) mouse claudin-2 or mutants generated by site-directed mu-
tagenesis (QuikChange kit; Agilent Technologies) were cloned 
downstream of the Tet-responsive element into pRevTREP, lipo-
fected into the viral packaging line, PT67, and a stable polyclonal 
population selected with hygromycin. Viral supernatant was then 
used to infect MDCK I TetOff cells ( Angelow et al., 2007b ) in the 
presence of polybrene, and stable clones were selected using clon-
ing cylinders. High-throughput screening of clones was performed 
by seeding them into optical glass-bottomed 96-well culture plates 
(Thermo Fisher Scientifi c) in the presence (Dox+) or absence 
(Dox Ϫ ) of 20 ng/ml doxycycline, immunostaining them with 
claudin-2 antibody (Invitrogen), and identifying positive clones 
by fl uorescence microscopy. Double labeling with anti-ZO1 (Invit-
rogen) was used to confi rm correct localization of claudin-2 to the 
tight junction. Claudin-2 protein expression was confi rmed by 
immunoblotting. An infrared fl uorescence secondary antibody 
(Alexa Fluor 680) was used so that blots could be scanned with an 
infrared detection system (Li-Cor Odyssey) and the bands digi-
tally quantitated. The effect of claudin-2 on expression of endoge-
nous tight junction proteins was assessed by immunoblotting with 
antibodies to claudins 1, 3, 4, and 7 (Invitrogen). 
For freeze-fracture electron microscopy, confl uent monolayers 
were fi xed in 2% glutaraldehyde at 4 ° C for 30 min and processed 
as described previously ( Yu et al., 2003 ). To quantify the number 
of parallel strands in the tight junctions, electron micrographs 
were overlayed with a transparency marked with gridlines, and 
the number of strands crossing each line was counted. The differ-
ence in the median number of strands between Dox+ and Dox Ϫ 
cells was compared using the Wilcoxon ranked-sum test. </p>

<p>Ussing Chamber Electrophysiological Studies 
Our methods are identical to those described previously ( Yu et al., 
2003 ; Angelow et al., 2006 ), with the exception that we have modi-
fi ed the way we correct for liquid junction potentials (vide infra). 
Cells were plated at confl uent density on Snapwell fi lters (Corn-
ing) and cultured for 8 d, which we fi nd is suffi cient to achieve 
steady-state transepithelial resistance and maximal induction of ex-
pression in the TetOff system. The fi lters were mounted in Ussing 
chambers stirred with gas lifts in 100% O 2 at 37 ° C, and voltage/ 
current clamped using Ag/AgCl electrodes bridged by 3 M KCl/3% 
agar pipettes. The standard Ringer solution used at baseline con-
tained (in mM): 150 NaCl, 2 CaCl 2 , 1 MgCl 2 , 10 glucose, and 10 
Tris-HEPES, pH 7.4. In general, data were acquired at 1-s intervals 
using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Acquire and Analyze software</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Physiological Instruments</rs>). 
Conductance and voltage measurements for each condition were 
derived by averaging 5 -10 s worth of data (depending on stability) 
and reported as a single measurement for each monolayer. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Comparison of the different transepithelial transport 
routes. Transcellular/transmembrane channels (left) mediate ion 
transport (arrow) perpendicular to the plane of the lipid bilayer 
(gray), with the pore wall formed predominantly by intramem-
brane domains of the channel polypeptide (orange). Paracellular 
pores such as claudins (right) mediate transport parallel to and 
extracellular to the lipid bilayer, with the pore walls presumably 
constituted by the extracellular domains of claudin polypeptides. </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>Conductance Scanning 
The relative conductance of trans-and paracellular pathways in 
the claudin-2 -expressing cells was determined by high-resolution 
conductance scanning of cell monolayers in horizontal Ussing 
chambers, as described previously ( Gitter et al., 1997 ). An alter-
nating current (24 Hz, 20 μ A) was passed across the epithelium, 
and the electric fi eld generated in the apical bath solution was 
measured with a pair of microelectrodes (vertical tip distance, 
30 -80 μ m) held above the epithelial surface. With the electric 
fi eld measured and the specifi c resistivity of the solution, the local 
current density was calculated. This and the transepithelial volt-
age yielded the local conductance, which was measured in the 
center of the cell body and at the lateral border directly over the 
tight junction. </p>

<p>Radiotracer Flux Assay 
Unidirectional fl uxes of </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>Ca 
2+ were measured in 1-cm 
2 Transwell 
fi lters, as described previously ( Yu et al., 2003 ). In brief, cells were 
bathed in DMEM with 5% FBS (Ca 
2+ concentration of 1.8 mM). 
Trace </p>

<p>45 </p>

<p>CaCl was added to the apical compartment to achieve a 
specifi c activity of &gt; 50 Ci/mol. At 0.5-, 1-, and 2-h intervals (dur-
ing which transport was linear), 100 μ l of solution was withdrawn 
from the basolateral compartment for scintillation counting. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis 
Where permeability or conductance of claudin-2 is reported, we 
took measurements obtained in Dox+ cells and subtracted them 
from the values in Dox Ϫ cells studied in parallel. Values are re-
ported as mean ± SE of measurements performed on three mono-
layers for each condition, unless otherwise specifi ed, and are 
representative of at least two independent experiments. Differ-
ences between the means of continuously distributed variables 
were assessed by the two-tailed unpaired t test, or one-way ANOVA 
with Tukey ' s correction for multiple comparisons, as appropriate. 
P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically signifi cant. </p>

<p>Brownian Dynamics Simulation 
Given the lack of structural detail available for this channel, we 
built our model of claudin-2 in rough analogy to cation-selective 
ligand-gated ion channels (e.g., nicotinic acetylcholine recep-
tors), based on the following points of similarity: (1) minimum 
pore radius; (2) cation selectivity; and (3) channel pore constric-
tion at the location of critical charged groups ( Imoto et al., 1988 ), 
which helps to confer cation selectivity, inter alia. The rationale 
for designing our model channel is to qualitatively support the 
experimental electrophysiology studies reported in this work. </p>

<p>For biionic potentials in which the basolateral chamber was 
exchanged from 150 mM NaCl to 150 mM M 
+ Cl 
Ϫ (where M 
+ is 
another inorganic or organic cation), </p>

<p>V 
RT 
F 
1n 
, 
= 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>ae 
è ç </p>

<p>ö 
ø ÷ </p>

<p>g b 
b 
1 
(6) </p>

<p>where ␥ = P M /P Na . The mean activity coeffi cient of each mon-
ovalent cation halide salt was assumed to be the same as that of 
NaCl. The error in determination of the permeability ratio from 
this approximation was estimated to be no more than 4%. 
Claudin-2 pore size was estimated by a Renkin sieving model 
( Renkin, 1954 ) in which the pore was assumed to be a cylinder of 
diameter, D , across which spherical cations of diameter, d , diffuse. 
For the sake of simplicity, the sole source of friction was assumed 
to be hydrodynamic drag, which, according to the Stokes-Einstein 
relationship, is proportional to d ( Dwyer et al., 1980 ). Thus, the 
apparent permeability of each organic cation, P , was fi t by nonlin-
ear regression to the equation, </p>

<p>P 
A 
d </p>

<p>d 
D 
, </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>= 
-
ae 
è ç </p>

<p>ö 
ø ÷ 
1 
(7) </p>

<p>where A is a composite constant refl ecting both intrinsic pore 
properties and the number of pores. Organic cation diameters 
were derived from empirical data by Hille using Corey-Pauling-
Koltum space-fi lling molecular models ( Dwyer et al., 1980 ). 
For studies of acidifi cation, concentrated HCl was added to one 
or both hemichambers (in most studies to achieve a fi nal pH of 4), 
and conductance was monitored at 1-s intervals. The rate of change 
of conductance was fi tted to a single exponential curve. The titration 
curve of conductance, G, at different pH was fi t to a Hill equation, </p>

<p>G 
G 
K 
H </p>

<p>K 
H </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>= 
+ é ë 
ù û </p>

<p>+ é ë 
ù û </p>

<p>ì 
í 
ï </p>

<p>î ï </p>

<p>ü 
ý 
ï </p>

<p>þ ï </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
max </p>

<p>, 
a 
(8) </p>

<p>where G max is the maximum conductance, and ␣ is a proportion-
ality constant. Values for the equilibrium constant, K a , and the Hill 
coeffi cient, n , were then estimated. 
In studies of temperature dependence, the temperature in the 
Ussing chamber was directly monitored by immersion of a metal 
thermocouple probe, and the water bath was adjusted to achieve 
target solution temperatures in the range of 16 to 37 ° C. Data for 
each monolayer was then fi tted by nonlinear regression to the 
Arrhenius equation to obtain an individual best-fi t estimate of the 
activation energy ( Yu et al., 2003 ; Angelow et al., 2006 ). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Ussing chamber setup and 
method of correcting for junction poten-
tials. The sign of the potential is indicated 
by the arrows, which show the potential of 
the arrow head with respect to the arrow 
tail. Liquid junction potentials in the agar 
bridge pipettes (V L 
a and V L 
b ) are calcu-
lated as the potential of the solution with 
respect to the pipette. V EF and V EM are the 
apparent apical-basolateral potentials that 
are measured experimentally. (A) Setup 
with only a blank fi lter inserted between 
the hemichambers. The potential across 
the blank fi lter, V F , is defi ned as the api-
cal potential with respect to the basolat-
eral side. (B) Setup with a fi lter on which a 
monolayer of cells has been cultured. The 
potential across the monolayer and its fi l-
ter is V M . </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>dependent displacement for ion k , as detailed below. In the pres-
ent implementation, this new confi guration was accepted if 
Rand 
W 
&lt; 
-
exp( 
), 
bD 
where Rand is a uniform random number 
on the interval [0, 1] and ␤ = ( k B T ) </p>

<p>Ϫ 1 </p>

<p>. ⌬ W is the energy change 
between the old and the new confi gurations based on the chosen 
ion k with charge q k . In the present study, ⌬ W was calculated as: </p>

<p>DW W 
W </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>new 
k </p>

<p>old </p>

<p>= 
-
(9) </p>

<p>(10) 
W q 
q 
q q 
r 
qq </p>

<p>k 
k k </p>

<p>stat 
k k </p>

<p>self 
k j </p>

<p>w 
j k </p>

<p>coul 
kj 
k j kj </p>

<p>diel </p>

<p>j k </p>

<p>= 
+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>¹ 
¹ </p>

<p>å 
å </p>

<p>f 
f 
e 
f 
f 
( ) 
q q q 
r </p>

<p>q q 
k T 
D z D </p>

<p>k D </p>

<p>w </p>

<p>coul 
kD </p>

<p>k D kD </p>

<p>diel 
B 
k 
k </p>

<p>e 
f </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>( ) </p>

<p>ln( ( )/ ), 
+ 
-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>where q j and q D are the charges of ion j and D65, respectively. 
Furthermore, D k 
0 and D k ( z ) are the diffusion constants of an ion </p>

<p>k in the bulk and at position z , respectively. The fi rst term in the 
right hand side of Eq. 10 is the effective electrostatic potential 
due to charges (excluding D65) in the fi rst extracellular domain. 
Electrostatic calculations (solutions of the Poisson ' s equation with 
an applied external potential ⌬ V = V L Ϫ V R ) were performed on a 
133 × 133 × 165 lattice with a lattice spacing of 0.5 Å . The second 
term represents the dielectric self-energy or the image potential 
due to the charged ion k . The third term calculates Coulombic in-
teractions between pairs of ions in a dielectrically uniform envi-
ronment characterized by the water dielectric constant w , and 
the fourth term corresponds to the image potential experienced 
by ion k due to the surface charge induced by ion j . These two 
terms account for the ion -ion interaction in a dielectric-inhomo-
geneous medium. The fi fth term corresponds to Coulombic in-
teractions between residue D65 and the chosen ion k in a 
dielectrically uniform environment, and the sixth term contrib-
utes to the image potential experienced by ion k due to the sur-
face charge induced by residue D65. These two terms together 
estimate the Coulombic interactions between ion and the charged 
residue D65. The effects of the dielectric inhomogeneity of the 
channel environment on the ion -ion and ion -D65 electrostatic 
interactions (the fourth and sixth terms in Eq. 10) were imple-
mented using an effi cient empirical pair potential ( Cheng and 
Coalson, 2005 ; Cheng et al., 2007 ): </p>

<p>f 
f f </p>

<p>kj </p>

<p>diel 
k k </p>

<p>diel 
j j </p>

<p>diel 
kj </p>

<p>cr L 
= 
-</p>

<p>¬ 
¬ </p>

<p>2 
e x p ( 
/ ) , 
(11) </p>

<p>where f k k </p>

<p>diel 
¬ </p>

<p>and f j j </p>

<p>diel </p>

<p>¬ are the dielectric contribution to the 
self-energy (or the image potential) for ions k and j with a unit 
(proton) charge. f kD 
diel was also calculated using Eq. 11, with 
f D D </p>

<p>diel 
¬ </p>

<p>taken to be the image potential near the pore surface. A 
detailed description for calculating f k k </p>

<p>diel </p>

<p>¬ can be found in Cheng 
and Coalson (2005) . L is the length of the channel, and r kj is the 
distance between the ions k and j , and c = 2.0. Finally, the last term 
in Eq. 10 is included to account for the effect of the nonuniform 
ion diffusion constant profi le, which in the model considered in 
this study varies only along the channel direction. The diffusion 
constants and the associated ion displacements taken in one DMC 
step obeyed the relation: </p>

<p>h z 
D z h 
D </p>

<p>k 
k 
k 
k </p>

<p>( ) / ( ) 
/ , </p>

<p>2 
0 2 
0 </p>

<p>= 
(12) </p>

<p>where h z 
k ( ) and h k 
0 are the associated ion displacement at posi-
tion z and bulk solution for ion k , respectively. To synchronize 
time between the mobile ions, the ion displacement in the bulk 
for different cations was related to that of chloride ion as follows: </p>

<p>In our Brownian dynamics simulations, claudin-2 was modeled as 
a cylindrical pore with a diameter of 6.5 Å , based on our experi-
mental estimates ( Fig. 7 B ). The pore was assumed to have a 
length of 10 Å , connected to two cone-like vestibules on either 
side, which represent the entrances to the pore and are in contact 
with the extracellular solution ( Fig. 11 A ) (see Online Supple-
mental Material II for details of our simulations, including the 
channel geometry; Fig. S4; both are available at http://www.jgp 
.org/cgi/content/full/jgp.200810154/DC1). The widest part of 
these vestibules was assumed to be 7.6 Å in radius, and the entire 
length of the paracellular pore was assumed to be 32 Å . For sim-
plicity, the dielectric constant inside the aqueous pore was as-
sumed to be the same as that in the bulk solution ( Graf et al., 
2000, 2004 ; Cheng et al., 2005 ), with w = 80, and the cell/claudin-2 
was characterized by a uniform effective dielectric constant, p = 20, 
which falls within the range of previously adopted protein dielec-
tric constant ( Smith et al., 1993 ; Simonson and Brooks, 1996 ; 
Pitera et al., 2001 ). For transmembrane ion channels ( Corry 
et al., 2001 ; Cheng et al., 2005 ), a comparatively smaller p (i.e., 
p = 2 -5) is usually used to account for the low dielectric constant in 
the interior of lipids (i.e., = 2) ( Pethig, 1979 ). For a paracellular 
pore, we anticipate a larger effective dielectric constant should be 
used for p because the pore is formed by the extracellular pro-
tein (i.e., p = 10 -40) and the dipole layer ( Andersen and Fuchs, 
1975 ) formed by the lipid head groups may contribute to an in-
crease in the effective dielectric constant for the cell. D65 was 
treated explicitly as a negatively charged spherical particle to 
mimic the carboxylate moiety of this residue, which is character-
ized by its size R D , charge q D , and the distance between the chan-
nel centerline and the sphere center R C , and located in the middle 
of the pore. The particle description of D65 allowed us to pre-
serve some molecular-level properties of the D65 residue. All 
other charged residues (E53, D76, R30, and K48) in the fi rst ex-
tracellular domain were treated as point charges, and the calcula-
tion of electrostatic potential due to these charges was performed 
by solving Poisson ' s equation. Claudins are multimeric and have 
been proposed to form hexamers ( Mitic et al., 2003 ); therefore, 
residue point charges and D65 particles were inserted six times, 
60 ° apart. The effective charges were assumed to be 0.2 e and 
Ϫ 0.2 e for positive and negative point charges, respectively. For 
simplicity, the positive charges were assumed to face away from 
the channel and be separated from their neighboring negative 
charges by 2.5 Å in the radial direction (perpendicular to the 
channel axis; compare Fig. 11 A ). 
We used a dynamic Monte Carlo (DMC) method to simulate 
ion permeation through the claudin-2 paracellular pore. Com-
plete computational details of our DMC algorithm and its applica-
tion to ion permeation through protein channels can be found in 
the literature ( Graf et al., 2000 ; Cheng et al., 2005, 2007 ; Cheng 
and Coalson, 2005 ). In our DMC algorithm for ion permeation, 
confi gurations were generated by random changes of the ion 
positions. The total number of ions was characterized by N = 
N L + N R + N I + N v . Here, N L and N R are the fi xed numbers of ions on 
the left and right boundaries (gray buffer regions in Fig. 11 A ), which 
were obtained by integrating the given boundary concentrations 
C L and C R over the volumes of the boundary layers. The constant 
concentration boundary condition was imposed by randomly dis-
tributing N L or N R ions in the buffer regions at each Monte Carlo 
cycle. N I is the number of ions inside the system, and N v is the 
number of virtual ions. The total number of ions N is fi xed, and 
N I fl uctuates. N v was introduced only for counting purposes and is 
included to account for dynamic fl uctuation of the number of 
ions in the interior of the system, and to ensure the proportional-
ity of Monte Carlo cycles to real time ( Graf et al., 2000 ). 
One Monte Carlo cycle consisted of N steps. At each step, one 
ion k was randomly chosen to move ± h in one direction ( x , y , or z ) 
if the chosen ion was not a virtual one, where h is a position-</p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>Online Supplemental Material 
In Online Supplemental Material I, we describe in detail the ra-
tionale and procedures used to correct for liquid junction poten-
tials and studies to validate our method. In Online Supplemental 
Material II, we give the full details of our Brownian dynamics sim-
ulations. The physicochemical properties of mobile ions used in 
the simulations are listed in Table S4. Additional simulations were 
performed to determine the sensitivity of claudin-2 pore behavior 
to changes in the channel geometry, protein dielectric constants, 
and ion diffusivity profi les (Fig. S4 and Tables S5 and S6), and to 
changes in the electrostatic fi eld strength generated from D65 
(Figs. S5 and S6). In Online Supplemental Material III, we show the 
results of conductance measurements in the presence of different 
alkali metal cations. The online supplemental material is available 
at http://www.jgp.org/cgi/content/full/jgp.200810154/DC1. </p>

<p>R E S U LT S </p>

<p>Characterization of WT Claudin-2 -expressing Cells </p>

<p>MDCK I TetOff claudin-2 cells exhibit inducible expres-
sion of mouse WT claudin-2 in the absence of doxycy-
cline (Dox Ϫ ), which was completely suppressed in the 
presence of doxycycline (Dox+) ( Fig. 3 A ). By immuno-
fl uorescence, claudin-2 was predominantly colocalized 
with ZO-1 at the apical junctional complex, with some 
additional intracellular staining ( Fig. 3 B ). Induction of 
claudin-2 did not affect the levels of the other claudins 
known to be expressed endogenously in MDCK I cells 
( Fig. 3 C ), and the number of tight junction strands and 
the strand morphology were both found to be un-
changed ( Fig. 3 D ). Cells induced to express claudin-2 
(Dox Ϫ ) had an ‫ف‬ 10-fold increase in transepithelial 
conductance ( Fig. 4 A ). Conductance scanning showed 
that claudin-2 expression markedly increased the con-
ductance near the intercellular junctions, but not at the 
cell bodies, confi rming that the route of claudin-2 con-
ductance was paracellular ( Fig. 5 A ). The dose depen-
dence of the claudin-2 effect was assessed by varying the 
concentration of doxycycline. We found that the in-
crease in conductance mirrored claudin-2 protein levels </p>

<p>h 
D 
h 
D </p>

<p>X 
X 
Cl 
Cl </p>

<p>0 2 
0 
0 2 
0 </p>

<p>/ 
/ , 
= 
(13) </p>

<p>where h X 
0 , h Cl 
0 and D X 
0 , D Cl 
0 are the bulk displacement and 
diffusivity for cations (X represents Li 
+ , Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, Rb 
+ , or Cs </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) and 
chloride ions, respectively. The total simulation time T s is related 
to the number of the Monte Carlo cycles N c as: </p>

<p>T s </p>

<p>Cl 
c </p>

<p>Cl </p>

<p>h N 
D 
= </p>

<p>0 2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>6 
. 
(14) </p>

<p>Note that in our DMC method to simulate ion permeation, a 
hard core -excluded volume potential was also included. In particu-
lar, we did not permit overlap between an ion and the protein chan-
nel, between any two ions, or between ions and D65 residues. If an 
attempted move gave rise to this type of overlap, it was rejected. 
The computational box (excluding the buffer region) had a 
size of L x × L y × L z = 66 × 66 × 82 Å . The constructed model chan-
nel extended from z = Ϫ 16 ( Å ) to z = 16 ( Å ). To our knowledge, 
the diffusion constant of an ion inside a protein channel has yet 
to be experimentally measured for any channel. On the basis of 
molecular dynamics investigations of diffusion constants for K </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>and Cl 
Ϫ inside the OmpF porin channel ( Im and Roux, 2002 ) 
and K 
+ in gramicidin A ( Mamonov et al., 2006 ), the diffusivities 
for different ions in claudin-2 were assumed to be linearly re-
duced from their bulk values near the channel entrance ( z L = Ϫ 20 Å 
and z R = 20 Å ) to half their bulk values ( z L = Ϫ 16 Å and z R = 16 Å ), 
and maintained at half their bulk diffusivities throughout the 
whole pore domain ( Ϫ 16 Å &lt; z &lt; 16 Å ). (Note that using an inter-
nal diffusion constant of roughly half the bulk diffusion constant 
of permeant Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ ions in two independent Brownian dy-
namics simulations of ion fl ow through the glycine receptor, 
which has a pore diameter of approximately 6 Å , yielded conduc-
tance values in reasonable agreement with experiments [ O ' Mara 
et al., 2003 ; Cheng et al., 2005 ]. The radii and the bulk diffusivi-
ties of different ions were taken from Pauling [1948] and Hille 
[2001] and are listed in Table S4, which is available at http:// 
www.jgp.org/cgi/content/full/jgp.200810154/DC1.) For simpli-
fi cation, the charged residue D65 was assumed to be fi xed. In the 
present study, R D = 0.5 Å , R c = 3.75 Å , q D = Ϫ 0.1 (e), and f D D </p>

<p>diel </p>

<p>« = 3 0 
. 
K B T were used for D65. The displacement of Cl 
Ϫ ions in the bulk 
was set to h Cl 
0 = 0.5 Å for all simulations. The dilution potential 
and biionic potential were extracted from the Brownian dynamics 
simulations following the same procedure used in the experimen-
tal studies. </p>

<p>Figure 3. Characterization of MDCK I TetOff cells stably transfected with WT claudin-2. (A) Immunoblot of claudin-2 in lysate from 
cells grown in the presence (+) or absence ( Ϫ ) of doxycycline (Dox). (B) Double immunofl uorescence staining of Dox Ϫ cells using an 
antibody to claudin-2 (left) and ZO-1 (right). En face confocal images (top) and vertical images (bottom) at the position indicated by 
the green line are shown. (C) Effect of claudin-2 induction on expression of other tight junction membrane proteins. Cell lysates were 
immunoblotted with antibodies against the indicated claudin isoforms or occludin. (D) Frequency histogram of tight junction strand 
counts measured in freeze-fracture replicas (154 counts per replica). Median strand number for both Dox+ and Dox Ϫ cells was 4. </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>varied within the physiological range, without evidence 
of saturation ( Fig. 5, B and C ). The apparently linear 
conductance -concentration relationship makes it un-
likely that a surface charge effect is the cause of the 
Na 
+ selectivity. 
What is the basis for the cation selectivity of claudin-2? 
To investigate the interaction between permeating 
cations and the claudin-2 pore, we determined the per-
meability of claudin-2 to other alkali metal cations us-
ing biionic potentials ( Fig. 7 A and Table I ). The 
permeability sequence was found to be: K 
+ &gt; Rb 
+ &gt; Na 
+ &gt; 
Li 
+ &gt; &gt; Cs 
+ . This sequence is quite different from the 
sequence of their free-solution mobilities and resem-
bles Eisenman selectivity sequence V -VIII. This sug-
gests that permeating cations have to dehydrate to 
enter the claudin-2 pore, and that there must be a 
moderately high fi eld strength, negatively charged in-
teraction site within the pore that stabilizes the dehy-
drated cation ( Diamond and Wright, 1969 ; Eisenman 
and Horn, 1983 ). This would also explain the high se-
lectivity for cations over anions. However, the ratio be-
tween the permeabilities of the most permeable cation 
(K 
+ ) and the least permeable (Cs 
+ ) was 1.6, which is 
quite narrow and suggests that the interaction site is 
partially hydrated. To assess the size of the claudin-2 </p>

<p>( Fig. 6 ), consistent with the idea that the increase in con-
ductance occurs through claudin-2 pores. 
To determine the relative and absolute permeability 
to Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ , NaCl dilution potentials were measured 
( Fig. 4 B ). Dilution potentials determined at different api-
cal/basolateral NaCl activity ratios fi t well to a Goldman-
Hodgkin-Katz equation ( Fig. 4 C ). We therefore used 
150 mM NaCl/75 mM NaCl dilution potentials and the 
Goldman-Hodgkin-Katz equation to derive relative per-
meabilities for Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ . Table I lists the raw data, 
which is summarized in Fig. 4 D . Induction of claudin-2 
increased P Na by ‫ف‬ 10-fold compared with control Dox+ 
cells; P Cl was increased approximately fourfold. By sub-
tracting the conductance and permeability in Dox+ 
cells from that in Dox Ϫ cells, we derived the increase in 
transepithelial conductance and permeability attribut-
able to the introduction of claudin-2 -based paracellu-
lar pores ( Fig. 4 E ). We therefore have a quantitative 
measure of the macroscopic conductance and permea-
bility of a claudin-based pore. By this method, the per-
meability of claudin-2 to Na 
+ was determined to be 7.5 ± 
0.9 times its permeability to Cl 
Ϫ . Thus, claudin-2 forms 
cation-selective pores. Furthermore, these pores ap-
pear to be nonrectifying and exhibit a fairly linear rela-
tionship between conductance and Na 
+ concentrations </p>

<p>Figure 4. Conductance and NaCl permeability of the WT claudin-2 pore. (A) Transepithelial conductance in MDCK I TetOff cells that 
were either uninduced (Dox+) or induced to express WT claudin-2 (Dox Ϫ ). Columns show mean ± SE ( n = 3 monolayers in a single 
experiment) and are representative of four independent experiments. (B) Raw voltage traces, V TE (apical with reference to basolateral), 
acquired in a typical NaCl dilution potential experiment. The NaCl concentrations of the Ringer solutions on each side of the monolay-
ers are shown at the top (in mM). Gaps in acquisition occurred during solution exchange. (C) Determination of relative permeability 
from NaCl dilution potentials. The transepithelial diffusion potential, V TE , was determined at different NaCl activity ratios (apical activity/ 
basolateral activity) and plotted on a log-linear scale. Data were fi t by nonlinear regression to the Goldman-Hodgkin-Katz equation with 
best-fi t values (95% CI) for P Na /P Cl of 1.5 (1.4 -1.6) for Dox+ and 6.3 (5.7 -6.8) for Dox Ϫ . (D) Permeability to Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ in Dox+ and 
Dox Ϫ cells, determined from dilution potential measurements (see A for color code). (E) Apparent permeability of the claudin-2 pore 
to Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ , determined by subtracting measurements in Dox+ cells from those in Dox Ϫ cells. </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>pore, consistent with the predictions of the alkali metal 
Eisenman sequence. 
A protein can form a negatively charged site from fi xed 
net charges or partial charges from dipoles. When the pH 
of the extracellular fl uid was lowered, claudin-2 conduc-
tance fell promptly, at a rate (time constant 8.2 ± 0.02 s) 
similar to that of solution mixing in our Ussing chambers, 
suggesting a diffusion-limited process ( Fig. 7 C ). Moreover, </p>

<p>pore, its permeability to three organic cations, methyl-
amine, ethylamine, and tetramethylammonium, was 
determined and fi t to a Renkin equation ( Fig. 7 B and 
Table II ). The pore diameter estimated by nonlinear 
regression was 6.5 ± 0.3 Å . This is smaller than the di-
ameter of a hydrated Na 
+ ion, 7.2 Å ( Nightingale, 1959 ), 
so that Na 
+ would likely have to shed at least part of 
its hydration shell to permeate through the claudin-2 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Characteristics of the WT claudin-2 pore conductance. (A) Conductance scanning to distinguish the effect of claudin-2 on transcel-
lular from paracellular conductance. Transcellular conductance was determined by scanning above the cell body, and paracellular conductance 
was determined by scanning over the lateral cell border (TJ). Results show the mean of 12 -15 conductance measurements per site performed 
on two fi lters each. (B) Relationship between transepithelial voltage (V) and the current (I) carried by claudin-2. (C) Relationship between 
extracellular Na 
+ activity and claudin-2 conductance. Na 
+ concentration was adjusted by isosmotic replacement of NaCl with mannitol. </p>

<p>TA B L E I </p>

<p>Alkali Metal Cation Diffusion Potential Measurements and Calculations of Permeability </p>

<p>WT 
E53Q 
D65N 
D76N 
TM </p>

<p>Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ 
Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ 
Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ 
Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ 
Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ </p>

<p>Mean SE Mean SE Mean SD Mean SE Mean SE Mean SE Mean SE Mean SE Mean SE Mean SE </p>

<p>Conductance (mS) 
0.90 0.08 9.52 0.20 0.32 0.03 10.43 0.13 0.79 0.04 3.87 0.04 0.51 0.05 9.10 0.34 0.42 0.01 
2.76 0.24 </p>

<p>2:1 NaCl dilution potential 
(mV) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Ϫ 5.43 0.38 Ϫ 11.93 0.41 Ϫ 0.30 0.80 Ϫ 12.33 0.70 Ϫ 2.77 0.38 Ϫ 9.56 0.63 Ϫ 3.47 0.87 Ϫ 12.05 0.43 2.62 0.40 Ϫ 6.74 0.26 </p>

<p>Biionic potentials (mV) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>LiCl 
Ϫ 2.31 0.52 Ϫ 1.73 0.42 Ϫ 3.17 0.30 Ϫ 2.36 0.27 Ϫ 4.35 0.33 Ϫ 7.57 0.30 Ϫ 2.42 0.43 Ϫ 2.30 0.82 Ϫ 3.02 0.35 Ϫ 7.07 0.24 </p>

<p>KCl 
4.78 0.53 4.98 0.46 4.47 0.69 5.63 0.50 5.32 0.52 6.04 0.42 4.92 0.51 4.91 0.44 5.17 0.61 
5.71 0.29 </p>

<p>RbCl 
3.31 0.28 2.07 0.49 4.79 0.54 2.17 0.46 4.83 0.56 3.54 0.23 4.23 0.53 2.35 0.59 5.95 0.66 
3.75 0.25 </p>

<p>CsCl 
Ϫ 0.74 0.24 Ϫ 5.46 0.58 3.87 0.24 Ϫ 6.91 0.50 2.60 0.39 Ϫ 1.75 0.32 1.73 0.58 Ϫ 4.73 0.72 5.48 0.56 Ϫ 0.77 0.23 </p>

<p>Relative permeabilities </p>

<p>P Na /P Cl 
1.99 0.10 6.11 0.55 1.05 0.10 6.98 1.08 1.41 0.07 3.79 0.39 1.56 0.16 6.32 0.62 0.73 0.04 
2.39 0.09 </p>

<p>P Li /P Na 
0.88 0.03 0.93 0.02 0.78 0.02 0.90 0.01 0.74 0.02 0.69 0.01 0.86 0.03 0.90 0.03 0.74 0.04 
0.67 0.01 </p>

<p>P K /P Na 
1.29 0.03 1.24 0.03 1.37 0.08 1.27 0.03 1.38 0.05 1.32 0.03 1.34 0.05 1.24 0.03 1.51 0.08 
1.34 0.02 </p>

<p>P Rb /P Na 
1.20 0.01 1.10 0.02 1.39 0.06 1.10 0.02 1.34 0.05 1.18 0.02 1.29 0.05 1.11 0.03 1.60 0.09 
1.21 0.02 </p>

<p>P Cs /P Na 
0.96 0.01 0.79 0.02 1.31 0.03 0.74 0.01 1.18 0.03 0.92 0.01 1.11 0.04 0.81 0.02 1.55 0.08 
0.96 0.01 </p>

<p>Absolute permeabilities ( × 
10 
Ϫ 6 cm/s) </p>

<p>P Na 
1.47 0.11 20.21 0.50 0.40 0.04 22.43 0.25 1.14 0.06 7.55 0.12 0.75 0.05 19.38 0.45 0.43 0.01 
4.80 0.41 </p>

<p>P Li 
1.30 0.14 18.72 0.61 0.31 0.03 20.24 0.50 0.85 0.07 5.19 0.17 0.65 0.05 17.50 0.30 0.32 0.02 
3.22 0.32 </p>

<p>P K 
1.90 0.11 25.04 0.64 0.54 0.06 28.50 0.51 1.57 0.07 9.99 0.21 1.01 0.08 23.97 1.09 0.66 0.03 
6.42 0.48 </p>

<p>P Rb 
1.76 0.12 22.12 0.62 0.55 0.06 24.62 0.43 1.53 0.07 8.91 0.11 0.97 0.09 21.50 1.09 0.69 0.03 
5.83 0.47 </p>

<p>P Cs 
1.41 0.09 15.86 0.42 0.52 0.06 16.55 0.34 1.34 0.06 6.95 0.08 0.84 0.07 15.78 0.84 0.67 0.03 
4.61 0.40 </p>

<p>P Cl 
0.75 0.10 3.36 0.29 0.39 0.05 3.39 0.57 0.81 0.05 2.03 0.20 0.50 0.09 3.15 0.41 0.60 0.02 
2.02 0.19 </p>

<p>Data have been corrected for fi lter and fl uid resistance and for liquid junction potentials as described in the online supplemental material and are representative of 
one experiment, showing the mean and standard error of three monolayers each. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Diffusion potentials are measured on the side containing 150 mM NaCl, relative to the side with 75 mM NaCl (dilution potential) or 150 mM XCl (biionic 
potentials). </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>tivity to show convincingly that the fi rst extracellular 
domain of claudins lines the paracellular pore ( Colegio 
et al., 2002, 2003 ; Van Itallie et al., 2003 ). However, it is 
unclear whether these mutants also inform on the loca-
tion of the ion selectivity fi lter or merely refl ect artifi -
cially created electrostatic fi elds within the pore that 
affect ion permeation. Indeed, the fact that mutations 
of most charged residues in the fi rst extracellular do-
main have a similar effect would suggest the latter. 
There are three acidic residues in the fi rst extracellular 
loop of claudin-2: E53, D65, and D76. To test the hy-
pothesis that one or more of these might be responsible 
for the negatively charged cation-interaction site in the 
claudin-2 pore, we mutated each of these to its neutral, 
polar counterpart (E53Q, D65N, and D76N), generated 
a triple mutant (TM) bearing all three mutations, and 
generated stable, inducible MDCK I TetOff cell lines ex-
pressing each mutant. By neutralizing instead of revers-
ing the normal charge at each site, we expect to pinpoint 
only those residues that are part of the normal selectiv-
ity mechanism. Clones were selected that expressed simi-
lar levels of claudin-2 protein to WT and showed good 
induction and suppression. Mutant cell lines exhibited 
similar levels of expression and subcellular localization 
of claudin-2 protein to the WT claudin-2 clone, and 
similarly had little effect on expression of endogenous 
claudins ( Fig. 8 ). 
When the conductance and Na 
+ and Cl 
Ϫ permeability 
of the mutant claudin-2 proteins were measured, E53Q 
and D76N were found to be very similar to WT claudin-2 
(WT). However, D65N exhibited threefold lower con-
ductance and Na 
+ permeability, with no change in Cl </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>permeability, and the TM was indistinguishable from 
D65N ( Fig. 9, A and B ). Thus, D65 is required for maxi-
mum cation permeability of claudin-2. The temperature 
dependence of conductance and Na 
+ permeability was 
measured and fi t to the Arrhenius equation to deter-
mine the activation energy of permeation (E a ). Mutation 
of D65 to N increased the activation energy for conduc-
tance (41.8 ± 4.3 kJ/mol vs. 39.7 ± 1.9 kJ/mol for WT) 
and P Na (42.7 ± 2.0 kJ/mol vs. 39.0 ± 1.4 kJ/mol for WT) 
( Fig. 9, C and D ). The observed changes of 2 -4 kJ/mol 
are the right order of magnitude to account for the per-
meability changes (an e -fold reduction in P Na would be 
expected with an increase in the height of the energy 
barrier of 1 RT = 2.6 kJ/mol) and suggest that D65N in 
some way impedes the kinetics of Na 
+ permeation, rather 
than reducing the number of available pores. Further-
more, the permeability pattern of organic cations and 
estimated pore diameter (5.8 ± 0.3 Å ) of D65N was not 
signifi cantly different from that of WT claudin-2 ( Fig. 7 B ), 
excluding steric hindrance as the explanation. Thus, 
the most likely explanation is that D65 forms part of the 
electrostatic cation interaction site. 
Three independent experiments suggest that D65 is 
part of the negatively charged interaction site. First, we </p>

<p>the acidifi cation-induced reduction in conductance was 
due predominantly to a reduction in the Na 
+ permeability 
of claudin-2 ( Fig. 7 D ), with no apparent change in Cl </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>permeability. This suggests that acidifi cation is titrating 
and neutralizing fi xed net negative charge(s) at the cation 
interaction site. Consistent with this, the relationship be-
tween pH and conductance could be fi t to a single-site 
model with a Hill coeffi cient of 1.0 and a pK a of 4.9 ± 0.1, 
which is well within the pK a range for the side chain car-
boxylate groups of acidic amino acid residues ( Fig. 7 E ). </p>

<p>Characterization of Cells Expressing Charge-neutralizing 
Mutants of Claudin-2 </p>

<p>Anderson, van Itallie, and colleagues have used charge-
reversing mutations that alter paracellular charge selec-</p>

<p>Figure 6. Dose -response relationship between claudin-2 protein 
level and Na 
+ permeability. (A) Immunoblot showing expression 
of WT claudin-2 (24 kD band) induced (no doxycycline) or sup-
pressed with varying concentrations of doxycycline. (B) Quantita-
tion of immunoblot bands to assess claudin-2 protein abundance. 
(C) Permeability to Na 
+ (P Na ), as determined by NaCl dilution 
potential measurement. </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>mutants were very similar, with the exception of Li 
+ . 
The relative permeability to Li 
+ , P Li /P Na , was ‫ف‬ 1 for WT, 
E53Q, and D76N. However, D65N and TM exhibited 
markedly lower P Li /P Na ; their curves were completely 
superimposable, and the predicted selectivity sequence 
was K 
+ &gt; Rb 
+ &gt; Na 
+ &gt; Cs 
+ &gt; &gt; Li 
+ (Eisenman sequence V). 
Li 
+ is the smallest and hence most strongly hydrated al-
kali metal. In order for Li 
+ to permeate a narrow pore 
such as claudin-2, the huge energy cost of dehydration 
must be offset by an energetically favorable interaction 
with a site within the pore. Inspection of Eisenman ' s se-
quences shows that as the fi eld strength of an electro-
static interaction site decreases, the fi rst consequence is 
that the relative position of Li 
+ is progressively demoted. 
Thus, the relative permeability of Li 
+ is a highly sensitive 
marker of the fi eld strength of an intrapore electrostatic 
interaction site, and its reduction in D65N and TM 
strongly supports the notion that the side chain of D65 
is part of such a site. 
Third, we showed that acidifi cation to pH 4.0 mark-
edly reduced the conductance of E53Q and D76N to the 
same extent as WT, whereas D65N and TM showed much 
less inhibition, suggesting loss of a titratable, negatively </p>

<p>were able to demonstrate by radiotracer fl ux assay that 
Ca 
2+ passes through WT claudin-2 pores with a permea-
bility approximately fourfold lower than Na 
+ . If D65 is 
an electrostatic interaction site for permeating cations, 
one would expect abolition of the net charge to have a 
disproportionately large effect on the permeability of 
polyvalent, compared with monovalent, cations. Indeed, 
whereas P Na (WT)/P Na (D65N) was 2.9 ± 0.1, P Ca (WT)/ 
P Ca (D65N) was 22.1 ± 0.8, indicating that loss of the car-
boxylate side chain of D65 disproportionately inhibits 
Ca 
2+ permeation ( Fig. 10 A ). 
Second, we determined the alkali metal cation per-
meability sequence for all the mutants. E53Q and D76N 
exhibited high permeabilities to all the alkali metal cat-
ions, and the selectivity was identical to WT. D65N and 
TM, however, both showed substantially lower permea-
bilities to all the alkali metal cations and, more impor-
tantly, a differently shaped selectivity profi le ( Fig. 10 C ). 
To control for the large differences in overall permea-
bility, we normalized all the values for each mutant to its 
P Na and plotted the relative permeabilities of each cat-
ion, X </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>, as P X /P Na ( Fig. 10 D ). Now one can see that the 
relative permeabilities for most of the cations for all the </p>

<p>Figure 7. Biophysical properties of the WT claudin-2 pore. (A) Permeability of WT claudin-2 to alkali metal cations, as determined by 
biionic potentials. (B) Estimation of pore size. The permeability of WT and D65N claudin-2 to organic cations (P X ) was calculated from 
biionic potentials. Curves were fi t by nonlinear regression to a Renkin equation with pore diameter, D , of 6.5 ± 0.3 Å (WT) and 5.8 ± 0.3 Å 
(D65N). MA, methylamine; EA, ethylamine; TMA, tetramethylammonium. (Inset) Data are replotted as √ (P X /P Na ) versus diameter to 
show linear fi t. (C) Conductance trace showing the effect of acidifi cation of the apical compartment to pH 4.0 on cells expressing WT 
claudin-2. (D) Summary of effect of acidifi cation to pH 4.0 on conductance and P Na of WT claudin-2. (E) Effect of acidifi cation to dif-
ferent pH on conductance, G, relative to that at pH 7. The curve shows the fi t to a Hill equation, G = G max { (K a + ␣ [H 
+ ] 
n )/(K a + [H 
+ ] 
n ) } , 
where G max is the maximum conductance, K a is the equilibrium constant, n is the Hill coeffi cient, and ␣ is a proportionality constant. 
Best-fi t values were n = 1.0 and pK a = 4.9 ± 0.1. </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>charged side chain of aspartate-65 positioned at the 
center and facing into the lumen ( Fig. 11 A ). Because 
claudins are likely multimeric and possibly hexameric, 
we assumed that D65 contributed six identical partial 
charges. The claudin-2 pore shows no obvious current 
rectifi cation, so we further assumed that D65 is located 
in the middle of the selectivity fi lter to avoid possible 
current rectifi cation arising from asymmetry of the 
channel geometry and fi xed charge location. Referring 
to the (symmetric) channel geometry presented in 
Fig. 11 A , placing D65 5 Å away from the channel center 
toward the left channel entrance induced a slight cur-
rent rectifi cation characterized by ␥ +40mv / ␥ Ϫ 40mv = 1.25 
because more cations were attracted into the channel 
entrance from the left side (at +40 mV) than from the 
right side (at Ϫ 40 mV). 
As expected, this simple model was suffi cient to re-
produce the high degree of cation selectivity of the 
pore. This model pore exhibited P Cl /P Na of 0.07 ± 0.03 </p>

<p>charged site ( Fig. 10 B ). Examination of alkali metal 
selectivity revealed that acidifi cation of WT claudin-2 
showed a trend to reduce relative Li 
+ permeability, con-
sistent with titration of the negative charge on the inter-
action site ( Fig. 10 E ). Finally, when D65 was mutated to 
N and acidifi ed to pH 4, the magnitude of the reduction 
in Li 
+ permeability was the same as with either D65N or 
acidifi cation alone; in other words, there was no additive 
effect. This is consistent with the hypothesis that the 
functional consequence of acidifi cation was caused by 
titration of the side chain carboxylate of D65. </p>

<p>Brownian Dynamics Modeling of Claudin-2 Pore Behavior </p>

<p>Further evidence in support of the mechanism for 
charge and alkali metal selectivity of claudin-2 was ob-
tained by using Brownian dynamics simulations to 
model the behavior of the pore. We used a simple model 
in which the pore was assumed to be a 6.5-Å diameter 
cylinder with conical vestibules and the negatively </p>

<p>TA B L E I I </p>

<p>Organic Cation Diffusion Potential Measurements and Calculations of Permeability </p>

<p>WT 
D65N </p>

<p>Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ 
Dox+ 
Dox Ϫ </p>

<p>Mean diameter ( Å ) </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE 
Mean 
SE </p>

<p>Conductance (mS) 
0.82 
0.07 
6.20 
0.22 
1.30 
0.10 
3.59 
0.26 </p>

<p>2:1 NaCl dilution potential (mV) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Ϫ 2.12 
0.47 
Ϫ 11.68 
0.30 Ϫ 0.33 
0.22 Ϫ 9.09 
0.19 </p>

<p>Biionic potentials (mV) </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Methylamine 
1.67 
0.14 
Ϫ 2.42 
0.28 
2.07 
0.15 Ϫ 1.55 
0.35 </p>

<p>Ethylamine 
Ϫ 1.19 
0.25 
Ϫ 8.08 
0.39 Ϫ 0.67 
0.26 Ϫ 6.96 
0.47 </p>

<p>TMA 
Ϫ 3.20 
0.36 
Ϫ 11.84 
0.43 Ϫ 2.55 
0.30 Ϫ 10.05 
0.53 </p>

<p>TEA 
Ϫ 4.18 
0.29 
Ϫ 12.03 
0.41 Ϫ 3.50 
0.25 Ϫ 10.10 
0.49 </p>

<p>Arginine 
Ϫ 4.07 
0.35 
Ϫ 10.60 
0.52 Ϫ 3.21 
0.31 Ϫ 8.81 
0.60 </p>

<p>NMDG 
Ϫ 4.77 
0.41 
Ϫ 11.18 
0.19 Ϫ 3.73 
0.28 Ϫ 8.79 
0.64 </p>

<p>Relative permeabilities </p>

<p>P Na /P Cl 
1.33 
0.08 
5.94 
0.42 
1.04 
0.03 
3.45 
0.11 </p>

<p>P Methylamine /P Na 
1.11 
0.02 
0.70 
0.02 
1.19 
0.02 
0.75 
0.03 </p>

<p>P Ethylamine /P Na 
0.75 
0.03 
0.31 
0.02 
0.80 
0.03 
0.33 
0.03 </p>

<p>P TMA /P Na 
0.52 
0.03 
0.09 
0.03 
0.55 
0.04 
0.13 
0.03 </p>

<p>P TEA /P Na 
0.41 
0.02 
0.08 
0.02 
0.43 
0.03 
0.12 
0.03 </p>

<p>P Arginine /P Na 
0.40 
0.04 
0.16 
0.04 
0.47 
0.04 
0.19 
0.04 </p>

<p>P NMDG /P Na 
0.32 
0.05 
0.12 
0.02 
0.41 
0.04 
0.19 
0.04 </p>

<p>Absolute permeabilities ( × 10 
Ϫ 6 cm/s) </p>

<p>P Na 
1.90 
1.14 
0.08 
13.03 
0.45 
1.64 
0.12 
6.86 
0.47 </p>

<p>P Methylamine 
3.78 
1.28 
0.11 
9.16 
0.55 
1.96 
0.17 
5.23 
0.47 </p>

<p>P Ethylamine 
4.58 
0.87 
0.08 
4.12 
0.45 
1.33 
0.14 
2.33 
0.29 </p>

<p>P TMA 
5.50 
0.59 
0.06 
1.30 
0.40 
0.94 
0.11 
0.93 
0.22 </p>

<p>P TEA 
6.58 
0.46 
0.04 
1.16 
0.39 
0.74 
0.09 
0.90 
0.20 </p>

<p>P Arginine 
6.96 
0.54 
0.08 
2.24 
0.64 
0.84 
0.09 
1.34 
0.28 </p>

<p>P NMDG 
7.29 
0.44 
0.07 
1.73 
0.29 
0.72 
0.08 
1.35 
0.30 </p>

<p>Data have been corrected for fi lter and fl uid resistance and for liquid junction potentials as described in the online supplemental material and summarize 
several independent experiments ( n = 12 monolayers, except for arginine and NMDG biionic potentials, where n = 6). 
a The mean diameter of the alkali metal cations is defi ned as twice the Pauling radius of the nonhydrated ion. The mean diameter of the organic cations, 
derived from the data of Dwyer et al. (1980) , is defi ned as the geometric mean of the dimensions of a rectangular box that would contain the ion as 
determined using Corey-Pauling-Koltum space-fi lling molecular models. 
b Diffusion potentials are measured on the side containing 150 mM NaCl, relative to the side with 75 mM NaCl (dilution potential) or 75 mM NaCl/75 mM 
XCl (biionic potentials). </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>Our model explains why we observed a linear con-
ductance -concentration profi le ( Fig. 5 C ) instead of 
a saturating function, as would be expected with an 
Na 
+ binding site. Our model predicts that saturation 
does in fact occur, but only at very high Na 
+ concentra-
tions (half-maximal conductance at an Na 
+ activity of 
600 mM), so that the relationship appears pseudolin-
ear at the physiological Na 
+ concentrations used in </p>

<p>and a linear current -voltage relationship ( Fig. 11 B ). 
Neutralizing the charge on D65 (equivalent to the 
D65N mutation) reduced Na permeability by ‫ف‬ 2/3. Ad-
ditionally, it was able to discriminate between the behav-
iors of different alkali metal cations to a certain degree 
based on the different sizes and the different diffusivity 
profi les of the various permeating cations. Thus, the 
model closely resembles our experimental results. </p>

<p>Figure 8. Characterization of MDCK I TetOff cell lines expressing charge-neutralizing mutants of claudin-2. (A) Immunoblot of clau-
din-2 expression in clones stably transfected with WT claudin-2 (WT), the indicated individual claudin-2 mutants, and a TM (TM = 
E53Q, D65N, and D76N) grown in the presence (+) or absence ( Ϫ ) of doxycycline (Dox), using antibodies to the indicated claudin 
isoforms. (B) Confocal images showing immunofl uorescence localization of mutant claudin-2 protein in Dox Ϫ cells. (C) Effect of clau-
din-2 induction on expression of other tight junction membrane proteins. Cell lysates were immunoblotted with antibodies against the 
indicated claudin isoforms or occludin. (A and C) White lines indicate that intervening lanes have been spliced out. </p>

<p>Figure 9. Effect of charge-neu-
tralizing mutations in the fi rst 
extracellular domain on clau-
din-2 permeability. (A and B) 
Conductance and Na 
+ and Cl </p>

<p>Ϫ </p>

<p>permeability of claudin-2 WT 
(WT) and mutants (TM = E53Q, 
D65N, and D76N). *, P &lt; 0.001 
compared with WT. (C) Arrhe-
nius plot showing the relation-
ship between conductance (log 
scale) and the reciprocal of 
the absolute temperature (T). 
(D) Activation energies (E a ) for 
conductance and permeability 
to Na 
+ and Li 
+ , determined by 
linear regression from Arrhenius 
plots. *, P &lt; 0.05; **, P &lt; 0.01. </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>among different cations will be K, Cs, Rb &gt; Na &gt; Li, 
based on bulk ion diffusivities ( Pauling, 1948 ) (com-
pare Table S4). (2) Entropic effects (i.e., excluded vol-
ume effect). Assuming the same ion diffusivity profi les 
for all cations (compare Table S6, model 4), the rela-
tive permeability ratio among different cations is Li &gt; 
Na &gt; K &gt; Rb &gt; Cs. Our results show that relatively small 
differences in cation radius can result in detectable 
differences in selectivity when the geometric features 
of the channel, dielectric and diffusion constants for 
the ions, etc., are chosen appropriately. It should be 
noted, however, that our simple model is unsuccessful 
in one respect: when the negative charge on the D65 
residue is abolished, the relative permeability plot re-
mains qualitatively similar to that shown in Fig. 11 D 
for the anionic D65 case. That is, the relative permea-
bility of Li 
+ does not decrease in the Brownian dynam-
ics simulations as it does experimentally (compare 
Fig. 10 D ). This failure may be due to the highly sim-
plifi ed rendering of the D65 residue adopted here, as 
noted in Discussion below. </p>

<p>our experiments ( Fig. 11 C ). The model also allows 
us to estimate the conductance of a single claudin-2 
pore over a range of Na 
+ concentrations. At a concen-
tration of 150 mM Na 
+ , the conductance was ‫ف‬ 70 pS, 
and at saturation it was 450 pS. 
Fig. 11 D shows the sequence of cation selectivity 
predicted by the Brownian dynamics model developed 
herein, which bears a respectable similarity to the cor-
responding experimental curve shown in Fig. 7 A . It is 
not obvious a priori that such a model can distinguish 
between cations of the same valence, and indeed pre-
vious discussions have expressed pessimism concern-
ing the fl exibility of Brownian dynamics simulations in 
this regard ( Corry et al., 2005 ). The primary differ-
ences between, say, an Na 
+ ion and a Cs 
+ ion in this 
type of simulation are the radius of the bare ion and 
its bulk diffusivity. Thus, there are two competing ef-
fects in our numerical models that determine the rela-
tive permeability ratio among different alkali cations. 
(1) Ion diffusivity profi les. Assuming the same ion size 
for all alkali cations, the relative permeability ratio </p>

<p>Figure 10. Evidence that aspartate-65 
is an electrostatic cation interaction 
site. (A) Effect of D65N on permeabil-
ity to Ca </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>, as measured by radiotracer 
fl ux assay. (B) Effect of acidifi cation to 
pH 4.0 on P Na of WT and mutant clau-
din-2. (C and D) Absolute and relative 
permeabilities to alkali metal cations 
of WT and mutant claudin-2 (see B 
for explanation of symbols). (E) Rela-
tive permeability to Li 
+ (P Li /P Na ) of 
WT or D65N claudin-2 at pH 7.0 or 4. 
*, P &lt; 0.01; **, P &lt; 0.001 compared with 
WT at pH 7.0 ( n = 6 -9). </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>This means that even if claudin-2 did subtly alter the com-
position or arrangement of endogenous tight junction 
strands, any such effects on conductance would be small 
relative to the conductance increase due to the insertion 
of claudin-2 pores, and so the accuracy of our measure-
ments should not be signifi cantly compromised. 
It is generally assumed that paracellular pores are 
wide and fairly nonselective. However, we fi nd that clau-
din-2 is narrow ( ‫ف‬ 6.5 Å diameter), and cation selective 
(P Na /P Cl = 7.5). There are inherent limitations in any 
method to estimate pore diameter. We chose to use cat-
ions as size probes because we wished to know the effec-
tive size of the pore for cation permeation. However, 
there are only a few small nitrogenous organic cations. 
Moreover, the chemical characteristics, and particularly 
the availability of groups for hydrogen bonding, of dif-
ferent nitrogenous cations are quite different. To the 
extent that this may affect interactions with the pore 
wall, their permeability is not a pure function of size. 
Thus, it is reassuring to fi nd that our estimate is not dis-
similar from that of Van Itallie et al. (2008) , who used 
noncharged polyethylene glycols as size probes and re-
cently reported that claudin-2 forms size-restrictive 
pores of ‫ف‬ 8 Å in diameter. They also found a small size-
independent component of permeability; consistent 
with this, we have found that even very large cations ex-
hibit low but detectable levels of permeability through </p>

<p>D I S C U S S I O N </p>

<p>Here, we determine the transepithelial conductance 
and permeability of MDCK I cells induced to express 
claudin-2 and subtract it from measurements done in 
the control, uninduced state. We suggest that this yields 
a quantitative measure of the macroscopic conductance 
and cation permeability of claudin-2 -based pores. Our 
reasoning is supported by three observations. First, 
claudin-2 induction does not alter the number of tight 
junction strands. Thus, claudin-2 pores are presumably 
inserted into existing strands, and their conductance 
would be expected to be additive over the background 
conductance. Second, claudin-2 does not substantially 
alter the expression of other known endogenous tight 
junction membrane proteins (claudins 1, 3, 4, and 7, 
and occludin). Thus, changes in paracellular perme-
ability are probably not confounded by changes in en-
dogenous tight junction proteins, although we cannot 
exclude the possibility that other as yet unidentifi ed en-
dogenous claudins could be affected. We currently do 
not have a structural explanation of how " extra " clau-
din molecules can insert into existing strands without 
displacing endogenous tight junction proteins. Third, 
the conductance of overexpressed claudin-2 is very high 
compared with the baseline transepithelial conductance 
of MDCK I cells, so that the signal to noise ratio is high. </p>

<p>Figure 11. Brownian dynamics 
modeling of the claudin-2 pore. 
(A) Model of the WT claudin-2 pore. 
E53 and D76 are positioned near 
the pore entrances. Residue D65 is 
placed in the middle and represented 
by a charged sphere characterized by 
its size R D , charge q D , and the distance 
between the pore centerline and the 
sphere center, R C . (B) Current -volt-
age relationship obtained in sym-
metric 150 mM NaCl. Open symbols 
with error bars represent numerical 
simulation data. (C) Conductance -
concentration profi le obtained from 
simulations with symmetrical NaCl 
concentrations up to 450 nM. Data 
points within the experimental range 
(up to a Na 
+ activity of 113 mM or 
concentration of 150 mM) are fi t by 
a dashed line. The solid line shows 
a curve fi t of the entire dataset to 
the Michaelis-Menten equation: G = 
G max /(1 + Na s /[Na]), where G max = 
450 pS and Na s = 600 mM. (D) Alkali 
metal cation selectivity (displayed as 
permeability relative to that of Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>) 
determined by the biionic potentials 
obtained in our numerical simula-
tions (shown as fi lled squares with 
error bars). For comparison, the ex-
perimental values (from Fig. 7 A ) are 
shown as open circles. </p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>

<p>site, whereas the other acidic residues in the fi rst extra-
cellular domain, E53 and D76, are not. The role of the 
fi rst extracellular domain in determining charge selec-
tivity of claudins has already been fi rmly established 
( Colegio et al., 2002, 2003 ; Van Itallie et al., 2003, 2006 ). 
However, our fi ndings differ substantially from those of 
James Anderson ' s group. Van Itallie, Colegio, and col-
leagues used analysis of the number of charged residues 
in WT claudins, and the effect of charge-reversing mu-
tations to indicate that charge selectivity depends on 
the additive effect of all the charged residues in the sec-
ond half of the fi rst extracellular loop ( Colegio et al., 
2002 ; Van Itallie et al., 2003 ). This would suggest a 
mechanism in which the general electrostatic environ-
ment within the pore determines charge selectivity, and 
not a discrete binding site. However, charge-reversing 
mutations are potentially misleading because they in-
troduce new charges that did not exist in the native pro-
tein and therefore may refl ect artifi cially created 
electrostatic effects, rather than inform on the location 
of the normal selectivity fi lter. 
Our fi ndings also differ from those of Hou et al (2005) . 
They performed charge-neutralizing mutations in clau-
din-16 and found fi ve acidic residues in the fi rst extra-
cellular loop that affected cation permeability and were 
interspersed with other acidic residues that had no ef-
fect. Mutation of each of the fi ve functionally important 
residues had only a modest effect (11 -33% reduction in </p>

<p>claudin-2 ( Table II ). The identity of this larger perme-
ation pathway remains unclear. 
The mechanism for the remarkable cation selectivity 
of claudin-2 is likely to be the presence of a negatively 
charged electrostatic binding site that interacts with 
partially dehydrated permeating cations. This is based 
on the fi nding that the permeability of alkali metal cat-
ions follows a high-order Eisenman sequence, and that 
the cation selectivity is abrogated by extracellular acidi-
fi cation. Acidifi cation could of course be acting alloste-
rically at a distant site to alter claudin-2 conformation 
and hence permeability. However, the fi nding that acid-
ifi cation reduces P Li /P Na and changes the alkali metal 
selectivity to a lower-order Eisenman sequence strongly 
suggests that it is titrating the negatively charged bind-
ing site. The suggestion that this is an intrapore site and 
not a surface charge is also supported by the fi nding of 
a linear conductance -concentration relationship. At 
low Na 
+ concentrations and hence low ionic strength, 
screening of any surface charges by the bulk solution is 
minimized and the local Na 
+ concentration at the pore 
entrance would be increased ( Green and Andersen, 
1991 ). This would be expected to result in anomalously 
high conductance at low Na 
+ concentrations. Instead, 
we observe a linear relationship, suggesting that the 
negatively charged site is within the pore. 
Our charge-neutralizing mutations show convincingly 
that D65 is an important contributor to this binding </p>

<p>Figure 12. Alignment of the 
amino acid sequences of the 
predicted fi rst extracellular do-
main of the known mouse clau-
din isoforms using <rs type="software">Clustal-W</rs>. 
Acidic residues are shaded pink, 
and basic residues are shaded 
blue. Residues that align at the 
homologous position to amino 
acids 65 and 66 of claudin-2 are 
indicated by arrows. </p>

<p>Yu et al. </p>



<p>served cation selectivity. Interestingly, our method of 
modeling the intrapore charge and the permeating 
ions as fi xed and mobile spheres, similar to the ap-
proach by Eisenman (1962) , has yielded the fi rst exam-
ple of a Brownian dynamics model that can distinguish 
clearly between the permeabilities of the different alkali 
metal cations. In this model, consistent with experimen-
tal suggestion of dehydrated permeating cations, different 
alkali metal cations are assumed to be fully dehydrated 
(for simplifi cation) and distinguished by their bare ion 
sizes and diffusivities. Ions having a smaller radius can 
approach the charge on D65 more closely, as well as giv-
ing it access to a larger accessible volume (entropic ef-
fects, i.e., excluded volume effect) in the selectivity fi lter. 
This increases the ion occupancy of the selectivity fi lter 
for smaller ions, and thus increases the permeability for 
smaller ions (see further discussion in the online supple-
mental material). 
There are limitations to our model. Because of its sim-
plicity it cannot simulate all aspects of claudin-2 behav-
ior. Abolition of the charge on D65 does reduce P Na . 
However, our computational model differs from our ex-
perimental fi ndings in predicting that P Cl would in-
crease and that the alkali metal cation selectivity would 
not change appreciably (see online supplemental mate-
rial). Further refi nement of our fi rst-pass model will be 
necessary to account for these observations, for exam-
ple, by including more molecular detail in the modeling 
of the D65 residue (concerning both its geometric struc-
ture and the distribution of negative charge along this 
structure in the case of the anion form of the residue). 
Not surprisingly, given that our model contains a dis-
crete binding site, it predicts that the conductance -con-
centration relationship will be saturating at suffi ciently 
high Na 
+ concentrations. This is a testable prediction 
that would presumably distinguish it from a model in 
which multiple pore charges contribute to a diffuse elec-
trostatic environment. So far our attempts to test this 
have been unsuccessful because supraphysiologic Na </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>concentrations have osmotic effects on the cell that dis-
rupt transepithelial conductance (unpublished data). 
Our model also predicts a single-pore conductance of 
70 pS at the physiological Na 
+ concentrations in which 
we observe a macroscopic claudin-2 conductance of 
‫ف‬ 10 mS/cm 
2 . As discussed in the online supplemental 
material, the channel geometry and the choice of protein 
dielectric constant affect the predicted single-channel 
conductance. For example, while keeping all other pa-
rameters the same, a cylindrical channel with a uniform 
pore size of 3.25 and 32 Å in length gave a channel con-
ductance almost 1.7 times smaller than the claudin-2 
model with conical vestibules (same minimum pore size 
and channel length, but with a funnel-like channel 
entrance). However, despite some inevitable uncertain-
ties regarding the claudin-2 model channel, our Brown-
ian dynamics simulations together with the deduced </p>

<p>P Na ), and combining the mutations appeared to be addi-
tive ( Hou et al., 2005 ). At fi rst sight, these results would 
seem to suggest that the fi rst extracellular domain of 
claudin-16 is folded in such a way as to bring together 
the side groups of multiple acidic residues that are ar-
ranged nonlinearly, thus forming the selectivity fi lter. 
However, it is important to remember that replacement of 
a charged residue, even with a neutral residue, can have 
multiple consequences, including steric effects and dis-
ruption of folding due to the abolition of salt bridges, all 
of which could abrogate permeability. Thus, without 
specifi c studies to prove that the mutation directly af-
fects electrostatic interaction between the pore and the 
permeating ion (such as alkali metal selectivity sequences 
and pH titration), the composition of the selectivity fi l-
ter in claudin-16 remains unproven. 
When the amino acid sequences of the fi rst extracel-
lular loop of all claudins are aligned ( Fig. 12 ), one can 
observe that the homologous position to D65 in clau-
din-2 has a basic residue in the majority (15/22) of the 
other isoforms. The only other isoform with an acidic 
residue at this position is claudin-16, which also acts as a 
cation-selective pore. Furthermore, the next position 
downstream, 66, is also occupied by an acidic residue in 
claudin-16; the only other claudins that have an acidic 
residue here are 10b and 15, the only other known cat-
ion-selective, pore-forming claudins ( Van Itallie et al., 
2003, 2006 ), and 22 (whose function is unknown). 
Finally, position 64 is occupied by one of the two invari-
ant cysteines found in the extracellular domain of all 
claudins, suggesting that it may have a structural role, 
perhaps in intramolecular disulfi de bonding. We there-
fore postulate that C64 anchors the two residues at posi-
tions 65 and 66 so that their side chains protrude into 
the lumen of the pore and can contribute to an electro-
static cation interaction site. 
Our Brownian dynamics simulations show that our 
experimental results can be mimicked by a very simple 
pore model. The tertiary structure of the extracellular 
domains of claudin has not yet been solved, and so sev-
eral somewhat arbitrary assumptions had to be made to 
construct this fi rst-pass model. Furthermore, we per-
formed sensitivity analyses (see Online Supplemental 
Material II) to investigate the effect of the channel ge-
ometry, protein dielectric constants, and the effective 
charges and positions of D65 on ion permeation 
through the claudin-2 model pore. We found that over 
experimentally reasonable ranges of these parameters, 
the basic computational conclusions reached for the 
claudin-2 model pore developed herein did not change. 
The value of this model is that it clearly shows that two 
competing factors -the ion diffusivity and the ion 
size -can determine the relative permeability ratio of 
cations observed in the claudin-2. Additionally, it shows 
that the mere presence of D65 contributing the major 
intrapore charges could be suffi cient to explain the ob-</p>



<p>Cation Selectivity of Claudin-2 Pore </p>



<p>maximum channel conductance (with respect to varia-
tions in concentration as well as the assumed effective 
charge on D65) suggest a maximum single-channel 
conductance on the order of ‫ف‬ 100 pS for claudin-2. 
MDCK cells are approximately hexagonal and have an 
average radius of 7 μ m ( Cereijido et al., 1983 ), and 
hence an area of 1.5 × 10 
Ϫ 6 cm 
2 and a cell perimeter of 
42 μ m. From this, we estimate that the conductance of 
the intercellular junction must be 100 pS per 100 nm. 
We do not explicitly account for strand number in our 
model, but assuming there are four identical strands 
in a series, we would estimate that there is one claudin-2 
pore every 25 nm along each tight junction strand, a 
fairly low pore density. 
In conclusion, our data suggest that claudin-2 forms 
narrow, water-fi lled cation-selective paracellular pores. 
Cation selectivity is achieved by a negatively charged 
site within the pore with which partially dehydrated 
permeating cations interact, and which can be titrated 
by pH. Our studies further suggest that a signifi cant 
part of this interaction site is contributed by the car-
boxylate side chain of D65 and suggest that the ho-
mologous residues at positions 65 and 66 may play 
similar roles in other claudin family members. Thus, 
paracellular claudin-based pores use discrete intrapore 
electrostatic interactions to achieve high conductance 
together with charge selectivity. </p>

<p>We thank Drs. Alicia McDonough and Kwang Kim for sharing 
their equipment, and Dr. Robert Chow for reading an early ver-
sion of the manuscript. We also wish to thank the reviewers, who 
played a collaborative role in revising aspects of this manuscript, 
particularly with regard to the method of correcting for liquid 
junction potentials. This turned out to be critical in arriving at 
quantitatively accurate data and changed our conclusions signifi -
cantly, and has also led to a signifi cant change in the way we now 
perform diffusion potential experiments in our laboratories. 
This work was supported by National Institutes of Health 
grants DK062283 (to A.S.L. Yu), HL25822 (to E.E. Schneeberger), 
and DK48522 (to the USC Center for Liver Diseases, for the Con-
focal Microscopy Sub-Core). The work of M.H. Cheng and R.D. 
Coalson was supported in part by the National Science Founda-
tion (grant CHE-0518044). </p>

<p>Lawrence G. Palmer served as editor. </p>

<p>Submitted: 3 November 2008 
Accepted: 8 December 2008 </p>

<p>R E F E R E N C E S </p>



<p>Yu et al. </p>





</text></tei>