<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2935919" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Keywords: clustering; children; mortality; Matlab; Bangladesh </p>

<p>Received: 27 April 2010; Revised: 17 June 2010; Accepted: 29 June 2010; Published: 30 August 2010 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>country's health policy aims to provide health 
services to all who need them and achieve spatial 
parity in coverage. Despite the aim of spatial 
parity, the recent 2009 Multiple Indicator Cluster Survey 
of the Bangladesh Bureau of Statistics, the national 
statistical organisation of the government, shows large 
disparities between districts in education, child health, 
maternal health, access to safe drinking water and 
improved sanitation (1). The findings reveal that spatial 
and environmental factors affect health and social 
development. The most deprived spatial units (districts) 
need special interventions and budget allocations in 
order to catch up with the rest of the country and achieve 
spatial parity. Spatial disparities may also exist within 
districts and sub-districts between lower administrative 
units such as unions or villages. 
Identifying spatial disparity requires population-based, 
up-to-date and reliable statistics on health indicators </p>

<p>and appropriate analytical tools. Such statistics, to our 
knowledge, are lacking in Bangladesh. Until now, routine 
registration of births and deaths is incomplete or non-
functioning. Basic demographic measures often come 
from a Health and Demographic Surveillance System 
(HDSS) operating in a well-defined population of 
small size. The size of the population under the HDSS 
in Matlab Á a rural area of Bangladesh Á is 224,039, 
covering 142 villages (2). Villages may not be very cohesive 
communities, but there are shared experiences among 
villagers because of their geographic closeness and 
exposure to the same common social networks (3). People 
of the same village go to the same market and to the 
same mosque or temple for prayer, irrespective of their 
wealth and education. Village-level institutions: schools, 
mosques, temples, clubs, etc., are influential forums for 
dissemination of ideas and homogenisation of knowledge 
and values. The overall village-level economic, social, </p>

<p>ae INDEPTH Mortality Clustering Supplement </p>

<p>Global Health Action 2010. # 2010 Nurul Alam et al. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-
Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), permitting all non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction 
in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>Citation: Global Health Action Supplement 1, 2010. DOI: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.5252 </p>

<p>environmental and spatial factors shape behaviour 
affecting health (4). 
The method of identifying spatial disparity is spatial 
mapping of health events, such as mortality, morbidity 
and access to health services. Statistical methodology to 
identify spatial disparity is under ongoing development. 
With technological advancement, more analytical tools 
have become available, and the Geographic Information 
System (GIS) has been developed in recent decades as a 
powerful and rapid tool to investigate spatial patterns 
in disease incidence or health services. One such tool is 
Kulldorff's (5) spatial scan statistic, which takes into 
consideration spatial distribution of the population to 
identify areas with high disease incidence or use of health 
services. This helps prioritising areas for analysis of cause 
and planning remedial actions. Kulldorff et al. (6) have 
extended the spatial scan statistic into a spaceÁtime scan 
statistic to identify disparities in terms of space and time. 
In countries with incomplete registration of vital 
events, survey and surveillance data are used to show 
spatial disparity. Data from the demographic surveillance 
research project in Nouna, Burkina Faso, showed non-
random distribution of childhood mortality (7). A recent 
study using geographic data from 10 Demographic and 
Health Surveys from West Africa shows that child 
mortality rates were higher in extremely dense (more 
than 1,000 persons per square kilometre) and extremely 
dispersed (fewer than 25 person per square kilometre) 
populations (8). Mortality rates are also higher in land-
locked areas. The study of spatio-temporal patterns of 
malaria in Chiang Mai, Thailand, in 2001Á2006 showed 
clustering of villages with elevated proportions of malaria 
cases (9). Multilevel analysis showed significant spatial 
variations between villages in seeking treatment for sick 
children in Matlab, Bangladesh (10). These findings help 
planners identify high-risk areas and thus pinpoint 
interventions more effectively. 
The objective of this study is to identify villages 
and periods of high under-five mortality in Matlab, 
Bangladesh, using HDSS data in 1998Á2007. Estimating 
mortality risks in high-risk villages, adjusting for village-
level education and economic status is another objective of 
the study. </p>

<p>Study population and methods </p>

<p>Data for this study came from Matlab, where the 
International Centre for Diarrhoeal Disease Research, 
Bangladesh (ICDDR, B) maintains the HDSS since 1966. 
Matlab is 55 km south-west of Dhaka Á the capital city 
of Bangladesh. The population under surveillance is 
224,039. The majority are Muslims (88%) and the rest 
are Hindus (12%). The main occupations of men are 
agriculture, fishery and livestock, and trade. Women 
usually do household chores. Despite the low level of 
economic development, fertility and mortality </p>

<p>transitions have been progressing slowly for the last 
four decades (2). 
The HDSS area consists of 142 villages of varying 
population size; ranging from 117 to 9,466 (9). The 
average population of a village is 1,578. Community 
female interviewers visited every household monthly up 
to 2006 and bi-monthly from 2007 to record vital 
events (births, deaths, migration, marriages and marital 
disruptions) that happened since their last visit. Since 
1986, each death is subject to verbal autopsy for 
assessment of possible cause of death. Two tiers of 
supervision and an independent quality control team 
ensure that registration of vital events is complete and the 
date of the event is precise. Data on the number of deaths 
and children aged below 5 years in the HDSS area in 
1998Á2007 were obtained from the HDSS longitudinal 
database and disaggregated by village and year. 
The 1996 socioeconomic census recorded individual's 
education, occupation and household durables: bed stand, 
chair-table, cupboard, radio, television, bike (including 
motorbike), land owned, materials of wall, roof and floor 
of the main dwelling unit and type of toilet used. These 
durables were used to classify households into quintiles 
(11). A principal components analysis of household 
durables retained one factor and assigned a factor score 
to each household. The higher the score, the higher the 
number of household assets, indicating better long-term 
economic status of the household. The factor score was 
used to divide the households into quintiles Á from the 
lowest 20% to the highest 20%. A higher household assets 
quintile reflects the higher economic status of the house-
hold. Adult (aged 15 years or older) education (measured 
by persons having education class 5 or higher) and 
household-level assets quintiles were aggregated across 
all households in the village to compute the village-level 
adult education rate (in percent) and economic status 
(percentage of households in top two asset quintiles). 
Villages are not homogeneous in education and economic 
status. Village-level adult education varied from 34 to 
83% and economic status from 19 to 57%. Clustering in 
mortality at the village-level may be an effect of 
clustering of the risk factors; education and poverty at 
village-level. 
Small villages (having less than 1,000 inhabitants) are 
merged with adjacent villages that are more similar in 
terms of adult education and economic status. After 
merging the small villages, we are left with 90 villages (or 
clusters) for analysis. GIS of the HDSS generates spatial 
data: geo-coordinates of each bari (group of households 
that share a common yard and whose heads are usually 
related by blood) and land marks (tube-wells, health 
facilities, schools, markets, mosques and temples) in 
degree decimal format. <rs type="software">ArcGIS</rs> software is used to create 
a polygon of each village and to pick the centroid 
(defined by the centre of gravity). In case of centroids </p>

<p>Spatio-temporal patterns of under-five mortality in Matlab HDSS </p>

<p>Citation: Global Health Action Supplement 1, 2010. DOI: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.5252 </p>



<p>lying outside polygons of irregular and complex shapes, 
the option 'INSIDE' in ArcGIS guaranteed the polygon 
centres lie inside the polygon. </p>

<p>Data analysis 
Overall childhood mortality rates per 1,000 under-five 
children and 95% confidence intervals assuming a Poisson 
distribution of deaths were calculated for each year of 
1998Á2007. Yearly number of deaths and children aged 
below 5 years were disaggregated by village. Childhood 
death rates by village i, i 01,. . ., 90 for years j, j 01998, . . ., 
2007 using DR ij 0d ij /n ij , where n ij denotes the midyear 
population children aged 0Á4 years in village i and year j, 
and d ij is the corresponding observed number of deaths. 
Kulldorff et al. (5, 6) have extended the spatial scan 
statistic into a spaceÁtime scan statistic to identify spatial 
and temporal units with high mortality risks. In this 
study, we used Kulldorff's spaceÁtime scan statistic, 
which takes into consideration spatial and temporal 
distributions of the population as follows. The window 
imposed on the HDSS area is cylindrical with a circular 
geographic base and with height corresponding to time. 
The centre of the base is one of several possible cent-
roids located throughout the HDSS area and the height 
reflects any possible time interval. The cylindrical win-
dow is then moved in space and time and it allows 
the centre of the circular geographic base to move across 
the HDSS villages. For any given position of the centre, 
the radius of the circular base changes continuously so 
that it can take any value between zero and an upper limit 
of 50% of the total population. A village is captured if it 
lies in the circular base. Therefore, the circular base is able 
to include a different set of neighbouring villages. This 
scanning was applied to HDSS data for the time window 
1998Á2007 to scan for space and time with high mortality 
rates. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>A total of 3,434 under-five deaths were reported in the 
Matlab HDSS area for 1998Á2007 with an average yearly 
rate of 13.0 deaths per 1,000 under-five child-years (Fig. 1). 
The corresponding cumulative rate up to age 5 years is 
calculated as (1Áexp (Á5)0.013)) 00.063 (or 63 per 1,000 
live births). In the study period, there was a clear gradual 
decline in mortality; the rate fell from 18.0 in 1998 to 9.2 
in 2007; a 49% reduction in a 10-year period. Disaggregation 
of yearly mortality rates by village shows high fluctuation 
in rates within and between villages and years for small 
numbers. Some small villages did not have any deaths in </p>

<p>some years and some had more than expected by chance. In 
1998, mortality rates in the villages ranged from 0.0 to 37.8, 
and in 2007, mortality rates in the villages ranged from 0.0 
to 27.9. 
The <rs type="software">SaTScan</rs> </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>option 'purely temporal analysis' 
showed a significantly higher mortality in 1998Á2002 
compared to 2003Á2007 (Table 1). An alternative analysis 
using Poisson regression showed a highly significant (pB 
0.001) linear mortality decline over the full period 1998Á 
2007. 
The spaceÁtime analysis using the discrete Poisson 
model reveals spatial disparities in under-five mortality in 
1998Á2002, but not in 2003Á2007 (Table 2). Analysis 
identified three statistically significant sets of villages with 
high childhood mortality (Fig. 2). Each cluster consists of 
a set of villages adjacent to each other. 
Despite the homogeneity in many other aspects, 
villages are heterogeneous in education and economic 
status. One may hypothesise that spatial disparity in 
mortality is due to spatial disparities in the distribution of 
the risk factors. To examine the hypothesis, logistic 
regression analysis is undertaken for high-risk clusters 
identified by the spaceÁtime analysis. The dependent 
variable was death of the child before the fifth birthday 
(coded '1' if died, '0' if survived). The independent 
variables were the risk order of the clusters of villages 
and adult education and economic status at village level. 
The most likely cluster of villages was coded '1', the 
secondary cluster 1 of villages coded '2', the secondary 
cluster 2 of villages coded '3' and the rest of the villages 
were coded '0' (or reference category). Model I contained 
the risk factor, 'risk order of the cluster' only and Model 
II contained the risk factors, 'risk order of the cluster' 
plus village-level education and economic status. These 
two models show the changes in odds ratio and log 
likelihood statistics for adjusting for education and 
economic status at village level. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Yearly death rate (and 95% Poisson CI) per 1,000 
under-five children, 1998Á2007. </p>

<p>Table 1. Under-five mortality in the HDSS area for 1998Á2007 using purely temporal analysis scanning for high rates </p>

<p>Type 
Period 
Cases 
Expected 
Relative risk 
p-Value </p>

<p>Most likely 
1998Á2002 
2,047 
1,824.3 
1.31 
pB0.001 </p>

<p>Nurul Alam et al. </p>



<p>Citation: Global Health Action Supplement 1, 2010. DOI: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.5252 </p>

<p>Logistic regression Model I shows that two of the 
three sets of villages identified as high risk by Kulldorff's 
spaceÁtime analysis remained as high risks (Table 3). The 
secondary cluster 2 with marginally high risks turned out 
to be non-significant. The factor 'village-level economic 
status', but not 'adult education' was negatively associated 
with the high mortality risk. The odds ratios reduced, but 
remained significant after controlling for the village-level 
economic status. The reduction is also indicated by 
the deviance between the two log likelihoods, which is 
distributed as Chi-square and is found significant. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>The gradual decline in under-five mortality in the HDSS 
area is consistent with the results of the nationally 
representative sample survey, the five Bangladesh Demo-
graphic and Health Surveys conducted between 1993 and 
2007, and the National Sample Vital Registration System </p>

<p>(12, 13). Concentration of deaths was observed in 1998Á 
2002, but not in 2003Á2007. The lack of concentration 
in 2003Á2007 was not due to systematic error in the 
reporting of births and deaths across villages over the 
years. Monthly (and bi-monthly from 2007) household 
visits to register vital events and pregnancy, two tiers of 
supervision and checking by an independent quality 
control team ruled out the possibilities of under-or 
over-reporting. Each death in an HDSS area is subject 
to verbal autopsy for assigning possible cause of 
death, which minimises the chances of missing neonatal 
deaths and misclassification between stillbirths and early 
neonatal deaths. 
Identifying clusters with high mortality risks is a first 
step in prioritising areas for analysis of cause and planning 
of remedial actions. SpaceÁtime analysis using Kulldorff's 
method (6) identified two clusters of villages with high 
mortality risks in 1998Á2002. This reveals that mortality </p>

<p>Table 2. Under-five mortality in the HDSS area for 1998Á2007 using spatialÁtemporal analysis scanning for high rates </p>

<p>Period 
Type 
Location 
Cases 
Expected 
Relative risk 
p-Value </p>

<p>1998Á2002 
Most likely 
22 villages 
677 
509.8 
1.41 
pB0.001 </p>

<p>Secondary 
18 villages 
393 
288.6 
1.41 
pB0.001 
1998 
Secondary 
9 villages 
59 
31.3 
1.90 
p00.068 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Map showing sets of villages with high under-five mortality rates in the HDSS area for 1998Á2002. </p>

<p>Spatio-temporal patterns of under-five mortality in Matlab HDSS </p>

<p>Citation: Global Health Action Supplement 1, 2010. DOI: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.5252 </p>



<p>decline was faster in the high-risk clusters than in the 
average-risk cluster and achieved equity. A common 
drawback of Kulldorff's method is that clusters are defined 
as circles or cylindrical windows with circular base (5, 6). 
Actual clusters (or villages) are irregular in shape. This 
feature has some implications for the interpretation of the 
results. If a village with low mortality is surrounded by 
villages with high mortality, it is included in the cluster 
although some characteristics of the village are different 
from other villages. If clustering of mortality is, say, along 
the river, then a circular shape is not appropriate to detect 
it. The first limitation is similar to that of the control trial 
cohort, and the overall effect on the result would be small. 
The second limitation can be minimised by viewing an 
<rs type="software">ArcGIS</rs> map. 
Each high-risk cluster comprises a set of adjacent 
villages. The most likely mortality cluster consists of 
22 villages adjacent to each other. They are in close 
proximity of the big river, the 'Meghna', and are exposed 
to more natural disasters such as river erosion and 
monsoon flooding. The secondary cluster consists of 18 
villages on the banks of the rivers Gumti and Dhonogoha 
and in adjacent low-lying areas. These villages are remote 
Á far away from the sub-district town and health facility. 
What causes difference in mortality between clusters 
demands in-depth study. 
People in high-risk clusters may be of lower education 
and economic status compared to their peers in aver-
age risk clusters in addition to the natural disasters and 
geo-access to health services. Control for the village-
level adult education and household economic status 
reduced the odds ratios of dying in the high-risk clusters a 
little, but remained significant. This suggests that spatial 
and some environmental factors in addition to edu-
cation and economic factors affect health. Causal factors 
may be at the demand side (hygiene and health care </p>

<p>seeking) and supply side (availability and accessibility). 
Non-random distribution of local formal or informal 
health facilities and access to them may be causing 
the inter-cluster differences in under-five mortality. The 
overall cluster-level variance for childhood mortality is 
quite small, but significant. This is expected because the 
clusters are adjacent to each other. The populations 
across clusters can be somewhat homogeneous in 
terms of health belief and practice and environmental 
factors. 
That education at the village level was not associated 
with mortality risks is a surprise and needs investigation 
in the future. Perhaps education benefits one's family 
members, not others in the community. Another possibi-
lity is error (over or under) in self-reported education, 
which is likely to be random and underestimate the 
mortality effect. Socioeconomic status of households was 
determined in 1996 Á 2 years before the study period, and 
must have changed over the years. Such change across 
villages can be uniform or non-uniform, but there is no 
data to determine what it was. Non-uniform change, if 
any, may have disproportionately affected the result. 
Error in measurement of economic status also under-
estimates the strength of the association. In conclusion, 
the findings indicate that spatial disparity observed in 
childhood mortality in the HDSS area in 1998Á2002 has 
disappeared in recent years in which there have been 
lower mortality rates. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This research activity was funded by ICDDR, B and its donors, 
which provide unrestricted support to the Centre for its operations 
and research. Current donors providing unrestricted support 
include: Australian Agency for International Development 
(AusAID), Government of the People's Republic of Bangladesh, 
Canadian International Development Agency (CIDA), Embassy of </p>

<p>Table 3. Odds ratios (and 95% CI) of under-five deaths for the risk factors </p>

<p>Odds ratio (95% CI) </p>

<p>Risk factors 
Model I 
Model II </p>

<p>Risk order of the cluster: </p>

<p>Average likely cluster (reference) 
1 
1 </p>

<p>Most likely cluster 
1.24* (1.15Á1.35) 
1.17* (1.08Á1.27) </p>

<p>Secondary cluster 1 
1.31* (1.19Á1.44) 
1.21* (1.09Á1.33) </p>

<p>Secondary cluster 2 
1.08 (0.95Á1.23) 
1.03 (0.90Á1.16) </p>

<p>Village-level factors: </p>

<p>Adults with education class 5' (%) 
0.998 (0.994Á1.003) </p>

<p>Households in top two quintiles (%) 
0.985* (0.980Á0.991) </p>

<p>Log likelihood (df) 
(18878.9 (3), pB0.001 
(18857.1 (5), pB0.001 </p>

<p>*pB0.01. 
Note: The dependent variable was coded '1' if the child had died, otherwise coded '0'. </p>

<p>Nurul Alam et al. </p>



<p>Citation: Global Health Action Supplement 1, 2010. DOI: 10.3402/gha.v3i0.5252 </p>

<p>the Kingdom of the Netherlands (EKN), Swedish International 
Development Cooperation Agency (Sida), Swiss Agency for 
Development and Cooperation (SDC), and Department for Inter-
national Development, UK (DFID). We gratefully acknowledge 
these donors for their support and commitment to the Centre's 
research efforts. <rs id="software-5" type="software">SaTScan</rs> 
TM is a trademark of <rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Martin Kulldorff</rs>. The 
<rs id="software-6" type="software">SaTScan</rs> 
TM software was developed under the joint auspices of (<rs corresp="#software-6" type="creator">(a) Martin Kulldorff, (b) the National Cancer Institute and (c) Farzad Mostashari of the New York City Department of Health and Mental Hygiene</rs>. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest and funding </p>

<p>The authors have not received any funding or benefits 
from industry to conduct this study. </p>





</text></tei>