<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2741607" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:14+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: The aim of this study was to determine human papillomavirus (HPV) types distribution in cervical preneoplasic 
lesions in a Southern Spanish population and their relationship between HPV type and grade of histopathological 
abnormality. Finally, 232 cervical samples from 135 women with previous cytological abnormalities were included in this 
study. Colposcopy studies and biopsies were performed. Haematoxylin-eosin stained slides were observed and detection 
of HPV DNA in cervical swabs was carried out with use of a polymerase chain reaction and microarrays technology. The 
relationship between the presence of HPV infection and diagnostic variables was evaluated. HPV 16 was the most 
common type followed by HPV 58, 51, 33 and 31. However, the two HPV types targeted in the prophylactic vaccines 
such as HPV type 16 and 18 were detected in only 37 (21.2%) and 2 (1.1%) cases respectively. Thirty-three (18.9%) of 
samples were infected with multiple types, the majority of them with two types. In addition, during the follow-up of 
patients many changes in type distribution were observed. Several studies will be necessary in order to evaluate the HPV 
type distribution for therapeutically and prophylactic purposes such as vaccine treatment. Also, because of the differences 
obtained depending of use of various DNA technologies, the performance of some comparative studies of the different 
methods from detection of HPV would be advisable in a high population of patients and with the most homogeneous 
conditions possible. </p>

<p>Human papillomavirus (HPV) is small, icosahedral and 
non-enveloped viruse now grouped in the papillomaviridae 
family. The HPV genome consists of a single molecule of 
double-stranded circular DNA within a capsid composed of 
two structural proteins (L1 and L2 proteins) [1]. </p>

<p>At the moment, more than 100 types of HPV have been 
identified and these correspond to 16 different genus; their 
classification is now based on the nucleotide sequences 
comparison of specific regions such as coding regions of E6, 
E7 and L1 proteins [2]. Depending of this, the types have 
less than 90% of homology in the sequences of such regions. 
The clinically most important genus is the -papillomavirus 
which contain all HPV associated with mucosal lesions. -
papillomaviruses include all the kind of virus associated with 
epidermodysplasia verruciformis. </p>

<p>HPV is one of the most common causes of sexually 
transmitted diseases worldwide. The current prevalence of 
HPV infection in women range to 2-44%, being Asia and 
Europe where it can found the less percentage of infection 
[3]. </p>

<p>HPV is associated with a wide variety of clinical 
conditions and diseases that range from innocuous lesions to 
certain neoplasias. Firstly, HPV was recognized as the cause 
of cutaneous warts, although this infection is also related </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Infectious Pathology Unit, 
Department of Pathology, Hospital Universitario Virgen de las Nieves, 
Avenida Fuerzas Armadas, 2, 18014 Granada, Spain; Tel: 958 02 06 91; 
Fax: 958 02 01 32; E-mail: fernando.cobo.sspa@juntadeandalucia.es </p>

<p>to focal epithelial hyperplasia of the oral cavity (Heck's 
disease), epidermodysplasia verruciformis, recurrent 
respiratory papillomatosis and conjunctival papillomas and 
carcinomas [4]. Moreover, several epidemiological studies 
permit to conclude that certain HPV type infections are a 
necessary factor for the development to cervical cancer [5-7]. 
These kind of neoplasias represent the second most common 
cancer in women worldwide and contribute with 
approximately 10% of overall female cancers. Other tumours 
HPV-related are anal, vaginal, vulvar, penile, laryngeal and 
oropharyngeal cancer, so HPV is estimated responsible to 
5% of all kind of neoplasias worldwide [8]. In fact, in 1990 
was described the presence of HPV type 16 in laryngeal 
carcinomas [9]. </p>

<p>From an epidemiological point of view and based on 
their association with cervical cancer and precursor lesions, 
HPV s have been classified in both high-risk and low-risk 
HPV types; now, there are also two additional groups: 
probably carcinogenic high-risk and non-determinate risk of 
carcinogenesis [10]. </p>

<p>The commonest HPV infection diagnostic methods in 
cervical pathology have been the cytology (both 
conventional and monolayer cytology) by means of 
Papanicolaou-stained smear (Pap smear) [11] and histology, 
in which patients with abnormal cytology are usually 
evaluated by colposcopy and biopsy. Molecular methods to 
detect HPV DNA sequences (include the possibility of HPV 
typing) have been recently introduced in order to improve 
this diagnosis. </p>

<p>Recently, both the Federal Drug Administration (FDA) 
and the European Agency for the Evaluation of Medicinal </p>

<p>HPV in Cervical Cytology </p>

<p>The Open Virology Journal, 2009, Volume 3 61 </p>

<p>Products (EMEA) have approved and regulated the use of 
two HPV vaccines (Gardasil 
® and Cervarix 
® ) [12]. In phase 
II/III studies, both vaccines have demonstrated safety and 
efficacy to the prevention of HPV infections caused by the 
viral types including in these. </p>

<p>The main objective of this study was to perform the 
diagnosis of HPV infection in a group of female patients 
with cytological abnormalities referred to the Cervix Cancer 
Diagnosis Unit (CCDU) of our hospital by means of 
histopathological and molecular techniques; additionally, a 
correlation between both methods was also carried out. 
Moreover, a second objective was to stablish a relationship 
between HPV type and grade of histopathological 
abnormality. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODOLOGY </p>

<p>Study Design and Population </p>

<p>The patients included in this study were first-visited from 
February 2006 to February 2007; a population-based cohort 
of women with cytological abnormalities visualized by 
means of Pap smears (presence of non-reactive atypical 
cells) was used in this study. The total number of Pap smears 
performed during the study period by the Early Cervical 
Cancer Detection Program (ECCDP) was 45,000, 
approximately. The population came from a health area of 
approximately 450,000 inhabitants corresponding to the 
North of the province of Granada (Andalucía, Spain). From 
these, 250,000 are eligible women for participation in the 
ECCDP, but only 1,500 women were send from the health 
basic centres to the CCDU of our Hospital to complete the 
study. Finally, 232 samples for HPV typing and 173 biopsies 
corresponding to 135 women were included in this report. 
The main inclusion criterion was the presence of cytological 
alterations in the Pap smears and further remission to our 
hospital in order to complete the study. The only exclusion 
criteria were women who refusing to continue in follow up. 
The follow-up visits were established each 6 months during 
3 years. The collected data were the patient age, HPV types 
and biopsy sample diagnosis. This histological diagnosis was 
classified in five categories as follows: inflammatory/reactive 
lesions, undetermined/not conclusive lesions such as atypia 
borderline, LSIL (low-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions), 
HSIL (high-grade squamous intraepithelial lesions), and 
invasive carcinoma. </p>

<p>Collection of Data and Specimens </p>

<p>The patients were studied and treated according the 
protocol of the Department of Gynaecology and Obstetric of 
our Hospital. The patients finally included in the study 
signed an inform consent approved by the ethical committee 
of our Hospital. In the first and follow-up visits at the 
hospital, the women were interviewed by a trained physician 
in order to know information about risk factors for cervical 
cancer. Furthermore, a gynaecologist performed a pelvic 
examination including a colposcopy study and, it was 
necessary, a biopsy sample was taken. Biopsy specimens 
were formalin fixed and further paraffin embedded 
(Histosec 
® , Merck, Darmstadt, Germany) by means of 
manufacture's recommendation; later, a pathological report 
was then discharged. Simultaneously, a cervical swab </p>

<p>without transport medium was collected for HPV DNA 
detection and typing study. </p>

<p>HPV Detection and Typing </p>

<p>Detection of HPV DNA in cervical swabs was carried out 
by means of a polymerase chain reaction (PCR)-based assay 
and further typing by the kit Clinical Arrays 
® (Genómica, 
Madrid, Spain) [13]. The detection limit of this technique is 
10 copies of DNA virus, without any difference among HPV 
types. Briefly, the samples were processed as follows: the 
DNA extraction, purification and amplification was carried 
out by means of this kit, amplifying a DNA-target of 450 bp 
inside L1 protein. A 9-min initial denaturation step at 95º C, 
45 cycles of 1 min at 94º C, 1 min at 55º C, 1 min at 72º C, 
and a chain final elongation step at 72º C for 9 min. The 
HPV typing was then performed by means a new 
technological platform based in low density microarrays 
hybridization assay (Clinical Arrays 
® genotyping), in which 
the microchip is inserted at the bottom of a Eppendorf tube. 
The presence of the 35 most important HPV genotypes could 
be analyzed by means of this method. The extracted DNA 
remain frozen and stored in the Tumour and Tissue Bank at 
our hospital. </p>

<p>Twenty-three DNA samples were send to the National 
Centre of Microbiology, the reference centre in Spain, in 
order to carry out an external quality control. This 
establishment used a Real-Time PCR method (Roche Linear 
Array) for the HPV diagnosis and typing [14]. These 
samples were selected on basis to peculiar results such as the 
presence of numerous (multiple infections) or infrequent 
(uncommon) HPV types. </p>

<p>Statistical Analysis </p>

<p>The statistical software package <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">13.0</rs> for Windows 
was used for this analysis. A descriptive analysis of the 
variables was firstly carried out; the percentages were 
calculated for the qualitative variables and means and 
standard deviations for the numerical variable. </p>

<p>Later, the relationship between the dependent variable 
(HPV presence or not) and the independent variables (age 
and diagnostic variables) was performed by means of the 
chi-square test, and we consider a significant value p&lt; 0.01. </p>

<p>The sample size (number of patients included in the study 
of 135) was calculated in basis to an error of 4%. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Study Subjects </p>

<p>Of the 135 women who were included in this study, 72 
(53%) were 34 years old or younger, 38 (28%) were between 
35 and 44 years old and 25 (18%) were 45 years old or older. 
The mean age at enrolment was 35 years (standard deviation 
= 10.4 years). </p>

<p>A total of 232 samples for HPV typing corresponding to 
135 women were consecutively included in this study. In 
addition, 173 biopsies were taken. The histological diagnosis 
was: 67 with inflammatory/reactive non specific lesions, 68 
with LSIL, 24 with HSIL and 14 with atypia borderline; in 
the remaining samples, the histological study was not 
performed due to a gynaecologist criteria. All the samples 
were simultaneously tested for HPV DNA presence. </p>



<p>Cobo et al. </p>

<p>Specific Prevalence of HPV Genotypes </p>

<p>A total of 174 samples (75%) were positive for HPV 
DNA and 55 (23.7%) were negative. In three samples, DNA 
was not obtained (Table 1). </p>

<p>Table 1. Human Papillomavirus (HPV) Type Distribution in 
Cervical Samples Detected by PCR-Microarrays in 
Granada, Spain </p>

<p>HPV Detection 
Nº (%) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Positive </p>

<p>Negative </p>

<p>DNA no detected </p>

<p>Single infections </p>

<p>Multiple infections </p>

<p>2 types </p>

<p>&gt; 2 types </p>

<p>Type specific </p>

<p>HPV 16 </p>

<p>HPV 53 </p>

<p>HPV 6 </p>

<p>HPV 66 </p>

<p>HPV 58 </p>

<p>HPV 61 </p>

<p>HPV 51 </p>

<p>HPV 33 </p>

<p>HPV 31 </p>

<p>HPV 11 </p>

<p>HPV 72 </p>

<p>HPV 18 </p>

<p>HPV 62 </p>

<p>HPV 81 </p>

<p>HPV 70 </p>

<p>HPV 56 </p>

<p>HPV 84 </p>

<p>174 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>141 (81.03%) </p>

<p>33 (18.9%) </p>

<p>24 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>37 (21.2%) </p>

<p>16 (9.1%) </p>

<p>16 (9.1%) </p>

<p>12 (6.8%) </p>

<p>11 (6.3%) </p>

<p>9 (5.1%) </p>

<p>8 (4.5%) </p>

<p>7 (4.02%) </p>

<p>5 (2.8%) </p>

<p>5 (2.8%) </p>

<p>5 (2.8%) </p>

<p>2 (1.1%) </p>

<p>2 (1.1%) </p>

<p>2 (1.1%) </p>

<p>2 (1.1%) </p>

<p>1 (0.5%) </p>

<p>1 (0.5%) </p>

<p>* N (%): from the positive cases (n= 174). </p>

<p>From positive cases (n=174), 141 (81.03%) were infected 
with a single HPV type, and 33 (18.9%) were infected with 
multiple types. When the infection was caused by an only 
type, high-risk types supposed 73 samples (51.7%). HPV 16 
was the most common type (37 samples/21.2%), followed by 
HPV type 58 (11 samples/6.3%). The infection with low-risk 
types was found in 39 samples (27.6%), and the type 6 was 
the most common infection in this group (16 samples/9.1%). 
Finally, infection with probable high-risk types was obtained 
in 28 samples (16.09%) (caused with HPV type 53 and 66). 
Only one case was caused with an unclassified HPV type. </p>

<p>With respect to the group of infections with multiple types, 
the majority of them were caused with 2 types (24 
samples/72.7%). Three or more types was only obtained in 9 
(27.2%) of total cases. In these co-infections, 19 (57%) had only 
high-risk types and 11 (33%) had both high and low-risk types. 
One case had co-infection by not classified HPV types (HPV 
83, 84), and also one case had co-infection by a low-risk HPV 
type and probable high-risk HPV type. Curiously, the most 
common type involved in the co-infections was HPV 51 (12 
samples/36%), followed by HPV 16 (10 samples/30%) (Table 2). </p>

<p>Taking into account overall data, HPV type 16 was the 
most common virus (47 samples/27.01%), followed by HPV 
type 51 (20 samples/11.4%) and type 58 (19 
samples/10.9%). </p>

<p>Table 2. Multiple HPV Infections in the Southern Spanish 
Health Area. Granada, Spain </p>

<p>Patient 
HPV Types </p>

<p>3 
6, 16 </p>

<p>9 
6, 16, 18, 33, 58 </p>

<p>11 
6, 54 </p>

<p>19 
31, 51, 84 </p>

<p>28 
16, 70 </p>

<p>35 
11, 58, 66 </p>

<p>62 
56, 61 </p>

<p>65 
31, 81 </p>

<p>70 
31, 62 </p>

<p>72 
58, 66 </p>

<p>75 
33, 58 </p>

<p>76 
16, 51 </p>

<p>77 
83, 84 </p>

<p>81 
11, 66 </p>

<p>82 
6, 16 </p>

<p>87 
16, 66, 70 </p>

<p>93 
51, 58 </p>

<p>93 
51, 58 </p>

<p>98 
18, 31, 51 </p>

<p>99 
6, 16 </p>

<p>100 
16, 53 </p>

<p>106 
6, 16, 18, 31, 53 </p>

<p>107 
51, 52 </p>

<p>108 
16, 33, 58 </p>

<p>116 
51, 66 </p>

<p>118 
16, 51 </p>

<p>120 
51, 53 </p>

<p>120 
51, 53 </p>

<p>121 
33, 52, 53 </p>

<p>127 
6, 51 </p>

<p>130 
53, 58 </p>

<p>131 
52, 56 </p>

<p>133 
51, 53, 66 </p>

<p>External Quality Control </p>

<p>In order to assure an adequate quality control of this 
analysis, 23 samples were selected and sent to our National 
Reference Centre (National Centre for Microbiology, </p>

<p>HPV in Cervical Cytology </p>

<p>The Open Virology Journal, 2009, Volume 3 63 </p>

<p>Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Madrid). In general, the control 
was satisfactory. In all cases, both institutions detected the 
same HPV types, but in several samples, both institutions 
detected additional HPV types. Only in four cases, there 
were additional HPV types only obtained by our method; 
also, in 4 cases both, our laboratory and the National 
Reference Centre, obtained the same results. In one case, in 
which we have not found DNA, the external centre observed 
3 HPV types. In Table 3, these results can be observed. </p>

<p>Evolution of HPV Infection </p>

<p>Two o more HPV analysis was carried out in 74 women. 
Independently of HPV type or histological diagnosis, in 40 
cases (54%) HPV infection disappeared during the study 
period. In 17 women (23%), HPV types were the same in all 
analysis. In 5 women (6%) additional HPV types could be 
observed in further analysis, and in 4 (5%) a decrease of 
HPV types could be found. Only in two women with low-
risk HPV types were changed to high-risk HPV types. 
Finally high-risk HPV infection in 4 patients disappeared 
and later low-risk HPV types were found. In Table 4, it can 
see these results. </p>

<p>Risk Associated with HPV </p>

<p>With respect to relationship between the patients' age 
and the HPV presence or not, statistical significant 
differences in the age ranges ( 34, 35-44, &gt; 44 years old) 
were not observed (chi square, p= 0.157). </p>

<p>Also, a correlation between the presence of HPV in each 
group of histological diagnosis was carried out. The 
statistical analysis of this study was not relevant in our 
samples (Table 5). Briefly, in the LSIL and HSIL groups a 
higher number of high-risk HPV types than in the 
inflammatory lesions and ASCUS groups were observed; 
however, these differences were not statistical significant. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Two main stages could be consider in HPV epidemiology: 
type distribution of cervical HPV infection in women with 
normal cytology and in women with abnormal cytology. 
Recently, a meta-analysis of relevant studies about the 
worldwide prevalence and type distribution of cervical HPV 
DNA in women with normal cytology has been published [3]. 
In this manuscript, the overall HPV prevalence was estimated to 
be 10.4%. However, there were some differences depending of </p>

<p>Table 3. Correlation Between our Results and the External Quality Control (National Centre for Microbiology, Madrid, Spain) in 
23 Samples with Multiple Infections </p>

<p>Patient 
Types Obtained with our Method (Microarrays) 
Types Obtained in the External Control </p>

<p>3 
6, 16 
16 </p>

<p>9 
6, 16, 18, 33, 58 
6, 16, 18, 33, 58 + 39, 42, 62, CP6108 </p>

<p>28 
16, 70 
16, 70 + 45, 62 </p>

<p>62 
56, 61 
56, 61 + 73 </p>

<p>65 
31, 81 
31, 81 </p>

<p>70 
31, 62 
31, 62 </p>

<p>75 
33, 58 
33, 58 + 42 </p>

<p>76 
16, 51 
16, 51 + 35, 45 </p>

<p>77 
83, 84 
83, 84 </p>

<p>87 
16, 66, 70 
16, 66, 70 + 52, 55, 56 </p>

<p>93 
51, 58 
51, 58 + 42 </p>

<p>98 
18, 31, 51 
18, 31, 51 + 42, 55, 62, 73 </p>

<p>100 
16, 53 
16, 53 + 62, 67 </p>

<p>106 
6, 16, 18, 31, 53 
6, 16, 18, 31, 53 + 52 </p>

<p>107 
51, 52 
51 </p>

<p>108 
16, 33, 58 
16, 33, 58+ 51, IS39 </p>

<p>116 
51, 66 
51, 66 + 16, 35, 40, 61, 81, 84 </p>

<p>118 
16, 51 
51, CP6108 </p>

<p>120 
51, 53 
51, 53 </p>

<p>121 
33, 52, 53 
33, 53 </p>

<p>130 
NO DNA 
53, 58, CP6108 </p>

<p>131 
52, 56 
52, 56 + 54 </p>

<p>133 
51, 53, 66 
51, 53, 66 + 42, 56, CP6108 </p>

<p>* Note the differences between both methods highlighted in bold. </p>



<p>Cobo et al. </p>

<p>the region of origin. Africa and Central America and Mexico 
were the regions where it found a higher prevalence of HPV 
infection, while Europe and Asia had less infection prevalence. 
In Europe a north/south pattern could be observed, with HPV 
prevalence decreasing with decreasing latitude [3]. In this study, 
HPV16 is the most common HPV type and the five most 
common HPV types in HPV-positive women worldwide were 
HPV16, HPV18, HPV31, HPV58 and HPV52, being 50% of all 
HPV infections [3]. </p>

<p>Other studies focused with the distribution of HPV types 
in women with cervical lesions. In a recent report, HPV 16 
and 18 were the most frequent HPV types identified in 
invasive cancers (80%), but the distribution patterns of HPV 
types in the intraepithelial lesions was highly varied [15]. </p>

<p>In Spain, there are a few reports on HPV epidemiology. 
In 2006 a study performed in Alicante and Madrid was 
published, revealing that the prevalence of HPV infection 
among general population was 10.7% [16]. In this paper, the 
most commonest HPV types in the general population were 
types 16, 31, 52, 68 and 51. </p>

<p>Four years ago, de Sanjosé et al. [17] published data 
about the prevalence of HPV infection in female residents in 
an area of Barcelona (Spain). In this population, the age-
adjusted HPV prevalence was 3% and the most common 
types of HPV infection were type 16, 35 and 31. </p>

<p>Recently, another study has been performed in Spain in 
women with abnormal cervical cytology [18]. In this 
manuscript, the highest percentage of women with a positive 
result for HPV was found in patients with HSIL. </p>

<p>Other Spanish studies have been focused in some sub-
populations such as migrant women from Latin America [19]  and in imprisoned women [20]. </p>

<p>In Andalusia, a southern Spain region, until this moment 
there are not previously published data about prevalence and 
HPV types distribution, so further evaluation on this issue 
needs to be addressed. </p>

<p>The main problem of these studies is their 
heterogeneicity taking into account the different methods 
used to evaluate the HPV infections. Until now, the hybrid 
capture method (Digene 
® HPV test) is the only FDA </p>

<p>Table 4. Evolution of HPV Infection in Women with Two or More HPV Analysis. Granada, Spain </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>Patient 
First Sample 
Second Sample 
Third Sample 
Fourth Sample 
Evolution </p>

<p>6 
HPV 18 
HPV 66 
HR -probable HR </p>

<p>11 
HPV 66 
HPV 16 
HPV 6 
HPV 6, 54 
Probable HR -HR -LR </p>

<p>18 
HPV 58 
HPV 51 
HPV 11 
HR -HR -LR </p>

<p>19 
HPV 31 
HPV 31, 51, 84 
HR -HR + undetermined </p>

<p>27 
HPV 53 
HPV 11 
Probable HR -LR </p>

<p> 
HPV 11 
HPV 11, 58, 66 
LR -LR + HR + probable HR </p>

<p>46 
HPV 16 
HPV 6 
HR -LR </p>

<p>72 
HPV 58, 66 
HPV 58 
HR + probable HR -HR </p>

<p>75 
HPV 33, 58 
HPV 33 
HR -HR </p>

<p>81 
HPV 33 
HPV 11, 66 
HR -LR + probable HR </p>

<p>82 
HPV 6, 16 
HPV 51 
LR + HR -HR </p>

<p>104 
HPV 6 
HPV 56 
LR -HR </p>

<p>123 
HPV 58 
HPV 6 
HR -LR </p>

<p>127 
HPV 51 
HPV 6, 51 
HR -LR + HR </p>

<p>133 
HPV 51, 53, 66 
HPV 66 
HR + probable HR -probable HR </p>

<p>* In 40 women, HPV DNA disappeared in further analysis; in 17 patients, HPV type was the same in all samples. 
HR: High-risk cancer; LR: Low-risk cancer. </p>

<p>Table 5. Correlation Between Histological Diagnosis and HPV DNA Detection for Cervical Samples. Granada, Spain </p>

<p>HPV 
Biopsy Diagnosis 
Negative 
Low-Risk 
High-Risk 
Probable High-Risk 
Multiple Infections </p>

<p>Inflammatory lesions 
19 
14 
16 
12 
6 </p>

<p>ASCUS (Atypia borderline) 
5 
0 
4 
2 
3 </p>

<p>LSIL 
4 
13 
26 
11 
14 </p>

<p>HSIL 
0 
4 
17 
0 
3 </p>

<p>No histological study 
26 
7 
9 
3 
7 </p>

<p>* In 3 cases DNA was not obtained. </p>

<p>HPV in Cervical Cytology </p>

<p>The Open Virology Journal, 2009, Volume 3 65 </p>

<p>approved test to screen for the presence or absence of 
high/low-risk oncogenic HPV types [21]. However, several 
other technologies are being used for this purpose such as the 
in situ hybridization [22], polymerase chain reaction [23], 
real-time PCR [14] and new array methods [13]. It is 
apparent that there are substantial differences with respect to 
the sensitivity of the different diagnostic methods that should 
be assessed. In general in our study, the concordance with 
respect to the results obtained from both institutions was 
high, but some differences could be observed; real-time PCR 
(Roche) seems more sensitive than array method 
(Genomica). For example, in one case in which we did not 
found DNA, the use of a real-time PCR method in this 
sample led to obtain a positive result (three HPV types). For 
this reason, we believe that the performance of some 
comparative studies of the different methods from detection 
of HPV would be advisable in a high population of patients 
and with the most homogeneous conditions possible. </p>

<p>In our study there are several data that could be 
enhanced. Firstly, a higher percentage of infection with 
multiple types was obtained (33 samples/18.9%) with respect 
to other Spanish studies [10, 17], and the majority of them 
were caused with two HPV types. In the majority of articles 
HPV types 16, 18, 31 were the most common HPV types 
obtained [3, 15, 17]. However, in our study HPV type 18 
only was obtained in two samples (1.1%). These data are 
agreeing with other published studies in Spain [17, 18], in 
which HPV type 18 does not appear as a common type in the 
general population in our country. Secondly, HPV type 16 
was the most common type in all studies, but there was some 
differences with respect to the prevalence to the other HPV 
types. In our study, the prevalence of HPV type 16 was 
lower than those described in the medical literature (about 
50%) [15]. HPV type 16 and 18 are the two main target of 
both vaccines, so the address of prevalence of these types is 
important. In the majority of studies, HPV 16 and 18 cause 
70-80% of lesions [3, 15, 17]; however, in our study the 
prevalence of both types taken together was 22.3%. This fact 
is highlighted for the introduction of vaccines in a precise 
population. From an epidemiological point of view, the 
performance of these kind of works in a local level is 
important, because it is necessary to know the different 
epidemiological patterns to apply the correct diagnostic, 
prophylactic and therapeutically measures in each area. </p>

<p>Third, in the majority of women included in our study, 
the HPV infections (high and low-risk types) disappeared 
promptly in the follow-up (6-12 months), so it could be 
speculate that the strength control of these patients is the 
better attitude and no additional treatment is necessary for 
them. The high percentage of infection with probable high-
risk types (28 samples/16.09%) is another factor to take into 
account in order to keeping alert with these women. </p>

<p>Fourth, another important result is the low correlation 
between the histological lesions and the HPV DNA detection 
for cervical samples (Table 5). In our opinion, this fact could 
be due to several reasons: the presence of high variability in 
harvesting samples (no clearly visible or established lesions, 
endocervical location, suboptimal collection of samples), the 
different sensitivity and specificity of our diagnosis method 
(Table 2) with respect to other methods, the biological 
characteristics of the viruses and finally the variability in the </p>

<p>interpretation of the histological features and absence of 
reliable criteria. This feature is an important issue because 
the histological diagnosis in cervical pathology is the "gold 
standard". The absence of complete reliability is a common 
problem in all kinds of biopsies come from different organs 
and tissues, above all in low-grade neoplastic lesions. 
Moreover, in spite of this inconvenient, microscopic 
evaluation of cervical biopsies has a high level of accuracy 
done by expert pathologists. Thus, the absence of 
concordance between HPV typing and the histological 
diagnosis means that HPV could be present in cervical 
epithelial cells without produce atypical changes or minimal 
cellular alterations identified by means of cytology. In fact, 
in our study 48 of 67 (71.6%) samples with reactive 
conditions were positive for HPV infection, although 9 of 14 
(64.2%), 64 of 68 (94.1%) and 24 of 24 (100%) were also 
positive for HPV DNA and were diagnosed of atypia 
borderline, LSIL and HSIL respectively. In addition, another 
relevant aspect is the presence of 26 of 52 (50%) cases with 
HPV infection in patients without changes in colposcopic 
examination (no biopsies were taken by the gynaecologist). </p>

<p>This fact is important in order to avoid that healthy 
women without dysplasic atypical changes in the cervical 
epithelium (histopathological study) could be considerate ill, 
only based in positive HPV typing. Evidence-based 
information must be released to the general population for 
public health educational purposes. </p>

<p>Quality controlled screening programs and preventive 
measures are really necessaries to reduce the incidence of 
HPV infection and the incidence of cervical cancer. 
Epidemiologic studies clearly demonstrated that infection 
with HPV high-risk types is essential for the development of 
cervical cancer [24]. At the moment, the only two 
prophylactic vaccines available for clinical use are generated 
by recombinant technologies and are composed of viral-like 
particles. Cervarix produced by GlaxoSmithKline is a 
bivalent vaccine (HPV 16-18), while Gardasil produced by 
Merck is a quadrivalent vaccine (HPV 6-11-16-18). Until 
now, little is known about their comparative efficacy, safety 
and duration of protection. These data will be available in 
the future when these vaccines be widely worldwide applied. </p>

<p>However, after the analysis of the different 
epidemiological published studies, it can see that the 
epidemiological patterns of HPV types prevalence could be 
different depending of the region of origin. In many 
countries, these vaccines could prevent 50% of all HPV 
infections in women without cytological alterations [3], but 
also 70-80% of HPV infections caused in high-risk lesions or 
invasive carcinoma [15]. In our area, and taking into account 
the data shown in this paper, only approximately 30% of 
HPV infections that led to precursor neoplastic cervical 
lesions could be favoured with the introduction of the 
recently approved vaccines. In addition, it is necessary to 
study the prevalence of HPV types related to cervical 
carcinoma because we do not know the prevalence of HPV 
types that cause invasive carcinoma in our geographic area 
(the types that cause invasive cancer have a different 
distribution with respect those causing preneoplastic lesions) 
[15]. Thus, assessment of the distribution of HPV types in 
each health area will be a very important factor to indicate 
the vaccines. They imply that more epidemiological studies </p>



<p>Cobo et al. </p>

<p>are necessary to know the HPV type prevalence in each area 
and regional variation in the distribution of certain HPV 
types should be taken into account in the future production 
of vaccines. </p>

<p>Moreover, it can speculate that the generalized 
introduction of these vaccines could produce an 
epidemiological pattern change, so in the further several 
years the majority of HPV infections will be produced for 
different HPV types with oncogenic risk than 16 and 18. 
Other situations that could be considerate are as follows: 
HPV prevalence in immunodepressed patients and the effect 
of vaccine in the origin and evolution of non-gynaecological 
HPV-induced cancers (oral, anal, oropharyngeal). </p>

<p>CONCLUSION </p>

<p>Regional variations in prevalence and distribution of 
HPV types have been demonstrated in several 
epidemiological studies. In some countries such as Spain, 
these changes could also be due to the increase of migrant 
women from Latin America [19], Eastern Europe [25] and 
North Africa [26] countries, so health service providers must 
establish continuous localized screening programs in order to 
identify the HPV infections. Moreover, apart of the change 
of the HPV types distribution pattern, an increase of the 
multiple infections can be observed. In our study, a higher 
percentage of infection with multiple types was obtained (33 
samples/18.9%) with respect to other Spanish studies [10,  17]. Also, in this study, the prevalence of HPV type 16 was 
lower than those described in the medical literature (about 
50%) [15]. In the majority of women included in our study, 
HPV infections (high and low-risk types) disappeared 
promptly in the follow-up (6-12 months) and there was low 
correlation between the histological lesions and the HPV 
DNA detection for cervical samples, so further studies are 
neccesaries to address this fact. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>We would like acknowledge Ms. Angela Barnie for 
checking the English language of this manuscript. </p>



<p>Received: July 8, 2009 
Revised: July 27, 2009 
Accepted: August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>© Cobo et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http: //creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/ 
3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>