<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2956241" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:18+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The congruence between self reported drug use and urinalysis data among 89 consecutive 
opioid dependents at their first contact in an outpatient clinic was examined. For this purpose self 
reports of drug use within preceding 72 hr, laboratory analysis of urine samples by thin layer 
chromatography (TLC) were carried out for various drugs. The same samples were also confirmed by 
gas liquid chromatography (GL C). Many subjects reported concomitant poly-drug use. The base rate 
was found to be low for other drugs besides heroin. The conclusion could be dra wn more con vincingly 
as regard heroin use. Inaccuracy in self-report of drug use has been observed using GLC as a gold 
standard. The subjects are likely to be more accurate when they report abstinence than when reporting 
drug use. These results also suggest that clinicians should be cautious while prescribing agonist/ 
partial agonists especially based on only self-report for long term maintenance program, as many 
patients may not be really physiolologically dependent. </p>

<p>A total of 89 male consecutive new 
patients, with opiate dependence were examined 
and interviewed at their first contact by two 
psychiatrists to obtain information on drug use. 
Their demographic data (age, sex, education, 
occupation, marital status) were recorded. Self-
reports of commonly abused drug in our setting 
within preceding 72 hr were also recorded. 
Immediately after interview and clinical 
examination, 50ml of urine samples were 
collected from each patient under close 
supervision and were submitted for laboratory </p>



<p>RAKA JAIN era/. </p>

<p>TABLE 
GLC DATA VERSUS SELF REPORT IN PAST 72 HR </p>

<p>Drug </p>

<p>Morphine </p>

<p>Buprenorphine </p>

<p>Diazepam </p>

<p>Nitrazepam </p>

<p>V </p>

<p>True postives </p>

<p>34.8 </p>

<p>12.4 </p>

<p>15.7 </p>

<p>6.7 </p>

<p>True Negatives </p>

<p>19.1 </p>

<p>76.4 </p>

<p>61.8 </p>

<p>57.3 </p>

<p>Positive 
Predictive 
Value </p>

<p>43.7 </p>

<p>55 </p>

<p>66.7 </p>

<p>31.6 </p>

<p>Negative 
Predictive 
Value </p>

<p>94.4 </p>

<p>98.6 </p>

<p>80.9 </p>

<p>72.9 </p>

<p>Diagnoistic 
Accuracy </p>

<p>54 </p>

<p>88.8 </p>

<p>77.5 </p>

<p>64 </p>

<p>-
analysis. All urine samples were hydrolyzed and 
were screened for drugs by thin layer 
chromatography (TLC) (Jain,1998). Further, 
confirmation of TLC urinalysis results was done 
by gas liquid chromatography. Descriptive 
statistics, positive and negative predictive values 
diagnostic accuracy was calculated by using 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">Biomedical data processing (BMDP) statistical 
package</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 7.0</rs>. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The mean age of the subjects were 32.3 
years (SD=9.3), 67% were married, 36% were 
illiterate and others had varied level of education. 
Even though these subjects were dependent on 
heroin, many were multi-drug users. In past 72 
hr,79.8% of the subjects had used heroin,22.5% 
buprenorphine,4.5 % d-propoxyphene, 23.6 % 
diazepam, 21.3% nitrazepam, 16.8% pheniramine 
and 11.2% promethazine as per self report. Table 
shows the results of GLC urinalysis data against 
self reports respectively. The results can be 
interpreted with certainty for the four compounds: 
morphine, buprenorphine, diazepam, nitrazepam. 
For the remaining compounds, the base rate was 
low. It was observed that GLC yielded more true 
positives than TLC urinalysis results. Positive 
predictive value varied between 43.7%-66.7%, 
except for nitrazepam and negative predictive 
ranged between 72.9%-98.6%. Diagnostic 
accuracy (i.e. congruence between self report and 
urinalysis was overall high (64%-88.8%) for all 
the drugs except for morphine (54%). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our findings suggest that even though 
some of the subjects were poly-drug users, most 
had used heroin exclusively. Only on some 
occasions ranging between 4-24%, subjects had 
used other compounds. Most of the conclusions 
can be drawn convincingly as regard heroin use, 
due to low base rate of use of other drugs. The 
finding of this study should be interpreted in the 
light of the fact that information was collected at 
the first treatment contact at our Centre. Yet, the 
true positives in the sample (by GLC) were a 
minority. 
More true positives and less true negatives 
were obtained from GLC as compared to TLC urine 
analysis results. This may be influenced by 
several factors viz. limited sensitivity of TLC test, 
consumption of drug prior to 24 hours by the 
subject, purity of drug purchased on the street 
etc.(Preston et al., 1997). In this study diagnostic 
accuracy was found to be low for morphine. A 
major finding of this study is that, subjects over-
report heroin (morphine), buprenorphine and 
nitrazepam use as the positive predictive value 
was low. Negative predictive value was high 
suggesting that negative self report of drug use is 
usually quite reliable. This study is in accordance 
of previous finding from our Centre that patients 
sometimes over-report or underreport their drug 
use (Jain,2000). Over-reporting or under-reporting 
has also been seen in Western studies (Magura 
etal.,1987; Mieczkowskietal.,1991). In contrast, 
subjects are likely to be more accurate when they </p>



<p>SELF-REPORT AND URINALYSIS </p>

<p>are abstinent(no drug use). Clinicians should be 
made aware of these findings as many of the 
patients may not be really physiologically opioid 
dependent and they should be cautious while 
prescribing long term opioid agonist. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This study was supported by Drug 
Dependence Treatment Centre, All India Institute 
of Medical Sciences (AIIMS), New Delhi, India. </p>





</text></tei>