<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2677890" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.5-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-05-09T04:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>We introduce a technology for the rapid identifica-
tion and sequencing of conserved DNA elements 
employing a novel suspension array based on nano-
liter (nl)-reactors made from alginate. The reactors 
have a volume of 35 nl and serve as reaction com-
partments during monoseptic growth of microbial 
library clones, colony lysis, thermocycling and 
screening for sequence motifs via semi-quantitative 
fluorescence analyses. nl-Reactors were kept in 
suspension during all high-throughput steps which 
allowed performing the protocol in a highly space-
effective fashion and at negligible expenses of 
consumables and reagents. As a first application, 
11 high-quality microsatellites for polymorphism 
studies in cassava were isolated and sequenced 
out of a library of 20 000 clones in 2 days. The tech-
nology is widely scalable and we envision that 
throughputs for nl-reactor based screenings can 
be increased up to 100 000 and more samples 
per day thereby efficiently complementing pro-
tocols based on established deep-sequencing 
technologies. </p>

<p>Identification of conserved DNA fragments in poorly 
characterized DNA samples (e.g. metagenomic or 
genomic libraries) is a challenge (1,2). We introduce a 
novel technology based on nl-reactors for screening of </p>

<p>large libraries. The technology was adapted to the identi-
fication of conserved sequence motifs in the genome of 
cassava and we argue that any microbial library can 
be screened in this way. As key steps are based on well-
established and robust techniques (e.g. DNA amplification 
by microbial growth, PCR and Sanger sequencing) the 
protocol can be easily extended to other applications. </p>

<p>Fishing for conserved DNA motifs </p>

<p>A prerequisite for the successful sequencing of an individ-
ual DNA molecule out of a mixture of DNA molecules 
is the dilution of the DNA molecules down to a level at 
which single molecules are obtained. Afterwards these 
single molecules are arrayed in a fashion guaranteeing 
that no cross-contamination between samples occurs. 
One of the most-efficient methods for compartmentaliza-
tion of single DNA molecules is to clone them into repli-
cating elements (e.g. plasmids, fosmids or BACs) (3-5) 
and to transform microbial hosts with these. By doing 
so, single DNA molecules are arrayed in a very small 
volume which in the case of single Escherichia coli cells, 
for instance, is in the order of a few femtoliters. The DNA 
is then rapidly amplified upon growth of the clones. 
However, in order not to mix the clones and therefore 
also the genetic information during growth, a secondary 
array for monoseptic (i.e. comprising offspring of one 
clone only) cell cultivation has to be employed. Such 
arrays are typically agar plates providing convenient 
means for monoseptic growth of single cells on solid 
support (6,7). 
However, processing and handling of larger quantities 
of plates employed for colony expansion and picking 
is rather laborious and requires a highly automated </p>

<p>Author's contributions 
M.W. carried out the described experiments and wrote the manuscript. M.B. contributed with thermocycler programming. H.V. reviewed the plant 
part of the manuscript. R.P., A.J.M., R.R., J.M. and S.P. supervised and improved critical parts of the work. M.H. was the responsible senior 
researcher on the project. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +41 44 632 4315; Fax: +41 44 632 1325; Email: martin.held@bsse.ethz.ch </p>

<p>ß 2009 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>environment (5). Furthermore, agar plates cannot be used 
as reaction vessels for in vitro DNA manipulations 
(e.g. PCR or sequencing). Thus, cells have to be trans-
ferred into another array, typically a microtiter plate, 
thereby slowing down the process and requiring additional 
equipment. As a result, processing of 100 000 clones per 
day is probably already close to the practicable limit for 
most screening applications (8) employing microbial 
clones. This is one of the reasons why novel technologies 
(1,9) from within the field of ultra-high-throughput 
screening (HTS) do not rely on the arraying of single 
molecules in cells anymore but employ immobilization 
on surfaces [e.g. microbeads (10,11) or microchips (12)] 
or in microemulsions (13-17) as main compartmentaliza-
tion mechanisms. 
Still, single molecule arraying in cells has a number of 
advantages: First, error rates during amplification of the 
DNA by cell growth are much lower than in vitro (5). 
Second, the information content per array element, i.e. 
the length of the screened fragment is much larger than 
in the competing in vitro systems (3). Third, by the simple 
application of antibiotic selection pressure, array elements 
with contents (transformed clones) can be very efficiently 
separated from empty ones (i.e. clones that do not contain 
a DNA fragment) (6). Fourth, amplification of certain 
sequences such as repeating regions requires specific con-
ditions in vitro (9) whereas cells generally provide an 
appropriate environment for polynucleotide amplification 
probably with the exception of a few cases where coinci-
dently toxic gene products are synthesized (18). Fifth, cells 
can also be used for functional screenings, i.e. for screen-
ings where first the phenotype is screened and only clones 
featuring the desired properties are sequenced (19). 
We demonstrate a PCR-based method for HTS of 
microbial DNA libraries at screening rates of at least 
20 000 samples per run. This requires the combination of 
conventional cloning and bacterial library construction 
methods with high-throughput technologies for thermocy-
cling and hit-candidate isolation. The core of the technol-
ogy is the use of hydrogel microcarriers that are produced 
by laminar jet break-up technology and serve as growth 
and reaction compartments. The microcarriers have a 
diameter of $400 mm and a volume of $35 nl and are 
subsequently referred to as nl-reactors. The key feature 
of nl-reactors is their capability to retain high-molecular-
weight components such as cells, plasmid constructs 
or PCR products while at the same time allowing low-
molecular-weight components (i.e. nutrients, or mono-
and oligonucleotides for PCR) as well as some proteins 
(in this case DNA polymerase) to continuously access and 
leave the reactor (see Figure 1). Due to these properties, 
PCR products are accumulated within the nl-reactors 
during thermocycling and positive samples can be 
straightforwardly isolated on the basis of the fluores-
cence-intensity of nl-reactors after staining of the 
embedded double-stranded DNA. 
In this article, we report a sequence-based screening of 
a cassava (Manihot esculenta) shot-gun library in E. coli 
for identification of microsatellites for gene-marker devel-
opment (see Figure 2). An equivalent of $8 million base 
pairs was screened within 2 days and it can be foreseen </p>

<p>that the method can be readily adapted to uncover the 
diversity of gene sequences sharing conserved motifs, e.g. 
within non-sequenced organisms and environmental 
libraries. The process is easy to scale-up and we envisage 
that throughput can be easily increased further to 200 mil-
lion bases or more per day. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Unless mentioned otherwise, media and media 
components were obtained from Fluka (Buchs, 
Switzerland). </p>

<p>Preparation of cell suspension in alginate and production 
of nl-reactors </p>

<p>Two 40 ml aliquots of electrocompetent E. coli Top10 
(F-
mcrA 
Á(mrr-hsdRMS-mcrBC) 
'80lacZÁM15 
ÁlacX74 recA1 araD139 Á(ara-leu)7697 galU galK rpsL 
endA1 nupG, Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA) harboring plas-
mid pMMBs207-Km14-GFPc (20) with a gfp-mut2 gene 
constitutively expressed from an unregulated P tac pro-
moter were transformed with 2 ml of ligation mixture 
of a cassava library (gDNA digested with Bsp143I 
(Fermentas International, Burlington, Canada), size 
selected (350-700 bp) and ligated into a commercially 
BamHI-digested and dephosphorylated pUC19 vector 
(Fermentas 
International, 
Burlington, 
Canada). 
Transformation was carried out with a Genepulser 
(Biorad, Hercules, CA) at 1.25 kV in a 1 mm cuvette. 
Cells were incubated directly after the pulse in 1 ml SOC 
medium (30 min; 378C) and centrifuged (5 min; 5000 g) in 
order to remove non-transformed plasmid DNA. The cell-
pellet was resuspended in 1 ml SOC medium supplemented 
with antibiotics (30 mg/l chloramphenicol; 100 mg/l ampi-
cillin), incubated (45 min; 378C) and centrifuged (5 min; 
5000 g). The supernatant was discarded. The cell-
pellet was resuspended in 20 ml salt solution (9 g/l NaCl, </p>

<p>High MW compounds 
e.g. cells/colonies, DNA </p>

<p>Low MW compounds 
e.g. reagents, nutrients, indicators </p>

<p>Figure 1. nl-Reactors' characteristics. nl-Reactors consist of a highly 
thermostable hydrogel and have a volume of 35 nl (diameter of 
400 mm). The porosity of the capsule allows free diffusion of low molec-
ular compounds whereas high-molecular-weight structures cannot pene-
trate. Embedded E. coli cells can therefore feed on externally provided 
nutrients and readily expand to colonies that remain immobilized 
within the nl-reactor. Similarly, larger DNA elements such as plasmids 
that were liberated from the colonies upon lysis or PCR products 
formed by thermocycling are also retained, while PCR reagents can 
continuously access and leave the nl-reactor. </p>

<p>e57 Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 </p>

<p>
1 g/l KCl) containing 25 mg autoclaved graphite powder, 
added to 20 ml of a sterile-filtered 3% alginate solution in 
a 50 ml screw-top tube, and mixed by gently inverting the 
tube manually (5 min; room temperature). 
The alginate-cell suspension was immediately pro-
cessed with a laminar jet break-up encapsulator (Nisco 
Engineering AG, Zurich) with a nozzle of 150 mm in </p>

<p>diameter at a frequency of 1050 Hz. The resulting droplets 
of $500 mm diameter (65 nl) were collected in a continu-
ously stirred beaker (120 ml maximal filling volume; 
200 r.p.m.) filled with 100 ml hardening solution (50 mM 
BaCl 2 ). The nl-reactors were allowed to mature for 30 min 
which caused the gel-capsules to shrink to diameters of 
$400 mm (35 nL). </p>

<p>insert </p>

<p>A A T A C T G T A C C T C T G A C A C A C A C A C A C A C A C </p>

<p>1. Library construction 
Digestion and ligation of 
target-DNA into plasmid DNA 
(according to current standard 
protocols). </p>

<p>14 h </p>

<p>2. Transformation of fluores-
cent E. coli 
Transformation &amp; selection in 
liquid culture. Transformed cells 
are suspended in alginate 
precursor solution for encapsula-
tion. </p>

<p>1.5 h </p>

<p>3. Cell encapsulation in 
nL-reactors 
Formation of alginate micro-
droplets containing Poisson-
distributed cells by laminar jet 
break-up. </p>

<p>0.5 h (660'000 nL-reactors) </p>

<p>4. Proliferation of individual 
clones in nL-reactors 
Colony expansion within 
nL-reactors until ~50'000 cells 
are obtained. </p>

<p>15.5 h </p>

<p>5. Enrichment of monoclonal 
nL-reactors 
Monoclonal nL-reactors are 
separated from empty and 
polyclonal reactors with a 
particle analyzer and sorter 
(COPAS). </p>

<p>3 h (200'000 nL-reactors) </p>

<p>6. PCR screening of compart-
mentalized colonies 
Monoseptic nL-reactors are 
washed &amp; PCR is performed 
employing a customized thermo-
cycler. </p>

<p>3 h (20'000 nL-reactors) </p>

<p>7. Analysis &amp; dispensing of 
PCR positives into 96-well 
plates 
nL-Reactors are washed and 
stained for visualization of PCR 
positives. Positive nL-reactors 
are dispensed into 96-well 
plates. </p>

<p>0.5 h (20'000 nL-reactors) </p>

<p>8. Recovery of plasmid DNA 
DNA of PCR-positive nL-reactors 
is extracted in 96-well plates. </p>

<p>3 h </p>

<p>9. Plasmid-insert amplification 
The entire inserts of the 
extracted plasmids are amplified 
by PCR. </p>

<p>2 h </p>

<p>10. Sequence analysis with 
Sanger sequencing reaction 
The PCR products are cleaned 
up and sequenced by conven-
tional Sanger sequencing 
protocols employing capillary 
electrophoresis. </p>

<p>5 h </p>

<p>PCR reagents </p>

<p>nutrients </p>

<p>insert </p>

<p>pUC19 </p>

<p>waste </p>

<p>waste~4 </p>

<p>8 h total screening time </p>

<p>Figure 2. Flow chart-high throughput colony PCR screening in nL-reactors. </p>

<p> 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 e57 </p>

<p>Proliferation of E. coli in nl-reactors and determination 
of colony diameter </p>

<p>The nl-reactors were recovered from the hardening solu-
tion by sieving (100 mm Falcon sieve; BD, Franklin Lakes, 
NJ) and washed three times in 150 ml of growth-medium 
(4 g/l Bacto yeast extract; 1 g/l Bacto tryptone; 1 g/l gly-
cerol, 1 mM BaCl 2 ; 10 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.0; 30 mg/l 
chloramphenicol; 100 mg/l ampicillin). Aliquots of $3 g 
wet nl-reactors were added to Petri dishes containing 
30 ml of growth medium. The plates were covered with 
their lids and incubated for 14 h at 308C. Afterwards 
ampicillin was added to the medium to 100 mg/l and the 
plates were incubated for an additional 1.5 h (378C). 
nl-Reactors were recovered from the dishes, sieved, 
washed three times with 50 ml washing solution (10 mM 
Tris pH 8.0, 0.1 mM BaCl 2 ; pH 8.0) and kept on ice until 
processing by Complex Object Parametric Analyzer and 
Sorter (COPAS; Union Biometrica, Holliston, MA). Later 
the average colony diameter and cell number was deter-
mined by analyzing 30 colonies that had been grown 
within the nl-reactor by fluorescence microscopy under 
the assumption that a typical E. coli cell volume is 2 fl. </p>

<p>COPAS analysis for enrichment of monoclonal 
microcarriers </p>

<p>Monoseptic nl-reactors harboring one colony only were 
enriched by COPAS sorting employing the '<rs type="software">Profiler</rs>' soft-
ware (21). Pulse shape diagram recording was triggered by 
the opacity signal [threshold &gt;25 AU (arbitrary units); 
signal gain factor 1.5; measuring range 0-65500 AU]. nl-
Reactor size is expressed as time-of-flight [(ToF); gated 
range 400-750 ToF, arbitrary units]. Fluorescence signals 
for colony detection were generally recorded at 510 nm, 
which is the emission maximum of the employed GFP 
[ex 488 nm, photon multiplier settings (PMT) 800 V; gain 
factor 1.0; measuring range 0-65 500 AU; peak-
profiling was initiated at &gt;20 000 AU; gated range 
60 000-65 500]. The COPAS-device was operated at an 
average frequency of 30 Hz and coincidence settings for 
dispensing into microtiter plates were adjusted to 'pure'-
mode which guarantees that nl-reactors are only sorted-
out if no other reactor is coincidentally within the same 
droplet. A detailed description of the cell encapsulation, 
proliferation and isolation procedure employed for enrich-
ment of monoseptic nl-reactors by COPAS, was published 
elsewhere (21). </p>

<p>In-bead PCR screening of embedded colonies </p>

<p>A total number of 20 000 enriched monoseptical nl-reac-
tors were suspended in a 50 ml Falcon tube in 10 ml of 
ddH 2 O. The cells were lyzed by heat (10 min in a water 
bath at 968C). The microcarriers were washed once in 
50 ml washing solution and three times in 50 mL ddH 2 O 
and directly added to a poly(fluoro acrylate) PCR-bag 
(Welch Fluorocarbon, Dover, NH; 100 Â 100 mm; thick-
ness: 50 mm) containing 10 ml PCR reagent [ddH 2 O con-
taining: 1 M betaine; 5% DMSO; 1 Â PCR buffer; 0.1 mM 
BaCl 2 ; 0.2 mM of each dNTPs; 0.2 mM primer M13F 
(-21); 0.2 mM primer GA 9 ; 700 U Taq polymerase; </p>

<p>Genscript, Piscataway, NJ]. All gas bubbles were 
removed, the PCR-bag was air-tightly sealed, and cycled 
on a custom-built flat-screen thermocycler that consisted 
of a chamber flanked by aluminum plates which contained 
channels for water circulation for temperature control (32 
cycles; 90 s at 968C; 180 s at 558C) exerted by two water-
baths (Huber Polystat CC3; set to 968C and 568C, respec-
tively). Numerically, controlled thermo-switching between 
the two water cycles was realized with four valves (m&amp;m 
international, Bedford, UK) controlling the in-and outlet 
of the water baths and a customized <rs id="software-2" type="software">LabView</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">National Instruments</rs>; Austin; TX) program controlling the relay-
switch station USB-Erb24 (Measurement Computing 
Corp., Norton, MA). After cycling, the beads were recov-
ered from the bag by sieving, washed with 50 ml washing 
solution and 250 ml ddH 2 O and suspended in a Petri dish 
with 20 ml washing solution containing 1Â SYBR Green I 
dye (Invitrogen; Carlsbad; CA) in order to stain PCR-
products prior to another COPAS analysis. Microscopic 
pictures were taken by a Zeiss Axio Star Plus fluorescence 
microscope (Carl Zeiss AG; Go¨ttingen; Germany) using 
an excitation filter at 488 nm and an emission long-pass 
filter &gt;520 nm in combination with phase contrast 
microscopy. </p>

<p>Screening for PCR positive nl-reactors </p>

<p>All nl-reactors recovered after thermocycling were added 
to the COPAS sample cup and analyzed. Both, object 
diameter (based on extinction) as well as fluorescence 
intensity (510 nm) of each nl-reactor, were measured con-
comitantly by pulse shape analysis (COPAS profiler soft-
ware). First, the system was calibrated by analyzing 300 
nl-reactors in order to set an adaptive fluorescence inten-
sity threshold just above the main, non-fluorescent, popu-
lation, which was evaluated to be at 780 AU (at 510 nm). 
Next, gates for a ToF value of 600-1000 AU were applied 
for dispensing of nL-reactors into a 96-well microtiter 
plate. For sampling of the control group, the same ToF 
gates were applied and 48 putatively PCR-negative 
nl-reactors featuring signal intensities below the adaptive 
threshold (600-780 AU) were sorted out. All samples were 
immediately processed further in order to recover the plas-
mids (see next section). </p>

<p>Plasmid extraction with cetyl trimethylammonium 
bromide (CTAB) </p>

<p>For plasmid extraction, we adapted a method developed 
by Allen et al. (22). An aliquot of 90 ml of freshly prepared 
and pre-warmed (508C) CTAB DNA extraction buffer 
[100 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0); 1.4 M NaCl; 2.5% w/v 
CTAB; 0.5% w/v N-lauryl sarcosine] was added to a 
well containing a single isolated nl-reactor (one reactor 
per MT-plate well), plates were air-tightly sealed by 
8-cap strips, incubated in a PCR cycler (Mastercycler, 
Eppendorf, 658C; 45 min) and every 5 min vigorously agi-
tated by hand for 10 s in order to dissolve the nl-reactor. 
After centrifugation at 3200 g for 30 s, 90 ml of chloroform/ 
isoamylalcohol (24/1) were added and plates were agitated 
by hand until turbid emulsions were formed in the wells 
($15 s). Plates were centrifuged (30 min at 3200 g) and an </p>

<p>e57 Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 </p>

<p>
aliquot of 33 ml was withdrawn from the aqueous phase, 
transferred to another microtiter plate, and DNA was 
precipitated by ethanol (77 ml per well). After overnight 
incubation at -808C, samples were centrifuged (45 min; 
3220 g; 08C) and supernatants were discarded prior to 
washing (100 ml of 70% EtOH, chilled to -208C and cen-
trifuged for 30 min; 3220 g; 08C). Once more, supernatants 
were discarded and the remaining liquid was allowed to 
evaporate at room temperature. </p>

<p>Insert amplification by PCR </p>

<p>PCR reagents [25 ml comprising: 1Â PCR Buffer, 200 mM 
of each dNTP, 200 nM of primer M13F(-43) and 
M13R(+86), 1.75 U Taq DNA polymerase] were added 
to the dried pellet and the plasmid inserts were amplified 
by PCR (denaturation at 958C for 1 min, then 40 cycles of: 
958C for 30 s, 558C for 30 s, 728C for 1 min, and final 
elongation: 728C for 2 min). After cycling, 5 ml of each 
sample were loaded on a 1.5% agarose gel in order to 
determine the number of PCR-amplified fragments per 
sample, the insert size as well as the approximate PCR 
product concentration. All samples yielding a single 
band of at least 100 ng of DNA on the gel (equivalent to 
20 ng/ml concentration in the well) were sent out for 
Sanger sequencing with a M13 reverse primer (GATC 
Biotech, Konstanz, Germany). </p>

<p>Polymorphism test </p>

<p>Clone-redundancy was tested with the <rs id="software-5" type="software">DNA Star</rs> Software 
(<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">DNAstar inc.</rs>., Madison, WI). Default assembly param-
eters were used: match size: 12 bp; minimum match 
percentage: 80%; minimum sequence length 100 bp; max-
imum added gaps per kb in contig: 70 bp; maximum added 
gaps per kb in sequence: 70 bp; last group considered: 2; 
gap penalty: 0.00; gap length penalty: 0.70. 
Only sequences with a match to the screening primer of 
10 bases or more were used to subsequently design micro-
satellite markers. Next, PCR primers flanking the CT-rich 
region were designed by the <rs type="software">primer-3</rs> software; http://fok 
ker.wi.mit.edu/primer3/input.htm). Amplicon length poly-
morphism of microsatellite markers was tested by PCR on 
seven different cassava cultivars (91/02322; TMS60444; 
95/0306; 98/0002; TAI-8; PER-183; COL-1505) using 
FAM-labeled primers. PCRs were performed in a final 
volume of 20 ml: 1Â PCR Buffer, 200 mM each dNTP, 
200 nM of each primer, 5 ng template; 1.75 U Taq DNA 
polymerase; cycling conditions: initial denaturation: 958C 
for 1 min; 35 cycles: 958C for 30 s, 568C for 30 s, 728C for 
40 s; final elongation: 728C for 2 min. Fragments were 
separated by capillary electrophoresis on an ABI 3700 
(Applied Biosystems; Foster City; CA) and analyzed 
by the <rs id="software-7" type="software">GeneMarker</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-7" type="creator">Softgenetics</rs>; State College; PA) soft-
ware. Polymorphic information content (PIC) was calcu-
lated according to Anderson et al. (23). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The objective of this study was the detection and 
sequence determination of specific DNA-motifs from a 
genomic cassava library using an essentially freely scalable </p>

<p>approach employing gel-like, suspended nl-reactors as 
reaction compartments. </p>

<p>Cell encapsulation and proliferation in nl-reactors </p>

<p>The feasibility of the approach was investigated for 
a genomic cassava library (average insert length 
350-700 bp) in E. coli. The sample throughput was 
monitored over all process steps (see Table 1). Freshly 
transformed cells synthesizing a green fluorescent protein 
(GFP) from Aequorea victoria were embedded into 
nl-reactors (660 000 reactors total; average degree of occu-
pation with colonies 10.8%) and propagated from single 
cell status to colonies of $50 000 cells. This was confirmed 
manually by fluorescence microscopy. Next, 20 000 mono-
septic nl-reactors were isolated by COPAS-sorting (21). 
During this step, the number of reactors containing no 
or more than one colony, and reactor multiplets (24), inev-
itably formed during nl-reactor production, was reduced 
to a minimum (Table 1). </p>

<p>Highly parallelized nl-PCR and PCR-product detection </p>

<p>All 20 000 monoseptic nL-reactors were pooled in one 
reaction compartment and subjected to 32 rounds of 
two-step thermocycling with a vector-specific forward 
primer and a reverse primer with specificity for the desired 
SSR-sequences, i.e. poly(CT) repeats (see Supplementary 
Figure 1). After thermocycling, the bead population was 
stained with the DNA double-strand specific dye SYBR 
Green I (see Figure 3) and 66 fluorescent reactors were 
isolated in another COPAS run (Figure 4). </p>

<p>Identification of SSRs of at least 10 bp </p>

<p>After isolation of all 66 putatively positive nl-reactors 
(fluorescent intensity &gt;780 AU) and dispersion into a </p>

<p>Table 1. Sample flow over all process steps </p>

<p>Step 
Processed 
nl-reactors </p>

<p>Selected 
events </p>

<p>Array 
format </p>

<p>Enrichment 
193 000 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>20 000 </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Suspension 
PCR and hit selection 
20 000 
66 </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Suspension 
Plasmid isolation 
66 
52 </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>96-well plate 
Insert sequencing 
52 
52 </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>96-well plate 
Polymorphic microsatellites 
37 </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>96-well plate </p>

<p>Overview over sample streams during HTS for novel SSRs (short 
sequence repeats) in a cassava genomic library. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>The subset of the 660 000 empty and colonized nl-reactors that was 
analyzed and sorted in order to isolate 20 000 monoseptic nl-reactors; 
colony diameter of 32 mm AE 7 mm. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Sorted and monoseptically enriched nl-reactors (still containing $1 to 
2% polyclonal reactors and roughly 2% multiplets) (21). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>nl-reactors displaying fluorescence intensity &gt;780 AU dispensed into 
microtiter plate. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Plasmid extraction confirmed by PCR. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Sanger sequencing. </p>

<p>f </p>

<p>Sequences matching the screening primer by 10 or more bases (eight 
sequences were redundant and not used for polymorphism studies). </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>Based on polymorphism tests employing seven cassava cultivars 
(for details see text). </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 8 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 e57 </p>

<p>micro-titer plate, the plasmid content of the reactors was 
isolated and presence or absence of the plasmid, presum-
ably harboring the SSR sequence, was verified by ampli-
fication of the insert with PCR using two vector-specific 
primers (see Supplementary Figure 1). Length and quan-
tity of the PCR products was determined and the results 
indicated that 52 of the 66 reactors (79%) carried a single 
PCR-product in sufficient quantity (&gt;100 ng) to allow 
sequencing (Supplementary Figure 1). The sequencing 
results indicated that 37 plasmids (71%) showed a 
match of at least 10 bp between sequence and SSR-specific 
primer, which was defined as a criterion for the presence of 
a microsatellite. The 15 remaining nl-reactors carried an 
insert with less than 10 matching bases (4 matches: 6, 
5 matches: 1, 7 matches: 3, 8 matches: 3, 9 matches: 2) 
while of the 37 sequences matching by 10 or more, eight 
were redundant. In summary, the procedure delivered thus 
29 potentially unique and useful SSR markers (Table 2) 
out of an original library of 20 000 monoseptically 
enriched nl-reactors. These sequences were then subjected 
to additional polymorphism studies in seven cassava 
cultivars. 
Within the set of the 48 randomly collected nl-reactors 
with a fluorescence intensity below the adaptive threshold 
(i.e. collected from the interval between 600 and 780 AU, 
Figure 4) that served as a control, plasmid isolation and 
insert amplification succeeded in 35 cases (73%), and of 
these only eight clones (23% of 35) had a primer match of 
10 or more bases while the remaining 27 clones had a 
match of nine or less. The results from this control 
group indicate that tailoring of the adaptive threshold is 
important in order to obtain a high ratio of nl-reactors 
featuring a one-to-one ratio between fluorescence intensity 
and primer match. </p>

<p>Design of microsatellite markers and polymorphism studies </p>

<p>The sequence information obtained from all 29 clones 
(fluorescence intensity &gt;780 AU) featuring a primer 
match of 10 or more was utilized for the design of primers 
for polymorphism studies (Table 2). Generally, a suffi-
ciently large number of bases could be extracted from 
the data to allow the design of primers likely to target 
a unique address in the poorly characterized genome of 
cassava (25). 
The polymorphic information content (PIC), a value 
commonly used in population studies as a measure of 
genetic marker polymorphism, was then determined in 
seven cassava cultivars (see Supplementary Figure 1). In 
total, 11 high-quality microsatellites with a PIC of more 
than zero had thus been isolated (Table 2). Several micro-
satellite primer pairs (2, 11, 22, 24 and 27) were poly-
morphic in only two loci and therefore resulted in a PIC 
of 0.41. Samples 13, 16, 21, 26 and 28, led to the isolation 
of markers with an increasing PIC while one marker 
(sample 29) was found to be indeed polymorph in all cul-
tivars and is therefore rather valuable for population 
studies. 
Thus, 29 individual CT-containing clones had been iso-
lated (Table 2) from a sequence space of at least 7.8 Mbp 
(see 'Discussion and conclusions' section for the ratio-
nale). This suggests an SSR frequency of one in 270 kb. 
This frequency is well within the range of the CT-repeat </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>500 
600 
700 
800 
900 
1000 </p>

<p>Time of flight (TOF) [AU] 
Integrated signal intensity (510 nm) [AU] </p>

<p>Figure 4. nl-Reactor analysis by COPAS after thermocycling. nl-
Reactor fluorescence (excitation: 488 nm; emission: 510 nm) and size 
(indexed by ToF) were COPAS-analyzed and 66 reactors above an 
adaptive fluorescence threshold of 780 AU (dotted line) were isolated. 
Due to apparatus specific limitations of the COPAS sorter, not all but 
$80% of all reactors above the dotted line could be isolated. In the 
region between 600 (solid line) and 780 AU (dotted line), 48 nl-reactors 
were randomly collected and served later as a control. The number of 
nl-reactors containing inserts that matched to the SSR-specific primer 
by at least 10 bases (red circles) amounted on 56% above the threshold 
and on 17% only in the control. Similarly, 23% of all inserts in the 
putative positive fraction yielded a match of &lt;10 bp (blue triangle) 
while in the control 56% belonged to that class. nl-Reactors from 
which plasmid isolation and insert amplification by PCR did not suc-
ceed after liquefaction of the gel-carrier are labeled by an 'X'. Signals 
beyond TOF = 900 AU stem from nl-reactors with multiple volumes 
(about 2% of the total) that have not been completely eliminated by 
COPAS during the first enrichment of monoseptic nl-reactors. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>400 µm </p>

<p>Figure 3. Monoseptic nl-reactors after two-step PCR and staining of 
double-stranded DNA with SYBR Green I. Double-stranded DNA 
entangled in nl-reactors was stained with SYBR Green I dye and fluor-
esces in a green-yellowish color. (a) nl-reactor filled with fluorescent 
PCR product. (b) nl-reactor without PCR product, only the SYBR 
Green I dye binding to the DNA of the lysed colonies fluoresces, 
though small coronas around the colony debris might develop (c). 
The small reddish spots within the reactors are graphite particles (see 
'Materials and Methods' section). </p>

<p>e57 Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 </p>

<p>
abundances typically found in higher plants (one in 
290 kb) (26). The overall efficiency of the protocol from 
PCR-product-sensing to polymorphism-isolation is 11 in 
66 (17%) which is comparable to a process efficiency of 
$20% generally found in the field of microsatellite marker 
development (27). 
In the sampling window below the adaptive intensity 
threshold, eight sequences still had a primer match of 10 
or more. However, in only four cases, primer match 
regions were located at a sufficient distance from the mul-
tiple cloning site of the vector to enable the straightfor-
ward design of primers for polymorphism studies in 
cassava. Based on the PIC-values, however, none of 
these microsatellites was of sufficient quality to serve as 
a marker for future polymorphisms studies in cassava. 
Interestingly, the average of the polymorphic informa-
tion content (PIC) as well as the percentage of poly-
morphic sequences therefore increased with an increasing 
number of bases in the insert matching with the screening 
primer. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>nl-Reactors were employed in a 3D suspension array 
for the compartmentalized growth of an E. coli library 
starting from single clones and directly afterwards for a 
PCR-based colony screening. Large numbers of both, 
colonized nl-reactors and post-PCR samples were ana-
lyzed and sorted by COPAS and the desired fractions of 
monoseptically inoculated nl-reactors and PCR-positive 
samples were directly isolated. Furthermore, plasmids 
identified on the basis of the PCR signal could be easily 
recovered from the nl-reactors and were subsequently sub-
jected to further characterizations, in this case Sanger-
sequencing. The entire procedure did not require more 
than 48 h with an effective hands-on time of $10 h. It 
required only three microtiter plates, in contrast to current 
protocols for microsatellite identification which are sub-
stantially longer and more expensive (cells are plated on 
solid support followed by individual PCR screenings or 
colony hybridizations). 
The longest distance between the vector-specific primer 
and an insert-sequence that was complementary to the 
screening primer was 391 bp (see Table 2). This suggests 
that during PCR at least 391 bases of each of the 20 000 
inserts harbored by the screened nl-reactors were scanned 
for regions matching the screening primer. Therefore, we 
reason that at least 7.8 Mbp were sampled during analysis 
of 20 000 colonies. However, as PCR in solution can be 
employed for amplification of fragments of several thou-
sand base pairs, we believe that the length of the screened 
fragments can be improved further. 
If compared to the classical approaches with two-
dimensional arrays (i.e. microtiter plates or agar plates), 
the volumes employed here for 3D-arrays for cell expan-
sion (600 ml) and PCR (10 ml), were rather low and could 
easily be scaled up by a factor of at least 10 without any 
substantial change of the technology. Furthermore, all 
samples can be handled in one compartment during each 
single step in the entire screening protocol, which greatly 
facilitated the required manipulations such as addition of 
reagents or incubations. For that reason, no sophisticated 
robotics had to be employed. 
The time-limiting step of the protocol is the standard-
ization of the library after growth by COPAS sorting, 
which proceeds at a frequency of approximately 30 Hz. 
From our experience, COPAS devices can be operated 
for at least seven hours during an 8-h working shift. Still, 
throughput for this step will remain limited to roughly 
750 000 events per shift. All other steps that are carried 
out in suspensions (nl-reactor production, cell growth, sus-
pension PCR, and isolation of PCR-positives) require 
approximately another 2 days. Under the conservative 
assumption that inserts of 2 kb could be screened during 
PCR and assuming further that roughly 15% of all syn-
thesized nl-reactors contain single colonies (as it was the 
case in this example), the total number of screened bases 
could thus easily amount to approx. 200 Mbp per day. 
Another obvious measure for further increasing the 
throughput is of course to replace COPAS-sorting by 
another technology such as fluorescence-assisted cell sort-
ing (FACS). Sorting particles by FACS will however have </p>

<p>Table 2. Sequencing results of all clones featuring a primer match of at 
least 10 bases </p>

<p>SSR 
match </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Integrated 
signal </p>

<p>Sensor 
fragment </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Sequence 
length </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>PIC 
d Subgroups 
of Cultivars </p>

<p>e </p>

<p># [bp] 
[AU] 
[bp] 
[bp] 
[-] 
[#] </p>

<p>1 10 
811 
59 
245 
0.00 7 
2 10 
837 
269 
325 
0.41 2; 5 
3 10 
837 
322 
338 
0.00 7 
4 10 
978 
133 
308 
0.00 7 
5 10 
808/856 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>133 
174 
0.00 7 
6 11 
789 
396 
546 
0.00 7 
7 11 
806 
59 
418 
0.00 7 
8 11 
890 
171 
504 
0.00 7 
9 11 
940/840/786 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>133 
236 
0.00 7 
10 12 
802 
117 
397 
0.00 7 
11 12 
818 
200 
222 
0.41 2; 5 
12 12 
821 
149 
610 
0.00 7 
13 12 
825 
133 
277 
0.49 3; 4 
14 12 
835 
124 
261 
0.00 7 
15 12 
836 
313 
384 
0.00 7 
16 12 
863 
168 
384 
0.73 3; 1; 1; 1; 1 
17 12 
897 
149 
323 
0.00 7 
18 12 
910 
112 
261 
0.00 7 
19 12 
882/885/784/861 
Ã 104 
332 
0.00 7 
20 13 
842 
118 
263 
0.00 7 
21 13 
919 
210 
280 
0.78 1; 1; 1; 2; 2 
22 13 
1047 
157 
416 
0.41 2; 5 
23 13 
909/654/793 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>86 
315 
0.00 7 
24 14 
815/871/696 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>117 
348 
0.41 2; 5 
25 14 
823/607 </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>117 
420 
0.00 7 
26 15 
957 
127 
237 
0.65 2; 2; 3 
27 15 
1043 
117 
462 
0.41 2; 5 
28 17 
908 
163 
262 
0.69 1; 1, 2; 3 
29 17 
957 
157 
283 
0.86 1; 1; 1; 1; 1; 1; 1; </p>

<p>a Number of base pairs matching with the sensing primer. </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Length of the sensor fragment employed for identification of PCR 
positive clones expressed as the distance of the M13 forward primer 
to the location at which the screening-primer putatively bound to the 
insert. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>The insert was sequenced employing a vector specific M13 reverse 
primer. </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>PIC = polymorphic information content; polymorphisms were tested 
in seven different cassava cultivars. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Total number of cultivars carrying the same microsatellite allele. 
Ã Redundant clones 
Bold font: polymorphic microsatellite markers; primers and sequences 
are listed in Supplementary Data 1. </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 8 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 e57 </p>

<p>to provide a volume in the lower picoliter (pl)-range and 
such particles can not be reliably produced by the laminar 
jet technology that was employed for capsule synthesis 
here. However, we are currently working on the develop-
ment and standardization of the technologies required for 
the synthesis of hydrogel pl-reactors. 
We argue that the sequence-specific amplification com-
bined with high throughput screening makes this technol-
ogy suitable for other protocols and generally for all cases 
where 'rare' events are sought. Especially screening 
of gene homologues or miRNA precursors (28,29) in 
non-sequenced species and particularly metagenomic 
approaches, e.g. 'fishing' for new enzymes in metagenomic 
libraries, or localization of insertion sequences in muta-
genized genomes (e. g. transposons for random mutagen-
esis) will be greatly facilitated. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We are indebted to the R'equipe program of the Swiss 
National Science Foundation for generous support in 
acquiring the COPAS Plus Biosorter. We also are 
indebted to H. Hilbi for the gift of plasmid pMMB207-
Km14-GFPc, to Bernhard Koller for the support with 
SSR libraries in preliminary tests, and to Maria 
Domenica Moccia for the gift of plasmid pCT16 used in 
optimization experiments. Additionally, we would like to 
thank the four anonymous reviewers for the valuable 
input. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The Swiss Commission for Technology and Innovation 
grants (to M.W., M.H. and R.P.). Funding for open 
access charge: The Swiss Commission for Technology 
and Innovation (KTI/CTI). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>e57 Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 8 
PAGE 8 OF 8 </p>

</text></tei>