<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2927939" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:26+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-To test whether brain fatty acid uptake is en-
hanced in obese subjects with metabolic syndrome (MS) and 
whether weight reduction modifies it. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-We measured brain 
fatty acid uptake in a group of 23 patients with MS and 7 
age-matched healthy control subjects during fasting conditions 
using positron emission tomography (PET) with [ 
11 C]-palmitate 
and [ 
18 F]fluoro-6-thia-heptadecanoic acid ([ 
18 F]-FTHA). Sixteen 
MS subjects were restudied after 6 weeks of very low calorie diet 
intervention. </p>

<p>RESULTS-At baseline, brain global fatty acid uptake derived 
from [ 
18 F]-FTHA was 50% higher in patients with MS compared 
with control subjects. The mean percentage increment was 130% 
in the white matter, 47% in the gray matter, and uniform across 
brain regions. In the MS group, the nonoxidized fraction mea-
sured using [ 
11 C]-palmitate was 86% higher. Brain fatty acid 
uptake measured with [ 
18 F]-FTHA-PET was associated with age, 
fasting serum insulin, and homeostasis model assessment 
(HOMA) index. Both total and nonoxidized fractions of fatty acid 
uptake were associated with BMI. Rapid weight reduction de-
creased brain fatty acid uptake by 17%. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-To our knowledge, this is the first study on 
humans to observe enhanced brain fatty acid uptake in patients 
with MS. Both fatty acid uptake and accumulation appear to be 
increased in MS patients and reversed by weight reduction. 
A </p>

<p>lthough the brain does not use free fatty acids 
(FFAs) as an energy source, recent evidence 
suggests that FFAs and, specifically, their inter-
mediates could have a key role in the central 
control of energy balance regulation and feeding (1-5). 
Both brain FFA uptake and metabolism are currently 
insufficiently defined, whereas the importance of FFAs in 
the pathogenesis of metabolic syndrome (MS) is demon-</p>

<p>strated widely in other organs (6,7). Animal studies have 
demonstrated that hypothalamic sensing of circulating 
fatty acids in general is believed to be important in 
controlling nutrient intake and, thus, energy balance. For 
example, Pocai et al. (5) showed that manipulation of 
central hypothalamic FFA metabolism normalizes energy 
and glucose homeostasis in overfed rats. These regulatory 
processes are difficult to address in humans in vivo, and 
most data in this regard have been demonstrated in small 
animals (1,4,5,8). More work is needed to clarify the 
mechanisms behind the complex hypothalamic regulatory 
circuitry that regulates energy expenditure and feeding 
behavior. 
Positron emission tomography (PET) and other meth-
ods have been used to evaluate the fate of long-chain 
saturated fatty acid carbon-labeled-palmitate (9 -12). PET 
provides a method for noninvasive, quantitative, and re-
gional measurement of FFA uptake, thus making it ideal 
for studying metabolism in different tissues (13). The 
status of brain FFA metabolism in MS is currently un-
known. Therefore, our aim was to use PET to examine 
possible difference in the brain FFA-uptake rates between 
MS patients and healthy individuals. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Subjects. Twenty-three subjects with MS (age 43 Ϯ 7 years, BMI 33.6 Ϯ 4.0 
kg/m 
2 , 8 men and 15 women) and 7 age-matched healthy men (age 42 Ϯ 11 
years, BMI 26.8 Ϯ 2.5 kg/m 
2 ) (Table 1) were recruited, mostly from an 
occupational healthy service clinic. Healthy patients were nonobese and had 
normal oral glucose tolerance test results, whereas the 23 MS patients had MS 
according to the current International Diabetes Federation criteria (14) (Table 
2). According to the criteria, a person defined as having MS must have central 
obesity, defined as increased waist circumference plus at least two other 
additional criteria (raised triglycerides/blood pressure/fasting glucose or 
reduced HDL). Subjects were told to use no alcohol during the study period. 
Smoking was an exclusion criterion. Only 1 of 23 subjects with MS used 
medication (ACE inhibitor for blood pressure). Written informed consents 
were obtained after explaining the purpose and potential risks of the study to 
the subjects. The study protocol was approved by the Ethics Committee of the 
Hospital District of Southwest Finland and conducted according to the 
principles of the declaration of Helsinki. 
Study design. The study was designed to assess 1) the differences between 
MS patients and healthy individuals at baseline, and 2) the effect of a very low 
caloric diet (VLCD) in MS patients. Two PET studies were performed, first 
with [ 
11 C]-palmitate, and thereafter with [ 
18 F]fluoro-6-thia-heptadecanoic acid 
([ 
18 F]-FTHA), either during the same day or on separate days within 1 week. 
A subgroup of patients with MS (n ϭ 16) were prescribed a VLCD. All daily 
meals were replaced by diet products for 6 weeks (Nutrifast, Leiras, Finland, 
2.3 MJ (megajoule), 4.5 g fat, 59 g protein, and 72 g carbohydrate per day). 
After the diet there was a 1-week recovery period with an isocaloric diet to 
avoid catabolic state. The isocaloric diet was based on estimations of energy 
expenditure and was introduced by a physician. The assessments using PET 
were repeated. Magnetic resonance images were obtained for anatomical 
reference. 
Production and nature of radiotracers. The production of [ 
11 C]-palmitate 
(half-life 20.4 min) (15) and the production of [ 
18 F]-FTHA (half-life 109 min): 
(16) are described elsewhere. The radiochemical purity of the final product </p>

<p>From the 
was Ͼ98% for both tracers. [  18 F]-FTHA ([ 
18 F]fluoro-6-thia-heptadecanoic acid) 
is a long-chain FA analog that has a sulfur-substitution in the sixth carbon and 
a radioactive fluorine-18 label. [  18 F]-FTHA which is taken up by tissues and 
subsequently either enters mitochondria or is incorporated into complex 
lipids (16). In mitochondria, [  18 F]FTHA undergoes initial steps of ␤-oxidation 
and is thereafter trapped as further ␤-oxidation is blocked by its sulfur 
heteroatom (17). Because of these properties, [  18 F]-FTHA provides optimal 
target-to-background signal in PET images. 
In vivo validation of biodistribution of [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>C]-palmitate 
in pig brain. To validate the biodistribution of both [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ 
13 C]-
palmitate in brain, we used data from in vivo pig [ 
18 F]-FTHA biodistribution 
study (18), and completed the study by analyzing the biodistribution of stable 
[ 
13 C]-palmitate from frozen brain samples obtained from the same animals. 
The study protocol and analysis of [  18 F]-FTHA has been described in detail 
elsewhere (18), and the palmitate information is provided in an online 
appendix in an online appendix available at http://diabetes.diabetesjournals. 
org/cgi/content/full/db09-0138/DC1. The results are provided in Table 3. 
Roughly 62% from [ 
13 C]-palmitate and 69% from [ 
18 F]-FTHA was found in brain 
lipids. Most of the [ 
13 C]-palmitate in brain lipids was found in phospholipids, 
and only trace amounts were found in triglycerides and fatty acids. [ 
18 F]-FTHA 
was found mostly in triglycerides. 
PET studies. Patients were scanned in the fasting state, and they refrained 
from drinks containing caffeine, smoking, and all medications for 12 h before 
the PET scan. Studies were performed in a supine position. Two catheters 
were inserted in the antecubital veins of different arms: one for saline infusion 
and tracer injection, and another for blood sampling. [ 
11 C]-palmitate scan was 
performed before [ 
18 F]-FTHA. [ 
18 F]-FTHA scan was started after 7 half-lives of 
[ 
11 C]-palmitate had occurred. The mean doses of injected [ 
11 C]-palmitate and 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA were 312 Ϯ 148 MBq and 182 Ϯ 17 MBq. With [ 
11 C]-palmitate, 
dynamic brain scanning started immediately after injection (frames 8ϫ15s, </p>

<p>2ϫ30s, 2ϫ120s, 1ϫ180s, and 2ϫ300s). Healthy individuals and MS patients not 
subscribed to VLCD were scanned with [ 
18 F]-FTHA immediately after injec-
tion (frames 3ϫ60s, 1ϫ120s, 5ϫ300s, 2ϫ600s). For MS patients subscribed to 
VLCD, [ 
18 F]-FTHA scanning started 70 min after injection and was static (600 
s). During the scans, arterialized venous blood samples were drawn for the 
determination of plasma radioactivity (0, 15, 30, 45, 60, 75, 90, 105 s, and 2, 3, 
4, 5, 10, 15, 20, 30, 40, 50 min for both [ 
11 C]-palmitate and [ 
18 F]-FTHA, and 
additional time points of 60, 70, 80, and 90 min for [ 
18 F]-FTHA). Serum FFAs, 
insulin and glucose concentrations were measured at 0, 10, and 30 min after 
the [ 
11 C]-palmitate injection, and 0, 30, 60, and 90 min after the [ 
18 F]-FTHA 
injection. 
Image acquisition, processing, and corrections. Most studies were per-
formed using GE Discovery PET-CT STE (GE, Medical Systems, Milwaukee, 
WI), but because of the short half-life of [ 
11 C]-palmitate, Siemens ECAT HRϩ 
(Knoxville, TN) and GE Advance (GE Medical Systems, Milwaukee, WI) were 
in use when this tracer was divided. The second study was scanned with same 
camera-protocol as the first study. Data were corrected for dead-time, decay, 
and photon attenuation. PET images were reconstructed in GE Advance using 
a 128 ϫ 128 matrix with a 30-cm field of view (FOV) in three-dimensional (3D) 
mode and Filtered Back Projection (FBP) reconstruction, in Siemens HRϩ 
using 128 ϫ 128 matrix with zoom two (28.8 cm FOV) in 3D mode and FBP 
reconstruction and in PET-CT using 128 ϫ 128 matrix with 35 cm FOV in 3D 
mode and Iterative Ordered Subset Expectation Maximization (OSEM) recon-
struction (VUEPoint). 
Calculation of the parametric fractional uptake rate image. Brain 
fractional uptake indexes for [ 
11 C]-palmitate and [ 
18 F]-FTHA were calculated 
by dividing the brain radioactivity by the integral of the plasma unmetabolized 
radioactivity curve at 15 min. The modeling gives results that are independent 
of the injected tracer dose. The fractional uptake rate (FUR) image from 
dynamic brain scanning was calculated from 10 -20 min. 
Analysis of PET images. The detailed description of regional and voxel level 
PET image analyses and statistical analyses of regional FUR estimates are 
provided in the online appendix. All values are expressed as mean Ϯ SD. 
P values Ͻ 0.05 are considered statistically significant. 
Biochemical analyses. Details of biochemical analyses are provided in the 
online appendix. 
Statistical analysis of biochemical and anthropometric data. Student t 
test was used in baseline to compare results between MS patients and the 
control group. A paired Student t test was used to compare changes in the MS 
group before and after VLCD. Correlations were analyzed using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SAS Enter- prise Guide</rs> 4.1 (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">4.1.0.471</rs>; <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">SAS Institute, Cary, NC</rs>). The normality of variables 
was assessed by the Shapiro-Wilkins test. Variables with normal distribution 
were calculated using Pearson correlation, and non-normal Spearman corre-
lation was used. All values are expressed as mean Ϯ SD. P values Ͻ 0.05 are 
considered statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Metabolic characteristics during the study. Compared 
with the healthy control subjects, patients with MS had 
higher fasting plasma glucose concentrations (Table 1), 
but otherwise no significant differences in oral glucose 
tolerance test (OGTT) results between healthy control 
patients and MS patients were found. After VLCD, subjects 
with MS lost weight ϳ11.1 kg (range 7.2-15.4 kg, P Ͻ 
0.0001), whereas total cholesterol (P Ͻ 0.0001), LDL (P Ͻ </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Baseline anthropometric and metabolic characteristics </p>

<p>Metabolic 
syndrome 
Healthy 
P value </p>

<p>n (female/male) 
23 (15/8) 
7 (0/7) 
Age, years 
43 Ϯ 7 
4 2Ϯ 11 
NS 
Weight, kg 
98.7 Ϯ 12.1 
84.9 Ϯ 8.6 
0.009 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>33.6 Ϯ 4.0 
26.8 Ϯ 2.5 
Ͻ0.0003 
Fasting glucose, mg/dl 
109.8 Ϯ 12.6 
97.2 Ϯ 3.6 
Ͻ0.02 
OGTT glucose, 60 min, 
mg/dl 
156.6 Ϯ 54.0 176.4 Ϯ 12.6 
NS 
OGTT glucose, 120 min, 
mg/dl 
129.6 Ϯ 52.2 100.8 Ϯ 19.8 
NS 
Fasting insulin, mU/l 
6.8 Ϯ 2.6 
3.9 Ϯ 1.6 
0.02 
Total cholesterol, mg/dl 185.6 Ϯ 34.8 170.1 Ϯ 23.2 
NS 
HDL cholesterol, mg/dl 
50.3 Ϯ 11.6 
50.3 Ϯ 7.7 
NS 
Triglycerides, mg/dl 
115.1 Ϯ 53.1 88.6 Ϯ 53.1 
NS 
LDL cholesterol, mg/dl 
112.1 Ϯ 34.8 100.5 Ϯ 23.2 
NS 
HOMA index 
1.8 Ϯ 0.7 
0.9 Ϯ 0.4 
0.02 </p>

<p>Data are mean Ϯ SD unless otherwise indicated. Fasting insulin 
values are from PET-scanning day. Homeostasis model assessment 
(HOMA) index calculated (fasting insulin ϫ fasting glucose)/22.5. P 
values obtained from Student t test. NS, not significant. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Characteristics of MS group according to International Diabetes 
Federation criteria </p>

<p>Metabolic 
syndrome </p>

<p>n (female/male) 
23 (15/8) 
Increased waist circumference (women Ն80 cm, 
men Ն94 cm) 
23 (15/8) 
Raised triglycerides (Ͼ150.6 mg/dl) 
4 (2/2) 
Lowered HDL cholesterol (women Ͻ49.9 mg/dl; 
men Ͻ39.8 mg/dl ) 
7 (5/2) 
Raised systolic blood pressure (Ͼ130 mmHg) 
14 (10/4) 
Raised diastolic blood pressure (Ͼ85 mmHg) 
15 (11/4) 
Raised fasting plasma glucose (Ն100.8 mg/dl) 
18 (12/6) </p>

<p>TABLE 3 
Percentage distribution of brain ͓ 
13 C͔-palmitate and ͓ 
18 F͔-FTHA 
uptake in vivo </p>

<p>Radioactivity 
distribution from 
total lipids ϩ Aq* 
͓ 
13 C͔-palmitate ͓ 
18 F͔-FTHA </p>

<p>Paired 
Student 
t test </p>

<p>Aq* % 
37.7 Ϯ 0.0 † 
30.9 Ϯ 9.7 
NS 
All lipids % 
62.3 Ϯ 0.0 
69.1 Ϯ 9.7 
NS 
Triglycerides % 
0.6 Ϯ 0.2 
53.4 Ϯ 11.3 P ϭ 0.0001 
Fatty acids % 
2.2 Ϯ 0.1 
6.3 Ϯ 3.3 
NS 
Phospholipids % 
59.4 Ϯ 0.3 
9.4 Ϯ 3.2 
P Ͻ 0.0001 </p>

<p>Number of pigs (͓ 
18 F͔-FTHA n ϭ 8, ͓ 
13 C͔-palmitate n ϭ 6). *Hydro-
philic phase.  †The hydrophilic phase of ͓ 
13 C͔-palmitate is estimated 
based on tracer brain distribution curve at 3-h time point, published 
by Miller et al. (11). NS, not significant. </p>

<p>BRAIN FATTY ACID UPTAKE IN METABOLIC SYNDROME </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 59, SEPTEMBER 2010 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>0.0001), and triglycerides (P Ͻ 0.002) also improved (Table 
4). Changes in fasting plasma glucose concentration and in 
fasting insulin after VLCD were significant. The percentage 
decrease in fasting insulin was 37.4%. 
Brain fatty acid tracer accumulation over time. After 
injection, [  18 F]-FTHA radioactivity in the brain increased 
over time (Fig. 1A). As shown previously, plasma [  18 F]-
FTHA and [ 
11 C]-palmitate concentration decreased </p>

<p>quickly after injection (9,19,20). The increase in tissue 
radioactivity over time with [ 
18 F]-FTHA reflects label 
trapping (Fig. 1). As shown in an example of brain image 
after [ 
18 F]-FTHA injection (Fig. 2), radioactivity was high-
est in the thalamus (the two largest gray matter nuclei in 
the center of the transaxial image), followed by high 
uptake in the basal ganglia and throughout the cerebral 
cortex. 
Brain FFA uptake in healthy subjects and patients 
with MS. When brain FFA uptake was measured using 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA and the values of plasma FFA concentration 
during PET, the brain FFA uptake was significantly higher 
in patients with MS compared with healthy subjects (Fig. 
2). The mean percentage increase was ϩ130% in the white 
matter and ϩ47% in the gray matter, and respective 
standardized effect sizes were 1.83 and 0.88. The main 
effect of the group was significant in the repeated mea-
sures ANOVA (rmANOVA) (F ϭ 7.38, P ϭ 0.012), whereas 
no effect from the scanner was observed. In addition, the 
group ϫ region interaction was significant (F ϭ 5.35, P ϭ 
0.016), indicating that the group difference in [ 
18 F]-FTHA 
uptake was not uniform across brain regions. Regional 
ANOVAs indicated significant group differences in all 
regions: white matter (P ϭ 0.001), anterior cingulate (P ϭ 
0.038), parietal (P ϭ 0.015), temporal (P ϭ 0.015) and 
prefrontal cortex (P ϭ 0.020), amygdala-hippocampal 
complex (P ϭ 0.014), striatum (P ϭ 0.019), and hypothal-
amus (P ϭ 0.007). The mean percentage increment in the 
hypothalamic area was ϩ52% among the subjects with MS 
compared with healthy subjects. No scanner effects were 
seen in any region. A marked elevation was also found in 
the brain uptake of [  11 C]-palmitate in patients with MS 
when compared with healthy controls (Fig. 2). The aver-
age increase was ϩ83.8% in the white matter and ϩ87.7% 
in the gray matter. The standardized effect sizes were of 
large magnitude, 1.24 in both the white and gray matter. 
The rmANOVA also demonstrated a significant main effect 
of group (P ϭ 0.017). Because different PET-scanners were 
used in this study, we wanted to test whether the use of 
different PET-scanners would have an impact on the 
findings. The rmANOVA demonstrated no effects of the 
scanner (P ϭ 0.959). The group ϫ region interaction was 
also significant (P ϭ 0.016), suggesting that elevation of 
[ 
11 C]-palmitate uptake in the brain in patients with MS 
might vary across brain regions. In ANOVA models, pre-
dicting regional [  11 C]-palmitate uptake with group status 
and scanner demonstrated significant group differences in 
all brain regions: white matter (P ϭ 0.021), anterior 
cingulate (P ϭ 0.028), parietal (P ϭ 0.011), temporal (P ϭ 
0.013) and prefrontal cortex (P ϭ 0.015), amygdala-hip-
pocampal complex (P ϭ 0.016), striatum (P ϭ 0.029) and 
hypothalamus (P ϭ 0.016). The mean percentage change in 
hypothalamic area was ϩ88% among the subjects with MS 
compared with healthy subjects. The uptake of [ 
18 F]-FTHA 
correlated positively with [ 
11 C]-palmitate in all analyzed 
brain areas, and all the correlations were statistically 
significant. For the hypothalamus, the correlation r value 
was 0.58 (P ϭ 0.003). 
The effect of dieting on brain FFA uptake. There was 
a substantial reduction in the brain uptake of [  18 F]-FTHA 
in patients with MS after VLCD (Fig. 3). The mean percent-
age decrease was Ϫ17.5% in the white matter and Ϫ17.6% 
in the gray matter. In the rmANOVA, the main effect of 
repetition was statistically significant (P ϭ 0.010), whereas 
the repetition ϫ region interaction was not (P ϭ 0.099). 
The latter suggests that the decrease in tracer uptake was </p>

<p>TABLE 4 
Anthropometric and metabolic characteristics after VLCD </p>

<p>Before VLCD After VLCD P value </p>

<p>Weight, kg 
100.4 Ϯ 11.7 
89.4 Ϯ 11.1 Ͻ0.0001 
BMI, kg/m </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>34.0 Ϯ 3.9 
30.2 Ϯ 3.9 
Ͻ0.0001 
Fasting glucose, mg/dl 180.0 Ϯ 10.8 
102.6 Ϯ 9.0 
0.02 
OGTT glucose, 60 
min, mg/dl 
138.6 Ϯ 39.6 117.0 Ϯ 36.0 
NS 
OGTT glucose, 120 
min, mg/dl 
111.6 Ϯ 27.0 104.4 Ϯ 23.4 
NS 
Fasting insulin, mU/l 
6.8 Ϯ 2.6 
4.6 Ϯ 2.2 
Ͻ0.0001 
Total cholesterol, 
mg/dl 
189.5 Ϯ 30.9 143.1 Ϯ 23.2 Ͻ0.0001 
HDL cholesterol, 
mg/dl 
50.3 Ϯ 11.6 
50.3 Ϯ 7.7 
NS 
Triglycerides, mg/dl 
106.3 Ϯ 44.3 
79.7 Ϯ 26.6 
Ͻ0.002 
LDL cholesterol, 
mg/dl 
116.0 Ϯ 30.9 
81.2 Ϯ 19.3 Ͻ0.0001 
HOMA index † 
1.8 Ϯ 0.7 
1.2 Ϯ 0.7 
Ͻ0.0002 
Free fatty acids, 
mmol/l 
0.61 Ϯ 0.17 
0.56 Ϯ 0.14 
NS </p>

<p>Data are mean Ϯ SD. Number of subjects ϭ 16 (11 females and 5 
males).  †HOMA index calculated (fasting insulin ϫ fasting glucose)/ 
22.5; fasting insulin values are from PET-scanning day. P values 
obtained from paired Student t test. NS, not significant; VLCD, very 
low calorie diet. </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 </p>

<p>Brain activity curve 
[ 18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA </p>

<p>Time (minutes) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.2 </p>

<p>1.4 </p>

<p>1.6 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 </p>

<p>Brain activity curve 
[ 11 </p>

<p>C]-palmitate </p>

<p>Time (minutes) </p>

<p>Healthy 
Metabolic Syndrome </p>

<p>FIG. 1. An example of a time course of brain tissue radioactivity after 
intravenous injection of [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ 
11 C]-palmitate from one 
nonobese healthy subject and one obese subject with MS. The values 
are given as standardized uptake values (SUVs), and values are nor-
malized to the dosage (MBq), and body weight (kg). The resulting SUV 
value has been multiplied with individual blood FFA level. The increase 
in brain radioactivity over time with [ 
18 F]-FTHA reflects tracer trap-
ping. Black circles, healthy; white circles, MS. </p>

<p>A. KARMI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 59, SEPTEMBER 2010 </p>

<p>
uniform across brain regions. Therefore, to avoid type 1 
errors, regional changes were not formally assessed. This 
result was confirmed using a voxel-based mapping analy-
sis (Fig. 3). The change in [ 
11 C]-palmitate uptake was 
highly variable between individuals, with the average 
across regions ranging from Ϫ37% to ϩ210% and the 
average across individuals being ϩ32% (SD 74%). The 
rmANOVA did not show any significant change in [  11 C]-
palmitate uptake after VLCD (Fig. 3, main effect of repe-
tition: P ϭ 0.712, repetition ϫ region interaction: P ϭ 
0.676). The change in [  18 F]-FTHA uptake versus change in 
[ 
11 C]-palmitate correlated positively in all brain areas, and 
all of the correlations were statistically significant. For the 
hypothalamus, the correlation r value was 0.56 (P Ͻ 0.05). 
Fatty acid uptake and metabolic characteristics. 
Brain fatty acid uptake measured with [ 
18 F]-FTHA-PET 
was positively associated with age (P ϭ 0.007, r ϭ 0.52), 
fasting serum insulin (P Ͻ 0.05, r ϭ 0.40) and homeostasis 
model assessment (HOMA) index (P ϭ 0.04, r ϭ 0.41) (Fig. 
4). The correlation between [  18 F]-FTHA and age persisted 
after the data were adjusted for BMI (P Ͻ 0.03, r ϭ 0.46). 
Both total and nonoxidized fraction of fatty acid uptake 
were positively associated with the BMI (total: P ϭ 0.002, 
nonoxidized: P ϭ 0.004). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>To our knowledge, this is the first study to investigate 
brain FFA uptake in obese patients with MS. The main 
finding of the study is that patients with MS have higher 
FFA uptake in the brain compared with healthy subjects. 
Weight loss reduced FFA uptake more in healthy subjects, </p>

<p>and this was more due to decreased FFA oxidation rather 
than decreased metabolic FFA utilization. 
We and others have previously used [ 
18 F]-FTHA and 
PET to quantify regional FFA metabolism, especially in 
myocardium and skeletal muscle (18,20,21). Recently we 
showed that [ 
18 F]-FTHA accumulates in the brain in sig-
nificant amounts (18), thus making it a reliable tracer to 
quantify brain FFA uptake. The brain tissue-input ratio for 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA ratio was high, suggesting that [ 
18 F]-FTHA 
crosses the blood-brain barrier and accumulates persis-
tently and in measurable amounts. More than half of the 
tracer was going into the lipids, and less than half into the 
breakdown products (18). These breakdown products 
likely represent oxidation, so the study results suggest that 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA reflects total uptake. [  11 C]-palmitate has been 
shown to accumulate in monkey brain (9) and the ex-
tracted fraction is independent of cerebral flow (22). 
Palmitate accumulation in the brain has also been verified 
in rats (11,23-25), and the flux is proportional to published 
values for regional brain oxidative metabolism (23). Long-
chain saturated fatty acids such as [ 
11 C]-palmitate enter, to 
a large extent (50 -60%), via ␤-oxidation in mitochondria, 
creating radioactive, aqueous metabolites, particularly glu-
tamate, glutamine, and aspartate, whereas the other half is 
incorporated into lipids (22,26,27). After the fast oxidation 
of [  11 C]-palmitate, the remaining radioactivity thus enters 
the stable lipid pool of the brain representing nonoxidative 
residual. It has been suggested that 83% of brain radioac-
tivity is in stable compartments within 2 min after a 
steady-state level of plasma palmitate is achieved (9). 
Plasma [ 
11 C]-palmitate activity in our study was stable </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>White Matter 
Gray Matter </p>

<p>Healthy 
Metabolic Syndrome </p>

<p>+84% 
+88% </p>

<p>* 
* </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.50 </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.70 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>0.90 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>White Matter 
Gray Matter </p>

<p>Brain [ 18 
F]-FTHA uptake 
(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>Brain [ 11 
C]-Palmitate uptake </p>

<p>(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>+130% 
+47% </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0.010 </p>

<p>0.002 </p>

<p>0.005 </p>

<p>0.001 </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Left: Baseline brain white and gray matter uptake rates of [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA (A) and [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]-palmitate (B). P values were calculated using Student 
t test. *P value of 0.01; **P value of 0.0006. NS, not significant. White bars, healthy; black bars, MS. Right: Transaxial, coronal, and sagittal 
sections of group-wise [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA-PET and [ 
11 C]-palmitate-PET images of the brain in healthy controls (A and C) and MS patients (B and D). A: 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA-PET healthy control. B: [ 
18 F]-FTHA PET MS. C: [ 
11 C]-palmitate-PET healthy control. D: [ 
11 C]-palmitate-PET MS. Images represent 
average spatially normalized uptake images, and the scale is mmol/(100g ؋ min). In the PET images, the highest activity is shown in red as an 
index of tracer accumulation. The difference between [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ 
11 C]-palmitate is that [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA is metabolically trapped whereas 
[ 
11 C]-palmitate is not. Higher activity of [ 
18 F]-FTHA reflects the accumulation of the tracer in the brain tissue. (A high-quality digital 
representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>BRAIN FATTY ACID UPTAKE IN METABOLIC SYNDROME </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 59, SEPTEMBER 2010 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>shortly after 5 min in each person. Because the analysis 
was done using time frames of 10 -20 min, the palmitate 
results from brain can be considered to represent incor-
poration to stable compartments, and thus the so-called 
nonoxidative residual. We speculate that by combining the 
information from [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ 
11 C]-palmitate, it may 
be possible to estimate the brain FFA oxidative compo-
nent as the difference between total and nonoxidative fatty 
acid uptake ([ 
18 F]-FTHA minus [ 
11 C]-palmitate). From our 
in vivo validation study, we found that both [ 
13 C]-palmitate 
and [ 
18 F]-FTHA are incorporated into the brain in measur-
able amounts. The percentage found in the brain hydro-
philic and lipid pool did not differ between tracers, 
whereas a difference was seen in distribution within the 
lipid pool. From both tracers, we found that more than 60% 
were found in the lipid pool; [ 
18 F]-FTHA was mainly in 
triglycerides, whereas [  13 C]-palmitate was mainly recov-</p>

<p>ered from phospholipids. The conversion of [ 
18 F]-FTHA to 
phospholipids might be different because of steric or 
charge hindrance. However, the in vivo validation was to 
show that both tracers are stored in the brain in similar 
amounts. The distribution of tracers within lipid pool itself 
is not addressed since PET cannot distinguish between 
these storage forms. 
The brain uptake of [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ 
11 C]-palmitate was 
increased in patients with MS compared with healthy 
individuals. The difference with [  18 F]-FTHA was not uni-
formly increased in all brain areas. The total FFA uptake 
was significantly greater in the white matter among sub-
jects with MS compared with healthy controls, and the 
increment appeared to be of larger magnitude than that in 
the gray matter. The increase in white matter [  18 F]-FTHA 
uptake could contribute to previous findings of brain white 
matter expansion among obese subjects (28). The differ-</p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>0.60 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.20 </p>

<p>White Matter 
Gray Matter </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>-17.5% 
-17.6% </p>

<p>0.00 </p>

<p>0.05 </p>

<p>0.10 </p>

<p>0.15 </p>

<p>0.20 </p>

<p>0.25 </p>

<p>0.30 </p>

<p>0.35 </p>

<p>0.40 </p>

<p>White Matter 
Gray Matter </p>

<p>Before 
After </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>NS </p>

<p>Brain [ 18 
F]-FTHA uptake 
(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>Brain [ 11 
C]-Palmitate uptake </p>

<p>(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Left: Graphs show the results of brain white and gray matter uptake of [ 
18 F]-FTHA and [ </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>C]-palmitate in the MS group before and after 
VLCD. P values were calculated using paired Student t test. *P value &lt; 0.02; **P value of 0.009; NS, not significant; black bars, before VLCD; white 
bars, after VLCD. Right: Results from the voxel-based mapping analysis. Results are rendered on an anatomical brain model; red areas illustrate 
brain regions where [ 
18 F]-FTHA uptake was significantly reduced after dieting among MS patients (T max ‫؍‬ 4.21 at (؊66, ؊22, 48), kE ‫؍‬ 161,315, 
cluster-level corrected P &lt; 0.0005). (A high-quality digital representation of this figure is available in the online issue.) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
50 
55 
60 
65 </p>

<p>Age, years </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>3.0 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 </p>

<p>Insulin mU/L </p>

<p>Brain [ 18 
F]-FTHA uptake 
(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>Brain [ 18 
F]-FTHA uptake 
(µmol/100g x </p>

<p>min) </p>

<p>FIG. 4. The brain uptake of [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA representing total brain FFA uptake positively correlated with fasting insulin (P &lt; 0.05; r ‫؍‬ 0.40) and 
age (P ‫؍‬ 0.007; r ‫؍‬ 0.52). Fasting insulin values are taken from OGTT. </p>

<p>A. KARMI AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org 
DIABETES, VOL. 59, SEPTEMBER 2010 </p>

<p>
ence with [ 
11 C]-palmitate between groups was more uni-
form and thus statistically significant in all analyzed areas. 
The hypothalamic area, now associated with fatty acid 
sensing and regulation of energy balance and feeding (2,4), 
had also increased uptake of both [ 
11 C]-palmitate and 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA. Weight loss reduced the [ 
18 F]-FTHA uptake 
uniformly in all brain regions, including the hypothalamus. 
It is hypothesized that reduced [ 
18 F]-FTHA uptake simul-
taneously with no change in [ 
11 C]-palmitate uptake might 
reflect reduction in brain FFA oxidative component. This 
result is in line with a recent rodent study in which 
inhibition of hypothalamic ␤-oxidation normalized the 
energy homeostasis of the animals (5). Thus, the changes 
in the oxidative component seem to be related more to 
weight control and satiety, supporting our finding that 
oxidative metabolism is different in the obese MS group 
and could be partially reversed by weight loss. There was 
no statistically significant difference in nonoxidative stor-
age component after weight loss, but the change in [ 
11 C]-
palmitate uptake was highly variable between individuals. 
The reason why a decrease was seen in [ 
18 F]-FTHA uptake 
but not in [ 
11 C]-palmitate could be that oxidative metabo-
lism might be more flexible in nature, whereas the synthe-
sis of complex lipids may be more preserved due to its 
important structural role in the brain. In addition, these 
studies were conducted under fasting conditions, which 
are characterized by activation of FFA oxidative metabo-
lism. This may also help explain why intervention-related 
differences in this process are more easily identified than 
those in storage. The dieting period did not affect fasting 
plasma FFA levels, thus multiplying image data with 
individual FFA level does not contribute to the observed 
decrease in FFA uptake. 
Our findings are consistent with recent studies implicat-
ing the role of hypothalamic fatty acid sensing and their 
role in the regulation of feeding, energy balance (2,4,5), 
and peripheral physiologic processes (29). The normaliza-
tion of hypothalamic lipid sensing has been linked to 
normalization of energy and glucose homeostasis (5). 
From our study results, it seems that the normal catabolic 
effect of central FFAs is disturbed in obesity, and this is at 
least partially reversible after weight loss. Peripheral insu-
lin resistance contributing to MS could also affect the 
brain. In healthy pigs, hyperinsulinemia induced ϳ20 -50% 
decrease in brain [ </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>F]-FTHA radioactivity compared with 
fasting state (18). The hypothesized central insulin resis-
tance could interfere with brain glucose utilization, thus 
resulting in compensatory increased FFA uptake and FFA 
oxidation. Weight loss is known to improve insulin sensi-
tivity and plasma lipid profile (30). The beneficial effect of 
weight loss was observed in our study among MS patients; 
in addition to beneficial peripheral effects, FFA uptake in 
the brain was uniformly decreased due to a decrease in 
FFA oxidation. The correlations from our study corrobo-
rate this line of interference: FFA uptake was positively 
correlated with BMI, plasma insulin, and HOMA-index; 
among these, BMI had the strongest correlation. Brain 
FFA uptake also increased with ageing, suggesting that 
ageing is related to degenerative changes in the metabolic 
processes, and reinforcing the theory that age is a risk 
factor for MS. 
Given that the activation of hypothalamic nuclei can 
result in changes in sympathetic tone, and that hypothal-
amus is a key regulator in feeding and energy balance, it is 
interesting to hypothesize that central FFAs could contrib-
ute to increased sympathetic tone in obesity. Previous </p>

<p>studies support both positive and negative effects of 
central lipids in sympathetic tone. It has been reported 
that central lipid infusion resulting in increased brain 
lipids might modulate sympathoadrenal response (31), and 
that intracerebrovascular infusion of fatty acids might 
lower sympathetic activity. Unfortunately, we did not have 
any direct measurements to address this question. 
Limitations in this study were the small number of 
subjects in the healthy control group and the fact that all 
of the healthy subjects were males. If sex is used in the 
statistical model as a covariate, the group difference in 
[ 
18 F]-FTHA uptake persists in the white matter (group ϫ 
region: F ϭ 6.72, P ϭ 0.007; main effect of group in the 
white matter: F ϭ 4.92, P ϭ 0.037), but not in other brain 
regions, and no significant effects are seen with [  18 F]-
palmitate. In addition, female patients with MS had higher 
uptake values for both radioligands than male patients 
with MS. Future studies including healthy females should 
establish whether a significant interaction exists between 
sex and disease status, such that female patients may be 
more severely affected than male patients, as current data 
suggest. However, we think that a simple confounding 
main effect of sex is unlikely to explain the current results, 
based on three facts. First, [  18 F]-FTHA uptake is increased 
in MS in white matter even when sex is taken into account. 
Second, significant correlations were seen between fatty 
acid uptake and clinical variables, such as BMI and fasting 
plasma glucose, suggesting that increased fatty acid up-
take is more likely related to metabolic abnormalities than 
sex alone. Third, the significant decrease in fatty acid 
uptake after weight loss argues against a main effect of sex 
because such main effect would not be reversible. Never-
theless, we acknowledge the skewed sex distribution as a 
limitation to the interpretation of the results, and recom-
mend that sex be taken into account in future studies. The 
number of subjects having MS differs in cross-section 
versus VLCD intervention. The first phase of the study was 
only cross-sectional. After having positive results from 
phase 1, we wanted to study in more detail the possibility 
that brain FFA uptake is related to weight. The more 
comprehensive phase two (VLCD intervention) was intro-
duced in the study protocol and the last 16 of 23 subjects 
took part in this phase. Another limiting factor is that the 
brain kinetics of [  18 F]-FTHA is not known so well as in 
other organs and was assumed to be taken up as natural 
palmitate. Although the in vivo biodistribution of [  18 F]-
FTHA in the brain suggests that [  18 F]-FTHA represents 
total uptake, it does not prove that it equals uptake of 
natural FFAs. In our study, the total oxidation of [ 
11 C]-
palmitate was found to be less than 50%. In the animal 
studies, it has been found that approximately 60% of the 
[ 
11 C]-palmitate enters to ␤-oxidation (9). It is possible that 
the kinetic properties of [ 
18 F]-FTHA differ slightly from 
our assumption, explaining the slight difference between 
our study and animal studies. Nevertheless, this would not 
affect the differences found between the two groups. The 
dosages of injected tracers did not explain the findings, 
even when weight was taken into account. In addition, the 
isocaloric diet was not controlled, but the subjects were 
free to eat what they wanted. So the quality and quantity of 
the foods probably differ between subjects. 
To conclude, we have found that patients fulfilling the 
International Diabetes Federation criteria of metabolic 
syndrome have increased brain FFA uptake when com-
pared with healthy subjects. Weight loss is able to partly 
reverse this abnormality. These novel findings highlight </p>

<p>BRAIN FATTY ACID UPTAKE IN METABOLIC SYNDROME </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 59, SEPTEMBER 2010 
diabetes.diabetesjournals.org </p>

<p>the possible role of brain FFAs in regulation of body 
weight. It seems that the normal catabolic effect of central 
FFAs is disturbed in MS and this is partially reversed after 
weight loss. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>The study was conducted in the Finnish Centre of Excel-
lence in Molecular Imaging in Cardiovascular and Meta-
bolic Research, supported by the Academy of Finland, 
University of Turku, Turku University Hospital, and Åbo 
Academy University. Support was also received by grants 
from the HEPADIP EU FP6 program, the Novo Nordisk 
Foundation, and the Hertta and Veikko Valtonen 
Foundation. 
No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this 
article were reported. 
A.K. wrote the manuscript, researched data, contributed 
to discussion, and reviewed/edited the manuscript. P.I. 
and P.N. contributed to discussion and reviewed/edited 
the manuscript. A.V., K.V., V.O. J.K., T.V., L.G., and M.H.-S. 
researched data. J.H. researched data, wrote the manu-
script, and reviewed/edited the manuscript. B.A.F. re-
searched data and contributed to discussion. K.N. 
reviewed the manuscript. O.S. researched data and re-
viewed the manuscript. </p>

<p> </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>