<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2978351" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-04T06:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A simple and efficient approach that scans across a 
defined gene region and systematically produces all </p>

<p>possible single-codon mutations within that region 
would be highly desirable for many applications. 
Random mutagenesis, coupled with genetic screening or 
selection strategies to identify desired phenotypes, is often 
used to isolate proteins with modified activities or to 
identify critical residues in proteins (1-3). Protein-coding 
DNA regions are typically mutagenized in vitro using 
codon cassette mutagenesis, site-directed mutagenesis, 
chemical modification of nucleotides, or error-prone 
PCR conditions (4-7). Error-prone PCR-based strategies 
are biased towards certain nucleotides or nucleotide com-
binations, rarely produce two or three base changes in a 
single codon, typically do not achieve saturation, may 
introduce multiple amino acid changes per product, and 
cannot be controlled in detail. Codon cassette mutagenesis 
requires specific sequence conditions and targets a single 
codon at a time, thus requiring considerable effort if sat-
uration of extended gene regions is desired (5,8). More 
directed approaches, such as site-directed mutagenesis or 
its extensions to alanine scanning (9) and iterative satur-
ation mutagenesis (10), sample only selected residues and 
are labor-intensive for saturation mutagenesis of large 
gene regions or whole genes. The All-Codon Scanning 
(ACS) strategy presented here overcomes many of the 
above restrictions. ACS allows the systematic change of 
each codon in a defined gene region into all other codons, 
while yielding only a single changed codon per mutagen-
esis product. 
ACS mutagenesis of small and large regions of the 
human tumor suppressor gene p53 was used here to 
identify amino acid changes that can restore activity of 
p53 mutants found in human cancer. The p53 gene 
encodes a tumor suppressor protein that is a key cellular 
defense against cancer (11). p53 mutations occur in $50% 
of human cancers, and about three-quarters of those </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 949 824 9442; Fax: +1 949 824 2688; Email: pkaiser@uci.edu 
Correspondence may also be addressed to Richard H. Lathrop. Tel: +1 949 824 4021; Fax: +1 949 824 4056; Email: rickl@uci.edu 
Present address: 
Kirsty Salmon, Verdezyne, Inc., Carlsbad, CA 92010, USA </p>

<p>Published online 25 June 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 20 7079-7088 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq571 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>mutations are single-point missense mutations in the p53 
core domain (12,13). Restoring p53 activity in human 
tumors is therefore theoretically possible. Indeed, 
reactivated p53 holds great therapeutic promise because 
animal models have shown that reintroduction of active 
p53, even in advanced tumors, leads to tumor regression 
(14-16). As demonstrated in vivo, p53 cancer mutants can 
be reactivated through intragenic second-site suppressor 
mutations (17-19). These so-called 'cancer rescue' muta-
tions suggest that drugs mimicking suppressor mutations 
might be designed (20). Therefore, studies on cancer 
rescue mutations aim to identify regions in p53 where per-
turbations may cause p53 reactivation. Cancer rescue mu-
tations may also influence protein-protein interactions or 
protein stability without necessarily inducing major struc-
tural disruptions. Thus, identification of many or all p53 
cancer rescue mutations could provide a better structure-
function understanding of the phenomenon of p53 reacti-
vation and support future drug development efforts. 
As described below, the ACS strategy can be combined 
with synthetic DNA technologies to optimize hybridiza-
tion fidelity. Several computational approaches exist that 
allow the design of synthetic DNA molecules and encom-
pass a number of DNA sequence-determined properties 
without changing the encoded protein sequence (21-25). 
This is of course possible because of the degeneracy of the 
genetic code, and allows simultaneous optimization for 
several arbitrarily specified sequence properties, such as 
its own self-assembly, codon usage (26), GC/AT ratio 
(27,28), translational kinetics (29), codon-pair bias 
(30-32) and other DNA structural scales (33). 
Particularly useful for the ACS strategy is the 
Computational Optimized DNA Assembly (CODA) 
system (34), which exploits the degeneracy of the genetic 
code to perform multiple sequence optimizations, 
including removal of deleterious RNA cross-
hybridizations and secondary structures. The resulting 
global thermodynamic optimization of the DNA 
sequence implies that every location in the gene is 
assigned a globally unique thermodynamic address. 
However, any modern gene design software that 
removes RNA cross-hybridizations and secondary struc-
ture may be used instead of CODA. 
The ACS strategy described here is a quick and simple 
method that overcomes several shortcomings of current 
scanning mutagenesis approaches. ACS creates a 
sequence defined gene library with (i) each individual 
codon in a specific target region changed to all other 
possible codons, and (ii) only a single codon change per 
mutagenesis product. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Materials </p>

<p>Oligonucleotides were purchased from Integrated DNA 
Technologies (Coralville, IA, USA). PfuUltra II ultra 
DNA Polymerase was purchased from Strategene 
(La Jolla, CA, USA). Restriction enzymes and T4 DNA 
ligase were obtained from New England Biolabs (Ipswich, 
MA, USA). </p>

<p>ACS mutagenesis </p>

<p>A pool of 10 forward and 10 reverse oligonucleotides, 
each with a single randomized NNN codon at its center 
was used in each mutagenesis reaction. NNN yields all 
possible codons and so reduces the possibility of codon-
level effects that might interfere with translation or expres-
sion (e.g. rare codons or bad codon pairs), while the stop 
codons are inactive in our genetic selection and so were 
not seen. The ACS method can be modified easily to use 
NNK or NNS (or any desired triplets) for use where there 
was less concern about codon-level effects or stop codons 
would be deleterious. Similarly, in applications where 
DNA synthesis bias would be a concern, custom prepar-
ation of oligonucleotides with balanced base ratios is 
available 
(http://www.idtdna.com/catalog/analytical/ 
Page1.aspx). 
The constant flanking regions surrounding each NNN 
codon matched the target incorporation site and were 
extended at least four bases past any other NNN codon. 
Consequently, incorporation of any mutagenesis oligo-
nucleotide into a product must mask any previously 
incorporated NNN, and so only one NNN codon is 
possible in any product. Mutagenesis oligonucleotide ex-
tension can potentially lead to a bias towards products 
that are generated from oligonucleotides with higher an-
nealing temperatures. To overcome this problem we used 
the Stratagene online mutagenesis oligonucleotide 
designer (http://www.stratagene.com/sdmdesigner/default 
.aspx) to obtain roughly equal annealing temperatures 
greater than 68 
C. 
The 50 ml PCR reaction was carried out with 50 ng tem-
plates, 6 mM total primer concentration (300 nM of each 
forward and reverse primer), 400 mM dNTPs and 5 U of 
Pfu Ultra II polymerase. The reaction was initiated at 
94 
C for 10 min, followed by 18 cycles (30 s at 94 
C, 40 s 
at 55 
C and 200 s at 72 
C), and concluded by incubation 
at 72 
C for 15 min. The amplification products were 
digested with Dpn1 to remove the methylated template 
plasmids. At this point, a plasmid library containing com-
pletely saturated target regions of a gene of interest can be 
generated by transformation into Escherichia coli. 
Alternatively, the mutagenized products can be amplified 
by PCR and introduced into target vectors by homolo-
gous recombination or used in many other standard 
applications. </p>

<p>Yeast assays to identify and evaluate intragenic 
suppressor mutations </p>

<p>A region containing the p53 core domain (amino acids 
50-334) was re-amplified from the mutagenesis mix. The 
PCR products were purified (QIAquick 
TM PCR purifica-
tion kit, Qiagen, Germany) and used to generate 
p53-expression plasmids in yeast using the gap-repair 
strategy (35). To identify mutations that reactivate p53 
cancer mutants we used a p53-tester yeast strain. 
Growth of this yeast strain in medium lacking uracil 
depends on active p53 because the URA3 gene is engin-
eered to be under transcriptional control of p53 (18,36). 
The plasmid pTW300, which is a centromeric plasmid 
expressing human p53 under control of the ADH1 </p>



<p>promoter (36), was gapped with AgeI/StuI. These restric-
tion sites are positioned so that the ACS final PCR 
products overlapped with both ends of the gapped 
plasmids by at least 60 nt at both sites. Taking advantage 
of the highly efficient homologous recombination 
in Saccharomyces cerevisiae, 500 ng of the PCR products 
and 500 ng of the gapped plasmid were co-transformed 
into yeast strain RB379. The p53-tester yeast strain 
RB379 was engineered so that expression of the URA3 
gene is dependent on active p53 (18). Cells were directly 
plated onto SC plates lacking uracil and incubated at 
37 
C, thus selecting for repaired, functional plasmids 
and a possibly functional p53 molecule. These plasmids 
were directly sequenced from yeast cells, after colony-
PCR amplification (Genewiz, San Diego, CA, USA). </p>

<p>CODA optimization and assembly of the full length 
p53 gene </p>

<p>The p53 gene sequence was CODA-optimized to encode 
its own correct self-assembly as described (34). 
Computations were performed on a 64-node cluster 
of 3 GHz Xeon dual processors. Computer code is avail-
able upon request. The p53 sequence was also designed 
for optimal expression in S. cerevisiae using synonymous 
codon substitutions. Codon usage for yeast was estimated 
using the codon adaptation index (37) and codon 
pair statistics (30-32,38). The CODA output is a list 
of DNA oligonucleotide sequences and a set of instruc-
tions for combining the purchased oligonucleotides 
by polymerase extension and PCR into the full length 
synthetic gene. 
For each overlapping intermediate DNA fragment, the 
constituent oligonucleotide set was mixed to final concen-
trations of 0.1 mM with an excess (1 mM) of the 5 
0 and 
3 
0 primer oligonucleotide. Each oligonucleotide set was 
extended to an intermediate DNA fragment by a PCR 
reaction using 2.5 U of PfuUltra II ultra DNA polymerase 
(Stratagene), 200 mM dNTPs (Roche Diagnostics, 
Indianapolis, IN) and 1X PfuUltra reaction buffer. 
These reactions were performed in a MJ Research 
PTC-225 thermal cycler using the following calculated-
control protocol: 10 min denaturation step at 95 
C, 
followed by 35 cycles of 30 s at 95 
C, 30 s at 68 
C 
and 20 s at 72 
C, and a final step of 5 min at 72 
C. 
The PCR products were subjected to electrophoresis in a 
1% agarose gel, PCR purified (Quiaquick PCR clean up, 
Quiagen, Valencia, CA, USA), and quantified by 
NanoDrop (Thermo Scientific, Wilmington, DE, USA). 
Each overlapping intermediate DNA fragment was 
mixed to a final concentration of 0.1 mM along with 
1 mM NdeI/BamHI cloning oligonucleotides, 2.5 U of 
PfuUltra II ultra DNA polymerase (Stratagene), 200 mM 
dNTPs (Roche Diagnostics, Indianapolis, IN), and 
1Â PfuUltra reaction buffer. These primer extension and 
PCR amplification reactions were performed in a MJ 
Research PTC-225 thermal cycler as above, but with 45 s 
extension at 72 
C. The full-length p53 gene was separated 
in a 1% agarose gel, PCR purified, and cloned into a 
pCODA vector. The sequence was confirmed by DNA 
sequencing. </p>

<p>Cell culture and p53 evaluation methods </p>

<p>H1299 and Saos-2 cell lines (p53 negative) were grown 
in high-glucose DMEM with 10% fetal bovine serum. 
All transfections were done with Lipofectamine 
2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) according to the 
manufacturer's protocol. All experiments were done in 
triplicate. p53-dependent reporter activity values were 
normalized to Renilla luciferase activity by co-transfection 
with expression plasmids carrying the Firefly luciferase 
gene under the control of the p21 promoter and a CMV 
promoter driven p53 (36). Cells were harvested 48 h after 
transfection and analyzed for luciferase activity with the 
Dual-Glo Luciferase Assay System (Promega, Madison, 
WI, USA) according to the manufacturer's protocol. 
Light emission was detected with the Monolight 
2010 luminometer (Analytical Luminescence Laboratory, 
San Diego, CA, USA). </p>

<p>Three dimensional visualization of p53 mutants </p>

<p>The location of cancer mutants and cancer rescue mutants 
in the p53 3D structure was visualized using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Visual 
Molecular Dynamics</rs> (VMD) (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://www.ks.uiuc.edu/Research/vmd/</rs>/). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Self-assembly of CODA-optimized human p53 </p>

<p>A CODA-optimized human p53 core domain DNA 
sequence was optimized to code for the same amino acid 
sequence as the native gene, to be easily self-assembled 
from synthetic oligonucleotides by polymerase extension, 
respect hypothesized codon usage and codon pair prefer-
ences (30-32) in yeast, and especially to avoid RNA sec-
ondary structure and off-target cross-hybridization, which 
is known to be a source of mutagenesis failure (33). 
Nucleotide changes required to achieve these properties 
(Figure 1A) were computed by the CODA algorithm as 
described (34). 
Briefly, the p53 gene was divided into six overlapping 
intermediate DNA fragments, each of which was 
subdivided into 10 short overlapping and abutting oligo-
nucleotides. There exists a temperature gap within which, 
with high thermodynamic probability, correct hybridiza-
tions are annealed and incorrect hybridizations are 
melted. The melting temperature distributions of the 
CODA-designed p53 sequence show a melting tempera-
ture gap of 20 
C (Figure 1B), which essentially results in 
a globally unique thermodynamic address for each 
location in the target gene and thereby minimizes muta-
genesis difficulties due to miss-priming and cross-
hybridization. Self-assembled overlapping intermediate 
DNA fragments were obtained by primer extension and 
PCR amplification. The overlapping intermediate DNA 
fragments were combined in another PCR amplification 
reaction to generate a single product, sequence verified, 
full-length p53 core domain (Figure 1C). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 20 7081 </p>

<p>ACS mutagenesis </p>

<p>ACS is a single-tube PCR-based mutagenesis strategy 
that creates all 64 possible codons at each single position 
in a 30 bp wide target region of a gene of interest. 
Individual reactions were restricted to 30-bp sections 
to restrict oligonucleotide length and so avoid unwanted </p>

<p>mutations due to oligonucleotide synthesis errors. 
The novel arrangement and site-specific hybridization 
of multiplexed overlapping oligonucleotides, described 
below, results in only a single codon change per gene 
product. Thus, library complexity remains practical for 
down-stream applications (Figure 2). </p>

<p>Figure 1. Self-assembly of CODA-designed human p53. (A) Alignment of the natural human p53 and CODA-optimized synthetic p53 core domain 
sequences. The boxed nucleotides indicate changes in the nucleotide sequence. Note that the amino acid sequence is unchanged. (B) Comparison of 
melting temperature (Tm) profiles of correct and incorrect hybridizations between the native human p53 DNA sequence (x axis) and the 
CODA-optimized p53 DNA sequence (y axis). Each point corresponds to the assembly Tm for the native (x axis) and CODA-optimized (y axis) 
DNA sequences for the same construction oligonucleotide or intermediate DNA fragment, as calculated using the method of Larsen et al. (34). 
Points above the dashed lines correspond to T m s of correct hybridizations and points below correspond to T m s of incorrect hybridizations. The 
correct and incorrect hybridization T m s overlap in the native sequence but are well separated in the CODA-optimized sequence, which implies that 
every annealing location in the CODA-optimized sequence has a globally unique thermodynamic address that is well separated from every other 
annealing location. (C) p53 self-assembly. Overlapping oligonucleotides were used to self-assemble fragments one to six and extended by a PCR to 
generate intermediate DNA fragments (lanes 1-6). The six intermediate DNA fragments were mixed together and extended by overlap extension and 
PCR amplification to generate the synthetic p53 core domain (lane 7). </p>



<p>First, we verified by sequencing more than 500 
randomly chosen individual mutagenesis products that, 
at a given amino acid position, all 64 possible codon in-
sertions were observed, and all 20 amino acids were rep-
resented at approximately their expected frequencies 
(correlation coefficient r = 0.79) (Figure 3). We observed 
a very high mutagenesis efficiency (&gt;95%), which we at-
tribute to the unique thermodynamic profile of the syn-
thetic gene design. The melting temperature distributions 
of the CODA-designed p53 sequence show a melting tem-
perature gap of 20 
C (Figure 1B). Thus, correct annealing 
of any given oligonucleotide was strongly favored over 
hybridization at an incorrect position. Even with a 3-nt 
mismatch mutagenesis oligonucleotide, the temperature 
gap between correct hybridizations and incorrect hybrid-
izations remained at a very selective 15 
C. This 
high thermal gap avoids annealing to incorrect gene loca-
tions and solves one of the main obstacles to effi-
ciently produce sequence-defined multiplexed DNA 
libraries (33). </p>

<p>Next, we chose the region encoding amino acids 232-
241 of p53 to test the efficiency of ACS mutagenesis in 
identification of rescue mutations for the p53 
R158L cancer 
mutant. Amino acid region 232-241 in mutant p53 </p>

<p>R158L </p>

<p>was specifically selected because it had been extensively 
explored previously by error-prone PCR and was 
identified as a 'global suppressor motif' due to the accu-
mulation of cancer rescue mutations (36). The region con-
taining the p53 core domain was re-amplified from the 
mutagenesis mix. The PCR products were purified and 
used to generate p53-expression plasmids in yeast using 
the gap-repair strategy (Figure 2). As described in detail 
in the 'Materials and Methods' section, a p53-tester yeast 
strain with p53-controlled expression of the selectable 
URA3 gene was used for these experiments to identify 
mutations that restore p53 activity (36). 
For each ACS reaction we obtained at least 200 000 
transformants, ensuring full coverage of all generated 
mutants. Specifically, considering mutations at 10 
possible codon locations, each of which can have any </p>

<p>Figure 2. Schematic representation of the ACS strategy and the p53 cancer mutant rescue screen. A set of overlapping, degenerate oligonucleotides 
with roughly equal initial annealing temperatures was designed to change each single codon in a 30 bp wide region. Parallel reactions can be used to 
mutagenize large regions or entire genes. Parent plasmids were removed by Dpn1 digestion. At this point, a plasmid library containing completely 
saturated target regions of a gene of interest could be generated by transformation into E. coli. Alternatively, the mutagenized products could be 
amplified by PCR and introduced into target vectors by homologous recombination, or be used in many other standard applications. To select 
intragenic mutants that restore activity to p53 mutants found in human cancer, the p53 core domain was amplified from the mutagenized pool and 
introduced into a p53-tester yeast strain by homologous recombination. Yeast cells expressing re-activated p53 were identified by uracil prototrophy. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 20 7083 </p>

<p>one of 64 codons, the 640 theoretical different mutants are 
covered by &gt;200 000 transformants with &gt;300-fold 
coverage (as &gt;200 000/640). Such high coverage almost 
certainly guarantees that every codon change was repre-
sented (P &lt; 1.0e À 130 by the binomial distribution with 
Bonferoni correction for 640 trials). 
ACS mutagenesis of the p53 region encoding amino 
acids 232-241 identified all five previously described 
rescue mutants and one new mutation (Y234L) that 
reactivated the p53 
R158L cancer mutant (Table 1). 
Interestingly, the Y234L mutation required a minimum 
of 2 nt changes and so is unlikely to be found using 
error-prone PCR, thus providing evidence for the value 
of our exhaustive approach. </p>

<p>ACS identified p53 cancer rescue mutations in amino acid 
region 114 to 123 </p>

<p>We next wanted to scan a novel region in p53 for 
reactivating second-site mutations that can restore 
activity to p53 mutants. We considered the 10 p53 
cancer mutants that are most commonly found in 
human cancer and can be constructed so that they differ 
by two or more nucleic acid changes from the wild-type 
(R249S, G245S, H179R, R273H, R248L, R158L, R280T, 
P151S, P152L, P278L). Cancer mutants were restricted to 
those with multiple nucleotide changes from wild-type p53 
to minimize false-positive errors due to spontaneous re-
version, although analysis of the experimental results later 
indicated that this precaution was not necessary. These 10 
cancer mutants were used for ACS mutagenesis of amino 
acid region 114-123. Note that one of these p53 mutants 
(p53 
R158L ) was used in the ACS experiment targeting 
region 232-241. Region 114-123 was considered a poten-
tial cancer rescue region because multiple amino acid 
changes occurred there spontaneously in previous cancer 
rescue mutant screens but no single amino acid change 
cancer rescue mutations had been found previously [(36); 
Brachmann, R. K., personal communication]. In addition, 
a structure-based computational classifier trained to </p>

<p>predict regions in p53 that likely contain cancer rescue 
mutations selected region 114-123 (39). Therefore, this 
region was thought likely to include single amino acid 
cancer rescue mutants and was selected for ACS. 
We obtained a minimum of 200 000 yeast transformants 
for each library, which represents &gt;300-fold coverage of 
the expected 640 mutants in each library. We isolated a 
total of 146 transformants that grew on plates lacking 
uracil. The p53 core domains of all 146 potential rescue 
mutants were amplified by colony PCR and sequenced. 
Three of the isolated uracil prototroph strains contained 
wild-type p53, which was likely a result of reversion of the 
cancer mutation due to selection pressure. However, the 
vast majority of sequences (143) retained the cancer 
mutation. A total of 13 different potential rescue 
mutants showed both the cancer mutation and a second 
mutation that changed the amino acid sequence in the 
mutagenized region. All potential rescue mutants were 
regenerated using site directed mutagenesis, transformed 
into the p53-tester yeast strain, and analyzed for their 
ability to confer uracil prototrophy (Figure 4). All 
rescue mutations were confirmed. Six of them had a 
strong reactivation activity, whereas seven showed only 
a very small gain in activity compared to the cancer 
mutant and were not further tested (Table 2). We 
measured p53 activity of the strong rescue mutants in </p>

<p>Figure 3. Representation of the experimental and theoretical frequency of codons in position 239 obtained by ACS. </p>

<p>Table 1. Summary of p53 cancer rescue mutants obtained by ACS 
targeting amino acid region 232-241 of p53 cancer mutant p53 </p>

<p>R158L </p>

<p>p53 Cancer 
mutant </p>

<p>Rescue 
mutation </p>

<p>R158L 
N239Y 
R158L 
N239F 
R158L 
N239R 
R158L 
N235K 
R158L 
Y234V 
R158L 
Y234L* </p>

<p>Asterisks label rescue mutants that required at least 2-nt changes for 
that amino-acid substitution. New rescue mutants are in boldface. </p>



<p>human H1299 cells, which lack endogenous p53 activity. 
p53 cancer mutants and rescue mutants were expressed in 
H1299 cells and activity was measured using a 
p53-dependent luciferase reporter (18) (Figure 4). 
Without exception, mutations confirmed in the yeast-
based screen also reactivated p53 cancer mutants in 
human cells. 
All p53 cancer rescue mutants identified in amino acid 
region 114-123 were new and had not been identified by 
previous error-prone PCR mutagenesis approaches using 
the same yeast-based p53 activity assay. ACS resulted in a 
mutant that reactivated the p53 cancer mutant p53 </p>

<p>P152L </p>

<p>, 
which had not been rescued before. Importantly, three out 
of the six identified amino acid changes that strongly re-
activated p53 cancer mutants required 2-or 3-nt changes. 
Such mutations are underrepresented in current in vivo or 
in vitro mutagenesis approaches, but were easily identified 
using our complete and unbiased exhaustive approach. </p>

<p>Combined ACS reactions to scan larger domains or 
entire genes </p>

<p>ACS reactions easily can be performed in parallel to 
produce gene libraries that target much larger gene 
regions or entire genes. We used ACS to saturate all 200 
amino acids of the p53 core domain with all possible single 
amino acid changes. The ACS method consists of 
single-tube reactions, each covering a region of 30 bases. 
Twenty parallel ACS reactions were performed and the 
mutagenesis products were introduced to the p53-tester 
yeast strain (Figure 2). Combining these single ACS reac-
tions produced a completely saturated library with exactly 
one mutation in each product. At the same time, the 
modularity of the system allows to avoid the modification 
of specific gene areas of interest or even key residues, such 
as the p53 cancer mutation itself. 
The three p53 cancer mutants p53 </p>

<p>R175H </p>

<p>, p53 
R273H and 
p53 
G245S were exhaustively scanned for single-change 
cancer rescue mutants throughout the 200 amino acid 
core region. We selected these particular cancer mutants 
due to their specific characteristics. p53 
R175H is the most 
common cancer mutant found in human tumors, but re-
version to wild-type requires only a single nucleotide 
change and we were concerned about a potentially high 
spontaneous reversion rate interfering with ACS 
screening. Eventually, however, random reversion to 
wild-type p53 turned out to be insignificant. We also 
chose to analyze p53 
R273H , the most common cancer 
mutant that differs by 2-nt changes from wild-type p53, 
to avoid altogether the possibility of spontaneous rever-
sion. Neither cancer mutant had been rescued previously 
by intragenic single amino acid changes, and thus might 
have been too stringent an initial test case for ACS. 
Therefore, we also analyzed p53 
G245S , the most common 
cancer mutant that had been rescued previously by a 
single amino acid change. 
Table 3 summarizes the results of ACS saturation mu-
tagenesis on the 200 amino acids in the p53 core domain 
for these three different cancer mutants. p53 
R175H could 
not be reactivated by a single amino acid change. For 
p53 
R273H and p53 
G245S , we recovered all previously </p>

<p>Wild-type p53 </p>

<p>P152L </p>

<p>P152L_L114P </p>

<p>P152L_H115D </p>

<p>P152L_T118Y </p>

<p>Wild-type p53 
G245S </p>

<p>G245S_T123P </p>

<p>R158L </p>

<p>R158L_L114P </p>

<p>R158L_H115D </p>

<p>-HIS 
-URA </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Figure 4. Reactivation of p53 cancer mutants by second site mutations 
in amino acid region 114-123. (A) Yeast cells expressing the URA3 
gene from a p53-dependent promoter were transformed with centro-
meric plasmids (HIS3 selection marker) expressing wild-type human 
p53, or the mutants indicated, under control of the ADH1 promoter. 
Serial dilutions of cells grown to mid-log phase in medium lacking 
histidine were spotted onto plates either lacking histidine or uracil. 
Growth on plates lacking uracil is dependent on expression of the 
URA3 gene and is a measure of p53 activity. Mutants are named 
with the cancer mutation appearing first followed by the putative 
cancer rescue mutation. (B) p53 transcriptional activity was evaluated 
in transient reporter gene assays in H1299 cells, which lack endogenous 
p53 activity. Firefly luciferase activity, adjusted for transfection effi-
ciency with Renilla luciferase activity, was determined 48 h after trans-
fection. The activity of wild-type p53 was set to 100%. SD were 
calculated from at least three independent experiments. </p>

<p>Table 2. Summary of p53 cancer rescue mutants obtained by ACS 
targeting amino acid region 114-123 of 10 p53 cancer mutants 
commonly found in human tumors (R249S, G245S, H179R, R273H, 
R248L, R158L, R280T, P151S, P152L, P278L) </p>

<p>p53 Cancer mutant 
Rescue mutation 
G245S 
T123P 
R158L 
L114P* 
R158L 
H115D 
R158L 
L114P* 
P152L 
H115D 
P152L 
T118Y* </p>

<p>p53 Cancer mutant 
Weak Rescue mutation 
R158L 
T123S 
R158L 
H115N* 
P152L 
T123G* 
P152L 
T123A 
P152L 
T123P* 
P152L 
T123S 
P152L 
H115E* </p>

<p>Asterisks and boldface are as in Table 1. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 20 7085 </p>

<p>known single rescue mutations and identified six new re-
activation sites (Table 3). Three of the six new sites 
required two or three changes from wild-type p53, and 
so are unlikely to be seen using error-prone PCR. These 
results further demonstrate the utility of ACS for efficient, 
economic, and systematic saturation scanning muta-
genesis in defined gene sections. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>In summary, the ACS strategy creates a sequence defined 
gene library, which changes each individual codon in a 
specific target region into all possible codons, with only 
a single codon change per mutagenesis product. The ACS 
approach is fast, simple, and generally applicable to any 
problem that requires systematic changes of defined 
regions in a DNA sequence, including protein design, 
directed evolution, structure/function analyses and 
promoter studies. 
Individual ACS mutagenesis reactions can target 
changes in a single codon (or even a single base pair 
position) for as many as 30 contiguous base pairs. The 
upper base pair target limit restricts primer length to 
avoid incorporation of mutations due to primer synthesis 
errors, considering a typical error rate of one per 600 
synthesized nucleotides (40-43). By performing parallel 
reactions, mutagenesis can be expanded to larger regions 
or whole genes. The ACS system allows complete control 
over the target regions; specific gene sections, or even 
specific nucleotides, easily can be protected from mutagen-
esis. Thus, ACS is an adaptable and versatile tool. 
Here, ACS was used to mutagenize small and large 
regions of the human tumor suppressor gene p53. Eleven 
common p53 cancer mutants, which collectively are found 
in well over one million diagnosed cancer cases per year, 
were tested. Reactivating intragenic mutations for four of 
them were identified. Moreover, the p53 cancer mutants 
p53 
P152L and p53 
R273H had not been reactivated previous-
ly by single amino acid changes. Thus, ACS obtained 
more complete biological information than previously 
had been obtained using methods such as error-prone 
PCR (Supplementary Table S1). Notably, 7 out of the </p>

<p>12 strong new p53 cancer rescue mutants we identified in 
this study required 2-or 3-nt changes, confirming the 
utility of ACS as an unbiased approach. 
To understand better the regions selected and their re-
lationship to the p53 protein, it is helpful to consider mo-
lecular visualizations of p53 (Figure 5). Cancer mutations 
are indicated in red and rescue mutations in green. The 3D 
locations are consistent with the hypothesis that different 
p53 cancer rescue mutants require different rescue mech-
anisms (44-46), and suggest that different rescue regions 
may correspond to distinct modes of cancer mutant reacti-
vation. For example, rescue mutations for the p53 cancer 
mutant p53 
R273H are located in distinct regions that do not 
overlap with rescue regions associated with other cancer 
mutants (Figure 5). A comprehensive identification of 
such rescue regions using ACS or similar approaches 
may contribute to targeted drug development, as it helps 
to identify surface exposed, drug accessible sites on p53 
where perturbations may result in reactivation. 
A significant proportion of human tumors express full 
length but mutated, inactive p53. Consequently, there are 
ongoing efforts to find small molecule drugs that mimic 
the cancer rescue effect of reactivating p53 second-site sup-
pressor mutations (44,45,47,48). Despite impressive 
progress, efforts are hampered by a limited understanding 
of the p53 mutation-structure/function relationship 
(13,46,49,50). The ACS strategy described here has 
expanded and diversified the collection of rescue muta-
tions that reactivate p53 cancer mutants. We hope that 
these efforts will lead to further insight into general struc-
tural changes that can rescue p53 cancer mutants, and 
thereby facilitate rational drug design approaches that 
seek to exploit similar effects. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>G245S 
P152L </p>

<p>R158L 
R273H </p>

<p>Figure 5. Three-dimensional location of cancer mutants and their 
rescue mutations. The 3D structure of p53 (51) was visualized with 
<rs type="software">Visual Molecular Dynamics</rs> (52). Positions of cancer mutations are 
indicated in red and positions of rescue mutations are in green. </p>

<p>Table 3. Summary of p53 cancer rescue mutants obtained by ACS 
targeting the 600-nt region encoding the p53 core domain of cancer 
mutants p53 
R273H and p53 </p>

<p>G245S </p>

<p>p53 Cancer 
mutant </p>

<p>Rescue 
mutation </p>

<p>G245S 
N239F 
G245S 
F113L 
G245S 
S240Y 
G245S 
T123P 
G245S 
N239Y 
R273H 
S240R* 
R273H 
S240Q* 
R273H 
C242R 
R273H 
N263V* </p>

<p>Asterisks and boldface are as in Table 1. </p>



<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Lydia Ho, Faezeh Salehi and Chris Wassman 
for helpful discussion and technical assistance. S. A. D. 
acknowledges support from the National Institutes of 
Health Biomedical Informatics Training Program. 
Materials and computer code will be provided under the 
terms of the standard Materials Transfer Agreement of 
the Regents of the University of California. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>National Institutes of Health BISTI (grant number 
CA-112560, partial); National Science Foundation (grant 
number IIS-0326037). National Institutes of Health 
Biomedical Informatics Training Program (grant number 
LM-07443 to S.A.D.). Funding for open access charge: 
National Institutes of Health BISTI (grant number 
CA-112560); National Science Foundation (grant 
number IIS-0326037). </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 20 7087 </p>





</text></tei>