<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2887951" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:25+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>A systematic search was performed for DNA-
binding sequences of YgiP, an uncharacterized tran-
scription factor of Escherichia coli, by using the 
Genomic SELEX. The complete sequence of Escherichia coli genome has 
revealed the presence of 4453 protein-coding sequences 
shared between two laboratory strains, MG1655 
and W3110, of K-12 lineage (1). The function of each 
gene product has been experimentally determined or 
computationally predicted for about half of the genes, </p>

<p>but a large number of genes are still left uncharacterized 
(1) even though E. coli has long been used as a model 
organism in the modern molecular biology since its isola-
tion (2). One major research subject of the post-genome 
sequencing era is the identification of physiological func-
tions for all these uncharacterized genes. Most of these 
genes are, however, not expressed in laboratory culture 
conditions and thus supposed to be needed for the 
survival of E. coli under stressful conditions in nature. 
The expression of these uncharacterized stress-response 
genes must be under the control of stress-response regula-
tory systems. This line of research encounters with the 
difficulty that arises from the lack of knowledge about 
factors and conditions required for expression of each of 
these silent genes under laboratory culture conditions. 
Transcription of the E. coli genome is considered to 
be under the control of approximately 300 species of tran-
scription factors (3-5), which altogether control the distri-
bution of about 2000 molecules of RNA polymerase 
among 4453 genes within the genome (3,5,6). The regula-
tory roles, however, remain unidentified for about 
100 species of the transcription factor (5) presumably 
because those putative factors are needed for regulation 
of the genes, which are expressed in response to as-yet 
unidentified environmental stresses. Ordinary genetic 
approach is not useful without knowledge of factors and 
conditions for expression of their regulatory functions. To 
identify the regulatory roles of hitherto uncharacterized 
putative transcription factors, we have performed a sys-
tematic search for the identification of DNA sequences 
recognized by each of 300 species of DNA-binding tran-
scription factors from E. coli by using the newly developed 
Genomic SELEX (systematic evolution of ligands by 
exponential enrichment) system (7). Since the binding 
sites of prokaryotic transcription factors are generally 
located within or near the promoters, we can predict the 
target promoters, genes and operons from the binding site 
maps of test factors as have been successfully employed 
for Cra (7), RstA (8), PdhR (9), RutR (10), TyrR (11), 
NemR (12), AllR (13), CitB (14), LeuO (15) and AscG 
(16). Once the consensus recognition sequence is identified </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel/Fax: +81 42 387 6231; Email: aishiham@hosei.ac.jp </p>

<p>Published online 15 February 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3605-3618 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkq077 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>after genomic SELEX screening, the in silico search for 
other targets becomes possible using the information of 
whole genome sequence. 
The LysR family of DNA-binding regulators exists in 
diverse bacterial genera, archea and algal chloroplasts, 
and participate in diverse cellular activities, including 
nitrogen fixation, oxidative stress response and bacte-
rial virulence (17). Escherichia coli contains a total of 
54 families of transcription factor, of which the LysR 
family is the most abundant including 45 members (4,5). 
LysR family proteins contain an N-terminal helix-turn-
helix motif, but the consensus sequence of DNA binding 
is different between LysR family members, indicating that 
each controls a different set of genes or promoters with a 
unique recognition sequence. In this study, a systematic 
search was performed for identification of the target 
genes under the control of YgiP, an uncharacterized 
LysR-family transcription factor, by using this newly 
developed genomic SELEX system. In prokaryotes, the 
genes encoding transcription regulatory proteins are gen-
erally located on the genome adjoining to the target genes 
for regulation. Relying on this rule, Oshima and Biville (18) 
predicted that YgiP is involved in regulation of the adjacent 
ttdA-ttdB genes encoding tartrate dehydrogenase and 
propose to name YgiP as TtdR. After cloning-sequencing 
(SELEX-clos) and tilling array analysis (SELEX-chip) of 
SELEX fragments, however, we have obtained a large 
number of YgiP-binding sequences from hundreds of loci 
within the E. coli genome, including the ttdR-ttdA spacer 
sequence. After gel-shift and DNase-footprinting assays, 
YgiP was found to be a DNA-binding protein with affinity 
to AT-rich sequences. Both the number of binding sites on 
the genome and the sequence preference are similar to the 
known nucleoid proteins such as Fis and IHF (5,19,20). By 
using the quantitative immuno-blotting (21), we found the 
intracellular concentration of YgiP was very low in 
growing E. coli cells under aerobic conditions; however, 
under hypoxic or anaerobic culture conditions, the YgiP 
level increased more than 100-fold, reaching to the level 
as high as those of major nucleoid proteins HU and IHF. 
A mutant E. coli lacking ygiP showed retarded growth 
under anaerobic conditions. The binding mode of YgiP 
to DNA was investigated by atomic force microscory 
(AFM). These observations altogether indicate that YgiP 
has dual functions, playing the architectural role for 
genome folding and the global regulatory role in transcrip-
tion of a number of genes, as in the case of the nucleoid 
proteins Fis and IHF. We then conclude that YgiP is 
a hitherto unidentified nucleoid protein in E. coli growing 
under anaerobic conditions, and propose to rename YgiP 
(or TtdR) to Dan (DNA-binding protein under anaerobic 
conditions), which belongs to the same family of growth 
phase-specific nucleoid proteins as Fis in exponential 
growth phase (22,23) and Dps in stationary phase (24). </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Bacterial strains and culture conditions </p>

<p>The E. coli strains used in this work were KP7600 (W3110 
typeA lacI 
q lacZDM15 galK2 galK22) and JD24074 </p>

<p>(KP7600 dan) which was constructed by a transposon 
insertion method (a gift from T. Miki). Cells were grown 
at 37 
C in Luria-Bertani (LB) or M9-0.4% glucose 
medium. Overnight culture in LB medium was diluted 
1000-fold into fresh LB or M9 medium. For the aerobic 
culture, the incubation was carried out at 37 
C with a 
constant sharking to an appropriate cell density. The cell 
density was determined by measuring the absorbance at 
600 nm. 
For hypoxic culture, bacteria were suspended in 15-ml 
centrifuge tubes with silicone stoppers to make the initial 
cell density of 0.1 OD 600 and anoxia was achieved to expel 
any remaining air by chemical duty pump (Millipore) 
for 60 min. Cell culture was maintained at 37 
C without 
shaking. On the other hand, anaerobic culture was carried 
out using COY chamber (COY Laboratory Products, 
Inc.) under the constant circulation of nitrogen (95%)-
hydrogen (5%) mixed gas equipped with a palladium 
catalyst. </p>

<p>Purification of Dan protein </p>

<p>For construction of plasmid pDan for Dan expression, a 
DNA fragment corresponding to the Dan-coding region 
was amplified by PCR using E. coli W3110 genome DNA 
as a template and a pair of primers, which were designed 
so as to hybridize upstream or downstream of the Dan-
coding sequence. After digestion with NdeI and NotI, 
PCP products were cloned into pET21a(+) (Novagen) 
between NdeI and NotI sites. The plasmid construct was 
confirmed by DNA sequencing. For protein expression, 
the pDan plasmid was transformed into E. coli BL21 
(DE3). Expression of Dan was induced by adding IPTG 
(isopropyl-b-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside). Purification of 
over-expressed His-tagged Dan was performed under the 
standard purification procedure (7-16). </p>

<p>Genomic SELEX </p>

<p>The genomic SELEX screening was performed as 
described previously (7-16). In brief, 5 pmol of a mixture 
of genome DNA fragments of 150-300 bp in length and 
10 pmol His-tagged Dan were mixed in a binding buffer 
(10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0 at 4 
C, 3 mM Mg-acetate, 
150 mM NaCl and 0.1 mM EDTA) and incubated for 
30 min at 37 
C. The mixture was applied onto Ni-NTA 
column and after washing unbound DNA with the 
binding buffer containing 10 mM imidazole, DNA-Dan 
complexes were eluted with an elution buffer containing 
200 mM imidazole. 
The sequences of DNA fragments obtained by the 
genomic SELEX screening were identified by both 
SELEX-chip and SELEX-clos procedures. For SELEX-
chip analysis, DNA fragments were subjected to 
the Microarray assay using a tilling array consisting 
of 22 000 60-bp-long oligonucleotide probes aligned at 
160 bp intervals along the E. coli genome (25). Dan-
bound SELEX DNA fragments and the original mixture 
of genome DNA fragments used in the genomic SELEX 
screening were differentially labeled with Cy5 and Cy3, 
respectively. The two labeled DNA samples were 
combined and hybridized to the tilling microarray </p>



<p>(Oxford Gene Technology, Oxford, UK). The Cy5/Cy3 
intensity ratio was measured for each spot, and plotted 
against the corresponding position on the E. coli 
KP7600 chromosome, creating the genome-wide profiles 
of Dan binding. Peaks that exhibited a Cy5/Cy3 ratio of 
&gt;3.5 with two or more consecutive probes were selected as 
Dan-binding sites (for the typical pattern see Figure 1). 
In SELEX-clos (cloning and sequencing) procedure, the 
same SELEX DNA fragments as used for SELEX-chip 
were cloned into pT7 into pT7 Blue-T vector (Novagen) 
and transformed into E. coli DH5a for amplification. The 
DNA fragments were regenerated by polymerase chain 
reaction (PCR) using amplified plasmids as template 
and fluorescent-labeled T7-primer (5 
0 -TAATACGACTC 
ACTATAGGG-3 
0 ) for sequencing with ABI DNA 
sequencer 3130Â. </p>

<p>Gel mobility shift assay </p>

<p>Gel shift assay was performed as described previously 
(8,9). In brief, probes were generated by PCR amplifica-
tion of Dan-binding sequences in SELEX using a pair of 
primers, 5 
0 fluorescein isothiocyanate (FITC)-labeled T7-F 
primer (5 
0 -TAATACGACTACTATAGGG-3 
0 ) and T7-R 
primer (5 
0 -GGTTTTCCCAGTCACACGACG-3 
0 ), the 
genomic SELEX plasmids containing the respective Dan 
recognition sequences as templates, and Ex Taq DNA 
polymerase. PCR products with FITC at their termini 
were purified by PAGE. For gel shift assays, 0.5 pmol 
each of the FITC-labeled probes was incubated at 37 
C 
for 30 min with various amounts of Dan in 15 ml of gel 
shift buffer consisting of 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.8 at 4 
C, 
150 mM NaCl, 3 mM Mg acetate. After the addition of 
DNA dye solution, the mixture was directly subjected to 
6% PAGE. Fluorescent-labeled DNA in gels was detected 
using Pharos FX plus system (Bio-Rad). The setting of </p>

<p>excitation and emission wavelength was 488 and 532 nm, 
respectively. </p>

<p>DNase-I footprinting assay </p>

<p>DNase-I footprinting assay was carried out using FITC-
labeled DNA fragments as described previously (8,9). 
Each 2.0 pmol of FITC-labeled probes was incubated at 
37 
C for 30 min with various amounts of Dan in DNase-I 
footprinting buffer consisting of 25 ml of 10 mM Tris-HCl 
(pH 7.8), 50 mM NaCl, 3 mM magnesium acetate, 5 mM 
CaCl 2 and 25 mg/ml BSA. After incubation for 30 min, 
DNA digestion was initiated by the addition of 0.05 U 
of DNase I (TAKARA). After digestion for 40 s at 
25 
C, the reaction was terminated by the addition of 
25 ml of phenol. Digested products were precipitated 
with ethanol, dissolved in formamide-dye solution and 
analyzed by electrophoresis on a 6% polyacrylamide gel 
containing 7 M urea. </p>

<p>AFM observation </p>

<p>For observation of Dan-DNA complexes by AFM, 
plasmid pGRdan was constructed, which carried the 
ttdA-dan spacer sequence within the promoter assay 
vector pGR (26). Mixtures of 200 ng pGRdan DNA and 
5-800 ng of Dan protein in a binding buffer [50 mM 
HEPES-KOH (pH 7.6), 1 mM EDTA, 500 mM NaCl, 
1 mM DTT] were incubated for 30 min at 37 
C. After 
cross-linking DNA-protein by treatment with 0.1% 
glutaraldehyde for 1 h at 4 
C, the samples were diluted 
to make the final DNA concentration of $5 ng/ml with a 
dilution buffer [5 mM HEPES-KOH (pH 7.6), 2 mM 
MgCl 2 ] and directly spotted onto a freshly cleaved mica 
substrate pretreated with 10 mM spermidine. After 10 min, 
the mica was gently washed with distilled water and dried 
under nitrogen gas. Imaging was performed in Tapping </p>

<p>Figure 1. Distribution of Dan-binding sequences on the E. coli genome. Mixtures of Dan-binding DNA fragments isolated by the genomic SELEX 
were subjected to the DNA microarray analysis. Binding signals (y-axis) are plotted against the location along the E. coli genome (x-axis). The genes 
showing high-level peaks above the cutoff level of 3.5 are indicated. The genes with asterisk represent those identified by SELEX-clos (see 
Supplementary Table 1). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3607 </p>

<p>Mode 
TM with a Multimode 
TM AFM (Veeco, Santa 
Barbara, CA, USA) operation with a Nanoscope IIIa </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>controller. For scanning, Olympus silicon cantilevers 
(OMCL-AC160TS-W2) with spring constants between 
36 and 75 N/m were used. The scan frequency was typi-
cally 1.5 Hz per line and the modulation amplitude was 
a few nanometers. Analysis of the DNA-Dan complexes 
was performed using the <rs type="software">Nanoscope</rs> software. Two-
dimensional images in brightness and contrast were 
optimized for the purpose of clarity. Three-dimensional 
images were created with the <rs type="software">Nanoscope</rs> software and 
exported in TIFF format. </p>

<p>Quantitative immunoblot analysis </p>

<p>A quantitative western blot analysis was carried out by 
standard method as described previously (21). In brief, 
E. coli cells grown in 10 ml of either LB or M9-0.4% 
glucose medium under both aerobic and anaerobic 
culture conditions were harvested by centrifugation and 
resuspended in 0.3 ml lysis buffer (50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 
7.5, 50 mM NaCl, 5% glycerol and 1 mM dithiothreitol), 
and then lysozyme was added to a final concentration 
of 20 mg/ml. Total proteins were subjected to 12% 
SDS-PAGE and blotted on to a plyvinylidene difluoride 
(PVDF) membranes using semi-dry transfer apparatus. 
Membranes were first immuno-detected with anti-Dan 
and then developed with an enhanced chemiluminescence 
kit (Amersham-Pharmacia Biotech). The image was 
analyzed with a LAS-1000 Plus Lumino-Image Analyzer 
and Image Gauge (Fuji Film). </p>

<p>Indirect immuno-fluorescence microscopy </p>

<p>The procedure for indirect immuno-fluorescence micros-
copy was essentially the same as previously described 
(27,28). In brief, cells were fixed by treatment with 80% 
methanol for 1 h at 25 
C, and deposited on to a poly 
L-lysine-coated slide. After air drying, cells were treated 
with 2 mg/ml lysozyme solution at room temperature for 
5 min. The slide was treated 99% methanol for 1 min, and 
then with acetone for 1 min until complete dryness. After 
washing with PBS containing 0.05% Tween 20) and 2% 
bovine serum albumin (BSA) for 15 min for blocking, the 
sample was treated with 200-500-fold diluted anti-Dan 
antibodies for 1 h at room temperature. After washing 
with Tween-containing PBS, the sample was treated at 
room temperature for 1 h with 500-fold diluted goat 
anti-rabbit IgG antibodies conjugated with a fluorescence 
compound Cy3. After washing with Tween-containing 
PBS, the sample was treated with 10 ml of DAPI (4 
0 ,6-
diamidino-2-phenylindole dihydrochloride, 10 mg/ml) for 
1 min for staining DNA, and covered with one drop of 
mountain medium (1 mg/ml p-phenylenediamine and 
90% glycerol in PBS, pH 9.0). The immuno-stained 
samples were observed with a fluorescence and phase-
contrast microscope (100Âobjective lens; Olympus, 
Japan) equipped with a chilled, high sensitive digital 
CCD camera, Regita EXi (NIPPON ROPER, Japan), 
connected to a computer. Different filter cassettes were 
used for observation of Cy3 and DAPI fluorescence. The 
images were transferred directly to a Windows XP and </p>

<p>processed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image-Pro Plus</rs> <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 6.0</rs> software. 
The specificity of the observed immuno-stained fluores-
cent signal was verified by the absence of the signal in 
corresponding immuno-stained samples prepared using 
the respective dan null mutant cells. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Genomic SELEX search for Dan-binding sequences </p>

<p>For the identification of DNA sequences that are 
recognized by E. coli Dan, we employed the 'Genomic 
SELEX' system (7), in which a mixture of genome 
DNA fragments was used instead of mixtures of 
oligonucleotides with all possible sequences as used in 
the original SELEX (systematic evolution of ligands by 
exponential enrichment) (29-31). The 'Genomic SELEX' 
has since been successfully employed for identification of 
the sets of genes under the control of some known and 
unknown transcription factors (7-16). From a mixture of 
DNA fragments of E. coli K12 W3350 and a two-fold 
molar excess of the purified His-tagged Dan protein, 
Dan-DNA complexes were affinity purified using Ni-
NTA resin. In the early stage of this genomic SELEX 
cycle, the Dan-bound DNA fragments formed smear 
bands on PAGE as did the original genome fragment 
mixture. After four and five SELEX cycles, however, the 
width of gel bands decreased, indicating certain enrich-
ment of specific DNA fragments with Dan-binding 
activity. For sequence identification of Dan-bound DNA 
fragments, we first employed the cloning-sequencing 
method (SELEX-clos), in which the DNA fragment 
mixtures were recovered from the gels, PCR-amplified 
and subjected to the ordinary procedure of cloning and 
sequencing (7). 
After four cycles of the 'Genomic SELEX' screening, 
a total of 333 independent SELEX clones were isolated 
by the SELEX-clos method, which were classified into 
two different groups based on the location on the E. coli 
genome relative to the genes (Table 1). Group A included 
149 independent clones, each carrying a unique sequence </p>

<p>Table 1. Dan-bound DNA fragments </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Group No. of 
clones </p>

<p>No. of 
loci </p>

<p>Total 
no.of 
clones </p>

<p>Group No. of 
clones </p>

<p>No. of 
loci </p>

<p>Total 
no.of 
clones </p>

<p>A 
6 9 
1 
6 9 
B 
1 9 
1 
1 9 
22 
1 
22 
15 
1 
15 
10 
1 
10 
10 
1 
10 
4 
4 
1 6 
4 
3 
1 2 
2 
7 
1 4 
3 
4 
1 2 
1 
18 
18 
2 
34 
68 
1 
4 8 
4 8 </p>

<p>32 
149 
92 
184 </p>

<p>a Using the genomic SELEX method, a total of 333 DNA fragments 
have been isolated as complexes with the purified Dan protein. 
A total of 149 group A clones contained the sequences from spacer 
regions between the neighboring genes, while a total of 184 group B 
clones carried the sequences within the coding frames. 
The location of all the SELEX fragments on the genome is described in 
Table 2 and Supplementary Tables 1 and 2. </p>



<p>from 32 different spacer regions between two neighboring 
genes on the E. coli genome (Supplementary Table 1A). 
In prokaryotes, the recognition DNA sequences by tran-
scription regulatory factors are generally located within or 
near the promoters of target genes. If Dan is such a 
specific DNA-binding transcription factor, the regulation 
targets may be the genes, which are located downstream 
of these Dan-binding sites (shown by arrows in 
Supplementary Table 1A). 
Of the total 149 group-A library, 69 clones contained 
two different but partially overlapping 297-bp-long 
segments of the spacer region of divergently transcribed 
dan (renamed from ygiP and ttdR) and ttdA (between 
nucleotides 3 204 211 and 3 204 508 of the E. coli 
MG1655 genome) (Supplementary Table 1A). The two 
different 297-bp-long segments overlapped in 63-bp 
sequence, indicating that the Dan-binding sequence is 
located within this narrow region of 63 bp in length. The 
number of SELEX isolates by a test transcription factor 
correlates with its affinity to the target sequence (7-16), 
we predicted that Dan has a strong affinity to this dan-
ttdA spacer region. This sequence with strong affinity to 
Dan is located upstream of its own gene and upstream 
of the divergently transcribed ttdAB genes encoding 
L-tartrate dehydratase. One possible function of Dan is 
the autogenous control of its own expression, but Dan 
may also play a regulatory role in expression of the neigh-
boring and divergently transcribed ttdA-ttdB-ygjE operon 
as predicted based on the gene organization (18). A total 
of 22 clones from group-A library carried sequences from 
the ffh-ypjD spacer; 10 clones from the maoC-paaA spacer; 
four clones each from the yfaZ-yfaO, ygdH-sdaC, 
fimB-fimE and cadB-cadC spacers; two clones each from 
seven different spacers; and one clone each from other 
18 spacers (Supplementary Table 1A). 
On the other hand, group B included 184 independent 
clones (Supplementary Table 1B), which were derived 
from a total of 95 protein-coding regions, including 
19 clones from nrfE; 15 clones from yhfS; 10 clones 
from ebgA; 4 clones each from yagM, mltB, yegB, and 
yiiG; three clones each from kdpB, yegB, yfcN and yjbI; 
and two clones each from 35 different loci (Supplementary 
Table 1B). After the genome-wide screening by the 
Genomic SELEX, we realized that the DNA-binding 
sites are located within protein-coding sequences for a 
specific set of transcription factors (32). The ratio 
between group-A and group-B libraries is different 
between more than 50 species of transcription factor so 
far examined by the Genomic SELEX (Ishihama, A., 
unpublished data), implying that transcription factors 
associated within protein-coding sequences play an as 
yet unidentified regulatory role(s). 
The high level of heterogeneity in the SELEX DNA 
library indicates that Dan binds to a larger number of 
sites on the genome. With use of the SELEX-clos 
method, we must have identified only a fraction of DNA 
fragments with high affinity to Dan. In order to identify 
the whole set of potential Dan-binding sites, we then sub-
jected the DNA fragment mixtures to a tilling array 
analysis (SELEX-chip). The array herein employed 
consists of 22 000 60-mer-oligonucleotides that correspond </p>

<p>to evenly spaced sections of the E. coli genome at $160-bp 
intervals (25). Dan-binding SELEX fragments isolated 
after five and six cycles of the Genomic SELEX were 
labeled with Cy5 while the original DNA fragment 
library used for SELEX screening were labeled with 
Cy3. The fluorescent-labeled DNA mixture was subjected 
to hybridization with the tilling array (an Oxford Gene 
Technology product). After washing and scanning, Cy5/ 
Cy3 signal intensity ratio was calculated for each of 22 000 
probes. 
A total of 688 peaks with Dan-binding activity could be 
identified when the cutoff level of Cy5/Cy3 ratio was set at 
3.5 (Figure 1). A total of 333 independent clones were 
isolated from 124 different locations by the SELEX-clos 
analysis, while a total of 688 sites were identified by the 
SELEX-chip analysis, indicating that the screening was 
not saturated for the SELEX-clos analysis. Most of the 
Dan-binding sites identified by the SELEX-clos analysis 
(see Supplementary Table 1) were included in the data 
collection of SELEX-chip analysis (see Supplementary 
Table 2. Note that the genes identified by SELEX-clos 
are indicated by asterisk in Figure 1). In agreement with 
the results of SELEX-clos analysis, the signals were 
detected on both coding and non-coding sections 
of the E. coli genome (Table 2). Of a total of 688 
Dan-binding sites, 504 were located within intergenic 
non-coding regions (group-A) (Table 2; for details see 
Supplementary Table 2A), while 184 were within coding 
regions (group-B) (Table 2; for details see Supplementary 
Table 2B). Even though the combination of total non-
coding sequences is &lt;10% of the whole E. coli genome, 
$80% of the Dan-binding sites are located within the 
non-coding sequences (Table 2). This supports the predic-
tion that Dan plays a regulatory role of the genome 
function. </p>

<p>DNA-binding activity of Dan: Gel mobility shift assay </p>

<p>One unique feature of the SELEX-clos and SELEX-chip 
analyses with Dan is the large number of its binding sites </p>

<p>Table 2. Location of Dan-binding DNA fragments identified by 
SELEX-chip </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Classification 
Group-A 
Group-B </p>

<p>Gene for metabolism 
78 
25 
Genetic information genes 
77 
19 
Information processing genes 
76 
13 
Membrane-related Genes 
25 
3 
Phage-derived genes 
21 
13 
Genes for other functions 
43 
20 
Conserved protein genes 
59 
23 
Genes with unknown function 
125 
68 </p>

<p>504 
184 </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>DNA fragment mixtures obtained by the Genomic SELEX were sub-
jected to the SELEX-chip analysis. 
When Dan-binding sites were picked up at the Cy5/Cy3 ratio above 
3.5, a total of 688 peaks were identified (see Figure 1), which could be 
classified into two groups: A, Dan-binding sites within spacer regions 
between two genes; A, Dan-binding sites within spacer regions; B, 
Dan-binding sites are located within open reading frames. These 
genes are categorized based on the functions of gene products (for 
details see Supplementary Tables 3 and 4). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3609 </p>

<p>within the entire E. coli genome. With respect to the 
number of DNA-binding sites, Dan is different from the 
well-characterized global regulators so far examined by 
the genomic SELEX, including CRP, Cra, RstA, PdhR, 
RutR, TyrR, NemR, AllR and CitB (7-10,12,13). Instead 
Dan is rather similar to those of major nucleoid proteins 
such as HU, IHF, H-NS and Fis (5). The number of 
DNA-binding sites by the nucleoid proteins with regula-
tory roles such as Fis and IHF ranges several hundreds as 
detected by Genomic SELEX screening (Kori,A. and 
Ishihama,A., unpublished data). 
For the confirmation of Dan binding to the DNA 
sequences identified by the Genomic SELEX screening, 
we performed the gel mobility shift assay for five 
representative DNA probes from SELEX-clos and 
SELEX-chip library: dan-ttdA (Figure 2A), maoC-paaA 
(Figure 2B), yfaZ-yfaO (Figure 2C) and intZ-yffL 
(Figure 2D) from group A, and ygaD-[mltB]-srlA 
(Figure 2E) and perR-[insN]-ykfC (Figure 2F) from 
group B. In parallel, we analyzed several DNA probes 
from non-peak fractions of the SELEX-chip pattern, 
including ykgI-ykgC (Figure 2G) and yjbR-[uvrA]-ssb 
(Figure 2H). The 179-bp-long dan-ttdA probe with high-
affinity to Dan formed a ladder consisting of at least eight 
bands on PAGE (Figure 2A), indicating that more than 
eight Dan molecules are able to bind to this 179-bp-long 
DNA segment (one Dan molecule per 20-bp-long DNA 
on average) in a sequential manner. Similar pattern 
of Dan binding was observed in all other SELEX DNA </p>

<p>fragments tested, including all four group-A probes, dan-
ttdA (Figure 2A), maoC-paaA (Figure 2B), yfaZ-yfaO 
(Figure 2C), intZ-yffL (Figure 2D) and two group-B 
probes, ygaD-[mltB]-srlA (Figure 2E) and perR-[insN]-
ykfC (Figure 2F). However, gel retardation was not 
observed with probes with non-peak probes, yjbR-
[uvrA]-ssb (Figure 2G) and ykgI-ykgC (Figure 2H), 
selected from the SELEX-chip pattern (Figure 1). The 
gel shift assay indicates that a certain level of the 
sequence selectivity of DNA binding by Dan. The gel 
mobility shift pattern of multi-step-complex formation is 
essentially the same with those of the major nucleoid 
proteins, HU and IHF (19), indicating that protein 
oligomerization takes place on DNA-bound Dan mole-
cules (see below for AFM images). 
The apparent K d value of Dan ranges 10-100 nM 
depending on the probe DNA as estimated from the 
level of conversion of free DNA to Dan-DNA complexes. 
This value is slightly higher than those of Fis and 
IHF (19). The order of Dan-binding affinity among 
the probes examined was: dan-ttdA, yfaZ-yfaO &gt; ygaD-
[mltB]-srlA, intZ-yffL &gt; maoC-paaA, perR-[insN]-ykfC 
(Figure 2). </p>

<p>DNA-binding specificity of Dan: DNase-I footprinting 
assay </p>

<p>The sequence specificity of DNA binding by Dan was 
then analyzed by DNase-I footprinting using the dan-
ttdA spacer probe, which was the most abundant </p>

<p>Figure 2. Gel mobility shift assay. Fluorescent-labeled DNA probes, each containing a SELEX segment from the dan-ttdA (A), maoC-paaA (B), 
yfaZ-yfaO (C), intZ-yffL (D), ygaD-[mltB]-srlA (E) and perR-insN (F) regions, or an unrelated reference fragment from yjbR-[uvrA]-ssb (G) and 
ykgI-ykgC spacer (H) were incubated at 37 
C for 30 min with the indicated amounts (lane 1, 0; lane 2, 5 pmol; lane 3, 10 pmol; lane 4, 20 pmol; and 
lane 5, 30 pmol) of Dan. The reaction mixtures were directly subjected to PAGE. </p>



<p>segment isolated by the Genomic SELEX screening 
(see Supplementary Table 1A) and formed at least 
eight Dan-DNA complex bands by gel shift assay 
(Figure 2A). After brief treatment with DNase I, at least 
four protected regions were identified (Figure 3A), of 
which three (Dan-I, Dan-II and Dan-III) covered 
14-bp-long sequences and one (Dan-IV) covered 29-bp 
sequence, suggesting that two molecules of Dan are 
associated with Dan-IV site, designated as Dan-IV-1 and 
Dan-IV-2 (Figure 3B). Besides the protection against 
DNase-I digestion, a hypersensitive site was also 
detected near the center within the protected regions as 
in the case of Dan-III region (Figure 3A). All the pro-
tected regions by Dan against DNase-I digestion 
included GTTNATT consensus sequence (Figure 3C). 
Similar GTTNATT-like sequences were identified in 
all other Dan-binding sites identified by both SELEX-
clos and SELEX-chip (data not shown). After search of 
GTTNATT consensus sequence in the entire E. coli 
genome using the coliBASE database program 
(http://xbase.bham.uk/), a total of 1869 Dan-binding 
sites on top strand and 1860 sites on bottom strand were 
predicted to exist in the E. coli MG1655 genome. Sequence 
logo analysis of all these sequences indicates a high-level 
conservation of this 6-bp consensus GTTNATT sequence 
(Figure 3D). </p>

<p>AFM imaging of Dan-DNA complexes </p>

<p>The binding mode of major E. coli nucleoid proteins has 
been studied in vitro by observing their DNA complexes 
immobilized on mica using atomic force microscopy 
(AFM) (33-38). The native nucleoid conformation of 
E. coli was also investigated successfully with AFM 
(39,40). AFM analysis provides some distinct advantages 
over bulk biochemical assays, particularly when studying 
DNA-protein interactions. For analysis of structural char-
acteristics of Dan-DNA interaction, we also employed 
AFM to directly visualize Dan-DNA complexes. The 
mode of Dan binding to DNA was studied using a 
circular pGRdan plasmid (10-bp dan-promoter assay 
vector) as a probe, which contains the dan-ttdA spacer 
region with Dan-binding activity in the promoter assay 
vector pGRP (26). By gel mobility shift assay, this 
sequence formed multiple bands of Dan-DNA complexes 
at moderate protein concentrations below the aggregation 
thresholds (Figure 2A). 
Dan-DNA complexes were observed with AFM in the 
presence of various concentrations of Dan (Figure 4A-C; 
also see Supplementary Figure 1). At low Dan concentra-
tions below the Dan/DNA molar ratio of 1/40, Dan 
bound to various positions along the entire plasmid 
DNA (Figure 4A). At high Dan concentrations &gt;1/10, 
the Dan-DNA complexes were converted into rod-like </p>

<p>Figure 3. Identification of the Dan box sequence. (A) Fluorescent-labeled SELEX segment (1.0 pmol) from the dan-ttdA spacer was incubated in the 
absence or presence of increasing concentrations of purified Dan (10, 20 and 40 pmol from left to right) and then subjected to DNase-I foot-printing 
assays. Lanes A, T, G and C represent the respective sequence ladders. (B) Four Dan-binding sites were identified on the dan-ttdA spacer sequence. 
(C) The Dan-box sequence GTTAAT was predicted after sequence comparison of four Dan-binding sites. Similar sequences were identified among a 
total of 688 Dan-binding fragments selected by Genomic SELEX. Using this Dan-box sequence, a total of about 1860 sites were predicted to be 
present in the entire E. coli genome. (D) Logo representation of Dan-binding site derived from sequences in in silico analysis. Logos were generated 
using weblogo (http://weblogo.berkeley.edu/). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3611 </p>

<p>Dan-DNA complexes fully covered with Dan molecules 
(Figure 4C). At intermediate Dan concentrations, both 
forms of Dan-DNA complexes, i.e. plasmid DNA with 
Dan associated at various positions (form-I) and DNA 
fully covered with Dan, were observed (form-II) 
(Figure 4B and Supplementary Figure 1; for the model 
Figure 8). 
A number of AFM images were subjected to a statistical 
analysis to identify the width, height and length of Dan-
DNA complexes. The histograms of width and length are 
shown in Figure 4D and E, respectively, while the histo-
gram of height is shown in Supplementary Figure 2. 
The analysis of AFM images clearly indicates the drastic 
conformational transitions of Dan-DNA complexes with 
the increase in the amount of associated Dan molecules. </p>

<p>Width distribution. The width of Dan-DNA complexes 
at the site of Dan binding slightly increased upon 
increase in Dan concentration (Figure 4D and 
Supplementary Figure 2). At low Dan concentrations 
below the Dan-to-DNA molar ratio of 1/40, the width 
of single Dan molecule on DNA was estimated to be 
27-32 nm. The width of peak position increased 1.5-
2-fold reaching to around 45 nm concomitant with the 
increase in Dan concentration. At the Dan/DNA input 
ratio above 1, Dan-DNA complexes with the width </p>

<p>larger than 50 nm were observed. This finding implies 
that Dan induces local DNA folding, giving the larger 
image of Dan-DNA dots at the site of Dan binding (for 
a model Figure 8). </p>

<p>Length distribution. The contour length of Dan-DNA 
complexes gradually decreased $2-fold from 2.5-2.7 mm 
to 0.8-1.2 mm concomitant with the increase in Dan 
concentration (Figure 4E), supporting the notion that 
Dan binding induces DNA compaction. Since the length 
fluctuation increased upon increase in Dan concentration, 
the images were classified into three groups, group-I 
(&lt;0.96 mm), group-II (between 0.96 and 2.08 mm) and 
group-III (2.08-3.20 mm), with respect to the contour 
length (Figures 4E and 5). Under the AFM imaging con-
dition employed, the average length of naked plasmid 
DNA was estimated to be 3.265 ± 0.201 mm. At low 
Dan concentrations, the proportion of group-III images 
dominated $80% (close to naked DNA) (Figure 5). 
Under the same conditions, a single molecule of Dan 
binds, on average, at various positions along each probe 
DNA (Figure 4A). The slight decrease in DNA length 
after binding Dan may be explained by local folding of 
DNA at the site of Dan binding. At intermediate Dan 
concentrations, a number of Dan molecules bind to the 
probe DNA and as a result, the proportion of shortest </p>

<p>Figure 4. AFM images of Dan-DNA complexes. (A-C) Dan-pGRdan DNA complexes were formed at input Dan/DNA weight ratios of 1/40 (A), 
1/4 (B) and 1/1 (C), respectively. AFM images were taken by the standard procedure as described in 'Materials and Methods' section. Black 
arrowheads show naked DNA region, while white arrowheads highlight DNA-bound Dan molecules. All images represent 500 Â 500 nm 
2 area and 
scale bars indicate 100 nm. (D) Width of DNA-bound Dan dots was measured for a number of Dan dots observed in each AFM image. (E) DNA 
contour length was measured for a number of Dan-DNA complexes in each AFM image. </p>



<p>group-I complexes became maximum (Figure 5) in agree-
ment with the interpretation that local folding takes place 
at each site of Dan binding. Accordingly, the longest 
group-III complexes disappeared upon further increase 
in Dan concentration, and instead the proportion of 
intermediate-sized group-II increased linearly (Figure 5). 
At the highest Dan concentration used, group-III 
complexes appeared again, presumably due to tail-to-head 
association of rod-like complexes fully covered with Dan 
proteins. </p>

<p>Height distribution. The height of naked DNA was 
around 0.5-0.6 nm, but upon binding of Dan, increased 
almost 10-fold to around 5 nm (Supplementary Figure 3). 
Thereafter, the height stayed rather constant around 5 nm 
up to the Dan concentrations analyzed, i.e. Dan/DNA 
ratio of 1/0.25 (Supplementary Figure 3F). </p>

<p>Role of Dan in transition of the nucleoid architecture </p>

<p>The protein composition of nucleoid has been studied in 
details for E. coli grown under laboratory culture condi-
tions (20,41), but Dan has never been identified as a major 
nucleoid component in steady-state growing cells under </p>

<p>the ordinary laboratory culture conditions. We then 
measured the intracellular concentration of Dan under 
various culture conditions by using the quantitative 
western blot analysis (5,21). When E. coli cells were 
grown under aerobic conditions in either rich (LB) or 
poor (M9-0.4% glucose) medium, the level of Dan was 
&lt;10% of the level of RNA polymerase a subunit 
(Figure 6A). Under the same culture conditions, the 
level of a subunit is $5000 molecules per genome equiva-
lent of DNA (3,41), while the major nucleoid proteins 
(HU, IHF and H-NS) in exponentially growing E. coli 
cells range from 5000 to 50 000 molecules per genome 
(5,20,41). Thus, Dan has never been identified as a struc-
tural component of the E. coli nucleoid because the 
intracellular level of Dan is &lt;1% of the major nucleoid 
proteins. 
Next, we measured the Dan level in E. coli cells grown 
under various stressful conditions. Under a hypoxic 
culture condition, the level of Dan was 1.5-to 2.0-fold 
higher than the RpoA level in both rich and poor media 
and from exponential growth to stationary phase 
(Figure 6B). On the basis of RpoA level ($5000 molecules 
per genome equivalent DNA), the level of Dan was 
estimated to range 7000-9000 molecules per genome. In 
late stationary phase, the Dan level was significantly 
higher in the poor medium than in the rich medium 
(Figure 5B, 96-144 h culture). This finding suggests that 
Dan plays a role in either maintenance of the nucleoid 
architecture and/or expression of the nucleoid function 
under the anaerobic conditions. 
We also examined the Dan level at both log and 
stationary phase and in not only standard LB medium 
but also 20% LB, 20% LB containing 0.2% glucose or 
0.2% arabinose, and DMEM medium (data not shown). 
The intracellular level of Dan was as close as that in 
aerobic culture in LB and M9-0.2% glucose medium 
(Figure 5A). Little induction of Dan was also observed 
at both low (4.5) and high (9.0) pH in M9-0.2% glucose, 
and at high osmolarity (3% NaCl in LB, and 20% poly-
ethylene glycol-6000 in LB) (data not shown). None of 
these culture conditions induced the synthesis of Dan 
protein, supporting the notion that Dan is specifically 
induced under anaerobic conditions. </p>

<p>Intracellular localization of Dan </p>

<p>Previously we analyzed the intracellular localization 
of nucleoid proteins by indirect immuno-fluorescent 
labeling, and classified them into two groups: one group 
is proteins including HU, IHF, H-NS and Dps uniformly 
distributed within the nucleoid; another group is proteins 
including Fis located at specific loci within the nucleoid 
(28). Consequently, we observed the intracellular distribu-
tion of Dan in E. coli grown under aerobic and hypoxic 
conditions. The intracellular level of Dan within the 
aerobically grown wild-type KP7600 cells is very low 
(Figure 6A), showing a faint staining with anti-Dan 
antibodies (Figure 7A, W1-W4). This faint staining was 
not detected in the mutant JD24074 lacking the dan gene 
(Figure 7A, M1-M4). </p>

<p>Figure 5. Contour length of Dan-DNA complexes. (A) Dan-pGRdan 
DNA complexes were formed at various input Dan/DNA ratios (1/40, 
1/20, 1/10, 1/4, 1/2, 1/1 and 1/0.25). Contour length of AFM images 
was measured for a number of complexes from each AFM image. The 
Dan-pGRdan complexes were classified into three groups based on the 
length: group-I, shorter than 960 nm; group-II, 960-2080 nm; and 
group-III, 2080-3200 nm. Data represent the mean value obtained 
from more than 100 samples (N &gt; 100). (B) The relative amounts of 
three groups of Dan-DNA complex were plotted against the input 
Dan/DNA ratios. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3613 </p>

<p>Under the hypoxic conditions, Dan was markedly 
induced (Figure 6B), and formed highly stained dots 
(Figure 7B, W1-W4; Figure 6D, W), indicated that Dan 
belongs to the group-II nucleoid proteins, including Fis, 
Rob (CbpB), CbpA and IciA, which show irregular distri-
bution within the nucleoid (28). The distribution pattern is 
mostly similar to that of Fis, a bifuctional nucleoid protein 
with the regulatory activity of a set of growth-related 
genes. In the highly induced wild-type E. coli cells under 
the hypoxic conditions, Dan is enriched near the interface 
between the nucleoid and cytoplasm (or the surface 
of nucleoid), suggesting that some of the over-produced 
Dan is enriched in the boundary between nucleoid and 
cytoplasm. In the dan mutant, no immuno-stained Dan 
dots were detected (Figure 7B, M1-M4; Figure 6D, M), 
indicating that Dan could not be detected by the immuno-
staining method using the same anti-Dan antibody. 
Considering all these results, we conclude that Dan is 
a nucleoid protein specific in cells growing under anaero-
bic conditions, and thus belongs to the family of nucleoid 
proteins that are produced only at specific growth phases 
or under specific growth conditions. As in the case of 
other major nucleoid proteins (3,5,36), Dan may have 
functional dichotomy, controlling both the structure and 
function of the nucleoid. In fact, Dan was proposed to 
regulate the neighboring ttdA-ttdB-ygiE operon (18). </p>

<p>Growth of Dan-defective E. coli mutant under anaerobic 
conditions </p>

<p>Dan was identified as a nucleoid protein in cells growing 
under hypoxic or anaerobic conditions, implying that Dan 
plays a role in cell survival under anaerobic conditions. </p>

<p>We constructed an E. coli mutant defective in the dan gene 
and compared the cell growth between wild-type and dan-
defective mutants. In M9-0.4% glucose medium, the 
growth rate of the mutant was about 10-20% slower 
than the rate of wild-type E. coli even under aerobic 
conditions. Under the anaerobic culture condition, both 
the growth rate and saturation level of the dan-defective 
mutant were approximately 50% lower than those of wild-
type control is also reduced (Supplementary Figure 4). 
The mutant cells tended to aggregate, forming sediments 
on the bottom of culture flask. These observations alto-
gether indicate that Dan is needed for full growth under 
anaerobic conditions. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The aim of this research was to identify target genes or 
promoters recognized by Dan, one of the uncharacterized 
putative transcription factors, renamed from YgiP and 
TtdR (18). A collection of DNA fragments isolated after 
the genomic SELEX screening included at least 688 differ-
ent sequences. Taken together with the gel shift and 
DNase-footprinting patterns, we concluded that Dan is 
a DNA-binding protein with recognition preference of 
GTTNATT sequence. </p>

<p>DNA-binding mode of Dan </p>

<p>Direct observation of nucleoid protein-DNA complexes 
with AFM has been successfully employed for analysis 
of protein-DNA complexes with E. coli H-NS (33,34), 
HU (35), Fis (36), Dps (37) as well as HU-like protein </p>

<p>Figure 6. Intracellular concentration of the Dan protein. (A1) Wild-type E. coli KP7600 was grown in both LB and M9-0.4% glucose media at 37 
C 
for various times under aerobic conditions. Cell lysates were prepared at various growth phases (lanes 1 and 7, log-phase at 0.3 OD 600 ; lanes 2 and 8, 
log-phase at 0.6 OD 600 ; lanes 3 and 9, late log-phase, 1.0 OD 600 ; lanes 4 and 10, 24-h stationary-phase; lane 5 and 11, 48-h stationary-phase; lanes 
6 and 12, 72-h stationary-phase) and subjected to quantitative western blots analysis against anti-Dan and anti-RpoA antibodies. (A2) The intensity 
of immuno-blot bands was measured with a LAS-1000 Plus Lumino-Image analyzer and <rs id="software-4" type="software">IMAGE GAUGE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Fuji Film</rs>). (B1) Wild-type E. coli 
KP7600 was grown in both LB and M9-0.4% glucose media at 37 
C for various times under hypoxic culture conditions. Cell lysates were prepared 
at various growth phases (lanes 1 and 7, log-phase at 0.3 OD 600 ; lanes 2 and 8, log-phase at 0.6 OD 600 ; lanes 3 and 9, late log-phase, 1.0 OD 600 ; lanes 
4 and 10, 24-h stationary-phase; lane 5 and 11, 48-h stationary-phase; lanes 6 and 12, 72-h stationary-phase) and subjected to western blots analysis 
against anti-Dan and anti-RpoA antibodies. (B2) The intensity of immuno-blot bands was measured with a LAS-1000 Plus Lumino-Image analyzer 
and <rs id="software-5" type="software">IMAGE GAUGE</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Fuji Film</rs>). </p>



<p>HCc3 of dianoflagellate (42), The pattern of DNA 
compaction by Dan is rather similar to that of HCc3 
from dianoflagellate, which lacks histones but retains 
permanently condensed chromosome. Both Dan and 
HCc3 proteins form bundle architectures for 
DNA compaction in protein concentration-dependent 
manner. </p>

<p>After statistical analysis of AFM images formed 
with increasing concentrations of Dan (Figure 4; 
Supplementary Figures 2 and 3), we propose a model of 
two forms of Dan-DNA complexes (Figure 8). At low 
Dan concentrations, Dan binds to various positions on 
plasmid DNA in non-specific manner (Form-I) and 
upon increase in the Dan concentration, more Dan </p>

<p>Figure 7. Intracellular localization of the Dan protein. Wild-type E. coli KP7600 and its dan mutant JD24074 were grown in M9-0.4% glucose 
media for 24 h at 37 
C under hypoxic conditions, and subjected to the indirect immuno-fluorescent microscopy according to the standard procedure 
described in 'Materials and Methods' section. (A) Wild-type strain KP7600 (W1-W4) and the dan mutant JD24074 (M1-M4) were grown 
under aerobic (A) or hypoxic (B) conditions. W1 and M1 represent; W2 and M2, Indirect immuno-blot against anti-Dan; W3 and M3, 
DAPI-staining; W4 and M4, merged images of DAPI and immuno-stained patterns. (C, D) The area shown by dotted square is expanded. 
Anti-Dan antibody was raised in rabbits using the purified Dan as an antigen. Cys3-labeled anti-rabbit IgG antibody was used as the secondary 
antibody. White bars indicate 5 mm. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3615 </p>

<p>molecules binds through protein-protein interactions, ulti-
mately forming the Dan-saturated complexes (Form-II) 
(Figure 8A). The height of DNA-bound Dan is rather 
constant independent of the protein concentrations, but 
the width increased with the increase in Dan concentra-
tion. This extension in the contour width may be due to 
local folding of DNA at the site of Dan binding as 
observed with AFM (Figure 8B). The length of Dan-
DNA form-I complexes is smaller than that of pGRdan 
plasmid (Figure 5), supporting our proposal that Dan 
plays a role in local folding of DNA, ultimately leading 
to DNA compaction. By adding excess Dan, the length of 
Dan-DNA rods increased again (Figure 5). One explana-
tion of the elongation of Dan-DNA complex rods at high 
Dan concentrations might be condensation of Dan-DNA 
rods by forming tail-to-head joining. </p>

<p>Physiological roles of Dan </p>

<p>With respect to the mode of DNA binding, Dan is appar-
ently similar to the major nucleoid proteins HU and IHF, 
but it has never been identified as a protein component of 
the isolated nucleoids from E. coli cells grown under lab-
oratory culture conditions (5,19,41). After testing various 
culture conditions, we found that Dan is highly expressed 
in cells grown under hypoxic or anaerobic conditions. 
In the E. coli nucleoid, two groups of the nucleoid 
protein exist, universal nucleoid proteins (UNP) that </p>

<p>always stay in the nucleoid; and growth condition-
specific nucleoid proteins (GNP) that appear only at 
specific growth phases or under specific growth conditions 
(5,41). For instance, Fis is synthesized preferentially 
in growing cells (19,43) and plays an essential role for 
maintenance of the nucleoid competent for transcription 
of the growth-related genes (3,5,41). Fis is one of the key 
global regulators of a number of genes for adaptation 
to external conditions such as the availability of oxygen 
and nutrients (22,23). On the other hand, Dps (DNA-
binding protein form starved cells) is the major nucleoid 
protein only in starved stationary-phase cells (6,20,24) 
and plays roles in protecting resting bacterial cells from 
environmental stresses such as high levels of toxic iron. 
During the transition of E. coli cells from exponential 
growth to stationary phase, marked changes take place 
on the cell shape and properties, allowing physical sepa-
ration of cells at different stages (44). Growth-coupled 
transformation of the E. coli nucleoid from exponential 
growth phase-specific fibrous structures to stationary 
phase-specific rod forms (41) depends on the association 
of Dps to the genome DNA. This group of nucleoid 
proteins may be stored on the nucleoid surface, forming 
dots as detected by indirect immuno-staining (28; also 
Figure 7). 
Since Dan is highly expressed under anaerobic and 
starved conditions (Figure 6B), it may play a role in </p>

<p>Figure 8. Model of Dan-induced DNA compaction. (A) On the bases of AFM image analysis of Dan-pGRdan DNA complexes formed at increasing 
concentrations of Dan (see Figure 1), we propose a model of the conformational change of plasmid DNA. At low Dan concentrations, Dan binds 
various positions on pGRdan in non-specific manner (Form I). Each Dan may play a role of seeding for further assembly of additional Dan 
molecules. At high Dan concentration, the increased number of Dan molecules bound to DNA strand, leading to extension of Dan oligomers along 
the DNA strand and ultimately covering the entire DNA surface (Form 2). Typical AFM images of form-I and form-II Dan-DNA complexes are 
shown on left (500 Â 500 nm 
2 area; scale bars, 100 nm). DNA strand is represented by a red line while Dan is represented by an orange rod. (B) A 
model of local conformation of DNA-bound Dan dots. Shortening of the contour length of pGRdan DNA might be due to local folding of DNA at 
the site of Dan binding (for details see text). </p>



<p>protection of the genome DNA from anaerobic stress. 
Dan contains two sets of Cys-Cys pair: one consisting 
of Cys 
170 and Cys 
193 , and another of Cys 
288 and Cys 
296 . 
In the case of OxyR transcription factor, the Cys-Cys pair 
is involved in redox sensing (45). This motif is also 
involved in metal chelating, suggesting a role of Dan in 
resistance of a metal, as does Dps against iron. Thus, the 
reversible disulfide bond formation may also be involved 
in structural and functional control of the Dan protein. 
A group of Gram-positive bacteria such as Bacillus subtilis 
form spores for protection of the genome and survival 
under harmful stresses. On the contrary, Gram-negative 
bacteria such as E. coli that do not form spores must 
harbor another system for survival under stressful condi-
tions. Dan and Dps play essential roles for protection of 
the genome during dormant stage. 
The major nucleoid proteins, HU, IHF, H-NS and Fis, 
in exponential growth phase E. coli under aerobic condi-
tions are all known to have functional dichotomy (5). 
Likewise, Dan may play dual roles, i.e. an architectural 
role and a global regulator of transcription. Non-coding 
sequence of the E. coli genome is less than 10%, 
but approximately two-third of the total number of 
Dan-binding sites is located within the intergenic spacer 
regions where regulatory signals of the genome functions 
such as transcription are located. Along this line, Dan may 
be involved in the regulation of genome transcription 
under anaerobic conditions. Such a biased localization 
of binding sequences was also observed for the major 
nucleoid proteins with functional dichotomy (46). 
Oshima and Biville (18) predicted that YgiP, here 
renamed to Dan, is involved in regulation of the 
adjacent ttdA-ttdB-ygiE operon. Interestingly, tartrate 
dehydratase encoded by ttdA-ttdB for uptake of anti-
oxidant tartrate is required for anaerobic growth on 
glycerol as a carbon source. Our findings extend this 
concept and further indicate that Dan is a bifunctional 
nucleoid protein, playing dual roles both in structuring 
the nucleoid under anaerobic growth conditions and in 
regulation of a set of genes needed for growth under 
anaerobic conditions. Along this line, besides the ttdA-
ttdB-ygiE operon, a set of genes must exist, which are 
induced in the presence of Dan altogether contribute to 
the E. coli survival under the anaerobic conditions such as 
within animals. </p>

<p>SUMMARY AND IMPLICATIONS </p>

<p>The bacterial genome is associated with a set of DNA-
binding architectural proteins, altogether forming 
the nucleoid. The major nucleoid proteins can be classified 
into two groups, UNP and GNP. The GNP-group 
proteins are interchangeable depending on the growth 
conditions or growth phases, including Fis in expo-
nentially growing cells in rich media and Dps in starved 
cells in stationary growth phase. Here we discovered Dan 
(DNA-binding protein under anaerobic conditions) as the 
third member of the GNP. The growth of mutants lacking 
Dan is retarded under anaerobic conditions. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Dr. Takenori Miki for providing the E. coli 
mutant lacking the dan gene, Naoki Kobayashi and 
Minami Naruse for the initial SELEX screening, and 
Ayako Kori and Kayoko Yamada for expression and puri-
fication of Dan, and Tomohiro Shimda, Hiroshi 
Ogasawara and Kaneyoshi Yamamoto for discussion. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Grants-in-Aid for (Scientific Research Priority Area 
17076016 and Scientific Research 18310133) from the 
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and 
Technology of Japan. Funding for open access charge: 
Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and 
Technology of Japan. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 11 3617 </p>





</text></tei>