<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2703206" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Carbonic anhydrase (CA) in the carotid body (CB) plays an important role in the maintenance of blood PO 2 and 
PCO 2 /pH homeostasis by regulating ventilation. It has been observed that the activity of CA in the rabbit CB is stronger 
under hypoxic conditions than under normoxic and hyperoxic conditions. In conditions of chronic hypoxia, the volume of 
the CB increases significantly because the number of type I and II cells increases. So far, the number of CA molecules in 
the CB has not been assessed. We develop a technique to quantify the number of CA molecules in the CB. The CBs were 
dissected out from 8 rats, immediately frozen with liquid nitrogen, pulverized and centrifuged. The proteins extracted 
from CB tissue were heat-denatured and separated by electrophoresis on a 12.5% denatured-polyacrylamide gel (SDS-
PAGE); a 31 kDa protein band was determined which reacted with a rabbit polyclonal antibody specific for rat CA-II in 
Western blot analysis. The immunoreactive 31 kDa CA-II protein was detected and quantified by laser scanner 
densitometry using 
125 I-rProtein A as a tracer. The mean 
125 I radioactivity emitted by the antibody bound CA-II was 31277 
cpm. This value corresponds to 4.57 ng CA-II. When compared with a rat CA-II calibration curve, an average of number 
of 3.54 x 10 
7 CA-II molecules were quantified for 1 g of whole CB tissue. This is a sensitive and accurate 
radioimmunoassay technique and may be useful in future studies on the role of CA-II in different pathophysiologic 
conditions. </p>

<p>The carotid body (CB), alternatively called "carotid 
glomus", is a small cluster of chemoreceptors and supporting 
cells located near the bifurcation of the carotid artery. The 
main function of the CB is to maintain homeostasis of blood 
oxygen partial pressure (PO 2 ), carbon dioxide partial 
pressure (PaCO 2 ), and acid-base balance by regulating 
ventilation. The chemoreceptors in the CB are innervated by 
a branch of the glossopharyngeal nerve, which projects to the 
respiratory center in the brainstem. A decrease in arterial 
PaO 2 or an increase in PaCO 2 and acidity, when detected by 
the chemoreceptors, stimulates the CB nerve and activates a 
respiratory reflex, which leads to an increase in ventilation 
so as to restore normal blood PO 2 and PCO 2 /pH. The rapid 
response of the CB to changes in PaCO 2 /pH depends on the 
function of carbonic anhydrase (CA), an enzyme found in 
many mammalian cells and tissues, including the CB [1,2]. 
CA catalyzes the hydration of CO 2 to facilitate the rapid </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Department of 
Anesthesiology, SUNY Upstate Medical University, Syracuse, New York, 
13210. USA;; E-mail: yangz@upstate.edu </p>

<p>restoration of normal intracellular pH in response to the 
changes in extracellular PaCO2. This chemical stimulus is 
coupled with a release of neurotransmitters from the CB that 
generates action potentials in the central nervous system's 
afferent nerve terminal. </p>

<p>CA was first identified in the CB by Lee and 
Mattenheimer in 1964 [3], and at least 14 distinct CA 
isozymes have been identified currently [4]. According to 
their cellular localizations, these isozymes have been 
characterized into four broad aubgroups, which, in turn 
consist of several isoforms: the cytosolic CAs (CA-I, CA-II, 
CA-III, CA-VII and CA XIII), mitochondrial CAs (CA-VA 
and CA-VB), secreted CAs (CA-VI) and membrane-
associated CAs (CA-IV, CA-IX, CA-XII, CA-XIV and CA-
XV) [5]. CA-II is found in the cytosol of cells in numerous 
organs. In the CB, CA-II is found in glomus or type I cells, 
as well as in the nerve bundles. It may also exist in vascular 
smooth muscle cells [6]. In the CB, the catalytic activity of 
CA-II isozyme is stronger than that of the other two 
isozymes expressed at this anatomical site, CA-I and CA-III. 
In the rabbit, it has been observed that the whole CA activity 
in the CB is stronger under hypoxic condition than under </p>



<p>Di Tano et al. </p>

<p>normoxic and hyperoxic conditions [7]. 
. However, it is still 
unknown whether the hypoxia-related increase in CA 
activity is due to increase in the specific activity of CA 
molecule or increase in the number of CA molecules, or both 
mechanisms. It would help us to better understand the role of 
CA in the maintenance of homeostasis if the number of CA 
molecules could be sensitively and accurately quantified. </p>

<p>This leads us to develop a new technique to 
quantitatively measure the numbers of CA molecules in the 
CB by using Western blot (WB), SDS-PAGE electrophoresis 
and indirect radioimmunoassay techniques. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>Tissue Collection </p>

<p>The proposed study was approved by Chieti University's 
Ethical Committee for the Use of Animals and was 
conducted in accordance with the guidelines established by 
the US National Institutes of Health. Eight pathogen-free 
female Wistar rats (Charles River Laboratories, Inc. 
Wilmington, MA) weighing between 250-300 gram were 
used. All rats were anesthetized by intraperitoneal injection 
of 40 mg/kg pentobarbital sodium. A longitudinal incision 
was made in the middle cervical skin, and the regions of the 
carotid bifurcation were surgically exposed. Then, a left 
thoracotomy was made to expose the heart. A modified 
Tyrode's 
solution 
(N-2-hydroxyethylpiperazine-N'-2-
ethanesulfonic acid/NaOH, pH 7.4) equilibrated at a given PO 2 
of 20 Torr at 37°C) was perfused through the heart, 
maintaining the temperature at 35.5 +/-0.5 °C, until the 
efferent perfusate was blood-free [1]. Then, CBs were 
quickly dissected out and placed on a Petri dish with ice cold 
Tyrode's solution to remove the surrounding fat and 
connective tissue under a binocular microscope. Residual 
blood cells were carefully removed by osmotic shock and 
washing with MilliQ H 2 O. Finally, the CBs were frozen with 
liquid nitrogen, until further process for CA-II assay. </p>

<p>Preparation and Determinations of Protein Extract </p>

<p>Frozen CB samples were pulverized using a micro-pestle 
of borosilicate glass, while kept in liquid nitrogen, and 
homogenized in ice-cold Laemmli buffer (2% sodium 
dodecyl sulphate, 10% glycerol, 5% 2-mercaptoethanol, 62.5 
mM Tris HCl, pH 6.8) [8] mixed with protease inhibitor 
cocktail at 1:100 (P8340 Sigma-Aldrich). CB weights were 
obtained by subtracting the weight of the homogenization 
buffer from the weight of the each CB homogenate. Then, 
the tissue homogenates were incubated at 4°C for 1 hour 
with gentle agitation and centrifuged at 12000 rpm for 20 
minutes, at 4°C. The protein concentration in the supernatant 
was determined using a BCA protein assay kit (Pierce 
Chemical, Rockford, IL), according to the enhanced protocol 
(linear range of detection of 5-250 g/ml of protein). </p>

<p>Antiserum </p>

<p>Rabbit antiserum to purified (SDS-denatured) rat CA-II 
isozyme was generously provided by Dr S.J. Dodgson 
(Department of Physiology, School of Medicine, University 
of Pennsylvania). Preparation of the immunogen, 
immunization 
regimen, 
serum 
preparation 
and 
characterization according to description of Dodgson and his 
colleagues [9, 10]. For Western blot analysis, the rabbit </p>

<p>polyclonal anti-CA II antibody reacted specifically with the 
rat and bovine isozyme CA-II [8]. Determination of standard 
curves and radioimmunoassay to assess maximum binding of 
CA-II in the presence of antibody excess were performed as 
described by Jeffery et al. [9]. </p>

<p>Purified Rat CA-II </p>

<p>Purified rat CA-II was kindly provided by Dr. Dodgson. 
Briefly, the rat CA-II isozyme was purified from rat 
hemolysate by affinity chromatography on sulfonamide 
columns [11] (ProntoSIL). </p>

<p>Amino acid analysis of the putative CA-II was performed 
by trypsin digestion and amino acid terminal sequence 
according to Linder et al. [12]. The CO 2 hydration activity of 
the 31 kDa protein from rat hemolysate was determined 
using a potentiometric assay as described by Wistrand and 
Wahlstrand [13]. </p>

<p>Electrophoretic Separation of CB Protein Extract and 
Identification of CA-II </p>

<p>Equal amounts of lysates containing 250 μg of CB 
cytoplasmic proteins extract (in 30 μl) were added with 5x 
running buffer (final concentration: 50 mM Tris-
hydrochloride pH 6.8, 10 mM dithiothreitol, 2% SDS, 10% 
glycerol, 0.001% bromophenol blue) heat-denatured (at 95°C 
for 5 min) and electrophoresed trough a 12.5% SDS-
polyacryl-amide gel. </p>

<p>For determination of the relative motilities (relative 
molecular weight [M r ]), marker polypeptides were also 
electrophoresed with protein samples, in a non contiguous 
lane to avoid contaminations, and blotted to nitrocellulose, 
namely: rabbit muscle phosphorylase b (97.4 kDa), bovine 
serum albumin (66.2 kDa), hen egg-white albumin (45 kDa), 
bovine carbonic anhydrase (31 kDa), soybean trypsin 
inhibitor (21.5 kDa), and hen egg white lysozyme (14.4 kDa) 
(Bio-Rad Laboratories, Richmond, CA). Densitometer 
tracings of the unstained polyacrylamide gel at 280 nm were 
obtained by a Photovolt Densitometer Model 520 A 
(Photovolt Corporation, New York, NY). The absolute 
integrated optical density of each band was analyzed by 
<rs id="software-0" type="software">GelPro analyzer</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">MediaCybernetics</rs>, Silver Spring, 
MD), which allowed to calculate the molecular weight of the 
unknown bands in the CB samples. </p>

<p>Electroblotting and Indirect Radioimmunoassay of CA-II </p>

<p>Following the electrophoresis, rat CB protein (from 250 
g tissue) was transferred from the gels on to Protran 
nitrocellulose membrane (0.1 μm, Scheiler &amp; Schuell, 
Dassel, Germany, Cat. No. 401180) by electroelution using a 
Transblot apparatus (Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) at 
100 mA (30V) overnight, at 4°C. For transfer, the gel was 
soaked in the blotting buffer (Tris/glycine, pH 7.4, 
containing 20% (v/v) methanol) and placed in a sandwich 
made up of filter paper soaked in 0.5% SDS, the gel, 
nitrocellulose membrane and filter paper soaked in the 
blotting buffer. The efficiency of electrotransfer of proteins 
was checked by staining the gels after transfer with 
Coomassie brilliant blue R-250 (ICN Biomedicals, Aurora, 
OH) and analyzing the gel by densitometry. </p>

<p>The nitrocellulose sheet was washed and first incubated 
overnight at 4°C with blocking buffer (3% bovine serum </p>

<p>Measurement of CA-II Molecule Number in Rat Carotid Body </p>

<p>The Open Respiratory Medicine Journal, 2009, Volume 3 69 </p>

<p>albumin Fraction V in NTE-NP40 (150 mM NaCl, 50 mM 
Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 2 mM EDTA, 0.1% Nonidet-P40; all 
chemicals from Sigma, St. Louis, MO); then the membranes 
were sealed in plastic bag containing a 1:100 dilution of 
rabbit anti-rat CA-II antiserum [8], for 3 h at room 
temperature, on a rocking platform. Thereafter, the 
membrane was washed three times with NTE-NP40 for 10 
min and then incubated in 2 ml of blocking buffer containing 
20 l 
125 I-rProtein A (2 x 10 
5 cpm; 50 ng; NEX-146 stock 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>cpm/μg; Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA) for 1 h at room 
temperature. Protein A reacts with most common IgG 
subclasses and is therefore suitable for direct 
autoradiographic detection of membrane-bound antibody in 
western blotting applications with low background binding 
and signal. After 1.5 h incubation, the unbound 
125 I-rProtein 
A was removed by washing with NTE-NP40 three times at 
37°C for 2 h. </p>

<p>The membranes were exposed for 3 days to a high-density 
phosphor imaging screen (Bio-Rad Laboratories), which 
captures latent images produced by the emissions of the </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I 
radioisotope. Upon laser-induced stimulation, light was 
emitted from the storage phosphor screen in proportion to the 
amount of radioactivity in the sample. Wide linear dynamic 
range (5 orders of magnitude) enables quantitation and 
visualization of both weak and strong signals in a single 
exposure. After digitalization of the results, the screen was 
exposed to extra-bright light of ImageEraser light box and 
reused. A laser scanning densitometer (GS-250 Molecular 
Imager System; Bio-Rad Laboratories, Hercules, CA) was 
used to convert the radioactive signals emitted by the 
immunoreactive areas on the phosphor screen into 
digital images for subsequent densitometric analysis by the 
software package <rs id="software-1" type="software">Phosphor Analyst</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Bio-Rad Laboratories</rs>, 
Hercules, CA) [14]. The radioactive signal emitted by 
unloaded parallel lanes in the same gel was considered as 
background. CA-II quantitation was performed 4 independent 
experiments. </p>

<p>Calibration Curve for CA-II Assay </p>

<p>Aliquots of purified rat CA-II (kindly provided by Dr 
Dodgson, University of Pennsylvania) were used to define a 
calibration curve for rat CB CA-II. Escalating known 
concentrations of purified CA-II isozyme (0.625, 1.25, 2.5, 
5, and 10 ng) were eletrophoresed, blotted and detected (as 
described in the previous paragraph) using various 
combinations of concentrations of anti-CA-II antibody and 
calibration curves were drawn and detected with 1:100 anti-
CA II antibody and 50 ng 
125 I-rProtein A (stock at 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>cpm/μg; NEX-146, Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA). 
Assay accuracy was evaluated from 3 replicas of the 
experiment. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The weight of each CB ranged from 50 to 80 μg (mean = 
63 g, S.D.= 10), for a total CB weight of 1015 μg as shown 
in Table 1. </p>

<p>The proteins were extracted from 16 CB (in 8 rats) and 
analyzed by SDS-PAGE electrophoresis to verify the 
presence of the CA-II isozyme. Under denaturing conditions, 
the electrophoresis revealed a broad spectrum of protein 
bands according to the different molecular weights. As </p>

<p>shown in Figs. (1, 2), a band at the position of 31 kDa 
molecular weight was revealed, which represents the CA-II 
isozyme, as evidenced by the standard control marker. This 
method enabled us to obtain quantitative data by measuring </p>

<p>Table 1. </p>

<p>Normal Wistar Rat 
Carotid Body Weights Weight </p>

<p>CB No. 
CB Weight ( g) </p>

<p>1° 
58 </p>

<p>1B 
61 </p>

<p>2° 
72 </p>

<p>2B 
76 </p>

<p>3° 
50 </p>

<p>3B 
54 </p>

<p>4° 
74 </p>

<p>4B 
61 </p>

<p>5° 
80 </p>

<p>5B 
71 </p>

<p>6° 
51 </p>

<p>6B 
55 </p>

<p>7° 
53 </p>

<p>7B 
59 </p>

<p>8° 
68 </p>

<p>8B 
72 </p>

<p>Total weight weight ( g) 
1015 </p>

<p>Mean 
63 </p>

<p>S.D. 
10 </p>

<p>the radioactivity emitted by the complex formed by </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I-
rProtein A+antibody+CA-II isozyme. Protein A binds to the 
Fc region of mammalian immunoglobulins, including rabbit 
IgG in a 1:1 molar ratio [15], in turn, IgG molecules owns two 
antigen binding sites. Therefore, the number of CA-II 
molecules bound to 
125 I-rProtein A could be calculated from 
the radioactivity detected by the imaging screen as shown in 
Fig. (2). By laser scanning densitometry we measured a mean 
of 31277 cpm emitted by the 31 KDa immunoreactive band, 
i.e. by 
125 I-rProtein A; such radioactivity value corresponds to 
3.1 ng 
125 I-rProtein A. Making the assumption that the molar 
ratio of the complex 
125 I-rProteinA-Antibody-CAII is 1:1:2, 
and considering the corresponding apparent molecular 
weights, 4.6 ng CA-II was estimated ([3.1 ng/42000 
Da]*31000 Da*2). Therefore, since 1 molecule mass equals 
31 kDa, that is 5.15 x 10 
-11 ng, the deduced number of CA-II 
molecules within the immunoreactive band is 4.6 ng /5.15 x 
10 
-11 ng = 8.84 x 10 
10 ; that is, approximately 3.54 x 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>molecules/μg CB tissue. </p>

<p>In order to verify the accuracy of our radioimmunoassay 
for CA-II in the rat CB, we defined also a calibration curve 
for CA-II as shown in Table 2 and Fig. (3). A linear 
correlation between protein amounts and detected </p>



<p>Di Tano et al. </p>

<p>radioactivity was found in the range 0.625-10 ng CA-II 
(R 
2 =0.9958). </p>

<p>A linear relationship between 
125 I radioactivity and the 
amount of standard CA-II was obtained using 1:100 dilution 
antibody dilution and 50 ng 
125 I-rProtein A (stock 10 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>cpm/μg; NEX-146, Perkin Elmer, Waltham, MA, USA). 
When control serum from non immune rabbit was used 
instead of the rabbit anti rat CA-II, no protein band was 
detected (data not shown). </p>

<p>Fig. (2). Western blot analysis of carbonic anhydrase II. The digital 
image of immunoreactive band from rat CB extract is at position of 
31 kDa, which represents the CA-II, as evidenced by the standard 
bovine carbonic anhydrase-II marker. CB: carotid body; M: 
standard control marker. </p>

<p>Table 2. </p>

<p>Calibration Curve </p>

<p>Purified CA-II (ng) 
125 I Radioactivity (cpm) </p>

<p>2.0 
13639 </p>

<p>3.5 
24145 </p>

<p>5.0 
31277 </p>

<p>6.5 
41437 </p>

<p>8.0 
46916 </p>

<p>As shown in Table 3, the weights of calculated CA-II 
according to calibration curve were very close to detected 
(observed) CA-II from the radioactivity data with an 
accuracy of 0.098. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The homeostasis of blood PO 2 and PCO 2 /pH is well 
maintained via the control of ventilation under normal 
physiological conditions. Either the decrease in arterial PO 2 
or the increase in PCO 2 and acidity stimulates the respiratory 
center of the brainstem resulting in an increase in ventilation 
and restoration of blood PO 2 and PCO 2 /pH. The 
chemoreceptors located in the CB play an important role in </p>

<p>Fig. (1). SDS-PAGE and Densitometry analysis of carbonic anhydrase II. The densitometric profile in upper figure shows the standard peak 
optical density and distance from the start point, which represents different molecular weight protein and corresponds to SDS-PAGE detected 
proteins. The standard CA-II protein is at the position 31.0 kDa band. Lower figure shows the peaks and distances of immunoreactive 
proteins extracted from carotid body obtained by SDS-PAGE. An immunoreactive protein peak showed at position 31 kDa confirms the 
presence of CA II in rat carotid body. Only the molecular weight region between 97.4 and 14.4 kDa is shown. </p>

<p>Measurement of CA-II Molecule Number in Rat Carotid Body </p>

<p>The Open Respiratory Medicine Journal, 2009, Volume 3 71 </p>

<p>rapid response to a change in blood PCO 2 and PaCO 2 /pH 
mainly mediated by the CA activity. </p>

<p>Table 3. </p>

<p>CA-II 
CB Sample 
(250 g) </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I 
(cpm) </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I Counts (ng) 
Calibration Curve 
(1) (ng) </p>

<p>1 
31017 
4.5 
4.9 </p>

<p>2 
31512 
4.5 
5.0 </p>

<p>3 
32133 
4.6 
5.1 </p>

<p>4 
32847 
4.7 
5.2 </p>

<p>Mean 
31877 
4.6 
5.1 </p>

<p>S.D. 
791 
0.096 
0.129 </p>

<p>Accuracy: (5.1-4.6)/5.1=0.098. 
(1) y = 5589.7x + 3534. </p>

<p>CA is an enzyme of 31 kDa, whose active site contains a 
zinc atom. CA catalyzes the reversible hydration-dehydration 
of CO 2 -HCO 3 
-. Since CA activity speeds up the reaction 
between CO 2 and H 2 O with formation of H 
+ and HCO 3 
-, this 
enzyme could be responsible for the sensitivity of the CB to 
CO 2 by mediating the changes in extracellular pH. CB is 
highly sensitive to sudden changes in arterial blood PCO 2 , as 
well as positive or negative variations of pH [15-17]. The 
presence of CA in the CB has brought about several 
investigators to speculate its physiologic role in homeostasis 
of PO 2 , PCO 2 /pH [18-20]. CA activity in CB cells is 
essential for the speed of chemotransduction and amplitude 
of the initial response to CO 2 and for its subsequent actions 
[12,14,17]. CA was first identified in the CB by Lee and </p>

<p>Mattenheimer in 1964 [3], and, to date, at least 14 CA 
isozymes have been identified by various methods [8,9,16-
18,21,22]. Yamamoto et al. [6] used immunoreactive assay 
and Western blot analysis to demonstrate the existence of 
CA isozymes I, II, and III in the rat CB. CA-II was mainly 
distributed in type I cells and nerve bundles. The results of 
the present study provide further evidence of CA-II in rat 
CB. Furthermore, the present study, at first time, provides 
the total number of CA-II molecules in rat CB. </p>

<p>Using a potentiometric method, Botré et al. identified at 
least two forms of CA in rabbit CB. One form of CA was 
found in the cytosol, and another was membrane-bound [16]. 
Later, Yamamoto et al. [19] identified CA isozymes I, II, and 
III. Porster et al. pointed out that CA-II activity is stronger 
than CA-I and CA-III [14]. Additionally, Foster et al. 
observed that CA-II mainly catalyses the CO 2 and H 2 O 
reaction to produce H 
+ and HCO </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>3 , which is critical to blood-
gas CO 2 exchange. CA-I and CA-III may play a supporting 
role in this process [23]. In the present study, in order to 
accurately identify and quantify CA in the CB of the rat, only 
CA-II was studied. We observed it with one-dimensional SDS 
PAGE electrophoresis and confirmed it with Western blot 
analysis using an anti-CA-II antibody and radio-labeled 
125 I. 
Additionally, we calculated the concentration of CA-II in CB 
tissue. Our study demonstrates that this technique provides a 
sensitive and accurate way to quantify the CA molecular 
numbers. </p>

<p>An early study showed that overall CA activity in rabbit 
CB was stronger under hypoxic conditions than under 
normal or hyperoxic conditions [6]. Under chronic hypoxia, 
the size of the CB increased significantly as a consequence 
of the increased number of type I and type II cells [23]. It is </p>

<p>y = 5589.7x + 3534 
R 
2 = 0.9908 </p>

<p>10000 </p>

<p>15000 </p>

<p>20000 </p>

<p>25000 </p>

<p>30000 </p>

<p>35000 </p>

<p>40000 </p>

<p>45000 </p>

<p>50000 </p>

<p>1.0 
2.0 
3.0 
4.0 
5.0 
6.0 
7.0 
8.0 
9.0 </p>

<p>CA-II (ng) </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>I radioactivity (cpm) </p>

<p>Fig. (3). Correlation between 
125 I radioactivity and amount of standard carbonic anhydrase. The figure shows a positive linear relationship 
between 
125 I radioactivity reading (cpm) and carbonic anhydrase weight ( g). Data are represented as mean value of three independent 
curves. </p>



<p>Di Tano et al. </p>

<p>unclear whether the increased activity of CA or the increased 
volume of the CB during chronic hypoxia is due to increased 
efficiency of CA or to an increase in the number of CA-
producing cells. The present study provides a useful 
technique that will enable us to measure CA concentrations 
directly and compare them among various conditions. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>The authors wish to thank Dr. Danielle Masursky, 
Department of Anesthesiology, Upstate Medical University 
for her editorial assistance. </p>



<p>Received: December 22, 2008 
Revised: March 11, 2009 
Accepted: March 16, 2009 </p>

<p>© Di Tano et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. 
This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>