<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2722173" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:03+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Regulation of the immune response to self-and foreign antigens is vitally important for 
limiting immune pathology associated with both infections and hypersensitivity condi-
tions. Control of autoimmune conditions can be reinforced by tolerance induction with 
peptide epitopes, but the mechanism is not currently understood. Repetitive intranasal 
administration of soluble peptide induces peripheral tolerance in myelin basic protein 
(MBP)-specific TCR transgenic mice. This is characterized by the presence of anergic, 
interleukin (IL)-10-secreting CD4 + T cells with regulatory function (IL-10 T reg cells). 
The differentiation pathway of peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells was investigated. CD4 + 
T cells became anergic after their second encounter with a high-affinity MBP peptide 
analogue. Loss of proliferative capacity correlated with a switch from the Th1-associated 
cytokines IL-2 and interferon (IFN)- to the regulatory cytokine IL-10. Nevertheless, 
IL-10 T reg cells retained the capacity to produce IFN- and concomitantly expressed 
T-bet, demonstrating their Th1 origin. IL-10 T reg cells suppressed dendritic cell matura-
tion, prevented Th1 cell differentiation, and thereby created a negative feedback loop for 
Th1-driven immune pathology. These findings demonstrate that Th1 responses can be self-
limiting in the context of peripheral tolerance to a self-antigen. </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Serum cytokine levels associated with tolerization 
Peripheral tolerance is induced in the Tg4 TCR transgenic 
mouse by repeated i.n. administration of antigenic peptide 
(Burkhart et al., 1999). This results in the generation of 
IL-10-secreting T reg cells capable of suppressing immune 
responses in vivo (Sundstedt et al., 2003). To investigate the dif-
ferentiation pathway of peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells, we 
first sought to determine changes in the serum cytokine profile 
over the course of tolerization in Tg4 Rag1 / mice. Serum 
concentrations of IL-2, IFN-, IL-17, IL-4, IL-5, and IL-10 
were assessed at 2 h after successive i.n. peptide administration 
(Fig. 1). The 2-h time point represents the peak of cytokine 
secretion, as determined previously (Sundstedt et al., 2003). As 
shown in Fig. 1, distinct patterns of serum cytokine levels 
emerged. The Th1 cytokines IL-2 and IFN- followed a similar 
profile, with the mean serum levels peaking after the second i.n. 
peptide treatment and decreasing to near background thereafter. 
IL-17 secretion was delayed relative to the Th1 cytokines with a 
peak after the fourth i.n. peptide administration. In marked con-
trast, the Th2 cytokines IL-4 and IL-5 were secreted at only very 
low levels over the entire course of i.n. peptide treatment. Secre-
tion of the immunoregulatory cytokine IL-10 peaked after the 
fifth i.n. peptide treatment, and although its level subsequently 
decreased, it remained above those of all other cytokines tested. 
These results suggest that repeated peptide administration leads </p>

<p>in both murine and human systems. However, in contrast to 
T helper cells, the differentiation of induced T reg cells 
remains poorly defined. 
i.n. administration of a soluble peptide induces periph-
eral tolerance in TCR transgenic (Tg4) mice specific for the 
acetylated N-terminal peptide Ac1-9 of murine myelin basic 
protein (MBP). Increasing the affinity of the peptide for 
I-A u greatly enhances the tolerogenicity of the peptide in 
the Tg4 mouse (Liu et al., 1995). After a single i.n. dose of 
a high-affinity analogue of the MBP epitope, Ac1-9[4Y], 
with a tyrosine substituting the lysine at position four, T cell 
deletion is only transient and incomplete (Burkhart et al., 
1999). Instead, Tg4 CD4 + T cells become anergic and 
exhibit a shift in cytokine secretion profile toward IL-10 after 
repeated i.n. treatment with peptide (Burkhart et al., 1999). 
Evidence for the generation of CD4 + T cells with a regula-
tory phenotype in this model stems from both in vitro and 
in vivo suppression assays (Sundstedt et al., 2003). Thus, i.n. 
treatment with MBP Ac1-9[4Y] induces active tolerance in 
the form of IL-10-secreting T reg cells (IL-10 T reg cells) 
rather than deletion. A role for IL-10 in suppression in vivo 
and in experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis pro-
tection was demonstrated by anti-IL-10 (Burkhart et al., 
1999) and anti-IL-10R (Sundstedt et al., 2003) antibody 
administration. IL-10 has important immunosuppressive 
and antiinflammatory effects on immune responses to both 
foreign and self-antigens (Moore et al., 2001) that are pri-
marily mediated by its inhibitory activities on the function 
of APCs (de Waal Malefyt et al., 1991). Although the role 
of IL-10 in suppression of experimental autoimmune en-
cephalomyelitis in the Tg4 model is not known, the effect 
of IL-10 on antigen presentation and inflammation is a 
likely mechanism. Naturally occurring FoxP3 + T reg cells 
form a part of the Tg4 CD4 + T cell repertoire and may rely 
on IL-10 to mediate suppression, as previously shown in 
other inflammatory settings (Asseman et al., 1999). Even so, 
peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells were found to be distinct 
in origin from naturally occurring T reg cells in that they do 
not express Foxp3 (Vieira et al., 2004). Genetic depletion of 
FoxP3 + T reg cells from the CD4 + T cell repertoire in the 
RAG-deficient Tg4 mouse gives rise to spontaneous EAE. 
However, the onset of disease can be prevented by repeti-
tive treatment with i.n. peptide, correlating with the gener-
ation of IL-10 T reg cells (Nicolson et al., 2006). 
It has been proposed that induced IL-10 T reg cells arise 
from fully differentiated T effector cells that have lost the ability 
to secrete their hallmark cytokines as a result of chronic antigenic 
stimulation (O'Garra et al., 2004). Alternatively, induced IL-10 
T reg cells could arise directly from naive precursors without a 
T effector phase. In this study, we investigate the ontogeny of 
induced IL-10 T reg cells generated by repeated i.n. peptide 
treatment. By following the differentiation pathway taken by 
CD4 + T cells over the course of tolerance induction, we dem-
onstrate that peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells are of Th1 origin 
and that IL-10 T reg cells complete the negative feedback loop 
of pathogenic Th1 responses in autoimmunity. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Changes in serum cytokine profile over the course of 
tolerance induction. Tg4 Rag1 / mice were bled before treatment and 
after each successive i.n. MBP Ac1-9[4Y] administration. Serum concen-
trations of IL-2, IL-10, IFN-, IL-17, IL-4, and IL-5 were measured by cyto-
metric bead assay. Results show the mean serum cytokine concentration 
of six to eight mice per treatment group on pooled data from two sepa-
rate experiments. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>below the detection level throughout the course of i.n. pep-
tide treatment, irrespective of the addition of rhIL-2 (not 
depicted). These results support the findings of previous 
studies showing that IL-2 reverses the anergy of peptide-
induced IL-10 T reg cells from mice treated with 10 doses 
of i.n. peptide without changing their cytokine secretion 
pattern (Anderson et al., 2005). </p>

<p>Peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells differentiate 
via the Th1 pathway 
To determine which cells were secreting IL-10, the propor-
tion of CD4 + T cells producing IL-2, IFN-, IL-17, and/or 
IL-10 at the single-cell level was determined by intracellular </p>

<p>to suppression of the Th1-associated cytokines, IL-2 and IFN-, 
produced as an early response to antigen in vivo, while sparing 
IL-10 production. </p>

<p>CD4 + T cell tolerance encompasses anergy, down-regulation 
of IFN-, and increased IL-10 production 
Although the serum cytokine profile provides an overall pic-
ture of the immune response to i.n. peptide administration, it 
does not allow discrimination of cytokine production by dif-
ferent cellular components of the immune system. We there-
fore investigated the contribution of CD4 + T cells to the 
aforementioned changes in serum cytokine concentrations. 
Tg4 CD4 + T cells were previously shown to respond to the 
first i.n. peptide treatment by initial proliferation and expan-
sion accompanied by a cytokine burst (Burkhart et al., 1999). 
Indeed, splenocytes from Tg4 Rag1 / mice, after successive 
i.n. MBP Ac1-9[4Y] treatments, showed a fourfold increase 
in their number at 2 h after the second treatment compared 
with untreated mice; the number of splenocytes decreased 
with subsequent i.n. peptide treatments (Fig. S1 A). The 
number of CD4 + T cells in the peptide-treated Tg4 Rag1 / 
spleens increased with a similar pattern to that of whole sple-
nocytes during the course of tolerance induction (Fig. S1 B). 
Given that CD4 + T cells from Tg4 mice treated repeatedly 
with i.n. peptide appear profoundly unresponsive (Sundstedt 
et al., 2003), we determined the kinetics of anergy induction 
as well as changes in the CD4 + T cell cytokine profile over 
the course of tolerization in Tg4 Rag1 / mice. As shown in 
Fig. 2 A, CD4 + T cells from mice either left untreated or 
treated once with i.n. peptide proliferated vigorously in 
response to antigen restimulation in vitro. However, the 
level of CD4 + T cell proliferation declined dramatically upon 
subsequent i.n. peptide treatments (Fig. 2 A). The addition of 
recombinant human IL-2 (rhIL-2) to the unresponsive CD4 + 
T cells led to recovery of proliferation (Fig. 2 B), thereby 
demonstrating that the cells were in a state of clonal anergy. 
Supernatants from the CD4 + T cell proliferation assays were 
collected and analyzed for IL-2, IFN-, IL-4 and IL-10 levels 
by ELISA. Fig. 2 C shows changes in CD4 + T cell cytokine 
secretion after successive i.n. peptide treatments. CD4 + T cells 
from mice either left untreated or treated once with i.n. pep-
tide secreted high levels of IL-2 and IFN- when restimu-
lated with antigen in vitro. Levels of both cytokines decreased 
dramatically after just two i.n. peptide treatments (Fig. 2 C, 
top and middle, respectively). IL-10 was only detected in 
cultures of CD4 + T cells from mice treated three times or 
more, i.e., after the decrease in IL-2 and IFN- secretion 
(Fig. 2 C, bottom). A similar inverse relationship between 
IL-2 and IL-10 was also observed in the analysis of serum 
cytokines (Fig. 1). Although the addition of rhIL-2 restored 
proliferation (Fig. 2 A), it did not have an effect on endoge-
nous IL-2 secretion and resulted in only a minor increase in 
IFN- production by CD4 + T cells isolated after the tenth 
i.n. peptide treatment (Fig. 2 D, top and middle, respectively). 
In contrast, the secretion of IL-10 was greatly augmented by 
the presence of rhIL-2 (Fig. 2 D, bottom). IL-4 remained </p>

<p>Figure 2. Anergy-associated down-regulation of Th1 cytokines 
and increase in IL-10 production by CD4 + T cells during tolerization. 
Splenic CD4 + T cells were positively selected from untreated or i.n. MBP 
Ac1-9[4Y]-treated Tg4 Rag1 / mice at 2 h after each peptide adminis-
tration. 5 × 10 4 CD4 + T cells per well were cultured with 100 µg/ml of 
MBP Ac1-9[4K] in the presence of 10 5 autologous irradiated CD4 
depleted splenocytes as APCs and, where indicated, 20 U/ml of rhIL-2. 
(A and B) Proliferative responses were measured at 72 h by 3 [H]thymidine 
incorporation in the absence or presence of rhIL-2. Results are depicted as 
the mean thymidine incorporation ± SEM. (C and D) Cytokine responses 
of CD4 + T cells from the cultures described in A and B were measured by 
ELISA at 24 h (IL-2) and 72 h (IFN- and IL-10) after in vitro restimulation 
in the absence or presence of rhIL-2. Results are depicted as the mean 
cytokine production in ng/ml of supernatant ± SEM. Data in each panel 
are representative of three individual experiments. </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>

<p>cytokine staining. Previous work had shown that the combi-
nation of PMA and ionomycin was a sufficiently potent stim-
ulus to induce synthesis of cytokines whose transcription had 
been inhibited through anergy induction (Macian et al., 
2002). We have taken advantage of this phenomenon to 
investigate the cytokine history of peptide-induced IL-10 
T reg cells. After antigenic stimulation in vitro, 41% of 
CD4 + T cells from untreated mice produced IL-2 (mean 
fluorescence intensity [MFI] = 1,383) or IFN- (MFI = 
7,670) when the cells were treated with PMA and ionomycin, 
whereas production of IL-17 and IL-10 was not induced 
(Fig. 3 A). A lower proportion of CD4 + T cells from mice 
treated with 10 doses of i.n. peptide produced IL-2 (MFI = 
727), whereas a similar percentage produced IFN- (MFI = 
5,808) upon restimulation with PMA and ionomycin, albeit 
with lower MFI. In addition, up to 19% of these CD4 + 
T cells produced IL-10. Interestingly, the majority of 
IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells coproduced IFN- (Fig. 3 B). 
A similar pattern of cytokine secretion was observed when 
peptide-induced T reg cells were activated in vivo with a 
dose of i.n. peptide 2 h before PMA and ionomycin stimula-
tion in vitro (unpublished data). No IL-17 was detected in 
CD4 + T cells from either untreated or peptide-treated mice 
(Fig. 3 A), suggesting that the IL-17 detected in serum (Fig. 1) 
originated from a different cellular source, such as NKT cells, 
monocytes, and/or granulocytes (Hue et al., 2006; Michel 
et al., 2007). These results demonstrate that the peptide-induced 
IL-10 T reg population is composed of cells capable of secreting 
IL-10 in response to antigen whose Th1 origin was revealed 
by the induction of IL-2 and IFN- synthesis after stimula-
tion with PMA and ionomycin. </p>

<p>Gene expression associated with the differentiation 
of peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells 
Further evidence in favor of the Th1 origin of peptide-
induced IL-10 T reg cells was provided by the analysis of 
lineage-determining transcription factors. Changes in the 
relative mRNA expression of Th1 and Th2 master regulators 
t-bet and gata-3 by CD4 + T cells were monitored by quantita-
tive real-time RT-PCR over the course of tolerization. As 
shown in Fig. 4 A, the relative expression of t-bet increased 
25-fold after the first i.n. peptide treatment and reached a 
plateau of 100-fold after the second i.n. peptide treatment. 
Conversely, the relative expression of gata-3 decreased after 
the first i.n. peptide treatment in comparison to the level seen 
in untreated mice (Fig. 4 B). In addition to T-bet, a previous </p>

<p>Figure 3. Th1 differentiation pathway of IL-10 T reg cells from 
tolerized mice. Tg4 Rag1 / mice were treated with a minimum of 10 i.n. 
doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. Splenic CD4 + T cells were positively selected </p>

<p>from either untreated or peptide-treated mice 3 d after the last treatment 
and cultured with 10 µg/ml of MBP Ac1-9[4K] in the presence of irradi-
ated B10.PL splenocytes as APCs. RhIL-2 (20 U/ml) was added on d 1 and 3 
to CD4 + T cell cultures from peptide-treated and untreated mice, 
respectively. (A and B) Intracellular cytokine staining for IL-2, IFN-, IL-17, 
and IL-10 was performed on d 7 of culture after additional restimulation 
with PMA and ionomycin. Depicted are density plots of V8 + T cells with 
cytokine gates based on isotype controls. Data are representative of at 
least three individual experiments. </p>



<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>with IL-10 secretion (Fig. 2, C and D). To assess T-bet expres-
sion by IL-10 T reg cells, we used a cytokine capture assay to 
enrich IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells. The IL-10-secreting 
fraction comprised CD25 high , CD69 high to CD69 intermediate , 
CD62L low , and CD44 high CD4 + T cells characteristic of acti-
vated, antigen-experienced CD4 + T cells (unpublished data). 
Essentially all IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells expressed T-bet, 
as also found in in vitro-differentiated Th1, but not Th2, </p>

<p>study revealed expression of the anergy-associated gene egr-2 
and the co-stimulatory molecule icos in Tg4 CD4 + T cells 
from i.n. peptide-treated mice (Anderson et al., 2006). Expres-
sion of Egr-2 was strikingly up-regulated after the second i.n. 
peptide administration (Fig. 4 C), correlating with reduced 
proliferation (Fig. 2 A). Up-regulation of icos was delayed by 
one i.n. peptide treatment relative to egr-2 and T-bet (Fig. 4 D). 
Instead, icos expression appeared to be more closely associated </p>

<p>Figure 4. Expression of genes associated with differentiation of IL-10 T reg cells. (A-D) Tg4 Rag1 / mice were treated with a minimum of 
10 i.n. doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. Total RNA was extracted from splenic CD4 + T cells positively selected from either untreated or peptide-treated mice at 2 h 
after each peptide treatment. The RNA was reverse transcribed and expression levels of the transcription factors t-bet, gata-3, egr-2, and the co-stimula-
tory molecule icos were determined by quantitative real-time PCR after normalization to 2-microglobulin expression. Results show the relative expres-
sion of the gene of interest from three accumulated experiments at each time point. (E) Enriched IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells from Tg4 mice treated with 
a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y] and in vitro-differentiated Th1 and Th2 cells were stained for surface V8 and intracellular T-bet (black 
line) or isotype control (gray line). The depicted density plot of IL-10-enriched CD4 + T cells is gated on V8 + T cells. The histogram of the IL-10 + cell frac-
tion is gated on V8 + IL-10 + cells and Th1/Th2 cell histograms on V8 + T cells. Data are representative of at least three individual experiments. 
(F) FACS-sorted IL-10 + , IL-10 + IFN- + , and IL-10 + IFN-  Tg4 CD4 + T cells were analyzed for T-bet expression by Western blot, with Th1 and naive 
(CD4 + CD62L + ) cells used as positive and negative controls for T-bet detection, respectively. Data are representative of two individual experiments. </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>

<p>(Fig. 5 C). Furthermore, increased levels of IFN-, but 
not IL-2, were sustained in sera from peptide-treated Tg4 
IL-10 / mice (Fig. S2). In contrast, IL-10, as opposed to 
IFN-, was detected in CD4 + T cell cultures from peptide-
treated, control Tg4 mice (Fig. 5, C and D). These results 
suggest that treatment with i.n. peptide in the absence of 
IL-10 results in priming rather than tolerance induction, 
demonstrating the role for IL-10 in negative feedback regu-
lation of Th1 responses. </p>

<p>Differentiation of peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells 
is independent of extrinsic IL-10 
Previous studies have shown that exogenous IL-10 encour-
ages differentiation of IL-10-secreting T reg cells in vitro 
(Groux et al., 1996). We used an adoptive transfer model to 
investigate whether differentiation of peptide-induced IL-10 
T reg cells depends on IL-10 secretion by other cells such as 
APCs. As shown in Fig. 6, transfer of Tg4 CD4 + T cells into 
B10.PL recipients followed by repeated peptide treatment led 
to the differentiation of IFN--producing Tg4 cells, up to 
8% of which coproduced IL-10 after activation with PMA 
and ionomycin. Transfer of Tg4 CD4 + T cells into IL-10-
deficient B10.PL recipient mice allowed the differentiation 
of a population of cells with a similar proportion coproducing 
IFN- and IL-10, as well as a markedly distinct population 
(22%) producing IL-10 only. Neither group of control mice </p>

<p>cells (Fig. 4 E). Because a significant proportion of IL-10-
secreting CD4 + T cells from mice treated with 10 doses of i.n. 
peptide coproduced IFN-, CD4 + T cells from peptide-treated 
mice were sorted into IL-10 + , IL-10 + IFN- + , and IL-10 + 
IFN-  CD4 + T cell fractions to reveal T-bet expression by 
each subset (Fig. 4 F). The Western blot results show T-bet 
protein expression in the sorted, IL-10-secreting T cell frac-
tion as a whole, and importantly, in both the IL-10 + IFN- + 
and IL-10 + IFN-  CD4 + T cell subpopulations. This clearly 
demonstrates that IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells retain T-bet 
expression despite losing the ability to secrete IFN-, thus 
further confirming their Th1 origin. </p>

<p>Negative feedback regulation of Th1 responses by IL-10 
T reg cells is dependent on IL-10 
The role of IL-10 in the induction of tolerance has been 
addressed by assessing the effect of repeated i.n. peptide 
treatment on CD4 + T cells from Tg4 IL-10 / mice. A 
comparison of in vitro proliferative responses from peptide-
treated Tg4 or Tg4 IL-10 / mice revealed that CD4 + 
T cells from both mouse strains were anergic (Fig. 5 A). This 
correlated with a marked reduction in IL-2 production, 
which is consistent with clonal anergy (Fig. 5 B). Despite 
their anergic state, however, CD4 + T cells from peptide-
treated Tg4 IL-10 / mice secreted IFN- at levels equiva-
lent or higher than CD4 + T cells from untreated Tg4 mice </p>

<p>Figure 5. Role of IL-10 in down-regulation of Th1 cytokines in tolerance. Tg4 and Tg4 IL-10 / mice were treated with a minimum of 10 i.n. 
doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. Splenic CD4 + T cells were positively selected from either untreated Tg4 or peptide-treated Tg4 and Tg4 IL-10 / mice 3 d after 
the last peptide treatment. 5 × 10 4 CD4 + T cells per well were cultured with 10 5 irradiated B10.PL splenocytes as APCs in the presence of a 10-fold 
titration of MBP Ac1-9[4K], ranging from 0.1 to 100 µg/ml. (A) Proliferative responses were measured at 72 h by 3 [H]thymidine incorporation. Results 
are depicted as the mean thymidine incorporation ± SEM. (B-D) Cytokine responses of CD4 + T cells from the above cultures were measured by ELISA 
at 24 h (IL-2) and 72 h (IFN- and IL-10) after in vitro restimulation. Results are expressed as the mean cytokine production in nanogram/milliliter of 
supernatant ± SEM. Data are representative of at least three individual experiments. </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>demonstrating maximal increase in MHC class II and the 
co-stimulatory molecules CD80 and CD86 at 24 h after 
stimulation (Moser et al., 1995). Expression of CD80 and 
CD86, as well as CD40, was further enhanced by co-culture 
of splenic DCs with CD4 + T cells from untreated Tg4 mice 
in the presence of antigen (Fig. 7 A). This was, however, 
suppressed by cognate interaction with IL-10 T reg cells 
from peptide-treated Tg4 mice. CD80 and CD86 expression 
was suppressed, and this suppression was largely reversed 
with anti-IL-10R, but not with isotype control antibody 
(Fig. 7 A, top and middle). The presence of anti-IL-10R anti-
body, however, fully reversed suppression of CD40 expres-
sion (Fig. 7 A, bottom). In contrast to CD4 + T cells from 
peptide-treated Tg4 mice, only very low level suppression of 
CD80, CD86, and CD40 expression was observed in splenic 
DCs co-cultured with CD4 + T cells from peptide-treated 
Tg4 IL-10 / mice (Fig. 7 A). 
IL-12 secretion is associated with DC maturation (Macatonia 
et al., 1995; Heufler et al., 1996) and optimal secretion of this 
cytokine is reported to depend on cognate interaction with 
activated T cells (Heufler et al., 1996; Koch et al., 1996; 
Winzler et al., 1997). IL-12 production by splenic DCs 
cultured with either naive CD4 + T cells or peptide-induced 
IL-10 T reg cells was investigated. Fig. 7 B shows the level of 
IL-12 secretion by splenic DCs after 24 h co-culture in vitro. 
In contrast to splenic DCs co-cultured with naive CD4 + 
T cells, which displayed increased IL-12 production in the 
presence of antigen, IL-12 production by splenic DCs co-
cultured with IL-10 T reg cells from peptide-treated Tg4 
mice was abrogated in an antigen-specific manner. Whereas 
IL-10 T reg cells alone induced a slight reduction in IL-12 
production, the addition of antigen almost completely inhib-
ited production of the cytokine. Importantly, this effect was 
shown to be specific for IL-10, as it was reversed in the pres-
ence of anti-IL-10R antibody, whereas the addition of a 
control antibody had no effect on IL-12 production. Fur-
thermore, CD4 + T cells from Tg4 IL-10 / mice did not 
suppress DC IL-12 secretion. 
To demonstrate the in vivo relevance of peptide-induced 
IL-10 T reg cell-DC interactions, the functional properties 
of DCs isolated from either naive Tg4 mice or mice ren-
dered tolerant by i.n. peptide treatment were further evalu-
ated. Compared with splenic DCs from naive mice, DCs 
from tolerant mice were less effective at inducing naive 
CD4 + T cell proliferation in vitro (Fig. 8 A). Furthermore, 
splenic DCs from peptide-treated mice failed to support 
secretion of Th1-associated cytokines by these cells (Fig. 8 B). 
The defective induction of IL-2 and IFN- secretion by 
naive CD4 + T cells in the co-cultures correlated with mark-
edly reduced IL-12 secretion (Fig. 8 B). The suppressive 
properties of IL-10 T reg cells therefore extend to DC func-
tion as well as phenotype. Collectively, our results reveal a 
classical negative feedback loop whereby chronically acti-
vated Th1 cells differentiate into IL-10 T reg cells capable 
of regulating DC function, thus preventing further genera-
tion of Th1 cells. </p>

<p>produced significant amounts of IL-10, and levels of IFN- 
were reduced (Fig. 6, bottom). IL-4 was not detected in 
either set of recipients (unpublished data). These data suggest 
that there is no requirement for IL-10 from non-T cells for 
the differentiation of IL-10 T reg cells. In fact, the ability of 
non-T cells to secrete IL-10 may limit the differentiation of 
IL-10 T reg cells. </p>

<p>Peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells suppress DC function 
in an IL-10-dependent manner 
Although IL-10 derived from non-T cells does not appear to 
be required for peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cell differentia-
tion, our previous studies showed that IL-10 plays an essen-
tial role in T cell regulatory activity (Burkhart et al., 1999; 
Sundstedt et al., 2003). A potential negative feedback func-
tion for IL-10 T reg cells was investigated by studying their 
effect on DC activity. IL-10 is known to inhibit the function 
of macrophages and DCs by inhibiting their expression of 
MHC class II and co-stimulatory molecules and their proin-
flammatory cytokine secretion (Moore et al., 2001). The 
direct effect of peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells on DC 
maturation was evaluated in vitro. As shown previously, 
splenic DCs undergo maturation when cultured in vitro, </p>

<p>Figure 6. Redundancy of non-T cell-derived IL-10 in IL-10 T reg 
cell differentiation. Negatively selected Tg4 CD4 + T cells at 2 × 10 7 per 
mouse were adoptively transferred into either B10.PL or B10.PL IL-10 / 
recipients. 7 d later, mice were treated with a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of 
MBP Ac1-9[4Y] at 3-4 d intervals or left untreated as controls. Spleens 
from peptide-treated recipient mice were collected 3 d after the last pep-
tide treatment. Tg4 CD4 + T cells were selected by culturing with 10 µg/ml 
of Ac1-9[4K] and rhIL-2 for 7 d and stained for surface V8 and intracel-
lular IFN- or IL-10 after additional restimulation with PMA and ionomy-
cin. The depicted contour plots are gated on V8 + T cells with quadrants 
based on isotype controls. Data are representative of at least three indi-
vidual experiments. </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>

<p>Figure 7. IL-10R signaling requirement for IL-10 T reg cell-mediated suppression of DC function. Tg4 and Tg4 IL-10 / mice were treated with 
a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. Splenic DCs were isolated from untreated B10.PL mouse spleens and 5 × 10 4 DCs were cultured either alone 
or with equal numbers of CD4 + T cells positively selected from untreated or peptide-treated Tg4 or Tg4 IL-10 / mice. 100 µg/ml of Ac1-9[4K] and/or </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>10 µg/ml of anti-IL-10R or isotype control antibody were added where indicated. (A) After 24 h, DCs were stained for surface CD11c, CD80, CD86, and 
CD40. Results are depicted histograms for each surface protein after gating on CD11c + cells, with x and y axes showing the fluorescence intensity and 
percentage of max, respectively. (B) Supernatant cultures described in A were analyzed for IL-12 by ELISA at 24 h after in vitro restimulation. Results are 
depicted as the mean IL-12 production in nanogram/milliliter of supernatant ± SEM. Data are representative of at least two individual experiments. </p>



<p>DISCUSSION 
Our results demonstrate how IL-10 T reg cells can be gener-
ated from Th1 precursors coincident with anergy induction 
under conditions involving repeated exposure to self-anti-
gen. Peptide-induced IL-10 T reg cells block DC function in 
an IL-10-dependent manner and thereby complete a nega-
tive feedback loop of Th1 responses. 
By studying the effect of chronic antigen exposure on a 
homogenous T cell population in RAG gene-deficient mice, 
we were able to exclude the influence of FoxP3 + T reg cells 
and B cells on IL-10 T reg cell generation (Dieckmann et al., 
2002; Fillatreau et al., 2002; Mauri et al., 2003). Although 
FoxP3 + T reg cells and IL-10-secreting B cells can promote </p>

<p>IL-10 T reg cell generation, the results of this and other stud-
ies (Levings et al., 2005; Nicolson et al., 2006) demonstrate 
that the differentiation of IL-10 T reg cells can occur inde-
pendently. The induction of IL-10 T reg cells in this model 
requires repeated administration of peptide antigen. This has 
allowed us to study the kinetics of IL-10 T reg cell genera-
tion. The initial response to soluble peptide was marked by 
secretion of the Th1 cytokines IL-2 and IFN-, followed by 
the induction of anergy and a switch to IL-10 secretion. The 
development of anergy after the second peptide administra-
tion is consistent with previous studies showing that naive 
cells are resistant to anergy induction (Hayashi et al., 1998; 
Andris et al., 2004). The induction of anergy in our study 
correlates with a high level of egr-2 expression throughout 
the course of i.n. peptide treatment. Egr-2 has previously been 
associated with T cell anergy (Harris et al., 2004; Safford et al., 
2005). Recent studies have shown that Egr-2 regulates the 
expression of the cell cycle inhibitor p21cip1 (Anderson 
et al., 2006) and that deletion of the Egr-2 gene in T cells 
leads to loss of homeostatic control (Zhu et al., 2008). In ad-
dition, anergized CD4 + T cells from i.n. peptide-treated Tg4 
mice have membrane proximal signaling defects affecting 
MAP kinase, PKC and calcium driven pathways (Anderson 
et al., 2006). As shown in other models of peripheral toler-
ance (Blackman et al., 1991; Macian et al., 2002), anergy can 
be overridden by treatment with agents capable of circum-
venting this membrane proximal block in signaling. Although 
exogenous IL-2 promotes proliferation of IL-10 T reg cells, 
it stimulates expression of Th1 cytokines to only a small 
degree. Macian et al. (2002) have shown that PMA and iono-
mycin treatment stimulated IFN- production in anergic 
Th1 cells. We adopted this approach to investigate which cyto-
kines were suppressed as a consequence of the anergy in-
duced by repetitive i.n. peptide administration. IL-10 T reg 
cells from i.n. peptide-treated mice produced IL-2 and IFN- 
at low or undetectable levels when stimulated with antigen. 
The same cells reexpressed IL-2 and IFN-, however, when 
stimulated with PMA and ionomycin. Interestingly, the ma-
jority of IL-10 T reg cells coproduce IFN- when activated 
with PMA and ionomycin, confirming their Th1 origin. The 
expression of Th1-associated transcription factor T-bet is 
maintained over the course of i.n. peptide treatment and can 
be detected in the IL-10-secreting fraction, both IFN- + and 
IFN-  , of CD4 + T cells from i.n. peptide-treated mice. Be-
cause of the lack of IFN- expression by IL-10 T reg cells 
upon antigen stimulation in vivo (Anderson et al., 2005), the 
observed T-bet expression is most likely regulated by an 
IFN- independent mechanism such as TCR activation. 
Although anergy abrogates the production of IL-2 and IFN-, 
it permits the production of IL-10. Recent evidence has </p>

<p>Figure 8. Role of IL-10 in negative feedback regulation of Th1 
responses. Tg4 mice were treated with a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of 
MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. Splenic DCs were isolated from both untreated and pep-
tide-treated Tg4 mice that were administered 100 µg of MBP Ac1-9[4Y] 
3 h previously. CD4 + T cells positively selected from untreated Tg4 mouse 
spleens were cultured at 5 × 10 4 per well in the presence of a twofold 
titration of irradiated DCs at a ratio ranging from 80:1 to 10:1 and 10 µg/ml 
of Ac1-9[4K]. (A) Proliferative responses were measured at 72 h by 
3 [H]thymidine incorporation. Results are depicted as the mean thymidine 
incorporation ± SEM. (B) Cytokine responses of CD4 + T cell from the 10:1 
cultures were measured by ELISA at 24 h (IL-2) and 72 h (IFN- and IL-12) 
after in vitro restimulation. Results are depicted as the mean cytokine 
production in ng/ml of supernatant ± SEM. Data are representative of two 
individual experiments. </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>

<p>role in protecting against excessive inflammation-associated 
pathology, suggesting an involvement in a negative feedback 
loop of Th1 responses. Here, we show for the first time that 
the generation of self-peptide-specific IL-10-secreting cells 
of Th1 origin depends primarily on repeated antigen en-
counter through the T cell receptor, and a similar mechanism 
could explain why such cells arise during the course of 
chronic infection. 
The IL-10 T reg cells generated by repeated peptide 
administration are immune suppressive in vitro, inhibit T cell 
activation in vivo (Sundstedt et al., 2003), and, most impor-
tantly, suppress inflammatory autoimmune disease of the 
CNS in an IL-10-dependent fashion (Burkhart et al., 1999; 
O'Neill, et al., 2006). As yet, however, the mechanism of 
suppression mediated by IL-10 T reg cells has not been de-
fined. In this study, IL-10 T reg cells were shown to suppress 
DC maturation and potently block IL-12 secretion. Our 
results support previous observations showing that IL-10 
inhibits APC-dependent induction of Th1 cells by APC-
derived IL-12 (Hino and Nariuchi, 1996; De Smedt et al., 
1997). As previously suggested, bidirectional signaling between 
T cells and APCs, primarily via CD40-CD40L interaction, 
optimizes secretion of IL-12 (Heufler et al., 1996; Koch 
et al., 1996; Winzler et al., 1997). This appears to be overrid-
den by IL-10 secretion in the case of IL-10 T reg cells. In-
deed, DCs isolated from peptide-treated mice are unable to 
support Th1 cell differentiation. This demonstrates that DCs 
subjected to IL-10 conditioning in vivo do not immediately 
revert to an immunostimulatory phenotype when isolated 
from IL-10 T reg cells. 
The influence of IL-10 T reg cells on DC function re-
veals a classical, negative feedback loop that has evolved to 
control the immune response to antigen and limit immune 
pathology. Repeated antigen encounter leads to anergy in-
duction among Th1 cells and a shift in cytokine production 
from IFN- to IL-10. The resulting IL-10 T reg cells sup-
press DC maturation and IL-12 secretion, resulting in cessa-
tion of the ongoing Th1 response. We propose that i.n. 
administration of peptide antigens mimics the course of 
chronic infection for the induction of IL-10 T reg cells. This 
important finding not only advances our understanding of 
the mechanisms involved in the generation of peripheral tol-
erance but also demonstrates how self-limitation of Th1 re-
sponses could be used by antigen-directed therapy in the 
treatment of autoimmune diseases. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Mice. All experimental mice were maintained under specific pathogen-free 
conditions. B10.PL (H2 u ) mice were originally obtained from The Jackson 
Laboratory. The Tg4 TCR transgenic mouse expressing V8.2 TCR spe-
cific for MBP Ac1-9 in the context of I-A u was described previously (Liu 
et al., 1995) and backcrossed for over 12 generations onto the B10.PL (H2 u ) 
background. In Tg4 TCR transgenic mice, 95-100% of all CD4 + T cells 
express V  8, whereas the diversity of V chains is unknown. Generation of 
Tg4 Rag1 / mice was also previously described (Nicolson et al., 2006). Tg4 
IL-10 / mice were generated by crossing Tg4 mice with a B10.129P2(B6)-
Il10 tmlCgn /J strain originally obtained from The Jackson Laboratory and bred </p>

<p>shown that induced T reg cells demonstrate enhanced activa-
tion of the p38-MAPKAP-K2/3 pathway (Ohkusu-Tsukada 
et al., 2004; Adler et al., 2007). The use of a p38-specific inhibi-
tor in T cells anergized in vivo by superantigen exposure 
allowed recovery of IL-2, but inhibited IL-10 secretion. The 
p38 pathway can, therefore, differentially regulate both the 
cell cycle and IL-10 transcription. 
The role of cytokines in the generation of IL-10 T reg 
cells is unknown. IL-2 and IL-12 have been reported to 
induce IL-10 expression in human T cells (Jeannin et al., 
1996). A role for IL-2 signaling in IL-10 expression is sup-
ported by the in vitro enhancement of IL-10 secretion after 
addition of IL-2 in this study. Although exogenous IL-2 may 
increase IL-10 secretion by permitting proliferation rather 
than directly promoting its production, there is evidence for 
IL-2-driven enhancement of IL-10 production by other 
T reg cell populations, including FoxP3 + T reg cells (Barthlott 
et al., 2005) and cytotoxic T reg cells (Tsuji-Takayama et al., 
2008). The role of IFN- in the generation of IL-10 T reg 
cells remains unclear. Generation of human IL-10-secreting 
Th1 cells was not affected by blocking antibodies against 
IFN- (Windhagen et al., 1996). Conversely, anti-IFN- 
suppressed the generation of IL-10 T reg cells after stimula-
tion with a B7H1-Ig fusion protein (Ding et al., 2006). Fur-
thermore, Shaw et al. (2006) proposed a model in which 
IFN- secretion by Th1 cells promotes IL-10 production 
among neighboring T cells by up-regulating ICOS-L expres-
sion on APCs. An association between IL-10 secretion and 
ICOS expression among CD4 + T cells has been shown pre-
viously (Lohning et al., 2003; Kohyama et al., 2004). As gen-
eration of IL-10 T reg cells by i.n. peptide administration is 
also associated with the induction of ICOS expression, such 
a mechanism could operate in our model. Although it is well 
established that growth of T cells in the presence of exoge-
nous IL-10 leads to the generation of IL-10-secreting regula-
tory (Tr1) cells (Roncarolo et al., 2006), the role of exogenous 
IL-10 in generation of IL-10-secreting cells of Th1 origin is 
debatable. We have noted that IL-10 secretion by non-T 
cells is not required for and appears to suppress the generation 
of such cells in the face of chronic antigen encounter. Fur-
thermore, IL-10 + IFN- + CD4 + T cells are generated during 
chronic infection with Toxoplasma gondii, even when IL-10 
signaling is blocked by anti-IL-10R (Jankovic et al., 2007). 
These data imply that the induction of IL-10 transcription in 
IL-10-secreting cells of Th1 origin is not dependent on 
exogenous IL-10. 
T cell populations secreting both IFN- and IL-10 are 
found in both mouse and man (Trinchieri, 2007; O'Garra 
and Vieira, 2007; Haringer et al., 2009) and have been impli-
cated in regulating the immune response to persistent infec-
tions with intracellular pathogens (Trinchieri, 2001; Anderson 
et al., 2007; Jankovic et al., 2007). The common feature of 
these infections is the development of a chronic stage of dis-
ease characterized by IL-10 secretion whereby low levels of 
the pathogen prevail and provide protection against subse-
quent reinfection. Under these circumstances, IL-10 plays a </p>

<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>Flow cytometry. Staining for intracellular cytokine expression was per-
formed using the CytoFix/CytoPerm Plus kit with GolgiStop (BD). CD4 + 
T cell cultures were restimulated with PMA and ionomycin (Sigma-Aldrich) 
at a final concentration of 5 ng/ml and 500 ng/ml of culture, respectively, 
for 3 h in the presence of GolgiStop. Cells were surface stained with anti-
V8 FITC, and intracellularly with anti-IL-2 APC, anti-IL-4 PE, anti-
IL-10 APC, anti-IL-17 PE, and anti-IFN- PE antibodies, or isotype 
controls (BD). For T-bet staining, enriched IL-10-secreting cells were 
stained with surface anti-V8 and intracellularly with either anti-T-bet 
Alexa Fluor 647 or mouse IgG1 isotype control antibody, using permeabili-
zation buffers recommended by the manufacturer (eBioscience). For DC 
co-stimulatory molecule staining, splenic DCs were cultured either alone or 
with an equal number of CD4 + T cells from naive or peptide-treated mice 
in the presence of 100 µg/ml of Ac1-9[4K] and, where indicated, with 
10 µg/ml of anti-IL-10R (clone 1B1.3a) or isotype control (BD) antibody. 
After 24 h, DCs were surface stained with anti-CD11c FITC, anti-CD40 
PE and biotinylated anti-CD80 and anti-CD86 (BD) paired with Streptavi-
din Tricolor (Invitrogen). Fluorescence intensity was measured on a FACS-
Calibur or BD LSR II flow cytometer (BD) and analyzed using <rs id="software-2" type="software">FlowJo</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Tree Star, Inc.</rs>.) FACS analysis software. </p>

<p>Western blot analysis. Total protein isolated from FACS-sorted IL-10 + , 
IL-10 + IFN- + , and IL-10 + IFN- -CD4 + T cells, naive (CD4 + CD62L + ) 
T cells and in vitro-differentiated Th1 cells with RIPA lysis and extraction 
buffer supplemented with protease inhibitor cocktail, PMSF, and sodium 
orthovanadate (Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc.) was run on a 12.5% SDS-
PAGE gel at 50,000 cells per lane. Protein was transferred onto Hybond C 
nitrocellulose blotting membrane (GE Healthcare), blocked for 1 h with 
PBS containing 0.1% Tween-20 and 5% BSA (Sigma-Aldrich), incubated 
overnight with 0.4 µg/ml anti-T-bet antibody (Santa Cruz Biotechnology) 
at 4°C, followed by 1 µg/ml rabbit anti-mouse IgG-HRP secondary anti-
body (Abcam) for 1 h at room temperature. The T-bet protein was detected 
with ECL (GE Healthcare) and Kodak Biomax films. </p>

<p>Quantitative real-time PCR. CD4 + T cells were isolated from untreated 
or peptide-treated mice by positive selection, and total RNA was extracted 
from the cell pellets with TRIzol according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions (Invitrogen). Extracted RNA was reverse transcribed with Superscript 
III RNase H  Reverse transcription (20 U/µl) and random primer oligonu-
cleotides (15 ng/µl; Invitrogen). A negative control for subsequent PCR 
reactions was provided by omitting Superscript III RTase from reactions. 
The sequences of primers (Sigma-Aldrich) were as follows: t-bet, 5-CTA-
AGCAAGGACGGCGAATG-3 (forward) and 5-CACCAAGACCA-
CATCCACAAA-3 (reverse); egr-2, 5-GGCGGGAGATGGCATGAT-3 
(forward) and 5-CCCATGTAGGTGAAGGTCTGGT-3 (reverse); icos, 
5-TGCAGGTGTGACCTCATAAGC-3 (forward) and 5-GCCCTGT-
GGTCCAGAAAATA-3 (reverse); gata-3, 5-ACCGGGTTCGGATG-
TAAGTC-3 (forward) and 5-GTTCACACACTCCCTGCCTTCT-3 
(reverse); and the housekeeping gene  2 -microglobulin, 5-GCTATC-
CAGAAAACCCCTCAA-3 (forward) and 5-CGGGTGGAACTGTGT-
TACGT-3 (reverse). For transcript quantitation, PCR reactions were 
performed in a final volume of 20 µl containing cDNA template, Platinum 
SYBR Green qPCR Supermix-UDG (Invitrogen), and forward/reverse 
primers (t-bet, egr-2, icos, and  2 -microglobulin concentrations 0.2 µM and gata-3 
0.1 µM). Fluorescent amplicons were derived after an initial denaturation 
step at 95°C for 2 min, 35 cycles of amplification of 30 s at 94°C, 30 s an-
nealing at 58°C (t-bet, egr-2, icos, and  2 -microglobulin) or 64°C (gata-3), 30 s 
extension at 72°C, and finally detected on an Opticon 2 DNA Engine (Bio-
Rad Laboratories). </p>

<p>Online supplemental material. Fig. S1 shows changes in the splenocyte 
and splenic CD4 + T cell numbers during the course of tolerance induction 
in the Tg4 Rag1 / mouse. Fig. S2 shows changes in the serum cytokine 
profile of Tg4 IL-10 / mice assessed at 2 h after successive i.n. peptide </p>

<p>to provide a homozygous Tg4 IL-10 / (H2 u ) line. The non-TCR trans-
genic IL-10 / (H2 u ) littermates, hereafter termed B10.PL IL-10 / mice, 
were bred for experimental controls. All experiments were approved by the 
UK Home Office and performed according to animal welfare codes directed 
by the University of Bristol ethical review committee. </p>

<p>Peptides. The acetylated N-terminal peptide Ac1-9[4K] (AcASQKRP-
SQR) of murine MBP and its higher MHC affinity analogue Ac1-9[4Y] 
(AcASQYRPSQR) with a tyrosine substituting the lysine at position four 
were synthesized on an AMS 422 multiple peptide synthesizer (Abimed 
Analyes-Technik) using standard fluorenyl methoxycarbonyl chemistry. </p>

<p>i.n. administration of MBP Ac1-9[4Y]. MBP Ac1-9[4Y] was adminis-
tered i.n. at 80 g of peptide in 20 ml of PBS under light isoflurane anesthe-
sia at 3-4-d intervals over a period of 5 wk. CD4 + T cells from mice treated 
with a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y] are referred to as IL-10 
T reg cells. </p>

<p>Adoptive transfer. For adoptive transfer, recipients received 2 × 10 7 CD4 + 
T cells by i.v. injection. </p>

<p>Cell separation. Purified CD4 + T cells were isolated from spleens by mag-
netic separation using mouse CD4 (L3T4) MicroBeads (positive selection), 
CD4 + T cell Isolation kit (negative selection), or CD4 + CD62L + T cell Isolation 
kit according to the manufacturer's instructions (Miltenyi Biotec). For T-bet 
flow cytometry staining of IL-10-secreting CD4 + T cells, splenocytes from 
mice treated with a minimum of 10 i.n. doses of MBP Ac1-9[4Y] were re-
stimulated with 10 µg/ml of MBP Ac1-9[4K] overnight with additional PMA 
and ionomycin stimulation for the last 3 h of culture. IL-10-secreting CD4 + 
T cells were enriched by IL-10 Secretion Assay according to the manufacturer's 
instructions (Miltenyi Biotec). For Western blot analysis, CD4 + T cells from 
peptide-treated mice activated with a dose of i.n. Ac1-9[4Y] for 2 h, followed 
by an additional 3 h PMA and ionomycin stimulation in vitro, were dually 
labeled for IL-10 and IFN- secretion before sorting on FACSVantage cell 
sorter (BD) into IL-10 + , IL-10 + IFN- + , and IL-10 + IFN-  T cell populations 
(gating on live [7AAD  ; BD] V8 + T cells). Splenic DCs were isolated from 
B10.PL spleens using collagenase IV (Worthington) and DNase I (Roche) fol-
lowed by magnetic separation with CD11c MicroBeads (Miltenyi Biotec). </p>

<p>T cell proliferation assays and cultures. CD4 + T cells were cultured at 
5 × 10 4 per well in complete RPMI medium in round-bottomed 96-well 
plates at 37°C and 5% CO 2 humidified atmosphere in the presence of 10 5 
per well autologous, irradiated CD4-depleted splenocytes or B10.PL spleno-
cytes as APCs. Alternatively, splenic DCs were used as APCs ranging from 
an 80:1 to a 10:1 ratio of CD4 + T cells to DCs. MBP Ac1-9[4K] ranging 
from 0.1 to 100 µg/ml and 20 U/ml of rhIL-2 were added to cultures where 
indicated. After 72 h, wells were pulsed with 0.5 µCi [ 3 H]thymidine over-
night and the incorporated radioactivity (corrected cpm) was measured on a 
liquid scintillation -counter (1450 Microbeta; Wallac). For Th1 and Th2 
cell lines, rmIL-12 (PeproTech) and anti-IL-4 antibody (clone 11B11; BD) 
or rmIL-4 (PeproTech) were added at a final concentration of 5 ng/ml and 
10 µg/ml or 10 ng/ml of culture, respectively. RhIL-2 was added at 20 U/ml 
on day 3 to both Th1 and Th2 cultures. </p>

<p>Cytokine protein levels. Multiplex Fluorescent Bead Immunoassay was 
used to measure the amount of IL-2, IL-4, IL-5, IL-10, IL-17, and IFN- in 
mouse serum samples according to the manufacturer's instructions (Bender 
MedSystems). Fluorescence intensity was measured on a FACSCanto flow 
cytometer (BD) and analyzed using the manufacturer's own software. Con-
ventional sandwich ELISA was performed according to the manufacturer's 
instructions to assay the quantity of IL-2, IL-4, IL-10, IFN- (paired anti-
bodies), and IL-12 (OptEIA kit; BD) in cell culture supernatants. Optical 
densities were measured at 450/595 nm on a SpectraMax 190 microplate 
reader and the amount of cytokines present quantified with standard curves 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">SoftMax</rs> Pro software (both from <rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs>). </p>



<p>ANTIGEN-INDUCED REGULATION OF THE TH1 RESPONSE | Gabryšová et al. </p>



<p>We thank Dr. S. Minaee for critical reading of this manuscript. We also thank Miss 
L.E.L. Falk and Mrs. J.D. Radcliffe for assistance with the breeding of mice. The 
authors wish to acknowledge the assistance of Dr. Andrew Herman for cell sorting 
at the University of Bristol Cellular and Molecular Medicine Flow Cytometry Facility. 
This work was supported by the Wellcome Trust and the MS Society of Great 
Britain and Northern Ireland. 
The authors have no conflicting financial interests. </p>

<p>Submitted: 23 September 2008 
Accepted: 22 June 2009 </p>



<p>JEM VOL. 206, August 3, 2009 </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>





</text></tei>