<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2742187" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T19:53+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The evolutionarily conserved serine/threonine protein kinase 
target of rapamycin (TOR), a central effector of cell growth, 
controls diverse metabolic outputs, including protein transla-
tion, mRNA transcription, cytoskeletal organization, autophagy, 
and cell death (Wullschleger et al., 2006). Although most of the 
research on TOR has focused on its growth-promoting activity, 
hyperactive TOR signaling can also enhance the induction of 
cell death by various signals (Shah et al., 2004; Ghosh et al., 
2006), and inhibition of TOR signaling can protect cells against 
proapoptotic insults (Ravikumar et al., 2006). The mechanisms 
underlying the relationship between TOR signaling and cell 
death are largely unknown, but the induction of autophagy that 
occurs when TOR activity is suppressed has been proposed to 
alleviate cellular toxicity in several neurodegenerative disease 
models (Rubinsztein et al., 2007; Mizushima et al., 2008). 
Although unchecked autophagy can sometimes lead to 
cell death (Berry and Baehrecke, 2007; Scott et al., 2007), in 
vivo autophagy is mainly involved in eliminating damaged </p>

<p>organelles or proteins with compromised function and can 
actually protect cells against death signals (Levine and Yuan, 
2005; Klionsky, 2007). In fact, disruption of basal autophagy 
by loss of function of either Atg5 or Atg7, genes which are 
necessary for autophagosome formation, can lead to neuro-
degeneration in otherwise normal neurons (Hara et al., 2006; 
Komatsu et al., 2006, 2007). 
The prosurvival function of autophagy might have a pro-
tective role against the development of several diseases, most 
notably neurodegenerative diseases involving formation of intra-
cellular aggregates (Rubinsztein et al., 2007). Many pathogenic 
aggregate-prone proteins, including polyglutamine (polyQ)-
expanded huntingtin are strongly dependent on autophagy for 
their degradation (Ravikumar et al., 2002; Berger et al., 2006; 
Shibata et al., 2006), and rapamycin attenuates accumulation 
of mutated huntingtin proteins and cell death in Huntington's 
disease (HD) models (Ravikumar et al., 2004; Shibata et al., 
2006). These findings have led to the proposition that autoph-
agy induction might be used to treat neurodegenerative dis-
eases such as HD (Ravikumar et al., 2002). However, it has not </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>arget of rapamycin (TOR) signaling is a regulator 
of cell growth. TOR activity can also enhance cell 
death, and the TOR inhibitor rapamycin protects 
cells against proapoptotic stimuli. Autophagy, which 
can protect against cell death, is negatively regulated 
by TOR, and disruption of autophagy by mutation of 
Atg5 or Atg7 can lead to neurodegeneration. However, 
the implied functional connection between TOR signal-
ing, autophagy, and cell death or degeneration has not 
been rigorously tested. Using the Drosophila melano-
gaster visual system, we show in this study that hyper-</p>

<p>activation of TOR leads to photoreceptor cell death in 
an age-and light-dependent manner and that this is 
because of TOR's ability to suppress autophagy. We 
also find that genetically inhibiting TOR or inducing 
autophagy suppresses cell death in Drosophila models 
of Huntington's disease and phospholipase C (norpA)-
mediated retinal degeneration. Thus, our data indicate 
that TOR induces cell death by suppressing autophagy 
and provide direct genetic evidence that autophagy 
alleviates cell death in several common types of neuro-
degenerative disease. </p>

<p>TOR­mediated autophagy regulates cell death 
in Drosophila neurodegenerative disease </p>

<p>Tao Wang, Uyen Lao, and Bruce A. Edgar </p>

<p>Basic Sciences Division, Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center, Seattle, WA 98109 </p>

<p>© 2009 Wang et al. This article is distributed under the terms of an Attribution-
Noncommercial-Share Alike-No Mirror Sites license for the first six months after the publica­ 
tion date (see http://www.jcb.org/misc/terms.shtml). After six months it is available under a 
Creative Commons License (Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported license, 
as described at http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by­nc­sa/3.0/). </p>

<p>T H E J O U R N A L O F C E L L B I O L O G Y </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 186 • NUMBER 5 • 2009 
704 </p>

<p>1999), we generated eyes homozygous for a tsc1 loss of function 
allele. Whereas young tsc1 29 mosaic flies (&lt;2 d old) had all seven 
rhabdomeres (Fig. 1 E), almost no rhabdomeres were present in 
the eyes of tsc1 29 mosaic flies after 20 d of light/dark cycling 
(Fig. 1, F and G). This is consistent with our observation that 
overexpressed Rheb led to photoreceptor cell degeneration. 
TOR kinase controls cell growth in part via two well-
characterized regulators of protein translation, the P70 ribosomal 
S6 kinase (S6K) and eukaryotic initiation factor 4E-binding 
protein (4EBP). Therefore, we considered the possibility that 
TOR might affect retinal degeneration by inducing cellular 
overgrowth, as promoted by S6K and 4EBP. Both GMR&gt;rheb 
flies and tsc1 29 mosaic flies had hypertrophic eyes (Fig. S1). To 
reduce this hypertrophy, we used UAS-rheb/+;ninaE-Gal4/+ 
(ninaE&gt;rheb) flies, which only expressed Rheb in adult R1-R6 
photoreceptors. The eyes of ninaE&gt;rheb flies were similar in 
size to controls (Fig. S1) and had normal retinal morphology 
when the flies were young (&lt;2 d old; Fig. 2 A). However, few 
R1-R6 rhabdomeres were detected in light-exposed 30-d-old 
ninaE&gt;rheb flies, although R7 rhabdomeres were generally 
present (Fig. 2, B and F). To further test the idea that cell over-
growth might be responsible for neuronal degeneration in the 
presence of excess TOR activity, we examined the ommatidial 
morphology of both GMR-Gal4/UAS-s6k TE (GMR&gt;s6k) flies, 
which overexpress constitutively active S6K, and thor 2 flies, 
which are mutant for 4EBP (Teleman et al., 2005). After 30 d of 
light/dark cycling, photoreceptors were preserved normally in 
both the GMR&gt;s6k flies and the thor 2 flies (Fig. 2, C, D, and F). 
This indicates that Rheb-induced photoreceptor cell death 
occurs independently of S6K and 4EBP and is most likely not 
a consequence of increased cell growth. 
Because TOR drives negative feedback regulation of 
phosphatidylinositol 3 kinase (PI3K) signaling via S6K and 
IRS1 (Harrington et al., 2004; Shah et al., 2004), increases in 
TOR activity can decrease the activity of AKT, which is a uni-
versal survival signal (Datta et al., 1999). To test whether Rheb 
induced neuronal cell death through PI3K/AKT, we over-
expressed PTEN (phosphatase and tensin homologue), a negative 
effector of PI3K signaling (Gao et al., 2000). No photoreceptor 
cell death was detected in 30-d-old GMR-Gal4/UAS-pten 
(GMR&gt;pten) flies exposed to light (Fig. 2, E and F), suggesting 
that a reduction of PI3K/AKT activity is probably not responsi-
ble for Rheb-induced photoreceptor cell death. 
In addition to growth signaling, TOR is important as a 
negative regulator of autophagy. To assess the possibility that 
TOR activation might cause neuronal degeneration by sup-
pressing autophagy, we first tested whether a mutation in atg7 
(Juhász et al., 2007), a gene required for autophagy, could in-
duce photoreceptor cell loss. Whereas all seven rhabdomeres 
were typically detected in the ommatidia of young (&lt;2 d old) 
atg7 d77 flies, after 20 d of light/dark cycling, few rhabdomeres 
were detected (Fig. 3, A-D). 
We reasoned that if retinal degeneration caused by hyper-
active TOR is caused by the suppression of autophagy, the 
reactivation of autophagy might suppress cell death caused 
by excessive TOR activity. Because overexpression of Atg1 
is sufficient to induce high levels of autophagy in Drosophila </p>

<p>been genetically tested whether inhibition of TOR activity can 
suppress neuronal cell death in disease models or whether such 
suppression is autophagy dependent. Furthermore, it is not yet 
clear whether controlling TOR pathway activity and autophagy 
might suppress neurodegenerative diseases not associated with 
protein aggregation. Moreover, TOR activity, autophagy, and 
neurodegenerative cell death have not been functionally linked 
by genetic tests, although their association has been discussed 
(Ravikumar et al., 2004). 
The Drosophila melanogaster visual system has proven 
to be a powerful genetic model for dissecting the molecular 
mechanisms underlying neurodegenerative diseases (Bilen 
and Bonini, 2005; Wang and Montell, 2007). Using the Dro-
sophila visual system, we found that hyperactivation of TOR 
signaling led to neuronal cell death in an age-and light-
dependent manner, and this was mediated via the suppression 
of autophagy. Either genetically inhibiting TOR or directly in-
ducing autophagy also suppressed cell death in HD model. We 
further demonstrate that autophagy induction also greatly sup-
pressed retinal degeneration associated with norpA mutations, 
possibly by mediating the turnover of toxic rhodopsin-arrestin 
complexes generated during phototransduction. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>TOR kinase is activated by the small GTPase Ras homologue 
enriched in brain protein (Rheb). The tuberous sclerosis com-
plex (TSC) gene products Tsc1 and Tsc2 form a GTPase-
activating protein that suppresses Rheb activity and thereby 
negatively regulates TOR kinase activity (Wullschleger et al., 
2006). Therefore, to activate the TOR pathway, we over-
expressed Rheb in Drosophila compound eyes using the Gal4/ 
upstream activator sequence (UAS) system. Using the trans-
gene combination UAS-rheb and glass multiple reporter 
(GMR)-Gal4 (an eye-specific Gal4 driver), we selectively over-
expressed Rheb in photoreceptor neurons. The Drosophila 
compound eye consists of 800 repetitive units, known as 
ommatidia, each of which includes seven photoreceptor cells 
in any given plane of a tangential section. Each photoreceptor 
cell contains a microvillar structure, the rhabdomere, which 
is the photoreception organelle and is centrally located in the 
ommatidium (Fig. 1 A, R). Control retinas (GMR-Gal4/+) had 
all seven photoreceptor cells in each ommatidium regardless 
of their age or whether or not they were maintained in the 
light or dark (Fig. 1, A and G). Young GMR-Gal4 UAS-rheb/+ 
(GMR&gt;rheb) flies had normal eye morphology, although the 
ommatidium size was much larger than in controls (Fig. S1). 
However, GMR&gt;rheb flies underwent an age-dependent loss 
of photoreceptor cells when cultured on a 12-h light/12-h dark 
cycle (Fig. 1, B, C, and G). Interestingly, GMR&gt;rheb flies 
cultured in continuous darkness lost photoreceptor cells more 
slowly than those exposed to light (Fig. 1, D and G), indicat-
ing that photoreceptor degeneration in the Rheb-overexpressing 
eyes was dependent on phototransduction. 
We also assayed photoreceptor cell death associated 
with mutation of tsc1, an essential negative regulator of Rheb. 
Using the ey-Gal4 UAS-FLP/hid system (Stowers and Schwarz, </p>

<p>705 
TOR REGULATES CELL DEATH THROUGH AUTOPHAGY • Wang et al. </p>

<p>autophagy in the eye by overexpression of Atg1 did not sup-
press TOR activity. Compared with ninaE&gt;rheb flies, which 
lost most major photoreceptor neurons after 30 d of light/ 
dark culture, ninaE&gt;rheb/ninaE-atg1 flies retained most of 
their photoreceptor cells (Fig. 3, E-H). Thus, these results 
show that enforced autophagy can suppress TOR-dependent 
neural degeneration, strongly supporting the idea that TOR-
induced neuronal cell death is a consequence of the inhibi-
tion of autophagy. </p>

<p>(Scott et al., 2007), we generated transgenic flies expressing 
tagged Atg1 under the control of the ninaE promoter (ninaE-
atg1). In ninaE-atg1 flies, high levels of Atg1-MYC protein 
were detected in the head, and autophagy, as assayed by 
LysoTracker staining, was strongly increased in photorecep-
tor cell bodies (Fig. S2). Although it has been hypothesized 
that autophagy can down-regulate TOR (Lee et al., 2007), we 
observed that S6K phosphorylation was not affected by the 
ninaE-atg1 transgene (Fig. S2), implying that induction of </p>

<p>Figure 1. Light-dependent photoreceptor degeneration in flies with overexpression of Rheb. (A-F) Examination of the morphology by transmission EM. 
Cross sections were obtained from 2 (D2)­ or 20­d­old (D20) flies maintained under 12­h light/12­h dark cycle, with the exception of the dark­reared 
GMR&gt;rheb. 20­d­old control (GMR-Gal4/+; A), 2­d­old GMR&gt;rheb (B), 20­d­old GMR&gt;rheb (C), 20­d­old GMR&gt;rheb reared in the dark (D), 2­d­old tsc1 29 
(E), and 20­d­old tsc1 29 (F) are shown. (G) The time course of retinal degeneration, as determined by examining the number of rhabdomeres per omma­ 
tidium. Error bars indicate SD. R, rhabdomere. Bar, 2 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 186 • NUMBER 5 • 2009 </p>

<p>
induction of autophagy by overexpressed ATG1 (ninaE-atg1) 
also suppressed photoreceptor cell death in the HQ120 flies 
(Fig. 4, A and D). These results support the idea that inducing 
autophagy by inhibiting TOR can suppress neurodegenerative 
diseases involving protein aggregates such as HD. 
To further explore the mechanisms underlying TOR's neural-
protective function, we used two well-known genetic models of 
retinal degeneration. NinaE RH27 encodes a dominant mutant in 
the major rhodopsin Rh1, which promotes retinal cell death 
through apoptosis (Davidson and Steller, 1998). NinaE RH27 flies 
started to lose photoreceptor cells after 25 d of 12-h light/12-h 
dark cycling (Fig. S3, A and D). Overexpression of TSC1 and 
TSC2 (GMR&gt;Tsc1/2) did not attenuate cell death in the 
NinaE RH27 flies and even had converse effects (Fig. S3, B and E). 
Moreover, direct induction of autophagy by overexpression 
of Atg1 did not suppress cell death caused by the dominant 
NinaE RH27 mutation (Fig. S3, C and F). Thus, the suppression of 
TOR activity or the induction of autophagy cannot protect cells 
from all kinds of cell death. In this case, caspase-dependent 
apoptosis appeared to be TOR independent. 
In a second neurodegeneration model, mutations in the 
Drosophila phospholipase C gene norpA result in light-dependent 
retinal degeneration triggered by the accumulation of cytosolic </p>

<p>It has been proposed that suppression of TOR activity and 
the induction of autophagy have protective roles toward many 
neurodegenerative diseases (Ravikumar et al., 2004). One such 
condition is HD, a devastating autosomal dominant neuro-
degenerative disease caused by polyQ-expanded huntingtin 
protein. In animal models of HD, the TOR inhibitor rapamycin 
can attenuate cell death (Ravikumar et al., 2004), and mutations 
in autophagy genes can enhance polyQ aggregation and neuro-
degeneration (Jia et al., 2007). However, whether the effects 
of TOR on polyQ-mediated neurodegeneration are caused by 
its regulation of autophagy has not been directly or genetically 
tested. On the contrary, one recent study using the Drosophila 
eye implicated S6K and PDK1 rather than autophagy as en-
hancers of polyQ-mediated neurodegeneration (Nelson et al., 
2005). To explore the role of TOR-dependent autophagy in 
HD, we expressed N-terminal fragments of human huntingtin 
that contain 120 glutamine residues in photoreceptor neurons 
(Jackson et al., 1998). The GMR-htt.Q120 flies (HQ120) mani-
fested strong age-dependent loss of rhabdomeres and photo-
receptor cells in an optical neutralization assay and by EM 
(Fig. 4, A and B). Inhibition of TOR by overexpression of TSC1 
and TSC2 (GMR&gt;Tsc1/2) largely suppressed neural degen-
eration caused by HQ120 (Fig. 4, A-C). Furthermore, direct </p>

<p>Figure 2. Rheb induced cell death independent of cell growth. (A-E) Examination of the morphology of 2­d­old (D2) ninaE&gt;rheb (A), 30­d­old (D30) 
ninaE&gt;rheb (B), 30­d­old GMR&gt;s6k (C), 30­d­old thor 2 (D), and 30­d­old GMR&gt;pten ommatidia (E) by transmission EM. Cross sections of retinas were 
obtained from 30­d­old flies kept under a 12­h light/12­h dark cycle except D2 ninaE&gt;rheb flies (A), which were &lt;2 d old. (F) Mean number of rhabdo­ 
meres per ommatidium from 30­d­old flies. Error bars indicate SD. Bar, 2 µm. </p>

<p>707 
TOR REGULATES CELL DEATH THROUGH AUTOPHAGY • Wang et al. </p>

<p>rhodopsin-arrestin complexes (Alloway et al., 2000). Neuronal 
degeneration in the norpA model cannot be suppressed by the 
inhibitors of apoptosis and thus seems not to be mediated by 
apoptosis (Hsu et al., 2004). We found that norpA P24 mutants 
underwent rapid retinal degeneration, such that the animals had 
detectable loss of photoreceptors cells by 4 d and were almost 
devoid of photoreceptor cells by day 10 (Fig. 5, A and B). The 
norpA-mediated degeneration was significantly suppressed by 
overexpression of either TSC1 and TSC2 or Atg1 in photo-
receptor cells (Fig. 5, A, C, and D). Thus, the suppression of 
autophagy by TOR activity is a critical component in norpA-
mediated neurodegeneration. 
Stable rhodopsin-arrestin complexes are known to trig-
ger the cell death that occurs in the norpA mutants (Alloway 
et al., 2000), and therefore, we considered whether autophagy 
might suppress norpA-mediated cell death by clearing these 
toxic complexes. To test this, we assayed the percentage of 
major arrestin (Arr2) bound to rhodopsin using a coprecipitation 
assay. We found that exposure to light for 1 h caused 45% of 
the Arr2 to bind to rhodopsin in wild-type eyes, whereas &gt;60% 
was bound in norpA mutants (Fig. 5, E and F). However, in 
both norpA P24 ;ninaE-atg1 and norpA P24 ;GMR&gt;Tsc1/2 flies, the 
fraction of rhodopsin-bound Arr2 was decreased back nearly to 
the wild-type level without changing the overall rhodopsin/Arr2 
ratio (Fig. 5, E and F). These data illustrate that autophagy can 
help eliminate rhodopsin-arrestin complexes and thus reduce 
their toxicity in the norpA model of retinal degeneration. 
Overall, our results indicate that constraining TOR activity 
is crucial for neuronal survival, especially in highly active neu-
rons, and that this is caused by, in large part, TOR's function as 
a suppressor of autophagy. Importantly, we found that the direct 
induction of autophagy by overexpression of Atg1 largely sup-
pressed Rheb-induced photoreceptor cell death as well as photo-
receptor neural degeneration in Drosophila models of HD and 
phospholipase C deletion. Our results support the idea that the 
continuous clearance of cytosolic components through autoph-
agy is important for preventing the accumulation of toxic proteins 
that would otherwise disrupt neural function and ultimately lead 
to neurodegeneration. 
Autophagy has been shown to be important in the clear-
ance of cellular aggregates in several neurodegenerative disease 
models (Ravikumar et al., 2002; Webb et al., 2003; Iwata et al., 
2005). Moreover, recent studies have suggested that the TOR 
inhibitor rapamycin can attenuate cell death in several intra-
cytosolic proteinopathies and that this might occur through the 
up-regulation of autophagy (Ravikumar et al., 2004; Berger 
et al., 2006). Thus, our genetic demonstration that suppression 
of TOR or activation of autophagy can cell-autonomously sup-
press neurodegeneration in a polyQ aggregation model provides 
direct genetic evidence to support this prevailing view of neuro-
degenerative diseases. Interestingly, heat shock proteins such 
as Hsp70 and Hsp40, which function as chaperones to prevent 
protein aggregation, as well as several components of the ubiq-
uitin proteasome can suppress polyQ-induced degeneration 
(Warrick et al., 1999; Fernandez-Funez et al., 2000; Kazemi-
Esfarjani and Benzer, 2000). Like autophagy, both pathways have 
key roles in protein quality control, emphasizing the significant </p>

<p>Figure 3. Rheb/TOR signaling drives photoreceptor cell death by sup-
pressing autophagy. (A-C) Transmission EM images of cross sections from 
wild type (w 1118 ; A), atg7 d77 (B), and atg7 d77 dark reared (C). The sec­ 
tions were obtained from 30­d­old flies maintained under 12­h light/12­h 
dark cycle, with the exception of dark­reared atg7 d77 (C). (D) Histogram 
of the mean number of rhabdomeres per ommatidium from 30­d­old flies. 
(E-G) Retinal morphology of ninaE&gt;rheb (E), ninaE-atg1 (F), and 
ninaE&gt;rheb/ninaE-atg1 (G). The sections were obtained from 30­d­old 
flies maintained under 12­h light/12­h dark cycle. (H) Histogram of the 
mean number of rhabdomeres per ommatidium from 30­d­old flies. (D and H) 
Error bars indicate SD. Bar, 2 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 186 • NUMBER 5 • 2009 </p>

<p>
that arise via unchecked cell growth are commonly believed to be 
the principal adverse effect in TSC disease, cell death has been de-
tected inside these tumors (Maldonado et al., 2003; Zeng et al., 
2007). Thus, an alternative explanation for some of the symptoms 
of TSC such as seizures is that they arise as a consequence of 
neural cell death and neurodegeneration. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Drosophila stocks 
ninaE-Gal4, GMR-Gal4, and GMR-htt.Q120 flies were obtained from the 
Bloomington Stock Center. UAS-rheb, tsc1 29 , UAS-Tsc1, UAS-Tsc2, UAS-
pten, UAS-s6k, and thor 2 flies were previously described (Gao et al., 
2000; Gao and Pan, 2001; Saucedo et al., 2003; Teleman et al., 2005; 
Scott et al., 2007). H. Steller (The Rockefeller University, New York, NY) 
provided NinaE RH27 flies. C. Montell (The Johns Hopkins University, Balti­ 
more, MD) provided norpA P24 flies. T. Neufeld (University of Minnesota, 
Minneapolis, MN) provided atg7 d77 flies. </p>

<p>Genotypes 
Fig. 1 shows GMR-Gal4/+, GMR&gt;rheb, and tsc1 29 (ey-Gal4 UAS-FLP;P 
[neoFRT]82B GMR-hid/P[neoFRT]82B tsc1 29 ). Fig. 2 shows ninaE&gt;rheb, 
GMR&gt;pten, thor 2 , and GMR&gt;s6k. Fig. 3 shows atg7 d77 , ninaE-atg1 (+;ninaE-
atg1/+;ninaE-atg1/+), and ninaE&gt;rheb/ninaE-atg1 (UAS-rheb/ninaE-
atg1;ninaE-Gal4/ninaE-atg1). Fig. 4 shows HQ120 (GMR-HQ120), 
HQ120;GMR&gt;Tsc1/2 (GMR-Gal4/GMR-HQ120;UAS-Tsc1 UAS-Tsc2/+), </p>

<p>role of protein quality control in protecting cells from toxic 
aggregates such as those formed from polyQ aggregation. 
However, many neural cell death models and most retinal 
degeneration diseases are not known to involve the formation of 
protein aggregates. Thus, one outstanding question was whether 
TOR signaling and autophagy could modulate the cellular tox-
icity of unaggregated proteins. The toxic rhodopsin-arrestin 
complexes that form as a result of phototransduction, promot-
ing retinal degeneration in norpA mutants, provided a good test 
case because rhodopsin-arrestin complexes are not detected in 
aggregates. We found that either TOR-dependent or -independent 
autophagy could suppress the accumulation of rhodopsin-arrestin 
in norpA mutants and that either mode of autophagy activation 
could alleviate retinal degeneration. We believe that these data 
support a model in which autophagy can suppress neural de-
generation by removing toxic soluble proteins as well as toxic 
protein aggregates. Therefore, therapy involving the inhibition 
of TOR or other means for inducing autophagy might be ap-
plied to neurological diseases rather generally. 
TSC disease is a heritable disease caused by the hyperacti-
vation of TOR signaling that occurs after somatic loss of hetero-
zygosity in either Tsc2 or Tsc1. Although benign neural tumors </p>

<p>Figure 4. Neuronal degeneration in HQ120 flies was suppressed by overexpression of TSC1/2 or Atg1. (A) Time course of photoreceptor degeneration 
was determined by the optical neutralization technique. The flies were reared under a 12­h light/12­h dark cycle. Each data point was based on the 
examination of ≥60 ommatidia from at least four flies. Error bars indicate SD. (B-D) Retinal morphology of 10­d­old flies examined by transmission EM. 
HQ120 (B), HQ120;GMR&gt;Tsc1/2 (C), and HQ120;ninaE-atg1 (D) are shown. Bar, 2 µm. </p>

<p>709 
TOR REGULATES CELL DEATH THROUGH AUTOPHAGY • Wang et al. </p>

<p>in the photoreceptor cells, a GFP tag was added to the C terminus of Rh1 
and subsequently subcloned into the pcNX vector. The constructs were in­ 
jected into w 1118 embryos, and transformants were identified on the basis 
of eye pigmentation. </p>

<p>EM 
Adult fly heads were dissected and fixed in a solution with 2% paraformal­ 
dehyde, 4% glutaraldehyde, and 0.1 M phosphate, pH 7.4, for 12 h at </p>

<p>and HQ120;ninaE-atg1 (GMR-HQ120/ninaE-atg1;ninaE-atg1). Fig. 5 shows 
norpA P24 , norpA P24 ;GMR&gt;Tsc1/2 (norpA P24 ;GMR-Gal4/+;UAS-Tsc1 UAS-
Tsc2/+), and norpA P24 ;ninaE-atg1 (norpA P24 ;ninaE-atg1/+;ninaE-atg1/+). </p>

<p>Generation of transgenic Drosophila 
To express MYC­tagged ATG1 under control of the ninaE (Rh1) promoter, 
the full­length atg1 cDNA with a C­terminal MYC tag was subcloned into 
the pcNX vector (Wang and Montell, 2006). To express GFP­labeled Rh1 </p>

<p>Figure 5. Suppression of retinal degeneration in norpA flies by overexpression of either TSC1/2 or Atg1. (A) The time course of retinal degeneration, as deter­ 
mined by optical neutralization. (B-D) Examination of retinal morphology by transmission EM. norpA P24 (B), norpA P24 ;GMR&gt;Tsc1/2 (C), and norpA P24 ;ninaE-
atg1 (D) are shown. 10­d­old flies under light/dark cycle were used. (E and F) Stable rhodopsin-arrestin complexes in norpA P24 flies were reduced by 
overexpression of either TSC1/2 or Atg1. (E) Western blot of fractions from fly heads exposed to light for 1 h. Pellet (P) and supernatant (S) fractions are 
indicated. Dark­reared flies &lt;2 d old were used. (F) Histogram quantifying the percent of Arr2 bound to rhodopsin after treatment with 1 h of light. The asterisk 
indicates a statistically significant difference relative to wild type (Student's unpaired t test; *, P &lt; 0.05). (A and F) Error bars indicate SD. Bar, 2 µm. </p>

<p>JCB • VOLUME 186 • NUMBER 5 • 2009 </p>



<p>
4°C and in a solution with 1% osmium tetroxide and 0.1 M phosphate, 
pH 7.4, for 2 h at 4°C. The tissues were then dehydrated in a series of ethanol 
solutions (10­min washes in 10, 25, 50, 75, and 100% ethanol) and em­ 
bedded in LR white resin. Thin sections (85 nm) were prepared at a depth 
of 30-40 µm and were examined by transmission EM using a transmission 
electron microscope (model 1230; JEOL) at room temperature. The images 
were acquired using a bottom­mount charge­coupled device camera (Ultra­ 
scan 1000; Gatan, Inc.), and <rs id="software-0" type="software">Digital Micrograph</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Gatan, Inc.</rs>.) 
was used to convert images into tiff files. </p>

<p>Optical neutralization 
The optical neutralization assay was described previously (Franceschini 
and Kirschfeld, 1971). In brief, heads were dissected and immersed in 
immersion oil. Pictures were acquired using a microscope (DMRB; Leica). </p>

<p>Arr2 binding assays 
Fly heads were exposed to light for 1.5 h and homogenized in TBS buffer 
(150 mM NaCl, 20 mM Tris, pH 7.5, and 1× protease inhibitor cocktail) 
with a Pellet Pestle (Kimble­Kontes). Pellet and supernatant fractions were 
separated by centrifuge at 12,000 g for 20 min (centrifuge 5415c; Eppen­ 
dorf). Proteins from each fraction were fractionated by SDS­PAGE and were 
transferred at 30 V to Immobilon­P transfer membranes (Millipore) in Tris­ 
glycine buffer. The blots were probed with rabbit anti­Arr2 and mouse anti­ 
Rh1 antibodies (Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank) and subsequently 
with IRDye 800-labeled anti-rabbit IgG and IRDye 680-labeled mouse 
IgG (LI­COR Biosciences). Signals were then detected using an Odyssey 
infrared imaging system (LI­COR Biosciences). </p>

<p>LysoTracker staining of dissected ommatidia 
Ommatidia from adult flies were dissected in glass culture dishes (MatTek) 
filled with Schneider's Drosophila medium (Wang et al., 2008). The disso­ 
ciated ommatidia were attached to poly­d­lysine-coated glass surfaces by 
placing in an incubator for 12 h at room temperature. The ommatidia were 
washed once in PBS, and the cells were subsequently loaded with 100 nM 
LysoTracker red DND­99 for 20 min under light condition. Live cell images 
were acquired using a microscope (Eclipse; Nikon) with a Plan­Apochromat 
40× air immersion objective, and images were acquired with a charge­ 
coupled device camera (CoolSNAP HQ2; Roper Scientific) at room tem­ 
perature and NIS­Elements software (Nikon). The images were transferred 
into <rs id="software-1" type="software">Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">7.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Adobe</rs>) to assemble the figures. </p>

<p>Online supplemental material 
Fig. S1 shows normal retinal cell size in flies with overexpression of 
Rheb by the ninaE promoter. Fig. S2 shows expression of MYC­tagged 
Atg1 and increase of autophagy without affecting S6K phosphorylation 
in ninaE-atg1 retinas. Fig. S3 shows that overexpression of TSC1/2 or 
Atg1 does not suppress the retinal degeneration in NinaE RH27 flies. 
Online supplemental material is available at http://www.jcb.org/cgi/ 
content/full/jcb.200904090/DC1. </p>

<p>We thank the Bloomington Stock Center and Drs. T. Neufeld, H. Steller, and 
C. Montell for fly stocks. We also thank B. Schneider and J. Bousman for pre-
paring sections of compound eyes, Dr. H. Brown for helpful comments on the 
manuscript, and members of the Edgar laboratory for helpful suggestions. 
This work was supported by National Institutes of Health grant R01 
NS058230 to B.A. Edgar and a Damon Runyon Cancer Research Foundation 
Fellowship to T. Wang. </p>

<p>Submitted: 17 April 2009 
Accepted: 30 July 2009 </p>



</text></tei>