<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2816832" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs id="software-1" type="software">GeneScan</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">3.7</rs><rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">Applied Biosystems</rs>Rapid prenatal diagnosis of common chromosome aneuploidies have been suc-
cessful through quantitative fluoresent PCR (QF-PCR) assays and small tandem 
repeat (STR) markers. The purpose of our study was to investigate the clinical 
feasibility for rapid prenatal detection of Down syndrome using the quantitative flu-
orescent PCR in uncultured amniocytes. DNA was extracted from uncultured amni-
otic fluid of normal karyotype (n=200) and of Down syndrome (n=21). It was ampli-
fied using QF-PCR with four STR markers located on chromosome 21. Among 
normal samples, the ranges of diallelic peaks for at least one STR marker were 
1.0-1.3 for D21S11, 1.0-1.4 for D21S1411 and 1.0-1.5 for D21S1270. Down syn-
drome samples showed trisomic triallelic patterns or trisomic diallelic patterns. The 
sensitivity, specificity, and efficiency of the assay for detecting Down syndrome 
were 95.4%, 100%, and 99.5%, respectively. Rapid prenatal diagnosis of Down 
syndrome using QF-PCR is a reliable technique that aids clinical management of 
pregnancy. </p>



<p>M.-H. Lee, H.-M. Ryu, D.-J. Kim, et al. </p>

<p>with 47,+21 showed trisomic triallelic patterns with an allele 
peak ratio 1:1:1, or trisomic diallelic patterns with an allele 
peak ratio 2:1 (Fig. 1). However, one case that showed low-
level mosaicism with a karyotype of 47,XX,+21[23]/46,XX 
[218] failed to be detected by QF-PCR. In complete trisom-</p>

<p>ic 21 samples, the ranges of diallelic peaks were 1.6-2.4 for 
D21S11, 2.2-2.7 for D21S1411, and 1.7-2.9 for D21S1270 
(Table 3). </p>

<p>*Reference: Mann, et al. 2001 (10). </p>

<p>Marker 
Labeling 
Allele range (bp) 
Location </p>

<p>D21S11 
6-FAM 
214-242 
21q21 
D21S1411 
NED 
266-319 
21q22.3 
D21S1270 
6-FAM 
285-340 
21q21-22.1 
D21S1412 
6-FAM 
384-414 
21q22.2 </p>

<p>Table 1. STR markers used for quantitative fluorescent PCR* </p>

<p>Mean 
SD 
Range </p>

<p>Ratio of peak areas in 
heterozygous samples 
Homozygous 
samples (n) </p>

<p>Heterozygous 
samples (n) 
Marker </p>

<p>D21S11 
165 
35 
1.1 
0.11 
1.0-1.3 
D21S1411 169 
31 
1.1 
0.17 
1.0-1.4 
D21S1270 167 
33 
1.2 
0.12 
1.0-1.5 
D21S1412 
2 
1 
1.1 
0.11 
1.0-1.2 </p>

<p>Table 2. Polymorphism and ratio of peak areas in 200 normal 
samples </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Electrophoregram of the QF-PCR products from normal and trisomy 21 samples. Fragment size in bp shown on horizontal axis, 
arbitrary fluorescence units shown on vertical axis. Markers labelled according to locus, size, and peak areas. Normal diploid sample: all 
markers are heterozygous and exhibit two peaks with a 1:1 ratio. Trisomy 21 sample: chromosome 21 markers exhibit three peaks with a 
1:1:1 ratio or two peaks with a 2:1 ratio. </p>

<p>D21S11 </p>

<p>Normal diploid </p>

<p>Trisomy 21 </p>

<p>241.42 </p>

<p>863 </p>

<p>D21S11 </p>

<p>244.65 </p>

<p>3353 </p>

<p>D21S1270 </p>

<p>300.63 </p>

<p>1457 </p>

<p>D21S1411 </p>

<p>297.59 </p>

<p>845 </p>

<p>D21S1411 </p>

<p>305.79 </p>

<p>687 </p>

<p>D21S1411 </p>

<p>326.13 </p>

<p>564 </p>

<p>D21S1270 </p>

<p>317.07 </p>

<p>601 </p>

<p>D21S11 </p>

<p>248.65 </p>

<p>1659 </p>

<p>D21S1270 </p>

<p>301.53 </p>

<p>829 </p>

<p>D21S1270 </p>

<p>800 
600 
400 
200 </p>

<p>800 
600 
400 
200 </p>

<p>800 
600 
400 
200 </p>

<p>3,000 
2,000 
1,000 </p>

<p>190 
200 
210 
220 
230 
240 
250 
260 
270 
280 
290 
300 
310 
320 
330 
340 
350 
360 </p>

<p>190 
200 
210 
220 
230 
240 
250 
260 
270 
280 
290 
300 
310 
320 
330 
340 
350 
360 </p>

<p>313.99 </p>

<p>802 </p>

<p>D21S1411 </p>

<p>310.80 </p>

<p>834 </p>

<p>D21S1411 </p>

<p>315.02 </p>

<p>698 </p>

<p>D21S11 </p>

<p>253.42 </p>

<p>764 </p>

<p>Rapid Prenatal Diagnosis </p>



<p>All but one normal samples were heterozygous and infor-
mative for at least one STR marker (Table 4). 
The sensitivity, specificity, and efficiency of QF-PCR for 
the detection of Down syndrome were 95.4%, 100%, and 
99.5%, respectively. The false positive and the false nega-
tive rates were 0% (0/200) and 4.7% (1/21), respectively. 
All results were obtained within 24 to 48 hr. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>QF-PCR for the detection of chromosome specific repeat-
ed sequences has been improved to include several STR (3, 
4). It is based on the incorporation of fluorochromes into the 
products of PCR amplification via oligonucleotide primers 
specific for each STR and on the assumption that, within the 
early exponential phase of PCR amplification, the amount 
of specific STR produced is proportional to the quantity of 
initial target sequence (12). In normal heterozygotes, the ratio 
of the fluorescent intensity of the two peaks should be close 
to 1:1. If the STR marker is highly polymorphic, few nor-
mal subjects should be homozygotes and show one peak. In 
a trisomic patient, the three doses of an STR marker can be 
detected either as three peaks of fluorescent intensity with a 
ratio 1:1:1 (trisomic triallelic) or as a pattern of two peaks 
with a ratio 2:1 (trisomic diallelic). Using the high polymor-
phism of the STR markers, very few trisomic patients should 
show a single peak of fluorescent intensity (4). 
Our results present that the fluorescent intensity ratios 
showed a definite difference between normal disomic dial-
lelic samples and diallelic trisomy 21 samples. 
In the present study, we used the markers as published pre-
viously. It was shown that heterozygosity of markers was low 
in our population compared to the published data (Table 5). 
At the D21S11 and D21S1411 markers, a significant dif-
ferences were found. We expected a difference of genetic diver-
sity between an ethnic groups and it was supported by other 
previous reports (13-16). 
Although 4 samples showed heterozygous for only one STR, 
even after using the extra marker, the use of combined STR 
markers could reduce the likelihood of homozygosity and 
consequently, the frequency of uninformative STR patterns. 
Only one out of 220 samples was homozygous for all STR </p>

<p>tested (Table 4). As a results, we emphasize that the infor-
mative rate of our experiment is prominent than other stud-
ies so far (5, 8, 9, 16). 
Yoon et al. reported three false positive in the multiplex 
QF-PCR using two of STR markers for Down syndrome (16). 
As it is well known, the preferential amplification of multi-
plex PCR is a potential problem that result in an incorrect 
genetic typing and is effected by low denaturation tempera-
tures, low amount of DNA, and differential allelic priming. 
In this study, there were no false positive results from mul-
tiplex QF-PCR using three of STR markers. It is reported 
that a maximum primer set used in the multiplex QF-PCR 
is twelve up to now (10). 
One case of low level mosaicism for trisomy 21 with a karyo-
type of 47,XX,+21[23]/46,XX[218] resulted in a false nega-
tive result. Several studies reported that mosaicism for trisomy 
was able to be detected by QF-PCR (10, 11), but based on 
our own and other published experiences, mosaicism, mater-
nal contamination, structural abnormality, deletion and dupli-
cation syndrome are not likely to be detected by the QF-PCR 
technique (8, 9). However, it is possible that future develop-
ment, such as the use of extensive panel of markers to cover 
other key chromosomes, will result in significant improve-
ments in the detection rate. 
An advantage of using QF-PCR technique is that it is less 
time consuming and less laborious and this assay is useful 
on small volumes of amniotic fluid (1-2 mL). In this study, 
some results were obtained within 8 hr. 
Our experiment demonstrates that QF-PCR can provide 
a rapid and accurate clinical method for prenatal identifica-
tion of Down syndrome and also serve as an adjunctive test 
to help cytogenetics to reduce significant amounts of emo-
tional stress experienced by patients and physicians. In fur-</p>

<p>Mean SD Range </p>

<p>Ratio of peak areas 
in diallelic samples 
Diallelic 
samples (n) </p>

<p>Monoallelic 
samples (n) </p>

<p>Triallelic 
samples (n) 
Marker </p>

<p>D21S11 
9 
9 
2 
2.0 0.34 1.6-2.4 
D21S1411 
5 
9 
6 
2.3 0.14 2.2-2.7 
D21S1270 
5 
15 
0 
2.2 0.55 1.7-2.9 </p>

<p>*One case with mosaicism was excluded. </p>

<p>Table 3. Polymorphism and ratio of peak areas in trisomy 21 
samples* </p>

<p>STR marker 
Homozygous % (n) Heterozygous % (n) </p>

<p>D21S11 
16.8 (37/220) 
83.2 (183/220) 
D21S1411 
16.8 (37/220) 
83.2 (183/220) 
D21S1270 
15.0 (33/220) 
85.0 (187/220) 
D21S11+D21S1411+D21S1270 1.4 (3/220) 
D21S11+D21S1411+D21S1270 
+D21S1412 
0.45 (1/220) </p>

<p>*One of false negative was excluded. </p>

<p>Table 4. Evaluation for each STR marker and combined STR 
markers* </p>

<p>STR marker </p>

<p>Heterozygous frequency </p>

<p>Reference 
(Mann et al., 
2001) </p>

<p>Reference 
(Mann et al., 
2001) </p>

<p>Present study 
(Korean 
group) </p>

<p>Present study 
(Korean 
group) </p>

<p>Allele range (bp) </p>

<p>D21S11 
0.9 
0.83 
214-242 
239-268 
D21S1411 
0.933 
0.83 
266-319 
294-338 
D21S1270 
0.86 
0.85 
285-340 
292-329 </p>

<p>Table 5. Evaluation of markers in the Korean population </p>



<p>M.-H. Lee, H.-M. Ryu, D.-J. Kim, et al. </p>

<p>ther studies, we will test a larger scale population with expand-
ed panel of markers for other numerical aberrations, such as 
trisomy 13 or 18 and sex chromosome aneuploidies. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENT </p>

<p>This study was supported by a grant of the Cheil Medical 
Encouragement Foundation. </p>



</text></tei>