<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2686461" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:11+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The Pathway Interaction Database (PID, http://pid. 
nci.nih.gov) is a freely available collection of curated 
and peer-reviewed pathways composed of human 
molecular signaling and regulatory events and 
key cellular processes. The Pathway Interaction Database (PID, http://pid.nci. 
nih.gov) is a growing collection of human signaling and 
regulatory pathways curated from peer-reviewed literature 
and stored in a computable format. PID was designed to 
deal with two issues affecting the representation of biolog-
ical processes: the arbitrariness of pathway boundaries 
and the need to capture knowledge at different levels </p>

<p>of detail. Pathway boundaries are often arbitrary and 
overlapping: different biologists might include different 
biochemical interactions in, for example, 'the p53 signal-
ing pathway'; and it is not unusual for two pathways 
representing distinct processes to have one or more inter-
actions in common. This fuzziness simply reflects the fact 
that terms like 'the p53 signaling pathway' and 'the BCR 
signaling pathway' are high-level concepts of convenience, 
designating slices through the very complex mix of con-
current processes in the cell. An important goal of PID is 
to provide an operational definition of high-level concepts 
like 'the BCR signaling pathway' (Figure 1) in the form of 
predefined pathways, while at the same time allowing a 
user to explore novel networks composed computationally 
from the universe of interactions underlying the predefined 
pathways. Current knowledge of the components of any 
given biological process is uneven. For example, for some 
protein interactants the precise posttranslational modifica-
tions might be known, while for other interactants perhaps 
the only sure knowledge is that the protein is 'active'. PID 
provides descriptive mechanisms to cover both of these 
cases. The ability to represent information at different 
levels of detail is also useful in communicating generaliza-
tions. For example, it is sometimes useful to encapsulate a 
complex process, such as cytoskeleton reorganization as a 
single event or to treat as a single entity a set of proteins, 
such as Class 1A PI3Ks that are functionally equivalent in 
catalyzing a given event. PID has mechanisms for dealing 
with incomplete knowledge, for encapsulating complex 
events and for expressing generalizations. 
PID has adopted a network-level representation, similar 
to Reactome (1), HumanCyc (2) and KEGG (3). Like 
Reactome and HumanCyc, PID annotates interactions 
with citations to the literature. PID differs from 
Reactome, HumanCyc and KEGG in its focus on signal-
ing and regulatory pathways; it does not attempt to cover 
metabolic processes or generic mechanisms like transcrip-
tion and translation (see Table 1 for a comparison of PID 
with other publicly accessible pathway databases). PID 
contains only structured data and it links to but does 
not reproduce molecular information readily available </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 301 435 1535; Fax:+1 301 480 6641; Email: schaefec@mail.nih.gov </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>from other sources, such as nucleotide or amino 
acid sequence, molecular weight and chemical formula. 
The principal source of data in PID is the highly curated 
'NCI-Nature Curated' collection of pathways, but PID 
also includes two other sources of data: data imported 
into the PID data model from Reactome's Biological 
Pathways Exchange (BioPAX) Level 2 (4) export, and 
an import of information from the BioCarta collection 
of pathways (Table 2). All data in PID is freely available, 
without restriction on use. Bulk downloads are available 
in BioPAX Level 2, a standard format for exchanging 
pathway information, and a PID-specific XML format 
at http://pid.nci.nih.gov/PID/download.shtml. </p>

<p>DATA MODEL </p>

<p>In PID, an interaction is an event with its participating 
molecules and conditions. A PID pathway is a network of 
these events connected by the participant molecules. PID 
recognizes four kinds of molecules: small molecules (called 
compounds), RNA, proteins and complexes. PID recog-
nizes five kinds of events: gene regulation (called transcri-
ption, but encompassing both transcription and 
translation), molecule transport (called translocation), 
small-molecule conversion (called reaction), protein-
protein interactions (called modification) and black-box 
processes whose internal composition is not provided 
(called macroprocesses). In addition, an entire pathway 
can be abstracted and used as a single event in another 
pathway. As a participant in an event, a molecule may </p>

<p>have one of four roles: input, output, positive regulator 
and negative regulator. These roles define simple relations: 
an interaction consumes its inputs (but not its regulators) 
and produces its outputs; and the inputs, positive regula-
tors and the absence of negative regulators are jointly the 
necessary and sufficient causes of the interaction. 
Each molecule in PID has a defining entity, called a 
basic molecule. Basic molecules are distinguished by 
their nucleotide or amino acid sequence (for macromole-
cules) or by their chemical formula (for small molecules). 
While PID does not record the sequence of a macromole-
cule or the chemical formula for a small molecule, each 
protein or RNA is associated with a UniProt or Entrez 
Gene accession and most small molecules are associated 
with Chemical Abstracts Service (CAS) registry numbers. 
A basic molecule has a primary name and may have multi-
ple aliases. Each molecule use, as an interactant in an 
interaction or as a component of a complex, references 
its corresponding basic molecule. Each molecule use may 
have additional information, including posttranslational 
modifications (for proteins) and cellular location and 
activity state (for all molecule types). 
A basic protein molecule has a single identifying 
UniProt accession associated with a particular amino 
acid sequence. If the particular isoform of a protein used 
in an interaction is not known, then the basic protein mole-
cule may be associated with an Entrez Gene identifier 
instead of a UniProt accession; in PID, this method of 
identifying proteins is restricted almost entirely to the uncu-
rated section of the database imported from BioCarta. </p>

<p>Figure 1. BCR signaling pathway. The pathway header information includes the date of the latest revision; the data curation or import source; the 
curator; the reviewers; the stable pathway identifier; links to a pathway-specific molecule list and a pathway-specific references list; and links to 
pathway graphic and text data exchange format options. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D675 </p>

<p>A use of a protein as a participant in an interaction or 
component of a complex may have additional attributes: 
posttranslational modifications, an abstract activity-state 
attribute and a cellular location attribute. Currently, PID 
uses 13 types of posttranslational modifications, with 
phosphorylation being by far the most frequently used 
modification (Table 3). The abstract activity-state attri-
bute, with values such as 'active' and 'inactive', allows 
curators to distinguish functionally different forms of a 
protein even if the precise covalent modifications are not 
known. Values for the cellular location attribute are 
drawn from the Gene Ontology (GO) cellular component 
vocabulary (5). Cleaved subunits of a precursor protein 
are not distinguished by the posttranslational modifica-
tion mechanism; rather they are treated as basic protein 
molecules separate from each other and from the precur-
sor. However, PID explicitly relates the cleaved subunit 
to its precursor and records the cleavage coordinates 
when these are known. A PID protein corresponds 
roughly to a BioPAX Level 3 protein reference, while a 
BioPAX Level 3 protein corresponds to a PID protein 
use (with posttranslational modifications and cellular 
location). 
PID allows the definition of generic proteins, com-
plexes, small molecules and RNA molecules. A generic 
molecule is called a family, but is not restricted to the 
traditional protein families defined by sequence similarity: 
any set of proteins (or other type of molecule) that are in 
some respect functionally equivalent may be grouped in a 
family. Individual protein members of a protein family 
may have posttranslational modifications or activity 
states. The family itself can be used as a participant in 
an interaction, or as a component of a complex. 
Because data are entered by multiple curators and 
because the database contains data from multiple sources, 
PID needs rules for determining equivalence of molecules. 
Two basic molecules that are neither families nor com-
plexes are equivalent if they have the same external data-
base accession (e.g. UniProt or Entrez Gene), or if, in 
cases where neither has an external database accession, 
they have the same name. Two molecule uses (as partici-
pant in an interaction or component of a complex or 
member of a family) are equivalent if they refer to the 
same basic molecule, and have the same (or no) posttran-
slational modifications, and have the same (or no) 
activity-state attribute, and have the same (or no) cellular 
location attribute. Two basic families (or complexes) are 
equivalent, if they have the same number of members (or 
components) and if for each member (component) of one, 
there is an equivalent member (component) in the other. 
These rules are applied recursively to define, for example, 
equivalent uses of complexes with components that are 
families. Equivalence of molecule uses is the basis on 
which novel networks are constructed: any two interac-
tions in the database may be joined in a network if one 
interaction has a participant that is equivalent to a parti-
cipant in the other interaction. Analogous rules of equiva-
lence are implemented for interactions and entire 
networks, allowing equivalent (redundant) interactions 
to be pruned from the novel networks. </p>

<p>Table 1. Open access human pathway databases </p>

<p>BioCarta </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>HumanCyc </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>KEGG </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Panther </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>PID </p>

<p>Reactome </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Scope of content </p>

<p>Metabolic and 
signaling pathways 
Metabolic pathways Metabolic, regulatory, </p>

<p>signaling, disease and </p>

<p>drug pathways </p>

<p>Metabolic and 
regulatory pathways 
Signaling and regulatory 
pathways </p>

<p>Metabolic, signaling and 
regulatory pathways </p>

<p>Human pathways </p>

<p>353 </p>

<p>226 </p>

<p>208 </p>

<p>165 </p>

<p>77 </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>Human events </p>

<p>&gt;3000 </p>

<p>1493 </p>

<p>5083 </p>

<p>1500 </p>

<p>4373 </p>

<p>2806 </p>

<p>Curation 
Type </p>

<p>Manual </p>

<p>Part manual/part 
computational </p>

<p>Manual </p>

<p>Manual </p>

<p>Manual </p>

<p>Manual </p>

<p>Expert review </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>Literature reference 
annotation </p>

<p>For pathways </p>

<p>For pathways </p>

<p>For pathways </p>

<p>Optional </p>

<p>For each event </p>

<p>For each event </p>

<p>Capture of evidence types </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Yes </p>

<p>No </p>

<p>Data visualization </p>

<p>Non interactive 
predefined pathways </p>

<p>Interactive predefined 
pathways </p>

<p>Interactive predefined 
pathways </p>

<p>Noninteractive 
predefined pathways </p>

<p>Interactive predefined 
pathways and dynamically 
generated interactive network maps </p>

<p>Interactive predefined 
pathways </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Data from http://www.biocarta.com/ (as of September, 2008). </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>Data from http://humancyc.org/ (as of September, 2008). </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>Data from http://www.genome.jp/kegg/xml/hsa/index.html (as of September, 2008). </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>Data from Nucleic Acids Research 
2007, 35(Database issue):D247-D252. </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>Data from http://www.reactome.org/ (as of September, 2008). </p>



<p>An interaction may be supported by one or more 
citations to the literature. Currently, interactions in the 
NCI-Nature Curated data source are annotated with 
3105 distinct PubMed references. In addition, an interac-
tion may be annotated with one or more evidence codes 
that specify the kind of evidence adduced in the citations 
in support of the interaction (Table 4). 
A predefined pathway is a curated pathway representing 
a known biological process. At present, every pathway 
stored in the PID database is a predefined pathway and 
every interaction in the database is a member of at least 
one predefined pathway. However, the search and retriev-
al tools allow the user to compose novel pathways from 
interactions defined in the predefined pathways. This abil-
ity to recombine interactions and to thus create novel 
pathways is a distinguishing feature of PID. 
Since the original BioCarta diagrams were not asso-
ciated with an explicit data model, the import of the 
BioCarta pathway data did not challenge the PID data 
model. The original BioCarta diagrams show protein-
protein interactions, but the semantics of the connecting 
arrows are implicit. The import of these pathways into 
PID required the interpretation of each interaction and 
the manual encoding of the semantics in the PID data 
model. This was tedious, but since the original BioCarta 
pathways were underspecified, the process did not entail 
loss of information. In contrast, the import of the 
Reactome data is automated but does entail some loss 
of information. PID uses Reactome's BioPAX export as 
the source for the imported Reactome data. Some features </p>

<p>of Reactome are not expressible in BioPAX Level 2. 
For example, Reactome has 'entity sets', which corre-
spond roughly to PID's molecule families. However, 
since BioPAX Level 2 lacks the means to specify an 
entity set, this information was lost in the import process. 
Along with other important enhancements, this is being 
corrected in BioPAX Level 3. On the other hand, 
Reactome has some features that are expressible in 
BioPAX Level 2 but have no correspondence in PID. 
For example, in Reactome it is possible to explicitly spe-
cify that one interaction is a predecessor ('preceding 
event') of another, and this is also directly expressible in 
BioPAX Level 2. However, in PID the predecessor rela-
tion is implicit, inferred from the identity of interactants 
and the directionality of inputs and outputs. Con-
sequently, the predecessor relation between two Reactome 
interactions that do not share an interactant is lost in the 
PID import. </p>

<p>DATA CURATION </p>

<p>Nature Publishing Group (NPG) editors create the NCI-
Nature Curated pathways. Pathways selected for curation 
are based on potential drug targets, suggestions made by 
users and reviewers, and other molecules known to be of 
interest to the cell signaling community. A list of NCI-
Nature Curated pathways, along with a list of the path-
ways imported from Reactome and BioCarta, can be 
found on the Browse pathways page of the PID website: 
http://pid.nci.nih.gov/browse_pathways.shtml 
In curating, editors synthesize meaningful networks of 
events into defined pathways and adhere to the PID data 
model for consistency in data representation: molecules 
and biological processes are annotated with standardized 
names and unambiguous identifiers; and signaling and 
regulatory events are annotated with evidence codes and 
references. To ensure accurate data representation, editors 
assemble pathways from data that is principally derived 
from primary research publications. The majority of data 
in PID is human; however, if a finding discovered in 
another mammal is also deemed to occur in humans, edi-
tors may decide to include this finding, but will also record 
that the evidence was inferred from another species. Prior 
to publication, all pathways are reviewed by one or more 
experts in a field for accuracy and completeness. </p>

<p>Table 4. Evidence in NCI-Nature Curated data source </p>

<p>Code 
Evidence kind 
Uses </p>

<p>IAE 
Inferred from array experiments 
3 
IDA 
Inferred from direct assay 
1780 
IEP 
Inferred from expression pattern 
37 
IFC 
Inferred from functional complementation 
13 
IGI 
Inferred from genetic interaction 
12 
IMP 
Inferred from mutant phenotype 
1689 
IOS 
Inferred from other species 
1139 
IPI 
Inferred from physical interaction 
1203 
RGE 
Inferred from reporter gene expression 
311 </p>

<p>Table 2. Summary of all data sources </p>

<p>NCI-Nature 
Curated </p>

<p>Reactome 
imported </p>

<p>BioCarta 
imported </p>

<p>Pathways 
77 
63 
254 
Subpathways 
42 
753 
0 
Interactions 
4373 
3466 
3003 
Proteins 
2607 
2692 
4218 
Small molecules 
135 
617 
205 
Complexes 
1949 
1897 
880 </p>

<p>Table 3. Posttranslational modifications in NIC-Nature Curated data 
source </p>

<p>Modification type 
All uses 
Unique 
modifications </p>

<p>Acetylation 
111 
46 
Farnesylation 
7 
4 
Geranylgeranylation 
2 
2 
Glycosaminoglycan 
9 
2 
Glycosylation 
135 
15 
Hydroxylation 
13 
3 
Methylation 
13 
2 
Myristoylation 
15 
4 
Oxidation 
8 
4 
Palmitoylation 
52 
14 
Phosphorylation 
7403 
1070 
Sumoylation 
50 
10 
Ubiquitination 
149 
52 </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D677 </p>

<p>Any pathway curation effort must decide to what extent 
to annotate pathways and interactions with information 
about the larger biological context, including the cell types 
in which a set of interactions is known to occur and the 
role of individual pathways in specific pathologies. Using 
the GO biological process vocabulary, PID curators are 
able to connect interactants and interactions to macropro-
cesses that characterize particular cell types (e.g. 'endothe-
lial cell migration'). While, it would be desirable to 
annotate each interaction with the list of cell types in 
which the interaction has been observed, PID does not 
at present attempt to supply this level of detail. Given 
the sparseness of available data, it would be necessary to 
specify not only positive findings but also negative find-
ings in order to prevent a lack of data from being misin-
terpreted as the absence of the interaction in a particular 
cell type. PID has a few pathways that explicitly describe a 
particular pathological response (e.g. 'Cellular roles of 
anthrax toxin'); however, the focus of PID is normal 
human biology. The assumption is that a 'pathological 
pathway' relies on the signaling topology of normal biol-
ogy but deviates from normal biology in quantity (e.g. 
overabundance of a protein), in co-occurrence (abnormal 
presence of two reactants at the same time in the same 
cellular compartment), or in the introduction of specific 
abnormal reactants (e.g. the anthrax toxin or the consti-
tutively active BCR/ABL fusion protein). Curators are 
able to specify abnormal reactants; however, this feature 
has not been used extensively to date. As described in the 
next section, an important use of the batch query is for a 
researcher to overlay experimental information about 
such deviations onto the normal signaling topology and 
thus visualize possible perturbations. </p>

<p>WEB INTERFACE AND APPLICATION </p>

<p>PID provides several query options: a simple query, an 
advanced query, a connected molecules query and a 
batch query. In the simple query, the user provides the 
name, alias or accession of a molecule or biological pro-
cess; wildcarding is permitted. The query will return a list 
of all uses of the molecule, as simplex or as participant in a 
complex, and all uses of the biological process, in the 
database, with hyperlinks to visualizations of the relevant 
predefined pathways containing the queried entities. The 
user also has the option to visualize the novel network(s) 
that include all interactions using the queried entities. The 
advanced query allows the user to construct the set of 
novel networks from interactions that: (i) involve any of 
a set of user-specified molecules, or (ii) are part of any 
predefined pathway whose name includes a user-specified 
key word, or (iii) have a user-specified GO biological pro-
cess term or National Cancer Institute (NCI) Thesaurus 
(6) term as their event type or condition. An important 
feature of the advanced query is the provision for includ-
ing interactions that are immediately upstream or down-
stream of the set of interactions retrieved by molecule, 
pathway name or GO/NCI Thesaurus term. The con-
nected molecules query allows a user to find a novel net-
work that connects two or more molecules specified by </p>

<p>name, alias or accession. The query will find only one of 
the possibly many networks satisfying the constraint, but 
the one found will have the minimum number of interac-
tions. Finally, the batch query allows a user to upload one 
or two lists of molecule identifiers (name, alias or acces-
sion). The user has two options: to analyze the number of 
molecules in the lists that 'hit' each predefined pathway or 
to construct the novel network(s) that include all interac-
tions using any of the listed molecules. For the first 
option, the query uses a hypergeometric distribution to 
compute the probability that each pathway in the data-
base is hit by molecules in either of the lists. The query 
returns a list of pathways ordered by P-value. In the visua-
lization of a predefined pathway (first option) or novel 
pathway (second option), molecules from the first list 
are colored blue, molecules from the second list are 
colored red and any molecules appearing in both lists 
are colored purple. Supplementary Figure 1 presents an 
example of invoking the batch query with a single mole-
cule list, the 120 protein kinases found by Greenman et al. 
(7) to have at least one cancer-predisposing mutation. 
Selecting the predefined pathways option, one can see 
that this list samples a small number of pathways, 
biased toward immune cell signaling, at a P &lt; 0.0001. 
While PID associates a single external database acces-
sion (typically a UniProt accession) with a protein, the 
query interface searches PID not only by UniProt acces-
sion, but also by related gene identifiers (HUGO symbol, 
alias, Entrez Gene identifier). Any predefined pathway or 
novel network can be visualized in either GIF (graphics 
interchange format) or SVG (scalable vector graphics) 
graphic mode. Network graphics are all automatically 
constructed from the underlying data using the 
<rs type="software">GraphViz</rs> package (8). Events and molecule uses in the 
graphics are hyperlinked to HTML pages of information 
about the interaction or molecule. In addition, any prede-
fined pathway or novel network can be exported in native 
PID XML or BioPAX Level 2 formats. Using the BioPAX 
export, a user can also visualize PID pathways in 
<rs id="software-1" type="software">Cytoscape</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-1" type="url">http://cytoscape.org</rs>) a popular third-party 
network visualization tool (9). For any predefined path-
way, the user can obtain (and export to tab-separated 
format) a list of literature citations and participating 
molecules. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION AND FUTURE DIRECTIONS </p>

<p>PID is a highly structured, curated database of molecular 
interactions and events that compose human cell signaling 
and regulatory pathways. A particular strength of PID is 
the ability to create novel networks that can reveal parallel 
alternative paths to events of interest, like activation of a 
protein or disassembly of a complex in the DNA repair 
process. In cancer biology, such a view can elucidate the 
variety of strategies that a given type of cancer may adopt, 
explain why a single-agent therapy is not effective and 
suggest potential multi-agent therapies. Increasingly, 
molecular networks are recognized as frameworks for 
integrating and interpreting experimental data. For exam-
ple, by using pathways as the integrating framework, </p>



<p>the Cancer Genome Atlas project has mapped genomic 
abnormalities of different types-copy number, mutation 
and methylation-to a set of oncogenic processes (10). At 
present, most attempts to profile tumor subtypes have 
relied on DNA and RNA assays. However, as high-
throughput proteomic methods improve the kind of 
detailed information on posttranslational modifications 
of proteins available in PID will be essential in mapping 
more accurately the state of a cell. 
Consistent with its focus on interactions and events 
derived from curated signaling cascades and regulatory 
processes, PID does not at present include interaction 
data deriving from high-throughput protein-protein inter-
action experiments. This reflects not a judgment on the 
quality of high-throughput data, but a recognition that 
there are databases specifically designed to provide access 
to this data (11, 12, 13). However, while it does not lead 
directly to the construction of signaling cascades, informa-
tion from high-throughput protein-protein interaction 
experiments can be useful in interpreting the curated path-
ways and assessing their completeness. For example, a 
high-throughput protein-protein interaction experiment 
can identify an unexpected binding partner for a catalyst, 
suggesting the possibility that the in vivo presence of the 
partner can sequester the catalyst and thus turn off down-
stream interactions. In the future, PID will allow users to 
take advantage of high-throughput protein-protein inter-
action data, either by allowing users to upload interaction 
sets to be added to the novel networks created by PID 
queries or by querying other data sources (such as 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">Pathway Commons</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="url">http://pathwaycommons.org</rs>) as 
needed to support a user query. The PID data model is 
currently being integrated with NCI's Cancer Bioinfor-
matics Infrastructure Objects model (caBIO) (14), thereby 
making PID data accessible on NCI's caGrid (15). </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>The National Cancer Institute. Funding for open access 
charge: National Cancer Institute. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, Database issue D679 </p>

</text></tei>