<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2991579" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-11-11T23:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: Korean red ginseng (KRG) is a potent antioxidant and a free radical scavenger. 
This study was designed to determine whether KRG could protect against dysfunction 
and oxidative stress induced by torsion-detorsion injury in rat testis. 
Materials and Methods: Six-week-old male Sprague-Dawley rats were randomly div-
ided into four groups: a sham-operated control group (C), a sham-operated and 
KRG-treated group (K), a 2 hours torsion and detorsion group (T), and a 2 hours torsion 
and detorsion and KRG-treated group (T＋K). We measured testis weight and hormone 
levels and reactive oxygen species (ROS) from the left renal vein. Superoxide gen-
eration was measured on the basis of lucigenin-enhanced chemiluminescence in testis 
tissue. 
Results: Testicular weight was significantly higher in the T＋K group than in the T 
group; however, there were no significant differences in hormone levels between the 
4 groups. The mean level of ROS and superoxide production was significantly higher 
in the T group than in the C group, whereas administration of KRG attenuated this 
increase. Upon histologic evaluation, the T group was found to have cellular disarray, 
a lack of cellular cohesiveness, degenerative changes in the germinal cells, and less dis-
tinct changes in the seminiferous tubules, whereas the T＋K group had a germinal epi-
thelial layer that appeared nearly normal. 
Conclusions: The present study demonstrated that KRG recovered the testis dysfunc-
tion in the rat testis by suppressing superoxide production. </p>

<p>Testicular torsion is a urologic emergency. The testicular 
salvage rate following surgical detorsion has been reported 
to range from 42% to 88% [1,2], but it is unclear whether 
these testes were actually saved with respect to testicular 
spermatogenic function [3]. A testis injury produced by 
reperfusion can be more severe than that induced by ische-
mia [4]. This is because the reperfusion component typi-
cally involves the generation of toxic reactive oxygen spe-
cies (ROS) with the return of blood flow following a period 
of ischemia [5]. 
Panax ginseng (P. ginseng) C. A. Mayer has been used </p>

<p>for thousands of years in Asia due to its wide spectrum of 
medicinal effects. This compound has a wide range of phar-
macologic and physiologic actions, such as anti-aging, im-
munoenhancement, anti-stress, and anti-tumor activity 
[6-8]. It has long been known that P. ginseng has protective 
properties against free radical attack [9-11]. Indeed, P. gin-
seng administration to rats has been shown to prevent my-
ocardial ischemia-reperfusion (I-R) damage induced by hy-
perbaric oxygen [11]. Protective effects of P. ginseng 
against hepatic oxidative stress induced by exhaustive ex-
ercise and against skeletal muscle injury caused by oxida-
tive stress induced by acute exercise have also been re-
ported [12,13]. Among the currently available P. ginseng </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2010;51:794-799 </p>

<p>Effect of Korean Red Ginseng on Testicular Torsion </p>



<p>products, Korean red ginseng (KRG, Ginseng Radix Rubra) 
has the most potent multiple pharmacologic actions for an-
ticancer, antihypertension, antidiabetes, and anti-noci-
ception effects and for improving weak body conditions 
[14]. Recently, KRG was also found to possess anti-stress 
and antioxidant activities [15]. 
Although KRG has been investigated for multiple pur-
poses, its effect on I-R injury of the testes during testicular 
torsion and detorsion has not yet been evaluated. In the 
present study, we aimed to evaluate the effects of KRG on 
testicular damage in a rat testicular I-R injury model. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>1. Administration of KRG 
Steamed ginseng (KRG, Cheong-Kwan-Jang) was pur-
chased from the Korea Ginseng Corporation (Daejeon, 
Korea) and dissolved in distilled water. KRG (100 mg/kg 
per day) was administered orally for 4 weeks after surgery 
and continued until the end of the experiment. </p>

<p>2. Experimental protocol 
Forty 6-week-old male Sprague-Dawley rats (150±25 g, 
Jung-ang, Inc., Daejeon, Korea) were randomly divided in-
to four groups: a sham-operated group (C), a sham-operated 
and KRG-treated group (K), a 2 hours torsion and detorsion 
group (T), and a 2 hours torsion and detorsion and KRG-
treated group (T＋K). The sham-operated group was used 
as the baseline group. All animals underwent an adapta-
tion period of 1 week in cages under normal conditions be-
fore the surgical procedure. At the age of 7 weeks, the C and 
K groups underwent a sham operation and the T and T＋K 
groups underwent testicular torsion followed by detorsion. 
The C and T groups were fed tap water, whereas the K and 
T＋K groups were fed water with KRG for 4 weeks. After 
4 weeks, the rats were anesthetized and the left testes were 
removed. After the testes were removed, they were dis-
sected to remove the fat tissue and blood vessels, after 
which the tunica albuginea was eliminated. The testis was 
then weighed and longitudinally bisected. Half of the testes 
were immediately stored in organ baths to determine the 
superoxide level, whereas the remainder were fixed in 
Bouin's solution for histological examination. Fresh hep-
arinized blood samples from the left renal vein were also 
obtained to assess the antioxidant enzyme, ROS, and hor-
monal levels of follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH), lutei-
nizing hormone (LH), and testosterone. The remainder of 
the testis was stored at −70 o C for biochemical assay. </p>

<p>3. Animal model 
Male Sprague-Dawley rats (160±20 g, 7 weeks old) were 
fasted for 24 hours before the experiments, but were pro-
vided with tap water. In all protocols, a combination of 80 
mg/kg ketamine (Huons Corp. Seoul, Korea) and 12 mg/kg 
xylazine (Bayer Health Care, Germany) was used to induce 
anesthesia. All operations were conducted under sterile 
conditions. Throughout the anesthesia, body temperature </p>

<p>was maintained by using a heating pad. In the sham-oper-
ated group, the left testis was removed through a midscrotal 
vertical incision. A 5-0 silk suture was then placed through 
the tunica albuginea, the left testis was placed into the 
scrotum, and the incision was closed. In the torsion and de-
torsion group, the left testis was exposed through the same 
incision. The left testis was rotated 720 o in a counter-
clockwise direction and maintained in this torsion position 
by fixing the testis to the scrotum with a 5-0 silk suture. 
After 2 hours of torsion, the testis was counter-rotated 
to the natural position. </p>

<p>4. Measurement of testis weight 
After 4 weeks of KRG administration, we measured the left 
testis weight. </p>

<p>5. Measurement of hormone levels 
Blood was collected from the left renal vein into a bottle 
and the levels of FSH, LH, and testosterone were then 
measured at a laboratory (Sam-kwang, Seoul, Korea). </p>

<p>6. Histological evaluation 
All tissue specimens were kept in Bouin's solution. 
Following the fixation procedure, tissue specimens were 
embedded in paraffin, sectioned at a thickness of 5 μm, and 
then stained with H&amp;E. </p>

<p>7. Measurement of superoxide production 
A lucigenin-enhanced chemiluminescence assay was used 
to measure the level of superoxide production as previously 
reported [16,17]. Lucigenin (bis-N-methylacridinium ni-
trate) luminescens specifically in the presence of super-
oxide. Dark-adapted lucigenin solution (5 μmol/l) was pre-
pared in aerated Krebs-HEPES buffer (NaCl 100 mmol/l, 
KCl 4.7 mmol/l, CaCl2 1.9 mmol/l, MgSO4 1.2 mmol/l, 
K2HPO4 1.03 mmol/l, NaHCO3 25 mmol/l, Na-HEPES 20 
mmol/l, pH 7.4). The testis parenchyme was then trans-
ferred into scintillation vials containing Krebs-HEPES 
buffer with 5 μM lucigenin. The chemiluminescence, which 
occurred over the ensuing 2 minutes in response to the ad-
dition of 100 μM NADPH, was then recorded. After sub-
traction of the value of a blank, the emitted light units were 
used as a measure of superoxide production. Values are ex-
pressed as relative light units per 1 μg of tissue (RLU/1 μg 
tissue). </p>

<p>8. Assessment of oxidative stress markers 
The blood levels of ROS were determined by using the free 
oxygen radical test (FORT). To conduct the FORT, blood 
samples from the left renal vein were immediately thawed 
and mixed with an acidic buffer that contained transition 
metals. The radical species produced by the reaction is the 
area directly proportional to the quantity of lipid peroxides 
present in the sample that interacts with an additive 
(phenylenediamine derivative) to form a radical molecule 
that can be detected at 505 nm by a spectrophotometer 
(Form CR 2000, Callegari, Parma, Italy). The intensity of </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2010;51:794-799 </p>



<p>Kim et al </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Weight of the testis. C: a sham-operated group, K: a 
sham-operated and KRG-treated group, T: a 2 hours torsion and 
detorsion group, T＋K: a 2 hours torsion and detorsion and 
KRG-treated group. </p>

<p>TABLE 1. Hormonal levels of experimental rats </p>

<p>C 
K 
T 
T ＋K </p>

<p>FSH 
0.12±0.16 
0.14±0.09 
0.16±0.03 
0.16±0.10 
LH 
0.14±0.16 
0.12±0.02 
0.17±0.01 
0.08±0.07 
Testosterone 
2.01±1.5 
3.5±1.8 
2.2±1.1 
2.7±1.4 </p>

<p>C: a sham-operated group, K: a sham-operated and KRG-treated group, T: a 2 hours torsion and detorsion group, T＋K: a 2 hours torsion 
and detorsion and KRG-treated group, FSH: follicle-stimulating hormone, LH: luteinizing hormone </p>

<p>the color corresponds directly to the quantity of peroxy and 
alkoxy radicals that form upon addition of the transition 
metals. All results are expressed as FORT units, where 1 
FORT unit corresponds to 0.26 mg/l of H2O2. Higher levels 
of FORT indicate higher oxidative stress levels. </p>

<p>9. Statistical analysis 
Data are expressed as the mean±standard error of mean 
(SEM). <rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 11.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SPSS Inc.</rs>., Chicago, IL, USA) was 
used to evaluate the data. One-way and two-way ANOVAs 
were used to evaluate the hormonal levels. The Mann-
Whitney method analysis of variance was used to evaluate 
the other parameters. Values of p＜0.05 were considered 
to be statistically significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>1. Weight of the testis 
The testicular weights of groups C and K were significantly 
different from the weights of groups T and T＋K. In addi-
tion, although there were no significant differences in the 
testicular weights of groups C and K, the testicular weights 
of groups T and T＋K differed significantly (Fig. 1). </p>

<p>2. Results of hormone levels 
There were no significant differences in the hormone levels </p>

<p>(FSH, LH, and testosterone) of the 4 groups (Table 1). </p>

<p>3. Results of histological evaluation 
The normal appearance of the testicular structure of rats 
was determined by evaluation of group C (Fig. 2A), which 
had a normal arrangement of germinative cells in the semi-
niferous tubules. The appearance of group K (Fig. 2B) was 
similar to that of group C. However, group T (Fig. 2C) 
showed cellular disarray, a lack of cellular cohesiveness, 
degenerative changes in the germinal cells, and less dis-
tinct changes in the seminiferous tubule. In the T＋K group 
(Fig. 2D), the germinal epithelial layer appeared nearly 
normal. </p>

<p>4. Results of superoxide production 
The basal testis superoxide was quantified by lucige-
nin-enhanced chemiluminescence. The superoxide levels 
were significantly higher in the T group (278.3±39.6 for 
the T group vs. 181±16.8 for the C group and 189.5±13.2 
for the K group; all values RLU/1 mg tissue, p＜0.05). The 
superoxide level decreased significantly in response to 
treatment with KRG (173.3±13.0 RLU/1 mg tissue, p＜ 
0.05). NADPH-driven superoxide production was mark-
edly increased in the T group (Fig. 3), whereas it was sig-
nificantly decreased by treatment with KRG. </p>

<p>5. Assessment of oxidative stress markers: FORT 
As shown in Fig. 4, the mean level of FORT, which is an 
oxidative stress marker, was significantly higher in the T 
group than in the C group (386.2±43.9 FORT units vs. 
240.5±27.9 FORT units, p＜0.05). KRG administration at-
tenuated the increase in the testis FORT level (286.0±26.8 
FORT units, p＜0.05). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Testicular torsion is the twisting of the spermatic cord, 
which cuts off the blood supply to the testicle and sur-
rounding structures within the scrotum. Testicular torsion 
is a very common surgical emergency [18]. If surgery is 
performed within hours, most testicles can be saved, al-
though there is an increased risk of decreased sperm pro-
duction and fertility and atrophy of the testis [19,20]. 
Testicular torsion-detorsion is an I-R injury to the testis. 
In this study, we evaluated KRG treatment to determine 
whether it could protect the testis from injury associated 
with testicular torsion and detorsion. To accomplish this, </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2010;51:794-799 </p>

<p>Effect of Korean Red Ginseng on Testicular Torsion </p>



<p>FIG. 2. Representative microphotographs of cross-sections of the seminiferous tubules from SD rats. (A: group C, B: group K, C: group 
T, D: group T＋K) (H&amp;E, x400). C: a sham-operated group, K: a sham-operated and KRG-treated group, T: a 2 hours torsion and 
detorsion group, T＋K: a 2 hours torsion and detorsion and KRG-treated group. </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Lucigenin-enhanced chemiluminescence, reflective of 
testis superoxide levels. Luminescence was recorded in the 
absence or presence of NADPH (100 μmol/l). C: a sham-operated 
group, K: a sham-operated and KRG-treated group, T: a 2 hours 
torsion and detorsion group, T＋K: a 2 hours torsion and 
detorsion and KRG-treated group. </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Results of oxidative stress markers: free oxygen radical 
test (FORT). C: a sham-operated group, K: a sham-operated and 
KRG-treated group, T: a 2 hours torsion and detorsion group, T 
＋K: a 2 hours torsion and detorsion and KRG-treated group. </p>

<p>we measured the superoxide level of the I-R damaged tes-
tis tissue with and without KRG treatment. This study is 
the first report to evaluate the effects of KRG, a potent an-</p>

<p>tioxidant, on the formation of ROS in rat testis due to I-R 
injury. The results of the study demonstrated that KRG re-
covered the testis dysfunction caused by ischemia and 
subsequent reperfusion in the rat testis by suppressing su-
peroxide production. </p>

<p>Korean J Urol 2010;51:794-799 </p>



<p>Kim et al </p>

<p>It has been suggested that many substances are im-
portant to the prevention of testis dysfunction secondary 
to ischemia and reperfusion. Unsal et al reported the pro-
tective effects of garlic extract on rat testis subjected to 
a torsion and detorsion model [21]. In their study, the au-
thors concluded that the effect of garlic extract appeared 
to occur through inhibition of the xanthine oxidase-medi-
ated I-R injury cascade. Cay et al reported that N-ace-
tylcysteine may be a useful agent for preventing the oxida-
tive effects of reperfusion injury following torsion [22]. 
Additionally, Lim et al reported that pretreatment with al-
lopurinol prevented I-R injury in testis [23]. 
Among the components of P. ginseng, KRG has been 
shown to exhibit a variety of antioxidative actions. Kitts 
et al reported that North American ginseng extract exhibits 
effective antioxidant activity in both lipid and aqueous me-
dia via the chelation of metal ions and scavenging of free 
radicals [24]. Kim et al reported that red ginseng aqueous 
extract had free radical scavenging activity [25]. Indeed, 
red ginseng extracts are known to scavenge hydroxyl and 
superoxide radicals. P. ginseng has been shown to have a 
remarkable capacity to protect brain tissue proteins from 
oxidative damage in vitro [26]. Furthermore, the crude 
saponin fraction of KRG was found to abrogate the gen-
eration of NADPH-driven superoxide in rats [15]. Overall, 
the aforementioned studies indicate that KRG is a useful 
adjuvant for the protection of I-R-induced oxidative 
injury. Therefore, it is likely that KRG also has protective 
effects against I-R-induced oxidative injury of the testis, 
which was confirmed in the present study. 
Ischemia is not an isolated event, and when reversible, 
it is followed by reperfusion. Reperfusion may cause a more 
severe injury than ischemia alone [8]. I-R injury is asso-
ciated with the over-generation of ROS, such as hypo-
chlorous acid, nitric oxide, hydrogen peroxide, superoxide 
anion, and hydroxyl radicals [3]. ROS cause damage to DNA 
and impair the protein function and peroxidation of lipids. 
Lipid peroxides rupture the membranes and cause struc-
tural and functional alterations in the testis. Reperfusion 
of the ischemic tissue promotes the generation of ROS, 
which arises from activation of the xanthine oxidase system 
in parenchymal cells or from leukocytes penetrating into 
interstitial tissue. These substances have destructive ef-
fects on various cellular functions and lead to increased mi-
crovascular permeability, interstitial edema, impaired 
vasoregulation, inflammatory cell infiltration, and paren-
chymal cell dysfunction and necrosis. Therefore, ROS may 
directly damage the seminiferous tubules in the testis. Free 
radical reduction for the treatment of I-R injury has been 
found to prevent post-ischemic testis dysfunction [27]. 
The FORT provides an indirect measure of hydro-
peroxides, which are a useful measure of oxidative stress 
because they indicate the presence of intermediate oxida-
tive products of lipids, amino acids, and peptides. Increases 
in FORT values most likely indicate an increase in the oxi-
dation of lipids, which occurs in lipid bilayers and lipid par-
ticles [28]. This oxidative marker also reflects specific cel-</p>

<p>lular oxidation events. Abramson et al suggested that oxi-
dative stress, as measured by the free radical oxygen test, 
may be a determinant of C-reactive protein levels and pro-
mote pro-atherosclerotic inflammatory processes [29]. In 
the present study, the correlation between FORT and the 
acute-phase reactant C-reactive protein was evaluated 
and a significant positive correlation was found. Increasing 
FORT values also indicate inflammatory processes. I-R led 
to increased oxidative stress in the testis, but KRG had a 
protective effect against the oxidation of lipid bilayers and 
inflammatory processes. 
Among various sources of superoxide such as NADPH 
oxidase, xanthine oxidase, lipoxygenase, mitochondrial 
oxidase, and nitric oxide synthase, NADPH oxidase appears 
to be the principal source of superoxide in several animal 
models. In the present study, KRG inhibited basal super-
oxide production and NADPH oxidase in the testis. KRG in-
hibits the generation of reactive oxygen species that dam-
age the cellular membranes. Post-treatment with KRG 
protects this continuing membrane damage that underlies 
progressive testis dysfunction. 
In conclusion, KRG is a potent antioxidant agent that 
protects against oxidative damage to the testis tissue. KRG 
treatment prevents testis dysfunction via decreased pro-
duction of NADPH oxidase and superoxide. Based on the 
results of this study, we suggest that KRG may play a role 
in the protection of I-R-induced oxidant injury in the rat 
testis. However, in vivo and in vitro studies are required 
to determine the exact role that KRG plays in the protection 
of the testes against I-R injury. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>The results of the present study demonstrated that I-R 
leads to testis dysfunction, as well as the induction of ROS. 
The present study demonstrated that KRG recovered the 
testis dysfunction caused by ischemia and subsequent re-
perfusion in the rat testis through the suppression of su-
peroxide production. Further studies are needed to explain 
the mechanisms of protection. </p>

<p>Conflicts of Interest 
The authors have nothing to disclose. </p>



<p>Korean J Urol 2010;51:794-799 </p>

<p>Effect of Korean Red Ginseng on Testicular Torsion </p>





</text></tei>