<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2529246" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:29+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Mass spectrometry (MS) has become increasingly 
important for tissue specific protein quantification at 
the isoform level, as well as for the analysis of protein 
post-translational regulation mechanisms and turnover 
rates. Thanks to the development of high accuracy 
mass spectrometers, peptide sequencing without prior 
knowledge of the amino acid sequence-de novo 
sequencing-can be performed. In this work, absolute 
quantification of a set of key enzymes involved in 
carbon and nitrogen metabolism in Medicago trunca-
tula 'Jemalong A17' root nodules is presented. Among 
them, sucrose synthase (SuSy; EC 2.4.1.13), one of the 
central enzymes in sucrose cleavage in root nodules, 
has been further characterized and the relative phos-
phorylation state of the three most abundant isoforms 
has been quantified. De novo sequencing provided 
sequence information of a so far unidentified peptide, 
most probably belonging to SuSy2, the second most 
abundant isoform in M. truncatula root nodules. TiO 2 -
phosphopeptide enrichment led to the identification of 
not only a phosphorylation site at Ser11 in SuSy1, but 
also of several novel phosphorylation sites present in 
other root nodule proteins such as alkaline invertase 
(AI; EC 3.2.1.26) and an RNA-binding protein. </p>

<p>Legumes are able to establish nitrogen-fixing symbiotic 
relations with soil bacteria generally termed rhizobia. This 
symbiosis is beneficial for both partners: plants provide 
a carbon source and nutrients for the microsymbiont 
which, in return, produces a reduced form of nitrogen 
directly assimilatable by the plant. Sucrose is the main 
carbohydrate transported via phloem to sink tissues like 
nodules, where it is metabolized by either SuSy or AI 
(Morell and Copeland, 1984; Flemetakis et al., 2006). 
SuSy is a cytosolic enzyme, which catalyses the cleavage 
of sucrose to fructose and UDP-glucose (Okamoto and 
Akazawa, 1980). This enzyme is considered primarily 
responsible for sucrose metabolism in mature nitrogen-
fixing nodules, as it has been shown to be essential for 
symbiotic nitrogen fixation in a variety of legume plants 
(Gordon et al., 1999; Horst et al., 2007; Kuster et al., 
2007). In addition, it has been demonstrated that SuSy is </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail: wienkoop@mpimp-golm.mpg.de 
Abbreviations: AAT, aspartate aminotransferase; AI, alkaline invertase; AS, asparagine synthetase; GDH, glutamate dehydrogenase; GOGAT, glutamate 
synthase; GS, glutamine synthetase; LC-MS/MS, liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry; Q-TOF, quadrupole time of flight; SuSy, sucrose 
synthase. </p>

<p>ª 2008 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which 
permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>involved in the regulation of nitrogen fixation under 
different abiotic stresses, both at the transcriptional and 
post-transcriptional level (Gonzalez et al., 1995; Gordon 
et al., 1997; Zhang et al., 1999). 
SuSy has been well-characterized at the molecular level 
in the model legume Medicago truncatula (Hohnjec et al., 
1999, 2003). Based on transcriptional profiles, five iso-
forms have been described that are expressed in root 
nodules. However, a recent multi-dimensional LC-MS/ 
MS-based proteomic profiling study which identified 
around 400 proteins from M. truncatula root nodules was 
only able to identify SuSy1, the most abundant isoform 
(Larrainzar et al., 2007). In contrast to shotgun proteomic 
techniques, targeted MS approaches allow for the de-
tection and quantification of low abundance proteins 
present in complex samples (Wienkoop and Weckwerth, 
2006; Mallick et al., 2007). While western blots are very 
sensitive and have been widely used for semi-quantitative 
protein analysis, absolute quantification can only be 
achieved when used in conjunction isoform specific 
antibodies and is subsequently scarcely used (Duncan 
et al., 2006). Thus, the fact that protein quantification by 
western blots is only relative, the requirement of specific 
antibodies, together with the limitation in the number of 
proteins detectable per analysis, has led to the develop-
ment of alternative LC/MS-based techniques such as the 
so-called 'mass western' (Lehmann et al., 2008). 
In this current work, a selective LC-MS/MS-based 
method using synthetic isotope-labelled peptides (Wienkoop 
and Weckwerth, 2006) has been applied for accurate 
quantification of SuSy proteins and other nodule meta-
bolic enzymes (Fig. 1). Within a single analysis, several 
proteins involved in root nodule N metabolism as well as 
SuSy were detected and quantified with high sensitivity in 
absolute terms. Specific identification of different SuSy 
isoforms sharing high sequence similarity is presented. 
Furthermore, phosphopeptide-enrichment techniques have </p>

<p>been applied to analyse the state of SuSy1 phosphoryla-
tion as well as for the identification of new phosphoryla-
tion sites in several nodule proteins. A schematic 
overview of the workflow can be found in Fig. 1. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant growth conditions and nodule harvest 
Medicago truncatula 'Jemalong A17' plants were inoculated with 
Sinorhizobium meliloti strain 2011. Plants were grown in 1.0 l pots 
with a mixture of vermiculite:perlite (5:2 v:v) as substrate under 
controlled environment conditions (14/10 h day/night, 22/16 °C 
temperature, and 70/60% relative humidity). The photosynthetic 
photon flux was 600 lmol m À2 s À1 . When plants were 10 weeks 
old, root nodules were collected, frozen in liquid nitrogen and 
stored at -80 °C for further analysis. </p>

<p>Protein extraction 
Nodules (0.1 g fresh weight) were homogenized in a mortar and 
pestle with 0.5 ml ice-cold homogenization buffer (50 mM HEPES, 
pH 7.8). Homogenates were centrifuged at 2000 g at 4 °C for 15 
min and supernatants were collected and kept as nodule plant 
fractions. </p>

<p>Generation of stable isotope-labelled peptides 
For absolute quantification of SuSy and proteins involved in nodule 
N assimilation, isoform-specific 13 C/ 15 N leucine-labelled peptides 
were synthesized (Thermo Electron, Ulm, Germany) and employed 
as internal standard peptides. Two approaches were used for the 
selection of peptides, empirical (i) and theoretical (ii). </p>

<p>(i) Many of the proteins that were to be targeted for quantitation 
had already been previously identified by MS (Larrainzar et al., 
2007). Consequently, peptides derived from these proteins were 
already known and can be found in the ProMEX spectral library 
(Hummel et al., 2007). From this list of peptides, isoform-specific 
peptides were selected according to the recommendations of 
Thermo Electron in the instructions for the design of heavy peptide 
standards. The guidelines advise on sequence length and on the 
avoidance of certain amino acids that are common targets of 
uncontrolled modifications and in some cases were limiting factors 
for the successful selection of candidate peptides. </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Schematic workflow of the different MS analysis carried out. ID, identification. </p>



<p>(ii) Peptides selected for quantitation that had not been 
identified by MS in previous studies were designed based on 
proteotypic peptide prediction. In the case of the SuSy isoforms 
where peptides from SuSy1 have previously been identified, the 
peptide sequences were aligned and proteotypic peptides from the 
other isoforms selected based on similarity to a known peptide from 
SuSy1. These peptides displayed changes in amino acid composi-
tion that resulted in significant mass differences and thus a specific 
proteotypic peptide for each isoform (Fig. 2, framed segment). </p>

<p>Detailed information about peptide sequences and specific single 
reaction monitoring transition data can be found in Table 1. Peptide 
mass shifts caused by methionine oxidation reactions were below 
1% and, therefore, did not significantly influence the quantification. </p>

<p>SDS-PAGE and in-gel protein digestion 
Prior to mass western analyses, plant nodule protein extracts (80 lg 
of protein per sample) were separated by SDS-PAGE on 6% (w/v) 
polyacrylamide gels. After electrophoresis, proteins were visualized 
using Gel-Code Blue Stain reagent (Pierce Biotechnology, Rockford, 
USA). For the specific analysis of SuSy isoforms and determination 
of phosphorylation levels, gel bands corresponding to a molecular 
weight of approximately 90 kDa were cut out and standard synthetic 
peptides were added. For the identification of novel phosphopro-
teins, bands in the range between 25-60 kDa were also excised from 
the gels. A total number of four gel band replicates were analysed. 
In-gel digestion was carried out as previously described by 
Shevchenko et al. (1996). </p>

<p>In-solution protein digestion 
Aliquots containing 50 lg of plant nodule proteins were digested 
overnight at 37 °C with Porosyzme immobilized trypsin beads </p>

<p>(1:10, v/v, Applied Biosystems, Darmstadt, Germany). After 
centrifugation to remove beads the peptide mixtures were desalted 
using SPEC C18 columns according to the manufacturer's instruc-
tions (Varian, Darmstadt, Germany). Desalted digest solutions were 
dried and pellets stored at -20 °C until use. Four biological 
replicates were analysed. </p>

<p>Phosphopeptide enrichment 
For the identification of novel nodule phosphopeptides, gel digests 
corresponding to protein bands within the range of 25-60 kDa were 
loaded onto titanium dioxide columns (TiO 2 , TopTips) purchased 
from SunChrom (Friedrichsdorf, Germany). Phosphopeptide enrich-
ment was carried out as previously described by Mazanek et al. 
(2007). </p>

<p>Determination of phosphorylation stoichiometry 
To determine the relative phosphorylation states of proteins, 
corresponding bands were excised from SDS-PAGE gels, digested, 
and analysed by MS. Relative abundance was assessed by comparing 
peak areas for the phosphorylated and non-phosphorylated tryptic 
peptides (see also 'Orbitrap settings for the identification of 
phosphopeptides and relative phosphorylation state analysis', and 
the workflow diagram in Fig. 1). </p>

<p>Q-TOF settings for de novo sequencing analysis 
For de novo sequencing, gel digests corresponding to SuSy were 
loaded onto a HPLC system (Waters 2695 Alliance, Waters GmbH, 
Eschborn, Germany) directly coupled to a Q-TOF mass spectrom-
eter (Waters GmbH, Eschborn, Germany). Peptides were eluted 
using a 15-min gradient from 0-80% (v/v) acetonitrile (ACN)/0.1% 
(v/v) formic acid (FA) using a C18 column (15031 mm, Jupiter 4l </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Alignment of SuSy isoforms sequences of M. truncatula. The de novo peptide sequence is included in bold as part of SuSy2 isoform. Framed 
segment indicates the proteotypic peptides from the SuSy isofroms selected for absolute quantification. </p>

<p>Absolute quantification of nodule proteins based on mass western and phosphoproteomics 3309 </p>

<p>Proteo 90A, Phenomenex, Aschaffenburg, Germany). De novo 
sequencing was performed using <rs type="software">Mass Lynx software</rs> (Waters 
GmbH, Eschborn, Germany). The software was programmed to 
screen for the doubly charged precursor masses 521.7 and 602.8 of 
the known SuSy peptides (ALESEMLSR and SIGNGVQFLNR, 
corresponding to SuSy1; TC100410), a mass 527.2 for ALENEM-
LAR (corresponding to isoform SuSy2; TC95820) and a mass of 
602.8 plus a mass shift of 0.5, in an attempt to identify a possible 
sequence variation due to amino acid differences encoded by single 
nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs), for example, glutamine (Q)/ 
glutamic acid (E) or asparagine (N)/aspartic acid (D) exchange. </p>

<p>Triple quadrupole settings for absolute quantification 
For the identification and absolute quantification of different SuSy 
isoforms, a one-dimensional (1D) nano-flow LC-MS/MS system 
equipped with a pre-column (Agilent, Zeesen, Germany) was 
employed. Peptides were eluted using a monolithic column (Merck, 
Darmstadt, Germany) of 15 cm length and 0.1 mm internal diameter 
during a 30 min gradient from 5% to 100% (v/v) methanol/0.1% (v/v) 
FA with a controlled flow rate of 0.7 ll min À1 . 1 pmol of each 
internal standard peptide was added to the protein sample prior to 
analysis, as peptides at this concentration have been shown to lie 
within the linear range of detection (Wienkoop and Weckwerth, 
2006). MS analysis was performed on a TSQ Quantum Discovery 
MAX mass spectrometer (Thermo Electron, Ulm, Germany) 
operated in the positive mode and tuned to its optimum sensitivity 
for each standard peptide as previously described (Glinski and 
Weckwerth, 2005). Scan width for all MRMs (multiple reaction 
monitoring) was 0.7 mass units, and resolution was set to 0.25 and 
0.7 mass units for Q1 and Q3, respectively. The dwell time per 
transition was 50 ms, spray voltage was set to 1.8 kV and 
temperature of heated transfer capillary was set to 150 °C. Collision 
energies used for recorded transitions are summarized in Table 1. 
Absolute quantification was performed based on peak integration. </p>

<p>Orbitrap settings for the identification of phosphopeptides and 
relative phosphorylation state analysis 
After phosphopeptide enrichment, TiO 2 -peptide eluates were loaded 
on a 1D nano-flow LC-MS/MS system equipped with pre-column </p>

<p>(Agilent, Zeesen, Germany). A monolithic column (Merck, 
Darmstadt, Germany) of 15 cm length and 0.1 mm internal diameter 
was coupled to an Orbitrap LTQ XL mass spectrometer (Thermo 
Electron, Ulm, Germany). Peptides were eluted during a 50-min 
gradient from 5-100% (v/v) methanol/0.1% (v/v) FA with a con-
trolled flow rate of 0.5 ll min À1 . For precursor masses determi-
nations, resolution and accuracy of the Orbitrap were set to 
3000 ppm and 2 ppm, respectively. MS/MS measurements 
were performed on wideband mode. Spray voltage was set to 1.8 
kV and temperature of the heated transfer capillary was set to 
150 °C. Potential phosphopeptide candidates were evaluated 
using <rs id="software-1" type="software">MSQuant</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">1.4</rs> software. A post-translational modification 
(PTM) score for localization, which estimates the probability to 
find an actual phosphorylation site based on fragment ions 
(Olsen et al., 2006), is shown in Table 2. For the relative 
quantification of phosphorylation levels, gel digests were directly 
analysed using the same settings as described for phosphopeptide 
identification. </p>

<p>Results and discussion </p>

<p>Detection of different SuSy isoforms in M. truncatula 
root nodules 
Although detection of three SuSy isoforms using isoform-
specific antibodies has been reported in maize (Duncan 
et al., 2006), multi-dimensional LC-MS/MS and western 
blot analysis did not allow detection of SuSy isoforms 
other than SuSy1 in M. truncatula root nodules (Larrainzar 
et al., 2007). This is probably due to the relatively low 
abundance of the other isoforms, together with the 
similarity they share at the amino acid sequence level, 
which limits an MS/MS-based discrimination. Figure 2 
represents an alignment of the N-terminal region of the 
five described SuSy isoform sequences. Sequences for 
SuSy1 and SuSy3 (TC94447) appear to be complete, 
whereas the known sequences for SuSy2 (TC95820), </p>

<p>Table 1. Triple quadrupole tune settings for the specific standard peptides used for absolute quantification </p>

<p>Peptide sequences employed in this work, as well as their corresponding precursor masses and product ions are given. Stable isotope-labelled leucine 
residues are marked in bold. </p>

<p>TC code 
Name 
Peptide sequence 
Standard peptide 
Native peptide </p>

<p>Precursor 
ion (m/z) </p>

<p>Product 
ions (m/z) </p>

<p>Collision 
energy </p>

<p>Precursor 
ion (m/z) </p>

<p>Productions 
(m/z) </p>

<p>Collision 
energy </p>

<p>TC100391 
AS 
STYAWGLEAR 
580.7 
738.3 
19 
577.2 
731.3 
19 
TC100393 
AS 
STFAWGLEAR 
572.8 
552.2 
18 
569.3 
545.2 
18 
TC106729 
GS1a 
ITEIAGVVVSFDPK 
741.4 
243.9 
36 
737.9 
243.9 
36 
TC106808 
GS1b 
HETADINTFLWGVANR 
617.6 
702.3 
19 
615.3 
702.3 
19 
TC106913 
GS2 
IHIEAYGEGNER 
465.5 
475.1 
14 
463.2 
475.1 
14 
TC94780 
GOGAT 
EVLVDFDNLLPK 
704.9 
1166 
17 
701.4 
1159 
17 
TC94631 
AAT2 
ATAELLLGADNPAIK 
752.4 
785.4 
22 
748.9 
785.4 
22 
TC106918 
AAT1 
TEEGKPLVLDVVR 
487.9 
917.6 
19 
485.6 
910.6 
19 
TC94623 
AAT 
IPSGHGYDDFEVVR 
534.2 
744.3 
18 
530.9 
739.3 
18 
TC94704 
GDH 
GLDIPSLLK 
481.8 
564.3 
15 
478.3 
557.3 
15 
TC100410 
SuSy1 
VHSLKER 
438.2 
639.3 
18 
434.7 
632.3 
18 
TC100410 
SuSy1 
ALESEMLSR 
521.7 
851.4 
18 
518.2 
851.4 
18 
TC95820 
SuSy2 
ALENEMLAR 
527.2 
862.4 
18 
523.7 
862.4 
18 
TC94447 
SuSy3 
ALENEMLR 
491.7 
791.3 
17 
488.2 
791.3 
17 
TC99016 
SuSy5 
ALEEELLQK 
540.2 
888.5 
18 
536.7 
888.5 
18 </p>

<p>3310 Wienkoop et al. </p>

<p>SuSy5 (TC99016), and SuSy4 (TC98648) are estimated to 
be 72, 40, and 19%, respectively. To improve the 
detection of different SuSy isoforms in root nodules 
further, two approaches were carried out: (i) targeted 
screening for peptide sequence variation using a Q-TOF 
mass spectrometer with high mass accuracy; and (ii) 
multiple reaction monitoring on a triple quadrupole based 
on predicted proteotypic peptides. </p>

<p>Identification of a new SuSy peptide sequence 
When comparing sequences of protein isoforms, it is 
common to find certain amino acid differences encoded 
by SNPs [i.e. glutamine (Q) for glutamic acid (E) or 
asparagine (N) for aspartic acid (D)]. These sequence 
variations are translated into mass differences in peptides 
enabling isoform discrimination using MS. Looking for 
this type of polymorphism, the predicted amino acid 
sequences of the SuSy isoforms were aligned (Fig. 2) and 
examined for potential candidates with this type of 
polymorphism. A SuSy1 tryptic peptide containing some 
of the above-mentioned residues was subsequently chosen 
(SIGNGVQFLNR). After screening the gel sample for 
masses corresponding to the doubly charged peptide, two 
ions were selected: one corresponding to a mass-to-charge 
ratio (m/z) of 602.8 derived from a SuSy1 tryptic peptide, 
and the other peptide of unknown sequence with an m/z </p>

<p>of 603.3. De novo sequencing was performed on the 
unknown ion and was identified as the peptide 
(SI)GDGVQFLNR (Fig. 3), which did not match any of 
the previously reported sequences (Fig. 2). The observed 
mass difference corresponds to a shift starting from ion 
y7, explained by a replacement of D instead of the 
original N residue present in SuSy1. The only other 
possible combination producing a 603.3 m/z peptide 
would be the replacement of isoleucine (I) for leucine (L) 
in the N-terminal region. However, as this region appears 
to be well-conserved in the amino acid sequence of SuSy 
in different legume plants (data not shown), this alterna-
tive appears to be less likely. Furthermore, peptides 
derived from both SuSy1 and SuSy2 were detected during 
the analysis of 1D-PAGE samples (see Materials and 
methods and Fig. 2), further supporting the hypothesis 
that the new peptide is driven from SuSy2 (Fig. 2). 
Interestingly, SuSy2 is the second most abundant isoform 
in M. truncatula root nodules at the transcript level 
(Hohnjec et al., 2003). </p>

<p>Mass western of different SuSy isoforms in root 
nodules 
For the specific absolute quantification of protein iso-
forms, a technique based on high resolution multiple 
reaction monitoring in a triple quadrupole mass spectrom-
eter, called mass western, has recently been established 
(Lehmann et al., 2008). Instead of antibodies, isoform-
specific stable isotope-labelled peptides are synthesized. 
These are then employed as internal standards and added 
to protein samples, which are subsequently digested either 
in gel or directly in solution (Wienkoop and Weckwerth, 
2006). As the concentration of the standard peptides is 
known, absolute quantification of native proteins is 
achievable in fmol lg À1 of total protein. 
In the present study, four standard peptides specific for 
each of the isoforms SuSy1, 2, 3, and 5 were selected 
(Table 1). As only 19% of the SuSy4 sequence is </p>

<p>Table 2. Phosphopeptides found in M. truncatula root nodules 
after TiO 2 -enrichment and MSQuant validation (PTM: post-
translational modification) </p>

<p>Protein 
Peptide sequence 
Phospho 
site </p>

<p>Mascot 
score </p>

<p>MSQuant 
PTM score </p>

<p>TC106886 AGLDNYDNYS(p)PGGR Ser65 
69 
114 
SGFNTPAS(p)SAR 
Ser77 
48 
73 
TC101080 KHASS(p)PPPDSPSQ 
DSVEKPTYVR </p>

<p>Ser21 
53 
60 </p>

<p>TC97295 HQSAAT(p)PTPTAGAR Thr33 
40 
70 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Q-TOF driven MS/MS spectrum of the de novo sequence for a tryptic peptide with m/z 603.3 (SIGDGVQFLNR). </p>

<p>Absolute quantification of nodule proteins based on mass western and phosphoproteomics 3311 </p>

<p>available (Fig. 2), this isoform was excluded from the 
analysis. Out of the four isoforms analysed, absolute 
quantification was only possible for three of them 
(Table 3; Fig. 4). SuSy5 appeared either to be below the 
detection limit or not present in nodules under the 
conditions investigated. Results show that SuSy2 is the 
second most abundant isoform present in M. truncatula 
root nodules. This finding further supports the hypothesis 
that the de novo peptide sequence belongs to this second </p>

<p>isoform. Due to the high sensitivity of this technique, 
SuSy3 was also successfully identified, despite its much 
weaker signal (Fig. 4). Absolute quantification of the 
different isoforms shows that the protein ratios for 
SuSy1:SuSy2:SuSy3 are 1:0.013:0.0018 (Table 3). These 
results are in agreement with a recent transcript analysis in 
pea nodules (Marino et al., 2008), where the ratio for the 
three isoforms was 1:0.002:1.7 3 10 À5 . From a technical 
point of view, the four orders of magnitude range 
determined in a single analysis corresponds to the current 
maximum capacity for a MS-based analysis (Wienkoop 
et al., 2006; Wienkoop and Weckwerth, 2006). This 
limitation is mainly due to the limit of detection of each 
peptide and the loading capacity of the columns. Never-
theless, the sensitivity (2 ng) in the present study has been 
shown to be comparable to those of western blots 
(Lehmann et al., 2008). A significant advantage of the 
mass western is that it allows for absolute quantification 
and for multiple targets to be analysed in a single run. 
Furthermore, mass western provides a direct measurement 
of protein concentration, not available by transcript 
analysis. </p>

<p>Table 3. Absolute quantification of three different SuSy iso-
forms in M. truncatula root nodules after in-gel digestion (n¼4) </p>

<p>TC Code 
Name 
Specific amount a </p>

<p>fmol lg À1 
protein </p>

<p>pmol per 
gel slide </p>

<p>ng per 
gel slide </p>

<p>TC100410 
SuSy1 
16062.21 
12.8 
1000 
TC95820 
SuSy2 
2.160.03 
0.170 
16 
TC94447 
SuSy3 
0.360.25 
0.023 
2 
TC99016 
SuSy5 
n.d. 
n.d. 
n.d. </p>

<p>a n.d., Not detected. </p>

<p>23.10 </p>

<p>23.24 </p>

<p>NL: 
1.57E5 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
521.70@-
18.00 [ 
721.95-851.75] </p>

<p>NL: 
2.01E7 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
518.20@-
18.00 [ 
721.95-851.75] </p>

<p>NL: 
1.40E5 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
527.20@-
18.00 [ 
732.95-862.75] </p>

<p>NL: 
7.80E4 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
523.80@-
18.00 [ 
732.95-862.75] </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
50 </p>

<p>Time(min) </p>

<p>5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 
35 
40 
45 
50 </p>

<p>Time(min) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 
0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>22.95 </p>

<p>32.24 
32.21 </p>

<p>NL: 
2.58E5 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
491.70@-
17.00 [ 
191.65-791.65] </p>

<p>NL: 
3.17E4 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
488.20@-
17.00 [ 
184.65-791.65] </p>

<p>NL: 
2.15E6 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
540.20@-
18.00 [ 
191.65-888.85] </p>

<p>NL: 
6.94E2 
TIC F: + p 
SRM ms2 
536.80@-
18.00 [ 
184.65-888.85] </p>

<p>TC100410 </p>

<p>TC95820 
TC99016 </p>

<p>TC94447 </p>

<p>Standard iontrace 
Standard iontrace </p>

<p>Standard iontrace 
Standard iontrace </p>

<p>Native iontrace </p>

<p>Native iontrace 
Native iontrace </p>

<p>Native iontrace </p>

<p>RT: 23.10 </p>

<p>RT: 23.24 
RT: 25.46 </p>

<p>RT: 22.96 </p>

<p>Relative Abundance 
Relative Abundance </p>

<p>SuSy1 </p>

<p>SuSy2 </p>

<p>SuSy3 </p>

<p>SuSy5 </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Mass western of four SuSy isoforms detected in M. truncatula root nodule protein extract using a triple quadrupole mass spectrometer and 
specific stable isotope-labelled standard peptides (see Table 1). </p>



<p>Absolute quantification of proteins involved in N 
metabolism present in complex nodule protein 
samples </p>

<p>Absolute quantification enables the analysis of complete 
metabolic pathways in complex protein samples in a single 
analysis. In contrast to the previous analysis, where the 
starting materials employed were in-gel digests, absolute 
quantification was also carried out using nodule extract 
protein samples as the starting material. Internal standard 
peptides for glutamine synthetase (GS), glutamate de-
hydrogenase (GDH), asparagine synthetase (AS), and 
aspartate aminotransferase (AAT) were synthesized (pep-
tide sequences shown in Table 1), and these metabolic 
enzymes, together with SuSy, were subjected to absolute 
quantification (Table 4). Regarding SuSy, only the most 
abundant isoform, SuSy1, representing about 1% of the 
total nodule proteins, was detected. The reason for this 
might be a higher signal-to-noise ratio of a complex 
protein sample compared to the pre-fractionated gel 
sample used in the previous analysis. However, the 
absolute amount of SuSy1 appears to be slightly higher in 
the complex nodule protein analysis indicating that the in-
gel analysis may be even more sensitive. 
Most of these enzymes involved in nodule N metabo-
lism (GS, GDH, AAT) are well characterized and their 
activities are routinely assessed (Vance, 2008). Although 
most of the N exported from temperate climate nodules is 
in the form of asparagine, detection of AS activity in plant 
tissues is extremely difficult (Lea et al., 2007). The 
reasons for this are not clear, but they may be related to 
the presence of inhibitors (Joy et al., 1983), asparaginase 
activity (Streeter, 1977) or protein instability (Huber and 
Streeter, 1985). To overcome these limitations, quantifica-
tion of AS gene expression has been suggested to be 
a good semi-quantitative indicator of its activity levels, 
showing a good correlation with asparagine:aspartate 
ratios transported to the shoot via the xylem (Antunes 
et al., 2008). The strategy shown in the present paper may </p>

<p>provide a more accurate alternative for the quantification 
of AS in nodules. </p>

<p>Identification of phosphorylation sites and 
determination of the phosphorylation state of SuSy1 
in nodules under normal growth conditions </p>

<p>SuSy has been shown to be phosphorylated in a number 
of tissues in different plants. While initial evidence that 
SuSy was phosphorylated came from work on maize cell 
cultures (Shaw et al., 1994), it was Huber et al. (1996) 
who first characterized a phosphorylation site at Ser15 in 
SuSy isolated from maize leaves. Further studies have 
described other phosphorylation sites in maize (Hardin 
et al., 2003) and legume plants like soybean (Zhang and 
Chollet, 1997; Zhang et al., 1999; Komina et al., 2002). 
In particular, Zhang et al. (1999) described a putative 
seryl-phosphorylation domain near the N-terminus of the 
protein (LTRVHS 11 LRER) in soybean. This motif, which 
was reported to be the primary phosphorylation site of 
nodule soybean SuSy in planta, is present in practically 
all the SuSy sequences reported to date. 
In the present work, MS analysis revealed that SuSy1 
from the nodules of M. truncatula is also phosphorylated 
at Ser11, the same residue identified as phosphorylated in 
soybean and homologous to Ser15 in maize SuSy1 
(VHS 11 LKER; spectra can be found in <rs id="software-5" type="software">ProMEX</rs> database 
<rs corresp="#software-5" type="url">http://promex.mpimp-golm.mpg.de/home.shtml</rs>). In addi-
tion, the relative phosphorylation state of the protein was 
analysed and quantified by comparing peak areas of the 
phosphorylated and non-phosphorylated tryptic peptides 
derived from the same analysis (see also 'Determination 
of phosphorylation stoichiometry', and the workflow 
diagram in Fig. 1). 
M. truncatula nodule SuSy1 was found to be hyper-
phosphorylated, as the phosphopeptide was 1.7-fold more 
abundant than the non-phosphorylated peptide. The 
meaning of this hyperphosphorylation state remains the 
subject of much debate. In soybean, in vitro studies 
suggest that nodule SuSy sucrose-cleavage activity is not 
dependent on the phosphorylation state of the protein, but 
rather influences the attachment of this enzyme to the 
membrane (Zhang et al., 1999). However, studies in 
maize have shown that leaf SuSy is activated when 
phosphorylated at its primary site (Ser15), while phos-
phorylation at Ser170 would trigger degradation of the 
enzyme (Hardin et al., 2003, 2004). More recently, it has 
been suggested that sucrose concentration and phosphor-
ylation may regulate SuSy oligomerization and F-actin 
association in maize kernels and seedlings (Duncan and 
Huber, 2007). Regarding membrane attachment, Komina 
et al. (2002) investigated the phosphorylation state of 
membrane and soluble SuSy forms of nodules in soybean. 
Using several non-MS-based approaches, the microsomal 
SuSy fraction was found to be hypophosphorylated </p>

<p>Table 4. Absolute quantification of several proteins involved in 
C and N metabolism in M. truncatula root nodules after gel free 
shotgun analysis </p>

<p>TC Code 
Name 
fmol mg À1 protein a </p>

<p>TC100410 
SuSy1 
195.2623.7 
TC95820 
SuSy2 
n.d. 
TC94447 
SuSy3 
n.d. 
TC100391 
AS 
76.562.5 
TC100393 
AS 
90.568.5 
TC106729 
GS1a 
98.961.0 
TC106808 
GS1b 
29.668.6 
TC106913 
GS2 
23.865.8 
TC94631 
AAT2 
44.360.9 
TC106918 
AAT1 
5.160.9 
TC94623 
AAT 
20.764.1 
TC94704 
GDH 
51.169.3 </p>

<p>a n.d., Not detected. </p>

<p>Absolute quantification of nodule proteins based on mass western and phosphoproteomics 3313 </p>

<p>relative to the soluble form (on an equivalent SuSy protein 
base). Although abiotic stresses seem to have a negative 
impact on SuSy abundance, as well as on its phosphory-
lation levels (data not shown), the physiological meaning 
of a state of hyper-or hypophosphorylation remains to be 
elucidated. </p>

<p>Other phosphoproteins found in nodules 
SuSy is one of the most characterized nodule proteins in 
legumes. Due to its relatively high abundance in root 
nodules and, specifically with regard to M. truncatula, its 
hyperphosphorylation state, it is understandable that the 
conserved Ser11 phosphopeptide has been described 
several times. In order to identify novel putative phos-
phorylated proteins in M. truncatula root nodules, a phos-
phopeptide enrichment strategy based on TiO 2 -affinity 
chromatography was carried out. As a result, several other 
phosphopetides were identified (Table 2). Among them, 
two phosphopeptides (AGLDNYDNYS 65 PGGR and 
SGFNTPAS 77 SAR) belonging to AI (TC106886), the 
other enzyme with a sucrose-cleavage activity in nodules. 
In contrast to SuSy, relative peak area quantification of 
both peptides indicated that AI is mostly hypophospory-
lated in nodules. The non-phosphorylated to the phos-
phorylated forms of Ser65 and Ser77 were determined to 
be in a ratio of 1:0.01:0.03, respectively. It has been 
suggested that AI is post-transcriptionally regulated 
through an interaction with a phospho-binding 14-3-3 
protein in developing barley grains (Alexander and 
Morris, 2006). However, to our knowledge this is the first 
report where the actual phosphorylation sites of the 
protein are described. Several other phosphopeptides were 
found that belong to a putative RNA-binding protein 
(TC101080) and a hypothetical protein (TC97295), which 
is similar to a universal stress response protein described 
in Arabidopsis thaliana (At4g27320) (Table 2). Although, 
thus far, little is known about the function of these 
proteins in nodules, they may be considered interesting 
candidates for further studies given the roles of phosphor-
ylation in metabolic regulation. 
Nevertheless, several other nodule proteins have been 
suggested to be phosphorylated and were not identified in 
this present study. This is the case for both GS (Lima et al., 
2006) and phosphoenolpyruvate decarboxylase (Zhang 
et al., 1995) from M. truncatula. Previously reported 
phosphopeptides from GS did not appear to be detectable 
after tryptic digestion, but may be detected using different 
proteolytic enzymes. In the case of phosphoenolpyruvate 
decarboxylase, phosphopeptides were not detected using 
the current approach as its molecular weight was out of 
range of the analysed bands subjected to TiO 2 enrichment. 
Therefore, future analysis may include a wider range of 
molecular weights to identify new nodule protein subject 
to protein phosphorylation. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>This study has demonstrated for the first time the absolute 
quantification of three distinct M. truncatula SuSy isoforms 
in an independent tissue-specific manner. It is shown 
that, besides the nodule-enhanced SuSy1, two other protein 
isoforms are present in root nodules at quantifiable 
amounts. De novo sequencing allowed for the identification 
of a new peptide sequence, most probably driven from the 
second most abundant isoform SuSy2, which complements 
the existing sequence information based on transcript data. 
Absolute quantification of N metabolism enzymes was 
carried out, enabling the discrimination of different protein 
isoforms from a single analysis, even when those isoforms 
were present at very low amounts. Nodule SuSy1 was 
shown to be hyperphosphorylated at Ser11 in M. truncatula 
and novel phosphoproteins present in nodules were 
identified. All peptides found in this study can be viewed 
in the <rs type="software">ProMEX</rs> spectral library (Hummel et al., 2007). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>We thank Joshua L Heazlewood and Waltraud Schulze for helpful 
discussion. A special thank you to Wolfgang  and 
Joshua L Heazlewood for proof reading. EL is the holder of 
a  de Profesorado Universitario PhD fellowship from the 
Spanish Ministry of Education and Science. EL, EMG, and CA-I 
acknowledge financial support from DGI-MEC (Spain) grant 
AGL2005-0274/AGR and its associated FEDER funding. CA-I also 
wishes to acknowledge the support provided by the Mobility 
Programme of the Spanish Ministry of Education and Science. </p>



<p>Absolute quantification of nodule proteins based on mass western and phosphoproteomics 3315 </p>

</text></tei>