<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2678927" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.3-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-12-07T20:06+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE) is a prototype auto-
immune disease characterized by autoantibody production and 
multiple organ damage. Both strong genetic predisposing 
factors and environmental effects are involved in the disease, 
and there are apparent population differences in terms of 
disease prevalence and manifestations (1). Asians have a </p>

<p>higher disease prevalence (100 patients/100 000 for women) 
and more renal involvement (2 -4) than Caucasians. Population 
differences in term of susceptibility genes were also well docu-
mented (5 -7). Identifying differences in genetic susceptibility 
towards the disease could shed light on the mechanisms of the 
disease and have implications on its clinical intervention. 
In several recent studies, ITGAM has been found to be 
associated with SLE (8 -11). In the study of Nath et al., </p>

<p> † Present address: Division of Medicine and Therapeutics, Ninewells Hospital and Medical School, Dundee, DD1 9SY, Tayside, UK. </p>

<p>Ã </p>

<p>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ86 85228554481; Fax: þ86 85228551523; Email: lauylung@hkucc.hku.hk </p>

<p># 2009. The Author(s) </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ 
licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is 
properly cited. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 
2063-2070 
doi:10.1093/hmg/ddp118 
Advance Access published on March 13, 2009 </p>

<p>SNP rs1143679, a non-synonymous SNP that converts Argi-
nine 77 to Histidine, showed the most significant association 
with the disease in Caucasians and also in two African-
American populations, among many other SNPs in the gene 
also with significant association. The study by Nath et al. 
found that any haplotype carrying the risk allele at 
rs1143679 explained the global haplotype association. In a 
recent study by Han et al. (11), the association and the role 
of rs1143679 were confirmed in several different ethnicities, 
such as Hispanic-and African-Americans, Mexicans and 
Colombians, with large number of samples studied. 
However, in their study, two Asian populations, the Japanese 
and Koreans, with a combination of 907 cases and 594 con-
trols examined, were found to be monomorphic on the SNPs 
associated with the disease in other populations. 
In this study, we have examined the involvement of ITGAM 
in two Asian populations: Chinese living in Hong Kong and 
Thai living in Bangkok. This study includes two independent 
experimental settings. In a genome-wide association study 
(GWAS), we genotyped 314 SLE samples collected in Hong 
Kong using Illumina 550K Beadchip and analyzed the data 
against 920 control samples. In another setting, by direct 
sequencing, we genotyped four SNPs in ITGAM, namely 
rs1143679, rs9888739, rs1143683 and rs1143678, in 918 
SLE cases and 1440 healthy controls from our Hong Kong col-
lection as well as case -control study samples collected in 
Thailand. Our study confirmed the association of the gene 
with SLE in these two populations. It also points out some 
potential differences between our findings and the reported 
results from other ethnicities. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Association of ITGAM with SLE by GWAS </p>

<p>We genotyped 320 SLE samples randomly selected from our 
Hong Kong SLE collection by Illunima 550K Beadchip, and 
314 of them passed quality control. We analyzed our case 
samples against 920 controls, which include 400 healthy indi-
viduals of Chinese ethnicity and 520 samples from two other 
studies on schizophrenia and HBV infection in Hong Kong 
Chinese. The allele frequencies of the ITGAM SNPs were 
found to be very similar in the three different control 
groups. In Table 1, we listed the SNPs in and around 
ITGAM (within 100 kb up-and down-stream of the gene) 
that showed significant association with the disease, together 
with rs11574637, the SNP that was found to be associated 
with SLE in the study of Hom et al. It can be seen from 
Figure 1 that all the five SNPs showed significant association 
with SLE in ITGAM have high linkage disequilibrium (LD) 
with each other. SNP rs11574637 was not associated with 
SLE in our population, a finding different from result reported 
by Hom et al. This result probably reflected the LD difference 
of rs11574637 with other SNPs in the ITGAM gene between 
the two populations (e.g. between rs1143683 and 
rs11574637, r 2 ¼ 0.8 and 0.65 in Caucasians and Chinese, 
respectively, Fig. 1). As speculated by Hom et al. and later 
confirmed by two other studies (8 -10), the association seen 
from rs11574637 is probably due to the LD with the non-
synonymous SNPs in the ITGAM gene. </p>

<p>Using the samples from our Hong Kong SLE collection, we 
further genotyped four SNPs that were found to be associated 
with SLE in the previous studies as well as from findings from 
our own GWAS. SNP rs1143679 was not on the Illumina 
550K Beadchip but was found to play a pivotal role in 
disease association reported by Nath et al. (10), and was there-
fore included for further study. In both Hong Kong samples 
and samples from Thailand, the association of ITGAM with 
SLE was confirmed (Table 2). Interestingly, the risk alleles 
are much lower in frequency in our populations compared 
with other populations, especially for the risk alleles in 
Hong Kong Chinese. Of the four SNPs genotyped, only 
rs1143683 and rs1143679 showed significant association 
with the disease in Hong Kong samples. The Thai samples 
showed much higher allele frequencies for these SNPs in the 
controls and significant association for all four SNPs geno-
typed. It seems that the risk alleles may have larger effect 
sizes in the Thai samples, but testing for heterogeneity of 
the ORs between the two populations were not significant. 
However, the negative result in the heterogeneity test 
between the two populations could be just a reflection of 
low power for this analysis. </p>

<p>Involvement of ITGAM towards severe disease 
manifestations </p>

<p>Since SLE is an extremely heterogeneous disease, we went on 
to ask the question whether the risk alleles in ITGAM are also 
associated with different manifestations in our Hong Kong 
samples. The risk alleles in the gene seem to show association 
only in the patients with renal nephritis but not in patients 
without, and comparison between patients with and without 
renal nephritis is significant for both rs1143683 and 
rs1143679 (P ¼ 0.022 and 0.029, respectively, Table 3). 
Similar findings were detected for patients with neurological 
disorders, for which significant association were found in 
patients positive for the phenotype despite the small sample 
size (n ¼ 46), whereas the association is marginally significant 
for the phenotype-negative patients (Table 3). For several 
other manifestations, the risk SNPs showed higher ORs in 
patients positive for the subphenotypes than in patients nega-
tive for them, such as on anti-dsDNA antibody, hematological 
disorder and immunological disorder, although patients-only 
analysis did not show significant difference. Interestingly, 
the risk alleles seem to associate with the disease in patients 
negative for photosensitivity. It should be noted that the sig-
nificance in statistics is before correction for multiple 
testing, and the subphenotype stratification test is prone to 
both false-positive and false-negative results (see Supplemen-
tary Material, Figs S1-S2 for power calculation of this study). 
A definitive conclusion for subphenotype association probably 
requires a significant increase in sample size and/or replication 
work in other Asian collections. </p>

<p>Independently contributing variants to the association </p>

<p>The studies by Nath et al. and Han et al. have demonstrated that 
the association on ITGAM gene probably stem from the risk 
allele at rs1143679, which converts Arginine 77 to Histidine. 
From analyzing the Hong Kong samples by logistic regression </p>

<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

<p>and conditioning on each single SNP, none of the SNPs geno-
typed showed significant association independent of one 
another, probably reflected the low power of the study on rare 
alleles. Logistic regression analysis on Thai samples indicates 
that rs1143679 remains significant when controlling the effect 
of rs9888739 or rs1143678. However, both rs1143679 and 
rs1143683 lose significant association when analyzed with 
each other in the logistic regression analysis. 
Haplotype analysis of the Hong Kong samples showed only 
marginal significance in disease association for haplotype 
TTAT formed by rs1143679, rs9888739, rs1143683 and 
rs1143678 (P ¼ 0.021). Not surprisingly, none of the tests on 
an independent contribution from the SNPs in the haplotype 
analysis produced significant results. For the Thai samples, for 
whom the risk alleles have significantly higher frequencies, hap-
lotype TTAT increased from 1.69% in controls to 6.46% in 
cases, and gave a P-value of 3.20 Â 10 25 for disease associ-
ation. Independent effect of rs1143679 toward the haplotype 
association is significant (P ¼ 0.0074, significant difference 
between haplotypes TTAT and CTAT). Surprisingly, indepen-
dent effect test for rs1143683 is also significant in the haplotype 
test (P ¼ 0.0061, significant difference between the effect of 
haplotypes CCAC and CCGC formed by the four SNPs). 
When analyzed conditioning on the effect of rs1143679, there 
is also a residual effect of the haplotypes (P ¼ 0.046), indicating 
association besides rs1143679. 
SNP rs1143683 seems to be the most ancient allele among the 
four SNPs with the highest minor allele (risk allele) frequency 
among the four SNPs and the D'-values equal to 1 among all 
four SNPs. Therefore, in addition to performing statistical analy-
sis, we took away the samples carrying the T allele (the rare, risk 
allele) of rs1143679 from the analysis and analyzed the rest of the 
samples. For the Hong Kong samples, rs1143683 remains signifi-
cantly associated with the disease (OR: 1.63, 95% CI: 1.00-2.65, 
P ¼ 0.046). For the Thai samples, rs1143683 has an OR of 1.70 
when the remaining samples were analyzed, but the effect failed 
to show significance (P ¼ 0.14), presumably due to the small 
sample size. Altogether, these results seem to indicate that, in 
addition to supporting an independent contribution from 
rs1143679, other variants, probably rs1143683, may have inde-
pendent effect of its own. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The risk allele of rs1143679 (T) has a frequency of 9 -11% in 
European-, Hispanic-and African-Americans and the Gullah </p>

<p>population, as well as Mexicans and Colombians, and 
showed significant association with SLE in all the tested 
populations (10,11). However, in Japanese and Korean 
populations, the risk SNP was found to be monomorphic. In 
the study with Hong Kong Chinese and the Thai populations, 
we confirmed existence of the risk alleles in our populations 
and their association with the disease, thus filling the last 
missing piece on the picture of the association of the gene 
across different ethnicities. 
We found that both rs1143863 and rs1143679 reached sig-
nificance in the allelic association test in Hong Kong samples 
(P ¼ 0.0037 and 0.021, respectively, Table 2), despite low-
allele frequencies and low power of the study on rare SNPs. 
The GWAS data showed slightly higher effect size (OR) 
than the replication study (Tables 1 and 2), which may have 
reflected a sample selection bias since 74% of the patients 
are positive for renal nephritis for the GWAS samples, com-
paring with only 47% in the overall (replication) samples 
(included the SLE samples in the GWAS). Interestingly, the 
allele frequencies for these SNPs are considerably higher in 
the Thai samples, although still much lower than those in 
the Caucasians (Table 2). The Thai samples also showed 
higher ORs on all the tested SNPs than the Hong Kong 
samples (Table 2). 
In both Hong Kong and Thai populations, rs1143679 has an 
intermediate LD with the other three SNPs genotyped (Fig. 1, 
r 2 ¼ 0.4 -0.6), allowing testing of its independent effect on the 
disease association. Although our data support a vital role for 
rs1143679, it seems that rs1143683, which converts alanine at 
position 858 of the protein to valine, may have further contri-
bution toward disease association. On top of all the statistical 
analysis, we observed significant disease association from 
rs1143683 after excluding all the samples carrying the risk 
allele of rs1143679, supporting independent contribution 
besides rs1143679. The relative lower LD between 
rs1143679 and other disease-associated variants in our popu-
lations (Fig. 1) is probably the explanation for the different 
findings from other populations and from our two Asian popu-
lations. It is also possible that there could be a population 
difference in the effect of rs1143683. The low-allele frequen-
cies for these variants in our populations reduce the power of 
our study, and it will be important to have other studies reex-
amine the issue of independent contribution of these SNPs. 
It seems that in our Hong Kong samples, the association is 
tightly related to lupus nephritis (Table 3). The risk alleles also 
seem to be associated with some other severe manifestations 
of the disease. The confirmation of the ITGAM gene with </p>

<p>Table 1. SNPs in the ITGAM locus showed association with SLE in GWAS </p>

<p>SNP 
Minor allele 
MAF (SLE) 
MAF (control) 
P-value 
OR 
L95 
U95 </p>

<p>rs9937837 
31206440 
G 
0.043 
0.021 
0.00077 
2.09 
1.35 
3.24 
rs9888739 
31220754 
T 
0.038 
0.018 
0.00085 
2.17 
1.36 
3.46 
rs1143683 
31244389 
T 
0.040 
0.019 
0.00064 
2.18 
1.38 
3.44 
rs7193268 
31248498 
T 
0.040 
0.019 
0.00064 
2.18 
1.38 
3.44 
rs1143678 
31250506 
T 
0.040 
0.019 
0.00064 
2.18 
1.38 
3.44 
rs11574637 a 
31276375 
C 
0.016 
0.015 
0.84 
1.07 
0.55 
2.10 </p>

<p>MAF, minor allele frequency. </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>SNP rs11574637 was included since it was a SNP previously found to be associated in Caucasians in the study of Hom et al. (9). </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 
2065 </p>

<p>SLE susceptibility in our two Asian populations seems 
convincing and consistent with previous reports from other 
ethnicities (8 -11). However, proving connection of the </p>

<p>genetic variants in this gene with different manifestations 
will need much increased sample size and replications from 
other collections. Elucidating connections between genetic </p>

<p>Figure 1. LD comparison between Hong Kong Chinese, Thai and Caucasians. (A) Structure of the ITGAM gene from <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">NCBI</rs> <rs id="software-2" type="software">MapViewer</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">Build 36.3</rs>) and the 
position of relevant SNPs in this genomic region. (B) Analysis of LD for the relevant SNPs in this locus for different populations. These include: Hong Kong 
Chinese genotyped by Sequencing (Sequen_HK) and Illumina Beadchip (Illumkna550K), Thai samples genotyped by sequencing (Sequen_Thai) and HapMap 
Caucasians data (HapMap_Cau). Colour scheme is according to Haploview r 2 scheme with darker colour representing better r 2 -value. Numbers in each cell stand 
for pairwise r 2 -values and an empty cell means pairwise r 2 equals to 1 between the corresponding SNPs. </p>

<p>2066 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

<p>variations and clinical manifestations, especially severe, 
potentially life-threatening ones, will play crucial role in our 
understanding of disease mechanisms and improving clinical 
intervention. To reach this goal, meta-analysis from different 
studies is important, since it will be difficult for a single 
study to have the sample size needed to reach a definitive 
answer in stratification analysis, especially for genetic variants 
of low-allele frequencies. 
The product of ITGAM, integrin-a M (CD11bþ), is a mol-
ecule that combines with integrin-b 2 to form a leukocyte-
specific integrin. The a M b 2 -integrin is important in the 
adherence of neutrophils and monocytes to stimulated endo-
thelium and in the phagocytosis of complement-coated par-
ticles. Ligation of the complement C3 activation product 
iC3b to integrin-a M on antigen-presenting cells results in the 
production of TGFb2 and IL10, a process that is essential 
for the induction of tolerance (12). Molad et al. (13) reported 
that neutrophils from SLE patients with more active disease 
expressed greater CD11b/CD18 than those from controls or 
patients with less active disease. In addition to clearance of 
immune complexes, ITGAM may suppress differentiation of 
helper T-cell type 17 (Th17), a pathway that has been 
shown to be involved in autoimmunity (14,15). ITGAM 
deficiency may also lead to enhanced IL6 production by 
antigen presenting cells, which subsequently promotes prefer-
ential differentiation of naı¨ve T cells to Th17 (16). 
Despite of the across population association of the gene 
with SLE susceptibility, further work is needed to understand 
how exactly the risk alleles affect the disease. Another ques-
tion is whether two other non-synonymous polymorphisms, 
A858V coded by rs1143683 and P1146S coded by 
rs1143678, also play any role in the disease in addition to 
R77H coded by SNP re1143679, as statistical analysis is 
often incapable of distinguishing the effect of different var-
iants when they have high LD with each other, and much 
increased sample sizes are needed to tell them apart. It 
seems that P1146 is at a position even better conserved than 
R77 in the protein in evolutionary courses (Supplementary 
Material, Fig. S3). Functional studies and applying the </p>

<p>knowledge so obtained in clinical interventions are important 
steps to be taken following genetic findings. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>The Hong Kong SLE patients were recruited from three Hong 
Kong hospitals: Queen Mary Hospital, Tuen Mun Hospital and 
Pamela Youde Nethersole Eastern Hospital. Medical records 
were reviewed to confirm that subjects met the criteria of 
the American College of Rheumatology for SLE diagnosis. 
The patients are all self-reported Chinese ethnicity living in 
Hong Kong. These included 836 females and 74 males with 
a mean age of 44.6 years. The study was approved by the Insti-
tutional Review Board of the University of Hong Kong and 
Hospital Authority, Hong Kong West Cluster, New Territory 
West Cluster and Hong Kong East Cluster, and all patients 
gave informed consent. Clinical and serological data and auto-
antibody profile were recorded at the time of diagnoses. Renal 
involvement was defined by proteinuria .0.5 gm/day or 
biopsy-proven lupus nephritis. Hematological disorders 
included leukopenia, lymphopenia, thrombocytopenia and/or 
hemolytic anemia. Neurological disorders included psychosis, 
depression, seizure, aseptic meningitis, cognitive dysfunction 
and organic brain syndrome. A total of 1440 Hong Kong 
Chinese blood donors from Hong Kong Red Cross were 
recruited as controls. These included 519 females and 918 
males with a mean age of 29.6 years. They are also self-
reported to be of Chinese ethnicity. 
Two hundred and seventy-eight Thai patients with SLE 
(female:male ratio ¼ 260:18; mean age: 35.6 years) attending 
King Chulalongkorn Memorial Hospital, a tertiary referral 
center in Bangkok, who fulfilled at least four of the American 
College of Rheumatology 1982 revised criteria for SLE, were 
included in this study. Three hundred and eighty-three Thai 
normal control subjects (female:male ratio ¼ 331:52; mean 
age:35.8years) were recruited from unrelated voluntary 
healthy donors from the same ethnic background and 
geographic area. The study was approved by the Ethics </p>

<p>Table 2. Replication of SLE association by Sequencing in the Hong Kong and Thai collections </p>

<p>SNP 
rs1143679 
rs9888739 
rs1143683 
rs1143678 
SNP position 
Exon 3 (R77H) 
Intron 14 
Exon 21 (A858V) 
Exon 30 (P1146S) 
Minor alleles 
T 
T 
A 
T </p>

<p>Hong Kong 
Control MAF, (%) 
0.51 
1.4 
1.72 
1.47 
SLE MAF (%) 
1.13 
2.14 
3.05 
2.2 
OR (95% CI) 
2.21 (1.11-4.42) 
1.54 (0.97-2.44) 
1.79 (1.20-2.67) 
1.51 (0.96-2.37) 
P-value 
0.021 
0.063 
0.0037 
0.073 
Thai 
Control MAF, (%) 
2.10 
3.41 
4.61 
3.29 
SLE MAF (%) 
6.22 
8.33 
10.31 
8.81 
OR (95% CI) 
3.10 (1.61-5.98) 
2.58 (1.49-4.44) 
2.38 (1.47-3.84) 
2.84 (1.65-4.90) 
P-value 
4.1 Â 10 24 
4.4 Â 10 24 
2.7 Â 10 24 
9.4 Â 10 25 
Joint 
Joint OR (95% CI) 
2.82 (1.74-4.59) 
1.91 (1.35-2.71) 
1.82 (1.33-2.50) 
1.95 (1.38-2.75) 
Joint P-value 
1.25 Â 10 25 
2.30 Â 10 24 
1.70 Â 10 24 
1.07 Â 10 24 
Heterogeneity P 
0.49 
0.16 
0.25 
0.08 
Caucasians 
Control MAF (%) 
10.0 
12.7 
15.2 
16.8 
SLE MAF (%) 
17.0 
18.9 
23.1 
21.4 
P-value 
1.7 Â 10 217 
1.61 Â 10 223 
6.03 Â 10 28 
8.5 Â 10 214 
OR (95% CI) 
1.78 (1.56-2.03) (10) 
1.62 (1.47-1.78) (8) 
1.67 (1.39-2.01) (10) 
1.40 (1.28-1.53) (8) </p>

<p>MAF, minor allele frequency. </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

<p>
Table 3. Association of ITGAM SNPs with SLE analyzed by subphenotypes stratification </p>

<p>Subphenotype 
Comparison 
rs1143679 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>rs1143683 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>rs1143678 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>Renal involvement 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 343) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>3.61 (1.63-7.98), P ¼ 0.00073 2.42 (1.51-3.89), P ¼ 0.00017 1.95 (1.10-3.47), P ¼ 0.02 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 392) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.08 (0.35-3.28), P ¼ 0.90 
1.18 (0.67-2.08), P ¼ 0.57 
1.22 (0.65-2.30), P ¼ 0.53 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.076 
P ¼ 0.055 
P ¼ 0.28 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 343) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 392) </p>

<p>3.35 (1.06-10.58), P ¼ 0.029 2.05 (1.10-3.85), P ¼ 0.022 
1.60 (0.77-3.31), P ¼ 0.21 </p>

<p>Anti-dsDNA ab 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 515) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.56 (1.18-5.56), P ¼ 0.014 
1.81 (1.15-2.84), P ¼ 0.0094 1.57 (0.92-2.67), P ¼ 0.096 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 220) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.44 (0.41-5.04), P ¼ 0.56 
1.59 (0.84-3.00), P ¼ 0.15 
1.52 (0.73-3.15), P ¼ 0.26 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.44 
P ¼ 0.75 
P ¼ 0.94 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 515) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 220) </p>

<p>1.78 (0.50-6.36), P ¼ 0.37 
1.14 (0.58-2.25), P ¼ 0.70 
1.04 (0.47-2.29), P ¼ 0.93 </p>

<p>Arthritis 
SLE (þ)(n ¼ 360) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.73 (0.66-4.52), P ¼ 0.26 
1.43 (0.83-2.46), P ¼ 0.20 
1.62 (0.90-2.91), P ¼ 0.10 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 375) versus 
control(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.73 (1.18-6.33), P ¼ 0.015 
2.07 (1.27-3.36), P ¼ 0.003 
1.48 (0.80-2.74), P ¼ 0.21 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.48 
P ¼ 0.32 
P ¼ 0.84 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 360) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 375) </p>

<p>0.63 (0.22-1.79), P ¼ 0.39 
0.69 (0.37-1.28), P ¼ 0.24 
1.09 (0.53-2.25), P ¼ 0.81 </p>

<p>Onset_age 
SLE (,27) (n ¼ 339) versus 
control (n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.91 (0.73-5.00), P ¼ 0.18 
1.83 (1.10-3.07), P ¼ 0.019 
1.57 (0.84-2.90), P ¼ 0.15 </p>

<p>SLE (!27) (n ¼ 396) versus 
control (n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.48 (1.07-5.75), P ¼ 0.029 
1.66 (1.00-2.76), P ¼ 0.048 
1.54 (0.86-2.77), P ¼ 0.15 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.69 
P ¼ 0.79 
P ¼ 0.97 
SLE (,27) versus SLE (!27) 
0.77 (0.27-2.18), P ¼ 0.62 
1.11 (0.60-2.03), P ¼ 0.75 
1.02 (0.49-2.10), P ¼ 0.96 
Malar rash 
SLE (þ)(n ¼ 329) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>3.23 (1.43-7.30), P ¼ 0.003 
1.78 (1.05-3.00), P ¼ 0.03 
2.04 (1.16-3.60), P ¼ 0.011 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 406) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.36 (0.49-3.80), P ¼ 0.55 
1.71 (1.04-2.81), P ¼ 0.033 
1.14 (0.60-2.19), P ¼ 0.69 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.19 
P¼0.91 
P ¼ 0.18 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 329) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 406) </p>

<p>2.37 (0.81-6.97), P ¼ 0.11 
1.04 (0.57-1.92), P ¼ 0.90 
1.79 (0.86-3.75), P ¼ 0.12 </p>

<p>Anti-Ro ab 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 328) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.29 (0.92-5.71), P ¼ 0.066 
1.80 (1.07-3.05), P ¼ 0.026 
1.96 (1.10-3.48), P ¼ 0.020 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 407) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.15 (0.90-5.15), P ¼ 0.08 
1.69 (1.02-2.78), P ¼ 0.037 
1.22 (0.65-2.30), P ¼ 0.54 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.92 
P ¼ 0.86 
P ¼ 0.28 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 328) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 407) </p>

<p>1.07 (0.38-2.96), P ¼ 0.90 
1.07 (0.58-1.96), P ¼ 0.83 
1.60 (0.77-3.33), P ¼ 0.20 </p>

<p>Hematological 
disorder </p>

<p>SLE (þ) (n ¼ 364) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.73 (1.17-6.33), P ¼ 0.015 
1.83 (1.10-3.04), P ¼ 0.018 
1.92 (1.09-3.37), P ¼ 0.021 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 371) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.73 (0.66-4.52) P ¼ 0.26 
1.65 (0.99-2.77), P ¼ 0.053 
1.21 (0.63-2.31) P ¼ 0.57 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.61 
P ¼ 0.87 
P ¼ 0.28 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 364) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 371) </p>

<p>1.39 (0.50-3.85), P ¼ 0.53 
1.06 (0.58-1.95), P ¼ 0.85 
1.60 (0.77-3.31), P ¼ 0.21 </p>

<p>Immunological 
disorder </p>

<p>SLE (þ) (n ¼ 469) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.79 (1.28-6.05), P ¼ 0.007 
1.97 (1.25-3.10), P ¼ 0.003 
1.79 (1.06-3.03), P ¼ 0.03 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 266) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.22 (0.35-4.26), P ¼ 0.76 
1.34 (0.71-2.53), P ¼ 0.37 
1.14 (0.53-2.45), P ¼ 0.74 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.26 
P ¼ 0.33 
P ¼ 0.34 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 469) versus SLE 
(2)(n ¼ 266) </p>

<p>2.29 (0.64-8.15), P ¼ 0.19 
1.47 (0.75-2.89), P ¼ 0.26 
1.57 (0.69-3.55), P ¼ 0.28 </p>

<p>Neurological disorder 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 46) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>4.73 (1.06-21.13), P ¼ 0.025 4.05 (1.69-9.72), P ¼ 0.0007 4.24 (1.63-11.03), 
P ¼ 0.0013 
SLE (2) (n ¼ 689) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.05 (0.96-4.37), P ¼ 0.06 
1.59 (1.04-2.45), P ¼ 0.032 
1.38 (0.83-2.28), P ¼ 0.21 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.31 
P ¼ 0.051 
P ¼ 0.032 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 46) versus SLE 
(2)(n ¼ 689) </p>

<p>2.31 (0.51-10.39), P ¼ 0.26 
2.54 (1.04-6.21), P ¼ 0.034 
3.08 (1.15-8.25), P ¼ 0.019 </p>

<p>Continued </p>

<p>2068 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

<p>Committee of the King Chulalongkorn University and the sub-
jects all gave informed consent (17). </p>

<p>GWAS </p>

<p>Samples were genotyped by Illumina 550K Human Beadchip. 
Initial phase of quality control of the chip data includes geno-
type call rate (.95%), minor allele frequencies (.1%), 
Hardy -Weinberg equilibrium test (P . 0.05), relationship 
test among individuals and all analyses were performed by 
Plink (18). Hidden population structure was examined by 
Eigenstrat (19). </p>

<p>Replication </p>

<p>Four of the ITGAM SNPs were genotyped in the replication 
phase by direct sequencing of the PCR products. Primer 
sequences: SNP rs1143683: forward: TGACTGTGAGAAAT-
GATGGTGAGGA and reverse: CCAGGAGTTCTGACCT 
CTGAGTTTTC. SNP rs1143679: forward: AGTGCGACTA 
CAGCACAGGCTCAT and reverse: GAGACAAGGAGGTC 
TGACGGTGAA. SNP rs9888739: forward: TCACTCCTA 
AATTTCCCTAAAAATATGGA and reverse: GAAAGAAC 
CATGAGCATGAGCTATTT. SNP rs1143678: forward: TG 
TCGCTCTCACTGCCCTCCTCT and reverse: CTACGTG 
TGGTCTGGGCAGAGTC. PCR condition used is as </p>

<p>Table 3. Continued </p>

<p>Subphenotype 
Comparison 
rs1143679 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>rs1143683 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>rs1143678 OR (95% CI), 
P-value </p>

<p>Oral ulcer 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 95) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.42 (0.55-10.75), P ¼ 0.23 
0.66 (0.16-2.73), P ¼ 0.56 
0.84 (0.20-3.49), P ¼ 0.81 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 640) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.19 (1.03-4.67), P ¼ 0.038 
1.89 (1.28-2.87), P ¼ 0.0023 1.65 (1.02-2.69), P ¼ 0.041 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.9 
P ¼ 0.15 
P ¼ 0.37 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 95) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 640) </p>

<p>1.11 (0.25-4.95), P ¼ 0.89 
0.35 (0.08-1.45), P ¼ 0.13 
0.51 (0.12-2.15), P ¼ 0.35 </p>

<p>Photosensitivity 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 151) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>0.70 (0.09-5.38), P ¼ 0.73 
0.77 (0.28-2.16), P ¼ 0.62 
0.98 (0.35-2.77), P ¼ 0.98 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 584) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.62 (1.24-5.51), P ¼ 0.0085 1.99 (1.31-3.05), P ¼ 0.0011 1.70 (1.03-2.81), P ¼ 0.034 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.21 
P ¼ 0.086 
P ¼ 0.35 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 151) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 584) </p>

<p>0.27 (0.04-2.06), P ¼ 0.17 
0.39 (0.14-1.10), P ¼ 0.064 
0.58 (0.2-1.67), P ¼ 0.31 </p>

<p>RNP 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 142) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>3.80 (1.36-10.63), P ¼ 0.0063 1.67 (0.78-3.56), P ¼ 0.18 
2.13 (0.98-4.59), P ¼ 0.05 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 593) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.83 (0.81-4.14), P ¼ 0.14 
1.76 (1.14-2.72), P ¼ 0.010 
1.41 (0.84-2.39), P ¼ 0.19 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.27 
P ¼ 0.91 
P ¼ 0.39 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 142) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 593) </p>

<p>2.07 (0.70-6.11), P ¼ 0.18 
0.95 (0.44-2.08), P ¼ 0.90 
1.50 (0.66-3.42), P ¼ 0.33 </p>

<p>Serositis 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 72) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>4.73 (1.34-16.66), P ¼ 0.0078 2.55 (1.07-6.05), P ¼ 0.03 
2.20 (0.77-6.23), P ¼ 0.13 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 663) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.96 (0.90-4.24), P ¼ 0.083 
1.67 (1.08-2.54), P ¼ 0.02 
1.49 (0.90-2.45), P ¼ 0.12 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.33 
P ¼ 0.38 
P ¼ 0.5 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 72) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 663) </p>

<p>2.42 (0.67-8.67), P ¼ 0.16 
1.54 (0.64-3.72), P ¼ 0.33 
1.48 (0.51-4.31), P ¼ 0.47 </p>

<p>Discoid rash 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 81) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>3.9 (1.11-13.72), P ¼ 0.022 
2.13 (0.90-5.05), P ¼ 0.078 
1.83 (0.65-5.20), P ¼ 0.25 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 654) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.00 (0.92-4.34), P ¼ 0.073 
1.69 (1.1-2.59), P ¼ 0.015 
1.52 (0.92-2.50), P ¼ 0.10 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.36 
P ¼ 0.63 
P ¼ 0.75 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 81) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 654) </p>

<p>1.95 (0.54-6.99), P ¼ 0.30 
1.26 (0.52-3.04), P ¼ 0.60 
1.21 (0.42-3.52), P ¼ 0.73 </p>

<p>Anti-sm autoantibody 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 65) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>3.23 (0.73-14.37), P ¼ 0.103 1.76 (0.62-4.94), P ¼ 0.28 
1.69 (0.51-5.53), P ¼ 0.38 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 670) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.11 (0.99-4.51), P ¼ 0.048 
1.74 (1.14-2.65), P ¼ 0.0094 1.54 (0.94-2.52), P ¼ 0.084 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.62 
P ¼ 0.99 
P ¼ 0.89 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 65) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 670) </p>

<p>1.53 (0.34-6.85), P ¼ 0.58 
1.01 (0.35-2.87), P ¼ 0.99 
1.10 (0.33-3.67), P ¼ 0.88 </p>

<p>Anti-La autoantibody 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 94) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>1.13 (0.15-8.67), P ¼ 0.90 
1.25 (0.45-3.51), P ¼ 0.67 
1.59 (0.56-4.51), P ¼ 0.38 </p>

<p>SLE (2) (n ¼ 641) versus control 
(n ¼ 1440) </p>

<p>2.38 (1.13-5.01), P ¼ 0.019 
1.81 (1.19-2.77), P ¼ 0.0052 1.55 (0.94-2.55), P ¼ 0.084 </p>

<p>Heterogeneity test of OR 
P ¼ 0.5 
P ¼ 0.51 
P ¼ 0.96 
SLE (þ) (n ¼ 94) versus SLE 
(2) (n ¼ 641) </p>

<p>0.48 (0.06-3.64), P ¼ 0.46 
0.69 (0.24-1.96), P ¼ 0.49 
1.03 (0.36-2.99), P ¼ 0.96 </p>

<p>Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

<p>
follows: 968C, 5 min; 968C, 30 s; 588C, 50 s; 728C, 1 min; for 
40 cycles: 728C, 10 min. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>All SNPs were tested for significant deviation from Hardy -
Weinberg equilibrium in controls and all passed the test 
with P-values . 0.05. The SNPs were analyzed for an associ-
ation with the disease by means of comparison of the minor 
allele frequency in patients and controls (basic allelic test) 
as well as other tests using <rs type="software">Plink</rs> (18). LD patterns were ana-
lyzed and displayed by <rs type="software">HaploView</rs> (20). Association of the 
SNPs with disease risk was also corrected by logistic 
regression using age and sex as covariates and the associations 
found in this study remain significant after all the corrections. 
Average ORs and P-values jointly analyzed from both the 
Hong Kong Chinese and the Thai populations were obtained 
by CMH test of association conditional on SNP differences 
between the two populations. Potential heterogeneity of ORs 
for a given SNP between the two populations was tested 
both by Breslow -Day test and by partitioning the x 2 statistic 
between the two populations. Test of independent contribution 
of a SNP controlling for the effect of other SNPs in the same 
gene was done by logistic regression as well as haplotype ana-
lyses. Association with subphenotype was analyzed by com-
paring cases with a certain subphenotype with controls, 
cases without the subphenotype with controls, heterogeneity 
test of two ORs so derived and direct comparison of the 
cases with and without the subphenotypes. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL </p>

<p>Supplementary Material is available at HMG online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>This study was partially supported by the Shun Tak District 
Min Yuen Tong of Hong Kong. </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this 
article was provided by The University of Hong Kong. </p>



<p> 
Human Molecular Genetics, 2009, Vol. 18, No. 11 </p>

</text></tei>