<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2602909" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:01+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Copper,zinc superoxide dismutase (SOD1) in mammals is 
activated principally via a copper chaperone (CCS) and to a 
lesser degree by a CCS-independent pathway of unknown 
nature. In this study, we have characterized the requirement 
for CCS in activating SOD1 from Drosophila. A CCS-null 
mutant (Ccs 
n29E ) of Drosophila was created and found to phe-
notypically resemble Drosophila SOD1-null mutants in terms 
of reduced adult life span, hypersensitivity to oxidative stress, 
and loss of cytosolic aconitase activity. However, the pheno-
types of CCS-null flies were less severe, consistent with some 
CCS-independent activation of Drosophila SOD1 (dSOD1). 
Yet SOD1 activity was not detectable in Ccs 
n29E flies, due 
largely to a striking loss of SOD1 protein. In contrast, human 
SOD1 expressed in CCS-null flies is robustly active and res-
cues the deficits in adult life span and sensitivity to oxidative 
stress. The dependence of dSOD1 on CCS was also observed 
in a yeast expression system where the dSOD1 polypeptide 
exhibited unusual instability in CCS-null (ccs1⌬) yeast. The 
residual dSOD1 polypeptide in ccs1⌬ yeast was nevertheless 
active, consistent with CCS-independent activation. Stability 
of dSOD1 in ccs1⌬ cells was readily restored by expression of 
either yeast or Drosophila CCS, and this required copper 
insertion into the enzyme. The yeast expression system also 
revealed some species specificity for CCS. Yeast SOD1 exhib-
its preference for yeast CCS over Drosophila CCS, whereas 
dSOD1 is fully activated with either CCS molecule. Such var-
iation in mechanisms of copper activation of SOD1 could 
reflect evolutionary responses to unique oxygen and/or cop-
per environments faced by divergent species. </p>

<p>opment, survival, and aging. Mutant Drosophila lacking SOD1 
survive well as embryos and larvae but experience high rates of 
mortality as late pupae and early adults. Surviving adults exhibit 
a median life span about 10% of normal, severely reduced fer-
tility, hypersensitivity to a variety of oxidative stress conditions 
(10), retinal degeneration (11), and increased rates of spontane-
ous somatic and germ line mutation (12). The high rate of early 
mortality in SOD1-null mutants is related to a general pattern 
of premature aging as reflected by the precocious onset and 
rapid progression of patterns of marker gene expression that 
typify normal senescence (13). Clearly, SOD1 plays a critical 
role in the biology and life history of Drosophila, but the bio-
chemistry of the maturation process for this critical enzyme has 
not been explored. Here we describe a single CCS-encoding 
gene from Drosophila and the biological and biochemical con-
sequences of losing the copper chaperone for SOD1. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Drosophila Stocks, Culture Conditions-The Sod1 
n108 and 
ry 
ϩ5 strains are described in Ref, 10. hSOD1 was expressed 
using lines carrying UAS-hSod1 and the GAL4 driver line, 
daGAL4 
G32 as described (14). Stocks were maintained at 
25°C on standard cornmeal and agar medium unless other-
wise stated. 
The copper chaperone coding region was amplified by PCR 
(primers CCS5 ϩ CCS7) using DNA extracted from a Drosoph-
ila Canton S adult cDNA library (Stratagene catalog number 
936603). The 930-bp PCR product was blunt-ended and sub-
cloned into the SmaI site of pBluescriptIISK (Stratagene) to 
generate the vector pBCC. The transformation vector pUCC 
was constructed by subcloning the EcoRI-NotI fragment of 
pBCC into pUAST (15). 
Yeast Strains, Growth Conditions, Plasmids-Yeast strains 
used in this study were derived from EG103 (MAT␣, 
leu2-3,112, his3⌬1, trp1-289, ura3-52) (16) and include KS107 
(sod1⌬) (17) and LS101 (sod1⌬ ccs1⌬) (18). Cells were propa-
gated at 30°C either in enriched yeast extract, peptone-based 
medium supplemented with 2% glucose (YPD), or in synthetic 
complete (SC) medium (19). Solid medium was supplemented 
with 15 mg/liter ergosterol and 0.5% Tween 80 to enhance 
growth in anaerobic conditions. 
Yeast expression plasmids for dSOD1 and dCCS were pro-
duced using cDNA clone RE52090 (Open Biosystems) for 
dSOD1 and plasmid pUCC for dCCS. The coding sequences for 
dSOD1 and dCCS were PCR0-amplified introducing 5Ј BglII 
and 3Ј SnaBI sites in dSOD1 and 5Ј MluI and 3Ј RsrII sites in 
dCCS. The dSOD1 PCR product was digested with the appro-
priate enzymes and ligated into pLS108 (18) cut with BglII/ 
SnaBI, replacing the yeast SOD1 coding sequence with that of 
dSOD1 resulting in plasmid pLJ373. The digested dCCS PCR 
product was inserted into pLJ366 (a derivative of pLS113 (18) 
with an MluI site just prior to the yCCS1 start codon and an 
RsrII site immediately after the stop codon), replacing the 
yCCS1 coding sequence with that of dCCS, generating plasmid 
pLJ375. Both dSOD1 and dCCS were under control of their 
corresponding S. cerevisiae regulatory sequences. The 
sequence integrity of these plasmids was ensured by double-
stranded DNA sequencing (DNA Analysis Facility, The Johns </p>

<p>Hopkins University). Yeast CCS1 plasmids pHAL-413, pLS008 
(C229S, C231S), and pLS010 (K136E, G137E) have been 
described previously (18). Domain I mutation in yCCS1 (C17S, 
C20S) was introduced using the QuikChange mutagenesis kit 
(Stratagene) using pHAL-413 as a template (4) resulting in plas-
mid pPS031. 
SOD1 In-gel Activity Assay-To analyze SOD1 activity from 
Drosophila, five males were homogenized in 50 l of 1% Triton 
X-100. 10 l of supernatant was transferred to a tube contain-
ing an equal volume of loading buffer (125 mM Tris-HCl, pH 
6.8, 20% glycerol, 0.01% bromphenol blue). 20 l was run on a 
10% polyacrylamide (4% stacking) gel. The gel was incubated in 
nitro blue tetrazolium (2 mg/ml) for 5 min followed by incuba-
tion in 36 mM K 2 HPO 4 , 0.035 mM riboflavin, 0.3% TEMED for 7 
min and then washed several times in H 2 O as described (20). 
SOD enzymatic activity was assayed from yeast grown shak-
ing in selected SC medium to an A 600 of 1.5. Yeast lysates were 
generated by glass bead homogenization in a buffer containing 
0.6 M sorbitol, 10 mM HEPES, pH 7.2, and protease inhibitors. 
Analysis of SOD activity by nondenaturing gel electrophoresis 
using 12% pre-cast gel (Invitrogen) and staining with nitro blue 
tetrazolium was performed as described previously (21) except 
that 10 mM EDTA was added to the native running buffer. 
SOD1 Spectrophotometric Assay-24 -48-h-old males were 
homogenized in B1 (50 mM sodium phosphate, pH 7.4, 0.1 mM 
EDTA). The supernatant was extracted twice with chloroform 
(0.15 V), ethanol (0.25 V) with a 15-min incubation time for 
each extraction. SOD1 activity was determined spectrophoto-
metrically by monitoring the autooxidation of 6-hydroxydopa-
mine (6-HD) at 490 nm at 37°C in 500 l of B1 containing 0.1 
mM 6-HD (22). Protein concentration was determined by using 
the Bio-Rad protein assay. 
Aconitase Activity Assay-30 adult males were homogenized 
in 120 l of extraction buffer (0.6 mM MnCl 2 , 2 mM citric acid, 
50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0) and centrifuged at 13,000 ϫ g. Sam-
ples were electrophoresed on Sepraphore III membranes (Pall 
Corp.). Aconitase was detected by incubation of the membrane 
in 100 mM potassium phosphate, pH 6.5, 1 mM NADPH, 2 mM 
cis-aconitic acid, 1.2 mM 3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-di-
phenyltetrazolium bromide, 0.3 mM phenazine methosulfate, 
25 mM MgCl 2 , and 5 units/ml isocitrate dehydrogenase (23, 24). 
Western Blotting-For analysis of SOD1 from Drosophila, 
males were homogenized in 1% Triton X-100. The extracts 
were centrifuged at 13,000 ϫ g for 5 min at 4°C, and the super-
natant was transferred to a tube containing an equal volume of 
loading buffer (125 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.2, 4% SDS, 10% mercap-
toethanol, 20% glycerol, 0.01% bromphenol blue). Samples 
were boiled for 5 min, and 10 g of total protein was separated 
on a SDS-polyacrylamide gel (4% stacking, 15% separating). 
The protein was transferred to nitrocellulose membrane 
(ECL) and probed with sheep anti-human Cu,Zn superoxide 
dismutase (Cedarlane catalog number K9007C) and rabbit 
anti-sheep IgG horseradish peroxidase conjugate (Chemi-
con catalog number AP147P). The ECL Western blotting 
detection reagents (RPN 2109, Amersham Biosciences) was 
used for detection. 
Immunoblot analysis of Cu,Zn-SOD expressed in yeast 
was carried out with cell lysates prepared as described above </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 • DECEMBER 19, 2008 </p>

<p>and a polyclonal antibody that displays strong reactivity with 
Cu,Zn-SODs from several species (JH765) at a 1:5000 dilu-
tion (8). Detection utilized an Alexa Fluor 680 goat anti-
rabbit secondary antibody (Invitrogen), and immunoblots 
were visualized using the Odyssey infrared imagining system 
(Licor Biosciences). 
Drosophila Life Span Determination-0 -24-h-old males 
were collected, 25 males per vial, and kept on cornmeal food 
containing tegosept. 200 males of each line were used. The vials 
were kept at 25°C. Flies were transferred to fresh food every 
2-3 days. 
Drosophila Paraquat Resistance-0 -24-h-old males were 
collected and kept on cornmeal food for 24 h, 10 males in each 
vial. They were then transferred to vials containing 3-mm paper 
filter disks saturated with 250 l of 1% sucrose, 1% sucrose 
containing 2 mM paraquat (Sigma) or 1% sucrose and 5 mM 
paraquat. The vials were stored at 25°C in the dark, and flies 
were enumerated after 24 h as originally described (10). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>dCcs, the Copper Chaperone of SOD1 Gene of Drosophila-
The Drosophila genomic homologue of yeast and mammalian 
Ccs was initially identified by isolation of a SOD1-like sequence 
from a Drosophila genomic library, later verified by sequence 
annotation in Flybase (CG17753, FBgn0010531, and confirmed 
by amplification of a Ccs cDNA from a D. melanogaster cDNA 
library (Fig. 1A). The architecture of the native Drosophila gene </p>

<p>includes a 795-bp coding sequence interrupted by two small 
introns of 51 and 61 bp, respectively. The nearest open reading 
frame (CG11867) is ϳ5 kb upstream from the 5Ј-transcription 
start site. The encoded sequence contains the expected region 
of high homology to SOD1 (2) in the central domain II of CCS; 
the domain III CXC is conserved. Unexpectedly, the domain I 
CXXC copper-binding motif is absent (Fig. 1B). A comparison 
to all known CCS-like molecules in the data base revealed that 
the absence of a CXXC motif in Drosophila CCS is unique. Of 
20 CCS sequences analyzed from fungi to humans, only D. 
melanogaster and Anopheles gambiae lack the MXCXXC cop-
per-binding site (Table 1). However, all 20 CCS molecules 
retain the CXC copper site in domain III. 
Ccs Deletion Mutation-A loss of function mutation of Ccs 
(Ccs 
n29E ), generated by an apparent imprecise excision of a P 
element located near Ccs in the autosomal enhancer-detector 
parent strain, H340 (25), was identified by recovery of a strain, 
29E, with reduced SOD1 activity and a set of phenotypes exhib-
ited by known SOD1 deficiency mutants (see below). Sequence 
analysis of Ccs, restriction analysis by Southern hybridization, 
and SOD1 activity all indicated that Ccs is functionally and 
structurally intact in H340. The genomic deletion in Ccs </p>

<p>n29E </p>

<p>includes 1617 bp of 5Ј-upstream region and 1907 bp down-
stream from the transcription start site, including all of the first 
exon, the first intron, and 124 bp of the second exon (Fig. 1A). 
Ccs transcripts are relatively rare throughout normal develop-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Drosophila CCS. A, genomic architecture of Ccs, the Drosophila copper chaperone for superoxide dismutase 1 (Fly Base Annotation CG17753, 
FBgn0010531). The gene is located in cytogenetic region 46F1 of D. melanogaster chromosome 2. H340 is the Ccs 
ϩ parent chromosome. 29E is the mutant 
chromosome containing a 1907-bp deletion extending upstream from bp 124 of the 2nd exon through the first intron, the first exon and 1717 bp of the 
5Ј-noncoding region. The precise details of the origin of 29E from H340 are unknown. B, domain structure of Drosophila CCS. </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>

<p>DECEMBER 19, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 35395 </p>

<p>ment in H340 and are undetectable by Northern blot analysis in 
29E (data not shown). 
Loss of SOD1 Enzymatic Activity in CCS-null Flies-Because 
the only known assay for CCS function is via its role in the 
activation of SOD1, we assayed SOD1 activity in extracts of 
H340 and 29E using two functionally different methods, the 
in-gel with nitro blue tetrazolium reduction interference assay 
and the spectrophotometric 6-hydroxydopamine reduction 
interference assay (Fig. 2, A and B). Using both methods, we 
were unable to detect significant SOD1 activity in 29E. Loss of 
CCS in 29E appears to have no effect on the activity of the 
mitochondrial manganese-containing SOD2 (see Fig. 4A). 
These results by themselves would suggest that CCS in Dro-
sophila, as in yeast and mammals, is specifically required for 
activating SOD1. 
However, analysis of SOD1 protein levels revealed that the 
steady state level of SOD1 polypeptide in 29E is reduced to 
about one-quarter of its normal level in H340 (Fig. 2C). Thus, 
the loss of SOD1 activity in 29E probably arises primarily from 
the reduced level of SOD1 protein in the absence of CCS. Fur-
ther analysis confirmed that the lack of SOD1 activity in 29E is 
not because of a mutation in the Sod1 gene. </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Deficiency of CCS Reduces the Functional Level of Specific 
Iron-Sulfur Protein Sentinels-The cytosolic and mitochon-
drial aconitases both contain cubane [4Fe-4S] centers that are 
sensitive targets of inactivation by superoxide (23, 26). Steady 
state levels of these activities in Drosophila are significantly 
reduced in the absence of SOD1 and SOD2, respectively (24). 
Assay of cACON and mACON activities in 29E shows that 
cACON activity is selectively depleted by about 50% (H340 
ϳ1.6 ϫ 29E), with no detectable affect on the activity of 
mACON (Fig. 2D). Taken together, these data indicate that at 
the biochemical level, the absence of dCCS is equivalent to a 
deficiency in SOD1. The important question then arises, does 
this parallel extend to whole organism phenotypes? 
Genetic Ablation of CCS Elicits Broad Phenotypic Con-
sequences-At a minimum, the mutational loss of CCS should 
generate a set of phenotypes predicted by the loss of SOD1, 
including reduced adult life span with little or no overt effect on 
pre-adult development and hypersensitivity to applied oxida-
tive stress. Both of these expected phenotypes are realized. Fig. 
3A shows that the absence of CCS confers early onset adult 
mortality with an ϳ30% reduction in the median adult life span. 
In contrast, 29E displays the extreme toxic hypersensitivity to 
the redox cycling agent, paraquat, exhibited by SOD1-null (Fig. 
3B). In these respects, 29E appears to phenocopy a weakly 
expressing SOD1 hypomorphic mutant. Based on previous 
studies with RNA interference-mediated knockdown of SOD1 
(27), and transgenic rescue of SOD1-null mutants (28), which 
show that paraquat toxicity is a more sensitive indicator of 
SOD1 deficiency than life span, the phenotype of 29E is consist-
ent with the presence in 29E of a very small residual level of 
SOD1 activity which, although below the level of detection by 
conventional assays of whole-fly extracts, is sufficient to extend 
median adult life span (ϳ30 days) beyond the 10-day median 
life span of SOD1-null mutants. Such activity, if it were to 
occur, would have to arise via CCS-independent activation of 
apo-SOD1 (see below). 
Human SOD1 Is Active in CCS-null Drosophila and Restores 
Their Adult Life Span-In earlier work (14), we described the 
functional expression of human SOD1 (hSOD1) in Drosophila 
in a Ccs 
ϩ genetic background. Since then, the CCS-independ-
ent activation of hSOD1 has been described (7, 9). Here we 
investigated the activation of hSOD1 in flies in the absence of 
functional dCCS. As would be expected from this SOD1 capa-
ble of CCS independent activation, hSOD1 is quite active in 
CCS-null flies (Fig. 4A). Moreover, hSOD1 functions biologi-
cally to rescue the early mortality and reduced median life span 
of CCS-null flies (Fig. 4B). These results demonstrate the pres-
ence in Drosophila of a CCS-independent pathway capable of 
robust activation of heterologous hSOD1 while giving only 
weak activation of homologous dSOD1. 
CCS-independent Activation of Drosophila SOD1 Revealed in 
Yeast Expression System-Based on amino acid sequence alone, 
dSOD1 is predicted to acquire copper independently of CCS. 
Studies with yeast, human, and C. elegans SOD1 have identified 
a pair of prolines near the C terminus that can prohibit CCS-</p>

<p>4 The possibility remained that the lack of SOD1 activity in the Ccs deletion 
strain, 29E, was actually caused by a cryptic loss-of-function mutation in 
the Sod1 gene itself. We tested this possibility by examining the SOD1 
dimeric isoforms present in hybrids generated by crossing 29E to a strain 
bearing Sod1 
s , a mutant allele that encodes an electrophoretically slow but 
enzymatically active variant of SOD1. The capacity of the Sod1 gene in 29E 
to produce a functionally active SOD1 apoprotein can be diagnosed by the 
presence of a novel SOD1 
F /SOD1 
S dimeric protein in the 29E/Sod1 
S hybrid. 
The data in supplemental Fig. S1, showing the presence of an enzymati-
cally active SOD1 
F /SOD1 
S hybrid, provides conclusive evidence that the 
lack of SOD1 activity in 29E is not because of a mutation in the Sod1 gene. 
We are therefore able to conclude with confidence that the lack of SOD1 </p>

<p>activity and SOD1 protein in 29E is the indirect consequence of the loss of 
CCS and not because of a loss-of-function mutation in the Sod1 gene. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Drosophila CCS lacks domain 1 MTCXXC </p>

<p>The presence of the domain I MXCXXC and domain III CXC sequences was exam-
ined in CCS proteins from fungi, plants, and animals. Sequences were obtained from 
the GenBank 
TM database. Alignments were performed with <rs id="software-0" type="software">Geneious</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version3.0.6</rs>). </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 • DECEMBER 19, 2008 </p>

<p>independent activation (7, 8). Yeast SOD1 naturally contains 
these prolines and is incapable of CCS-independent activation, 
whereas mammalian and C. elegans SOD1 with nonproline res-
idues at these positions can be activated independently of CCS. 
Drosophila SOD1 also lacks these prolines (Fig. 5A) leading us 
to predict that dSOD1 should not exhibit dependence on CCS 
for activity. And although from the phenotype of dCCS-nulls 
we inferred the presence of a residual level of SOD1 activity, the 
instability of dSOD1 in the absence of CCS obscures any meas-
urable CCS-independent activation of dSOD1 that might occur 
in the Drosophila model. We therefore turned to a yeast expres-
sion system to further examine Drosophila CCS and SOD1. 
To test the comparative functionality of dSOD1 in the 
absence of CCS, the coding sequences for human, yeast, and 
Drosophila SOD1 were all placed under control of the S. cerevi-
siae SOD1 gene promoter and analyzed for SOD1 activity and </p>

<p>protein levels in CCS1 
ϩ versus 
ccs1⌬ yeast. As in CCS-null flies 
(Fig. 2C), dSOD1 appears highly 
unstable in ccs1⌬ yeast (Fig. 5B), and 
dSOD1 activity was initially difficult 
to discern (Fig. 5B, lane 6). Yet when 
increasing levels of cell lysate were 
analyzed, the dSOD1 polypeptide 
was readily detected, and CCS-inde-
pendent activation of dSOD1 
became apparent (Fig. 5B, lane 9), 
similar to levels seen with human 
SOD1 (lane 4). Hence, dSOD1 does 
have the capacity to be activated by 
the CCS-independent pathway, 
ostensibly explaining the less severe 
phenotypes of a CCS-null fly com-
pared with a SOD1-null mutant. 
Role of CCS in Helping to Stabilize 
dSOD1-The dramatic loss of the 
dSOD1 polypeptide in both ccs1⌬ 
null yeast (Fig. 5B) and in CCS null 
flies (Fig. 2C) is atypical, and it is not 
observed with yeast and human 
SOD1 analyzed in parallel (Fig. 5B, 
lanes 2 and 4). This loss in dSOD1 
can be rescued by expressing either 
yeast CCS or Drosophila CCS in the 
ccs1⌬ yeast (Fig. 6C, lanes 8 and 9). 
This apparent stabilization of 
dSOD1 requires physical interac-
tions between CCS and SOD1, as a 
K136E, G137E derivative of yeast 
CCS that cannot dock with SOD1 
(29) fails to increase dSOD1 levels 
(Fig. 6A, lane 4). To test whether 
SOD1-CCS interactions are by 
themselves sufficient, we employed 
a C229S,C231S mutant of yeast 
CCS. The highly conserved cys-
teines Cys-229 and Cys-231 in 
domain III of CCS are needed for 
copper transfer and disulfide oxidation in SOD1, and a 
C229S,C231S mutant of CCS can dock with SOD1 but cannot 
activate the enzyme (29, 30). As seen in Fig. 6A, lane 3, 
C229S,C231S yCCS failed to stabilize dSOD1, indicating that 
copper transfer and/or disulfide oxidation are required. To 
directly test the requirement for copper, yeast cells were starved 
for copper by treatment with the Cu(I) chelator, bathocuproine 
sulfonate (31). Under such copper-limiting conditions, levels of 
the dSOD1 polypeptide were lowered even in cells expressing 
wild type CCS from yeast or Drosophila (Fig. 6B). Together, 
these studies indicate that apo-dSOD1 is unusually unstable 
and that CCS affords stability to dSOD1 by activating the 
enzyme through copper insertion and/or disulfide oxidation. 
Unique N Terminus of Drosophila CCS-As mentioned 
above, Drosophila CCS lacks the MXCXXC copper-binding 
motif that is well conserved in CCS molecules from phyloge-</p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Loss of CCS affects SOD1 and mAconitase. A, in-gel activity assay of SOD1. H340 is the dCcs 
ϩ parent 
stock from which the CCS-null mutant, Ccs 
n29E , was derived. 29E is Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E . H340/29E is Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
n29E . 
Both strains are homozygous for Sod1 
ϩ . B, spectrophotometric assay of SOD1 activity based on 6-HD reduc-
tion. Extracts were treated with Triton X-100 to eliminate interference from mitochondrial superoxide dis-
mutase (SOD2). See "Experimental Procedures" for details. Note, the "background activity" found in 29E 
extracts is also present in SOD1-null mutant extracts. C, dSOD1 is reduced in the absence of CCS. Extracts were 
prepared from H340 and 29E adult males, and SOD1 protein was detected in Western immunoblots with 
anti-SOD1 antibody. Top, immunoblot analysis; bottom, densitometric quantitation of immunoblot where 
100 ϭ amount of dSOD1 polypeptide in H340. 29E is Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E . H340 is Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ . Both strains are 
homozygous for Sod1 
ϩ . D, selective loss of cytosolic aconitase (cACON) activity in the absence of CCS. Aconi-
tase activities in extracts of 2-3-day-old adult males were assayed after electrophoretic separation. mACON 
and cACON indicate mitochondrial and cytosolic aconitase activities, respectively. Top, zymogram analysis; 
bottom, densitometric quantitation of zymogram where 100 ϭ level of cACON activity in H340. mACON activity 
remained unaffected in the absence of CCS. 29E is Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E . H340 is Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ . H340/29E is Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
n29E . 
All strains are homozygous for Sod1 
ϩ . </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>

<p>DECEMBER 19, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 35397 </p>

<p>netically distant taxa. In fact, an inspection of CCS molecules 
across diverse species reveals that with the exception of Dro-
sophila and mosquito CCS, all CCS molecules identified to date 
harbor these cysteines (Table 1). Interestingly, we observed that 
Drosophila CCS is very poor at activating yeast SOD1 com-
pared with the homologous yeast CCS expressed from the iden-
tical yeast CCS1 gene promoter (Fig. 6C, lanes 2 and 3). By 
comparison, fly CCS was nearly as effective as yeast CCS in 
activating human SOD1 (Fig. 6C, lanes 5 and 6), and Drosophila 
SOD1 exhibited no apparent preference for CCS and showed 
strong activation by both CCS molecules (lanes 8 and 9). To 
address whether the yeast SOD1 preference for yeast CCS 
reflected loss of the conserved MXCXXC cysteines, we tested 
the effects of a C17S,C20S substitution in yeast CCS. As seen in 
Fig. 6D, this mutant retains the ability to fully activate yeast </p>

<p>SOD1. Despite the well conserved nature of domain I CXXC in 
CCS, these cysteines are not essential for activating SOD1. 
These results also demonstrate that the apparent poor reactiv-
ity between fly CCS and yeast SOD1 is not simply explained by 
the absence of these CXXC cysteines. In any case, SOD1 mole-
cules from phylogenetically distant organisms exhibit unique 
preferences in copper activation pathways. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>CCS in Drosophila is encoded by a single genomic gene, Ccs. 
Mutational inactivation of Ccs generates a set of phenotypes 
that are equivalent to those from a weakly expressing SOD1 
hypomorphic mutation, and are consistent with the notion that 
CCS appears to have a single function in Drosophila, which is to </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. CCS deficiency confers early adult mortality and enhanced sen-
sitivity to the redox cycling agent, paraquat. A, early mortality of CCS-null 
adults. Survival of at least 125 males of each genotype on standard cornmeal 
food was followed at 25°C with enumeration and transfer of survivors to fresh 
bottles every 2-3 days. Ccs 
ϩ is H340, the Ccs 
ϩ parent stock from which Ccs </p>

<p>n29E </p>

<p>was derived. Ccs 
n29E is Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E . Both stocks are homozygous for Sod1 
ϩ . 
Inset, early mortality of SOD1-null adults. Sod1 
Ϫ is Sod1 
n108 /Sod1 
n108 , Sod1 
ϩ is 
the wild type stock, ry 
ϩ5 . Both stocks are homozygous for Ccs 
ϩ . B, paraquat 
sensitivity of CCS-null adults. Ccs 
ϩ is H340, the Ccs 
ϩ parent stock from which 
Ccs 
n29E was derived. Ccs 
n29E is Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E . Both stocks are homozygous for 
Sod1 
ϩ . Inset, paraquat sensitivity of SOD1-null adults. Sod1 
Ϫ is Sod1 
n108 / 
Sod1 
n108 . Sod1 
ϩ is the wild type stock, ry </p>

<p>ϩ5 </p>

<p>. Both stocks are homozygous for 
Ccs 
ϩ . Young adult males (at least 200 flies per genotype, 10 flies per vial) were 
exposed to 2 mM paraquat. Survivors were enumerated after 24 h. Paraquat 
data represent the mean Ϯ S.D. of at least three independent determinations. </p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Expression of hSOD1 in CCS-null Drosophila. A, hSOD1 
expressed in Drosophila is enzymatically active in the absence of CCS. 
In-gel activity assay of SOD used extracts of young adult males. hSOD1 was 
expressed in Ccs 
ϩ/ϩ and Ccs 
Ϫ/Ϫ flies using the GAL4/UAS system. Geno-
types (by lane) are as follows: lane 1, Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ ; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , 
daGAL4 
G32 ; lane 2, Ccs 
Ϫ /Ccs 
Ϫ ; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ ; lane 3, Ccs 
Ϫ /Ccs 
Ϫ ; dSod1 
ϩ / 
dSod1 
ϩ ; daGAL4 
G32 ; lane 4, Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ, UAS-hSod1; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ ; lane 5, 
Ccs 
Ϫ /Ccs 
Ϫ , UAS-hSod1; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ ; lane 6, Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ , UAS-hSod1; 
dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 ; lane 7, Ccs 
Ϫ /Ccs 
Ϫ , UAS-hSod1; dSod1 
ϩ / 
dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . The UAS-hSod1 transgene is on recombinant 2nd 
chromosomes carrying Ccs 
ϩ or Ccs 
Ϫ . Ccs 
Ϫ ϭ Ccs 
n29E . B, human SOD1 res-
cues flies deficient in CCS. Genotypes are as follows: Ccs 
ϩ/ϩ ,Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
ϩ ; 
dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . Ccs 
ϩ/Ϫ , Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
n29E ; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod 
ϩ , 
daGAL4 
G32 . Ccs 
Ϫ/Ϫ , Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E ; dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . Ccs 
ϩ/Ϫ , 
hSod1(a), Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
n29E , UAS-hSod1(a); dSod1 
ϩ /dSod 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . Ccs 
Ϫ/Ϫ , 
hSod1(a), Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E , UAS-hSod1(a); dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . 
Ccs 
ϩ/Ϫ , hSod1(b): Ccs 
ϩ /Ccs 
n29E , UAS-hSod1(b); dSod1 
ϩ /dSod1 
ϩ , 
daGAL4 
G32 . Ccs 
Ϫ/ Ϫ, hSod1(b): Ccs 
n29E /Ccs 
n29E , UAS-hSod1(b); dSod1 
ϩ / 
dSod1 
ϩ , daGAL4 
G32 . Note that all strains are homozygous for dSod1 
ϩ and 
hemizygous for daGAL4 
G32 , the latter of which is known to impose a mild 
dominant reduction of adult life span (compare with Fig. 3A). hSod1(a), 
hSod1(b) are independently selected recombinant 2nd chromosomes car-
rying both Ccs 
n29E and UAS-hSod1. Note that hSOD1 appears to super-
rescue in the absence of CCS. </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 • DECEMBER 19, 2008 </p>

<p>mediate the activation of apo-SOD1 by copper. Compared 
with the severity of phenotypes caused by SOD1 deficiency 
(either genomic null mutation or RNA interference knock-
down), the CCS-null phenotypes are unexpectedly mild. 
This likely arises from a vanishingly small amount of CCS-
independent SOD1 activity that is at or just below the 
threshold of detectability in fly extracts and could only be 
discerned in concentrated lysates from yeast cells expressing 
dSOD1. Considering the rather severe phenotype of SOD1-
null flies with respect to adult life span and oxidative stress 
resistance (10), these findings suggest that only a very small 
fraction of wild type SOD1 is actually required for adult via-
bility in the absence of oxidative stress, whereas the bulk of 
SOD1 is utilized in defense against oxidative stress. This 
view is supported by the contrasting modest and severe 
effects of CCS deficiency on life span and paraquat resist-
ance, respectively. Thus, the age of onset and severity of early 
adult mortality in CCS-nulls is markedly less than in SOD1-
nulls, whereas the hypersensitivity of CCS-nulls to paraquat 
is essentially equivalent to that of SOD1-nulls. 
It is also possible that the residual SOD1 activity in CCS-nulls 
reflects the presence of enzymatically active SOD1 in just one 
or a small number of cell types in which the CCS-independent 
activation pathway is particularly 
active. Although we know of no 
direct evidence in support of this 
possibility, the ectopic expression of 
the CCS-independent hSOD1 in 
motor neurons, which confers 
robust rescue of the SOD1-null 
adult life span (14), suggests that 
motor neurons do possess an active 
CCS-independent activation path-
way; consequently, motor neurons 
could potentially be one such cell 
type that could activate dSOD1 in 
the absence of CCS. Because Dro-
sophila life span is sensitive to SOD1 
activity in motor neurons, the func-
tioning of the CCS-independent 
activation pathway in motor neu-
rons could also help explain why 
CCS deficiency has such a modest 
effect on adult life span relative to 
the severe life span reduction con-
ferred by SOD1 deficiency. Alterna-
tively, and as discussed later, our 
results are consistent with the pos-
sibility that although most cells can 
survive under normal conditions 
with little SOD1, some cells may 
require more than the residual level 
of SOD1 activity present in CCS-
nulls under conditions of applied 
oxidative stress (paraquat) or 
increased metabolic activity (motor 
neurons). Finally, it is also plausible 
that cell type variation in copper </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Expression of Drosophila SOD1 (dSOD1) in yeast. A, an align-
ment of the C-terminal region of SOD1 molecules from S. cerevisiae, human, 
and Drosophila, highlighting the proline residues known to preclude CCS-
independent activation of yeast SOD1 (5). B, coding sequences for S. cerevi-
siae, human, and Drosophila SOD1 were placed under control of the S. cerevi-
siae SOD1 gene promoter and used to transform a yeast strain that was sod1⌬ 
and either CCS1 (yCCS:ϩ) or ccs1⌬ (yCCS:Ϫ) as indicated. SOD1 lysates were 
analyzed for SOD1 activity (top) or SOD1 protein levels using an antibody 
directed against C. elegans Cu,Zn-SOD1 that cross-reacts well with diverse 
SOD1 molecules (6). Amounts of lysate protein analyzed are as follows: lanes 
1-6, 5 g; lane 7, 10 g; lane 8, 25 g; lane 9, 50 g. Strains analyzed include 
KS107 (sod1⌬) and LS101 (sod1⌬ ccs1⌬). </p>

<p>FIGURE 6. Role of copper and CCS in stabilizing the dSOD1 expressed in yeast. A sod1⌬ ccs1⌬ yeast strain 
expressing the designated SOD1 and CCS molecules was analyzed for SOD1 activity and SOD1 polypeptide 
levels using 10 g of cell lysate protein for each sample. A, strains expressing dSOD1 and either wild type (WT) 
or the indicated mutant versions of S. cerevisiae CCS1 or empty vector were analyzed for steady state levels of 
the dSOD1 polypeptide. Top, immunoblot analysis; bottom, quantitation of immunoblot by Odyssey quantita-
tion software (version 1.2) where 100 ϭ amount of dSOD1 polypeptide accumulated in cells expressing WT 
CCS1. B, cells expressing dSOD1 and either S. cerevisiae CCS1 or Drosophila CCS driven by the S. cerevisiae CCS1 
promoter were grown in the presence of 100 M bathocuproine sulfonate where indicated (ϩ), and dSOD1 
polypeptide levels measured as in A where 100 ϭ amount of dSOD1 polypeptide with no addition of batho-
cuproine sulfonate. C, cells expressing either yeast, human, or Drosophila SOD1 in combination with either 
yeast or Drosophila CCS or with vector as indicated were analyzed for SOD1 activity and SOD1 protein levels as 
Fig. 5B. D, cells expressing yeast SOD1 and either wild type or the indicated mutant versions of S. cerevisiae CCS1 
were analyzed for SOD1 activity and protein levels as in Fig. 5B. </p>

<p>Drosophila CCS </p>

<p>DECEMBER 19, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 35399 </p>

<p>availability could, in principle, underpin such cell type specific-
ity in CCS-independent activation of SOD1. 
Drosophila SOD1 can now be added to the growing list of 
SOD1 molecules that can obtain copper independently of CCS. 
Currently, the only Cu,Zn-SOD known to solely rely on CCS is 
the SOD1 of S. cerevisiae. It is curious that yeast does not need 
a CCS independent pathway, yet retains the ability to activate 
heterologous SODs independent of CCS. A likely explanation is 
that the factors for CCS independent activation serve another 
function in the cell. For example, CCS independent activation 
may involve metal binding or thiol-reactive molecules that par-
ticipate in more general metal homeostasis and/or redox 
control. 
Drosophila SOD1 appears unique in that the apo-form is very 
unstable in the absence of the copper chaperone. The apparent 
instability is not because of the Drosophila host, as human 
SOD1 expressed in CCS-null flies shows no polypeptide loss, 
and in the heterologous yeast expression system, ccs1⌬ muta-
tions affect loss of dSOD1 but not yeast or human SOD1 exam-
ined in parallel. Moreover, in CCS 
Ϫ/Ϫ mouse models, the mam-
malian SOD1 polypeptide is stable (32). This loss of dSOD1 in 
the absence of CCS is in fact reminiscent of what has been 
observed with certain amyotrophic lateral sclerosis mutants of 
human SOD1 associated with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis 
(33). Because CCS both inserts copper and oxidizes the SOD1 
disulfide, either one or both of these post-translational modifi-
cations must be important stabilizing factors for the dSOD1 
molecule. 
Prior to these studies, apo-inactive SOD1 was generally 
thought to stably accumulate in cells, allowing for rapid enzyme 
activation by CCS without the need for new SOD1 synthesis 
(31, 34). Yet Drosophila SOD1 does not stably accumulate in 
the inactive apo-form. Consequently, the high level of enzyme 
activity that is required to defend against oxidative challenge 
would require de novo SOD1 synthesis. The inability of CCS-
null adults, which are constitutively deficient in SOD1 activity, 
to mount a successful defense against paraquat-induced oxida-
tive stress is consistent with this scenario. It is also possible that 
available copper is limiting in Drosophila, and it would be dis-
advantageous to produce more copper-binding SOD1 than is 
needed. 
With the exception of certain insects, CCS molecules from 
diverse eukaryotes harbor an MXCXXC near the N terminus 
that is a well characterized Cu(I) site (35). Although earlier 
studies with human CCS indicated that the MXCXXC cysteines 
may be necessary for SOD1 activation in vivo (36), studies with 
recombinant CCS in vitro indicate that only the C-terminal 
CXC cysteines are needed to bind and transfer the metal (37, 
38). We observed that the MXCXXC motif is not required for 
activation of yeast SOD1 in vivo; copper binding and transfer 
must occur exclusively via the C-terminal CXC motif of CCS 
and the same must be true for dCCS lacking the N-terminal 
cysteines. It remains possible that in certain species, the N-ter-
minal MXCXXC site becomes critical for maintaining SOD1 
activity when oxygen and/or copper are limiting reagents for 
CCS. If true, the absence of such a motif in Drosophila CCS 
would minimize copper loading of SOD1 when pools of the 
metal are sparse. However, the biological consequences of tran-</p>

<p>sient fluctuations in copper availability may be minimized by 
the relative stability of metalated SOD1 coupled with the low 
cell turnover in the post-mitotic Drosophila adult. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank Kalpana White and Maryanne Fener-
jian for sending us the 29E (Ccs 
n29E ) and H340 strains that provided 
the genetic foundation for the Drosophila work. We also thank Pete 
Anderson and Shawna Wicks for assistance in constructing and 
maintaining Drosophila stocks, for help with phenotypic assays, and 
for many helpful discussions. </p>



<p>Drosophila CCS </p>



<p>VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 • DECEMBER 19, 2008 </p>



<p>Drosophila CCS </p>

<p>DECEMBER 19, 2008 • VOLUME 283 • NUMBER 51 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 35401 </p>

</text></tei>