<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2911847" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-14T13:23+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Shewanellae are facultative g-proteobacteria whose remarkable respiratory versatility has resulted in interest in their utility 
for bioremediation of heavy metals and radionuclides and for energy generation in microbial fuel cells. Extensive experi-
mental efforts over the last several years and the availability of 21 sequenced Shewanella genomes made it possible to 
collect and integrate a wealth of information on the genus into one public resource providing new avenues for making 
biological discoveries and for developing a system level understanding of the cellular processes. The Shewanella knowl-
edgebase was established in 2005 to provide a framework for integrated genome-based studies on Shewanella ecophy-
siology. The present version of the knowledgebase provides access to a diverse set of experimental and genomic data along 
with tools for curation of genome annotations and visualization and integration of genomic data with experimental data. 
As a demonstration of the utility of this resource, we examined a single microarray data set from Shewanella oneidensis 
MR-1 for new insights into regulatory processes. The integrated analysis of the data predicted a new type of bacterial 
transcriptional regulation involving co-transcription of the intergenic region with the downstream gene and suggested a 
biological role for co-transcription that likely prevents the binding of a regulator of the upstream gene to the regulator 
binding site located in the intergenic region. </p>

<p>Revealing the biological role of 
the IGs transcription using 
knowledgebase: a case study </p>

<p>Several SF transcriptomic and proteomic analyses were con-
ducted to investigate MR1 cellular adaptations that occur 
during transitioning from aerobic to anaerobic growth on 
fumarate. While the data collected was initially examined 
only to identify differentially expressed genes and proteins, 
further biological insights into MR1 behavior can be 
derived from the same data set through integration with 
other data types within the SKB, enabled by SKB tools. 
Below, we provide an example of such an analysis of the 
data from one of the SF studies (Project 'PNLcrp'). The ex-
perimental data chosen was produced using Affymetrix 
microarray's designed to probe transcripts derived from 
both genes and IGs (51). Probes of IGs included on the 
array were intended to probe a transcription of regions 
between two closest genes with a unidirectional orienta-
tion. IGs for convergent and divergent orientations of 
genes were not included in the microarray design. Some 
of the IGs probed by the microarray were rather long and 
included opposite strands of two or more genes, i.e. they 
represented antisense transcription. For example, the IG 
labeled as SO0016_SO0022 was downstream of SO0022 
and upstream of SO0016, and transcription of the IG was 
assumed from the 'plus' strand, i.e. in the same direction as 
the up-and downstream genes. In the example, the IG tran-
scription was from the stop codon of SO0016 to the start 
codon of SO0022 and included antisense sequences of five 
predicted genes transcribed from the 'minus' strand. If two 
genes were transcribed from the 'minus' strand, then the IG 
between them was also considered to be transcribed in the 
same direction. For example, transcription of the IG labeled 
as SO0197_SO0196 was assumed from the negative strain. 
This IG did not include antisense sequences of genes, but its 
transcription might prevent binding of a regulator of the 
upstream gene, which was SO0196. The microarray was 
used to measure abundances of transcripts extracted from 
wild-type and a Crp(À) mutant (52). The RNA was collected 
at various time points (0, 20, 40, 60, 90, 120 min, 4, 8, 12, 
24 h, steady-state) during the transition from aerobic 
growth with lactate to anaerobic growth with lactate and 
fumarate. The focus of our study was to examine changes 
in expression of IGs and how these changes correlated with 
changes in expression of the genes that were adjacent to 
the IG and transcribed in the same direction. Using SKB 
tools, we also addressed questions about a biological role 
of the IG transcription, namely, if generation of antisense 
transcripts in the studied conditions plays a role in gene 
silencing or in changing accessibility of regulators to their 
binding sites in gene promoters. </p>

<p>Almost half of the IGs and more than half of the 
genes significantly change their expression level in 
the Crp(À) mutant relative to the wild-type during 
the transition from aerobic to anaerobic growth </p>

<p>To identify IGs and genes with significant changes in gene 
expression the statistical analysis of the data was imple-
mented as a two class unpaired experiment, with one class 
referring to the Crp(À) mutant and the other to the 
wild-type strain of MR1. Biological replicates and time 
points were combined because of the high pair-wise correl-
ation between them (87-99%) across genes and IGs within 
either the wild-type or Crp(À) mutant expression profiles 
(Supplementary Data 1). Stanford <rs type="software">Significance Analysis of Microarray (SAM</rs>) software (53) was used for the analysis 
with the recommended parameters and a threshold for 
false discovery rate of 0.06%. Results of the analysis 
(Supplementary Data 2) revealed that almost half of the 
IGs and more than half of the genes significantly changed, 
either decreased or increased, the level of their expression in 
the Crp(À) mutant relative to the wild-type. The percentage 
of IGs yielding significantly decreased expression was about 
the same (28%) as the percentage of genes that were re-
pressed (31%). About 15% of IGs and 21% of genes had a 
significantly increased level of expression. Thus, a change in 
the growth condition in combination with the knockout of 
Crp, a regulator of the MR1 response to the change, induced 
significant transcriptional reprogramming of not only 
genes, but also of IGs in the MR1 genome. </p>

<p>Many IGs are transcribed with only up-or 
downstream gene, but not as a part of the operon </p>

<p>One potential explanation of significant changes in tran-
scription of an IG is that these changes may be coordinated 
with the transcription of the adjacent genes. This was the 
initial hypothesis of the study underlying the microarray 
design. Each IG probed by the array had adjacent genes 
transcribed in the same direction. The IG and its up-and 
downstream genes could belong to the same operon and 
were transcribed and changed their expression together. 
To validate the hypothesis we have examined whether 
changes in IG transcription levels correlate with the expres-
sion of the adjacent genes (up-and downstream). We aver-
aged the expression levels across time points and replicates 
for each strain and calculated the log(2) ratio of the aver-
age values for IGs/genes so that changes in the expression 
level of each IG and its adjacent genes in the mutant strain 
versus the wild-type strain could be compared. Microarray 
data was re-mapped to the current MR1 gene models, 
which have been extensively manually curated (see 'knowl-
edgebase description' for details), to update the assign-
ment of the IGs/genes and then compiled in a table 
(Supplementary Data 3) comprised of the IG log(2) ratio 
along with current annotations and log(2) ratios of 
its up-and downstream genes. Pearson correlation </p>

<p>.<rs type="software">SAM</rs><rs type="software">SAM</rs><rs type="software">Muscle</rs><rs type="software">Jalview</rs>Figure 4. Regulation of pykA, hexR and enzymes of the ED pathway in MR1 and overlay of the regulatory information with the 
experimental data. The figure indicates that enzymes of the ED pathway (SO2486_ SO2489) as well as pykA are significantly 
upregulated in the Crp(À) mutant, but hexR and the intergenic region between hexR and pykA are downregulated. The regu-
latory information provided in the first track of the browser (TractorDB) gives an explanation for the observed changes in the 
gene expressions. It indicates that the genes, hexR and pykA and the operon with the enzymes of the ED pathway have binding 
sites in their promoters predicted by TractorDB. Thus, both genes and the operon are likely regulated by Crp. In the wild-type 
strain of MR1, the ED pathway is not active because of upregulation of hexR by Crp during the transition from aerobic to 
anaerobic conditions. The Crp(À) mutant strain does not produce Crp; therefore, the transcriptional repressor HexR is absent in 
the mutant, and enzymes of the ED pathway, which were suppressed by HexR in the wild-type strain, are upregulated in the 
Crp(À) strain. </p>

<p>the consensus binding site for ArcA, which likely activates 
the ED operon in aerobic conditions (45). </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The unique combination of experimental data, computa-
tional predictions, curated genome annotations and visual-
ization tools in SKB provides a unique opportunity for 
researches to discover new biological regularities not only 
related to Shewanella species, but also to all bacterial or-
ganisms. The presented case study demonstrates only some 
of the available opportunities and capabilities. Although 
the biological role of IG transcription suggested in the 
study is only a hypothesis and will require further experi-
mental validation, the discovery of the potential role was 
significantly facilitated by the collected information and 
the tools provided in SKB. </p>

<p>We thank members of the Shewanella Federation for their 
contribution in developing the resource and in data 
submission. We are especially grateful to Jim Fredrickson, </p>

<p>Anna Obraztsova, Miriam Land, Timothy Gardner, 
Alexander Beliaev, Mary Lipton, Grigoriy Pinchuk, Lee 
Ann McCue and Dmitry Rodionov. We also want to thank 
anonymous reviewers of the manuscript for thoughtful 
suggestions and comments on the study. </p>

<p>Funding </p>

<p>Shewanella Federation consortium; Genomic Science 
Program of the Office of Biological and Environmental 
Research; US Department of Energy (DOE). Funding 
for open access charge: Office of Biological and 
Environmental Research, U.S. Department of Energy (DOE). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest. None declared. </p>



<p>2. Hau,H.H. and Gralnick,J.A. (2007) Ecology and biotechnology of the 
genus Shewanella. Annu. Rev. Microbiol., 61, 237-258. </p>

<p>3. Pinchuk,G.E., Rodionov,D.A., Yang,C. et al. (2009) Genomic recon-
struction of Shewanella oneidensis MR-1 metabolism reveals a pre-
viously uncharacterized machinery for lactate utilization. Proc. Natl 
Acad. Sci. USA, 106, 2874-2879. </p>

<p>Figure 5. The alignment of a conserved regulatory locus in the Shewanella genomes in the intergenic region between hexR and 
zwf genes. The locus is located from À56 to À103 nc upstream of zwf and has three adjacent binding sites for ArcA, HexR and 
Crp, respectively. The Crp binding site (TAAAAATAGATGCATTTAACAAATTC) was extracted from ShewRegDB. It was predicted by 
TractorDB (24). The HexR binding site is identified by similarity to HexR binding site consensus in Pseudomonas species (60, 61). 
The HexR binding site in Shewanella perfectly matches the Pseudomonas aeruginosa binding site (TGTTGTttaattACtACA) with 
the same location (À71 nt 5 
0 of the transcriptional start site of zwf (59). Binding of HexR to this binding site in P. aeruginosa 
was experimentally confirmed by gel shift assays. The HexR binding site in Shewanella has a perfect consensus 
TGTTGTTATATTACAACA across the species. The alignment also indicates that in Shewanella spp. the HexR binding site overlaps 
the Crp binding site. Thus, in some growth conditions, the ED pathway may be activated by Crp, but HexR binding to the site can 
prevent the pathway activation. In the Crp(À) mutant, hexR is downregulated and releases the ED operon for activation by other 
transcription factors, like ArcA, for example. One of the binding sites for the two-component response regulator ArcA is 
demonstrated with the consensus (5 
0 -GTTAgctagAATGTTA-3 
0 ). </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 11 of 13 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2010, Article ID baq012, doi:10.1093/database/baq012 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>



<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

<p>Page 13 of 13 </p>

<p>Database, Vol. 2010, Article ID baq012, doi:10.1093/database/baq012 </p>

<p>Original article </p>

<p>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................. </p>

</text></tei>