<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2698157" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T21:02+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Objective: This study was undertaken for the purpose of describing the CT 
features of intra-abdominal extra-hepatic metastases from gastrointestinal stro-
mal tumors in patients who were treated with imatinib. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods: Eleven patients with intra-abdominal extra-hepatic 
metastases from gastrointestinal stromal tumors, who were treated with imatinib 
between May 2001 and December 2003, were included in this study. The clinical 
findings and CT scans were retrospectively reviewed. The metastatic lesions 
were assessed according to the location, size (greatest diameter), attenuation, 
and the enhancing pattern before and after imatinib treatment. </p>

<p>Results: Prior to the treatment, the sizes and attenuation values of the 
metastatic lesions ranged from 5 to 20 cm and from 63 to 131 H, respectively. 
The metastatic lesions showed a heterogeneous enhancement pattern on the 
contrast-enhanced CT scans. After the treatment, the metastatic lesions became 
smaller in all 11 patients, and the corresponding attenuation value ranged from 
15 to 51 H. The metastatic lesions became homogeneous and cystic in appear-
ance on the follow-up CT scans, mimicking ascites. </p>

<p>Conclusion: Intra-abdominal extra-hepatic metastases of patients with gas-
trointestinal stromal tumors treated with imatinib may appear as well-circum-
scribed cystic lesions on contrast-enhanced CT. These metastases are likely to 
become smaller and resemble ascites, but may persist indefinitely on the follow-
up CT. </p>

<p>astrointestinal stromal tumors, formerly classified as leiomyomas or 
leiomyosarcomas, constitute the most common form of mesenchymal 
tumor in the gastrointestinal tract, with the stomach being the most 
common site of origin (1). The diagnosis of these tumors became feasible through the 
application of CD117 immunohistochemistry, which allows these neoplasms to be 
distinguished from leiomyomas or leiomyosarcomas (2). Moreover, the recently 
developed KIT-tyrosine kinase inhibitor (STI 571, imatinib [Gleevec], Novartis, 
Basel, Switzerland) has dramatically improved the treatment of gastrointestinal 
stromal tumors (3). 
The radiologic findings of gastrointestinal stromal tumors were recently described in 
the radiologic literature (1, 4 8), and are ostensibly similar to those of the previously 
described leiomyomas or leiomyosarcomas (9). The characteristic features of this 
disease are its recurrence at the primary site and the presence of metastases, primarily 
in the liver and the peritoneum (4). Recently, it was reported that the hepatic 
metastases in patients treated with imatinib resembled cystic lesions (10 12). In line 
with these observations, our findings indicate that when gastrointestinal stromal </p>

<p>Kim et al. </p>



<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 
Table 1. Summary of the 11 Patients with Intraabdominal Extrahepatic Metastasis from Gastrointestinal Stromal Tumor Treated with Imatinib </p>

<p>Patient Age/ Site of </p>

<p>Site of </p>

<p>Clinical 
Initial Findings of Metastasis </p>

<p>1st F/U </p>

<p>Last F/U under Imatinib therapy </p>

<p>Comment </p>

<p>Number Sex Primary 
Metastatic Symptom Metastatic </p>

<p>Interval 
Hounsfield Attenuation Size </p>

<p>Interval 
Hounsfield Attenuation Size </p>

<p>Interval 
Hounsfield Attenuation </p>

<p>Tumor </p>

<p>Lesions </p>

<p>Lesion </p>

<p>between 
Measurements Pattern </p>

<p>after 
between Measurements Pattern after </p>

<p>between Measurements Pattern </p>

<p>Size (cm) Operation and </p>

<p>Imatinib </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Imatinib </p>

<p>Initial </p>

<p>Detection of </p>

<p>Therapy Detection </p>

<p>Therapy Detection </p>

<p>Metastasis </p>

<p>(cm) and 1st F/U </p>

<p>(cm) and Last F/U </p>

<p>(months) </p>

<p>(weeks) </p>

<p>(months) </p>

<p>01 
59/M Stomach </p>

<p>Local </p>

<p>Abdominal </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>07 </p>

<p>73 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>03 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>36 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>&lt; 1 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>recur </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>02 
46/M Stomach Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>72 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>03 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>&lt; 1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>Homo Aggravated </p>

<p>seeding, </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>11 months </p>

<p>liver </p>

<p>later </p>

<p>03 
65/M Stomach Peritoneal Abdominal </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>09 </p>

<p>88 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>04 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>F/U loss </p>

<p>seeding, </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>liver </p>

<p>04 
26/M Stomach </p>

<p>Local </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>09 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>106 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>03 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>recur </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>05 
68/M Stomach Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>81 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>seeding </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>06 
42/M Rectum </p>

<p>Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>38 </p>

<p>67 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>03 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>39 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>17 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>seeding, </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>liver </p>

<p>07 
52/M Mesentery Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>07 </p>

<p>28 </p>

<p>131 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>04 </p>

<p>51 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>seeding </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>08 
58/M Mesentery Peritoneal Abdominal </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>79 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>04 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>33 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>04 </p>

<p>21 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>seeding </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>09 
41/M Small </p>

<p>Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>74 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>04 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>06 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>bowel </p>

<p>seeding </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>10 
58/M Small </p>

<p>Peritoneal Abdominal </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>63 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>03 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>44 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>&lt; 1 </p>

<p>14 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>bowel </p>

<p>seeding </p>

<p>pain </p>

<p>11 
34/M Small </p>

<p>Peritoneal </p>

<p>Routine </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>16 </p>

<p>82 </p>

<p>Hetero </p>

<p>05 </p>

<p>08 </p>

<p>35 </p>

<p>Homo </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>11 </p>

<p>28 
Homo Aggravated </p>

<p>bowel </p>

<p>seeding, </p>

<p>F/U </p>

<p>2 months </p>

<p>liver </p>

<p>later </p>

<p>tumors are treated with imatinib, the intra-abdominal 
extra-hepatic metastases come to have a homogeneous or 
almost homogeneous low density, simulating cystic masses 
or ascites on CT. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>From May 2001 to December 2003, 11 patients with 
intra-abdominal extra-hepatic metastases from gastroin-
testinal stromal tumor were treated with imatinib. Their 
mean age was 50 years, ranging from 34 to 68 years, and 
all were men. The mean time between the initial diagnosis 
of the gastrointestinal stromal tumor and the diagnosis of 
metastases was 19 months (range, 7 38 months). The 
primary sites were the stomach (n=5), the small bowel 
(n=3), the rectum (n=1), and the mesentery (n=2). In all 
patients, the primary tumors were removed by curative 
surgery. The presence of metastatic lesions was confirmed 
by biopsy (n=5) or radiologic studies and clinical follow-up 
(n=6). The criterion for the diagnosis of metastasis was the 
presence of new lesions detected in the follow-up CT scan, 
which were not detected in the initial CT scan and which </p>

<p>changed in size on the follow-up CT scan after imatinib 
treatment. In all patients, CD117 expression in the primary 
gastrointestinal stromal tumors (n=6) or metastatic lesions 
(n=5) was proved by immunohistochemical studies. All 
patients were treated with the oral administration of 400 
mg of imatinib daily. The clinical symptoms, duration of 
imatinib therapy, and CT scan reports were reviewed. The 
institutional review board at our hospital did not require 
approval or informed patient consent for the review of the 
medical records and images. 
All patients underwent CT scans prior to the administra-
tion of imatinib and 4 10 weeks after the initiation of the 
imatinib therapy. Ten patients underwent two or more 
follow-up CT scans 4 22 months after the initiation of the 
treatment with imatinib. The CT scan data were available 
on a picture archiving and communications system (PACS; 
Marotech, Seoul, Korea) for all patients. The CT scans 
were performed using a Somatom Plus-4 (Siemens Medical 
Systems, Erlangen, Germany), a HiSpeed Advantage 
scanner (General Electric Medical Systems, Milwaukee, 
WI), or a MX8000 four-detector row CT scanner (Philips 
Medical Systems, Cleveland, OH). Each patient received </p>

<p>Imatinib Causes Cystic Changes in Intraabdominal Extrahepatic Metastases from GI Tract Stromal Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 </p>

<p>159 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 1. A 34-year-old man with peritoneal seeding and liver 
metastases after resection of gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the 
duodenum. 
A. CT scan before treatment shows multiple heterogeneous 
masses (82 H) (M) compressing inferior vena cava (arrowhead) 
and superior mesenteric vein (arrow). Metastatic lesion in liver 
(curved arrow). 
B. CT scan obtained after 8 weeks of treatment with imatinib 
shows peritoneal and hepatic metastases that have decreased in 
size and density (35 H). Note the decompressed inferior vena cava 
and superior mesenteric vein and shrunk metastatic lesions in the 
liver. 
C. CT scan obtained 2 months after stopping imatinib therapy 
shows increased size and density of peritoneal and hepatic 
metastases. After resumption of imatinib therapy, the metastatic 
lesions showed cystic changes again (now shown). </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>120 mL of a nonionic contrast material (Iopromide, 
Ultravist 370; Schering Korea, Seoul, Korea) through an 
18-gauge angiographic catheter inserted into a forearm 
vein. The contrast material was injected at a rate of 2.5 
mL/sec using an automatic injector. In the case of the 
single-detector scanner, a helical CT scan was performed 
with the following parameters: 5 7 mm collimation, 1:1 
table pitch, and 5 7 mm reconstruction intervals. In the 
case of the MX8000 scanner, the parameters were 2.5 mm 
detector collimation, 20 mm/sec table speed, 5 mm slice 
thickness, and a 5 mm reconstruction interval. The delay 
between the contrast material administration and scanning 
was 55 70 seconds. 
Two radiologists reviewed all of the CT scans retrospec-
tively, and the final interpretations were reached by 
consensus. All images were reviewed on a 2,000 2,000 
PACS monitor. The presence of the metastatic lesion and 
its size before and after the imatinib treatment were 
compared. The metastatic lesions were assessed according 
to their location, size (greatest diameter), attenuation, and </p>

<p>enhancing pattern. If multiple metastatic lesions were 
detected, the largest lesion was recorded. For the objective 
analysis, the CT attenuation value was measured in a 
circular region of interest with a diameter of 10 mm. The 
CT attenuation value was measured three times by a single 
radiologist and the mean value was recorded. In the case of 
a heterogeneous mass, the CT attenuation value was 
measured in the solid portion of the tumor. The CT attenu-
ation value before and after the imatinib treatment was 
compared using the paired t-test. Statistical analyses were 
performed using a computer software package (<rs id="software-0" type="software">SPSS</rs>, 
<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">version 10.0</rs>; SPSS, Chicago, Ill). A p value of less than .05 
was considered to indicate a statistically significant differ-
ence. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>The clinical and radiologic findings are summarized in 
Table 1. One patient (patient 3) was lost to follow-up after 
1 month of imatinib therapy. Two patients (patients 2 and </p>

<p>Kim et al. </p>

<p>160 </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 2. A 68-year-old man with peritoneal seeding after resection of 
gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the stomach. 
A. CT scan before treatment shows 15 13 cm heterogeneous 
metastatic lesion (81 H) (G) in left subphrenic space. Note small 
metastatic nodule (arrow) in right subphrenic space and ascites (15 
H). 
B. CT scan obtained after 8 weeks of treatment with imatinib 
shows metastatic lesion (G) that has decreased in size to 8 6 cm 
and is cyst-like in appearance lesion (28 H) around spleen (S). 
Note the disappearance of the ascites. 
C. CT scan obtained after 13 months of treatment with imatinib 
shows 5 3.5 cm cystic lesion (20 H). </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>11) stopped imatinib therapy 10 and 11 months, respec-
tively, after the initiation of the treatment. The remaining 
8 patients were under imatinib therapy for periods ranging 
from 4 to 22 months at the time this article was written. 
On the contrast-enhanced CT, the metastatic lesions 
were detected in the peritoneal cavity (n=9), and at the 
surgical bed of the primary site (n=2). In four patients, 
metastasis was also detected in the liver. Prior to the 
treatment, the mean size of the metastatic lesions was 10.4 
4.9, ranging from 5 to 20 cm, and they showed a hetero-
geneous enhancement pattern on the contrast-enhanced 
CT scans. 
After the treatment, the mean size of the metastatic 
lesions was 5.8 3.6, ranging from 3 to 15 cm, on the first 
follow-up CT scan, showing a reduction in size for all 11 
patients. On the first follow-up CT scan, the attenuation of 
the metastatic lesions was homogeneous in eight patients 
(Figs. 1 and 2), and heterogeneous in three patients (Fig. 
3). In cases of peritoneal seeding, the metastatic lesions 
developed a cystic appearance, mimicking ascites (Figs. 2 
and 3). In reviewing the original CT reports, it was found 
that the cystic change of the tumor was described as ascites 
or fluid collection in three patients. 
Prior to the treatment, the mean attenuation value of the 
metastatic lesions was 83 20 H, ranging from 63 to 131 
H. On the first follow-up CT scan, the mean attenuation 
value was 34 13 H, ranging from 15 to 51 H. This differ-
ence in the mean CT attenuation value was statistically 
significant (p &lt; 0.01). 
On the subsequent CT scans, the metastatic lesions 
became smaller, homogeneous and cystic during imatinib 
therapy. However, they did not disappear completely and 
were always detected throughout the study in all patients. </p>

<p>In two patients who showed a heterogeneous enhancement 
pattern on the first follow-up CT scan, the metastatic 
lesions became homogeneous on the second follow-up CT 
scan obtained 3 and 4 months, respectively, after the initia-
tion of treatment. 
Two patients (patients 2 and 11) stopped imatinib 
therapy 10 and 11 months, respectively, after the initiation 
of the treatment. The disease was found to have 
progressed in these 2 patients 11 and 2 months, respec-
tively, after the termination of the treatment, with the 
metastatic lesions increasing in size and attenuation, and 
showing a heterogeneous enhancement pattern on the CT 
scans (Fig. 1C). These two patients resumed imatinib 
therapy, and their metastatic lesions subsequently became 
smaller and homogeneous on the follow-up CT scans. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Conventional chemotherapeutic agents are rarely 
effective against gastrointestinal stromal tumors. The new 
chemotherapeutic agent, imatinib, has been applied and 
the results are extremely encouraging. The rationale 
behind imatinib treatment for gastrointestinal stromal 
tumors lies in the fact that the KIT (encodes the human 
homolog of the proto-oncogene c-kit) gene mutation has 
been detected frequently in gastrointestinal stromal 
tumors. This mutation induces the constitutive activation 
of the tyrosine kinase receptor, causing the proliferation of 
tumor cells (2). Imatinib is highly effective in bringing 
about a reduction in KIT tyrosine kinase activity. 
Gastrointestinal stromal tumors frequently spread to the 
liver and the peritoneum (4). On the CT scan of the portal 
venous phase, the metastases within the liver are usually </p>

<p>Imatinib Causes Cystic Changes in Intraabdominal Extrahepatic Metastases from GI Tract Stromal Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 </p>

<p>161 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. A 52-year-old man with peritoneal seeding after resection of gastrointestinal stromal tumor of the mesentery. 
A. CT scan before treatment shows multiple peritoneal implants (arrows) in both paracolic gutters. 
B. CT scan obtained after 4 weeks of treatment with imatinib shows that the metastatic lesions in the right paracolic gutter have some 
solid components, while that in the left paracolic gutter resembles ascites. </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>heterogeneous and peripherally enhanced, similar to 
primary tumors (4). The low attenuation in the center of 
these metastatic lesions often indicates the presence of 
necrosis in the center of the solid mass. The peripheral 
enhanced portion represents viable solid tumor. Peritoneal 
metastasis shows a CT appearance similar to that of 
metastasis in the liver. 
In the peritoneum, metastatic lesions treated with 
imatinib may appear as ascites or fluid collection. In 
reviewing the original CT reports, we found that the cystic 
change of the tumor was described as ascites or fluid 
collection in three patients. Although long-term follow-up 
is needed, metastatic lesions in the peritoneum gradually 
decrease in size, although they may persist for months or 
years, which is not the case for ascites. The density of the 
metastases decreased to 15 51 H on the first CT scan after 
the treatment and then to 15 28 H on the follow-up CT 
scan, which is close to that of ascites. Metastases can be 
distinguished from ascites by reviewing the change in the 
attenuation value and the previous CT scan. Ideally, the 
scans should be interpreted by a radiologist who is familiar 
with scans of peritoneal metastases from gastrointestinal 
stromal tumors following imatinib treatment, in order to 
avoid the underestimation of the extent of the tumors. 
The mechanism that induces the cystic change after 
imatinib treatment is not clear. In several reported cases, 
histological examination of the tumors treated with 
imatinib showed areas with extensive necrosis, hyalinized 
areas with sparse, scattered tumor cells containing small, 
condensed nuclei and areas with viable tumor cells (10 
12). 
The optimal duration of the treatment is not yet known 
(13). It is not clear whether viable tumor cells with 
malignant potential persist within the cystic lesions and, 
consequently, the continuous maintenance of imatinib 
treatment is required. In this study, two patients whose 
metastatic lesions became small and cystic after imatinib 
therapy, experienced aggravation of metastasis after 
termination of the imatinib treatment. 
Traditionally, the response to cancer treatment in solid 
tumors is evaluated by subsequent clinical or radiological 
assessments, and is defined as a significant decrease in the 
measurable tumor dimensions. A reduction in the viable 
tumor cell fraction, however, does not always result in a 
volume reduction, since tumor tissue can be replaced by 
necrotic or fibrotic tissue, and morphological images are 
often unable to differentiate between these different tissue 
types. In recent years, metabolic imaging with positron 
emission tomography (PET) has become increasingly 
important in cancer management. Although the perfor-
mances of PET and CT are comparable in terms of the </p>

<p>process of staging before the initiation of imatinib therapy, 
PET can evaluate the tumor response as early as 1 week 
after the start of treatment, preceding the CT response by 
several weeks (14). Treatment-induced changes resulting in 
tumor cell death or growth arrest should therefore result in 
a subsequent reduction in glucose uptake, making this 
technique a sensitive and early marker for response 
evaluation. 
There are several limitations to this study. First, this was 
a retrospective review of cases collected over a number of 
years for which CT scans were performed irregularly, 
depending on the condition of the patients. Second, 
unenhanced images were not obtained in all patients, and 
it is unclear whether or not any subtle enhancement 
changes are present in the metastatic lesions. Third, we did 
not provide any pathologic correlation in any of the cases. 
Pathologic correlation with the radiologic findings for 
metastatic lesions is helpful for clinicians as well as for 
radiologists. 
In conclusion, after treatment with imatinib, responsive 
intra-abdominal extra-hepatic metastases of gastrointesti-
nal stromal tumors appear as well-defined cystic lesions on 
contrast-enhanced CT. These metastases become smaller 
and resemble ascites, but may be detected for a long time 
on the follow-up CT scans. </p>



<p>Kim et al. </p>



<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 </p>



<p>Imatinib Causes Cystic Changes in Intraabdominal Extrahepatic Metastases from GI Tract Stromal Tumors </p>

<p>Korean J Radiol 5(3), September 2004 </p>



</text></tei>