<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2034468" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:20+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Proteins that bind DNA play a critical role in regulating 
gene structure, replication and expression in all organisms. 
Biochemical and structural analyses of proteins that bind 
specific DNA sequences have begun to provide insight 
into the molecular basis of both DNA binding and 
sequence-specific DNA recognition (1-3). These analyses 
have identified protein folds for DNA binding, together 
with a few general rules for the protein-mediated 
recognition of specific DNA bases (1,4,5). This work has 
also begun to suggest ways to modify the recognition 
specificity of existing, sequence-specific DNA-binding 
proteins. Two classes of site-specific DNA-binding </p>

<p>proteins that have been the focus for efforts to engineer 
new DNA recognition specificities are the Type II 
restriction endonucleases (6), and sequence-specific tran-
scription factors (1,7). 
The homing endonucleases, a group of highly sequence-
specific DNA-binding proteins, are also being investigated 
for recognition specificity engineering. Four different 
families of homing endonuclease proteins have been 
identified on the basis of protein sequence comparisons, 
and one or more families have been identified in all 
Kingdoms of life (8,9). The physiologic role of homing 
endonucleases is to target the lateral transfer of parasitic 
DNA elements known as mobile introns by making a 
highly sequence-specific DNA double-strand break in an 
intron-less recipient allele (8,9). 
The high site specificity of many homing endonucleases 
reflects a combination of long (15-40 bp) DNA target or 
'homing' sites, together with a high degree of sequence 
specificity at most target site base-pair positions. A second 
intrinsic property of many homing endonucleases is tight 
coupling of site recognition to catalysis (10). This is a 
particularly attractive feature of homing endonucleases, in 
contrast to other potential genome engineering reagents 
such as zinc finger nucleases (11). High site specificity 
and tight coupling of site binding to catalysis may 
reflect the evolutionary history of many homing endonu-
cleases: these two properties in concert permit the 
continued lateral transfer-and thus the persistence-of 
endonuclease-encoding mobile introns to related target 
sites, while minimizing spurious chromosome cleavage 
events (12,13). 
Our aim was to determine whether structure-guided 
protein engineering could be used to alter the DNA 
recognition specificity of the eukaryotic homing endonu-
clease I-PpoI, a member of the His-Cys box family of 
homing endonucleases. I-PpoI was originally identified as 
an open reading frame in a self-splicing mobile intron 
found in extrachromosomal copies of the 28S rRNA genes 
of Physarum polycephalum, a Plasmodial myxomycete 
slime mold (14). It is the best characterized member of the 
His-Cys box family of homing endonucleases, one family </p>

<p>Present address: 
Jennifer L. Eklund, University of Michigan School of Education, Ann Arbor, MI, USA. </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: 206 616 7392; Fax: 206 543 3967; Email: monnat@u.washington.edu </p>

<p>ß 2007 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>in the aab-Me or His-Me endonuclease superfamily 
(15,16), and has not thus far been a focus for structure-
guided design. 
The active form of I-PpoI is a 36 kDa homodimer that 
cleaves a 15-bp semi-palindromic DNA target site in the 
28S Physarum rDNA locus, and in the corresponding 
large subunit rRNA genes of all eukaryotes [(17-19); 
Figure 1]. Rare target sites may also exist outside the 
rDNA repeats (20). We had previously determined high-
resolution apo-and co-crystal structures of native and 
mutant forms of I-PpoI that allowed us to identify the 
molecular basis for high affinity site binding and cleavage 
(21,22). We had also identified amino acid changes that 
interfere with I-PpoI catalysis or site binding, together 
with DNA base-pair changes that disrupted target site 
cleavage by native I-PpoI protein (23-26). These data were 
used to construct a yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) screening 
assay to identify I-PpoI protein variants able to bind a 
specific mutant target site in vivo. Biochemical character-
ization together with computational modeling were used </p>

<p>to gain insight into the molecular basis for mutant site 
recognition and cleavage by variant I-PpoI proteins. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Plasmids and yeast strains </p>

<p>Yeast reporter plasmids were constructed using the YEp24 
two-micron plasmid vector or the integrating plasmid 
vector pRS404 (27,28). An I-PpoI-specific YEp24-lacZ 
reporter was constructed by inserting I-PpoI target sites 
into the SalI site upstream of a cyc5 promoter and lacZ 
gene. Target site inserts were prepared by annealing 
phosphorylated oligonucleotides (PPOSITES5 and 
PPOSITES6; all oligonucleotide sequences are given in 
Supplementary Data Table 1), or oligonucleotides that 
when annealed created three oriented copies of native or 
mutant I-PpoI target sites (oligonucleotides PPOX3_WT 
and _6 #1-4). Yep24-HIS3Ppo was constructed from the 
resulting plasmids by replacing the lacZ gene with a PCR 
fragment containing the budding yeast HIS3 gene. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Amino acid geometries were determined from the I-PpoI co-crystal structure (21). (A) Stereo representation of the native I-PpoI 
DNA-protein interface. Canonical contacts are present between Q63:AE6A and R74:AE7G. The native AE6A/T base pair is shown in yellow. Amino 
acid geometries were modeled using RosettaDesign. Sequence-specific hydrogen bonds are shown as black dotted lines. (B) Sequence of the native 
I-PpoI target or 'homing' site. Site cleavage across the minor groove (staggered line) generates complementary 4 base, 3 
0 OH-extended single-stranded 
ends. The convention for numbering target site base-pair positions is shown above the top strand. (C) Sequence and cleavage sensitivity of native and 
five variant I-PpoI target sites with palindromic base substitutions (shown lower case bold) at positions AE3 to AE7 assayed for native I-PpoI cleavage 
sensitivity. Cleavage sensitivity is indicated to the right of each sequence ('+++', fully sensitive; '-', no cleavage). (D) Representative cleavage 
assays of native and mutant I-PpoI target sites by native I-PpoI protein. Linearized plasmid DNA (10 mM) was digested for 1 h with 10 pM to 1 mM 
native I-PpoI prior to agarose gel electrophoresis. ('uncut', plasmid substrates; 'cut', site-specific cleavage products). </p>



<p>An integrating version of Yep24-HIS3Ppo was con-
structed by transferring an EcoRI fragment containing a 
multiple-cloning site, minimal promoter and HIS3 gene 
into the yeast TRP1 integration vector pRS404, and then 
inserting three copies of the native or +6C/-6G mutant 
I-PpoI target site as described earlier Yeast containing an 
integrated copy of pRS404-HIS3Ppo were constructed by 
transforming MfeI-cleaved linear plasmid DNA into yeast 
strain W1588-4C (MATa ade2-1 can1-100 his3-11, 15 
leu2-3, 112trp1-1 ura3-1 RAD5), followed by selection on 
SD media lacking tryptophan (29,30). Selection for HIS3 
reporter expression was performed by growth on SD 
medium lacking histidine, followed by a demonstration of 
growth suppression by 3 mM 3-aminotriazole. All reporter 
plasmids and strains were verified by DNA sequencing of 
the I-PpoI target site region. </p>

<p>Generation of I-PpoI protein variants </p>

<p>CR library. Expression plasmids for Ppo-activation 
domain (AD) fusion proteins were constructed by insert-
ing I-PpoI open reading frame cassettes in-frame into the 
GAL4 activation domain plasmid pOAD (kindly provided 
by Stan Fields, University of WA, USA). The corrected 
map and sequence of this plasmid can be found at: 
depts.washington.edu/sfields/protocols/pOAD.html. After 
removing flanking BamHI sites, the open reading frame of 
catalytically inactive H98A I-PpoI was inserted into the 
NcoI and PstI sites of pOAD to form pOAD-Ppo. A 3 kb 
insert or 'dummy' fragment was inserted into the NdeI-
BamHI site in the I-PpoI ORF to create pOAD-Ppo+d. 
This 'dummy' fragment was subsequently replaced with an 
oligonucleotide insert encoding 25 codons of the I-PpoI 
ORF to restore the open reading frame and randomize 
I-PpoI residues N57, R61, Q63, K65 and R74. This insert 
was constructed by the annealing of three oligonucleo-
tides, PPO(-)5, PPO+ NDEI and PPO NDEI SPLINT 
and ligation, at 500-fold molar excess, into NdeI-cut 
pOAD-Ppo+d. The PPO(-)5 oligonucleotide region con-
taining randomized codons was converted to double-
stranded DNA by primer extension with Klenow DNA 
polymerase prior to cleaving the resulting insert and 
plasmid with BamHI (31), ligation and electroporation 
into E. coli TB1 cells. The number of independent 
transformants was determined by plating a small portion 
of the pooled transformation, and the library was 
amplified by growth overnight in 1 l of L-broth followed 
by plasmid DNA isolation [(32); Qiagen MegaPrep]. </p>

<p>RD1 and RD2 libraries. The RD1 and RD2 libraries were 
constructed by replacing the region encompassing I-PpoI 
residues 55-76 with an insert generated by PCR-mediated 
assembly of degenerate oligonucleotides. Five oligonu-
cleotides (the 4 +6G_B oligonucleotides and PPOOADN 
were used to assemble the N-terminal portion of the 
I-PpoI H98A ORF. Two +6G_E oligonucleotides and 
PPOOADC (RD1) or PPOOADCdeg (RD2) were used to 
assemble the C-terminal portion of the I-PpoI ORF. 
PPOADCdeg included a 9 bp randomized 'molecular bar 
tag' sequence to allow different starting plasmids to be 
distinguished. Both PCR assembly products were gel </p>

<p>purified by polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE). 
The N-terminal assembly product was extended in a 
second PCR reaction using a pool of 27 (RD1) or 18 
(RD2) +6_M oligonucleotides together with PPOOADN. 
The resulting product was gel-purified and amplified 
with recombination cloning primers AD70F and AD70R 
(kindly provided by Stan Fields, University of WA; http:// 
depts.washington.edu/sfields/protocols/protocols.html) to 
generate a full-length I-PpoI open reading frame insert, 
and then used for in vivo gap repair of PvuII + NcoI-
cleaved pOAD-Ppo plasmid DNA. 
Ppo-AD libraries were characterized by sequencing 
plasmid DNA isolated from independent colonies. 
Seventy-four CR library plasmids were sequenced, 11 
from plasmid preps and 63 from PCR products generated 
using PADSCREENF and PADSCREENB oligonucleo-
tides. RD1 and RD2 were characterized by sequencing 
yeast colony PCR products. PCR and the sequencing were 
performed with PADSEQF and 882 oligonucleotide 
primers. The resulting forward and reverse sequences 
were aligned using Sequencher (www.sequencher.com). </p>

<p>Site-directed mutagenesis. The I-PpoI open reading frame 
was subcloned from Ppo-AD fusion plasmids into a 
pET11c derivative containing an N-terminal hexa-
histidine affinity purification tag prior to expression in 
E. coli and purification by Ni-NTA affinity chromato-
graphy (Qiagen). The pET11c-histagPpo expression vector 
was constructed by annealing oligonucleotides pET-
histagf and pET-histagr containing the affinity tag, 
followed by ligation into the NdeI site of pET-Ppo (23), 
to generate pET11c-histagPpo. Site-directed mutagenesis 
using a QuikChange protocol (Stratagene) was then used 
to generate pET vectors expressing variants A, B, C, F, P, 
Q, R, S, T, Y and H98A/L116A. Variants U, V and W 
were made by site-directed mutagenesis of the variant C 
expression vector. Variants D, E, G, H, J, K, L, M and 
N were constructed by inserting an NcoI-BamHI frag-
ment from RD2 Ppo-AD plasmids into the open reading 
frame of pET11c-histagPpo. </p>

<p>Library screening and b-galactosidase activity assays </p>

<p>CR or RD library screening was performed by trans-
forming CR or RD plasmid libraries, together with the 
+6C/-6G lacZ reporter plasmid Yep24-lacZPpo, into 
cells possessing an integrated copy of the pRS404-
HIS3Ppo reporter plasmid. The resulting cells were then 
selected for growth on histidine-minus media followed by 
a visual screen for b-galactosidase activity. The number of 
independent co-transformants was determined by plating 
a small known fraction of the transformed yeast on 
SD-leucine-uracil plates. Library screening was per-
formed by dense plating of transformed cells on 
SD-leucine-uracil-histidine plates supplemented with 
3 mM 3-aminotriazole, followed by growth at 308C for 
7 days. Large colonies were then picked into 1 ml 96-well 
deep blocks containing SD-leucine-uracil media and 
grown for 7 days without shaking at 308C. 
A colorometric screen for b-galactosidase reporter gene 
induction was used to identify Ppo-AD plasmids with </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 17 5841 </p>

<p>in vivo site-binding activity. In brief, cells were pelleted, 
then resuspended and permeabilized in Z-buffer using 
SDS and chloroform (33). The b-galactosidase substrate 
ONPG was added to 0.6 mg/ml, and wells were incubated 
at 308C to monitor color change. Incubations were 
stopped between 2 and 4 h by adding Na 2 CO 3 prior to 
visual screening to identify positive wells by comparison 
against positive control (H98A Ppo-AD and native I-PpoI 
site lacZ reporter) or negative control (H98A Ppo-AD and 
mutant +6C/-6G site lacZ reporter) cells. 
Ppo-AD coding plasmids were recovered from activity-
positive cells by use of either a Qiagen or Sigma miniprep 
kit, amplified by transformation and growth in E. coli, 
and then transformed into yeast strain W1588-4C. We 
assayed at least eight transformants from each original 
positive colony for b-galactosidase induction by ONPG 
assay prior to streaking cells on SD-leucine plates 
supplemented with 5-fluoroorotic acid (5-FOA) to elim-
inate the URA3 reporter plasmid. In order to verify site-
specific b-galactosidase induction, plasmid DNAs from 
activity-positive cultures were retransformed as described 
above with a +6C/À6G or native site reporter plasmid. 
The DNA sequence of the Ppo-AD open reading frame 
was determined from the same plasmid preparation by 
sequencing using a PADSCREENF sequencing primer. 
Quantitative b-galactosidase activity assays were per-
formed to further characterize several I-PpoI variants by 
using a modification of the screening assay as described 
above (33). Cells were grown overnight at 308C in 
SD-leucine-uracil media. Cell density was determined by 
measuring absorbance at 600 nm, and 2 ml of each culture 
was pelleted and resuspended in 0.8 ml of Z-buffer 
followed by the addition of 50 ml 0.1% SDS and 50 ml 
chloroform with vortexing for 30 s. Activity was measured 
by adding 160 ml of 4 mg/ml ONPG in Z-buffer followed 
by incubation at 308C, and stopped by adding 0.4 ml 
Na 2 CO 3 after the development of yellow color. Cell debris 
was spun out of reactions prior to measuring absorbance 
at 420 nm and calculating units of b-galactosidase activity. 
All reported values represent an average of three 
independent determinations. </p>

<p>Protein expression and purification </p>

<p>Variant I-PpoI proteins subcloned into pET11c-histagPpo 
were expressed in E. coli host strain BL21(DE3) 
(Novagen). Single colonies were picked into 2-3 ml of 
L-broth supplemented with 100 mg/ml carbenicillin and 
0.2% glucose, then grown overnight at 378C. Overnight 
cultures (300 ml each) were then diluted into 100 ml of 
L-broth supplemented with carbenicillin and 1 mM zinc 
acetate and grown for 2-4 h at 378C. Protein production 
was induced by adding 1 mM IPTG. After induction 
for 3-5 h at 378C, cells were pelleted and stored overnight 
at À808C. 
Protein was purified from frozen cell pellets by thawing 
and resuspending cells in 1 ml of lysis buffer (50 mM 
NaH 2 PO 4 , 300 mM NaCl and 10 mM imidazole) contain-
ing 1 mg/ml lysozyme on ice, followed by the addition of 
protease inhibitors (1 mM PMSF, 1 mg/ml leupeptin and 
1 mg/ml pepstatin) and sonication. RNAse A (10 mg/ml) </p>

<p>and DNAse I (5 mg/ml) were added to cell lysates followed 
by incubation on ice for 15 min. Cell debris was pelleted at 
48C, and Ni-NTA resin (100 ml; Qiagen) was added to the 
cleared supernatant prior to incubation at 48C on a roller 
for 1-2 h. Resin was pelleted from the supernatant in 
a benchtop centrifuge at 48C, washed once with 1 ml of 
20 mM imidazole buffer (50 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 300 mM NaCl 
and 20 mM imidazole), and then washed twice with 1 ml 
50 mM imidazole buffer (50 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 300 mM NaCl 
and 50 mM imidazole). Protein was eluted with 3 Â 50 ml 
washes of 50 mM NaH 2 PO 4 , 300 mM NaCl and 250 mM 
imidazole. Eluates were pooled to determine protein 
concentration by Bradford assay prior to the addition 
of glycerol to 50% (v/v) and storage at À208C. 
Polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis of protein samples 
followed by Coommassie staining indicated that I-PpoI 
protein preparations were typically &gt;75% pure with no 
other major contaminating bands. </p>

<p>Site-binding affinity and cleavage assays </p>

<p>The binding affinity (K d ) and cleavage of I-PpoI target 
sites were determined as previously described (26). The 
substrates for binding affinity assays were formed by 
annealing gel-purified PPOx1 oligonucleotide pairs in 
which (+) strand oligonucleotides had been end-labeled 
with 
32 P. K d values were determined from a minimum of 
two, or in most cases three, independent assays. Cleavage 
assays were performed using linearized plasmids contain-
ing either three copies of native or mutant I-PpoI target 
sites inserted into the SalI site of pRS404-HIS3Ppo, or 
single site PPOx1_Sal oligonucleotides pairs that had been 
annealed and inserted into pBlueScriptII KS(+) plasmid 
DNA (Stratagene). pRS404 plasmids were linearized with 
SnaBI, and pBluescriptII plasmids with XmnI, prior to 
performing cleavage assays. </p>

<p>Computational modeling of I-PpoI variants </p>

<p>Modeling of the I-PpoI DNA interface of native and 
variant proteins was done using <rs type="software">RosettaDesign</rs> (34,35). 
In brief, changes to the substrate DNA sequence and the 
amino acid sequence of the protein were simulated in 
silico, and the DNA-protein complex was allowed to relax 
according to an energy function that mimics protein 
folding. I-PpoI variants E, G and T were modeled and 
visualized for inspection using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">PyMOL</rs> molecular 
viewer (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">DeLano Scientific LLC</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Cleavage sensitivity of I-PpoI target site variants </p>

<p>We identified I-PpoI target sites that were cleavage-
resistant when challenged with native I-PpoI protein. We 
focused initially on 5-bp positions, AE3 to AE7, and on base-
pair substitutions at these sites that were known to affect 
cleavage efficiency on the basis of previous homing site 
degeneracy, biochemical or functional analyses (24,25,36). 
These base-pair positions are in a well-ordered part of the 
I-PpoI DNA-protein interface (Figure 1A). Palindromic 
AE3 G&gt;A/C&gt;T and AE4 G&gt;C/T&gt;G base-pair substitutions </p>



<p>were permissive of cleavage only at high protein concen-
trations (10 nM for the AE3 position; 1 mM for the AE4 
position). In contrast, base-pair substitutions at positions 
AE5 (T&gt;A/C&gt;T), AE6 (A&gt;C/T&gt;G) and AE7 (G&gt;A/C&gt;T) 
completely inhibited cleavage at all protein concentrations 
tested (Figure 1D; data not shown). Of the six possible 
base-pair changes from the native +6A/À6T target site, 
+6A&gt;C/À6T&gt;G substitutions most strongly inhibited 
site cleavage by native I-PpoI (Figure 1C and D; data not 
shown). We chose this target site for re-engineering of the 
site recognition specificity of I-PpoI. </p>

<p>A yeast one-hybrid screening assay </p>

<p>A yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) screen was used to identify 
I-PpoI protein variants that bound the +6C/À6G target 
site in vivo to induce reporter gene expression. To establish 
this assay, we fused a Saccharomyces cerevisiae Gal4p 
transcriptional activation domain to the N-terminus of 
catalytically inactive H98A I-PpoI to generate Ppo-AD. 
The H98A substitution was incorporated to abolish the 
catalytic activity of I-PpoI without disrupting high affinity </p>

<p>site binding [Figure 2A; (22,23,26)]. A Ppo-AD negative 
control protein was constructed by fusing L116A I-PpoI 
to the Gal4p activation domain. L116A I-PpoI is 
catalytically inactive, and does not bind I-PpoI target 
site DNA (26). Reporter activity was determined using a 
budding yeast HIS3 or plasmid-borne bacterial lacZ 
reporter genes located downstream of 1 or more I-PpoI 
target site and a minimal promoter (Figure 2B). Site 
binding was quantified by the induction of b-galactosidase 
activity, and was strongest when the lacZ reporter gene 
was flanked by 6 direct repeats of the native I-PpoI target 
site: 25-to-75-fold above the 'no site' or negative control 
background. The Gal4-L116A Ppo-AD negative control 
protein did not induce reporter expression above back-
ground on any target site or number of repeats (Figure 2C; 
data not shown). We performed all subsequent library 
screens using reporter genes flanked by three target sites, 
as these reporters could be readily constructed and gave 
reporter activity well above background. </p>

<p>Generation and screening of I-PpoI protein variant libraries </p>

<p>In order to generate protein variants to screen against 
the mutant +6C/À6G target site, we made substitutions 
in the I-PpoI DNA-protein interface at residues that 
contacted base-pair position 6 or adjacent base-pair 
positions. This 'contacting residue' (CR) library was 
designed to allow all 20 amino acid residues at positions 
N57, R61, Q63, K65 and R74, and had a maximum 
potential complexity of 3.2 Â 10 
6 (20 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>) protein variants. 
The resulting CR library was difficult to construct, and 
thus not large enough to encompass all predicted variants. 
Upon experimental verification, the CR library was found 
to encode 1.6 Â 105 different protein variants that each 
had an average of 4.7 amino acid substitutions 
(CR library, Table 1). 
The CR library was screened by Y1H in two steps. 
We isolated yeast transformants that grew on histidine-
minus plates containing 3-aminotriazole (3-AT), and then 
determined whether the same Ppo-AD plasmids could 
induce in vivo b-galactosidase expression. The Ppo-AD 
open reading frame of active variants was then sequenced 
to identify amino acid substitution(s) that conferred in vivo 
activity. Among the 2 Â 10 
6 colony transformants and 
4600 His+ colonies screened, only one CR library 
transformant had in vivo activity on both reporter genes. 
This variant (variant A, Table 2) had four amino acid 
substitutions at residue positions randomized during CR 
library construction. 
Variant A served as a starting point for the construction 
of two additional, rationally designed (RD) libraries that 
were used to further explore determinants of I-PpoI 
recognition and in vivo activity on native and +6C/À6G 
target sites. The first RD library allowed +6C/À6G 
contacting residue 63 to vary among seven amino acid 
residues: the native Q, or D, E, K, N, R or Y. Neighboring 
b-strand residues A55, N57, W62, Y64, R74 and G76 were 
substituted with residues that differed slightly in size and/ 
or polarity from native residues found at these positions 
(RD1; Table 1). The predicted maximum complexity of 
the RD1 library was 3.5 Â 10 
4 . Sequencing indicated that </p>

<p>Figure 2. Yeast one-hybrid assay used to identify GAL4-I-PpoI fusion 
proteins that bind target site DNA in vivo. (A) GAL4-I-PpoI fusion 
protein generated by inserting the open reading frame of H98A I-PpoI 
downstream of the GAL4 transcriptional transactivation domain 
(GAL4-AD). The H98A substitution abolishes I-PpoI catalytic activity 
without affecting site-binding affinity. (B) Reporter genes to detect 
in vivo binding of GAL4-I-PpoI were constructed in the yeast plasmid 
YEp24 or in the TRP1 integration vector pRS404 by inserting three 
direct repeats of native or mutant I-PpoI target site upstream of a 
minimal promoter and the budding yeast HIS3 or bacterial lacZ gene. 
(C) In vivo activity of H98A (positive control) and L116A (negative 
control) GAL4-I-PpoI fusion proteins in budding yeast, on native or 
+6C/-6G target site b-galactosidase reporter plasmids. Activity is 
measured by a quantitative b-galactosidase activity assay (see Methods 
section). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 17 5843 </p>

<p>72% of RD1 Ppo-AD plasmids had intact open reading 
frames. Thus the completed RD1 library of 1.8 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>members was sufficiently large to include all RD1 design 
variants (RD1, Table 1). 
In vivo screening of RD1 against +6C/À6G target site 
reporter genes yielded 352 His+ colonies, and 15 plasmids 
from this pool were verified by re-transformation and 
quantitative lacZ activity prior to sequencing. Five active 
Ppo-AD plasmids had the same Ppo-AD amino acid 
substitutions found in variant A (Table 2). Six different 
RD1 starting plasmids harbored the same Q63R and 
K65R substitutions (Table 2, variant E), as indicated by 
plasmid DNA sequence differences. Four other plasmids 
had the variant E Q63R and K65R substitutions together 
with 2 to 4 other substitutions at residues targeted during 
library construction (variants B, C, D and F; Table 2). 
A second rationally designed library was constructed to 
determine whether additional residue substitutions could 
augment the in vivo activity of Ppo-AD proteins identified 
in the CR and RD1 libraries. The RD2 library design 
features were: (i) three positions were fixed as residues 
found in active variants of RD1 (63R, 64Y and 76G); 
(ii) residue 55 was an A, G, L or V, and residue 62 was an 
F or W, again as previously identified in active variants; 
(iii) contacting residues 57, 61, 65 and 74 were varied </p>

<p>Table 2. Biochemical properties and residue substitutions in I-PpoI variants </p>

<p>Variant 
Source 
Binding K d (nM) 
Site cleavage 
Residue at position </p>

<p>WT 
+6C/À6G 
WT 
+6C/À6G 
55 
57 
61 
62 
63 
64 
65 
74 
76 </p>

<p>H98A 
SDM 
0.11 AE 0.02 
!1000 
++++ 
No 
A 
N 
R 
W 
Q 
Y 
K 
R 
G 
L116A 
SDM 
350 AE 60 
!1000 
No 
No 
T 
SDM 
0.034 AE 0.01 
6 AE 1.5 
++++ 
+/À 
R 
B 
RD1 
110 AE 10 
130 AE 30 
No 
No 
G 
F 
R 
R 
T 
U 
SDM 
130 AE 40 
!1000 
+++ 
No 
V 
C 
R 
T 
Y 
SDM 
180 AE 60 
!1000 
+ 
No 
C 
R 
R 
D 
RD1, RD2 
230 AE 40 
240 AE 80 
No 
No 
L 
R 
R 
E 
RD1, RD2 
280 AE 90 
140 AE 40 
++ 
No 
R 
R 
H 
RD2 
460 AE 140 
310 AE 90 
No 
No 
F 
R 
R 
P 
SDM 
480 AE 30 
570 AE 150 
++++ 
No 
V 
R 
SDM 
500 AE 20 
!1000 
No 
No 
K 
Q 
SDM 
620 AE 90 
570 AE 160 
++ 
No 
A 
W 
SDM 
620 AE 160 
480 AE 100 
No 
No 
V 
C 
R 
R 
A 
CR, RD1 
630 AE 190 
!1000 
No 
No 
C 
R 
R 
T 
J 
RD2 
760 AE 40 
430 AE 50 
No 
No 
I 
R 
R 
V 
SDM 
810 AE 120 
540 AE 140 
No 
No 
V 
C 
R 
T 
S 
SDM 
820 AE 170 
!1000 
++ 
No 
R 
G 
RD2 
!1000 
190 AE 40 
No 
No 
K 
R 
R 
N 
RD2 
!1000 
300 AE 10 
No 
No 
V 
K 
R 
R 
C 
RD1 
!1000 
440 AE 80 
No 
No 
V 
C 
R 
R 
T 
L 
RD2 
!1000 
500 AE 100 
No 
No 
L 
K 
R 
R 
M 
RD2 
!1000 
!1000 
No 
No 
L 
F 
R 
R 
K 
RD2 
!1000 
!1000 
No 
No 
L 
K 
F 
R 
R 
F 
RD1 
!1000 
!1000 
No 
No 
I 
C 
I 
R 
W 
R 
T 
I </p>

<p>The designation and source of each I-PpoI variant protein are listed in the first two columns. Positive (H98A) and negative (L116A) control proteins 
are listed in the first two rows for comparison. Binding affinities for native and +6C/-6G target site DNAs, determined by gel shift assay, are given 
in columns 3 and 4 and are arranged in order of decreasing affinity for the native I-PpoI target site. The ability of each I-PpoI variant to cleave 
native or +6C/-6G target site DNA was determined after reverting the catalytically inactivating H98A substitution that was required to establish the 
yeast one-hybrid assay. The final columns detail amino acid substitutions at nine positions in the DNA-protein interface. A blank box indicates 
presence of the native residue (shown top in single letter code). Key: CR, contacting residue library; RD1, RD2, rationally designed protein variant 
libraries RD1 and RD2; SDM, site-directed mutagenesis. Note: This Table has been reformatted in Supplementary table 2 to show variants 
rank-ordered on the basis of increasing number of residue substitutions at nine positions in the DNA-protein interface. </p>

<p>Table 1. Residue substitutions and library statistics for three I-PpoI 
yeast one hybrid libraries and screens </p>

<p>Residue 
I-Ppol variant library </p>

<p>CR 
RD1 
RD2 </p>

<p>A55 
A,G,V,L,I 
A,G,V,L 
N57 
All 
N,C 
Y,E,D,R,K,Q,N,C 
R61 
All 
Y,E,D,R,K,Q,N,C 
W62 
W,F,L,I,Y 
F,W 
Q63 
All 
Y,E,D,R,K,Q,N R 
Y64 
Y,F,S,T,W 
K65 
All 
K,R 
Y,E,D,R,K,Q,N,C 
R74 
All 
R,T 
Y,E,D,R,K,Q,N,C 
G76 
A,G,V,L,I 
Maximum 
complexity </p>

<p>3.2 Â 10 
6 3.5 Â 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>3.2 Â 10 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Library size 
1.6 Â 10 
5 1.8 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>1.4 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>Colonies 
His-screened </p>

<p>2 Â 10 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>2.5 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>2.1 Â 10 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>His+lacZ+ 
plasmids recovered </p>

<p>1 
6 
9 </p>

<p>The nine I-PpoI amino acid residues targeted for substitution during 
library constructions are indicated in the left column, together with 
substitutions made at each residue in the contacting residue (CR) or 
two rationally designed (RD1 and RD2) protein variant libraries. 
Maximum complexity is the predicted complexity of the library. 
Library size is the experimental complexity of the library, determined 
from the number of independent colonies that contained inact open 
reading frames. </p>



<p>among eight amino acid residues commonly found in 
homing endonuclease DNA-protein interfaces (Y, E, D, 
R, K, Q, N, C; Table 1, RD2) and (iv) inclusion of a 9 bp 
post-C-terminal 'molecular bar code' to allow different 
RD2 plasmid molecules to be identified and distinguished. 
The RD2 library had a predicted maximum complexity of 
3.2 Â 10 
4 . Sequencing indicated that 67% of RD2 library 
plasmids had intact Ppo-AD open reading frames. Thus 
the completed RD2 library of 1.4 Â 10 
5 members was 
sufficiently large to include all designed RD2 variants. 
Thirty-five RD2 plasmids displayed in vivo activity 
against +6C/-6G reporter genes. These plasmids encoded 
nine different Ppo-AD proteins: seven Ppo-AD variants 
were unique to the RD2 library (variants G, H, J, K, L, M 
and N), whereas two variants had been previously 
identified in RD1 (variants D and E; Table 2). Ppo-AD 
variants D, H, K and L were independently isolated, from 
3 to 6 times each from RD2, as indicated by plasmid 
molecular bar code sequences. In addition to these library 
variants, we constructed nine I-PpoI variants (variants P 
to Y, Table 2) by site-directed mutagenesis. This was done 
to determine the contribution of specific amino acid 
residues identified in the CR, RD1 and RD2 libraries to 
target site binding and cleavage. We reasoned that specific 
residue substitutions in library isolates might promote or 
interfere with site binding and cleavage, and thus wanted 
to assay individual substitutions in defined sequence 
contexts. These site-directed mutants were generated, in 
consequence, in either the native or variant A or C I-PpoI 
sequence contexts. </p>

<p>Biochemical characterization of I-PpoI variant proteins </p>

<p>In order to characterize the site-binding properties of 
Ppo-AD variants, we expressed and purified variant 
proteins from E. coli and then determined their dissocia-
tion constants (K d 's) on native and on +6C/-6G target 
site DNAs. We also determined the ability of selected 
variants to induce reporter gene expression in vivo to allow 
a comparison of in vitro and in vivo site-binding properties 
(Figure 3). The I-PpoI portion of each Ppo-AD fusion 
protein was subcloned into a pET11c expression vector 
containing an N-terminal six-histidine tag to facilitate 
purification. In order to assay site cleavage as well as 
binding by specific variant proteins, we used site-directed 
mutagenesis to revert the catalytically inactivating H98A 
substitution required to establish our Y1H assay. 
Dissociation constants for variant proteins were deter-
mined by electrophoretic gel mobility shift analysis using 
+6C/À6G and native target site DNAs. Fourteen of 22 
variants displayed a higher affinity for +6C/À6G homing 
site DNA than did native I-PpoI, although this site-
binding preference was modest (typically &lt;5-fold; 
Table 2). Seven of the remaining variants displayed no 
site-binding preference. One variant, T, displayed high 
binding affinity for both the native and +6C/À6G target 
sites and a 175-fold higher affinity for native target site 
DNA (Table 2). We also determined the binding affinity of 
native I-PpoI and four variant proteins on target site 
DNAs with base-pair substitutions at the AE6 position, the 
AE7 position and in one instance AE6/AE7 position </p>

<p>substitutions. The variants had amino acid substitutions 
at position 63 contacting the AE6 bp; at residue 74 
contacting the AE7 bp; and at residues 55, 57 and 65 in 
adjacent regions of the DNA-protein interface. None of 
these variant proteins bound any mutant target site DNA 
with high site affinity or specificity (Table 2, and 
Supplementary Table 2). 
Seven of 22 variant I-PpoI proteins cleaved native 
homing site DNA in vitro. Cleavage activity was 
determined on linear plasmid substrates that contained a 
single I-PpoI target site. Both native I-PpoI and variant T 
bound and cleaved native target site DNA, though did not 
cleave +6C/-6G target site DNA in the presence of Mg </p>

<p>2+ </p>

<p>or Mn 
2+ (Figure 3A; data not shown). Other variant 
proteins with activity cleaved only native target site DNA 
(variants E, P, Q, S, U and Y; Table 2, Figure 3A). 
In order to better understand the relationship between 
biochemical properties and in vivo activity of variant 
proteins, we quantified the ability of six variants to induce 
a lacZ reporter gene in budding yeast. Variants A, C, E, 
G, J and T were chosen for analysis as they represent a 
range of in vitro binding affinities. Expression plasmids for 
each variant as a Ppo-AD fusion were transformed into 
yeast containing a native or +6C/-6G target site LacZ 
reporter gene plasmid. b-Galactosidase activity was 
quantified for three independent colonies grown in liquid 
media and assayed on the same day. Protein variants C, G 
and J had higher activity on +6C/-6G than on native 
target site reporters. This paralleled the 1.8-to-5.3-fold 
higher binding affinity of these variant proteins for +6C/-
6G sites (Table 2 and Figure 3B). A graphical summary of 
in vitro site binding and site cleavage analyses, for all 
variants, is shown in Figure 3 (panels C and D). </p>

<p>Computational modeling and analysis of I-PpoI protein 
variants </p>

<p>Structural modeling of base pair and residue substitutions 
in the I-PpoI DNA-protein interface was used to gain 
mechanistic insight into the properties of several I-PpoI 
variant proteins. When I-PpoI is bound to native target 
site DNA, Q63 makes an energetically favorable, gluta-
mine:adenine contact with two hydrogen bonds to adenine 
6. R74 makes a canonical contact with guanine 7. K65 
makes an H-bond contact to guanine 9, whereas R61 
makes a series of backbone contacts between base pairs 
3 and 4 (Figure 1A). Modeling indicates the +6C/-6G 
base-pair substitution inhibits site binding and cleavage by 
disrupting the glutamine:adenine 6 contact, and by forcing 
the Q63 residue to rotate 1358 into and in part disrupt the 
adjacent R74:guanine 7 bp contact (Figure 4A and B). 
Several residue substitutions found in variant G could 
in part restore mutant +6C/-6G target site binding. These 
were Q63R at the +6C/-6G base-pair-contacting position 
(present in 17 variants) K65R (present in 17 variants) 
and R61K (present in 4 variants; Table 2 and Figure 4, 
compare panels B and C). Modeling indicates that Q63R 
substitutions can in part restore mutant site-binding 
affinity by making a new contact at base-pair position 5, 
and by restoring an R74:guanine 7 canonical base-pair 
contact (Figure 4C). Modeling also provides an </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 17 5845 </p>

<p>explanation for why selected variants with Q63R sub-
stitutions, e.g. variant E, show preferential binding of the 
mutant +6C/À6G target site: when R63 packs in the 
native DNA interface, it leaves a small cavity adjacent to 
the native AE6 A/T base pairs. This cavity is partially filled 
by the cytosine in the +6C/-6G substrate (Figures 1A and 
4B; data not shown). These results indicate that the native 
contacting residue, Q63, acts as a gatekeeper at the 
AE6 A:T base pair by controlling contacts at this and 
adjacent base-pair positions. 
Variant T, which contains a K65R substitution, showed 
a marked increase in binding affinity for both native and 
+6C/-6C target sites. Modeling of this substitution </p>

<p>revealed that K65 forms a single H-bond to the guanine 
base at base pair 9, whereas K65R substitution make two 
H-bonds to base pairs at positions 8 and 9 (compare 
Figure 4 panels B and C). These contacts are energetically 
more favorable than the single contact made by the native 
K65 residue (À1.22 units for R65 versus À1.09 units for 
K65; <rs type="software">RosettaDesign</rs> analyses not shown). Neither K nor 
R65 residues contact target site position 6, and thus do not 
discriminate between native or mutant +6C/-6G target 
site DNAs. 
R61K substitutions decrease the DNA-binding affinity 
of I-PpoI, while increasing target site selectivity to favor 
the binding of mutant, +6C/-6G target site DNA </p>

<p>Figure 3. Target site cleavage and site binding by I-PpoI variant proteins. (A) In vitro cleavage of native and +6C/-6G target site DNAs by native 
and 8 variant I-PpoI proteins. Plasmid DNA (10 nM) containing a native (WT, top panel) or +6C/-6G variant (bottom panel) target site was cut 
with XmnI to generate a 3 kb linear DNA substrate ('uncut') that was cleaved with 0.1 mM native (WT lanes) or variant I-PpoI protein (rightmost 8 
lanes, Y to C) for 30 min at 378C. I-PpoI target site-specific cleavage generated 2 and 1 kb product fragments ('cut'). M = 1 kb DNA size marker 
(New England Biolabs). Controls include plasmid cleaved with XmnI alone (-lanes) or plasmid cleaved with XmnI, and with AflII that cleaves the 
central 6 bp of the I-PpoI target site (+ lanes). (B) In vivo yeast one-hybrid reporter gene activity of selected I-PpoI protein variants. LacZ reporter 
gene activity was determined by expressing specific proteins in yeast in the presence of native (site W) or +6C/-6G (site 6) I-PpoI target site reporter 
plasmids, then measuring b-galactosidase activity in permeabilized cells using ONPG as a substrate. Proteins included as controls were H98A Ppo-
AD (98A; positive control) and L116A (116A; negative control). Variant T was assayed independently of the other five variants shown, and thus is 
displayed with a simultaneously performed H98A control (rightmost 4 bars). All activities represent the mean AE SD of three independent colonies 
grown and assayed on the same day. (C and D) Graphical summary of I-PpoI variant protein site binding and cleavage properties. Site-binding 
affinities (nM) for native (X axis) or +6C/-6G (Y axis) target site DNAs. Variant proteins with partial or full cleavage activity on native homing site 
DNA are indicated, respectively, by circled X's or filled circles. Only one I-PpoI variant protein, T, had any detectable cleavage activity on +6C/-6G 
target site DNA. The identities of the variants in the dashed line box in the upper right of panel C are shown in expanded panel D. </p>



<p>(compare, e.g. variants E and G, Table 2). Modeling 
indicates that the R61K substitution modifies back-
bone contacts in the native interface between base pair 
positions 3 and 4 (Figure 4, compare panels B and C). 
These backbone positions are immediately adjacent to 
the scissile phosphate, and form part of the most 
deformed region of the I-PpoI:DNA substrate complex 
(21). The selectivity of K61 variants for mutant target 
site DNA is likely explained by sequence-dependent 
conformation changes in the DNA-protein interface, 
as no new contacts are established with mutant target 
site DNA. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>We used a yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) assay to isolate and 
characterize variants of the I-PpoI homing endonuclease 
with altered DNA target recognition specificity. Variants 
were isolated using a mutant binding site target with 
symmetrical AE6 bp position substitutions that abolished 
site binding and cleavage by native I-PpoI. We reasoned 
that amino acid substitutions in the DNA-protein inter-
face adjacent to this target site position, at contacting 
residue 63 alone or in conjunction with other sub-
stitutions, might restore high site-binding affinity and </p>

<p>Figure 4. Molecular modeling of I-PpoI variant protein on native and mutant target site DNAs. The native AE6A/T base pair is shown in yellow, 
while the mutant AE6C/G base pair is shown in purple. Amino acid geometries pictured with the mutant target site were modeled using 
RosettaDesign. Relevant sequence-specific hydrogen bonds are shown as black dotted lines. (A) Geometry of position 6 contacting residue Q63 on 
native A:T and mutant C:G target sites. The mutant À6C base (purple) forces Q63 to rotate 1358 to alleviate a stearic clash (shown as crossed arc 
lines). (B) Rotation of Q63 forced by the AE6C/G base-pair substitution disrupts the canonical R74:guanine contacts made at adjacent base-pair 
position 7. (C) Stereo representation of I-PpoI variant G modeled with the AE6C/G mutant DNA target. R63 interacts with AE5G, and allows R74 to 
again contact base pair position 7. R65 makes two H-bonds to target site base-pairs 8 and 9, which increases the overall affinity of I-PpoI for native 
and mutant DNA target sites. R61K substitutions alter DNA backbone contacts near the scissile phosphate between base pairs 2 and 3 (compare 
panel C with B or Figure 1A). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 17 5847 </p>

<p>specificity in vivo. This strategy resembles Y1H screens 
that have been used to identify and characterize site-
specific DNA-binding proteins from yeast and other 
organisms. One similar precedent reported for homing 
endonucleases was the use of a bacterial two-hybrid screen 
to explore the recognition specificity of the LAGLIDADG 
homing endonuclease PI-SceI (37). 
The variant I-PpoI proteins we generated contained 
from 1 to 8 amino acid substitutions in the DNA-protein 
interface (Tables 1 and 2). Most variants had low site-
binding affinities (100-1000 nM K d 's), and a modest (2-
to-10-fold) preference to bind native or mutant target 
site DNA. One exception, variant T with only a K65R 
substitution, had high binding affinities for native and 
mutant target site DNAs that included a clear (&lt;175-fold) 
preference for native site binding. Cleavage competence 
was assayed by reverting the catalytically inactivating 
H98A substitution required to establish the Y1H screen, 
and then assaying proteins for the ability to cleave native 
or mutant target site DNAs. We found little correlation 
among site binding, discrimination and cleavage proper-
ties of individual variant proteins (Table 2 and Figure 3, 
panels C and D). One likely explanation for this is that I-
PpoI must bind and bend substrate DNA in order to 
generate a productive substrate complex (21,22,26). Our 
hypothesis is that active variants (e.g. variants U, S or P, 
Figure 3A and Table 2) retain the ability to both bind and 
bend site DNA to permit cleavage. 
Structure-based molecular modeling of I-PpoI variant 
proteins on both native and mutant target site DNAs 
was used to gain insight into the contribution of specific 
residue substitutions to the biochemical behavior of 
variant proteins. Modeling revealed that Q63R substitu-
tions fail to confer AE6 mutant target site specificity by 
virtue of loss of a canonical glutamine:adenine contact at 
position 6, together with partial disruption of a canonical 
arginine:guanine contact at the adjacent base pair position 
7. Q63R variants were nonetheless able to discriminate in 
favor of mutant +6C/-6G target sites by packing more 
favorably with mutant 6C than with the native 6A target 
site base, while making a high quality contact at the 
adjacent position 5 base pair (Figure 4). K65R substitu-
tions, in contrast, increase affinity for native and AE6 
mutant target sites by making an additional H-bond to 
bridge base pair positions 8 and 9 [Figures 1 and 4 (panels 
B and C)]. 
R61K substitutions, in contrast, appear to alter site 
binding by modifying DNA backbone contacts immedi-
ately adjacent to the scissile phosphate located between 
base pairs 2 and 3 [(21); Figure 4]. This type of indirect 
readout may be strongly influenced by local, sequence-
dependent DNA conformation (38,39). These sequence-
dependent effects may be further amplified by DNA 
substrate deformation in this region of the I-PpoI 
substrate complex, and thus interfere with correct position-
ing of the scissile phosphate (Figures 1 and 4) (21,26). 
The Y1H screening assay we used employed the 
canonical two-hybrid reporters HIS3 and lacZ that, 
respectively, confer a growth advantage or have readily 
detectable activity at low expression levels. The sensitivity 
of these reporters, in retrospect, permitted the </p>

<p>identification of I-PpoI variants with modest in vivo 
activity and site-binding affinity (Table 2 and Figure 3). 
One explanation for the failure to recover I-PpoI variants 
with high affinity and specificity for +6C/-6G mutant 
target site DNA is that they were not present in our 
starting libraries. This may be the case for the initial 
randomized contacting residue (CR) library, which was 
too large to be exhaustively screened. The smaller 
rationally designed libraries (RD1 and RD2), in contrast, 
were exhaustively screened but may have been too small to 
encode a high affinity binding variant. 
The experimental and computational analyses described 
above indicate one productive approach to alter the 
DNA recognition specificity of I-PpoI and other homing 
endonuclease proteins. Computational DNA-protein 
interface design can be used to predict different residue 
substitutions that may confer high binding affinity and 
specificity for a mutant target site DNA. The resulting 
protein variants can then be rank-ordered on the basis of 
predicted DNA-binding energies, and further evaluated 
for structural quality by molecular modeling. This general 
approach has already been shown to work for single base-
pair positions in I-MsoI, a member of the LAGLIDADG 
homing endonuclease family (40), and should be 
applicable to His-Cys box proteins such as I-PpoI. 
A prerequisite for this engineering approach is a high 
resolution co-crystal structure. 
In addition to protein computational design, it should 
also be possible to improve the experimental selection or 
screening assays to identify variant proteins with high 
site-binding affinity and specificity. For example, the Y1H 
assay could be adapted to use reporter genes or selections 
that would require comparatively high levels of expression 
to identify active variants. Alternatively, a combination of 
positive and negative selection could be used to recover 
variants with high site-binding affinity and specificity (41). 
Homing endonucleases remain the most attractive 
starting point for the generation of new, highly 
sequence-specific proteins for biology and medicine. 
They encode a wide range of different DNA recognition 
specificities, and display high site-binding specificity that is 
tightly linked to DNA cleavage. Homing endonucleases 
including I-PpoI have already been successfully expressed 
in human cells. They cleave their target sites with high site 
specificity (19,42-44), and thus are being used to promote 
site-specific recombination (45) and high resolution DNA 
double-strand break repair analyses (20). The precedents 
outlined above indicate that it should be possible in the 
near future to generate many highly sequence-specific 
homing endonuclease variants useful for genome engi-
neering, disease therapy or disease prevention. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Mike Moser, Meggen S. Chadsey and Alden 
Hackmann for help, respectively, with experimental </p>



<p>design, library construction and graphics support. Stan 
Fields and his laboratory provided generous help in 
establishing the yeast one-hybrid assay, and Barry L. 
Stoddard for I-PpoI structure determinations, initial 
structural modeling and continuous discussion. U.S. 
National Institutes of Health RO1 and T32 funding 
(RO1 CA88942 to R.J.M., Jr; T32 GM07735 to J.L.E. 
T32 GM07270 to J.E. and T32 GM007266 and T32 
CA077116 to U. U.). U. U. is also the recipient of a 
Poncin Fund Award. Funding to pay the Open Access 
publication charges for this article was provided by the 
U.S. National Institutes of Health. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2007, Vol. 35, No. 17 5849 </p>





</text></tei>