<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2804221" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-07T23:34+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>GLP-1 (glucagon-like peptide-1) is an incretin released from 
intestinal L-cells in response to food intake. Activation of the 
GLP-1 receptor potentiates the synthesis and release of insulin 
from pancreatic ␤-cells in a glucose-dependent manner. The 
GLP-1 receptor belongs to class B of the G-protein-coupled recep-
tors, a subfamily characterized by a large N-terminal extracellular 
ligand binding domain. Exendin-4 and GLP-1 are 50% identical, 
and exendin-4 is a full agonist with similar affinity and potency for 
the GLP-1 receptor. We recently solved the crystal structure of the 
GLP-1 receptor extracellular domain in complex with the compet-
itive antagonist exendin-4(9 -39). Interestingly, the isolated extra-
cellular domain binds exendin-4 with much higher affinity than the 
endogenous agonist GLP-1. Here, we have solved the crystal struc-
ture of the extracellular domain in complex with GLP-1 to 2.1 Å 
resolution. The structure shows that important hydrophobic 
ligand-receptor interactions are conserved in agonist-and antago-
nist-bound forms of the extracellular domain, but certain residues 
in the ligand-binding site adopt a GLP-1-specific conformation. 
GLP-1 is a kinked but continuous ␣-helix from Thr 
13 to Val 
33 when 
bound to the extracellular domain. We supplemented the crystal 
structure with site-directed mutagenesis to link the structural 
information of the isolated extracellular domain with the bind-
ing properties of the full-length receptor. The data support the 
existence of differences in the binding modes of GLP-1 and 
exendin-4 on the full-length GLP-1 receptor. </p>

<p>formation, and the C-terminal part of the ligands binds the 
ECD in agreement with the two-domain binding mechanism. 
Several receptor models have been proposed for full-length 
class B receptors (20 -23). However, the orientation of the ECD 
relative to the TM domain is uncertain. 
Exendin-4 is a 39-amino acid peptide, which was originally 
isolated from the venom of the lizard Heloderma suspectum 
(24). GLP-1 and exendin-4 are 50% identical, and exendin-4 is a 
full agonist with similar affinity and potency for the full-length 
GLP-1R (25). However, structure-activity studies have demon-
strated interesting differences between the binding modes of 
GLP-1 and exendin-4. 1) The isolated ECD binds exendin-4 
with high affinity (IC 50 of 6 nM) and GLP-1 with low affinity 
(IC 50 Ͼ500 nM) (26, 27). 2) GLP-1 binding is more sensitive to 
site-directed mutagenesis of the TM domain compared with 
exendin-4 binding (28 -30). 3) GLP-1 is much more sensitive to 
N-terminal truncation than exendin-4 (31). N-terminally trun-
cated exendin-4 variants maintain high affinity but are unable 
to activate GLP-1R, i.e. competitive antagonist, whereas N-ter-
minal truncation of GLP-1 severely affects both binding and 
activation (31). Clearly, the interaction between the N-terminal 
part of GLP-1 and the TM domain is critical for binding and 
activation of GLP-1R. 
Exendin-4(9 -39) is a truncated form of exendin-4, and a 
competitive antagonist that maintains high affinity for GLP-1R 
through interactions with the ECD (IC 50 value of 6 nM for the 
isolated ECD) (27, 32). We recently solved the crystal structure 
of the GLP-1R ECD in complex with exendin-4(9 -39) (18). 
Exendin-4(9 -39) is ␣-helical in the ECD-bound conformation 
except for the C-terminal segment, the so-called Trp cage (33,  34). In solution, the helical propensity of exendin-4 is higher 
than that of GLP-1 (27, 33). Biophysical studies showed a pos-
itive correlation between ␣-helical propensity in solution and 
affinity for the GLP-1R ECD (27). Moreover, charged residues 
of exendin-4 interact with the ECD in a manner not possible for 
GLP-1 (18). Hence, the high affinity of exendin-4 for the ECD 
may be a combination of high helical propensity in solution and 
unique receptor interactions. 
Here, we report the crystal structure of the GLP-1R ECD in 
complex with its endogenous agonist GLP-1. We supple-
mented the crystal structure with site-directed mutagenesis to 
link the structural information of the isolated ECD with the 
binding properties of the full-length receptor. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Protein and Peptide Preparation-The GLP-1R ECD was 
prepared as described previously (27). Briefly, N-terminal His 6 -
tagged ECD was expressed in Escherichia coli inclusion bodies, 
isolated as inclusion body protein, solubilized in guanidine-HCl 
and dithiothreitol, dialyzed against guanidine-HCl to remove 
the dithiothreitol, and refolded using L-Arg and a 1:5 molar 
ratio of reduced and oxidized glutathione. The refolded ECD 
was purified by hydrophobic interaction chromatography and 
size exclusion chromatography in 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5, 0.1 
M Na 2 SO 4 , 2% glycerol. The His 6 tag was removed by thrombin 
cleavage. The purified GLP-1R ECD consisted of four amino 
acids, Gly-Ser-His-Met, of the linker attached to the N-termi-
nus of ECD (Arg 
24 -Tyr 
145 ), M r ϭ 14,723 g/mol after removal of </p>

<p>the His 6 tag. Native GLP-1(7-37)-OH was synthesized as 
described previously (12). 
Purification and Crystallization of the GLP-1-bound Extra-
cellular Domain-The purified GLP-1R ECD was concentrated 
to 1.2 mg/ml, mixed with 3-fold molar excess of GLP-1(7-37) 
(dissolved in 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.5), and incubated overnight 
at 4°C. The GLP-1-bound ECD was purified by size exclusion 
chromatography on a Superdex 75 column in 10 mM Tris-HCl, 
pH 7.5, at a flow rate of 0.3 ml/min and characterized by SDS-
PAGE (supplemental Fig. S1). The complex was concentrated 
to 4 mg/ml and crystallized by hanging drop vapor diffusion. 
The crystallization conditions were initially identified using the 
Crystal Screen from Hampton Research and subsequently opti-
mized to 0.1 M N(2-acetamido)iminodiacetic acid, pH 6.9, 14 
volume % (Ϯ)-2-methyl-2,4-pentanediol and 9 mM n-decyl-␤-
D-thiomaltoside. Single crystals were flashed cooled in liquid N 2 
using 30% glycerol in the cryo solution. 
Data Collection and Structure Determination-Diffraction 
data were collected from a single crystal using beamline 1911-3 
at MAX-lab (Lund, Sweden). The data were integrated and 
scaled using XDS (35). The crystals belonged to space group 
P2 1 22 1 with the unit cell dimensions a ϭ 35.7 Å, b ϭ 42.7 Å, and 
c ϭ 95.1 Å. The phases and electron density map were obtained 
by molecular replacement using Phaser running in the CCP4 
program interface with one complex in the asymmetric unit. 
Refinement was done using COOT (36) and REFMAC5 (37). 
Well defined electron density was obtained for GLP-1 residues 
Thr 
11 *-Val 
33 * and for ECD residues Val 
30 -Glu 
128 . Poor den-
sity was observed for GLP-1 residues Gly </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>*, Lys 
34 *, and Gly 
35 * 
and ECD residues Thr 
29 and Asn 
115 . No electron density was 
observed for His 
7 *-Glu 
9 * and Arg 
36 *-Gly 
37 * of GLP-1. Our 
final structure contains GLP-1 residues Gly 
10 *-Gly 
35 * and ECD 
residues Thr 
29 -Glu 
128 , but it should be noted that the confor-
mation of Lys 
34 * of GLP-1 is very uncertain, and because of the 
poor density we have chosen to show Asn 
115 as Gly. The final 
GLP-1-bound ECD structure has 116 residues in preferred 
regions, 5 in allowed regions and only 1 outlier (Glu 
68 in the 
␤-turn between ␤ 1 and ␤ 2 shown in Fig. 1A) in the Ramachan-
dran plot. The structure containing 73 water molecules and a 
detergent molecule (n-decyl-␤-D-thiomaltoside) has a working 
R-factor of 0.181% and a free R-factor of 0.226%. Data collection 
and refinement statistics are summarized in Table 1. Coordi-
nates and structure factors are deposited in the Protein Data 
Bank under accession code 3IOL. Molecular graphics were pre-
pared in PyMOL (46). 
Receptor Constructs-The cDNA encoding the human GLP-
1R was originally obtained from Dr. B. Thorens (9) and sub-
cloned into the mammalian expression vector pcDNA3.1/ 
v5-His-TOPO (Invitrogen). The presence of the C-terminal 
His 6 tag was previously shown not to influence the functional 
response of the receptor (12). Site-directed mutagenesis of 
GLP-1R was done using QuikChange 
TM (Stratagene). Plasmid 
DNA was generated using the NucleoBond Xtra Maxi Plus kit 
(Macherey-Nagel), and the desired mutations were confirmed 
by dideoxynucleotide sequencing. 
Cell Culture and Receptor Expression-Human embryonic 
kidney (HEK) 293 cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified 
Eagle's medium (BioWhittaker) supplemented with 10 volume </p>

<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 • JANUARY 1, 2010 </p>

<p>% fetal bovine serum and 1 volume % penicillin/streptomycin 
(100 units/ml) in T175 flasks. HEK293 cells were transiently 
transfected with 21 g of GLP-1R DNA using the FuGENE </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>transfection reagent (Roche Applied Science), harvested 
24 h after transfection, and used directly in functional exper-
iments or plasma membrane preparations as described pre-
viously (12). 
Functional Assay-Transiently transfected HEK293 cells 
expressing wild-type GLP-1R or mutant receptors were har-
vested and resuspended in assay buffer (Flashplate, 
PerkinElmer Life Sciences) to a cell density of 2.4 ϫ 10 
6 cells/ 
ml. GLP-1(7-37)-acid and exendin-4 were diluted in phos-
phate-buffered saline with 0.02 volume % Tween 20. Cells in 
assay buffer (50 l) and GLP-1 or exendin-4 (50 l) were mixed 
in 96-well FlashPlates (PerkinElmer Life Sciences), gently agi-
tated for 5 min, and incubated for 25 min at room temperature. 
The resulting intracellular level of cAMP was measured accord-
ing to supplier's manual and analyzed by nonlinear regression/ 
sigmoidal dose-response fitting using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs>.). </p>

<p>Receptor Binding Assay-Freshly 
thawed plasma membrane prepara-
tions from transiently transfected 
HEK293 cells expressing GLP-1R 
(20 g protein/well) were pulled 
through a 25-gauge needle three 
times and diluted in assay buffer (50 
mM HEPES, 5 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM 
EGTA, 0.005 volume % Tween 20, 
pH 7.4). GLP-1 and exendin-4 were 
diluted in assay buffer. The concen-
tration range was 1 pM to 100 nM 
for GLP-1 and exendin-4. 
125 I-GLP-
1(7-36)-amide (2.2 Ci/mol) was 
dissolved in assay buffer and added 
at 50,000 cpm per well to a final 
concentration of 50 pM. Nonspe-
cific binding was determined with 
1 M GLP-1. Membrane prepara-
tion and radioligand were mixed in 
96-well 0.65-m filter plates (Milli-
pore) with either diluted GLP-1 or 
exendin-4 and incubated for 1 h at 
37°C. Subsequently, bound and 
unbound radioligands were sepa-
rated by vacuum filtration (Milli-
pore vacuum manifold). The filters 
were washed twice in 100 l of cold 
assay buffer and left to dry. Data 
were analyzed by nonlinear regres-
sion, and the expression level (B max ) 
was calculated using <rs id="software-1" type="software">Prism</rs> <rs corresp="#software-1" type="version-number">5.0</rs> 
(<rs corresp="#software-1" type="creator">GraphPad Software, Inc</rs>.). </p>

<p>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Purification, Crystallization, and 
Structure Determination-The GLP-
1R ECD was expressed in E. coli 
inclusion bodies, refolded, and purified as described previously 
(27). A complex of GLP-1 and the ECD was purified by size 
exclusion chromatography (supplemental Fig. S1). The purified 
complex was characterized by SDS-PAGE (supplemental Fig. 
S1), concentrated, and crystallized by hanging drop vapor dif-
fusion. Diffraction data were collected from a single crystal 
using the beamline 1911-3 at MAX-lab (Lund, Sweden), and 
the structure of GLP-1 in complex with the GLP-1R ECD was 
solved to 2.1 Å resolution by molecular replacement (Fig. 
1A). We removed exendin-4(9 -39) from the structure of the 
exendin-4(9 -39)-ECD complex (Protein Data Bank code 
3C59) and used the apo-form of GLP-1R ECD as the search 
model for the molecular replacement. GLP-1 was then built 
into the model; its position was unambiguous due to good elec-
tron density for most of the ligand. Data collection and refine-
ment statistics are summarized in Table 1. Throughout the text, 
GLP-1 and exendin-4 residues are designated with * and **, 
respectively. Exendin-4 is numbered 1-39 and GLP-1 is num-
bered 7-37, due to post-translational processing. The aligned 
sequences are illustrated in Fig. 1B. </p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Structure of the GLP-1-bound ECD of the GLP-1R. A, stereoview of GLP-1 (blue) bound to the ECD 
of the GLP-1R (␣-helix in black, ␤-strands in red, and loops in gray). Disulfide bridges are shown as orange sticks. 
Residues Cys 
62 -Asp 
67 (␤ 1 ) and Ala 
70 -Gly 
75 (␤ 2 ) constitute the first region of antiparallel ␤-sheets, and the 
second region is comprised of residues Gly 
78 -Ser 
84 (␤ 3 ) and His 
99 -Thr 
105 (␤ 4 ), which is shown in red. Our final 
structure contains GLP-1 residues Gly 
10 *-Gly 
35 *. The residues that interact with GLP-1R ECD lie within Ala 
24 * 
and Val 
33 *, which are shown as sticks. B, sequence alignment of GLP-1, exendin-4, GIP, GLP-2, glucagon, and 
PACAP(1-27). Fully conserved residues are highlighted in yellow, and partially conserved residues are high-
lighted in green. The residues of GLP-1 and exendin-4 that interact with GLP-1R ECD are colored blue. The 
underlined residues symbolize residues of GLP-1 in ␣-helical conformation when bound to the ECD. Residue 
number 1 of exendin-4 corresponds to residue number 7 of GLP-1. </p>

<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>

<p>JANUARY 1, 2010 • VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 725 </p>

<p>Structure of the GLP-1R Extracellular Domain-The crystal 
structure of the ECD in the GLP-1-bound form shown here is 
very similar to the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound form shown previ-
ously (root mean square deviation of 0.79 Å for C 
␣ atoms of the 
ECD) (18). The ligand-binding sites are identical, which is not 
surprising given the competitive binding of GLP-1 and 
exendin-4 for the full-length GLP-1R as well as the isolated 
ECD (27). However, we have previously shown that divergent 
residues in the two ligands are responsible for their different 
physical properties in solution and their different affinity for 
the ECD (27). As described below, these divergent residues give 
rise to structural differences in the two ligand-bound forms of 
the ECD at the level of specific side chain conformations. </p>

<p>Structure of GLP-1 and Its Interactions with the Extracellular 
Domain of GLP-1R-GLP-1 is a continuous ␣-helix from 
Thr 
13 * to Val 
33 *, with a kink around Gly 
22 *. The residues 
between Ala 
24 * and Val 
33 * interact with the ECD (Fig. 1, A and 
B). The amphiphilic nature of this ␣-helical segment enables 
hydrophilic and hydrophobic interactions through opposite 
faces of the ␣-helix. The hydrophilic face is comprised by resi-
dues Gln 
23 *, Lys 
26 *, Glu 
27 *, and Lys 
34 *. Lys 
26 * is the only one of 
these that may interact directly with the ECD (Fig. 2A). The side 
chain of Lys 
26 * may form a hydrogen bond with the side chain of 
Glu 
128 (ϳ3.0 Å), but the B-factor is rather high for both residues 
(ϳ25 compared with 10 for well defined residues), suggesting 
that this is not a strong interaction. In particular, the electron 
density of the Lys 
26 * side chain is rather weak. In exendin-4(9 -
39), the amphiphilic character is more pronounced, and the 
␣-helical conformation is further stabilized by intramolecular 
interactions between Glu 
16 **, Glu 
17 **, Arg 
20 **, Glu 
24 **, and 
Lys 
27 ** on the hydrophilic face (18). In addition, Arg 
20 ** and 
Lys 
27 ** interact with Glu 
128 and Glu 
127 of the ECD, respectively 
(18). The corresponding intramolecular stabilization is not pos-
sible in GLP-1 due to a less favorable alignment of oppositely 
charged residues (Fig. 1B), and Glu 
127 of the ECD is not 
involved in binding of GLP-1 (Fig. 2A). 
The hydrophobic face of GLP-1, which interacts with the 
ECD, is defined by Ala 
24 *, Ala 
25 *, Phe 
28 *, Ile 
29 *, Leu 
32 *, and 
Val 
33 * (Fig. 2B). The importance of Phe 
28 *, Ile </p>

<p>29 </p>

<p>*, and Leu 
32 * in 
GLP-1 binding has been demonstrated previously by Ala scan-
ning of GLP-1 (38). Substitution of Phe 
28 * with Ala had the 
most severe effect on GLP-1 affinity in the Ala scan (IC 50 value 
increased by 1300-fold), and indeed Phe 
28 * is centrally posi-
tioned in the ligand-receptor interface emphasizing the impor-
tance of this hydrophobic ligand-receptor interaction. The 
I29*A and L32*A substitutions also reduced GLP-1 affinity sig-
nificantly (IC 50 value increased by 93-and 17-fold, respectively) 
(38). Trp 
31 * is also on the hydrophobic face of GLP-1 but is 
rather solvent-exposed and does not interact with the ECD 
(Fig. 2B). Trp 
31 * is conserved in the 
glucagon peptide family (GLP-1, 
exendin-4, glucagon, GIP, and 
GLP-2, see Fig. 1B), which implies a 
unique role of this residue. How-
ever, substitution of Trp 
31 * with Ala 
only reduced the binding affinity of 
GLP-1 slightly at the full-length 
GLP-1R (38), so the role of Trp 
31 * in 
receptor binding is unclear. 
Val 
33 * is the final residue in the 
␣-helix of GLP-1, and it is the final 
residue in the C terminus of GLP-1 
that interacts with the ECD (Fig. 2, 
A and C). The side chain of Val 
33 * 
makes hydrophobic contacts with 
Tyr 
69 and Leu 
123 , and the backbone 
carbonyl of Val 
33 * interacts through 
a hydrogen bond with one of the ter-
minal nitrogens of Arg 
121 (Fig. 2, A 
and C). The other terminal nitrogen 
of Arg 
121 interacts with a water mol-</p>

<p>FIGURE 2. Interactions between GLP-1 and GLP-1R ECD. A, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 and its hydrophilic 
interactions with GLP-1R ECD. GLP-1 is colored in cyan, and residues Gln 
23 *, Lys 
26 *, Glu 
27 *, Trp 
31 *, and Val 
33 * are 
illustrated as sticks. Receptor residues Arg 
121 , Leu 
123 , Glu 
127 , and Glu 
128 are shown as sticks. The surface of the 
hydrophilic binding cavity of ECD is illustrated in gray. B, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 and its hydrophobic inter-
actions with GLP-1R ECD. GLP-1 residues Ala 
24 *, Glu 
27 *, Phe 
28 *, Trp 
31 *, and Leu 
32 * are illustrated as sticks, and 
so are ECD residues Leu 
32 , Trp 
39 , Asp 
67 , and Arg 
121 . The surface of the hydrophobic binding cavity of ECD is 
illustrated in gray. C, ribbon diagram illustrating a common motif found in the GLP-1R ECD and in the GIP 
receptor ECD. The side chain of Arg 
121 interacts with the backbone carbonyls of Asp 
67 and Leu 
32 * through a 
water molecule. GLP-1 residues Leu 
32 * and Val 
33 * are illustrated as sticks, and so are ECD residues Asp 
67 and 
Arg 
121 . </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Data collection and refinement statistics </p>

<p>The data set was collected from a single crystal. Values in parentheses are for the 
highest resolution shell (2.2-2.1 Å). </p>

<p>Space group 
P2 1 22 1 </p>

<p>Unit cell dimensions (Å) 
A 
35.7 
B 
42.7 
C 
95.1 </p>

<p>Data collection 
Wavelength 
1.0 Å 
Resolution range 
95.1-2.1 Å (2.2-2.1 Å) 
Total reflections 
73,811 
Unique reflections 
10,348 
Completeness 
97.9% 
I/(I) 
14.0 (5.3) 
R sym 
11.1 (44.9) </p>

<p>Refinement statistics 
No. of non-hydrogen atoms 
1109 
Resolution 
95.1-2.1 Å (2.155-2.100 Å) 
Total reflections 
8786 
Reflections in test set 
429 
R work 
0.181 (0.187) 
R free 
0.226 (0.255) 
Average B-factors 
13.6 </p>

<p>Root mean square deviation 
Bond lengths 
0.02 Å 
Bond angles 
1.7°C </p>

<p>rystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 • JANUARY 1, 2010 </p>

<p>ecule, which is also coordinated by the backbone carbonyl 
groups of Asp 
67 and Leu 
32 * (Fig. 2C). A water molecule is coor-
dinated by the same residues in the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound 
ECD, and Arg 
121 interacts with the backbone carbonyl of 
Lys 
27 ** of exendin-4(9 -39) in a manner similar to the interac-
tion with Val 
33 * of GLP-1. Even though exendin-4 has a C-ter-
minal nine-residue extension, the so-called Trp cage, the extent 
of the ␣-helix is similar for GLP-1 and exendin-4, and this par-
ticular length of the ␣-helix fits nicely into the ECD binding 
pocket. 
Judging from the two ligand-bound ECD structures, the 
hydrophobic ligand-receptor interface is highly conserved, and 
the C-terminal ␣-helical structure of the ligands ends at the 
same position with a similar arrangement of receptor interac-
tions mediated by the backbone of the ligand. Hence, the dif-
ferential affinity for the ECD may best be explained by the lower 
␣-helical propensity of GLP-1 in solution and by weaker recep-
tor interactions compared with exendin-4, as suggested previ-
ously (27). 
Unique Structural Features of the GLP-1-bound Extracellu-
lar Domain-The divergent residues in GLP-1 and exendin-4 
are not only responsible for the different physical properties 
of the ligands in solution and their differential affinity for the 
GLP-1R ECD, they also influence the conformation of certain 
residues in the ECD structures. The crystal structure presented 
here suggests that one diverging residue in the two ligands 
(Val 
33 * of GLP-1 and Lys 
27 ** of exendin-4(9 -39)) causes a shift 
in the conformations of four residues in (or close to) the binding 
pocket of the ECD, namely Glu 
127 , Leu 
123 , Arg 
121 , and Pro </p>

<p>119 </p>

<p>(Fig. 3A). In exendin-4(9 -39), Lys 
27 ** interacts with Glu 
127 , 
and the positioning of the Lys 
27 ** side chain appears to be 
guided by a hydrophobic interaction with Leu 
123 . In GLP-1, 
Val 
33 * is unable to interact with Glu 
127 causing Glu 
127 to 
change rotamer conformation and point its side chain away 
from GLP-1. The side chain of Leu 
123 is flipped toward Arg 
121 , </p>

<p>which again is flipped toward 
Pro 
119 , thereby closing an otherwise 
water-accessible cavity observed in 
the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound struc-
ture (Fig. 3A). The closing of this 
cavity is assisted by a side chain flip 
of Pro 
119 toward Arg 
121 . The appar-
ent GLP-1-specific conformations 
affect the conserved core of the ECD 
by rotating the guanidine group of 
Arg 
102 and by decreasing the dis-
tance between Asp 
67 and Arg </p>

<p>102 </p>

<p>compared with the exendin-4(9 -
39)-bound structure without affect-
ing the relative position and confor-
mation of Trp 
72 and Trp 
110 (Fig. 
3B). This enables a direct interac-
tion through a hydrogen bond 
between Asp 
67 and Arg 
102 unlike 
what we observed in the exendin-
4(9 -39)-bound structure, where a 
water molecule mediated the inter-
action between Asp 
67 and Arg </p>

<p>102 </p>

<p>(Fig. 3B). The functional consequences of the ligand-specific 
conformational differences are not known. 
Site-directed Mutagenesis of the GLP-1R-To link the struc-
tural information of the isolated ECD with the binding and 
functional properties of the full-length receptor, we targeted 
the ligand-binding site of the ECD by site-directed mutagene-
sis. The mutants were characterized by their ability to bind 
GLP-1 and exendin-4, using the agonist 
125 I-GLP-1 tracer, and 
by their ability to stimulate cAMP production in response to 
GLP-1 and exendin-4 (Table 2). The main objective was to 
search for mutations with differential effect on GLP-1 and 
exendin-4. We initially focused on Glu 
127 , which showed an 
obvious conformational difference in the two ligand-bound 
structures (Fig. 3A), Glu 
127 interacts directly with exendin-
4(9 -39) but not with GLP-1 (18). The ECD structures suggest 
that the hydrogen-bonding potential of Glu 
127 is important for 
exendin-4 binding but not for binding of GLP-1, and this is 
supported by the site-directed mutagenesis data (Table 2). 
Mutation of Glu 
127 to Ala reduced the affinity for exendin-4 but 
not for GLP-1 (6.8-versus 1.7-fold, respectively). Glu 
128 inter-
acts with a positively charged residue in both GLP-1 and 
exendin-4, which may explain why the E128A substitution did 
not have a differential effect on the binding affinity of GLP-1 
and exendin-4. The differential effect of the E127A mutation on 
GLP-1 and exendin-4 binding is rather small compared with 
the differential affinity of the isolated ECD shown previously 
(27). Clearly, the superior helical propensity of exendin-4 con-
tributes strongly to its high affinity for the ECD. 
Several interactions are conserved in the two ECD structures, 
and mutagenesis of the implicated receptor residues was not 
expected to have differential effects on ligand binding (Table 2). 
Surprisingly, the L32A mutation reduced both the affinity 
and potency of exendin-4 relative to GLP-1 (7.1-and 9.5-fold, 
respectively, see Table 2 and Fig. 4), demonstrating a ligand-
specific effect of the L32A mutation. Neither the potency nor </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Differences between the GLP-1-and exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure of ECD. Ribbon diagrams 
showing significant differences in side chain conformations between the GLP-1-bound structure and the 
exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure of GLP-1R ECD. Receptor and ligand residues are highlighted in blue for the 
GLP-1-bound structure and in orange for the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure. Water molecules in orange are 
present only in the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound structure. A, one diverging residue, Val 
33 * of GLP-1 and Lys 
27 ** of 
exendin-4(9 -39), causes a shift in the conformations of four residues, namely Glu 
127 , Leu 
123 , Arg 
121 , and Pro 
119 . 
B, GLP-1-specific conformations affect the conserved core of the ECD by rotating the guanidine group of Arg </p>

<p>102 </p>

<p>and by decreasing the distance between Asp 
67 and Arg 
102 compared with the exendin-4(9 -39)-bound struc-
ture without affecting the relative position of Trp 
72 and Trp 
110 . </p>

<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>

<p>JANUARY 1, 2010 • VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 727 </p>

<p>the affinity of GLP-1 was affected by the L32A mutation (Fig. 4), 
and the expression level of the receptor was similar to wild-type 
GLP-1R, which confirmed the structural integrity of this </p>

<p>receptor mutant. Leu 
32 is the first 
residue in the ␣-helix of the GLP-1R 
ECD, and it defines the border of 
the hydrophobic binding cavity by 
interacting with Ala 
24 *, Ala 
25 *, and 
Phe 
28 * (Fig. 2B). The results suggest 
that Leu 
32 is important for the bind-
ing of exendin-4 but not for the 
binding of GLP-1 to GLP-1R. It is 
difficult to give a structural explana-
tion of the ligand-specific effect of 
the L32A mutation by comparing 
the two ligand-bound forms of the 
ECD, because the structural differ-
ences in this region are quite subtle. 
Nevertheless, the ligand-specific 
effect of the L32A mutation sup-
ports the existence of differences in 
the binding modes of GLP-1 and 
exendin-4 to the full-length GLP-1R. 
Clearly, the two-domain binding 
mechanism of the full-length GLP-
1R is more complex than binding of 
the isolated ECD. 
Conformation of GLP-1, Recep-
tor-bound and in Solution-GLP-1 
is highly flexible in aqueous buffers, 
whereas in trifluoroethanol a single-
stranded ␣-helix forms (Thr 
13 * to 
Lys 
34 *) with a less defined ␣-helical 
region around Gly 
22 *, as demon-
strated by NMR spectroscopy (33,  39). Structure-activity studies of 
GLP-1 showed that side chain to 
side chain cyclization by lactam 
bridge formation of residues 16 -20 
and 18 -22 were well tolerated. Cyclization of residues 11-15 
improved potency for GLP-1R compared with the linear coun-</p>

<p>FIGURE 4. Functional and binding properties of the L32A GLP-1R mutant. Upper panel, stimulation of cAMP 
production by transiently transfected HEK293 cells expressing the L32A mutant by GLP-1 (squares, A) and 
exendin-4 (circles, B). Dashed dose-response curves represent cAMP production by GLP-1 and exendin-4 at the 
wild-type GLP-1R, respectively. Lower panel, competition binding assay on plasma membranes from tran-
siently transfected HEK293 cells expressing the L32A mutant. GLP-1 binding curves are presented with squares 
(C) and exendin-4 curves with circles (D). Dashed binding curves represent 
125 I-GLP-1 displacement by GLP-1 
and exendin-4 at the wild-type GLP-1R. Data are normalized according to 
125 I-GLP-1 binding and correspond to 
three independent experiments performed in duplicate. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Functional and binding experiments with GLP-1R mutants </p>

<p>EC 50 and IC 50 values are given in pM and nM, respectively, and expression levels are given in fmol/mg total protein. Data represent the mean Ϯ S.E. of three or more 
independent experiments performed in duplicate. The EC 50 or IC 50 values of GLP-1 and exendin-4 are compared with the wild-type GLP-1R using the unpaired t test. 
Numbers in parentheses equal the relative difference between EC 50 or IC 50 values of GLP-1 and exendin-4 at each mutant compared with the wild-type receptor. ND means 
not detectable, possibly due to no expression or no binding. * indicates p Ͻ 0.05; **, p Ͻ 0.01; and no asterisk means no significant difference. </p>

<p>Mutant 
EC 50 
IC 50 
Expression level 
GLP-1 
Exendin-4 
GLP-1 
Exendin-4 </p>

<p>pM 
nM 
fmol/mg </p>

<p>Wild type 
11 Ϯ 3.2 
5.5 Ϯ 1.7 
1.0 Ϯ 0.20 
0.76 Ϯ 0.19 
5.5 Ϯ 0.16 
L32A 
12 Ϯ 2.7 (1.1) 
52 Ϯ 24 (9.5) 
1.1 Ϯ 0.17 (1.1) 
5.4 Ϯ 1.5* (7.1) 
6.0 Ϯ 0.40 
T35A 
30 Ϯ 7.4 (2.7) 
23 Ϯ 12 (4.2) 
3.1 Ϯ 0.80 (3.1) 
0.44 Ϯ 0.1** (0.6) 
0.38 Ϯ 0.01 
V36A 
57 Ϯ 32 (5.2) 
36 Ϯ 20 (6.5) 
2.8 Ϯ 0.86 (2.8) 
0.98 Ϯ 0.34 (1.3) 
5.7 Ϯ 0.28 
E68A 
15 Ϯ 2.4 (1.4) 
9.5 Ϯ 4.2 (1.7) 
1.9 Ϯ 0.90 (1.9) 
0.48 Ϯ 0.07 (0.6) 
5.7 Ϯ 0.07 
Y69A 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
Y88A 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
L89A 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
ND 
P90A 
55 Ϯ 12* (5.0) 
30 Ϯ 7.3* (5.5) 
2.8 Ϯ 1.6 (2.8) 
1.6 Ϯ 0.28 (2.1) 
5.6 Ϯ 0.22 
R121A 
51 Ϯ 13* (4.6) 
44 Ϯ 10* (8.0) 
2.3 Ϯ 1.1 (2.3) 
1.2 Ϯ 0.02 (1.6) 
5.7 Ϯ 0.37 
L123A 
17 Ϯ 4.6 (1.5) 
9.5 Ϯ 1.9 (1.7) 
1.1 Ϯ 0.38 (1.1) 
0.33 Ϯ 0.04 (0.4) 
2.6 Ϯ 0.09 
E127A 
13 Ϯ 4.2 (1.2) 
11 Ϯ 0.45* (2.0) 
1.7 Ϯ 0.76 (1.7) 
5.2 Ϯ 2.0 (6.8) 
5.6 Ϯ 0.46 
E127Q 
12 Ϯ 3.3 (1.1) 
6.8 Ϯ 1.4 (1.2) 
1.1 Ϯ 0.27 (1.1) 
0.82 Ϯ 0.15 (1.1) 
6.11 Ϯ 0.21 
E128A 
28 Ϯ 6.2 (2.5) 
25 Ϯ 6.7* (4.5) 
2.7 Ϯ 0.91 (2.7) 
1.8 Ϯ 0.48 (2.4) 
6.0 Ϯ 0.49 
E128Q 
10 Ϯ 3.0 (0.9) 
8.0 Ϯ 3.3 (1.5) 
0.66 Ϯ 0.11 (0.7) 
0.45 Ϯ 0.1 (0.6) 
5.2 Ϯ 0.12 </p>

<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 • JANUARY 1, 2010 </p>

<p>terpart (40, 41). These data support the existence of an ␣-helical 
conformation in the N-terminal part of GLP-1 when bound to 
the full-length GLP-1R. It is interesting that in the ECD-bound 
structure, the Thr </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>*-Glu 
21 * segment of GLP-1 adopts an 
␣-helical conformation even though this segment does not 
interact with the ECD. The C-terminal segment of GLP-1 
(Ala 
24 *-Val 
33 *) is stabilized in a specific ␣-helical conformation 
through binding to the ECD. This may subsequently stabilize an 
␣-helical conformation in the N-terminal part of the ligand 
(Thr </p>

<p>13 </p>

<p>*-Glu 
21 *). This hypothesis is supported by the solution 
structure of GLP-1 in different concentrations of trifluoroetha-
nol (39). GLP-1 is a random coil in pure water, but adding tri-
fluoroethanol enables the C-terminal segment of GLP-1 to 
adopt an ␣-helix conformation. The C-terminal ␣-helix is grad-
ually extended toward the N-terminus of the peptide with 
increasing concentrations of trifluoroethanol (39), and it seems 
possible that a similar mechanism is initiated upon binding of 
GLP-1 to the ECD. It was recently proposed that ␣-helix for-</p>

<p>mation of the ligand upon binding 
to the ECD is an important step in 
the activation of class B GPCRs (23). 
As shown in Fig. 5A, the ␣-helix 
of GLP-1 has a central distortion of 
the backbone around Gly 
22 *, which 
is not observed in the exendin-4(9 -
39)-bound structure. The distortion 
is also observed in the NMR struc-
tures of GLP-1 in solution (39). 
However, we cannot exclude that 
the kink observed in the crystal 
structure is a result of crystal pack-
ing between the N-terminal part of 
GLP-1 (Gly 
10 *-Glu 
21 *) and symme-
try-related ECDs rather than a func-
tionally important characteristic of 
GLP-1 (Fig. 5, B-D). Substitution of 
Gly </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>* with Ala was previously shown 
not to affect the functionality or the 
binding affinity of GLP-1, which sug-
gests that flexibility around Gly </p>

<p>22 </p>

<p>* is 
not required for binding to or acti-
vation of GLP-1R (38). Interest-
ingly, Leu 
32 of the ECD is positioned 
right next to the kink of GLP-1 (Fig. 
5A). Thus, we have demonstrated a 
ligand-specific effect of the L32A 
mutation and have shown that 
ECD-bound GLP-1 has a kink right 
next to Leu 
32 , whereas ECD-bound 
exendin-4(9 -39) is straight. This 
may be a coincidence, but it is 
tempting to speculate that there is a 
connection between the structural 
difference of the ligands (kinked or 
straight helix) and the differential 
effect of the L32A mutant on bind-
ing of the ligands. 
A three-dimensional model of 
GLP-1R was recently published (21). From the NMR structure 
of GLP-1 in trifluoroethanol (Protein Data Bank code 1D0R 
(39)), it was suggested that GLP-1 might assume one of two 
forms when bound to GLP-1R, a slightly kinked ␣-helix or an 
L-shaped ␣-helix, and the authors concluded that the L-shaped 
␣-helix conformation of GLP-1 seemed more reasonable 
(21). The crystal structure presented here is more compatible 
with the kinked conformation of GLP-1. 
The structure of His 
7 *-Gly 
10 * was not determined in this 
study probably due to the inherent flexibility in this part of 
GLP-1 and other peptide ligands for class B receptors (33, 39,  42, 43). The only structural evidence showing a unique confor-
mation comes from a structural study of PACAP(1-21) com-
paring micelle-and receptor-bound states. Residues 1-7 of 
PACAP(1-21) adopt a specific ␤-coil structure upon receptor 
binding followed by an ␣-helical structure of residues 8 -21 
(44). The relevance of the receptor-bound PACAP(1-21) struc-
ture for GLP-1 in particular is supported by a previous study of </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Crystal packing. A, superposition of ECD-bound GLP-1 (blue) and exendin-4(9 -39) (cyan). GLP-1 
residue Gly 
22 * denotes a kink in the ␣-helix, which is situated in close proximity to Leu 
32 of the ECD. B, crystal 
packing involving symmetry-related complex molecules. C, ribbon diagram of GLP-1 (blue) and its interactions 
with the ligand of a symmetry-related molecule. Residues Tyr 
19 *, Gln 
23 *, and Glu 
27 * are shown as sticks, and the 
surface of the GLP-1R ECD is shown in gray. The packing of complex molecules allows Tyr 
19 * to interact with 
Gln 
23 * (3 Å) and Glu 
27 * (2.5 Å) in a symmetry-related ligand molecule. D, interactions between GLP-1 and 
residues of symmetry-related ECD molecules. GLP-1 residues Thr 
11 * , Thr 
13 *, Ser 
14 *, and Glu 
21 * are shown as 
sticks. The backbone carbonyl of Thr 
11 * could form a weak hydrogen bond (3.2 Å) to the backbone amide of 
Gln 
112 , the backbone amide of Thr 
13 * could form a hydrogen bond (2.9 Å) to the backbone carbonyl of Gln 
112 , 
and the backbone amide of Ser 
14 * may form a hydrogen bond (3 Å) to the side chain of Asp 
114 . The side chain 
of Glu 
21 * forms a hydrogen bond to the backbone amide of Phe 
80 (2.6 Å). </p>

<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>

<p>JANUARY 1, 2010 • VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 729 </p>

<p>chimeric PACAP/GLP-1 peptides (45). Substituting five resi-
dues from the N-terminus of GLP-1 with those of PACAP (three 
nonconserved, Fig. 1B) had no effect on either the affinity or 
potency for GLP-1R. Thus, on the basis of both sequence 
homology and structure-activity, GLP-1 would be expected to 
adopt a similar conformation upon binding to the GLP-1R TM 
domain. 
Conclusion-The crystal structure presented here shows 
the molecular details of GLP-1 binding to the GLP-1R ECD, 
an essential step in the two-domain binding mechanism of 
GLP-1R and class B GPCRs in general. Collectively, results 
from structural characterization of GLP-1 in solution, struc-
ture-activity analyses of GLP-1 analogues, and the crystal struc-
ture of GLP-1 bound to the GLP-1R ECD presented here sug-
gest that GLP-1 is a continuous ␣-helix from Thr 
13 * to Val 
33 * 
when bound to the full-length GLP-1R. This is important infor-
mation for the design of peptide therapeutics targeting GLP-
1R. GLP-1 and exendin-4 share the same binding site of the 
GLP-1R ECD, but the ligand-specific effects on the ECD struc-
ture and the ligand-specific effects of receptor mutagenesis 
support the existence of differences in the binding modes of 
GLP-1 and exendin-4 to the full-length GLP-1R. The nature of 
these differences as well as the active conformation of peptide 
agonists (kinked or not) and a better understanding of the two-
domain binding mechanism await structural characterization 
of the full-length GLP-1R. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank Lone Bayer and Thomas S. Harkes for 
skillful laboratory assistance, the staff at the MAX-lab beamline 
I911-3 for technical help during data collection, and Henning 
Thøgersen for discussions. </p>



<p>Crystal Structure of Receptor-bound GLP-1 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 1 • JANUARY 1, 2010 </p>

</text></tei>