<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2724645" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:47+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract: Objectives: This study investigates coincidence of the most-prominent point and the mid-point on upper ante-
rior teeth in relation to the use of straight-wire appliances. </p>

<p>Materials and Methods: Alginate impressions of the upper jaw were obtained from forty Caucasian patients. Impressions 
were cast using hard dental stone. The teeth on each upper study model (canine to canine) were marked along the facial 
axis of the clinical crown (FACC line) then separated using a very thin diamond disc. Each tooth was mounted on a glass 
slide using sticky wax and cut into two halves down this FACC line. Images were acquired of the sections and a straight 
line connecting the gingival margin and the incisal edge was drawn on the flat cut surfaces (now the proximal cross-
sectional view). From this line, perpendicular lines were drawn at the mid-point and most prominent point to the labial 
curve. Coincidence rate was calculated or whether the most prominent point was gingival or incisal to the mid-point. </p>

<p>Results: Approximately 80% of upper central incisors had coincident mid-and most-prominent points. Upper lateral inci-
sors and canine teeth had approximately 50% coincidence. The vast majority of cases without coincidence showed the 
most-prominent point incisal to the mid-point for all tooth kinds with just 5% or less gingival. </p>

<p>Conclusions: The high proportions of non-coincident examples found suggest that clinicians should be aware of individ-
ual variation and that this may possibly effect 3 
rd order alignment. </p>

<p>Modern orthodontics has been described as the creation 
of the finest occlusal relationship within the framework of 
acceptable facial aesthetics and stability of occlusal result 
[1]. This requires positioning the crown of each individual 
tooth in its appropriate position for optimum function and 
appearance. Straight-wire appliances were designed to re-
duce or eliminate the need for placing bends in fully engaged 
straight arch wires. Andrews [2] studied the average torque 
angles, rotation angles, height and depth of each facial sur-
face of each tooth type from untreated and treated patients 
having excellent occlusion. He found that when the brackets 
are precisely positioned at the midpoint of the facial axis and 
aligned with the facial axis, they collectively become the 
appliance providing specific tip, torque, rotation angle, 
height and depth position for each tooth. Limitations have 
been found in the effectiveness of this bracket system due to 
several factors, the most important of which is inaccurate 
bracket positioning [3]. This inaccuracy can only partly be 
blamed on clinician error as positioning the brackets on the 
mid-point should ideally be the same location as the most-
prominent point [2] to ensure the desired torque effects and 
tooth movement. These points, however, do not always coin-
cide and in fact may vary around each other to a large de-
gree. </p>

<p>*Address correspondence to this author at the Dental Sciences, University 
of Liverpool, UK; Tel 0151 7065118; Fax 0151 7065239; 
E-mail: r.n.smith@liverpool.ac.uk </p>

<p>This study was conducted to evaluate the coincidence 
rate of the mid-and most-prominent points on the labial sur-
face of upper central and lateral incisors and upper canines 
and possible implications when using straight wire appli-
ances. </p>

<p>METHOD </p>

<p>One hundred and fifty patients presenting for treatment in 
the Orthodontic Department, School of Clinical Dentistry, 
Sheffield, UK were examined by one Orthodontist. Each 
patient file contained a medical questionnaire signed by the 
patient's guardian, along with a written examination sheet 
signed by an orthodontic consultant indicating the level of 
the patient's oral hygiene, general records, x-ray records and 
occlusion type. Any missing teeth, supernumerary teeth or 
other abnormalities were also noted. From the one hundred 
and fifty patients, forty fulfilled the following inclusion/ ex-
clusion criteria: all patients were of Caucasian origin, aged 
between 13-16 years, had fully erupted upper incisor and 
canine teeth, good oral hygiene, with a healthy gingival mar-
gin around the upper anterior teeth, intact teeth e.g. no resto-
rations, attrition or abrasion, mild or no crowding in the ante-
rior region and the cases did not exhibit any abnormality of 
tooth number, form or structure and no medical or other 
health problems. This sample size exceeded others used 
within the department for morphology studies after statistical 
advice and calculation. The authors suggest that further cal-
culations may be required when considering cases other than 
those with class 1 relationships. </p>

<p>168 The Open Dentistry Journal, 2009, Volume 3 </p>

<p>Smith et al. </p>

<p>The age of the sample was limited to between 13 and 16 
years old to ensure that the teeth of interest were fully 
erupted but not worn. There were no restorations of their 
crowns. </p>

<p>An alginate impression (Alginoplast, Bayer) was taken of 
the upper jaw of the forty patients using hard dental stone 
(Kaffir D, British Gypsum. All the study models were dupli-
cated using Erkoflex (2mm EVA, Erkodent, Germany). </p>

<p>SECTIONING THE UPPER ANTERIOR TEETH </p>

<p>All practical work was carried out by one examiner. The 
upper anterior teeth on each study model (canine to canine) 
were marked along the facial axis of the clinical crown 
FACC line [4], with a thin pencil (size 0.3 mm). The FACC 
line was located manually using electronic callipers accurate 
to 0.01mm (Mitutoyo, Japan). A pencil line was placed down 
the centre of the labial surface to pass through 2 marks made 
halfway between the calliper widths at 2 different positions 
down the crown length. A line was then drawn through these 
points to meet with the gingival margin in one direction and 
the incisal edge in the other direction (Fig. 1). The teeth were 
individually separated using a very thin diamond disc (Mi-
croslice II precision slicing machine, Malvern Instrument, 
England) with a round annular blade having the cutting sur-
face on the inner edge. The blade was approximately 17.5cm 
in diameter and 0.3mm thick. Each tooth was mounted on a 
glass slide using red wax and yellow sticky wax. The labial 
tooth surface was aligned parallel to the glass slide, so that 
the FACC line was perpendicular to the slide edge to aid 
alignment for cutting the tooth along this line. Information 
for later identification was added to each slide prior to cut-
ting. The slides were placed on the platform beneath the cut-
ting disc and adjusted such that the pencil line was parallel to 
the cutting edge of the blade. The platform of the machine 
was adjustable (0.01mm steps) facilitating precise position-</p>

<p>ing of the slide. Red and green marker spots were used for 
identifying the mesial and distal portion of each sectioned 
tooth and included in subsequent imaging. </p>

<p>IMAGE ANALYSIS SYSTEM </p>

<p>A computerised image analysis system [5] was used to 
analyse the study models. A 32-bit digital camera (Kodak 
Nikon DCS 410, with a 1.5 mega pixel resolution in an array 
of 1012 1524 pixels, producing 4.6 MB TIF files) was at-
tached to a copy stand (Kaiser, Germany) using an adjustable 
camera mount. The copy stand had a base marked with a grid 
to aid specimen relocation. The camera was connected to a 
computer (Viglen CX1 Dual processor, 2 850 MH 2 CPU's, 
Viglen Ltd, UK) via an Adaptec 2940 SCSI card (KJP Ltd, 
UK). Light was provided by two white fluorescent tubes on 
the right and left side of the copy stand. Each light was ad-
justable in all three planes. </p>

<p>ACQUISITION AND STORAGE OF IMAGES </p>

<p>Images were displayed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> acquisi-
tion software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">V5.02</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Adobe Systems</rs>, Ltd, Europe) and 
viewed within ten seconds on the computer screen. Once 
acquired, each image was checked for quality and re-imaged 
if necessary. The images were saved as tagged image format 
files (TIFFs) as this format contains all of the original data. 
A permanent database was created of the original images. </p>

<p>PROXIMAL SURFACE OF UPPER ANTERIOR 
TEETH </p>

<p>Each tooth section was placed on a blue rubber base to 
provide consistent background contrast when imaged, and a 
steel rule was placed on the base adjacent to the tooth section 
for calibrating the image. All the sections were positioned 
with the same orientation to remove the need to rotate the 
images on screen later. Following acquisition each image </p>

<p>Fig. (1). Proximal section of a central incisor displaying the variables. </p>

<p>Mid-and Most-Prominent Point Location </p>

<p>The Open Dentistry Journal, 2009, Volume 3 169 </p>

<p>was viewed using "<rs type="software">Adobe PhotoShop</rs>" and was re-imaged if 
required. </p>

<p>The perimeter of the labial curve was traced from the 
gingival margin to the incisal edge. A straight line connect-
ing the gingival margin and the incisal edge called the 
proximal line was then drawn (Fig. 1). The distance (L2) 
from the proximal line to the labial curve at the mid point 
was then obtained using the 'length' option within the <rs id="software-2" type="software">Image 
Pro Plus</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">version 4</rs>, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Media Cybernetics</rs>, UK). Simi-
larly, the most prominent point of the labial curve to the 
proximal line was obtained by drawing a tangent parallel to 
the proximal line using the length option (L3). The point at 
which the tangent was the greatest length from the labial 
curve was the most prominent point. The vertical distance 
between L2 and L3 along the proximal line was determined 
(L4). L4 was measured and was either negative or positive in 
value, according to the position of the most prominent point 
being incisal or gingival respectively to the mid-point (Fig. 
1). </p>

<p>DATA ANALYSIS </p>

<p>The reliability of the total procedure was calculated from 
20 of the study models (10 male and 10 female randomly 
selected) and included duplicating study models, re-
sectioning and re-imaging the cut sections. The labial curve 
(gingival margin to incisal tip along the labial edge of the </p>

<p>section) and the proximal line were used to show that the 
mesial and distal portions of the teeth were reproducibly 
created and that either side could have been chosen. The 
mean difference, standard deviation of the difference, stan-
dard error of the difference and intra-operator repeatability 
coefficients were calculated as well as Fleiss [6] Intra-class 
Correlation Coefficient of Reliability (ICCC). Bland Altman 
plots were produced for all repeat measures to ensure no 
size/error relationships and to check for outliers and bias [7]. </p>

<p>For L2, L3 and L4 forty cases were assessed for the ex-
perimental data including the mean value, standard deviation 
and range (minimum and maximum values). A negative L4 
value signifies the most-prominent point is incisal to the 
mid-point, whereas a positive L4 values infers the most-
prominent point is gingival to the mid-point (Fig. 2). The 
authors would also like to recognise the importance of fur-
ther study assessing the shape of posterior teeth. These could 
not be considered here due to time constraints of the main 
author. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Reliability </p>

<p>Table 1 shows that comparison of measurement of the la-
bial curve and the proximal line from both mesial and distal 
gave 'excellent repeatability' according to Donner and Eli-</p>

<p>Fig. (2). Examples of the most-prominent point presenting coincident, incisal and gingival to the mid-point of the labial curve. </p>

<p>Table 1. Reliability of the Preparation of the Proximal View Slices (N=40) </p>

<p>Variable 
Labial Curve 
Proximal Line </p>

<p>Mean difference </p>

<p>0.00 mm 
0.03 mm </p>

<p>SD of differences </p>

<p>0.44 mm 
0.22 mm </p>

<p>SE of differences 
0.10mm 
0.050mm </p>

<p>Repeatability coefficient 
0.86mm 
0.43mm </p>

<p>ICCC 
0.94 
0.95 </p>



<p>Smith et al. </p>

<p>asziw [8] classification of Fleiss ICCC [6]. This indicates the 
model preparation, cutting and imaging and variable meas-
urement was repeatable. This data also qualifies that either 
the mesial or distal slice could be used, with confidence and 
produce the same findings (Table 1). It was clear from the 
Bland Altman plots and the fact that all the mean differences 
were less than 1.96 x Standard error that the method pro-
duced no significant bias. </p>

<p>Table 2 shows repeat measurements for variables L2, L3 
and L4 for all three tooth types. Repeat measures were taken 
a week after the initial measurement. All the variable meas-
urements produced 'excellent repeatability' with no signifi-
cant bias found. </p>

<p>Tables 3 and 4 show the anterior labial curve is not flat 
(has a most-prominent point) and is often not symmetrically 
curved, as there are a high percentage of cases displaying a 
difference between the position of the mid-point and the </p>

<p>Table 2. Reliability of Slice Preparation and Measurement (N=40). Left and Right Teeth Combined (mm) </p>

<p>Central Incisors 
Lateral Incisors 
Canines </p>

<p>Variable 
L2 
L3 
L4 
L2 
L3 
L4 
L2 
L3 
L4 </p>

<p>Mean difference 
0.02 
0.03 
0.00 
0.03 
0.02 
0.00 
0.02 
0.03 
0.00 </p>

<p>SD of differ-
ences 
0.09 
0.08 
0.06 
0.08 
0.08 
0.01 
0.09 
0.09 
0.08 </p>

<p>SE of differ-
ences 
0.02 
0.02 
0.01 
0.02 
0.02 
0.00 
0.02 
0.02 
0.02 </p>

<p>Repeatability 
coefficient 
0.18 
0.16 
0.12 
0.16 
0.16 
0.02 
0.18 
0.18 
0.16 </p>

<p>ICCC 
0.93 
0.93 
0.98 
0.83 
0.81 
0.99 
0.95 
0.95 
0.99 </p>

<p>Table 3. Descriptive Statistics for L2, L3 and L4 for 40 Right and Left Upper Anterior Teeth (mm) </p>

<p>Variable 
Range 
Mean 
Std. Deviation </p>

<p>L2 
0.77, 1.91 
1.18 
0.25 </p>

<p>L3 
0.77, 1.91 
1.20 
0.27 
Upper right central incisors </p>

<p>L4 
-2.08, 1.10 
-0.14 
0.59 </p>

<p>L2 
0.39, 1.64 
1.08 
0.30 </p>

<p>L3 
0.74, 1.64 
1.14 
0.24 
Upper left central incisors </p>

<p>L4 
-2.69, 1.02 
-0.56 
1.07 </p>

<p>L2 
0.50, 1.42 
0.90 
0.19 </p>

<p>L3 
0.68, 1.42 
0.97 
0.16 
Upper Right Lateral Incisors </p>

<p>L4 
-2.25, 1.07 
-0.89 
0.95 </p>

<p>L2 
0.57, 1.50 
0.94 
0.22 </p>

<p>L3 
0.70, 1.50 
1.00 
0.19 
Upper Left Lateral Incisors </p>

<p>L4 
-2.14, 0.00 
-0.69 
0.86 </p>

<p>L2 
0.59, 1.87 
1.01 
0.29 </p>

<p>L3 
0.75, 1.99 
1.08 
0.27 
Upper Right Canines </p>

<p>L4 
-2.50, 0.90 
-0.75 
0.96 </p>

<p>L2 
0.61, 2.02 
1.07 
0.31 </p>

<p>L3 
0.61, 2.07 
1.11 
0.32 
Upper Left Canines </p>

<p>L4 
-2.62, 1.40 
-0.33 
0.91 </p>

<p>Mid-and Most-Prominent Point Location </p>

<p>The Open Dentistry Journal, 2009, Volume 3 171 </p>

<p>most-prominent point. The most-prominent point on all tooth 
types was mainly incisal to the mid-point if it was not coin-
cident with only a small percentage gingival to the mid-
point. The upper lateral incisors showed the greatest number 
of instances where the most-prominent point was incisal, 
followed by the canines with the central incisors showing the 
greatest coincidence and therefore symmetry. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>From Tables 1 and 2 it is clear that this method was re-
peatable and therefore a sound approach to assessing the 
curvature of upper anterior teeth from study models. All 
ICCC's were in the excellent range of reliability and the 
Bland Altman plots showed no significant bias and accept-
able repeatability coefficients. </p>

<p>Previous research studies have investigated the variation 
of tooth morphology and its relationship to bracket position-
ing. Variation in labial tooth surface morphology affects the 
angle at which a bracket may be seated in relation to the fa-
cial axis of the clinical crown. It has been presumed, in re-
spect of bracket placement, that the mid-points and most-
prominent points are coincident on the labial surface of ante-
rior teeth [4,9]. This study has shown, for the first time that 
these two points show coincidence at approximately 80% on 
central incisors reducing to approximately 50% on lateral 
incisors and canines. This means that on approximately 20% 
of central incisors and 50% of laterals and canines, brackets 
will be placed at the mid-point of the labial curve when it is 
not the most-prominent point. In this situation the labial 
curve is not symmetrical vertically about the mid-point such 
that the bracket will not sit in the preferred position parallel 
to the proximal line (facial axis of the clinical crown) as 
mentioned by Andrews [2]. This situation could introduce 
axial forces affecting the inclination of these teeth (3 
rd order 
correction) and increase the need for extra final adjustment 
after initial alignment. Our data is in agreement with previ-
ous tooth morphology studies on labial surface variation [10-
15] but provides extra specific information regarding mid-
and most-prominent point coincidence and location. </p>

<p>This study only considered class 1 relationships from pa-
tients requiring minor adjustments only to the lower denti-
tion. The size and shape of a tooth will obviously affect the 
amount of torgue/ force required but the effect of each meas-
urement variation would require a separate study. This paper </p>

<p>and study discuss' the effect of the curvature of the tooth 
surface and therefore difference between the mid and most 
prominent points only. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS </p>

<p>This method of preparing proximal sections of upper an-
terior teeth from study models and there subsequent meas-
urement by image analysis, has demonstrated a reliable way 
of assessing coincidence of mid-and most-prominent points 
on the labial surface of upper anterior teeth. </p>

<p>The assessment of mid-and most-prominent point loca-
tion on the central incisor cases showed greatest symmetry 
with only 20% of cases having non coincident mid-and 
most-prominent points whilst lateral incisors and canines 
presented with approximately 50% non coincidence. </p>

<p>The, overall, high proportions of non-coincident exam-
ples found suggest that clinicians should be aware of indi-
vidual variation and that this may possibly effect 3 
rd order 
alignment. </p>



<p>Table 4. Percentage of Most-Prominent Point's Found Coincident, Incisal or Gingival to the Mid-Point's on Upper Anterior Teeth </p>

<p>Tooth Type 
Tooth Location 
Coincident 
Incisal 
Gingival </p>

<p>Right 
82.5% 
12.5% 
5.0% 
Upper Central Incisors 
Left 
72.5% 
25.0% 
2.5% </p>

<p>Right 
47.5% 
50.0% 
2.5% 
Upper Lateral Incisors 
Left 
60.0% 
40.0% 
0.0% </p>

<p>Right 
55.0% 
42.5% 
2.5% 
Upper Canines 
Left 
75.0% 
20.0% 
5.0% </p>



<p>Smith et al. </p>



<p>Received: September 26, 2008 
Revised: November 06, 2008 
Accepted: June 08, 2009 </p>

<p>© Smith et al.; Licensee Bentham Open. </p>

<p>This is an open access article licensed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License 
(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/) which permits unrestricted, non-commercial use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the 
work is properly cited. </p>

</text></tei>