<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2682500" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:36+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract </p>

<p>Few molecular studies have been devoted to the finger drop process that occurs during banana fruit ripening. Recent 
studies revealed the involvement of changes in the properties of cell wall polysaccharides in the pedicel rupture area. 
In this study, the expression of cell-wall modifying genes was monitored in peel tissue during post-harvest ripening 
of Cavendish banana fruit, at median area (control zone) and compared with that in the pedicel rupture area (drop 
zone). To this end, three pectin methylesterase (PME) and seven xyloglucan endotransglycosylase/hydrolase (XTH) 
genes were isolated. The accumulation of their mRNAs and those of polygalaturonase, expansin, and pectate lyase 
genes already isolated from banana were examined. During post-harvest ripening, transcripts of all genes were 
detected in both zones, but accumulated differentially. MaPME1, MaPG1, and MaXTH4 mRNA levels did not change 
in either zone. Levels of MaPME3 and MaPG3 mRNAs increased greatly only in the control zone and at the late 
ripening stages. For other genes, the main molecular changes occurred 1-4 d after ripening induction. MaPME2, 
MaPEL1, MaPEL2, MaPG4, MaXTH6, MaXTH8, MaXTH9, MaEXP1, MaEXP4, and MaEXP5 accumulated highly in the 
drop zone, contrary to MaXTH3 and MaXTH5, and MaEXP2 throughout ripening. For MaPG2, MaXET1, and MaXET2 
genes, high accumulation in the drop zone was transient. The transcriptional data obtained from all genes examined 
suggested that finger drop and peel softening involved similar mechanisms. These findings also led to the proposal 
of a sequence of molecular events leading to finger drop and to suggest some candidates. </p>

<p>Banana is the second ranking fruit crop in the world, with 
an annual world production of ;70 million metric tons 
(FAOstat, 2007 faostat.fao.org/site/567/DesktopDefault. 
aspx?). Banana fruit ripening is characterized by a burst of </p>

<p>ethylene production and respiration concomitantly with 
physicochemical and biochemical changes, including chlo-
rophyll breakdown, increased starch degradation and sugar 
synthesis, and fruit softening. Finger drop is one of the </p>

<p>* To whom correspondence should be addressed. didier.mbeguie-a-mbeguie@cirad.fr 
ª 2009 The Author(s). </p>

<p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-
nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>main features closely associated with the banana ripening 
process. This process, which was reported for the first time 
in the triploid Cavendish AAA group, involves physiologi-
cal softening and weakening, thus causing individual fruit in 
a hand to separate from the crown (Hicks, 1934; Baldry  et al., 1981; Semple and Thompson 1988). Bananas are 
marketed in hands of generally 4-9 fruits. Dislodgement of 
individual fruits from the hand considerably reduces the 
commercial value of the product because hands with fingers 
missing or fingers without pedicels cannot be sold to 
consumers. The finger drop process thus reduces the 
economic value of bananas. Despite this important eco-
nomic impact, few studies have been devoted to gaining an 
insight into the physiological mechanisms related to banana 
finger drop. Susceptibility to finger drop varies widely 
according to cultivars and their ripening conditions, with 
triploid cultivars being less susceptible than tetraploids 
(New and Marriot, 1983). Among triploid cultivars, Valery 
is less susceptible than Gros Michel, and Hom Tong (Musa 
acuminata, AAA) shows massive drop while Namwa (Musa 
sp., ABB) does not (New and Marriot, 1983; Saengpook  et al., 2007). In addition to cultivars, the level of fruit 
development ripening conditions (including ethylene, hu-
midity, and temperature) also affect the susceptibility to 
banana finger drop (Semple and Thompson, 1988; Paull,  1996; Imsabai et al., 2006). Studies on the physiological 
mechanisms of banana finger drop have only recently been 
carried out and, to our knowledge, performed only at the 
biochemical level. In a study on two varieties that display 
massive (Hom Tong variety) and no finger drop (Namwa 
variety), respectively, Imsabai et al. (2006) showed that peel 
water content and thickness did not affect the finger drop 
process. By contrast, differential changes in the water-and 
CDTA-soluble fractions, and in the insoluble pectin frac-
tion at the peel rupture area in the Hom Tong variety 
indicated high pectin breakdown and degradation activity 
in this variety. The authors also showed that this pectin 
breakdown was mainly the result of pectate lyase and 
polygalacturonase enzymes, as their corresponding activities 
increased concomitantly in the peel rupture area of the 
Hom Tong variety as compared with those of the Namwa 
variety. It is now assumed that cell wall modifications 
that occur during fruit ripening correspond to a complex 
process involving different mechanisms, including enzy-
matic and non-enzymatic degradation of cell wall compo-
nents (Dumville and Fry, 2003; Bennett and Labavitch,  2008), cell wall synthesis (Mitcham et al., 1989, 1991; Greve  and Labavitch, 1991; Huysamer et al., 1997; Rose and  Bennett, 1999) and/or loosening of the cell wall network 
mediated by non-enzymatic proteins like expansin 
(Brummell, 2006). Enzymatic degradation of cell wall 
components is the result of the induction, at both molecular 
and biochemical levels, of pectolic and/or non-pectolitic cell 
wall-modifying proteins (CWMPs) according to the specific 
class of polysaccharides used as substrate. The pectolytic 
enzymes include endo-and exo-polygalacturonases (endo-
EC 3.2.1.15; exo-EC 3.2.1.67), pectate lyases (PEL; EC 4.2. 
2.2), pectin methylesterases (PME; EC 3.1.1.11), pectin </p>

<p>acetylesterases (PAE; EC 3.1.1.-), b-galactosidases (EC 3.2. 
1.23), and a-L-arabinofuranosidases (EC 3.2.1.55) (Vicente  et al., 2007; Goulao and Oliveira, 2008). These enzymes are 
able to cleave or modify the nature of the polysaccharide 
backbone or to remove neutral sugars from branched 
side-chains. Non-pectolytic enzymes are responsible for 
hemicellulose modifications and include endo-1,4-b-
glucanases (EGase; EC 3.2.1.4), endo-1,4-b-xylanases (EC 
3.2.1.8), b-xylanases (EC 3.2.1.37), and xyloglucan endo-
transglycosylase/hydrolases (XTH; EC 2.4.1.207). Many of 
these proteins have been investigated, at both molecular and 
biochemical levels, in relationship with banana fruit soften-
ing. A co-ordinated increase in mRNA abundance, de novo 
synthesis or activity of a number of putative cell wall-
modifying enzymes that may be responsible for or contrib-
ute significantly to polymer modifications has been observed 
(Dominguez-Puigjaner et al., 1997; Pua et al., 2001;  Marin-Rodriguez et al., 2003; Trivedi and Nath, 2004; Asif  and Nath, 2005; Zhuang et al., 2006, 2007; Sane et al.,  2007). 
As none of these genes have been examined in relation to 
finger drop, an attempt was made to investigate, at the 
molecular level, the putative relationship between the 
expression of some cell wall-modifying genes (CWMGs) 
and the finger drop process in order to identify: (i) the 
putative physiological mechanism of the cell wall metabo-
lism involved in the finger drop process, and (ii) relevant 
genes involved for purposes of identification of functional 
molecular markers. 
Banana is a complex species and attempts to improve the 
fruit quality through breeding strategies is complex and 
difficult to set up. Access to functional molecular markers 
derived from relevant genes associated with fruit quality 
traits should therefore provide a valuable and helpful 
resource for the development of new crossing strategies and 
the selection process. Moreover, gaining further insight into 
the molecular mechanisms that govern the elaboration of 
fruit quality traits and their regulation is a key prerequisite 
for the development of other strategies to improve banana 
quality traits like post-harvest technology and/or biotech-
nology approaches. 
In the present study, the accumulation of mRNA genes 
encoding a broad array of enzymes known to hydrolyse or 
modify the fine structure of cell wall polysaccharides was 
examined, with the view of correlating particular mecha-
nisms and genes with previously observed changes in cell 
wall composition during finger drop. </p>

<p>Materials and methods </p>

<p>Plant material </p>

<p>All tissues used in this study were harvested from three 
banana plants (Musa acuminata, AAA, Cavendish, cv. 
Grande Naine) grown at the CIRAD research station 
(elevation: 250 m; andosol; rainfall: 3500 mm year 
À1 ), 
Guadeloupe (French West Indies). During growth, bunches </p>



<p>on banana plants were covered with blue plastic bags to 
hamper insect infestations, and to streamline the develop-
ment of whole fruits on the bunch. Green fruits were 
harvested at commercial ripeness, as determined on the 
basis of the heat unit concept (Ganry and Meyer, 1975;  Jullien et al., 2008). At each harvesting time, only internal 
fingers of the median hand on the bunch, considered as 
comparable (Liu, 1976), were taken into account for each 
bunch. After harvest, all fruits were kept for 24 h at 20°C 
in chambers ventilated with humidified air before treatment 
with 10 000 ppm of azethyl (95% nitrogen/5% ethylene) for 
24 h at 20°C and ambient humidity. From 1-7 d after 
treatment (DAT), a sample of three fruits was taken daily 
for finger drop measurement. Immediately at the end of 
each measurement, peel tissues corresponding to the median 
part of the fruit (control zone) and to the rupture area of 
the fruit pedicel (drop zone) (Fig. 1) were sampled, 
separately frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at -80°C 
until use. </p>

<p>Measurement of finger drop variations during 
post-harvest ripening of fruit </p>

<p>Finger drop was estimated by measuring the pedicel 
rupture force using a TA-XT2 penetrometer and an adapted 
probe as follows. Banana fruit were attached 6 cm above 
a table with a large clip. The probe was pressed down to 
a depth of 40 mm and at a constant speed of 5 mm s 
À1 , at 
the pedicel until it separated from the fruit (Chillet et al.,  2008). The required force was expressed in Newtons (N). 
All of these measurements were performed in triplicate on 
three separate fruits and the experiment was repeat three 
times. </p>

<p>Isolation of banana fruit genes coding for xyloglucan 
endotransglycosylase/hydrolase-like (XTH-like) and 
pectin methylesterase-like (PME-like) </p>

<p>Partial cDNAs encoding banana XTH-like genes were 
amplified using the 3# RACE-PCR method (Frohman, 1990). 
Total RNA was extracted separately from peel tissue from 
control and drop zones of banana fruit taken at commercial 
ripeness, and at 1-4 DAT, using the modified hot-borate 
method (Wan and Wilkins, 1994; Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié et al.,  2008a). According to the manufacturer's instructions, 2 lg of 
each RNA extract was DNAse-treated using RQI DNase 
(Promega, Charbonières, France) before being separately 
reverse-transcribed into cDNA using Oligo-dT 17 primers 
(Frohman, 1990; see Supplementary Table S1 at JXB online) 
and AMV reverse transcriptase enzyme (Promega). These 
cDNA were pooled and 1 ll of this mixture was subjected to 
3# RACE-PCR with Xth-F1 and dT 17 -adapter primers in 
a 25 ll reaction containing 13 Taq buffer (Eurobio, 
Courtaboeuf, France), 150 nM of dNTP, 1.5 mM of MgCl 2 , 
200 nM of each primer, and 1 U of Taq polymerase. Xth-F1 
is a degenerated forward primer designed from a conserved 
HDE(I/M)DFEF region among plant XTH-like proteins 
(Table 1). The PCR program involved one cycle of 1 min at 
94°C for template denaturation and Taq activation followed 
by 40 cycles of 30 s at 94°C for template denaturation, 1 min 
at 40°C for primer annealing, and 2 min at 72°C for 
template elongation. The isolated cDNA fragments (approx-
imately 1100 bp) were cloned into pGEM-T vector using the 
pGEM-T Easy Cloning kit (Promega) and sequenced by 
Cogenics (Grenoble, France). GenBank accession numbers 
are FJ264506 (MaXTH3), FJ264507 (MaXTH4), FJ264508 
(MaXTH5), FJ264509 (MaXTH6), FJ264510 (MaXTH7), 
FJ264511 (MaXTH8), and FJ264512 (MaXTH9). </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Measurement of finger drop variations during post-harvest ripening of Cavendish banana through pedicel rupture force 
measurement. Banana fruits harvested at the mature green stage were stored overnight at 20°C before treatment with 10 000 ppm of 
azethyl (5% ethylene+95% nitrogen) for 24 h. Fruits were further kept at 20°C in air for 7 d to ripen. Banana finger drop was evaluated 
on the basis of the pedicel rupture force expressed in Newtons (N). This force was measured daily from the harvesting point (Ht) to day 7, 
as described by Chillet et al. (2008). Each data point is the mean of values obtained from at least four fruits originating from four replicate 
bunches. Vertical bars indicate standard deviation (SD). When no bar is shown, the SD is smaller than the symbol. </p>

<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2023 </p>

<p>For pectin methylesterase genes, one partial cDNA and 
two genomic sequences coding for banana PME-like genes 
were isolated in this study. The partial cDNA sequence was 
isolated throughout EST sequencing. PME genomic sequen-
ces were identified throughout sequencing and annotation 
of BAC clones MAC077E20 (accession number AC226050) 
and MAC088K20 (accession number AC226051), isolated 
from a Cavendish BAC library (Piffanelli et al., 2003). </p>

<p>Bioinformatic sequence analysis </p>

<p>The sequence similarity of the genes isolated in this study 
was determined using the online BLAST (Altschul et al.,  1997) and BLAST 2 sequence (Tatusova and Madden,  1999) programs on the National Center for Biotechnology 
Information <rs type="software">BLAST</rs> website (National Library of Medi-
cine, Bethesda, MD). For sequence comparison throughout 
the <rs id="software-14" type="software">BLAST</rs> <rs corresp="#software-14" type="version-number">2</rs> program, two additional parameters were 
introduced, Qcov and Scov, which allows us to take into 
account the difference of the length between sequences. 
Query coverage (Qcov) is the ratio of length of the match by 
length of the query sequence. This value indicates the part 
of the query sequence covered by the alignment. Similarly, 
Subject coverage (Scov) was calculated as the ratio of length 
of the match by length of the subject or target length, and 
indicates the part of the subject or target sequence covered 
by the alignment. </p>

<p>All sequence alignments and phylogenetic tree construc-
tion were performed using the ClustalX algorithm with the 
Gonnet residue weights (Thompson et al., 1997). For XTHs 
genes, the pair-wise alignment parameters used included 
a gap opening penalty of 35 and a gap extension penalty of 
0.75. For multiple alignments, the gap opening penalty was 
15, with a gap extension penalty of 0.3 and the delay 
divergent sequences was set at 25%. The consensus tree was 
drawn using the <rs id="software-15" type="software">TREE VIEW</rs> program (<rs corresp="#software-15" type="creator">Page</rs>, 1996). 
Search motifs in the promoter regions of MA-PME 
genomic sequences was found by screening the PLACE 
(Prestridge, 1991; Higo et al., 1999) and PLANT CARE 
(Lescot et al., 2002) databases. In silico prediction of 5#-
and 3#-UTR regions of MA-PME genes and prediction of 
signal peptides were performed using EuGène 3.2 with rice 
parameters (Foissac et al., 2008) and SignalP 3.0 (Bendtsen  et al., 2004) programs, respectively. </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide primers for gene expression through 
real-time qPCR and end-point PCR analysis </p>

<p>The oligonucleotide primers used for RT-qPCR analysis 
were designed using the Primer 3 freeware program (Roten  and Skaletsky, 2000) according to the default criteria and 
the corresponding sequences are described in Supplemen-
tary Table S1 at JXB online. Except for polygalacturonase 
genes MaPG3 and MaPG4, whose primers were designed </p>

<p>Table 1. Sequence analysis and comparison of banana PME genes </p>

<p>Analysis of nucleotide and polypeptide sequences of PME genes isolated in this study. The features of nucleotide and polypeptide sequences 
of MaPME1 cDNA and those of the two genomic sequences of MaPME2 and MaPME3 are given in (A). A comparison of nucleotide and 
polypeptide sequences of MaPME genes (B), including determination of Scov and Qcov values, was performed using BLAST 2 (Tatusova and  Madden, 1999). </p>

<p>(A) </p>

<p>Sequence 
Gene or 
cDNA 
length (bp) </p>

<p>Polypeptide 
length (aa) </p>

<p>MW 
(kDa) </p>

<p>pI 
Promoter 
length </p>

<p>Exon 
1 </p>

<p>Intron 
Exon 
2 </p>

<p>MaPME1 
1923 
565 
61 
7.8 
-
-
-
-
MaPME2 
3365 
559 
61 
6.7 
1162 
960 
68 
720 
MaPME3 
3186 
574 
62 
7.06 
1000 
1029 
81 
696 </p>

<p>(B) </p>

<p>Polypeptides 
MaPME1: 1845 bp (565 aa) </p>

<p>Length 
% identity 
(similarity) </p>

<p>Scov 
Qcov </p>

<p>MaPME1 
565 
-
-
-
MaPME2 
559 
46 (60) 
81.06 
81.93 
MaPME3 
574 
47 (59) 
97.17 
95.64 </p>

<p>Nucleotides 
CDS </p>

<p>Length 
% identity 
Scov 
Qcov </p>

<p>MaPME1 
1895 
-
-
-
MaPME2 
2135 
75 
9.3 
8.2 
MaPME3 
2104 
75 
27.7 
24.9 </p>



<p>within the divergent coding region, all other primers were 
designed within the 3#-UTR region. The lengths of all PCR 
products ranged from 125 bp to 247 bp. The gene specificity 
of all primer sets was tested using the following three 
independent procedures: (i) BLAST searches against Gen-
Bank databases were performed for each primer to check 
that no member of a primer set matched another sequence 
in the banana genome; (ii) the specificity of PCR amplifica-
tion was examined by monitoring the dissociation curves 
during qPCR reactions using the ABI PRISM 7000 
sequence detection system (Applied Biosystems, Courta-
boeuf, France); (iii) individual PCR products were sepa-
rated on 2% agarose gels and stained with ethidium 
bromide to examine their size and ensure that a single PCR 
product was detected for each primer pair, in accordance 
with the single peak observed in the dissociation curve. As 
for the MaPME2 and MaPME3 genes, the corresponding 
specific primers were designed based on the 3#-UTR 
predicted from the corresponding genomic sequence. The 
generated PCR fragment was further cloned and sequenced 
to confirm that it corresponded to a PME genomic 
sequence. </p>

<p>Real-time qPCR analysis </p>

<p>All qPCR experiments were performed on an ABI 7000 
sequence detection apparatus (Applied Biosystems, Courta-
boeuf, France) using the SYBR Green PCR Master Mix as 
described by Mbéguié-A-Mbéguié et al. (2008b). Two 
micrograms of total RNA extracted from different banana 
fruit tissues and organs treated with RQ1 DNase (Promega, 
Charbonnières, France) to remove possible contaminating 
genomic DNA were used. First-strand cDNA was synthe-
sized from these RNA using AMV reverse transcriptase 
enzymes (Promega, Charbonnières, France) and random 
hexamers according to the manufacturer's instructions. To 
hamper the effect of putative PCR inhibitors that might be 
present in the reverse transcriptase reaction, as well as 
pipetting errors, the cDNA was 10-fold diluted with 
distilled water, and 5 ll of the diluted cDNA was used as 
a template for qPCR analysis. The qPCR program included 
one cycle of 5 min at 94°C for template denaturation and 
Taq activation, followed by 40 cycles of 30 s at 94°C for 
template denaturation, 15 s at 50°C for primer annealing, 
and 30 s at 72°C for primer elongation. Fluorescence was 
analysed using Sequence Detection Software (Applied 
Biosystems Courtaboeuf, France). A cycle threshold value 
(Ct) was calculated from the amplification curves by 
selecting the optimal DRn (emission of reporter dye over 
starting background fluorescence) in the exponential por-
tion of the amplification plot. 
The amplification efficiency of all primer sets was de-
termined by qPCR analysis as described previously. To this 
end, we used 6 log of 2-fold serial dilutions made from 
a pool of cDNA reverse-transcribed from a mixture of RQI 
DNase-treated mRNA from different banana fruit tissues 
and organs. For each dilution, a qPCR was run in triplicate. 
The efficiency (slope) ranges were 83-100% (3.3-3.7), 87-</p>

<p>100% (3.3-3.6), 73.3-77.3% (4.02-4.1), and 72-92% (3.12-
4.2) for expansin, pectin methylesterase, polygalacturonase, 
pectate lyase, and xyloglucan endotransferase/hydrolase 
genes, respectively. They were measured using the Ct slope 
method (data not shown) and the formula E x ¼10 
(-1/slope) -1. 
The relative fold differences in expression of each gene 
between samples were determined using the 2 
ÀDDCt formula 
(Livak and Schmittgen, 2001). For each gene and sample, 
a qPCR was performed in triplicate on two independent 
RNA extracts as described above. The MA-ACT gene was 
used as the internal control to standardize the difference 
between template amounts and fruit tissues taken at harvest 
before ripening induction was used as the calibrator. </p>

<p>Results </p>

<p>Finger drop evolution of banana fruit measured via the 
pedicel rupture force </p>

<p>Banana fruits were harvested at commercial harvest grade 
corresponding to approximately 90 days after flowering 
(DAF). According to the rupture force measurement (Fig. 1), 
Cavendish banana finger drop started 1 d after ripening 
induction and continued progressively throughout the post-
harvest ripening stage. However, a marked decreased was 
observed between days 1 to 3 after ripening induction, with 
more than a 2-fold decrease in the pedicel rupture force. As 
the pedicel rupture force pattern is considered to be a way 
of measuring banana finger drop (Saengpook et al., 2007), 
our data suggest that our experimental conditions led to the 
development of the finger drop process of Cavendish 
banana. </p>

<p>Cloning of MaXTH genes from banana fruit and 
sequence analysis </p>

<p>Seven partial cDNA fragments encoding XTH-like poly-
peptides were isolated from of banana peel tissue. As two 
banana XTH homologues, MaXET1 and MaXET2, were 
previously isolated and registered in the GenBank database 
(Lu et al., 2004), the XTH cDNAs isolated in this study 
were named MaXTH3 to MaXTH9. The sequence homol-
ogy between MaXTH cDNA ranges from 3.1% to 71% at 
the nucleotide level and from 12% to 81% at the amino acid 
level, with MaXTH5 and MaXTH6 being highly homolo-
gous pairs. Compared with MaXET1 and MaXET2 genes, 
a high homology was observed with MaXTH7 and 
MaXTH4, respectively. Analysis of the predicted MaXTH 
polypeptides revealed that they contained a DEIDFEFLG 
motif conserved within glycosyl hydrolase family 16 (GH16) 
enzymes and, adjacent to the putative active site, the 
potential N-linked glycosylation site N-X-S/T motif. For 
MaXTH5 and MaXTH6, this last motif was substituted by 
the N-V-R motif which is characteristic of group-3 XTHs 
(Campbell and Braam, 1999; Johanson et al., 2004; see 
Supplementary Fig. S1 at JXB online). 
A phylogenetic tree was constructed to investigate the 
evolutionary relationships of XTHs polypeptides from the </p>

<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2025 </p>

<p>partial banana cDNA and those from rice, tomato, and 
Arabidopsis (Fig. 2). Our data showed an organization of 
XTH proteins into two major clusters (I and II) as observed 
with rice XTH proteins (Yokoyama et al., 2004), another 
monocotyledonous species as banana. A classification into 
four XTH families was observed in Arabidopsis, tomato, 
two dicotyledonous species, and in a broad range of plant 
species (Nishitani, 1997; Campbell and Braam, 1999; Rose  et al., 2002; Saladié et al., 2006). Compared with this 
organization, our data indicated that cluster II mainly 
consisted of XTH proteins of family 2 of dicotyledons 
together with MaXTH4 and MaXTH9. Cluster I can be 
divided into two subclusters. The first one included 
MaXET1 and MaXET2, and MaXTH3, MaXTH5, 
MaXTH6, MaXTH7, and MaXTH8. It mainly consisted of 
XTH proteins of families 3 and 4 of dicotyledons. The 
second one mainly consisted of XTH proteins of families 1 
and 2 of dicotyledons. </p>

<p>Cloning MaPME genes from banana fruit and 
sequences analysis </p>

<p>Three genes encoding a putative banana PME polypeptide 
have been isolated by Musa sequence data mining. Musa 
EST sequences produced one partial cDNA sequence 
(MaPME1 accession number FJ264505). A similarity search 
in available Musa BAC sequences produced two BAC 
sequences: MaC077E20 (GenBank accession number 
AC226050) and MaC088K20 (GenBank accession number 
AC226051) of 177 729 bp and 152 711 bp, respectively. 
Automatic and manual annotation of these BACs showed 
that they contained 26 and 19 predicted genes in addition to 
1 and 3 repetitive elements, respectively. The two BACs 
sequences are schematically shown in Supplementary Fig. S2 
at JXB online. They are collinear and share an overlapping 
region of 130 kbp. Both sequences contained one common 
identical putative PME gene (MaPME2). MaC077E20 
contained an additional putative PME gene (MaPME3). 
Only the putative complete MaPME2 and MaPME3 genes 
from BAC MaCO77E20 were subsequently used in this 
study. The features of MaPME cDNAs and genomic 
sequences are described in Table 1A. The putative promoter 
regions of both MaPME2 and MaPME3 genes were 
analysed. They contained numerous cis-regulatory sequences 
that might be involved in tissue-specific or developmentally-
regulated gene expression (see Supplementary Table S2 at 
JXB online). A sulphur-responsive element that contains the 
auxin-response factor (ARF) binding sequence (GAGACA) 
and the copper/O 2 -reponsive element appeared to be specific 
to MaPME2 and MaPME3 promoter sequences, respectively. 
The predicted coding region of MaPME1 cDNA, 
MaPME2 and MaPME3 genomic sequences were com-
pared at both nucleotide and polypeptide levels (Table 1B). 
MaPME2 and MaPME3 genes shared 7% identity at the 
nucleotide level, while at the amino acid level, they showed 
38% and 56% identity and similarity, respectively. Com-
pared to MaPME1 cDNA, MaPME2 and MaPME3 
genomic sequences diverged at the nucleotide level. Indeed, </p>

<p>the high percentage of identity (75%) observed between 
these sequences is not significant as it was obtained in 
a short portion of their nucleotide sequence, as shown by 
the low Scov and Qcov values (less than 10% with 
MaPME2 and 25% with MaPME3). At the polypeptide 
level, MaPME2 and MaPME3 shared 46% and 60% 
identity and similarity, respectively, with polypeptides 
predicted from MaPME1 cDNA. The predicted polypep-
tides of the three MaPME genes presented features that are 
conserved in all PME polypeptides. Among these, there are 
the pre-and pro-sequences at the N-terminal extension, and 
five polypeptide segments that are characteristic of the 
C-terminal catalytic region, which constitutes the mature 
PME enzyme: GxYxE, QAVAL, QDTL, DFIFG, LGRPW 
(Micheli, 2001; Markovic and Janecek, 2004; see Supple-
mentary Fig. S2 at JXB online). The pre-region or signal 
peptide required for protein targeting to the endoplasmic 
reticulum is cleaved in the first step of maturation. Accord-
ing to the SignalP 3.0 program (Bendtsen et al., 2004); it 
was localized between amino acid residues 24-25 and 27-28 
for MaPME2 and MaPME3, respectively. Pro-sequence 
cleavage of the covalently attached mature enzyme may 
occur in the second step of maturation close to the 
RR(K)LL(M) motif (Markovic and Janecek, 2004; see 
Supplementary Fig. S2 at JXB online), thus leading to pro-
sequence lengths of 200 and 217 amino acid residues for 
MaPME2 and MaPME3, respectively. Based on the 
Arabidopsis PME sequence analysis, PME genes have been 
classified into two types: type I and II, having a long 
N-terminal pro-region and a short or absent pro-region, 
respectively. The role of the pro-region is currently un-
known (Micheli, 2001; Markovic and Janecek, 2004;  Giovane et al., 2004; Pelloux, 2007). The long N-terminal 
pro-sequence of MaPME2 and MaPME3 predicted poly-
peptides suggests that both genes belong to type I. </p>

<p>Expression of pectolytic genes in peel tissues from 
control and drop zones during banana fruit ripening </p>

<p>Three classes of pectolytic genes were examined in peel 
tissue during banana fruit ripening and in relation to finger 
drop. Among these, three genes encode pectin methylester-
ase MaPME1 to MaPME3, four encode polygalacturonase 
(MaPG1 to MaPG4; Asif and Nath, 2005), two encode 
pectate lyase (MaPEL1 and MaPEL2; Dominguez-Puigjaner 
et al., 1997; Pua et al., 2001), and four encode expansin 
protein (MaEXP1, 2, 4, and 5; Sane et al., 2007). Gene 
expression experiments were performed in triplicate on two 
independent RNA extracts and gave the same results. 
Pectolytic genes examined in his study were differentially 
expressed during ripening and in both the control and drop 
zones (Fig. 3). MaPEL1 and MaPEL2, and MaPG4 genes 
were the most expressed genes compared with the others. 
Among the three MaPME genes, MaPME1 was the least 
expressed in peel tissue compared with the other two. Its 
expression decreased during ripening in both zones (Fig. 3A). 
By contrast, MaPME2 was the most expressed in the drop 
zone. In the control zone, its mRNA level remained </p>



<p>Fig. 2. Phylogenetic alignment of banana, tomato, Arabidopsis, and rice xyloglucan endotransglycosylase/hydrolases (XTHs). The 
regions in common between the XTH polypeptide sequences of banana (MaXTHn and MaXETn), tomato (SlXTHn), Arabidopsis (AtXTHn), 
and rice were used to contruct a phylogenetic tree using the <rs type="software">ClustalX</rs> program. The resulting slanted cladogram was visualized with the 
TREEVIEW program (Page, 1996). The sequences were grouped into two distinct groups (I-II). The numbers 1 to 4 indicate the four 
families groups identified in tomato and Arabidopsis and applied to a broad range of plant species (Nishitani, 1997; Campbell and  Braam, 1999; Rose et al., 2002; Saladié et al., 2006). The tomato and Arabidopsis thaliana XTH sequences used in this study are 
available online at http://labs.plantbio.cornell.edu/XTH/genes.htm. The rice XTHs were retrieved from the Rice genome research program 
(http://RiceGAAS.dna.affrc.go.jp, 7 February 2009) and are indicated in the cladogram by their gene number assigned by RiceGAAS. 
Banana MaXET1 and MaXET2 have been registered in GenBank under accession numbers EF103137 and EF103136, respectively. </p>

<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2027 </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Expression of banana pectolytic genes in banana peel tissue from the control and drop zones. Quantitative real-time PCR (RT-
qPCR) was used to analyse mRNA accumulation of banana pectolytic genes, including pectin methylesterase (A), pectate lyase (B), and 
polygalacturonase (C) in peel tissue sampled from the middle area (control zone) and rupture area (drop zone). The y-axis represents the 
relative fold difference in mRNA level and was calculated using the 2 
-DDCt formula (Livak and Schmittgen, 2001) with actin as reference. </p>

<p>The mRNA fold difference was relative to that of fruit taken at harvest time (Ht) used as calibrator. Each data point is the mean of values 
obtained from qPCR reactions performed in triplicate on one cDNA sample. Each sample was prepared from four fruits from three 
replicate bunches. Two biological experiments were performed and they gave similar results. Vertical bars indicate standard deviation 
(SD). When no bar is shown, the SD is smaller than the symbol. </p>



<p>constant during the first 6 d after ripening induction. A 
slight increase was only observed in overripe fruit taken 7 
d after ripening induction. In the drop zone and from day 1 
after ripening induction to day 6, the MaPME2 mRNA 
level was approximately 2-fold increased on average, 
compared with the control zone, with a maximum 3-fold 
increase observed 2 d after ripening induction and a mini-
mum observed in overripe fruit taken 7 d after ripening 
induction. During ripening, no marked changes were 
observed on the MaPME3 mRNA level in both control 
and drop zones, except at the late ripening stage when 
MaPME3 mRNA accumulated approximately 2-fold more 
in the control zone than in the drop zone. 
From day 1 to day 7 after ripening induction, both 
MaPEL1 and MaPEL2 mRNA levels increased drastically 
and continuously in the control zone (Fig. 3B). One day 
after ripening induction, MaPEL1 and MaPEL2 mRNA 
were 2-fold more expressed in the drop zone than in the 
control zone. The time-course of both MaPEL1 and 
MaPEL2 mRNA presented a transient decrease (4-fold) in 
the drop zone at day 2 after ripening induction. Thereafter, 
transcripts of both MaPEL genes increased to reach a level 
comparable with that of the control zone at day 3 for 
MaPEL2 and 4 for MaPEL1, respectively. 
Concerning polygalacturonase genes, the four cDNAs 
previously isolated in banana present, at nucleotide level, 
a high percentage of identity. MaPG1 and MaPG2 were 
98% identical, although MaPG1 has an additional 160 bp. 
MaPG3 and MaPG4 were over 90% identical while MaPG2 
and MaPG3 were only 30% identical (Asif and Nath, 2005). 
Despite this, a set of qPCR primers was designed, as specific 
as possible, for each MaPG gene. For MaPG1 that spans 
the entire MaPG2 cDNA, primers were designed within the 
additional 160 bp in the 3#-UTR. For MaPG2, there was 
a failure to identify a divergent region with MaPG1 to 
design a specific MaPG2 primer. Nevertheless, MaPG1 and 
MaPG2 displayed quite different accumulation patterns, 
suggesting that putative cross amplification of the MaPG1 
gene with the MaPG2 primer set would not have interfered 
during the gene expression analysis. No marked changes 
were observed on MaPG1 gene expression during fruit 
ripening in both the control and drop zones (Fig. 3C). In 
the control zone, the time-course of MaPG2 mRNA 
accumulation increased during ripening from day 1 to day 
4 after ripening induction and decreased thereafter. A 
similar pattern was observed for MaPG2 in the drop zone, 
except for a marked but transient decrease (2-fold) observed 
at day 2 after ripening induction. The mRNA level of the 
MaPG3 gene decreased during ripening in the same manner 
in both the control and drop zones until day 6 after ripening 
induction. In overripe fruit taken at day 7, this level was 
approximately 10-fold higher in the control zone than in the 
drop zone. However, this level remained comparable to that 
of green fruit sampled at harvest. Finally, concerning 
MaPG4, the corresponding transcript was drastically in-
duced in the control zone during the late ripening stages, 
namely 5, 6, and 7 d after ripening induction. In the drop 
zone, two peaks of MaPG4 mRNA accumulation were </p>

<p>observed. The first one occurred 1 d after ripening in-
duction, with approximately 400-fold more expression in 
the drop zone than in the control zone, and the second one, 
during the late ripening stage, began at day 5 after ripening 
induction and reached its maximum at day 7, but at a 2-fold 
lower level than in the control zone. </p>

<p>Expression of MaXTH genes in peel tissues from control 
and drop zones during banana fruit ripening </p>

<p>In addition to the two XET genes, namely MaXET1 and 
MaXET2, previously isolated from banana fruit (Lu et al.,  2004), seven other cDNA sequences were isolated in this 
study. In accordance with the nomenclature proposed by 
Rose et al. (2002), these cDNAs were named MaXTH3 to 
MaXTH9. Specific primers designed within the 3#-UTR 
regions of each XET and XTH genes were used to examine 
the corresponding gene expression throughout qPCR anal-
ysis. Figure 4 shows the expression pattern in the drop and 
control zones of the nine XTH genes during banana fruit 
ripening. Except for MaXTH4, all other XTHs examined in 
this study were induced at different magnitudes in banana 
peel tissue, in the control and drop zones. In the control 
zone, MaXET1 mRNA was transiently induced during 
ripening with maximum expression observed 4 d after 
ripening induction; in line with previous Northern blot data 
reported in banana (Lu et al., 2004). Four XTH genes 
(MaXET1, MaXTH6, MaXTH8, and MaXTH9) were 
highly induced at the transcriptional level in the drop zone 
as compared to the control zone. However, this induction 
was transient, with a maximum of mRNA accumulation 
observed 3-4 d after ripening induction. MaXTH9 was the 
most highly and transiently expressed as compared to the 
four others, while MaXTH8 expression decreased slowly 
during the late ripening stage. By contrast, two XTH genes 
(MaXTH3 and MaXTH5) were more highly and differen-
tially expressed in the control zone than in the drop zone. 
MaXTH3 was transiently induced in the control zone with 
a maximum observed 3 d after ripening induction, while in 
the drop zone no marked change was observed during post-
harvest ripening. MaXTH5 was less expressed in the drop 
zone compared to the control zone. In this area, MaXTH5 
presented two peaks of expression at days 3 and 7 after 
ripening, respectively. In the control zone, MaXET2 and 
MaXTH7 mRNA accumulation peaked twice at days 2 and 
7, and at days 2 and 4 after ripening induction, respectively. 
In the drop zone, a high mRNA accumulation of MaXET2 
and MaXTH7 genes was transient at days 4 and 3 after 
ripening induction, respectively. At this ripening stage, both 
genes were highly expressed in the drop zone compared to 
the control. </p>

<p>Expression of MaEXP genes in peel tissues from 
control-and drop zones, during banana fruit ripening </p>

<p>Based on five sequences of expansin genes already isolated 
from banana fruit (Trivedi and Nath, 2004; Sane et al.,  2007), specific primers were designed from the </p>

<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2029 </p>

<p>corresponding 3#-UTR regions and used to examine expan-
sin gene expression in both the control and drop zones (Fig. 
5). Except for MaEXP3, from which there was a failure to 
get a single PCR product, the four other expansin genes 
were differentially expressed in control and drop zone </p>

<p>tissues. By contrast with those of MaEXP2, mRNAs of 
MaEXP1, MaEXP4, and MaEXP5 accumulated to a greater 
extent in the drop zone than in the control zone. MaEXP2 
mRNA presented a different accumulation pattern in both 
the control and drop zones as compared to the three other </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Expression of banana XTH genes in banana peel tissue from the control and drop zones. Quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR) 
was used to analyse the mRNA accumulation of banana xyloglucan transglycosylase/hydrolase genes in peel tissue sampled from the 
middle area (control zone) and rupture area (drop zone). The y-axis represents the relative fold difference in mRNA level and was 
calculated using the 2 
-DDCT formula (Livak and Schmittgen, 2001), with actin as reference. The mRNA fold difference was relative to that </p>

<p>of fruit taken at harvest time (Ht) used as calibrator. Each data point is the mean of values obtained from qPCR reactions performed in 
triplicate on one cDNA sample. Each sample was prepared from four fruits from three replicate bunches. Two biological experiments 
were performed and they gave similar results. Vertical bars indicate standard deviation (SD). When no bar is shown, the SD is smaller 
than the symbol. </p>



<p>expansin genes analysed in this study. In the control zone, 
its mRNA began to accumulate 1 d after ripening induction 
and increased drastically (approximately 20-34-fold) until 
day 4 after ripening induction, when it peaked. Then this 
level slightly decreased at days 5 and 6, before increasing (2-
fold) at day 7 after ripening induction. In the drop zone, 
MaEXP2 mRNA accumulated continuously from days 1 to 
6 after ripening induction, where it peaked before de-
creasing at day 7. Compared to the pattern in the control 
zone, MaEXP2 was on average 1.3-20-fold less expressed in 
the drop zone during post-harvest ripening, except at day 6 
where this expression was comparable in the two tissues. 
MaEXP1 mRNA sharply accumulated (480-fold) 1 d after 
ripening induction. This level decreased at day 2 to reach 
a level comparable to that of the control zone before 
increasing transiently, on average 2-fold more, from days 
4-6. At day 7, the MaEXP1 mRNA level had reduced to 
a level comparable to that of the control zone. A marked 
increase in the MaEXP4 mRNA level was observed during 
the late ripening stages, namely 4, 5, and 6 d after ripening 
induction before decreasing approximately 3-fold at day 7 
after ripening induction. Compared to the control zone and 
except at the last ripening stage (day 7), MaEXP4 mRNA 
accumulated, on average, 2-fold more in the drop zone after 
ripening, even during the first ripening stages (1-3 d after 
ripening induction), while this level was constant in the 
drop zone. In the drop zone, MaEXP5 gene expression was 
transiently induced until day 4 after ripening induction, 
where it peaked before decreasing during the last three </p>

<p>ripening stages. The same pattern was observed in the 
control zone, except that (i) peak mRNA accumulation was 
observed 3 d after ripening induction, and (ii) with a 2-fold 
increase at the last ripening stage (day 7). Compared to the 
control zone, the MaEXP5 mRNA level was higher in the 
drop zone except at the last ripening stage. </p>

<p>Discussion </p>

<p>In the work described here, changes in the expression of 
various CWMGs (cell wall modifying genes) were examined 
in relationship with the banana finger drop process. This 
study was primarily aimed at identifying genes whose 
expression in the drop zone could be linked to the cell wall 
disassembly and property changes observed during banana 
ripening and finger drop by Imsabai et al. (2006) and 
Saengpook et al. (2007). 
Current evidence suggests that cellulose disassembly is 
not a significant contributor to cell wall disassembly during 
fruit ripening (Fisher and Bennett, 1991; Newman and  Redgwell, 2002; Bennett and Labavitch, 2008). Therefore, 
our molecular studies were focused on pectolytic and 
hemicellulosic genes and those involved in physical cell wall 
properties. Taken together, our data indicated that cell wall 
changes that occur in the finger drop area involve major 
cell wall components, including xyloglucan and pectin, and 
also cell wall physical properties, namely cell wall loosening 
mediated by expansin. Overall, major changes in cell wall </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Expression of expansin genes in banana peel tissue from the control and drop zones. Quantitative real-time PCR (RT-qPCR) was 
used to analyse the mRNA accumulation of banana expansin genes in peel tissue sampled from the middle area (control zone) and 
rupture area (drop zone). The y-axis represents the relative fold difference in mRNA level and was calculated using the 2 
-DDCt formula </p>

<p>(Livak and Schmittgen, 2001) with actin as reference. The mRNA fold difference was relative to that of fruit taken at harvest time (Ht) 
used as calibrator. Each data point is the mean of values obtained from qPCR reactions performed in triplicate on one cDNA sample. 
Each sample was prepared from four fruits originated from three replicate bunches. Two biological experiments were performed and they 
gave similar results. Vertical bars indicate standard deviation (SD). When no bar is shown, the SD is smaller than the symbol. </p>

<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2031 </p>

<p>modifying gene expression occurred 1-4 d after ripening 
induction, but in a sequential manner. Firstly, there were 
changes in the expression of pectolytic and cell wall 
loosening genes, mainly during days 1-2, followed by those 
of xyloglucan genes, mainly during days 3-4. Moreover, 
within each mechanism, there was also sequential induction 
of the different genes involved. 
The results of a comparative analysis of CWMG expres-
sion in drop and control zones allows the selection of 
candidate genes involved in the finger drop process. 
Assuming that the activity of CWMGs examined in this 
study such as PEL or PG are mainly regulated at the 
transcriptional level in banana (Pathak and Sanwal, 1998;  Marin-Rodriguez et al., 2003; Lohani et al., 2004), it is 
considered that CWMGs expressed more in the drop zone 
than in the control zone were candidates. 
A positive correlation was obtained between the banana 
cultivar prone to finger drop and PEL activity (Imsabai  et al., 2006). Both MaPEL1 and MaPEL2, whose mRNA 
levels increased by 2-fold and 1.6-fold in the drop zone, 
possibly induced this increased PEL activity in the drop 
zone. Therefore, both MaPEL1 and MaPEL2 genes could 
be considered as candidates. Imsabai et al. (2006) reported 
that no clear change in PG activity was correlated with the 
finger drop process, and that PME activity does not 
account for the breakage of pectin associated with the 
finger drop process. Despite this, MaPME2 and MaPG4 
could also be considered as putative candidates of finger 
drop based on the marked change in their mRNA 
accumulation in the drop zone relative to the control zone. 
The discrepancy between PG and PME gene expression and 
activities could be explained by post-transcriptional regula-
tion of the activation of enzyme activity or subcellular 
localization (targeting cell walls). It is also possible that the 
PG and PME activities reported by Imsabai et al. (2006)  might represent global activities that do not reflect a puta-
tive change in the activity of the different PG and PME 
isoforms. Note that the PG enzyme activity measured 
during banana fruit ripening suggested that more than the 
three identified isoforms might exist in fruit (Pathak and  Sanwal, 1998; Pathak et al., 2000). For other cell wall 
components, MaEXP1, MaEXP4, and MaEXP5 genes 
appeared to be the main candidates involved in cell wall 
loosening related to finger drop, with MaEXP1 being the 
main one, while MaXET1, MaXET2, MaXTH6, MaXTH7, 
MaXTH8, and MaXTH9 appeared to be candidates for 
xyloglucan metabolism. 
XTH proteins can display two distinct enzymatic activities, 
including transglycosylase enzymatic (XET) activity leading 
to xyloglycan chain synthesis or xyloglucan hydrolase activity 
(XEH) resulting in their degradation. These two activities are 
not correlated with the protein structure and subsequently 
with the XTH protein organization (Rose et al., 2002; Fry  2005; Saladié et al., 2006). On the other hand, the in-
volvement of cell wall synthesis, including the xyloglucan 
component, throughout ripening and mainly between mature 
green and turning stages prior to perceptible softening, have 
been reported in tomato, i.e. another fleshy fruit like banana </p>

<p>(Mitcham et al., 1989, 1991; Greve and Labavitch; 1991;  Huysamer et al., 1997; Rose and Bennett, 1999). Because the 
XTH gene expression and phylogenetic data reported in this 
study do not presume the activity and the function of 
corresponding proteins, the involvement of both xyloglucan 
synthesis and degradation mediated by XTH proteins in the 
finger drop process cannot therefore be excluded. 
Cell wall modification that occurs during the ripening 
process is complex. Although the data reported here 
highlight the involvement of the main cell wall modification 
enzymes, including PG, PEL, XTHs, and EXP, the 
possibility cannot be overlooked that, other secondary but 
important enzymes (b-galactosidase or a-L-arabinofuranosi-
dase) or non-enzymatic mechanisms such as cell wall 
solubilization (Dumville and Fry, 2003; Zhuang et al.,  2006, 2007) could be involved in the finger drop process. 
Ethylene production and fruit softening are two main 
features that characterize the ripening process of climacteric 
and fleshy fruit like banana. Our data suggested that finger 
drop could be related to these two processes. Indeed, finger 
drop implies transcriptional changes in genes that are also 
involved in fruit softening. However, some genes seem to 
be specific to softening (MaXTH5, MaXTH3, and 
MaEXP2), finger drop (MaPME2, MaEXP1, MaEXP4, 
and MaEXP5, MaXTH6, MaXTH8, and MaXTH9), or 
both (MaPG4, MaPEL1, and MaPEL2; MaXET1, 
MaXET2, and MaXTH7). Moreover, the two processes 
seem to be quite distinct in this variety, as shown by the 
type of genes involved and their sequential induction, with 
finger drop being the main induced process followed by 
softening. Regarding ethylene, our data showed that 
Cavendish banana fruit developed finger drop mainly 
during the early stage of fruit ripening (days 1-4), a period 
corresponding to a burst of ethylene production. Concom-
itantly, a high level of transcription of some ripening-and 
ethylene-dependent genes like MaEXP1 and MaPELs (Pua  et al., 2001; Trivedi and Nath, 2004) was also observed. It 
would be interesting to examine the relationship between 
ethylene production during ripening and the finger drop 
process. Does the specific induction of the banana finger 
drop process involve, at molecular level, ethylene production 
and/or require the ethylene transduction pathway or not? 
In conclusion, the data reported here represent a sub-
stantial contribution towards understanding the post-
harvest banana finger drop phenomenon at the molecular 
level. More specifically, the identification of several cell 
wall-modifying genes with expression profiles related to 
finger drop provided us with good candidates for functional 
studies in banana species. These candidate genes could be 
useful in molecular breeding schemes for banana improve-
ment using cultivars differing in their proneness to develop 
finger drop and which are currently being assessed. </p>

<p>Supplementary data </p>

<p>Supplementary data can be found at JXB online. 
Table S1. Sequences of primers used in this study. </p>



<p>Table S2. Different cis-regulatory elements found within 
the promoter of MaPME2 and MaPME3 genomic sequences. 
Fig. S1. Multiple sequence alignment of polypeptide 
sequences of banana XTH genes. 
Fig. S2. BAC localization and structure of banana PME 
genes and multiple sequence alignment of polypeptide 
sequences. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements </p>

<p>This research was supported by the DOCUP (Document 
Unique de Programmation) 2000-2006 fund and The 
Generation Challenge Program (GCP-SP2-project no. 15). </p>



<p>Expression of cell wall-modifying genes from banana and finger drop process | 2033 </p>





</text></tei>