<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2638544" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.2-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-10-20T00:54+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>10 areas are all sites with deidentified birth certificate infor-
mation on parental age and other relevant variables included in 
the Network database and include sites in Alabama, Arizona, 
Arkansas, Colorado, Georgia, Maryland, Missouri, New Jersey, 
North Carolina, and Wisconsin. 
The cohort serving as the comparison group includes all 
livebirths to mothers residing in any 1 of the study areas in 
1994, with complete information available from birth cer-
tificates on maternal and paternal age, birth order, and 
other variables. We used 2 data sources to construct the 
cohort: 1994 deidentified birth records for the Wisconsin 
study area provided by the Wisconsin Department of 
Health and Family Services and, for the remaining sites, 
the National Center for Health Statistics public use natality 
data files (9). The public use file includes county of resi-
dence for births in densely populated counties, which en-
abled us to ascertain deidentified birth information for all 
births in most of the counties. We were unable to precisely 
obtain counts of births occurring in sparsely populated 
counties in which 13,043 (4.1%) of the study-area births 
occurred in 1994. For these counties, we obtained county-
level aggregate information on the total number of births in 
1994 and their distribution by variables such as maternal 
marital status, ethnicity, and age and selected a stratified 
random sample of deidentified birth records (equal in num-
ber and similar in distribution by maternal marital status, 
ethnicity, and age to all livebirths occurring in the respec-
tive counties in 1994) from sparsely populated counties of 
the state in which the study area was located. The full co-
hort included 326,785 livebirths, of which 73,438 (22.5%) </p>

<p>were excluded because of missing paternal age. The cohort 
serving as the comparison group thus included the 253,347 
livebirths with complete information on parental age and 
other key variables (Table 1). 
The total number of children aged 8 years residing in the 
study areas in 2002 determined by the Autism and 
Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network surveillance 
system to have an ASD was 2,142. Birth certificate infor-
mation was available for 1,517 (70.8%) of these children, 
who were born in the same state as their state of residence in 
2002. The remaining 29.2% of cases were excluded from 
this analysis because of missing birth certificate informa-
tion. The case group for the present analysis was further 
restricted to the 1,251 children (58.4% of the total ASD case 
group) for whom information on both parents' age as well as 
birth order and gestational age was available. Our final sam-
ple was comparable to the total population of ASD cases 
regarding demographic factors and ASD case characteristics 
(Table 1). </p>

<p>Case definition </p>

<p>ASDs include behaviorally defined neurodevelopmental 
disorders diagnosed through clinical observation, and they 
encompass impairments in social, communicative, and be-
havioral development, often accompanied by abnormalities 
in intellectual functioning, learning, attention, and sensory 
processing. For this study, children with ASD included 
members of the birth cohort residing in the study area in 
2002 who met Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental </p>

<p>Table 1. Characteristics of the 1994 Birth Cohort and ASD Cases, 10 Study Sites From the US Centers for Disease 
Control and Prevention's Autism and Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network </p>

<p>Full Birth 
Cohort: All 
Livebirths in 
the 10 Study 
Areas </p>

<p>Birth Cohort 
With Complete 
Information on 
Parental Age </p>

<p>All Children 
Aged 8 Years 
With ASD 
Residing in 
the 10 Study 
Areas in 2002 </p>

<p>ASD Cases 
With Any Birth 
Certificate 
Information </p>

<p>ASD Cases 
With Complete 
Information on 
Parental Age </p>

<p>No. (%) 
326,785 (100) 253,347 (77.5) 2,142 (100) 
1,517 (70.8) 
1,251 (58.4) </p>

<p>Median maternal age, years 
27 
28 
29 
29 </p>

<p>Median paternal age, years 
30 
31 </p>

<p>Maternal age &lt;20 years, % 
13.8 
8.5 
8.0 
5.4 </p>

<p>Maternal age 35 years, % 
10.9 
12.6 
16.2 
17.2 </p>

<p>Boys, % 
51.2 
51.4 
81.2 
81.7 
81.8 </p>

<p>White, % 
60.1 
67.6 
63.1 
65.5 
69.0 </p>

<p>Black, % 
23.7 
16.5 
22.1 
22.7 
17.2 </p>

<p>Hispanic, % 
12.0 
11.1 
10.5 
9.3 
9.2 </p>

<p>Gestational age &lt;37 weeks, % 9.8 
8.7 
13.6 
12.5 </p>

<p>Gestational age &lt;28 weeks, % 0.8 
0.6 
1.9 
1.5 </p>

<p>Autistic disorder, % 
81.0 
80.8 
80.7 </p>

<p>Confirmed intellectual 
impairment, % a </p>

<p>32.4 
32.7 
30.9 </p>

<p>Confirmed normal 
intelligence, % a </p>

<p>43.2 
42.1 
43.2 </p>

<p>Abbreviation: ASD, autism spectrum disorder. 
a Information to confirm intellectual functioning was missing for approximately 25% of ASD cases. </p>

<p>Parental Age and Autism 1269 </p>

<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>Disorders, Fourth Edition, Text Revision criteria for autistic 
disorder; pervasive developmental disorders-not otherwise 
specified (PDD-NOS (http://www.cdc.gov/ncbddd/autism/ 
overview_diagnostic_criteria.htm), including atypical au-
tism); or Asperger's disorder (10) based on a comprehensive 
review of educational and clinical records by trained clini-
cians. Children were classified by clinician reviewers as 
having an ASD if they had either a documented previous 
classification of ASD (65%) or an evaluation record from an 
educational or medical setting indicating unusual behaviors 
consistent with ASD (35%). For children previously identi-
fied as having an ASD, case status was confirmed on the 
basis of evaluation records. For children without a docu-
mented ASD classification, data were abstracted on all rel-
evant ASD and developmental behaviors from education or 
medical evaluations to determine whether behaviors de-
scribed in the evaluations by clinical reviewers were consis-
tent with the diagnostic criteria. Because case status was 
determined solely on the basis of information contained in 
evaluation records, and because Diagnostic and Statistical 
Manual of Mental Disorders, Fourth Edition, Text Revision 
criteria are less well defined for PDD-NOS than for autistic 
disorder, the surveillance protocol for determining whether 
a child could be classified as having PDD-NOS required 
documentation of at least 1 behavior considered to be an 
ASD discriminator, such as being oblivious to others when 
there is a clear social opportunity or demonstrating atypical 
and persistent focus on sensory input (11). 
Of the 1,251 ASD cases, 80.7% were determined to meet 
criteria for autistic disorder, while there was insufficient in-
formation for those remaining to distinguish between autis-
tic disorder, Asperger's disorder, or PDD-NOS. Information 
from standardized intelligence tests was available for ap-
proximately 75% of the ASD cases. On the basis of this 
information, children with ASD were classified as having 
intellectual impairment (an IQ of &lt;70) versus normal in-
telligence. Further details regarding the 2002 Autism and 
Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network sample 
and methodology have been reported previously (8, 11). </p>

<p>Analytic strategy and statistical methods </p>

<p>Potential for confounding effects of birth order, gender, 
and other variables was evaluated by first examining un-
adjusted associations between each potential confounder and 
the independent variables of maternal and paternal age as 
well as the dependent variable, ASD case status. Variables 
were considered to be potentially confounding factors if 
they were associated with both parental age and ASD. Un-
adjusted odds ratios with confidence intervals were com-
puted to evaluate the magnitude of these associations, and 
unconditional logistic regression models were fit to estimate 
adjusted odds ratios and 95% confidence intervals. Statisti-
cal significance was evaluated by using chi-square tests for 
categorical variables and analysis of variance for continuous 
variables. 
To enhance the comparability of our findings with those 
from other studies, we fit 2 types of models, 1 with parental 
ages categorized into 6 categories: &lt;20, 20-24, 25-29, 30-34, 
35-39, 40 years; and the other with parental age as a con-</p>

<p>tinuous variable with the odds ratio scaled to reflect a 10-year 
difference in age (4). Although we found the association 
between parental age and autism risk to be similar across 
the 10 sites, to adjust for potential site-to-site variability we 
included site dummy variables in all multivariable models. 
To evaluate interaction or modifying effects of each covariate 
and of ASD subtypes on the associations between parental 
age and ASD, we performed stratified analyses. We also tested 
interaction terms for maternal age by paternal age and 2-way 
and 3-way interaction terms for each parent's age by the other 
covariates in the regression models, but we identified no 
significant interactions. <rs id="software-0" type="software">SAS</rs> version <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">9.1.3</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute, Inc.</rs>., Cary, North Carolina) was used for all statis-
tical analyses. 
This research involved secondary analysis of deidentified 
data and was approved by the University of Wisconsin 
Institutional Review Board. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>In unadjusted analyses, both mean maternal age and mean 
paternal age were significantly higher for ASD cases than 
for the birth cohort as a whole (Table 2). Table 2 also shows 
that mean parental ages differed significantly in unadjusted 
analyses across categories of birth order, maternal educa-
tion, ethnicity, multiple birth, gestational age, and birth 
weight for gestational age, but not for gender. With parental 
age 25-29 years as the reference group, the odds of develop-
ing ASD was significantly reduced for parental age &lt;20 years 
and increased for maternal age 35 and paternal age 40 
years (Table 3, unadjusted odds ratios). We therefore used 
these age cutoffs (maternal age 35, paternal age 40 years) 
to classify each parent's age as ''older'' versus ''younger.'' 
Other significant predictors of ASD in unadjusted analyses 
included low birth order, male gender, advanced maternal 
education, and preterm birth (Table 3). </p>

<p>Multivariable analysis of parental ages modeled as 
categorical variables </p>

<p>After we adjusted for the other parent's age and other 
covariates, the increases in ASD risk associated with mater-
nal age 35 years and paternal age 40 years (relative to 
age 25-29 years) were slightly reduced compared with the 
unadjusted analysis (Table 3). In contrast, the results for 
birth order suggest that the decline in ASD risk associated 
with increasing birth order is somewhat stronger in the ad-
justed analysis than in the unadjusted analysis (Table 3). In 
addition, the apparent increase in ASD risk associated with 
higher levels of maternal education in the unadjusted anal-
ysis is no longer evident in the adjusted model, suggesting 
that the apparent maternal education effect is due to its 
association with parental age (Table 3). </p>

<p>Parental ages modeled as continuous variables </p>

<p>In unadjusted analyses, the risk of developing ASD in-
creased significantly with each 10-year increase in both ma-
ternal age and paternal age. After adjustment for age of the </p>

<p>1270 Durkin et al. </p>

<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>other parent and other covariates, each 10-year increase in 
maternal age was associated with a 20% increase in ASD 
risk (odds ratio ¼ 1.2, 95% confidence interval: 1.1, 1.4) 
while each 10-year increase in paternal age was associated 
with a 30% increase in ASD risk (odds ratio ¼ 1.3, 95% 
confidence interval: 1.1, 1.5). </p>

<p>Combined effects of parental age and birth order </p>

<p>The risk of ASD within each of 3 parental age categories 
(both parents ''younger,'' 1 parent ''older,'' and both parents 
''older'') was highest among firstborn children and declined 
with increasing birth order (Table 4). Considering the </p>

<p>Table 2. Unadjusted Mean Maternal and Paternal Ages at Delivery for ASD Cases Compared 
With the Cohort as a Whole, and in the Cohort as a Whole Stratified by Covariate Categories, 
1994 Birth Cohort From 10 Study Sites From the US Centers for Disease Control and 
Prevention's Autism and Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network </p>

<p>No. 
% </p>

<p>Mean Age, years </p>

<p>Maternal 
Paternal </p>

<p>ASD case status </p>

<p>ASD cases 
1,251 
29.0 a 
31.4 a </p>

<p>Birth cohort (comparison group) 
253,347 
28.0 a 
30.1 a </p>

<p>Birth order </p>

<p>1st 
105,140 
41.3 
26.1 a 
28.3 a </p>

<p>2nd 
88,065 
34.6 
28.5 a 
30.7 a </p>

<p>3rd 
39,902 
15.7 
30.0 a 
32.0 a </p>

<p>4th 
21,491 
8.4 
31.5 a 
33.5 a </p>

<p>Gender </p>

<p>Boys 
131,258 
51.6 
28.0 
30.2 </p>

<p>Girls 
123,340 
48.4 
28.0 
30.1 </p>

<p>Maternal education </p>

<p>&lt;High school 
37,377 
14.7 
23.1 a 
26.2 a </p>

<p>High school graduate 
83,093 
32.8 
26.8 a 
29.1 a </p>

<p>Some college 
60,105 
23.7 
28.5 a 
30.6 a </p>

<p>4-year college graduate 
73,302 
29.0 
31.4 a 
33.0 a </p>

<p>Child's race/ethnicity </p>

<p>Non-Hispanic white 
172,148 
67.6 
28.7 a 
30.7 a </p>

<p>Non-Hispanic black 
42,133 
16.6 
26.2 a 
28.6 a </p>

<p>Hispanic 
28,309 
11.1 
26.3 a 
28.6 a </p>

<p>Other and mixed 
12,008 
4.7 
28.3 a 
31.1 a </p>

<p>Multiple birth </p>

<p>Singleton 
247,329 
97.1 
27.9 a 
30.1 a </p>

<p>Multiple 
7,269 
2.9 
29.5 a 
31.5 a </p>

<p>Gestational age, weeks </p>

<p>&lt;28 
1,566 
0.6 
27.7 a 
29.7 a </p>

<p>28-36 
20,652 
8.1 
27.9 a 
30.0 a </p>

<p>37-41 
226,128 
88.8 
28.0 a 
30.2 a </p>

<p>&gt;41 
6,252 
2.5 
27.4 a 
29.6 a </p>

<p>Birth weight for gestational age b </p>

<p>&gt;2 SDs below the mean 
4,245 
1.7 
27.3 a 
29.8 a </p>

<p>1-2 SDs below the mean 
30,325 
11.9 
27.1 a 
29.5 a </p>

<p>Within 1 SD of the mean 
180,919 
71.1 
27.9 a 
30.1 a </p>

<p>1-2 SDs above the mean 
31,855 
12.5 
28.9 a 
30.9 a </p>

<p>&gt;2 SDs above the mean 
7,254 
2.9 
29.5 a 
31.6 a </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ASD, autism spectrum disorder; SD, standard deviation. 
a Analysis of variance across all strata for this variable P &lt; 0.0001. 
b Number of standard deviations from the mean birth weight at a given gestational age for each 
gender based on all 1994 US births. </p>

<p>Parental Age and Autism 1271 </p>

<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>Table 3. Distribution of ASD Cases and Birth Cohort Comparison Group by Parental Age Categories and Other Independent Variables, and 
Unadjusted and Adjusted Odds Ratios With 95% Confidence Intervals, 1994 Birth Cohort From 10 Study Sites From the US Centers for Disease 
Control and Prevention's Autism and Developmental Disabilities Monitoring Network </p>

<p>ASD Cases </p>

<p>Birth Cohort 
Comparison 
Group 
Unadjusted 
OR 
95% CI </p>

<p>Maternal Age 
at Delivery, 
years </p>

<p>Adjusted 
OR a 
95% CI </p>

<p>No. 
% 
No. 
% </p>

<p>Maternal age at delivery, years 
&lt;20 
67 
5.4 
21,507 
8.5 
0.6 b 
0.5, 0.8 
0.7 b 
0.5, 1.0 
20-24 
238 
19.0 
55,583 
21.9 
0.9 
0.7, 1.0 
0.9 
0.8, 1.1 
25-29 
366 
29.3 
75,053 
29.6 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
30-34 
365 
29.2 
69,357 
27.4 
1.1 
0.9, 1.2 
1.1 
0.9, 1.3 
35-39 
185 
14.8 
27,330 
10.8 
1.4 b 
1.2, 1.7 
35 c 
1.3 b 
1.1, 1.6 
40 
30 
2.4 
4,517 
1.8 
1.4 
0.9, 2.0 
Paternal age at delivery, years 
&lt;20 
26 
2.1 
9,734 
3.8 
0.6 b 
0.4, 0.8 
0.6 
0.4, 1.0 
20-24 
162 
13.0 
42,020 
16.6 
0.8 
0.7, 1.0 
0.9 
0.7, 1.1 
25-29 
322 
25.7 
67,080 
26.5 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
30-34 
379 
30.3 
75,179 
29.7 
1.1 
0.9, 1.2 
1.0 
0.9, 1.2 
35-39 
219 
17.5 
40,283 
15.9 
1.1 
1.0, 1.4 
1.0 
0.9, 1.3 
40 
143 
11.4 
19,051 
7.5 
1.6 b 
1.3, 1.9 
1.4 b 
1.1, 1.8 
Birth order 
1st 
588 
47.0 
104,552 
41.2 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
2nd 
425 
34.0 
87,640 
34.6 
0.9 
0.8, 1.0 
0.8 b 
0.7, 0.9 
3rd 
168 
13.4 
39,734 
15.7 
0.8 b 
0.6, 0.9 
0.6 b 
0.5, 0.8 
4th 
70 
5.6 
21,421 
8.5 
0.6 b 
0.5, 0.7 
0.5 b 
0.4, 0.6 
Gender 
Boys 
1,023 
81.8 
130,235 
51.4 
4.2 b 
3.7, 4.9 
4.2 b 
3.7, 4.9 
Girls 
228 
18.2 
123,112 
48.6 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
Maternal education 
&lt;High school 
136 
10.9 
37,241 
14.7 
0.8 b 
0.6, 0.9 
1.0 
0.8, 1.2 
High school graduate 
394 
31.5 
82,699 
32.6 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
Some college 
303 
24.2 
60,105 
23.7 
1.1 
0.9, 1.2 
1.0 
0.9, 1.2 
4-year college graduate 
418 
33.4 
73,302 
28.9 
1.2 b 
1.0, 1.4 
1.0 
0.9, 1.2 
Child's race/ethnicity 
Non-Hispanic white 
863 
69.0 
171,285 
67.6 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
Non-Hispanic black 
215 
17.2 
41,918 
16.5 
1.0 
0.9, 1.2 
1.0 
0.9, 1.2 
Hispanic 
115 
9.2 
28,194 
11.1 
0.8 
0.7, 1.0 
0.9 
0.7, 1.2 
Other and mixed 
58 
4.6 
11,950 
4.7 
1.0 
0.7, 1.3 
0.9 
0.7, 1.1 
Multiple birth 
Singleton 
1,209 
96.6 
246,120 
97.2 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
Multiple 
42 
3.3 
7,227 
2.8 
1.2 
0.9, 1.6 
1.0 
0.7, 1.4 
Gestational age, weeks 
&lt;28 
19 
1.5 
1,547 
0.6 
2.6 b 
1.7, 4.1 
2.5 b 
1.6, 3.9 
28-36 
137 
11.0 
20,515 
8.1 
1.4 b 
1.2, 1.7 
1.4 b 
1.2, 1.7 
37-41 
1,061 
84.8 
225,067 
88.8 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
&gt;41 
34 
2.7 
6,218 
2.5 
1.2 
0.8, 1.6 
1.1 
0.8, 1.5 
Birth weight for gestational age 
2 SDs below the mean 
22 
1.8 
4,223 
1.7 
1.1 
0.7, 1.6 
1.1 
0.7, 1.6 
1-2 SDs below the mean 
153 
12.3 
30,172 
11.9 
1.1 
0.9, 1.2 
1.1 
0.9, 1.3 
Within 1 SD of the mean 
874 
69.9 
180,045 
71.1 
1.0 
Reference 
1.0 
Reference 
1-2 SDs above the mean 
161 
12.9 
31,694 
12.5 
1.0 
0.8, 1.2 
1.0 
0.9, 1.3 
&gt;2 SDs above the mean 
41 
3.3 
7,213 
2.9 
1.2 
0.9, 1.6 
1.3 
0.9, 1.6 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ASD, autism spectrum disorder; CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio; SD, standard deviation. 
a Adjusted for all other variables in this column in addition to site indicators. 
b Odds ratios with confidence intervals that exclude 1.0. 
c Because the increased risk was similar for ages 35-39 and 40 years, the high-risk maternal age category was defined as 35 years. </p>



<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>combined effects of parental age and birth order, we excluded 
from the analysis births to mothers aged &lt;20 years and found 
the lowest risk group to be third-or later-born offspring of 
mothers aged 20-34 years and fathers aged &lt;40 years. Com-
pared with that for this group, the risk of ASD increased with 
both declining birth order and increasing number of older 
parents. The highest risk group included firstborn offspring 
of mothers aged 35 years and fathers aged 40 years, with 
a risk 3 times that of the reference group (Table 4). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Our findings are consistent with those recently reported 
from a large study of members of a California health main-
tenance organization (4) that found the risk of ASD to be 
positively and independently associated with both maternal 
and paternal age, with adjusted odds ratios nearly identical 
to those reported here. These findings contrast somewhat 
with 5 other recent epidemiologic studies that found only 
1 or neither parent's age to be associated with ASD risk after 
controlling for the other parent's age (2, 3, 12-14). 
The lack of consistency across studies could be due to 
limitations of sample size and of population representation 
of previous studies as well as other methodological differ-
ences, including autism case definitions and inclusion crite-
ria and the ability to control for important variables. The 
present study included a large sample of children with suf-
ficient information to enable evaluation of separate and 
combined effects of each parent's age as well as birth order 
and other variables. With more than 1,200 cases, it included 
over 50% more cases and thus more statistical power than 
any of the previous studies examining independent effects of 
maternal and paternal age on ASD risk. 
Another advantage of this study is the population-based 
nature and diversity of the cohort, allowing control for fac-
tors that may confound the association between parental age 
and ASD. Maternal education is 1 variable we considered to 
be a potentially confounding factor because it is associated 
with maternal age and has been observed to be related to 
ASD risk (15). Our results, however, suggest that the asso-
ciation between advanced maternal education and ASD risk 
observed in unadjusted analysis may be spurious and due to 
confounding by parental age. </p>

<p>The results of this study also demonstrate the importance 
of controlling for birth order in evaluating independent ef-
fects of parental age on ASD risk. Because birth order in-
creases with parental age and, in this and other studies, has 
been found to be negatively associated with ASD risk, failure 
to control for birth order may mask a positive association 
between parental age and ASD risk. Two of the previous 
studies reporting an association between advancing maternal 
age and ASD (2, 4) also had adjusted for birth order and, 
similar to the present study, found birth order to be negatively 
associated with ASD. 
An additional advantage of this study is its restriction to 
a single birth year, thereby controlling for temporal trends in 
recent decades in both ASD prevalence and parental ages at 
the birth of their children. This feature of the study allows 
estimation of the association between parental age and ASD 
risk independently of temporal trends in diagnostic practices 
or other factors. </p>

<p>Public health implications </p>

<p>The strength of the independent associations between 
maternal and paternal age and ASD risk, as indicated by 
the odds ratios in the range of 1.2-1.4 reported here, is 
modest. However, the observation that these effects are in-
dependent of each other and of low birth order raises the 
likelihood that the combined effects of parental age and 
birth order may have important public health implications. 
Mean maternal age in the United States has increased 
steadily since the 1970s, particularly for firstborn children, 
for whom mean maternal age at delivery increased by 3.8 
years between 1970 and 2004 (16). In addition, the propor-
tion of births to women aged 35 years began increasing in 
the United States after 1980, when it was 5%; by 2004, it 
had increased to 14.2% (17, 18). During this same period, 
fertility rates for men aged 40 years also increased each 
year, while fertility among men aged &lt;30 years declined 
(16). With the decline in average family size in recent dec-
ades, we would also expect the proportion of children who 
are firstborn to have increased. Similar trends are occurring 
in other developed countries (7). The results of this study 
raise the question of whether some portion of the recent rise 
in ASD prevalence (19) may be linked to recent trends in </p>

<p>Table 4. Adjusted Odds Ratios a With 95% Confidence Intervals Indicating Increasing Risk of ASD With Parental Age b and Decreasing Risk With 
Birth Order, 1994 Birth Cohort From 10 Study Sites From the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention's Autism and Developmental 
Disabilities Monitoring Network </p>

<p>Birth Order </p>

<p>Both Parents Younger (Mother 
Aged 20-34 and Father Aged &lt;40 Years) </p>

<p>Only 1 Parent Older (Mother 
Aged  ‡35 or Father Aged  ‡40 Years) </p>

<p>Both Parents Older (Mother Aged 
 ‡35 and Father Aged  ‡40 Years) </p>

<p>No. 
% of Total 
Cohort 
OR 
95% CI 
No. 
% of Total 
Cohort 
OR 
95% CI 
No. 
% of Total 
Cohort 
OR 
95% CI </p>

<p>1st 
77, 883 
33.4 
1.7 c 
1.4, 2.1 
8,102 
13.4 
2.3 c 
1.7, 3.2 
2,462 
1.1 
3.1 c 
2.0, 4.7 </p>

<p>2nd 
70, 123 
30.1 
1.4 c 
1.2, 1.8 
10,796 
4.6 
2.0 c 
1.5, 2.7 
3,234 
1.4 
2.3 c 
1.7, 3.2 </p>

<p>3rd 
44, 329 
19.0 
1.0 
Reference 
11,619 
5.0 
1.7 c 
1.3, 2.3 
4,666 
2.0 
1.8 c 
1.2, 2.7 </p>

<p>Abbreviations: ASD, autism spectrum disorder; CI, confidence interval; OR, odds ratio. 
a Adjusted for gender, gestational age, birth weight for gestational age, multiple birth, maternal ethnicity and education, and site indicators. 
b Births to mothers aged &lt;20 years were excluded. 
c Odds ratios with confidence intervals that exclude 1.0. </p>

<p>Parental Age and Autism 1273 </p>

<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>parental age and family size. A further question is whether 
a modest increase in prevalence associated with advancing 
parental age and low birth order may have contributed to 
a greater awareness of ASD and, in turn, increases in mea-
sured prevalence. The tendency for older parents of firstborn 
children to have higher levels of educational achievement and 
resources than other parents could further contribute to in-
creased awareness and an expansion of the diagnosis of ASD. </p>

<p>Potential etiologic implications of parental age effects </p>

<p>Because we observed independent effects of the age of 
each parent on ASD risk, the possible mechanisms for these 
effects could include a broad range of processes associated 
with either or both maternal and paternal age. The observed 
paternal age effect independent of maternal age could point 
to a causal role of gene mutations in male germ cells, be-
cause the probability or selection of these mutations in-
creases as men age (20, 21). The independent effect of 
maternal age, on the other hand, may point to age-related 
chromosome changes, pregnancy complications, or environ-
mental exposures during pregnancy. Independent effects of 
1 or both parents' ages also could point to a role of accu-
mulated environmental exposures that may have mutagenic 
effects on gametes or could result from a combination of 
mechanisms (21, 22). 
The association between advanced maternal and paternal 
age and ASD is also consistent with a potential role of in-
fertility treatments or assisted reproductive technologies, the 
uses of which have increased in the past decade, especially by 
women and men of advanced reproductive age (23). Numer-
ous studies have found associations between these technolo-
gies and adverse pregnancy outcomes, including those due to 
epigenetic effects (24-27), although a recent review found no 
evidence of elevated rates of autism among children born 
after in vitro fertilization techniques (28). Even though we 
have no information about exposure to these treatments in our 
cohort, the observation that firstborn children of older parents 
had the highest ASD risk is consistent with a possible in-
fertility treatment effect because women who give birth after 
infertility treatment are more likely to be primiparous than 
those represented in the general birth cohort. However, the 
association between multiple birth and ASD in this study was 
weak and not statistically significant (Table 3, unadjusted 
odds ratio), whereas assisted reproduction technologies are 
strongly associated with multiple birth (23). 
Another unmeasured factor in the present study poten-
tially associated with both advanced parental age and 
ASD risk in offspring is psychopathology or behavioral 
traits of parents that may result in both delayed parenthood 
and genetic susceptibility to autism in offspring (14). </p>

<p>Birth-order effects </p>

<p>The observation in this and at least 2 previous studies (2, 4) 
that the risk of developing ASD was highest for firstborn 
children and declined with increasing birth order is a pattern 
also observed for other childhood disorders, including type I 
diabetes and atopy, and is cited as support for the ''hygiene 
hypothesis.'' According to this hypothesis, firstborn children </p>

<p>are exposed to fewer infections from other children early in 
childhood and, because of delayed immunologic challenge, 
may be more likely to develop autoimmune responses includ-
ing those that may adversely affect neurodevelopment (29). 
Another possible factor that could lead to the observed birth-
order effect is exposure to potentially neurotoxic, fat-soluble 
chemicals accumulated in maternal tissue that have been 
passed to offspring transplacentally or through breast milk 
(30). Because of accumulation over a lifetime, the load of 
such neurotoxins transmitted might be expected to be highest 
for firstborn children, particularly when combined with ad-
vanced maternal age. Another possible explanation for the 
observed birth order effect is ''stoppage'' or a tendency for 
parents of 1 child with ASD not to have subsequent children 
because of the demands of parenting a child with a disability 
or concerns about genetic susceptibility (31), thus increasing 
the likelihood in the cohort as a whole that a child with ASD 
will have a low birth order. Information available for the 
present study did not allow examination of these hypotheses. 
Another important limitation of this study is that the co-
hort available for analysis excludes births with missing pa-
ternal age information. Because this exclusion applied to 
both the ASD cases and the comparison group (Table 1), 
we would not expect it to have resulted in biased estimates 
of the association between ASD and parental age. In a sep-
arate analysis, we examined the association between mater-
nal age and ASD without adjusting for paternal age and 
including the full birth cohort, and we found the association 
between maternal age and ASD to be the same as that ob-
served in the subcohort with paternal age. 
Another limitation is that the birth cohort comparison 
group includes about 1% of births of children who died 
postnatally in addition to an undetermined number who 
moved out of the study area between birth and the age of 
8 years, whereas children who died postnatally and those 
moving out of the study area after birth are excluded from 
the case group. Because of this limitation, we could not 
estimate cumulative incidence of ASD. Nonetheless, this 
limitation is unlikely to have biased the estimated odds ra-
tios reported in this study, particularly those adjusted for 
factors such as gestational age and birth weight for gesta-
tional age, which are strongly associated with postnatal 
mortality. Another possible explanation for the increase in 
ASD among offspring of older parents, but one we cannot 
evaluate with the data available, is that, compared with 
younger parents, older parents may be more aware of de-
velopmental abnormalities and better able to access diag-
nostic and special educational services. Other limitations 
are that parity pertains to only mothers and does not take 
into account the number of previous births fathered by the 
fathers represented in the cohort, potential for residual con-
founding by factors not measured in the present study, pos-
sible misclassification of ASD case status, and missing 
information on paternal education. </p>

<p>Conclusion </p>

<p>The results of this study provide the most compelling 
evidence to date that ASD risk increases with both maternal 
and paternal age and decreases with birth order. Further </p>



<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

<p>research involving large, well-characterized birth cohorts 
followed longitudinally will be required to confirm these 
findings and adequately evaluate the range of alternative ge-
netic and environmental hypotheses that this and other stud-
ies raise regarding parental age and birth-order effects on 
ASD risk. Smaller, focused studies may also be useful, such 
as Crow's idea to look for mutations responsible for com-
plex disorders of unknown etiology and with parental age 
effects by studying affected families with older parents (20). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>Author affiliations: Department of Population Health 
Sciences, School of Medicine and Public Health, Univer-
sity of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin (Maureen 
S. Durkin, Matthew J. Maenner); Department of Pediatrics, 
School of Medicine and Public Health, University of 
Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin (Maureen S. 
Durkin, Lewis Leavitt); Waisman Center, University of 
Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, Wisconsin (Maureen S. 
Durkin, Matthew J. Maenner, Lewis Leavitt); Depart-
ment of Epidemiology, Drexel University, Philadelphia, 
Pennsylvania (Craig J. Newschaffer); Department of 
Epidemiology, Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public 
Health, Baltimore, Maryland (Li-Ching Lee); Department 
of Pediatrics, University of Arizona College of Medicine, 
Tucson, Arizona (Christopher M. Cunniff); Department of 
Epidemiology, School of Public Health, University of North 
Carolina at Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina (Julie L. 
Daniels); Department of Maternal and Child Health, School 
of Public Health, University of Alabama at Birmingham, 
Birmingham, Alabama (Russell S. Kirby); Department of 
Public Health and Environment, State of Colorado, Denver, 
Colorado (Lisa Miller); Department of Pediatrics, New Jersey 
Medical School, University of Medicine and Dentistry of 
New Jersey, Trenton, New Jersey (Walter Zahorodny); and 
National Center on Birth Defects and Developmental Disabil-
ities, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, 
Georgia (Laura A. Schieve). 
This work was funded by the Centers for Disease Control 
and Prevention, Cooperative Agreements UR3/CCU523235 
and UR3/DD000078. Additional funding for graduate stu-
dent support for data analysis was provided by the Univer-
sity of Wisconsin. 
The findings and conclusions in this report are those of 
the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of the 
Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. 
Conflict of interest: none declared. </p>





<p>Am J Epidemiol 2008;168:1268-1276 </p>

</text></tei>