<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2447753" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p><rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs>ABSTRACT </p>

<p><rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> is a new software for multiple alignment 
of nucleic acid sequences, which are recognized to 
be hard to align. The idea is that the multiple align-
ment process should be improved by taking into 
account the putative function of the sequences. In 
this perspective, MAGNOLIA is especially designed 
for sequences that are intended to be either protein-
coding or structural RNAs. It extracts information 
from the similarities and differences in the data, and 
searches for a specific evolutionary pattern between 
sequences before aligning them. The alignment step 
then incorporates this information to achieve higher 
accuracy. The website is available at http://bioinfo. 
lifl.fr/magnolia. </p>

<p>More and more newly sequenced genomes are becoming 
available every week. Tiling arrays are also gaining 
popularity for detecting novel transcripts in sequenced 
genomes. In this context, sequence annotation is an 
essential step in understanding the genome and the tran-
scriptome of a species. Comparative genomics has proven 
to be a promising approach to address this problem. 
Large-scale comparisons of prokaryotic and eukaryotic 
genomes reveal thousands of conserved regions obtained 
by homology or synteny. These regions might be protein-
coding sequences (1) or non-coding RNA genes (2,3,4). 
Annotation by comparative analysis typically involves 
two steps: first aligning the sequences, then analysing 
the multiple alignment to detect an evolutionary pattern 
that is representative of the selection pressure. This idea 
is exploited in <rs type="software">Exoniphy</rs> (5) for exon detection, in <rs type="software">RNAz</rs> 
(6) or <rs type="software">Evofold</rs> (7) for structural RNA prediction or in 
Qrna (8), that implements both a coding and an non-
coding model for RNAs. In this computational protocol, 
high-quality sequence alignment is an essential pre-
requisite step. This task, however, is difficult because 
sequence similarity is often reduced at the nucleic level. </p>

<p>Regarding protein coding genes, nucleic acid sequences 
exhibit a much larger sequence heterogeneity compared to 
their encoded amino acid sequences due to the redundancy 
of the genetic code. It is well known that the combination 
of nucleic acid and amino acid sequence information 
leads to improved alignments (9,10). The same situation 
holds for non-coding RNA genes. The spatial structure 
evolves slower than its primary structure. So pure-
sequence-based multiple alignment tools perform poorly 
on low-homology datasets of structural RNAs (11). In 
this article, we present the <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> website, whose 
objective is to provide an advanced tool for aligning 
nucleic acid sequences. The idea is to get rid of the 
dichotomy between aligning and predicting the function. 
If we assume that sequences are either protein-coding or 
structural RNAs, it is possible to incorporate some 
functional information into the alignment algorithm to 
improve the result. The multiple alignment can then be 
used as a starting point to refine the comparative analysis 
or to carry out further predictions, such as motif finding 
or phylogeny reconstruction. </p>

<p>METHODS </p>

<p>The method has two steps. First, it tries to predict the 
function of the sequences according to the substitution 
pattern between sequences. Second, a multiple alignment 
is built based on the putative function of the sequences. If 
the sequences are recognized as coding sequences, then the 
multiple alignment uses the amino acid sequences. If the 
sequences are recognized to contain a conserved second-
ary structure, then the mutiple alignment takes into 
consideration long-range base pair interactions. 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> includes three specific modules: <rs type="software">Protea</rs> 
for protein coding sequences, <rs type="software">caRNAc</rs> and <rs type="software">gardenia</rs> for 
structural RNAs. The overall scenario is summed up in 
Figure 1. 
<rs type="software">Protea</rs> implements an evolutionary model for protein-
coding sequences (12). Here the idea is that the selection 
pressure tends to preserve the encoded amino acid 
sequence, and it is possible to identifies coding sequences 
by looking for a global conservation of common </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: (33) 3 59 57 79 16; Fax: (33) 3 59 57 78 50; Email: Helene.Touzet@lifl.fr </p>

<p>ß 2008 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>reading frames. The method first identifies best potential 
reading frames from each pair of sequences, and then 
incorporates this information into a frame graph from 
which a coding significancy score is calculated. By 
doing so, it also predicts the associated reading frame for 
each sequence. If the sequences are classified as protein-
coding sequences, then the multiple alignment of nucleic 
acid sequences is built from the hypothetical amino 
acid sequences using <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> (13), <rs id="software-29" type="software">Dialign</rs><rs corresp="#software-29" type="version-number">2</rs> (10) or 
<rs type="software">T-coffee</rs> (14). <rs type="software">caRNAc</rs> is for structural RNA genes (15). In 
this model, the selection pressure tends to preserve the 
secondary structure of the molecule, and mutations should 
retain the ability to form base pairs into energetically 
favorable stems. 
<rs type="software">caRNAc</rs> is able to recover a conserved secondary struc-
ture from a set of unaligned sequences. This idea is also 
present in refs. (16,17), that fold and align several 
sequences at the same time, for example. But these pro-
grams are still computationally demanding. We circum-
vent the problem by using a heuristics approach. The 
algorithm uses a Sankoff-based dynamic programing 
approach to identify conserved strutures for all pairs of 
sequences. Then all pairwise foldings are combined into 
a graph-theoretical structure called the stem graph. 
Only frequent common stems that correspond to highly 
connected subgraphs in the stem graph are retained. 
<rs type="software">Gardenia</rs> is used to build the multiple alignment for 
potential structural RNA sequences. The method takes 
into account both the nucleic sequence and the putative 
common secondary structure predicted by <rs type="software">caRNAc</rs>. It 
relies on the dynamic programming algorithm for pair-
wise comparison proposed in ref. (18). RNA sequences are 
encoded as arc-annotated sequences, and a multiple align-
ment for a set of arc-annotated sequences is a nested 
common supersequence. The edit scheme incorporates 
evolutionary operations concerning free bases (base 
substitution, base deletion) and base pairs (arc-mismatch, 
arc-removing, arc-breaking, arc-altering), originally 
defined in ref. (19). It is easy to show that this problem 
is NP-hard. We take a heuristic approach and use a </p>

<p>progressive method. The method starts with constructing 
all pairwise alignments to determine the degree of 
similarity for each pair of sequences. Then it combines 
sequences into a multiple alignment by an ascending 
hierarchical clustering. Pairwise alignment of super-
sequences rely on the same algorithm as pairwise 
alignments for arc-annotated sequences. This is made 
possible because supersequences can be viewed as a nested 
arc-annotated sequences on an extended alphabet. The 
score of one node is its SP (sum-of-pairs) score. Lastly, the 
space search of the dynamic programming alignment is 
pruned using constraints coming from the <rs type="software">caRNAc</rs> 
output. This provides a significant speed up. </p>

<p>WEB SERVER </p>

<p>Input </p>

<p><rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> requires as input data a set of RNA or 
DNA sequences in the standard FASTA format. This set 
should contain at least two distinct sequences and at most 
ten sequences. It can be stored in a file to be uploaded to 
the server, or pasted directly in the text box. </p>

<p>Output </p>

<p>A typical run of <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> takes a few seconds. 
Upon completion of a job, <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> displays the 
result on a new web page. The job assigned a unique 
identifier that can be used to retrieve results for one week. 
All results are available for download in <rs type="software">Clustal</rs> and 
bracket-dot format. 
If input sequences are annotated as coding sequences, 
then two multiple alignments are displayed. The first 
alignment is built on the putative amino acid sequences 
obtained by virtual translation using the predicted reading 
frame, and the second alignment is the corresponding 
alignment on nucleic acid sequences obtained by reverse 
translation, allowing for frameshifts. Codons in the nucleic 
acid sequences are put in color: two base triplets coding for </p>

<p>gardenia 
caRNAc </p>

<p>protea 
ClustalW, Dialign, 
T-coffee </p>

<p>O U T P U T </p>

<p>I N P U T 
all sequences </p>

<p>all sequences </p>

<p>primary + secondary 
structures </p>

<p>aminoacid 
sequences </p>

<p>2 sequences </p>

<p>2 sequences </p>

<p>set of nucleic 
acid sequences 
all pairs 
of sequences </p>

<p>conserved 
2ary structure 
stem graph </p>

<p>frame graph 
conserved 
reading frame </p>

<p>classification 
coding/other </p>

<p>multiple 
alignment </p>

<p>classification 
structural/other </p>

<p>multiple 
alignment </p>

<p>Figure 1. <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> scenario. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W15 </p>

<p>the same amino acid bear the same color. The color choice 
is inspired from the <rs type="software">RasMol</rs> amino acid color scheme. 
Figure 2 shows an example of <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> output 
obtained with a family of protein-coding sequences. 
If input sequences are annotated as structural RNA 
genes, then a multiple alignment taking into consideration 
the primary structure accompanied by the secondary 
structure is displayed. Concerning the secondary struc-
ture, base pairings are indicated in bracket-dot format: 
Each base-pair is represented by a pair of matching 
brackets and unpaired bases are represented by dots. The 
lack of pseudoknots in the secondary structure ensures 
that this notation defines a unique folding. Moreover, 
stems in the alignment are highlighted in colors. Figure 3 
shows an example of output obtained with a family of 
non-coding RNAs. For each sequence, the individual 
putative secondary structure is also provided in five 
formats: CT, JPEG, PS, bracket-dot format and as a list 
of constrained base pairings. JPEG and PS files are 
automatically produced from the CT file using the 
<rs type="software">NAview</rs> layout program (22). 
Some data sets are not identified as coding RNAs nor as 
non-coding RNAs. The first possibility is that the 
sequences might have an alternative function, such as 
untranslated regions in messenger RNAs, promoter 
elements, etc. The second possibility is that the sequences 
are highly conserved. In this context, the comparative 
analysis approach used by <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> is not suitable. 
The evolutionary signal is too weak and the sequences do 
not exhibit any significant mutational bias towards any 
model. This is an intrinsic limitation of the method. But 
this limitation is harmless for practical purposes, because 
standard multiple sequence alignment tools usually yield 
good results on high-identity data sets. So when the 
average identity percentage is greater than 90%, the server 
outputs a warning message and provides a default 
multiple alignment constructed directly with <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs> 
on the initial data set. 
One final point worth mentioning is that the classifica-
tion is not mutually exclusive. Some sequences might 
contain conserved secondary structure elements within a 
coding region. Two such examples are the cis-acting </p>

<p>regulatory element from the human rhinoviruses, that is 
located in the open reading frame of the capsid proteins 
[RFAM -RF00220 (21)], or the Hepatitis C stem-loop 
VII structure found in the coding region of the RNA-
dependent RNA polymerase gene NS5B [RFAM -
RF000468 (21)]. In such cases, <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> releases 
two multiple alignments. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS </p>

<p>We evaluate the accuracy of the method on two large data 
sets: Pandit (20) and BRaliBase II (11). Pandit is a registry 
of families of homologous protein domains, accompanied 
by curated RNA sequence alignments. BRaliBase II is a 
set of non-coding RNA families that has been used to 
establish a benchmark of multiple sequence alignment 
programs upon structural RNAs. It is composed of four 
families: Group II introns, 5S rRNA, tRNA and U5 
spliceosomal RNA. </p>

<p>Results on pandit database </p>

<p>For each family, we selected a subset of four sequences at 
random. It remains 6491 families, whose average sequence 
length is 604 bp. 6122 (94.3%) families are correctly 
classified as coding sequences, among them more than 
99% with the correct reading frame predicted for each 
sequence. Less than 3% of the families are classified as 
structural RNA. To estimate the quality of the alignments, 
we used the sum-of-pairs score (SPS) of the <rs type="software">Baliscore</rs> 
software (23). The SPS is calculated such that it increases 
with the number of sequences correctly aligned. We 
compared <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> with <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs>, <rs type="software">T-coffee</rs> and 
Dialign2 on the same nucleic acid sequences. Results are 
displayed in Figure 4. </p>

<p>Results on BRaliBase II benchmark data </p>

<p>This benchmark contains 388 alignments, that are 
classified into high, medium and low identity data sets. 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> failed to identify a structural evolutionary 
pattern for 20% of them and falsely assigned a protein 
coding function for 7% of them. Following ref. (11), we 
use the structure conservation index (SCI) to assess the </p>

<p>Figure 3. Alignment for five tRNA sequences (BRaliBase II -aln 13). The average length is 76 nt and the average identity percentage is 51.0%. 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> finds three common stems (in blue, green and orange). All pairings are correct, and the multiple alignment is consistent with the 
reference alignment available in RFAM-RF00005 (21). </p>

<p>Figure 2. Alignment for Zn-finger in Ran binding proteins (PFAM PF00641). The average length is 92 nt and the average identity percentage is 
45.1%. Triplets are colorized according to the encoded amino acid. The reference alignment provided in Pandit is almost identical (20). </p>



<p>accuracy of alignments. This score provides a measure of 
the conserved secondary structure information contained 
within the alignment. Results for <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> are 
reported in Figure 5, together with results for other 
alignment tools used in the benchmark. We also evaluated 
the accuracy of the secondary structure found by 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> and compared it to two recent structural 
alignment programs: <rs type="software">Murlet</rs> (16) and <rs type="software">Mlocarna</rs> (17). For 
each <rs type="software">software</rs> and for each identity class, we computed the 
percentage of correct base pairings amongst the set of 
predicted base pairings. Results are shown in Table 1. It 
appears that <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> has similar performances as 
<rs type="software">Murlet</rs> and outperforms <rs type="software">Mlocarna</rs>. Furthermore, the 
total runtime is more than 12 times faster for 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> than for the two other methods (&lt; 20 min 
for the whole data set, compared to more than 4 hours). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for 
this article was provided by CNRS (Centre National de la 
Recherche Scientifique). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>Table 1. Accuracy percentage for <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs>, <rs type="software">Murlet</rs> and <rs type="software">Mlocarna</rs> 
for reference secondary structures of <rs id="software-75" type="software">BRaliBase</rs> <rs corresp="#software-75" type="version-number">II</rs> </p>

<p>Identity class </p>

<p>Low 
Medium 
High </p>

<p>MAGNOLIA 
72.0% 
76.3% 
87.0% 
Murlet 
78.1% 
76.2% 
77.8% 
Mlocarna 
68% 
71.1% 
78.9% </p>

<p>30 
40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Percent Identity </p>

<p>SPS </p>

<p>Reference 
Magnolia (ClustalW) 
Magnolia (Dialign2) 
Magnolia (T-Coffee) 
ClustalW 
Dialign2 
T-Coffee </p>

<p>Figure 4. <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> alignments on <rs type="software">Pandit</rs>. The x-axis represents the 
average identity percentage and the y-axis represents the SPS value. For 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs>, we tried all possible combinations concerning the 
alignment tool in the amino acid alignment step: <rs type="software">ClustalW</rs>, <rs type="software">T-coffee</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Dialign2</rs>. For <rs type="software">Dialign2</rs>, we selected the appropriate option 
Translation of nucleotide diagonals into peptide diagonals when compar-
ing the nucleic acid sequences. <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> clearly outperforms other 
methods. </p>

<p>40 
50 
60 
70 
80 
90 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Percent Identity </p>

<p>SCI </p>

<p>Reference 
Magnolia 
ClustalW 
DIALIGN 
MUSCLE 
PCMA 
POA 
POA (g,p) </p>

<p>ProAlign 
Prrn 
Prrn (S10) 
T-Coffee 
T-Coffee (c) 
Handel 
MAFFT 
Align-m (1) </p>

<p>Figure 5. <rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> alignments on BRaliBase II. The x-axis 
represents the average identity percentage and the y-axis represents 
the SCI value. The above curve is calculated from reference alignments. 
<rs type="software">MAGNOLIA</rs> appears to be the closest curve to the reference curve for 
identity percentage ranging from 40% to 80%. For higher identity 
percentages, all methods show similar performances. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2008, Vol. 36, Web Server issue W17 </p>





</text></tei>