<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2943325" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:37+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>A single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) in codon 129 of the 
human prion gene, leading to a change from methionine to 
valine at residue 129 of prion protein (PrP), has been shown to 
be a determinant in the susceptibility to prion disease. However, 
the molecular basis of this effect remains unexplained. In the 
current study, we determined crystal structures of prion seg-
ments having either Met or Val at residue 129. These 6-residue 
segments of PrP centered on residue 129 are "steric zippers," 
pairs of interacting -sheets. Both structures of these "homozy-
gous steric zippers" reveal direct intermolecular interactions 
between Met or Val in one sheet and the identical residue in the 
mating sheet. These two structures, plus a structure-based 
model of the heterozygous Met-Val steric zipper, suggest an 
explanation for the previously observed effects of this locus on 
prion disease susceptibility and progression. </p>

<p>steric zippers are devoid of water; instead they are self-comple-
mentary in shape with the side chains of the two sheets tightly 
abutting or interdigitating. The polymorphic methionine or 
valine side chains at residue 129 are each found at the dry inter-
face between the -sheets. The differences we observe in these 
interfaces offer a hypothesis for why susceptibility to prion dis-
ease is greater in homozygous than in heterozygous individuals. </p>

<p>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES </p>

<p>Crystallization-Segment peptides were purchased from CS 
BIO Inc. (Menlo Park, CA) in 35-50-mg batches with 99% 
purity as lyophilized powders. Both were dissolved in 20 mM 
Bis-Tris to buffer the effect of residual trifluoroacetic acid. 
Crystals GYMLGS (Met 129 ) were grown within hours at pep-
tide concentrations of 25 mg/ml by exposing the protein to 200 
mM buffers with higher pH (5) using the hanging drop 
method. Best diffraction quality crystals were obtained from 
200 mM Tris, pH 7.0. Although GYVLGS (Val 129 ) also readily 
formed crystals when exposed to higher pH buffers, they were 
thin and diffracted poorly. Screening using kits from Hampton 
Research (Aliso Viejo, CA) were used to search for better qual-
ity crystals. After optimization, diffraction quality crystals came 
from a 0.1 M ammonium sulfate, 0.1 M sodium acetate, pH 5.5, 
17% PEG 10,000 with the Val 129 segment at a concentration of 
32 mg/ml. 
Data Collection-Crystals of the segments grew as thin nee-
dles and required the use of microdiffraction beamlines at the 
Advanced Photon Source (APS) in Chicago, IL and the Swiss 
Light Source (SLS) in Villigen, Switzerland. Crystals were 
cooled to 180 °C during data collection. Data were collected 
using 5° wedges. 
Data Processing-Indexing of diffraction images was per-
formed using the programs DENZO (15) or XDS (16). Scaling of 
data was performed using the program <rs type="software">SCALEPACK</rs> (15). The 
merged scaled data were imported into the CCP4 format with 
programs from the CCP4 program suite organized under the 
CCP4i interface (17). 
Structure Determination and Refinement-Phases were 
determined using the molecular replacement method with ide-
alized polyalanine -strands using the program <rs type="software">PHASER</rs> (18). 
The program COOT (19) was used for model building along 
with rounds of refinement with the program REFMAC (20). 
Statistics for structure determination and atomic refinement 
are given in Table 1. 
Creating Models of Mixed Interfaces-The program pdbset 
from the CCP4 program suite (17) was used to create a pair of </p>

<p>stacked -sheets using crystallographic symmetry operations 
outlined in the REMARK 350 fields found in the Protein Data 
Bank (PDB) files defining the biological assembly for each 
respective structure. The program COOT (19) was used to 
superimpose strands of the GYVLGS onto the biological assem-
bly of GYMLGS and vice versa. 
Features of Peptide Structures and Models-Programs from 
the CCP4 program suite were used to calculate structural align-
ments and statistics for interpreting differences and similarities 
between segment interfaces (17). The programs pdbset and 
areaimol were used to calculate the area buried in between the 
sheet-to-sheet interface. Similarly, the programs pdbset and sc 
were used to calculate the surface complementarity of the inter-
faces. The program lsqkab was used for structural alignments 
and to calculate r.m.s.d values between segments. The program 
hollow was used to model voids in the Met 129 and Val 129 mixed 
models (21). 
Illustration of Structures-Protein structures and models 
were illustrated using the program <rs type="software">PyMOL</rs> (22). 
Accession Codes-The structures have been deposited in the 
protein data bank as 3NHC for the GYMLGS (Met 129 ) segment 
and 3NHD for the GYVLGS (Val 129 ) segment. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Segment 127-132 of human prion protein with methionine 
or valine at residue 129 forms similar steric zippers but with 
distinct interfaces. Segments with amino acid sequences GYM-
LGS (Met 129 ) and GYVLGS (Val 129 ) crystallized with similar 
space group symmetry and unit cell dimensions (Table 1). Both 
form antiparallel steric zippers with the adjacent -strands in 
each -sheet running in opposite directions and the pairs of 
-sheets aligned face-to-face (Class 8) (13). In both structures, 
-strands stack up to form nearly identical antiparallel -sheets 
in which the same residues stack on each other in the main-</p>

<p>FIGURE 1. Atomic structure of the globular domain of human PrP C with 
Val 129 (PDB ID: 3hak) shown in graphic representation (8). Segment 127-
132, the focus of the present study, is shaded in pink, showing that it includes 
the first -strand, 1. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Statistics of x-ray diffraction data collection and atomic refinement 
of the structures </p>

<p>Crystal segment name </p>

<p>GYMLGS (Met 129 ) GYVLGS (Val 129 ) </p>

<p>Data Collection 
Collected at 
SLS X06SA 
APS 24-ID-E 
Space group 
P2 1 2 1 2 1 
P2 1 2 1 2 
Resolution (Å) 
1.55 
1.9 
Unit cell dimensions: a, b, c (Å) 9.55, 18.15, 45.16 41.17, 18.95, 9.58 
Measured reflections 
6260 
3616 
Unique reflections 
1163 
637 
Overall completeness (%) 
90.9 
91.5 
Last shell completeness (%) 
78.2 
56.4 
Overall redundancy 
5.4 
5.7 
Last shell redundancy 
5.1 
3.2 
Overall R sym 
0.19 
0.19 
Last shell R sym 
0.40 
0.22 
Overall I/ 
6.56 
6.11 
Last shell I/ 
2.54 
8.43 
Last shell (Å) 
1.61-1.55 
1.97-1.90 </p>

<p>Refinement 
R work 
0.22 
0.22 
R free (test set) 
0.25 (10.5%) 
0.26 (10.1%) 
r.m.s.d. bond length (Å) 
0.013 Å 
0.015 Å 
r.m.s.d. angle (°) 
1.54 
1.48 
Number of peptide atoms 
95 
84 
Number of solvent atoms 
4 
19 
Average B factor of peptide (Å 2 ) 
13.6 
8.7 
Average B factor of solvent (Å 2 ) 
39.0 
28.0 
PDB code 
3NHC 
3NHD </p>

<p>REPORT: Consequences of Polymorphism at PrP Residue 129 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 39 • SEPTEMBER 24, 2010 </p>

<p>chain hydrogen-bonding direction (fibril axis), Gly 127 on Ser 132 , 
Tyr 128 on Gly 131 ,and Met/Val 129 on Leu 130 (Fig. 2c). 
In contrast to the similarities of their individual -sheets, we 
find key differences at the interfaces between their pairs of 
-sheets. Some of these differences are immediately apparent 
from a view down the fibril axis (Fig. 2, a and b). The planes of 
the two -sheets of GYMLGS are parallel to each other, 
whereas the planes of the two GYVLGS sheets form a chevron 
resulting in a smaller interface. In GYVLGS (Fig. 2a), the inter-
face between -sheets is formed by interdigitation of stacked 
pairs of smaller side chains, Gly 127 /Ser 132 and Val 129 /Leu 130 , </p>

<p>whereas in GYMLGS (Fig. 2b), the interface is dominated by 
interdigitation of stacked pairs of larger side chains, Tyr 128 / 
Gly 131 and Met 129 /Leu 130 . In summary, both PrP segment poly-
morphs form steric zippers characteristic of the aggregated state of 
amyloids and prions, and both appear capable of lending stability 
to PrP Sc but with different packing geometry (Table 2). 
Having determined the structures of individual Met 129 and 
Val 129 steric zipper interfaces, we can model the hypothetical 
interface of a steric zipper made up of mixed GYMLGS and 
GYVLGS segments. We constructed such a model by superim-
posing one -strand of GYMLGS on a -strand of the experi-
mentally determined steric zipper of GYVLGS. In this model, 
every possible rotamer of the methionine residue results in a 
steric clash with either the Ser 132 and Val 129 side chains or the 
main chain of the opposite -sheet (Fig. 2, d and g). Conversely, 
when GYVLGS -strands are superimposed onto -strands of 
the steric zipper interface of GYMLGS, large voids are found 
that would not permit efficient van der Waals packing of resi-
dues in the steric zipper interface (Fig. 2, e, f, h, and i). From the 
hypothetical models of mixed Met 129 /Val 129 interfaces, we 
infer that such "heterozygous steric zippers" are structurally 
disfavored for the PrP segment around residue 129, as com-
pared with the "homozygous steric zippers" containing Met 129 
and Val 129 . In short, the heterozygous steric zipper for the PrP 
segment in the vicinity of residue 129 appears less likely to form 
than the homozygous steric zippers. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Evidence suggests that steric zippers are at the core of the 
pathological form of prion, PrP Sc , giving rise to its appearance 
as unbranched rods, affinity for amyloid-specific dyes, and 
diagnostic cross-diffraction pattern (23-25). In yeast prions, 
steric zippers are also implied in the mechanism of non-Men-
delian inheritance by the obligate conversion of prion to the 
amyloid state (26 -31). Prions in the amyloid state act as nuclei 
seeding the conversion to the amyloid state of the same protein 
from its soluble monomeric form. The amyloid state can then 
pass on to progeny cells. Progression and transmission of prion 
disease in mammals has been suggested to take place in a sim-
ilar seeding of PrP C by PrP Sc (32-34). 
Previous work has demonstrated that the architecture of amy-
loid fibrils is determined by specific short segments of the fibril-
forming protein that form the steric zipper spine of the fibril (12-
14, 35, 36). In this sense, structures of amyloid and prion fibrils are 
unlike those of globular and membrane proteins in which many 
segments of the protein contribute to the stability of the struc-
ture. This localization of structural determinants in amyloids is </p>

<p>FIGURE 2. a and b, x-ray-derived atomic structures of the homozygous 
steric zippers of Met 129 (a) and Val 129 (b) segments of human prion resi-
dues 127-132, viewed down the fibril axis. The segment backbone is 
shown as a ribbon with side chains represented as sticks. The steric zipper 
interfaces are highlighted by showing interdigitated residues in space-
filling mode to emphasize the difference between the GYMLGS (Met 129 ) 
and GYVLGS (Val 129 ) segments and the efficient van der Waals packing of 
atoms in these interfaces. The carbon atoms in GYMLGS are colored in 
black, and in GYVLGS, they are in pink except when showing the side 
chains of Met 129 and Val 129 , which are colored in blue. Red atoms represent 
oxygen, and yellow represents sulfur. c, one -sheet of the GYMLGS 
viewed perpendicular to the fibril axis, which is parallel to the length of 
the page. Residues Gly 127 and Gly 131 are colored in black, residues Tyr 128 , 
Leu 130 , and Ser 132 are in white, and residue Met 129 is in blue. The antipar-
allel nature of the -sheets results in the alternating stacking of blue and 
white as well as black and white residues up and down the fibril axis. Both 
faces of the -sheets are equivalent. d, a model of one strand of GYMLGS 
onto the steric zipper interface of GYVLGS, viewed down the fibril axis 
illustrates that in such a heterozygous steric zipper, the methionine side 
chain would create steric clashes with the peptide backbone and the 
neighboring side chains. Steric clashes are represented by yellow stars. e 
and f, models of GYVLGS strands into the steric zipper interface of 
GYMLGS, viewed down the fibril axis, illustrate that the valine side chains 
leave large voids within the steric zipper interface. Although the voids 
may not be evident from the space-filling representation of the interface, 
f shows a surface representation (in red) of the voids created by incorpo-
rating GYVLGS strands into the GYMLGS interface. g-i, these panels show 
the mixed GYVLGS/GYMLGS steric zipper models viewed perpendicular to 
their fiber axes. This offers another perspective of the interface between 
the antiparallel -sheets as well as the steric clash of a GYMLGS strand 
modeled onto GYVLGS interface and the voids created by GYVLGS strands 
modeled into the GYMLGS interface. </p>

<p>TABLE 2 
Structural features of the homozygous steric zipper interfaces at 
position 129 </p>

<p>GYMLGS (Met 129 ) GYVLGS (Val 129 ) </p>

<p>Origin of PrP sequence 
Human 127-132 
Human 127-132 
Amino acid sequence 
GYMLGS 
GYVLGS 
Surface complementarity (Sc) 
0.74 
0.75 
Surface area buried in interface (Å 2 ) 
135 1 
119 4 
Sheet-to-sheet distance (Å) 
9.61 1.24 
9.04 2.51 a 
Class of steric zipper 
Class 8 (antiparallel) Class 8 (antiparallel) 
a The large S.D. is reflective of the chevron shape of the steric zipper interface, where 
one end is tightly packed and close together while the other is spread farther apart. 
The value here is an average of the distance. </p>

<p>REPORT: Consequences of Polymorphism at PrP Residue 129 </p>

<p>SEPTEMBER 24, 2010 • VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 39 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 29673 </p>

<p>why it is possible to predict protein segments that form fibrils 
(37), yet prediction of structures of globular and membrane 
proteins remains a great challenge. Furthermore, the structure-
determining segments of amyloids/prions can be crystallized, 
and their structures can be determined. In the work reported 
here, we focus on segment 127-132 of PrP, which forms a steric 
zipper and whose structure can be studied apart from the rest of 
the protein. 
Evidence that steric zippers, such as those reported here, are 
structurally related to those in full-length proteins is provided by 
our previous finding that these short, complementary structures 
can act as nuclei during the ordered aggregation of full-length pro-
teins into amyloid (35). Both the Met 129 and the Val 129 steric zip-
pers can thus represent the three-dimensional structure of an 
intermolecular protein-protein interface of the disease-associated 
PrP Sc isoform found in homozygous individuals. The two struc-
tures are of interest because they are the first structural evidence 
for a protein-protein interface in an amyloid-like conformation 
involving mutual interaction of the methionine or valine side 
chains of the polymorphism at residue 129. The pronounced mod-
ulating effect of this polymorphism on susceptibility to prion dis-
ease suggests that this interaction must be intimately linked to the 
structure of PrP Sc and may act as a site of nucleation. 
The Met 129 and Val 129 steric zipper structures show how 
substitution of a single side chain at a nucleation site can influ-
ence the three-dimensional structure of this amyloid-like inter-
face, highlighting the importance of primary structure (or 
sequence) in forming a steric zipper interface capable of effi-
cient nucleation. Our models of heterozygous steric zippers 
suggest that a nucleus in individuals that are heterozygous at 
residue 129 would be less stable than either of the homozygous 
nuclei. This is analogous to the observation that the most effi-
cient inhibitor of the growth of crystals of chicken lysozyme is 
the structurally identical turkey lysozyme where differences in 
amino acid side chains on the surfaces of the proteins make 
assembly into a coherent crystal less efficient (38). Simply put, 
forming an ordered array, such as an amyloid fibril, from two 
different building blocks is less probable than from just one. 
The two steric zipper structures (Fig. 2, a and b) and the two 
models (Fig. 2, d-i) lead to a hypothesis; humans homozygous 
for either Met 129 or Val 129 are susceptible to prion disease 
because the PrP segment centered at either residue forms a 
stable homozygous steric zipper. In contrast, humans heterozy-
gous for PrP at residue 129 are less susceptible to prion disease 
because a steric zipper involving one PrP molecule with Met 129 
and one molecule of Val 129 is less stable than either of the two 
homozygous steric zippers. Such a hypothesis would not 
exclude heterozygous individuals from prion disease because 
heterozygotes contain many molecules of each type, and steric 
zippers arising from segregated pools of either polymorph are 
still possible but less likely due to the entropic barrier. 
Our hypothesis for human susceptibility to prion disease can 
be extended to interpret observations of incubation time in the 
development of prion disease. A fundamental property of amy-
loid in vitro is that its formation from monomers is preceded by 
a lag time, which can be shortened by introduction of a nucleus 
(39). Similarly, the long incubation times for prion and amyloid 
diseases with the slow accumulation of fibrils and plaques sug-</p>

<p>gest a very significant energy barrier to nucleation in vivo (12). 
According to our hypothesis, the presence of prion protein with 
both Met 129 and Val 129 in heterozygous individuals would 
lessen the probability of a stable nucleus forming at this site 
because of the less favorable packing and would consequently 
lengthen incubation times. This is indeed what is observed; case 
studies of heterozygous individuals with kuru have suggested 
that in such circumstances, the incubation period of the disease 
may be as long as 40 -50 years (2, 40). 
It is also possible that the longer incubation times in het-
erozygous individuals are due to nucleation of PrP Sc at seg-
ments other than around residue 129, albeit less efficiently. 
Amyloid formation can be nucleated by more than just one 
segment and can involve multiple segments of a protein. For 
example, Wiltzius et al. (14) found that various segments of the 
islet amyloid polypeptide form steric zippers and serve as 
nucleating sites leading to different "strains" of amyloid. Simi-
larly, PrP Sc has been shown to have different strains, which have 
been attributed to different conformations of the protein in the 
aggregated state (41, 42). The crystal structures of the 6-residue 
127-132 segment presented here only represent a fraction of 
residues known to be in the core 90 -231 residues of infectious 
PrP Sc ; hence other segments must also be involved in the struc-
ture of amyloid from PrP and present possible alternative 
nucleation sites. Kinetic studies of amyloid formation by 
recombinant PrP with Met 129 , Val 129 , or a mixed population 
have not been consistent in recapitulating the same effects of 
the 129 polymorphism as seen in vivo, suggesting that in vitro, 
PrP amyloid may nucleate more efficiently along other inter-
faces (43-47). Consistent with this idea, we have found that PrP 
has multiple segments that form steric zippers. 3 
Pathogenic mutations have been documented that work syn-
ergistically with the 129 polymorphism to cause prion disease. 
These underscore the idea that other segments of PrP are 
involved in forming steric zipper interactions in the structure of 
PrP Sc (48). Some of these mutations are distal to residue 129, 
such as P102L, D178N, E200K, and V210I, which have been 
found in multiple families affected by prion disease. These fur-
ther support the involvement of intramolecular interactions 
between multiple steric zipper segments of PrP Sc , such as those 
between the segments containing the 129 polymorphism and 
those with the pathogenic mutation. Other pathogenic muta-
tions are proximal to the polymorphic residue 129 such as 
G131V, which caused Gerstmann--Scheinker syn-
drome in a patient who was homozygous for Met 129 (49). In the 
structures of the 127-132 segments, residue Gly 131 is stacked 
on Tyr 128 , which in the case of the pathogenic Val mutation 
would cause considerable steric clashes. The G131V patho-
genic mutation would therefore cause a considerably different 
steric zipper packing, which as pathology suggests would nucle-
ate amyloid assembly even more efficiently. 
Clearly the transformation of PrP C to PrP Sc depends on more 
than the segment around residue 129. However, our atomic 
structures, the first that show the interactions of this segment in 
the aggregated state, reveal a pattern of intermolecular contacts </p>

<p>3 M. I. Apostol, M. R. Sawaya, D. Cascio, and D. Eisenberg, unpublished results. </p>

<p>REPORT: Consequences of Polymorphism at PrP Residue 129 </p>



<p>VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 39 • SEPTEMBER 24, 2010 </p>

<p>involving residues Met 129 and Val 129 that is consistent with 
previous studies of PrP disease susceptibility and progression. 
The structures suggest a possible mechanism for the sequence 
dependence of human susceptibility to prion diseases, which up 
to now has remained mysterious. </p>

<p>Acknowledgments-We thank the staff of the SLS beamline X-06-SA 
and APS beamline 24-ID-E for support and assistance with data col-
lection. We thank Magdalena Ivanova and Nicole Wheatley for crit-
ical reading of the manuscript. </p>



<p>REPORT: Consequences of Polymorphism at PrP Residue 129 </p>

<p>SEPTEMBER 24, 2010 • VOLUME 285 • NUMBER 39 </p>

<p>JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY 29675 </p>

</text></tei>