<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2927682" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-07T18:15+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT 
Objectives To determine if genetic variation in genes 
in the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, the 
primary stress response system, infl uences susceptibility 
to developing musculoskeletal pain. 
Methods Pain and comorbidity data was collected 
at three time points in a prospective population-based 
cohort study. Pairwise tagging single nucleotide 
polymorphisms (SNPs) were selected and genotyped for 
seven genes. Genetic association analysis was carried out 
using zero-infl ated negative binomial regression to test 
for association between SNPs and the maximum number 
of pain sites across the three time points in participants 
reporting pain, reported as proportional changes with 
95% CIs. SNPs were also tested for association with 
chronic widespread pain (CWP) using logistic regression 
reporting odds ratios and 95% CI. 
Results A total of 75 SNPs were successfully genotyped 
in 994 participants including 164 cases with persistent 
CWP and 172 pain-free controls. Multiple SNPs in 
SERPINA6 were associated with the maximum number 
of pain sites; for example, each copy of the T allele of 
rs941601 was associated with having 16% (proportional 
change=1.16, 95% CI 1.04 to 1.28, p=0.006) more pain 
sites compared to participants with the CC genotype. 
SERPINA6 gene SNPs were also associated with CWP. 
Signifi cant associations between the maximum number of 
pain sites and SNPs in the CRHBP and POMC genes were 
also observed and a SNP in MC2R was also associated 
with CWP. Associations between SNPs and comorbidity 
of poor sleep quality and depression explained some of 
the associations observed. 
Conclusions Genetic variation in HPA axis genes was 
associated with musculoskeletal pain; however, some of the 
associations were explained by comorbidities. Replication of 
these fi ndings is required in independent cohorts. </p>

<p>Musculoskeletal pain is common in the general 
population with up to 33% of people reporting low 
back pain (LBP) and approximately 11% reporting 
chronic widespread pain (CWP). 1 Stress has been 
associated with musculoskeletal pain syndromes 2 3 
and psychological distress has been shown to be a 
strong predictor for the onset of CWP. 4 
The body's primary stress response system, the 
hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal (HPA) axis, has 
been shown to be hyporesponsive in patients with 
fi bromyalgia and patients with LBP. 5 6 In a cohort 
of participants free of CWP those who went onto 
develop it showed reduced morning and increased 
evening levels of cortisol and higher levels of </p>

<p>Genetic variation in the hypothalamic-pituitary-adrenal 
stress axis infl uences susceptibility to musculoskeletal 
pain: results from the EPIFUND study </p>

<p>Kate L Holliday, 1 Barbara I Nicholl, 1 Gary J Macfarlane, 2 Wendy Thomson, 1 Kelly A 
Davies, 1 John McBeth 1 </p>

<p>1 Arc Epidemiology Unit, 
University of Manchester, 
Manchester, UK 
2 Aberdeen Pain Research 
Collaboration (Epidemiology 
Group), School of Medicine 
and Dentistry, University of 
Aberdeen, UK </p>

<p>Correspondence to 
Dr Kate L Holliday, arc 
Epidemiology Unit, University of 
Manchester, Stopford Building, 
Oxford Road, Manchester 
M13 9PT, UK; kate.holliday@ 
manchester.ac.uk </p>

<p>KLH and BIN contributed 
equally to this work. </p>

<p>Accepted 17 August 2009 </p>

<p>cortisol following a dexamethasone test (HPA axis 
suppression test). This suggests that individuals 
developing CWP show a blunting of the cortisol 
diurnal rhythm and a failure to suppress the HPA 
axis indicating a hypoactive HPA axis. 
It has been hypothesised that the abnormal 
functioning of the HPA axis in musculoskeletal 
pain could be due stressors such as severe adverse 
events in early life, which have been shown to 
result in dysfunction of the HPA axis 7 8 or altered 
levels of neurotransmitters such as reduced seroto-
nin levels, as observed in fi bromyalgia, 9 10 which 
stimulates adrenocorticotrophin (ACTH) and corti-
cotrophin releasing hormone (CRH) in response to 
stress. Genetic variation in genes key to HPA axis 
function could also play a role in musculoskeletal 
pain susceptibility. Individuals may respond inef-
fi ciently to stressors due to their genetic makeup, 
which may in turn render them more susceptible 
to developing musculoskeletal pain. 
Twin studies have estimated that genetics 
explains 50% of the variance in pain syndromes. 11 12 
Pain thresholds, which are reduced in patients with 
CWP, 13 have also been shown to have a genetic 
component, 14, 15 however, one study did not fi nd 
evidence of this. 16 Attempts to identify the genes 
involved in CWP susceptibility and experimen-
tal pain sensitivity have been limited to date and 
problematic in their study design. The most prev-
alent problem is a lack of suffi cient sample size to 
detect the likely modest effects of individual genes. 
Insuffi cient representation of the genetic variation 
within candidate genes and not considering the 
role of comorbidities are also common problems. 17 
In this study we aimed to determine if genetic 
variation within the HPA axis pathway genes 
CRH, CRH receptor 1 (CRHR1), CRH binding protein 
(CRHBP), the ACTH precursor pro-opiomelanocortin 
(POMC) and its receptor (MC2R), the glucocorti-
coid receptor (NR3C1) and corticosteroid binding glob-
ulin (SERPINA6), is associated with susceptibility 
to musculoskeletal pain while accounting for the 
effects of comorbidities. </p>

<p>METHODS 
Participants </p>

<p>Pain and psychological data was collected at three 
time points over a 4-year period via a postal survey 
as part of a prospective population-based cohort 
study, EPIFUND (for 'Epidemiology of Functional 
Disorders'). Participants aged 25-65 years were 
recruited from three primary care registers in the 
northwest of England. </p>

<p>Extended report </p>

<p>Ann Rheum Dis 2010;69:556-560. doi:10.1136/ard.2009.116137 </p>

<p>
Pain phenotype </p>

<p>Participants were asked to indicate the site of any pain expe-
rienced for 1 day or longer in the past month on blank body 
manikins (front, back and sides) and to indicate if their pain had 
lasted for more than 3 months. Participants were classifi ed two 
ways. (1) A 'total pain' score was constructed which ranged 
from 0 (no pain) to 29 (pain in all sites of the body) using the 
Manchester coding system 18 19 (fi gure 1). For each participant 
the maximum number of pain sites across the three time points 
was determined. (2) CWP was classifi ed using American College 
of Rheumatology criteria. Cases were defi ned as participants 
with CWP ≥2 time points and controls were pain free at all three 
time points. </p>

<p>Ascertainment of comorbidities </p>

<p>Anxiety, depression, psychological distress and sleep quality 
were assessed at baseline. Anxiety and depression were mea-
sured using the Hospital Anxiety and Depression (HAD) scale. 20 
The HAD questionnaire contains seven items on anxiety and 
seven items on depression in the last week. Each question is 
answered on a 4-point Likert scale (0-3) with total scores ranging 
from 0 to 21. Higher scores are indicative of a higher probability 
of having an anxiety or depressive disorder. The General Health 
Questionnaire 21 (12-item version) was used to assess levels of 
psychological distress. Scores range from 0 to 12 with higher 
scores indicating higher levels of psychological distress. Sleep 
quality was assessed using the Estimation of Sleep Problems 
Scale. 22 A total of 4 items on recent sleep problems (sleep onset, 
sleep maintenance, early wakening and non-restorative sleep) 
were assessed on a 5-point scale (0-5) resulting in a total score 
of between 0 and 20, with higher scores indicating poorer sleep 
quality. </p>

<p>Genetic analysis </p>

<p>Participants were asked to provide a buccal swab sample for 
genetic analysis with informed consent. The sample collection and 
DNA extraction methods were adapted from Freeman et al. 23 
Pairwise tagging single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs, 
r 2 ≥0.8) with a minor allele frequency ≥5% were selected for 
CRH, CRHBP, CRHR1, POMC, MC2R, NR3C1 and SERPINA6 
and their 10 kb fl anking regions using <rs type="software">Tagger</rs>. 24 SNPs were geno-
typed using Sequenom MassARRAY technology following the 
manufacturer's instructions (http://www.sequenom.com). </p>

<p>Sample and assay quality control thresholds were set to 90%. 
Allele frequencies were checked for consistency with HapMap 
data and tested for deviation from Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium 
(HWE) and excluded from the analysis if p≤0.01 in the total pop-
ulation. Linkage disequilibrium (LD) between SNPs was exam-
ined using <rs id="software-3" type="software">Haploview</rs> <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">version 3.32</rs>. 25 </p>

<p>Statistical analysis </p>

<p>Analysis was conducted using <rs id="software-4" type="software">STATA</rs> <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">V.9.2</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-4" type="creator">Stata, College Station, Texas, USA</rs>). p Values &lt;0.05 were considered statisti-
cally signifi cant. </p>

<p>Total number of pain sites 
The distribution of the maximum number of pain sites was pos-
itively skewed with 17% of participants reporting no pain. To 
account for this and overdispersion of the data a zero-infl ated 
negative binomial regression (ZINB) model was used. ZINB 
tests whether a SNP is associated with the odds of reporting 
no pain (logit) as well as testing for association between a SNP 
and the maximum number of pain sites in participants who 
have reported pain (negative binomial). Participants report-
ing pain can range from having acute pain at a single site to 
chronic pain at multiple sites, therefore, treating them as a 
referent group to determine if a SNP is associated with the 
odds of reporting no pain is a crude analysis and so the results 
of the logit portion of the model are not reported. Initially a 
test for trend was conducted. Where there was no evidence 
of a trend association, recessive (AA and Aa vs aa) and dom-
inant (AA vs Aa and aa) models of association were tested. 
The results of the negative binomial portion of the model are 
reported as the proportional change in the number of pain 
sites with 95% CIs. 
The effects of four variables; depression, anxiety, psycholog-
ical distress and sleep quality on the maximum number of pain 
sites was assessed using ZINB and only depression and sleep 
were independently associated (data not shown). Therefore, 
SNPs signifi cantly associated with the maximum number of 
pain sites were tested for association with HAD depression 
score (using negative binomial regression) and sleep quality 
score (using ZINB). Where there was evidence of an associa-
tion between a SNP and depression or sleep quality the model 
was adjusted for the associated comorbidity (depression and/or 
sleep) to determine if the SNP associations with the maximum 
number of pain sites were occurring independently of these 
comorbid factors. Interactions between SNPs (associated with 
the maximum number of pain sites) and depression and sleep 
were also tested to determine if they were acting as effect modi-
fi ers on the associations observed with pain. </p>

<p>CWP 
SNPs were tested for association with CWP using the Cochran-
Armitage trend test. Where there was no evidence of a trend 
association, recessive and dominant models of association were 
tested using a χ 2 test. Logistic regression was used to estimate 
odds ratios (OR) and 95% CI. 
Haplotype structure was determined using the confi dence 
bounds method in <rs type="software">Haploview</rs>. 26 The expectation-maximisation 
algorithm was used to estimate haplotype frequencies. The 
overall distribution of haplotypes was compared between 
patients with CWP and pain-free controls using a χ 2 test. The 
frequency of each individual haplotype was also compared to 
the combined frequency of the other haplotypes between cases 
and controls using the χ 2 test. Haplotype inference and associa-
tion testing was conducted in <rs type="software">PLINK</rs>. 27 
Figure 1 Pain sites used to calculate total pain score (Manchester coding). </p>

<p>Extended report </p>

<p>Ann Rheum Dis 2010;69:556-560. doi:10.1136/ard.2009.116137 </p>

<p>
Depression and sleep were independently associated with 
CWP (data not shown). Signifi cant associations with CWP were 
adjusted for depression and/or sleep if there was evidence of 
association between the SNP and depression and/or sleep, to 
determine if the associations were occurring independently of 
these comorbid factors. Interactions between SNPs (associated 
with CWP) and depression and sleep were also tested to deter-
mine if they were moderating the relationship between the SNP 
and CWP. </p>

<p>RESULTS 
Participants </p>

<p>DNA samples were obtained from 1189 participants with pain 
data at all time points. Samples from 195 (16%) participants 
were not successfully genotyped for 90% of the SNPs and were 
excluded from the analysis. The characteristics of the resulting </p>

<p>994 participants are given in table 1. The nested case-control 
study of CWP consisted of 164 cases and 172 controls. HAD 
depression and sleep quality scores in the cases were signifi -
cantly (Mann-Whitney U test, p&lt;0.001) higher than in the con-
trols (table 1). </p>

<p>Genotyping </p>

<p>Of the 88 SNPs selected, 75 were successfully genotyped and in 
HWE (p&gt;0.01). Coverage of HapMap SNPs (r 2 &lt;0.8) was 100% 
for POMC, 92% for CRHR1 and MC2R, 87% for SERPINA6, 
84% for NR3C1, 67% for CRH and 60% for CRHBP. </p>

<p>Total number of pain sites </p>

<p>Four SNPs spanning 5' to intron 4 of SERPINA6 showed asso-
ciation with the maximum number of pain sites in participants 
reporting pain. rs941601 and rs746530 both showed a signifi cant 
trend for an increase in the maximum number of pain sites, in 
participants reporting pain, with the number of copies of the 
minor allele. A signifi cant increase in the maximum number of 
pain sites was observed in participants with two copies of the 
minor allele (recessive effect) for rs11627241 and rs1998056 com-
pared to participants with zero copies or one copy (table 2). 
In participants reporting pain, having one or two copies of the 
minor allele of rs3769371 in POMC was associated with a reduc-
tion in the maximum number of pain sites compared to having 
zero copies (dominant effect). Conversely, rs1875999 in CRHBP 
was associated with an increased maximum number of pain sites 
in participants with one or two copies of the minor allele com-
pared to participants with zero copies (table 2) and also showed 
evidence of association with an increased likelihood of depres-
sion (proportional change=1.10, 95% CI 1.00 to 1.20, p=0.047 
for each copy of the minor allele) and poor sleep quality (propor-
tional change=1.15, 95% CI 1.06 to 1.25, p=0.001 for each copy 
of the minor allele in participants reporting sleep problems (sleep 
quality score ≥1)). Adjusting the association between the maxi-
mum number of pain sites and rs1875999 for HAD depression 
score and sleep quality rendered the association non-signifi cant 
(proportional change=1.01, 95% CI 0.91 to 1.11, p=0.860). 
There was no evidence of interaction between the SNPs, associ-
ated with pain, and depression or sleep on the maximum number 
of pain sites. There was also no evidence of association between 
the maximum number of pain sites in participants reporting pain 
and SNPs genotyped in CRH, CRHR1, MC2R and NR3C1. </p>

<p>CWP </p>

<p>Two SNPs in SERPINA6 were signifi cantly associated with CWP. 
Rs941601 and rs8022616 showed a signifi cant trend for increasing 
and decreasing the odds of having CWP with the number of cop-
ies of the minor allele, respectively (table 3). These two SNPs are </p>

<p>Table 1 Participant characteristics </p>

<p>Total population </p>

<p>CWP analysis </p>

<p>Cases 
Controls </p>

<p>n 
994 
164 
172 
Median age (95% CI) 50.9 (49.8 to 52.0) 
52.6 (50.3 to 53.9) 48.5 (46.4 to 51.6) 
% Female 
58 
66 
57 
Median depression 
score (95% CI) </p>

<p>3 (2 to 3) 
5 (4 to 6) 
2 (1 to 2) </p>

<p>Median sleep score 
(95% CI) </p>

<p>5 (5 to 5) 
11 (10 to 13) 
3 (2 to 4) </p>

<p>CWP, chronic widespread pain. </p>

<p>Table 2 Signifi cant associations with the maximum number of pain 
sites in participants reporting pain </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP 
Genotype n </p>

<p>Proportional 
change (95% CI) 
p Value </p>

<p>SERPINA6 
rs941601 
CC 
604 
Reference 
-
CT 
202 
1.16 (1.04 to 1.28) 
0.006 
TT 
16 
1.34 (1.09 to 1.64) 
0.006 
rs11627241 CC and CT 772 
Reference 
-
TT 
50 
1.27 (1.03 to 1.57) 
0.026 
rs1998056 
CC and CG 671 
Reference 
-
GG 
149 
1.18 (1.03 to 1.34) 
0.017 
rs746530 
GG 
352 
Reference 
-
GA 
360 
1.10 (1.02 to 1.19) 
0.011 
AA 
101 
1.21 (1.05 to 1.41) 
0.011 
POMC 
rs3769671 
AA 
740 
Reference 
-
AC and CC 
65 
0.81 (0.67 to 0.99) 
0.040 
CRHBP 
rs1875999 
TT 
373 
Reference 
-</p>

<p>TC and CC 444 
1.12 (1.01 to 1.24) 
0.036 </p>

<p>SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>Table 3 Signifi cant associations with CWP </p>

<p>Gene 
SNP 
Genotype </p>

<p>n (%) </p>

<p>OR (95% CI) 
p Value 
Cases 
Controls </p>

<p>SERPINA6 
rs941601 
CC 
117 (71) 
138 (81) 
Reference 
-
CT 
43 (26) 
31 (18) 
1.61 (1.02 to 2.55) 
0.040 
TT 
4 (3) 
2 (1) 
2.59 (1.03 to 6.52) 
0.040 
rs8022616 
AA 
142 (87) 
131 (77) 
Reference 
-
AG 
20 (12) 
36 (21) 
0.58 (0.34 to 0.97) 
0.037 
GG 
2 (1) 
3 (2) 
0.33 (0.12 to 0.93) 
0.037 
MC2R 
rs11661134 
GG 
132 (84) 
158 (92) 
Reference 
-</p>

<p>AG and AA 
26 (16) 
14 (8) 
2.22 (1.12 to 4.43) 
0.023 </p>

<p>CWP, chronic widespread pain; SNP, single nucleotide polymorphism. </p>

<p>Extended report </p>

<p>Ann Rheum Dis 2010;69:556-560. doi:10.1136/ard.2009.116137 </p>

<p>
located within a 3-kb haplotype block containing four other SNPs 
spanning intron 3 to intron 4 (fi gure 2). Six common haplotypes 
were identifi ed in this block. Although the overall haplotype dis-
tribution did not signifi cantly differ between cases and controls 
(p=0.09), the haplotype containing the minor T allele of rs941601 
and the common A allele of rs8022616 was signifi cantly more fre-
quent in cases (16%) than controls (10%), p=0.041. Conversely, 
the haplotype containing the common C allele of rs941601 and 
the variant G allele of rs8022616 was signifi cantly more common 
in controls (13%) than cases (7%), p=0.019 (table 4). 
The SERPINA6 SNP rs8022616 showed evidence of asso-
ciation with a reduced likelihood of depression (proportional 
change=0.80, 95% CI 0.69 to 0.92, p=0.002 for each copy of 
the minor allele) and improved sleep quality (proportional 
change=0.86, 95% CI 0.76 to 0.98, p=0.02) for each copy of the 
minor allele in participants reporting sleep problems. Adjusting 
the association between rs8022616 and CWP for HAD depres-
sion score and sleep quality score rendered it non-signifi cant 
(p=0.275) but the odds of having CWP was still reduced, pro-
portional change=0.69, 95% CI 0.35 to 1.35. 
A single SNP in MC2R, rs11661134, was associated with an 
increased odds of having CWP in participants with one or two 
copies of the minor A allele compared to participants with zero 
copies (OR=2.24, 95% CI 1.14 to 4.39, p=0.02). There was no 
evidence of interaction between SNPs associated with CWP </p>

<p>with depression or sleep on CWP susceptibility and no evidence 
of association with SNPs in CRH, CRHR1, CRHBP, POMC or 
NR3C1 and CWP. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Here we report the fi ndings of the fi rst population-based study 
to examine the role of HPA axis genes in musculoskeletal pain 
susceptibility. The fi ndings suggest that genetic variation in the 
HPA axis, most notably in the corticosteroid binding globulin 
gene (SERPINA6), has a role in susceptibility to CWP and mus-
culoskeletal pain in the population, however, comorbidities 
seem to explain some of the associations observed. 
Multiple SNPs in SERPINA6 were associated with the maxi-
mum number of pain sites in participants reporting pain and two 
SNPs in this gene, rs941601 and rs8022616, also showed evidence 
of association with CWP and are located within a single haplo-
type block. However, no effect of the haplotype over and above 
the individual effects of the SNPs was observed due to there being 
no evidence of recombination between the SNPs (D'=1). Genetic 
associations were also observed between a SNP in MC2R and 
CWP, and between SNPs in CRHBP and POMC with the maxi-
mum number of pain sites in participants reporting pain. 
Genetic variation in the HPA axis may infl uence other pain-
related factors such as psychological comorbidities and sleep 
quality. Consequently SNPs associating with pain were tested for 
association with these factors. The minor allele of the SERPINA6 
SNP, rs8022616, was associated with a reduced likelihood of 
developing a depressive disorder and increased sleep quality. 
The minor C allele of the CRHBP SNP, rs1875999, was associated 
with increased likelihood of developing a depressive disorder and 
reduced sleep quality. This is in contrast to a previous report in 
which the common T allele of rs1875999 was signifi cantly asso-
ciated with increased odds of having major depressive disorder 
in a Swedish population. 28 These factors appear to explain the 
associations between these two SNPs and pain as they became 
non-signifi cant after adjustment for them; however, a reduced 
odds of having CWP was still observed in participants with the 
minor allele of rs8022616. Genetic variation in SERPINA6 could 
infl uence pain and psychological factors independently as previ-
ous fi ndings from the EPIFUND study showed that HPA axis dys-
function increases the odds of developing CWP independently of 
depression and other psychological factors. 29 
Chronic fatigue syndrome (CFS) shares some similarity in its 
aetiology and symptoms with CWP and evidence of hypofunc-
tion of the HPA axis in CFS has been reported. 30 Therefore, the 
same genes may be associated with CFS and pain susceptibil-
ity. Polymorphisms in NR3C1 have previously been associated 
with CFS 31 and shown to distinguish between different classes 
of CFS. 32 
However, there was no evidence of association between SNPs 
in NR3C1 and musculoskeletal pain in this study. The most likely 
explanation for this is the modest sample size most notably in 
the previous studies but also in this study. Alternatively the pre-
vious genetic associations observed with CFS may be specifi c to 
CFS rather than being genetic predictors for functional somatic 
syndromes. 
SNPs in NR3C1 have also been shown to infl uence cortisol 
levels. 33 34 However, none of the SNPs that we observed in asso-
ciation with pain here have as yet been tested for association 
with HPA axis function. This will be an important step in order 
to determine how the SNPs may be functioning via the HPA axis 
to infl uence pain susceptibility. 
One of the strengths of this study is the phenotypes used. 
Cases had reported CWP at at least two of the three time points, </p>

<p>Figure 2 Linkage disequilibrium and haplotype block structure of 
SERPINA6 in the study population. Single nucleotide polymorphisms 
(SNPs) genotyped and their position in SERPINA6 are shown with 
pairwise linkage disequilibrium (LD; colour coded by r 2 (white=0, 
black=1) and numbered by D′ (if no number D′=1)) and haplotype 
block structure as defi ned by the confi dence bounds method. 26 </p>

<p>Table 4 Haplotype analysis of SERPINA6 with CWP </p>

<p>Combination of SNPs </p>

<p>Overall 
distribution 
p value </p>

<p>Distribution of individual haplotypes </p>

<p>Haplotype Case % Control % p Value </p>

<p>rs941601-rs3790036-
rs2144835-rs11629171-
rs8022616-rs11622665 </p>

<p>0.09 
CACCAG 
0.21 
0.22 
0.881 
CATTGA 
0.07 
0.13 
0.019 </p>

<p>CGTTAA 
0.16 
0.17 
0.651 </p>

<p>CACCAA 
0.14 
0.15 
0.762 </p>

<p>TATCAA 
0.16 
0.10 
0.041 </p>

<p>CATCCA 
0.26 
0.23 
0.401 </p>

<p>CWP, chronic widespread pain. </p>

<p>Extended report </p>

<p>Ann Rheum Dis 2010;69:556-560. doi:10.1136/ard.2009.116137 </p>

<p>
providing a robust phenotype, and were compared to a pain-
free control group to avoid erroneous associations due to the 
presence of non-persistent CWP, WP or regional pain disorders 
which may also be infl uenced by genetic variation in the HPA 
axis. However, this results in a limited sample size. A novel 
method was used to quantify pain by creating a composite score 
of the number of body regions, from 0 to 29, making it possible 
to examine the relationship between genetic variation and mus-
culoskeletal pain in the entire study population thus increasing 
statistical power. 
One limitation of the study is that ethnicity of participants 
was not determined; however, participants were derived from 
predominantly white Caucasian geographic areas. Another limi-
tation of our study is that due to limited power we have chosen 
not to correct for multiple testing. Indeed correcting for the num-
ber of effective tests, accounting for LD between SNPs, using the 
methodology proposed by Li and Ji 35 would result in a p value 
cut-off of 0.00037; none of the associations observed reached 
this level of signifi cance. However, this method of correction 
is comparatively stringent and may result in false negatives if 
applied. To be certain whether these are true pain susceptibility 
loci or false positives, independent replication of these fi ndings 
in larger cohorts is essential. 
It was anticipated that similar fi ndings would be detected 
with the two pain outcomes as the patients with CWP also tend 
to have a high number of pain sites. There is some consistency 
between the fi ndings of the CWP and maximum number of pain 
sites analysis but also some discrepancies. This may be explained 
by the reduced power in the CWP analysis or because the max-
imum pain score is capturing acute and chronic pain which may 
not be infl uenced by the same genetic factors. 
In conclusion, we report the fi rst evidence that genetic vari-
ation in the primary stress response system infl uences suscep-
tibility to musculoskeletal pain in a general population sample. 
However, the associations reported are modest, sometimes 
explained by psychological comorbidity and require replication 
in a large independent cohort to determine whether they play a 
role in the aetiology of musculoskeletal pain. </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors would like to thank the participants and staff 
at the three general practices who contributed to the EPIFUND study. They also 
thank the administrative and laboratory staff at the arc Epidemiology Unit for their 
contributions to the project. </p>

<p>Funding The study was funded by a grant from the Arthritis Research Campaign, grant 
Ref: 17552. </p>

<p>Competing interests None. </p>

<p>Ethics approval This study was conducted with the approval of the local research 
ethics committee and the University of Manchester. </p>

<p>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. </p>



</text></tei>