<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2963829" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:16+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>T </p>

<p>he mammalian kidney is a model organ for pattern forma-
tion. Th e formation of its functional units, the nephrons, 
depends on branching morphogenesis, mesenchymal -epi-
thelial transition and inductive signalling </p>

<p>1,2   . Th e process of nephron 
formation is extraordinarily sensitive to the eff ects of adverse envi-
ronmental events during certain critical windows of development. 
Fetal malnutrition, the most common form of developmental chal-
lenge, results in an irreversible reduction of nephrons </p>

<p>3 -5   . In humans, 
the loss of nephrons caused by maternal low caloric intake or by 
placental insuffi ciency encompasses increased risk for renal disease 
and hypertension </p>

<p>6,7   . 
Th e ubiquitous integral plasma membrane protein, Na,K-ATPase, 
can, in addition to its well-studied function as an ion pump, function 
as a signal transducer 
8,9 . Ouabain, a highly specifi c Na,K-ATPase 
ligand, tethers the catalytic α -subunit of Na,K-ATPase with the inosi-
tol 1,4,5-trisphosphate receptor (IP3R), and triggers the release of a 
series of calcium waves </p>

<p>10 -13   . Calcium waves have emerged as a key 
regulator of early development </p>

<p>14,15   . However, little is known about 
the role of calcium in pattern formation and cell diff erentiation dur-
ing later stages of embryonic life in mammals. Downstream eff ects 
of ouabain signalling include activation of the calcium-dependent 
transcription factor nuclear factor (NF)-κ B and protection from 
apoptosis </p>

<p>16   . As those factors are implicated in developmental proc-
esses, we decided to study whether the signalling cascade triggered 
by ouabain might aff ect the developmental programming in kidneys 
exposed to malnutrition. 
To examine whether ouabain -calcium -NF-κ B signalling might 
rescue the development of fetal kidneys exposed to malnutrition, 
we fi rst used kidney explants from 14-day-old embryonic rats held 
in culture for 3 days. To mimic malnutrition, kidneys were serum 
deprived for 24 h. Imaging of intracellular calcium was performed 
in the outer cell layers of explanted kidneys. Spontaneous calcium 
waves were observed in the majority of cells, and both acute and 
chronic exposure to ouabain, in concentrations that had little or 
no eff ect on Na,K-ATPase pump function, were found to increase 
the number of calcium waves. As expected, serum-deprived 
kidneys displayed severe retardation of nephron formation and 
robust increase in apoptotic index (AI), but these eff ects were abo-
lished if the kidneys were exposed to ouabain in concentrations 
that had no eff ect on intracellular sodium. To assess the role of the 
ouabain -calcium -NF-κ B signalling pathway, we deprived the intra-
cellular stores of calcium and blocked the transcriptional capacity 
of NF-κ B. To obtain proof of principle that ouabain rescues the 
develop ment of embryonic kidneys exposed to malnutrition, nephron 
endowment was examined in off spring of rat dams that had been 
given a low-protein diet and treated with ouabain or vehicle 
throughout pregnancy. </p>

<p>Results 
Calcium activity in metanephric blastema cells . To investigate 
whether spontaneous calcium activity can be observed at the 
time of nephron induction, we took advantage of the fact that 
branching morphogenesis occurs in the explanted kidney. Rat 
embryonic kidneys were removed at E14 and held in culture for 
3 days. Imaging of intracellular calcium was performed in the outer 
cell layers of the kidney, consisting mainly of metanephric blastema 
cells in close contact with the epithelial ureteric bud, which triggers 
the epithelial conversion of blastema cells and the formation of 
primitive nephrons ( Fig. 1a,b ). Repetitive transient increases 
(waves) in intracellular calcium were observed in a majority of 
cells ( Fig. 1b -d and Supplementary Movie 1 ). Th ese calcium waves 
could be attributed to the release of calcium from intracellular 
stores. Cyclopiazonic acid (CPA), a sarco-endoplasmic reticulum 
Ca 
2 + -ATPase inhibitor, was used to deplete intracellular calcium 
stores. Application of the inhibitor caused, as expected, a temporary 
rise in intracellular calcium ( Fig. 1e ). Spontaneous calcium waves </p>

<p>were rarely observed aft er the initial temporary rise. Th e role of 
extracellular calcium in the propagation of waves was investigated 
using blockers of voltage-gated calcium channels or by removal of 
calcium from the perfusion buff er. Notably, infl ux of calcium from 
the extracellular space seemed to be of little importance for the 
spontaneous calcium activity in the embryonic kidney ( Fig. 1f,g ). 
Calcium waves were still observed in cells exposed to calcium-free 
extracellular medium and endured in the presence of nifedipine, 
an inhibitor of voltage-gated calcium channels. Th is is, to the best 
of our knowledge, the fi rst time that repetitive calcium waves have 
been observed in embryonic mammalian kidney. Repetitive calcium 
transients confer a unique precision and sensitivity on the activation 
of downstream target functions because of the numerous possibilities </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
Time (min) </p>

<p>Region number </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
60 
Time (min) </p>

<p>Region number </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>CPA 30 μM </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 
0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Nifedipine 50 µM </p>

<p>0 
10 20 30 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>2.0 
1.5 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>Zero Ca 2+ </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>X </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>Y </p>

<p>Z </p>

<p>40μm </p>

<p>1 
2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>30μm </p>

<p>F/F </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>F/F </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>F/F </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Figure 1 | Spontaneous calcium waves in embryonic rat kidney 
explants. ( a ) Orthogonal view of confocal images of embryonic kidney 
immunostained with Wt1 (red) and E-cadherin (green) antibodies to 
identify metanephric cells and ureteric bud cells, respectively. Note that the 
focal plane (dashed white line in the bottom image) is positioned beneath 
mesenchymal cells to visualize the underlying ureteric bud. ( b ) Pseudo-
coloured confocal image of an embryonic kidney loaded with the calcium-
sensitive dye Oregon Green BAPTA-1 / AM (10 μ M). Cells correspond 
to Wt1-labelled cells (red) within the selected region shown in panel a 
(yellow dashed region; yellow box, bottom and right image). ( c ) One hour 
recording of spontaneous calcium transients from regions 1 -5 shown in 
panel b. Traces presented as normalized fl uorescent intensity, F / F 0 . 
( d ) Binary representation of calcium traces shown in panel c. Each vertical 
line corresponds to a calcium peak defi ned as 9 % above background. 
( e ) Application of 30 μ M CPA caused a temporary rise in calcium, the 
calcium activity was negligible thereafter. ( f ) Kidneys were exposed to 
calcium-free extracellular solution, which did not affect the spontaneous 
activity during the observation period. ( g ) Spontaneous calcium transients 
were still observed after application of 50 μ M nifedipine. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>of temporal variations 
17 . Th e current observations should off er new 
tools for studies and understanding of pattern formation and kidney 
development. </p>

<p>Exposure to ouabain increases calcium activity . Exposure of 
embryo nic kidneys to ouabain caused a signifi cant increase in the 
number of calcium waves ( Fig. 2a,b ). Kidneys were exposed to 
vehicle or 10 μ M ouabain, a concentration that should activate the 
signalling function of Na,K-ATPase 
16 but have little eff ect on the 
pump function ( Fig. 2e ). Recordings were taken for 26 min, and the 
number of calcium waves per cell was counted. We found a signifi cant 
increase in the number of cells that displayed fi ve or more waves 
during the recording in ouabain-treated kidneys ( Fig. 2b ). 
We next examined the role of ouabain signalling in embryonic 
kidneys exposed to malnutrition. To mimic malnutrition, explanted 
kidneys were fi rst cultured with standard serum (10 % fetal bovine 
serum, FBS), and then starved by reducing the serum concentration 
to 0.2 % and exposed either to vehicle or to 10 nM ouabain for 24 h. 
As the on-rate of ouabain binding exceeds the off -rate 
18 , eff ective 
concentrations of ouabain can be considerably reduced (from 
10 μ M to 10 nM) when longer exposure times are used </p>

<p>13   . Spontane-
ous calcium activity was present in both groups of serum-deprived 
kidneys, but important quantitative diff erences were observed 
between ouabain and vehicle-exposed kidneys. In kidneys exposed 
to ouabain, signifi cantly more cells displayed multiple calcium 
waves per unit time compared with kidneys not exposed to ouabain 
( Fig. 2c,d ). Exposure to 10 nM ouabain for 24 h did not aff ect the 
intracellular sodium concentration ( Fig. 2f ). </p>

<p>Ouabain inhibits cell death and increases proliferation . Th e tran-
scription factor NF-κ B is a pleiotropic regulator of the inducible 
expression of many genes. Activation of NF-κ B is a calcium-dependent 
process </p>

<p>19   . Activation of the Na,K-ATPase / IP3R signalling pathway 
by ouabain has been demonstrated to trigger nuclear transloca-
tion and activation of NF-κ B. Here, we show that ouabain activates 
NF-κ B in serum-deprived kidneys ( Fig. 3a ). NF-κ B activates genes 
modulating apoptosis 
20 and development, as well as responses of the 
immune system. Apoptosis was found to be a prominent feature in 
serum-deprived kidney explants ( Fig. 3b ). Th e AI was 7.0 ± 1.7 % 
aft er serum deprivation for 24 h, whereas in kidneys exposed to nor-
mal serum for the entire culture period of 72 h, the AI was 1.9 ± 0.3 % , 
which is in the range of that previously reported. It is important to 
note that the apoptotic eff ect was completely abolished if kidneys 
were exposed to ouabain during the time of serum deprivation (AI 
1.2 ± 0.1 % ) ( Fig. 3b,c ). Th e antiapoptotic eff ect of ouabain required 
calcium release from intracellular stores. Th us, when serum-deprived 
kidneys were incubated with both ouabain and CPA, the AI was no 
longer diff erent from that observed in vehicle-treated kidneys. CPA 
alone had no eff ect on the AI. To assess the link between ouabain-
dependent NF-κ B activation and protection from apoptosis in the 
embryonic kidney, we used helenalin, an NF-κ B inhibitor. Helena-
lin abolished the antiapoptotic eff ect of ouabain, but had no eff ect 
on apoptosis on its own ( Fig. 3c ). 
Low concentrations of ouabain, which do not perturb the rest-
ing cellular ionic milieu, can stimulate cell proliferation 
21 . In rat 
embryonic kidney explants, the majority of proliferating cells are 
observed in metanephric blastema cells. Ouabain signalling was 
found to enhance cell proliferation in these cells to approximately 
15 % ( Fig. 3d,e ). </p>

<p>Ouabain increases expression of NF-B target genes . Th e molecu-
lar mechanisms by which NF-κ B protects from apoptosis in the embry-
onic kidney are not well understood. Th ey may involve enhanced 
activation of Wt1 and Pax2 , which belong to the large number of 
well-characterized genes that have been identifi ed to have a crucial 
role in pattern formation and diff erentiation of the embryonic kidney. </p>

<p>Both genes are activated by calcium signalling pathways and 
NF-κ B </p>

<p>22,23   . Th e expression of Wt1 and Pax2 mRNA was similar in 
serum-exposed and serum-deprived kidneys ( Fig. 4a,b ). In contrast, </p>

<p>Relative frequency of cells </p>

<p>with five or more waves (%) </p>

<p>Relative frequency of cells </p>

<p>with five or more waves (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>Relative frequency (%) </p>

<p>Relative frequency (%) </p>

<p>Min </p>

<p>Max </p>

<p>25-75% </p>

<p>Median </p>

<p>10% FBS </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>0.2% FBS </p>

<p>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>Time (min) </p>

<p>ΔR/R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>R/R </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 50 
1000 
0.8 </p>

<p>0.9 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.1 </p>

<p>1.2 
Control 
10 nM Ouabain </p>

<p>0 mM 
5 mM 15 mM 
μM </p>

<p>0 
1 0 
2 0 
3 0 
4 0 
5 0 
Time (min) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
≥5 </p>

<p>Waves per cell </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
≥5 
Waves per cell </p>

<p>P&lt;0.05 </p>

<p>P &lt;0.05 </p>

<p>[Na + ] o </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
-
10μM Ouabain </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
-
10nM Ouabain </p>

<p>Figure 2 | Ouabain increases the number of spontaneous calcium 
waves. ( a , b ) Acute effect of ouabain. Kidneys were grown in standard 
serum conditions (10 % FBS) and treated with vehicle (white bars) or 
10 μ M ouabain 1.5 h before and throughout the recording (grey bars). 
( a ) Histogram of the number of waves per cell during the observation 
period of 26 min. ( b ) Box plot of the relative frequency of cells that displayed 
multiple (fi ve or more) calcium waves during the observation period of 
26 min. Statistical signifi cance was estimated using the Mann -Whitney 
U -test, P &lt; 0.05, z = − 2.0831, n = 7 for vehicle-treated (white box) and 
n = 8 for ouabain-treated (grey box) kidneys. ( c , d ) Chronic effect of 
ouabain. The kidneys were serum deprived (0.2 % FBS) and treated with 
vehicle (white bars) or 10 nM ouabain (grey bars) for the last 24 h of culture. 
( c ) Histogram of the number of waves per cell during the observation period 
of 26 min. ( d ) Box plot of the relative frequency of cells that displayed 
multiple (fi ve or more) calcium waves during the observation period of 
26 min. Statistical signifi cance was estimated using the Mann -Whitney 
U -test, P &lt; 0.05, z = − 2.506, n = 10 for vehicle-treated (white box) and n = 12 
for ouabain-treated (grey box) kidneys. ( e , f ) Intracellular measurements 
of sodium in primary cultures of rat proximal tubule cells. ( e ) Ouabain 
dose -response. Cells were treated with different concentrations of ouabain. 
Graph shows the normalized 340 / 380 nm ratio, which increases as more 
sodium is accumulated in cells because of inhibition of Na,K-ATPase. Trace 
is an average from 15 cells. ( f ) Rat proximal tubule cells were treated with 
10 nM ouabain or vehicle for 24 h. Three-point calibration using sodium 
ionophores was performed to measure the baseline sodium concentration 
(0 -5 min). There were no differences between the initial sodium 
concentrations in ouabain-treated cells compared with cells treated with 
vehicle. Ouabain trace is an average of 20 cells. Control trace is an average 
of 40 cells. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>serum-deprived kidneys that had been exposed to ouabain had 
increased expression levels of Wt1 and Pax2 mRNA ( Fig. 4a,b ). 
Th ese results imply that exposure to malnutrition did not have 
a direct eff ect on Na,K-ATPase / IP3R signalling, but that the 
enhancement of this signal by treatment with exogenous ouabain 
could function to compensate for the loss of other, so far not identi-
fi ed, factors. Th e ouabain eff ects on Wt1 and Pax2 mRNA were abo-
lished in kidneys simultaneously exposed to ouabain and helenalin 
( Fig. 4c,d ). </p>

<p>Ouabain rescues nephron formation ex vivo and in vivo . As 
fetal malnutrition is associated with enhanced renal apoptosis and 
decreased rate of cell proliferation </p>

<p>24   , we next sought to determine 
whether ouabain may protect from the eff ects of malnutrition on </p>

<p>nephron endowment. E14 kidneys were either cultured under 
standard serum conditions (10 % FBS) for the entire culture period, 
or serum starved (0.2 % FBS) during the last 24 h of culture in the 
presence or absence of 10 nM ouabain. Kidneys were subsequently 
stained with markers for glomeruli and branching tubules ( Fig. 5a ). 
Serum deprivation caused a profound decrease in the number of 
glomeruli, but exposure to ouabain almost completely prevented 
this eff ect ( Fig. 5b ). Th e rescuing eff ect of ouabain required the 
release of calcium from the intracellular stores, as well as activa-
tion of NF-κ B ( Supplementary Fig. S1 ). Ureteric branching was also 
retarded by serum deprivation but rescued by exposure to ouabain 
( Supplementary Fig. S1 ). 
Th e studies conducted on kidney explants collectively indicate 
that ouabain protects from the adverse eff ects of malnutrition on 
kidney development. To test this concept in vivo , pregnant rats were 
given a low-protein diet. Minipumps delivering either ouabain or 
vehicle were implanted subcutaneously during the second day of 
pregnancy. Pregnant rats receiving a normal protein diet served 
as control. Th e off spring of all groups were killed at the age of 
4 weeks and kidneys were processed for stereological examination 
of glomeruli number. In rats, formation of glomeruli is completed at 
1 week of age. Consistent with reports from other investigators </p>

<p>24,25   , 
we found a highly signifi cant reduction in the number of glomer-
uli in the low-protein group as compared with the normal protein 
group. It is important to note that this reduction was abolished in 
the off spring of low protein-diet-fed mothers that had been exposed 
to ouabain during pregnancy ( Fig. 5c,d ). </p>

<p>Discussion 
In this study, we present a feasible principle for prevention of 
adverse fetal programming. Th e concept of fetal programming has 
emerged from a large number of human epidemiological and animal 
experimental studies, demonstrating a link between adverse expo-
sures during fetal life and adult-onset diseases </p>

<p>26,27   . Th e kidney is 
extraordinarily sensitive to the eff ects of an adverse environment </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>Apoptotic index % </p>

<p>10nM Ouabain </p>

<p>P &lt;0.001 </p>

<p>+ 
-
Activated NF-κB </p>

<p>% of Control </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>9 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>18 </p>

<p>BrdU Index (%) </p>

<p>P&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>P &lt;0.01 </p>

<p>0.2% FBS + 10nM Ouabain 
0.2% FBS 
10% FBS </p>

<p>5% FBS +1nM Ouabain 
5% FBS </p>

<p>100μm </p>

<p>50μm </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-
-
-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>1μM Helenalin </p>

<p>1μM CPA </p>

<p>10nM Ouabain </p>

<p>0.2% FBS </p>

<p>10% FBS </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
-
1nM Ouabain </p>

<p>5% FBS </p>

<p>Figure 3 | Ouabain protects from apoptosis in malnourished kidneys 
through the Na,K-ATPase / IP3R / NF-B signalling pathway. 
( a ) Ouabain increased NF-κ B abundance in the nucleus. NF-κ B p65 Trans-
aminase assay was used to detect translocation of NF-κ B to the nucleus. 
Values are mean ± s.e.m.; P &lt; 0.001, n = 3. ( b ) Representative confocal 
images of embryonic kidneys labelled with terminal deoxynucleotidyl 
transferase-mediated dUTP nick-end labelling (TUNEL, red) to detect 
apoptotic cells and 4 ′ ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole (DAPI, blue) to detect 
nuclei. ( c ) Ouabain reduced serum deprivation-triggered apoptosis in 
kidneys. AI was given as % of apoptotic cells. AI was determined by 
analysing 3 -4 randomly selected areas, with 1,000 -2,000 cells in each 
area, from three independent experiments. A volume of 1 μ M CPA or 
1 μ M helenalin abolished the antiapoptotic effect of ouabain. Values are 
mean ± s.e.m., P &lt; 0.01, n = 3. ( d ) Embryonic kidneys labelled with BrdU 
(5-bromodeoxyuridine, green) and DAPI (blue) to detect proliferating 
cells and cell nuclei, respectively. ( e ) Ouabain signifi cantly stimulated cell 
proliferation. BrdU index was given as % of BrdU-positive cells. In each 
preparation, 5 -7 randomly selected areas were examined and in each area 
around 1,000 DAPI-stained cells were counted. Values are mean ± s.e.m., 
P &lt; 0.01, n = 3. </p>

<p>Pax2 
Wt1 </p>

<p>Pax2 
Wt1 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>175 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>mRNA expression (%) </p>

<p>mRNA expression (%) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>150 
mRNA expression (%) </p>

<p>mRNA expression (%) </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>-</p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-
-</p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>+ 
+ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>10nM Ouabain </p>

<p>0.2% FBS </p>

<p>10% FBS </p>

<p>10nM Ouabain </p>

<p>1μM Helenalin </p>

<p>0.2% FBS </p>

<p>Figure 4 | Ouabain increases expression of Wt1 and Pax2 . ( a , b ) 
Expression of Pax2 mRNA ( a ) and Wt1 mRNA ( b ) in kidneys cultured on 
fi lters with or without ouabain, relative to control (10 % FBS), n = 7; Pax2 , 
P &lt; 0.01; Wt1 , P &lt; 0.01. ( c , d ) Expression of Pax2 ( c ) and Wt1 ( d ) in kidney 
explants treated with 1 μ M helenalin alone or combined with ouabain, 
relative to control (0.2 % FBS). Helenalin treatment abolished the increased 
expression of both genes observed after ouabain treatment, n = 7. Values 
are mean ± s.e.m. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>



<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>during critical windows of development. We have used the kidney 
as a model organ to test whether ouabain-triggered calcium -NF-κ B 
signalling may rescue from the eff ects of adverse developmental 
programming. 
Ouabain-triggered calcium release is mediated by direct inter-
action between Na,K-ATPase and the IP3R </p>

<p>9,13   . As these ubiquitous 
proteins are expressed from the very fi rst developmental stage, and 
as the role of calcium 
1 and NF-κ B 
28,29 signalling during development 
is well documented, we hypothesized that the Na,K-ATPase / IP3R 
signalosome might have a protective eff ect during development. 
Th e eff ects that Na,K-ATPase / IP3R signalling will have on normal 
development remain to be elucidated. Several lines of evidence sug-
gest that ouabain is a mammalian hormone produced in the adrenals 
and hypothalamus </p>

<p>30   , and that circulating levels of ouabain are high 
during pregnancy </p>

<p>31   . Ouabain functions by stabilizing Na,K-ATPase 
in one conformation. It is possible that, during development, altera-
tions in the conformational equilibrium of Na,K-ATPase, which 
would favour an interaction with the IP3R, might occur even in the 
absence of a ligand. 
Our results have important medical and socio-economical 
consequences. Experimental models have unequivocally shown that 
fetal malnutrition, caused by maternal calorie restriction or placental </p>

<p>insuffi ciency, leads to off spring with fewer glomeruli. Similarly, it 
has been unequivocally shown that low nephron endowment has 
an adverse eff ect on the outcome of all kidney diseases and is a 
major risk factor for chronic renal disease </p>

<p>3,6,7,25,32   . Studies on autopsy 
material have confi rmed that low birth weight, a hallmark of fetal 
growth restriction, is associated with reduced number of neph-
rons in humans </p>

<p>33,34   . A recent large cohort study, comprising data 
on all births in Norway between 1967 and 2004, showed that low 
birth weight was associated with a 70 % increased risk for end-stage 
renal failure 
35 . Chronic kidney diseases represent a major socio-
economical burden, both in industrial and developing countries. For 
example, there are now more than 20 million Americans who have 
some evidence of chronic kidney disease and are at risk of develop-
ing kidney failure, and the annual costs to treat kidney disease in 
the United States are more than one quarter (27.6 % ) of Medicare ' s 
expenditures </p>

<p>36   . Cardiovascular and renal disease risks are entwined 
through hormonal mechanisms, and chronic kidney diseases are 
associated with increased risk for hypertension and death in cardio-
vascular disease. Yet, despite overwhelming evidence that fetal 
malnutrition endangers kidney development and results in an irre-
versible loss of nephrons and increased risk for renal disease and 
hypertension, there is, as yet, no drug available that would allevi-
ate the eff ects of fetal malnutrition on nephron formation. Results 
from this study imply that ouabain, or analogues of ouabain, can 
effi ciently be used for this purpose. </p>

<p>Methods </p>

<p>Organ culture . Animal experiments were approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of the Karolinska Institutet. Embryonic methanephroi 
were isolated from E14 Sprague -Dawley rat embryos, and cultured on a Transwell 
fi lter (0.4-μ m pore size, CoStar ) within individual wells of a 12-well tissue culture 
dish containing 800 μ l of Dulbecco ' s modifi ed Eagle ' s medium / F12 media 
( Invitrogen ) supplemented with 10 % FBS. Th e kidneys were cultured at 37 ° C in 
an air atmosphere containing 5 % CO 2 and 100 % humidity for a total of 72 h. 
To starve kidneys, 0.2 % FBS was used during the last 24 h of culture. </p>

<p>Calcium imaging . Kidneys were loaded 50 -80 min before recording with the 
calcium-sensitive dye Oregon Green BAPTA-1 / AM (10 μ M, Molecular Probes ), 
and perfused with Krebs Ringer Buff er, consisting of, in mM, 100 NaCl, 4 KCl, 
20 HEPES, 25 NaHCO 3 , 1 CaCl 2 , 1.2 MgCl 2 , 1 NaH 2 PO 4 · H 2 O, 10 D -glucose, 
pH 7.35, at 37 ° C. In one protocol, CaCl 2 was excluded and replaced with 250 μ M 
ethylene glycol bis( β -aminoethylether)-N,N,N ′ , N ′ ,-tetraacetic acid ( Fig. 1f ). In-
tracellular calcium was imaged at 0.5 Hz using an argon laser (488 nm) and LP505 
long-pass fi lter on a LSM 510 Zeiss Duo inverted microscope . Image analysis was 
performed using <rs id="software-0" type="software">ImageJ</rs> ( <rs corresp="#software-0" type="url">http://www.rsbweb.nih.gov/ij</rs>/ ) and custom-made scripts 
in MATLAB ( Th e MathWorks ). Each calcium trace was normalized using median 
fi ltered baseline fl uorescence. Low amplitude and high frequency noise were 
removed from the normalized signal using wavelet transformations (Daubechies 
3-d order). In the normalized and fi ltered data, a wave was defi ned as a signal that 
is 9 % over baseline 
37 . </p>

<p>In vitro model . Whole-mount immunostaining of kidney explants was used to 
quantify the number of glomeruli and ureteric buds. Anti-E-cadherin (mouse, 
1:500 dilution, BD Bioscience ) and anti-Wt1 (rabbit, 1:200, Santa Cruz ) were 
used to detect ureteric branches and glomeruli, respectively. Alexa 488 antimouse 
(1:200, Molecular Probes ) and Alexa 546 antirabbit (1:400, Molecular Probes ) were 
used as secondary antibodies. Glomeruli and ureteric terminal tips were counted 
in the largest sagittal cross-section from each kidney. Th e number of glomeruli and 
ureteric terminal tips per maximal cross-section was taken as an index of total kid-
ney glomeruli and ureteric tip numbers 
38 . Results are given as the percentage of the 
number of glomeruli and ureteric branches observed in the control kidney, which 
is exposed to standard serum (10 % FBS) during the entire culture period. 
AI was determined using the ' ApopTag Red In Situ Apoptosis Detection kit ' 
( Chemicon ) according to the protocol for cryosectioned samples. Bromo-deoxi-
uridine, BrdU, incorporation was used to estimate cell proliferation. Th e cell 
proliferation kit (RPN20, Amersham Biosciences ) was used according to the manu-
facturer ' s recommendations for cryopreserved and cryosectioned samples. NF-κ B 
activity was measured by Th e TransAM NF κ B p65 Kit ( Active Motif ) according to 
the manufacturer ' s recommendations. Th ree to four kidneys grown on the same 
fi lter were used for nuclear extraction for each sample. </p>

<p>Ouabain treatment . Rat kidney cells are known to predominantly express the 
Na,K-ATPase α 1 isoform. Th is isoform is, in rodents, much less sensitive to oua-
bain than the α 2 and α 3-isoforms. Supplementary Figure S2 shows that the </p>

<p>Glomeruli number </p>

<p>% of control kidney </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>Total number of glomeruli </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>8 x 10 4 
P&lt; 0.01 </p>

<p>P&lt;0.01 </p>

<p>Normal 
Diet </p>

<p>Low 
Protein </p>

<p>Low 
Protein 
+Ouabain </p>

<p>Min </p>

<p>Max </p>

<p>25-75% 
Median </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>+ 
+ </p>

<p>+ 
-
-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>-</p>

<p>Ouabain </p>

<p>0.2% FBS </p>

<p>10% FBS </p>

<p>500 μm </p>

<p>Figure 5 | Ouabain rescues nephrogenesis in fetal malnutrition. 
( a ) Representative confocal image of kidney stained with Wt1 (red) and 
E-cadherin (green) antibodies to identify newly formed glomeruli and 
ureteric branches. ( b ) Serum deprivation in embryonic kidney explants 
( n = 15) decreased the number of glomeruli by 38 ± 4 % , compared with 
kidneys grown in 10 % FBS ( n = 9). In serum-deprived kidneys treated with 
ouabain ( n = 14), the number of glomeruli was not signifi cantly different 
than in kidneys grown in 10 % FBS. Values are mean ± s.e.m. P &lt; 0.01. 
( c ) Representative image of haematoxylin-and eosin-stained kidney used 
for the stereological examination of total glomeruli number. ( d ) Total 
number of glomeruli in 4-week-old rats exposed to a normal protein diet or 
a low-protein diet with or without ouabain during fetal life. Diagram shows 
total number of glomeruli per kidney. The total number of glomeruli per 
kidney, in rats exposed to low protein, was signifi cantly reduced. Ouabain 
rescued the effect of a low-protein diet with regard to glomeruli formation. 
The number of glomeruli in the low protein / ouabain-treated group was 
not different from the number of glomeruli in the control group. Statistical 
signifi cance was estimated using a two-tailed U -test, P &lt; 0.01, z = 2.836. 
n = 8 kidneys / group. </p>

<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>

<p>embryonic kidneys we studied only express the α 1-isoform. Th e ouabain concen-
tration required for signal activation is lower than that required for inhibition of 
ion transport </p>

<p>13,16 </p>

<p>. Here, we show that acute exposure to 10 μ M ouabain, which is 
the concentration we use for acute treatments, has a negligible eff ect on intracellu-
lar sodium concentration ( Fig. 2e ). As the on-rate of ouabain exceeds the off -rate 
18 , 
eff ective concentrations of ouabain can be considerably reduced when longer expo-
sure times are used. A volume of 10 nM ouabain was added to the culture medium 
during the last 24 h of culture. A 24 h exposure of rat renal cells to 10 nM ouabain 
had no eff ect on intracellular sodium concentration ( Fig. 2f ). In the proliferation 
protocol ( Fig. 3d,e ), we observed signifi cant eff ects using 1 nM ouabain. </p>

<p>Intracellular sodium measurements . Primary cultures of rat proximal tubule 
cells were prepared as described previously 
10,39,40 . Th e cells were loaded with 10 μ M 
SBFI-AM ( Invitrogen ) for 45 min at room temperature, followed by washing and 
30 min de-esterifi cation in normal media with 1 mM Probenecid ( Invitrogen ) 
at 37 ° C. Sodium measurements were taken at 35 ° C in a closed chamber ( FCS3 , 
Bioptechs ) with a cooled CCD camera ( ORCA-ERG , Hamamatsu ) mounted on 
an upright microscope ( Axioskop 2 FS , Zeiss ) with a Zeiss Fluar 40 × 1.3 NA oil 
objective. Excitation at 340 and 380 nm was performed with a monochromator 
( Polychrome IV , TILL Photonics ). Data acquisition and analysis was performed 
using <rs id="software-2" type="software">MetaFluor</rs> ( <rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">Molecular Devices</rs> ). Cells were superfused with Krebs-Ringer 
with 1 mM probenecid. Calibration was performed using perfusion buff er with 
[Na 
+ ] + [K 
+ ] + [Choline 
+ ] = 140 and [Na 
+ ] = 0, 5 or 15 mM, with 6 μ M Gramicidin D , 
20 μ M Monensin and 1 mM Ouabain (all from Sigma ). </p>

<p>Expression of Wt1 and Pax2 genes . Total RNA was extracted from a single em-
bryonic kidney using the Aurum Total RNA Mini Kit ( Bio-Rad ) according to the 
manufacturer ' s recommendations. Relative real-time reverse transcription -PCR 
was performed according to the manufacturer ' s recommendations for iScript 
One-Step RT -PCR Kit with SYBR Green ( Bio-Rad ). Quantifi cation was performed 
in quadruplet for each sample. Commercial 18S Classic II primers ( Ambion ) were 
used to control genomic DNA contamination, to normalize RNA quality and start-
ing quantity, as well as random tube-to-tube variation in reverse transcription (RT) 
and PCR reactions. Serial dilution of reference RNA sample as template was used 
to generate standard curve for each real-time RT -PCR experiment. Th e standard 
curve was constructed by plotting the log of the starting quantity of total RNA 
against the C t value. Th e starting quantity of Wt1 and Pax2 mRNA in each test 
sample was estimated using <rs id="software-3" type="software">iQ iCycler</rs> soft ware ( <rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Bio-Rad</rs> ) using values from the 
standard curve and normalized using 18S RNA as reference. Values are presented 
as % of control (10 % FBS in Figure 4a,b , 0.2 % FBS in Figure 4c,d ). Rat Wt1 mRNA 
structure 
41 (accession number X69716) was used to select Wt1-specifi c prim-
ers: upper, 5 ′ -TGCCACACCCCTACCGACAGTT-3 ′ ; lower, 5 ′ -CTTCAAGG-
TAGCTCCGAGGTTCATC-3 ′ . Th e position of rat Wt1 primers corresponds to 
a common part of all Wt1 mRNA splice variants. Th e rat Pax2 mRNA structure </p>

<p>42   (accession number XM_239083) was used to select Pax2-specifi c primers: upper, 
5 ′ -TACACTGATCCTGCCCACATTAGA-3 ′ ; lower, 5 ′ -GGATAGGAAGGAC 
GCTCAAAGACT-3 ′ . Th e rat Pax2 PCR fragment corresponds to human Pax2 
mRNA splice variants A and E (accession numbers NM_003987 and NM_003990, 
respectively). </p>

<p>In vivo study . Pregnant Sprague -Dawley rats ( Scanbur AB ) were given either 
a low (9 % ) or a normal (18 % ) protein diet ( Special Diets Services ) immediately 
aft er mating. Under Isofl uran anaesthesia, osmotic pumps ( Alzet Osmotic Pumps ), 
delivering either ouabain dissolved in PBS (15 μ g ouabain per kg body weight per 
day) or vehicle, were implanted subcutaneously on the second day of pregnancy. 
Th is daily dose of ouabain has previously been shown to result in plasma levels 
of ouabain around 1 nM 
43 and to have little side eff ects, except a slight increase in 
systolic (but not diastolic) pressure 
44 . Th e off spring of the three groups were killed 
at the age of 4 weeks and their kidneys were processed for stereological examina-
tion of glomerular number. Th e gender distribution was similar in all groups. 
Paraffi n-embedded kidneys were serially sectioned (10 -20 μ m slices) and stained 
with haematoxylin and eosin. High-resolution images were recorded using a 
5 × 0.16 NA objective and a motorized stage to cover the full area of each section. 
Images were automatically stitched together for a fi eld of view of 15 × 15 mm. Th e 
contrast of each image was adjusted to maximize detection of glomeruli. Stere-
ological analysis was performed using a modifi ed form of the disector method. Th e 
disector method is based on the analysis of image pairs, images taken of sections in 
direct succession, and identifi cation of unique objects 
25 . Th e density of glomeruli 
was calculated as the number of unique glomeruli divided by the volume of the 
slice. Kidneys were weighed immediately aft er dissection and kidney volume was 
calculated from the volume / weight ratio 1.040 
25 . Total number of glomeruli per 
kidney was calculated as density multiplied by volume. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis . Statistical signifi cance of the stereological counting of the 
total number of glomeruli per kidney, the acute eff ect of ouabain and chronic 
exposure to low doses of ouabain on calcium activity and the results of the in 
vivo experiments were estimated by the nonparametric Mann -Whitney U -test 
(two-tailed, P &lt; 0.05). For other data, one-way analysis of variance was applied 
( P &lt; 0.05). </p>



<p>ARTICLE </p>

<p>7 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 </p>

<p>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 1:42 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms1043 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </p>

<p>© 2010 Macmillan Publishers Limited. All rights reserved. </p>



<p>Acknowledgments </p>

<p>Th is work was supported by grants from the Swedish Research Council, Familjen Erling-
Perssons Stift else, the S ö derberg Foundations, the Swedish Heart-Lung Foundation, 
the M ä rta och Gunnar V. Philipson Foundation and the National Natural Science 
Foundation of China. We thank Ilaria Perini for experimental assistance and Jacob 
Kowalewski for help with calcium data analysis. </p>

<p>Author contributions </p>

<p>J.L., G.R.K., M.K., P.K.-Z. and X.-L.L. conducted experiments and analysed data. M.K. and 
G.R.K. were involved in the experimental design. A.A., J.L. and H.B. were involved in the 
overall study design. A.-C.E. was involved in the study design of the in vivo experiments. 
S.Z. designed and performed the quantitative RT -PCR analysis. A.A., M.K., G.R.K., J.L. 
and X.-L.L. wrote the paper. A.A. initiated the project. J.L. and G.R.K. contributed equally 
to the study. All authors discussed the results and commented on the paper. </p>

<p>Additional information </p>

<p>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper on http: / / www.nature.com/ 
naturecommunications </p>

<p>Competing fi nancial interests: Th e authors declare no competing fi nancial interests. </p>

<p>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ 
reprintsandpermissions/ </p>

<p>How to cite this article: Li, J. et al. Ouabain protects against adverse developmental 
programming of the kidney. Nat. Commun. 1:42 doi: 10.1038 / ncomms1043 (2010). </p>

<p>License: Th is work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-
Share Alike 3.0 Unported License. To view a copy of this license, visit http:// 
creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/ </p>

</text></tei>