<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2768238" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Purpose: To study the epidemic characteristics, transmission sources and routes of various subtypes of human 
immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) and sequence variations in Henan, central China. To provide theoretical 
foundation for Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS) prevention strategy in this region where the 
primary HIV transmission route was through former paid blood donation. Materials and Methods: HIV-1 gene 
env and gag were amplified by nested polymerase chain reaction (PCR) from uncultured peripheral blood 
mononuclear cells (PBMCs) obtained from 1,287 HIV-1 confirmed samples in Henan. Results: Among 1,287 
samples, 5 HIV-1 strains were found including subtypes B' (95.9%), C (0.47%) and recombinant subtypes CRF 
07_BC (1.09%), CRF 08_BC (1.79%) and CRF 01_AE (0.78%). Phylogenetic tree analysis found that 1,234 
Henan subtype B' were closely related to those commonly found in Thailand, and were distantly related to other 
international subtypes. The dominant strain in former blood plasma donors (FPDs) was subtype B', and the 
dominant strains in sexual transmission were subtype B' and BC. Among HIV patients who were most likely 
infected through routes other than paid blood donation, the percentage of non-B' subtypes was much higher than 
those of FPD. Conclusion: These findings suggest that the prevailing strain of HIV-1 in Henan is subtype B', 
similar to the B' subtype found in Thailand. In addition, for the first time we found subtypes C and recombinant 
subtypes CRF07_BC, CRF08_BC and CRF01_AE in this region. Indicating that the subtype feature of HIV-1 
became more complicated than before in central China. </p>

<p>That can more efficiently adapt to the localized 
outbreaks in regions such as Henan. 
Henan province is located in central China where in the 
mid-1990s thousands of paid blood donors were infected 
with HIV through the use of unsanitary equipments and 
the practice of reinjecting communally centrifuged red 
blood cells back into donors. After the banning of such 
practices in 1998, the Chinese government carried out the 
first mass screening of the former blood plasma donors 
(FPDs) in 2004 . By 2006, Henan was found to have 
21,828 confirmed cases of AIDS, and 35,232 cases of HIV 
with 7,107 recorded deaths from AIDS. 7-9 Henan province 
has the second highest concentration of HIV/AIDS in the 
country, and 53% of all AIDS patients undergoing ARV 
treatment live in Henan. 10 
Data collected from screenings in Henan have provided 
important information about the epidemiology of HIV in 
this community, but until now there has been little research 
into the subtypes distribution within this population. The 
following research and epidemiology analyses were carried 
out with 1287 HIV-1 samples found in Henan between 
year 2006 and 2007. </p>

<p>Specimens 
A total of 1,287 HIV-1 samples found in Henan between 
year 2006 and 2007, were confirmed as HIV positives. We 
collected 5-7 mL blood from peripheral vein of each 
subject. Anticoagulant ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid 
(EDTA) (1.5%) was used and centrifuged at 1,200 r.p.m. 
for 20 min within 4 hours after collection. Extracted 
Peripheral Blood Mononuclear Cells (PBMCs) of blood , 
preserving at -20˚C. </p>

<p>Extract nucleic acid 
We used DNA Blood Mini Kit (German QIAGEN Com-
pany, Hilden, Germany) to extract HIV-1 pre virus DNA 
from blood PBMCs according to the manual. Add 6 
µg/mL the lysate into protease K solution (10 mmol/L tris-
HCl, pH 8.4, 50 mmol/L KCl, 2.5 mmol/L MgCl2, 0.1% 
gelatin, 0.45% NP40, 0.45% Tween 228), making i t 6× 
106 cell density. Protease K was inactivated by heating at 
95˚C for 15 minutes, and the samples were stored at -20˚C. </p>

<p>PCR amplification and cloning 
According to the method of nested PCR, we designed 
several primers 11 (Table 1) and amplified HIV-1 gene env 
and gag. Primers were used for PCR sequence analysis of 
HIV-1 gene env and gag. 
Thermal cycling conditions of gene env as follows: For 
the 1st PCR reaction with primer (Env-B1/Env-4), 94˚C 
for 3 minutes, 52˚C 30 seconds , 72˚C 3 minutes, 1 cycle; 
94˚C 30 seconds, 52˚C 30 seconds, 72˚C 1 minute, 30 
cycles; 72˚C 10 minutes for extension. We take 1/10 matter 
of the 1st PCR reaction production, and process the 2nd 
PCR reaction with primer (Env-7/Env-8), the condition 
was at 94˚C for 3 minutes, 55˚C 30 seconds, 72˚C 3 min-
utes, 1 cycle at 94˚C for 30 seconds, 55˚C 30 seconds, 
72˚C 1 minute, 30 cycles: 72˚C for 10 minutes extension. 
Thermal cycling conditions of gene gag was a follows: 
For the 1st PCR reaction with the primer (gagF2/gage2), at 
94˚C for 5 minutes, 52˚C 1 minute, 72˚C 150 seconds, 1 
cycle; 94˚C 30 seconds, 52˚C 30 seconds, 72˚C 90 
seconds, 30 cycles: 72˚C 10 minutes prolong. We take 
1/10 matter of the 1st PCR reaction product, and processed 
the 2nd PCR reaction with primer (306/c--gag) as follows; 
at 94˚C for 2 minutes, 50˚C 50 seconds, 72˚C 90 seconds, 
1 cycle; 94˚C 30s, 50˚C 30s, 72˚C 1 min, 35 cycles: 72˚C 
for 10 minutes extension. </p>

<p>HIV-1 Subtypes Prevalence in Central China </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 50 Number 5 October 2009 </p>

<p>645 </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Table 1. Primers Used for PCR Sequence Analysis of HIV-1 Gene Env and Gag 
Primer 
Sequence 
Direction Location (HXB2) Length 
Env 
Env-B1 ATGGGATCAAAGCCTAAAGCCATGTG Forward 
6557 -6582 
1255 bp 
Env-4 
GCCCATAGTGCTTCCTGCTGCTCC 
Reverse 
7811 -7792 
Env-7 
TGTCAGCACAGTACAATGTACACATG Forward 
7002 -7021 
668 bp 
Env-8 
TTCACTTCTCCAATTGTCC 
Reverse 
7668 -7648 
Env-D 
CTGTTAAATGGCAGTCTGGCAG 
Gag 
GagF2 
ATG GGTGCG AGAGCGTCARTATTAA Forward 
790 -814 
1243 bp 
Gage2 
TCCAACAGCCCTTTTTCCTAGG 
Reverse 
2032 -2011 
306 
GGGAAA AAATTC GCT TAA GGCC 
Forward 
836 -857 
672 bp 
c-gag 
TAG TTC CTG CTA TRT CAC TTCC 
Reverse 
1507 -1486 </p>

<p>PCR, polymerase chain reaction. </p>

<p>Purification of PCR product 
PCR product after 1% gelose gelatin electrophoresis was 
checked and compared with standard markers, cutting 
peculiar amplify stripe (Qiaex of Qiaegen Company, 
Hilden, Germany) and HIV-1 DNA fragment was purified 
according to the manual. The circulatory DNA was 
dissolved as 10 mmol/L in Tris-HCl buffer (pH 8.7), after 
gelose gelatin electrophoresis and compared with standard 
molecular weight to estimate the amount of nucleic acid. </p>

<p>Nucleic acid sequence analyses 
We used env-D and 306 as sequence analyses primer, and 
used purified PCR product as template, using ABI Com-
pany mark sequence analyses Kit. We performed the seq-
uencing analysis by 9,600 PCR apparatus produced by PE 
Company. The dosage of template was about 1 µg and the 
dosage of primer was 6 pmol . </p>

<p>Sequence software analysis 
The nucleotide sequence of 1,287 samples aligned with 
<rs id="software-2" type="software">CLUSTAL W</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-2" type="creator">European Bioinformatics Institute</rs>, 
Cambridge, UK) software, 11 and the results acquired were 
and used for phylogenetic tree analysis after artificial 
adjustment. Reference sequence, which was downloaded 
from Los Alamos HIV Sequence Database (Los Alamos 
National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NM, USA), was used to 
identify the subtype of obtained sequence; Genetic distance 
between sequences was assessed using the software <rs id="software-3" type="software">MEGA</rs> 
<rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">3.1</rs> Kimura 2-parameter (Center for Evolutionary 
Functional Geromics The Biodesign Institute, Tempe, AZ, 
USA), 12 and phylogenetic tree was reestablished with 
neighbor-joining method. </p>

<p>Statistical analysis 
The intraclass genetic diversity and interclass genetic 
divergence were calculated with Kimura 2 parameter 
model. Statistical analysis was done by Mann-Whitney U 
test 13 and p value less than 0.05 was considered statistically 
significant. </p>

<p>Subtype analysis of HIV-1 
There were subtypes B',C and recombinant subtypes CRF 
07_BC, CRF08_BC, CRF01_AE in 1,287 samples. And 
respective percentages were 95.9% (1,234/1,287), 0.47% 
(6/1,287), 1.09% (14/1,287), 1.79% (23/1,287), and 0.78% 
(10/1,287). </p>

<p>Transmission routes 
As shown in Table 2, among the HIV patients whose trans-
mission routes were not former paid blood donors, the 
percentage of no-B' subtype was much higher than that of 
former paid blood donors. </p>

<p>Area dstributing caracteristic of HIV-1 subtype 
Among 1,287 HIV-1 samples, male constituted 680 
samples and female 607 samples. Age was between 18-59 
years. 1,144 as former paid blood donors (89.7%). 104 
infected by sex transmission (8.02%), 21 infected by 
receiving blood (1.63%), 10 infected by mother-to-child 
(MTC) transmission of HIV (0.78%), and 8 infected by 
injection drug use (IDU) (0.62%). There were 388 indivi-
duals who took medicine; 212 individuals taking Stavu-
dine (D4T) + Lamivudine (3TC) + Nevirapine (NVP). 147 
individuals Zidovudine (AZT) + 3TC + NVP, and 29 
individuals D4T + 3TC + Efavirenz (EFV). 
The main transmission route in Henan was paid blood 
donation. In these populations, most of former paid blood 
donors were subtypes B'. Among them, 1,201 were Henan 
natives. And 86 came from other provinces. There were 53 
samples that were no-B'subtype and, 45 samples from 
Henan native, including 11 samples that had outgoing 
working history. Eight no-B'subtype samples came from 
other provinces, including 1 sample from patient in Jiang-
men Guangdong (subtype CRF07_BC), who had no regular 
job. Other 5 samples came from immigrants from ruili 
yunnan, and they were all female living in xiangxian xuch-</p>

<p>Fei Zhao, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 50 Number 5 October 2009 </p>

<p>646 </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Table 2. The Transmit Routes of HIV-1 Subtype in Henan </p>

<p>Sex transmission MTC 
Former paid 
Receive blood 
IDU 
Total 
blood donate 
C 
3 (2.89%) 
1 (10.0%) 
2 (0.18%) 
0 
0 
6 
CRF07_BC 
8 (7.71%) 
2 (20.0%) 
2 (0.174%) 
0 
2 (25.0%) 
14 
CRF08_BC 
14 (13.49%) 
0 
8 (0.696%) 
1 (4.76%) 
0 
23 
CRF01_AE 
4 (3.85%) 
0 
5 (0.44%) 
1 (4.76%) 
0 
10 
B' 
75 (72.1%) 
7 (70.0%) 
1,127 (98.5%) 19 (90.5%) 6 (75.0%) 1,234 
Total 
104 
10 
1144 
21 
8 
1,287 </p>

<p>HIV-1, human immunodeficiency virus type 1; MTC, mother to child; IDU, injecting drug user. </p>



<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 50 Number 5 October 2009 </p>



<p>hn68 
hn70 
hn64 
hn73 
hn65 
hn72 
01AE. CM240 
hn67 
hn71 
hn69 
hn66 
01 AE.93JP NH1 
hn34 
hn22 
hn27 
hn30 
hn21 
hn28 
hn23 
hn33 
hn31 
07 BC.C54A 
hn32 
hn29 
hn25 
hn26 
hn24 
hn41 
hn37 
hn52 
hn59 
hn35 
hn44 
08 BC.97CNGX 6F 
hn47 
hn36 
hn51 
hn56 
hn49 
hn55 
hn50 
hn38 
hn42 
hn46 
hn39 
hn53 
hn40 
hn43 
hn54 
hn48 
hn45 
B.TH.90.BK132 
hn10 
hn08 
hn06 
B.RL42 
hn01 
hn09 
hn04 
hn07 
hn05 
hn03 
hn02 
A1.SE7253 
A2.97CDKTB48 
J.SE7022 
G.SE6165 
H.V1991 
D.94UG114 
hn62 
C.961W0502 
hn58 
hn63 
C.951N21068 
hn60 
hn59 
hn61 
N.YBF106 
O.SEMP1300 </p>

<p>0.3 
0.2 
0.1 
0.0 </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Phylogenetic analysis of the HIV-1 env C2 -V3 coding region of samples 
from Henan. We get all 53 non-B' subtypes and choose 10 B' subtype. </p>

<p>hn68 
hn73 
hn64 
hn67 
01AE. CM240 
hn66 
hn70 
hn72 
hn65 
01 AE.93JP NH1 
hn71 
hn69 
hn26 
hn34 
hn21 
hn30 
hn29 
07 BC.C54A 
hn22 
hn33 
hn23 
hn27 
hn25 
hn28 
hn24 
hn31 
hn32 
hn44 
hn57 
hn54 
hn48 
hn41 
hn38 
hn35 
08 BC.97CNGX 6F 
hn42 
hn39 
hn46 
hn50 
hn49 
hn53 
hn55 
hn56 
hn40 
hn52 
hn47 
hn45 
hn36 
hn51 
hn37 
hn43 
A1.SE94.SE7253 
A2.CDKTB48 
H.BE93.V1991 
C.SE.93.SE6165 
J.SE.94.SE7022 
C.951N21068 
hn58 
hn60 
hn62 
hn61 
hn63 
C.951N21068 
hn59 
C.ET.86.ETH2220 
D.UG.94.94UG114 
F1.FR96.MP411 
F2.CM.95.MP257 
K.CD.97.EQTB11C 
B.TH.90.BK132 
hn07 
hn03 
hn10 
hn05 
hn09 
hn04 
hn01 
hn08 
hn02 
B.RL42 
hn06 
O.SEMP1300 
N.YBF106 </p>

<p>0.15 
0.10 
0.05 
0.00 </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Phylogenetic analysis of the HIV-1 gag P24 coding region of samples from 
Henan. We get all 53 non-B' subtypes and choose 10 B' subtype. </p>

<p>ang; 2 samples (all subtype CRF08_BC) had IDU history, 
2 samples (subtype CRF01_AE and C) were infected by 
sex transmit, and 1 samples (subtype CRF01_AE) came 
from a former paid blood donor. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic tree analysis 
Phy1ogenetic analysis of the HlV-l env C2-V3 and gag 
P24 coding region of 1,278 samples from Henan by the 
neighbor-joining method. Genetic distances were 
calculated by the Kimura two-Parameter model. The scale 
indicates the relative phylogenetic distance. Bootstrap 
values were generated from bootstraprep replicates, and 
values greater than 70% are labeled. Reference isolates 
from other types N, O, subtype A, B, C, D, G, H, J and 
recombinant from CRF01_AE, CRF07_BC and 
CRF08_BC were downlo-aded from the HIV-l databases 
(http://hiv-web.lanl.gov). The bar represents l% genetic 
distance. 
From 2 figures, 10 AE sequence (hn 64-73) can be seen 
clustered together with subtype CRF01-AE.Th.Cm240. 
The inner group genetic distance of CRF01_AE were 
(5.676 ± 0.135)% (env), (4.329 ± 0.127)% (gag). In com-
parison with the sequence of respective international strains 
CRF01-AE.Th.Cm240, the genetic distance was (7.332 ± 
0.158)% (env), (6.562 ± 0.208)% (gag). 
10 B' sequence (hn1-10) clustered together with sub-
typeB.CN.RL42. The inner group genetic distance of B' 
was (7.342 ± 0.265)% (env), (6.831 ± 0.211)% (gag). In 
comparison with the sequence of respective international 
strains B.CN.RL42, the genetic distances were (9.327 ± 
0.245) % (env), and (8.562 ± 0.208)% (gag). 
14 CRF07_BC (hn21-34) clustered together with subtype 
CRF07-BC.CN.97.CN54A. 
The inner group genetic distance of CRF07_BC was 
(7.356 ± 0.265)% (env), (6.877 ± 0.201)% (gag). In com-
parison with the sequence of respective international strains 
B.CN.RL42, the genetic distances were (9.218 ± 0.167)% 
(env), and (8.551 ± 0.145)% (gag). 
23 CRF08_BC (hn35-57) clustered together with subtype 
CRF08-BC.97CNGX6F. 
The inner group genetic distances of CRF08_BC were 
(7.356 ± 0.265)% (env), and (6.877 ± 0.201)% (gag). In 
comparison with the sequence of respective international 
strains 08-BC.97CNGX.6F, the genetic distances were 
(6.278 ± 0.194)% (env), and (5.891 ± 0.121)% (gag). 
6 C sequence (hn 58-63) clustered together with sub-
type C.95IN21068. The inner group genetic distances of C 
were (4.576 ± 0.126)% (env), and (4.655 ± 0.209)% (gag). 
In comparison with the sequence of respective internatio-
nal strains C.95in21068 , the genetic distances were (5.214 
± 0.183)% (env), and (5.558 ± 0.156)% (gag). </p>

<p>Few countries to date have undertaken investigation of 
HIV molecular epidemiology in a multi-population setting 
in multiple locations. Although some have attempted to 
establish a database of comprehensive molecular epidemi-
ology data, budgetary, logistical, and time constraints have 
impeded past efforts. 14 
Between 1996 and 1998, China launched a program 
known as the National HIV Molecular Epidemiology 
Investigation Research Plan in which a comprehensive 
survey of all HIV-1 subtypes in China was documented. 
HIV-1 subtypes, A, B, C, D, E, F, G, BC, were found in 
addition to HIV-2, and the study also investigated the 
distribution situation of different populations and geogra-
phical locations. Of the 19 confirmed samples of HIV-1 
positive individuals from Henan, all were found to be 
Thailand subtype B'. From 2002 to 2004, the National 
Center for AIDS/STD Control and Prevention (NCAIDS) 
launched the National HIV Molecular Epidemiology 
Investigation Database Program, and in its first project 
1048 HIV positives samples from 26 provinces and munici-
palities were collected. 16 The results showed that 28 former 
paid blood donors from Henan were all of subtype B', 
confirming the results of the earlier survey study. 15-18 
As an inland province in central China, Henan province-
along with Hubei, Shanxi, Hebei, Shandong, and Anhui-is 
relatively underdeveloped and its rural population was 
particularly vulnerable to the commercial blood/plasma 
collection that took place in the early to mid 1990s. 19 As a 
result of unsanitary practices, many FPDs were infected 
with HIV, eventually accounting for 9.7% of all infections 
in China by 2003. 20,21 In more developed areas of China 
such as Guangdong, Jiangsu, and Fujian, the most pre-
valent subtypes of HIV-1 are A, AE, BC and are primarily 
transmitted through heterosexual intercourse sex and 
needle-sharing practices among injecting drug users 
(IDU). 22,23 In developing areas including Henan and Anhui, 
however, the prevailing subtype is B', with a low percen-
tage of subtypes C and AE, and the main transmission 
route is through unsanitary blood donation practices. 24 
The most recent round of research on HIV-1 strains in 
Henan is the most comprehensive and large scale HIV 
molecular epidemiology investigation to date, with a total 
of 1,287 samples from 18 cities. In addition, the popula-
tions sampled include not only FPD but also female sex 
workers (FSW), IDU, and men who have sex with men 
(MSM). Because this data were combined with infor-
mation from earlier molecular epidemiology surveillance 
work in the early stages of the HIV epidemic in Henan, the </p>

<p>Fei Zhao, et al. </p>

<p>Yonsei Med J http://www.eymj.org Volume 50 Number 5 October 2009 </p>



<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>results in this paper were based on the most compre-
hensive dataset available on the topic. 
Tracing the variation of HIV strains in an epidemic with 
regional diversity and multiple routes of transmission is 
important for developing better clinical treatment methods 
and to inform vaccine research. This study found that the 
HIV-1 subtypes found in Henan are more diverse than 
ever, signaling the need for corresponding preventive mea-
sure and further sophistication in the development of anti-
retroviral treatment therapies . </p>







</text></tei>