<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2661600" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-In skeletal muscle, insulin stimulates glucose 
transport activity three-to fourfold, and a large part of this 
stimulation is associated with a net translocation of GLUT4 from 
an intracellular compartment to the cell surface. We examined 
the extent to which insulin or the AMP-activated protein kinase 
activator AICAR can lead to a stimulation of the exocytosis limb 
of the GLUT4 translocation pathway and thereby account for the 
net increase in glucose transport activity. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Using a biotinylated 
photoaffinity label, we tagged endogenous GLUT4 and studied 
the kinetics of exocytosis of the tagged protein in rat and human 
skeletal muscle in response to insulin or AICAR. Isolated ep-
itrochlearis muscles were obtained from male Wistar rats. Vastus 
lateralis skeletal muscle strips were prepared from open muscle 
biopsies obtained from six healthy men (age 39 Ϯ 11 years and 
BMI 25.8 Ϯ 0.8 kg/m 
2 ). </p>

<p>RESULTS-In rat epitrochlearis muscle, insulin exposure leads 
to a sixfold stimulation of the GLUT4 exocytosis rate (with basal 
and insulin-stimulated rate constants of 0.010 and 0.067 min 
Ϫ1 , 
respectively). In human vastus lateralis muscle, insulin stimu-
lates GLUT4 translocation by a similar sixfold increase in the 
exocytosis rate constant (with basal and insulin-stimulated rate 
constants of 0.011 and 0.075 min 
Ϫ1 , respectively). In contrast, 
AICAR treatment does not markedly increase exocytosis in 
either rat or human muscle. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-Insulin stimulation of the GLUT4 exocytosis 
rate constant is sufficient to account for most of the observed 
increase in glucose transport activity in rat and human muscle. 
. Moreover, skeletal muscle GLUT4 trans-
location and glucose transport are increased in response 
to a wide range of stimulatory factors including contrac-
tion, changes in calcium release, and changes in the 
cellular energy status and AMP levels (19). 
To determine the extent to which insulin action stimu-
lates the exocytosis limb of the GLUT4 translocation 
pathway, and thereby account for the net increase in 
translocation, we have developed new methods for study-
ing GLUT4 translocation in rat epitrochlearis and human 
vastus lateralis skeletal muscle. We have specifically ex-
amined whether the stimulation of exocytosis following 
exposure to insulin or the AMP precursor analogue AICAR 
(5-aminoimidazole-4-carboxamide ribonucleoside) can 
fully account for associated increases in glucose transport 
activity. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Epitrochlearis muscle isolation. Male Wistar rats (150 -200 g) were ob-
tained from B&amp;K Universal, Sollentuna, Sweden. Animals were housed under 
a 12-h light/12-h dark cycle and had free access to water and standard rodent 
chow and were fasted (5 h) before each experiment. The Stockholm North 
Animal Ethics Committee approved all studies. Rats were anesthetized with 
an intraperitoneal injection of sodium pentobarbital (5 mg/100 g body wt i.p.). 
Isolated epitrochlearis muscles were incubated at 30°C. All incubation media 
were prepared from pregassed (95% O 2 /5% CO 2 ) Krebs-Henseleit buffer (KHB) 
containing 5 mmol/l HEPES and 0.1% BSA (radioimmunoassay grade). The gas 
phase in the vials was maintained at 95% O 2 /5% CO 2 . 
Open muscle biopsy. Six healthy men with no known family history of 
metabolic disorder (aged 39 Ϯ 11 years and BMI 25.8 Ϯ 0.8 kg/m 
2 ) volunteered 
for the muscle biopsy procedure. All subjects were instructed to avoid 
strenuous exercise for 72 h before the muscle biopsy. The subjects reported 
to the laboratory after an overnight fast. The study protocol was approved by </p>

<p>From the 
the ethics committee of the Karolinska Institutet, and informed consent was 
received from all subjects before participation. 
Open biopsies were taken from vastus lateralis muscle under local anes-
thesia (5 mg/ml mepivakain chloride), as previously described (20,11). Muscle 
strips were dissected, mounted on Plexiglass clamps, and incubated in vitro in 
pregassed (95% O 2 and 5% CO 2 ) KHB in a shaking water bath at 35°C. 
Glucose transport. Isolated rat epitrochlearis muscles were incubated in 
pregassed KHB containing 15 mmol/l mannitol and 5 mmol/l glucose for 20 
min. Muscles were transferred to fresh KHB and incubated with either 120 
nmol/l insulin or 1 mmol/l AICAR for the times specified in the figure legends. 
Muscles were then transferred to fresh KHB containing 20 mmol/l mannitol 
and incubated for 10 min to rinse excess glucose, followed by incubation for 
12 min in KHB containing 5 mmol/l 3-O-methyl-D-[ 
3 H]-glucose (800 Ci/mmol) 
and 15 mmol/l [ 
14 C]-mannitol (53 Ci/mmol). Muscles were blotted of excess 
fluid, frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored at Ϫ80°C. Glucose transport rate 
was analyzed by the accumulation of intracellular 3-O-methyl [ 
3 H] glucose 
(21). 
Akt and AMP-activated protein kinase phosphorylation. Muscles were 
homogenized and protein phosphorylation was determined as previously 
described (22) by Western blot analysis using anti-phospho-Ser473 Akt, 
anti-phospho-Thr172 AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK)-␣, or anti-
phospho-Ser79 acetyl CoA carboxylase antibodies (from Cell Signaling 
Laboratories). 
GP15 photoaffinity tagging of GLUT4. A biotin tag was introduced into 
GLUT4 using a photolabeling procedure. Muscles were incubated at 18°C for 
8 min in the presence of 1 mmol/l glucose-photolabel-15 (GP15) (23,24) and 
then irradiated for 2 min in a Rayonet photochemical reactor (Southern New 
England Ultraviolet, Branford, CT) using 300-nm lamps. Muscles were rinsed 
four times in ice-cold PBS and either frozen directly in liquid nitrogen or 
transferred for continued incubation. Muscles were stored at Ϫ80°C until 
analysis. GP15-tagged GLUT4 was identified as described (12) for the similar 
but shorter photoaffinity labeling compound Bio-LC-ATB-BMPA. 
Steady-state internalization of GLUT4. For internalization-trafficking time 
course experiments, rat epitrochlearis muscles were first incubated in KHB 
containing 15 mmol/l mannitol and 5 mmol/l glucose at 30°C for 20 min. 
Muscles were then transferred to fresh KHB and incubated with either 120 
nmol/l insulin for 30 min or 1 mmol/l AICAR for 50 min. Insulin and AICAR 
concentrations were maintained at these constant levels throughout the 
remainder of the protocol. Before GP15 photoaffinity tagging of GLUT4, 
muscles were transferred to fresh KHB containing 20 mmol/l mannitol for 10 
min to rinse away glucose. KHB was cooled to 18°C during photoaffinity 
tagging to slow transporter recycling. 
After irradiation, muscles were washed once in KHB at 18°C to remove 
excess GP15 label and were then transferred to fresh KHB and incubated at 
30°C to initiate internalization of the biotin-tagged GLUT4. At the specified 
internalization time points, 80 g/ml avidin (Pierce Chemical, Rockford, IL) 
was added for 6 min at 30°C to block transporters that were still at the cell 
surface. Muscles were rinsed four times in ice-cold PBS, frozen directly in 
liquid nitrogen, and stored at Ϫ80°C until analysis. The maximum signal of 
GLUT4, which internalized and escaped the surface quenching, was deter-
mined in each experiment from insulin-or AICAR-stimulated samples that 
were returned to the basal state and allowed to internalize the biotinylated 
GLUT4 for 60 min. Initial GLUT4 signal was determined in samples incubated 
without the addition of avidin. 
Exocytosis of GLUT4. For exocytosis experiments, human vastus lateralis 
muscles or rat epitrochlearis muscles were incubated at 35 or 30°C, respec-
tively. After 20 min, muscles were transferred to fresh KHB containing 12 
nmol/l insulin. Insulin-stimulated muscles were photoaffinity labeled with 
GP15 and subsequently washed with MES buffer (KHB with MES replacing 
HEPES), pH 6.0, for 5 min to terminate insulin stimulation. Muscles were 
maintained in KHB for 40 min to obtain maximal internalization. To begin the 
determination of exocytosis, 160 g/ml avidin was added for 6 min. Thereaf-
ter, muscles were transferred to KHB with or without 120 nmol/l insulin or 1 
mmol/l AICAR for specified times. The rate of loss of the internal transporters 
as they became quenched by the surface avidin was determined at the 
indicated time points. 
Curve fitting and analysis of rate constants. Values for net internalization 
of GLUT4 under steady-state conditions were curve fitted using a two-
parameter equation: F ϭ (1.0 Ϫ E).exp(Ϫk.t) ϩ E, where F is the fraction of 
GLUT4 remaining at the surface, E is the equilibrium position for internaliza-
tion, k is the net internalization-rate constant, and t is time. The contributions 
from exocytosis (kex) and endocytosis (ken) to the progress to equilibrium 
were determined using the following equation: F ϭ {kex ϩ ken.exp[Ϫt.(kex ϩ 
ken)]}/(kex ϩ ken) (11). Values for unidirectional exocytosis of GLUT4 were 
curve fitted to a single exponential equation: F ϭ exp(Ϫ k.t), where F is the 
fraction of GLUT4 remaining internal, and k is the exocytosis rate constant, 
and t is time. Individual experiments were analyzed, and the resulting </p>

<p>parameters were used to obtain mean and SE values, which were then 
compared in unpaired t tests. Differences were considered significant at P Ͻ 
0.05. Analysis and curve fitting were carried out using <rs type="software">Graphpad Prism</rs> 
software. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Comparison of insulin and AICAR treatment on glu-
cose transport activity in rat epitrochlearis muscle. 
Insulin stimulation of epitrochlearis muscle leads to a 
rapid increase in glucose transport activity that reaches an 
equilibrium level of stimulation three-to fourfold above 
basal levels within 20 min (Fig. 1A). Conversely, in re-
sponse to AICAR, the maximum level of stimulation is 
slower in onset and only reaches a level of stimulation 
ϳ2.5-fold above basal after 60 min. The maximum levels of 
stimulation by insulin and AICAR are maintained at a 
steady state for a further 30 min. At the steady state, the 
stimulation of glucose transport activity by insulin is 
slightly higher than that induced by AICAR. We assessed 
whether changes in the kinetics of GLUT4 trafficking 
induced by these treatments could account for the differ-
ences observed in glucose transport activity. We used an </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Comparison of the stimulation of glucose transport and cell-
surface GLUT4 levels by insulin and AICAR in rat epitrochlearis 
muscle. A: Transport rates were determined from measurements of 
3-O-methyl-D-[ 
3 H]-glucose uptake into muscle specimens incubated for 
the indicated times in the presence of 120 nmol/l insulin or 1 mmol/l 
AICAR. Results are means ؎ SE of six experiments. B: Levels of cell 
surface GLUT4 were determined by labeling muscle strips with GP15 
photolabel following 30 min of incubation with 120 nmol/l insulin (f) 
and 50 min of incubation with 1 mmol/l AICAR (Ⅺ). Labeled samples 
were solubilized, and the biotin-tagged GLUT4 was precipitated on 
immobilized streptavidin, resolved on SDS-PAGE gels, and then de-
tected and quantified by blotting with GLUT4 antibody. Results are 
means ؎ SE of six (insulin) and five (AICAR) experiments. </p>

<p>GLUT4 TRAFFICKING IN MUSCLE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

<p>impermeable probe (GP15) to tag GLUT4 transporters at 
the cell surface. GP15 consists of a glucose moiety that is 
recognized by the GLUT4 binding site and a biotin tag that 
can interact with avidin or streptavidin. The biotin and 
glucose moieties are separated by a very long spacer that 
allows access of avidin to the tagged transporter (23,24). 
We found that the higher increase in glucose transport 
activity following insulin stimulation versus AICAR stim-
ulation is matched by a slightly but insignificantly higher 
level of steady-state GLUT4 labeling by GP15 (Fig. 1B). 
In addition to the observed differences in the rate of 
onset of the maximal stimulation of glucose transport 
activity, insulin and AICAR produce a markedly different 
pattern of early signaling changes in the intermediate 
serine kinases, Akt/protein kinase B, and AMPK. Insulin, 
but not AICAR, action leads to a marked stimulation of Akt 
phosphorylation (Fig. 2A). Conversely, AICAR, but not 
insulin, action leads to a robust stimulation of AMPK 
phosphorylation (Fig. 2B) and the downstream AMPK 
substrate acetylCoA carboxylase (Fig. 2C). The slight 
increase in AMPK phosphorylation following insulin treat-
ment is not significant over a series of experiments or 
when corrected for total AMPK levels. The maximally 
rapid time frame for insulin-stimulated increase in Akt 
phosphorylation was within 2-10 min, and the AICAR-
stimulated increase in AMPK phosphorylation also oc-
curred rapidly and reached a maximum within 30 min (25) 
(H.K.R.K., A.V.C., H.A.K., J.Y., F.K., H.W.-H., J.R.Z., G.D.H., 
unpublished data). This increase is more rapid than the 
increase to maximal levels of glucose transport activity 
(Fig. 1A). 
Steady-state GLUT4 trafficking in insulin-and 
AICAR-stimulated rat epitrochlearis muscle. The 
maintenance of steady-state and maximal levels of glucose 
transport activity and cell-surface GLUT4 content (Fig. 1) 
could be due to a pulse of GLUT4 translocation, which is 
then followed by a cessation of subsequent movement as 
the cell signaling processes continue. Alternatively, 
GLUT4 could continue to recycle under steady-state con-
ditions, and the cell-surface GLUT4 level could be main-
tained by a net balance of a fast exocytosis and a fast </p>

<p>endocytosis rate of translocation. In adipocytes, GLUT4 
appears to continuously recycle during insulin-stimulated 
signaling (13,26,27). Therefore, we determined whether 
GLUT4 continues to recycle in rat skeletal muscle. The 
rate of net internalization of GP15-tagged GLUT4 under 
steady-state stimulation by either insulin or AICAR has 
been measured by separating the GLUT4 that remains at 
the cell surface from that which has been internalized. To 
do this, avidin is added to the muscle specimens after 
labeling. The initial cell-surface labeling (first lane in Fig. 
3A) is reduced by the avidin addition at the beginning of 
the time course (second lane in Fig. 3A). At subsequent 
times of incubation, GLUT4 internalizes and escapes the 
extracellular avidin. This gives a steady rise in the internal 
signal from the tagged GLUT4 at 5-60 min (Fig. 3A). The 
steady-state insulin stimulation is associated with rapid 
internalization that is almost complete within 10 min. The 
final level of net internalization occurs when approxi-
mately half the initial cell-surface GLUT4 is internalized 
(Fig. 3B). At this point, the exocytosis and endocytosis are 
balanced to maintain the surface levels of GLUT4. Con-
versely, the steady-state AICAR stimulation is associated 
with a slower initial net internalization, particularly over 
the first 5 min where the fraction of internalization is lower 
than that occurring in insulin-stimulated muscle. Addition-
ally, the rate of progress to the equilibrium level is not 
complete until 30 -60 min (Fig. 3B). This is associated with 
a slower rate constant for net internalization between 
AICAR-and insulin-stimulated muscles (0.059 vs. 0.134 
min 
Ϫ1 , respectively). Furthermore, the final equilibrium 
level of internalized GLUT4 is reached at a lower cell-
surface fraction (0.29) than that associated with insulin 
stimulation (0.52) (Fig. 3C). Further analysis of the steady-
state data (Fig. 3D) indicates that AICAR treatment is 
associated with a slower endocytosis rate constant (0.042 
vs. 0.068 min 
Ϫ1 ) and a much slower exocytosis rate 
constant (0.017 vs. 0.067 min 
Ϫ1 ). These kinetic parameters 
predict that the levels of glucose transport activity and 
cell-surface GLUT4 in AICAR-treated muscle will be 55% of 
those in insulin-treated muscle. These values are in rea-
sonable agreement with data presented in Fig. 1. 
The steady-state data reveal important differences in the 
kinetics of GLUT4 trafficking following insulin or AICAR 
treatment. However, the net internalization of GLUT4 
under these conditions is a complex kinetic process that 
involves both endocytosis of GLUT4 and its recycling 
(exocytosis). To further address whether AICAR-or insu-
lin-stimulated glucose transport and signaling activities 
occur by a convergent mechanism, we simplified our study 
design in subsequent experiments to only measure the 
exocytosis rate constant. 
Exocytosis of GLUT4 in insulin-and AICAR-stimu-
lated rat epitrochlearis muscle. To more directly mea-
sure the kinetic parameters of exocytosis, a procedure 
was adopted in which GP15-tagged GLUT4 was internal-
ized and then the unidirectional return to the cell surface 
was monitored. To internalize the GP15-tagged GLUT4, it 
was necessary to first label insulin-stimulated muscle and 
then reverse the stimulated state by washing with a low pH 
buffer that disassociates insulin from its receptor (28). To 
check that this procedure is adequately effective, we 
monitored the reversal of Akt phosphorylation (Fig. 2A). 
Akt phosphorylation is reduced toward basal levels within 
100 min. The return to basal levels of phosphorylation is 
incomplete; however, it is only necessary that the reversal 
process is sufficient to allow a detectable portion of </p>

<p>rat epitrochlearis </p>

<p>p-Akt Ser473 </p>

<p>p-ACC Ser79 </p>

<p>p-AMPK Thr172 </p>

<p>human skeletal muscle </p>

<p>B a s a l 
A I C A R 
I n s u l i n 1 
I n s u l i n 2 
R e c o v e r y 1 
R e c o v e r y 2 </p>

<p>p-Akt Ser473 </p>

<p>rat epitrochlearis </p>

<p>rat epitrochlearis </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Phospho-protein signaling in rat epitrochlearis and human 
vastus lateralis muscle. Immunoblots of p-Akt Ser473 (A), p-AMPK 
Thr172 (B), and p-CoA carboxylase Ser79 (C) in lysates of rat 
epitrochlearis and p-Akt Ser 473 (D) in human vastus lateralis muscle. 
Muscle lysates were resolved on SDS-PAGE, transferred to nitrocel-
lulose membranes, and incubated overnight with phospho-specific 
antibodies. Immunoreactive proteins were visualized by enhanced 
chemiluminescence. Conditions are as follows: basal, initial basal; 
insulin 1, 12 nmol/l insulin stimulation for 52 min; recovery 1, 102-min 
recovery after removal of initial insulin stimulation; insulin 2, restimu-
lation with 120 nmol/l insulin for 50 min after recovery; AICAR, 
restimulation with 1 mmol/l AICAR for 50 min after recovery; and 
recovery 2, 162-min recovery after removal of initial insulin stimula-
tion. The figure includes representative immunoblots from six inde-
pendent experiments. </p>

<p>H.K.R. KARLSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

<p>
GP15-GLUT4 to be internalized, and this was found to be 
adequate (Fig. 4A). 
The movement of GLUT4 from the internal compart-
ment to the plasma membrane was rendered unidirec-
tional by the addition of avidin at the cell exterior 
throughout the time course used to study the exocytosis. 
As the GLUT4 reaches the cell surface, its signal is 
quenched by avidin binding. The GLUT4 signal that re-
mains in the cell, therefore, represents the fraction of 
GLUT4 remaining internally, and this decreases with time 
(Fig. 4A). This allows curve fitting to a single exponential 
function even when the scatter in the data points is quite 
large (Fig. 4B). The scatter is an unavoidable consequence 
of working with single muscle samples for each time 
course data point. Insulin treatment increases the rate 
constant for exocytosis sixfold (0.010 in the basal state to 
0.067 min 
Ϫ1 in the insulin-stimulated state; P Ͻ 0.05). 
However, AICAR treatment does not significantly increase 
the apparent exocytosis rate constant. The rate constant is 
0.012 min 
Ϫ1 , which is close to the basal value. This 
exocytosis rate constant is in reasonable agreement with 
the steady-state exocytosis rate constant in AICAR-treated 
cells (0.017 min </p>

<p>Ϫ1 </p>

<p>). 
A limitation of the fitting of a single exponential function 
is that it assumes that the internal GLUT4 signal decreases 
continuously to zero. However, it may not (29,30). In the </p>

<p>basal and AICAR-treated cells, the release of GLUT4 may 
occur in a pulse and the internal GLUT4 signal may reach 
a plateau point at which no further release occurs. Thus, 
AICAR may stimulate a portion of the internal GLUT4 to 
be released. The fitting method we have employed may 
lead to an underestimate of the rate constant for this 
partial release. Unfortunately, the data are insufficiently 
precise for further analysis of this possibility. The more 
limited exocytosis response to AICAR cannot be due to a 
slow onset in AMPK activation, as we have compared 
basal and AICAR at times of exocytosis up to 120 min. 
Furthermore, the steady-state parameters were obtained 
following an extensive treatment with AICAR. Taking into 
consideration both the steady-state and the direct exocy-
tosis measurements, we cannot exclude the possibility of 
an AICAR-mediated increase in exocytosis; however, this 
effect is clearly smaller, or more limited as a pulse of 
release of GLUT4, than that occurring in insulin-treated 
muscle. 
Exocytosis of GLUT4 in insulin-and AICAR-stimu-
lated human vastus lateralis muscle. The exocytosis 
approach characterized in the isolated rat epitrochlearis 
muscle system was applied to human muscle strips. We 
confirmed that the reversal procedure adopted for the rat 
epitrochlearis was also applicable to human muscle (Fig. 
2B). A comparison of basal and insulin-treated muscle </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Internalization of GP15-tagged GLUT4 under steady-state stimulation with insulin or AICAR in rat epitrochlearis muscle. Muscle strips 
were incubated with 120 nmol/l insulin or 1 mmol/l AICAR and then labeled with GP15. The GP15-tagged GLUT4 was then allowed to internalize 
for the indicated times. To separately identify internalized GLUT4, avidin was added to the medium to quench the signal from cell surface-located 
GLUT4. Internal GLUT4 was then solubilized, and the biotin-tagged GLUT4 was precipitated on immobilized streptavidin, resolved on SDS-PAGE 
gels, and detected and quantified by immunoblot analysis with a GLUT4 antibody. A: Representative blots. init, initial labeling without avidin 
addition. B: By comparison of the initial GLUT4 signal with the signal at the indicated times, the level of cell-surface GLUT4 was calculated. C 
and D: Curve fitting to data from separate experiments was used to calculate rate constants as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. The 
curves in B were computed from the average rate constants in C. Results are the means ؎ SE of four experiments. *P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>GLUT4 TRAFFICKING IN MUSCLE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

<p>revealed clear insulin stimulation in the GP15-tagged 
GLUT4 movement out of the internal compartment and 
toward the cell surface (Fig. 5A). Curve-fitting analysis 
(Fig. 5B) and analysis of separate experiments (Fig. 5C) 
revealed that the exocytosis rate constant was increased 
six-to sevenfold (from 0.011 to 0.075 min 
Ϫ1 ). These 
rate-constant values and the six-to sevenfold stimulation 
are very similar to the changes occurring in rat epitroch-
learis muscle. This suggests that the same kinetic process 
is present, even under conditions in which the levels of 
glucose transport are quite different. The six-to sevenfold 
increase in glucose transport activity does not occur in 
human muscle, but this is not necessarily inconsistent 
with a large change in GLUT4 translocation, as additional 
factors may influence the glucose transport activity. The 
effect of AICAR on GLUT4 exocytosis in human muscle is 
less clear, partly because of the large scatter in data points 
derived from the samples available in the study (Fig. 5B). 
Calculation of the exocytosis rate constants (0.017 min 
Ϫ1 , 
Fig. 5C) indicated that there may be some slight, but 
statistically insignificant, stimulation of exocytosis above 
basal levels following AICAR treatment of the muscle 
strips. The observed exocytosis rate constant is, however, 
identical to that derived from the steady-state exocytosis 
experiment in AICAR-treated rat muscle. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Analysis of the trafficking kinetic data parameters for 
GLUT4 translocation in skeletal muscle is essential to 
resolve the site of convergence with the insulin-signaling </p>

<p>steps. If the site of insulin action is more fully resolved, 
this would help define where defects in GLUT4 traffic 
occur in insulin-resistant states and type 2 diabetes. By 
applying and extending use of our GLUT4-labeling tech-
nique, we have provided some of the first evidence that 
GLUT4 exocytosis in rat and human skeletal muscle is the 
major site of insulin action and that the magnitude of the 
stimulation of the exocytosis rate constant is sufficient to 
account for the observed insulin stimulation of glucose 
transport. 
Studies on relatively simpler cell-culture systems have 
revealed that GLUT4 traffics through multiple compart-
ments (31,32). In skeletal muscle, additional complexities 
in the trafficking route occur because of the large fibrous 
cell structures and the presence of a more complex 
transverse-tubule network of membranes. Recent studies 
on green fluorescent protein-tagged GLUT4 in skeletal 
muscle have highlighted the importance of the transverse-
tubule system and have led to the hypothesis that GLUT4 
is not translocated over long distances in skeletal muscle 
but is recruited from GLUT4 satellite compartments local-
ized close to the transverse tubules (17,18). Our photola-
beling approach is complementary to studies on GFP-
GLUT4, because we tag endogenous GLUT4, rather than 
expressed recombinant protein. However, the approach 
does not provide information on any potential differences 
in trafficking at the sarcolemma or the transverse tubules. 
Previous autoradiography studies using a tritiated version 
of a GLUT4 photolabel have provided evidence that the 
label does penetrate and label GLUT4 in the transverse-</p>

<p>FIG. 4. Exocytosis of GP15-tagged GLUT4 in rat epitrochlearis muscle. Muscle speci-
mens were incubated with 12 nmol/l insulin and labeled with GP15. Insulin action was 
then terminated by washing with a pH 6.0 buffer, and the tagged GLUT4 was allowed to 
internalize for 40 min. Muscle specimens were maintained in the basal state or 
stimulated with either 120 nmol/l insulin or 1 mmol/l AICAR for the indicated times. 
Avidin was added at the cell surface throughout the restimulation time courses; this 
reduced the signal for GLUT4 that exocytosed to the cell surface, thereby reducing the 
signal from internal GLUT4. The remaining internal GLUT4 was then solubilized, and 
the biotin-tagged GLUT4 was precipitated on immobilized streptavidin, resolved on 
SDS-PAGE gels, and detected and quantified by immunoblot analysis with a GLUT4 
antibody. A: Representative blots. C: Curve fitting for internal GLUT4 was carried out 
for the basal , insulin, and AICAR treatments and data from separate experiments were used to calculate rate constants as described in RESEARCH 
DESIGN AND METHODS. B: The curves were computed from the average rate constants in C. Results are means ؎ SE. Data are derived from seven, 
five, and three experiments for basal, insulin, and AICAR treatments, respectively. Basal experiments had at least three time points, but these 
were varied to allow comparison with early and late time points for the insulin or AICAR stimulations. *P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>H.K.R. KARLSSON AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

<p>
tubule locations in skeletal muscle (33). Additionally, 
molecules as large as a fragment antigen binding of an 
antibody can permeate into transverse-tubule spaces in 
heart muscle (34). 
The six-to sevenfold stimulation of the GLUT4 exocy-
tosis rate in the present study is greater than the fold 
stimulation of glucose transport. This effect is consistent 
with data on cell-surface GLUT4 labeling in rat (35) and 
human (12) skeletal muscle. This may occur because 
glucose transport is dependent on additional transporters 
such as GLUT1 that respond less effectively to insulin. 
Changes in GLUT4 endocytosis and storage will also 
influence the level of stimulation of transport activity. The 
absolute values of the rate constants obtained from rat 
(0.01 for basal and 0.067 min 
Ϫ1 for insulin at 30°C) and 
human (0.011 and 0.075 min 
Ϫ1 at 37°C) skeletal muscle 
studies are remarkably close to adipose cell studies. For 
example, basal and insulin-stimulated rate constants for 
GLUT4 exocytosis in 3T3-L1 adipocytes are 0.01 and 0.09 
min 
Ϫ1 , respectively, at 37°C (27). When the GP15 photola-
bel in rat adipocytes was used, slightly higher values were 
obtained (23). The similarity of these rate constants sug-
gests that the same fundamental process rate limits 
GLUT4 movement in these diverse systems and that this 
process is relatively unaltered by divergent cell architec-
ture and membrane tubule complexities in these differing 
cell types. 
Our studies on the AICAR compound are less clear. 
There are several technical problems associated with its 
use, including its slow onset of action. Even when GLUT4 </p>

<p>exocytosis is studied over 120 min, there is no clear 
evidence that this process is stimulated. In cardiac myo-
cytes, AMPK activation following hypoxia, mitochondrial 
inhibition (36), or metformin treatment (37) is associated 
with a reduction in GLUT4 endocytosis. Mitochondrial 
inhibition and a combination of AICAR treatment and PKC 
stimulation also lead to inhibition of GLUT4 internaliza-
tion in L6 muscle cells (38). We find that the initial rate of 
net internalization and endocytosis of GLUT4 in rat skel-
etal muscle is also reduced, but these changes do not 
reach statistical significance. The reduction in net inter-
nalization that is evident at early time points is masked in 
the steady-state experiments by the progress to a lower 
equilibrium level for the equilibration of the GP15-tagged 
GLUT4 during AICAR treatment. The endocytosis of 
GLUT4 is always a more difficult kinetic parameter to 
obtain and interpret than the unidirectional exocytosis 
parameter. This is because internalization is a net process, 
involving both endocytosis and re-exocytosis, and some 
recycling of GLUT4 will inevitably occur. These limitations 
may account for some of the controversies that surround 
the issue of whether insulin markedly reduces GLUT4 
endocytosis (16,39,40). 
Whether the observed 50% reduction in GLUT4 net 
internalization is sufficient to account for the full magni-
tude of the AICAR stimulation of glucose transport (a two-
to threefold stimulation) is incompletely resolved in this 
study. The slow onset of the increase in glucose transport 
is also consistent with a slowing of GLUT4 endocytosis. 
Our data suggest that a single site of convergence of </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Exocytosis of GP15-tagged GLUT4 in human vastus lateralis muscle. Muscle 
strips were incubated with 12 nmol/l insulin and then labeled with GP15. Insulin action 
was then terminated by washing with a pH 6.0 buffer, and the tagged GLUT4 was allowed 
to internalize for 40 min. The strips were then maintained in the basal state or 
stimulated with either 120 nmol/l insulin or 1 mmol/l AICAR for the indicated times. 
Avidin was added at the cell surface throughout the restimulation time courses; this 
reduced the signal for GLUT4 that exocytosed to the cell surface, thereby reducing the 
signal from internal GLUT4. The remaining internal GLUT4 was then solubilized and the 
biotin-tagged GLUT4 was precipitated on immobilized streptavidin, resolved on SDS-
PAGE gels, and detected and quantified by immunoblot analysis with a GLUT4 antibody. 
A: Representative blots. C: Curve fitting was carried out for the basal, insulin, and 
AICAR treatments, and data from separate experiments were used to calculate rate constants as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. B: The 
curves were computed from the average rate constants in C. Results are means ؎ SE. Where no error bar is shown, n ‫؍‬ 2. Data are derived from 
four, four, and two experiments for basal, insulin, or AICAR treatment, respectively. In basal experiments, time points were varied to allow 
comparison with early and late time points for the insulin and AICAR stimulations. *P &lt; 0.05. </p>

<p>GLUT4 TRAFFICKING IN MUSCLE </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

<p>AMPK-and Akt-signaling pathways on a single intermedi-
ate such as AS160 (7,41-43) cannot fully and simulta-
neously account for regulation of GLUT4 traffic at the level 
of both exocytosis and endocytosis. Indeed, AS160 action 
is reported to be localized to the exocytosis rather than the 
endocytosis arm of GLUT4 traffic (40). 
The steady-state recycling experiments are of interest 
and mechanistic importance because they show that in 
muscle, GLUT4 continues to recycle in both the insulin-
and AICAR-stimulated states. In contrast to earlier (44,45), 
but not later, versions of the translocation hypothesis (13), 
GLUT4 is not released as a transitory pulse to the cell 
surface where it would then be resident while the stimulus 
remains. Instead, GLUT4 continues to recycle even when 
the stimulus is maintained (13,27). However, the observed 
recycling could be consistent with a variant of the pulse 
model in which GLUT4 is released in a pulse from a 
reservoir compartment to the cell surface and then on to 
the endosome system, within which it continues to recycle 
while the stimulus remains (29,30). 
In conclusion, our demonstration that exocytosis is the 
major site of insulin action on GLUT4 traffic in rat and 
human skeletal muscle suggests that a focus on this limb 
of the GLUT4 traffic pathway in insulin-resistant condi-
tions such as type 2 diabetes will be necessary and 
appropriate to resolve defects in glucose metabolism in 
future studies. Because of the technical challenges and 
limitations described above, the photolabeling approach 
will only give a partial and incomplete analysis in future 
studies. Nevertheless, the approach described is comple-
mentary to more dynamic studies in which GLUT4 is 
analyzed at a detailed subcellular level (18). </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work was supported by grants from the Medical 
Research Council (U.K.), the Wellcome Trust, the Euro-
pean Foundation for the Study of Diabetes, the Swedish 
Research Council, the Swedish Diabetes Association, the 
Strategic Research Foundation, the Knut and Alice Wal-
lenberg Foundation, the Finnish Cultural Foundation and 
Commission of the European Communities (contract nos. 
LSHM-CT-2004-005272 EXGENESIS and LSHM-CT-2004-
512013 EUGENE2), the European Research Council, the 
Finnish Academy of Science, the Finnish Diabetes Re-
search Foundation, and the Sigrid Juselius Foundation. 
This study also received grant support from the Novo 
Nordisk Research Foundation. No other potential conflicts 
of interest relevant to this article were reported. </p>

<p> </p>



<p>
 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, APRIL 2009 </p>

</text></tei>