<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2881388" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-08-19T00:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Motivation: The results of initial analyses for many high-throughput 
technologies commonly take the form of gene or protein sets, and 
one of the ensuing tasks is to evaluate the functional coherence of 
these sets. The study of gene set function most commonly makes 
use of controlled vocabulary in the form of ontology annotations. 
For a given gene set, the statistical significance of observing these 
annotations or 'enrichment' may be tested using a number of 
methods. Instead of testing for significance of individual terms, this 
study is concerned with the task of assessing the global functional 
coherence of gene sets, for which novel metrics and statistical 
methods have been devised. 
Results: The metrics of this study are based on the topological 
properties of graphs comprised of genes and their Gene Ontology 
annotations. A novel aspect of these methods is that both the 
enrichment of annotations and the relationships among annotations 
are considered when determining the significance of functional 
coherence. We applied our methods to perform analyses on an 
existing database and on microarray experimental results. Here, we 
demonstrated that our approach is highly discriminative in terms 
of differentiating coherent gene sets from random ones and that it 
provides biologically sensible evaluations in microarray analysis. We 
further used examples to show the utility of graph visualization as a 
tool for studying the functional coherence of gene sets. 
Availability: The implementation is provided as a freely accessible 
For a gene set, the functional coherence is a measure of the strength 
of the relatedness of the functions associated with the genes, which 
can be used to differentiate a set of genes performing coherently 
related functions from ones consisting of randomly grouped genes. 
It is commonly evaluated by analyzing the genes' functional 
annotations, which are almost invariably in the form of the controlled 
vocabulary from the Gene Ontology (GO; Ashburner et al., 2000; 
Brown et al., 2000; Huang et al., 2009; Khatri and Dr˘ aghici, 2005; 
Mateos et al., 2002). The vocabulary terms are organized as a 
graph, with concepts ranging from very general to very specific. </p>

<p> *  To whom correspondence should be addressed. </p>

<p>They are used to annotate gene products by a variety of methods, 
including human curation, based on evidence from the literature. 
The annotations capture what is known about the biology. Functional 
coherence can be reflected in two aspects. First, whether genes share 
similar functions or whether they participate in the same biological 
processes. For example, if a sufficient number of genes from a set 
are annotated with a common GO term, the annotation is considered 
to be 'enriched' and, therefore, the genes are deemed functionally 
coherent. Second, whether the distinct functions are related. The 
relationship between functional annotations can be either semantic 
or biological in nature. For example, if a gene is annotated with the 
term regulation of apoptosis and another one is labeled with the term 
induction of apoptosis, their functions can be considered coherent 
because the terms are semantically alike. Alternatively, annotations 
can be semantically distinct, e.g. apoptosis and electron transport 
chain, yet their co-occurrence in a gene set can be biologically 
meaningful if many genes in the set participate in both processes. 
Ideally, a measure of functional coherence should take the above 
aspects into account during evaluation. To date, a method unifying 
the enrichment and relatedness aspects of functional coherence 
remains to be developed. 
The first aspect of functional coherence, evaluating GO term 
enrichment, is usually performed by various count-based methods 
that evaluate the probability of observing a GO term in a set 
by random chance-to determine if an individual term is over-
represented in a gene set. The widely used count-based methods 
are based on the hypergeometric distribution or other similar 
probabilistic models (Cho et al., 2001; Huang et al., 2009; Khatri 
and Dr˘ aghici, 2005; Man et al., 2000). The merits and limitations of 
this family of methods are well documented (Khatri and Dr˘ aghici, 
2005; Zheng and Lu, 2007). Since the objective of count-based 
methods is focused on individual terms, directly utilizing their 
results, e.g. P-values, to assess overall coherence encounters the 
following difficulties: (i) schemes (ad hoc or sophisticated) need to 
be devised in order to combine the results of individual tests into a 
unified measure; (ii) the relationships among the terms are ignored 
by treating each annotation independently; and (iii) multiple testing 
potentially leads to false positives results, thus a less reliable unified 
measure. 
The second aspect, evaluating the relatedness among distinct 
annotations, has been investigated in several studies that utilized the 
directed acyclic graph (DAG) representation of the GO. A number 
of studies have used the ontology graph structure in the context of 
functional analyses; however, the specific purpose or information 
used often differs from the methods proposed in this study, making 
a direct comparison between methods less meaningful. One theme 
is to find the representative summary term(s) utilizing the graph </p>

<p>© The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i80 i79-i87 </p>

<p>A.J.Richards et al. </p>

<p>structure. For example, the lowest common ancestor terms have been 
used to find summarizing GO terms (Lee et al., 2004). Making use 
of the topology of the GO graph, Alexa et al. (2006) devised several 
algorithms to identify the representative GO terms and further to 
reweight the scores of the terms. Another theme utilizing the GO 
graph structure is to quantify the semantic relationships among the 
GO terms and derive statistics to assess their similarity. For example, 
the average of pairwise shortest paths between the annotated terms 
has been used to develop both pairwise and group-level measures 
of gene set similarity (Ruths et al., 2009; Wang et al., 2007). Other 
authors have used semantic similarity to summarize the results of 
enrichment analyses (Xu et al., 2009). Another measure of similarity, 
the total ancestry measure, was developed by Yu and co-workers 
(Yu et al., 2007) to summarize the functional similarity of GO terms 
from a gene set. Furthermore, GO graph-based studies have been 
carried out to evaluate the functional coherence of gene sets via the 
integration of multiple data sources. Several methods make use of 
microarray expression data (Goeman and Mansmann, 2008; Kong 
et al., 2006), while others use the biomedical literature associated 
with genes (Raychaudhuri and Altman, 2003; Zheng and Lu, 2007). 
However, none of these methods have considered both aspects 
of functional coherence, nor have they explicitly considered the 
relationships among GO terms co-annotating genes, which provide 
additional biological information. 
In this study, we introduce a novel approach to assess the 
functional coherence of gene sets by taking into account both the 
enrichment of GO terms and their relationships among terms, of 
which a conceptual overview is illustrated in Figure 1. Our methods 
offer three novel aspects. First, the genes and their annotations are 
represented with a subgraph derived from the GO graph, in which 
genes and GO terms are represented as nodes, and their relationships 
are represented as quantifiable edges (gene-to-term and term-to-
term). By studying the topological properties of the graph with 
methods from graph theory (Barabási and Oltvai, 2004; Newman, 
2003), we have identified a set of metrics that reflect both the 
enrichment of GO terms and the relationships among them, which 
makes possible the differentiation of known coherent gene sets from 
randomly grouped ones. Second, we utilized the information of co-
annotation of genes by a pair GO terms, a source of information 
ignored by most of contemporary methods, to further enhance the 
discriminative power of the graph-based metrics. Finally, we have 
developed a principled framework by employing simulation and 
non-parametric statistical methods, which enables us to directly 
test the null hypothesis that a gene set consists of random grouped 
genes. When applied to the gene sets from the Kyoto Encyclopedia 
of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) database (Kanehisa et al., 2006), 
the metrics were shown to be highly discriminative in terms of 
differentiating known coherent gene sets from random ones; when 
tested on gene sets derived from microarray analysis, the metrics 
provided biologically sensible assessments. </p>

<p>2 METHODS </p>

<p>2.1 Constructing GO-based graphs </p>

<p>For each organism considered in the study (Saccharomyces cerevisiae, 
Mus musculus and Homo sapiens), a specific gene-GO association file 
was downloaded from the website of the GO Annotation project of the 
European Bioinformatics Institute (August 13, 2009) from http://www 
.geneontology.org/GO.current.annotations.shtml. Additionally, on the same </p>

<p>Fig. 1. Conceptual overview of graph-based functional coherence 
evaluation. (A) A graph representation of the GO is constructed and referred 
to as a GOGeneGraph, in which a node is a GO term or a gene, and an 
edge reflects the semantic relationship between a pair of GO terms or gene-
term relationship. (B) A GOI is produced by high-throughput technology 
or other methods. (C) A GO Steiner tree is extracted and several types 
of network statistics of the GO Steiner tree are collected. (D) Through 
simulation experiments, the distributions of the network statistics from 
randomly grouped gene sets are estimated. (E) The hypothesis that the GOI 
belongs to the population of the random gene sets is tested and a P-value is 
returned. In addition, users may choose from several visualization tools to 
discover more about the functional relationships between the GOI. </p>

<p>day an ontology file was downloaded from http://archive.geneontology.org/ 
latest-termdb/go_daily-termdb.obo-xml.gz. The definition file was also 
downloaded from the GO website and it was used to construct a DAG 
in the biological process subspace. We have developed a Python library 
with a set of application programming interfaces for building different GO-
related graphs and performing various queries (Muller et al., 2009). This 
library is based on the Python package <rs type="software">NetworkX</rs> (Hagberg et al., 2008). 
In a graph representation of the GO, referred to as GOGraph, each node 
(vertex) represents a GO term and each directed edge corresponds to the 
IS_A relationship between a parent-child GO term pair. The directed edges 
between terms represent their semantic relationship such that the concept of 
a parent node subsumes those of its children nodes. Hence, the constructed 
GOGraph obeys the 'true path rule' or in other words the pathway from a 
child term to the most top-level parent is always true. Then, genes are added 
as another type of node to the GOGraph via an edge to its associated GO 
term(s) to create the GOGeneGraph. The GOGeneGraph is further modified 
by the addition of edges between terms that share the same gene annotations. 
Associating GO terms with the genes they annotate enables the calculation of 
semantic distance for edges from a GOGraph using the established methods, 
see Section 2.2 for details. After initialization of the edge distances, the 
graph is further transformed into a weighted, undirected graph, so that the 
functional coherence of list of GO terms can be reflected by connectivity 
and distances among the terms rather than the directionality. The algorithm 
for constructing a GOGeneGraph is detailed in Supplementary Algorithm 1. </p>

<p>2.2 Semantic distance </p>

<p>A commonly used method to measure the semantic distance between terms 
is based on information theory, in which differences in the information </p>

<p>i80 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i81 i79-i87 </p>

<p>Graph-based gene set coherence </p>

<p>content (IC; Jiang and Conrath, 1998; Lord et al., 2003; Pesquita et al., 
2009; Resnik, 1995) of semantic entities are employed as a measure of the 
semantic distance. Adopting the same principle, the IC of a GO term was 
calculated as follows: 
IC(t) =−lnP(t), 
(1) 
where P(t) is the number of annotation instances for the term divided by total 
number of annotation instances from the annotation database. We can then 
define the semantic distance between a parent-child pair of GO terms as </p>

<p>dist(t p ,t c ) =|IC(t p )−IC(t c )|. 
(2) </p>

<p>Adding gene nodes into a GOGraph introduces new paths/connections 
between a pair of GO terms (through term-gene-term paths), if they share one 
or more genes. Thus, a GOGeneGraph not only provides information about 
the semantic relationship between terms according to the GO definitions, but 
also reveals the presence of biological relationships between terms according 
to biological annotation evidence. To quantify the strength of a biological 
relationship, a new term-to-term edge is added between a pair of terms 
sharing one or more genes. The distance for a given new edge is then set 
to the length of the semantic edge in the GOGraph G occupying the fifth 
percentile d P 5 divided by the number of genes shared by the pair </p>

<p>d i,j = 
d P 5 ∈{d G } 
|g i,j | 
, 
(3) </p>

<p>where d G is the set of all edge distances in the GOGraph G and |g i,j | is 
the number of genes providing biological connections between GO terms 
i and j. Equation 3 reflects the following reasonings: (i) co-annotation is 
relatively rare event and often biologically meaningful, thus its semantic 
distance should correspond to a significantly short distance for which we 
chose the fifth percentile of all edges; and (ii) the more genes that provide 
the connection between a pair of GO terms, the shorter the distance and the 
stronger the biological relationship between the terms. </p>

<p>2.3 Extracting a GO Steiner tree </p>

<p>Given a gene set, the GO terms associated with the genes, referred to as seed 
terms, are identified in the GOGeneGraph. To investigate the relationship 
among the seed terms, we extract a subgraph connecting the seed terms, 
including both inherited term-term and augmented term-term edges [see 
Equations (2) and (3)], such that the sum of all edge lengths for the subgraph 
is minimized for all possible subgraphs connecting the terms. The problem 
of finding such a subgraph is known as the Steiner-tree problem in computer 
science (Gilbert and Pollak, 1968). We refer to the Steiner tree subgraph of a 
GOGeneGraph as a GO Steiner tree (T st ). In this study, Kou's algorithm (Kou 
et al., 1981) is adopted to extract a GO Steiner tree from a GOGeneGraph. 
The heuristic algorithm for obtaining T st is summarized in Supplementary 
Algorithm 2. </p>

<p>2.4 Graph-based functional coherence metrics </p>

<p>Three metrics were devised based on the topological properties of GO Steiner 
trees in order to reflect the functional coherence of a gene set. Building on the 
concept of enrichment, we define the number of genes associated with a seed 
term as seed degree (k s ) and the averaged seed degree of a tree, is denoted as 
k s , which reflects a global measure of enrichment for the GO terms in the </p>

<p>gene set. To integrate the semantic relationships between terms, we define 
the sum of the lengths of all edges within a tree as the total length (l) of a 
GO Steiner tree, which reflects the overall relatedness of the functions. We 
also define k rs = ks 
l as a measure of relative seed degree, which combines 
the above two aspects of functional coherence. The GO Steiner-tree metrics 
k s and l are produced by summing a number of variables, in proportion to </p>

<p>the size of a gene set n and with respect to a given n they tend to be Gaussian 
distributed, with estimable parameters µ n and σ 2 
n . </p>

<p>2.5 Non-parametric regression </p>

<p>The distribution of the aforementioned metrics change as the size of the gene 
set (n) changes. In particular, the mean and variance may exhibit a distinct </p>

<p>relationship with the get set size. To capture these relationships, we adopted 
a non-parametric regression method (Nadaraya, 1964) to estimate the means 
and variances, µ n and σ 2 
n , of trees as nonlinear functions of n. Let y n denote 
the value of a metric from a GO Steiner tree with size of n. We then define 
the following relationships: </p>

<p>µ n = f (n) 
(4) </p>

<p>σ 2 
n = g(n) 
(5) </p>

<p>y n ∼ N (µ n ,σ 2 
n ). 
(6) </p>

<p>The relationship between the gene set size n and the parameters governing 
the graph-based metrics y n for the random gene sets was investigated by 
sampling a large number of randomly generated gene sets as training data, 
D ={(y i ,n i )} </p>

<p>|D| </p>

<p>i=1 , followed by estimation of the parameters µ n and σ 2 
n for a 
n as follows: </p>

<p>ˆ 
µ n = </p>

<p>|D| </p>

<p>i=1 w n (n i )y i 
|D| </p>

<p>i=1 w n (n i ) </p>

<p>(7) </p>

<p>ˆ 
σ 2 
n = </p>

<p>|D| </p>

<p>i=1 w n (n i )(y i − ˆ 
µ n ) 2 
|D| </p>

<p>i=1 w n (n i ) </p>

<p>(8) </p>

<p>w n (n i ) = exp </p>



<p>− 
1 
p 
(n i −n) 2 </p>



<p>, 
(9) </p>

<p>where wn(n i ) </p>

<p>|D| 
i=1 wn(n i ) </p>

<p>is the Nadaraya-Watson weight for the i-th observation </p>

<p>and w n the Gaussian kernel function with bandwidth parameter p, which 
was set to 15 for all regressions in this study. All numerical analyses were 
carried out using the Python package Numpy (http://numpy.scipy.org) and 
the statistical language R (http://www.r-project.org). 
The assumption that k s and l are Gaussian distributed with respect to the 
size of a gene set n was tested using the Shapiro-Wilk (Shapiro and Wilk, 
1965) test, as implemented in R, and the results (see Supplementary Methods) 
indicate that the P-value for observing a statistic from a tree with n genes 
can be calculated according to the Gaussian distribution function. Under 
certain assumptions, the distribution of the statistic k rs can be represented 
using a Cauchy distribution. However, empirical results indicated that the 
majority of samples could be represented with Gaussian distributions , which 
also provided better discriminative performances. Hence, the P-values for 
k rs were determined according to the Gaussian distribution. All tests for </p>

<p>significance are one-sided. A value of k s or k rs is considered to be 
significant if it is higher than an upper critical value; while a value of l 
is significant when it is less than a lower critical value. </p>

<p>3 RESULTS </p>

<p>3.1 Capturing the functional relationships of genes 
with GO-based graphs </p>

<p>In this research, we studied the functional coherence of gene sets 
through the investigation of the relationships between constituent 
genes in GO graph space. To this end, we first constructed a 
GOGraph, which consists of only GO terms (nodes) and their 
ontology relationships (edges) as defined by the GO. Then, we added 
all annotated genes as nodes to the GOGraph, based on the instances 
specified in the GO database, leading to a graph consisting of both 
types of nodes, which is referred to as a GOGeneGraph. During 
the process, we further augmented the GOGeneGraph by adding 
edges between pairs of GO nodes that were used to co-annotate one 
or more genes. After augmentation, a GOGeneGraph was further 
transformed into a weighted, undirected graph, of which an edge's 
length was calculated according to the semantic distance between a 
pair of GO terms. More details about the graph construction are </p>

<p>i81 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i82 i79-i87 </p>

<p>A.J.Richards et al. </p>

<p>Table 1. Examples of term-term co-annotation in S.cerevisiae </p>

<p>Term 1 
Term 2 
No. genes 
Example genes </p>

<p>GO:0051301 
cell division 
GO:0019953 
sexual reproduction 
37 
SEC15, BEM1, BOI1 
Semantically 
GO:0008219 
cell death 
GO:0055114 
oxidation reduction 
25 
CYT1, COX8, ATP3 
dissimilar 
GO:0000910 
cytokinesis 
GO:0000003 
reproduction 
23 
BUD3, SEC15, SEC3 
terms 
GO:0019740 
nitrogen utilization 
GO:0015696 
ammonium transport 
6 
MEP2, ADY2, ATO2 
GO:0042493 
response to drug 
GO:0007047 
cell wall organization 
6 
ECM17, PHO85, FPS1 </p>

<p>GO:0006281 
DNA repair 
GO:0006974 
response to DNA damage stimulus 
35 
MSH6, ELG1, RAD27 
Semantically 
GO:0016568 
chromatin modification 
GO:0016573 
histone acetylation 
17 
SPT3, TAF9, YNG1 
similar 
GO:0034605 
cellular response to heat 
GO:0009266 
response to temperature stimulus 
12 
TPS1, HSP104, ECM4 
terms 
GO:0015849 
organic acid transport 
GO:0015837 
amine transport 
12 
GAP1, BAP3, LYP1 
GO:0051276 
chromosome organization 
GO:0006338 
chromatin remodeling 
6 
ISW1, VPS71, SWC4 </p>

<p>available in Section 2 and in a report on the utilized software 
package (Muller et al., 2009). The motivation for augmenting a 
GOGeneGraph is that co-annotation by a pair of GO terms, whether 
semantically close or remote, is generally biologically meaningful. 
Table 1 provides examples of co-annotation instances in yeast. For 
example, co-annotation of 25 genes by the two semantically remote 
terms, cell death and oxidation reduction, may be puzzling at first 
glance, but it is less surprising when one understands that many 
of the genes involved in oxidation reduction are also involved 
in the process of programmed cell death. On the other hand, co-
annotation by the terms with closely related semantic meanings is 
understandable as the genes themselves are likely closely related 
in function. In both cases, taking co-annotation into account during 
functional coherence analysis will reflect the biological relationships 
between GO terms that are not explicitly considered in most previous 
GO-based function analysis methods. </p>

<p>3.2 Comparing GO graphs across species </p>

<p>To assess if our approach can be broadly applied in different species, 
we first analyzed the properties of the GO graphs from different 
species to determine if their characteristics are comparable across 
species, because many GO terms and annotated genes are species-
specific. Additionally, because the graphical representation of the 
GO represents the organization of biological concepts and the gene 
annotations reflect contemporary knowledge of the biology of genes, 
it is of interest to investigate how the concepts and genes are 
organized in the gene-concept space. We constructed and studied 
species-specific graphs, corresponding to the biological process 
domain of the GO, for three organisms: S.cerevisiae, M.musculus 
and H.sapiens, and we then investigated the topological properties 
of the graphs for comparison. 
A common way to summarize the topology of a graph is to study 
the relationship between the node degree k (the number of edges 
connected to a node) and the cumulative degree distribution P(k) 
(the probability that a node has a degree greater than or equal to k) 
in logarithmic scales (Newman, 2003). Figure 2A-C shows that for 
the GOGraphs, despite differences in the number of annotations and 
genes between species-specific graphs, the relationship between k 
and P(k) can be fitted with a similar power-law curve for all three 
species. The similar degree distributions in Figure 2A-C suggest 
that biological concepts are organized in a similar fashion across 
the organisms. The nearly linear relationships in the panels indicate </p>

<p>Fig. 2. Comparison of GOGraph network topology of different species. 
(A-C) The log-log plots for the cumulative term degree distributions of 
GOGraphs for S.cerevisiae, M.musculus and H.sapiens. The horizontal axis 
is node degree k, and the vertical axis is cumulative probability P(k), where 
k corresponds to the number edges connecting to a node, and P(k) is the 
probability that a node has k or more degree. (D-F) The cumulative degree 
distributions for GOGeneGraphs augmented by adding all annotated genes 
from the three species, respectively. (G-I) The distributions (histograms) of 
edge distances of GOGraphs for the species. </p>

<p>that the GOGraphs have the characteristics of scale-free graphs with 
a hub-spoke-like organization (Barabási and Oltvai, 2004; Newman, 
2003). With respect to the GO, this means that some concepts 
are highly connected and play critical roles in connecting various 
concepts. Similarly, the GOGeneGraphs from the three species 
have comparable power-law exponents and are thus similar in 
architecture (Fig. 2D-F). These results indicate that some GO terms 
are used to annotate a large number of genes, and some genes are 
connected with multiple GO terms. In addition to degree, histograms 
of edge distances are shown (Fig. 2G-I) in order to quantitatively </p>

<p>i82 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i83 i79-i87 </p>

<p>Graph-based gene set coherence </p>

<p>summarize the semantic relationships among the GO terms. The 
overall similarity of the plots for the three species indicates that the 
graph properties and, thus, functional coherence metrics based on 
these properties, are likely to be applicable to other species with 
similar annotation topologies. </p>

<p>3.3 Metrics for capturing functional coherence </p>

<p>Given a set of genes, we extract a subgraph of GOGeneGraph, which 
connects the genes through their function annotations to reflect how 
genes are functionally related to each other. We further constrain 
the subgraph to have the shortest total semantic distance among all 
possible subgraphs connecting the genes, which leads to a subgraph 
commonly referred to as Steiner tree (see Section 2). In a GO Steiner 
tree, in addition to the GO terms directly associated to the genes, seed 
terms, more terms (nodes) may be included to provide connections 
among all seed terms. A GO Steiner tree not only reflects how 
genes are annotated but also represents how the functions of the 
genes are related to each other. Thus, the properties of a GO Steiner 
tree can be used to evaluate both aspects of functional coherence-
the enrichment of functional annotations and the relatedness of the 
distinct annotations. 
Three metrics were devised based on the topological properties of 
GO Steiner trees in order to reflect the functional coherence of a gene 
set: the sum of the lengths of all edges within the tree l, the averaged 
seed degree of a tree k s and the combined metric k rs = k s 
l . The 
values of the metrics can be interpreted as follows. A greater k s 
than expected by random chance indicates a functionally coherent 
gene set, because many genes within the set share the same function 
annotations. A smaller l than expected by random chance represents a 
functionally coherent gene set, because the annotations of the genes 
are semantically or biologically related. Similarly, a greater k rs 
than expected denotes a more coherent gene set, because in such 
a set either many genes share the same function annotations or the 
function of the genes are closely related to each other or both. The 
quantities measured with these metrics are collectively referred to 
as network statistics. 
We further investigated if the network statistics were different 
between functionally coherent gene sets and randomly grouped ones. 
By sampling from all annotated genes in a genome, we produced 
a large number of randomly grouped gene sets of various sizes to 
serve as samples from a population of non-coherent gene sets. For 
comparison, we extracted the pathways from the KEGG database 
(Kawashima et al., 2003) and used the corresponding genes as 
samples of coherent gene sets. Each network statistic was plotted 
as a function of the size of the gene sets n, because the values 
of the metrics, in particular l, vary with the size of the gene sets. 
Figure 3A-C summarizes the results for the S.cerevisiae data in a 
scatter plot. In Figure 3A, k s increases as a nonlinear function of 
n for random groups, and the data points from the KEGG pathways 
significantly deviate from the trend of the random sets. Indeed, 
most functionally coherent data are above the estimated means (see 
Section 2) of the random gene sets with similar sizes, indicating 
that the GO terms in the KEGG gene sets are more enriched. 
Figure 3B plots l as a function of group size n. While the data 
exhibit a monotonically increasing function for the random groups, 
the lengths (l) of the GO Steiner trees for the KEGG pathways are 
significantly shorter than those from the random sets, indicating that 
the GO terms from the KEGG gene sets are more closely related </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B 
E </p>

<p>C 
F </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Fig. 3. Network statistics of random and coherent gene sets. (A-C) The 
network statistics corresponding to 8850 randomly sampled gene sets 
(gray dots) and 90 pathways (black crosses) from the KEGG database for 
S.cerevisiae are shown as functions of gene set size n for the three metrics, 
k s , l and k rs . The red lines in (A-C) are the means of the random gene sets </p>

<p>as functions of n fitted with the Nadaraya-Watson method (see Section 2). 
(D-F) The ROC curves for the network statistics, where AUC values are 
shown in Table 2. (D-F) illustrate the discriminative performance for k s , 
l and k rs , respectively. The colors indicate the species and the colored 
diamonds show the sensitivity and false positive rates of the metrics when 
the P-value threshold is set at 0.05. </p>

<p>(semantically or biologically) than in randomly grouped gene sets. 
The results measured by the unified coherence metric k rs , shown 
in Figure 3C, also suggest that the groups are separable. </p>

<p>3.4 Statistical testing and discriminative analysis </p>

<p>We further evaluate the discriminative power of the metrics in 
terms of classification accuracy. Our approach was to train a model 
that employs a non-parametric regression method to capture the 
distributions of the network statistics from randomly sampled gene 
sets. Under the null hypothesis that any gene set belongs to the 
random gene set population, the trained model can determine the 
P-value for an arbitrary gene set-the probability that the set is 
comprised of randomly drawn genes. As for the hypothesis testing, 
the P-value returned by the model can also be used for discriminative 
analysis. In the latter case, the model can further classify a gene set 
into a coherent or non-coherent class based on a predefined threshold 
P-value. Under this setting, the discriminative power of a metric can 
be assessed with the receiver operating characteristics (ROCs) curve 
(Zweig and Campbell, 1993) analysis, in which the area under the </p>

<p>i83 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i84 i79-i87 </p>

<p>A.J.Richards et al. </p>

<p>Table 2. A comparison of AUC values with the addition of augmented edges 
and without. The differences between the methods are most noticeable in the 
M.musculus and H.sapiens organisms. The column of AUC values with the 
addition of co-annotation edges corresponds to the curves in Figure 3D-F. </p>

<p>Species 
Metric 
AUC with 
AUC without </p>

<p>&lt; k s &gt; 
0.983 
0.985 
S.cerevisiae 
l 
0.974 
0.883 
&lt; k rs &gt; 
0.988 
0.968 </p>

<p>&lt; k s &gt; 
0.759 
0.757 
M.musculus 
l 
0.824 
0.689 
&lt; k rs &gt; 
0.823 
0.614 </p>

<p>&lt; k s &gt; 
0.967 
0.967 
H.sapiens 
l 
0.923 
0.767 
&lt; k rs &gt; 
0.948 
0.813 </p>

<p>ROC curve (AUC) is used as a measure of discriminative power. 
The closer an AUC value is to one, the stronger the discriminative 
ability. 
We performed ROC analyses for each of the three selected 
metrics, k s , l and k rs , using the KEGG pathways as positive 
cases and randomly sampled gene sets with corresponding sizes 
as negative cases. The results for all three species are shown in 
Figure 3D-F. The AUC values are listed in Table 2 for all the 
species and for each metric. The results indicate that the graph-
based metrics are highly discriminative, with AUC values &gt;0.9 
for S.cerevisiae and H.sapiens. The AUC values for M.musculus, 
although not as high as other two species, can also be considered 
excellent. To illustrate the effect of augmenting a GOGeneGraph 
with co-annotation edges, Table 2 also compares the AUC values 
obtained from GO Steiner trees with and without augmented edges. 
This empirically indicates that augmenting GOGeneGraph with co-
annotation edges significantly enhances the discriminative power of 
our methods. 
We noted that by testing against a null distribution of random 
sets, our statistical test served directly the goal of evaluating if a 
gene set consists of random-grouped genes. As such it transcends 
the conventional count-based approaches that concentrate on testing 
whether or not an observed GO term in a gene set is a random 
event, which is tangentially related to the original goal. As shown 
in Figure 3, a P-value of 0.05 from our test serves as an almost 
optimal decision threshold for all three metrics in all species. Thus, 
this conventional threshold (P&lt; 0.05) of statistical significance can 
be readily applied in our statistical test, whereas in the count-based 
methods one often needs to adjust the significance threshold to avoid 
false positive calls (Cho et al., 2001; Huang et al., 2009; Khatri and 
Dr˘ aghici, 2005; Man et al., 2000). </p>

<p>3.5 Robustness of the metrics </p>

<p>It is inevitable that results from high-throughput approaches contain 
noise of varying degrees. To evaluate the robustness of the metrics 
against noise, we performed a noise simulation experiment by 
replacing different percentages of the genes from KEGG pathways 
with randomly selected ones, followed by the evaluation of the 
metrics' discriminative power. As an example, we studied the 
discriminative power of the unified metric (k rs ) tested with </p>

<p>0 
20 
40 
60 
80 100 
Percent noise </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Significant pathways (%) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>S. cerevisiae </p>

<p>M. musculus </p>

<p>H. sapiens </p>

<p>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 
1 -Specificity </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 % </p>

<p>20 % </p>

<p>40 % </p>

<p>60 % </p>

<p>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 
1 -Specificity </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 % </p>

<p>20 % </p>

<p>40 % </p>

<p>60 % </p>

<p>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 
1 -Specificity </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>0.8 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>Sensitivity </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0 % </p>

<p>20 % </p>

<p>40 % </p>

<p>60 % </p>

<p>Fig. 4. Testing for metric robustness. In a noise simulation experiment, P-
values derived from the k rs method were used to evaluate the robustness of 
the metrics in the presence of different amounts of simulated noise. (A) With 
the P ≤ 0.05 as the threshold, the percent of KEGG pathways classified as 
coherent in the presence of noise was plotted against the percent of simulated 
noise. The line colors indicate the species. (B-D) The ROC curves using 
k rs in presence of different degrees of noise are shown for S.cerevisiae, </p>

<p>M.musculus and H.sapiens, respectively. Specifically, the AUCs for curves 
with 0-60% (increasing by 20%) are presented. </p>

<p>contaminated data for all three species (Fig. 4). With a P-value 
threshold at 0.05, we examined the percent of KEGG pathways 
that were classified as coherent after introducing different degrees 
of noise. The results are plotted as a function of the percent 
of noise in Figure 4A. Our metric classified the majority of the 
lightly contaminated (noise &lt;30%) KEGG gene sets as coherent 
and the heavily contaminated (noise &gt;60%) ones as non-coherent. 
The ROC curves in the presence of different amounts of noise for 
S.cerevisiae, M.musculus and H.sapiens are shown in Figure 4B-D, 
respectively. Overall, the figure shows that k rs retains a high degree 
of discriminative power, even with a relatively large amount of noise 
under these simulation conditions. </p>

<p>3.6 Application to microarray gene expression analysis </p>

<p>To evaluate the performance of the metrics at a systems level, we 
investigated the metrics developed in this study using a real world 
microarray dataset. We collected microarray data from yeast cells 
subjected to oxidative stress (see Supplementary Methods), and the 
k-means clustering algorithm (Tavazoie et al., 1999) was employed 
to partition the genes into 225 clusters, among which 132 clusters 
had a number of genes that fell between 5 and 300. These clusters 
were further investigated using our GO Steiner tree methods. We 
assess the performance of the methods in several ways (Fig. 5). 
We investigated the relationship between the P-values produced 
by graph-based metrics and cluster size (Fig. 5A). As a comparison, 
we also calculated the enrichment P-values of each GO term </p>

<p>i84 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i85 i79-i87 </p>

<p>Graph-based gene set coherence </p>

<p>10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 
Cluster size (genes) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.3 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>p-value </p>

<p>0 
10 
20 
30 
40 
50 
% of significant clusters </p>

<p>Silhouette index range </p>

<p>-0.1-0.09 </p>

<p>0.09-0.21 </p>

<p>0.21-0.28 </p>

<p>0.28-0.57 </p>

<p>A 
B </p>

<p>Fig. 5. Application to microarray analysis. (A) The relationship between 
the P-values by the metrics and cluster size. The black circles correspond 
to results for clusters tested by the k rs method and the blue diamonds 
indicate those of the count-based one. The points for each method have 
two sizes where the larger ones denote differentially expressed clusters 
that were statistically significant (≤0.05) as determined by a GSA method. 
(B) The relationship between significance calls by k rs and silhouette index. 
According to their silhouette index ranks, the 132 clusters were divided into 
four evenly sized groups then the percent of clusters classified as significant 
within each group was plotted. </p>

<p>within the clusters based on a hypergeometric assumption (Cho 
et al., 2001; Kong et al., 2006), and an averaged P-value of the 
cluster was determined and subsequently plotted in Figure 5A. The 
P-values from the GO term enrichment analysis are often sensitive 
to geneome size and the extent of annotation completeness (Khatri 
and Dr˘ aghici, 2005). Similarly, if these methods are extended to 
evaluate global functional coherence of a gene set as by simple 
averaging of P-values the results can be shown to be sensitive 
to the gene set sizes. The averaged P-values by the count-based 
metric showed a clear trend as a nearly linear function of the size 
of the clusters; in contrast, the P-values from the graph-based 
metric span a broader range, indicating cluster size has little if 
any impact on its coherence evaluation. The results confirm a 
well-known phenomenon that GO terms observed within a small 
cluster are more likely to be evaluated as 'enriched' due to the 
characteristics of hypergeometric distribution (Khatri and Dr˘ aghici, 
2005; Zheng and Lu, 2007). The panel also shows that the clusters 
evaluated as significant by the graph-based metric tend to be rich 
with differentially expressed genes per a gene set analysis (GSA) 
method (Efron and Tibshirani, 2007). 
To further investigate the results, we assessed how well 
the graph-based functional coherence evaluations agree with a 
metric commonly used to measure similarity of profiles within a 
cluster-the silhouette index (Rousseeuw, 1987). An underpinning 
assumption for many microarray analysis methods is that closely 
co-regulated genes, whose expression profiles are tightly clustered 
within a gene set (reflected as a high silhouette index) are likely 
to function coherently (Eisen et al., 1998). The results (Fig. 5B) 
indicate that, as the silhouette value increases, a cluster is more 
likely to be evaluated as significant by the graph-based metric. 
Lastly, we assessed the functional coherence of the clusters by 
manually studying their annotations and their GO Steiner trees. 
We found that according to expert assessment, many biologically 
coherent clusters were correctly classified by the graph-based metric. </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>Fig. 6. Steiner tree visualization. (A) An example of GO Steiner tree 
visualization for a gene cluster involved in retinal degeneration. Oval nodes 
are GO term nodes, with cyan ovals representing the seed terms and open 
ovals denoting the GO terms needed to connect all seed terms. A black 
edge represents the semantic edge defined in the GOGraph and a red edge 
is an augmenting edge representing the connection between GO terms 
that co-annotate proteins. A gene is represented with a black box and the 
dashed edges denote gene-to-term relationship. Summarizing annotation 
descriptions are displayed as text. The whole gene expression cluster takes 
the form of several distinct groups. (B) One group (subgraph) of interest is 
examined more closely to highlight the characteristics of a more functionally 
coherent part of the overall GO Steiner tree. The GO terms labeled with a 
number are further explained in the Supplementary Results. </p>

<p>For example, our graph-based evaluation correctly called a cluster 
of genes rich with ribosomal proteins as coherent gene set, thus 
conforming with well-documented knowledge that the expressions 
of these genes are significantly and coordinately repressed during 
various cellular stresses (Gasch and Werner-Washburne, 2002). 
Overall, the results demonstrate the ability of this method to filter 
through large amounts of potentially interesting gene sets in order 
to focus on those of relevant biological interest. </p>

<p>3.7 Visualization </p>

<p>Visualization provides another means to assess the functional 
coherence of a gene set beyond solely relying on P-values. 
Visualization allows for the generation of new hypotheses based 
on the functional groupings of genes and terms and the way they 
are connected, and equally important it may be used to confirm 
existing knowledge about the underlying biology. To this end, we 
have implemented a web application. 
As an example to illustrate the utility of visualization, we explored 
the GO Steiner tree for a set of genes published in a study on retina 
degeneration (Rohrer et al., 2004) (Fig. 6). An evaluation with k rs 
resulted in a significant P-value of 0.043, suggesting that the GO 
terms from the gene set are more coherent than random. Indeed, 
when inspecting the GO Steiner tree for the gene set, we found that 
there are two major clusters of nodes consisting of both genes and </p>

<p>i85 </p>

<p>[11:05 12/5/2010 Bioinformatics-btq203.tex] </p>

<p>Page: i86 i79-i87 </p>

<p>A.J.Richards et al. </p>

<p>GO terms. One cluster consists of 99 GO terms associated with one 
gene, Drd2, while another is comprised of 7 genes and 18 highly 
connected GO terms. Visualization thus enabled, in this case of this 
cluster, the user to focus in immediately on the most biologically 
interesting part of the GO Steiner tree. Observing the clusters also 
helped to explain why the gene set was considered statistically 
significant, supporting the idea that exploring a GO Steiner tree is 
an efficient means to facilitates functional investigation. 
Visualization helped us derive the following biological thoughts 
and insights. The animal model analyzed here is the rd1 mouse 
(Farber, 1995), a very well-studied model for retinitis pigmentosa 
(RP), a disease resulting in rod photoreceptor degeneration. Many 
pathophysiological aspects of the disease model were correctly 
recognized by the GO terms phototransduction, ion transport, 
apoptosis regulation and cone development. Photoreceptor cell death 
in this model can be slowed down using dopaminergic agonists 
(regulation of dopamine), which provides the rationale for Drd2 
(Ogilvie and Speck, 2002). It is known that the photoreceptor 
cell death leads to cytoskeleton reorganization and changes in 
protein localization both within the dying cell as well as in the 
remaining surviving cells. Visualization provides the user with a 
method to investigate functional subgraphs of a GO Steiner tree. 
For example, by visualizing the functional cluster subplot (Fig. 6B) 
it is easier to tease out the relationships between genes and terms 
than it is with a list of annotations alone. The subplot along with 
the annotation descriptions (see Supplemental Results) provide the 
genes associated with the cells surviving initial apoptotic events. 
These cells reorganize into a novel network due to migration and 
proliferation of certain cell types (Marc et al., 2007). Because, no 
links exist yet for Scg2 and Thy1 in photoreceptor degeneration, this 
leads to the generation of hypotheses that may be used to characterize 
their roles in the rd1 model and ultimately in RP. There are grounds 
for further investigation, because Scg2 is expressed in the retina 
(Liu et al., 2006) during development and Thy1 is crucial for retinal 
development (Simon et al., 1999). </p>

<p>4 DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The main goal of this study was to introduce functional coherence 
metrics with high levels of discriminative power, based on the 
currently available GO annotations. Moreover, the method was 
intentionally developed independent of data types that are used 
to generate the gene set of interest (GOI). Two graph-based 
metrics, k s and l, were developed, where the former measures the 
enrichment of functional annotations, and the latter summarizes the 
relatedness of the annotations. Furthermore, k rs was devised so that 
both aspects of functional coherence can be evaluated with a unified 
metric. In addition to quantitative evaluation, we have also provided 
tools to visualize GO Steiner trees as a means to further assess the 
results by inspecting how genes and annotations are organized, rather 
than solely relying on P-values. In the real world application, the 
metrics returned biologically sensible calls. The advantages of these 
metrics include but are not necessarily limited to the following: 
(i) by incorporating semantic and biological relationships in the 
evaluation, our methods treat genes annotated with semantically 
close GO terms as functionally similar; (ii) providing an global 
evaluation method for proteins/gene sets, rather than treating each 
function annotation of genes as independent; and (iii) addressing the 
multiple testing problem by reducing the number of tests. However, </p>

<p>like all GO-based evaluation methods, the metrics are dependent on 
how well genes are annotated. Therefore, the utilities of the metrics 
are limited when considering species that have less comprehensive 
annotations, and the metrics may reflect potential annotation biases 
from the databases. This is likely to hold true for localized areas of 
the GOGraph as well. 
The discriminative power of the graph-based metrics may be 
attributed to the following factors. First, the methods capture 
the key properties that differentiate coherent gene sets from 
random ones-GO terms in a functionally coherent gene set are 
more likely to be enriched and their functions are more closely 
related semantically and biologically. In addition to the semantic 
relationships considered, our metrics further take into account the 
relationships among GO terms that co-annotate genes, which leads 
to a better performance. Second, through a sampling approach, our 
method accurately estimates the distribution of network statistics of 
the randomly grouped gene sets, which is directly relevant to the task 
at hand-determining if an arbitrary gene set consists of randomly 
grouped genes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>We thank Tomas M. Asbury, Elizabeth G. Hill, John H. Schwacke 
and Kellie J. Sims for valuable discussion. Alan Wilder for technical 
assistance and Yusuf Hannun for generously providing yeast strains. </p>

<p>Funding: National Institutes of Health of the United States (grants 
R01LM009153, 5R01LM010144 to X.L., T15LM07438 to X.L. and 
A.J.R., 2P20RR107677 to X.L. and R01EY13520 to B.R.). </p>

<p>Conflict of Interest: none declared. </p>



</text></tei>