<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2570388" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-12T00:50+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Fatty acid-induced mitochondrial uncoupling 
and oxidative stress have been proposed to reduce cardiac 
efficiency and contribute to cardiac dysfunction in type 2 diabe-
tes. We hypothesized that mitochondrial uncoupling may also 
contribute to reduced cardiac efficiency and contractile dysfunc-
tion in the type 1 diabetic Akita mouse model (Akita). </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Cardiac function and 
substrate utilization were determined in isolated working hearts 
and in vivo function by echocardiography. Mitochondrial func-
tion and coupling were determined in saponin-permeabilized 
fibers, and proton leak kinetics was determined in isolated 
mitochondria. Hydrogen peroxide production and aconitase ac-
tivity were measured in isolated mitochondria, and total reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) were measured in heart homogenates. </p>

<p>RESULTS-Resting cardiac function was normal in Akita mice, 
and myocardial insulin sensitivity was preserved. Although Akita 
hearts oxidized more fatty acids, myocardial O 2 consumption 
was not increased, and cardiac efficiency was not reduced. 
ADP-stimulated mitochondrial oxygen consumption and ATP 
synthesis were decreased, and mitochondria showed grossly 
abnormal morphology in Akita. There was no evidence of oxida-
tive stress, and despite a twofold increase in uncoupling protein 
3 (UCP3) content, ATP-to-O ratios and proton leak kinetics were 
unchanged, even after perfusion of Akita hearts with 1 mmol/l 
palmitate. </p>

<p>addition, the severity of diabetes can vary considerably in 
this model, and mitochondrial dysfunction may or may not 
occur (17). To circumvent these concerns, genetic models 
of type 1 diabetes are increasingly used, and the Animal 
Models of Diabetic Complications Consortium (AMDCC) 
has proposed the Akita diabetic mouse as a useful model 
with which to study the chronic complications of type 1 
diabetes (18). This mouse develops diabetes as a conse-
quence of a single base pair substitution in the Ins2 gene, 
resulting in improper folding of proinsulin, which leads to 
protein aggregate-induced endoplasmic reticulum stress 
in pancreatic islets (19,20) and eventual ␤-cell failure (19). 
Akita mice are severely hyperglycemic by 5-6 weeks of 
age and develop typical chronic complications of diabetes, 
such as retinopathy, neuropathy, and nephropathy (21,22). 
In this study, we hypothesized that mitochondrial un-
coupling may also contribute to reduced cardiac efficiency 
and contractile dysfunction in type 1 diabetes. To test our 
hypothesis, we measured cardiac contractile function, 
energy substrate metabolism, and mitochondrial function 
and coupling in the type 1 diabetic Akita mouse model 
(Akita). The main finding of this study was that Akita 
hearts are protected from fatty acid-induced mitochon-
drial uncoupling despite increased UCP3 expression. Our 
data imply that mechanisms for mitochondrial dysfunction 
differ importantly between insulin-deficient type 1 and 
insulin-resistant type 2 diabetic hearts. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Male Akita mice (C57BL/6) and C57BL/6 controls were obtained from The 
Jackson Laboratories (Bar Harbor, ME) and housed at 22°C with free access 
to water and food with a light cycle of 12 h light and 12 h dark. Animals were 
studied in accordance with protocols approved by the Institutional Animal 
Care and Use Committee of the University of Utah. All studies were performed 
in random-fed animals. 
Serum analyses. Free fatty acid concentrations, triacylglycerol levels, and 
blood glucose levels were measured as previously described (4). 
Echocardiography. Contractile function and left ventricular chamber dimen-
sions were measured as described previously (23). 
Heart perfusions. Contractile function and substrate metabolism were 
measured in isolated working hearts perfused with Krebs-Henseleit buffer 
(KHB) containing 5 mmol/l glucose and 0.4 mmol/l palmitate in the presence 
or absence of 1 nmol/l insulin as previously described (3). For some 
mitochondrial respiration studies, hearts were perfused in the Langendorff 
mode with KHB containing 11 mmol/l glucose and 1 mmol/l palmitate for 30 
min (5). The effect of a calcium-induced increase in workload on contractility 
was investigated in Langendorff-perfused hearts with KHB (5 mmol/l glucose 
and 0.4 mmol/l palmitate) (5). Hearts were perfused for 40 min, and calcium 
was raised from 2 to 4 mmol/l after 20 min. 
Mitochondrial function. Saponin-permeabilized fibers were prepared from 
freshly excised or Langendorff-preperfused hearts as described previously (5). 
Respiration and ATP synthesis were measured using 20 mol/l palmitoyl 
carnitine, 10 mmol/l pyruvate, or 5 mmol/l glutamate as substrates, each 
combined with 2 mmol/l malate. Respiration was measured in the presence of 
substrate alone (V 0 ), after addition of 1 mmol/l ADP (V ADP ), and after addition 
of 1 g/ml F 0 F 1 -ATPase inhibitor oligomycin (V Oligo ). 
Proton leak kinetics. Proton leak measurements were performed in hearts 
that were preperfused for 20 min with 11 mmol/l glucose and 1 mmol/l 
palmitate. Mitochondria were prepared from whole hearts by differential 
centrifugation, and proton leak kinetics was measured in the presence of 20 
mol/l palmitoyl carnitine as previously described (6,24). 
Electron microscopy. Hearts were freshly excised and immediately washed 
in ice-cold saline. Samples were collected from left ventricular myocardium 
and processed as described previously (6). Mitochondrial volume density and 
number were analyzed by stereology in a blinded fashion using the point-
counting method (6,25). 
Hydrogen peroxide production. Mitochondrial hydrogen peroxide (H 2 O 2 ) 
generation was measured using succinate as a substrate as described previ-
ously (6). To block H 2 O 2 production at complex I, 10 mol/l rotenone was 
added to the reaction. Mitochondrial H 2 O 2 production is widely accepted as a 
measure of mitochondrial superoxide production. </p>

<p>Oxidative stress. Tissue ROS levels were measured by the conversion of 
nonfluorescent 2Ј, 7Ј-dichlorofluorescein-diacetate (DCFDA) to the highly 
fluorescent 2Ј, 7Ј-dichlorofluorescein (DCF) in the presence of esterases and 
ROS (26) (for details, see the supplementary methods available in an online 
appendix at http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-0079). Activity of mitochondrial 
aconitase was measured in isolated mitochondria as described previously 
(27). 
RNA extraction and quantitative RT-PCR. Total RNA was extracted from 
hearts with Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA), purified with the 
RNEasy kit (Qiagen, Valencia, CA), and reverse transcribed (6). Data were 
normalized by expressing them relative to the levels of the invariant transcript 
16S RNA. Primer sequences and accession numbers are presented in supple-
mentary Table 1. 
Western blot analysis. Isolated mitochondria or whole-cell extracts were 
prepared as described previously and resolved by SDS-PAGE (5,6). For 
antibody conditions see supplementary methods in the online appendix. 
Protein concentrations were determined using the Micro BCA Protein Assay 
kit (Pierce, Rockford, IL), and equal protein loading was verified by Coomas-
sie staining. 
Statistical analysis. Data are presented as means Ϯ SE. When comparing 
two groups, significance was determined using a Student's t test. Effects of 
calcium-induced increase in contractility were analyzed using a paired t test. 
Analysis of working heart perfusions Ϯ insulin was performed using 
one-way ANOVA. Significance was assessed by Fisher's protected least 
significant difference test. For all analyses, the <rs id="software-0" type="software">Statview</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">5.0.1</rs> software 
package was used (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">SAS Institute</rs>, Cary, NC), and significant difference was 
accepted when P Ͻ 0.05. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Serum metabolites and cardiac growth. Akita diabetic 
mice develop type 1 diabetes as early as 5-6 weeks of age 
and show normal survival until 6 months of age but then 
show a dramatic decrease in survival with almost no 
survivors by 12 months of age (19). To investigate the 
long-term effects of type 1 diabetes on the heart, we chose 
to investigate mice mainly at 24 weeks of age. Serum 
glucose levels were markedly increased in Akita mice at 24 
weeks of age (138 Ϯ 5 vs. 566 Ϯ 21 mg/dl; P Ͻ 0.05). 
Hyperglycemia was accompanied by increased serum fatty 
acid levels (261 Ϯ 43 vs. 537 Ϯ 72 mol/l; P Ͻ 0.05) and 
increased serum triacylglycerol levels (0.98 Ϯ 0.11 vs. 
2.40 Ϯ 0.54 mmol/l; P Ͻ 0.05). In contrast to wild-type 
mice, Akita mice showed no increase in body weights as 
they aged (supplementary Table 2). Heart weights and 
tibia lengths were measured at 10, 24, and 54 weeks of age 
in the Akita mice (supplementary Table 2). Although 
heart-to-tibia length ratios were not different at 10 weeks, 
we observed reduced ratios at 24 and 54 weeks of age. 
Heart weight-to-body weight ratios were not reduced, 
indicating that the reduction in heart size parallels the 
general catabolic state of diabetic Akita mice. 
Cardiac function. Cardiac contractile function and cham-
ber dimensions were examined in Akita diabetic mice by 
echocardiography at 20, 36, and 54 weeks of age. Frac-
tional shortening and ejection fraction were not different 
at any age (Table 1), and there were no differences in 
chamber dimensions in diabetic and nondiabetic mice 
(supplementary Table 3). Cardiac output was increased at 
20 weeks of age but was lower at 54 weeks of age in Akita 
mice, which was likely due to a moderate but nonsignifi-
cant reduction in heart rate. Because adaptations of the 
neurohumoral system can mask the presence of contrac-
tile dysfunction in vivo, we investigated contractile func-
tion in isolated working hearts in the absence and 
presence of insulin (Fig. 1A-C). In the absence of insulin, 
left ventricular developed pressure was reduced in 24-
week-old Akita mice, and a trend toward increased cardiac 
output in Akita hearts led to no differences in cardiac 
power. Insulin had a positive inotropic effect in wild-type </p>

<p>H. BUGGER AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
hearts, which was blunted in Akita mice. Heart rates 
(bpm) were not significantly changed from baseline by 
insulin (basal vs. insulin: wild type, 263 Ϯ 8 vs. 281 Ϯ 8; 
Akita, 290 Ϯ 5 vs. 310 Ϯ 9). To further evaluate myocardial 
contractile reserve, Langendorff-perfused hearts were ex-
amined under normal and increased calcium concentra-
tions. Contractile parameters were similar in 15-week-old 
wild-type and Akita mice under baseline conditions (2 
mmol/l calcium). Changing perfusion conditions to 4 
mmol/l calcium significantly increased systolic pressure, 
developed pressure, and rate pressure product in wild-
type and Akita mice by equivalent extents (supplementary 
Table 4). Thus, despite persistent hyperglycemia, Akita 
mice exhibited modest left ventricular dysfunction that 
was evident mainly in insulin-perfused working hearts. In 
contrast to ob/ob mice (5), short-term inotropic reserves 
were maintained. 
Substrate metabolism, insulin signaling, and cardiac 
efficiency. Decreased cardiac efficiency is believed to be 
an important contributor to the development of contrac-
tile dysfunction in type 2 diabetic models and has been 
postulated to result from fatty acid-induced mitochon-</p>

<p>drial uncoupling (1). We therefore measured cardiac 
substrate utilization and oxygen consumption in iso-
lated working hearts of 24-week-old Akita mice in the 
absence and presence of insulin. Palmitate oxidation 
rates were increased and glucose oxidation rates were 
decreased in the presence or absence of 1 nmol/l insulin 
in Akita hearts compared with the wild type (Fig. 1D and 
E). Despite increased fatty acid oxidation, myocardial 
Vo 2 and cardiac efficiency were not different between 
wild-type and Akita mice (Fig. 1G and H). Of interest, 
metabolic insulin responsiveness was retained in Akita 
hearts. Thus, insulin-suppressed palmitate oxidation 
increased glycolysis and glucose oxidation in both wild-
type and Akita mice (Fig. 1D-F). Consistent with intact 
metabolic insulin signaling, insulin-stimulated Akt phos-
phorylation on Ser 
473 was maintained in hearts of 10-and 
24-week-old mice (Fig. 2A and B). Thus, despite increased 
fatty acid utilization, Akita hearts maintained normal insu-
lin sensitivity. 
Mitochondrial oxygen consumption and respiratory 
coupling. The absence of reduced cardiac efficiency was 
unexpected and revealed an important difference between </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Substrate oxidation and contractile performance of Akita hearts. 24-week-old wild-type and Akita mouse hearts were perfused in the 
isolated working mode without insulin (basal) or in the presence of 1 nmol/l insulin (n ‫؍‬ 4 -5). A: Left ventricular-developed pressure (LVDevP). 
B: Cardiac output. C: Cardiac power. D: Palmitate oxidation. E: Glucose oxidation. F: Glycolysis. G: Oxygen consumption. H: Cardiac efficiency. 
*P &lt; 0.05 vs. wild type, ⌿P &lt; 0.05 vs. without insulin. </p>

<p>TABLE 1 
Echocardiographic evaluation of contractile function in wild-type and Akita mice at 20, 36, and 54 weeks of age </p>

<p>n </p>

<p>Fractional 
shortening (%) </p>

<p>Ejection 
fraction (%) </p>

<p>Heart rate 
(bpm) </p>

<p>Stroke volume 
(l/g body wt) </p>

<p>Cardiac output 
(l ⅐ min 
Ϫ1 ⅐ 
g 
Ϫ1 body wt) </p>

<p>Wild type (20 weeks) 
9 
38.6 Ϯ 2.4 
76 Ϯ 3 
415 Ϯ 12 
1.13 Ϯ 0.03 
467 Ϯ 14 
Akita (20 weeks) 
7 
38.7 Ϯ 2.4 
76 Ϯ 3 
472 Ϯ 31 
1.12 Ϯ 0.07 
527 Ϯ 15* 
Wild type (36 weeks) 
6 
39.6 Ϯ 1.2 
78 Ϯ 1 
470 Ϯ 41 
0.97 Ϯ 0.04 
456 Ϯ 25 
Akita (36 weeks) 
5 
39.7 Ϯ 2.7 
78 Ϯ 3 
421 Ϯ 29 
1.13 Ϯ 0.04* 
476 Ϯ 33 
Wild type (54 weeks) 
6 
24.6 Ϯ 1.9 
57 Ϯ 3 
523 Ϯ 29 
1.00 Ϯ 0.10 
524 Ϯ 28 
Akita (54 weeks) 
6 
27.6 Ϯ 1.9 
62 Ϯ 3 
448 Ϯ 28 
0.95 Ϯ 0.04 
426 Ϯ 28* </p>

<p>Data are means Ϯ SE unless otherwise indicated. *P Ͻ 0.05 vs. wild type. </p>

<p>MITOCHONDRIAL UNCOUPLING IN TYPE 1 DIABETES HEARTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>the type 1 diabetic Akita mouse and type 2 diabetic mouse 
models. Because mitochondrial uncoupling may underlie 
impaired cardiac efficiency in type 2 diabetic hearts (1,5,6), 
we hypothesized that mitochondrial coupling would be 
normal in Akita hearts. Mitochondrial function was ini-
tially evaluated in fibers that were prepared from freshly 
isolated mouse hearts. In hearts from 24-week-old mice, 
maximal ADP-stimulated mitochondrial oxygen consump-
tion (V ADP ) and ATP synthesis were unchanged using </p>

<p>palmitoyl carnitine as a substrate (Fig. 3A and E), but V ADP 
and ATP synthesis were significantly reduced in Akita 
mice using pyruvate (Fig. 3B and F) or glutamate (Fig. 3C 
and G) as substrates. Although a respiratory defect was 
evident, there was no evidence for mitochondrial uncou-
pling. Rates of oligomycin-insensitive respirations (V oligo ) 
and ATP-to-O ratios were unchanged with any substrate, 
indicating intact coupling of ATP synthesis to oxygen 
consumption. In 10-week-old mice, similar reductions in </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Intact insulin signaling in Akita hearts. Representative Western blot images showing cardiac protein levels of phosphorylated Akt (p-Akt) 
on Ser 
473 and total levels of Akt (t-Akt) and densitometric quantification of the ratio of p-Akt to t-Akt (p-Akt/t-Akt) after isolated working heart 
perfusions in the absence (basal) or presence of 1 nmol/l insulin at the age of 10 weeks (A) and 24 weeks (B). *P &lt; 0.05 vs. basal, ⌿P &lt; 0.05 vs. 
wild-type (WT). </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Preserved mitochondrial coupling and impaired mitochondrial oxidative capacity in Akita hearts. Mitochondrial respiratory rates (A-C) 
and ATP synthesis and ATP-to-O ratios (E-G) of saponin-permeabilized cardiac fibers from 24-week-old wild-type (WT) and Akita mice using 
palmitoyl carnitine (A and E), pyruvate (B and F), or glutamate (C and G) as a substrate (n ‫؍‬ 6). Similar data were also obtained in 10-week-old 
mice after incubation with glutamate (D and H), n ‫؍‬ 6. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. wild type. </p>

<p>H. BUGGER AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
glutamate-supported respirations (V ADP ) were observed 
(Fig. 3D). ATP synthesis rates were proportionately re-
duced; thus, ATP-to-O ratios were not different (Fig. 3H). 
We previously reported that mitochondrial uncoupling 
became evident in ob/ob and db/db mouse hearts after 
hearts were perfused with increased concentrations of 
fatty acids (5,6). Thus, palmitoyl carnitine respirations 
were determined in permeabilized fibers from hearts of 
10-week-old Akita and control mice after perfusion with 11 
mmol/l glucose and 1 mmol/l palmitate (Fig. 4A and B). 
Under these conditions, we observed no differences in 
V ADP , V oligo , ATP production rates, or ATP-to-O ratios. 
Finally, to provide more definitive evidence for the ab-
sence of mitochondrial uncoupling in Akita hearts, we 
isolated mitochondria from hearts of 24-week-old Akita 
mice after perfusion of hearts with 11 mmol/l glucose and 
1 mmol/l palmitate and measured proton leak kinetics 
(Fig. 4C). Proton leak kinetics curves were entirely over-
lapping between mitochondria from Akita mice and non-
diabetic controls, indicating the absence of mitochondrial 
uncoupling. 
Expression of mitochondrial genes and mitochon-
drial morphology. To understand the molecular basis for 
impaired mitochondrial respiratory capacity with gluta-
mate and pyruvate, we investigated gene expression in 
Akita and wild-type hearts at 24 weeks of age (Fig. 5A). 
Expression of genes encoding for subunits of the electron 
transport chain was reduced for four of five genes exam-
ined in Akita mice. In contrast, two forms of peroxisome 
proliferator-activated ␥ coactivator-1 (PGC-1␣ and PGC-
1␤) and their downstream mediators (nuclear respiratory 
factor 1 [NRF1], mitochondrial transcription factor A 
[TFAm], and estogen-related receptor-␣ [ERR␣]) were not 
differentially expressed. Genes encoding for peroxisome 
proliferator-activated receptor ␣ (PPAR␣) and for en-
zymes and transporters of fatty acid utilization did not 
show a uniform trend toward increased expression except </p>

<p>for malonyl CoA decarboxylase. Expression of GLUT1 and 
GLUT4 was reduced, and expression of pyruvate dehydro-
genase kinase 4 (PDK4) was increased in Akita, consistent 
with impaired glucose oxidation in Akita. Interestingly, 
expression of UCP2 and UCP3 was significantly increased 
in Akita, and these changes were accompanied by in-
creased expression of mitochondrial thioesterase 1 
(MTE1). Consistent with increased mRNA levels, there 
was a twofold increase in UCP3 protein content (Fig. 5B). 
This observation is of particular interest because we 
detected no evidence of mitochondrial uncoupling in 
mitochondria from Akita mice. 
Electron microscopy revealed markedly reduced cristae 
density in Akita but not in wild-type mice (Fig. 6A). Of the 
images evaluated, 75% showed lipid droplets in Akita mice, 
but no lipid droplets were observed in wild-type mice 
(arrows in Fig. 6A). Although mitochondrial volume den-
sity was increased in Akita mice, mitochondrial number 
was unchanged between the groups (Fig. 6B and C). 
No evidence for oxidative stress or increased ROS in 
Akita hearts. Thus far, we have shown that Akita mito-
chondria reveal defects in oxygen consumption in the 
absence of mitochondrial uncoupling (despite increased 
UCP3 content). We previously demonstrated that in type 2 
diabetic db/db mice, fatty acid-induced mitochondrial 
uncoupling is mediated by activation of UCPs in the 
presence of increased ROS production and evidence of 
oxidative stress. These results suggested that increased 
ROS is required for activation of UCPs in diabetic hearts 
(6). We therefore hypothesized that the absence of mito-
chondrial uncoupling in Akita hearts despite increased 
UCP3 content was due to reduced ROS in Akita hearts. 
Consistent with this hypothesis, there was no increase in 
mitochondrial H 2 O 2 production. Akita mice showed a 
38 -46% decrease in mitochondrial H 2 O 2 generation com-
pared with wild-type mice at 10 or 24 weeks of age (Fig. 7A 
and D). Addition of the complex I inhibitor rotenone </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Fatty acid perfusion does not induce mitochondrial uncoupling. 
Mitochondrial respiratory rates (A) and ATP synthesis and ATP-to-O ratios 
(B) of saponin-permeabilized cardiac fibers generated from 24-week-old 
wild-type (WT) and Akita mouse hearts that were perfused with KHB 
containing 11 mmol/l glucose and 1 mmol/l palmitate. Palmitoyl carnitine was 
used as respiratory substrate (n ‫؍‬ 6). C: Proton leak kinetics of mitochon-
dria isolated from 24-week-old wild-type and Akita mouse hearts preperfused 
with KHB containing 11 mmol/l glucose and 1 mmol/l palmitate. Palmitoyl 
carnitine was used as respiratory substrate (n ‫؍‬ 6). </p>

<p>MITOCHONDRIAL UNCOUPLING IN TYPE 1 DIABETES HEARTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>abolished mitochondrial H 2 O 2 production, suggesting that 
mitochondrial ROS production mainly arises from com-
plex I in wild-type and Akita mice. Mitochondrial aconi-
tase activity was not decreased in Akita mice at both ages 
(Fig. 7B and E), and oxidation of 2Ј-7Ј-dichlofluoroscein 
diacetate (DCFDA), a measure of tissue ROS levels, was 
unaltered in 24-week-old hearts (Fig. 7C). In addition, 
there was no induction of antioxidant defense pathways. 
Transcript levels of glutathione peroxidase 1, mitochon-
drial manganese superoxide dismutase (SOD2), and per-
oxiredoxin 3 (PRDX3) were either unchanged or even 
reduced in Akita (Fig. 5A). Similarly, protein levels of 
SOD2 and PRDX3 were unchanged between the groups 
(Fig. 7F and G). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Reduced cardiac efficiency is a well-described character-
istic of type 2 diabetic hearts in animal models and 
humans (3,28). In this study, we addressed the following 
question: Do impaired cardiac efficiency and fatty acid-
induced mitochondrial uncoupling contribute to cardiac 
contractile dysfunction in type 1 diabetic Akita mice? 
Similar to type 2 diabetic hearts, substrate metabolism 
shifts toward increased fatty acid metabolism, and mito-
chondrial oxidative capacity is impaired. However, in 
contrast to type 2 diabetic mouse models, Akita mice show 
relatively preserved contractile function under ambient 
conditions, no impairment in cardiac efficiency, and no 
evidence of mitochondrial uncoupling (normal V oligo , ATP-
to-O ratios, and proton leak). Perfusion of hearts with high 
fatty acid concentrations was not sufficient to induce </p>

<p>mitochondrial uncoupling despite the presence of in-
creased UCP3 levels. Moreover, the absence of oxidative 
stress distinguishes the Akita mouse from type 2 diabetic 
models. Thus, the molecular mechanisms for mitochon-
drial dysfunction importantly differ between insulin-defi-
cient type 1 and insulin-resistant type 2 diabetic mice. We 
also show that increased UCP3 does not invariably lead to 
increased mitochondrial uncoupling in the heart, support-
ing the hypothesis that fatty acid-induced mitochondrial 
uncoupling in diabetic hearts may require a concomitant 
increase in ROS generation. 
The absence of mitochondrial uncoupling in Akita 
hearts was associated with the absence of oxidative stress. 
Mitochondrial superoxide production, measured as H 2 O 2 
generation, was actually decreased, and the activity of 
mitochondrial aconitase and oxidation of DCFDA, which 
are independent measures of oxidative damage, were 
unaltered in Akita hearts. The association of mitochon-
drial uncoupling with increased ROS and lipid peroxide 
generation in type 2 diabetic db/db hearts (6) and the lack 
of uncoupling and the absence of oxidative stress in type 
1 diabetic Akita hearts suggest a causal interdependence 
of ROS production and mitochondrial uncoupling in dia-
betic hearts. Superoxide increases proton conductance by 
UCP3 in isolated rat skeletal muscle mitochondria, and 
lipid peroxidation products, such as hydroxynonenal, in-
crease proton leak in isolated mitochondria from multiple 
tissues, including the heart, via UCPs and adenine nucle-
otide translocator (7,24). Although fatty acids appear to be 
required for proton transport of UCP2 and UCP3 when 
reconstituted in liposomes, Echtay et al. (24) showed that </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Reduced OXPHOS expression and increased UCP expression. A: Myocardial gene expression in 24-week-old wild-type (WT) and Akita mice 
normalized to 16S RNA transcript levels (n ‫؍‬ 8). Values represent fold change in mRNA transcript levels relative to wild type, which was assigned 
as one (dashed line). B: Representative Western blot images and densitometric quantification of UCP3 protein levels in isolated mitochondria 
from 24-week-old wild-type and Akita mice (n ‫؍‬ 4). Coomassie blue staining was used as a loading control. *P &lt; 0.05 vs. wild type. </p>

<p>H. BUGGER AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>
hydroxynonenal-induced proton conductance does not 
require the presence of fatty acids (29). Thus, it appears 
that for fatty acid-induced mitochondrial uncoupling, as 
observed to occur in type 2 diabetic hearts, an increase in 
ROS may be required in addition to increased fatty acid 
availability and utilization. 
The absence of oxidative stress or of any increase in 
ROS or H 2 O 2 production in Akita hearts was unexpected. 
Inhibition of mitochondrial H 2 O 2 production in the pres-
ence of rotenone suggested that complex I accounted for 
most of the ROS production in Akita and control hearts. 
This contrasts with similar studies in mitochondria iso-
lated from db/db hearts in which additional mitochondrial 
complexes (likely complex III) also contributed to ROS 
generation (6). The reduction in ROS generation in Akita 
mice suggested that there might be a defect at the level of </p>

<p>mitochondrial complex I. This was also supported by the 
observation that mitochondrial respirations in the pres-
ence of glutamate and pyruvate, which are complex I 
substrates, were also reduced, whereas this was not the 
case with palmitoyl carnitine that delivers reducing equiv-
alents to complex I and complex II. Thus, a simple 
increase in substrate flux might not be sufficient to in-
crease mitochondrial ROS generation in diabetic hearts in 
the absence of specific alterations in mitochondrial com-
plex activities that amplify ROS generation. 
Oxidative stress has been proposed to contribute to 
mitochondrial dysfunction in the hearts of type 1 diabetes 
mouse models (30,31). In the present study, we demon-
strated impaired mitochondrial function and perturbed 
mitochondrial morphology in the absence of any evidence 
of oxidative stress. Interestingly, impaired mitochondrial 
morphology in the type 1 diabetic OVE26 mouse can be 
normalized by overexpression of manganese superoxide 
dismutase (MnSOD) or catalase in the heart, but MnSOD-
deficient mice die from early dilated cardiomyopathy and 
have normal cardiac mitochondrial morphology (30 -32). 
In other transgenic models, knockout of the mitochondrial 
transcription factor A leads to reduced mitochondrial DNA 
replication and transcription and enlarged mitochondria 
with abnormal cristae morphology, and combined deletion 
of the cardiac insulin and IGF1 receptor results in im-
paired oxidative phosphorylation (OXPHOS) gene tran-
scription and decreased mitochondria that appeared to be 
less dense in electron micrographs (33-35). Thus, in some 
contexts, changes in the content of electron transport 
chain subunits can be associated with changes in mito-
chondrial morphology. Because insulin is a positive regu-
lator of OXPHOS gene expression and because OXPHOS 
gene expression is decreased in the Akita mouse heart, 
insulin deficiency as opposed to oxidative stress might be 
an important contributor to mitochondrial dysfunction 
and altered morphology in the Akita mouse model (36,37). 
Defective insulin signaling has been reported to reduce 
expression levels of genes involved in ␤-oxidation (23), yet 
fatty acid oxidation genes were unchanged or increased in 
Akita mice. We believe that this reflects the impact of 
PPAR␣ activation in the face of increased fatty acid 
availability. 
An important observation in the present study is that 
increased content of UCP3 in the heart should not be 
taken to indicate increased mitochondrial uncoupling. We 
previously reported that increased mitochondrial uncou-
pling activity can occur in the absence of any changes in 
UCP3 content in hearts from ob/ob and db/db mice (5,6). It 
is important to discuss what might drive UCP3 levels in 
Akita mouse hearts. Besides detoxification of ROS, UCP3 
has been postulated to play a role in the regulation of fatty 
acid metabolism. Conditions associated with increased 
fatty acid availability, such as fasting, high-fat feeding, and 
diabetes, result in increased UCP3 expression, likely due 
to increased PPAR␣ signaling (12,38 -40). In general, mus-
cle UCP3 protein content is negatively related to fatty acid 
oxidative capacity, and induction of UCP3 is most pro-
nounced in glycolytic muscle upon fasting and high-fat 
feeding (41,42). Thus, increased UCP3 expression may 
reflect an adaptive response to fatty acid overload (43). 
Based on the fatty acid cycling model, it has been pro-
posed that export of fatty acid anions from the matrix 
into the intermembrane space via UCPs may help to 
lower intramitochondrial fatty acid levels if increased 
fatty acid availability exceeds mitochondrial oxidative </p>

<p>FIG. 6. Altered mitochondrial morphology in Akita hearts. Represen-
tative longitudinal electron microscopy images of left ventricular wall 
of 24-week-old wild-type (WT) and Akita mice (A), stereological 
quantification of mitochondrial volume density (B), and mitochondrial 
number (C) (n ‫؍‬ 4). Magnifications (؋10,000 and ؋40,000) are shown 
on each image, and black arrows on the images indicate lipid droplets. 
*P &lt; 0.05 vs. wild type. </p>

<p>MITOCHONDRIAL UNCOUPLING IN TYPE 1 DIABETES HEARTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

<p>capacity (43-45). Thereby, oxidation of intramitochon-
drial fatty acids into harmful lipid peroxides could be 
prevented. Expression of MTE1 often parallels that of 
UCP3, and this was also the case in the present study. 
MTE1 catalyzes conversion of acyl-CoAs back to fatty 
acid anions, which can then be translocated out of the 
matrix by UCPs (13,29). In the cytosol, they may be 
reesterified and oxidized in the mitochondria, stored as 
triglycerides, or used for other pathways. Nonesterified 
fatty acids can be generated within mitochondria and 
exported from the matrix, and these events are mark-
edly increased in cardiac mitochondria from streptozo-
tocin-induced type 1 diabetic rats (13). Despite 
increased basal fatty acid oxidation, Akita mice also 
revealed increased lipid droplets; thus, it is tempting to 
speculate that fatty acyl-CoAs would be converted to 
fatty acid anions by increased MTE1 activity, exported 
by UCP3, reesterified, and stored as triglycerides. Thus, 
UCPs would contribute to match fatty acid availability 
with oxidation to prevent intramitochondrial lipotoxic 
effects. 
A number of important differences between Akita mice 
and previously evaluated models of type 2 diabetes were 
observed (3-6,8). First, there was a relative preservation 
of cardiac function and preserved inotropic responses to a 
calcium-induced increase in workload. This likely reflects 
the more profound mitochondrial dysfunction in the type 2 
models and a greater degree of mitochondrial uncoupling. 
Preliminary studies do suggest, though, that cardiac dys-
function may develop in Akita mice after a longer-term 
hemodynamic challenge, such as after isoproterenol infu-
sion (supplementary results and supplementary Table 5), 
but the mechanisms for this remains to be elucidated. 
Second, insulin sensitivity was preserved in Akita hearts in 
contrast to the insulin resistance reported in models of 
type 2 diabetes (2,3). Although insulin levels in diabetic 
Akita are 40% of insulin levels in nondiabetic controls (19), 
these ambient insulin concentrations might be sufficient to </p>

<p>maintain mitochondrial function to a greater extent than 
models in which insulin signaling is severely impaired. 
Finally, myocardial Vo 2 was not increased despite in-
creased oxidation rates of exogenous palmitate. Although 
this may partly reflect the absence of mitochondrial un-
coupling, it is also possible that reduced oxidation of 
glucose and endogenous triglycerides coupled with mito-
chondrial dysfunction reduced myocardial Vo 2 in intact 
perfused hearts. 
In conclusion, despite a significant increase in UCP3 
content, insulin-deficient Akita hearts do not develop fatty 
acid-induced mitochondrial uncoupling, suggesting that 
underlying mechanisms for mitochondrial dysfunction 
may importantly differ between insulin-responsive type 1 
versus insulin-resistant type 2 diabetic hearts. Increased 
UCP3 levels do not invariably lead to increased mitochon-
drial uncoupling in the heart, thereby supporting the 
hypothesis that fatty acid-induced mitochondrial uncou-
pling in diabetic hearts requires a concomitant increase in 
ROS or lipid peroxide generation. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>H.B. has received a postdoctoral fellowship grant from the 
German Research Foundation. S.B. has received postdoc-
toral fellowships from the Juvenile Diabetes Research 
Foundation and the American Heart Association (AHA). 
V.G.Z. has received a postdoctoral fellowship from the 
AHA Western Affiliates. S.E.L. has received a VA Merit 
Award. E.D.A. is an established investigator of the AHA. 
This study was supported by National Institutes of Health 
Grants UO1-HL-70525, UO1-HL-087947 (AMDCC), and 
RO1-HL-070070. </p>



<p>H. BUGGER AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>



<p>
MITOCHONDRIAL UNCOUPLING IN TYPE 1 DIABETES HEARTS </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, NOVEMBER 2008 </p>

</text></tei>