<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2646063" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2018-07-19T20:30+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>NOD/LtJ mice (NOD, H2 g7 ) were purchased from the Jackson Laboratories 
(Bar Harbor, ME). Mice (8 -10 weeks old) were placed on either a normal 
chow diet (Purina Rodent Chow 5015) or diet containing Sitagliptin (MK0431) 
(21) (Purina Rodent Chow 5015 plus 4 g MK0431/kg; Research Diets, New 
Brunswick, NJ) ad libitum. From the mice that had been fed a normal chow 
diet, two groups of diabetic mice were studied. Immediately after the islet 
transplantation, group 1 mice received the normal chow diet for the remainder 
of the study (NCD Tx), whereas group 2 mice were fed the MK0431-containing 
diet (Post MK0431 Tx). Group 3 mice were animals that had received the 
MK0431 diet for 1 month before surgery and for the remainder of the study 
(Pre MK0431 Tx). In a second study, mice were fed either normal chow diet 
or MK0431 for a period of 4 weeks. All animal experiments were conducted in 
accordance with the guidelines put forth by the University of British Columbia 
Committee on Animal Care and the Canadian Council on Animal Care. 
DPP-IV activity assays. To measure the plasma DPP-IV activity, a fluoro-
metric assay was used as previously described (20). 
Islet isolation and islet gene transfer. Islets were isolated from nondia-
betic male NOD/LtJ mice (8 -12 weeks old) by collagenase digestion (22). 
Recombinant adenovirus-expressing HSV1-Sr39TK was produced and ex-
panded by infection of human embryonic kidney-293 cells (23). Islets were 
exposed to rAD-TK as previously described (20,24,25). </p>

<p>From the Islet transplantation. A cohort of 70 female NOD/LtJ mice was divided into 
two randomly selected groups of 35, and from the age of 8 -10 weeks, one 
group of mice received a normal chow diet while the second received a diet 
containing MK0431 (4 g/kg). When mice developed diabetes, defined as a 
blood glucose level of 15 mmol/l for 3 consecutive days, they received an 
islet transplant. Islets (200 obtained from nondiabetic male NOD/LtJ mice and 
infected with 250 multiplicities of infection [MOI] of rAD-TK) were trans-
planted under the kidney capsule as described previously (20,24,25). 
Plasma glucose determinations, intraperitoneal glucose tolerance 
tests, and plasma hormone measurements. Nonfasting blood glucose 
levels were measured in mouse-tail blood using a SureStep Glucose analyzer 
(LifeScan) at the time points indicated in Figs. 1 and 2. For the intraperitoneal 
glucose tolerance tests (IPGTTs), mice were fasted for 4 h, and blood glucose 
levels were measured at 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, and 120 min after the glucose 
challenge (2 g/kg). Blood samples with glucose levels 27.8 mmol/l were 
diluted with blood from nondiabetic mice and levels calculated. Plasma 
insulin, glucagon, and active GLP-1 levels were determined using a Multiplex 
assay kit (Linco Research). </p>

<p>Synthesis of 9-(4-[ 18 F]-fluoro-3-hydroxymethylbutyl)-guanine. 9-(4-
[ 18 F]-fluoro-3-hydroxymethylbutyl)-guanine ([ 18 F]FHBG) was synthesized by a 
modification of the method of Ponde et al. (26) as previously described (24). 
Micropositron emission tomography. A PET reporter gene (PRG)/PET 
reporter probe (PRP) system was used, as previously described (20,24,25). 
HSV1-sr39tk was expressed in islets as described above. The probe, [ 18 F]F-
HBG, was systemically administered and its retention in islets, after phos-
phorylation by rAD-TK, was quantified by micropositron emission tomography 
(microPET) imaging. Transplanted mice were scanned using a Focus120 (CTI 
Concorde) system that yielded 63 slices, 1.2 mm apart with an in-plane 
resolution of 2 mm full-width at half-maximum (27). Image reconstruction and 
data analysis were performed as previously described (20,24,25). 
Insulitis scoring and measurement of relative -cell area. Paraffin-
embedded pancreatic sections were stained with hematoxylin-eosin (H-E), 
and islets were examined in a blinded manner under the microscope to 
evaluate the degree of mononuclear cell infiltration. The degree of insulitis 
was scored in the following five categories: 0, intact islet; 25% of the islet 
infiltrated; 25-50% of the islet infiltrated; 50 -75% of the islet infiltrated; and </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
Body Weight (g) </p>

<p>D 
E </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>5.0 </p>

<p>7.5 </p>

<p>10.0 </p>

<p>12.5 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) </p>

<p>Food Consumption (g/day) </p>

<p>** ** ** ** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** ** ** ** 
** ** </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
DPP-IV activity (% basal) </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
Active Plasma GLP-1 Levels (pM) </p>

<p>C 
B </p>

<p>Islet Tx </p>

<p>1 st 
2 nd 
3 rd 
4 th </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** ** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>MK0431 </p>

<p>NCD </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 
-4 </p>

<p>I. NCD Tx: 
II. Post MK0431 Tx: 
III. Pre MK0431 Tx: </p>

<p>Weeks: </p>

<p>FIG. 1. The effects of MK0431 in diabetic NOD mice after islet transplantation. A: Schematic diagram of group design. Islets isolated from 
nondiabetic NOD mice were infected with 250 MOI of rAD-TK, 200 of which were transplanted under the right kidney capsule of diabetic female 
NOD mice. Islet-transplanted diabetic NOD mice were fed as follows: group 1, normal chow diet throughout (NCD Tx); group 2, MK0431 diet after 
transplant (Post MK0431 Tx); group 3, MK0431 diet 1 month before and after transplant (Pre MK0431 Tx). B and C: The effects of MK0431 on 
plasma DPP-IV activity (B) and plasma active GLP-1 levels (C) in diabetic NOD mice after islet transplantation. D-I: The effects of MK0431 on 
food consumption (D), body weight (E), water intake (F), nonfasting (G) and fasting (H) glycemic control, and survival rates (I) in diabetic NOD 
mice after islet transplantation. Number of animals: n 57 per group: NCD Tx group (E), Post MK0431 Tx group (*), and Pre MK0431 Tx group 
(F). All data represent means SE, and significance was tested using ANOVA with a Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where **P &lt; 0.05 vs. NCD Tx. 
and E: NCD T. o and *: Post MK0431 Tx. f and F: Pre MK0431 Tx. </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF MK0431 ON ISLET GRAFT SURVIVAL </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>75% of the islet infiltrated. The degree of insulitis in 20 -25 islets per mouse 
was evaluated. -Cell area was measured on the sections of each pancreas 
stained for insulin. Morphometric evaluation of the total -cell area was 
performed by computer-assisted image analysis (<rs id="software-0" type="software">Northern Eclipse</rs> <rs corresp="#software-0" type="version-number">ver. 6</rs>) 
using light and immunofluorescence microscopy. The area of insulin-positive 
cells and the total area of the tissue section were evaluated for each section, 
and the percentage -cell area was calculated by the ratio of the area occupied 
by insulin-positive cells to the total pancreatic area. 
CD4 T-cells isolation. For isolation of T-cells, spleen cell suspensions were 
prepared from female NOD mice. CD4 T-cells were enriched using the 
SpinSep Mouse CD4 T Cell separation kit (Stem Cell Technologies), and the 
purity of CD4 T-cells was confirmed by flow cytometry. 
Migration assay. CD4 T-cells were plated on membrane inserts (8-m pore 
size) in serum-free RPMI 1640, and cell migration was assayed using Transwell 
chambers (Corning), in the presence or absence of purified porcine kidney 
DPP-IV (32.1 units/mg; 100 mU/ml final concentration; provided by Dr. 
Hans-Ulrich Demuth, Probiodrug, Halle, Germany) (28) DPP-IV inhibitor 
(100 mol/l). After 1 h, cells on the upper surface were removed mechanically, 
and cells that had migrated into the lower compartment were counted. The 
extent of migration was then expressed relative to the control sample. 
Rac1 guanosine triphosphate (GTP) binding assay. Total cellular extracts 
were isolated from CD4 T-cells and Rac1 GTP binding assays performed 
using the fluorophore-based RhoGEF exchange assay kit (Cytoskeleton, 
Denver, CO), and data were normalized to protein concentration. 
cAMP measurements. CD4 T-cells were incubated for 30 min with GIP, 100 
nmol/l GLP-1 or 100 mU/ml purified porcine DPP-IV in the presence of 0.5 
mmol/l IBMX. cAMP concentration in the cell extracts was determined using 
the Parameter cyclic AMP assay kit (R&amp;D Systems). 
Protein kinase A activity assay. Activity was measured using a protein 
kinase A (PKA) kinase activity assay kit (Stressgen, Mississauga, ON) accord-
ing to the manufacturer's protocol. The enzyme activity was normalized to 
protein concentration, and data are shown as the relative activity to control. 
Western blot analysis. Total cellular extracts were separated on a 15% 
SDS-polyacrylamide gel and transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes (Bio-
Rad). Probing of the membranes was performed with antibodies to phospho-
p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) (threonine-180/tyrosine-182), 
p38 MAPK, phospho-p42/44 MAPK (threonine-202/tyrosine-204), p42/44 
MAPK, phospho-stress-activated protein kinase/Jun NH 2 -terminal kinase </p>

<p>(SAPK/JNK) (threonine-183/tyrosine-185), phospho-protein kinase B (PKB) 
(serine-473), phospho-PKB (threonine-308), PKB, and -actin (Cell Signaling 
Technology, Beverly, MA). Immunoreactive bands were visualized by en-
hanced chemiluminescence (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) using horserad-
ish peroxidase-conjugated IgG secondary antibodies. 
Statistical analysis. Data are expressed as means SE. Data were analyzed 
using the linear regression analysis program PRISM (GraphPad, San Diego, 
CA), and area under the curves were calculated using the algorithm provided 
in the Prism software package. Significance was tested using ANOVA with 
Newman-Keuls hoc test (P 0.05) as indicated in figure legends. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>MK0431 treatment improves islet graft survival in 
diabetic NOD mice. Islet-transplanted, diabetic NOD 
mice were studied to determine the effect of MK0431 
treatment on graft survival. Three groups of mice were 
studied, as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS: group 
1 received normal chow diet throughout the study period 
(NCD Tx), group 2 received MK0431 only after transplant 
(Post MK0431 Tx), and group 3 received MK0431 before 
and after transplant (Fig. 1A). Importantly, of mice that 
were treated with MK0431 before receiving the transplant, 
only 22.8% (8 of 35) became diabetic, compared with 40% 
(14 of 35) of the mice receiving normal chow diet. 
For the transplants, islets were infected with a rAD-TK, 
recombinant adenovirus expressing HSV1-sr39tk, the 
gene for a mutant form of herpes simplex virus 1 thymi-
dine kinase, to enable PET imaging (29,30), and inserted 
under the kidney capsule of diabetic female NOD mice. 
The effect of recombinant adenoviral infection on NOD 
islet function was addressed with in vitro studies. Insulin 
secretory capacity was preserved in 250 MOI rAD-TK-
treated islets, compared with untreated or control rAD--</p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) </p>

<p>Water Intake (ml/day) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>** ** 
** 
** ** ** 
** </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) </p>

<p>Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>** ** ** ** ** ** ** 
** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) </p>

<p>Fasting Blood </p>

<p>Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>H 
I </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>125 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
Survival Rate (%) </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>4 th </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Continued. </p>

<p>S.-J. KIM AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>
gal virus-treated islets (supplementary Fig. 1A, available 
in an online appendix at http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-
1101). Furthermore, although small decreases in mean cell 
viability were observed with both rAD-TK-and rAD--
gal-treated islets compared with untreated islets, these </p>

<p>reductions did not reach statistical significance (supple-
mentary Fig. 1B), indicating that 250 MOI was an appro-
priate dose for further studies. The DPP-IV activity in 
plasma from nondiabetic NOD mice was 67.2 4.3 mU/ml, 
whereas levels measured at the time of islet transplanta-</p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0 
30 
60 
90 
120 </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>3 rd week </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>AUC </p>

<p>0 
30 
60 
90 
120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>4 th week </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>8000 </p>

<p>NCD Post Pre </p>

<p>AUC </p>

<p>0 
30 
60 
90 
120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>1 st week </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>NCD Post Pre </p>

<p>AUC </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 
30 
60 
90 
120 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>75 </p>

<p>Time (mins) 
Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>2 nd week </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2000 </p>

<p>4000 </p>

<p>6000 </p>

<p>NCD Post Pre </p>

<p>AUC </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
Plasma Glucagon Levels (pM) </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>st 
nd 
rd 
th </p>

<p>## 
## </p>

<p>## 
## </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 
0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>250 </p>

<p>Time (weeks after Tx) 
Plasma Insulin Levels (pM) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>st 
nd 
rd 
th </p>

<p>0 mins 
15 mins 
Pre MK0431 Tx </p>

<p>1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>st 
nd 
rd 
th </p>

<p>1 st 
2 nd 
3 rd 
4 th </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>[ 18 
F]-FHBG (%ID/g) </p>

<p>Time (Weeks after Tx) </p>

<p>Scale 
% ID/g </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>17.6 </p>

<p>** 
** 
** 
** </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>NCD Post Pre </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Time-course monitoring of glucose responses, plasma chemis-
try, and islet graft survival after islet transplantation. On the indicated 
days after transplantation, IPGTTs (A), plasma insulin (B), and gluca-
gon (C) levels were determined in the mice described in the legend to 
Fig. 1A. Blood glucose levels were measured at 0, 15, 30, 60, 90, and 120 
min after the glucose challenge (2 g/kg): NCD Tx group (), Post 
MK0431 Tx group (*), and Pre MK0431 Tx group (•). D: Time-course 
monitoring of MicroPET signals detected from recipient diabetic 
mice after islet transplantation. Mice described in the legend to Fig. 
1A were injected with [ 18 F]FHBG on the indicated days after trans-
plantation and scanned. Regions of interest were placed on the kidney 
area of the microPET image, and two peak values of percent ID/g from 
the two time activity curves for each region were used for determina-
tion of the signals. All data represent the mean SE, and significance 
was tested using ANOVA with a Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where 
**P &lt; 0.05 vs. NCD Tx and ##P &lt; 0.05 vs. 0 min, Pre MK0431 Tx. 
(Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-1101 for a high-quality digi-
tal representation of this figure.) , NCD Tx; o, Post MK0431 Tx; f, 
Pre MK0431 Tx. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-1101 for a 
high-quality digital representation of this figure.) </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF MK0431 ON ISLET GRAFT SURVIVAL </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>tion were 100.7 7.1 mU/ml in the NCD diabetic group, 
93.8 16.5 mU/ml in the post-MK0431 Tx group, and 
52.1 11.8 mU/ml in the pre-MK0431 Tx group (n 57 
per group). Plasma DPP-IV activity in the NCD Tx group 
progressively increased to levels that were 300 -400% 
greater than at the initiation of the study. Both pre-and 
post-MK0431 Tx groups showed significantly reduced 
DPP-IV activity compared with the NCD group (Fig. 1B). 
Plasma levels of active (NH 2 -terminally intact) GLP-1 were 
significantly increased in both pre-and post-MK0431 Tx 
groups, demonstrating protection of circulating incretin 
from DPP-IV-mediated degradation (Fig. 1C). For the first 
0.5 week after transplantation, the pre-MK0431 Tx group 
tended to be slightly heavier (Fig. 1D), eat less food (Fig. 
1E), and drink less water (Fig. 1F) than the post-MK0431 
Tx group; however, this difference was not statistically 
significant. The NCD and post-MK0431 Tx groups then lost 
body weight (Fig. 1D) despite their greater food and water 
intake (Fig. 1E and F), whereas the pre-MK0431 Tx group 
maintained body weight and food and water intake re-
mained stable (Fig. 1D-F). By 0.5 weeks after transplan-
tation, nonfasting blood glucose levels were normalized in 
the pre-MK0431 Tx group, whereas levels in NCD and 
post-MK0431 Tx groups progressively increased from 1 
week on (Fig. 1G). A similar trend was evident for fasting 
blood glucose (Fig. 1H). During the course of the study, 
80% of the NCD Tx group and 40% of the post-MK0431 Tx 
group died, probably as a result of the severe hyperglyce-
mia, whereas all of the pre-MK0431 Tx group survived 
(Fig. 1I). 
IPGTTs were performed after transplantation (n 57 
animals/group). As expected, with the suboptimal trans-
planted islet mass, IPGTTs showed a rapid deterioration of 
glucose handling in NCD and post-MK0431 Tx groups. By 
contrast, the pre-MK0431 Tx group preserved the capacity 
to regulate blood glucose levels normally until the end of 
the study (Fig. 2A). Both basal and glucose-stimulated 
plasma insulin levels in the NCD and post-MK0431 Tx 
groups were below 6.2 pmol/l (the detection limit of the 
assay), whereas the pre-MK0431 Tx group showed stable 
insulin secretory responses to glucose stimulation (Fig. 
2B). Although plasma glucagon levels increased substan-
tially in the NCD Tx group over the 3 weeks after trans-
plantation, glucagon levels in the post-MK0431 Tx group 
remained low and were further decreased in the pre-
MK0431 Tx group (Fig. 2C). The effect of MK0431 on islet 
graft survival was further assessed by microPET imaging. 
The PET signal from transplanted islets in the NCD and 
post-MK0431 Tx groups decreased dramatically within 1 
week, whereas mice in the pre-MK0431 Tx group showed 
sustained PET signals for up to 4 weeks after transplanta-
tion (Fig. 2D). These results indicated that MK0431 pre-
treatment resulted in prolongation of islet graft survival. 
Modulation of the immune system in MK0431-treated 
mice. In view of the reduced incidence of diabetes in the 
pre-MK0431 Tx group and the prolonged islet graft sur-
vival, we considered it likely that the action of MK0431 in 
NOD mice involved modulation of the immune system 
during the 1-month pretreatment period. To determine 
whether MK0431 administration could impact immune cell 
infiltration of transplanted islets, the development of insu-
litis was examined in female NOD mice receiving normal 
chow diet or MK0431 diets for 1 month starting at 8 -10 
weeks of age (Fig. 3A). By 12-14 weeks of age, the 
incidence of diabetes was substantially decreased in the 
MK0431 group compared with the NCD group; 17.6% (3 of </p>

<p>17) of the mice developed diabetes in the MK0431 group 
and 35% (6 of 17) in the NCD group. Animals with glucose 
15 mmol/l were grouped as "normal" and those with 
glucose 15 mmol/l as "diabetic." There were no signifi-
cant differences in blood glucose levels between the 
diabetic mice that had been fed normal chow diet 21.1 
2.5 (n 6) and those receiving MK0431 diet 20.7 2.8 
(n 3) (Fig. 3B). However, histochemical analysis re-
vealed that islets in sections from the diabetic MK0431 
group exhibited a more intact structure, whereas the 
majority of islets in the diabetic NCD group showed severe 
insulitis: 90 and 70% of the islets in NCD diabetic and 
MK0431 diabetic mice, respectively, were infiltrated by 
25% (Fig. 3C). Treatment with MK0431 resulted in signif-
icantly increased islet -cell area in both the mice with 
normal plasma glucose and the diabetic mice: normal mice 
-cell area, NCD: 0.37 0.03%; MK0432: 0.61 0.05%; 
diabetic mice -cell area, 0.01 0.003%; and MK0431: 
0.12 0.02% (Fig. 3D). 
Mechanisms underlying the DPP-IV-mediated reduc-
tion in lymphocytic infiltration. Potential mechanisms 
by which DPP-IV inhibitor treatment protected islets from 
severe lymphocytic infiltration were next assessed. CD4 
T-cells have been considered to be essential for the 
development of diabetes through recognition of -cell 
antigens in the context of the class II major histocompat-
ibility complex (MHC) I-A g7. The identification of an islet-
specific CD4 T-cell clone for the acceleration of diabetes 
in young NOD mice (31) led us to consider the potential 
involvement of DPP-IV-mediated CD4 T-cell migration. 
The in vitro migration of splenic CD4 T-cells isolated 
from the diabetic NCD group was significantly increased 
when compared with the normal NCD group, and MK0431 
treatment partially restored the levels toward normal (Fig. 
3E). The extent of CD4 T-cell migration correlated well 
with plasma DPP-IV activity and blood glucose levels (r 2 
0.85, P 0.0001 for plasma DPP-IV activity and r 2 0.79, 
P 0.0001 for fasting blood glucose levels; Fig. 3F and G). 
These results suggested that the prolonged islet graft 
survival observed in the pre-MK0431 Tx group was at least 
partially due to immunomodulation. 
The effect of MK0431 treatment on signaling modules 
potentially involved in the regulation of CD4 T-cell 
migration was then studied. Rac1 is a member of the 
-GTPase family and has been shown to play an important 
role in cytoskeletal reorganization, membrane trafficking, 
cell growth, and development (32,33). In view of this role, 
we examined the Rac1 GTP binding activity in splenic 
T-cells from normal chow diet and MK0431-treated NOD 
mice. As shown in Fig. 4A, Rac1 GTP binding activity in 
CD4 T-cells of the diabetic NCD group was substantially 
reduced in the diabetic MK0431-treated group. On the 
other hand, there were no significant changes in the level 
of phosphorylation of a number of other signaling mole-
cules, including p38 MAPK (Thr180/Tyr182), SAPK/JNK 
(Thr183/Tyr185), p42/44 MAPK (Thr202/Tyr204), PKB 
(Ser473), or PKB (Thr308) (Fig. 4B-F). Further in vitro 
studies were then performed to determine whether ele-
vated circulating incretins or DPP-IV itself were likely 
responsible for the increase in T-cell migration and Rac1 
activity. CD4 T-cells were isolated from the spleen of 
nondiabetic female NOD mice and treated with DPP-IV, 
GIP, or GLP-1 in the presence or absence of DPP-IV 
inhibitor. As shown in Fig. 5A, treatment of CD4 T-cells 
with DPP-IV resulted in 1.6-fold increase in T-cell migra-
tion that was abolished by DPP-IV inhibitor treatment. </p>

<p>S.-J. KIM AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>
0 </p>

<p>50 
100 
150 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>DPP-IV activity (mU/ml) </p>

<p>R 2 = 0.85 
P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>0 
5 
10 
15 
20 
25 
30 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>Blood Glucose Levels (mmol/l) </p>

<p>R 2 = 0.79 
P &lt; 0.0001 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>CD4 + 
T Cell Migration </p>

<p>(fold difference vs </p>

<p>Control) </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>β 
Relative -cell Area (%) </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>CD4 + 
T Cell Migration </p>

<p>(fold difference vs Control) 
CD4 + 
T Cell Migration </p>

<p>(fold difference vs Control) </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic 
Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic 
Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>0 % 
&lt; 25 % 
25-50 % 
50-75 % 
&gt; 75 % </p>

<p>Percentage of Islets </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 
1 
2 
3 
4 </p>

<p>1 st 
2 nd 
3 rd 
4 th </p>

<p>NCD : </p>

<p>MK0431 : </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>25 </p>

<p>Blood Glucose Levels </p>

<p>(mmol/l) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>N.S. </p>

<p>Weeks: </p>

<p>Normal Diabetic Normal Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>0 % 
&lt; 25 % </p>

<p>25 -50 % 
50 -75 % 
&gt; 75 % </p>

<p>Normal Diabetic Normal Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>FIG. 3. MK0431 regulates the migration of CD4 T-cells. A: Schematic diagram of group design. Female NOD mice (8 -10 weeks old) were placed 
on normal chow diet (NCD group) or MK0431 diet (MK0431 group) for 1 month. B: Nonfasting blood glucose levels. C: Representative pancreatic 
sections from 12-to 14-week-old littermate female NOD mice stained with H-E were shown. The extent of insulitis was assessed as described in 
RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. D: Relative -cell area. -Cell area was expressed as the percentage of sectional pancreas area as described in 
RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. E: CD4 T-cells were isolated from the spleen of NCD and MK0431 group. The migration of CD4 T-cells was 
determined using Transwell chamber as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. Correlation between migration of splenic CD4 T-cells and 
plasma DPP-IV activity (F) and blood glucose levels (G). Data were analyzed using the linear regression analysis program <rs type="software">PRISM</rs>. All data 
represent mean SE, and significance was tested using ANOVA with a Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where **P &lt; 0.05 vs. normal NCD group and 
##P &lt; 0.05 vs. diabetic NCD group. (Please see http://dx.doi.org/10.2337/db08-1101 for a high-quality digital representation of this figure.) </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF MK0431 ON ISLET GRAFT SURVIVAL </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>Neither GIP nor GLP-1 exhibited significant effects on 
T-cell migration. In preliminary studies, similar effects of 
DPP-IV on migration of human T-cell lymphoma Jurkat 
cells were observed. Treatment resulted in 3.8-fold in-
creases in migration that were abolished by DPP-IV inhib-
itor treatment (supplementary Fig. 2, available in the 
online appendix). </p>

<p>Treatment with DPP-IV also increased Rac1 GTP bind-
ing activity, whereas both GIP and GLP-1 had no effect 
(Fig. 5B). There were also no significant effects of DPP-IV, 
GIP, or GLP-1, in the presence or absence of DPP-IV 
inhibitor, on phosphorylation of other signaling proteins 
examined (Fig. 5C-G), strongly suggesting that DPP-IV 
regulates the migration of CD4 T-cells directly via a 
pathway involving Rac1. 
Both PKA activation of Rac1 (34) and Rac1 activation of 
PKA (35) have been described in different cell types. 
Involvement of the cAMP/PKA pathway in DPP-IV action 
on CD4 T-cells was therefore studied. Treatment of 
splenic CD4 T-cells with 100 mU/ml DPP-IV for 30 min 
resulted in 2.7-fold increase in cAMP concentration 
compared with control, and DPP-IV inhibitor abolished the 
effect (Fig. 6A). By contrast, treatment with GIP or GLP-1 
(100 nmol/l) had no significant effects on cAMP levels (Fig. 
6A). MK0431 decreased DPP-IV-mediated PKA activation 
in a concentration-dependent manner (Fig. 6B). The low 
concentrations that resulted in inhibition support a spe-
cific action of MK0431 on DPP-IV. Additionally, MK0431 
did not inhibit the PKA stimulatory effect of 6-Bnz-cAMP, 
a PKA-selective, PDE-resistant cAMP analog (Fig. 6C). 
This suggests that the activation is upstream of cAMP 
production, probably at an extracellular level. As ex-
pected, when PKA was inhibited by either H-89 or Rp-
cAMPs, DPP-IV was no longer capable of stimulating PKA, 
and DPP-IV inhibition exhibited no further effect (data not 
shown). Together, these results strongly support a mech-
anism for DPP-IV-mediated PKA activation proximal to, or 
at the level of, adenylate cyclase. Forskolin, a direct 
activator of adenylyl cyclase, was found to mimic the 
effect of DPP-IV on CD4 T-cell migration, and responses 
to both DPP-IV and forskolin were greatly reduced by 
administration of the selective PKA inhibitor H-89 (Fig. 
6D). Similarly, DPP-IV and forskolin both increased Rac1 
GTP binding, whereas H-89 abolished their effects (Fig. 
6E). Together, these results strongly suggest that DPP-IV 
activates a pathway involving the production of cAMP and 
activation of PKA and Rac1, resulting in increased CD4 
T-cell migration. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Two major developments have been responsible for dra-
matically improving the long-term success of islet trans-
plantation and allowing islet-alone grafts: the development 
of automated methods for human islet isolation (36) and 
improved immunosuppression (37), culminating in what is 
known as the "Edmonton Protocol" (37,38). However, 
despite major successes, with current procedures, at least 
two donor pancreata are generally needed to achieve 
insulin independence because of the loss of islet viability 
both during isolation and after transplantation. Addition-
ally, only 67% (39) and 10% (40) of transplant recipients 
have been shown to be insulin independent at the end of 1 
and 5 years, respectively. The causes of loss after trans-
plant are multiple, and apoptosis is thought to play a 
critical role. Because the incretin hormones GIP and 
GLP-1 have been reported to stimulate -cell proliferation 
and survival (1-3,5-7), increasing the concentrations of 
bioactive incretin hormones through DPP-IV inhibitor 
treatment could offer therapeutic advantages in type 1 
diabetic patients receiving islet transplants. In the present 
study, MK0431 pretreatment was shown to exert beneficial 
effects on glycemia in mice receiving islet transplants, as </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>β 
β 
→ </p>

<p>← </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>p38 MAP Kinase </p>

<p>p-p38 MAP Kinase 
(Thr180/Tyr182) </p>

<p>p-SAPK/JNK 
(Thr183/Tyr185) </p>

<p>β -actin </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>p46 
SAPK/JNK 1 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>GTP bound to Rac1 </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vs. Control) </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>p-PKB (Thr308) → </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>PKB → </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>p-PKB (Ser473) </p>

<p>PKB </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>p-p42/44 MAP Kinase 
(Thr202/Tyr204) </p>

<p>p42/44 MAP Kinase </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>Normal 
Diabetic </p>

<p>NCD 
MK0431 Diet </p>

<p>Normal Diabetic Normal Diabetic </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Signaling modules potentially involved in the effect of MK0431 
on splenic CD4 T-cells. A: Rac1 GTP binding activity. Total cellular 
extracts were isolated from CD4 T-cells described in Fig. 3 legend; 
Rac1 GTP binding activity was determined as described in RESEARCH 
DESIGN AND METHODS; and the data are expressed as fold difference vs. 
normal NCD group. Western blot analyses were performed with anti-
bodies against phosphorylated p38MAPK (Thr180/Tyr182) (B), SAPK/ 
JNK (Thr183/Tyr185) (C), p42/44 MAPK (Thr202/Tyr204) (D), PKB 
(Ser473) (E), PKB (Thr308) (F), and actin. Western blots are repre-
sentative of n 3, and significance was tested using ANOVA with a 
Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where **P &lt; 0.05 vs. normal NCD group 
and ##P &lt; 0.05 vs. diabetic NCD group. </p>

<p>S.-J. KIM AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>
indicated by metabolic studies and microPET imaging 
(Figs. 1 and 2). In contrast to the preserved GSIS of the 
pre-MK0431 Tx group (Fig. 2A), glucose tolerance rapidly </p>

<p>deteriorated in both the NCD and post-MK0431 Tx groups, 
and these two groups showed greatly attenuated PET 
signals (Fig. 2D). In a subsequent study, it was shown that </p>

<p>← ← </p>

<p>p-SAPK/JNK 
(Thr183/Tyr185) → → </p>

<p>→ → </p>

<p>→ → </p>

<p>→ → </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>p46 
SAPK/JNK 1 </p>

<p>← </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>-actin 
β 
→ </p>

<p>p-p42/44 MAP Kinase 
(Thr202/Tyr204) → </p>

<p>p42/44 MAP Kinase 
→ </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GIP 
GIP 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GLP-1 GLP-1 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GIP 
GIP 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GLP-1 GLP-1 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>p38 MAP Kinase → </p>

<p>p-p38 MAP Kinase 
(Thr180/Tyr182) → </p>

<p>Control GIP 
GIP 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GLP-1 GLP-1 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>→ </p>

<p>p-PKB (Thr308) → </p>

<p>PKB → </p>

<p>G </p>

<p>Control GIP 
GIP 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GLP-1 GLP-1 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>p-PKB (Ser473) → </p>

<p>PKB → </p>

<p>F </p>

<p>Control GIP 
GIP 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control GLP-1 GLP-1 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV DPP-IV 
+ DPP-IVi </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ + + </p>

<p>_ 
_ + 
_ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>GIP (100 nM): </p>

<p>GLP-1 (100 nM): </p>

<p>DPP-IV (100 mU/ml): </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ + + </p>

<p>DPP-IV inhibitor (100 µM): </p>

<p>GIP (100 nM): </p>

<p>GLP-1 (100 nM): </p>

<p>DPP-IV (100 mU/ml): </p>

<p>DPP-IV inhibitor (100 µM): </p>

<p>_ 
_ + 
_ 
_ 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>CD4 + 
T Cell Migration </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vs.Control) </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ _ 
+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + 
_ 
+ 
_ + </p>

<p>_ _ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ _ 
+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + 
_ 
+ 
_ + </p>

<p>_ _ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
+ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ _ 
+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + 
_ 
+ 
_ + </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>GTP bound to Rac1 </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vs. Control) </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ 
_ + + _ _ 
_ 
_ 
_ + + _ _ 
_ </p>

<p>FIG. 5. The effect of sDPP-IV and incretins on splenic CD4 T-cells. CD4 T-cells were isolated from the spleen of nondiabetic female NOD mice placed 
on normal chow diet. T-cells were stimulated with purified porcine DPP-IV (100 mU/ml), GIP or GLP-1 (100 nmol/l) in the presence or absence of 100 
mol/l DPP-IV inhibitor for 1 h. A: Splenic CD4 T-cell migration. The migration of splenic CD4 T-cells were determined using Transwell chamber 
(Corning) as described in RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS. B: Rac1 GTP binding activity. Total cellular extracts were isolated, and Rac1 GTP binding activity 
was determined. C-G: Total cellular extracts were isolated, and Western blot analyses were performed with antibodies against phosphorylated p38MAPK 
(Thr180/Tyr182) (C), SAPK/JNK (Thr183/Tyr185) (D), p42/44 MAP Kinase (Thr202/Tyr204) (E), PKB (Ser473) (F), PKB (Thr308) (G), and actin. Western 
blots are representative of n 3, and significance was tested using ANOVA with a Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where **P &lt; 0.05 vs. control. </p>

<p>EFFECTS OF MK0431 ON ISLET GRAFT SURVIVAL </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>despite improved islet structural integrity in the diabetic 
MK0431 group compared with that in the diabetic NCD 
group (Fig. 3C), there were no significant differences in 
nonfasting blood glucose levels between the groups (Fig. 
3B). Additionally, no significant differences in nonfasting 
blood glucose levels were observed even in 2-month 
MK0431-pretreated mice (data not shown). However, be-
cause MK0431 treatment resulted in the preservation of 
pancreatic -cells in both mice with normal glucose toler-
ance and the diabetic group (Fig. 3D), we cannot exclude 
a significant contribution from the residual islets to the 
overall beneficial effects of MK0431 pretreatment on gly-
cemia in the mice receiving islet transplants. 
There is considerable evidence supporting a critical role 
for DPP-IV in immune regulation, including delivery of a 
costimulatory signal for T-cell activation (41). Acute rejec-</p>

<p>tion in experimental models of cardiac allograft transplan-
tation was shown to be associated with increased serum 
DPP-IV activity, and inhibition resulted in abrogated acute 
and accelerated rejection (42,43). Additionally, inhibition 
of intragraft DPP-IV significantly reduced ischemia/reper-
fusion-associated pulmonary injury, allowing for success-
ful lung transplantation (44). In the present study, islet 
graft survival was only prolonged significantly in the pre-
MK0431 group. Despite similar active GLP-1 levels in the 
pre-and post-MK0431 Tx groups (Fig. 1C), the post-
MK0431 Tx group showed only minor improvements in 
glucose homeostasis, with mean fasting glucose levels 
slightly lower than the NCD Tx group over the first 2 
weeks (Fig. 1H) and a small enhancement in glucose 
tolerance at 4th week (Fig. 2A). Second, NCD and post-
MK0431 Tx groups showed significantly attenuated PET </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ + 
_ 
+ _ </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>## </p>

<p>## 
## 
## </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>cAMP Concentration 
(pmol/ml) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ + 
_ 
+ _ </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>GIP (100 nM): </p>

<p>GLP-1 (100 nM): </p>

<p>DPP-IV (100 mU/ml): </p>

<p>+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ + </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ 
_ 
_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>DPP-IV inhibitor (100 µM): </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ + 
_ 
+ 
+ 
_ </p>

<p>_ _ </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>2.5 </p>

<p>Relative PKA activity </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vs Control) </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>DPP-IV (100 mU/ml): </p>

<p>_ 
+ </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>10 
1 
0.1 
0.01 </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>** 
** ** ** ** ** </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>Relative PKA activity </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vsControl) </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>6-Bnz-cAMP (100 µM): </p>

<p>MK0431 (µM): </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>100 
10 
1 
0.1 
0.01 </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.5 </p>

<p>1.0 </p>

<p>1.5 </p>

<p>2.0 </p>

<p>CD4 + 
T Cell Migration </p>

<p>(fold difference vs Control) </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>GTP bound to Rac1 </p>

<p>(fold difference </p>

<p>vs Control) </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>E </p>

<p>MK0431 (µM): </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ 
_ </p>

<p>_ </p>

<p>_ 
+ 
+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ 
_ 
+ 
+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ 
_ 
+ 
+ 
+ + 
+ 
+ </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV FSK H-89 DPP-IV 
+ H-89 </p>

<p>FSK 
+ H-89 </p>

<p>Control DPP-IV FSK H-89 DPP-IV 
+ H-89 </p>

<p>FSK 
+ H-89 </p>

<p>FIG. 6. The effect of sDPP-IV on cAMP accumulation and the 
involvement of cAMP/PKA/Rac1 pathway in DPP-IV-mediated 
CD4 T-cells migration. A: DPP-IV-mediated cAMP accumula-
tion. Splenic CD4 T-cells were stimulated for 30 min with GIP, 
100 nmol/l GLP-1, or 100 mU/ml purified porcine DPP-IV in the 
presence of 0.5 mmol/l IBMX, and cAMP concentrations were 
determined in the cell extracts. B: Effect of MK0431 on DPP-IV-
mediated PKA activation. Splenic CD4 T-cells were treated 
with 100 mU/ml purified porcine DPP-IV in the presence of 
indicated concentration of MK0431, and PKA activity was de-
termined. C: Effect of MK0431 on 6-Bnz-cAMP-mediated PKA 
activation. Splenic CD4 T-cells were treated with 100 mol/l 
6-Bnz-cAMP in the presence of indicated concentration of 
MK0431, and PKA was activity determined. D: Effect of PKA 
inhibition on DPP-IV-mediated T-cell migration. CD4 T-cells 
were stimulated for 1 h with 100 mU/ml DPP-IV or 10 mol/l 
forskolin in the presence or absence of 10 mol/l H-89, and cell 
migration was determined. E: Effect of PKA inhibition on DPP-
IV-mediated Rac1 activation. CD4 T-cells were treated as 
described above, and Rac1 GTP binding activity was determined. 
All data represent means SE, and significance was tested 
using ANOVA with a Newman-Keuls post hoc test, where **P &lt; 
0.05 vs. control and ##P &lt; 0.05 vs. DPP-IV. </p>

<p>S.-J. KIM AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>
signals from the 1st week compared with those of the 
pre-MK0431 Tx group (Fig. 2D). These results strongly 
suggest that MK0431 modulated the immune function of 
DPP-IV during the 1-month pretreatment period, thus 
contributing to islet graft survival in the NOD mice. The 
pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes involves activation of 
autoimmune T-cells followed by their homing in on the 
pancreatic islets, resulting in the destruction of -cells. It 
was previously reported that soluble DPP-IV (sCD26) had 
an enhancing effect on transendothelial T-cell migration 
mediated through its intrinsic DPP-IV enzyme activity 
(45). In the present study, migration of splenic CD4 
T-cells prepared from the diabetic NCD group was 
significantly increased compared with that of the non-
diabetic NCD group, and MK0431 treatment partially 
restored the levels toward normal (Fig. 3E). 
Active, GTP-bound Rac1 plays an important role in the 
control of cell migration by regulating actin-rich lamelli-
podial protrusions that are critical for the generation of 
driving force of cell movement (46). Recently, it was 
shown that basal activation of Rac1 via MHC class II 
molecule stimulation is essential for CD4 T-cell motility, 
and self-ligand deprivation is associated with reduced 
levels of active Rac1 (47). In the present study, enhanced 
Rac1 GTP binding activity in CD4 T-cells of the diabetic 
NCD group was found to be decreased in the diabetic 
MK0431-treated group (Fig. 4A). Furthermore, DPP-IV 
directly influenced the migration of CD4 T-cells and Rac1 
GTP binding activity (Fig. 5). It is therefore conceivable 
that increased plasma DPP-IV activity in diabetic NCD 
mice led to increased CD4 T-cell migration by regulating 
Rac1 GTP binding activity, whereas MK0431 attenuated 
autoimmune diabetes partially through decreasing CD4 
T-cell migration. Strong evidence for the involvement of 
increased cAMP production and PKA activation in DPP-
IV-mediated CD4 T-cell migration was obtained (Fig. 
6A-D), although it is unclear as to the protein activation 
sequence. In the current studies, DPP-IV and forskolin 
activation of Rac1 (Fig. 6E) were all ablated by treatment 
with the PKA inhibitor H89, suggesting that Rac1 is down-
stream of PKA. Although the effect of cAMP/PKA on cell 
migration has been reported to be positive or negative 
depending on the cell type, the spatial-temporal distribution 
and activation of cAMP/PKA during the regulation of cell 
migration are likely to be critical components of its action 
(48). 
Although the results reported in the present study 
suggest that direct inhibitor effects on DPP-IV, and not 
increased levels of active GIP and GLP-1, are mainly 
responsible for the improvements in graft retention, we 
have not completely ruled out a contribution from the 
incretins or other factors. Additionally, the reduced inci-
dence of diabetes in the MK0431-treated group may well 
involve the incretins. The long-acting GLP-1 receptor ago-
nist exendin-4, has been shown to synergize with anti-CD3 
monoclonal antibody treatment in reversing diabetes in 
NOD mice by enhancing the recovery of -cells (49). 
Furthermore, continuous administration of GLP-1 to pre-
diabetic NOD mice reduced diabetic incidence by regulat-
ing -cell proliferation and apoptosis (50). More recently, 
the GLP-1 receptor was shown to be expressed in lym-
phoid tissue, and exendin-4 treatment increased the num-
ber of CD4 and CD8 T-cells in the lymph nodes and 
reduced the number of CD4 CD25 Foxp3 regulatory 
T-cells in the thymus, suggesting direct effects of GLP-1 on 
the immune system (51). However, exendin-4 treatment </p>

<p>was not associated with significant changes in the number 
of CD4 and CD8 T-cells or B-cells in the spleen (51). In 
the present study, neither GIP nor GLP-1 treatment pro-
duced significant effects on splenic CD4 T-cell migration 
in vitro (Fig. 5), whereas DPP-IV was stimulatory. The 
reason for the diverse effects of GLP-1/exendin-4 on the 
different subset of T-cells in vivo is not understood, but 
the potential for DPP-IV to modify additional subsets of 
lymphocytes, including those in lymph nodes and the 
thymus, requires further investigation. The beneficial ac-
tions of DPP-IV inhibitors and DPP-IV-resistant GLP-1 
receptor agonists in type 2 diabetes have mainly been 
attributed to increased incretin receptor-mediated re-
sponses. Although it has been recognized that DPP-IV also 
plays a significant role in modulating immune function, no 
beneficial sequelae of inhibiting such actions in diabetes have 
been described. The ability of the DPP-IV inhibitor MK0431 to 
prolong islet graft survival by reducing immunocyte migra-
tion and islet infiltration suggests that the underlying cAMP/ 
PKA/Rac1 could be an additional drug target. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>C.H.S.M. has received funding from Merck Frosst Canada. 
C.H.S.M. has served on the Scientific Advisory Board for 
Probiodrug; has been a consultant for Marck Frosst Can-
ada, Merck, Boehringer Ingleheim, and Takeda; and has 
received funding for basic research from Probiodrug, OSI, 
and Merck Frosst. 
No other potential conflicts of interest relevant to this 
article were reported. 
We thank Dr. Thomas J. Ruth, Salma Jivan, and Tri-
University Meason Facility for support and the preparation 
of [ 18 F]FHBG, Siobhan McCormick for excellent technical 
assistance, S. Gambhir (Stanford University) for the HSV1-
sr39TK construct, and Dr. H.-U. Demuth (Probiodrug) for 
the GIP, GLP-1, and DPP-IV. </p>



<p>EFFECTS OF MK0431 ON ISLET GRAFT SURVIVAL </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>



<p>S.-J. KIM AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 58, MARCH 2009 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>