<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2731890" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-23T20:38+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>Potential promoters in the genome of Escherichia 
coli were searched by pattern recognition software 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> and classified on the basis of positions 
relative to gene borders. Beside the expected pro-
moters located in front of the coding sequences 
we found a considerable amount of intragenic 
promoter-like signals with a putative ability to 
drive either antisense or alternative transcription 
and revealed unusual genomic regions with extre-
mely high density of predicted transcription start 
points (promoter 'islands'), some of which are 
located in coding sequences. <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores con-
verted into probability of RNA polymerase binding 
demonstrated certain correlation with the enzyme 
retention registered by ChIP-on-chip technique; 
however, in 'dense' regions the value of correlation 
coefficient is lower than throughout the entire 
genome. Experimental verification confirmed the 
ability of RNA polymerase to interact and form 
multiple open complexes within promoter 'island' 
associated with appY, yet transcription efficiency 
was lower than might be expected. Analysis of 
expression data revealed the same tendency for 
other promoter 'islands', thus assuming functional 
relevance of non-productive RNA polymerase bind-
ing. Our data indicate that genomic DNA of E. coli is 
enriched by numerous unusual promoter-like sites 
with biological role yet to be understood. </p>

<p>Even though expression data are now available for many 
organisms, a possibility to use them for tracking cell tran-
scriptional output upon varying conditions requires a com-
prehensive map of genome regulatory elements. Currently 
there are two approaches opening a way to depict this 
map: computational search of promoter regions [most 
recent algorithms: (1-10)], and ChIP-on-chip spotting of </p>

<p>RNA polymerase (RNAPol)-binding sites (11-14). In this 
study we tried to understand how predictable the data 
obtained in silico are and to what extent they correlate 
with the data obtained in vivo. 
The genome-scale mapping of promoter sites has been 
performed by our pattern recognition software <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> 
(6,7). The same as other protocols operating with 
position-specific weight matrices, <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> has an advan-
tage of predicting transcription start points (TSP) (the 
main promoter attribute, which is determined experimen-
tally), rather than to define promoter regions as extensive 
genomic loci (9,10,15,16). Upon scanning <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> con-
siders any nucleotide as a probable point of transcription 
initiation and scores this probability by searching for 
promoter-specific elements in proper positions. Rather 
high precision and low rate of false positives made our 
software suitable for genome scanning, providing a possi-
bility to compare in silico and in vivo data. In the present 
work, we describe an overall map of TSPs predicted by 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>; evaluate the degree of correlation between 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores and RNAPol-binding efficiency regis-
tered by two independent research groups (12,13); focus 
attention on intragenic TSPs and promoter 'islands' 
having high density of transcription signals over long dis-
tance; and verify capacity of one 'island' to bind RNAPol 
and initiate RNA synthesis. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>An essence of computational approach </p>

<p>Our scoring system was designed as originally suggested 
by Hertz and Stormo (17). Sensitivity of this algorithm 
tested on our sets was the same as reported (Figure 1B). 
To increase the performance of this approach, we took 
into account sequence-dependent structural features in 
the genomic environment of promoter sites (6, 7). The 
final version of <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> (7) was refined on 271 experi-
mentally identified non-homologous and non-overlapping 
s 
70 -promoters with a single TSP precisely pointed out by 
the previous version of our software (6). All sequences 
were 411-bp long (À255/+155 according to the start 
point nominated as 0). Allowed variations of the spacer, </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +7 4967 73 91 40; Fax: +7 4967 33 05 09; Email: ozoline@icb.psn.ru </p>

<p>ß 2009 The Author(s) 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>and the distance between the TSP and the element -10 
were 14-21 and 2-9 bp, respectively. Variable length of 
the spacer was accounted by the matrix penalizing devia-
tions from the optimal 17 bp in accordance with their fre-
quencies in the training promoter set. The varying distance 
between element À10 and the TSP, ignored by previously 
published protocols, was taken into account the same way. 
Weight matrices corresponding to consensus elements À35 
and À10 evaluated hexanucleotides, rather than 25 and 
19 bp sequences, accounted by Hertz and Stormo 
(Figure 1A and B). They contain 6 Â 4 scores equal to 
natural logarithms of normalized occurrence frequencies 
for each nucleotide at each position in preliminarily 
aligned promoters. Percentage of particular nucleotides 
in the genome was used for normalization. Sequence pref-
erence nearby the TSP previously accounted by a 12 Â 4 
weight matrix (17) was scored by the matrix precisely 
reflecting the distribution of dinucleotides in À1/0. 
Dinucleotides forming the 'extended À10 element' were 
accounted the same way. Since frequency coefficients 
depend on promoter alignment, optimal matrices were 
generated by the procedure of expectation-maximization. 
Additional sequence motifs were scored by the set of 34 
cascade matrices exemplified in ref. (7). They include di-, 
tri-and tetranucleotides having occurrence frequencies at 
least 5 SD higher than the background level in the partic-
ular positions of 34 promoter subregions (Figure 1B). 
These matrices represent: </p>

<p>(i) Sequence motifs potentially interacting with RNA 
polymerase a-subunits, including (A) n -tracts as per-
fect targets (18). 
(ii) (T) n -and (A) n (T) n -tracts able to promote additional 
protein-protein or DNA-protein contacts by indu-
cing proper bending of the DNA helix (19). 
(iii) Elements containing flexible YR steps (Y = T = C, 
R = A = G) favoring adaptive isomerization of the 
promoter DNA (20). 
(iv) Other motifs previously revealed by cluster analysis 
(21). </p>

<p>Cascade matrices consider all sequence elements domi-
nant in a particular promoter subregion, but only the most 
significant one found in a certain promoter is taken into 
account. Thus, for instance, there are 30 motifs dominat-
ing in the region À48/À41. The most frequent of them, 
hence the most significant one, is ATAA if located in posi-
tion À44. It gives 0.91 to the overall score. Slightly less 
significant (contribution 0.82) is TATA if located in À45. 
Thus, for promoter containing TATAT in À45/À41 the 
overall score increases by 0.82, while for promoter, con-
taining TATAA -by 0.91, rather than by 0.91+0.82. 
Lack of accounted motifs in a particular subregion of a 
promoter was penalized based on probability of their 
absence in this place in the training set. 
Ten cascade matrices were used to formalize the pres-
ence of mixed w-tracts (w = A = T), highly typical for 
promoter DNA. They are regularly distributed with 1 or 
1.5 helix turns periodicity (Figure 1B) and may participate 
in polymerase sliding along DNA (22). To focus attention 
on the observed regularity we search for www(n) 7,8 www </p>

<p>and www(n) 13,14 www thus minimizing overlap with 
(A) n -and (T) n -specific matrices. 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> also takes into account perfect direct and 
inverted repeats (5-11 bp long separated by 5 or 6 bp) as 
potential targets for interaction with regulatory proteins. 
They are scored as natural logarithms of lengths if 
centered in subregions of their frequent occurrence 
(Figure 1B). 
The contributions of both types of repeats and elements 
accounted by cascade matrices were reduced by coeffi-
cients estimated as a ratio of the average information con-
tent [quantified as described in ref. (23)] in the particular 
subregion to the information content in the sixth position 
of the aligned element -35 (the least significant among 
conservative base pairs). This reduction was aimed to 
balance the endowment of additional elements with that 
of conservative base pairs. Inputs of all elements were 
summarized, giving the total score (S), which reflects the 
probability for any nucleotide to be a TSP and therefore 
the probability of its upstream region to bind RNAPol 
and fulfill promoter function. 
Performance of the program was tested on a set of 
290 known promoters and two control sets (CSs). All 
sequences were 411 bp long (À255/+155 according to 
real or virtual TSPs). The testing compilation was com-
posed of experimentally characterized s 
70 promoters not 
included in the training set. To increase the size of this set 
we allowed the presence of promoters ($30%) with mul-
tiple TSPs (for instance discussed below dcuA), while 
homologous or overlapping promoters were excluded. 
CS1 was composed of 273 coding sequences taken from 
the fixed position of all convergent genes longer than 
700 bp, separated by 50-bp intergenic space, which 
are not associated with promoter 'islands' (see below) 
and have 5 
0 -ends similarly annotated in U00096 and 
U00096.2 E. coli gene maps. Sequences were taken so as 
virtual TSPs were 250 bp far from initiating codon (fall in 
position 254 inside the gene). This strategy minimizes the 
probability to pick out functional promoter for alternative 
transcription or for yet unidentified genes in intergenic 
regions. Having AT-content (48.3%) very close to that 
of the whole genome (49.2%) CS1 roughly represents nat-
ural sequences, which RNAPol has to bypass. CS2 
was composed of 400 random sequences with the same 
AT-content as in chromosomal DNA. (All compilations 
are available by request.) Promoters were considered as 
recognized by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> if experimentally mapped 
TSP(s) or a neighboring nucleotide (AE2) had score 
higher than threshold level. Using this criteria and the 
last version of <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> we identified 85.5% of promoters 
from the test compilation at zero level of false positives 
(level 1, Figure 1) in both CSs (S max = 3.4). Thus, at this 
level the combination of sensitivity (percentage of recog-
nized promoters = 85.5%) and specificity (percentage 
of unrecognized non-promoter sequences = 100%) of 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> was better than that of previously suggested 
algorithms (68.7-82% and 82.2-99.1%, respectively) 
[(2,15,24) and Figure 1C]. Approximately 80% of recog-
nized promoters possess experimentally mapped TSPs 
coinciding (in the range of AE 2 bp) with positions of local 
S maxima, i.e. nearly 70% of natural TSPs are accurately </p>



<p>predicted by our software, which is also better than pre-
viously reported (&lt;50%) (1,17). </p>

<p>Experimental procedures </p>

<p>The E. coli K12 strain was used as a source of genomic 
DNA and total RNA. DNA was isolated by phenol-
chloroform extraction. Total RNA was purified as 
described in ref. (25). 
Three DNA fragments containing part of promoter 
'island' associated with appY were obtained by PCR. 
A 406-bp fragment spanning over the region À260/+146 
relative to the initiating codon of appY was amplified 
using the primers 5 
0 -GCAAGAGGTTTCAGGTGCGTT 
GTAGTGAG-3 
0 (F1) and 5 
0 -CTTAGTTTAGAGGGGC 
AT-3 
0 (R1). Shortened (378 bp) and elongated (471 bp) 
templates were obtained with F1 + 5 
0 -CCCTTCTAGAT 
TTGTCGCTTACAATAAA-3 
0 (R2) (À260/+118) and 
5 
0 -GATAAGATCTGCAAGTAAAAATGATACTC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>(F2) + R1 (À325/+146), respectively. 
RNAPol-s 
70 -binding ability was tested by gel-
retardation and potassium permanganate footprinting. 
Complexes were formed at 378C in buffer containing 
50 mM Tris-HCl (pH 8.0), 0.1 mM EDTA, 0.1 mM 
DTT, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 mM NaCl, 250 mkg/ml BSA, 
1 pm of 406-bp DNA-fragment and 2-8 pm of RNAPol. 
Templates for permanganate footprinting were 
32 P-
labeled. Interaction was allowed for 30 min. In gel-shift 
experiments, 20 mkg/ml of heparin was added before load-
ing the sample on 4% polyacrylamide gel pre-warmed to 
378C. Gels were run at the same temperature and stained 
by ethydium bromide. Footprinting assays were per-
formed according to (26). Unpaired thymines in open 
transcription complexes were modified by potassium per-
manganate and revealed after piperidine treatment. The 
products of chemical hydrolysis were separated in 8% 
polyacrylamide gel in the presence of 8 M urea and visua-
lized by radioautography. 
Primer extension was carried out using RevertAid </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>M-MulV reverse transcriptase (Fermentas), 4 pm of 
32 P-labeled primer and variable amounts of total RNA 
(1-6 mkg) purified from E. coli cells grown either in LB 
or M9 media and harvested at logarithmic or stationary 
phases. Before the reaction the mixture of RNA and 
primer was heated at 728C for 10 min; cooled down to 
588C, and primer annealing was allowed for 3 min. Then 
the probe was chilled on ice, mixed with the buffer pro-
vided by manufacturer and incubated with the enzyme at 
428C for 45 min. Reverse transcription was terminated by 
heating. cDNA was precipitated by N-butanol and ana-
lyzed the same way as the products of permanganate 
footprinting. 
Single round transcription was carried out as described 
previously (27). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Figure 1 demonstrates advantage given by each additional 
element (Figure 1B) and increased sensitivity of the pro-
gram (Figure 1C and D) for the whole testing compilation 
and positively regulated promoters. All additional </p>

<p>elements improve the resolution but the largest contribu-
tion is given by w-tracts increasing sensitivity for 27.6% 
(Figure 1B). This high significance of additional elements 
provides a chance to detect regulatory regions in newly 
sequenced genomes if information about their own pro-
moters is insufficient. 
Figure 2 exemplifies promoters accurately recognized 
(fadB) and unrecognized (dcuA) by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>. The start 
point of fadB-transcription exactly fits the experimentally 
mapped TSP (Figure 2B), while the original program (17) 
suggests intragenic P1 as a dominant transcription signal 
(Figure 2A) and algorithm developed by Huerta and 
Collado-Vides (1) predicts fadB promoter $150 bp 
upstream of the real TSP [see Figure 4 in (1)]. 
Unrecognized promoter P dcuA (Figure 2D-F) has four 
TSPs, experimentally mapped 69-72 bp upstream of the 
initiating codon (28). S values at these positions vary in 
the range À2.1/À5.7, i.e. far below the level required for 
recognition. All promoter-specific elements in P dcuA are 
weakly pronounced, thus no refinement of the current 
scoring system can compensate for these negative values. 
Although it can not be excluded that P dcuA has some 
important determinants, which are not formalized by 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>, limitations of experimental mapping performed 
by primer extension (28) also may result in some difference 
between apparent and actual TSPs. Reverse transcriptase, 
for example, can stop at sites with stable hairpins in 
mRNA structure. In this case, the registered site of tran-
scription initiation would be pointed out downstream 
from the real one. <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> predicts a good candidate 
(P2) perfectly fitting the RNAPol-binding site registered 
by ChIP-on-chip assay (Figure 2F). Thus, comparing 
in silico and in vivo data one should take into account 
finite sensitivity and selectivity of computer model as 
well as limited accuracy of experimental approaches. 
Even though <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> may be further improved on the 
basis of additional features, current version predicts TSPs 
with rather high accuracy and was used to depict the 
genome-wide distribution of potentially transcribed 
regions. </p>

<p>Genome scanning revealed unexpected intragenic promoters </p>

<p>The genome sequence of E. coli K12 (NCBI, GenBank 
entry U00096.2) was used for large-scale promoter predic-
tion (see Supplementary Table 1 for all <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores 
on both strands). Only signals with S &gt;7.44 (level 2 
in Figure 1D) were considered reliable. This cut-off level 
provides a possibility to identify only 51.0% of known 
promoters (Figure 1D) but ensures p &lt; 0.000043 
(Student's T-test statistics) if average S (À5.0) and SD 
(3.1) were estimated using scores of CS1. Artificially gen-
erated sequences of CS2 showed the same variability of 
S (SD = 3.1) but average score was higher (À4.2), thus 
assuming $2.5-fold higher p-value (p &lt; 0.00011). A total 
of 30 188 individual or clustered TSPs (Figure 2) forming 
$5000 promoter-like regions were found. Since only half 
of known promoters have TSPs with S &gt;7.44, the data 
obtained presume existence of more than 9000 of separate 
promoter-like sites, which is twice greater than the number 
of annotated genes in the genome of E. coli. To what </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4921 </p>

<p>extent this excess could be explained by the presence of 
false positives? 
Relying on p-values only 399-928 of 30 188 predicted 
TSPs (1-3%) may be false signals (4 639 675 bp Â 2 Â p). 
However, intragenic and artificial sequences of CS1 and 
CS2 may be deficient in some promoter-specific features. 
That is why <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> performance was further tested in 
intergenic regions separating convergent genes, even </p>

<p>though each of them may contain yet unidentified genes. 
Predicted TSPs were searched in the central part of inter-
genic space (!250 bp from the ends of flanking genes) so 
as to ensure that only non-coding sequences undergo scor-
ing. Only 15 regions between convergent genes are longer 
than 500 bp but two of them overlap with promoter 
'islands' (see below) and were eliminated. The total 
length of the remaining ones is 10 226 bp (both strands). </p>

<p>Figure 1. (A) Positions of base pairs accounted by Hertz and Stormo (17). (B) Promoter-specific elements scored by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> (preferred positions are 
marked by vertical tics). Ciphers on the right indicate their contribution to S (percentage of promoters additionally recognized at levels 1 and 2). 
(C and D) Discriminative capacity of algorithm suggested by Hertz and Stormo (C) and <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> (D) tested on natural sequences. Blue plots represent 
distribution of scores for virtual TSPs ascribed to +256 position of CS1 sequences. These data were used to estimate the average value of S, standard 
deviation and threshold levels (indicated by horizontal arrows). Red curves show distribution of scores for experimentally mapped TSPs of testing 
compilation (AE2 bp variations are allowed to pick out position with maximal score). These variations are aimed to compensate possible experimental or 
computational inaccuracy. In case of promoters with multiple TSPs, their scores were compared and the maximal one was plotted. These data are used 
to estimate percentage of recognized promoters (indicated above horizontal arrows) at two levels (S &gt; 3.4 and 7.44). Distribution of scores for TSPs 
of promoters regulated by repressors and activators are shown by small gray and large open circles, respectively. Ciphers in parenthesis indicate 
sensitivity of <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> for positively regulated promoters. Vertical arrows and ciphers above indicate position and value of average S. (E-G) 
Distribution of S for all positions in the AE2 (E), AE5 (F) and AE10 (G) areas around virtual TSPs of CS1 (blue symbols) and real starts of testing 
compilation (red circles). Vertical lines delimit points with S exceeding levels 1 and 2. Percentage of positions with S &gt; 7.44 is indicated nearby. </p>



<p>As expected, AT-content of these regions is slightly higher 
(49.2%) than that of CS1 (48.3%). Altogether they 
contain four predicted TSPs (one per $2500 bp). If all of 
them are spurious, the probability to come across a false 
positive is 0.00039, i.e. higher than p-values mentioned 
above. However, two predicted TSPs are perfectly suitable 
for small regulatory RNAs HB_48 and HB_139 predicted 
by Carter et al. (29) and one is located in front of IS 
yi21_6. Supposing that they belong to real promoters, 
false positive rate given by statistic analysis and scanning 
procedure correspond to each other. Even if p = 0.00039 
is taken as a real frequency of false signals, still $90% 
of TSPs predicted by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> should be considered as 
promoter-like signals deserving more detailed analysis. 
An important question is how to perceive <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> 
signals forming clusters near real and accurately recog-
nized by PlatProm TSPs (see Figure 2B for example). 
Should they be considered as false positives or not? 
To address this question we compared distribution of </p>

<p>scores in positions surrounding real (test compilation) 
and virtual (CS1) transcription starts (Figure 1E-G). An 
average S quantified for CS1 remains almost constant if 
the size of analyzed area increases. The number of signals 
exceeding 'level 1' in AE 2 and AE 5 bp area (11 and 24, 
respectively) corresponds to the expected values (11 and 
26, respectively) if CS2 statistic is used but is twice larger 
than expected from p-value (&lt;0.0038) calculated on the 
basis of CS1 scores (6 and 12). The rate of false positives 
given by CS2 statistic is, therefore, quite realistic. It 
assumes 0.63 probability for the presence of highly scoring 
position in the AE 10 area around virtual TSPs of CS1 (total 
number of positions is 5733). One signal with S &gt;7.44 
('level 2') was really registered in this region (Figure 1G). 
Portion of positions with S exceeding 'level 2' and the 
average S decrease upon widening of the analyzed area 
around real promoters, however, distribution of their 
scores does not reveal expected maxima typical for CS1 
(Figure 1E and F). Only in AE10 region S-values show </p>

<p>Figure 2. Distribution of potential TSPs within regulatory regions of fadB/pepQ (A-C) and dcuA/aspA (D-F) as predicted by Hertz and Stormo 
algorithm (top panels) and <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> (middle panels). Black lines mark the coding sequences. Upward and downward bars reflect promoter scores 
quantified for the '+' and 'À' strands, respectively. X-axis is placed at 'level 1' (Figure 1). Dashed lines indicate 'level 2'. Red bars and arrows 
correspond to the experimentally mapped TSPs. Bottom plots show ChIP-on-chip data (13) for analyzed regions. Dashed arrows in plots (B) and (C) 
confine genomic area around the predicted or experimentally mapped TSP(s), where interaction with RNAPol was verified. Dashed arrows in plots 
(E) and (F) outline area nearby registered RNAPol-binding site, where predicted TSPs were searched. </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4923 </p>

<p>noticeable divergence. That means that <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores 
around real TSPs are higher than background values. 
Thus, the total number of positions with S &gt;3.4 for 
AE2 bp area (1681 points) is significantly larger (852) 
than the total number of experimentally mapped starts 
including multiple ones (480). Detailed examination 
showed that $92% of additional signals are generated 
by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> using the same frame for À35 and À10 hexa-
nucleotides as position with maximal S. Remaining 
ones correspond to alternative À10 element (4.4%) or 
À10 and À35 elements (3.6%), suggesting the presence 
of overlapping promoter. Promoters with multiple TSPs 
tend to have additional signals corresponding to alterna-
tive pair of core elements. Thus, in all cases <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> 
signals proximal to known TSPs denote the presence of 
either the same or alternative promoter and should not be 
considered as false positives. 
Predicted TSPs were classified in respect to the borders 
of mapped genes considering 750 bp as the allowed dis-
tance between the predicted transcription starts and the 
coding sequences of downstream genes [$10% of known 
promoters are 250-700 bp far from the coding sequences 
(6)]. Most predicted TSPs were ranked by this strategy 
as 'expected' promoters (Figure 3), although some of 
them fall into upstream genes (see, for instance P2 in 
Figure 2E). 
Approximately 19% of the remaining TSPs were found 
on the opposite strand of coding sequences (Figure 3). 
Antisense RNAs, if initiated therein, may block transla-
tion by base pairing with mRNAs, regulate their stability 
or interfere in other molecular processes. Such RNAs 
control expression of many plasmid and transposon 
genes, but until now they were not considered typical for 
bacterial regulatory networks. Nonetheless several lines of 
evidence support our predictions: </p>

<p>(i) Microarray probes that query expression of anti-
sense strands gave positive hybridization signals </p>

<p>for all genes possessing predicted antisense promo-
ters (30). 
(ii) Among RNAs matching antisense strands and 
found by Vogel et al. (31) and Kawano et al. (32), 
10 species may be transcribed from intragenic pro-
moters predicted by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>. 
(iii) aRNAs I002 (33) and GadY (34) have 5 
0 -ends 
exactly pointed out by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>. 
(iv) Two intragenic promoters found by <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> 
within the coding sequences of hns and htgA/yaaW 
appeared to be active in vitro (35). </p>

<p>Thus, the first amusing outcome obtained from the 
genome scanning was a large amount of genes containing 
promoters with antisense orientation. 
Unexpected intragenic promoters of another group 
have sense orientation (Figure 3). About 23% of corre-
sponding TSPs lie &lt;50 bp downstream from the initiating 
codon. They were not considered as candidates for 
independent transcription initiation, since corresponding 
promoter-like regions may participate in polymerase trap-
ping near real promoters (1). Some intragenic promoters 
may intensify transcription of properly oriented down-
stream genes. If they are also ignored, there are still 
$400 potential TSPs with a less comprehensible destina-
tion. Some of them may produce RNAs antisense to 
mRNAs of the convergently oriented downstream genes. 
Synthesis of shortened mRNAs seems to be the most 
exotic assumption to date. At the same time, <rs id="software-33" type="software">ORF 
Finder</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-33" type="creator">NCBI</rs>) reveals alternative ORFs supplied with a 
suitable Shine-Dalgarno sequence downstream of $50% 
of intragenic co-directed promoters. </p>

<p>The genome of E. coli has promoter 'islands' with high 
density of promoter-like signals </p>

<p>In silico promoter mapping revealed 78 unusual genomic 
regions spanning for at least 300 bp and containing eight 
or more potential TSPs on any strand in the running </p>

<p>Figure 3. Classification of predicted TSPs in respect to their genomic positioning. The main group contains anticipated transcription starts located 
either within intergenic regions or &lt;750 bp upstream of open reading frames. Schemes on the right illustrate all possible variants of their genomic 
environment. Schemes on the left exemplify positions of unexpected intragenic promoter-like sites. </p>



<p>window of 100 bp. Figure 4B exemplifies this phenom-
enon. We call these regions 'promoter islands' (PI) so as 
to distinguish them from clustered 'promoter-like signals' 
(Figure 2B) found in front of almost all (92%) genes of 
E. coli (1,36). ChIP-on-chip assays registered complexes 
with RNAPol for all three PIs in Figure 4 (D and E). 
However, transcription efficiency from appY-associated 
PI1 seemed to be much weaker than that from PI3, 
containing promoters for ompT and pauD and PI2 carry-
ing out antisense transcription from ompT (Figure 4F). </p>

<p>This curious observation prompted us to verify promoter 
activity within the appY genomic locus. 
In perfect conformity with ChIP-on-chip data 
(Figure 4D and E), the 406-bp DNA fragment, containing 
both the expected intergenic promoters and unusual intra-
genic promoter-like sites within appY, formed two major 
heparin-resistant complexes with RNAPol (Figure 5A). 
Their relative abundance depended on enzyme:DNA 
ratio, supposing two or more sites for simultaneous inter-
action with the enzyme. Permanganate footprinting </p>

<p>Figure 4. (A) Scheme illustrating the strategy used to convert <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores into probability of RNAPol binding (P). Fifty-nucleotide microarray 
probe is shown as a gray zigzag line. Dashed and composite lines represent two strands of DNA trapped by RNAPol. To take into account both 
orientations of the enzyme (gray triangle) P was calculated as the sum of S near the expected TSPs on both strands (indicated by braces). The most 
adequate values of P are expected if a given probe exactly fits to a promoter but allowed (AE8 bp) variation in position of the potential start ensures 
capturing scores of promoters shifted by 1-6 bp as well (microarray probes are distributed along DNA with 12 bp periodicity). Plot (C) shows the 
result of this converting procedure for <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores predicted in 57 9670-596 200 bp genomic region (B). Horizontal gray lines indicate gene 
positioning. The X-axis is placed at 'level 2'. Known TSPs of P cusR and P cusC are indicated. Three braces in plot (B) confine promoter 'islands'. Tick 
marks indicate positions of primers used for PCR. (D) RNAPol-binding efficiency represented as log 2 of the ratio of hybridization signal obtained 
with DNA co-immunoprecipitated with the enzyme by b 
0 -specific antibody to control DNA recovered from complexes without specific immunopre-
cipitation (12). (E) The same as (D) but s-specific antibody was used to collect RNAPol-DNA complexes (13). (F) Transcription efficiency from the 
top and the bottom strands, respectively, represented as log 2 of the ratio of fluorescence signals originated from hybridized cDNA to signals obtained 
from hybridized sonicated genomic DNA (13). </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4925 </p>

<p>revealed four transcription bubbles, assuming formation 
of transcriptionally competent open complexes 
(Figure 5B). Three of them lie $190 (I), $155 (II) and 
$90 bp (III) upstream from the appY ATG codon, and 
are suitable candidates for appY promoters, while the 
fourth one is located within the coding sequence 
(Figure 5C). Single round transcription assay performed 
with the same DNA fragment (Figure 5D, lane 2) testified 
synthesis of two major RNA-products: $305 and $237 nt. 
Two additional templates were used to ascribe them to 
particular transcription bubbles. The longer product 
may be initiated at either PII, or PIV (Figure 5C). </p>

<p>It remains unchanged when template shortened in the 
coding region was used (lane 3), while becomes $65 nt 
longer when DNA fragment elongated in opposite direc-
tion was taken for transcription assay (lane 1). Thus we 
conclude that $305 nt-RNA is initiated at PIV and is tran-
scribed in antisense direction. Since the $237 nt-product, 
vice versa, remains unchanged when the longer DNA 
fragment is used but becomes shorter in the case of the 
shortened template, it can be transcribed only from PIII 
towards the coding sequence of appY and, therefore, may 
represent appY-mRNA. However, reverse transcription 
from total RNA failed to reveal the expected cDNAs in </p>

<p>Figure 5. Experimental verification of promoter activity within PI1 (Figure 4B). All procedures are described in 'Materials and methods' section. 
(A) Gel-shift assays were performed at different RNAPol-DNA ratios as indicated above the gel. (B) Local DNA melting as revealed by potassium 
permanganate footprinting. The 5 
0 -end of F1 (C) was </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-labeled. 'G'-sequencing ladder. Arabic ciphers on the right indicate positions of unpaired 
thymines respective to the appY ATG codon. Transcription bubbles are denoted by Roman numerals. (C) Positioning of transcription bubbles (I-IV) 
in the analyzed DNA fragment. Horizontal lines mark unpaired thymines. Bent arrows with size roughly reflecting the value of S show expected 
directions of transcription. The lengths of the expected RNA products to the end of DNA fragment amplified with F1 and R1 are indicated nearby. 
Arrows are white if corresponding RNAs were registered either in vitro (D) or in vivo (F, E). Straight arrows show directions of sense and antisense 
transcription according to appY. (D) Single-round transcription assay. Arrows show transcripts with migration rate altered due to changed length of 
the templates. End-to-end products are indicated by asterisks ('a' and 's' denote antisense and sense directions). (E) and (F) Products of reverse 
transcription from the total RNA using R1 (E) and F1 (F). Bacterial cells were harvested at logarithmic and stationary phases as indicated. Lanes M 
and ciphers nearby calibrate gels on D-F plots. </p>



<p>any of five experiments performed in different conditions 
(Figure 5E). 
Low-transcription efficiency of appY in vivo is consistent 
with the expression data [Figure 4F, (13)] and the data 
obtained by Isalan et al. (37), who tested nearly 600 
cross-combinations of genes encoding transcription regu-
lators or s-factors and their promoters. Reporter gene 
expression [Supplementary 1_GFP; (37)] indicated 
increased transcription in 17 out of 22 constructions 
when cognate promoters were replaced by appY regula-
tory region, thus assuming very high activity of appY pro-
moter. The effect, however, was quite opposite if the appY 
coding sequence was fused to different promoters. 
Transcription efficiency of the reporter gene significantly 
decreased practically for all promoters. Thus, it appears to 
be that strong interaction with RNAPol and even ability 
to form open complexes do not necessarily result in effi-
cient RNA synthesis. In the case of appY transcription 
depends on impediments buried in its coding sequence. 
Intragenic promoter-like sites certainly may play such a 
role. Genomic DNA of E. coli, therefore, contains several 
types of promoter-like sites with poorly understood func-
tion. ChIP-on-chip data were used to evaluate the ability 
of predicted promoters to bind RNAPol in the genome-
wide scale. </p>

<p>Coordinates of predicted promoters overlap with 
RNAPol-binding sites found in vivo </p>

<p>Three questions were addressed to compare in silico 
and in vivo data: </p>

<p>(i) how many predicted TSPs are associated with the 
registered sites of RNAPol binding; 
(ii) how many RNAPol-binding sites are associated 
with the predicted TSPs; 
(iii) how many PIs form complexes with RNAPol 
in vivo? </p>

<p>To answer the first question, we used the whole set of 
30 188 predicted TSPs. They form 4810 clusters or single 
promoter-like sites separated from each other by at least 
100 bp (overlapping clusters on opposite DNA strands 
were combined). Predicted TSPs or TSP clusters were con-
sidered as confirmed by in vivo data, if at least one positive 
chip probe was found by Reppas et al. [(13); experiment B] 
within a AE 100 bp surrounding region (Figure 2B and C 
illustrate scrutinized area). Ninety-four percent of individ-
ual TSPs (or 77% of promoter clusters) fall into genomic 
loci interacting with RNAPol in vivo or are located within 
the allowed distance. Thus, most predicted promoters 
of all types perform at least one promoter function. 
To address the second question, we used the set of 
microarray probes efficiently hybridized with enzyme-
trapped DNAs. A total of 51 922 probes show fluorescent 
signal at least 2-fold higher if RNAPol-DNA complexes 
were extracted using specific antibodies (Figure 2F). They 
represent 1209 continuous genomic regions. RNAPol res-
idence sites observed in vivo were considered related to 
potential promoters if at least one TSP with S &gt; 7.44 
was found within region covered by oligonucleotide 
probes or in AE100 bp surrounding area. Ninety-three </p>

<p>percent of individual probes (86.8% of continuous 
regions) appeared to be associated with predicted pro-
moter sites. 
All 78 promoter 'islands' form extensive complexes 
with RNAPol (Supplementary Table 2). This coincident 
disposition of TSPs found in silico and polymerase-bind-
ing sites registered in vivo allows considering coordinates 
of predicted TSPs as a valid map of transcription signals. </p>

<p>Scores of predicted promoters correlate with efficiency 
of RNA polymerase binding </p>

<p>At the last step we estimated the degree of correlation 
between the values of <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> scores, and efficiencies 
of RNAPol binding. Since S reflects probability of any 
single nucleotide in the genome to be a TSP, while 
ChIP-on-chip method estimates efficiency of RNAPol 
binding to a particular genomic region represented by 
50 nt probes on high-density tiled microarrays, the pattern 
of S should be converted into a comparable mode. 
Converting procedure should take into account that the 
geometrical center of RNAPol-binding site does not coin-
cide with the TSP. Moreover, as RNAPol in vivo interacts 
with double-stranded DNA, samples prepared for chip-
hybridization contained both strands of enzyme-trapped 
fragments. Thus, fluorescent signal registered for a partic-
ular probe may result from two types of complexes 
differing in enzyme orientation (Figure 4A). Supposing 
each 50 nt probe as a target for interaction with polymer-
ase we thus considered the sum of S corresponding to the 
virtual TSPs on both strands as a probability of enzyme 
binding (P): </p>

<p>P ¼ AESðtÞ þ AESðbÞ: 
1 </p>

<p>As the spacer length and the distance between the TSP 
and À10 element differ in real promoters, AE8 nt variation 
in +1 positioning has been allowed. Location of these 
regions relative to 5 
0 -ends was selected experimentally 
as position giving maximal correlation coefficient (R) 
between P and hybridization signals. Figure 4C shows 
the predicted TSPs of the Figure 4B converted in such a 
way. X-axis is shifted 1.96 SD (1 SD = 55.2) above the 
background level of P (average value of all negative P), 
providing p &lt; 0.05 for positive values. 
Log 2 ratios [(log 2 ) B ] reflecting efficiencies of RNAPol 
binding in vivo, obtained by Herring et al. in experiment 
2 (12) and by Reppas et al. in experiment B (13) were used 
to estimate correlation with P. Even though hybridization 
signals registered by two experimental assays differ in 
amplitude (Figure 4D and E), their profiles resemble 
each other and the pattern of P (Figure 4C). Quantified 
values of R are 0.51 (R H ) and 0.38 (R R ), respectively 
(Figure 6). R H is comparable with R values estimated 
for three replicates performed in similar conditions by 
the same research group (R = 0.46; 0.48 and 0.52) (12). 
Are these R H and R R values high or not? Although 
the data obtained in silico and in vivo reflect the same 
phenomena: anticipated and registered interaction with 
RNAPol, there are some peculiarities decreasing evaluated 
correlation. <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs>, for instance, accounts putative 
modules for interaction with regulatory proteins as </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4927 </p>

<p>positive elements, though repressors decrease polymerase 
binding. Many weak RNAPol-binding sites are not 
detected in vivo due to low signal-to-noise ratio (12) but 
<rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> discriminates them. Intensity of ChIP signals 
from some promoters may disproportionately decrease 
due to possibility of epitope occlusion by other inter-
actions (12). Finally, <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> is currently attuned to 
s 
70 -specific promoters, while s 
70 -specific antibodies pre-
cipitate s 
28 as well (13). Usage of b 
0 -specific antibodies 
in combination with rifampicin-chase selection allows 
promoters of all types to be extracted. Considering all 
these realities, we conclude that both values of R are 
rather high. </p>

<p>Promoter 'islands' have unusual functional features </p>

<p>The shape of Figure 6A reveals 2106 outliers with lower 
than expected hybridization signals (red symbols), which 
can not be attributed to experimental or technical errors, 
since oligonucleotide probes to the same genomic regions 
in the other ChIP-on-chip data set also tend to weaker 
hybridization (Figure 6B). This phenomenon can not be 
also explained by repressor functioning since the percent-
age of probes representing genes with inhibited transcrip-
tion (22%) among these outlying probes approximately 
equals the percentage (25%) of such genes in the 
genome [RegulonDB 5.5 (38)]. Further analysis showed 
that almost all out-of-ordered probes correspond to 
regions with multiple promoter-like sites and every one 
of 78 promoter 'islands' turned out to be represented in 
the prominent part of Figure 6A. They comprise 32% of 
all the deviating probes, rather than 0.7% expected by 
chance. R H and R R for promoter 'islands' are low: 0.09 
and 0.17, respectively. Thus, it appears that polymerase 
recognizes any single promoter-like site within the region 
of multiple competing promoters with less predictable effi-
ciency than across the whole genome. High density of 
promoter-like sites tends to weaken rather than strengthen 
RNAPol binding. 
To explore further this phenomenon a set of 181 known 
promoters accurately recognized in silico and possessing 
no more than two additional <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> signal(s) on either 
strand in a AE50 bp area was compiled (Supplementary 
Table 3). Amid others it contains promoters P fadB , P cusC , 
and P cusR (Figures 2 and 4). Only 21 promoters from this 
set contribute to the population of 2106 outlying probes 
by 42 representatives, which is exactly as much as expected 
by chance ($2%). The set of 'normal' promoters was com-
pared with 78 PIs in terms of RNAPol binding and tran-
scription efficiency calculated as described in Figure 6 
legend (Supplementary Tables 2 and 3, and Figure 6C). 
All PIs and 87% of 'normal' promoters (Supplementary 
Tables 2 and 3) form complexes with RNAPol. At the 
same time RNA synthesis has been detected for 107 
'normal' promoters (59%) but only for 20 out of 156 
(78 Â 2) genomic loci flanking promoter 'islands' (13%). 
Figure 6C illustrates expression efficiency and RNAPol 
binding for two compared groups. Points representing 
promoter 'islands' are mainly concentrated in the 
bottom part of the plot. The yield of particular RNAs in 
the cell may, therefore, depend on the presence of </p>

<p>Figure 6. Correlation between P and efficiency of enzyme binding 
(log 2 ) B as registered by ChIP-on-chip assays in experiment 2 carried 
out by Herring et al. (12) (A) and experiment B performed by Reppas 
et al. (13) (B). Only the '+' strand probes [185 519 and 191 088 for (A) 
and (B), respectively] are plotted. Outlying points on plot (A) are dis-
sected by invisible lines equally shifted above and below the median and 
colored. Red and blue symbols on plot (B) represent the same genomic 
regions in the Reppas et al. (13) data set. Since blue outliers in the 
second data set tend to fit better to the expected range of log 2 ratios, 
this slight deviation was not considered as regular and was not further 
analyzed. Points representing promoter 'islands' 1-3 (Figure 4B) are 
shown in green. The indicated values of R were quantified for the 
whole set of microarray probes using (log 2 ) B and P averaged within 
running window 3. (C) Correlation between RNAPol binding (log 2 ) B 
and expression (log 2 ) E efficiencies plotted for 78 PIs (red symbols) and 
181 single promoters (blue symbols). For PIs (log 2 ) B were quantified as 
average values of ChIP-on-chip signals for all probes covering corre-
sponding genomic areas (Supplementary Table 2). (Log 2 ) E was first 
quantified as an average log 2 ratio of chip signals obtained upon 
cDNA hybridization with 10 probes representing the 250-bp region 
downstream from the last predicted TSP on each strand. Two values 
characterizing transcription in both directions were then compared and 
the largest one was considered as the measure of expression efficiency. 
Other variants of (log 2 ) E calculation see in Supplementary Table 2. 
(Log 2 ) B and (log 2 ) E for 'normal' promoters were quantified within 
250 bp region upstream and downstream from the position +1, respec-
tively (Supplementary Table 3). Both (log 2 ) B and (log 2 ) E were averaged 
for two replicates of Reppas et al. (13) data set. First-order regression 
lines show apparent dependence between (log 2 ) B and (log 2 ) E for both 
promoter 'islands' and 'normal' promoters. </p>



<p>competing promoters, which makes genomic regions dif-
fering in abundance of transcription signals dissimilar in 
terms of functional characteristics. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Comprehensive annotation of newly sequenced genomes 
implying mapping of genes along with their regulatory 
elements is currently becoming a long-term strategy 
appealing for effective promoter-finders. In the case of 
genes encoding proteins, rRNAs and tRNAs, which by 
itself are accurately identified by almost perfectly attuned 
computer programs, promoter-finders may assist in local-
ization of regulatory regions. In the case of genes encoding 
small untranslated RNAs they are used to point out posi-
tions where sRNAs may be initiated (29,39), whereas 
other programs classify potential products as putative 
sRNAs based on their thermodynamic features and fold-
ing propensity. In the case of aRNAs promoter-finders 
may provide unique indicators of potential antisense tran-
scription. So far only two dozens of aRNAs at least partly 
synthesized from the antisense strands of other genes have 
been found in E. coli. This rather small number apparently 
does not reflect their multiplicity, as genome-wide expres-
sion studies registered a huge amount of RNAs generated 
from antisense strands (30); <rs type="software">PlatProm</rs> predicted many 
potential promoters for antisense transcription, while 
ChIP-on-chip technique detected suitable intragenic 
RNAPol-binding sites (12,13). Even though many signals 
registered by microarrays may result from run-through 
transcripts unterminated at 3 
0 -ends of neighboring genes, 
some promoters predicted in silico may be false positives 
while intragenic RNAPol-binding sites may represent 
paused elongation complexes, combined data vote for 
antisense transcription in bacteria. 
Along with potential TSPs for antisense transcription 
our screen revealed a large number of intragenic promo-
ters with sense orientation and preferred location near the 
initiating codon. Though expediency of alternative tran-
scription remains vague, very similar phenomenon has 
been recently registered in eukaryotic genomes [see, e.g. 
ref. (40)]. In the chromosome of E. coli, there are several 
pairs of extensively overlapping genes encoding two pro-
teins or a protein and an untranslated RNA. Many of 
them may be transcribed from common promoters. 
However genes hokC, tpr and ygeN with 5 
0 -ends mapped 
within mokC, rttR and ygeO, respectively, as well as 46 
transcripts partly matching sense strand and detected in 
the fraction of short RNAs by Vogel et al. (31) may be 
also initiated from their own promoters predicted by 
PlatProm. Internal promoters with sense orientation 
may, thus, mark candidates for alternative transcription. 
The data obtained drew attention to 78 regions with 
high density of TSPs over long distance. Fifty-five of 
them at least partly overlap with intergenic loci presumed 
to contain active promoters, nine of which are mapped 
experimentally. They initiate RNA synthesis from single 
or several (up to eight) positions. Multiplicity of the TSPs 
might, therefore, be exploited by transcription machinery. 
Four promoter-rich clusters lie between convergently </p>

<p>transcribed genes like in the case of appY/ompT 
(Figure 4B). Their transcription activity, if detected, 
assumes either presence of yet unidentified genes in inter-
genic regions or antisense transcription in one or both 
directions. Putative sRNA IS021 (39), for instance, may 
be synthesized between appY and ompT, while gene for 
sRNA HB_171 is predicted between ygcE and ygcF (29). 
The most interesting are the remaining 19 PIs either 
immersed into one coding sequence or covering the junc-
tion point between two operonic genes, where promoter 
activity is not required. 
Even though all 78 promoter 'islands' bind RNAPol 
in vivo, transcription has been detected for only 13 geno-
mic loci (Figure 6C). In all but one case (PI submerged 
into the wbbK coding sequence) they occupy intergenic 
regions. PI1 (Figure 4B) exemplifies cluster with weak 
expression observed in only one experiment (Supplemen-
tary Table 2). Our data show that RNAPol can interact 
with PI1 and initiate RNA synthesis in both directions 
in vitro but primer extension (Figure 5E) failed to reveal 
the presence of appY-mRNA among RNAs produced 
in vivo. This transcriptional silence makes the value of 
R between promoter scores within PIs and corresponding 
(log 2 ) E statistically insignificant, whereas faint correlation 
between these parameters was registered for the subset of 
'normal' promoters (0.16) and even the whole set of pre-
dicted promoter-like regions (0.075). That means that the 
overall transcription from multiple TSPs does not repre-
sent the sum of expected outputs from individual ones. 
Some sites seem to bind RNAPol without initiating pro-
ductive synthesis, thus performing only part of functions 
commonly ascribed to promoter regions. If so, they may 
be considered as a kind of suppressor elements. 
Currently it is not clear whether promoter 'islands' 
found in this study and 'clusters with high density of 
promoter-like signals' (1,36) reflect one and the same phe-
nomenon. Previously discovered clusters are defined as 
accessories of intergenic loci, surrounding functional 
promoters and participating in their proper regulation, 
while 23 PIs ($30%) are located far from expected pro-
moters. Ninety-two percent of E. coli genes have promo-
ters surrounded by other promoter-like signals (36). This 
clustering, thus, should be considered as a feature typical 
for E. coli genes, while 'single' promoters should be 
ranked as a peculiarity. At the same time only 78 regions 
have extremely high density of potential TSPs assuming 
their special role in genome organization and function. 
Since DNA of all but three PIs has high potentiality to 
undergo stress-induced deformations [(10); http://www 
.genomecenter.ucdavis.edu/benham/sidd_database/], there 
is a reason to suggest a possibility that PIs participate in 
structural remodeling of bacterial chromosome. 
Our conclusions were drawn on the basis of compara-
tive analysis of data sets obtained in silico and in vivo. 
Although both methods have certain limitations if used 
separately, together they provide valid information on 
the genome positioning of RNAPol-binding sites and 
allow spotting a larger set of potential promoters. Thus, 
even weak binding signals associated with a predicted TSP 
may indicate the presence of an active promoter, whereas 
complex formation with the enzyme nearby low scoring </p>

<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4929 </p>

<p>promoters supports their functionality. Moreover, the 
combined use of two approaches allows mapping of all 
types of transcribed regions including those encoding 
untranslated RNA species, hardly identifiable by other 
computational screens. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Russian Foundation for Basic Research (07-04-01066). </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>







<p>Nucleic Acids Research, 2009, Vol. 37, No. 15 4931 </p>

</text></tei>