<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2950835" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-22T17:09+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>Abstract.-The recent explosion in the availability of genetic sequence data has made large-scale phylogenetic inference 
routine in many life sciences laboratories. The outcomes of such analyses are, typically, a variety of candidate phyloge-
netic relationships or tree topologies, even when the power of genome-scale data is exploited. Because much phylogenetic 
information must be buried in such topology distributions, it is important to reveal that information as effectively as pos-
sible; however, existing methods need to adopt complex structures to represent such information. Hence, researchers, in 
particular those not experts in evolutionary studies, sometimes hesitate to adopt these methods and much phylogenetic 
information could be overlooked and wasted. In this paper, we propose the centroid wheel tree representation, which is 
an informative representation of phylogenetic topology distributions, and which can be readily interpreted even by nonex-
perts. Furthermore, we mathematically prove this to be the most balanced representation of phylogenetic topologies and 
efficiently solvable in the framework of the traveling salesman problem, for which very sophisticated program packages 
are available. This theoretically and practically superior representation should aid biologists faced with abundant data. 
The centroid representation introduced here is fairly general, so it can be applied to other fields that are characterized by 
high-dimensional solution spaces and large quantities of noisy data. The software is implemented in Java and available via 
. , T N . In addition, the traditional con-
sensus tree that CWT relies on is also a centroid repre-
sentation regarding the split incongruity loss function, 
which quantifies how the split sets of two trees dis-
agree with each other. See the Appendix for details and 
proofs. 
It is useful to provide some intuitive explanation of 
the fact that a CWT is the centroid representation here. 
Imagine a heap of stones, each of which has a drawing 
of a phylogenetic topology and whose mass is pro-
portional to the probability of the tree. If we place the 
stones so that similar topologies are close to each other, 
a map of a topology distribution is created, as in Hillis 
et al. (2005) and Nye (2008). If this distribution is uni-
modal and unbiased, the heaviest stone or the best tree 
is anticipated to be at the "center" of the distribution 
and represent it well, although sometimes this assump-
tion does not hold true, as discussed in the references 
above. Instead, the CWT representation tries to find the 
centroid (or the center of gravity) of the topologies, by 
placing them on a light plate on which each position 
corresponds to a wheel tree. In classical mechanics, the 
centroid is the point that balances the moment of grav-
ity and minimizes the sum of the products of mass and 
squared distances. This clearly resembles the definition 
of a CWT, as we use the cost functions defined above 
instead of the squared distances, to quantify how close 
a wheel tree and a phylogenetic topology are. There-
fore, the CWT representation can be regarded as the 
centroid that balances the background topology distri-
butions best. </p>

<p>APPLICATIONS 
Visualization of CWTs </p>

<p>In addition to making the circular orderings around 
multifurcating wheel nodes best represent the topology 
distributions, it is useful if some statistical information 
on them is available. Our current implementation of the 
CWT program provides visualization as in Figure 3. 
First, as in ordinary phylogenetic representations, 
numbers at internal branches are the proportions of 
the input trees containing the corresponding splits. 
Second, numbers around the wheel nodes indicate the 
proportions that the flanking splits constitute in a mono-
phyletic group. For example, in Figure 3, Z 1 % of the 
trees have the 3-furcation {a | d | b,c,e,f} (i.e., the three 
splits {a | b,c,d,e,f}, {d | a,b,c,e,f}, and {a,d | b,c,e,f}). 
Third, numbers within wheel nodes indicate the extent 
to which each circular ordering of the branches naturally 
represents the candidate topologies. In other words, the 
numbers indicate the proportion of the input topolo-
gies that can be restored by just "pulling out" branches 
without changing the orderings. (See the right-hand </p>

<p>588 </p>

<p>SYSTEMATIC BIOLOGY </p>

<p>VOL. 59 </p>

<p>FIGURE 3. Information that the CWT representation conveys. 
Branches around multifurcating nodes (wheel nodes) are circularly or-
dered by the procedure in Figure 2. As in the ordinary phylogenetic 
representations, numbers at internal branches (X) are the support val-
ues of the corresponding splits. Numbers around wheel nodes (Z 1 , . . . , 
Z 5 ) indicate the proportions of the flanking splits that constitute a 3-
furcation. Numbers within wheel nodes (Y) indicate the proportions 
of the input trees for which their circular ordering is the best (i.e., does 
not require traversing the same branches three times to visit all splits). 
Note that the input trees that do not have all the split sets adjacent to 
the wheel node are also used to estimate the values within and around 
the wheel nodes. Options for displaying the strict supports excluding 
them and the average distances are also available. </p>

<p>box in Figure 3 for an example. As another example, 
the value for the wheel node in Figure 1d is 85%, which 
is the total support of the first and second topologies 
in Figure 1a). Mathematically, this equals the propor-
tion of the ordering that constitutes a shortest TSP tour, 
given the distance matrices derived using each topology 
only. 
Note that, at the default settings, the values within 
and around the wheel nodes are calculated "on the 
assumption of the consensus tree topology." For the 
input trees that do not have all the split sets adjacent 
to the wheel node, the proportion of topologies within 
all possible combinations of the corresponding branch 
positions (see "Formulation" and Fig. 2b) that con-
tain the corresponding topologies are added to those 
values. Therefore, they are not strict support values 
(like the ones at internal branches) but expected val-
ues based on the assumption of the consensus tree 
topology. For the users' sake, the current implementa-
tion also offers options for showing the strict values 
that input trees contain the corresponding topologies 
as well as the average distances used for the TSP 
calculation. </p>

<p>CWT Applied to a Real Data Set 
Figure 4a is a CWT representation derived from a real 
data set. The input trees were 246 phylogenetic trees 
obtained by applying the maximum-likelihood method 
to reliable single-copy orthologs conserved among 21 
fungal species (downloaded from FUNYBASE; Marthey 
et al. 2008); a 60% threshold was used in building the 
consensus tree. 
The wheel node indicated by the thick arrow connects 
the four splits Ago, Kla, X, and Y. This node indicates </p>

<p>that, given the topology of the consensus tree, 73% of 
the input trees are expected to contain either of the splits 
{Ago,Kla | X,Y} or {Kla,X | Ago,Y}, and 39% and 34% 
contain the 3-furcations {Ago | Kla | X,Y} and {Kla | 
X | Ago,Y}, respectively. Neither the best tree nor the 
consensus tree representation provides such detailed 
information, unless multiple trees are used or the tree 
shapes are abandoned as in the phylogenetic network 
representation (Fig. 4b). Note that the values on the 
opposite sides of the wheel nodes are the same. This is 
because in cases of 4-furcating nodes, for example, if 
the splits Ago and Kla are adjacent (i.e., {Ago | Kla 
| X,Y}) then X and Y are adjacent (i.e., {X | Y | Ago, 
Kla}). This property does not hold true without the 
consensus tree topology assumption, because the input 
trees can contain trees that do not contain the splits 
X and Y and in such cases trees with {Ago | Kla | 
X,Y} can be without {X | Y | Ago,Kla} (Fig. 4a, left 
sides of the dotted rectangles). It is also worthwhile 
to examine the average distance around each wheel 
node used in the TSP calculation (Fig. 4a, right sides 
of the dotted rectangles); in cases of 4-furcating nodes, 
the distances between splits are equal to the propor-
tions that they do not constitute in a monophyletic 
group. 
In addition, because a CWT uses a tree shape, tax-
onomic groups at multiple levels can be recognized 
fairly intuitively. In particular, a CWT can suggest the 
existence of taxonomic groups with support below the 
consensus-tree threshold, in addition to those making 
splits on the consensus trees, as successive branches 
around wheel nodes. Figure 5a is a CWT representa-
tion of the same data set as in Figure 4, based on an 
80% consensus tree. To avoid a cluttered appearance be-
cause of the many multifurcations, a color visualization 
option that uses colors instead of numbers is used to 
show the support values around the wheel nodes. For 
example, the thick gray arc lines α, β, γ, and δ indicate 
the class Eurotiomycetes, class Sordariomycetes, order 
Hypocreales, and subphylum Agaricomycotina, respec-
tively. An interesting application is the star-like CWT, 
obtained by specifying high threshold values where no 
split is supported at a level above the threshold (Fig. 5b; 
branch lengths are ignored and only the topology is 
shown). The star-like CWT shows "the optimal sequen-
tial ordering" of all taxa based on the distribution of 
the input topologies and, as a result, many biological 
groups appear as successive branches around the wheel 
node (thick gray arc lines). By virtue of the sophistica-
tion of the present TSP solvers (Applegate et al.), it takes 
only a few seconds to obtain such star-like CWTs of this 
size. </p>

<p>Characteristics of CWTs Clarified by an Artificial Data Set 
To help understand how the CWT representation 
works, we show an artificially created example that 
sheds light on the characteristics of CWTs. Figure 6a 
is a data set containing 15 trees, and Figure 6b,c are 
the produced CWT representations based on the 50% </p>



<p>IWASAKI AND TAKAGI-CENTROID WHEEL TREE REPRESENTATION OF PHYLOGENIES </p>



<p>FIGURE 4. CWT for 264 trees based on single orthologs conserved over 21 fungal species. a) CWT based on the 60% consensus tree. The 
values at the wheel nodes include the estimated values for trees that do not contain all splits adjacent to them (default option). For each wheel 
node, the strict values excluding them and the average distances are shown in the dotted rectangles on the left and right sides, respectively. 
For the branch lengths, those stored in the original database (Marthey et al. 2008) are directly incorporated in their original units. b) Consensus 
phylogenetic network with a threshold of 0.2 (Holland and Moulton 2003). The scientific names of the species are as follows: majority-rule consensus tree showing support values 
and average distances, respectively. The strict option 
does not change the support values because there is no 
nontrivial split exceeding the 50% threshold (Fig. 6d) 
and the consensus tree contains trivial splits only. Fig-
ure 6e shows the sums of the distances between each 
split pair, which are used for the TSP calculation for the 
circular ordering determination. 
Two notable characteristics of CWT are demonstrated 
with this example. First, though the most frequent split 
is {c,e | a,b,d} (Fig. 6d), the distance between c and e is 
not the smallest (Fig. 6e). In other words, they are given </p>

<p>the highest priority if we construct a consensus tree by 
adopting highly supported splits in a greedy manner 
(Greedy consensus tree, Fig. 6f) but not if we build the 
CWT. This is because the CWT considers more informa-
tion than the existences of splits, that is, it also considers 
the distances between them. In this example, though 
the split {a,b | c,d,e} appears only once, the splits a 
and b are always within a distance of 1 in all trees and 
thus the cost for making them successively becomes 
small. Such differences can be made clear by visualiz-
ing and comparing the support values and the average 
distances (Fig. 6b,c; we recommend trying these options, </p>

<p>590 </p>

<p>SYSTEMATIC BIOLOGY </p>

<p>VOL. 59 </p>

<p>FIGURE 5. Taxonomic groups as successive branches around wheel nodes. a) CWT based on the 80% consensus tree for the same data set as 
in Figure 4. This is the color visualization, which uses colors instead of numbers to show values around the wheel nodes, to avoid a cluttered 
appearance. Thick gray arc lines indicate taxonomic groups that appear as successive splits around the wheel nodes. The support values include 
the estimated values for trees that do not contain all splits adjacent to the wheel nodes (default option). b) A star-like CWT based on the 100% 
consensus tree. The 21 species line up in the optimal order based on the cost function and the TSP solution. Many taxonomic groups constitute 
successive branches around the wheel node (gray arcs). </p>

<p>especially if weak support values are displayed). Though 
the support for the 3-furcation {c | e | a,b,d} is over twice 
as ones of {a | d | b,c,e} and {b | d | a,c,e}, the distances 
between c and e, a and d, and b and d are the same. 
<rs id="software-3" type="software">Java SE</rs><rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">5.0</rs><rs type="software">Phyutility</rs><rs type="software">Apache XML Graphics</rs><rs type="software">Args4j</rs></p>

<p>APPENDIX 
Definitions 
Let T 1 , . . . , T N be N input phylogenetic trees and 
w 1 , . . . , w N be their weights. Each phylogenetic tree is 
defined by T i = (V i , E i ), where V i is the set of all exter-
nal and internal nodes and E i is the set of all branches 
(edges). Hereafter, all trees are assumed to have the 
same set of taxa X = {x 1 , . . . , x M } on the external nodes. 
Any branch e on a tree T = (V, E) splits the taxa 
set X into two groups. We call such a bipartition sys-
tem Split(e, T). Let SplitSet(T) = {Split(e, T)|e ∈ E} and </p>

<p>Freq(s) be the weighted frequency of the trees that con-
tain the split s in T 1 , . . . , T N , i.e., Freq(s) = </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 δ i w i 
where δ i = 1 if s ∈ SplitSet(T i ) and δ i = 0 otherwise. 
AdjBranches(v, T) is the set of branches directly at-
tached to node v on T, and MultiFurcatingNodes(T) = 
{v ∈ V||AdjBranches(v, T)| 4}. If e ∈ AdjBranches(v, T), 
Descendants(e, v, T) is the subset of X that can be tra-
versed from the node adjacent to e that is not v, without 
crossing e. Let ExtBranch(x, T) be an external branch on 
T attached to the taxon x. 
For X sub ⊆ X and {x a , x b } ⊆ X sub , we define Dist(x a , x b , 
X sub , T) as follows. First, recursively remove any exter-
nal branch e from T if e / 
∈ {ExtBranch(x, T)|x ∈ X sub }. 
Second, recursively remove any internal node v if 
|AdjBranches(v, T)| = 2 by replacing AdjBranches(v, T) 
with one internal branch to keep the tree T connected. 
Then Dist(x a , x b , X sub , T) is the minimum number of 
edges on the converted tree T that separate ExtBranch 
(x a , T ) and ExtBranch(x b , T ). Note that ExtBranch(x a , T ) 
and ExtBranch(x b , T ) themselves are not counted 
(i.e., if they are adjacent each other, then Dist(x a , x b , 
X sub , T) = 0). </p>

<p>Pseudocode for Obtaining CWTs </p>

<p>Given T 1 , . . . , T N , w 1 , . . . , w N , and a threshold value 
γ for building the consensus tree, the following pseu-
docode produces a CWT. Note that the function c is 
symmetric. i.e., c(e p , e q ) ≡ c(e q , e p ). </p>

<p>Construct the consensus tree T C = (V C , E C ), where </p>

<p>SplitSet(T C ) = s|Freq(s) γ </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>w i . </p>

<p>For each v ∈ MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) { 
{e 1 , e 2 , . . . , e k } = AdjBranches(v, T C ) 
For each {p, q} ⊂ {1, 2, . . . , k} { 
Set c(e p , e q ) = 0 
For each T i ∈ T 1 , . . . , T N { 
For each taxa set X sub = {x 1 , x 2 , . . . , x k } that 
∀ 1 t k x t ∈ Descendants(e t , v, T c ) { </p>

<p>c(e p , e q ) = c(e p , e q ) + Dist(x p , x q , X sub , T i ) • w i / </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>| </p>

<p>Descendants(e t , v, T c )| 
} 
} 
} 
Find the TSP cycle (e f (1) e f (2) • • • e f (k) ) for AdjBranches 
(v, T C ), which minimizes </p>

<p>k−1 </p>

<p>t=1 c(e f (t) , e f (t+1) )+c(e f (k) , e f (1) ) 
} 
Lay out T C by following the TSP-cycle orderings for the 
branches around MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ). </p>

<p>Consensus Tree is the Centroid Representation 
It can be shown that the consensus tree is in fact the 
centroid representation of all candidate trees regarding 
the loss function of "split incongruity", which quan-
tifies the degree of disagreement between split sets of 
two trees. More precisely, given a tree representation </p>



<p>IWASAKI AND TAKAGI-CENTROID WHEEL TREE REPRESENTATION OF PHYLOGENIES </p>



<p>T = (V , E ) and a candidate tree T i = (V i , E i ), the "split 
incongruity loss function" is defined as </p>

<p>L split (T , T i ) = ξ • FP (T , T i ) + FN (T , T i ) , </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>FP (T , T i ) = |{s |s ∈ SplitSet (T ) ∧ s / 
∈ SplitSet (T i ) }| </p>

<p>FN (T , T i ) = |{s |s / 
∈ SplitSet (T ) ∧ s ∈ SplitSet (T i ) }| </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>This function becomes large if T contains splits that 
are absent from T i ("false positives") and vice versa 
("false negatives"). ξ designates the relative penalties 
for the two types of errors and usually ξ ≥ 1 because by 
convention false positives are more undesirable, given 
that they would exaggerate weak phylogenetic signals. 
To obtain the centroid representation, it is necessary to 
know the posterior probability P(T i |D) in addition to 
the loss function and, for example, both bootstrap and 
Bayesian methods have been developed to give approx-
imate values for P(T i |D) (Felsenstein 1985; Huelsenbeck 
et al. 2001). If we define w 1 , . . . , w N as w i ∝ P(T i |D), the 
"split incongruity centroid tree" T SplitCentroid is the tree 
that fulfills </p>

<p>SplitSet T SplitCentroid = s 
ξ 
1 + ξ </p>

<p>Freq (s) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 w i </p>

<p>(Berry and Gascuel 1996; Holder et al. 2008; Margush 
and McMorris 1981). Therefore, T SplitCentroid with the 
penalty parameter ξ is the consensus tree with the 
threshold ξ/(1 + ξ). In other words, the consensus tree 
with the threshold γ is T SplitCentroid with the penalty pa-
rameter γ/(1 − γ). Note that if 1 ≤ ξ then 1/2 ≤ γ &lt; 1. </p>

<p>CWT is the Centroid Representation in Double Metrics 
As was already described, the consensus tree T C = 
(V C , E C ) still possesses ambiguity with regard to branch 
orderings around the multifurcating nodes. Each lay-
out can be specified by a function f (v, t) : V C × N → N 
that is defined for v ∈ MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) and 
t = 1, . . . , k(v, T C ), where k(v, T C ) = |AdjBranches(v, T C )| 
and {e 1 , e 2 , . . . , e k(v,T C ) } = AdjBranches(v, T C ), and the 
cycle (e f (v,1) e f (v,2) . . . e f (v,k(v,T C )) ) specifies the circular 
ordering of AdjBranches(v, T C ). In the following para-
graph, we show that, among every possible layout of 
consensus trees, the CWT is the centroid representation 
regarding the loss function of "layout incongruity". 
Let Φ = (T C , f ) be a layout-specified tree representa-
tion of T C . Then, the "layout incongruity loss function" 
is defined as </p>

<p>L Layout (Φ, T i ) = </p>

<p>v∈MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) </p>

<p>l Layout (Φ, v, T i ), </p>

<p>where </p>

<p>l Layout (Φ, v, T i ) = </p>

<p>k(v,T C )−1 </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 
 
 </p>

<p>{X sub ={x 1, x 2, ...,x k(v,T C ) }|∀ 1 t k(v,T C ) x t ∈Descendants(e t ,v,T c )} </p>

<p>Dist(x f (v,t) , x f (v,t+1) , X sub , T i ) </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>|Descendants(e t , v, T c )| </p>

<p> </p>

<p> 
 
 
 </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>{X sub ={x 1, x 2, ...,x k(v,T C ) }|∀ 1 t k(v,T C ) x t ∈Descendants(e t ,v,T c )} </p>

<p>Dist(x f (v,k(v,T C )) , x f (v,1) , X sub , T i ) </p>

<p>k </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>|Descendants(e t , v, T c )| </p>

<p>. </p>

<p>Intuitively, for each split pair s a and s a that correspond 
to successive branches around each multifurcating node 
v in Φ, l Layout sums the distances on the tree T i between 
the expected positions of the corresponding branches on 
the assumption of the topology T C . Then, L Layout sums it 
for all wheel nodes to quantify how well Φ represents T i . 
Then the "layout incongruity centroid tree" Φ LayoutCentroid 
is the tree representation that minimizes the expected 
L Layout for all T 1 , . . . , T N : </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>L Layout (Φ, T i ) P (T i |D ) </p>

<p>∝ </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>v∈MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) </p>

<p>l Layout (Φ, T i , v) </p>

<p> </p>

<p> w i </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>v∈MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) </p>

<p>N </p>

<p>i=1 </p>

<p>l Layout (Φ, T i , v) • w i </p>

<p>= </p>

<p>v∈MultiFurcatingNodes(T C ) </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>k(v,T C )−1 </p>

<p>t=1 </p>

<p>c(e f (v,t) , e f (v,t+1) ) </p>

<p>+ c(e f (v,(v,T C )) , e f (v,1) ) </p>

<p> </p>

<p> </p>

<p>where c is the traveling cost calculated in the pseu-
docode. The final term is a minimum if we choose f 
to minimize the term in the bracket for each multifur-
cating node v, because they are independent of each 
other. Such an f is exactly the TSP tour obtained in the 
pseudocode; therefore, CWT is Φ LayoutCentroid and the 
most balanced according to the two measures of split 
incongruity and layout incongruity. </p>

</text></tei>