<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2890158" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-06-24T04:40+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>The genus Marasmius was considered a rather homogene-
ous group until the end of the last century (e.g. Antonín &amp; 
Noordeloos 1993). However, Moncalvo et al. (2002) showed 
that it is polyphyletic and its members belong to a number of 
distinct clades (/omphalotaceae, /physalacriaceae, /maras-
miaceae). According to other studies (Wilson &amp; Desjardin 2005, 
Matheny et al. 2006), only the sections Marasmius, Hygrome 
trici, Globulares and Sicci belong to Marasmius s.str. (family 
Marasmiaceae), whereas species of the sections Globulares 
and Sicci belong to one section called Globulares. Moreover, 
species of this section forming a hymeniform pileipellis of 
smooth (Globulares) or broom cells (Sicci) do not even belong 
to separate subsections, but are intermixed (Desjardin pers. 
comm.). </p>

<p>In this paper, South Korean species of Globulares with smooth 
pileipellis cells and no setae (not mixed with broom cells of the 
Siccus-type and well-developed setae = former sect. Sicci, ser. 
Spinulosi) are studied as part of a project on the genus Maras 
mius and related taxa in the Republic of Korea. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHODS </p>

<p>Macroscopic and microscopic studies </p>

<p>Macroscopic descriptions of collected specimens are based 
on fresh basidiocarps and made by the first and the second 
author. Microscopic features are described from dried material 
mounted in H 2 O, KOH, Melzer's reagent and Congo Red using 
an Olympus BX-50 light microscope with a magnification of 
×1 000. For basidiospores, the factors E (quotient of length and 
width in any one spore) and Q (mean of E-values) are used. 
Authors of fungal names are cited according to the International 
Plant Names Index Authors website (http://www.ipni.org/ipni/au-
thorsearchpage.do). Colour abbreviations follow Kornerup &amp; 
Wanscher (1983) and herbarium abbreviations are according to 
Holmgren &amp; Holmgren (1998). For the list of studied specimens, 
including GenBank numbers, see Table 1. </p>

<p>DNA extraction, PCR amplification and sequencing </p>

<p>DNA extraction was undertaken as described previously by Lee 
&amp; Taylor (1990). Genomic DNA was extracted using a small 
piece (3 -4 mm 
3 ) of the basidiocarp. </p>

<p>PCR primers LR0R (5' ACC CGC TGA ACT TAA GC 3') and 
LR7 (5' TAC TAC CAC CAA GAT CT 3') were used for amplifi-
cation of the LSU (the nuclear large ribosomal subunit) region 
of rDNA (Moncalvo et al. 2002). PCR cycling started with 3 min 
at 94 °C, denaturation for 30 s at 94 °C, annealing for 45 s at 
45 °C, and extension for 90 s at 72 °C. Thirty-five cycles were 
run with the first denaturation and last extension times. </p>

<p>PCR amplification of rDNA ITS (the internal transcribed spacer) 
region was performed according to the modified method of 
Gardes &amp; Bruns (1993). The forward primer ITS1-F (5' CTT 
GGT CAT TTA GAG GAA GTA A 3') and reverse primer ITS4-B 
(5' CAG GAG ACT TGT ACA CGG TCC AG 3') were used for 
selective amplification of the complete ITS region of rDNA. 
Temperature cycling was performed with denaturation for 30 s 
at 94 °C, annealing for 30 s at 56 °C, and extension for 1 min at 
72 °C. Thirty-five cycles were run with the first denaturation and 
last extension times extended to 2 and 5 min, respectively. </p>

<p>Purified DNAs were directly sequenced on an ABI Prism TM 
377 DNA automatic DNA Sequencer (Applied Biosystems, 
Foster City, CA, USA) using a BigDye™ cycle sequencing 
kit, v3.1 (Applied Biosystems). Primers were identical with 
those in ITS whereas LR0R, LR7 and the internal primer LR3 
(5' CCG TGT TTC AAG ACG GG 3') were used for amplification 
in LSU, respectively. </p>

<p>Sequence alignment and phylogenetic analysis </p>

<p>Sequences were edited with the <rs id="software-2" type="software">DNASTAR</rs> software, <rs corresp="#software-2" type="version-number">v5.0.5</rs> 
(DNAstar, Madison, WI, USA). Alignment of the sequences 
was performed using <rs id="software-3" type="software">CLUSTAL_X</rs> (Thompson et al. <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-date">1997</rs>). 
Phylogenetic trees were obtained from the data using Bayesian 
modelling (MCMC). MCMC analysis was performed using Mr-
Bayes, <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">v3.0b4</rs> (Ronquist &amp; Huelsenbeck 2003). This program 
performs a Bayesian inference of the phylogeny, using Metro-
polis-coupled Markov chain Monte Carlo analyses (Geyer 
1991). For a given dataset, the general time reversible (GTR) 
model was employed with gamma-distributed substitution 
rates. Markov chains were run for 10 
6 generations, saving a </p>

<p>Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2. 
Marasmius sect. Globulares </p>

<p>V. Antonín 
1 , R. Ryoo 
2 , H.-D. Shin </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>1 Moravian Museum, Department of Botany, Zelný trh 6, CZ-659 37 Brno, 
Czech Republic; corresponding author e-mail: vantonin@mzm.cz. 
2 Korea University, Division of Environmental Science and Ecological Engi-
neering, Seoul 136-701, Republic of Korea. </p>

<p>Abstract Seven species of Marasmius sect. Globulares with smooth pileipellis cells (sect. Globulares s. Singer) 
have been collected in the Republic of Korea (South Korea) to date, viz. M. aurantioferrugineus, M. brunneospermus, 
M. maximus, M. nivicola, M. purpureostriatus, M. wynneae and M. fusicystidiosus. Descriptions of their macro-and 
microscopic features with a discussion of similar taxa are given. Their taxonomic position was confirmed using DNA 
data. Marasmius fusicystidiosus is described as a new species. A key to aid in their identification is also provided. </p>

<p>Article info Received: 13 August 2009; Accepted: 1 February 2010; Published: 4 March 2010. </p>

<p>Key words </p>

<p>ITS 
LSU 
nomenclature 
taxonomy </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 24, 2010 </p>

<p>tree every 100th generation. Among these, the first 1 000 trees 
were discarded. MrBayes was used to compute a 50 % majority 
rule consensus of the remaining trees to obtain estimates of 
the posterior probabilities (PPs) of the groups. Sequences of 
Marasmius rotula and M. capillaris were selected as outgroup 
taxa for rooting purposes. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Key to the species of sect. Globulares with smooth 
pileipellis cells in the Republic of Korea </p>

<p>1. Pileus distinctly sulcate, striped, centre and striae violet 
brown, sulcae whitish; lamellae distant (L = c. 12); basidio-
spores large, 21-25 × 5.0-6.5 μm; pleurocystidia absent; 
caulocystidia absent . . . . . . . . . . 6. M. purpureostriatus 
1. Pileus sulcate or not, but never striate, colour different; 
lamellae closer (L &gt; 16); basidiospores distinctly smaller, 
less than 15 μm long; pleuro-and caulocystidia absent or 
present . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2 </p>

<p>2. Pleurocystidia present . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3 
2. Pleurocystidia absent . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4 </p>

<p>3. Stipe long and slender, up to 110 × 3 mm; basidiospores 
(8.0 -)8.5 -10 × 3.5 -4.0 μm, average = 8.9 × 3.7 μm; chei-
locystidia 12 -23 × 5.0 -12 μm; pleurocystidia fusoid, some-
times pedicellate; caulocystidia absent . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 3. M. fusicystidiosus 
3. Stipe shorter and more robust, 30-60 × 2.5-6 mm; basidio-
spores 6.0-8.0 × 3.0-4.0 μm, average = 7.4 × 3.4 μm; chei-
locystidia 21-42 × 7.0 -10(-14) μm; pleurocystidia fusoid, 
subcylindrical, sublageniform; caulocystidia present, numer-
ous . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 2. M. brunneospermus </p>

<p>4. Pileus orange-ferrugineous; basidiospores 11.5-15 × (4.0-) 
4.5 -6.0 μm . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1. M. aurantioferrugineus 
4. Pileus differently coloured, never orange-ferrugineous; basi-
diospores smaller, never over 10 μm long . . . . . . . . . . . 5 </p>

<p>5. Basidiocarps robust, macroscopically similar to M. oreades; 
basidiospores 7.0 -9.5(-10) × 4.5 -6.0 μm, average = 8.5 
× 5.1 μm; caulocystidia numerous, forming a compact layer 
of interwoven, cylindrical, narrowly clavate, subfusoid, nar-
rowly cylindrical, often irregular or branched, up to 10 μm 
wide cells . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 4. M. maximus 
5. Basidiocarps less robust, single or in clusters, never macro-
scopically reminding M. oreades; basidiospores 6.5-8.0 × 
3.7-5.0 μm, average = 7.2-7.3 × 3.6-4.1 μm; caulocystidia 
not forming a compact layer . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 6 </p>

<p>6. Pileus white-off, whitish to yellowish white or pale yellow with 
brownish or greyish tinge at centre, never violaceous tinged; 
lamellae distinctly anastomosed already when young, white, 
pale yellow, greyish cream or pale cream; basal tomentum 
forming a ± solid mycelial mat around stipe base . . . . . . . 
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 5. M. nivicola 
6. Pileus white or grey-ochraceous when young, then milky 
white, grey, or grey-violaceous; lamellae not intervenose 
or only when old, white to cream or grey, sometimes with 
violaceous tinge; basal tomentum never forming a ± solid 
mycelial mat around stipe base . . . . . . . . . 7. M. wynneae </p>

<p>1. Marasmius aurantioferrugineus Hongo, Mem. Fac. Lib. 
Arts Educ. Shiga Univ., Nat. Sci. 15: 74. 1965. -Fig. 1c, 2 </p>

<p>Pileus 30-70 mm broad, convex, then expanded, obtuse, with 
involute margin when young, dry, radially rugose, orange-fer-
rugineous. Lamellae subdistant, adnate to almost free. Stipe 
50-120 × 3-6 mm, cylindrical, with broadened base, straight, 
silky-fibrillose, twisted, pruinose at apex, solid, whitish. Context 
thick in centre, thin at margin, tough, white, with mild taste and 
indistinct smell (according to Hongo 1965). Basidiospores 11.5-
15 × (4.0-)4.5-6.0 μm, average = 13.2 × 4.7 μm, E = 2.3-3.3, 
Q = 2.7-2.9, fusoid, clavate, sublacrimoid, smooth, hyaline; 
slightly thick-walled spores present. Basidia 26-28 × 8.0-11 
μm, 4-spored, clavate. Basidioles up to 42 × 5.0-10 μm, cylindri-
cal, clavate or subfusoid. Cheilocystidia 15-30 × 6.0-11(-14) 
μm, clavate, fusoid, subcylindrical, (sub)vesiculose, irregular or 
regular, thin-walled. Pleurocystidia absent. Trama hyphae made 
up of cylindrical to (sub)inflated, ± thin-walled, hyaline, smooth 
or minutely incrusted, up to 15(-20) μm wide cells. Pileipellis a 
hymeniderm composed of cells 20-41 × (8.0-)10-22(-30) μm, 
clavate or pyriform, pedicellate and capitate or subvesiculose, 
regular, rarely irregular, thin-to slightly thick-walled, smooth, 
subhyaline to pale orange-brown in KOH. Stipitipellis a cutis of 
cylindrical, parallel, slightly thick-walled, smooth, up to 6.0 μm 
wide hyphae. Caulocystidia appressed to erect, (13-)22-45 
× 5.0-9.0 μm, cylindrical, (narrowly) clavate, (sub)fusoid, ob-
tuse, thin-to slightly thick-walled. Clamp connections present 
in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Pileipellis, hymenium and basidio-
spores non-dextrinoid (but thick-walled spores dextrinoid), caulo-
cystidia non-dextrinoid or dextrinoid, other tissues distinctly 
dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On fallen needles of Pinus densiflora and a coni-
ferous tree. </p>

<p>Species 
Locality 
Herbarium specimen 
GenBank acc. number </p>

<p>ITS 
LSU </p>

<p>M. aurantioferrugineus 
RK, Hongcheon, Bukbang-myeon 
BRNM 714752 
FJ904944 
FJ904962 
M. aurantioferrugineus 
RK, Pyeongchang, Bongpyung-myeon, Heungjeong-ri, Mt Heungjeong 
HCCN -GBDS 2861 
FJ904945 
FJ904963 
M. aurantioferrugineus 
RK, Hongcheon, Bukbang-myeon 
HCCN -3517 
FJ904946 
FJ904964 
M. brunneospermus 
RK, Seoul, Hongreung Arboretum 
BRNM 714568 
FJ904966 
FJ904948 
M. brunneospermus 
RK, Mt Sobaeksan National Park, Saebat valley 
BRNM 714569 
FJ904967 
FJ904949 
M. brunneospermus 
RK, Seoul, Hongreung Arboretum 
BRNM 714670 
FJ904968 
FJ904950 
M. brunneospermus 
RK, Seoul, Mt Achasan 
BRNM 714669 
FJ904965 
FJ904947 
M. brunneospermus 
J, Kanagawa, Yamato 
KPM-NC 0005011 (holotype) 
FJ904969 
FJ904951 
M. fusicystidiosus 
RK, Jeju, Jocheon-eup, Seonheul-ri 
BRNM 714567 
FJ917624 
FJ936144 
M. maximus 
RK, Jeju, Jeju City Park 
BRNM 714570 
FJ904976 
FJ904959 
M. maximus 
RK, Jeju, Udo-myeon 
BRNM 714571 
FJ904977 
FJ904958 
M. maximus 
RK, Seoul, Sangam World Cup Park 
BRNM 714671 
FJ904975 
FJ904957 
M. maximus 
RK, Seoul, Jungreung stream 
BRNM 714672 
FJ904974 
FJ904956 
M. nivicola 
RK, Mt Sobaeksan National Park, Darian river valley 
BRNM 714572 
FJ904970 
FJ904952 
M. nivicola 
RK, Mt Sobaeksan National Park, Darian river valley 
BRNM 714573 
FJ904971 
FJ904953 
M. nivicola 
RK, Chuncheon, Dongsan-myeon, Bongmyeong-ri 
BRNM 714574 
FJ904972 
FJ904954 
M. nivicola 
J, Kanagawa prefecture, Yamato-shi 
KPM-NC 0006038 (holotype) 
FJ904973 
FJ904955 
M. purpureostriatus 
RK, Jeju, Jocheon-eup, Seonheul-ri 
BRNM 714566 
FJ904978 
FJ904960 
M. wynneae 
RK, Mt Yongmun, Yongmun-myeon, Sinjum-ri 
HCCN -G86 
FJ904979 
FJ904961 </p>

<p>Table 1 List of specimens used for molecular studies. Abbreviations: RK = Republic of Korea, J = Japan. </p>



<p>V. Antonín et al.: Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2 </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Republic of KoRea, Pyeongchang, Bongpyung-my-
eon, Heungjeong-ri, Mt Heungjeong, 1 Sept. 1995, Y.H. Park, HCCN -GBDS 
2861; Hongcheon, Bukbang-myeon, Experimental forest of Kangwon National 
University, alt. c. 1080 m, 37°48'48.69"N, 127°51'04.14"E, 25 Aug. 1990, 
Y.S. Kim, HCCN 3517; Hongcheon, Bukbang-myeon, Experimental forest of 
Kangwon National University, alt. c. 1080 m, 37°48'48.69"N, 127°51'04.14"E, 
28 Aug. 2008, R. Ryoo KG 254, BRNM 714752. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius aurantioferrugineus is a very distinct 
species characterised by a large, orange-ferrugineous pileus, a 
rather long and wide stipe, large clavate, fusoid to sublacrimoid 
basidiospores, and the absence of pleurocystidia. </p>

<p>Among species with a similarly coloured pileus, M. heineman 
nianus, described from Africa, has larger cheilocystidia ((16-) 
22-61.5 × 6.2-12.5 μm) and well-developed pleurocystidia (An-
tonín 1998, 2007). Marasmius veigasii has lamellae and stipe 
concolorous with pileus, basidiospores c. 16 × 4 μm and absent </p>

<p>cystidia; M. pseudocollinus has a smaller, only 8-31 mm broad 
pileus, a smaller stipe (20-38 × 1.5-2.5(-4) mm), smaller ba-
sidiospores (6.5-7.5 × 3.3-3.5 μm) and absent cheilocystidia; 
M. silvicola has differently shaped and smaller basidiospores 
(4.5-8.3 × 2.5-4.2 μm; Desjardin et al. 2000 (5-)6-7 × 2-3.5 
μm) and present pleurocystidia (Singer 1976). </p>

<p>Marasmius aurantioferrugineus is only known from East Asia 
(China, Japan, and Republic of Korea) and the Russia Far East 
(Primorsky Territory; Bulakh &amp; Covorova 2000). </p>

<p>2. Marasmius brunneospermus Har.Takah., Mycoscience 
40, 6: 477. 1999. -Fig. 1b, 3 </p>

<p>Basidiocarps single. Pileus 20-50 mm broad, conical-hemi-
spherical when young, then broadly conical or convex with 
obtuse, then applanate to slightly depressed centre and invo-</p>

<p>Fig. 1 Photos of basidiocarps. a. Marasmius purpureostriatus; b. M. brunneospermus; c. M. aurantioferrugineus; d. M. maximus; e, f, g. M. nivicola. Photos 
by: a -b, d-g: V. Antonín; c. R. Ryoo. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>g </p>

<p>e </p>

<p>f </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 24, 2010 </p>

<p>lute, then inflexed to straight margin, hygrophanous, glabrous, 
smooth to slightly (pitted) rugulose, either yellowish white (be-
tween 3 -4A3) or light brown (slightly paler than 6C -D), then 
dark brown centre (7F7) and light brown (paler than 6C-D4) 
margin. Lamellae moderately close to distant, L = 22 -24, 
l = 2 -3(-4), emarginate and attached with a small tooth to 
almost free, slightly sinuate, yellowish white (3 -4A3), then 
brownish orange (± 5B3, paler than 6C5), with concolorous, 
uneven, finely pubescent edge. Stipe 30 -60 × 2.5 -6 mm, cy-
lindrical, subcylindrical to clavate towards base (up to 10 mm), 
entirely finely tomentose, then ± glabrescent, tough but fragile, 
sometimes twisted, either yellowish white (3 -4A3) and then 
concolorous with lamellae (brownish orange) and pale ochra-
ceous towards base, or pale whitish brownish at apex and then 
greyish brownish (6D4-5); basal tomentum white or whitish and 
sometimes forming a mycelial math around stipe base. Context 
whitish to pale cream in pileus, concolorous with surface under 
pileipellis, hollow in stipe, with faintly fungoid smell and mild 
taste. Basidiospores 6.0 -8.0 × 3.0 -4.0 μm, average = 7.4 × 
3.4 μm, E = (1.5 -)1.8 -2.4, Q = (1.9 -)2.1-2.2, ellipsoid, el-
lipsoid-fusoid or (sub)cylindrical, sometimes subphaseoliform, 
smooth, hyaline, both thin-and thick-walled. Basidia 28-32 × 
6.5-7.0 μm, 4-spored, clavate. Basidioles 17-35 × 3.0-8.0 
μm, cylindrical, clavate or subfusoid. Cheilocystidia 21-42 × 
7.0-10(-14) μm, variable in form, clavate, fusoid, subcylindrical, 
sublageniform, irregular, rostrate or branched, thin-to ± slightly 
thick-walled. Pleurocystidia (28 -)46 -75 × (6.0 -)9.0 -15 μm, 
fusoid, subcylindrical, sublageniform, sometimes rostrate or 
pimpled, with refractive contents, thin-walled. Trama hyphae 
cylindrical or subinflated, thin-to slightly thick-walled, hyaline, 
up to 15 μm wide. Pileipellis a hymeniderm composed of cells 
18-41 × 12 -26 μm, clavate or (sub)vesiculose, sometimes 
pedicellate, thin-to slightly thick-walled, smooth, with pale 
greyish brownish walls in KOH. Pileocystidia scattered, 26-65 
× 8.0-15 μm, (sub)cylindrical or (broadly) fusoid, often rostrate, 
rostrum sometimes irregular, sometimes with one septum, 
obtuse, thin-walled, irregular. Stipitipellis a cutis of cylindrical, </p>

<p>parallel, slightly thick-walled, smooth or minutely incrusted, up 
to 6.0 μm wide hyphae; medulla hyphae minutely incrusted, 
up to 20 μm wide. Caulocystidia numerous, 13-55 × 6.0-15 
μm, variable in shape, fusoid, clavate, cylindrical, lageniform, 
sometimes irregular or rostrate, thin-to slightly thick-walled. 
Clamp connections present in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Basidiospores non-dextrinoid, pilei-
pellis and caulocystidia non-dextrinoid to slightly dextrinoid, pileo-
cystidia and other tissues distinctly dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On detritus of Pinus densiflora, Acer sp., and Mag 
nolia sp. in an arboretum or a park, detritus of Larix sp. in a 
mixed forest with Pinus multiflora, and Corylus sp. on calcare-
ous soil along a rivulet. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Republic of KoRea, Seoul, Hongreung Arboretum, 
alt. c. 130 m, 37°35'40"N, 127°02'44"E, 18 July 2007, V. Antonín 07.80 
&amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 714568; Seoul, Hongreung Arboretum, alt. c. 175 m, 
37°35'44"N, 127°02'39.44"E, 24 July 2008, R. Ryoo KG 237, BRNM 714670; 
Danyang, Sobaeksan National Park, Saebat valley, 36°59'20"N, 128°27'40"E, 
18 July 2007, J.G. Han, V. Antonín 07.48, BRNM 714569; Hongcheon, city 
park, alt. c. 200 m, 37°40'55"N, 127°52'17"E, 16 July 2009, H.D. Shin, V. 
Antonín 09.122, BRNM 714895; Suwon, the former campus of the Seoul 
National University, alt. c. 65 m, 37°16'07"N, 126°59'15"E, 21 July 2009, 
H.D. Shin, V. Antonín 09.148, BRNM 718805. -Japan, Kanagawa, Yamato, 
27 May 1998, H. Takahashi, holotype KPM-NC 0005011. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius brunneospermus is characterised by 
having moderately large basidiocarps with a pale coloured 
pileus, rather small basidiospores, well-developed cheilo-and 
pleurocystidia and a brown spore print. Our collections agree 
well with Takahashi's description and photos (Takahashi 1999) 
with the exceptions of the presence of pileocystidia and spore 
print colour. Pileocystidia are, however, scattered and indistinct 
in all specimens and may represent aberrant forms of pileipellis 
cells. Takahashi (1999) described and photographed a spore 
print as brown, but our collections have pale yellow-orange 
coloured basidiospores. Because our fungi agree with the </p>

<p>Fig. 2 Marasmius aurantioferrugineus. a. Pileipellis cells; b. cheilocystidia; 
c. basidiospores; d. caulocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Fig. 3 Marasmius brunneospermus. a. Pileipellis cells; b. basidiospores; 
c. cheilocystidia; d. pleurocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b 
d </p>

<p>a </p>



<p>V. Antonín et al.: Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2 </p>

<p>type specimen not only macro-and microscopically but also 
using molecular methods, the spore print colour described by 
Takahashi may be caused under the influence of growing condi-
tions of the fungi. The collection from the Hongreung Arboretum 
(KG 237) differs in having ellipsoid or fusoid-ellipsoid (never 
cylindrical or phaseoliform) basidiospores of the same size but 
different E (1.5 -2.1) and Q (1.9) ratio. However, this character 
falls within the variability of M. brunneospermus. </p>

<p>The presence of a brown spore print represents a unique char-
acter in Marasmius. Among other white-spored species with 
well-developed pleurocystidia and vestured stipe, M. silvicola, 
known from Argentina and Java, Indonesia, has a dark reddish 
orangish brown pileus when moist fading to brownish orange or 
brownish yellow and a more robust stipe, 80 -140 × 5 -10 μm 
(Desjardin et al. 2000); M. muramwyanensis, from Africa, has 
a membranaceous, centrally brown-beige and marginally beige 
or greyish orange pileus and smaller basidiospores, 5.0-6.2 
× 2.9 -3.7 μm (Antonín 2007). Marasmius lilacinus, from the 
USA, differs by having a lilaceous tinged pileus and different 
basidiospores (6.5 -8 × 4 -5 μm), while M. nigrodiscus, also 
from the USA, by differently shaped cheilocystidia, larger pleu-
rocystidia (45 -120 × 7-18 mm), and filamentous caulocystidia 
(Halling 1983). </p>

<p>Marasmius brunneospermus has been found only in East Asia 
(Japan, Takahashi 1999; Republic of Korea) to date. </p>

<p>3. Marasmius fusicystidiosus Antonín, R. Ryoo &amp; H.D. Shin, 
sp. nov. -MycoBank MB515578; Fig. 4 </p>

<p>Pileo 30-50 mm lato, plano cum centro leviter depresso, leviter sulcato, 
rubro-ochraceo-brunneo. Lamellis luteo-albidis vel aurantiaco-albidis, acie 
concolore. Stipite usque 110 × 3 mm, cylindraceo, basim bulboso-clavato, 
apice luteo-albido, ad basim pallide brunneo. Basidiosporis (8.0 -) 8.5 -10 × 
3.5 -4.0 μm, fusiformibus, subcylindraceis, hyalinis. Cheilocystidiis 12 -23 
× 5.0 -12 μm, clavatis, fusiformibus, subcylindraceis, saepe irregularibus, 
lobatis vel subcoralloideis, tenuitunicatis. Pleurocystidiis 43-77 × 6.0-13 μm, 
fusiformibus, iterum pedicellatis, saepe rostratis, tenuitunicatis. Pileipellis hy-
meniformis, e cellulis clavatis vel pyriformibus, 20-29 × 12-18 μm, laevibus. 
Pileocystidiis et caulocystidiis absentibus. Hyphis dextrinoideis, fibulatis. </p>

<p>Holotypus. Republic of Korea, insula Jeju, Jocheon-eup, Seonheul-ri, 5. VII. 
2008, V. Antonín 08.58 (holotypus in herbario BRNM 714567 asservatur). </p>

<p>Basidiocarps single. Pileus 30 -50 mm broad, applanate with 
plane to slightly depressed centre and straight margin, hygro-
phanous, translucently striate, smooth at centre, slightly sul-
cate up to 2/3, glabrous, lustrous when moist and then very </p>

<p>slightly sticky, reddish ochre-brown (6-7C5) at centre, slightly 
paler towards margin. Lamellae moderately close, L = c. 30, 
l = 2-3, emarginate and attached with tooth, slightly nodulose 
at base, yellowish white to orange-white (± 4-5A2) with con-
colorous, ± smooth edge. Stipe up to 110 × 3 mm, cylindrical, 
slightly broadened at apex, bulbose-clavate (8 mm) at base, 
non-insititious, fistulose, slightly striate at apex (descending 
lamellae teeth), slightly fibrillose otherwise, slightly fibrillose-
tomentose (apex), concolorous with lamellae at apex, light 
brown (± 6D5) otherwise; with rich whitish basal tomentum. 
Context concolorous with pileus surface (in pileus) and stipe 
(in stipe) surface colour, hollow in stipe, without any special 
smell. Basidiospores (8.0-)8.5-10 × 3.5-4.0 μm, average = 
8.9 × 3.7 μm, E = 2.1-2.8, Q = 2.4, fusoid, navicular, sub-
cylindrical, smooth, thin-walled, hyaline; slightly thick-walled 
spores also present. Basidia 25-28 × 6.5-7.5 μm, 4-spored, 
clavate. Basidioles 15-30 × 3.0-7.0 μm, cylindrical, clavate 
or subfusoid. Cheilocystidia 12-23 × 5.0-12 μm, variable in 
shape, clavate, fusoid, subcylindrical, often irregular, lobate 
to subcoralloid, thin-walled. Pleurocystidia 43 -77 × 6.0 -13 
μm, fusoid, sometimes pedicellate, often pimpled, thin-walled, 
refractive. Trama hyphae formed by cylindrical or fusoid, thin-
to slightly thick-walled, often minutely incrusted, hyaline, up to 
25 μm wide cells. Pileipellis a hymeniderm composed of cells 
20-29 × 12-18 μm, clavate or pyriform, thin-to slightly thick-
walled, smooth, pale yellowish in KOH. Stipitipellis a cutis of 
cylindrical, parallel, slightly thick-walled, smooth, up to 8.0 μm 
wide hyphae. Caulocystidia absent; scattered (sub)erect, ± 
cylindrical, obtuse, thin-walled terminal cells present. Clamp 
connections present in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Basidiospores and hymenium non-
dextrinoid, pileipellis non-dextrinoid or slightly dextrinoid, and 
caulocystidioid cells and trama dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On detritus in a mixed forest (Pinus densiflora, 
Quercus spp. and Cryptomeria sp.). </p>

<p>Specimen examined. Republic of KoRea, Jeju, Jocheon-eup, Seonheul-ri, 
alt. c. 95 m, 33°31'01"N, 126°42'27"E, 5 July 2008, V. Antonín 08.58, holotype 
BRNM 714567. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius fusicystidiosus is a distinct species 
macroscopically similar to M. brunneospermus. It differs mainly 
by the size and shape of basidiospores and size of cheilo-
cystidia. </p>

<p>Among other species with well-developed pleurocystidia, 
Marasmius calvus, from Sri Lanka, has a centrally pale fawn 
and marginally fuscous brown pileus, narrower basidiospores 
(8 -10.5 × 2.7-3.5 μm) and cheilocystidia similar to pleuro-
cystidia (Pegler 1986, Desjardin et al. 2000); M. cystidiosus, 
known from the USA, has cheilocystidia that are of a different 
shape, similar to the pleurocystidia (Gilliam 1976, Halling 1983). 
Marasmius silvicola, known from several countries in South 
America and from Java, Indonesia, differs by smaller basidio-
spores ((5-)6-7 × 2-3.5 μm; Singer 1976: 4.5-8.3 × 2.5-4.2 
μm) and the presence of caulocystidia (Desjardin et al. 2000); 
M. goossensiae, from tropical Africa, differs by a cream col-
oured pileus with fuligineous or ochraceous brown centre 
and smaller basidiospores, 6.2-7.9(-9.2) × 3.5-4.2 μm; and 
M. muramwyanensis, also from tropical Africa, differs by smaller 
basidiospores (5.0-6.2 × 2.9-3.7 μm), differently shaped pleu-
rocystidia and the presence of caulocystidia (Antonín 2007). 
Marasmius phlebodiscus, described from Papua New Guinea, 
has a wrinkled pileus and smaller basidiospores, 5-6.5 × 3-3.5 
μm (Desjardin &amp; Horak 1997), and M. riparius, from Argentina, 
has a context with a slight unpleasant smell of rotten cabbage, 
broader basidiospores (8.2 -10 × 4.8 -5.5 μm) and smaller 
pleurocystidia (40-44 × 8-9 μm), that are similarly shaped to 
cheilocystidia (Singer 1976). </p>

<p>Fig. 4 Marasmius fusicystidiosus. a. Pileipellis cells; b. basidiospores; 
c. cheilocystidia; d. pleurocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 24, 2010 </p>

<p>4. Marasmius maximus Hongo, Mem. Fac. Lib. Arts Educ. 
Shiga Univ., Nat. Sci. 12: 39. 1962. -Fig. 1d, 5 </p>

<p>Basidiocarps in groups. Pileus 25 -65 mm broad, convex-
conical with broad obtuse umbo and inflexed margin, then 
plano-convex to applanate with slightly undulate margin and 
low obtuse central umbo, with finally ± straight margin, cen-
tre smooth or slightly rugulose, otherwise radially sulcate, 
especially in older specimens, glabrous, crenulate at margin, 
hygrophanous, slightly translucently striate at margin when 
young, ochre-brown (not in K-W) at centre, otherwise pale 
brownish to pale ochraceous. Lamellae distant, L = 14 -25, 
l = 2-3, emarginate and attached with very small tooth to ± 
free, broad, rather thick, intervenose when old, whitish to pale 
cream-yellow (3-4A2) with concolorous, ± smooth edge. Stipe 
52-85 × 2 -6 mm, cylindrical to slightly broadened at base, 
non-insititious, tough-elastic, tomentose with tomentum later 
cracking and forming ± large tomentose scales, concolorous 
with lamellae or slightly darker at apex, pale brown at base in 
young specimens, then brown to dark brown (7E -F7) towards 
base in older basidiocarps. Context whitish, under surface 
with pileipellis colour, with a pleasant fungoid smell and mild 
taste. Basidiospores 7.0 -10.25 × 4.5 -6.0 μm, average = 8.7 
× 5.2 μm, E = 1.4 -2.0, Q = 1.6 -1.8, (broadly) ellipsoid-fusoid, 
fusoid, smooth, hyaline. Basidia 35-48 × 7.0-9.5 μm, 4-spored, 
clavate. Basidioles 23-45 × 3.0-9.0 μm, cylindrical, clavate or 
subfusoid. Cheilocystidia (15-)20-30(-40) × 4.0-11 μm, vari-
able in shape, clavate, fusoid, subcylindrical, mostly irregular, 
lobate, branched to coralloid, thin-walled. Pleurocystidia absent. 
Trama hyphae consisting of cylindrical, thin-to slightly thick-
walled, hyaline, up to 10 μm wide cells. Pileipellis a hymeniderm 
composed of cells 17-30(-40) × (7.5 -)10 -18 μm, clavate 
or pyriform, regular, irregular or with scattered projection(s), 
thin-to slightly thick-walled, smooth, hyaline to pale yellowish 
in KOH; subpileipellis hyphae often incrusted. Stipitipellis a 
cutis of cylindrical, parallel, slightly thick-walled, smooth, up to 
6.0(-8.0) μm wide hyphae. Caulocystidia numerous, forming 
a compact layer, interwoven, 20 -55 × 6.0 -11 μm, cylindrical, </p>

<p>narrowly clavate, subfusoid, often irregular or branched, thin-to 
less frequently slightly thick-walled. Clamp connections present 
in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Pileipellis, hymenium and basidio-
spores non-dextrinoid, caulocystidia non-dextrinoid or dextri-
noid, other tissues distinctly dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On soil in grass of a meadow and a wayside, on 
leaves under Forsythia koreana, and on needles of Pinus den 
siflora. </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Republic of KoRea, Jeju, alt. c. 20 m, 33°30'46"N, 
126°30'53"E, 4 July 2008, V. Antonín 08.54 &amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 714570; 
Jeju, Udo-myeon, alt. c. 90 m, 33°29'34"N, 126°30'53"E, 4 July 2008, V. An 
tonín 08.56 &amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 714571; Seoul, Bukhansan National Park, 
Jungreung stream, alt. c. 532 m, 37°37'13.86"N, 126°59'38.65"E, 13 July 
2008, R. Ryoo KG 224, BRNM 714672; Seoul, Sangam World Cup Park, alt. 
c. 95 m, 37°34'15.25"N, 126°53'48.84"E, 14 July 2008, R. Ryoo KG 229, 
BRNM 714671; Seoul, Korean Forest Research Institute, Hongreung Arbore-
tum, alt. c. 130 m, 37°35'40"N, 127°02'44"E, 10 July 2009, V. Antonín 09.65 &amp; 
R. Ryoo, BRNM 714896; Seoul, Korean Forest Research Institute, Hon-
greung Arboretum, alt. c. 130 m, 37°35'40"N, 127°02'44"E, 13 July 2009, 
V. Antonín 09.91 &amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 714897; Hongcheon, city park, alt. c. 200 m, 
37°40'55"N, 127°52'17"E, 16 July 2009, H.D. Shin, V. Antonín 09.121, 
BRNM 714898; Seoul, Korea University, Science Campus, alt. c. 75 m, 
37°35'09"N, 127°01'33"E, 18 July 2009, V. Antonín 09.124 &amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 
718781; Chiaksan National Park, Wonju, between N.P. Office and Guryongsa, 
alt. 310 -360 m, 37°24'17"N, 128°03'00"E, 19 July 2009, V. Antonín 09.130, 
H.D. Shin &amp; R. Ryoo, BRNM 718787. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius maximus is a distinct species macro-
scopically similar to M. oreades. It differs by the character 
of the stipe vesture, size of basidiospores and presence of 
cheilocystidia. </p>

<p>Another species with developed cheilocystidia and a distinct 
stipe vesture, M. silvicola, known from Argentina and Java, 
Indonesia, has a dark reddish orangish brown pileus when 
moist, fading to brownish orange or brownish yellow, and 
smaller basidiospores, (5-)6-7 × 2-3.5 μm (Desjardin et al. 
2000; 4.5-8.3 × 2.5-4.2 μm according to Singer 1976). Mar 
asmius heinemannianus, described from Africa and having 
very similar basidiocarps, has a reddish brown pileus, larger 
basidiospores (10.8-14.5 × (4.2-)4.6-6.0(-6.6) μm), larger 
cheilocystidia ((16-)22-61.5 × 6.2-12.5 μm) and well-devel-
oped pleurocystidia (Antonín 1998, 2007). Among other African 
species, M. arborescens has a smaller, 10-20(-28) mm broad, 
white to whitish pileus, larger basidiospores ((6.9-)8-11.5 × 
3.0-4.0(-4.2) μm) and grows in dense fascicles. Marasmius 
lacteoides differs by a smaller, 8-30 mm broad, whitish yellow-
ish pileus and smaller basidiospores (6.3-8.5(-10) × 3.5-4.5 
mm); M. muramwyanensis by a membranaceous pileus, only 
up to 45 mm broad, smaller basidiospores (5.0-6.2 × 2.9-3.7 
μm) and the presence of well-developed pleurocystidia (An-
tonín 2007). </p>

<p>Marasmius maximus is only known from East Asia (Japan, 
Hongo 1962; Republic of Korea). </p>

<p>5. Marasmius nivicola Har.Takah., Mycoscience 41: 541. 
2000. -Fig. 1e-g, 6 </p>

<p>Basidiocarps single or in groups. Pileus 5-40 mm broad, coni-
cal-convex to convex with obtuse centre or with indistinct umbo 
with small umbilicus when young, soon becoming plane, then 
umbilicate when old, margin involute, then ± straight and uplifted 
when old, except for centre ± radially rugulose, then entirely 
rugulose when old, weakly striate at margin, hygrophanous, 
translucently striate, more distinct when old, glabrous, white-off, 
whitish to yellowish white or pale yellow (2-3A3, 4A-B3) with 
brownish or whitish greyish tinge at centre when old. Lamellae 
± distant to moderately close, L = (10-)16-27, l = 2-3, adnate 
or slightly emarginate with small tooth, later without it, up to 1 
mm wide, distinctly anastomosed already when young, always </p>

<p>Fig. 5 Marasmius maximus. a. Pileipellis cells; b. cheilocystidia; c. basidio-
spores. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>a </p>



<p>V. Antonín et al.: Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2 </p>

<p>irregular to branched with distinct tuberculate anastomoses 
when old, white, pale yellow (3 -4A3), greyish cream to pale 
cream, with concolorous, apparently smooth to finely pubescent 
edge. Stipe (12 -)20 -70 × 1-2(-4) mm, cylindrical, laterally 
compressed especially when old, slightly tapering towards 
base, slightly tomentose-pubescent or furfuraceous especially 
in upper half, white to cream (concolorous with lamellae) at 
apex, through brownish orange (6C7) becoming brownish grey 
(6C2), orange-brown or reddish brown (8D-E8) towards base; 
basal tomentum rich, hairy or tomentose and forming a ± solid 
mycelial mat around stipe base, whitish to pale ochraceous. 
Context whitish, in cortex with colour of surface, hollow in stipe, 
with fungoid smell and bitterish taste. Basidiospores 6.5-8.0 × 
3.7-5.0 μm, average = 7.2 × 3.6 μm, E = 1.6-2.3, Q = 1.7-2.0, 
ellipsoid, ellipsoid-fusoid, sublacrimoid or (sub)amygdaloid, 
smooth, hyaline, thin-walled. Basidia 24 -29 × 6.5 -8.5 μm, 4-
spored, clavate. Basidioles 13 -33 × 3.0 -9.0 μm, cylindrical, 
clavate or subfusoid. Cheilocystidia (12-)16-31 × (5.0-)6.0-11 
μm, clavate, clavate-fusoid, subcylindrical, sometimes irregular 
or branched, thin-walled. Pleurocystidia absent. Trama hyphae 
cylindrical or subinflated, thin-to slightly thick-walled, minutely 
incrusted, hyaline, up to 20 μm wide. Pileipellis a hymeniderm 
composed of cells 15 -35 × 10 -20 μm, clavate, pyriform, 
fusoid, subutriform or subvesiculose, sometimes pedicellate, 
rarely irregular, smooth, ± thin-walled, hyaline to pale yellowish 
in KOH. Pileocystidia absent. Stipitipellis a cutis of cylindrical, 
parallel, thick-walled (up to 0.5(-0.75) μm thick), incrusted, 
up to 6.0(-10) μm wide hyphae with greyish yellowish walls 
in KOH. Caulocystidia 18 -42 × (3.5 -)5.0 -12 μm, adpressed 
to erect, clavate, subcylindrical, fusoid, sometimes irregular 
or with projections, thin-to slightly thick-walled, with hyaline 
to pale greyish or yellowish walls in KOH. Clamp connections 
present in all tissues. </p>

<p>Chemical reactions -Basidiospores, pileipellis, some caulo-
cystidia and hymenium non-dextrinoid, other tissues dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On detritus and twigs of Pinus multiflora, Larix 
sibirica, Quercus mongolica and Quercus sp., on calcareous 
soil along a rivulet and in a mixed forest (dominated by Quercus 
sp. div., Pinus densiflora and Larix sibirica). </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Republic of KoRea, Dnayang, Sobaeksan National 
Park, Darian river valley between Darian pokpo (falls) and N.P. Northern office, 
36°59'20"N, 128°27'40"E, 14 July 2007, V. Antonín (07.51), J.G. Han, R. Ryoo, 
H.D. Shin &amp; M.J. Park, BRNM 714572; Dnayang, Sobaeksan National Park, 
Darian river valley between Darian pokpo (falls) and N.P. Northern office, 
36°59'20"N, 128°27'40"E, 14 July 2007, V. Antonín (07.53) &amp; H.D. Shin, BRNM 
714573; Chuncheon, Dongsan-myeon, Bongmyeong-ri, Experimental forest 
of the Kangwon National University, 37°46'46"N, 127°48'59"E, alt. c. 212 m, 
22 July 2007, V. Antonín 07.101, BRNM 714574; Hoengseong, Mt Maebong-
san, alt. c. 230 -270 m, 37°29'25"N, 127°51'04"E, 20 July 2007, V. Antonín 
07.143, BRNM 718800; Suwon, the former campus of the Seoul National 
University, alt. c. 65 m, 37°16'07"N, 126°59'15"E, 21 July 2009, H.D. Shin, V. 
Antonín 09.149, BRNM 718806; Gapcheon, Mt Homyeongsan, alt. c. 235 m, 
37°32'12"N, 128°06'22"E, 27 July 2009, V. Antonín 09.167 &amp; R. Ryoo, 
BRNM 718824. -Japan, Kanagawa prefecture, Yamato-shi, 20 June 1999, 
H. Takahashi, holotype KPM -NC 0006038. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius nivicola is characterised by having a 
whitish, yellowish white or pale yellow pileus, distinctly inter-
venose lamellae (already when young), present cheilo-and 
caulocystidia and absent pleurocystidia. </p>

<p>Marasmius pellucidus, known from Indonesia, Malaysia, New 
Caledonia, Sri Lanka and Singapore, has a thin-fleshed pileus, 
a longer ((20-)40-150 × (1-)2-3 mm), pruinose stipe and 
slightly smaller basidiospores, (6-)6.5-8(-8.5) × (2.5-)3-4 
μm (Wannathes et al. 2004). </p>

<p>Marasmius nivicola has been found only in East Asia (Japan, 
Takahashi 2000; Republic of Korea) to date. </p>

<p>6. Marasmius purpureostriatus Hongo, J. Jap. Bot. 33: 344. 
1958. -Fig. 1a, 7 </p>

<p>Basidiocarps single. Pileus 17 mm broad, conical, except for 
± smooth centre distinctly and deeply sulcate, with straight and 
crenulate margin, striped, centre and striae violet brown (11E4), 
sulcae whitish. Lamellae distant, L = 12; l = 0(-1), emarginate 
with very small tooth to free, fusoid, pale grey (11B-C1), with 
pale purplish tinged, finely pubescent edge. Stipe 74 × 1 mm, 
cylindrical, slightly broadened above, subbulbose at base, non-
insititious, smooth, glabrous, silky lustrous, concolorous with 
lamellae at apex, up to reddish brown or violet brown (9-10E5) 
towards base; rich basal tomentum ochre-yellow. Context mem-
branaceous, without any distinct smell. Basidiospores 21-25 × 
5.0-6.5 μm, average = 22.6 × 5.8 μm, E = 3.4-4.6, Q = 3.95, 
clavate, fusoid or lacrimoid, sometimes septate, smooth, hya-
line, both non-dextrinoid, thin-and dextrinoid thick-walled. Ba-
sidia 38-45 × 10-11 μm, 4-spored, clavate. Basidioles 22-50 
× up to 12 μm, subcylindrical, clavate or fusoid. Cheilocystidia 
(15 -)20 -35 × 10 -15 μm, broadly clavate, fusoid, utriform, 
sometimes irregular or with projection(s), thin-walled. Pleuro-
cystidia absent. Trama hyphae made up of cylindrical or fusoid 
cells, thin-to slightly thick-walled, hyaline, up to 15 μm wide. 
Pileipellis a hymeniderm composed of cells 21-32 × 12-18 μm, 
clavate, pyriform or vesiculose, ± regular, thin-walled, smooth, 
subhyaline in KOH. Stipitipellis a cutis of cylindrical, parallel, 
slightly thick-walled, smooth, up to 5.0 μm wide hyphae with 
olivaceous brown walls in KOH. Caulocystidia absent. Clamp 
connections present in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Pileipellis, hymenium and basidio-
spores non-dextrinoid except for thick-walled spores, which 
are dextrinoid, other tissues distinctly dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On detritus in a mixed forest (Pinus densiflora, 
Quercus spp., Cryptomeria sp.). </p>

<p>Fig. 6 Marasmius nivicola. a. pileipellis cells; b. cheilocystidia; c. basidio-
spores; d. caulocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 24, 2010 </p>

<p>Specimens examined. Republic of KoRea, Jeju, Jocheon-eup, Seonheul-
ri, alt. c. 95 m, 33°31'01"N, 126°42'27"E, 5 July 2008, R. Ryoo &amp; V. Antonín 
08.57, BRNM 714566. -Japan, Otsu City, Ishujama, Hiratsu-cho, 7 May 
1957, T. Hongo 1609, isotype ZT 3221; Nara City, 24 April 1958, T. Hongo, 
ex herb. Hongo 1749, L 0650197. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius purpureostriatus is a very distinct spe-
cies especially characterised by a striate pileus, glabrous stipe, 
large basidiospores and broadly clavate, fusoid, utriform, some-
times irregular cheilocystidia. </p>

<p>The most similar species is Marasmius pseudopurpureostriatus 
Wannathes et al., recently described from Thailand. It differs 
by having a larger pileus (14 -38 mm diam) with paler colours, 
a broader stipe (62 -80 × 1.5 -3 mm) and slightly smaller ba-
sidiospores (20 -25 × 5 -6.2 μm) with a mean length 22.8 μm 
(Wannathes et al. 2009b). However, our collection of M. pur 
pureostriatus has the same spore size, but our molecular stud-
ies proved that our collection belongs to this species. </p>

<p>Among other species with smooth pileus cells and striate pileus, 
M. viridis, from Papua New Guinea, differs by an olivaceous 
pileus, M. musisporus, also from Papua New Guinea, has a 
purplish lilac pileus with yellow striae, a reddish brown stipe 
and distinctly larger basidiospores, 30-40 × 4.5-5.0 μm in size 
(Desjardin &amp; Horak 1997). Marasmius ditopotramus, described 
from Bolivia, has a pileus and stipe without any purplish tinge 
and smaller basidiospores, 7-9 × 4.5 -4.8 μm (Singer 1976). 
The African species M. violaceoides has a violaceous, violet 
brown or brown pileus with pale violaceous striae, whitish 
to pale greyish orange lamellae, narrower basidiospores 
(15.5-22.3 × 3.3 -5.0 μm) and shorter cheilocystidia (14-24 
× (4.2 -)6.2 -9.2 μm). Other African species: M. zenkeri, has 
a pileus up to 100 mm broad, pale lilac lamellae, a robust 
((40-)120 -170 × 2 -12 mm) fuligineous, dark reddish brown 
or chestnut brown stipe, and large cheilocystidia (14 -50 × 
10-15 μm); M. bekolacongoli has yellow coloured or tinged 
pileus striae, yellow-white to pale lemon-yellow lamellae, a more </p>

<p>robust (50-150 × 2.5-6(-10) mm) stipe without purplish tinge 
and different basidiospores (17.5-24.5(-26) × (3.8-)4.2-5.4 
μm, Q = 5.1); M. brunneolus has a pileus without any purplish 
tinge, a more robust stipe (70-180 × 3-6 mm) also without any 
purplish tinge and slightly different basidiospores (15.5-25.5 × 
3.8-5.4 μm, Q = 4.4-4.6); and M. staudtii differs especially by 
having well-developed pleurocystidia (Antonín 2007). </p>

<p>Marasmius purpureostriatus has been collected in East Asia 
(Japan, Hongo 1958; Malaysia, Thailand, Tan et al. 2009, 
Wannathes et al. 2009a; Republic of Korea) and Papua New 
Guinea (Desjardin &amp; Horak 1997, Tan et al. 2009). </p>

<p>7. Marasmius wynneae Berk. &amp; Broome, Ann. Mag. Nat. Hist., 
ser. III, 3: 358. 1859. -Fig. 8 </p>

<p>Basidiocarps single or in (rich) clusters. Pileus (6 -)10 -50 
mm, hemispherical to broadly conical with more or less distinct 
papilla or slightly depressed centre when young, expanding 
to convex or applanate with low, obtuse umbo or slightly de-
pressed centre, with involute then deflexed or straight, finally 
sometimes slightly reflexed margin, hygrophanous, slightly 
translucently striate up to half the radius when moist, white or 
grey-ochraceous when young, then milky white, grey, or grey-
violaceous, usually with paler margin, pallescent on drying, 
smooth, glabrous or rugulose to subsulcate in old specimens. 
Lamellae distant, L = 16-29, l = 2-3, free to emarginate with 
small decurrent tooth, segmentiform to ventricose, rather thick, 
intervenose when old, white to cream or grey, sometimes with 
violaceous tinge, with entire to eroded, concolorous edge. Stipe 
20-85 × 1-4.5 mm, cylindrical or slightly compressed, without 
or rarely with a shallow longitudinal groove, sometimes curved 
at base, slightly broadened at apex, often attenuated towards 
base, sometimes slightly twisted, very variable in colour, from 
entirely white to white at apex with short brown or brown-orange </p>

<p>Fig. 7 Marasmius purpureostriatus. a. Pileipellis cells; b. basidiospores; 
c. cheilocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c 
b </p>

<p>a </p>

<p>Fig. 8 Marasmius wynneae. a. Pileipellis cells; b. cheilocystidia; c. basidio-
spores; d. caulocystidia. -Scale bar = 20 μm. </p>

<p>c </p>

<p>b </p>

<p>d </p>

<p>a </p>



<p>V. Antonín et al.: Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2 </p>

<p>zone towards dark red-brown below, or almost entirely brown 
to orange-brown with red-brown tinge at base only, sometimes 
entirely red-brown when old, scatteredly flocculose-squamu-
lose, with abundant white basal tomentum, fistulose. Context 
concolorous with surface in cortex of pileus and stipe, whitish 
in pileus. Smell pleasant (fungoid or like bitter almonds) to 
slightly unpleasantly acid. Taste mild, after longer mastication 
slightly astringent as in Xerocomus badius (according to An-
tonín &amp; Noordeloos 2009). Basidiospores 6.5 -8.0 × 3.7-4.5 
μm, average = 7.3 × 4.1 μm, E = 1.7-2.0, Q = 1.8, ellipsoid, 
sublacrimoid, smooth, hyaline, thin-walled. Basidium (one 
found) 24 × 6.5 μm, 4-spored, clavate. Basidioles up to 30 × 
4.0-8.0 μm, cylindrical, clavate or (sub)fusoid. Cheilocystidia 
15-29 × 6.0-11 μm, clavate, capitate and pedicellate, smooth, 
mostly irregular, lobate or branched, rarely regular, thin-walled. 
Pleurocystidia absent. Trama hyphae cylindrical or subinflated, 
± thin-walled, smooth or minutely incrusted, hyaline, up to 15 
μm wide. Pileipellis a hymeniderm composed of cells 14-27 × 
(8.0-)10 -17 μm, clavate, pyriform, subvesiculose, sometimes 
irregular, smooth, thin-walled. Pileocystidia absent. Stipitipellis 
a cutis of cylindrical, parallel, slightly thick-walled, up to 5.0 μm 
wide hyphae. Caulocystidia 22 -48 × 7.0 -14 μm, adpressed to 
erect, clavate, subcylindrical, fusoid or capitate, sometimes ir-
regular or with projection(s), thin-to slightly thick-walled. Clamp 
connections present in all tissues. 
Chemical reactions -Basidiospores, pileipellis and hy-
menium non-dextrinoid, other tissues dextrinoid. 
Habitat -On fallen needles of a coniferous tree. </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.77 </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.98 </p>

<p>0.69 </p>

<p>0.63 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.56 </p>

<p>0.53 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.71 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>M. rotula AF261345 </p>

<p>M. rotula DQ457686 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714570 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714672 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714571 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714671 </p>

<p>M. aurantioferrugineus HCCN -GBDS 2861 
M. aurantioferrugineus HCCN 3517 </p>

<p>M. aurantioferrugineus BRNM 714752 </p>

<p>M. nivicola KPM -NC 0006038 
M. nivicola BRNM 714574 
M. nivicola BRNM 714572 
M. nivicola BRNM 714573 </p>

<p>M. fusicystidiosus BRNM 714567 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714569 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714568 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus KPM -NC 0005011 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714669 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714670 </p>

<p>M. wynneae EF160082* </p>

<p>M. wynneae EF160081* </p>

<p>M. wynneae HCCN -G 86 </p>

<p>M. mbalmayoensis EF160092* </p>

<p>M. mbalmayoensis EF160091* 
M. bekolacongoli EF160089* </p>

<p>M. bekolacongoli EF160080* </p>

<p>M. purpureostriatus BRNM 714566 </p>

<p>M. oreades DQ156126* </p>

<p>M. oreades EF160080* </p>

<p>0.91 </p>

<p>Fig. 9 Phylogenetic tree -LSU. Phylogenetic tree for Marasmius sect. 
Globulares species on the n-LSU rDNA (nuclear large subunit ribosomal 
DNA) sequences, showing mean branch lengths of a 50 % majority rule 
consensus tree, obtained from an MCMC analysis of one million generations. 
An asterisk (*) denotes a sequence from GenBank. </p>

<p>Specimen examined. Republic of KoRea, Yangpyeong, Yongmun-myeon, 
Sinjum-ri, Mt Yongmun, 30 June 1993, Y.S. Kim, HCCN -G86. </p>

<p>Notes -Marasmius wynneae is characterised by a white, 
grey-ochraceous, milky white, grey, or grey-violaceous pileus 
and stipe, a mostly distinctly squamulose stipe, small basidio-
spores, and irregularly shaped cheilocystidia. The only known 
collection from the Republic of Korea was found in the HCCN 
herbarium (Suwon), which fully agrees with European material. 
For details about synonyms, name and taxonomy, see Antonín 
&amp; Noordeloos (2010). </p>

<p>Marasmius wynneae is a widely distributed species in Europe 
and has also been recorded from northern Africa (Malençon &amp; 
Bertault 1975). In East Asia, it is known only from the Republic 
of Korea. </p>

<p>Phylogenetic analysis </p>

<p>Based on nuclear ribosomal large subunit (LSU) and internal 
transcribed spacer (ITS) rDNA sequences obtained in this 
study and from GenBank, the phylogenetic relationships of 
species in genus Marasmius sect. Globulares were inferred 
from MCMC analyses. LSU and ITS sequences were aligned 
and the ends trimmed to create a dataset of 760 and 651 base 
pairs, respectively. MrBayes was used to compute a 50 % 
majority rule consensus for 10 
6 generations with a tree saved 
every 100th generation. The first 1 000 trees were discarded 
and the remaining trees obtained estimates for the posterior 
probabilities of group. The phylogenetic trees is shown in Fig. 9 
(LSU) and Fig. 10 (ITS). </p>



<p>Persoonia -Volume 24, 2010 </p>

<p>The circumscription of seven species based on morphological 
characteristics is concordant with those suggested by LSU 
and ITS sequences similarity. The new species Marasmius fusi 
cystidiosus forms a distinct branch sister of M. brunneospermus 
in the LSU and ITS rDNA analyses. Marasmius brunneospermus 
and M. nivicola specimens collected in Korea form monophyletic 
groups with the respective type specimens of M. brunneospermus 
(KPM-NC 0005011) and M. nivicola (KPM-NC 0006038). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Phylogenetic data inferred from LSU and ITS sequences sup-
port the recognition of species delimited by macro-and micro-
morphological characteristics. In this study, LSU and ITS rDNA 
sequences datasets aid in differentiating morphologically similar 
species. The result of this study are concordant with phylogenetic 
data of Marasmius in previous studies of Tan et al. (2009) and 
Wannathes et al. (2009a). </p>

<p>Acknowledgements The authors are much obliged to Yousuke Degawa 
(KPM, Kanagawa Prefectural Museum of Natural History, Odawara, Japan) 
for a loan of the type specimens of Marasmius brunneospermus and M. nivi 
cola, Egon Horak (ZT, Zürich, Switzerland) for loaning the isotype specimen of 
M. purpureostriatus, and to curators of the herbaria L and NIAST (Suwon) for 
loaning other herbarium specimens. The authors also wish to thank Zdeně k 
Pouzar (Prague, Czech Republic) for correcting the Latin diagnosis, and Jan 
W. Jongepier (Veselí nad Moravou, Czech Republic) for correcting our English 
manuscript. The collecting trip to the Republic of Korea and the studies of 
the collected material of the first author were supported by the Grant Agency 
of the Czech Republic (No. 206/07/J003). Other authors were supported by 
the Korea Research Foundation Grant funded by the Korea Government 
(KRF-2006-F00001). We are grateful to Dennis Desjardin (San Francisco 
State University, California, USA) for critically reviewing our manuscript. </p>



<p>M. purpureostriatus BRNM 714566 </p>

<p>M. aurantioferrugineus HCCN -GBDS 2861 
M. aurantioferrugineus HCCN 3517 </p>

<p>M. aurantioferrugineus BRNM 714752 </p>

<p>M. rotula DQ182506 </p>

<p>M. capillaris FJ596829 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.82 </p>

<p>0.80 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.1 </p>

<p>M. nivicola KPM -NC 0006038 </p>

<p>M. nivicola BRNM 714572 </p>

<p>M. nivicola BRNM 714573 </p>

<p>M. nivicola BRNM 714574 </p>

<p>0.52 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714570 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714672 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714571 </p>

<p>M. maximus BRNM 714671 </p>

<p>M. wynneae HCCN -G 86 </p>

<p>M. oreades DQ490641* </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714569 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714670 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714669 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus BRNM 714568 </p>

<p>M. fusicystidiosus BRNM 714567 </p>

<p>M. brunneospermus KPM -NC 0005011 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.87 </p>

<p>1.00 </p>

<p>0.67 </p>

<p>Fig. 10 Phylogenetic tree -ITS. Phylogenetic tree for Marasmius sect. Globulares species inferred from a Bayesian analysis of the complete ITS region (ITS1, 
5.8S rDNA, and ITS2), showing mean branch lengths of a 50 % majority rule consensus tree, obtained from an MCMC analysis of one million generations. An 
asterisk (*) denotes a sequence from GenBank. </p>



<p>V. Antonín et al.: Marasmioid and gymnopoid fungi of the Republic of Korea. 2 </p>



</text></tei>