<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2551693" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-03T15:49+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>OBJECTIVE-Sulforaphane is an activator of transcription factor 
NF-E2-related factor-2 (nrf2) that regulates gene expression 
through the promoter antioxidant response element (ARE). Nrf2 
regulates the transcription of a battery of protective and metabolic 
enzymes. The aim of this study was to assess whether activation of 
nrf2 by sulforaphane in human microvascular endothelial cells 
prevents metabolic dysfunction in hyperglycemia. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Human microvascu-
lar HMEC-1 endothelial cells were incubated in low and high 
glucose concentrations (5 and 30 mmol/l, respectively), and 
activation of nrf2 was assessed by nuclear translocation. The 
effects of sulforaphane on multiple pathways of biochemical 
dysfunction, increased reactive oxygen species (ROS) formation, 
hexosamine pathway, protein kinase C (PKC) pathway, and 
increased formation of methylglyoxal were assessed. </p>

<p>RESULTS-Activation of nrf2 by sulforaphane induced nuclear 
translocation of nrf2 and increased ARE-linked gene expression, for 
example, three-to fivefold increased expression of transketolase 
and glutathione reductase. Hyperglycemia increased the formation 
of ROS-an effect linked to mitochondrial dysfunction and pre-
vented by sulforaphane. ROS formation was increased further by 
knockdown of nrf2 and transketolase expression. This also abol-
ished the counteracting effect of sulforaphane, suggesting mediation 
by nrf2 and related increase of transketolase expression. Sulfora-
phane also prevented hyperglycemia-induced activation of the hex-
osamine and PKC pathways and prevented increased cellular 
accumulation and excretion of the glycating agent methylglyoxal. </p>

<p>CONCLUSIONS-We conclude that activation of nrf2 may prevent 
biochemical dysfunction and related functional responses of endothe-
lial cells induced by hyperglycemia in which increased expression of 
transketolase has a pivotal role. autoregulatory feedback loop (23). Nrf2 also undergoes 
nuclear export, establishing cytoplasmic/nuclear dynamic 
shuttling (24). Recent research has suggested that the 
serine/threonine kinase CK2 has a role in nuclear import of 
nrf2 and that both CK2 and tyrosine kinase Fyn influence 
nuclear export and degradation of nrf2 (25,26) (Fig. 1A). </p>

<p>There is an active nrf2-Keap-1 system in vascular endo-
thelial cells (27). 
The role, if any, of nrf2-linked gene expression in 
countering endothelial dysfunction in hyperglycemia has 
not been disclosed. Disposal of glyceraldehyde-3-phos-
phate and fructose-6-phosphate by the reductive pentose-</p>

<p>Nucleus </p>

<p>Cell cytosol </p>

<p>Cell scaffolding </p>

<p>(microfilaments) </p>

<p>Dissociation </p>

<p>Nuclear membrane </p>

<p>Inactive 
protein 
complex </p>

<p>Sulforaphane </p>

<p>Modified Keap-1 </p>

<p>(proteasome) </p>

<p>Cell proteolysis </p>

<p>Maf F, G and K </p>

<p>5'-TMAnnRTGAYnnnGCR-3' </p>

<p>ARE </p>

<p>Maf </p>

<p>Nuclear 
export </p>

<p>Maf </p>

<p>Increased expression of protective proteins 
(GST, NQO1, TK, TA, GCL, GSHRd, AKRd, nrf2, keap1 and others) </p>

<p>nrf2 P </p>

<p>Nuclear 
translocation </p>

<p>CK2 </p>

<p>Phosphorylation </p>

<p>nrf2 P </p>

<p>CK2 </p>

<p>nrf2 P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>Fyn </p>

<p>nrf2 P </p>

<p>P </p>

<p>nrf2 </p>

<p>Phosphorylation </p>

<p>Phosphatase </p>

<p>nrf2 P </p>

<p>Rbx-1 </p>

<p>E2 
Ub </p>

<p>N C S 
S 
CH 3 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>N 
H 
C 
S 
CH 3 </p>

<p>O </p>

<p>S </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>Keap1 </p>

<p>Keap1 </p>

<p>Cul-3 </p>

<p>nrf2 </p>

<p>Aldolase </p>

<p>TPI </p>

<p>Pyruvate + NADH </p>

<p>L-Lactate + NAD </p>

<p>+ </p>

<p>Glucose </p>

<p>G-6-P 
isomerase </p>

<p>Hexokinase </p>

<p>F-6-P </p>

<p>Phospho-
fructokinase </p>

<p>F-1,6-bis-P </p>

<p>ATP 
ADP </p>

<p>Aldolase </p>

<p>GA3P </p>

<p>G-6-P 
isomerase </p>

<p>G-6-P </p>

<p>ADP </p>

<p>ATP </p>

<p>DHAP </p>

<p>G-3-P </p>

<p>Hexosamine 
pathway </p>

<p>PKC activation </p>

<p>Mitochondrial 
dysfunction </p>

<p>AGE 
formation </p>

<p>MG </p>

<p>GA3PDH </p>

<p>Polyol 
pathway </p>

<p>R-5-P </p>

<p>Reductive pentose 
phosphate pathway </p>

<p>Nrf2-mediated induction of 
transketolase expression </p>

<p>Transketolase </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>FIG. 1. Nrf2 activation and transketolase expression in human HMEC-1 endothelial cells in vitro. A: Schematic diagram showing activation of nrf2 
and dynamic nuclear-cytoplasmic shuttling of nrf2 for ARE-linked expression. B: Multiple pathways of biochemical dysfunction induced by 
hyperglycemia in microvascular endothelial cells and effect of nrf2 activated, ARE-mediated induction of transketolase expression. Other 
mechanisms of biochemical dysfunction may be involved. </p>

<p>ROLE OF ACTIVATION OF nrf2 </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>phosphate pathway induced by activation of nrf2 and 
increased expression of transketolase suggested a possi-
ble mechanism of intervention. In this report, we show 
that activation of nrf2 by the dietary activator sulfora-
phane, limited to concentration ranges found in plasma 
after consumption of broccoli (28) for relevance to future 
clinical dietary intervention, increased the expression of 
protective enzymes under ARE-linked transcriptional con-
trol and prevented metabolic dysfunction in endothelial 
cells induced by hyperglycemia in which increased expres-
sion of transketolase has a critical role. </p>

<p>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS </p>

<p>Reagents. MCDB-131 medium, FCS, Alexa Fluor 488 rabbit anti-mouse IgG 
and 2Ј,7Ј-dichlorodihydrofluorescein diacetate (H 2 DCFDA) were purchased 
from Invitrogen (Paisley, U.K.). Monoclonal (mouse) anti-O-linked N-acetyl-
glucosamine (Clone RL2) was purchased from Abcam (Cambridge, U.K.). All 
other chemicals were obtained from Sigma-Aldrich (Poole, Dorset, U.K.), 
unless otherwise stated. 
Cell culture. Human microvascular HMEC-1 endothelial cells were cultured 
as described previously (29). HMEC-1 cells (4 -6 ϫ 10 
6 ) were incubated in 
MCDB-131 medium with 10% serum, 10 mmol/l L-glutamine, 10 ng/ml epider-
mal growth factor, and 1 g/ml hydrocortisone in 92-mm-diameter Petri dishes 
with low glucose (5 mmol/l) and high glucose (30 mmol/l) in the absence and 
presence of 4 mol/l sulforaphane for 6 -48 h, trypsinized, and analyzed as 
described below. 
Small interfering RNA transfection. HMEC-1 endothelial cells were incu-
bated in MCDB-131 medium with 10% serum and then transfected with small 
interfering RNA (siRNA) for nrf2 (SI00657030; Qiagen) or transketolase 
(SI02653791) using the HiPerfect transfection reagent according to the man-
ufacturer's instructions. The incubation was then continued with normal 
medium for 24 h. Cultures were then continued with low and high glucose 
concentrations in the absence and presence of 4 mol/l sulforaphane for 6 or 
24 h and/or other additives. Knockdown was confirmed by real-time RT-PCR 
for nrf2 and transketolase. RNA was extracted using the RNeasy minikit 
(Qiagen), reverse transcribed by SuperScript III First Strand Synthesis system 
(Invitrogen), and quantified by real-time RT-PCR using the TaqMan MGB 
probes, designed and supplied by Applied Biosystems. Knockdown was 60% 
for transketolase and Ͼ90% for nrf2. 
Nuclear translocation of nrf2 by immunoblotting. Nuclear and cytosolic 
proteins were isolated from HMEC-1 cells incubated with and without 
sulforaphane using a CelLytic NuCLEAR extraction kit (Sigma). Trypsinized 
cells were washed in PBS at 4°C, and the cell pellet was lysed with hypotonic 
lysate buffer containing dithiothreitol, a protease inhibitor cocktail, and 
IGEPAL CA-630 on ice for 15 min. The lysate was centrifuged (11,000 ϫ g, 30 s, 
4°C), and the supernatant was used for the cytosolic extract. The pellet (crude 
nuclear fraction) was treated with extraction buffer containing dithiothreitol 
and protease inhibitor cocktail at 4°C for 30 min, vortex mixed, and centri-
fuged (21,000 ϫ g, 4°C, 5 min). The supernatant was collected for the nuclear 
extract. All protein extracts were frozen at Ϫ80°C immediately until further 
analysis. The protein concentration was determined with EZQ Protein Quan-
titation kit (Invitrogen). 
Proteins in the cytosolic and nuclear fractions were separated by 10% 
SDS-PAGE and transferred electrophoretically onto polyvinylidene difluoride 
membrane, and the membrane was blocked with 5% nonfat milk in Tris-
buffered saline-Tween buffer (10 mmol/l Tris-HCl, pH 7.5; 150 mmol/l NaCl; 
and 0.05% Tween-20). The membrane was probed with anti-nrf2 antibody 
(H-300; 1:1,500 dilution) overnight at 4°C. After washing, the membrane was 
incubated with horseradish peroxidase-conjugated second antibody (1:3,000 
diluted; Sigma) for 1 h at room temperature, and immunoconjugate was 
detected with enhanced chemiluminescence. The membrane was then incu-
bated with stripping buffer (100 mmol/l ␤-mercaptoethanol, 2% SDS, and 62.5 
mmol/l Tris-HCl, pH 6.8), blocked with 5% nonfat milk in Tris-buffered 
saline-Tween buffer, and reprobed with antibodies to reference proteins 
␤-actin and lamin A. Protein band intensities were quantified using <rs id="software-0" type="software">Image- Quant TL</rs> software (<rs corresp="#software-0" type="creator">Amersham Biosciences</rs>). 
Characterization of biochemical dysfunction. The intracellular formation 
of ROS was detected using the fluorogenic probe H 2 DCFDA. Cells (2 ϫ 10 
6 ) 
were incubated with and without sulforaphane and mitochondrial inhibitors 
for 24 h, washed with PBS, and then incubated further with 20 mol/l 
H 2 DCFDA for 45 min, washed again, and analyzed by flow cytometry. Shorter 
incubations of 1-h preincubation in hyperglycemia with and without mito-
chondrial inhibitors were also performed by microplate fluorescence mea-</p>

<p>surements, normalizing the fluorescence intensity to cell number. The effect of 
treatments on cell viability was assessed by Trypan blue exclusion. 
Hexosamine pathway activity was assessed by a quantitative dot Western 
blot assay for O-linked N-acetylglucosamine modified protein. Cytosolic 
protein extracts (0.7 g in 5 l PBS) were immunoblotted with RL2 antibody 
(1:800 dilution in blocking buffer) for 3 h at room temperature, blocked with 
10% BSA, and washed (30). The immunocomplexes were detected with Alexa 
Fluor 488 rabbit anti-mouse IgG (1:700 dilution) and quantified by microplate 
fluorimetry. The concentrations of methylglyoxal in HMEC-1 cells and me-
dium of cultures with and without sulforaphane were determined by deriva-
tization with 1,2-diaminobenzene and quantitation by liquid chromatography 
with tandem mass spectrometric detection and stable isotopic dilution 
analysis (12). PKC activity was assayed in membrane and particulate fractions 
of HMEC-1 cells with exogenous diacylglycerol (1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycerol; 
DAG) activator and epidermal growth factor receptor peptide fragment 
VRKRTLRRL as substrate (9). 
Statistical analyses. All statistical analyses were performed using paired 
Student's t test, and results are expressed as means Ϯ SD. A P value Ͻ0.05 was 
considered to be significant. </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>Activation of nrf2 and ARE-linked gene expression in 
endothelial cells by the dietary activator sulfora-
phane. We investigated the activation status of nrf2 in 
human microvascular endothelial cells by assessing nu-
clear translocation of human nrf2 by immunoblotting in 
cytosolic and nuclear fractions and confocal microscopy 
of nrf2-GFP fusion protein. HMEC-1 endothelial cells 
incubated in model hyperglycemia (30 mmol/l glucose) 
showed no significant nuclear translocation of nrf2 with 
respect to normoglycemic control (5 mmol/l glucose) after 
incubation for 6 h. Addition of 4 mol/l sulforaphane gave 
a twofold increase in nuclear nrf2 in both normoglycemic 
and hyperglycemic cultures. In the normoglycemic cul-
ture, the concentration of nrf2 in the cytosol was de-
creased concomitantly; whereas in the hyperglycemic 
culture, the concentration of nrf2 in the cytosol was 
increased. This suggests that the double insult of hyper-
glycemia and sulforaphane increased the cellular content 
of nrf2 protein (Fig. 2A and B). This concentration of 
sulforaphane did not induce significant cytotoxicity in 
HMEC-1 cells in incubations for up to 48 h, as assessed in 
previous studies (31). Transketolase activity of HMEC-1 
cells was determined spectrophotometrically, as we have 
previously described (9). 
Real-time RT-PCR analysis of target ARE-linked gene 
expression revealed a marked fivefold induction of transke-
tolase mRNA in cells stimulated with sulforaphane (Fig. 3A) 
and a lower, three-to fourfold increase in GSHRd mRNA 
(Fig. 3B). The cytosolic activity of transketolase was in-
creased 40 -60% by exposure to sulforaphane (Fig. 3C). The 
increase in expression of transketolase induced by sulfora-
phane in normoglycemic and hyperglycemic cultures was 
prevented by knockdown of nrf2 expression (Fig. 3A). To 
confirm that there is an ARE-linked induction of gene expres-
sion by sulforaphane in HMEC-1 cells, we studied the mRNA 
levels of the typical nrf2-linked, ARE-mediated gene, NQO1. 
NQO1 expression, normalized to culture in normoglycemia, 
was increased approximately twofold in HMEC-1 cells incu-
bated with 4 mol/l sulforaphane in normoglycemic and 
hyperglycemic conditions. Basal and sulforaphane-induced 
expression of NQO1 in hyperglycemic culture was decreased 
56 and 31%, respectively, by knockdown of nrf2 with siRNA 
(Fig. 3D). 
Increased formation of ROS by endothelial cells in 
hyperglycemia, reversal by sulforaphane, and critical 
role of transketolase. To examine the effect of ARE-
linked gene expression on biochemical dysfunction in </p>

<p>M. XUE AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
hyperglycemia, the cellular production of ROS was quan-
tified. Hyperglycemic culture of endothelial cells produced 
a threefold increased formation of ROS (Fig. 4A). This was 
not induced by the addition of 25 mmol/l L-glucose (which 
does not permeate into endothelial cells) to the normogly-
cemic control. Incubation of endothelial cells with sulfora-
phane reversed the increase in ROS by 73%, suggesting 
that activation of ARE-linked gene expression prevented 
increased ROS formation. Increased ROS formation by 
HMEC-1 cells in hyperglycemic cultures was prevented by </p>

<p>incubation for 60 min with mitochondrial inhibitors (ROS 
formation [percentage of normoglycemic control]: 10 
mol/l p-trifluoromethoxycarbonylcyanide phenylhydra-
zone, 94 Ϯ 3%; 5 mol/l rotenone, 104 Ϯ 3%; and 2 mol/l 
myxothiazole, 88 Ϯ 3%). This suggests that dysfunction of 
mitochondria was a primary source of the increased ROS 
and electron flux, although complexes I and III contrib-
uted to this effect. Incubation of HMEC-1 cells with these 
inhibitors for 24 h decreased cell viability by 40 -50% and 
masked the effect of rotenone. </p>

<p>Nrf2 </p>

<p>Lamin A </p>

<p>N 
N 
N 
H 
H 
H H + H + H + N + N + N + 
SFN SFN SFN SFN SFN SFN </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>3 </p>

<p>N 
H 
H + S F N 
N + S F N </p>

<p>Nrf2/lamin A 
(intensity ratio) </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>N 
N 
N 
H 
H 
H 
H + H + H + N + N + N + 
SFN SFN SFN SFN SFN SFN 
Nrf2 </p>

<p>β-Actin </p>

<p>0.0 </p>

<p>0.2 </p>

<p>0.4 </p>

<p>0.6 </p>

<p>N 
H 
H + S F N 
N + S F N </p>

<p>Nrf2/β-actin </p>

<p>(intensity ratio) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>FIG. 2. Nuclear translocation of nrf2 in human HMEC-1 endothelial cells in vitro activated by sulforaphane. Nuclear fraction (A) and cytosolic 
fraction (B) immunoblotting for nrf2 (98-kDa band). Densitometric intensity ratios are means ؎ SD (n ‫؍‬ 3). N, 5 mmol/l glucose; H, 30 mmol/l 
glucose; N؉SFN, 5 mmol/l glucose ؉ 4 mol/l sulforaphane; and H؉SFN, 30 mmol/l glucose ؉ 4 mol/l sulforaphane. *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, and 
***P &lt; 0.001 with respect to N; 
E P &lt; 0.05 and 
EE P &lt; 0.01 with respect to H. </p>

<p>ROLE OF ACTIVATION OF nrf2 </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>We next sought evidence of whether the prevention of 
increased formation of ROS was dependent on nrf2. We 
transfected endothelial cells with siRNA to knockdown ex-
pression of nrf2 and confirmed this by PCR and real-time 
RT-PCR (Fig. 4B). Decreasing the expression of nrf2 exacer-
bated ROS production in both normoglycemic and hypergly-
cemic cultures; ROS was increased 145% with 5 mmol/l 
glucose and 190% with 30 mmol/l glucose, with respect to 
cells with 5 and 30 mmol/l glucose transfected with scram-
bled siRNA. The increased formation of ROS with nrf2 
knockdown was maintained and not reversed by sulfora-
phane, which is consistent with the prevention of increased </p>

<p>ROS by sulforaphane being mediated by activation of nrf2 
rather than a direct antioxidant effect of sulforaphane. 
Knockdown of transketolase by transfection of endothelial 
cells with siRNA also exacerbated ROS production in both 
normoglycemic and hyperglycemic cultures: ROS was in-
creased 247 and 131%, respectively, with respect to cultures 
with 5 and 30 mmol/l glucose transfected with scrambled 
siRNA. The increased formation of ROS with transketolase 
siRNA knockdown was maintained and not reversed by 
sulforaphane, consistent with the prevention of increased 
ROS by sulforaphane being mediated by increased expres-
sion of transketolase (Fig. 4B). </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N+SFN H+SFN N(ANnrf2) H(ANnrf2) N+SFN 
(ANnrf2) </p>

<p>H+SFN 
(ANnrf2) </p>

<p>TK/β-actin mRNA </p>

<p>(% of control) </p>

<p>* 
** </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>N = 5 mM glucose 
H = 30 mM glucose </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>300 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>500 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F N 
H + S F N </p>

<p>GSHRd/β-actin mRNA </p>

<p>(% of control) </p>

<p>** 
** </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>15 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F N 
H + S F N </p>

<p>Transketolase activity 
(mU/mg protein) </p>

<p>*** 
** </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>50 </p>

<p>100 </p>

<p>150 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N+SFN 
H+SFN 
H(ANnrf2) 
H+SFN 
(ANnrf2) </p>

<p>NQO1/β-actin mRNA </p>

<p>(% of control) </p>

<p>** 
*** </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>** 
* </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>FIG. 3. Effect of sulforaphane on ARE-linked gene expression in HMEC-1 endothelial cells in hyperglycemic culture in vitro. A: Effect of 
hyperglycemia and sulforaphane on expression of transketolase, with and without knockdown of nrf2. B: Effect of hyperglycemia and 
sulforaphane on expression of GSHRd. C: Transketolase activity of HMEC-1 cells; effect of hyperglycemia and sulforaphane. D: Effect of 
hyperglycemia and sulforaphane on expression of NQO1. Transketolase, GSHRd, and NQO1 mRNA were quantified by real-time RT-PCR; 
AN(nrf2), transfection for nrf2 knockdown. Data are means ؎ SD (n ‫؍‬ 3, except n ‫؍‬ 6 for transketolase activity). *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, and 
***P &lt; 0.001 with respect to N; 
EE P &lt; 0.01 with respect to H. </p>

<p>M. XUE AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
Multiple pathways of biochemical dysfunction in en-
dothelial cells in hyperglycemia and reversal by sul-
foraphane. Reversal of increased mitochondrial ROS 
formation is expected to counter biochemical dysfunction 
in multiple pathways. Hyperglycemia increased the activ-
ity of PKC by 180% in the cytosolic fraction and by 347% in 
the membrane fraction of HMEC-1 endothelial cells. These 
increases were reversed partially in both cytosolic and 
membrane fractions by sulforaphane: The hyperglycemia-
induced increase in PKC activity was reversed 40% in the 
cytosolic fraction and 67% in the membrane fraction (Fig. 
5A and B). Similarly, hexosamine pathway-activated en-
zymatic O-linked glycosylation increased twofold in hyper-
glycemia and was reversed by sulforaphane (Fig. 5C). 
Finally, the concentrations of methylglyoxal in HMEC-1 
cells and medium was increased twofold in hyperglycemia 
and reversed by sulforaphane (Fig. 5D). </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>The reversal of biochemical dysfunction of endothelial 
cells in hyperglycemia by sulforaphane suggests that acti-</p>

<p>vation of nrf2 and related ARE-linked gene expression is a 
novel strategy to suppress endothelial cell dysfunction and 
possibly also the development of vascular disease in 
diabetes. For example, decreased cellular and extracellu-
lar secretion of methylglyoxal is expected to prevent 
dicarbonyl glycation of cellular and extracellular matrix 
proteins and to prevent hyperglycemia-induced endothe-
lial cell detachment and anoikis (12). Similarly increased 
ARE-linked gene expression in human aortal endothelial 
cells engineered by adenovirus-mediated expression of 
Nrf2 protected human aortal endothelial cells from cyto-
toxicity induced by hydrogen peroxide and tumor necrosis 
factor-␣-induced increased expression of monocyte che-
moattractant protein-1 and vascular adhesion molecule-1. 
This suggests that increased activation of nrf2 may also 
confer antiatherogenic activity (32). 
Activation of nrf2 by sulforaphane produced nuclear 
accumulation of the 98-kDa band of nrf2 protein. The 
98-kDa band has ARE binding activity and is produced 
by kinase CK2-catalyzed phosphorylation. Nrf2 levels in 
cells are regulated by further phosphorylation, nuclear </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>N 
H 
H (L-) 
N+SFN 
H+SFN </p>

<p>Fluoresence intensity 
(arb. units) </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>o </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>200 </p>

<p>400 </p>

<p>600 </p>

<p>800 </p>

<p>1000 </p>

<p>1200 </p>

<p>N+AN 
(nrf2) </p>

<p>H+AN 
(nrf2) </p>

<p>N+SFN 
+AN(nrf2) </p>

<p>H+SFN 
+AN(nrf2) </p>

<p>N+AN (TK) H+AN (TK) N+SFN 
+AN(TK) </p>

<p>H+SFN 
+AN(TK) </p>

<p>N+AN 
(scr) </p>

<p>H+AN 
(scr) </p>

<p>Fluoresence intensity 
(arb. units) </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>*** 
*** </p>

<p>ooo 
ooo </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>ooo </p>

<p>FIG. 4. Biochemical dysfunction in HMEC-1 endothelial cells in hyperglycemic culture and reversal by sulforaphane in vitro: ROS formation. A and 
B: Assessment of cellular ROS formation. H(L؊), 5 mmol/l D(؉)-glucose with 25 mmol/l L(؊)-glucose; AN(nrf2), transfection with siRNA for nrf2 
knockdown; AN(TK), transfection with siRNA for transketolase knockdown; and AN(scr), transfection with scrambled sequence siRNA. Data are 
means ؎ SD (n ‫؍‬ 3). * and 
E Significance with respect to normoglycemic (N) and hyperglycemic (H) control, respectively, with 1, 2, and 3 symbols 
representing P &lt; 0.05, 0.01, and 0.001, respectively. </p>

<p>ROLE OF ACTIVATION OF nrf2 </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>export, and degradation, which may be enhanced by 
ARE-linked expression of Keap1 (23,26,33). Nrf2 may 
also exhibit ARE-linked expression. Quantitative West-
ern blotting for nrf2 revealed increased nrf2 in both the 
nucleus and cytosol in hyperglycemia with sulforaphane 
treatment, suggesting that total cellular nrf2 protein had 
increased but only with costimulation from both sul-
foraphane and hyperglycemia. The expression of nrf2 is 
ARE-regulated with nrf2 binding to its own promoter 
(17). Hyperglycemia may synergize with sulforaphane 
to increase nrf2 via ARE-induced expression by in-
creasing endogenous activators of nrf2, such as 4-
hydroxynonenal (34), increasing the activity of CK2 
via Ca 
2ϩ /calmodulin-dependent mechanisms (25,35) or 
other activatory mechanism. This may reflect an ARE-
linked, antistress response to hyperglycemia in endothe-
lial cells, albeit too weak to mount an adequate defense 
against the metabolic insult. 
Although nrf2 activation leads to increased expression 
of enzymes linked to antioxidant functions countering 
oxidative stress, in this study, increased expression of 
transketolase made a critical and pivotal intervention. The 
increased reductive pentosephosphate pathway activity 
thereby achieved counters the accumulation of triosephos-
phates and fructose-6-phosphate driving metabolic dys-
function (9). The protective role of the reductive 
pentosephosphate pathway in ARE-linked gene expression 
has hitherto not been identified, although increased tran-
sketolase expression is associated with the dietary restric-
tion model of healthy ageing (36). Enzymatic activity of 
transketolase in the pentosephosphate pathway produces 
indirectly the NADPH cofactor for other ARE-linked gene 
products, GSHRd, AKRd, NQO1, and thioredoxin reduc-</p>

<p>tase, that contribute to countering the effects of oxidative 
stress (37). Therefore, contributions of other ARE-linked 
gene expression in synergism with transketolase in rever-
sal metabolic dysfunction in hyperglycemia cannot be 
excluded. 
Multiple pathways of biochemical dysfunction in 
HMEC-1 cells induced by hyperglycemia were reversed by 
sulforaphane, except reversal of PKC activation was resis-
tant to the response. This may be due to ARE-linked 
induced expression of 1-acylglycerol-3-phosphate O-acyl-
transferase 3 by sulforaphane (38). This enzyme converts 
lysophosphatidic acid to phosphatidic acid, a precursor of 
the PKC activator DAG in de novo synthesis stimulated in 
hyperglycemia. The increased expression of this ARE-
linked gene may maintain increased levels of DAG, 
although the increased concentrations of glycolytic inter-
mediates upstream driving de novo synthesis of DAG are 
expected to have been corrected. Prolonged exposure to 
increased levels of DAG has been suggested as a stimulus 
of increased PKC expression in hyperglycemia associated 
with diabetes that may underlie the increased specific 
activity of PKC in both membrane and cytosolic cell 
fractions found herein. Alternatively, when we studied 
activation of transketolase by high-dose thiamine supple-
ments (7), we also found an incomplete reversal of hyper-
glycemia-induced increase in PKC activity. This may 
suggest that factors other than those influenced by tran-
sketolase contribute to PKC activation in hyperglycemia. 
The prevention of nrf2 activation by sulforaphane by 
addition of GSH may be interpreted as an effect of GSH 
acting as an antioxidant. However, sulforaphane and other 
isothiocyanates bind reversibly to nonprotein thiols, such 
as GSH, decreasing the concentration of free sulforaphane </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>8 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>12 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F N 
H + S F N 
Cytosolic PKC activity 
(pmol/min/mg protein) </p>

<p>*** 
* </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>A </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>4 </p>

<p>6 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F N 
H + S F N 
Membrane PKC activity 
(pmol/min/mg protein) </p>

<p>* </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>B </p>

<p>ooo </p>

<p>30 </p>

<p>C </p>

<p>3 
100 </p>

<p>120 </p>

<p>*** </p>

<p>D </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>10 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F v 
H + S F N </p>

<p>Fluorescence </p>

<p>(arb. units/ug protein) </p>

<p>ooo 
ooo </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>1 </p>

<p>2 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>20 </p>

<p>40 </p>

<p>60 </p>

<p>80 </p>

<p>N 
H 
N + S F N H + S F N </p>

<p>[MG] 
cellular (pmol/10 6 </p>

<p>cells) </p>

<p>[MG] 
medium (nM) </p>

<p>ooo </p>

<p>oo </p>

<p>** </p>

<p>FIG. 5. Biochemical dysfunction in HMEC-1 endothelial cells in hyperglycemic culture and reversal by sulforaphane in vitro. A and B: Cytosolic 
and membrane PKC activity, respectively. C: O-linked protein glycosylation of cell protein extracts. D: Effect on methylglyoxal concentrations: 
concentration in culture medium (f) and cellular content (Ⅺ). Data are means ؎ SD (n ‫؍‬ 3). *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, and ***P &lt; 0.001 with respect 
to N; 
EE P &lt; 0.01 and 
EEE P &lt; 0.001 with respect to H. </p>

<p>M. XUE AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
available to modify Keap1. The residual low concentration 
of free sulforaphane is inadequate to produce a pharma-
cological response and undergoes slow inactivation by 
spontaneous hydrolysis (39). The inhibition of nrf2 activa-
tion by GSH may, therefore, also reflect interception of 
sulforaphane in the extracellular medium and prevention 
of it reaching the cellular receptors, such as Keap1. 
Sulforaphane and related isothiocyanates are cytotoxic 
to endothelial cells and other cells at higher concentra-
tions than used herein (typically 20 -40 mol/l) (31,40). 
The cytotoxicity is mediated through interactions with 
death receptors and apoptotic signaling (41), also involv-
ing inhibition of p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (42), 
mitogen-activated protein kinase kinase kinase-1 (43), 
and protein phosphatase M3/6 (44), and activation of 
extracellular signal-related kinase 1/2 and Jun NH 2 -
terminal kinase (45). This is independent of the disruption 
of the Keap1-nrf2 complex. Such concentrations of sul-
foraphane are higher than achieved by Brassica spp. 
vegetable consumption (28), and related cell signaling is 
expected to be of limited relevance to dietary exposures of 
sulforaphane. 
There was increased formation of ROS by HMEC-1 cells 
in model hyperglycemia of 30 mmol/l D-glucose. The lack 
of similar effect induced by L-glucose indicated that glu-
cose entry and metabolism into cells was required for 
increased ROS formation. Increased ROS formation was 
linked to mitochondrial dysfunction, consistent with pre-
vious reports (10), in which complexes I and III were 
involved-the former probably by reverse electron flow 
from complex II (46). Incubation of HMEC-1 cells with the 
mitochondrial inhibitors for 24 h produced significant 
cytotoxicity and masked the role of complex I in hyper-
glycemia-induced ROS formation. Incubation with inhibi-
tors for 1 h did not induce cytotoxicity. Similar effects may 
have compromised the outcome of previous studies of this 
type (47). Other sources of increased ROS formation in 
microvascular endothelial cells in hyperglycemia have 
been identified: activation of vascular NADPH oxidase; 
inactivation and uncoupling of endothelial nitric oxide 
synthase (48,49); and related upstream signaling linked to 
poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase (PARP) (7), aldose reduc-
tase (50), and the xanthine/xanthine oxidase system (51). 
Mitochondrial metabolism appears to be a major site of 
ROS formation in the HMEC-1 cell culture model. There 
are interrelated mechanisms, however, that may explain 
how sulforaphane-induced ARE-linked gene expression 
could prevent activation of other pathways. Activation of 
PARP may be prevented by sulforaphane-induced in-
creased expression of antioxidant enzymes, preventing 
oxidative damage to DNA. The activation of the polyol 
pathway may be prevented by sulforaphane decreasing the 
cellular concentration of methylglyoxal and thereby pre-
venting methylglyoxal-induced expression of aldose re-
ductase (52). 
These findings provide the biochemical basis for the link 
of a vegetable-rich diet with decreased endothelial dys-
function (53), including that part of the Mediterranean diet 
(54), suggesting that dietary exposure to nrf2 activators 
derived from cruciferous vegetables may have be involved. 
The functional importance of this finding requires further 
evaluation. It is expected that the protective effect of nrf2 
activators may be stratified by severity of exposure to 
hyperglycemia, with increasing effects in the nondiabetic, 
impaired glucose tolerance, and diabetic populations. Hy-
perglycemia alone did not induce ARE-linked gene expres-</p>

<p>sion in HMEC-1 endothelial cells, even when confronted 
with damaging insults of oxidative stress and accumula-
tion of dicarbonyls. Physiological activators of nrf2 are 
thought to be the lipid peroxidation-derived aldehyde, 
4-hydroxynonenal, and J 3 -isoprostanes (34,55). The meta-
bolic insult of hyperglycemia is of nonlipidic origin. This 
may be why the nrf2 system does not respond strongly to 
it. There is now evidence that diabetes does induce a weak 
nrf2-mediated protective response, for example, in the 
high-fat-diet mouse model of type 2 diabetes (56). The 
weak response suggests that an effective protection to 
prevent vascular disease has not been mounted and, 
therefore, provides a clear future opportunity for pharma-
cological intervention. Cruciferous vegetable consumption 
and synthetic activators of nrf2 are expected to decrease 
the risk of vascular disease in diabetes. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGMENTS </p>

<p>This work has received support from the Juvenile Diabetes 
Research Foundation International (New York), the Well-
come Trust (U.K.), and the Biotechnology and Biosciences 
Research Council (U.K.). </p>



<p>ROLE OF ACTIVATION OF nrf2 </p>

<p> 
DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>



<p>M. XUE AND ASSOCIATES </p>

<p>DIABETES, VOL. 57, OCTOBER 2008 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>