<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><teiHeader><fileDesc xml:id="PMC2853139" /><encodingDesc><appInfo><application version="0.5.6-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2019-07-11T07:05+0000"><ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref></application></appInfo></encodingDesc></teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<p>ABSTRACT </p>

<p>The current arsenal of molecular tools for site-
directed cleavage of single-stranded DNA (ssDNA) 
is limited. Here, we describe a method for targeted 
DNA cleavage that requires only the presence of 
an A nucleotide at the target position. The proce-
dure involves hybridization of a complementary 
oligonucleotide probe to the target sequence. The 
probe is designed to create a deliberate G:A 
mismatch at the desired position of cleavage. The 
DNA repair enzyme MutY glycosylase recognizes 
the mismatch structure and selectively removes 
the mispaired A from the duplex to create an 
abasic site in the target strand. Addition of an 
AP-endonuclease, such as Endonuclease IV, 
subsequently cleaves the backbone dividing the 
DNA strand into two fragments. With an appropriate 
choice of an AP-cleaving enzyme, the 3 
0 -and 
5 
0 -ends of the cleaved DNA are suitable to take 
part in subsequent enzymatic reactions such as 
priming for polymerization or joining by DNA 
ligation. We define suitable standard reaction con-
ditions for glycosylase/AP-cleaving enzyme (G/AP) 
cleavage, and demonstrate the use of the method 
in an improved scheme for in situ detection using 
target-primed rolling-circle amplification of padlock 
probes. </p>

<p>Many of our successes in genetic research stem from 
the ability to manipulate DNA molecules in a highly 
precise manner. Amidst the current molecular tools, only 
a small subset has been developed for targeted cleavage of 
single-stranded DNA (ssDNA). A common route towards 
cleavage of synthetic ssDNA as well as genomic targets </p>

<p>that have been rendered single-stranded (1) is by hybrid-
ization of an oligonucleotide probe to the desired site of 
cleavage. The probe and target form a short double-
stranded (ds) DNA segment that can be targeted by a 
larger assortment of traditional cleavage strategies. 
Restriction endonucleases (2,3), for example, can be 
directed to cleave at the duplex structure if the duplex 
contains an appropriate recognition sequence. Although 
there are over 600 of these enzymatic scissors available 
commercially (4), the dependence on a multi-nucleotide 
recognition sequence can hamper the choice of exactly 
where the cut should occur. This is an important 
concern when targeting specific genomic sequences/ 
duplexes, as the desired site of cleavage may not 
coincide with the natural distribution of the recognition 
sequence within the genome. Also, each additional 
sequence to be cleaved requires a different restriction 
enzyme which can dramatically increase costs. There 
exist a few nicking enzymes (4) (http://www.neb.com/ 
nebecomm/tech_reference/restriction_enzymes/feature_ 
article_nicking.asp) that cleave just one strand of the 
duplex, however these enzymes suffer the same limitation 
of recognition sequence dependence as any other restric-
tion enzyme. 
To circumvent some of these problems, a cleavage 
strategy involving targeting oligonucleotides has been 
developed (5). In this approach, oligonucleotides are engi-
neered to contain two parts; a sequence that base pairs 
with the target of interest, and a sequence that folds into 
a hairpin loop and forms the recognition sequence for 
FokI endonuclease. Hybridization of the probe targets 
the desired sequence, and cleavage of the probe-target 
hybrid is mediated by FokI bound in the hairpin loop 
(5). Optimal performance is observed when the 
probe-target duplex is formed first followed by addition 
of the restriction enzyme (5). Inherent to this method is 
the use of restriction enzymes that cleave outside of their 
recognition sequence. In general, these type IIS enzymes 
are thought to bind to DNA as monomers for the most </p>

<p>*To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +46 18 4715101; Fax: +46 18 4714808; Email: mathias.howell@genpat.uu.se </p>

<p>Published online 15 January 2010 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 e99 
doi:10.1093/nar/gkp1238 </p>

<p>ß The Author(s) 2010. Published by Oxford University Press. 
This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/ 
by-nc/2.5), which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </p>

<p>part, but tend to involve dimerization of the cleavage 
domains of adjacent enzyme molecules for DNA 
cleavage (6,7). For this reason, many type IIS enzymes 
are much more active on DNA molecules that contain 
multiple recognition sites. We propose an alternative 
approach that combines the targeting accuracy of probe 
hybridization, while avoiding the potential limitations of 
type IIS restriction enzymes. 
The technique described here maintains the use of 
oligonucleotide probes for targeting the location of the 
cleavage site. Rather than depending on hairpins or 
other extraneous structures, however, the probe incorpo-
rates a G residue that mispairs with an A in the target 
sequence. 
Cleavage of the target strand can then be mediated by a 
pair of DNA repair enzymes (Figure 1) (8). Addition of 
the DNA repair enzyme MutY glycosylase (9,10), which 
specifically recognizes G-A mismatches, selectively 
removes the adenine from the G:A duplex (11) creating 
an apurinic (AP) site in the target DNA strand. Next, the 
abasic site can be severed using an enzyme with 
AP-cleaving activity such as Endonuclease IV. As there 
are several enzymes used here that recognize and cleave 
AP sites through different chemical mechanisms (12), we 
will refer to them collectively as AP-cleaving enzymes. The 
combined glycosylase/AP-cleaving (G/AP) reactions thus 
cleave the target strand while preserving the probe 
molecule intact; a critical feature in some probe-directed 
analyses as exemplified by the padlock probe application 
described here. Briefly, padlock probes are linear 
oligonucleotides which can be circularized by DNA 
ligase when correctly hybridized to target DNA sequences 
(13). If the padlock probe hybridizes close to the 3 
0 -end of 
the target DNA fragment, the target itself can serve as the 
primer for the rolling circle amplification (RCA). This 
target-primed RCA enables intracellular localization of 
sequences for in situ analyses of cells and tissues (14). 
The approach is effective; however, RCA is inhibited in 
cases where the padlock probe hybridizes away from the 
3 
0 -end of the target (15). Here, we show that simple inte-
gration of a single nucleotide mismatch in the padlock 
probe is sufficient to direct G/AP cleavage of the target 
DNA, thus producing the primer for the RCA reaction. In 
addition, with an appropriate selection of AP-cleaving 
enzyme the cleaved fragments are suitable to participate 
in polymerization, ligation, or other further enzymatic 
reaction steps. 
Herein, we explore the enzymatic properties of MutY 
glycosylase, a series of AP-cleaving enzymes, and condi-
tions for combining the two activities. We also apply the 
site-directed cleavage mechanism for in situ detection of 
mtDNA using padlock probes and target-primed RCA. </p>

<p>MATERIALS AND METHOD </p>

<p>32-P labeling of target strands </p>

<p>Oligonucleotide sequences are found in Table 1. 
32 P-labeling of the target strands (target_MutY and 
target_AP (20 nM)) 5 
0 -termini was performed using 
60 nM [g-
32 P]ATP (Amersham) and 0.2 U/ml T4 </p>

<p>polynucleotide kinase (T4 PNK) (Fermentas) in the 
supplied Reaction buffer A (1Â) for 15 min at 37 
C, 
followed by inactivation of the T4 PNK for 5 min at 
65 
C. Eighty nanomolar target strand (track_relig1) was 
32 P-labeled with 80 nM [g-
32 P]ATP and 0.2 U/ml 
OptiKinase (USB) in the supplied OptiKinase buffer 
(1Â) for 30 min at 37 
C followed by inactivation of 
the OptiKinase for 10 min at 65 
C. After labeling, 
oligonucleotides were purified in illustra MicroSpin </p>

<p>TM </p>

<p>G-50 Columns (GE Healthcare) at 3000 r.p.m. for 2 min. </p>

<p>Hybridization of oligonucleotides and site-specific 
cleavage of mismatch with MutY glycosylase and 
AP-cleaving enzyme </p>

<p>Two nanomolar of labeled target (target_MutY for the 
MutY glycosylase test and target_AP for the AP test) 
and 4 nM of probe (probe_MutY for MutY glycosylase 
test and probe_AP for AP test) were hybridized in 1 Â G/ 
AP buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, 30 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 
100 mM KCl and 1 mM DTT) for 10 min at 65 
C and then 
slowly cooled to room temperature. For the MutY 
glycosylase test, 640 nM MutY glycosylase (USB) was 
added to the hybridized duplex. The cleavage of the 
target strand was performed with 1 M NaOH incubated 
for 20 min at 95 
C. For comparison of the AP-cleaving 
enzymes, 0.05 U/ml UDG (Fermentas) was combined 
pair wise with 0.05 U/ml of the following AP-cleaving 
enzymes: Ape 1 (New England Biolabs), Endonuclease 
III (New England Biolabs), Endonuclease IV 
(Fermentas), Endonuclease V (Fermentas), Exonuclease 
III (Fermentas) and Fpg (New England Biolabs). Each 
reaction also contained 0.1 mg/ml BSA (New England 
Biolabs) and 1 Â G/AP buffer, mixed with 1 nM of the 
annealing product. Incubations were for 30 min at 37 
C 
for total cleavage. </p>

<p>Figure 1. Strategy for strand-specific cleavage using MutY glycosylase 
and AP-cleaving enzymes. When oligonucleotides are hybridized to 
each other, a G:A mismatch is created (i) which is recognized by 
MutY glycosylase. (ii) MutY glycosylase removes the mispaired A 
and (iii) the abasic site is nicked by an AP-cleaving enzyme, for 
example Endonuclease IV. The star indicates the </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-labeling of the 
target strand. The R's in the figure indicate residual side groups. </p>

<p>e99 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 </p>

<p>
5 
0 -Ligation of oligonucleotide after MutY glycosylase and 
Endonuclease IV treatment </p>

<p>The tracking oligo was created by adding 15 nM of 
the labeled track_relig1 with 15 nM track_relig2 and 
hybridizing to 15 nM probe_relig in a mixture of 0.2 U/ 
ml Ampligase (Epicentre), 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.3, 
25 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM NAD, 0.01 % 
Triton X-100 and 0.1 mg/ml BSA for 2 min at 75 
C, 1 min 
at 45 
C, 2 min at 30 
C and finally 2 min at 45 
C. The 
duplex was cleaved at the mismatched site by the 
addition of 80 nM of MutY glycosylase and 0.1 U/ml 
Endonuclease IV in a mixture with 0.1 mg/ml BSA and 
1 Â G/AP buffer for 30 min at 37 
C for total cleavage. 
Fourteen nanomolars of the ligation strand (lig_relig) 
was mixed with 3.5 nM cleaved product in a mixture of 
0.2 U/ml Ampligase (Epicentre), 20 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.3, 
25 mM KCl, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 0.5 mM NAD, 0.01 % Triton 
X-100 and 0.1 mg/ml BSA for 2 min at 75 
C, 1 min at 45 
C, 
2 min at 30 
C and finally 30 min at 45 
C. For ligation with 
T4 DNA ligase, the duplex was mixed with 0.1 U/ml T4 
DNA ligase (Fermentas), 10 mM Tris-Acetate pH 7.5, 
10 mM MgAc 2 , 50 mM KAc, 1 mM ATP (Fermentas) 
and 0.1 mg/ml BSA for 2 min at 75 
C, 1 min at 45 
C, 
2 min at 30 
C, 30 min at 37 
C and finally 10 min at 65 
C 
(the T4 DNA ligase was added prior to the incubation 
at 37 
C). </p>

<p>Polyacrylamide gel </p>

<p>The samples were mixed with loading buffer (95% 
formamide, 25 mM EDTA and 5 mg/ml blue dextran) 
and denatured for 2 min at 90 
C. The samples were 
loaded onto a 12% polyacrylamide gel (25 Â 25 Â 0.03 cm) 
[20 ml 12% polyacrylamide/7 M urea with 100 ml 10% 
ammonium persulphate (Sigma Aldrich) and 10 ml 100% 
TEMED (Fluka)] and separated for 1 h at 20 W. The 
gels were exposed to a Phosphoimaging screen (Science 
Imaging Scandinavia IP-MS2325) for $1 h before 
analysis on a Phosphoimager using the <rs type="software">Image Reader</rs> 
and <rs type="software">Image Process</rs> software. </p>

<p>Site-specific cleavage of blocked 3 
0 -end with MutY 
glycosylase/Endonuclease IV </p>

<p>One micromolar of the padlock probe (plp_cleave) was 
phosphorylated with 0.2 U/ml T4 PNK enzyme, the 
supplied reaction buffer A (1Â) and 1 mM ATP for 
15 min at 37 
C following inactivation of the enzyme at 
65 
C for 10 min. The hybridization and ligation of the 
padlock probe (10 nM) to the 3 
0 blocked and non-blocked 
templates (target-blocked_cleave, target-nonblocked_ 
cleave) (30 nM) was performed in mixtures of 25 mU/ml 
T4 DNA ligase, 1 Â È29 DNA polymerase buffer 
(Fermentas), 1 mM ATP, 0.2 mg/ml BSA for 30 min 
at 37 
C and 10 min at 65 
C for inactivation of ligase. 
For cleavage of the blocked 3 
0 -end, 1 nM of the 
oligonucleotide duplexes were mixed with 12 nM MutY 
glycosylase, 25 mU/ml Endonuclease IV in 1 Â G/AP 
buffer for 45 min at 37 
C. After removal of blocked 
3 
0 -end, RCA was performed by mixing 100 pM of the 
circularized oligonucleotides with 4 mU/ml È29 DNA </p>

<p>Table 1. Oligonucleotide sequences 
Test </p>

<p>Oligo </p>

<p>Names </p>

<p>Sequences </p>

<p>MutY glycosylase test </p>

<p>Probe </p>

<p>probe_MutY </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-TAAGAAGAGGAATTGCCTTTCCTACGACCTCAATGCACATGTTTGGCTCCTCTTCCCAGGGGTATGTTGT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Target </p>

<p>target_MutY </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-*TCAGCTGACAACATACCCATGGGAAGAGGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>AP test </p>

<p>Probe </p>

<p>probe_AP </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-TCAGCTGACAACGTACCCATGGGAAGAGGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Target </p>

<p>target_AP </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-*TCCTCTTCCCAGGGGTAUGTTGTCAGCTGA-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Ligation after cleavage </p>

<p>Probe </p>

<p>probe_relig </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-ATCAGTCGACAAAGAGACCCTGGAAGGGTACCGTGCGCCTGGTAGCAAATAGTCCGTCATGTGTTAGATGC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tracking probe 1 </p>

<p>track_relig1 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-*CTACCAGGCGCACGGTACC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Tracking probe 2 </p>

<p>track_relig2 </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-ATGACGGAATATTTG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Ligation probe </p>

<p>lig_relig </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-TAACACATGACGGAC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Cleavage of blocked end </p>

<p>Padlock probe </p>

<p>plp_cleave </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-TAAGAAGAGGAATTGCCTTTCCTACGACCTCAATGCACATGTTTGGCTCCTCTTCCCAGGGGTATGTTGT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Target blocked </p>

<p>target-blocked_cleave </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-GCAATTCCTCTTCTTAACAACATACCCATGGUUU-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Target non-blocked </p>

<p>target-nonblocked_cleave </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-CAATTCCTCTTCTTAACAACATACCCATG-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Detection probe </p>

<p>det_cleave </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-Cy3-CCTCAATGCACATGTTTGGCTCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>In situ 
detection of mtDNA </p>

<p>Padlock probe </p>

<p>plp_insitu </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-TAAGAAGAGGAATTGCCTTTCCTACGACCTCAATGCACATGTTTGGCTCCTCTTCCCAGGGGTATGTTGT-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Detection probe </p>

<p>det_insitu </p>

<p>5 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>-Cy5-CCTCAATGCACATGTTTGGCTCC-3 </p>

<p>0 </p>

<p>Bold letters indicate the site of the mismatch upon oligonucleotide annealing. 
*Where the </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P-label is introduced. </p>

<p>Underlined sequences indicate the target complements of the padlock probes. </p>

<p>Italic letters in padlock probes indicate detection probe sequences. </p>

<p> 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 e99 </p>

<p>polymerase (Fermentas), 1 Â È29 DNA polymerase 
buffer, 100 mM dNTP (Fermentas) and 0.2 mg/ml BSA for 
60 min at 37 
C and 10 min at 65 
C for inactivation of 
polymerase. Hybridization of 5 nM detection probe 
(det_cleave) to the rolling circle product (RCP) (50 pM) 
was performed in 0.1% Tween-20 (Sigma), 20 mM Tris-
HCl, 500 mM NaCl and 20 mM EDTA at 65 
C for 10 min, 
then at 37 
C for 30 min. The final samples were pumped 
through a thermoplastic microchannel, mounted in 
a standard confocal fluorescence microscope (LSM 5 
META, Zeiss) to detect individual RCPs. The samples 
were run in triplicates and the raw data files generated 
an output file that allowed the RCPs to be counted 
using Matlab. The technique is described in ref. (16). </p>

<p>Cells and pretreatments for in situ detection </p>

<p>143B cells were cultured in Dulbecco's Modified Eagles 
medium (Gibco) without phenol red, with 10% fetal calf 
serum (Sigma), 50 mg/ml uridine, 0.1% glucose, 292 mg/ml 
L-glutamine, 100 U/ml penicillin and 100 mg/ml streptomy-
cin. The cells were grown on glass microscope slides and 
fixed in 70% ethanol for 20 min at room temperature. The 
cells were permeabilized using 0.01% pepsin (Sigma) in 
0.1 M HCl for 90 s at 37 
C, followed by washing in PBS. 
Subsequent incubations in the procedure for in situ detec-
tion were carried out in a volume of 20 ml under 
22 Â 22 mm coverslips, except for the RCA reaction, 
which was performed in a volume of 40 ml in a silicone 
chamber. </p>

<p>Target preparation with restriction enzyme and 
exonuclease </p>

<p>For hybridization of the padlock probe to the DNA, we 
first rendered the target sequence single-stranded by using 
a combination of restriction enzymes and exonucleases. 
The genomic DNA was initially restriction digested with 
0.5 U/ml of MscI, BsmI or BtsI (New England Biolabs) for 
30 min at 37 
C in the NEB buffer 4 (MscI and BtsI) or 
NEB buffer 2 (BsmI) with 0.2 mg/ml BSA followed by a 
rinse in a wash buffer (0.1 M Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 0.15 M 
NaCl and 0.05% Tween-20). The digested ends were 
made single-stranded by exonucleolysis using 0.4 U/ml of 
the 5 
0 -3 
0 T7 exonuclease (New England Biolabs) at 37 
C 
for 15 min in the buffer supplied, supplemented with 
0.2 mg/ml BSA and 5% glycerol. The slides were then 
rinsed in wash buffer. </p>

<p>Padlock probe hybridization and ligation </p>

<p>Two micromolar of the padlock probe (plp_insitu) was 
phosphorylated in 0.2 U/ml T4 PNK enzyme, the 
supplied reaction buffer A (1Â) and 1 mM ATP for 
15 min at 37 
C followed by inactivation of the enzyme 
at 65 
C for 10 min. Hybridization and ligation were per-
formed in a single reaction containing 100 nM of the 
padlock probe in a solution of 10 mM Tris-Acetate pH 
7.5, 10 mM MgAc 2 , 50 mM KAc, 250 mM NaCl, 1 mM 
ATP, 0.2 mg/ml BSA and 0.1 U/ml T4 DNA ligase for 
15 min at 37 
C. The slides were first washed in 2 Â SSC, 
0.05% Tween-20 for 5 min at 37 
C then rinsed in wash 
buffer. Cleavage of the target strand at the mismatch site </p>

<p>was performed by 1.54 mM MutY glycosylase and 0.1 U/ml 
Endonuclease IV in 1 Â G/AP buffer containing 1 mg/ml 
BSA for 30 min at 37 
C. This was followed by rinsing 
the slides in wash buffer and dehydration in a series of 
70%, 85% and 100% ethanol. 
The RCA reactions were performed in rubber silicone 
reaction chambers in G/AP buffer, 0.25 mM dNTP, 
0.2 mg/ml BSA, 5% glycerol and 1 U/ml È29 DNA 
polymerase at 37 
C for 30 min on a shaking platform. 
The silicone chambers were removed from the slides 
before rinsing them in wash buffer. Following polymeriza-
tion, 250 nM of the detection probe (det_insitu) was 
hybridized to the RCPs in 2xSSC and 20% formamide 
at 37 
C for 15 min. After rinsing in wash buffer, the 
slides were dehydrated before being mounted for micros-
copy in Vectashield (Vector Laboratories) containing 
10 ng/ml DAPI. </p>

<p>Image analysis </p>

<p>For visualization of the cells and RCPs, an epifluorescence 
microscope (Axioplan II, Zeiss) equipped with a 100 W 
mercury lamp and excitation and emission filters for 
DAPI and Cy5, was used together with a CCD camera 
(C4742-95, Hamamatsu) for acquiring images. A 40Â 
objective (Plan-neofluar, Zeiss) was used and images 
were collected using the <rs id="software-3" type="software">AxioVision</rs> software <rs corresp="#software-3" type="version-number">4.4</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-3" type="creator">Zeiss</rs>). 
The RCPs were quantified using the <rs id="software-4" type="software">BlobFinder</rs> software 
(17) (version <rs corresp="#software-4" type="version-number">3.0_beta</rs>) and images were thresholded 
for visualization in <rs id="software-5" type="software">Adobe Photoshop</rs> <rs corresp="#software-5" type="version-number">CS3</rs> (<rs corresp="#software-5" type="creator">Adobe Systems Inc</rs>). </p>

<p>RESULTS </p>

<p>MutY glycosylase activities </p>

<p>The primary role of glycosylases in DNA repair is the 
recognition and removal of modified, damaged or mis-
matched nucleotide bases (18). The removal mechanism 
involves hydrolysis of the N-glycosidic bond that 
connects the nucleobases to the sugar backbone of the 
DNA molecule (Figure 1). This hydrolysis leaves the 
DNA backbone intact, producing an apurinic (G and A) 
or apyrimidinic (C, T and U) (AP) lesion at the position of 
the incorrect nucleotide. In normal DNA repair, base 
excision is followed by successive enzymatic steps of 
cleavage, polymerization and ligation which serve to 
fully repair the DNA molecule (19). 
The MutY adenine glycosylase employed here is a 
member of the base excision repair (BER) pathway in 
Escherichia coli. The enzyme recognizes non-cognate 
basepairing between A and G (10,20), A and oxidized 
guanine (7,8-dihydro-8-oxo-2'-deoxy-guanosine or OG) 
(21-23), and to a lesser extent A to C (24) (Figure 2A). 
In the presence of duplex DNA structures containing G:A 
or OG:A mismatched base pairs, MutY glycosylase 
selectively removes the undamaged A from the structure. 
Although seemingly counter-intuitive, the mechanism 
compensates for the cell's replication machinery which 
frequently mis-incorporates A residues across from 
oxidized G (25). A two-phase repair process is thus nec-
essary to reconstitute the original DNA molecule; first, the </p>

<p>e99 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 </p>

<p>
replacement of the A residue with a C in one strand, 
followed by replacement of the OG with an unmodified 
G in the complementary DNA strand. 
The enzymatic activity of MutY glycosylase was ini-
tially examined in a model system composed of a pair 
of base-paired oligonucleotides. Hybridization resulted 
in a DNA duplex containing a centrally located G:A 
mismatch. The A containing strand was end labeled with 
32 P. MutY glycosylase enzyme was then added in 50-fold 
excess over substrate and after incubation, base (NaOH) 
and/or heat was used to break the oligonucleotide at the 
abasic sites created by MutY glycosylase. Cleaved and 
uncleaved DNA molecules were separated by denaturing 
PAGE and results were recorded on a Phosphoimager. 
As shown in Figure 2A, the presence of MutY 
glycosylase alone was sufficient to generate the cleaved 
fragment with a ratio of cleaved to uncleaved of $50%. 
This observation indicates that MutY glycosylase from 
this commercial vendor appears to harbor some 
AP-cleaving activity, allowing the enzyme preparation to 
exert both G and AP activities. Upon addition of base and 
high temperature incubation, the fuzzy band disappears </p>

<p>and the ratio between cleaved and non-cleaved band 
intensities reaches a maximum of $85% for this model 
system. The cleavage efficiency from the literature and 
from other model systems in our lab indicate that the 
MutY glycosylase efficiency ranges between 50% and 
99% (23). </p>

<p>AP-cleaving activity </p>

<p>AP-cleaving enzymes are responsible for cleaving abasic 
sites during DNA repair. AP-endonucleases such as 
Ape 1, Endonuclease IV and Endonuclease V recognize 
AP lesions and cleave the phosphodiester backbone by a 
hydrolytic mechanism (26). Fpg and other AP-lyases sever 
the sugar-phosphate backbone through elimination reac-
tions (12). Depending on whether the cleavage occurs 3 
0 or 
5 
0 of the ribose, the reactions occur via b-or d-elimination 
reaction, respectively (Figure 2B). Endonuclease V is a 
notable exception as it cleaves at the 2nd phosphodiester 
bond 3 
0 of the abasic lesion (27). 
We created an experimental set-up to evaluate the 
activity of AP-cleaving enzymes on abasic substrates in </p>

<p>Figure 2. Overview of the glycosylases and AP-cleaving enzymes presented herein. (A) (i) The hydrolysis mechanism creating abasic sites, (ii) the 
different glycosylases MutY, TDG (thymine DNA glycosylase) and UDG, the corresponding substrates they are recognizing and possible 
AP-activity, (iii) hydrolysis of target strand by MutY and cleavage of abasic sites by NaOH and/or 95 
C heat. (B) The different AP-cleaving 
enzymes and their effects and efficiencies. (i) b-or d-elimination of the DNA phosphodiester backbone depending on the AP-cleaving enzyme, (ii) the 
different AP-cleaving enzymes that have been compared are Ape 1, Endonuclease III, Endonuclease IV, Endonuclease V, Exonuclease III and Fpg. 
The way of elimination (b or d) of abasic sites are presented as well as what phosphodiester bond they have as cleavage site and what terminus they 
leave at the 5 
0 -and 3 
0 -end, (iii) efficiencies of AP-cleaving enzymes on abasic sites. The abasic sites are created through removal of uracils by UDG 
and cleaved by addition of different AP-cleaving enzymes. Positive control (pos) represents NaOH and 95 
C heat, while negative control (neg) 
is without addition of AP-cleaving enzyme. </p>

<p>PAGE 5 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 e99 </p>

<p>a manner that was independent of MutY glycosylase 
activity. The substrate consisted of hybridized, comple-
mentary oligonucleotides with one strand containing 
a centrally located 2 
0 -deoxyuridine (dU). The U strand 
was labeled with </p>

<p>32 </p>

<p>P. The U was removed by treatment 
with uracil DNA glycosylase (UDG), generating an abasic 
site in the oligonucleotide duplex. Six different enzymes 
were tested (present in at least a 50-fold molar excess 
of enzyme to substrate) along with base treatment and 
heat as a chemical control (Figure 2B). Endonuclease 
III, Endonuclease IV, Exonuclease III and MutM 
[formamidopyrimidine-DNA glycosylase (Fpg)] showed 
near 100% conversion of the 30 base fragment to the 17 
base fragment as expected upon cleavage at the abasic site. 
Ape 1 showed a $65% cleavage in these experiments, and 
Endonuclease V appeared not to cleave the substrate to 
any significant extent. A possible explanation for the poor 
performance of Ape 1 and Endonuclease V is that buffer 
and assay conditions necessary for the present protocol 
differ greatly from the manufacturers' recommended 
buffers and assay conditions for these two enzymes. </p>

<p>DNA target cleavage and ligation </p>

<p>Cleavage of DNA molecules by the combined action of 
glycosylases and AP-endonucleases or AP-lyases has been 
observed during the exploration of the enzymes roles in 
DNA repair (26). Several methods in molecular biology 
have further adapted the use of G/AP-cleaving enzymes 
for the modification of synthetic and amplified DNA 
molecules (28). For example, the USER 
TM cloning kit 
(New England Biolabs) uses a combination of UDG and 
Endo VIII for digestion of uracil containing PCR 
products for subsequent cloning (29). The procedure 
does not require in vitro ligation as the bacterial host 
repair mechanism is employed to join the nick sites upon 
transformation. In mutation detection or allele discrimi-
nation, the presence of a mutation results in cleavage of a 
mismatched probe molecule (30). The cleavage event is 
subsequently detected as a reduction in probe length or 
loss of energy transfer between donor and acceptor 
fluorophores located on opposing sides of the cleavage 
site. The purpose of this work is to expand the use of 
these DNA repair enzymes, beyond applications on syn-
thetic or amplified DNA molecules, for modification of 
non-amplified DNA for subsequent manipulation of the 
generated DNA fragments. However, the combinations of 
enzymes as well as the cleavage conditions defined herein 
are also useful for manipulation of synthetic 
oligonucleotides. 
A series of experiments were designed to investigate the 
efficiency of ligation using DNA fragments generated by 
G/AP reactions (Figure 3A). As an initial step, an 
internally labeled tracking oligo was created by ligating 
a 5 
0 -
32 P labeled oligonucleotide with an adjacently 
hybridized oligonucleotide. The resultant 34 nt tracking 
oligo formed an imperfect duplex with the ligation 
template, resulting in a G:A mismatch. Following MutY 
glycosylase treatment, the abasic sites were cleaved with 
AP-cleaving enzyme Endonuclease IV which reduced the 
length of the tracking probe to 17 nt. Then, a 23 nt </p>

<p>oligonucleotide was added to anneal immediately 5 
0 to 
the nick site. Successful ligation by T4 ligase thus 
resulted in increasing the length of the tracking oligo to 
40 nt. Since the tracking oligo was radio-labeled, changes 
in the oligonucleotides length were detectable by PAGE 
(Figure 3B). Well over 75% of the oligonucleotides under-
went both cleavage in the G/AP reaction and ligation at 
the cleaved site. Interestingly, as can be seen in Figure 2B, 
Endonuclease IV leaves a sugar at the 5 
0 side of the lesion 
after lysis of abasic sites. The presence of the 
deoxyribose-5 
0 -phosphate (dR5P) should inhibit ligation, 
however, Endonuclease IV proved to be one of the better 
AP-cleaving enzymes to use in this configuration. This is 
probably due to the spontaneous loss of extremely labile 
5 
0 -terminal dR5P (31) in aqueous solutions. </p>

<p>DNA target cleavage and polymerization </p>

<p>A model system was used to test if DNA fragments 
generated by G/AP cleavage could serve as primers for 
RCA reactions. In this setup, the sequence of a padlock 
probe was designed to create a G:A mismatch when 
hybridized to a target sequence (Figure 4A). Additionally, 
the target oligonucleotide was synthesized with a series </p>

<p>Figure 3. Ligation after MutY/Endo IV strand-specific nicking. 
(A) Mechanism for 5 
0 -end ligation after nicking with MutY/Endo IV. 
Endo IV leaves a ligatable 5 
0 -end which can be joined to the 3 
0 -OH of a 
probe hybridized in juxtaposition through ligation. (i) Probe hybridiza-
tion creating G:A mismatch. (ii) Recognition of mismatch and removal 
of an A residue by MutY. (iii) AP-site recognition by Endo IV and 
cleavage of 5 
0 DNA backbone. (iv) Ligation of probe to the 5 
0 -end after 
cleavage. (B) MutY/Endo IV cleavage efficiency and 5 
0 ligation effi-
ciency after MutY/Endo IV. Lane 1, labeled oligonucleotide (34 nt). 
Lane 2, cleaved product after MutY/Endo IV (17 nt). Lane 3, the 
ligation probe joined by ligation to the 5 
0 -end terminus created by 
Endo IV (40 nt product). </p>

<p>e99 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 </p>

<p>
of 2 
0 -O-methyl-RNA residues to block degradation 
of the 3 
0 -end (32). These modified nucleotides were non-
complementary to the padlock probe, ensuring that the 
È29 DNA polymerase could not prime the RCA 
directly. Cleavage of the target by G/AP activity 
removes the blocked end generating a 3 
0 -end that should 
be suitable to prime an RCA reaction. 
Padlock probes were hybridized to 3 
0 blocked target 
oligonucleotides and ligated. Following exposure to 
either MutY glycosylase or Endonuclease IV, individually 
or in combination, RCA was performed and resulting 
RCPs were quantified in a microfluidic device (16). As 
can be seen in Figure 4B, exposure to glycosylase or AP-
cleaving enzyme individually was insufficient to allow 
priming of the RCA reaction. However, with both 
enzymes, nearly 100% of the targets were converted to 
primers as estimated by comparing with targets that 
lacked the 3 
0 modification. </p>

<p>In situ detection of mtDNA </p>

<p>Padlock probes have been successfully implemented 
to detect mitochondrial sequences in situ (14). The 
design of such experiments involves cleavage of the 
mitochondrial genomes with restriction enzymes, 
followed by 5 
0 exonucleolytic degradation of one of the 
genome strands. The 5 
0 exonuclease serves to expose a 
single-stranded target sequence for hybridization of the 
padlock probe. Padlock probes are hybridized, ligated 
and amplified by RCA, where the cleaved genomic </p>

<p>fragment serves as the primer for the È29 DNA 
polymerase. In cases where the DNA target extends a 
few nucleotides beyond the hybridization site of the 
padlock probe, the inherent 3 
0 exonucleolytic activity of 
È29 effectively digests the extension to initiate RCA. 
RCPs are subsequently detected using fluorescence 
microscopy. 
One consistent observation has been that the reaction is 
more efficient when the restriction site is closer to the 
padlock probe hybridization site. This could be attributed 
to either inefficiencies in the genome preparation step (14), 
inhibition of È29's exonucleolytic activity, or a combina-
tion thereof. A plausible explanation for the reduction in 
single-stranded exonucleolytic activity may be that longer 
fragments are more likely to form secondary structures. 
Additionally, 3 
0 -ends involved in hairpins could act as a 
primer for 'fold-back' synthesis using the target strand as 
a template instead of the circularized padlock probe. 
Figure 5A outlines the strategy taken to test if G/ 
AP-mediated cleavage of mismatched sequences could 
increase the efficiency of the target-primed in situ RCA 
of padlock probes. Similar to previous experiments, 
restriction enzymes were first used to cut the genome, 
and an exonuclease was applied to prepare the single-
stranded target for probe hybridization. Following 
ligation, samples were digested with G/AP enzymes, 
amplified by RCA, and exposed to fluorescence labeled 
detection probes. The cells were finally studied using an 
epifluorescence microscope. </p>

<p>Figure 4. Removal of blocked 3 
0 -end with MutY/Endo IV for RCA. (A) The mechanism of removal of the 3 
0 blocking end with MutY/Endo IV. 
(i) An oligonucleotide with a blocked 3 
0 -end serves as a target for padlock hybridization and ligation. The duplex formed between the probe/target 
creates a G:A mismatch. (ii) Recognition and cleavage of mismatch by MutY glycosylase/Endo IV resulting in removal of the blocked 3 
0 -end. 
(iii) RCA and detection of RCPs. (B) Results from quantification of RCPs with the digital RCA technique. Briefly the procedure involves hybrid-
ization of fluorescently labeled detection oligonucleotides to the RCPs followed by pumping the solution through a microfluidic channel that is 
mounted on a fluorescent microscope. The imaged RCPs show up as distinct fluorescent spots that are quantified using imaging software. The 
resulting number of RCPs was counted in the different blocked (B) or non-blocked (NB) samples: negative control (no MutY/Endo IV added) (B), 
MutY (B), Endo IV (B), MutY/Endo IV (B) and positive control (NB). Error bars indicate standard deviations. </p>

<p>PAGE 7 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 e99 </p>

<p>Two series of experiments were the initial restriction 
digestion of the genome occurred at different nucleotide 
distances from the padlock hybridization position. One set 
of experiments used the restriction enzyme BsmI which 
cleaved the target roughly 40 nt from the padlock probe 
hybridization site, and a second set of experiments 
used BtsI which cleaved 400 nt from the padlock site. 
As Figure 5B demonstrates, addition of the G/AP step 
results in a notable increase in the number of RCPs 
detected compared to reactions where the G/AP step 
was omitted. For both the 40 and 400 nucleotide over-
hangs, roughly 2.5-3.5 times more RCPs were observed 
compared to negative controls (no G/AP). Thus, addition </p>

<p>of the G/AP treatment step in the target-primed RCA 
method enables some relaxation of assay design criteria. </p>

<p>DISCUSSION </p>

<p>Along with serving vital functions in maintaining healthy 
genomes, glycosylases and AP-cleaving enzymes are effec-
tive and versatile biotechnology tools for in vitro manip-
ulation of nucleic acids. Cleavage of DNA fragments 
basically follows a two-step mechanism. First, MutY 
glycosylase disunites the base from the sugar-phosphate 
backbone. Scission of the target DNA strand is the con-
sequence of subsequent hydrolysis of the apurinic site with </p>

<p>Figure 5. In situ detection of mitochondrial DNA using padlock probes and RCA. (A) (i) Genomic DNA is made single-stranded by restriction 
enzyme digestion and exonucleolytic digestion of one of the genomic DNA strands. This step generates a single-stranded DNA segment at the desired 
target site. (ii) Hybridization and ligation of a padlock probe. The resulting probe/target duplex contains a G:A mispair, respectively. The target 
strand is then cleaved at the mismatch site by MutY/Endo IV. (iii) The padlock probe is amplified by RCA followed by detection probe hybrid-
ization to the RCPs. (B) The effect of MutY/Endo IV when applied in situ on fixed cells detecting mitochondrial DNA. For comparison, the 
mitochondrial genome was cleaved at two different distances from hybridization site of the padlock probe. (i) Cleavage using restriction enzyme BsmI 
with a restriction site $40 bp 3 
0 from padlock target site without and (ii) with an addition of MutY/Endo IV. (iii) Cleavage using restriction enzyme 
BtsI $400 bp 3 
0 from padlock probe site without and (iv) with addition of MutY/Endo IV. The average number of RCPs per cell, as determined by 
the <rs type="software">BlobFinder</rs> program, is displayed in the upper right corner of each picture. Cell nuclei were stained blue using DAPI and RCPs were stained 
using fluorescence labeled oligonucleotides and are shown in purple. Scale bar, 20 mm. </p>

<p>e99 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 </p>

<p>
one of several enzymes exhibiting AP-cleaving activity. 
The purpose of this work has been to optimize and dem-
onstrate the use of G/AP as a general tool for probe-
directed cleavage of single-stranded DNA sequences. 
For the in situ padlock probe application described here, 
G/AP-mediated cleavage effectively prepares the target to 
serve as a primer for the subsequent rolling circle reaction. 
Resulting RCPs remain localized and can reveal the 
cellular location of the target sequences. 
Some key advantages of this probe-directed cleavage 
approach include the simplicity of design, which only 
requires substitution of a T for a G in the probe 
sequence. Standard nucleotides are used in the probes, 
avoiding the need for expensive synthesis of oligonucleo-
tides with exotic modifications such as OG. With proper 
oligonucleotide design, multiple sequences could be 
targeted simultaneously with a common pair of G/AP 
enzymes and reaction conditions. It is furthermore of par-
ticular importance in the padlock probe application that 
the probe that directs the cleavage reaction remains intact. 
Thus, in our application, the site-directed cleavage can be 
directed by the padlock probe sequence without 
destroying the padlock probe itself. The approach is 
directly applicable to synthetic and single-stranded DNA 
species such as cDNA, however as demonstrated herein, 
the approach can also be used for cleavage of genomes if 
the target sequence is first rendered single-stranded. 
Despite an extensive scientific literature regarding the 
characterization of G/AP, the protocol that we arrived 
at herein could only be discovered by empirical work. 
For example, in our hands the best combination for 
cleavage of single-stranded U-containing fragments is 
UDG and Fpg (Supplementary Figure 1). In addition, 
many enzymes have more than one catalytic activity and 
DNA repair enzymes are no exception. We noticed that 
quite a few of the AP-cleaving enzymes tested herein 
also show weak to moderate exonuclease activity (data 
not shown). The exonuclease activity is dependent on 
Mg++ concentration (33), so for in vitro use, simply 
omitting MgCl 2 from buffer systems helped to reduce 
undesired exonuclease activity while leaving the 
AP-cleaving activity intact. Regarding the extensive 
debate in the scientific literature about the classification 
of MutY glycosylases (11,24), the enzyme as provided by 
the two commercial sources and used here appears 
to harbor both glycosylase and partial lyase activity. 
In our hands, MutY glycosylase thus exhibits bifunctional 
properties rather than behaving strictly as a monofunc-
tional glycosylase. That being said, many of the 
AP-cleaving enzymes described here showed much 
higher cleaving efficiencies than MutY glycosylase on its 
own. 
We conclude that in a growing repertoire of molecular 
tools, members of DNA repair pathways can serve as 
valuable companions to restriction enzymes for the 
catalytic manipulation of nucleic acids. </p>

<p>SUPPLEMENTARY DATA </p>

<p>Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online. </p>

<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS </p>

<p>The authors are grateful to Dr Tomas Lindahl for 
his insightful discussions regarding glycosylases and 
AP-cleaving enzymes, and also to the reviewers for their 
constructive input into the article. </p>

<p>FUNDING </p>

<p>Foundations of Knut and Alice Wallenberg, Go¨ran 
Gustafsson, and Erik K. Fernstro¨m; Swedish Research 
Council and the European Community's Seventh 
Framework Program (FP7/2007-2013) under grant agree-
ment [HEALTH-F4-2008-201418] entitled READNA; the 
Sixth Framework Program under the grant agreement 
entitled COMICS. Funding for open access charge: M.N. </p>

<p>Conflict of interest statement. None declared. </p>



<p>PAGE 9 OF 10 
Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 e99 </p>



<p>e99 Nucleic Acids Research, 2010, Vol. 38, No. 7 </p>

<p>
</p></text></tei>